<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4213703" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The performance of animals managed on pasture is 
directly related to the quantitative and qualitative 
availability of forage, which is subjected to variations 
throughout the year. Thus, strategic supplementation is an 
alternative to improve productive efficiency through 
providing the limiting nutrients to achieve the objectives of 
the production system. 
Nutrient intake, digestibility and metabolism are factors 
that affect animal performance, however feed intake, can be 
influenced by factors inherent to the feeds such as 
palatability, texture, visual appearance, and factors linked to 
the animals, like emotional state, social interaction and 
apprenticeship (Mertens, 1994). The effect of supplement </p>

<p>on intake can be additive, when the supplement intake is 
aggregated to the current ingestion of the animal; and 
substitutive, when the supplement intake reduces forage 
intake without improving animal performance (Barbosa et 
al., 2001). Additionally, the ingestion of supplement 
changes the ingestive behavior of grazing ruminants 
(Marques et al, 2005) and when part of the required 
nutrients is met by supplement intake, the efficiency in the 
use of the energy from the diet may improve due to the 
better conditions for the activity of the ruminal microbiota 
(Silva et al, 2005). Thus, the grazing time may reduce, the 
idle and rumination times may increase and the feed intake 
by the animals may improve. Therefore, the ingestive 
behavior can be influenced according to the type of 
ingredient used in the supplement. Additionally, the 
physical structure and chemical composition can also affect 
the ingestive behavior, influencing the feeding time. 
The use of supplements based on corn as an energy 
component may result in high costs for production systems, </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. </p>

<p>Vol. 27, No. 11 : 1584-1592 November 2014 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5713/ajas.2014.14233 </p>

<p>www.ajas.info </p>

<p>pISSN 1011-2367 eISSN 1976-5517 </p>

<p>Ingestive Behavior of Heifers Supplemented with Glycerin in 
Substitution of Corn on Brachiaria brizantha Pasture </p>

<p>L. M. A. M. Facuri, R. R. Silva*, F. F. da Silva, G. G. P. de Carvalho, C. B. Sampaio, F. B. L. Mendes, 
M. M. Lisboa, D. S. Barroso, V. M. Carvalho, and M. M. S. Pereira 
Universidade Estadual do Sudoeste da Bahia, Itapetinga, Bahia 45700-000, Brazil </p>

<p>ABSTRACT: The objective was to evaluate the ingestive behavior of crossbred heifers finished on a Brachiaria brizantha cv. </p>

<p>Marandu pasture receiving four levels of glycerin in their supplementation. Thirty-six crossbred heifers with average initial weight of 
264.83±3.83 kg and 20 months of age were distributed into a completely randomized design with four treatments and nine replications: 
control (0%), 4.82%, 10.12%, and 15.56% glycerin in the dry matter. The grazing time reduced linearly (p&lt;0.05), whereas the time spent 
on activities like rumination, idleness, trough and total chewing time were quadratically affected (p&lt;0.05). Bite rate and number of 
bites/day were quadratically influenced (p&lt;0.05). The number of bites/swallowed cud and the number of bites/minute, however, 
increased linearly (p&lt;0.05). Although the time spent on each cud and number of chews per cud were not affected (p&gt;0.05).The number 
of rumination periods reduced linearly (p&lt;0.05), whereas the number of grazing, idle and trough periods, and the times per grazing, idle, 
rumination and trough periods were quadratically affected (p&lt;0.05). The feed and rumination efficiencies of the dry matter, non-fibrous 
carbohydrates, pasture dry matter and concentrate were quadratically affected (p&gt;0.05) whereas the feed efficiency of neutral detergent 
fiber reduced linearly (p&lt;0.05). Addition of glycerin in substitution of corn in supplements for animals managed on pastures does not 
influenced feed intake, but reduces the grazing time and increases the idle time. The supplementation also improves feed and rumination 
efficiencies. (Key Words: Biodiesel, Efficiency, Ethology, Glycerin, Ingestion) </p>

<p>Copyright © 2014 by Asian-Australasian Journal of Animal Sciences </p>

<p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>* Corresponding Author: Robério Rodrigues Silva. E-mail: 
rrsilva.uesb@hotmail.com </p>

<p>Submitted Mar. 31, 2014; Revised Jun. 5, 2014; Accepted Jun. 28, 2014 </p>

<p>Facuri et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1584-1592 </p>



<p>when animals are finished on pasture. Hence, alternative 
energy sources can be efficient in reducing the production 
costs provided they do not compromise intake or animal 
performance. Among the alternative sources of food energy 
is glycerin, a by-product from the biodiesel industry, which 
has been used in supplementation systems as a substitute for 
corn, because it presents similar energy characteristics and 
also because ruminants are able to use the glycerol present 
in the glycerin as a gluconeogenic precursor (Chung et al., 
2007) for the maintenance of plasma glucose levels. 
The chemical composition of glycerin is highly variable, 
as it changes according to the raw material utilized for 
biodiesel production (Elam et al., 2008). Because of the 
glycerol content, the use of glycerin in substitution of corn 
results in rapid ruminal fermentation (Trabue et al., 2007), 
which causes alterations in the ingestive behavior. In the 
literature, effects of the use of glycerin in supplementation 
as regards the ingestive behavior of pasture-finished cattle 
are controversial. 
The objective of this study was to evaluate the ingestive 
behavior of crossbred heifers finished on a Brachiaria 
brizantha cv. Marandu pasture receiving four different 
levels of glycerin in their supplementation. </p>

<p>MATERIAL AND METHODS </p>

<p>The experiment was conducted from July to December 
2010 on Princesa do Mateiro Farm, located in Ribeirão do 
Largo, BA, Brazil, The experimental period was 135 days, 
of which the first 14 days were used for animals to adapt to 
the management and experimental diets. The animals were </p>

<p>kept on a pasture-production, rotational grazing system on 
Brachiaria brizantha cv. Marandugrass in a 14-ha area 
which was divided into 11 paddocks. 
Thirty-six Nellore heifers with average initial weight of 
264.83±3.83 kg and 14 months of age were distributed into 
a completely randomized design with four treatments and 
nine replications, as follows: G0, control; G5, 4.82%; G10, 
10.12%; and G15, 15.56% glycerin in substitution of corn 
in the ingested dietary dry matter (DM) (Table 1). The 
supplement was provided once daily (10 00 h) in an 
uncovered plastic trough. The diets were formulated 
according to the NRC (2000) to contain equal amounts of 
protein and energy (Tables 1 and 2), with a roughage-to-
concentrate ratio of 63.40:36.6. The glycerin utilized was 
produced in a soybean biodiesel-extracting company 
(BIOPAR, Rolândia, PR, Brazil) and contained 81.20% 
glycerol. The chemical composition of glycerin was 
determined at Instituto de Tecnologia do Paraná (TECPAR). </p>

<p>Table 1. Ingredient composition of the total diet </p>

<p>Ingredients 
(% DM) </p>

<p>Inclusion of glycerin (% DM) 1 
G0 1 
G5 2 
G10 2 
G15 4 
Forage 
63.40 
63.40 
63.40 
63.40 
Soybean meal 
7.53 
8.67 
9.86 
11.09 
Corn 
28.42 
22.67 
16.69 
10.48 
Glycerin 
0.00 
4.60 
9.38 
14.35 
Mineral salt 
0.65 
0.66 
0.67 
0.69 
Total 
100.00 
100.00 
100.00 
100.00 </p>

<p>DM, dry matter. 
1 G0, no glycerin; G5, 4.82% glycerin; G10, 10.12% glycerin; G15, 
15.56% glycerin. </p>

<p>Table 2. Chemical composition of the Brachiaria brizanta cv. Marandu and of the concentrates (% of DM), total dry matter availability, 
residual biomass, stocking rate, accumulation rate and forage allowance </p>

<p>Ingredients 
Brachiaria brizantha 
Inclusion of glycerin (% DM) 1 
G0 
G5 
G10 
G15 
DM (%) 
35.97 
81.99 
83.56 
85.19 
86.89 
CP (%) 
6.50 
18.08 
17.99 
17.91 
17.82 
EE (%) 
2.20 
5.12 
4.30 
3.45 
2.57 
TC (%) 
62.85 
71.76 
60.26 
48.30 
35.87 
NFC (%) 
17.18 
54.62 
45.27 
35.55 
25.45 
NDF (%) 
69.14 
17.14 
14.99 
12.75 
10.42 
ADF (%) 
39.81 
6.10 
5.72 
5.32 
4.90 
MM (%) 
8.15 
3.27 
3.73 
4.20 
4.69 
TDN (%) 
59.08 
79.44 
79.20 
78.93 
78.65 
DMA (kg/ha) 
5,064.06 
DRB (kg DM/ha/d) 
52.78 
SR (AU/ha) 
1.73 
AR (kg DM/ha/d) 
13.55 
FA (kg DM/100 kg BW/d) 
8.50 </p>

<p>DM, dry matter; CP, crude protein; EE, ether extract; TC, total carbohydrates; NFC, non-fibrous carbohydrates; NDF, neutral detergent fiber; ADF, acid 
detergent fiber; MM, mineral matter; TDN, total digestible nutrients (Sniffen et al. [1992]); DMA, dry matter availability; DRB, daily residual forage </p>

<p>biomass; SR, stocking rate; AR, dry matter accumulation rate; FA, forage allowance; BW, body weight. </p>

<p>¹ G0, no glycerin; G5, 4.82% glycerin; G10, 10.12% glycerin; G15, 15.56% glycerin. </p>

<p>Facuri et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1584-1592 </p>

<p>
The pasture was evaluated every 28 days to estimate the 
DM availability (Table 2) by removing 12 samples collected 
from the soil level with a 0.25 m 2 frame according to the 
method described by Wilm et al. (1944). To reduce the 
influence of biomass variation among paddocks, the heifers 
remained in each paddock for seven days, and then 
randomly transferred to another paddock. The daily residual 
biomass of DM (Table 2) was estimated in the four 
paddocks according to the double-sampling method (Wilm 
et al., 1994). Before the cut, the DM of the biomass of the 
sample was visually estimated. The values of the visually 
estimated samples cut when the frame was thrown 40 times 
were utilized, and subsequently the forage biomass was 
calculated and expressed in kg/ha, by the equation proposed 
by Gardner (1986). 
The DM accumulation in the different experimental 
periods was calculated by multiplying the daily 
accumulation rate (DAR) of DM by the number of days in 
the period. The DAR was estimated by the equation 
proposed by Campbell (1966): DAR J = (G i -F i -1)/n, in 
which DAR J = daily DM accumulation rate in period j, in 
kg DM/ha/d; G i = average final DM in the four empty 
paddocks at instant i, in kg DM/ha; F i-1 = average initial 
DM present in the empty paddocks at instant i-1, in kg 
DM/ha; n = number of days in period j. The forage 
allowance was calculated according to the formula: </p>

<p>Forage allowance (FA) 
= {[total residual biomass (RBM) 
×area+daily accumulation rate×area] 
/total body weight (BW)}×100 </p>

<p>in which: FA, in kg DM/100 kg body weight (BW) d; 
RBM, in kg/ha day DM; DAR, in kg DM/ha day; BW, in 
kg/ha. 
The forage samples collected by the double-sampling 
technique were weighed separately on field, and sub-
samples were taken from this material and their structural 
components leaf blade, stem, and dead material (MM) were 
separated and their individual dry weight obtained. Samples 
of forage were pre-dried in a forced air-circulation oven at 
55°C to 65°C for 72 h. 
To estimate the fecal production, LIPE (isolated, 
purified and enriched lignin from Eucalyptus grandis, 
UFMG, Minas Gerais, Brazil) was used as external marker, 
which was administered daily at the dose of one capsule 
after the supply of the morning concentrate, for seven days. 
The first three days were used for adaptation and regulation 
of the excretion of the marker, and the other four for feces 
collection. The feces were collected (approximately 300 g) 
directly from the pasture, right after excretion, taking the 
necessary precautions to avoid contamination of the 
samples with the soil. They were stored in plastic bags, </p>

<p>labeled and frozen. 
The DM, ash, crude protein (CP), and ether extract (EE) 
contents in the samples of feed, orts samples and feces were 
analyzed according to Silva and Queiroz (2002). The 
organic matter content was estimated by subtracting the 
ash from the DM content. The total carbohydrates (TC) 
were estimated according to Sniffen et al. (1992), as 
follows: TC = 100-(%CP+%EE+%ash). The non-fibrous 
carbohydrates corrected for the residual ash and protein 
(NFCap) were calculated according to Kearl (1992): NFCap 
= (100 -%NDFap -%CP -%EE -% ash). The total digestible 
nutrients (TDN) were calculated according to Weiss (1999), 
but utilizing the neutral detergent fiber (NDF) and non-
fibrous carbohydrates (NFC) corrected for residual ash and 
protein. 
The ingestive behavior was evaluated by means of 
visual observations during two 24-hour periods, with 5-
minute intervals to identify the times spent on the grazing, 
rumination, idle and trough activities and total chewing 
time (TCT). Animals in each treatment were visually 
assessed by one trained observer for two hours and six 
hours of rest and thus, for each treatment four observers 
were used. Throughout the day, each observer worked for 6 
hours and rested 18 hours. The entire experiment used 16 
observers who were positioned strategically so as not to 
disturb the animals. 
The bite rate of the animals on each treatment was 
estimated as the time spent by the animal to perform 20 
bites (Hodgson, 1982). To calculate the bite mass, the total 
daily intake was divided by the total daily bites (Jamieson 
and Hodgson, 1979). The results of the observations of bites 
and swallowing were recorded in six occasions throughout 
the day, according to Baggio et al. (2009), with three 
evaluations in the morning and another three in the 
afternoon. These observations were also used to determine 
the number of bites per day, which is the product between 
bite rate and grazing time. 
The count of the number of rumination chews and the 
determination of the time spent on the rumination of each, 
per animal, were performed with the use of a digital 
stopwatch. To obtain the average number of chews and the 
average time, three cuds were observed in three different 
periods of the day (0900 to 1200 h, 1500 to 1800 h, and 
1900 to 2100 h), according to Bürger et al. (2000). To 
determine the number of daily cuds, the total rumination 
time was divided by the average time spent on the 
rumination of each cud, as described previously. 
The variables g of DM and NDF/meal were obtained by 
dividing the average individual intake of each fraction by 
the number of eating periods per day (in 24 hours). The feed 
and rumination efficiencies, expressed as g/h DM and g/h 
NDF, were obtained by dividing the average daily intakes of 
DM and NDF by the total time spent eating and/or </p>

<p>Facuri et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1584-1592 </p>



<p>ruminating in 24 hours, respectively. The variables g of DM 
and NDF/cud were obtained by dividing the average 
individual intake of each fraction by the number of 
ruminated cuds per day (in 24 hours). 
The results were analyzed by variance analysis and 
regression equations, using the Analysis System of the 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">System Analysis and Statistical Genetics</rs> package (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2001</rs>). </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Substitution of corn for glycerin of medium purity in the 
supplement did not affect (p&gt;0.05) the intakes of DM from 
concentrate (concentrate DM), DM from pasture (pasture 
DM), total DM intake (TDMI), neutral detergent fiber 
intake (NDFI) or non-fibrous carbohydrates intake (NFCI) 
during the finishing of heifers (Table 3). The average 
concentrate DM intake was equal (2.57 kg/d) for all the 
groups, since it was fixed at 0.85% of the live weight of the 
animals, for the treatments. Likewise, the average pasture 
DM intake was similar for all treatments (3.92 kg/d), with 
no additive or substitutive effect of addition of the glycerin 
levels on forage intake. 
The average intake observed for TDM (concentrate DM 
+pasture DM) was 6.49 kg/d. Such results agree with those 
observed by Farias et al. (2012), who did not find an effect 
of substitution of corn for crude glycerin at the levels of 
0.0%, 2.8%, 6.1%, and 9.1%, in the total DM, on TDMI 
(6.2 kg/d) of heifers reared under conditions similar to the 
present study. On the other hand, adding 0.0%, 2.0%, 4.0%, 
8.0%, 12%, and 16% glycerin to a diet for confined heifers, 
Parsons et al. (2009) observed a decrease in DMI from 
2.0% glycerin. According to these authors, the addition of </p>

<p>over 5% glycerin to the diet can affect the activity of the 
rumen microorganisms, interfering with ruminal 
fermentation. However, in the present study, addition of up 
to 13.0% glycerin did not show such interference. 
The times spent on the grazing, rumination, idle and 
trough activities and the TCT were affected (p&lt;0.05) by 
inclusion of glycerin in the diet (Table 3). The grazing time 
decreased linearly (p&lt;0.05), and addition of 15% glycerin 
in the total DM reduced the grazing time by 127 minutes in 
relation to the animals fed supplement without glycerin. 
Such behavior indicates that the animals that did not receive 
glycerin in the diet needed more time to ingest the same 
amount of DM as those fed it, given that no significant 
differences were found in intake. 
The time spent idle was quadratically affected (p&lt;0.05) 
by the replacement of corn with glycerin (Table 3); with 
5.25% of glycerin in the total DM, the animals spent 701.12 
min of their time idle. According to Parsons et al. (2009), 
glycerol is almost totally converted to propionate in the 
rumen, which is the first to signal the end of the meals by 
increasing adenosine triphosphate production due to its use 
for glucose production, which signals satiety (Krehbiel, 
2008). Thus, because 91% of the glycerin utilized in this 
experiment consisted of glycerol, a momentary satiation can 
be observed, caused by the rapid energy uptake, thereby 
increasing the idle time by the animals. 
Similarly, the rumination time was quadratically 
affected (p&lt;0.05) by addition of glycerin to the diet (Table 
3), and with 7.16% of glycerin the animals spent 246.32 
min ruminating, which corresponds to approximately 41 
more minutes than those that did not receive glycerin. The 
variation in rumination time can be attributed to the </p>

<p>Table 3. Effect of addition of glycerin levels on nutrient intake and times spent on the grazing, idle, rumination and trough activities by 
supplemented heifers on a Brachiaria brizantha pasture </p>

<p>Item 
Inclusion of glycerin 1 
Mean 
CV 
p-value 
R 2 
G0 
G5 
G10 
G15 
L 
Q 
------------------------Intake (kg/d) -------------------------
Pasture DM 
3.83 
3.93 
3.91 
4.02 
3.92 
9.01 
0.32 
1.00 
-
Concentrate DM 
2.57 
2.57 
2.57 
2.57 
2.57 
17.64 
1.00 
1.00 
-
TDMI 
6.40 
6.50 
6.48 
6.59 
6.49 
8.66 
0.53 
0.71 
-
NDF ap I 
2.77 
2.83 
2.81 
2.88 
2.82 
7.91 
0.31 
0.94 
-
NFCI 
1.41 
1.27 
1.21 
1.36 
1.31 
18.17 
0.86 
0.08 
-
----------------------------Minutes/d -------------------------
Grazing 2 
471.67 
438.33 
420.83 
345.28 
419.03 
9.76 
0.00 
0.13 
0.97 
Idle 3 
738.33 
724.72 
718.33 
883.61 
766.25 
5.83 
0.00 
0.00 
0.93 
Rumination 4 
205.56 
211.67 
265.00 
166.94 
212.29 
11.47 
0.09 
0.00 
0.60 
Trough 5 
24.44 
65.28 
35.83 
44.17 
42.43 
25.52 
0.07 
0.00 
0.35 
TCT 6 
677.22 
650.00 
685.83 
512.22 
631.32 
7.09 
0.00 
0.00 
0.81 </p>

<p>CV, coefficient of variation; DM, dry matter; TDMI, total dry matter intake; NDFapI, intake of neutral detergent fiber corrected for the residual ash and 
protein; NFCI, non-fibrous carbohydrates intake; TCT, total chewing time. 
¹ G0, no glycerin; G5, 4.82% glycerin; G10, 10.12% glycerin; G15, 15.56% glycerin. 
2 Y = 477.470-7.66451X. 3 Y = 746.751-17.3654X+1.65228X 2 . 4 Y = 195.010+14.3312X-1.00058X 2 . 
5 Y = 30.6370+5.02204X-0.288225X 2 . 6 Y = 662.612-12.3434X+1.36405X 2 . </p>

<p>Facuri et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1584-1592 </p>

<p>
exclusive nature of each activity performed by an animal, 
therefore two activites cannot to be performed at the same 
time. In the present study, the rumination time was 
inversely proportional to the time the animals remained idle. 
Another explanation for the variation observed in grazing 
time is that the formation of cuds is proportional to the 
grazing time (Bremm et al., 2008). Under similar conditions 
to those of the present experiment, Farias et al. (2012) did 
not observe an effect of increasing levels of glycerin on the 
rumination time of heifers reared on pasture. Silva et al. 
(2005) also did not observe changes in the rumination time 
of supplemented grazing heifers. 
The time eating at the trough (trough; Table 3) was also 
quadratically affected (p&lt;0.05): with 8.8% addition of 
glycerin to the diet, the animals remained approximately 53 
minutes at the trough. This result is in line with the 
observation of Farias et al. (2012), who added 2.8%, 6.1%, 
and 9.1% glycerin to the diet of supplemented heifers on 
Brachiaria brizantha pasture. According to these authors, 
the increase in trough time with up to 6.1% of addition of 
glycerin to the diet was due to the difficulty shown by the 
animals to adapt to the glycerin. However, in the present 
study, it was observed that this adaptation difficulty 
occurred until glycerin reached 10% of the diet. After a 
certain level of ingestion, the animals would be used to the 
sweet taste of glycerin, which promoted rapid ingestion of 
the concentrate. We must stress that even with reduction of 
trough time with 15% of glycerin, concentrate intake was 
not lower. On the other hand, for Elam et al. (2008), 
addition of glycerin to the concentrate increased the time of 
permanence at the trough, due to the substitution of the time 
intended for grazing or rumination with the ingestion of 
concentrate (Bremm et al., 2005; Bremm et al., 2008). 
The TCT (grazing+rumination) was quadratically 
affected (p&lt;0.05) by addition of glycerin to the diet, and 
with 4.52% of glycerin, the animals took less time (634 
min) to consume the same amount of DM and NDF as those 
that were not fed glycerin (677 min). The behavioral 
variable TCT is linked to the grazing (Gary et al., 1970; 
Stricklin and Kauts-Scnavy, 1984) and rumination times. 
However, it can be observed that the behavior verified for </p>

<p>this variable was determined by the observations made, 
especially for grazing time (Table 3). 
The bite mass is the variable mainly responsible for the 
variation in the daily forage intake of grazing animals, 
because it is directly influenced by the sward structure 
(Hodgson and Jamieson, 1981), whereas the bite rate and 
grazing time have a secondary role (Forbes, 1988). In this 
context, in the present study, we observed that substitution 
of corn with increasing glycerin levels in the supplement of 
the heifers did not affect (p&gt;0.05) the bite mass (BITM, g 
DM/bite), since the forage allowance was the same for all 
the animals (Table 2). 
The bite rate (BITR, n of bites/min) was quadratically 
affected as well (p&lt;0.05), and addition of 10.39% glycerin 
to the diet caused the heifers to reach a maximum of 49.35 
bites per minute (Table 4). Addition of glycerin to the diet at 
up to 10% of the total DM might have led the animals to 
become more selective during grazing, causing them to 
travel longer distances and better choose the forage, seeking 
the best parts of the plants (Bremm et al., 2008). 
The variable number of bites/swallowed cud and 
number of bites/minute (BITM) increased linearly (p&lt;0.05), 
whereas the number of bites/day showed quadratic behavior 
(p&lt;0.05) with peak at glycerin inclusion of 8.2%, resulting 
in 22,440.7 bites/day, respectively (Table 4). Such 
variations were inversely proportional to the grazing time 
(Table 3) and to the bite rate (Table 4), which led to 
compensation in pasture DM intake maintaining the 
similarity of this variable among the treatments. 
The variable time spent per ruminated cud (time/cud) 
and number of chews per cud (chews/cud) were not 
influenced (p&gt;0.05) by the level of inclusion of glycerin in 
the total diet (Table 5). On the other hand, the number of 
cuds per day (cuds/d) was quadratically affected (p&lt;0.05), 
and with 6.8% glycerin the animals increased the number of 
cuds to 289.1, indicating a greater need to form cuds to be 
chewed. Once the cud was formed, the average chewing 
time was similar (p&gt;0.05) among the levels of replacement 
of corn by glycerin. The average number of chews/cud 
(46.05) was similar to that observed by Silva et al. (2005), 
who supplied different levels of supplement to heifers on a </p>

<p>Table 4. Influence of addition of glycerin levels on the bite traits in supplemented heifers on a Brachiaria brizantha pasture </p>

<p>Item 
Inclusion of glycerin (% DM) 1 
Mean 
CV 
p-value 
R 2 
G0 
G5 
G10 
G15 
L 
Q 
BITM 
0.23 
0.16 
0.22 
0.21 
0.20 
21.31 
0.65 
0.06 
-
BITR 2 
36.50 
45.35 
49.61 
46.08 
44.38 
11.99 
0.01 
0.01 
0.99 
BITN 3 
21.31 
43.85 
35.60 
44.80 
36.39 
14.80 
0.01 
0.01 
0.55 
BITmin 4 
35.47 
58.59 
43.39 
59.05 
49.13 
18.48 
0.00 
0.23 
0.38 
BITday 5 
16.746 
25.911 
18.278 
20.292 
20.307 
21.424 
0.01 
0.01 
0.67 </p>

<p>DM, dry matter; CV, coefficient of variation; BITM, bite mass (g DM/bite); BITR, bite rate (nof bites/min); BITN, number of bites per swallowed cud; 
BITmin, number of bites per minute; BITday, number of bites per day. 
1 G0, no glycerin; G5, 4.82% glycerin; G10, 10.12% glycerin; G15, 15.56% glycerin. 
2 Y = 36.3974+2.49261X-0.119867 X 2 . 3 Y = 41.1130+1.05087X; 4 Y = 46.0591+0.402337X. 5 Y = 18255.8+1023.38X-62.5678X 2 . </p>

<p>Facuri et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1584-1592 </p>



<p>Brachiaria decumbens pasture. Farias et al. (2012), on the 
other hand, observed quadratic effect on the same variable, 
adding crude glycerin to the diet of supplemented heifers on 
a Brachiaria brizantha pasture. 
Quadratic effect (p&lt;0.05) was observed on the number 
of periods of the activities performed by the heifers, with 
increments of 0.12 grazing periods (NGP), 11.59 idle 
periods (NIP) and 4.41 periods at the trough (NTP) with 
addition of 2.97%, 11.59%, and 8.14% glycerin to the diet, 
respectively. These results indicate that although there was 
reduction in the total grazing time (Table 3) and a trend 
towards reduction in NGP with levels of addition above 3% 
(Table 6), no reduction in pasture DM intake was observed 
(Table 3), which indicates that the animals utilized other 
behavioral elements to maintain the DM intake. However, 
addition of glycerin to the diet linearly reduced the number 
of rumination periods (NRP), which indicates that glycerin 
inclusion may affect both the total time (Table 3) and the 
number of rumination periods (Table 6) in a similar way. 
However, Farias et al. (2012) reported that both the duration 
(time) and number of rumination periods are affected by 
other types of mechanisms and not by the glycerin levels. 
The influence of the glycerin levels on NGP and NRP 
might have affected the behavior observed in NIP (Table 6), 
which was directly proportional to the total idle time (Table </p>

<p>3), demonstrating that the animals spent more time on this 
activity, which may be related to the metabolism of the 
glycerol present in the supplement with glycerin (Trabue et 
al., 2007). 
The increase in the number of visits to the trough (NTP 
= 5.85 times per day) up to the level of 8.1% glycerin may 
be related to the difficulty of animals to adapt to the 
glycerin, which made them ingest the concentrate in small 
quantities, without, however, interfering with the total 
concentrate intake. Yet, from 10% of inclusion of glycerin, 
the increase in its palatability or sweet taste and astringency 
made the animals start to consume the concentrate faster 
(Ooi et al., 2004). 
The time spent per grazing period (TGP) was influenced 
in a quadratic manner (p&lt;0.05), and 5.3% of glycerin in the 
DM caused the heifers to spend 20.39 minutes grazing in 
each period. Thus, we can observe that the interaction 
between the number of grazing periods and the time spent 
on this activity might have caused the reduction in the 
grazing time in min/day (Table 3). Likewise, the time per 
idle period was quadratically affected (p&lt;0.05) therefore, 
with addition of 5.27% glycerin the animals spent the least 
time idle (20.8 min) (Table 6). Like TGP, we can observe 
that the time spent in each idle period was the main factor 
influencing the total idle time in min/d (Table 3). </p>

<p>Table 5. Effect of addition of glycerin levels on the rumination characteristics of supplemented heifers on Brachiaria brizantha pastures </p>

<p>Activity 
Inclusion of glycerin (% DM) 1 
Mean 
CV 
p-value 
R 2 
G00 1 
G5 
G10 
G15 
L 
Q 
Cuds/d 1 
248.74 
260.34 
300.78 
201.21 
252.74 
18.43 
0.15 
0.01 
0.72 
Time/cud 
50.02 
49.52 
54.31 
50.35 
51.05 
13.42 
0.71 
0.45 
-
Chews/cud 
44.61 
44.67 
47.38 
47.52 
46.05 
14.49 
0.26 
1.00 
-</p>

<p>DM, dry matter; CV, coefficient of variation; Cuds/d, number of cuds per day; Time/cud, time spent per ruminated cud, in seconds; Chews/cud, number of 
chews per cud. 
¹ G0, no glycerin; G5, 4.82% glycerin; G10, 10.12% glycerin; G15, 15.56% glycerin. 
2 Y = 239.773+14.4516X-1.05749X 2 . </p>

<p>Table 6. Effect of addition of glycerin levels on the number of periods and duration (minutes) per period of the activities performed by 
supplemented heifers on a Brachiaria brizantha pasture </p>

<p>Item 
Inclusion of glycerin (% DM) 1 
Mean 
CV 
p-value 
R 2 
G0 
G5 
G10 
G15 
L 
Q 
NGP 2 
21.89 
20.78 
20.11 
12.77 
18.89 
13.72 
0.01 
0.01 
0.95 
NIP 3 
28.67 
33.00 
29.67 
21.22 
28.14 
9.18 
0.01 
0.01 
1.00 
NRP 4 
18.00 
7.67 
13.22 
6.89 
11.44 
27.13 
0.01 
0.06 
0.48 
NTP 5 
1.44 
7.33 
3.67 
3.44 
3.97 
33.43 
0.25 
0.01 
0.53 
TGP 6 
21.85 
21.32 
21.06 
27.56 
22.95 
14.74 
0.01 
0.01 
0.96 
TIP 7 
25.91 
22.08 
24.33 
42.29 
28.65 
11.73 
0.01 
0.01 
0.98 
TRP 8 
12.19 
29.11 
20.20 
25.32 
21.71 
24.03 
0.01 
0.01 
0.21 
TTP 9 
18.75 
9.08 
12.37 
13.71 
13.48 
43.68 
0.18 
0.01 
0.77 </p>

<p>DM, dry matter; CV, coefficient of variation; NGP, number of grazing; NRP, number of rumination, NIP, number of idle, NTP, number of trough periods; 
TGP, time per grazing; TRP, time per rumination; TIP, time per idle;TTP, time per trough periods. 
¹ G0, no glycerin; G5, 4.82% glycerin; G10, 10.12% glycerin; G15, 15.56% glycerin. 
2 Y = 21.5131+0.334327X-0.0562701X 2 . 3 Y = 28.8634+1.30488X-0.116100 X 2 . 4 Y = 15.4545-0.525912X. 
5 Y = 2.20020+0.896800X-0.0551019X 2 . 6 Y = 22.1855-0.683539X-0.0649817X 2 . 7 Y = 26.3569-2.10286X-0.199329X 2 . 
8 Y = 14.4841+2.23324X-0.106650X 2 . 9 Y = 17.86-1.7997X+0.1016X 2 . </p>

<p>Facuri et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1584-1592 </p>

<p>
The time per rumination period (TRP) was quadratically 
affected (p&lt;0.05), with peak at 10.46% glycerin addition 
with a 26.2 min of rumination in each period. In this case, 
the linear decrease in NRP was not sufficient to determine 
the total rumination time of heifers, in min/d (Table 3). 
Contrastingly, the variation observed in TRP was 
proportional to the variation observed in the total 
rumination time, in min/d (Table 3). 
The time per trough period was also quadratically 
affected (p&lt;0.05), decreasing to 10.89 min/period at the 
level of 8.85% glycerin. Although the animals increased the 
NTP, there was a reduction in the time they remained there. 
Thus, we can observe that the trough time (Table 3) was 
determined by increase in NTP and not by the NGP. 
Intakes of NDF, NFC, DM, pasture DM and concentrate 
DM as kg/meal (Table 7) were quadratically affected 
(p&lt;0.05), with minimum points of 0.23, 0.10, 0.04, 0.17, </p>

<p>and 0.52 kg with 5.22, 5.21, 6.06, 3.93, and 9.75% glycerin, 
respectively. Similarly, the rumination of NDF and NFC, 
DM, pasture DM, and concentrate DM as g/cud were 
quadratically affected (p&lt;0.05), reducing to 22.14, 9.89, 
4.38, 13.71, and 9.17 g/cud when glycerin was added at 
7.22%, 6.08%, 6.97%, 6.05%, and 6.30% to the diet. 
The feed efficiency represents the speed of ingestion of 
nutrients as a function of the time (Santana Jr et al., 2013). 
In this context, we can observe that the feed efficiencies of 
DM, NFC, concentrate DM and pasture DM, as kg/h, 
showed quadratic behavior (p&lt;0.05) (Table 7). The feed 
efficiencies of DM, NFC, and concentrate DM were lowest 
(0.77, 0.18, and 3.17) when glycerin was included at 2.55%, 
5.23%, and 10.06%, respectively. On the other hand, the 
feed efficiency of pasture DM was highest (0.51 kg/h) with 
addition of 4.25% glycerin. The feed efficiency of NDF, 
however, was positively and linearly affected with addition </p>

<p>Table 7. Effect of the levels of glycerin on intake, rumination, and feed and rumination efficiencies in supplemented heifers on a 
Brachiaria brizantha pasture </p>

<p>Items 
Inclusion of glycerin (% DM) 1 
Mean 
CV 
p-value 
R 2 
G0 
G5 
G10 
G15 
L 
Q 
Intake (kg/meal) 
DM 1 
0.28 
0.23 
0.28 
0.41 
0.30 
16.37 
0.01 
0.01 
1.00 
NDF 2 
0.12 
0.10 
0.12 
0.18 
0.13 
16.11 
0.01 
0.01 
1.00 
NFC 3 
0.06 
0.05 
0.05 
0.08 
0.06 
24.16 
0.01 
0.01 
1.00 
Pasture DM 4 
0.18 
0.19 
0.20 
0.32 
0.22 
17.23 
0.01 
0.01 
0.94 
Conc. DM 5 
2.02 
0.37 
0.98 
0.84 
1.05 
59.70 
0.01 
0.01 
0.69 
Rumination (g/cud) 
DM 6 
26.25 
25.71 
22.23 
33.77 
26.99 
20.06 
0.02 
0.01 
0.77 
NDF 7 
11.35 
11.15 
9.61 
14.81 
11.73 
19.04 
0.01 
0.01 
0.78 
NFC 8 
5.77 
5.07 
4.19 
6.96 
5.50 
27.98 
0.25 
0.01 
0.85 
Pasture DM 9 
15.73 
15.48 
13.33 
20.66 
16.30 
19.16 
0.01 
0.01 
0.78 
Conc. DM 10 
10.53 
10.22 
8.90 
13.11 
10.69 
27.74 
0.15 
0.03 
0.77 
Feed efficiency (kg/h) 
DM 11 
0.78 
0.78 
0.86 
1.02 
0.86 
12.11 
0.01 
0.02 
0.82 
NDF 12 
0.31 
0.39 
0.40 
0.50 
0.40 
19.16 
0.01 
0.67 
0.93 
NFC 13 
0.18 
0.18 
0.17 
0.24 
0.19 
27.44 
0.01 
0.02 
0.93 
Pasture DM 14 
0.49 
0.54 
0.56 
0.70 
0.58 
13.30 
0.01 
0.09 
0.86 
Conc. DM 15 
6.67 
2.46 
4.59 
3.60 
4.33 
32.67 
0.01 
0.01 
0.53 
Rumination efficiency (kg/h) 
DM 16 
1.89 
1.87 
1.47 
2.43 
1.91 
17.03 
0.01 
0.01 
0.99 
NDF 17 
0.81 
0.81 
0.64 
1.06 
0.83 
15.50 
0.01 
0.01 
0.68 
NFC 18 
0.41 
0.37 
0.27 
0.50 
0.39 
17.01 
0.06 
0.01 
0.97 
Pasture DM 19 
1.13 
1.13 
0.89 
1.48 
1.16 
15.68 
0.01 
0.01 
0.68 
Conc. DM 20 
0.76 
0.74 
0.58 
0.94 
0.76 
26.74 
0.19 
0.01 
0.68 </p>



<p>Facuri et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1584-1592 </p>



<p>of the glycerin levels (p&lt;0.05) (Table 7). 
The quadratic effect observed in the present study 
demonstrates that from 2.5% glycerin in the diet, the intake 
efficiency of heifers improved by approximately 30% in 
relation to the feed efficiency of the animals that consumed 
the supplement without glycerin. These results are in line 
with those obtained by Farias et al. (2012), who, with the 
addition of up to 3.8% glycerin to the diet of heifers reared 
on pasture the DM feed efficiency decreased, but then it 
improved again until 9.1% of addition of glycerin. 
The use of low-digestibility feeds is controlled by the 
rumination efficiency; higher feed intake and better 
productive performance are promoted by higher amounts of 
ruminated feed during 8 or 9 hours, typical for rumination 
(Stricklin and Kautz-Scanavy, 1984). The rumination 
efficiency of DM, NDF, NFC, and DM from the pasture and 
concentrate were quadratically influenced, with minimum 
points of 1.58, 0.69, 0.30, 0.96, and 0.63 kg/h when the 
glycerin levels added were 6.48%, 6.40%, 7.16%, 6.35%, 
and 6.70%, respectively. 
The effects of use of NDF observed in this study 
indicate that since glycerin is devoid of NDF in its 
composition, when it is utilized in the supplementation of 
animals managed on pasture, it is effective in maintaining 
the feed and rumination activities, given that no influence as 
regards DM intake was observed in this study. Thus, we can 
infer that levels similar to those utilized in this study did not 
impair forage intake. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Addition of glycerin in substitution of corn in 
supplements for animals managed on pastures does not 
influence feed intake, but reduces the grazing time and 
increases the idle time; this indicates that glycerol acts as a 
gluconeogenic precursor, which increases satiety. Glycerin 
supplementation also improves the use of DM and neutral 
detergent fiber from pasture and concentrate through the 
better feed and rumination efficiencies. </p>



<p>Facuri et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1584-1592 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>