<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4107842" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The promotion of choice and control for older people is a policy priority for social 
care services in the United Kingdom and is at the heart of recent drives to personalise 
services. Increasingly, we are seeing a move away from institutionalised care (e.g. in 
care homes) towards enablement, with more services being delivered in community-
based settings. Extra care housing has been promoted as a purpose-built, community-
based alternative to residential care for older people. However, whilst accounts of 
users' experiences in particular service types are plentiful, the use of different 
instrumentation and measures makes comparison between settings difficult. We 
combined data from four studies where participants were older people either living in 
care homes or extra care housing or receiving care at home. All of these studies asked 
participants to rate their control over daily life, using the Adult Social Care Outcomes 
Toolkit (ASCOT). This paper presents the results of an ordinal logistic regression 
analysis indicating that, after controlling for differences in age, ability to perform 
activities of daily living and self-rated health, setting had a significant effect on older 
people's sense of control. Residents in care homes and extra care housing report 
similar levels of control over daily life but consistently report feeling more in control 
than older people receiving care at home. Implications for policy and practice are 
discussed. </p>

<p>The promotion of choice and control for older people is a policy priority for 
both health and social care services in the United Kingdom (UK) and is at 
the heart of recent drives to personalise services and move service users 
and carers on to personal budgets (PBs) (Department of Health ; HM 
Government ). Research has indicated that personalisation in the form </p>

<p>* Personal Social Services Research Unit, University of Kent, Canterbury, UK. </p>

<p>Ageing &amp; Society , , -. f Cambridge University Press  
The online version of this article is published within an Open Access environment subject 
to the conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 
licence &lt; http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/./ &gt; . The written permission 
of Cambridge University Press must be obtained for commercial re-use. 
doi:./SX </p>

<p> </p>

<p>of PBs can deliver positive outcomes, including increased control, for 
services users (Glendinning et al. ; Hatton and Waters ). However, 
there is also evidence that older people may not in fact experience increased 
control over their lives when using PBs (Hatton and Waters ; 
Netten et al. b; Slay ). Various suggestions have been put forward 
in attempting to explain this: it may be that the process of planning and 
managing a PB results in greater anxiety for older people than younger 
people (Netten et al. b); PBs for older people are often much lower 
than for other groups (Slay ); and older people may be less likely to 
use PBs in ways found to be associated with positive outcomes, such as taking 
the PB as a direct payment, and are more likely to have their PB managed 
by the council, therefore not truly gaining control (Hatton and Waters 
). </p>

<p>In addition, a recent inquiry into older people and human rights in home 
care by the Equality and Human Rights Commission (EHRC) raised 
concerns about the effectiveness of PBs and direct payments for offering 
older people more choice and control (EHRC ). The EHRC found 
evidence of PBs being delivered poorly, with some older people finding the 
responsibilities of PBs daunting and disempowering and others 'being 
moved onto budgets managed by the local authority without gaining any 
choice and control over care provision' (: ). 
For older people receiving care, it seems that having control is less to do 
with managing by oneself and more to do with having control over the 
delegation of their care and responsibilities (Bamford and Bruce ; 
Qureshi et al. ) and influencing how and when care and support 
is delivered (Gabriel and Bowling ; Qureshi and Henwood ; 
Qureshi et al. ). What older people describe as being important to them 
is having control over their daily lives (Hayden, Boaz and Taylor ; Raynes 
; Tester et al. ) with personalised, responsive services, regardless of </p>

<p>how their funding is arranged (EHRC ). However, an increasing 
challenge for policy makers and practitioners is how best to provide this 
when faced with a growing population of older people with diverse needs 
and wishes. 
Increasingly, we have seen a move away from institutionalised care (e.g. in 
care homes) towards 'enablement', with more services being delivered in 
community-based settings (Department of Health ; Windle et al. ). 
Indeed, key to the policies of previous and current UK governments has 
been the aim to help people maintain their independence in their own 
homes for as long as possible, receiving domiciliary care and adaptations 
to their home as needed (Department for Communities and Local 
Government ; Department of Health ; Office of the Deputy 
Prime Minister ). Ageing in place can be problematic, however, not </p>

<p> Lisa Callaghan and Ann-Marie Towers </p>

<p>least because much of Britain's housing stock is unsuitable for adaptation 
(Darton and Muncer ). Restricted to living in only one or two rooms, 
many older people report being prisoners in their own homes, socially 
isolated and at risk from depression and anxiety (Baker ; Bartholomeou 
; Oldman ; Riseborough and Niner ). In some instances, </p>

<p>systemic failings in the delivery of domiciliary care have led to some older 
people's basic human rights being failed (EHRC ). Accounts of the 
negative aspects of 'staying put' (Aronson ; Barrett, Hale and Gauld 
; EHRC ) have led some to question the 'rightness' of striving to </p>

<p>maintain independence when living alone with increasing frailty (Aronson 
; Boyle ; Dalley ). </p>

<p>Housing with care, such as extra care housing (ECH) or continuing care 
retirement communities, has been promoted as a purpose-built, community-
based alternative to moving into residential care for older people (e.g. 
Department of Health ). It aims to meet the housing, care and support 
needs of older people, while helping them to maintain independence in 
private accommodation (Department of Health ), and is seen as a 
positive option for older people in current social care policy (Department of 
Health ). Key features of ECH are that it is primarily for older people; 
accommodation is self-contained; care is delivered flexibly by staff often 
based onsite; staff are available  hours a day; domestic care is available; 
meals are usually available; and it offers security of tenure (Laing and 
Buisson ). The expectation is that ECH will afford older people a 
greater sense of control over their lives than more institutional settings, such 
as care homes, whilst avoiding the pitfalls of 'staying put', such as disjointed 
care, social isolation and inappropriate housing. 
There have been several studies in which older people living in ECH have 
been asked about their experiences and have reported high levels of 
satisfaction (see Croucher, Hicks and Jackson ). Feeling that they have 
retained more control over their lives than they would have in residential 
care is frequently mentioned as being valued. However, the evidence has 
largely come from evaluations of new and innovative housing with care 
schemes, which market themselves as promoting independence and 
providing positive alternatives to institutional models of care (Croucher, 
Hicks and Jackson ). In fact, a recent study of the expectations and 
experiences of older people moving into residential care (Darton ) 
suggests that the expectation that residential care is associated with a total 
loss of control and independence can be overly pessimistic. Most of the 
 residents, interviewed after settling into a care home, told researchers </p>

<p>they had more control over their lives than they had expected before moving 
in and the percentage rating their quality of life as good or very good rose by 
 per cent (Darton ). Furthermore, Boyle () found that older </p>

<p> 
Older people's experiences in different care settings </p>

<p>people in residential care experienced the most control and people 
receiving domiciliary care the least, when she conducted semi-structured 
interviews with older people living in care homes (residential and nursing) 
or in the community. 
Surprisingly, studies such as Boyle's () are difficult to find in the UK 
literature. There has been seemingly little research directly comparing older 
people's sense of control in different care settings, despite the policy agenda. 
Most research has tended to look more broadly at older people's experiences 
in a single setting: care homes (Bowers et al. ; Darton ; Kane et al. 
; Raynes ; Taylor et al. ; Train et al. ); ECH (Bäumker et al. 
; Callaghan, Netten and Darton ; see also Croucher, Hicks and </p>

<p>Jackson  for a review) or home care (Aronson ; Barrett, Hale and 
Gauld ; EHRC ; Raynes et al. ). Where comparisons have been 
made, they have tended to focus on broader quality of life issues or physical 
and cognitive functioning, and have focused on comparing two main care 
options, such as extra care to domiciliary care (Bernard et al. ; Gardner, 
Browning and Kendig ; Kingston et al. ; Kneale ), extra care to 
residential care (Darton et al. a) or domiciliary care to residential care 
(Boyle ). 
Thus, important questions remain about the relative benefits of different 
settings with respect to control over daily life. Comparisons are difficult to 
make because where studies have asked about 'control', they have done so in 
different ways using a variety of scales and methods. Studies typically have a 
broader focus on user satisfaction, wellbeing or quality of life, and although 
control is frequently mentioned, it has not always been asked about in a way 
that is easily quantifiable. There is also the issue that people use the term 
'control' interchangeably with concepts such as autonomy, independence, </p>

<p>locus of control and many more (see Skinner  for a review of relevant 
terminology). For the purposes of this paper, we are talking specifically 
about control over daily life, which is desired and valued by service users 
(Hayden, Boaz and Taylor ; Raynes ; Tester et al. ) and 
defined here within the framework of social care-related quality of life 
(SCRQoL) (Netten et al. a). </p>

<p>Social care-related quality of life </p>

<p>The Adult Social Care Outcomes Toolkit (ASCOT) (Netten et al. a) has 
been developed and designed to measure those aspects of quality of life 
specifically relating to social care and can be applied across different care 
settings (http://www.pssru.ac.uk/ascot/). A series of studies has investigated 
and tested the domains of quality of life most relevant to social care in a </p>

<p> Lisa Callaghan and Ann-Marie Towers </p>

<p>number of different contexts, including in care homes for older people and 
people with a learning disability (Netten et al. , c), day centres for 
older people (Caiels et al. ) and an evaluation of individual budgets 
(Glendinning et al. ). The items have demonstrated good construct 
validity with older people (Malley et al. ). The eight domains of SCRQoL 
that the ASCOT measure draws on are described in Table . 
The ASCOT was developed over a number of years and through a variety 
of studies, meaning that the wording of some of the domains has changed 
significantly over time and between studies. However, the control over daily life 
domain has changed relatively little and what differences do exist can be 
largely resolved through some simple recoding and collapsing of response 
categories (see Method section for further details). Over the course of four 
different research studies (Callaghan, Netten and Darton ; Netten et al. 
, a; Towers ), we have collected data about older people's </p>

<p>control over daily life in different care settings. Thus, the aim of this paper is to 
examine the association between control over daily life and the setting in 
which older people receive care and support (be that in ECH, care homes or 
at home). </p>

<p>T A B L E . Social care-related quality of life (SCRQoL) domains </p>

<p>Domains of SCRQoL 
Definition </p>

<p>Personal cleanliness and 
comfort </p>

<p>The service user feels he/she is personally clean and 
comfortable and looks presentable or, at best, is dressed and 
groomed in a way that reflects his/her personal preferences. 
Safety 
The service user feels safe and secure. This means being free 
from fear of abuse, falling or other physical harm, and fear of 
being attacked or robbed. 
Control over daily life 
The service user can choose what to do and when to do it, 
having control over his/her daily life and activities. 
Accommodation cleanliness 
and comfort </p>

<p>The service user feels their home environment, including all 
the rooms, is clean and comfortable. 
Food and nutrition 
The service user feels he/she has a nutritious, varied and 
culturally appropriate diet with enough food and drink that 
he/she enjoys at regular and timely intervals. 
Occupation 
The service user is sufficiently occupied in a range of 
meaningful activities, whether it be formal employment, 
unpaid work, caring for others or leisure activities. 
Social participation and 
involvement </p>

<p>The service user is content with their social situation, where 
social situation is taken to mean the sustenance of 
meaningful relationships with friends, family and feeling 
involved or part of a community, should this be important to 
the service user. 
Dignity 
The negative and positive psychological impact of support 
and care on the service user's personal sense of significance. </p>

<p>Source : http://www.pssru.ac.uk/ascot/domains.php. </p>

<p> 
Older people's experiences in different care settings </p>

<p>Method </p>

<p>The research procedures for each project received ethical approval from an 
appropriate board, and information collected was subject to informed 
consent. </p>

<p>Study : 'Social Well-being in Extra Care Housing' project </p>

<p>Between  and , the Personal Social Services Research Unit 
(PSSRU) at the University of Kent undertook an evaluation of the first two 
rounds of the English Department of Health's £ million Extra Care 
Housing Funding Initiative (-), evaluating  new-build ECH 
schemes that received initial support from the fund and which opened 
between  and  (Darton et al. b; Netten et al. a). 
Each scheme planned to provide social activities for residents and facilitate 
community participation. This presented an opportunity to add to the data 
being collected by investigating the development of the social life of these 
schemes and exploring the social wellbeing of residents. This aspect of the 
work was funded by the Joseph Rowntree Foundation (JRF), and research was 
carried out over three years, between  and  (Callaghan, Netten and 
Darton ). The project involved  of the schemes included in the main 
evaluation. It focused on the first year after each scheme opened, and aimed 
to identify how schemes had begun to develop community and social activities 
during their first six months. Following this, differences in individual social 
wellbeing in schemes one year after opening were identified. 
The data used for the analysis described here were collected through a 
structured questionnaire which included questions about the social life at the 
scheme, levels of participation and barriers to taking part, contact with friends 
and family, as well as overall quality of life and self-perceived health (SPH). 
This questionnaire also included the control over daily life question from the 
ASCOT. Trained fieldworkers for each scheme were available to offer support 
in completing this questionnaire, and in fact many residents preferred to take 
up this option. All residents were invited to take part, and  completed 
questionnaires were received. For the purposes of this paper, we draw on a 
subset () of these questionnaires, only using those from people living in 
extra care schemes (not villages) and receiving care. The project also made 
use of information collected as part of the main evaluation about residents' 
demographic information, health, dependency and service receipt. </p>

<p>Study : 'Measuring the Outcomes of Care Homes' project </p>

<p>This research project was part of the 'Measuring Outcomes for Public Service 
Users' (MOPSU) project, which was funded over three years (-) by </p>

<p> Lisa Callaghan and Ann-Marie Towers </p>

<p>the Treasury under the Invest to Save budget and led by the Office for 
National Statistics. The aim of the project was to develop and test an 
approach to measuring outcomes of the care and support provided to 
residents of care homes for older people and people with learning 
disabilities (Netten et al. ). 
The project developed and tested a multi-method approach to measuring 
outcomes to address the challenge of obtaining meaningful data from care 
home residents who may be very vulnerable and have cognitive impairments 
or communication difficulties. As part of this multi-method approach, 
fieldworkers conducted structured observations and interviews with staff. </p>

<p>Where residents had capacity to consent and were able to understand the 
questions and communicate their responses, structured, face-to-face inter-
views also took place. 
The care homes that took part in the study were randomly selected from 
homes in England that had recently been or were imminently due an 
inspection by the regulator, which at the time was the Commission for Social 
Care Inspection. The study aimed to include a representative number of care 
homes from all quality ratings (poor, adequate, good and excellent), 
however, we had difficulty recruiting homes rated as 'poor' to the study and 
these were under-represented in the sample (Netten et al. ). 
Detailed data were collected by trained fieldworkers for up to five 
residents per home. Information about the residents' age, ethnicity, physical 
functioning, and care and nursing needs was collected alongside data on 
SCRQoL, as measured by the ASCOT. Final ASCOT ratings were based on 
the evidence collected using the multi-method approach. For those unable 
to take part in a structured interview, ASCOT scores are based on fieldworker 
observations and staff ratings. This is not comparable to the other studies 
reported here, where service user views were collected directly through 
interviews. Consequently, for the purposes of the present analysis, we have 
included only those residents that took part in the face-to-face interviews and 
gave their own ratings control over daily life as measured by the ASCOT. This 
is directly comparable with the other studies included in this analysis. </p>

<p>Study : 'Control and Well-being' project </p>

<p>This project was conducted as part of the PSSRU's programme of research 
funded by the English Department of Health (Towers ). The project 
involved comparing older people's sense of control and psychological 
wellbeing in care homes and ECH in two local authorities in England. It also 
collected information about how much control people had over various 
aspects of their daily routine and examined whether there was an association 
between this and feeling in control. The research question was whether good </p>

<p> 
Older people's experiences in different care settings </p>

<p>quality care homes could afford their residents as much choice and control 
as housing with care schemes. Consequently, all the care homes that took 
part in the study were considered to be good homes by the local authority 
and had met or exceeded the regulator's standards for 'Choice and Control'. 
Local authorities also considered all of the participating extra care schemes 
to be providing good quality housing and care. 
Trained fieldworkers conducted face-to-face interviews with  older 
people living in care homes (N = ) and very sheltered housing (a precursor 
to extra care) (N = ). Information in addition to the ASCOT control over 
daily life question included: residents' demographic information, health and 
dependency, questions about control over daily routine and subjective 
wellbeing. For the purposes of this paper, only the care home sample has 
been included in the analysis and merged with the care home sample from 
Study  to boost sample sizes. </p>

<p>Study : 'Outcomes of Social Care for Adults' project </p>

<p>The overall aim of this project was to develop the final version of the ASCOT 
preference-weighted measure of outcome that would reflect the impact on 
and value of social care to those who use such services (Netten et al. a). 
The project consisted of two stages. The first phase involved development 
and feasibility work while during the second phase the preference weights 
for the final measure were estimated. 
As part of the development of the measure, the questions were tested 
through the annual user experience survey (UES) conducted by local 
councils. During , ten councils across England took part in the UES 
of older people (aged over ) receiving home care services. From the 
respondents to the UES, a sampling frame was generated from those who 
indicated that they would be happy to take part in further research. This 
resulted in a sample of  people (a response rate of %), which is the 
sample used for the analysis presented in this paper. Data were collected 
through face-to-face interviews, and interviewers were briefed prior to 
interviewing. Information in addition to the SCRQoL questions included 
demographic characteristics, service receipt, quality of life and psychological 
wellbeing, health, dependency, feelings of control, social contact and 
support, and participation in groups and volunteering. </p>

<p>Current analysis </p>

<p>As described above, the aim of the current project was to examine the 
association between control over daily life and the setting in which older 
people receive care and support (be that in ECH, care homes or at home). </p>

<p> Lisa Callaghan and Ann-Marie Towers </p>

<p>Measures. Social care-related quality of life : The wording used for the </p>

<p>control over daily life question was slightly different across the four projects 
described above. However, the question measures the same underlying 
concepts, and in analysis particular categories are used to indicate 'high', 
'some' and 'no' needs in each domain. This is in keeping with the latest </p>

<p>ASCOT terminology (www.pssru.ac.uk/ASCOT). Table  shows the question 
wording for each category, and the level of need each was designed to 
indicate. For each variable, scores were recoded to indicate no need, some 
need or high need. </p>

<p>Dependency and health: The four projects collected a variety of data about </p>

<p>participants' demographic characteristics, health and dependency. For the 
present analysis, we only included measures that were common to them all. 
For dependency, each project included some of the questions used to make 
up the Barthel Index of Activities of Daily Living (Mahoney and Barthel 
), a summary measure used to indicate the participant's ability to </p>

<p>perform a range of 'activities of daily living' (ADLs), such as getting in and 
out of bed, moving around inside the home and using the toilet. Each item is 
scored according to four levels of ability, indicating ability to do the activity 
'on your own without difficulty', 'on your own with difficulty', 'only with help' </p>

<p>or 'not at all'. If all items are used, an index can be computed to indicate 
dependency on a scale. </p>

<p>T A B L E . Wording of control question and level of need </p>

<p>Question wording 
Level of need </p>

<p>Setting: Extra care housing: 
Which of the following statements best describes your present situation? 
I feel in control of my daily life 
No needs 
The help I get here helps me feel in control of my daily life 
No needs 
I have some control over my daily life but not enough 
Some needs 
I have no control over my daily life 
High needs 
Setting: Care homes: 
Which of the following statements best describes how much control you 
have over your daily life? 
I feel in control of my daily life 
No needs 
With help I feel in control of my daily life 
No needs 
I have some control over my daily life but not enough 
Some needs 
I have no control over my daily life 
High needs 
Setting: Receiving care at home: 
Which of the following statements best describes how much control you 
have over your daily life? 
I have as much control over my daily life as I want 
No needs 
I have adequate control over my daily life 
No needs 
I have some control over my daily life but not enough 
Some needs 
I have no control over my daily life 
High needs </p>

<p> 
Older people's experiences in different care settings </p>

<p>Six items (out of a possible ten) from this measure were present across all 
datasets, and so these items were used to indicate dependency in the current 
analysis. These six items measured: ability to wash face and hands; to use the 
toilet; to get in and out of bed or chair; to get around indoors; to get dressed 
and undressed; and to use the bath or shower. Scores for each item could 
range from  to , and were summed to give a dependency score from  
(total independence) to  (most dependent). Cronbach's alpha for these 
six items was ., showing very good internal reliability. 
Additional information that was available consistently across all three 
projects was age group, gender and SPH. The SPH question used was that 
recommended by the World Health Organisation (WHO-Europe ), 
and asks respondents to rate their general health on a five-point scale, with 
scores ranging from  ('very good') to  ('very bad'). </p>

<p>Analysis. Data were analysed using a variety of techniques, reflecting the </p>

<p>different levels of measurement of the variables of interest. For comparisons 
between participants in different settings, chi-squared (χ  ) tests were used 
when the variable was categorical in nature, using Cramer's V as a measure of 
strength of association. When the variable was continuous, t-tests or analysis 
of variance were used. Post-hoc comparisons (the Scheffé test) were used 
where appropriate to compare differences between groups. 
To explore relationships between background variables and outcome 
variables, non-parametric tests of correlation were employed (Spearman's 
rho). Chi-squared (χ  ) tests of association were used to explore relationships 
between the outcome variables and setting. 
Ordinal logistic regression was used to assess whether there was an 
independent effect of setting on feelings of control over daily life, 
controlling for the effects of background variables as necessary. The 
statistical analyses were undertaken using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">PASW Statistics</rs> , release 
version .. (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., ) computer program. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Participants </p>

<p>The sample used for the current analysis comprised of all those participants 
in the samples described above who had the opportunity to answer the 
question on control over daily life, and who were aged over . We excluded 
the very sheltered housing residents from Study  on the basis that these 
housing models were not directly comparable to newer extra care schemes 
from Study . A large number of participants from the ECH sample were not 
receiving care and support. To make sure the groups from different settings </p>

<p> Lisa Callaghan and Ann-Marie Towers </p>

<p>were comparable, we restricted the sample to only those people who were 
receiving care and support. Previous PSSRU research into extra care has 
indicated that people living in extra care schemes and people living in extra 
care villages are quite different in terms of their dependency, with village 
residents being less dependent, and that the experiences of those living 
in schemes and villages can be quite different (Bäumker et al. ; 
Callaghan, Netten and Darton ), and so for the ECH sample, we also 
excluded those people living in villages (N = ) (due to the small number, it 
was not feasible to analyse them as a separate group). This resulted in a total 
sample of  people:  people from ECH,  people from care homes 
and  people receiving care at home. 
The care home sample used in the analysis for this paper was made up of care 
home residents drawn from two studies (Studies  and  described above). 
However, tests indicated that there were no significant differences between 
these two groups on any of the demographic, health or dependency variables. 
The care home sample drawn from the 'Measuring Outcomes of Care 
Homes' project (N = ) was a subsample of the larger sample used in the 
original study (N = ), representing those people who were able to take 
part in an interview and self-report. Tests indicated that there was no 
difference in the proportions of men to women between the self-report 
group and the rest of the sample, in age or in SPH scores, but that the 
subsample were significantly less dependent than the rest of the sample, 
with a mean dependency score of . (standard deviation (SD) = .) 
compared to . (SD = .) (t = ., degrees of freedom (df) = , 
p &lt; .). This difference is to be expected given that only the most able 
care home residents are able to take part in structured interviews. 
The majority of people in our final sample as a whole (approximately 
%) were aged between  and . Twenty-two per cent were over  and </p>

<p>the minority remaining were between  and  (exact age was not available 
for all samples, so is not reported here). Seventy per cent of the sample were 
female, a proportion that might be expected among the older population 
(Office for National Statistics ). Forty-four per cent of participants rated 
their health as fair, while a further  per cent rated their health as good or 
very good. The remainder rated their health as bad or very bad. In terms of 
dependency, the average score on our measure of help needed with ADLs 
was . (SD = ., range = -). Information on marital status was not 
available for the care home participants, so is not reported here. </p>

<p>Key differences related to setting </p>

<p>In order to check for covariates of setting that may have an effect on control 
scores, differences between participants in the four settings were examined. </p>

<p> 
Older people's experiences in different care settings </p>

<p>Table  shows the characteristics of participants in each setting. There was 
a significant difference in age according to setting (χ  = ., df=, 
p &lt; .; Cramer's V = ., p &lt; .). In extra care schemes, there were 
fewer people over the age of  than might be expected if there was no 
relationship. In contrast, in care homes, there were more people than might 
be expected over the age of , but fewer people than might be expected 
aged - and aged -. More people living at home were aged - 
than might be expected, and fewer of this group were aged over . 
Although exact age was not available, we might surmise that care home 
residents were the oldest on average, which is unsurprising given that the 
profile of people living in care homes is becoming older and increasingly 
dependent (Laing and Buisson ). There was no significant relationship 
between gender and setting. 
There was a significant relationship between SPH and setting (χ  = ., 
df = , p &lt; .; Cramer's V = ., p &lt; .), with more extra care 
residents than expected rating their health as 'fair', but fewer rating their </p>

<p>T A B L E . Characteristics of participants in each setting </p>

<p>Extra care 
housing 
(N = ) </p>

<p>Care homes 
(N = ) </p>

<p>Receiving care 
at home 
(N = ) </p>

<p>p 
N 
% 
N 
% 
N 
% </p>

<p>Age group: 
- 
 
. 
 
 . 
 
. 
&lt; . 
- 
 
. 
 
. 
 
. 
- 
 
. 
 
. 
 
. 
 and over 
 
. 
 
. 
 
. 
Missing 
 
  
 </p>

<p>Gender: 
Male 
 
. 
 
. 
 
. 
. 
Female 
 
. 
 
. 
 
. 
Missing 
 
 
 </p>

<p>Self-perceived health: 
Very good 
 
 . 
 
. 
 
. 
&lt; . 
Good 
 
. 
 
. 
 
. 
Fair 
 
. 
 
. 
 
. 
Bad 
 
. 
 
. 
 
. 
Very bad 
 
 . 
 
 . 
 
. 
Missing 
 
 
 </p>

<p>Dependency -ADL score: 
Mean 
. 
. 
. 
. 
Standard deviation 
. 
. 
. 
Range 
- 
- 
- 
Missing 
 
 
 </p>

<p>Note : ADL: activities of daily living. </p>

<p> Lisa Callaghan and Ann-Marie Towers </p>

<p>health as very good. People receiving care at home were also less likely to rate 
their health as very good, and were more likely to rate their health as bad. In 
contrast, care home residents were more likely to rate their health as good or 
very good, and less likely to rate it as bad or very bad. 
Turning to dependency, as measured by level of need for help with ADLs, 
again there was a significant relationship with setting (F(, ) = ., 
p = .). Post-hoc comparison tests (Scheffé) indicated that the only 
significant difference was that people receiving care at home were more 
dependent than care home residents ( p = .); higher scores indicating 
greater dependency. These results are likely to reflect the fact that our care 
home sample includes only the less-dependent care home residents; those 
able to take part in the structured interviews. </p>

<p>Relationships between background variables </p>

<p>The relationships between these background variables (dependency, SPH, 
age and gender) were tested. There was a significant relationship between 
dependency and SPH (r = ., p &lt; .) with greater dependency related 
to worse SPH, and between dependency and age (r = À ., p = .), with 
older age being associated -surprisingly -with being less dependent. When 
examined by setting (extra care, care home and home care), the association 
between age and dependency was only significant for older home care 
recipients. This relationship is not present in the population from which it 
was drawn, which had a higher proportion of older people aged over  years 
old (Malley et al. ). Perhaps, in the very top age bands, only the most 
able home care recipients agreed to take part in the research, explaining the 
weak but significant relationship we have found here. Age was also associated 
with gender, with women being older on average than men (r = ., 
p &lt; .). </p>

<p>Control over daily life </p>

<p>Control over daily life was significantly related to dependency (r = À ., 
p &lt; .) and SPH (r = À ., p &lt; .), with greater dependency and 
worse SPH associated with feeling less in control. Older age was associated 
with feeling more in control (r = ., p = .) but when this was examined 
by setting, the relationship only held in ECH. There was no association with 
gender. 
Table  shows that feelings of control over daily life varied according to 
setting (χ  = ., df=, p &lt; .; Cramer's V = ., p &lt; .). More 
extra care scheme residents and more care home residents had 'no needs' 
(i.e. felt that they had control over their daily lives) than might be expected if </p>

<p> 
Older people's experiences in different care settings </p>

<p>there was no association, compared with fewer than expected people 
receiving care at home. Fewer extra care scheme residents and fewer care 
home residents, but more people receiving care at home, had some needs 
than might be expected. More people receiving care at home had high 
needs than might be expected. 
These results are interesting, but the associations presented earlier 
between some of the background variables and setting indicate that it is 
important to control for potential confounds (dependency, age and SPH) in 
order to assess whether setting has an independent effect on feelings of control 
over daily life. In order to do this, ordinal logistic regression (Hosmer and 
Lemeshow ; Tabachnick and Fidell ) was used to assess the unique 
effect of setting on level of control while background factors (dependency, 
SPH and age) were controlled. The goal here was specifically to study the 
association between control and setting, rather than to predict category 
membership; ordinal regression can be used for either or both (Norusis 
). </p>

<p>Although ordinal regression has fewer assumptions than multiple linear 
regression, there are nonetheless a number of assumptions that must be met 
(Norusis ; Strand, Cadwallader and Firth ). Initial models failed 
some of the assumptions, mainly due to extremely high numbers of empty 
cells produced by combinations of the variables of interest. In order to 
address this, some categories of the SPH and age variables which contained 
few responses were collapsed (in the case of SPH, 'good' and 'very good', and 
'bad' and 'very bad' were grouped together, while the age groups - and 
- were also combined). Nonetheless, the final model still contained a </p>

<p>large number of cells with low or zero counts, meaning that goodness-of-fit 
tests must be treated with caution (Norusis ; Strand, Cadwallader and </p>

<p>T A B L E . Control over daily life by setting </p>

<p>Extra care schemes 
(N = ) </p>

<p>Care homes 
(N = ) </p>

<p>Receiving care at home 
(N = ) </p>

<p>No needs: 
Count (%) 
 (.) 
 (.) 
 (.) 
Expected count 
. 
. 
. 
Adjusted residual 
. 
 . 
À . </p>

<p>Some needs: 
Count (%) 
 (.) 
 (.) 
 (.) 
Expected count 
. 
  . 
  . 
Adjusted residual 
À . 
À . 
 . </p>

<p>High needs: 
Count (%) 
 (.) 
 (.) 
 (.) 
Expected count 
. 
  . 
  . 
Adjusted residual 
À . 
À . 
 . </p>

<p> Lisa Callaghan and Ann-Marie Towers </p>

<p>Firth ). The ratio of case to variables was acceptable, even when 
accounting for missing variables. The Test of Parallel Lines indicated that 
the assumption of proportional odds was met. 
The ordinal regression model contained four explanatory variables: 
setting (the key variable of interest), age group, SPH and dependency (ADL 
score). Gender was removed from the model as it was not found to be 
significant. The outcome variable was control over daily life, with three levels: 
high needs (no control), some needs (some control but not enough) and no 
needs (in control of daily life). The model was a significant improvement 
over the baseline (intercept only) model, χ  (,) = ., p &lt; .. 
It analysed  cases and excluded  due to missing data on one or 
more variables. The model explained between  per cent (Cox and Snell 
R  ) and  per cent (Nagelkerke R  ) of the variance in feelings of control, 
and the model fit statistics suggested that the model was a good fit although, 
as noted above, this should be treated with caution. As the proportion of 
variance explained is fairly low, the model is likely to be a poor predictor of 
outcome for any particular individual; but this does not negate the fact that 
there is a statistically significant difference in the average level of control for 
people with different levels of SPH and dependency and living in different 
settings. 
Each of the explanatory variables made a unique contribution to the 
model. Table  shows the contribution of the individual variables. As we 
might expect, as dependency increases, the probability of feeling in control 
over daily life decreases: the odds of feeling more in control decrease by . 
for each unit increase in the dependency scale. Similarly, those rating their 
health as 'very good' or 'good' were . times more likely, and those rating 
their health as 'fair' . times more likely, to feel in control than those 
rating their health as 'bad' or 'very bad'. It seems that, unsurprisingly, feeling 
more in control over daily life is associated with being less dependent and 
rating health more positively. 
One level of the age group variable was significantly related to control: 
participants aged - were . times less likely to feel in control than 
those over , although there was no effect for people aged -, 
suggesting that the relationship between age and feelings of control is not 
straightforward. 
Turning to setting, people living in extra care schemes were . times 
more likely to feel in control than those receiving care at home, while people 
living in care homes were . times more likely to feel in control than those 
receiving care at home. The relative values of the coefficients indicate that, 
when compared to those receiving care at home, those living in extra care 
schemes are most likely to feel in control, followed by those in care homes, 
with people receiving care at home least likely to feel in control. </p>

<p> 
Older people's experiences in different care settings </p>

<p>The model described above has a flaw; it only tells us how extra care and 
care homes compare with home care. It cannot tell us how care homes and 
extra care compare with each other, and we are interested in the relationship 
between all three settings. Consequently, the analysis was re-run, using 
exactly the same model, but changing the 'base category' of the setting 
variable, to care homes. When care homes were the reference category, the 
model indicated that people receiving care at home were . times less 
likely to feel in control than those living in care homes, but there was no 
significant effect when comparing the experiences of extra care and care 
home residents (see Table ). 
Taking these results together, it would seem that there is some evidence 
that ECH residents in our sample were the most likely to feel more in control 
of their daily lives. However, the analysis seems to suggest quite strongly that 
people receiving care at home in our sample were less likely to feel in control 
than both extra care and care home residents, even after controlling for the 
effects of confounds such as dependency, age and SPH. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The main objective of this paper was to compare older people's sense of 
control in different care settings: at home, in ECH and in care homes. 
Drawing on work developing the ASCOT, we were able to use comparable 
data from four different research studies to achieve this. Logistic regression </p>

<p>T A B L E . Ordinal regression analysis of control over daily life as a 
function of setting and background variables </p>

<p>Variable 
Parameter 
B 
SE 
OR 
% CI 
p </p>

<p>Threshold 
High needs 
À . . -
À . to À . &lt; .** 
Some needs 
À . . -
À . to À . &lt; .** 
Dependency 
(Continuous 
scale) </p>

<p>À . . . À . to À . &lt; .** </p>

<p>Self-perceived 
health (base  = very 
bad, bad) </p>

<p>Very good, 
good </p>

<p>. . . 
. to . 
&lt; .** </p>

<p>Fair 
. . . 
. to . 
.** 
Age group 
(base =  +) </p>

<p>- 
À . . . À . to . 
. 
- 
À . . . À . to À . 
.* 
Setting (base = home 
care) </p>

<p>Extra care 
housing </p>

<p>. . . 
. to . 
&lt; .** </p>

<p>Care homes 
. . . 
. to . 
.** </p>

<p>Notes: SE: standard error. OR: odds ratio. CI: confidence interval. . 'Base' refers to the variable 
parameter against which comparisons are made. For dependency, higher scores equate to being 
more dependent. 
Significance levels: * p &lt; ., ** p &lt; .. </p>

<p> Lisa Callaghan and Ann-Marie Towers </p>

<p>analyses showed a consistent pattern of results. Even after controlling for the 
independent effects of dependency, self-rated health and age group, setting 
had a significant effect on older people's sense of control. Residents in care 
homes and ECH reported similar levels of control over daily life but 
consistently reported feeling more in control than older people living at 
home and receiving home care. 
The results presented here mirror those found by Boyle (). They are 
interesting but perhaps not surprising given recent accounts of the poor 
quality of domiciliary care in England (EHRC ). We know from 
previous research that older people value having control over the delegation 
of their care and responsibilities (Bamford and Bruce ; Qureshi et al. 
) and influencing how and when care and support is delivered (Gabriel </p>

<p>and Bowling ; Qureshi and Henwood ; Qureshi et al. ). In 
home care this is sometimes not the case (Aronson ; EHRC ; 
Raynes et al. ) and is arguably more difficult to achieve in a community-
based model than in a group housing-based model, such as extra care or 
residential care. 
Aspects of ECH frequently reported as important and valued by older 
people are: having your own front door; the philosophy of ageing in place 
and maintaining independence; care and support on site; location and 
transport; design and facilities; social factors; and feeling safe and secure 
(Baker ; Bartholomeou ; Croucher, Hicks and Jackson ; 
Croucher, Pleace and Bevan ; Oldman ). Thus, it seems that 
people do not have to 'stay put' to feel they have retained their 
independence and sense of living in their own home but by moving into 
housing with care they can benefit from the care, support and social aspects 
associated with living in a more communal setting. Similarly, older people 
who had recently moved into residential care told researchers that they had 
more control over their daily lives than they expected, their quality of life had 
improved, their health needs were better met and they were socialising as 
much or more than they used to (Darton ). </p>

<p>T A B L E . Ordinal regression analysis, with 'care homes' as base category </p>

<p>Variable 
Parameter 
B 
SE 
OR 
% CI 
p </p>

<p>Setting (base  = care 
homes) </p>

<p>Home care 
À . 
. 
. 
À . to À . 
.** 
Extra care 
housing </p>

<p>. 
. 
. 
À . to . 
. </p>

<p>Notes: SE: standard error. OR: odds ratio. CI: confidence interval. . 'Base' refers to the variable 
parameter against which comparisons are made. 
Significance level : ** p &lt; .. </p>

<p> 
Older people's experiences in different care settings </p>

<p>Whilst it is important to acknowledge and address the issues with receiving 
care at home, we also need to recognise the role of financial constraints. The 
benefits associated with on-site care in care homes and ECH come at a cost. 
Residential care homes are expensive and generally reserved for the most 
dependent (Laing and Buisson ; Wanless ). It would be wholly 
inappropriate and detrimental to people's control over daily life to move 
into a care home prematurely, when only a few hours care and support a 
week is required. However, perhaps the current system has gone too far the 
other way? We know that the recent trend in service deployment is away from 
low-level service interventions towards more intensive service packages, with 
a decline in the number of people receiving home care but an increase in the 
number of hours of care provided overall, reflecting in part increases in local 
authority eligibility criteria (Laing and Buisson ). Whilst home care 
should and could go beyond the provision of personal care and help with basic 
ADLs, for state-funded care this is rarely the case for older people. This is an 
issue related to resource levels: per capita social care funding is lower for older 
people than for younger people with equivalent levels of need (Forder 
) and there is also evidence that PBs for older people are often lower </p>

<p>than for younger groups (Slay ). Additional funding and resources 
would be required to help people get out of their houses, engage in social 
activities or make them feel safe. Theories of environmental fit have long 
considered the issues associated with changing levels of dependency 
(Iwarsson ; Iwarsson et al. ; Lawton ). Our needs change as 
we age and our physical and social environment must also change to 
accommodate these needs (Commission for Architecture and Built 
Environment ). For example, a large garden that was once a pleasure 
to maintain becomes a burden and a source of concern. Without 
appropriate support, home may no longer be considered a place of refuge 
but rather a place of disempowerment and, in some extreme cases, a place of 
imprisonment (Baker ; Bartholomeou ; Boyle ; Oldman 
; Riseborough and Niner ). </p>

<p>Extra care housing offers a third way, a compromise between 'staying put' 
and institutional care. However, people living in extra care -if supported 
by the local authority -are funded through a number of other sources 
alongside social care funding: housing benefit; other welfare benefits; 
and Supporting People funding (Laing and Buisson ). This means 
that the overall cost to the state is likely to be more than that for 
people receiving care at home in the community, at least in the short term, 
although it may be that there are savings to be gained in the longer term 
(Kneale ). There is also is evidence that ECH can provide a cost-
effective alternative to care homes for some older people (Bäumker et al. 
). </p>

<p> Lisa Callaghan and Ann-Marie Towers </p>

<p>The level of ECH provision is, however, fairly small. The Elderly 
Accommodation Counsel () estimates that there were around , 
units of extra care accommodation in England in . In comparison, 
there were , personal care places and , nursing home places 
in care homes in the UK (Laing and Buisson ). Although the Labour 
government attempted to stimulate growth in the market through provision 
of the Extra Care Housing Initiative Fund (-), investment in ECH is 
likely to be reduced given the lack of public funds in the current financial 
climate, particularly if decision makers are focused on short-rather than 
longer-term cost savings. In addition, access to ECH schemes is restricted by 
the eligibility criteria set by the schemes, whether these are as basic as age, 
links to the local community and housing needs, or shaped by more specific 
criteria set by local authorities seeking to place individuals in schemes based 
on additional factors such as health and dependency (Bäumker et al. ). 
Thus, in reality, a large proportion of older people with a need for care and 
support will remain in their own accommodation in the community. 
Given these restrictions, efforts may be best directed at improving services 
for older people living in their own homes and increasing access to and 
uptake of services that get people out of their houses, socialising and 
engaging with their community, and receiving care and support in more 
flexible ways, thus increasing their sense of control. Perhaps one solution </p>

<p>would be for ECH to act as a 'hub', delivering personalised care and support 
to people in the local community, who can also come to the scheme for 
communal activities (see e.g. Blood and Pannell ). However, it is not 
clear that this would necessarily overcome the issues associated with 
scheduled care, which when not available 'on-site' is difficult to provide on 
demand. In theory, the continued drive towards personalisation of services 
and giving service users a PB to spend as they wish to meet their needs should 
result in increased control over how and when care is delivered; however, as 
noted above, the evidence does not yet indicate that this is the case for all 
older people receiving care at home (EHRC ). Nonetheless, the sample 
of home care recipients used for the analysis in this paper were receiving 
conventional home care rather than purchasing this themselves through a 
PB, and we cannot rule out the possibility that our findings would be 
different if data were collected from people experiencing the new system. 
This paper has drawn from a body of work undertaken during the 
development of the ASCOT. It is based on secondary analysis and was not the 
primary purpose for data collection. Limitations to this approach include: 
compromises over the variables included in the model (e.g. a reduced 
number of indicators for ADLs); variation in the position of the dependent 
variable in the interview schedules; and some variation in the wording of the 
dependent variable as it was developed over time. Regarding the latter, </p>

<p> 
Older people's experiences in different care settings </p>

<p>however, it should be noted that the only differences in response categories 
were with the top two levels and we overcame these by collapsing them into a 
single 'no needs' category. This is in line with current ASCOT scoring for use 
in care homes and housing with care (see www.pssru.ac.uk/ASCOT). 
We should also note that the samples included here are not entirely 
representative of the populations from which they were drawn. In the care 
home sample, we only included those able to take part in structured 
interviews: the more 'independent' residents. In the extra care sample, we 
only included people receiving care and so compared with the other people 
living in their schemes they are less able/independent. For home care, our 
sample is fairly representative. The only difference worth noting is that, 
compared with the population from which it was drawn, our sample has 
proportionally less people aged over . We have controlled for differences 
in dependency in the regression but what we cannot control for is the effect 
of 'reference category'. 
A common problem in quality of life research is understanding the 
appraisal system used when judging subjective questions such as 'how is your 
general health' and 'how would you rate your quality of life' (Schwartz and 
Rapkin ). Perhaps the care home residents included in our sample felt 
more in control than the home care sample because they compared their 
own situation to that of the frail, less independent residents they lived with? 
Had we self-report interviews with all residents, we would be able to look at 
this more closely. However, because the more dependent residents lacked 
capacity to take part in face-to-face interview, we only have third-party 
judgements of their control over daily life, which is not directly comparable. 
The extra care residents reported better control over daily life than home 
care users, despite requiring more care than the population from which they 
are drawn. This bodes well for extra care but does not aid interpretation of 
the findings from home care users. 
Finally, the length of time a person receives social care may be an 
unmeasured contributing factor to people's responses. Policies to keep 
people out of care homes for as long as possible mean that many have had 
time to adjust to worsening health and receipt of care by the time they move 
in. Comparatively, people receiving home care may still be struggling to 
adapt to their own physical frailty and this might be reflected in their 
responses to the control over daily life question. Ultimately, without asking 
people to explain their own individual appraisal process when answering the 
questions, it is very difficult to resolve these issues (Schwartz and Rapkin 
). The focus of our analysis was on social care-related control over daily </p>

<p>life and our aim was to explore whether this varied according to the care 
model: care at home, extra care and care homes. The analysis suggests it 
does. The more able care home residents, those most closely comparable to </p>

<p> Lisa Callaghan and Ann-Marie Towers </p>

<p>extra care residents, report very similar levels of control over daily life to 
people living in ECH facilities. The majority feel in control over their daily 
lives. By comparison, older home care users consistently report lower levels 
of control. Primary research exploring the issues identified in this paper is 
urgently required to address our concerns about frail older people living in 
their own homes and receiving social care. This is a population capable of 
taking part in surveys and face-to-face interviews. What would make them 
feel more in control of their daily lives? We have identified several possible 
explanations for our findings but only by working with service users and their 
families, providers and commissioners can significant steps be made to 
improve outcomes through more personalised services and service delivery. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This paper draws on four projects supported by different funders: () the Social 
Well-being project, funded by the Joseph Rowntree Foundation; () the Measuring 
Outcomes of Public Service Users project, funded over three years (-) by the 
UK Treasury and led by the Office of National Statistics; () the Control and 
Well-being project, funded by the Department of Health as part of a long-term 
programme of research; and () the Outcomes of Social Care for Adults project, 
funded by the UK National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) Health Technology 
Assessment Programme (project reference number //). The analysis and 
write-up of this paper was funded by the Quality and Outcomes of Person Centred 
Care Research Unit (QORU). The views and opinions expressed are those of the 
authors alone and do not necessarily reflect those of the funders. We are very grateful 
to all those who participated in the research and to those who collected the data. 
We are also grateful to Professor Ann Netten and Professor Julien Forder for their 
comments and advice. </p>



<p>Accepted  February ; first published online  May  </p>

<p>Address for correspondence: 
Ann-Marie Towers, Personal Social Services Research Unit (PSSRU), 
University of Kent, Canterbury CT NF, UK. </p>

<p>E-mail: A.Towers@kent.ac.uk </p>

<p> 
Older people's experiences in different care settings </p>

</text></tei>