<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4040663" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>small molecules to inhibit smoothened (Smo) (such as 
Cyclopamine, GDC-0449, LDE225, BMS-833923 (XL139), 
IPI-926, PF-04449913, LEQ506, and TAK-441). 
14 However, 
these strategies might not be applicable to the treatment of 
tumors that harbor molecular lesions downstream of Smo. 
In earlier studies, we have illustrated that constitutive activation 
of the Hh signaling pathway in chondrosarcoma is rarely 
caused by PTCH1 or SMO mutations, 
15 and therefore the 
aberrant activation of the pathway in chondrosarcoma is more 
likely due to downstream molecules, such as GLI proteins, 
which act as very important nuclear executors and mediate Hh 
signaling at the distal end of the pathway. On the basis of 
recent data on GLI transcription factors we have concluded 
that GLI1, and not GLI2 or Gli3, is the direct transcriptional 
Hh-target gene, which determines the cell's response to the 
Hh pathway activity and might be the causal agent in multiple 
cellular processes such as proliferation, cell cycle, and cell 
survival. In this paper, we investigated the effects of Gli1 small 
interfering RNA (siRNA) on human chondrosarcoma cell lines 
SW1353 and JJ012. Our results indicated that knockdown of 
Gli1 expression not only attenuated the affected Hh signal 
pathway but also suppressed cell growth and cell cycle 
progression, and induced apoptosis as well as autophagy, 
and the extracellular signal-regulated kinases (ERK)1/2 
activity may mediate these antiproliferative events induced 
by Gli1 inhibition. Thus, blocking the expression of Gli1 would 
be an ideal strategy for combating chondrosarcoma. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Expression of IHh pathway members in the normal 
articular cartilage, in chondrosarcoma, and in their 
corresponding cell lines HC-a, SW1353, and JJ012. We 
first examined the expressions of key members in the IHh 
pathway using immunohistochemistry (IHC), qPCR and 
western blot analysis (WB) in 20 samples taken from the 
normal articular cartilage and chondrosarcoma tissues. 
qPCR data are not shown here because the CT values in 
articular cartilage samples were too high to obtain apart from 
IHh. IHC (Figure 1a) and WB (Figure 1b) analyses showed 
that PTHrP, PTCH1, SMO, and Gli1 were all expressed in 
chondrosarcoma but not in the normal articular cartilage 
tissues. On the other hand, expression of IHh was detected 
in both tissues, but was significantly elevated in chondro-
sarcoma compared with the articular cartilage (Figure 1b). 
As visualized by immunohistochemistry, Gli1 displayed an 
absolutely nuclear expression pattern, whereas others 
stained on cell membranes and in the cytoplasm 
(Figure 1a). To further validate our results, we analyzed the 
expression of these genes in their corresponding cell lines 
HC-a, SW1353, and JJ012 by PCR and WB. Similar results 
were obtained (Figures 1c and d). These findings indicate 
that there was an active IHh pathway in chondrosarcoma, 
which is essential for tumor growth, recurrence, metastasis, 
and cell survival. </p>

<p>16   Cell viability was reduced by Gli1 siRNA but not by the 
SMO inhibitor cyclopamine. As the IHh pathway is 
activated in chondrosarcoma, it was interesting to study 
whether inhibition of the pathway with a natural small-</p>

<p>molecule cyclopamine, a specific SMO inhibitor, would kill 
SW1353 and JJ012 cells. Our results showed that adding 
up to 20 mM cyclopamine in the culture medium did not 
affect cell viability in the two chondrosarcoma cell lines 
(Figure 2a). On the basis of the results, the activator of the 
pathway in chondrosarcoma might be located downstream 
of SMO, being a transcription factor such as GLI1. To test 
this hypothesis, we used siRNA to knock down Gli1 
expression to see whether Gli1 was involved in the 
regulation of viability and proliferation in the chondrosar-
coma cell lines. Our results showed that the mRNA and 
protein levels of Gli1 in SW1353 and JJ012 cells were 
reduced significantly 24, 48, and 72 h after siGli1 transfec-
tion; data collected 48 h after the knockdown treatment are 
shown in Figures 2b and c. The cell viabilities assayed by 
MTS showed constant decline with increase in time after the 
Gli1 siRNA transfection and were only about 30-55% of the 
values before the transfection in JJ012 and SW1352, 
respectively (Figure 2d). </p>

<p>The active IHh signal pathway can be attenuated by 
siGli1 but not by cyclopamine. To further verify the 
findings, we assessed the net effect of siGli1 or cyclopamine 
on the expression of the key members in the pathway. 
We found that RNAi-mediated knockdown of Gli1 in 
chondrosarcoma cell lines diminished not only the secretion 
of IHh and PTHrP but also the expression of PTCH1 and 
SMO, whereas cyclopamine did not affect their expression 
except that of SMO (Figures 3a and b). This is in contrast to 
previous studies in which cyclopamine clearly downregulated 
GLI1 and PTCH1. 
17,18 That is, the whole Hh signal 
transduction cascade was weakened by Gli1 siRNA but not 
by the SMO inhibitor cyclopamine. </p>

<p>Gli1 inhibition promoted G2/M cell cycle arrest and 
apoptosis. Forty-eight hours after siGli1 treatment, the cells 
appeared to stop proliferation and arrested at the G2/M 
phase (Figure 4a). As a result, the proportion of cells at the 
G2/M stage was increased by 13.88±0.76% and 
13.68 ± 1.16% in SW1353 and JJ012, respectively, com-
pared with untreated controls (Figure 4c). As shown by flow 
cytometric analysis, there were increased proportions of 
early apoptotic cells (marked as LR in Figure 4b) and late 
apoptotic cells (marked as UR in Figure 4b) 48 h after siGli1 
transfection, which increased by 14.89±0.82% and 
27.69 ± 1.24% in SW1353 and JJ012, respectively, as 
compared with controls (Figure 4d). </p>

<p>Correlative changes of molecules in the process of 
proliferation, cell cycle, and apoptosis after treatment 
with siGli1. To further test the functions of Gli1 in the 
process of proliferation, cell cycle, and apoptosis we 
performed immunocytochemical analysis for Ki-67 and WB 
analysis for proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA), 
CyclinB1, pRb, Bax, Bcl-2, BCL-xl, and Caspase3. PCNA 
functions in cell cycle progression and serves as an attractive 
assay of cell proliferation; 
19 Ki-67 is a nuclear protein that is 
expressed in proliferating cells and may be required for 
maintaining cell proliferation. Ki-67 has been used as a 
marker for cell proliferation of solid tumors and some </p>

<p>Gli1 inhibition suppressed chondrosarcoma 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>hematological malignancies. 
20 CyclinB has an integral role in 
the progression of cells into and out of M phase, which is 
necessary for cells to enter mitosis and therefore necessary 
for cell division. 
21 Rb is a tumor suppressor protein that has 
important roles in the checkpoint of cell cycle. Downregula-
tion of pRb expression increases both the S-and G2/M 
phase cell fractions of lung fibroblasts. 
22 In our study, the 
expressions of PCNA, Ki-67, cyclinB, and pRb were inhibited 
after treatment with siGli1 for 48 h in chondrosarcoma cell 
lines (Figure 5). These data supported our in vitro evidence 
pointing to the critical role of Gli1 in the G2/M mitotic/ 
transition phase. </p>

<p>To understand the mechanism of apoptosis exerted by 
siGli1, we studied the effect of siGli1 on the expression of pro-
apoptotic protein Bax, anti-apoptotic proteins Bcl-2 and Bcl-xl, 
and caspase3. As shown in Figure 5, there were significant 
inhibitions of Bcl-2 and Bcl-xl expression after treatment with 
siGli1 for 48 h, but no obvious changes in the expression of 
Bax. In addition, cleavage of caspase3, which requires 
proteolytic processing of its inactive zymogen into activated 
p17 and p12 fragments, 
23 had not been detected during the 
execution of the apoptotic cascade (Figure 5). These 
observations suggest that the Bcl-2 family of proteins, but 
not caspase3, controls apoptotic programmed cell death. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Expression of IHh pathway members in the normal articular cartilage, in chondrosarcoma. and in their corresponding cell lines HC-a SW1353 and JJ012. (a and b) 
IHC and WB analyses for IHh, PTHrP, PTCH, SMO, and Gli1 were performed in tissue sections from the normal articular cartilage and chondrosarcoma, and the staining 
intensities and location of IHC were evaluated. (c and d) Next, these proteins were examined by qPCR and WB in human articular chondrocyte cell line HC-a and 
chondrosarcoma cell lines SW1353 and JJ012 (*Po0.05, **Po0.01 versus HC-a) </p>

<p>Gli1 inhibition suppressed chondrosarcoma 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Gli1 downregulation, not cyclopamine, induced autop-
hagy by regulating mTOR phosphorylation. Autophagy-
associated cell death is another type of programmed cell </p>

<p>death after the discovery of apoptosis and necrosis by 
maintaining an important homeostatic mechanism that 
removes damaged or unnecessary proteins and organelles </p>

<p>Figure 2 Cell viability was reduced by Gli1 siRNA but not by the SMO inhibitor cyclopamine. (a and b) The Gli1 siRNA transfection efficiency was measured by qPCR and 
WB. (c) Cell viability of cyclopamine and Gli1 siRNA in chondrosarcoma cell lines was tested by MTS assay; cells were incubated with 0, 5, 10, and 20 mM of cyclopamine for 
24 h (P40.05 versus control). (d) Cells were treated with Gli1 siRNA for the indicated time. All data are expressed as the mean ± S.D. of three independent experiments 
(*Po0.05, **Po0.01 versus controls) </p>

<p>Figure 3 The active IHh signal pathway can be attenuated by siGli1 but not by cyclopamine. Cells s were treated with Gli1 siRNA and cyclopamine (10 mM) for 24 h. 
Changes in the expression of IHh, PTHrP, PTCH, SMO, and Gli1 were examined by qPCR (a) and WB (b). The data are presented as mean ± S.D. of three independent 
experiments (*Po0.05, **Po0.01, 
# P40.05 versus controls) </p>

<p>Gli1 inhibition suppressed chondrosarcoma 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>and recycles cytoplasmic contents through a process by 
which these components are engulfed in autophagosomes 
and then digested via the lysosomal pathway. 
24 Induction of 
autophagy might be a novel approach for anticancer therapy. 
To investigate whether Gli1 is involved in autophagy, 
transmission electron microscopy was performed to examine 
the ultrastructures of autophagy. Representative images 
depicting the ultrastructures of autophagy, such as autopha-
gosome-like vacuoles with double-membrane structures 
(Figures 6a and b black arrow) and segments of the 
double-membrane formed between a vacuole and mitochon-
drion (Figures 6a and c white arrow), are shown in Figure 6a. </p>

<p>Expression of LC3-II visualized by immunofluorescence is 
recognized as a means to track changes in autophagosome 
formation in living cells. LC3 is processed from LC3-I to LC3-
II during autophagy. LC3-II is inserted into newly formed 
autophagosome membranes. 
25 Therefore, we investigated 
the impact of Gli1 expression on LC3-II production. 
Our results show that silencing Gli1 with siRNAs increased 
the LC3-II localization in the cytoplasm in both cell lines 
(Figure 6b) and resulted in the accumulation of LC3-II and 
degradation of P62 (a known autophagy substrate) 
(Figure 6c). In contrast, no such effect was detected in 
cyclopamine-treated cells (Figure 6d). </p>

<p>Figure 4 Gli1 inhibition promoted G2/M cell cycle arrest and apoptosis. (a) Cells treated with siGli1 for 48 h were fixed in 70% ethanol, permeabilized in Triton-X, digested 
with RNAse A, and stained with propidium iodide. (b) Apoptotic cells were measured with the Annexin V/FITC kit according to the manufacturer's instructions and analyzed by 
flow cytometry after treatment with siGli1 for 48 h. (c) The bar chart shows the percentage of cells in cell cycle. The treatment groups are labeled on the horizontal axis. The 
siGli1 treatment led to a significant increase in the proportion of cells in the G2/M phase in the two cell lines tested. (d) The pictures demonstrate one of three similar 
experiments in chondrosarcoma cell lines and show a significant increase in the early and late apoptotic index </p>

<p>Gli1 inhibition suppressed chondrosarcoma 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>To further explore the contribution of Gli1 to autophagy 
regulation, we studied the relationship between Gli1 and 
mTOR. We observed that silenced expression of Gli1 
decreased mTOR phosphorylation, but rapamycin, which 
stimulates autophagy through mechanisms involving mTOR 
kinase inactivation, had no effect on Gli1. We also analyzed 
the phosphorylation of p70S6K, a marker of mTOR activity, 
and found that it followed the same trend as mTOR 
(Figure 6e). Densitometry was performed for quantification, 
and the ratios of P-mTOR and P-p70S6K to b-actin are 
presented in Figure 6f. These outcomes elicited down-
regulated expression of Gli1-induced autophagy depending 
on mTOR dephosphorylation. </p>

<p>Autophagy inhibition prevented siGli1-mediated cell 
death. Autophagy has been associated with both cell death 
and survival depending on the cellular context and stimu-
lus. 
26 Given that autophagy can be induced by siGli1, 
we evaluated whether autophagy induced by Gli1 inhibition </p>

<p>had a role in cell death. A link between autophagy and cell 
death has been demonstrated using pharmacological (e.g., 
3-Methyladenine (3-MA), chloroquine (CQ), bafilomycin A1, 
or monensin) and genetic (silencing of Atg5, Atg7, Beclin1, 
Atg10, or Atg12) approaches for suppression of autophagy. </p>

<p>27   3-MA can block the induction of LC3-II puncta formation. </p>

<p>28   CQ is a lysosomotropic agent that has been suggested to 
inhibit autophagy by perturbing lysosomal function. 
27 Cells 
treated with siGli1 in the presence of 3-MA (2.5 mM) and CQ 
(30 mg/ml) demonstrated that 3-MA and CQ significantly 
enhanced the viability of cells in response to Gli1 inhibition 
(Figure 7a). To further test this possibility, we invalidated the 
expression of autophagic genes Atg7 and Beclin1 (Figure 7b) 
and quantified the production of LC3-II (Figure 7c). Similarly, 
RNA interference (RNAi) directed against the autophagy 
genes atg7 and beclin1 blocked cell death in chondrosar-
coma cells transfected with siGli1 (Figure 7d). These results 
support the possibility that autophagy inhibition prevented 
siGli1-mediated cell death. </p>

<p>Figure 5 Correlative changes of molecules in the process of proliferation, cell cycle, and apoptosis after treatment with siGli1. Forty-eight hours after siGli1 treatment, 
we performed immunocytochemical analysis for Ki-67 and WB analysis for PCNA, CyclinB1, pRb, Bax, Bcl-2, BCL-xl, and Caspase3 </p>

<p>Gli1 inhibition suppressed chondrosarcoma 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>ERK1/2 activity mediated antiproliferative events. The 
ERK signaling pathway has a crucial role in almost all cell 
functions and therefore requires exquisite control of its 
spatiotemporal activity. 
29 On treatment of Gli1 siRNA-
transfected cells with the MAPK/ERK kinase inhibitor 
U0126 (10 mM; U0126 is not toxic up to 10 mM in SW1353 
and JJ012 cells) we found that U0126 improved the cell 
vitality that had been reduced by Gli1 siRNA (Figure 8a), 
resulting in the release of most cells from arrest at the G2/M 
stage (Figure 8b) and also strongly reduced apoptosis </p>

<p>(Figure 8c) in Gli1 siRNA-transfected chondrosarcoma cells. 
In addition, U0126 also significantly reduced LC3-II puncta 
formation, which implied that Gli1 inhibition-induced autop-
hagy was attenuated in U0126 treatment (Figure 8d), and the 
MEK/ERK-related signaling pathway contributed to autop-
hagy in the chondrosarcoma cell lines. To further determine 
whether the involvement of MEK/ERK signaling is a direct or 
indirect consequence of depressed Gli1 activity, we treated 
the cells with siGli1 and U0126 for 24 h and found that 
reduction in Gli1 expression promoted ERK phosphorylation </p>

<p>Figure 6 Gli1 downregulation, not cyclopamine, induced autophagy by regulating mTOR phosphorylation. (a) Representative TEM images depict ultrastructures of 
autophagy SW1353 and JJ012 cells transfected with Gli1 siRNA for 24 h. Autophagosome-like vacuoles with double-membrane structures (black arrow) and segment of the 
double-membrane being formed between a vacuole and mitochondrion (white arrow). (b) Cells were grown on coverslips and transfected with Gli1 siRNA for 24 h. They were 
then incubated overnight at 4 1C with rabbit polyclonal anti-LC3 Ab (1 : 200) and then sequentially in anti-rabbit IgG conjugated with Dylight 488 (1 : 400) for 2 h at room 
temperature. The cells were then visualized by confocal microscopy. The data were normally distributed and statistically analyzed using one-way ANOVA. The double asterisk 
denotes that the group is statistically different from the control groups (**Po0.01). (c) WB was used to detect the expression of LC3-II (an autophagosome marker) and P62 
(a known autophagy substrate) after transfection with Gli1 siRNA and being incubated with cyclopamine (10 mM) for 24 h. Downregulated expression of Gli1 induced 
accumulation of Lc3-II and degradation of p62 (a known autophagy substrate). (d) However, cyclopamine had no effect on Lc3-II and p62. (e) The relationship between Gli1 
and mTOR was also studied. (f) Densitometry was performed for quantification, and the ratios of P-mTOR and P-p70S6K to b-actin are presented </p>

<p>Gli1 inhibition suppressed chondrosarcoma 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>but had no impact on MEK1/2 and that U0126 inhibited both 
activated and inactivated MEK1/2 as well as activated ERK1/ 
2 pathways, leading to the repression of GLI1. Taken 
together, the current data showing that depressed Gli1 
activity promoted ERK activity and that Gli1 activity was also 
dependent on MEK/ERK signaling highlight the possible 
presence of a novel feedback mechanism that modulates 
GLI1 activity (Figure 8e). Many studies associate the MEK/ 
ERK signal pathway's oncogenic potential to increased cell 
survival. Paradoxically, depending on the cell type and 
stimulus, ERK activity has been shown to mediate different 
antiproliferative events such as apoptosis, autophagy, and 
senescence in vitro and in vivo. 
30 Therefore, we hold the 
opinion that phosphorylation-ERK contributed to the cell 
cycle arrest, apoptosis, and autophagy induced by Gli1 
inhibition in chondrosarcoma cell lines. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>According to our studies, we find that the IHh signal pathway is 
disturbed in chondrosarcoma. Overexpression of PTCH1 and 
Gli1 or a constitutively active IHh-PTHrp signal pathway may 
lead to musculoskeletal tumorigenesis. 
31-33 Coincidentally, 
it is exciting to discover that knockdown of Gli1 expression by 
siRNA downregulated the expression of major Hh signal 
pathway members, including IHh, PTHrP, PTCH1, and SMO. 
This was probably due to insufficient Gli1 protein translocation 
into the nucleus to initiate the transcription of the Hh pathway 
genes, such as Gli1 and PTCH1, as well as many survival-
promoting molecules. 
14 In the present study, SMO levels </p>

<p>appeared to be insufficient for stimulating the pathway, </p>

<p>34   so did chondrosarcoma in our study, but the expression of 
SMO was downregulated by siGli1. Thus, the whole Hh signal 
transduction cascade was weakened and corrected by 
knockdown of Gli1 expression. We also confirmed that siGli1 
decreased the proliferation rate as well as PCNA and Ki-67 
expression, which has already been abundantly implicated in 
other cancers, such as in BCCs and meduloblastomas. </p>

<p>35,36   Recent work has provided insight into the fact that Hh 
influences the expression and activity of core cell cycle 
components at multiple points within the cell cycle in a variety 
of circumstances. 
37 Intriguingly, we found that siGli1 induced 
cell cycle G2/M phase arrest by downregulating cyclinB and 
Rb phosphorylation, thereby rendering chondrosarcoma cells 
quiescent and prohibiting tumor progression. Furthermore, 
the Bcl-2 protein family has a central role in the control of 
apoptosis and is also thought to be involved in resistance to 
conventional cancer treatment. 
38 It is the Gli1 siRNA that 
affected Bcl-2 and Bcl-xl expression and led to apoptosis in 
sw1353 and JJ012 cells. 
Autophagy is an important homeostatic mechanism that 
removes damaged or unnecessary proteins and dysfunctional 
cellular organelles and recycles cytoplasmic contents in all 
living cells. 
39 The process of autophagy was initially identified 
as a cell survival mechanism in response to stress. </p>

<p>40   However, under certain conditions, autophagy results in a 
form of cell death now described as type II programmed cell 
death. 
41 It had been reported that the Hh signaling pathway 
regulates autophagy. 
42-44 Jimenez-Sanchez et al. 
42 have 
confirmed that Gli2 is necessary for the inhibition of autophagy </p>

<p>Figure 7 Autophagy inhibition prevented siGli1-mediated cell death. (a) Cells were transfected with Gli1 siRNA. After 6 h, cells were exposed to 3-MA (2.5 mM) or CQ 
(30 mg/ml) for 48 h. Then cell viability was tested using an MTS assay. (b and c) SW1353 and JJ012 cells were transfected with siGli1 in the presence of Atg7 and Beclin1 
siRNA; 48 h after transfection, the cells were analyzed by immunoblotting with the indicated antibodies. (d) The viability of SW1353 and JJ012 cells in (c) was analyzed by the 
MTS assay as described in Materials and Methods. Data are presented as mean ± S.D. and are representative of three independent experiments (*Po0.05, **Po0.01 
versus controls) </p>

<p>Gli1 inhibition suppressed chondrosarcoma 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>by Hh signal, but they were unable to completely exclude the 
contribution of Gli1 and Gli3 to autophagy regulation. The 
mechanism by which Gli1 regulates autophagy is still unclear 
and the role of autophagy in cell growth and cell death in 
chondrosarcoma is still being debated considerably. In our 
study, it was found, for the first time to our knowledge, that Gli1 
inhibition, not cyclopamine, induced synthesis of autophago-
some in chondrosarcoma. Autophagy has been implicated in 
maintaining cancer cell survival, but its precise role is 
ambiguous. Autophagy also functions as a mechanism of 
pro-cell death, depending on the cellular context that when 
unrestrained can result in progressive consumption of cellular 
components and subsequent cell death and might mediate 
resistance to anticancer therapies such as radiation, che-
motherapy, and some targeted therapies. 
45-47 In addition, 
autophagy inhibition prevented siGli1-mediated cell death. 
It strengthened our point of view that induction of autophagic 
cell death is a useful alternative approach to killing tumor cells. 
Induction of autophagy is a possible antitumor mechanism of 
action of allosteric inhibitors of mTORC1. One such rapalog, 
rapamycin, is used as an antirejection drug in organ transplant 
recipients and has demonstrated anticancer activity in myxoid 
chondrosarcoma as well. 
48 Recent studies have shown that 
activated mTOR/S6K1 pathway promotes Gli1 transcriptional 
activity and oncogenic function, 
49 but our study hold the 
opposite view that Gli1 transcription factor appears to be no 
changes treated with rapamycin, whereas silenced the 
expression of Gli1 with siRNAs lead to mTOR dephosphor-
ylation then induced autophagy-associated cell death sug-
gested that Gli1 may be located at the upstream of mTOR in 
chondrosarcoma cells. Consequently, when treating resistant 
tumors such as recurrent chondrosarcoma, antineoplastics 
leading to autophagy-associated cell death might prove to be </p>

<p>a unique form of combinational therapy rather than a novel 
target for anticancer therapy. </p>

<p>46   In the investigations on the mechanism of these antiproli-
ferative events induced by Gli1 inhibition, it has been shown 
that constitutive activation of ERK by active Raf, 
50 cadmium, </p>

<p>51   or IGF-I receptor 
52 induces a form of cell death that is 
correlated with extensive cell rounding and with the formation 
of cytoplasmic macrovacuoles, which pushes the nucleus and 
the cytoplasm to the side of the quiescent and dying cell. 
We also found that there is a crosstalk between the Hh and the 
MEK/ERK signal pathway and that ERK1/2 activity mediates 
these antiproliferative events. On the basis of these findings, 
we propose a tentative regulatory mechansim of IHh and Gli1 
in Figure 8f. 
However, it should be noted that the study we had 
examined is limited to in vitro cell lines, and a significant 
number of challenges still need to be overcome for a 
successful in vivo study. Although there are animal studies 
that do support the possibility of an RNAi mechanism of action 
from administered siRNA, 
53 our in vivo study, using naked 
siRNA or siRNA by liposomal delivery, suggested non-RNAi 
mechanisms of action for chondrosarcoma suppression. 
Therefore, we are trying to find a new delivery system that 
can provide effective delivery of functional siRNA to animals 
with chondrosarcoma. 
In conclusion, knockdown of IHh-Gli1 signaling by Gli1-
specific siRNAs not only attenuated the disturbed IHh signal 
pathway but also curbed the growth and survival of the treated 
chondrosarcoma cells. The related mechanisms were also 
systematically demonstrated in this paper. This will not only 
advance our understanding of chondrosarcoma development at 
the molecular level but also lead to an important new opportunity 
in which therapeutic effects might be achieved by Gli1 inhibitors. </p>

<p>Figure 8 ERK1/2 activity mediated antiproliferative events. Cells were transfected with Gli1 siRNA. After 6 h the cells were exposed to the MAPK/ERK kinase inhibitor 
U0126 (10 mM) or not for 24 h. (a) Cell viability was tested using an MTS assay. (b and c) Cell cycle and apoptosis were analyzed by flow cytometry. (d) LC3-II puncta formation 
was visualized by confocal microscopy. (e) Thereafter, cells were exposed to siGli1 and U0126 for 24 h to determine whether the involvement of MEK/ERK signaling is a direct 
or indirect consequence of depressed Gli1 activity. Cell lysates were prepared and analyzed by immunoblotting using the indicated antibodies (*Po0.05, **Po0.01 versus 
controls). (f) Detailed molecular regulation mechansim of Gli1. (-) Stimulatory modification. (&gt;) Inhibitory modification. (X) Signal dysfunction </p>

<p>Gli1 inhibition suppressed chondrosarcoma 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
Human articular cartilage and chondrosarcoma specimens, cell 
lines, and reagents. The fresh human normal articular cartilage and 
chondrosarcoma specimen were obtained under the approved protocols of the 
Institutional Ethics Review Boards of Peking University People's Hospital. 
Informed consent for the experimental use of surgical specimens was obtained 
from all patients in written form according to the hospital's ethical guidelines. 
Excisions obtained after surgery were properly conserved for the experiment. 
The human articular chondrocyte cell line HC-a (Sciencell, Carlsbad, CA, USA) 
and two chondrosarcoma cell lines SW1353 (ATCC HTB-94; Manassas, VA, USA) 
and JJ012 (JJ012; a gift from Dr. J Block, Rush Medical College, Chicago, IL, 
USA) were used in the study. HC-a cells were maintained in DMEM supplemented 
with 10% fetal bovine serum, plus antibiotics. SW1353 was maintained in L-15 
medium, whereas JJ012 cells were grown in RPMI-1640 medium supplemented 
with FBS and antibiotics. The following reagents were purchased from Sigma-
Aldrich (Sciencell): cyclopamine (C4116), 3-Methyladenine (M9281), 3-Methyla-
denine U0126 (U120), and polyclonal antibodies against LC3 (L7543) and P62 
(N1163). Rabbit monoclonal anti-IHh (ab39634), anti-PTHrP (ab16827), anti-PT 
CHed (ab39266), and anti-SMO (ab5694) were purchased from Abcam (Abcam, 
Cambridge, UK). Anti-Gli1 (3538), anti-Phospho-MEK1/2 (9154), anti-MEK1/2 
(9126), anti-Phospho-ERK1/2 (4344), anti-ERK1/2 (4695), and anti-b-actin were 
from Cell Signaling Technology (Beverly, MA, USA). </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry. Paraffin sections were reacted with rabbit poly-
clonal anti-IHh, anti-PTHrP, anti-PTCH, anti-SMO, and anti-Gli1 antibodies (1 : 200 
dilution). Sections stained with nonimmune rabbit serum (1 : 200 dilution) in 
phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) instead of primary antibody served as negative 
controls. Cells exhibiting positive staining on cell membranes and in the cytoplasm 
and nucleus were counted in at least 10 representative fields ( Â 400 
magnification) and the mean percentage of positive cells was calculated. 
Immunostaining was assessed by two independent pathologists blinded to clinical 
characteristics and outcomes. </p>

<p>RNAi and cell transfection. The siRNAs against Gli1 were designed by 
OriGene Technologies (Rockville, MD, USA, SR301820). The siRNAs, 21nt-long, 
double-stranded, were purified and desalted by the provider. Their sequences 
were as follows: sense strand siGli1 primer 5 
0 -GCCACCAAGCUAACCUCAU 
GUTT-3 
0 and antisense strand siGli1 primer 5 
0 -ACAUGAGGUUAGCUUG 
GUGGCTT-3 
0 . The following nonspecific siRNAs were used as control: forward 
5 
0 -UUCUCCGAACGUGUCACGUTT-3 
0 and reverse 5 
0 -ACGUGACACGUUCGGA 
GAATT-3 
0 . For transfection, cells were transfected with the siRNAs using the 
Lipofectamine 2000 kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) according to the 
manufacturer's instructions after cells were grown to B60% confluence. </p>

<p>Cell viability assay. Cell viability was investigated using an MTS 
(3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-5-(3-carboxymethoxyphenyl)-2-(4-sulfophenyl)-2H-tet-
razolium (inner salt; Sigma, M2003) assay. The cells were suspended in 0.2 ml of 
medium at a concentration of 5000 cells/well and incubated overnight in 96-well 
plates. Absorbance at 490 nm was measured using a microplate reader 
(Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Cell cycle and apoptosis analysis by flow cytometry. Cells were 
fixed in 70% ethanol, permeabilized in Triton-X, digested with RNAse A, and 
stained with propidium iodide. Apoptotic cells were measured with Annexin V/FITC 
kit (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer's 
instructions and analyzed by flow cytometry after compound treatment as 
described previously. </p>

<p>54   RNA extraction and qPCR analysis. Total RNA was isolated from 
SW1353 and JJ012 cells with Trizol reagent (Oakville, Ontario, Canada), 
according to the manufacturer's instructions. After purification, RNA was converted 
to complementary DNA (cDNA) using the First-Strand cDNA synthesis kit 
(ReverTra Ace kit Toyobo, Tokyo, Japan) according to the manufacturer's 
instructions. The cDNA was amplified from 2 mg of total RNA using Super Script 
one-step RT-PCR or qPCR with the platinum Taq system (Invitrogen). The primers 
used for amplification of IHh, PTHrP, PTCH,SMO, Gli1, and GAPDH transcripts 
were as follows: IHh forward 5 
0 -CGTCGTGGTGTAGTCATAG-3 
0 and IHh reverse 
5 
0 -GGATGTGTCTTGAGGAGTG-3 
0 ; PTHrP forward 5 
0 -CGATTCTTCCTTCACCA 
TCT-3 
0 and PTHrP reverse 5 
0 -CGTCTCCACCTTGTTAGTT-3 
0 ; PTCH forward </p>

<p>5 
0 -TGTGATGGATGCTGGAACCT-3 
0 and PTCH reverse 5-
0 CCTACATAATGCCT 
GCCTCTAC-3 
0 ; SMO forward 5 
0 -GTTCTCCTATATCCTCCTTCTC-3 
0 and SMO 
reverse 5 
0 -CTTCCTGCTGTCTGATTCTT-3 
0 ; Gli1 forward 5 
0 -CCAACCTCTGTCTA 
CTCAC-3 
0 and Gli1 reverse 5 
0 -CCTGTTCTGGCTTGACTT-3 
0 ; GAPDH forward 
5-
0 GAAGGTCGGAGTCAACGGATTT-3 
0 and GAPDH reverse 5-
0 ATGGGTGGA 
ATC;ATATTGGAAC-3 
0 . The reactions were performed in a 96-well optical plate 
(Applied Biosystems, Warrington, UK) at 94 1C for 2 min, followed by 38 cycles of 
94 1C for 45 s, 56 1C for 45 s, and 72 1C for 40 s. </p>

<p>Western blotting and Immunofluorescence analysis. For western 
blotting, equal amounts of proteins collected from different cell lysates or fractions 
were resolved on 8-15% SDS-PAGE using a NuPAGE system (Invitrogen), and 
then transferred onto PVDF membranes according to the manufacturer's 
instructions. 
55 For immunofluorescence, cells were grown on coverslips and 
transfected with the Gli1 siRNA, incubated overnight at 4 1C with rabbit polyclonal 
anti-LC3 Ab (1 : 200), and then reacted with anti-rabbit IgG conjugated with Dylight 
488 (1 : 400) for 2 h at room temperature. After washing with PBS, the cells 
were mounted on vectashield and visualized using confocal microscopy 
(Leica, Heidelberg, Germany). </p>

<p>56,57   Transmission electron microscopy. Transmission Electron Microscopy 
(TEM) was performed on cells 48 h after Gli1 siRNA transfection. Cells were 
digested with 0.25% trypsin and suspended at a density of 1.0 Â 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>/ml. Then 3% 
glutaraldehyde was added for 3 h at 4 1C for fixation. Ultrathin sections (100 nm) 
were prepared, stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate, and examined under 
an electron transmission microscope (H-600; Hitachi, Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. The <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">19.0</rs> software package was used to perform 
all statistical analyses. Data were analyzed by one-way analysis of variance with 
the multiple comparison test of Bonferroni. Unpaired Student's t-tests were used 
for comparison between two groups. Data are shown as mean ± S.D. A value of 
Po0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest 
The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements. We appreciate the Health Science Center of Peking 
University for providing experimental instruments and technical assistance. This 
work was supported by the Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 81072189, 
81272381, and 81001193). </p>



<p> 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease is an open-access journal 
published by Nature Publishing Group. This work is 
licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit 
http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>Gli1 inhibition suppressed chondrosarcoma 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

</text></tei>