<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4585391" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background Ghrelin and obestatin are peptides of the gut-brain axis aff ecting appetite and 
gastrointestinal motility. </p>

<p>Methods We conducted a cross-sectional, case-control study to determine pre-and postprandial 
serum levels of total ghrelin and obestatin along with gastric emptying scintigraphy in children with 
symptoms suggestive of delayed gastric emptying time (GET), not attributable to any identifi able cause. </p>

<p>Results Twenty children with symptoms suggestive of delayed GET, of whom 9 had delayed 
GET, and 20 age-matched healthy children were enrolled. Preprandial ghrelin and obestatin 
were higher compared to controls (GHR mean level in patients and controls: 1162 pg/mL and 
401 pg/mL respectively; P&lt;0.05; OB mean level in patients and controls: 417 pg/mL and 325 pg/ 
mL respectively; not statistically signifi cant). Postprandial ghrelin was signifi cantly decreased 
in the subgroup of patients with delayed GET (GHR mean level in children with normal and 
prolonged GET: 1237 pg/mL and 584 pg/mL respectively; P&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Conclusion Obestatin and ghrelin were deranged in children with symptoms indicative of delayed 
GET of unexplained etiology. Gastric emptying was prolonged in almost half of the patients thus gastric 
emptying scintigraphy should be considered in the investigation of children with such symptomatology. </p>

<p>Ghrelin (GHR) and obestatin (OB) are peptides secreted 
by the stomach [1]. Th e gene of human GHR is located on 
chromosome 3p26-p25 and encodes a polypeptide called 
preproghrelin which undergoes a stepwise proteolytic cleavage 
generating GHR and subsequently OB [2]. GHR is orexigenic 
and promotes gastrointestinal (GI) motility whereas OB exerts 
anorexigenic eff ects, decelerates gastric emptying time and 
small bowel activity and reduces body weight [3]. </p>

<p>Early satiety, bloating, nausea and vomiting are symptoms 
frequently encountered in pediatrics; delayed gastric 
emptying time (GET) has been implicated as an underlying 
pathophysiological mechanism for the abovementioned 
symptoms [4,5]. 
We hypothesized that GHR and OB are implicated in the 
pathogenesis of delayed GET, in the absence of mechanical 
gastric outlet obstruction, in children presenting with 
symptoms of delayed GET that persist &gt;6 months and for 
which no cause was identifi ed [6,7]. 
Th e aim of this study was to assess GET as well as pre- and 
postprandial levels of GHR and OB and examine their 
association. </p>

<p>Patients and methods </p>

<p>Study subjects </p>

<p>All children referred for further investigation at a tertiary 
center (Pediatric Gastronterology Unit; 4th Pediatric 
Department, Papageorgiou Hospital; Aristotle University of 
Th essaloniki; Greece) for symptoms (duration &gt;6 months) </p>

<p>a 4 th Pediatric Department (Efstratios Saliakellis, Georgios Varlamis, 
Maria Fotoulaki); b 3 rd Nuclear Medicine Department (Nikolaos 
Karatzas, Ioannis Iakovou), Papageorgiou Hospital, Aristotle University, 
Th essaloniki, Greece; c 1 st Pediatric Department, Ippokratio Hospital, 
Aristotle University (Evangelia Farmaki), Th essaloniki, Greece </p>

<p>Confl ict of Interest: None </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Efstratios Saliakellis MD, PhD, 4 th Department 
of Pediatrics, Aristotle University of Th essaloniki, Medical School, 
Papageorgiou Hospital, Ring Road Nea Efk arpia, 56403 Th essaloniki, 
Greece, Tel.: +30 2313 323000, Fax: +30 2313 323918, e-mail: efstratios. 
saliakellis@gmail.com </p>

<p>Received 18 March 2015; accepted 30 May 2015 </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Ghrelin, obestatin and gastric emptying in children 453 </p>

<p>Annals of Gastroenterology 28 </p>

<p>indicative of delayed GET between March 2007 and March 
2013 were included in the study. 
Twenty healthy, age-matched children without any GI 
symptoms or evidence of other organic disease were also 
recruited as controls among patients examined at the pediatric 
outpatient clinic for routine assessment. Inclusion and 
exclusion criteria are shown in (Table 1). 
Th is study had institutional approval and was conducted 
according to Helsinki Declaration. Written informed consent 
was obtained from all study participants. </p>

<p>Assessment for potential organic disorders </p>

<p>All children of the present cohort were investigated for 
the presence of organic diseases with detailed clinical history, 
careful physical examination and a number of laboratory 
tests. Th e latter included complete blood count, baseline 
biochemistry with liver, pancreatic and renal function tests, 
C-reactive protein, erythrocyte sedimentation rate, urinalysis 
with culture, stool microscopy, and screening for celiac disease 
(total IgA and IgA anti-tissue transglutaminase antibodies) 
and H. pylori infection (serum anti-H. pylori IgG and IgM 
antibodies). Mechanical upper GI obstruction or anatomical 
abnormality was excluded in all patients with a combination of 
upper GI contrast series and/or esophagogastroduodenoscopy 
(EGD). </p>

<p>Gastric emptying scintigraphy </p>

<p>Aft er an overnight fast children underwent a 2-h gastric 
emptying scintigraphy with a standardized meal of solids. 
Th e meal consisted of 2 AA scrambled eggs labeled with 
technetium 99m ( 99m Tc) sulfur colloid (1 mCi), two thin slices 
of white bread, 1 teaspoon of butter (5 g) and 150mL of water 
to ease the ingestion process as the patients had to consume 
the aforementioned meal within 10 min. Th e amount of the 
test meal was calculated according to patient body surface area 
(test meal in g/1.73 m 2 ). </p>

<p>Immediately aft er meal ingestion all children were placed in 
the upright position in front of a γ-camera with parallel-hole 
collimator (Vertex-Plus Epic, ADAC/Philips). Anterior and 
posterior abdominal images were acquired at 15 min intervals 
for 1 min for a total duration of 2 h. Areas of interest were 
subsequently set in the stomach area and the rate at which the 
radioactive material left the stomach was calculated based on 
the geometric mean. 
Gastric half-emptying time (T 1/2 ) was defi ned as the time 
by which 50% of the radiolabeled meal of solids had left the 
stomach. GET was considered delayed if T 1/2 was &gt;90 min. 
In the intervals of image acquisition children were allowed 
to walk outside the γ-camera room; however, and until the 
test was over, they were neither allowed to eat or drink nor to 
engage in intense play. </p>

<p>Blood sample collection and analysis </p>

<p>Venous blood samples (4 mL) were collected between 
08:00-09:00 am immediately prior to the ingestion of the meal 
for the scintigraphic gastric emptying study and 2 h later, 
upon completion of the test. Th e blood samples were collected 
into biochemistry tubes (not containing EDTA, aprotinin or 
hydrochloric acid), and were immediately centrifuged at 4 o C 
for 5 min at 3000 rpm. Sera were subsequently extracted and 
stored at -24 o C. 
Serum total GHR and OB were measured using the human 
GHR and OB RIA commercially available kits (Phoenix 
Pharmaceuticals, Inc., Burlingame, California, USA). Due 
to ethical reasons gastric emptying scintigraphy was not 
performed and only morning fasting blood samples were 
collected for the measurement of preprandial levels of total 
GHR and OB in the control group. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Patient characteristics, serum levels of GHR and OB, 
GHR/OB ratio and GET T 1/2 are expressed as mean ± standard 
deviation and as median and range depending on the normality 
of the distributions of continuous variables as assessed with 
Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. 
Comparisons of preprandial GHR and OB as well as 
GHR/OB ratio between patients and controls were performed 
with Student's t-test, whereas paired t-test was used for 
comparisons between pre-and postprandial levels. Finally, 
t-test was also used to compare both pre-and postprandial 
levels between patients with normal and delayed GET. 
Categorical variables were compared using chi-square test. 
Furthermore the adjusted eff ect of diff erent factors [gender, 
age, body mass index (BMI z-score)] on GET, levels of GHR 
and OB, GHR/OB (pre-and postprandial) was explored 
using multiple regression analysis. Statistical analyses were 
performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 17.0</rs> soft ware (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>, 
Chicago, IL). P values &lt;0.05 were considered statistically 
signifi cant. </p>

<p>Table 1 Inclusion and exclusion study criteria 
Inclusion criteria 
• Age &lt;14 years 
• Symptoms present ≥6 months 
• No evidence of organic disease despite extensive diagnostic 
work-up </p>

<p>Exclusion criteria 
• Presence of gastric outlet obstruction and/or upper GI 
anatomical abnormality 
• Presence of other GI symptoms (e.g. swallowing disorders, 
dysphagia, gastro-esophageal refl ux, abnormal bowel habits) 
• Previous abdominal surgery and/or other major surgery 
• Evidence of organic disease (present or past) which could 
account for the patient's symptomatology (e.g. food allergy, 
hypothyroidism) 
• Inability to ingest the gastric scintigraphy meal within 10 min or 
total inability to receive it (e.g. egg allergy) </p>

<p>GI, gastrointestinal </p>



<p>Annals of Gastroenterology 28 </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Demographics and clinical characteristics </p>

<p>Twenty prepubertal children (7 male, 35%) with symptoms 
suggestive of delayed GET (early satiety, postprandial 
fullness, nausea, vomiting) that remained of unexplained 
etiology (duration of symptoms &gt;6 months) were identifi ed 
and included in the study. Of note, the initial diagnostic 
work-up which included a complete blood count, baseline 
biochemistry with liver, pancreatic and renal function tests, 
C-reactive protein, erythrocyte sedimentation rate, urinalysis 
with culture, stool microscopy, celiac disease (total IgA and 
IgA antitissue transglutaminase antibodies) and H. pylori 
(serum IgM and IgG antibodies) screening was within normal 
range. Furthermore, no mechanical upper GI obstruction or 
anatomical abnormality was revealed in any patient by means 
of a combination of upper GI contrast series and/or EGD. Of 
note, the histopathology of the biopsies taken during all EGD 
procedures was also without any abnormalities. Demographic 
data and baseline patient characteristics are presented in 
(Table 2). Twenty healthy, age-matched controls were also 
included. </p>

<p>GET </p>

<p>Nine of 20 patients had delayed GET (T 1/2 &gt;90 min). Th e 
median time for gastric emptying rate was 80.5 (range: 55-210) 
min. GET was not signifi cantly aff ected by age, gender and 
BMI (adjusted eff ect as assessed with regression analysis). </p>

<p>Serum total GHR and OB levels </p>

<p>Th e preprandial levels of GHR, OB and the GHR/OB ratio 
were signifi cantly higher in patients compared to controls 
(P&lt;0.05) (Fig. 1). Postprandially (patient group) there was a 
decrease in GHR and an increase in OB levels which were not 
statistically signifi cant; however the postprandial GHR/OB 
ratio was found to be signifi cantly lower (Fig. 2). Moreover, 
the postprandial levels of GHR and the GHR/OB ratio (but 
not OB) were signifi cantly lower in the patients who had 
delayed GET (P&lt;0.05) (Fig. 3). Pre-and postprandial levels 
of GHR, OB were not signifi cantly aff ected by patient/control 
characteristics (adjusted eff ect, regression analysis). </p>

<p>Table 2 Study participants' clinical characteristics and laboratory 
fi ndings </p>

<p>Variable 
Patients 
Controls </p>

<p>Number 
20 
20 </p>

<p>Median age, years (range) 
6 (2-12) 
8 (2-12) </p>

<p>Gender ratio, male: female 
7:13 
10:10 </p>

<p>BMI z-score (±SD) 
−1.99±1.79 
0.24±0.69 </p>

<p>Symptoms (number of patients, %) 
Early Satiety 
Bloating 
Failure to thrive 
Occasional nausea/vomiting </p>

<p>20 (100) 
11 (55) 
12 (60) 
4 (20) </p>

<p>N/A </p>

<p>GHR preprandial (pg/mL; mean±SD) 1161.9±760.3 401.1±254.6 </p>

<p>GHR postprandial (pg/mL; mean±SD) 943.3±564.1 
N/A </p>

<p>OB preprandial (pg/mL; mean±SD) 
416.7±110.2 325.3±163.6 </p>

<p>OB postprandial (pg/mL; mean±SD) 
535.1±155.2 
N/A </p>

<p>GHR/OB preprandial (mean±SD) 
2.8±1.5 
1.3±0.6 </p>

<p>GHR/OB postprandial (mean±SD) 
1.7±0.8 
N/A </p>

<p>GET T1/2 (min; median, range) 
80.5 (55-210) 
N/A </p>

<p>N/A, not applicable; SD, standard deviation; BMI, body mass index; 
GHR, ghrelin; OB, obestatin; GET, gastric emptying time; GET T 1/2 , gastric 
half-emptying time </p>

<p>Figure 1 Preprandial levels of GHR, OB and GHR/OB ratio in patient 
and control groups 
GHR, ghrelin; OB, obestatin; GHR, OB and GHR/OB values represent 
mean values </p>

<p>pg/mL </p>

<p>Preprandial GRH 
Preprandial OB Preprandial GHR/OB </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 </p>

<p>1162 </p>

<p>401 
417 
325 
2.8 
1.3 </p>

<p>Patients 
Controls </p>

<p>1400 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Pre- and postprandial levels of GHR, OB and GHR/OB ratio 
in patient group 
GHR, ghrelin; OB, obestatin; GHR, OB and GHR/OB values represent 
mean values </p>

<p>1400 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>pg/mL </p>

<p>GHR 
GHR/OB 
OB </p>

<p>1162 </p>

<p>943 </p>

<p>417 </p>

<p>535 </p>

<p>2.8 
1.7 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 </p>

<p>Postprandial </p>

<p>Preprandial </p>

<p>Figure 3 Pre- and postprandial levels of GHR, OB and GHR/OB ratio 
in patients with normal and delayed gastric emptying time (GET) 
GHR, ghrelin; OB, obestatin; GHR, OB and GHR/OB values represent 
mean values </p>

<p>pg/mL </p>

<p>1400 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Preprandial OB 
Preprandial GHR 
Preprandial GHR/OB 
Postprandial OB 
Postprandial GHR 
Postprandial GHR/OB </p>

<p>1308 </p>

<p>983 </p>

<p>451 
374 
2.8 2.7 </p>

<p>1237 </p>

<p>584 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 </p>

<p>591 
466 </p>

<p>2.1 
1.2 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 </p>

<p>Normal GET </p>

<p>Delayed GET </p>

<p>Ghrelin, obestatin and gastric emptying in children 455 </p>

<p>Annals of Gastroenterology 28 </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In the present study we assessed GET and total GHR, OB 
serum levels in children with persistent (&gt;6 months) and 
unexplained symptoms of delayed gastric emptying. We found 
that: GET was prolonged in 9 out 20 patients; preprandial 
GHR and OB levels were signifi cantly higher in patients than 
controls; patients with delayed GET had signifi cantly lower 
postprandial GHR and GHR/OB ratio compared to those with 
normal GET. 
Approximately 50% (9/20) of the patients had delayed 
GET of solids as assessed with the gold standard method of 
scintigraphic imaging of a radiolabeled meal [8,9]. Th is fi nding 
is in line with results published by other researchers and 
highlights the fact that delayed GE is possibly implicated in 
the pathogenesis of dyspeptic symptoms [10]. Interestingly, in 
the other 50% of the patients GET was normal indicating that 
another cause should be sought for their symptomatology. 
Th e preprandial levels of GHR and OB were higher in 
our patients as compared to controls. Th is is an interesting 
fi nding which is in contrast with the lower preprandial GHR, 
OB levels demonstrated by other researchers in adults with 
functional dyspepsia [11]. Our results however are similar with 
studies in children with poor appetite and adults with anorexia 
nervosa (AN) which revealed increased preprandial levels of 
GHR and OB particularly in AN patients compared to healthy 
subjects [12-14]. 
Of note, Ang et al have demonstrated that GHR increases 
the gastric tone in the fasting state and inhibits gastric 
accommodation when administered during a meal [15]. Th e 
latter could possibly explain the symptoms of early satiety and 
postprandial fullness in the patients of the present study who 
had signifi cantly higher preprandial GHR levels. 
Finally, we have shown that the postprandial levels of GHR 
and the GHR/OB ratio are signifi cantly lower amongst patients 
with delayed GET. Limited data exist on the correlation 
between GHR and GET in patients with dyspeptic symptoms. 
Lee et al did not fi nd a signifi cant correlation between pre-/ 
postprandial GHR and GET in adults with dysmotility-like 
functional dyspepsia, although 5 out 7 patients with abnormally 
low preprandial GHR had delayed GET [11]. Noteworthily, 
postprandial OB was found to increase in our patients however 
this was not statistically signifi cant. Th e resulting imbalance in 
the GHR/OB ratio may be implicated in the pathogenesis of 
dyspeptic symptoms, although further research is required to 
validate this hypothesis [12,13]. 
Th e interplay between gut peptides such as GHR, OB and 
GI motility is still the subject of research, however due to the 
scarce data our results are not easily interpreted [11,15,16]. 
We have measured total GHR, which is considered as an 
acceptable surrogate for acylated GHR, and not its isoforms (acyl-
and des-acyl-GHR) which have opposite biologic properties 
(acyl-GHR: orexigenic, promotes GI motility, des-acyl-GHR: 
opposite eff ects) [3,11,17-19]. A potential imbalance between the 
two could also partially explain our results. 
Polymorphisms in the preproghrelin gene, diff erences in the 
transcriptional, translational and post-translational processes </p>

<p>could also lead to disturbances in the production of GHR and 
OB [13,14,20,21]. Moreover the role of sequence variants in the 
coding region of GHR receptor (growth hormone secretagogue 
receptor -GHSR1a) and genetic variations of the enzyme 
responsible for its acylation and thus biologic activity (GHR 
O-acyltransferase, GOAT) have also been explored in the 
regulation of body weight in children and in adults with AN, 
without, however, defi nitive conclusions [22,23]. 
Limitations of the present study include the small 
number of patients and the fact that total serum GHR 
was measured without discrimination between acyl-GHR 
which promotes the appetite and GI motility and des-
acyl-GHR that has biological properties similar to OB [1]. 
Moreover, postprandial serum levels of GHR, OB along with 
scintigraphic evaluation of GET have not been assessed in 
controls as this was not ethically acceptable. Furthermore 
amongst the various parameters of the gastric sensorimotor 
function that could cause symptoms similar to the ones 
described, GET was the only one assessed, as other diagnostic 
modalities, e.g. electrogastrogram and barostat, were not 
available in our institution. 
Strengths of the study include the homogeneous and 
carefully selected population and the fact that it off ers a novel 
insight regarding the role of GHR and OB in children with GI 
symptoms. 
In conclusion, our data suggest that delayed gastric emptying 
is common in children with unexplained dyspeptic symptoms. 
In these patients, GHR and OB are deranged suggesting that 
they may play a role, not as yet fully clarifi ed, in the regulation 
of gastric motility and the pathogenesis of such symptoms. </p>

<p>Summary Box </p>

<p>What is already known: </p>

<p>• Ghrelin and obestatin are peptides of the gut-brain 
axis aff ecting appetite and gastrointestinal motility 
• Delayed gastric emptying has been implicated in 
the pathogenesis of dyspeptic symptoms (e.g. early 
satiety, bloating) 
• Th e complex mechanisms regulating gastric 
motility in children are still not well understood </p>

<p>What the new fi ndings are: </p>

<p>• Delayed gastric emptying was not uncommon in 
children with unexplained dyspeptic symptoms 
• Serum levels of ghrelin and obestatin were 
deranged in children with symptoms suggestive 
of delayed gastric emptying not attributable to any 
identifi able cause 
• Ghrelin to obestatin ratio seems to aff ect gastric 
emptying time in children with the aforementioned 
symptomatology </p>



<p>Annals of Gastroenterology 28 </p>

<p>Further studies are warranted to fully understand their role, 
particularly in view of the therapeutic potential of ghrelin in 
the treatment of gut motility disorders. </p>



</text></tei>