<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4616920" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>SUMMARY </p>

<p>The efficacy of nitazoxanide (NTZ) against toxocariasis was investigated in an experimental murine model and results were 
compared to those obtained using mebendazole. Sixty male BALB/c mice, aged six to eight weeks-old, were divided into groups 
of 10 each; fifty were orally infected with 300 larvaed eggs of T. canis and grouped as follows, G I: infected untreated mice; G II: 
infected mice treated with MBZ (15 mg/kg/day) 10 days postinfection (dpi); G III: infected mice treated with NTZ (20 mg/kg/day) 
10 dpi; G IV: infected mice treated with MBZ 60 dpi; G V: infected mice treated with NTZ 60 dpi; GVI: control group comprising 
uninfected mice. Mice were bled via retro-orbital plexus on four occasions between 30 and 120 dpi. Sera were processed using the 
ELISA technique to detect IgG anti-Toxocara antibodies. At 120 dpi, mice were sacrificed for larval recovery in the CNS, liver, lungs, 
kidneys, eyes and carcass. Results showed similar levels of anti-Toxocara IgG antibodies among mice infected but not submitted to 
treatment and groups treated with MBZ or NTZ, 10 and 60 dpi. Larval recovery showed similar values in groups treated with NTZ 
and MBZ 10 dpi. MBZ showed better efficacy 60 dpi, with a 72.6% reduction in the parasite load compared with NTZ, which showed 
only 46.5% reduction. We conclude that administration of these anthelmintics did not modify the humoral response in experimental 
infection by T. canis. No parasitological cure was observed with either drug; however, a greater reduction in parasite load was achieved 
following treatment with MBZ. </p>

<p>Human infection by Toxocara larvae is considered an important 
and frequent zoonosis worldwide, and the main cause of visceral larva 
migrans (VLM) and other related syndromes. In humans, the main 
etiological agents for these syndromes are Toxocara canis and T. cati, 
respectively, ascarids of dogs and cats </p>

<p>5,11,16   . </p>

<p>Several drugs are currently used to treat VLM in humans, and 
benzimidazole anthelmintics have shown moderate or good efficacy in the 
resolution of clinical signs or symptoms </p>

<p>16,28   . Experimentally, however, the 
various drugs tested in a murine model, which, as occurs in humans, are 
paratenic hosts species for Toxocara spp. larvae, showed a reduction of 
the parasite load that did not result in complete parasitological cure </p>

<p>1,6,22   . 
The same situation probably occurs in the treatment of infected humans. </p>

<p>In recent years, studies have demonstrated the efficacy of 
nitazoxanide in the treatment of infections caused by certain protozoa, 
helminths, anaerobic bacteria and hepatitis C virus 
19 , but few reports 
exist concerning its use in the treatment of infections caused by helminth 
larvae, particularly, roundworm larvae </p>

<p>15   . More recently, DELGADO et </p>

<p>al. 
9 reported an efficacy of 61.2% in the treatment of mice experimentally 
infected by T. canis. </p>

<p>The aim of this study was to evaluate the response of mice 
experimentally infected by T. canis following treatment with nitazoxanide 
on the tenth and sixtieth days after infection (dpi), regarding the reduction 
in parasitic load and the humoral response represented by anti-Toxocara 
IgG antibodies, compared to the response obtained in mice treated with 
mebendazole, previously considered a good schedule in the reduction 
of T. canis load in mice </p>

<p>21   . </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Eggs: T. canis eggs used in this experiment were obtained from adult 
female worms, eliminated by naturally infected dogs following treatment 
with piperazine. After dissecting the worms, eggs were incubated in 2% 
formalin at 26 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C for four to six weeks, and washed in filtered water to 
remove formalin before use. </p>

<p>Mice infection and treatment: Sixty male BALB/c mice, aged six 
to eight weeks-old, provided by the Faculty of Medicine of São Paulo </p>

<p>LESCANO, S.A.Z.; SANTOS, S.V.; ASSIS, J.M.L. &amp; CHIEFFI, P.P. -Efficacy of nitazoxanide against Toxocara canis: larval recovery and humoral immune response in experimentally infected 
mice. Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo, 57(4): 337-41, 2015. </p>

<p>338 </p>

<p>University, were divided into groups of 10 mice each. Fifty mice were 
infected by stomach tube with 300 T. canis embryonated eggs in 200 
μL of filtered water suspension, and ten mice were maintained as an 
uninfected control group, receiving filtered water alone, as indicated 
in Table 1. All the animals used in this study received water and a 
commercial diet ad lib and were treated in accordance to the ethical 
guidelines of the Institutional Experimental Guidelines for animal 
studies (CEUA) of the Institute of Tropical Medicine of São Paulo 
University (IMT/USP). </p>

<p>At the acute phase of infection, 10 days postinfection (dpi), mice 
from group II were treated per os with mebendazole (15 mg/kg/day), 
and those from group III with nitazoxanide (20 mg/kg/day), for five 
consecutive days. Groups IV and V were treated with mebendazole 
and nitazoxanide respectively, using the same doses at 60 dpi (chronic 
phase of the infection) for the same period. Group I remained untreated 
throughout the experiment. </p>

<p>Sera collection: All groups were anesthetized with 100 mg/kg of 
xylazine and 10 mg/kg of ketamine, and bled by orbital plexus puncture 
at 30, 60, 90 and 120 dpi. The sera obtained were frozen and stored in 
aliquots in plastic micro tubes at -20 °C, for subsequent processing by 
ELISA. </p>

<p>Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (Ig ELISA): Serum samples 
collected from mice with different treatment schedules were examined 
by ELISA to detect IgG class anti-Toxocara antibodies; using excretion-
secretion T. canis antigen (TES) prepared from the culture of infective 
larvae of this parasite in Eagle medium, according to a standardized 
technique described by DE SAVIGNY et al. 
10 and modified in our 
laboratory. Different concentrations of ES antigen of T. canis were tested 
using positive and negative control sera and a protein concentration of 
20 μg/mL (100 mL per well in plate) was determined to performe the 
tests. Mouse sera were diluted in PBS-T-Gelatin at 1:800. The enzyme 
conjugate anti-mouse IgG labeled with horseradish peroxidase (g-chain 
specific, Sigma Immunochemicals) was used at 1:4,000 dilution. A 
mixture of H 2 O 2 and O-phenylenediamine (1.2-Benzenediamine) (Sigma 
Chemical Co.) [C 6 H 8 N 2 . 2HCl], diluted in citrate-phosphate buffer, was 
used as substrate. </p>

<p>The results were evaluated by spectrophotometric reading at a 
wavelength of 492 nm in Titertek Multiskan apparatus MCC/340 P 
version 2.20 (Lab-Systems, Finland). To calculate the threshold of </p>

<p>reactivity ("cut-off") the mean optical density (OD) of readings of sera 
from control group mice was considered, plus two standard deviations. 
As a positive control, serum samples from three mice infected for 90 
days were used 
18 and, as a negative control, serum samples from mice 
bled before infection were used. </p>

<p>T. canis larval recovery in tissues: At the end of the experiment 
(120 dpi), mice from all the infected groups were sacrificed by cervical 
dislocation and larvae were recovered from their brains and carcasses, 
following digestion with 0.5% HCl for 24 h at 37 ºC. Sedimental liquid 
was centrifuged for two min at 1500 rpm, 2 mL of the sediment were 
collected, thoroughly mixed, and 0.1 mL samples were viewed under a 
light microscope to determine larval counts </p>

<p>33   . </p>

<p>Statistics: Arithmetic mean and standard deviation were used to 
present data. One-way ANOVA and Tukey test for multiple comparisons 
were conducted with Optical Density (OD) readings of sera from 
infected and treated mice from different groups, and two-way ANOVA 
and Bonferroni post test were used to compare larval recovery in tissues 
using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Prisma</rs> program, version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0</rs>. Differences were considered to 
be significant when p &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>An issue that has not been fully resolved is the way of assessing 
drugs used in the treatment of experimental toxocariasis, in which the 
murine model is the most frequently used. Numerous authors have used 
the recovery of T. canis larvae, following digestion of the carcass and 
some organs of experimentally infected mice </p>

<p>14,23,24,28,31   . Others, however, 
have employed immunological techniques 
3,7 . In this study, we sought 
to determine the kinetics of IgG anti-Toxocara antibodies in mice, 
experimentally infected with larvae of this nematode and subsequently 
treated with mebendazole (MBZ) or nitazoxanide (NTZ), as well as 
observing larval recovery after acid digestion of different mouse organs 
and tissues. </p>

<p>The humoral antibody response of the IgG class anti-Toxocara (Fig. 
1 and 2) was detected within the first 30 dpi, which remained positive up 
to 120 dpi in both groups treated with both anthelmintic drugs. Moreover, 
a marked increase in antibodies was observed between 90 and 120 dpi. 
This reactivity is probably due to the continuous release of Toxocara 
antigens even by dead larvae, from antigens stored in their cuticles. 
On the other hand, it is known that most anthelmintics do not reach 
all larvae present in the host 
8,21 . No other significant differences were 
observed in the levels of anti-Toxocara antibodies among mice treated 
with nitazoxanide or mebendazole compared with the group infected, 
but not submitted to treatment. </p>

<p>Comparing the amount of T. canis larvae recovered in various organs 
of mice treated with mebendazole or nitazoxanide with the result in the 
group not submitted to treatment, differences were only observed when 
the treatment occurred after 60 days of infection (Table 2). Moreover, 
the difference was significantly more evident in the group treated with 
mebendazole. </p>

<p>Posttreatment larval recovery, in all the organs analyzed, revealed a 
decrease in the amount of larvae recovered in the central nervous system 
of the mice (Table 3). </p>

<p>Table 1 
Experimental infection and treatment of BALB/c mice with different doses of 
mebendazole and nitazoxanide </p>

<p>Group 
Infection phase 
Drug/ dose </p>

<p>I 
Infected 
No treatment </p>

<p>II 
Acute phase 
mebendazole (15 mg/kg/day) </p>

<p>III 
Acute phase 
nitazoxanide (20 mg/kg/day) </p>

<p>IV 
Chronic phase 
mebendazole (15 mg/kg/day) </p>

<p>V 
Chronic phase 
nitazoxanide (20 mg/kg/day) </p>

<p>Control 
Noninfected 
No treatment </p>

<p>LESCANO, S.A.Z.; SANTOS, S.V.; ASSIS, J.M.L. &amp; CHIEFFI, P.P. -Efficacy of nitazoxanide against Toxocara canis: larval recovery and humoral immune response in experimentally infected 
mice. Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo, 57(4): 337-41, 2015. </p>

<p>339 </p>

<p>Previous studies indicated that mice and other murine behave like 
paratenic hosts when infected by larvae of T. canis 
30 and are therefore 
suitable models for studying host-parasite relationships in the case of </p>

<p>human infection with this nematode </p>

<p>4,11   . In C57BL/6 and BALB/c mice 
infected with T. canis and untreated, the larvae can be found in the brain 
and carcass, even up to a year after inoculation, with a slight reduction 
in the total larval count </p>

<p>17,20   . Various anthelmintics have been used in 
the treatment of murine toxocariasis, in order to evaluate their efficacy: 
mebendazole, albendazole, fenbendazole and thiabendazole. The first 
three, and diethylcarbamazine, were recommended by the WHO in 1995 
as effective drugs against toxocariasis </p>

<p>20   . According to SMITH et al. 
29 , 
mebendazole seems to be a good alternative for toxocariasis treatment in 
paratenic hosts. LESCANO et al. 
21 also reported a significant decrease in 
the parasite load of mice experimentally infected by T. canis and treated 
with mebendazole, thiabendazole or ivermectin. </p>

<p>Nitazoxanide (NTZ) is a novel compound with broad-spectrum 
activity against several genera of parasites, including intestinal protozoa, 
helminths and anaerobic bacteria </p>

<p>13,32   . Its activity is associated with the 
inhibition of enzymatic activity of pyruvate ferredoxin oxidoreductase 
(PEOR) and against the disulfide isomerase protein (PDI), an essential 
enzyme for anaerobic metabolism. However, the mode of action of NTZ 
and its principal metabolite, tizoxanide, on nematodes is unknown </p>

<p>27   . Its 
use has been approved for treatment of humans with diseases caused 
by Giardia intestinalis and Cryptosporidium </p>

<p>2,25   , and DELGADO et al. </p>

<p>9   reported some efficacy against T. canis larvae in experimental infections. </p>

<p>The results of this research suggest that the humoral immune response 
is not an appropriate parameter for evaluating drug efficacy in paratenic 
hosts experimentally infected by T. canis. However, at the end of the 
experiment, larval recovery was shown to be the most appropriate tool 
for evaluating drug efficacy in this experimental model. </p>

<p>Fig. 1 -Dynamics of ELISA circulating anti-T. canis Ig G antibodies in BALB/c mice 
infected with Toxocara canis eggs and treated in the acute phase of infection (10dpi) with 
G II-mebendazole () or G III-nitazoxanide (), comparing with the G I () infected 
non-treated group. </p>

<p>Fig. 2 -Dynamics of ELISA circulating anti-T. canis Ig G antibodies in BALB/c mice 
infected with Toxocara canis eggs and treated in the chronic phase of infection (60 dpi) 
with G IV-mebendazole () or G V-nitazoxanide (), comparing with the G I () infected 
non-treated group. </p>

<p>Table 2 
Toxocara canis larval recovery in BALB/c mice treated with MBZ or 
NTZ in the acute and chronic phases of experimental infection 
(mean and standard deviation). </p>

<p>Groups 
Acute phase 
Chronic phase </p>

<p>MBZ 
84.4 ± 38.1 
24.6 ± 23.9 * </p>

<p>NTZ 
71.6 ± 24.3 
48.3 ± 27.7 </p>

<p>Infected untreated 
89.9 ± 22.9 </p>

<p>MBZ = mebendazole; NTZ = nitazoxanide; * p &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>Table 3 
Mean number and standard deviation of Toxocara canis larvae recovered in organs and tissues of BALB/c mice infected and treated with 
MBZ or NTZ in the acute and chronic phases of infection </p>

<p>GI (Non treated) </p>

<p>Acute 
Chronic </p>

<p>GII-MBZ 
GIII-NTZ 
GIV-MBZ 
GV-NTZ </p>

<p>Carcass 
59 ± 11.59 
45.4 ± 10.21 
42.6 ± 16.94 
16 ±14.54 
38.6 ± 22.52 </p>

<p>Liver 
2.8 ± 2.16 
2.8 ± 2.38 
1.6 ± 1.67 
0.4 ± 0.89 
1.2 ± 1.6 </p>

<p>Lungs 
0.4 ± 0.89 
0 
0.2 ± 0.44 
0 
0 </p>

<p>Kidneys 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>Brain 
26.8 ± 16.11 
35.8 ± 31.52 
27 ± 14.37 
8.2 ± 8.64 
7.4 ± 3.43 </p>

<p>Eyes 
0.8 ± 1.30 
0.4 ± 0.54 
0.2 ± 0.44 
0 
0.8 ± 1.30 </p>

<p>LESCANO, S.A.Z.; SANTOS, S.V.; ASSIS, J.M.L. &amp; CHIEFFI, P.P. -Efficacy of nitazoxanide against Toxocara canis: larval recovery and humoral immune response in experimentally infected 
mice. Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo, 57(4): 337-41, 2015. </p>

<p>340 </p>

<p>Considering the larval recovery results, the relative ineffectiveness 
of mebendazole or nitazoxanide administration in the treatment of 
Toxocara infections in the murine model is evident and this is probably 
true in the case of human infections by T. canis, which would result in 
visceral larva migrans syndrome. Despite these fairly moderate results, 
the greater reduction observed in the parasite load following mebendazole 
administration, compared with the results achieved when nitazoxanide 
was used, deserves some attention. </p>

<p>RESUMO </p>

<p>Eficácia da nitazoxanida contra Toxocara canis: recuperação 
larvária e resposta imune humoral em camundongos 
experimentalmente infectados </p>

<p>Foi investigada a eficácia da nitazoxanida (NTZ) na toxocaríase 
murina experimental e os resultados comparados com os obtidos usando 
mebendazol (MBZ). Sessenta camundongos BALB/c machos, com idade 
entre seis e oito semanas foram divididos em grupos de 10 cada, 50 foram 
infectados oralmente com 300 ovos larvados de T. canis e agrupados a 
seguir: GI: camundongos infectados não tratados; GII: camundongos 
infectados tratados com MBZ (15 mg/kg/dia) 10 dias pós-infecção 
(dpi); GIII: camundongos infectados tratados com NTZ (20 mg/kg/dia) 
10 dpi, GIV: camundongos infectados tratados com MBZ 60 dpi; GV: 
camundongos infectados tratados com NTZ 60 dpi; GVI: controle não 
infectado. Os camundongos foram sangrados via plexo retro orbitário 
em quatro ocasiões entre o 30º e 120º dpi. Os soros foram processados 
pela técnica de ELISA para detecção de anticorpos IgG anti-Toxocara. 
Aos 120 dpi, os animais foram sacrificados para a recuperação larvária 
do SNC, fígado, pulmões, rins, olhos e carcaça. Os resultados mostraram 
níveis similares de anticorpos IgG anti-Toxocara entre os camundongos 
infectados mas não submetidos a tratamento e os grupos infectados e 
tratados com MBZ ou NTZ, aos 10 e 60 dpi. Os valores da recuperação 
larval foram similares nos grupos tratados com NTZ e MBZ 10 dpi. 
MBZ mostrou melhor eficácia aos 60 dpi, com redução de 72,6% da 
carga parasitária comparada com NTZ, que mostrou redução somente 
de 46,5%. Concluímos que a administração destes anti-helmínticos não 
modificou a resposta humoral na infecção experimental por T. canis. Não 
foi observada cura parasitológica com nenhuma das drogas; porém maior 
redução na carga parasitária foi obtida após o tratamento com MBZ. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT </p>

<p>The authors have no conflict of interest to declare. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by the Medical Research Laboratory 
(LIM-06), and J.L. Assis was supported by a scholarship from the 
Administrative Development Foundation (FUNDAP). </p>



<p>LIBRARY OF THE </p>

<p>SÃO PAULO INSTITUTE OF TROPICAL MEDICINE </p>

<p>Website: http://www.imt.usp.br/sobre-o-imtsp/biblioteca 
Address: Biblioteca do Instituto de Medicina Tropical de São Paulo da Universidade de São Paulo 
Av. Dr. Enéas de Carvalho Aguiar, 470. 
05403-000 -São Paulo -SP -Brazil. </p>

<p>Telephone: 5511 3061-7003 </p>

<p>The Library of the São Paulo Institute of Tropical Medicine (IMTSP Library) was created on January 
15, 1959 in order to serve all those who are interested in tropical diseases. </p>

<p>The IMTSP Library has a collection consisting of books, theses, annals of congresses, journals, 
and reference works. </p>

<p>The collection of the Library can be searched through the USP Bibliographic Database -Dedalus 
at the URL http://200.144.190.234/F </p>

</text></tei>