<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4649725" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Introduction: The purpose of the study was to evaluate the performance and usability of the FreeStyle 
Ò LibreÔ 
Flash glucose monitoring system (Abbott Diabetes Care, Alameda, CA) for interstitial glucose results compared 
with capillary blood glucose results. 
Materials and Methods: Seventy-two study participants with type 1 or type 2 diabetes were enrolled by four 
U.S. clinical sites. A sensor was inserted on the back of each upper arm for up to 14 days. Three factory-only 
calibrated sensor lots were used in the study. Sensor glucose measurements were compared with capillary blood 
glucose (BG) results (approximately eight per day) obtained using the BG meter built into the reader (BG 
reference) and with the YSI analyzer (Yellow Springs Instrument, Yellow Springs, OH) reference tests at three 
clinic visits (32 samples per visit). Sensor readings were masked to the participants. 
Results: The accuracy of the results was demonstrated against capillary BG reference values, with 86.7% of 
sensor results within Consensus Error Grid Zone A. The percentage of readings within Consensus Error Grid 
Zone A on Days 2, 7, and 14 was 88.4%, 89.2%, and 85.2%, respectively. The overall mean absolute relative 
difference was 11.4%. The mean lag time between sensor and YSI reference values was 4.5 -4.8 min. Sensor 
accuracy was not affected by factors such as body mass index, age, type of diabetes, clinical site, insulin 
administration, or hemoglobin A1c. 
Conclusions: Interstitial glucose measurements with the FreeStyle Libre system were found to be accurate 
compared with capillary BG reference values, with accuracy remaining stable over 14 days of wear and 
unaffected by patient characteristics. </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>apillary and venous blood glucose (BG) values are 
typically used as reference to evaluate the accuracy of in 
vivo sensor devices. 
1-5 Clinical laboratories use venous 
samples analyzed using a laboratory analyzer, whereas lay 
users use capillary BG measurements measured using a glu-
cose meter for the calibration of sensors. 
6-8 Glucose con-
centrations between the capillary and venous samples differ, 
and therefore the sample type used for calibration versus </p>

<p>reference measurement may influence the results of an ac-
curacy evaluation. 
9,10 The FreeStyle 
Ò LibreÔ Flash glucose 
monitoring system (Abbott Diabetes Care, Alameda, CA), 
hereafter referred to as the ''System,'' is an interstitial glucose 
monitoring system intended to be a replacement for the cap-
illary BG measurement. Therefore, capillary BG may be 
considered an appropriate comparator in evaluating the per-
formance and accuracy of this factory-only calibrated System. 
Additionally, capillary BG provides more reference points 
and represents real-life accuracy during daily patient use. </p>

<p>1 AMCR Institute, Escondido, California. 
2 Atlanta Diabetes Associates, Atlanta, Georgia. 
3 Diablo Clinical Research, Walnut Creek, California. 
4 Rainier Clinical Research Center, Renton, Washington. 
5 Clinical Affairs, Abbott Diabetes Care, Alameda, California. 
This study is registered with ClinicalTrials.gov with clinical trial registration number NCT02073058. 
ª The Author(s) 2015; Published by Mary Ann Liebert, Inc. This Open Access article is distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution Noncommercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits any noncommercial use, 
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited. </p>

<p>DIABETES TECHNOLOGY &amp; THERAPEUTICS 
Volume 17, Number 11, 2015 
DOI: 10.1089/dia.2014.0378 </p>



<p>The System has several features that distinguish it from 
existing sensor technology. The wired enzyme sensor is cali-
brated in the factory and therefore requires no user calibration 
during 14 days of wear. This feature differs from existing 
sensors, which require multiple fingerstick BG measure-
ments over the life of the sensor for calibration. 
11,12 The entire 
System's on-body sensor patch worn on the back of the upper 
arm is disposable after use. The hand-held reader with the 
built-in FreeStyle Precision BG meter is used to scan the 
sensor to receive a glucose result along with historic results 
with a 15-min frequency for up to 8 h. The BG readings on the 
built-in meter are independent of, and do not influence, sensor 
readings. The System displays trends and alerts on the Reader 
but does not have real-time alarms, which may provide a good 
option for individuals who complain of alarm fatigue. </p>

<p>11,13 </p>

<p>The objective of this article is to describe the performance 
and usability of the System by comparing its scanned sensor 
results with capillary BG values measured using the built-in 
BG meter. Performance against the venous blood reference is 
provided for comparison. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>This prospective, single-arm, clinical study was conducted 
at four U.S. clinical sites. The protocol and informed consent 
forms were approved by a central Institutional Review Board, 
and all subjects provided written informed consent before 
enrollment in the study. 
Study participants inserted and wore the sensor on the back 
of each upper arm (two sensors total), without any over-
bandage, for up to 14 days. Three factory-calibrated pro-
duction sensor lots were used for the study. This number is 
consistent with the industry practice to demonstrate the per-
formance of reagent systems across multiple production lots. 
There were three scheduled in-clinic visits during the 
14-day sensor wear period, where venous blood samples were 
collected every 15 min over an 8-h period for YSI analyzer 
(Yellow Springs Instrument, Yellow Springs, OH) reference 
tests. The first in-clinic visit was between Day 1 and 3, the 
second in-clinic visit was between Day 4 and 9, and the third 
in-clinic visit was between Day 10 and 14. Twenty-four (of 
144) sensors that were dislodged prior to the second in-clinic 
visit were replaced; sensors that were dislodged after that 
time were not replaced. 
At least eight capillary BG tests, using the BG meter built 
into the reader, were required to be performed on each day of 
the sensor wear, both at home and in the clinic. One strip lot 
was used to minimize lot-to-lot variation. The preferred 
testing was upon waking, before each meal, an hour after 
each meal, and at bedtime. Immediately after each BG test, 
participants obtained a confirmation of a successful sensor 
scan. Sensor readings were masked to participants, who were 
asked to maintain their established diabetes management 
plan. There was no manipulation of the glucose levels of the 
subjects except for their normal meal and insulin doses. Cap-
illary BG tests coincided with venous YSI samples drawn 
during in-clinic visits. 
A linear mixed model was used to assess sensitivity and 
mean absolute relative difference (MARD) between inser-
tion sites, with subject as a random effect and insertion site 
(left arm, right arm) and lot as fixed effects. The lag between 
the System sensor and YSI reference was evaluated using </p>

<p>a model that characterizes delay with a time constant. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Analyses were carried out using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.2</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, NC). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Seventy-two of 75 study participants were included in the 
evaluation. Three participants exited after Visit 1 (two could 
not comply with study visits, and one had non-study-related 
severe hypoglycemia prior to sensor insertion with unknown 
complications). The subject characteristics of the study par-
ticipants are provided in Table 1. 
The real-time glucose level was available for 99.2% 
(25,834/26,045) of sensor scans, where complete sensor data 
were transferred to the reader. In total, 13,195 BG and 12,172 
YSI reference results were paired with sensor glucose results. 
Twenty-eight pairs were excluded because the reference 
glucose result was beyond the BG system's dynamic range 
(20-500 mg/dL), and 114 pairs were excluded because the 
sensor result was beyond the System's dynamic range (40-
500 mg/dL). The percentages of results in Zone A of the 
Consensus and Clarke Error Grids were 86.7% and 85.5%, 
respectively (Fig. 1). The percentages of sensor results in 
Zones A and B of the Consensus and Clarke Error Grids were 
99.7% and 99.0%, respectively, whereas 86.2% and 82.8% of 
sensor results were within -15 mg/dL or -20% of BG ref-
erence and venous reference, respectively. Continuous glu-
cose error grid analysis (EGA) versus venous reference 
showed 96.5% (11,232/11,640) of the data categorized as 
clinically accurate, and a further 2.4% (274/11,640) were 
classified as benign errors. 
The overall MARD was 11.4% for sensor results with 
capillary BG reference. The overall MARD in the clinic alone 
for sensors' results with capillary BG reference and with YSI 
reference was 12.1% and 12%, respectively. A detailed dif-
ference analysis against capillary and venous blood reference </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline Characteristics 
of Study Participants </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Mean -SD Median 
Range </p>

<p>Age (years) 
46.4 -15.1 48.5 
18-71 
Weight 
Pounds 
182.2 -42.1 175.8 102.0-299.8 
Kilograms 
82.6 -19.1 79.7 46.3-136.0 
Height 
Inches 
67.1 -4.3 66.5 
59-81 
Meters 
1.70 -0.11 1.69 1.50-2.06 </p>

<p>Body mass index (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 28.3 -5.3 27.4 18.7-47.2 
Years since diagnosis 
23.0 -13.1 22.3 
2.4-50.6 
Total number of 
injections per day 
(n = 33 subjects) </p>

<p>4.6 -1.1 
4 
3-8 </p>

<p>HbA1c (%) 
7.8 -1.2 
7.8 
5.5-11.5 
Number of BG tests 
per day </p>

<p>7.4 -1.0 
7.7 
4.0-9.6 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) levels were measured at the start of 
the study. The number of tests per day was calculated from the test 
records on the FreeStyle Libre Reader. 
BG, blood glucose. </p>

<p> 
BAILEY ET AL. </p>

<p>FIG. 1. (Left panel) 
Consensus and (right panel) 
Clarke Error Grid Analysis comparing the FreeStyle Libre sensor readings with capillary blood glucose reference values </p>

<p>using the FreeStyle Precision meter built into the Reader. </p>



<p>is provided in Table 2. The variation in MARD against BG 
reference for different sensors is shown in Figure 2, with the 
linear mixed model estimating the between-subjects variance 
component to be 44% of the total variation. There was no 
significant difference between left and right arm insertion 
sites (11.2% and 11.4%; P = 0.5950). </p>

<p>The System's sensor results were highly correlated to 
capillary BG. Regression analysis produced a slope of 1.02, 
an intercept of -6.4 mg/dL, and a correlation coefficient of 
0.95 (range, 23-498 mg/dL). The coefficient of variation of 
sensitivity (as measured by slope) between sensors was 8.5%, 
8.6%, and 8.9% for each sensor lot. This variation was </p>

<p>Table 2. Difference Analysis Compared with Capillary and Venous Reference Under Various Conditions </p>

<p>Reference, glucose </p>

<p>Days 1-14 
Days 2-14 
Day 
(7 a.m.-</p>

<p>Night 
(11 p.m. </p>

<p>Without hypoglycemia/ 
rapid change </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>range, parameter 
All 
Home Clinic 
All 
Home Clinic 11 p.m.) -7 a.m.) 
All 
Clinic </p>

<p>Capillary, BG 
&lt; 100 mg/dL 
MAD (mg/dL) 11.3 
11.3 
11.8 
11.0 
11.0 
10.6 
11.5 
10.4 
10.3 
8.4 
n 
2,153 1,946 
207 
1,985 1,813 
172 
1,787 
366 
905 
97 
 ‡ 100 mg/dL 
MARD (%) 
10.7 
10.5 
11.8 
10.2 
10.2 
10.4 
10.8 
9.9 
10.2 
11.1 
n 
11,042 9,642 1,400 9,987 8,878 1,109 
9,717 
1,325 
9,341 
1,236 
All 
% 
11.4 
11.3 
12.1 
11.0 
11.0 
10.7 
11.5 
10.8 
10.4 
11.0 
n 
13,195 11,588 1,607 11,972 1,0691 1,281 
11,504 
1,691 
10,246 
1,333 
Venous, YSI 
&lt; 100 mg/dL 
MAD (mg/dL) 
-
-
13.4 
-
-
12.6 
-
-
-
10.2 
n 
-
-
1,475 
-
-
1,327 
-
-
-
620 
 ‡ 100 mg/dL 
MARD (%) 
-
-
11.4 
-
-
10.3 
-
-
-
10.9 
n 
-
-
10,697 
-
-
8,789 
-
-
-
9,722 
All 
% 
-
-
12.0 
-
-
11.0 
-
-
-
11.0 
n 
-
-
12,172 
-
-
10,116 
-
-
-
1,0342 </p>

<p>a Excluding rapidly changing/hypoglycemia (80 mg/dL) and impending hypoglycemia. 
BG, blood glucose; MAD, mean absolute difference, MARD, mean absolute relative difference. </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Histogram of the mean absolute relative difference (MARD) per sensor. </p>

<p>790 
BAILEY ET AL. </p>

<p>predominantly due to between-sensor variance, with the 
linear mixed model estimating the between-subjects variance 
component to be 37% of the total. There were no statistically 
significant differences in sensor sensitivity (i.e., slope) be-
tween insertion sites on either the right or left arm (P = 0.5542). 
Performance of the System was stable across the 14 days of 
wear after the first day. The percentage of readings within 
Consensus Error Grid Zone A (BG reference) on Days 2, 7, 
and 14 was 88.4%, 89.2%, and 85.2%, respectively (Fig. 3), 
and the MARD on the same days was 11.9%, 10.9%, and 
10.8%, respectively. 
The mean time to first glucose results was 1 h 1 min 
(n = 168), and 100% of sensors were able to provide inter-
stitial glucose results within 1 h 10 min after insertion. The 
mean lag time between the System sensor and YSI reference 
was 4.5 -4.8 min. 
Sensor accuracy was not affected by factors such as body 
mass index (BMI), age, type of diabetes, clinical site, insulin 
administration, or hemoglobin A1c, as the percentages of 
readings within Consensus Error Grid Zone A were similar 
(Fig. 4). 
At Days 1 and 15, study participants completed a ques-
tionnaire specific to this study and rated their experience with 
the System on a scale of 0 (strongly agree) to 4 (strongly 
disagree) for several subjective categories. On Day 1, the 
scorecard included seven statements about ease of use, pain 
compared with fingerstick, adequacy of packaging informa-
tion, and pain or bleeding when applying the sensor to either 
arm. On Day 15, the scorecard included nine statements 
about the sensor relative to comfort of wear, ease of wear, 
whether the sensor got in the way of daily activities, pain 
compared with fingerstick, easier than fingerstick, and ery-
thema or edema after removal of sensor from either arm. A 
score of 0, 1, or 2 was considered a favorable response. On 
Day 1, favorable ratings were reported by most respondents 
( ‡97.2%; n = 72) for seven of seven subjective statements. </p>

<p>Likewise, on Day 15 the majority of respondents ( ‡94.4%; 
n = 72) reported favorable ratings for nine of nine subjective 
statements. 
In total, 98.6% (142/144; both arms of 72 respondents) of 
responses were favorable ratings of £ 2 for the statement 
''The amount of pain I felt when applying the Sensor was 
acceptable.'' A favorable response of £ 2 was also reported 
by 99.3% (143/144) of responses for statement ''The amount 
of bleeding I experienced when applying the Sensor was 
acceptable.'' 
There were no unexpected adverse device effects re-
ported during the clinical study. One participant had a se-
rious adverse event (severe hypoglycemia prior to sensor 
insertion) not related to the study or device. Skin issues 
observed in 202 site exams of 72 study participants were as 
follows: moderate to severe itching 0.5% of the time, 
moderate erythema 4.0% of the time, and 98.6% of the in-
sertions had a pain rating of £ 2. Rate of mild incidences 
was &lt; 9% for any individual category of skin issues men-
tioned above, including edema, rash, induration, bruising, 
bleeding, and others. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study evaluated the performance and usability of the 
FreeStyle Libre system. Study results showed agreement 
between the System's sensor readings and capillary BG and 
venous reference. The capillary BG reference provided a 
wider distribution of glucose results and covered up to 14 
days of wear. Therefore, capillary BG was used as the pri-
mary comparator for the System's performance evaluation. 
Capillary BG reference provides more reference points and 
represents real-life accuracy during daily patient use. One 
strip lot was used as the capillary BG reference across all 
clinical sites and sensor lots so there were adequate data to 
determine variation between sensor lots and sites without 
confounding results with multiple strip lots. 
The System is unique among existing interstitial glucose 
monitoring technologies in that the wired enzyme factory-
only calibrated sensor has wear time of up to 14 days without 
additional calibration. This lack of reliance on an external BG 
monitor for calibration is a potential advantage as errors in 
BG meters could potentially lead to glucose monitoring 
system errors. Sensors requiring routine user calibration 
several times daily can be affected by glucose instability, 
such as observed postprandially. 
15 Sensor delays or lag be-
tween interstitial readings and venous or capillary readings 
have also been shown to vary among sensors, 
16 with newer-
generation sensors demonstrating less lag time. </p>

<p>15,17,18 </p>

<p>Differences among interstitial, 
14,19,20 capillary, and venous 
readings must also be considered when comparing accuracy 
outcomes. 
9,10,21-23 Sources contributing to differences be-
tween capillary BG versus venous YSI readings include the 
amount of blood used for testing, delays in analysis from 
the time of sampling, and differences in the composition of the 
blood samples. </p>

<p>9,10 </p>

<p>Collectively, these differences limit the direct comparison 
of accuracy outcomes among sensor technologies. Therefore, 
the present study was compared with reported outcomes with 
similar wired enzyme technology, factory-calibrated sensors, 
and those reporting accuracy outcomes using Consensus 
EGA. In a study of 55 subjects who wore a wired enzyme, </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Stability of accuracy across 14 days of Freestyle 
Libre sensor wear: Consensus Error Grid Zone A (green), 
Zone B (blue), and Zone C (red). N is the number of paired 
sensor and reference data points per day of wear for all 
sensors used in the study. </p>

<p>FACTORY-CALIBRATED FLASH GLUCOSE MONITORING </p>

<p>
factory-calibrated sensor for up to 14 days, results demon-
strated MARD of 12.2%, with 88.0% of sensor readings 
within Zone A of Consensus EGA and minimal change in 
sensor sensitivity over the 14-day wear time. 
24 Similarly, 
another study evaluating the feasibility of a factory-calibrated </p>

<p>sensor using wired enzyme technology for 5 days demon-
strated a MARD of 13.4%, and 83.5% of readings were within 
Zone A of Consensus EGA. 
25 Results from those published 
studies were consistent with the outcomes in the present study. 
Accuracy of the System was similar across 14 days of sensor </p>

<p>FIG. 4. Accuracy of the FreeStyle 
Libre sensor as a function of various 
factors or patient characteristics: (A) 
diabetes type, (B) sex, (C) insertion site, 
(D) insulin administration (Insulin Ad) 
(continuous subcutaneous insulin infu-
sion [CSII] or multiple daily insulin in-
jections [MDI]), (E) body mass index 
(BMI), (F) hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c), 
(G) age, and (H) rate of change. 
Consensus Error Grid zones were Zone 
A (green), Zone B (blue), and Zone 
C (red). </p>

<p>792 
BAILEY ET AL. </p>

<p>wear with the exception of the first day of wear, which had the 
lowest accuracy (Consensus EGA showed 72.0% in Zone A 
for Day 1 compared with 88.4% in Zone A for Day 2). This 
may be due in part to the body's natural inflammatory re-
sponse to sensor insertion, which has been shown to affect 
glucose concentration in interstitial fluid. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>In the present study, the System's sensor did not show any 
marked differences in accuracy outcomes relative to BMI, 
age, type of diabetes, clinical site, insulin administration, or 
hemoglobin A1c. In comparison, the accuracy (Clarke EGA) 
of the FreeStyle Navigator 
Ò sensor (Abbott Diabetes Care), 
which used a sensor with the same wired enzyme technology, 
as reported by Weinstein et al., 
27 did not differ as a function 
of age, sex, ethnicity, years since diagnosis of diabetes, 
or sensors worn on either the arm or abdomen but differed 
depending on the subject's BMI. The percentage of readings 
in Zone A (Clarke EGA) for participants who had a BMI of 
&lt;25 kg/m 
2 was 78.8% compared with 84.4% for participants 
with a BMI of &gt;30 kg/m 
2 , which the authors suggested could 
have been attributed to differences in blood flow relative to 
subcutaneous adipose tissue thickness. The present study 
with the System included a broad range of BMI (18.7-
47.2 kg/m 
2 ), which did not affect the sensor accuracy. Place-
ment of the System's sensor was on both arms for each 
subject, and future studies could evaluate the effects of sensor 
accuracy in different locations on the body. 
These results have clinical implications for individuals 
with diabetes and for the clinicians who treat them. Several 
randomized controlled studies have revealed better hemo-
globin A1c outcomes associated with the frequency of sensor 
wear. 
28-32 Thus, a sensor with a longer wear period that does 
not require fingerstick calibration with its associated burden 
and pain may support more frequent sensor use with im-
proved glycemic outcomes. This system with no additional 
fingerstick may also benefit groups that have demonstrated 
poor adoption of persistent sensor use. 
The System's sensor provides a broader interval and volume 
of measurements, including day and night readings, which can 
be used to evaluate glucose patterns and trends. In comparison, 
capillary BG readings provide single, intermittent measure-
ments, which may not capture intervals of extreme variability 
or nocturnal events. In a recent study, it was demonstrated that 
the use of continuous glucose monitoring with or without 
alarms reduces time spent outside glucose targets compared 
with self-monitoring of BG. 
13 The System provides the user 
with the current glucose result, glucose pattern, and trend in-
formation on the display of the hand-held reader when the 
sensor is scanned. This type of monitoring system may benefit 
individuals who have ceased sensor use due to alarm fatigue, 
becoming overwhelmed by alarms. 
11 Limitations of the cur-
rent study are single body site used for data collection, limited 
venous reference data over the 14-day wear due to practical 
limitation of obtaining blood, and a limited number of sensor 
lots used in the study. Further research is needed to evaluate 
whether the System could provide additional benefits such as 
improvement in glycemic outcomes with continued use over 
time, as well as improved compliance with sensor wear. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>In this prospective study, the performance of the factor-
only calibrated FreeStyle Libre Flash glucose monitoring </p>

<p>system was demonstrated by the accuracy of sensor readings 
and the stability of accurate readings over 14 days of use. The 
accuracy of the System was unaffected by subject charac-
teristics, making it suitable for a broad range of individuals. 
Under normal conditions, the System provides an easy to use 
and comfortable sensor wear experience for up to 14 days 
without the need for fingerstick measurements. It is antici-
pated that the provision of comprehensive glucose data for up 
to 14 days with reduced pain and burden for the end user will 
support enhanced diabetes management. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank Joe Bugler for his critical review of the 
manuscript and Zoe K. Welsh for graphical and statistical 
support. Suzie Webster (ConsignMed, Inc.) provided medical 
writing and editorial assistance. Funding for this study was 
provided by Abbott Diabetes Care. </p>

<p>Author Disclosure Statement </p>

<p>S.A. is an employee of Abbott Diabetes Care. M.P.C., 
L.J.K., T.B., and B.W.B. were the study investigators and 
declare that no competing financial interests exist. </p>



<p>FACTORY-CALIBRATED FLASH GLUCOSE MONITORING 
793 </p>



<p>Address correspondence to: 
Shridhara Alva, PhD 
Clinical Affairs 
Abbott Diabetes Care 
1360 South Loop Road 
Alameda, CA 94502 </p>

<p>E-mail: Shridhara.alva@abbott.com </p>

<p>794 
BAILEY ET AL. </p>

</text></tei>