<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4963544" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Rice is the staple food for most of the people in India. 
It is the largest consumed calorie source among the food 
grains. Rice production in India crossed the mark of 100 
million Metric tons in 2011 -12 accounting for 22.81% of 
global production in that year 
1) . The post-harvest process-</p>

<p>ing of paddy (de-husking) is the oldest and the largest agro 
processing industry of the country. It is a basic process that 
can be found in local towns and villages across the coun-
try. Assam has been ranked 1 
st in rice production (51 lakh </p>

<p>metric ton) with productivity of 1,969 kg per hectare 
2) . </p>

<p>Approximately, Assam consists of 5,560 rice mills which 
include 1,363 modern and remaining traditional mills 
3) . In </p>

<p>traditional rice mill, at a time minimum 4 -5 workers are 
required to monitor and control all the operations. There-
fore, a large number of workers are employed in the rice 
milling industry in Assam, India. 
It has been reported 
4, 5) that dust is a major problem </p>

<p>Mechanical intervention for reducing dust 
concentration in traditional rice mills </p>

<p>Prabhanjan K. PRANAV 
1 * and Mrinmoy BISWAS </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 Department of Agricultural Engineering, NERIST, India </p>

<p>Received September 19, 2015 and accepted January 18, 2016 
Published online in J-STAGE January 30, 2016 </p>

<p>Abstract: A huge number of workers are employed in traditional rice mills where they are poten-
tially exposed to dust. In this study a dust collection system was developed to capture the airborne 
dust in the rice mill. The feeding and sieving section of the mill was identified as major dust creating 
zone. The dust was captured by creating suitable air stream at feeding and sieving sections of the 
mill and collected in cyclone dust collector. The air stream was created by blower which was selected 
on the basis to get minimum air speed of 0.5 m/s in the working zones of workers. It was observed 
that the developed system is successfully collects the significant amount of dust and able to reduce 
the dust concentration up to 58%. Further, the respirable dust concentration reduced to below 5 
mg/m 
3 throughout the mill which is within the recommended limit of dust exposure. </p>

<p>Key words: Dust concentration, Respirable dust, Rice mill, Air borne dust, Air stream </p>

<p>in traditional rice mills of Assam. Dust is scientifically 
defined as "Small, dry, solid particles projected into the 
air by natural forces, such as wind, volcanic eruption, and 
by mechanical or man-made processes such as crushing, 
grinding, milling, drilling, demolition, shovelling, convey-
ing, screening, bagging, and sweeping" 
6) . Dust particles </p>

<p>are usually in the size range from about 1 to 100 μm in 
diameter, divided into three types 
7) (i) respirable fraction </p>

<p>(D 50 = 4 μm size) (ii) thoracic fraction (D 50 = 10 μm size) 
and (iii) inhalable fraction (D 50 = 100 μm size). As per 
report 
4) , total dust concentration is 80, 59 and 49 mg/m 
3 , at </p>

<p>feeding-cum-sieving, polishing and packaging sections of 
the rice mill, respectively. The respirable dust concentra-
tion at feeding-cum sieving section is 9 -11 mg/m 
3 which </p>

<p>are much higher than the recommended value (5 mg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) 
8) . </p>

<p>Dust as health issue for workers 
It is proven fact that exposure to organic dust have high 
prevalence of respiratory diseases, such as asthma, chronic 
bronchitis, extrinsic allergic alveoli ties, toxic syndrome, 
and interstitial lung. These occupational diseases depend 
up on the dust concentration and duration of exposure 
apart from variation in personal immunity. The Swedish </p>

<p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. </p>

<p>P PRANAV et al. </p>



<p>Industrial Health 2016, 54, 315-323 </p>

<p>National Board of Occupational Safety and Health has 
prescribed the dust exposure limit of 10 mg/m 
3 and 5 mg/ </p>

<p>m 
3 for normal and organic dust, respectively. Many stud-</p>

<p>ies have demonstrated and concluded that occupational 
diseases constitute serious health and economic problems 
to the nations. Occupational hygienists must look at the 
working environment. Several reports 
9 -11) have suggested </p>

<p>that unprotected dust exposures in agricultural work sta-
tions may lead to pulmonary fibrosis. 
Grain dust has also long history diseases and its adverse 
effects on various organs such as eyes, nose, skin, lung and 
the airways 
12) . Asthma has been well documented as being </p>

<p>a result of dust exposure. However, few studies have been 
reported on the effect of dust exposure in rice mill. The 
major dust hazards for workers in rice mills are the dust 
emissions from different sections i.e. dumping of rice at 
a place for subsequent collection in gunny bags, feed of 
paddy from gunny bags to the dumping pit, cleaning of 
paddy grains, removal of husk from the paddy and polish-
ing of rice. In addition, a dusty mill increases the risk of 
workers' injury and fire hazard, which results in less pro-
duction, higher insurance rates, and lawsuits. The increas-
ing global attention on control of air pollution has made 
the containment of nuisance dust from rice milling opera-
tions within enclosures more imperative. 
From these point of view, it is resolved that huge man 
power are employed in traditional rice mills of Assam </p>

<p>and they are potentially exposed to dust which might lead 
to adverse effect on their health. Therefore, a study was 
planned to develop a dust collection system to capture the 
airborne dust by creating air stream at feeding and sieving 
sections of the rice mill. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Measurement of dust 
Dust exposure to rice mill workers was measured with 
the help of Respicon Particle Sampler {Model: 8522, TSI, 
USA; Instrument type-two stage, virtual impactor, with 
three stage gravimetric filter sampler; 50% cut aerody-
namic dia.-Inlet: 100 micron, Stage 1: 4 micron, Stage 2: 
10 micron, Stage 3: all remaining particles; Filter type-37 
mm diameter fiberglass without organic binders or PVC 
filters with 5.0 micrometer pore size; Sample flow rate-3.11 
liters per minute} before and after mechanical interven-
tion. The Respicon Particle Sampler (RPS) has three filters 
where different sizes of dust are being collected. The dust 
was measured by two methods: 
(i) Sampler was mounted in the breathing zone of worker 
(Fig. 1a) and allowed him to perform his work from 
4 to 7 hours. The data collected through this method 
is presents as dust at feeding-cum-sieving section 
because the same person was moving from feeding to 
sieving during work. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. View of mounted RPS on worker and fixed in a section. </p>

<p>300 mm Hemisphere 
around nose and mouth </p>

<p>Particle sampler </p>

<p>Belt </p>

<p>(a) Mounted on worker 
(b) Fixed mounting on feeding 
section </p>

<p>TO DEVELOP DUST COLLECTION SYSTEM IN RICE MILL </p>



<p>(ii) Sampler was fixed at one place (Fig. 1b) and started 
collecting dust for 4 to 7 hours during the mill opera-
tion. The dust concentration was collected at various 
zones viz feeding, sieving, polishing and packaging 
via this method. 
To determine the mass concentration of each of the 
size fractions, the three Respicon Particle Sampler filters 
were post-weighed on the same digital micro-balance as 
was used to pre-weigh the filters. The calculation of dust 
concentration of each size fraction namely respirable, tho-
racic, inhalable and total dust was carried out through <rs id="software-0" type="software">Data Spread</rs> sheet (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">TSI</rs>, USA) using Eqs. 1 to 4. </p>

<p>Respirable Fraction mg/m³ </p>

<p>( 
)= </p>

<p>× 
× </p>

<p>m 
Q ts </p>

<p>1 1000 
1 
…(1) </p>

<p>Thoracic Fraction mg/m³ 
( 
) 
( 
) </p>

<p>( 
)= </p>

<p>+ 
× 
+ 
× </p>

<p>m m 
Q Q 
ts </p>

<p>1 
2 1000 
1 
2 
…(2) </p>

<p>Inhalable Fraction mg/m³ 
( 
) 
( 
) </p>

<p>( 
)= </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
× 
+ 
+ 
× </p>

<p>m m m 
Q Q Q 
ts </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 1000 
1 
2 
3 
…(3) </p>

<p>Total dust concentration = respirable + thoracic + 
inhalable fraction …(4) </p>

<p>where, m1 = Mass deposited on filter #1; mg 
m2 = Mass deposited on filter #2; mg 
m3 = Mass deposited on filter #3; mg 
Q1 = Flow rate through filter #1; l/min 
Q2 = Flow rate through filter #2; l/min 
Q3 = Flow rate through filter #3; l/min 
ts = Sample duration; minutes </p>

<p>Selection of site 
The mechanical intervention was carried out in an exist-
ing traditional rice mill at Narayanpur, North Lakhimpur 
districts of Assam. This mill is located about 45 km away 
from NERIST. The mill was established in the year of 
1988. The milling capacity of the mill is approximately 
35 -40 quintal per day. Approximately, 10 persons work in 
this mill per day in different shifts. This mill was selected 
on the basis of some mutual agreements between mill 
owner and authors. </p>

<p>Modification at feeding section 
Modification at feeding section is very important as dust 
start propagating from feeding section as soon as paddy 
bags open. To capture the upward propagating dust before </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Venturi shaped cylinder and its incorporation at feeding section of rice mill. </p>

<p>a. Front view of venturi shaped opening cylinder </p>

<p>b. Incorporation of cylinder at feeding section </p>

<p>P PRANAV et al. </p>



<p>Industrial Health 2016, 54, 315-323 </p>

<p>it reaches to the nose level of workers, a horizontal air suc-
tion is provided at a height of 1.0 m from the ground. The 
horizontal length of suction zone is kept 1.0 m as per the 
working zone of workers at feeding section. Venturi shaped 
cylinder having minimum opening of 5 cm at the middle 
and maximum of 10 cm at the end of cylinder is used to 
make uniform suction through out the working zone. The 
suction line is connected to a high capacity blower. The 
venturi shaped cylinder with suction line and it incorpora-
tion at feeding section is shown in Fig. 2. </p>

<p>Modification at sieving section 
A rectangular shaped hood of size 100 × 100 × 80 cm 
(length × width × slant height) was fabricated according to 
the existing sieve size of 180 × 100 cm (length × width). 
The fabricated hood on the sieve with dimensions is shown 
in Fig. 3. The basic purpose of the hood is to collect and 
capture the airborne dust which was created over the sieve 
due to sieving action. An air suction pipe is provided at 
0.25 m above the bottom portion of hood as per the suit-
ability of fitting and other existing arrangements. From top </p>

<p>of the hood paddy falls on the sieve through elevator at 
constant rate. A necessary partition is provided between 
air suction and paddy falling point to avoid paddy flow in 
air suction line. A gap of 0.13 m is provided between top 
of the sieve and bottom of the hood because of frequent 
cleaning of sieve is required by hand. Further, the gap is 
also useful to make the air flow. </p>

<p>Selection of blower 
A dust capturing system was designed to collect the air 
borne dust from sieving and feeding section of a rice mill. 
The overall dust collecting system is shown in Fig. 4. The 
blower capacity was calculated on the basis of required air 
velocity at feeding plus sieving section. As per literature 
13) , </p>

<p>the minimum required velocity to capture air borne dust is 
0.5 m/s. </p>

<p>Calculation for feeding section 
From trial and error method in a laboratory experiment 
it was observed that air velocity of 6.5 m/s at suction inlet 
creates minimum air velocity of 0.5 m/s throughout the </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Fabrication of hood over sieve to capture air borne dust due to sieving. </p>

<p>TO DEVELOP DUST COLLECTION SYSTEM IN RICE MILL </p>



<p>feeding zone. To get the better air flow uniformity, the suc-
tion inlet cut in venture shaped as shown in Fig. 2a. Fur-
ther, the calculated area of opening of venture shaped cyl-
inder is 0.075 m 
2 . </p>

<p>Therefore, air suction rate at feeding section = 0.075 
m 
2 × 6.5 m/s = 0.488 m 
3 /s = 29.25 m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>/min. </p>

<p>Calculation for sieving section 
The opening face of designed hood is 1 m 
2 against the </p>

<p>sieve size of 1.8 m 
2 . By trial and error method, it was cal-</p>

<p>culated that the required average air velocity at opening 
face of hood should be 1.2 m/s to create the minimum 0.5 
m/s speed at remotest corner of the sieve. 
Therefore, air suction rate at sieving section = 1 m 
2 × 1.2 </p>

<p>m/s = 1.2 m 
3 /s = 72 m 
3 /min. </p>

<p>Total required capacity of blower = 29.25 + 72 = 101.25 
m 
3 /min = 3,576 CFM≈3,600 CFM </p>

<p>Hence, a blower operated by 3-pashe electric motor with 
specification of 3,600 CFM flow rate, 2,800 rpm speed, 
152 mm of water column static pressure, and 5 hp rated 
power was selected to get the desired air suction at sieving 
as well feeding section. </p>

<p>Measurement of air velocity 
After installing a designed blower, the air velocity cre-</p>

<p>Fig. 4. Overall view of dust collection system. </p>

<p>Feeding 
section </p>

<p>Sieving 
section </p>

<p>Blower </p>

<p>Main carrying pipe </p>

<p>To cyclone dust collector </p>

<p>ated by the blower at feeding and sieving section was 
measured to identify the zone creating air velocity more 
than 0.5 m/s. The velocity of air was measured by Portable 
Thermal Environment and Heat Stress Monitor (Make: 
Quest Technologies). The velocity was measured in the 
grid developed at 10 cm × 10 cm at feeding and sieving 
section. The developed grid at feeding and sieving section 
is shown in Figs. 5 and 6, respectively. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Grid points of air velocity measurement at feeding section. </p>

<p>P PRANAV et al. </p>



<p>Industrial Health 2016, 54, 315-323 </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Grid points of air velocity measurement at sieving section. </p>

<p>Results and Discussion </p>

<p>Velocity profile at feeding section 
The measured velocity at feeding section as per the grid 
was used to develop contour plot as shown in Fig. 7. It is 
revealed that air velocity more than 0.5 m/s was observed 
at about 0.7 m distance from the middle of opening cylin-
der. The contour of 0.5 m/s speed is indicated by bold line 
in Fig. 7 which is fully dust free zone. Further, at 0.3 m 
above and below the line of opening, 0.5 m/s air speed was 
observed up to 0.4 m only (Fig. 8). The air speed of 0.5 m/s 
is referred to discuss because this is the minimum required 
velocity to blow the airborne dust of less than 10 µm as per 
the WHO </p>

<p>13)   . The working area of worker in feeding zone 
was witnessed 1 m × 1 m but it was observed that most of 
the time, workers work within 0.7 m × 0.7 m area where 
measured air speed was more than 0.5 m/s. </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Velocity profile at feeding section in the line of air opening of cylinder. </p>

<p>Lateral distance of feeding zone, cm </p>

<p>Longitudinal distance of feeding zone, </p>

<p>Origin </p>

<p>Velocity, m/s </p>

<p>TO DEVELOP DUST COLLECTION SYSTEM IN RICE MILL </p>



<p>Fig. 8. Velocity profile at 0.3 m up and down from the central line of opening. </p>

<p>Velocity, m/s </p>

<p>Lateral distance of feeding zone, cm </p>

<p>Longitudinal distance of feeding zone, </p>

<p>Origin </p>

<p>Fig. 9. Velocity profile at sieving section on the sieve. </p>

<p>Length of sieve, cm </p>

<p>Width of sieve, cm </p>

<p>Velocity, m/s </p>

<p>Boundary of sieve </p>

<p>P PRANAV et al. </p>



<p>Industrial Health 2016, 54, 315-323 </p>

<p>Fig. 10. Comparison of various dust concentration before and after modification. </p>

<p>(a) Feeding-cum-sieving section </p>

<p>(b) 
) 
c 
( 
n 
o 
i 
t 
c 
e 
s 
g 
n 
i 
d 
e 
e 
F 
Sieving section </p>

<p>(52.3) </p>

<p>(59.6) </p>

<p>(60.4) </p>

<p>(59.2) </p>

<p>(49.9) </p>

<p>(55.7) </p>

<p>(56.0) </p>

<p>(55.2) </p>

<p>(45.3) </p>

<p>(57.0) </p>

<p>(59.1) </p>

<p>(56.8) </p>

<p>Velocity profile at sieving section 
The air velocity created by blower above the sieve was 
also measured at sieving section. The contour of air veloc-
ity is shown in Fig. 9. The straight continuous lines indi-
cate the boundary of the sieve. From the figure, it is clear 
that air velocity is more than 0.65 m/s above the sieve. 
Further, the air velocity was more than 0.5 m/s outside the 
sieve up to 20 cm in three sides which is working zone of 
the workers. </p>

<p>Dust concentration 
The dust concentrations at feeding, sieving, policing and 
packaging were measured before and after modification at 
feeding and sieving section by fixing particle dust sampler 
at one place. However, dust was also measured by mount-
ing the sampler in the breathing zone of worker who was 
working at feeding as well as sieving section which is pre-
sented as dust at feeding-cum-sieving section. 
A comparison of dust concentration (respirable, thoracic 
and inhalable and total dust) before and after modification 
at feeding, sieving and feeding-cum-sieving is represented 
in Fig. 10. The figure in parenthesis above the bar graph </p>

<p>indicates the percentage reduction in dust concentration 
due to modification. It is revealed that there is significant 
reduction in total dust concentration 55 to 59 percent. The 
total dust concentration after modification at feeding-cum-
sieving section varied from 31 -34 mg/m 
3 compared to </p>

<p>that of 73 -80 mg/m 
3 before modification. The respirable </p>

<p>dust is reduced to the lower than recommended limit of 5 
mg/m 
3 at all the sections. The developed system is very </p>

<p>much feasible and cost effective for traditional rice mills of 
Assam. From the subjective analysis it was also observed 
that workers' working hour enhanced by 18 -20% with the 
adaptation of dust reduction system which interns as finan-
cial benefits. All the previous trial for dust separation was 
to enhance the quality of final rice product not to reduce 
the air borne dust. This system is typically for reducing the 
air borne dust which was affecting the worker health. This 
technology can also be used in other similar industry. 
Further, the effect of modification at sieving and feed-
ing section was also observed at polishing and packaging 
because dust was propagating to these sections mainly 
from feeding and sieving section only. It was observed that 
respirable dust reduced up to 52 per cent at polishing and </p>

<p>TO DEVELOP DUST COLLECTION SYSTEM IN RICE MILL </p>



<p>Fig. 11. Effect of modification on polishing and packaging section. </p>

<p>packaging sections. The effect of modification at polishing 
and packaging is presented graphically in Fig. 11. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>A dust collection system was incorporated in feeding 
and sieving section of rice mill by creating an air stream 
to capture the air borne dust. This modification reduced the 
total dust concentration in the range of 56 to 58% at feed-
ing-cum-sieving section. The respirable dust concentration 
reduced to 4.24 from 8.89 mg/m 
3 after modification which </p>

<p>comes under the recommended limit of 5 mg/m 
3 . Further, </p>

<p>significant effect of modification was also observed at the 
polishing and packaging section. The same technology 
may be used in others similar industry for the betterment of 
workers for their health and efficiency. </p>

<p>Acknowledgement </p>

<p>Authors hearty thank to Dr. L. P. Gite, Project coordina-
tor, All India Coordinated Research Project on Ergonomics 
and Safety in Agriculture, ICAR, New Delhi for full finan-
cial support and valuable guidance. </p>



</text></tei>