<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4513216" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Introduction and Aim Data from prescription databases 
are increasingly being used to study associations between 
maternal medications used in pregnancy and congenital 
anomalies. We therefore investigated the extent to which 
prescriptions reflect the actual use of medication during 
pregnancy, and whether medicines used during pregnancy 
are taken according to the prescribed dosage and duration. 
Methods We performed a cross-sectional study in a pop-
ulation-based congenital anomaly register (EUROCAT 
Northern Netherlands). We included 202 women who had at 
least one prescription during their pregnancy and who gave 
birth between 2009 and 2011. Compliance with the pre-
scribed medication was verified by telephone interview. We 
calculated the compliance rates for several medication </p>

<p>groups by dividing the number of mothers who confirmed 
they had taken the medication by the total number to whom it 
had been prescribed. Compliance was positive if the mother 
confirmed she took the medication, even if she only took one 
of several prescriptions from the same medication group. For 
each prescription taken, we also determined whether her use 
conformed to the prescribed dosage and duration. 
Results During the first trimester, the compliance rates 
ranged from 0.84 (for chronic diseases) to 0.92 (for preg-
nancy-related symptoms). Most of the medications actually 
taken were used at the prescribed dosage or lower. More 
than half of the medications actually taken were used for 
the duration prescribed or shorter. 
Conclusion Prescription records are generally a relatively 
reliable source of data for research into associations 
between medication use in pregnancy and congenital 
anomalies compared with other data sources. Pharmacy 
records of medication use in pregnancy might represent an </p>

<p>Key Points </p>

<p>Healthcare databases are increasingly being used to 
study associations between maternal medications 
used in pregnancy and congenital anomalies. </p>

<p>A disadvantage of using healthcare databases is a 
lack of clarity around whether prescribed/dispensed 
medication is actually taken. </p>

<p>For most medication groups, prescription records are 
a relatively reliable source of data for research into 
associations between medication use in pregnancy 
and congenital anomalies compared with other data 
sources. </p>

<p>The abstract has been submitted to be presented in poster form at the 
Approximately 80 % of all women use one or more med-
ications during pregnancy [1]. However, whether new 
medicines have any teratogenic effects is largely unknown, 
since data obtained from animal studies cannot always be 
translated to humans, and pregnant women are excluded 
from clinical trials for ethical reasons [2]. For chronic ill-
nesses, the use of medication during pregnancy is often 
unavoidable. The use of some specific medications might 
result in a higher risk of specific congenital anomalies, 
such as the anti-epileptic medication valproic acid, which 
results in an increased risk of spina bifida if used in the first 
trimester of pregnancy [3]. Given that certain medications 
are unavoidable during pregnancy and the severity of some 
congenital anomalies, research into associations between 
them is highly relevant. 
Two types of information are frequently used in studies 
on medication use in pregnancy: self-reports (interviews 
and questionnaires) and 'medical' records (information 
extracted from medical files, or pharmacy or health insur-
ance records). The use of pharmacy databases, which hold 
data on prescriptions to individuals, is relatively easy. 
Furthermore, the data are registered prospectively. How-
ever, one cannot assume the patient actually takes the 
medication prescribed [4]. Non-compliance can result in 
misclassification of exposure and lead to bias in study 
outcomes [5, 6]. Since data from pharmacy databases are 
increasingly being used for research into associations 
between medication use in pregnancy and congenital 
anomalies [7, 8], it is important to verify patients' com-
pliance with the prescribed medication. 
The aim of this study is to investigate the extent to 
which prescriptions reflect the actual use of medication 
during pregnancy, and whether medicines used during 
pregnancy are taken according to the prescribed dosage and 
duration. </p>

<p>2 Methods </p>

<p>2.1 Setting </p>

<p>We conducted a cross-sectional study in which we inves-
tigated how accurately prescriptions reflect the actual use </p>

<p>of medications during pregnancy by verifying their use and 
dosage and the duration for which they were taken. We 
used data from women who had had a child with a con-
genital anomaly in 2009-2011 and who participated in a 
population-based congenital anomaly register in the 
northern Netherlands (EUROCAT NNL). This region has 
approximately 17,000 births per year [9], which is 
approximately 10 % of all births in the Netherlands [10]. 
All pregnancy outcomes involving a congenital anomaly 
are registered, including live births, stillbirths (a fetus of 
C24 weeks' gestation that died in the uterus or during birth 
[11]), spontaneous abortions (a fetus of \24 weeks' ges-
tation that died naturally), and terminations of pregnancy 
for a fetal anomaly (TOPFA) [11]. For the live births, the 
age limit for inclusion in the registry is 10 years. 
Parental informed consent was required for registration, 
and the parents were sent a questionnaire enquiring about 
their socio-demographic characteristics and potential risk 
factors, including use of medicines. The questionnaire also 
asked for permission for the mother's pharmacy records for 
the period from 3 months before conception up to delivery 
to be requested. After the completed questionnaire and 
pharmacy information was received, one of our research 
assistants interviewed the mother by telephone. The 
research assistant asked about each prescription and 
checked whether the mother actually took it and whether 
she followed the prescribed dose and duration [12]. 
For this study, we included data from mothers who gave 
birth or had a termination of pregnancy between 2009 and 
2011, who received at least one prescription medication 
during their pregnancy, and who were interviewed between 
1 January 2011 and 1 February 2012. </p>

<p>2.2 Medication </p>

<p>In our analyses, we only included prescribed medication 
dispensed by community pharmacies. We had no infor-
mation on medication dispensed during hospitalization or 
medication that was bought over the counter (OTC). 
In vitro fertilization (IVF) medication and contraceptives 
were excluded since the intake of these medicines is cycle-
dependent, which makes the exact use difficult to deter-
mine. Homeopathic medicines, herbals, allergens, antipar-
asitic products, insecticides, and repellents were also 
excluded, because they are available OTC and are rarely 
prescribed. 
For each medication, we extracted the following infor-
mation: brand or generic name, Anatomical Therapeutic 
Chemical (ATC) code [13], formulation (oral, inhalation, 
dermal), date of prescription, total amount prescribed, and 
daily dosage. 
Medicines were categorized into three main groups 
(medication for chronic conditions, medication for </p>

<p> 
L. de Jonge et al. </p>

<p>occasional and short-term use, and medication for preg-
nancy-related problems) and several subgroups among 
these main groups adapted from the scheme used by 
Bakker et al. [1] and shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>2.3 Compliance </p>

<p>The women were sent a list of their prescribed medication 
before the telephone interview. In the telephone interview, 
compliance with each prescription was verified on the basis 
of standard questions (see the electronic supplementary 
material [ESM] 1). Within the interview, it was empha-
sized that the questions on medication use were asked in 
order to collect data to perform research on congenital 
anomalies and not to suggest a possible association with 
the condition of the child. </p>

<p>If a mother confirmed that she had taken her prescribed 
medication, we defined her as a compliant user for that 
medication, irrespective of whether she had used the 
medication exactly as prescribed (correct dosage and cor-
rect duration). If a medication was prescribed more than 
once and the mother had taken just one prescription, she 
was still counted as a compliant user for that medication. 
As this broad definition of compliance might overesti-
mate actual compliance, we also applied a stricter defini-
tion of compliance to investigate the effect of any 
overestimation. In the strict definition, a mother was 
counted as a 'compliant user' only if all of the prescriptions 
of a specific medication were actually taken. If a medica-
tion was prescribed more than once but not all the pre-
scriptions had been taken, she was not counted as a 
'compliant user'. 
We also focused on compliance by grouping the pre-
scriptions according to the different modes of application: 
oral, dermatological, inhalation, vaginal, rectal, ear, eye, 
and nasal preparations, and injections. Compliance for each 
of these groups was calculated according to the broad 
definition. 
The compliance rate for a medication or medication 
subgroup was calculated by dividing the number of com-
pliant users by the total number of mothers who had been 
prescribed that medication according to their pharmacy 
records: </p>

<p>number of compliant users 
total number of mothers given a prescription </p>

<p>For the compliance rate, the 95 % confidence intervals 
(CIs) were calculated using the Wald formula [14]: </p>

<p>Compliance AE 1:96 Â </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi 
p Á ð1 À pÞ 
n </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>The Wald-formula can be applied when n 9 p [ 5 and 
n 9 (1 -p) [ 5. If this condition was not met, we applied 
the Wilson formula to calculate the 95 % CI: </p>

<p>K ¼ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 z </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>n ¼ z 2 AE </p>

<p>z Á 
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi </p>

<p>KÁðn À KÞ 
n </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>z 2 
4 </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>n þ z 2 </p>

<p>in case of a 95 % CI, z = 1.96 [14]. 
The compliance rate was calculated for the first trime-
ster and for the entire pregnancy. The first day of the last 
menstruation was defined as 'day 0'. The first trimester was 
defined as the period between day 0 and day 98, whereas 
the entire pregnancy was defined as the period between day 
0 and date of birth. The date of prescription determined 
whether the medication was counted as 'first trimester' or 
'entire pregnancy', even if the medication was prescribed 
in the first trimester but also used in the second or third 
trimester. </p>

<p>Table 1 Classification of the main groups and subgroups of medi-
cations prescribed during pregnancy </p>

<p>Medication 
(Part of) ATC code </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Medicines for chronic diseases </p>

<p>Antihypertensives, vasoprotectives, 
beta-blocking agents, calcium 
channel blockers </p>

<p>C02, C05, C07, C08 </p>

<p>Corticosteroids, dermatological 
preparations </p>

<p>D07 </p>

<p>Medicines for obstructive airway 
diseases </p>

<p>R03 </p>

<p>Medicines for short-term or occasional use </p>

<p>Medicines for functional 
gastrointestinal disorders, for 
peptic ulcers and gastro-
esophageal reflux disease </p>

<p>A02B, A03, excl A03FA01 </p>

<p>Dermatologicals, excluding anti-
psoriatics and corticosteroids, 
dermatological preparations </p>

<p>D excl D05 and D07 (D01, 
D02, D06, D08, D10, D11) </p>

<p>Antifungals for dermatological use D01 
Emollients and protectives 
D02 </p>

<p>Antibacterials for systemic use 
J01 </p>

<p>Anxiolytics, hypnotics, and 
sedatives </p>

<p>N05B, N05C </p>

<p>Ear, eye, nose, and throat 
preparations </p>

<p>R01, R02A, R05, S01, S02, 
S03 </p>

<p>Medicines for pregnancy-related symptoms </p>

<p>Antacids 
A02A </p>

<p>Anti-emetics 
A03FA01, A04A, N05AB04, 
R06AD, R06AE </p>

<p>Laxatives 
A06 </p>

<p>Multivitamins containing folic acid 
or folic acid and its derivatives </p>

<p>A11BA, B03B </p>

<p>Iron preparations 
B03A </p>

<p>Gynecological anti-infectives and 
antiseptics </p>

<p>G01 </p>

<p>a Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) code [13] </p>

<p>Actual Use of Medications Prescribed During Pregnancy </p>

<p>
To minimize the influence of coincidental findings, the 
compliance rate was only calculated if at least ten mothers 
had been prescribed a specific medication subgroup. This 
means that the total number of prescriptions and mothers in 
the three main groups is not necessarily the sum of the 
subgroups. </p>

<p>2.4 Prescriptions per Mother, and Prescribed 
Dosage and Duration </p>

<p>In addition to the compliance, for each medication we 
calculated the proportion that was actually taken according 
to the dosage and duration prescribed. We also counted the 
number of mothers who had one or more prescriptions for 
each medication group and subgroup. We used <rs id="software-0" type="software">PASW 
Statistics</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">22</rs> and <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> 
Ò <rs id="software-1" type="software">Excel</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2007</rs> for the 
calculations. </p>

<p>3 Results </p>

<p>During the data collection period from 1 January 2011 to 1 
February 2012, a total of 735 congenital anomaly cases 
were fully registered, and we received pharmacy records 
for 420 of the pregnancies. After selecting for pharmacy 
records that covered the period of 3 months before con-
ception up to delivery, covering mothers who gave birth 
between 2009 and 2011, and that contained complete 
information on medications prescribed, date of prescrip-
tion, and amount and dose prescribed, we had 202 preg-
nancies to study (Fig. 1). The time period between date of 
telephone interview and date of birth ranged from 2 to 
35 months with a median of 13 months (interquartile range 
[IQR] 7.75-18). </p>

<p>3.1 Characteristics of the Cases </p>

<p>A total of 29 % (59/202) cases were born in 2009; 50 % 
(101/202) in 2010; and 21 % (42/202) in 2011. Most 
(80 %, 162/202) were live births; 6 % (12/202) were 
stillbirths or spontaneous abortions, and 12 % (24/202) 
were TOPFAs. Nine pregnancies ended before the end of 
the first trimester (before day 98): eight of these were 
TOPFAs and one was a spontaneous abortion. </p>

<p>3.2 Prescriptions </p>

<p>During pregnancy, 38 % (77/202) of the mothers were 
prescribed at least one medication for a chronic disease, 
and 64 % (49/77) of these had more than one prescription 
for a medication in that specific group. A total of 63 % 
(128/202) of the mothers were prescribed at least one 
medication for short-term or occasional use, and 58 % (74/ </p>

<p>128) of these had more than one prescription for medicines 
in that specific group. A total of 55 % (112/202) of the 
mothers were prescribed at least one medicine for preg-
nancy-related symptoms, and 58 % (65/112) of these had 
more than one prescription in that specific group; see 
Table 2. 
In the group of 202 mothers, a total of 817 prescriptions 
were prescribed for 142 different medicines during preg-
nancy. The number of prescriptions per mother during 
pregnancy varied between 1 and 29 (median 3). During the 
entire pregnancy, miconazole (gyno), meclozine combi-
nations (Emesafene </p>

<p>Ò </p>

<p>), amoxicillin, nitrofurantoin, and 
ferrous fumarate were most commonly prescribed. With 
the exception of nitrofurantoin and ferrous fumarate, these 
medications were also most frequently prescribed in the 
first trimester. </p>

<p>3.3 Compliance </p>

<p>During the first trimester, the compliance rates between the 
three main groups ranged from 0.84 to 0.92. The highest 
compliance rate, 0.92 (95 % confidence interval [CI] 
0.82-0.96), was seen for medicines for pregnancy-related 
symptoms, while rates for medicines for chronic diseases 
and for short-term or occasional use were comparable: 0.84 
(95 % CI 0.74-0.95) and 0.86 (95 % CI 0.78-0.94), 
respectively. For the entire pregnancy, the compliance rates 
between the three main groups ranged from 0.90 to 0.95. 
The highest compliance rate, 0.95 (95 % CI 0.90-0.99), 
was seen for medicines for pregnancy-related symptoms, 
while rates for chronic diseases and for short-term or 
occasional use were 0.92 (95 % CI 0.86-0.98) and 0.90 
(95 % CI 0.85-0.95), respectively. See Table 2. 
When we calculated the compliance rates for a selected 
group that included only the live births and stillbirths, or 
when we applied the strict definition of compliance, we 
found the rates were comparable (see ESM 2). 
Looking at the medication subgroups, relatively low 
compliance rates (0.69-0.82) for the first trimester were 
found for corticosteroids, dermatological preparations; 
antibacterials for systemic use; ear, eye, nose, and throat 
preparations; and anti-emetics. High compliance rates 
(1.00) for the first trimester were found for multivitamins 
containing folic acid, or folic acid and its derivatives, and 
for gynecological anti-infectives and antiseptics. 
Relatively low compliance rates (0.73-0.88) for the 
entire pregnancy were found for corticosteroids, dermato-
logical preparations; dermatologicals excluding anti-pso-
riatics and corticosteroids; antifungals for dermatological 
use; antibacterials for systemic use; anxiolytics, hypnotics 
and sedatives; ear, eye, nose, and throat preparations; anti-
emetics; and laxatives. High compliance rates (0.98-1.00) 
for the entire pregnancy were found for anti-hypertensives, </p>

<p> 
L. de Jonge et al. </p>

<p>vasoprotectives, beta blockers, calcium channel blockers; 
multivitamins containing folic acid, or folic acid and its 
derivatives; and gynecological anti-infective and antisep-
tics (Table 2). 
Focusing on the administration forms, for the first tri-
mester, the compliance rates ranged from 0.69 (ear, eye, 
nose preparations) to 1.00 (vaginal preparations). For the 
entire pregnancy, the compliance rates ranged from 0.78 
(ear, eye, nose preparations) to 0.98 (vaginal preparations). 
We examined whether the time period between date of 
telephone interview and date of birth influenced the results. 
We divided the group into women with a short time 
between the date of telephone interview and date of birth 
(B7.75 months [first quartile]) and a long time between the 
date of telephone interview and date of birth (C18 months 
[fourth quartile]). For all medicines together, the compli-
ance was slightly higher in the 'short time' group (n = 50) 
(0.98 [95 % CI 0.90-1.00]) than in the 'long time' group </p>

<p>(n = 56) (0.93 [95 % CI 0.83-0.97]), but this was not 
statistically significant (Fisher's exact test p = 0.367). </p>

<p>3.4 Dosage and Duration Conform to Prescription </p>

<p>For the medication that was actually taken, we determined 
whether each prescription was taken as prescribed in terms 
of the dosage and duration. Of the medication used during 
the first trimester, the dosage taken was according to that 
prescribed for 68 % (95 % CI 58-79) of the medicines for 
chronic use and up to 88 % (95 % CI 82-94) of the 
medicines for pregnancy-related symptoms. Where the 
dosage used was not according to that prescribed, it was 
lower than prescribed for 93 % (95 % CI 69-99) of the 
medicines for chronic use and those for short-term or 
occasional use and up to 100 % (95 % CI 68-100) of the 
medicines for pregnancy-related symptoms. The duration 
was according to that prescribed for 55 % (95 % CI 44-66) </p>

<p>735 cases were registered in EUROCAT 
NNL in the period from 1 January 2011 
to 1 February 2012 </p>

<p>315 cases were registered but their pharmacy records 
were not received in the specified period </p>

<p>For 420 cases, we received pharmacy 
records in the period from 1 January 
2011 to 1 February 2012 </p>

<p>98 pharmacy records reported 'no medicines dispensed 
in the relevant pregnancy period' </p>

<p>8 pharmacy records reported 'no information on 
medication use available for all or part of the 
pregnancy period', 'no information on medication use 
available for that woman at all' or 'did not provide 
information on medication use for the relevant 
pregnancy period' </p>

<p>314 pharmacy records had information 
on medication use for the entire 
pregnancy period </p>

<p>59 pharmacy records were for mothers whose children 
were born before 1 January 2009 </p>

<p>255 pharmacy records were for mothers 
whose children were born in 2009 or 
later </p>

<p>53 pharmacy records were unreadable or the 
prescription was unclear </p>

<p>202 pharmacy records were included 
(202 pregnancies in 202 women) </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Case selection flowchart </p>

<p>Actual Use of Medications Prescribed During Pregnancy </p>

<p>
Table 2 Overview of the numbers of prescriptions, the women to whom they were prescribed and their compliance rate for the first trimester and 
the entire pregnancy </p>

<p>Medication 
A 
B </p>

<p>Prx 
(n) </p>

<p>Maximum no. 
of prx per 
pregnancy </p>

<p>Women given a 
prx at least 
once (n) </p>

<p>Women 
with [1 
prx (n) </p>

<p>% Women who 
confirmed use of 
C1 prx (n) </p>

<p>Compliance rate 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>First trimester </p>

<p>All medicines together 
314 19 
129 
75 
58 117 
0.91 (0.86-0.96) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Medicines for chronic diseases 
together </p>

<p>85 
5 
45 
24 
53 
38 
0.84 (0.74-0.95) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Antihypertensives, vasoprotectives, 
beta blocking agents, CCBs </p>

<p>8 
3 </p>

<p>a 
a 
a 
a 
a </p>

<p>Corticosteroids, dermatological 
preparations </p>

<p>15 
2 
13 
2 
15 
9 
0.69 (0.42-0.87) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Medicines for obstructive airway 
diseases </p>

<p>21 
5 
10 
6 
60 
9 
0.90 (0.60-0.98)c </p>

<p>Medicines for short-term and 
occasional use together </p>

<p>113 
6 
70 
24 
34 
60 
0.86 (0.78-0.94) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Medicines for functional GI 
disorders and medicines for peptic 
ulcer and GORD </p>

<p>18 
3 
12 
4 
33 
11 
0.92 (0.65-0.99) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Dermatologicals exclusive anti-
psoriatics and corticosteroids, 
dermatological preparations </p>

<p>27 
4 
20 
4 
20 
18 
0.90 (0.70-0.97) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Antifungals for dermatological use 
7 
1 </p>

<p>a 
a 
a 
a 
a </p>

<p>Emollients and protectives 
8 
3 </p>

<p>a 
a 
a 
a 
a </p>

<p>Antibacterials for systemic use 
31 
2 
28 
3 
10 
23 
0.82 (0.64-0.92) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Anxiolytics, hypnotics and sedatives 
3 
1 </p>

<p>a 
a 
a 
a 
a </p>

<p>Ear, eye, nose and throat 
preparations </p>

<p>17 
2 
13 
4 
30 
9 
0.69 (0.42-0.87) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Medicines for pregnancy-related 
symptoms </p>

<p>116 
8 
60 
27 
45 
55 
0.92 (0.82-0.96) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Antacids 
1 
1 </p>

<p>a 
a 
a 
a 
a </p>

<p>Anti-emetics 
47 
7 
26 
9 
35 
21 
0.81 (0.62-0.91) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Laxatives 
11 
2 </p>

<p>a 
a 
a 
a 
a </p>

<p>Multivitamins containing folic acid 
or folic acid and its derivatives </p>

<p>19 
3 
14 
4 
29 
14 
1.00 (0.78-1.00) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Iron preparations 
11 
3 </p>

<p>a 
a 
a 
a 
a </p>

<p>Gynecological anti-infectives and 
antiseptics </p>

<p>27 
2 
23 
4 
17 
23 
1.00 (0.86-1.00) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Entire pregnancy </p>

<p>All medicines together 
817 29 
202 
140 
69 193 
0.96 (0.93-0.98) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Medicines for chronic diseases 
together </p>

<p>212 10 
77 
49 
64 
71 
0.92 (0.86-0.98) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Antihypertensives, vasoprotectives, 
beta-blocking agents, CCBs </p>

<p>45 10 
20 
10 
50 
20 
1.00 (0.84-1.00) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Corticosteroids, dermatological 
preparations </p>

<p>43 
9 
24 
7 
29 
18 
0.75 (0.58-0.92) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Medicines for obstructive airway 
diseases </p>

<p>47 
7 
17 
9 
53 
16 
0.94 (0.73-0.99) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Medicines for short-term and 
occasional use together </p>

<p>317 12 
128 
74 
58 115 
0.90 (0.85-0.95) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Medicines for functional GI 
disorders and medicines for peptic 
ulcer and GORD </p>

<p>37 
6 
17 
7 
41 
16 
0.94 (0.73-0.99) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p> 
L. de Jonge et al. </p>

<p>(medicines for chronic use) and up to 66 % (95 % CI 
57-75) (medicines for pregnancy-related symptoms). 
Where the duration of use was not according to that pre-
scribed, it was shorter than prescribed for medicines for 
chronic use (54 % [95 % CI 34-74]) and for pregnancy-
related symptoms (77 % [95 % CI 61-93]), but it was 
longer for short-term or occasional use (0.56 [95 % CI 
37-74]). 
Of the medicines used during the entire pregnancy, the 
dosage taken conformed to that prescribed for 75 % (95 % 
CI 69-81) (medicines for chronic use) and up to 87 % 
(95 % CI 82-91) (for pregnancy-related symptoms). Where 
the dosage taken was not according to that prescribed, it 
was lower: 97 % (95 % CI 84-99) (medicines for chronic 
use) and up to 100 % (95 % CI 85-100) (for pregnancy-
related symptoms). The duration conformed to the pre-
scription for 63 % (95 % CI 57-68) (medicines for short-
term or occasional use) and up to 69 % (95 % CI 63-74) 
(for pregnancy-related symptoms). Where the duration was 
not according to that prescribed, it was shorter for 
medicines for short-term or occasional use (56 % [95 % CI </p>

<p>45-66]) and for pregnancy-related symptoms (71 % [95 % 
CI 60-82]). See Table 3. </p>

<p>4 Discussion </p>

<p>We investigated the actual use of medication prescribed 
during pregnancy, based on 817 prescriptions prescribed to 
202 mothers of children with congenital anomalies. The 
reported compliance for any medication prescribed ranged 
from 0.84 (medicines for chronic diseases) to 0.92 (for 
pregnancy-related symptoms) in the first trimester, with the 
lowest values for 'corticosteroids, dermatological prepa-
rations' and 'ear, eye, nose and throat preparations' [0.69] 
and the highest values for 'multivitamins containing folic 
acid or folic acid and its derivatives' and 'gynecological 
anti-infectives and antiseptics' [1.00]. For the entire preg-
nancy, the reported compliance for any medication pre-
scribed ranged from 0.90 (medicines for short-term or 
occasional use) to 0.95 (for pregnancy-related symptoms), 
with the lowest values for 'anxiolytics, hypnotics and </p>

<p>Table 2 continued </p>

<p>Medication 
A 
B </p>

<p>Prx 
(n) </p>

<p>Maximum no. 
of prx per 
pregnancy </p>

<p>Women given a 
prx at least 
once (n) </p>

<p>Women 
with [1 
prx (n) </p>

<p>% Women who 
confirmed use of 
C1 prx (n) </p>

<p>Compliance rate 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Dermatologicals exclusive anti-
psoriatics and corticosteroids, 
dermatological preparations </p>

<p>65 
5 
38 
14 
37 
34 
0.89 (0.76-0.96) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Antifungals for dermatological use 
21 
3 
16 
3 
19 
14 
0.88 (0.64-0.97) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Emollients and protectives 
28 
4 
14 
7 
50 
13 
0.93 (0.69-0.99) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Antibacterials for systemic use 
107 
6 
67 
24 
36 
57 
0.85 (0.77-0.94) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Anxiolytics, hypnotics and sedatives 
13 
2 
11 
2 
18 
8 
0.73 (0.43-0.90) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Ear, eye, nose, and throat 
preparations </p>

<p>54 
6 
31 
14 
45 
26 
0.84 (0.67-0.93) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Medicines for pregnancy-related 
symptoms </p>

<p>288 19 
112 
65 
58 106 
0.95 (0.90-0.99) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Antacids 
25 
4 
14 
5 
36 
13 
0.93 (0.69-0.99) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Anti-emetics 
71 19 
30 
11 
37 
24 
0.80 (0.66-0.94) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Laxatives 
33 
4 
22 
7 
32 
18 
0.82 (0.61-0.93) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Multivitamins containing folic acid 
or folic acid and its derivatives </p>

<p>34 
4 
16 
8 
50 
16 
1.00 (0.81-1.00) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Iron preparations 
42 
4 
22 
11 
50 
19 
0.86 (0.67-0.95) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Gynecological anti-infectives and 
antiseptics </p>

<p>83 
5 
52 
22 
42 
51 
0.98 (0.90-1.00) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Columns marked 'A' focus on the prescriptions and the distribution; columns marked 'B' focus on the number of women to whom prescriptions 
were given, whether they receive one or more prescriptions, and their compliance rates </p>

<p>CCBs calcium channel blockers, CI confidence interval, GI gastrointestinal, GORD gastroesophageal reflux disease, prx prescription 
a \10 women were prescribed in this subgroup </p>

<p>b Wald method was applied </p>

<p>c Wilson method was applied </p>

<p>Actual Use of Medications Prescribed During Pregnancy </p>

<p>
Table 3 
Use of medication conforming to the prescribed dosage and duration </p>

<p>Medication </p>

<p>Prx actually taken 
(n, 100%) </p>

<p>Conforming to </p>

<p>prx (n) </p>

<p>% (95% CI) </p>

<p>Not 
recalled </p>

<p>(n) </p>

<p>% (95% CI) </p>

<p>Not conforming 
to prx (n) </p>

<p>% (95% CI) 
Lower dose among those not 
conforming to prx (n) </p>

<p>% (95% CI) </p>

<p>Conforming to prescribed dosage </p>

<p>First trimester 
All medicines </p>

<p>277 </p>

<p>218 </p>

<p>78.7 (73.9-83.5) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>8.3 (5.1-11.6) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>13.0 (9.0-17.0) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>94.4 (81.9-98.5) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>All together </p>

<p>76 </p>

<p>52 </p>

<p>68.4 (58.0-78.9) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>11.8 (4.6-19.1) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>18.4 (9.7-27.1) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>92.9 (68.5-98.7) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>For chronic diseases together </p>

<p>94 </p>

<p>71 </p>

<p>75.5 (66.8-84.2) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>9.6 (3.6-15.5) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>14.9 (7.7-22.1) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>92.9 (68.5-98.7) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>For short-term and 
occasional use together </p>

<p>107 </p>

<p>94 </p>

<p>87.9 (81.7-94.0) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4.7 (0.7-8.7) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>7.5 (2.5-12.5) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>100.0 (67.6-100) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Entire pregnancy 
For pregnancy-related 
symptoms </p>

<p>736 </p>

<p>589 </p>

<p>80.0 (77.1-82.9) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>7.6 (5.7-9.5) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>91 </p>

<p>12.4 (10.0-14.7) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>89 </p>

<p>97.8 (92.3-99.4) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>All together </p>

<p>197 </p>

<p>147 </p>

<p>74.6 (68.5-80.7) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>9.6 (5.5-13.8) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>15.7 (10.7-20.8) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>96.8 (83.8-99.4) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>For chronic diseases together 273 </p>

<p>212 </p>

<p>77.7 (72.7-82.6) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>8.1 (4.8-11.3) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>14.3 (10.1-18.4) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>97.4 (86.8-99.5) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>For short-term and 
occasional use together </p>

<p>266 </p>

<p>230 </p>

<p>86.5 (82.4-90.6) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>5.6 (2.9-8.4) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>7.9 (4.7-11.1) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>100.0 (84.5-100) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Conforming to prescribed duration </p>

<p>First trimester 
All medicines </p>

<p>277 </p>

<p>168 </p>

<p>60.6 (54.9-66.4) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>11.6 (7.8-15.3) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>77 </p>

<p>27.8 (22.5-33.1) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>58.4 (47.4-69.4) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>All together </p>

<p>76 </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>55.3 (44.1-66.4) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>13.2 (5.6-20.8) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>31.6 (21.1-42.0) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>54.2 (34.2-74.1) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>For chronic diseases together </p>

<p>94 </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>58.5 (48.6-68.5) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>12.8 (6.0-19.5) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>28.7 (19.6-37.9) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>44.4 (25.7-63.2) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>For short-term and 
occasional use together </p>

<p>107 </p>

<p>71 </p>

<p>66.4 (57.4-75.3) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>9.3 (3.8-14.9) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>24.3 (16.2-32.4) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>76.9 (60.7-93.1) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Entire pregnancy 
For pregnancy-related 
symptoms </p>

<p>736 </p>

<p>482 </p>

<p>65.5 (62.1-68.9) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>7.9 (5.9-9.8) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>196 </p>

<p>26.6 (23.4-29.8) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>116 </p>

<p>59.2 (52.3-66.1) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>All together </p>

<p>197 </p>

<p>128 </p>

<p>65.0 (58.3-71.6) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10.2 (5.9-14.4) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>49 </p>

<p>24.9 (18.8-30.9) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>49.0 (35.0-63.0) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>For chronic diseases together 273 </p>

<p>171 </p>

<p>62.6 (56.9-68.4) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>7.7 (4.5-10.9) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>81 </p>

<p>29.7 (24.3-35.1) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>55.6 (44.7-66.4) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>For short-term and 
occasional use together </p>

<p>266 </p>

<p>183 </p>

<p>68.8 (63.2-74.4) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>6.4 (3.5-9.3) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>66 </p>

<p>24.8 (19.6-30.0) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>71.2 (60.3-82.1) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Prx </p>

<p>prescription </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Wald method was applied </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Wilson method was applied </p>

<p> 
L. de Jonge et al. </p>

<p>sedatives' [0.73] and the highest values for 'multivitamins 
containing folic acid or folic acid and its derivatives' and 
'antihypertensives, vasoprotectives, beta blocking agents, 
calcium channel blockers' [1.00]. Most of the medicines 
actually taken were reported as having been taken 
according to the dosage prescribed and, if not, the dosage 
taken was lower. More than half of the medicines actually 
taken were used for the duration prescribed and, if not, the 
duration was mostly shorter. 
Reports in the literature show a wide range in compli-
ance rates for different medicines in general [15, 16]. One 
study showed that, in the general population, the compli-
ance rates for medicines for chronic use were between 40 
and 50 %, and the compliance rates for medicines for 
short-term use were between 70 and 80 % [17]. </p>

<p>4.1 Comparison with Other Studies </p>

<p>In a Dutch study in 1990, interviews regarding medication 
use during pregnancy were performed within 2 weeks after 
birth, and the results were compared with pharmacy 
records. The study found that interviews were preferable to 
pharmacy records in the case of OTC medicines used. 
However, pharmacy records were found to provide more 
reliable information for longer recall periods and where 
mothers used multiple and/or repeated medicines [18]. In a 
Danish study, researchers compared data in the North 
Jutland Prescription Database (NJPD) with data from 
interviews in the Danish National Birth Cohort (DNBC) 
and calculated the compliance rates. In this study, the 
researchers defined compliance as the probability of 
mothers reporting the use of medicines in the DNBC after a 
prescription had been dispensed, so in fact the mothers' 
recall was investigated. The study reported a 'compliance' 
of 70-100 % for medicines for chronic use and of 12-59 % 
for medicines for short-term use [5]. In another study, in 
the EUROCAT NNL, the maternal recall of prescribed 
medication during pregnancy was investigated by com-
paring the results of a paper questionnaire using indication-
oriented questions with the medication registered in the 
EUROCAT NNL database based on information from the 
pharmacy. The sensitivity was calculated as the proportion 
of women who reported prescription medication use in the 
questionnaire among those who had been exposed to that 
medication according to the registry data. A woman was 
recorded as having been exposed when she confirmed (in a 
telephone interview) that she had taken the medication 
prescribed or when she mentioned using OTC medicines. 
For medication for chronic use, a sensitivity of 0.47 (95 % 
CI 0.40-0.55) was found, i.e., the use of medicines for 
chronic use was reported in the questionnaire by 47 % of 
the mothers who had received a prescription for a medi-
cation for chronic use. For medication for occasional or </p>

<p>short-term use, and for pregnancy-related symptoms, the 
sensitivity was 0.34 (0.29-0.40) and 0.51 (0.43-0.58), 
respectively [19]. 
With respect to medication for chronic use, our results 
are in line with those of the Danish study. However, for 
medicines for short-term use, the compliance in our study 
was higher, although the Danish study investigated the 
recall [5]. Compared with the results from the EUROCAT 
NNL study, which investigated maternal recall, the repor-
ted compliance in our study is higher for all groups [19]. 
This can be explained by the self-reporting based on 
interviews and questionnaires, like the Danish and 
EUROCAT NNL studies, being affected by several aspects 
influencing accurate recall [20, 21], such as language bar-
riers, time pressure, or the woman's circumstances, like 
perception, expectation, experience, and education [22-
24]. One would therefore expect to see under-reporting of 
medication use in pregnancy when using interviews or 
questionnaires without the support of pharmacy records 
[19, 25]. 
The compliance rates for selected groups (excluding 
spontaneous abortions and TOPFAs and applying a strict 
definition of 'compliance') were similar to those reported 
here (see ESM 2). Although the dosage of a medication and 
duration of exposure are considered relevant factors in 
affecting pregnancy outcomes [26], the quality of these 
parameters in studies using routinely collected adminis-
trative data has not been thoroughly examined [27]. Nev-
ertheless, it is important to look at specific medicines or 
groups of medicines to investigate whether the dosage or 
duration changes during pregnancy. For example, one 
study showed that 39 % of women who used anti-asth-
matics during pregnancy actually discontinued or reduced 
their medicines [28]. </p>

<p>4.2 Strengths and Limitations </p>

<p>To our knowledge, this is the first study in which compli-
ance has been investigated by verifying pharmacy records 
in a structured telephone interview with each mother. 
Although the women were sent a list of their prescribed 
medication before the interview, the question still arises as 
to how accurately they can recall the actual use of a pre-
scribed medication retrospectively. The period between 
date of telephone interview and date of birth ranged from 2 
to 35 months. The compliance rate did not differ signifi-
cantly among the 'short time' and the 'long time' group; 
however, regardless of time between the telephone inter-
view and the date of birth, correct recall of the use of a 
certain medication (particular, that for short-term use) may 
be difficult. It is possible that women give positive answers 
to please the interviewer or deny the use of a medication if 
they feel guilty about their child's condition. </p>

<p>Actual Use of Medications Prescribed During Pregnancy </p>

<p>
In addition, we only measured compliance in a selected 
group of women who gave birth to a child with a congenital 
anomaly. Therefore, by definition, the results are not 
applicable to the general pregnant population. If women 
who gave birth to a child with a congenital anomaly recall 
events during pregnancy better than women with a healthy 
child (for instance, because they try to find an explanation 
for their child's congenital anomaly), recall bias has to be 
taken into account in studies using unaffected controls [29]. 
Further research is recommended to investigate compliance 
in the general pregnant population. 
Our broad definition of compliance might lead to an 
overestimation of the compliance rate, although we found 
that applying a strict definition of compliance did not affect 
the compliance rates. 
Finally, we could only investigate compliance for cer-
tain common medication groups, since we did not have 
enough power to calculate compliance for specific 
medicines. </p>

<p>5 Conclusion </p>

<p>Prescription records are generally a relatively reliable 
source of data for research into associations between 
medication use in pregnancy and congenital anomalies 
compared with other data sources. The medication use in 
pregnancy based on pharmacy records might represent an 
overestimation, which should be taken into account. 
However, our results show that, except for 'Corticos-
teroids, dermatological preparations'; 'Ear, eye, nose, and 
throat preparations', and 'Anxiolytics, hypnotics and 
sedatives', this overestimation seems generally minimal. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments The authors thank J. L. Senior for editorial 
assistance. </p>

<p>Funding EUROCAT Northern Netherlands is funded by the Min-
istry of Health, Welfare and Sports. This study was conducted as part 
of the EUROmediCAT project, funded under the European Union's 
Seventh Framework Program. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest Linda de Jonge, Hermien E. K. de Walle, Irene 
M. van Langen, Lolkje T. W. de Jong-van den Berg, and Marian K. 
Bakker declare that they have no conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>

<p>Contribution to authorship L. de Jonge was responsible for study 
design, statistical analysis, interpreting the findings, and writing the 
manuscript. H. E. K. de Walle, and IM van Langen contributed to all 
revisions of the manuscript. L. T. W. de Jong-van den Berg and M. 
K. Bakker were responsible for supervising the study and contributed 
to all revisions of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which per-
mits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any </p>

<p>medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) 
and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and 
indicate if changes were made. </p>



<p> 
L. de Jonge et al. </p>



<p>Actual Use of Medications Prescribed During Pregnancy </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>