<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4717961" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Decreased platelet (PLT) count is one of the independent risk factors for mortality in intensive care unit (ICU) patients. This 
study was to investigate the relationship between PLT indices and illness severity and their performances in predicting hospital mortality. 
Methods: Adult patients who admitted to ICU of Changzheng Hospital from January 2011 to September 2012 and met inclusion criteria 
were included in this study. Univariate analysis was used to identify potential independent risk factors for mortality. Multiple logistic 
regression analysis was used to calculate adjusted odds ratio for mortality in patients with normal or abnormal PLT indices. The relationship 
between PLT indices and illness severity were assessed by the Acute Physiology and Chronic Health Evaluation II (APACHE II) scores or 
sequential organ failure assessment (SOFA) scores in patients with normal and abnormal PLT indices. The performances of PLT indices 
in predicting mortality were assessed by receiver operating curves and diagnostic parameters. The survival curves between patients with 
normal and abnormal PLT indices were compared using Kaplan-Meier method. 
Results: From January 2011 to September 2012, 261 of 361 patients (204 survivors and 57 nonsurvivors) met the inclusion criteria. After 
adjustment for clinical variables, PLT count &lt;100 × 10 12 /L (P = 0.011), plateletcrit (PCT) &lt;0.108 (P = 0.002), mean platelet volume (MPV) 
&gt;11.3 fL (P = 0.023) and platelet distribution width (PDW) percentage &gt;17% (P = 0.009) were identified as independent risk factors 
for mortality. The APACHE II and SOFA scores were 14.0 (9.0-20.0) and 7.0 (5.0-10.5) in the "low PLT" tertile, 13.0 (8.0-16.0) and 
7.0 (4.0-11.0) in the "low PCT" tertile, 14.0 (9.3-19.0) and 7.0 (4.0-9.8) in the "high MPV" tertile, 14.0 (10.5-20.0) and 7.0 (5.0-11.0) 
in the "high PDW" tertile, all of which were higher than those in patients with normal indices. Patients with decreased PLT and PCT 
values (all P &lt; 0.001), or increased MPV and PDW values (P = 0.007 and 0.003, respectively) had shortened length of survival than 
those with normal PLT indices. 
Conclusions: Patients with abnormally low PLT count, high MPV value, and high PDW value were associated with more severe illness 
and had higher risk of death as compared to patients with normal PLT indices. </p>

<p>Key words: Mean Platelet Volume; Platelet Count; Platelet Distribution Width; Platelet Indices; Plateletcrit </p>

<p>Address for correspondence: Dr. Zhao-Fen Lin, 
Department of Emergency Medicine, Changzheng Hospital, Second 
Military Medical University, Shanghai 200003, China 
E-Mail: linzhaofen@hotmail.com </p>

<p>Access this article online </p>

<p>Quick Response Code: 
Website: 
www.cmj.org </p>

<p>DOI: 
10.4103/0366-6999.161346 </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ August 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 15 </p>



<p>infants, and the increment was correlated to the severity of 
sepsis. [8] In addition, in patients with cirrhosis and ascites, 
elevated PDW and MPV were accurate diagnostic predictors 
for ascitic fluid infection. [9] In addition, elevated PDW 
and MPV were associated with higher risk of in-hospital 
cardiovascular adverse events in patients with ST-segment 
elevation myocardial infarction undergoing primary 
percutaneous coronary intervention. [10] All these evidences 
indicated that PLT indices may be treated as indictors in 
a series of diseases. Thus, we conducted a retrospective 
study, which included patients who admitted to our ICU 
from January 2011 to September 2012, to explore whether 
PLT indices (PLT, PCT, MPV, and PDW) could be used to 
determine the severity of illness and to predict death events 
in critically ill patients. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>Patients who admitted to ICU of Changzheng Hospital from 
January 2011 to September 2012 were included. The general 
conditions, diagnosis at admission, laboratory examinations, 
treatment measures, length of ICU stay, outcomes, and 
other data regarding patients' in-hospital information were 
obtained from the Electronic Medical Records System. Only 
the data and the illness severity scores recorded at admission 
were used for analysis. In cases when patients admitted into 
hospital multiple times, only the data drew from the first 
record was considered. </p>

<p>Inclusion and exclusion criteria </p>

<p>Inclusion criteria 
(1) Age ranged from 18 to 75 years; (2) all PLT indices and 
in-hospital information were fully available; (3) the length 
of stay in ICU was more than 24 h. </p>

<p>Exclusion criteria 
(1) Pregnant and maternity women; (2) patients with 
active hemorrhage; (3) patients with hematological 
diseases (including anemia, hypersplenia, lymphoma 
or leukemia, rheumatism, and bone marrow diseases); 
(4) patients who had infused with blood or PLTs prior to 
their admission; (5) patients who had used anti-PLT drugs 
such as clopidogrel prior to their admission; (6) patients who 
had received radiotherapy or chemotherapy or bone marrow 
transplantation 1 month prior to admission. </p>

<p>The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the 
Second Military Medical University and conducted in 
accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. Informed 
consent was obtained from all participants or legal 
representatives. </p>

<p>Assessment of outcomes </p>

<p>The assessment of outcomes included: (1) The odds 
ratio (OR) for mortality in patients with normal and 
abnormal PLT indices; (2) the relationship between all 
PLT indices and the APACHE II scores or sequential organ 
failure assessment (SOFA) scores; (3) the performance </p>

<p>of received operating curves (ROCs) of all PLT indices 
in predicting patients' death events; (4) the difference of 
survival curves between patients with normal and abnormal 
PLT indices. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Normally distributed data were expressed as mean ± standard 
deviation (SD), and comparisons between groups were 
performed using a Student's t-test. Abnormally distributed 
data were expressed as median and interquartile range (M, 
IQR), and comparisons between groups were performed 
using a Wilcoxon rank sum test. Categorical variables were 
presented as numerical data and percentages, statistical 
comparisons were conducted by a Chi-square (χ 2 ) test. In 
univariate analysis, variables with P &lt; 0.1 between survivals 
and deaths were considered as potential risk factors for 
mortality and included into a multivariable logistic regression 
model for adjustment. After every PLT index had been 
adjusted by clinical covariates, the ORs for mortality in 
patients with normal or abnormal PLT indices were presented. 
Hosmer-Lemeshow test was applied to test Goodness-of-fit 
properties. Collinearity was determined by variance inflation 
factor (VIF). The value of VIF more than 5 indicated the 
existence of multicollinearity. [11] Second, to explore the 
relationship between PLT indices and illness severity, we 
first divided each PLT index into tertiles of the normal range, 
higher than upper limit, lower than lower limit. Then, we 
plotted the distribution of APACHE II scores and SOFA 
scores in each tertile to investigate whether the patients with 
abnormal PLT indices were associated with higher illness 
scores. Third, to evaluate the performance of the PLT indices 
in predicting death events, we built the ROCs for every index 
and compared the area under the curves (AUC). We also 
calculated optimal cut-off point (where the Youden index 
reached the maximum value) [12] and the diagnostic parameters 
including sensitivity, specificity, positive likelihood ratio, 
negative likelihood ratio and diagnostic accuracy for each 
PLT index. Finally, to compare the prognosis in patient with 
normal and abnormal PLT indices, we used the Kaplan-
Meier method to construct survival curves for the each 
group. Log-rank test was used for comparison of different 
survival curves between patients with normal and abnormal 
PLT indices. All the statistical analysis was performed 
using Stata10 software (StataCorp LP, College Station, TX, 
USA), P &lt; 0.05 was considered as statistically significant. 
All the diagrams were constructed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software Inc.</rs>., CA, USA). </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>General information of patients </p>

<p>A total of 361 patients were admitted to ICU from January 
2011 to September 2012, of which 261 patients met 
the inclusion criteria. The clinical characteristics of the 
survival group and the death group were summarized 
in Table 1. There were 191 male patients and 70 female 
patients, and their death rates were 18.3% and 31.4%, 
respectively. Respiratory disease (25.7%), trauma (12.3%) </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ August 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 15 </p>

<p>
and cardiovascular disease (10.0%) were the most common 
etiology among all the patients. Patients who died in 
hospital were elder (P = 0.002) and had higher APACHE 
II and SOFA scores (P &lt; 0.001) than survivors. Among 
laboratory examinations, serum creatinine and serum 
lactate were significantly higher in death patients than 
survivors (P &lt; 0.001 and P = 0.001, respectively). Among 
the four PLT indices, PLT and PCT were lower in death 
patients (P = 0.001 and P &lt; 0.001, respectively) while MPV 
and PDW were higher in the death patients (P = 0.011 and 
P &lt; 0.001, respectively). </p>

<p>Adjusted odds ratio of abnormal platelet indices in 
multivariate regression model </p>

<p>As the results of univariate analysis presented in Table 1, 
gender, age, APACHE II, SOFA scores, mechanical 
ventilation, blood lactic acid, serum creatinine and all 
PLT indices were selected as potential risk factors for 
death and entered in the multivariate analysis. After 
adjustment for well-established clinical risk factors, 
PLT &lt;100 × 10 12 /L (OR: 1.96 [1.21-2.32], P = 0.011), 
PCT &lt; 0.108 (OR: 1.97 [1.60-2.09], P = 0.002), MPV &gt;11.3 
fL (OR: 1.15 [1.02-2.36], P = 0.023) and PDW &gt;17% </p>

<p>(OR: 2.38 [1.14-4.99], P = 0.009) were identified as the 
independent risk factors for mortality [Table 2]. </p>

<p>The receiver operating curves of platelet indices on 
predicting mortality </p>

<p>The ROCs of four PLT indices on predicting mortality were 
shown in Figure 1 and Table 3. PLT and MPV obtained the 
largest areas under ROCs of 0.78 and 0.79, respectively. 
PCT and PDW obtained lesser areas under ROCs of 0.66 
and 0.68, respectively. The sensitivity and specificity for PLT 
were 60.1% and 91.2%, both of which were slightly higher 
than those of MPV (58.2% and 90.2%). However, MPV has 
the highest diagnostic accuracy (83.5%) among the four PLT 
indices. PLT count and MPV also obtained better positive 
likelihood ratio (6.9 and 6.0) and the negative ratio (0.4 and 
0.5) compared to those of PCT and PDW. </p>

<p>The relationship between platelet indices and Acute 
Physiology and Chronic Health Evaluation II scores and 
sequential organ failure assessment scores </p>

<p>All the PLT indices were divided into tertiles of normal 
range, higher than upper limit, lower than lower limit. 
APACHE II and SOFA scores in each tertile were presented </p>

<p>Table 1: Characteristics of patients on admission by survivors and death </p>

<p>Variables 
Survivors (n = 204) 
Nonsurvivors (n = 57) 
Total (n = 261) 
P </p>

<p>Male, n (%) 
156 (76.5) 
35 (61.4) 
191 (73.2) 
0.023 
Age, years, median (IQR) 
52 (43-61) 
64 (53-76) 
57 (46-65) 
0.002 
APACHE II scores, median (IQR) 
11 (8-16) 
18 (13-25.5) 
12 (9-18) 
&lt;0.001 
SOFA scores, median (IQR) 
5 (3-8) 
9 (7-14) 
6 (3-8) 
&lt;0.001 
Etiology, n (%) 
Cardiovascular 
21 (10.3) 
5 (8.8) 
26 (10.0) 
&gt;0.05 
Pulmonary 
54 (26.5) 
13 (22.8) 
67 (25.7) 
&gt;0.05 
Neurological 
20 (9.8) 
5 (8.8) 
25 (9.6) 
&gt;0.05 
Renal failure 
8 (3.9) 
3 (5.3) 
11 (4.2) 
&gt;0.05 
Hepatic failure 
8 (3.9) 
2 (3.5) 
10 (3.8) 
&gt;0.05 
Digestive 
8 (3.9) 
3 (5.3) 
11 (4.2) 
&gt;0.05 
Endocrine 
5 (2.5) 
2 (3.5) 
7 (2.7) 
&gt;0.05 
Multiple organ failure 
18 (8.8) 
5 (8.7) 
23 (8.8) 
&gt;0.05 
Trauma 
25 (12.3) 
7 (12.3) 
32 (12.3) 
&gt;0.05 
Shock 
14 (6.9) 
5 (8.8) 
19 (7.3) 
&gt;0.05 
Sepsis 
17 (8.3) 
5 (8.8) 
22 (8.4) 
&gt;0.05 
Unclassified 
6 (2.9) 
2 (3.5) 
8 (3.1) 
&gt;0.05 
Mechanical ventilation, n (%) 
89 (43.6) 
36 (63.1) 
125 (47.9) 
0.013 
Laboratory examinations, mean ± SD 
WBC count, ×10 9 /L 
9.2 ± 5.6 
10.6 ± 6.3 
9.5 ± 5.8 
&gt;0.05 
Total bilirubin, µmol/L 
22.7 ± 28.1 
31.2 ± 39.8 
24.6 ± 31.0 
&gt;0.05 
Urea nitrogen, mmol/L 
6.7 ± 8.9 
9.3 ± 12.3 
7.3 ± 9.7 
&gt;0.05 
Serum creatinine, µmol/L 
73.2 ± 89.7 
123.7 ± 196.3 
84.2 ± 121.3 
0.006 
Blood lactic acid, mmol/L 
2.3 ± 3.6 
4.3 ± 6.7 
2.7 ± 4.5 
0.003 
Platelet indices, mean ± SD 
PLT, ×10 9 /L 
196.5 ± 103.3 
141.1 ± 48.3 
178.5 ± 100.6 
&lt;0.001 
PCT 
0.26 ± 0.20 
0.17 ± 0.09 
0.22 ± 0.18 
0.001 
MPV, fL 
12.8 ± 8.5 
15.8 ± 4.3 
13.4 ± 7.9 
0.011 
PDW, % 
14.5 ± 3.2 
17.0 ± 4.4 
15.0 ± 3.6 
&lt;0.001 
Characteristics and clinical information of patients on admission were obtained from EMRS. IQR: Interquartile range; APACHE II: Acute Physiology 
and Chronic Health Evaluation II; SOFA: Sequential organ failure assessment; SD: Standard deviation; WBC: White blood cell; PLT: Platelet count; 
PCT: Plateletcrit; MPV: Mean platelet volume; PDW: Platelet distribution width percentage; EMRS: Electronic Medical Records System. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ August 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 15 </p>



<p>in Figure 2. For PLT, the M and IQR of the APACHE II and 
SOFA scores in the "low PLT" tertile were 14.0 (9.0-20.0) 
and 7.0 (5.0-10.5), respectively. Correspondingly, the 
APACHE II and SOFA scores in the "normal PLT" 
tertile were 12.0 (9.0-18.0; P = 0.170) and 6.0 (3.0-8.0; 
P = 0.002), respectively. For PCT, the APACHE II and 
SOFA scores in the "low PCT" tertile were 13.0 (8.0-16.0) 
and 7.0 (4.0-11.0), respectively, and were not significantly 
different to those in the "normal PCT" tertile, which were 
12.0 (8.0-22.5; P = 0.531) and 6.0 (3.0-8.0; P = 0.141), 
respectively. For MPV, the APACHE II and SOFA scores 
in the "high MPV" tertile were 14.0 (9.3-19.0) and 
7.0 (4.0-9.8) respectively and were significantly higher than 
those in the "normal MPV" tertile that were 10.5 (8.0-16.0; 
P = 0.008) and 5.0 (2.0-7.3; P = 0.001), respectively. For 
PDW, the APACHE II and SOFA scores in the "high PDW" 
were 14.0 (10.5-20.0) and 7.0 (5.0-11.0) respectively and 
were higher than that in the "normal PDW" tertile, which </p>

<p>were 11.0 (8.0-16.0; P = 0.002) and 5.0 (3.0-8.0; P = 0.001), 
respectively. </p>

<p>Survival curves by patients with normal and abnormal 
platelet indices </p>

<p>The 28-day survival curves for patients with normal and 
abnormal PLT indices were shown in Figure 3. Patients with 
decreased PLT and PCT values had significantly shortened 
length of survival than those with normal PLT and PCT 
values (both P &lt; 0.001). Similarly, patients with increased 
MPV and PDW values had significantly shortened length 
of survival than those with normal range of MPV and 
PDW (P = 0.007 and 0.003, respectively). </p>

<p>dIscussIon </p>

<p>In our study, we found that patients with abnormally low 
PLT, abnormally high MPV value and abnormally high 
PDW value had higher APACHE II and SOFA scores than 
those with normally PLT indices, indicating that patients 
with abovementioned abnormally PLT indices were likely to 
have more severe illness. In addition, we also demonstrated 
that patients with reduced PLT and PCT or increased MPV </p>

<p>Figure 1: ROC for platelet indices in predicting mortality. The area 
under ROC (AUC) for MPV, PCT, PLT and PDW were 0.78, 0.66, 0.79, 
0.68. The AUC for the combined index of MPV and PLT was 0.80. 
ROC: Receiver operating curve; AUC: Area under the ROC curve; 
MPV: Mean platelet volume; PCT: Plateletcrit; PLT: Platelet; PDW: Platelet 
distribution width percentage. </p>

<p>Table 2: The ORs of platelet indices for mortality after 
adjustment </p>

<p>Platelet indices 
OR 95% CI P for OR P of Hosmer-
Lemeshow 
goodness of fit </p>

<p>PLT, ×10 12 /L 
0.683 </p>

<p>100-300 (reference) 
1 
-
-
&lt;100 
1.96 1.21-2.32 0.011 
&gt;300 
0.86 0.56-3.41 0.998 
PCT 
0.559 
0.108-0.282 (reference) 1 
&lt;0.108 
1.97 1.60-2.09 0.002 
&gt;0.282 
0.81 0.62-3.21 0.162 
MPV, fL 
0.721 
7.7-11.3 (reference) 
1 
-
-
&lt;7.7 
1.21 0.13-10.21 0.897 
&gt;11.3 
1.15 1.02-2.36 0.023 
PDW, % 
0.530 
10-17 (reference) 
1 
-
-
&lt;10 
1.70 0.34-3.37 0.511 
&gt;17 
2.38 1.14-4.99 0.009 
Platelet indices were divided into three tertiles of lower than low limit, 
higher than up limit and normal range as presented in table. The normal 
range was considered as reference. ORs were adjusted for variables 
including gender, age, APACHE II, SOFA scores, mechanical ventilation, 
blood lactic acid, serum creatinine. PLT: Platelet; PCT: Plateletcrit; 
MPV: Mean platelet volume; PDW: Platelet distribution width 
percentage; ORs: Odds ratios; CI: Confidence interval; APACHE II: 
Acute Physiology and Chronic Health Evaluation II; SOFA: Sequential 
organ failure assessment. </p>

<p>Table 3: Diagnostic parameters of ROCs by platelet indices on predicting mortality </p>

<p>Platelet indices 
AUC 
Optimal cut-off point 
Sensitivity, % 
Specificity, % 
Diagnostic accuracy, % 
PLR 
NLR </p>

<p>PLT 
0.78 
169 
60.1 
91.2 
66.9 
6.9 
0.4 
PCT 
0.66 
0.18 
67.5 
63.2 
66.5 
1.8 
0.5 
MPV 
0.79 
15.1 
58.2 
90.2 
83.5 
6.0 
0.5 
PDW 
0.68 
16.1 
60.0 
67.5 
65.9 
1.8 
0.6 
ROC: Receiver operating curve; AUC: Area under the ROC curve; PLR: Positive likelihood ratio; NLR: Negative likelihood ratio; PLT: Platelet; PCT: 
Plateletcrit; MPV: Mean platelet volume; PDW: Platelet distribution width percentage. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ August 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 15 </p>

<p>
and PDW had shortened length of survival as compared to 
patients with normal PLT indices. </p>

<p>Platelet indices are a group of indices that are used to measure 
the PLT count and PLT morphology. Under physiological 
conditions, the amount of PLTs in blood can be maintained in 
an equilibrium state by regeneration and elimination. Thus, 
either the PLT or their morphology remains relatively constant. 
Under pathophysiological conditions, any factor which could 
inhibit PLT regeneration, increase their activation or accelerate 
their death once overwhelming the capacity of self-regulation 
will cause changes in both PLT count and morphology and thus 
results in a change in PLT indices. [13] Researches have shown 
that activation of the coagulation system, severe infection, 
trauma, systemic inflammatory reaction syndrome and 
thrombotic diseases could all result in changes in PLT indices. 
Reduction in PLT has been proved to be one of the independent 
risk factors for ICU patients. [14,15] PCT is the arithmetic product 
of PLT count and PLT volume, which is positively correlated 
with PLT. A reduction of PLT and PCT simultaneously 
indicates that PLTs have been excessively consumed. MPV is 
the measure of PLT volume. When PLTs have been excessively </p>

<p>consumed, bone marrow will produce a large amount of 
immature PLTs which have larger volume than mature ones. 
At that time, both newly produced PLTs with large volume 
and mature PLTs with small volume simultaneously present in 
the blood, therefore, both MPV and PDW (coefficient of PLT 
variation) will be increased correspondingly. [5] Thus, instead of 
only measuring PLT as has been done previously, to measure all 
of the PLT indices, will provide us a more comprehensive view 
of illness severity and an insight into potential etiology which 
has been induced changes in PLTs indices. Two previously 
published researches reported that in sepsis or septic shock 
patients, in-hospital mortality was negatively correlated with 
PLT and PCT values, and positively correlated with MPV and 
PDW values. In addition, increased MPV and PDW have been 
considered as predictors of poor outcomes among a number 
of diseases, including sleep apnea syndrome, [16] chronic 
obstructive pulmonary disease, [17] myocardial infarction [18] 
and infection. [19] </p>

<p>Our study found that PLT indices were also useful in 
determining illness severity and predicting prognosis 
in critically ill patients. In our univariate analysis, we </p>

<p>Figure 2: APACHE II and SOFA scores in patients with normal and abnormal platelet indices. The four platelet indices of PLT, PCT, MPV, and PDW 
were divided into three tertiles of lower than low limit, higher than up limit and normal range. The APACHE II and SOFA scores were calculated 
and graphically depicted as median, interquartile range, maximum value and minimum value. APACHE II: Acute Physiology and Chronic Health 
Evaluation II; SOFA: Sequential organ failure assessment; PLT: Platelet; PCT: Plateletcrit; MPV: Mean platelet volume; PDW: Platelet distribution 
width percentage. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ August 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 15 </p>



<p>Figure 3: Kaplan-Meier survival curves for patients with normal and abnormal platelet indices were compared and log-rank test were assessed 
for significance. PLT: Platelet; PCT: Plateletcrit; MPV: Mean platelet volume; PDW: Platelet distribution width percentage. </p>

<p>found that patients who had lower PLT and PCT were 
more likely to die than those who had normal PLT and 
PCT. Similarly, patients who had higher MPV and PDW 
were associated with higher mortality as compared 
to those with normal MPV and PDW. In multivariate 
logistic regression model, reduced PLT count and PCT, 
increased MPV and PDW were still four independent risk 
factors for mortality even after they were adjusted for 
other covariates related to clinical variables. To analyze 
the performance of PLT indices in predicting mortality, 
we built the ROC for each PLT index and calculated the 
diagnostic parameters for all the PLT indices. In our 
study, PLT and MPV possessed the largest areas under 
ROC of 0.78 and 0.79, respectively. In addition, MPV 
also ranked the supreme of predictive accuracy among 
the four indices. Thus, MPV was inferred to be the 
optimal predictive indicator. However, in another study, 
which reported that all the AUCs of PLT indices were 
lower than 0.65 when predicting mortality, indicating a 
poor operating performance. [5] One possible explanation 
for the poor performance of ROCs may be the inclusion 
criteria of patients used in that study was not specified. 
For example, the patients who had received PLT infusion 
were not excluded in that study. Additionally, patients 
came from various regions could have variations in PLT 
indices. [19] In the following survival analysis, we found 
that patients with abnormally low PLT, abnormally low 
PCT value, abnormally high MPV value or abnormally 
high PDW value had significantly shortened length of 
survival than those with normal PLT indices. </p>

<p>Our studies also have several limitations. First, due to more 
specified inclusion and exclusion criteria in this study, a 
number of patients were precluded and inevitably resulted 
in limited sample size. Second, we did not conduct stratified 
analysis on whether there was a difference when PLT 
indices were applied as a predictor in patients with different 
disease. This was because patients in our ICU often bear 
several etiologies, making it difficult to discriminate the 
effect of a certain disease on PLT indices. Third, this is a 
retrospective study that inevitably had a risk to introduce 
selective bias. Forth, although we found that several 
abnormal PLT indices were associated with higher risk 
of death and more severe illness, the causal relationship 
cannot be verified in the present study. Our study also has 
several strong points. First, to our knowledge, previous 
studies were mainly focused on the relationship between 
PLT indices and patients prognosis. However, in this study, 
we found that a linkage between abnormal PLT indices and 
illness severity. Second, we selected patients by a more 
specified criteria, which could partly eliminate the effects 
of cofounders. </p>

<p>With the progress in health care examination, increasing 
novel indices have been applied in diagnosis and prediction 
of clinical outcomes, such as red blood cell β-subunit, [20] 
soluble CD14 subtype [21] and presepsin. [22] However, these 
novel diagnostic indices are expensive and ineffective in 
timeliness. PLT indices can be simply and rapidly measured 
from routine blood examination that is inexpensive and 
repeatable, providing a simple and convenient stratification </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ August 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 15 </p>

<p>
tool for illness severity. If a patient presents reduced PLT 
count and PCT indices or elevated MPV and PDW indices 
at admission, more intensive supervision and aggressive 
treatment may be needed to prevent exacerbation. </p>

<p>In conclusion, PLT indices are valuable indicators of illness 
severity and effective predictors of clinical outcomes. 
Abnormally low PLT, high MPV value, and high PDW value 
are associated with more severe illness. In addition, patients 
have higher risk of death when they present reduced PLT 
count and PCT or increased MPV and PDW as compared 
to patient with normal PLT indices. </p>

<p>references </p>



<p>Received: 15-01-2015 Edited by: Xin Chen 
How to cite this article: Zhang S, Cui YL, Diao MY, Chen DC, Lin ZF. 
Use of Platelet Indices for Determining Illness Severity and Predicting 
Prognosis in Critically Ill Patients. Chin Med J 2015;128:2012-8. </p>

<p>Source of Support: Nil. Conflict of Interest: None declared. </p>

</text></tei>