<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4120377" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives: To determine the effectiveness of a single </p>

<p>perioperative prophylactic 2 g dose of cephalexin in 
preventing surgical site infection (SSI) following 
excision of skin lesions from the lower limb. </p>

<p>Design: Prospective double-blinded placebo-</p>

<p>controlled trial testing for difference in infection rates. </p>

<p>Setting: Primary care in regional North Queensland, </p>

<p>Australia. </p>

<p>Participants: 52 patients undergoing lower limb skin </p>

<p>lesion excision. </p>

<p>Interventions: 2 g dose of cephalexin 30-60 min </p>

<p>before excision. </p>

<p>Main outcome measures: Incidence of SSI. 
Results: Incidence of SSI was 12.5% (95% CI 2.7% </p>

<p>to 32.4%) in the cephalexin group compared with 
35.7% (95% CI 18.6% to 55.9%) in the placebo group 
( p=0.064). This represented an absolute reduction of 
23.21% (95% CI −0.39% to 46.82%), relative 
reduction of 65.00% (95% CI −12.70% to 89.13%) 
and number-needed-to-treat of 4.3. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Administration of a single 2 g dose of </p>

<p>cephalexin 30-60 min before skin lesion excision from 
the lower limb may produce a reduction in the 
incidence of infection; however, this study was 
underpowered to statistically determine this. </p>

<p>workload, and this proportion is even greater 
for Queensland GPs, given that this State has 
the highest incidence of skin cancer. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>General practice dermatological surgery may 
differ from a hospital setting, with most pro-
cedures taking place in treatment rooms 
rather than in formal operating theatres. 
Surgical site infection (SSI) is one of the 
few complications of this relatively minor 
surgery. These infections often require anti-
biotics and repeat consultations to assess 
wound healing. They can potentially lead to 
significant bacteraemic complications and 
impair cosmetic outcome. 
7 The acceptable 
rate of infection following clean minor 
surgery (class 1) is less than 5%. 
8-12 This is 
reflected in skin lesion excisions, with a rate 
of between 1% and 3% in most studies. </p>

<p>13-18 </p>

<p>The exceptions are studies conducted by the 
present authors in 2005 and 2009 which 
reported infection rates of 8.6% and 
11.7%. 
19 20 The reason for this higher infec-
tion rate remains unclear, but might be 
related to tropical humidity. Even within 
cohorts with a low overall incidence of infec-
tion, some procedures may be at higher risk 
because of the body site, pathology or 
patient factors and infection rates may be 
greater than 5% in these high-risk groups. 
Previously identified risk factors include </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ Blinded randomised design with placebo control. 
▪ Standardised protocol for excision and follow-up. 
▪ Collection of a large amount of demographic, 
medical and excision-related data for comparison 
of groups. 
▪ Underpowered study due to small sample size. 
▪ Higher than anticipated infection rate with no 
clear underlying reason. </p>

<p>Smith SC, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005270. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005270 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>excisions from the region of the lower leg, ear and 
nose, 
16 20-22 excisions of skin cancers 
20 21 and excisions 
from patients with diabetes. 
20 In tropical North 
Queensland, the infection rates following excisions from 
the lower limb ranged from 14.75% to 18.18%. </p>

<p>19 20 </p>

<p>Several expert groups-including the Mayo Clinic's 
Department of Dermatological Surgery 
7 23 24 -have sug-
gested that a single oral dose of perioperative antibiotic 
prophylaxis may be indicated in certain 'high risk' situa-
tions such as excisions from the lower limb. If effective, 
this may be a low-cost and easily implemented method 
of reducing the incidence of SSI in selected situations. 
Recommendations such as these are however yet to be 
tested in clinical trials. 
This trial sought to determine the efficacy of a 2 g 
dose of cephalexin given 30-60 min prior to skin lesion 
excision from the lower limb in preventing the subse-
quent development of an SSI. </p>

<p>METHODOLOGY 
Trial design 
We carried out a randomised double-blind placebo-
controlled trial involving patients presenting for minor 
skin excisions from the lower limb. </p>

<p>Setting and participants 
The study was conducted in two private general practices 
in Mackay, Queensland (latitude 21E8S; inhabitants 
77 293 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>) between September 2011 and May 2012. One of 
the participating practices was an open access designated 
skin cancer clinic which was run by two GPs specialising in 
skin cancer management. The other centre offered a full 
range of primary care services and all doctors working at 
the practice were involved in the study. 
Consecutive patients presenting at either practice for a 
skin lesion excision from the lower limb were invited to 
participate. Exclusion criteria are shown in box 1. For 
patients having multiple excisions meeting inclusion cri-
teria on the same or subsequent days, data were only 
analysed for the first excision conducted which met the 
inclusion criteria. 
Demographic information was collected as well as clin-
ical information about diabetes, anticoagulation and any </p>

<p>other predetermined significant medical conditions. A 
body site map was used to record the excision site. At 
the end of the study, practice nurses were asked to 
re-examine computer records to fill in any missing data. 
The principal researcher visited participating GPs and 
practice nurses prior to the start of and regularly during 
the trial to ensure that data collection was standardised. </p>

<p>Intervention and control 
The intervention arm of the trial consisted of a 2 g dose 
of cephalexin administered 30-60 min before an exci-
sion. The cephalexin (Keflex 500 mg capsules)was com-
pounded into generic gel capsules (SurgiPack Empty 
Gelatine Capsules, Size '00', 0.95 mL capacity). Rice 
flour was used to fill the placebo capsules as it had an 
identical appearance to the cephalexin powder and no 
foreseeable adverse effects. Each dose consisted of four 
capsules filled with either cephalexin or rice flour. </p>

<p>Randomisation and blinding 
A computer-generated random number table was used 
to randomise a consecutive sequence of numbers into 
two groups-intervention and control-in permuted 
blocks of 20 with a 1:1 ratio. These numbers were used 
to label medicine jars containing the corresponding cap-
sules. The content of the individual jar was known only 
to the principal researcher who had no direct involve-
ment with participants or in data collection. All others 
involved in the trial were blinded to the capsule identity. </p>

<p>Participant recruitment and trial protocol 
Eligible participants were identified by a practice nurse 
or doctor at the time of their pre-excision appointment. 
All patients provided signed consent before enrolling in 
the study. Participants were given a numbered medicine 
jar along with written and verbal instructions to take the 
four capsules 30-60 min before their excision 
appointment. </p>

<p>Surgical wound management protocol 
Workshops were run at the participating practices to 
develop guidelines to ensure that excision management 
was standardised. The excision was performed using an 
aseptic technique and skin preparation with 2% chlorhexi-
dine solution. Wounds were dressed with non-waterproof 
adhesive fabric dressings. Patients were provided with 
verbal and written instructions regarding wound care, 
including the need for wounds to be kept dry and covered 
for the first 2 days and for topical antiseptics or antibiotics 
not to be used. Time to removal of sutures (ROS) was 12-
16 days at the treating doctor's discretion. </p>

<p>Outcome measures 
Wounds were assessed for infection by the practice nurse 
or doctor at the time of ROS, or sooner if patients 
re-presented earlier with a perceived infection. Our def-
inition of SSI was based on the presence of any of the 
criteria shown in box 2. These were adapted from the </p>

<p>Box 1 Exclusion criteria for participant recruitment </p>

<p>&lt;18 years old or not capable of providing informed consent. 
Declined to participate. 
Currently taking antibiotics or treating clinician feels they are clin-
ically indicated for antibiotic treatment following excision. 
Repair of lacerations or lesions considered as contaminated/ 
infected prior to surgery. 
Excision not utilising primary closure (eg, shave biopsy or 
curette). 
Excision of a sebaceous cyst. 
Patient unable to return for suture removal. 
Penicillin or cephalosporin allergy. </p>



<p>Smith SC, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005270. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005270 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Centre for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) defin-
ition for superficial SSI. 
26 Information was also collected 
on wound swabs performed, prescription of antibiotics 
and number of follow-up visits. Patients were asked 
about any adverse effects which could be attributed to 
the trial medication. </p>

<p>Sample size 
Our sample size was calculated on the basis of previous 
studies 
19 20 which predicted a baseline infection rate of 
15% from the lower limb. We decided that an absolute 
reduction in the SSI rate of 10% or more would be clin-
ically significant. To reach this conclusion with statistical 
confidence ( power 80%, α error 5%), it was calculated 
that a sample size of 282 excisions would be required. 
The trial was conducted as part of an honours 
research project which ran over a 2-year period. The 
decision was made to cease data collection once the 
desired sample size of 282 was collected or by May 2012 
to allow time for completion of the honours thesis. </p>

<p>Statistical methods 
Data were entered and stored in a Microsoft Access data-
base and statistical analysis and tests conducted in <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs> 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS Statistics</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.20</rs>. Numeric data were summarised 
using median values and IQRs. Categorical variables </p>

<p>were reported as proportions with Clopper-Pearson 95% 
CIs calculated for incidence of infection. 
Fisher's exact test was used to test the primary hypoth-
esis; absolute and relative risk reductions were calculated 
with 95% CIs as well as the number-needed-to-treat 
(NNT). Comparison of other infection-related para-
meters, such as prescription of antibiotics and number 
of additional visits, was conducted with Fisher's exact 
test and Mann-Whitney U tests, respectively. 
No provisions were made for an interim analysis as it 
was felt that there was low risk of potential harm. </p>

<p>Ethics approval and trial registration 
The trial was registered on the Australian New Zealand 
Clinical Trials Registry (ACTRN: 12611000595910) prior 
to its start. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Of a total of 78 excisions from the lower limb conducted 
during the collection period, 26 cases were excluded 
from the study (figure 1). Fifty-two cases were subse-
quently randomised and underwent skin lesion excision. 
Three participants forgot to take the trial medication 
prior to their excision, and one participant treated his 
wound with a topical antiseptic. Follow-up was com-
pleted in all 52 (100%) participants randomised. Six 
doctors across the two practices were involved, each 
recruiting between 3 and 18 patients. </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics 
Comorbid conditions (excluding diabetes) were more 
common among those cases randomised to the cepha-
lexin group compared with placebo (87.5% vs 67.9%) 
and antihypertensive use was also higher (70.8% vs </p>

<p>Box 2 Criteria for presence of a surgical site infection* </p>

<p>Purulent discharge. 
Erythema &gt;1 cm from the wound margin. 
Localised swelling. 
Patient reports increased tenderness at the wound site. 
Patient reports increased heat at the wound site. 
*Presence of any one or more of these criteria was deemed to 
represent the presence of a surgical site infection. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Trial profile (ROS, 
removal of sutures). </p>

<p>Smith SC, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005270. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005270 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>50%). The median excision size was 6 mm smaller in 
the cephalexin group (table 1). </p>

<p>Outcome measures and estimates 
The primary intention-to-treat analysis was conducted on 
all 52 cases which were randomised and in which the 
excision was performed (table 2). A secondary per 
protocol analysis was also performed that examined only 
cases where patients took their allocated trial medication 
and did not violate trial protocol (table 3). 
In the intention-to-treat analysis, the incidence of SSI 
in the intervention group was 12.5% (3/24) compared 
with 35.7% (10/28) in the control group. This 
approached statistical significance ( p=0.064), producing 
an absolute reduction of 23.21% (95% CI −0.39% to 
46.82%), relative reduction of 65.00% (95% CI −12.70% 
to 89.13%) and an NNT of 4.3. 
There were also clinically relevant reductions in anti-
biotic prescriptions and follow-up visits. These were also 
not of statistical significance (table 2). </p>

<p>In the per protocol analysis, the difference in incidence 
of infection was statistically significant (8.7% (2/23) vs 
36% (9/25); p=0.039). The relative risk reduction for an 
SSI produced by prophylaxis was 75.85% (95% CI −0.30% 
to 94.18%), resulting in an absolute risk reduction of 
27.30% (95% CI −3.50% to 51.10%) and an NNT of 3.7. 
No adverse effects attributed to the trial medication 
were reported by participants. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
In this trial, a 2 g dose of cephalexin 30-60 min before 
skin lesion excision from the lower limb was associated 
with a relative reduction in infection rate of 65% and an 
absolute reduction of 23.2% from a baseline infection 
rate of 35.7-12.5%. Based on these findings, the NNT 
with prophylactic cephalexin was 4.31 in order to 
prevent one infection following excision from the lower 
limb. Additionally, prophylaxis resulted in a reduction in 
the number of therapeutic antibiotic courses required 
and number of follow-up visits. </p>

<p>Table 1 Baseline characteristics* </p>

<p>Cephalexin (n=24) 
Placebo (n=28) </p>

<p>Age (years) 
69.5 [61.25-78.75] 
69.5 [59.25-75.75] 
Male 
54.2 (13) 
53.6 (15) 
Occupation 
Retired 
58.3 (14) 
60.7 (17) 
Unemployed 
0 (0) 
10.7 (3) 
Working 
41.7 (10) 
28.6 (8) 
Smoking status 
Current smoker 
8.3 (2) 
7.1 (2) 
Ex-smoker 
50 (12) 
35.7 (10) 
Never smoked 
41.7 (10) 
57.1 (16) 
Alcohol consumption 
Non-drinker 
45.8 (11) 
32.1 (9) 
Occasional (&lt;1 day/week) 
16.7 (4) 
21.4 (6) 
Weekly 
37.5 (9) 
39.3 (11) 
Comorbid conditions † 
87.5 (21) 
67.9 (19) 
Diabetes 
25.0 (6) 
21.4 (6) 
Anticoagulant use ‡ 
29.2 (7) 
25 (7) 
Antihypertensive use 
70.8 (17) 
50.0 (14) 
Time from pill consumption to excision (min) 
61.5 [50-75] 
60 [48.25-65.75] 
Below knee 
83.3 (20) 
82.1 (23) 
Excision size (mm) 
22.5 [17.25-31.75] 
28.5 [22-36] 
Type of repair 
Simple closure 
45.8 (11) 
60.7 (17) 
Two-layer closure 
50 (12) 
32.1 (9) 
Skin flaps 
4.2 (1) 
7.1 (2) 
Histology 
NMSC 
75.0 (18) 
75.0 (21) 
Melanoma 
4.2 (1) 
3.6 (1) 
Other benign 
21.4 (6) 
29.2 (7) </p>

<p>*Data are median [IQR] or percentage (number). 
 †Comorbid conditions included; cephalexin group: hypertension (n=15), COPD 3, regular oral steroids (n=0), regular inhaled steroids (n=0), 
PVD (n=1), IHD (n=0) current cancer (n=0), other (n=12); placebo group: hypertension (n=11), COPD 1, regular oral steroids (n=0), regular 
inhaled steroids (n=1), PVD (n=0), IHD (n=1) current cancer (n=0), other (n=14). 
 ‡Cephalexin group: aspirin (n=7), clopidogrel (n=0) and/or warfarin (n=1); placebo group: aspirin (n=5), clopidogrel (n=1) and/or warfarin 
(n=1). 
COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; IHD, ischaemic heart disease; NMSC, non-melanomatous skin cancers; PVD, peripheral 
vascular disease. </p>



<p>Smith SC, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005270. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005270 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Limitations 
Although these findings met our predetermined level 
for clinical relevance, an absolute reduction of infection 
rate by 10%, they were not statistically significant 
( p=0.064). Furthermore, a slower than predicted recruit-
ment rate, and time constraints of the honours research 
project, resulted in the trial being terminated well 
before the calculated sample size was achieved. As such, 
this trial was unable to address the proposed hypothesis 
and no definitive conclusions can be drawn from it on 
the actual efficacy of antibiotic prophylaxis. 
Various characteristics influence SSI and although 
information on as many variables as possible was 
recorded, it is difficult to ensure that all baseline data 
are comparable. Several characteristics did vary notably 
between the prophylaxis and placebo groups in this 
study. Given that the study was underpowered and did 
not achieve statistical significance, it was decided not to 
pursue adjustment for these imbalances using multiple 
logistic regression. Future studies, appropriately powered 
to address this hypothesis, will need to adjust for such 
baseline difference as well as consider cluster analysis 
based on individual GPs to limit the confounding effect 
on variable training, experience and outcomes among 
practitioners. </p>

<p>Even when using guidelines, the diagnosis of infection 
is still subjective and there may be interobserver and 
intraobserver variation. 
27 The 1992 CDC definition of 
SSI that we chose to use has limitations. However, it is 
the most widely implemented standard definition of 
wound infection 
27 and is the closest to a gold standard 
available. We have no evidence to support intrapractice 
and interpractice reproducibility of measurement and 
recording procedures. This is also an area which future 
studies may consider addressing. </p>

<p>Generalisability 
The baseline infection rate for lower limb excisions in 
this trial was considerably higher than that reported 
in other studies, including those previously conducted 
in Mackay. 
19 20 The underlying reason for this is uncer-
tain, but may be related to the majority of the excisions 
being from below the knee, a site that has previously 
been identified as being at an even higher risk of infec-
tion. Furthermore, the infection rate in studies con-
ducted in Mackay has consistently been higher than that 
reported in other centres. This further adds to the argu-
ment that climate/environmental factors may be import-
ant determinants of SSI following skin lesion excision. 
Owing to the higher than expected infection rate, there </p>

<p>Table 2 Primary and secondary outcome measures intention-to-treat analysis* </p>

<p>Cephalexin (n=24) 
Placebo (n=28) 
Risk difference (95% CI) 
p Value </p>

<p>Number of infections 
3 
10 
0.35 (0.11 to 1.13) 
0.064 
Infection rate (95% CI) 
12.5 (2.7 to 32.4) 
35.7 (18.6 to 55.9) 
NA 
Prescription of antibiotics 
3 
6 
0.58 (0.16 to 2.09) 
0.480 
Number of additional follow-up visits required 
Median 
0 [0-0] 
0 [0-1] 
NA 
0.164 
Total (Range) 
7 (0-3) 
26 (0-10) 
NA 
Additional total amount of antibiotics (excluding prophylaxis) (mg) † 
Median 
0 [0-0] 
0 [0-0] 
NA 
0.290 
Total (Range) 
27 000 (0-12 000) 
146 750 (0-66 750) 
NA </p>

<p>*Data are median (IQR) (range) or number (%) unless otherwise stated; 95% CI for infection rate are the Clopper-Pearson interval; p values 
are Fisher's exact test or the Mann-Whitney U test for categorical and continuous variables, respectively. 
 †Cephalexin group: cephalexin (15 000 mg), flucloxacillin (12 000 mg); placebo group: cephalexin (100 000 mg), flucloxacillin (24 000 mg); 
ciprofloxacin (14 000 mg), amoxicillin/clavulonic acid (8750 mg). 
NA, not applicable. </p>

<p>Table 3 Primary and secondary outcome measures per protocol analysis* </p>

<p>Cephalexin (n=23) 
Placebo (n=25) 
Risk difference (95% CI) 
p Value </p>

<p>Number of infections 
2 
9 
0.24 (0.06 to 1.00) 
0.039 
Infection rate (95% CI) 
8.7 (1.1 to 28.0) 
36.0 (18 to 57.5) 
NA 
Prescription of antibiotics 
2 (8.7%) 
6(24.0%) 
0.36 (0.08 to 1.62) 
0.249 
Number of additional follow-up visits required 
Median 
0 [0-0] 
0 [0-1] 
NA 
0.058 
Total 
5 
26 
NA </p>

<p>95% CI for infection rates are the Clopper-Pearson interval. 
*Data are median [IQR] or number (%) unless otherwise stated; 95% CI for infection rate are the Clopper-Pearson interval; p values are 
Fisher's exact test or the Mann-Whitney U test for categorical and continuous variables, respectively. 
NA, not available. </p>

<p>Smith SC, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005270. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005270 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>may be limitations to extrapolating these results to other 
centres, where the baseline infection is lower. However, 
similar relative reductions have been produced with 
prophylactic regimens, including single dose parenteral 
antibiotics, in settings with lower baseline infection rates 
(table 4). 
Antibiotic prophylaxis is probably prescribed exces-
sively or inappropriately for dermatological surgery and 
is thought to be best reserved for high-risk patients such 
as excisions from the lower limb. 
7 23 24 There are no 
data available on the current prescribing habits of 
Australian GPs regarding oral prophylaxis for minor 
excisions. The decision to prescribe antibiotic prophy-
laxis is complicated; in addition to efficacy, antibiotic 
costs, adverse effects and resistance must also be taken 
into account. 
The role of antibiotic prophylaxis in the prevention of 
SSI following skin lesion excision remains controver-
sial. 
32 Randomised trials have demonstrated that topical 
antibiotic prophylaxis is ineffective and should not be 
used. 
33 34 Infusion of antibiotic mixed with local </p>

<p>anaesthetic, and systemic prophylactic regimes, have pro-
duced significant reductions in infection rates. </p>

<p>31 29 35 36 </p>

<p>The limited available literature has demonstrated 
comparable relative reductions in SSI to this study 
(table 4). 
28-31 Two of these studies examined the use of 
oral prophylaxis 
28 30 while the other two considerably 
larger studies examined various regimens of intramuscu-
lar cefazolin. 
31 29 With the exception of Amland et al </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>and one arm of the 1994 study by Bencini et al, 
29 all of 
these studies examined short courses of prophylaxis 
rather than single doses. Although variations in the 
study populations and protocols make comparison diffi-
cult, the reductions achieved in this study appear to be 
at least similar to those achieved with short courses of 
prophylaxis and parenteral methods of delivery. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
In this study, a 2 g dose of cephalexin 30-60 min before 
skin lesion excisions from the lower limb was associated 
with a reduced risk of SSI from 35.7% to 12.5%, </p>

<p>Table 4 Studies of systemic antibiotic prophylaxis for skin lesion excision </p>

<p>Study, 
country </p>

<p>Setting and 
sample size 
Intervention and control 
Wound type </p>

<p>Infection rate 
(relative reduction) </p>

<p>Amland 
et al, </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>Norway </p>

<p>Plastic surgery 
unit, 60 patients </p>

<p>Control: placebo 
Intervention: single dose 1000 mg 
orally azithromycin the night before 
surgery </p>

<p>Skin cancer surgery 
Control: 16.0% 
Azithromycin: 5.7% 
(0.36) </p>

<p>Bencini 
et al, 
29 Italy </p>

<p>Outpatient 
dermatologic 
surgery unit, 
527 patients </p>

<p>A: no prophylaxis 
B: 1 g intramuscular cefazolin 12 
hourly for 48 h before and after 
surgery 
C: 1 g intramuscular cefazolin 12 
hourly from 2 h before surgery to 24 h 
after 
D: single 1 g intramuscular dose 
cefazolin 2 h before surgery </p>

<p>Excisions from 
contamination-prone areas 
(groin, axillae, interdigital 
spaces of feet) </p>

<p>A: 12% 
B: 4.6% (0.38)* 
C: 0.77% (0.064)* 
D: 2% (0.17)* </p>

<p>Czarnecki 
et al, </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Australia </p>

<p>Outpatient 
dermatology 
clinic, 
97 lesions </p>

<p>Intervention 1: 500 mg orally 
cephalexin three times a day, starting 
2 days before and continuing 24 h 
postoperatively 
Intervention 2: topical mupirocin three 
times a day from 2 days before and 
continuing 24 h postoperatively 
Control: cetrimide-chlorhexidine cream 
2 days before and continuing 24 h 
postoperatively </p>

<p>Ulcerated skin cancers which 
cultured positive for 
Staphylococcus aureus or 
Gram-negative bacteria </p>

<p>Control: 21.7% 
Intervention 
1: 2.7% (0.12)* 
Intervention 
2: 0% (0)* </p>

<p>Bencini 
et al, 
31 Italy </p>

<p>Outpatient 
dermatologic 
surgery unit, 
2165 patients </p>

<p>A: no antibiotic 
B: 1 g intramuscular cefazolin 12 
hourly immediately after surgery 
continuing for 3 days 
C: 250 mg cefazolin powder applied 
locally during surgery 
D: 1 g cefazolin intramuscular 12 
hourly starting 2 days before and 
continuing 2 days after surgery </p>

<p>Excision of skin lesions 
A: 4.3% 
B: 1.5% (0.35)* 
C: 0.9% (0.21)* 
D: 0.2% (0.047)* </p>

<p>*Statistically significant reduction compared to control. </p>



<p>Smith SC, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005270. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005270 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>producing an absolute reduction of 23.2%, a relative 
reduction of 65% and an NNT of 4.3. This reduction, 
however, was not statistically significant ( p=0.064), and 
the trial was underpowered to address the hypothesis. As 
such, no definitive conclusion can be drawn on the effi-
cacy of oral prophylaxis for lower limb skin lesion exci-
sion from this trial. Given the potential benefits, further 
investigation is warranted. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors thank Ms Laurie, Ms Robyn Cavanagh, Ms 
Debbie Kimber, Ms Tracy Maloney, Ms Julie O'Sullivan, Ms Catherine Weiske, 
Dr Sheldon Browning, Dr Andrea Cosgrove, Dr AllisonDischer, Dr Luke Notely, 
Dr O'Neill, Dr Lutie Van den Berg and PHCRED Townsville. </p>

<p>Contributors SCS established and oversaw the study design and 
implementation, compiled the data and conducted the primary analysis. CFH 
conceived the study idea, identified suitable practices and assisted in study 
design and analysis. PGB assisted in sample size calculation and study 
analysis. All authors contributed to manuscript production. </p>

<p>Funding This study was funded jointly through funds available from the 
James Cook University Honours programme and CFH's University Research 
account and through general funds available to CFH from the Primary Health 
Care Research and Information Service for primary care research in Mackay. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval James Cook University Human Research Ethics Committee. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement Extra data can be accessed via the Dryad data 
repository at http://datadryad.org/ with the doi:10.5061/dryad.k3r47. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>



<p>Smith SC, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005270. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005270 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>