<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4242897" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: We performed this analysis to distinguish the differences in two subtypes of lung 
invasive mucinous adenocarcinoma (IMA) with different kinds of morphological performances, 
in clinicopathological and molecular features, as well as prognosis. 
Methods: On the basis of morphological performance, we divided lung IMAs into two 
subgroups, mucus-in-cell adenocarcinoma (MICA) and mucus-out-of-cell adenocarcinoma 
(MOCA). We investigated differences in clinicopathological characteristics, recurrence-free 
survival (RFS), overall survival (OS), and a spectrum of well-identified driver-gene mutations, 
including EGFR, KRAS, HER2, BRAF, ALK, ROS1, and RET, between the two subgroups. 
Results: Of 1,699 lung adenocarcinomas, 148 were identified as IMAs (97 MICAs and 
51 MOCAs). The MICA patient group had significantly better RFS than did the MOCA group 
(39.4 months versus 33.0 months, respectively, log rank P=0.020) and significantly better OS 
(54.2 months versus 45.1 months, log rank P=0.034). There were no differences in RFS and 
OS between those with IMAs and those with mucus-negative adenocarcinomas. The frequency 
of the EGFR gene mutation was significantly higher in MOCAs than in MICAs (P,0.001). In 
contrast, the KRAS gene had a significantly higher mutational frequency in MICAs (P=0.01). 
MOCAs also had a significantly higher incidence of lymph-node metastasis (P,0.05). 
Conclusion: To our knowledge, this study represents the first comparison of clinical features, 
molecular alterations, and prognosis in morphological subgroups of lung IMAs. Clinical and 
pathological features in conjunction with molecular data indicate that IMA should be divided 
into different subgroups. 
Non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC) is the leading cause of cancer-related death 
worldwide. 
1 The most common pathological subtype of diagnosed NSCLC is adeno-
carcinoma, which has an increasing prevalence. A new classification for lung adeno-
carcinoma was proposed by an international multidisciplinary expert panel from 
International Association for the Study of Lung Cancer/American Thoracic Society/ 
European Respiratory Society (IASLC/ATS/ERS) in 2011, 
2 while the definition of 
mucinous bronchioloalveolar carcinoma is no longer used. Invasive mucinous adeno-
carcinoma (IMA) was recognized as a separate subtype of lung adenocarcinoma, which 
was supposed to contain components of columnar or goblet cells with abundant intra-
cellular or extracellular mucus admixed with invasive adenocarcinoma patterns with </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
18 November 2014 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2014:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2128 </p>

<p>Cai et al </p>

<p>stromal invasion. Compared with other lung adenocarcinoma 
subtypes, IMA has different immunohistochemical and 
molecular features, as well as a different prognosis. </p>

<p>3-5 </p>

<p>Mucinous adenocarcinoma occurs in various organs and 
has two main kinds of histological appearance. In one, the 
tumor is composed of columnar or goblet cells with abundant 
intracellular mucus accumulation; in the other, the tumor 
has abundant extracellular mucus admixed with invasive 
adenocarcinoma patterns with stromal invasion. IMAs occur-
ring in lung also share the above two kinds of histological 
appearance. We performed this retrospective study on sur-
gically resected lung IMAs, with the aim to distinguish the 
differences in clinicopathological feature, molecular features, 
and prognosis between IMAs subgroups with these two kinds 
of morphological performance. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Patients and specimens </p>

<p>From October 2007 to April 2013, patients with newly 
diagnosed primary lung cancer were consecutively enrolled. 
Inclusion criteria for this study included: 1) patients under-
went complete resection of the primary lesion; 2) pathological 
diagnosis of adenocarcinoma was reconfirmed by two pathol-
ogists (L Shen and Y Li); and 3) samples had a minimum of 
50% tumor cells and sufficient corresponding normal tissue 
for mutational analysis. Patients who received any neoadju-
vant chemotherapy or radiotherapy were excluded. Written 
informed consent was acquired from all the enrolled patients. 
This study was approved by our institutional review board. </p>

<p>Clinical and pathological characteristics </p>

<p>Clinicopathological data were collected for analyses of the 
association with IMA subtypes. Sex, smoking history, age at 
diagnosis, pathological cancer stage, histological type, and 
tumor differentiation were included. If a diagnosis of lung 
adenocarcinoma was made, histological subtypes according 
to the new IASLC/ATS/ERS multidisciplinary classification 
were collected. 
2 The abbreviation "MICA" was used to rep-
resent mucus-in-cell adenocarcinoma, while "MOCA" was 
used to define mucus-out-of-cell adenocarcinoma (Figure 1A, 
MICA; Figure 1B, MOCA). Tumors in which .50% of cells 
contained abundant intracytoplasmic mucus were considered 
to be MICA, whereas tumors with few cells having intra-
cytoplasmic mucus but with abundant extracellular mucus 
admixed with invasive adenocarcinoma patterns were consid-
ered to be MOCA. Lung adenocarcinoma without a mucinous 
component was defined as "mucus-negative". Patients were 
interviewed every 3 months after the date of diagnosis, either </p>

<p>in the clinic or by telephone, about disease recurrence and 
survival information. Recurrence-free survival (RFS) was 
calculated from the date of diagnosis to the date of recurrence 
or last-time follow-up. Overall survival (OS) was defined as 
the time elapsed between date of diagnosis to date of cancer-
related death or last-time follow-up. </p>

<p>Mutation and gene-fusion analysis </p>

<p>After the surgery, tissue samples were divided into two 
parts. One part was fixed using formalin and embedded 
with paraffin to make a pathological section; the other part 
was snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen at the time of resection 
and stored in liquid nitrogen. RNA and DNA were extracted 
from tumors, and distant histological normal lung after frozen 
specimens were dissected into TRIZOL (Life Technologies, 
CA, USA). Total RNA samples were reverse transcribed into 
complementary DNA. 
EGFR (exons 18-21), KRAS (exons 2-3), HER2 (exons 
18-21), BRAF (exons 11-15), PIK3CA (exons 9 and 20) 
were amplified by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using 
complementary DNA. Amplified products were assessed 
using the Sanger direct-sequencing method 
6 in forward and 
reverse directions to detect mutations. All mutations were 
verified by analysis of an independent PCR isolate. 
7 A com-
bined strategy of quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) 
and reverse-transcriptase PCR (RT-PCR) was performed to 
assess ALK, ROS1, and RET fusion, with validation using 
fluorescent in situ hybridization. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>We adopted Pearson χ 
2 test or Fisher's exact test to assess 
the correlations between clinicopathological variables 
and IMA subtypes. Survival curves were made using the 
Kaplan-Meier method. Recurrence-free survival and overall 
survival were compared using log-rank test. Cox regression 
was performed to assess the effect of clinicopathological 
characteristics, including IMA subtypes, upon survival. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Different morphological appearances of lung invasive adenocarcinoma. 
Notes: (A) Mucus-in-cell adenocarcinoma (.50% of tumor cells with 
abundant intracytoplasmic mucus; 10*10 magnification). (B) Mucus-out-of-cell 
adenocarcinoma (tumor cells with abundant extracellular mucus admixed with 
invasive adenocarcinoma patterns; 10×10 magnification). </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2014:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2129 </p>

<p>Subgroups of lung invasive mucinous adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>The statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">16.0</rs> for 
Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). All the tests were 
two-tailed, and statistical significance was set as P,0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Of 1,699 lung adenocarcinomas, 148 tumors turned out to 
be IMAs; of these, 97 were MICAs and 51 were MOCAs. 
There were 73 women and 75 men in this group, ranging in 
age at diagnosis from 23-84 years of age (median, 60 years). 
Nonsmokers comprised 67.6% (100 of 148) of patients. The 
number of patients with pathological stage I, II, and III cancer 
was 90, 22, and 36, respectively (Table 1). 
Through further comparison of the clinicopathological 
features between MICA and MOCA, we found that MOCAs 
had a significantly higher incidence of lymph-node metastasis 
(26.8% versus 43.1%, P,0.05). There was no significant dif-
ference between the two categories in sex or age at diagnosis, 
nor in smoking history. The morphological performance </p>

<p>of mucus was not significantly correlated with tumor size, 
pathological stage, or lymphovascular invasion (Table 1). 
In the 148 IMA cases, we detected 45 (30.4%) EGFR 
mutations, 25 (16.9%) KRAS mutations, nine (6.1%) HER2 
mutations, and two BRAF (1.3%) mutations. We also found 
20 (13.5%) ALK fusions, six (4.1%) RET fusions, and three 
(2.0%) ROS1 fusions. All of these molecular alterations were 
mutually exclusive. Further, 27 (18.2%) MICA and 11 (7.4%) 
MOCA harbored none of the above molecular changes. The 
frequency of EGFR gene mutation was significantly higher in 
MOCAs than in MICAs (49.1% versus 20.6%, P,0.001). In 
contrast, the KRAS gene had a significantly higher mutational 
frequency in MICAs (22.7% versus 5.9%, P=0.01). The fre-
quency of other well-identified driver-gene mutations did not 
significantly vary with different morphological performance 
of mucus (Table 1). 
We further compared the clinical outcomes between 79 
IMA and 439 consecutive mucus-negative lung adenocar-
cinomas, all of which were diagnosed from October 2007 
to October 2011. We analyzed RFS and OS data from these 
two subgroups of patients. The median follow-up phase 
for the IMA group was 43.6 months and for the mucus-
negative group was 48.5 months. The RFS and OS were not 
significantly different between IMA and mucus-negative 
lung adenocarcinoma groups (RFS: 37.2 months versus 38.8 
months, respectively, log-rank P=0.524; OS: 49.5 months 
versus 63.5 months, respectively, log-rank P=0.650; Figure 
2A and B). When IMAs were divided into MICA and MOCA 
subgroups and compared with the mucus-negative group, 
survival data showed a trend of difference between the three 
groups, but the results failed to reach statistical significance 
(RFS: MICA versus mucus-negative, log-rank P=0.189; 
RFS: MOCA versus mucus-negative, log-rank P=0.648; 
OS: MICA versus mucus-negative, log-rank P=0.312; OS: 
MOCA versus mucus-negative, log-rank P=0.106; Figure 
2C and D). 
We then compared clinical outcomes between 38 MICAs 
and 41 MOCAs. Median follow-up time for the MICA group 
was 39.6 months and for the MOCA group was 41.5 months. 
Compared with the MICA group, the MOCA group had 
significantly worse RFS (39.4 months versus 33.0 months, 
respectively, log-rank P=0.020) and OS (54.2 months 
versus 45.1 months, respectively, log-rank P=0.034) 
(Figure 2C and D). Smoking history was also correlated 
with worse RFS (31.4 months versus 39.9 months, respec-
tively, log-rank P=0.021) in IMAs, but no significant differ-
ences were found in OS (47.9 months versus 50.6 months, 
respectively, log-rank P=0.47). Lymph node metastasis also </p>

<p>Table 1 Clinicopathological and molecular features of mucus-in-
cell adenocarcinoma and mucus-out-of-cell adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>Variables 
MICA (n=97) 
MOCA (n=51) 
P-value </p>

<p>Sex 
Male 
45 
30 
0.151 
Female 
52 
21 
Age, years 
$60 
48 
25 
0.957 </p>

<p>,59 
49 
26 
Smoking history 
Smoker 
27 
21 
0.099 
Never 
70 
30 
Tumor size 
#3 cm 
62 
28 
0.286 </p>

<p>.3 cm 
35 
23 
Cancer stage 
I/II 
76 
36 
0.296 
III 
21 
15 
Lymphovascular invasion 
+ 
17 
10 
0.099 </p>

<p>-
80 
41 
Lymph node metastasis 
N0 
71 
29 
0.044 
N1-N3 
26 
22 
Mutational status 
EGFR mutation 
20 
25 
,0.001 
KRAS mutation 
22 
3 
0.01 
HER2 mutation 
5 
4 
0.515 
BRAF mutation 
2 
0 
0.302 
ALK fusion 
16 
4 
0.206 
ROS1 fusion 
2 
1 
0.999 
RET fusion 
3 
3 
0.415 
Pan-negative 
27 
11 
0.407 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: MICA, mucus-in-cell adenocarcinoma; MOCA, mucus-out-of-cell 
adenocarcinoma. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2014:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2130 </p>

<p>Cai et al </p>

<p>predict worse RFS (31.6 months versus 41.0 months, log 
rank P=0.007) and OS (44.3 months versus 53.0 months, 
log rank P=0.018) in 79 IMAs. Age at diagnosis, sex, lym-
phovascular invasion, and driver-gene mutational status had 
no significant correlations with RFS and OS. Multivariate 
analysis of survival significance was also performed, with 
age at diagnosis, sex, smoking history, mucus pattern, lym-
phovascular invasion, lymph node metastasis, and EGFR 
gene mutational status included. Lymph-node metastasis 
was the only independent factor of RFS (odd ratio =3.24, 
95% confidence interval =1.32-4.76, P,0.01), but had no 
significance for predicting OS. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Since the appearance of the IASLC/ATS/ERS classification 
of lung adenocarcinoma in 2011, many studies have focused 
on the influence of pathological subtype on prognosis and 
molecular change. 
9-11 IMAs, which account for 2%-10% of 
lung adenocarcinoma cases in East Asia, Europe, and the 
United States, 
11-13 were considered to be more malignant 
than other common subtypes of lung adenocarcinoma, such 
as lepidic and acinar subtypes. 
14 To our knowledge, this </p>

<p>is the first study to focus on the differences in prognosis 
and molecular alterations in IMA subgroups with different 
morphological features. Therefore, we performed this study 
to investigate if it is reasonable to divide invasive mucinous 
lung adenocarcinoma into separate parts. 
Some previous studies demonstrated that IMAs cor-
related with worse prognosis. 
4,15 However, in some recent 
studies, IMA subtype failed to reach statistical significance 
as a worse prognosis predictor. 
16 Considering this discrep-
ancy on the predictive value of IMA subtype on prognosis, 
we performed survival analysis between IMA patients and 
mucus-negative patients. Our results indicated that the IMA 
patients did not have a worse prognosis than mucus-negative 
patients do. Dividing IMAs into two subgroups by different 
morphological performance and comparing all groups, we 
found that patients with MICA showed a potential trend of 
better prognosis than did mucus-negative patients, while 
MOCAs seemed to have the worst prognosis of all three 
subgroups. Our results indicated that IMA subtype alone may 
not be an adequate predictor for worse prognosis. Different 
morphological performances may have potential predictive 
value on clinical outcome. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>Recurrence-free survival </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>Months </p>

<p>IMAs </p>

<p>IMAs censored </p>

<p>Mucus-negative </p>

<p>Mucus-negative censored </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>Overall survival </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>Months </p>

<p>IMAs </p>

<p>IMAs censored </p>

<p>Mucus-negative </p>

<p>Mucus-negative censored </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>Recurrence-free survival </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0 
2 0 
4 0 </p>

<p>Months </p>

<p>60 
80 </p>

<p>MICAs </p>

<p>Mucus-negative </p>

<p>Mucus-negative censored </p>

<p>MOCAs </p>

<p>MICAs censored 
MOCAs censored </p>

<p>MICAs </p>

<p>Mucus-negative </p>

<p>Mucus-negative censored </p>

<p>MOCAs </p>

<p>MICAs censored 
MOCAs censored </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>Overall survival </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0 
2 0 
4 0 </p>

<p>Months </p>

<p>60 
80 
100 </p>

<p>0 
2 0 
4 0 
6 0 
8 0 
0 
2 0 
4 0 
6 0 
80 
100 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Recurrence-free and overall survival. 
Notes: (A) Recurrence-free survival of IMAs or mucus-negative adenocarcinomas. (B) Overall survival of IMAs or mucus-negative adenocarcinomas. (C) Recurrence-free 
survival of MICAs, MOCAs, or mucus-negative adenocarcinomas. (D) Overall survival of MICAs, MOCAs, or mucus-negative adenocarcinomas. 
Abbreviations: IMA, invasive mucinous adenocarcinoma; MICA, mucus-in-cell adenocarcinoma; MOCA, mucus-out-of-cell adenocarcinoma. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2014:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2131 </p>

<p>Subgroups of lung invasive mucinous adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>We also observed distinct prognoses between IMAs with 
different morphological performance. Patients with MICA 
had a better RFS and OS than did their counterparts with 
MOCA. Lymph-node metastasis also occurred more fre-
quently in patients with MOCA. To our knowledge, no simi-
lar study has revealed different clinical outcomes between 
invasive mucinous lung adenocarcinoma subgroups with 
different mucus distributions. Mucinous adenocarcinomas 
in other organs are also associated with lymph-node metas-
tasis and worse prognosis, 
17-20 and mucus is considered to 
play a critical role in the development of cancer. 
21 Thus, we 
suspect that the common phenomenon is related to the same 
mucinous component in different cancers. When the mucus 
is out of the cell, the tumor may have aggressive biological 
behavior. However, further study is needed to form a more 
reliable conclusion. 
Lung IMA was reported to be associated with higher fre-
quency of KRAS mutation and resistance to EGFR tyrosine 
kinase inhibitor. 
12,22,23 In our series, the frequency of EGFR 
and KRAS mutation was 30.4% and 16.9%, respectively. Also, 
a higher prevalence of ALK fusion was observed in IMAs than 
in unselected lung adenocarcinoma. 
24 We further analyzed 
the association between morphological feature and molecular 
alteration, finding that the frequency of EGFR mutation was 
remarkably higher in MOCAs than in MICAs and that KRAS 
mutation significantly prevailed in MICAs. These findings 
suggest that there is a distinct difference in molecular change 
in these two subgroups of IMA, and that MICAs and MOCAs 
are two different kinds of adenocarcinoma. Therefore, more 
accurate distinction is required to be made in IMAs. 
The weakness of our work was that this was a retrospec-
tive study. The clinical outcomes had limited significance, 
because some of these patients had different postoperative 
treatments. Meanwhile, a sample size of 148 patients was 
too small to prove the differences between IMA subgroups 
with different morphological features. This issue should be 
confirmed by further research with larger samples. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>We found various subtypes of lung IMAs. There are dis-
tinct morphological performances, driver-gene mutation 
distributions, and clinical outcomes in the two subgroups of 
patients. A more precise definition of IMA should be taken 
into consideration in the future. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors acknowledge financial support from the 
Key Construction Program of the National "985" Project </p>

<p>(Grant No 985III-YFX0102), the National Natural Science 
Foundation of China (Grants No 81172218 and 81101761), 
the Science and Technology Commission of Shanghai 
Municipality (Program of Shanghai Subject Chief Scientist; 
Grant No 12XD1402000), the Foundation of Shanghai Health 
Administration (Grant No 20114206), and the Shanghai Hos-
pital Development Center (Grant No SHDC12012308). The 
authors thanked Yuanshan Fu for language proofreading. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors declare that no benefits in any form have been 
received or will be received from a commercial party related 
directly or indirectly to the subject of this article. The authors 
report no other conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open access 
journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2014:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2132 </p>

<p>Cai et al </p>



</text></tei>