<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4860852" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective: As the population ages, the incidence of </p>

<p>heart valve disease (HVD) is increasing. The aim of 
treatment is to improve prognosis and quality of life. 
Standard surgical treatment is being superseded by 
new catheter-based treatments, many of which are as 
yet unproven. The need for appropriate instruments to 
measure quality of life in patients receiving treatment 
for HVD has therefore never been greater. </p>

<p>Methods: In this prospective observational study, a </p>

<p>generic instrument, Euroqol, and a disease-specific one 
(Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire-
MLHFQ) were, for the first time, formally tested before 
and after surgery in 84 patients with HVD who 
completed their treatment. Patients were interviewed on 
the night before surgery and 6-12 weeks after being 
discharged. Instruments were tested for validity, 
reliability, responsiveness, sensitivity and 
interpretability. </p>

<p>Results: Both Euroqol and MLHFQ registered </p>

<p>significant improvements in patients' health. Tests for 
validity were significantly positive for both Euroqol and 
MLHFQ. Tests for reliability and responsiveness were 
very positive for MLHFQ, less so for EQ-5D. There was 
a moderate ceiling effect in the postoperative Index 
scores of Euroqol and a moderate floor effect in 
MLHFQ. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Both instruments together performed </p>

<p>very well in assessing the health of patients 
undergoing surgical treatment of HVD. As the 
incidence of HVD increases and therapeutic options 
increase, measurement of PROMS using these two 
instruments should become a matter of routine. </p>

<p>with significant morbidity, which may limit its 
usefulness in the elderly patient. </p>

<p>1-3 </p>

<p>In recent years, a number of percutaneous 
catheter-based treatments have become avail-
able. As patients get older and associated 
morbidities increase, demand for these new 
costly treatments will also undoubtedly 
increase. The efficacy of many of these treat-
ments, however, remains unproven. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>The main objectives of any treatment of 
heart valve disease are to improve quality of 
life and survival. As the population ages and </p>

<p>KEY QUESTIONS </p>

<p>What is already known about this subject? </p>

<p>▸ The incidence of heart valve disease is increas-
ing as the population ages. 
▸ The need for percutaneous treatments of heart 
valve disease is likely to increase dramatically. 
▸ There are insufficient published data on quality 
of life assessment of the effect of heart valve 
disease and their treatments. 
▸ There are no published data on the formal 
assessment of Patient-Reported Outcome 
Measures (PROMS) instruments in this popula-
tion of patients. </p>

<p>What does this study add? </p>

<p>▸ Euroqol and Minnesota Living with Heart Failure 
Questionnaire (MLHFQ) perform very well as 
instruments for assessing quality of life in patients 
with heart valve disease undergoing surgery. </p>

<p>How might this impact on clinical practice? </p>

<p>▸ Commissioners paying for any treatment of 
patients with heart valve disease should insist 
that PROMS (specifically Euroqol and MLHFQ) 
should be measured routinely. 
▸ PROMs measurement with Euroqol and MLHFQ 
should be part of any publication looking at the 
effectiveness of treatments of patients with heart 
failure. </p>

<p>Holmes C, Briffa N. Open Heart 2016;3:e000315. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2015-000315 </p>



<p>Valvular heart disease </p>

<p>therapeutic options increase, the need for valid Quality 
of Life Questionnaires to assess and compare treatments 
of heart valve disease has never been greater. </p>

<p>1-3 </p>

<p>Patient-reported outcome measures (PROMs or PROs in 
the USA) are instruments used to measure quality of life. 
They are used to measure the impact illness has on patients' 
lives as well as the effect and efficacy of treatments. </p>

<p>5 6 </p>

<p>PROMs can be generic-assessing key aspects of the 
effect of general health-or disease-specific, assessing 
health-related quality of life in relation to a specific 
disease. 
5 7-12 Although PROMS in patients with heart 
valve disease have been measured as part of either a 
study of patients with heart failure 
14 or of patients 
undergoing heart surgery in general, the performance 
of PROMS instruments has never been formally evalu-
ated in this particular population of patients. </p>

<p>Objectives 
In this prospective observational clinical study, we have 
formally tested two PROMS instruments in patients 
undergoing surgery for specifically heart valve disease. 
The first is generic, EuroQol (EQ-5D), and the other 
disease-specific, Minnesota Living with Heart Failure 
Questionnaire (MLHFQ). </p>

<p>3 7 13-17 </p>

<p>METHODS 
PROMS instruments are formally evaluated for their use-
fulness within an intended population by measurement 
of their validity, reliability, responsiveness, sensitivity and 
interpretability. </p>

<p>9 18-20 </p>

<p>Validity is the ability of the questionnaire to accurately 
measure the intended outcome, that is, those who score 
poorly are indeed in poor health. Three different 
aspects of validity are measured: content, construct and 
criterion. 
Content validity refers to appropriateness and accept-
ability of the questions. 
Construct validity measures the ability of different 
domains of the questionnaire to differentiate between 
different levels of (ill) health and whether those in 
poorer health are scoring themselves appropriately. 
Criterion validity assesses whether the PROMS results 
correlate with previously accepted measures (concur-
rent) and how well PROMS scores can predict outcome 
after treatment ( predictive). </p>

<p>9 18-21 </p>

<p>Reliability: of a PROMS instrument measures the con-
sistency of the results if the questionnaire is repeated in 
the same population. This can be measured by test-
retest, that is, applying the test repeatedly in the same 
population whose health has not altered. If test-retest is 
not possible, internal consistency is assessed. This mea-
sures correlation between items that measures similar 
quality of life domains. A Cronbach's α (measure of 
internal consistency) of 0.7-0.9 is evidence of strong 
internal consistency and therefore reliability. </p>

<p>9 18-20 </p>

<p>Responsiveness: of a PROMS instrument assesses 
whether the instrument can detect changes over time </p>

<p>that matter to patients. It is measured using the Cohen 
effect size. A Cohen effect size of 0.8 or more is consid-
ered large. </p>

<p>9 18-20 22 </p>

<p>Interpretability: of an instrument is an assessment of 
whether the measured change is clinically significant 
and is specific to the condition and intervention being 
investigated. It is evaluated using the minimum clinically 
important difference (MCID). This is the smallest 
change in score associated with a significant improve-
ment in their health. </p>

<p>19 23 24 </p>

<p>Study design 
Prospective observational clinical study 
Study participants and setting 
Adults aged 18 years or older, who were scheduled to 
undergo heart valve surgery for a diagnosis of significant 
heart valves disease (stenosis, regurgitation or both) at 
the South Yorkshire Cardiothoracic Centre in Sheffield, 
England, were eligible for the study. 
Patients underwent heart valve surgery between 
October 2012 and February 2013. Inclusion criteria were 
proficiency in English, sufficient cognitive capacity and 
availability for telephone follow-up. 
The Department of Clinical Effectiveness at Sheffield 
Teaching Hospitals National Health Service Trust gave 
approval for this service review. Patients were given an 
information leaflet several days before surgery and con-
sented for the study just prior to the preop 
questionnaire. </p>

<p>Data source 
Patients completed the preoperative questionnaire face 
to face with the investigator on the night before surgery. 
Six to 12 weeks after surgery, they completed the post-
operative questionnaire by telephone or by post if this 
was not possible. 
5 6 21 25 Demographic data as well as 
basic information on the patients' diagnosis and treat-
ment were collected from the cardiac surgery database. </p>

<p>Study size 
A formal power calculation was not performed. The 
number of patients included in the study was deter-
mined by time available (9 months) to the research 
student (C H) </p>

<p>Variables-the HQoL instruments 
Generic 
EQ-5D (EuroQol) is the most common generic HQoL 
instrument used in Europe. It provides a single index 
score of a patient''s health status. It has two components. 
In the first, the patient has to score 1 (the best) to 3 
(the worst) in five domains-usual activity, mobility, 
anxiety or depression, pain and discomfort, and self-
care. The score thus provides a five digit code of health 
status example 12321. The code is used to create an 
index score using a weighted system derived from a table 
of figures generated from a UK population sample 
(figure 1). </p>



<p>Holmes C, Briffa N. Open Heart 2016;3:e000315. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2015-000315 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>The second component of Euroqol is a visual ana-
logue scale (VAS) of the patient overall health status 
ranging from 0 to 100, with 0 being the worst health 
state imaginable and 100 being the best. </p>

<p>7 12-14 26 </p>

<p>Disease-specific 
The Minnesota living with heart failure questionnaire 
(MLHFQ) is a 21 item questionnaire which measures </p>

<p>three aspects of the health-related quality of life-phys-
ical, emotional and socioeconomic table 1. Patients are 
asked to score the effect of their illness on a particular 
aspect of their lives over the past month, on a scale of 
0-5. 0 represents no effect, whereas 5 represents a large 
effect. The lower the score, the better the patient''s 
health. A score of less than 24 signifies good health, 24-
45 moderate health and 45-105 (maximum) poor 
health. One of the items of the MLHFQ relating to 
medical costs was not used. The healthcare system in the 
UK is universally available, funded through general tax-
ation and free at the point of care. 
The total potential score for the study was therefore 100. 
A change in the score of five or more (with treatment) 
is regarded as significant. 
Educational licenses to use both instruments in this 
academic study (Bachelor of Medical Science Thesis) 
were obtained from the Euroqol Foundation and the 
University of Minnesota. </p>

<p>3 14 15 17 26 27 </p>

<p>NYHA status (New York Heart Association Class of 
Cardiac-related Dyspnoea) 
This was assessed at the same two time points. Class 
ranged from I (no symptoms) to IV (severe limitation 
with symptoms at rest). </p>

<p>Statistical methods 
Change in QoL 
Pre and postoperative scores were compared using 
Paired t test. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Change in PROMS score with surgery. PROMS, 
Patient-Reported Outcome Measures; MLHFQ, Minnesota 
Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire; VAS, visual analogue 
score. </p>

<p>Table 1 List of questions in the Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire </p>

<p>The following questions ask how much your heart failure (heart condition) affected your life during the past month (4 weeks). 
After each question, circle the 0, 1, 2, 3, 4 or 5 to show how much your life was affected 
If a question does not apply to you, circle the 0 after that question. Did your heart failure prevent you from living as you 
wanted during the past month (4 weeks) by 
-No (0) Very Little (1) Very Much(5) 
1. Causing swelling in your ankles or legs? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
2. Making you sit or lie down to rest during the day? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
3. Making your walking about or climbing stairs difficult? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
4. Making your working around the house or yard difficult? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
5. Making your going places away from home difficult? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
6. Making your sleeping well at night difficult? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
7. Making your relating to or doing things with your friends or family difficult? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
8. Making your working to earn a living difficult? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
9. Making your recreational pastimes, sports or hobbies difficult? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
10. Making your sexual activities difficult? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
11. Making you eat less of the foods you like? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
12. Making you short of breath? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
13. Making you tired, fatigued or low on energy? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
14. Making you stay in a hospital? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
15. Costing you money for medical care? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
16. Giving you side effects from treatments? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
17. Making you feel you are a burden to your family or friends? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
18. Making you feel a loss of self-control in your life? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
19. Making you worry? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
20. Making it difficult for you to concentrate or remember things? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 
21. Making you feel depressed? 
0 1 2 3 4 5 </p>

<p>Holmes C, Briffa N. Open Heart 2016;3:e000315. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2015-000315 </p>



<p>Valvular heart disease </p>

<p>Instrument effectiveness 
Content validity was assessed qualitatively by assessing 
whether 
PROMs 
are 
credible, 
sensible 
and 
comprehensive. 
Construct validity-analysis of variance of the PROMS 
scores of different groups ranked by their NYHA status 
(New York Heart Association Class of Cardiac-related 
Dyspnoea)-Kruskall-Wallis. 
Concurrent validity-calculation of correlation 
between all PROMS scores ( pre and postop) and 
respective NHYA scores for both instruments-
Spearman rank correlation coefficient. 
Predictive criterion-calculation of correlation 
between preoperative PROM scores and difference in 
scores achieved after surgery for both instruments-
Spearman rank correlation coefficient. 
Reliability-calculation of correlation of individual 
items within a domain; items scoring the same HRQoL 
domains are expected to be highly correlated-
Cronbach's α 
Responsiveness-the mean change in score after treat-
ment divided by the SD of the baseline scores-Cohen 
effect size 
Sensitivity-estimation of floor and ceiling effects-
percentage scoring at the highest and lowest possible 
scores. 
Interpretability-measurement of MCID-the differ-
ence between postoperative scores of patients who felt 
'much better' and those who felt 'no different' </p>

<p>21 22 24 </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed using the <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> 
package. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Participants 
Of the 98 eligible patients, 92 were recruited and of 
these 84 completed the study. </p>

<p>Descriptive data 
Patient and procedure characteristics are outlined in 
table 2. </p>

<p>MAIN RESULTS 
Change in QoL score 
EQ5L 
Index score pre 0.78 (95% CI 0.73 to 0.83) 
Index score post 0.88 (0.84 to 0.92) 
p&lt;0.001 
VAS score pre 63.9 (59.5 to 68.3) 
VAS score post 76.7 (72.6 to 80.7) 
p&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>MLHFQ 
Pre score 32.11 (27.4 to 36.78) 
Post Score 11.6 (7.79 to 15.4) 
p&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Instrument effectiveness 
EQ5D 
Validity: 
Construct, see table 3 
Concurrent criterion-Spearman rank correlation coef-
ficient for index scores-0.26 ( p=0.017), for VAS scores 
-0.33 ( p=0.001) 
Predictive criterion-Spearman rank coefficient for 
index score 0.74 ( p&lt;0.001) and for VAS scores-0.33 
( p=0.001) 
Reliability-Cronbach's α 0.68 (≥0.7) 
Responsiveness-Cohen effect size for index scores-
0.46, for VAS scores 0.64. 
Sensitivity-no floor effects pre (1.2% index and VAS 
scores) or postoperative (1.2% index and VAS scores) 
Mild ceiling effect in preop index scores (39.3%) and 
moderate ceiling effect in the postoperative index score 
(63.1%) 
Interpretability-MCID for index scores 0.125 (95% CI 
0.0056 to 0.2412) p=0.001 </p>

<p>MLHFQ 
Validity: 
Construct, see table 3 
Concurrent criterion-Spearman rank correlation coef-
ficient-0.54 ( p&lt;0.001) 
Predictive criterion-Spearman rank correlation coeffi-
cient-0.54 ( p&lt;0.001) 
Reliability-Cronbach's α 0.914 
Responsiveness-Cohen's effect size 0.95. </p>

<p>Table 2 Patient and procedure characteristics </p>

<p>Age (mean, SD, range) 
69.6±10.4, 40-88 
Male 
72% 
Comorbidity 
Hypertension 
48% 
Hypercholesterolaemia 
41% 
Elective 
81% 
Duration of symptoms in months, 
(median, IQR, range) </p>

<p>24, 38, 0.5-144 </p>

<p>Single valve disease and intervention 
89% 
Type of valve disease 
Aortic stenosis 
57% 
Mitral regurgitation 
13% 
Aortic regurgitation 
8% 
Mixed aortic pathology 
8% 
Mitral stenosis 
1% 
Mixed mitral pathology 
1% 
Multiple valve disease 
12% 
Type of surgery for those with single valve disease 
Replacement 
53% 
Replacement and other 
40% 
Repair 
4% 
Repair and other 
3% </p>



<p>Holmes C, Briffa N. Open Heart 2016;3:e000315. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2015-000315 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>Sensitivity-Percentage scoring 0 for the 20 questions-
3.6%-85.7%. Percentage scoring 5-3.6%-28%, suggest-
ing a floor effect </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Measurement of PROMS or the formal assessment of 
the effect of disease and its treatment on a patient's 
quality of life is becoming increasingly important in 
modern healthcare. They are used as an assessment of 
efficacy of treatments as well as an outcome measure to 
assess performance of institutions who deliver the 
treatment. </p>

<p>5 6 </p>

<p>Formal assessment of PROMS in patients undergoing 
major joint replacement, varicose vein surgery and 
hernia repair is now routine for all patients being 
treated for these conditions in the UK National Health 
Service. 
5 6 A pilot study has examined the use of 
PROMS undergoing percutaneous and surgical revascu-
larisation of significant coronary artery disease. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>Owing to an ageing population, the incidence of sig-
nificant heart valve disease is increasing. Ten per cent of 
all humans aged 80 or older will have significant aortic 
stenosis, the most common valve dysfunction in the 
developed world. 
29 Asymptomatic patients can live a 
long time with significant heart valve dysfunction. Once 
symptoms set in, however, patients quickly become dis-
abled with symptoms of breathlessness, chest pain and 
fluid retention, and their prognosis rapidly worsens if 
the valve disease is left untreated. </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Until fairly recently, the mainstay of treatment has 
been open heart surgery. Although effective, and 
despite the recent increase in 'minimally-invasive' tech-
niques, surgery remains a treatment associated with sig-
nificant morbidity and mortality. This becomes more 
prominent in older patients. In addition, many patients 
do not seem to get the presumed benefit from undergo-
ing major heart surgery. </p>

<p>29 30 </p>

<p>Over the past 5 years, there has been a rapid increase in 
the uptake of non-surgical catheter-based solutions, most 
common of which is the transcutaneous aortic implant-
ation (TAVI) (TAVR replacement in the USA) procedure. 
A number of devices for the treatment of mitral valve 
regurgitation (the second most common valve dysfunction 
in the developed world) are just over the horizon. These 
devices are very expensive and many are of unproven 
worth. In a world of cash-strapped healthcare systems, </p>

<p>evidence-based means of assessing the effect of disease 
and its treatment are urgently required. 
The standard for assessing PROMS in any condition is 
to use two instruments-a generic one and a disease-
specific one. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Euroqol is by far the most commonly used generic 
instrument in Europe. It has been shown in many 
studies of patients with various conditions to be an 
effective way of assessing quality of life before and after 
treatment. </p>

<p>7 12-14 26 </p>

<p>A comprehensive formal review of PROMS instru-
ments in patients receiving medical treatment for heart 
failure by the PROMS group at Oxford University con-
cluded that the Euroqol and MLHFQ were the most 
appropriate to measure quality of life in this group of 
patients. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Key results 
In this study, we examined the performance of Euroqol 
and MLHFQ PROMS in patients receiving surgical treat-
ment for heart valve disease. This is the first study to for-
mally evaluate any PROMS instruments in this 
population of patients. 
We have demonstrated a significant improvement in 
health status using Euroqol. The instrument has been 
shown to be significantly valid but performed less well in 
the assessment of reliability and responsiveness. A 
Cronbach score of 0.68 in the reliability test was only just 
below the significant figure of 0.7 or higher. Since this 
study looked at completed responses from only 87 patients, 
it is highly likely that a more appropriately powered study 
would have come up with a higher score. </p>

<p>3 5 6 9 17-22 </p>

<p>The performance of the MLHFQ instrument was very 
impressive, even though the number of participating 
patients was small. It showed significant improvements 
in health status after surgery and tests of validity, reliabil-
ity and responsiveness were all highly significant with p 
values of &lt;0.001. </p>

<p>3 9 17-22 </p>

<p>Limitations 
There are a number of limitations to this study, namely 
the relatively small number of patients studied and the 
fact that the postoperative questionnaire was only con-
ducted once at 6 weeks. The other obvious limitation is 
that the featured treatment did not include percutan-
eous options. </p>

<p>Table 3 Results of construct validity of Euroqol and MLHFQ using NHYA status as a comparator </p>

<p>NYHA 
EQ-5D INDEX SCORE (mean, 95% CI) 
EQ-5D VAS SCORE 
MLHFQ </p>

<p>NYHA 2 
0.82 (0.766 to 0.88) 
70 (65.2 to 75) 
21 (16.7 to 21.21) 
NYHA 3 
0.77 (0.692 to 0.848) 
57 (49 to 65.2) 
40.4 (33.01 to 47.85) 
NYHA 4 
0.57 (0.33 to 0.815) 
51 (31.1 to 72.5) 
60 (43.78 to 77.12) 
p Value 
0.056 
0.007 (ANOVA) 
0.02 (Kruskal-Wallis) </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>ANOVA, analysis of variance; MLHFQ,Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire; NYHA, New York Heart Association; VAS, visual 
analogue score. </p>

<p>Holmes C, Briffa N. Open Heart 2016;3:e000315. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2015-000315 </p>



<p>Valvular heart disease </p>

<p>Interpretation 
Nonetheless, we have shown that Euroqol and MLHFQ fit 
the bill very nicely for the assessment of the effect of heart 
valve disease and its treatment on patients' quality of life. </p>

<p>Generalisability 
The case for routine measurement of PROMS is strong. 
With the inevitable rapid expansion in percutaneous 
treatments and its associated costs, occurring in the near 
future, we would urge all commissioners to require pro-
viders to adopt these instruments in the management of 
patients undergoing treatment of heart valve disease as a 
matter of routine. </p>

<p>5 6 </p>

<p>Measurement of PROMS using Euroqol and MLHFQ 
should also be part of every research study looking at 
the effectiveness of treatments in patients with heart 
valve disease. </p>

<p>Twitter Follow Norman Briffa at @chestcracker </p>

<p>Contributors This work was undertaken as part of an intercalated Bachelor of 
Medical Science Degree of CH. CH collected and analysed the data and wrote 
the first draft. NB supervised CH and wrote the final draft of the paper. </p>

<p>Funding Funding for this study was obtained through the Sheffield Hospitals 
Charitable Trust. </p>

<p>Competing interests NB is treasurer to the British Heart Valve Society. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement All data gathered in this study were used in the 
analysis and preparation of this paper. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Holmes C, Briffa N. Open Heart 2016;3:e000315. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2015-000315 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

</text></tei>