<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4728087" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:38+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background : Cerebral ischemia is as a result of insufficient cerebral blood flow for cerebral metabolic functions. Resveratrol is a natural phytoalex-
in that can be extracted from grape's skin and had potent role in treating the cerebral ischemia. Apoptosis, a genetically programmed cellular event 
which occurs after ischemia and leads to biochemical and morphological changes in cells. There are some useful markers for apoptosis like Bcl-2, 
bax, and p53. The last reports, researchers verify the apoptosis with early markers like Annexin V. 
Methods : We preferred in this experimental study a model of global cerebral infarction which was induced by bilateral common carotid artery oc-
clusion method. Rats were randomly divided into 4 groups : sham, ischemia-reperfusion (I/R), I/R plus 20 mg/kg resveratrol and I/R plus 40 mg/kg 
resveratrol. Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Sigmastat</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.5</rs> ve <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM</rs> <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS Statistics</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">20</rs>. We considered a result significant when p&lt;0.001. 
Results : After administration of resveratrol, Bcl-2 and Annexin levels were significantly increased (p&lt;0.001). Depending on the dose of resveratrol, 
Bcl2 levels increased, p53 levels decreased but Annexin V did not effected. P53 levels were significantly increased in ishemia group, so apoptosis is 
higher compared to other groups. 
Conclusion : In the acute period, Annexin V levels misleading us because the apoptotic cell counts could not reach a certain level. Therefore we 
should support our results with bcl-2 and p53. </p>

<p>Key Words : Resveratrol · Brain Ischemia · Annexin V · Bcl-2 · p53. </p>

<p>Laboratory Investigation </p>

<p>• Received : November 3, 2014 • Revised : June 14, 2015 • Accepted : July 15, 2015 
• Address for reprints : Orhan Kalemci, M.D. </p>

<p>Department of Neurosurgery, Dokuz Eylul University, School of Medicine Hospital, Inciralti-I </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>zmir 35340, Turkey 
Tel : +90-232-4123305, Fax : +90-232-2788802, E-mail : okalemci@gmail.com 
• This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>J Korean Neurosurg Soc 58 (6) : 508-512, 2015 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3340/jkns.2015.58.6.508 </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 The Korean Neurosurgical Society </p>

<p>Print ISSN 2005-3711 On-line ISSN 1598-7876 </p>

<p>www.jkns.or.kr </p>



<p>Neuroprotective Effects of Resveratrol on Acute Brain Ischemia Reperfusion Injury | C Kizmazoglu, et al. </p>

<p>resveratrol; Group III, BCA occlusion for 30 min; followed by 20 
mg/kg resveratrol i.p. (n=10) followed by reperfusion for 24 h 
(n=10); Group IV, BCA occlusion for 30 min, followed by 40 mg/ 
kg resveratrol i.p. (n=10); Group V, BCA occlusion for 30 min, 
followed by DMSO (solvent). </p>

<p>Experimental induction of global cerebral infarction </p>

<p>In this experimental study, we preferred a model of global ce-
rebral infarction which was induced by bilateral common carot-
id artery occlusion method (Fig. 1) </p>

<p>10) </p>

<p>. 
Rats were anesthetized with thiopental sodium (30 mg/kg). 
Cervical vertebrae and the common carotid arteries were then 
exposed and carefully separated from the vagus nerve. These ar-
teries were occluded for 30 min followed by reperfusion for 4 h. 
The rectal temperature was maintained at 37±0.5 °C with a feed-
back-controlled heating pad. animals which did not lose the 
righting reflex or which convulsed during the ischemic episode 
were excluded. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Sigmastat</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">3.5</rs> and 
<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">IBM</rs> <rs id="software-3" type="software">SPSS Statistics</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">21</rs>. Continuous variables are expressed as 
mean±standard deviation. Relationships between Bcl-2 and p53 
levels were determined using analysis of variance (ANOVA). 
The variables did not show normal distribution in comparison 
between Annexin V levels, we used Kruskal-Wallis one-way 
analysis of variance. As multiple comparison test annexin V lev-
els were measured by Tukey's test. We considered a significant </p>

<p>nally leading to cell death. Caspase-3 is believed to be the main 
executioner protease of apoptotic caspase </p>

<p>36) </p>

<p>. 
Resveratrol is a natural phytoalexin that can be extracted from 
grape' s skin. Resveratrol was reported to have antioxidant, antiin-
flammatory, antidiabetic, and antiaging, control of cell cycle, and 
apoptosis </p>

<p>11,28,49) </p>

<p>. Earlier reports suggested that antioxidants and 
anti-inflammatory agents had potent role in treating the cerebral 
ischemia-reperfusion injury </p>

<p>5,49) </p>

<p>. Antiphospholipid antibodies 
(aPLs) are associated with some neurologic disorders. Annexins 
are a family of calcium-dependent phospholipid-binding pro-
teins. The potent anticoagulant activity of annexin V is derived 
from its inhibitory effect on prothrombin activation </p>

<p>32,42) </p>

<p>. Antian-
nexin V antibody (aAV) has an important role in trombotic 
events in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus and an-
tiphospholipid syndrome 
12) aAV plays a role in cerebral thrombot-
ic events by inhibiting the anticoagulant activity of annexin V </p>

<p>16) </p>

<p>. 
p53 is an important modulator of cell death and survival, and 
its inhibition could be a therapeutic approach to several neuropa-
thologies </p>

<p>9) </p>

<p>. Bcl-2, a gene located at chromosome 18q21, blocks 
apoptosis without affecting cellular proliferation. Increases in the 
expression of bcl-2 stop apoptosis and inhibits neuron death. p53 
induced apoptosis activate Bax and cause neuronal apoptosis </p>

<p>41) </p>

<p>. 
Bcl-2 is a distinguished anti-apoptotic protein that binds to Bax 
to inhibit apoptosis </p>

<p>24) </p>

<p>. p53 induced downregulation of Bcl-2 and 
upregulation of Bax promote cytochrome C release from the mi-
tochondria and caspase-3 activation causes cell death </p>

<p>14,35) </p>

<p>. 
In this study we have aimed to show the effects of resveratrol 
with the comparison results of annexin V, p53, Bcl-2 levels after 
ischemia in rats. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>All experimental procedures and animal care were in accor-
dance with the guidelines of Eskisehir Osmangazi University, 
Faculty of Medicine. The experimental protocols used in this 
study were also approved by the Animal Experimental Ethic 
Committee of Eskişehir Osmangazi University (Date and deci-
sion number : 25.07.2013, 351). 
Rat Annexin V ELISA kit (sc 4252-AK, Santa Cruz Biotech-
nology, TX, USA), rat p53 ELISA kit (Cloud-Clone Corp., Hous-
ton, TX, USA), rat Bcl-2 ELISA kit (Cloud-Clone Corp., Hous-
ton, TX, USA) and resveratrol (Sigma-Aldrich, St, Louis, MO, 
USA) were used for measuring the serum levels of these apoptot-
ic markers. 
All efforts were made to minimize animal suffering and to reduce 
the number of animals used. In the present study, 50 Sprague-Daw-
ley female rats (250-300 g weight) were used. The rats were moni-
tored at a suitable temperature (21±2°C) and moist environment 
(60±5% humidity). Rats was observed in this environment for one 
week before starting the experiment to adapt to the environment. 
The animals included in the study were divided into five 
groups (Table 1). Group I, Sham, no ischemia (n=10), Group II : 
bilateral carotid artery (BCA) occlusion for 30 min (n=10), no </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Rat carotid artery. </p>

<p>Table 1. Groups of the study </p>

<p>Group 
n </p>

<p>I. Sham 
10 
II. Ischemia 
10 </p>

<p>III. Resveratrol 40 mg/kg 
10 </p>

<p>IV. Resveratrol 20 mg/kg 
10 
V. Solvent (DMSO) 
10 </p>



<p>J Korean Neurosurg Soc 58 | December 2015 </p>

<p>result when p&lt;0.001. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>After resveratrol administration, Bcl-2 levels were significantly 
increased when compared to the ishemia group (p&lt;0.001). De-
pending on the dose of resveratrol, we have observed that Bcl-2 
levels increase. We have found that the solvent did not change 
Bcl-2 levels (Fig. 2). p53 levels were significantly increased in ish-
emia group, so apoptosis is higher compared to other groups. 
Depending on the dose of resveratrol, we observed that p53 levels 
decrease so the apoptosis (Fig. 3). Our data revealed that Annexin </p>

<p>V levels were significantly increased in ischemia group compared 
to other groups. However, depending on the dose of resveratrol 
dsaAnnexin V levels did not change (Fig. 4, Table 2). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The annual incidence of stroke around the world is 15 mil-
lion, with a mortality of 5 million and permanent sequelae, dis-
ability and dependency on others of 5 million patients </p>

<p>23) </p>

<p>. It is 
estimated that the stroke rate will rise significantly in the fu-
ture </p>

<p>45) </p>

<p>. During the stroke, several mechanisms are responsible 
for the neuronal injury including increased excitotoxicity, calci-
um overload, formation of free radicals and inhibition of protein 
synthesis </p>

<p>33,46) </p>

<p>. During ischemia/reperfusion, resveratrol modu-
late the neurotransmitters and neuromodulator protects the 
brain from ischemia </p>

<p>17) </p>

<p>. Li et al. 
18) showed that treatment with 
resveratrol improve neurological function and decrease infarct 
volume as compared to ischemia rats. The neuroprotective 
mechanism of resveratrol are not clarified and further investiga-
tion must be conducted </p>

<p>18) </p>

<p>. Apoptosis, inflammatory response, 
and free radical formation are responsible for the neuronal cell 
death. Apoptosis, a programmed cell death, activated by the cell 
ischemia </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>. A family of proteases known as caspases plays an 
important role in apoptosis. There are two ways of caspase acti-
vation : cell death receptor mediated and mitochondrial. The 
Bcl-2 family includes both antiapoptotic proteins (Bcl-2, Bcl-
xL, A1/Bfl1, Boo/Diva, Bcl-w, Mcl-1, Nrf3) and proapoptotic 
proteins (Bax, Bak, Bok/Mtd) </p>

<p>17) </p>

<p>. Cytochrome C induces cell </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Comparison of the serum Annexin V levels in the groups (Kruskal-
Wallis one way, p&lt;0.001). </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
Group I 
(sham) </p>

<p>Group II 
(ischemia) </p>

<p>Group III 
(resveratrol 
20 mg) </p>

<p>Group IV 
(resveratrol 
40 mg) </p>

<p>Group V 
(solvent) </p>

<p>Comparison of Annexin V levels </p>

<p>25% 
Median 
75% </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Comparison of the serum Bcl 2 levels in the groups (ANOVA, 
p&lt;0.001). </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
Group II 
(ischemia) </p>

<p>Group III 
(resveratrol 
20 mg) </p>

<p>Group IV 
(resveratrol 
40 mg) </p>

<p>Group I 
(sham) </p>

<p>Group V 
(solvent) </p>

<p>Bcl-2 levels </p>

<p>Fig.3. Comparison of the serum p53 levels in the groups (ANOVA, 
p&lt;0.001). </p>

<p>8000 </p>

<p>7000 </p>

<p>6000 </p>

<p>5000 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>3000 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>0 
Group II 
(ischemia) </p>

<p>Group III 
(resveratrol 
20 mg) </p>

<p>Group IV 
(resveratrol 
40 mg) </p>

<p>Group I 
(sham) </p>

<p>Group V 
(solvent) </p>

<p>p53 levels </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of the serum Annexin V levels in the groups (Kruskal-Wallis one way, p&lt;0.001) </p>

<p>Groups 
n 
25% 
Median 
75% </p>

<p>Group I (sham) 
10 
45.6 
54 
063 
Group II (ischemia) 
10 
239 
269 
289 </p>

<p>Group III (resveratrol 40 mg/kg) 
10 
131 
169 
212 </p>

<p>Group IV (resveratrol 20 mg/kg) 
10 
76 
89 
165 
Group V [solvent (DMSO)] 
10 
215 
262 
278 </p>



<p>Neuroprotective Effects of Resveratrol on Acute Brain Ischemia Reperfusion Injury | C Kizmazoglu, et al. </p>

<p>death by activation of caspase 9 and 3 in the mitochondrial 
pathway of apoptosis 
4) . The mitochondrial release of cyto-
chrome C in brain ischemia is caused by proapototic Bax gene, 
but it' s not the only way of apoptosis. Apoptosis can be activated 
in the absence of caspase activity. Apoptosis-inducing factor 
(AIF), which is found in the mitochondrial intermembranous 
space, releases as a result of absence of ATP, causing apoptosis </p>

<p>3) </p>

<p>. 
Antioxidant and anti-inflammatory agents can limit the re-
perfusion injury during the ishemia 
13,15,33,48) . Some research 
showed that resveratrol has a neuroprotective effects in rats </p>

<p>29,39,47) </p>

<p>. 
There is no standard treatment for the reperfusion injury. Oxi-
dative stress and inflammation have an important role in cere-
bral ischemia and reperfusion injury </p>

<p>15,30) </p>

<p>. Resveratrol has a neu-
roprotective effect in cerebral ischemic models </p>

<p>39,44) </p>

<p>. Resveratrol 
can prevent a wide variety of conditions including cancer, car-
diovascular, diabetes and neurological disorders </p>

<p>2,25,43) </p>

<p>. Resvera-
trol exerts multiple biological effects, including anti-inflammato-
ry, antiproliferative, antiplatelet and potent antioxidant effects </p>

<p>4,11) </p>

<p>. 
The present study indicates that resveratrol presents a neuro-
protective effect on cerebral ischemic rats by measuring Annex-
in 5, p53, and bcl-2. Li et al. 
19) indicated that resveratrol attenu-
ates ischemic neuronal apoptosis by up regulating bcl-2. In our 
study after resveratrol administration, Bcl-2 levels were signifi-
cantly increased when compared to the ishemia group. Shin et 
al. 
38) showed that in the ischemic brain, resveratrol modulate 
the proteins and protects the brain. Annexin 5 has been exten-
sively used as an indicator of early apoptosis due to its inherent 
property of selectively interacting with phosphatidyl serine. The 
physiologic functions of Annexin 5 include suppression of blood 
coagulation and platelet aggregation by occlusion of exposed PS 
from access by coagulation factors </p>

<p>37) </p>

<p>. In our study we found that 
Annexin V levels were significantly increased in ischemia group 
compared to other groups. However, depending on the dose of 
resveratrol Annexin V levels did not change. Resveratrol affects 
the activation of a variety of intracellular signal pathways. Mol-
chadsky et al. 
27) showed that resveratrol induces p53 activation in 
vascular smooth muscle cells (VSMCs ). Unlike Molchadsky et 
al. </p>

<p>27) </p>

<p>, Zheng et al. 
50) showed that p53 decreased myocardin ex-
pression; hence inhibited differentiation from mesenchymal cells 
to smooth muscle cells. We observed that p53 levels decreases 
after the administration of resveratrol. Orsu et al. 
30) indicated 
that resveratrol showed significant cerebroprotective action me-
diated by anti-oxidant and anti-inflammatory mechanisms. Lu 
et al. 
22) suggest that resveratrol prepared by RES loaded nanopar-
ticles shows enhanced neuron protection against oxidative stress 
in cultured neurons exposed to H2O2 both in a short time and in 
longer time treatment over bax and bcl 2 genes. 
In conclusion, we suggest that resveratrol is a natural drug 
with minimal side effects and it might be effective medical thera-
phy for the treatment of acute ischemic stroke. </p>





<p>J Korean Neurosurg Soc 58 | December 2015 </p>



</text></tei>