<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4205716" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Results: Of the 413 users, the majority of whom with 
progressive neuromuscular disorders (NMDs) (n=358), 284 patients initially used 
noninvasive mechanical ventilation (NIV), while 63 others who were using trache-
ostomy mechanical ventilation switched to NIV as part of their rehabilitation. The 
NMD patients began HMV at an earlier age (34.9±20.3 yrs), and used for longer 
(14.7±7.5) hours than patients with non-neuromuscular causes of respiratory im-
pairment. Conclusion: Noninvasive management was preferred over invasive ones, 
and transition to the former was a result of PM&amp;R interventions. </p>

<p>Advances in medical care have resulted in more patients requiring long-term home 
mechanical ventilation (HMV), and all too often results in ventilator users left with 
tracheostomy tubes without physical medicine and rehabilitation (PM&amp;R) inter-
ventions. 
1 The cornerstone of PM&amp;R intervention is pulmonary rehabilitation 
(PR). While most of the clinical care of pulmonary disease is limited to medical 
treatments, PR deals with a comprehensive intervention, based on a thorough pa-
tient assessment, followed by patient-tailored therapies, which include exercise 
training, education and behavioral changes designed to improve physical and psy-
chological condition of people with chronic respiratory diseases. 
2 PR has long 
been directed to improving the medical and functional status of patients with pa-
renchymal lung diseases such as chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, 
3 however, 
similar principles have generally been ignored for patients with neuromuscular 
diseases (NMDs). These measures can also be of value for patients with NMDs. In 
addition, the use of inspiratory and expiratory muscle aids, including noninvasive 
mechanical ventilation (NIV) and mechanically assisted coughing (MAC), can fa-
cilitate the decannulation of invasively managed ventilator users to more desirable </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2014.55.6.1729 
pISSN: 0513-5796, eISSN: 1976-2437 </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J 55(6):1729-1735, 2014 </p>

<p>Dong Hyun Kim, et al. </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 55 Number 6 November 2014 </p>



<p>subjects air stacking, 
7 and the expiratory phase assisted by 
application of an abdominal thrust. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>5) The ventilatory status was monitored by arterial blood 
gas analysis (ABGA) or by monitoring oxyhemoglobin sat-
uration (SpO2) and end tidal carbon dioxide (EtCO2) via 
oximetry and capnometry (Microcap plus, Oridion Ltd., Je-
rusalem, Israel) just before HMV prescription, while using 
mechanical ventilation. For those who could not perform 
1)-4) due to intubation or a tracheostomy tube as well as 
intolerance of breathing with the tube transiently capped for 
the measurement, the same test was performed after the 
decannulation or extubation. 
Statistical analysis was made by <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.0</rs> for windows 
version (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA), paired t-test was 
used to find the statistical significance between FVC in sit-
ting and supine position in NMD groups, and Wilcoxon 
signed rank test was used for the comparison of non-NMD 
groups. </p>

<p>Application of NIV 
When patients presented with subjective symptoms of hy-
poventilation or when ventilatory abnormality was suspect-
ed from the result of a single daytime ABGA or EtCO2 and 
SpO2 measurement, overnight noninvasive monitoring was 
performed to detect latent hypercapnea. Initial NIV applica-
tion was considered when patients showed elevated noctur-
nal EtCO2 levels (&gt;45 mm Hg) with or without multiple 
nocturnal SpO2 below 95% on serial overnight monitoring. 
Nasal interfaces (Goldseal nasal mask, Respironics, Murrys-
vill, PA, USA) or oronasal interfaces (Performa Track 
TM SE 
mask, Respironics, Murrysvill, PA, USA) were used for the 
transition from TMV to NIV. Candidates for decannulation 
and transition to NIV had the ability to attain APCF &gt;160 L/ 
min and had minimal or no dysphagia or dysarthria before 
intubation or tracheostomy. All TMV patients who fulfilled 
the above criteria without ongoing lung parenchymal lesions 
were included once for the transition training, and the 
decannulation processes were performed as previously de-
scribed. 
9 Patients who could not follow commands or did 
not cooperate with training in NIV or with assist coughing 
were excluded from the consideration for decannulation. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The demographics and ventilator use characteristics of the 
patients are described in Table 1 and 2. </p>

<p>noninvasive aids. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Comprehensive surveys on HMV have been carried out 
in Europe, North America, Chile, and Japan, 
5 but not in Ko-
rea. Based on our previous 10 years of experience, therefore, 
we aimed to describe HMV and the role of PM&amp;R in opti-
mizing it. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients with chronic respiratory failure requiring HMV 
were included in the study. We retrospectively reviewed 
their data from March 2000 when we first adopted system-
ized PM&amp;R intervention to the HMV program at Gangnam 
Severance hospital until December 2009. </p>

<p>The management status of patients with HMV 
The following parameters were investigated; basic demo-
graphic characteristics of all patients, causes of chronic res-
pirator dependence, type and mode of mechanical ventila-
tor use, tracheostomy mechanical ventilation (TMV) vs. 
NIV use and any transition between them. We supplement-
ed medical record reviews with telephone surveys of those 
with incomplete records or who had been lost to follow-up 
for over two years. For patients who were decannulated of 
their tracheostomy tubes, we analyzed the data before and 
after the decannulation. A follow-up survey was performed 
in October 2010 to explore any changes in HMV status. </p>

<p>Pulmonary function evaluations 
1) Forced vital capacity (FVC) was measured in sitting 
and supine positions using a spirometer (Micro 
TM spirome-
ter; CareFusion 232 Ltd., Chatham, UK). The highest of 3 
attempts was recorded as the FVC. We calculated predicted 
FVC values (FVCpre) based on age and height. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>2) The maximal inspiratory pressure and maximal expira-
tory pressure measured in mouth in sitting position with an 
effort sustained for at least 1 second (MicroRPM; CareFu-
sion 232 Ltd., Chatham, UK) to gauge inspiratory and expi-
ratory muscle strength, respectively. The highest value of 3 
or more attempts was used. 
3) Peak cough flow (PCF) was measured by a peak flow-
meter (ASSESS </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>; Health Scan Products Inc., Cedar Grove, 
NJ, USA) with the patient coughing as hard as possible and 
the highest value of 3 or more attempts was recorded. 
4) Assisted PCF (APCF) was measured by the same peak 
flow meter, but the inspiratory phase was augmented by the </p>

<p>HMV in South Korea </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 55 Number 6 November 2014 </p>



<p>failure to NIV were accompanying bulbar muscle weakness 
and insufficient cooperation due to either young age (&lt;7 yrs 
old) or mental retardation (Table 5-2). Details of the 63 ini-
tial TMV users who succeeded in decannulation are de-
scribed in Table 6-1 and 6-2, and flow diagram of HMV ap-
plication by lapse of time is described in Fig. 1. 
The most frequently prescribed mode of HMV was assist-
ed controlled ventilation based on volume cycled systems. 
Although there were initially 42 bilevel positive airway 
pressure (BiPAP) and 3 continuous positive airway pressure 
users, all except for 4 patients [2 myotonic muscular dystro-
phy (MMD), 1 SMA and 1 cerebral disease] who were us-
ing BiPAP were switched to assist control mode ventilation 
on prescription. Major cause of the mode change was either 
unsatisfactory ventilation results or patients' maladjustment 
to the preset modes. 
At initial HMV application, 231 patients used nocturnal 
HMV, 125 patients used HMV nocturnally plus some day-
time, and 57 patients required near full time HMV (≥22 
hours). When the application time was reinvestigated in 
2010, 16 patients no longer used HMV; 5 voluntarily quit-
ted the use of HMV against advice, 11 totally weaned off 
HMV. Changes of HMV dependent hours in each diagnos-
tic group are described in Table 4 and 5. </p>

<p>Pulmonary function evaluations 
Of the 413 patients, we analyzed the data of 306 patients 
whose pulmonary function tests at initial HMV application 
were available (Table 3). The results of pulmonary function 
assessment were used to determine when and how HMV 
was used. </p>

<p>Methods of HMV 
Of the 284 patients who initially used NIV, NMD accounted 
for the majority (97.5%). On the follow up, 233 patients 
were still using NIV, and of 46 patients who switched to 
TMV, 42 were amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) who 
could not tolerate NIV any further because of stridor occur-
ring from upper airway spasticity and paralysis (Table 4). 
One spinal muscular atrophy (SMA) patient started noctur-
nal NIV, but underwent tracheostomy due to extubation fail-
ure after scoliosis surgery. After transition training of NIV, 
he succeeded in decannulation once again, and is using noc-
turnal NIV. One spinal cord injury (SCI) patient developed 
hypoxic brain injury, and 2 myopathy patients underwent 
emergency tracheostomies during respiratory arrests. 
One hundred twenty-nine patients started HMV invasive-
ly; 121 were using TMV, and the other 8 patients were ex-
tubated to NIV (Table 5-1). Two major causes of transition </p>

<p>Table 1. Basal Characteristics and Initial Mode of HMV in Progressive Neuromuscular Disease Patients </p>

<p>Myopathy 
ALS (n=141) 
SMA (n=25) 
Total (n=358) 
DMD (n=113) 
Others (n=79) </p>

<p>Current age (yr) 
23.5±5.5 
33.0±17.8 
59.3±11.3 
15.6±10.9 
39.2±20.5 </p>

<p>Age at ventilator application (yr) 
19.6±4.8 
28.8±17.8 
54.8±11.1 
10.8±11.2 
34.9±20.3 </p>

<p>Male/female 
113/0 
41/38 
95/46 
19/6 
268/90 </p>

<p>TMV/NIV 
11/102 
19/60 
38/103 
13/12 
81/277 </p>

<p>HMV, home mechanical ventilation; TMV, tracheostomy mechanical ventilation; NIV, noninvasive mechanical ventilation; DMD, Duchenne muscular dys-
trophy; ALS, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis; SMA, spinal muscular atrophy. 
Values are mean±standard deviation. Others: Becker's muscular dystrophy (n=5), congenital myopathy (n=11), Emery-Dreifuss muscular dystrophy (n=2), 
fascioscapulohumeral dystrophy (n=6), limb-girdle muscular dystrophy (n=3), mitochondrial cytopathy (n=4), myotonic muscular dystrophy (n=13), non-
specific progressive muscular dystrophy (n=23), inclusion body myositis (n=2), Klippel-Feil syndrome (n=1), critical illness myopathy (n=1), myotubular my-
opathy (n=1), nemaline myopathy (n=1), Nonaka myopathy (n=1), polimyositis (n=1), Pompe's disease (n=3), Swartz-Jampel syndrome (n=1). </p>

<p>Table 2. Basal Characteristics and Initial Mode of HMV in Non-Neuromuscular Disease Patients </p>

<p>SCI (n=32) 
Cerebral diseases (n=10) Miscellaneous (n=13) 
Total (n=55) </p>

<p>Current age (yr) 
48.0±17.9 
46.8±20.2 
48.9±17.1 
48.0±17.8 </p>

<p>Age at ventilator application (yr) 
45.5±18.0 
45.1±21.0 
45.5±17.3 
45.4±18.0 </p>

<p>Male/female 
26/6 
4/6 
7/6 
37/18 </p>

<p>TMV/NIV 
30/2 
9/1 
9/4 
48/7 </p>

<p>HMV, home mechanical ventilation; TMV, tracheostomy mechanical ventilation; NIV, noninvasive mechanical ventilation; SCI, spinal cord injury. 
Values are mean±standard deviation. Miscellaneous: lung parenchymal disease (n=3) (s/p lung transplantation, bilateral phrenic N. palsy, Tuberculosis de-
stroyed lung), Guillian-Barre syndrome (n=4), central hypoalveolarsyndrome (n=1), Down syndrome with obstructive sleep apnea (n=1), cor pulmonale due 
to kyphoscoliosis (n=2), myesthenia gravis (n=2). </p>

<p>Dong Hyun Kim, et al. </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 55 Number 6 November 2014 </p>



<p>Table 3. Results of Pulmonary Function Assessment </p>

<p>Myopathy </p>

<p>ALS (n=95) </p>

<p>SMA (n=17) </p>

<p>SCI (n=22) </p>

<p>Cerebral 
diseases (n=4) </p>

<p>Miscellaneous </p>

<p>(n=8) </p>

<p>Total (n=306) </p>

<p>DMD (n=100) </p>

<p>Others (n=60) </p>

<p>FVCsit (mL) </p>

<p>653.4±403.1 </p>

<p>1017.1±644.9 </p>

<p>1143.6±629.0 </p>

<p>617.3±390.5 </p>

<p>709.5±322.1 </p>

<p>1115.0±265.0 </p>

<p>1043.8±422.0 </p>

<p>878.4±579.9 </p>

<p>preFVCsit </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>17.9±12.7 </p>

<p>28.9±16.3* </p>

<p>28.7±16.0 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>22.5±12.5 </p>

<p>17.2±8.0 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>33.0±12.1 </p>

<p>28.7±8.1 </p>

<p>22.2±16.7 </p>

<p>FVCsup (mL) </p>

<p>619.6±385.2 </p>

<p>842.4±560.4 </p>

<p>966.0±531.2 </p>

<p>623.8±398.2 </p>

<p>810±326.3 </p>

<p>1197.5±143.4 </p>

<p>921.3±324.7 </p>

<p>781.3±500.1 </p>

<p>preFVCsup </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>16.7±11.3 </p>

<p>23.6±14.4* </p>

<p>24.0±12.9 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>22.2±11.7 </p>

<p>18.6±8.7 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>35.2±8.7 </p>

<p>25.5±5.9 </p>

<p>19.7±13.9 </p>

<p>PCF (L/min) </p>

<p>148.2±58.1 </p>

<p>194.3±73.6 </p>

<p>184.0±77.2 </p>

<p>173.1±88.0 </p>

<p>124±18.2 </p>

<p>170.0±127.3 </p>

<p>189.3±77.9 </p>

<p>161.2±83.1 </p>

<p>APCF (L/min) </p>

<p>267.1±164.3 </p>

<p>340.7±344.0 </p>

<p>267.6±105.4 </p>

<p>194±98.2 </p>

<p>207.9±75.2 </p>

<p>190±84.9 </p>

<p>235.0±60.6 </p>

<p>192.3±100.3 </p>

<p>MIP (cmH2O) </p>

<p>18.0±10.4 </p>

<p>26.4±14.4 </p>

<p>19.9±12.9 </p>

<p>26.0±18.5 </p>

<p>18.8±9.5 </p>

<p>20.7±3.8 </p>

<p>29.0±16.2 </p>

<p>21.7±13.3 </p>

<p>MIPpre (%) </p>

<p>18.3±11.1 </p>

<p>34.5±19.2 </p>

<p>25.6±16.8 </p>

<p>31.5±25.6 </p>

<p>23.5±13.5 </p>

<p>27.8±1.8 </p>

<p>36.0±15.3 </p>

<p>20.3±11.7 </p>

<p>MEP (cmH2O) </p>

<p>18.4±9.8 </p>

<p>34.9±20.6 </p>

<p>26.6±19.6 </p>

<p>24.6±19.6 </p>

<p>21.2±20.7 </p>

<p>39.7±31.0 </p>

<p>57.9±52.7 </p>

<p>25.4±20.9 </p>

<p>MEPpre (%) </p>

<p>13.1±7.9 </p>

<p>33.3±20.6 </p>

<p>23.1±16.2 </p>

<p>19.3±16.7 </p>

<p>19.2±22.9 </p>

<p>35.1±18.2 </p>

<p>48.1±35.4 </p>

<p>23.2±18.3 </p>

<p>DMD, Duchenne muscular dystrophy; ALS, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis; SMA, spinal muscular atrophy; SCI, spinal cord injury; FVCsit, forced vital capacity in sitting position; preFVCsit, </p>

<p>normal predicted value of FVC in sit-</p>

<p>ting position; FVCsup, forced vital capacity in supine position; preFVCsup, 
normal predicted value of FVC in supine position; PCF, peak cough flow; APCF, assisted peak cough flow; MIP, maximal inspiratory pressure; MIPpre, </p>

<p>normal predicted value of MIP; MEP, maximal expiratory pressure; MEPpre, normal predicted value of MEP. 
Miscellaneous: lung parenchymal disease (n=3), Guillian-Barre syndrome (n=4), central hypoalveolar syndrome (n=1), Down syndrome with obstructive sleep apnea (n=1), cor pulmonale due to kyphoscoliosis (n=2), myes-</p>

<p>thenia gravis (n=2). Values are mean±standard deviation. 
*p&lt;0.05, comparison of preFVCsit </p>

<p>and preFVCsup 
in other myopathy group. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05, comparison of preFVCsit </p>

<p>and preFVCsup 
in ALS group. </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05, comparison of preFVCsit </p>

<p>and preFVCsup 
in SCI group. </p>

<p>Table 4. Details of Initial NIV Users (n=284) </p>

<p>Myopathy </p>

<p>ALS (n=103) </p>

<p>SMA (n=12) </p>

<p>SCI (n=2) </p>

<p>Cerebral diseases 
(n=1) </p>

<p>Miscellaneous </p>

<p>(n=4) </p>

<p>Total (n=284) </p>

<p>DMD (n=102) </p>

<p>Others (n=60) </p>

<p>Initial HMV (hrs/day) </p>

<p>8.6±3.7 </p>

<p>7.9±2.5 </p>

<p>8.3±5.8 </p>

<p>6.8±1.3 </p>

<p>8.0±2.8 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>7.8±1.0 </p>

<p>8.3±4.4 </p>

<p>Follow-up HMV (hrs/day) </p>

<p>12.8±6.3 </p>

<p>10.0±5.5 </p>

<p>19.2±7.4 </p>

<p>8.3±1.8 </p>

<p>15.0±12.7 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>6.0±4.1 </p>

<p>13.9±7.4 </p>

<p>Regular PM&amp;R intervention </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>86 </p>

<p>Mode of HMV at follow-up; 
TMV/NIV/weaning </p>

<p>1/100/1 </p>

<p>2/56/2 </p>

<p>42/60/1 </p>

<p>0/12/0 </p>

<p>1/1/0 </p>

<p>0/1/0 </p>

<p>0/3/1 </p>

<p>46/233/5 </p>

<p>HMV, home mechanical ventilation; TMV, tracheostomy mechanical ventilation; NIV, noninvasive mechanical ventilation; DMD, Duchenne muscular dystrophy; ALS, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis; SMA, spinal muscular 
atrophy; SCI, spinal cord injury; PM&amp;R, physical medicine and rehabilitation. 
Values are mean±standard deviation. Others: Becker's muscular dystrophy (n=5), congenital myopathy (n=7), Emery-Dreifuss muscular dystrophy (n=2), fascioscapulohumeral dystrophy (n=5), limb-girdle muscular dys-
trophy (n=3), mitochondrial cytopathy (n=2), myotonic muscular dystrophy (n=10), non-specific progressive muscular dystrophy (n=18), inclusion body myositis (n=2), nemaline myopathy (n=1), Nonaka myopathy (n=1), 
polimyositis (n=1), Pompe's disease (n=2), Swartz-Jampel syndrome (n=1), Miscellaneous: central hypoalveolar syndrome (n=1), cor pulmonale due to kyphoscoliosis (n=2), myesthenia gravis (n=1). </p>

<p>HMV in South Korea </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 55 Number 6 November 2014 </p>



<p>public subsidy for NMDs, and the characteristics of a center 
at which the survey was conducted may contribute to this. 
PM&amp;R intervention for patients with chronic respiratory 
failure mainly consists of regular monitoring of ventilation 
and pulmonary function, maintenance of pulmonary com-
pliance, optimization of sputum clearance, and timely ap-
plication as well as transition training to NIV. In the present 
study, only 96 patients received regular PM&amp;R check-ups 
before the onset of subjective symptoms or overt respirato-
ry failure occurred. Although 10 patients initially used TMV, 
9 were severe bulbar ALS patients. In contrast, 62 of the 
decannulated patients (98.4%) did not benefit from early 
PM&amp;R check-ups before developing respiratory failure. Al-
though they finally succeeded in decannulation, patients 
could have avoided unnecessary invasive procedures which </p>

<p>Management of patients with HMV 
Among the HMV users investigated, only 96 patients [ALS 
41, Duchenne muscular dystrophy (DMD) 40, SMA 2, oth-
er myopathy 13] received regular PM&amp;R interventions in-
cluding serial pulmonary function evaluations and ventila-
tion monitoring. Eighty-six patients from this group started 
NIV, and 10 initially used TMV. Of the 86 NIV users, 68 
were maintaining NIV, but 18 (ALS 16, MMD 1, DMD 1) 
were switched to TMV during follow-up periods (Table 4 
and 5-1). Nine initial TMV users, except 1 SMA who suc-
ceeded in decannulation, were still using TMV at the fol-
low-up. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Although a few studies exist on the management status of 
ventilatory impairment in NMDs, 
10,11 the present study is 
the first report which contains detailed information of dif-
ferent disease groups in relation to HMV in Korea. Previous 
surveys revealed variations between countries in the propor-
tion of lung and neuromuscular patients ventilated, preferred 
ventilator and interface types. 
1,5 The most striking difference 
of our result is higher proportion of NIV in NMDs, most 
likely due to a large number of patients with regular PM&amp;R 
check-ups. NIV is currently identified as a preferred ventila-
tion strategy and recommended only if the basic require-
ments such as proper swallowing function, basic coopera-
tion, and ability of self-expectoration are fulfilled. 
11,12 Despite 
the advantages, ventilation via tracheostomy still accounts 
for the highest percentage in NMDs worldwide. 
1,5 Total num-
ber of progressive NMD patients is also high in this study. 
Improved availability to HMV since the introduction of a </p>

<p>Table 5-1. Details of Initial TMV Users (n=129) </p>

<p>Myopathy 
ALS 
(n=38) </p>

<p>SMA 
(n=13) </p>

<p>SCI 
(n=30) </p>

<p>Cerebral 
diseases 
(n=9) </p>

<p>Miscella-
neous 
(n=9) </p>

<p>Total 
(n=129) 
DMD 
(n=11) </p>

<p>Others 
(n=19) </p>

<p>Initial HMV (hrs/day) 
13.5±7.7 
14.2±7.8 
15.0±7.8 
14.5±9.3 
14.2±7.6 
14.5±8.5 
7.8±2.0 
14.0±7.7 
Follow-up HMV (hrs/day) 
13.8±6.7 
15.8±7.6 
20.1±6.2 
17.8±7.2 
9.6±8.4 
7.7±7.6 
4.7±4.8 
13.8±8.6 
Regular PM&amp;R intervention 
0 
0 
9 
1 
0 
0 
0 
10 </p>

<p>Mode of HMV at follow-up; 
TMV/NIV/weaning 
3/8/0 
10/9/0 
35/3/0 
7/6/0 
9/15/6 
6/2/1 
1/4/4 
71/47/11 </p>

<p>HMV, home mechanical ventilation; TMV, tracheostomy mechanical ventilation; NIV, noninvasive mechanical ventilation; DMD, Duchenne muscular dys-
trophy; ALS, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis; SMA, spinal muscular atrophy; SCI, spinal cord injury; PM&amp;R, physical medicine and rehabilitation. 
Values are mean±standard deviation. Others: congenital myopathy (n=4), fascioscapulohumeral dystrophy (n=1), mitochondrial cytopathy (n=2), myotonic 
muscular dystrophy (n=3), nonspecific progressive muscular dystrophy (n=5), Klippel-Feil syndrome (n=1), critical illness myopathy (n=1), myotubular my-
opathy (n=1), Pompe's disease (n=1). Miscellaneous: lung parenchymal disease (n=3) (s/p lung transplantation, bilateral phrenic N. palsy, tuberculosis 
destroyed lung), Guillian-Barre syndrome (n=4), Down syndrome with obstructive sleep apnea (n=1), myesthenia gravis (n=1). </p>

<p>Table 5-2. Causes of Initial TMV Use (n=129) </p>

<p>Detailed reasons for initial TMV application 
No. of 
patients </p>

<p>1 Elective tracheostomy </p>

<p>NIV failure due to bulbar symptoms and/or 
poor compliance 
21 </p>

<p>NIV failure due to young age, mental 
retardation or hypoxic brain injury 
4 </p>

<p>2 
Tracheostomy due to repeated extubation/ 
weaning failure 
4 </p>

<p>3 Admitted or transferred with tracheostomy state </p>

<p>Failure in decannulation &amp; maintenance of 
tracheostomy 
33 </p>

<p>Success in decannulation &amp; switched to NIV 
55 
4 Admitted or transferred with intubation 
Failure in extubation &amp; tracheostomy 
4 
Success in extubation &amp; switch to NIV 
8 
TMV, tracheostomy mechanical ventilation; NIV, noninvasive mechanical 
ventilation. </p>

<p>Dong Hyun Kim, et al. </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 55 Number 6 November 2014 </p>



<p>tures, 
14,15 aggressive use of continuous NIV and MAC can 
result in more favorable outcomes and better survival. 
A growing population of patients exist who have chronic 
respiratory failure due to conditions such as NMDs, SCI, or 
lung parenchymal disorders, and who require either trache-
ostomy or mask ventilation. 
1,8 However, the lack of concrete 
local guidelines and shortage of experienced physicians spe-
cialized in PM&amp;R interventions are the main obstacles to ex-
tensively employ the management. Furthermore, the avail-
ability and practical details of complex respiratory support at 
home involve many variables. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>caused pain, increased medical costs and hospitalization if 
they had been optimally managed at the onset. 
Of the 413 patients, 293 turned out to be alive at the fol-
low-up in 2010, whereas 120 patients were either expired or 
presumed to be dead; 118 of them were NMDs (ALS 86, 
DMD 15, other myopathies 14, SMA 3), and 2 were non-
NMD patients (1 SCI, 1 brain stem glioma). Specific causes 
of death were not fully investigated in this study. In spite of 
prolonged median survival of these patients, respiratory 
failure comprised the major cause of death to certain NMD 
patients, especially in ALS. 
13 As proven in recent litera-</p>

<p>Table 6-1. Details of the Decannulated Patients (n=63) </p>

<p>Myopathy 
ALS 
(n=5) </p>

<p>SMA 
(n=6) </p>

<p>SCI 
(n=22) </p>

<p>Cerebral 
diseases 
(n=3) </p>

<p>Miscella-
neous 
(n=9) </p>

<p>Total 
(n=63) 
DMD 
(n=8) </p>

<p>Others 
(n=10) </p>

<p>Hrs/day of HMV at 
decannulation 
9.5±4.5 
8.6±2.8 
13.2±9.9 
10.0±6.9 
12.8±7.1 
7.7±1.2 
7.8±2.0 
10.5±6.0 </p>

<p>Hrs/day of HMV at 
follow-up 
12.1±4.9 
11.5±6.1 
19.7±7.5 
12.8±6.2 
5.4±4.1 
4.7±4.0 
4.7±4.8 
8.7±6.5 </p>

<p>Mode of HMV at follow-up; 
TMV/NIV/weaning 
0/8/0 
1/9/0 
2/3/0 
0/6/0 
1/15/6 
0/2/1 
1/4/4 
5/47/11 </p>

<p>HMV, home mechanical ventilation; TMV, tracheostomy mechanical ventilation; NIV, noninvasive mechanical ventilation; DMD, Duchenne muscular dys-
trophy; ALS, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis; SMA, spinal muscular atrophy; SCI, spinal cord injury. 
Values are mean±standard deviation. Other myopathies: congenital myopathy (n=3), fascioscapulohumeral dystrophy (n=1), mitochondrial cytopathy (n=1), 
myotonic muscular dystrophy (n=1), non-specific progressive muscular dystrophy (n=2), Klippel-Feil syndrome (n=1), Pompe's disease (n=1). Miscellaneous: 
lung parenchymal disease (n=3) (s/p lung transplantation, bilateral phrenic N. palsy, Tbc dystroyed lung), Guillian-Barre syndrome (n=4), Down syndrome 
with obstructive sleep apnea (n=1), myesthenia gravis (n=1). </p>

<p>Table 6-2. Specific Transitions from Decannulation to TMV (n=5) </p>

<p>No. of patients 
Diagnosis 
Causes of transition to tracheostomy 
1 
MMD 
Sudden cardiac arrest 
2 
ALS 
End-stage illness 
1 
Tetraplegic SCI 
Sudden mucus plugging leading to hypoxic brain injury 
1 
Tuberculosis destroyed lung 
Severe pneumonia 
TMV, tracheostomy mechanical ventilation; MMD, myotonic muscular dystrophy; ALS, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis; SCI, spinal cord injury. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Flow diagram of HMV application. HMV, home mechanical ventilation; TMV, tracheostomy mechanical ventilation; NIV, noninvasive 
mechanical ventilation. </p>

<p>Total patient (n=413) </p>

<p>Decannulation (n=63) 
Seal off 55 
Extubation 8 </p>

<p>Tracheostomy 
(n=47) </p>

<p>Tracheostomy 
(n=5) </p>

<p>Decannulation 
(n=1) </p>

<p>Initial </p>

<p>Follow up </p>

<p>TMV (n=129) 
NIV (n=284) </p>

<p>TMV (n=117) 
Weaning (n=16) 
NIV (n=280) </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>HMV in South Korea </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 55 Number 6 November 2014 </p>





<p>Even though this study includes a large number of HMV 
users, the results cannot fully reflect general status of Korea. 
Future collaboration with several district university hospitals 
will be necessary to expand the results. 
In conclusion, a thorough understanding and application 
of PM&amp;R interventions can be of value in improving the 
care and quality of life for patients with long-term HMV. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by a faculty research grant of Yon-
sei University College of Medicine for 2010 (6-2010-0025). </p>



</text></tei>