<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4630049" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Some adipokines are produced in adipose tissue, while others 
are partially secreted by infiltrating macrophages and stromal 
cells. 
1 Among adipokines, adiponectin is only expressed by 
adipocytes, and stromal vascular cells of adipose tissue. Adi-
ponectin is known to increase insulin-stimulated glucose up-
take by enhancing Akt phosphorylation. Plasma adiponectin 
levels have been found to be correlated with body mass index 
(BMI), type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM), and coronary vascu-
lar disease (CVD). Additionally, decreased expression, secre-
tion, and circulating levels of adiponectin have been reported in 
obese populations. 
1-3 Adiponectin treatment reduces the ex-
pression of endotoxin-induced pro-inflammatory cytokines and </p>

<p>The Impact of CDH13 Polymorphism and 
Statin Administration on TG/HDL Ratio 
in Cardiovascular Patients </p>

<p>Jung Ran Choi </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Yangsoo Jang </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, Sungjoo Kim Yoon </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, Jong Keun Park </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, 
Sungbin Richard Sorn </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>, Mi-Young Park </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>, and Myoungsook Lee </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Food and Nutrition, and Research Institute of Obesity Sciences, Sungshin Women's University, Seoul; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cardiovascular Genome Center, Cardiology Division, Department of Internal Medicine, Severance Cardiovascular Hospital, Yonsei University 
College of Medicine, Seoul; </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Research Institute of Molecular Genetics, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul; </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>School of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul; </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Institute of Health and Environment, Graduate School of Public Health, Seoul National University, Seoul, Korea. </p>

<p>Purpose: Adiponectin is expressed in adipose tissue, and is affected by smoking, obesity, and genetic factors, such as CDH13 poly-
morphism, contributing to the development of coronary vascular diseases (CVDs). 
Materials and Methods: We investigated the effect of genetic variations of CDH13 (rs3865188) on blood chemistry and adiponec-
tin levels in 345 CVD patients undergoing statin-free or statin treatment. 
Results: Genetic variation in CDH13 was significantly correlated with several clinical factors, including adiponectin, diastolic blood 
pressure, triglyceride (TG), and insulin levels. Subjects with the T allele (mutant form) had significantly lower adiponectin levels 
than those with the A allele. Total cholesterol (TC), low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDLc), TG/high-density lipoprotein cho-
lesterol (HDLc) ratio, and HDL3b subtype were markedly decreased in statin treated subjects regardless of having the A or T allele. 
TG and TG/HDL in the statin-free group with TT genotype of the rs3865188 was higher than in the others but they were not dif-
ferent in the statin-treated subjects. We observed a significant difference in adiponectin levels between patients with the A and T 
alleles in the statin-free group; meanwhile, no difference in adiponectin levels was noted in the statin group. Plasma levels of other 
cytokines, leptin, visfatin, interleukin-6 (IL-6), and tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), were not different among the CDH13 genotypes 
according to statin administration. Body mass index (BMI), TG, insulin, HDL3b, and TG/HDL ratio showed negative correlations 
with adiponectin levels. 
Conclusion: Plasma adiponectin levels and TG/HDL ratio were significantly different according to variants of CDH13 and statin 
administration in Korean patients with CVD. </p>

<p>Key Words: Adiponectin, CDH13, statin, TG/HDL, HDL3b </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J 2015 Nov;56(6):1604-1612 
http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.6.1604 </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>pISSN: 0513-5796 · eISSN: 1976-2437 </p>

<p>Received: February 2, 2015 Revised: July 21, 2015 
Accepted: July 21, 2015 
Co-corresponding authors: Myoungsook Lee, PhD, Department of Food and Nutri-
tion, and Research Institute of Obesity Sciences, Sungshin Women's University, 55 
Dobong-ro 76ga-gil, Gangbuk-gu, Seoul 01133, Korea. 
Tel: 82-2-920-7211, Fax: 82-2-920-2078, E-mail: mlee@sungshin.ac.kr and 
Yangsoo Jang, MD, PhD, Cardiovascular Genome Center, Cardiology Division, De-
partment of Internal Medicine, Severance Cardiovascular Hospital, Yonsei Universi-
ty College of Medicine, 50-1 Yonsei-ro, Seodaemun-gu, Seoul 03722, Korea. 
Tel: 82-2-2228-8445, Fax: 82-2-393-2041, E-mail: jangys1212@yuhs.ac </p>

<p>•The authors have no financial conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>© Copyright: Yonsei University College of Medicine 2015 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Com-
mons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/ licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and repro-
duction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.6.1604 </p>

<p>Jung Ran Choi, et al. </p>

<p>increases anti-inflammatory interleukin-10 (IL-10) expression in 
monocytes and macrophages. Exogenous administration of adi-
ponectin also decreases allergic airway inflammation in mice. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>In spite of its anti-inflammatory and anti-atherogenic effects, 
adiponectin is potentially associated with adverse clinical out-
comes, such as mortality. As plasma adiponectin levels are st-
rongly influenced by single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) 
of the gene encoding T-cadherin [the cadherin 13 preprotein 
(CDH13)], several studies had been conducted to examine the 
possible associations between CDH13 genotype and plasma 
adiponectin levels. 
5 CDH13, a 95 kd glycoprotein, is an atypi-
cal member of the cadherin family of cell adhesion molecules. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Unlike classical cadherins, it has low adhesive characters and 
is attached to the cell membrane via a glycosylphosphatidyli-
nositol anchor, as it lacks both transmembrane and cytoplas-
mic domains. 
6 CDH13 functions as a negative regulating mol-
ecule during the development of the nervous system and is in-
volved in migratory processes, tumorigenesis, and angiogene-
sis. 
7,8 Moreover, CDH13 is involved in endoplasmic reticulum 
(ER) stress responses. Several studies suggested CDH13 is up-
regulated in endothelial cells after induction of ER stress and 
protect these cells from apoptosis in reaction to the proapop-
totic response. 
9 Another report observed that GRP78, a molecu-
lar chaperone similar to CDH13, was involved in pro-survival 
responses to ER stress, as a signaling partner to CDH13, along 
to the surface of endothelial cells. 
10 Recently, several CDH13 
SNPs, such as rs3865188, have been reported to be determi-
nants of blood adiponectin levels in Asians. The association of 
rs11646213 in CDH13 and blood pressure phenotype has also 
been investigated in European cohorts. Another SNP, rs4783244, 
was also shown to be associated with metabolic syndrome 
phenotype in Taiwanese. 
11 However, the association between 
CDH13 variations and cardiometabolic disease is not com-
pletely clear. 
Statins [or 3-hydroxy-3-methyl-glutaryl (HMG)-CoA reduc-
tase inhibitors] are known to be effective in reducing risk of 
cardiovascular events in patients with CVD by lowering cho-
lesterol synthesis. 
12 Several reports have demonstrated that st-
atin shows pleiotropic effects in modulating endothelial func-
tion, stable angina pectoris, inflammation, and thrombosis. </p>

<p>13,14 </p>

<p>However, only the impact of APOE on statin treatment effica-
cy has been reported, although the APOE4 allele is associated 
with a poor response to statin treatment. 
15 Therefore, in this 
study, we aimed to examin the effect of CDH13 rs3865188 on 
adiponectin levels and lipid profiles in 345 statin-free or statin-
treated outpatients enrolled with the Cardiovascular Center at 
Severance Hospital in Seoul, Korea. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study population </p>

<p>A total of 345 outpatients were recruited from the Cardiovas-</p>

<p>cular Genome Center Registry from the Yonsei University Col-
lege of Medicine, supported by The Ministry of Health and 
Welfare. Briefly, consecutive subjects who visited the Cardio-
vascular Center at Severance Hospital in Seoul, Korea from July 
2008 to December 2009 were prospectively screened for dys-
lipidemia [triglyceride (TG) &gt;150 mg/dL; high-density lipo-
protein-cholesterol (HDLc) &lt;40 mg/dL for men, HDL &lt;50 mg/ 
dL for women]. Subjects who exhibited positive results for dys-
lipidemia on three separate visits and patients who had taken 
anti-hyperlipidemic medications such as statins were also in-
cluded. For further analysis of the association between genetic 
variants and other metabolic traits, the study population was 
divided into two groups: a statin-free group and a statin group. 
We analyzed the effects of CDH13 rs3865188 on blood chem-
istry with statin groups compared to the statin free groups. This 
study was conducted according to the guidelines of the Decla-
ration of Helsinki, and was approved by the Institutional Re-
view Board of Yonsei University Medical Center (IRB#: 4-2001-
0039). Written informed consent was obtained from all study 
participants. </p>

<p>Clinical data and blood samples </p>

<p>On the day of enrollment, clinical data including demographic 
variables and medical history were recorded. We calculated 
BMI as a ratio of weight (kg) divided by the height (m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). Blood 
lipid profiles [total cholesterol (TC), low-density lipoprotein-
cholesterol (LDLc), HDLc, TG, and HDL subtypes], fasting blo-
od sugar (FBS), insulin, enzymes related to HDL metabolism 
[lecithin cholesterol acyltransferase (LCAT) and cholesteryl es-
ter transfer protein (CETP)], and adipocytokines [adiponectin, 
leptin, monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1), visfatin, 
IL-6, tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α)] were obtained from se-
rum or plasma collected after an overnight fast and kept at -80°C 
until further analysis. FBS, TC, and TG were measured using a 
Hitachi-7600 analyzer (Hitachi Ltd., Tokyo, Japan), and LDLc 
was calculated by Friedewald equation. The 600 µL of fresh 
serum, kept at 4°C for less than 1 day, used for HDL subclasses 
after HDL fraction was isolated by new micro-ultracentrifuga-
tion at 1.063&lt;d&lt;1.21 g/mL (Hitachi CS150GXL, CS140AT fixed 
angle rotor, Tokyo, Japan), and separation of HDL subfrac-
tions were conducted as previously reported. 
16 All cytokines, 
as well as LCAT and CETP, were measured by enzyme immu-
noassay using an ELISA kit (Diichi Pure Chemicals, Tokyo, Ja-
pan). Serum adiponectin and insulin levels were measured by 
an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (Mesdia Co. Ltd., 
Seoul, Korea). 
17 The intra-and inter-assay variances for adipo-
nectin were 6.3-7.4% and 4.5-8.6%, respectively. </p>

<p>Sequencing and genotyping </p>

<p>PCR primers were designed to independently amplify CDH13 
fragments. Primer sequences are available on request. PCR 
products were purified and then sequenced using a BigDye 
Terminator Cycle Sequencing Kit (version 3.1, ABI, Foster City, </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.6.1604 </p>



<p>CDH13 Gene and Statin on TG/HDL in CVD </p>

<p>CA, USA) and an ABI 3730×1 automated sequencer (Applied 
Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). The sequencing primers 
were the same as those used for PCR amplification. SNPs iden-
tified in the CDH13 gene by whole gene sequencing were geno-
typed. Genomic DNA was extracted from 5 mL of peripheral 
venous blood using a commercially available isolation kit 
(QuickGene SP Kit DNA whole blood, Fujifilm, Tokyo, Japan). 
Genotyping was performed using the TaqMan fluorogenic 5' 
nuclease assay (ABI). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Group differences for categorical variables were assessed by 
chi-square test, and continuous variables were examined by 
Student's t-test. The association between genotype and adipo-
nectin level was evaluated using odds ratios (ORs) and 95% 
confidence intervals (CIs) from chi-square tests and logistic </p>

<p>regression analyses. The results are presented as mean±st-
andard error range. p-values for each genotype and allele were 
evaluated by χ 2 analysis and Fisher's exact test. A p-value with 
three decimal places was taken to indicate statistically signifi-
cant differences between statin-free and statin-treated sub-
jects of the study. Associations between clinical variables, such 
as age, BMI, and TC, were analyzed by Pearson correlation 
test. All analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 18.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Characteristics of the study population according 
to genotype and alleles of rs3865188 </p>

<p>Characteristics of the population are shown in Table 1. The 345 </p>

<p>Table 1. Anthropometric and Clinical Characteristics of Cardiovascular Disease Patients According to Allele and Genotype of CDH13 Gene SNP 
(rs3865188) </p>

<p>Variables 
Total 
(n=345) </p>

<p>Genotype 
Allele 
AA (n=170) 
AT (n=128) 
TT (n=36) 
p value* 
A (n=469) 
T (n=201) 
p value* 
Adiponectin 
5.81±3.70 
006.25±3.76 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>005.79±3.66 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>003.97±3.29 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.046 
6.13±3.72 
5.08±3.60 
0.016 
Age (yr) 
62.56±10.00 
63.31±10.07 
61.91±9.53 
62.92±10.38 
0.481 
62.93±9.92 
62.28±9.80 
0.451 
BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
25.09±3.25 
24.91±3.23 
25.40±3.49 
24.78±2.44 
0.371 
25.04±3.31 
25.17±3.15 
0.618 
SBP (mm Hg) 
116.73±13.49 
116.90±12.27 
115.29±14.15 
118.33±12.98 
0.382 
116.47±12.79 116.40±13.75 
0.929 
DBP (mm Hg) 
71.39±8.30 
72.09±7.70 
69.96±7.81 
72.22±7.96 
0.052 
71.52±7.77 
70.79±7.90 
0.717 
TC (mg/dL) 
150.50±38.74 
147.64±37.80 
155.60±39.89 
146.88±36.84 
0.176 
149.82±38.47 152.46±38.87 
0.419 
TG (mg/dL) 
142.71±81.29 
134.96±78.14 
147.77±80.39 
158.13±90.92 
0.184 
138.46±78.80 151.50±84.00 
0.055 
HDLc (mg/dL) 
39.96±9.69 
40.47±9.66 
39.49±9.41 
39.63±10.38 
0.668 
40.20±9.58 
39.54±9.72 
0.411 
LDLc (mg/dL) 
85.72±31.51 
83.04±30.57 
90.88±32.31 
81.30±31.18 
0.067 
85.18±31.19 
87.43±32.09 
0.403 
TG/HDL 
3.94±2.97 
3.67±2.84 
4.10±2.96 
4.48±3.39 
0.226 
3.79±2.87 
4.24±3.11 
0.070 
Insulin 
10.91±11.26 
12.36±14.19 
9.87±8.12 
8.70±4.84 
0.088 
11.66±12.80 
9.45±7.11 
0.006 
HOMA-IR 
3.63±5.50 
3.96±7.02 
3.57±4.01 
2.41±1.37 
0.328 
3.85±6.31 
3.15±3.35 
0.069 
FBS 
125.00±52.84 
118.49±42.13 
134.00±65.52 
116.13±41.93 
0.026 
122.73±50.00 127.57±58.58 
0.316 
CRP 
0.33±0.78 
0.26±0.60 
0.49±1.07 
0.23±0.41 
0.344 
0.31±0.75 
0.39±0.87 
0.550 
Leptin 
29.55±30.05 
27.25±29.86 
35.36±34.14 
22.61±12.87 
0.145 
29.28±31.05 
30.36±28.38 
0.751 
MCP-1 
44.81±38.40 
40.08±34.28 
53.97±44.53 
42.03±36.00 
0.084 
43.55±37.44 
49.29±41.46 
0.219 
Visfatin 
1.87±0.12 
1.86±0.12 
1.87±0.12 
1.89±0.13 
0.489 
1.86±0.12 
1.88±0.12 
0.208 
IL-6 
37.48±56.05 
40.40±58.46 
38.56±60.67 
24.70±26.81 
0.530 
39.94±58.78 
33.12±50.40 
0.312 
TNF-α 
26.95±32.07 
29.68±39.62 
23.30±19.95 
22.92±15.81 
0.406 
28.09±35.71 
23.15±18.29 
0.087 
BUN 
16.38±4.77 
16.33±4.55 
16.13±4.54 
17.63±6.39 
0.344 
16.28±4.53 
16.65±5.26 
0.414 
Uric acid 
5.37±1.45 
5.31±1.44 
5.37±1.50 
5.59±1.31 
0.699 
5.33±1.45 
5.45±1.43 
0.418 
HDL2b 
31.79±3.08 
31.96±3.01 
31.52±3.08 
31.89±3.23 
0.509 
31.83±3.03 
31.65±3.12 
0.505 
HDL2a 
22.27±1.57 
22.19±1.72 
22.39±1.39 
22.15±1.58 
0.550 
22.24±1.63 
22.30±1.45 
0.679 
HDL3a 
18.56±1.70 
18.45±1.71 
18.68±1.62 
18.51±1.71 
0.548 
18.52±1.68 
18.62±1.64 
0.495 
HDL3b 
12.73±1.51 
12.70±1.47 
12.81±1.55 
12.63±1.57 
0.787 
12.73±1.49 
12.75±1.55 
0.919 
HDL3c 
14.55±2.33 
14.54±2.46 
14.58±2.20 
14.71±2.45 
0.932 
14.55±2.38 
14.63±2.28 
0.719 
LCAT mass 
8.72±2.76 
8.62±2.84 
8.80±2.83 
8.98±2.36 
0.809 
8.67±2.83 
8.87±2.64 
0.491 
CETP mass 
1.62±0.67 
1.55±0.56 
1.67±0.68 
1.63±0.74 
0.466 
1.58±0.59 
1.66±0.70 
0.312 
LCAT/CETP 
6.13±2.80 
6.15±2.78 
6.06±2.76 
6.47±3.18 
0.821 
6.12±2.77 
6.21±2.91 
0.782 
SNP, single nucleotide polymorphism; BMI, body mass index; SBP, systolic blood pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; TC, total cholesterol; TG, triglyceride; HDLc, 
high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDLc, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol; FBS, fasting blood sugar; CRP, C-reactive protein; MCP-1, monocyte chemoattrac-
tant protein-1; IL-6, interleukin 6; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α; HOMA-IR, homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance. 
Values with different alphabets are significantly different among the groups by ANOVA at p&lt;0.005. 
*p value was estimated by ANOVA and t-test. </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.6.1604 </p>

<p>Jung Ran Choi, et al. </p>

<p>subjects recruited were aged 62.56±10.0 years, and 67.3% (n= 
233) of the total population were men. Subjects with the CDH13 
SNP showed significant differences in several clinical factors, 
including adiponectin level; diastolic blood pressure (DBP); 
and levels of FBS, insulin, and TG (Table 1). Subjects with the T 
allele (mutant form) had significantly lower adiponectin and 
insulin levels and significantly higher plasma TG than those 
with the A allele (wild-type form) (p&lt;0.05). In contrast, alleles 
of the CDH13 gene showed a divergent trend when compared 
with the genotype. There were significant differences in FBS 
level and DBP between heterozygous subjects with the AT al-
lele and homozygous subjects with an AA or TT allele, which 
may have contributed to the non-significant differences ob-
served in the FBS level and DBP between A and T alleles. Oth-
er blood chemistry data, such as lipid profiles with HDL sub-
types or inflammatory cytokines, did not differ by CDH13 </p>

<p>genotype or allele types. </p>

<p>CDH13 variants and statin treatment on lipid risk factors </p>

<p>One SNP (rs3865188) was significantly associated with adipo-
nectin level. In the additive model, adiponectin level was not 
associated with a decreased risk of dyslipidemia (OR=0.732, 
95% CI, 0.349-1.545, p=0.406) (data not shown). Subjects with 
the A allele had higher adiponectin levels than those with the 
T allele in the statin-free group, but there were no differences 
in statin groups (Table 2). There was also a difference in TG/ 
HDL levels between subjects with the T allele and those with 
the A allele in the statin-free group. Moreover, there was no 
difference in TG/HDL and adiponectin levels in the statin 
group. The subjects with a minor T allele of rs3865188 had 
higher LDLc and MCP-1 levels, whereas those with rs3865188 
had lower insulin levels in the statin group (p=0.003). Statin </p>

<p>Table 2. Anthropometric and Clinical Characteristics of Cardiovascular Disease Patients with CDH13 SNP (rs3865188) Alleles According to Statin Ad-
ministration </p>

<p>Variables 
Statin-free group (n=177) 
Statin group (n=168) 
p value* 
Total 
A 
T 
p value </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Total 
A 
T 
p value </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Adiponectin 
5.83±3.45 
6.25±3.70 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>4.78±2.56 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.007 
5.79±4.00 
5.99±3.77 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>5.45±4.61 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>0.441 
0.073 
Age (yr) 
62.31±10.13 
62.92±9.72 
62.22±10.15 
0.543 
62.87±9.84 
62.97±10.14 
62.43±9.44 
0.654 
0.898 
BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
24.96±.3.07 
24.77±3.10 
25.21±2.91 
0.228 
25.23±3.41 
25.31±3.48 
25.15±3.40 
0.709 
0.341 
SBP (mm Hg) 
116.88±13.74 
116.02±12.26 116.81±14.59 
0.606 
116.52±13.21 116.87±13.32 115.82±12.78 
0.516 
0.855 
DBP (mm Hg) 
71.78±8.26 
71.61±7.33 
71.32±7.23 
0.733 
74.66±48.40 74.09±41.42 
76.79±64.49 
0.654 
0.586 
TC (mg/dL) 
161.62±38.52 
161.57±38.12 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>161.81±38.06 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.958 
138.77±35.47 137.86±35.05 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>141.92±37.22 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.346 
&lt;0.001 
TG (mg/dL) 
149.81±85.70 
140.85±76.21 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>164.83±97.75 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.026 
135.23±75.90 136.04±81.44 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>136.46±62.29 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.936 
0.017 
HDLc (mg/dL) 
39.37±10.13 
39.94±9.92 
38.83±10.54 
0.345 
40.58±9.19 
40.46±9.24 
40.35±8.69 
0.901 
0.540 
LDLc (mg/dL) 
95.23±31.61 
96.46±30.80 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>92.46±32.69 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.277 
75.71±28.21 73.71±27.19 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>81.77±30.57 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.020 
&lt;0.001 
TG/HDL 
4.23±3.15 
3.87±2.71 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>4.81±3.78 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.022 
3.64±2.73 
3.71±3.03 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>3.59±1.93 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.745 
0.007 
Insulin 
10.78±11.69 
11.24±13.22 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>9.86±8.10 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>0.328 
11.06±10.82 12.09±12.36 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>8.99±5.80 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.003 
0.114 
HOMA-IR 
3.80±6.84 
4.03±8.00 
3.32±3.72 
0.392 
3.44±3.54 
3.66±3.80 
2.96±2.88 
0.076 
0.418 
FBS 
125.16±54.81 
123.63±53.75 127.33±58.63 
0.569 
124.84±50.86 121.81±45.98 127.84±58.84 
0.388 
0.730 
CRP 
0.31±0.57 
0.29±0.55 
0.38±0.62 
0.435 
0.36±1.03 
0.35±0.98 
0.41±1.20 
0.845 
0.905 
Leptin 
30.66±31.88 
31.36±34.95 
29.66±24.10 
0.738 
28.17±27.75 26.72±25.36 
31.24±33.29 
0.346 
0.668 
MCP-1 
44.76±43.61 
45.94±43.76 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>43.29±44.42 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.703 
44.88±31.05 40.61±27.63 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>56.89±36.47 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.011 
0.134 
Visfatin 
1.87±0.11 
1.88±0.12 
1.87±0.10 
0.940 
1.86±0.13 
1.85±0.12 
1.89±0.15 
0.067 
0.148 
IL-6 
38.30±56.34 
38.90±56.35 
38.01±57.96 
0.922 
36.47±56.03 41.23±61.89 
26.93±38.53 
0.090 
0.569 
TNF-α 
29.54±39.36 
31.50±43.89 
22.44±20.71 
0.053 
23.74±19.40 23.88±21.22 
24.05±14.84 
0.980 
0.140 
BUN 
16.10±4.56 
15.90±4.22 
16.68±5.30 
0.183 
16.72±4.99 
16.72±4.86 
16.61±5.24 
0.874 
0.327 
Uric acid 
5.31±1.51 
5.24±1.52 
5.38±1.46 
0.530 
5.43±1.39 
5.41±1.38 
5.51±1.40 
0.598 
0.567 
HDL2b 
31.50±2.94 
32.06±3.25 
32.03±3.12 
0.393 
32.11±3.21 
32.06±3.25 
32.03±3.12 
0.944 
0.173 
HDL2a 
22.20±1.42 
22.33±1.86 
22.42±1.42 
0.808 
22.34±1.73 
22.33±1.86 
22.42±1.42 
0.715 
0.512 
HDL3a 
18.59±1.51 
18.52±1.93 
18.61±1.79 
0.550 
18.52±1.89 
18.52±1.93 
18.61±1.79 
0.694 
0.925 
HDL3b 
12.92±1.37 
12.54±1.67 
12.53±1.53 
0.897 
12.53±1.63 
12.54±1.67 
12.53±1.53 
0.969 
0.021 
HDL3c 
14.76±2.16 
14.33±2.61 
14.33±2.30 
0.622 
14.33±2.50 
14.33±2.61 
14.33±2.30 
0.996 
0.116 
LCAT mass 
8.71±2.78 
8.66±2.83 
8.96±2.73 
0.464 
8.73±2.74 
8.68±2.84 
8.77±2.57 
0.819 
0.890 
CETP mass 
1.64±0.75 
1.62±0.62 
1.62±0.76 
0.990 
1.59±0.58 
1.55±0.57 
1.69±0.63 
0.111 
0.488 
LCAT/CETP 
6.14±2.89 
5.98±2.76 
6.58±3.10 
0.164 
6.12±2.72 
6.26±2.77 
5.83±2.67 
0.283 
0.363 
SNP, single nucleotide polymorphism; BMI, body mass index; SBP, systolic blood pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; TC, total cholesterol; TG, triglyceride; HDLc, 
high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDLc, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol; FBS, fasting blood sugar; CRP, C-reactive protein; MCP-1, monocyte chemoattrac-
tant protein-1; IL-6, interleukin 6; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α; HOMA-IR, homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance. 
Values with different alphabets are significantly different among the groups by ANOVA at p&lt;0.05. 
*p value was estimated by ANOVA, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>p value was estimated by t-test. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.6.1604 </p>



<p>CDH13 Gene and Statin on TG/HDL in CVD </p>

<p>treatment strongly decreased TC, LDLc, TG/HDL ratio, and 
HDL3b subfractions regardless of having the A or T allele, re-
spectively. In the statin-free group, subjects with the TT geno-
type of the rs3865188 SNP had lower adiponectin levels 
(p=0.032) and higher TG levels (p=0.025) (Fig. l). In the statin 
group, however, the TT genotype was strongly associated with 
reductions in TG levels and in TG/HDL. Plasma adiponectin 
levels were significantly increased for individuals with the AT 
genotype and those who underwent statin treatment. </p>

<p>Trends in inflammation markers in subjects who 
underwent statin treatment </p>

<p>Subjects in the statin group with the TT genotype had higher 
MCP-1 levels than patients in the statin-free group with the 
same genotype (57.92±40.90 vs. 26.14±22.39). Statin treatment 
did not effect reductions in MCP-1 among persons with the AT 
genotype (Fig. 1). In terms of allele distribution, there was a sig-
nificant difference in MCP-1 levels in subjects with the T allele, 
compared to those in subjects with the A allele, in the statin 
group (p=0.009) (Table 2). On the other hand, individuals with 
the AT genotype in the statin group had higher leptin levels 
than wild type patients and mutant homozygous patients. Plas-
ma levels for other cytokines, leptin, visfatin, IL-6, and TNF-α 
did not differ according to CDH13 genotype or statin admin-
istration. TNF-α levels were lower for the T allele than the A 
allele (Table 2). </p>

<p>Risk factors related to adiponectin level </p>

<p>Parametric Pearson correlation analysis of the data revealed </p>

<p>that the adiponectin level is significantly positively correlated 
with sex (r=0.339, p&lt;0.001), HDL level (r=0.353, p&lt;0.001), and 
HDL2b level (r=0.367, p&lt;0.001). Meanwhile, TG level (r=-0.210, 
p=0.005), BMI (r=-0.224, p=0.003), insulin level (r=-0.252, p= 
0.001), HDL3b (r=-0.325, p&lt;0.001), and TG/HDL ratio (r=-0.227, 
p=0.002) showed negative correlations (data not shown). In the 
statin-free and statin groups, linear regression analysis was per-
formed to estimate the relative contributions of clinical vari-
ables, such as BMI, TG level, insulin level, and HDL2b fraction, 
to the inter-individual variations in adiponectin level. Therein, 
TG level was associated with adiponectin level in statin-free 
individuals with the T allele, not the A allele. In the statin group, 
there was no association between TG and adiponectin levels 
in individuals with the T allele (Fig. 2). Plasma adiponectin level 
was negatively associated with TG/HDL ratio in patients with 
the AT genotype in the statin-free group. However, the effect 
of the AT genotype was not observed upon statin treatment. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study is the first to suggest a significant association be-
tween SNPs located within CDH13 and statin treatment on 
plasma adiponectin levels and lipid profiles in Korean cardio-
vascular patients with dyslipidemia. First, we found that plas-
ma adiponectin levels decreased according to CDH13 geno-
types, in order to from major AA to minor TT types. Although 
the mechanism of the transcriptional regulation of CDH13 is 
not clear, a nucleotide variant in the promoter region is asso-</p>

<p>Fig. 1. Plasma levels of adiponectin (A), TG/HDL (B), LDLc (C), HDL3b (D) subtypes according to CDH13 genotypes whether the stain was taken or not. Val-
ues with different alphabets are significantly different among the CHD13 gene genotypes. TG, triglyceride; HDL, high-density lipoprotein; LDLc, low-densi-
ty lipoprotein cholesterol. </p>

<p>14 
12 
10 
8 
6 
4 
2 
0 </p>

<p>140 
120 
100 
80 
60 
40 
20 
0 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>15 
14.5 
14 
13.5 
13 
12.5 
12 
11.5 
11 </p>

<p>AA </p>

<p>AA </p>

<p>AA </p>

<p>AA </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>b 
ab </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a 
ab </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>AA </p>

<p>AA </p>

<p>AA </p>

<p>AA </p>

<p>AT </p>

<p>AT </p>

<p>AT </p>

<p>AT </p>

<p>AT </p>

<p>AT </p>

<p>AT </p>

<p>AT </p>

<p>Statin-free </p>

<p>Statin-free </p>

<p>Statin-free </p>

<p>Statin-free </p>

<p>p=0.032 </p>

<p>p=NS </p>

<p>p=0.027 </p>

<p>p=0.021 </p>

<p>p=NS </p>

<p>p=0.038 </p>

<p>p=NS </p>

<p>Statin </p>

<p>Statin </p>

<p>Statin </p>

<p>Statin </p>

<p>TT </p>

<p>TT </p>

<p>TT </p>

<p>TT </p>

<p>TT </p>

<p>TT </p>

<p>TT </p>

<p>TT </p>

<p>Adiponectin </p>

<p>LDLc (mg/dL) </p>

<p>TG/HDL </p>

<p>HDL3b </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.6.1604 </p>

<p>Jung Ran Choi, et al. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Correlation of adiponectin and clinical variables according to genotype distribution of rs3865188. Body mass index (BMI) was negatively correlated 
with adiponectin in only the AA genotype (p=0.009) in contrast to the TT genotype in statin group; meanwhile, AT genotype can be offset by TT genotype, 
compared to AA and TT genotype (A and B). Plasma adiponectin was related with TG in A allele of patients taking statin (C and D), and it was related with 
TG/HDL ratio in the AT genotype in statin-free group. However, with statin treatment, the effect of AT genotype disappeared (E and F). TG, triglyceride; 
HDL, high-density lipoprotein. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>20.00 </p>

<p>15.00 </p>

<p>10.00 </p>

<p>5.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>20.00 </p>

<p>15.00 </p>

<p>10.00 </p>

<p>5.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>20.00 </p>

<p>15.00 </p>

<p>10.00 </p>

<p>5.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>25.00 </p>

<p>20.00 </p>

<p>15.00 </p>

<p>10.00 </p>

<p>5.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>25.00 </p>

<p>20.00 </p>

<p>15.00 </p>

<p>10.00 </p>

<p>5.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>25.00 </p>

<p>20.00 </p>

<p>15.00 </p>

<p>10.00 </p>

<p>5.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>15.00 20.00 25.00 30.00 35.00 40.00 </p>

<p>0.00 
100.00 200.00 300.00 400.00 500.00 </p>

<p>0.00 
5.00 
10.00 15.00 20.00 25.00 </p>

<p>15.00 
20.00 
25.00 
30.00 
35.00 </p>

<p>0.00 
200.00 
400.00 
600.00 </p>

<p>0.00 
5.00 
10.00 15.00 20.00 25.00 </p>

<p>BMI </p>

<p>TG </p>

<p>TG/HDL ratio </p>

<p>BMI </p>

<p>TG </p>

<p>TG/HDL ratio </p>

<p>Statin-free group 
Statin group </p>

<p>Adiponectin </p>

<p>Adiponectin </p>

<p>Adiponectin </p>

<p>Adiponectin </p>

<p>Adiponectin </p>

<p>Adiponectin </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.6.1604 </p>



<p>CDH13 Gene and Statin on TG/HDL in CVD </p>

<p>ciated with increased promoter activity, and also plays a cru-
cial role in its expression. 
18,19 Even though rs3865188 is not lo-
cated in the promoter region of CDH13, we demonstrated in 
the present study that this variant is positively associated with 
adiponectin levels. 
18 This is similar to the findings of previous 
studies, and our results suggest that the CDH13 variant 
rs3865188 may regulate adiponectin levels. The traditional 
cardiovascular risk factors, including age, sex, hypertension, 
smoking, hypercholesterolemia, and body mass index, have 
been reported. 
20 Another study investigated the role of T-cad-
herin expression in regulating adiponectin levels, and the in-
volvement of CDH13 or adiponectin levels in the development 
of cardiometabolic diseases. 
11 Furthermore, several reports 
have found that CDH13 variants have modulating effects on 
metabolic traits, and they increase the risk of metabolic syn-
drome, diabetes mellitus, and ischemic stroke. In contrast to 
these previous studies, rs3865188 variants were not associated 
with risk of cardiometabolic diseases including dyslipidemia 
in our study. However, TG, TG/HDL, and adiponectin levels ac-
cording to CDH13 genotypes or allele types might be changed 
by statin administration. This suggests that increases in plas-
ma adiponectin levels upon statin administration are strongly 
associated with particular genes. 
We also found that CDH13 SNP (rs3865188) is strongly as-
sociated with metabolic traits, including BP and plasma levels 
of FBS, insulin, and TG and that adiponectin levels are not neg-
atively associated with dyslipidemia described by TG/HDL. 
Recently, an association between a CDH13 SNP and BP was 
identified in a subsequent genome-wide association study. In 
particular, carriers of the minor allele of CDH13 rs11646213 
showed a decreased risk of hypertension, while carriers of 
rs3096277 and rs254340 (located in intron 11) showed an as-
sociation with BP. 
21 Evidence of the involvement of CDH13 in 
BP regulation was demonstrated in another population-based 
cohort (Framingham Heart Study). 
21 In hypertension subjects, 
minor allele carriers of rs12444338 had a lower risk of hyper-
tension, although the association was marginal after adjusting 
for confounders. In addition, the mean carotid intima-media 
thickness (IMT) was significantly associated with rs12444338 
(p=0.02) and rs1048612 (p=0.02). 
22 In this study, genotypes of 
the SNP rs3865188 were also associated with DBP. Interest-
ingly, we observed lower insulin levels with increased adipo-
nectin levels in statin-treated subjects with the T allele, com-
pared to statin-free groups with the A allele. CDH13 strongly 
influences circulating adiponectin levels and is associated 
with a beneficial metabolic profile: the positive relationship 
between adiponectin and insulin sensitivity in East Asian 
populations appears to be causal. 
23 In the present study, plas-
ma adiponectin levels were negatively associated with TG and 
TG/HDL ratio in patients with the AT genotype in the statin-
free group. In the statin group, however, the effect of the AT 
genotype disappeared, because adiponectin levels was in-
creased by statin administration. We found that statin treat-</p>

<p>ment significantly decreased TC, LDLc, TG/HDL ratio, and 
HDL3b fraction, compared to statin-free individuals, and in-
creased adiponectin in persons having mutant alleles of the 
CDH13 gene. In general, a shifting toward small-sized HDL 
was changed by serum TG or TC elevation. Besides, serum TG 
level is a more important factor to change the components of 
small HDL such as HDL3b or HDL3c, compared to serum TC 
level. 
16 Even though we do not know whether adiponectin 
causes these lipid abnormalities and, thus, whether it is partly 
responsible for atherogenic risk, high TG/HDL is associated 
with low plasma adiponectin concentrations in nondiabetic 
women. 
24 In our study, the interaction between CDH13 gene 
and statin may effect HDL subpopulations according to chang-
ing plasma TG and TC levels. 
Many studies have revealed that statin administered before 
or after CAD or stroke onset can decrease mortality and en-
hance the short-term and/or long-term outcomes of ischemic 
stroke. 
25,26 However, inflammation is not included in the list of 
classic risk factors for atherosclerosis, although it seems to be 
an additional important therapeutic target for the reduction of 
cardiovascular risk. The secretion of biologically active mole-
cules including MCP-1 has an ominous impact on atherogen-
esis. Nevertheless, adiponectin has a protective effect against 
the development of cardiovascular disease, and its levels are 
reduced in metabolic syndrome. 
27,28 The use of drugs such as 
statin for treating dyslipidemia and its modifying effects on 
lipid profiles has been the focus of recent studies, which sug-
gest that therapeutic targeting of inflammation may be used as 
a strategy to decrease cardiovascular risk. 
29 Some reports show 
that the use of rosuvastatin, a HMG-CoA reductase inhibitor, 
leads to a significant reduction in cardiovascular events in in-
dividuals without dyslipidemia with elevated high-sensitivity 
C-reactive protein levels, a marker of systemic inflammation. </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>In the present study, statin did not affect inflammatory cyto-
kines, such as MCP-1, leptin, visfatin, IL-6, and TNF-α. Mean-
while, patients in the statin group with the TT genotype exhib-
ited higher MCP-1 levels than those in the statin-free group. 
Since plasma adiponectin level was increased by statin in TT 
genotypes, we assumed that adiponectin and MCP-1 was bal-
anced to offset the increased CVD. 
The impact of genetic polymorphisms on statin treatment ef-
ficacy has been analyzed in several clinical trials, and the vari-
ants in more than 30 different genes have been investigated. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Even though knowledge obtained in this field is quickly grow-
ing, results have not been replicated in larger patient groups. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Only the APOE4 allele has been shown to be associated with a 
poor response to statin treatment. Other genes examined in-
clude only APOA5 or cholesterol 7-α hydroxylase. One report 
detected a potential variant within the APOE/C1/C3 gene clus-
ter that could influence statin treatment efficacy, and another 
pilot study suggested that the rs4149056 variant within the SL-
CO1B1 gene had possible sex-dependent effects on statin treat-
ment efficacy. 
31 CDH13 is highly expressed in several tissues, </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.6.1604 </p>

<p>Jung Ran Choi, et al. </p>

<p>including the heart, aortic wall, neurons of the brain cortex and 
spinal cord, and small blood vessels, as well as in a variety of 
cell types, such as vascular endothelial cells, smooth muscle 
cells, pericytes, cardiomyocytes, and cancer cells. 
11,32 Reports 
on cellular signaling have observed that both LDL and adipo-
nectin are specific ligands for T-cadherin, a product of CDH13. 
The binding of LDL or adiponectin to T-cadherin stimulates the 
nuclear factor-κB signaling pathway, which plays an important 
role in inflammation, and serves as a link between obesity and 
vascular disease. 
19,33 In addition, T-cadherin might modulate 
vascular remodeling, neointima formation, inflammation-re-
lated phenomena, and atherosclerosis development by regu-
lating the adiponectin levels in the blood and various tissues. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>In the present study, we showed the contribution of variants of 
CDH13 to statin treatment efficacy. However, the genetic ef-
fects of CDH13 rs3865188 and the complexity of the develop-
ment of cardiometabolic diseases was not evaluated in the 
present study, because there was not enough data to demon-
strate an association between one variant of CDH13 and statin 
treatment. 
There are several limitations of this study. First, we could 
not find any reports that provided an explanation of the asso-
ciation between the CDH13 polymorphism and statin treat-
ment efficacy. There is abundant research demonstrating the 
association of adiponectin levels and the CDH13 gene in sev-
eral populations. However, we observed that studies in which 
genes that affect statin treatment efficacy have been identi-
fied, including the APOE/C1/C3 gene cluster, do not provide 
sufficient data to demonstrate the association of CDH13 and 
statin treatment. A similar problem was encountered in our 
study. Second, only one variant of CDH13 (rs3865188) was ex-
amined in our study; this is not sufficient to effectively evalu-
ate the association between the CDH13 gene and adiponectin 
levels. Third, we did not perform any analysis to predict the ef-
fects of pharmacotherapy, and the individual efficacy of a 
drug was determined through genetic analysis only. 
In the present study, we found that the genotypes of CDH13 
play a crucial role in regulating adiponectin levels with plasma 
lipid profiles undergoing statin treatment in Korean CVD and 
dyslipidemia patients. The results of genetic analyses con-
ducted in the future may help clinicians select the most effec-
tive and safe treatment for each individual patient. Although 
the economical and health benefits of such approaches are 
evident, we are still at the early stages of this research and only 
beginning to understand the genetic factors that determine 
statin treatment efficacy. Nevertheless, the novel variations 
within CDH13 may be utilized for better clinical management 
of coronary artery diseases in the future. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study was funded by the Ministry of Health and Welfare 
(A000385) and Mid-career Researcher Program through NRF </p>

<p>grant funded by the MEST (2010-0000147), Republic of Korea. </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.6.1604 </p>





</text></tei>