<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4411514" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs id="software-1" type="software">FlowJo</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">ver. 7.6.5</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Tree Star</rs><rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPadPrism4</rs>Figure 2. Treatment with vp-genkwa 
after HSV-1 infection reduces viral 
replication. (A) Effect of vp-genkwa 
pretreatment on HSV-1 replication. 
(B) Effect of vp-genkwa post-
treatment on HSV-1 replication. 
Groups of BALB/c mice (n=5) were 
infected i.vag. with HSV-1 after (A) 
and before (B) oral administration of 
vp-genkwa (10 mpk). Viral titers in 
vaginal lavages collected at 2 and 4 
dpi were determined by plaque 
assay. </p>

<p>in the control of viral secretion in vaginal lavages, whereas 
vp-genkwa treatment after HSV-1 infection reduced viral titers 
in vaginal lavages (Fig. 2). Thus, this result indicates that 
vp-genkwa treatment after HSV-1 infection might control 
HSV-1 replication in the vaginal tract. </p>

<p>Increased NK cell activity in vp-genkwa-treated 
mice following HSV-1 infection </p>

<p>Vaginal infiltration of innate leukocytes, such as granulocytes 
and monocytes/macrophages, are thought to contribute to 
HSV infection resistance via direct and indirect mechanisms 
(10,11). Moreover, NK cells reportedly play a crucial role in 
regulating vaginal inflammation caused by HSV-1 infection 
(4,5). Thus, we decided to explore the regulatory role of 
vp-genkwa treatment on NK cell activity. First, we determined 
the frequency and absolute number of CD3 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>NK1.1 </p>

<p>＋ </p>

<p>NKp46 </p>

<p>＋ </p>

<p>NK cells in the spleen of mice treated with vp-genkwa before 
and after HSV-1 infection 3 dpi. In spite of vp-genkwa treat-
ment before and after HSV-1 infection, our results did not in-
dicate any changes in the frequency or absolute number of 
NK cells, except that vp-genkwa treatment before HSV-1 in-
fection slightly increased the percentage of NK cells in the 
spleen (Fig. 3A). However, intriguingly, vp-genkwa treatment 
after HSV-1 infection increased the frequency and absolute 
number of IFN-γ-and granzyme B-producing NK cells, 
whereas pre-treatment with vp-genkwa before HSV-1 in-
fection did not affect the frequency or absolute number of 
IFN-γ-and granzyme B-producing NK cells (Fig. 3B and C). </p>

<p>These data indicate that vp-genkwa treatment after HSV-1 in-
fection increases NK cell activity because IFN-γ and gran-
zyme B expressed on activated NK cells are involved in erad-
icating virions and killing virus-infected cells. Supportively, 
secreted IFN-γ was detected at higher levels in vaginal lav-
ages of mice treated with vp-genkwa after HSV-1 infection, 
compared to that of mice treated with vehicle and vp-genkwa 
before HSV-1 infection (Fig. 4). Collectively, these results in-
dicate that the enhanced resistance of mice treated with 
vp-genkwa after HSV-1 infection is closely associated with in-
creased NK cell activity. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Examination of genital HSV infection using a murine model 
has significantly contributed to our understanding of the role 
of innate and adaptive immune cells during vaginal in-
flammation and CNS-invasion. In the present study, we dem-
onstrated using a murine infection model that treatment with 
vp-genkwa at optimal doses after, but not before, HSV-1 in-
fection provides enhanced resistance, as reflected by reduced 
mortality and clinical severity. Further, the reduction in viral 
secretion in vaginal lavages of mice treated with vp-genkwa 
after infection supported the observed decrease in the clinical 
signs caused by mucosal HSV-1 infection. Interestingly, the 
reduction in mortality and clinical signs in mice treated with 
vp-genkwa after viral infection was closely associated with 
enhanced NK cell activation, which indicates the involvement </p>

<p>Anti-herpes Activity of Vp-genkwa by NK Cell Activation 
Erdenebileg Uyangaa, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 15, No. 2: 91-99, April, 2015 </p>

<p>
Figure 3. Enhancement of NK cell activity in vp-genkwa-treated mice 
following HSV-1 infection. (A) The frequency and absolute number 
of NK cells in the spleen of mice treated with vp-genkwa. The 
splenocytes were prepared from mice that were pre-and post-treated 
with vp-genkwa (10 mpk) 3 dpi, and used to enumerate NK cells 
(CD3 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>NK1.1 </p>

<p>＋ </p>

<p>NKp46 </p>

<p>＋ </p>

<p>) using FACS analysis. The left graph denotes 
the average percentage of NK cells in the spleen, and the right graph 
shows the absolute number of NK cells in the spleens of four mice 
per group. (B and C) The frequency and absolute number of NK cells 
producing IFN-γ and granzyme B. The splenocytes were prepared 
from mice pre-and post-treated with vp-genkwa 3 dpi and stimulated 
with PMA plus ionomycin. The frequency and absolute number of 
IFN-γ-(B) and granzyme B (C; GrB)-producing cells in NK cells (CD3 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>NK1.This study was supported by a National Research Foundation 
of Korea (NRF) grant, funded by the Korea Government 
(MISP) (2012R1A2A1A03670284). The funder had no role in 
study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, 
or preparation of manuscript. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors have no financial conflict of interest. </p>



<p>Anti-herpes Activity of Vp-genkwa by NK Cell Activation 
Erdenebileg Uyangaa, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 15, No. 2: 91-99, April, 2015 </p>

<p>
J. Bozzola, and E. L. Parr. 1994. A mouse model for studies 
of mucosal immunity to vaginal infection by herpes simplex </p>

<p>virus type 2. Lab. Invest. 70: 369-380. </p>

<p>11. Uyangaa, E., A. M. Patil, and S. K. Eo. 2014. Prophylactic 
and therapeutic modulation of innate and adaptive immunity </p>

<p>against mucosal infection of herpes simplex virus. Immune 
Netw. 14: 187-200. </p>



<p>Anti-herpes Activity of Vp-genkwa by NK Cell Activation 
Erdenebileg Uyangaa, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 15, No. 2: 91-99, April, 2015 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>