<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4219874" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: The development of microbial resistance to the existing anti-microbial agents has become a real 
challenge and a serious problem facing patients suffering from skin infections. Seeds of Nigella sativa have been 
used for a long time in folk medicine for the treatment of skin infections. Production of new potent agents is 
urgently needed, especially for hospitals and health care centers. This study is designed to explore anti-microbial 
effect of extract from the Nigella sativa seeds against skin pustules infection. 
Methods: The in vivo anti-microbial effect of the Nigella sativa seeds extract at a concentration of 33% on pus-
tules staphylococcal Skin Infections was assessed and compared with standard drug mupirocin on 40 neonates 
.All neonates were divided and examined into two experimental and control groups randomly. Recovery times 
were compared between two groups. 
Results: The mean of recovery time in experimental group was 75/1 with SD= ± 12, and the mean of recovery 
time in control group was 69/4 with SD = ± 8/7.There was no significant difference in recovery time between 
two groups (p value = 0/131). 
Conclusion: In clinical practice, the agent of Nigella Sativa recovered as pustular from tissues of all patients. 
While the extract was as nearly effective as the standard drug, mupirocin, no side effect was observed. </p>

<p>Keywords: Nigella sativa, Saphylococcal skin infection, Neonate. 
This clinical trial study has been registered in IRCT with 201104206243N code. </p>

<p>Cite this article as: Rafati S, Niakan M, Naseri M. Anti-microbial effect of Nigella sativa seed extract against staphylococcal skin Infec-</p>

<p>tion. Med J Islam Repub Iran 2014 (8 June). Vol. 28:42. </p>

<p>Introduction 
S. aurous is the most common cause of 
pyogenic infection of skin and soft tissue; 
causing impetigo, cellulitis, abscess, om-
phalitis. These infections may lead to seri-
ous local and systemic complications. Most 
neonates are colonized within the first week 
of life with S. aurous. Mupirocin is a bacte-
ricidal ointment used against localized in-
fection (1). However the developing mi-
crobial resistance to the existing anti-
microbial agents has become a serious 
problem. Resistance to Mupirocin has been 
reported in many infectious incidences (1-
2). Therefore, production of new potent 
agents is urgently needed, especially for </p>

<p>hospitals and health centers. It is well 
known that Seeds of Nigella sativa have 
been used for centuries as a traditional 
medicine for the treatment of various dis-
eases, including skin infections (2-3). 
Previous studies have shown the anti-
microbial effects of N. sativa seeds against 
different pathogenic microbes. The essen-
tial oil of the seeds have also dose-
dependent anti-bacterial effects on gram-
positive (S. aurous) and gram-negative (E. 
coli) bacteria (4). The fixed oil had more 
potent anti-bacterial effect against gram-
positive than gram-negative bacteria (5). 
The in vivo anti-microbial effect of the 
aqueous extract of N. sativa seeds was also </p>

<p>Nigella sativa, staphylococcus infection ,neonate </p>



<p>MJIRI, Vol. 28.42. 8 June 2014 </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>investigated in animals. Most studies on the 
anti-microbial potential of plant extracts, 
active ingredients and/or chemical drugs 
have been tested on experimental animals 
(2). 
The purpose of the present study was to 
examine the anti-microbial effect of N. sa-
tiva oil extract against patients with skin 
infections and to explore the effectiveness 
of extract on the clearance of cutaneous 
staphylococcal infection in neonates. </p>

<p>Methods 
A clinical trial study was designed and 
conducted on 40 icteric newborns with pus-
tular infection, with no other diseases, 23 
males, and 17 females, aged between 6-11 
days. 
Inclusion criteria: all included cases were 
healthy term neonates without fever and 
sepsis, or systemic involvement .They were 
hospitalized for indirect hyper biliru-
binemia. They had less than 11 pustules on 
neck, around the umbilicus, the inguinal or 
auxiliary but not on the face. During this 
course oral antibiotics or disinfectants were 
not used. 
Selection of Nigella sativa (NS): N. sativa 
were purchased from an herbal shop in Is-
fahan, Iran. Then Formulation of N. sativa 
was prepared by33% crude extract of N. 
sativa under cold pressure in department of 
pharmacology. The reference number and 
place of deposition of a voucher specimen 
of the plant material was PMP 708 from 
Faculty of Traditional Iranian Medicine, 
Tehran University of Medical Sciences, 
Iran. 
Because this was the first study in hu-
mans especially neonates, for prevention of 
any reaction, the concentraion of active 
component (Nigella) was low (33%) (2). 
In clinical studies a pediatrician visited 
neonates on admission and clinical diagno-
sis of purulent pustule was confirmed. She 
also visited all neonates three times a day 
and but no treatment was performed on ne-
onates. Informed consent obtained from </p>

<p>each patient parents included in the study 
and the study protocol conformed to the 
ethical guidelines of the 1975 Declaration 
of Helsinki as reflected in a priori approval 
by the shahed university research commit-
tee. 
Microbiologic sampling with a sterile 
swab was done on each child with Infec-
tions. Formulation of Nigella Sativa was 
used topically for twenty infants in the ex-
perimental group and Mupirocin for twenty 
infants in the control group. Two groups 
were selected by simple randome tech-
nique. In experimental group a drop of 
black seed extract was used topically three 
times daily on the skin lesions for 4 days. 
In control group a topical Mupirocin oint-
ment was used three times daily on the skin 
lesions for 4 days. Clinical results analyzed 
and a questionnaire was completed each 
day. Treatment in both groups was identi-
cal. Recovery identified by pediatric exam-
ination was; dry pustules with no pus or 
discharge. Pediatrician visited all neonates 
three times a day for further evaluation. 
The recovery times were recorded accord-
ing to hour. The mean of recovery times 
between the two groups were compared. 
Statistical analysis data were presented as 
means, and SD. Comparisons between 
groups were performed by using T-test, 
fisher exact test on a statistical software 
package (<rs type="software">SPSS</rs>). Differences between the 
groups considered significant, when p-
value was less than 0.05. </p>

<p>Results 
To detect effect of Nigella on cutaneous 
staphylococcal infection we compared Ni-
gella with mupirocin on cutaneous staphy-
lococcal infection. Neonatal weights were 
2/9-3/5 kg with ages of 6-11 days. Statis-
tical information of study and control 
groups is seen in Table 1. There was no 
significant difference in age between two 
groups. 
Types of bacteria isolated were seen in 
two groups are presented in Table 2. </p>

<p>S. Rafati, et al. </p>



<p>MJIRI, Vol. 28.42. 8 June 2014 </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>Antimicrobial effect of extract of Nigella 
with mupirocin was compared through re-
covery time (Table 3). The mean of recov-
ery time in experimental group was 75/1 
with SD= ± 12, and mean of recovery time 
in control group was 69/4 with SD= ± 8/7 
There was no significant difference in re-
covery time between two groups. p = 0/69. </p>

<p>Discussion 
This study explored the effect of black 
seed products on the Staphylococcus au-
rous and Staphylococcus epidermidis popu-
lations in neonates with skin pustules. Bac-
terial samples were collected from infants 
who were hospitalized. This study was 
evaluated based on comparing the recovery 
time. There was no significant difference in 
recovery time between two groups. 
Clinical study on the same field of black 
seed on the Staphylococcus infection in 
human are not found and the effect of this 
plant are found only on laboratory animals. 
In a study conducted on rat by Maryam, the 
extracts shown to have significant inhibito-
ry effect against gram-positive bacteria. 
However, the extract revealed an equal ef-
fect with the standard drug, on the clear-
ance of staphylococcal ATCC 29923 infec-
tion in vitro (2). </p>

<p>Other study done by Shahidi Benjar et al 
also investigated Black seed products indi-
cated a good effect on the standard Staphy-
lococcus aurous (6). 
In a study conducted by Niakan et al, the 
antimicrobial effect of oil extract of black 
seed against two common Staphylococcus 
aurous in laboratory was studied. They 
concluded that the anti-microbial effect of 
NS oil extract is comparable with antibiot-
ics such as Ceftazidime, Cefaclor, 
Cefamandole, Cefuroxime. They recom-
mend experimental use of NS. to control 
Staphylococcus aurous infection (7). 
G. Fico studied Antimicrobial activity of 
crude extracts, fractions and the essential 
oil. The antimicrobial screening was carried 
out against, Staphylococcus aurous 
(ATCC29213) and Staphylococcus epider-
midis (ATCC12228), for the essential oil. 
The essential oil showed antibacterial activ-
ity against Bacillus cereus and Staphylo-
coccus aurous (Gram positive bacteria) (8). 
Zuridah and colleges investigated in vitro 
antibacterial effects of seed extracts on 
standard gram positive and negative bacte-
rial strains. The best result was seen on S. 
aurous (9). 
Mashhadian studied the antibacterial and 
antifungal effects of extracts of the seeds </p>

<p>Table 1. Neonatal age in two groups of Nigella (GROUP 1) and Mupirocin (GROUP 2) 
Mean 
Standard 
Deviation 
Minimum Maximum 
p </p>

<p>Group 
Group 
1 
Age(day) 
8,45 
1,15 
7 
11 
0.875 
2 
Age(day) 
8,50 
0,83 
7 
10 </p>

<p>Table 2. Various bacteria in two groups of Nigella (GROUP 1) and Mupirocin (GROUP 2) 
Bacteria 
S aurous 
S epidermis 
Group 
1 
Count 
13 
7 
65.0% 
35.0% 
2 
Count 
15 
5 
75.0% 
25.0% 
Total 
Count 
28 
12 
30.0% </p>

<p>Table 3. Recovery time in two groups of Nigella (GROUP 1) and Mupirocin (GROUP 2) 
Mean 
Standard 
Deviation 
p value </p>

<p>Group 
1 
Recovery 
time (hr) 
75/1 
12 
0/69 </p>

<p>Group 
2 
Recovery 
time (hr) 
69/4 
8/7 </p>

<p>Nigella sativa, staphylococcus infection ,neonate </p>



<p>MJIRI, Vol. 28.42. 8 June 2014 </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>against common and hospital strains of 
Candida 
albicans, 
coagulase-positive 
Staphylococcus aurous and Pseudomonas 
aeroginosa and compared them with stand-
ard drugs such as clotrimazole, cloxacillin 
and gentamicin. Their results showed that 
NS extracts produce antimicrobial activity 
against a broad range of microbes and es-
pecially on multiple antibiotic resistant bac-
teria (4). 
M T Salman showed that NS seed oil 
possesses antimicrobial activity against 
several multidrug resistant pathogenic bac-
teria in vitro and may be used topically in 
susceptible cases. The oil showed pro-
nounced dose dependant antibacterial activ-
ity and being more effective against gram 
positive Staphylococcus aurous, S. epider-
midis than gram negative bacteria (5). </p>

<p>Conclusion 
This study indicated that the product of 
this plant in the treatment of localized in-
fection is almost similar to mupirocin. Our 
results are in agreement with others who 
showed that NS extracts produce antimi-
crobial activity against staphylococcal In-
fections. Therefore; further studies should 
be followed with better formula to evaluate 
the drug. </p>



</text></tei>