<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4273078" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:43+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. [Purpose] This study was performed to investigate the effects of yogic exercises on life stress and 
blood glucose levels in nursing students. [Subjects and Methods] The study was a randomized controlled trial. 
Twenty-seven undergraduate nursing students were randomly selected, with 12 assigned to an exercise group and 
15 assigned to a control group. The yogic exercises intervention was undertaken for 60 minutes one day a week for 
12 weeks. It consisted of physical exercise (surya namaskara) combined with relaxation and meditation (shavasana 
and yoga nidra). Life stress was measured by the Life Stress Scale for College Students, and postprandial blood glu-
cose levels were measured with a digital glucometer. [Results] The exercise group measurements were significantly 
decreased in both life stress and postprandial blood glucose levels compared with the control group. [Conclusion] 
These findings indicate that yogic exercises would reduce life stress and lower postprandial blood glucose levels in 
nursing students. 
Stress is a multidimensional and universal phenomenon. 
Stress in nursing students is common and is process orient-
ed. Nursing students are constantly under various stressors 
such as academic performance, isolation from the group, 
change in environment, change in food type, irregular diet, 
clinical challenges, economic problems, future prospects, 
problems with the value system of current society, self-ex-
pectations, and expectations from family and peers etc 1-6) . 
If these stressors are not managed properly, they can have 
negative effects on the physical and psychological health of 
nursing students 1-3) . Furthermore, these problems can cause 
academic failure and/or limited growth as a valuable em-
ployee 2, 4, 7) . Therefore, it is necessary to put in place vari-
ous activities and behaviors to prevent and reduce life stress 
in nursing students 4, 6-7) . 
All these stressors have adverse effects on the autonomic 
nervous system, pineal and hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal 
axis that interrupt the healthy operation of the homeostatic 
mechanisms of the body 8) . This has damaging effects on 
various parameters of the body, and one of the common 
parameters is blood glucose 2) . It is observed that stress in-
creases both short-term and long-term blood glucose levels, 
and if it increases one or both of them beyond the normal </p>

<p>limits, stress can cause persistent high blood glucose levels, 
resulting in diabetes mellitus 2) . 
There are various ways to reduce stress, and one of them 
is yoga. Yoga, which integrates various postures, breathing 
exercises, and meditation, is beneficial in reducing stress. 
The mechanisms by which yoga influences well-being are 
likely complex biochemical and physiological mechanisms 
consisting of reduced sympathetic nervous tone, activation 
of antagonistic neuromuscular systems, and stimulation 
of the limbic system 9) . Therefore, yoga has been reported 
to lower levels of sympathetic hormones. That is to say, 
breathing exercises during yoga practice reduce sympathet-
ic tone, increases parasympathetic activity, and help to re-
duce stress in yoga practictioners 10) . Meditation also brings 
about a hypometabolic state and reduces stress induced by 
sympathetic overactivity 11) . 
Also, yogic exercise has a direct influence on pancreatic 
secretion by rejuvenation of the pancreatic cells through 
alternate abdominal contractions and relaxation 12, 13) , and 
yogic exercise reduces blood glucose levels due to muscular 
exercise and relaxation 12, 13) . The dynamic stretching of the 
body during yoga asanas is postulated to rejuvenate pancre-
atic cells, increase insulin secretion, and hence correct the 
impaired insulin secretion in chronic diabetes 14) . Ultimate-
ly, yoga practice has been proven to affect mental balance of 
an individual by allying apprehension and stress and bring-
ing about hormonal balance and feelings of well-being 2) . 
In previous studies, researchers have indicated that yoga 
intervention played an effective role in decreasing stress 
and improving general well-being in medical students 2, 15) . 
In spite of its known positive effects on physical and psy-
chological variables, no studies have been conducted with </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. 
26: 2003-2006, 2014 </p>

<p>Corresponding author. Sang Dol Kim (E-mail: nu11110@ 
kangwon.ac.kr) </p>

<p>©2014 The Society of Physical Therapy Science. Published by IPEC Inc. </p>

<p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Cre-</p>

<p>ative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-</p>

<p>nd) License &lt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/&gt;. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 26, No. 12, 2014 </p>

<p>
yogic programs to manage nursing students' life stress. 
Hence, the purpose of this randomized controlled trial 
study was to evaluate the effect of yogic exercises on life 
stress and biochemical markers of stress such as blood glu-
cose levels in nursing students. </p>

<p>SUBJECTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>This study was a randomized controlled trial. The sub-
jects of this study were 27 healthy female undergraduate 
nursing students aged 20-23 years with no medical diseas-
es, no history of drug abuse, and no experience with yoga 
exercise. Participants having a family history of diabetes 
mellitus were excluded from the study. The participants 
were recruited by using our nursing department's Internet 
homepage. The subjects were all volunteer nursing stu-
dents. All participants received detailed information on 
the purpose and usefulness of this study and were provided 
a written consent form. After the participants signed the 
informed consent form, they were randomly assigned by 
a random permuted block design using a random number 
table, to 1 of 2 groups, either the yoga exercise (n=15) or 
control group (n=15). Twenty-seven subjects completed the 
entire study, 12 in the yoga exercise group and 15 in the 
control group. Three subjects dropped out of the study be-
fore completing the posttest due to personal reasons. The 
institutional review board of Kangwon National University 
approved this study. Demographic information, Life Stress 
Scale, and postprandial blood glucose levels were measured 
as pretest data. The Life Stress Scale and postprandial blood 
glucose levels were also measured as posttest data. 
Life Stress was measured by the Life Stress Scale for 
College Students 16) . This instrument consisted of 50 items 
scored using a 4-point Likert scale (0=never, 3=very of-
ten) measuring sources of life stress in 8 subscales-econ-
omy, lover, faculty, family, the future, values, grades, and 
friends. A higher score indicates a higher level of perceived 
stress. In this study, the internal consistency (Cronbach's 
alpha) of the Life Stress Scale was 0.93. 
After completing Life Stress Scale surveys, postpran-
dial blood glucose levels were measured as a stress-related </p>

<p>biomarker. Measurements were taken from the participants 
both before commencement of the study and also after the 
yogic intervention was over. Postprandial blood glucose 
levels were measured with a digital glucometer (Accu-
Chek. Sr. no-CN55303545723, Roche Diagnosis, Indianap-
olis, IN, USA). 
Yogic exercises were conducted for about one hour, once 
a week for 12 weeks. The yoga instructor was certificated 
by Bihar Yoga Bharati in India. The yogic exercises were 
done in the Department of Nursing. Cyclic form yoga ex-
ercises were chosen because of the availability of scientific 
studies on this type of yoga 17, 18) . Cyclic yoga exercises 
refers to surya namaskara and yoga nidra. Surya namas-
kara translates as "sun salutations," and this type of yoga 
is composed of 12 postures and breathing exercises. Also 
yoga nidra, which means "psychic sleep," is a specific yo-
gic relaxation and meditation practice 19) . The cyclic yoga 
performed in this study consisted of the following practices 
(Table 1). Under the guidance and supervision of the yoga 
expert, after practicing 10 cycles of surya namaskara for 20 
minutes, the subjects performed the shavasana pose for 5 
minutes of relaxation. Finally, the subjects performed yoga 
nidra. Yoga nidra is performed in the shavasana pose. It has 
several steps, such as resolve, rotation of consciousness, 
awareness of the breath, feeling and sensation, visualiza-
tion, and ending the practice with resolve. 
Statistical analyses were conducted using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> pro-
gram (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.1</rs>) for Windows. All data are presented as 
the mean ± SD. A t test was used to test for the homogene-
ity of demographic and clinical characteristics between the 
exercise and control group. Significant differences between 
groups were determined using unpaired t tests. Significant 
differences within groups were determined using paired t 
tests. The level of statistical significance was considered to 
be a probability value of less than 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>No significant differences in age were found between the 
yoga group and the control group (Table 2). There were no 
significant differences in the pre-intervention Life Stress </p>

<p>Table 1. Yogic exercise process </p>

<p>Step 1: surya namaskara (20 min/10 cycles) 
Step 2: shavasana (5 min) 
Step 3: yoga nidra (35 min/1 cycle) 
(postures and breathing exercise) 
(relaxation) 
(meditation and relaxation) </p>

<p>1. Pranamasana (prayer pose) 
1. Shavasana (corpse pose) 
1. Resolve 
2. Hasta Utthanasana (raised arms pose) 
2. Rotation of consciousness 
3. Padahastasana (hand to foot pose) 
3. Awareness of the breath 
4. Ashwa Sanchalanasana (equestrian pose) 
4. Feeling and sensation 
5. Parvatasana (mountain pose) 
5. Visualization 
6. Ashtanga Namaskara (salute with eight part) 
6. Ending the practice with resolve 
7. Bhujangasana (cobra pose) 
8. Parvatasana (mountain pose) 
9. Ashwa Sanchalanasana (equestrian pose) 
10. Padahastasana (hand to foot pose) 
11. Hasta Utthanasana (raised arms pose) 
12. Pranamasana (prayer pose) </p>



<p>Scale score or pre-intervention postprandial blood glucose 
level between the two groups (Table 2). 
The Life Stress Score significantly differed between the 
2 groups (yoga group vs. control group, p&lt;0.001) and over 
time (pretest vs. posttest, p&lt;0.001). For the yoga group, 
the mean post-intervention Life Stress score (mean ± SD, 
0.77 ± 0.49) was significantly decreased compared with the 
mean pre-intervention Life Stress score (mean ± SD, 1.6 ± 
0.3). Of the Life Stress subscales, the score for the grades 
subscale was the highest. The Life Stress subscale scores 
of economy, lover, family, the future, values, grades, and 
friends were decreased significantly in the yoga group after 
the yogic exercises, respectively (Table 3). 
The postprandial blood glucose level significantly dif-
fered between the 2 groups (yoga group vs. control group, 
p&lt;0.001) and over time (pretest vs. posttest, p&lt;0.05). For 
the yoga group, the mean post-intervention postprandial 
blood glucose level (mean ± SD, 81.3 ± 8.7) was signifi-
cantly decreased compared with the mean pre-intervention 
postprandial blood glucose level (mean ± SD, 90.0 ± 11.4). 
For the control group, the mean post-intervention postpran-
dial blood glucose level (mean ± SD, 103.4 ± 8.2) was signif-
icantly increased compared with the mean pre-intervention 
postprandial blood glucose level (mean ± SD, 89.6 ± 9.9) 
(Table 3). </p>

<p>DISSCUSSION </p>

<p>As shown in the study results, after 12 weeks of yogic 
exercises, Life Stress Scale scores were significantly de-
creased compared with those before starting yoga practice. 
Additionally, nursing students in the yoga exercise group 
had a significant decrease in their stress levels over this 12-
week period, while those in the control group had an in-
crease in their stress levels. These findings are similar to 
the findings of Simard and Henry, who found that Perceived 
Stress Scale levels significantly decreased from baseline to 
mid-term, an improvement that persisted to the end of the 
intervention 15) . They assessed the impact of a short yoga 
intervention on female medical students' health for a 16-</p>

<p>week period. They also pointed out that a yoga intervention 
may be effective in decreasing stress and improving gen-
eral well-being in medical students. Besides, the findings of 
Beets &amp; Mitchell indicated that despite short yoga program 
exposure, acute changes in mental health indicators such as 
stress were observed 20) . Similarly, the findings of Yoshihara 
et al. suggested that yoga can improve mental health status 
and has implications for the prevention of psychosomatic 
symptoms in healthy women 17) . In addition, Sharma sys-
tematically reviewed 17 articles related to yoga for stress 
management 8) . As a result, they reported that of the 17 stud-
ies, 12 demonstrated positive changes in psychological or 
physiological outcomes related to stress. Like the previous 
studies, the present study also supports the paradigm that 
yoga exercise can have beneficial effects in reducing psy-
chological problems such as stress in nursing students. 
Of the Life Stress subscales in this study, the grades sub-
scale had the highest score. This result is inconsistent with 
the concept that academic factors are a greater perceived 
cause of stress in nursing students 1, 5, 6) . Over the past 2 
decades, many forms of intervention have been suggested 
to help nursing students with their stress. Most recently, 
one researcher recommended biofeedback, humor, peer in-
structors, mentors, and mindfulness training interventions 
for stress centered around academic challenges in nursing 
students 2, 5, 6, 21-23) . However, no recent studies have been 
conducted with a new generation of yoga exercises to help </p>

<p>Table 2. Homogeneity test for age, life stress, and blood glucose 
level between the experimental and control group </p>

<p>Variables 
Experimental 
group Mean ± SD </p>

<p>Control group 
Mean ± SD </p>

<p>Age (years) 
21.0 ± 0.2 
21.0 ± 0.3 
Life stress (score) 
1.6 ± 0.3 
1.6 ± 0.3 
Economy 
1.6 ± 0.5 
1.7 ± 0.5 
Lover 
1.3 ± 0.4 
1.4 ± 0.4 
Faculty 
1.2 ± 0.8 
1.3 ± 0.8 
Family 
1.3 ± 0.4 
1.2 ± 0.4 
Future 
2.0 ± 0.4 
1.9 ± 0.3 
Value 
1.8 ± 0.6 
1.9 ± 0.5 
Grades 
2.4 ± 0.4 
2.2 ± 0.5 
Friend 
1.3 ± 0.4 
1.1 ± 0.3 
PPG (mg/dl) 
90.0 ± 11.5 
89.6 ± 9.9 </p>

<p>PPG: postprandial blood glucose, SD: standard deviation </p>

<p>Table 3. Effects of yogic exercises on life stress and postprandial 
blood glucose level </p>

<p>Group 
Pretest 
Posttest </p>

<p>Difference 
(Posttest-
pretest) 
Mean ± SD Mean ± SD 
Mean ± SD </p>

<p>Life stress 
(score) </p>

<p>Yoga 
1.6 ± 0.3 
0.7 ± 0.4*** −0.8 ± 0.6*** 
Control 
1.6 ± 0.3 
1.7 ± 0.2 
0.1 ± 0.3 
Economy Yoga 
1.6 ± 0.5 
0.6 ± 0.5*** −1.0 ± 0.6*** 
Control 
1.7 ± 0.5 
1.9 ± 0.5 
0.1 ± 0.5 
Lover 
Yoga 
1.2 ± 0.4 
0.5 ± 0.5** −0.7 ± 0.7** 
Control 
1.4 ± 0.4 
1.5 ± 0.6 
0.1 ± 0.7 
Faculty 
Yoga 
1.1 ± 0.7 
0.1 ± 0.2*** −1.0 ± 0.7 
Control 
1.2 ± 0.8 
0.6 ± 0.7 
−0.6 ± 1.1 
Family 
Yoga 
1.2 ± 0.3 
0.5 ± 0.5** −0.7 ± 0.6*** 
Control 
1.2 ± 0.4 
1.4 ± 0.4 
0.1 ± 0.4 
Future 
Yoga 
2.0 ± 0.3 
1.1 ± 0.7** −0.8 ± 0.8*** 
Control 
1.8 ± 0.3 
2.1 ± 0.3 
0.2 ± 0.4 
Values 
Yoga 
1.8 ± 0.5 
0.7 ± 0.6*** −1.0 ± 0.7*** 
Control 
1.9 ± 0.5 
2.2 ± 0.3 
0.2 ± 0.6 
Grades 
Yoga 
2.4 ± 0.4 
1.6 ± 0.7* 
−0.7 ± 0.8*** 
Control 
2.2 ± 0.5 
2.6 ± 0.3 
0.3 ± 0.5 
Friends 
Yoga 
1.2 ± 0.3 
0.6 ± 0.5** −0.6 ± 0.6*** 
Control 
1.1 ± 0.3 
1.2 ± 0.3 
0.1 ± 0.3 
PPG 
(mg/dl) </p>

<p>Yoga 
90.0 ± 11.4 81.3 ± 8.7** −8.7 ± 7.5*** 
Control 89.6 ± 9.9 103.4 ± 8.2** 13.8 ± 13.7 </p>

<p>*p&lt;0.05; **p&lt;0.01; ***p&lt;0.001; PPG: postprandial blood glu-
cose level, SD: standard deviation </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 26, No. 12, 2014 </p>

<p>
reduce nursing students' stress. Ultimately, these findings 
suggest that the nursing students in the yoga exercise group 
were able to control the same level of stress over the 12-
week period even though they experienced more stressors 
and demands from their academic conditions. It is very im-
portant for nurse educators to help nursing students manage 
their stress in order to prevent additional problems. 
In the present study, the postprandial blood glucose level 
was measured as a biochemical indicator of stress. Fasting 
blood sugar levels could not be checked because of the time 
of the yoga class as the participants' personal situations. 
The yoga class started at 5 PM every Thursday. 
After practicing yoga for 12 weeks, postprandial blood 
glucose levels were significantly decreased in the yoga 
group. This finding is similar to that of Shende et al., who 
found that both fasting and postprandial blood glucose lev-
els were significantly improved in the yoga group, whereas 
there was no significant improvement in the postprandial 
blood glucose levels in their control group not practicing 
yoga pranayama 4) . They assessed the effect of pranayama 
on the blood glucose level of 60 medical students and found 
that a short-term intervention of yogic exercise helps in 
reducing the stress in medical students, which is reflected 
by improvement in both fasting and postprandial blood 
glucose levels. They also emphasized that the beneficial 
effects of yoga on fasting and postprandial blood glucose 
levels are well documented. As stated, most of these stud-
ies have been done on patients with known diseases. How-
ever, there is very little data available on the effect of yoga 
exercise composed of surya namaskara (which means sun 
salutations) and yoga nidra (which means psychic sleep) on 
the blood glucose levels in healthy subjects. The findings 
of the present study also support those of Jensen, Stevens, 
and Kenny, who stated that yoga nidra is related to psycho-
neuro-physiological parameters 24) . Numerous studies have 
shown yoga to have an immediate downregulating effect 
on both the pineal and hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis 
responses to stress 12-15) . The performance of asana led to 
increased sensitivity of the B cells of the pancreas to the 
glucose signal. It also increased the sensitivity of the pro-
gressive long-term effect of asanas. Therefore, it was also 
found that brief yoga-based relaxation training normalizes 
the functions of the autonomic nervous system 15) . As shown 
in previous studies, the findings of the present study suggest 
that yogic exercises can improve stress and stress biomark-
ers in nursing students. However, follow-up studies will be 
needed to evaluate the effect on biochemical parameters 
of stress such as cortisol and blood glucose in nursing stu-
dents. To my knowledge, this is the first study to demon-
strate the effect of yoga exercise on the blood glucose level 
of healthy nursing students. 
The present study has some limitations. Use of only fe-
male subjects meant that we could not make comparisons 
between males and females. The participants were not on a 
strict and uniform diet plan, and this may have influenced 
the study results. Despite these limitations, these findings 
suggest that cyclic yoga exercise can improve not only the 
score of Life Stress, but also the postprandial blood glucose 
level in nursing students. </p>



</text></tei>