<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4266938" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>a b s t r a c t 
Objective. To evaluate gastrointestinal and cardiovascular adverse event risks associated with optical colonoscopy 
(OC) among Medicare outpatients who received computed tomography colonography (CTC) as their initial method 
of colorectal evaluation. Methods. Medicare claims were compared between 6114 outpatients ≥66 years who 
. 
OC patients were matched on county of residence and year of evaluation. Outcomes included lower gastrointestinal 
bleeding, gastrointestinal perforation, other gastrointestinal events and cardiovascular events resulting in an 
emergency department visit or hospitalization within 30 days. Results. Among 1000 outpatients undergoing 
initial CTC, 12.4 experienced lower gastrointestinal bleeding, 0.7 perforation, 18.0 other gastrointestinal events 
and 45.5 cardiovascular events within 30 days. After multivariate adjustment, risks of lower gastrointestinal 
bleeding, other gastrointestinal events and cardiovascular events were higher with initial OC than CTC, with 
or without subsequent OC (Odds Ratio 1.91 95 Confidence Interval [1.47,2.49], Odds Ratio 1.35 95 Confidence 
Interval [1.07,1.69] and Odds Ratio 1.38 95 Confidence Interval [1.18,1.62], respectively); however, perforation 
risk did not differ (p = 0.10). This pattern is similar in older and symptomatic populations. Conclusion. Rates of 
gastrointestinal bleeding, other gastrointestinal events and cardiovascular events are lower following initial CTC 
than OC, but rates of perforation do not differ. 
Preventive Medicine Reports </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : h t t p : / / e e s . e l s e v i e r . c o m / p m e d r </p>

<p>without biopsy (Warren et al., 2009; Rutter et al., 2012; Levin et al., 
2006)) driven by the findings of the CTC. To provide clinical context 
CTC patients were compared to a cohort of patients who received initial 
OC and also stratified by asymptomatic (i.e. screening) and symptomatic 
(i.e. diagnostic) indications (Pickhardt, 2006; Atkin et al., 2013). </p>

<p>Materials &amp; methods </p>

<p>Design overview </p>

<p>This Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act compliant 
study using de-identified Medicare claims data was exempt from institu-
tional review board approval. We performed a retrospective cohort study 
of all Medicare beneficiaries ≥ 66 years of age in the United States with a 
claim for CTC between January 2007 and December 2008 and a randomly selected 
group of patients with a claim for OC during the same time period, matched 9:1 by 
county of residence and year of colorectal evaluation. Approximately 98% of 
adults in the United States ages 65 and older are enrolled in Medicare, making 
Medicare data a robust source of health care utilization (RDA Center, 2012). 
Adverse events resulting in an emergency department visit or inpatient admission 
30 days following either procedure were determined from Medicare Provider 
Analysis and Review, Outpatient and Carrier files using appropriate Current 
Procedural Terminology/Healthcare Common Procedure Coding System 
(CPT/HCPCS) and International Classification of Disease, Ninth Edition, Clinical 
Modification (ICD-9-CM) codes (e-Table 1). We used a 30 day time interval for 
the assessment of complications to ensure a comparable follow-up interval in 
both cohorts based on prior data about complications from OC (Warren et al., 
2009). Claims were also used to identify comorbidities associated with increased 
likelihood of adverse events in the year preceding either CTC or OC and 
comparable adverse events in the preceding 90 days. The analysis focused on pa-
tients who had either initial CTC, defined as no OC on the same day or within the 
prior 12 months, or initial OC, defined as no OC within the prior 12 months. Al-
though 14% of the initial CTC patients in our study underwent OC within the 
12 months after CTC, similar to published rates of 13-15% in the literature (Kim 
et al., 2010; Macari et al., 2011), only 3% (187/6114) of initial CTC patients received 
OC within 30 days. Due to this small sample size a separate analysis of adverse 
events among patients who received OC within 30 days of CTC was not performed. 
However, additional analyses stratified patients by asymptomatic (i.e. screening) 
and symptomatic (i.e. diagnostic) indications using ICD-9 codes from the CTC or 
OC claim, based on a previously utilized algorithm (Ko et al., 2010; Zafar et al., 
2013); a full list of codes is provided in e-Table 1. </p>

<p>Setting and participants </p>

<p>We excluded patients (a) enrolled in a Medicare Health Maintenance 
Organization within the year preceding or 30 days following CTC (n = 7429); 
or (b) disenrolled from Medicare Part A or B coverage during the same time 
interval (n = 558). Similar to prior methodology (Warren et al., 2009), we 
excluded patients with a significant prior colonic disease that increased the 
risk of perforation including Crohn's disease or ulcerative colitis (n = 2067), 
prior colorectal cancer (n = 6385), or diverticulitis in the preceding year 
(n = 11,169). Because the objective of our study was to evaluate patients 
who received CTC as the first method of colorectal evaluation we excluded 
patients who received CTC with OC either in the prior 12 months (n = 3595) 
or on the same day (n = 3197). Similarly, OC patients who received OC within 
the prior 12 months were excluded (n = 1994). We also excluded patients with 
more than one OC within 30 days of the initial OC or CTC (n = 6). Eighteen 
patients were excluded for CTC claims in the year preceding OC or CTC and 
thirteen patients were excluded for incomplete billing data. No patients 
were excluded on the basis of an incomplete procedure. The final study 
population was comprised of 153,316 patients (Fig. 1). These 153,316 patients 
included 3609 CTC and 115,691 OC patients from a prior publication (Zafar 
et al., 2013). Differences in study populations are due to inclusion and/or 
exclusion criteria stemming from the disparate foci of these publications. </p>

<p>Outcomes and follow-up </p>

<p>Four groups of adverse events requiring emergency department visits or 
inpatient admissions were identified in the 30 days following either procedure: 
lower gastrointestinal bleeding or administration of blood transfusions (excluding </p>

<p>patients with transfusions performed 90 days prior to either procedure), gastro-
intestinal perforation, other gastrointestinal events (paralytic ileus, nausea, 
vomiting and dehydration, abdominal pain), and cardiovascular events (myocar-
dial infarction or angina; arrhythmias; congestive heart failure [CHF]; cardiac or 
respiratory arrest; or syncope, hypotension, or shock). These adverse events 
were chosen as they have been associated with complications of OC, which is 
the traditional method of colorectal evaluation. Similar adverse events in the 
90 days preceding CTC or OC were also recorded. Death within 30 days was 
evaluated, although cause of death cannot be inferred from claims data. 
We accounted for common comorbidities associated with these adverse 
events using claims data from the year preceding CTC or OC including: atrial 
fibrillation/flutter, congestive heart failure,chronic pulmonary disease, stroke, 
diabetes, renal failure, diverticulosis, and obesity (Rabeneck et al., 2008; 
Warren et al., 2009; Lohsiriwat, 2010). 
Sociodemographic characteristics including gender, age, and race were 
obtained from beneficiary summary files. Age was categorized into three groups 
(66-74, 75-84, and ≥85 years) and race into five groups (White, Black, Hispanic, 
Asian, and other). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Chi-square analysis was used to compare sociodemographic and clinical 
characteristics, unadjusted risks of adverse events, and mortality within 
30 days between patients who received initial CTC and OC. Unadjusted 
risks of adverse events were included as these data have not been previously 
reported using claims data. Given the cohort study design a generalized linear 
regression with a logit link and binomial distribution was used to estimate the 
odds ratios (OR) of adverse events between patients undergoing CTC and OC by 
indication (i.e. symptomatic versus asymptomatic) controlling for differences in 
patient characteristics including gender, age, race, comorbidities associated with 
studied adverse events, and adverse events in the preceding 90 days. Due to 
low event rates for the targeted adverse events there is limited concern of 
overestimation of the risk ratio, which is approximated by the OR in cohort 
studies. Statistical significance was declared for results with a two-sided p-value 
of b 0.05. We used <rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 11</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">STATA Corp</rs>) for all statistical analyses. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The final cohort included 6114 initial CTC outpatients with a mean 
age of 76.7 years (age range, 66-103 years; 2223 males [mean age 77; 
age range 66-96]; 3891 females [mean age 77; age range 66-103]) 
and 149,202 initial OC outpatients with a mean age of 74.4 years (age 
range, 66-104 years; 67,586 males [mean age 74; age range 66-101]; 
81,616 females [mean age 75; age range 66-104]). Women, patients 
N75 years of age and Whites were more likely to receive CTC as their 
initial method of colorectal evaluation than OC (Table 1). Patients 
undergoing initial CTC had a higher prevalence of comorbidities than 
patients undergoing initial OC, except for diabetes, diverticulosis and 
obesity. Among patients referred to initial CTC, with or without OC in 
the subsequent 30 days, the unadjusted risk of lower gastrointestinal 
bleeding per 1000 patients was 12.4, of perforation was 0.7, of other 
gastrointestinal events was 18.0 and of cardiovascular events was 
45.5. Of note, perforation rates were low in both cohorts (4/6114 
[0.7%] initial CTC and 181/149,202 [1.2%], initial OC). Similar proportions 
of patients died within 30 days in both cohorts. 
Multivariate regression was performed to account for differences in 
gender, age, race, comorbidities associated with adverse events, and 
adverse events in the preceding 90 days. This revealed a higher risk of 
lower gastrointestinal bleeding, other gastrointestinal events and 
cardiovascular events among patients who underwent initial OC 
compared to initial CTC in the subsequent 30 days (OR 1.91 95CI 
[1.47,2.49], OR 1.35 95CI [1.07,1.69] and OR 1.38 95CI [1.18,1.62], 
respectively), but no difference in the risk of perforation (Table 2). 
Similarly, even with adjustment for age, patients greater than 75 years 
who received either CTC or OC demonstrated a higher risk of lower 
gastrointestinal bleeding, other gastrointestinal events, and cardiovascu-
lar events than patients less than 75 years (OR 2.98 95CI [2.61,3.41], OR 
1.39 95CI [1.26,1.53], and OR 1.44 95CI [1.33,1.55], respectively). </p>

<p> 
H.M. Zafar et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 1 (2014) 3-8 </p>

<p>We also examined whether this pattern differed depending on the 
presence of symptoms. Higher unadjusted adverse event rates per 
1000 patients were demonstrated among those with symptoms relative 
to those without symptoms within both cohorts (Table 3). Following 
adjustment for gender, age, race, comorbidities associated with adverse 
events, and adverse events in the preceding 90 days, symptomatic 
patients referred to initial OC were found to have higher adjusted 
rates of lower gastrointestinal bleeding, other gastrointestinal events 
and cardiovascular events compared to symptomatic patients referred 
to initial CTC, with or without OC in the subsequent 30 days (OR 1.92 
95CI [1.47, 2.51], OR 1.35 95CI [1.07,1.70], OR 1.43 95CI [1.22, 1.68], 
respectively) (Table 4). Again, even with adjustment for age, higher 
rates of lower gastrointestinal bleeding, other gastrointestinal events 
and cardiovascular events were demonstrated among symptomatic 
patients greater than 75 years compared to patients less than 75 years 
(OR 2.70 95CI [2.43,3.21], OR 1.77 95CI [1.53,2.05], OR 2.37 95CI 
[2.14,2.63], respectively) (Table 4). A similar pattern was observed 
within the asymptomatic cohort, but did not reach significance. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Our study demonstrates that patients ≥66 years of age who undergo 
initial CTC, with or without subsequent OC within 30 days, have lower </p>

<p>risks of lower gastrointestinal bleeding, other gastrointestinal events 
and cardiovascular events compared to patients who undergo initial OC. 
However, the risk of perforation does not differ between initial CTC and 
OC. This pattern is similar among symptomatic, asymptomatic and older 
patients, although it did not reach significance for asymptomatic patients. 
The findings in this population based study differ somewhat from 
prior case series demonstrating lower unadjusted rates of perforation 
among patients who undergo CTC (0.00-0.05%) (Pickhardt, 2006; Kim 
et al., 2007) and of cardiovascular events (0.05-0.06 per 1000 diagnostic 
CTC procedures) (Pickhardt, 2006; Burling et al., 2006). Differences in 
our results may reflect limitations of prior study populations, follow 
up interval, or measurement approach. Alternatively, these findings 
may reflect the small number of perforations identified in our 
study; particularly within the CTC cohort. Although we used the same 
methodology to identify perforations in both cohorts (i.e., emergency 
department visits and hospitalizations), CTC is more sensitive to 
sub-clinical perforation than OC due to the ability to visualize small 
amount of pneumoperitoneum (Pendse and Taylor, 2013). It is 
reassuring that our results are similar to perforation rates from a 
study where patients with pneumoperitoneum on CTC were referred 
to the emergency department (0.6 per 1000 CTC procedures) (Sosna 
et al., 2006), which resembles our measurement approach. Our 
results also extend the previously published literature about the </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Study population. </p>

<p> 
H.M. Zafar et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 1 (2014) 3-8 </p>

<p>risks of adverse events from CTC among Medicare patients in that we 
are the first study to assess the risk of lower gastrointestinal bleeding 
following CTC. 
Given that clinicians and patients desire data on the risks of initial 
CTC relative to initial OC, we have provided comparative data between 
these two procedures. Our analyses suggest that patients who undergo 
initial CTC, with or without subsequent OC, may experience lower rates 
of serious gastrointestinal, other gastrointestinal and cardiovascular </p>

<p>events compared to patients who receive initial OC. This finding is 
intuitively reasonable, given that CTC does not require sedation and 
the intention of CTC is to selectively refer the approximately 8-15% of 
patients with suspected clinically significant polyps (N6 mm) and 
masses to OC for further evaluation (Kim et al., 2007, 2010; Macari 
et al., 2011). However, it is important to recognize that we were unable 
to fully adjust for differences between the groups based upon the 
information available in claims data. Patients who receive CTC are 
generally sicker than patients who receive OC (Zafar et al., 2013). 
Furthermore, given the standard CTC technique, which does not include 
intravenous contrast, the use of a 30 day time interval is conservative 
and may include adverse events not directly related to this procedure. 
As such, our results may underestimate the differences between these 
two examinations. 
Even after adjustment, we found that the risk of adverse events 
following CTC depends upon patient age (comparing patients 75 and 
older to patients under 75). Higher risk of lower gastrointestinal bleeding 
and cardiovascular events among patients older than 75 years who 
undergo colorectal evaluation are concordant with prior studies 
evaluating OC (Rabeneck et al., 2008; Singh et al., 2010; Warren et al., 
2009; Rutter et al., 2012), but has not previously been demonstrated 
for CTC. Both the US Preventive Services Task Force and the American 
College of Physicians recommend against routine screening of patients 
older than 75 due to increased risk of complications, competing causes 
of mortality and demonstrated benefit at least 7 years after screening 
(Qaseem et al., 2012; Whitlock et al., 2008). Our findings support the 
inclusion of CTC in these recommendations. 
Our study has several limitations. We used billing codes from Medi-
care claims rather than medical record review to determine adverse 
events. No studies validating the use of billing claims for CTC have been 
reported. However, prior studies have demonstrated high sensitivity 
and specificity for the assessment of procedures, including endoscopy, 
using Medicare claims compared to medical charts (Schenck et al., 
2007; Ko et al., 2011; Javitt et al., 1993) and high likelihood of identifying 
diagnoses and select adverse events in Medicare claims (Fowles et al., 
1995). It is reassuring that our unadjusted adverse event risks among 
the OC cohort are similar to prior studies (Warren et al., 2009). We did 
not perform a randomized control trial, and there are likely to be unmea-
sured confounders or selection effects that we were unable to include in 
our adjustments. The technique utilized for CTC cannot be derived from 
claims data but is potentially important given that manual insufflation, 
luminal disease and use of a rectal balloon are associated with perforation 
(Pickhardt, 2006; Burling et al., 2006; Sosna et al., 2006; Pendse and 
Taylor, 2013). Some of the adverse events specific to CT, such as radiation 
risk, cannot be measured with claims data. Although our findings may 
not generalize to younger patients, colorectal cancer is predominantly a 
disease of the elderly. 
In conclusion, our study demonstrates that adverse event rates 
following initial CTC among the elderly are low, with the greatest 
risk for cardiovascular events. Rates of lower gastrointestinal </p>

<p>Table 1 
Frequency of Medicare outpatient characteristics and unadjusted adverse events within 
30 days of receiving initial CT colonography (CTC) or initial optical colonoscopy (OC) 
between January 2007 and December 2008, (%). </p>

<p>Initial CTC 
Initial OC 
p 
value 
(n = 6114) (n = 149,202) </p>

<p>Gender 
b.001 
Male 
2223 (36.4) 
67,586 (45.3) 
Female 
3891 (63.6) 
81,616 (54.7) 
Age 
b.001 
66-74 
2500 (40.9) 
82,411 (55.2) 
75-84 
2700 (44.2) 
55,893 (37.5) 
≥85 
914 (14.9) 
10,898 (7.3) 
Race 
b.001 
White 
5688 (93.0) 130,481 (87.5) 
Black 
239 (3.9) 
10,133 (6.8) 
Other </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>78 (1.3) 
2946 (2.0) 
Asian 
52 (0.9) 
3197 (2.1) 
Hispanic 
57 (0.9) 
2445 (1.6) 
Comorbidities associated with adverse events 
Atrial fibrillation/flutter 
1610 (26.3) 
18,813 (12.6) b.001 
Congestive heart failure 
1298 (21.2) 
19,735 (13.2) b.001 
Chronic pulmonary disease 
1759 (28.8) 
34,149 (22.9) b.001 
Diabetes 
1729 (28.3) 
45,040 (30.2) 0.001 
Stroke 
1419 (23.2) 
24,457 (16.4) b.001 
Renal disease 
636 (10.4) 
12,827 (8.6) 
b.001 
Diverticulosis 
2617 (42.8) 
85,437 (57.3) b.001 
Obesity 
298 (4.9) 
8010 (5.4) 
0.092 
Unadjusted adverse events within 30 days 
(risk per 1000 Medicare beneficiaries) 
Gastrointestinal bleeding/transfusion 
76 (12.4) 
2471 (16.6) 0.013 
Perforation 
4 (0.7) 
181 (1.2) 
0.214 
Other GI 
110 (18.0) 
2692 (18.0) 0.997 
Paralytic ileus 
11 (1.8) 
573 (3.8) 
0.011 
Nausea, vomiting or dehydration 
75 (12.3) 
1721 (11.4) 0.623 
Abdominal pain 
34 (5.6) 
695 (4.7) 
0.311 
Cardiovascular disease 
278 (45.5) 
5167 (34.6) b.001 
MI or angina </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>49 (8.0) 
1112 (7.5) 
0.617 
Arrhythmias 
148 (24.2) 
2754 (18.5) 0.001 
CHF 
119 (19.5) 
1874 (12.6) b.001 
Cardiac or respiratory arrest </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>28 (4.6) 
544 (3.6) 
0.238 
Syncope, hypotension or shock 
49 (8.0) 
945 (6.3) 
0.106 
Mortality 
Death within 30 days 
21 (0.3) 
499 (0.3) 
0.905 </p>

<p>a Other includes Unknown and Native American. 
b Including chest pain. 
c Not including shortness of breath. </p>

<p>Table 2 
Regression analysis of adverse events among Medicare outpatients who received initial CT colonography (CTC) or initial optical colonoscopy (OC) between January 2007 and December 
2008 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Gastrointestinal bleed 
Perforation 
Other gastrointestinal 
events </p>

<p>Cardiovascular events </p>

<p>OR 
95% CI 
OR 
95% CI 
OR 
95% CI 
OR 
95% CI </p>

<p>Total population (n = 155,316) 
Type of examination 
Initial CTC (n = 6114) 
Initial OC (n = 149,202) 
1.91 
[1.47,2.49] 
2.62 
[0.84,8.22] 
1.35 
[1.07,1.69] 
1.38 
[1.18,1.62] 
Age 
66-74 (ref) 
75-84 
1.38 
[1.24,1.53] 
1.18 
[0.84,1.66] 
1.39 
[1.26,1.53] 
1.44 
[1.33,1.55] 
≥85 
2.98 
[2.61,3.41] 
0.75 
[0.38,1.46] 
1.87 
[1.63,2.15] 
2.54 
[2.29,2.80] </p>

<p>a Regression analyses are adjusted for gender, age, race, comorbidities associated with adverse events (i.e. atrial fibrillation/flutter, congestive heart failure, chronic pulmonary disease, </p>

<p>diabetes, stroke, renal disease, diverticulosis, obesity), and adverse events in preceding 90 days. </p>

<p> 
H.M. Zafar et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 1 (2014) 3-8 </p>

<p>bleeding, other gastrointestinal events and cardiovascular events are 
lower following initial CTC, with or without subsequent OC, than fol-
lowing initial OC; similar rates of perforation may stem from the 
small number of perforations in both cohorts. A similar pattern was 
demonstrated among patients N 75 years of age and those with 
symptoms referable to colorectal cancer. These data can help prima-
ry care providers and patients seeking to understand complications 
associated with these methods of colorectal cancer screening and 
targeted diagnostic evaluation. 
Supplementary data to this article can be found online at http://dx. 
doi.org/10.1016/j.pmedr.2014.08.001. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement </p>

<p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interests. </p>



<p>Table 3 
Unadjusted risk per 1000 Medicare outpatients for adverse events within 30 days of initial CT colonography (CTC) or initial optical colonoscopy (OC) received between January 2007 and 
December 2008 by indication. </p>

<p>Initial CTC 
Initial OC </p>

<p>Asymptomatic 
Symptomatic 
Asymptomatic 
Symptomatic </p>

<p>(n = 1384) 
(n = 4730) 
(n = 54,039) 
(n = 95,163) </p>

<p>Events 
Events 
Events 
Events </p>

<p>(n) 
Risk 
(n) 
Risk 
(n) 
Risk 
(n) 
Risk </p>

<p>Gastrointestinal bleeding 
4 
2.9 
72 
15.2 
371 
6.9 
2100 
22.1 
Perforation 
1 
0.7 
3 
0.6 
46 
0.9 
135 
1.4 
Other GI 
5 
3.6 
105 
22.2 
311 
5.8 
2381 
25 
Ileus 
0 
0 
11 
2.3 
76 
1.4 
497 
5.2 
Nausea, vomiting or dehydration 
4 
2.9 
71 
15 
169 
3.1 
1552 
16.3 
Abdominal pain 
2 
1.4 
32 
6.8 
107 
2 
588 
6.2 
CVD events 
26 
18.8 
252 
53.3 
610 
11.3 
4557 
47.9 
MI or angina </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>4 
2.9 
45 
9.5 
176 
3.3 
936 
9.8 
Arrhythmias 
14 
10.1 
134 
28.3 
329 
6.1 
2425 
25.5 
CHF 
5 
3.6 
114 
24.1 
94 
1.7 
1780 
18.7 
Cardiac or respiratory arrest </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1 
0.7 
27 
5.7 
43 
0.8 
501 
5.3 
9 
6.5 
40 
8.5 
149 
2.8 
796 
8.4 </p>

<p>a Including chest pain. 
b Not including shortness of breath. </p>

<p>Table 4 
Regression analysis of adverse events among Medicare outpatients who received initial CT colonography (CTC) or initial optical colonoscopy (OC) between January 2007 and December 
2008 by indication </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Gastrointestinal bleed 
Perforation 
Other gastrointestinal 
events </p>

<p>Cardiovascular events </p>

<p>OR 
95% CI 
OR 
95% CI 
OR 
95% CI 
OR 
95% CI </p>



<p> 
H.M. Zafar et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 1 (2014) 3-8 </p>



<p> 
H.M. Zafar et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 1 (2014) 3-8 </p>

</text></tei>