<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4521673" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: Poor adherence to cardioprotective medications after acute coronary syndrome (ACS) </p>

<p>hospitalization is associated with increased risk of rehospitalization and mortality. Clinical 
trials of multifaceted interventions have improved medication adherence with varying results. 
Patients' perspectives on interventions could help researchers interpret inconsistent outcomes. 
Identifying factors that patients believe would improve adherence might inform the design of 
future interventions and make them more parsimonious and sustainable. The objective of this 
study was to obtain patients' perspectives on adherence to medical regimens after experienc-
ing an ACS event and their participation in a medication adherence randomized control trial 
following their hospitalization. 
Patients and methods: Sixty-four in-depth interviews were conducted with ACS patients </p>

<p>who participated in an efficacious, multifaceted, medication adherence randomized control trial. 
Interview transcripts were analyzed using the constant comparative approach. 
Results: Participants described their post-ACS event experiences and how they affected their </p>

<p>adherence behaviors. Patients reported that adherence decisions were facilitated by mutually 
respectful and collaborative provider-patient treatment planning. Frequent interactions with 
providers and medication refill reminder calls supported improved adherence. Additional 
facilitators included having social support, adherence routines, and positive attitudes toward 
an ACS event. The majority of patients expressed that being active participants in health care 
decision-making contributed to their health. 
Conclusion: Our findings demonstrate that respectful collaborative communication can con-</p>

<p>tribute to medication adherence after ACS hospitalization. These results suggest a potential 
role for training health-care providers, including pharmacists, social workers, registered nurses, 
etc, to elicit and acknowledge the patients' views regarding medication treatment in order to 
improve adherence. Future research is needed with providers to understand how they elicit and 
acknowledge patients' views, particularly in the face of nonadherence, and with patients to 
understand how to empower them to share their opinions with their providers. 
Acute coronary syndrome (ACS) is the leading cause of death and disability in the 
United States. 1 Nonadherence to proven cardiovascular medications is common follow-
ing hospitalization for an ACS event and may result in serious complications, including 
recurrent hospitalization and death. 2-6 Multifaceted interventions targeting medication 
adherence and health behaviors have demonstrated varying results. 7,8 Understanding 
patients' perspectives on their experiences following an ACS event and their opinions 
of the effectiveness of such interventions may support adherence behaviors. 9 </p>

<p>correspondence: Anne lambert-Kerzner 
Veterans health Administration (VA) 
eastern colorado health care system, 
1055 clermont st, Denver, cO 80220, 
UsA 
Tel +1 720 857 5129 
email anne.lambert-kerzner@va.gov </p>

<p>Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Patient Preference and Adherence 
24 July 2015 </p>

<p>Patient Preference and Adherence 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1054 </p>

<p>lambert-Kerzner et al </p>

<p>The high prevalence of medication nonadherence fol-
lowing an ACS event is not surprising considering that 
evidence-based treatment plans are often complex and 
lifelong. 2-6 Adherence declines over time following hospital 
discharge, with one-third of patients stopping at least one 
medication within 1 month 3-6 and 40% of patients discontinu-
ing statins within 1 year. 2,3,10 Mitigating the consequences 
of poor adherence to cardiac medications remains a major 
public health challenge. 11 
Therefore, understanding and identifying factors that 
support positive adherence behavior in a predominately older 
male population, who are at a higher risk for an ACS event, 1 
is needed to shed light on this pervasive issue. While the 
literature identifies barriers to adherence, including health 
systems, condition, patient, therapy, and socioeconomic-
related factors, 11 no prior studies have identified patients' per-
spectives on supportive adherence factors after an ACS event 
and their participation in a medication adherence randomized 
control trial (RCT). Recommendations of the International 
Expert Forum on Patient Adherence 9,12 support exploring 
patients' beliefs about adherence. Moreover, intervention 
experts such as the Medical Research Council 13-15 support 
exploring participants' perspectives on the effectiveness of 
the interventions. 
The goal of this qualitative study was to obtain patients' 
perspectives on supportive adherence factors to medical regi-
mens after experiencing an ACS event and their participation 
in an RCT that facilitated medication adherence following 
their hospitalization. </p>

<p>Material and methods 
study design and sample </p>

<p>Participants in this qualitative study were enrolled in the 
"Multi-Faceted Intervention to Improve Cardiac Medica-
tion Adherence and Secondary Prevention Measures -The 
Medication Study." 2,3 The details of the study have been 
published previously. 2,3 The RCT enrolled 253 patients 
and compared medication adherence at 1 year between 
usual care and a multimodal intervention. This intervention 
comprised: 1) medication reconciliation and patient sup-
port provided by study pharmacists; 2) patient education; 
3) automated medication refill reminder calls on specific 
days prior to the refill day and monthly educational calls; 
and 4) collaboration between pharmacists and clinicians 
when needed. The RCT was conducted at four Veterans 
Health Administration medical centers (Denver, Little 
Rock, Durham, and Seattle) and significantly improved 
the proportion of patients adherent to medications (patient </p>

<p>days covered .0.80) compared to usual care (89.3% vs 
73.9%, P=0.003). 2,3 </p>

<p>Data collection </p>

<p>Owing to budget constraints, we utilized a convenience 
sample at the Denver site by approaching all participants 
who completed the final visit (n=51). All those approached 
agreed to participate in the interviews. Then to assess new or 
different data from the other three sites, the project managers 
at their respective sites randomly chose participants and asked 
if they would participate in the interviews. In Seattle, seven 
patients were approached and all of them agreed; in Little 
Rock, five were approached and three of them agreed; and 
in Durham, three of them were approached and all of them 
agreed. This sample was interviewed in person or through 
telephone by a member of the trained qualitative team (ALK, 
MSM, KMF, and MK). Qualitative interview data were col-
lected from August 2011 to May 2013. The purpose of the 
interview was to gather 1) in-depth understanding about the 
experience after an ACS event; 2) the effect of relationships 
with providers on their adherence behaviors; and 3) opinions 
about the RCT study. The 45-60-minute interviews were 
audiotaped and transcribed verbatim. Baseline demographics, 
including age, sex, race, body mass index, diabetes mellitus, 
and coronary artery disease, were obtained to characterize 
the study population. This qualitative study was approved 
as part of the RCT by the Colorado Multiple Institutional 
Review Board. 2,3 </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>An iterative analysis, drawing primarily on constant com-
parative methodology, was used. This involved moving 
back and forth between interview transcripts to support the 
evolution of the process by identifying emerging themes and 
defining the relationships between them. 16-19 The validity and 
the accuracy/reliability of the early codes were established 
by each member of the experienced qualitative team (ALK, 
MSM, KMF, and KBF) analyzing the initial four transcripts, 
coming to consensus, thus defining the initial codebook. 
Emergent codes were added throughout the analysis. The 
remaining interviews were divided among the team and 
coded using <rs id="software-0" type="software">ATLAS.ti</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">ATLAS.ti Scientific Software Development GmbH</rs>). The consistency of coding/interpreta-
tion was checked at biweekly meetings where discrepancies 
were addressed through consensus. Triangulation of the 
qualitative findings, observations, and the RCT quantita-
tive findings were integrated and documented with an audit 
trail. 16-19 Illustrative quotes were selected by consensus with </p>

<p>Patient Preference and Adherence 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1055 </p>

<p>Patients' perspectives on factors relating to adherence to post-Acs </p>

<p>all members of the analytic team to ensure representativeness 
across roles and participating sites. </p>

<p>Participants </p>

<p>Sixty-four patients who completed the final study visit were 
interviewed. The majority of the patients interviewed were 
from Denver (n=51), Seattle (n=7), Little Rock (n=3), and 
Durham (n=3). Of the 64 patients, 33 (52%) were from the 
intervention group and 31 (48%) from the usual care. 
Baseline demographics and comorbidities were compa-
rable between the two groups (Table 1). Most participants 
were male (97%) and white (75%). The majority of partici-
pants were 50 years and older (95%) with a mean age of 
66.5 years, similar to the Veterans Health Administration 
population. We compared adherence between the inter-
viewed subgroups (intervention and control patients) and 
the corresponding patients in the entire RCT intervention 
and control groups. For example, the adherence of the inter-
viewed intervention patients was compared to the total RCT 
intervention patients. Through this comparison, we found 
that the qualitative subgroups (intervention and control) 
were more adherent than the corresponding groups in the 
entire RCT (97% vs 89% for the intervention and 80% vs 
73% for the control). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Understanding patients' experiences after an ACS event 
shed important insight into reasons behind their adherence 
behaviors. Although patients shared the same diagnosis, their 
experiences of the ACS event, its consequences, and the ways 
in which it impacted their health behavior decisions varied. 
Patients identified positive and accepting attitudes toward 
their cardiac issues, supportive social relationships, and </p>

<p>specific adherence tools as being important in improving their 
lifestyles. The most consistent insight shared by patients was 
that bidirectional communication and specifically, mutually 
respectful collaboration about their treatment plan between 
themselves, their care providers, and families led to better 
medication adherence. </p>

<p>experiencing an Acs event </p>

<p>Most patients experiencing an ACS event considered it to be 
profound and life-changing. Many stated their life changed 
due to mental and physical limitations, which affected 
multiple aspects of their lives, including relationships with 
significant others, their identity, roles in their lives, and 
activities they enjoyed doing with others. </p>

<p>Everything changed … I got back to religion, I got in a better </p>

<p>relationship with my wife and my kids 'cause I didn't know </p>

<p>how long I was going to be around! </p>

<p>It means that I can't do what I used to be able to do and </p>

<p>frankly I get, oh, not depressed but a little sad […] I can't </p>

<p>even mow my own lawn, … And, it concerns me because </p>

<p>I used to be a really strong guy. </p>

<p>A few patients lost their sense of identity and self-esteem 
from no longer being able to complete everyday tasks and 
participate in leisure activities. </p>

<p>Very depressing, 'cause it stopped everything I did. I can't </p>

<p>do what I did before, like fly airplanes and so on. I was a </p>

<p>pilot for a living, so I lost that, it was my hobby and every-</p>

<p>thing so it changed my whole life. </p>

<p>Many patients admitted to being fearful, concerned, dev-
astated, sad, or depressed in the year after experiencing their 
ACS event. For some, these negative emotional trajectories 
monopolized their lives. </p>

<p>Very strenuous, you know, physically and mentally. Having </p>

<p>this heart condition you don't know when you're … gonna </p>

<p>have the next one, you know, the next heart attack so. </p>

<p>effect of experiencing an Acs event on 
adherence behaviors </p>

<p>Ultimately, the impact of the ACS event itself was a double-
edged sword, either motivating or hindering patients' abilities 
to effectively change their health behaviors. Most patients 
were motivated to improve their health behaviors. </p>

<p>They […] put stents in and it […] woke me up and now I </p>

<p>work out every day </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>Table 1 comparison of demographics between intervention and 
usual care groups </p>

<p>Demographics 
Intervention 
(n=33, 52%) </p>

<p>Usual care 
(n=31, 48%) </p>

<p>sex 
Male 
32 
30 
Female 
1 
1 
Mean age (sD) 
66.0 (9.8) 
67.1 (9.7) 
race 
White, n (%) 
24 (73) 
24 (77) 
non-white, n (%) 
9 (27) 
7 (23) 
comorbidities 
Mean BMi (sD) 
32.0 (7.4) 
32.0 (7.1) 
DM, n (%) 
14 (42) 
10 (32) 
cAD, n (%) 
20 (63) 
18 (58) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: sD, standard deviation; BMi, body mass index; DM, diabetes 
mellitus; cAD, coronary artery disease. </p>

<p>Patient Preference and Adherence 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1056 </p>

<p>lambert-Kerzner et al </p>

<p>It was devastating. […] it made me really […] look at my </p>

<p>life, change it. </p>

<p>Approximately half of the patients said having positive 
and accepting attitudes toward their cardiac issues allowed 
them to forge ahead and become proactive in improving 
their lifestyles. </p>

<p>It means that I need to take better care of myself. Give up </p>

<p>the old habits of smoking, […] and to take my prescribed </p>

<p>medication on time. Try to eat a balanced diet and try to </p>

<p>keep my health better and my weight down, cholesterol </p>

<p>down. There's just so many things we have to live for, […] </p>

<p>grandchildren, […] And my wife, […] so […] got to watch </p>

<p>my health. </p>

<p>For others, these emotions paralyzed their ability to 
move forward. They were fearful of having another heart 
attack, and a few patients described a realization of their 
mortality, resulting in their refusal to adhere to prescribed 
medications, activities, and/or stopped previous exercise 
routines. </p>

<p>Before, it was basically five days … a week … I would be </p>

<p>in the gym doing some sort of activity [and after]. Little </p>

<p>more than the desire to not work out due to the heart attack. </p>

<p>The fear that I'm gonna do something wrong and wind up </p>

<p>exacerbating the condition. </p>

<p>effect of relationships with providers on 
adherence behaviors </p>

<p>Positive health-care relationships </p>

<p>Two-third of the patients identified the importance of bidi-
rectional communication in their relationship with their 
providers. They expressed the importance of being heard, 
and shared that they were comfortable disagreeing with the 
providers' recommendations and wanted providers to be open 
to hearing patients' perspectives, thus defining a mutually 
respectful collaboration with their providers. Moreover, these 
patients felt they were active participants in the development 
of their treatment plan, which they believed was essential for 
high quality care. </p>

<p>[…] how [would he] know what was best for me if I can't </p>

<p>tell him how I feel about it? </p>

<p>These patients emphasized the importance of being able 
to ask clarifying questions about their treatment plans with-
out fear of a condescending response. Patients shared that 
they were equally responsible in this relationship and it was 
their duty to help providers remember specific details about </p>

<p>themselves. Participants reported that bidirectional com-
munication with their providers, specifically collaboration in 
their development of a treatment plan, supported constructive 
adherence decisions. </p>

<p>Yep, with the primary care, we were talking about some-</p>

<p>thing […] about medications actually and I believe he </p>

<p>said something to the effect of taking the medications he </p>

<p>prescribes and he wasn't being combative about it, but I </p>

<p>made sure that the context of the instruction was that I </p>

<p>agreed with taking the medication. You know in the long </p>

<p>run, people can prescribe medication but it is up to me to </p>

<p>decide if I will take it or not, and I take it by the way. </p>

<p>Two-third of the intervention arm had positive expe-
riences, specifically with the study pharmacists, who 
were perceived to be supportive providers and caring 
individuals. </p>

<p>It [working with the pharmacist] makes me feel important, </p>

<p>like I am a person, not just a number. [and]. Makes me </p>

<p>want to do it. </p>

<p>Especially on the heart medicines. Uh … that … it made </p>

<p>me think that it musta' been more important than I thought </p>

<p>it was … to have these people contact me on a regular basis </p>

<p>to make sure I was takin' it. So I think it did show me a little </p>

<p>bit more of the importance of … of taking them. </p>

<p>negative health-care relationships </p>

<p>However, some patients shared negative experiences with 
their providers and described a lack of basic communication. 
Seventeen percent of the patients said they were not com-
fortable sharing divergent opinions or misunderstandings of 
medications with their providers. Nine percent specifically 
said they would not tell their provider if they disagreed with 
the prescribed treatment. </p>

<p>But I just don't want to argue with him to tell him, he's </p>

<p>not in my body. And I know what I feel and he can't tell </p>

<p>me what I feel. </p>

<p>Adherence was negatively affected when patients were 
concerned about the side effects of medications but not 
comfortable discussing these with their provider. </p>

<p>Well, they keep telling me that everything is fine, [if] </p>

<p>everything is fine, then I don't see the reason why I can't </p>

<p>get off of them [medications]. </p>

<p>When a patient was asked his perspective when talking 
about medicines with his doctor, he replied: </p>

<p>Patient Preference and Adherence 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1057 </p>

<p>Patients' perspectives on factors relating to adherence to post-Acs </p>

<p>I don't under stand them sometimes. [Patient (P)] </p>

<p>Do you ask questions? [Interviewer (I)] </p>

<p>No … I don't know I just don't. [P] </p>

<p>Can you tell us why you did not take them (the medi-</p>

<p>cines)? [I] </p>

<p>Because I was afraid of the medicine I was taking. I </p>

<p>didn't know how I would react on it. [P] </p>

<p>Okay, could you tell me a little bit about why you do </p>

<p>not think you could disagree with the doctor? [I] </p>

<p>I'm just not that type. [P] </p>

<p>Finally, a few patients shared that their providers were 
not open to hearing patients' opinions. One woman shared 
that she felt comfortable telling a provider she did not agree 
with him, even if the provider did not respond well. </p>

<p>Oh yeah, I do … but they don't. Well you know it's my </p>

<p>body, and I have to live in it, they don't. </p>

<p>And: </p>

<p>And he's acting like I got no business being there … Nobody </p>

<p>knows my body like I know my body! And he finally agreed </p>

<p>to do another arteriogram and that's when they found out </p>

<p>that one graft was 100% blocked! </p>

<p>Others shared their providers were condescending. </p>

<p>The doctors don't think that we're capable of understand-</p>

<p>ing sometimes. </p>

<p>supplementary adherence factors </p>

<p>Most of the participants realized they needed help to adhere 
to their medical regimens and identified supportive factors, 
including social support from family members, friends, 
and neighbors; pill boxes; storing medications in an easily 
seen place; taking them the same time every day; using the 
alarm on phones/watches; and writing in a notebook or on 
the medication lids. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The objective of this study was to elicit patients' perspectives 
on their experiences after an ACS hospitalization and their 
participation in an adherence intervention. More specifically, 
we intended to elicit patients' perspectives on their adher-
ence behaviors to recommended medical regimens, includ-
ing medications and health behaviors. This predominately 
male, veteran population exhibited above average adherence 
to their cardiovascular medications, allowing us to identify 
factors relating to high adherence in a high-risk population. 
Veterans expressed the significance of feeling cared for </p>

<p>by their providers, including the study pharmacists, which 
empowered them to be active in their health care. We found 
that a focus on a mutually respectful collaboration supported 
adherence decisions. 
The importance of patient-provider communication is 
well documented in the health communication literature, 
especially among patients with human immunodeficiency 
virus (HIV). 20-29 Mulder et al 28 and Apollo et al 29 highlight that 
HIV patients desire to go beyond just sharing in the decision-
making process. They want to be collaborative in the process 
of medication decision-making. Our study contributes to the 
literature by identifying similar findings within patients with 
cardiovascular disease, specifically ACS. In fact, adherence 
experts have emphasized that understanding adherence 
behaviors in relation to each disease condition was an impor-
tant aspect of adherence to the prescribed medications. 22-25 
In contrast to prior studies that have focused on nonadherence 
behaviors, our unique study focuses on facilitators of adher-
ence. Understanding this unique population of predominately 
older males, who remain at higher risk for an ACS event, 1 
provides a contemporary perspective into adherence behav-
iors. The distinctiveness of the male adherence behavior 
indicates that worse health outcomes are due in part to men's 
health-related beliefs and behaviors, which include denial 
of weakness or vulnerability, control, and the appearance of 
being strong with the dismissal of need for help. 30,31 Men may 
believe it is unacceptable to express emotional or physical pain 
with other men. 30 These male-specific factors may explain 
the post-ACS reactions of participants that resulted in their 
inability to adhere to prescribed medications, activities, and/or 
stopping previous exercise routines and discomfort sharing 
their feelings with their providers. 
Therapeutic Alliance, 32-35 a theory that describes a 
patient's and a physician's working alliance in relation to 
the patient's health and health care decisions, further sup-
ports our findings of why patients were paralyzed in their 
ability to move forward and the importance of collabora-
tive care. ACS events can evoke complex psychological 
reactions, as described by the veterans. Patients vary in 
their capacity to use this information about their health 
productively to develop and maintain new health behav-
iors. When patients struggle to adhere to medications, they 
may have difficulty communicating this information to 
their physician. 32-35 Therefore, the importance of patients' 
and physicians' shared sense of purpose and effort around 
treatment goals is paramount to the quality of the patients' 
outcomes. Our findings demonstrated that when patients 
were more engaged and participated in the development of </p>

<p>Patient Preference and Adherence 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1058 </p>

<p>lambert-Kerzner et al </p>

<p>the treatment plan, they were more likely to implement the 
treatment plan. Consequently, patients were empowered, 
gaining greater control over decisions and actions that 
affected their health. 36 
Yet, despite the importance of increased patient involve-
ment and empowerment around health-care decisions, such 
as in Patient-Centered Care and Shared Decision Making 37,38 
paradigms, not all practitioners are successful implementing 
these shared and collaborative decision-making concepts. 39,40 
Mulder et al found that when patients failed to adhere, pro-
viders reverted to a more paternalistic approach, using risk 
communication about consequences of nonadherence. 28 
Moreover, when providers fail to utilize a collaborative pro-
cess with patients, they are unaware of the actual adherence 
behavior of the patient. When the provider is aware the patient 
will not follow through with the prescribed treatment plan, 
the collaborative process allows the provider the opportunity 
to offer alternative options, which may not be optimal but 
ultimately may be better than no care. </p>

<p>Potential limitations </p>

<p>Our results are based on patients enrolled in an RCT and 
may be subject to attribution bias. The study comprises 
mainly male participants. However, since men are at a 
higher risk for an ACS event, understanding the male 
perspective might be considered a strength of the study. 
The study results were based on interview data and did 
not include any direct observations of the patients using 
the intervention components. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In conclusion, our findings, from the patients' perspectives, 
confirm that the collaborative patient-provider relationship 
can enhance and contribute to medication adherence in an 
already adherent population. As we have stated, the overall 
adherence rate of these patients in both intervention and 
control groups was above average, which is not typically 
representative of this population. 
These results suggest a potential role for training health 
care providers to elicit and acknowledge patients' views and 
empower patients to speak up regarding medication treatment 
in order to improve adherence. Therefore, further research is 
needed with providers in order to understand how they elicit 
and acknowledge patients' views regarding treatment over 
time, particularly in the face of nonadherence. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest 
in this work. </p>



</text></tei>