<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4173757" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Radioimmunotherapy using a radiolabeled monoclonal antibody that targets tumor </p>

<p>cells has been shown to be efficient for the treatment of many malignant cancers, with reduced 
side effects. However, the blood-brain barrier (BBB) inhibits the transport of intravenous 
antibodies to tumors in the brain. Recent studies have demonstrated that focused ultrasound 
(FUS) combined with microbubbles (MBs) is a promising method to transiently disrupt the 
BBB for the drug delivery to the central nervous system. To find the optimal FUS and MBs 
that can induce reversible increase in the BBB permeability, we employed minimally invasive 
multiphoton microscopy to quantify the BBB permeability to dextran-155 kDa with similar 
molecular weight to an antibody by applying different doses of FUS in the presence of MBs 
with an optimal size and concentration. The cerebral microcirculation was observed through a 
section of frontoparietal bone thinned with a micro-grinder. About 5 minutes after applying the 
FUS on the thinned skull in the presence of MBs for 1 minute, TRITC (tetramethylrhodamine 
isothiocyanate)-dextran-155 kDa in 1% bovine serum albumin in mammalian Ringer's solution 
was injected into the cerebral circulation via the ipsilateral carotid artery by a syringe pump. 
Simultaneously, the temporal images were collected from the brain parenchyma ~100-200 μm 
below the pia mater. Permeability was determined from the rate of tissue solute accumulation 
around individual microvessels. After several trials, we found the optimal dose of FUS. At the 
optimal dose, permeability increased by ~14-fold after 5 minutes post-FUS, and permeability 
returned to the control level after 25 minutes. FUS without MBs or MBs injected without FUS 
did not change the permeability. Our method provides an accurate in vivo assessment for the 
transient BBB permeability change under the treatment of FUS. The optimal FUS dose found 
for the reversible BBB permeability increase without BBB disruption is reliable and can be 
applied to future clinical trials. 
Macromolecules such as monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) have attracted attention 
because of their potential clinical benefits. More recently, mAbs conjugated with radio-
isotopes, or radioimmunotherapy, administered into the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), have 
proven safe in Phase I clinical trials for the treatment of leptomeningeal cancers (one 
type of brain cancer), and the patients survived for extended periods of time. 1 While 
these studies have been shown to extend life, the methods are less than ideal because 
of their invasiveness and slow rate of diffusion from the CSF into the parenchyma. </p>

<p>correspondence: Bingmei M Fu 
Department of Biomedical engineering, 
The city college of the city University 
of New York, 160 convent avenue, 
New York, NY 10031, Usa 
Tel +1 212 650 7531 
Fax +1 212 650 6727 
email fu@ccny.cuny.edu </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of Nanomedicine 
18 September 2014 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4438 </p>

<p>shi et al </p>

<p>Access to the brain parenchyma is characteristically limited 
to cells lying close to the ventricles or infusion sites due to 
small diffusion distances of drugs and drug carriers through 
the interstitial space. 2 The surface area of the blood-brain 
barrier (BBB) is 5,000 times that of the blood-CSF barrier, 
and therefore the BBB is considered to be the primary barrier 
controlling the uptake of drugs into the brain parenchyma. 3 
Thus, a more ideal route of administration would be through 
the systemic blood stream if obstacles related to BBB pen-
etration of these macromolecules could be circumvented. 
Among the numerous strategies to deliver therapeutic 
drugs into the central nervous system, the focused ultrasound 
(FUS) sonication combined with microbubbles (MBs) has 
been shown to be effective in transiently disrupting the BBB 
for noninvasive drug delivery. 4-7 At appropriate acoustic 
power density (or pressure), burst repetition rate (BRR), duty 
cycle, sonication duration, and in the presence of MBs with 
proper materials, sizes, and concentrations, FUS can achieve 
noninvasive, selective, and localized disruption of the BBB 
without visible damage to the brain tissue. 8-11 
FUS-induced BBB disruption has been widely assessed 
by using magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) or post-FUS 
histological examination. 6,7,12-22 Indirect MRI collects the 
images of brain slices in the presence of an MRI contrast 
agent such as gadolinium to access the BBB disruption in 
different locations of the brain. Alternatively, post-FUS 
histological examination relates the BBB disruption to the 
amount of Evans blue extravasation in the brain tissue after 
the dye is intravenously injected into the blood circulation 
before or after sonication. However, the sub-millimeter 
spatial resolution of the MRI studies and the postmortem 
histological examinations only assess the relatively large 
leakage of the BBB, and these methods are restricted to 
the exploration of a region that is much larger than a single 
microvessel with its surrounding tissue. Therefore, the BBB 
disruption assessed by the MRI and histological examination 
is more qualitative than quantitative. 23,24 
To overcome aforementioned limitations, two-photon 
microscopy can be employed to quantitatively access the 
enhanced permeability of the cerebral vasculature after FUS. 25 
In addition to micrometer spatial resolution, two-photon 
microscopy offers the advantage of deep tissue penetration, 
which is essential for the BBB permeability measurement. 
However, in the studies from Nhan et al 25 the MBs for enhanc-
ing the FUS effect and the fluorescently labeled test solutes 
were injected via the animal tail vein. This administration 
route leads to the uneven distribution of MBs and uncertainty 
in the MB concentration in both the FUS-stimulated region </p>

<p>and in the test solute concentration in cerebral microvessels, 
resulting in inaccurate assessments of the dynamics of FUS-
enhanced BBB permeability. In addition, their study only 
estimated the permeability index in a region of ~500 μm ×500 
μm containing many types of blood vessels, not the true BBB </p>

<p>permeability at the individual microvessel level. 
The objective of the current study was to use our newly 
developed multiphoton microscopy 23 to more accurately 
assess the FUS-induced BBB permeability change in vivo. To 
accomplish this aim, MBs were generated and selected for the 
optimal size in inducing reversible BBB disruptions. 7,15,26,27 
Subsequently, the MBs were injected via the carotid artery 
at a constant rate to achieve a constant concentration in the 
cerebral microvessels in the region of sonication, where the 
"optimal" concentration was based on previous studies. 6,7,21,28 
After FUS in the presence of MBs, tetramethylrhodamine 
isothiocyanate (TRITC)-dextran-155 kDa, a model mAbs 
macromolecule, was injected via the carotid artery, and 
the BBB permeability was determined for an individual 
microvessel by a method described by Yuan et al. 24 Our 
current study enabled us to find optimal FUS and MBs that 
can induce reversible increase in the BBB permeability to 
macromolecules. These findings will contribute to design-
ing efficient and safe delivery strategies for the brain drug 
delivery, particularly for the delivery of antibodies. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Microbubble preparation </p>

<p>Lipid 1,2-distearoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (DSPC; 
Avanti Polar Lipids Inc., Alabaster, AL, USA) was dis-
solved in chloroform (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, 
MA, USA). Stabilizing agent polyoxyethylene 40 stearate 
(PEG40S; Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA) was dis-
solved in filtered deionized water (18 MΩ, Direct-Q; EMD 
Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA). All solutions were prepared 
using 1% bovine serum albumin (BSA) in Ringer's solution 
(pH 7.4-7.45) (see below for the composition), and glassware 
was previously cleaned with reagent alcohol (90:5:5 vol% 
of ethanol/methanol/isopropanol; Sigma-Aldrich). 29,30 MBs 
were prepared as previously described. 31 
MBs having too large sizes may induce harmful effects 
such as blocking the blood flow in the pulmonary microves-
sels, while those having too small sizes may have no effects 
on enhancing the BBB permeability. 10,11 In order to narrow 
down the size distribution of the MBs to near the optimal 
size of around 2 μm in diameter, 7,10 size isolation was 
performed by centrifugation. 30 Briefly, MB solution was 
placed into a centrifuge (5702R; Eppendorf North America, </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4439 </p>

<p>enhanced BBB permeability by ultrasound </p>

<p>Hauppauge, NY, USA) for 1 minute at 100 RCF (relative 
centrifugal force) to remove bubbles larger than ~4 μm. 
The infranatant was collected and centrifuged for another 
1 minute at 200 RCF to remove bubbles greater than ~3 μm 
in diameter. Then, the infranatant was collected again and 
centrifuged for 7 minutes at 300 RCF to concentrate all 
bubbles with a diameter around ~2 μm. 26 The last step was 
repeated three times to ensure the complete removal of the 
remaining aggregates that did not form MBs. Size distribu-
tions were analyzed by using a laser particle size analyzer 
(LA-950; Horiba Inc., Irvine, CA, USA). Figure 1 shows the 
size distribution curve of the MBs generated by our tech-
nique, which have the optimal size of ~2 μm as an ultrasound 
contrast agent in in vivo ultrasound imaging and treatment 
applications. 7,10,11,26,32-34 The MB concentration prepared for 
injection was ~1.7×10 6 bubbles/mL, which is in an optimal 
concentration range for reversible disruption of the BBB 
based on the study by Yang et al. 7 </p>

<p>animal preparation </p>

<p>In vivo experiments were conducted on adult female Sprague 
Dawley rats (250-300 g, age 3-4 months; Hilltop Labora-
tory Animals Inc., Scottsdale, PA, USA). All procedures and 
the animal use were approved by the Institutional Animal 
Care and Use Committee of the City College of New York. 
Rats were anesthetized with pentobarbital sodium injected 
subcutaneously (initial dosage 65 mg/kg bodyweight). 
A heating pad was used to keep the rat at its body temperature. 
The depth of anesthesia was monitored for the absence of 
withdrawal reflex to toe pinch and absence of blink reflex. 
Anesthesia was further checked every 15 minutes during the 
experiment; an additional 3 mg/dose pentobarbital was given 
when needed. At the end of the experiments, an overdose of 
pentobarbital (100 mg/kg) was administered intravenously 
to euthanize the animal. </p>

<p>The preparation of the rat skull observation area was the 
same as that previously described. 23,24 Briefly, the skull in the 
region of interest (ROI) was exposed by shaving off the hair 
and cutting away the skin and connective tissue. A section 
of the frontoparietal bone (either left or right) was carefully 
ground with a high speed micro-grinder (0-50,000 rpm, DLT 
50KBU; Brasseler USA, Savannah, GA, USA) until a part 
of it (~4 mm ×6 mm) became soft and translucent. During 
the process, artificial CSF (ACSF) at room temperature was 
applied to the surface of the skull to dispel the heat due to 
grinding. After grinding, the left or the right carotid artery 
was cannulated with PE50 tubing. The rat was then placed 
on a stereotaxic alignment system (SAS 597; David Kopf 
Instruments, Tujunga, CA, USA), and its head was fixed with 
two ear bars and a mouth clamp. After FUS treatment, the 
cerebral microvessels were observed under the objective lens 
of a multiphoton microscope through the thinned part of the 
skull and the BBB permeability was determined. </p>

<p>Solutions and fluorescent test solute </p>

<p>Mammalian ringer's solution </p>

<p>Mammalian Ringer's solution was used for all perfusates, 
which was composed of (in mM) NaCl 132, KCl 4.6, MgSO 4 
1.2, CaCl 2 2.0, NaHCO 3 5.0, glucose 5.5, and HEPES (2-[4-
(2-hydroxyethyl)piperazin-1-yl]ethanesulfonic acid) 20. 
The pH was buffered to 7.40-7.45 by adjusting the ratio of 
HEPES acid to base. In addition, both the washout solution 
and the fluorescent dye solution contained 10 mg/mL BSA 
(A4378; Sigma-Aldrich). 24 The solutions were made fresh on 
the day of use to avoid binding to the serum albumin. </p>

<p>acsF </p>

<p>The ACSF solution composition was (in mM) NaCl 110.5, 
KCl 4.7, CaCl 2 2.5, KH 2 PO 4 1.1, MgSO 4 ⋅7H 2 O 1.25, NaHCO 3 
25, and HEPES 15, 35 and the solution was buffered to 
pH 7.4±0.5. </p>

<p>Test solute </p>

<p>TRITC-dextran-155 kDa (molecular weight 155,000, Stokes 
radius ~8.5 nm; Sigma-Aldrich) was used at the concentration 
of 1 mg/mL in 1% BSA in Ringer's solution. The concentra-
tion of 1 mg/mL was in the linear range (0-2 mg/mL) of the 
concentration versus intensity curve, which was calibrated in 
vitro using the same settings as in the in vivo experiments. 
All the solutions were oxygenated by bubbling with the 
compressed gas composed of 95% oxygen and 5% carbon 
dioxide (Airgas; Bethlehem, PA, USA) for 5 minutes before 
being injected into the cerebral circulation. </p>

<p>Number (%) </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>Diameter (µm) </p>

<p>Figure 1 size distribution of the microbubbles generated in the current study. 
Notes: The error bars indicate the standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4440 </p>

<p>shi et al </p>

<p>Ultrasound equipment and calibration </p>

<p>A spherical 1-MHz FUS transducer (Ws50-P50; Ultran, State 
College, PA, USA) with a focal length of 50 mm and a focal 
area diameter of 3 mm was used in this study. The power was 
generated by a function generator (AFG3251; Tektronix Inc., 
Beaverton, OR, USA). An ultrasound power meter (UPM-
DI-1AV; Ohmic Instruments, Easton, MD, USA) was used 
to measure the acoustic pressure generated by the ultrasound 
transducer in a degaussed water bath at room temperature. 
The acoustic pressure measured was automatically converted 
into power by the power meter system. 
To determine the relationship of ultrasound power as a func-
tion of BRR (in kilohertz) and peak-to-peak voltage (in volts), 
powers were measured at varying BRRs (200-1,000 kHz) 
and voltages (1-5 V). The duty cycle was kept constant at 
5% for tested pulses from 200 to 1,000 kHz. Figure 2 dem-
onstrates the calibration results of the acoustic power density 
(power per unit focus area) versus voltage and BRR for the 
devices used in the current study. Dots are measured data, 
and the surface is the best fitting. </p>

<p>FUs sonication with MBs </p>

<p>Figure 3A illustrates the setup of ultrasound sonication. The 
ultrasound probe was placed in a custom-made clear acrylic 
adapter and was attached to a stereotaxic alignment system. 
The adapter allowed placement of the ultrasound probe in one 
end and a rubber-latex sheet (300-series, North; McMaster 
Carr, Robbinsville, NJ, USA) in the other. The reservoir water 
was degassed with a vacuum pressure pump (Air Cadet 420-
1901; Thermo Fisher Scientific) at room temperature (25°C). 
By implementing the stereotaxic alignment system, the focal 
area of the ultrasound probe was easily and accurately located 
over the rat's head by softly pressuring the latex-sheet water </p>

<p>reservoir over the thinned skull. Formation of air bubbles or air 
layers between the rat's skull and the rubber-latex sheet was 
avoided by applying an ultrasound transmission gel (National 
Medical Alliance, Carmel, IN, USA). After the rat was placed 
on the stereotaxic instrument and its head was fixed, the FUS 
sonication was applied to the brain through the thinned skull, 
while the MBs were injected simultaneously into the carotid 
artery at a constant flow rate ~3 mL/min by a syringe pump. 
We applied ultrasound at several acoustic powers (in a range 
of ~2.85-15.00 W/cm 2 ) with different BRRs and voltages 
(Figure 2) to find the proper FUS dose for a reversible increase 
of the BBB permeability in the presence of our MBs. </p>

<p>Two-photon microscopy and image 
collection </p>

<p>The microvessels were observed with a 40× lens (water 
immersion, NA 0.8; Olympus Corporation, Tokyo, Japan), 
and the 12-bit images were collected by a two-photon 
microscopy system (Ultima; Prairie Technologies Inc., 
Middleton, WI, USA). For TRITC-dextran-155 kDa, the 
excitation wavelength of the two-photon microscope was 
set to 840 nm. 
After ultrasound sonication for ~1 minute in the pres-
ence of MBs, 6,7 the rat was immediately placed under the 
objective of the two-photon microscope. The syringe was 
replaced by the one filled with TRITC-dextran-155 kDa 
solution (tracer) (Figure 3B). The tracer solution was then 
introduced into the cerebral circulation via the carotid 
artery at a constant flow rate of ~3 mL/min 23,36 for 1 minute 
in an interval of 5 minutes. Simultaneously, the images of 
the ROI containing the microvessels and the surrounding 
brain tissue were captured for 1 minute at 5-minute inter-
vals up to 25 minutes. The images of 239 μm ×239 μm </p>

<p>Power (W/cm 2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 5 
4 
3 
2 
1 
0 0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1,000 </p>

<p>Volt age (V) 
B ur st re pe tit io n 
ra te (K H z) </p>

<p>Figure 2 calibration results for the acoustic power density as a function of voltage and burst repetition rate for the focused ultrasound transducer used in the current study. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4441 </p>

<p>enhanced BBB permeability by ultrasound </p>

<p>(512×512) were collected at a rate of ~1 second per image. 
The corresponding resolution is 0.467 μm ×0.467 μm. 
The collected images were then transferred to an image 
acquisition and analysis workstation to determine the BBB 
solute permeability. </p>

<p>experimental protocol </p>

<p>Figure 3C summarizes the experimental protocol for FUS 
effects on the BBB solute permeability. The MBs at a con-
centration of ~1.7×10 6 bubbles/mL were injected via rat 
carotid artery at a constant speed of ~3 mL/min, the normal 
blood flow velocity at the carotid artery; after 10-15 seconds, </p>

<p>the MBs reach the microvascular bed ~100-200 μm below 
the pia mater, 23 and the FUS sonication was administrated 
for 1 minute. After sonication, the rat head was mounted 
into the multiphoton microscope, and the ROI with cerebral 
microvessels was found. This took about 5 minutes. Then, 
the images for determining the BBB solute permeability were 
collected for 1 minute at a rate of one image per second in a 
5-minute interval, up to 25 minutes. For comparison, three 
control experiments were performed: 1) measurement of 
permeability in the presence of 1% BSA in Ringer's solution 
only, no MBs and FUS; 2) same protocol, with only MBs; 
3) same protocol, with only FUS. </p>

<p>Tracer </p>

<p>Multiphoton 
microscope 
Computer </p>

<p>2λ </p>

<p>Ear bar </p>

<p>FUS and MB 
injection </p>

<p>Mount to 2P microscopy 
and find ROI 
Image collection, ~1 minute every 5 minutes up 
to 25 minutes </p>

<p>Injection of fluorescently-labeled solutes 
during image collection </p>

<p>~5 minutes </p>

<p>~1 minute </p>

<p>~25 minutes </p>

<p>Ultrasound probe </p>

<p>Water reservoir </p>

<p>Pulse 
generator </p>

<p>Syringe pump 
(Microbubbles) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 3 Illustrations of experimental setups. 
Notes: (A) schematic of the setup for the ultrasound sonication and MB injection to the cerebral circulation. sonication on the thinned skull region starts simultaneously 
while the MBs are injected through the carotid artery at a rate of ~3 ml/min. (B) schematic of the blood-brain barrier solute permeability measurement by multiphoton 
microscopy. While TrITc-dextran-155 kDa (tracer) is injected through the carotid artery at a rate of ~3 ml/min, the images of the rOI containing several microvessels and 
the surrounding brain tissue are collected. Permeability is determined off-line by analyzing the collected images. (C) Experimental timeline and protocol for the FUs sonication 
and blood-brain barrier permeability measurement. 
Abbreviations: 2P, two-photon; FUs, focused ultrasound; rOI, region of interest; MB, microbubble; TrITc, tetramethylrhodamine isothiocyanate. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4442 </p>

<p>shi et al </p>

<p>Determination of the BBB solute 
permeability </p>

<p>We used the similar method as in our previous study for 
permeability of pial microvessels 24 to determine permeability 
of cerebral microvessels ~100-200 μm below the pia mater. 
Most of the microvessels chosen were post-capillary venules 
of 15-40 μm diameter for the permeability measurement, 
and around 1/4 of the microvessels were capillaries. 24,35 The 
reasons that we currently only measured the permeability of 
post-capillary venules and capillaries were: 1) to avoid the 
influence of smooth muscle cells at arteries, arterioles, and 
large venules, which would contract under stimuli and affect 
the permeability measurement; 35 2) our previous studies on 
the BBB permeability were also conducted on this type of 
post-capillary venules. 23,24 
The permeability was determined off-line from the 
pre-collected images by using <rs id="software-0" type="software">ImageJ</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">National Institutes of Health</rs>, Bethesda, MD, USA). Figure 4A shows a typi-
cal image of an ROI (~239 μm ×239 μm) with a couple of 
microvessels and surrounding brain tissue. The total fluores-
cence intensity in a rectangular window including a vessel 
lumen and the surrounding tissue (Figure 4A) was measured 
by ImageJ. The measuring window was ~50-100 μm long 
and ~30-60 μm wide and was set at least 10 μm from the 
base of the bifurcation to avoid solute contamination from 
the side arms. The criteria for the size and placement of the 
measuring window were 1) the vessel segment is straight, </p>

<p>2) the dye does not spread out of the window during the time 
for permeability measurement (10-60 seconds), and 3) no 
dye contamination from the neighboring vessels into the 
window. When the criteria were satisfied, permeability was 
determined using the equation, 24,37 </p>

<p>P = 1/ΔI 0 * (dI/dt) 0 * r/2, 
(1) </p>

<p>where P is permeability, ΔI 0 is the step increase of the 
fluorescence intensity in the window when the dye just fills 
up the vessel lumen (Figure 4B), (dI/dt) 0 is the slope of the 
increasing curve of the total intensity I versus time t when 
the solute further transfers into the surrounding tissue, and 
r is the vessel radius. </p>

<p>Corrections for influence of red blood 
cells, free dye, and solvent drag on BBB 
permeability </p>

<p>The fluorescence dye solution was injected into the brain at 
the rate of 3 mL/min, the same as the normal blood perfu-
sion rate. 36,38 Although at this perfusion rate the blood was 
assumed to be replaced by the fluorescence solution, there 
was still residue blood (red blood cells [RBCs]) in the cere-
bral microvessels, which would overestimate the measured 
BBB permeability by ~11%, as estimated in Yuan et al. 24 
In addition to RBCs, free dye would overestimate the per-
meability to fluorescently labeled solutes. 24,39 The influence </p>

<p>50 μm </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>0 
2 0 
4 0 
6 0 
8 0 </p>

<p>Intensity (x10 7 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Time (seconds) </p>

<p>∆I 0 </p>

<p>(dI/dt) 0 </p>

<p>B 
A </p>

<p>Figure 4 Determination of the blood-brain barrier solute permeability. 
Notes: (A) Illustration of the scanning region comprising several microvessels ~100-200 μm below the pia mater. The region area is ~239 μm ×239 μm. The yellow frame 
enclosed area is the region of interest used to determine the blood-brain barrier permeability to a solute. (B) Total fluorescence intensity in the region of interest as a 
function of perfusion time. Fluorescence intensity in the figure is proportional to the total mass of solute accumulated in the measuring region surrounding the microvessel. 
The slope of regression line over the initial linear accumulation (dI/dt) 0 (red line) is used to determine permeability P = 1/ΔI 0 * (dI/dt) 0 * r/2, where ΔI 0 (black line with 
arrowheads) is the step intensity increase when the dye just fills up the vessel lumen, and r is the radius of the vessel. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4443 </p>

<p>enhanced BBB permeability by ultrasound </p>

<p>of the free dye on the solute permeability was estimated by 
using equation, 39 </p>

<p>P correct = [1/(1-F)]P measure -[F/(1-F)]P freedye , 
(2) </p>

<p>where P measure was measured permeability; P freedye was 
measured permeability of NaF (14.6×10 -7 cm/s), 23 since 
the molecular weight of TRITC (479) is close to that of 
NaF (376); F ~0.3% was the intensity ratio of the free dye 
filtrate to the original fluorescently labeled solution for 
TRITC-dextran-155 kDa; and P correct was the corrected solute 
permeability. 
The above apparent permeability P corrected for the 
RBCs and free dye still overestimates the true diffusive solute 
permeability P d due to the coupling of solute flux with water 
flow (solvent drag). The P d for TRITC-dextran-155 kDa was 
calculated by using the following equations, 39,40 </p>

<p>P P 
p </p>

<p>p 
L 
p </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>p 
e ff </p>

<p>= 
− 
+ 
− 
exp ( 
) 
( 
) 
, 
1 
1 σ ∆ 
(3) </p>

<p>P 
L 
p </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>p 
e ff </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>= 
− 
( 
) 
, 
1 σ ∆ 
(4) </p>

<p>where P is the measured apparent permeability; P e is the 
Péclet number; L p is the hydraulic conductivity of the 
microvessel, which is ~2.0×10 -9 cm/s/cm H 2 O for the cere-
bral microvessels; 23,41 σ is the reflection coefficient of the 
microvessel to the solute, and Δp eff is the effective filtration 
pressure across the microvessel wall, obtained from </p>

<p>∆ 
∆ 
∆ 
∆ 
p 
p </p>

<p>eff </p>

<p>albumin 
albumin 
dye solute 
d ye solute </p>

<p>= 
− 
− </p>

<p>− 
− </p>

<p>σ 
π 
σ 
π 
, (5) </p>

<p>where Δp and Δπ are the hydrostatic and oncotic pressure dif-
ferences across the microvessel wall. The superscript dye-sol-
ute is TRITC-dextran-155 kDa; σ of rat cerebral microvessels 
to the test solutes were estimated based on previous studies 24 
according to the molecule sizes; σ dextran-155 kDa was estimated 
to be 0.96; Δp in the cerebral microvessel was ~10 cm H 2 O; 
and Δπ albumin was 3.6 cm H 2 O for 10 mg/mL BSA. 24 </p>

<p>Data analysis and statistics </p>

<p>The BBB permeability to dextran-155 kDa, measured at a 
specific time in the control group was used to normalize those 
in the test and sham control groups at the same time. Data 
were presented as mean ± standard error unless otherwise 
specified. Significance was assumed for probability level 
P0.05 using a two-way analysis of variance followed by </p>

<p>a Tukey's post hoc analysis (<rs id="software-1" type="software">JMP</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., Cary, 
NC, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The ultrasound power (voltage, BRR, and duty cycle), 
sonication duration, MB size, and MB concentration are 
important factors in controlling the BBB-disruption levels 
and determining whether the increased BBB permeability 
is reversible. 6,7,11,15,21,25 Based on prior literature, 6,7,10,21 we 
fixed the MB size to ~2 μm, MB concentration to ~1.7×10 6 
bubbles/mL, and sonication time to ~1 minute. Subse-
quently, we adjusted the voltage and BRR while keeping 
the duty cycle constant at 5% to generate different acoustic 
powers. Figure 5A shows a disrupted BBB after ~5 min-
utes by applying a power of ~13.1 W/cm 2 (voltage =4 V 
and BRR =500 kHz) for 1 minute. We then reduced the 
power to ~6.3 W/cm 2 (voltage =2.5 V and BRR =500 kHz). 
Figure 5B shows the image of the cerebral microvessels 
taken after ~20 minutes by applying 1-minute sonication 
at this dose. Although there was no visible BBB disrup-
tion, the increased permeability was not reversible in 
~60 minutes (the measurement was stopped after 60 minutes). </p>

<p>The corresponding BBB permeability measured after 5, 10, 
30, and 60 minutes was found to be 27.1×10 -7 , 23.5×10 -7 , 
23.6×10 -7 , and 19.6×10 -7 cm/s, respectively. These values 
are more than ten-fold greater than the control values without 
FUS treatment (Table 1). Reducing the power to 3.4 W/cm 2 
by decreasing the voltage to 1.25 V, there was no change 
in the BBB permeability for 60 minutes. However, keeping 
the same power of ~6.3 W/cm 2 , but reducing the voltage to 
1.25 V and increasing the BRR to 1,000 kHz, we were able to 
achieve a reversible BBB permeability increase in ~30 min-
utes. Figure 5C shows the image of the cerebral microvessels 
after ~20 minutes by applying this reversible acoustic dose 
for 1 minute. For comparison, Figure 5D shows the image of 
microvessels under the control condition without FUS and 
MBs. The fluorescence intensity in the surrounding tissue of 
the microvessels was noticeably higher in Figures 5B and 
C than that in Figure 5D, indicating more tracers passing 
across the microvessel due to the FUS-induced permeability 
increase in the presence of MBs. 
Figure 6 compares the BBB permeability to dextran-
155 kDa, under controls and under the treatment of the 
optimized FUS (6.3 W/cm 2 when voltage =1.25 V and 
BRR =1,000 kHz) in the presence of MBs. The solid line with 
filled squares in Figure 6 demonstrates the response of perme-
ability to FUS in the presence of MBs as a function of time. 
At 5 minutes post-FUS, the mean permeability increased </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4444 </p>

<p>shi et al </p>

<p>50 μm </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>50 μm </p>

<p>50 μm 
50 μm </p>

<p>Figure 5 representative images of the scanning region under various conditions. 
Notes: (A) after ~5 minutes post-FUs at the dose of acoustic power density 13.1 W/cm 2 (voltage =4 V, Brr =500 khz) with MB injection. (B) after ~20 minutes post-FUs at 
a lower dose of 6.3 W/cm 2 (voltage =2.5 V, Brr =500 khz) with MB injection. (C) after ~20 minutes post-FUs at the same lower dose of 6.3 W/cm 2 , but reduced voltage =1.25 V 
and increased Brr =1,000 khz, with MB injection. (D) Under control condition, with neither ultrasound sonication nor MB injection. 
Abbreviations: Brr, burst repetition rate; FUs, focused ultrasound; MB, microbubble. </p>

<p>Table 1 cerebral microvessel permeability (P) to TrITc-dextran-155 kDa under various conditions at different time points and the 
corresponding corrected P for the rBcs, free dye, and solvent drag </p>

<p>Group 
Vessel 
radius (μm) 
(mean ± SE) </p>

<p>Time 
(minutes) </p>

<p>P (measured) 
(×10 -7 cm/s) 
(mean ± SE) </p>

<p>P (corrected 
for RBC) 
(×10 -7 cm/s) </p>

<p>P (corrected 
for RBC and 
free dye) 
(×10 -7 cm/s) </p>

<p>P d (corrected for 
RBC, free dye, 
and solvent drag) 
(×10 -7 cm/s) </p>

<p>P d /P (corrected 
for RBC and 
free dye) </p>

<p>Ultrasound 
and bubble 
(n=15) </p>

<p>10.7±1.0 
5 
19.57±4.49 
17.42 
17.42 
16.99 
0.9752 
10 
14.46±2.07 
12.87 
12.87 
12.86 
0.9998 
15 
11.02±2.92 
9.81 
9.80 
9.80 
0.9997 
20 
5.12±1.30 
4.55 
4.54 
4.54 
0.9994 
25 
2.34±0.61 
2.08 
2.07 
2.07 
0.9988 
Bubble only 
(n=6) </p>

<p>8.1±1.5 
5 
1.40±0.36 
1.25 
1.23 
1.23 
0.9979 
25 
1.38±0.47 
1.23 
1.21 
1.21 
0.9979 
Ultrasound 
only (n=6) </p>

<p>7.9±1.4 
5 
1.51±0.33 
1.34 
1.33 
1.33 
0.9981 
25 
1.24±0.24 
1.10 
1.09 
1.09 
0.9976 
control 
(n=6) </p>

<p>6.8±1.3 
0 
1.13±0.19 
1.00 
0.99 
0.99 
0.9974 
5 
1.37±0.21 
1.22 
1.21 
1.21 
0.9979 
25 
1.72±0.17 
1.53 
1.52 
1.51 
0.9983 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: TrITc, tetramethylrhodamine isothiocyanate; rBc, red blood cell; se, standard error of the mean; P d , diffusive permeability. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4445 </p>

<p>enhanced BBB permeability by ultrasound </p>

<p>to (19.6±4.5)×10 -7 cm/s (n=15), a significant increase of 
14.3 (±4.1)-fold compared with the control (P=0.025). 
The mean permeability at 10, 15, 20, and 25 minutes was 
(14.5±2.1)×10 -7 , (11.0±2.9)×10 -7 , (5.1±1.3)×10 -7 , and 
(2.3±0.6)×10 -7 cm/s, respectively, representing increases of 
11.5 (±3.3, P=0.001), 6.8 (±2.1, P=0.052), 2.9 (±1.0, P=0.11), 
and 1.4 (±0.5, P=0.45)-fold compared with the control group. 
At 15 minutes post-FUS, permeability started to recover 
values similar to the control; after 25 minutes, permeability 
completely returned to the value comparable to the control, 
indicating a reversible BBB permeability increase under this 
FUS dose in the presence of MBs. 
For comparison, the permeability of the control 
group (n=6) measured at 0, 5, 10, 15, 20, and 25 minutes 
was (1.1±0.2)×10 -7 , (1.4±0.2)×10 -7 , (1.4±0.3)×10 -7 , 
(1.6±0.3)×10 -7 , (1.8±0.5)×10 -7 , and (1.7±0.3)×10 -7 cm/s, 
respectively. The permeability of that under only MB injec-
tion without sonication (bubble only, n=6) at 5, 10, 15, 20, and 
25 minutes was (1.4±0.4)×10 -7 , (1.1±0.3)×10 -7 , (1.2±0.1)×10 -7 , 
(1.3±0.9)×10 -7 , and (1.4±0.5)×10 -7 cm/s, respectively. The 
permeability of that under FUS in the absence of MBs 
("ultrasound only", n=6) at 5, 10, 15, 20, and 25 minutes 
was (1.5±0.3)×10 -7 , (1.6±0.4)×10 -7 , (1.3±0.2)×10 -7 , 
(1.1±0.1)×10 -7 , and (1.2±0.2)×10 -7 cm/s, respectively. They 
have no significant differences compared with the control 
group (P0.6). 
Table 1 summarizes the measured permeability and its 
corrected value for the RBCs, free dye, and solvent drag 
under various conditions at specific times. Since the ratio of </p>

<p>the diffusive permeability, P d , to the apparent permeability 
corrected after RBC and free dye was more than 97.5%, 
the solvent drag contribution to the BBB permeability to 
TRITC-dextran-155 kDa was negligible. In contrast, the 
solvent drag contribution to the macromolecule permeabil-
ity is significant in rat mesenteric microvessels due to two 
orders of magnitude higher hydraulic conductivity. 37 Table 
1 also summarizes the mean radius of the microvessels for 
each group. Since there was no significant difference in the 
BBB permeability between the post-capillary venules and 
the capillaries (P0.09), we only gave a mean size for these 
two types of microvessels. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Nhan et al 25 used two-photon microscopy to investigate 
the reversible and localized BBB disruption induced by 
FUS in the presence of MBs by imaging the cerebral 
vasculature during BBB disruption and observing the 
extravasation of fluorescently labeled solutes in real-time 
in vivo. They found that the threshold acoustic pressure for 
a successful induction in BBB disruption was 0.4-0.6 MPa 
by combining the MBs with a similar size and a reduced 
concentration as those used in the current study. Under 
this dose of FUS and the MBs, they observed a visible 
BBB disruption in the cerebral microvasculature, which 
peaked around 5 minutes, especially for microvessels with 
diameter of 10-30 μm. By using a formula in Dreher et al 42 
they converted the extravasation rate of the fluorescently 
labeled solutes to a global permeability index for the </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 </p>

<p>P/P control </p>

<p>Time (minutes) </p>

<p>Ultrasound and bubble (n=15) </p>

<p>Bubble only (n=6) </p>

<p>Ultrasound only (n=6) </p>

<p>Control (n=6) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Figure 6 Normalized blood-brain barrier permeability as a function of time. 
Notes: The solid line with () is for the treatment by ultrasound of 6.3 W/cm 2 (voltage =1.25 V, burst repetition rate =1,000 khz) in the presence of microbubbles. The 
dash-dot-dash line with () is for microbubbles only, with microbubble injection but without ultrasound sonication. The long dashed line with (Δ) is for ultrasound only, with 
ultrasound sonication in the absence of microbubbles. The short dashed line with (×) is for the control, with neither ultrasound nor microbubbles. *P-value 0.05 compared 
with the control. 
Abbreviation: P, permeability. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4446 </p>

<p>shi et al </p>

<p>entire microvasculature, which peaked around 5 minutes 
and returned to the baseline in 20 minutes for test solutes, 
dextran-10k and -70k, in their study. Their estimated FUS-
induced microvasculature permeability index changing 
patterns are similar to those in the individual microvessels 
under the current study. However, we found that under 
0.43 MPa (13.1 W/cm 2 ) of our FUS, the wall of the indi-
vidual microvessel was disrupted and could not go back to 
its baseline (Figure 5A). Even at a reduced power of 0.3 MPa 
(6.3 W/cm 2 ) with a voltage of 2.5 V, the permeability of 
the individual microvessel could not go back to its baseline 
value in ~60 minutes (Figure 5B). 
The study from Nhan et al 25 was invaluable in narrow-
ing parameter space and defining a consistent methodology. 
However, the method in Nhan et al 25 had some limitations. 
First, being injected via the tail vein, MBs would go back 
to the right ventricle of the heart, through the pulmonary 
circulation before they go into the systemic circulation and 
reach the cerebral microvessels. Along this journey, the MBs 
would be trapped in the pulmonary microvessels with smaller 
diameters, be diluted, and result in an uncertain concentration 
in brain microvessels. This would induce inaccurate assess-
ment of proper parameters for the FUS which can induce 
transient BBB permeability increase. Second, the equation 
they used to determine the microvasculature permeability 
assumes a constant driving force that is represented by the 
fluorescent intensity difference between the intravascular and 
extravascular spaces along the microvessel. However, tail 
vein injection of the fluorescently labeled solutes might not 
achieve a constant driving force along the microvessel due to 
the plasma clearance. Third, because of the poor drainage in 
the brain tissue, the built-up extravascular tracers could not be 
cleared out in time and may induce a saturated extravascular 
concentration or an extravascular concentration which is 
higher than the intravascular one, resulting in an inaccurate 
assessment of microvascular permeability by using the for-
mula in Dreher et al. 42 Fourth, the region of ~500 μm ×500 μm 
from where they determined the permeability, contains many 
types of microvessels including arterioles and venules. Post-
capillary venules and capillaries were suggested to be more 
suitable for permeability study since they are relatively less 
contractible or expandable under stimulations. 35 These prop-
erties are necessary for accurate determination of the BBB 
permeability under FUS stimulations. 35 Finally, their method 
can only give a relative permeability index, not the true 
solute permeability for a microvessel defined by the Kedem-
Katchalsky equation. 42 To overcome the aforementioned 
limitations, in our work we used multiphoton microscopy </p>

<p>with a higher spatial resolution to accurately determine the 
BBB permeability for the individual post-capillary venule or 
capillary under the FUS treatment. By injecting both MBs 
and fluorescently labeled test solutes through the carotid 
artery, we can achieve a more constant concentration in the 
cerebral microvessels. 
Previous studies have shown that the ultrasound power 
(voltage, BRR, and duty cycle), sonication duration, and MB 
size and concentration are important factors in controlling 
the BBB-disruption levels and determining whether or not 
the increased BBB permeability is reversible. 6,7,11,15,21,25 Using 
MRI, the acoustic power threshold of opening the BBB was 
found to be 0.15-0.3 MPa. 43 Whereas, the power threshold 
using two-photon microscopy was found to be 0.4-0.6 MPa. 25 
Using the same MB size and concentrations, we found that 
the FUS with the same power (0.3 MPa or 6.3 W/cm 2 ) at the 
reduced voltage and increased BRR induced a reversible BBB 
permeability increase compared with that with higher volt-
age and lower BRR, which did not exhibit reversibility. The 
mechanism responsible for this is unknown. Under this range 
of the FUS power, the thermal effect is negligible. 44 Other 
possible mechanisms for increasing the BBB permeability 
by FUS-driven MB activities in the cerebral microvessels 
include stable cavitation (stable small oscillation) and inertial 
cavitation (large amplitude oscillation). 11,45,46 These activities 
can generate calcium transient, 11,22,47 which may be respon-
sible for the transient increase in the BBB permeability. 48 
The increased Ca 2+ concentration in brain microvascular 
endothelial cells by FUS-driven MBs 22 is similar to that 
induced by bradykinin, histamine, and adenosine triphosphate 
(ATP), which are known to transiently increase the BBB 
permeability. 49,50 The increased magnitude and the temporal 
pattern in the permeability of an individual cerebral microves-
sel induced by the optimized FUS and MBs in the current 
study are similar to those in the permeability of an individual 
mesenteric microvessel induced by ATP in a study by He 
and Curry, 51 which also demonstrated the same pattern in 
endothelial Ca 2+ concentration changes. This similarity sug-
gests the mechanism of calcium transient by the FUS-driven 
MB activities in our study. Further investigation needs to be 
done to confirm this mechanism. 
In summary, in order to find the optimal FUS and MBs 
that can induce reversible increase in the BBB permeabil-
ity for the purpose of brain drug delivery, we employed 
minimally invasive multiphoton microscopy to quantify the 
BBB permeability to dextran-155 kDa with similar molecu-
lar weight to an antibody. We applyed different doses of 
FUS in the presence of MBs with an "optimal" size and </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4447 </p>

<p>enhanced BBB permeability by ultrasound </p>

<p>concentration. After several trials, we found the optimal dose 
of FUS that can transiently increase the BBB permeability. 
Our analysis was the first study at the individual microves-
sel level which provides an accurate in vivo assessment for 
the transient BBB permeability change under the treatment 
of FUS/MBs. The optimal FUS dose found for the revers-
ible BBB permeability increase without BBB disruption is 
reliable and can be applied to future clinical trials in radio-
immunotherapy. Our method can also be used to assess the 
optimal parameters of FUS/MBs to deliver other types of 
therapeutic agents and drug carriers. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Dr Adrian Rodriguez-Contreras for his assis-
tance in using the multiphoton imaging system, Dr Hoau-
Yan Wang for the oxygen bubbling setup, and Dr Marom 
Bikson for the function generator. This work was partially 
supported by NIH-CA153325 and CUNY SEED grant 
93348-14-01. RT and JB would like to thank the National 
Science Foundation (NSF) award NSF/CBET-0967365 
for funding. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>All authors contributed toward data analysis, drafting, and 
revising the paper and agree to be accountable for all aspects 
of the work. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>

<p>References </p>



<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-nanomedicine-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of Nanomedicine is an international, peer-
reviewed journal focusing on the application of nanotechnology 
in diagnostics, therapeutics, and drug delivery systems throughout 
the biomedical field. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, 
MedLine, CAS, SciSearch®, Current Contents®/Clinical Medicine, </p>

<p>Journal Citation Reports/Science Edition, EMBase, Scopus and the 
Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The manuscript management system 
is completely online and includes a very quick and fair peer-review 
system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/ 
testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4448 </p>



</text></tei>