<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4215594" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Eye blinks, typically occurring 15-20 times per minute, rarely capture attention during face-to-face interaction. To determine the 
extent to which eye blinks affect the viewer's brain activity, we recorded magnetoencephalographic brain responses to natural blinks, 
and to the same blinks slowed down to 38% of the original speed. The stimuli were presented on video once every 2.3-6.2 s. As a 
control, we presented two horizontal black bars moving with the same time courses and the same extent as the eyelids in the blink 
video. Both types of blinks and bars elicited clear responses peaking at about 200 ms in the occipital areas, with no systematic differ-
ences between hemispheres. For the bars, these main responses were (as expected) weaker (by 24%) and later (by 33 ms) to slow-
motion than normal-speed stimuli. For blinks, however, the responses to both normal-speed and slow-motion stimuli were of the same 
amplitude and latency. Our results demonstrate that the brain not only responds to other persons' eye blinks, but that the responses 
are as fast and of equal size even when the blinks are considerably slowed down. We interpret this finding to reflect the increased 
social salience of the slowed-down blinks that counteracted the general tendency of the brain to react more weakly and more slowly 
to slowly-vs. quickly-changing stimuli. This finding may relate to the social importance of facial gestures, including eye blinks. </p>

<p>Spontaneous eye blinks usually occur 15-20 times per minute, 
interrupting visual input each time for 200-400 ms. Their well-
established physiological role is to moisten and clean the cornea. 
But do eye blinks play other functional roles as well? 
Blinking rate decreases during tasks that require visual attention 
(Oh et al., 2012), and video viewers tend to blink more during 
scenes that contain less relevant information (Nakano et al., 2009). 
Similarly, blinks cluster around pauses in speech seen on video, but 
only when the voice can be heard (Nakano &amp; Kitazawa, 2010). 
Such inter-subject synchronization of eye blinks suggests that blinks 
play a role beyond corneal moistening, likely related to human 
social interaction. Eye blinks also affect the judgments that people 
make about others: those who blink very often are perceived as ner-
vous or careless (Omori &amp; Miyata, 2001). 
Less is known about how the eye blinks of others activate the 
viewer's brain. In a recent scalp electroencephalography (EEG) 
study, a sequence of three images simulating eye blinks elicited sev-
eral successive evoked potential deflections peaking at 100-600 ms 
(Brefczynski-Lewis et al., 2011). To investigate how the human 
brain reacts to natural blinks, we recorded magnetoencephalographic 
(MEG) brain responses to eye blinks presented via video. We also 
presented the same blinks in slow motion. The aim was two-fold: 
first, to determine whether these slow stimuli would evoke any brain </p>

<p>responses; and, if so, to examine whether these responses would be 
weaker and more prolonged compared with responses to normal-
speed stimuli, as would be expected on the basis of the general ten-
dency of the brain to react weaker and later to stimuli changing at 
slower speed (for a review, see Heinrich, 2007). As control stimuli, 
we presented two horizontal black bars that had similar size, loca-
tion and movement characteristics as the eyelids during the blinks. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Subjects </p>

<p>Eleven healthy volunteers (five female, six male, age 21-55 years, 
mean age 26 years; 10 right-and one left-handed) participated in the 
experiment. The experiment conformed with the Code of Ethics of the 
World Medical Association Declaration of Helsinki [JAMA (2013), 
310, 2191-2194], and all subjects signed an informed consent before 
participation. However, the study was not preregistered in a publicly 
accessible database before recruitment of the subjects because no such 
procedure exists in Finland. The MEG recordings had prior approval 
by the Coordinating Ethics Committee of Hospital District of Helsinki 
and Uusimaa (#28/13/03/00/11 and #95/13/03/00/08). </p>

<p>Stimuli and tasks </p>

<p>The stimulus was a video sequence comprising both normal and 
slowed-down blinks of a female staying immobile and looking at the 
camera. Only her face was visible (Fig. 1). The video was constructed </p>

<p>Correspondence: A. Mandel, as above. 
E-mail: anne.mandel@aalto.fi </p>

<p>Received 17 March 2014, accepted 6 April 2014 </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. European Journal of Neuroscience published by Federation of European Neuroscience Societies and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. 
This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and 
distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>European Journal of Neuroscience, Vol. 40, pp. 2576-2580, 2014 
doi:10.1111/ejn.12611 </p>

<p>from these two video clips, both of them repeated 102 times in a ran-
dom order and without breaks in-between, with the restriction that the 
same blink (either normal or slow) did not occur more than twice in a 
row. The normal-speed clip lasted for 2718 ms, with a single voluntary 
452-ms blink starting at 1000 ms. The slow-motion clip was generated 
by slowing down the normal-speed video to 38% of the original speed, 
so that it lasted for 7135 ms, with a 1200-ms blink starting at 2634 ms. 
To keep the subject's attention, five other normal-speed videos 
(2038-2686 ms in duration) of facial expressions (aimed to convey 
'thinking', 'agreeing', 'confused', 'smiling' and 'disgusted', per-
formed by the same person whose eye blinks were shown) were 
inserted between the blink video clips once after every 34 stimuli. 
The subjects were told to memorize the expressions and to recog-
nize them after the session from a list of 10 possible expressions. A 
blank gray screen appeared for 1 s before and after each expression 
video. The complete stimulus sequence lasted for about 17 min. 
The original eye-blink video was recorded with a high-speed cam-
era (Fastec InLine 1000, Fastec Imaging, San Diego, CA, USA) at 
500 frames/s in front of a white background. The videos were pre-
sented to the subject with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Experiment Builder</rs> 
TM software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v. 1.10.1</rs> 
(SR Research, Ottawa, ON, Canada). Due to video-projector restric-
tions, the presentation frame rate was 60 frames/s, so that only every 
seventh frame of the normal-speed stimulus and every third frame of 
the slow-motion stimulus was shown. Both videos appeared smooth 
and natural. The background color and the luminance of the screen 
were matched to the background of the video. 
The videos were presented on a screen (width 72 cm, height 
54 cm) placed 1 m in front of the subject's eyes, so that the size of the 
face in the video was approximately 14 cm 9 20 cm (visual angle 
11.5 deg 9 8.0 deg) in the center of the screen, and the size of an eye 
was approximately 2.6 cm 9 1.2 cm. The eyelid was moving verti-
cally approximately 1.2 cm during the blink. The Michelson contrasts 
between different eye features (cornea, eye white, eyelashes and eye-
lid) varied between 0.5 and 0.8, with an average contrast of 0.65. 
We aimed to create control stimuli that would have the same move-
ment characteristics as the eye blink, but would not resemble human 
eyes or facial gestures. Therefore, we showed videos of two horizontal 
black bars (constructed and presented at 30 frames/s) moving up and 
down on a gray background in the middle of the screen; the sizes, 
locations and movement time courses of the bars were matched to 
those of the blinks (Fig. 1): two bars (2.6 cm 9 0.035 cm) were mov-
ing 1.2 cm vertically on the screen with a time course similar to that 
of the blinks. During the 'open' and 'closed' periods, the bars 
remained at the highest or lowest position, correspondingly. The 
Michelson contrast between the bars and the background was 0.6. </p>

<p>Each experiment started with a control condition in which 102 nor-
mal-speed and 102 slow-motion bars were pseudo-randomized similar 
to the stimuli in the blink videos (but with no facial expressions in-
between). The subjects were informed that a second visual task would 
follow, but its content (eye blinks) was not mentioned. After having 
seen the bar videos, the subjects were asked to freely describe what (if 
anything) the bar motion had resembled in their opinion. </p>

<p>Data acquisition </p>

<p>Magnetoencephalographic signals were recorded with a 306-channel 
whole-scalp neuromagnetometer (Elekta Neuromag Oy, Helsinki, 
Finland) in a magnetically shielded room (Euroshield, Eura, Finland) 
in the MEG Core of the Brain Research Unit of Aalto University. 
This MEG device comprises 102 sensor units, each containing two 
orthogonal planar gradiometers and one magnetometer. The signals 
were bandpass-filtered to 0.03-200 Hz, digitized at 600 Hz and 
averaged online, time-locked to the beginning of the blinks in the 
videos. The analysed period extended from À500 to 2000 ms (nor-
mal) or to 4000 ms (slow) from the blink onset. 
Vertical electro-oculogram (EOG) was measured between elec-
trodes located above and below the left eye, and horizontal EOG 
between electrodes on the left and right lateral eye canthi. Both 
EOGs were averaged, time-locked to stimulus onsets to later verify 
that artifacts from the subjects' own blinking did not contaminate 
the observed brain responses. 
Four head-position-indicator coils were attached to the subject's 
scalp, and head coordinates were registered with a 3D digitizer by iden-
tifying the locations of the coils together with the locations of three ana-
tomical landmarks (nasion and left and right preauricular points) and 
some additional points on the scalp. At the beginning of each measure-
ment block, the position of the subject's head in the MEG helmet was 
measured by inducing weak currents into the indicator coils. 
The subject was instructed to sit still and relax, and to observe the 
stimuli attentively. No instruction was given about eye blinking or where 
to direct the gaze. The whole experiment lasted for about 1 h, including 
the preparation, MEG measurement and answering of the questionnaire 
about the facial expressions observed during the measurement. </p>

<p>Analysis </p>

<p>MEG recordings </p>

<p>The MEG data were preprocessed with the temporal signal-space-sepa-
ration method (Taulu &amp; Simola, 2006; Taulu &amp; Hari, 2009) using the 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">MaxFilter</rs> 
TM software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 2.2</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Elekta Neuromag Oy</rs>, Helsinki, Fin-</p>

<p>1000 (ms) </p>

<p>2634 (ms) 
3301 </p>

<p>452 
1266 </p>

<p>OPEN 
OPEN </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>BLINK </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Schematic presentation of the eye blink (top images) and bar (bottom images) stimuli. Durations of events in normal-speed (top scale) and slow-motion 
(bottom scale) videos are indicated: eyes open (OPEN); blink (BLINK); and eyes fully open again (OPEN). Dashed lines were added on top and below the bars 
and the eyes to indicate the similar movement amplitude for eye blinks and bars to improve the readability of this figure; the line was not present in the stimuli 
presented to the subjects. </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. European Journal of Neuroscience published by Federation of European Neuroscience Societies and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. 
European Journal of Neuroscience, 40, 2576-2580 </p>

<p>Brain responses to observed eye blinks 2577 </p>

<p>land). We computed vector sums over each pair of planar gradiometers 
to minimize the effect of source orientation in the analysed waveforms: 
the signals from the two orthogonal planar gradiometers in each MEG 
sensor were squared, summed, and finally the square root was 
computed of the sum. Thus, the resulting signals were always positive. 
We next computed areal averages of the vector sums over the 
posterior parieto-temporo-occipital brain regions, separately for each 
subject's left hemisphere (nine sensor pairs), central area (eight pairs) 
and right hemisphere (nine pairs; for area selection, Fig. 2). For each 
subject, the areal mean signals were normalized according to the indi-
vidual maximum in any of the three areas (over all conditions); the 
maximum was allowed to occur at any time after the start of the blink 
in the video during the 2-s (normal-speed stimuli) or 4-s (slow-motion 
stimuli) analysis periods. We compared areal mean signals instead of 
carrying out source analysis because the field patterns of the long-last-
ing signals were not dipolar and did not allow reliable source modeling. 
The peak amplitudes of the first prominent responses were mea-
sured with respect to a 500-ms baseline preceding the blink onset; dur-
ing the baseline period, the immobile face was visible. Before the 
amplitude measurements, the signals were low-pass-filtered at 30 Hz. 
To define the response onset, we searched for the best-fitting slope 
of the increasing areal mean response before the first prominent peak 
(polyfit function in <rs id="software-2" type="software">Matlab</rs> 
â <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 8.0.0.783</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">MathWorks</rs>, Natick, </p>

<p>MA, USA); before slope fitting, the peak amplitudes were normalized 
to 1. Response onset was defined as the crossing point of the slope and 
the mean + 2 standard deviations of the baseline amplitude. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Behavioral results </p>

<p>After the bar videos, we asked the subjects to freely elaborate whether 
the bars had reminded them of anything. Ten out of 11 subjects said 
that the bars resembled human or cartoon character's eyes, and one 
subject mentioned old computer games; two additional notes referred 
to a computer game and a nodding head. 
After the blink videos, all 11 participants remembered having seen a 
'smiling' and a 'thinking' face, and 10 subjects recalled the 'confused' 
and nine the 'disgusted' expressions. The 'agreeing' expression was </p>

<p>rather difficult to describe verbally and, accordingly, was recognized 
only by four subjects. Altogether, the participants recognized 
4.3 AE 0.1 (mean AE SEM) out of the five facial expressions. </p>

<p>Brain responses </p>

<p>Figure 2 shows the areal mean responses for normal-speed (blue) 
and slow-motion (red) blinks (top) and bars (bottom) separately in </p>

<p>BAR </p>

<p>BLINK </p>

<p>Normalized amplitude </p>

<p>Time (s) </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0 
2 
0 
1 
2 
1 </p>

<p>RIGHT 
CENTRAL 
LEFT </p>

<p>Normal speed 
Slow motion </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Mean AE SEM responses across all 11 subjects to normal-speed (blue lines and light blue bands) and slow-motion (red) blinks (top) and bars (bottom). 
The areal average responses are shown separately for the left-hemisphere, central and right-hemisphere posterior regions (see the schematic heads above). The 
duration of the normal-speed (light blue) and slow-motion (light red) stimulus is shown on the horizontal axis. </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>Normalized amplitude </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
1.0 
0 </p>

<p>Normalized amplitude </p>

<p>Normal speed 
Slow motion </p>

<p>BAR </p>

<p>BLINK </p>

<p>Time (s) </p>

<p>-0.2 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Mean AE SEM responses across all 11 subjects to normal-speed (blue 
lines and light blue bands) vs. slow-motion (red) blinks (top) and bars (bot-
tom), calculated over 52 occipital planar gradiometer channels. The duration 
of the normal-speed (blue) and slow-motion (red) stimulus is shown on the 
horizontal axis. </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. European Journal of Neuroscience published by Federation of European Neuroscience Societies and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. 
European Journal of Neuroscience, 40, 2576-2580 </p>



<p>the left-hemisphere, midline and right-hemisphere posterior parieto-
temporo-occipital regions, where the responses to both types of 
stimuli were most prominent. The responses did not differ between 
these areas in any of the measured parameters (onset time, rising 
slope, peak latency, peak amplitude), and we therefore carried out 
further analyses on signals averaged across these three areas. 
Figure 3 depicts the signals averaged over the three areas for blinks 
and bars. Responses to normal-speed eye blinks started at 
151 AE 15 ms (mean AE SEM) and peaked at 196 AE 16 ms. The corre-
sponding values for slow-motion blinks were 157 AE 17 and 
210 AE 14 ms. Thus, the responses to normal and slow-motion blinks 
did not differ either in onset or peak latencies, nor did their rising slopes 
differ. The normalized peak amplitudes were 44.8 AE 7.1% (out of indi-
vidual response maxima) for normal-speed blinks and 49.2 AE 7.2% for 
slow-motion blinks; the maximum signals (over all stimulus types) 
were obtained later than the first peak (on average, at 359 AE 39 ms). 
In contrast to responses to blinks (that did not differ between nor-
mal-speed and slow-motion stimuli), responses to bars started 
24 AE 7 ms earlier to normal-speed than slow-motion stimuli (main 
effect for speed F 1,10 = 11.2, P = 0.007), but the rise times (slopes) 
did not differ. The responses peaked on average 33 ms earlier to 
normal-speed than slow-motion bars (231 AE 3 vs. 264 AE 12 ms; 
F 1,10 = 8.6; P = 0.015), and the normalized responses were on 
average a third stronger to normal-speed than slow-motion bars (nor-
malized values 76.1 AE 6.6% vs. 58.2 AE 5.6%; main effect for speed 
F 1,10 = 18.2; P = 0.002). 
Compared with responses to eye blinks, the responses to bar stimuli 
(Fig. 3, bottom panel) started significantly later. The delay was 
34 AE 13 ms for normal-speed and 52 AE 19 ms for slow-motion stim-
uli; an ANOVA for stimulus (bar vs. blink) 9 speed (normal speed vs. 
slow motion) showed a main effect for stimulus type (F 1,10 = 17.4, 
P = 0.002). Responses peaked later to bars than blinks. The delay was 
35 AE 14 ms for normal-speed and 54 AE 19 ms for slow-motion stim-
uli, respectively; an ANOVA for stimulus 9 speed showed a main effect 
for stimulus type (F 1,10 = 20.1, P = 0.001). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Brain activity related to observed eye blinks vs. to socially 
irrelevant moving objects </p>

<p>By recording MEG brain responses to eye blinks shown on video, we 
found that other person's eye blinks elicit clear responses in the view-
er's brain. Interestingly, neither the strengths nor the onsets or peak 
latencies differed between the blinks shown at normal speed vs. slow 
motion, with the speed decreased to 38% of the original. In contrast, 
responses to bars used as control stimuli were weaker and delayed 
when the stimulus speed was slowed down. This latter effect agrees 
with earlier findings that brain responses decrease when light-spot 
stimuli move at slower speed (Kawakami et al., 2002). Accordingly, 
transient cortical responses to simple auditory stimuli peak later to 
stimuli with slower rise times (for a review, see Hari, 1990). Cortical 
responses to blinks thus behaved clearly differently than expected on 
the basis of simple physical characteristics, as the strengths and peak 
latencies did not differ between considerably slowed-down and nor-
mal-speed eye blinks. </p>

<p>Social significance of other person's eye blinks </p>

<p>Blinks are socially relevant for the perceiver as they can give clues 
about the mental and physical state of the other person: blinking rate 
decreases (compared with silent rest) during cognitively demanding </p>

<p>tasks (Fukuda, 1994; Bentivoglio et al., 1997; Oh et al., 2012), but 
rises during conversation (Bentivoglio et al., 1997) and during pro-
longed wakefulness (Barbato et al., 1995). Reduced blinking rate 
can signal subjective salience of an observed object, and the effect 
is present already in children (Shultz et al., 2011). Moreover, people 
tend to blink less while they tell a lie and, immediately after the lie 
is told, they blink more again (Leal &amp; Vrij, 2008). 
Blinking rate can be disturbed in several brain and mental diseases, 
such as schizophrenia (Chan &amp; Chen, 2004), Parkinson's disease (Ag-
ostino et al., 2008) and attention-deficit-hyperactivity disorder (Ca-
plan et al., 1996); medication can contribute to these changes. People 
with autism do not synchronize their blinking with the speaker seen 
on a video, in contrast to what healthy subjects do (Nakano et al., 
2011), suggesting that reacting to other person's eye blinks is one sign 
of successful behavioral inter-subject synchronization. 
The slow-motion eye blinks may have even higher salience for 
the perceiver than the normal blinks because of their unusual time 
course that makes the person appear drowsy or odd, thereby adding 
social significance to the expression. Attention is known to enhance 
cortical responses during visual discrimination (Spitzer et al., 1988) 
and spatial-attention tasks (Kanwisher &amp; Wojciulik, 2000). More-
over, socially relevant stimuli, such as emotional vs. neutral faces, 
elicit stronger EEG responses in posterior temporal brain regions 
even when the perceivers concentrate on, for example, gender and 
not emotion (Sato et al., 2001). Therefore, it is possible that 
enhanced attention to slow-motion blinks contributed to the short 
latencies and large amplitudes of the responses. </p>

<p>Brain responses to eye blinks vs. to other observed facial 
gestures </p>

<p>So far, brain responses to observed eye blinks have been studied 
only rarely. In a previous EEG experiment, images of closed eyes 
were shown for 33 ms in-between open-eyes baseline images so that 
the sequence of pictures did not include any real eyelid movements 
(Brefczynski-Lewis et al., 2011). These 'blinks' elicited robust 
occipito-temporal P100 and right-hemisphere-lateralized N170 resp-
onses, which did not differ from responses to gaze movements and 
eye closures also presented within the same stimulus sequence. In 
our study, the natural blinks were considerably longer than 33 ms 
(lasting for about 450 ms), and the responses to them peaked about 
200 ms after blink onset in the parieto-temporo-occipital cortex. 
The human brain is known to react to many observed facial ges-
tures, including gaze shifts and mouth movements that activate, in 
addition to the early visual cortex, for example, the superior temporal 
sulcus (STS) and the MT/V5 area (for a review, see Puce &amp; Perrett, 
2003). Social context or meaning of the observed facial gestures 
modifies the viewer's brain responses. For example, the 150-160-ms 
MEG responses arising from the MT/V5 region were stronger to 
gaze-change stimuli, composed of two images generating a percept of 
apparent movement, when the gaze shifted towards rather than away 
from the viewer (Watanabe et al., 2006). On the other hand, the 
170-ms temporal-lobe EEG response (N170) was weaker to direct 
than averted gaze (Puce et al., 2000). In a more complex social 
setting, where the subjects were viewing images of three faces, N170 
was unaffected, but the later EEG responses (P350 and P500) were 
modified by the scenario involving social attention (Carrick et al., 
2007). 
In addition to eye gaze, various mouth expressions can activate 
several brain regions. In an MEG study, static face images with both 
verbal and non-verbal mouth shapes triggered an activation sequence 
from the occipital visual areas to the STS, then to the inferior parie-</p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. European Journal of Neuroscience published by Federation of European Neuroscience Societies and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. 
European Journal of Neuroscience, 40, 2576-2580 </p>

<p>Brain responses to observed eye blinks 2579 </p>

<p>tal cortex, and finally to the inferior frontal cortex and the primary 
motor cortex (Nishitani &amp; Hari, 2002). The full activation sequence 
took about 220-250 ms. 
Another example of how facial movements that are potential 
social cues can modulate the observer's brain responses comes from 
a functional magnetic resonance imaging study of yawning: videos 
of yawning faces elicited significantly stronger activity in the right 
posterior STS and in the anterior STS of both hemispheres than did 
non-nameable mouth movements (Sch€ urmann et al., 2005). 
In our study, both the socially relevant eye blinks and the moving 
bars used as control stimuli (but often interpreted as eyelid move-
ments), elicited similar temporo-occipital responses peaking about 
200 ms after the movement onset. A clear difference, however, was 
seen in the reactivity to stimulus speed: only responses to blinks, 
and not to bars, differed between the normal-speed and slowed-
down stimuli. </p>

<p>Caveats </p>

<p>Our blink and control (bar) stimuli differed in many visual features. 
Still, 10 out of 11 subjects reported that the bars reminded them of 
human eye blinks, probably reflecting the predisposition to perceive 
faces in various visual patterns. Good examples are the famous 
paintings by Giuseppe Arcimboldo (1526-1593) persuading viewers 
to perceive faces in paintings containing only vegetables, fruits, fish, 
miniature humans or inanimate objects. Accordingly, it is very diffi-
cult to create control stimuli for human blinks that would be similar 
to the original stimuli in low-level physical features but would not 
elicit an impression of blinking or a human face. 
Although we saw that the responses to eye blinks started and peaked 
earlier compared with similarly moving bars, this effect could be due 
to differences in physical stimulus features. Therefore, drawing any 
conclusions from those direct comparisons between responses to 
blinks vs. bars would not be well-founded. Nevertheless, the differ-
ences between blink and bar stimuli cannot explain the differences 
between responses to normal and slow-motion stimuli of the same type. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Taken together, our results show that normal eye blinks are clearly 
registered in the viewer's brain, and that the responses remain 
equally fast and strong even when the speed of the blinks is consid-
erably slowed down. This behavior contrasts responses to other sim-
ilarly moving stimuli as they become weaker and delayed when the 
speed of the stimulus decreases. These findings support the view 
that eye blinks of other persons are socially relevant behavioral 
events and they should be adequately considered when studying 
social interaction. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This study was supported by the European Research Council (Advanced 
Grant No. 232946), the Academy of Finland (Grants No. 131483 and No. 
263800), the aivoAALTO research project of Aalto University, and the Finn-
ish Graduate School of Neuroscience. The authors thank Mia Illman for help 
in MEG measurements, Cathy Nangini for language checking, and Infradex 
(Vantaa, Finland) for the opportunity to use the high-speed camera for stimu-
lus recordings. </p>

<p>Abbreviations </p>

<p>EEG, electroencephalography; EOG, electro-oculogram; MEG, magnetoen-
cephalography; STS, superior temporal sulcus. </p>



<p>© 2014 The Authors. European Journal of Neuroscience published by Federation of European Neuroscience Societies and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. 
European Journal of Neuroscience, 40, 2576-2580 </p>



</text></tei>