<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4818058" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: The present study aimed to identify the psychological profiles of professional futsal 
players in terms of the gender schema and to evaluate the physiological parameters (speed, accel-
eration, strength, and power) and fatigue index of these athletes according to their gender profiles 
and relative to their positions on the court. The Masculine Inventory of the Self-concept Gender 
Schemas was used to classify the sample into typological groups, and the Running Anaerobic 
Sprint Test was used to measure the physiological parameters (speed, acceleration, strength, 
and power) and the fatigue index. The study sample was composed of 64 male professional 
futsal players who competed in the National Indoor Soccer league in 2013; the subjects had 
an average weight of 76.00±6.7 kg. Among the athletes studied, 23 (35.9%) were classified as 
heteroschematic female, 22 (34.4%) as heteroschematic male, and 19 (29.7%) as isoschematic. 
Regarding their positions on the court, eleven were goalkeepers (17.2%), 13 (20.3%) were 
defenders, 28 (43.8%) were midfielders, and 12 (18.8%) were attackers. The players had similar 
weights even when belonging to different typological groups and having different positions in the 
court. However, it is worth noting that male heteroschematic players had a greater mean weight 
(77.11±5.93 kg) and that the goalkeeper was, on average, the heaviest player (79.36±8.14 kg). 
The results of the physiological parameter analysis relative to typological group showed that, on 
average, high-level soccer players presented similar performance profiles in different rounds, as 
statistically significant differences were not found in any of the studied physiological variables 
(weight, distance, speed, acceleration, strength, power, and fatigue index). Although the results 
of this research did not reveal statistically significant differences between the groups in terms 
of the assessed variables, we observed that some results related to personality traits associated 
with both the male and female components could help to clarify and establish relationships with 
some strategic aspects inherent to futsal. 
Sport science has become a popular area of study in recent decades. 
1 Scientists, research-
ers, coaches, and all professionals from fields related to sport science have been motivated 
to constantly seek solutions to various problems related to the pursuit of optimal athletic 
performance, such as knowledge of physiological and psychological characteristics, which 
is essential to improve the structure of training in futsal, for instance. </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>In recent decades, sport psychology professionals have contributed significant 
improvements to the performances of athletes, coaches, and other professionals in 
sports and exercise fields. 
3 These improvements resulted from the assistance provided </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Psychology Research and Behavior Management 
24 March 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Psychology Research and Behavior Management 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>nascimento et al </p>

<p>to all individuals involved in sports-related assessment in an 
attempt to facilitate the development of better coping strate-
gies for withstanding psychological and physiological factors 
involved in training and competition. 
4 Regarding psychologi-
cal factors, athletes who are outgoing, assertive, and intrinsi-
cally motivated, among other features, have been observed to 
stand out from those with other personality traits. </p>

<p>4,5 </p>

<p>Regarding the physiological factors needed for good 
futsal performance, Chagas et al declared speed, strength, 
power in the lower limbs, resistance, agility, and a suitable 
body composition to be essential performance attributes. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>The universal symptom of fatigue, which is not directly 
related to acute or chronic illness, is among the most com-
mon complaints of high-performance athletes in relation to 
the practice of any high-performance sport. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Although it is difficult to determine the cause of fatigue, 
which is affected by many factors, Foss and Keteyian, </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Santos et al, 
9 and Lepers et al 
10 define muscular fatigue as the 
inability of a given muscle to maintain and continue power 
generation during a particular activity. 
Over the years, the concept of fatigue has undergone 
several changes. In the literature, descriptions of fatigue 
development in different types of exercise have been 
published, along with research intended to elucidate the 
processes and mechanisms involved. However, the litera-
ture has revealed different points of view that depend on 
the mechanisms and processes associated with fatigue. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>The study 
11 was important, because their aim is to improve 
athletic performance. 
According to Gomes et al, 
1 high-performance sport has 
evolved significantly worldwide in recent decades. Because 
of this evolutionary process, the study of sports training has 
adopted a practical approach to athletic preparation, using 
widespread scientific knowledge as guidance for intervention 
in the technical commissioning of the team. For example, 
some of the many challenges faced by the practitioners of 
sports science in training include assessment of futsal ath-
letes' fatigue levels and identification of which conditions 
are better for training and competition. </p>

<p>12-14 </p>

<p>Futsal is among the most practiced sports in Brazil, but 
questions regarding the best type of training and best perfor-
mance of players have not yet been addressed satisfactorily. 
A systematic analysis of literature related to this discipline 
revealed that studies attempting to identify factors related 
to fatigue (eg, psychological aspects) are scarce. Although 
psychological aspects are an important variable in the per-
formance of elite athletes, coaches and coaching staff still </p>

<p>base their training on empiricism, without consolidating their 
working methodologies with scientific evidence. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>In this sense, it becomes important to understand the 
cognitive and emotional schemas of the high-performance 
athlete in order to draw inferences about future behavior in 
competition situations. 
5 This concern regarding athletes' cog-
nitive styles is not new to the field of sports psychology, and 
some researchers have sought and still seek the ideal athletic 
psychological traits, or personality structures that are better 
adjusted to events occurring in a sporting context. </p>

<p>15-18 </p>

<p>For example, Markus et al defined self-concept as a 
multidimensional structure composed of cognitive, affective, 
and behavioral components, resulting in patterns of self-
perception and perception of others. 
19 Therefore, a person's 
self-concept is not inherent to the self-being but is rather a 
construction developed throughout life, resulting from that 
person's interpersonal relationships, family, school, and 
social environment, and self-perceptions of success and 
failure derived from personal experience. Athletes are the 
results of all of these influences, and their performances are 
directly affected by the individual personalities they have con-
structed throughout their lives. The self-schema is an impor-
tant aspect of self-concept; this is considered an important 
feature and is used by individuals in their self-descriptions. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Self-schemas act as lenses that shape, filter, focus, and guide 
perception, and thus, influence the way in which information 
is processed. Among the existing self-schemas, those related 
to gender are formed from observations and experiences of 
the characteristics, roles, and norms pertaining to the con-
structs of masculinity and femininity. As each individual has 
experiences consistent with gender constructs during social 
interaction, they eventually incorporate these experiences 
in different proportions and measures, resulting in specific 
cognitive schemas called gender schemas. In Brazilian 
culture, for example, characteristics such as sensitivity, 
gentleness, emotionalism, sensuality, fragility, and passivity 
are considered relevant to femininity, whereas rationality, 
aggressiveness, competitiveness, objectivity, individualism, 
and stubbornness are considered relevant to masculinity. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>During a game, elite athletes encounter situations wherein 
these psychological constructs can directly influence how 
they face the challenges of competition, and hence, their 
performance. It thus becomes critical for coaches not only 
to identify this intervening variable, but also, if possible, to 
achieve control over it. 
Despite the search for an ideal athletic psychological 
profile, as justified by the pursuit of better performance, </p>

<p>Psychology Research and Behavior Management 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>How psychological profiles influence athletes' physiology </p>

<p>Melo et al 
4 and Melo and Giavoni 
5 concluded that there 
is no such ideal profile. 
4,5 Different profiles may be better 
suited to different sport disciplines, depending on their 
specific characteristics. In addition, suitable profiles may 
vary depending on the player's position on the court/field 
(team sports), type of competition (in the case of individual 
sports), and specific action taking place. Therefore, it can be 
stated that there is no single ideal psychological profile, but 
rather several profiles that require specification. 
Despite the importance of investigating possible causes 
that lead an individual to experience fatigue during exercise, 
an investigation of the psychological aspects that influence 
this fatigue has also become an area of interest for all sports 
professionals working in the field of high-performance sports. 
The reviewed literature suggests differences between the 
fatigue levels of men and women; however, as the purpose of 
this study was to evaluate differences between the genders, 
no comparative studies of these differences were found. 
Overall, health-related studies treat gender as sex, when in 
fact gender and sex have two different definitions. Sex refers 
exclusively to the biological and physiological characteris-
tics related to men or women. Gender refers to the addition 
of the psychological aspects of masculinity and femininity 
(eg, behaviors, attitudes, social roles) to the characteristics 
of sex. 
22 All of these studies originated from a study by 
Giavoni, 
23 who constructed mathematical models capable of 
assessing the gender profiles of men (Masculine Inventory of 
the Self-concept Gender Schemas [IMEGA]) and feminine 
(IFEGA) and classifying these profiles as heteroschematic 
masculine, heteroschematic feminine, or isoschematic. This 
classification identifies the psychological gender profile of 
an individual independently of sex. 
The present study aimed to identify the psychological 
profiles of professional futsal players in terms of the gender 
schema and to evaluate the physiological parameters (speed, 
acceleration, strength, power) and fatigue index of these 
athletes, according to their gender profiles and relative to 
their positions on the court. The hypothesis of the current 
research is that the results in the Running Anaerobic Sprint 
Test (RAST), which assesses the fatigue index, would be 
higher in a male heteroschematic gender profile than in the 
isoschematic and female heteroschematic profiles, because 
futsal is taken mainly as a sport with similar traits to those 
that constitute the male schemas in the Brazilian culture, and 
therefore, the male heteroschematic athlete would engage 
more in the practice of this sport, either in trainings or com-
petitions, as well as in RAST. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>The current study was submitted to the Research Ethics 
Committee of the Catholic University of Brasília (CEP/ 
UCB). Ethics approval was granted (approval number CAAE 
00949012.0.0000.0029) and written informed consent was 
obtained from participants. </p>

<p>The sample </p>

<p>The current study sample was composed of 64 professional 
male futsal players who constituted a sample of all athletes 
competing in the 2013 National Indoor Soccer League. This 
was a convenience sample, because the withdrawal of at least 
15 subjects was required from each profile (heteroschematic 
male, heteroschematic female, and isoschematic). Author 
MGBN was not informed about the psychological profiles 
of the sample in order to ensure a double-blind study free of 
any researcher bias. Each participant received a statement of 
informed consent form informing them about the research 
purposes and possible risks and benefits of the study, as well 
as the voluntary nature of their participation. All sample 
members were treated as a single group, and data related to the 
psychological gender profiles derived from their self-concepts 
as well as muscle fatigue were collected. These data were col-
lected within each athlete's or team's training environment. 
The inclusion criteria were: 
1. status as an athlete from a team that participated in the 
2013 National Indoor Soccer League; 
2. attendance for all required data collection procedures; 
3. adult category; and 
4. agreement with the specifications of the informed consent 
form. </p>

<p>Instruments and procedures 
iMega </p>

<p>IMEGA is a psychometric instrument used to assess male 
and female individuals according the self-concept schemes. 
It is an identification related to social and cultural construc-
tion of the personality of each subject. Validation of the 
Portuguese-language version in Brazil was carried out by 
Giavoni and Tamayo. </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>IMEGA features 83 items, of which 41 belong to the male 
scale and 42 belong to the female scale. The subject uses a 
variation ranging from zero to four to express how much he 
identifies with each item. The male scale is based on neglect, 
rationality, boldness, and aggressiveness factors, while the 
female scale is based on integrity, sensuality, insecurity, 
emotionality, and sensitivity factors. </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Psychology Research and Behavior Management 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>44 </p>

<p>nascimento et al </p>

<p>From the interaction between more or less prevalent char-
acteristics, a three-dimensional vector is formed, which rep-
resents the spatial form of the male or female scheme (male 
heteroschematic and female heteroschematic, respectively). 
There is also the possibility that the interaction between 
contemplated characteristics by IMEGA identify a hybrid 
scheme called isoschematic. </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>The athletes were instructed not to communicate with 
each other during the application of IMEGA and not to 
comment on this assessment before completing the other 
data collection procedures. </p>

<p>RasT </p>

<p>RAST is a field test used to assess anaerobic capacity accord-
ing to four values: maximum power, average power, minimum 
power, and fatigue index. Test validation was performed by 
Zagatto et al. 
25 RAST is composed of six 35 m sprints; sub-
jects perform all sprints at maximum speed. All test times 
are recorded in seconds, and measurements are precise to 
hundredths of a second. Each run is separated from the next 
by an interval of 10 seconds. The end of this interval, which 
is also the starting point for the next sprint, is indicated by a 
sound stimulus (whistle). 
The 35 m stretch was delimited by two electronic bar-
riers (Multi-Full Sprint, Hidrofit, Belo Horizonte, Brazil) 
equipped with photocells. These instruments identified the 
moment when the subjects left the starting point and the 
moment when they reached the finishing point, and trans-
mitted this information to a connected computer. A specific 
computer program processed the data and generated test 
results. A 10 yard length was marked with cones before the 
first electronic barrier and after the second electronic barrier, 
to provide space for deceleration after each run. </p>

<p>Assessment of fatigue 
Assessment of fatigue by RAST </p>

<p>The assessment of fatigue by RAST was calculated using 
the fatigue index. It was therefore necessary to calculate the 
power of each run according to the following formula: </p>

<p>Power 
(Body Mass) (Distance) 
(Time) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>= 
× 
(1) </p>

<p>Body mass is expressed in kilograms, distance in meters, 
time in seconds, and power values in watts. Maximum 
power corresponds to the power used in the fastest run, 
and minimum power corresponds to the power used in the 
slowest run. </p>

<p>Once identified, maximum power and minimum power 
were used to obtain the fatigue index value using the fol-
lowing formula: </p>

<p>Fatigue Index 
Maximum Power Minimum Power 
Sum total of the 6 runs 
= 
− </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>IMEGA self-concept questionnaire </p>

<p>The self-concept questionnaire was applied in the host cities 
of teams participating in the National Indoor Soccer League. 
The questionnaire was administered by author MGBN, and 
custody of the materials (completed questionnaires) was the 
responsibility of the research team. </p>

<p>Statistical treatment </p>

<p>To investigate the hypothesis of this study <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 22</rs> for Windows was used. One-way analysis of variance 
(ANOVA) and one-way repeated ANOVA for repeated data 
were conducted. The aim of the one-way ANOVA was to 
compare the averages of several physiological parameters 
relative to the groups; a difference in the mean physiologi-
cal parameter values of the three groups would result in a 
statistical difference between subjects classified as hetero-
schematic male, isoschematic, and heteroschematic female. 
Accordingly, the calculated P-value would be less than the 
adopted significance level (5%). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The study sample was composed of 64 male professional 
futsal players who competed in the National Indoor Soc-
cer league in 2013; the subjects had an average weight of 
76.00±6.7 kg. Among the athletes studied, 23 (35.9%) were 
classified as heteroschematic female, 22 (34.4%) as hetero-
schematic male, and 19 (29.7%) as isoschematic. Regarding 
their positions on the court, eleven athletes were goalkeep-
ers (17.2%), 13 (20.3%) were defenders, 28 (43.8%) were 
midfielders, and 12 (18.8%) were attackers. The players had 
similar weights, even when belonging to different typological 
groups and having different positions on the court. However, 
it is worth noting that male heteroschematic players had a 
greater mean weight (77.11±5.93 kg) and that the goalkeeper 
was, on average, the heaviest player (79.36±8.14 kg). The 
analytic results are shown in Tables 1 and 2. 
Athletes classified as heteroschematic males started 
sprints at the highest speed but ended at the same speed as 
the isoschematic athletes. The differences were statistically 
insignificant. Heteroschematic male athletes began with </p>

<p>Psychology Research and Behavior Management 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>How psychological profiles influence athletes' physiology </p>

<p>Table 1 Physiological parameters relative to psychological 
gender profile </p>

<p>Psychological 
gender profile </p>

<p>Average Standard 
deviations </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Physiological and anthropometric parameters 
Weight (kg) 
hM 
76.7 
7.4 
0.51 
isO 
75 
6.8 
hF 
77.1 
5.9 
Total 
76 
6.7 
sprint 1 
(35 m) </p>

<p>hM 
4.9 
0.3 
0.64 
isO 
5 
0.3 
hF 
5 
0.3 
Total 
5 
0.3 
sprint 2 
(35 m) </p>

<p>hM 
5 
0.3 
0.57 
isO 
5.1 
0.3 
hF 
5.1 
0.3 
Total 
5.1 
0.3 
sprint 3 
(35 m) </p>

<p>hM 
5.2 
0.3 
0.59 
isO 
5.2 
0.3 
hF 
5.3 
0.2 
Total 
5.2 
0.3 
sprint 4 
(35 m) </p>

<p>hM 
5.3 
0.2 
0.61 
isO 
5.4 
0.3 
hF 
5.4 
0.3 
Total 
5.4 
0.3 
sprint 5 
(35 m) </p>

<p>hM 
5.5 
0.3 
0.76 
isO 
5.5 
0.2 
hF 
5.5 
0.3 
Total 
5.5 
0.3 
sprint 6 
(35 m) </p>

<p>hM 
5.5 
0.3 
0.47 
isO 
5.6 
0.3 
hF 
5.7 
0.3 
Total 
5.6 
0.3 
Physiological parameters 
speed 1 
hM 
7.1 
0.4 
0.63 
isO 
7 
0.4 
hF 
7 
0.4 
Total 
7 
0.4 
speed 2 
hM 
7 
0.4 
0.55 
isO 
6.9 
0.3 
hF 
6.9 
0.3 
Total 
6.9 
0.4 
speed 3 
hM 
6.8 
0.3 
0.57 
isO 
6.7 
0.4 
hF 
6.7 
0.3 
Total 
6.7 
0.3 
speed 4 
hM 
6.6 
0.3 
0.63 
isO 
6.5 
0.3 
hF 
6.5 
0.3 
Total 
6.5 
0.3 
speed 5 
hM 
6.4 
0.3 
0.79 
isO 
6.4 
0.3 
hF 
6.3 
0.4 
Total 
6.4 
0.3 
speed 6 
hM 
6.3 
0.3 
0.45 
isO 
6.2 
0.3 
hF 
6.2 
0.3 
Total 
6.2 
0.3 </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>Table 1 (Continued) </p>

<p>Psychological 
gender profile </p>

<p>Average Standard 
deviations </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>acceleration 1 hM 
1.5 
0.2 
0.62 
isO 
1.4 
0.2 
hF 
1.4 
0.2 
Total 
1.4 
0.2 
acceleration 2 hM 
1.4 
0.2 
0.54 
isO 
1.4 
0.1 
hF 
1.4 
0.1 
Total 
1.4 
0.1 
acceleration 3 hM 
1.3 
0.1 
0.54 
isO 
1.3 
0.1 
hF 
1.3 
0.1 
Total 
1.3 
0.1 
acceleration 4 hM 
1.2 
0.1 
0.64 
isO 
1.2 
0.1 
hF 
1.2 
0.1 
Total 
1.2 
0.1 
acceleration 5 hM 
1.2 
0.1 
0.72 
isO 
1.2 
0.1 
hF 
1.1 
0.1 
Total 
1.2 
0.1 
acceleration 6 hM 
1.1 
0.1 
0.44 
isO 
1.1 
0.1 
hF 
1.1 
0.1 
Total 
1.1 
0.1 
strength 1 
hM 
111.1 
15.1 
0.38 
isO 
105 
15 
hF 
109.5 
16.2 
Total 
107.8 
15.4 
strength 2 
hM 
107.8 
17.6 
0.4 
isO 
101.6 
13.5 
hF 
104.9 
15.2 
Total 
104.2 
15.1 
strength 3 
hM 
101.5 
16.2 
0.44 
isO 
96 
12.7 
hF 
98.6 
14.1 
Total 
98.2 
14 
strength 4 
hM 
95.1 
14.7 
0.5 
isO 
90.5 
12 
hF 
92.8 
13 
Total 
92.3 
13 
strength 5 
hM 
91 
14.7 
0.59 
isO 
87.1 
10.1 
hF 
88.9 
14.8 
Total 
88.6 
12.6 
strength 6 
hM 
88.3 
15.5 
0.41 
isO 
83.4 
9.8 
hF 
84.7 
12.4 
Total 
85.1 
12.2 
Power 1 
hM 
794.6 
143.2 
0.42 
isO 
739.1 
140.6 
hF 
775.3 
152.9 
Total 
763.5 
144.3 
Power 2 
hM 
758.9 
157.7 
0.4 
isO 
702.7 
122.7 
hF 
726.9 
138.3 
Total 
724.1 
136.5 </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>Psychology Research and Behavior Management 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>46 </p>

<p>nascimento et al </p>

<p>Table 1 (Continued) </p>

<p>Psychological 
gender profile </p>

<p>Average Standard 
deviations </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Power 3 
hM 
693 
138.5 
0.45 
isO 
645.7 
111.3 
hF 
661.5 
121.7 
Total 
662.5 
121.3 
Power 4 
hM 
627.9 
120.4 
0.53 
isO 
590.3 
103.4 
hF 
603.9 
109.2 
Total 
603.9 
109 
Power 5 
hM 
586.8 
116.4 
0.64 
isO 
556.7 
83.5 
hF 
567.7 
126.4 
Total 
567.6 
104.2 
Power 6 
hM 
562.8 
124.4 
0.4 
isO 
522.6 
84 
hF 
526.9 
99.9 
Total 
534.4 
100.1 
Maximum 
power </p>

<p>hM 
812.8 
160.7 
0.37 
isO 
750.5 
136.6 
hF 
779 
146.3 
Total 
774.6 
145.8 
Minimum 
power </p>

<p>hM 
558 
115.3 
0.43 
isO 
521.7 
82.8 
hF 
522.3 
101.5 
Total 
531.5 
97 
Mean power 
hM 
670.7 
123 
0.42 
isO 
626.2 
99.7 
hF 
643.7 
118.2 
Total 
642.6 
111 
Fatigue index 
hM 
30.8 
10 
0.48 
isO 
29.9 
6.7 
hF 
32.8 
6.7 
Total 
30.9 
7.7 
Delta 
hM 
254.8 
101.8 
0.46 
isO 
228.8 
80.3 
hF 
256.7 
75 
Total 
243.1 
84.9 </p>

<p>Notes: Speed was measured in m/s, acceleration in m/s </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, strength in kg/m/s </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, and power 
in watts. 
Abbreviations: ISO, isoschematic; HF, heteroschematic feminine; HM, heteroschematic 
masculine. </p>

<p>Table 2 Male and female factors relative to the athletes' court 
positions </p>

<p>Factors 
Court 
positions </p>

<p>Average Standard 
deviations </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Self-centeredness goalkeeper 0.9697 
0.6 
0.91 
Defender 
0.8846 
0.5 
Midfielder 
0.9539 
0.5 
attacker 
0.8438 
0.5 
Total 
0.9219 
0.5 
Boldness 
goalkeeper 3.3306 
0.4 
0.14 
Defender 
2.9231 
0.5 
Midfielder 
2.9935 
0.5 
attacker 
2.947 
0.4 
Total 
3.0284 
0.5 
Rationality 
goalkeeper 3.0152 
0.5 
0.53 
Defender 
2.8205 
0.6 
Midfielder 
2.9405 
0.5 
attacker 
3.1111 
0.4 
Total 
2.9609 
0.5 
integrity 
goalkeeper 3.5124 
0.3 
0.48 
Defender 
3.3636 
0.3 
Midfielder 
3.4026 
0.4 
attacker 
3.553 
0.3 
Total 
3.4418 
0.4 
sensuality 
goalkeeper 1.974 
0.9 
0.75 
Defender 
1.9121 
0.9 
Midfielder 
2.1378 
1 
attacker 
1.8095 
1 
Total 
2.0022 
0.9 
insecurity 
goalkeeper 1.1948 
0.6 
0.69 
Defender 
1.5055 
0.5 
Midfielder 
1.3724 
0.6 
attacker 
1.3452 
0.8 
Total 
1.3638 
0.6 
emotionalism 
goalkeeper 3.5455 
0.5 
0.57 
Defender 
3.3538 
0.7 
Midfielder 
3.1286 
1 
attacker 
3.3167 
1 
Total 
3.2813 
0.9 
sensitivity 
goalkeeper 3.5333 
0.4 
0.56 
Defender 
3,359 
0.4 
Midfielder 
3.3024 
0.5 
attacker 
3.4556 
0.5 
Total 
3.3823 
0.5 
standard male 
goalkeeper 4.6426 
0.6 
0.3 
Defender 
4.1955 
0.6 
Midfielder 
4.3493 
0.6 
attacker 
4.4123 
0.4 
Total 
4.3803 
0.6 
Standard female 
goalkeeper 4.3128 
0.6 
1 
Defender 
4.2727 
0.5 
Midfielder 
4.2946 
0.7 
attacker 
4.2976 
0.6 
Total 
4.2939 
0.6 </p>

<p>a small difference relative to the other groups; however, 
these athletes ended with the same acceleration as the iso-
schematic and heteroschematic female athletes. Athletes 
classified as heteroschematic males started and ended with 
greater strength values. However, there were no statistically 
significant (P.0.05) differences in terms of strength among 
the groups. 
Athletes need more power and less fatigue to maintain 
peak performance. The fatigue indices of the three groups 
were similar. The data proved the lack of significant dif-
ferences between the groups relative to the fatigue index 
(P=0.48). When analyzing the data descriptively, because the </p>

<p>P-values obtained in the test prevented any type of statistical 
inference for the entire target population, it was observed that 
heteroschematic female players had a higher fatigue index, 
thus contradicting the findings of a similar study conducted 
by Gomes et al. 
1 The results of the physiological parameter </p>

<p>Psychology Research and Behavior Management 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>How psychological profiles influence athletes' physiology </p>

<p>analysis relative to typological group showed that, on average, 
high-level soccer players presented similar performance pro-
files in different rounds, as statistically significant differences 
were not found in any of the studied physiological variables 
(weight, distance, speed, acceleration, strength, power, and 
fatigue index). 
According to an exploratory data analysis, goalkeepers 
were found to have higher fatigue indices, whereas attack-
ers had lower indices. However, the results obtained in this 
study were not significantly different (P=0.41). There were 
no statistical differences in male and female factors relative 
to the athletes' court positions. The male factors of self-
centeredness, rationality, and boldness received P-values 
of 0.91, 0.14, and 0.53, respectively. The female factors of 
integrity, sensuality, insecurity, sensitivity, and emotionalism 
also received P-values of ,0.05 (0.48, 0.75, 0.69, 0.57, and 
0.56, respectively). The correct observation would be that 
there are no differences between gender schemes (HM, ISO, 
and HF) (P=0.10). However, the male factors of rationalism 
and boldness had P-values of ,0.05 (P=0.00). The hetero-
schematic male and isoschematic groups had significantly 
higher scores than the heteroschematic female group for both 
the boldness and the rationality factors (Figure 1). 
Significant differences were observed for all female fac-
tors except integrity (P=0.18). The respective P-values for 
sensuality, insecurity, sensitivity, and emotionalism were 
all ,0.05 (0.01, 0.01, 0.00, and 0.01, respectively). When 
compared with other typological groups, the results showed 
that heteroschematic females had significantly higher values 
with respect to the factors of sensuality, insecurity, emotion-
alism, and sensitivity (Figure 2). 
The chi-square test at a confidence level of 95% was 
used to determine whether associations existed between 
court positions and typological groups. The test found no 
predominance of any typological group in terms of specific 
player positions (P=0.60). However, we observed some </p>

<p>possible associations through a descriptive percentage data 
analysis (Figure 3). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>According to the above data, there are possible associations 
between the attacker and midfielder positions and the het-
eroschematic male typological group, between defending 
athletes and the heteroschematic female group, and between 
the goalkeeper and the isoschematic group. The analysis 
suggested that the midfielder and attacker positions favor 
male factors, whereas the defending position favors female 
factors. 
Related research concerning the relationship between 
personality type and choice of sporting discipline has been 
the subject of investigation for many researchers. 
26-29 Most 
studies 
27-30 have understood the concept of personality to 
be associated with individual differences; however, there is 
disagreement regarding whether personality is a subjective or 
a behavioral trait. We are anxious to find a pattern or model 
in the field of sports psychology that can characterize the 
high-performance athlete. Explanations for issues ranging 
from methods and techniques to the relationship between 
typology and the selection of a particular sport that are suf-
ficiently conclusive to satisfy coaches and athletes, or even 
scholars, have not yet been reached. 
Machado evaluated the relationship between personal-
ity and sports practice and detected some common ground 
between these factors. 
30 He concluded that the individual's 
psychological state influences their behavior and psy-
chological response during exercise, that sports practice 
has a favorable effect on the social development process, 
and that physical activities become more effective when 
associated with cognitive work. In the sports domain, 
personality is considered a poor predictor of performance 
but is a predictor of the long-term conversion of skills into 
achievements. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>Self-centeredness </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>Boldness </p>

<p>HM </p>

<p>HF </p>

<p>ISO </p>

<p>Rationality </p>

<p>Figure 1 Averages of male factors according to typological group. 
Abbreviations: HM, heteroschematic male; HF, heteroschematic female; ISO, 
isoschematic. </p>

<p>Integrity </p>

<p>HF </p>

<p>ISO </p>

<p>HM </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>6.0 </p>

<p>8.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>12.0 </p>

<p>Insecurity 
Sensuality 
Emotionalism Sensitivity </p>

<p>Figure 2 Averages of female factors according to typological group. 
Abbreviations: HM, heteroschematic masculine; HF, heteroschematic feminine; 
ISO, isoschematic. </p>

<p>Psychology Research and Behavior Management 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>48 </p>

<p>nascimento et al </p>

<p>Heteroschematic male </p>

<p>-1.0 </p>

<p>-1.0 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>-0.5 
0.0 
0.5 </p>

<p>Dimension 1 </p>

<p>Dimension 2 </p>

<p>1.0 
1 .5 </p>

<p>Heteroschematic female </p>

<p>Isoschematic </p>

<p>Psychological profile 
Position at indoor court </p>

<p>Defender </p>

<p>Goalkeeper </p>

<p>Attacker </p>

<p>Midfielder </p>

<p>Figure 3 Perceptual map of positions and typological groups as determined via a correspondence analysis. 
Notes: Dimension 1 explains 56.0% of the inertia of the cloud, while dimension 2 explains 44%. These two dimensions are sufficient to retain the maximum possible 
variability (inertia). This Perceptual map displays major contributions of the model in opposition to the origin and is based on individual quadrants. In the first quadrant we 
observe a possible association between the pivot and wing position while the typological group is heteroschematic. In the third quadrant we can see the goalkeeper with an 
isoschematic configuration and in the fourth quadrant the athlete standing with the female is heteroschematic in configuration. The chi-square test at a confidence level of 
95% was used to determine whether associations existed between court positions and typological groups. The test found no predominance of any typological group in terms 
of specific player positions (P=0.60). Nevertheless , we can see that there is a higher correlation with the heteroschematic male attackers -the closer the typological group 
is on the court position, the greater the correlation between them. </p>

<p>Allport stated that personality traits are unchangeable 
(immutable) aspects of the individual that accompany changing 
(mutable) aspects. 
32 Currently, the most widely used taxonomy 
in sports psychology is the so-called Big Five Factors (BFF). </p>

<p>33-</p>

<p>41 The BFF addresses five dimensions: extraversion, agreeable-
ness, conscientiousness, neuroticism, and openness. </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>The research conducted by Weinberg and Gould indicated 
that the main investigations into the personalities of athletes have 
been oriented to the identification of a number of defining traits. </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>A personality trait is a characteristic tendency of an individual 
to act and behave in a certain manner. These investigations, </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>which are mainly based on personality questionnaires, focus on 
the determination of personality traits corresponding to sports 
participation and the achievement of better results in competi-
tions. The possibility of identifying those traits and to what 
degree they are present in athletes might allow us to anticipate 
the athlete's behavior, or at least their psychological reactions. 
A small number of studies 
35-38,40,41 concerning the per-
sonality traits of footballers from the perspective of the BFF 
theory have been published worldwide; very few have been 
published in the Brazilian context. Although several studies </p>

<p>1,43 </p>

<p>have investigated both the characteristics of football play-
ers and multiple applications of the BFF theory, the lack of 
articles linking these aspects demonstrates that the study of </p>

<p>psychological traits remains unused as a tool to map and 
possibly anticipate the advantages, difficulties, and general 
behaviors of football players. 
Melo et al suggested that the athletic personality trait 
assessment could be viewed from an alternative perspective: 
the psychological gender profile assessment used in the current 
study. 
43 Early research linking gender profiles and sports used 
the Bem Sex Role Inventory (BSRI). The BSRI was developed 
in 1971 by Dr Sandra Lipsitz Bem and has been widely used 
in research up to the present. 
44-48 The purpose of this inventory 
was to characterize personality as either masculine, feminine, 
androgynous, or undifferentiated. The BSRI is based on gender 
stereotypes; therefore, its real goal is to measure how well an 
individual fits into his/her traditional sex role. 
Several studies using interactive models of gender sche-
mas have been conducted in Brazil. It is worth highlighting 
the research reported by Custódio, 
49 Alves et al, 
50 Gomes 
et al, 
1 Marques et al, 
51 and Leite. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>In this study, we identified the personality traits of pro-
fessional athletes from the Brazilian Indoor Soccer League, 
according to the work of Giovani and Tamayo. 
21 Beginning 
from the social constructs of masculinity and femininity, 
Giovani and Tamayo developed and validated a psychometric 
instrument that enabled evaluation of the gender schemas </p>

<p>Psychology Research and Behavior Management 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>How psychological profiles influence athletes' physiology </p>

<p>associated with self-concept. 
21 The concepts of masculinity 
and femininity are psychological social constructs that have 
been used since the beginning of the century. 
After identifying the interactive model typological groups 
to which high-performance futsal athletes belonged, we 
expected heteroschematic male subjects to perceive futsal as a 
sport with traits similar to those that comprise the male schema, 
and that they would accordingly be more engaged in the sport 
through either training or competition, as well as physical fit-
ness tests. This was because in addition to the predominantly 
male nature of soccer and futsal in Brazil, which is a game 
composed of strong features that define masculinity (aggres-
siveness, strength, endurance, pain tolerance, resistance to 
fatigue, among others), these subjects would exhibit a tendency 
toward individualism and would value traits such as overcom-
ing limitations, self-determination, self-realization, power, 
competitiveness, and hedonism. Conversely, heteroschematic 
female subjects were expected to exhibit lower engagement 
in the activities that permeate this sport, because they would 
perceive the masculine traits of the discipline as incongruent 
with the structure of their predominant schema. Furthermore, 
given the collectivist nature of the female schema, these 
individuals would not exhibit a desire to overcome their own 
limits, embrace competitiveness, or other traits valued by 
individualists. These subjects would rather consider that the 
advancement of their goals and personal development would 
be directly related to appreciation and prestige of the group. 
The isoschematic type was expected to exhibit an intermediate 
performance relative to the other groups, as this group com-
prises a mix of the male and female schemas. The presence of 
a developed male schema would not cause these individuals to 
consider futsal as a discipline in which traits were inconsistent 
with their personality structure. Accordingly, because of this 
perception, the behavior of these individuals would tend to be 
similar to that displayed by heteroschematic males in terms of 
valuing individualistic traits such as self-determination, self-
realization, power, and hedonism. However, the presence of 
the female schema softens this individualistic trend and inserts 
the collectivist perspective of seeking self-improvement and 
self-realization while simultaneously seeking the cohesion, 
success, and well-being of the team. 
Futsal is a sport that combines individualistic traits (drib-
bling, feinting, finishing) and collective traits (collective 
coordination of attack and defense). In this sense, building 
and structuring a team with athletes belonging to only one 
typological classification of gender schemas could be a mis-
take, as there are certainly very powerful athletes who are 
suitable for individual actions (techniques) but who fatigue </p>

<p>easily due to the commitment with which they perform their 
tasks; these athletes would therefore not have a collectivist 
vision of the game and the team. 
On the other hand, the opposite is not recommended by 
the authors either, as a team composed of only players char-
acterized by the collectivistic aspect and who do not present 
individualistic characteristics would be highly detrimental. 
Therefore, the best approach is to evaluate the individual 
characteristics of athletes and to structure and compose the 
team according to the demands imposed by each game. 
From the analytical perspective of applicability, these 
results allow technical staff to intervene by taking advantage 
of the psychological profiles of futsal athletes to define the 
best team lineup for the game. However, this variable should 
not be analyzed in isolation but instead while considering 
other predictors of sports performance such as physical, 
cognitive, and coordination abilities. 
Thus, the psychological profile can be used to guide 
technical staff members in the design of a tactical game 
plan. This can done by determining which athletes should 
be used in attacking and defending situations and by taking 
into account the needs of each futsal match to maximize 
the athletes' physical, technical, tactical, and psychological 
performances, with the goal of tactically overcoming their 
opponents in the search for victory. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Although the results of this research did not reveal statisti-
cally significant differences between the groups in terms of 
the assessed variables, we observed that some results related 
to personality traits associated with both the male and female 
components could help to clarify and establish relationships 
with some strategic aspects inherent to futsal. This study is 
considered unique because it studied the influences of the 
psychological profiles of gender schemas of self-concept on 
the physical fitness of elite futsal players through an assess-
ment of their performances regarding the main physical skills 
used in the sport. Based on these results, a suggestion of this 
study is the use of gender schema typology for guiding the 
athletes participating in this sport, with the aim of better per-
formance in specific court functions or even to solve certain 
problem situations within the game, as athletes belonging 
to different typological groups will likely exhibit different 
responses when subjected to the same game situation. 
In futsal, there are often many talented athletes with good 
physical capabilities, extremely well-developed technical 
skills, and great cognitive abilities, all of which provide the 
opportunity to produce a satisfactory athletic performance. </p>

<p>Psychology Research and Behavior Management 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>nascimento et al </p>

<p>However, these athletes quite often fail to succeed in the sport 
or to exhibit inconsistent performances when exposed to 
certain requirements and/or moments of intense competition. 
Quite possibly, a better understanding of the psychological 
makeup of these athletes could be used for guidance in order 
to maximize their performances at a competitive level. 
The study of athletes' psychological profiles relative to the 
gender schema of self-concept can also be used as a talent 
detection support mechanism. However, for this process to 
be established as effective, reliable, and valid, other factors 
involved in the athlete formation process must be considered, 
including technical, tactical, physiological, social, and cultural 
variables. These considerations are required to ensure that 
technical staff decision-making processes occur through a 
contextualized analysis of data (global decision making), 
rather than an analytical form that considers only one interven-
ing sports performance variable (partial decision making). 
Regarding the small number of studies conducted on 
athletes of this discipline, another contribution of this study 
is the data concerning the studied dependent variables such 
as force, acceleration, and anaerobic power; these data could 
serve as a reference for prescribing activities or even for 
future studies. The results concerning the anaerobic power 
variable might also serve as an indicator of good performance 
in high-level soccer players. 
The main limitation of this study was, perhaps, the small 
number of athletes; it is possible that as a result of the small 
sample, no statistically significant results were achieved. 
Another limitation was the lack of assessment regarding the 
technical and tactical components of the game, as the study 
was limited to an only the physical component. 
In order to fill knowledge gaps such as those remaining 
in psychology and sports science disciplines, future research 
should correlate the psychological gender schema types with 
behavioral, physiological, and biochemical variables, as well 
as technical and tactical components, because those factors 
affect sports performance. Furthermore, studies should be 
conducted to compare psychological profiles with physical 
fitness in a selected sample of elite female futsal players. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Psychology Research and Behavior Management </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/psychology-research-and-behavior-management-journal </p>

<p>Psychology Research and Behavior Management is an international, peer-
reviewed, open access journal focusing on the science of psychology and 
its application in behavior management to develop improved outcomes 
in the clinical, educational, sports and business arenas. Specific topics 
covered include: Neuroscience, memory &amp; decision making; Behavior </p>

<p>modification &amp; management; Clinical applications; Business &amp; sports 
performance management; Social and developmental studies; Animal 
studies. The manuscript management system is completely online and 
includes a quick and fair peer-review system. Visit http://www.dovepress. 
com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Psychology Research and Behavior Management 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>