<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4616395" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:27+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Inflammation is highly prevalent among peritoneal dialysis </p>

<p>(PD) patients. High-sensitivity C-reactive protein (hs-CRP) is the most 
widely used inflammatory marker in clinical medicine and is correlated 
with mortality in PD patients. Air pollution is associated with systemic 
inflammation. The aim of this cross-sectional study was to assess the 
role of air pollutants and other clinical variables on hs-CRP values in PD 
patients. 
We recruited a total of 175 patients who had been undergoing 
continuous ambulatory PD or automated PD for at least 4 months and 
regularly followed up. Air pollution levels were recorded by a network 
of 27 monitoring stations near or in the patients' living areas throughout 
Taiwan. The 12-month average concentrations of particulate matter 
(PM) with an aerodynamic diameter of &lt;10 and &lt;2.5 mm (PM 10 and 
PM 2.5 ), sulfur dioxide (SO 2 ), nitrogen dioxide (NO 2 ), carbon monoxide 
(CO), and ozone (O 3 ) were included. 
In stepwise linear regression, after adjustment for related factors, 
white blood cell count (b: 0.27, 95% confidence interval [CI] [0.71, 
2.11]) and CO level (b: 0.17, 95% CI [2.5, 21.32]) were positively 
associated with hs-CRP and serum albumin levels (b: À0.25, 95% CI 
[À13.69, À3.96]) and normalized protein nitrogen appearance 
(b: À0.18, 95% CI [À17.7, À2.51]) was negatively associated with 
hs-CRP. However, serum indoxyl sulfate and p-cresyl sulfate levels 
were not significantly associated with hs-CRP (P &gt; 0.05). 
In PD patients, the environmental CO level was positively correlated 
with hs-CRP level. </p>

<p>(Medicine 93(26):e181) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: Al = blood aluminum, APD = automated PD, CAD 
= coronary artery disease, CAPD = continuous ambulatory PD, 
CKD = chronic kidney disease, CO = carbon monoxide, Cr = 
creatinine, CVD = cardiovascular disease, DM = diabetes mellitus, 
ESRD = end-stage renal disease, hs-CRP = high-sensitivity C-
reactive protein, iPTH = intact parathyroid hormone, IS = indoxyl 
sulfate, NO 2 = nitrogen dioxide, nPNA = normalized protein 
nitrogen appearance, O 3 = ozone, PCS = p-cresyl sulfate, PD = </p>

<p>peritoneal dialysis, PM = particulate matter, PM 10 = particulate 
matter with an aerodynamic diameter 10 mm, PM 2.5 = particulate 
matter with an aerodynamic diameter 2.5 mm, SO 2 = sulfur 
dioxide, WBC = white blood cell count. </p>

<p>T he prevalence of inflammation among peritoneal dialysis </p>

<p>(PD) patients is high. Inflammation is a powerful predictor 
of mortality and cardiovascular death in patients with end-stage 
renal disease (ESRD). The causes of inflammation in PD 
patients are complex and multifactorial, including factors 
related or unrelated to dialysis. 1 The dialysis-related factors 
causing chronic inflammation in PD patients include peritoneal 
catheter use, glucose in the dialysate, peritonitis, exit-site 
infection, and endotoxins/cytokines from the dialysate; those 
factors unrelated to dialysis include loss of residual renal 
function, 2-5 accumulation of uremic toxins, other comorbid-
ities, malnutrition, or other infections. 1 Chronic kidney disease 
(CKD) may act as a potent stimulus of inflammation. 6,7 Protein-
bound uremic toxins such as p-cresyl sulfate (PCS) and indoxyl 
sulfate (IS) are associated with atherosclerosis and endothelial 
dysfunction, and activation of atherosclerotic proinflammatory 
markers. 8-11 C-reactive protein (CRP) is the most widely used 
inflammatory marker in clinical medicine. A change in residual 
kidney function has also been associated with an increase in 
CRP in PD patients. 12 Several other studies reported a similar 
association between increased CRP level and increased 
mortality in both hemodialysis 13,14 and PD patients. 3,15-17 
Interestingly, several studies have revealed that air pollution 
is associated with systemic inflammation. 18-20 The 6 most 
common air pollutants are particulate matter (PM), lead (Pb), 
sulfur dioxide (SO 2 ), nitrogen oxides (NO x ), ozone (O 3 ), and 
carbon monoxide (CO). 21 Poor air quality has a profound and 
lasting effect on human health, particularly on the respiratory, 
cardiovascular, 22,23 and central nervous systems. 24-26 In a 
recent study, chronic CO exposure was associated with arterial 
wall thickness and an elevated level of high-sensitivity CRP (hs-
CRP). 27 To our knowledge, few studies have investigated air 
pollution as a dialysis-unrelated factor causing chronic inflam-
mation in PD patients. The aim of this prospective cross-
sectional study was to assess the role of air pollutants and other 
clinical variables on hs-CRP values in PD patients. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>This study was approved by the ethical committee of the 
Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Linkou, Taiwan, and per-
formed in accordance with the principles of the Declaration 
of Helsinki. All the data were analyzed anonymously, and all 
patients' records and information were anonymized and dei-
dentified before analysis. Furthermore, all information was </p>

<p>Editor: Pavlos Malindretos. 
Received: June 23, 2014; revised: September 17, 2014; accepted: 
September 20, 2014. 
From the Department of Nephrology and Division of Clinical Toxicology 
(W-HH, T-HY); Department of Internal Medicine (M-JC, Y-JS), Chang 
Gung Memorial Hospital, Linkou; and Chang Gung University College of 
Medicine (W-HH, T-HY), Taoyuan, Taiwan. 
Correspondence: Wen-Hung Huang, Department of Nephrology, Chang 
Gung Memorial Hospital, 5, Fu-Shing St., Gueishan, Taoyuan 333, 
Taiwan (e-mail: williammedia@yahoo.com.tw). 
The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose. 
Copyright # 2014 Wolters Kluwer Health | Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins. 
This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons 
Attribution-ShareAlike License 4.0, which allows others to remix, tweak, 
and build upon the work, even for commercial purposes, as long as the 
author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical 
terms. 
ISSN: 0025-7974 
DOI: 10.1097/MD.0000000000000181 </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 93, Number 26, November 2014 </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 1 </p>

<p>securely protected (by delinking identifying information from 
the main data set) and available to investigators only. Finally, all 
primary data were collected according to the Strengthening the 
Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology guidelines. </p>

<p>Study Population </p>

<p>Initially, we randomly recruited a total of 175 patients who 
had been undergoing continuous ambulatory PD (CAPD) or 
automated PD (APD) for at least 4 months and regularly 
followed up at a PD center in Chang Gung Memorial Hospital. 
All patients were randomly recruited between October 1 and 
November 30, 2009. Patients with a history of dialysis-related 
infection or other types of active infections within 3 months 
before study inclusion were excluded. PD supplies (CAPD and 
APD solutions) were obtained from Baxter Healthcare SA, 
Singapore. All patients gave their informed written consent. 
Age, gender, and clinical data were obtained from the patients' 
medical records. All medical records during the study period, 
including medical history, laboratory data, and inclusion and 
exclusion factors, were reviewed by 2 nephrology specialists 
(W-HH and T-HY) and 1 general physician (M-JC). </p>

<p>Sample Collection </p>

<p>Fasting blood, urine, and dialysate samples were collected 
on the same day between October 1 and November 30, 2009 
during each patient's yearly routine examination, which 
included a peritoneal membrane function test. The plasma, 
dialysate, and urine concentrations of creatinine (Cr), serum 
albumin, and urea nitrogen were measured using routine labora-
tory methods. On the basis of the studies on the contributions of 
PCS and IS in the pathogenesis of vascular injury through 
endothelial dysfunction, 8,10 proliferation of vascular smooth 
muscle cells, 9 activation of atherosclerotic proinflammatory 
markers, 11 and suppression of endothelial repair, 28 we measured 
the serum concentrations of total formed IS and PCS for their 
correlation with the hs-CRP level. Protein nitrogen appearance 
was normalized to body weight (nPNA). Anuria was defined as 
24-hour urine volume &lt;50 cm 3 . Residual renal function was 
calculated as follows: (renal normalized urea nitrogen clearance 
þ renal normalized Cr clearance)/2. Owing to the lack of any 
definite hs-CRP cutoff level indicating an inflammatory state in 
PD patients, inflammation was defined as an hs-CRP level of 
!10 mg/L, a level that has been correlated with increased 
mortality risk in PD patients. 17 Levels of the air pollutants 
were also categorized into high and low according to the median 
value of each of the 6 air pollutants. The method for testing of IS 
and PCS was referenced from a previous study. 29 </p>

<p>Air Quality Status and Analysis </p>

<p>To verify our inference that levels of air pollutants are 
correlated with hs-CRP values in PD patients, we analyzed the 
database and cited the report on the air quality status in Taiwan, 
using the data from the Taiwan Air Quality Monitoring Network 
operated by the Environmental Protection Administration. 30 We 
recorded and analyzed the difference in air quality from the 
previous 12-month average exposure concentration of air pol-
lutants according to the patients' living areas. To the best of our 
knowledge, the appropriate averaging time for the air pollution 
effect on inflammation is unclear. Previous studies showed that 
the effect is spread overall for several days, 19,31 months, 32 or 
even years. 33 From the above-cited studies, we considered the 
previous 12-month average exposure concentration of air pol-
lutants for each subject's examination. The referenced items </p>

<p>included previous 12-month average concentrations of PM with 
an aerodynamic diameter of &lt;10 and &lt;2.5 mm (PM 10 and 
PM 2.5 ), SO 2 , NO 2 , CO, and O 3 . Air pollution levels were 
recorded by a network of 27 monitoring stations near or in 
the patients' living areas throughout Taiwan. The most northern 
living area is Hsichih District and the most southern area is 
Changhua City. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>The Kolmogorov-Smirnov test was used to test if vari-
ables were to be normally distributed. A P value &gt;0.05 was 
required to assume a normal distribution. Data are expressed in 
terms of median and interquartile range in nonnormal distri-
bution variables and as mean AE standard deviation in normal 
distribution variables. Comparisons between groups were per-
formed using the Mann-Whitney test and Student t test. x 2 or 
Fisher exact tests were used to analyze the correlation between 
categorical variables. To calculate the relative correlation of the 
hs-CRP value, standardized coefficients (b) and 95% CIs were 
obtained using linear regression models. Univariate and step-
wise linear regression analyses were used. The following factors 
were investigated: PM 10 , SO 2 , NO 2 , CO, O 3 , PM 2.5 , age, PD 
duration, serum Cr level, white blood cell count (WBC), nPNA, 
serum albumin, serum total IS, serum total PCS, residual renal 
function test, intact parathyroid hormone level (iPTH), blood 
aluminum (Al) level, diabetes mellitus (DM), coronary artery 
disease (CAD), and hypertension. All the nominal variables in 
linear regression were transformed into dummy coding. Missing 
data was approached with listwise deletion. All statistical 
analyses were performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for the 
Social Sciences</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 12.0</rs> for Windows (SPSS Inc, Chicago, 
IL). A P value of &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Patient Characteristics </p>

<p>A total of 175 patients from a single PD center were 
enrolled in this study. Fourteen patients received APD and 
161 patients received CAPD. Table 1 lists the characteristics 
of the study subjects (mean age, 50 years). Of all patients, 125 
were women and 78 patients showed anuria. Furthermore, the 
daily exchange volume was 9.85 L. The median hs-CRP level 
was 2.8 mg/L (range, 1.2-7.6 mg/L). Fifteen patients (8.5%) 
were habitual users of tobacco. The median concentration of 
PM 10 was 49.1 mg/m 3 ; SO 2 , 5.2 ppb; NO 2 , 20.1 ppb; CO, 
0.53 ppm; O 3 , 28.7 ppb; and PM 2.5 , 29.6 mg/m 3 . The causes 
of ESRD were diabetic nephropathy (n ¼ 21), polycystic kidney 
disease (n ¼ 1), glomerular disease (n ¼ 79), malignant hyper-
tension (n ¼ 15), obstructive nephropathy (n ¼ 3), lupus nephri-
tis (n ¼ 4), gouty nephropathy (n ¼ 2), tubulointerstitial disease 
(n ¼ 2), and unknown factors (n ¼ 48). </p>

<p>Factors Associated With hs-CRP Level in Patients 
With PD </p>

<p>The correlation between CO and hs-CRP was revealed in 
Figure 1 (r ¼ 0.16, P ¼ 0.03). To further investigate the corre-
lation between inflammation (hs-CRP !10 mg/L) and the 6 air 
pollutants, we categorized the levels into high and low levels 
according to each pollutant's median value and analyzed the 
results with the linear trend for ordinal variables analysis. The 
median value of PM 10 was 49.1 mg/m 3 ; SO 2 , 5.2 ppb; NO 2 , 20.1 
ppb; CO, 0.53 ppm; O 3 , 28.7 ppb; and PM 2.5 , 29.6 mg/m 3 . 
Table 2 shows that among the 6 air pollutants, a high level </p>

<p>Huang et al 
Medicine Volume 93, Number 26, November 2014 </p>



<p># 2014 Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins </p>

<p>of CO was significantly (P ¼ 0.04) associated with a high level 
of hs-CRP (!10 mg/L); however, all the other pollutants did 
not show a significant association (P &gt; 0.05). In this study, 
75 patients lived in the area of higher level of CO and other 
100 patients lived with contrary condition. Thirty patients had 
inflammation status. Except for gender, no related clinical 
variables were different between these 2 groups (Table 3). 
To further clarify the factors associated with hs-CRP level in 
our study patients, we used univariate and multivariate linear 
regression ''stepwise'' methods, for analyses. PM 10 , SO 2 , NO 2 , 
CO, O 3 , PM 2.5 , age, PD duration, serum Cr level, WBC, nPNA, 
serum albumin level, serum total IS, serum total PCS, residual 
renal function test, iPTH, blood Al level, DM, CAD, and 
hypertension were investigated as clinical variables. Table 4 
revealed that in univariate linear regression, the environmental 
CO level (b: 0.16, 95% CI [0.91, 21.27]), blood Al level (b: 
0.16, 95% CI [0.17, 3.91]), and blood WBC (b: 0.24, 95% CI 
[0.51, 1.98]) were positively associated with hs-CRP and serum 
albumin levels (b: À0.22, 95% CI [À12.95, À2.78]), and log 
nPNA (b: À0.24, 95% CI [À50.47, À12.75]) was negatively </p>

<p>associated with hs-CRP level. Except for CO, the other air 
pollutants were not associated with hs-CRP level (P &gt; 0.05). 
Furthermore, in the ''stepwise'' model of linear regression, 
after adjustment for related factors, blood WBC (b: 0.28, 95% 
CI [0.73, 2.12]) and CO level (b: 0.17, 95% CI [2.54, 21.27]) 
were positively associated with hs-CRP and serum albumin 
levels (b: À0.25, 95% CI [À13.51, À3.93]), and log nPNA 
(b: À0.18, 95% CI [À17.25, À2.33]) was negatively associated 
with hs-CRP level. However, serum IS and PCS levels were not 
significantly associated with hs-CRP level (P &gt; 0.05). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we have shown that after adjustment for 
related risk factors, the level of the air pollutant CO was 
significantly positively associated with the level of the inflam-
mation marker hs-CRP in PD patients. 
It is well known that cardiovascular disease (CVD) is the 
leading cause of death in patients with ESRD, and chronic 
inflammation is a risk factor correlated with CVD. Inflam-
mation is highly prevalent in the PD population. When esti-
mated by CRP level with different cutoff values and assay 
sensitivities, the prevalence of inflammation varied between 
12% and 65%. 34 The causes of inflammation in PD patients are 
multifactorial, 1,35 primarily systemic infection, glucose in the 
dialysate, peritonitis, malnutrition, residual renal function, and 
accumulation uremic toxins. 1,35 Bergstrom 36 showed an import-
ant association between increased CRP level and increased 
mortality in hemodialysis patients. A number of other studies 
reported a similar association between increased CRP level and 
increased mortality in both hemodialysis 13,14 and PD 
patients. 3,15,16 Herzig et al 15 showed in a study of 50 PD patients 
that an increased CRP level was associated with an increased 
risk of acute myocardial infarction. Wang et al 3 also pointed out 
that an increased CRP level predicts mortality and cardiovas-
cular death independent of other clinical, cardiovascular, dialy-
sis, nutritional, and biochemical parameters. Iseki et al 17 
reported that in a 5-year follow-up study, a CRP level of 
10 mg/L or higher was associated with a &gt;3-fold increased 
mortality in PD patients. An increased CRP level has also been </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Characteristics of the 175 Peritoneal Dialysis 
Patients </p>

<p>N ¼ 175 
Mean AE SD or Median (IR) </p>

<p>Age, y 
49.8 AE 10.8 
BSA, m 2 
1.58 AE 0.16 
Drain volume, L/d 
9.85 AE 2.09 
Urine volume, L/d 
0.1 (0-0.4) 
PD duration, mo 
62.3 AE 40.2 
Sex (M/F) 
(50/125) 
Smoking (no.) 
15 
Serum Cr, mg/dL 
11.44 AE 2.64 
WBC, Â10 9 /L 
7.64 AE 2.36 
Al, mg/L 
0.8 (0.3-1.3) 
iPTH, pg/dL 
150 (63.2-482) 
Albumin, g/L 
4.1 AE 0.3 
nPNA, g/kg/d 
1.01 (0.87-1.15) 
hs-CRP, mg/L 
2.8 (1.2-7.6) 
KT/V P 
2.03 AE 0.4 
KT/V K 
0.05 (0-0.26) 
CCrn K, L/wk/1.73 m 2 
2.18 (0-10.81) 
CCrn P, L/wk/1.73 m 2 
46.82 AE 11.39 
Serum total-form IS, mg/L 
41.3 (29.9-50.8) 
Serum total-form PCS, mg/L 
18.6 (8.0-30.3) 
Environmental PM 10 , mg/m 3 
49.1 (44.9-56.2) 
Environmental SO 2 , ppb 
5.2 (3.9-5.9) 
Environmental NO 2 , ppb 
20.1 (16.4-22.0) 
Environmental CO, ppm 
0.53 (0.44-0.57) 
Environmental O 3 , ppb 
28.7 (27.6-30.1) 
Environmental PM 2.5 , mg/m 3 
29.69 (26.4-29.8) </p>

<p>Al ¼ aluminum, BSA ¼ body surface area, CCrn K ¼ normalized 
renal creatinine clearance, CCrn P ¼ normalized peritoneal creatinine 
clearance, CO ¼ carbon monoxide, Cr ¼ creatinine, hs-CRP ¼ high-sen-
sitivity C-reactive protein, iPTH ¼ intact parathyroid hormone, 
IR ¼ interquartile range, IS ¼ indoxyl sulfate, KT/V K ¼ renal KT/V, 
KT/V 
P ¼ peritoneal 
KT/V, 
NO 2 ¼ nitrogen 
dioxide, 
nPNA ¼ normalized protein nitrogen appearance, O 3 ¼ ozone, 
PCS ¼ p-cresyl sulfate, PD ¼ peritoneal dialysis, PM 10 ¼ particulate 
matter with aerodynamic diameter &lt;10 mm, PM 2.5 ¼ particulate matter 
with aerodynamic diameter &lt;2.5 mm, SO 2 ¼ sulfur dioxide, 
WBC ¼ white blood cell count. </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.20 
0.40 
0.60 </p>

<p>Concentration of CO (ppm) </p>

<p>0.80 
1.00 </p>

<p>20.00 </p>

<p>40.00 </p>

<p>60.00 </p>

<p>80.00 </p>

<p>100.00 </p>

<p>HS-CRP (mg/L) </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Relationship between airborne CO and hs-CRP 
(r ¼ 0.16, P ¼ 0.03). CO ¼ carbon monoxide, hs-CRP ¼ high-sen-
sitivity C-reactive protein. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 93, Number 26, November 2014 
CO and Inflammation in PD Patients </p>

<p># 2014 Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 3 </p>

<p>shown to predict cardiovascular events in PD patients indepen-
dent of other traditional and nontraditional risk factors. 37 
Interestingly, several studies have revealed that air pollu-
tion is associated with systemic inflammation. 18-20 The 6 most 
common air pollutants are PM, Pb, SO 2 , NO x , O 3 , and CO. 21 
The effects of poor air quality on human health are profound and 
lasting, and principally affect the respiratory and cardiovascular 
systems. 22,23 In addition, air pollution has been associated with 
increased incidence of and mortality from CAD. 38 In a large 
population and long follow-up study of 6 US cities (Harvard Six 
Cities study), 22 a significant association was noted between air 
pollution and mortality after adjustment for smoking, particu-
larly in cities where pollutant levels were highest. An extended </p>

<p>follow-up of the Harvard Six Cities study showed that cardi-
ovascular and lung cancer mortality rates were each positively 
associated with fine particulate air pollution (PM 2.5 ). 39 
To our knowledge, reports on the association between 
inflammation and air pollution in PD patients are limited. In 
this study, we found that the CO level is positively associated 
with the level of hs-CRP after adjustment for related risk 
factors. CO is a colorless, odorless, and tasteless gas that is 
slightly lighter than air. It occurs in various natural and artificial 
environments. However, with increasing industrialization and 
urbanization, CO is chiefly emitted from the exhaust of internal 
combustion engines and industrial production, as well as from 
incomplete combustion of various other fuels. CO is toxic to </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Comparison of Patients With Low and High-Environmental CO Exposure </p>

<p>Low CO (n ¼ 100) 
High CO (n ¼ 75) 
P </p>

<p>Age 
49.37 AE 10.23 
50.42 AE 11.66 
0.53 
Smoking 
8 
7 
0.48 
CVD 
3 
0 
0.18 
Hypertension 
45 
33 
0.51 
DM 
14 
7 
0.24 
HBV 
10 
7 
0.54 
HCV 
6 
1 
0.11 
BSA, m 2 
1.57 AE 0.153 
1.58 AE 0.17 
0.60 
PD duration, mo 
58 AE 38.2 
67.92 AE 42.26 
0.11 
Residual renal function 
2.1 (0-10.7) 
1.5 (0-8.9) 
0.49 
Sex (M/F) 
22/78 
28/47 
0.02 
CT ratio 
0.50 AE 0.06 
0.50 AE 0.071 
0.64 
Serum Cr, mg/dl 
11.37 AE 2.86 
11.54 AE 2.60 
0.67 
WBC, Â10 9 /L 
7.64 AE 2.54 
7.64 AE 2.12 
0.99 
Al, mg/L 
0.8 (0.2-1.27) 
0.8 (0.4-1.3) 
0.31 
iPTH, pg/dL 
126 (63.2-361) 
249 (63.2-550) 
0.31 
Albumin, g/L 
4.05 AE 0.34 
4.10 AE 0.34 
0.29 
nPNA, g/kg/d 
1.02 AE 0.19 
1.02 AE 0.245 
0.88 
KT/V P 
2.01 AE 0.40 
2.05 AE 0.40 
0.48 
KT/V K 
0.055 (0-0.28) 
0.03 (0-0.21) 
0.99 
CCrn K, L/wk/1.73 m 2 
2.55 (0-12.3) 
1.69 (0-9.74) 
0.99 
CCrn P, L/wk/1.73 m 2 
50.56 AE 12.05 
52.43 AE 11.11 
0.28 </p>

<p>Al ¼ aluminum, BSA ¼ body surface areas, CCrn K ¼ normalized renal creatinine clearance, CCrn P ¼ normalized peritoneal creatinine clearance, 
Cr ¼ creatinine, CT ¼ cardiothoracic, CVD ¼ cardiovascular disease, DM ¼ diabetes mellitus, HBV ¼ hepatitis B virus infection, HCV ¼ hepatitis C 
virus infection, hs-CRP ¼ high-sensitivity C-reactive protein, iPTH ¼ intact parathyroid hormone, KT/V K ¼ renal KT/V, KT/V P ¼ peritoneal KT/V, 
nPNA ¼ normalized protein nitrogen appearance, PD ¼ peritoneal dialysis, WBC ¼ white blood cell counts. Low CO exposure: level lower than or 
equal the level of median (0.53 ppm) of environmental CO level. High CO exposure: level higher than the level of median (0.53 ppm) of environmental 
CO level. Residual renal function presented as: (normalized renal urea nitrogen clearance þ CCRn K)/2. </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Linear Trend for Ordinal Variables Analysis of Air Pollutants and hs-CRP </p>

<p>PM 10 
SO 2 
NO 2 
CO 
O 3 
PM 2.5 </p>

<p>Low </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>High y Low </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>High y Low </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>High y Low </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>High y Low </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>High y Low </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>High y </p>

<p>hs-CRP &lt;10 mg/L 
70 
75 
88 
57 
89 
56 
88 
57 
77 
68 
97 
48 
hs-CRP !10 mg/L 
19 
11 
15 
15 
14 
16 
12 
18 
13 
17 
17 
13 
P for trend 
0.13 
0.28 
0.13 
0.04 
0.33 
0.28 </p>

<p>CO ¼ environmental carbon monoxide, hs-CRP ¼ high-sensitivity C-reactive protein, NO 2 ¼ environmental nitrogen dioxide, O 3 ¼ environmental 
ozone, PM 10 ¼ environmental particulate matter with aerodynamic diameter &lt;10 mm, PM 2.5 ¼ environmental particulate matter with aerodynamic 
diameter &lt;2.5 mm, SO 2 ¼ environmental sulfur dioxide. 
Ã Level lower than the median level of each air pollutant. 
y Level higher than or equal to the median level of each air pollutant. </p>

<p>Huang et al 
Medicine Volume 93, Number 26, November 2014 </p>

<p>4 | www.md-journal.com </p>

<p># 2014 Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins </p>

<p>humans and animals at higher concentrations. Acute CO poi-
soning is known to occur worldwide, and its major compli-
cations involve the central nervous and cardiovascular systems. 
However, our knowledge about the effects of chronic CO 
poisoning is limited, especially in PD patients. The results of 
chronic CO exposure in human and animal studies are conflict-
ing. Many animal studies 40-42 have shown that short-term 
and low-level CO exposure may protect against inflammatory 
and reactive oxygen-inducing stimuli. In other studies, inter-
mittent CO exposure caused damage to the arterial wall and 
resulted in atherosclerosis. 43-45 Epidemiological studies have 
shown that high levels of environmental CO were correlated 
with CVD and mortality. 46,47 In a recent study, Davutoglu 
et al 27 showed that hs-CRP levels and carotid intima-media 
thickness are increased in subjects with chronic CO exposure. 
The mechanism by which chronic CO exposure increases hs-
CRP level is not clear. However, in the study by Davutoglu et al, 
one limitation is that environmental CO level and other air 
pollutants were not measured. From the above-cited studies, we 
could infer that short-term and low-level CO exposure may 
have anti-inflammatory effects in animals. However, chronic 
CO exposure may damage the arterial wall and result in 
atherosclerosis. In our study, we found that in PD patients, 
the environmental CO level was positively correlated with hs-
CRP level. This result agrees with the findings of the studies 
cited above. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>In conclusion, this cross-sectional study shows that in 
patients with PD, the environmental CO level is associated 
with the level of hs-CRP. Further studies are required to clarify 
the role of environmental air pollutants in inflammation and 
related comorbidities in PD patients. </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>This study has several limitations. Among them is the cross-
sectional nature of the observation and that the study group is 
predominantly represented by women. In our PD center, the 
patients themselves choose between PD and HD. Considering 
the working environment and home-care conditions, most 
women chose PD. On the contrary, according to the limitations 
in technology and information on indoor air quality, we used the 
previous 1-year average air quality published by the Environ-
mental Protection Administration Executive Yuan, Taiwan to 
represent the air quality of the patients' living areas. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS 
The authors would like to thank the members of the 
Statistic Center and the Peritoneal Dialysis Center, Chang 
Gung Memorial Hospital, Linkou, Taiwan, for their invaluable 
and dedicated assistance </p>

<p>TABLE 4. Linear Regression Analysis Between Clinical Variables and hs-CRP Level (N ¼ 175) </p>

<p>hs-CRP </p>

<p>Univariate Linear Regression b (95% CI) </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>P 
Stepwise Linear Regression b (95% CI) </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>PM 10 
À0.01 (À0.25, 0.20) 
0.83 
SO 2 
0.03 (À0.93, 1.46) 
0.66 
NO 2 
0.13 (À0.04, 0.83) 
0.07 
CO 
0.16 (0.91, 21.27) 
0.03 
0.17 (2.54, 21.27) 
0.01 
O 3 
À0.09 (À1.02, 0.23) 
0.21 
PM 2.5 
0.03 (À0.35, 0.58) 
0.63 
Age 
0.13 (À0.01, 0.31) 
0.07 
Cr 
À0.03 (À0.8, 0.51) 
0.64 
WBC 
0.24 (0.51, 1.98) 
0.001 
0.28 (0.73, 2.12) 
&lt;0.001 
Log nPNA 
À0.24 (À50.47, À12.75) 
0.001 
À0.18 (À17.25, À2.33) 
0.009 
Albumin 
À0.22 (À12.95, À2.78) 
0.003 
À0.25 (À13.51, À3.93) 
&lt;0.001 
Log iPTH 
À0.02 (À3.51, 2.64) 
0.78 
Al 
0.16 (0.17, 3.91) 
0.03 
IS 
À0.04 (À0.13, 0.07) 
0.57 
PCS 
À0.12 (À0.19, 0.01) 
0.10 
Duration 
0.07 (À0.02, 0.06) 
0.32 
Residual renal function y 
À0.11 (À0.26, 0.03) 
0.14 
DM 
0.10 (À1.58, 9.33) 
0.16 
CAD 
À0.05 (À18.55, 8.89) 
0.48 
HTN 
À0.008 (À3.78, 3.39) 
0.91 
Smoking 
0.09 (À2.41, 10.27) 
0.22 </p>

<p>Initially, univariate linear regression analysis was performed to identify the variables associated with hs-CRP levels in 175 patients. WBC, blood Al, 
environmental CO, albumin, and nPNA were associated with hs-CRP levels. In a further analysis with stepwise linear regression, WBC, albumin, 
nPNA, and CO were found to be associated with hs-CRP levels. Al ¼ aluminum, CAD ¼ coronary arterial disease, CCrn K ¼ normalized renal 
creatinine clearance, CI ¼ confidence interval, CO ¼ carbon monoxide, Cr ¼ creatinine, DM ¼ diabetes mellitus, hsCRP ¼ high-sensitivity C-reactive 
protein, HTN ¼ hypertension, iPTH ¼ intact parathyroid hormone, IS ¼ indoxyl sulfate, KT/V K ¼ renal KT/V, NO 2 , nitrogen dioxide, 
nPNA ¼ normalized protein nitrogen appearance, O 3 ¼ ozone, PCS ¼ p-cresyl sulfate, PM 10 , particulate matter with aerodynamic diameter 
&lt;10 mm, PM 2.5 ¼ particulate matter with aerodynamic diameter &lt;2.5 mm, SO 2 ¼ sulfur dioxide, WBC ¼ white blood cell count. 
Ã Linear regression standardized coefficients (b) and 95% CIs. 
y Residual renal function calculated as follows: (normalized renal urea nitrogen clearance þ CCRn K)/2. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 93, Number 26, November 2014 
CO and Inflammation in PD Patients </p>

<p># 2014 Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 5 </p>



<p>Huang et al 
Medicine Volume 93, Number 26, November 2014 </p>



<p># 2014 Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins </p>



<p>Medicine Volume 93, Number 26, November 2014 
CO and Inflammation in PD Patients </p>

<p># 2014 Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 7 </p>

</text></tei>