<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4069613" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>We have used whole genome paired-end Illumina sequence data to identify tandem duplications in 20 isofemale lines of 
Drosophila yakuba and 20 isofemale lines of D. simulans and performed genome wide validation with PacBio long 
molecule sequencing. We identify 1,415 tandem duplications that are segregating in D. yakuba as well as 975 duplications 
in D. simulans, indicating greater variation in D. yakuba. Additionally, we observe high rates of secondary deletions at 
duplicated sites, with 8% of duplicated sites in D. simulans and 17% of sites in D. yakuba modified with deletions. These 
secondary deletions are consistent with the action of the large loop mismatch repair system acting to remove polymor-
phic tandem duplication, resulting in rapid dynamics of gain and loss in duplicated alleles and a richer substrate of 
genetic novelty than has been previously reported. Most duplications are present in only single strains, suggesting that 
deleterious impacts are common. Drosophila simulans shows larger numbers of whole gene duplications in com-
parison to larger proportions of gene fragments in D. yakuba. Drosophila simulans displays an excess of high-
frequency variants on the X chromosome, consistent with adaptive evolution through duplications on the D. 
simulans X or demographic forces driving duplicates to high frequency. We identify 78 chimeric genes in D. 
yakuba and 38 chimeric genes in D. simulans, as well as 143 cases of recruited noncoding sequence in D. yakuba 
and 96 in D. simulans, in agreement with rates of chimeric gene origination in D. melanogaster. Together, these 
results suggest that tandem duplications often result in complex variation beyond whole gene duplications that 
offers a rich substrate of standing variation that is likely to contribute both to detrimental phenotypes and disease, 
as well as to adaptive evolutionary change. </p>

<p>Gene duplications are an essential source of genetic novelty 
that can be useful in adaptation and in the origins of devel-
opmental complexity across phyla (Conant and Wolfe 2008). 
Additionally, duplicate sequences are commonly found in 
mammalian stem cells (Liang et al. 2008), cancer cell lines 
(Inaki and Liu 2012), and are associated with autoimmune 
disease, HIV susceptibility, Crohn's disease, asthma, allergies, 
and autism (Ionita-Laza et al. 2009). Distinguishing the pro-
pensity with which gene duplications serve as causative dis-
ease factors as opposed to a source of favorable variation 
depends heavily on accurate ascertainment of their occur-
ance and frequencies in the population. 
In the Drosophila, there is substantial variation in the 
number and types of duplicate genes that are present in 
the sequenced reference genomes (Hahn et al. 2007) 
though the extent to which selection might drive rapid fixa-
tion of duplicate genes or whether mutation rates differ 
across species remains uncertain. Furthermore, these surveys 
of single strains from each species may not be representative 
of the variation present in populations and offer only limited </p>

<p>opportunities to study their role in adaptation. The advent of 
Illumina sequencing has made population genomics of com-
plex mutations in nonmodel Drosophila readily tractable. 
Paired-end Illumina sequencing offers the opportunity to 
survey copy number variation using definitive sequence-
based comparisons that are free from complications related 
to sole use of coverage or hybridization intensities. Through 
the identification of paired-end reads that map in abnormal 
orientations, we can identify a high-confidence data set de-
scribing tandem duplications in sample populations (Tuzun 
et al. 2005; Korbel et al. 2007; Cridland and Thornton 2010). 
Drosophila yakuba and D. simulans offer the opportunity 
to compare the role of tandem duplications in species that 
have high levels of nucleotide diversity and large effective 
population sizes of N e % 10 
6 (Sawyer and Hartl 1992; Eyre-
Walker et al. 2002; Bachtrog et al. 2006), allowing us to com-
pare mutational and adaptive processes in independent 
systems where neutral forces of genetic drift should be 
minimal. 
If different chromosomes produce tandem duplica-
tions at different rates, we may expect them to contribute </p>

<p>ß The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, 
provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p> 
Mol. Biol. Evol. 31(7):1750-1766 doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 Advance Access publication April 7, 2014 </p>

<p>differentially to adaptive changes. In D. melanogaster, the X 
chromosome contains greater repetitive content (Mackay 
et al. 2012), displays different gene density (Adams et al. 
2000), has potentially smaller population sizes (Wright 1931; 
Andolfatto 2001), lower levels of background selection 
(Charlesworth 2012), and an excess of genes involved in 
female-specific expression (Ranz et al. 2003) in comparison 
to the autosomes. Furthermore, the X chromosome is hemi-
zygous in males, exposing recessive mutations to the full 
effects of selection more often than comparable loci on the 
autosomes (Charlesworth et al. 1987). Hence, the incidence of 
duplications on the X and the types of genes affected may 
differ from the autosomes, and thereby produce different 
impacts on phenotypic evolution. 
Many copy number variants are thought to be nonneutral 
(Hu and Worton 1992; Emerson et al. 2008; Cardoso-Moreira 
et al. 2011), especially when they capture partial gene se-
quences or create chimeric gene structures (Rogers and 
Hartl 2012) or result in recruitment of noncoding sequences 
(Lee and Reinhardt 2012). Such modifications are likely to 
change gene regulatory profiles (Rogers and Hartl 2012), in-
creasing the likelihood of nonneutral phenotypes. Surveys in 
D. melanogaster have identified large numbers of such vari-
ants (Emerson et al. 2008; Rogers et al. 2009; Cardoso-Moreira 
et al. 2011, 2012; Lee and Reinhardt 2012). Establishing profiles 
of partial gene duplication, whole gene duplication, chimera 
formation, and recruitment of noncoding sequence are 
essential to a complete understanding of the roles tandem 
duplicates play in beneficial and detrimental phenotypic 
changes across species. 
Here, we describe the number, types, and genomic loca-
tions of tandem duplications segregating in 20 strains of 
D. yakuba and in 20 strains of D. simulans and discuss differ-
ences across species and across chromosomes, as well as their 
potential to create novel gene constructs. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>We have sequenced the complete genomes of 20 isofemale 
lines of D. yakuba and 20 isofemale lines D. simulans each 
inbred in the lab for 9-12 generations to produce effectively 
haploid samples, as well as the reference genome stocks of </p>

<p>each species (as a control for genome quality and false pos-
itives) (Drosophila Twelve Genomes Consortium 2007; Hu 
et al. 2013). Genomes are sequenced to high coverage of 
50-150Â for a total of 42 complete genomes (supplementary 
tables S1-S5, Supplementary Material online, see Materials 
and Methods). We have used mapping orientation of 
paired-end reads to identify recently derived, segregating du-
plications in these samples &lt;25 kb in length that are sup-
ported by three or more divergently oriented read pairs (see 
Materials and Methods, supplementary text S1, tables S6 and 
S7, Supplementary Material online). We limit analysis to re-
gions of the genome, which can be assayed with coverage 
depth of three or more reads across all strains, corresponding 
to the detection limit for tandem duplicates. We identify 
1,415 segregating tandem duplications in D. yakuba and 
975 segregating tandem duplications in D. simulans (fig. 1), 
including large numbers of gene duplications (table 1) with 
a low false positive rate (supplementary table S8, 
Supplementary Material online). We assess the numbers 
and types of gene duplications, differences in duplication 
rates and sizes across chromosomes, and describe evidence 
of secondary modification through deletions, which will 
influence the extent to which these variants can serve as a 
source of genetic novelty. </p>

<p>Genotyping and Quality Control </p>

<p>Divergently oriented paired-end reads are effective indicators 
of tandem duplications (Tuzun et al. 2005; Cridland and 
Thornton 2010; Mills et al. 2011; Zichner et al. 2013). We 
have used paired-end read orientation (fig. 2) combined 
with increased coverage in genomic sequencing (fig. 3) to 
identify tandem duplications in population samples of 
D. yakuba and D. simulans. Divergently oriented reads indic-
ative of putative tandem duplications were clustered within a 
single strain, with three or more divergently oriented read 
pairs within the strain required to define each tandem dupli-
cation (see Materials and Methods). Duplications were then 
clustered across strains with coordinates defined as the max-
imum span of divergent reads across all strains. The distribu-
tion of supporting read pairs is highly skewed, with 3-4 
supporting read pairs for many calls (supplementary fig. S1, </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Tandem duplications in 20 sample strains of Drosophila yakuba. Regions spanned by divergently oriented reads are shown with sample strains 
plotted on different rows, whereas axes list genomic location in Mbp. Duplications are more common around the centromeres, especially on 
chromosome 2. Frequencies are shaded in grayscale according to frequency, with high-frequency variants shown in solid black. The D. simulans X 
chromosome appears to have an excess of high-frequency variants in comparison to the D. simulans autosomes and the D. yakuba X chromosome. </p>

<p>1751 </p>

<p>Tandem Duplications in Nonmodel Drosophila . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>Supplementary Material online). To account for duplications 
which may be undetected, we additionally included variants 
that showed 2-fold increases (fig. 3) in quantile normalized 
coverage (supplementary figs. S2 and S3, Supplementary 
Material online) and which are supported by one or more 
divergently oriented read pairs were also identified as having 
duplications if the duplicate was present in a second strain, 
thereby correcting sample frequency estimates for false neg-
atives (see Materials and Methods, supplementary text S1, 
Supplementary Material online). We retained only those 
tandem duplicates which are not present in outgroup refer-
ence genomes of D. melanogaster, D. erecta, and D. yakuba or 
D. simulans as defined in a BLAST search (see Materials and 
Methods) suggesting recent origins. 
Using divergently oriented paired-end reads, we have iden-
tified 1,415 segregating tandem duplications across 20 sample 
strains of D. yakuba, in comparison to 975 segregating </p>

<p>tandem duplications in 20 lines of D. simulans, with signifi-
cantly more duplicates identified in D. yakuba than in 
D. simulans (one-sided t-test, t ¼ À3:8126, df ¼ 24:593, 
P ¼ 0:0004089). More variants are identified in D. yakuba 
in spite of higher coverage in D. simulans (supplementary 
table S4, Supplementary Material online), suggesting that 
the difference is likely to be biological rather than technical. 
In fact, the number of variants identified is only weakly cor-
related with coverage per strain (fig. 4) a product of sequenc-
ing to the saturation point of coverage (supplementary table 
S9, Supplementary Material online). Downsampling reads 
from D. yakuba CY17C, which was sequenced to 151Â, we 
find that the portion of the genome covered with three or 
more reads (the detection limit of our assay) plateaus at 
roughly 45Â (supplementary table S9, Supplementary 
Material online) though lower coverage data used in previous 
studies (Alkan et al. 2009; Sudmant et al. 2010; Mills et al. 
2011; Zichner et al. 2013) will be far from this plateau. The 
tandem duplications identified across these sample strains 
cover 2.574% of the assayable genome of the X and four 
major autosomes in D. yakuba and 1.837% of the assayable 
genome of the X and four major autosomes in D. simulans. 
We are able to identify tandem duplications as small as 66 bp 
in D. yakuba and 78 bp in D. simulans. 
We have successfully polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-am-
plified </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>46 randomly chosen variants in D. yakuba and </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>42 var-
iants in D. simulans. The rate of PCR confirmation in D. 
simulans is not significantly different from previous studies 
of copy number variants, but we observe significant differ-
ences between D. yakuba and all other confirmation rates 
(supplementary table S10, Supplementary Material online). In 
view of this disparity, combined with difficulties of PCR 
primer design for variants whose precise structures are un-
known, we generated PacBio long molecule sequencing data 
for four strains of D. yakuba in order to more reliably estimate 
the false positive rate (supplementary table S11, 
Supplementary Material online). PacBio long molecule se-
quencing has recently been used to validate targeted dupli-
cations in human genome data (Huddleston et al. 2014). We 
extend this approach to genome wide identification and val-
idation of tandem duplications, and have generated PacBio 
reads for four different sample strains of D. yakuba. Across 
these four strains, we observe confirmation of 661 out of 688 
mutations, for a maximum false positive rate of 3.9% (supple-
mentary table S8, Supplementary Material online), though 
some variants may be unconfirmed due to low clone cover-
age in a region. Hence, the duplicates identified with paired-
end reads in high coverage genomic sequence data are 
extremely accurate and comparable to or better than previ-
ous methods or attempts to identify and validate duplicates 
using lower coverage genomic sequences or microarrays 
(Alkan et al. 2009; Sudmant et al. 2010; Cardoso-Moreira 
et al. 2011; Mills et al. 2011; Zichner et al. 2013). Split read 
mapping with short Illumina reads performed poorly in com-
parison and failed to confirm 88.3% of variants, and break-
point assembly was possible for &lt;60% of variants in spite of 
high rates of confirmation with PacBio (see supplementary 
text S1, Supplementary Material online). Thus, requiring these </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Coverage change for a duplication on chromosome 3 L in Line 9 
of Drosophila yakuba. Regions spanned by divergently oriented reads are 
shaded. Sample coverage is shown in black, whereas reference genome 
coverage is shown in gray. </p>

<p>FIG. 2. A tandem duplication in a sample that was then used to gen-
erate paired-end Illumina libraries. Duplications should be apparent 
through divergently oriented read pairs when mapping onto the refer-
ence genome. Tandem duplications require a minimum of three diver-
gently oriented read pairs. Duplication span is recorded as the minimum 
and maximum coordinates spanned by divergent reads. </p>

<p>Table 1. Duplicated Regions in Drosophila yakuba and D. simulans. </p>

<p>D. yakuba 
D. simulans 
Whole gene 
248 
296 
Partial gene 
745 
462 
Intergenic 
745 
577 </p>



<p>Rogers et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>criteria would exclude the majority of variant calls and would 
likely be biased against duplicates with formation facilitated 
by repetitive sequences. Where duplicate breakpoints contain 
repetitive or low complexity sequences, or where subsequent 
modification of alleles through deletion has altered surround-
ing sequence, PCRs are likely to fail, and we would suggest 
that confirmation using long molecule sequencing is far more 
reliable in the face of complex structures. Further description 
of genomic sequences, tandem duplications, and discussion 
of paired-end read performance in high-coverage genomic 
sequencing data in comparison to other methods is available 
in supplementary text S1, Supplementary Material online. </p>

<p>Complex Variation </p>

<p>We identified deletions that have occurred in duplicated al-
leles using long-spanning read pairs 600 bp or longer, corre-
sponding approximately to the 99.9th percentile of fragment 
lengths in the reference genomes (supplementary table S5, 
Supplementary Material online). Out of 880 duplications 
! 600 bp in length in D. yakuba, which could be surveyed 
for deletions within duplications using long-spanning reads, 
151 (17%) contain long-spanning read pairs covering 50% or 
more of the duplicate sequence in one or more strain, indic-
ative of subsequent deletion, multiple independent short-
range dispersed duplications, or incomplete duplication 
(fig. 5). In D. simulans, </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>486 (8%) duplications ! 600 bp contain 
long-spanning reads covering 50% or more of duplicated se-
quence in one or more strains. Among 69 such modified 
variants in D. yakuba that are present in multiple strains, 66 
have at least one strain that lacks these long-spanning reads, 
whereas 12 out of 14 variants in D. simulans lack long-span-
ning reads in one or more strains. Given large numbers of </p>

<p>unaltered duplicates, the most parsimonious explanation is 
that deletions are most often secondary modification and 
that the majority of these constructs forms through full 
length duplication and subsequent deletion rather than 
independent dispersed duplications. 
In one well-characterized example, we have identified a 
duplication which spans the chimeric retrogene jingwei 
(jgw) (Long and Langley 1993), which houses a deletion up-
stream from jgw (fig. 6). The duplication is defined by ten </p>

<p>FIG. 4. Number of variants versus coverage by line in Drosophila yakuba (A) and D. simulans (B). Regression line (blue) and 95% confidence interval 
(gray) are shown. Correlation between coverage and number of duplications is low (D. yakuba adjusted R 
2 ¼ 0:21, D. simulans adjusted R 
2 ¼ 0:03). </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Complex breakpoints and subsequent modification of tandem 
duplications. Short-range dispersed duplications, duplication with inser-
tion of novel sequence, and duplication with subsequent deletion will all 
display the same signals of divergently oriented reads. Although all of 
these indicate that duplication has occurred, signals solely from short 
sequence read pairs are unlikely to capture the full complexity of 
duplication events. </p>

<p>1753 </p>

<p>Tandem Duplications in Nonmodel Drosophila . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>divergent read pairs and confirmed by split read mapping in 
PacBio long molecule sequencing, whereas the deletion is 
supported by 20 long-spanning read pairs in line NY66-2 
and gapped alignment in PacBio reads (fig. 6). The same du-
plication and deletion are independently confirmed with 
PacBio sequences in line CY21B3. The duplication spanning 
jgw is found at a frequency of </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>20 strains, whereas the deletion 
shown is observed only in CY21B3 and NY66-2, suggesting 
that the deletions is a secondary modification. A second 
independent duplication spans jgw in </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>20 strains and is con-
firmed in PacBio data, indicating that the region has been 
modified multiple times in different strains. 
Deletions are exceptionally common in Drosophila (Petrov 
et al. 1996), and several genetic mechanisms might offer means 
of excision in a short time frame after duplication. The large 
loop mismatch repair system can facilitate deletions of dupli-
cated sequence to modify duplicated sequence as long as 
variants are polymorphic. The presence of unpaired dupli-
cated DNA during meiosis or mitosis would commonly 
invoke the action of the large loop mismatch repair system, 
which if resolved imprecisely, could result in the construct 
observed (fig. 7). Deletions lying within a duplication have a 
median size of 3.6 kb in D. yakuba and 1.8 kb in D. simulans. 
Such large deletions are well outside the norm for genome 
wide large deletions in mutation accumulation lines of 
D. melanogaster, which show an average 409 bp and maxi-
mum of 2.6 kb (Schrider et al. 2013). Deletions of this size 
however are consistent with the size of excised fragments in 
large loop mismatch repair of several kilobases (Kearney et al. 
2001). Deletion during nonhomologous end joining or homol-
ogy-mediated replication slippage might produce deletions as 
well though it is unclear whether mutation rates are naturally 
high enough to operate in short time frames. Thus, we would 
expect modification of duplicated alleles to be extremely 
common, especially in deletion-biased Drosophila. </p>

<p>Differences in Gene Duplications across Species </p>

<p>Duplicated coding sequences can diverge to produce novel 
peptides, novel regulatory profiles, or specialized subfunctions 
(Conant and Wolfe 2008). In order to determine the extent to 
which genes are likely to be duplicated and whether particular 
categories of gene duplications are more likely to be favored, 
we identified coding sequences captured by tandem duplica-
tions. We find large numbers of segregating gene duplications 
in both D. yakuba and D. simulans including hundreds of </p>

<p>FIG. 6. Read mapping patterns indicative of a modified duplication surrounding jingwei in Drosophila yakuba line NY66-2. Duplications are indicated 
with divergently oriented paired-end reads (blue) as well as with split read mapping of long molecule sequencing (purple). Deletions in one copy are 
suggested by gapped read mapping of long molecule reads (red) as well as multiple long-spanning read pairs at the tail of mapping distances in paired-
end read sequencing (green) just upstream from jgw. Up to 20% of duplicates observed have long-spanning read pairs indicative of putative deletions in 
one or more alleles in the population. </p>

<p>FIG. 7. Secondary deletion via large loop mismatch repair. A tandem 
duplication forms via ectopic recombination or replication slippage. At 
some point prior to fixation in the population the duplication pairs with 
an unduplicated chromatid in meiosis or mitosis, invoking the action of 
the large loop mismatch repair system. Imprecise excision results in a 
modified duplicate with partially deleted sequence. Large loop mis-
match repair requires that duplications are polymorphic, and would 
therefore produce secondary modification over short timescales, result-
ing in rapid modification of tandem duplicates. </p>



<p>Rogers et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>whole gene duplications (table 1). We used the maximum 
span of divergently oriented reads across all strains to identify 
tandem duplications that capture gene sequences in D. 
yakuba or D. simulans and to determine their propensity to 
capture whole and partial gene sequences. 
We find that 47.3% of tandem duplications in D. yakuba 
and 40.8% in D. simulans capture coding sequences. The av-
erage duplicated gene in D. yakuba covers 45.9% of the gene 
sequence and 60.5% of the gene sequence in D. simulans. 
There are 670 duplications that capture gene sequences, 
spanning 845 different genes in D. yakuba, whereas 398 du-
plications span 478 genes in D. simulans. Some 103 genes in D. 
yakuba and 65 genes in D. simulans are captured in multiple 
independent duplications, with some genes falling in as many 
as six independent putative duplications as defined by diver-
gently oriented reads in D. yakuba and 32 independent pu-
tative duplications in D. simulans. Such high rate of 
independent duplications in D. simulans is consistent with 
previous studies using microarrays (Cardoso-Moreira et al. 
2012). In total 993 gene fragments in D. yakuba and 758 
gene fragments in D. simulans exist as segregating copy 
number variants in the population, and 56 genes are dupli-
cated in both species. 
Assuming that unmodified duplications without deletions 
represent the original mutated state, in D. yakuba, </p>

<p>274 </p>

<p>845 (27.6%) 
of duplicated gene fragments span more than 80% of gene 
sequence and capture the translation start site whereas 65 
(7.7%) capture 20% or less and the translation start site. In 
D. simulans </p>

<p>317 </p>

<p>478 (66.3%) duplicated gene sequences capture 
80% or more of the gene sequence and the translation start, 
and 34 (7.1%) capture 20% or less and include the translation 
start. Based on a resampling of gene duplications in D. yakuba, 
D. simulans houses an overabundance of whole or nearly 
whole gene duplications (P &lt; 10 
À7 ) and an underrepresen-
tation of small fragments (P ¼ 0:00291), suggesting differ-
ences in the occurrence of whole gene duplications across 
species due either to mutational pressures or selection. </p>

<p>Duplicate Genes and Rapidly Evolving Phenotypes </p>

<p>Biases in the rates at which duplications form in different 
genomic regions or a greater propensity for selection to 
favor duplications in specific functional classes can result in 
a bias in gene ontology (GO) categories among duplicated 
genes. We used <rs type="software">DAVID GO</rs> analysis software to identify over-
represented functions among duplicate genes in D. yakuba 
and D. simulans. In D. yakuba, we observe 678 duplicated 
genes with orthologs in D. melanogaster. Overrepresented 
functional categories include immunoglobulins, extracellular 
matrix, chitins and aminoglycans, immune response and 
wound healing, drug and hormone metabolism, chorion de-
velopment, chemosensory response and development, and 
morphogenesis (supplementary table S13, Supplementary 
Material online). In D. simulans, we observe 478 duplicated 
genes with orthologs in D. melanogaster. Overrepresented GO 
categories include cytochromes and oxidoreductases plus 
toxin metabolism, immune response to microbes, phosopho-
lipid 
metabolism, 
chemosensory 
processing, </p>

<p>carboxylesterases, glutathion transferase and drug metabo-
lism, and sarcomeres (supplementary table S13, 
Supplementary Material online). In D. simulans, 65 genes 
were involved in multiple independent duplications that 
have distinct breakpoints. Overrepresented GO categories in-
clude immune response to bacteria, chorion development 
and oogenesis, chemosensory perception, and organic 
cation membrane transport (supplementary table S14, 
Supplementary Material online). In D. yakuba among 72 
genes duplicated independently, chorion development and 
oogenesis, cell signaling, immune response, sensory process-
ing, and development are overrepresented (supplementary 
table S14, Supplementary Material online). 
There are 25 high-frequency variants found at a sample 
frequency of </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>20 or greater in D. simulans, including lipases and 
endopeptidases expressed in male accessory glands and sev-
eral genes involved in immune response to microbes (supple-
mentary table S15, Supplementary Material online). One gene 
arose independently and has reached high frequency twice in 
D. simulans. In D. yakuba, we observe 13 high-frequency var-
iants, including endopeptidases and adenosine monopho-
sphate dependent ligases (supplementary table S15, 
Supplementary Material online). Both male reproductive pro-
teins (Wong and Wolfner 2012) and immune response to 
pathogens (Lazarro and Clark 2012) are known for their 
rapid evolution, and therefore these genes are strong candi-
dates to search for evidence of ongoing selective sweeps. 
Though mutational biases can produce similarities in GO 
categories, the overabundance of toxin metabolism genes 
and immune response peptides in both species as well as 
the overrepresentation of chemoreceptors, chitin cuticle 
genes, and oogenesis factors suggests that duplications are 
likely key players in rapidly evolving systems. </p>

<p>Chimeric Genes and Altered Coding Sequences </p>

<p>If only one boundary of a tandem duplication falls within a 
coding sequence and thereby copies the 5 
0 end of a gene, the 
resulting construct will recruit formerly noncoding sequence 
to form the 3 
0 end of the coding sequence (fig. 8A). 
We observe 143 cases of recruitment of noncoding se-
quence in D. yakuba (supplementary tables S16 and S17, 
Supplementary Material online) and 96 cases in D. simulans 
(supplementary tables S18 and S19, Supplementary Material 
online). Several of these are found at moderate frequencies 
&gt;50%. Overrepresented GO categories among genes in 
D. simulans include immune defense and sarcomeres, 
whereas genes with recruited sequence in D. yakuba show 
an overrepresentation of genes involved in locomotory be-
havior. We observe one high-frequency variant in D. yakuba 
at a sample frequency of </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>20 , an Adenylate cyclase involved in 
locomotor rhythm as well as two high-frequency variants in 
D. simulans LysB, an antimicrobial humoral response gene, 
and a gene of unknown function. These high-frequency 
chimeras are strong candidates for selective sweeps. 
If both boundaries fall within different coding sequences, 
tandem duplications can create chimeric genes (fig. 8B) 
(Rogers et al. 2009). We find 130 tandem duplications in D. </p>



<p>Tandem Duplications in Nonmodel Drosophila . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>yakuba and 76 in D. simulans where both breakpoints fall 
within nonoverlapping coding sequences. Some 11 of the 130 
duplications in D. yakuba and 30 of 76 in D. simulans have 
both breakpoints in gene sequences face one another and as 
such are not expected to create new open reading frames, as 
the constructs will lack promoters. Another 40 of the 130 
duplications in D. yakuba and 8 of 76 in D. simulans have 
both breakpoints in gene sequences, and will have promoters 
that can potentially transcribe sequences from both strands 
of DNA (fig. 9, supplementary tables S20 and S21, 
Supplementary Material online). Only 78 chimeric coding 
sequences in D. yakuba (supplementary tables S22 and S23, 
Supplementary Material online) and 38 chimeric genes in D. 
simulans (supplementary table S24, Supplementary Material 
online) have parental genes in parallel orientation. Among the 
parental genes of these chimeras, cytochromes and genes 
involved in drug metabolism are overrepresented in D. 
yakuba. Other functional categories which are present but 
not overrepresented include endopeptidases, signaling glyco-
peptides, and sensory signal transduction peptides. Among 
parental genes in D. simulans, cytochromes and insecticide 
metabolism genes, sensory perception genes, and endopepti-
dase genes are overrepresented. Additional categories present 
include signal peptides, endocytosis genes, and oogenesis 
genes. Several such constructs are found at moderate fre-
quencies above 10/20, suggesting that they are at least not 
detrimental. However, two chimeras in D. yakuba are found 
at high frequency. One formed from a combination of 
GE12441 and GE12442 is at a frequency of 16/20, and one 
formed from GE12353 and GE12354 is at a frequency of 19/20. 
In D. simulans one chimera, formed from CG11598 and 
CG11608, is at a frequency of 20/20. All of these genes are 
lipases or endopeptidases. These high-frequency variants are 
strong candidates for selective sweeps. 
Compared with the number of tandem duplications that 
capture coding sequences, the number of duplications which 
form chimeric genes indicates that chimeric constructs </p>

<p>derived from parental genes in parallel orientation form as 
a result of 10.4% of tandem duplications that capture genes in 
D. yakuba and 9.5% of tandem duplications that capture 
coding sequences in D. simulans. These numbers are in gen-
eral agreement with rates of chimeric genes formation esti-
mated from a within-genome study of D. melanogaster of 
16.0% compared with the rate of formation of duplicate 
genes (Rogers et al. 2009). </p>

<p>Association with Transposable Elements and Direct 
Repeats </p>

<p>Repetitive sequences are known to facilitate ectopic recom-
bination events that commonly yield tandem duplications 
(Lim and Simmons 1994). In D. yakuba, 179 (12.7%) 
tandem duplications fall within 1 kb of a transposable ele-
ment (TE) in at least one sample strain that has a duplication 
and 52 (3.7%) fall within 100 bp of a TE (supplementary table 
S25, Supplementary Material online). In D. simulans, 122 
(12.5%) lie within 1 kb of a TE and 53 (5.4%) fall within 
100 bp of a TE (supplementary table S25, Supplementary 
Material online). Additionally, 125 (8.8%) of duplications in 
D. yakuba have 100 bp or more of direct repeated sequence in 
the 500 bp up and downstream of duplication boundaries 
and 237 (16.7%) have 30 bp or more in the reference sequence 
as identified in a BLASTn comparison of regions flanking 
divergently oriented read spans at an E value 10 
À5 (sup-
plementary table S25, Supplementary Material online). In 
D. simulans, 56 (5.7%) have 100 bp or more of direct repeated 
sequence in the 500 bp up and downstream of duplication 
boundaries in the reference and 150 (14.4%) have 30 bp or 
more of repeated sequence (supplementary table S25, 
Supplementary Material online). In total 371 duplications in 
D. yakuba and 243 duplications in D. simulans either lie within 
1 kb of a TE in at least one strain or are flanked by 30 bp or 
more of direct repeated sequence. Hence, a maximum of 
26.2% of duplications identified in D. yakuba and 24.9% of 
duplications identified in D. simulans may have been facili-
tated by ectopic recombination between large repeats, con-
sistent with previous estimates from single genome studies of 
30% in D. melanogaster but somewhat higher than those in 
D. yakuba of 12% (Zhou et al. 2008). 
In D. yakuba, 14.4% of duplications with 100 bp or more of 
repetitive sequence and 21.1% of duplications with 30 bp or 
more are located on the X. In contrast, 46.4% of duplications </p>

<p>FIG. 8. Abnormal gene structures. Duplicated sequence is highlighted 
with bold colors and is framed by the dashed box. (A) The partial du-
plication of a coding sequence (blue) results in the recruitment of pre-
viously upstream noncoding sequence (dashed lines) to create a novel 
open reading frame (blue and turquoise). (B) Tandem duplication where 
both boundaries fall within coding sequences results in a chimeric gene. </p>

<p>FIG. 9. Dual promoter genes. Duplicated sequence is highlighted with 
bold colors and is framed by the dashed box. Tandem duplication where 
both boundaries fall within coding sequences results in a chimeric gene 
which contains two promoters, one which facilitates transcription in 
one direction, the other facilitating transcription from the opposite 
strand. The chimera is capable of making partial antisense transcripts. </p>



<p>Rogers et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>in D. simulans with 100 bp or more of direct repeated se-
quence in the reference and 44.7% with more than 30 bp of 
repeated sequence in the D. simulans reference lie on the X 
chromosome. Based on a resampling of randomly chosen 
duplications, duplications on the X chromosome are overrep-
resented among duplications with direct repeats (P &lt; 10 
À7 ) 
but the same is not true of duplicates with direct repeats in 
D. yakuba (P ¼ 0:248). A genome wide BLASTn comparison 
shows that direct repeats are not overrepresented on the 
D. simulans X chromosome and cannot explain the observed 
association (supplementary table S26, Supplementary 
Material online). Hence, duplication via ectopic recombina-
tion may be exceptionally common on the X chromosome in 
D. simulans. </p>

<p>Excess of Duplications on the D. simulans X </p>

<p>The distribution of duplication sizes was calculated for each 
major chromosomal arm in each species. Average duplicate 
size is 2,518 bp, in close agreement with that observed in 
mutation accumulation lines in D. melanogaster (Schrider 
et al. 2013) but somewhat larger than that observed using 
microarrays in D. simulans (Cardoso-Moreira et al. 2011). The 
X chromosome in D. yakuba displays an overabundance of 
small duplications in comparison to each of the autosomes in 
a Tukey's Honestly Significant Difference (HSD) test after cor-
rection for multiple testing with 27% of duplicates 500 bp or 
less (P 6:8 Â 10 
À5 , figs. 1 and 10A, supplementary table 
S27, Supplementary Material online). Chromosome 2 R is also 
significantly different from the other three major autosomal 
arms (P 2:95 Â 10 
À3 , fig. 10A, supplementary table S27, 
Supplementary Material online). However, in D. simulans 
there is no significant difference between the X and 2R, 2L, 
and 3R even though the X houses a greater density of </p>

<p>duplications (fig. 10B). The D. simulans chromosome 3L is 
different from 2L (P ¼ 0:029, fig. 10B, supplementary table 
S27, Supplementary Material online). 
We observe a significant effect in the number of duplica-
tions per mapped base pair by chromosome in both 
D. yakuba (Fð5,109Þ ¼ 8:321, P ¼ 1:09 Â 10 
6 ) and D. simu-
lans (Fð5,113Þ ¼ 36:74, P &lt; 2 Â 10 
À16 ). In a post hoc 
Tukey's HSD test with correction for multiple testing, the 
D. simulans X chromosome contains more duplications 
per mapped base pair than any of the autosomes, with 316 
duplications (P 1:0537 Â 10 
À4 , supplementary table S28, 
Supplementary Material online, figs. 1 and 11). Chromosome 
2 R contains an excess of duplicates in comparison to chro-
mosome 3 R (P ¼ 0:032), but all other pairwise comparisons 
of the four major autosomes are not significant. Chromosome 
4 contains an excess of duplications per mapped base pair in 
comparison to all other chromosomes in both D. simulans 
and D. yakuba. In D. yakuba, the X is different from 3 L 
(P ¼ 0:039) but not from any other autosome. Some 11 of 
the 25 duplicates in D. simulans are at a frequency of </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>20 strains 
or greater (44%) on the X (fig. 1). In comparison, only 2 of the 
13 high-frequency duplications in D. yakuba (15.4%) are 
located on the X, nor do we see a comparable 
overabundance of duplications on the D. yakuba X. These 
results point to a clear excess of duplications on the X chro-
mosome in D. simulans in comparison to the autosomes, 
as well as an overabundance of duplications on the fourth 
chromosome in both species. 
Given the excess of duplications associated with repetitive 
content on the D. simulans X, repetitive elements may be an 
important factor in forming the observed overabundance of 
duplications on the D. simulans X. Although mutational and 
selective processes can lead to a bias in the number of </p>

<p>FIG. 10. Cumulative distribution function for duplication sizes for the X and four major autosomal arms in (A) Drosophila yakuba and (B) D. simulans. 
The X chromosome in D. yakuba (red) is significantly different from all autosomes (P &lt; 10 
À3 ) due to a large number of small duplications 500 bp or 
less. Chromosome 2 R (blue) is also different from Chr2L and 3 R (P &lt; 0:05). In D. simulans, chromosome 3 L (green) is significantly different 2 L, 3 R, 
and the X. </p>



<p>Tandem Duplications in Nonmodel Drosophila . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>duplications that form on different chromosomes, the excess 
of high-frequency variants on the D. simulans X at a frequency 
of 20 out of 20 would suggest that at least some of the over-
abundance on the D. simulans X is due to selective forces or 
demography resulting in duplicates spreading through the 
population. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We have used paired-end reads to describe tandem duplica-
tions in sample strains of D. yakuba and D. simulans, their 
sample frequencies, and the genes that they affect. We use 
high coverage Illumina genomic sequencing data of 50Â 
or greater to successfully identify tandem duplications 
among individually sequenced isofemale lines derived 
from natural populations. We have filtered tandem duplica-
tions to include recently derived segregating tandem dupli-
cates that are not present in the reference genome 
of each species for genomic regions that have coverage of 
three or more read pairs across all sequenced strains. We 
show high rates of confirmation using long molecule PacBio 
sequences with 96.1% of variants showing evidence of 
confirmation. 
We identify 1,415 tandem duplicates in D. yakuba and 975 
in D. simulans, indicating that there is substantial standing 
variation segregating in populations that may contribute 
adaptive evolution and the instance of detrimental pheno-
types. We identify hundreds of chimeric genes and cases 
where genes recruit formerly noncoding sequence. We have 
shown an excess of duplications on the D. simulans X chro-
mosome as well as an overabundance of whole gene dupli-
cations in D. simulans, suggestive of selection acting on 
duplications. </p>

<p>Rapid Modification of Duplicated Alleles </p>

<p>Standing variation is expected to play a major role in adap-
tation and evolutionary change (Barrett and Schluter 2008). If 
the span of standing variation in populations is limited, the dy-
namics, genomic content, and variability of standing variation 
in populations are likely to play a defining role in evolutionary 
outcomes. The observed span of tandem duplications across 
strains is limited, with 2.574% of the assayable genome of the 
X and four major autosomes in D. yakuba and 1.837% of the 
assayable genome of the X and four major autosomes in 
D. simulans. Yet, the variation that is observed portrays a 
dynamic picture of gains and losses with evidence that dupli-
cations can induce subsequent deletions through large loop 
mismatch repair, suggesting that regions that are duplicated 
create genomic instability. The resulting expansion and con-
traction of genomic sequences will contribute to greater var-
iability in these limited regions than has been suggested to 
date, offering wider variation upon which selection can act. 
Up to 17% of duplications in D. yakuba and 8% of duplica-
tions in D. simulans show long-spanning reads in one or more 
strains, indicative of complex changes such as subsequent 
deletion, insertion of foreign sequence, or incomplete or 
short-range dispersed duplication (fig. 5). These results are 
consistent with complex breakpoints previously observed in 
D. melanogaster (Cridland and Thornton 2010). Moreover, 
coverage changes for certain variants are consistent with 
duplication followed by subsequent deletion in one or both 
copies (supplementary fig. S4, Supplementary Material 
online). Hence, the current pool of genetic diversity will in 
fact be far greater than simple interpretation of divergently 
oriented reads or split read mapping might indicate. The 
majority of such changes has one or more strains with no </p>

<p>FIG. 11. Number of Duplications per bp on the X and major autosomes in Drosophila yakuba and D. simulans. The X chromosome in D. simulans 
contains an excess of duplications in comparison with the autosomes. Chromosome 2 R also contains more duplications per bp than chromosome 3 R 
but no other autosomes are significantly different. Chromosome 4, the dot chromosome, has more duplications per mapped bp in both D. yakuba and 
D. simulans than any other chromosome. </p>



<p>Rogers et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>signs of modification, suggesting that these variants are pri-
marily duplications followed by deletions. 
Secondary deletions of recently duplicated alleles may be 
exceptionally common, especially in deletion-biased genomes 
such as Drosophila. Deletion of excess unpaired DNA for 
polymorphic duplicates during large loop mismatch repair, 
excision of TEs, replication slippage, and deletion during 
nonhomologous end joining all offer common mechanisms 
that are likely to remove portions of duplicated alleles. 
Among these mechanisms, the large loop mismatch repair 
system specifically targets newly added DNA and is likely to 
be a driving force in the rapid modification of duplicated 
alleles. In the ideal case, precise excision would simply 
return the construct to singleton state resulting in a rapid 
cycle of mutations and reversions. However, when such re-
moval is imprecise, these subsequent deletions are likely to 
modify duplicated sequences leaving incompletely duplicated 
segments. The average distance spanned by these putative 
deletions is over 2 kb, well above the mean for deletions ob-
served in mutation accumulation lines of D. melanogaster 
(Schrider et al. 2013), but in agreement with the amount of 
DNA that can be efficiently removed by large loop mismatch 
repair (Kearney et al. 2001). 
Duplications have the potential to induce secondary dele-
tions quickly, whereas variants remain polymorphic, thereby 
offering mechanisms for rapid and potentially drastic geno-
mic change that can potentially alter gene content, dosage, 
and regulation. Variation in populations, while limited in its 
genomic scope, may offer multiple variant forms at individual 
duplication sites. Thus, the substrate that is present for selec-
tion and adaptation will be far richer than a simple duplica-
tion or single copy, but rather can take on these complex 
forms of modified variants that remain largely unexplored in 
terms of their molecular and evolutionary impacts. Thus, al-
though the observed amount of variation is limited to only a 
fraction of the genome, the level of variation at these dupli-
cated sites portrays an exceptionally dynamic flux of duplica-
tions and deletions at these sites that will result in changes in 
the content and organization of the genome and therefore 
is expected to have a strong influence on evolutionary 
outcomes. 
Drosophila yakuba displays 1.5 times as many duplications 
in comparison to D. simulans, as well as a 2-fold enrichment in 
the percentage of variants with signals of deletion in one or 
more copy and higher population level mutation rates. The 
rapid flux of duplication and deletion observed in D. yakuba 
has produced a wider array of standing variation, which is 
expected to have a significant effect on evolutionary trajec-
tories. Drosophila yakuba will likely display not only a greater 
tendency toward pathogenic phenotypes associated with 
tandem duplicates (Hu and Worton 1992; Emerson et al. 
2008) but also a greater source of standing variation that 
can be useful in adaptation and the development of novel 
traits (Conant and Wolfe 2008). Estimates of N e in D. yakuba 
are higher than in D. simulans. We would thus expect greater 
instances of detrimental duplicates to be higher in D. simulans 
than in D. yakuba, but neutral mutations will collect more 
quickly across populations of D. yakuba due to high N e . </p>

<p>Hence, we suggest that the overabundance of duplicates in 
D. yakuba is not due to drift. Neither do we observe an excess 
of high-frequency variants in D. yakuba that might be sug-
gestive of selection, especially with respect to polymorphic 
variants. 
Based on birth-death models of gene families, D. simulans 
is suggested to have high rates of duplication, whereas 
D. yakuba showed only moderate rates of gene family evolu-
tion (Hahn et al. 2007). This may in fact be influenced by the 
overabundance of whole gene duplicates in D. simulans and 
not a reflection of genome wide mutation rates. The dichot-
omy between reference genomes and genome wide polymor-
phic variants might putatively be driven by selection for 
whole gene duplicates in D. simulans or mutational biases 
toward whole gene duplications. </p>

<p>Chimeric Genes </p>

<p>Chimeric genes are a known source of genetic novelty that are 
more likely to produce regulatory changes, alterations in cel-
lular targeting and membrane bound domains, as well as 
selective sweeps in comparison to whole gene duplications 
(Rogers and Hartl 2012). Chimeric genes have been known to 
produce peptides with novel functions in Drosophila (Long 
and Langley 1993; Ranz et al. 2003; Zhang et al. 2004) and in 
humans (Zhang et al. 2009; Ohshima and Igarashi 2010) and 
many are associated with adaptive bursts of amino acid sub-
stitutions (Jones and Begun 2005; Jones et al. 2005). We ob-
serve large numbers of recently derived chimeric constructs 
within populations, with 222 chimeric genes or genes 
that recruit noncoding sequence in D. yakuba and 134 in 
D. simulans, even in a limited sample of 20 strains per species. 
In spite of their known role in adaptation, the majority of 
copy number variants is thought to be detrimental (Hu and 
Worton 1992; Emerson et al. 2008; Cardoso-Moreira et al. 
2011). Chimeric genes are associated with human cancers, 
and the molecular changes associated with chimera forma-
tion may contribute to their role as causative factors in 
human disease. The molecular changes that are facilitated 
by chimera formation (Rogers and Hartl 2012) likely contrib-
ute to their detrimental impacts on organisms and their role 
in disease as well as their potential for adaptation. We observe 
large numbers of chimeric genes that are identified as single 
variants in the population. Thus, chimeras may play the dual 
role of key players in adaptation to novel environments and 
as agents of detrimental phenotypic changes. The large 
amounts of standing variation observed may therefore con-
tribute to disease alleles in populations, and proper identifi-
cation is likely to be important for studies in human health. </p>

<p>Breakpoint Determination </p>

<p>Many variants have breakpoints that cannot be assembled de 
novo from Illumina sequences (supplementary table S30, 
Supplementary Material online). Yet, we observe a 96.1% con-
firmation rate using PacBio reads. These results imply that 
breakpoints are often repetitive, low complexity sequence or 
contain novel insertions and secondary events that are diffi-
cult to determine from paired-end read mapping alone or </p>

<p>1759 </p>

<p>Tandem Duplications in Nonmodel Drosophila . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>current naive de novo assembly methods. Hence, although 
paired-end Illumina read mapping is highly accurate, it cannot 
ascertain breakpoints to single base pair resolution in the 
majority of cases. Moreover, requiring breakpoint assembly 
to identify duplications will produce a strong ascertainment 
bias against up to 50% of all variants. This bias is more severe 
for small variants, even in Drosophila, which have compact 
genomes and few repeats in comparison to plants or verte-
brates. Thus, short high-throughput Illumina reads orienta-
tion mapping offers an accurate but incomplete picture of 
variation present in the population, which can now be clar-
ified with low coverage long read sequencing data. 
Microarrays and coverage are subject to affects of misprob-
ing, mismapping, and large amounts of noise relative to signal 
(supplementary fig. S4, Supplementary Material online). 
However, where accurate, arrays may reflect the span of du-
plicated segments more accurately than divergent reads alone 
as they would accurately reflect deletion after duplication. 
However, the presence of complex events such as subsequent 
deletions may, if not properly identified and accounted for, 
overestimate of the mutation rate of duplications and under-
estimate their frequency in the population by claiming a 
modified variant as an independent duplication. Here, the 
directional nature and spatial relationships of read pair map-
ping show advantages: Divergently oriented reads distinguish 
duplication, whereas long spanning properly oriented reads 
can indicate a deletion with greater clarity and properly iden-
tify subsequent modification. Identifying putative deletions in 
duplicated sequences requires a tight distribution of insert 
sizes during library preparation (supplementary table S5, 
Supplementary Material online) but offers a far more com-
plete picture of variation that is segregating in populations 
and more accurate estimation of variant frequencies that is 
well worth the effort. </p>

<p>The X Chromosome </p>

<p>The D. simulans X chromosome appears to be unusual in that 
it contains an excess of duplications per mapped base pair in 
comparison to the autosomes, and an overabundance of 
duplications associated with long repeats. Within-genome 
surveys of nonsynonymous mutations in the D. simulans ref-
erence (Andolfatto et al. 2011) and large numbers of high-
frequency derived variants among nonsynonymous sites and 
untranslated regions in D. simulans (Haddrill et al. 2008) in-
dicate widespread selective sweeps acting on the X chromo-
some. Similarly, we identify an excess of variants identified at 
high frequency on the D. simulans X, consistent with previous 
work using microarrays (Cardoso-Moreira et al. 2011). In D. 
melanogaster, the X chromosome contains greater repetitive 
content (Mackay et al. 2012), displays different gene density 
(Adams et al. 2000), has potentially smaller population sizes 
(Wright 1931; Andolfatto 2001), lower levels of background 
selection (Charlesworth 2012), and an excess of genes in-
volved in female-specific expression (Ranz et al. 2003) in com-
parison to the autosomes. Moreover, X chromosomes are 
subject to selfish genetic elements and often play a role in 
speciation (Presgraves 2008). Thus, the X chromosome may </p>

<p>be exceptionally subject to widespread selection, and the role 
of tandem duplicates as responders to selective pressures 
deserves future exploration. 
Similar patterns of high frequency variation have not been 
observed in D. yakuba, suggesting that evolution proceeds 
differently across the different species. The D. yakuba X chro-
mosome has an excess of small duplications, which might 
potentially indicate selection acting against large duplications 
on the D. yakuba X. Tandem duplications are known to be 
detrimental, and given the hemizygous state of the X chro-
mosome in males, we would expect purifying selection to act 
quickly on the X. The extent to which these patterns observed 
in D. yakuba may be driven by selection or demography 
remains to be seen and is an important open question 
deserving of future study. </p>

<p>Methodological Approach </p>

<p>Originally, high-throughput detection of copy number varia-
tion relied on microarrays or single nucleotide polymorphism 
chips available at the time (Dopman and Hartl 2007; Emerson 
et al. 2008; Ionita-Laza et al. 2009; Conrad et al. 2010) and 
therefore suffers from problems of misprobing, variable hy-
bridization intensities, and dye effects, producing large 
amounts of noise relative to signal (Ionita-Laza et al. 2009). 
More recent studies have focused solely on changes in 
Illumina or 454 coverage analogous to changes in hybridiza-
tion intensity (Sudmant et al. 2010). We have used coverage 
changes in combination with divergently oriented reads to 
identify variants using comparisons to a resequenced refer-
ence and quantile normalized coverage data to correct for 
stochastic coverage changes, repetitive content, GC bias, and 
low complexity sequence, resulting in robust variant calls. 
Furthermore, the common practice of retaining only variants 
that are present in multiple samples or at particular genotype 
frequencies (Conrad et al. 2010), detected by multiple inde-
pendent methods (Alkan et al. 2009; Mills et al. 2011; Zichner 
et al. 2013), or that are larger than several kilobases (Alkan 
et al. 2009; Xie and Tammi 2009; Sudmant et al. 2010) can lead 
to severe ascertainment bias both with respect to the types of 
variants that are present, the estimation of their prevalence 
within populations and contribution to disease phenotypes, 
and the evolutionary impacts of duplicated sequences. 
With more recent improvements in Illumina sequencing 
technology, we have been able to sequence strains individu-
ally to 50Â or greater coverage. The use of paired-end reads in 
extremely high-coverage data provides clear advantages over 
previous work using roughly 3.6-25Â with subsets sequenced 
to 30-42Â (Sudmant et al. 2010; Mills et al. 2011; Zichner 
et al. 2013), or 16Â (Alkan et al. 2009). The high-coverage data 
presented here cover the majority of the assayable genome 
and we exclude only a few percent of variant calls due 
to low coverage across strains (supplementary table S9, 
Supplementary Material online). Thus, we are able to identify 
hundreds of events that have three or more supporting di-
vergent read pairs that might be missed at lower coverage 
(supplementary fig. S1, Supplementary Material online). We 
have additionally filtered sequences to exclude ancestral </p>



<p>Rogers et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>duplications, similarly to previous work in humans (Mills et al. 
2011) allowing for identification of derived mutations. The 
result is a high-confidence data set for recently derived 
tandem duplications in data that effectively surveys the ma-
jority of the assayable genome. This high coverage is essential 
in ensuring valid results from the sole use of paired-end read 
orientation. However, the types of duplications that can be 
detected are highly dependent on sequencing library insert 
size. For breakpoints with large amounts of repetitive se-
quence, reads separated by 300 bp may not be sufficient to 
overcome difficulties of read mapping. Additionally, the min-
imum duplication size is also limited by insert size. Capturing 
these types of constructs using paired-end reads, especially in 
organisms with large amounts of repetitive content, including 
nested TEs, will require a more diverse range of library insert 
sizes, a factor that is likely to be important for surveys of larger, 
more repetitive genomes. 
We are able to identify copy number variants as small as 
66 bp using divergently oriented paired-end reads, even in 
cases where nucleotide divergence between paralogs or par-
tially repetitive sequence might otherwise complicate their 
discovery through coverage changes or split read mapping 
using short reads. Divergently oriented reads are additionally 
reliable to detect duplications in regions where distributions 
of coverage are too irregular to allow for automated detection 
of duplicates. We observe a high 96.1% confirmation rate of 
variants among four sample strains of D. yakuba using PacBio 
reads up to 24 kb in length, suggesting that paired-end reads 
in high coverage genomic sequencing will grossly outperform 
previous methods which show high false positive and false 
negative rates. Moreover, the use of the newly annotated 
D. simulans genome (Hu et al. 2013) based on a single iso-
female line will result in improved accuracy in comparison to 
previous studies in D. simulans (Cardoso-Moreira et al. 2011). 
The general principles of the paired-end approach should be 
broadly applicable and similar methods already have been 
used to identify chromosomal inversions in natural popula-
tions (Corbett-Detig et al. 2012). PacBio reads can confirm 
structural variants with high rates of success, even given low 
coverage and nucleotide high error rates (Huddleston et al. 
2014) and we have extended this approach to our genome 
wide survey. However, the ambiguity of split read mapping in 
the face of repetitive elements can still complicate de novo 
duplicate discovery using split read mapping of long reads. 
Furthermore, for the present, generating high-coverage geno-
mic sequencing equivalent to that of our paired-end Illumina 
data is not cost-effective. However, this technology and 
similar long read approaches are likely to offer advantages 
in confirming or discovering structural variants such as 
tandem duplications, as well as de novo assembly, that is, 
worth future exploration. 
We are able to identify and confirm a large number of 
complex gene structures, such as chimeric genes, recruitment 
of adjacent noncoding sequence, potential coding sequence 
disruption, and potential selective silencing of expression. 
These complex mutations are often associated with cancer 
and other diseases (Ionita-Laza et al. 2009; Inaki and Liu 2012) 
and are most likely to cause pathogenic outcomes. Hence, the </p>

<p>methods described here will be broadly applicable in genome-
wide association studies and clinical studies as well as in evo-
lutionary genetics of nonmodel systems where next genera-
tion sequencing has so recently made population genomics 
readily tractable. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Here, we have described the landscape of standing variation 
for tandem duplications in isofemale lines derived from nat-
ural populations of D. yakuba and D. simulans with high ac-
curacy. The resulting portrait of hundreds to thousands of 
variants, including large numbers of complex breakpoints, 
modifying deletions, cases of recruited noncoding sequence, 
and dozens of chimeric genes per species reveals a rich sub-
strate of segregating variation across populations. We show 
that although the span of duplications across the genome is 
quite limited duplicates can induce secondary mutations and 
result in dynamic changes, resulting in greater variation across 
mutated sites that offers more abundant variation for use in 
adaptation than has been previously portrayed. The ways in 
which this variation influences adaptive evolution and pro-
duces molecular changes will clarify the extent to which mu-
tational profiles define evolutionary outcomes and the ways 
in which molecular changes associated with tandem duplica-
tions serve as causative factors in disease. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Population Samples </p>

<p>We surveyed variation in ten lines of D. yakuba from Nairobi, 
Kenya and ten from Nguti, Cameroon (collected by 
P. Andolfatto 2002) as well as ten lines of D. simulans from 
Madagascar (collected by B. Ballard in 2002) and ten strains 
from Nairobi, Kenya (collected by P. Andolfatto in 2006). Flies 
from these isofemale lines (i.e., descendants from a single wild-
caught female) were inbred in the lab for 9-12 generations of 
sibling mating. These should provide effectively haploid sam-
ples of allelic variation representative of natural populations. 
In addition to the 20 inbred lines derived from wild-caught 
flies, we also sequenced the reference strains for each species. 
For D. simulans, the reference strain is the w 
501 stock (UCSD 
stock center 14021-0251.011), whose sequence is described in 
Hu et al. (2013). For D. yakuba, the reference strain is UCSD 
stock center 14021-0261.01, and the genome sequence is pre-
viously described in Drosophila Twelve Genomes Consortium 
(2007). The majority of the wild-caught strains and the 
D. yakuba reference stock were sequenced with three lanes 
of paired-end sequencing at the UC Irvine Genomics High 
Throughput Facility (http://dmaf.biochem.uci.edu, last 
accessed April 2014). The sequencing of the D. simulans ref-
erence strain was described in Hu et al. (2013). The number of 
lanes and read lengths per lane are summarized in supple-
mentary tables S1 and S2, Supplementary Material online. </p>

<p>Alignment to Reference </p>

<p>The sequencing reads were aligned to the appropriate refer-
ence genome (Drosophila Twelve Genomes Consortium 
2007; Hu et al. 2013) using <rs id="software-1" type="software">bwa</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 0.5.9</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Li and Durbin</rs> </p>

<p>1761 </p>

<p>Tandem Duplications in Nonmodel Drosophila . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>2009) with the following parameters, bwa aln Àl 13 Àm 
50000000 ÀR 5000. The resulting paired-end mappings 
were resolved via the "sampe" module of bwa (bwa sampe 
Àa 5000 ÀN 5000 Àn 500), and the output was sorted and 
converted into a "bam" file using <rs id="software-2" type="software">samtools</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 0.1.18</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Li et al</rs>. <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-date">2009</rs>). In the alignment and resolution commands, 
Àl is the hash sized used for seeding alignments, and the 
ÀR, Àa, ÀN, and Àn refer to how many alignments are 
recorded for reads mapping to multiple locations in the ref-
erence. After the paired-end mapping resolution, the bam 
files from each lane of sequencing were merged into a 
single bam file sorted according to position along the refer-
ence genome. A second bam file, sorted by read name, was 
then created for use as input into our clustering software. </p>

<p>Clustering Abnormal Mapping Events </p>

<p>Tandem duplications should be readily apparent among 
mapped reads as sequenced read pairs that map in divergent 
orientations (Tuzun et al. 2005; Cridland and Thornton 2010; 
Mills et al. 2011; Zichner et al. 2013), provided that tandem 
duplications with respect to a reference genome result in a 
single novel junction. Figure 2 shows a putative genomic 
sample that contains a tandem duplication of a gene that 
was used to generate paired-end sequencing reads. We al-
lowed for up to two mismatches within mapped reads in 
order to capture divergent read calls in sample strains that 
have moderate numbers of nucleotide differences. Reads were 
required to map uniquely, and so if duplication breakpoints 
contain entirely repetitive sequences with no divergence 
across copies in the genome, they will not be found. These 
limitations will, however, have minimal effects (see supple-
mentary text S1, Supplementary Material online). 
Sets of read pairs in the same strain that are located within 
the 99.9th quantile of the mapping distance between prop-
erly mapped pairs from one another were clustered together 
into a single duplication. In practice, this threshold distance is 
roughly 1 kb. Tandem duplications were identified as regions 
where three or more divergently oriented read pairs cluster to 
the same location in a single strain. Allowing fewer divergent 
reads leads to a large number of false positive duplication calls 
due to cloning and sequencing errors. Further detail is offered 
in supplementary text S1, Supplementary Material online. </p>

<p>PacBio Alignment and Analysis </p>

<p>FASTQ files of PacBio reads were aligned to the D. yakuba 
reference (Drosophila Twelve Genomes Consortium 2007) 
using blasr (Chaisson and Tesler 2012), available from 
https://github.com/PacificBiosciences/blasr (last accessed 
October 2013), with default options and storing the resulting 
alignments in a bam file. Alignments from regions within 1 kb 
of putative tandem duplications called using short read data 
(divergent read orientation plus an increase in coverage) were 
extracted from the bam files using samtools 0.1.18 (Li et al. 
2009). Reads falling within these regions were then pulled and 
realigned to the reference using a BLASTn (Altschul et al. 
1990) with low complexity filters turned off (ÀF F) at an E 
value cutoff of 0.1 to allow for short alignments given the high </p>

<p>error rate of PacBio sequencing. Alignment using BLASTn 
proved important because it revealed cases where the bam 
files resulting from blasr alignments failed to record sec-
ondary hits for a read, especially in cases where alignments are 
on the order of hundreds of base pairs. Here, confirmation 
benefits from long sequences which can anchor reads 
uniquely to a region, producing greater confidence in split 
read alignments. Variants were considered confirmed 
whether two segments of a single PacBio subread which do 
not overlap by more than 20% align to overlapping sections of 
the reference (supplementary fig. S5B, Supplementary 
Material online) or whether a single read aligns in split for-
mation with the downstream end of the read aligning to an 
upstream region of the reference (supplementary fig. S5A and 
C-E, Supplementary Material online). An event was consid-
ered not confirmed whether there were no long reads show-
ing any of the alignment patterns in supplementary figure S5, 
Supplementary Material online, within 1 kb of the variant. 
Variants were considered definite false positives if clearly con-
tradicted by at least one read spanning the entire putatively 
duplicated region as defined by Illumina read mapping and 
adjacent reference. Some of these unconfirmed variants may 
be due to low clone coverage in the region or lack of sufficient 
read lengths rather than false positives. </p>

<p>HMM and Coverage Changes </p>

<p>To detect increases and decreases relative to reference rese-
quencing, we quantile normalized coverage for each strain in 
R so that coverage displayed an equal median and variance 
across all strains (Bolstad et al. 2003). Such normalization 
renders tests of differing coverage robust in the face of differ-
ing sequence depth across samples or across sites and is es-
sential for reliable confirmation of tandem duplicate calls 
(Bolstad et al. 2003). 
We developed a hidden Markov model (HMM) to identify 
statistically significant increases in coverage at duplicated 
sites. In the HMM, hidden states are defined by copy 
number and they act to effect differential emission probabil-
ities for the observed outcomes of coverage depth at dupli-
cated or nonduplicated sites. We modeled differences in 
coverage for sample strains relative to the reference as the 
difference in two normal distributed random variables each 
with a mean and variance corresponding to the observed 
mean and variance in the reference in the given window. 
Detailed methods of the HMM and decoding are provided 
in supplementary text S1, Supplementary Material online. </p>

<p>Deletions and Complex Duplication Events </p>

<p>In order to determine the extent to which secondary 
deletions, incomplete duplications, or short-range dispersed 
duplicates result in complex structures that are not represen-
tative of classic duplications, we identified long-spanning read 
pairs that lie within tandem duplications. We identified read 
pairs with an estimated template length of ! 600 bp, corre-
sponding to roughly the 99.9th percentile of fragment 
lengths in the reference genome (supplementary table S5, 
Supplementary Material online). Long-spanning reads </p>



<p>Rogers et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>whose end points lie within 200 bp of one another and which 
are fully contained within the duplication endpoints were 
clustered together. Clusters supported by five or more read 
pairs (corresponding to a putative P value of 10 
À15 ) were 
recorded as signs of deletion or other complex 
rearrangement. </p>

<p>Sample Frequency of Variants </p>

<p>Complex mutations that are present in two different strains 
and have divergent reads spanning regions on both the 5 
0 and 
3 
0 ends that fall within 100 bp of one another in the two 
strains are considered to be equivalent duplications. 
Although divergently oriented reads reliably identify duplica-
tions, the true boundaries of the duplication may differ from 
the divergent read spans by several bases, especially in cases 
where repetitive or low complexity sequence lies at break-
points, a complication which is not addressed in recent work 
(Mills et al. 2011; Zichner et al. 2013). For each duplication, the 
minimum of divergent read starts and the maximum of 
divergent read stops across all strains were recorded to indi-
cate the span of the duplication. These breakpoints were 
assembled and confirmed in silico using phrap and lastz 
(supplementary text S1, Supplementary Material online). 
In order to correct frequencies for the effects of false neg-
atives, we used a combination of coverage and divergently 
oriented reads to identify tandem duplicates in additional 
strains. For each duplication present based on three or 
more pairs divergent reads in at least one strain, a different 
strain which had at least one divergently oriented read pair 
and displayed 2-fold or greater coverage increases as deter-
mined by the HMM across at least 75% of the duplication's 
span was also recorded as having that particular duplication 
as well. 
We retained tandem duplicates with divergent read pairs 
where the minimum start and the maximum stop after clus-
tering were &lt;25 kb apart. Although there may be some 
tandem duplications larger than 25 kb, divergent read pairs 
at a greater distance are substantially less likely to display 
2-fold coverage changes across the entire span and are there-
fore more consistent with translocations within chromo-
somes (supplementary table S31, Supplementary Material 
online). Unannotated duplications in the reference are likely 
to be biased toward specific sizes, GO classes, or genomic 
locations and are likely to artificially influence statistical 
tests. We removed duplications that were also identified in 
the reference, and did not include these in downstream anal-
yses of duplication sizes or numbers, GO, or site frequency 
spectra. </p>

<p>Polarizing Ancestral State </p>

<p>All tandem duplications identified are polymorphic in popu-
lations and are therefore expected to be extremely young. 
However, tandem duplications may be identified in sample 
strains relative to the references if they are new mutations in 
the sample or if they represent ancestral sequence that has 
returned to single copy in the reference through deletion. In 
order to identify duplications that represent the ancestral </p>

<p>state, we pulled reference sequence corresponding to the 
maximum duplicate span and ran a BLASTn comparison of 
the sequence against the D. melanogaster, D. erecta, and 
D. yakuba or D. simulans reference genomes at an E value 
cutoff of 10 
À5 . 
Ancestral tandem duplications were defined as any seg-
ment that has two hits on the same chromosome of the given 
reference that lie within 200 kb of one another, excluding 
unlocalized sequence and heterochromatin annotations 
where assembly and annotations are uncertain. Ancestral du-
plications that are shared across species should be separated 
by moderate numbers of nucleotide differences, and therefore 
are expected to be correctly assembled across outgroups. Hits 
must have at least 85% nucleotide identity and must span at 
least 80% of the contig spanned by divergently oriented reads 
in the sample. Based on these requirements, we removed 8.1% 
of duplications in D. simulans and 3.3% in D. yakuba, suggest-
ing that the vast majority of duplicates identified are recently 
derived, as expected. Extended methods as well as detailed 
description of sequence data and confirmation are provided 
in supplementary text S1, Supplementary Material online. All 
data files are available at molpopogen.org/Data (last accessed 
April 11, 2014). Aligned bam files were deposited in the 
National Institutes of Health Short Read Archive under acces-
sion numbers SRP040290 and SRP029453. Sequenced stocks 
were deposited in the University of California, San Diego 
(UCSD) stock center with stock numbers 14021-0261.38-
14021-0261.51 and 14021-0251.293-14021-0251.311. </p>

<p>TE Annotation and Repetitive Content </p>

<p>TEs were initially identified in the D. simulans and D. yakuba 
reference sequences by identifying all read pairs where one 
member of the pair aligned uniquely to the reference and the 
other member of the pair aligned multiply. This has been 
previously demonstrated to be an indication of a TE break-
point (Mackay et al. 2012; Cridland et al. 2013). All locations 
to which these multiply aligning reads align were recorded 
and a fasta file of these putative TE locations was generated. 
Putative TE sequences were then aligned to the set of anno-
tated TEs in version 5 of the D. melanogaster reference down-
loaded from flybase (www.flybase.org, last accessed December 
2011) using tblastx (Altschul et al. 1990) with the following 
parameters (Àf 999 ÀF "" Àe 10 
À4 Àm 8). Regions of the 
reference sequence that aligned to a D. melanogaster TE with 
an E value of 10 
À9 were kept and annotated as TEs. We 
then extracted 500 bp to either side of the annotated regions 
of the reference and aligned these regions to the set of D. 
melanogaster TEs, as earlier. This procedure was performed 
twice to capture the full length of TE sequence in the refer-
ence genomes. 
Once TEs were annotated in the reference genomes, TEs 
were detected in the 20 sample genomes (Mackay et al. 2012) 
which include both TE presence and TE absence calls. Briefly, 
initial TE detection was done by identifying all read pairs 
where one member of the pair aligned uniquely to the refer-
ence and the other member aligned to any known TE se-
quence were identified. Unique reads were clustered if they 
aligned to the same strand of the same chromosome, within a </p>



<p>Tandem Duplications in Nonmodel Drosophila . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>given threshold distance. This threshold was defined as the 
99th quantile of mapping distances observed for uniquely 
mapping read pairs that are properly paired and lie in the 
expected orientation on opposite strands. At least three read 
pairs from each of the left and right estimates, in the correct 
orientation and correct strand, were required to indicate a TE. 
Phrap (version 1.090518) (Ewing and Green 1998) with 
the following parameters (Àforcelevel 10 Àminscore 10 
Àminmatch 10) was used to reassemble the local area 
around the TE insertion breakpoint. Contigs were classified 
according to TE family based on alignments in a BLASTn 
search (Altschul et al. 1990). 
Following the initial TE detection phase we examined each 
position where a TE was identified, including TEs identified in 
the appropriate reference, in each other line in that species. At 
this stage, we were able to both identify TEs which had pre-
viously been missed by our pipeline as well as to make ab-
sence calls by reconstructing a contig that spans the TE 
insertion location. Repetitive content independent of 
TEs was defined using an all-by-all BLASTn comparison 
(Altschul et al. 1990) of sequence 500-bp upstream and 
downstream of duplication coordinates in the D. yakuba 
and D. simulans references at an E value 10 
À5 with no 
filter for low complexity or repetitive sequences. We used a 
resampling approach to identify overrepresentation of dupli-
cations associated with direct repeats. We performed 
10,000,000 replicates choosing the same number of tandem 
duplications at random and determining whether an equal or 
greater number was identified on the X chromosome. 
Tandem repeats which might putatively facilitate ectopic 
recombination may hinder identification of tandem dupli-
cates if repeat sequences are identical. We performed an 
all-by-all BLASTn of all chromosomes for each of the reference 
genomes at an E value of 10 
À5 with low complexity filters 
turned off (ÀF F). Ignoring identical self hits, we identified all 
directly repeated sequences with &gt;99.5% nucleotide identity 
which are &gt;300 bp in length and which lie within 25 kb of one 
another, in accordance with the criteria for identifying 
duplicates. </p>

<p>Identifying Duplicated Coding Sequence </p>

<p>Gene duplications were defined as any divergent read 
calls whose maximum span across all lines overlaps with 
the annotated CDS coordinates. Drosophila yakuba CDS 
annotations were based on flybase release D. yakuba r.1.3. 
Gene annotations for the recent reassembly of the D. simu-
lans reference were produced by aligning all D. melanogaster 
CDS to the D. simulans reference in a tblastx. Percent cover-
age of the CDS was defined based on the portion of the 
corresponding genomic sequence from start to stop that 
was covered by the maximum span of divergent read calls 
across all strains. </p>

<p>Gene Ontology </p>

<p>We used <rs id="software-5" type="software">DAVID GO</rs> analysis software (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="url">http://david.abcc.ncifcrf.gov/</rs>/, last accessed March 2013) to determine whether 
any functional categories were overrepresented at duplicated </p>

<p>genes. Functional data for D. yakuba and D. simulans are not 
readily available in many cases, and thus we identified func-
tional classes in the D. melanogaster orthologs as classified in 
Flybase. GO clustering threshold was set to low and signifi-
cance was defined using a cutoff of EASE ! 1:0: The <rs type="software">DAVID</rs> 
clustering software uses Fuzzy Heuristic Partitioning to iden-
tify genes with related functional terms at all levels of GO 
from cellular processes to known phenotypes. </p>

<p>Differences among Chromosomes </p>

<p>We calculated the size of duplications that span &lt;25 kb in 
each sample strain, excluding duplications identified in the 
reference, as incorrectly assembled duplicates are likely be 
biased toward repetitive and low complexity sequence. 
Significant differences in duplication sizes were identified 
using analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Tukey's HSD test 
on the log normalized distribution of duplication sizes by 
chromosome. 
We calculated the number of duplications that span 
&lt;25 kb on each major chromosomal arm for each sample 
strain, excluding duplications identified in the reference. The 
number of duplications was then normalized by the number 
of mapped bases in the reference to adjust for different chro-
mosome sizes and coverage. Differences in the number of 
duplications per base pair were identified using ANOVA 
and Tukey's HSD test. There was no significant difference in 
the number of duplications present across lines. </p>

<p>Supplementary Material </p>

<p>Supplementary text S1, tables S1-S31, and figures S1-S5 are 
available at Molecular Biology and Evolution online (http:// 
www.mbe.oxfordjournals.org/). </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank Elizabeth G. King, Anthony D. Long, and 
Alexis S. Harrison, and Trevor Bedford for helpful discussions, 
as well as Portola Coffee Labs for a supportive writing envi-
ronment. J. J. Emerson gave valuable advice on the use of lastz 
and the University of California-San Cruz (UCSC) toolkit. 
B. Ballard shared D. simulans fly stocks collected from 
Madagascar. The authors also thank several anonymous re-
viewers whose comments substantially improved the manu-
script. This work is supported by a National Institute of 
General Medical Sciences at the National Institute of Health 
Ruth Kirschtein National Research Service Award F32-
GM099377 to R.L.R. Research funds were provided by 
National Institute of General Medical Sciences at the 
National Institute of Health grant R01-GM085183 to K.R.T. 
and R01-GM083228 to P.A. All sequencing and PacBio library 
preparations were performed at the UC Irvine High 
Throughput Genomics facility, which is supported by the 
National Cancer Institute of the National Institutes of 
Health under Award Number P30CA062203. The content is 
solely the responsibility of the authors and does not neces-
sarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of 
Health. The funders had no role in study design, data </p>



<p>Rogers et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of 
the manuscript. </p>









<p>Rogers et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msu124 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

</text></tei>