<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4527497" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT. Previously, we reported that ovarian hormones affect the immune response against E. coli isolated from the dogs affected with 
pyometra. In order to investigate mechanisms underlying the immune modulation, we examined the effects of ovarian hormones on the 
generation of dendritic cells (DCs), the most potent antigen presenting cell. DCs were differentiated from peripheral blood monocytes 
(PBMOs) using a cytokine cocktail. Both estrogen receptor and progesterone receptors were expressed by the PBMOs and immature DCs. 
When various ovarian hormones were added to the culture for the DC differentiation, progesterone significantly decreased the expression 
of DC maturation markers, such as CD1a, CD80 and CD86, on mature DCs. Conversely, the addition of estrogen to the cultures increased 
the expression of CD86, but not other maturation makers. Furthermore, DCs differentiated in the presence of progesterone did not stimulate 
allogeneic mononuclear cells in PB. Taken together, these results indicate that progesterone diminishes the maturation of DCs, leading to 
decreased immune responses against invading pathogens. 
V. WIJEWARDANA ET AL. </p>

<p>
the concentration used in experiments. 
Preparation of cells: Collection of PBMOs and induction 
of DCs were performed as described previously [19]. In 
brief, PB was collected from dogs in anestrus. CD14 + PB-
MOs were isolated from PB mononuclear cells using anti-
human CD14 microbeads (Miltenyi Biotec GmbH, Begisch-
Gladbach, Germany). To induce differentiation to DCs, the 
isolated PBMOs (1 × 10 6 /ml) were cultured in wells of 24 
well-culture plates (Asahi Techno Glass, Shizuoka, Japan) 
with 2 ml culture medium which was composed of 1.5 ml 
PRMI1640 supplemented with fetal bovine serum (FBS) 
(10%) and 0.5 ml TCCM. The cultures were incubated at 
37°C with various concentrations of ovarian hormones. As 
the untreated control, vehicle (ethanol) was added to the cul-
ture. Cells were harvested on day 6 or day 12 to investigate 
either immature or mature DCs. Thus, the early 6 days in the 
culture were considered as the differentiation period, and the 
late 6 days, as the maturation period. 
Reverse transcription (RT) -PCR: Total RNA was from 
PBMOs (1 × 10 6 ), immature DCs (1 × 10 6 ) or ovarian cells 
as a positive control. The RT reaction and the PCR for 
estrogen receptor (ER) α, ERβ and a housekeeping gene 
18s rRNA was performed as previously described [6]. To 
perform the PCR for progesterone receptor (PR), using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Primer</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3</rs> software [13], we designed primers as follows: 
sense, 5′-CAGGTGTACCAGCCGTACCT-3′; antisense, 
5′-ACAGGTTGTGGGAGAGCAAC-3′. 
Flow cytometry: Flow cytometry (FCM) was performed 
as described previously [17, 20]. Cells harvested from the 
cultures were stained with the following monoclonal anti-
bodies (mAbs): FITC-conjugated mouse anti-human CD1a 
mAb (clone NA1/34-HLK, Serotec, Oxford, U.K.), rat 
anti-canine MHC class II mAb (clone YKIX.334.2, Serotec), 
PE-Cy5-conjugated mouse anti-human CD14 mAb (clone 
TÜK4, Serotec), biotin conjugated rat anti-mouse CD80 
mAb (clone 1G10, Becton Dickinson, Franklin Lakes, NJ, 
U.S.A.) and mouse anti-human CD86 mAb (clone FUN-1, 
Becton Dickinson). Staining with biotin conjugated mAb 
was followed by incubation with streptavidin-PerCP-Cy5.5 
(Becton Dickinson). Before staining, the anti-CD86 mAb 
was labeled by PE conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG (Mo-
lecular Probe) for 5 min at room temperature. The excess 
of PE-goat anti-mouse IgG was neutralized by excess puri-
fied mouse IgG (Sigma). After the staining, the cells were 
fixed and analyzed using a flow cytometer (FACSCalibur™: 
Becton Dickinson). Background of the fluorescence was 
adjusted using following isotype-control: FITC-conjugated 
mouse IgG2a (eBioscience, San Diego, CA, U.S.A.), FITC-
conjugated rat IgG2a (eBioscience) and biotin-conjugated 
rat IgG2a (eBioscience). To determine the expression 
intensity of the surface antigens specified above, the mean 
peak channel of the fluorescence intensity was calculated by 
software (CellQuest™: Becton Dickinson) after the FCM 
analysis and expressed as mean expression intensity (MEI). 
Mixed leukocyte reactions (MLR): MLR was carried out 
as described previously [19]. In outline, PBMOs were in-
cubated in the cultures for DC-induction with progesterone, 
17-OHP or estrogen for 12 days. After the incubation, cells </p>

<p>in graded doses were cultured with allogeneic PB mono-
nuclear cells (10 5 ) in 0.2 ml RPMI 1640 supplemented with 
10% FBS for 4 days. Cell proliferation was quantified by 
incubation of the cells with [ 3 H]-thymidine (PerkinElmer ® 
Life and Analytical Sciences, Boston, MA, U.S.A.). 
Statistical analysis: Experimental groups were compared 
using analysis of variance followed by Fisher's protected 
least significant difference (PLSD), implemented using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Stat- View</rs> ® software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Hulinks Inc</rs>., Tokyo, Japan). To compare two 
parameters against each other, Student's t test was used. The 
significance level was set at P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Expression of ovarian hormonal receptors: As the first step 
for elucidating the effect of ovarian hormones on the matura-
tion of DCs, we examined expression of the receptors for ovar-
ian hormones in PBMOs and DCs generated in vitro. As shown 
in Fig. 1, the PBMOs expressed PR. They slightly expressed 
ERβ, but not ERα. Similarly, cells harvested on day 6 of the 
culture expressed ERβ and PR. However, cells harvested on 
day 12 did not express any receptor (data not shown). 
Effect of ovarian hormones on the maturation of DCs: 
Since we have found that an antigen presenting molecule, 
CD1a and co-stimulatory molecules, CD80 and CD86, sig-
nificantly relate to DC maturation [17, 20], we investigate 
effect of ovarian hormones on the expression of these mol-
ecules. It is confirmed that expression of all surface markers 
investigated in this study significantly increased on the day 6 
cultured cells, compared with monocytes as reported previ-
ously [17, 20] (data not shown). As shown in Fig. 2, the in-
tensity of the expression was expressed as MFI calculated by 
the software mentioned. Moreover, since we have found that 
17-OHP does not affect the immune responses of the dog PB 
mononuclear cells, we used that as a control for progesterone. 
As shown in Fig. 3, when the expression of CD80 or CD86 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Expression of receptor for ovarian hormones. The expression 
of receptor for ovarian hormones by PBMOs and the cells collected 
from the DC-inducing culture (Day 6 cell) was examined by RT-
PCR and compared with that by ovary (OV) used as a positive 
control. </p>

<p>PROGESTERONE INHIBITS DC MATURATION </p>



<p>on the day 12 cultured cells was investigated, 17-OHP did not 
significantly affect the expression up to 1 µM. By addition 
of progesterone, the expression of CD80 and CD86 of cells 
decreased in a dose dependent manner and significantly lower 
than that of the 17-OHP culture at 1 µM, when compared with 
an untreated control. In contrast, by addition of estrogen, the 
expression of those molecules increased in a dose dependent 
manner and significantly higher CD80 expression at 2 and 
20 nM when compared with an untreated control. The signifi-
cantly higher CD86 expression was also observed with 20 nM 
estrogen. Then, we investigated the expression of those co-
stimulatory molecules and antigen-presenting molecules, 
MHC class II and CD1a on the day 6 and the day 12 cells in 
the cultures containing 1 µM progesterone, 1 µM 17-OHP or 
2 nM estrogen. As shown in Fig. 4, both progesterone and es-
trogen did not significantly affect the expression of any inves-</p>

<p>tigated molecules on the day 6 cells and that of MHC class II 
on the day 12 cells. The expression of CD80 of the cells in the 
progesterone culture did not increase from day 6 to day 12. 
However, the expression of the cells in the 17-OHP and the 
estrogen culture significantly increased during the 6 days. The 
expression of CD1a and CD86 on the day 12 cells in culture 
of any hormones used significantly increased when compared 
with that on the day 6 cells. Among the day 12 cells, however, 
the expression of those molecules of the cells in the proges-
terone culture was significantly lower than that on cells in the 
17-OHP or the estrogen culture. 
Effect of ovarian hormones on the immune stimulation by 
DCs: Finally, we examined the immune-stimulating ability of 
DCs that were exposed to ovarian hormones during differen-
tiation and maturation. In this experiment, we added ovarian 
hormones into the DC-inducing culture to mimic the maximal </p>

<p>Fig. 2. CD80 vs. FSC profile of cells incubated with various ovarian hormones. PBMOs (10 6 /ml) 
were incubated with progesterone (P) (1 µM), 17α-hydroxy progesterone (17-OHP; a metabolite of 
progesterone) (1 µM) or estrogen (E) (2 nM) in the presence of 25%TCCM for 12 days. After the 
incubation, expression of CD80 and forward scatter (FSC; size) of cells was examined in FCM. Dotted 
lines indicate the mean expression intensity (MEI). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Effect of ovarian hormones on expression of surface antigens characteristically expressed by 
DCs. PBMCs were incubated with various concentrations of progesterone (black circles), 17-OHP 
(white circles) or estrogen (gray circles) in the presence of TCCM for 12 days. As the untreated control, 
vehicle (ethanol) was added to the culture (a white square). After the incubation, the MEI of CD80 or 
CD86 was evaluated in the FCM. Four experiments were independently performed using nine dogs. 
Results were expressed as mean ± SE. *significantly increased and **significantly decreased, com-
pared with the untreated control, P&lt;0.05 by Fisher's PLSD </p>

<p>V. WIJEWARDANA ET AL. </p>

<p>
concentration in blood during the estrus cycle of the dog, i.e. 
0.1 µM progesterone (17-OHP) and 0.2 nM estrogen [3]. As 
shown in Fig. 5, the proliferation of PB mononuclear cells 
increased as was with the addition of DCs generated in the 
culture of estrogen or 17-OHP. However, when DCs generated 
in the progesterone culture were added to the MLR, the prolif-
eration did not increase with the escalating number of the DC. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we examined the effects of ovarian hor-
mones on the generation of DCs to investigate a mechanism 
underlying the immune modulation by ovarian hormones, 
which is intimately connected to the incidence of pyome-
tra in the dog [16]. It has been reported that progesterone 
directly inhibits the development of Th1 cells [12] and that 
estradiol-17β enhances Th1 cell responsiveness via estrogen 
receptor-α and -β [11]. However, it is expected the differ-
entiation and maturation of DCs should be affected by the 
hormones because DC is the sole initiator of primary im-
mune responses and the most potent activator of secondary 
responses [15]. According to the previous study [19], we 
induced DCs from PBMOs and estimated the cells collected 
from the DC-inducing culture on day 6 as the immature DC 
and cells collected on day 12 as the mature DC. 
When the receptors for ovarian hormones were examined, 
the expression of PR and ERβ was found on PBMOs, precur-
sors and immature DCs. Expression of receptors for ovarian 
hormones in the DCs has been reported in other species 
[2, 4, 5]. These results suggest that PBMOs and the imma-</p>

<p>ture DCs are affected by progesterone and estrogen. 
In the examination of surface markers, progesterone sig-
nificantly decreased expression of CD1a, CD80 and CD86 
on the mature DC, but not on the immature DCs. We have 
found that the expression of these markers significantly 
relates to DC maturation [17, 20]. Moreover, although the 
significant decrease of the expression was shown at ten 
times more concentration of that physically observed, the 
allogeneic MLRs significantly decreased using the DCs 
derived from the culture containing progesterone at the 
concentration physically observed in blood during diestrus 
[3]. These results suggest that progesterone significantly 
inhibits the DC-maturation, but not the DC-differentiation. 
The inhibitory effect of progesterone on the maturation was 
also observed in mouse DC [9]. The immature DCs not only 
show weak in immune stimulation, but also induce immune 
tolerance [10]. In contrast to our results, Segere et al. re-
ported that progesterone and estrogen did not effect on the 
maturation of dendritic cells derived from human monocytes 
[14]. However, in their study, hormones were added to the 
cultures where monocytes had differentiated into immature 
DCs (on day 4) and incubated with the immature DCs for 
only 24 hr. In our system, the hormones were added at the 
beginning of the culture and existed for 12 days. Thus, the 
discrepancy between their result and ours may be due to 
the difference of the experimental system. In the diestrus 
of the dog, the maximal level of progesterone on blood is 
maintained for 20-30 days, while the level of estrogen is 
kept very low [3]. Therefore, our system more reflects the 
hormone condition in the diestrus of the dog. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Effect of ovarian hormones on expression of surface antigens characteristically expressed by DCs. 
PBMOs were incubated with progesterone (black bars), 17-OHP (white bars) or estrogen (gray bars) in the 
presence of TCCM for 6 or 12 days. After the incubation, the MEI of indicated molecules was evaluated in the 
FCM. Nine experiments were independently performed using nine dogs. Results were expressed as mean ± SE. 
*significantly increased, compared with "Day 6". a vs. b, b vs c, d vs. e, e vs. f and g vs. h, P&lt;0.05 by Fisher's 
PLSD. </p>

<p>PROGESTERONE INHIBITS DC MATURATION </p>



<p>Taken all evidences together, it is concluded that the inhi-
bition of the DC-maturation by progesterone is a mechanism 
of the immune suppression in the diestrus, which indirectly 
induces the increased incidence of pyometra in the dog. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENT. This study was supported by a 
Grant-in-Aid for Science Research (B) No.233807 from the 
Japan Society for the Promotion of Science. </p>



<p>Fig. 5. Effect of ovarian hormones on immune stimulatory activity 
of DC. Allogeneic PB mononuclear cells were incubated for 4 
days with various numbers of the cells cultured with progesterone 
(black circles), 17-OHP (white circle) or estrogen (gray cycles) in 
the presence of TCCM. After the incubation, proliferation of the 
PB mononuclear cells was evaluated by measuring radioactivity 
of [ 3 H]-thymidine incorporated. The white square indicates the 
background proliferation of PB mononuclear cells (no DCs added). 
Four experiments were independently performed using eight dogs. 
Results were expressed as mean ± SE. Significantly increased 
P&lt;0.05 (*) and P&lt;0.001 (**), compared with the background by 
Fisher's PLSD. </p>

</text></tei>