<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4540847" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. [Purpose] The aim of the present study was to investigate the current evidence for the effect of exercise 
on glycemic control, the lipid profile, body composition, vascular health, and complications in Korean patients with 
type 2 diabetes. [Subjects and Methods] The subjects were 1,263 patients receiving outpatient care at 13 general 
hospitals located in Seoul and Gyeonggido who were subjected to examinations in the areas of blood glucose man-
agement, complications management, and diabetes education between March 19 and May 29, 2013. The relations 
between exercise and various regulatory factors including patient's general and clinical characteristics, metabolic 
regulation, achievement of goals for metabolic regulation, and complication incidence in patients with type 2 dia-
betes were investigated. [Results] Exercise management was associated with a decrease in systolic blood pressure, 
fasting glucose, postprandial glucose, hemoglobin A1c, total cholesterol, triglyceride, and low-density lipoprotein 
Regarding achievement of goals for metabolic regulation, significant odds ratios were observed for the effect of 
exercise treatment on blood pressure, fasting glucose, postprandial glucose, hemoglobin A1c, triglyceride, HDL 
in men, and BMI in patients with type 2 diabetes. Moreover, exercise management was associated with decreased 
occurrence of cerebrovasculopathy. [Conclusion] In conclusion, exercise induced metabolic regulation of glycemic 
control, the lipid profile, and body composition, as well as vascular health and complications, in Korean patients 
with type 2 diabetes. 
Type 2 diabetes mellitus is a widely known chronic 
metabolic disease in nearly all countries that is characterized 
by an increase in the blood-glucose level resulting from im-
pairment of β-cell function relative to insulin sensitivity 1, 2) . 
It is associated with changes in body mass index (BMI), 
glycemic control, the quality of life, and the others as well as 
complications related to the cardiovascular, renal, optic, and </p>

<p>neural system 2-4) . 
The prevalence of type 2 diabetes has become a leading 
global factor of mortality and morbidity 5) . The population 
with type 2 diabetes would increase worldwide by 11.4% 
from 366 million in 2011 to 522 million by 2030, represent-
ing about one in 10 adult. In Korea, the prevalence rate of 
diabetes is expected to be similar to the global trend, and the 
global rate has increased approximately seven-fold, from 1.5 
to 9.9%, during the past 40 years 6) . In particular, diabetes 
has become one of the leading causes of death, and the rate 
of death is the twice as high as that among persons without 
the disorder 3, 7) . Although there has been noticeable develop-
ment of new treatment modalities for diabetes, many studies 
have reported that the prevalence of diabetes is expected to 
double over the next 25 years 5) . 
Clinical trials for patients with diabetes are focused on 
intensive glycemic control to prevent hypoglycemia by mul-</p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. 
27: 2189-2193, 2015 </p>

<p>*Corresponding author. Min Hee Kim (E-mail: kmh12@eulji. 
ac.kr) </p>

<p>©2015 The Society of Physical Therapy Science. Published by IPEC Inc. 
This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Cre-
ative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-
nd) License &lt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/&gt;. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 27, No. 7, 2015 </p>

<p>
tifactorial interventions 8, 9) . Adjustment of food intake, phar-
macological therapy, and exercise are suggested as the three 
major sources of therapy for type 2 diabetes 10) . Especially, 
exercise is an important part of the diabetes management 
plan. Exercise improves longevity and ameliorates the health 
of patients with type 2 diabetes. It has an well-known impact 
on glycated hemoglobin as well as independent effects on 
other parameters of cardio-metabolic risk by promoting 
endothelial function 11) . 
Although most guidelines has emphasized the importance 
of exercise training and numerous studies have demonstrated 
effects on diabetes in experimental environments, large-
scale research of relations between these interventions and 
diabetes have been lacking until recent years in Korea 12) . 
Therefore, the aim of present study was to investigate the 
current evidence for the effect of exercise on glycemic con-
trol, the lipid profile, body composition, vascular health, and 
complications in a number of patients with type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p>SUBJECTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>This study was performed for two months, from March 
19, 2013, to May 29, 2013, at 13 general hospitals located in 
Seoul and Gyeonggi province, Republic of Korea. Patients 
over 20 year old and registered as having type 2 diabetes, 
excluding those with type 1 diabetes and those who were 
unfit on the day they were diagnosed, were invited to par-
ticipate. Based on these criteria, there were 2,626 possible 
participants who had visited outpatient clinics and received 
medical care for 6 months. This study was approved by 
the Institutional Review Board (IRB) of each participant's 
hospital. In this study, we surveyed the management of the 
1,263 type 2 diabetic patients of 13 general hospitals in the 
Republic of Korea according to the American Diabetes As-
sociation (ADA) guidelines 8) . 
Using medical records, we investigated socio-economic 
data, disease-related data, blood sampling tests, prescription 
drugs, co-morbidities and complications. We developed 
and used a questionnaire based on previous study. BMI was 
calculated as weight (kg) divided by height (m) squared. 
To understand the management, we checked the results of 
angiography and hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c), serum lipid, 
fasting blood sugar, 2-hour postprandial glucose, and mi-
croalbuminuria test which are the indexes for blood sugar 
management. We also investigated behavioral treatment, 
oral hypoglycemic agents, insulin, insulin with an oral hy-
poglycemic agent and insulin pumps in the case of diabetes 
treatment. For comorbid medication, we investigated hy-
pertension drugs, anticoagulation agents and anti-lipidemic 
agents. We investigated the 1 year results, and if there were 
no records or the records were one or more years old, the pa-
tient was considered to have had no check-up. For the appro-
priate metabolic control level, we checked the blood sugar 
level, blood pressure, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol 
(LDL-C) &lt; 100 mg/dL, high-density lipoprotein, and serum 
lipid level. We followed the target standards of the ADA 
which were the HbA1c &lt; 7.0%, blood pressure &lt; 130/80 
mmHg, cholesterol (HDL-C) &gt; 40 mg/dL (male) or 55 mg/ 
dL (female), and triglyceride &lt; 150 mg/dL 8) . Regarding 
complications, we included only those diagnosed based on </p>

<p>the patients' medical records. For complications, we counted 
cases in which patients had related drug prescriptions even 
if there was no diagnosis and cases in which there were 
diseases diagnosed based on the patients' medical records. 
If the patients had received education at other institutions, 
the education was excluded because of lack of clear records 
and quality control. When patients were medicated with hy-
pertension-and dyslipidemia-related drugs, we whether or 
not there were medical records. All cancers were included. 
All statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> for 
Windows (v. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">12.0 K</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). The 
results were expressed as the mean ± standard deviation 
(SD) and number (percent). The general and clinical char-
acteristics of the patients in the exercise and non-exercise 
groups, including age, height, weight, and others results, 
were analyzed with the independent t-test. Differences were 
considered statistically significant when p &lt; 0.05. Pearson's 
correlation coefficients were used to assess the relation 
between metabolic regulation (blood pressure, glucose, 
HbA1c, total cholesterol, triglyceride, and HDL and LDL 
cholesterol) and exercise in patients with type 2 diabetes. 
Moreover, univariate logistic regression was used to assess 
the associations between achievement of goals for metabolic 
regulation of medical characteristics and complications and 
exercise in patients with type 2 diabetes. The odds ratios for 
each factor in each model were calculated with Wald-type 
95% confidence intervals. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Characteristics of the study population were analyzed 
(Table 1). Among the 1,263 diabetic participants, 734 
routinely performed exercise for management of diabetes. 
The baseline characteristics of the participants revealed an 
average age of 60.6 years with a slightly higher propor-
tion of males (58.1%) than females (41.9%). There were 
no significant differences in height (163.5±8.6 cm vs. 
162.5±9.7 cm), weight (66.6±11.0 kg vs. 67.6±11.9 kg), and 
duration of diabetes (10.4±8.0 years vs. 10.5±8.5 years) be-
tween the exercise and non-exercise groups. However, there 
was a significant difference in BMI (24.9±3.1 vs. 25.5±3.6) 
between the two groups. In the exercise group, 46.6% of 
the participants had hypertension, 14.9% of the participants 
had hyperlipidemia, 63.9% of the participants had received 
education concerning diabetes. In the non-exercise group, 
53.5% of the participants had hypertension (53.5%), 18.3% 
of the participants had hyperlipidemia, and 57.5% of the 
participants had received education concerning diabetes. An 
oral agent was applied for diabetes therapy for most of the 
participants in the two groups (71.9% vs. 69.4%). 
The correlation coefficients showed an association be-
tween metabolic regulation variables and exercise manage-
ment. Most metabolic regulation variables had associations 
with exercise, except for diastolic blood pressure (DBP) 
(Table 2). Exercise management was associated with a 
decrease in the levels of systolic blood pressure (SBP), fast-
ing glucose, postprandial glucose, HbA1c, total cholesterol, 
triglyceride, and LDL. 
In order to calculate the odds ratio for exercise and 
achievement of goals for metabolic regulation in patients </p>



<p>with type 2 diabetes, univariate logistic regression was 
performed (Table 3). Regarding achievement of goals for 
metabolic regulation, significant odds ratios were observed </p>

<p>for the effect of exercise treatment on blood pressure, fasting 
glucose, postprandial glucose, HbA1c, triglyceride, HDL in 
men, and BMI in the patients with type 2 diabetes. 
Moreover, the odds ratios for exercise and complication 
incidence in patients with type 2 diabetes were also analyzed 
(Table 4). Exercise management was associated with de-
creased occurrence of cerebrovasculopathy. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Type 2 diabetes mellitus is associated with changes in 
all organ systems involved in human health including the </p>

<p>Table 1. General and clinical characteristics of the patients in the 
exercise and non-exercise groups </p>

<p>Variable 
Total 
Exercise 
Non-
exercise 
Mean±SD 
Mean±SD 
Mean±SD </p>

<p>N 
1,263 
734 
529 
Age (yr) 
60.6±11.6 
60.4±11.0 
60.9±12.5 
Height (cm) 
163.1±9.1 
163.5±8.6 
162.5±9.7 
Weight (kg) 
67.0±11.4 
66.6±11.0 
67.6±11.9 
BMI (kg/m 2 ) 
25.1±3.3* 
24.9±3.1 
25.5±3.6 
Onset (yr) 
50.1±11.1 
50.0±10.6 
50.4±11.9 
Duration of diabetes 
(yr) 
10.5±8.3 
10.4±8.0 
10.5±8.5 </p>

<p>N (%) 
N (%) 
Gender 
Male 
Female </p>

<p>734 (58.1) 
529 (41.9) </p>

<p>440 (59.9) 
294 (40.1) </p>

<p>294 (55.6) 
235 (44.4) 
Hypertension 
625 (49.5)* 342 (46.6) 
283 (53.5) 
Hyperlipidemia 
206 (16.3) 
109 (14.9) 
97 (18.3) 
Therapy of diabetes 
Diet 
48 (3.8) 
24 (3.3) 
24 (4.5) 
Oral agent 
895 (70.9) 
528 (71.9) 
367 (69.4) 
Oral agent+inulin 
236 (18.7) 
137 (18.7) 
99 (18.7) 
Insulin 
78 (6.2) 
43 (5.8) 
35 (6.6) 
Education experience 773 (61.2)* 
469 (63.9) 
304 (57.5) </p>

<p>Characteristics of the study population were investigated us-
ing medical records including disease-related data and data for 
blood sampling tests, prescription drugs, comorbidities, and 
complications. Each value is presented as the mean ± SD of the 
values measured during the survey. Statistical analysis was per-
formed by using independent t-test. *p &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>Table 2. The correlation coefficients for metabolic regulation and 
exercise in patients with type 2 diabetes </p>

<p>Variable 
Exercise 
Non-exercise 
Correlation 
coefficients 
Mean±SD 
Mean±SD </p>

<p>SBP 
123.9±14.0 
126.1±14.8 
−0.1* 
DBP 
74.3±9.9 
75.1±10.0 
−0.0 
Fasting glucose 
132.8±38.0 140.9±45.0 
−1.0* 
Postprandial glucose 
192.1±69.3 
210.1±75.5 
−0.1* 
HbA1c 
7.2±1.2 
7.6±1.6 
−0.1* 
Total cholesterol 
162.5±34.8 
167.4±40.1 
−0.1* 
Triglyceride 
131.0±84.5 
157.0±95.1 
−0.1* 
HDL 
50.1±14.5 
47.7±13.1 
0.9* 
LDL 
92.5±30.2 
99.1±58.7 
−0.1* </p>

<p>The relations between metabolic regulation (blood pressure, glu-
cose, HbA1c, total cholesterol, triglyceride, and HDL and LDL 
cholesterol) and exercise in patients with type 2 diabetes were 
analyzed. Pearson's correlation coefficients were used for as-
sessment. *p &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>Table 3. Odds ratio for exercise and achievement of goals for 
metabolic regulation in patients with type 2 diabetes </p>

<p>Variable 
Goal 
Exercise 
Non-exer-
cise </p>

<p>Odds 
ratio 
Achieve-
ment (%) </p>

<p>Achieve-
ment (%) </p>

<p>Blood pressure 
&lt;130/80 384 (52.3) 
242 (45.7) 
1.3* 
Fasting glucose 
&lt;130 
372 (53.1) 
222 (42.0) 
1.3* 
Postprandial 
glucose </p>

<p>&lt;180 
299 (40.7) 
158 (29.9) 
1.5* </p>

<p>HbA1c 
&lt;7.0 
371 (50.5) 
214 (40.5) 
1.5* 
&lt;6.5 
199 (27.1) 
114 (21.6) 
1.3* 
Total cholesterol 
&lt;200 
597 (81.3) 
394 (74.5) 
1.3 
Triglyceride 
&lt;150 
518 (70.6) 
288 (54.4) 
2.0* 
HDL 
Men 
&gt;40 
295 (67.0) 
163 (55.4) 
1.3* 
Women 
&gt;50 
138 (46.9) 
104 (44.3) 
1.3 
LDL 
&lt;100 
399 (54.4) 
274 (51.8) 
1.2 
BMI 
18.5-24.9 383 (52.2) 
241 (45.6) 
1.3* </p>

<p>Odds ratios for exercise and achievement of goals for metabolic 
regulation in patients with type 2 diabetes were calculated by 
univariate logistic regression. Achievement of goals was decided 
based on the target standards of the ADA, which were the HbA1c 
&lt; 7.0%, blood pressure &lt; 130/80 mmHg, LDL-C &lt; 100 mg/dL, 
HDL-C &gt; 40 mg/dL (male) or 55 mg/dL (female), and triglycer-
ide &lt; 150 mg/dL. Odds ratios for each factor in each model were 
calculated with Wald-type 95% confidence intervals. *p &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>Table 4. Odds ratio for exercise and complication incidence in 
patients with type 2 diabetes </p>

<p>Variable 
Exercise 
Non-exercise 
Odds 
ratio 
Complication 
incidence (%) </p>

<p>Complication 
incidence (%) </p>

<p>Neuropathy 
147 (20.0) 
110 (20.8) 
1.0 
Cerebrovasculopathy 
64 (8.7) 
65 (12.3) 
0.7* 
Cardiovasculopathy 
164 (22.3) 
121 (22.9) 
1.0 </p>

<p>Odds ratio for exercise and complication incidence in patients 
with type 2 diabetes were calculated. Univariate logistic regres-
sion was used to assess the associations between complications 
and exercise in type 2 diabetes. Odds ratios for each factor in 
each model were calculated with Wald-type 95% confidence in-
tervals. *p &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 27, No. 7, 2015 </p>

<p>
digestive, cardiovascular, renal, optic, and neural systems. 
For type 2 diabetes, the three major sources of therapy are 
adjustment of food intake, pharmacological therapy, and ex-
ercise. Among them, exercise makes up an important part of 
diabetes management and ameliorates the health of patients 
with type 2 diabetes. Therefore, the aim of present study was 
to investigate the current evidence for the effect of exercise 
on glycemic control, lipid profile, body composition, vascu-
lar health, and complications in a number of patients with 
type 2 diabetes to understand the apparent relations between 
exercise and health. 
Diabetes affects both body mass and muscle quality, 
due to poor vascular supply and peripheral neuropathy 13) . 
Among the characteristics of the study population, there was 
a significant difference in only BMI between the exercise 
and non-exercise groups in the present results. The BMI 
value represents a highly important risk factor for type 2 
diabetes, and exercise adjusts the BMI by reducing visceral 
fat and increasing the fat-free mass 7, 14)  Our results showed an association between metabolic reg-
ulation variables and exercise management. Most metabolic 
regulation variables had associations with exercise. Exercise 
management was associated with a decrease in SBP, fast-
ing glucose, postprandial glucose, HbA1c, total cholesterol, 
triglyceride, and LDL. Umpierre et al. demonstrated that 
aerobic exercise intervention improved HbA1c by 0.73% 15) . 
Furthermore, it is well known that aerobic exercise enhances 
glycemic control, raising it to a moderate level 5) . Endurance 
exercise helps to decrease LDL-C, however, it had no impact 
on HDL, total cholesterol, and triglycerides 16) . 
Moreover, in the present results concerning exercise and 
achievement of goals for metabolic regulation in patients 
with type 2 diabetes, significant odds ratios were observed 
for the effect of exercise treatment on blood pressure, fast-
ing glucose, postprandial glucose, HbA1c, triglyceride, 
HDL in men, and BMI in the patients with type 2 diabetes. 
These results are related to the effect of exercise through the 
regulation of energy metabolism in type 2 diabetes. Exercise 
induces a change in fuel usage by working muscle from 
nonesterified fatty acids to a blend of nonesterified fatty 
acids, glucose, and muscle glycogen 10) . During exercise, the 
neuroendocrine system would control fuel mobilization 12) . 
These changes induce a decrease in insulin secretion and 
increase in glucagon, catecholamine, and cortisol secre-
tion. Moreover, these neural and endocrine changes cause 
deficits in fuel availability, neural activity from the acting 
limb, visceral organs, and baroreceptor control of heart 
rate 17) . The exercise-induced increase in glucagon evokes 
glycogenolysis and gluconeogenesis as well as hepatic 
amino metabolism and fat oxidation. The decrease in insulin 
is essential to the full glycogenolytic response during exer-
cise. The exercise-induced increase in endogenous glucose 
production is important in regulation of whole-body glucose 
homeostasis 10) . 
Meanwhile, in our results concerning exercise and com-
plication incidence in patients with type 2 diabetes, exercise 
management was associated with decreased occurrence of 
cerebrovasculopathy. Previous studies reported that aerobic 
exercise had valuable effects on metabolic parameters such 
as glycemic control, fasting blood glucose level, and the </p>

<p>lipid profile, and decreased the risk factors in type 2 dia-
betes 2) . It also improved endothelial function and vascular 
complications by reducing arterial stiffness 18) . 
The present study demonstrated that exercise was as-
sociated with metabolic regulation of glycemic control, 
the lipid profile, and body composition, as well as vascular 
health and complications, in 1,263 Korean patients with type 
2 diabetes. These results from this large-scale study could 
explain the apparent relations between exercise and diabetic 
health. Therefore, these facts imply that exercise leads to a 
more healthy life and reduces disorders and complications 
in patients with type 2 diabetes. More research related to 
the importance of exercise in terms of its various beneficial 
aspects is needed for people with type 2 diabetes in other 
countries. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </p>

<p>This research was supported by a grant from the Korean 
Association of Diabetes Nurse Educators. </p>







</text></tei>