<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4362380" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>13,19 </p>

<p>Since our initial report, a number of other cell therapy groups 
have confirmed our observations and extended the range of this 
platform. For example, Rosenberg's group (Jin et al.) showed that 
G-Rex devices could be used to expand tumor infiltrating lympho-
cytes more efficiently and at a reduced cost compared with 24-well 
plates. 
12 Similarly, Chakraborty et al. expanded regulatory T cells in 
the G-Rex to numbers far in excess of those achieved using tradi-
tional tissue culture methods, 
21 while Lapteva et al. demonstrated 
superior natural killer cell expansion using the G-Rex when com-
pared with gas-permeable cell culture bags. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>However, despite these impressive results, it is unclear whether 
the G-Rex has yet reached its full potential. To address this issue and 
identify the "optimized" culture conditions, we (i) investigated the 
maximal cell output per unit of surface area that could be achieved, 
(ii) identified the optimal initial cell seeding density (cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>), 
(iii) determined the minimum media volume required to support 
maximum cell output, and (iv) characterized cell growth kinetics. 
We then integrated these findings into the design of a novel G-Rex 
M series-a fully optimized cell culture platform. 
With support from NHLBI-PACT, we have now defined optimized 
cell culture parameters that can be used in the G-Rex M series, which 
reliably produces 100-fold cell expansion in only 10 days without 
media replenishment. Importantly, these conditions are scalable, </p>

<p>Received 14 January 2014; accepted 24 March 2014 </p>

<p>Broader implementation of cell-based therapies has been hindered by the logistics associated with the expansion of clinically 
relevant cell numbers ex vivo. To overcome this limitation, Wilson Wolf Manufacturing developed the G-Rex, a cell culture flask with 
a gas-permeable membrane at the base that supports large media volumes without compromising gas exchange. Although this 
culture platform has recently gained traction with the scientific community due to its superior performance when compared with 
traditional culture systems, the limits of this technology have yet to be explored. In this study, we investigated multiple variables 
including optimal seeding density and media volume, as well as maximum cell output per unit of surface area. Additionally, we have 
identified a novel means of estimating culture growth kinetics. All of these parameters were subsequently integrated into a novel 
G-Rex "M" series, which can accommodate these optimal conditions. A multicenter study confirmed that this fully optimized cell cul-
ture system can reliably produce a 100-fold cell expansion in only 10 days using 1L of medium. The G-Rex M series is linearly scalable 
and adaptable as a closed system, allowing an easy translation of preclinical protocols into the good manufacturing practice. </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy -Methods &amp; Clinical Development (2014) 1, 14015; doi:10.1038/mtm.2014.15; published online 14 May 2014 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Center for Cell and Gene Therapy, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston Methodist Hospital, Texas Children's Hospital, Houston, Texas, USA; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Wilson Wolf Manufacturing Corporation, 
New Brighton, Minnesota, USA; </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Celgene Cellular Therapeutics, Celgene Corporation, Warren, New Jersey, USA; </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>University of Wisconsin-Madison, Waisman Biomanufacturing, 
Madison, Wisconsin, USA; </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Center for Applied Technology Development, Beckman Research Institute of City of Hope, Duarte, California, USA. Correspondence: Juan F Vera 
(jfvera@txch.org) </p>

<p>Optimizing the production of suspension cells using the 
G-Rex "M" series </p>

<p>Pradip Bajgain </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Roopa Mucharla </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, John Wilson </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, Dan Welch </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, Usanarat Anurathapan </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Bitao Liang </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, Xiaohua Lu </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, Kyle Ripple </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>, 
John M Centanni </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>, Christine Hall </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>, David Hsu </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>, Larry A Couture </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>, Shubhranshu Gupta </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Adrian P Gee </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Helen E Heslop </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Ann M Leen </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, 
Cliona M Rooney 
1 and Juan F Vera </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>ARTICle </p>



<p>Molecular Therapy -Methods &amp; Clinical Development (2014) 14015 
© 2014 The American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>Optimized cell culture in G-Rex 
P Bajgain et al. </p>

<p>resulting in similar cell output in open and good manufacturing 
practice-compliant closed system devices, which ranged in surface 
area from 5 to 500 cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. In addition, we demonstrate that glucose con-
sumption inversely correlates with cell number, providing a rapid and 
accurate means of monitoring cell expansion over time. The combina-
tion of these different benefits, which have been confirmed by both 
academic (City of Hope and University of Wisconsin-Madison) and 
commercial (Celgene Corporation) partners, maximizes the G-Rex 
performance while simplifying the manufacturing process. </p>

<p>ReSUlTS 
Identifying the maximum cell numbers per surface area in the G-Rex 
We have previously demonstrated that the expansion of antigen-
specific T cells, natural killer cells, regulatory T cells, and cell lines 
in G-Rex devices is superior to that achieved in conventional tissue 
culture-treated plates or gas-permeable bags. 
12,13,20-24 This is due to 
the increased cell viability and improved expansion facilitated by the 
gas-permeable membrane at the base of the G-Rex, which supports 
optimal gas exchange while accommodating large media volumes 
above, ensuring that nutrients are not limiting. 
13,19 To determine the 
maximum cell output that could be achieved in the G-Rex if nutri-
ents were unlimited, we seeded K562 cells at a density of 1 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>cells/cm 
2 in the G-Rex 10 device (surface area = 10 cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) or in a 24-well 
plate (surface area = 2 cm 
2 per well) and cultured them for 14 days. 
To ensure that the medium was not limiting in either condition, both 
cultures were replenished every 2-3 days with fresh medium, and 
cell growth and viability were assessed by cell counting using try-
pan blue exclusion. As shown in Figure 1a, even with unrestricted 
nutrients, cell numbers in the 24-well plates plateaued by day 6 of 
culture and remained relatively static thereafter, resulting in a total 
of 1.6 ± 0.05 × 10 
6 cells/cm 
2 on day 14. In contrast, cell numbers in 
the G-Rex 10 consistently and exponentially increased from day 3 of 
culture, peaking on day 9 at 13.8 ± 0.6 × 10 
6 cells/cm 
2 and remaining 
relatively stable thereafter (13.0 ± 0.4 × 10 
6 cells/cm 
2 on day 14). Thus, 
expansion in the G-Rex was significantly greater than that achieved 
in 24-well plates with a fold change of 13.8 ± 0.6 versus 1.4 ± 0.06, 
respectively, on day 9 (n = 3; P &lt; 0.0001) (Figure 1b). </p>

<p>Identifying the optimal seeding density to support maximum cell 
output 
Next, to determine if the maximum cell output achieved (per cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
could be increased by optimizing the initial cell density, we seeded 
G-Rex devices with K562 cells at densities ranging from 6.25 × 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>to 1 × 10 
6 cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. Cultures received a half medium change every </p>

<p>day (to remove medium as a potential limiting factor), and cell 
expansion was monitored by counting every 2-3 days over a 14-day 
culture period (n = 3 per condition). As shown in Figure 2a, G-Rex 
devices seeded at 6.25 × 10 
4 cells/cm 
2 remained in lag phase for an 
extended period of time, suggesting that a minimum threshold of 
cell-to-cell contact is required to support rapid cell growth. In con-
trast, devices seeded with cell densities ranging from 1.25 × 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>to 1 × 10 
6 cells/cm 
2 yielded maximum cell numbers of ~1.38 × 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>cells/cm 
2 by day 9 of culture (initial cells/cm 
2 to maximum cells/ 
cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>: 1.25 × 10 
5 to 13.7 ± 0.5 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>; 2.5 × 10 
5 to 14.0 ± 0.3 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>; 5 × 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>to 13.9 ± 0.7 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>; 1 × 10 
6 to 13.8 ± 0.6 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>). This suggests that 
irrespective of the initial seeding density, the maximum cell num-
ber that can be supported by the G-Rex is ~1.4 × 10 
7 cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(Figure 2a,b). As shown in Figure 2c, the maximum fold expansion 
(109.76 ± 3.9) was observed in the cultures initiated with 1.25 × 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, which was significantly higher than that achieved in any 
of the other conditions tested. This indicates that, although the 
maximum density of K562 cells is always ~1.4 × 10 
7 cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, cell 
output and fold expansion can be maximized by utilizing the lowest 
possible initial seeding density (1.25 × 10 
5 cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). </p>

<p>Identifying the optimal medium volume to support maximal cell 
expansion 
Having identified the optimal initial seeding density, we next 
wanted to define the optimal volume of medium that would sup-
port maximal cell output. Thus, we initiated cultures with 1.25 × 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>K562 cells/cm 
2 and supplemented the devices (n = 3 per condition) 
with various medium volumes ranging from 0.5 to 20 ml/cm 
2 on 
day 0. From that point on, medium was not replenished and cul-
ture performance was assessed daily by cell counting. As shown 
in Figure 3a, when using from 0.5 to 10 ml of medium per cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, 
there was a direct correlation between volume and cell expan-
sion. Thereafter, however, there was no benefit conferred by higher 
medium volumes (Figure 3a). We next explored how best to provide 
this medium volume to the cells. Figure 3b shows the different feed-
ing schedules tested, which included (i) a total of 10 ml of medium 
per cm 
2 divided into four feedings (2.5 ml/cm 
2 added on days 0, 6, 
12, and 18), (ii) 10 ml provided in two feedings (5 ml/cm 
2 added on 
days 0 and 12), and (iii) 10 ml/cm 
2 added up-front. Figure 3b shows 
that, irrespective of the feeding schedule, the maximum cell den-
sity achieved was similar (schedule (i) 11.4 ± 1.3 × 10 
6 cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>; 
schedule (ii) 11.8 ± 0.8 × 10 
6 cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>; schedule (iii) 12.9 ± 0.6 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>cells/cm 
2 (n = 3)). However, cultures that received all 10 ml/cm 
2 of 
medium up-front (schedule (iii)) grew exponentially and reached 
their maximum cell density by day 9-10 of culture, whereas addi-
tion of medium in a staggered fashion resulted in an interrupted 
growth pattern where the cells fluctuated between log and lag 
phase growth, prolonging the time until maximal cell output was 
achieved. Thus, we have demonstrated that 10 ml of medium per 
cm 
2 administered at culture setup results in the shortest time 
required to achieve maximum cell numbers. </p>

<p>Measuring glucose as a surrogate for culture performance 
Traditionally, in order to accurately quantify cell numbers, one must 
first generate a homogenous cell suspension from which to sample. 
However, since the G-Rex accommodates large media volumes 
(e.g., 10 ml/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>), cell resuspension is challenging. To address this 
issue, we sought to identify an alternate marker that could be used 
to predict cell growth. We initiated G-Rex cultures (n = 3) using 
optimal conditions (1.25 × 10 
5 K562 cells/cm 
2 with 10 ml medium/ 
cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) and measured glucose in the medium by sampling 20 µl of </p>

<p>Figure 1 G-Rex supports higher cell number per surface area. Panel 
(a) shows the expansion of K562 cells seeded at an initial density of 
1 × 10 
6 cells/cm 
2 in conventional cultureware (24-well plates) versus cell 
expansion in the G-Rex devices which were seeded at the same initial 
seeding density. A half medium change was performed every day for 
both conditions. Panel (b) shows the fold expansion of K562 cells in 
G-Rex versus 24-well plates on day 14 of culture. </p>

<p>0 
0 
3 
6 
9 </p>

<p>Days in culture </p>

<p>12 
14 
G-Rex 
24-well plate </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.0001 
P &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>9 
Cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(× 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) 
12 </p>

<p>15 
G-Rex 
Plate </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Fold expansion </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>a 
b </p>



<p>Optimized cell culture in G-Rex 
P Bajgain et al. </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy -Methods &amp; Clinical Development (2014) 14015 
© 2014 The American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>the culture supernatant daily using a standard glucometer. At the 
same time points, we resuspended the cultures and quantified cell 
numbers by cell counting using trypan blue exclusion. As shown in 
Figure 4a, the glucose concentration in the G-Rex devices progres-
sively decreased over the culture period (250.3 ± 1.5, 229.7 ± 2.9, 
158.3 ± 0.6, 45.7 ± 1.5 mg/dl on days 0, 3, 6, and 9, respectively), 
which inversely correlated with an increase in cell numbers deter-
mined by cell counting (0.125 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>, 0.9 ± 0.1 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>, 5.43 ± 0.3 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>, 
and 12.87 ± 0.6 × 10 
6 cells/cm 
2 on days 0, 3, 6, and 9, respectively). 
Based on this inverse correlation, we developed a formula to calcu-
late cell number based solely on glucose measurements. The for-
mula is as follows: </p>

<p>Estimated number of cells = 
− 
× 
× × 
[( 
) / ] [ / ] 
A B C 
D E F G </p>

<p>Where A = initial glucose concentration in medium, B = current glu-
cose concentration, C = glucose consumed to achieve maximum 
cell number, D = initial medium volume, E = total medium required 
for maximum cell number, F = maximum cell density, G = G-Rex sur-
face area (Figure 4b). 
To validate this formula, we established a culture in the G-Rex 
device with 1.25 × 10 
5 cells/cm 
2 and 10 ml medium/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. Cells were 
quantified (i) by cell counting using trypan blue exclusion, (ii) by 
flow cytometry using Trucount™ beads, and (iii) by glucose mea-
surement. As shown in Figure 4c, on day 4, we calculated that the 
device contained a total of 16.7 ± 2.6 × 10 
6 cells based on glucose 
measurement, which was similar to the number obtained by man-
ual cell counting and flow cytometric analysis (15.1 ± 1.8 × 10 
6 and </p>

<p>15.0 ± 0.75 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>; P = 0.33 and P = 0.44, respectively) (n = 3). Similar 
correlations were observed at subsequent time points. On days 8 
and 12, calculated cell numbers based on glucose depletion were 
68.3 ± 2.9 × 10 
6 and 98.3 ± 5.8 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>, respectively, which were not 
significantly different from the cell numbers as assessed by manual 
cell counting (66.1 ± 15.7 × 10 
6 and 97.1 ± 0.45 × 10 
6 ; P = 0.82 and 
P = 0.74, respectively, (n = 3)) or flow cytometry (67.4 ± 1.9 × 10 
6 and 
106.3 ± 8.5 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>; P = 0.68 and P = 0.25, respectively (n = 3)). These 
results suggest that cell numbers can be calculated accurately by 
simply measuring glucose in cell culture supernatant. </p>

<p>Multicenter validation of the G-Rex M series 
Based on these observations, Wilson Wolf Manufacturing designed 
the G-Rex M series (as seen in Figure 5a), a novel cell culture plat-
form built to incorporate these ideal culture conditions. To deter-
mine whether the results achieved in G-Rex 100M in our Center 
could be reproduced in other institutions, we conducted a multi-
center study supported by the NHLBI-Production Assistance for 
Cellular Therapies (PACT) program. We provided our optimized 
culture recommendations to both academic institutions (City of 
Hope and University of Wisconsin-Madison) and a biotech com-
pany (Celgene) and asked them to repeat our G-Rex expansion 
experiments. As illustrated in Figure 5b, when the group at Celgene 
cultured K562 cells at an initial seeding density of 1.25 × 10 
5 cells/ 
cm 
2 in a G-Rex 100M (100 cm 
2 surface area) with 1L of medium 
(10 ml/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>), the total cell number achieved by day 12 of culture 
was 1.56 × 10 
9 (15.6 × 10 
6 cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, n = 1), which was similar to our </p>

<p>Figure 2 Identifying the optimal seeding density to support maximum cell output. Panel (a) shows the expansion of K562 cells in G-Rex devices that 
were initiated with different seeding densities (0.0025, 0.125, 0.25, 0.50, and 1.0 × 10 
6 cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). A half medium change was performed every day in 
all conditions. Panel (b) shows the final cell number on day 14 of culture (reported as cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). Panel (c) shows the fold increase in the cell numbers 
on day 9. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>6.25 × 10 
4 1.25 × 10 
5 2.50 × 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Initial seeding density (cells/cm 
2 ) </p>

<p>5.0 × 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>1.0 × 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(× 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Fold expansion </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>6.25 × 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 </p>

<p>Days in culture </p>

<p>6.25 × 10 
4 /cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.25 × 10 
5 /cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2.50 × 10 
5 /cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>5.0 × 10 
5 /cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.0 × 10 
6 /cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>12 
14 </p>

<p>1.25 × 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>2.50 × 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Initial seeding density (cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>5.0 × 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>1.0 × 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(× 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>



<p>Optimized cell culture in G-Rex 
P Bajgain et al. </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy -Methods &amp; Clinical Development (2014) 14015 
© 2014 The American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>findings (12.9 ± 0.6 × 10 
6 cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, n = 3). Next, to confirm that the 
maximum cell output remained fixed regardless of the initial seed-
ing density, K562 cells were cultured at 2.5 × 10 
5 cells/cm 
2 in a G-Rex 
100M in 1L of medium and, as shown in Figure 5c, after 12 days of 
culture, our group, City of Hope, and Celgene all reported similar 
total cell numbers (1.30 × 10 
9 (n = 3), 1.46 × 10 
9 (n = 1), and 1.35 × 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>(n = 1), respectively). As expected, regardless of initial seeding den-
sity, maximum number of cells obtained was the same, confirming 
that the highest expansion is achieved by using the lowest seed-
ing density possible (Figure 5d,e). These data, collected at different 
institutions, validate the use of the G-Rex as a highly reproducible 
platform for the culture of suspension cells and confirms that our 
optimized conditions produce highly predictable results. </p>

<p>The G-Rex is linearly scalable 
To determine whether the G-Rex could operate as a scalable 
platform if the protocol was normalized by surface area, we ini-
tiated cultures using G-Rex 5 (surface area = 5 cm 
2 ), G-Rex 100M 
(surface area = 100 cm 
2 ), and G-Rex 500M (surface area = 500 cm 
2 ) 
(Figure 6a) with an initial seeding density of 1.25 × 10 
5 cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(0.625 × 10 
6 , 12.5 × 10 
6 , and 62.5 × 10 
6 total cells, respectively) in 
10 ml medium per cm 
2 (50, 1,000, and 5,000 ml total volume, respec-
tively). Culture performance was assessed every 2 days by measur-
ing glucose concentration, and cell numbers were quantified by 
counting using a traditional hemocytometer on day 10 of culture. 
As shown in Figure 6b, the total cell number achieved in the G-Rex 
5, 100, and 500 devices was 53.6 ± 2.5 × 10 
6 , 1286.7 ± 58.6 × 10 
6 , 
and 6030.6 ± 344.3 × 10 
6 (n = 3), respectively, corresponding </p>

<p>to a cell density per cm 
2 of 12.2 ± 0.4 × 10 
6 , 12.9 ± 0.6 × 10 
6 , and 
12.1 ± 0.6 × 10 
6 , respectively (Figure 6c). Thus, despite the sub-
stantial differences in surface area, the fold increase (97.4 ± 4.5-
fold, 102.9 ± 5.9-fold, and 96.5 ± 5.7-fold, respectively-Figure 6d) 
and total cell output achieved per cm 
2 were similar and entirely 
predictable, confirming the linear scalability of this platform. 
Additionally, the rate of glucose consumption in all three G-Rex 
devices was essentially identical as illustrated in Figure 6e, which 
suggests that our formula can be applied to estimate cell num-
bers, irrespective of the G-Rex surface area. </p>

<p>Semiautomated collection of cells in a closed system G-Rex 
In the manufacture of a clinical cell product, a closed cell culture 
system is preferable due to the assurance of sterility throughout 
the culture process. As illustrated in Figure 6a, the G-Rex can oper-
ate as either an open or closed system. In order to harvest the cells 
expanded in the closed system G-Rex without exposing the culture </p>

<p>Figure 3 Identifying the optimal volume of medium to support maximal 
cell expansion. Panel (a) shows the maximum cell output per cm 
2 that 
was achieved in G-Rex devices that were seeded at an initial seeding 
density of 0.125 cells/cm 
2 and supplemented with different volumes of 
medium per cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. Panel (b) shows the expansion of cultures that received 
a total of 10 ml medium/cm 
2 provided in (i) four increments of 2.5 ml/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, 
(ii) two increments of 5 ml/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, or (iii) 10 ml/cm 
2 up-front. </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
2 
5 
1 0 </p>

<p>Volume of media (ml/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>P = 0.13 </p>

<p>P = 0.0009 </p>

<p>P = 0.0021 </p>

<p>P = 0.0001 </p>

<p>P = 0.88 
P = 0.83 </p>

<p>P = 0.15 </p>

<p>15 
20 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(× 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) 
12 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>0 
0 
3 
6 
9 
13 </p>

<p>Days in culture </p>

<p>16 
20 
24 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 
10 ml/cm 
2 (2.5 ml × 4) </p>

<p>10 ml/cm 
2 (5 ml × 2) </p>

<p>10 ml/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(× 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Figure 4 Measuring glucose as a surrogate for culture performance. 
Panel (a) shows the glucose concentration in culture medium, as 
measured using a standard glucometer, and the inverse correlation 
between glucose and cell number. Panel (b) shows the formula we 
developed to calculate the number of cells in the culture based on the 
glucose concentration in the culture medium. Panel (c) shows the cell 
number obtained by: (i) hemocytometer counting, (ii) flow cytometry, 
and (iii) the glucose consumption formula. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>Hemocytometer </p>

<p>A = Initial glucose concentration in medium </p>

<p>Estimated cell number = </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 
Glucose (mg/dl) </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 
Glucose </p>

<p>Cells </p>

<p>3 
6 </p>

<p>Days in culture </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>F 
× 
× 
G 
× 
(A − B) </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B = Current glucose concentration </p>

<p>C = Glucose consumed to achieve maximum cell number </p>

<p>D = Initial medium volume 
E = Total medium required for maximum cell number 
F = Maximum cell density </p>

<p>G = G-Rex surface area </p>

<p>Flow </p>

<p>Formula </p>

<p>Days in culture 
Cell number (× 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Cell/cm 2 (× 10 6 ) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>12 
8 
4 </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>



<p>Optimized cell culture in G-Rex 
P Bajgain et al. </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy -Methods &amp; Clinical Development (2014) 14015 
© 2014 The American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>to the environment, Wilson Wolf developed the "GatheRex, " a semi-
automated system that allows the operator to drain the excess 
media present in the culture and collect cells without risk of con-
tamination. The process is divided into two stages: (i) cell concen-
trating and (ii) cell harvesting. </p>

<p>1. The GatheRex (Figure 7a,b) operates via an air pump which 
pressurizes the G-Rex device with sterile air, allowing 90% of 
the medium residing above the cells to be displaced into a 
medium collection bag. Once this process is complete, optical 
detector #1 senses the presence of air in the medium collec-
tion line, automatically stopping the pump. 
2. Prior to beginning the harvest process, the operator must 
resuspend the cells using the residual 10% of the medium by 
manually swirling the G-Rex to dislodge cells from the gas-
permeable membrane. The air pump is then reactivated, and </p>

<p>the resuspended cells are drawn into the cell collection bag. 
This phase will automatically end once optical detector #2 
detects air in the cell collection line. For more detailed instruc-
tions, see Materials and Methods and Supplementary Video. </p>

<p>Finally, to demonstrate the efficiency of cell recovery using the 
GatheRex, we seeded 3 G-Rex 100M devices with 0.125 × 10 
6 cells/ 
cm 
2 in 1 l (10 ml/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) of medium. The cells were allowed to expand 
for 10 days, then harvested using the GatheRex. Subsequently, cells 
in the (i) cell collection bag, (ii) medium collection bag, (iii) medium 
collection line, and (iv) residual cells in the G-Rex were quantified by 
manual counting using a hemocytometer. As shown in Figure 7c, 
the total cell number in the cell collection bag (1269.3 ± 91.4 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>cells) was similar to that achieved by manual cell harvesting 
(1286.7 ± 58.6 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>), with minimal loss due to cell retention in the 
medium collection bag (3.73 ± 1.2 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) or the G-Rex device/tubing </p>

<p>Figure 5 Results from our multicenter study validating our optimized G-Rex culture conditions. Panel (a) shows a schematic diagram of the G-Rex 100M 
device and protocol for cell culture. Panel (b) shows a comparison between the expansion of K562 cells obtained at Baylor College of Medicine and 
Celgene Corporation using an initial seeding density of 1.25 × 10 
5 cells/cm 
2 in a G-Rex 100M with 1 l of medium. Panel (c) shows a comparison between 
the expansion of K562 cells obtained at our Center (Baylor), Celgene Corporation, and City of Hope when G-Rex 100M devices were seeded at 2.5 × 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>cells/cm 
2 in 1L of medium. Panel (d) shows the final cell output obtained when G-Rex 100M devices were seeded at either 1.25 × 10 
5 cells/cm 
2 (Baylor 
and Celgene Corporation) or 2.5 × 10 
5 cells/cm 
2 (Baylor, Celgene Corporation, and City of Hope) in 1L of medium. Panel (e) shows the fold expansion of 
K562 cells in the experiments described in panel d. </p>

<p>1 
0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>1,000 </p>

<p>10,000 
Celgene </p>

<p>Media: 1,000 ml (10 ml/cm 
2 ) </p>

<p>Day 0 
D ay 12 </p>

<p>G-Rex100 M 
G-Rex100 M </p>

<p>Seeding densities </p>

<p>b) 1.25 × 10 
7 cells (0.125 × 10 
6 /cm 
2 ) </p>

<p>c) 2.50 × 10 
7 cells (0.25 × 10 
6 /cm 
2 ) </p>

<p>b) 1.42 × 10 
9 cells (14.2 × 10 
6 /cm 
2 ) </p>

<p>c) 1.45 × 10 
9 cells (14.5 × 10 
6 /cm 
2 ) </p>

<p>Baylor </p>

<p>Celgene 
Baylor 
City of hope </p>

<p>Cell number (× 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>1,000 </p>

<p>10,000 </p>

<p>Cell number (× 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Days in culture </p>

<p>0 
12 </p>

<p>Days in culture </p>

<p>0.125 
0.250 </p>

<p>Initial cells/cm 
2 (× 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>0.125 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Final cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(× 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) 
15 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>0.250 </p>

<p>Initial cells/cm 
2 (× 10 
6 ) </p>

<p>P = 0.004 </p>

<p>P = 0.86 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Fold expansion </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Cell harvest </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
c </p>

<p>d 
e </p>



<p>Optimized cell culture in G-Rex 
P Bajgain et al. </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy -Methods &amp; Clinical Development (2014) 14015 
© 2014 The American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>(0.76 ± 0.13 × 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>). These results confirm the efficiency of cell collec-
tion achieved using the GatheRex. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
In this study, we evaluated different variables that contribute to 
optimal G-Rex performance and incorporated these observations 
into the design of the G-Rex M series, which can accommodate the 
optimized conditions required to support maximum cell output. The 
use of G-Rex M devices in combination with our newly optimized 
protocol allows the operator to initiate a suspension culture with a 
small number of cells (1.25 × 10 
5 cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) and achieve a 100-fold 
expansion in only 10 days using just 10 ml of culture medium per 
cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-significantly exceeding that previously achieved in tissue 
culture plates or bags. 
13,20,21,25 Furthermore, since cells were supple-
mented with medium as a one-time up-front addition, we were </p>

<p>able to utilize glucose depletion as a means to predict culture per-
formance and quantify total cell numbers at different time points. 
Importantly, the optimal culture conditions, initially established in 
a small scale G-Rex device with a surface area of 5 cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, were linearly 
scalable provided that initial seeding cell density and media volume 
were normalized by surface area. Finally, the results achieved at our 
center have been validated in a multicenter study, confirming this 
as a robust platform for cell expansion. 
In previous studies, we and others have demonstrated the clear 
superiority of the G-Rex over conventional cultureware with respect 
to the expansion of a variety of suspension cell types (antigen-
specific and primary T cells, cell lines, tumor infiltrating lympho-
cytes, natural killer cells, and regulatory T cells). 
24,26,27 Importantly, in 
each of these studies, the functional capacity of the generated cells 
was comparable or superior to those generated by conventional </p>

<p>Figure 6 The G-Rex is linearly scalable. Panel (a) shows schematic diagrams of the G-Rex 5, 100M, and 500M (to scale). Panel (b) shows the final cell 
density (cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) achieved in a G-Rex 5, G-Rex-100, and G-Rex 500 after 12 days of culture. Panel (c) shows the expansion profile of K562 cells in three 
different G-Rex devices (G-Rex 5, 100, and 500) between days 0 and 12. Panel (d) shows the fold expansion of the cells cultured in G-Rex 5, 100, and 500 
devices. Panel (e) illustrates the glucose consumption by K562 cells cultured in G-Rex 5, G-Rex 100, and G-Rex 500 over 13 days of culture. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>Day 0 
D ay 10 
0 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>1,000 </p>

<p>10,000 
G-Rex 5 </p>

<p>G-Rex 100 </p>

<p>G-Rex 500 </p>

<p>G-Rex 5 </p>

<p>G-Rex 100 </p>

<p>G-Rex 500 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 
Glucose (mg/dl) </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>Cell number (× 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Cell/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(× 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Fold expansion </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
G-Rex 5 
G-Rex 100 </p>

<p>b 
c </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>G-Rex 500 
0 
2 
4 
6 </p>

<p>Days in culture </p>

<p>8 
1 0 </p>

<p>G-Rex 5 
G-Rex 100 
G-Rex 500 </p>

<p>G-Rex 5 </p>

<p>G-Rex 100 </p>

<p>G-Rex 500 </p>

<p>12 </p>



<p>Optimized cell culture in G-Rex 
P Bajgain et al. </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy -Methods &amp; Clinical Development (2014) 14015 
© 2014 The American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>means. 
12,21,22 However, it remained unclear whether the G-Rex was 
being used to its full potential, precipitating the current study to 
identify (i) the optimal seeding cell density, (ii) the maximal cell out-
put that could be achieved, (iii) the volume of medium that would 
support maximal cell growth, and (iv) cell growth kinetics. 
By first evaluating different cell seeding densities, we were able 
to identify the threshold K562 cell number required to support 
cell expansion. The minimum number of cells per cm 
2 required to 
support cell expansion is likely to differ depending on cell size, as 
smaller cells need a higher initial seeding density to ensure adequate </p>

<p>cell-to-cell contact. However, once the optimal seeding density has 
been identified, this number remains constant for any particular cell 
type. Additionally, as long as nutrients are not a limiting factor, and 
seeding density is above the critical threshold, the maximum num-
ber of cells per cm 
2 that can be obtained is the same. This finding 
suggests that the system can reach its maximum potential by initiat-
ing the culture with the lowest seeding density possible. 
Another variable that we examined in the current study was the 
optimal medium volume required for maximum output. In our previ-
ous studies, we established that the superior cell growth supported 
by the G-Rex was due in large part to the gas-permeable silicone 
membrane at the base of the device, which allows optimal exchange 
of oxygen and carbon dioxide. 
12,13,19 As a result, gas exchange remains 
unaffected by medium height, allowing the addition of large media 
volumes which cannot be supported by conventional cultureware. 
This increased volume not only provides additional nutrients to sup-
port cell proliferation but also serves as a buffer to dilute cellular 
metabolic and toxic by-products. 
19,20 To define the optimal media 
volume, we added volumes ranging from 0.5 to 20 ml/cm 
2 and 
observed a correlation between volume and cell numbers obtained. 
However, this relationship plateaued at 10 ml/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, identifying this 
as the minimum volume required to achieve maximum cell output. 
Furthermore, contrary to what would be expected, the maximum 
cell output was achieved more rapidly (~day 10 of culture) when 
the entire volume of medium was provided at the initiation of the 
culture, rather than periodically replenished. This is likely due to the 
fact that an up-front medium addition delivers a steady rather than 
fluctuating supply of nutrients to the cells, allowing them to remain 
in log phase growth for a longer period of time. An additional advan-
tage to this sole medium addition at culture initiation is the reduc-
tion in required culture manipulations and the risk of contamination, 
unlike conventional cultures which require frequent feeding. 
Large cell cultures systems traditionally require mechanical 
assistance, either by rocking or stirring of the culture device (as in 
stirred tank and WAVE bioreactors) or by perfusion of the media (as 
in hollow fiber bioreactors) to allow uniform distribution of nutri-
ents needed to promote cell growth. 
26,28-35 The G-Rex is unique in its 
ability to support cell cultures with large media volumes in a static 
environment without resorting to mechanical agitation. This phe-
nomenon is likely caused by a thermal differential between the heat 
source (the incubator) and the medium. Therefore, due to convec-
tion, warmer medium adjacent to the walls of the G-Rex will move 
toward the core, displacing colder media to the periphery. This cycle 
is perpetuated, resulting in a homogenous mixing of the medium 
without disturbing the cells growing on the silicone membrane. This 
also has the secondary benefit of facilitating cell harvesting since as 
much as 90% of the medium can be removed from the G-Rex with-
out disrupting the cell layer on the silicone base. Subsequently, the 
final cell product can be resuspended in a concentrated form in the 
small volume of remaining medium. 
The G-Rex is the only cell culture system capable of supporting 
significant cell expansion (100-fold) with a single up-front addi-
tion of medium. We demonstrated this to be true not only for K562 
cells but also for primary T cells genetically modified to express a 
chimeric antigen receptor (Supplementary Figure S1). This unique 
characteristic allows not only a cost-effective use of resources but 
also the measurement of elements within the media that predict 
the kinetics of cell growth. For example, we observed an inverse 
correlation between cell number and glucose consumption during 
logarithmic phase cell growth. Therefore, by measuring glucose lev-
els at culture initiation and monitoring depletion over time, one can 
calculate the number of cells at any given time. Sampling medium </p>

<p>Figure 7 Automated collection of cells in a closed G-Rex system. 
Panel (a) shows the setup of "GatheRex" draining the excess medium 
to concentrate the cells: (1) pump, (2) 0.2-µm sterile filter, (3) medium 
collection button, (4) medium line clamp, (5,6) medium/supplements 
input ports, (7) medium sampling port, (8) medium collection port, 
(9) medium bag, (10) medium, and (11) medium line optical detector. 
Panel (b) shows the GatheRex harvesting the concentrated cells: 
(12) resuspended cells, (13) cell collection button, (14) cell line clamp, (15) 
cell collection port, (16) cell collection bag, (17) harvested cells, and (18) 
cell line optical detector. Panel (c) shows a comparison in cell recovery 
achieved when cells are collected manually versus by the GatheRex. 
To confirm the absence of cells in cell collection tubing, the medium 
collection bag or the G-Rex following cell collection with the GatheRex, 
each component was washed with media and residual cells were 
harvested and counted. </p>

<p>0 
Cell bag 
Media bag </p>

<p>Manual 
GatheRex </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>5,6 10 </p>

<p>2 
7 8 
4 3 
1 
11 
9 
10 </p>

<p>14 
16 </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>13 
18 </p>

<p>3.7 </p>

<p>1,286.7 
1,296.3 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>G-Rex + 
tubing </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>Cell number (× 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>900 </p>

<p>1,200 </p>

<p>1,500 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>



<p>Optimized cell culture in G-Rex 
P Bajgain et al. </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy -Methods &amp; Clinical Development (2014) 14015 
© 2014 The American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>

<p>for the assessment of nutrient and/or metabolic waste concentra-
tion is much simpler than other methods of calculating cell number, 
and results achieved are comparable to conventional cell counting 
by trypan blue exclusion or flow cytometry. Importantly, glucose 
concentration was the same irrespective of where the sample for 
analysis was drawn from, confirming the homogeneous nature of 
the medium in the G-Rex. 
The optimal G-Rex cell culture conditions identified through 
our study led to the design of the G-Rex M series that accom-
modates 10 ml/cm 
2 medium. We validated the robustness of 
this optimized platform in a PACT-sponsored multicenter study 
involving both academic and commercial partners. Finally, from 
a commercial perspective, we demonstrated that the optimized 
culture conditions and results were linearly scalable and adapt-
able as a closed system, facilitating not only the development of 
novel cell therapies but also the clinical translation of cell-based 
therapeutics. </p>

<p>MATeRIAlS AND MeTHODS 
Cell lines </p>

<p>The human immortalized chronic erythroid leukemia cell line, K562, the 
prostate cancer cell line, DU145, and human embryonic kidney cell line, 
293T, were obtained from the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC, 
Rockville, MD). K562 cells were maintained in complete RPMI 1640 (Hyclone 
Laboratories, Logan, UT) containing 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine 
serum (Hyclone Laboratories), 1% GlutaMAX (Gibco by Life Technologies 
Corporation, Grand Island, NY), and 1% Pen Strep (Gibco by Life Technologies 
Corporation). DU145 and 293T cells were maintained in complete Iscove's 
modified Dulbecco's media (Gibco by Life Technologies Corporation), 10% 
fetal bovine serum (Hyclone Laboratories), and 1% GlutaMAX. Cells were 
maintained in a 37°C incubator at 5% CO 2 . </p>

<p>Culture devices </p>

<p>For the expansion experiments, K562 cells were cultured in complete RPMI 
and conventional tissue culture-treated 24-well plates (BD Biosciences, 
Bedford, MA) and in G-Rex devices (Wilson Wolf Manufacturing, New 
Brighton, MN) at the stated seeding densities. </p>

<p>Glucose measurement </p>

<p>About 0.5 ml of culture supernatant was obtained from the G-Rex devices 
without disturbing the cells. ACCU-CHEK Active glucose test strips (Roche 
Diagnostics, Indianapolis, IN) were mounted onto the ACCU-CHEK Active 
glucose meter (Roche Diagnostics) and 20 µl of the supernatant sample was 
added on the sample loading area on the test strip. Glucose concentrations 
were calculated and reported as mg of glucose/dl supernatant. </p>

<p>Quantification of cells </p>

<p>Hemocytometer. For quantification by cell counting, samples were taken 
from 24-well plates and G-Rex devices after cultures had been uniformly re-
suspended by mixing using a 3 ml transfer pipette (BD Biosciences, Franklin 
Lakes, NJ). Ten microliters of the homogeneous cell samples were mixed at 
a 1:1 ratio with Trypan Blue (Sigma Aldrich, St Louis, MO), then 10 µl of the 
cell-Trypan Blue mixture was loaded on a hemocytometer (Hausser Scientif-
ic, Horsham, PA) and visually examined under an inverted light microscope 
(Olympus, Center Valley, PA) and counted using trypan blue exclusion to 
distinguish between live and dead cells. Counts from two 1 × 1 mm quad-
rants were averaged and multiplied by 1 × 10 
4 × dilution factor to obtain 
number of cells/ml. </p>

<p>Flow cytometer. Cells were resuspended by vigorous mixing using a 25 ml 
serological pipette (BD Biosciences). Then 1 ml of resuspended cells was 
transferred into a 5 ml polystyrene tube (BD Biosciences, Durham, NC), 
washed with 1× phosphate-buffered saline (Sigma Aldrich), spun for 5 
minutes at 400g, and the supernatant discarded. The cell pellet was subse-
quently resuspended in 100 µl phosphate-buffered saline, 50 µl of Count-
Bright absolute counting beads (Life Technologies Corporation) was added </p>

<p>and each tube was vortexed briefly before acquiring the samples. Gallios 
Flow Cytometer (Beckman Coulter, Brea, CA) was used to acquire the data 
by gating on the beads. Cells were quantified using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Kaluza analysis</rs> soft-
ware (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Beckman Coulter</rs>), and the formula provided by the bead manufac-
turer was used to calculate the absolute number of cells (Life Technologies 
Corporation). </p>

<p>Formula. Cells present in the culture were quantified by using the formula 
(Figure 4b) based on the glucose concentration in the culture medium at 
the time the samples were acquired. </p>

<p>Chromium release assay </p>

<p>Chimeric antigen receptor-modified PSCA-directed T cells were generated 
as previously described, 
36 and their cytotoxicity specificity was measured in 
a standard 6-hour </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>Cr release assay, 
36 using E:T ratios ranging from 40:1 to 
5:1, with DU145 and 293T cells as targets. </p>

<p>Cell harvesting using the GatheRex </p>

<p>1. The GatheRex (Figure 7) is a device that pumps air (1) through a 
0.2-µm sterile filter (2). Once activated (orange →) (3), the clamp on 
the medium collection line (4) is opened while the cell collection line 
(14) remains closed. The G-Rex is pressurized, allowing 90% of the me-
dium residing above the cells to be displaced through the collection 
port (8) and into the collection bag (9). Once this process is complete, 
optical detector #1 (11) senses the presence of air in the medium col-
lection line, automatically stopping the pump. At this stage, the system 
is ready to initiate cell harvest. 
2. Prior to beginning the harvest process, the operator must resuspend 
the cells using the residual 10% of the medium present in the G-Rex. 
Cell collection is initiated by activating the system (blue →) (13), 
which will clamp the medium collection line and open the cell col-
lection line (14). The pump is then reactivated, and the resuspended 
cells are drawn through the cell collection port into the cell collection 
bag (16). This phase will automatically end once optical detector #2 
(18) detects air in the cell collection line. 
3. (Optional) At this point, the operator may wish to "rinse" the G-Rex 
to ensure collection of residual cells in the tubing and flask. The 
wash is activated by opening the clamp on the media collection line 
(orange ←) allowing a portion of the medium in the collection bag 
to flow back into the G-Rex. Once the system is rinsed, the pump can 
be reactivated (blue →), opening the clamp and allowing the residual 
cells to enter the cell collection bag. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>All in vitro data are represented as mean ± SD unless otherwise indicated. 
Data were analyzed by using the unpaired Student's t-test to compare the 
differences between the two experimental groups after appropriate log-
transformation. A P value of &lt;0.05 was accepted as an indicator of significant 
difference. </p>

<p>CONFlICT OF INTeReST </p>

<p>Present research in Center for Cell and Gene Therapy receives support from Celgene 
Corporation, of which authors B.L. and X.L. are employees, but the current work was 
not supported by Celgene. J.W. and D.W. are employees, and J.F.V. is a scientific advisor 
for Wilson Wolf Manufacturing, which partially supported this work by providing some 
G-Rex prototypes and reagents. J.W., D.W., and J.F.V. have joint patents on the G-Rex 
technology. </p>

<p>ACKNOWleDGMeNTS </p>

<p>This work was supported in part by the Production Assistance for Cellular Therapies 
(PACT) program (NHLBI contract #HHSN268201000007C), P01CA094237 and 
CA094237 from the NIH and a SCOR award from the Leukemia and Lymphoma 
Society. We also appreciate the support of the Adrienne Helis Malvin Medical Research 
Foundation through its direct engagement in the continuous active conduct of medi-
cal research in conjunction with Baylor College of Medicine. J.F.V. is supported by an 
Idea Development Award from the Department of Defense Prostate Cancer Research 
Program (no. W81XWH-11-1-0625). Finally, we appreciate the shared resources pro-
vided by the Dan L Duncan Cancer Center support grant P30CA125123. </p>



<p>Optimized cell culture in G-Rex 
P Bajgain et al. </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy -Methods &amp; Clinical Development (2014) 14015 
© 2014 The American Society of Gene &amp; Cell Therapy </p>



</text></tei>