<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4812582" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. The aim of the present study was to determine the 
usefulness of the positron emission tomography/computed 
tomography (PET/CT) with 
18 F-fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG) in 
the detection of recurrence or metastasization of differentiated 
thyroid carcinoma (DTC) in patients with abnormal thyro-
globulin levels and negative findings on the 
131 I-diagnostic 
whole-body scanning (dWBS). Fifteen patients with DTC, 
abnormal thyroglobulin levels, and negative 
131 I-dWBS 
findings were scanned using the 
18 F-FDG PET/CT. Positive 
diagnosis was based on postoperative histologic findings, and 
clinical and imaging follow-up results obtained in the subse-
quent 6 months. In addition, preoperative and postoperative 
thyroglobulin levels were compared. Using the findings of 
18 F-FDG PET/CT and data on confirmed positive diagnosis, 
sensitivity and positive predictive value (PPV) were calcu-
lated. Sensitivity and PPV of PET/CT in detecting recurrence 
or metastasisization of DTC were 93.30 and 91.40%, respec-
tively. Furthermore, postoperative thyroglobulin levels were 
markedly lower compared to the preoperative levels (respec-
tively, 4.67±1.71 vs. 58.53±18.34 ng/ml; p&lt;0.05). PET/CT scan 
with 
18 F-FDG is an informative technique for the detection 
of recurrent or metastasized DTC in patients with abnormal 
thyroglobulin levels and negative </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>The incidence of thyroid carcinoma is the highest among head 
and neck carcinomas. Differentiated thyroid carcinoma (DTC) 
accounts for 90% of thyroid cancers, with 20% of patients 
experiencing disease relapse, which decreases survival 
rates (1). A timely diagnosis of thyroid cancer recurrence is 
critical. Evaluation of serum thyroglobulin and </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>I-diagnostic </p>

<p>whole-body scanning (dWBS) are the most commonly 
employed detection techniques. However, 15-20% of patients 
with abnormal thyroglobulin levels show negative findings on </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>I-dWBS (2,3). Furthermore, it is difficult to differentiate the 
recurrence of DTC from cicatricial tissue by computed tomog-
raphy (CT), positron emission tomography (PET), magnetic 
resonance imaging (MRI), or ultrasound (4). Subsequently, 
PET/CT has been introduced in the diagnostics of DTC, since 
PET/CT shows metabolic activity and anatomical abnormali-
ties, characteristic of the tumour. 
Between December 2005 and June 2013, 
18 F-fluorodeoxy-
glucose (FDG) PET/CT was utilized to diagnose 15 patients 
with DTC. The results identified 
18 F-FDG PET/CT as a valu-
able detecting technique for the recurrence or metastasization 
of DTC. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Patients. Fifteen patients with DTC were admitted to the 
Department of Nuclear Medicine of the Xuzhou Central 
Hospital (Xuzhou, China) between December 2005 and 
June 2013. There were 3 male and 12 female patients, aged 
25-58 years, with a median age of 46 years (Table I). The 
patients were diagnosed with DTC, and underwent total or 
subtotal thyroidectomy. 
The pathological types comprised 14 cases of papillary 
carcinoma and 1 case of follicular carcinoma. The patients 
received 1 or several courses of postoperative treatment with 
131 I: 1 patient was treated once, 4 patients were treated twice, 
6 patients were treated three times, 2 patients were treated 
four times, 1 patient was treated six times, and the remaining 
patient was treated eight times. At the follow up after the 
treatment, elevated levels of thyroglobulin (&gt;20 ng/ml) and 
negative 
131 I-dWBS findings were present in each of these 
patients. Subsequently, tumour recurrence or metastasization 
was suspected. The patients underwent PET/CT examination. 
Patients continued receiving thyroidin pills following surgery, 
including during PET/CT, to avoid deterioration of the tumour. </p>

<p>18 F-FDG PET/CT imaging. The Philips GXL 16 PET/CT scan-
ning instrument (Philips Medical Systems, Inc., Cleveland, OH, 
USA) was used. The patients fasted for ≥6 h prior to scanning. 
Strict blood glucose levels (non-diabetic patients, &lt;6.1 mmol/l; 
patients with diabetes, &lt;8.3 mmol/l) were maintained. The 
patients were intravenously administered 270-370 MBq of </p>

<p>Usefulness of PET/CT in the diagnosis of recurrent or 
metastasized differentiated thyroid carcinoma </p>

<p>CUN-ZHI LU 
1 , SU-SHENG CAO 
2 , WEI WANG 
2 , JUN LIU 
2 , NING FU 
1 and FENG LU </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Departments of 
1 Nuclear Medicine and </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Thyroid Surgery, Xuzhou Central Hospital, Xuzhou, Jiangsu 221009, P.R. China </p>

<p>Received October 7, 2015; Accepted February 15, 2016 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/ol.2016.4229 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Dr Su-Sheng Cao, Department of Thyroid </p>

<p>Surgery, Xuzhou Central Hospital, 199 Liberation of South Road, 
Xuzhou, Jiangsu 221009, P.R. China 
E-mail: cssxzsy@126.com </p>

<p>Key words: </p>

<p>18 F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography/ 
computed tomography, differentiated thyroid carcinoma, tumour 
recurrence, metastasization </p>

<p>LU et al: </p>

<p>18 F-FDG PET/CT TO DETECT RECURRENT OR METASTASIZED DTC </p>



<p>Table I. Demographic and clinical data of 15 study patients. </p>

<p>Patient, 
Age, Histological type 
PET/CT 
Surgery/follow-up 
Preoperative 
Postoperative 
no. 
Gender years of the tumour 
diagnosis 
confirmation 
thyroglobulin, ng/ml thyroglobulin, ng/m </p>

<p>1 
Female 36 
Papillary 
2 cervical 
2 in neck 
53.36 
4.34 
carcinoma 
lymph nodes 
2 
Female 45 
Papillary 
2 cervical 
2 in neck 
34.51 
2.47 
carcinoma 
lymph nodes 
3 
Male 
33 
Papillary 
2 cervical 
2 in neck 
61.74 
5.02 
carcinoma 
lymph nodes 
4 
Female 48 
Follicular 
4 cervical 
4 in neck 
66.85 
5.77 
carcinoma 
lymph nodes 
5 
Female 25 
Papillary 
3 cervical 
2 in neck 
56.27 
4.73 
carcinoma 
lymph nodes 
6 
Female 58 
Papillary 
4 cervical 
3 in neck 
72.02 
6.08 
carcinoma 
lymph nodes 
7 
Male 
55 
Papillary 
2 cervical 
2 in neck 
42.25 
3.34 
carcinoma 
lymph nodes 
8 
Female 29 
Papillary 
2 cervical 
2 in neck 
58.13 
4.86 
carcinoma 
lymph nodes 
9 
Female 52 
Papillary 
2 cervical 
2 in neck 
49.61 
3.53 
carcinoma 
lymph nodes 
10 
Female 40 
Papillary 
1 cervical 
1 in neck 
26.68 
1.18 
carcinoma 
lymph node 
11 
Female 50 
Papillary 
5 cervical 
4 in neck 
83.43 
6.71 
carcinoma 
lymph nodes 
12 
Female 42 
Papillary 
3 cervical 
3 in neck 
92.62 
7.29 
carcinoma 
lymph nodes 
13 
Female 52 
Papillary 
3 cervical 
3 in neck 
63.45 
5.43 
carcinoma 
lymph nodes 
14 
Female 49 
Papillary 
3 in the lung and 
3 in lung and 
475.03 
-
carcinoma 
2 in the mediastinum 2 in mediastinum 
15 
Male 
46 
Papillary 
Negative 
1 in neck 
46.02 
-
carcinoma </p>

<p>PET, positron emission tomography; CT, computed tomography. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Cervical lymph node metastasis revealed by positron emission tomography/computed tomography (PET/CT) scanning. (A) CT imaging shows no 
significant neck mass. (B) PET imaging shows two lumpy abnormal radioactive concentration shadows on the right side of the neck. (C) PET/CT imaging 
shows two abnormal fluorodeoxyglucose hypermetabolism areas in the sternocleidomastoid region of the right side of the neck, which were considered 
lymph node metastases. </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY LETTERS 11: 2420-2423, 2016 </p>



<p>18 F-FDG (4.4 MBq/kg). After 60 min and prior to the scan-
ning, the patients were required to empty their bladders. 
Collection ranges were from the basilar part to the 
proximal femur. The 16-slice helical CT scanning param-
eters were 140 kV, 320 mA, with flat sweeping. Data were 
analyzed by image fusion following iterative reconstruction, 
obtaining coronal, sagittal and cross-sectional CT, PET and 
PET/CT fusion images. The PET/CT images were reviewed 
independently by two radiologists who calculated a standard-
ized uptake value of radioactive hot lesion. A standardized 
uptake value of ≥2.5 localized in metastatic regions was 
considered as indicative of tumour metastasization. </p>

<p>Diagnostic criteria of tumour recurrence or metastasization. 
Based on the positive results of PET/CT scanning, the lesions 
located in the neck underwent surgical excision, and post-
operative histopathology was carried out. The patients were 
monitored for their serum thyroglobulin levels for 1 month. If 
the lesions were located in the organs where surgical excision 
was problematic, the status was determined by clinical situa-
tion and the follow-up imaging results within 6 months after 
the initial PET/CT examination. </p>

<p>Data analysis. The PET/CT images were qualitatively ranked 
as true positive, false negative, and false positive. Sensitivity 
and positive predictive value (PPV) for the diagnosis of recur-
rence and metastasization of DTC were calculated. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. The <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.0</rs> statistical software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS, Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) was used for statistical analysis. Data 
were presented as mean ± standard deviation. The differences 
were tested using the paired t-test. P&lt;0.05 was considered to 
indicate a statistically significant difference. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>In 14 patients, PET/CT scanning had a sensitivity of 93.33%. 
The 14 patients were found to have 40 tumour recurrences 
or metastases, of which 35 were cervical lymph node metas-
tases (Fig. 1). The tumours were excised and were identified 
by postoperative pathology as being tumour metastases in 
32 cases and as inflammatory changes in 3 cases. Thus, PPV 
comprised 91.43%. In 1 patient, 5 lumps were located in the 
lungs and the mediastinum. No biopsy or surgical intervention 
were conducted in this patient. The lumps increased during 
the follow up for 6 months, confirming their metastatic nature. 
One patient had negative PET/CT findings and developed 
neck lumps after 6 months of follow up, which were confirmed 
as tumour metastases. 
A total of 13 patients with preoperative serum thyro-
globulin levels of 58.53±18.34 ng/ml underwent surgery. Their 
postoperation serum thyroglobulin levels were 4.67±1.71 ng/ml 
(p&lt;0.05 vs. preoperative). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Examination of thyroglobulin levels and </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>I-dWBS following 
treatment is important for tumour monitoring and the detection 
of metastasization in DTC (5). Elevated thyroglobulin levels 
indicate recurrence or metastasization, resulting in </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>I-dWBS </p>

<p>scans being able to locate the tumour. When 
131 I-dWBS 
shows negative findings, B-mode ultrasound, CT, MRI, PET 
or other imaging techniques are used to localize recurrent or 
metastatic tumour. The first three methods are mainly used 
to locate the tumour by anatomical abnormalities, while 
PET reveals the tumour through metabolic abnormalities (6). 
Each of these techniques has its advantages and limitations. 
By contrast, PET/CT imaging can simultaneously reveal 
metabolic status and anatomical location of the lesion, thus 
combining the advantages of PET and CT (7). This technique 
is useful in difficult diagnoses, such as that for postoperative 
scars or nodules, which lack typical benign or malignant signs. 
Malignant tumours consume glucose at 10-fold higher rates 
than normal or scar tissue, and this feature enables precise 
differential diagnosis in those cases (8). Therefore, combined 
functional and morphological examination during PET/CT 
can improve the ability to detect recurrent and metastatic 
tumours (9). 
The diagnostic efficiency of 
18 F-FDG PET/CT imaging 
in the postoperative follow up of patients with DTC depends 
on patient selection, sample size, thyroglobulin levels, and 
thyroid-stimulating hormone levels (10). Sensitivity and PPV 
for recurrence and metastasization of DTC range from 66 
to 93.3% and from 87.5 to 100%, respectively (11-13). These 
values are significantly higher than those achieved by B-mode 
ultrasound, CT, MRI, or PET alone. In the present study, 
sensitivity and PPV were 93.33 and 91.43%, respectively, 
for patients with positive thyroglobulin levels and negative 
131 I-dWBS findings. This is in agreeement with previous 
findings (14-19). In such patients, metastatic tumour is more 
aggressive, which leads to elevation of the sensitivity of 
18 F-FDG PET/CT imaging. However, tumours that uptake 
iodine do not uptake FDG, therefore, 
18 F-FDG PET/CT cannot 
fully replace 
131 I-dWBS and should not be recommended for 
routine screening for recurrent or metastatic DTC. 
In conclusion, findings of the present study indicate that 
18 F-FDG PET/CT imaging is an informative technique for the 
detection of recurrence or metastasization of DTC in patients 
with positive thyroglobulin levels and negative </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>I-dWBS. </p>



<p>LU et al: </p>

<p>18 F-FDG PET/CT TO DETECT RECURRENT OR METASTASIZED DTC </p>





</text></tei>