<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4327276" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Endodontic retreatment requires removal of pre-existing 
endodontic filling material and disinfection of the root canal 
system. This is accomplished during chemomechanical 
reinstrumentation. In order to remove filling materials without 
damage to the tooth, chemical solvents are used to solubilise 
gutta-percha 
1,2,5 . Orange oil, eucalyptol, xylol, chloroform, 
halothane, and rectified turpentine have all been used as 
adjuncts to remove endodontic filling materials 
13,15,16,21 . 
Retreatment has also been done combining heat with a 
solvent, in order to remove filling material from thermafil-
obturated teeth 
33 . It has been shown that ultrasonic 
instrumentation required significantly less time to remove 
root fillings than hand instrumentation 
16 Others authors have 
shown that rotary instruments remove more filling materials 
during endodontic retreatment than manual instruments 
3,12,17 . </p>

<p>Additionally, Nd:YAP laser was shown to be effective for 
root canal preparation during retreatment because it 
preserves the root canal dentin walls and does not cause 
temperature raise in the root, which could potentially harm 
the periodontal tissues </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>. Furthermore, orange oil has been 
shown not only to be effective 
11 , but also to be less cytotoxic 
than eucalyptol, xylol, chloroform and halothane </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>, during 
endodontic retreatment procedures. 
Studies have reported that it is essential to remove all 
root canal filling material from anatomic ramifications and 
dentinal tubules to ensure cleaner root canal walls </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>. This 
facilitates chemomechanical preparation and antimicrobial 
dressing to access all ramifications of the entire root canal 
system during retreatment and decrease the residual 
microbial population 
4,6,28,30,32 . In spite of all different 
retreatment strategies, studies have shown that it is not 
possible to obtain root canal walls completely free of debris </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>J Appl Oral Sci. 2008;16(1):24-9 </p>

<p>and residual infection </p>

<p>14, 31. </p>

<p>The aim of the present study was to evaluate, by 
scanning electron microscopy (SEM), the efficacy of 
chloroform, orange oil and eucalyptol as adjuncts during 
endodontic retreatment on the removal of obturation material 
from dentinal tubules. </p>

<p>MATERIAL AND METHODS </p>

<p>Forty human maxillary canines were obtained from the 
tooth bank of the Federal Fluminense University. Teeth with 
straight roots were selected and then radiographed to ensure 
that they had a single canal, mature apex and less than 5 
degree curvature. 
Teeth were sectioned to provide remaining roots 
measuring 21 mm in length. Working length was set at 20 
mm and the root canals were prepared using K-files according 
to a crown-down technique. Instrumentation began with K-
file size 80, and progressively smaller K-files were used to 
prepare to a final apical size #30 K-file (Dentsply Maillefer, 
Ballaigues, Switzerland) 
Canals were irrigated with 2 mL 5.25% NaOCl (Formula 
&amp; Ação Farmácia, São Paulo, SP, Brazil) at each change of 
instrument. When instrumentation was completed, canals 
were irrigated with 20 mL 10% citric acid (Formula &amp; Ação 
Farmácia, São Paulo, SP, Brazil) to remove smear layer, 
followed by rinsing with 20 mL distilled water. 
The canals were dried with paper points before obturation 
with gutta-percha and Endofill sealer (Dentsply, Petrópolis, 
RJ, Brazil). The root canals were obturated using the lateral 
compaction technique employing standardized gutta-percha 
master cones (Dentsply, Petrópolis, RJ, Brazil), finger 
spreaders and accessory cones. Excess gutta percha was 
removed at the canal entrance with heated instruments, 
before vertical compaction was used to condense gutta 
percha at the coronal root third. The coronal access cavities 
of the specimens were sealed with a temporary filling material 
(Coltosol; Coltene-Whaledent, Cuyahoga Falls, OH, USA). 
Radiographs of each specimen were taken to ensure 
homogeneity of root canal obturation, lack of voids and 
proper length of the root canal filling material, before storage 
at 37ºC in 100% humidity (artificial saliva) for 3 months. The 
teeth were assigned to four groups of ten roots each, 
according to the solvent employed: Group I: Control (no 
solvent), Group II: chloroform (Fórmula &amp; Ação Farmácia 
de Manipulação, São Paulo, SP), Group III: orange oil 
(Fórmula &amp; Ação Farmácia de Manipulação, São Paulo, SP), 
and Group IV: eucalyptol (Fórmula &amp; Ação Farmácia de 
Manipulação, São Paulo, SP). In the control group, the filling 
material was not removed. 
A reservoir for solvents was created within the coronal 
root third using #2 (0.70 mm) and #3 (0.09 mm) Gates Glidden 
drills to a depth of 3 mm beyond the canal entrance. 0.4 mL 
of each solvent was delivered with a syringe to sample 
reservoirs. After 2 minutes, to allow for solvent penetration, 
crown-down instrumentation was initiated to remove gutta 
percha using a size 60 K-file. Every 30 seconds, canal debris </p>

<p>was removed by rinsing with 2.0 mL 5.25 % NaOCl using a 
30-gauge irrigation needle, before adding solvent and using 
sequentially smaller diameter files to remove gutta percha 
using a reaming motion. The endpoint of instrumentation 
was determined when a #30 K-file reached the working 
length. The total time required to remove the filling material 
was 5 minutes. 
Apical patency was ensured with #10 K-file before final 
irrigation with 10 mL of citric acid and 10 mL with 5.25% 
NaOCl. All canals were then dried with paper points. 
Longitudinal grooves were prepared on the external 
surface of all roots before splitting the samples into two 
halves. One half of each sample was mounted on an SEM 
specimen holder before placement in a vacuum chamber 
and coating with a 20-nm thick gold-palladium layer. 
Microscopic analyses were done using a scanning electron 
microscope (DSM940, ZEISS, Oberkochen, Germany). SEM 
images were obtained with an acceleration tension of 20kV, 
in modes of secondary (SE) and back-scattered (BSE) 
electrons. All sample preparation procedures were performed 
by the same operator. 
For evaluation purposes, each specimen was divided 
into cervical, middle and apical thirds. A single evaluator, 
who was blinded to the specimen location, examined only 
the central region of the middle and apical thirds. SEM 
micrographs of the center of the middle and apical third 
regions were taken at X500 magnification that corresponded 
to an area of 367.2 µm 
2. The number of open dentinal tubules 
per area unit was quantified using <rs id="software-1" type="software">image Pro Plus</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">4.5</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Media Cybernetics</rs>, Silver Spring, MD, USA). The number 
of dentinal tubules free of filling materials per mm2 was 
statistically evaluated by Kruskall-Wallis test (p&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The median of the numbers of dentinal tubules free of 
filling materials per mm 
2 is displayed on Table 1. Although 
there was a tendency for orange oil to yield a larger number 
of dentinal tubules free of filling material per mm 
2 compared 
to chloroform and Eucalyptol, this difference was not 
statistically significant (p&lt;0.05) for both the middle and the 
apical root canal thirds. However, all three tested solvents 
had significantly more visible dentinal tubules free of filling 
materials than the control group (p&lt;0.05). 
Figures 1 and 2 represent SEM micrographs of the 
evaluated areas, in the middle and apical root thirds 
respectively, showing dentinal tubules free of filling materials 
after the endodontic retreatment using the tested solvents. 
White arrows in these figures point to open dentinal tubules. </p>



<p>COMPARATIVE SEM EVALUATION OF THREE SOLVENTS USED IN ENDODONTIC RETREATMENT: AN EX VIVO STUDY </p>

<p>FIGURE 1-Representative SEM micrographs of samples from the middle root third: A) Control, B) Chloroform, C) Eucalyptol, 
D) Orange oil. Note the presence of only few open dentinal tubules (arrows). Original magnification X500 </p>

<p>Third 
Control 
Chloroform 
Orange oil 
Eucalyptol </p>

<p>Mean 
Mean 
Mean 
Mean </p>

<p>(Range) 
(Range) 
(Range) 
(Range) </p>

<p>Number 
Middle 
1332.25 
6160.46* 
6332.35* 
6286.98* </p>

<p>of tubules 
(242) 
(2027) 
(1335) 
(1345) </p>

<p>Apical 
1053.12 
3552.05** 
3575.53** 
3501.29** </p>

<p>(135) 
(876) 
(1000) 
(946) </p>

<p>TABLE 1-Means of the number of dentinal tubules free of filling materials per mm 
2 in each group </p>

<p>*, **: No statistically significant difference (p&gt;0.05) using Kruskall-Wallis test. </p>



<p>SCELZA M F Z, COIL J M, MACIEL A C de C, OLIVEIRA L R L, SCELZA P </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The retreatment of a previously filled root canal is 
indicated when there is a persistent periradicular disease 
resulting from coronal microleakage, incomplete cleaning 
and shaping, and complex anatomy. Procedures for removal 
of root fillings include the use of stainless steel hand files, 
heat, ultrasonic, laser, rotary systems and 
solvents </p>

<p>2,9,14,22,28,29,31 </p>

<p>. In this study, 40 maxillary canines were 
chosen because of their round anatomic shape, which would 
facilitate the removal of the filling material. 
Complications during retreatment procedures may be 
accounted for by the resistance of the filling material to </p>

<p>instrument penetration </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>. In this context, solvents serve as 
useful adjuncts to the action of the mechanical action 
instruments. 
Although many endodontic retreatment studies have 
been reported, little clinical data are available regarding the 
time required to keep root canals soaked in solvents during 
retreatment. Removal of gutta-percha using hand files with 
or without solvent can be time-consuming, especially when 
the root canal filling material is well condensed 
20. A mean 
time of 1.5-10.8 minutes have been reported in laboratorial 
studies for retreatment of canals filled with laterally 
condensed gutta-percha and sealer 
6, 18, 20, 30 . Our study 
allowed 5 minutes to remove the obturation material. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2-Representative SEM micrographs of samples from the apical root third: A) Control, B) Chloroform, C) Eucalyptol, 
D) Orange oil. Note the presence of only few open dentinal tubules (arrows). Original magnification X500 </p>



<p>COMPARATIVE SEM EVALUATION OF THREE SOLVENTS USED IN ENDODONTIC RETREATMENT: AN EX VIVO STUDY </p>

<p>In this study, samples were maintained at 100% humidity 
at 37°C for 3 months to simulate oral conditions </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>, prior to 
retreatment. However, studies have used different storage 
times, ranging from 2 to 3 weeks 
6,20 . It is conceivable that 
different storage methods and length of storage time may 
affect the cleaning of the root canal system. 
The results indicated that there was no significant 
difference in the number of dentinal tubules free of filling 
materials among the tested solvents. Our study corroborates 
the results published elsewhere, which revealed that it is 
not possible to obtain root canal walls completely free of 
debris 
14, 31 . 
SEM studies have been proved to allow examination of 
dentinal tubules with respect to the presence of filling 
materials 
6,26,27 . Complex root canal systems can make it 
difficult to clean the root canal system efficiently. In the 
present study, SEM micrographs showed dentinal tubules 
free of filling material remnants. The apical third presented 
the smallest number of clean dentinal tubules, compared to 
the middle root third. 
The present work employed 10% citric acid to remove 
smear layer 
23 prior to root canal system obturation. Other 
studies have examined sealer penetration into dentinal 
tubules after smear layer removal 
10,19 . These studies have 
found a greater penetration of filling materials into dentinal 
tubules and enhanced material adhesion to the canal walls. 
Such a mechanical plug may further become a problem during 
retreatment procedures. 
Our results revealed that there was no difference in the 
number of clean dentinal tubules amongst the different tested 
solvents, in the middle or apical thirds. This is no consistent 
with the findings of a previous study, which showed that 
chloroform was more effective than eucalyptus oil in 
dissolving root canal sealers </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>. Another study compared 
chloroform with 18 essential oils, including eucalyptol and 
orange oil 
15 . These studies evaluated the capacity of 
dissolving sealers using standard ring moulds and gutta 
percha cone fragments, respectively. These authors found 
that only chloroform and rectified turpentine oil dissolved 
gutta-percha completely. The results of the present study 
were different because SEM was used only to evaluate 
dentinal tubules regarding the presence of root filling 
material. 
Chloroform, halothane and turpentine oil have been 
described as cytotoxic solvents 
1 . In a recent study, orange 
oil was found to be more biocompatible than chloroform 
and eucalyptol </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>. In the present study orange oil performed 
equally to chloroform and eucalyptol. Therefore, orange oil 
can be recommended as a suitable alternative to those 
products. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>During endodontic retreatment of root canals filled with 
gutta-percha and sealer, orange oil, chloroform and 
eucalyptol performed equally for removal of the filling 
material from dentinal tubules, but superior to retreatment </p>

<p>without the use of a solvent. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This research was supported by FAPERJ (Process # E-
26171593-02). </p>





<p>SCELZA M F Z, COIL J M, MACIEL A C de C, OLIVEIRA L R L, SCELZA P </p>





<p>COMPARATIVE SEM EVALUATION OF THREE SOLVENTS USED IN ENDODONTIC RETREATMENT: AN EX VIVO STUDY </p>

</text></tei>