<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4791326" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Toll-like receptor 3 (TLR3) recognizes viral double-stranded 
RNA. It stimulates pro-inflammatory cytokine and interferon 
production. Here we reported the expression of a novel iso-
form of TLR3 in human astrocyte cell lines whose message is 
generated by alternative splicing. The isoform represents the 
N-terminus of the protein. It lacks many of the leucine-rich re-
peat domains, the transmembrane domain, and the intra-
cellular Toll/interleukin-1 receptor domain of TLR3. Type I in-
terferons (interferon- and interferon-) induced the expression 
of this isoform. Exogenous overexpression of this isoform in-
hibited interferon regulatory factor 3, signal transducers and 
activators of transcription 1, and Inhibitor of kappa B  signal-
ing following stimulation. This isoform of TLR3 also inhibited 
the production of chemokine interferon--inducible protein 10. 
Our study clearly demonstrated that the expression of this iso-
form of TLR3 was a negative regulator of signaling pathways 
and that it was inducible by type I interferons. We also found 
that this isoform could modulate inflammation in the brain. 
[BMB Reports 2015; 48(12): 696-701] </p>

<p>Toll-like receptor 3 (TLR3) is a pattern recognition receptor 
(PRR) that recognizes double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) during vi-
ral replication in endolysosomal compartments or on cell sur-
faces (1). Recognition of viral RNA by TLR3 triggers several in-
tracellular signaling pathways that lead to activation of mi-
togen-activated protein kinases (MAPKs), nuclear factor B 
(NF-B), and interferon regulatory factor 3 (IRF3), resulting in 
the production of pro-inflammatory cytokines and type I inter-
ferons (IFNs) (2, 3). TLR3 is expressed in various kinds of cells, 
including dendritic cells, fibroblasts, intestinal epithelial cells, 
and astrocytes. Depending on the cell type, TLR3 represents </p>

<p>different cellular response (4-6). Within distinct immunological 
milieu of the brain, TLR3 has been found to be necessary for 
the secretion of TNF-, IL-12p40, and IL-6 in murine micro-
glial cells after being stimulated by polyinosinic-polycytidylic 
acid (poly(I:C)) (7). In viral infections such as experimental in-
fection with simian immunodeficiency virus and human im-
munodeficiency virus encephalitis, TLR3 expression is upregu-
lated, leading to the induction of active innate immune re-
sponses in the brain (8). Following intracerebroventricular ad-
ministration of poly(I:C) to mimic viral infection in the central 
nervous system, TLR3 signaling is activated, resulting in con-
textual memory and enhanced susceptibility to seizures (9, 10). 
Similar effects of viral infection on brain function have been 
reported in encephalitis and associated epileptic activity (11-
13). These reports suggest that inflammation as innate immune 
response is important in neurological disorders and in anti-vi-
ral defenses. 
Astrocytes perform a variety of physiological functions such 
as forming the blood-brain barrier, transporting nutrients, and 
maintaining ion balances for the normal physiology of the 
brain. In addition, astrocytes play an important role in diseases 
related to neuro-inflammation (14, 15). Astrocytes express nu-
merous PRRs to allow for the recognition of diverse patho-
gen-associated molecular patterns (PAMPs) (16-18). We have 
previously reported that TLR3 is expressed in astrocytes and 
that its activation induces the expression of IL-6 (19). We have 
reported that an isoform of TLR3 lacking 192 bp is produced 
by alternative splicing in primary astrocytes and astrocyte cell 
lines (20). However, the mechanistic role of this isoform is 
unclear. In this study, we report a novel isoform of TLR3 that is 
induced by type I IFNs in astrocyte cell lines. It downregulated 
poly(I:C)-induced TLR3 signaling. This isoform might have an 
immune-modulatory function during brain inflammation and 
other pathological conditions. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>An isoform of TLR3 is expressed in human astrocyte cell lines </p>

<p>To investigate whether TLR3 has additional splice variants, we 
examined the expression level of TLR3 transcripts using differ-
ent sets of primers corresponding to the 5'-or the 3'-UTR. 
A172 cells expressed a novel isoform of TLR3 that contained </p>

<p>An inhibitory TLR3 isoform is inducible by IFNs 
Jin-Won Seo, et al. </p>

<p>697 
http://bmbreports.org 
BMB Reports </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Identification of a novel splice-
isoform of human TLR3 in A172 cells. 
(A) Schematic diagram of wild type 
TLR3 gene with depiction of primer sets 
used for RT-PCR. (B) RT-PCR analysis 
of the wild type TLR3 and its novel 
isoform using mRNA from A172 cells. 
(C) Amino acid sequences of TLR3 and 
the novel TLR3 isoform. (D) cDNA and 
protein sequences of wild type TLR3 
and its novel isoform. Numbers on the 
left indicate nucleotides, and numbers 
in parentheses on the right indicate 
amino acids. The asterisks indicate the 
portion missing from the isoform. The 
TLR3 isoform is related to wild type 
TLR3 by alternative splicing. The splice 
donor (gt) and acceptor (ag) sequences 
at positions 966-967 and 2,586-2,587, 
respectively, are in boxes. The splicing 
event introduces a frame-shift, resulting 
in the novel TLR3 isoform with a pre-
dicted protein sequence containing 299 
amino acids shown in the grey box. </p>

<p>an open reading frame of 900 bp in length, including a stop 
codon. We obtained similar results using three different sets of 
primers (Fig. 1A, B). This isoform lacked the region of 966-
2,587 bp encoding a considerable number of the leucine rich 
repeat (LRR) domains, the transmembrane domain, and the in-
tracellular toll/IL-1 receptor (TIR) domain responsible for signal 
transduction (Fig. 1C). The C-terminal 11 amino acids of this </p>

<p>TLR3 isoform differed from those of the TLR3 wild type as a re-
sult of a frame-shift introduced by alternative splicing. The al-
ternative splicing occurred between the donor "GT" (region of 
967-968 bp) and acceptor "AG" (region of 2,586-2,587 bp), in-
troducing a frame-shift mutation and a stop codon "TGA" at re-
gion of 2,621-2,623 bp, resulting in translation of a 299 amino 
acid polypeptide (Fig. 1D). </p>

<p>An inhibitory TLR3 isoform is inducible by IFNs 
Jin-Won Seo, et al. </p>

<p>698 BMB Reports 
http://bmbreports.org </p>

<p>Fig. 2. The TLR3 isoform is a natural 
transcript in human astrocyte cell lines 
that is upregulated by type I IFNs. Both 
A172 (human glioblastoma) and NHA 
(normal human astrocyte) cells express 
wild type TLR3 and the novel isoform 
of TLR3. (A) A172 cells were treated with 
IFN- and IFN- for 24 h. (B) NHA 
cells were treated with IFN- for the in-
dicated time periods. M denotes a 1-kb 
ladder as nucleotide size marker. The 
experiments were repeated five times 
and a representative result is shown. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Overexpression of the TLR3 iso-
form downregulates poly(I:C)-induced 
activation of IRF3, STAT1, and IB in 
A172 cell lines. A172 cells were trans-
fected with pCMV-Myc/TLR3 isoform 
and stimulated with 25 g/ml of poly 
(I:C) for the indicated time periods. Total 
cell lysates were analyzed by immuno-
blotting using anti-phospho-IRF3 (Ser396), 
anti-IRF-3, anti-phospho-IB (Ser32), an-
ti-IB, anti-phospho-STAT1 (Tyr701), or 
anti-tubulin antibody. The experiments 
were repeated twice and a representa-
tive result is shown. </p>

<p>IFN-/ increases the transcript of the novel isoform of TLR3 
in astrocyte cell lines </p>

<p>Upon viral infection, TLR3 will produce type I IFNs via activat-
ing IRF3. To assess the effect of type I IFNs on the transcription 
of the novel isoform of TLR3, A172 and NHA cells were treat-
ed with IFN- or IFN-. As a result, the transcription of this 
novel isoform of TLR3 was increased (Fig. 2A) after treatment 
with IFN- or IFN-. The transcript of this novel isoform of 
TLR3 was detectable starting at 3 h post treatment. Its level 
was increased until 24 h after IFN- treatment (Fig. 2B). </p>

<p>Overexpression of the novel isoform of TLR3 inhibits TLR3 
signaling </p>

<p>Next, we determined whether the expression of the novel </p>

<p>TLR3 isoform would influence TLR3 signaling pathway in-
duced by poly(I:C). Our results revealed that the poly(I:C) treat-
ment induced phosphorylation of interferon regulatory factor 3 
(IRF3), Inhibitor of kappa B  (IB), and signal transducers 
and activators of transcription 1 (STAT1) via TLR3 signaling in 
the control group (Fig. 3). When the isoform was exogenously 
overexpressed, phosphorylation levels of IRF3, IB, and 
STAT1 were significantly reduced compared to the mock trans-
fection control (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Expression of the novel isoform of TLR3 affects the production 
of interferon--inducible protein 10 (IP-10) </p>

<p>To determine the effect of expression of the novel isoform of 
TLR3 on the secretion of antiviral chemokines, IP-10 was se-</p>

<p>An inhibitory TLR3 isoform is inducible by IFNs 
Jin-Won Seo, et al. </p>

<p>699 
http://bmbreports.org 
BMB Reports </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Poly(I:C)-induced secretion of IP-10 was decreased by ex-
ogenous expression of the novel isoform of TLR3 in a dose-de-
pendent manner. A172 cells were transiently transfected with pCMV-
Myc/TLR3 isoform (0.3-1.2 g), incubated for 24 h, and stimulated 
with 10 g/ml of poly(I:C) for 12 h. Mock vector was transfected 
at 0.3 g. Culture supernatants were harvested to measure the 
production of IP-10 by ELISA. Data represent mean ± S.E. *P ＜ 
0.05, **P ＜ 0.01, ***P ＜ 0.001. </p>

<p>lected as the major cytokine induced by TLR3 signaling. Upon 
ligation with poly(I:C), TLR3 stimulated IP-10 secretion via 
JAK/STAT pathway. Consistent with the inhibitory effect of 
TLR3 isoform expression on the activation of IRF3, IB, and 
STAT1 (Fig. 3), the production of IP-10 was decreased in a 
dose-dependent manner in cells exogenously overexpressing 
the TLR3 isoform (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Endosomal TLRs such as TLR3, TLR7, and TLR9 can recognize 
nucleic acids derived from viruses and bacteria. They play im-
portant roles in innate immunity as well as pathological con-
ditions (21). These TLRs can recognize self-DNA and RNA as-
sociated with several autoimmune diseases such as rheuma-
toid arthritis, systemic lupus erythematosus, and psoriasis (22, 
23). Normally, self-nucleic acids are not detected by endo-
somal TLRs because there are several regulatory mechanisms, 
including receptor localization, association with accessory pro-
teins, and proteolytic cleavage (24). For example, protease-
mediated regulation of TLR depends on the type of protease 
that is active. When TLR9 is cleaved by acidic pH-dependent 
protease such as cathepsins or asparagine endopeptidase, pro-
duced C-terminal cleaved fragments of TLR9 can augment 
TLR9 activation. On the other hand, when TLR9 is cleaved by 
neutral pH-dependent proteases, produced N-terminal frag-
ments of TLR9 can inhibit TLR9 signaling (25, 26). 
In the brain, TLR3 is abundantly expressed in microglia and 
astrocytes. TLR3 is active in anti-viral immune responses and 
some autoimmune diseases such as multiple sclerosis and ex-
perimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (27, 28). Recent </p>

<p>studies have shown that TLR3 cleavage by cysteine proteases 
will produce C-or N-terminal fragments that are involved in 
the activation of the receptor (29-31). 
In this study, we found a novel isoform of TLR3 generated 
by alternative splicing in astrocyte cell lines. This novel iso-
form has only LRRs 1-10. It lacks the entire transmembrane 
and cytoplasmic TIR domains. The expression of this isoform 
was induced by the treatment with type I IFNs. Interestingly, 
when the isoform was exogenously overexpressed, poly(I:C)-
induced TLR3 activation was significantly reduced. Moreover, 
the secretion of IFN-responsive chemokine IP-10 was decreased 
in cells overexpressing this isoform. These negative regulatory 
effects of this TLR3 isoform may be caused by competition for 
ligand binding because this TLR3 isoform has dsRNA binding 
sites (LRR1 and LRR3), whereas it lacks the cytoplasmic TIR 
domain required for signal transduction (25, 32). 
In summary, our results demonstrated that the expression of 
a novel isoform of TLR3 was induced by type I IFNs and that 
its protein product negatively regulated TLR3 activity. Therefore, 
this novel isoform of TLR3 might have immune-modulatory 
function in brain inflammation and some pathological condi-
tions. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Reagents </p>

<p>Poly(I:C) was purchased from Invivogen (San Diego, CA, USA). 
Recombinant human IFN- and IFN- were purchased from 
ProSpec (East Brunswick, NJ, USA). Anti-phospho-IRF3 (Ser396), 
anti-IRF-3, anti-phospho-IB (Ser32), anti-IB, and anti-
phospho-STAT1 (Tyr701) antibodies were purchased from Cell 
Signaling Technology Inc. (Danvers, MA, USA). Anti-tubulin 
antibody was purchased from Abcam (Cambridge, MA, USA). </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>Human glioblastoma cell line A172 was obtained from ATCC 
and cultured in DMEM medium containing 10% fetal bovine 
serum (FBS) and penicillin-streptomycin (100 units/ml and 100 
g/ml, respectively) at 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C in a humidified 5% CO2 incubator. 
Normal human astrocyte (NHA) cells were cultured in DMEM/ 
F-12 medium containing 10% FBS, 10 g/ml of blasticidin, 0.2 
g/ml of puromycin, and penicillin-streptomycin (100 units/ml 
and 100 g/ml, respectively) at 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C in a humidified 5% CO2 
incubator. </p>

<p>RT-PCR </p>

<p>A172 cells (1 × 10 
6 cells per well) were treated with or with-
out IFN- or IFN- (500 units/ml, respectively) for 24 h. NHA 
cells (5 × 10 
5 cells per well) were treated with IFN- (500 
units/ml). After incubation, total RNA was isolated from A172 
or NHA cells using RNeasy Mini kit (Qiagen, Santa Claris, CA, 
USA). A total of 2 g of total RNA was used to synthesize 
cDNA with random primers and M-MLV Reverse Transcriptase 
(Invitrogen). RT-PCR was performed using ex Taq polymerase </p>

<p>An inhibitory TLR3 isoform is inducible by IFNs 
Jin-Won Seo, et al. </p>

<p>700 BMB Reports 
http://bmbreports.org </p>

<p>(Takara, Tokyo, Japan). The following primers were used for 
RT-PCR: F (5'-GAA AGG CTA GCA GTC ATC CAA-3'), R1 
(5'-CAA AAA TAG GCC TGA AAT AAG-3'), R2 (5'-TAT GAA 
TAA ACA AAT TAT AAC AC-3'), R3 (5'-TTT CTC CTT TGC 
TAA TTG AAT-3'). The following PCR conditions were used: 
denaturation at 94 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C for 1 min, annealing at 50 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C for 30s, and 
extension at 72 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C for 2 min. After 30 cycles, an additional ex-
tension at 72 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C for 10 min was performed. These primers were 
designed based on human TLR3 mRNA sequences obtained 
from GenBank (accession No. NM_003265.2). </p>

<p>Cloning of the TLR3 isoform </p>

<p>Total RNA was isolated from A172 cells (1 × 10 
6 cells) using 
RNeasy Mini kit (Qiagen). A total of 3 g of total RNA was 
used for cDNA synthesis with M-MLV Reverse Transcriptase 
(Invitrogen) using forward (5'-G GCC ATG GAG GCC ATG 
AGA CAG ACT TTG CCT TGT ATC-3') and reverse (5'-CCG 
GAA TTC TCA ATA GCT TGT TGA ACT GCA TGA TGT-3') 
primers. A vector for TLR3 isoform expression was constructed 
by inserting PCR-amplified cDNA digested with SfiI and EcoRI 
into pCMV-Myc vector (Clontech, Palo Alto, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Western blot </p>

<p>A172 cells were cultured in 6-well plates at 3 × 10 
5 cells per 
well and transiently transfected with 1 g of pCMV-Myc 
(mock) or pCMV-Myc/TLR3 isoform for 24 h. Cells were stimu-
lated with 25 g/ml of poly(I:C) for indicated time periods. 
After stimulation, cells were harvested and lysed with lysis buf-
fer (150 mM sodium chloride, 1.0% NP-40, 50 mM Tris, pH 
8.0) containing protease and phosphatase inhibitor cocktails 
(GenDEPOT, TX, USA). Cell lysates were centrifuged and su-
pernatants were stored at -80 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C. Protein concentrations of ly-
sates were measured using Bradford protein assay. Fifty micro-
grams of each protein sample was separated by 12% SDS-
PAGE and transferred onto a nitrocellulose membrane (GE 
Healthcare, Waukesha, WI, USA). Membranes were incubated 
with anti-phospho-IRF3 (Ser 398), anti-IRF-3, anti-phospho-IB 
(Ser 32), anti-IB, anti-phospho-STAT1 (Tyr 701), or anti-tu-
bulin antibody. Protein bands were detected using a West-save 
up western blot detection kit (Ab Frontier, Seoul, Korea). </p>

<p>Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) </p>

<p>A172 cells were cultured in 6-well plates at 3 × 10 
5 cells per 
well and transiently transfected with 0.3-1.2 g of pCMV-
Myc/TLR3 isoform using Fugene 6 reagent according to in-
structions of the manufacturer (Roche, Basel, Switzerland). 
Mock vector (pCMV-Myc) was transfected at 0.3 g per well. 
After 24 h, cells were stimulated with 10 g/ml of poly(I:C) for 
12 h. Culture supernatants were harvested and stored at -80 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C. 
ELISA was performed with a human cytokine IP-10 assay kit 
(BD Bioscience, San Jose, CA, USA). The optical density (O.D.) 
at 450 nm was determined. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>One-way ANOVA was performed for statistical analysis using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">PRISM</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.01</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software, Inc.</rs>., La Jolla, CA, 
USA). P ＜ 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by the National Research Foundation 
of Korea (NRF) grant funded by the Korea government (MEST) 
(No. 2012R1A4A1029061). </p>



</text></tei>