<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4280887" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT: The metabotropic glutamate (mGlu) receptors are crit-
ically involved in enabling the persistency of forms of synaptic plasticity 
that are believed to underlie hippocampus-dependent memory. These 
receptors and in particular, mGlu5, are also required for hippocampus-
dependent learning and memory. In the hippocampus, synaptic plastic-
ity is one of the mechanisms by which spatial information may be 
represented. Another mechanism involves increased firing of place cells. 
Place cells increase their firing activity when an animal is in a specific 
spatial location. Inhibition of factors that are essential for synaptic plas-
ticity, such as N-methyl-D-aspartate receptors or protein synthesis, also 
impair place cell activity. This raises the question as to whether mGlu 
receptors, that are so important for synaptic plasticity and spatial mem-
ory, are also important for place cell encoding. We examined location-
dependent place cell firing i.e. place fields. We observed that antago-
nism of mGlu5, using 2-methyl-6-(phenylethynyl) pyridine (MPEP) had 
no effect on place field profiles in a familiar environment. However, in 
a novel environment mGlu5-antagonism affected long-term place field 
stability, reduced place cell firing and spatial information. These data 
strongly suggest a role for mGlu5 in the mechanisms underlying infor-
mational content and long-term stability of place fields, and add to evi-
dence supporting the importance of these receptors for hippocampal 
function. Group I metabotropic glutamate (mGlu) receptors that consist of 
the receptor subtypes 1 (mGlu1) and 5 (mGlu5) are critically 
involved in persistent hippocampal synaptic plasticity and spatial 
learning (Balschun and Wetzel, 1998, 2002; Balschun et al., 1999, 
2006; Naie and Manahan-Vaughan, 2004, 2005; Manahan-Vaughan </p>

<p>and Braunewell, 2005; Bikbaev et al., 2008; Pop-
kirov and Manahan-Vaughan, 2011). 
Whereas the activation of N-methyl-D-aspartate 
(NMDA) receptors is critically required for the induc-
tion phase of synaptic plasticity (Dudek and Bear, 
1992; Bear and Malenka, 1994; Hrabetova and Sack-
tor, 1997; Manahan-Vaughan, 1997; Hrabetova et al., 
2000; Raymond et al., 2000), the activation of mGlu 
receptors is crucial for the maintenance phase of plas-
ticity (Manahan-Vaughan, 1997, 2000; Bikbaev et al., 
2008). Furthermore, induction of both persistent (&gt;24 
h) LTP (Manahan-Vaughan et al., 2003), and the 
acquisition of spatial memories (Riedel et al., 2000) 
leads to increased hippocampal expression of mGlu5. 
In addition, dendritic protein synthesis is triggered by 
mGlu5 (Huber et al., 2000, 2001). This suggests that 
mGlu5 contributes to synaptic restructuring that 
upholds persistent information storage and bridges the 
gap between acute NMDA receptor activation and the 
triggering of downstream cascades necessary for protein 
synthesis (Mukherjee and Manahan-Vaughan, 2013). 
Hippocampal place cells exhibit a spatially restricted 
firing pattern, and are active only when animals are in 
a specific location of an environment (O'Keefe and 
Dostrovsky, 1971). There are two main features of 
place cells that make them important in the spatial 
memory system. First, place cells tend to be stable by 
repeated exposure to the same environment. This kind 
of stability can last for days, weeks, or even months 
(Thompson and Best, 1990). Second, when an animal 
enters a new environment, the firing pattern of place 
cells changes in an unpredictable manner (known as 
remapping). Place cells may shift their firing rate, 
change their place field location or switch on or off. 
Once place fields are newly formed, they are preserved, 
and can be stable regardless of their activity or lack of 
it in another environment (Bostock et al., 1991; Wil-
son and McNaughton, 1993). 
Long-term stability of newly formed place fields is 
impaired by blocking NMDA receptors (Kentros 
et al., 1998), blocking protein synthesis in the brain 
(Agnihotri et al., 2004), or deleting the transcription 
factor zif268/egr1 (Renaudineau et al., 2009), all of 
which are essential for long-term synaptic plasticity. 
On the other hand, afferent stimulation that induces 
LTP, abolishes existing place fields, creates new place 
fields, and rearranges the temporal relationship within 
neighboring place cells (Dragoi et al., 2003), all of </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribu-
tion-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and distribution in 
any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-com-
mercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. 
1 Department of Neurophysiology, Medical Faculty; 
2 International 
Graduate School for Neuroscience, Ruhr University Bochum, Germany 
Additional Supporting Information may be found in the online version of 
this article. 
Grant sponsor: German Research Foundation (DFG). 
*Correspondence to: Denise Manahan-Vaughan, Department of Neuro-
physiology, Medical Faculty, Ruhr University Bochum, MA 4/150, Uni-
versitaetsstr. 150, 44780 Bochum, Germany. 
E-mail: denise.manahan-vaughan@rub.de 
Accepted for publication 3 June 2014. 
DOI 10.1002/hipo.22314 
Published online 6 June 2014 in Wiley Online Library 
(wileyonlinelibrary.com). </p>

<p>V C 2014 THE AUTHORS. HIPPOCAMPUS PUBLISHED BY WILEY PERIODICALS, INC. </p>

<p>HIPPOCAMPUS 24:1330-1340 (2014) </p>

<p>which are consistent with "remapping" upon entering a novel 
environment. 
The abovementioned findings show interesting parallels with 
synaptic plasticity: NMDA receptors are crucial for the induc-
tion phase of synaptic plasticity (Dudek and Bear, 1992; Mul-
key and Malenka, 1992), and transcription and protein 
synthesis are necessary in the very late phases (Frey et al., 
1988; Manahan-Vaughan et al., 2000). Given the importance 
of mGlu receptors and in particular mGlu5 for persistent syn-
aptic plasticity, this provokes the question as to whether 
mGlu5 plays a role in place field formation and/or stability. In 
this study, we addressed this issue by examining changes in 
place field stability, firing frequencies and spatial selectivity by 
blocking mGlu5 during navigation in spatial environments. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Subjects </p>

<p>The present study was carried out in accordance with the 
European Communities Council Directive of September 22, 
2010 (2010/63/EU) for care of laboratory animals. All experi-
ments were performed according to the guidelines of the Ger-
man Animal Protection Law and were approved by the North 
Rhine-Westphalia State Authority (Bezirksamt, Arnsberg). All 
efforts were made to reduce the number of animals used. 
Male Wistar rats (8-to 9-weeks old) were housed individually 
and maintained on a 12-h light/12-h dark cycle. The animals 
were given sufficient food to maintain 90% of their free-feeding 
weight and ad libitum access to water. They were handled indi-
vidually for 10 min per day, 1 week before surgery. </p>

<p>Electrodes and Microdrives </p>

<p>One lightweight microdrive (Axona, St. Albans, UK) was 
chronically implanted in each rat (8-9 weeks at the time of sur-
gery). Each microdrive held four tetrodes made of four twisted 
bundles of Formvar-coated electrodes (25 mm) platinum-iridium 
wires (A-M systems, USA). The tetrodes were strengthened 
respectively with cyanoacrylate glue and inserted into a cannula, 
which was attached to the microdrive. One full rotation of the 
mechanical drive produces a vertical movement of 200 mm with-
out rotating the cannula or the electrodes. </p>

<p>Surgery </p>

<p>Each rat was chronically implanted with a microdrive as fol-
lows. Animals were anaesthetized with an initial dose of sodium 
pentobarbital (52 mg kg </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>, i.p.) and placed in a stereotactic unit. 
Body temperature was monitored throughout the operation and 
the anaesthetic dose was adjusted to maintain surgical anesthesia. 
A hole was drilled (1.2 mm diameter) over the right hippocam-
pus. The tetrodes were placed in the cortex just above the CA1 
hippocampal subfield (bregma 23.8 mm AP, 3.0 mm ML, and 
1.5 mm DV). They were lowered into the CA1 cell layer in the </p>

<p>screening phase after surgery, by turning the microdrive. So as to 
protect exposed part of tetrodes between the skull surface and the 
bottom of the cannula, a sleeve made of 19-gauge tubing was 
pulled down over the exposed tetrodes to a depth just below the 
skull surface, the top of which overlapped the cannula. Three 
holes were drilled in the frontal, parietal and occipital bone 
respectively, into which small jewelers' screws were inserted. The 
microdrive was then anchored to the jewelers' screws and the skull 
surface by dental acrylic (Paladur, Heraeus Kulzer GmbH). One 
of screws also served as the electrical ground. The wound was 
dusted with chlorhexidine antiseptic powder (Riemser, Germany). 
The animals were treated before and after surgery with an analgesic 
(Meloxicam, Vetmedca GmbH, Ingelheim, Germany). The ani-
mals were allowed at least 7 days to recover from surgery before 
screenings were conducted. During this period, they were moni-
tored closely for infection or distress and handled regularly. </p>

<p>Drug Treatment </p>

<p>The negative allosteric mGlu5 modulator 2-methyl-6-(phenyl-
ethynyl) pyridine (MPEP; Tocris) was dissolved in 0.9% NaCl. 
MPEP or vehicle was injected intraperitoneally (i.p.) according 
to body weight (30 mg kg 
21 or an equivalent volume of vehicle: 
ml kg </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>). MPEP or vehicle (0.9% NaCl) was given 30 min 
prior to the next recording trial to ensure adequate time for the 
drug to reach the brain and to observe for any effect of the 
injection procedure. Although this treatment route will affect 
mGlu5 in extrahippocampal structures, previous studies have 
confirmed an equivalent inhibition of hippocampal LTP occurs 
with this antagonist dose, as that which occurs following intrace-
rebral injection of MPEP (Naie and Manahan-Vaughan, 2004; 
Tsanov and Manahan-Vaughan, 2009). </p>

<p>Single-Unit Recordings </p>

<p>In the screening phase, rats were examined once or twice daily 
for unit activity in a screening box that was visually distinct 
from, and in a different room to, the test arena. Neural activities 
were passed through AC-coupled, unity-gain operational ampli-
fiers, which were mounted on a headstage (Axona, UK) con-
nected close to the rat's head through a socket that fitted onto 
the microdrive plug. The headstage was linked to a pre-amplifier 
via lightweight hearing-aid wires. The buffered signal from the 
headstage was amplified 6,000-30,000 times in the pre-amplifier 
and then digitized (48 kHz) and bandpass filtered (0.6-7 kHz) 
in the dacqUSB system unit (Axona, UK). Each tetrode could 
be recorded differentially being referenced by one electrode of 
another tetrode. One of the recording channels was dedicated to 
EEG recording. The position of the rat was monitored by a 
video camera mounted directly above the platform and con-
verted into x-y coordinates by a tracking system which detected 
a small light mounted on the headstage near the rat's head. </p>

<p>Data Analysis </p>

<p>Data analysis was performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Tint</rs> analysis software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Axona</rs>, UK). The collected waveforms from the system unit </p>

<p>PLACE FIELD STABILITY REQUIRES MGLU5 </p>

<p>
Hippocampus </p>

<p>were displayed as clusters by plotting the peak-to-peak amplitude 
of each spike on one electrode against that on each of the other 
three. The clusters were isolated initially by hand. Complex 
spike cells with one or two firing fields were separated on the 
basis of spike shape, firing rate, and firing location. At least 50 
spikes were isolated for each cluster. Once the cluster was iso-
lated, a boundary of cluster was automatically generated by <rs id="software-1" type="software">Tint</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Axona</rs>, UK). Then the same boundary was applied for 
cluster cutting in all other trials. After the cluster cutting, firing 
rate maps for each cell were visualized and smoothed using <rs type="software">Tint</rs>, 
which divided the camera view arena into 64 3 64 square bins 
with a side length of 2.5 cm. The firing rate for a given cell in 
each bin indicated the spike number divided by dwell time in 
that bin. The firing rate maps were presented in color with a 
lowest firing rate (i.e., 0 Hz) in blue and the highest in red. 
Place field was defined as the contiguous group of pixels possess-
ing a firing rate higher than half of the peak firing rate and cov-
ering &lt;60% of the size of the recording arena. If a place cell 
was identified with one or more place fields, recordings were 
repeated two to three time on the same day and at least once 
more on the second day to verify its stability. If no qualified cell 
activity was identified, the tetrodes were advanced 25-50 mm 
and rats were returned to their home cages for at least 2 h. The 
maximum movement of tetrodes per day was 150 mm. 
For each place cell, the firing rate map for each trial was exam-
ined to determine: (1) place field size; (2) average firing rate; (3) 
peak firing rate; (4) mean infield firing rate; (5) mean outfield fir-
ing rate; (6) spatial information content; and (7) spatial coher-
ence. The size of the place field was calculated as the percentage 
of the recording arena by the place field. The average firing rate 
was determined by dividing the number of spikes that occurred 
over the entire trial by the duration of the trial. The peak firing 
rate was determined as the highest firing rate of all pixels within 
the place field of the cell. Mean infield and outfield firing rates 
were defined as the mean values for the firing rates of all pixels 
within (infield) and outside (outfield) the place field. The spatial 
information content, measured in bits/spike, is a measure of how 
much information about the spatial location of the animal is con-
tained within the activity of the cell. It was calculated using the 
methods described by Skaggs et al. (1993). Spatial coherence is a 
measure of the spatial contiguity of the neuron's activity. It deter-
mines the "smoothness" of place fields in firing ratemaps. It was 
calculated in steps described by Muller and Kubie (1989). 
The similarity between firing ratemaps in each pair of trials was 
analyzed using a correlation procedure as follows. Each map was 
decomposed into a 32 3 32-element matrix. Each pixel in one 
matrix was correlated, by a Pearson's correlation, with its equivalent 
pixel in the second map. Pixels with a zero firing rate in both met-
rics were discarded. Correlation measures were not applied to trial-
pairs, in which cells turned on/off due to remapping. </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>Various statistical analyses were applied to measures of place 
cell characteristics. Normality test (Kolmogorov-Smirnov) was 
first applied to each data set to examine whether data match </p>

<p>the pattern expected if the data was drawn from a population 
with a normal distribution. T tests were applied to analyze dif-
ferences between groups when data were pooled from all trials 
in familiar or novel environments. Two-way analysis of variance 
(ANOVA) with Fisher's post hoc tests were applied to detect 
differences between groups across multiple trials. Statistical sig-
nificance was defined as P 0.05. </p>

<p>Behavioral Apparatus </p>

<p>All screening for units took place in an open field square 
box with a floor of dimensions 80 cm 3 80 cm, and walls 
70 cm high. When well-isolated place cells with stable fields 
were confirmed, experiments were performed following the 
experimental protocol described below (Fig. 1). Two boxes 
were used in this experiment. A square box, which was previ-
ously described for screening, served as a familiar environment. 
Rats spent at least 10 min per day for longer than 2 weeks in 
this box. A circular box (diameter, 85 cm; height, 90 cm) was 
used as a novel environment. The color, texture and material 
of the floor and walls were all different between both. </p>

<p>Experimental Protocol </p>

<p>The experimental structure is shown in Figure 1. Animals 
were first allowed to explore the familiar or novel box for 1.5 
min before the first trial of a day. This was to minimize the 
factor that place fields were less stable during the first minutes. 
In the following descriptions, the code "D" stands for the 
experimental day. The "S" stands for the "square arena" which 
is familiar to animals and "R" stands for the "round arena," 
which is novel to animals. On Day 0, at least two place cells 
were identified (D0S1) and confirmed (D0S2) in the square 
familiar box. On Day 1, cells were confirmed again in the 
familiar box (D1S0). If their firing pattern on the spike clusters 
were not shifted from the ones from last trials, rats were 
injected i.p. with either vehicle or MPEP. If the spike clusters 
were shifted, experiment stopped and returned to D0S1. After 
the injection, rats were kept in their home cages for 30 min 
before D1S1 started. Trial D1S1 was to test whether injection 
of vehicle/MPEP affected place fields in the familiar environ-
ment which were already established. In trial D1R1, rats were 
placed into a novel circular box. The question for this trial was 
to ask whether MPEP affected the formation of place fields for 
the first time in a new environment. Trial D1S2 was used to 
test whether, after injection with MPEP, exposure to a novel 
environment disrupted place fields established in a familiar 
environment, i.e., in D1S1. These trials took a total time of 
about 1 h, after which rats were returned to their home cages 
and were kept there for 1 h. Trial D1R2 allowed us to find 
out if newly formed place fields in the novel environment were 
still stable after an interval of 2 h, and trial D1S3 provided 
both a check of cell stability in familiar environment and a 
baseline for day 2 recordings. On day 2, trial D2S1 allowed us 
to check again for place field stability in the familiar environ-
ment, and trial D2R1 allowed us to examine whether newly 
formed place fields were stable after a long interval of about </p>

<p> 
ZHANG AND MANAHAN-VAUGHAN </p>

<p>Hippocampus </p>

<p>24 h. Trial D2S2 provided yet another check of stability, and 
trial D2R2 allowed us to see if the place fields in the novel 
environment were the same as in trial D2R1. The protocol for 
day 1 and day 2 consisted of 10 trials, each for 5 min, with an 
inter-trial interval of 10 min, during which the rats were 
removed from the recording box. </p>

<p>Histological Analysis </p>

<p>The location of the recording and stimulation electrodes was 
verified by postmortem histological visualization. The tissue 
was fixed, coronal slices were obtained and Nissl stained (Man-
ahan-Vaughan et al.,1998). Animals with misplaced electrodes 
were not included in the data analysis. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>A total of 52 cells were recorded from the CA1 region of 13 
rats (7 rats in the control group and 6 in the MPEP group), of 
which 27 cells were recorded in the control group and 25 cells 
in the MPEP group. Firing rate maps in all trials are shown in 
the Supporting Information figures (Figs. S1 and S2). Three 
cells (cell 14, 23, 27) in the control group (11%) and three 
cells (cell 2, 4, 10) in the MPEP group (12%) became silent 
when animals were placed in the novel environment. One cell </p>

<p>in the control group (cell 17) and one cell in the MPEP group 
(cell 9) were lost on Day 2. They were excluded from the sta-
tistical analysis. One cell (cell 20 in the control group) became 
silent in the familiar environment on Day 2, but retained its 
firing pattern in the novel environment. Two cells in the 
MPEP group (cell 17, 25) fired only in the novel environment. </p>

<p>Pre-established Place Fields in a Familiar 
Environment Were Not Affected by mGlu5 
Antagonism </p>

<p>In the familiar environment, the correlation coefficient 
between D1S0 and D1S1 indicated high similarity in both the 
control group (mean 6 SEM: 0.78 6 0.03) and the MPEP 
group (mean 6 SEM: 0.82 6 0.02; Fig. 2). No significant dif-
ference between groups was observed through all trials by 
ANOVA. This suggests that injection of either vehicle or 
MPEP did not affect the stability of place fields, which were 
already established in a familiar environment. High correlation 
values between D1S1 and D1S2 (mean 6 SEM: 0.79 6 0.04 
control and 0.81 6 0.02 MPEP), D1S2 and D1S3 (mean-
6 SEM: 0.76 6 0.03 control and 0.85 6 0.02 MPEP), D1S3 
and D2S1 (mean 6 SEM: 0.83 6 0.02 control and 0.81 6 0.03 
MPEP), D2S1 and D2S2 (mean 6 SEM: 0.79 6 0.03 control 
and 0.84 6 0.02 MPEP) suggest that the maintenance of a pre-
established place field in a familiar environment did not 
require mGlu5 activation. Examples of three cells from the </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. 
Overview of the experimental protocol for place 
cell recordings. All trials during 3 experimental days are illus-
trated. Two boxes were used in this experiment. A square box, 
which was previously used for unit screening, served as a familiar 
environment. Rats spent at least 10 min per day for longer than 2 
weeks in this box. A circular box was used as a novel environment. 
The color, texture and material of the floor and walls were all dif-
ferent between both. On Day 0, place cells were identified (D0S1) 
and confirmed (D0S2) in the square familiar box. On Day 1, cells 
were confirmed again in the familiar box (D1S0), after which rats 
were injected i.p. with either vehicle or MPEP. After the injection, 
rats were kept in their home cages for 30 min before D1S1 
started. Trial D1S1 was to test whether pre-established place fields 
were compromised by the injection. In trial D1R1, rats were 
placed into a novel circular box. The formation of place fields was 
observed in this trial. Trial D1S2 is to test whether exposure to a </p>

<p>novel environment disrupted place fields established in familiar 
environment in both groups of animals. These trials took a total 
time of about 1 h, after which rats were returned to their home-
cages and remained for 1 h. Trial D1R2 allowed us to know if 
newly formed place fields in the novel environment were still sta-
ble after an interval of 2 h. Stability of place fields in the familiar 
environment was checked again in D1S3. On day 2, place field 
stability was first checked in the familiar environment in D1S1. 
Trial D2R1 allowed us to examine whether newly formed place 
fields were stable after a long interval of about 24 h. One hour 
later, trial D2S2 provided yet another check of stability, and trial 
D2R2 allowed us to see if the place fields in the novel environ-
ment were the same as in trial D2R1. The protocol for day 1 and 
day 2 consisted of 10 trials, each for 5 min, with an inter-trial 
interval of 10 min, during which the rats were removed from the 
recording box and returned to their home cages. </p>

<p>PLACE FIELD STABILITY REQUIRES MGLU5 </p>

<p>
Hippocampus </p>

<p>control group (Fig. 3a) and three cells from the MPEP group 
(Fig. 4a) show the kind of firing patterns that were recorded in 
the familiar environment. </p>

<p>Formation of Place Fields in Novel Environment 
Was Not Impaired by mGlu5 Antagonism </p>

<p>As shown in Figure 2, the firing pattern of place cells in the 
familiar environment showed a high spatial correlation between 
D1S0 and D1S1 in both groups (mean 6 SEM: 0.78 6 0.03 in 
control group; 0.82 6 0.02 in MPEP group. Exposure to the 
novel environment induced the formation of new spatial firing 
patterns in both groups of animals (Fig. 5). This was evidenced 
by a significantly lower spatial correlation between D1S1 and 
D1R1, which was the first trial where the animals entered 
the novel environment (mean 6 SEM: 0.05 6 0.05 control and 
0.11 6 0.05 MPEP; indicating remapping) (ANOVA: </p>

<p>F(1, 87) 5 302.91, P &lt; 0.05). There was no difference in spatial 
correlations in D1S1-D1R1 between control and MPEP groups. </p>

<p>Long-term Place Field Stability, But Not Short-
term Stability, in a Novel Environment is 
Impaired by Antagonism of mGlu5 </p>

<p>In the novel environment, short-term stability of newly formed 
place fields was unaffected by vehicle or MPEP, which was evi-
denced by a high correlation between D1R1 and D1R2 (mean-
6 SEM: 0.65 6 0.05 control and 0.70 6 0.06 MPEP; Fig. 6). 
However, the correlation between D1R2 and D2R1 in the 
MPEP group (mean 6 SEM: 0.18 6 0.08) was significantly lower 
than that in the control group (mean 6 SEM: 0.66 6 0.06), sug-
gesting impaired long-term stability (ANOVA 1 Fisher's post hoc 
tests: P &lt; 0.05). This can be seen in the examples of firing pat-
terns of cells in the control group (Fig. 3b) and MPEP group 
(Fig. 4b), and suggests the global remapping occurred between 
Day 1 and Day 2 in animals that were treated by MPEP. </p>

<p>Spatial Information Content Obtained in a 
Novel Environment is Impaired by Antagonism 
of mGlu5 </p>

<p>In the familiar environment, spatial information of place cell 
firing in both control and MPEP groups remained at a simi-
larly high level (Fig. 7a) (ANOVA: F(1, 250) 5 0.18572, 
P &gt; 0.05), whereas, in the novel environment, spatial informa-
tion content was lower in the MPEP group (Fig. 7a) (ANOVA: 
F(1, 150) 5 14.165, P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Spatial Coherence was Impaired in Both 
Familiar and Novel Environment by Antagonism 
of mGlu5 </p>

<p>In the familiar environment, the spatial coherence of place 
cell firing was lower in the MPEP group compared to the con-
trol group (Fig. 7b) (ANOVA: F(1, 250) 5 15.440, P &lt; 0.05). 
In the novel environment, the mean value of spatial coherence 
was also lower in the MPEP group (Fig. 7b). However, no </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. 
Stable spatial correlations of firing pattern in each 
pair of trials in the familiar environment. The correlation coeffi-
cient was calculated from the trial-pairs indicated, in the familiar 
environment. ANOVA was applied to detect differences between 
control and MPEP groups. No significant difference was observed. 
Bar chart shows mean value 6 SEM. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. 
Place cells of control animals showed stable firing 
patterns in the familiar and novel environment. Firing rate maps 
of three cells detected through all trials in the familiar environ-
ment are shown in (a). Recordings were conducted in a square 
box. All cells showed stable firing patterns through all trials in the 
familiar environment. Firing rate maps of three cells through all </p>

<p>trials in the novel environment are shown in (b). Recordings were 
conducted in a circular box. All cells showed stable firing patterns 
through all trials in the novel environment (c). Spike waveforms 
of corresponding cells recorded by tetrodes in a time window of 2 
msec are shown. </p>

<p> 
ZHANG AND MANAHAN-VAUGHAN </p>

<p>Hippocampus </p>

<p>significant difference was observed between the two groups 
(ANOVA: F(1, 150) 5 3.43, P 5 0.06). </p>

<p>Peak Firing Rate and Infield Firing Rate are 
Lower in a Novel Environment When mGlu5 
Receptors are Antagonized </p>

<p>In the MPEP group, the peak firing rate and the infield fir-
ing rate of the place cells were significantly lower in the novel 
environment compared to the rates observed in the familiar 
environment, whereas average firing rates and outfield firing 
rates remained stable (Table 1, t test: P &lt; 0.001). In the control 
group, all firing rate measures remained stable in both the 
familiar and novel environments (Table 1, t test: P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Average Velocity and Place Field Size are 
Unaffected by mGlu5 Antagonism </p>

<p>Average velocity and place field size were normalized to their 
average values through all trials. No significance was observed 
between two groups by ANOVA (Fig. 8). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we provide the first evidence that the metabo-
tropic glutamate (mGlu) receptor, mGlu5 is important for </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. 
Place cells of MPEP-treated animals exhibited 
remapping 24 h after exploration in the novel environment. 
(a) Firing rate maps of three cells through all trials in the familiar 
environment. Recordings were conducted in a square box. All cells 
showed stable firing patterns through all trials in the familiar envi-
ronment (b). Firing rate maps of three cells through all trials in </p>

<p>the novel environment. Recordings were conducted in a circular 
box. Cells showed stable firing patterns in two trials on the first 
day, but remapped on the second day. The remapping firing pat-
terns were preserved and repeatable after a following recording 
trial on the second day. (c) Spike waveforms of corresponding cells 
recorded by tetrodes in a time window of 2 msec are shown. </p>

<p>FIGURE 5. 
Spatial correlations between familiar-familiar and 
familiar-novel environments indicated remapping upon entering a 
novel environment. The correlation coefficients were calculated 
from indicated trial-pairs in both groups. Correlation contents of 
D1S1-D1R1 were significantly lower than those of D1S0-D1S1 in 
both groups. No significance was observed between groups. Bar 
chart shows mean value 6 SEM. (ANOVA 1 Fisher's post hoc test; 
*: P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>FIGURE 6. 
Correlations of firing pattern in each trial-pair in 
the novel environment showed remapping 24 h after an initial 
exposure to a novel environment. The correlation coefficients were 
calculated from indicated trial-pairs in the novel environment. Sig-
nificantly decreased spatial correlations were observed in the 
MPEP group in D1R2-D2R1, while those in other trial-pairs in 
the MPEP group were as high as those in the control group. Bar 
chart shows mean value 6 SEM. (ANOVA 1 Fisher's post hoc test; 
*: P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>PLACE FIELD STABILITY REQUIRES MGLU5 </p>

<p>
Hippocampus </p>

<p>long-term information storage at the level of place fields. We 
observed that antagonism of mGlu5 prevents long-term place 
field stability, reduces information content and reduces place 
cell firing rates in a novel environment. This suggests that 
mGlu5 is necessary for the stabilization of spatial information 
that is encoded by place cells. This observation creates an 
intriguing link between place cells, hippocampus-dependent 
spatial memory and synaptic plasticity, as it has been widely 
documented that mGlu5 is essential for both latter 
phenomena. 
The role of mGlu5 in synaptic plasticity and hippocampus-
dependent spatial memory has been extensively studied (see 
Mukherjee and Manahan-Vaughan, 2013, for review). Activa-
tion of the receptor is necessary to enable persistent synaptic 
plasticity (Naie and Manahan-Vaughan, 2004; Popkirov and 
Manahan-Vaughan, 2011) whereby the NMDA receptor pref-
erentially enables induction of plasticity to occur. Thus, at least 
for the CA1 region, the NMDA receptor enables the initial 
calcium influx required for the immediate change in synaptic 
strength that occurs followed patterned afferent stimulation 
(Dudek and Bear, 1992; Mulkey and Malenka, 1992; 
Manahan-Vaughan, 1997) and which enables plasticity to </p>

<p>endure for several minutes, whereas activation of mGlu5 
strengthens the synaptic response such that it endures for at 
least 4 h (Naie and Manahan-Vaughan, 2004; Popkirov and 
Manahan-Vaughan, 2011). To enable plasticity that endures for 
longer periods of several hours, days or more, protein synthesis 
must be triggered (Frey et al., 1988; Manahan-Vaughan et al., 
2000). 
MGlu5 mediates the prolongation of synaptic plasticity 
through a variety of mechanisms. As a group I mGlu receptor 
subtype, it is positively coupled to phospholipase C (Nakanishi 
et al., 1994; Pin and Duvoisin, 1995) and when activated, ena-
bles that calcium is released from intracellular stores. The 
receptor can also facilitate calcium entry through NMDA 
receptors (Mannaioni et al., 2001) and activates somatic cal-
cium transients, thus affecting frequency accommodation in 
hippocampal synapses (Niswender and Conn, 2010). MGlu5 
also enables neuronal oscillations in the hippocampus that are 
presumably the vehicle for neuronal information transfer across 
this structure (Bikbaev et al., 2008), and is intrinsically 
involved in the induction and maintenance phases of both per-
sistent LTP (Balschun and Wetzel, 2002; Naie and Manahan-
Vaughan, 2004; Manahan-Vaughan and Braunewell, 2005; </p>

<p>FIGURE 7. 
Spatial information contents and spatial coherence 
were impaired in the MPEP group. Spatial information contents 
(A) and spatial coherence (B) of place fields in the familiar and 
novel environment are illustrated. Spatial information in the con-
trol and MPEP group was equally high in the familiar environ-</p>

<p>ment. But in the novel environment, spatial information was 
lower in the MPEP group. Spatial coherence in the MPEP group 
was significantly decreased in the familiar environment but only 
showed a non-significant decrease in the novel environment 
(ANOVA, *: P &lt; 0.05). Bar chart shows mean value 6 SEM. </p>

<p>TABLE 1. </p>

<p>Average Firing Rate, Peak Firing Rate, Infield and Outfield Firing Rate of Cells in Control and MPEP Group Between Familiar and Novel 
Environment </p>

<p>Firing rate (Hz) </p>

<p>Control group 
MPEP group </p>

<p>Familiar environment 
Novel environment 
Significance 
Familiar environment 
Novel environment 
Significance </p>

<p>Average 
0.28 6 0.02 
0.31 6 0.05 
n.s. 
0.29 6 0.02 
0.25 6 0.03 
n.s. 
Peak 
3.06 6 0.20 
2.81 6 0.44 
n.s. 
3.69 6 0.19 
2.12 6 0.19 
P &lt; 0.005 
Infield 
2.18 6 0.15 
1.99 6 0.32 
n.s. 
2.37 6 0.13 
1.39 6 0.15 
P &lt; 0.05 
Outfield 
0.16 6 0.01 
0.18 6 0.03 
n.s. 
0.17 6 0.01 
0.16 6 0.02 
n.s. </p>

<p>t test; n.s.: non-significant. </p>

<p> 
ZHANG AND MANAHAN-VAUGHAN </p>

<p>Hippocampus </p>

<p>Neyman and Manahan-Vaughan, 2008) and LTD (Neyman 
and Manahan-Vaughan, 2008). Prolonged mGluR5 blockade 
leads to a decrease of both theta and gamma power in the den-
tate gyrus (Bikbaev et al., 2008) and activation of mGlu5 
increases excitability in layer V pyramidal neurons (Sourdet 
et al., 2003). Both findings suggest that mGlu5 might be 
essential in the precise temporal encoding required for spatial 
memory. Changes in neuronal oscillations mediated by mGlu5 
antagonism could thus have affected place cell stability by 
reducing available information content. In line with this, 
mGlu5 is essential for many forms of hippocampus-dependent 
learning including inhibitory avoidance learning (Simonyi 
et al., 2007), spatial alternation (Riedel et al., 1999; Balschun 
et al., 2002), spatial context (object-place) learning (Popkirov 
and Manahan-Vaughan, 2011), spatial working and reference 
memory (Naie and Manahan-Vaughan, 2004), object recogni-
tion memory (Barker et al., 2006), spatial learning in a water 
maze (Richter-Levin et al., 1994; Bordi et al., 1996). Altera-
tions in mGlu5 function and/or expression are also a major 
factor in fragile-X mental retardation (Giuffrida et al., 2005; 
Fatemi et al., 2011). 
In light of the substantial body of evidence supporting an 
intrinsic role for mGlu5 in hippocampus-dependent learning 
and synaptic plasticity, it is perhaps not all that surprising that 
we identified a role for mGlu5 in place cell encoding. A not 
too delicate interplay between place cell encoding and LTP has 
been described, whereby afferent stimulation to the hippocam-
pus to induce LTP obliterates place fields and facilitate remap-
ping (Dragoi et al., 2003) The exact nature of the relationship 
between LTP and place cell encoding is unclear, but it may be 
that LTP serves under certain circumstances to generate a tab-
ula rasa after which new information may be stored in the hip-
pocampus, or that it identifies and selects synapses that engage 
in information encoding of a particular (spatial) experience </p>

<p>(Kemp and Manahan-Vaughan, 2007). Nonetheless, it is clear 
that both LTP and LTD play an important role in the enable-
ment of long-term information storage by the hippocampus 
(Kemp and Manahan-Vaughan, 2007, 2008) and that both 
plasticity phenomena require mGlu5 activation (Mukherjee 
and Manahan-Vaughan, 2013). 
In this study, the main characteristics of place cells in the 
familiar environment, such as spatial correlation, spatial infor-
mation content and place field size, were not affected by 
mGlu5 antagonism. This is consistent with reports on the 
effects of blocking NMDA receptors (Kentros et al., 1998), 
blocking protein synthesis in the brain (Agnihotri et al., 2004) 
or deleting the transcription factor zif268/egr1 (Renaudineau 
et al., 2009) on place fields. Thus, once the spatial representa-
tion had been created, mGlu5 receptors were not required. 
However, upon entering a novel environment, both vehicle and 
MPEP-injected rats readily demonstrated remapping. The 
degree of remapping was highly similar in both groups of ani-
mals. Our findings are distinct to a study that explored the 
contribution of NMDA receptors to place field stability. Here, 
it was reported the initial remapping process that occurs in ani-
mals injected with an antagonist of NMDA receptors, was not 
complete, whereby the initial firing pattern in the novel envi-
ronment partially resembled the pattern observed in the famil-
iar environment (Kentros et al., 1998). We can think of two 
possible reasons for the difference in our findings with regard 
to mGlu5 antagonism and this study that addressed the effects 
if NMDA receptor antagonism: the first one is that NMDA 
receptors, but not the mGlu5 receptors, are partially involved 
in the initial remapping. NMDA receptors, mGlu5 receptors 
and protein synthesis are essential for different and contiguous 
phases of persistent long-term synaptic plasticity. Exposure to a 
new spatial environment facilitates the expression of persistent 
synaptic plasticity (Kemp and Manahan-Vaughan, 2004). This </p>

<p>FIGURE 8. 
Average running speed and place field size of place cells in each trial. (a) Run-
ning speed of rats was normalized to its average speed throughout all trials. No significant dif-
ference was observed between groups. (b) The size of each place field was calculated with 
regard to the size of the recording box in each trial and was normalized to its average size 
throughout all trials. No significant difference was observed between groups. Bar chart shows 
mean value 6 SEM (ANOVA, P &gt; 0.05). </p>

<p>PLACE FIELD STABILITY REQUIRES MGLU5 </p>

<p>
Hippocampus </p>

<p>phenomenon, referred to as learning-facilitated plasticity is also 
prevented by NMDA receptor and mGlu5 receptor antagonism 
(Popkirov and Manahan, 2011), whereby NMDA receptor 
antagonism prevents the induction of plasticity and mGlu5 
antagonism prevents the transition of the early, induction phase 
of plasticity into a more lasting form. This suggests that the 
different effects on initial remapping seen during NMDA 
receptor and mGlu5 receptor antagonism reflect the triggering 
and contribution of distinct components that parallel the tem-
poral dynamics of long-term synaptic plasticity phenomena. 
The second possible reason may lie within the saliency of the 
novel environment. In the NMDA receptor antagonism experi-
ment described above (Kentros et al., 1998), the difference 
between the novel and familiar environment derived mainly 
from the color of the cylinder and the color of the cue card. In 
our study, the shape of the environment became physically 
changed from a familiar square to a novel circular arena. Thus, 
is also possible that the difference between the two environ-
ments in our study drove complete remapping in both the con-
trol and MPEP groups of animals. 
In contrast to the lack of necessity for mGlu5 activation for 
the generation of new place fields, one important finding of 
this study is that the long-term (&gt;24 h) stability of newly 
formed place fields in a novel environment was impaired by 
mGlu5-antagonism (although short-term stability remained 
intact). This finding offers an interesting parallel to the key 
role of mGlu5 in enabling long-term plasticity (Mukherjee and 
Manahan-Vaughan, 2013). Most of the cells in MPEP-injected 
rats, which initially established place fields in a novel environ-
ment, remapped on the second experiment day, when re-
exposed to the same environment. This contrasts to the stable 
firing pattern of place cells in vehicle-injected rats. This finding 
suggests that mGlu5 is essential for long-term but not short-
term stability of spatial representation in the hippocampus. 
Moreover, in contrast to the stable place cell firing pattern 
observed in the familiar environment, where spatial memory 
had been effectively consolidated, place cells of MPEP-treated 
rats in the non-consolidated novel environment expressed dif-
ferent firing patterns after a long interval of 24 h. This finding 
suggests that mGlu5 is critical for the stabilization of newly 
formed spatial representations that have not been consolidated. 
Inhibition of mGlu5 might impair the spatial accuracy of 
place cell firing patterns: place cells in MPEP-injected rats fired 
in a more sparse and less spatially selective manner compared 
to those in vehicle-injected rats, as indicated by several place 
field measures, such as spatial information content and sparsity. 
This finding contrasts with the reports from others with regard 
to the lack of involvement of NMDA receptors or protein syn-
thesis in these aspects of place cell encoding. A significant 
decrease in firing rate measures such as peak and infield firing 
rates were detected, when the animals moved from the familiar 
to the novel environment in the MPEP group. One possible 
explanation is that such changes might be correlated to elevated 
neuronal excitability. Activation of mGlu leads to enhanced 
neuronal and an increase in postsynaptic intracellular calcium 
(Abdul-Ghani et al., 1996). In addition, mGlu5 activates </p>

<p>somatic calcium transients (Niswender and Conn, 2010). 
MGlu5 also changes calcium flow through NMDA receptors 
(Jia et al., 1998; Mannaioni et al., 2001; Attucci et al., 2001). 
We observed that antagonism of mGlu5 results in a reduction 
of spatial information in the novel environment, and a reduc-
tion in spatial coherence in both the familiar and novel envi-
ronments. However, since the mGlu5 antagonist was applied 
systemically, we cannot exclude the possibility that extrahippo-
campal effects of the antagonist also influenced on place cell 
activity. 
NMDA receptors and mGlu5 clearly play a very important 
role in hippocampal synaptic plasticity and information encod-
ing. Antagonism of NMDA receptors not only prevents the 
induction of many forms of hippocampal synaptic plasticity 
(Nicoll and Malenka, 1999), it also disrupts experience-
dependent place cell expansion (Ekstrom et al., 2001). MGlu5, 
on the other hand is required for persistent synaptic plasticity, 
hippocampal neuronal oscillations and long-term spatial learn-
ing (Mukherjee and Manahan-Vaughan, 2013). However, syn-
aptic plasticity and place cell stability may require other key 
neurotransmitter receptors. A key role in persistent synaptic 
plasticity and learning has also been described, for example, for 
mGlu1 (Mukherjee and Manahan-Vaughan, 2013) and for 
group II mGlu receptors (Manahan-Vaughan, 1997; Altinbilek 
and Manahan-Vaughan, 2009). 
In conclusion, our data support that mGlu5 plays an impor-
tant role in the enablement of the stability and longevity of the 
encoding of spatial representations by place cells. This, on the 
one hand emphasises the importance of these receptors for hip-
pocampal functioning, and on the other hand, draws an inter-
esting link between other information storage processes in the 
hippocampus such as synaptic plasticity and place cell encod-
ing. Taken together with findings of other reports as to the sig-
nificance of plasticity-relevant factors such as the NMDA 
receptors and protein synthesis for place cell responses, this 
suggests that synaptic plasticity and place cell encoding may be 
highly intertwined. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank Jens Klausunitzer and Juliane B€ oge for 
technical assistance and Nadine Kollosch for animal care. </p>



<p> 
ZHANG AND MANAHAN-VAUGHAN </p>

<p>Hippocampus </p>



<p>PLACE FIELD STABILITY REQUIRES MGLU5 </p>

<p>
Hippocampus </p>



<p> 
ZHANG AND MANAHAN-VAUGHAN </p>

<p>Hippocampus </p>

</text></tei>