<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4589713" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>How to cite the article: 
Kamble SS, Khandeparker RV, Somasundaram P, Raghav S, 
Babaji RP, Varghese TJ. Comparative evaluation of dimensional 
accuracy of elastomeric impression materials when treated with 
autoclave, microwave and chemical disinfection. J Int Oral Health 
2015;7(9):22-24. 
Abstract: 
Background: Impression materials during impression 
procedure often get infected with various infectious diseases. 
Hence, disinfection of impression materials with various 
disinfectants is advised to protect the dental team. Disinfection 
can alter the dimensional accuracy of impression materials. 
The present study was aimed to evaluate the dimensional 
accuracy of elastomeric impression materials when treated with 
different disinfectants; autoclave, chemical, and microwave 
method. 
Materials and Methods: The impression materials used for the 
study were, dentsply aquasil (addition silicone polyvinylsiloxane 
syringe and putty), zetaplus (condensation silicone putty and 
light body), and impregum penta soft (polyether). All impressions 
were made according to manufacturer's instructions. Dimensional 
changes were measured before and after different disinfection 
procedures. 
Result: Dentsply aquasil showed smallest dimensional change 
(−0.0046%) and impregum penta soft highest linear dimensional 
changes (−0.026%). All the tested elastomeric impression materials 
showed some degree of dimensional changes. 
Conclusion: The present study showed that all the disinfection 
procedures produce minor dimensional changes of impression 
material. However, it was within American Dental Association 
specification. Hence, steam autoclaving and microwave method 
can be used as an alternative method to chemical sterilization as an 
effective method. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
This study uses three different types of impression materials; 
dentsply aquasil (addition type), zetaplus (condensation 
type), and impregum penta soft (polyether type) (Table 1). 30 
impressions with 10 for each group impression materials were 
made according to manufacturer's instructions. The stainless 
steel die was used according to ADA specification no.19 and 
ISO International standard 4823 to fabricate specimens. </p>

<p>4-6 </p>

<p>The syringe material was dispensed directly from cartridge </p>



<p>Journal of International Oral Health 2015; 7(9):22-24 </p>

<p>Dimensional accuracy of elastomeric impression materials after autoclave 
microwave, and chemical disinfection … Kamble SS et al </p>

<p>on surface, and the tray material was placed over light body 
material. </p>

<p>The mold consisted of a base was scored with 3 horizontal lines 
perpendicular to 2 vertical lines with each 0.050 mm wide. 
3.8 mm internal diameter steel ring was positioned accurately 
on the base and perforated steel plate was used to apply pressure 
after loading elastomers. Initially, the metal ring was placed 
on the base of the mold fallowed by direct injection of light 
body material onto platform. Then tray material was mixed 
and loaded according to manufacturer instruction. Excess 
materials were removed through perforation. The specimens 
were allowed to set in thermostatically controlled water bath at 
37°C to simulate oral condition. Total of 30 specimens with 10 
for each group (materials) were fabricated. After fabricating the 
samples, the distance between the inner profiles of horizontal 
line was measured (0.005 mm) using microscope before and 
after subjecting to disinfection with autoclave (Group-1), 
chemical -1% sodium hypochlorite (Group-2), and microwave 
(Group-3) methods by same examiner. Mean values were 
tabulated and analyzed using t-test and <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version21</rs>. The percentage of dimensional change was assessed 
using formula; dimensional change % = (A-B)/A × 100, where 
"A" is distance between the inner profile of horizontal line 
before disinfection and "B" is after disinfection procedure. </p>

<p>Results 
The Tables 2 indicates % of linear dimensional change of 
different elastomeric materials after different disinfection 
procedures dentsply aquasil showed smallest dimensional 
change (−0.0046%) and impregum penta soft highest linear 
dimensional changes (−0.026%). With chemical disinfection 
linear expansion occurred. Highest contraction occurred 
with microwave method compared to autoclave and chemical 
type. The Tables 3 indicates dimensional change of different 
elastomeric materials after different disinfection procedures. 
All the tested elastomeric impression materials showed some 
degree of dimensional changes (Table 3). </p>

<p>Discussion 
Accurate reproduction of surface details of the oral structure 
is must after impression making. Disinfection of impression 
materials is advised to avoid cross infection. Impression 
materials may show dimensional changes after disinfection. 
Chemical disinfection alone is insufficient hence autoclave 
at high temperature is necessary to kill microbes and their </p>

<p>spores. Microwave sterilization is used as an alternative 
approach, where electromagnetic energy from the microwave 
is considered to be alternative to the conventional method. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>This study measures the dimensional changes of impression 
materials after chemical, autoclave, and microwave sterilization. </p>

<p>In the present study, microwaving method showed highest 
dimensional changes followed by autoclave method and 
chemical sterilization (Tables 2 and 3). This could be because 
of elastomer fluid intake in microwave method and dry nature 
of microwave. Results of our studies are similar to studies by 
Ramakrishnaiah et al. 2012 and Cynthia et al. 2003. 
4,7 Warden 
et al. from their study concluded that steam autoclaving of 
impression is a safe method of microbial reduction. 
8 Thota 
et al. from their study suggested that autoclave disinfection 
is effective for addition and condensation silicon, compare 
to polyether since polyether is hydrophilic which has to be 
disinfected by chemical means. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Chemical disinfection produced minimal dimensional 
changes compared to other two methods. Tullner et al. 
observed no clinical significant dimensional changes with 
disinfection using 2% gluteraldehyde. 
9 Ivanis et al. (2000) 
concluded that polyether expanded with chlorhexidine 0.5% 
disinfection compared to addition and condensation type. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Ahila and Subramanian. (2012) observed no significant 
dimensional changes after disinfecting impression materials 
with glutaraldehyde, povidone, and sodium hypochlorite. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Katyayan et al. (2011) and Walker et al. (2007) concluded 
that dimensional changes of elastomer was within ADA 
specification after disinfection with phenol and 0.5% sodium 
hypochlorite. 
5,11 Similar results were observed by Guiraldo 
et al. (2012); Dorner et al. (2014); Garrofé et al. (2011). </p>

<p>1,12,13 </p>

<p>It has been observed that elastomer expand with chemical 
sterilization and contract with autoclave and microwave 
method. 
4 All of the tested impression materials were quite 
accurate before disinfection, but showed some degree of 
dimensional changes after disinfection. These dimensional 
changes is well below the ADA specification slandered &lt;0.5%. </p>

<p>Conclusion 
The present study showed that all the disinfection procedures 
produce minor dimensional changes of impression material. 
However, it is within ADA specification. Hence, steam 
autoclaving and microwave method can be used as an 
alternative method to chemical sterilization as an effective 
method. </p>

<p>Table 1: Elastomeric impression materials used in present study. </p>

<p>Product 
Type 
Manufacturer </p>

<p>Dentsply Aquasil 
Addition silicone 
polyvinylsiloxane syringe 
and putty </p>

<p>Dentsply/caulk, milford, 
DE </p>

<p>Zetaplus 
Condensation silicone 
putty and light body 
Impregum penta soft 
Polyether 
3M ESPE, St. Paul, MN </p>

<p>Table 2: Linear dimensional changes (%) of impression materials after 
disinfection procedure. </p>

<p>Materials 
Group-1 (%) Group-2 (%) Group-3 (%) </p>

<p>Dentsply aquasil 
−0.0046 
+0.0026 
−0.024 
Zetaplus 
−0.0082 
+0.0039 
−0.022 
Impregum penta soft 
−0.0048 
+0.0034 
−0.026 </p>



<p>Journal of International Oral Health 2015; 7(9):22-24 </p>

<p>Dimensional accuracy of elastomeric impression materials after autoclave 
microwave, and chemical disinfection … Kamble SS et al </p>



<p>Table 3: Mean and standard deviation of elastomeric materials after disinfection. </p>

<p>Materials 
Group-1 
Group-2 
Group-3 
Before mean 
(SD) </p>

<p>After mean 
(SD) </p>

<p>P value Before mean 
(SD) </p>

<p>After mean 
(SD) </p>

<p>P value Before mean 
(SD) </p>

<p>After mean 
(SD) </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>Dentsply aquasil 
27.0455 (0.0078) 27.0421 (0.0004) 
0.003 
27.0455 (0.0078) 27.0441 (0.0005) 
0.003 
27.0455 (0.0078) 27.0348 (0.0005) 
0.000 
Zetaplus 
27.0455 (0.0078) 27.0426 (0.0003) 
0.003 
27.0455 (0.0078) 27.0458 (0.0005) 
0.202 
27.0455 (0.0078) 27.0338 (0.0005) 
0.000 
Impregum penta soft 27.0455 (0.0078) 27.0428 (0.0003) 
0.003 
27.0455 (0.0078) 27.0448 (0.0005) 
0.000 
27.0455 (0.0078) 27.0342 (0.0005) 
0.000 </p>

<p>SD: Standard deviation </p>

</text></tei>