<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4047866" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The female predominance of LAM, coupled with the genetic 
data indicating that LAM cells are metastatic, suggests that 
estradiol may promote the metastasis of Tsc2-deficient cells. 
Both LAM cells and angiomyolipoma cells express estradiol 
receptor alpha and progesterone receptor, and the symptoms 
of LAM can worsen during pregnancy. 
1-3 Although we have 
previously found that estradiol promotes the survival and 
metastasis of Tsc2-deficient cells, the molecular and cellular 
mechanisms that may underlie this are not completely 
understood. 
We report here that estradiol treatment of TSC2-deficient 
cells is associated with elevated levels of pentose phosphate 
pathway intermediates, Akt-dependent membrane transloca-
tion of the glucose transporters (GLUT1 or GLUT4), and 
enhanced glucose uptake in vitro and in vivo. 6-amino-
nicotinamide (6-AN), a competitive inhibitor of the pentose 
phosphate pathway, 
13 suppressed estradiol-induced cell 
survival in vitro and in vivo. Taken together, these data reveal 
that pentose phosphate pathway is a critical component of the 
estradiol-dependent cell survival of TSC2-deficient cells, and 
point toward novel therapeutic targets for LAM and potentially 
for other hormonally dependent neoplasms associated with 
mTORC1 activation. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Identification of estradiol-induced metabolic signature 
of the pentose phosphate pathway in Tsc2-deficient 
cells. To elucidate pro-survival events mediated by estradiol 
(E 2 ) in Tsc2-deficient rat uterus-derived ELT3 cells, </p>

<p>14,15 </p>

<p>we performed a metabolomics screen by LC/MS/MS. 
A significant increase in glycolysis and pentose phosphate 
pathway intermediates (Figure 1a), including glucose (3.6-
fold), glucose-6-phosphate (2.6-fold), fructose-6-phosphate 
(2.5-fold), ribose (3.6-fold), ribose-5-phosphate (2.2-fold), 
and ribulose-5-phosphate (2.2-fold), were observed in 
E 2 -stimulated cells at 24 h (Figure 1b). Furthermore, E 2 
increased the cellular levels of NADPH (Figure 1c) and 
decreased the levels of reactive oxygen species (ROS) 
(Figure 1d) in the presence or absence of hydrogen peroxide 
(H 2 O 2 ) at 24 h. However, E 2 did not affect the secretion of 
lactate, the end product of glycolysis (Figure 1e). 
To determine the effect of E 2 in the survival of TSC2-
deficient cells under oxidative stress, cells were treated with </p>

<p>H 2 O 2 or vehicle for 0.5 h in the presence or absence of E 2 for 
additional 24 h. H 2 O 2 -triggered cell death was strongly 
rescued by E 2 stimulation by 26% (Po0.01) in comparison 
with vehicle control in LAM patient-derived cells (Figures 
1f and g). Using the PI exclusion assay, E 2 significantly 
reduced H 2 O 2 -induced cell death by 50% (Po0.01) relative to 
control in rat-derived cells (Figures 1h and i). These data 
suggest that E 2 enhances the survival of ELT3 cells 
particularly under conditions of oxidative stress. Collectively, 
these data indicate that E 2 promotes pentose phosphate 
pathway addiction in cells lacking TSC2 (Figure 1j). </p>

<p>Estradiol reactivates Akt in TSC2-deficient cells in vitro 
and in vivo. To define signaling events that potentially 
mediate E 2 -enhanced glucose metabolism, we examined the 
activation of Akt and ERK1/2, which are known signaling 
molecules influenced by E 2 . Under basal conditions, levels of 
phospho-Akt S473 were lower in TSC2-deficient LAM 
patient-derived cells relative to TSC2-addback cells 
(Figure 2a), as expected. Interestingly, E 2 strongly reacti-
vates Akt (S473) at 1 h and sustains Akt activation to 24 h 
in TSC2-deficient LAM patient-derived cells (TSC2 À ) 
(Figure 2b). We also found that E 2 activates ERK1/2 
(T202/Y204), as expected. In contrast, E 2 modestly stimu-
lates Akt at 1 h to 8 h in TSC2-re-expressing cells (TSC2 þ ) 
(Figure 2c). Notably, E 2 did not further enhance phosphor-
ylation of ribosomal protein S6 (S6) (S235/236) (Figures 2b 
and c). Next, we examined Akt activation in Tsc2-deficient 
ELT3 cells, and found that E 2 stimulation resulted in a 
biphasic activation of Akt at 15-30 min and 6 h in vitro 
(Figure 2d). E 2 also induced a biphasic activation of ERK1/2, 
as previously reported. </p>

<p>16-18 </p>

<p>To assess the effect of E 2 in Akt activation in vivo, we 
subcutaneously inoculated ELT3 cells into ovariectomized 
female SCID mice supplemented with E 2 or placebo. E 2 
treatment led to a 2.3-fold increase of tumor volume at 
8 weeks post cell inoculation (Figure 2e). Immunoblotting 
analysis showed that xenograft tumors from E 2 -treated mice 
have higher levels of phospho-Akt (S473) and phospho-ERK 
(T202/Y204) compared with placebo treatment (Figure 2f). 
Moreover, immunohistochemical staining showed that 
xenograft tumors from E 2 -treated mice exhibit higher levels 
of phospho-Akt (Ser473) relative to the placebo treatment 
(Figure 2g). Because Tsc2-deficient cells exhibit low Akt </p>

<p>Figure 1 Identification of estradiol-induced metabolic signature of pentose phosphate pathway in Tsc2-deficient cells in vitro. (a) ELT3 (Tsc2-deficient rat uterus-derived) cells 
were treated with estradiol (10 nM) for 2 and 24 h. Cellular metabolites were profiled by mass spectrometry (n ¼ 5) (Metabolon LC-MS/MS). (b) Box-plots of glucose, glucose-6-
phosphate, fructose-6-phophate, ribose, ribose-5-phosphate, and ribulose-5-phosphate are shown. Data show the mean of five sets of independent samples. (c) Cellular NADPH 
levels were measured in rat-derived Tsc2-deficient cells treated with control or estradiol (10 nM) for 2 and 24 h. Data were normalized to total protein level. Results are representative 
of three sets of independent samples per group from three experiments. (d) Cellular ROS levels were measured using DCFH-DA in rat-derived Tsc2-deficient cells treated with 
control or estradiol (10 nM) for 24 h. Cells were incubated with hydrogen peroxide (H 2 O 2 ) (0.5 mM) for 1 h before measurement. Data were normalized to total cell number. Results 
are representative of eight independent samples per group from three experiments. (e) Extracellular lactate levels were measured in rat-derived Tsc2-deficient cells treated with 
control or estradiol (10 nM) for 24 h. FBS (10%) stimulation was included as a positive control. Lactate levels were normalized to total proteins. Results are representative of three 
sets of independent samples per group from three experiments. (f) Patient-derived TSC2-deficient cells were treated with control or estradiol (10 nM) for 24 h, and then incubated 
with hydrogen peroxide (0.5 mM) for 0.5 h. Cell morphology was recorded using phase-contrast microscopy. (g) Patient-derived TSC2-deficient cells were treated with control or 
estradiol (10 nM) for 24 h, and then incubated with H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM) for 0.5 h. Cell death was measured using the propidium iodide (PI) exclusion assay. Proportion of dead cells was 
normalized to the total number of variable cells. Results are representative of eight independent samples per group from three experiments. (h) Rat-derived Tsc2-deficient cells were 
treated with control or estradiol (10 nM) for 24 h, and then incubated with hydrogen peroxide (0.5 mM) for 1 h. Cell morphology was recorded using phase-contrast microscopy. 
(i) Rat-derived Tsc2-deficient cells were treated with control or estradiol (10 nM) for 24 h, and then incubated with H 2 O 2 (0.5 mM) for 1 h. Cell death was measured using the PI 
exclusion assay. Proportion of dead cells was normalized to the total number of variable cells. Results are representative of eight independent samples per group from three 
experiments. (j) Scheme of glucose metabolism in TSC2-deficient cells treated with estradiol. *Po0.05, **Po0.01 </p>

<p>Estradiol enhances glucose utilization via Akt 
Y Sun et al </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>E 2 -2h 
E 2 -24h </p>

<p>Min 
Max </p>

<p>Glucose </p>

<p>Relative level </p>

<p>Relative level 
Relative level 
Relative level </p>

<p>Relative level 
Relative level </p>

<p>Con E 2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 
** </p>

<p>Glucose-6 
-phosphate </p>

<p>Con E 2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 
** </p>

<p>Con E 2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>Fructose-6 
-phosphate </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Ribose </p>

<p>Con E 2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 
** </p>

<p>Ribose-5 
-phosphate </p>

<p>Con E 2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 
** </p>

<p>Riboluse-5 
-phosphate </p>

<p>Con E 2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 
** </p>

<p>NADPH ng/ g protein </p>

<p>2h 
24h </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 
Control </p>

<p>E 2 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ROS relative level </p>

<p>Control E 2 
Control E 2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 
** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>H 2 O 2 
Lactate / cell total protein 
(nmol/ g) </p>

<p>Control 
E 2 
FBS </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>N / S </p>

<p>Vehicle </p>

<p>H 
2 O </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Control 
E 2 </p>

<p>Control 
E 2 </p>

<p>Vehicle </p>

<p>H 
2 O </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cell death % </p>

<p>Control E 2 Control E 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>H 2 O 2 </p>

<p>Cell death % </p>

<p>Control E 2 Control E 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>H 2 O 2 </p>

<p>Rat derived cells (TSC2-) </p>

<p>Rat derived cells (TSC2-) 
Rat derived cells (TSC2-) 
Rat derived cells (TSC2-) </p>

<p>Patient derived cells (TSC2-) 
Patient derived cells (TSC2-) </p>

<p>Rat derived cells (TSC2-) 
Rat derived cells (TSC2-) </p>

<p>Estradiol enhances glucose utilization via Akt 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>activation due to feedback inhibition mechanism, 
19 these data 
reveal that E 2 reactivates Akt pathway in cells lacking TSC2. </p>

<p>Estradiol promotes plasma membrane translocation of 
glucose transporters GLUT1 or GLUT4 and glucose 
uptake in an Akt-dependent manner. Glucose entry into 
cells is facilitated by proper localization of glucose transpor-
ters including GLUT1 and GLUT4. 
20 To examine the impact 
of E 2 on GLUT1 and GLUT4 localization, TSC2-deficient 
LAM patient-derived or rat-derived cells were treated with E 2 
for 24 h. Confocal microscopy showed that E 2 promoted 
plasma membrane translocation of GLUT4, but not GLUT1, 
compared with control in LAM patient-derived cells 
(Figure 3a). Interestingly, treatment of mTORC1 inhibitor 
rapamycin led to plasma membrane translocation of GLUT4. </p>

<p>Importantly, E 2 -promoted membrane localization of GLUT4 
was abolished by wortmannin treatment (Figure 3a). 
Furthermore, Akt inhibitors MK2206 and wortmannin strongly 
suppressed E 2 -induced phosphorylation of Akt (S473), but 
not phosphorylation of ERK or S6, in patient-derived cells 
(Figure 3b). Moreover, analysis of rat-derived Tsc2-deficient 
cells showed that rapamycin treatment led to plasma 
membrane localization of GLUT1 (Figure 3c). Importantly, 
E 2 promoted membrane localization of GLUT1, which was 
abolished by wortmannin treatment (Figure 3c). Immunoblot 
analysis showed that wortmannin treatment markedly 
decreased E 2 -induced phosphorylation of Akt (S473), but 
not phosphorylation of S6 (Figure 3d). Together, these data 
suggest that Akt specifically mediates the effect of E 2 on 
GLUT1 or GLUT4 trafficking in TSC2-deficient cells. </p>

<p>TSC2 </p>

<p>p-Akt(S473) </p>

<p>p-ERK 
(Thr202/Tyr204) </p>

<p>p-S6 </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>Rapamycin -
+ 
+ 
-</p>

<p>TSC2-
TSC2+ </p>

<p>Patient derived 
cells (TSC2-) </p>

<p>TSC2 
p-Akt(S473) </p>

<p>p-ERK 
(Thr202/Tyr204) 
p-S6 
-actin </p>

<p>E 2 </p>

<p>0 0.25 0.5 1 2 4 6 8 12 24 </p>

<p>Rat derived cells (TSC2-) </p>

<p>TSC2 </p>

<p>p-Akt(S473) 
p-ERK 
(Thr202/Tyr204) 
p-S6 </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>E 2 (hr) 0 0.25 1 2 4 6 8 12 24 </p>

<p>Patient derived cells (TSC2-) </p>

<p>p-Akt(S473) 
p-ERK 
(Thr202/Tyr204) </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>E 2 (hr) </p>

<p>p-S6 </p>

<p>TSC2 </p>

<p>0 0.25 1 2 4 6 8 12 24 </p>

<p>Patient derived cells (TSC2+) </p>

<p>Phospho-Akt (Ser473) </p>

<p>Xenograft tumor </p>

<p>Placebo 
E 2 </p>

<p>Tumor volume (mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Placebo 
E 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 
** </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>p-ERK 
(Thr202/Tyr204) </p>

<p>p-Akt(S473) </p>

<p>Placebo </p>

<p>E 2 (hr) </p>

<p>Figure 2 Estradiol reactivates the Akt signaling pathway in vitro and in vivo. (a) Immunoblot analyses of TSC2, phospho-Akt (Ser473), phospho-ERK1/2 (Thr202/Tyr204), 
phospho-S6 (Ser235/236), and b-actin in patient-derived TSC2-deficient or TSC2-re-expressing cells treated with control or rapamycin for 12 h. Results are representative of 
three independent experiments. (b and c) Immunoblot analyses of TSC2, phospho-Akt (S473), phospho-ERK (Thr202/Tyr204), phospho-S6 (Ser235/236), and b-actin in 
patient-derived TSC2-deficient or TSC2-re-expressing cells treated with estradiol. Results are representative of three different experiments. (d) Immunoblot analyses of TSC2, 
phospho-Akt (S473), phospho-ERK (Thr202/Tyr204), phospho-S6 (Ser235/236), and b-actin in rat-derived Tsc2-deficient cells treated with estradiol. Results are 
representative of three different experiments. (e) ELT3 cells were subcutaneously injected into female ovariectomized mice implanted with estradiol or placebo pellets. Tumor 
volume was calculated at week 8 post cell inoculation. (f) Immunoblot analyses of phospho-Akt (S473), phospho-ERK (Thr202/Tyr204), and b-actin in xenograft tumors from 
mice treated with estradiol or placebo. (g) Immunohistochemistry of phospho-Akt (Ser473) in xenograft tumors of rat-derived Tsc2-deficient cells from mice treated with 
estradiol or placebo. Results are representative of five mice in each group. **Po0.01 </p>

<p>Estradiol enhances glucose utilization via Akt 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>E2 </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>E2 </p>

<p>Rapamycin </p>

<p>E2+Wort </p>

<p>Patient derived cells(TSC2-) </p>

<p>GLUT1 
GLUT4 </p>

<p>p-Akt(S473) 
p-ERK 
(Thr202/Tyr204) </p>

<p>p-S6 </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
E 
2 E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+ M 
K E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+ W </p>

<p>o r t </p>

<p>Patient derived cells 
(TSC2-) </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>E2 </p>

<p>Rapamycin </p>

<p>E2+Wort </p>

<p>Rat derived cells(TSC2-) </p>

<p>p-Akt(S473) </p>

<p>p-S6 </p>

<p>p-ERK 
(Thr202/Tyr204) </p>

<p>Control 
E 2 
E 2 +Wort </p>

<p>Rat derived cells (TSC2-) </p>

<p>Patient derived cells(TSC2-) </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2-NBDG </p>

<p>Control 
E 2 
E 2 +Wort E 2 +Rapa </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>Relative glucose level 
(medium) </p>

<p>Control 
E 2 
E 2 +Wort </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>Placebo </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Control 
E 2 
Tumor FDG Uptake </p>

<p>Avg intensity 40 min </p>

<p>Patient derived cells (TSC2-) 
Rat derived cells (TSC2-) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>p=0.015 </p>

<p>SUV=4 </p>

<p>SUV=1 </p>

<p>L 
R </p>

<p>L 
R </p>

<p>sagittal 
coronal 
transverse </p>

<p>Relative glucose uptake </p>

<p>Figure 3 Estradiol enhances GLUT1 and GLUT4 plasma membrane translocation and glucose uptake via PI3K/Akt in TSC2-deficient cells. (a) Patient-derived Tsc2-
deficient cells were treated with rapamycin (10 nM), wortmannin (500 nM) for 15 min, and then treated with control or estradiol (10 nM) for 12 h. Subcellular localization of 
GLUT1 and GLUT4 was examined using confocal microscopy. (b) Patient-derived Tsc2-deficient cells treated with estradiol (10 nM) at 12 h in the presence or absence of 
MK2206 (2 mM) or wortmannin (500 nM) for 15 min. Immunoblot analyses of phospho-Akt (Ser473), phospho-ERK1/2 (Thr202/Tyr204), phospho-S6 (Ser235/236), and 
b-actin. Results are representative of three independent experiments. (c) Rat-derived Tsc2-deficient cells were treated with rapamycin (10 nM), or wortmannin (1 mM) for 
15 min, and then treated with control or estradiol (10 nM) for 24 h. Subcellular localization of GLUT1 was examined using confocal microscopy. (d) Patient-derived 
TSC2-deficient cells treated with estradiol (10 nM) at 12 h in the presence or absence of wortmannin (500 nM) for 15 min. Immunoblot analyses of phospho-Akt (Ser473), 
phospho-ERK1/2 (Thr202/Tyr204), phospho-S6 (Ser235/236), and b-actin. Results are representative of three independent experiments. (e) 2-NBDG uptake was measured 
in patient-derived cells treated with control or estradiol. (f) Glucose uptake was measured by 2-NBDG fluorescence in patient-derived TSC2-deficient cells treated 
with estradiol in the presence or absence of wortmannin (500 nM) or rapamycin (10 nM) for 15 min before treatment. (g) Rat-derived Tsc2-deficient cells were treated with 
wortmannin (500 nM) for 15 min, and then treated with control or estradiol (10 nM) for 24 h. Extracellular glucose levels were measured in conditioned media. Data were 
normalized to the control group. (h) Representative images of [ </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>F]FDG-PET/CT scanning of estradiol or placebo-treated mice bearing xenograft tumors of ELT3 cells. (i) The 
graph indicates the average intensity at 40 min of tumor FDG uptake. *Po0.05, **Po0.01 </p>

<p>Estradiol enhances glucose utilization via Akt 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>To determine the impact of E 2 on glucose uptake in vitro, we 
first assessed the direct glucose uptake using 2-NBDG 
(2-(N-(7-nitrobenz-2-oxa-1,3-diazol-4-yl)amino)-2-deoxyglucose), 
a fluorescently labeled deoxyglucose analog. Confocal 
microscopy showed that E 2 treatment led to higher levels of 
internalized 2-NBDG relative to vehicle treatment (Figure 3e). 
Fluorescent quantification showed that E 2 treatment 
increased 2-NBDG uptake by 60% (Po0.01) at 30 min 
compared with vehicle treatment (Figure 3f), and this was 
significantly decreased by wortmannin treatment (Po0.01), </p>

<p>but not affected by rapamycin treatment in patient-derived 
cells (Figure 3f). We next examined the rate of glucose 
consumption in conditioned media. E 2 significantly increased 
glucose consumption by B10% (Po0.01) in comparison with 
vehicle at 24 h (Figure 3g), indicating that E 2 enhanced 
glucose uptake in rat-derived Tsc2-deficient ELT3 cells. 
Importantly, wortmannin treatment reduced the rate of 
E 2 -enhanced glucose uptake (Figure 3g). Collectively, these 
data demonstrate that Akt specifically mediates the effect of 
E 2 on glucose uptake in cells lacking TSC2 in vitro. </p>

<p>G6PD relative expression </p>

<p>Control 
E 2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>G6PD </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>G6PD relative ratio 
to? -actin </p>

<p>0 0.25 0.5 1 2 4 6 8 12 24hr </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>** 
* 
* </p>

<p>p-Akt(S473) </p>

<p>G6PD </p>

<p>p-ERK 
(T202/Y204) 
p-S6 </p>

<p>E 
2 E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+ I C 
I E </p>

<p>2 E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+ M 
K E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+ W </p>

<p>o r t </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+ A 
Z D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+ P D </p>

<p>Patient derived cells 
(TSC2-) 
Patient derived cells (TSC2-) 
Patient derived cells (TSC2-) </p>

<p>G6PD 
-actin 
-actin </p>

<p>E 2 (hr) 0 0.25 1 2 4 6 8 12 24 </p>

<p>E 2 (hr) 0 0.25 
1 2 4 6 8 12 24 
0.5 
G6PD relative ratio 
to </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>0 0.25 1 2 4 6 8 12 24hr </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Rat derived cells (TSC2-) </p>

<p>G6PD </p>

<p>Placebo </p>

<p>G6PD relative ratio 
to? -actin </p>

<p>Placebo 
E2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Placebo 
E 2 </p>

<p>E 2 </p>

<p>G6PD </p>

<p>Subcutaneous tumors 
of Tsc2-null rat-derived 
cells in mice </p>

<p>Lung metastatic lesions 
of Tsc2-null rat-derived 
cells in mice </p>

<p>Rat derived (TSC2-) SQ tumors </p>

<p>75 m 
75 m 
75 m 
75 m </p>

<p>50 m 
50 m 
50 m 
50 m </p>

<p>75 m 
75 m 
75 m 
75 m </p>

<p>50 m 
50 m 
50 m 
50 m </p>

<p>Figure 4 G6PD expression is elevated in Tsc2-deficient cells in vitro and in vivo. (a) Transcript levels of G6PD were measured using real-time RT-PCR in patient-derived 
TSC2-deficient cells treated with control or estradiol. (b) Immunoblot analyses of G6PD and b-actin in patient-derived TSC2-deficient cells treated with estradiol. 
A densitometry analysis of G6PD was performed. Results are representative of three different experiments. (c) Immunoblot analyses of phospho-Akt (Ser473), G6PD, 
phospho-ERK1/2 (Thr202/Tyr204), phospho-S6 (Ser235/236), and b-actin in patient-derived TSC2-deficient cells treated with estradiol for 12 h in the presence or absence of 
MK2206 (2 mM), wortmannin (500 nM), AZD6244 (500 nM), or PD98059 (50 mM) for 15 min before treatment. Results are representative of three different experiments. 
(d) Immunoblot analyses of G6PD and b-actin in rat-derived Tsc2-deficient cells treated with estradiol at the indicated time points. A densitometry analysis of G6PD was 
performed. Results are representative of three different experiments. (e) Immunoblot analyses levels of G6PD and b-actin in xenograft tumors of ELT3 cells. A densitometry 
analysis of G6PD was performed. Results are representative of three different experiments. (f) Immunohistochemistry of G6PD in xenograft tumors of ELT3 cells and lung 
metastatic lesions from mice treated with estradiol or placebo. Results are representative of five mice in each group. *Po0.05, **Po0.01 </p>

<p>Estradiol enhances glucose utilization via Akt 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>To determine whether E 2 affects glucose uptake in vivo, E 2 
or placebo-treated mice bearing established xenograft tumors 
of Tsc2-deficient ELT3 cells were subjected to 2-[ 
18 F]Fluoro-
2-deoxyglucose positron emission tomography/computed 
tomography (FDG-PET/CT) imaging. The representative 
images show the [ 
18 F]FDG-PET/CT scanning of E 2 or 
placebo-treated mice bearing xenograft tumors of ELT3 cells </p>

<p>(Figure 3h). The FDG uptake in the tumors on the left for both 
mice appeared to be similar. However, standardized uptake 
value (SUV) max measured over the volume of the tumor 
indicated a higher FDG uptake in E 2 (SUV max ¼ 7.54 (right) 
and 6.88 (left)) than in the control animal (SUV max ¼ 4.72 
(right) and 3.74 (left)) (Figure 3i). The average tumor FDG 
uptake increased by B50% in E 2 -treated mice relative to </p>

<p>Z-Score of G6PD value </p>

<p>Control 
E2 </p>

<p>-1.5 </p>

<p>-1.0 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>MCF-7 cells </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>GDS3217 </p>

<p>GDS2323 </p>

<p>Z-Score of G6PD value </p>

<p>Z-Score of G6PD value </p>

<p>Z-Score of G6PD value </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>-1.5 </p>

<p>-1.0 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>E 2 starvation 
days 
MCF-7 cells </p>

<p>GDS4061 </p>

<p>Control 
ER silence </p>

<p>-1.5 </p>

<p>-1.0 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>MCF-7 cells </p>

<p>GDS4067 </p>

<p>-1.0 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>MDA231 
(ER-) </p>

<p>ZR75 
(ER+) </p>

<p>B6TC hybrid 
(E2 indepen-
dent) </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>Figure 5 G6PD expression is estradiol-dependent in female cancers. (a) Genomic alterations of G6pd were determined in TCGA-curated female cancers including ovary, 
uterine, cervix, and breast. 
23 The colored boxes denote various alterations: green, mutation; dark blue, deletion; red, amplification; gray, multiple alterations. (b-e) Levels of 
G6pd mRNA were determined using cDNA microarray analyses of publicly available microarray data sets. (b) Breast cancer MCF-7 cells were treated with estradiol or control 
(GEO data set GDS3217). (c) MCF-7 cells were estradiol starved for 0, 1, or 2 days (GEO data set GDS2323). (d) MCF-7 cells were transfected with estrogen receptor a 
(ERa)-siRNA (ERa silence) or control-siRNA (control) (GEO data set GDS4061). (e) MDA231 (ER-negative), ZR75 (ER-positive), and B6TC hybrid (estrogen-independent) 
(GEO data set GDS4067). **Po0.01 </p>

<p>Estradiol enhances glucose utilization via Akt 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>placebo-treated mice (P ¼ 0.015, Figure 3i). These data 
indicate that E 2 enhances glucose uptake by Tsc2-deficient 
tumor cells in vivo. </p>

<p>Estradiol increases the expression of glucose-6-phos-
phate dehydrogenase in vitro and in vivo. To explore the 
impact of E 2 on the flux of glucose to pentose phosphate 
pathway at the mechanistic level in TSC2-deficient cells, we 
first examined the transcript levels of glucose-6-phosphate 
dehydrogenase (G6PD), the first rate-limiting enzyme of the 
pentose phosphate pathway. E 2 treatment increased the 
transcript levels of G6PD at 24 h by Btwofold relative to 
vehicle control in patient-derived cells (Po0.05, Figure 4a). It 
has been reported that G6PD alternative splicing is one of 
the regulatory mechanisms responsible for G6PD expres-
sion. 
21,22 We performed real-time RT-PCR analysis using 
primers specific to the pre-mRNA and mature mRNA of 
G6PD. We found that estradiol treatment did not alter the 
G6PD mature mRNA/pre-mRNA ratio in LAM patient-derived 
cells (Supplementary Figure S1). Furthermore, cells stimu-
lated by E 2 exhibited higher levels of G6PD protein by 
Btwofold at 2-24 h in patient-derived cells (Po0.01, 
Figure 4b). Importantly, the estrogen receptor antagonist 
ICI 182 780 (Faslodex or Fulvestrant) strongly reduced E 2 -
increased G6PD protein in patient-derived cells (Figure 4c). 
To examine whether Akt is a critical mediator of G6PD 
expression, we treated patient-derived cells with MK-2206 
(an allosteric Akt inhibitor), or wortmannin (an irreversible 
PI3K inhibitor) for 24 h. We found that both inhibitors 
markedly reduced E 2 -increased G6PD protein (Figure 4c), 
further supporting that Akt is a critical component in E 2 -
altered glucose metabolism in cells lacking TSC2. Interest-
ingly, MEK/1/2 inhibitors AZD6244 or PD98059 had modest 
effect on E 2 -enhanced G6PD expression (Figure 4c). We 
also found that E 2 increased the levels of G6PD protein in 
rat-derived cells within 24 h (Figure 4d), consistent with the 
findings in patient-derived cells. Importantly, E 2 treatment did 
not affect the levels of G6PD protein in TSC2-re-expressing 
patient-derived (Supplementary Figure S2A) or rat-derived 
cells (Supplementary Figure S2B). 
Next, we examined the effect of E 2 on G6PD expression in 
cells lacking TSC2 in vivo. Xenograft tumors of ELT3 cells 
from E 2 -treated mice exhibited a 3.5-fold increase of G6PD 
expression relative to placebo treatment (Po0.01, Figure 4e). </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry showed that G6PD accumulation was 
more evident in xenograft tumors from E 2 -treated mice 
compared with placebo-treated mice (Figure 4f). Importantly, 
cells in lung metastatic lesions from E 2 -treated mice showed 
abundant accumulation of G6PD (Figure 4f). These data 
demonstrate that E 2 enhances the expression of G6PD in 
cells lacking TSC2 both in vitro and in vivo. </p>

<p>G6PD expression is estradiol dependent in female 
cancers. We have found that estradiol increased the 
expression of G6PD in mTORC1 hyperactive cells. To 
examine the levels of G6PD in other female cancers, we 
first analyzed the frequency of genomic alterations of G6pd 
from The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) data set. 
23 Despite 
the mutation, deletion, and multiple alterations, G6pd 
amplification frequency was higher in ovary cancer (B9%), 
cervix cancer (3%), uterine cancer (2%), and breast cancer 
(2%) (Figure 5a). To examine the impact of E 2 on the levels 
of G6pd transcript in breast cancer cells, we analyzed 
publicly available expression array data sets. E 2 stimulation 
significantly increased the transcript levels of G6pd com-
pared with vehicle control in MCF-7 cells (GDS3217 data 
set) 
24 (Figure 5b). E 2 starvation for 2 days significantly 
decreased the transcript levels of G6pd relative to 1-day E 2 
starvation or regular condition in MCF-7 cells (GDS2323 data 
set) 
25 (Figure 5c). Molecular depletion of ERa reduced the 
transcript levels of G6pd in MCF-7 cells (GDS4061 data 
set) 
26 (Figure 5d). Furthermore, ER-positive breast cancer 
cell line ZR75 displayed higher transcript levels of G6pd 
relative to ER-negative MDA231 cell line and E 2 -independent 
B6TC hybrid cell line (GDS4067 data set) 
27 (Figure 5e). 
Taken together, these data indicate that levels of G6PD are 
dependent on E 2 and its cognate receptor in female 
predominant cancers including breast cancer cells, consis-
tent with our findings in TSC2-deficient cells. </p>

<p>Depletion of G6PD attenuates estradiol-enhanced 
survival of TSC2-deficient cells in vitro and in vivo. To 
determine whether inhibition of G6PD impacts the survival of 
ELT3 cells in vitro, we downregulated G6PD using siRNA in 
ELT3 cells, achieving B50% downregulation (Figure 6a). 
G6PD knockdown prevented E 2 -decreased ROS production 
in comparison with control siRNA (Figure 6b). Importantly, 
G6PD downregulation significantly suppressed E 2 -enhanced </p>

<p>Figure 6 Depletion of G6PD attenuates estradiol-enhanced survival of Tsc2-deficient cells in vitro and in vivo. (a) Tsc2-deficient cells were transfected with control siRNA 
or G6PD siRNA for 48 h, and then treated with control or estradiol for 6 h. Levels of G6PD, phospho-S6 (Ser235/236), and b-actin were assessed by immunoblot. The graph 
indicates the ratio of G6PD to b-actin. Results are representative of three different experiments. (b) Tsc2-deficient cells were transfected with control siRNA or G6PD siRNA for 
48 h, and then treated with control or estradiol for 24 h. Hydrogen peroxide (0.5 mM) was added for 1 h before measurement. Cellular ROS level was measured with the 
DCFH-DA. Data were normalized to total cell number. Results are representative of eight sets of independent samples per group from three experiments. (c) Cell death was 
measured using propidium iodide (PI) exclusion assay. Data were normalized to total cell number. Results are representative of eight sets of independent samples per group 
from three experiments. (d) Tsc2-deficient cells were treated with 6-AN (10 mM) for 1 h, and then treated with control or estradiol for 24 h. G6PD activity was determined. 
(e) Tsc2-deficient cells were treated with 6-AN (10 mM) for 1 h, and then treated with control or estradiol (10 nM) for 2 and 24 h. Cellular NADPH level was measured. Data were 
normalized to total protein level. Results are representative of three sets of independent samples per group from three experiments. (f) Tsc2-deficient cells were treated with 
6-AN (10 mM) for 1 h, and then treated with control or estradiol (10 nM) for 24 h. Cellular ROS level was measured with the DCFH-DA. Data were normalized to cell number. 
Results are representative of eight sets of independent samples per group from three experiments. (g) Tsc2-deficient cells were treated with 6-AN (10 mM) for 1 h, and then 
treated with control or estradiol (10 nM) for 24 h. Cell death was measured using the PI exclusion assay. Data were normalized to cell number. Results are representative of 
eight sets of independent samples per group from three experiments. (h) Female CB17 SCID mice were supplemented with estradiol for 1 week, and then treated with 6-AN or 
vehicle for 2 days. ELT3-luciferase cells were treated with 6-AN for 18 h, and then injected intravenously into mice (n ¼ 5/group). Lung colonization was measured using 
bioluminescence at 0.5, 6, and 24 h after injection. Representative images are shown. Total photon flux/second present in the chest regions in estradiol (n ¼ 5) and estradiol 
plus 6-AN-treated (n ¼ 5) animals. (i) Scheme of estradiol-promoted pentose phosphate pathway addiction in TSC2-deficient cells. *Po0.05, **Po0.01 </p>

<p>Estradiol enhances glucose utilization via Akt 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>survival of Tsc2-deficient ELT3 cells after H 2 O 2 treatment 
(Figure 6c). 
To inhibit G6PD pharmacologically, we treated Tsc2-
deficient cells with 6-AN, an inhibitor of G6PD and pentose 
phosphate pathway. 6-AN treatment significantly decreased </p>

<p>E 2 -induced G6PD activity (Po0.01, Figure 6d), E 2 -enhanced 
cellular level of NADPH (Po0.01, Figure 6e), and E 2 -reduced 
ROS production (Po0.05, Figure 6f). Importantly, 6-AN 
treatment significantly suppressed E 2 -enhanced survival 
of ELT3 cells after H 2 O 2 treatment (Po0.05, Figure 6g). </p>

<p>G6PD </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>E 2 
-
+ 
+ 
-</p>

<p>Control 
siRNA </p>

<p>G6PD 
siRNA </p>

<p>G6PD relative ratio 
to? -actin </p>

<p>Control 
Control 
E 2 
E 2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>N/S </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ROS relative level </p>

<p>Control E 2 
6-AN E 2 +6-AN </p>

<p>E2 
E 2 +6-AN </p>

<p>E2 
E 2 +6-AN </p>

<p>E 2 
E 2 +6-AN </p>

<p>E 2 
E 2 +6-AN </p>

<p>E 2 
E 2 +6-AN </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>N/S </p>

<p>ROS relative level </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>N/S </p>

<p>N/S </p>

<p>E 2 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
H 2 O 2 </p>

<p>E 2 
H 2 O 2 </p>

<p>Control siRNA 
G6PD siRNA </p>

<p>Cell death % </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
Control siRNA 
G6PD siRNA </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>N/S </p>

<p>N/S </p>

<p>G6PD Activity (mU/mg) </p>

<p>Control 
E 2 
E2+6-AN </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>* 
** </p>

<p>Control 
E 2 
6-AN E 2 +6-AN </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>N/S </p>

<p>Cell death % </p>

<p>Control 
6-AN </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>N/S </p>

<p>0.5h </p>

<p>6h </p>

<p>24h </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 
* </p>

<p>NADPH ng/ g protein </p>

<p>Estradiol enhances glucose utilization via Akt 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>These data indicate that depletion of G6PD attenuates 
E 2 -enhanced survival of ELT3 cells in vitro. 
To investigate further the role of G6PD on the survival of 
ELT3 cells in vivo, ELT3 luciferase cells 
28 were intravenously 
injected into mice treated with E 2 alone or E 2 plus 6-AN. At 0.5 
and 6 h post cell inoculation, similar levels of bioluminescence 
were observed in the chest regions of all mice. At 24 h, the 
bioluminescence in the chest regions of the E 2 plus 
6-AN-treated mice was decreased by B80% as compared 
with that in the E 2 -treated mice (Po0.05, Figure 6h). These 
data support a model in which inhibition of G6PD attenuates 
E 2 -enhanced survival of Tsc2-deficient cells in vivo. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>LAM is a female predominant lung disease characterized by 
the abnormal proliferation of smooth muscle cells and 
progressive cyst formation that can lead to respiratory 
failure. 
1-3 The gender specificity of LAM suggests that 
estradiol may contribute to disease progression, whereas 
mTORC1, which is hyperactive in LAM cells, is a master 
regulator of cellular metabolism. However, the role of estradiol 
in regulating the metabolism in Tsc2-deficient cells has not 
been extensively investigated. In this study, we identified an 
estradiol-enhanced glucose and pentose phosphate pathway 
signature in Tsc2-deficient rat uterine leiomyoma-derived 
ELT3 cells in vitro. Estradiol treatment led to increased cellular 
NADPH and decreased ROS and enhanced cell survival under 
oxidative stress. Estradiol also induced plasma membrane 
translocation of GLUT1 or GLUT4 and increased glucose 
uptake in a PI3K/Akt-dependent manner. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>F-FDG-PET/CT 
imaging showed enhanced glucose uptake in xenograft 
tumors from estradiol-treated mice. Depletion of G6PD, a 
rate-limiting enzyme for the pentose phosphate pathway, 
suppressed estradiol-enhanced survival of Tsc2-deficient cells 
in vitro and in vivo. Collectively, these data indicate that 
estradiol promotes glucose metabolism through the pentose 
phosphate pathway in cells with mTORC1 hyperactivation and 
enhances cell survival under oxidative stress. 
Alterations in cellular energy metabolism are a hallmark of 
cancer, 
6 and there are many indications that metabolic 
reprogramming is particularly critical for the survival of 
Tsc2-deficient cells. Glucose addiction of Tsc2-deficient cells 
has been reported, 
8 suggesting that glucose metabolism is 
essential for the survival of Tsc2-deficient cells. TSC2 deficiency 
leads to increased transcript levels of glucose metabolism 
genes. 
10 Cells with mTORC1 activation express high levels of 
glycolytic proteins PKM2. 
11 Somewhat surprisingly, however, 
the mTORC1 inhibitor rapamycin reduces lactate production but 
does not affect cellular ATP levels in Tsc2 
À / À MEF cells. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Together, these reports highlight connections between cellular 
metabolic alterations and glucose utilization that is likely to 
impact TSC2-deficient LAM cells. 
18 F-FDG-PET scanning has been performed in LAM 
patients. One case report described a strong FDG uptake in 
pulmonary LAM. 
29 Moreover, Young et al. 
30 performed 
FDG-PET scanning in 12 LAM patients and FDG-PET was 
negative for all patients. Reasons for the negativity of 
FDG-PET in LAM patients may include: (1) the sensitivity of 
PET detection because of the diffused infiltration of LAM </p>

<p>cells; (2) emphysema-like destruction of lung parenchyma; </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(3) downregulation and cytoplasmic localization of glucose 
transporters in cells lacking TSC2; 
31 (4) glucose uptake and 
PET positivity may be cyclical, depending on circulating 
estrogen levels. 
We previously showed that estradiol promotes the metastasis 
of Tsc2-deficient ELT3 tumors in a MEK1/2-dependent 
manner. 
28 Here, we report that estradiol promotes glucose 
metabolism via the pentose phosphate pathway in TSC2-
deficient cells, associated with a MEK1/2-independent but PI3K/ 
Akt-dependent plasma membrane translocation of GLUT1 or 
GLUT4. This is particularly interesting, because it has been 
previously demonstrated that Glut1 and Glut4 are localized in the 
cytoplasm but not in the plasma membrane in Tsc2-deficient 
cells, 
31 which may limit their ability to proliferate especially under 
conditions of bioenergetic stress. Our finding that estradiol is 
sufficient to restore membrane localization of the GLUT1 or 
GLUT4 transporter and enhance glucose uptake may, therefore, 
represent a key pathogenic mechanism underlying the female 
predominance of LAM (Figure 6i). 
LAM can lead to respiratory failure and death. 
1-3 The recent 
MILES trial demonstrated that the mTORC1 inhibitor 
Sirolimus stabilizes lung function in women with LAM. 
However, lung function decline resumed upon drug 
discontinuation. 
32 Therefore, despite many advances in the 
clinical care of women with LAM, there remains a critical need 
for improved therapeutic options. The fact that estradiol 
promotes glucose utilization and cell survival via the pentose 
phosphate pathway suggests that inhibiting the PPP could 
selectively inhibit estrogen-induced cell survival. Consistent 
with this hypothesis, we found that 6-AN blocked estrogen-
induced survival both in vivo and in vitro, suggesting a 
novel therapeutic approach for LAM. Our data suggest that 
inhibiting estrogen-dependent cellular metabolic pathways 
could block the pro-survival effects of estrogen on LAM cells, 
without the need to ablate the entire hormonal signaling axis. 
In the long term, it is possible that metabolically focused 
strategies in LAM could have preferable side effect profiles 
compared with hormonal ablation in terms of bone health and 
other parameters; clearly additional pre-clinical and clinical 
studies will be needed to test this concept. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
Cell line and culture. Eker rat uterine leiomyoma-derived cells (ELT3), </p>

<p>14,15 </p>

<p>ELT3 luciferase-expressing cells, 
28 and LAM patient-derived cells (developed from 
a sporadic LAM-associated renal angiomyolipoma cells carrying biallelic mutations 
of the TSC2 gene 
33 ) were cultured in IIA complete medium supplemented with 
10% FBS. Prior to estradiol stimulation, cells were starved in serum-free and 
phenol red-free IIA media for 24 h. </p>

<p>Antibodies and chemicals. The following chemicals were used: 17-beta-
estradiol, wortmannin and DAPI (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA), rapamycin 
(L C Laboratories, Woburn, MA, USA), PD98059 (Cell Signaling Technologies, 
Danvers, MA, USA), MK2206 (Active Biochem, Maplewood, NJ, USA), and 
AZD6244 (L C Laboratories). Antibodies included phospho-ERK1/2 (T202/Y204), 
phospho-S6 (S235/236), phospho-Akt (S473) and TSC2 (Cell Signaling 
Technologies), G6PD and GLUT1 (H-43) (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Dallas, 
TX, USA), GLUT4 and b-actin (Sigma-Aldrich), and Alexa Fluor 488 Goat Anti-
Rabbit IgG (Invitrogen, Grand Island, NY, USA). </p>

<p>Metabolomic profiling. Cell pellets were submitted to Metabolon Inc. 
(Durham, NC, USA) for sample extraction and analysis. Briefly, Metabolon </p>

<p>Estradiol enhances glucose utilization via Akt 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

<p>performed cold methanol extraction of cell pellets and these extracts were split into 
three aliquots. These aliquots were processed and characterized by one of the 
three analytical methods previously described. </p>

<p>34,35 </p>

<p>Cellular NADPH quantification. Cells were seeded in 12-well plates, 
treated with siRNA or inhibitors, and then stimulated with control or estradiol 
(10 nM). Cells (1 Â 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>) were harvested and lysates were extracted with 200 ml of 
extraction buffer following the manufacture's instruction. Levels of NADPH were 
measured using the NADP/NADPH Assay kit (Abcam, Cambridge, MA, USA) and 
normalized to total cellular proteins. </p>

<p>Quantification of ROS. Cells were seeded in 96-well plates and incubated 
with 50 mM DCFH-DA in 1 Â -DPBS for 45 min at 37 1C. Fluorescence was read at 
485 nm/525 nm. Levels of cellular ROS were normalized to the total number 
of cells. </p>

<p>Measurement of cell survival. Cells were plated in 96-well plates, 
incubated with propidium iodide (5 mM) in 100 ml 1 Â -DPBS for 30 min at 37 1C. 
Fluorescence was read at 530 nm/620 nm. Data were represented as percentage 
of dead cells relative to the total number of cells. Cell growth was measured using 
crystal violet assay. </p>

<p>Immunoblotting. Cells were lysed in M-PER buffer (Pierce, Rockford, IL, 
USA) supplemented with protease inhibitors and phosphatase inhibitor cocktails. 
Cleared cell lysates were obtained by centrifugation at 14 000 r.p.m. for 10 min at 
4 1C and then subjected to immunoblotting. </p>

<p>Animal studies. All animal work was performed in accordance with 
protocols approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee-
Children Hospital Boston. For xenograft tumor establishment, 1 week 
before cell inoculation, mice were implanted with estradiol pellets (90-day 
release, 2.5 mg/pellet, Innovative Research of America, Sarasota, FL, USA) or 
placebo pellets. Two million ELT3 cells were inoculated bilaterally into the 
posterior back region of the mice. Mice bearing subcutaneous tumors 
(B250 mm 
3 ) underwent FDG-PET scanning. For the intravenous model, 0.5 
million ELT3 luciferase cells in a volume of 100 ml were injected intravenously 
into the tail vein of the CB-17 SCID mice pretreated with estradiol (500 nM in 
drinking water) for 2 days before cell injection. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry. Sections were deparaffinized, incubated with 
primary antibodies and biotinylated secondary antibodies, and counterstained 
with Gill's Hematoxylin. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence. Cells were plated on glass coverslips, serum starved 
overnight, treated with rapamycin (10 nM) or wortmannin (500 nM) for 15 min, and 
then stimulated with control or estradiol (10 nM) for 12 or 24 h. Cells were fixed 
with 50% methanol plus 50% acetone for 2 min, blocked in 1% BSA/PBS/Tween 
20 (0.05%) for 30 min, incubated with primary antibody for 1 h and then secondary 
antibodies for 1 h. Images were captured with a FluoView FV-10i Olympus Laser 
Point Scanning Confocal Microscope, Olympus (Center Valley, PA, USA). </p>

<p>2-NBDG uptake. 2-[N-(7-nitrobenz-2-oxa-1,3-diazol-4-yl)amino]-2-deoxyglu-
cose (2-NBDG, Cayman Chemical, Ann Arbor, MI, USA), a glucose analog 
fluorescently labeled at the two position, is a substrate for glucose transporters. </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>Cells were cultured in IIA medium with 10% FBS, starved with serum-free and 
phenol-free IIA medium overnight, pretreated with inhibitors for 15 min, and then 
stimulated with E 2 (10 nM) for 24 h. Medium was changed to phenol-free serum-
free glucose-free DMEM with 50 mmol/l 2-NBDG for 30 min. Internalization of 
2-NBDG was monitored using confocal microscopy. 2-NBDG uptake was 
quantified using fluorescence intensity and normalized to control. </p>

<p>Glucose assay. Cells were seeded in 12-well plates, treated with inhibitors, 
and then stimulated with control or estradiol (10 nM). Conditioned media was 
collected and subjected to glucose quantification using the Glucose (HK) Assay Kit 
(Sigma-Aldrich). </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>F-FDG-PET imaging. Mice bearing subcutaneous tumors (B250 mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) 
were intravenously injected with 150 mCi of [ 
18 F]FDG. After 30 min, animals were 
anesthetized with 2% isofluorane, and imaged for 15 min using a small animal </p>

<p>PET/CT scanner (eXplore Vista, GE Healthcare, Waukesha, WI, USA). Images 
were reconstructed using Fourier rebinning (FORE) and ordered subsets 
expectation maximization algorithm with 16 subsets and 2 iterations. The voxel 
dimensions of the reconstructed images were 0.39 Â 0.39 Â 0.78 mm 
3 . [ </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>F]FDG 
uptake in each mouse normalized to the body weight and injected FDG dose, and 
was presented as SUV. </p>

<p>TCGA data analysis. Genomic alterations of G6pd data for all TCGA cases 
were analyzed from TCGA data sets obtained from the cBioPortal for Cancer 
Genomics (http://www.cbioportal.org/public-portal/index.do). </p>

<p>Gene expression analysis. The publicly available microarray GEO data 
sets (www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/) were collected. The Z-score of G6pd mRNA was 
used for data analysis. </p>

<p>siRNA transfection. Control-siRNA (50 nM) or G6PD-siRNA (Dharmacon, 
Pittsburgh, PA, USA) were transfected in cells using TransIT-TKO reagent 
(Mirus, Madison, WI, USA). Cells were harvested at 48-60 h post transfection. </p>

<p>G6PD activity assay. Cells were seeded in 12-well plates, treated with 
inhibitors, and then stimulated with control or estradiol (10 nM). Cells (1 Â 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>) 
were collected and lysates were extracted with 200 ml of extraction buffer following 
the manufacture's protocol. G6PD activity was quantified using G6PD Activity 
Colorimetric Assay kit (Biovision, Milpitas, CA, USA). G6PD activity was 
normalized to total protein levels. </p>

<p><rs id="software-1" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">6.0</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs></p>

<p>Conflict of Interest 
The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements. We are grateful for Dr. C Walker (Texas A&amp;M Health 
Science Center) for providing ELT3 cells. This study is supported by The LAM 
Foundation, The Adler Foundation, The LAM Treatment Alliance, the National 
Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases, and the National Heart 
Lung and Blood Institute to EPH, The LAM Foundation grant and NIH Grant 
GM51405 to JB, and the National Heart Lung and Blood Institute (HL98216) to JJY. 
XG is a LAM Foundation fellow. </p>



<p>Estradiol enhances glucose utilization via Akt 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease is an open-access journal 
published by Nature Publishing Group. This work is 
licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. The images or other third party 
material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons 
license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is 
not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to 
obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. 
To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on Cell Death and Disease website (http://www.nature.com/cddis) </p>

<p>Estradiol enhances glucose utilization via Akt 
Y Sun et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Disease </p>

</text></tei>