<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4317475" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>BACKGROUND/OBJECTIVES: Recently, anthocyanins have been reported to have various biological activities. Furthermore, 
anthocyanin-rich purple corn extract (PCE) ameliorated insulin resistance and reduced diabetes-associated mesanginal fibrosis 
and inflammation, suggesting that it may have benefits for the prevention of diabetes and diabetes complications. In this 
study, we determined the anthocyanins and non-anthocyanin component of PCE by HPLC-ESI-MS and investigated its anti-diabetic 
activity and mechanisms using C57BL/KsJ db/db mice. 
MATERIALS/METHODS: The db/db mice were divided into four groups: diabetic control group (DC), 10 or 50 mg/kg PCE (PCE 
10 or PCE 50), or 10 mg/kg pinitol (pinitol 10) and treated with drugs once per day for 8 weeks. During the experiment, 
body weight and blood glucose levels were measured every week. At the end of treatment, we measured several diabetic 
parameters. 
RESULTS: Compared to the DC group, Fasting blood glucose levels were 68% lower in PCE 50 group and 51% lower in the 
pinitol 10 group. Furthermore, the PCE 50 group showed 2-fold increased C-peptide and adiponectin levels and 20% decreased 
HbA1c levels, than in the DC group. In pancreatic islets morphology, the PCE-or pinitol-treated mice showed significant 
prevention of pancreatic β-cell damage and higher insulin content. Microarray analyses results indicating that gene and protein 
expressions associated with glycolysis and fatty acid metabolism in liver and fat tissues. In addition, purple corn extract increased 
the phosphorylation of AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) and decreased phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase (PEPCK), glucose 
6-phosphatase (G6pase) genes in liver, and also increased glucose transporter 4 (GLUT4) expressions in skeletal muscle. 
CONCLUSIONS: Our results suggested that PCE exerted anti-diabetic effects through protection of pancreatic β-cells, increase 
of insulin secretion and AMPK activation in the liver of C57BL/KsJ db/db mice. </p>

<p>Diabetes mellitus is a chronic metabolic disease that now 
affects 3% of the world's population. The disease is charac-
terized by chronic hyperglycemia, disorders of carbohydrate 
and lipid metabolism, and microvascular pathology in the retina, 
renal glomeruli and peripheral nerves [1]. 
Recently, here has been a growing interest in hypoglycemic 
agents from natural products, especially those derived from 
plants, because compared to synthetic sources, plant sources 
are usually considered to be less toxic, and to have fewer side 
effects [2]. Many traditional remedies for diabetes mellitus 
involve the use of plant sources, and over 200 pure phyto-</p>

<p>chemicals are currently known to have hypoglycemic properties. 
However, most of them have been shown to exert little or no 
effect on glycemic control in experimental studies [3]. Purple 
corn (Zea mays L.), is rich in anthocyanins and bioactive phenolics. 
It has been cultivated and used for centuries to prepare drinks 
and desserts in South America, mainly in Peru and Bolivia [4]. 
The anthocyanins present in the flowers, leaves, cobs, and seeds 
of Andean purple corn have previously been characterized, and 
the major anthocyanins identified were cyanidin-3-dimalonyl-
glucoside, cyandin-3-glucoside, pelargonidin-3-glucoside, peonidin-
3-glucoside, and their respective malonated counterparts [5]. 
Recently, anthocyanins have been reported to have various 
biological activities, such as antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, </p>

<p>This work was supported by the grant from the Ministry for Food, Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries through Korea Institute of Planning and Evaluation for 
technology of Food, Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries (No. 109163-3) and the Inter-ER Cooperation Projects funded by the Ministry of Knowledge Economy (MKE) 
and Korea Institute for Advancement of Technology (KIAT) and Priority Research Centers Program and Hallym University Specialization Fund (HRF-S-12) and Basic 
Science Research Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the Ministry of Education (NRF-2012R1A1A2008842) 
 § Corresponding Author: Soon Sung Lim, Tel. 82-33-248-2133, Fax. 82-33-251-0663, Email. limss@hallym.ac.kr </p>

<p>Received: December 27, 2013, Revised: September 30, 2014, Accepted: October 8, 2014 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Bo Huang et al. </p>



<p>anti-mutagenic, and anticancer activities [6-9]. Furthermore, 
anthocyanin-rich purple corn extract (PCE) ameliorated insulin 
resistance and reduced diabetes-associated mesanginal fibrosis 
and inflammation, suggesting that it may have benefits for the 
prevention of diabetes and diabetes complications [10,11]. 
In this study, we determined the anthocyanins and non-
anthocyanin component of PCE by high-performance liquid 
chromatography electrospray tandem mass spectrometry (HPLC-
ESI-MS) and investigated its anti-diabetic activity and mecha-
nisms using C57BL/KsJ db/db mice, a type 2 diabetes animal 
model. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Materials 
Purple corn kernels were provided by the Corn Research 
Institute in Gangwon Province, Korea. The voucher specimen 
(No. RIC-2329) was deposited and maintained at the center for 
efficacy assessment and development of functional foods and 
drugs (Regional Innovation Center), Hallym University, Chuncheon, 
Korea. Dried purple corn kernels (5 kg) were ground and mixed 
with 30 L of 30% ethanol-water solution in a glass chamber, 
which was used to perform the extraction at room temperature 
for 20 h. The extracts were combined and concentrated under 
reduced pressure by using a Model EYELA N-1000 rotary 
evaporator (Tokyo Rikakikai, Tokyo, Japan) and freeze-dried 
(yield: 410 g, 8.2%). The dried extract was stored at -20°C until 
used for the following experiments. </p>

<p>Animals 
Six-week old C57BL/KsJ db/db mice were purchased from 
Central Lab Animal (SLC, Japan). All animals were acclimatized 
to the laboratory environment for 1 week before the experi-
ment. Mice were allowed free access to drinking water and food 
under constant room temperature (22 ± 2°C) and humidity (50% 
± 10%) under an automatic 12 h light/12 h dark cycle. The mice 
were cared for and treated in accordance with the guidelines 
of the Committee on Care and Use of Laboratory Animal 
Resources, National Research Council, USA. The mice were 
randomly divided into 4 groups: diabetic control (DC), PCE 10 
mg/kg (PCE 10), PCE 50 mg/kg (PCE 50), pinitol 10 mg/kg (Pinitol 
10). Each group was treated with drugs by oral administration 
once per day for 8 weeks. During the experiment, body weights 
and blood glucose levels of the mice were measured once every 
week. All animal experiment procedures conducted in accor-
dance with guidelines and approval of the Institutional Animal 
Care and Use Committees (IACUC) of Hallym University (Hallym-
2012-37). </p>

<p>High performance liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry 
Separation of anthocyanins and non-anthocyanins was cond-
ucted on a reverse-phase Capcell Pak C18 UG 120 S5 column 
(4.6×150 mm I.D., 4 μm; Shiseido Co., Ltd, Tokyo, Japan) using 
a Finnigan Surveyor high-performance liquid chromatography 
(HPLC) system (Thermo Quest, San Jose, CA, USA) at an ambient 
temperature. The mobile phase was a binary elution of 5% 
formic acid solution (A) and 100% methanol (B) under the 
following gradient conditions: initial, 20% B; 7 min, 20% B; 15 </p>

<p>min, 25% B; 32 min, 50% B; 36 min, 100% B; 38 min, 100% 
B; 40 min, 20% B and 45 min, 20% B. The flow rate was 700 
μl/min, and the injection volume was 10 μl. Eluted substances 
were detected at 280 nm and 570 nm by using a photodiode-
array detector between 200 and 600 nm with a bandwidth of 
1 nm. For the identification of major components, the column 
elute was split, and 0.2 ml·min 
-1 was directed to a Finnigan LCQ 
Advantage ion-trap MS (Thermo Quest, San Jose, CA, USA) equi-
pped with an electrospray ionization (ESI) interface after passing 
through the flow cell of the photodiode-array detector. Analysis 
was carried out using positive ion monitoring at a capillary 
temperature of 280°C, spray voltage of 5.5 kV, capillary voltage 
of 10 V and tube lens offset of -5.0 V. Spectral data were 
recorded using He gas as a collision gas. Anthocyanins and 
non-anthocyanins were detected using m/z value following 
MS/MS. The MS/MS collision energy was set to 35%. Data were 
collected using dual analysis in fullscan mode from 100 to 1000 
atomic mass units and MS/MS modes. Data were processed 
using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Xcalibur</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">2.0 version</rs> software program (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Thermo Electron Corporation</rs>, San Jose, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Oral glucose tolerance test 
The mice were fasted for 12 h prior to the experiment, and 
PCE was administered orally 30 min prior to the glucose 
challenge. Glucose (1.5 g/kg) was orally administered at 0 min, 
and blood was withdrawn from the orbital venous plexus at 
0 min, 30 min, 60 min, 90 min and 120 min after glucose 
administration. Blood glucose levels were determined by the 
glucose oxidase method [12]. </p>

<p>Blood biomarker 
Blood samples were drawn from an antecubital vein. Serum 
was separated immediately by centrifugation (2000 × g at 4°C 
for 3 min) and stored at -70°C. Serum concentrations of trigly-
cerides (TG), total cholesterol and high-density lipoprotein (HDL) 
were analyzed using commercial kits (971769, 981771 and 
971656, respectively, Thermo Electron Corporation, Vantaa, 
Finland) and Thermo Fisher Konelab 20XTi Analyzer (Thermo 
Electron Corporation, SeoKwang LABOTECH, Seoul, Korea). 
Blood glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c) was measured on an 
HbA1c Analyzer (HLCr-723GHb G7; Tosoh, Aarhus V, Denmark). 
Serum insulin, adiponectin, C-peptide, and glucagon concen-
trations were determined using a mouse insulin ELISA kit, 
C-peptide ELISA kit, and Glucagon ELISA kit, respectively (all 
from Shibayagi Co.,Ltd., Shibukawa, Japan). </p>

<p>Western blot analysis 
After sacrificing the mice, adipose tissues were immediately 
removed, instantly placed in liquid nitrogen, and subsequently 
stored at -70°C. Protein extracts were prepared using a protein 
extraction kit (Intron Biotechnology Inc., Seoul, Korea). Lysates 
(30 μg) were electroblotted onto a nitrocellulose membrane 
following separation using 10% SDS-polyacrylamide gel electro-
phoresis. Blotted membranes were incubated for 1 h with 
blocking solution (tris-buffered saline with Tween 20. [TBST]) 
containing 5% skim milk (w/v) at room temperature, followed 
by incubation overnight at 4°C with 1 : 1000 dilution of AMP 
activated protein kinase (AMPK), phosphor-AMP-activated protein </p>



<p>Anti-diabetic effect of purple corn extract </p>

<p>Peak 
Rt 
(min) </p>

<p>UV/Vis 
λMax 
(nm) </p>

<p>LC-ESI-MS 
Compounds </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>[M] </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>(m/z) </p>

<p>Fragments 
(m/z) </p>

<p>1 
4.03 259, 274 154 
protocatechuic acid </p>

<p>2 
7.56 260, 292 168 
vanillic acid </p>

<p>3 10.53 242, 293 170 
2,4,6-tribenzoic acid </p>

<p>4 13.07 243, 309 164 
p-hydroxycinnamic acid </p>

<p>5 12.36 251, 326 194 
ferulic acid </p>

<p>6 13.07 256, 353 464 
303 
hirsutrin </p>

<p>7 15.19 254, 353 478 
317 
3'-methoxyhirsutrin </p>

<p>8 
5.38 515, 279 449 
287 
cyanidin 3-glucoside </p>

<p>9 
7.38 504, 278 433 
271 
pelargonidin 3-glucoside </p>

<p>10 8.22 515, 279 463 
301 
peonidin 3-glucoside </p>

<p>11 9.66 517, 280 535 
449, 287 cyanidin 3-(6"-malonyl-glucoside) </p>

<p>12 11.29 517, 279 549 
301 
peonidin 3-(6"-malonyl-glucoside) 
a Compounds 1-12 were identified based on photodiode-array absorbance and mass 
fragmentation pattern. Rt, retention time; UV/Vis, ultraviolet-visible spectroscopy; 
LC-ESI-MS, liquid chromatography-electrospray ionization-mass spectrometry. </p>

<p>Table 1. Identification of the major components detected of PCE </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>Fig. 1. HPLC chromatography of major components of PCE. Non-anthocyanins (A) </p>

<p>and anthocyanins (B) were detected at 280 nm and 570 nm, respectively. </p>

<p>kinase (p-AMPK), acetyl-coA carboxylase (ACC), phosphor-acetyl-
coA carboxylase (p-ACC) primary antibody (Cellsignaling, Danvers, 
MA, USA). Membranes were washed 4 times with 0.1% TBST 
and incubated with 1 : 3000 dilution of horseradish peroxidase-
conjugated goat anti-rabbit or donkey anti-rabbit IgG secondary 
antibody for 1 h at room temperature. Membranes were washed 
four times in TBST and then developed by WEST-ZOL 
® PLUS 
(Intron Biotechnology Inc., Seoul, Korea). </p>

<p>RNA isolation and reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction 
(RT-PCR) 
Total mRNA was isolated from db/db mice liver using an 
Easy-Blue kit (Intron Biotechnology Inc, Seoul, Korea) according 
to the manufacture's instructions. From each sample, total RNA 
(10 μg) was reverse transcribed into cDNA using the Moloney 
murine leukemia virus transcriptase and Oligo (dT) 15 primers 
(Promega, Medison, WI, USA) as primers. Sequence of primers 
are following: PEPCK (phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase) 
sense ATG CCT CCT CAG CTG CAT A, anti-sense TTA CAT CTG 
CGT GAT TCT CTG TT; G6pase (glucose 6-phosphatase) sense 
ACC CTG GTA GCC CTG TCT TT, anti-sense GGG CTG TGT CTT 
CTG TGT CG; actin sense GTC GTA CCA CTG GCA TTG TG, 
anti-sense GCC ATC TCC TGC TCA AAG TC; GLUT4 (glucose 
transpoter 4) sense CAA CGT GCC TGG GTA GGC A, anti-sense 
GCC ATC TCC CCC GCG CGG T; CPN (cyclophilin) sense ATG 
GTC AAC CCC ACC GTG, anti-sense TTA GAG TTG TCC ACA GTC 
GGA GA. The primers were added at a final concentration of 
0.5 μM to a 25 μL reaction mixture containing 20 mM Tris-HCL 
(pH 8.4), 50 mM KCl, 1.5 mM MgCl2, 0.5 mM each dNTP, 5 μL 
of cDNA, and 2.5 units of Taq DNA polymerase (Takara Korea 
Biomedical Inc., Seoul, Korea). The PCR conditions were dena-
turation at 95°C for 1min, annealing at 57°C for 1 min, and 
extension at 72°C for 1 min. The RT-PCR products were electro-
phoresed in 1% agarose gels under 100 V and stained with 
0.5 μg/mL ethidium bromide. </p>

<p>Microarray analysis 
For gene expression profiling, the synthesis of target cRNA 
probes and hybridization were performed using Agilent's Low 
RNA Input Linear Amplification Kit (Agilent Technnology, Santa 
Clara, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
Fluorescent-labeled cRNA target was quantified using ND-1000 
spectrophotometer (NanoDrop Technologies, Inc., Wilmington, 
DE, USA). The hybridization images were analyzed by Agilent 
DNA microarray Scanner (Agilent Technology, Santa Clara, CA, 
USA) and the data quantification was performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Agilent 
Feature Extraction software</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">9.3.2.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">(Agilent Technology, Santa Clara, CA, USA)</rs>). The average fluorescence intensity for each spot 
was calculated and local background was subtracted. All data 
normalization and selection of fold-changed genes were 
performed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">GeneSpringGX</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">7.3.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">(Agilent Technology, Santa Clara, CA, USA)</rs>). </p>

<p>Pancreas histology and immunohistochemistry 
The pancreas was removed and fixed in 10% (v/v) neutral 
buffered formalin, processed routinely, and embedded in 
paraffin wax. Paraffin sections were cut at 4 μm thickness and 
deparaffinized in xylene for 5 min, and rehydrated through </p>

<p>graded ethanol solutions. The sections were stained with hema-
toxylin and eosin (H&amp;E). For immunohistochemistry, rehydrated 
sections were treated with 3% (v/v) H2O2 in methanol for 30 
min to block endogenous peroxidase, washed with 0.01 mM 
phosphate buffer for 10 min, and then immunostained with the 
monoclonal mouse anti-insulin primary antibody. The antigen-
antibody complex was visualized by an avidin-biotin peroxidase 
complex solution using an ABC kit (Vector Laboratories, Burlin-
game, CA, USA) with 3, 3-diamino benzidine (Zymed Labora-
tories, San Francisco, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Data were expressed as mean values ± SE and comparisons 
of data were carried out using Student's unpaired t-test or 
one-way ANOVA, as appropriate. Mean values were considered 
significantly different when P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Identification of anthocyanins and non-anthocyanins from PCE 
by LC-MS 
HPLC spectra at λ = 280 nm showed that 7 non-anthocyanins </p>

<p>Bo Huang et al. </p>



<p>DC 
PCE 10 
PCE 50 
Pinitol 10 </p>

<p>Body weight (g) 
56.4 ± 7.3 
56.2 ± 4.3 
60.2 ± 2.3 
56.8 ± 4.6 </p>

<p>Food intake (g/n, 8 week) 
425.9 
376.3 
375.8 
393.1 </p>

<p>Water intake (mL/n, 8 week) 
1373 
927 
874 
736 </p>

<p>Blood glucose (mM) 
29.4 ± 1.1 
14.2 ± 1.9*** 
9.4 ± 1.2*** 
14.3 ± 0.6*** </p>

<p>Insulin (μU/mL) 
244.5 ± 42.8 
446.0 ± 27.0*** 
226.5 ± 41.7 
381.2 ± 44.8** </p>

<p>C-peptide (ng/mL) 
3.5 ± 1.0 
5.1 ± 1.4 
6.8 ± 1.3* 
6.8 ± 1.8 </p>

<p>HbA1c (%) 
9.8 ± 0.7 
8.6 ± 1.0 
7.8 ± 0.8* 
8.0 ± 0.5 </p>

<p>Adiponectin (ng/mL) 
1739.7 ± 326.4 
2765.5 ± 277.5* 
2662.7 ± 415.8* 
2036.2 ± 311.3 </p>

<p>Glucagon (pg/mL) 
246.3 ± 44.8 
201.9 ± 33.9 
148.8 ± 35.3* 
185.7 ± 39.8 </p>

<p>Plasma lipids </p>

<p>Triglyceride (mg/dL) 
222.0 ± 29.4 
116.0 ± 30.4** 
105.1 ± 28.6** 
131.8 ± 25.7** </p>

<p>Total cholesterol (mg/dL) 
190.3 ± 24.8 
197.3 ± 21.6 
205.6 ± 33.8 
171.8 ± 20.0 </p>

<p>HDL-cholesterol (mg/dL) 
70.0 ± 7.3 
87.3 ± 10.3 
90.8 ± 8.0* 
78.2 ± 11.1 
Data are mean ± SE (n = 6) </p>

<p>* P &lt; 0.05, ** P &lt; 0.01, *** P &lt; 0.001 compared to diabetic control (DC) group </p>

<p>Table 2. Metabolic parameters on administration of purple corn extract in db/db mice </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Oral glucose tolerance test (A) after 12 h of food deprivation in db/db 
mice. (B) Area under the blood-glucose concentration curve was measured over 
the next 120 min (AUC-120 min). Values represent mean ± SE (n = 6). *P &lt; 0.05 vs. </p>

<p>Cont. </p>

<p>were identified by their HPLC retention times, elution order, 
spectroscopic characteristics and fragmentation pattern by 
comparison with previously reported literature (Fig. 1A). The 7 
major non-anthocyanins were identified as protocatechuic acid, 
vanillic acid, 2, 4, 6-tribenzoic acid, p-hydroxycinnamic acid, 
ferulic acid, hirsutrin, and 3' -methoxyhirsutrin. Fig. 1B shows 
the chromatograms of anthocyanins identified in PCE. The 5 
major anthocyanins were identified as cyanidin 3-glucoside, 
pelargonidin 3-glucoside, peonidin 3-glucoside, cyanidin 3-(6"-
malonyl-glucoside), and peonidin 3-(6"-malonyl-glucoside) by 
using LC-ESI-MS (Table 1). The MS/MS spectra of the antho-
cyanins provided clear and characteristic fragmentation data. 
The aglycones of anthocyanins were cyanidin (molecular weight 
[MW; 287]), peonidin (MW; 301) and pelargonidin (MW; 271). </p>

<p>Effect of PCE on metabolic parameters 
Table 2 shows the effects of PCE (10, 50) and pinitol 10 on 
metabolic parameters in diabetic db/db mice treated for 8 
weeks. Compared to DC group, there were no significant diffe-
rences in body weight between DC and PCE (10, 50) and pinitol 
10 groups. PCE (10, 50) and pinitol 10 groups showed decrease 
in food and water intake but not significant. Plasma glucose 
levels were significantly decreased by 52% (P &lt; 0.001) in PCE 
10, 68% (P &lt; 0.001) in PCE 50 and 52% (P &lt; 0.001) in Pinitol 10 
compared to DC. The serum insulin level in the PCE 10 and 
Pinitol 10 treated db/db mice was significantly increased by 1.8 
fold (P &lt; 0.001), 1.5 fold (P &lt; 0.001) as compared to the control 
groups, respectively. 
The level of serum C-peptide increased by 1.4 and 1.9 (P &lt; 
0.05) fold in the PCE 10 and PCE 50 groups, respectively. HbA1c 
levels in the PCE 50 mice were decreased by 20% (P &lt; 0.05), 
when compared to DC group. In the PCE 10 and PCE 50 groups, 
adiponectin levels were enhanced by 59% (P &lt; 0.05) and 53% 
(P &lt; 0.05), respectively, compared with the DC group. In this 
experiment, glucagon levels in PCE 50 treated mice were 
decreased by 40% (P &lt; 0.05) when compared to DC group, and 
these data revealed a similar trend in serum insulin levels. In 
the PCE 10, 50 and pinitol 10 groups, triglyceride (TG) levels 
were lowered by 48% (P &lt; 0.01), 53% (P &lt; 0.01) and 41% (P &lt; </p>

<p>0.01) compared with the DC group, respectively. The total 
cholesterol (TC) level in the PCE treated groups showed no 
significant differences, but the HDL-cholesterol level in the PCE 
50 group was significantly higher (by 28%) than those in the 
DC group. </p>

<p>Effect of PCE on oral glucose tolerance test 
Oral glucose tolerance tests were performed to determine the 
effect of a single oral dose of PCE on glucose tolerance using 
the db/db mice (Fig. 2). Glucose challenge dramatically increased 
blood glucose levels in control mice, whereas PCE-treated </p>



<p>Anti-diabetic effect of purple corn extract </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Microscopic view of pancreas sections and immunostaining of insulin 
Control, PCE 10, PCE 50 and pinitol 10 group. H &amp; E, magnification × 200. </p>

<p>(A) 
(B) </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Effects of PCE on phosphorylations of hepatic AMPK and ACC protein (A), PEPCK, G6pase, or GLUT4 (B) mRNA levels in liver, muscle. The amount of RNA loaded </p>

<p>in each lane was confirmed by RT-PCR of CPN or Actin mRNA. </p>

<p>Tissues 
Accession no. 
Gene name 
Fold change 
Function </p>

<p>Liver </p>

<p>Up-regulated </p>

<p>NM_010292 
Glucokinase 
2.78 
Glycolysis </p>

<p>NM_011099 
Pyruvate kinase, muscle 
2.29 
Glycolysis </p>

<p>Adipose </p>

<p>Up-regulated </p>

<p>NM_015729 
Acyl-Coenzyme A oxidase 1, palmitoyl 
2.16 
Fatty acid metabolism </p>

<p>NM_007760 
Carnitine acetyltransferase 
3.95 
Fatty acid metabolism </p>

<p>Down-regulated </p>

<p>NM_027976 
Acyl-CoA synthetase long-chain family member 5 
0.49 
Fatty acid metabolism </p>

<p>Table 3. Differentially expressed genes in the liver and adipose tissue of PCE 50 treated db/db mice </p>

<p>groups had suppressed blood glucose levels 30, 60, and 90 min 
after glucose load (Fig. 2A). When the area under the curve 
(AUC) was compared between groups, the PCE 10 and PCE 50 
groups showed 12% and 13% reduction, respectively, compared 
to the control group (Fig. 2B). </p>

<p>Morphology and insulin immunostaining in pancreas 
Typical H&amp;E staining results obtained upon histological exami-
nation were shown in Fig. 3. The diabetic islets in control mice </p>

<p>were atrophied, indicating β-cell damage. PCE treatment pre-
vented islet destruction and resulted in significantly preserved 
insulin levels (brown in the cytoplasm of pancreatic tissue 
sections) in a concentration-dependent manner. </p>

<p>Liver and adipose tissue molecular profiles 
To compare the gene expression profiles of PCE treated and 
control db/db mice, we used microarray assay in the liver and 
adipose tissue (Table 3). Among 25,262 genes expressed in liver 
and 27,730 genes expressed in adipose tissue, we found 2 genes 
significantly up-regulated in liver and 3 genes in adipose tissue 
showing significant up-or down-regulation, compared to the DC 
group. </p>

<p>AMPK, GLUT4 and gluconeogenesis gene expression 
As shown in Fig. 4, PCE markedly phosphorylated AMPK and 
ACC compared to DC group (Fig 4A). In addition, PCE-treated 
groups over expressed the mRNA of GLUT4 in the skeletal 
muscle, indicating facilitation of glucose uptake into the 
insulin-dependent tissue. Interestingly, expression of PEPCK and 
G6Pase, a rate-limiting enzyme in gluconeogenesis pathway, 
was almost completely decreased compared to DC group (Fig. </p>

<p>Bo Huang et al. </p>



<p>4B). As a result, through AMPK activation, PCE reduced hepatic 
glucose production through inhibiting PEPCK and G6Pase 
expression and higher mRNA expression of GLUT4 in PCE-
treated mice reflects an increase in glucose flux into skeletal 
muscle. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we demonstrated that PCE significantly ameli-
orated hyperglycemia and hyperlipidemia by reducing the blood 
glucose levels and increasing the serum insulin, C-peptide, 
HbA1c, and adiponectin concentrations in type 2 diabetic 
C57BL/KsJ db/db mice. Diabetes mellitus is sub-divided into two 
main forms. Type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM) is mainly due to 
an auto-immunemediated destruction of pancreatic β-cell islets. 
On the other hand, type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) is chara-
cterized by insufficient insulin secretion and insulin resistance 
[13]. Type 2 diabetes is a chronic metabolic disorder affecting 
approximately 3% of population worldwide. But the conven-
tional pharmacological treatments for type 2 diabetes have a 
number of limitations, such as adverse effects and high rates 
of secondary failure [14]. Anthocyanins are a subclass of flavo-
noids that have been reported to improve insulin resistance 
and hyperlipidemia in several models of obesity and diabetes 
in rodents [15]. Interest in anthocyanins as natural colorants 
and valueadded ingredients has increased due to their color 
characteristics and potential health benefits. Chinese purple 
corn extracts were a natural source of anthocyanins and were 
stable over a wide range of temperatures and times [16]. This 
study identified 7 major non-anthocyanins and 5 major antho-
cyanins in puple corn extracts (Table 1, Fig. 1). Recent studies 
indicate that diabetic atherosclerosis is not only a disease of 
hyperlipidemia but also an inflammatory disorder [17]. Existing 
evidence indicates that obesity-related insulin resistance results 
in a systemic prothrombotic state and might enhance the 
progression of atherosclerotic lesions [18]. In our study, we 
found that PCE 10 and PCE 50 groups showed 52% and 68% 
reduction in blood glucose levels, respectively, compared to DC 
group, but not significantly change body weight, food and 
water intake (Table 2). The serum insulin level in the PCE 10 
and Pinitol 10 treated db/db mice was significantly increased 
by 1.8 fold, 1.5 fold as compared to the control groups, respe-
ctively. Pinitol (D-3-O-methyl-chiro-inositol) has been reported 
to exert insulin-like effects. Pinitol extracted from Bougainvillea 
spectabilis reduced blood glucose in animal models of diabetes 
[19]. And also administration of PCE for 8 weeks resulted in 
significantly increased serum insulin, C-peptide, and adiponectin 
concentrations as compared to the DC group (Table 2). Similarly, 
Hong et al. [20] had reported that insulin level increased after 
treatment of purple corn anthocyanins in pancreatic β-cell. In 
the present study was also a significant increase in the levels 
of serum insulin and less destructed β-cells after administration 
of PCE to db/db mice. PCE less destructed β-cells and increased 
insulin secretion by decreasing blood glucose (Fig. 3). 
OGTT is one of the most critical criteria for evaluating the 
effectiveness of hypoglycemic drugs [21]. PCE might enhance 
glucose utilization because they significantly reduced the blood 
glucose level in db/db mice. In glucose-fed mice, the elevated </p>

<p>blood glucose levels remained higher after 120 min. PCE signifi-
cantly inhibited increases in the blood glucose level during the 
OGTT in db/db mice (Fig. 2). PCE significantly improved glucose 
tolerance and this fact could be attributed to the potentiation 
of the insulin effect of plasma by increasing the pancreatic 
secretion of insulin from existing β-cells or its release from 
bound insulin. 
GK, G6pase, and glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) 
are important enzymes in carbohydrate metabolism [22]. 
Analysis of liver enzyme activity in the present study indicated 
that GK activity was also increased following PCE 50 treatment, 
by 37% as compared to the DC group (data not shown). Acyl-
Coenzyme A oxidase 1 (ACOX1) and carnitine acetyltransferase 
(Cpt) are important proteins involved in fatty acid β-oxidation 
[23-27] and acyl-CoA synthetase long-chain family member 5 
(ACSL5) is involved in lipogenesis [28, 29]. Microarray analysis 
identified 2 genes with increased liver expression levels and 
3 genes with altered adipose expression in PCE-treated db/db 
mice (Table 3). These results indicated that PCE may affect 
expression of some genes involved in carbohydrate and lipid 
metabolism and promote fatty acid oxidation in adipose tissue. 
AMPK belongs to the family of energy sensing enzymes that 
are activated by cellular stresses resulting in ATP depletion, thus 
acting like a 'fuel gauge' [30]. Upon activation, AMPK functions 
to restore cellular ATP by inhibiting ATP consumption processes 
as well as accelerating ATP generation processes [31]. This 
cascade is activated by stresses such as prolonged exercise, 
electrical stimulation of skeletal muscle, heart muscle ischemia, 
and through inhibition of the tricarboxylic acid cycle or 
oxidative phosphorylation [32,33]. As shown in Fig. 4A, PCE 
significantly phosphorylated AMPK and ACC compared to DC 
group. The phosphorylation of ACC decreases its activity and 
the concentration of malonyl CoA, the resulting product from 
the reaction, was decreased so that the activity of carnitine 
palmitoyltransferase (CPT1), which delivers fatty acid by using 
mitochondrial for acid oxidation was promoted [34]. In general, 
activation of AMPK down-regulates biosynthetic pathways such 
as fatty acid and cholesterol biosynthesis, yet switches on 
catabolic pathways that generate ATP, such as fatty acid oxidation, 
glucose uptake and glycolysis. In this study, we founded that 
PCE reduced hepatic glucose production through AMPK activation 
and ACC inactivation and decreased PEPCK or G6Pase gene 
expression (Fig. 4B). The AMPK pathway is a major mechanism 
enhancing glucose transport into skeletal muscle [35]. Skeletal 
muscle is the main site for glucose disposal in the body and 
there are two ways to stimulate glucose uptake into skeletal 
muscle: insulin dependent and insulin independent. Insulin resistance 
is one of the early defects detected in the muscle of diabetes 
patients and insulin resistance is mainly caused by insulin signaling 
pathway defects. Activation of AMPK by AICAR in rat or muscle 
cells overexpressing constitutively active AMPK increases glucose 
uptake and causes translocation of the glucose transporters GLUT1 
and GLUT4 from microvesicles to the plasma membrane, esta-
blishing the link between AMPK activation, glucose transport 
and the translocation of glucose transporters [35]. As shown 
in Fig. 4B, PCE markedly stimulated GLUT4 gene expression. 
Our results suggest that PCE significantly decreased blood 
glucose levels by increasing the levels of insulin, C-peptide, </p>



<p>Anti-diabetic effect of purple corn extract </p>

<p>adiponectin and also activating AMPK, decreased PEPCK, G6pase 
genes in liver, and GLUT4 expressions in skeletal muscle. Since 
PCE, controlled hyperglycemia and hyperlipidemia in db/db 
mice, it may be a successive candidate for treatment of type 
2 diabetes. The extensive in vivo studies and clinical evaluation 
of PCE have to carry out to validate the previous observations. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Jong Bin Ji, Se Jin Choi, Set Byeol Kim, Jeong Geun 
Byeon and Soo Kyeong Lee for helpful experiments in this study. </p>



<p>Bo Huang et al. </p>





</text></tei>