<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4733777" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>IntroductIon </p>

<p>Approximately 15-20% of percutaneous coronary 
intervention (PCI) are performed to treat coronary 
bifurcations lesions. 
[1,2] Coronary bifurcation lesions are one 
of the most challenging subsets in interventional cardiology, 
and the treatment is still the subject of substantial debate. 
Several randomized clinical trials have recommended a 
provisional technique of stenting as the routine bifurcation 
stenting technique. 
[3-6] However, side branch (SB) occlusion 
after main vessel (MV) stenting is a serious procedural 
complication for the provisional approach. Previous studies 
have reported that the reference vessel diameter (RVD) of 
the SB and the prevalence of a stenosis at SB ostium were 
independent predictors of SB occlusion, 
[7-9] but numerous 
factors such as clinical and angiographic characteristics </p>

<p>could impact the risk of SB occlusion. Accordingly, this study 
was designed to characterize the incidence and predictors of 
major SB occlusion during coronary bifurcation intervention 
in a cohort of consecutive patients who underwent PCI in a 
single center for cardiovascular disease. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study population </p>

<p>All the patients enrolled in our study population were patients 
with coronary bifurcation lesions, which were defined as a 
coronary artery narrowing occurring adjacent to or involving 
the origin of a significant SB. 
Background: Major side branch (SB) occlusion is one of the most serious complications during percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) 
for bifurcation lesions. We aimed to characterize the incidence and predictors of major SB occlusion during coronary bifurcation intervention. 
Methods: We selected consecutive patients undergoing PCI (using one stent or provisional two stent strategy) for bifurcation lesions 
with major SB. All clinical characteristics, coronary angiography findings, PCI procedural factors and quantitative coronary angiographic 
analysis data were collected. Multivariate logistic regression analysis was performed to identify independent predictors of SB occlusion. 
SB occlusion after main vessel (MV) stenting was defined as no blood flow or any thrombolysis in myocardial infarction (TIMI) flow 
grade decrease in SB after MV stenting. 
Results: Among all 652 bifurcation lesions, 32 (4.91%) SBs occluded. No blood flow occurred in 18 lesions and TIMI flow grade 
decreasing occurred in 14 lesions. In multivariate analysis, diameter ratio between MV/SB (odds ratio [OR]: 7.71, 95% confidence interval 
[CI]: 1.53-38.85, P = 0.01), bifurcation angle (OR: 1.03, 95% CI: 1.02-1.05, P &lt; 0.01), diameter stenosis of SB before MV stenting 
(OR: 1.05, 95% CI: 1.03-1.07, P &lt; 0.01), TIMI flow grade of SB before MV stenting (OR: 3.59, 95% CI: 1.48-8.72, P &lt; 0.01) and left 
ventricular eject fraction (LVEF) (OR: 1.06, 95% CI: 1.02-1.11, P &lt; 0.01) were independent predictors of SB occlusion. 
Conclusions: Among clinical and angiographic findings, diameter ratio between MV/SB, bifurcation angle, diameter stenosis of SB 
before MV stenting, TIMI flow grade of SB before MV stenting and LVEF were predictive of major SB occlusion after MV stenting. </p>

<p>Key words: Coronary Bifurcation Lesions; Major Side Branch Occlusion; Percutaneous Coronary Intervention </p>

<p>Address for correspondence: Dr. Ke-Fei Dou, 
Department of Cardiology, State Key Laboratory of Cardiovascular Disease, 
Cardiovascular Institute, Fuwai Hospital and National Center for Cardiovascular 
Diseases, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical 
College, A 167, Beilishi Road, Xicheng District, Beijing 100037, China 
E-Mail: drdoukefei@126.com </p>

<p>Access this article online </p>

<p>Quick Response Code: 
Website: 
www.cmj.org </p>

<p>DOI: 
10.4103/0366-6999.157654 </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ June 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 11 </p>

<p>
lesion consists at least one major SB. The definition of major 
SB was consistent with previous studies: RVD measured by 
quantitative coronary angiography (QCA) ≥2.0 mm. 
[11,12] To 
investigate predictors of SB occlusion after MV stenting, 
exclusion criteria was: Patients undergoing elective SB 
stenting before MV stenting. Among the 7007 patients, 5172 
patients without bifurcation lesions and 290 patients with 
bifurcation lesions undergoing elective SB stenting were 
excluded. 908 coronary bifurcation patients with SB baseline 
reference diameter &lt;2.0mm were also excluded. Finally, 
637 patients with 652 bifurcation lesions which met all the 
inclusion criteria and had no exclusion criteria were included 
in this study [Figure 1]. Primary endpoint of the study was 
SB occlusion, which was defined as no blood flow or any 
thrombolysis in myocardial infarction (TIMI) flow grade 
decrease in SB after MV stenting. The Ethics Committee of 
the Cardiovascular Institute and Fuwai Hospital approved 
this study. </p>

<p>Procedure and periprocedural practices </p>

<p>Coronary angioplasty was performed in the conventional 
manner and coronary stents or other procedures/devices 
were used only when required. In all cases, the interventional 
strategy and instrumentation used were at the discretion of the 
interventional cardiologists. Decisions on treatment strategy 
for bifurcation lesions were made by individual operators. The 
administration of periprocedural antiplatelet and antithrombotic 
medications was based on the operator's discretion and current 
guidelines. Administration of 300 mg clopidogrel and 300 mg 
aspirin as loading doses within the 24 h before the procedure 
was mandatory. Lifelong aspirin (100 mg/d) was prescribed to 
all patients. At least 12 months of clopidogrel (75 mg/d) was 
recommended to all patients. </p>

<p>Data collection and quantitative coronary angiography </p>

<p>Clinical data were obtained through a review of the medical 
records. All baseline and procedural coronary angiography 
were reviewed and analyzed by an independent core laboratory 
at Fuwai Hospital. Coronary angiography findings including 
bifurcation location, Medina classification, baseline and post </p>

<p>procedural TIMI flow grade in MV and SB as well as plaque 
distribution were recorded. Procedural characteristics such as 
SB predilation and jailed wire in the SB were also observed. </p>

<p>Quantitative coronary angiography was performed using 
standard quantitative analyses and definitions. 
[13] A main principle 
of our QCA approach was to ensure as little observer interference 
as possible. Angiograms obtained at baseline and before MV 
stenting were analyzed with the use of a computer-based system 
dedicated to bifurcation analysis (Qangio XA, version 7.3, Medis, 
Leiden, the Netherlands). We obtained quantitative angiographic 
measurements of the four segments of the bifurcation lesion: The 
proximal MV segment, the distal MV segment, the SB segment 
and the bifurcation core segment [Figure 2]. Bifurcation core is 
defined as the central part of the bifurcation which begins where 
the common vessel starts to split into two branches and ends at 
the carinal point, 
[14] which area was calculated by the <rs type="software">Qangio XA</rs> software. We also obtained the bifurcation angle (the angle 
between the distal MV and the SB) from the analysis system. </p>

<p>In addition to the inherent data from the QCA analysis, 
another innovative variable was calculated based on the QCA 
data: Diameter ratio between MV/SB (formula = [reference 
diameter of proximal MV + reference diameter of distal 
MV]/2 [reference diameter of SB]), which is a parameter 
reflects the relative plaque burden of SB. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Continuous data are presented as mean ± standard deviation 
(SD) and were compared using the Student's t-test. Categorical 
variables were summarized as counts and percentages and 
were compared by Chi-square test or Fisher's exact test as 
appropriate. </p>

<p>Multivariate logistic regression analysis was performed 
to identify independent predictors of SB occlusion. The 
covariates that were either statistically significant on 
univariate analysis (P &lt; 0.25) or considered important were 
included in the multivariate model. Totally, 28 covariates 
were employed in the multivariate model, including diabetes, 
previous PCI, medina classification, plaque location, </p>

<p>Figure 1: Flowchart of the study. PCI: Percutaneous coronary intervention; SB: Side branch. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ June 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 11 </p>



<p>reference diameter of the proximal and distal MV, reference 
diameter of the SB, preprocedural percent diameter stenosis 
of the proximal MV, preprocedural percent diameter stenosis 
of the distal MV, true bifurcation lesions, lesion length of 
the MV and SB, bifurcation angle, predilation of the SB and 
jailed wire in SB. Estimates of the adjusted differences in 
risks are presented with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) of 
the difference. All P values were two-tailed, and a P &lt; 0.05 
was considered as statistically significant. All analyses were 
performed with <rs id="software-1" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">9.4</rs> system (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, NC, 
USA). </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>Patient, lesion and procedural characteristics </p>

<p>Side branch occlusion occurred in 32 (4.9%) of 652 
bifurcation lesions treated with one stent technique or MV 
stenting first strategy. Patients and lesions were divided into 
two groups according to SB occlusion or not. </p>

<p>Patient characteristics are shown in Table 1. All the baseline 
characteristics were balanced between the two groups. 
Lesion characteristics are presented in Table 2. Medina 
classification and plaque distribution differ significantly 
between the two study groups. Procedure data are shown in 
Table 3. All the data except the rate of jailed wire in SB are 
significantly different between the two groups. QCA data 
are presented in Table 4. There are significant differences 
between the two groups in diameter stenosis of proximal 
MV, bifurcation core and SB. However, regarding the lesion 
length, there were no significantly different between the two 
groups of all four parts. Lesions in SB occlusion group have 
higher bifurcation angle, diameter ratio between MV/SB and 
diameter stenosis of SB before MV stenting. </p>

<p>Fate of occluded side branch after main vessel stenting </p>

<p>No blood flow occurred in 18 (56.3%) lesions and TIMI flow 
grade decreasing occurred in 14 (43.7%) lesions. Blood flow 
in SB was restored spontaneously in 2 (6.3%) lesions and 
by SB intervention in 3 (9.4%) lesions of 32 occluded SB. 
A total of 27 (84.4%) lesions were occluded permanently. 
For SB interventions, rewiring and balloon angioplasty was 
performed in 4 SBs, among them, 1 SB was permanently 
occluded despite rewiring and ballooning. </p>

<p>Predictors of side branch occlusion </p>

<p>Independent predictors of SB occlusion are presented in 
Table 5. After adjustment using a multiple logistic regression 
model, diameter ratio between MV/SB and TIMI flow grade 
of SB before stenting is two important predictors. Bifurcation 
angle, diameter stenosis of SB before MV stenting and 
left ventricular eject fraction (LVEF) are also predictive 
of SB occlusion. Preprocedural diameter stenosis of the 
proximal MV, distal MV was not independent predictors of 
major SB occlusion. Also, the lesion length of proximal MV, </p>

<p>Table 1: Characteristics of patients undergoing PCI </p>

<p>Characteristics 
SB occlusion (n = 31) 
No SB occlusion (n = 606) 
P </p>

<p>Age, years 
57.5 ± 12.2 
57.7 ± 10.2 
0.93 
Male 
26/31 (83.9) 
494/606 (81.5) 
0.74 
BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>26.4 ± 3.2 
26.1 ± 3.3 
0.70 
Diabetes 
10/31 (32.3) 
152/606 (25.1) 
0.37 
Hypertension 
18/31 (58.1) 
356/606 (58.9) 
0.92 
Hyperlipemia 
24/31 (77.4) 
477/606 (79.0) 
0.84 
Myocardial infarction in 1-month 
8/31 (25.8) 
109/606 (18.0) 
0.27 
Emergency PCI 
3/31 (9.7) 
14/606 (2.3) 
0.06 
Unstable angina 
12/31 (38.7) 
281/606 (46.5) 
0.40 
LVEF 
59.5 ± 9.9 
63.1 ± 7.7 
0.06 
Previous myocardial infarction (&gt;1-month) 
7/31 (22.6) 
99/606 (16.3) 
0.36 
Previous PCI 
7/31 (22.6) 
99/606 (16.4) 
0.37 
Previous CABG 
0/31 (0) 
2/606 (0.3) 
0.75 
Previous stroke 
5/31 (16.1) 
66/606 (10.9) 
0.55 
Family history of CAD 
3/31 (9.7) 
104/606 (17.2) 
0.40 
Previous peripheral vascular disease 
4/31 (12.9) 
93/606 (15.4) 
0.90 
Smoking history 
14/31 (45.2) 
242/606 (40.1) 
0.57 
Values presented as n/N (%) or mean ± SD. SB: Side branch; BMI: Body mass index; PCI: Percutaneous coronary intervention; LVEF: Left ventricular 
ejection fraction; CABG: Coronary artery bypass grafting; CAD: Coronary artery disease; SD: Standard deviation. </p>

<p>Figure 2: Schematic diagram of quantitative coronary angiographic 
analysis. Bifurcation lesions were analyzed as four segments: The 
proximal MV segment, the distal MV segment, the SB segment and the 
bifurcation core segment. MV: Main vessel; SB: Side branch. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ June 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 11 </p>

<p>
Table 2: Lesion characteristics </p>

<p>Characteristics 
SB occlusion (n = 32) 
No SB occlusion (n = 620) 
P </p>

<p>Coronary distribution 
Right dominant coronary 
30/32 (93.8) 
568/620 (91.6) 
0.69 
Left dominant coronary 
1/32 (3.1) 
38/620 (6.1) 
Codominant coronary 
1/32 (3.1) 
14/620 (2.3) 
Location of bifurcation 
LM 
0/32 (0) 
30/620 (4.8) 
0.49 
LAD 
16/32 (50.0) 
336/620 (54.2) 
LCX 
7/32 (21.9) 
124/600 (20.0) 
RCA 
9/32 (28.1) 
130/600 (21.0) 
Medina classification 
1,0,0 
5/32 (15.6) 
182/620 (29.4) 
&lt;0.01 
0,1,0 
3/32 (9.4) 
204/620 (32.9) 
1,1,0 
3/32 (9.4) 
79/620 (12.7) 
1,1,1 
9/32 (28.1) 
78/620 (12.6) 
0,0,1 
1/32 (3.1) 
2/620 (0.3) 
1,0,1 
5/32 (15.6) 
42/620 (6.8) 
0,1,1 
6/32 (18.8) 
33/620 (5.3) 
MV 
Plaque located at the same side of SB 
18/32 (56.3) 
174/620 (28.1) 
&lt;0.01 
Moderate-severe lesion calcification 
4/32 (12.5) 
27/593 (4.4) 
0.09 
Moderate-severe angulation 
15/32 (46.9) 
347/620 (56.0) 
0.31 
Thrombosis 
2/32 (6.3) 
22/620 (3.5) 
0.76 
Preprocedural TIMI flow grade 
TIMI 1 
5/32 (15.6) 
27/620 (4.4) 
0.12 
TIMI 2 
5/32 (15.6) 
72/620 (11.6) 
TIMI 3 
22/32 (68.8) 
521/620 (84.0) 
Irregular plaque 
3/32 (9.4) 
21/620 (3.4) 
0.20 
SB 
Moderate-severe lesion calcification 
0/32 (0) 
2/620 (0.3) 
1.00 
Moderate-severe angulation 
2/32 (6.3) 
26/620 (4.2) 
0.91 
Thrombosis 
0/32 (0) 
1/620 (0.2) 
1.00 
Preprocedural TIMI flow grade 
TIMI 1 
0/32 (0) 
4/620 (0.6) 
0.63 
TIMI 2 
3/32 (9.4) 
8/620 (1.3) 
TIMI 3 
29/32 (90.6) 
608/620 (98.1) 
Irregular plaque 
1/32 (3.1) 
5/600 (0.8) 
0.70 
Values presented as n/N (%). SB: Side branch; LM: Left main; LAD: Left anterior descending; LCX: Left circumflex; OM: Obtuse marginal branch; 
RCA: Right coronary artery; MV: Main vessel; TIMI: Thrombolysis in myocardial infarction. </p>

<p>distal MV, bifurcation core and SB were not predictive of 
major SB occlusion. </p>

<p>Using SB occlusion after MV stenting as a state variable 
and these five independent predictors were as test variables, 
a receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve was 
generated [Figure 3]. The area under the ROC curve was 
0.84 (95% CI: 0.81-0.87, P &lt; 0.01). </p>

<p>dIscussIon </p>

<p>Nowadays, the provisional strategy has been considered as 
the preferred stenting technique in the majority of coronary 
bifurcation lesions. Provisional technique of stenting has been 
found to be noninferior to elective double stenting with respect 
to clinical outcome in 5-year follow-up. 
[15] However, abrupt 
closure of the SB may occur after MV stent implantation. The 
complication of SB occlusion in complex bifurcation lesions </p>

<p>Figure 3: Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve. The area under 
ROC curve was 0.84 (95% confidence interval: 0.81-0.87, P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ June 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 11 </p>



<p>Table 3: Procedural characteristics </p>

<p>Characteristics 
SB occlusion (n = 32) 
No SB occlusion (n = 620) 
P </p>

<p>MV 
Dissection before MV stenting 
2/32 (6.3) 
8/620 (1.3) 
0.14 
TIMI flow grade before MV stenting 
TIMI 0 
0/32 (0) 
1/620 (0.2) 
0.50 
TIMI 1 
2/32 (6.3) 
3/620 (0.5) 
TIMI 2 
1/32 (3.1) 
3/620 (0.5) 
TIMI 3 
29/32 (90.6) 
613/620 (98.9) 
SB 
SB predilation 
4/32 (12.5) 
116/620 (18.7) 
0.38 
TIMI flow grade before MV stenting 
TIMI 0 
1/32 (3.1) 
0/620 (0) 
0.17 
TIMI 1 
2/32 (6.3) 
0/620 (0) 
TIMI 2 
1/32 (3.1) 
3/620 (0.5) 
TIMI 3 
28/32 (87.5) 
617/620 (99.5) 
Jailed wire in SB 
5/32 (15.6) 
227/620 (36.6) 
0.016 
Values presented as n/N (%). SB: Side branch; MV: Main vessel; TIMI: Thrombolysis in myocardial infarction. </p>

<p>Table 4: Quantitative coronary angiographic analysis </p>

<p>Items 
SB occlusion (n = 32) 
No SB occlusion (n = 620) 
P </p>

<p>Proximal MV 
Reference diameter (mm) 
3.2 ± 0.4 
3.1 ± 0.5 
0.20 
Diameter stenosis (%) 
64.0 ± 27.9 
53.4 ± 28.8 
0.04 
Lesion length (mm) 
10.0 ± 4.6 
12.3 ± 7.3 
0.07 
Distal MV 
Reference diameter (mm) 
2.9 ± 0.5 
2.7 ± 0.5 
0.03 
Diameter stenosis (%) 
57.6 ± 24.2 
56.5 ± 25.3 
0.79 
Lesion length (mm) 
9.9 ± 7.4 
9.6 ± 7.1 
0.84 
SB 
Reference diameter (mm) 
2.3 ± 0.2 
2.3 ± 0.3 
0.14 
Diameter stenosis (%) 
52.8 ± 23.4 
32.3 ± 21.0 
&lt;0.01 
Lesion length (mm) 
3.9 ± 2.2 
3.6 ± 2.1 
0.45 
Bifurcation core 
Reference diameter (mm) 
3.1 ± 0.5 
3.0 ± 0.5 
0.14 
Diameter stenosis (%) 
47.2 ± 31. 7 
33.0 ± 28.9 
0.02 
Lesion length (mm) 
3.5 ± 1.6 
3.1 ± 1.8 
0.14 
Bifurcation angle (°) 
66.7 ± 26.3 
53.5 ± 21.0 
&lt;0.01 
Diameter ratio between MV/SB 
1.4 ± 0.2 
1.3 ± 0.2 
0.01 
The most severe diameter stenosis of MV (%) 
79.4 ± 16.0 
74.7 ± 15.6 
0.11 
Total lesion length of MV (mm) 
23.4 ± 9.2 
25.0 ± 10.0 
0.34 
Diameter stenosis of SB before MV stenting (%) 
54.1 ± 23.3 
33.5 ± 19.2 
&lt;0.01 
Diameter stenosis of MV before MV stenting (%) 
57.0 ± 16.6 
52.8 ± 15.8 
0.18 
Values presented as mean ± SD. SB: Side branch; MV: Main vessel; SD: Standard deviation. </p>

<p>limits the utilization of provisional stenting. Identifying the 
predictors of SB occlusion could help to select the optimal 
intervention strategy during coronary bifurcation PCI. 
Although previous studies have reported that the RVD of 
the SB and the SB ostial stenosis are independent predictors 
of SB occlusion, 
[7,8] SB occlusions are determined by many 
factors including the clinical and angiographic characteristics. 
Accordingly, our study sought to characterize the predictors 
of SB occlusion during coronary bifurcation intervention in a 
cohort of consecutive patients who underwent PCI in a large 
single center for cardiovascular disease. </p>

<p>Table 5: Independent predictors of SB occlusion </p>

<p>Variables 
OR 
95% CI 
P </p>

<p>Diameter ratio between MV/SB 
7.71 
1.53-38.85 
0.01 
Bifurcation angle 
1.03 
1.02-1.05 
&lt;0.01 
Diameter stenosis of SB before 
MV stenting </p>

<p>1.05 
1.03-1.07 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>TIMI flow grade of SB before 
MV stenting </p>

<p>3.59 
1.48-8.72 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Left ventricular eject 
fraction (1% decrement) </p>

<p>1.06 
1.02-1.11 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>CI: Confidence interval; SB: Side branch; MV: Main vessel; 
TIMI: Thrombolysis in myocardial infarction; OR: Odds ratio. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ June 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 11 </p>

<p>
The major findings of this study are that: (1) Angiography 
characteristics like diameter stenosis of SB before MV 
stenting, TIMI flow grade of SB before MV stenting 
and bifurcation angle are independent predictors of SB 
occlusion; (2) Innovative parameter in this study "diameter 
ratio between MV/SB" is an important predictor of SB 
occlusion; (3) LVEF is also predictive for SB occlusion 
after MV stenting. </p>

<p>Diameter stenosis of SB at baseline has been reported to 
be a predictive factor of SB occlusion, 
[7,16-18] also, diameter 
stenosis of SB before MV stenting has been considered as an 
independent predictor of SB occlusion. 
[6,19] Diameter stenosis 
of SB before MV stenting can reflect the real plaque burden 
and lesion severity of SB. Both diameter stenosis of SB at 
baseline and diameter stenosis of SB before MV stenting 
were enrolled in the present study and only diameter stenosis 
of SB before MV stenting was selected as an independent 
predictor. Arteries with lower TIMI flow grade are more 
likely to have thrombus or other complex lesion features, 
and, therefore, are more likely to have SB occlusion. Previous 
study has reported that preprocedural TIMI Grade 2 flow in 
SB was a predictive factor for SB occlusion. 
[19] In our study, 
TIMI flow grade of SB before MV stenting was found to be 
an independent predictor of SB occlusion after MV stenting. 
We also found that the risk of SB occlusion increased as the 
ratio of the diameter between MV/SB increased, which is 
concordant with the results of previous studies. 
[20] Diameter 
ratio between MV/SB reflects the relative plaque volume 
of MV. Larger diameter ratio between MV/SB indicates 
relatively larger plaque burden to SB. </p>

<p>One study found that LVEF &lt;50% was a risk factor for 
periprocedural myocardial infarction (hazard ratio: 2.08, 
95% CI: 1.13-3.82, P = 0.018). 
[21] Hahn et al. have reported 
that LVEF of patients in SB occlusion group (median: 56.0%, 
interquartile range: 47.0-63.0%) were significantly lower 
than patients in no SB group (median: 60.0%, interquartile 
range: 54.0-65.7%) (P &lt; 0.01). 
[18] However, Hahn et al. 
failed to detect LVEF as an independent predictor of SB 
occlusion in multivariable analysis. LVEF was selected as 
an independent predictor of SB occlusion after adjustment 
using a multivariable model in the present study. One 
potential explanation is that lower LVEF may directly reflect 
impaired coronary blood flow, 
[22,23] which could contribute 
to SB occlusion. </p>

<p>The effect of bifurcation angle on the rate of SB occlusion 
during PCI is controversial. Previous studies have reported 
that smaller angle in coronary bifurcations predicted higher 
SB compromise, restenosis, and major adverse cardiac 
events (MACE) rates based on small sample size. </p>

<p>[20]   However, Yoshitaka Goto et al. reported that bifurcation 
angle was not associated with SB compromise after MV 
stenting. 
[24] On the other hand, Dzavik et al. found that 
bifurcation angle &gt;50° is an independent predictor of MACE 
after bifurcation crush stenting. 
[25] In our study, a wide 
bifurcation angle predicted SB occlusion after MV stenting. 
Part of the explanation was that bifurcations with smaller </p>

<p>bifurcation angle was easier for flow diversion into SB and 
too large bifurcation angle might increase the pressure drop 
and flow resistance, 
[26] thus increasing the SB occlusion risk. 
Another potential explanation was that increasing bifurcation 
angle decreased wall shear stress and increases oscillatory 
shear index significantly around the carina, 
[27] which might 
induce plaque proliferation at the bifurcation region. </p>

<p>[28,29]   Higher plaque volume in bifurcation core may contribute 
to the higher SB occlusion risk. </p>

<p>Both jailed wire in SB and predilatation of SB were 
considered as potential factors affecting SB occlusion in the 
present study. After univariate analysis, jailed wire in SB and 
predilatation of SB were employed in the multivariate model; 
however, none of them was selected as an independent risk 
factor for SB occlusion. The results of the present study 
was consistent with previous studies 
[18] and differences in 
technique were not independent predictors of SB occlusion. 
Although jailed wire in SB and other procedural factors 
may affect the SB occlusion and SB flow recovery, none of 
these factors were selected as independent predictors of SB 
occlusion in the present study. Acute coronary syndrome has 
reported to be an independent predictor of SB occlusion, </p>

<p>[18]   nevertheless, there is no significant difference in unstable 
angina, myocardial infarction within 1 month or emergency 
PCI between the two groups in the present study. Other 
factors which may be considered as predictors of SB 
occlusion like thrombus burden and lesion length of SB were 
also not selected as independent predictors of SB occlusion. 
Additional prospective clinical studies may further help to 
clarify these questions. </p>

<p>Previous studies have reported that the incidence of 
SB occlusion was 7.37-19.00%. 
[8,9,30] In our study, the 
rate of SB occlusion was 4.91%. This wide range of SB 
occlusion rate can be attributable to the difference in RVD 
of SB in these studies. Smaller RVD was an independent 
predictor of SB occlusion reported in the previous study, </p>

<p>[9]   and the rate of SB occlusion do increase as the RVD of 
SB become smaller. 
[8,9,30] Compared with these previous 
studies, the mean RVD of SB was larger in the present 
study (2.3 ± 0.2 mm), which may explain the relative lower 
incidence of SB occlusion. </p>

<p>In the present study, the mean reference of SB was 
2.3 ± 0.2 mm in SB occlusion group, and not all SBs were 
suitable for stent implantation. Selective two-stent strategy 
is helpful to prevent SB occlusion for large SB with high 
risk of occlusion. For these relative small SBs with high 
occlusion risk, jailed-balloon technique is recommended in 
consideration of that jailed-balloon technique was associated 
with a high procedural success rate, lower rates of SB loss 
and MACE at late follow-up. </p>

<p>[31,32]   Compared with previous studies, the strength of our study 
is that we have included all the clinical, angiographic, 
procedural factors as well as other innovative parameters 
like diameter ratio between MV/SB in this large-scale study, 
which is significantly predictive of SB occlusion. Another </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ June 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 11 </p>



<p>strength of our study was that the study was conducted in 
a consecutive cohort of bifurcation patients, which could 
reflect the real-world clinical practice. </p>

<p>There are several limitations of our study. First, we designed 
our trial as a mechanistic angiographic study that addressed 
the issue of identifying predictors of SB occlusion after 
MV stenting. Hence, our study was not powered to address 
clinical endpoints, but further studies are needed to research 
the impact on long-term clinical outcomes. Second, selection 
of treatment strategies, stent types, and other instruments 
were at the discretion of operators. Our findings are subject 
to selection bias and compounded with unmeasured 
variables. Additionally, due to the low incidence of major 
SB occlusion, only 32 cases of SB occlusion were included 
in the present study, there is a possibility of statistical over 
fit which could limit reproducibility of this model in other 
populations. </p>

<p>In conclusion, among clinical and coronary angiographic 
findings, diameter ratio between MV/SB, bifurcation angle, 
diameter stenosis of SB before MV stenting, TIMI flow 
grade of SB before MV stenting and LVEF were predictive 
of major SB occlusion after MV stenting. </p>

<p>references </p>



<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ June 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 11 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>