<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4985391" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Essential tremor (ET) is the most common movement </p>

<p>disorder that is frequently treated by propranolol or primidone. How-
ever, 30% of patients with ET do not respond to either propranolol or 
primidone. The objective of this study was to assess the efficacy and 
safety of topiramate for ET. 
We searched the MEDLINE, EMBASE, and the Cochrane Central 
Register of Controlled Trials for relevant randomized controlled trials 
on the effects of topiramate for ET. A meta-analysis technique was 
applied to estimate the efficacy and safety of topiramate. The primary 
outcome was the change in the Fahn-Tolosa-Marin tremor rating scale 
(TRS). The secondary outcomes included the respective change in the 
location, motor tasks/function and function disability scores, and 
adverse events. 
We included 3 randomized controlled trials with a total of 294 
participants. Topiramate was significantly better than placebo in redu-
cing TRS of patients with ET (mean difference [MD] À8.58, 95% 
confidence interval [CI] À15.46 to À1.70). Changes from the scales of 
upper limb tremor severity (MD À5.12, 95% CI À7.79 to À2.45), motor 
tasks/function (MD À5.07, 95% CI À7.12 to À3.03), and functional 
disability (MD À4.72, 95% CI À6.77 to À2.67) were significantly 
greater with topiramate than with placebo. More participants taking 
topiramate experienced adverse events leading to withdrawal than those 
taking placebo (risk difference 19%, 95% CI 11%-27%). 
There is consistent evidence supporting the efficacy of topiramate in 
treating ET; however, a significant proportion of participants withdrew 
due to its adverse effects. </p>

<p>(Medicine 94(43):e1809) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: AE = adverse event, AMPA = 2-amino-3-(3-
hydroxy-5-methyl-isoxazol-4-yl) propanoic acid, CI = confidence 
interval, ET = essential tremor, GABA = g-aminobutyric acid, MD 
= mean difference, RCT = randomized controlled trial, RD = risk 
difference, TRS = Fahn-Tolosa-Marin tremor rating scale. </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>ssential tremor (ET) is the most common movement dis-
order, affecting about 5% of those age 60 years or older. 
1 ET 
usually affects both upper extremities and may involve the head, 
lower limbs, neck, and voice. 
1 A small amount of alcohol 
temporarily ameliorate the tremor, 
2 frequently leading to exces-
sive alcohol intake in ET patients. 
3 Propranolol and primidone 
are considered the first-line treatments for ET. 
4,5 However, it 
has been estimated that 30% of patients with ET do not respond 
to either propranolol or primidone. 
6-8 Propranolol may cause 
fatigue, muscle weakness, impotence, and sleep disorders. 
Propranolol is contraindicated in patients with asthma and heart 
block and has clinical interactions with other drugs frequently 
used by the elderly, such as digoxin, calcium channel blockers, 
and antiarrhythmics. 
9 Primidone causes dizziness. Its active 
metabolite, phenobarbital, interferes with the metabolism of 
many drugs including warfarin. 
9 Hence, there is a need for 
alternative treatment options for ET. 
Topiramate is an anticonvulsant medication with several 
different mechanisms of action including enhancement of the 
g-aminobutyric acid (GABA) activity, carbonic anhydrase 
inhibition, antagonism of 2-amino-3-(3-hydroxy-5-methyl-
isoxazol-4-yl) propanoic acid (AMPA)/kainite receptors, and 
blockade of voltage-dependent calcium and sodium channels. </p>

<p>10   Topiramate has been approved for use in epilepsy and migraine 
prophylaxis, 
11,12 though not for ET yet. Based on the limited 
data from clinical trials, topiramate may lead to significant 
tremor reduction and improved functional disability compared 
with placebo, 
13-16 and has been proposed as a potential treat-
ment of ET. 
17 On the other hand, adverse effects, including 
concentration deficit, paresthesia, and nausea, were common in 
the patients treated with topiramate. 
18 A systemic review is thus 
needed to clarify the evident level of topiramate in treating ET. 
Herein, we conducted a systemic review and meta-analysis of 
randomized controlled trials (RCTs) to evaluate the efficacy and 
safety of topiramate in treating ET. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>We searched the MEDLINE, EMBASE, and the Cochrane 
Central Register of Controlled Trials for relevant RCTs from 
inception to May 9, 2015. We used a search strategy that 
combined ''topiramate'' and ''tremor.'' When searching the 
MEDLINE and EMBASE, we applied the RCT search filters 
devised by the Cochrane Collaboration. 
19 The complete search 
strategy is listed in the Supporting Information. The inclusion 
criteria of studies were RCTs that assessed the efficacy of 
topiramate in treating ET and reported useable data that could 
be extracted to assess the following outcomes. The primary 
outcome was the change in the overall score of the Fahn-
Tolosa-Marin tremor rating scale (TRS). 
20 The secondary 
outcomes were the respective change in the location, motor 
tasks/function, function disability subscales, and adverse events 
(AEs). </p>

<p>Editor: Sarah Mosaad. 
Received: July 25, 2015; revised: September 4, 2015; accepted: September 
17, 2015. 
From the College of Medicine, Chang Gung University (K-HC, C-CC); 
Department of Neurology, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Linkou, 
Taoyuan (K-HC); Department of Dermatology, Far Eastern Memorial 
Hospital, New Taipei (S-HW); and Centre for Evidence-Based Medicine 
and Department of Dermatology, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Chiayi, 
Taiwan (C-CC). 
Correspondence: Ching-Chi Chi, Department of Dermatology, Chang Gung 
Memorial Hospital, Chiayi, 6, Sec West, Chia-Pu Rd, Puzih, Chiayi 
61363, Taiwan (e-mail: chingchi@cgmh.org.tw). 
The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose. 
Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. 
This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License 4.0, where it is 
permissible to download, share and reproduce the work in any medium, 
provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or 
used commercially. 
ISSN: 0025-7974 
DOI: 10.1097/MD.0000000000001809 </p>

<p>Medicine </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>SYSTEMATIC REVIEW AND META-ANALYSIS </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 43, October 2015 </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 1 </p>

<p>Two authors (KC and CC), who were not blinded to the 
names of authors and institutions, screened the search results 
and selected relevant trials independently. One author (CC) 
extracted data from the relevant trials and used the Cochrane 
Collaboration tool for assessing risk of bias to evaluate the 
quality of the included trials. 
19 Another author (KC) checked 
the data and quality assessment. Disagreement was resolved by 
discussion, with a third author available for arbitration (SW). 
We conducted a meta-analysis to obtain the pooled inter-
vention effect estimates. We expressed the estimates as mean 
difference (MD) and 95% confidence interval (CI) for continu-
ous outcomes, and as risk difference (RD) and 95% CI for 
dichotomous outcomes. We calculated the I 
2 statistic to assess 
the degree of statistical heterogeneity across the included trials. 
A fixe-model was applied when there was no or low hetero-
geneity (I 
2 &lt; 50%), while a random-effects model was applied 
when there was substantial heterogeneity (I 
2 ! 50%). 
19 We used 
the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Review Manager</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">The Nordic Cochrane Centre</rs>, The 
Cochrane Collaboration, Copenhagen, Denmark, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">2012</rs>) for 
meta-analysis. 
This study used published data and thus ethical approval 
was not necessary. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Description of Studies </p>

<p>The PRISMA study flow chart is shown in Figure 1. A total 
of 117 records were identified from our search and 2 additional 
records were obtained after screening relevant reviews. Five 
RCTs were identified from these records. We selected studies 
that had assessed primary outcomes by TRS during the follow-
up. One RCT was excluded owing to the lack of TRS assess-
ment. 
15 The data of 1 RCT 
21 were repeatedly used in another 
publication; 
16 therefore, we only included the latter in this meta-
analysis. A total of 3 RCTs with 294 participants met our 
inclusion criteria and were included. 
13,14,16 The characteristics 
of these included trials are shown in Table 1. All the included 
trials were of moderate quality when appraised by using the 
Cochrane Collaboration tool for assessing risk of bias in 
randomized trials (Figure 2). </p>

<p>19   Efficacy </p>

<p>The efficacy estimates of topiramate in ET are presented in 
Figure 3. All 3 included trials reported the Fahn-Tolosa-Marin 
TRS overall score, 
13,14,16 with 2 of them reporting the respect-
ive scores of the subscales. 
14,16 When compared to placebo, 
topiramate had a significantly greater reduction in TRS overall 
score (MD À8.58, 95% CI À15.46 to À1.70, Figure 3A). Also, 
improvement with topiramate was greater than with placebo in 
all subscales. Changes from the subscale of upper limb tremor 
severity were significantly greater with topiramate than with 
placebo (MD À5.12, 95% CI À7.79 to À2.45, Figure 3B). Also, 
topiramate demonstrated a significant greater reduction in the 
subscales of motor tasks/function (MD À5.07, 95% CI À7.12 to 
À3.03, Figure 3C) and functional disability (MD À4.72, 95% CI 
À6.77 to À2.67, Figure 3D) than placebo. </p>

<p>Safety </p>

<p>Two included trials reported data on AEs, 
14,16 but the other 
included trial did not. 
13 The safety data are presented in Figure 4. 
When compared to participants taking placebo, a higher pro-
portion of those taking topiramate withdrew from treatments due </p>

<p>to AEs (RD 19%, 95% CI 11%-27%, Figure 4A). The following 
AEs were more frequently reported by participants taking topir-
amate than those taking placebo: paresthesia (RD 18%, 95% CI 
11%-24%, Figure 4B), taste perversion (RD 16%, 95% CI 10%-
23%, Figure 4C), concentration/attention difficulty (RD 13%, 
95% CI 4%-22%, Figure 4D) decreased appetite (RD 9%, 95% 
CI 4%-15%, Figure 4E), memory difficulty (RD 8%, 95% CI 
4%-13%, Figure 4F). We found no significant differences 
between participants taking topiramate and those taking placebo 
as to the frequency of other AEs such as weight loss, nausea, 
headache, dizziness, thirst, and upper respiratory tract infection 
(data not shown). </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. PRISMA study flow chart. </p>

<p>Chang et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 43, October 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The present study found consistent evidence showing that 
topiramate significantly improved ET, including upper extre-
mity tremor severity, motor task performance, and functional 
disability. These data support topiramate as an alternative 
therapeutic option in patients with ET that are unresponsive or 
who were intolerant to propranolol or primidone. However, 
the adverse effects of topiramate, including paresthesia, taste </p>

<p>perversion, and concentration/attention difficulty, decreased 
appetite and memory difficulty, led to withdrawal of treat-
ment, raising the concern of tolerability in treating ET with 
topiramate. 
The observed efficacy of topiramate in treating ET could 
be explained by one of the proposed mechanisms of action of 
topiramate, such as modulation of GABA A receptors. 
22 ET may 
be caused by a deficiency in the a1-subunit of the GABA A 
receptor, as demonstrated in a knockout model in mice. 
23 This 
animal model overlaps, in some clinical characteristics, with ET 
in humans, and it seems likely that the model reflects the 
inherited pathophysiologic processes, where there is a loss of 
inhibitory neurotransmission by cerebellar Purkinje cells. </p>

<p>23   This mechanism elucidates that a dysfunction in the cerebellar 
GABAergic system in ET, while topiramate could treat ET via 
enhancement of this GABAergic neurotransmission. 
On the other hand, our study revealed an increased risk of 
development of AEs, such as sensory changes (paresthesia or 
taste perversion), cognitive dysfunction (impaired attention, 
concentration, or memory), or decreased appetite, in the ET 
participants taking topiramate. Paresthesia or taste perversion 
induced by topiramate may be related to its carbonic anhy-
drase inhibition. 
18 Increased metabolic activities following 
high-frequency neuronal firings result in an increase in the 
intracellular concentration of bicarbonate. 
24 Given the excit-
atory effect of bicarbonate, it is possible that the inhibition of 
carbonic anhydrase ameliorates the neuronal excitation. In 
addition, the ability of topiramate to inhibit carbonic anhy-
drase is also supposed to be related to the activation of 
hyperpolarizing K 
þ conductance and then enhance the elec-
trical stabilization of neurons. 
25 As a leading cause of drug 
withdrawal, 
26 topiramate-induced cognitive dysfunction is an 
important adverse effect that affects the tolerability of drug 
compliance. Neuroimaging studies have demonstrated a sig-
nificant GABAergic potentiation with topiramate, 
27,28 which 
may disturb cognitive function by inhibitory enhancement. </p>

<p>29 -  31 The suppression of appetite by topiramate drives its use in 
eating disorders. 
32 It has been shown that stimulation of the 
lateral hypothalamus by AMPA/kainite agonist causes an 
intense rapid dose-dependent increase in food intake. 
33 Thus 
suppression of AMPA/kainite receptor by topiramate might 
contribute to decreased appetite. However, this appetite sup-
pression in the patients with ET seemed not to result in the 
weight reduction, which is reported in the trials of topiramate 
for other diseases. </p>

<p>34,35   TABLE 1. Characteristics of Included Trials </p>

<p>Study Author, 
Publication Year </p>

<p>Participants 
Interventions 
Outcomes 
Notes </p>

<p>Connor et al, 2008 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>62 Patients with symptomatic 
essential tremor involving the 
hands, head, or voice according 
to the criteria of the Tremor 
Investigation Group </p>

<p>Topiramate (400 mg/ 
day or maximum 
tolerated dose) or 
placebo for 10 weeks </p>

<p>Fahn-Tolosa-Marin Tremor 
Rating Scale (TRS) overall score. 
Respective scores of location, 
motor tasks/function, and 
function disability subscales. 
Adverse events </p>

<p>Setting: University Medical 
Centers. Country: US. 
Funding source: Ortho-
McNeil Neurologics, Inc. </p>

<p>Ondo et al, 2006 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>208 Patients with moderate to 
severe essential tremor of the 
upper limbs as defined by the 
Tremor Investigation Group </p>

<p>Topiramate (400 mg/ 
day or maximum 
tolerated dose) or 
placebo for 24 weeks </p>

<p>TRS overall score. Respective 
scores of location, motor tasks/ 
function, and function disability 
subscales. Adverse events </p>

<p>Setting: University Medical 
Centers. Country: US. 
Funding source: Ortho-
McNeil Neurologics, Inc. 
Carrasco Vargas et al, 
2011 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>24 Patients with essential tremor in 
the hands or arms according to 
the criteria of the Tremor 
Investigation Group </p>

<p>Topiramate (200 mg/ 
day or maximum 
tolerated dose) or 
placebo for 15 days </p>

<p>TRS overall score 
Setting: Medical Center. 
Country: Spain. Funding 
source: Not reported. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Risk of bias of included trials (green refers to low risk of 
bias, yellow for unclear, and red for high risk of bias). </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 43, October 2015 
Topiramate for Essential Tremor </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 3 </p>

<p>In addition to ET, topiramate is applied to the treatment 
of migraine, 
12 epilepsy, 
11 and diabetic neuropathy. 
36 A few 
well-known complications of topiramate, such as visual 
events, 
37 renal calculi, 
38 and word finding difficulties, 
39,40 were 
identified in the trial focusing on these disorders. Ciliochoroidal 
effusion syndrome, uveitis, and visual field defects were 
reported in the patients with migraine or epilepsy receiving 
topiramate treatment. 
37 The exact mechanism by which topir-
amate triggers these visual events is not completely understood. 
Most studies on topiramate and renal calculi are reported from 
epileptic patients. 
41,42 The majority of renal stones reported 
with topiramate are calcium phosphate or calcium oxalate, </p>

<p>43,44   which is believed to be due to renal tubular acidosis by 
inhibition of carbonic anhydrase type II and IV in the proximal 
and distal renal tubules. 
45,46 Word-finding difficulties have 
been described in epileptic and migrainous patients treated with 
topiramate. 
39,40 The asymmetry of neurotransmitter systems 
may explain the greater susceptibility of language areas to </p>

<p>antiepileptic drugs containing sulfhydryl residues such as topir-
amate and zonisamide. 
47 As a CYP3A4 inducer, topiramate 
may accelerate the hepatic elimination of oral contraceptives. </p>

<p>48   Female patients taking topiramate may at risks of contraceptive 
failure and unintended pregnancy. These adverse effects need to 
be attended in topiramate-treated patients with ET as well. 
The interpretation of this meta-analysis may be con-
strained by publication bias, methodological rigor of the 
included trials, and statistical accuracy. It is possible that only 
studies showing a benefit in treating ET with topiramate have 
been published. However, we could not assess the publication 
bias by funnel plot because only 3 trials were included. 
19 The 
different treatment dosages (maximum dose: 400 mg in 2 
trials, 
14,16 200 mg in the other trial) 
13 and experimental duration 
(24 weeks, 
14 10 weeks, 
16 and 15 days) 
16 may have affected the 
estimates of treatment effects. Since this is a meta-analysis of 
study-level data (instead of an individual patient data meta-
analysis), we were unable to adjust for confounding variables. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Efficacy of topiramate in treating essential tremor. </p>

<p>Chang et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 43, October 2015 </p>

<p>4 | www.md-journal.com </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>Nevertheless, the baseline characteristics of those taking topir-
amate and placebo across the 3 included trials were comparable. 
Topiramate has not been compared to propranolol or to primi-
done in treating ET. Therefore, the comparative effectiveness of 
topiramate is unknown. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>This meta-analysis included 3 RCTs consistently demon-
strating the efficacy of topiramate in treating ET, but also 
revealing a high risk of adverse effects that may lead to with-
drawals. Further studies using more statistically sophisticated </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Safety of topiramate in treating essential tremor. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 43, October 2015 
Topiramate for Essential Tremor </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 5 </p>

<p>methods may be able to more precisely explore the effect and 
the optimal dose of topiramate in treating ET. Head-to-head 
trials comparing topiramate with propranolol or to primidone 
are needed to obtain their comparative effectiveness. </p>



<p>Chang et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 43, October 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>



<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 43, October 2015 
Topiramate for Essential Tremor </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 7 </p>

</text></tei>