<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4250666" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: To investigate the involvement of ephrinB2 in periodontal tissue 
remodeling in compression areas during orthodontic tooth movement and the 
effects of compressive force on EphB4 and ephrinB2 expression in osteoblasts 
and osteoclasts. Methods: A rat model of experimental tooth movement was 
established to examine the histological changes and the localization of ephrinB2 
in compressed periodontal tissues during experimental tooth movement. 
RAW264.7 cells and ST2 cells, used as precursor cells of osteoclasts and 
osteoblasts, respectively, were subjected to compressive force in vitro. The gene 
expression of EphB4 and ephrinB2, as well as bone-associated factors including 
Runx2, Sp7, NFATc1, and calcitonin receptor, were examined by quantitative 
real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR). Results: Histological examination 
of the compression areas of alveolar bone from experimental rats showed that 
osteoclastogenic activities were promoted while osteogenic activities were 
inhibited. Immunohistochemistry revealed that ephrinB2 was strongly expressed 
in osteoclasts in these areas. Quantitative real-time PCR showed that mRNA 
levels of NFATc1, calcitonin receptor, and ephrinB2 were increased significantly 
in compressed RAW264.7 cells, and the expression of ephrinB2, EphB4, Sp7, 
and Runx2 was decreased significantly in compressed ST2 cells. Conclusions: 
Our results indicate that compressive force can regulate EphB4 and ephrinB2 
expression in osteoblasts and osteoclasts, which might contribute to alveolar 
bone resorption in compression areas during orthodontic tooth movement. 
[Korean J Orthod 2014;44(6):320-329] </p>

<p>Orthodontic tooth movement is coupled with the 
remodeling of alveolar bone, which occurs due to 
mechanical forces such as compression and tension. 1,2 
Compressive force causes bone resorption on the 
compressed side of an orthodontically moving tooth, 
resulting in tooth movement. Two major cell types 
that are actively involved in the remodeling of alveolar 
bone are osteoblasts and osteoclasts. They are sensitive 
communicators between microenvironment and genome, 
capable of restoring system homeostasis disturbed by 
orthodontic mechanics. 3 Under the load of orthodontic 
forces, many molecular reactions occur in and around 
these cells. However, the mechanism of these reactions 
has not been fully elucidated. A more comprehensive 
understanding of the underlying mechanism will provide 
valuable information for the development of agents 
regulating the activities of osteoblasts and osteoclasts to 
better control the bone resorption in compression areas, 
which is the rate-limiting step in orthodontic tooth 
movement. 4 
Some effectors of bone remodeling have been 
reported, and one of the most well-studied molecular 
networks in this process is the receptor activator of 
nuclear factor kappa B (RANK)/RANK ligand (RANKL)/ 
osteoprotegerin (OPG) pathway. 5-7 Osteoblasts can 
regulate osteoclast differentiation via this pathway. 
OPG is one of the rate-limiting agents for osteoclast 
differentiation and function, 8 since it can block the 
membrane docking of RANK and RANKL. Recently, 
another family of molecules known as ephrin/Eph has 
been demonstrated to modulate the differentiation 
of osteoblasts and osteoclasts. 9-11 Similar to RANK 
and RANKL, ephrins and Ephs have a ligand-receptor 
relationship-ephrins are transmembrane ligands, 
and Ephs are tyrosine kinase receptors. Interaction 
between ephrinB-and EphB-expressing cells results in 
bidirectional signal transduction. The activation of EphB 
receptors by ephrinB ligands is referred to as "forward 
signaling", whereas the activation of ephrinB ligands by 
EphB receptors is designated "reverse signaling". Ephrin 
and Eph were characterized initially through their roles 
in embryogenesis, 12 as ephrin-Eph signaling is critically 
involved in neural development, cell morphogenesis, 
tissue patterning, and angiogenesis. 13 
Within the ephrin/Eph family, EphB4 and its preferred 
ligand, ephrinB2, have been studied intensively in 
osteoblasts and osteoclasts. EphrinB2 expression is 
induced during osteoclast differentiation, and then 
reverse signaling through this ligand suppresses 
osteoclast differentiation, forming a negative feedback 
loop. 9 Moreover, forward signaling through the EphB4 
receptor on osteoblasts enhances their differentiation. </p>

<p>The bidirectional activation of the ephrinB2-EphB4 
signaling pathway in osteoclasts and osteoblasts leads 
to the suppression of osteoclast differentiation with 
concurrent stimulation of osteoblast differentiation 
and, consequently, bone formation. The communication 
between ephrinB2 and EphB4 has recently been 
shown to be involved in the stimulation of osteoblast 
differentiation within the osteoblast lineage. 14,15 In 
addition, ephrinB2 and EphB4 have been demonstrated 
to be regulated by mechanical forces in endothelial 
progenitor cells and periodontal ligament fibroblasts. 16-18 
It was shown that mechanical strain induced ephrinB2 
upregulation in periodontal ligament fibroblasts, 
contributing to osteogenesis at tension sites of 
orthodontic tooth movement. 17 However, the effects of 
compressive force on these two molecules in osteoblasts 
and osteoclasts have not been clearly elucidated. 
Our objective was to investigate the involvement 
of ephrinB2 in periodontal tissue remodeling in 
compression areas during orthodontic tooth movement 
and the effect of compressive force on ephrinB2 and 
EphB4 expression in osteoblasts and osteoclasts. We 
hypothesized that compressive force would affect 
alveolar bone remodeling through the regulation of 
ephrinB2 and EphB4 expression during orthodontic 
tooth movement. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Materials 
The murine monocyte/macrophage cell line RAW264.7 
and stromal cell line ST2 were obtained from the 
Chinese Academy of Sciences Cell Bank (Shanghai, 
China). A four-point bending system was obtained from 
Sichuan University (Chengdu, China). The force-loading 
plates were made from the bottom part of the 75-cm 2 
cell canted-neck culture flasks (Falcon #353135; Corning 
Life Sciences, Tewksbury, MA, USA), each 3 × 8 cm 2 in 
area and 1.15 mm thick. Rabbit anti-human ephrinB2 
polyclonal antibodies were purchased from Santa Cruz 
Biotechnology (Santa Cruz, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Experimental tooth movement 
All procedures involving animals were approved by the 
Animal Care and Use Committee of Jilin University. The 
animals used were 8-week-old male Wistar rats, with 
an average weight of 200 g. The rats were anesthetized 
by intramuscular injection with 0.2 mL·kg −1 Sumianxin 
(Academy of Military Medical Sciences, Changchun, 
China). A nickel-titanium closed-coil spring exerting 
an orthodontic force of 50 cN was ligated unilaterally 
to the maxillary first molar and incisor (Figure 1). The 
maxillary first molar on the opposite side was not moved 
and was used as the control group. We examined a total </p>

<p>Hou et al • Compressive force regulates ephrinB2 and EphB4 </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>

<p>
http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2014.44.6.320 </p>

<p>of 10 teeth in five rats. Experimental tooth movement 
was conducted for 3 days (n = 5). </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry of ephrinB2 
Rats were sacrificed by intracardial perfusion with 
4% paraformaldehyde in 0.1 M of phosphate buffer 
(pH 7.4) under anesthesia. The maxillae were dissected 
and molar-bearing segments of alveolar bone were 
cut from each side and further fixed overnight in 
4% paraformaldehyde buffer. The specimens were 
decalcified in 10% ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid 
solution (pH 7.4) for 8 weeks, and further dehydrated 
in ascending concentrations of ethanol and embedded 
in paraffin. Serial 5-μm-thick sections including the 
crestal areas mesial and distal to the maxillary molars 
were cut and mounted on L-poly-lysine-coated glass 
slides. Sections were stained with hematoxylin and 
eosin and immunohistochemistry was performed. For 
immunohistochemistry staining, endogenous peroxidase 
in the tissue section was blocked with 1% hydrogen 
peroxide for 10 minutes and then further blocked with 
1% goat serum in phosphate-buffered saline for 30 
minutes. The primary antibody used was polyclonal 
rabbit anti-human ephrinB2. An immunohistochemistry 
staining kit (Maixin Bio, Fuzhou, China) was used for 
further staining. Finally, sections were counterstained 
with hematoxylin and mounted. Negative controls were 
labeled using the same procedures, but omitting the 
incubation with primary antibodies. Staining density 
was analyzed using Image-Pro Plus (Media Cybernetics, 
Bethesda, MD, USA) and represented as the mean 
density. </p>

<p>Cell cultures 
RAW264.7 cells were maintained in low-glucose 
Dulbecco's modified Eagle medium (L-DMEM; Life 
Technologies, Gaithersburg, MD, USA) and ST2 cells in 
alpha-minimum essential medium containing 10% fetal </p>

<p>bovine serum (Life Technologies), 100 U·mL −1 penicillin, 
and 100 mg·mL −1 streptomycin (Life Technologies) 
at 37 o C in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO 2 . The 
medium was changed every 2−3 days. The cells were 
seeded onto the force-loading plate at a density of 1 
× 10 5 cells·cm −2 . RAW264.7 cells on the force-loading 
plates were cultured in L-DMEM containing 50 ng·mL −1 
recombinant mouse RANKL (rmRANKL; R&amp;D Systems, 
Minneapolis, MN, USA). RAW cells differentiated 
into tartrate resistant acid phosphatase-positive 
multinucleated osteoclastic cells in the presence of 
RANKL. 19 </p>

<p>Application of cyclic compressive force 
The force-loading plates were subjected to cyclic 
uniaxial compressive strain by the four-point bending 
system 20 at 0.5 Hz (Figure 2). Cells were loaded 
with compressive force at 2000 με (με is defined as 
deformation, with 1,000 με corresponding to 0.1% 
deformation) for 1, 2, and 4 hours, respectively. Control 
cells were cultured on similar plates without any 
mechanical loading and kept in the same incubator. </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) 
Cells were harvested after 1, 2, and 4 hours of the 
application of compressive force. Total RNA was 
extracted using an EASYspin RNA extraction reagent 
kit (Biomed, Beijing, China) from cells cultured on the 
plates according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
RNA was reverse-transcribed using the PrimerScript ® 
RT reagent kit (Takara, Dalian, China) with gDNA eraser 
to synthesize cDNA. qPCR (n = 3) was performed using 
SYBR Green Premix Ex Taq (Takara) and the MxPro 
Mx3005P real-time PCR detection system (Agilent 
Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA). Glyceraldehyde 
3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) was used as 
a normalization control. The primers used for qPCR 
were shown in Table 1. The cycling conditions were as </p>

<p>Figure 1. A rat model of orthodontic tooth movement can provide compressive force on alveolar bone. A nickel-titanium 
closed-coil spring exerting an orthodontic force was ligated unilaterally to the maxillary first molar and incisor. The 
maxillary first molar on the other side was without movement and was used as the control group. A, Lateral and occlusal 
view of the rat maxillae with appliance. B, The principle of orthodontic tooth movement: when the tooth was subjected 
to mechanical loading, some compression areas occurred on the alveolar bone surface around the tooth. </p>

<p>Hou et al • Compressive force regulates ephrinB2 and EphB4 </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>

<p>
http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2014.44.6.320 </p>

<p>follows: 95 o C for 30 seconds followed by 40 cycles of 
95 o C for 5 seconds, 55 o C for 30 seconds, and 72 o C for 1 
minute. The 2 -ΔΔCt method was used for calculating the 
relative expression levels, and values were the average of 
triplicate measurements. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
All experiments were performed on at least three 
individuals. Results are presented as the mean ± standard 
deviation (SD). The significance of the differences was 
determined using the two-tailed Student's t-test and 
one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). The difference 
was considered significant if p &lt; 0.05. The IBM <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> </p>

<p><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 19.0</rs> for Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Co.</rs>., Armonk, NY, USA) was 
used for statistical analysis. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Histological changes and ephrinB2 expression in 
the compression areas of periodontal tissues in 
experimental rats 
Histological examination showed a gap between 
the first and second molar indicating that the loaded 
maxillary first molar was moved mesially. In the 
compression area, the surface of alveolar bone was 
rough and there were resorption lacunae on the bone </p>

<p>Cell suspension </p>

<p>Plastic plate </p>

<p>A A </p>

<p>B B </p>

<p>C 
C </p>

<p>D 
E </p>

<p>Cyclic load </p>

<p>Cells </p>

<p>Figure 2. A four-point bending system can provide cyclic uniaxial compressive force on adherent cells in vitro. A, 
Actuator. B, Digital-control part. C, Culture dish with pressure head. D, Schematic representation of the apparatus used 
for application of mechanical force to cell cultures. The cell suspension was plated on a plastic plate, then, after 2 hours 
of cultivation, cells were subjected to cyclic compressive force in culture medium. E, The principle of the four-point 
bending system used for compressive force application (conceptual diagram). </p>

<p>Hou et al • Compressive force regulates ephrinB2 and EphB4 </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>

<p>
http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2014.44.6.320 </p>

<p>surface (Figure 3). Multinucleated osteoclasts were seen 
adjacent to the alveolar bone surface. No osteoblasts 
were observed in the compression area. 
Since no osteoblasts were found in the compression 
area, only ephrinB2 was examined by immuno-
histochemistry. EphrinB2 immunoreactivity was observed 
in fibroblasts in periodontal tissues from both the 
control and experimental groups (Figure 4A and 4B). 
In periodontal tissues of the control group without 
tooth movement, ephrinB2 was weakly and uniformly 
expressed in periodontal fibroblasts (Figure 4A). In 
periodontal tissues of the experimental group, ephrinB2 
was strongly expressed in osteoclasts adjacent to alveolar 
bone in the compression area (Figure 4B). Negative 
controls showed no immunolabeling (Figure 4C). As 
shown in Table 2, the difference in ephrinB2 expression 
levels in periodontal tissues between the experimental 
and control groups was statistically significant (p &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Osteoclastogenic gene expression in compressed 
RAW264.7 cells 
In order to investigate whether compressive force could 
directly stimulate osteoclast differentiation, we applied 
cyclic uniaxial compressive force produced by a four-
point bending system to RAW264.7 cells. Following 
this, gene expression was assessed for two well-known 
markers of differentiated osteoclasts, nuclear factor 
of activated T cells cytoplasmic 1 (NFATc1) 21-23 and 
calcitonin receptor (CTR). 24 As shown in Figure 5A </p>

<p>and 5B, the levels of NFATc1 and CTR mRNA were 
significantly upregulated in RAW264.7 cells after 1 hour 
and 2 hours of the application of compressive force (p 
&lt; 0.05). Our data indicate that cyclic compressive force 
can promote the differentiation of osteoclasts. </p>

<p>EphrinB2 mRNA expression in RAW264.7 cells in 
response to compressive force 
To understand the relationship between compressive 
force and ephrinB2 expression in osteoclasts, we 
evaluated the expression of ephrinB2 in RAW264.7 cells. 
As shown in Figure 5C, there was a significant increase 
in the expression of the ephrinB2 gene after 1 hour and 
2 hours in compressed RAW264.7 cells (p &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Osteogenic gene expression in compressed ST2 cells 
To investigate the response of osteoblasts to 
compressive force, we performed an in vitro experiment 
using ST2 cells. The expression of the transcription 
factors Runx2 and Sp7 was assessed in these cells after 
the application of compressive force. Runx2 plays a key 
role in mediating osteoblast maturation and is necessary 
for normal osteogenesis, 25,26 while Sp7 is believed to 
be downstream of Runx2 and may promote osteoblast 
maturation. 27,28 As shown in Figure 6A and 6B, the 
mRNA levels of Runx2 and Sp7 were significantly 
decreased in ST2 cells after the application of 
compressive force (p &lt; 0.05). These findings suggest that 
compressive force can inhibit osteoblast differentiation. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Histological examination of the compression 
areas of periodontal tissues from the experimental group. 
Multinucleated osteoclasts were seen adjacent to the 
alveolar bone surface, with no osteoblasts observed. 
Hematoxylin and eosin stain, 200× magnification. 
AB, Alveolar bone; R, root of molar; OC, osteoclast. </p>

<p>Table 1. The primers used for qPCR of various genes </p>

<p>Gene 
Forward primer (5' → 3') 
Reverse primer (5' → 3') </p>

<p>GAPDH 
ATGGGGAAGGTGAAGGTC 
TAA AAGCAGCCCTGGTGACC </p>

<p>NFATc1 
CAAGTCTCACCACAGGGCTCACTA 
TCAGCCGTCCCAATGAACAG </p>

<p>CTR 
TTACCGACGAGCAACGCCTA 
ACGAGTGATGGCGTGGATAATG </p>

<p>Runx2 
GCACAAACATGGCCAGATTCA 
AAGCCATGGTGCCCGTTAG </p>

<p>Sp7 
AAGTTATGATGACGGGTCAGGTACA 
AGAAATCTACGAGCAAGGTCTCCAC </p>

<p>EphrinB2 
ACGGTCCAACAAGACGTCCA 
GCTGTTGCCATCGGTGCTA </p>

<p>EphB4 
AGTGGCTTCGAGCCATCAAGA 
CTCCTGGCTTAGCTTGGGACTTC </p>

<p>GAPDH, glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase; 
NFATc1, nuclear factor of activated T cells cytoplasmic 1; 
CTR, calcitonin receptor; Runx2, runt-related transcription 
factor 2; SP7, specificity protein 7; G, guanine; C, cytosine; A, 
adenine; T, thymine. </p>

<p>Hou et al • Compressive force regulates ephrinB2 and EphB4 </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>

<p>
http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2014.44.6.320 </p>

<p>EphB4 and ephrinB2 mRNA expression in ST2 cells in 
response to compressive force 
It has been reported that both EphB4 and ephrinB2 
are found in osteoblasts. To understand whether EphB4 
and ephrinB2 expression in osteoblasts is affected by 
compressive force, we evaluated the expression of these 
molecules in ST2 cells. As shown in Figure 6C and 6D, 
there was a significant decrease in the expression of the </p>

<p>EphB4 gene in ST2 cells after 1 hour and 2 hours of 
exposure to compressive force (p &lt; 0.05). A significant 
decrease in the expression of ephrinB2 was also detected 
after 4 hours of compressive force (p &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The findings of this study, which show the response 
of tissues in compression areas during orthodontic 
tooth movement, agree with many previous histological 
studies. 29,30 We determined that multinucleated 
osteoclasts adhered to resorption lacunae along the 
alveolar bone surface, and no osteoblasts were observed. 
EphrinB2 was examined by immunohistochemistry; 
however, since no osteoblasts were found in the 
compression area, EphB4 expression was not assessed. 
We observed strong expression of ephrinB2 in 
osteoclasts, suggesting that this ligand may be involved </p>

<p>Figure 4. Immunohistochemical analysis of ephrinB2 expression in periodontal tissues. A, Photomicrograph showing 
weak anti-ephrinB2 antibody immunolabeling of fibroblasts in periodontal tissues from the control group (without 
tooth movement). B, Photomicrograph showing strong anti-ephrinB2 antibody immunolabeling of osteoclasts in the 
compression area of periodontal tissues from the experimental group. C, Negative controls show no immunolabeling of 
osteoclasts. All images are at 200× magnification. 
AB, Alveolar bone; OC, osteoclast. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>AB </p>

<p>OC </p>

<p>AB </p>

<p>OC </p>

<p>AB </p>

<p>Table 2. EphrinB2 mean density in periodontal tissues 
with or without exposure to compressive force </p>

<p>Group 
Mean density </p>

<p>Control 
0.293 ± 0.034 </p>

<p>Compressive force 
0.436 ± 0.042* </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation. 
*p &lt; 0.05 compared with the control group. </p>

<p>Hou et al • Compressive force regulates ephrinB2 and EphB4 </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>

<p>
http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2014.44.6.320 </p>

<p>in periodontal tissue remodeling in the compression 
area during orthodontic tooth movement. However, it is 
unknown whether the applied orthodontic force directly 
induced this cellular reaction. To clarify this point, an in 
vitro study was performed to investigate the effects of 
compressive force on ephrinB2 and EphB4 in cultured 
osteoblasts and osteoclasts. 
The direct effect of mechanical force on osteoclast 
differentiation 19 has previously been investigated in only 
a few studies. These yielded limited information, as 
many analyses were done using primary cultured bone 
cells, which were mixtures of osteoclasts, osteoblasts, 
and other undifferentiated cells. In the present study, 
by analyzing changes in the gene expression of 
NFATc1 and CTR in RAW 264.7 cells we provided direct </p>

<p>evidence that compressive force can promote osteoclast 
differentiation. 
It has been found that ephrinB2, but not EphB4, is 
present in multinucleated osteoclasts and differentiating 
mononuclear osteoclasts. 9 As such, only ephrinB2 was 
examined in RAW264.7 cells in our study. Moreover, it 
has been reported that ephrinB2 expression is induced 
and upregulated during osteoclast differentiation. 
This molecule is markedly expressed at later stages of 
osteoclast differentiation, and its induction is dependent 
on NFATc1 and the proto-oncogene c-Fos. In our study, 
osteoclast differentiation was promoted by compressive 
force and accompanied by an increase in ephrinB2 
expression. Our results therefore support previous 
findings. </p>

<p>Figure 5. The effects of compressive force on osteoclastogenic gene and ephrinB2 expression in RAW264.7 cells. 
RAW264.7 cells stimulated with RANKL were exposed to compressive force or no force for 1, 2 and 4 hours. The mRNA 
expression of A, NFATc1, B, CTR, and C, ephrinB2 was then determined in control and compressed cells using quantitative 
real-time PCR. GAPDH was used as the internal reference gene. Data from one representative experiment of three are 
shown. 
RANKL, Receptor activator of nuclear factor kappa B ligand; NFATc1, nuclear factor of activated T cells cytoplasmic 1; 
CTR, calcitonin receptor; PCR, polymerase chain reaction; GAPDH, glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase. 
*p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>Hou et al • Compressive force regulates ephrinB2 and EphB4 </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>

<p>
http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2014.44.6.320 </p>

<p>Osteoblasts and osteoclasts are two major types of bone 
cells that are responsible for bone remodeling. These 
two types of cells can communicate with each other 
via ephrinB2-EphB4 bidirectional signal transduction. 
In addition, self-communication within osteoblasts 
is also possible because osteoblasts can express both 
ephrinB2 and EphB4. In our study, EphB4 and ephrinB2 
expression in ST2 cells was downregulated by compressive 
force. This downregulation would attenuate ephrinB2-
EphB4 signaling between osteoblasts and osteoclasts, 
as well as within the osteoblast lineage. Consequently, 
osteoblast differentiation and subsequent bone formation 
via the ephrinB2-EphB4 signaling pathway would be 
attenuated, which could facilitate bone resorption in 
compression areas of alveolar bone during orthodontic 
tooth movement. 
EphrinB2 has been demonstrated to be induced by the </p>

<p>c-Fos-NFATc1 transcriptional cascade in osteoclasts, 
and is expressed at a later stage of osteoclast differ-
entiation. Furthermore, EphB4-ephrinB2 reverse 
signaling through ephrinB2 suppresses c-Fos-NFATc1 
transcription and osteoclast differentiation, forming a 
negative feedback loop. 9 In our study, in vitro and in 
vivo ephrinB2 expression was induced by compressive 
force as well as osteoclast differentiation, which is 
consistent with previous studies. 
The molecular genetic processes underlying ortho-
dontic tooth movement function as a feedback system 
of checks and balances. 3 Activator molecules beget 
suppressor molecules and then return to their steady 
states, and examples of this system include tumor 
necrosis factor and its receptor, colony stimulating 
factor-1, OPG, and RANK and RANKL. 4 EphrinB2 
and EphB4 could be added to this list of regulatory </p>

<p>Figure 6. The effects of compressive force on the expression of osteogenic genes, ephrinB2, and EphB4 in ST2 cells. 
ST2 cells were exposed to compressive force or no force for 1, 2, and 4 hours. The mRNA expression of A, Runx2, B, 
Sp7, C, ephrinB2, and D, EphB4 was then determined in control and compressed cells. Glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate 
dehydrogenase (GAPDH) was used as the internal reference gene. Data from one representative experiment of three are 
shown. 
*p &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Hou et al • Compressive force regulates ephrinB2 and EphB4 </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>

<p>
http://dx.doi.org/10.4041/kjod.2014.44.6.320 </p>

<p>molecules, as our findings suggest they regulate bone 
resorption during orthodontic tooth movement. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>EphrinB2 and EphB4 are regulated by compressive 
force in osteoclasts and osteoblasts, and therefore may 
participate in the transduction of compressive force 
into osteoclastogenesis in compression areas during 
orthodontic tooth movement. </p>



<p>Hou et al • Compressive force regulates ephrinB2 and EphB4 </p>

<p>www.e-kjo.org </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>