<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4103437" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs type="software">CLC Genomics Workbench</rs>using paired-end libraries with 350-bp fragments. Reads were quality fi l-
tered, and the adapters were removed using libngs (https://github.com/ 
sylvainforet/libngs) using a minimum quality of 25 bp and a minimum read 
size of 150 bp. The genomic assemblies were carried out with <rs type="software">SPAdes</rs> 
( Bankevich et al., 2012 ) using the following options: "-k 21,33,55,77,99,127-
careful -t 16 -m 64". 
To design phylogenetic markers that are broadly applicable, we focused 
primer design on common regions of high sequence homology. Initially, we 
compared the four Sebacina isolates from Eriochilus against the C. huegelii 
isolate within <rs type="software">CLC Genomics Workbench</rs> software. This allowed us to target 
the high homology sequence regions shared across the fi ve isolates for posi-
tioning the primers. Out of the 58,295 successful reads of Sebacina from 
C. huegelii , there were 1251 shared reads with E. pulchellus (average length 
285 bp) and 950 to 1605 shared reads with E. dilatatus isolates (average length </p>

<p>1 Manuscript • Premise of the study: To investigate fungal species identity and diversity in mycorrhizal fungi of order Sebacinales, we devel-
oped phylogenetic markers. These new markers will enable future studies investigating species delineation and phylogenetic 
relationships of the fungal symbionts and facilitate investigations into evolutionary interactions among Sebacina species and 
their orchid hosts. 
• Methods and Results: We generated partial genome sequences for a Sebacina symbiont originating from Caladenia hue-
gelii with 454 genome sequencing and from three symbionts from Eriochilus dilatatus and one from E. pulchellus using 
Illumina sequencing. Six nuclear and two mitochondrial loci showed high variability (10-31% parsimony informative 
sites) for Sebacinales mycorrhizal fungi across four genera of Australian orchids ( Caladenia , Eriochilus , Elythranthera , 
and Glossodia ). 
• Conclusions: We obtained highly informative DNA markers that will allow investigation of mycorrhizal diversity of Sebaci-
naceae fungi associated with terrestrial orchids in Australia and worldwide. </p>



<p>Applications in Plant Sciences 2014 2 ( 6 ): 1400015 
Ruibal et al.-Phylogenetic markers for Sebacina 
doi:10.3732/apps.1400015 </p>

<p>http://www.bioone.org/loi/apps </p>

<p>profi le was used consisting of a 3-min denaturation at 94 ° C; followed by 12 
touchdown cycles at 94 ° C (30 s) with the fi rst annealing temperature at 66 ° C 
(40 s) (−3 ° C/second cycle) and a primer extension at 72 ° C (1 min); then 
30 cycles at 94 ° C (30 s), 48 ° C (40 s), 72 ° C (1 min); with a fi nal extension at 
72 ° C for 20 min. Products were sequenced bidirectionally with ABI PRISM 
BigDye Terminator version 3.1 sequencing kit on an ABI 3100 automated 
sequencer (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, California, USA). Sequences were 
edited using the program <rs id="software-4" type="software">Sequencher</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">version 4.7</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Gene Codes Corporation</rs>, 
Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA) and aligned in <rs id="software-5" type="software">Geneious Pro</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">version 6.1.6</rs> 
( Drummond et al., 2011 ). Consistent and high-quality amplifi cation of all 
tested Sebacina isolates occurred for eight primer sets ( Table 2 ). Estimates of 
variability across the alignment of up to 31 sequences were performed within 
<rs id="software-6" type="software">MEGA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">version 5.2</rs> ( Tamura et al., 2011 ). The eight markers revealed 15-40% 
nucleotide diversity and 11-31% parsimony informative sites across these 
sequences ( Table 2 ). </p>

<p>Phylogenetic analyses -A multiple sequence alignment was constructed 
using the alignment tool in <rs id="software-7" type="software">Geneious Pro</rs> <rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-number">version 6.1.6</rs> ( Drummond et al., 
2011 ) before performing manual checks and minor adjustments. Phyloge-
nies of individual and concatenated loci were estimated with a maximum 
likelihood (ML) analysis using <rs id="software-8" type="software">RAxML</rs> <rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">7.0.3</rs> ( Stamatakis et al., 2008 ). 
Support for nodes was assessed for ML trees using 1000 pseudoreplicates of 
nonparametric bootstrapping in RAxML. A GTR+G substitution model was 
used for all analyses as all other models are nested inside this model. Trees were 
visualized using <rs id="software-9" type="software">FigTree</rs> <rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-number">version 1.3.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-9" type="url">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/fi gtree/</rs>/) and midpoint rooted. Among the 31 isolates, eight to 12 well-supported 
clades were identifi ed with the newly developed loci ( Fig. 1 , Appendices 
S1-S7). </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>We successfully designed polymorphic markers for eight 
putative gene coding loci that successfully amplifi ed across 
the mycorrhizal fungi species complex S. vermifera. These 
new markers will allow investigations of the species diver-
sity, phylogenetic relationships, and the specifi city of orchid 
mycorrhizal associations for a wide range of Australian ter-
restrial orchids. </p>

<p>375 and 588 bp). GenBank BLAST searches (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/) 
were conducted on 159 of C. huegelii sequences with high homology with at 
least two Eriochilus isolates. A total of 31 sequences (out of the 159) were 
identified as being associated with annotated or predicted genes from 
Basidiomycota R. T. Moore or Ascomycota (Berk.) Caval.-Sm. fungi. Prim-
ing sites were selected for 19 consensus sequences using <rs type="software">Primer3</rs> ( Rozen and 
Skaletsky, 2000 ); selection was based on product length, ease of primer de-
sign, and gene designation. </p>

<p>Genetic marker amplifi cation success and sequence diversity -Success-
ful fungal isolation, following Roche et al. (2010) , was obtained for several 
Sebacina isolates from host species within the Australian orchid genera Ca-
ladenia (14 spp.), Glossodia (2 spp.), Eriochilus (3 spp.), and Elythranthera 
(1 sp.). A total of 31 isolates were evaluated for DNA sequence diversity with 
the new fungal primers described below ( Tables 1 and 2 , Appendix 1). This 
set represented one to four isolates each from the 13 most strongly supported 
phylogenetic clades as revealed by a preliminary screen with ITS (bootstrap 
support &gt;0.78; data not shown) of Sebacina isolates associated with several 
Australian orchids. 
PCR reactions were performed in 30-μ L reactions containing 2 μ L of 
20-100 ng of template DNA, 14.75 μ L of H 2 O, 6 μ L Mango Taq 5 × PCR buf-
fer (Bioline, Sydney, Australia), 1 μ L dNTPs (2.5 mM), 1.5 μ L of MgCl 2 
(50 mM), 2 μ L bovine serum albumin (BSA; 10 mg/mL), 1.5 μ L of each primer 
(10 μ M), and 1 unit of Mango Taq polymerase (Bioline). A touchdown thermal </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Characteristics of phylogenetic primers developed for Sebacina isolates in this study . </p>

<p>Locus 
Primer sequence (5 ′ -3 ′ ) </p>

<p>Top BLAST hit to annotated 
or predicted gene </p>

<p>E -value of top hit 
in GenBank 
Fragment length (bp) GenBank accession no. </p>

<p>C2754 
F: GAAGRCAATCYTCGGCTCCATA 
Serine/threonine protein phosphatase 
2e-57~951 
KJ410224-KJ410227 
R: CGATGGGTAGRCAGTTGAA 
C5129 #1 
F: TATGCGTCGTCATCGCTAAG 
Ca 2+ binding actin-bundling protein 
5e-110~1270 
KJ410219-KJ410223 
R: TCTCCTTCGGCATCAAAGTC 
C16699 #1 F: ATCAAGWTCCATCCTGAACTTTA Ca 2+ binding actin-bundling protein 
2e-49~895 
KJ410214-KJ410218 
R: ACCRAGGACAAGRGTCTTCT 
C19981 2 
F: ATCAGTCTCTSCGYCARAAG 
D -xylulose kinase 
9e-12~425 
KJ410209-KJ410213 
R: AGCCCATATARCCTTCATTTCC 
C28586 2 
F: ACAACGARAACTGCTGGGAC 
Septin ring protein 
8e-40~575 
KJ410204-KJ410208 
R: AGGAGGAAATCRCGCAAGTAGAC 
C43566 1 
F: ACGCCYACYTTYCCGTATCC 
Phosphatase DCR2 
7e-18~1150 
KJ410200-KJ410203 
R: CGAYCTYCATTTCAGCGTCT 
C11488* 3 F: GACTTTCAGGATTTTACTC 
NAD5 
0.0~840 
KJ410195-KJ410199 
R: ACTCCGTTTCCRAATAATTCTC 
C11804* 3 F: CRGCAAATGGWATTAAAG 
ATP synthase 
2e-65~500 
KJ410190-KJ410194 
R: CCTAGTTCWTAYTCTATTGCAC </p>

<p>* Mitochondrial marker. 
# Loci C5129 and C16699 partially overlap. 
1 Source for gene identifi cation: Martin et al. (2008) . 
2 Source for gene identifi cation: Stajich et al. (2010) . 
3 Source for gene identifi cation: Zuccaro et al. (2011) . </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Characteristics of markers in Sebacina mycorrhizal fungi from 
Australian orchids. </p>

<p>Locus </p>

<p>Amplifi cation 
success (%) </p>

<p>Aligned 
length (bp) </p>

<p>No. of variable 
sites (%) </p>

<p>Parsimony 
informative sites (%) </p>

<p>C2754 
95 
814 
20.2 
17.9 
C5129 
90 
1161 
29.3 
25.4 
C16699 
100 
781 
40.5 
29.7 
C5129+C16699 
90 
1592 
29.4 
25.3 
C19981 
100 
382 
35.3 
31.4 
C28586 
100 
516 
26.6 
23.6 
C43566 
94 
928 
34.3 
30.7 
C11488 
87 
740 
14.6 
10.7 
C11804 
77 
444 
29.7 
25.5 </p>

<p>Applications in Plant Sciences 2014 2 ( 6 ): 1400015 </p>

<p>Ruibal et al.-Phylogenetic markers for Sebacina 
doi:10.3732/apps.1400015 </p>

<p>3 of 4 
http://www.bioone.org/loi/apps </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Midpoint-rooted maximum likelihood tree for Sebacina vermifera obtained for eight concatenated loci (two mitochondrial and six nuclear 
loci). The tree with the highest log likelihood is shown. The numbers above the branches are maximum likelihood bootstrap values. Bootstrap values of 
≥ 70% are shown. The branch length is proportional to the inferred divergence level. The bar indicates substitutions per site. </p>

<p>LITERATURE CITED </p>





<p>Applications in Plant Sciences 2014 2 ( 6 ): 1400015 
Ruibal et al.-Phylogenetic markers for Sebacina 
doi:10.3732/apps.1400015 </p>

<p>http://www.bioone.org/loi/apps </p>

<p>APPENDIX 1 . Voucher information for Sebacina isolates used in this study. </p>

<p>Voucher specimen 
accession no. 1 
Host species 
Origin 
Collector 2 
GPS </p>

<p>CLM012 
Caladenia huegelii Rchb. f. 
Kings Park Botanical Gardens Collection, WA 
NS, KD 
31.9704 ° S, 115.822 ° E 
CLM015 
Caladenia arenicola Hopper &amp; A. P. Br. 
Kings Park Botanical Gardens Collection, WA 
NS, KD 
CLM016 
Caladenia huegelii Rchb. f. 
WA 
MMW 
CLM019 
Caladenia huegelii Rchb. f. 
WA 
MMW 
CLM096 
Caladenia tentaculata Schltdl. 
Maldon, VIC 
MMW 
36.997 ° S, 144.067 ° E 
CLM098 
Caladenia tentaculata Schltdl. 
Maldon, VIC 
MMW 
CLM129 
Caladenia tentaculata Schltdl. 
Inverleigh, VIC 
MMW 
38.030 ° S, 144.050 ° E 
CLM131 
Caladenia tentaculata Schltdl. 
Inverleigh, VIC 
MMW 
CLM134 
Caladenia tentaculata Schltdl. 
Wonthaggi, VIC 
MMW 
38.689 ° S, 145.589 ° E 
CLM204 
Caladenia cairnsiana F. Muell. 
WA 
RP 
33.523 ° S, 118.463 ° E 
CLM210 
Caladenia fl ava subsp. maculata Hopper &amp; A. P. Br. WA 
RP 
28.083 ° S, 114.222 ° E 
CLM217 
Caladenia arenicola Hopper &amp; A. P. Br. 
Kings Park Glasshouse Collection, WA 
RP 
31.970 ° S, 115.822 ° E 
CLM295 
Caladenia pusilla W. M. Curtis 
Bluff Hill, TAS 
NS 
CLM793 
Caladenia longicauda Lindl. 
Nyerilup Rd, WA 
MW 
33.866 ° S, 118.778 ° E 
CLM808 
Caladenia thinicola Hopper &amp; A. P. Br. 
Gracetown, WA 
MW 
33.857 ° S, 114.995 ° E 
CLM826 
Caladenia fl ava R. Br. 
Gracetown, WA 
MW 
CLM852 
Caladenia attingens Hopper &amp; A. P. Br. 
Gracetown, WA 
MW 
CLM879 
Caladenia paludosa Hopper &amp; A. P. Br. 
Yalingup, WA 
MW 
33.658 ° S, 115.034 ° E 
CLM895 
Caladenia fl ava R. Br. 
Milyeanup Rd, WA 
MW 
34.283 ° S, 115.275 ° E 
CLM905 
Caladenia attingens Hopper &amp; A. P. Br. 
Milyeanup Rd, WA 
MW 
CLM1006 
Caladenia longicauda Lindl. 
Toolbrunup Rd, WA 
MW 
34.099 ° S, 117.788 ° E 
CLM1022 
Caladenia nivalis Hopper &amp; A. P. Br. 
Moses Rock, WA 
MW 
33.768 ° S, 114.994 ° E 
CLM1028 
Caladenia applanata Hopper &amp; A. P. Br. 
Moses Rock, WA 
MW 
CLM1044 
Caladenia excelsa Hopper &amp; A. P. Br. 
Wilybrup Rd, WA 
MW 
33.805 ° S, 115.019 ° E 
CLM199 
Glossodia minor R. Br. 
Near Bendalong, NSW 
CCL 
35.114 ° S, 150.315 ° E 
CLM200 
Glossodia major R. Br. 
Near Bendalong, NSW 
CCL 
CLM839 
Elythranthera brunonis (Endl.) A. S. George 
Gracetown, WA 
MW 
33.857 ° S, 114.995 ° E 
CLM978 
Eriochilus pulchellus Hopper &amp; A. P. Br. 
Tindele Rd, WA 
RP 
CLM979 
Eriochilus dilatatus Lindl. 
Leeman/Dongara, WA 
RP 
29.520 ° S, 114.935 ° E 
CLM980 
Eriochilus dilatatus Lindl. 
Leeman/Dongara, WA 
RP 
CLM981 
Eriochilus dilatatus Lindl. 
Leeman/Dongara, WA 
RP </p>

<p>Note : NSW = New South Wales; TAS = Tasmania; VIC = Victoria; WA = Western Australia. 
1 Culture collections are stored in water at 5 ° C on fungal isolation media (FIM) slants ( Clements and Ellyard, 1979 ) and located in the author's laboratory 
at the Australian National University (ANU). 
2 Collectors: CCL = Celeste C. Linde; KD = Kingsley Dixon; MMW = Magali M. Wright; MW = Michael Whitehead; NS = Nigel Swartz; RP = Ryan 
Phillips. </p>



</text></tei>