<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4618831" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>SUMMARY </p>

<p>In this study, we sought evidence for alpha-synuclein (ASYN) expression in oligodendrocytes, as a possible endogenous source of ASYN 
to explain its presence in glial inclusions found in multiple system atrophy (MSA) and Parkinson's disease (PD). We identified ASYN in 
oligodendrocyte lineage progenitors isolated from the rodent brain, in oligodendrocytes generated from embryonic stem cells, and in 
induced pluripotent stem cells produced from fibroblasts of a healthy individual and patients diagnosed with MSA or PD, in cultures 
in vitro. Notably, we observed a significant decrease in ASYN during oligodendrocyte maturation. Additionally, we show the presence of 
transcripts in PDGFRA/CD140a 
+ cells and SOX10 
+ oligodendrocyte lineage nuclei isolated by FACS from rodent and human healthy </p>

<p>and diseased brains, respectively. Our work identifies ASYN in oligodendrocyte lineage cells, and it offers additional in vitro cellular 
models that should provide significant insights of the functional implication of ASYN during oligodendrocyte development and 
disease. </p>

<p>Multiple system atrophy (MSA) and Parkinson's disease 
(PD) are adult-onset progressive neurodegenerative dis-
eases that are hallmarked at the cellular level by the 
presence of alpha-synuclein (ASYN) protein containing 
inclusions. Interestingly, the inclusions are found in 
neurons in PD, where the SNCA gene encoding for ASYN 
protein is expressed, whereas they are prominent in 
oligodendrocytes as glial cytoplasmic inclusions (GCIs) 
in MSA (Papp et al., 1989; Stefanova et al., 2009). Because 
strong evidence showing that oligodendrocytes in the 
adult brain are capable of expressing SNCA is lacking, 
recent studies inspired from parkinsonian experimental 
models have proposed the interesting hypothesis that 
ASYN present in GCIs in MSA could be of neuronal origin 
and transfer to oligodendrocytes (Kisos et al., 2012; Reyes 
et al., 2014), where it would accumulate and potentially 
lead to oligodendrocyte dysfunction. However, more 
than a decade ago, Richter-Landsberg and coworkers re-
ported on the transient expression of Snca in cultures 
enriched in oligodendrocytes, prepared by mechanical 
shaking of mixed rat glial primary brain cultures 
(Richter-Landsberg et al., 2000). This finding, however, 
was neither confirmed nor further explored, and in vivo 
evidences of ASYN expression during oligodendrocyte 
maturation are still missing. Consequently, follow-up </p>

<p>studies mainly focused on understanding the functional 
consequences of wild-type or mutant human ASYN tar-
geted expression in oligodendrocytes in experimental 
models in vivo and in vitro (Kragh et al., 2013; Yazawa 
et al., 2005). 
To date, the origin of ASYN in GCIs in oligodendrocytes 
in MSA is still elusive, as is that of the few inclusions found 
in glial cells in the substantia nigra of people with PD 
(Wakabayashi et al., 2000). For these reasons, ASYN expres-
sion in oligodendrocytes remains to be firmly established, 
especially since investigations using patient material are 
still controversial (Asi et al., 2014; Miller et al., 2005). 
One way to explore ASYN expression in human oligoden-
drocytes is through the generation of human cellular 
models such as induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs), 
since patient oligodendrocytes are not always accessible 
postmortem. 
Here using several murine and human cellular models, 
we present compelling evidence for ASYN expression 
during oligodendrocyte lineage cell development. More-
over, we identified both ASYN protein and transcripts in 
purified PDGFRA/CD140a 
+ oligodendrocyte progenitors </p>

<p>and oligodendrocyte lineage SOX10 
+ nuclei, isolated by </p>

<p>fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) from the rodent 
wild-type brain and human healthy and diseased brains, 
respectively, therefore substantiating a functional role for 
ASYN in oligodendrocytes. </p>



<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>ASYN Protein and Transcripts Identified in O4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>Oligodendrocytes in Mouse Brain Primary Cultures 
Oligodendrocytes are abundantly produced during devel-
opment and at neonatal age (Kessaris et al., 2006). The 
postnatal forebrain, therefore, should provide a rapid 
source of oligodendrocytes at different stages of maturation 
for experimental investigations in vitro. 
We performed immunocytochemistry (ICC) on disso-
ciated cell cultures from mouse neonates, grown for </p>

<p>3 weeks in vitro (Figure 1A). These cultures were 
composed of beta-III-tubulin (B-III-TUB)-expressing neu-
rons (z2%), glial-fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP)-ex-
pressing astrocytes (z75%), IBA1-expressing microglia 
(z15%), and oligodendrocyte lineage-specific glycolipid 
antigen (O4)-positive oligodendrocytes (z8%) (Figures 
1B-1D; Figure S1A). Importantly, ICC for each of 
these cell-type-specific markers and ASYN showed spe-
cific localization of ASYN in B-III-TUB 
+ neurons and </p>

<p>in O4 
+ oligodendrocytes (Figures 1B-1D; Figures S1A </p>

<p>and S1B). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Localization of ASYN in Mouse 
Primary Neurons and Pre-oligodendro-
cyte Progenitors 
(A) Experimental approach used for gener-
ating rodent postnatal primary forebrain 
cultures is shown. 
(B) Rodent postnatal primary forebrain 
cultures aged 25 DIV contain B-III-TUB </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>neurons expressing Snca. The scale bar 
represents 50 mm. 
(C) Rodent postnatal primary forebrain 
cultures contain O4 
+ oligodendrocytes ex-
pressing ASYN. Nuclei are counterstained 
with DAPI. (Right) Higher magnification of 
the region of interest is shown. The scale 
bar represents 50 mm. 
(D) Quantification of neurons (B-III-TUB </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>), 
oligodendrocytes (O4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>), astrocytes (GFAP </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>), 
and microglia (IBA1 
+ and GAL-3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) co-ex-
pressing ASYN (white bars). Black bars 
represent quantification for each cell type. 
Values are indicated as the number of cells 
per field of view. Mean ± SEM; n = 3 inde-
pendent cultures. 
(E) Quantitative real-time PCR analysis 
shows the abundance (&gt;10-fold) of Snca 
transcripts in FACS-purified O4 
+ oligoden-
drocyte samples compared to whole primary 
culture sample. Oligodendrocyte enrichment 
is assessed by the quantification of oligo-
dendrocyte-specific marker transcripts and 
the absence of astrocytic Gfap transcripts 
(see Supplemental Experimental Proce-
dures). Mean ± SEM; n = 3-4 independent 
experiments; t test, *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01. 
(F) The set of primers we designed to assess 
mouse Snca expression by quantitative real-
time PCR recognizes a unique product of 
271 bp and was tested on two independent 
cultures. 
(G) Quantitative real-time PCR analysis shows significant enrichment in Cyclin-D1 transcripts in purified O4 
+ oligodendrocyte sample 
compared to whole primary culture sample. Mean ± SEM; n = 3 independent experiments; t test, *p &lt; 0.05. 
(H) Identification of KI67 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>/O4 
+ /ASYN 
+ oligodendrocyte in rodent postnatal primary forebrain culture. Nuclei are counterstained with 
DAPI. Insets show higher magnification of the region indicated with straight lines. The scale bar represents 50 mm. </p>

<p>Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 5 j 174-184 j August 11, 2015 j ª2015 The Authors 175 </p>

<p>(legend on next page) </p>



<p>We isolated O4 
+ oligodendrocytes by FACS from the rest </p>

<p>of the cells present in our primary cultures, and we measured 
the abundance of total Snca transcripts by quantitative real-
time PCR. Consistent over multiple rounds of experiments, 
our quantitative real-time PCR data clearly showed the pres-
ence of Snca transcripts (&gt;10-fold increase relative to the 
whole culture) in the O4 
+ -purified samples (Figures 1E and </p>

<p>1F), therefore suggesting that O4 
+ oligodendrocytes indeed </p>

<p>do express the Snca gene encoding for ASYN. 
Interestingly, we identified ASYN protein and Snca tran-
scripts in cycling oligodendrocytes, probably oligodendro-
cyte progenitors (Figures 1G and 1H). </p>

<p>Decreased ASYN Expression during Oligodendrocyte 
Maturation 
To become mature and capable of myelinating axons, oli-
godendrocytes undergo different stages of maturation, 
each characterized by temporal expression of specific 
markers (Zhang, 2001). 
Interestingly, while we previously found that &gt;90% of 
O4 
+ immature oligodendrocytes present in mice primary </p>

<p>postnatal forebrain cultures co-expressed ASYN, we ob-
served a strong reduction (up to 70% less compared to O4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>oligodendrocytes) in co-expression of ASYN and the mature 
oligodendrocyte markers 2 
0 ,3 
0 -cyclic nucleotide 3 
0 -phos-</p>

<p>phodiesterase (CNPASE, &lt;40%), galactocerebroside (GAL-
C, &lt;35%), and myelin basic protein (MBP, &lt;25%), clearly 
identifiable by confocal microscopy (Figures 2A and 2B; Fig-
ure S2). In marked contrast, ASYN expression was high in 
immature platelet-derived growth factor receptor alpha-
positive (PDGFRA) oligodendrocyte progenitors, measured </p>

<p>by ICC and quantitative real-time PCR (Figures 2C and 
2D). Our data, therefore, suggest that ASYN expression de-
creases during oligodendrocyte maturation and is present 
as early as PDGFRA 
+ oligodendrocyte progenitor stage. </p>

<p>To ascertain that ASYN expression was specific to oligo-
dendrocyte development and not the result of a transient 
expression due to the passage of cells isolated from the 
brain to an in vitro culture system, we investigated ASYN 
expression during the generation of oligodendrocytes 
from mouse embryonic stem cells (mESCs; Figure 2E). We 
derived ESC from wild-type mice, which we differentiated 
into oligodendrocytes using a previously published proto-
col (Czepiel et al., 2011). We first ascertained the downre-
gulation and upregulation of pluripotent marker Oct4 
and oligodendrocyte lineage-specific markers SRY (sex-
determining region Y)-box 10 (SOX10), PDGFRA, CNPASE, 
and MBP, respectively, by quantitative real-time PCR, west-
ern blot, and ICC (Figures 2F-2H; data not shown), during 
mESC differentiation. We next confirmed the abundance 
of Snca transcripts and ASYN protein in our cultures, by 
quantitative real-time PCR, western blot, and ICC (Figures 
2F-2H). Importantly, we found that the majority of O4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>oligodendrocytes expressed Snca (Figure 2H), and that, 
yet again, ASYN decreases during oligodendrocyte matura-
tion (Figure 2H). </p>

<p>Oligodendrocytes Generated from iPSCs from a 
Healthy Individual and Patients with PD or MSA Also 
Express SNCA 
Because ASYN expression in oligodendrocytes from MSA 
patients is debated and that in oligodendrocytes of people </p>

<p>Figure 2. ASYN Expression Decreases during Oligodendrocyte Maturation 
(A) Absence of ASYN in RIP 
+ and MBP 
+ oligodendrocytes detected by confocal microscopy. White arrows pinpoint oligodendrocyte cell 
bodies. The scale bar represents 50 mm. 
(B) Rodent postnatal primary forebrain cultures contain O4 
+ immature oligodendrocytes (z70% of total oligodendrocyte markers) and CNPASE </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, 
GAL-C </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, and MBP 
+ (&lt;20% for all three markers) mature oligodendrocytes. Mean ± SEM; n = 2-3 independent experiments. There is decreased co-
expression between ASYN and CNPASE, GAL-C, or MBP compared to O4 
+ oligodendrocytes. Mean ± SEM; n = 2-3 independent experiments. 
(C) Rodent postnatal primary forebrain cultures contain PDGFRA 
+ oligodendrocyte progenitors expressing ASYN. Nuclei are counterstained 
with DAPI. White arrowhead pinpoints an O4 
À /ASYN </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>/PDGFRA 
+ oligodendrocyte progenitor. The scale bar represents 50 mm. 
(D) Quantitative real-time PCR analysis shows the abundance (&gt;10-fold) of Snca transcripts in FACS-purified PDGFRA 
+ oligodendrocyte 
progenitor samples compared to PDGFRA 
+ oligodendrocyte progenitor-depleted samples. Enrichment in oligodendrocyte progenitors is 
assessed by the quantification of Pdgfra transcripts and the absence of astrocytic Gfap and mature oligodendrocytic Mbp transcripts. 
Mean ± SEM; n = 2-3 independent experiments. 
(E) Experimental approach used for assessing ASYN expression during rodent oligodendrocyte development. The mESCs were derived from a 
blastocyste aged E3.5 and subsequently differentiated into oligodendrocytes for a period of 4-5 weeks in vitro. 
(F) Quantitative real-time PCR shows the loss of Oct4 and upregulation of Nkx2.2, Pdgfra, Cnpase and Mbp, and Snca during the differ-
entiation of mESCs into oligodendrocytes. For each marker, values are presented as a percentage of the highest value. Mean ± SEM; n = 2 
independent experiments. 
(G) Western blotting confirms the downregulation of OCT4 and expression of the oligodendroglial markers and ASYN during the differ-
entiation of mESCs into oligodendrocytes. Blot is representative of two independent experiments. 
(H) ICC on mESC-differentiated cultures aged 36 DIV confirms the presence and absence of ASYN in PDGFRA 
+ and CNPASE </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, and MBP </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>oligodendrocytes, respectively. Quantifications are based on two differentiations. Images are representative of four independent dif-
ferentiations. Scale bars represent 50 mm. </p>

<p>Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 5 j 174-184 j August 11, 2015 j ª2015 The Authors 177 </p>

<p>(legend on next page) </p>



<p>with PD is still elusive, we generated iPSCs from fibroblasts 
(Figure 3A) of MSA patients diagnosed with cerebellar 
ataxia (MSA-C, patient 4) or parkinsonism (MSA-C, pa-
tient 6), a patient diagnosed with a familial form of PD (pa-
tient 3), and a healthy individual (patient 9), and assessed 
ASYN expression in oligodendrocyte lineage cells (Fig-
ure 3A). All iPSC clones selected were expanded and cryo-
preserved. Random clones were selected and processed 
for further analysis. Thus, clones CSC-3A, B, G, and S; 
CSC-4A and B; CSC-6A; and CSC-9A and B underwent 
rigorous characterization through a battery of tests (sum-
marized in Figure S3), which indicated that we had effec-
tively generated iPSCs. 
We attempted to generate oligodendrocytes from our 
iPSC lines. To rule out the possibility of chromosomal ab-
normalities influencing ASYN expression in iPSC-derived 
oligodendrocytes, we selected one clone per patient-
specific iPSC line presenting a normal karyotype to carry 
out most of our investigations. We devised a protocol, 
modified from that of Stacpoole and coworkers (Stacpoole 
et al., 2013), where we employed dual inhibition of 
SMAD signaling by small molecules LDN and SB to 
neutralize our cultures, sonic hedgehog-mediated ventral 
patterning, and PDGF-AA/IGF1/NT3/T3/HGF-mediated 
terminal differentiation. This modified protocol, proven 
efficient when applied to the human ESC lines H13 and 
H3 (Figure S4; data not shown), successfully produced 
oligodendrocyte progenitor cells (OPCs) and mature oli-
godendrocytes from iPSCs. Thus, by 60 days in vitro 
(DIV), nearly all SOX10 
+ cells co-expressed NKX2.2 and </p>

<p>OLIG2, NG2, and PDGFRA and O4 (Figures S5A-S5C 
and S6A), and those cells exhibited in majority an imma-
ture-bipolar morphology where ASYN could clearly be 
identified by confocal microscopy, quantitative real-time 
PCR, and western blot (Figures 3B and 3C; Figures S5 
and S6). Additionally, ASYN could be detected in neurons 
(Figure S5D), whereas it was absent in astrocytes (Fig-</p>

<p>ure S5E). Interestingly, from 65 DIV onward, O4 
+ oligo-</p>

<p>dendrocytes displayed a perinuclear localization of ASYN 
(Figures 3D and 3E), as we observed for mouse O4 
+ oligo-</p>

<p>dendrocytes (Figures 1 and 2). In cultures aged 110 DIV, 
ASYN expression could still be detected in a few CNPASE </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>and MBP 
+ mature oligodendrocytes (Figure 3D), some-</p>

<p>times as a perinuclear dot (Figure S6C; data not shown). 
Interestingly, the disease lines CSC-4A, CSC-4B, and 
CSC-3G gave rise to an accelerated high-yield generation 
of O4 
+ oligodendrocytes (up to 70% of live single cells) </p>

<p>in 70 DIV (Figure 3E). Finally, we confirmed the decrease 
in ASYN in O4 
+ oligodendrocytes over time (Figure 3F) </p>

<p>and the presence of SNCA transcripts in FACS-purified 
O4 
+ oligodendrocytes from the line CSC-3S aged 80 DIV </p>

<p>(Figure 3G). </p>

<p>ASYN Protein and Transcripts Identified in 
Oligodendrocytes from Mouse and Human Brains 
We identified Snca transcripts in PDGFRA/CD140a 
+ oligo-</p>

<p>dendrocyte progenitors freshly isolated by FACS from 
embryonic day (E)18 mouse brains (Figures 4A-4C). Impor-
tantly, we detected ASYN by ICC in nearly all oligodendro-
cytes present in homogenous cultures resulting from the 
isolation of E17.5 and E18 PDGFRA/CD140a 
+ oligodendro-</p>

<p>cyte progenitors (Figure 4D), ruling out the unlikely possi-
bility that ASYN may have been transferred from neurons 
to oligodendrocytes in primary cultures (Figure 1). When 
these progenitors matured into O4 
+ oligodendrocytes </p>

<p>(Sim et al., 2011), ASYN was still present, with the excep-
tion of a few oligodendrocytes having a more complex 
morphology (Figure 4D). 
Finally, we took advantage of a previously developed 
technique (Ernst et al., 2014; Yeung et al., 2014), to isolate 
human oligodendrocyte lineage nuclei by FACS, to assess 
the presence of SNCA transcripts (Figures 4E-4I). We 
prepared nuclei samples from the pons of snap-frozen 
postmortem tissue from the following six patients: three </p>

<p>Figure 3. ASYN in iPSC-Derived O4 
+ Oligodendrocytes 
(A) Experimental approach used for generating and assessing ASYN expression during human iPSC-derived oligodendrocyte development. 
Healthy individual, MSA-C, MSA-P, and PD patient's skin fibroblasts were reprogrammed by means of viral overexpression of stemness 
factors hKLF4, hC-MYC, hOCT4, and hSOX2. Following characterization, human iPSCs were subsequently differentiated into oligodendro-
cytes over a period of 110 DIV. 
(B) Western blotting confirms the expression of the oligodendroglial marker SOX10 and ASYN during the differentiation of human iPSCs 
into oligodendrocytes. Blot is representative of two independent experiments. Quantitative real-time PCR shows the upregulation of SNCA 
in iPSCs during oligodendrocyte differentiation. 
(C) Perinuclear localization of ASYN in immature O4 
+ oligodendrocytes aged 65 DIV revealed by ICC. Images are representative of two to 
three independent differentiations. Scale bars represent 50 mm. 
(D) Presence of ASYN in O4 
+ , CNPASE 
+ , and MBP 
+ oligodendrocytes aged 110 DIV revealed by ICC. (Middle, bottom left inset) O4 
+ /MBP 
À / 
ASYN 
À and O4 
+ /MBP 
+ /ASYN 
+ oligodendrocytes are shown. Scale bars represent 50 mm. 
(E) Quantification of O4 
+ oligodendrocytes by flow cytometry for eight PSC lines differentiated side by side. The early emergence of O4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>oligodendrocytes from line 4 was observed in separate rounds of differentiation. 
(F) Quantification of O4 
+ oligodendrocytes co-expressing ASYN over time is shown. 
(G) Quantitative real-time PCR shows SNCA transcripts in 3S iPSC-derived O4 
+ oligodendrocyte samples, purified by FACS. </p>

<p>Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 5 j 174-184 j August 11, 2015 j ª2015 The Authors 179 </p>

<p>(legend on next page) </p>



<p>healthy and three diagnosed with MSA with confirmed 
GCIs in oligodendrocytes (Figure S7A). We isolated from 
each sample the oligodendrocyte lineage SOX10 
+ nuclei </p>

<p>and quantified neuronal NEUN 
+ nuclei by FACS (Fig-</p>

<p>ure 4G; Figure S7B). We detected a lower proportion of 
neurons in the pons region of the MSA patients (Fig-
ure 4H), confirming the MSA diagnosis; we also found a 
lower percentage of SOX10 
+ nuclei in the diseased sam-</p>

<p>ples, although not significant (Figure 4H). Importantly, 
we could detect the presence of SNCA transcripts in 
oligodendrocyte lineage nuclei of two samples isolated 
from the brain of a healthy and an MSA patient (Figures 
4H and 4I), as described by Asi and coworkers (Asi et al., 
2014). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The absence of SNCA transcripts in oligodendrocytes in 
the adult brain of healthy and MSA patients has been re-
ported repeatedly (Iwai et al., 1995; Miller et al., 2005; 
Solano et al., 2000), but recent studies have challenged 
these results. Because MSA has been identified as a non-
genetic disorder, it is difficult to propose an explanation 
for the origin of ASYN in GCIs present in oligodendro-
cytes under pathological condition. This has led to the 
emergence of a hypothesis advocating a mechanism of 
cell-to-cell transfer of exogenous ASYN to oligodendro-
cytes, similar to that experimentally established from 
neuron-to-neuron in PD models (Hansen et al., 2011). 
However, the recent use of more advanced techniques, 
such as laser-capture micro-dissection, has allowed for 
the isolation of adult white matter glia from human post-
mortem tissue, resulting in the detection of SNCA tran-</p>

<p>scripts from MSA, idiopathic PD, and control cases (Asi 
et al., 2014). 
We clearly identified ASYN protein by ICC and western 
blotting and we detected transcripts by quantitative real-
time PCR in oligodendrocyte lineage cells from rodent and 
human origins (summarized in Figure 4J). We could not 
detect ASYN expression in astrocytes and microglia, which 
are cell types known to take up exogenous ASYN (Boza-
Serrano et al., 2014; Lee et al., 2010). Moreover, the few neu-
rons present in cultures combined with the multitude of 
media changes applied during the culture period, and the 
discovery of Snca/SNCA transcripts in freshly isolated oligo-
dendrocytes and ASYN protein in homogenous cultures of 
freshly isolated, maturing PDGFRA/CD140a 
+ oligodendro-</p>

<p>cyte progenitors, together allow us to rule out the possibility 
that healthy or dying neurons, even contaminating neu-
rons, may have released large quantities of ASYN, which 
would accumulate, not being sufficiently degraded, in the 
oligodendrocytes only. Moreover, we showed relocation of 
ASYN during oligodendrocyte differentiation from the pro-
cesses to the perinuclear space, where the protein appears 
as a single dot-like structure suggesting it is finally degraded. 
We identified SNCA transcripts in human SOX10 
+ oligo-</p>

<p>dendrocyte lineage nuclei samples isolated from healthy 
and MSA patients (Figure 4). This result is in line with 
recent observations (Asi et al., 2014). Whether ASYN 
expression identified in these two studies is reminiscent 
of a basal expression in quiescent OPCs, and the difference 
although not significant identified in oligodendrocytes 
from MSA and control samples is the result of a greater oli-
godendrogenesis probably triggered by neuronal injury 
(Ahmed et al., 2013) remain to be determined. 
We found a decrease of ASYN associated with oligo-
dendrocyte maturation characterized by complex cellular </p>

<p>Figure 4. ASYN in Oligodendrocytes In Vivo 
(A) Schematic representation shows the experimental approach used for assessing ASYN in the mouse embryonic brain. 
(B) Quantification of PDGFRA/CD140a 
+ oligodendrocyte progenitors and O4 
+ oligodendrocytes from the rodent brain at embryonic and 
postnatal stages, measured by FACS, is shown. 
(C) Loading of quantitative real-time PCR product confirms the presence of Snca transcripts in E18 PDGFRA/CD140a 
+ oligodendrocyte 
progenitors, freshly isolated by FACS, from the mouse embryonic brain. 
(D) Detection of ASYN in homogenous cultures from mouse embryonic PDGFRA/CD140a 
+ oligodendrocyte progenitors isolated by FACS at 
E17.5. ASYN is maintained in homogenous cultures of PDGFRA/CD140a 
+ oligodendrocyte progenitors maturing into O4 
+ oligodendrocytes. 
The scale bar represents 50 mm. 
(E) Schematic representation shows the experimental approach used for assessing ASYN expression in oligodendrocyte lineage nuclei 
isolated from the brain of healthy and MSA patients. 
(F) FACS plots represent the gating strategy employed for isolating SOX10 
+ oligodendrocyte lineage nuclei from the samples. 
(G) The decrease in the percentage of NEUN 
+ nuclei of the total population of all nuclei, in the pons region of MSA patients (n = 3) 
compared to control (n = 3), was measured by FACS. Mean ± SEM; t test, *p &lt; 0.05. 
(H) Quantitative real-time PCR shows SNCA transcripts in SOX10 
+ oligodendrocyte lineage nuclei samples purified by FACS from patients 
T172 and T4640. 
(I) Loading of quantitative real-time PCR product confirms the presence of SNCA transcripts. The set of primers used to assess human SNCA 
expression by quantitative real-time PCR recognizes a unique product of 163 bp (from Asi et al., 2014). 
(J) A summary of our findings is shown. </p>

<p>Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 5 j 174-184 j August 11, 2015 j ª2015 The Authors 181 </p>

<p>processes and expression of the mature marker MBP. Inter-
estingly, overexpression of ASYN in OPCs delays their 
maturation into MBP 
+ oligodendrocytes (Ettle et al., </p>

<p>2014). Additionally, we found that ASYN is decreased in 
pre-myelinating oligodendrocytes, regardless of the ge-
netic background of the iPSC (diseased or healthy). This 
observation, although made in vitro, may allow us to 
rule out that the origin of ASYN in GCIs in MSA, and 
glial inclusions in PD, may result from the accumula-
tion of a lifetime production of ASYN throughout glial 
lineages. 
Successful generation of patient-specific iPSCs, and 
their subsequent differentiation into brain cell types, 
has opened up unlimited access of patient brain cells 
to a growing number of investigators interested in 
studying neurodegenerative diseases. Here we have pio-
neered the generation of oligodendrocytes from MSA 
and familial PD iPSC lines. Our protocol for generating 
oligodendrocytes from human iPSCs, therefore, adds on 
to those recently developed for studying demyelination 
diseases (Douvaras et al., 2014; Numasawa-Kuroiwa 
et al., 2014; Piao et al., 2015; Stacpoole et al., 2013; 
Wang et al., 2013). Importantly, our iPSC models pro-
vide a greater number of lines available for studying 
synucleinopathies. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Use of Animals and Human Samples </p>

<p>All procedures were conducted in accordance with national and 
European Union directives. The derivation of mESC and genera-
tion of human iPSC lines using viral-mediated gene delivery 
were approved by the ethical committee for the use of laboratory 
animals at Lund University and the Swedish Work Environment 
Authority. </p>

<p>Primary Cell Cultures </p>

<p>Primary forebrain cultures were prepared from 1-to 3-day-old 
wild-type mice and cultured in DMEM (Life Technologies) supple-
mented with fetal bovine serum (FBS, 10% v/v) and P/S (1% v/v). 
After 3 weeks, cells were detached using trypsin, either for FACS 
analysis or to be seeded on 96-well plates. </p>

<p>Oligodendrocyte Differentiation from Mouse and 
Human PSCs </p>

<p>The mESC-derived oligodendrocytes were generated using a 
published protocol (Czepiel et al., 2011). Human PSC (hPSC)-
derived oligodendrocytes were generated using a protocol 
modified from a previously published study (Stacpoole et al., 
2013). </p>

<p>FACS </p>

<p>A FACSAria-III was used for cell sorting and analysis (MultiPark 
core facility). </p>

<p>Immunostainings and Image Acquisition </p>

<p>ICC was carried out using standard protocols. Images were ac-
quired using an inverted epifluorescent microscope LRI-Olympus 
IX-73 and a confocal microscope Leica SP8 (MultiPark core 
facility). </p>

<p>Statistical Analyses </p>

<p>All quantitative data were analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">6.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad</rs>). 
Sample groups were subjected to un-paired t test. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION </p>

<p>Supplemental Information includes Supplemental Experimental 
Procedures, seven figures, and two tables and can be found 
with this article online at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.stemcr. 
2015.07.002. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </p>

<p>M.D. performed experiments and analysis. S.H. assisted with re-
programming and characterization of iPSC lines. A.B.-S. assisted 
with primary cultures and western blotting. C.A. assisted with 
the differentiation of mESCs and hPSCs and stainings. M.S.Y. as-
sisted with nuclei purification. L.R. assisted with the derivation 
of mESCs, characterization of iPSC lines, and analysis. T.D., 
J.F., and S.G. provided reagents and input on experiments. 
M.D. and L.R. conceived the experiments and wrote the manu-
script. All authors gave input on the manuscript and approved 
its final version. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We are deeply thankful to V. Fossati and N. Lamas for helpful crit-
ical reading of the manuscript and to J. Goldman for generously 
providing the O4 antibody. We thank J.-Y. Li for providing access 
to wild-type mice for deriving mESCs; A. Collin for helping with 
karyotyping interpretation; C. Vignon for helping with the main-
tenance of the mESCs; A. Hammarberg, S. Giatrellis, and M. Toro 
for FACS advice; and J. Bigarreau for helping with graphic illustra-
tions. We are also thankful to P.H. Jensen for constructive feedback 
during the editing of the manuscript. Human fibroblast cell lines 
were obtained from Coriell, the Cell Line and DNA Biobank from 
Patients affected by Genetic Diseases (Istituto G. Gaslini), and 
the Parkinson Institute Biobank (http://www.parkinsonbiobank. 
com), members of the Telethon Network of Genetic Biobanks 
(project GTB12001) funded by Telethon Italy. We are thankful to 
the Brain Bank at Columbia University team for providing us 
with the human postmortem tissue samples. This work was sup-
ported by the Strong Research Environment MultiPark (multidisci-
plinary research on Parkinson's disease at Lund University) and 
through external grants to L.R. from the Jeanssons foundation; 
the Swedish Parkinson foundation (Parkinsonfonden); the Holger 
Crafoord foundation; the Segerfalk foundation; the Å ke Wibergs 
foundation; the Greta och Johan Kocks foundation; and donations 
for science, medicine, and technology at Fysiografen in Lund. L.R. 
is a young investigator supported by MultiPark-Strategic Research 
Environment at Lund University, funded by the Swedish govern-
ment, and partner of BrainStem-Stem Cell Center of Excellence 
in Neurology, funded by Innovation Fund Denmark. </p>



<p>Received: December 7, 2014 
Revised: July 6, 2015 
Accepted: July 6, 2015 
Published: July 30, 2015 </p>



<p>184 Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 5 j 174-184 j August 11, 2015 j ª2015 The Authors </p>

</text></tei>