<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4621286" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: The efficacy and safety of the combined treatment of refractory schizophrenia with 
antipsychotic medications and electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) remain uncertain. 
Aim: Conduct systematic review and meta-analysis of available literature in English and Chinese about ECT in 
the treatment of refractory schizophrenia. 
Methods: English and Chinese databases were searched for studies published prior to May 20, 2015 
regarding the efficacy and safety of the combined treatment of refractory schizophrenia with antipsychotic 
medications and ECT. Two researchers selected and evaluated studies independently using pre-defined 
criteria. <rs id="software-0" type="software">Review Manager</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.3</rs> software was used for data analysis. 
Results: A total of 22 randomized control studies, 18 of which were conducted in mainland China, were 
included in the analysis. Meta-analysis of data from 18 of the 22 studies with a pooled sample of 1394 
individuals found that compared to treatment with antipsychotic medications alone, combined treatment 
with antipsychotic medications and ECT had significantly higher rates of achieving study-specific criteria of 
'clinical improvement' (RR=1.25, 95%CI=1.14-1.37). Based on the Grades of Recommendation, Assessment, 
Development, and Evaluation (GRADE) criteria, the quality of evidence for this assessment of efficacy was 
'moderate'. However, the proportion of participants who experienced headache during the treatment was 
significantly higher in the combined treatment group (RR=9.10, 95%CI=3.97-20.86, based on a pooled sample 
of 517 from 8 studies) and the proportion who experienced memory impairment was also higher in the 
combined treatment group (RR=6.48, 95%CI=3.54-11.87, based on a pooled sample of 577 from 7 studies). 
The quality of evidence about these adverse events was rated as 'very low'. 
Conclusions: There are very few high quality randomized controlled clinical trials about the combination of 
antipsychotic medications and ECT in the treatment of refractory schizophrenia. This meta-analysis found 
that the combination of antipsychotic medications and ECT could improve psychiatric symptoms in patients 
with refractory schizophrenia, but the incomplete methodological information provided for most of the 
studies, publication bias (favoring studies with better outcomes in the combined treatment group), and 
the low quality of evidence about adverse outcomes, cognitive impairment, and overall functioning raise 
questions about the validity of the results. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>2.1 Search strategy 
We searched the following databases for studies 
published before May 1, 2015: Pubmed, Excerpta 
Medica dataBASE (EMBASE), The Cochrane Library, 
EBSCO, Chinese National Knowledge Infrastructure 
(CNKI), Chongqing VIP database for Chinese Technical 
Periodicals, WANFANG DATA, Chinese Biological Medical 
Literature Database, Taiwan Electronic Periodical 
Services, and ClinicalTrials.gov. We used the keywords 
'refractory,' 'schizophrenia,' 'psychosis,' 'electric shock,' 
'electroconvulsive,' 'clinical control study,' 'randomly, 
placebo', and 'randomly, trial' (and the Chinese 
equivalents) in the searches. Various combinations 
of these keywords were used to search for articles, 
reference lists of included articles were hand-checked 
for further relevant studies, and experts in the field 
were asked about ongoing studies. </p>

<p>2.2 Inclusion and exclusion criteria 
All reports of randomized controlled trails (RCTs) about 
the combined treatment of refractory schizophrenia 
with antipsychotic medications and ECT were screened </p>

<p>using the following inclusion criteria: a) a diagnosis 
of refractory (or 'treatment-resistant') schizophrenia 
made by psychiatrists; b) the control group was treated 
with antipsychotic medications; and c) the intervention 
group was treated with antipsychotic medication and 
ECT. Studies published in either English or Chinese 
were considered. Observational studies, anthropologic 
studies, review articles, research protocols, case reports, 
and duplicated reports were excluded. </p>

<p>2.3 Screening of articles 
All search results were imported into Endnote X5 
software. Two authors (WWZ and PCC) independently 
screened titles and abstracts after eliminating 
duplicates. The full texts of the remaining articles were 
screened according to the above inclusion and exclusion 
criteria. When the two authors disagreed about the 
inclusion of an article and were unable to agree after 
discussing the article, a third author (LCB) made the 
final determination. As shown in Figure 1, 22 studies 
were included in the final analysis. </p>

<p>2.4 Evaluation of risk of bias 
Two authors (WWZ and PCC) assessed the risk of 
bias independently for all included articles using the 
Cochrane Risk of Bias (RoB) [5] tool which considers seven 
specific items: random sequence generation; allocation 
concealment; blinding of participants and treating 
clinicians about group assignment; blinding of evaluators 
of outcomes about group assignment; incomplete data 
(attrition and exclusions); selective outcome reporting; 
and other biases (including study-specific biases or 
concerns about fraudulent results). Each aspect was 
rated as 'low risk of bias', 'high risk of bias', or 'unclear' 
(if insufficient information was provided in the article to 
make a determination). A third author's (LCB) opinion 
was sought when the two raters disagreed. 
We also evaluated the quality and level of evidence 
of each outcome variable for each of the 22 included 
studies using the Cochrane collaboration's Grades of 
Recommendation, Assessment, Development, and 
Evaluation (GRADE) software. This software assesses 
limitations of the design, consistency of results, indirect 
evidence, precision of results, publication bias, and 
effect size for each outcome. [5,6] The overall level of 
evidence is rated as 'high', 'medium', 'low', or 'very low'. </p>

<p>2.5 Outcome measures 
This meta-analysis was conducted to assess the 
efficacy and safety of the combination of antipsychotic 
medication and ECT in the treatment of patients with 
refractory schizophrenia. The primary outcome measure 
of effectiveness was the reduction in the total score 
of the main scale used to assess psychiatric symptoms 
during treatment. The primary outcome measure of 
adverse events was based on the score of the Treatment 
Emergent Symptom Scale (TESS). Secondary outcomes 
were the changes of cognitive and overall functioning 
after treatment. </p>

<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2015, Vol. 27, No. 4 </p>

<p>•208 • </p>

<p>2.6 Data extraction 
For each included study, two authors (WWZ and PCC) 
independently extracted data using a pre-designed 
data extraction form including the names of authors, 
publication year, sample size, number of outcome 
events, age of participants, and types of antipsychotics 
used. Discrepancies between the two coders were 
checked by a third author (LCB). </p>

<p>2.7 Analysis 
Based on the results of a previous study about risk of 
bias, [25] the overall risk of bias for each of the 22 studies 
was classified as 'low' if the ratings were 'low' for all 
seven items on the ROB tool, 'unclear' if any item is 
rated as 'unclear' and all other items are rated as 'low', 
and 'high' if any of the items are rated as 'high'. The 
kappa statistic was used to measure the inter-rater 
agreement between the two independent raters for the 
ratings of each item and for the overall rating. [7] Review 
Manager (RevMan 5.3) was used to estimate pooled 
the mean difference (MD) when the same continuous 
measure was used as the outcome measure in all 
included studies, the standard mean difference (SMD) 
when different continuous measures were used as 
outcome measures in included studies, and risk ratios 
(RR) for outcomes that were categorical measures. </p>

<p>Heterogeneity was measured using I 2 . [8] When I 2 is less 
than 50% and p&gt;0.10, the results were considered 
homogeneous and the fixed-effect model was used; 
when I 2 is greater than 50% but less than 75%, results 
were considered heterogeneous and the random-effect 
model was used. If I 2 is 75% or greater, we conducted 
sensitivity analysis to identify potential contributors 
to heterogeneity; if I 2 remained 75% or greater after 
removing outliers, we only provided descriptive results 
without pooling estimates. A funnel plot was used to 
evaluate potential publication bias. [5] </p>

<p>3 Results </p>

<p>3.1 Characteristics of included studies 
As shown in Figure 1, we identified a total of 1065 
articles in the selected databases. After removing 166 
duplicated articles using Endnote X5 software, there 
were 899 unduplicated reports. Based on the inclusion 
and exclusion criteria, 773 articles were excluded 
by reading the title and abstract and a further 104 
were excluded by reading the full text. The remaining 
22 articles [9-23,26-32] were included in the subsequent 
analyses: 18 (81.8%) were from China [10,12-16,18-22,26-32] 
and 4 (18.2%) from other countries; [9,11,17,23] all were 
published between 1999 and 2015. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Identification of included studies </p>

<p>1065 potential articles published prior to1 May 2015 were identified using a standardized search 
strategy (see methods section): 
143 PubMed 
737 EMBase 
103 Cochrane Library 
5 ClinicalTrials.gov 
27 Chinese National Knowledge Infrastructure (CNKI) 
8 Chongqing VIP database for Chinese Technical Periodicals 
15 WANFANG DATA 
27 Chinese Biological Medical Literature Database (SinoMed) </p>

<p>166 duplicated reports </p>

<p>899 unduplicated studies; 849 published in English, 50 in Chinese </p>

<p>Based on the following inclusion and exclusion criteria, 773 articles were excluded 
after reading the title and abstract and a further 104 articles were excluded after 
reading the full text 
• Randomized controlled trials published in English or Chinese that compare 
combined ECT and antipsychotic medication to antipsychotic medication alone 
in the treatment of refractory schizophrenia 
• Non-human studies, reviews, fora, case reports, and partial reports were 
excluded </p>

<p>22 unduplicated studies included in the analysis; 4 published in English, 18 in Chinese </p>

<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2015, Vol. 27, No. 4 </p>

<p>• 209 • </p>

<p>The characteristics of these 22 included studies are 
shown in Tables 1 and 2. </p>

<p>a) Definition of refractory schizophrenia: The inclusion 
and exclusion criteria varied across studies, but 
most studies used either the diagnostic criteria for 
schizophrenia established by the Chinese Society of 
Psychiatry (CCMD) [33] or the diagnostic criteria for 
schizophrenia developed by the American Psychiatric 
Association (DSM-IV), [34] required a duration of 
illness of at least 2 years (with one exception [9] ), 
and required unsatisfactory clinical results when 
previously using at least two types of antipsychotic 
medications. </p>

<p>b) Gender of participants: One study [32] only included 
females, but all other studies [9-23,26-31] included both 
males and females. </p>

<p>c) Age of participants: Three studies [9,17,27] did not 
describe the age of participants; the remaining 19 
studies [10-16, 18-23, 26,28-32] were conducted with adults 
ranging from 18 to 74 years of age. </p>

<p>d) Duration of illness: Among the 17 studies that 
provided the mean duration of illness among 
participants, [9,11-13,15,17-19,22,23,26-32] the range in the 
mean duration of illness was from 6 to 21 years. </p>

<p>e) Type of antipsychotic medication used in study: All 
participants received antipsychotic medications 
either alone or in combination with ECT. The 
medications employed included clozapine, 
olanzapine, risperidone, quetiapine, ziprasidone, 
chlorpromazine, and flupenthixol. </p>

<p>f) ECT sessions: Two studies [9,17] did not provide 
information on the number of ECT sessions; the 
remaining studies [10-16,18-32] reported using 6 to 24 
ECT sessions. Among the 18 studies [10-14,16,18, 20-23,26-
32] that provided information on ECT frequency, 
the range in frequency was from three sessions 
per week to two sessions per month. Only eight 
studies [11,12,13,17,22,23,28,31] reported on the type of ECT 
stimulus, which was either bilateral or bitemporal. </p>

<p>g) Outcome measures: Standard measures of 
psychiatric symptoms, primarily the Positive and 
Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) [35] and the Brief 
Psychiatric Rating Scale (BPRS), [36] were used to 
assess effectiveness, though the criteria used to 
determine clinical improvement varied somewhat 
across studies. Overall adverse events were 
assessed using TESS [37] in six studies. [10,13,18,20,28,30] 
Five studies reported results of cognitive 
functioning: two studies [11,23] used the Mini-
Mental State Examination (MMSE), [41] one study [18] 
used the Wisconsin Card Sorting Test (WCST), [42] 
and two studies [19,31] used the Wechsler Memory 
Scale (WMS). [43] Overall functioning was assessed 
using the Global Assessment of Functioning (GAF) </p>

<p>[38] </p>

<p>in three studies [11,18,28] and the Clinical Global 
Impression score (CGI) [44] in one study. [17] </p>

<p>h) Duration of follow-up: One study [26] did not provide 
information about the duration of follow-up; 
one study [14] had a 3 to 5 week follow-up; four 
studies [17,21,27,31] followed patients for 4 weeks; nine 
studies [9,10,15,19,20,22,23,30,32] followed patients for 8 
weeks; six studies [12,13 16,18,28,29] followed patients for 
12 weeks; and one study [11] followed patients for 24 
weeks. </p>

<p>3.2 Risk of bias and publication bias 
The results of the assessment of risk of bias in the 
22 studies are shown in Table 3. Most of the studies, 
particularly those from China, did not provide sufficient 
details about the methods used in the study, so the 
majority of the assessments for the seven items 
included in the Risk of Bias (ROB) tool [5] were rated 
as 'uncertain'. One study [17] used sham ECT and, thus, 
was double-blind; two other studies [11,23] used blinded 
outcome evaluators; and one study [23] reported that the 
participants and treating clinicians were not blinded; but 
none of the other studies provided information about 
blinding of the participant, the treating clinician, or the 
outcome evaluator. Only two studies [17,18] described the 
method of randomization. Overall, one study [23] was 
rated as 'high' risk of bias and the other studies were all 
rated as 'uncertain' risk of bias; none of the studies were 
classified as being at low-risk of bias. The inter-rater 
reliability of the two independent coders' assessment 
of overall risk of bias in the studies was acceptable 
(kappa=0.75). 
The funnel plot of the primary outcome of efficacy 
provided by 18 of the studies [9,10,12-16,18-20,22-23,26-27,29-32] is 
shown in Figure 2. There is substantial publication bias; 
the three smaller studies [9,19,23] were more likely to find a 
significant advantage for combined treatment with ECT 
plus antipsychotic medications versus the sole use of 
antipsychotic medications in the treatment of refractory 
schizophrenia. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Funnel plot of publication bias based on 
the primary outcome measure of efficacy 
in 18 of the 22 included studies </p>

<p>0.1 
0.2 
0.5 
1.0 
2.0 
5.0 
10.0 
20.0 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>Risk Ratio </p>

<p>Standard error </p>

<p>Table 1. Characteristics of 22 randomized controlled trials that compare treatment of refractory schizophrenia 
with combined ECT and antipsychotic medication versus treatment with antipsychotic medication 
alone </p>

<p>study 
treatment 
ECT group 
/control group </p>

<p>age 
ECT group 
/control group </p>

<p>sample size 
ECT group 
/control group </p>

<p>trial 
duration 
(weeks) </p>

<p>number 
of ECT 
sessions </p>

<p>blind 
evaluation </p>

<p>outcome 
measures 
(change 
required for 
'improvement') </p>

<p>Chanpattana 
1999 [11] 
ECT+ flupenthixol 
/flupenthixol 
20-49 
17 
/18 
24 
14 
yes 
BPRS; GAF; 
MMSE </p>

<p>Goswami 
2003 [17] 
ECT+chlorpromazine 
/sham ECT+chlorpromazine 
NA 
15 
/10 
4 
NA 
yes 
BPRS (20%) and 
CGI≤3 
or BPRS≤35 
Yang 
2005 [27] 
ECT+clozapine 
/clozapine 
NA 
30 
/30 
4 
6-12 
NA 
PANSS (20%) </p>

<p>Ding 
2007 [13] 
ECT+risperidone 
/risperidone 
36.5 
/38.7 
30 
/30 
12 
≥12 
NA 
PANSS (20%); 
TESS 
Cai 
2008 [10] 
ECT+clozapine 
/clozapine 
18-60 
50 
/50 
8 
6-12 
NA 
BPRS (25%); 
TESS 
Braga 
2009 [9] 
ECT+clozapine 
/clozapine 
NA 
21 
/17 
8 
NA 
NA 
BPRS (20%) </p>

<p>Jiang 
2009 [18] 
ECT+risperidone 
/risperidone 
38.3 
/39.7 
34 
/35 
12 
8-12 
NA 
PANSS (50%); 
TESS; WCST; 
GAF 
Zhou 
2009 [31] 
ECT+olanzepine 
/olanzepine 
43.1 
/42.2 
31 
/32 
4 
8-12 
NA 
PANSS (25%); 
WMS 
Liu 
2010a [21] 
ECT+various antipsychotics 
/various antipsychotics 
38.4 
/39.4 
37 
/35 
4 
12 
NA 
SANS (50%); 
SAPS (50%) 
Liu 
2010b [22] 
ECT+risperidone 
/clozapine 
28.6 
/27.9 
30 
/30 
8 
≥12 
NA 
PANSS (25%) </p>

<p>Ding 
2011 [14] 
ECT+various antipsychotics 
/various antipsychotics 
29.8 
/31.5 
100 
/100 
3-5 
9-15 
NA 
PANSS (50%) </p>

<p>Du 
2011 [15] 
ECT+clozapine 
/clozapine 
38.6 
30 
/30 
8 
10 
NA 
BPRS (25%) </p>

<p>Duo 
2003 [16] 
ECT+olanzepine 
/olanzepine 
43.8 
/42.7 
30 
/30 
12 
8-12 
NA 
PANSS (25%) </p>

<p>Jiang 
2011 [19] 
ECT+various antipsychotics 
/various antipsychotics 
43.4 
23 
/23 
8 
17-24 
NA 
PANSS (50%); 
WMS 
Yang 
2011 [28] 
ECT+risperidone 
/risperidone 
18-65 
35 
/36 
12 
12 
NA 
PANSS (25%); 
GAF; TESS 
Chen 
2012 [29] 
ECT+clozapine 
/clozapine 
31.9 
/33.6 
36 
/35 
12 
7-12 
NA 
PANSS (25%) </p>

<p>Wang 
2012 [32] 
ECT+quetiapine 
/quetiapine 
28.9 
/29.3 
31 
/31 
8 
10 
NA 
PANSS (25%) </p>

<p>Zhang 
2012 [30] 
ECT+olanzepine 
/olanzepine 
38.4 
42 
/42 
8 
16 
NA 
PANSS (25%); 
TESS 
Chen 
2013 [12] 
ECT+various antipsychotics 
/various antipsychotics 
18-60 
50 
/40 
12 
8-12 
NA 
PANSS (25%) </p>

<p>Jiang 
2013 [20] 
ECT+ziprasidone 
/ziprasidone+Clozapine 
21-74 
81 
/81 
8 
12 
NA 
BPRS (25%); 
TESS </p>

<p>Wang 
2013 [26] 
ECT+olanzepine 
/olanzepine 
45.5 
36 
/36 
NA 
10-12 
NA 
PANSS (25%) </p>

<p>Petrides 
2015 [23] 
ECT+clozapine 
/clozapine 
18-60 
20 
/19 
8 
20 
yes 
BPRS (40%); 
MMSE </p>

<p>ECT. electroconvulsive therapy 
NA, data not available 
BPRS, Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale [36] 
GAF, Global Assessment of Functioning [38] 
a only had female participants </p>

<p>MMSE, Mini-Mental Status Exam [41] 
PANSS, Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale [35] 
CGI, Clinical Global Impression [44] 
TESS, Treatment Emergent Symptoms Scale [37] </p>

<p>WCST, Wisconsin Card Sort Test [42] 
WMS, Weschler Memory Scale [43] 
SANS, Scale for Assessment of Negative Symptoms [40] 
SAPS, Scale for Assessment of Positive Symptoms [39] </p>

<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2015, Vol. 27, No. 4 </p>

<p>• 210 • </p>

<p>Table 2. Supplemental information for the 22 studies included in the systematic review </p>

<p>study </p>

<p>definition of 'treatment refractory schizophrenia' 
mean (sd) 
years of illness 
ECT group 
/control group </p>

<p>type 
of ECT 
stimulus </p>

<p>ECT 
frequency 
diagnostic 
criteria </p>

<p>number of 
failed drug 
trials </p>

<p>chlorpromazine-
equivalent dose 
(mg/d) </p>

<p>duration 
of illness 
severity 
of illness </p>

<p>Chanpattana 
1999 [11] 
NA 
≥2 
&gt;750 
≥2 years BPRS&gt;35 
13.7 (5.5) 
/14.2 (6.4) 
bilateral 
2-4/month </p>

<p>Goswami 
2003 [17] 
DSM-IV 
≥3 
&gt;1000 
≥5 years 
NA 
7.6 
/6.9 
bitemporal 
NA </p>

<p>Yang 
2005 [27] 
CCMD-3 
≥3 
NA 
≥5 years PANSS&gt;60 
6.3 (4.3) 
/6.0 (4.9) 
NA 
3/week </p>

<p>Ding 
2007 [13] 
CCMD-3 
≥3 
&gt;450 
≥5 years PANSS&gt;65 
9.7 (11.0) 
/9.7 (10.4) 
bitemporal 
1-2/week </p>

<p>Cai 
2008 [10] 
CCMD-3 
≥3 
&gt;600 
NA 
BPRS&gt;50 
1-10 a 
NA 
3/week </p>

<p>Braga 
2009 [9] 
NA 
NA 
&gt;250 
≥8 
weeks 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA </p>

<p>Jiang 
2009 [18] 
CCMD-3 
≥3 
NA 
≥5 years PANSS≥60 
12.6 (5.1) 
/12.4 (5.0) 
NA 
2-3/week </p>

<p>Zhou 
2009 [31] 
CCMD-3 
≥3 
&gt;600 
≥5 years PANSS≥60 
21.0 (7.8) 
/19.4 (9.9) 
bitemporal 
2-3/week </p>

<p>Liu 
2010a [21] 
CCMD-3 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
3/week </p>

<p>Liu 
2010b [22] 
CCMD-3 
≥3 
NA 
≥5 years PANSS≥60 
8.3 (4.2) 
/8.0 (3.2) 
bitemporal 
1-3/week </p>

<p>Ding 
2011 [14] 
CCMD-3 
≥3 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
3/week </p>

<p>Du 
2011 [15] 
CCMD-3 
≥3 
&gt;1000 
≥5 years BPRS≥45 
10.0 (4.0) 
NA 
NA </p>

<p>Duo 
2011 [16] 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
17.5 (5.6) 
/18.6 (4.2) 
NA 
2-3/week </p>

<p>Jiang 
2011 [19] 
CCMD-3 
≥2 
NA 
≥2 years PANSS≥60 
7.5 (7.6) 
NA 
NA </p>

<p>Yang 
2011 [28] 
CCMD-3 
≥3 
NA 
≥5 years PANSS≥60, 
11.2 (5.2) 
/10.3 (4.9) 
bitemporal 
2-3/week </p>

<p>Chen 
2012 [29] 
CCMD-3 
≥2 
&gt;600 
≥5 years PANSS&gt;60 
16.1 (11.6) 
/15.8 (11.2) 
NA 
2-3/week </p>

<p>Wang 
2012 [32] 
CCMD-3 
≥2 
&gt;600 
≥5 years PANSS≥60 
8.7 
NA 
3/week </p>

<p>Zhang 
2012 [30] 
CCMD-3 
≥3 
NA 
≥5 years PANSS&gt;60 
NA 
NA 
1-3/week </p>

<p>Chen 
2013 [12] 
CCMD-3 
≥3 
NA 
≥5 years PANSS&gt;60 
9.0 (1.7) 
/8.5 (0.9) 
bitemporal 
2-3/week </p>

<p>Jiang 
2013 [20] 
CCMD-2-R 
≥3 
NA 
NA 
NA 
7.9 
NA 
1-3/week </p>

<p>Wang 
2013 [26] 
CCMD-3 
≥3 
NA 
≥5 years 
NA 
13.2 (5.2) 
NA 
3/week </p>

<p>Petrides 
2015 [23] 
DSM-IV 
≥2 
&gt;600 
≥2 years BPRS; CGI b 
NA 
bilateral 
2-3/week </p>

<p>ECT, electroconvulsive therapy 
NA, data not available 
BPRS, Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale [36] 
PANSS, Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale [35] 
a range (not mean) in duration of illness </p>

<p>CGI, Clinical Global Impression [44] 
DSM-IV, 4 th edition of Diagnostic and Statistical Manual for mental disorders [34] 
CCMD-3, 3 rd edition of Chinese Classification of Mental Disorders [33] 
CCMD-2-R, Revised 2 nd edition of Chinese Classification of Mental Disorders [33] 
b one of the four psychotic items of BPRS&gt;4 or total score&gt;12; and CGI&gt;4 </p>

<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2015, Vol. 27, No. 4 </p>

<p>• 211 • </p>

<p>Table 3. Evaluation of risk of bias in the 22 included studies based on the seven items in the Cochrane Risk 
of Bias (RoB) tool </p>

<p>study 
random 
sequence 
generation </p>

<p>allocation 
concealment </p>

<p>blinding of 
participants 
and providers </p>

<p>blinding of 
outcome 
assessment </p>

<p>incomplete 
outcome 
data </p>

<p>selective 
reporting 
other 
biases a 
overall risk 
of bias b </p>

<p>Chanpattana, 1999 [11] Unclear 
Low 
Unclear 
Low 
Low 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Goswami, 2003 [17] 
Low 
Low 
Low 
Low 
Low 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Yang, 2005 [27] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Ding, 2007 [13] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Cai, 2008 [10] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Braga, 2009 [9] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Jiang, 2009 [18] 
Low 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Low 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Zhou, 2009 [31] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Liu, 2010a [21] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Low 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Liu, 2010b [22] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Ding, 2011 [14] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Low 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Du, 2011 [15] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Duo, 2011 [16] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Jiang, 2011 [19] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Yang, 2011 [28] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Low 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Chen, 2012 [29] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Wang, 2012 [32] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Zhang, 2012 [30] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Chen, 2013 12] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Jiang, 2013 [20] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Wang, 2013 [26] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear 
Unclear </p>

<p>Petrides, 2015 [23] 
Unclear 
Unclear 
High 
Low 
Low 
Unclear 
Unclear 
High </p>

<p>kappa c 
1.00 
1.00 
0.49 
0.82 
1.00 
1.00 
1.00 
0.75 </p>

<p>a Other biases considered include including study-specific biases or concerns about fraudulent results </p>

<p>b If any of seven items are coded high-risk of bias the overall study is classified as high-risk, if all seven items are coded as low-risk the overall study is 
classified as low-risk; all other studies (i.e., those with some items coded 'unclear' and no items coded as high-risk) are classified as 'unclear' 
c Weighted kappa values for inter-rater reliability of the two independent coders who assessed each item for the 23 studies </p>

<p>As shown in Table 4, based on the GRADE criteria 
the overall quality of the evidence about effectiveness 
(defined as percent of patients who showed 
'improvement' by the end of the trial) was rated as 
'moderate', but the quality of evidence about general 
side effects (assessed using TESS), cognitive functioning, 
and overall functioning was rated as 'very low'. The 
six studies that provided data about general side 
effects based on the TESS score [10,13,18,20,28,30] had very 
heterogeneous results and, thus, could not be pooled in 
a meta-analysis. </p>

<p>3.3 Efficacy </p>

<p>Eighteen studies with a pooled sample of 1394 
participants provided information on efficacy (i.e., 
percent of cases that achieved the study-specific criteria 
for 'improvement') at the end of the trial. [9,10,12-16,18-20,22-
23,26-27,29-32] The I 2 was satisfactory but the corresponding 
p-value was too small to justify considering the results 
of the various studies homogeneous (I 2 =38%, p=0.05), 
so a random-effect model was conducted. The result, 
shown in Figure 3, indicate that patients with refractory </p>

<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2015, Vol. 27, No. 4 </p>

<p>• 212 • </p>

<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2015, Vol. 27, No. 4 </p>

<p>• 213 • </p>

<p>Table 4. Summary of meta-analysis and GRADE assessments of quality of data about different outcome 
measures of randomized compared trials comparing ECT and antipsychotic medication versus 
medication alone in the treatment of treatment refractory schizophrenia </p>

<p>outcomes 
number of studies 
(pooled sample) </p>

<p>test for 
heterogeneity 
analytic 
model </p>

<p>test for 
overall effect estimate 
95% confidence 
interval of estimate 
GRADE 
I 2 
p 
Z 
p </p>

<p>effectiveness 
18 (1394) 
38% 
0.05 
fixed 
7.51 &lt;0.001 
1.31 
(RR) 
1.22 -1.41 
moderate </p>

<p>side effect (TESS) 
6 (534) 
81% 
&lt;0.01 
-
-
-
-
-
very low </p>

<p>cognitive function 
4 (199) 
65% 
0.04 
random 1.14 
0.25 
-0.28 
(SMD) 
-0.77 -0.20 
very low </p>

<p>overall function 
3 (157) 
48% 
0.14 
fixed 
7.26 
&lt;0.01 
10.25 
(MD) 
7.48 -13.01 
very low </p>

<p>GRADE, Grades of Recommendation, Assessment, Development, and Evaluation 
ECT, electroconvulsive therapy 
TESS, Treatment Emergent Symptom Scale [37] </p>

<p>RR, risk ratio 
SMD, standardized mean difference 
MD, mean difference </p>

<p>Figure 3. Forest plot of proportion of patients with refractory schizophrenia who achieve study-specific criteria 
of improvement following treatment with either ECT plus antipsychotic medications or antipsychotic 
medications alone </p>

<p>schizophrenia treated with the combination of ECT and 
antipsychotic medications are more likely to experience 
symptomatic improvement than patients treated with 
antipsychotic medications alone (RR=1.25, 95% CI =1.14-
1.37). </p>

<p>3.4 Adverse effects 
As shown in Table 5, six studies with a pooled sample 
of 534 participants reported TESS scores. [10,13,18,20,28,30] 
The TESS results from these studies were quite </p>

<p>heterogeneous, so it is only possible to provide a 
descriptive assessment of the results. Using the overall 
TESS score as the measure of the severity of adverse 
events, three of the studies [18,28,30] showed no significant 
differences between the two groups, one study [13] found 
significantly more severe adverse events in the ECT plus 
antipsychotic medication group, and two studies [10,20] 
found significantly more severe adverse events in the 
group that only received antipsychotic medication. </p>

<p>Study </p>

<p>Random effects model </p>

<p>Yang 2005 [27] 
Ding 2007 [13] 
Cai 2008 [10] 
Zhou 2009 [31] 
Jiang 2009 [18] 
Braga 2009 [9] 
Liu 2010b [22] 
Duo 2011 [16] 
Ding 2011 [14] 
Jiang 2011 [19] 
Du 2011 [15] 
Zhang 2012 [30] 
Wang 2012 [32] 
Chen 2012 [29] 
Jiang 2013 [20] 
Chen 2013 [12] 
Wang 2013 [26] 
Petrides 2015 [23] </p>

<p>Events </p>

<p>27 
19 
49 
21 
18 
12 
20 
18 
72 
12 
24 
40 
22 
34 
67 
44 
33 
10 </p>

<p>Total </p>

<p>703 </p>

<p>30 
30 
50 
31 
32 
21 
30 
30 
100 
23 
30 
42 
31 
36 
81 
50 
36 
20 </p>

<p>Events </p>

<p>22 
17 
42 
20 
11 
1 
17 
14 
63 
0 
20 
29 
21 
21 
57 
29 
22 
0 </p>

<p>Total </p>

<p>691 </p>

<p>30 
30 
50 
32 
35 
17 
30 
30 
100 
23 
30 
42 
31 
35 
81 
40 
36 
19 </p>

<p>0.5 
1 
2 
20 </p>

<p>Risk 
Ratio 
RR </p>

<p>1.25 </p>

<p>1.23 
1.12 
1.17 
1.08 
1.79 
9.71 
1.18 
1.29 
1.14 
25.00 
1.20 
1.38 
1.05 
1.57 
1.18 
1.21 
1.50 
19.98 </p>



<p>Weight </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>7.6% 
3.7% 
13.0% 
4.6% 
2.1% 
0.2% 
3.9% 
2.9% 
9.7% 
0.1% 
5.7% 
8.8% 
5.2% 
6.5% 
10.6% 
8.7% 
6.6% 
0.1% </p>

<p>ECT+antipsychotics antipsychotics </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: I 2 =38.1%, tau 2 =0.0121, p=0.0516 
Test for overall effect: Z=4.89, p&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2015, Vol. 27, No. 4 </p>

<p>• 214 • </p>

<p>Table 5. Results for six studies that used the Treatment Emergent Symptom Scale (TESS) to assess adverse 
events in patients with refractory schizophrenia treated with combined electroconvulsive therapy 
(ECT) and antipsychotic medication versus those treated with antipsychotic medication alone </p>

<p>study 
ECT + medication group 
medication only group 
mean difference 
[95% CI] 
n 
mean (sd) 
n 
mean (sd) </p>

<p>Ding, 2007 [13] 
30 
2.7 (2.4) 
30 
1.3 (1.2) 
1.44 [0.47, 2.41] </p>

<p>Cai 2008 [10] 
50 
2.9 (1.6) 
50 
3.7 (2.0) 
-0.76 [-1.47, -0.05] </p>

<p>Jiang 2009 [18] 
32 
7.7 (5.9) 
35 
6.8 (5.4) 
0.95 [-1.78, 3.68] </p>

<p>Yang 2011 [28] 
30 
8.2 (6.1) 
31 
7.9 (5.9) 
0.34 [-2.69, 3.37] </p>

<p>Zhang 2012 [30] 
42 
5.9 (2.7) 
42 
6.9 (2.7) 
-0.98 [-2.13, 0.17] </p>

<p>Jiang 2013 [20] 
81 
3.4 (0.8) 
81 
4.5 (1.1) 
-1.10 [-1.40, -0.80] </p>

<p>Table 6. Comparison of incidence of different adverse events in patients with refractory schizophrenia 
treated with electroconvulsive therapy and antipsychotic medications versus those treated only 
with antipsychotic medications </p>

<p>events 
number of 
studies 
participants 
I 2 
p 
statistical method 
(risk ratio) 
effect estimate 
[95% CI] </p>

<p>abnormal electrocardiogram 
6 
383 
32% 
0.20 
fixed 
0.83 [0.58, 1.19] </p>

<p>abnormal electroencephalogram 
2 
123 
85% 
0.01 
random 
1.97 [0.31, 12.65] </p>

<p>abnormal liver enzymes 
7 
448 
0% 
0.80 
fixed 
0.67 [0.34, 1.34] </p>

<p>akathisia 
4 
263 
0% 
0.80 
fixed 
0.69 [0.37, 1.26] </p>

<p>anorexia/decreased appetite 
1 
60 
not applicable 
fixed 
2.00 [0.19, 20.90] </p>

<p>blurred vision 
3 
203 
0% 
0.95 
fixed 
0.92 [0.37, 2.26] </p>

<p>constipation 
6 
388 
42% 
0.13 
fixed 
0.52 [0.37, 0.73] </p>

<p>decreased motor activity 
2 
140 
71% 
0.06 
random 
0.22 [0.02, 3.10] </p>

<p>dizziness 
5 
323 
51% 
0.08 
random 
1.23 [0.56, 2.70] </p>

<p>drowsiness 
7 
457 
61% 
0.02 
random 
0.71 [0.35, 1.42] </p>

<p>dry mouth 
3 
203 
0% 
0.85 
fixed 
1.03 [0.49, 2.18] </p>

<p>Extrapyramidal symptoms 
3 
182 
0% 
0.40 
fixed 
1.74 [0.84, 3.58] </p>

<p>headache 
8 
517 
7% 
0.37 
fixed 
9.10 [3.97, 20.86] </p>

<p>hypotension 
1 
60 
not applicable 
fixed 
0.33 [0.01, 7.87] </p>

<p>increased salivation 
5 
328 
54% 
0.07 
random 
0.41 [0.18, 0.93] </p>

<p>insomnia 
5 
322 
59% 
0.05 
random 
0.46 [0.07, 3.22] </p>

<p>leukopenia 
5 
336 
0% 
0.49 
fixed 
0.31 [0.12, 0.82] </p>

<p>memory impairment 
7 
577 
36% 
0.16 
fixed 
6.48 [3.54, 11.87] </p>

<p>menstrual disorder 
1 
60 
not applicable 
fixed 
1.50 [0.27, 8.34] </p>

<p>nasal congestion 
1 
63 
not applicable 
fixed 
3.09 [0.13, 73.17] </p>

<p>nausea/vomiting 
5 
334 
0% 
0.94 
fixed 
2.33 [0.99, 5.49] </p>

<p>rigidity 
2 
140 
0% 
0.65 
fixed 
0.69 [0.40, 1.18] </p>

<p>tachycardia 
4 
268 
0% 
0.58 
fixed 
0.77 [0.50, 1.21] </p>

<p>tremors 
2 
140 
0% 
0.82 
fixed 
0.77 [0.43, 1.38] </p>

<p>weakness 
3 
185 
0% 
0.43 
fixed 
0.25 [0.11, 0.59] 
weight gain 
7 
468 
4% 
0.40 
fixed 
0.61 [0.43, 0.87] </p>

<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2015, Vol. 27, No. 4 </p>

<p>• 215 • </p>

<p>Thirteen studies [13-15,18,22,23,26-32] provided information 
about specific adverse events. As shown in Table 6, a 
total of 26 kinds of adverse events were reported. Meta-
analysis of the results identified two adverse effects 
that were reported at a significantly higher frequency 
by patients receiving combined treatment with ECT plus 
antipsychotic medication than by patients treated with 
antipsychotic medications alone: headache (based on 
a pooled sample of 517 individuals from eight studies, 
OR=9.10, 95%CI=3.97-20.86) and memory impairment 
(based on a pooled sample of 577 individuals from 
seven studies, OR=6.48, 95%CI=3.54-11.87). </p>

<p>3.5 Cognitive function 
F i v e s t u d i e s r e p o r t e d c o g n i t i v e f u n c t i o n 
results, [11,18,19,23,31] but only four of them had data that 
could be pooled in a meta-analysis. [11,18,23,31] The meta-
analysis (Figure 4) comparing the standardized mean 
difference (SMD) in the final scale scores between 
groups used the total MMSE score [41] for the two studies 
that used MMSE, [11,23] the perseverative errors score 
from the WCST [42] for the study that used the WCST, [18] 
and the picture recognition score from the WMS [43] for 
the study that use the WMS. [31] The results for the study 
that use the WCST and for the study that used the WMS </p>

<p>Figure 4. Forest plot of standardized mean difference in scores of three cognitive measures among patients 
with refractory schizophrenia following treatment with either ECT plus antipsychotic medications or 
antipsychotic medications alone </p>

<p>indicate significantly greater cognitive impairment in the 
group treated with ECT and antipsychotic medications, 
but when pooled with results from the two studies that 
use MMSE to assess cognitive functioning, the overall 
results were not significantly different between the two 
groups (SMD=-0.28, 95%CI=-0.77~0.20). However, as 
stated previously (Table 4), the quality of evidence from 
these studies was rated as 'very low'. </p>

<p>3.6 Overall function </p>

<p>The meta-analysis of the three studies [9,16,26] that used 
the GAF to assess overall functioning at the end of the 
trial is shown in Figure 5. (The study that employed CGI 
to assess overall functioning [17] could not be included 
because the report for the study did not include a 
standard deviation for the mean CGI score.) For each 
of the three studies and for the pooled result for the 
studies, the overall functioning at the end of the study </p>

<p>was significantly better in the ECT plus antipsychotic 
medication group than in the group treated with 
antipsychotic medications alone ( MD=10.25, 
95%CI=7.48-13.01). However, the quality of evidence 
for these studies was rated as 'very low' based on the 
GRADE criteria. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>4.1 Main findings </p>

<p>Since the operational definition of 'refractory 
schizophrenia' was first proposed by Kane in 1995, [3] 
there has been increasing research about the 
identification and management of these hard-to-
treat patients. Previous meta-analyses conclude that 
clozapine can improve psychiatric symptoms and 
decrease the occurence of extrapyramidal side effects 
for about half of these refractory patients. [24] ECT is </p>

<p>Study </p>

<p>Random effects model </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: I 2 =64.7%, tau 2 =0.159, p=0.0366 </p>

<p>scale = WCST </p>

<p>scale = MMSE </p>

<p>scale = WMS </p>

<p>Random effects model </p>

<p>Random effects model </p>

<p>Random effects model </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: I 2 =N/N%, tau 2 =0, p=1 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: I 2 =63.6%, tau 2 =0.212, p=0.0976 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: I 2 =N/N%, tau 2 =0, p=1 </p>

<p>Jiang 2009 [18] </p>

<p>Chanpattana 1999 [11] 
Petrides 2015 [23] </p>

<p>Zhou 2009 [31] </p>

<p>98 </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>15 
20 </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>20.12 </p>

<p>27.67 
23.10 </p>

<p>5.97 </p>

<p>12.47 </p>

<p>3.68 
1.20 </p>

<p>1.83 </p>

<p>101 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>15 
19 </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>27.94 </p>

<p>25.13 
23.40 </p>

<p>7.31 </p>

<p>14.16 </p>

<p>4.88 
1.20 </p>

<p>2.12 </p>

<p>−2 
−1 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>Standardized 
Mean Difference 
SMD </p>

<p>−0.28 </p>

<p>−0.58 </p>

<p>0.14 </p>

<p>−0.67 </p>

<p>−0.58 </p>

<p>0.57 
−0.24 </p>

<p>−0.67 </p>

<p>95%CI </p>

<p>[−0.77; 0.20] </p>

<p>[−1.07; −0.09] </p>

<p>[−0.66; 0.94] </p>

<p>[−1.18; −0.16] </p>

<p>[−1.07; −0.09] </p>

<p>[−0.16; 1.30] </p>

<p>[−0.88; 0.39] </p>

<p>[−1.18; −0.16] </p>

<p>Weight </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>28.1% </p>

<p>44.5% </p>

<p>27.5% </p>

<p>28.1% </p>

<p>20.8% 
23.7% </p>

<p>27.5% </p>

<p>n mean 
sd 
ECT+antipsychotics 
n mean sd 
antipsychotics </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=2.31, p=0.02 </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=0.35, p=0.73 </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=2.57, p=0.01 </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=1.14, p=0.25 
Test for subgroup differences: I 2 =33.0%, Chi 2 =2.99, p=0.22 </p>

<p>an option for increasing the proportion of refractory 
patients who achieve satisfactory clinical outcomes, 
but there are few studies addressing this issue, possibly 
because of the reluctance of patients and clinicians to 
use ECT. 
Extensive screening of English-language and 
Chinese-language databases identified 22 RCTs on 
this topic, among which 4 were in English and 18 
were in Chinese, suggesting that the use of ECT as an 
adjunctive treatment in refractory schizophrenia is 
less controversial in China than abroad. The pooled 
result about efficacy (defined as the proportion of 
participants that achieved the study-specific criteria 
for 'improvement') included 1394 individuals that 
participated in 18 studies. It clearly indicated a superior 
clinical result for refractory patients who received 
combined treatment with ECT and antipsychotic 
medications (RR=1.25, 95% CI =1.14~1.37). Moreover, 
the quality of the evidence for this outcome using the 
GRADE criteria was rated as 'moderate', which means 
that the result is reasonably robust. We also found 
that patients who received combined treatment were 
much more likely to report headaches and memory 
impairment during the treatment and to have higher 
overall functioning at the end of treatment, but the 
quality of evidence for these findings was rated as 'very 
low'. </p>

<p>4.2 Limitations 
The low quality of the RCTs identified for inclusion in 
this review seriously limits the validity of the results, 
particularly the results related to the occurrence of 
adverse effects, cognitive impairment, and overall 
functioning. As shown in our assessment of the risk of 
bias, the main problem was that most of the reports 
on the included studies did not provide details about 
the methods employed in the study, resulting in an 
overall rating of the assessment of risk of bias of 
'uncertain' in 21 of the 22 included studies. </p>

<p>The most troubling problem was lack of blinding. 
Double blinding is difficult to achieve in studies involving 
ECT because of the practical and ethical problems of 
administering 'sham ECT', so it is not surprising that 
sham ECT was only used in 1 of the 22 included studies. 
On the other hand, it is relatively easy to blind raters 
who assess the outcome measures, but this was only 
done in 3 of the 22 studies. We also identified a clear 
publication bias, favoring publication of studies that find 
superior outcomes among patients receiving both ECT 
and antipsychotic medication. </p>

<p>4.3 Implication 
The current study systematically reviewed and 
evaluated all available RCTs about the efficacy and 
safety of the combined use of antipsychotics and ECT in 
the treatment of patients with refractory schizophrenia. 
Meta-analysis of the 22 identified studies found that 
compared to treatment with antipsychotic medications 
alone, combined treatment with ECT and antipsychotic 
medication resulted in improved clinical outcomes, 
higher rates of headaches and memory impairment 
during treatment, and better overall functioning at the 
end of treatment. However, given the low quality of the 
evidence in the studies and the existence of publication 
bias, these results must be considered suggestive, not 
definitive. Better designed studies that include more 
detailed description of the methods employed are 
needed to confirm (or disprove) these results. 
Studies about the use of ECT in schizophrenia 
are relatively common in China, so this is one area in 
which China could make an important contribution 
to the global literature. However, Chinese mental 
health researchers will not be able to make useful 
international contributions until they resolve common 
problems in the design and implementation of their 
studies, problems that could be easily addressed by 
strict adherence to the recommendations for RCTs in 
the CONSORT statement. [5] </p>

<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2015, Vol. 27, No. 4 </p>

<p>• 216 • </p>

<p>Figure 5. Forest plot of mean difference in scores of the Global Assessment of Functioning scale (GAF) among 
patients with refractory schizophrenia following treatment with either ECT plus antipsychotic 
medications or antipsychotic medications alone </p>

<p>Study </p>

<p>Fixed effect model </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: I 2 =48.2%, tau 2 =6.457, p=0.1448 </p>

<p>Chanpattana 1999 [11] 
Jiang 2009 [18] 
Yang 2011 [28] </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>77 </p>

<p>15 
32 
30 </p>

<p>mean </p>

<p>51.06 
63.47 
57.63 </p>

<p>sd </p>

<p>16.54 
8.76 
8.62 </p>

<p>ECT+antipsychotics 
n </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>15 
35 
30 </p>

<p>mean </p>

<p>32.00 
54.65 
47.57 </p>

<p>sd </p>

<p>8.49 
7.92 
7.86 </p>

<p>5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 </p>

<p>Mean 
Difference 
MD </p>

<p>10.25 </p>

<p>19.06 
8.82 
10.06 </p>

<p>95%CI </p>

<p>[7.48; 13.01] </p>

<p>[9.65; 28.47] 
[4.81; 12.83] 
[5.89; 14.23] </p>

<p>Weight </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>8.6% 
47.5% 
43.9% </p>

<p>antipsychotics </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=7.26, p&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>背景：抗精神病药物合并电抽搐治疗 (electroconvulsive </p>

<p>therapy, ECT) 对难治性精神分裂症患者的疗效和安全性 
还不确定。 </p>

<p>目的：对电抽搐治疗在难治性精神分裂症中的应用的 
相关中英文文献进行系统综述和 meta 分析。 </p>

<p>方法：在中英文数据库中检索 2015 年 5 月 20 日前发 </p>

<p>表的关于抗精神病药物合并 ECT 治疗难治性精神分裂 
症疗效和安全性的研究。由两名研究人员根据预先设 
定的标准独立筛选和评估文献。采用 Review Manager 
5.1 软件进行数据分析。 </p>

<p>结果：共纳入 22 项随机对照研究，其中在中国大陆 </p>

<p>开展的研究有 18 项。本研究对 22 项研究中的 18 项 
研究共 1394 例样本进行 meta 分析后发现，相比于 
单独使用抗精神病药物，抗精神病药物合并 ECT 治 
疗达到各研究特定的 " 临床改善 " 标准的比例要显著 
高 (RR=1.31, 95%CI=1.22-1.41)。根据推荐 GRADE 分级 
的评估、制定和评价标准 (Grades of Recommendation, 
Assessment, Development, and Evaluation, GRADE)， 该 
疗效评估的证据质量是"中等"。但是，在治疗过程 </p>

<p>中出现头痛的参与者比例在合并治疗组中显著更高 
（RR=9.10, 95%CI=3.97-20.86，基于 8 项研究 517 例样 
本）。合并治疗组中出现记忆受损的患者的比例也高 
（RR=6.48，95% CI=3.54-11.87， 基 于 7 项 研 究 577 例 
样本）。这些不良反应的证据质量被评定为"非常低"。 </p>

<p>结论：有关抗精神病药物合并 ECT 治疗难治性精神分 
裂症的高质量随机对照临床试验很少。该 meta 分析 
发现，抗精神病药物合并 ECT 可以改善难治性精神分 
裂症患者的精神症状，但大多数研究提供的方法学信 
息不全，存在发表偏倚（更偏向于合并治疗组结果相 
对好的研究），有关不良反应、认知受损和整体功能 
的证据质量较低，这使我们需要对结果的效度有所质 
疑。 </p>

<p>关键词：电抽搐治疗；抗精神病药物；难治性精神分 
裂症；系统综述；meta 分析 </p>

<p>本文全文中文版从 2015 年 10 月 26 日起在 
http://dx.doi.org/10.11919/j.issn.1002-0829.215093 可供免费阅览下载 </p>

<p>抗精神病药物合并电抽搐治疗对难治性精神分裂症患者的疗效和安全性：一项系统综述和 
meta 分析 </p>

<p>王文政，蒲城城，蒋江灵， 曹歆轶，王继军，赵敏，李春波 </p>



<p>Conflict of interest 
The authors report no conflict of interest related to this 
manuscript. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment 
We thank the reviewers of this analysis for their useful 
comments. </p>

<p>Funding 
This study was funded by Shanghai Shen Kang Hospital 
Development Center (SHDC12014111), the Science </p>

<p>and Technology Commission of Shanghai Municipality 
(13z2260500, 14411961400), the Shanghai Municipal 
Commission of Health and Family Planning (2013SY003, 
2013SY011, 2014ZYJB0002), and the Shanghai Health 
System Leadership in Health Research Program 
(XBR2011005). The funding agencies played no role in 
the design, analysis, or write up of the results of the 
study. </p>



</text></tei>