<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4628493" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Objectives: The aim of the present study was to develop a plate to treat mandibular angle fractures using the finite element 
method and mechanical testing. 
Material and Methods: A three-dimensional model of a fractured mandible was generated using <rs type="software">Rhinoceros 4.0 software</rs>. 
The models were exported to ANSYS </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, in which a static application of displacement (3 mm) was performed in the first molar 
region. Three groups were assessed according to the method of internal fixation (2 mm system): two non-locking plates; 
two locking plates and a new design locking plate. The computational model was transferred to an in vitro experiment with 
polyurethane mandibles. Each group contained five samples and was subjected to a linear loading test in a universal testing 
machine. 
Results: A balanced distribution of stress was associated with the new plate design. This plate modified the mechanical 
behavior of the fractured region, with less displacement between the fractured segments. In the mechanical test, the group 
with two locking plates exhibited greater resistance to the 3 mm displacement, with a statistically significant difference when 
compared with the new plate group (ANOVA, P = 0.016). 
Conclusions: The new plate exhibited a more balanced distribution of stress. However, the group with two locking plates 
exhibited greater mechanical resistance. </p>

<p>Fractures of the mandibular angle are the most 
problematic in the facial region due to the high 
frequency of complications after treatment. These 
complications mainly involve infections and non-
union [1]. Conceptually, stable fixation of the 
fragments minimizes sequestration while enabling 
post-operative function. In comminuted mandibular 
fractures, 2.4 mm locking plates are generally used, 
although the heavier variety of 2 mm locking plates is 
now becoming popular [2]. 
The plates employed should ensure functional, 
mechanical, and morphological rehabilitation [3]. 
The large number of studies on the treatment of 
mandibular angle fractures reflects the fact that a 
consensus has not been reached for a single, ideal 
treatment method. Biomechanical studies play an 
important role in improving the design and producing 
successful materials for medical and clinical purposes. 
The results of biomechanical studies do not always 
correspond to clinical outcomes and consequently, 
biomechanics are not the only factor to be considered 
when treating fractures [4]. Studies should try to 
simulate clinical conditions and parameters, which are 
more likely to provide the clinician with meaningful 
information [5]. 
The aim of the present study was to propose and 
analyse a three-dimensional finite element analysis 
(FEA) model to simulate the behaviour of a fractured 
mandible with a lost base segment, after reduction 
with osteosynthesis plates, in order to assess the 
displacement and stress fields. The results were used 
to support the design and development of a new 
osteosynthesis plate and to compare the mechanical 
behaviour of this plate with others in terms of the 
stabilization of fractured segments. </p>

<p>MATERIAL AND METHODS </p>

<p>The computer model of the mandible was constructed 
using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Rhinoceros 4.0 software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">McNeel North America, Seattle, WA</rs>) and was based on a previous 
three-dimensional model of a mandible taken from 
a data bank. The data bank model was created using 
images from the Multislice Helical Computed 
Tomography of human jaws (volunteers), with a 
cutting thickness of 1 mm [6]. The mandible was 
cut in the right side angle area to simulate a fracture 
with bone loss. In this model, the teeth were removed 
to simplify the modelling, and a geometric reference 
was created in the location of the right first molar </p>

<p>on the alveolar ridge. This reference was used to mark 
the region for future displacement application. The 
computer model of the titanium plates and screws was 
developed based on a sketch of products from Tóride </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>(Tóride Indústria e Comércio Ltd, Mogi-Mirim, São 
Paulo -Brazil). The three-dimensional geometry of 
the plates and screws was created using <rs type="software">Rhinoceros 
4.0 software</rs>. One 2 mm locking plate was developed 
based on information acquired from the literature 
regarding stress distribution and the use of a single 
tension band plate in mandibular angle fractures [7,8]. 
The plate was modelled using SolidWorks 
® 2012 X64 
edition SP02 (Dassault Systèmes S.A, USA). This 
model was imported to Rhinoceros 4.0 and adjusted 
for the mandible model. 
The mandibular fracture was fixed by three techniques 
of internal fixation: in Group I, one 4-hole 2 mm 
superior border plate was fixed with four screws with 
a 2 mm outer thread diameter (OTD) and a length of 
6 mm, while one 6-hole 2 mm inferior border plate 
was fixed with six 2 mm OTD, 12 mm long screws; 
in Group II, one 4-hole 2 mm locking superior 
border plate was fixed with four 2 mm OTD, 6 mm 
long locking screws, while one 6-hole 2 mm locking 
inferior border plate was fixed with six 2 mm OTD, 
12 mm long locking screws; in Group III, one newly 
designed 8-hole 2 mm locking plate was fixed with 
eight 2 mm OTD, 6 mm long locking screws. 
Each plate and screw needed to be in perfect contact 
with the bone. An attempt was made to place the 
plates according to standard clinical practice. Screws 
connecting the plates to the mandible were modelled 
without threads, with a diameter of 2 mm and a length 
that was appropriate for monocortical penetration 
(6 mm) on the superior border and bicortical 
penetration (12 mm) on the inferior border. 
The geometry was imported to the Ansys 
® 14.0.1. 2.0 
Framework (ANSYS 
® Inc., Houston, USA) to pre-
process the finite element model. All of the materials 
were considered to be homogenous, isotropic and 
linear elastic [9]. We elected to model the bone 
geometry as one homogeneous phase, similar to 
the synthetic material used to produce the mandible 
applied in the mechanical tests (polyurethane). The 
properties used for the polyurethane mandibular 
substratum were based on an isotropic Young´s 
modulus of 624.42 MPa and a Poisson´s ratio of 
0.2817 [10]. The properties of the titanium plates 
and screws followed the data provided by the 
manufacturer: the screws were made of Titanium alloy 
(Titanium-6Aluminum-4Vanadium; ASTM F-136) 
and the plates were made of commercially pure 
Titanium (ASTM F67) (Table 1). </p>

<p>http://www.ejomr.org/JOMR/archives/2015/3/e5/v6n3e5ht.htm </p>

<p>J Oral Maxillofac Res 2015 (Jul-Sep) | vol. 6 | No 3 | e5 | p.3 
(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF ORAL &amp; MAXILLOFACIAL RESEARCH 
Goulart et al. </p>

<p>The elements of the meshes used in the present 
study were quadratic tetrahedrons, generated with 
the following configurations: 1) mandibular ramus 
adjacent to the mandibular fracture, with a mean of 
1 mm for the edge of each geometric element in the 
cortical bone and 2 mm for the edge of the trabecular 
bone; 2) body of mandible and the left mandible 
side with a mean edge of 2 mm for each geometric 
element; 3) plates and screws with a mean edge of 0.3 
mm for each geometric element. The mean number 
of nodes and elements was 775,000 and 488,000, 
respectively. 
The mandible was constrained for all axes in the 
region of the temporomandibular joint and the 
coronoid process on both sides. A displacement of 
3 mm was applied to a point on the alveolar ridge, 
near the middle of the occlusal face of the first 
molar. The contact conditions between fractured 
segments were frictionless. The interaction between 
the plates and the heads of the conventional screws 
was considered frictionless. For the locking group, a 
perfectly glued (bonded) contact was applied. The 
interaction between the screws and the mandible was 
perfectly bonded. 
Mechanical static structural analysis was carried out. 
In addition, the displacement at a specific point above 
the fracture line and the reaction load at the point of 
displacement were assessed. All stress values were 
given in Megapascals (MPa) and the reaction load 
was given in Newtons (N). A colour scale with stress 
values was used to qualitatively assess the stress 
distribution in plates and screws. 
In the mechanical test a total of 15 synthetic 
polyurethane mandibles (Nacional Ossos, São 
Paulo, Brazil) were used in this investigation. One 
polyurethane mandible was sectioned at the right side 
angle, to simulate a fracture with a triangular defect 
in the base, using a diamond disc mounted on a hand 
piece. Subsequently, this model was sent to the factory 
for replication. The segment contained an isosceles 
triangle with the following dimensions: length of the 
side -15 mm; length of the inferior border defect -10 
mm. Mandibles were randomly separated into three 
groups according to the fixation technique used, as 
described in the FEA model. The plates and screws </p>

<p>Figure 1. Right side lateral view of the polyurethane mandible, 
fixed according to Group III. </p>

<p>Table 1. Properties of materials used in simulation at Ansys </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>Young's modulus 
(MPa) 
Poisson's ratio </p>

<p>Mandible -cortical 
and cancellous bone 
624.42 
0.28 </p>

<p>Titanium F136 
1.138 x 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0.34 </p>

<p>Titanium F67 
1.16 x 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0.34 </p>

<p>were fabricated by Tóride 
® . Each group contained 5 
polyurethane mandibles. Figure 1 displays one of the 
polyurethane mandibles (Group III). 
The adaptation of the titanium-based plates to 
the mandible was ensured by using the specific 
instruments offered in the manufacturer's set. To 
standardize the position of the plate, acrylic jigs 
were made for each sub-group and adapted to the 
lateral aspect of the polyurethane mandibles during 
the fixation of the plate. The sample groups were 
submitted to a linear loading test in the upper and 
lower areas of the first molar region using the Instron 
4411 (Instron Corp., Norwood, MA) servohydraulic 
material testing unit. 
The mandibles were included in acrylic in a 
mechanical testing structure that was custom-made for 
the present study. In the testing structure, the condyle 
and coronoid processes were fixed on both sides while 
the loading was applied to the occlusal surface of the 
first molar on the same side of the fracture. 
Instron 4411 produced linear displacement at a rate 
of 1 mm/min and the loading was continuously 
applied up to 5 mm of displacement. Load data for the 
reaction force (Newtons) was obtained for 1, 3 and 5 
mm of displacement. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>In the FEA the results were descriptive regarding 
displacement of fractured segment, reaction load 
and equivalent Von Mises Stress distribution. In the 
mechanical test, parametric data were expressed as 
mean and standard deviation (M [SD]). These values 
were derived and compared for statistical significance 
within the attachment categories and then tested using 
analysis of variance (one-way ANOVA). Values were 
considered significant at P &lt; 0.05. Mean values were 
compared using Tukey´s test. </p>

<p>http://www.ejomr.org/JOMR/archives/2015/3/e5/v6n3e5ht.htm </p>

<p>J Oral Maxillofac Res 2015 (Jul-Sep) | vol. 6 | No 3 | e5 | p.4 
(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF ORAL &amp; MAXILLOFACIAL RESEARCH 
Goulart et al. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>It was clear that the lower plate was placed under 
less stress than the upper plate in the FEA. The stress 
was mostly concentrated in the area of the first distal 
screw and around the plates that crossed the fracture 
line in Groups I and II. The stress distribution was 
similar for locking and non-locking plates in terms of 
sharing the load among the screws: the screws at the 
extremities do not share load. In the Group III, there 
is a more homogeneous stress distribution along the 
plates; however, it was more pronounced between 
the second and third screws of the upper area of the 
plate. Figures 2 to 4 display the stress distribution 
for the three techniques studied. In this model, </p>

<p>Figure 2. Von Mises Stress scale. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Equivalent Von Mises Stress distribution in plates 
and screws from Group I. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Equivalent Von Mises Stress distribution in plates 
and screws from Group II. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Equivalent Von Mises Stress distribution in plates 
and screws from Group III. </p>

<p>Table 2. Displacement of geometric reference (mm) in the finite 
element analysis model </p>

<p>Axis 
X 
Y 
Z 
Group I 
0.69 
0.51 
1.98 
Group II 
0.81 
0.59 
1.56 
Group III 
0.74 
0.28 
1.47 </p>

<p>Table 3. Force reaction in simulation of 3 mm of displacement </p>

<p>Reaction force (N) 
Group I 
467.35 
Group II 
651.67 
Group III 
594.41 </p>

<p>the fractured mandibular body tended to rotate, 
maintaining the central contact between the fractured 
segments. The displacement in the geometric 
reference was similar in all three groups, while 
Group III exhibited lower displacement values on 
the Y and Z axes. Table 2 displays the results of the 
displacement with geometric references. 
Group II exhibited the highest value of reaction force 
at specific displacement points. Table 3 displays the 
reaction force at the loading point of the three groups. </p>

<p>http://www.ejomr.org/JOMR/archives/2015/3/e5/v6n3e5ht.htm </p>

<p>J Oral Maxillofac Res 2015 (Jul-Sep) | vol. 6 | No 3 | e5 | p.5 
(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF ORAL &amp; MAXILLOFACIAL RESEARCH 
Goulart et al. </p>

<p>Table 4. Comparison of reaction force values (N) in between 
fixation groups </p>

<p>Displacement </p>

<p>1 mm 
3 mm 
5 mm </p>

<p>Mean (SD) </p>

<p>Group I 
44.96 (8.87) 113.87 (14.69) 155.58 (25.39) </p>

<p>Group II 
53.61 (9.83) 131.93 (16.1) 187.52 (19.93) </p>

<p>Group III 41.82 (9.94) 98.73 (16.9) 145.06 (36.28) </p>

<p>SD = Standard deviation. </p>

<p>In the mechanical test, fixation failure was not 
found in the groups with a displacement of 5 mm. 
Table 4 displays the loading for groups related to 
displacement. For 1 and 5 mm of displacement, 
no statistically significant differences were found 
between the groups in the one-way ANOVA 
(F = 2.03, P = 0.173; F = 3.11, P = 0.082). For 3 mm 
of displacement however, there was a statistically 
significant difference between the groups in the one-
way ANOVA (F = 5.44, P = 0.021). Tukey´s post-
hoc test revealed that the new plate exhibited a lower 
load at 3 mm of displacement (Mean 98.73 [16.9] N), 
which was statistically significant when compared 
with the two locking plates (Mean 131.93 [16.1] N; 
P = 0.016). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Several plates and screws with different geometric 
designs have been used in the treatment of mandibular 
angle fractures [11]. The geometric properties of these 
materials, as well as the number and location of the 
screws, have not yet ben definitely demonstrated. 
Existing practical techniques of internally stabilizing 
fractures of the mandible are mostly based on clinical 
experience [12]. The present study demonstrated 
patterns of stress distribution in the case of a 
mandibular angle fracture with bone loss. 
The geometric configuration and boundary conditions 
used in the FEA of mandibular fractures are diverse. 
To simplify the model, the teeth were removed, and 
the cortical and cancellous bones were modelled 
in polyurethane, as described in previous studies 
[9,10,12,13]. The contact between the segments was 
generally non-inexistent, with a gap of 1 or 2 mm [12]. 
Another model used a 1 mm callus section, placed 
between the two fractured mandible sections [13]. 
In the present study, we elected to apply a 
displacement of 3 mm in z direction above the 
ipsilateral first molar area. However, the literature 
contains studies that used bite force in a load point 
[9,12]. We assumed three-dimensional linear elastic 
behaviour for the entire model and frictionless 
unilateral contact between each side of the fractured 
mandible [14]. 
The new plate exhibited the lowest Von Mises stress 
values, which could be due to the more uniform 
distribution of the load on the plate. In Groups 
I and II, the upper plate exhibited a significant 
concentration of stress as the upper part of new 
designed plate. There is less material in the new plate 
design (eight screws instead of ten) and this plate is 
thinner than the lower locking plate (1 mm instead of </p>

<p>1.5 mm). New bone plates can support a greater load 
than commercially available plates with the same 
amount of material. In addition, new bone plates can 
be manufactured with less material to support the 
same load [15]. 
During the fracture healing period, the premature 
failure of plates must be prevented. The loads 
transmitted through the plates should not exceed the 
limit of the strength of the material. Screws near the 
fracture site are exposed to the greatest load [12]. The 
results of the present study confirmed these ideas, 
given that the screws near the fracture line and the site 
of the plates across the fracture exhibited the highest 
Von Mises stress values. 
On the other hand, using more screws and increasing 
the length of the plates helped to distribute the stress 
throughout the plates and screws. Distributing the 
stress improves the rigidity of the system, which 
can also be achieved by applying a more rigid plate 
or a second plate [12]. However, alterations to the 
design of plates, with less material, could improve 
the distribution of stress and the resistance of the 
system. In the present study, the reaction forces for the 
displacements of 1 mm and 5 mm were quite similar 
in all groups. 
The locking plate/screw reconstruction system 
used to treat mandibular fractures has the following 
advantages over other plating systems: these plates 
work as internal fixators; and they achieve stability 
by locking the screw to the plate [16]. A unique 
advantage of the locking screw/plate system is that 
the plate does not require intimate contact with the 
underlying bone, thereby making plate adaptation 
easier, preventing plate compression on the bone 
and minimizing bone traction against the plate [17]. 
To address these advantages in the new plate, it was 
necessary to include locking. Despite this fact, the 
mechanical advantages of the locking system may 
not necessarily reflect in a better clinical outcome, 
the postoperative complication rate in mandibular 
fractures does not seem to be influenced by the use of 
locking plates [18]. </p>

<p>http://www.ejomr.org/JOMR/archives/2015/3/e5/v6n3e5ht.htm </p>

<p>J Oral Maxillofac Res 2015 (Jul-Sep) | vol. 6 | No 3 | e5 | p.6 
(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF ORAL &amp; MAXILLOFACIAL RESEARCH 
Goulart et al. </p>

<p>One limitation of the present study, similar to most 
FEA models, was the assumption of a perfect bonding 
union between the bone and screws [9,12-14]. 
This does not occur in clinical situations and it is a 
significant limitation of this investigation. To reduce 
the limitation of this analysis, an in vitro test was 
performed to determine the differences between the 
groups. However, the complexity of the masticatory 
system and in vivo conditions can cause fixation 
systems to behave differently in a biomechanical 
testing unit [4]. 
Trivellato et al. [19] performed a biomechanical study 
to determine the effects of continuity on the inferior 
border in the treatment of mandibular fractures. The 
authors used polyurethane mandibles and a 2 mm 
titanium fixation system, which was applied according 
to the technique described by Champy et al. [7]. They 
found a statistically significant difference for fixation 
failure in the unfavourable group when the load was 
applied between the central incisors, confirming that 
the inferior border of the mandible with continuity 
provided better results than the inferior border of 
the mandible without continuity [19]. In the present 
study, the sample was sectioned in the same manner 
as the unfavourable fracture, without continuity of the 
inferior border. However, the aim of this study was to 
compare techniques of internal fixation. It is important 
to note that alterations in the load point could modify 
the mechanical response of the model. 
Due to the complexity of the current finite element 
model and mechanical test, the best form of validation 
can be achieved through a post-market study. In 
addition, the developed plate must undergo an 
optimization process. This could increase the efficacy 
of current devices while reducing their overall size 
and cumbersome nature. </p>

<p>The present study has limitations related to the 
study design. FEA did not incorporate teeth into the 
simulation. In addition, the model used was specific 
for a mandibular angle fracture with a segmental 
defect, and thus, was less generalized for all 
mandibular angle fractures. This new plate in relation 
to the osteosynthesis armamentarium will increase the 
costs once it can only be used for mandibular angle 
fractures. Finally, the present study contained the 
limitations inherent to all in vitro investigations. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>This finite element model confirmed that two 2 
mm locking plates provided more stiffness than the 
new plate. However, the new plate exhibited a more 
satisfactory distribution of stress. Furthermore, 
the new plate modifies the displacement pattern of 
fractured segments. The present study confirmed 
that two locking plates promote a better mechanical 
resistance for complex mandible fractures. Further 
studies using modifications of the mechanical 
condition should be performed to determine whether 
the new design is sufficiently stable to favour the 
healing of the mandible. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS AND DISCLOSURE 
STATEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest related to 
this study. </p>



<p>http://www.ejomr.org/JOMR/archives/2015/3/e5/v6n3e5ht.htm </p>

<p>J Oral Maxillofac Res 2015 (Jul-Sep) | vol. 6 | No 3 | e5 | p.7 
(page number not for citation purposes) </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF ORAL &amp; MAXILLOFACIAL RESEARCH 
Goulart et al. </p>



<p>To cite this article: 
Goulart DR, Kemmoku DT, Noritomi PY, de Moraes M. 
Development of a Titanium Plate for Mandibular Angle Fractures with a Bone Defect in the Lower Border: Finite Element 
Analysis and Mechanical Test. 
J Oral Maxillofac Res 2015;6(3):e5. 
URL: http://www.ejomr.org/JOMR/archives/2015/3/e5/v6n3e5.pdf 
doi: 10.5037/jomr.2015.6305 </p>

<p>Copyright © Goulart DR, Kemmoku DT, Noritomi PY, de Moraes M. Published in the JOURNAL OF ORAL &amp; 
MAXILLOFACIAL RESEARCH (http://www.ejomr.org), 30 September 2015. 
This is an open-access article, first published in the JOURNAL OF ORAL &amp; MAXILLOFACIAL RESEARCH, distributed 
under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivative Works 3.0 Unported License, which 
permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work and is 
properly cited. The copyright, license information and link to the original publication on (http://www.ejomr.org) must be 
included. </p>

</text></tei>