<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4385725" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>How to cite the article: 
Sastri MR, Tanpure VR, Palagi FB, Shinde SK, Ladhe K, Polepalle T. 
Study of the knowledge and attitude about principles and practices 
of orthodontic treatment among general dental practitioners and 
non-orthodontic specialties. J Int Oral Health 2015;7(3):44-48. 
Abstract: 
Background: General dental practitioners and non-orthodontic 
specialty can play an essential role of education and motivation 
of their patients about the principles and practice of orthodontic 
treatment; which can be very beneficial to the patient's lifestyle. 
It is, therefore, important to identify their level of knowledge and 
attitude toward orthodontic treatment. This study was planned 
to study this aspect in the form of comparative analysis in general 
dental practitioners and other specialties (except orthodontia) in 
dentistry. 
Materials and Methods: The study was done on 78 dentists, 
which was divided into two groups. Group I consisted of 46 
general dental practitioners and Group II consisted of 32 non-
orthodontic specialties. The study was carried out with the help of 
21 questionnaires, which consisted of 13 questions of orthodontic 
knowledge and 08 questions about the attitude toward orthodontic 
practice. The scores were calculated, and statistical analysis was 
done with the help of <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM</rs> <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> statistics <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">20</rs>, using Student's t-test. 
Results: The comparative analysis showed highly significant 
difference of knowledge and attitude score between general dental 
practitioners and non-orthodontic specialties (Student's t-test, 
P &lt; 0.001). Also the comparison was made between male and 
female practitioners, who showed more scores in case of male 
practitioners; but the difference was not significant statistically 
(Student's t-test, P &gt; 0.01). 
Conclusion: The results of the study were moderately satisfactory, 
and it showed the need for increased clinically oriented education 
of practice and concepts of orthodontic treatment. </p>

<p>Malocclusion means bad bite, and it consists of a spectrum 
of deviation from the normal or ideal occlusion to severe 
anomalies. 3,4 Malocclusion is defined as an "occlusion in which 
there is a molar relationship between the arches in any of 
the planes of spaces or in which there are anomalies in tooth 
position beyond the normal limits." Malocclusion usually 
creates feeling of shame for their facial appearance and may 
also give feeling of shy in their society. 4 </p>

<p>The outcomes of the orthodontic treatment are prevention 
of tissue damage, improvement in physical function and 
esthetic. The other major benefits are improving quality of life, 
development of self-confidence; and physical, psychological 
and social changes. 1-4 </p>

<p>It is important to educate the individuals about the benefits 
of the orthodontic treatment. This can be accomplished 
by a multi-disciplinary approach in which general dental 
practitioners and other non-orthodontic specialties can 
play the role of oral orthodontic health educators, but only 
if they have good knowledge and attitude of principles and 
practice of orthodontic treatment. Lew 5 has also stated 
that "practitioners should focus their attention beyond the 
orthodontic mechanotherapy to the more subjective aspects 
of patient discomfort and attitude toward treatment." 6 </p>

<p>Therefore, there is a need to identify the knowledge levels of 
dental practitioners with respect to the orthodontic treatment 
as they play an important role in inculcating healthy lifestyle </p>



<p>Journal of International Oral Health 2015; 7(3):44-48 
Knowledge and attitude about principles and practices of orthodontic treatment… 
Sastri MR et al </p>

<p>practices to their patients. This study was formulated for the 
comparative evaluation of the knowledge and attitude of the 
general dental practitioners and non-orthodontic specialties 
about the orthodontic treatment. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
The study was done on 78 dentists of age between 30 and 
50 years, which were divided into two groups. The study 
Group I consists of 46 general dental practitioners with a 
bachelor degree and Group II consists of 32 non-orthodontic 
specialties with a master degree in any subject of dentistry 
except orthodontia. These were selected from various regions 
of the Maharashtra, to study the knowledge and attitude 
toward principles and practice of orthodontic treatment. 
Total information about the study was given to all participants 
through personal contact, phone as well as through email, 
and the informed consent was obtained from each of the 
participants involved in the study. </p>

<p>Inclusion criteria 
1. General dental practitioner with bachelor degree 
2. Dentist with post-graduation degree in any branch (non-
orthodontic specialty) 
3. Age between 30 and 50 years. </p>

<p>Exclusion criteria 
1. Freshly pass-out dentists 
2. Dentists with age more than 50 years 
3. General dental practitioners, who stopped their practice. </p>

<p>The study was carried out based on specially prepared 
structured questionnaire containing 21 questions, which 
were validated by doing pilot study. The questionnaires 
were formulated for the study of the knowledge and attitude 
toward practice of orthodontic treatment of the general dental 
practitioners and non-orthodontic specialties. </p>

<p>A. Questionnaire for the knowledge of the orthodontic 
practice: 
In this, a total of 13 questions was formulated to study 
the knowledge of general dental surgeons and non-
orthodontics specialties. The questions were of Yes/No 
type questions and each correct answer were given a Score 
1 and incorrect answer was given score zero. The questions 
consists of their knowledge regarding starting age of 
orthodontic treatment, mixed orthodontic treatment 
in mixed dentition stage, facial appearance, functional 
therapy, proclined teeth, extraction of teeth for orthodontic 
purpose, habits, anchorage and retainers (Appendix I). For 
the scoring, Yes answer given score "one," except for the 
questions with marked as "N," for which score "one" was 
given for the answer No. 
B. Questionnaire to study attitude toward orthodontic 
practice: 
In this, 08 questions were prepared, which were also of </p>

<p>Yes/No type and scoring consists of Score 1 for correct 
answer and score zero for the wrong answer. In this the 
questions were formulated to study attitude toward 
orthodontic treatment like, diagnostic orthodontic 
procedures, opinion of orthodontist, giving information 
to patient about malocclusion when patient comes for the 
other dental treatment, orthodontic treatment in patients 
with periodontal problems, orthognathic surgeries and 
orthodontic treatment in missing teeth (Appendix II). In 
this section also, for the scoring, Yes answer given score 
"one," except for the questions with marked as "N," for 
which score "one" was given for the answer No. </p>

<p>The questionnaires were distributed through email to 
the general dental practitioners from various regions of 
Maharashtra. The emails were obtained from the dental 
association. They were told to send their answer through 
separate email containing the answers with questions number. 
The dentists in the nearby area of 100 km were contacted 
personally. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Scores were calculated based on the responses given by 
participants. The individual scores were summed up to get 
a total score. Statistical analysis was performed with the help 
of <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> statistics <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">20</rs>, with the help of Student's t-test. 
Descriptive statistics was calculated, and mean scores and 
standard deviation were obtained. </p>

<p>Results and Observations 
The study was done on 78 participants, consisting of 46 general 
dental practitioner and 32 non-orthodontic specialties. Out of 
these, 48 (61.53%) were males, and 30 were females (38.47%). 
(Table 1 and Graph 1) The age group selected was 30-50 years, 
to avoid the freshly passed-out students and old practitioners. </p>

<p>Table 1: Distribution of participants according to groups. </p>

<p>Group 
Males Females Total </p>

<p>Group I: General practitioners 
28 
18 
46 
Group II: Non-orthodontic specialties 
20 
12 
32 
Total 
48 
30 
78 </p>

<p>Graph 1: Distribution of participants according to groups 
and sex. </p>



<p>Journal of International Oral Health 2015; 7(3):44-48 
Knowledge and attitude about principles and practices of orthodontic treatment… 
Sastri MR et al </p>

<p>The total mean score of 21 questionnaires was calculated 
for the general dental practitioners and non-orthodontic 
specialties, which was 13.91 and 16.72, respectively (Table 2). </p>

<p>The scores of knowledge were compared between general 
dental practitioner (8.89) and non-orthodontic specialties 
(10.25), which showed that the scores were more for the 
non-orthodontic specialty and the difference was statistically 
highly significant (Table 3, Student's t-test, P &lt; 0.001). 
This indicates that the non-orthodontic specialties, which 
had given their 3 more years for the education of specialty 
in dentistry, had more knowledge about the orthodontic 
treatment (Graph 2). </p>

<p>Also, the scores of attitude were more for the non-orthodontic 
specialties (6.47) as compared to general dental practitioners 
(5.07), which also showed highly significant difference 
(Table 3, Student's t-test, P &lt; 0.001). This indicates that 
specialties had more positive attitude toward orthodontic 
treatment than general dental practitioners (Graph 2). </p>

<p>Comparison of the total score of 21 questionnaires was done 
between general dental practitioner, and non-orthodontic 
specialties were done, using Student's t-test. This was also </p>

<p>showed highly significant difference (Table 4, Student's t-test, 
P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Lastly, the scores of males and female participants of the study 
were compared, which showed that the scores were more 
for the male participants as compared to females, but the 
difference was not significant statistically (Table 5, Student's 
t test, P &gt; 0.01) (Graph 3). </p>

<p>Discussion 
After dental caries, malocclusion is the second most common 
dental disease in children and young adults. In India, the 
prevalence of malocclusion varies from 20% to 43%. For the 
improvement of the facial appearance, correction of dental 
malocclusion is an important factor, which is the main aim of the 
orthodontic treatment. 4,7 The essential factors having impact on 
deciding orthodontic treatment are esthetic improvement and 
psychological aspect. 7 The level of dental health knowledge, 
dental health attitude and dental health behavior are all 
interlinked, and this ultimately depends on the level of knowledge 
and positive attitude of the dental practitioners. 8 </p>

<p>In the present study, a comparative evaluation was done for the 
knowledge and attitude of the general dental practitioners and </p>

<p>Table 3: Comparison of the scores of the knowledge and attitude between general dental practitioner and non-orthodontic specialties, using Student's t-test. </p>

<p>Questionnaire 
Group 
n 
Mean±SD 
t value 
Significance </p>

<p>Knowledge 
General dental practitioner 
Non-orthodontic specialties </p>

<p>46 
32 </p>

<p>8.89±1.57 
10.25±1.34 </p>

<p>3.9906 
P&lt;0.001** </p>

<p>Attitude 
General dental practitioner 
Non-orthodontic specialties </p>

<p>46 
32 </p>

<p>5.07±1.16 
6.47±1.29 </p>

<p>5.0053 
P&lt;0.001** </p>

<p>**Difference was statistically significant, SD: Standard deviation </p>

<p>Table 2: The mean score of the knowledge and attitude according to groups and sex. </p>

<p>Group 
Questionnaire 
n 
Knowledge 
Attitude 
Total score </p>

<p>General dental practitioner 
Males 
Females 
Total mean score </p>

<p>28 
18 
46 </p>

<p>8.82 
9.00 
8.89 </p>

<p>5.10 
4.88 
5.07 </p>

<p>13.92 
13.88 
13.91 
Non-orthodontic specialties 
Males 
Females 
Total mean score </p>

<p>20 
12 
32 </p>

<p>10.30 
10.16 
10.25 </p>

<p>7.05 
5.50 
6.47 </p>

<p>17.35 
15.66 
16.72 </p>

<p>Graph 2: Comparison of scores of knowledge and attitude of 
general dental practitioners and non-orthodontic specialties. </p>

<p>Graph 3: Comparison of the total score of knowledge and 
attitude between male and female participants of the study. </p>



<p>Journal of International Oral Health 2015; 7(3):44-48 
Knowledge and attitude about principles and practices of orthodontic treatment… 
Sastri MR et al </p>

<p>non-orthodontic specialties, with the help of specially prepared 
questionnaires. When comparison of the knowledge scores 
between general dental practitioners and non-orthodontic 
specialties was done, it showed highly significant difference. 
Which indicates that the knowledge of the specialties in 
dentistry, which given three more years of their life for the 
education in specialty of dentistry, was more as compared to 
the general dental practitioners. </p>

<p>When all the participants were questioned knowledge question 
of start of the orthodontic treatment at any age, 78.2% of them 
answered positively. The treatment of malocclusions during mixed 
dentition stage and the importance of well-aligned teeth for the 
overall facial appearance were answered affirmatively by 67.9% 
and 85.8% respectively, in case of all participants. About 100% 
positive response was present for the awareness of extraction of few 
teeth for aligning of the irregular teeth, in case of non-orthodontic 
specialties and 87.5% for the general dental practitioners. The 
maximum positive response i.e. 91.3% was given by general dental 
practitioner for the effect of habits like mouth breathing or thumb 
sucking on alignment of the front teeth. </p>

<p>The percentage of "yes" answers for the questions of use of 
mini screws and retainers was 47.8% and 65.2% by the general 
practitioners and 75.0% and 81.2% by the non-orthodontic 
specialties respectively i.e. 75% of non-orthodontic specialties 
were aware of the fact that mini screws can replace molars for 
anchorage while 25% were not familiar with the concept. The 
results of the present study like treatment of malocclusions 
during mixed dentition period, use of functional appliance, 
awareness of the skeletal malocclusion, extraction for 
orthodontic treatment were in accordance with the study done 
by Niveda and Saravana. 9 </p>

<p>Also, the comparison of the attitude toward orthodontic 
practice and referral, between general dental practitioners </p>

<p>and non-orthodontic specialties showed highly significant 
difference. This showed that the specialties have more 
positive attitude toward the importance of the orthodontic 
treatment. </p>

<p>In study of attitude questions, the maximum correct response 
(80.4%) in general dental practitioners was given for the 
convincing of the orthodontic treatment and that in case of 
non-orthodontic specialties (87.5%) was given for the looking 
of the malocclusion on clinical examination when patient 
reports with any other complaints. The fact that the report 
of the patient for orthodontic treatment and orthognathic 
surgeries were approved positively by 56.2% and 65.6% 
respectively; in case of non-orthodontic specialties. </p>

<p>Among all participants, around 42.3% believe that orthodontic 
treatment can be done in patients with periodontal problems, 
while 57.7% did not. Only a small proportion of dentists 
(17.9%) denied orthodontic treatment for the patients with 
missing molars. </p>

<p>Comparison of the total score of knowledge and attitude 
were also compared between male and female participants. 
This showed, score was more in case of male participants 
as compared female participants, but the difference was not 
significant statistically. This showed that male practitioners 
had more positive knowledge and attitude than female dental 
practitioners, toward principles and practice of orthodontic 
therapy. </p>

<p>Conclusion 
This particular comparative study added more focus on the 
facts of existing condition and scenario of the knowledge and 
attitude of the general dental practitioners and other practicing 
specialties of dentistry toward the principles and practice of 
the orthodontic treatment. Therefore, the study showed the 
need for increased clinically oriented education of practice 
and concepts of orthodontic treatment. For this purpose, the 
syllabus during undergraduation should include more emphasis 
on therapeutic concepts, and continuing dental education 
programs can be helpful for the other dental practitioners to 
upgrade their knowledge of orthodontic treatment. </p>



<p>Table 4: Comparison of the total score of knowledge and attitude, 
between general dental practitioner and non-orthodontic specialties. </p>

<p>Group 
n Scores of knowledge 
and attitude 
(mean±SD) </p>

<p>t value Significance </p>

<p>General dental 
practitioner 
46 
13.91±1.68 
6.9149 
P&lt;0.001** </p>

<p>Non-orthodontic 
specialties 
32 
16.72±1.87 </p>

<p>**Difference was statistically significant, SD: Standard deviation </p>

<p>Table 5: Comparison of the total score of the knowledge and attitude 
between male and female participants. </p>

<p>Group 
n 
Total score of 
knowledge and 
attitude (mean±SD) </p>

<p>t value Significance </p>

<p>Males 
48 
15.35±2.37 
1.4604 
P&gt;0.01* 
Females 
30 
14.60±1.96 </p>

<p>*Difference was not significant statistically, SD: Standard deviation </p>





<p>Appendix (Questionnaires) 
Appendix I 
Questions of knowledge about principles and practice of orthodontic treatment (Yes/No type questions): 
1. Can orthodontic treatment be started at any age? 
2. Can malocclusions be treated during mixed dentition stage? 
3. Do you consider that well-aligned teeth are important for overall facial appearance? 
4. Do you aware of functional therapy? 
5. Do you know that functional appliance gives a better result when advised during pre-pubertal growth spurt period? 
6. Do you consider skeletal malocclusions when patients report to you with a complaint of incompetent lips and proclined teeth? 
7. Are you aware that few teeth may have to be removed for aligning irregular teeth? 
8. Is orthodontic treatment always requires extraction? (N) 
9. Do habits like mouth breathing or thumb-sucking has an effect on the front teeth alignment? 
10. Do you believe that straightening the teeth makes better smile, helps in mastication, better oral hygiene, easier to speak, healthy 
lifestyle? 
11. Do you know that temporomandibular joint disorders can be cured by orthodontic therapy? 
12. Do you aware of the fact that mini screws can replace molars for anchorage? 
13. Should retainers be worn after fixed appliance therapy? </p>

<p>Appendix II 
Questions of Attitude about principles and practice of orthodontic treatment (Yes/No type questions): </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>