<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4350160" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Intravenous regional block, called the Bier's block, refers to an analgesic technique applied for soft tissue surgeries and 
closed bone manipulations of the limbs. There are a number of complications in traditional method of block, including pain in tourniquet 
site, immediate return of pain after tourniquet deflation, wound hemostasis and some others. </p>

<p>Objectives: The aim of this study was to assess the outcomes and complications of our new method of blockage. 
Patients and Methods: In this experimental study, twenty-five patients undergoing hand surgery were prospectively studied. Induced 
anesthesia was a modification of the Bier's block with two concurrent changes including insertion of the intravenous cannula at the 
antecubital region rather than distal and the proximal anesthetic direction by an elastic band wrapped tightly around the proximal 
forearm distal to the cannulation site. The pain relief was measured by the verbal descriptive scale at intervals after block, during the 
operation, after deflation of the tourniquet and one hour after the operation. </p>

<p>Results: This study showed the presence of analgesia at surgical and tourniquet sites during the operation in 96% of patients, as well as 
considerable pain relief at surgical site during one hour after deflation of the tourniquet. </p>

<p>Conclusions: The study indicated advantages of this modified Bier's block compared to the traditional one including ability to perform 
surgery on upper limb bones and considerable pain relief at surgical and tourniquet sites during the operation until one hour thereafter. </p>

<p>Keywords:Nerve block; Upper Extremity; Anesthesia </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015, Iranian Society of Regional Anesthesia and Pain Medicine (ISRAPM). This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Com-
mons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material 
just in noncommercial usages, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>Intravenous (IV) regional block was first reported by a 
German surgeon, August Bier, in 1906 (1), by which the re-
quired analgesic state was achieved allowing to perform 
the surgery (1-4). This method of anesthesia is easy to per-
form (1, 4, 5). In this method, after preparing patient and 
performing veni-puncture at the distal end of the limb, 
a double tourniquet is applied to the proximal area (1). 
An Esmarch bandage is twisted around the limb, from 
the tips of the fingers to the tourniquet site. Tourniquet 
is then inflated up 100-150 mmHg over the patient's sys-
tolic blood pressure and the local anesthetic is injected 
through the distal vein (1, 2, 6). Yet it consists of disadvan-
tages including pain at the tourniquet site, accidental 
deflation of the tourniquet, local anesthetic toxicity, and 
instant recurrence of pain at surgical site following tour-
niquet deflation, especially when the operation requires 
hemostasis prior to wound closure (4, 7). </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>Since 1970, studies considered the efficacy of changing </p>

<p>the cannulation site from the conventional method to 
forearm and antecubital. In a study conducted on 100 
patients undergoing surgery under the Bier block, 50 pa-
tients with the traditional technique involving distal IV 
cannulation were compared to 50 with antecubital can-
nulation and no significant difference was observed be-
tween the two methods with a success rate of 98%. Other 
studies (8, 9) reported 98% success rate for this anesthetic 
method of limb operation. As far as the site of IV cannula-
tion was the only change made in previous studies, (9-12), 
we added a distal venous block in the present study to 
evaluate the efficacy of this modified Bier's block by pain 
assessment during tourniquet placement and through-
out the procedure until one hour post-deflation. </p>

<p>3. Patients and Methods </p>

<p>In this study, twenty-five patients candidate for elective 
or emergent open bone fixation of the forearm, carpus 
and/or hand referred to Hazrat Rasul Hospital, Tehran, 
Iran, were recruited. The operation should be performed </p>

<p>Jafarian A et al. </p>

<p>Anesth Pain Med. 2015;5(1):e22007 
2 </p>

<p>in 90 minutes. Exclusion criteria were patients' refusal 
to undergo the experiment, history of allergy to local 
anesthetics, presence of severe heart disease, severe hy-
potension, seizure, drug addiction, psychiatric diseases, 
use of antidepressants or anxiolytics, multiple trauma 
or other organs' involvement and underlying disease in 
which tourniquet application is contraindicated (such 
as the Raymond's disease and sickle cell disease or trait). 
The study received ethics committee approval from Iran 
University of Medical Sciences. All participants were in-
formed about the type and method of anesthesia and 
pain measurement individually by the anesthesiologist 
and written informed consent was obtained from them. 
To overcome some of traditional method's disadvantages, 
two changes were made as: 1) The IV cannula was insert-
ed into an antecubital vein; 2) an elastic band was firmly 
wrapped around the proximal forearm distal to the can-
nulation site. Lidocaine 0.5% (at least 4 mg/kg totally in 50 
mL) (1, 3, 4) was carefully administered via the IV cannula 
in less than 90 seconds. The forearm was held perpen-
dicular to the elbow, above the local anesthetic injection 
site, for five minutes. Then it was fastened with the elastic 
band distal to the cannulation site to keep the anesthetic 
agent in the proximal arm and prevent its distal spread. 
Tourniquet pressure and other details were the same as 
the traditional method. If pain was present at the tourni-
quet site, the distal tourniquet would be first inflated and 
the proximal one deflated. At the end of operation, the 
tourniquet was totally deflated. The pain was measured 
and recorded based on the standard verbal descriptive 
scale of 0-5 scores, presented in Table 1 (13). Data including 
pain at surgical site before the operation, five minutes af-
ter the block, every five minutes during the operation, be-
fore and after tourniquet entire deflation and then every 
ten minutes until one hour after the tourniquet deflation 
were recorded. For each patient pain at the tourniquet site 
was measured at ten minutes intervals separately after in-
flating the proximal tourniquet, after inflating the distal 
tourniquet and after deflating the proximal one through-
out the operation. Anatomic site of upper extremity bone 
undergoing the operation was lower forearm and hand, 
distal radius or ulna, carpus, metacarpus and phalanges. 
The type of bone surgery consisted of drilling in associa-
tion with applying pins, plates and screws. The operation 
length was individually recorded for each patient. Prior 
to the operation, an 18-gauge intravenous cannula was 
inserted on the contra lateral limb for fluid administra-
tion. Shortly after the cannula insertion, 1 µg/kg fentanyl 
and 0.015 µg/kg midazolam were administered for all 
patients. The tourniquet was carefully deflated following 
bone fixation to obtain surgical site hemostasis. Consid-
ering the side effects of local anesthetic toxicity, patients 
were evaluated during the operation as well as the first 
hour of operation (1, 4, 9). All patients with mild pain (&lt; 
1 on the pain score) following tourniquet deflation re-
ceived an extra dose of fentanyl (1-1.5 µg/kg). The protocol 
was to induce general anesthesia if intolerable pain was </p>

<p>experienced or if the operation took longer than 90 min-
utes. Throughout the first 24 hours of the operation, the 
site of operation was checked for thrombophlebitis, Volk-
mann ischemic paralysis and cellulitis every four hours 
and every 12 hours during the next 48 hours. Statistical 
analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13 for windows</rs>. The 
quantitative data was expressed as mean ± standard de-
viation (SD), while the qualitative data as frequency. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>The present study was conducted on 25 patients, includ-
ing 18 men (70%) and 7 women (30%), aged 21 to 70 years 
(37.4 ± 8.2). In total, 52% of the operations were emergent 
and 48% elective. Fixed bones were radius (28%), ulna 
(20%), carpus (8%), metacarpus (12%), phalanges (12%), ra-
dius and metacarpus (8%), dual metacarpi (8%) and ulna 
plus metacarpus (4%). Types of surgeries included drill-
ing and applying one pin (12%), drilling and applying 
more than one pin (36%), drilling and applying screws 
and plates (36%) and drilling and applying a screw (16%). 
The mean duration of operation was 57.3 minutes (25-90 
minutes) with no surgical complications. Table 2 shows 
pain at the site of operation after entire deflation of the 
tourniquet, when hemostasis was achieved (at the first 
20 minutes, every five minutes) and the pain at the site of 
operation, when the operation was already finished and 
no further manipulation was performed (within the last 
30, 40 and 60 minutes). As shown in Table 2, during the 
operation after the block at the first five minutes, 24 pa-
tients (96%) had no pain, one (4%) had mild pain and no 
patient experienced discomforting, distressing, horrible 
and excruciating. Within the initial 10 minutes, 22 (88%) 
patients felt no pain and only two (8%) had mild tourni-
quet pain. At the 20th minute, the frequency of patients 
with no pain was decreased to 64%. At the 30th, 40th and 
60th minutes after the operation, 13 (52%), 10 (40%) and 
3 (12%) patients experienced no pain, respectively and at 
60th minute, 16% experienced horrible pain. No signs of 
systemic toxicity were observed. Two patients felt light-
headedness during the first 1-3 minutes. One patient com-
plained of mild tongue numbness for 90 seconds and 
another for 2.5 minutes. One patient had 15% decreased 
heart rate for 3.5 minutes and 8% decrease in his mean 
arterial pressure. Since the symptoms were transient, no 
intervention was required. </p>

<p>Table 1. Verbal Descriptive Scale (VDS) </p>

<p>Score 
Description </p>

<p>0 
no pain </p>

<p>1 
mild pain </p>

<p>2 
discomforting pain </p>

<p>3 
distressing pain </p>

<p>4 
horrible pain </p>

<p>5 
excruciating pain </p>

<p>Jafarian A et al. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Anesth Pain Med. 2015;5(1):e22007 </p>

<p>Table 2. Pain Score at the Operation Site During 60 Minutes After Complete Deflation of Tourniquet a </p>

<p>Interval 
No Pain 
Mild 
Discomforting 
Distressing 
Horrible 
Excruciating </p>

<p>5 Minute 
24 (96) 
1 (4) 
0 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>10 Minute 
22 (88) 
2 (8) 
1 (4) 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>15 Minute 
19 (76) 
2 (8) 
3 (12) 
1 (4) 
0 
0 </p>

<p>20 Minute 
16 (64) 
4 (16) 
2 (8) 
3 (12) 
0 
0 </p>

<p>30 Minute 
13 (52) 
6 (24) 
5 (2) 
1 (4) 
0 
0 </p>

<p>40 Minute 
10 (40) 
8 (32) 
5 (20) 
2 (8) 
0 
0 </p>

<p>60 Minute 
3 (12) 
4 (16) 
9 (36) 
5 (20) 
4 (16) 
0 </p>

<p>a Data are presented as No. (%). </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>Disadvantages of the traditional method of intravenous 
regional anesthesia include pain at the tourniquet site, 
accidental deflation of the tourniquet, local anesthetic 
toxicity and instant recurrence of pain at the surgical site 
following tourniquet deflation (4, 7). To overcome some 
of these problems we made two changes in this tech-
nique, as discussed before, and assessed patients' pain 
with this modified method and found that no patients 
had excruciating or horrible pain. As Harmatz stated, in 
most countries the dosage of lidocaine used was 200-300 
mg, which is compatible to our study, and defined the 
recommended dosage of lidocaine in adults as 7 mg/kg 
and the toxicity rate as 4 mcg/mL (11). Mohr used 0.5% so-
lution of lidocaine in a dosage of 1.5-3 mg/kg according 
to physician's preference (3). He compared pain at the 
tourniquet site between traditional and modified meth-
ods of blockage. The comparison showed that pain relief 
at tourniquet site in the modified method was overall 
5% less than traditional (3). In the studies of evaluating 
tourniquet pain, pain was assessed in the two above-
mentioned separate steps. Inflation of distal tourniquet 
as well as deflation of the proximal one was reported to 
lessen pain at the site of tourniquet. In the present study, 
pain at the tourniquet site was evaluated independently 
in two steps. The reason for significant decrease in tour-
niquet pain in the second step may be attributed to in-
travenous cannula insertion site in the antecubital area 
as well as placing an obstacle behind the insertion area 
to force more diffusion of the anesthetic agent in veins 
of the elbow and arm. In some articles, efficacy of chang-
ing the IV cannula insertion site was studied to improve 
analgesia during the operation (2, 4, 8-12). Blyth et al. 
randomized 100 patients into two groups, comparing 
injection into the dorsum of the hand and the antecu-
bital fossa and reported no difference in anesthesia (14). 
No study has already assessed simultaneous use of the 
two measures, as far as we are concerned. Intravenous 
cannula insertion in the elbow and placing an obstacle 
distal to the venous line to let the local anesthetic agent 
diffuse in the elbow and lower arm immediately below 
the tourniquet. The overall success of the method men-</p>

<p>tioned in this study in relieving pain during the opera-
tion was 96%, while published studies, which included 
only inserting an intravenous cannula in antecubital or 
forearm areas, reported 98-100% success rates (8, 9, 12). In 
previous studies, analgesia was induced to perform an 
operation on soft tissues; however, in the present study 
all patients underwent bone surgery, in which the pain is 
more severe, due to vast and deep incision as well as pain-
ful manipulations and stimuli. Analgesia at the surgical 
site was evaluated independently during the operation; 
while two changes were applied in the block. In a study 
by Brown et al. performed on 1816 patients, insufficient 
analgesia was reported in 0.28% of patients (4). In anoth-
er study, inserting an IV cannula was assessed by tradi-
tional method in the forearm region in 30 patients with 
dislocated radius bone and no significant difference was 
reported regarding pain and side effects (5). In the last 
two studies, only the place of intravenous cannula inser-
tion to administer local anesthetic was changed. Yet the 
two simultaneous changes were made to induce anesthe-
sia to perform an open surgery on the bone in our study. 
In reliable references immediate recurrence of pain has 
been reported in most patients around 3-5 minutes after 
entire deflation of the tourniquet (1, 14, 15). In this study, 
tourniquet was completely released to allow wound he-
mostasis, although all the operations performed on bone 
were open. Subsequently patients felt generally less or no 
pain (Table 2). 
As mentioned after 20 minutes, the operation site had 
no external painful stimulation, and there was a pain at 
the site of operation experienced by all patients. Com-
pared to the traditional method of the Bier's block, in 
which the pain was usually severe 3-5 minutes after 
complete deflation of the tourniquet, (1, 4, 10, 16). It was 
significantly less in our patients under study. In other 
studies, there was no report of precise measuring pain 
at the site of operation following tourniquet release 
(3-5, 7, 8, 14, 15). The increasing score of pain observed 
in our patients may be partly due to natural course of 
pain, which increases over time. Another study showed 
that peripheral nerves endings of the limbs are fed with </p>

<p>Jafarian A et al. </p>

<p>Anesth Pain Med. 2015;5(1):e22007 
4 </p>

<p>tiny vessels, and injecting a local anesthetic agent in the 
venous system makes the local anesthetic diffuse to the 
nerve endings and brings about analgesia afterwards. 
This hypothesis is under complementary study by the 
researchers (12, 14, 15); therefore, using scientific and di-
agnostic methods in an independent project is notewor-
thy. The high duration of analgesic effect maintenance 
in this study may be due to penetration of analgesic 
agents to major nerve in the elbow and arm. According 
to our results, this method of block with two abovemen-
tioned changes is recommended for open surgeries on 
bones, in addition to surgeries on soft tissues of the 
limbs and/or bone closed manipulations. Furthermore, 
complementary studies are suggested to demonstrate 
the penetration of anesthetics through pooling of the 
veins located in elbow and arm, with two applied chang-
es in this method. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank Dr. Tamannaie and Ms. 
Pishgahroudsari for their great help in drafting and re-
viewing this manuscript. </p>

<p>Authors' Contributions </p>

<p>Study concept and design: Dr. Jafarian, Shariatzadeh, 
Javaheri, Hassani and Jesmi; acquisition of data: Dr. Ra-
mezani; analysis and interpretation of data: Dr. Jafarian, 
Shariatzadeh, Javaheri, Hassani and Jesmi; drafting of 
the manuscript: Dr. Ramezani, Jafarian, Shariatzadeh, Ja-
vaheri, Hassani and Jesmi; critical revision of the manu-
script for important intellectual content: Dr. Jafarian, 
Hassani and Jesmi; statistical analysis: Dr. Ramezani and 
Jafarian; administrative, technical, and material support: 
Dr. Jafarian, Shariatzadeh, Javaheri and Hassani; study su-
pervision: Dr. Jafarian and Hassani. </p>



</text></tei>