<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4475901" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>a b s t r a c t </p>

<p>Sarcopenia corresponds to the degenerative loss of skeletal muscle mass, quality, and strength associated 
with ageing and leads to a progressive impairment of mobility and quality of life. However, the cellular 
and molecular mechanisms involved in this process are not completely understood. A hallmark of cel-
lular and tissular ageing is the accumulation of oxidatively modified (carbonylated) proteins, leading to a 
decreased quality of the cellular proteome that could directly impact on normal cellular functions. Al-
though increased oxidative stress has been reported during skeletal muscle ageing, the oxidized protein 
targets, also referred as to the 'oxi-proteome' or 'carbonylome', have not been characterized yet. To better 
understand the mechanisms by which these damaged proteins build up and potentially affect muscle 
function, proteins targeted by these modifications have been identified in human rectus abdominis 
muscle obtained from young and old healthy donors using a bi-dimensional gel electrophoresis-based 
proteomic approach coupled with immunodetection of carbonylated proteins. Among evidenced protein 
spots, 17 were found as increased carbonylated in biopsies from old donors comparing to young coun-
terparts. These proteins are involved in key cellular functions such as cellular morphology and transport, 
muscle contraction and energy metabolism. Importantly, impairment of these pathways has been de-
scribed in skeletal muscle during ageing. Functional decline of these proteins due to irreversible oxi-
dation may therefore impact directly on the above-mentioned pathways, hence contributing to the 
generation of the sarcopenic phenotype. 
journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/redox </p>

<p>Redox Biology </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.redox.2015.05.006 
2213-2317/&amp; 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Abbreviations: 1D, one-dimensional; 2D, bi-dimensional; ATP, adenosine tripho-
sphate; CK, creatine kinase; DNP, 2-4-dinitrophenylhydrazone; DNPH, 2,4-dini-
trophenylhydrazine; GAPDH, glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase; GPD1, 
Glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase [NAD þ ], cytoplasmic; HSP70, Heat shock 
70 kDa protein; IEF, Isoelectric focusing; MM-CK, muscle-type creatine kinase; MS, 
mass spectrometry; MyBPC, myosin-binding protein C; PCr-CK, phosphocreatine-
creatine kinase; RA, rectus abdominis; RMI, relative modification index; ROS, re-
active oxygen species; ZASP, LIM domain-binding protein 3 
n Corresponding author at: Sorbonne Universités, UPMC Univ Paris 06, UMR </p>

<p>8256, Biological adaptation and ageing-IBPS, F-75005 Paris, France. 
E-mail address: bertrand.friguet@upmc.fr (B. Friguet). </p>

<p>Redox Biology 5 (2015) 267-274 </p>

<p>through macromolecular damage, the molecular mechanisms re-
main elusive. Protein post-translational modifications induced by 
ROS are important features of oxidative stress [11]. Among them, 
protein carbonyl content is by far the most commonly used marker 
of protein oxidation [12,13]. In fact, protein carbonylation occurs 
when proteins directly react with ROS, leading to the formation 
carbonyl groups (aldehydes and ketones) for instance on such 
amino acids side chains as arginine, lysine, threonine and proline. 
Introduction of carbonyl groups on proteins can also occur through 
the reaction of aldehydic products of lipid peroxidation and of 
dicarbonyl compounds upon glycation and glycoxidation. Since it 
often leads to a loss of protein function and an increased ther-
mosensitivity or hydrophobicity of the targeted protein [14,15], 
protein carbonylation has been considered as an indicator of 
protein damage. 
In human skeletal muscle, preliminary studies on vastus later-
alis and external intercostal muscles have shown increased accu-
mulation of protein carbonyls during ageing [16-19]. However, in 
most cases, the protein targets of these oxidative damages and 
their functional consequences have not been identified. Indeed, 
this is an essential step to get a complete view of protein oxidative 
modifications and to understand the mechanisms by which these 
oxidized proteins potentially contribute to muscle weakness and 
dysfunction during ageing. 
Therefore, proteomic studies, including the analysis of protein 
abundance as well as protein carbonylation are expected to pro-
vide valuable information to unravel the key molecular pathways 
implicated. In fact, proteomics and in particular bi-dimensional 
(2D) gels represent appropriate tools for the detection and iden-
tification of specific carbonylated proteins in a complex mixture 
[2,13,20]. The identification of such oxidatively modified proteins 
(i.e. the oxi-proteome components), can give some insights into 
the mechanisms by which these damaged proteins accumulate 
and potentially affect cellular and/or tissular function during 
ageing or in disease conditions [21]. In this paper, the occurrence 
and characterization of carbonylated proteins was studied in hu-
man rectus abdominis muscle obtained from young and old healthy 
donors. Although no significant differences in global protein car-
bonylation was observed at the proteome level, we have used 2D 
gel electrophoresis based proteomic approaches to improve the 
resolution of individual proteins for the quantitative analysis of 
their carbonylation status and further identification of these major 
skeletal muscle proteins that are targeted by oxidative damage 
during human rectus abdominis skeletal muscle ageing. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Human biopsies </p>

<p>Human rectus abdominis muscle biopsies were obtained during 
surgery. Each biopsy used has the written consent of the volunteer 
donor. A total of 22 human muscle biopsies were used: 11 from 
healthy men individuals between 0 to 12 years old (named young 
samples) and 11 from healthy men individuals between 52 and 
76 years old (named old samples) (Table 1). All muscle biopsies 
had an initial wet weight between 15 and 24 mg (Table 1). The 
study was approved by the Ethical Committee at the Uppsala 
University Hospital. </p>

<p>Protein extraction for proteomics analyses </p>

<p>Proteins extracts from skeletal muscle biopsies were obtained 
by physical disruption of the sample biopsies using a ULTRA-
TURRAX 
s T25 (IKA </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>) at 4°C in a lysis buffer containing 10 mM 
Tris-HCl (pH 7.4), 8 M urea, 2 M thiourea, 4% CHAPS and 20 mM </p>

<p>DTT. After incubation on ice for 20 min, soluble proteins were 
recovered after clarification by centrifugation for 40 min at 
21,000 g. Proteins were further precipitated using the 2D clean-up 
kit (GE Healthcare) and the resulting pellet was re-suspended into 
the same lysis buffer. Protein concentrations were determined by 
the Bradford Method [22] using the Bio-Rad Protein Kit Assay (Bio-
Rad). </p>

<p>Protein carbonyl immunodetection after derivatization with DNPH </p>

<p>Carbonylated proteins were derivatized with 2,4-dini-
trophenylhydrazine (DNPH) to form 2-4-dinitrophenylhydrazone 
(DNP) proteins adducts [23]. For total carbonyl quantification, 
equal quantities of proteins were loaded and separated by SDS-
PAGE 12% (v/v). Chemicals for SDS-PAGE were purchased from Bio-
Rad. All other chemicals were of analytical grade and obtained 
from Sigma-Aldrich. For the detection of carbonylated proteins, 
gels were electrotransferred onto Hybond-C nitrocellulose mem-
branes (GE Healthcare) and incubated with anti-DNP antibodies 
(1:5000, Sigma-Aldrich). Carbonylated proteins were revealed by a 
fluorescent anti-rabbit IgG 800CW (1:15,000) polyclonal antibody 
(LI-COR). Densitometry analyses were performed using NIH <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> 
software and the data are expressed as % volume in pixels. 
For 2D gel electrophoresis, derivatization of proteins carbonyls 
was achieved on IPG strips after isoelectric focusing (IEF), with a 
10 mM DNPH, 2 M HCl solution at room temperature (RT) as de-
scribed previously [24]. 500 mg of protein were diluted on a re-
hydratation buffer (7 M urea, 2 M thiourea, 1% Amberlite, 4% 
CHAPS, 1.2% Destreak (GE Healthcare), 0.5% Pharmalyte pH 3-10 
(GE Healthcare)) and loaded into 13 cm IPG strips pH 3-10 NL (GE 
Healthcare). Gel rehydration of the IPG strips was done overnight 
at RT in an Immobiline DryStrip rewelling tray. IEF was performed 
using an Ettan™ IPGphor™ 3 Isoelectric Focusing System (GE 
Healthcare) at 20°C using the following electrical profile: step, 
150 V for 11 h; grad, 1000 V for 3 h; grad, 8000 V for 2 h; step, 
8000 V for 1 h. Neutralization step after derivatization with DNPH 
was performed with 2 M Trizma-Base containing 30% of glycerol 
(GE Healthcare). Before SDS-PAGE, all IPG strips were equilibrated 
with a 6 M urea, 10% SDS and 30% Glycerol (GE Healthcare), 0.5 M 
Tris-HCl (pH 8.8) solution for 2 steps of 15 min: the first one with </p>

<p>Table 1 
Characteristics of the samples biopsies. </p>

<p>Sample no Donor age 
(years) </p>

<p>Wet weight (mg) Protein recovery ratio (w/w in %) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1 
0 
24.00 
7.0 
2 
1 
20.80 
4.3 
3 
5 
20.00 
7.6 
4 
9 
17.00 
9.3 
5 
6.5 
15.00 
7.1 
6 
10.75 
21.90 
7.6 
7 
12 
22.00 
9.1 
8 
7.1 
22.00 
9.7 
9 
76 
20.30 
9.5 
10 
70 
18.00 
8.3 
11 
74 
19.10 
7.8 
12 
66 
19.60 
8.0 
13 
74 
19.20 
8.4 
14 
65 
18.66 
5.2 
15 
65 
18.78 
6.6 
16 
71 
24.00 
10.8 
17 
12 
20.00 
15.6 
18 
3 
20.50 
3.6 
19 
9 
20.38 
11.0 
20 
56 
20.47 
7.4 
21 
61 
20.53 
17.1 
22 
52 
20.13 
27.2 </p>

<p>a Protein recovery ratio corresponds to the protein amount in mass / biopsy </p>

<p>mass. </p>

<p>S. Lourenço dos Santos et al. / Redox Biology 5 (2015) 267-274 </p>

<p>
equilibration solution containing 1% DTT and the second with 
equilibration solution containing 3% iodoacetamide. SDS-PAGE 
was carried out using the Protean II system (Bio-Rad). For each 
sample, two 12% (v/v) polyacrylamide gels were performed in 
parallel: one for total protein stains with Coomassie Brilliant Blue 
G-250 (Bio-Rad) for further mass spectrometry analysis; and the 
other with derivatized protein residues for electrotransfer onto 
nitrocellulose membranes, where total amount of proteins were 
stained by a Fast Green solution (Sigma-Aldrich) prior to anti-
bodies incubation for loading control. Membranes were then 
blocked with Odyssey blocking buffer (LI-COR) overnight at 4°C. 
Primary anti-DNP antibodies (1:5000, Sigma-Aldrich) were in-
cubated for 1 h at RT. Revelation was done by a fluorescent anti-
rabbit IgG 800CW (1:15,000) polyclonal antibody (LI-COR). 
Washing steps were done with a PBS/0.1% Tween solution. Car-
bonylated proteins were revealed by the Odyssey Infrared Imaging 
System (LI-COR). </p>

<p>Proteomics data acquisition and analysis </p>

<p>Spot detection and quantification were carried out using the 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">image Master 2D Platinum 7 software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">GE Healthcare</rs>). For com-
parison, we used the data expressed as spot % volume (%vol) in 
pixels, which corresponds to a normalized value of the spot vo-
lume by considering the total volume of all the spots present in the 
membrane [25]. To take into account the total amount of loaded 
protein in each IPG strip, we defined a %vol per carbonylated spot 
(N%vol) by normalizing the %vol of each anti-DNP incubated 
membrane with its corresponding %vol on the Fast Green-sta-
tioned membrane. The relative modification index ratio (RMI ratio) 
was obtained by dividing the N%vol of the old group of samples by 
the N%vol of the young one. </p>

<p>In-gel digestion and mass spectrometry </p>

<p>Spots of interest were manually excised from Coomassie Blue 
stained 12% (v/v) polyacrylamide gels and were automatically in-</p>

<p>Fig. 1. Analysis of total carbonylated proteins of human rectus abdominis muscle biopsies. (A) Carbonylated protein profiles from young and old human biopsies after 1D gel 
electrophoresis. Protein carbonyl were detected by Western-blotting against protein-DNP derivatives and monitored by fluorescent secondary antibody hybridation. (B) Total 
protein profiles stained with colloidal Coomassie brilliant blue G after 1D gel electrophoresis. (C) Densitometric analysis of carbonylated protein western-blots. Semi-
quantitative assessment of modified proteins was done using total protein staining for normalization. Relative values are expressed as mean7 S.D. (n¼ 11) and no significant 
difference was found between the young and old groups. </p>

<p>S. Lourenço dos Santos et al. / Redox Biology 5 (2015) 267-274 </p>

<p>
gel digested by trypsin [26] using a robot Freedom EVO 100 di-
gester/spotter robot (Tecan). Resulted peptides were then desalted 
for mass spectrometry (MS/MS) analysis. Results obtained were 
subjected to a search on the SwissProt database using the <rs type="software">MASCOT</rs> 
software (Matrix Science Ltd., London, UK). The software compares 
the <rs type="software">MASCOT</rs> peptide sequences derived from spectra with those in 
libraries for protein identification. Search parameters were as 
follows: database, SwissProt; taxonomy, all entries or mammalian; 
enzyme, trypsin; allow up to one missed cleavage; fixed mod-
ifications, none; variable modifications, methionine oxidation; 
peptide mass tolerance, 70 ppm; and fragment mass tolerance, 
500 ppm. </p>

<p>Results and discussion </p>

<p>Initial screening looking at changes at the global proteome le-
vel of carbonylated proteins was performed after derivatization of 
protein carbonyls with DNPH followed by immunodetection of 
DNP protein adducts after SDS-PAGE (Fig. 1A). Densitometry ana-
lysis was performed and normalized by total protein content for 
each sample (Fig. 1B and C). No significant differences at the global 
level in protein carbonyl content was detected between groups, in 
agreement with what was previously reported by Marzani et al. 
who did not find a statistical difference on protein carbonyl con-
tent during ageing in both rectus abdominis and vastus lateralis 
human muscles [18]. More recently, Fanò et al., using skeletal 
muscle biopsy samples obtained from vastus lateralis, found that 
protein carbonyls, showed a significant increase during ageing. 
However, this difference was not significant after splitting by 
gender [27]. Importantly, immunodetection of carbonylated pro-
teins after one-dimensional (1D) electrophoresis separation has </p>

<p>serious limitations for the resolution of single protein bands and 
can provide only restricted information. 
To further analyze the occurrence of protein carbonylation at 
the single protein level, 2D gel electrophoresis separation of pro-
tein extracts was performed prior to immunodetection of carbo-
nylated proteins. 2D gels are very appropriate to investigate pro-
tein isoforms since many post-translational modifications (such as 
carbonylation of arginine or lysine residues) often leads to changes 
in the isoelectric point of proteins, and thus shift the position of 
the protein in 2D gels. After electrotransfer onto nitrocellulose 
membranes total protein profiles were obtained by fast-green 
staining (Fig. 2). All the analyzed samples displayed a similar 
protein migration pattern, suggesting no drastic shifts in the 
protein profiles at the expression level (Fig. 2, right panels) be-
tween the two experimental groups. Immunodetection of carbo-
nylated proteins was performed after their derivatization by DNPH 
as described in Material and methods. Interestingly, the pattern of 
the modified proteins was not superimposable with the pattern 
obtained for the total protein staining, indicating that certain 
proteins represent preferential targets for these deleterious oxi-
dative modifications. Several proteins of high molecular weight 
were found preferentially carbonylated (Fig. 2, left panel) while 
certain proteins with an isoelectric point higher than 5, also ap-
peared to be preferentially carbonylated. 
A relative modification index (RMI) per spot was calculated in 
order to evidence differentially carbonylated proteins between the 
two experimental groups taking into account their protein ex-
pression levels. Seventeen protein spots exhibited an RMI ratio 
consistently higher than 1.3 (increasingly carbonylated) in all 
biopsies from the aged group as compared with the young one. On 
the other hand, fourteen protein spots showed decreased carbo-
nylation in the old group (RMI o0.7). Protein spots evidenced as </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Oxi-proteome analysis of young and old human skeletal muscle samples. Protein extracts from young (n ¼3) and old (n¼ 3) human skeletal muscle biopsies were 
separated by 2D gel electrophoresis. After the second dimension, gels were electrotransferred onto nitrocellulose membranes for subsequent immune detection of DPNH-
derivatized carbonylated proteins (left panels). Densitometry analysis was done by image Master 2D software (GE Healthcare) using total protein staining (right panels) as 
loading control. </p>

<p>S. Lourenço dos Santos et al. / Redox Biology 5 (2015) 267-274 </p>

<p>
increasingly carbonylated were excised from Coomassie Blue 
stained 2D gels (Fig. 3) and analyzed by MS/MS for protein iden-
tification. Protein spots that were identified in the aged group are 
listed in Table 2. Among the identified proteins, 8 are muscle 
specific, 4 are ubiquitous in different tissues and organ systems, 
and 2 proteins belong from plasma (Table 2). 
The identified skeletal muscle proteins were then analyzed and 
grouped by metabolic pathways and cellular functions. Major 
biological functions include muscle contraction, energy transduc-
tion and energy metabolism (Fig. 4). Among proteins involved in 
muscle contraction, we have found that myosin 7, troponin T, 
myosin-binding protein C (MyBPC), and LIM domain-binding 
protein 3 (ZASP) are increasingly carbonylated in aged muscle. 
Interestingly, the decreased speed of contraction observed in old 
age at both the muscle and motor protein levels is a hallmark of 
skeletal muscle ageing [28-31]. Myosin is a highly conserved 
protein that converts chemical energy into mechanical force and a 
key protein for muscle contraction. Previous studies have shown 
increased glycation of myosin in both fiber types of aged rats [32]. 
In addition, the carbonylated residues have been identified [33]. 
Interactions of myosin with cytoskeletal proteins such as titin, 
myomesin/M protein and MyBPC play an important role in thick 
filaments physiology. MyBPC contributes to the assembly and 
stabilization of thick filaments and modulates the formation of 
actomyosin cross-bridges, via direct interactions with both thick 
myosin and thin actin filaments [34,35]. The importance of MyBPC 
to muscle contraction is further emphasized by the discovery that 
mutations in genes encoding MyBPC cause myopathies in both 
skeletal [36,37] and cardiac muscles [38-40]. Increased oxidation 
of MyBPC, together with the previously reported age-dependent 
decrease of myosin isoforms and regulatory proteins like myosin 
binding proteins C and H [41-44], may contribute to the destabi-
lization of muscle fibers. In addition, perturbations in the thin 
sarcomere fillaments of muscle fibers have also been associated 
with differently expression of actin and its regulatory proteins 
such as troponin and tropomyosin [42,43,45,46]. Here we found </p>

<p>increased carbonylation levels of troponin T in the elderly. Tro-
ponin inhibits the actomyosin Mg 
2 þ -ATPase and the Ca 
2 þ release </p>

<p>from the sarcoplasmic reticulum inducing a change in the tropo-
nin-tropomyosin conformation that exposes myosin binding sites 
on the actin filament and activates the myosin ATPase, thereby 
allowing muscle contraction [47,48]. Since muscle contraction 
depends on myofibrillar thin filament interactions [49], the oxi-
dative damage to these proteins may well compromise this in-
teraction and hence muscle contraction. 
The motor functions of striated muscle crucially depend on the 
highly ordered arrays of thick myosin and thin actin filaments in 
sarcomeres. Although its detailed role has not been elucidated yet, 
the LIM domain-binding protein 3 (ZASP), found as increasingly 
carbonylated in aged rectus abdominis muscle, functions as an 
adapter to couple protein kinase C-mediated signaling to the cy-
toskeleton and to maintain Z-disc stability as well as cytoskeletal 
ultrastructure during contraction. Accumulation of this protein in 
its oxidized form may lead to protein aggregates formation and 
myofibril disintegration that may result in muscle weakness. 
Muscle contraction depends also in high-energy fluxes where 
creatine kinase plays a central role. During muscle contraction, 
myosin hydrolyzes ATP into ADP upon filament sliding. The re-
newal of ATP is achieved mainly by the phosphocreatine-creatine 
kinase (PCr-CK) system. Among the creatine kinase (CK) iso-
enzymes, the muscle-type CK (MM-CK) specifically binds to the 
myofibril M-line and is associated with the action-activated 
myosin ATPase as an intramyofibrillar ATP regenerator [50-52]. 
Since this MM-CK was found irreversibly oxidized in old rectus 
abdominis muscle, this could alter muscle metabolism and com-
promise muscle contraction in the elderly. Besides the PCr-CK 
system, the glycolytic network and its closer interaction between 
mitochondria and organelles also provide energy within muscle 
cells [53]. In this study, 3 glycolytic enzymes appear as highly 
carbonylated in old slow oxidative skeletal rectus abdominis mus-
cle: the fructose-bisphosphate aldolase A, the glycerol-3-phos-
phate dehydrogenase (GPD1) and the glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate 
dehydrogenase (GAPDH) (Table 2). Interestingly, several of these 
enzymes involved in anaerobic metabolism have been found de-
creased with age in murine and human skeletal muscle [54,55]. 
Although slow skeletal muscles uses mainly oxidative mi-
tochondrial processes to generate the levels of ATP needed to 
maintain contractile activity for long time without showing fatigue 
[53], they also rely in glycolysis for their energy production [56]. 
For this reason, muscle metabolism and contraction in aged ske-
letal muscle would be affected by irreversible carbonylation on 
glycolytic proteins, as previously reported in certain diseases when 
these glycolytic enzymes are not functional [57-62]. Defects in the 
muscle form of glycogen phosphorylase, another protein found 
increased carbonylated in old rectus abdominis muscle, are in-
volved in type 5 glycogen storage disease, also known as McArdle 
disease, a myopathy also characterized by exercise intolerance, 
such as easy fatigability, muscle cramps and contractures as well 
as muscle weakness [63,64]. Intramuscular glycogen acts as a 
readily available source of glucose-6-phosphate for glycolysis 
within skeletal muscle and glycogen phosphorylase catalyses the 
rate-limiting step in glycogenolysis [65]. Therefore, a deficiency in 
glycogen phosphorylase may result in the inability to mobilize 
muscle glycogen during anaerobic metabolism [66]. 
Although it is well recognized that ageing causes changes in the 
proteome, the nature and targets of these changes, their con-
sequences on skeletal muscle function and how they may con-
tribute to sarcopenia have not yet been completely elucidated. Our 
results suggest that oxidative stress during skeletal muscle ageing 
targets the contractile machinery, but also structural and reg-
ulatory proteins. In addition, the main mechanism of energy pro-
duction, the phosphocreatine kinase system was affected by </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Coomassie blue staining of one representative 2D gel. The numbers and 
positions of the 17 selected spots identified by MS/MS correspond to those found as 
consistently increased on the old group (RMI 41.3). </p>

<p>S. Lourenço dos Santos et al. / Redox Biology 5 (2015) 267-274 </p>

<p>
carbonylation in the elderly while other energetic metabolic 
pathways such as glycolysis appear to be also affected. Finally, the 
heat shock 70 kDa protein (HSP70), a key player in protein quality 
control with different identified roles in skeletal muscle [67], such 
as protection against oxidative stress, was also found highly car-
bonylated in old skeletal muscle. Up-regulation of heat shock 
proteins is a well know feature of muscle ageing [46,68,69]. Fur-
ther studies should address the functional status of the identified 
carbonylated proteins and related cellular pathways associated </p>

<p>with muscle dysfunction in order to reveal their role in the de-
velopment of the ageing phenotype. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors wish to acknowledge the FP7 EU-funded MyoAge 
Project (No. 223576), and COST Action CM1001, coordinated by Dr. 
Gillian Butler-Browne and Dr. Tilman Grune, respectively, as well </p>

<p>Table 2 
Localization of carbonylated proteins identified from old skeletal muscle biopsies. </p>

<p>Protein name and localization 
Swiss-Prot ac-
cession no </p>

<p>Protein 
spot no </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mascot 
score </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Sequence cov-
erage (%) </p>

<p>No. of sequenced 
peptides </p>

<p>Theoretical protein 
mass (kDa) </p>

<p>Theoretical 
PI </p>

<p>RMI 
ratio </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Ubiquitous proteins: 
Collagen alpha-1(VI) chain 
CO6A1_HUMAN 1 
205 
7 
5 
108 
5.3 
4.34 
Heat shock cognate 71 kDa protein 
HSP7C_HUMAN 5 
256 
15 
5 
71 
5.4 
1.63 
Glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase 
[NAD 
þ ], cytoplasmic (GPD1) </p>

<p>GPDA_HUMAN 
13 
214 
22 
4 
38 
5.8 
1.52 </p>

<p>Glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehy-
drogenase (GAPDH) </p>

<p>G3P_HUMAN 
14 
243 
12 
3 
36 
8.6 
1.67 </p>

<p>Glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehy-
drogenase (GAPDH) </p>

<p>G3P_HUMAN 
15 
424 
25 
5 
36 
8.6 
1.68 </p>

<p>Voltage-dependent anion-selective chan-
nel protein 1 </p>

<p>VDAC1_HUMAN 16 
685 
39 
8 
31 
8.6 
1.88 </p>

<p>Muscle specific proteins: 
Myosin-binding protein C, slow-type 
(MyBPC) </p>

<p>MYPC1_HUMAN 2 
119 
3 
3 
128 
5.8 
1.54 </p>

<p>Glycogen phosphorylase, muscle form 
PYGM_HUMAN 3 
882 
22 
13 
97 
6.6 
1.67 
Myosin-7 
MYH7_HUMAN 7 
63 
-
1 
223 
5.6 
3.12 
Creatine kinase M-type 
KCRM_HUMAN 8 
206 
9 
3 
43 
6.8 
1.44 
Creatine kinase M-type 
KCRM_HUMAN 9 
416 
20 
6 
43 
6.8 
1.54 
Fructose-bisphosphate aldolase A 
ALDOA_HUMAN 10 
611 
31 
7 
39 
8.3 
1.65 
Troponin T, slow skeletal muscle 
TNNT1_HUMAN 11 
512 
22 
6 
33 
5.9 
1.87 
Troponin T, slow skeletal muscle 
TNNT1_HUMAN 12 
244 
22 
5 
33 
5.9 
1.42 
LIM domain-binding protein 3 (ZASP) 
LDB3_HUMAN 
17 
206 
8 
4 
77 
8.5 
1.70 </p>

<p>Plasma proteins: 
Serotransferrin 
TRFE_HUMAN 
4 
399 
17 
10 
77 
6.8 
1.31 
Serum albumin 
ALBU_HUMAN 
6 
986 
29 
13 
69 
5.9 
1.33 </p>

<p>Spots of interest were identified by MALDI-TO-FTOF-MS as described under Material and methods. For each spot, different parameters clarifying protein identification by MS 
are indicated. 
a Protein spot number refers to the numbered spots in Fig. 3. 
b Mascot protein scores greater than 56 are significant (Po 0.05). 
c RMI ratio represents the Relative Modification Index ratio. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Functional grouping of muscle proteins increasingly oxidized with age. Increasingly oxidized muscle-specific proteins identified in aged rectus abdominis biopsies 
were grouped in three functional categories: muscle contraction, energy metabolism and energy transduction. </p>

<p>S. Lourenço dos Santos et al. / Redox Biology 5 (2015) 267-274 </p>

<p>
as the AFM-Téléthon for their support. In addition, they are very 
grateful to M. Cédric Broussard at the Plate-forme Protéomique 
Université Paris-Descartes 3P5 for performing the mass spectro-
metry analyses. </p>



<p>S. Lourenço dos Santos et al. / Redox Biology 5 (2015) 267-274 </p>



<p>
S. Lourenço dos Santos et al. / Redox Biology 5 (2015) 267-274 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>