<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4272497" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Introduction: In endeavor to suppress the cervical carcinoma there are several possible approaches including measures of primary and 
secondary prevention. So far effects of these measures on the number of cases and mortality rate of cervical carcinoma were modest. Only 
exception is organized testing based on cytological exam of the cervical smear -Pap test, which has proven to be highly effective in reduc-
ing the number of cases and mortality of cervical carcinoma in countries with this program. Goal of this research is analysis of correlation 
between abnormal cytological test results and pathohistological diagnosis of all patients in the analyzed period. Material and methods: 
Research is descriptive, analytical, comparative, and partly epidemiological. Results of cytological and pathohistological diagnostic in the 
period between January 1, 2009 and December 31, 2011 were used for analysis. All analyzed patients had colposcopy exam and Pap test, 
and patients with abnormal results of this test underwent cervical biopsy for pathohistological diagnostics. Results: We came to follow-
ing results and conclusions: total number of L-SIL and H-SIL (PAPA III) results was 395 (6.20%) in comparison to total sample of 5894 
(92.44%) patients. There is a statistically significant difference in relation to PHD result of cervical biopsy after L-SIL and H-SIL (PAPA II 
and IV), and highest statistical margin is in relation of CIN II changes to cytological findings, issued at Clinic of Obstetrics and Gynecol-
ogy and other health institutions. We come to conclusion that the highest percentage of patients with L-SIL and H-SIL findings is in age 
group between 0-29 years old. Statistical analysis has shown a positive trend in number of younger patients with L-SIL and H-SIL (PAPA 
III and IV), with average age of patients in 2011 being 31.12±9.12 years old. 
Cytological methods are applied starting from the mid-
19 
th century, when the researchers found abnormal cells 
in body fluids such as urine, sputum, exudates and gastric 
fluid. 
Papanicolaou (1928) in New York announced the era of 
modern diagnostic cytology, when he published an arti-
cle titled "A new diagnosis of cancer". Despite skepticism 
at the beginning of cytopathological era, the use of this 
method that is popularly known as "Pap" test is accepted 
as the most appropriate screening test for early detection 
of cancer and precancerous states of uterine cancer (1). 
Exfoliative cytology analyzes spontaneously exfoliat-
ed cells from the skin, mucous and serous membranes. 
Cytodiagnostics of the vaginal-cervical-endocervical 
(VCE) smear by volume is the largest in exfoliative cytol-
ogy, since it covers both the healthy and sick women. The 
smears include epithelial and non epithelial cells (2,3). 
In the universal effort for combating cervical cancer are 
available several possible approaches, including measures 
of primary and secondary prevention. So far, most of the 
effects of these measures on the incidence and mortality 
of cervical cancer were modest. The only exception seems </p>

<p>to represents organized screening based on the use of 
cytological examinations of the cervix (Pap test), which 
proved to be highly effective in reducing the incidence 
and mortality of cervical cancer in countries where it is 
implemented. Reduction of mortality caused by cervical 
cancer in the United States and other developed countries 
is significant, and this is due to the successful early di-
agnosis. Squamous intraepithelial lesions are detected in 
adolescents, young adults and adults. The peak incidence 
is at the age of about 30 years. Similarly, invasive carcino-
ma occurs earlier, in the third decade of life with a peak 
frequency at about 40 years, or 10-15 years later (4). 
Cytodiagnostics of conventional cervicovaginal smears 
or "Pap test" for half of a century is the basic method of 
secondary prevention of cervical cancer, which is applied 
at the same time as a classic test of choice for the detec-
tion of lesions and a differential-diagnostic method for 
predicting the histological diagnosis (5). In an effort to 
reduce potential errors and increase the overall sensitivity 
of the screening, during the past years has developed sev-
eral new techniques that have been proposed as a comple-
mentary method to conventional "Pap test". These include 
HPV DNA typization (6). There is an assumption that </p>

<p>ORIGINAL ARTICLE </p>

<p>doi: 10.5455/medarh.2014.68.106-109 </p>

<p>Med Arh. 2014 Apr; 68(2): 106-109 </p>

<p>Received: November 21th 2013 | Accepted: March 25th 2014 
© AVICENA 2014 </p>

<p>Published online: 22/04/2014 
Published print: 
04/2014 </p>

<p>Correlation of Cervical Smear and Pathohistological Findings </p>



<p>Med Arh. 2014 Apr; 68(2): 106-109 </p>

<p>during the last 25-30 years has increased the frequency of 
diagnosis of carcinoma in situ, and in part because of the 
efficiency of cytologic examination (7). 
In the history of medicine, the only case of reduced in-
cidence and mortality, as well as human malignancies is 
cervical cancers without medical intervention (8). </p>

<p>2. GOAL </p>

<p>The aim of the research is to analyze the correlation be-
tween the abnormal cytological findings and histological 
diagnosis in all patients during the observed period. </p>

<p>3. MATERIAL AND METHODS </p>

<p>The study was descriptive-analytical, comparative, 
partly epidemiological, and mainly clinical applicative. 
The study involved all patients who meet the criteria for 
inclusion in the study. Used are the results of cytological 
and histological diagnosis in the period from January 1, 
2009 to December 31, 2011. 
In all subjects had previously done colposcopic exam-
ination and Pap test, and in patients with abnormal find-
ings was also performed cervical biopsy for obtaining his-
topathological diagnosis. 
Colposcopy was performed using the Olympus colpo-
scope. The Pap test is taken from the front and rear lip 
and cervical canal. From the sample taken is made the cy-
tological smear, which is fixed on a microscopic slide and 
stained by the method of Pap-Nikolai. After staining was 
performed microscopic analysis of morphological char-
acteristics of the cells in the course of which are detected 
signs of cervical inflammation, causes infection, benign 
and malignant cells and other pathological changes. 
After the punch biopsy changes in the cervix, the sam-
ples were forwarded to the Department of Pathology at 
the further processing. 
For statistical analysis of the data obtained was used 
software package <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> for Windows. In the analysis of the 
results obtained, the following statistical methods were 
used: for continuous variables in the study as the first 
analysis of symmetry (normality) of their distribution by 
Kolmogornov-Smirnov and Shapiro-Wilk test. Since the 
distribution of continuous variables significantly deviated 
from normal (Gaussian) distribution, mean values and a 
measure of dispersion, for their comparison is used the </p>

<p>median and interquartile range and nonparametric test 
(ANOVA), normal and ordinal variables in the study were 
analyzed by χ2 test and in the lack of expected frequencies 
used Fisher's exact test. The statistical analysis used the 
Pearson χ2 test for difference distribution of nominal and 
ordinal data. </p>

<p>4. RESULTS </p>

<p>Table 1 shows the frequency of dysplasia (L-Sil and 
H-SIL) in relation to the normal cytological findings. 
Mann-Whitney test showed a statistically significant 
difference in the frequency of L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III) 
findings in relation to the period covered by this study. 
In 2010 was recorded the highest percentage compared 
to the total number of L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III) findings, 
Z=-4.913, p=0.004. 
Distribution of respondents by age group is displayed 
on Tables 2 and 3. 
Analysis of respondents by age groups compared to the 
period covered by this study has been determined that the 
highest percentage of patients was with L-SIL and H-SIL 
(Pap III and IV) findings for the age group under 29 years. 
The percentage and frequency of L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap 
III and IV) findings in women of older age groups linearly 
decreases and the lowest is in the age group 60-69 years. 
ANOVA test showed that there was no statistically sig-
nificant difference in the average age of patients with L-SIL 
and H-SIL (Pap III and IV) findings in relation to the test-
ed year, F=3.86, p=0,21. Statistical analysis showed a pos-
itive trend in terms that younger respondents have L-SIL 
and H-SIL (Pap III and IV) cytological findings, so that 
the average age of respondents in 2011 was 31.12±9.12 
years. </p>

<p>2009 
2010 
2011 
Total 
N 
% 
N 
% 
N 
% 
N 
% 
L-SIL; (PAP III) 
101 
4.34 
186 
9.50 
135 
6.46 
395 
6.20 
H-SIL (PAP IV) 
25 
1.07 
20 
1.02 
15 
0.72 
27 
0.42 
Normal cytological findings 
2202 
94.59 
1752 
89.48 
1940 
92.82 
5894 
92.44 
Total 
2328 
100.00 
1958 
100.00 
2090 
100.00 
6376 
100.00 </p>

<p>Table 1. The frequency of the L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III and Pap IV) findings in relation to other cytological findings (Pap test) </p>

<p>Age groups 
2009 
2010 
2011 
Total </p>

<p>N 
% 
N 
% 
N 
% 
N 
% 
≤29 
89 
45.88 
129 
55.13 
104 
51.74 
322 
51.19 
30-59 
96 
49.48 
99 
42.31 
92 
45.77 
287 
45.63 
≥60 
9 
4.64 
6 
2.56 
5 
2.49 
20 
3.18 
Total 
194 
100.00 
234 
100.00 
201 
100.00 
629 
100.00 </p>

<p>Table 2. The age groups of patients with L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III and IV) cytological findings </p>

<p>Mean 
SD 
SEM </p>

<p>95% Confidence 
Interval for Mean 
Min 
Max. 
Lower 
Bound </p>

<p>Upper 
Bound </p>

<p>2009 
33.85 10.46 
0.74 
32.39 
35.32 
19.00 
69.00 </p>

<p>2010 
33.14 10.51 
0.68 
31.80 
34.48 
19.00 
68.00 </p>

<p>2011 
31.12 
9.12 
0.65 
29.82 
32.42 
19.00 
66.00 </p>

<p>Total 
32.75 10.14 
0.40 
31.95 
33.54 
19.00 
69.00 </p>

<p>Table 3. The average age of patients with L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap 
III and IV) cytological findings in relation to the period covered 
by the survey </p>

<p>Correlation of Cervical Smear and Pathohistological Findings </p>



<p>Med Arh. 2014 Apr; 68(2): 106-109 </p>

<p>Table 4. Number of the performed biopsies in case of 
L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III and IV) findings, performed at 
the Clinic of Obstetrics and Gynecology and in other in-
stitutions, on annual basis. 
Pearson Chi square test showed a statistically signifi-
cant difference in the incidence of cytologic findings of 
L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III and IV), set by the cytologist at 
the Clinic of Obstetrics and Gynecology and other insti-
tutions, χ 
2 =93.85, p=0.000. 
The highest percentage of women who underwent cer-
vical biopsy had CIN I findings (n=283), followed by CIN 
II (n=165), CIN III (n=152). Histopathologic findings of 
CIN II and CIN III were the most frequent in 2010. 
Pearson Chi square test showed a statistically significant 
difference in the prevalence of histopathological diagnosis 
in relation to the total number of the performed biopsies. 
The most common finding was CIN I, while there is a 
small percentage difference in the incidence of CIN II and 
CIN III diagnosis, χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=15.68, p=0.016. </p>

<p>5. DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The incidence of cervical cancer is unacceptably high. It 
is believed that about 80% of all cases occur in less devel-
oped countries, because prevention programs are either 
non-existent or poorly implemented. 
There is a general opinion that organized national 
screening programs using Pap test produce the best re-
sults. This is best illustrated by data from Finland, where 
organized screening results were exceptional, reducing 
the incidence from 14.8/100,000 in 1963 to 2.8/100,000 in 
1992, reducing the total incidence by 69.6% (9). 
Due to the simplicity of implementation, VCE smear 
cytology is considered to be the best technique for screen-</p>

<p>ing. It is important to note that on the basis of cytology 
is not made a definitive diagnosis, it is always necessary 
to respect the protocol. Results may be false positive and 
false negative in range from 10 to 35%. A particular prob-
lem is definitely false negative results (10). 
The course of this research led to the following results. 
The highest percentage of L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III) 
findings was during 2010 and it was (186) 9.5%, and the 
lowest in 2009, where there was (101) 4.34%. In this peri-
od, the total number of L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III) findings 
amounted to 395 (6.20%) compared to other cytological 
findings-5894 (92.44%). 
Analysis of respondents by age group compared to the 
years covered by this study has been determined that the 
highest percentage of patients with L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap 
III and IV) findings was in the age group under 29 years. 
The percentage and frequency of L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap 
III and IV) findings in women of older age groups linearly 
decreases and is lowest in the age group from 60-69 years. 
Brotherton JM. and associates (11), in their study, "Does 
HPV type 16 or 18 in the prevalence of cervical intraepi-
thelial neoplasia grade 3 lesions vary by age? An import-
ant issue for postvaccination surveillance", stated that 
among the 317 women who were enrolled in the study, 
with diagnosis CIN III, 70% of them aged 16-25 years, was 
detected HPV, 16.59% in women age aged 26-35 years and 
48% in women older than 36 years. 
The study "Gynecologic malignancy in Tuzla Canton" 
by Fatusic and colleagues report that in the period from 
1993-2006, 27.11% of all women with cervical cancer is 
younger than 30 years (12). 
This situation can be attributed to insufficient informa-
tion, the motivation of young women for regular gyne-
cological examinations, as well as the absence of national 
screening program. 
According to the literature, the very frequency of cervi-
cal dysplasia and occurrence of HPV declines in percent-
age with age, so our results do not differ statistically from 
the research of other authors. 
ANOVA test showed that there was no statistically 
significant difference in the average age of patients with 
L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III and IV) findings in relation to 
the tested years. 
Statistical analysis showed a positive trend that younger 
respondents have L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III and IV) cyto-
logical findings, so that the average age of respondents in 
2011 is 31.12±9.12 years. </p>

<p>Year 
Total 
2009 
2010 
2011 </p>

<p>Biopsies </p>

<p>Clinic of Obstetrics 
and Gynecology </p>

<p>N 
126 
206 
80 
412 
% within biopsies 
30.6% 
50.0% 
19.4% 
100.0% 
% within years 
63.6% 
86.2% 
41.7% 
65.5% </p>

<p>Other </p>

<p>N 
72 
33 
112 
217 
% within biopsies 
33.2% 
15.2% 
51.6% 
100.0% 
% within years 
36.4% 
13.8% 
58.3% 
34.5% </p>

<p>Total </p>

<p>N 
198 
239 
192 
629 
% within biopsies 
31.5% 
38.0% 
30.5% 
100.0% 
% within years 
100.0% 
100.0% 
100.0% 
100.0% </p>

<p>Table 4 shows the total number of biopsies that are performed in the analyzed period. </p>

<p>Biopsies 
Total 
CoOaG Other </p>

<p>PHD </p>

<p>CIN I 
N 
161 
122 
283 
% 
56.9 
43.1 
100.0 </p>

<p>CIN II 
N 
98 
67 
165 
% 
59.4 
40.61 
100.0 </p>

<p>CIN III 
N 
137 
15 
152 
% 
90.1 
9.87 
100.0 </p>

<p>Total 
N 
396 
204 
600 
% 
66,00 
34.00 
100.0 
CoOaG=Clinic of Obstetrics and Gynecology </p>

<p>Table 5. Histopathological diagnosis after a biopsy of the cervix </p>

<p>Correlation of Cervical Smear and Pathohistological Findings </p>



<p>Med Arh. 2014 Apr; 68(2): 106-109 </p>

<p>Analyzing the number of the performed biopsies on the 
L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III and IV) findings, set at the Clinic 
of Gynecology and Obstetrics and in other institutions on 
an annual basis, we came up with the following results. 
Of the total number of the performed biopsies on the 
Clinic of Gynecology and Obstetrics, University of Sara-
jevo-629, cytological L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III and IV) 
finding was in 412 (65.5%) respondents who directly came 
to the Clinic of Gynecology and Obstetrics, and in 217 
(35.5%) of respondents cytological L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap 
III) finding was set at other medical institutions. The high-
est percentage of cervical biopsy due to L-SIL and H-SIL 
(Pap III and IV) findings was made in the 2010, 38% (239), 
and approximately the same number was made in 2009 
and 2011. The highest percentage of biopsies due to L-SIL 
and H-SIL (Pap III and IV) that was set in other medical 
institutions was made in 2011-112 (51.6%). 
On this basis we can say that there is statistically sig-
nificant difference in the frequency of cytologic findings 
of L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III and IV), set at the Clinic of 
Gynecology and Obstetrics and other institutions by the 
cytologist. The highest percentage of women who under-
went cervical biopsy had CIN I findings (n=283), followed 
by CIN II (n=165), CIN III (n=152). Histopathologic find-
ings of CIN II and CIN III were the most common in 2010. 
In relation to the total number of the performed biopsies 
there was a statistically significant difference in the inci-
dence of histopathological diagnosis. The most common 
finding CIN I, and the difference between CIN II and CIN 
III diagnosis was in a small percentage. 
In a study conducted by Kirschner et al. is stated that 
from the 290 analyzed cervical biopsies diagnosed with 
intraepithelial cervical neoplasia, 276 of them were HPV 
positive. HPV16 and HPV18 were found in about 75% of 
cervical intraepithelial lesions of high-grade in population 
of Denmark, and these two genotypes are considered as 
causes of at least 61.9% cases (13). 
In the study "Correlation of cervical cytology and histol-
ogy" conducted by Saha et al., 2004-2005, which includ-
ed 43 patients, 22 of them with benign lesions, 8 LSIL, 9 
HSIL and 1 ASCUS, came to the conclusion that the Pap 
test is in a statistically significant correlation with biopsy 
results (14). In the course of our research, analyzing the 
relationship between histopathologic diagnoses after cer-
vical biopsy in relation to the place of setting the diagno-
sis, we reached the following results. 
Of the total number of patients with CIN I (n=283) at 
the Clinic of Gynecology and Obstetrics was diagnosed in 
56.9%, and with a diagnosis of CIN I diagnosed in other 
institutions was 43.1%. With CIN II at the Clinic of Gyne-
cology and Obstetrics was 59.4%, and from other institu-
tions 40.6%. While the total number of women with CIN 
III (n=152) at the Clinic of Gynecology and Obstetrics 
was 90.1%, and women who were diagnosed at other clin-
ics was 9.9%. This results show that there is a statistically 
significant difference compared to the PHD biopsy of the 
cervix after L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III and IV) cytologic 
findings, and that the largest statistical difference is in 
case CIN III changes in relation to the cytological find-
ings, issued on the Clinic of Gynecology and Obstetrics 
and other medical institutions. </p>

<p>6. CONCLUSION </p>

<p>In this study, which was conducted at the Clinic of 
Gynecology and Obstetrics, Clinical Center of Sarajevo 
University from January 1, 2009 to December 31, 2012, 
were included a total of 2328 patients. We came to the fol-
lowing conclusions: The total number of L-SIL and H-SIL 
(Pap III) findings amounted to 395 (6.20%) compared to 
other cytological findings-5894 (92.44%). The frequen-
cy of H-SIL (Pap IV) was not statistically different in the 
observed period. The highest percentage of women who 
underwent cervical biopsy had CIN I findings (n=283). 
Histopathologic findings of CIN II and CIN III were the 
most common in 2010. There is a statistically significant 
difference compared to the PHD biopsy of the cervix after 
L-SIL and H-SIL (Pap III and IV) cytologic findings, and 
that the largest statistical difference in CIN III changes is 
in relation to the cytological findings, issued at the Clinic 
of Gynecology and Obstetrics and other health care in-
stitutions. The highest percentage of patients with L-SIL 
and H-SIL (Pap III and IV) findings was in the age group 
under 29 years. The percentage and frequency of L-SIL 
and H-SIL findings in women of older age groups linearly 
decreases and is lowest in the age group of 60-69 years. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST: NONE DECLARED </p>



</text></tei>