<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4221951" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Summary </p>

<p>Objective: To evaluate how an online toolkit may support 
ePrescribing deployments in National Health Service hos-
pitals, by assessing the type of knowledge-based resources 
currently sought by key stakeholders. 
Design: Questionnaire-based survey of attendees at a 
national ePrescribing symposium. 
Setting: 2013 National ePrescribing Symposium in London, 
UK. 
Participants: Eighty-four delegates were eligible for inclu-
sion in the survey, of whom 70 completed and returned the 
questionnaire. 
Main outcome measures: Estimate of the usefulness and 
type of content to be included in an ePrescribing toolkit. 
Results: Interest in a toolkit designed to support the imple-
mentation and use of ePrescribing systems was high 
(n ¼ 64; 91.4%). As could be expected given the current 
dearth of such a resource, few respondents (n ¼ 2; 2.9%) 
had access or used an ePrescribing toolkit at the time of the 
survey. Anticipated users for the toolkit included imple-
mentation (n ¼ 62; 88.6%) and information technology 
(n ¼ 61; 87.1%) teams, pharmacists (n ¼ 61; 87.1%), doc-
tors (n ¼ 58; 82.9%) and nurses (n ¼ 56; 80.0%). Summary 
guidance for every stage of the implementation (n ¼ 48; 
68.6%), planning and monitoring tools (n ¼ 47; 67.1%) 
and case studies of hospitals' experiences (n ¼ 45; 64.3%) 
were considered the most useful types of content. 
Conclusions: There is a clear need for reliable and up-to-
date knowledge to support ePrescribing system deploy-
ments and longer term use. The findings highlight how a 
toolkit may become a useful instrument for the manage-
ment of knowledge in the field, not least by allowing the 
exchange of ideas and shared learning. </p>

<p>Despite growing interest in and financial support for 
the deployment of ePrescribing systems 1-4 that offer 
varying degrees of functionality in the supply, admin-
istration, recording and prescribing of medication, 4 
there is relatively little experience of implementing 
and using these systems in National Health Service 
(NHS) hospitals in the UK. 4-6 The recently 
announced NHS 'Safer Wards, Safer Hospitals 
Technology Fund' 7 marks the beginning of a £1 bil-
lion investment in Information Technology (IT) over 
the next three years by the UK government and NHS 
organisations and provides strong evidence of the 
policy drive to support the establishment of health 
IT systems across NHS hospitals. This push for the 
digitisation of NHS hospitals has been driven by 
expectations that the introduction of new IT systems, 
or eHealth systems, may increase safety, 8-10 organisa-
tional efficiency in the delivery of care and medica-
tion, 11 as well as improved communication, 2,12 both 
within the hospital and between primary and second-
ary care settings. Efforts to establish paper-light 
environments across the NHS risk, however, being 
hampered by the lack of experience and knowledge 
of implementing eHealth systems in NHS hos-
pitals. 6,13 Appropriate knowledge-based support 
may go some way to addressing the immaturity of 
the UK eHealth landscape. The NHS Connecting 
for Health Programme has until recently provided 
an authoritative online resource to help promote 
and deliver eHealth services across the NHS, 14 
including ePrescribing. Many of these resources 
have now migrated to the Health and Social Care 
Information system portal, 15 a gateway to a wider </p>

<p>Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine Open; 
5(10) 1-9 
DOI: 10.1177/2054270414551658 </p>

<p>! 2014 The Author(s) </p>

<p>Creative Commons CC-BY-NC: This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 License (http://www. 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided 
the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access page (http://www.uk.sagepub.com/aboutus/openaccess.htm). </p>

<p>range of health informatics-related data and material. 
The availability and use of such knowledge is essen-
tial to support an organisation's ability to change and 
innovate. 16,17 It also facilitates the transfer and 
exchange of knowledge between research and practice 
and is a key underpinning of successful eHealth 
deployments. 18,19 
In line with such understandings, the National 
Institute for Health Research (NIHR) has commis-
sioned us to undertake a programme of research 
evaluating the implementation and adoption of 
ePrescribing systems in English hospitals. Part of 
this has included the development of a toolkit 13 that 
reflects the various stages and associated needs of 
users to successfully deploy, use and integrate a hos-
pital ePrescribing system. Building on the preliminary 
recommendations made in earlier work, 13 a study was 
designed to guide the subsequent toolkit prototype 
development. Since it is now well established that 
user involvement and participatory design are abso-
lute requisites in the planning and design of user-
friendly learning technologies and resources, 20,21 the 
study sought to map participants' information and 
knowledge needs in relation to ePrescribing imple-
mentation and adoption, in order to support the tool-
kit's usability. We report here on findings from this 
study. </p>

<p>Methods 
Study design </p>

<p>The National Symposium for the Health Service on 
deriving value from ePrescribing in hospitals held in 
June 2013 at the Royal Society in London, UK, was 
selected as the setting for the study, as it brought 
together key stakeholders, including delegates from 
46 different Hospital Trusts, 12 commercial organisa-
tions and eight policy and government bodies as well 
as academic researchers. A questionnaire-based 
survey was chosen as a relatively efficient data collec-
tion method within the limited time available in a 
conference setting. </p>

<p>Developing the questionnaire </p>

<p>The content and focus of the questionnaire (see 
Appendix 1) were informed by the needs of users as 
defined by the literature 1-13 as well as the research 
team's own experience as researchers and clinicians 
and contained nine numbered questions (closed-and 
open-ended) designed to investigate respondents' 
needs at different stages of the deployment of an 
ePrescribing system. Some questions contained mul-
tiple sub-questions to concentrate on areas of </p>

<p>interest, providing up to 41 data items per respondent 
and covering the following areas: </p>

<p>1. Respondents' role/place of work. 
2. Current access to a toolkit to support ePrescribing 
implementation and use, and interest in having 
access to an ePrescribing toolkit. 
3. Audience, type of content to include and user sup-
port required for an ePrescribing toolkit. 
4. Knowledge, perceived usefulness and usability of 
other toolkits in existence in the NHS. </p>

<p>These areas were targeted: first, to provide basic back-
ground information on respondents, thus allowing us 
to compare the sample to the wider ePrescribing stake-
holder base; second, to evaluate areas of need identi-
fied in research elsewhere; 13 and third, to explore 
pathways to better utilisation of knowledge. 16-19 At 
the end of the questionnaire, respondents were also 
encouraged to provide free text comments. 
The questionnaire was developed and piloted with 
seven members of the NIHR ePrescribing 
Programme team, which included doctors, pharma-
cists, social scientists and a Patient Public 
Involvement (PPI) group. This process allowed for 
increasing refinement of the questionnaire through 
feedback and testing. </p>

<p>Sampling and data collection </p>

<p>The questionnaire was distributed to all the delegates 
(n ¼ 99) who attended the National ePrescribing 
Symposium by placing one copy of the questionnaire 
in each delegate pack. The questionnaires were num-
bered serially with a unique reference number to 
track response rate and facilitate the exclusion of 
individuals associated with organising the event. 
Only delegates external to the ePrescribing Research 
team were eligible for inclusion in the survey, provid-
ing a sample size of n ¼ 84. This exclusion was applied 
to ensure that new insights could be collated which 
were not guided by the Research team's existing 
knowledge and to minimise the risks of introducing 
biases in the findings given that the toolkit is a major 
output from the Research Programme. No other 
exclusion criteria were applied. 
The questionnaire was self-administered to allow 
for a greater rate of participation within the limited 
one-day timeframe of the symposium and to maintain 
as much confidentiality and anonymity as possible 
within a public setting. Time was provided at the end 
of the opening keynote session of the conference for 
delegates to complete the questionnaire, and the 
majority was handed in to the research team at that 
point. Other opportunities throughout the course of </p>

<p> 
Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine Open 5(10) </p>

<p>the day were also available (i.e. during refreshment 
intervals). Reminders to complete and return the ques-
tionnaire were made in person by the research team 
and via posters at the conference. In two cases, the 
questionnaire was returned by post after the event. </p>

<p>Ethical considerations </p>

<p>All records of individual names or contact details were 
removed from the dataset prior to analysis to ensure 
that all responses remained anonymous. This involved 
removing identifiable information including place of 
work, name, email address or other contact details. 
Participation in the survey was completely voluntary 
and no incentives were used. The Programme of Work 
has been reviewed by and received ethical approval 
from the Centre for Population Health Sciences 
Ethics Review Group at the University of Edinburgh. </p>

<p>Data handling and analysis </p>

<p>The data collected were entered into a Microsoft 
Access 
database 
(Microsoft 
Corporation, 
Washington, USA) and identifiers removed. Fully 
anonymised data were then exported for analysis in 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Minitab</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">16</rs> Statistical Software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Minitab Inc.</rs>., 
Pennsylvania, USA), and descriptive statistics were 
obtained. The questionnaire contained only a small 
number of open-ended questions. Answers to these 
were either quantified through frequency counts (i.e. 
when respondents were asked for details of other 
toolkits they used c.f. Q.3 and Q.8) or coded manu-
ally and organised by type (e.g. for questions asking 
about 'other categories' not listed, c.f. Q.5 and Q.6). 
Additional comments obtained through free text were 
coded manually and organised by theme. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Sample </p>

<p>Seventy completed valid questionnaires were 
returned, providing a response rate of 83.3%. An ini-
tial analysis of the total sample revealed that pharma-
cists represented the majority of respondents (n ¼ 38; 
54.3%). Other groups of participants included NHS 
Managers, Policy, Research and Development (n ¼ 9; 
12.9%), IT staff (n ¼ 8; 11.4%), doctors (n ¼ 6; 8.6%) 
and suppliers (n ¼ 5; 7.1%). </p>

<p>Access, use and interest in an ePrescribing toolkit </p>

<p>Only a very small number of delegates reported 
having access to a toolkit specifically designed to sup-
port the implementation and adoption of ePrescribing </p>

<p>systems (n ¼ 2; 2.9%). The only two toolkits reported 
were a 'home-grown' product (n ¼ 1), developed 
within the hospital where it is currently used, and 
the NHS Connecting for Health website (n ¼ 1). It is 
worth pointing out that NHS Connecting for Health 
was also cited in responses obtained elsewhere in the 
questionnaire in relation to use and access to NHS 
relevant toolkits that are not solely dedicated to 
ePrescribing (see 'Experience of existing toolkits 
used in the NHS' section). Almost all the participants 
(n ¼ 64; 91.4%) indicated their interest in having 
access to an ePrescribing toolkit, with a small propor-
tion being undecided (n ¼ 5; 7.1%). 
Most respondents agreed that the ePrescribing 
toolkit should be aimed at the implementation 
(n ¼ 62; 88.6%) and IT teams (n ¼ 61; 87.1%), 
pharmacists (n ¼ 61; 87.1%), doctors (n ¼ 58; 
82.9%) and nurses (n ¼ 56; 80.0%). Far fewer 
respondents felt that it would be useful for those in 
overarching managerial roles such as the Trust Board 
(n ¼ 47; 67.1%) or NHS managers more generally 
(n ¼ 45; 64.3%) to have access to the toolkit. Other 
potential users, who were cited via free text, included 
allied health professionals (n ¼ 9), finance and admin-
istration staff (n ¼ 5) and patients and patient groups 
(n ¼ 4). 
Almost two-thirds of respondents stated that they 
would value hands-on expert support in using the 
toolkit to support local needs and practices (n ¼ 45; 
64.3%), with almost a third (n ¼ 22; 31.4%) 
undecided. </p>

<p>Content of the ePrescribing toolkit </p>

<p>Participants were asked to rate a list of content types 
on a scale ranging from 'very useful' to 'not useful at 
all' (see Table 1). The results indicated that a range of 
practical tools were needed to support an ePrescribing 
implementation. There was also considerable interest 
among the participants in discussing issues and shar-
ing ideas and knowledge on ePrescribing through case 
studies and via a discussion forum, rather than a 
social media platform. A small number of delegates 
provided details in free text of other specific areas of 
interests for inclusion in the toolkit, such as the inte-
gration of ePrescribing systems into electronic health 
records (EHRs), standards, benefits and impact, con-
ferences and meetings, how to conduct site visits, as 
well as guidance aimed specifically at the hospital 
board on 'how not to implement'. </p>

<p>Experience of existing toolkits used in the NHS </p>

<p>Delegates' awareness of the availability of tools and 
toolkits covering any area relevant to NHS staff was </p>

<p>Lee et al. </p>

<p>
markedly lower than levels of interest in an 
ePrescribing specific toolkit. Twenty-eight partici-
pants (40.0%) acknowledged the existence of NHS 
relevant toolkits, while the majority (n ¼ 41; 58.6%) 
either did not know (n ¼ 23; 32.9%) or was unsure 
(n ¼ 18; 25.7%) if such tools or toolkits were in exist-
ence (see Table 2). 
The tools and toolkits in existence and/or used by 
the respondents covered eHealth, medicines manage-
ment, hospital safety and efficiency, as well as patient 
engagement or interaction (see Table 3). The most 
frequently cited toolkit was NHS Connecting for 
Health (n ¼ 7), followed by the Productive Ward 
Toolkit (n ¼ 3) and Homecare (n ¼ 3). As well as 
having the highest frequency of citation, the NHS 
Connecting for Health toolkit was viewed favourably 
by delegates who had used it, with ease of use (8/10), 
quality of content (7.8/10) and breadth and depth of 
its coverage (7/10) all obtaining high scores. </p>

<p>Knowledge management and knowledge transfer </p>

<p>The space provided for additional comments offered 
interesting insights into the issues relating to 
ePrescribing knowledge management and knowledge 
transfer. First, it was noted that 'learning from 
others' was key to avoiding 're-inventing the wheel' 
or 'repeating the same mistakes' and could be forma-
lised through a mentoring programme to allow 'bud-
dying' of less experienced hospitals. Second, it was 
suggested that supporting local needs through the 
use of a toolkit may be complicated by an aspiration 
to provide generic support to all hospitals in England, 
aiming to implement an ePrescribing system. This 
tension between a designed-for-all toolkit versus 
one addressing local needs was further echoed in 
requests for content to be tailored to specific areas, 
sectors and specialities. Third, there was demand for </p>

<p>Table 1. Proposed content type and perceived usefulness. 
Type of material </p>

<p>Tools and 
checklists </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>forum </p>

<p>FAQs </p>

<p>Templates </p>

<p>Reference 
materials and 
publications 
Social media 
platform </p>

<p>Overview of 
deployment </p>

<p>of systems </p>

<p>Case 
studies </p>

<p>'How 
to' guides </p>

<p>Very useful </p>

<p>47 (67.1%) </p>

<p>29 (41.4%) </p>

<p>37 (52.9%) </p>

<p>43 (61.4%) </p>

<p>29 (41.4%) </p>

<p>9 (12.9%) </p>

<p>35 (50.0%) </p>

<p>45 (64.3%) </p>

<p>48 (68.6%) </p>

<p>Useful </p>

<p>21 (30.0%) </p>

<p>33 (47.1%) </p>

<p>28 (40.0%) </p>

<p>24 (34.3%) </p>

<p>32 (45.7%) </p>

<p>38 (54.3%) </p>

<p>28 (40.0%) </p>

<p>24 (34.3%) </p>

<p>20 (28.6%) </p>

<p>Neither useful or not useful </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>6 (8.6%) </p>

<p>4 (5.7%) </p>

<p>2 (2.9%) </p>

<p>2 (2.9%) </p>

<p>14 (20.0%) </p>

<p>6 (8.6%) </p>

<p>1 (1.4%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Not useful </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>7 (10.0%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Not useful at all </p>

<p>1 (1.4%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 (1.4%) </p>

<p>1 (1.4%) </p>

<p>1 (1.4%) </p>

<p>1 (1.4%) </p>

<p>1 (1.4%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>No response </p>

<p>1 (1.4%) </p>

<p>2 (2.9%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>6 (8.6%) </p>

<p>1 (1.4%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 (2.9%) </p>

<p>Total (N) </p>

<p>7 0 </p>

<p>7 0 </p>

<p>7 0 </p>

<p>7 0 </p>

<p>7 0 </p>

<p>7 0 </p>

<p>7 0 </p>

<p>7 0 </p>

<p>7 0 </p>

<p>Table 2. NHS relevant toolkit awareness, interest and 
current access to an ePrescribing toolkit among participants. </p>

<p>Awareness 
of NHS 
relevant 
toolkits </p>

<p>Interest in 
ePrescribing 
toolkit </p>

<p>Current access 
to a toolkit 
to support 
ePrescribing </p>

<p>Yes 
28 (40.0%) 64 (91.4%) 
2 (2.9%) </p>

<p>No 
23 (32.9%) 
1 (1.4%) 
54 (77.1%) </p>

<p>Not sure 
18 (25.7%) 
5 (7.1%) 
13 (18.6%) </p>

<p>No answer 
1 (1.4%) 
0 
1 (1.4%) </p>

<p>Total (N) 
70 
70 
70 </p>

<p> 
Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine Open 5(10) </p>

<p>a toolkit that is up-to-date in its content and appli-
cation. Novel uses, including interactive and visual 
capabilities, such as in situ simulation training or 
videos to provide visual support, were cited. 
Constantly updated material relating to technical 
and infrastructure guidance, as well as evaluation 
and audit requirements, were also highlighted as par-
ticularly important areas. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The findings from this study suggest a high degree of 
interest in developing a toolkit to support the roll-out </p>

<p>of ePrescribing systems in NHS hospitals. This 
should be of little surprise given the relatively nascent 
state of ePrescribing deployments in NHS hospitals 
and the patchy knowledge and unproven track-record 
of many hospitals implementing and adopting 
ePrescribing systems. The complexity and lengthy 
timescales needed to implement EHRs and associated 
challenges 6,22 clearly align stakeholders' needs to 
those of the aims of the toolkit. We should also be 
mindful when interpreting these findings of the 
study's limitations, notably the use of a convenience 
sample that had a relative over-representation of 
pharmacists (even if not atypical for such a study 
given this group's early involvement in ePrescribing 
projects) 4,23 as well as the low levels of use of existing 
ePrescribing support websites reported by the 
respondents. That said, we believe representatives 
from the majority of hospitals who are either plan-
ning to implement or have implemented ePrescribing 
systems attended this national event. Furthermore, 
the limited range of participants is a reminder of 
the need and opportunity for the toolkit to act as a 
vehicle for wider engagement with all those involved 
in the use of ePrescribing from patients right through 
to the Trust Board. 
The study's findings underline the demand for a 
toolkit that provides highly practical resources to 
help plan ePrescribing deployments as well as support 
their continued use, to a broad base of users. Such 
findings mirror the calls made by MacFarlane et al. 19 
who conclude in their work that there is indeed an 
immediate need to address 'the translational gap by 
developing tools . . . to promote implementation . . . in 
the field of eHealth'. The considerable interest in 
ensuring the toolkit can become both a practical 
resource centre, as well as a repository for 
ePrescribing knowledge and research in the UK and 
internationally, may go some way to help achieve 
this, 
by 
supporting 
improved 
knowledge 
exchange 16-18 in the field. Notwithstanding such 
aims, the study demonstrates how content is only 
one aspect of this exchange of knowledge: how 
ideas and expertise are shared and used matters too. 
The real value of the toolkit will thus come from its 
actual use, and further research is needed to evaluate 
how valuable this toolkit will become once in use, and 
whether support mechanisms such as mentoring 
could further promote applying usefully expert 
knowledge. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>The toolkit's potential role in helping address the 
knowledge gap facing hospitals in their deployment 
of ePrescribing systems is significant. This study has </p>

<p>Table 3. Toolkits cited and frequency (counts). </p>

<p>Toolkit Name/Area of specialisation </p>

<p>Frequency 
of citation </p>

<p>Agency for Healthcare 
Research &amp; Quality (AHRQ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Connecting For Health (CfH) 
7 </p>

<p>Chemocare 
1 </p>

<p>Choose &amp; Book 
1 </p>

<p>Dashboard Toolkit 
1 </p>

<p>Define 
1 </p>

<p>ePACT 
1 </p>

<p>Homecare 
3 </p>

<p>Infection Control Risk Assessment 
1 </p>

<p>Information Governance Toolkit 
2 </p>

<p>Keele 
1 </p>

<p>Medicines Best Practice 
1 </p>

<p>Mental Health Medicines Toolkit 
1 </p>

<p>Method M (Cerner) 
1 </p>

<p>National Institute for Clinical 
Excellence (NICE) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Non-Medical Prescribing Toolkit 
1 </p>

<p>Nursing Toolkit 
1 </p>

<p>Patient Information 
1 </p>

<p>Patient Safety Assessment (PSA) 
1 </p>

<p>Pharmacy Automation Toolkit 
2 </p>

<p>Productive Ward 
3 </p>

<p>Lee et al. </p>

<p>
arguably provided a better understanding of users' 
needs and aspirations for the toolkit which will 
enable it to offer a suitable range of resources to 
facilitate the introduction and longer term integration 
of ePrescribing systems. While helpful for the further 
elaboration of the tools and content of the toolkit 
itself, this is only a first step. Indeed the online and 
publicly accessible prototype of the ePrescribing tool-
kit 24 that this work has supported will now need to be 
further evaluated and critiqued by its users. It also 
remains essential for future work in this area to 
involve a broader base of ePrescribing knowledge 
users than those surveyed in this study. More atten-
tion will need to be paid in particular to groups, such 
as patients, whose knowledge needs have not been 
clearly addressed so far, and to establishing the best 
ways to reach out and engage with those who are at 
present not closely involved in the implementation 
and adoption of ePrescribing systems. </p>

<p>Declarations 
Competing interests: None declared </p>

<p>Funding: This work was supported by a programme of independ-</p>

<p>ent research funded by the NIHR under its Programme Grants for 
Applied Research scheme (RP-PG-1209-10099). The views 
expressed are those of the authors and not necessarily those of 
the NHS, the NIHR or the Department of Health. AS was sup-
ported by The Commonwealth Fund, a private independent foun-
dation based in New York City. The views presented here are those 
of the author and not necessarily those of The Commonwealth 
Fund, its directors, officers or staff. </p>

<p>Ethical approval: The Programme of Work has been reviewed by </p>

<p>and received ethical approval from the Centre for Population 
Health Sciences Ethics Review Group at the University of 
Edinburgh. </p>

<p>Guarantor: LL </p>

<p>Contributorship: LL designed the questionnaire, monitored </p>

<p>data collection, cleaned and analysed the data, drafted and revised 
the paper. KC contributed to the conception and design of the 
study, revised the draft questionnaire and paper. ASl contributed 
to the conception and design of the study, revised the draft ques-
tionnaire and paper. SPS contributed to the conception and design 
of the study, revised the draft questionnaire and paper. JC con-
ceived and designed the study, revised the draft questionnaire and 
paper. AS conceived and designed the study, revised the draft ques-
tionnaire and paper. Laura Marshall organised the Symposium. 
Rosemary Porteous entered the data into the Access Database. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements: We would like to thank all the delegates at </p>

<p>the conference who responded to the questionnaire. </p>

<p>Provenance: Not commissioned; peer-reviewed by William </p>

<p>Coppola </p>



<p> 
Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine Open 5(10) </p>



<p>Appendix 1. ePrescribing and Medicines Administration Toolkit for NHS Hospitals 
Short questionnaire </p>

<p>We have been commissioned by the NHS to produce a Toolkit to support the implementation and adoption of 
ePrescribing and Medicines Administration systems into NHS hospitals. We are asking ALL DELEGATES to 
kindly complete this short questionnaire, to help us better understand your needs. Your views are very important 
to us and we would be very grateful if you could take a few minutes to complete it. Thank you very much and please 
don't forget to hand in your completed questionnaire to a member of the conference team. </p>

<p>1. About you: 
(a) Job title: 
(b) Employer/place of work: 
2. Do you, your colleagues, and/or the NHS hospital(s) you work with, currently have access to a toolkit designed to 
support the implementation and/or use of an ePrescribing and Medicines Administration system? </p>

<p>Yes « 
No « (please go to question 4) 
Not sure « (please go to question 4) </p>

<p>3. If yes, which one? </p>

<p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>

<p>4. Would you, your colleagues, and/or the NHS hospital(s) you work with, find it useful to have an ePrescribing and 
Medicines Administration Toolkit for NHS Hospitals? </p>

<p>Yes « 
No « 
Not sure « </p>

<p>5. Who in your view should this ePrescribing and Medicines Administration Toolkit for NHS Hospitals be aimed at? 
Tick all that apply: </p>

<p>IT Team 
« </p>

<p>Implementation Team 
« 
Trust Board 
« 
Doctors 
« 
Nurses 
« 
Pharmacists 
« 
Managers 
« 
Others -Please specify 
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>

<p>« </p>

<p>Lee et al. </p>

<p>
6. The following question concerns your opinion on the type of content the ePrescribing and Medicines 
Administration Toolkit for NHS Hospitals should offer its users. Please consider your answer to each content 
type before placing a circle around the answer that most approximates your opinion. </p>

<p>How useful would you find the following content in an ePrescribing and Medicines Administration Toolkit for 
NHS Hospitals? </p>

<p>7. Would you, your colleagues and/or the hospital(s) you work with, value hands-on expert support to help apply the 
Toolkit to local needs and practices? </p>

<p>Yes « 
No « 
Not sure « </p>

<p>'How to' guides that explain key consid-
erations at every stage of the implemen-
tation, whether it is when writing a 
business case, going live, upgrading or 
maintaining a system </p>

<p>Very useful 
Useful 
Neither useful 
or not useful </p>

<p>Not useful 
Not useful 
at all </p>

<p>Case studies highlighting how other hospi-
tals have implemented their systems, 
what issues they have dealt with, and the 
lessons they have learnt </p>

<p>Very useful 
Useful 
Neither useful 
or not useful </p>

<p>Not useful 
Not useful 
at all </p>

<p>Tools and checklists that allow to estimate 
the costs of implementing a system, 
facilitate workflow mapping, support 
staff training plans, evaluate safety and 
other benefits, outline potential pitfalls 
and monitor how users feel about the 
system </p>

<p>Very useful 
Useful 
Neither useful 
or not useful </p>

<p>Not useful 
Not useful 
at all </p>

<p>An overview of the ePrescribing and 
Medicines Administration systems avail-
able in the UK and where they have been 
deployed </p>

<p>Very useful 
Useful 
Neither useful 
or not useful </p>

<p>Not useful 
Not useful 
at all </p>

<p>A social media platform where suppliers 
can present their products and hospitals 
can learn about products on offer and 
ask questions directly to suppliers </p>

<p>Very useful 
Useful 
Neither useful 
or not useful </p>

<p>Not useful 
Not useful 
at all </p>

<p>A discussion forum where individuals can 
share ideas and exchange knowledge 
relating to ePrescribing and Medicines 
Administration implementation within 
and across hospitals </p>

<p>Very useful 
Useful 
Neither useful 
or not useful </p>

<p>Not useful 
Not useful 
at all </p>

<p>FAQs on system types, implementation 
strategies and adoption processes </p>

<p>Very useful 
Useful 
Neither useful 
or not useful </p>

<p>Not useful 
Not useful 
at all 
Templates that can be used when drafting 
key documents and to support the plan-
ning and management of the project </p>

<p>Very useful 
Useful 
Neither useful 
or not useful </p>

<p>Not useful 
Not useful 
at all </p>

<p>Reference materials and publications 
Very useful 
Useful 
Neither useful 
or not useful </p>

<p>Not useful 
Not useful 
at all 
Other -Please specify 
Very useful 
Useful 
Neither useful 
or not useful </p>

<p>Not useful 
Not useful 
at all 
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>

<p> 
Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine Open 5(10) </p>

<p>8. The following questions are about your experience of using tools and/or toolkits aimed at supporting those working 
in the NHS. The tools/toolkits we ask you about below are not necessarily related to ePrescribing and Medicines 
Administration, and may cover any area relevant to those working in the NHS. </p>

<p>A. Are you aware of the existence of tools/toolkits used by or aimed at NHS staff? </p>

<p>Yes « 
No « (If no, go to question 9) 
Not sure « (if not sure, go to question 9) </p>

<p>B. If yes, which one(s)? </p>

<p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>

<p>C. For each of the tools/toolkits that you have used or are currently using, please provide a score out of 10 for each of 
the attributes listed in the table, where 0 ¼ the lowest score, and 10 ¼ the highest score. </p>

<p>9. Please use the space below to add any comments and/or suggestions on the subject of ePrescribing and Medicines 
Administration Tools and/or Toolkits: </p>

<p>If you would like to receive further updates on the development of the ePrescribing and Medicines 
Administration Toolkit for NHS Hospitals and the opportunity to comment on prototypes, please provide your 
email address: . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>

<p>Tool/Toolkit 
name or purpose </p>

<p>Ease of use 
(e.g. easy to locate relevant 
information, page layout, overall design) </p>

<p>Quality of content 
(e.g. reliable, relevant, 
useful, informative) </p>

<p>Content Coverage 
(e.g width and depth 
of coverage) </p>

<p> </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>