<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4621840" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Cytoplasmic dynein is a 1.2-MD multisubunit motor complex 
that powers movement of various cargoes toward the minus ends 
of microtubules. This ancient and highly conserved ATPase 
organizes the intracellular environment throughout the cell 
cycle; however, its myriad roles become especially apparent 
during mitosis when it functions in various aspects of spindle 
morphogenesis and positioning (Rusan et al., 2002; Goshima et  al., 2005; Yang et al., 2007; Ferenz et al., 2009; Siller and Doe,  2009). For instance, cortically anchored dynein motors position 
the spindle at the future site of cytokinesis (Eshel et al., 1993;  Li et al., 1993; Carminati and Stearns, 1997), a process that is 
particularly important during asymmetric cell divisions, when 
spindle position dictates the plane of cell division, and thus cell 
fate determination (Pease and Tirnauer, 2011; Williams et al.,  2011). The means by which dynein is delivered to the cell cor-
tex and subsequently activated to pull on astral microtubules 
emanating from spindle poles to move the spindle are unclear. 
Recent studies in budding and fission yeast have revealed 
two distinct mechanisms by which dynein can be targeted to 
the cell cortex, its site of action in both organisms (Markus  and Lee, 2011; Ananthanarayanan et al., 2013). During the 
meiotic prophase in fission yeast, studies suggest that dynein 
first binds along astral microtubules that are in close proxim-
ity to the cell cortex (Ananthanarayanan et al., 2013). Rather 
than walking toward the minus end of these microtubules, 
dynein undergoes one-dimensional diffusion until it encounters 
Mcp5, its cortical anchor. Once bound to Mcp5, dynein mo-</p>

<p>tors switch from diffusive to directed motion and consequently 
move the spindle appropriately. Thus, in addition to anchoring 
dynein at the cortex, Mcp5 appears to activate dynein motility 
by an unknown mechanism. 
A similar but somewhat distinct scenario takes place in 
budding yeast, in which dynein is first targeted to the plus ends 
of astral microtubules before being offloaded to cortical Num1 
(Mcp5 homologue) receptor sites, where it functions to move the 
mitotic spindle toward the daughter cell (Adames and Cooper,  2000; Lee et al., 2005; Markus and Lee, 2011). It is unknown if 
dynein motility is activated subsequent to offloading; however, 
several lines of evidence suggest that its activity is switched 
from being off at plus ends to being on at the cell cortex. For 
instance, in spite of its minus end-directed motility, dynein is 
transported to, and remains associated with, the plus ends of 
dynamic microtubules (Lee et al., 2003; Carvalho et al., 2004). 
Plus end targeting requires the dynein motor domain, the +TIP 
(plus end-tracking protein) Bik1 (CLIP-170 homologue), and 
the dynein-associated factor Pac1 (homologue of human LIS1; 
Lee et al., 2003; Sheeman et al., 2003; Markus et al., 2009). Re-
cent studies suggest that Pac1 plays two distinct and important 
roles in targeting dynein to plus ends. First, Pac1 mediates the 
interaction between dynein and plus end-bound Bik1 (Sheeman  et al., 2003; Roberts et al., 2014). Second, by inhibiting dynein 
motility (Markus and Lee, 2011; Huang et al., 2012), and/or 
by prolonging its microtubule attachment (Yamada et al., 2008;   Cortically anchored dynein orients the spindle through interactions with astral microtubules. In budding yeast, dynein is 
offloaded to Num1 receptors from microtubule plus ends. Rather than walking toward minus ends, dynein remains as-
sociated with plus ends due in part to its association with Pac1/LIS1, an inhibitor of dynein motility. The mechanism by 
which dynein is switched from "off" at the plus ends to "on" at the cell cortex remains unknown. Here, we show that 
overexpression of the coiled-coil domain of Num1 specifically depletes dynein-dynactin-Pac1/LIS1 complexes from 
microtubule plus ends and reduces dynein-Pac1/LIS1 colocalization. Depletion of dynein from plus ends requires its 
microtubule-binding domain, suggesting that motility is required. An enhanced Pac1/LIS1 affinity mutant of dynein or 
overexpression of Pac1/LIS1 rescues dynein plus end depletion. Live-cell imaging reveals minus end-directed dynein-
dynactin motility along microtubules upon overexpression of the coiled-coil domain of Num1, an event that is not 
observed in wild-type cells. Our findings indicate that dynein activity is directly switched "on" by Num1, which induces 
Pac1/LIS1 removal. </p>

<p>The dynein cortical anchor Num1 activates dynein 
motility by relieving Pac1/LIS1-mediated inhibition </p>

<p>Lindsay G. Lammers and Steven M. Markus </p>

<p>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Colorado State University, Fort Collins, CO 80523 </p>

<p>© 2015 Lammers and Markus This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution-
Noncommercial-Share Alike-No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the pub-
lication date (see http://www.rupress.org/terms). After six months it is available under a 
Creative Commons License (Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, 
as described at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). </p>

<p>Correspondence to Steven M. Markus: steven.markus@colostate.edu </p>

<p>Abbreviations used in this paper: MTBD, microtubule-binding domain; PH, 
pleckstrin homology; SPB, spindle pole body. </p>

<p>T H E J O U R N A L O F C E L L B I O L O G Y </p>

<p>JCB • Volume 211 • NumBer 2 • 2015 </p>

<p>
McKenney et al., 2010; Huang et al., 2012), Pac1 holds dynein 
at plus ends by keeping dynein in a nonmotile, or "off" state. 
Thus, plus end-associated dynein may be poised to walk toward 
the minus ends of microtubules but is prevented from doing so 
by Pac1. However, upon offloading to cortical Num1 receptor 
sites, dynein is active, as apparent by its capacity to pull on as-
tral microtubules and consequently move the spindle. Thus, in 
budding yeast, as in fission yeast, dynein may undergo a switch 
in its activity upon attachment to its cortical receptor. However, 
evidence for such a switch is lacking. 
Although factors have been identified that can inhibit 
dynein motility (e.g., MAP4, She1, and Pac1; Markus and Lee,  2011; Samora et al., 2011; Huang et al., 2012; Markus et al.,  2012), it remains unclear whether dynein from organisms other 
than fission yeast need to be switched on to perform their cel-
lular functions or whether they are constitutively active. Recent 
studies indicated that purified metazoan dynein is functional 
for motility in ensemble assays (e.g., microtubule gliding) but 
requires a stable interaction with the dynactin complex for 
single-molecule processivity (McKenney et al., 2014; Schlager  et al., 2014). Stabilization of the dynein-dynactin interaction 
by various coiled-coil-containing adaptor proteins (e.g., BicD2, 
Spindly, Hook3, and Rab11-Fip3) is sufficient to significantly 
enhance dynein processivity, and thereby "activate" dynein 
motility. This is in contrast to budding yeast dynein, which is 
processive in the absence of dynactin or other adaptors or reg-
ulators (Reck-Peterson et al., 2006). It is unclear whether such 
a mechanism generally governs dynein regulation within a cell, 
given that certain functions of dynein in animal cells, such as 
centrosome anchoring, pole focusing, and spindle length regu-
lation, have been shown to occur independently of several such 
adaptors (Raaijmakers et al., 2013). It is also unclear whether 
dynactin-mediated processivity enhancement is the means by 
which cortical dynein activity is promoted. Interestingly, plus 
end association of dynein in higher eukaryotes, which occurs 
in a dynactin-dependent manner, does not require such adaptor 
proteins (Splinter et al., 2012; Duellberg et al., 2014). Given 
the lack of minus end-directed motility of these plus end-
associated dynein motors, an interaction between dynein and 
dynactin is not necessarily sufficient to active dynein motility. 
Using budding yeast, we aimed to test the hypothesis that 
binding of dynein-dynactin to its cortical receptor provides the 
switch that activates cortical dynein activity. Dynein pathway 
function is best understood in this genetically tractable organ-
ism, in which many of the regulatory components and accessory 
chains, which are each encoded by only one gene, are highly con-
served. We found that overexpression of the dynein-dynactin-
interacting coiled-coil domain of Num1 (Num1 CC ) is sufficient to 
activate dynein motility, causing a depletion of dynein-dynactin 
from microtubule plus ends, their accumulation at minus ends, 
and their apparent minus end-directed motility along astral 
microtubules. Our data reveal that the mechanism for this ac-
tivation is likely a Num1 CC -mediated release of Pac1, a potent 
dynein inhibitor, from the dynein motor domain. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Overexpression of Num1 CC depletes dynein-
dynactin from microtubule plus ends </p>

<p>A recent study revealed that the N-terminal coiled-coil domain 
of Num1-the dynein cortical receptor-directly interacts with </p>

<p>dynein-dynactin complexes (Tang et al., 2012). If this region of 
Num1 (Num1 CC ; Fig. 1 A) is sufficient to activate dynein motil-
ity, we reasoned that its overexpression would result in (a) the 
depletion of dynein and dynactin from microtubule plus ends, 
and (b) an accumulation of dynein-dynactin at spindle pole 
bodies (SPBs), where microtubule minus ends are anchored 
(Fig. 1 B). We found this latter phenomenon to be an inherent 
property of dynein motility, because single-molecule motility 
experiments demonstrated that upon reaching the end of a mi-
crotubule, dynein pauses for several seconds before detaching, 
much longer than the dwell time of ∼0.1 s per step (Fig. S1 and 
Video 1). To test our hypothesis, we engineered yeast cells such 
that the galactose-inducible GAL1 promoter (GAL1p) was im-
mediately upstream of a truncated num1 CC allele (Fig. 1 C). Be-
cause Num1 CC is expressed from the native NUM1 locus, these 
cells do not possess a full-length Num1. Consequently, dynein 
and dynactin are excluded from the cell cortex and are unable to 
properly orient the spindle in these cells. 
In the absence of Num1 CC induction (by growth in 
glucose-containing media), we observed fluorescent foci of 
functional Dyn1-(dynein heavy chain) and Jnm1-3mCherry 
(p50 subunit of dynactin) fusions (Markus et al., 2011) at mi-
crotubule plus ends in 77.2% and 41.4% of cells, respectively 
(Fig. 1, D and E). In contrast, upon induction of Num1 CC over-
expression (by growth in galactose-containing media), the num-
ber of cells exhibiting Dyn1-and Jnm1-3mCherry plus end foci 
was reduced by approximately fivefold, to 14.8% and 8.1%, re-
spectively. Fluorescence intensity measurements revealed that 
those plus ends with Dyn1-and Jnm1-3mCherry foci had sig-
nificantly fewer molecules of each upon Num1 CC overexpres-
sion (Fig. 1 F). Coincident with the reduction in plus end dynein 
and dynactin, we also observed a four-to fivefold increase in 
the number of cells with Dyn1-and Jnm1-3mCherry foci at 
SPBs upon Num1 CC induction (also see Fig. 4 A, bottom). We 
observed similar results for Pac11-(dynein intermediate chain) 
and Dyn3-3mCherry (dynein light-intermediate chain; Fig. S2, 
A-E). In contrast, overexpression of Num1 CC had no effect on 
the extent of plus end localization of Bik1-3mCherry (CLIP170 
homologue), a protein that is required for the plus end target-
ing of dynein (Fig. S2, F and G; Sheeman et al., 2003). To de-
termine whether there is a cell cycle-regulated component to 
Num1 CC -mediated dynein relocalization, we categorized plus 
end and SPB localization frequencies into the following: G1, 
preanaphase, and anaphase (as determined by cell and spindle 
morphology; see Fig. S2 H). Although both G1 and preanaphase 
cells exhibited an equivalent extent of Num1 CC -mediated 
dynein relocalization, we found that anaphase cells were less 
susceptible to dynein plus end depletion, in spite of a significant 
enhancement in the prevalence of SPB localized dynein in these 
cells (Fig. S2 H). These findings are consistent with the higher 
frequency of dynein plus end localization noted in wild-type 
anaphase cells (Sheeman et al., 2003; Markus et al., 2009), and 
they further suggest that the plus end targeting mechanism is 
more robust at this point of the cell cycle. Collectively, our data 
indicate that overexpression of Num1 CC specifically depletes 
dynein-dynactin from microtubule plus ends. 
We next wanted to determine whether a Num1-dynein 
interaction was required for the plus end depletion phenotype. 
First, we introduced two point mutations within Num1 CC (L167E 
L170E; Num1 CC 
LL/EE ; Fig. 2 A) that disrupt its interaction with 
dynein-dynactin but have no effect on Num1 localization or its 
mitochondria cortical attachment function (Tang et al., 2012). </p>

<p>The Num1 cortical anchor activates dynein motility • lammers and markus </p>



<p>We found that overexpression of Num1 CC 
LL/EE (Fig. 1 C) had no 
effect on dynein plus end or SPB localization (Fig. 2, B and C), 
indicating that an intact dynein-dynactin binding surface within 
Num1 CC is required for plus end depletion. Second, we used two 
dynein motor domain variants (Dyn1 MOT OR and GST-Dyn1 MOT OR ) 
that are sufficient for association with microtubule plus ends but 
lack the N-terminal tail domain that is required for association 
with Num1 (Fig. 2 D; Markus et al., 2009). We found that Num1 CC 
overexpression had little effect on the frequency by which mo-
nomeric (nonmotile) Dyn1 MOT OR -3YFP or the dimeric (motile; 
Reck-Peterson et al., 2006) GST-Dyn1 MOT OR -3mCherry fragment 
was observed at plus ends or SPBs (Fig. 2, E and F). Collectively, 
these data indicate that Num1 CC -mediated plus end depletion of 
dynein requires an interaction between dynein and Num1 CC . </p>

<p>Several lines of evidence indicate that an intact dynein-
dynactin complex is required for interaction with Num1. Yeast 
dynactin deletion mutants exhibit a complete loss of cortical 
dynein and a higher than normal accumulation of dynein at 
microtubule plus ends (Lee et al., 2003, 2005). This latter ob-
servation is also noted in num1Δ mutants (Lee et al., 2003)  and is presumed to be attributable to an inability to offload 
dynein-dynactin to cortical Num1 receptor sites. Finally, a 
bead-immobilized recombinant Num1 CC fragment was suffi-
cient to isolate dynein from cell extracts but was unable to do 
so from extracts prepared from nip100Δ cells (homologue of 
human dynactin component p150Glued; Tang et al., 2012). To 
determine whether Num1 CC can deplete plus end dynein in the 
absence of dynactin, we overexpressed Num1 CC in nip100Δ </p>

<p>Figure 1. Overexpression of Num1 CC depletes dynein and dynactin from microtubule plus ends. (A) Schematic representation of Num1 and Num1 CC with 
domain structure indicated (CC1 and CC2, predicted coiled-coil domains; PH, plecktrin homology domain). (B) Diagram depicting experimental design 
(see text). (C) Western blot of GAL1p:num1 CC -13myc (wild-type or LL/EE mutant) cells grown in the absence or presence of galactose, as indicated, with 
loading control (anti-α-tubulin). (D) Representative images of GAL1p:num1 CC cells expressing mTurquoise2-Tub1 (α-tubulin) and either Dyn1-3mCherry 
(left) or Jnm1-3mCherry (right) used for quantitation in E and F. Cells were grown to mid-log phase in SD media supplemented with glucose (uninduced; 
−Num1 CC ) or galactose plus raffinose (induced; +Num1 CC ). Each image is a maximum-intensity projection of a 2-µm Z-stack of wide-field images. Arrows 
indicate plus end foci, and arrowheads indicate SPB foci. Bars, 2 µm. (E) The percentage of cells that exhibit plus end (red) or SPB (green) fluorescent foci 
is plotted for the strains shown in D. Plus end or SPB foci were identified in two-color movies and scored accordingly (see Materials and methods). Error 
bars represent the standard error of proportion (n ≥ 114 cells). (F) Box plot of fluorescence intensity values of plus end-associated Dyn1-or Jnm1-3mCherry 
foci (n ≥ 30 foci). Whiskers define the range of data, boxes encompass the 25th to 75th quartiles, the line depicts the median value, and the "x" depicts 
the mean value. See also Video 1 and Figs. S1, S2, and S3. </p>

<p>JCB • Volume 211 • NumBer 2 • 2015 </p>

<p>
cells. We found that Num1 CC overexpression reduced the fre-
quency of dynein plus end localization in nip100Δ cells to 
a lesser extent than in NIP100 cells (Fig. S3, A and B; 38% 
reduction in nip100Δ vs. 81% reduction in NIP100 cells; 
compare with Fig. 1 E); however, fluorescence intensity mea-
surements of plus end dynein revealed no significant differ-
ence (Fig. S3 C). These data suggest that the ability of dynein 
to interact with Num1 CC is compromised but not abolished in 
the absence of dynactin. 
We next asked whether plus end targeting of dynein 
is a requisite for Num1 CC -mediated accumulation of dynein 
at SPBs. To test this, we deleted either Pac1 or Bik1, both 
of which are required for dynein plus end targeting (Lee  et al., 2003; Sheeman et al., 2003). As expected, neither 
pac1Δ nor bik1Δ cells overexpressing Num1 CC exhibited 
plus end dynein foci; in addition, SPB localization of dynein 
was apparent in only a small number of cells in both mu-</p>

<p>tants, suggesting that the accumulation of dynein at SPBs 
requires a pool of dynein-dynactin at plus ends from which 
to draw (Fig. S3, D-G). </p>

<p>Microtubule binding by dynein is required 
for plus end depletion </p>

<p>If Num1 CC -mediated redistribution of dynein from plus ends 
to SPBs is a consequence of activated dynein motility, then 
we reasoned that a motility-incompetent dynein mutant would 
remain associated with plus ends in the presence of overex-
pressed Num1 CC . To test this, we generated a dynein mutant 
lacking its microtubule-binding domain (MTBD; Dyn1 ΔMT BD ; 
Fig. 3 A). Surprisingly, we found that in the absence of Num1 CC 
induction, Dyn1 ΔMT BD was capable of plus end binding (Fig. 3, 
B and C, top in B), indicating that dynein associates with plus 
ends independently of its MTBD, and thus likely through its 
interaction with Pac1 and Bik1. Furthermore, we found that the </p>

<p>Figure 2. Interaction between dynein and Num1 CC is required for plus end depletion. (A) Schematic representation of the Num1 CC 
LL/EE mutant. (B) Rep-
resentative images of GAL1p:num1 CC 
LL/EE and GAL1p:num1 CC cells expressing mTurquoise2-Tub1 and Dyn1-3mCherry used for quantitation in C. (C) 
The percentage of cells that exhibit plus end (red) or SPB (green) fluorescent foci is plotted for the strains overexpressing wild-type (WT) or mutant (LL/ 
EE) Num1 CC . Error bars represent the standard error of proportion (n ≥ 170 cells). (D) Diagram depicting dynein N-terminal (tail) and C-terminal (motor) 
domains and an artificially dimerized GST-Dyn1 MOT OR construct (see text). (E) Representative images of GAL1p:num1 CC cells expressing mTurquoise2-Tub1 
and Dyn1 MOT OR -3YFP used for quantitation in F. (F) The percentage of cells that exhibit plus end (red) or SPB (green) fluorescent Dyn1 MOT OR -3YFP or 
GST-Dyn1 MOT OR -3mCherry foci is plotted. Error bars represent the standard error of proportion (n ≥ 87 cells). All images are maximum-intensity projections 
of a 2-µm Z-stack of wide-field images. Arrows indicate plus end foci, and the arrowhead indicates the SPB focus. Bars, 2 µm. </p>

<p>The Num1 cortical anchor activates dynein motility • lammers and markus </p>



<p>extent of plus end localization of Dyn1 ΔMT BD was greater than 
wild-type Dyn1 (26% increase in frequency; 148% increase in 
intensity; P &lt; 0.0001), whereas its SPB localization was lower 
(Fig. 3, C and D; compare with Fig. 1, E and F). These data 
suggest that SPB localization of dynein in wild-type cells may 
be attributable to minus end-directed motility of active dynein 
motors. Consistent with our hypothesis, upon induction of 
Num1 CC overexpression, Dyn1 ΔMT BD localization to plus ends 
and SPBs remained unchanged (Fig. 3, C and D), suggesting 
that Num1 CC -mediated depletion of dynein from plus ends and 
accumulation at SPBs both require dynein motility. </p>

<p>Num1 CC has only a modest effect on 
dynein-dynactin interaction at plus ends </p>

<p>In contrast to yeast dynein, metazoan dynein exhibits mostly 
nonprocessive, diffusive motility in single-molecule assays 
(Miura et al., 2010; McKenney et al., 2014; Schlager et al.,  2014). A family of coiled-coil-containing adaptor proteins that 
recruit dynein and dynactin to various cellular sites was recently 
shown to be sufficient to activate processive single-molecule 
motility by stably linking dynein to dynactin (McKenney et  al., 2014; Schlager et al., 2014). Like these adaptor proteins, 
Num1 interacts only with intact dynein-dynactin complexes </p>

<p>Figure 3. The dynein MTBD is dis-
pensable for plus end targeting but is 
required for Num1 CC -mediated plus end de-
pletion. (A) Schematic representation of the 
Dyn1 ΔMT BD mutant. (B) Representative images of 
GAL1p:num1 CC cells expressing mTurquoise2-
Tub1 and Dyn1 ΔMT BD -3mCherry used for 
quantitation in C and D. (C) The percentage 
of cells that exhibit plus end (red) or SPB 
(green) Dyn1 ΔMT BD -3mCherry foci is plotted 
for cells shown in B. Error bars represent the 
standard error of proportion (n ≥ 126 cells). 
(D) Box plot of fluorescence intensity values 
of plus end-associated Dyn1 ΔMT BD -3mCherry 
(n ≥ 40 foci). (E and F) Representative im-
ages of GAL1p:num1 CC dyn1 ΔMT BD cells 
expressing mTurquoise2-Tub1 and either Jnm1-
(E) or Nip100-3mCherry (F) used for quan-
titation in G and H. (G) The percentage of 
dyn1 ΔMT BD cells that exhibit plus end or SPB 
Jnm1-or Nip100-3mCherry foci is plotted 
for GAL1p:num1 CC cells grown in glucose 
(−Num1 CC ) or galactose (+Num1 CC ; n ≥ 
100 cells). (H) Box plot of fluorescence inten-
sity values of plus end-associated Jnm1-or 
Nip100-3mCherry (n ≥ 56 foci). For all box 
plots, whiskers define the range of data, boxes 
encompass the 25th to 75th quartiles, the line 
depicts the median value, and the "x" depicts 
the mean value. All images are maximum-
intensity projections of a 2-µm Z-stack of wide-
field images. Arrows indicate plus end foci. 
Bars, 2 µm. See also Fig. S5. </p>

<p>JCB • Volume 211 • NumBer 2 • 2015 </p>

<p>
through its coiled-coil domain (Splinter et al., 2012; Tang et  al., 2012). Although dynein recruits dynactin to plus ends in a 
Num1-independent manner, dynactin is present at substoichio-
metric amounts relative to dynein (approximately three dynein 
to one dynactin; Markus et al., 2011). Thus, we reasoned that 
Num1 CC may activate dynein motility by enhancing the dynein-
dynactin interaction at plus ends. To test this, we assessed the 
extent by which Num1 CC affects dynein-mediated recruit-
ment of dynactin to plus ends. For these experiments, we used 
dyn1 ΔMT BD mutant cells, in which dynein remains associated at 
plus ends in spite of Num1 CC overexpression (see Fig. 3, B-D). 
We found that Num1 CC overexpression had no effect on the fre-
quency of observing plus end-localized dynactin (i.e., Jnm1-
or Nip100-3mCherry; Fig. 3, E-G); however, the fluorescence 
intensities of both Jnm1 and Nip100 at plus ends were mod-
estly, but significantly, increased (Fig. 3 H; 58.9% and 30.9%, 
respectively; P ≤ 0.0012), suggesting that Num1 CC may in fact 
enhance or stabilize the dynein-dynactin interaction. However, 
given the small apparent change in dynein-dynactin interaction 
at plus ends, and the observation that yeast dynein processivity 
enhancement by dynactin does not require additional factors in 
vitro (i.e., Num1; Kardon et al., 2009), it is unclear whether sta-
bilization of the dynein-dynactin interaction is the mechanism 
by which Num1 functions to activate dynein motility. For these 
reasons, we explored an alternative hypothesis. </p>

<p>Overexpression of Num1 CC reduces 
colocalization of dynein and Pac1 </p>

<p>Cells in which Pac1 is deleted exhibit a complete loss of plus 
end dynein (Lee et al., 2003; Markus et al., 2009), similar to our 
observations of cells overexpressing Num1 CC . We hypothesized 
that Num1 CC may deplete dynein from plus ends by interfering 
with dynein-Pac1 binding. To test this, we assessed localization 
of a functional Pac1-3mCherry fusion (Markus et al., 2011) in 
cells overexpressing Num1 CC . As we observed for dynein and 
dynactin, Pac1-3mCherry foci were depleted from microtubule 
plus ends upon Num1 CC overexpression (Fig. 4, A and B), con-
sistent with their codependence for plus end targeting (Markus  et al., 2011). However, in contrast to dynein and dynactin, the 
fraction of cells exhibiting Pac1-3mCherry foci at SPBs was 
reduced with respect to cells not expressing Num1 CC , suggest-
ing that dynein localizes at SPBs without Pac1 upon Num1 CC 
overexpression. This reduction in localization was not due to a 
decrease in Pac1 protein expression or stability, as indicated by 
immunoblotting (Fig. 4 D). Consistent with a Num1 CC -mediated 
reduction in the dynein-Pac1 interaction, we found that the frac-
tion of Dyn1-3YFP and Pac1-3mCherry foci that colocalized 
(either SPB or plus end) was reduced upon induction of Num1 CC 
(from 59.6% to 26.2%; Fig. 4 E), whereas the fraction of Dyn1-
3YFP foci alone (i.e., not colocalized with Pac1) increased 
(from 28.3% to 62.3%). These data suggest that overexpression 
of Num1 CC may disrupt plus end binding of dynein-dynactin by 
interfering with the dynein-Pac1 interaction. 
We next wanted to determine whether the reduction 
in Pac1-dynein colocalization was a direct consequence of 
Num1 CC -mediated Pac1-dynein dissociation, or whether it was 
a secondary consequence of dynein plus end depletion. To dis-
tinguish between these two possibilities, we ectopically targeted 
dynein to the plasma membrane using an exogenous pleckstrin 
homology (PH) domain, and we assessed the degree of colocal-
ization of Pac1 with cortical PH-Dyn1 in the presence of either 
Num1 CC 
LL/EE or Num1 CC . We found that the PH domain was </p>

<p>sufficient to target dynein (Fig. 4 F and Fig. S4 A) and dynactin 
(i.e., Jnm1; Fig. S4 B) to the cell cortex in cells lacking cortical 
Num1. Interestingly, we found a greater frequency of cortical 
PH-Dyn1-3mCherry foci in Num1 CC -overexpressing cells than 
in either Num1 CC 
LL/EE -overexpressing cells (45.5% vs. 13.9%, 
respectively) or NUM1 cells (21.3%; not depicted). In addition, 
we noted that Num1 CC -overexpressing cells exhibited larger 
cortical patches than either wild-type NUM1 or Num1 CC 
LL/EE -
overexpressing cells (Fig. S4 A; data not depicted). These data 
suggest that PH-Dyn1-Num1 CC complexes may be oligomeri-
zing at the cell cortex, which is consistent with the previously 
described role for the Num1 CC domain in the assembly of high-
er-order cortical patches (Tang et al., 2012). In cells overex-
pressing Num1 CC 
LL/EE , Pac1-3YFP colocalized with 65.3% 
of cortical PH-Dyn1-3mCherry foci; however, upon overex-
pression of Num1 CC , only 29.1% of PH-Dyn1-3mCherry foci 
contained Pac1-3YFP fluorescence (Fig. 4 G). Fluorescence in-
tensity measurements also revealed a significant reduction in the 
number of Pac1 molecules associated with cortical PH-dynein 
patches (Fig. 4 H). In contrast, we noted no significant change 
in either the frequency or intensity of colocalized dynactin (i.e., 
Jnm1; Fig. 4, I and J; and Fig. S4 B). These data support the no-
tion that Num1 CC disrupts the dynein-Pac1 interaction, thereby 
leading to the plus end depletion phenotype. </p>

<p>An enhanced Pac1 affinity mutant of 
dynein or Pac1 overexpression reduces 
the extent of Num1 CC -mediated plus end 
depletion of dynein </p>

<p>If a Num1 CC -mediated Pac1 unbinding event is the cause for 
plus end depletion of dynein-dynactin complexes, we reasoned 
that we could reduce the extent of Num1 CC -mediated dynein de-
pletion from microtubule plus ends by two different means: (a) 
enhancing the affinity of dynein for Pac1, or (b) overexpression 
of Pac1. To test the former, we used a yeast strain expressing a 
well-characterized, motility-competent dynein mutant (Dyn1 HL3 ) 
that exhibits higher affinity for Pac1 than wild-type dynein 
(Fig. 5 A; Markus and Lee, 2011). We predicted that Dyn1 HL3 
and Pac1 would be less susceptible to Num1 CC -mediated plus 
end depletion as a result of their higher affinity. Consistent with 
our hypothesis, induction of Num1 CC overexpression reduced 
the frequency of observing Dyn1 HL3 -3YFP and Pac1-3mCherry 
plus end foci by 40% and 22%, respectively (Fig. 5, B and C), 
much less than what we observed in wild-type DYN1 cells (re-
spective 81% and 67% reduction; compare with Fig. 1 E and 
Fig. 4 B). Fluorescence intensity measurements revealed no sig-
nificant change in the number of Dyn1 HL3 or Pac1 molecules at 
plus ends upon Num1 CC overexpression (Fig. 5 D). Thus, both 
Pac1 and Dyn1 HL3 are less susceptible to plus end depletion by 
Num1 CC overexpression in dyn1 HL3 cells. 
To test whether overexpression of Pac1 could rescue plus 
end depletion, we replaced the native PAC1 promoter with the 
GAL1 promoter, which is sufficient to induce &gt;10-fold higher 
Pac1 expression levels compared with wild-type cells (Markus  et al., 2011). To establish a baseline for Pac1 overexpression-
mediated enhancement of dynein plus end targeting, we first 
assessed dynein localization in cells overexpressing Pac1 and 
Num1 CC 
LL/EE , the latter of which has no discernible effect on 
dynein targeting (see Fig. 2, B and C). In these cells, we observed 
an increase in both frequency and mean fluorescence intensity 
of plus end dynein by 44% and 170%, respectively (Fig. 6, B 
and D), compared with cells overexpressing Num1 CC 
LL/EE and </p>

<p>The Num1 cortical anchor activates dynein motility • lammers and markus </p>



<p>expressing native levels of Pac1. In comparison, overexpression 
of Pac1 and wild-type Num1 CC reduced the frequency of plus 
end dynein by 47% (P &lt; 0.0001; compare GAL1p:PAC1 
with GAL1p:PAC1 num1 CC ), whereas the mean fluores-
cence intensity was not reduced significantly (30%; P = 0.1636; 
Fig. 6, B and D). These values are significantly less than the re-
spective 78% and 37% reduction in frequency and intensity we 
observed when Num1 CC alone was overexpressed (compared 
with Num1 CC 
LL/EE ; Fig. 6, C and E). Thus, Pac1 overexpres-
sion reduces the extent by which Num1 CC depletes dynein from 
microtubule plus ends. 
If Num1 CC depletes dynein from plus ends by inducing 
Pac1 release, then we reasoned that enhancing dynein plus end 
targeting by a Pac1-independent means would not be able to 
rescue plus end depletion to the same extent as Pac1 overex-
pression. To test this, we overexpressed Kip2, a kinesin-7 fam-
ily member that affects steady-state microtubule length (see 
Fig. 6 A, bottom) and plays a role in transporting dynein to 
microtubule plus ends (Carvalho et al., 2004; Markus et al.,  2009; Roberts et al., 2014). As with Pac1, we first established 
a baseline by which Kip2 overexpression enhances dynein plus 
end localization by imaging Dyn1-3mCherry in GAL1p:KIP2 </p>

<p>GAL1p:num1 CC 
LL/EE cells. Consistent with a role for Kip2 in 
transporting dynein away from minus ends and toward plus 
ends, overexpression of Kip2 enhanced the frequency of dynein 
plus end targeting by 19% and reduced the frequency of SPB 
targeting by 83% (P = 0.0019; Fig. 6 B). Fluorescence intensity 
measurements revealed a robust 147% increase in the number 
of dynein molecules per plus end (Fig. 6 D). When both Kip2 
and wild-type Num1 CC were overexpressed, the frequency and 
mean fluorescence intensity of plus end dynein was reduced by 
59% (P &lt; 0.0001) and 63% (P = 0.0012), respectively, compared 
with GAL1p:KIP2 GAL1p:num1 CC 
LL/EE cells (Fig. 6, B-E). 
The extent by which Kip2 overexpression reduces Num1 CC -
mediated plus end dynein depletion is therefore less than that of 
Pac1. Collectively, these data are consistent with our hypothe-
sis, and they suggest that Num1 CC and Pac1 are competing for 
binding to dynein-dynactin complexes. It is interesting to note 
that Pac1 binds to dynein within the C-terminal motor domain 
(Reck-Peterson et al., 2006; Markus et al., 2009; Huang et al.,  2012; Toropova et al., 2014), whereas Num1 associates with 
dynein via the N-terminal tail domain (Markus et al., 2009). 
Thus, interference with Dyn1-Pac1 binding by Num1 CC likely 
occurs by an allosteric mechanism. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Overexpression of Num1 CC de-
pletes Pac1 from plus ends and disrupts 
dynein-Pac1 interaction. (A) Representative im-
ages of GAL1p:num1 CC cells expressing mTur-
quoise2-Tub1, Pac1-3mCherry, and Dyn1-3YFP 
used for quantitation in B, C, and E. The arrow 
indicates the plus end focus, and arrowheads 
indicate SPB foci. (B) The percentage of cells 
that exhibit plus end (red) or SPB (green) fluo-
rescent Pac1-3mCherry foci is plotted for the 
cells shown in A. Error bars represent the stan-
dard error of proportion (n ≥ 122 cells). (C) 
Box plot of fluorescence intensity values of plus 
end-associated Pac1-3mCherry (n ≥ 26 foci). 
(D) Western blot of Pac1-13myc-expressing 
GAL1p:num1 CC or GAL1p:num1 CC 
LL/EE cells 
(as indicated) grown in galactose-containing 
media with loading control (anti-α-tubulin). (E) 
The extent of Pac1-3mCherry and Dyn1-3YFP 
colocalization is plotted for the indicated cells 
(n ≥ 61 fluorescent foci). (F) Representative 
images of GAL1p:PH-DYN1-3mCherry cells 
expressing Pac1-3YFP and either Num1 CC 
or Num1 CC 
LL/EE . Arrowheads indicate corti-
cal foci. (G and I) The percentage of cortical 
PH-Dyn1-3mCherry foci that colocalize with ei-
ther Pac1-3YFP (n ≥ 49 foci; G) or Jnm1-3YFP 
(n ≥ 55 foci; I) is plotted for cells expressing 
either Num1 CC or Num1 CC 
LL/EE . (H and J) Box 
plot of fluorescence intensity values for either 
cortical Pac1-3YFP (n ≥ 25 foci; H) or Jnm1-
3YFP foci (n ≥ 44 foci; one outlier was omitted 
from the plot for display purposes only; J). For 
all box plots, the whiskers define the range of 
data, boxes encompass the 25th to 75th quar-
tiles, the line depicts the median value, and 
the "x" depicts the mean value. All images 
are maximum-intensity projections of a 2-µm 
Z-stack of wide-field images. Bars, 2 µm. See 
also Fig. S4. WT, wild type. </p>

<p>JCB • Volume 211 • NumBer 2 • 2015 </p>

<p>
Num1 CC colocalizes with dynein-dynactin </p>

<p>Previous data indicate that Num1 CC interacts with dynein at 
SPBs and is found in the cytoplasm as bright foci (presumably 
aggregates; see Fig. S5, A and B, open arrows and cytoplasm, 
respectively; Tang et al., 2012). We found that localization of 
Num1 CC to the SPB is largely dependent on dynein, and more 
specifically, the MTBD of dynein (Fig. S5, A and B). Further-
more, cells in which dynein plus end targeting is restored-by 
overexpression of Pac1, deletion of the dynein MTBD, or use 
of Dyn1 HL3 -exhibit Num1 CC at plus ends, albeit at a low fre-
quency (Fig. S5, A-C). These data indicate that Num1 CC can 
bind plus end dynein (as well as the Dyn1 ΔMT BD and Dyn1 HL3 
mutants) and suggest that Num1 and Pac1 binding to dynein is 
not entirely mutually exclusive. The latter is consistent with the 
observation that Dyn1 HL3 -Pac1 complexes can offload together 
to Num1 cortical sites (Markus and Lee, 2011). </p>

<p>Direct observation of minus end-directed 
motion of dynein along astral microtubules </p>

<p>In budding yeast, dynein is targeted to microtubule plus ends 
by two distinct mechanisms: (a) direct recruitment from the </p>

<p>cytoplasm, and (b) Kip2-mediated plus end-directed transport 
along astral microtubules (Carvalho et al., 2004; Markus et  al., 2009). Evidence of the latter is apparent by the movement 
of fluorescent dynein speckles along astral microtubules to-
ward plus ends (Fig. 7 A and Video 2; Markus et al., 2009). In 
budding yeast, dynein is never observed moving in the oppo-
site direction-toward the minus ends of astral microtubules. 
Minus end-directed activity is only apparent when cortically 
anchored dynein motors move the spindle through interactions 
with astral microtubules. If depletion of dynein-dynactin from 
microtubule plus ends is a consequence of these motors being 
switched "on," then we reasoned that cells overexpressing 
Num1 CC would exhibit dynein molecules moving in a directed 
manner toward the minus ends of astral microtubules, as was 
recently observed in fission yeast expressing a Mcp5 ΔPH (Num1 
homologue) fragment (Ananthanarayanan et al., 2013). 
In uninduced cells (i.e., not expressing any Num1 CC ) 
or in those induced to express Num1 CC 
LL/EE , only plus end-
directed motility of dynein (or dynein ΔMT BD ) molecules was 
ever observed (Fig. 7 A and Video 2). We were unable to 
observe minus end-directed motility of dynein molecules </p>

<p>Figure 5. Dyn1 HL3 is less susceptible to Num1 CC -mediated plus end depletion. (A) Diagram depicting the Dyn1 HL3 high Pac1 affinity mutant, in which a 
helical linker has been inserted between the dynein tail and motor domains (Markus and Lee, 2011). (B) Representative images of GAL1p:num1 CC cells 
expressing mTurquoise2-Tub1 and either Dyn1 HL3 -3YFP (left) or Dyn1 HL3 and Pac1-3mCherry (right) used for quantitation in C and D. Each image is a 
maximum-intensity projection of a 2-µm Z-stack of wide-field images. Arrows indicate plus end foci, and arrowheads indicate SPB foci. Bars, 2 µm. (C) The 
percentage of cells that exhibit plus end (red) or SPB (green) fluorescent Dyn1 HL3 -3YFP (left) or Pac1-3mCherry (right) foci is plotted for the cells shown in 
B. Error bars represent the standard error of proportion (n ≥ 119 cells). (D) Box plot of fluorescence intensity values of plus end-associated Dyn1 HL3 -3YFP 
or Pac1-3mCherry (n ≥ 33 foci). Whiskers define the range of data, boxes encompass the 25th to 75th quartiles, the line depicts the median value, and 
the "x" depicts the mean value. See also Fig. S5. </p>

<p>The Num1 cortical anchor activates dynein motility • lammers and markus </p>



<p>in cells overexpressing Num1 CC , likely because of the ro-
bust depletion of dynein from microtubule plus ends in these 
cells. Thus, we chose to focus on cells in which Num1 CC -
mediated depletion of dynein plus end binding was partially 
restored: GAL1p:KIP2 and GAL1p:PAC1 cells. Strikingly, we 
observed numerous instances of minus end-directed motility 
of dynein in cells overexpressing Kip2 or Pac1 in addition to 
Num1 CC (Fig. 7, B and C; Fig. S5 D; Video 3; and Video 4). 
The mean velocity of minus end-directed dynein molecules 
along astral microtubules in GAL1p:KIP2 cells was slightly 
higher than that in GAL1p:PAC1 cells (55.3 nm/s, n = 22; 
vs. 41.7 nm/s, n = 9; Fig. 7 D); however, the values from 
both strains were very similar to the velocity of single mol-
ecules of purified dynein (∼70-100 nm/s; Reck-Peterson  et al., 2006; Markus and Lee, 2011; Huang et al., 2012)  and dynein-mediated spindle movements in this organism </p>

<p>(41 nm/s; Markus et al., 2011). Thus, overexpression of 
Num1 CC depletes dynein from microtubule plus ends by acti-
vating its minus end-directed motility. 
Although we were able to see Num1 CC -mediated minus 
end motility of dynactin (Jnm1-3YFP) in GAL1p:KIP2 cells 
(Fig. 7 B, iii), we were unable to observe examples of either 
Pac1 or Num1 CC moving toward the minus ends. The reason 
for the latter is unclear but may be a result of disengagement of 
Num1 CC from dynein subsequent to activation. Taken together 
with our other observations (i.e., the lack of Pac1 accumulation 
at SPBs in Num1 CC -overexpressing cells, the reduced colocal-
ization of Dyn1 and Pac1 in DYN1 and PH-DYN1 cells, and the 
ability of Pac1 overexpression to rescue Dyn1 plus end target-
ing), the apparent lack of minus end-directed Pac1 molecules 
further suggests that Num1 CC activates plus end dynein by re-
lieving Pac1-mediated inhibition. </p>

<p>Figure 6. Overexpression of Pac1 reduces 
the extent by which Num1 CC depletes plus end 
dynein. (A) Representative images of cells ex-
pressing mTurquoise2-Tub1, Dyn1-3mCherry, 
either Num1 CC or Num1 CC 
LL/EE , and either 
overexpressing Pac1 or Kip2, as indicated. 
Because of the distorted spindle phenotype 
in Kip2-overexpressing cells, Spc110-Venus 
was used to mark SPBs. All cells were grown 
in galactose-containing media to induce 
overexpression of Pac1, Kip2, Num1 CC , or 
Num1 CC 
LL/EE , as indicated. Each image is a 
maximum-intensity projection of a 2-µm Z-stack 
of wide-field images. For the top row (Pac1 
overexpressed), arrows indicate plus end foci, 
and arrowheads indicate SPB foci. For the 
bottom row (Kip2 overexpressed), arrows indi-
cate plus ends with or without foci. Bars, 2 µm. 
(B) The percentage of cells that exhibit plus end 
(red) or SPB (green) Dyn1-3mCherry foci is 
plotted for cells shown in A and for cells shown 
in Figs. 1 D and 2 B. Error bars represent the 
standard error of proportion (n ≥ 113 cells). 
(C) Extent by which Num1 CC overexpression 
reduced the frequency of observing dynein 
plus end foci compared with the respective 
PAC1 KIP2 isogenic parent strain overexpress-
ing Num1 CC 
LL/EE . Asterisks indicate a statisti-
cally significant percent decrease (see B for P 
values). (D) Box plot of fluorescence intensity 
values of plus end-associated Dyn1-3mCherry 
(n ≥ 31 foci). Whiskers define the range of 
data, boxes encompass the 25th to 75th quar-
tiles, the line depicts the median value, and 
the "x" depicts the mean value. (E) Extent by 
which Num1 CC overexpression reduced the 
number of dynein molecules (i.e., fluorescence 
intensity) at plus ends compared with the 
isogenic PAC1 KIP2 parent strain overexpress-
ing Num1 CC 
LL/EE . Asterisks indicate a statisti-
cally significant percent decrease (see D for P 
values). See also Fig. S5. WT, wild type. </p>

<p>JCB • Volume 211 • NumBer 2 • 2015 </p>

<p>
Discussion </p>

<p>When purified from various sources, including budding yeast 
and animal tissue, dynein motors are active as apparent from 
ATPase and microtubule gliding assays. Yeast dynein requires no 
additional factors for processive single-molecule motility (Reck- Peterson et al., 2006), whereas dynein isolated from animal tissue 
requires a combination of dynactin and various adaptor proteins 
that link dynein to dynactin (McKenney et al., 2014; Schlager  et al., 2014). This latter phenomenon helps explain how dynein 
activity is recruited to different vesicular or organellar com-
partments in animal cells, and thus how dynein activity is regu-
lated with spatial precision. For instance, one of these adaptors, 
BicD2, binds to Rab6 on various vesicular cargoes, and thereby 
recruits dynein-dynactin complexes, which allows for minus 
end-directed movements of these vesicular cargoes (Matanis et  al., 2002). Although mechanistically distinct, we have identi-
fied a similar mechanism at play in budding yeast. Specifically, 
Num1-mediated recruitment of dynein-dynactin complexes to 
the cell cortex is sufficient to (a) anchor dynein-dynactin com-
plexes at their site of activity, and (b) activate dynein for its 
spindle orientation function. Unlike animal cells, however, asso-
ciation with dynactin is not sufficient to activate dynein motility 
in yeast cells. Rather, our studies indicate that a Num1-mediated 
Pac1 dissociation event is responsible for switching dynein from 
being off at microtubule plus ends to on at the cell cortex. 
Our results revealed a small but significant Num1 CC -
mediated enhancement in the apparent dynein-dynactin inter-</p>

<p>action at plus ends (see Fig. 3 H). Although this effect appears 
to be minor compared with that of Num1 CC on the dynein-Pac1 
interaction, it is possible that, like the human adaptor proteins 
(e.g., BicD2 and Spindly), Num1 also plays a role in stabilizing 
the dynein-dynactin complex. If so, it may be that Num1 may 
further promote dynactin-mediated processivity enhancement 
of dynein in a manner reflective of the human adaptor proteins 
(McKenney et al., 2014; Schlager et al., 2014). Future studies 
will be needed to directly test this in a reconstituted system. 
Although dynactin does not activate yeast dynein motility, 
per se, it is interesting to note that dynein-dynactin binding is a 
rate-limiting step during the dynein offloading process. Quan-
titative fluorescence microscopy revealed a threefold excess of 
dynein relative to dynein-dynactin complexes at microtubule 
plus ends (Markus et al., 2011). Given the reliance of dynein 
on dynactin for offloading to Num1 receptor sites (Lee et al.,  2003), the limiting nature of dynactin at plus ends effectively 
restricts dynein pathway activity by limiting the number of 
cortical dynein-dynactin complexes. Increasing the number of 
intact dynein-dynactin complexes at plus ends by deletion of 
She1, which regulates their interaction in vivo (Woodruff et al.,  2009), results in an increased number of cortical dynein-dyn-
actin complexes, as well as enhanced dynein pathway activity 
(Markus et al., 2011). Thus, through mechanistically distinct 
processes, dynactin effectively activates dynein-mediated pro-
cesses both in animal and yeast cells. 
It is well established that Pac1 plays a central role in tar-
geting dynein-dynactin to microtubule plus ends in yeast (Lee </p>

<p>Figure 7. Direct observation of Num1 CC -
mediated minus end motility of dynein and 
dynactin. (A) Example kymographs of plus 
end-directed motility of dynein molecules 
along astral microtubules observed in unin-
duced GAL1p:num1 CC cells (left; -Num1 CC ) or 
in cells overexpressing Num1 CC 
LL/EE and Kip2 
(right). (B and C) Example kymographs depict-
ing minus end-directed motility of dynein or 
dynactin (i.e., Jnm1) along astral microtubules 
in cells overexpressing Num1 CC and either 
Kip2 (B) or Pac1 (C). Kymographs were gen-
erated from time-lapse images acquired using 
highly inclined and laminated optical sheet mi-
croscopy (see Materials and methods). Bars: 
(vertical) 1 min; (horizontal) 1 µm. (D) Velocity 
values for minus end-directed dynein runs ob-
served in either Pac1-or Kip2-overexpressing 
cells. See also Fig. S5 and Videos 2 and 3. </p>

<p>The Num1 cortical anchor activates dynein motility • lammers and markus </p>



<p>et al., 2003). Given the ability of Pac1 to reduce dynein motility 
in vitro (Markus and Lee, 2011; Huang et al., 2012), it has been 
postulated that Pac1 may hold dynein at plus ends in part by 
preventing its minus end-directed motility. At some point after 
or concomitant with dynein offloading, Pac1 dissociates from 
dynein and is never observed at cortical Num1 sites in wild-type 
cells (Lee et al., 2003). Given the observations presented here, 
we hypothesize that Num1 binding to dynein-dynactin triggers 
the dissociation of Pac1 from dynein. The fact that Dyn1 ΔMT BD 
is insensitive to Num1 CC overexpression suggests that microtu-
bule binding by dynein is a requisite for Pac1 dissociation. This 
suggests a mechanism whereby Num1 binding to the dynein tail 
domain (Markus et al., 2009) communicates allosteric changes 
to the motor head that, after microtubule binding, induce Pac1 
dissociation from its binding site (at the junction between AAA3 
and AAA4; Toropova et al., 2014) and consequently permit 
minus end-directed motility (see Fig. 8). The requisite micro-
tubule binding by dynein for Num1 CC -mediated Pac1 dissocia-
tion likely explains the plus end colocalization of Dyn1 ΔMT BD 
with Num1 CC (Fig. S5, A-C) and Pac1 (not depicted). 
It is interesting to note the apparent discrepancies be-
tween the requirements for plus end binding of yeast and human 
dynein. In budding yeast, the dynein motor domain, Pac1, and 
Bik1 are absolutely essential (Lee et al., 2003; Sheeman et al.,  2003; Markus et al., 2009), but dynactin is dispensable for this 
process (Lee et al., 2003). However, recent in vitro reconsti-
tution experiments with human dynein revealed a distinct plus 
end binding complex that requires EB1, the p150Glued subunit 
of dynactin, and the full-length dynein complex (i.e., the motor 
domain is not sufficient; Duellberg et al., 2014). These latter 
observations, which did not describe any minus end-directed 
dynein motility, suggest that dynein and dynactin (or at least 
p150Glued) can interact at plus ends in the absence of the re-
cently characterized adaptor proteins (e.g., Hook3, Spindly, and 
BicD2; McKenney et al., 2014; Schlager et al., 2014) and further 
suggest that their interaction is not sufficient for dynein motility. </p>

<p>Our observation that the MTBD of dynein is dispensable 
for plus end targeting was surprising and changes our under-
standing by which dynein recognizes and binds to microtubule 
plus ends. In light of this observation, we propose that dynein 
does not directly contact the plus end; rather, dynein associates 
with plus ends indirectly through its interactions with Pac1 and 
Bik1 (see Fig. 1 B). Evidence indicates that Pac1 enables dynein 
tip tracking in part by linking it to the plus end binding protein 
Bik1 (Sheeman et al., 2003; Roberts et al., 2014). Thus, the 
ability of Pac1 (and LIS1) to permit prolonged encounters be-
tween dynein and microtubules (McKenney et al., 2010; Huang  et al., 2012) is likely unrelated to plus end binding by dynein in 
this organism. However, it is conceivable that by maintaining 
dynein in an off state at plus ends, Pac1 may prevent minus end 
motility of dynein motors that are in very close proximity to 
the microtubule. Upon binding of Num1 CC , dynein may pivot 
(likely in a stochastic manner) such that it may contact the plus 
end directly through its MTBD, subsequently release Pac1, and 
then walk toward the minus end. An analogous situation may 
take place in wild-type cells: after offloading to Num1 receptor 
sites at the cortex, dynein is well positioned to contact the mi-
crotubule to initiate spindle movements, which in turn may trig-
ger Pac1 dissociation (Fig. 8). Recent structural studies support 
such a possibility: upon microtubule binding, conformational 
changes within the MTBD affect corresponding changes within 
the motor ring (Schmidt, 2015; Uchimura et al., 2015). These 
changes, which are propagated by the antiparallel coiled-coil 
that lead from the MTBD to the motor ring (via AAA4), could 
presumably affect Pac1 binding at the AAA3-AAA4 junction 
(see Fig. 8; Toropova et al., 2014). 
Consistent with Num1 affecting the dynein-Pac1 inter-
action, the dynein mutant with higher than normal affinity for 
Pac1 (Dyn1 HL3 ) was much less susceptible to Num1 CC -mediated 
plus end depletion. It is unclear why Dyn1 HL3 exhibits higher 
affinity for Pac1. This mutant was engineered such that a he-
lical linker was inserted between the tail and motor domains </p>

<p>Figure 8. Model for Num1-mediated acti-
vation of dynein-mediated spindle position-
ing. Our data suggest that at the moment of 
offloading (step 1), contact between dynein-
dynactin and cortical Num1 triggers a cas-
cade of events that ultimately leads to Pac1 
dissociation (step 3); however, the MTBD (dele-
tion of which interrupts this process) is required 
to make contact with the microtubule to initiate 
Pac1 dissociation (step 2). </p>

<p>JCB • Volume 211 • NumBer 2 • 2015 </p>

<p>
(Markus and Lee, 2011). In the context of the tertiary structure 
of the dynein motor, this region lies in close proximity to the 
Pac1 binding site (between AAA3 and AAA4; see Fig. 5 A). 
Taken together with an apparent enhanced affinity of a tail-less 
dynein construct (motor domain only) for Pac1 (Reck-Peterson  et al., 2006; Markus et al., 2009), it stands to reason that the tail 
domain plays a negative regulatory role in affecting Pac1 bind-
ing. Thus, whatever allosteric conformational change Num1 CC -
dynein tail binding induces is likely interrupted by insertion of 
the helical HL3 linker. 
The nature of the Num1 CC -dynein-dynactin interaction is 
currently unknown; however, a recent structural study revealed 
how human dynein-dynactin interacts with the coiled-coil-
containing adaptor protein BicD2 (Urnavicius et al., 2015). 
Given the importance of the Num1 coiled-coil domain in the 
dynein-dynactin interaction, and the observation that Num1 
(like BicD2) only interacts with intact dynein-dynactin com-
plexes (Splinter et al., 2012), it may be that Num1 exhibits a 
similar mode of binding (i.e., direct contact with the dynein tail 
domain, and the Arp1 filament). Future high-resolution struc-
tural studies of the dynein tail domain within the context of the 
Num1 CC -dynein-dynactin complex will be necessary to un-
derstand the network of interactions that define this enormous 
protein complex, as well as how the tail domain may possibly 
affect Pac1-motor domain binding. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Media and strain construction </p>

<p>All strains are derived from YEF473A (Bi and Pringle, 1996) and 
are listed in Table S1. We transformed yeast strains using the lith-
ium acetate method (Knop et al., 1999). Strains carrying null muta-
tions or fluorescently tagged components were constructed by PCR 
product-mediated transformation (Longtine et al., 1998) or by mating 
followed by tetrad dissection. Strains expressing mTurquoise2-Tub1 
were generated as described (Markus et al., 2015). Transformants 
were clonally purified by streaking to individual colonies on selective 
media. Proper tagging was confirmed by PCR and, in some cases, 
sequencing. Yeast synthetic defined (SD) media were obtained from 
Sunrise Science Products. 
To generate a yeast strain with point mutations in Num1 CC 
(L167E L170E; Fig. 2 A), we used the site-specific genomic muta-
genesis approach (Gray et al., 2004). In brief, after integration of the 
URA3 cassette into the num1 CC locus (replacing nucleotides 499-510, 
corresponding to amino acids L167-L170), a PCR product ampli-
fied from pSM37 (see Plasmid construction) containing the desired 
nucleotide substitutions was transformed into the URA3-integrated 
strain and subsequently selected on 5-fluoroorotic acid-containing 
plates. 5-Fluoroorotic acid-resistant colonies were selected and 
confirmed by colony PCR and sequencing of the genomic DNA re-
gion. A similar method was used to delete the MTBD (residues 
3,102-3,225) from DYN1. 
To generate a yeast strain expressing the GAL1p:PH-DYN1 
allele, a cassette containing KAN R ::GAL1p:PH was amplified from 
pFA6a-kanMX6-pGAL1-PH (see Plasmid construction) and used for 
integration immediately upstream of the DYN1-3mCherry locus. </p>

<p>Plasmid construction </p>

<p>Using isothermal assembly (Gibson et al., 2009), we generated a plas-
mid in which the L167E L170E point mutations were engineered into a 
plasmid encoding Num1 CC(95-303) -PCN-S-TEV-ZZ (pBSG02; Tang et al.,   2012). In brief, primers were used to separately amplify the N-terminal 
(nucleotides 283-498, corresponding to amino acids 95-166) and 
C-terminal (nucleotides 511-909, corresponding to amino acids 171-
303) portions of Num1 CC , such that the desired nucleotide substitutions 
were included in the reverse primer for the N-terminal portion and the 
forward primer for the C-terminal portion. After amplification, the 3′ 
and 5′ ends of the PCR products corresponding to the N-and C-termi-
nal regions, respectively, contained 20 nucleotides of sequence identity 
with each other, whereas the 5′ and 3′ ends of the N-and C-terminal re-
gions, respectively, contained 20 nucleotides of sequence identity with 
the NcoI-and NotI-digested pBSG02 vector. After digesting pBSG02 
with NcoI and NotI (to excise Num1 CC(95-303) wild type), the gel-
purified PCR products and digested vector were assembled in vitro as 
described (Gibson et al., 2009). Proper assembly was verified by re-
striction digest and DNA sequencing and resulted in pSM37 (encoding 
Num1 CC(95-303)  LL/EE -PCN-S-TEV-ZZ). 
To generate a plasmid with which to N-terminally tag Dyn1 with 
a PH domain, the PH domain of Num1 (amino acids 2,563-2,692) was 
amplified using a forward primer flanked with an XmaI site and a re-
verse primer flanked with a SalI site. The PCR product was digested 
with XmaI and SalI and ligated into pFA6a-kanMX6-PGAL1 (Longtine  et al., 1998) digested similarly, yielding pFA6a-kanMX6-PGAL1-PH. </p>

<p>Image acquisition, analysis, and dynein motility assay </p>

<p>Yeast cultures were imaged after growth at 30°C to mid-log phase in 
synthetic defined media supplemented with either 2% glucose (SD 
plus glucose) or 2% galactose plus 2% raffinose (SD plus galactose/ 
raffinose; the latter for induction of Num1 CC , Pac1, or Kip2, as in-
dicated). To assess the effects of Num1 CC on localization of dynein 
pathway components, GAL1p:num1 CC cells were induced in SD plus 
galactose/raffinose for 6 h before mounting cells for fluorescence mi-
croscopy. For wide-field fluorescence microscopy, yeast cells were 
imaged on an agarose pad containing 50 mM potassium phosphate 
buffer, pH 7, and images were collected at room temperature using a 
1.49 NA 100× objective on a Ti-E inverted microscope equipped with a 
Ti-S-E motorized stage (Nikon), piezo Z-control (Physik Instrumente), 
a SOLA SM II LE LED light engine (Lumencor), a motorized filter 
cube turret, and an iXon X3 DU897 cooled EM-CCD camera (Andor). 
The microscope system was controlled by <rs type="software">NIS-Elements</rs> software 
(Nikon). A step size of 1 µm was used to acquire 2-µm-thick Z-stack 
images. Sputtered/ET filter cube sets (Chroma Technology) were used 
for imaging mTurquoise2 (49001), GFP (49002), YFP (49003), and 
mCherry (49008) fluorescence. 
Image analysis was performed using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software (National 
Institutes of Health; kymographs in Fig. 7 were generated with the 
MultipleKymograph plugin). Plus end and SPB foci were identified 
in two (or three) color movies and scored accordingly. Specifically, 
plus end molecules were recognized as those foci that localized to the 
distal tips of dynamic microtubules (identified via mTurquoise2-Tub1 
imaging), whereas SPB molecules were recognized as those foci that 
localized to one of the spindle poles. Cortical molecules (e.g., in 
PH-Dyn1-expressing cells) were identified as those foci not associ-
ated with an astral microtubule plus end that remained stationary at 
the cell cortex for at least three frames. Two data sets were considered 
statistically significant if a Student's t test (assuming unequal vari-
ance) returned a p-value &lt; 0.05. 
For highly inclined and laminated optical sheet microscopy 
(Tokunaga et al., 2008), samples were prepared and imaged as above, 
except 488-and 561-nm lasers were used to excite YFP and mCherry, 
respectively. The laser illumination angle was adjusted individually for 
each sample to achieve the maximum signal-to-noise ratio. Emission 
filters were 525/50 nm for YFP and 600/50 for mCherry. </p>

<p>The Num1 cortical anchor activates dynein motility • lammers and markus </p>



<p>Purification of TAP (S tag-ZZ)-Dyn1-EGFP and the single-
molecule motility assay (Fig. S1 and Video 1) were performed as previ-
ously described (Markus and Lee, 2011; Markus et al., 2012). </p>

<p>Cell lysis and immunoblotting </p>

<p>For Western blotting, yeast cultures were grown at 30°C in 3 ml of 
either SD plus glucose or SD plus galactose/raffinose and harvested. 
Equal numbers of cells were pelleted and resuspended in 0.2 ml of 
0.1 M NaOH and incubated for 5 min at room temperature as described 
(Kushnirov, 2000). After centrifugation, the resulting cell pellet was 
resuspended in sample buffer and heated to ∼100°C for 3 min. Lysates 
were separated on a 10% SDS polyacrylamide gel and electroblotted 
to PVDF in 25 mM Tris and 192 mM glycine supplemented with 
0.05% SDS and 10% methanol for 30 min. Rabbit anti-c-Myc poly-
clonal (GenScript) or anti-α-tubulin (Applied Biological Materials, 
Inc.) monoclonal antibodies and HRP-conjugated goat anti-rabbit or 
anti-mouse antibody (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories) were 
used at 1:1,000, 1:1,000, 1:3,000, or 1:3,000, respectively. The che-
miluminescence signal was acquired on an ImageQuant LAS 500 gel 
documentation system. Immunoblots were exposed without saturat-
ing the camera's pixels. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material </p>

<p>Fig. S1 depicts the inherent ability of dynein to accumulate at micro-
tubule minus ends in vitro. Fig. S2 shows that Num1 CC overexpression 
depletes dynein light-intermediate (Dyn3) and intermediate (Pac11) 
chains, but not Bik1 from plus ends, and it also shows the effect of 
Num1 CC overexpression on Dyn1 localization throughout the cell cycle. 
Fig. S3 shows the role of dynactin (Nip100), Pac1, and Bik1 in the 
Num1 CC -mediated plus end depletion phenotype. Fig. S4 shows addi-
tional examples of PH-dynein localization as well as its colocalization 
with dynactin (Jnm1). Fig. S5 shows the localization of Num1 CC -EGFP 
in various mutant backgrounds and also shows additional examples of 
the minus end-directed motility of Dyn1 in Num1 CC -overexpressing 
cells. Video 1 shows a representative in vitro dynein single-molecule 
assay. Video 2 shows plus end-directed molecules of dynein in 
Kip2-and Num1 CC 
LL/EE -overexpressing cells, whereas Video 3 and 
Video 4 show minus end-directed molecules of dynein in Kip2-and 
Num1 CC -overexpressing cells. Table S1 shows strains used in this 
study. Online supplemental material is available at http://www.jcb.org/ 
cgi/content/full/jcb.201506119/DC1. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Dr. Randa Mahgoub for help with construction of the PH-
dynein yeast strains, Dr. Jennifer DeLuca for reagents and critical read-
ing of the manuscript, and members of Dr. DeLuca's laboratory for 
valuable discussions throughout this study. </p>

<p>This work was supported by startup funds provided from Colorado 
State University to S.M. Markus. </p>

<p>The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Submitted: 24 June 2015 
Accepted: 2 September 2015 </p>



<p>JCB • Volume 211 • NumBer 2 • 2015 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>