<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4162729" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Introduction: There is scant literature regarding the optimal resident physician staffing model of 
academic emergency departments (ED) that maximizes learning opportunities. A department of 
emergency medicine at a large inner-city academic hospital initiated a team-based staffing model. 
Its pre-interventional staffing model consisted of residents and attending physicians being separately 
assigned patients, resulting in residents working with two different faculty providers in the same shift. 
This study aimed to determine if the post-interventional team-based system, in which residents were 
paired with a single attending on each shift, would result in improved residents' learning and clinical 
experiences as manifested by resident evaluations and the number of patients seen. </p>

<p>Methods: This retrospective before-and-after study at an academic ED with an annual volume of 
52,000 patients examined the mean differences in five-point Likert-scale evaluations completed 
by residents assessing their ED rotation experiences in both the original and team-based staffing 
models. The residents were queried on their perceptions of feeling part of the team, decision-making 
autonomy, clinical experience, amount of supervision, quality of teaching, and overall rotational 
experience. We also analyzed the number of patients seen per hour by residents. Paired sample 
t-tests were performed. Residents who were in the program in the year preceding and proceeding 
the intervention were eligible for inclusion. </p>

<p>Results: 34 of 38 eligible residents were included (4 excluded for lack of evaluations in either 
the pre-or post-intervention period). There was a statistically significant improvement in resident 
perception of the quality and amount of teaching, 4.03 to 4.27 (mean difference=0.24, p=0.03). There 
were non-statistically significant trends toward improved mean scores for all other queries. Residents 
also saw more patients following the initiation of the team-based model, 1.24 to 1.56 patients per 
hour (mean difference=0.32, p=0.0005). </p>

<p>Conclusion: Adopting a team-based physician staffing model is associated with improved resident 
perceptions of quality and amount of teaching. Residents also experience a greater number of 
patient evaluations in a team-based model. [West J Emerg Med. 2014;15(6):682-686] </p>

<p>University of Maryland Baltimore County, Department of Emergency Health Services, 
Baltimore, Maryland 
University of Maryland School of Medicine, Department of Emergency Medicine, 
Baltimore, Maryland </p>

<p>* </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>requirements. The implementation of work hour rules forces 
residency programs to maximize learning opportunities 
for their residents. The Residency Review Committee in 
Emergency Medicine (RRC-EM) has adopted a 60-hour </p>

<p>Volume XV, NO. 6 : September 2014 </p>

<p> 
Western Journal of Emergency Medicine </p>

<p>Nable et al 
Implementation of Team-based Physician Staffing Model </p>

<p>clinical work week, which is more restrictive than the 80-
hour limit of the American College of Graduate Medical 
Education (ACGME). 
1 Emergency medicine residency 
programs are therefore confronted with a need to take full 
advantage of a limited amount of time to teach physicians-
in-training. Little has been published about the effect of 
emergency department (ED) physician staffing models on 
learners' attitudes and perceptions. 
In 2012, our EM residency program, located at an 
academic medical center, adopted a new resident staffing 
model for our ED. The previous staffing model included two 
faculty physicians, one senior resident, two interns, and one 
"swing" resident. The two faculty physicians geographically 
split the 30-bed acute ED. Urgent care patients are seen 
in a separate part of the studied ED; the described staffing 
changes did not affect the urgent care area. A senior resident 
in his or her final year of EM training supervised the two 
interns. Patients were assigned to the interns on an alternating 
basis. The swing resident, a PGY2 or PGY3+ resident, took 
responsibility for the most critically ill patients in the ED 
to decompress the workload on the interns by assuming 
responsibility for a fraction of the patients initially assigned 
to them. Because the attending physicians' bed assignments 
were determined geographically and the interns were 
assigned patients on an alternating basis, each intern had the 
opportunity to work with two faculty physicians on the same 
shift. The original staffing model is depicted in Figure 1. 
Since the swing resident was not directly assigned patient 
beds but was expected to self-select patients, the amount of 
intern load-leveling was highly dependent on the efficiency, 
speed, and motivation of the swing resident. A highly efficient 
resident was obviously more likely to lessen the interns' 
patient load. The number of patients seen by a resident on a 
shift has been shown to be directly related to perceived stress. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>We realized that the line of responsibility needs to be clearly 
delineated, because communication in a busy ED is complex, </p>

<p>requiring multiple interactions among staff members for 
each patient. 
3 In this model, only the attending was confined 
geographically, making it difficult for nurses to identify 
which resident was assigned to an individual patient. Finally, 
because residents worked with two attending physicians at the 
same time, the learning environment was less conducive to 
individualized instruction. </p>

<p>4,5 </p>

<p>After soliciting input from residents, nursing staff, 
and faculty physicians, we designed a new staffing model, 
which was implemented in June 2012. In this new team-
based approach, the ED is divided geographically between 
two teams. Each team consists of an attending physician, an 
upper-level (PGY2 or PGY3+) resident, and an intern. The 
new staffing model is depicted in Figure 2. We hypothesized 
that this new team-based system would improve residents' 
learning and clinical experiences, as manifested by higher 
rotation evaluation scores. We further hypothesized that the 
elimination of the "swing" resident, in favor of a second 
senior resident responsible for a defined set of ED beds, would 
result in an increase in patient exposure as manifested by 
higher patients seen per hour. This article describes the effects 
of the change in ED staffing. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Study Design 
This retrospective before-and-after study was based 
on de-identified data that were collected from an electronic 
resident evaluation system and an electronic patient tracking 
system. The study design was reviewed and approved by our 
institutional review board. </p>

<p>Study Setting and Population 
The study site is a 30-bed urban academic ED with 52,000 
patient visits per year and a 20% admission rate. We include 
in the study EM residents who worked in our ED between </p>

<p>Figure 1. Pre-intervention staffing model. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Post-intervention staffing model. </p>

<p>Western Journal of Emergency Medicine </p>

<p> 
Volume XV, NO. 6 : September 2014 </p>

<p>Implementation of Team-based Physician Staffing Model 
Nable et al </p>

<p>November 12, 2011, and April 28, 2013, with at least one 
rotation in both the pre-and post-intervention periods. </p>

<p>Study Protocol 
In EM residency program, all residents evaluate each 
of their rotations. We obtained data for this study using 
an Internet-based electronic evaluation tool, <rs type="software">E*Value</rs> 
(Minneapolis, Minnesota), which solicits and collects resident 
evaluations every 4 weeks. Data were de-identified and 
examined in aggregate so as to not attribute any evaluation 
score to an individual. 
The new team-based staffing model was implemented on 
June 24, 2012, the beginning of an academic year. Evaluations 
submitted by residents rotating in the ED between November 
14, 2011, and June 23, 2012, were considered pre-intervention 
evaluations. Residents are assigned to the ED on 4-week block 
rotations; a total of eight 4-week blocks were included in the 
pre-intervention period. Three 4-week block rotations (June 24 
to September 16, 2012) following institution of the new staffing 
model were considered a washout period to minimize effects 
introduced by staff members' adjustment to the change and the 
"July phenomenon," the tendency toward increased errors and 
decreased hospital efficiency at teaching hospitals at the start 
of the academic year. 
6 Evaluations completed during the eight 
4-week blocks between September 17, 2012, and April 28, 
2013, were considered the post-intervention group. 
Additionally, we determined the number of patients seen 
by each resident in the pre-intervention and post-intervention 
periods using a reporting function available through the study 
site's electronic patient tracking system <rs id="software-1" type="software">FirstNet</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Cerner</rs>, 
North Kansas City, Missouri). Resident work hours were 
retrieved via an electronic physician shift scheduling software 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">OnCall</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Spiral Software</rs>, Newton, Massachusetts). </p>

<p>Measures 
A five-point Likert scale was used to query all residents 
about their experience in the ED at the conclusion of their 
rotation. The questions that are the focus of this study are 
listed in Figure 3, as is the scale used by the residents to 
indicate their responses. The quantity of patient exposure by 
residents was measured as patients per hour (PPH). </p>

<p>Data Analysis 
We included in the final analysis evaluations and 
PPH by residents who rotated in the ED in both the pre-</p>

<p>intervention and post-intervention. The mean Likert scale 
scores for evaluations completed by the residents and PPH 
were calculated. We determined mean differences and 
corresponding 95% confidence intervals (CIs) between both 
periods among all residents using paired sample t-tests. 
<rs id="software-4" type="software">Statistician</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">2.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">xlQA</rs>, Melbourne, Australia) was used for 
data analysis. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Out of 38 residents who were in the program during 
both the pre-and post-intervention periods, evaluations were 
completed for both periods by 34 residents. To allow for 
paired sample t-tests, we included in the study analysis only 
those 34 residents who rotated in the ED in both periods and 
completed evaluations. 
The mean Likert scale scores are presented in Figure 4. 
Following the initiation of the team-based staffing model, 
there was a statistically-significant increase in the mean scores 
for the query regarding the quality and amount of teaching, 
which improved from 4.03 to 4.27 (mean difference=0.24, 
p=0.03). There were non-statistically significant trends toward 
improved mean scores for all other queries. 
Residents (PGY-2+) saw more patients following the 
initiation of the team-based model (Table). Prior to the team-
based staffing system, residents saw an average of 1.24 
PPH, with an increase to 1.56 PPH post-intervention (mean 
difference=0.32, p=0.0005, 95% confidence interval [0.17 to 
0.47])). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
In today's EM environment, characterized by high 
patient acuity, increasing patient volumes, and an emphasis 
on fast throughput, the time available for individual patient 
care and clinical education is often limited. 
7 This constraint 
is particularly important in the chaotic environment of the 
ED, where workloads are unpredictable and physicians are 
interrupted frequently. 
8,9 Team-based learning is a powerful </p>

<p>1. The amount of clinical experience I obtained this rotation was: 
2. The amount of responsibility and autonomy I was given for making patient care decisions and providing care was: 
3. The quality and amount of supervision provided by attendings and senior residents was: 
4. The quality and amount of teaching provided by attendings and senior residents was: 
5. Overall, the attendings and senior residents treated me fairly and with respect and made me feel "part of the team": 
6. Overall the rotation was: </p>

<p>Table. Resident productivity as measured by patients evaluated 
per hour (mean difference=0.32, p=0.0005). </p>

<p>Patients per hour 
Pre-intervention 
Post-intervention </p>

<p>Mean 
1.24 
1.56 </p>

<p>SD 
± 0.36 
± 0.39 </p>

<p>SD, standard deviation </p>

<p>Figure 3. Resident evaluation questions examined in this study in which all responses were on a scale of 1-5: 1, poor; 2, below 
average; 3, average; 4, above average; 5, exceptional. </p>

<p>Volume XV, NO. 6 : September 2014 </p>

<p> 
Western Journal of Emergency Medicine </p>

<p>Nable et al 
Implementation of Team-based Physician Staffing Model </p>

<p>pedagogical tool that has been classically applied to didactic 
teaching. 
10 Incorporating this type of educational tool into the 
clinical setting may improve residents' clinical experience 
and education. By applying a vigorous qualitative analysis 
to self-reports, we have identified several areas that residents 
perceive as improved after moving to a team-based physician-
staffing model. 
EM residents value participation in the work environment, 
focused learning moments, repetitive teaching cycles, and 
intense learning experiences. 
11 We feel that the structure of the 
clinical work environment, specifically using the physician-
staffing model, might have a significant impact on learners' 
attitudes and perceptions about their clinical experience. 
Qualitative reports and expert opinion regarding 
improvements in medical education have been well 
documented. 
12 In this study, moving from a staffing model led 
by senior residents to one based on teams trended toward a 
higher number of favorable responses to subjective questions 
related to residents' clinical experience in the ED. Significant 
improvements were found in subgroups related to patient care 
decisions, clinical experience, and teaching. 
Our residents' evaluations of their experience generally 
trended towards improved scores following the initiation of a 
team-based model. In our previous staffing model, the swing 
resident managed the most critically ill patients in the ED. In 
the team-based model, a number of changes could account for 
residents' improved attitudes about their clinical experience. 
First, team leaders were upper-level residents paired with a 
single attending and intern throughout an entire shift, which 
reduced confusion related to patient assignment during a busy 
clinical shift. Second, team leaders were expected to see a 
higher volume of patients during a given shift, as they were 
given a large and specific geographic responsibility within the 
ED (in contrast to the previous model's swing resident, who 
assumed care for patients at his or her own pace). And, third, 
having an intern available in the team-based structure allowed </p>

<p>the senior resident to share tasks, such as arranging follow-up, 
calling consults, and documenting patient care. Having the 
option to share these responsibilities might enhance residents' 
perceptions of their clinical experience. 
Perceptions of teaching quality significantly improved 
when the swing and team-based approaches were compared. A 
number of previous studies found that faculty members have 
a limited amount of direct interaction and observation of EM 
residents. 
13,14 We believe the team-based staffing model allows 
a higher-degree of interaction between faculty physicians and 
residents, increasing teaching efficiency. Managing patients 
using a team-based approach also encourages residents to 
discuss patient care decisions together more frequently, which 
encourages active participation, learning, and more efficient 
communication of "teachable moments" among multiple 
learners. Many of these techniques have been described as 
effective learning techniques. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Additionally, there was a significant improvement in the 
number of patients seen by the residents (PGY-2+) following 
the initiation of the team-based model. In the previous model, 
the swing resident could self-select his patients. Individual 
resident motivation and efficiency likely affected the number 
of patient evaluations. In the team-based model, however, the 
two senior residents geographically split the ED, reducing the 
ability of slower residents to select a fewer number of patients. 
Further research by our department will likely incorporate 
more specifically intern-level experience. The electronic 
patient tracking system used in our ED during the study 
period allowed associating only residents (PGY-2+) to 
patients. Interns were therefore not included in the resident 
productivity analysis. Since our patient tracking system now 
records patients evaluated by interns, how the educational 
experience of these first-year physicians is affected by staffing 
model changes can be more readily examined. The addition 
of a teaching resident in the staffing model, whose role is to 
provide more comprehensive and complimentary instruction </p>

<p>Figure 4. Mean evaluation responses by residents are shown. Each category corresponds to the questions in Figure 3 posed to each 
resident, who responded using a five-point Likert scale. Mean differences between the pre-intervention and post-intervention periods 
are calculated and 95% confidence intervals shown on the right. </p>

<p>Western Journal of Emergency Medicine </p>

<p> 
Volume XV, NO. 6 : September 2014 </p>

<p>Implementation of Team-based Physician Staffing Model 
Nable et al </p>

<p>Conflicts of Interest: By the WestJEM article submission 
agreement, all authors are required to disclose all affiliations, 
funding sources and financial or management relationships that 
could be perceived as potential sources of bias. The authors 
disclosed none. </p>



<p>of interns and medical students, will likely be studied. </p>

<p>LIMITATIONS 
A significant limitation of this study is that we used a 
non-validated survey tool to measure residents' responses. 
Our findings are based on self-reported perceptions and 
therefore do not directly measure any quantitative outcomes 
within the chosen survey categories. Although the ACGME 
Common Program Requirements mandate that resident 
feedback be used in assessing multiple aspects of a residency 
program's educational experiences, 
16 there is currently no 
uniform approach to obtaining such evaluative measures. 
The observed effects in resident perceptions of their ED 
educational experience may have varied had the queries been 
worded differently. The survey instrument used in this study, 
however, has been used at our institution for the last five 
years, allowing the program to internally ascertain trends. As a 
further limitation, residents were also not required to complete 
the survey until the rotation ended, so recall bias might have 
influenced their responses. Also, the increase in number of 
patients seen in the post-intervention staffing model may be 
a reflection of the improved efficiency expected of residents 
who are farther into their training program. Finally, this study 
did not examine effects on patient outcomes. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
Data are scarce regarding the effect of physician staffing 
models on residents' attitudes and perceptions about their 
clinical experience. Our results demonstrate that adopting a 
team-based physician staffing model can improve residents' 
perceptions about their educational experience. Our study 
also demonstrated that a team-based model was associated 
with an increased number of patient evaluations as compared 
to a staffing model in which residents could self-select their 
patients. We hope that the results from this study will be 
helpful in the development of ED physician staffing models 
that improve the teaching environment. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS 
The authors acknowledge Linda J. Kesselring, MS, ELS, 
the technical editor/writer in the Department of Emergency 
Medicine University of Maryland School of Medicine, for her 
contributions as copyeditor of the manuscript. The authors 
further acknowledge Michael Taigman, MA, instructor in 
the Department of Emergency Health Services University of 
Maryland Baltimore County for his guidance on this project. </p>

<p>Address for Correspondence: Jose Nable, MD, Department of 
Emergency Medicine, University of Maryland School of Medicine. 
Email: jnable@umem.org. </p>

</text></tei>