<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4740966" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Objectives: To estimate the national prevalence of cervical cancer (CCA) in women discharged from hospital 
after delivery, and to examine its associations with birth outcomes. </p>

<p>Methods: We did a retrospective cross-sectional analysis of maternal hospital discharges in the United States (1998-2009). 
We used the Nationwide Inpatient Sample (NIS) database to identify hospital stays for women who gave birth. We 
determined length of hospital stay, in-hospital mortality, and used ICD-9-CM codes to identify CCA and all outcomes of 
interest. Multivariable logistic regression modeling was used to calculate adjusted odds ratios (AOR) and 95% confidence 
intervals (CI) for the associations between CCA and feto-maternal outcome. </p>

<p>Results: In the 12-year period from 1998 to 2009, there were 8,387 delivery hospitalizations with a CCA diagnosis, a 
prevalence rate of 1.8 per 100,000 (95% CI=1.6, 1.9). After adjusting for potential confounders, CCA was associated with 
increased odds of maternal morbidities including: anemia (AOR, 1.78, 95% CI, 1.54-2.06), anxiety (AOR, 1.95, 95% CI, 
1.11-3.42), cesarean delivery (AOR, 1.67, 95% CI, 1.46-1.90), and prolonged hospital stay (AOR, 1.51, 95% CI, 1.30-
1.76), and preterm birth (AOR, 1.69, 95% CI, 1.46-1.97). </p>

<p>Conclusion: There is a recent increase in the prevalence of CCA during pregnancy. CCA is associated with severe feto-
maternal morbidities. Interventions that promote safer sexual practice and regular screening for CCA should be promoted 
widely among women of reproductive age to effectively reduce the prevalence of CCA during pregnancy and its impact 
on the health of mother and baby. </p>

<p>In recent years, the average age at which a woman 
delivers her first child has been increasing [1]. Considering 
this delay in childbearing to older ages, and the association 
between later age at first delivery and increased risk of 
several types of cancer, the expectation would be an increase 
in the number of women with a diagnosis of cancer during 
pregnancy [2]. Cervical cancer is one of the leading types of 
reproductive cancer among pregnant mothers [3]. Recently, a 
study of nine Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results 
(SEER) registries investigated trends of cervical cancer in the </p>

<p>*Address correspondence to this author at the Department of Women Children 
and Family Health Science, College of Nursing, University of Illinois, 845 S 
Damen Ave, Chicago, IL 60612, USA; E-mail: talk2mulie@gmail.com </p>

<p>United States (US) and reported an overall 54% reduction in the 
incidence of invasive cervical cancer over a 35-year period, 
from 13.07 per 100,000 (1973-1975) to 6.0 per 100,000 (2006- 2007) [4]. However, despite the comprehensive nature of their 
analyses, the authors did not look specifically at the rates and 
temporal trends of cervical cancer during pregnancy. Pregnancy 
provides a valuable opportunity to screen and diagnose women 
for cervical cancer as they are receiving routine antenatal care. </p>

<p>A recent study in Denmark reported that incidence of 
pregnancy-associated cancer, including cervical cancer, has 
been rising over the past 30 years [5]. These increases have 
been attributed largely to the aforementioned tendency for 
women to give birth at later ages, but also to increased 
detection rates due to an increased frequency of encounters 
with the healthcare system during pregnancy [4, 6]. An 
analysis of delivery hospitalizations in countries like the US, </p>

<p>Trends in Cervical Cancer Among Delivery-Related Discharges </p>

<p>The Open Nursing Journal, 2015, Volume 9 43 </p>

<p>where a high preponderance of deliveries occur in hospitals 
and other healthcare facilities [7] should provide improved 
estimates of the prevalence of pregnancy-associated cervical 
cancer. The National Inpatient Sample (NIS) series of 
databases, made available through the Healthcare Cost and 
Utilization Project (HCUP), makes it possible to investigate 
national rates and temporal trends of cervical cancer among 
pregnancy women. Furthermore, the availability of patient 
and hospital-level socio-demographic and geographic 
characteristics such as age, race, and urbanization in the NIS 
can facilitate analyses that identify particular subsets of 
pregnant women that may be at increased risk for cervical 
cancer, and can serve as a proxy for assessing the 
effectiveness of cervical cancer prevention programs in 
different regions of the US. </p>

<p>Having up-to-date, national estimates of the frequency 
and rate of pregnancy-related cervical cancer and 
understanding its association with maternal-fetal outcomes is 
critical to public health planning, resource allocation, and the 
provision of reliable data to decision-makers. This study 
fulfills that role as it aims to: 1) estimate the rates and 12-
year trends of cervical cancer among delivery-related 
hospitalizations in the US, overall and by patient and 
hospital characteristics; 2) investigate whether a cervical 
cancer diagnosis during pregnancy is associated with adverse 
maternal-fetal outcomes; and 3) estimate the impact of 
cervical cancer during pregnancy on the direct cost of 
medical care. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Study Design and Data Source </p>

<p>We conducted a cross-sectional analysis of hospital 
discharges in which a singleton delivery occurred, using 
1998-2009 annual data from the NIS, which is the largest all-
payer, publicly available inpatient database in the US [8]. 
The NIS dataset is created using a sampling technique that 
stratifies all non-federal community hospitals from states 
into groups based on five major hospital characteristics: 
rural/urban location, number of beds, geographic region, 
teaching status, and ownership. A 20% sample of hospitals is 
randomly drawn from each stratum and all inpatient 
discharge records from selected hospitals are included. The 
NIS database comprises hospital stratum identifiers and 
discharge-level sampling weights whose purpose is to 
facilitate the generation of national prevalence estimates. </p>

<p>Identifying Maternal Cases and Clinical Conditions </p>

<p>Delivery-related hospitalizations were identified using a 
two-step process. First, we used an HCUP-created variable, 
NEOMAT, designed to classify hospitalizations as maternal 
and/or neonatal [9]. Then we used the presence of a "V27.0" 
or "V27.1" International Classification of Diseases, Ninth 
Edition, Clinical Modification (ICD-9-CM) code to select 
women who had a singleton delivery during their 
hospitalization, either live-or stillborn. Each hospital 
discharge record contains ICD-9-CM codes for a patient's 
principal diagnosis and up to 14 secondary diagnoses. 
Beginning in 2009, the NIS included up to 24 secondary </p>

<p>diagnosis fields [10]. Once restricted to delivery 
hospitalizations, we identified women with a cervical cancer 
diagnosis using the presence of one or more of the following 
ICD-9-CM codes: 180.0, 180.1, 180.8, 180.9, 233.1, and 
795.06. Maternal co-morbidities and maternal-fetal 
outcomes, including early onset delivery and poor fetal 
growth, were also identified using ICD-9-CM codes. A 
detailed list of the specific ICD-9-CM diagnosis and 
procedure codes used in this study are presented in Appendix 
A </p>

<p>We used the maternal length of stay (LOS) during the 
delivery hospitalization as an indicator of healthcare 
utilization and as a proxy for the severity of complications 
during delivery. We defined a prolonged hospitalization as a 
LOS as one that met or exceeded the 95 
th percentile based on 
the distribution among all delivery hospitalizations (≥4 days 
in our sample). </p>

<p>Demographics and Covariates </p>

<p>To explore differences in baseline characteristics, we 
compared the distribution of selected socio-demographic, 
behavioral, and hospital characteristics of those with and 
without a cervical cancer diagnosis. We grouped maternal 
age in years into five clinically meaningful categories: &lt;20, 
20-24, 25-29, 30-34, and ≥35. Race was determined first by 
self-reported ethnicity (Hispanic or non-Hispanic), with the 
non-Hispanic (NH) group further subdivided by race (white, 
black, or other). Household income was estimated by HCUP 
using the mother's zip code of residence at delivery, and 
subsequently ranked into quartiles [8]. The primary payer for 
each hospitalization was classified into government 
(Medicare/Medicaid), private (commercial carriers and 
private HMOs and PPOs), or other (including self-pay and 
no charge). Hospital characteristics assessed included 
teaching status (teaching vs non-teaching), location (urban vs 
rural), and US geographic region (Northeast, Midwest, 
South, or West). </p>

<p>Cost Estimation </p>

<p>To examine the economic impact of pregnancy-related 
cervical cancer, hospital charges that are reported for each 
hospitalization were converted to a more reliable estimate of 
cost. Hospital charges reflect what a hospital bills for 
services, whereas the desired measure should represent an 
estimate of actual resource consumption. Markup for 
services from actual cost to what is charged varies over time, 
across hospitals, and even among different departments 
within the same hospital [11, 12]. To estimate the actual cost 
of direct medical care, we first multiplied the total charge of 
the hospitalization by a time-and hospital-specific cost-to-
charge ratio (CCR) provided by HCUP [13]. Then, we 
multiplied reported charges by an "adjustment factor" (AF) 
from HCUP. The AF adjusts for bias that results from 
interdepartmental variations in markup within each hospital 
[14]. For example, within the same hospital, the markup for 
a surgical procedure may be considerably higher than for a 
routine bed service; the AF attempts to adjust for those 
differences. The formula below summarizes the conversion 
of hospital charges into a refined cost estimate: </p>



<p>Mogos et al. </p>

<p>Total Cost = Total Charges * Hospital-Specific CCR * AF </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Descriptive statistics were used to estimate the national 
rate of cervical cancer among women delivering singleton 
offspring. All estimates were weighted to account for the 
complex sampling design of the NIS. We assessed the 
distribution of socio-demographic, behavioral, hospital 
characteristics, and selected clinical and perinatal conditions 
by cervical cancer status. Temporal trends in rates of cervical 
cancer during the 12-year study period were assessed using 
joinpoint regression. Joinpoint regression provides the best 
fitting model with time points where the rate changes 
(increase or decrease) significantly [15]. Each distinct 
temporal trend identified by the joinpoint model is described 
using the annual percent change [APC, average annual 
change over the years during a particular trend] and the 
average annual percent change [AAPC, an overall APC that 
characterizes the entire study period, even if there were 
statistically significant changes in the trend] [15]. For 
temporal analyses we used the NIS-Trends files, supplied by 
HCUP to ensure consistency in the trend weights and in 
definitions of data elements over time [16]. </p>

<p>Survey logistic regression modeling was used to estimate 
adjusted odds ratios (AOR) and 95% confidence intervals (CI) 
for the association between pregnancy-related cervical cancer 
and each outcome of interest. For each outcome, we 
constructed a crude (unadjusted) model and two multivariable 
(adjusted) models. Covariates were identified through a 
review of the literature and empirical bivariate analyses. In the 
first multivariable model, we adjusted for maternal 
demographics (age and race/ethnicity, household income, 
multiple gestations), maternal behaviors (tobacco, alcohol, and 
drug use), clinically diagnosed obesity, primary payer, and 
rural/urban status. In the second multivariable model, in 
addition to covariates in the first multivariate model, we also 
controlled for clinical and pregnancy-related complications. 
These complications were captured using a composite binary 
variable that indicated the presence or absence these 
conditions (see Table 2 for list of variables included in the 
composite variables). The individual clinical and pregnancy-
related conditions used to create the clinical and pregnancy-
related composite variables were also identified using ICD-9-
CM codes. Conditions were selected based on their 
documented association with our outcomes of interest. </p>

<p>To estimate the impact of pregnancy-related cervical 
cancer on the cost of inpatient care at delivery, we compared 
the mean, per women, direct medical cost between 
discharges with and without a cervical cancer diagnosis. 
Economic analyses were restricted to 2001-2009 since 
reliable CCRs to convert charges to costs were not available 
prior to 2001. Statistical analyses were performed with SAS 
software, version 9.3 (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, NC) and the 
<rs id="software-3" type="software">Joinpoint Regression Program</rs>, version <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">4.0.1</rs>. [17]. This 
study was considered exempt from institutional review board 
approval because of the de-identified nature of the data. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>In the 12-year period from 1998 to 2009, there were 
8,387 delivery hospitalizations with a cervical cancer 
diagnosis, a prevalence rate of 1.8 per 100,000 (95% CI=1.6, 
1.9). Over 60,000 (128 per 100,000) discharge records also 
had a diagnosis of one or more sexually transmitted 
infections (STI). Among the 47,446,658 delivery 
hospitalizations, the maternal age distribution was as 
follows: teenagers (10.9%), 20-34 years (75.1%), and 
advanced maternal age (14.0%). Most reported their race as 
white-NH (39.9%), followed by Hispanic (17.3%), black-NH 
(9.8%) and other-NH (7.6%). Over 25% of hospitalizations 
were missing race/ethnicity, a known limitation of state 
reporting to the NIS. Private insurance (including HMO) was 
the primary payment source (54.1%) followed by 
Medicaid/Medicare (39.5%), and others including self-pay 
and missing primary payer information (6.4%). The South 
accounted for 36.9% of delivery hospitalizations followed by 
West (24.8%), Midwest (21.6%) and Northeast (16.7%). 
87.5% of the discharges were from urban hospitals and 
12.5% from rural hospitals. </p>

<p>We assessed whether certain demographic, behavioral, 
hospital, and clinical conditions were associated with an 
increased odds of cervical cancer using multivariable logistic 
regression. After adjusting for year of discharge and all 
variables listed in Table 1 (tobacco use, alcohol use, drug 
abuse, being from the south or west region, low household 
income, diagnosis of human immunodeficiency virus [HIV]  or another STI), a number of characteristics were associated 
with pregnancy-related cervical cancer. Women who smoke 
during pregnancy were more likely to be diagnosed with 
cervical cancer when compared to women who didn't smoke 
(AOR=4.36; 95% CI: 3.74, 5.09). Other factors associated 
with increased risk of cervical cancer include: alcohol use 
(AOR=5.51; 95% CI: 2.44,12.46); drug abuse (AOR=2.71; 
95% CI: 1.93, 3.81); diagnosis of STD (AOR=2.67, 95% CI: 
1.67, 6.09) and HIV (AOR=6.19; 95% CI: 3.55, 10.79); 
presence of one or more maternal clinical conditions 
(AOR=1.56, 95% CI: 1.29, 1.89) or pregnancy-related 
complications (AOR=1.19, 95% CI: 1.04, 1.37). Compared 
to women from the highest household income areas, those 
with progressively lower household income had a 1.54 to 
2.30 times higher odds of pregnancy-related cervical cancer. 
Those from the Midwest and South regions had 39% and 
36% greater odds of cervical cancer, respectively, when 
compared to their counterparts from the West. </p>

<p>During the study period, the number of discharges with a 
cervical cancer diagnosis varied in frequency from a high of 
831 in 1998 to a low of 534 in 2006. Overall, we observed a 
non-significant 14.3% annual reduction in the rate from 1998 
to 2001 followed by a statistically significant 4.1% (95% CI: 
0.1, 8.2) annual increase from 2001 to 2009 (Fig. 1). Subgroup 
analysis of temporal trends by region showed a statistically 
significant 6.3% annual reduction in the rate of pregnancy-
related cervical cancer in the Northeast region. However, in 
the South and West regions there were no statistically 
significant trends in cervical cancer rates. </p>

<p>Trends in Cervical Cancer Among Delivery-Related Discharges </p>

<p>The Open Nursing Journal, 2015, Volume 9 45 </p>

<p>Table 1. Distribution of maternal socio-demographic, perinatal, behavioral, and hospital characteristics among delivery-related 
discharges, by cervical cancer (CCA) diagnosis status, HCUP-NIS, 1998-2009. </p>

<p>Characteristic 
N </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>CCA (%) 
No CCA (%) 
OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Overall 
47,446,658 
n/a </p>

<p>Maternal age (years) </p>

<p>&lt; 20 </p>

<p>20 -24 </p>

<p>25 -29 </p>

<p>30 -34 </p>

<p>≥ 35 </p>

<p>5,179,407 </p>

<p>11,694,618 </p>

<p>12,899,876 </p>

<p>11,020,945 </p>

<p>6,626,859 </p>

<p>6.43 </p>

<p>27.05 </p>

<p>32.21 </p>

<p>20.74 </p>

<p>13.57 </p>

<p>10.92 </p>

<p>26.64 </p>

<p>27.19 </p>

<p>23.23 </p>

<p>13.97 </p>

<p>0.50 (0.40-0.61) </p>

<p>0.93 (0.81-1.06) </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>0.75 (0.65-0.88) </p>

<p>0.82 (0.70-0.96) </p>

<p>Maternal race </p>

<p>White-NH </p>

<p>Black-NH </p>

<p>Hispanic </p>

<p>Other-NH </p>

<p>Missing/Unknown </p>

<p>18,951,456 </p>

<p>4,670,322 </p>

<p>8,203,578 </p>

<p>3,599,691 </p>

<p>12,021,611 </p>

<p>45.37 </p>

<p>9.53 </p>

<p>15.60 </p>

<p>3.74 </p>

<p>25.76 </p>

<p>39.94 </p>

<p>9.84 </p>

<p>17.29 </p>

<p>7.59 </p>

<p>25.33 </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>0.85 (0.70-1.04) </p>

<p>0.79 (0.63-1.00) </p>

<p>0.43 (0.33-0.57) </p>

<p>0.90 (0.76-1.05) </p>

<p>Tobacco use </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1,610,608 
13.29 
3.39 
4.36 (3.74-5.09) </p>

<p>Alcohol use </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>46,113 
0.53 
0.10 
5.51 (2.44-12.46) </p>

<p>Drug use </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>486,005 
2.72 
1.02 
2.71 (1.93-3.81) </p>

<p>Hospital region </p>

<p>Northeast </p>

<p>Midwest </p>

<p>South </p>

<p>West </p>

<p>7,937,070 </p>

<p>10,249,569 </p>

<p>17,498,148 </p>

<p>11,761,871 </p>

<p>13.30 </p>

<p>24.86 </p>

<p>41.34 </p>

<p>20.50 </p>

<p>16.73 </p>

<p>21.60 </p>

<p>36.88 </p>

<p>24.79 </p>

<p>0.96 (0.67-1.37) </p>

<p>1.39 (1.13-1.72) </p>

<p>1.36 (1.10-1.68) </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>Hospital location </p>

<p>Rural </p>

<p>Urban </p>

<p>5,893,039 </p>

<p>41,432,694 </p>

<p>15.87 </p>

<p>84.13 </p>

<p>12.45 </p>

<p>87.55 </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>0.75 (0.63-0.91) </p>

<p>Hospital teaching status </p>

<p>Non-teaching </p>

<p>Teaching </p>

<p>25,549,873 </p>

<p>21,775,860 </p>

<p>47.24 </p>

<p>52.76 </p>

<p>53.99 </p>

<p>46.01 </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>1.31 (1.12-1.54) </p>

<p>Hospital Bed size </p>

<p>Small </p>

<p>Medium </p>

<p>Large </p>

<p>5,324,708 </p>

<p>12,660,955 </p>

<p>29,340,070 </p>

<p>10.80 </p>

<p>25.77 </p>

<p>63.43 </p>

<p>11.25 </p>

<p>26.75 </p>

<p>62.00 </p>

<p>1.00 (0.80-1.24) </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>1.06 (0.89-1.27) </p>

<p>Household income </p>

<p>Lowest quartile </p>

<p>2 
nd quartile </p>

<p>3 
rd quartile </p>

<p>Highest quartile </p>

<p>Missing/Unknown </p>

<p>12,143,344 </p>

<p>11,981,361 </p>

<p>11,419,328 </p>

<p>11,092,423 </p>

<p>810,202 </p>

<p>34.21 </p>

<p>28.58 </p>

<p>21.61 </p>

<p>13.59 </p>

<p>2.01 </p>

<p>25.59 </p>

<p>25.25 </p>

<p>24.07 </p>

<p>23.38 </p>

<p>1.71 </p>

<p>2.30 (1.92-2.75) </p>

<p>1.95 (1.64-2.32) </p>

<p>1.54 (1.30-1.84) </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>2.03 (1.38-2.97) </p>

<p>Primary payer </p>

<p>Medicare/Medicaid </p>

<p>Private </p>

<p>Other </p>

<p>18,723,901 </p>

<p>25,662,632 </p>

<p>3,060,125 </p>

<p>1.61 </p>

<p>1.67 </p>

<p>0.73 </p>

<p>39.46 </p>

<p>54.09 </p>

<p>6.45 </p>

<p>1.82 (1.60-2.07) </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>1.38 (1.09-1.75) </p>

<p>Clinical comorbidities 
1,963,585 
5.87 
4.14 
1.45 (1.19-1.76) </p>

<p>Pregnancy comorbidities 
5,663,671 
13.91 
11.94 
1.19 (1.04-1.37) </p>

<p>STD 
60,740 
0.34 
0.13 
2.67 (1.67-6.09) </p>

<p>HIV 
51,071 
0.66 
0.11 
6.19 (3.55-10.79) </p>

<p>Obesity 
626,608 
1.50 
1.32 
1.14 (0.77-1.67) </p>

<p>CCA = cervical cancer, NH = non-Hispanic, OR = odds ratio, CI = confidence interval, STD = sexually transmitted disease, HIV = human immunodeficiency virus, 
a Weighted to 
estimate national frequency; sum of all groups may not add up to the total due to missing data, 
b Reference group is represented by the absence of the condition/characteristic. </p>



<p>Mogos et al. </p>

<p>Fig. (1). Overall Trend and Annual Percent Change (APC) of 
Cervical Cancer Diagnosis Among Delivery-Related Discharges in 
the United States by Region, HCUP-NIS, 1998-2009. APC = 
annual percent change, point estimate (95% confidence interval). 
Vertical axis: diagnosed Cervical Cancer per 100,000 discharges; 
Horizontal axis: year of study. *The APC for the joinpoint 
segment is statistically significantly different from zero (p&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Age-specific trend analyses showed a statistically 
significant 10.6% (95% CI: 4.6, 16.9) annual increase in 
pregnancy-related cervical cancer since 2001 among women 
aged 20-24 years (Fig. 2). Conversely, among women 25-29 
years old, there was an average 1.9% (95% CI: -4.8, -1.2) 
decrease in the rate during the study period. For other age </p>

<p>groups, the rate of pregnancy-related cervical cancer was 
either flat over time (30-34 years), or erratic without a 
statistically significant trend (&lt;20, 30-34, and 35+ years). 
We observed tendencies towards racial/ethnic differences in 
the both the rates and trends of pregnancy-related cervical 
cancer. There was an estimated 1.3% and 2.0% annual 
reduction for white-NH and black-NH, respectively (data not 
shown), and annual increases for Hispanics (APC=2.7%), 
and other-NH (APC=6.0%). Despite the differences in their 
point estimates, none of these trends were statistically 
significantly different from zero. 
Table 2 presents the associations between pregnancy-
related cervical cancer and selected maternal-fetal outcomes. 
After controlling for potential sociodemographic, behavioral, 
clinical, and hospital-related confounders, we observed 
between a 51% and 95% increased odds of adverse 
pregnancy outcomes among women with a cervical cancer 
diagnosis at the time of their delivery hospitalization. 
Women with a diagnosis of cervical cancer had 95% higher 
odds of being diagnosed with anxiety (95% CI= 1.11-3.42); 
78% higher odds of anemia (95% CI= 1.54-2.06); and 69% 
higher odds of preterm labor (95% CI= 1.46-1.97) than 
women without cervical cancer. We also observed an 
increased odds of delivery by cesarean section (AOR=1.67, 
95% CI= 1.46-1.90) and a prolonged hospital stay (AOR= 
1.51, 95% CI= 1.30-1.76) among women pregnancy-related 
cervical cancer. These adverse maternal-fetal outcomes 
translated into differences in the mean, per hospitalization, 
cost of inpatient medical care between women with ($4,745) </p>

<p>Fig. (2). Trend and Annual Percent Change (APC) of Cervical Cancer Diagnosis Among Delivery-Related Discharges in the United States 
by Maternal Age Group, HCUP-NIS, 1998-2009. APC = annual percent change, point estimate (95% confidence interval). Vertical axis: 
diagnosed cervical cancer per 100,000 discharges. Horizontal axis: year of discharge. *The APC for the joinpoint segment is statistically 
significantly different from zero (p&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Trends in Cervical Cancer Among Delivery-Related Discharges </p>

<p>The Open Nursing Journal, 2015, Volume 9 47 </p>

<p>with without ($3,986) pregnancy-related cervical cancer 
(p&lt;0.01), even when restricted to consideration of only the 
delivery hospitalization. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Albeit a relatively rare occurrence, cervical cancer during 
pregnancy is a tragic event that can pose life-threatening 
risks for the mother and developing fetus. Since more than 
98.5% of all births in the US occur in a healthcare setting 
[18], analyzing a nationally representative sample of 
inpatient hospitalizations could provide an accurate and 
reliable estimate of the prevalence of pregnancy-related 
cervical cancer. To our knowledge, this is the largest study in 
the US to assess the temporal trends in cervical cancer 
diagnoses among delivery hospitalizations and to investigate 
simultaneously the associations between cervical cancer and 
maternal-fetal morbidities. Previous studies on cervical 
cancer focused on trends among all women [4, 19, 20] and 
those that studied the prevalence within a pregnant 
population failed to assess its association with maternal co-
morbidities or pregnancy outcomes [5, 21-23]. The findings 
of this study contribute significantly to the literature by 
providing a basis for establishing recent rates and trends of 
pregnancy-related cervical cancer, assessing the increased 
risk for adverse outcomes that may be imposed by cervical 
cancer during pregnancy, and how that translates into 
differences in the direct medical costs associated with 
inpatient care at delivery. </p>

<p>In our 12-year national study, we observed a steady 
increase in the pregnancy-related cervical cancer from 2001-
2009. This is consistent a large study in Denmark that 
reported a trend of increasing prevalence of cervical cancer 
among pregnant mothers over the past 30 years (crude 
APC=0.8%; 95% CI: -0.6 to 2.1) [5]. Considering the near </p>

<p>universal availability of screening and vaccination programs 
in the US, the increasing trend in pregnancy-related cervical 
cancer is of concern. One possible explanation for our 
findings may be a product of the limitation of the NIS data -
the unit of analysis is a single discharge record, and 
discharges for the same woman cannot be linked together. 
Therefore, there is a potential for counting a diagnosis of 
cervical cancer for a woman multiple times. To increase the 
likelihood that a cervical cancer diagnosis for a particular 
woman (or for a particular pregnancy) is only counted once, 
we restricted our analyses to delivery hospitalizations. By 
broadening our scope to include all pregnancy-related 
discharge records, we would probably improve slightly our 
ability to capture cases of cervical cancer, but would very 
likely overestimate the prevalence of pregnancy-related 
cervical cancer due to the aforementioned consequence of 
multiple counting. Another plausible explanation for the 
increasing trend is that because of an increased frequency of 
medical encounters during pregnancy (e.g. antenatal care 
visits) women are more likely to have better awareness and 
consent to screening [4, 6]. One may also speculate that the 
increasing trend could be because of the concomitant 
increase in human papillomavirus (HPV) infections. Since 
our data do not provide information on HPV infection, we 
analyzed the prevalence and trends of a broader group of STI 
infections [24, 25]. As hypothesized, we observed an 11.2% 
[95% CI= 9.2-13.3] annual increase in the prevalence of 
STIs from 2000-2009, which could, in part, explain the 4.1% 
average annual increase in the pregnancy-related cervical 
cancer rate from 2001-2009. </p>

<p>In line with recent studies of cervical cancer in the 
general population [4, 26, 27], stratified analysis by 
race/ethnicity revealed a bigger decrease in pregnancy-
related cervical cancer among black-NH women than among 
white-NH women. Unlike black-NH and white-NH women, 
cervical cancer rates for Hispanic women increased, on </p>

<p>Table 2. Outcome rates, adjusted odds ratios, and 95% confidence intervals for the association between CCA and maternal-infant 
morbidity and mortality, HCUP-NIS, 1998-2009. </p>

<p>Outcomes </p>

<p>Rate </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>CCA 
No CCA 
Model 1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Model 2 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Model 3 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Maternal, Pregnancy-related </p>

<p>Cesarean section </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>346.2 
274.7 
1.40 (1.25-1.57) 
1.69 (1.49-1.92) 
1.67 (1.46-1.90) </p>

<p>Hospital stay ≥ 4 days </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>167.6 
122.9 
1.44 (1.24-1.66) 
1.54 (1.33-1.77) 
1.51 (1.30-1.76) </p>

<p>Maternal, Clinical Conditions </p>

<p>Anemia 
142.8 
80.0 
1.92 (1.67-2.20) 
1.80 (1.56-2.07) 
1.78 (1.54-2.06) </p>

<p>Anxiety 
9.3 
3.4 
2.74 (1.58-4.78) 
2.02 (1.16-3.53) 
1.95 (1.11-3.42) </p>

<p>Infant outcomes </p>

<p>Poor fetal growth 
24.7 
16.0 
1.57 (1.16-2.12) 
1.35(1.01-1.82) 
1.32 (0.98-1.78) </p>

<p>Preterm delivery 
114.7 
65.5 
1.85 (1.60-2.14) 
1.7 3(1.49-2.00) 
1.69 (1.46-1.97) </p>

<p>CCA=cervical cancer, OR=odds ratio, CI=confidence interval 
a Per 1,000 pregnancy-related discharges. 
b Unadjusted model with the presence of the condition as the outcome, CCA status as the exposure ("No CCA" is the reference group). 
c Model 1 + adjustment for maternal age, race/ethnicity, household income, tobacco, alcohol, and drug use, primary payer, rural/urban status, and obesity 
d Model 2 + additional adjustment for composite of clinical (coronary heart disease, hyperlipidemia, hypothyroidism, disorders of the adrenal gland, existing hypertension, diabetes 
mellitus, and depression) and pregnancy (preeclampsia, eclampsia, placenta abruptio, placenta accreta, placenta previa, gestational diabetes, and gestational hypertension) related 
conditions of the mother. 
e Additional adjustment for previous Cesarean section in Models 2 and 3. 
f Additional adjustment for discharge disposition status in Models 2 and 3. </p>



<p>Mogos et al. </p>

<p>average, 2.7% annually. Part of the racial/ethnic disparity 
could be due to variation in the utilization of cervical cancer 
prevention programs [28, 29]. A study based on analysis of 
data from the National Immunization Survey among teenage 
girls (13-17 years) reported lower rates of completion of the 
required HPV vaccine regimen among blacks and Hispanics 
[30, 31]. However, the racial/ethnic disparities in pregnancy-
related cervical cancer warrants further investigation. </p>

<p>Differences in pregnancy-related cervical cancer rates by 
geographic region of the US could be explained by baseline 
differences in the distribution of socio-demographic makeup 
of their respective populations, as well as in the prevalence 
of clinical and pregnancy-related complications. In assessing 
geographic differences, we attempted to adjust for patient 
and hospital characteristics; however, some residual 
confounding may persist and explain some of those findings. 
Stratified trend analyses by age demonstrated 10.6% and 
3.5% annual increases for women 20-25 years and ≥ 35 years 
of age respectively. The former peak (20-25 years) could be 
related to women becoming sexually active in their early 
teens [32] increasing the risk of being infected with HPV, a 
critical factor for cervical cancer [33]. The increasing rates 
observed among women of advanced maternal age (age ≥ 35 
years) could be due to the increased risk associated with 
having a first pregnancy later in life [34]. Unfortunately, 
neither parity nor time at first delivery is available in the 
NIS; therefore, we could not further investigate this 
hypothesis. </p>

<p>The increased rate of cesarean section and preterm 
delivery observed in our study are consistent with the results 
of previous studies that have investigated the impact of 
pregnancy-related reproductive or non-reproductive cancers 
[23, 35]. The increased likelihood of these adverse outcomes 
among woman with cervical cancer in pregnancy are in line 
with the theory that clinically aggressive types of cancers are 
more likely to be diagnosed at the time of delivery than less 
aggressive cancers. Diagnosis early in pregnancy could lead 
to a decision to deliver earlier by cesarean section, so that 
treatment of the aggressive cancer can begin as early as 
possible. Future studies with more in-depth clinical 
information should investigate the association between 
cervical cancer and pregnancy outcomes, stratified by 
histologic subtype. </p>

<p>Women with cervical cancer during pregnancy were 78% 
more likely to experience anxiety. A previous study reported 
symptoms of anxiety in patients receiving cervical cancer 
treatment [36] and long term cancer survivors [37]. The 
increased level of anxiety for a woman diagnosed with 
cervical cancer is likely due to increased concern for 
existential well-being of herself and her baby [38, 39]. 
Anemia is one of the major complications of many cancers 
[40], and impacts more than 40% of cancer patients [41]. It 
is established that women who are anemic during pregnancy 
are more likely to give birth to a preterm infant [42, 43]. In 
our study, women with cervical cancer were 95% more 
likely to be diagnosed with anemia. Therefore, the observed </p>

<p>increased risk of preterm birth among infants born to women 
with cervical cancer could be explained partly by the higher 
prevalence of anemia among cervical cancer patients [35,  44]. </p>

<p>The results of this study should be interpreted with the 
following limitations in mind. First, because of the 
administrative nature of the NIS data, we relied on ICD-9-
CM codes to identify cases of cervical cancer, clinical and 
pregnancy-related comorbidities, and behavioral conditions. 
These data are subject to errors in coding, which could lead 
to over-or under estimation of cases and other 
comorbidities. Second, it is possible that women with a 
cervical cancer diagnosis during pregnancy could receive 
more thorough assessment, follow-up, and extensive 
documentation of behavioral and clinical comorbidities 
compared to other pregnant women, which could lead to a 
diagnostic bias that results in differential misclassification 
and an overestimation of the measures of associations we 
report. Third, some states do not report race/ethnicity data 
(25% of discharges in this study were missing 
race/ethnicity), and the states that do categorize 
race/ethnicity do so in a non-uniform manner. HCUP 
attempts to standardize categorization of race/ethnicity to 
enabling comparisons but one should still interpret those 
findings with caution. Despite these known limitations of the 
NIS dataset, the large and representative sample of inpatient 
hospital discharges affords an efficient means of generating 
national estimates of pregnancy-related cervical cancer rates 
and trends. The substantial sample size also permitted our 
investigation of trends within geographic region and socio-
demographic subgroups. </p>

<p>In conclusion, there is a recent increase in the prevalence 
of cervical cancer during pregnancy. There is also evidence 
that pregnancy-related cervical cancer increases the 
likelihood of several maternal co-morbidities and adverse 
pregnancy outcomes. Interventions that promote safer sexual 
practice and regular screening for cervical cancer should be 
promoted widely among women of reproductive age in order 
to effectively reduce the prevalence of cervical cancer during 
pregnancy and its impact on the health of mother and baby. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors confirm that this article content has no 
conflict of interest. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This work partly supported by: (1) the National Institutes of 
Health through a grant on Cancer health disparities (award no. 
1P20MD003375-01) and the Agency for Health Care Research, 
(2) Quality through a grant on Clinically Enhanced Multi-
Purpose Administrative Data set for Comparative Effectiveness 
Research (award no. 1R0111HS019997) and (3) Indiana 
University School of Nursing. </p>

<p>Trends in Cervical Cancer Among Delivery-Related Discharges </p>

<p>The Open Nursing Journal, 2015, Volume 9 49 </p>



<p>APPENDIX A </p>

<p>List of International Classification of Diseases, 9 
th Edition, Clinical Modification Codes Used to Identify Selected 
Clinical and Behavioral Conditions. </p>

<p>Condition 
International Classification of Diseases, 9 
th Edition, Diagnosis Code </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Exposure </p>

<p>Cervical cancer 
180, 795.06, 233.1 </p>

<p>Comorbidities </p>

<p>Obesity 
278.00, 278.01, 278.03, 649.1x, V85.3x, V85.4x, V85.54, 793.91 </p>

<p>Pre-pregnancy hypertension 
401x, 402x, 403x, 404x, 405x, 642.0x, 642.1x, 642.2x, 642.7x </p>

<p>Pre-pregnancy diabetes 
249x, 250x, 648.0x </p>

<p>Coronary heart disease 
410x, 411x, 412x, 413x, 414x, 429.2 </p>

<p>Chronic renal disease 
581x, 582x, 583x, 585x, 587x, 646.2x </p>

<p>Anemia 
280x, 281x, 282x, 283x, 284x, 285x, 648.2x </p>

<p>Disorders of lipid metabolism (e.g., hyperlipidemia) 
272x </p>

<p>Hypothyroidism 
243x, 244x </p>

<p>Disorders of the adrenal glands 
255x </p>

<p>Cesarean section </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>74x </p>

<p>Gestational diabetes 
648.8x </p>

<p>Gestational hypertension 
642.3x </p>

<p>Pre-eclampsia 
642.4x, 642.5x </p>

<p>Eclampsia 
642.6x </p>

<p>Acute renal failure 
584x, 669.3x </p>

<p>HIV 
042x, 043x, 044x, 079.53, 279.10, 279.19, 795.71, 795.8, V08 </p>

<p>STD 
090.x, 091.x, 092.x, 093.x, 094.x, 095.x, 096.x, 097.x, 098.x, 099.x, 795.05, 795.15, 795.19, 
796.75, 796.69 </p>

<p>Perinatal history </p>

<p>Previous Cesarean section 
654.2x </p>

<p>Behavioral history </p>

<p>Tobacco use 
305.1, 649.0x, 989.84 </p>

<p>Alcohol use 
291x, 303x, 305.0x, 425.5, 760.71, V11.3 </p>

<p>Drug use 
292.0x, 292.1x, 292.2x, 292.8x, 304x, 305.2x, 305.3x, 305.4x, 305.5x, 305.6x, 305.7x, 305.9x, 
648.3x, 655.5x, 760.72, 779.5, 760.75, 965.00, 965.02, E935.1, E850.1 </p>

<p>Maternal outcomes </p>

<p>Anemia 
280x, 281x, 282x, 283x, 284x, 285x, 648.2x </p>

<p>Fetal outcomes </p>

<p>Preterm labor 
644.2x </p>

<p>Poor fetal growth 
656.5x </p>

<p>a The code suffix "x" represents all possible codes that follow the stated code prefix. 
b procedure codes, not diagnostic codes were used to define Cesarean section </p>



<p>Mogos et al. </p>



<p>Received: March 20, 2015 
Revised: June 2, 2015 
Accepted: June 15, 2015 </p>

<p>© Mogos et al.; Licensee Bentham Open. </p>

<p>This is an open access article licensed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) 
which permits unrestricted, non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the work is properly cited. </p>

</text></tei>