<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4874631" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Data on cardiac alterations such as left ventricular (LV) hypertrophy, diastolic 
dysfunction, and lower stroke volume in patients with COPD are discordant. In this study, we 
investigated whether early structural and functional cardiac changes occur in patients with 
COPD devoid of manifest cardiovascular disease, and we assessed their associations with 
clinical and functional features. 
Methods: Forty-nine patients with COPD belonging to all Global Initiative for Chronic 
Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) classes were enrolled and compared with 36 controls. All 
subjects underwent clinical history assessment, lung function testing, blood pressure measure-
ment, electrocardiography, and conventional and Doppler tissue echocardiography. Patients 
were also subjected to computed tomography to quantify emphysema score. 
Results: Patients with COPD had lower LV cavity associated with a marked increase in rela-
tive wall thickness (RWT), suggesting concentric remodeling without significant changes in 
LV mass. RWT was significantly associated with ratio of the forced expiratory volume in 1 
second to the forced vital capacity and emphysema score and was the only cardiac parameter 
that -after multivariate analysis -significantly correlated with COPD conditions in all individu-
als. Receiver operating characteristic curve analysis showed that RWT (with a cutoff point of 
0.42) predicted the severity of COPD with 83% specificity and 56% sensitivity (area under the 
curve =0.69, 95% confidence interval =0.59-0.81). Patients with COPD showed right ventricular 
to be functional but no structural changes. 
Conclusion: Patients with COPD without evident cardiovascular disease exhibit significant 
changes in LV geometry, resulting in concentric remodeling. In all individuals, RWT was 
significantly and independently related to COPD. However, its prognostic role should be 
determined in future studies. 
COPD is a major cause of mortality and morbidity. 
1 Extrapulmonary alterations, notably 
cardiac complications such as cor pulmonale, can be frequently observed in patients 
with COPD. In addition, coronary artery disease and heart failure may play important 
roles in mortality and morbidity in patients with COPD. 
2 Cardiovascular complica-
tions might not only be related to CODP itself but could also be due to a chronic sys-
temic inflammatory condition, in which heart and lungs are differentially involved. </p>

<p>3   Interestingly, changes in left ventricle function and structure such as left ventricular 
hypertrophy (LVH), diastolic dysfunction, and reduction in cardiac chambers and 
stroke volume have been described but might not be exclusively due to COPD. 
4-6 The 
lower preload caused by hyperinflation may be responsible for reduced left ventricular </p>

<p>Correspondence: giovanna Pelà 
Department of Clinical and experimental 
Medicine, University Medical school 
and University hospital Parma, 
Via gramsci 14, 43100 Parma, Italy 
email giovanna.pela@unipr.it </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of COPD 
13 May 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1016 </p>

<p>Pelà et al </p>

<p>(LV) and right ventricular (RV) dimensions 
4,5 yet, a causal 
link between COPD and increased LV mass (LVM) 
6 has not 
been clearly established. Notably, these authors demonstrated 
a higher (30% versus 20% in controls) prevalence of LVH in 
normoxemic, normotensive patients with COPD, unrelated 
to forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV 1 ). In that 
study, relative wall thickness (RWT) value (an index of LV 
geometry) was similar between patients with COPD and 
controls. 
6 Chronic inflammation or pronounced activation of 
the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system rather than airway 
obstruction could play major yet unclear roles. 
It is worth noting that an echocardiographic-detected 
LVH is a strong predictor of cardiovascular events, espe-
cially when combined with concentric remodeling revealed 
by an increased RWT. 
7,8 Therefore, the assessment of LV 
geometry in patients with COPD could have relevant clinical 
impacts in terms of improving risk stratification for future 
cardiovascular events and augmenting prognosis. Thus far, 
this issue remains poorly investigated. 
With the aim of characterizing cardiac remodeling in 
COPD, we selected patients from all Global Initiative for 
Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) classes, without 
history of cardiovascular disease, in order to exclude any con-
founding factor. The aims of the present work were twofold: 
1) to evaluate the influence of different degrees of airway 
obstruction and lung hyperinflation on cardiac structures by 
analyzing both the right and the left ventricles. By evaluating 
LVM and RWT, we wanted to quantify LV remodeling and the 
prevalence of LVH in COPD and 2) to study the relationship 
between LV remodeling and morbidity of a COPD cohort. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
study population </p>

<p>This study conforms to the Declaration of Helsinki and was 
approved by the Institutional Medical Ethics Committee of 
the University of Parma. All participants provided signed 
informed consent before recruitment (Protocol number 
41361). 
From 2008 to April 2015, we screened inpatients and 
outpatients of both sexes, affected by COPD ranging from 
mild-to-severe airflow obstruction, who were referred to the 
Lung Unit of the University Hospital of Parma. We selected 
only patients with COPD without previous diagnosis of car-
diac disorders such as coronary artery disease, heart failure, 
significant valvular dysfunction, cardiomyopathies, chronic 
atrial fibrillation, or pacemaker and left bundle branch blocks. 
Patients with systemic arterial hypertension higher than stage 
I and insulin-dependent diabetes were also excluded. Patients </p>

<p>with COPD were diagnosed and classified according to the 
GOLD criteria. As control group, we recruited sex-and age-
matched healthy subjects. Participants underwent spirometry 
and conventional and Doppler tissue echocardiography 
(DTE). Patients with COPD also underwent computed 
tomography (CT) scan. </p>

<p>Clinical examination </p>

<p>After recording their personal and parental medical history, 
study subjects underwent a physical examination and 12-lead 
resting electrocardiography; their blood pressure (BP) was 
determined in triplicate at 2-minute intervals (OMRON 705 
IT, Omron, Kyoto, Japan). A normal office BP was defined 
as #140/90 mmHg. 
9 Body mass index (BMI) was calculated 
in kg/m 
2 . </p>

<p>Pulmonary function testing </p>

<p>Pulmonary function was measured by a flow-sensing spiro-
meter connected to a computer for data analysis (Vmax 22 
and 6200, Sensor Medics, Yorba Linda, CA, USA). Functional 
residual capacity was measured by body plethysmography 
(Vmax 22 and 6200, Sensor Medics). Total lung capacity 
(TLC) was calculated as the sum of functional residual capacity 
and linked inspiratory capacity. Residual volume was obtained 
by subtracting vital capacity (VC) from TLC. At least three 
measurements were taken for each spirometry and lung vol-
ume variable to ensure reproducibility. Forced vital capacity 
(FVC), FEV 1 , RV, and TLC were recorded and expressed as 
percent of predicted value. FEV 1 /FVC and residual volume/ 
TLC were also recorded and expressed as a ratio. </p>

<p>Conventional and Doppler tissue 
echocardiography </p>

<p>M-mode, two-dimensional, and Doppler echocardiography 
were performed by one ultrasonography-experienced cardi-
ologist (GP), using commercially available, multihertz sector, 
2-4 MHz probe-equipped machines (Acuson Aspen, Siemens, 
Mountain View, CA, USA; Vivid S5, GE Healthcare, Wauwa-
tosa, WI, USA). The examination was feasible for screening 
cardiac parameters in all the patients with COPD, despite 
concerns that echocardiography windows might be poor. 
The interventricular septal (SWT) and posterior wall 
(PWT) thicknesses, systolic (ESD) and diastolic (EDD) LV 
diameters, absolute LVM, and indexed-to-body-surface-area 
(LVM/BSA) were calculated as previously described. </p>

<p>10,11   LVH was defined as an LVM/BSA of .95 g/m 
2 in women 
and .115 g/m 
2 in men. 
12 RWT was calculated as (SWT + 
PWT)/EDD, using the 0.42 cutoff to define eccentric (#0.42) </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1017 </p>

<p>left ventricular geometry and COPD </p>

<p>or concentric ($0.42) remodeling. 
12 Simpson's biplane rule-
based end-diastolic (EDV) and systolic (ESV) volumes and 
ejection fraction (EF) were calculated, while fractional short-
ening (FS) was calculated as ([EDV -ESV]/EDV) ×100. 
The RV cavity was measured from the long-axis parasternal 
view to extract the transversal dimension at end-diastole and 
end-systole. Using the apical four-chamber view, the longi-
tudinal axis (as the distance between the apex of the right 
ventricle and the center of the tricuspid ring) and the maximal 
transversal diameter, in the basal one-third of the RV inflow, 
were measured at the end-diastole. 
12 Pulmonary pressure was 
calculated directly by sampling the tricuspid insufficiency and 
indirectly by the acceleration time on pulmonary flow. 
Mitral and tricuspidal inflow patterns were analyzed from 
apical four-chamber view and E-and A-wave, and their ratios 
were considered as peak flow velocity and time velocity 
integral, to evaluate the conventional diastolic function of 
both ventricles. From the same projection, DTE analysis 
was performed at the lateral site and posteroseptum of mitral 
annulus and lateral site of tricuspidal annulus to assess myo-
cardial systolic (S) and diastolic (E′, A′) waves of LV and RV. 
All measurements were usually made in triplicate during 
different heart cycles, as previously reported. </p>

<p>11,13 </p>

<p>CT scan </p>

<p>Forty-three patients with COPD have been recently studied 
with 6-and 64-detector row CT scanners (Siemens Medi-
cal Solutions, Forchheim, Germany). All whole-lung CT 
scans were acquired during one deep inspiratory breath-hold 
without the use of any contrast medium. Both scanners were 
daily calibrated on air to allow reliable measurements and 
comparison between examinations. Standard 6-detector row 
CT scanner parameters were as follows: 120 kV, effective 
120 mAs, individual detector collimation 1 mm, gantry rota-
tion time of 0.5 second, and pitch 1.25. The 64-detector row 
CT scanner parameters were as follows: 120 kV, effective 
100 mAs, individual detector collimation 0.6 mm, gantry 
rotation time of 0.5 second, and pitch 1. 
CT images data were reconstructed at 1-mm-thick sec-
tions with a reconstruction increment of 1 mm and a sharp 
kernel (B70f). They were transferred to a personal computer 
running <rs id="software-0" type="software">MevisPULMO</rs> software (version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">1.4</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Fraunhofer MEVIS</rs>, Bremen, Germany) and analyzed for quantitative 
emphysema assessment by one operator (NS). A 3×3 kernel-
based axial Gauss smoothing was applied to minimize the 
noise in sharp kernel images. For the whole lung, emphysema 
extent was defined as percentage of lung voxels #-950 
Hounsfield units. </p>

<p>14   statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data are expressed as mean ± standard deviation (SD) or 
median (interquartile range) depending on the normality 
of data, assessed by using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. 
Consequently, controls and patients with COPD were com-
pared for each variable using parametric or nonparametric 
univariate statistics (Student's t-test or Mann-Whitney test). 
Pearson correlations were performed to analyze the associa-
tions between variables of lung function (such as GOLD 
class, spirometry data, and emphysema score) and cardiac 
chamber size. 
Multiple regression analysis was used to analyze the rela-
tionship between COPD disease and the echocardiographic-
based variables (LVM, RWT, and LV EDD), with age, heart 
rate (HR), BMI, and systolic BP or pulmonary pressure, 
respectively, for LV or RV parameters as the covariates. 
Smoking habits, FEV 1 , and FEV 1 /FVC were not included in 
the analysis as collinear with the presence of COPD disease 
(R-values .0.5 and variance inflation factor in multivariate 
models .2). 
To test if RWT was predictive of the severity of COPD 
disease in patients with COPD, receiver operating character-
istic (ROC) curve was done reporting the area under curve 
(AUC) value as general diagnostic tool, and the flex point, 
ie, where the sum of sensitivity and specificity reached a 
maximum, was used to divide the patients with COPD into 
two groups. 
Hospitalizations for patients with COPD were considered 
as 1) overall number of hospitalizations for COPD and/or 
CV events normalized for observation time, rounding the 
number as integer in 10 years and 2) time elapsing from 
the start of the study and the first hospitalization. In the first 
case, because of the distribution of hospitalization, an over-
dispersed Poisson regression model was performed. In the 
second case, a Cox regression model was applied. In both 
cases, the categorical variable RWT # cutoff point and . 
cutoff point was used. 
A two-tailed P-value ,0.05 was always considered as 
significant. <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">22.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>, Armonk, NY, 
USA) was used for all the statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Results 
Patients' characteristics </p>

<p>We scrutinized 56 COPD inpatients and outpatients. Seven 
patients with negative cardiovascular history were excluded 
during enrollment because of a mild valvular and/or dilative 
heart disease as detected by echocardiography. A total 
of 49 patients (45-85 years old) were finally enrolled. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Pelà et al </p>

<p>In 43 patients, CT scans were available. We screened 36 
healthy volunteers without previous history of respiratory, car-
diovascular, and metabolic disorders as the control group. 
The clinical data of patients with COPD and of their 
controls are presented in Table 1. Patients were slightly older 
than controls, but both groups matched for sex and anthropo-
metric parameters such as BMI and BSA. Systolic and dia-
stolic BPs of the two groups were superimposable, but HR was 
higher in patients than in controls. Smoking habits and medical 
history of hypertension were greater in COPD (P,0.001 and 
P,0.05, respectively). No significant difference was observed 
in the history of diabetes mellitus (Table 1). 
Pulmonary function values are listed in Table 2. All the 
GOLD-4 classes were homogenously (21%, 35%, 29%, </p>

<p>and 15%) represented. The emphysema score was 18%±13% 
ranging from 1% to 53%. A total of 33 (68%) patients with 
COPD received inhaled β2 agonist agents, 26 (53%) received 
inhaled steroids, and 17 (35%) received inhaled muscarinic 
antagonists. The majority of hypertensive individuals were 
treated with a monotherapy of antihypertensive agents, while 
only six patients with COPD received a combination therapy 
(four COPD and one control with β-blockers, 18 COPD and 
three controls with angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibi-
tors/angiotensin receptor blockers, and five COPD and one 
control with calcium antagonists). 
During follow-up (42.2 [SD: 20.7] months), seven 
patients with COPD died and 16 were hospitalized once 
or more for respiratory or cardiac complications (only two 
because of cardiovascular events). </p>

<p>echocardiography </p>

<p>Patients with COPD, as compared with controls, exhibited a 
significant decrease of LV chamber size as assessed by EDD 
and EDV, which was associated with a significant increase in 
SWT and a mild, nonsignificant increase in PWT. Therefore, 
RWT was markedly higher in patients, suggesting that concen-
tric remodeling occurs in COPD (Table 3). The absolute and 
indexed LVM were similar in the two groups as was the per-
centage of patients with positive ECHO criteria for LVH. 
LV systolic functions, assessed by FS and EF, were simi-
lar between the two groups, but stroke volume was lower in 
COPD versus controls (Table 4). The mitral inflow pattern 
showed significant reduction of the E/A ratios in patients 
with COPD, but no significant differences in systolic and 
diastolic functions were detected by DTE between the two 
groups (Table 4). </p>

<p>Table 1 anthropometric and clinical data </p>

<p>Parameter 
COPD 
(n=49) </p>

<p>Controls 
(n=36) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>age (years) 
66.3±9.1 62.7±6.5 ,0.05 
Male/female (%) 
76/24 
69/31 
ns 
height (cm) 
1.7±0.1 
1.7±0.1 
ns 
Weight (kg) 
72±13 
75±10 
ns 
BMI (kg/m 
2 ) 
25.3±4.0 25.8±3.0 ns 
Bsa (m 
2 ) 
1.8±0.2 
1.9±0.2 
ns 
sBP (mmhg) 
132±12 
131±11 
ns 
DBP (mmhg) 
82±8 
83±5 
ns 
hr (beats-per-minute) 
77±13 
67±8 
,0.001 
smokers (active and non) (%) 
90 
31 
,0.001 
arterial hypertension history I stage (%) 43 
19 
,0.05 
Diabetes mellitus (%) 
6 
0 
ns 
no hospitalization (%) 
32/49 (66) 0 
1 hospitalization (%) 
8 (16.7) 
-
.1 hospitalization (%) 
8 (16.7) 
-</p>

<p>Note: Data are mean ± standard deviation or percentage. 
Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; Bsa, body surface area; DBP, diastolic 
blood pressure; HR, heart rate; ns, nonsignificant; SBP, systolic blood pressure. </p>

<p>Table 2 lung functional characteristics </p>

<p>Spirometry and 
pletismography </p>

<p>COPD 
(n=49) </p>

<p>Controls 
(n=36) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>FeV 1 (l) 
1.6±0.8 
3.1±0.6 
,0.0001 
FeV 1 (%) 
57±25 
106±13 
,0.0001 
FVC (l) 
3.0±1.0 
4.0±0.8 
,0.0001 
FeV 1 /FVC 
49±12 
75±5 
,0.0001 
residual volume (l) 
3.4±1.3 
2.9±1.0 
ns 
residual volume (%) 
149±55 
126±46 
ns 
TlC (l) 
6.9±1.5 
7.2±1.4 
ns 
TlC (%) 
115±23 
115±20 
ns 
rV/TlC 
48±13 
41±16 
0.05 </p>

<p>Note: Data mean ± standard deviation or percentage. 
Abbreviations: FeV 1 , forced expiratory volume in 1 second; FVC, forced vital 
capacity; ns, nonsignificant; RV, right ventricular; TLC, total lung capacity. </p>

<p>Table 3 Cardiac structural characteristics assessed by echo-
cardiography </p>

<p>LV morphologic 
parameters </p>

<p>COPD 
(n=49) </p>

<p>Controls 
(n=36) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>end-diastolic diameter (mm) 
45±6 
48±4 
,0.01 
end-systolic diameter (mm) 
28±6 
29±5 
ns 
end-diastolic volume (ml) 
90±27 
101±18 
,0.05 
end-systolic volume (ml) 
29±12 
32±11 
ns 
septal thickness (mm) 
9.8±1.6 
9.0±1.4 
,0.05 
Posterior wall thickness (mm) 
9.4±1.4 
8.9±1.9 
ns 
rWT 
0.44±0.09 
0.37±0.05 
,0.001 
lVM (g) 
183±54 
191±50 
ns 
lVM/Bsa (g/m 
2 ) 
99±24 
100±22 
ns 
lV hypertrophy (%) 
36 
44 
ns </p>

<p>Note: Data mean ± standard deviation or percentage. 
Abbreviations: Bsa, body surface area; lV, left ventricular; lVM, left ventricular 
mass; rWT, relative wall thickness. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1019 </p>

<p>left ventricular geometry and COPD </p>

<p>Table 5 reports the results of RV assessment. A mild 
but nonsignificant increase in ventricular dimensions was 
observed in patients with COPD. The tricuspidal E-wave and 
the myocardial E′, E′/A′ ratios and S′-wave, all assessed as 
time-velocity integral, were reduced, suggesting impairments 
of both systolic and diastolic functions. Pulmonary pressure 
estimated by tricuspidal insufficiency was increased, and 
the acceleration time of pulmonary ejection was reduced in 
patients with COPD (Table 5). 
After univariate analysis, RWT was strongly correlated 
with FEV 1 , FEV 1 /FVC, GOLD class, and emphysema 
scores. EDD and EDV showed significant correlations only 
with the emphysema score. Finally, SWT correlated with 
FEV 1 , GOLD class, and CT score but not with FEV 1 /FVC 
(Table 6). 
Multiple regression analysis was performed to test 
the association between LV echocardiographic-derived 
parameters (RWT, SWT, EDD, and EDV) as outcomes and 
age, sex, BMI, systolic BP, HR, and the clinical condition 
(controls or COPD) as predictors (Table 7). Only RWT was 
associated with COPD. All echocardiographic variables -but 
not SWT -were related to HR. Sex, as expected, 
15 influenced 
LV structure. No association was found between the RV 
parameters and COPD. </p>

<p>ROC curve analysis showed that RWT, with a cutoff point 
of 0.40, predicted the severity of the disease with an 83% 
specificity and a 56% sensitivity (AUC =0.69, 95% CI =0.59-
0.81). Patients with COPD with RWT .0.40 versus patients 
with RWT #0.40 (RWT_CAT variable) showed a significant 
reduction of FEV 1 /FVC (P=0.017) and a significant increase 
in emphysema score (P=0.033), whereas FEV 1 and residual 
volume/TLC were not significantly different. 
Univariate statistics showed that RWT was associated 
with a higher number of hospitalizations (P=0.034). How-
ever, in the multivariate Poisson regression model including 
age, systolic BP, HR, body surface area, and FEV 1 /FVC, 
we did not detect significant differences, with FEV 1 /FVC 
(exp[B] =0.87 [0.79-0.95], P=0.003) and age (exp[B] =1.11 
[1.01-1.21], P=0.023) being the only significantly different 
variables. 
Data from the previous analysis were confirmed when 
the time between enrollment and first hospitalization was 
considered. Specifically, in a Cox regression model with the 
same covariates, age (HR =1.08 [1.00-1.17], P=0.047) and 
FEV 1 /FVC (HR =0.88 [0.80-0.96], P=0.005) were the only 
significantly different variables. </p>

<p>Table 4 left ventricular functional characteristics assessed by 
echocardiography </p>

<p>Parameter 
COPD 
(n=49) </p>

<p>Controls 
(n=36) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Fs (%) 
40±12 
42±6 
ns 
eF (%) 
69±6 
68±7 
ns 
sV (ml) 
61±17 
69±11 
,0.05 
Mitral e pv (cm/s) 
53.6±13.6 
58.3±13.2 
ns 
Mitral e tvi (cm) 
8.8±2.6 
10.2±2.0 
,0.05 
Mitral a pv (cm/s) 
69.8±12.3 
67.1±11.8 
ns 
Mitral a tvi (cm) 
8.4±1.9 
8.4±2.5 
ns 
Mitral e/a pv (cm/s) 
0.8±0.2 
0.9±0.1 
ns 
Mitral e/a tvi (cm) 
1.1±0.3 
1.3±0.4 
,0.01 
DTe s pv (cm/s) 
10.7±2.2 
10.6±2.1 
ns 
DTe s tvi (cm) 
2.1±0.8 
2.1±0.4 
ns </p>

<p>DTe e′ pv (cm/s) 
10.0±2.6 
9.8±2.4 
ns </p>

<p>DTe e′ tvi (cm) 
1.1±0.3 
1.1±0.4 
ns </p>

<p>DTe a′ pv (cm/s) 
13.9±3.1 
13.9±2.6 
ns </p>

<p>DTe a′ tvi (cm) 
1.2±0.3 
1.2±0.3 
ns </p>

<p>DTe e′/a′ pv 
0.9±0.9 
0.8±0.3 
ns </p>

<p>DTe e′/a′ tvi 
0.9±0.3 
0.9±0.4 
ns </p>

<p>Notes: Data mean ± standard deviation. Values from DTe analysis are the mean of 
septal and lateral walls. 
Abbreviations: a′, end-diastolic myocardial wave; DTe, Doppler tissue 
echocardiography; e′, proto-diastolic myocardial wave; eF, ejection fraction; Fs, 
fraction of shortening; pv, peak velocity; s, systolic myocardial wave; sV, stroke 
volume; tvi, time velocity integral. </p>

<p>Table 5 right ventricular characteristics assessed by echo-
cardiography </p>

<p>Right ventricle 
COPD 
(n=49) </p>

<p>Controls 
(n=36) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>end-diastolic diameter (mm) 
35.2±5.2 
33.4±4.1 
ns </p>

<p>end-systolic diameter (mm) 
25.2±4.7 
24.1±3.9 
ns </p>

<p>Trasversal diameter (mm) 
36.8±6.5 
36.3±5.1 
ns </p>

<p>longitudinal diameter (mm) 
65.7±8.7 
65.2±7.2 
ns </p>

<p>DTe s pv (cm/s) 
15.4±4.2 
16.1±4.2 
ns </p>

<p>DTe s tvi (cm) 
2.9±0.9 
3.2±0.7 
,0.05 
Tricuspid e pv (cm/s) 
40.9±8.9 
40.9±8.7 
ns </p>

<p>Tricuspid e tvi (cm) 
6.6±2.2 
7.7±2.1 
,0.05 
Tricuspid a pv (cm/s) 
42.5±9.5 
40.1±7.1 
ns </p>

<p>Tricuspid a tvi (cm) 
5.0±1.5 
5.1±1.4 
ns </p>

<p>DTe e′ pv (cm/s) 
13.1±4.0 
14.6±3.7 
ns </p>

<p>DTe e′ tvi (cm) 
2.1±0.8 
2.5±0.7 
0.01 </p>

<p>DTe a′ pv (cm/s) 
18.3±4.3 
18.5±4.2 
ns </p>

<p>DTe a′ tvi (cm) 
1.9±0.5 
1.9±0.5 
ns </p>

<p>Tricuspid e/a pv 
1.0±0.2 
1.0±0.3 
ns </p>

<p>Tricuspid e/a tvi 
1.4±0.5 
1.6±0.5 
ns </p>

<p>DTe e′/a′ pv 
0.7±0.2 
0.8±0.2 
ns </p>

<p>DTe e′/a′ tvi 
1.1±0.4 
1.3±0.3 
,0.05 
Pulmonary pressure (mmhg) 
30.9±8.2 
25.8±3.4 
,0.01 
AT on pulmonary flow (ms) 
119±29 
144±22 
,0.001 </p>

<p>Note: Data are mean ± standard deviation. 
Abbreviations: a′, end-diastolic myocardial wave; aT, acceleration time; DTe, 
Doppler tissue echocardiography; e′, proto-diastolic myocardial wave; pv, peak 
velocity; tvi, time velocity integral; s, systolic myocardial wave. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1020 </p>

<p>Pelà et al </p>

<p>Finally, overall patient survival was not considered in the 
statistical analysis because only seven patients died during 
our study. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The main finding of our study is that COPD is associated 
with LV structural changes characterized by a decrease in 
EDD and EDV as well as an alteration of ventricular geom-
etry, notably concentric remodeling. Other authors who 
used echocardiographic techniques and nuclear magnetic 
resonance 
,5,16 reported the relationship between COPD and 
decreased LV size, but this is the first report that provides 
evidence of direct links between pulmonary function, CT 
score, and LV geometry. 
In our study, patients with COPD had an increased RWT 
compared with controls; on average, the former showed 
RWT values .0.42, which was considered as the cutoff 
point beyond which concentric remodeling was diagnosed. </p>

<p>17   In addition, a more severe degree of respiratory disease was 
associated with a greater increase of concentric remodel-
ing, as indicated by the significant relationship between LV 
geometry and GOLD class, spirometry parameters, and CT 
emphysema score. Furthermore, the outcome of a multivariate 
statistical analysis including LV echocardiographic-derived 
parameters (RWT, SWT, EDD, and EDV) as dependent 
variables and age, sex, BMI, BP, HR and the clinical COPD </p>

<p>condition as predictors showed that only RWT was inde-
pendently related to COPD, whereas no relationship was 
observed with the other echocardiographic parameters. 
Our study does not confirm the LVH in COPD reported 
by Anderson et al. 
6 The absolute and indexed LVM was 
unchanged in our patients as compared with controls. It is 
noteworthy that our results are in agreement with those 
previously reported by echocardiography 
18 with the highly 
sophisticated technique -nuclear magnetic resonance. </p>

<p>4   Differences in the selection criteria may explain these 
discrepancies. For example, unlike the study by Anderson 
et al, 
6 our patients belonged to all GOLD classes. More-
over, our population included only patients with grade 1 
hypertension, treated mostly by monotherapy. We excluded 
hypertensive patients affected by grades 2 and 3 hypertension. 
A greater systolic BP in COPD versus controls, as demon-
strated by the ambulatory and 24-hour monitoring and the 
number of antihypertensive-per-treated patients with COPD 
(median =2), has also been reported by Anderson et al. </p>

<p>6   In addition, the age differences in our cohort were low (mean 
difference ~3 years), albeit weakly statistically significant. By 
contrast, in the study by Anderson et al, 
6 the COPD group was, 
on average, 10 years older than the controls. This ~10-year 
age difference between the two groups may be critical because 
population studies report that age is a strong determinant 
of LVM, independent of height, weight, and sex, both in </p>

<p>Table 7 Multiple regression analysis of the predicting relationship of COPD status with the echocardiographic-based variables, ie, 
rWT, eDV, eDD, and sWT </p>

<p>Variable 
RWT (R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=0.30) 
EDD (R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=0.35) 
EDV (R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=0.41) 
SWT (R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=0.34) </p>

<p>β (SE) 
Sig 
β (SE) 
Sig 
β (SE) 
Sig 
β (SE) 
Sig </p>

<p>COPD 
0.039 (0.017) 
0.027 
-1.83 (1.17) 
0.12 
-6.08 (4.77) 
0.21 
0.53 (0.32) 
0.11 
age 
0.001 (0.001) 
0.74 
-0.034 (0.077) 
0.66 
-0.31 (0.31) 
0.33 
0.018 (0.021) 
0.40 
sex 
-0.057 (0.021) 
0.009 
-2.63 (1.44) 
0.072 
-17.05 (5.89) 
0.005 
-1.65 (0.40) 
,0.001 
sBP 
-0.001 (0.001) 
0.062 
0.086 (0.050) 
0.090 
0.46 (0.20) 
0.021 
-0.035 (0.014) 
0.012 
BMI 
-0.005 (0.002) 
0.059 
0.39 (0.17) 
0.024 
1.14 (0.66) 
0.091 
0.038 (0.046) 
0.72 
hr 
0.002 (0.001) 
0.011 
-0.16 (0.05) 
0.003 
-0.76 (0.20) 
,0.001 
0.010 (0.014) 
0.82 </p>

<p>Notes: Age, HR, BMI, and SBP were considered as the covariates. Only RWT was significantly associated with COPD status. Data with statistical significance are shown in bold. 
Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; eDD, end-diastolic diameter; eDV, end-diastolic volume; hr, heart rate; rWT, relative wall thickness; se, standard error; sBP, systolic 
blood pressure; sWT, septal wall thickness. </p>

<p>Table 6 Correlations between lung function, CT score, and cardiac chamber size values </p>

<p>Variable 
EDD 
EDV 
RWT 
SWT </p>

<p>r 
P-value 
r 
P-value 
r 
P-value 
r 
P-value </p>

<p>FeV 1 
0.10 
ns 
0.16 
ns 
-0.35 
,0.05 
-0.32 
,0.05 
FeV 1 /FVC 
0.17 
ns 
0.18 
ns 
-0.34 
,0.05 
-0.22 
ns 
gOlD class 
-0.15 
ns 
-0.21 
ns 
0.36 
,0.01 
0.33 
,0.05 
CT score 
-0.36 
,0.01 
-0.28 
,0.05 
0.41 
,0.01 
0.28 
,0.05 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CT, computed tomography; eDD, left ventricular end-diastolic diameter; eDV, left ventricular end-diastolic volume; FeV 1 , forced expiratory volume in 
1 second; FVC, forced vital capacity; GOLD, Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease; ns, nonsignificant; RWT, relative wall thickness; SWT, septal wall 
thickness. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1021 </p>

<p>left ventricular geometry and COPD </p>

<p>childhood and in adults. 
19,20 In turn, the previously observed 
differences in LVM between COPD and controls could be 
mainly related to the different ages of the two groups. 
Although we did not find any difference in LVH between 
the two groups, our patients with COPD exhibited a signifi-
cant increase in RWT as compared with controls. This is cru-
cial to stratify cardiovascular risk in the general population, as 
a concentric LV remodeling (normal LV mass with increased 
RWT) is a well-known negative prognostic factor. </p>

<p>7,17   As previously demonstrated by Barr et al, 
16 the extent of 
emphysema on CT scanning was linearly related to cardiac 
dimensions expressed by EDD and EDV: a greater magnitude 
of emphysema corresponds to a greater reduction in LV cavity 
size. Several explanations have been proposed to explain the 
relationship between COPD and microcardia. First, there 
is a lower preload in left cardiac chambers mediated by an 
intrathoracic hypovolemia and a decrease of the pulmonary 
vascular bed caused by dynamic hyperinflation. 
4 This mecha-
nism may explain not only the reductions in LV diameters 
and volumes but also the lower stroke volumes 
16 and the 
supposed LV diastolic dysfunction found at the transmitral 
Doppler analysis. 
21 Indeed, the inflow pattern is not only an 
index of ventricular relaxation and compliance, but it is also 
influenced by others variables such as the preload and the 
HR. A lower preload can mimic an impaired LV relaxation 
in normal functioning heart. 
22 More sophisticated techniques, 
such as DTE, which analyzes the contraction and relaxation 
velocities directly on the myocardium, are less influenced 
by ventricular loads and provide more sensitive indexes of 
diastolic function. 
22-24 In our study, the E/A ratio from the 
mitral inflow pattern was significantly reduced in COPD, but 
the myocardial S-and E′-waves were preserved, excluding an 
impairment in the LV systolic and diastolic function. 
A leftward shift of the interventricular septum consequent 
to the increased right ventricular afterload could cause a 
decrease in LV cavity size. 
21,25 However, this premise is not 
entirely convincing because, in our study, the configuration 
of this wall did not differ between the two groups, and we 
did not find any significant RV enlargement despite the sig-
nificant increase in pulmonary artery pressure. Our findings 
are in agreement with previous studies 
4,5 that found even 
smaller RV secondary to the hyperinflation and subsequent 
lower preload to both heart chambers. In addition, patients 
with COPD had impaired RV systolic and diastolic func-
tions, as demonstrated by the significant reductions of S-and 
E′-waves, which were significantly related only to pulmonary 
artery pressure but not to CT score or FEV 1 /FVC. In sum-
mary, we report structural and functional cardiac changes </p>

<p>in COPD, but only RWT was independently related to the 
COPD condition (after multivariate analysis). 
To verify if RWT predicted the severity of the disease, 
we divided the COPD cohort into two groups according to 
the ROC curves analysis, and we observed that patients with 
RWT .0.40 were sicker, with more pronounced reduction 
in FEV 1 /FVC and more increase in CT score. The prognos-
tic role of RWT was also assessed in relation to respira-
tory and cardiac hospitalizations: only after the univariate 
statistics, but not after multivariate Poisson analysis, cardiac 
geometry was significantly related to this event, with age 
and FEV 1 /FVC being the only strong predictors. These 
analyses did not show LV geometry as morbidity predictor, 
confirming the role of age and clinical variables; however, 
we speculate that, in a larger series of patients, this structural 
cardiac index may prove a useful marker of hospitalization 
risk. During the follow-up, seven deaths occurred, but, 
owing to the limited number of fatal events, overall patient 
survival was not considered in the statistical analysis. How-
ever, the comparisons between survivors and nonsurvivors 
revealed that RWT was significantly higher (0.52 versus 0.42, 
P=0.014) in nonsurvivors, suggesting its potential prognostic 
value as mortality predictor, which has to be confirmed in 
the future with a greater number of fatal events. </p>

<p>Limitations and strengths </p>

<p>The first limitation of our study is the limited number of 
patients. We must emphasize that all enrolled subjects were 
thoroughly screened and selected for the absence of any 
significant comorbidities with effects on the structure and 
heart function. The average age of the two groups (.60 years) 
is the one in which it is difficult to encounter subjects free of 
cardiovascular disease, hypertension, or diabetes. 
The strength of the present study is that a single expert 
investigator recruited and appraised patients and per-
formed all echocardiographies, thus reducing analytical 
variability. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>We demonstrated that significant alterations -typified by a 
concentric remodeling -exist in the LV geometry of patients 
with COPD. LV geometry, compared with LVM, is a little-
known marker of cardiovascular risk. Such structural LV 
modifications are not associated with an increased LVM or 
with LV systolic and diastolic dysfunctions. RWT appears 
to be the only cardiac parameter independently related to 
COPD and could help identify those patients at greatest risk 
of cardiac complications. Further studies are warranted to </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-chronic-obstructive-pulmonary-disease-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of COPD is an international, peer-reviewed 
journal of therapeutics and pharmacology focusing on concise rapid 
reporting of clinical studies and reviews in COPD. Special focus is given 
to the pathophysiological processes underlying the disease, intervention 
programs, patient focused education, and self management protocols. </p>

<p>This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, MedLine and CAS. The 
manuscript management system is completely online and includes a 
very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1022 </p>

<p>Pelà et al </p>

<p>ascertain whether LV geometry is related to morbidity and 
mortality in COPD. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>The authors would like to acknowledge Dr Francesco Visioli, 
who critically revised the manuscript. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



</text></tei>