<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4755524" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Full-length (FL) cDNA sequences provide the most reliable evidence for the presence of genes in gen-
omes. In this report, detailed gene structures of barley, whole genome shotgun (WGS) and additional 
transcript data of the cultivar Haruna Nijo were quality controlled and compared with the published 
Morex genome information. Haruna Nijo scaffolds have longer total sequence length with much 
higher N50 and fewer sequences than those in Morex WGS contigs. The longer Haruna Nijo scaffolds 
provided efficient FLcDNA mapping, resulting in high coverage and detection of the transcription 
start sites. In combination with FLcDNAs and RNA-Seq data from four different tissue samples of 
Haruna Nijo, we identified 51,249 gene models on 30,606 loci. Overall sequence similarity between 
Haruna Nijo and Morex genome was 95.99%, while that of exon regions was higher (99.71%). These 
sequence and annotation data of Haruna Nijo are combined with Morex genome data and released 
from a genome browser. The genome sequence of Haruna Nijo may provide detailed gene structures 
in addition to the current Morex barley genome information. </p>

<p>Barley (Hordeum vulgare L.) is used for many purposes including 
human food, malting and animal feed. Coupled with its wide adaptabil-
ity in environments ranging from the highlands of Africa at the equator 
to the Arctic Regions in Scandinavia, barley is the fourth most important 
cereal crop (http://faostat.fao.org, 7 November 2015, date accessed). In 
addition, barley is an ancient crop that was domesticated ca. 10,000 yrs 
ago in the Fertile Crescent. 1 Decades of collection and curation of barley 
germplasm have resulted in substantial germplasm collections including: 
IPK (Germany), USDA-ARS (USA) and Okayama University (Japan). 2 
To fully exploit these in situ and ex situ collections for barley breeding 
and gene discovery, barley genome sequences of multiple genotypes are 
needed. </p>

<p>To generate the first genome sequence of barley, the International 
Barley Sequencing Consortium (IBSC) conducted BAC fingerprinting, 
BAC end sequencing, whole genome shotgun (WGS) sequencing, 
RNA-Seq analysis and genetic mapping and integrated these data to 
develop a gene-based genome sequence of the North American six-
row spring malting barley cultivar Morex. 3 Morex traces to barley 
germplasm of Manchurian origin with six-row inflorescence, which 
is not common for malting barleys other than the USA. Currently, 
Morex is the reference genome for barley genetics studies, and add-
itional efforts are in progress to improve the Morex genome se-
quence. 4,5 Three other barley genomes including Bowman, Barke 
and a Tibetan hulless genotype have been WGS sequenced 3,6 and pro-
vide additional sequence information for comparison to Morex. </p>

<p>DNA Research, 2016, 23(1), 21-28 
doi: 10.1093/dnares/dsv033 </p>

<p>Advance Access Publication Date: 29 November 2015 </p>

<p>Full Paper </p>

<p>© The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Kazusa DNA Research Institute. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any 
medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com </p>



<p>Haruna Nijo is a Japanese malting barley cultivar exhibiting excel-
lent malting quality for brewing beer. Historically, Japanese malting 
barleys have been developed by crossing European malting barley cul-
tivars and Japanese landraces and selecting for malting quality and 
adaptation to Japanese environments. Haruna Nijo was also devel-
oped by this approach in 1979 and has been extensively used as a 
foundation genotype of current Japanese breeding. Haruna Nijo has 
a high thermostability of β-amylase, 7 and it also shows different 
Bmy1 allele for β-amylase activity from Morex. 8 It is also shown 
that Haruna Nijo has a high malt extract (related to beer production) 
by QTL analysis. 9 To enhance the utility of Haruna Nijo for breeding, 
a suite of genomics resources were developed including: an EST collec-
tion, transcript map construction, 10,11 a BAC library, 12 454-based 
WGS sequencing 3 and full-length (FL) cDNA sequencing and 
analysis 13,14 (available at http://barleyflc.dna.affrc.go.jp/bexdb/, 7 
November 2015, date accessed, with functions of expression profiling 
and genome browsing). 
In the case of barley genome resources, the Morex reference gen-
ome and the Haruna Nijo FLcDNA sequences provide unique re-
sources in different genotypes. Thus, to enhance the utility of both 
resources they need to be compared and integrated. Sequence compar-
isons of the two different malting barley haplotypes will be much more 
useful than single haplotype information, as they provide the basis of 
structural and functional allelic diversity. Previous comparisons of 
WGS data and FLcDNA sequences from Haruna Nijo and the genome 
sequence from Morex demonstrated a large amount of sequence poly-
morphisms between the two genotypes. 3 For example, the genetic dis-
tance (dissimilarity) between Morex and Haruna Nijo by 1,536 SNPs 
of Illumina GoldenGate Assay is 0.50, which is larger than the differ-
ence (0.48) between Morex and Akashinriki (Japanese food barley). 15 
Thus, the Haruna Nijo FLcDNA and WGS sequences may provide 
useful gene annotations for the reference genotype Morex and a 
resource for future breeding and gene discovery activities. 
Our overall goal is to provide genome information of Haruna Nijo 
to annotate gene structures on the genome sequence of Morex. The 
four specific objectives of this study were to (i) generate high-quality 
genomic sequence of Haruna Nijo, (ii) map the precise position 
of genes identified in the Haruna Nijo genome, (iii) compare gene 
information between Haruna Nijo and Morex, and (iv) develop 
gene models based on the Haruna Nijo sequence data. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Plant materials and nucleic acid isolation </p>

<p>For DNA and RNA isolation from seedling tissues, seeds of Haruna 
Nijo were germinated on moist filter paper in Petri dishes at 20°C in 
the dark. For DNA isolation, shoots of ca. 5 cm were harvested and 
high-quality genomic DNA was isolated by DNeasy Plant Mini Kit 
(QIAGEN K.K., Japan). For RNA isolation, seedling shoot and seed-
ling root tissues were sampled from plants exhibiting 5 cm shoots. For 
the RNA samples from immature spike and immature seed samples, 
barley seeds were planted in pot with soil mixture (N: 120 mg l −1 ; P: 
100 mg l −1 ; K: 160 mg l −1 , pH 5.5) and grown in the greenhouse at 
20/15°C day/night temperature under natural light conditions. Imma-
ture spike samples were harvested from the leaf sheath 5 days before 
heading. Immature seeds were sampled 35 days after flowering 
(soft dough stage). Total RNA from immature seeds was isolated by 
TRIzol ® Reagent (Life Technologies, Japan) following the Plant 
RNA Isolation protocol. All RNA samples were purified by RNeasy 
Plant Mini Kit (QIAGEN K.K., Japan), and DNA was removed by 
RNase-Free DNase Set (QIAGEN K.K., Japan). </p>

<p>2.2. Library development </p>

<p>2.2.1. 454 long paired-end library 
The high-quality genomic DNA was fragmented in 8 k and 20 k by the 
Hydroshear (Digilab Inc., Holliston, MA, USA). The library was de-
veloped by a library preparation kit (Roche diagnostics, Japan) for 
long paired-end libraries (8 k and 20 k). Circularization was per-
formed according to the Roche Paired End Library Protocol, using 
Roche circularization adapters (Paired End Library Preparation Meth-
od Manual 20 kb and 8 kb Span; Roche Diagnostics, October 2009, 
Steps 3.1-3.7.3). Subsequently, the circularized fragments were 
fragmented again by nebulization to develop a sequencing library. </p>

<p>2.2.2. Illumina HiSeq sequencing library 
DNA (2 µg) was fragmented by nebulization. Libraries were prepared 
according to the manufacturer's instruction 'Preparing Samples for 
Paired-End Sequencing, Part # 1005063 Rev. A June 2008' of TruSeq 
DNA Sample Prep Kit (Illumina Japan). DNA fragments were size se-
lected (500 bp) following the Low-Throughput Protocol of TruSeq 
DNA Sample Prep Kit (Illumina Japan). The quality of the library 
(fragment length distribution) was checked by Agilent Bioanalyzer 
High Sensitivity DNA Assay (Agilent Technologies, Japan) and 
KAPA Library Quantification Kit (KK4835, Kapa Biosystems, MA, 
USA). </p>

<p>2.2.3. MiSeq RNA sequencing library 
Libraries for RNA-Seq analysis were developed from each RNA sam-
ple using TruSeq RNA Sample Prep Kit V2 (Illumina Japan). The 
protocol of TruSeq RNA Sample Preparation V2 Guide (Illumina 
Japan) was used with modification of fragment isolation from agarose 
gel electrophoresis and elution in EB (elution buffer) following the 
method in the TruSeq Sample Preparation Guide (Illumina Japan). 
The library was quantified with Agilent High Sensitivity DNA Kit 
(Agilent Technologies Japan) and Qubit 2.0 Fluorometer (Life Tech-
nologies Japan). </p>

<p>2.3. Sequencing </p>

<p>2.3.1. 454 FLX Titanium platform 
Each library was emulsion PCR amplified. The PCR-amplified frag-
ments on beads were washed, and the bead number was counted 
using a Coulter Counter Z1 single threshold instrument (Beckman 
Coulter Japan). The appropriate number of beads was applied on a 
pico titre plate according to the manufacturer's protocol. The FLX Ti-
tanium platform was used for sequencing (average read length 
500 bp). The pyrosequencing reaction data were base-called to gener-
ate sff format files using the software installed on the analysis server of 
the 454 sequencer (Roche diagnostics, Japan). </p>

<p>2.3.2. Illumina HiSeq platform 
The shotgun library was sequenced on an Illumina HiSeq 2000 to pro-
duce 2 × 101 paired-end reads. Raw data processing, base calling and 
quality control were performed with manufacture's standard pipeline. 
The quality of the output sequences was inspected using the FastQC 
program (http://www.bioinformatics.bbsrc.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/, 7 
November 2015, date accessed). </p>

<p>2.3.3. Illumina MiSeq RNA sequencing 
The RNA-Seq library was sequenced with MiSeq Reagent Kit V3 (2 
× 300 bp cycles) on MiSeq NGS system according to the MiSeq System </p>



<p>User Guide (Illumina Japan) and fastq files were generated from both 
ends of the fragments. </p>

<p>2.4. Assembly, sequence trimming and repeat masking </p>

<p>2.4.1. WGS assembly 
Illimina PE reads, 454 single-end reads and 454 long paired-end reads 
were hybrid assembled by the de novo assemble algorithm of CLC As-
sembly Cell ver. 3.2.2 installed on a linux server with a main memory 
of 256 Gb. </p>

<p>2.4.2. Sequence trimming and repeat masking 
Human, fungi (33 species) and microbial (2,777 species) nucleotide se-
quence data were obtained from NCBI. Each assembled contig sequence 
was queried on sequences of these species, and the contigs showing &gt;80% 
identity and &gt;50% of cumulative coverage by blastn 16 were assumed as 
alien sequences against the barley genome. For repeat masking, fasta 
files of Triticeae repeat sequence database (TREP Release 10: n = 1,717) </p>

<p>were downloaded from GrainGenes (http://wheat.pw.usda.gov/ITMI/ 
Repeats/, 7 November 2015, date accessed). In addition, new repetitive 
elements were generated from the Haruna Nijo genome assembly by 
RepeatModeler (http://www.repeatmasker.org/RepeatModeler.html, 7 
November 2015, date accessed). These two libraries were used for repeat 
masking the Haruna Nijo assembly by censor 17 with -mode norm mode. 
For the analysis of repeat distribution, only results of repeat masking by the 
TREP library were used. For comparison, genomes of Triticum aesti-
vum, 18 Triticum urartu 19 and Aegilops tauschii 20 were repeat masked in 
a similar manner as the Haruna Nijo genome. </p>

<p>2.5. FLcDNA/RNA-Seq mapping </p>

<p>2.5.1. FLcDNA mapping 
Of the two independent projects, 13,14 5,006 FLcDNAs were retrieved 
from NCBI 13 and 23,614 FLcDNAs 14 were downloaded from the 
bex-db (http://barleyflc.dna.affrc.go.jp/bexdb/). 21 Morex genome as-
sembly (contigs) was retrieved from the PGSB PlantsDB database 
(http://pgsb.helmholtz-muenchen.de/plant/plantsdb.jsp, 7 November 
2015, date accessed). 3 FLcDNAs were mapped both on the Haruna 
Nijo scaffolds and on the Morex contigs using blast+ with the para-
meters '-task blastn -evalue 10e −10 -lcase_masking', and with est2gen-
ome 22 in the EMBOSS package with the parameters '-align -mode 
both -gappenalty 8 -mismatch 6 -minscore 10'. FLcDNAs mapped 
to scaffolds with &gt;95% identity and &gt;50% coverage were accepted. 
Mapped regions with the highest identity were adopted for each 
FLcDNA. Overlapped FLcDNA sequences were clustered onto a 
locus on Haruna Nijo genome. </p>

<p>2.5.2. RNA-Seq analysis 
After trimming of low-quality nucleotide and adapter sequences by 
Trimmomatic, 23 reads derived from rRNA sequences were discarded 
by Bowtie2. 24 A set of programs, Bowtie2, 24 TopHat2 25 and Cuf-
flinks, 26 were used to map reads on the Haruna Nijo scaffolds. </p>

<p>Gene structures derived from FLcDNA mapping were utilized to de-
velop consensus gene models of the four library reads. To predict 
ORFs on the gene structures, blastx searches were conducted to Re-
fSeq and UniProtKB data sets. From the best hit of blastx results, 
the most reliable ORFs were determined with at least 70 amino 
acids in length. To assign gene function, <rs id="software-1" type="software">InterProScan</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">5</rs> 27 was con-
ducted on the predicted ORFs. Based on the InterPro domain, GO 
terms were assigned to each ORF, and GOslim 28 (http://agbase. 
msstate.edu/cgi-bin/tools/goslimviewer_select.pl, 7 November 2015, 
date accessed) was conducted. </p>

<p>2.5.3. RNA gene prediction 
From the silva database 29 (http://www.arb-silva.de/, 7 November 2015, 
date accessed), 17 barley rRNA sequences were downloaded. They were 
mapped on the Haruna Nijo scaffolds using blast+ with the parameters 
'-task blastn -evalue 0.01 -lcase_masking -num_descriptions 100' and </p>

<p>blast hits with &gt;98% identity and &gt;50% coverage were assumed as 
rRNAs. tRNA genes were predicted using the tRNAscan-SE ver. 
1.3.1 program. 30 Any tRNAs that were annotated as 'possible pseudo-
genes' were not counted. </p>

<p>2.5.4. Genome sequence comparison between Haruna Nijo 
and Morex 
The Haruna Nijo scaffolds were mapped on the Morex contigs using 
megablast with the parameters '-evalue 10e −10 -num_descriptions 5'. 
Since several query sequences were hit on the same target sequence, 
the best hit regions were identified. If more than one Morex contig 
was positioned on a Haruna Nijo scaffold, these contigs were aligned 
on the scaffold allowing 10% overlap of the contig sequences. </p>

<p>2.5.5. Morex gene mapping 
High confidence (HC) and low confidence (LC) genes of Morex were 
downloaded from the PGSB barley genome database and mapped to 
the Haruna Nijo scaffolds by GMAP 31 with &gt;95% identity and &gt;90% 
coverage. </p>

<p>3. Results and discussion </p>

<p>3.1. Assembly of the Haruna Nijo genome sequence </p>

<p>We analysed different platforms of WGS sequences of Haruna Nijo by 
hybrid assembly. A total of 305 Gbp of sequence data were generated 
by Illumina HiSeq paired-end reads and 454 Titanium long paired-end 
reads (8 K and 20 K) (Table 1). The hybrid assembly of Illumina and 
454 reads, which also include the published 454 Titanium single-end 
reads (25Gbp), 3 generated a total of 2,055,601,874 bp in 1,753,384 
scaffolds (contigs and gaps). After sequence trimming, the Haruna 
Nijo genome size was 2,005,970,762 bp in 1,712,236 scaffolds 
(Table 2). The N50 was ∼3.5 kb, which is 2.5 times larger than the 
published Morex WGS contigs. 3 The average sequence length in the 
Haruna Nijo scaffolds was longer than the Morex WGS contigs (Sup-
plementary Fig. S1). Compared with Morex WGS contigs, which were 
assembled with only Illumina paired-end reads, the longer Haruna </p>

<p>Table 2. Results of whole-genome assembly of Haruna Nijo and 
Morex 3 </p>

<p>Data 
Haruna Nijo 
Morex </p>

<p>Total length (bp) 
2,005,970,672 
1,868,648,155 
N50 bp 
3,539 
1,425 
No. of contigs/scaffolds 
1,712,236 
2,670,738 
No. of 'N' 
225,899,677 
50,995,654 
No. of non-'N' 
1,780,070,995 
1,817,652,501 
GC (%) 
45.0 
44.4 </p>

<p>Table 1. Sources of WGS sequencing data for Haruna Nijo </p>

<p>Method 
Read 
No. of reads 
No. of bases (bp) </p>

<p>Illumina 
Paired end (PE) 
3,005,632,276 
298,945,920,500 
454 
PE 20 kb 
14,242,510 
4,569,072,624 
454 
PE 8 kb 
2,955,788 
1,016,746,348 
454 
Single end 500 bp 3 
70,936,197 
25,410,875,001 </p>

<p>K. Sato et al. </p>

<p>
Nijo WGS assembly is likely due to assembling the Illumina 
paired-end reads and 454 longer single-end reads. </p>

<p>3.2. Repeat content of the Haruna Nijo genome </p>

<p>Previous studies have shown that the barley genome contains ∼80% re-
peated elements. 3 In the published WGS assemblies, 3 the relative fre-
quency was reduced to ∼60%, due to the degradation of redundant 
repeated sequences. On the assembly of Haruna Nijo WGS data, repeat 
analysis by the Triticeae repeat library (TREP) detected 55.9% as re-
peated sequences. After deleting unknown genomic regions ('N' sites), 
60.8% of the assembled sequences were classified as repeated sequences. 
The composition and distribution of repeat sequence categories were 
similar between Haruna Nijo and Morex (Fig. 1). Noteworthy, 
Gypsy, Copia retrotransposons and the CACTA DNA transposon 
showed higher frequencies than those normally observed in other Triti-
ceae species. When we compared repeat categories from Haruna Nijo, T. 
aestivum (common wheat) cv. Chinese Spring, T. urartu and A. tauschii, 
the frequency of Copia in Haruna Nijo was higher than those in the 
wheat genomes, while Haruna Nijo contained more CACTA and less 
Gypsy than those in wheat genomes (Supplementary Fig. S2). 
To identify unique repeat sequences in barley, de novo repeat se-
quences in the Haruna Nijo scaffolds were detected by RepeatModeler, 
which identified a total of 979 consensus sequences. The de novo repeat 
library and the TREP library were used for repeat masking. As a result, 
74.8% of the assembled sequences were masked ('N's were not masked 
and thus deleted from the calculation). The repeat masking by the de 
novo library identified 68.1% repeat sequences, which were much 
more than the masked repeats (60.8%) detected by the TREP library. </p>

<p>3.3. FLcDNA mapping </p>

<p>FLcDNA mapping on genome sequence provides reliable exon vs. 
intron structures on gene models. A non-redundant set of 28,620 
FLcDNA sequences 13,14 was mapped to the Haruna Nijo scaffolds. 
Blastn mapping revealed that 27,784 FLcDNAs (97%) showed </p>

<p>sequence similarities with the Haruna Nijo scaffolds. According to 
the results of the FLcDNA mapping to scaffolds, we analysed mapping 
coverage of 5′-end of each FLcDNA on Haruna Nijo scaffolds. The 
ratio of completely mapped FLcDNAs, which were mapped from 
the first nucleotide sequence, was &lt;10%. This shows that most of the 
FLcDNAs do not have the complete sequences on the 5′-end side 
exon. To analyse additional mapped FLcDNAs, we relaxed the map-
ping position to the first 10 nucleotide sequences. Then, the ratio of 
mapped FLcDNA was raised to 80% (Supplementary Fig. S3). GC con-
tents and CG-skew were analysed on the FLcDNAs having mapped 
5′-ends within 10 bp. The typical high GC contents and CG-skewed 
peaks at the transcription start sites were identified as previously 
observed in rice and Arabidopsis 32 (Supplementary Fig. S4). 
The longer Haruna Nijo scaffolds may contribute to the efficiency 
in FLcDNA mapping. The number of mapped FLcDNAs under the 
threshold of 50% mapping coverage was 26,240 in the Haruna Nijo 
scaffolds and 24,261 in the Morex contigs (Table 3). These numbers 
included FLcDNAs that mapped to either the Haruna Nijo scaffolds 
(1,985) or the Morex contigs (379). However, if the threshold of map-
ping coverage was raised to 95%, the number of mapped FLcDNAs 
decreased to 14,044 on the Morex contigs, while 19,485 were still 
mapped on the Haruna Nijo scaffolds. 
We also analysed the coverage of FLcDNA mapped reads on the 
Haruna Nijo scaffolds and the Morex contigs by comparing the 
mapped exon numbers of FLcDNAs between Haruna Nijo and 
Morex. Of the 24,255 FLcDNA gene models, 19,207 (79.2%) were 
mapped with the same number of exons both on the Haruna Nijo scaf-
folds and on the Morex contigs. Of these, 3,066 gene models had more 
exons in Haruna Nijo than that in Morex, while 1,982 gene models 
had more exons in Morex than Haruna Nijo. The start position ana-
lysis also showed that the Haruna Nijo scaffolds (6,842) had more 
mapped 5′-end sequences than the Morex contigs (1,721). 
These results indicated that the available genome sequences of 
Morex and Haruna Nijo are different, and there may be more cases </p>

<p>Figure 1. Distribution of TREP repeat categories on the Haruna Nijo and Morex barley genome assemblies. Frequency of each repeat content was calculated by the 
result of repeat masking using the TREP library. Total bases of each repeat region on the genomes were divided by those of all repeat regions. </p>

<p>24 
Barley genome annotations by Haruna Nijo </p>

<p>where FLcDNAs mapped with higher coverage on Haruna Nijo gen-
omes. For example, the entire FLcDNA (AK371953) for the cleistog-
amy1 (cly1 for closed flowering) gene, 33 which was mapped on a 
Haruna Nijo scaffold, while the 5′ region was not mapped on a 
Morex contig (Fig. 2). Moreover, flanking regions for the FLcDNA 
(3.6 Kb for upstream and 2.9 Kb for downstream regions) were pre-
sent on the Haruna Nijo scaffold to provide the opportunity to analyse 
the cis-element(s) of the gene. </p>

<p>3.4. Gene annotation </p>

<p>The IBSC presented 26,159 HC (high confidence) and 53,220 LC (low 
confidence) gene models by using RNA-Seq-based transcript and 
FLcDNAs. 3 This number of genes was larger than that of the Haruna 
Nijo FLcDNAs. Actually, of the 24,243 HC Morex gene models (in 
GFF file), only 7,645 had corresponding Haruna Nijo FLcDNAs, in-
dicating that the FLcDNAs sequence data were not deep enough to 
construct a comprehensive set of barley gene models. To obtain 
more comprehensive transcript sequences of Haruna Nijo, RNA-Seq 
data from four libraries of seedling shoot, seedling root, immature 
spike and immature seed were collected (Table 4). As reference gene 
structures, 26,240 gene models on 18,226 loci determined by 
FLcDNA mapping with 50% coverage (Table 3) were used for map-
ping RNA-Seq reads. Sequences of each RNA-Seq library mapped 
73.2-81.0% to each other, indicating that the concordant pair align-
ment rates were not much different among the libraries (Table 4). 
Sequences from all four libraries were combined by cuffmerge 26 and 
30,606 loci (51,249 gene models) were estimated. Of these, 12,390 
loci and 5,635 alternative variants were added on the Haruna Nijo 
gene models. 
We compared the Haruna Nijo gene models with the Morex HC 
and LC gene models. 3 We mapped 78.0% of Morex HC gene models 
and 72.2% of Morex LC gene models on Haruna Nijo gene models </p>

<p>with 95% coverage and 90% identity. Of these, 1,446 Morex gene 
models were mapped on multiple Haruna Nijo gene models. Cluster-
ing analysis showed that 21,381 Haruna Nijo gene models overlapped 
with Morex gene models on the Haruna Nijo scaffolds, while 9,225 
gene models did not overlap each other. 
Blastx search on RefSeq/UniProt showed that 48,619 gene models 
of Haruna Nijo were similar to known protein sequences. In addition, 
48,105 predicted ORFs on 28,422 gene models of 24,467 scaffolds 
were &gt;70 aa in length. Of these, 44,133 ORFs had Met at the start 
positions. Noteworthy, 23,882 ORFs derived from 25,897 mapped 
FLcDNA contained Met at the start position. 
InterProScan analysis showed that 26,956 ORFs on 19,438 loci 
contained 67,293 InterPro domains. While 2,760 InterPro domains 
were in the 'REPEAT' category, which may not have biological func-
tion, other 44,769 domains were 'DOMAIN' category (Supplemen-
tary Table S1). Moreover, GOslim analysis revealed that the gene 
content of Haruna Nijo (barley) and Nipponbare (rice) was quite 
similar (Supplementary Fig. S5). 
We also predicted rRNA genes on Haruna Nijo scaffolds. Based on 
the silva database, nine scaffolds were identified as rRNA regions. In the 
case of rice, rDNA genes compose nucleolar-organizing region (NOR) 
in which rDNA are aligned in tandem. In wheat, the chromosome-
based WGS analysis showed that the chromosome 6B contains 60% 
of the total rRNA gene (5,500 genes). 34 However, these regions could 
not be assembled by NGS data 35 due to the degeneration in the process 
of assembly. This was also true for the Haruna Nijo scaffolds which 
showed only nine scaffolds carrying rRNA sequences. The difficulty 
of assembling NOR was also reported in rice, 36 but the NOR assembly 
in WGS might be more difficult in general. 
tRNAs were also annotated by tRNAscan-SE. The spectrum of 
tRNA distribution across the genome was uneven but similar to the 
rice genome 37 (Supplementary Fig. S6). It is reported that tRNA Lys se-
quences are extraordinarily abundant in wheat chromosome 6B due to </p>

<p>Table 3. FLcDNA mapping on genome assemblies </p>

<p>Coverage (%) 
No. of hit FLcDNAs (ratio/total) </p>

<p>Haruna Nijo 
Morex 3 </p>

<p>50 
26,241 (0.917) 
24,621 (0.860) 
70 
22,835 (0.798) 
19,926 (0.696) 
80 
21,429 (0.749) 
17,706 (0.619) 
90 
20,153 (0.704) 
15,361 (0.537) 
95 
19,485 (0.681) 
14,044 (0.491) </p>

<p>Figure 2. Gene structure of closed flowering locus cly1 (AK371953). In the Haruna Nijo genome, the complete gene structures of cly1 including upstream and 
downstream regions were identified. In the Morex genome, 3 the first exon and upstream regions were truncated because of insufficient length of the contig. </p>

<p>Table 4. Sequencing and mapping results of Haruna Nijo RNA-Seq 
data </p>

<p>Sample 
No. of read 
pairs </p>

<p>Aligned 
pairs </p>

<p>Concordant pair 
alignment rate (%) </p>

<p>Leaf 
4,977,702 
3,738,352 
75.0 
Root 
3,981,366 
2,921,944 
73.2 
Seed 
7,024,371 
5,691,954 
81.0 
Spike 
4,292,946 
3,399,764 
79.1 </p>

<p>K. Sato et al. </p>

<p>
the abundance of the retrotransposon Gypsy. 35 The Haruna Nijo scaf-
folds also have higher rate of Gypsy; however, the number of tRNAs 
was smaller than that in wheat. </p>

<p>3.5. WGS assembly comparison between Haruna 
Nijo and Morex </p>

<p>There are several published 3 and ongoing efforts of sequencing BACs 
derived from Morex. BAC-based assemblies may provide longer se-
quences than WGS assemblies to estimate gene models on the genome. 
The final goal for developing Haruna Nijo gene models is to map them 
on the BAC-based Morex genome sequences. To understand the qual-
ity of current Haruna Nijo genome resources, sequences of the Haruna </p>

<p>Nijo scaffolds and the Morex contigs were aligned by megablast. An 
average sequence identity between Haruna Nijo and Morex was esti-
mated as 95.99% (Supplementary Table S2). We found that mapped 
regions of query were different when query and database sequences 
were exchanged between Haruna Nijo and Morex. This was caused 
by the difference of sequence length in two assemblies. In this analysis, 
we used the best hit of megablast for the calculation, and the other hits 
with lower coverage on Haruna Nijo scaffolds were discarded. There-
fore, the total length of aligned regions was decreased. Genome com-
parison of Haruna Nijo and Morex identified the occasions that the 
genomic regions of Haruna Nijo and Morex do not match. An ex-
ample of mismatch between two assemblies on chromosome 5H 
was that a region of the Haruna Nijo gene model of TCONS_ </p>

<p>Figure 3. Example screenshots of (A) Haruna Nijo contig_55003, (B) Morex contig_156845 and (C) Morex contig_68185 under the platform of Gbrowse. Separated 
genomic regions of Morex which correspond to the single FLcDNA region in Haruna Nijo. This figure is available in black and white in print and in colour at DNA 
Research online. </p>

<p> 
Barley genome annotations by Haruna Nijo </p>

<p>00033948 or TCONS_00033949 (Fig. 3A), which is supported by a 
FLcDNA, AK370496 that encodes bZIP transcription factor family 
protein on a contig_55003 (scaffold), was divided into two loci of 
MLOC_14578.1 on morex_contig_156845 (Fig. 3B) and MLOC_ 
75543 on morex_contig_68185 (Fig. 3C). Thus, we may find a better 
gene model if we compare multiple gene models derived from different 
assemblies. 
We also analysed conserved genic regions between Haruna Nijo 
and Morex by using mapped regions of FLcDNAs. The difference be-
tween Haruna Nijo scaffolds and FLcDNA sequences was 0.05% 
(1 bp of 2000bp in exon), which is still five times higher than the 
value of 0.01% in rice genome. 37 However, the sequence difference 
of exon regions between Haruna Nijo and Morex (identified by Har-
una Nijo FLcDNAs) was 0.29%, indicating that the sequence quality 
of scaffolds in Haruna Nijo was high compared with the haplotype 
difference between Haruna Nijo and Morex. </p>

<p>3.6. Conclusion </p>

<p>Based on this study, there are several advantages of using the Haruna 
Nijo sequence resources. The Haruna Nijo scaffolds provide a high-
quality genome sequence for the barley research community. In par-
ticular, the FLcDNA sequences, which are available only for Haruna 
Nijo, provide a key resource. In addition, the gene structures of 
Haruna Nijo provide supplementary data sets to the Morex genome 
sequence. Finally, the haplotype of Haruna Nijo is popular among 
the malting barley cultivars in the world and can be used as an alter-
native source of alleles for important traits in barley. </p>

<p>4. Availability </p>

<p>The short genomic reads used in the study are deposited at DDBJ-SRA 
under accession ID PRJDB4103. The scaffolds for the Hordeum vul-
gare cv. Haruna Nijo are available at http://barleyflc.dna.affrc.go.jp/ 
bexdb/pages/harunanijo_index.jsp for download. Genome browsing 
of the Haruna Nijo gene models are available on GBrowse [(http:// 
gmod.org/wiki/GBrowse) 38 at http://barleyflc.dna.affrc.go.jp/gb2/ </p>

<p>gbrowse/HarunaNijo_genome/.21]. All scaffolds were concatenated 
by 100 'Ns' from the longer scaffolds. Haruna Nijo scaffolds, 
FLcDNAs, RNA-Seq genes, repeat information, Morex contigs and 
Morex HC/LC genes are displayed (Fig. 3). From the Haruna Nijo 
genome browser, FLcDNA annotation data and Morex genome 
browser of bex-db could be accessed (Fig. 4). Moreover, users can ac-
cess the Haruna Nijo genome from FLcDNA information of bex-db. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We would like to express our thanks to Prof. Gary Muehlbauer, University of 
Minnesota for his critical reading and linguistic editing of the manuscript. Bar-
ley seeds were provided through the National Bioresource Project of Barley, 
MEXT of Japan. Analysis of Illumina HiSeq 2000 sequence reads was per-
formed by the Japan Advanced Plant Science Research Network (http://www. 
psr-net.riken.jp/index.html). This work was partly supported by the scientific 
technique research promotion program for agriculture, forestry fisheries and 
food industry to K.S. </p>

<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data are available at www.dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was pro-
vided by Okayama University to Kazuhiro Sato, corresponding author. </p>



<p>K. Sato et al. </p>



<p>
 
Barley genome annotations by Haruna Nijo </p>

</text></tei>