<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4039861" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T03:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives: To develop an instrument to assess </p>

<p>attitudes and underlying beliefs about back pain, and 
subsequently investigate its internal consistency and 
underlying structures. </p>

<p>Design: The instrument was developed by a </p>

<p>multidisciplinary team of clinicians and researchers 
based on analysis of qualitative interviews with people 
experiencing acute and chronic back pain. Exploratory 
analysis was conducted using data from a population-
based cross-sectional survey. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Attitudes and beliefs are important factors 
in the development of back pain and disabil-
ity. 
10 11 Systematic reviews have found fear 
avoidance beliefs (movement or activity 
being avoided for fear of pain or injury) and 
low expectations of recovery (expecting a 
delayed return to work or persistent pain) 
are independently associated with poor out-
comes, such as delayed return to work, activ-
ity limitation and pain persistence. 
12 13 An 
improved understanding of the beliefs on 
which these constructs are based, and an 
ability to assess these in people who have 
back pain and the general public, could help 
to inform and target interventions to posi-
tively influence beliefs. Such interventions 
may, in turn, improve outcomes. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ The Back Pain Attitudes Questionnaire (Back-PAQ) 
was developed based on in-depth interviews with 
people experiencing acute and chronic back pain. 
▪ The underlying structures and internal consist-
ency of the instrument were explored using a 
large data set of 602 responses. 
▪ The 34-item long form of the questionnaire 
appears to have adequate internal consistency 
and may be appropriate for future cross-sectional 
studies. 
▪ The 10-item short form may be appropriate for 
use as a screening tool, or an outcome assess-
ment instrument. This requires further testing of 
its construct validity, reliability, responsiveness 
to change and predictive ability. </p>

<p>Darlow B, Perry M, Mathieson F, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005251. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005251 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>Understanding the attitudes and beliefs of health pro-
fessionals is also important as these are associated with 
their patients' beliefs and their own adherence to clin-
ical guideline recommendations regarding the provision 
and content of patient explanations and work and activ-
ity advice. 
15 Guideline consistent care produces better 
patient outcomes and improved satisfaction at a lower 
cost. 
16 17 Clinicians influence their patients' understand-
ing of their problem and recovery expectations, with 
many messages given by clinicians reinforcing patient 
perceptions that their back is vulnerable and needs to 
be protected. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>A number of instruments have been developed to 
assess the attitudes and beliefs of people experiencing 
pain in general, 
19-21 and the attitudes of the general 
public to back pain. 
22 These scales have been developed 
based on analysis of the literature and clinical experi-
ence rather than patient views. Only the Back Beliefs 
Questionnaire 
22 specifically relates to beliefs about back 
pain. Although developed and written for people with 
pain or the general public, many of these instruments 
have been adapted for assessing health professionals' 
beliefs. 
23-26 The Health Care Providers Pain and 
Impairment Relationship Scale (HC-PAIRS) is one of 
the most commonly used measures. 
23 However, it 
assesses health professionals' views about people with 
back pain, rather than their own beliefs. Some research-
ers have also felt it necessary to append a disclaimer 
apologising for use of the term 'handicapped', which 
may be considered offensive. </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>Two questionnaires related to back pain have been 
developed specifically for health professionals: the Pain 
Attitudes and Beliefs Scale for Physical Therapists 
(PABS-PT) 
28 and the Attitudes to Back Pain Scale for 
musculoskeletal practitioners (ABS-mp). 
29 The PABS-PT 
aims to discriminate between biomedical and biopsycho-
social treatment orientations in the management of 
chronic low back pain. 
28 This instrument was developed 
by adapting items from four questionnaires developed 
for patients, as well as items developed by the research-
ers. Consequently, many items focus on patient manage-
ment rather than the therapist's own beliefs about back 
pain. A recent review found that evidence on the meas-
urement properties of the PABS, although promising, 
was still lacking and required further investigation of 
content validity, interpretability and reliability. 
30 The 
ABS-mp also focuses on clinicians' attitudes about man-
aging back pain rather than their own beliefs about the 
back and back pain. As some of the items relate to the 
healthcare system, the authors advised caution if using 
outside of the UK. </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>In order to understand beliefs about back pain we 
have conducted in-depth interviews with people experi-
encing acute and chronic back pain. 
18 These interviews 
have gone beyond the identification of attitudes asso-
ciated with poor outcomes by identifying beliefs which 
underlie these constructs. These include the back being 
seen as vulnerable to injury and in need of protection. </p>

<p>To test the validity of these findings among the broader 
New Zealand population we developed a novel survey 
instrument which incorporated items from previous 
surveys of population beliefs, as well as items specifically 
developed for the instrument. This instrument was 
designed to be appropriate for assessing beliefs of the 
general public, those experiencing back pain and health 
professionals. 
The purpose of this paper is to describe the develop-
ment of the instrument, and the subsequent item reduc-
tion, by means of exploratory analysis using principal 
components, to produce a scale which may be appropri-
ate for future clinical and research use. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Initial instrument development 
The development process for the Back Pain Attitudes 
Questionnaire (Back-PAQ) is summarised in figure 1. </p>

<p>Item generation 
Qualitative interviews 
In-depth interviews were conducted with 12 people 
experiencing acute back pain and 11 people experien-
cing chronic back pain in one region of New Zealand 
(for full details see Darlow et al 
18 ). These interviews 
aimed to explore underlying reasons for constructs like 
fear avoidance beliefs, low outcome expectations and 
catastrophising. Qualitative analysis, using the framework 
of Interpretive Description, 
31 identified six broad 
themes: (1) 'the vulnerability of the back'; (2) 'the need 
to protect the back'; (3) 'the correlation between pain 
and injury'; (4) 'the special nature of back pain' (its 
impact, difference to other pain conditions and the 
need for professional care); (5) 'activity participation 
while experiencing back pain'; and (6) 'the prognosis of 
back pain'. Items were developed to reflect these 
themes. </p>

<p>Comparator questions 
Items, consistent with themes which emerged in qualita-
tive interviews, were drawn from previous surveys of 
population beliefs administered in Australia, </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Belgium, 
32 Canada, 
33 Norway 
34 and the UK. 
35 The ori-
ginal wording was maintained as far as possible to allow 
direct comparison. </p>

<p>Item selection and refinement 
Items were suggested and reviewed by members of the 
multidisciplinary research team including: three phy-
siotherapists (BD, MP and GDB), a biostatistician with a 
psychology background ( JS), a general practitioner 
(TD), a clinical psychologist (FM), and an orthopaedic 
surgeon and rheumatologist (MM). All team members 
had experience in the conduct and analysis of back pain 
research and provided feedback on item suitability and 
wording. </p>



<p>Darlow B, Perry M, Mathieson F, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005251. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005251 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Thirty-four items were included in the draft instru-
ment: 27 from the qualitative analysis and seven from 
previous surveys. Items relating to similar concepts were 
included to explore alternative wording; redundancy was 
checked during data analysis. A full explanation of item 
derivation is provided in online supplementary appendix 
1. All items were written in the second person to person-
alise the survey and to clarify that respondents were 
being asked about their personal beliefs regarding their 
own back. Text readability was assessed using the 
Microsoft <rs id="software-0" type="software">Word</rs> Office Package (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microsoft Corp.</rs>, 
Redmond, WA), following the procedure described by 
Badarudeen and Sabharwal. </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>This provided a 
Flesch-Kinkaid grade of 2.9 (indicating the text is able to 
be read by a 3rd grader/9-year-old), and Flesch Reading 
Ease of 86.2% (scores from 90% to 100% indicate a text </p>

<p>can be easily understood by an average 11-year-old 
student). </p>

<p>Layout 
Items were divided into five sections containing concep-
tually related information. The layout was designed to 
improve ease of navigation and completion. 
37 A 5-point 
Likert scale was used and each scale point was labelled 
with a descriptive title, rather than a numeric value, to 
increase reliability and reduce positivity bias. 
37 The scale 
ranged from 'False' to 'True' (intermediate labels: 
'Possibly False', 'Unsure', 'Possibly True). 
35 The 'True' 
response option normally represented beliefs which are 
unhelpful for recovery from back pain. It was placed at 
the far end of the scale to reduce primacy effects (as 
analysis of qualitative interviews indicated this would be </p>

<p>Figure 1 Development of the 
Back Pain Attitudes 
Questionnaire (Back-PAQ). </p>

<p>Darlow B, Perry M, Mathieson F, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005251. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005251 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>selected more frequently). 
37 Eleven items (1, 2, 3, 15, 
16, 17, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31) were reversed compared with 
the normal direction of the survey. </p>

<p>Piloting of initial item set 
The draft instrument was prepiloted with members of 
the research team and research colleagues with back-
grounds in: general practice; survey instrument design; 
and conducting research with Maōri participants. The 
draft instrument was then piloted with a convenience 
sample of 35 people. These participants had a range of 
back pain experiences (including people with chronic 
back pain who had offered to participate in the qualita-
tive interviews but had not been recruited), a diverse 
age range and diverse occupational backgrounds. 
Pilot participants provided written and verbal qualita-
tive feedback. This indicated they were generally positive 
about the instrument and the item response options. 
Most participants reported taking about 5 min to com-
plete the scale. Revisions were made to instrument 
layout, item wording and sequencing, based on feed-
back. Online supplementary appendix 2 presents the 
instrument as it was received by respondents in the main 
survey. </p>

<p>Exploratory analysis and item reduction 
Participant selection and data collection 
The data utilised to conduct this analysis were collected 
during a study to assess the prevalence of attitudes and 
beliefs about back pain in New Zealand. The full methods 
and results of this study are available elsewhere. </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>Participants were eligible for inclusion if they were New 
Zealand citizens or residents aged 18 years and above. 
Participants were randomly selected from the New 
Zealand Electoral Roll (it is a legal requirement for all 
New Zealanders aged 18 years and above to be listed on 
this roll). Participants were excluded if they had an over-
seas postal address on the roll. In order to achieve an esti-
mation accuracy of ±5% for prevalence data, 400 complete 
responses were required (http://www.openepi.com, 
accessed 30 May 2012). The likely response rate was esti-
mated to be 40%, 
39 so 1000 respondents were randomly 
selected from the Electoral Roll by means of the 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">PostgreSQL</rs> database management system <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">V.9.1.4</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://postgresql.org/</rs>/; The PostgreSQL Global Development 
Group, California). Four hundred responses were also 
considered sufficient for analysis of principal compo-
nents. 
40 Data were collected via a postal survey with up to 
three reminders (two additional complete survey packs 
and one postcard). An online response option was also 
available (http://www.surveymonkey.com). </p>

<p>Statistical analyses 
Exploratory analysis and item reduction for use as research 
or clinical screening tool 
Exploratory analysis was performed to investigate under-
lying structures of the instrument. Principal Component 
Analysis with Varimax rotation was used to maximise the </p>

<p>distinction between components. 
41 Components needed 
to have a minimum Guttman-Kaiser eigenvalue of 1 to 
be selected. Items were removed if they had: (1) 
Pearson correlations with total scale score &lt;0.3; and (2) 
component loadings &lt;0.5. </p>

<p>Internal consistency 
Cronbach's α was calculated for the entire 34-item scale 
and the reduced scale resulting from exploratory analysis 
together with its principal components. As Cronbach's α 
depends on the absolute number of items included, </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>two criteria were used: for more than 10 items α &gt; 0.70 
was considered acceptable; for less than 10 items α&gt;0.50 
was considered acceptable. 
40 For the 34-item scale, the 
effect of item removal on consistency scores was ana-
lysed. For the reduced scale, inter-item correlations were 
assessed to ensure items correlated more with items 
within the same component than with items in other 
components. 
The frequency of missing data was assessed across the 
whole data set, and within subgroups based on back 
pain experience. Missing data were handled by means of 
conducting complete case analysis. The number of cases 
included for each analysis is reported within the results. </p>

<p>Scoring 
When the reduced item scale is used as a research or 
clinical screening tool, responses will be scored from −2 
('True') to +2 ('False'). Beliefs which are unhelpful for 
recovery from back pain attract negative scores and vice 
versa. This may allow clinicians to quickly interpret scale 
and component scores and identify where explanations 
could be directed. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Six-hundred and three responses were received; one 
response was excluded because the respondent reported 
an age of 17, and was therefore ineligible (one must be 
18 to be on the electoral roll; this indicated he was 
either not the intended recipient, or had provided 
incorrect information). Six hundred and two responses 
were included in the analysis. Respondent characteristics 
are presented in table 1. No item had more than 2.3% 
missing data. The number of surveys with all items 
answered was comparable between people with no back 
pain experience (88%), past back pain (88%) and 
people with current back pain (87%). </p>

<p>Data preparation 
To prepare data for principal component analysis and 
item reduction, items were checked for inter-item correl-
ation, as this would suggest redundancy. 
43 No items had 
Pearson correlations &gt;0.65. </p>

<p>Back-PAQ item reduction 
A total of 526 cases were included in the internal consist-
ency analysis (76 excluded due to incomplete data). The </p>



<p>Darlow B, Perry M, Mathieson F, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005251. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005251 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>complete 34-item scale had acceptable internal consist-
ency (α=0.70; 95% CI 0.66 to 0.73). No significant 
improvement in α resulted from the removal of any 
items. </p>

<p>Exploratory analysis of principal components 
The exploratory analysis process is presented in figure 2. </p>

<p>Model 1 
All 34 items were entered into a Principal Component 
Analysis. Bartlett's test of sphericity ( p&lt;0.001) and 
Kaiser-Meyer-Olkin testing (0.71) indicated component 
analysis was appropriate for this data set. 
40 43 The model 
was unable to converge with 25 iterations. Dividing data 
by back pain experience did not result in convergence, 
whereas dividing data by gender indicated 11 compo-
nents with eigenvalues ≥1. This model explained 60% of 
the variance in each gender group. Each component 
explained between 4% and 8% of the variance. It was 
conceivable that beliefs would be different in men and 
women, 
44 and so the analysis was continued with the 
male and female data sets separated. To reduce the vari-
ance, Pearson correlation coefficients were calculated 
between individual items and total scale scores. 
Fourteen items with correlations &lt;0.3 were removed, and 
the model was retested. </p>

<p>Model 2 
Twenty items were entered into the second model which 
indicated a seven component model in each gender 
group explaining 60% of the variance. Each component </p>

<p>explained between 6% and 11% of the variance. 
Although male and female data sets were separated with 
the intention of producing gender-specific instruments, 
five pairs of items (10 items total) with loadings &gt;0.5 
mapped to the same components in men and women. 
Fourteen items were removed because they either did 
not load &gt;0.5 to any components, or they loaded onto 
different components in men and women. </p>

<p>Model 3 
These 10 items were entered in the third model using 
combined male and female data sets. This model indi-
cated a five-component solution and accounted for 74% 
of the variance in the 10-item data set. No items cross-
loaded onto more than one component and there were 
acceptable communalities (table 2). 
43 Each item corre-
lated much more strongly within their component than 
between components. Each component was easily cate-
gorised, with four representing the original themes ('the 
vulnerability of the back', 'the relationship between back 
pain and injury', 'activity participation while experien-
cing back pain' and 'the prognosis of back pain'); an 
additional component ('psychological influences on 
recovery') had also emerged. Each of these components 
explained between 13.7% and 16.7% of the variance 
(table 3). Two of the original themes were lost; these 
were (1) 'the need to protect the back', and (2) 'the 
special nature of back pain'. A reduced component 
model was performed (forced model of four compo-
nents) to see whether this resulted in a better fitting 
model. The model showed a reduction in overall vari-
ance explained (64.1%). Internal consistency was accept-
able for the 10-item scale (α=0.61; 95%CI 0.56 to 0.66) 
and identified components (α between 0.50 and 0.78). 
Online supplementary appendix 3 presents the 10-item 
instrument. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
The Back-PAQ was designed so it could be answered by 
the general public, people with back pain and health 
professionals; this feature allows for use in a variety of 
contexts without modification, and also for the direct 
comparison of beliefs between groups. The instrument 
was tested with a large sample randomly selected from 
the general population and achieved a very good 
response rate (60%). The original long form of the 
instrument (34-item) and the reduced short form 
(10-item) resulting from Principal Component Analysis 
were found to have adequate internal consistency. 
Irrespective of back pain experience there was very little 
missing data. It appears the instrument was easy to com-
plete, and this may have assisted with the good response 
rate. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations 
A key strength of this instrument is that items were gen-
erated to reflect themes identified during in-depth </p>

<p>Table 1 Respondent characteristics </p>

<p>Characteristic 
n (percentage)* </p>

<p>Age (years; mean (range)) 
602 (50.6 (18-97)) 
Female 
331 (55) 
Male 
271 (45) 
Ethnicity † 
New Zealand European 
487 (80.9) 
Maōri 
81 (13.5) 
Asian 
45 (7.5) 
Pacific 
20 (3.3) 
Middle East/Latin American 
6 (1.0) 
Other 
3 (0.5) 
Not stated 
11 (1.8) 
Back pain history 
Never 
76 (12.6) 
Past 
361 (60.0) 
Current 
164 (27.2) 
Not stated 
1 (0.2) 
Healthcare professional use for back pain 
Never seen 
210 (34.9) 
Have seen 
389 (64.6) 
Not stated 
3 (0.5) </p>

<p>*Unless otherwise noted. 
 †Total equals more than 100% as respondents were able to select 
more than one category (39 respondents selected two ethnicity 
categories, 3 selected three). </p>

<p>Darlow B, Perry M, Mathieson F, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005251. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005251 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>interviews with people experiencing acute and chronic 
back pain. Consequently, items reflect issues that are of 
importance to this population. This should contribute 
to the content validity of the instrument. Although 
health professionals and people without back pain did 
not participate in these interviews, subsequent interview 
research with general practitioners has demonstrated 
they hold many similar beliefs (manuscript under review); 
as such this instrument may also be appropriate for 
exploring health professionals' beliefs. It is hoped that 
use of the second person throughout the instrument will 
result in people without back pain and health profes-
sionals presenting their own beliefs, rather than project-
ing their beliefs onto people with back pain, or providing </p>

<p>their beliefs about people with back pain. This feature 
may improve comparison of beliefs between groups. 
For many items, particularly those related to 'the need 
to protect the back' and 'the special nature of back 
pain', high proportions of respondents selected the 
most extreme option ('True'). Although this ceiling 
effect may limit the discriminative abilities of the 34-item 
long form Back-PAQ, responses indicate that beliefs 
about the need to have strong muscles, good posture 
and special lifting techniques are very commonly held, 
despite a lack of evidence to support them. These two 
original themes did not become part of the final 10-item 
short form Back-PAQ scale because they are non-
discriminating. Conceptually, the need to protect the </p>

<p>Figure 2 Back Pain Attitudes 
Questionnaire (Back-PAQ) 
exploratory analysis of principal 
components and item reduction. 
Components required an 
eigenvalue ≥1 to be retained. </p>



<p>Darlow B, Perry M, Mathieson F, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005251. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005251 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>back is related to the vulnerability of the back; this is 
reflected by one of the items in the final 'vulnerability' 
component coming from the original 'vulnerability' 
theme (item 6), and one from the 'protection' theme 
(item 11). 
Exploratory analysis was appropriate for this study 
because, although we had developed the items based on 
themes identified through qualitative interviews, we did 
not know the extent to which these items actually met 
our assumptions. 
45 There are many varied techniques for 
analysing latent constructs. 
46 This is an iterative process 
which involves researcher judgements; it is possible that 
other researchers or methods may have produced differ-
ent results. 
41 46 Notwithstanding this, the final model 
accounted for a large portion of the variance in the 
reduced data set, reflected the original interview themes 
on which the instrument was based and related well to 
the constructs identified by other researchers. </p>

<p>46 </p>

<p>The post hoc decision to split the data into male and 
female data sets to assist component identification, and 
then recombine the data into one data set for the final 
model could be viewed as being unusual; however, this 
process facilitated removal of items which had different 
latent constructs in men and women. Having a single 
tool which is appropriate for both genders should 
improve ease of use and interpretation. </p>

<p>Internal consistency of the 10-item Back-PAQ and its 
principal components, although acceptable, was low. 
This is unsurprising given the multiple dimensions, low 
number of items and similar variance explained by each 
component. 
40 42 47 The Back-PAQ was designed to have 
multiple themes which relate to different attitudes and 
beliefs about back pain. For this reason, Varimax rota-
tion was appropriate for analysing component loadings. 
The similar weightings that each of these components 
have is a strength of the instrument, with the hypothesis 
being that unhelpful beliefs on one component may be 
balanced out by helpful beliefs on another. Although 
widely used, and included in quality assessment cri-
teria, 
48 the use of α to measure internal consistency is 
debated. 
42 Low α is not a reason to discard the scale, 
given the reasons for its deflation are known, and the 
very high proportion of variance explained by these five 
components (74%). </p>

<p>Future research 
The Back-PAQ is expected to have good construct valid-
ity with five robust components identified and easily 
characterised. However, this requires further testing by 
means of: confirmatory factor analyses among specific 
populations (eg, health professionals); examining con-
vergent validity with existing instruments for assessing </p>

<p>Table 2 Varimax rotated structure coefficients from the final exploratory analysis five-component model </p>

<p>Item </p>

<p>Component* 
Communalities 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>6. It is easy to injure your back 
−0.003 
0.085 −0.028 0.036 
0.838 
0.711 
11. You could injure your back if you are not careful 
0.062 
0.071 
0.221 0.003 
0.774 
0.657 
13. Back pain means that you have injured your back 
0.050 
0.121 
0.863 0.060 −0.025 
0.767 
14. A twinge in your back can be the first sign of a serious 
injury </p>

<p>−0.116 
0.088 
0.788 0.014 
0.231 
0.695 </p>

<p>25. If you have back pain you should avoid exercise 
0.040 
0.173 
0.194 0.817 
0.004 
0.737 
27. If you have back pain you should try to stay active 
0.170 −0.028 −0.103 0.846 
0.039 
0.758 
30. Focusing on things other than the back helps you to 
recover from back pain </p>

<p>0.894 
0.028 −0.005 0.105 
0.045 
0.813 </p>

<p>31. Expecting your back pain to get better helps you to 
recover from back pain </p>

<p>0.896 
0.020 −0.049 0.101 
0.011 
0.816 </p>

<p>32. Once you have had back pain there is always a weakness −0.075 
0.843 
0.110 0.086 
0.090 
0.744 
33. There is a high chance that an episode of back pain will 
not resolve </p>

<p>0.123 
0.843 
0.094 0.044 
0.073 
0.743 </p>

<p>*A loading cut-off value of 0.5 was used for inclusion in components (these are indicated by bold typeface). </p>

<p>Table 3 Psychometric properties of the 10-item Back Pain Attitudes Questionnaire </p>

<p>Component 
Items Eigenvalue </p>

<p>Explained 
variance (%) α (95% CI) </p>

<p>Inter-item 
correlation n </p>

<p>1. Psychological influences on recovery 
30, 31 1.673 
16.7 
0.78 (0.74 to 0.82) 0.641 
594 
2. Prognosis of back pain 
32, 33 1.489 
14.9 
0.64 (0.57 to 0.69) 0.473 
595 
3. Relationship between back pain and injury 13, 14 1.487 
14.9 
0.60 (0.54 to 0.66) 0.444 
597 
4. Activity participation during back pain 
25, 27 1.420 
14.2 
0.58 (0.50 to 0.64) 0.423 
593 
5. Vulnerability of the back 
6, 11 1.372 
13.7 
0.50 (0.42 to 0.58) 0.350 
588 
Total score 
74.4 
0.61 (0.56 to 0.66) 0.138 
576 </p>

<p>Darlow B, Perry M, Mathieson F, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005251. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005251 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>beliefs in these three groups ( people with back pain, 
people without back pain and health professionals); and 
examining correlation with clinical behaviour among 
health professionals. The test-retest reliability and 
responsiveness to change also need to be assessed for 
each of these three groups. Finally, the predictive ability 
of the Back-PAQ on clinical outcomes needs to be exam-
ined for people with back pain and people who are pain-
free, as well as examining the influence of health profes-
sionals' beliefs (as measured by the Back-PAQ) on their 
patients' clinical outcomes. </p>

<p>48 </p>

<p>Implications 
The 34-item long form of this instrument may be useful 
for conducting cross-sectional surveys in other countries. 
The 10-item short form of the instrument may be useful 
as either a research instrument to measure changes in 
beliefs, or as a screening tool to predict outcome or 
direct management. The novel scoring system for the 
Back-PAQ means that it is very easy to interpret. 
Negative scores indicate beliefs which are presumed to 
be unhelpful for recovery from back pain, and positive 
scores vice versa. The five components may also indicate 
to health professionals areas in which a patient has 
unhelpful beliefs, so that they may focus explanation 
and reassurance on these areas. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS 
We have developed two instruments for assessing atti-
tudes about back pain among the general public, people 
with back pain and health professionals. The long form 
may be appropriate for use in future cross-sectional 
studies, and the short form may be appropriate for use 
as a screening tool, or an outcome assessment instru-
ment. Further testing of the 10-item Back-PAQ's 
construct validity, reliability, responsiveness to change 
and predictive ability needs to be conducted. </p>

<p>Author affiliations </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Primary Health Care and General Practice, University of Otago, 
Wellington, New Zealand </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Centre for Health Activity and Rehabilitation Research, School of 
Physiotherapy, University of Otago, Dunedin, New Zealand </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Psychological Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington, 
New Zealand </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Biostatistical Group, University of Otago, Wellington, New Zealand </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Centre for Health Sciences, School of Health Professions, Zurich University 
of Applied Sciences, Winterthur, Switzerland </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Gillies McIndoe Research Institute, Newtown, Wellington South, New Zealand </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors acknowledge the people who participated in 
qualitative interviews, those who piloted the draft instrument and those who 
responded to the postal survey. </p>

<p>Contributors BD, MP, FM, JS, MM, RM, GDB and AD were involved in the 
design of the study. BD conducted qualitative interviews; BD, MP, FM, GDB 
and AD analysed qualitative data. BD, MP, FM, JS, MM, GDB and AD 
developed the survey instrument. BD and RM did the statistical analysis. BD 
wrote the first draft. All the authors helped revise the paper. BD is the 
guarantor for the study. All the authors had full access to all of the data in the </p>

<p>study and can take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy 
of the data analysis. </p>

<p>Funding This study received funding from the Physiotherapy New Zealand 
Scholarship Trust and from Lotteries Health Research. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval This qualitative component of this study was approved by 
the New Zealand Central Regional Ethics Committee (CEN/11/EXP/014). The 
survey component was approved by the University of Otago Ethics Committee 
(D12/255). Consultation was undertaken with the Ngaī Tahu Research 
Consultation Committee. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement The data set used for exploratory analysis can be 
obtained by emailing ben.darlow@otago.ac.nz </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Darlow B, Perry M, Mathieson F, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005251. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005251 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>



<p>Darlow B, Perry M, Mathieson F, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e005251. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005251 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>