<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4672851" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>appears healthy. In some patients, periodontal tissue loss 
may commence before puberty, whereas in most patients the 
age of onset is during or somewhat after the circumpubertal 
period. Besides infection with specific microorganisms such 
as Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans and Porphyromonas 
gingivalis a host predisposition seems to play a key role in the 
pathogenesis of AgP, as evidenced by the familial aggregation 
of the disease. 
1 In contrast to chronic periodontitis, AgP is 
characterized by the age of onset of disease, rapid rate of disease 
progression, the nature and composition of the subgingival 
micro flora and alteration in host immune response. 
2 Patients 
with systemic diseases like hematological disorders will have 
severe bone loss similar to AgP, and it should be differentiated 
by assessing the systemic status, hematological parameters of 
the patient. Studies have shown that intra-osseous sarcoidosis, </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>eosinophilic granulomas, 
4 and alveolar bone actinomycosis 
shows the clinical features like mimicking AgP, and it should 
be differentiated by biopsy. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Systemic factors modify the periodontitis principally by acting 
on the normal immune and inflammatory defense cells. It has 
been seen that with the reduction in number or function of 
polymorphonuclear, there is increased rate and severity of 
the periodontal destruction. The blood cells have a vital role 
in supplying oxygen, maintaining hemostasis, and providing 
protection to the periodontal tissues. Systemic hematological 
disorders can thus have profound effects on the periodontium; 
if any of these functions is altered, they can have a detrimental 
effect on the integrity of the periodontium. 
6 For thousands of 
years, blood has been regarded as an ultimate body fluid that 
could indicate the disease processes. In the past decade, there 
has been a renewed interest in the ways in which periodontitis 
may affect the changes in cellular and molecular components 
of the peripheral blood. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>The current study was done to assess the levels of systemic 
inflammatory markers in serum of systemically healthy 
individuals and AgP patients. </p>

<p>Methods 
Study population 
This study was conducted in April of 2013, in the outpatient 
Department of Periodontology and Implantology, Rajah 
Muthiah Dental College, and Hospital, Tamil Nadu, India. 
The study included fifty systemically healthy subjects in the 
age group between 15 and 35 years and was divided into two 
groups as follows. Group I includes 25 periodontally healthy </p>



<p>Systemic inflammatory markers in aggressive periodontitis … Iqbal PS et al Journal of International Oral Health 2015; 7(Suppl 2):48-51 </p>

<p>individuals with fully functioning dentition. Group II includes 
25 patients diagnosed clinically AgP. All patients received the 
verbal explanation of the nature of the study and informed written 
consent was obtained. The study was approved by the Medical 
Ethical Committee of Rajah Muthiah Dental College and Hospital. </p>

<p>A detailed systemic and family history was recorded. Patients 
with a history of systemic diseases or conditions that causes 
periodontitis were not included in this study. The following 
patients were excluded, (1) history of diabetes, kidney disease, 
cancer, or fungal or respiratory infections; (2) patients 
hospitalized or under medication for the past 6 months 
(3) tobacco smoking or chewing patients; (4) patients with a 
previous history of periodontal therapy. </p>

<p>Clinical recordings 
Oral hygiene was recorded by using plaque index (PI) (Sillness 
and Loe 1964), gingival inflammation was scored using gingival 
index (GI), probing depth (PD) and clinical attachment level 
(CAL) measures were obtained from the four points of the 
teeth using a conventional periodontal probe (Hu-Friedy, 
Chicago, IL, USA). The probe was directed parallel to the 
long axis of the tooth. CAL measurements were made from 
the cemento-enamel junction to the bottom of the sulcus. All 
clinical data were recorded by one examiner. </p>

<p>Blood collection and analysis 
Two ml of venous serum samples were obtained by 
venipuncture in the antecubital fossa without excessive venous 
stasis and were collected for both case and control groups in 
two separate tubes. One ml of serum is transferred to a tube 
containing ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) and 
used for assessing the blood parameters by the hematological 
analyzer; the other without EDTA and was used for serum 
protein analyzes by the biochemical analyzer. Blood cell 
analysis included white blood cell (WBC) count, neutrophil 
count, lymphocyte count, platelet count (PLT), and mean 
platelet volume (MPV). Serum protein parameters included 
total protein (TP), albumin (ALB), and globulin (GLB). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
All the data were analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SYSTAT</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">12</rs> software 
programs, before applying statistical test Logarithmic 
transformation has been carried out. Analysis of Variance 
(ANOVA) statistical test was applied to compare the mean 
values of the three groups, SCHEFFE multiple comparison 
to assess the mean differences within the group and Pearson 
correlation coefficient test was applied to correlate the 
hematological parameters with periodontal clinical parameters. </p>

<p>Results 
The mean value for PI and GI were lower in the healthy 
group (0.40 ± 0.20 and 0.66 ± 0.17), when compared to AgP 
(1.54 ± 0.26 and 1.58 ± 0.40). The difference was found to be 
significant (P = 0.000). Similarly, the mean value for probing </p>

<p>pocket depth (PPD) and CAL were lower in Group 1 (1.56 
± 0.25 and 0.00 ± 0.00), when compared to AgP (6.00 ± 0.62 
and 6.00 ± 0.62) which was significant (P &lt; 0.000) (Table 1). </p>

<p>The mean ± standard deviation (SD) of all blood parameters 
in the test and control groups are presented in Table 2. </p>

<p>The mean and SD of WBC count were found to be 6.991 ± 
1.274, 8.241 ± 2.477 in the healthy and AgP group respectively. 
One-way ANOVA showed no significant statistical differences 
in the WBC count between the two groups with P value 
(&lt;0.228). The mean value for neutrophil count and the 
percentage were lower in the healthy group (3.96 ± 1.39 and 
58.93 ± 8.96), when compared to AgP. The difference was 
found to be non-significant (P &lt; 0.098). Similarly, the mean 
value for lymphocyte count was higher in the healthy group 
(2.29 ± 0.59) when compared to AgP (1.97 ± 0.54). The 
difference was found to be non-significant (P &lt; 0.119). The 
mean value for platelet and MPV were lower in AgP (247.50 
± 89.02 and 10.93 ± 1.58), when compared to healthy (247.96 
± 54.79 and 11.73 ± 1.12). The difference was found to be 
significant (P &lt; 0.005). </p>

<p>The mean ± SD of all serum protein parameters in the test and 
control groups are presented in Table 3. </p>

<p>The mean and SD of TP and ALB count were found to be 
higher in healthy (6.58 ± 0.72 and 4.04 ± 0.72), when compared 
to AgP (6.40 ± 0.88 and 3.92 ± 0.59). The difference was found 
to be non-significant (P &lt; 0.651). Similarly, the value for GLB 
count were found to be slightly higher in AgP (2.61 ± 0.57) 
when compared to healthy and AgP (2.58 ± 0.49). The 
differences were found to be non-significant (P &lt; 0.814). </p>

<p>Discussion 
Periodontitis is a chronic infectious condition of the 
supporting tissues of the teeth that is caused by a complex </p>

<p>Table 1: Clinical parameters between groups (mean±SD). </p>

<p>Clinical parameters 
Group-I 
Group-II </p>

<p>PI 
0.40±0.20 
1.54±0.26 
GI 
0.66±0.17 
1.58±0.40 
PPD 
1.56±0.25 
6.00±0.62 
CAL 
0.00±0.00 
6.00±0.62 </p>

<p>SD: Standard deviation, PI: Plaque index, GI: Gingival index, CAL: clinical attachment level, 
PPD: Probing pocket depth </p>

<p>Table 2: Blood parameters between groups (mean±SD). </p>

<p>Blood parameters 
Group-I 
Group-II </p>

<p>WBC 
6.99±1.27 
8.24±2.47 
Neutrophil count 
3.96±1.39 
5.45±2.37 
Lymphocyte count 
2.29±0.59 
1.97±0.54 
Neutrophil % 
58.93±8.96 
63.48±12.23 
Lymphocyte % 
32.45±8.07 
27.27±10.38 
Platelet count 
247.96±54.79 
247.50±89.02 
Mean platelet volume 
11.73±1.12 
10.93±1.58 </p>

<p>SD: Standard deviation, WBC: White blood cell </p>



<p>Systemic inflammatory markers in aggressive periodontitis … Iqbal PS et al Journal of International Oral Health 2015; 7(Suppl 2):48-51 </p>

<p>variety of anaerobic, gram-negative bacteria. Periodontal 
destruction probably results from the action of various toxic 
products released from the specific pathogenic subgingival 
plaque bacteria, as well as from the host responses elicited 
against the plaque bacteria and their products. Epidemiologic 
studies suggest that the periodontal problems increase the 
risk of systemic problems such as cardiovascular diseases, 
cerebrovascular diseases, atherosclerosis, and diabetes mellitus. </p>

<p>In recent past, less attention has been devoted to explore the 
role of chronic oral diseases on systemic health. It has been 
shown that periodontal bacteria or their products can directly 
invade the periodontal tissue and gain access to the systemic 
circulation. Several studies have shown the systemic effect of 
periodontal diseases. 
8 Traditionally, an elevation in the number 
of peripheral leukocytes and a variation in the levels of serum 
proteins identified as acute-phase proteins are the characteristic 
of infectious conditions. Changes in blood components may 
also be detected in patients with periodontitis. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>The aim of the present case control study was to assess the 
levels of systemic inflammatory markers such as WBC count, 
neutrophil count, lymphocyte count, platelet count, and 
also serum protein parameters such as TP, ALB, and GLB in 
patients with AgP. </p>

<p>Assessment of serum proteins were also carried out in the 
study because they reflect changes associated with the systemic 
inflammatory condition. </p>

<p>The elevated WBC counts in the peripheral blood have been 
used as a traditional method to diagnose an infection or 
inflammatory disease. The total numbers of leukocytes and 
neutrophils were positively associated with the severity and 
extent of periodontitis assessed by PPD, CAL, and percentage 
of disease sites. The increasing tendency of the number of 
systemic neutrophils is the same as the neutrophils infiltrated in 
local inflammatory periodontal tissues. In a study by Shi et al. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>demonstrated that the leukocytes infiltration into periodontal 
tissues is correlated well with the periodontal status. The 
inflammatory cytokines released from the periodontal 
infection sites may mediate the local and systemic response to 
periodontal pathogens. The elevated levels of blood leukocyte 
count may be a risk factor for coronary heart disease. </p>

<p>In the present study, oral hygiene status as assessed by (Loe 
and Silness 1963) PI, revealed an increase plaque score in AgP 
(1.547 ± 0.26) as compared to healthy controls (0.40 ± 0.20) </p>

<p>and were found to be statistically significant (P &lt; 0.000). The 
above results were in accordance to Susin and Albandar. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>An increase in PPD, CAL score in AgP (6.0 ± 0.62) when 
compared to healthy controls (1.56 ± 0.25) with P value &lt;0.000 
was observed in the present study. The above results were in 
accordance to López et al. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>In the present study, though the mean difference in the 
leukocyte count exists between the two groups (6.991 ± 1.274), 
(8.241 ± 2.477) in healthy, AgP respectively, it was found to 
be without the statistical significance. The above results were 
in contrast to the result of Havemose-Poulsen et al., 
13 Dosumu 
et al., 
14 who found higher leukocyte count in patients with AGP 
when compared to the healthy group. </p>

<p>A positive and statistically significant correlation was observed 
between plaque score, BI, PPD, CAL with that of the neutrophil 
count, which is similar to the result obtained by Havemose-
Poulsen et al., 
13 López et al., 
12 who concluded that traditional 
markers of inflammation reflect the extent and severity of 
periodontal tissue involvement, as the percentage of sites with 
PI, BOP, PPD ≥ 4 mm, CAL ≥ 2 mm positively correlate with 
the levels of leukocytes and neutrophils (P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Lymphocytes play a fundamental role in the pathogenesis of 
periodontitis. The nature of the adaptive immune response 
is controlled by T cells which in turn, regulates the B cells 
and antibody production. In the present study, lymphocytes 
count showed no statistical significance in the two groups 
studied (2.29 ± 0.59), (1.97 ± 0.54) in healthy and AgP 
groups respectively, which was in contrast to the result of 
López et al. (2008) 
12 who concluded that lymphocyte count 
and percentage were significantly lower in the AgP group 
(1.79 ± 0.48) than in the control group (2.03 ± 0.59). </p>

<p>Loos, 
7 who assessed the lymphocyte numbers and function 
in relation to periodontitis and smoking and found that the 
total number of lymphocytes did not differ between the 
groups (1.97 ± 0.56), (1.84 ± 0.51), (2.14 ± 0.56) in controls, 
moderate periodontitis, and severe periodontitis respectively. </p>

<p>It is known that inflammatory and infectious processes can 
result in an increase in the number of active thrombocytes; in 
this respect, the phenomenon of "reactive thrombocytosis." 
Therefore, it is evident that periodontitis is also associated with 
the variation in the number of thrombocyte. In the present 
study, though the mean difference in the platelet count exist 
between the two groups (247.96 ± 54.79), (274.500 ± 89.025) 
in healthy and AgP respectively without statistically significant, 
which was in accordance with the result of Dong et al. (2008), </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>showed no statistical significance were observed in reference to 
platelet count (226.93 ± 50.90) in healthy and (214.60 ± 51.72) 
in AgP. Al-Rasheed et al., 
15 assessed the elevation of WBC and 
platelet counts in patients having periodontitis. The results of </p>

<p>Table 3: Protein parameters between the groups (mean±SD). </p>

<p>Protein parameters 
Group-I 
Group-II 
P value </p>

<p>Total protein 
6.58±0.72 
6.40±0.88 
P&lt;0.651 
ALB 
4.04±0.72 
3.92±0.59 
P&lt;0.629 
GLB 
2.58±0.49 
2.61±0.57 
P&lt;0.814 </p>

<p>GLB: Globulin, ALB: Albumin </p>



<p>Systemic inflammatory markers in aggressive periodontitis … Iqbal PS et al Journal of International Oral Health 2015; 7(Suppl 2):48-51 </p>

<p>the study indicate that the group with periodontal infection 
has higher mean platelet counts (290.73 ± 56.56 × 10 
9 cells/L) 
compared to the healthy group (223.37 ± 50.27 × 10 
9 cells/L), 
and were statistically significant (P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Changes in the serum protein profile reflect changes in systemic 
inflammatory condition. The assessment of TP, ALB, GLB was 
carried out in the present study. TP and ALB and GLB count 
were found to be lower in AgP when compared to healthy 
individuals. </p>

<p>Conclusion 
Systemic infections have direct effect on the general health 
and well-being of an individual. Several studies have shown 
the relationship between periodontal diseases and systemic 
health, but until recently there was not enough literature to 
prove the relationship between AgP and systemic disease. 
Within the limitations of this study, it can be suggested that 
the patients with AgP have elevated blood parameters and 
decreased serum protein levels. These changes may affect the 
rate and progression of periodontal destruction. </p>



</text></tei>