<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4454910" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>‫والدائمة،‬ ‫اللبنية‬ ‫األسنان‬ ‫في‬ ‫األسنان‬ ‫تسوس‬ ‫انتشار‬ ‫مدى‬ ‫حتديد‬ ‫األهداف:‬ 
‫العربية‬ ‫اململكة‬ ‫الدمام،‬ ‫مدينة‬ ‫في‬ ‫املدارس‬ ‫ألطفال‬ ‫التنظيف‬ ‫عادات‬ ‫وتقييم‬ 
‫السعودية.‬ </p>

<p>‫العربية‬ ‫اململكة‬ ‫الدمام،‬ ‫مدينة‬ ‫في‬ ‫املقطعية‬ ‫الدراسة‬ ‫هذه‬ ‫أجريت‬ ‫الطريقة:‬ 
‫فبراير‬ ‫من‬ ‫املشاركني‬ ‫من‬ ‫الفم‬ ‫طريق‬ ‫عن‬ ‫الدراسة‬ ‫أجريت‬ ‫وقد‬ ‫السعودية.‬ 
‫هناك‬ ‫وكان‬ ‫شخص.‬ 711 ‫الدراسة‬ ‫هذه‬ ‫شملت‬ ‫وقد‬ ‫4102م.‬ ‫مايو‬ ‫حتى‬ 
‫فحصهم‬ ‫مت‬ ‫والذين‬ ‫سنوات،‬ 9 ‫إلى‬ 6 ‫بني‬ ‫ما‬ ‫أعمارهم‬ ‫تتراوح‬ ً 
‫طفال‬ 397 
‫ممن‬ ً 
‫طفال‬ 314 ‫هناك‬ ‫كان‬ ‫فقد‬ ‫ذلك‬ ‫إلى‬ ‫باإلضافة‬ ‫اللبنية.‬ ‫األسنان‬ ‫لتسوس‬ 
‫األسنان‬ ‫تسوس‬ ‫فحص‬ ‫مت‬ ‫والذين‬ ‫سنة‬ 10-12 ‫بني‬ ‫ما‬ ‫أعمارهم‬ ‫تتراوح‬ 
‫املسوسة‬ ‫والدائمة‬ ‫األساسية‬ ‫األسنان‬ ‫على‬ ‫دراسة‬ ‫متت‬ ‫ولقد‬ ‫لديهم.‬ ‫الدائمة‬ 
‫(األسنان‬ DMFT / ‫األساسية)‬ ‫(األسنان‬ DMFT[ ‫واحملشوة‬ ‫واملفقودة‬ 
‫الدائمة)].‬ </p>

<p>‫في‬ ‫األسنان‬ ‫تسوس‬ ‫انتشار‬ ‫معدل‬ ‫أن‬ ‫إلى‬ ‫الدراسة‬ ‫نتائج‬ ‫أشارت‬ ‫النتائج:‬ 
‫وكان‬ .)711 = ‫(العدد‬ 73% ‫كان‬ ‫قد‬ ً 
‫تقريبا‬ ‫والدائمة‬ ‫اللبنية‬ ‫األسنان‬ 
78% ‫حوالي‬ ً 
‫عاما‬ 6-9 ‫العمرية‬ ‫املرحلة‬ ‫لدى‬ ‫التسوس‬ ‫انتشار‬ ‫معدل‬ 
68% ‫حوالي‬ ‫سنة،‬ 10-12 ‫بني‬ ‫األطفال‬ ‫عمر‬ ‫كان‬ ‫حني‬ ‫في‬ ‫(العدد=793)،‬ 
6-9 ‫العمرية‬ ‫الفئة‬ ‫لدى‬ DMFT ‫قيمة‬ ‫معدل‬ ‫وكان‬ .)314 = ‫(العدد‬ 
،3.28±2.92 )d( ‫التسوس‬ ‫عامل‬ ‫معدل‬ ‫كان‬ ‫حيث‬ 3.13 ± 3.66 ً 
‫عاما‬ 
‫عامل‬ ‫معدل‬ ‫كان‬ ً ‫وأخيرا‬ ، 0.11±0.69 )m( ‫املفقودة‬ ‫األسنان‬ ‫عامل‬ ‫وكان‬ 
‫لدى‬ DMFT ‫قيمة‬ ‫معدل‬ ‫كان‬ ‫فيما‬ .0.26±0.9 )f( ‫احملشوة‬ ‫األسنان‬ 
‫التسوس‬ ‫عامل‬ ‫معدل‬ ‫كان‬ ‫حيث‬ 1.94±2.0 ً 
‫عاما‬ 10-12 ‫العمرية‬ ‫الفئة‬ 
، 0.03±0.22 )M( ‫املفقودة‬ ‫األسنان‬ ‫عامل‬ ‫وكان‬ ،1.76±1.85 )D( 
‫كان‬ ‫وقد‬ . 0.15±0.73 )F( ‫احملشوة‬ ‫األسنان‬ ‫عامل‬ ‫معدل‬ ‫كان‬ ً ‫وأخيرا‬ 
‫وهذا‬ ‫التسوس،‬ ‫من‬ ‫الوقاية‬ ‫على‬ ً 
‫إيجابيا‬ ‫أثرا‬ ً 
‫يوميا‬ ‫بالفرشاة‬ ‫األسنان‬ ‫لتفريش‬ 
‫اللبنية.‬ ‫األسنان‬ ‫تسوس‬ ‫في‬ ‫إحصائية‬ ‫داللة‬ ‫له‬ ‫كان‬ ‫التأثير‬ </p>

<p>‫والدائمة‬ ‫اللبنية‬ ‫األسنان‬ ‫في‬ ‫األسنان‬ ‫تسوس‬ ‫انتشار‬ ‫من‬ ‫الرغم‬ ‫على‬ ‫اخلامتة:‬ 
‫من‬ ‫مختلفة‬ ‫مدن‬ ‫من‬ ‫األخرى‬ ‫الدراسات‬ ‫به‬ ‫أفاد‬ ‫مبا‬ ً 
‫مقارنة‬ ً 
‫مرتفعا‬ ‫يكن‬ ‫لم‬ 
‫االعتبار‬ ‫بعني‬ ‫يؤخذ‬ ‫مازال‬ ‫التسوس‬ ‫انتشار‬ ‫أنه‬ ‫إال‬ ‫السعودية‬ ‫العربية‬ ‫اململكة‬ 
‫واألسنان‬ ‫الفم‬ ‫صحة‬ ‫وأهداف‬ )WHO( ‫العاملية‬ ‫الصحة‬ ‫منظمة‬ ‫قبل‬ ‫من‬ ‫في‬ 
‫وأولياء‬ ‫املعلمني‬ ‫وكذلك‬ ‫الطالب‬ ‫توعية‬ ‫فينبغي‬ ‫ولذلك‬ ‫املستقبل.‬ ‫في‬ 
‫املنتظمة‬ ‫والزيارات‬ ً ‫جيدا‬ ‫بالفرشاة‬ ‫األسنان‬ ‫تفريش‬ ‫أهمية‬ ‫حول‬ ‫األمور‬ 
‫األسنان.‬ ‫لطبيب‬ </p>

<p>Objectives: To determine the prevalence of dental 
caries in the primary and permanent teeth, and evaluate 
the brushing habits of school children in Dammam, 
Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (KSA). </p>

<p>Methods. This study was conducted at Dammam, KSA. 
Oral examination of the participants was conducted from 
February to May 2014. The total sample size for this cross-
sectional study was 711. There were 397 children between 
the age of 6-9 years, who were examined for primary teeth 
caries, and 314 between the age 10-12 years were examined 
for permanent teeth caries. Primary and permanent 
dentitions were studied for decayed, missing, and filled 
teeth (dmft [primary teeth], DMFT [permanent teeth]). </p>

<p>Results: The overall prevalence of dental caries in primary 
and permanent teeth was almost 73% (n=711). Among the 
6-9-year-old, the prevalence of caries was approximately 
78% (n=397) whereas, among the 10-12-year-old 
children, it was approximately 68% (n=314). Mean 
dmft value among the 6-9-year-olds was 3.66±3.13 
with decayed (d) component of 3.28±2.92, missing (m) 
component of 0.11±0.69, and filled (f ) component of 
0.26±0.9. Mean DMFT value among the 10-12-year-old 
children was 1.94±2.0 with decayed (D) component of 
1.76±1.85, missing (M) component of 0.03±0.22, and 
filled (F) of component 0.15±0.73. Daily tooth brushing 
had a positive effect on caries prevention, and this effect 
was statistically significant for caries in primary teeth. </p>

<p>Conclusion: Although the prevalence of dental caries in 
primary and permanent teeth was not found to be as high 
as other researchers reported from different cities of KSA, 
still the prevalence was high considering the World Health 
Organization future oral health goals. Awareness should 
be provided to students, as well as, teachers and parents 
regarding the importance of good brushing habits and 
regular dental visits. </p>



<p>Dental caries among schoolchildren in Dammam ... Farooqi et al </p>

<p>Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (6) www.smj.org.sa </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>ental caries is one of the most common cause of 
extraction of primary teeth in Saudi Arabia. 
1 In 
the past few decades, an increase in the prevalence of 
dental caries has been observed, which can be attributed 
to a change in lifestyle of Saudis, involving increased 
consumption of sugary food, carbonated drinks, and lack 
of awareness towards proper oral health maintenance. </p>

<p>2,3 </p>

<p>Generally, the prevalence of dental caries in developed 
countries is decreasing, while in underdeveloped and 
developing countries, the prevalence is on the rise. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>According to the statistics available from the World 
Health Organization (WHO), caries prevalence among 
the 12-year-old children from many European Union 
states (EU) has decreased considerably from 1970's to 
2006. 
5 This decline in the caries' prevalence among EU 
countries over a period of 35 years could be attributed 
to an increased awareness of oral hygiene maintenance, 
and use of fluoridated toothpaste. 
6 However, among 
underdeveloped countries where fluoridated toothpaste 
is not easily available, or not affordable in some cases, 
caries prevalence is still high. 
7 The area of dental caries 
prevalence is of great interest to local and international 
researchers, which can be indicated by a number of 
studies that have been performed in developed and 
developing countries regarding caries' prevalence. </p>

<p>8-10 </p>

<p>A study conducted in the urban and rural areas of 
Lahore, Pakistan to determine whether urbanization 
and family earnings are related to dental caries reported 
caries prevalence of 40.5%, and decayed (d), missing 
(m), and filled (f ) teeth (dmft [primary teeth]) score 
of 1.85 ± 3.26 in preschool children aged 3-5 years, </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>while another cross-sectional study performed in 
Chikar, Pakistan with convenience sampling of 311 
schoolchildren revealed an overall DMFT (permanent 
teeth) score of 3.3 in 5-20-year-olds. 
12 Several studies 
have been conducted in different parts of the Kingdom 
of Saudi Arabia (KSA) to report the prevalence of dental 
caries in schoolchildren. A study performed in Riyadh 
reported a dmft score of 6.1, decayed factor of 4.6, and 
no significant difference in the prevalence of caries in 
relation to gender among 789 pre-school children. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Farsi 
14 conducted a study to develop an association </p>

<p>between enamel defects and caries occurrence in 
Jeddah, KSA, and reported a dmft score of 3.9, and a 
strong association between enamel defects and caries 
prevalence among 4-5-year-olds. 
14 In 2012, caries 
prevalence in the maxillary and mandibular first molar 
in the age group of 7-10 years schoolchildren was 
determined in Abha city, and a mean DMFT of 2.74 
was reported. 
15 It was also concluded in the same study 
that caries prevalence in the first permanent molars from 
this region is higher than the recommended standards 
of the WHO. 
15 Extensive literature search was carried 
out to find studies regarding caries' prevalence from 
Dammam, KSA. The search resulted in only one study, 
which was conducted in 2008 on children with cleft lip 
and palate aged 1-6 years, and it reported a high dmft of 
10.54 from Dammam region. 
16 Since Dammam is one 
of the largest cities of the Eastern province of KSA, it 
would be interesting to observe caries' prevalence among 
schoolchildren from this city. Therefore, the aim of the 
present study was to determine the prevalence of dental 
caries in schoolchildren aged 6-12 years in Dammam, 
KSA using the dmft/DMFT index of dental caries. </p>

<p>Methods. This study was conducted at the Schools 
in Dammam, Saudi Arabia. Ethical approval was 
obtained from the Deanship of Scientific Research, 
University of Dammam, KSA before commencing 
the study. The participants for this study were chosen 
randomly from different schools of Dammam, and the 
schools were pre-informed regarding the objectives of 
the study. A written informed consent was obtained 
from the school administration and parents of children 
involved in the study. A team of 7 members was created, 
which comprised of 4 dentists and 3 dental assistants. 
All the dentists had previous experiences in the field 
of epidemiology. Three of the 4 dentists were involved 
in the examination of the participants, and the fourth 
conducted lectures regarding oral health awareness to the 
students after examination. Dental assistants recorded 
the data on a WHO form. 
17 Team member training 
started with a theoretical discussion after a power point 
presentation, and was followed by a pilot study, which 
was performed on 20 students that were not included 
in the study. This cross-sectional study was performed 
using stratified random sampling to calculate the sample. 
Seven hundred and eleven schoolchildren representing 
the age group 6-12 years, and belonging to the school-
going population of Dammam were subjected to dental 
examination according to the WHO diagnostic criteria. 
Oral examination of the participants was conducted </p>

<p>Disclosure. Authors have no conflict of interests, and 
the work was not supported or funded by any drug 
company. This study received a grant from the University 
of Dammam, Dammam, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia 
(Grant no. 2013142). </p>



<p>www.smj.org.sa Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (6) </p>

<p>Dental caries among schoolchildren in Dammam ... Farooqi et al </p>

<p>from February to May 2014. All participants were 
examined with disposable mirror, disposable probe, 
and disposable tweezers along with disposable masks 
and gloves. The examination procedure and forms used 
were based on WHO criteria. The inclusion criteria for 
the study were students between 6-12 years old, and 
residents of Dammam and Khobar municipality, as 
confirmed by the school registry. Each participant was 
asked questions regarding their age and brushing habits, 
and DMFT index was used to record the data, and the 
teeth, which were congenitally missing, or removed for 
orthodontic purposes were not considered as missing. 
To calculate the prevalence of dmft in primary teeth, 
the sum of dmft was divided by the sample size of 6-9-
year-old children. The same procedure was carried out 
to calculate the DMFT for permanent teeth for age 
between 10-12 years. 
The IBM <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for Social Sciences</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 19</rs> for Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corp</rs>, Armonk, NY, 
USA) was used for data entry and analysis. Descriptive 
and inferential statistics were performed to analyze 
the data. T-test was used to analyze any statistically 
significant difference between gender, nationality, and 
brushing habits with prevalence of caries. The analysis 
of variance (ANOVA) was employed to check the 
significance between age and caries prevalence. The level 
of significance was set at 0.05. Post hoc test was also 
used to check for any significant increase, or decrease 
in dental caries due to increase in age. Inter-examiner 
agreement was analyzed using Kappa statistics, and a 
high degree of agreement (Kappa index: 89.7%) was 
observed between the 2 examiners. </p>

<p>Results. Prevalence of primary teeth caries. The 
overall prevalence of dental caries in primary and 
permanent teeth was 73.3% among the total number 
of children examined for the present study. Among 
the 6-9-year-olds, the prevalence of caries was 77.8%. 
Among the age group 6-9 years (mean age: 7.63 ± 1.1), 
397 students (218 male, 179 female, and 160 Saudis, 
237 non-Saudi) were examined for the prevalence of 
caries. The mean dmft among 6-9-year-old children was 
3.66 ± 3.13 with a "d" component of 3.28 ± 2.92, "m" 
component of 0.11 ± 0.69, and "f " component of 0.26 
± 0.9. There was no significant effect in age, gender, or 
nationality on the prevalence of caries. Prevalence of 
caries in males was 3.56 ± 3.09 with "d" component 
of 3.13 ± 2.8, "m" component of 0.14 ± 0.85, and "f " 
component of 0.29 ± 0.96. While in females, it was 
found to be 3.78 ± 3.17 with a "d" component of 3.47 ± 
3.1, "m" component of 0.08 ± 0.4, and "f " component </p>

<p>0.22 ± 0.83. Among male Saudis, the average dmft score 
was 3.92 ± 3.25, while among non-Saudis, the score 
was 3.48 ± 3.04. Children were also asked whether they 
brush their teeth regularly. Three hundred and twenty 
one replied affirmatively, 72 replied negatively, and 4 
did not answer the question. Children who brushed 
daily had a mean dmft of 3.42 ± 3.00, and those who 
did not brush daily had a mean dmft of 4.79 ± 3.44, 
and the difference in mean was found to be statistically 
significant (p&lt;0.001). Variation in sample is shown in 
Figure 1, and variation in caries prevalence according to 
age of the children is presented in Table 1. 
Prevalence of permanent teeth caries. Among 10-
12-year-olds, the prevalence of caries was 68%. In the 
age group 10-12 years (mean age: 10.94 ± 0.833), 314 
students (188 male; 126 female and 117 Saudi; 197 
non-Saudi) were examined for the prevalence of caries. 
Mean DMFT was found to be 1.94 ± 2.0 with a "D" 
component of 1.76 ± 1.85, "M" component of 0.03 ± 
0.22, and "F" component of 0.15 ± 0.73. The DMFT 
among males was 2.06 ± 2.08, while in females it was 
1.76 ± 1.86. Effect of the variable nationality was also 
considered, and DMFT was calculated for Saudi and 
non-Saudi children. Mean DMFT for Saudi children 
was 2.23 ± 2.14, whereas among non-Saudis, it was 1.77 
± 1.89, and the difference in caries' prevalence among </p>

<p>Figure 1 -Distribution of sample for primary teeth caries according 
to age in a group of schoolchildren from Dammam, Saudi 
Arabia. </p>

<p>Table 1 -Prevalence of dental caries in primary dentition by age of 
schoolchildren from Dammam, Saudi Arabia (N=397). </p>

<p>Age 
Decayed 
Missing 
Filled 
Mean dmft 
6 
3.27 ± 3.5 
0.01 ± 0.11 
0.23 ± 0.72 
3.5 ± 3.52 
7 
3.65 ± 3.1 
0.21 ± 1.3 
0.24 ± 1.02 
4.1 ± 3.6 
8 
3.36 ± 2.6 
0.1 ± 0.5 
0.25 ± 0.9 
3.7 ± 2.8 
9 
2.99 ± 2.65 
0.14 ± 0.49 
0.30 ± 0.94 
3.43 ± 2.8) </p>

<p>Total 
3.28 ± 2.92 
0.11 ± 0.69 
0.26 ± 0.90 
3.66 ± 3.17 </p>

<p>dmft -decayed, missing, and filled teeth (primary teeth) </p>



<p>Dental caries among schoolchildren in Dammam ... Farooqi et al </p>

<p>Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (6) www.smj.org.sa </p>

<p>Saudi and non-Saudi students was found statistically 
significant (p=0.046). Post-hoc test (Tukey test) was 
employed to find a statistical significance between 
ages and caries' prevalence, and it was found that the 
increase in caries' prevalence between 10-12 years was 
statistically significant (p&lt;0.001). Eighty-two percent 
of children among this group used to brush their teeth 
daily but no statistical influence was found on caries' 
prevalence. Mean DMFT among those who brushed 
their teeth daily was 1.87 ± 1.97 with a "D" component 
of 1.72 ± 1.87, "M" component of 0.01 ± 0.09, and 
"F" component of 0.015 ± 0.67. On the other hand, 
mean DMFT of 2.26 ± 2.14 with a "D" component 
of 1.97 ± 1.74, "M" component of 0.1 ± 0.48, and "F" 
component of 0.19 ± 0.96 was found among students 
who did not brush daily. Variation in sample (Figure 2) 
and variation in caries prevalence according to age of 
the children is presented in Table 2. </p>

<p>Discussion. The overall prevalence of dental caries 
in primary and permanent teeth was 73.3% among 
the total number of children examined for the present 
study. Among the 6-9-year-old, the prevalence of caries 
was 77.8%, whereas among the 10-12-year-old, it was 
approximately 68%. The WHO/FDI (World Dental 
Federation) oral health goals to be achieved by the year </p>

<p>2000 reported that prevalence of caries in 5-6-year-olds 
should be less than 50%, and number of teeth affected 
from caries at the age of 12 should not be more than 
3. 
18 The results of this study revealed that approximately 
68% of 6-year-olds were suffering from caries, and this 
figure was quite high compared with the WHO oral 
health goals. 
18 Mean DMFT was 2.82 for 12-year-olds, 
which was under the desirable range set by the WHO. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Khan et al 
19 performed another literature search in 2013 
in KSA, in which studies published during 1999-2008 
were reviewed. The prevalence of primary teeth caries 
in KSA reported by this study 
19 during 1999-2008 was 
5.38, and for the permanent teeth it was 3.34. 
19 This 
study reported high caries' prevalence in KSA compared 
with the present study. Various other researchers 
reported high caries prevalence from different cities of 
KSA in contrast with the present study results, </p>

<p>13,20-24 </p>

<p>however, some studies have also reported decreased 
caries prevalence in primary and permanent teeth </p>

<p>25-30 </p>

<p>than the results reported in the current study. 
Khan et al 
31 published a review on the prevalence 
of dental caries in the Arab League, and the study 
reported caries prevalence of 4.34 in primary dentition, 
and 1.77 in permanent dentition. 
32 The population 
of Dammam city had better dental health of primary 
teeth found in this study compared with Khan et al's </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>study results. Azizi 
32 performed a study in the Northern 
Palestine reporting that the prevalence of caries among 
5-6-year-olds was approximately 76%, which is higher 
than what was reported in Dammam, KSA. Hashim et 
al 
33 performed a study in the United Arab Emirates to 
assess caries prevalence in primary dentition, and they 
detected caries among 73% of the screened children. 
We can conclude that in comparison with studies 
conducted in various countries of the Arab League 
revealed that the prevalence of caries among 6-12-
year-olds living in Dammam, KSA was lower than the 
rest. Furthermore, children were asked regarding their 
tooth brushing habits. Approximately 81% (n=576) 
of the children brushed their teeth daily, and among 
those, 61% (n=353) stated that they clean their teeth 
more than one time a day. In primary and permanent 
teeth, the trend was the same for brushing habits that 
caries incidence was low with daily brushing habit. 
Statistically the data was significant for primary, and 
insignificant for permanent dentition. Schools provide 
a perfect initial setting for children to get educated 
regarding proper oral hygiene maintenance, and to 
learn regarding prevention strategies, and acquiring 
oral health education at this stage would help them to 
develop lifelong skills to maintain and improve their 
oral health. </p>

<p>Figure 2 -Distribution of sample for permanent teeth caries according 
to age in a group of schoolchildren from Dammam, Saudi 
Arabia. </p>

<p>Table 2 -Prevalence of dental caries in permanent dentition by age of 
children from Dammam, Saudi Arabia (N=314). </p>

<p>Age 
Decayed 
Missing 
Filled 
Mean DMFT 
10 
1.26 ± 1.41 
0.02 ± 0.13 
0.03 ± 0.16 
1.3 ± 1.44 
11 
1.57 ± 1.74 
0.06 ± 0.37 
0.22 ± 0.89 
1.85 ± 2.04 
12 
2.59 ± 2.12 
0.0 ± 0.0 
0.24 ± 0.93 
2.82 ± 2.22 
Total 
1.76 ± 1.85 
0.03 ± 0.22 
0.15 ± 0.73 
1.94 ± 2.0 
DMFT -decayed, missing, and filled teeth (permanent teeth) </p>



<p>www.smj.org.sa Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (6) </p>

<p>Dental caries among schoolchildren in Dammam ... Farooqi et al </p>

<p>The present study had certain limitations, such as the 
sample size, which was not large enough to generalize 
the results. Dietary habits, socio-economic status, and 
education of parents also proved useful as important 
determinants of dental caries. 
In conclusion, it was found that the prevalence of 
primary and permanent teeth caries was not as high 
as other researchers reported from different cities of 
KSA, 
23-28 however, the figures were still high according 
to WHO/FDI oral health goals. 
18 Results revealed the 
positive impact of tooth brushing habits on caries, so it 
is highly recommended to make the students, as well 
as, teachers and parents be aware on the importance of 
brushing habits. Knowledge regarding the risk factors of 
dental caries will also help to control and reduce dental 
caries. Authors recommend to conduct further studies 
in which factors associated with caries will be studied. 
it is also recommended to repeat this kind of studies 
after few years so that the updated status of population's 
dental health would be reported. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment. The authors gratefully acknowledge the 
support provided by the administration of all the schools of Dammam, 
Saudi Arabia, which participated in this study. The authors would also 
like to thank all the children involved in this study for their utmost 
cooperation. We would also like to thank Dr. Abdul Aziz Al Amri and 
Dr. Mohammad Hassan Abdullah Al Abbad for their cooperation 
during data collection. </p>







</text></tei>