<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4230595" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT The dynamic relationship between constitutive and ligand-triggered clathrin-
mediated endocytosis is only poorly characterized, and it remains controversial whether 
clathrin-coated pits specialize to internalize particular receptor cargo. Here we analyzed the 
ligand-triggered endocytosis of the model G-protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs) β2-
adrenergic receptor (β2AR) and Mu-opioid receptor (MOR) at the level of individual endo-
cytic events using a total internal reflection fluorescence microscopy (TIRFM)-based assay. 
Similar to the constitutive endocytosis of transferrin receptor (TfR), ligand-triggered endocy-
tosis of β2AR occurs via quantized scission events hosted by clathrin spots and plaques of 
variable size and persistence. To address whether clathrin-coated structures (CCSs) specialize 
to internalize particular GPCRs, we adapted the TIRFM imaging assay to simultaneously 
quantify the internalization of TfR and the ligand-triggered endocytosis of the β2AR or MOR. 
Agonist-triggered β2AR or MOR endocytosis extended the maturation time of CCSs, as 
shown previously, but did not affect the rate of constitutive TfR endocytosis or loading of TfR 
into individual endocytic vesicles. Both the β2AR and the MOR receptors entered cells in the 
same vesicles as TfR, and the overall evidence for CCS specialization was weak. These data 
support a simple model in which different cargoes internalize through common CCSs. </p>

<p>Clathrin-mediated endocytosis is the main pathway for receptor 
internalization in eukaryotic cells. In this well-conserved pathway, </p>

<p>receptors concentrate at clathrin-coated pits through association 
with adaptors and internalize as coated pits invaginate and bud into 
the cell. Total internal reflection fluorescence microscopy (TIRFM) 
has become an important tool to analyze the spatial and temporal 
organization of clathrin-mediated endocytosis in living cells 
(Rappoport, 2008). However, there remains some controversy over 
what constitutes a "canonical" clathrin-coated pit in live-cell imag-
ing studies. Some studies suggest that receptor-mediated endocy-
tosis is restricted to discrete, punctate clathrin-coated pits, whereas 
larger and more stable clathrin plaques are endocytically inactive 
(Batchelder and Yarar, 2010) or constitute a unique pathway of endo-
cytosis (Saffarian et al., 2009). However, when individual constitutive 
endocytic events of transferrin receptor (TfR), tagged with pH-sensi-
tive super-ecliptic pHluorin (sePhl; Sankaranarayanan and Ryan, 
2000), were imaged directly using a TIRFM-based "pulsed pH" </p>

<p>Monitoring Editor 
David G. Drubin 
University of California, 
Berkeley </p>

<p>Received: Jun 17, 2014 
Revised: Jul 18, 2014 
Accepted: Jul 18, 2014 </p>

<p>This article was published online ahead of print in MBoC in Press (http://www 
.molbiolcell.org/cgi/doi/10.1091/mbc.E14-06-1112) on July 30, 2014. 
Address correspondence to: Christien J. Merrifield (christien.merrifield@lebs 
.cnrs-gif.fr). </p>

<p>© 2014 Lampe et al. This article is distributed by The American Society for Cell 
Biology under license from the author(s). Two months after publication it is avail-
able to the public under an Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported 
Creative Commons License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0). 
"ASCB </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>," "The American Society for Cell Biology </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>," and "Molecular Biology of 
the Cell 
® " are registered trademarks of The American Society of Cell Biology. </p>

<p>Abbreviations used: β2AR, β2-adrenergic receptor(s); CCS, clathrin-coated 
structure(s); GPCR, G-protein-coupled receptor(s); MOR, mu-opioid receptor(s); 
TfR, transferrin receptor(s); TIRFM, total internal reflection fluorescence micros-
copy. </p>

<p>Volume 25 October 1, 2014 </p>

<p>Dual single-scission event analysis | 3071 </p>

<p>could be detected while isoproterenol was washed on, and then 
off, the target cell. 
In an example HEK293 cell coexpressing green phl-β2AR and 
Clc-mCherry, phl-β2AR fluorescence was homogeneous across the 
plasma membrane and did not colocalize with punctate CCSs 
(Figure 1Ai). The cell was imaged with pH cycling for 250 s, and in 
an example image acquired at pH 5.5, no pH-resistant phl-β2AR 
was detected close to the plasma membrane (Figure 1Ai). At 250 s, 
the perfusion stream was switched to buffers containing 20 μM iso-
proterenol, which triggered rapid recruitment of phl-β2AR into CCSs 
(Figure 1Ai). In an example image acquired at pH 5.5, a population 
of brightly fluorescent punctae was revealed colocalized with 
Clc-mCherry labeled CCSs and with patches of phl-β2AR at pH 7.4 
(Figure 1Aii, yellow circles). Not all clathrin patches colocalized with 
a correlated spot of phl-β2AR at pH 7.4 (Figure 1Aii, white arrow-
head). These rare CCSs could represent coated pits that entirely 
lacked phl-β2AR (Cao et al., 1998), or they could be CCSs that 
pinched of at pH 5.5 or otherwise naturally acidified after scission; in 
either of the latter cases, the phl-β2AR cargo would be quenched 
and therefore invisible. The pH-resistant spots of phl-β2AR fluores-
cence in images acquired at pH 5.5 represented newly formed en-
docytic vesicles containing phl-β2AR that pinched off of the plasma 
membrane as the cell was perfused with a pulse of buffer at pH 7.4 
in the preceding image (Figure 1Aii, yellow circles). 
Phl-β2AR(+) scission events manifested as the abrupt appear-
ance of pH 5.5-resistant phl-β2AR spots colocalized with a cluster of 
phl-β2AR at pH 7.4 (Figure 1B). To quantify scission events, we used 
a semiautomated analysis similar to one described previously (Taylor 
et al., 2011). Acid-resistant phl-β2AR spots were tracked, their fluo-
rescence quantified, and bona fide scission events classified primar-
ily on the ratio of signal to noise (S/N) of the step increase in fluores-
cence (Figure 1B). 
The rapid clustering of phl-β2AR at CCSs was coordinated with a 
burst of detected scission events in images acquired at pH 5.5 
(Figure 1C, gray histogram). Analysis of a cumulative frequency plot 
(n = 1986 events, N = 3 cells) revealed a remarkably steady flux of 
scission events for the duration of isoproterenol exposure (Figure 
1C, blue line). At t = 850 s, the perfusion stream was switched back 
to buffer lacking isoproterenol, after which the rate of scission events 
tailed off over ∼200 s (Figure 1C). </p>

<p>β2AR(+) scission events occurred at clathrin spots 
and plaques </p>

<p>The dynamic characteristics of endocytically active CCSs and the 
relationship between clathrin-coated bud maturation and CCS life-
time remains only poorly appreciated (for discussion see Mooren 
et al., 2012). In general, endocytically active CCSs at the adherent 
surface of cells were considered to be discrete, punctate CCSs that 
nucleated, grew in fluorescence, maintained a stable plateau of 
fluorescence for some variable time (mean, ∼50 s), and abruptly 
disappeared upon internalization (Merrifield et al., 2002; Ehrlich 
et al., 2004; Loerke et al., 2009). Larger, persistent clathrin plaques 
were considered either to be endocytically inactive (Batchelder 
and Yarar, 2010) or to be involved in a different, "noncanonical" 
clathrin-mediated endocytic pathway (Saffarian et al., 2009). How-
ever, there is also evidence that the distinction of size classes of 
CCS is almost superfluous with regard to clathrin-coated bud for-
mation because in NIH3T3 cells, quantized TfR(+) scission events 
were hosted by both discrete, punctate CCSs and larger and more 
persistent clathrin patches, and either type of structure could po-
tentially host multiple scission events (Merrifield et al., 2005; Taylor 
et al., 2011). </p>

<p>assay, it was found that both punctate coated pits and larger plaques 
could host multiple discrete, quantized scission events (Merrifield 
et al., 2005; Taylor et al., 2011). The pulsed pH assay identified indi-
vidual scission events using the occlusion of fluorescently tagged, 
pH-sensitive receptor cargo from rhythmically imposed external pH 
changes (Merrifield et al., 2005; Taylor et al., 2011). Here we used 
the pulsed pH assay to determine the physical characteristics of 
clathrin-coated structures (CCSs) that endocytosed the two model 
G-protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs) β2-adrenergic receptor (β2AR) 
and Mu-opioid receptor (MOR). 
A second point of controversy is whether clathrin-coated pits can 
specialize to internalize specific cargo to the exclusion of other types 
of receptor. It has been suggested that CCPs can specialize to inter-
nalize different types of GPCR (Mundell et al., 2006) or to internalize 
particular GPCRs while excluding TfR, which implies that receptor 
sorting can start at the plasma membrane (Cao et al., 1998; Tosoni 
et al., 2005; Puthenveedu and von Zastrow, 2006). In an alternative 
model, all CCPs are capable of internalizing a mixture of receptor 
cargo via a variety of receptor-specific adaptor proteins (Keyel et al., 
2006), and receptor sorting begins only after internalization (Burd 
and Cullen, 2014). 
To probe the dynamic relationship between constitutive and li-
gand-triggered receptor-mediated endocytosis and to quantita-
tively analyze the cointernalization of different types of receptor at 
individual scission events, we extended the pulsed pH assay to si-
multaneously image two different receptors, with the TfR labeled 
green (with sePhl) and either β2AR or MOR labeled red with the 
moderately pH-sensitive fluorescent protein mApple (Shaner et al., 
2008). </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Single-event detection of β2-adrenergic receptor 
endocytosis </p>

<p>To measure the dynamics of constitutive clathrin-mediated endocy-
tosis in HEK293 cells, we used an optical assay to detect single-
scission events of TfR (Merrifield et al., 2005; Taylor et al., 2011). 
Briefly, TfR was tagged at the extracellular domain with super-eclip-
tic pHluorin, a pH-sensitive variant of green fluorescent protein 
(Miesenbock et al., 1998; Sankaranarayanan and Ryan, 2000) to 
produce TfR-phl (Merrifield et al., 2005). A large-diameter perfusion 
tip was brought close to the target cell, and perfusate was cycled 
between buffer of pH 7.4 and 5.5 in synchrony with image acquisi-
tion at 0.5 Hz using dual-color TIRFM (Merrifield et al., 2005; Taylor 
et al., 2011; Supplemental Figure S1A). Scission events manifested 
as the abrupt appearance of pH-resistant TfR-phl punctae in im-
ages acquired at pH 5.5, colocalized with CCSs labeled with 
mCherry-tagged clathrin light chain (Clc-mCherry; Supplemental 
Figure S1A). 
To detect single ligand-triggered endocytic events, we 
tagged the model GPCR β2AR at the extracellular N-terminus 
with super-ecliptic pHluorin to make phl-β2AR. The hemaggluti-
nin leader sequence was inserted N-terminal to pHluorin to 
ensure the correct membrane insertion of the receptor (see 
Materials and Methods). As shown in an earlier study, attach-
ment of pHluorin in front of the extracellular domain had negli-
gible effects on the pharmacokinetics of ligand-triggered β2AR 
endocytosis (Puthenveedu et al., 2010). To detect single-scission 
events, we used a perfusion system (Taylor et al., 2012) to inte-
grate rhythmic changes of extracellular pH with controlled perfu-
sion of the β2AR agonist isoproterenol, which rapidly triggers 
β2AR signaling and endocytosis (Staehelin and Simons, 1982; 
Supplemental Figure S1, B-D). Hence potential scission events </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>background features were quenched at pH 5.5 and so did not inter-
fere with the detection of CCSs or scission events. Strikingly, when 
β2AR(+) scission events were mapped to their host CCS, both clath-
rin punctae and clathrin plaques could host spot-like scission events 
(Figure 2, Bi and Bii). To quantify the distribution of scission events 
among spot-like CCSs and clathrin plaques for five cells, we seg-
mented images (see Materials and Methods) and quantified the 
pixel area of the phl-β2AR(+)-marking scission and the correspond-
ing "host" CCS, labeled with Mu2-mCherry, and plotted the result 
as a density scatterplot (Figure 2C). All scission events were the size 
of diffraction-limited spots, but a significant proportion (∼10%) of 
clathrin objects hosting scission events were significantly larger 
blobs and so classified as "plaques." Therefore (and as shown previ-
ously for TfR-phl; Taylor et al., 2011), both clathrin spots and plaques 
could host discrete, quantized scission events of phl-β2AR, and the </p>

<p>To define the dynamic characteristics of CCSs that hosted 
β2AR(+) scission events, we transfected HEK293 cells with phl-β2AR 
and Mu2-mCherry to label CCSs and detected and analyzed scis-
sion events as described. Similar to NIH3T3 fibroblasts, both spot-
like CCSs and larger and longer-lived clathrin plaques could exist at 
the adherent surface of HEK293 cells (Figure 2A). Persistent clathrin 
plaques occurred in a significant proportion (∼10%) of cells growing 
on fibronectin-coated coverslips and were most likely triggered by 
tight adhesion to the substrate (Batchelder and Yarar, 2010). On 
challenge with isoproterenol, phl-β2AR rapidly clustered at preexist-
ing spot-like CCSs (Puthenveedu and von Zastrow, 2006) and large 
clathrin plaques (Figure 2, A and Bi). As shown earlier, not all punc-
tate CCSs showed clear colocalization with phl-β2AR at pH 7.4 
(Figure 1Aii), and fine, finger-like projections at the lower surface of 
some HEK293 cells obscured things further (Figure 2Ai). These </p>

<p>FIGURE 1: Single-event analysis of β2AR internalization. (Ai) Example HEK293 cell expressing Clc-mCh (left) and 
phl-β2AR at pH7.4 (middle) and 2 s later at pH 5.5 (right); first image taken ∼428 s before addition of isoproterenol. At 
pH 5.5, cell-surface phl-β2AR quenched and no pH-resistant, phl-β2AR(+)endosomes were visible close to the plasma 
membrane. (Aii) Same cell 240 s after addition of isoproterenol. Phl-β2AR became concentrated at coated pits at pH 7.4 
(middle). When cell-surface phl-β2AR was quenched 2 s later at pH 5.5, acid-resistant endosomes containing phl-β2AR 
were clearly visible close to the plasma membrane. (Aiii) Expanded region indicated in Aii, showing Clc-mCh (magenta, 
top left), phl-β2AR at p H7.4 (green, middle left), and overlay (lower left). Three acid-resistant, phl-β2AR(+) endosomes 
were visible in the field (green, middle right) colocalized with CCS (yellow circles). (B) Time-resolved images of a 
single-scission event engulfing phl-β2AR. The fluorescence was quantified and bona fide scission events defined 
primarily on the basis of S/N (lower graph, scale: vertical 2.5 a.u., horizontal 33 s; see Materials and Methods for details). 
(C) Time course of detected scission events before, during, and after addition of isoproterenol. Summarized data from 
four cells showing the incidence of scission events over a 20-s time window (gray histogram) and the cumulative number 
of scission events (blue line). </p>

<p>Volume 25 October 1, 2014 </p>

<p>Dual single-scission event analysis | 3073 </p>

<p>relative sizes of clathrin spots and plaques 
are poor predictors of the endocytic poten-
tial of any given CCS. In previous studies, it 
was likely that the endocytic activity at the 
edges of clathrin plaques was masked by 
the bright fluorescence of the plaque itself 
and so remained undetected. This was veri-
fied when Mu2-mCherry fluorescence traces 
were classified according to whether they 
occurred at spots or plaques: the average 
fluorescence traces in each case showed a 
discrete dip after scission, presumably as 
the clathrin bud separated from the host 
structure and was uncoated (Figure 2D). </p>

<p>Lifetimes analysis of spot-like CCS 
hosting β2AR(+) scission events </p>

<p>We next focused on a more detailed analy-
sis of spot-like CCS lifetimes, since the dy-
namics of these structures are most readily 
analyzed, and the lifetime of spot-like 
coated pits was used previously as a read-
out of clathrin-coated pit maturation (Ehrlich 
et al., 2004; Puthenveedu and von Zastrow, 
2006; Loerke et al., 2009; Henry et al., 2012). 
To determine the maturation time of pro-
ductive clathrin-coated buds, we tracked 
Mu2-mCherry labeled CCSs and mapped 
them to bona fide scission events (Merrifield 
et al., 2005). As shown previously for TfR in 
fibroblasts (Merrifield et al., 2005; Taylor 
et al., 2011, 2012), spot-like CCSs most 
commonly hosted only one scission event 
but could potentially host multiple scission 
events (Figure 3, A and B). Strikingly, many 
scission events coincided with partial dim-
ming but not complete disappearance of 
the host CCS, and repeated trains of partial 
dimming resulted in characteristic sawtooth-
type profiles of Mu2-mCherry fluorescence 
(Figure 3A, right pair of traces). As described 
previously for NIH fibroblasts (Merrifield 
et al., 2005; Taylor et al., 2011), "nontermi-
nal" events, for which the host CCS did not 
completely disappear after scission, com-
prised a significant proportion of the total 
number of scission events (∼50%). By defini-
tion, terminal events coincided with the final 
disappearance of the host spot-like CCS 
(Figure 3A). 
Clearly, the overall lifetime of a spot-like 
CCS is not an entirely accurate readout for 
the time course of clathrin-coated bud mat-
uration. To estimate the time taken to form 
a productive clathrin bud, we measured the 
time between the first appearance (i.e., nu-
cleation) of spot-like CCSs and their corre-
lated first detected β2AR(+) scission event 
(Figure 3C). The median time was ∼119.6s, 
which is ∼53% longer than clathrin bud 
maturation in cells expressing only TfR-phl </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Discrete, quantized scission events internalized β2AR at clathrin spots and 
plaques. (A) An example HEK293 cell expressing the CCS marker Mu2-mCherry (magenta) and 
phl-β2AR (green) before (top) and after (bottom) challenge with isoproterenol. In this 
particular cell, CCSs appeared as discrete punctae and larger rosette-like plaques. (Bi) After 
challenge with isoproterenol, phl-β2AR was concentrated at both types of CCS, and discrete 
scission events were detected at either type of structure. (Bii) A map of detected scission 
events (red crosses) overlaid on an inverted image of Mu2-mCherry (black). Scission events 
were detected at both punctate CCSs and larger clathrin plaques. (C) Density scatterplot of 
Mu2-mCherry object area (ordinate) vs. newly scissioned phl-β2AR object area (abscissa). The 
fluorescence objects marking scission events are always spots but may colocalize to punctate 
or plaque-like CCSs. (D) Aligned and average fluorescence traces for Mu2-mCherry 
fluorescence at terminal punctate (black circles), nonterminal punctate (red circles), or 
plaque-like CCSs (open circles). All types of CCS show a drop in fluorescence after scission 
corresponding to CCV uncoating but differ in the persistence of fluorescence signal after 
scission. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: Lifetimes analysis of clathrin spots. (A) Example fluorescence traces for Mu2-mCherry (magenta) and 
phl-β2AR (green) for CCSs that hosted one, two, and seven scission events, respectively (arrows). (B) Histogram of the 
number of scission events detected per punctate CCS. A significant proportion (∼20%) of punctate CCSs hosted more 
than one scission event. (C) Histogram of the time between CCS nucleation and the first detected scission event for 
β2AR (median lifetime, 119.6 s). (D) The time between CCS nucleation and the first, second, or third detected scission 
event for TfR(+) scission events (black circles), β2AR(+) scission events (open circles), or MOR (gray circles) revealed that 
CCSs matured more slowly when loaded with β2AR or MOR. (E) Lifetimes histograms of punctate CCSs in cells 
expressing β2AR before challenge (Ei), during challenge (Eii), and after washout (Eiii) of isoproterenol. Eiii insert shows 
increase in median lifetime of CCS lifetime on isoproteronol challenge for four cells. </p>

<p>Volume 25 October 1, 2014 </p>

<p>Dual single-scission event analysis | 3075 </p>

<p>so a slightly more acidic wash of pH ∼5.0 was used to quench both 
red and green fluorescence. In an example HEK293 cell bathed in 
buffer at pH 7.4, TfR-phl was concentrated at CCSs and otherwise 
distributed evenly (Figure 4Ai, green). By contrast, mApp-β2AR fluo-
rescence was uniform, with no concentration at CCSs (Figure 4Ai, 
magenta). Images were acquired over a period of 400 s in conjunc-
tion with alternating pH to detect single TfR-phl(+) scission events 
as described. Before the addition of isoproterenol, no mApp-β2AR 
signal was detected at TfR-phl(+) scission events (Figure 4Bi). At t = 
402 s, isoproterenol was introduced into the rhythmically alternating 
perfusion streams to trigger mApp-β2AR endocytosis (Supplemen-
tal Figure S1 and Materials and Methods). After a further ∼60 s, 
mApp-β2AR coclustered with TfR-phl at CCS, and in an example 
TfR-phl(+) scission event, a robust step increase in mApp-β2AR fluo-
rescence was detected (Figure 4Bii). This could occur only if TfR-phl 
and mApp-β2AR pinched off in the same clathrin-coated vesicle. 
To visualize the flux of β2AR through the constitutive clathrin-
mediated endocytic pathway, we represented the fluorescence of 
bona fide TfR-phl(+) scission events as a density plot with "local 
time" (relative to the scission event) on the horizontal axis and 
"global time" (i.e., experimental time) descending on the vertical 
axis (Figure 4Ci) and plotted the average fluorescence of TfR-phl 
and mApp-β2AR before, during, and after isoproterenol challenge 
(Figure 4Cii). There was no detectable mApp-β2AR fluorescence at 
TfR (+) scission events before addition of isoproterenol, followed 
swiftly by a pulse of mApp-β2AR fluorescence, indicating cointernal-
ization of β2AR with TfR into clathrin-coated vesicles (Figure 4, Ci 
and Cii). The fluorescence of TfR(+) scission events-which corre-
sponds to the amount of receptor internalized by individual events-
remained relatively constant for the duration of the experiment, with 
a moderate increase after addition of isoproterenol (Figure 4Cii, 
green traces). The average fluorescence of mApp-β2AR internalized 
per scission event rapidly decayed during exposure to isoproterenol 
as mApp-β2AR was depleted from the plasma membrane (Figure 4, 
Ci and Cii). 
We established, in agreement with published results (Puthen-
veedu and von Zastrow, 2006), that an influx of β2AR into the clathrin-
mediated endocytic machinery extended the lifetime of spot-like 
CCS. However, did this correspond to a general slowing of the con-
stitutive endocytic rate? To answer this question, we measured the 
incidence rate of TfR-phl(+) scission events before, during, and after 
challenge with isoproterenol (Figure 5). In an example cluster of 
three cells, TfR-phl fluorescence at pH 7.4 showed a moderate de-
crease through the experiment, which was most likely due to bleach-
ing (Figure 5, A and B). By contrast, mApp-β2AR fluorescence at pH 
7.4 dramatically decreased with first-order kinetics upon isoprotere-
nol addition, followed by a recovery upon washout as the mApp-
β2AR was internalized and subsequently recycled (Puthenveedu 
and von Zastrow, 2006; Figure 5, A and C). For each cell, we defined 
a polygon of constant area that was contained within the footprint 
of the cell before, during, and after isoproterenol addition and mea-
sured the number of TfR-phl(+) scission events that occurred within 
the polygon over time. On addition of isoproterenol, there was a 
very modest, although insignificant, increase in the incidence rate of 
TfR-phl scission events (Figure 5D). We therefore conclude that li-
gand-triggered endocytosis of β2AR does not significantly change 
the overall incidence rate of constitutive endocytic scission events. 
To conclude, mApp-β2AR internalization was detected in at least 
some vesicles that constitutively internalized TfR-phl, and isoprot-
erenol-triggered mApp-β2AR endocytosis slows CCS maturation. 
We then sought to determine the degree of cointernalization of TfR 
and β2AR. </p>

<p>(t = 77 s; Figure 3D) but similar to the coated bud maturation time 
estimated for fibroblasts under similar conditions (Taylor et al., 
2011). Similar to earlier data from fibroblasts, the time between CCS 
nucleation and the nth detected scission event for TfR or β2AR was 
roughly linear (Figure 3D). To determine whether an alternative 
GPCR, MOR, had a similar effect on bud maturation time, we re-
peated the experiment and analysis using phl-MOR and Mu2-
mCherry. The MOR agonist [d-Ala </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, NMe-Phl </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>, Gly-ol </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>]-enkephalin 
(DAMGO) was used to trigger MOR endocytosis as described previ-
ously (Soohoo and Puthenveedu, 2013). The median time from CCS 
nucleation to the first detected MOR(+) scission event was ∼150 s, 
which is approximately twice as long as the clathrin bud maturation 
time in cells expressing only TfR-phl. 
In previous studies it was shown that the lifetime of punctate 
CCSs increased upon stimulation of β2AR internalization via a mech-
anism involving the actin cytoskeleton (Puthenveedu and von 
Zastrow, 2006) and receptor ubiquitination (Henry et al., 2012). An 
analysis of overall (unclassified) spot-like CCS lifetimes revealed a 
similar, although moderate, increase in median spot-like CCS life-
time upon isoproterenol challenge and ligand-triggered β2AR en-
docytosis (Figure 3E). By inspection, the increase in median lifetime 
corresponded to a moderate decrease in the frequency of short-
lived CCSs and consequent right shift of the lifetime distribution 
(compare Figure 3, Ei and Eii). 
To conclude, productive CCSs in HEK293 cells, competent for 
β2AR internalization, comprise a markedly heterogeneous set of 
punctate structures and patches with a wide range of lifetimes. The 
great majority of productive punctate CCSs host only one scission 
event, but both punctate CCSs and larger patches may host multi-
ple trains of scission events. Overall the simplest definition of a po-
tentially productive CCS is any CCS that colocalizes with phl-β2AR 
after isoproterenol challenge in which the phl-β2AR is accessible to 
externally imposed acidification. Finally, the maturation time of pro-
ductive spot-like CCSs was significantly increased by ligand-trig-
gered β2AR or MOR internalization. </p>

<p>The acute effects of ligand-triggered endocytosis on 
constitutive endocytosis </p>

<p>The dynamic relationship between constitutive clathrin-mediated 
endocytosis and ligand-triggered clathrin-mediated endocytosis re-
mains only poorly characterized. It has been suggested that ∼25% 
of CCSs preferentially internalize β2AR or TfR and ∼50% internalize 
both β2AR and TfR (Cao et al., 1998; but see von Zastrow and Ko-
bilka, 1992) and that a specialized subset of CCSs internalize β2AR 
(Puthenveedu and von Zastrow, 2006). It has also been suggested 
that CCSs may specialize to internalize other, different types of GP-
CRs (Mundell et al., 2006). In addition, although it is clear that β2AR 
clustering prolongs the lifetimes of the host coated pits (Puthenv-
eedu and von Zastrow, 2006), it is not clear whether ligand-triggered 
β2AR internalization acutely affects the rate of internalization of a 
constitutively endocytosed receptor such as TfR. Therefore experi-
ments were designed to explore the dynamic relationship between 
constitutive endocytosis of TfR and the ligand-triggered endocyto-
sis of β2AR and to establish what proportion of TfR(+) scission events 
were also β2AR(+). 
First, the moderately pH-sensitive red fluorescent protein mAp-
ple was inserted into the extracellular domain of β2AR to make 
mApp-β2AR, which, in turn, allowed simultaneous imaging of TfR-
phl (to detect single constitutive endocytic events) and mApp-β2AR 
(to detect ligand-triggered β2AR internalization) using the pulsed 
pH assay. The pK a of mApple (pK a 6.5; Shaner et al., 2008) is lower 
than that of sePhl (pK a 7.1; Sankaranarayanan and Ryan, 2000), and </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>Is there any evidence for coated-pit 
specialization? </p>

<p>In earlier work, it was shown, using immuno-
fluorescence, that three populations of CCS 
exist at the plasma membrane of HEK293 
cells after stimulation of β2AR internalization 
by isoproterenol (Cao et al., 1998). Approxi-
mately ∼25% of CCSs contained β2AR 
alone, ∼50% contained both β2AR and TfR, 
and ∼25% contained only TfR (Cao et al., 
1998). Here we revisited this measurement 
and determined the degree of coincidence 
of mApp-β2AR with TfR-phl in newly scis-
sioned endocytic vesicles. To do this, we 
measured mApp-β2AR signal at TfR-phl(+) 
scission events before, during, and after iso-
proterenol challenge, using a quantification 
algorithm developed to detect very weak 
fluorescence changes at fluorescent puncta 
(see Materials and Methods). 
We used two different approaches to es-
timate the proportion of TfR-phl(+)/mApp-
β2AR(+) scission events. In the first method, 
the fluorescence of mApple-β2AR was mea-
sured at TfR-phl(+) scission events in resting 
cells and the fluorescence distribution used 
to define an upper 95% confidence limit on 
basal red fluorescence above which events 
were scored as mApp-β2AR(+) after isoprot-
erenol challenge. For the example cell in 
Figure 4, 85% of TfR-phl(+) vesicles were 
also scored as mApp-β2AR(+) after isoprot-
erenol challenge (see Supplemental Figure 
S2 for details of quantification). To verify this 
analysis, we manually scored TfR-phl(+) scis-
sion events for β2AR fluorescence over a 
window from 60 s after isoproterenol addi-
tion to the end of isoproterenol stimulation 
200 s later. This analysis revealed that 89% 
of TfR(+) scission events were also β2AR(+) 
as judged by eye (n = 234 events, N = 3 
cells). 
These analysis depended on using the 
robust TfR-phl scission signal as a reference 
signal to measure constitutive scission 
events, and so it could not detect potential 
mApp-β2AR(+)/TfR-phl(-) scission events. 
These could correspond to scission of vesi-
cles from "specialized" CCSs that internal-
ized β2AR but excluded TfR. Moreover, 
using TfR-phl(+) scission events as a refer-
ence most likely underestimated the pro-
portion of TfR-phl(+)/mApp-β2AR(+) scis-
sion events, as the red mApple scission 
signal was dimmer than the green phl sig-
nal and prone to contamination by internal-
ized (but incompletely quenched) mApple-
β2AR fluorescence. The automated scission 
detection algorithm was adapted to detect 
the very faint candidate mApp-β2AR scis-
sion events (see Materials and Methods). 
Briefly, spot fluorescence was measured </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: mApple-β2AR clusters and internalizes with TfR-phl. (A) Example HEK293 cell 
expressing TfR-phl (green, left) and mApp-β2AR (magenta, right) at pH 7.4, 50 s before 
isoproterenol addition (top) and 550 s after isoproterenol challenge (bottom). After 
isoproterenol challenge, mApp-β2AR clustered with TfR-phl at CCSs. Images are averages of 
50 frames, acquired at 0.5 Hz, centered on the relative time point. (B) Example TfR-phl scission 
events before (Bi) and after (Bii) isoproterenol addition. After isoproterenol addition, mApp-
β2AR signal coincided with TfR-phl(+) scission events, indicating that the two receptors 
cointernalized in the same vesicles. (Ci) Density plot of aligned fluorescence changes (horizontal 
axis) associated with bona fide TfR-phl(+) scission events plotted against global time (vertical 
axis). The flux of mApp-β2AR receptor through the constitutive CME pathway appeared as a 
transient pulse of fluorescence signal (right). (Cii) Quantified average fluorescence traces of 
TfR-phl and mApp-β2AR over the time windows indicated in Ci. </p>

<p>Volume 25 October 1, 2014 </p>

<p>Dual single-scission event analysis | 3077 </p>

<p>a stepwise fluorescence increase with S/N ≥ 10 (see Materials and 
Methods). This eliminated false-positive events, which most likely 
represent endocytic vesicles briefly visiting the plasma membrane. 
The mApp-β2AR(+) scission events identified were classified as 
TfR-phl(+) if there was a correlated stepwise increase in TfR-phl </p>

<p>using a circle-minus-annulus measurement as before, but seg-
mented spots were excluded from the annulus measurement, giv-
ing a less noisy estimate of local background fluorescence. Candi-
date mApp-β2AR(+) scission events were classified as bona fide if 
they coincided with a cluster of mApp-β2AR at pH 7.4 and showed </p>

<p>FIGURE 5: The flux of TfR-phl(+) scission events through the constitutive endocytic pathway is only mildly affected by 
ligand-triggered β2AR internalization. (A) A group of 3 HEK293 cells before, during, and after challenge with 
isoproterenol, showing surface TfR-phl fluorescence (left) and mApple-β2AR fluorescence (right) at pH 7.4. 
(B) Quantification of fluorescence changes in cell indicated in A by asterisk. TfR-phl fluorescence (green) showed a 
moderate decrease during the course of the experiment. (C) By contrast, mApple-β2AR (magenta) showed a robust 
decrease in fluorescence, followed by a moderate increase upon isoproterenol washout (indicated by arrow). (D) The 
incidence rate of TfR-phl(+) scission events, expressed as events μm 
−2 s </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>, before, during, and after isoproterenol 
challenge. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>imaging data were generally less satisfactory. However, on chal-
lenge with DAMGO, mApp-MOR(+) scission events were readily 
detected, and the proportion of mApp-MOR(+)/TfR-phl(-) scission 
events was estimated as for β2AR. Of the events detected (132 
events, three cells), 81% were mApp-MOR(+)/TfR-phl(+), as op-
posed to the expected proportion of ∼50% (Figure 6, D-F). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This is, to our knowledge, the first time that ligand-triggered endo-
cytosis has been imaged at the level of single-scission events. The 
parallels with a similar analysis of constitutive TfR(+) scission events 
in NIH3T3 fibroblasts are striking (Merrifield et al., 2005; Taylor et al., 
2011, 2012). As for constitutive TfR endocytosis, the ligand-trig-
gered endocytosis of β2AR proceeds via quantized scission events 
hosted by an apparently diverse array of clathrin spots and plaques. 
A simple model to explain the observed diversity of CCS dynamics 
is that CCSs may occur as discrete clathrin-coated buds at the </p>

<p>fluorescence with S/N ≥ 5. Of the mApp-β2AR scission events 
identified, 95% coincided with a correlated TfR-phl(+) scission 
event (Figure 6, A-C). From this we conclude that, upon isoprot-
erenol challenge, there is only one population of constitutive en-
docytic vesicles in HEK293 cells that internalize both mApp-β2AR 
and TfR-phl. 
The MOR is an alternative GPCR that is believed to internalize, at 
least in part, from specialized CCPs, and it has been suggested that 
∼50% of CCPs can specialize to internalize MOR in HEK293 cells 
(Soohoo and Puthenveedu, 2013). To better estimate the propor-
tion of (putative) specialized MOR(+) scission events, we made a 
mApp-MOR construct, coexpressed it with TfR-phl in HEK-293 cells, 
and performed a pulsed pH assay as for β2AR. The MOR agonist 
DAMGO was used to trigger MOR endocytosis as described previ-
ously (Soohoo and Puthenveedu, 2013). In general, the response of 
mApp-MOR to DAMGO challenge was less robust, rapid, and re-
producible than the response mApp-β2AR to isoproterenol, and the </p>

<p>FIGURE 6: Estimating the proportion of GPCR(+)/TfR(-) scission events using either mApp-β2AR or mApp-MOR 
scission events as a reference. (Ai, Aii) Average time-resolved montage of mApp-β2AR(+)/TfR-phl(+) scission events. 
(Bi, Bii) Quantification of fluorescence at pH 5 or 7 for (Bi) mApp-BAR or (Bii) TfR-phl. (C) Ninety-five percent of 
mApp-β2AR(+) scission events were also TfR-phl(+). (Di, Dii) Average time-resolved montage of mAppMOR(+)/ 
TfR-phl(+) scission events. (Ei, Eii) Quantification of fluorescence at pH 5 or 7 for (Ei) mApp-MOR or (Eii) TfR-phl. 
(F) Eighty-one percent of mApp-MOR(+) scission events were also TfR-phl(+). </p>

<p>Volume 25 October 1, 2014 </p>

<p>Dual single-scission event analysis | 3079 </p>

<p>scission events changed little-and if any-
thing slightly increased-when mApp-β2AR 
was driven through the clathrin-mediated 
endocytic pathway, suggesting that al-
though the two receptors internalized in the 
same vesicles, they did not compete with 
one another. 
When the coincidence of Tfr-phl and 
mApp-MOR at endocytic events was ana-
lyzed, it was found that ∼19% of scission 
events were mApp-MOR(+)/TfR-phl(-), 
which was a substantially lower proportion 
than the expected ∼50% (Soohoo and 
Puthenveedu, 2013). These results therefore 
favor a model in which activated β2-AR and 
MOR hitchhike into the cell via constitutively 
internalizing clathrin-coated pits but can 
nonetheless modify the maturation times of 
the host CCSs (Figure 7). It remains possible that the ∼19% of scis-
sion events that apparently internalized MOR but not TfR represent 
specialized CCSs. However, as noted, detection limits and the pos-
sibility of false-positive TfR-phl(-)/mApp-MOR(+) must be kept in 
mind when considering this possibility. In the future, a similar experi-
mental strategy may be used to determine whether other types of 
receptor enter the cell via the same or specialized CCSs. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METhODS 
TIRFM and perfusion system </p>

<p>The dual-color TIRFM microscope has been described previously 
(Taylor et al., 2011). The four-channel perfusion system was based 
on a previously published design (Taylor et al., 2011) with the addi-
tion of three-way miniature valves to control addition/washout of 
drugs (part LFRX0500050B; Lee Company, Westbrook, CT). All con-
trol and switching electronics were designed and built in-house. </p>

<p>Pulsed pH assay </p>

<p>The pulsed pH assay was described previously (Merrifield et al., 
2005) and in more detail here in Supplemental Figure S1. Briefly, the 
perfused buffer was switched between pH 7.4 (HBS: 135 mM NaCl, 
5 mM KCl, 1.8 mM CaCl 2 , 0.4 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM d(+)-glucose, 
25 mM 4-(2-hydroxyethyl)-1-piperazineethanesulfonic acid, 2% fetal 
calf serum [FCS]) and pH 5.0 (MBS: 135 mM NaCl, 5 mM KCl, 
1.8 mM CaCl 2 , 0.4 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM d(+)-glucose, 25 mM 2-(N-
morpholino)ethanesulfonic acid, 2% FCS). To trigger β2AR internal-
ization, 20 mM isoproterenol was added to both HBS and 
MBS streams. All chemicals were bought from Sigma-Aldrich 
(St. Louis, MO). </p>

<p>Cell culture and transfection </p>

<p>HEK293 cells were grown DMEM (Life Technologies SAS, St. Aubin, 
France) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum in 10% CO 2 and 
at 37°C. Adherent HEK293 cells, growing in six-well plates, were 
transfected with the relevant plasmid(s) using Lipofectamine 2000 at 
24-48 h before imaging experiments and as per manufacturer's in-
struction (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). Cells were replated onto clean 
coverslips ∼4 h after transfection and allowed to adhere overnight 
ready for imaging the following morning. </p>

<p>Glass cleaning </p>

<p>Coverslips were cleaned as described previously (Merrifield et al., 
2005; Taylor et al., 2011). Briefly, coverslips were washed thrice in 
wash solution (0.01% DECON 90 [Decon Laboratories, Hove, United </p>

<p>plasma membrane (spot-like CCSs) or in association with a large, flat 
or gently curved patch of clathrin at the plasma membrane (plaque-
like CCSs; Figure 7). As noted previously, the latter types of structure 
have been observed by electron microscopy (Heuser, 1980; Maupin 
and Pollard, 1983). To fully understand the CCS dynamics observed 
by microscopy, the dynamics of both the bud and, if present, the 
associated clathrin patch must be considered. If the patch of clathrin 
at the membrane is absent, the coated bud will disappear once scis-
sion occurs in a terminal event (Figure 7). If a small patch of clathrin 
is left after scission, a nonterminal event will occur if a fresh bud re-
grows at the same site (Figure 7). If the associated patch is suffi-
ciently large and perhaps stabilized by adhesion (Batchelder and 
Yarar, 2010), it might sufficiently bright to obscure the loss of clathrin 
coat during budding events at or close to its edges, which would 
thus evade detection by conventional fluorescence microscopy, and 
it would appear as a plaque (Figure 7). Therefore CCSs are superfi-
cially heterogeneous even though they represent a common path-
way of receptor internalization. 
Similar to an earlier study (Puthenveedu and von Zastrow, 2006), 
it was found that ligand-triggered β2AR internalization moderately 
extends the lifetime of spot-like CCS by ∼53%. Here a prolongation 
of spot-like CCS lifetime was found using two different analyses: 
first, by tracking all spot-like CCSs before, during, and after ligand-
triggered β2AR endocytosis in the same set of cells, and second, by 
comparing the time between spot-like CCS nucleation and the first 
detected scission event for β2AR(+), MOR(+), or TfR(+) scission 
events in different sets of cells. It has been proposed that the pro-
longation of spot-like CCS lifetime by β2AR loading may be of func-
tional significance, perhaps reflecting the dynamics of a specialized 
subset of CCSs (Puthenveedu and von Zastrow, 2006; Henry et al., 
2012). Here, by simultaneously detecting the presence of TfR and 
β2AR in newly scissioned vesicles, it was shown that β2AR does in-
crease the lifetime of CCSs but that TfR and β2AR internalize in the 
same vesicles budding from CCSs. Moreover, despite the change in 
bud maturation time, the incidence rate of scission events remained 
remarkably constant before, during, and after ligand-triggered β2AR 
endocytosis. One possible explanation for the steady flux is that the 
number of CCSs increases in response to ligand-triggered endocy-
tosis and so compensates for increased bud maturation time. In-
deed, in an example cell expressing Mu2-mCherry and phl-MOR, 
the number of detected CCSs significantly increased after DAMGO 
stimulation (Supplemental Figure S3). Therefore the increase in 
CCS maturation time may be offset by simply nucleating more 
CCSs. It was also found that the amount of TfR-phl internalized by </p>

<p>FIGURE 7: A common pathway for constitutive TfR endocytosis and ligand-triggered GPCR 
endocytosis. Clathrin-coated pits can internalize both TfR (green lollipops) and GPCR (β2AR or 
MOR; red lollipops). </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>



<p>Plasmid design and construction </p>

<p>The design of TfR-phl has been described previously (Merrifield et al., 
2005). The yellow fluorescent protein (YFP) of YFP-β2AR (Dorsch 
et al., 2009) was replaced with super-ecliptic pHluorin using the 
BamHI and XbaI restriction sites (super-ecliptic pHluorin was ampli-
fied with the primers AAAAAGGATCCATGAAGACGATCATCGC-
CCTGAGCTACATCTTCTGCCTGGTATTCGCCAGTAAAGGAGAA-
GAACTTTTCACTGGAGTTGTCCC [also encoding a hemagglutinin 
signal sequence; Guan et al., 1992] and AAAAATCTAGATTTG-
TATAGTTCATCCATGCC). Phluorin was replaced with mApple to 
make mApple-β2AR using two sequential PCR reactions to reengi-
neer the human growth hormone signal sequence into the N-termi-
nus of mApple. To generate mApple-MOR, the entire open reading 
frame (ORF) of human MOR was synthesized (Eurofins MWG, Ebers-
berg, Germany) with appropriate 5′ and 3′ restriction sites and used 
to replace the β2AR ORF in phl-β2AR and mApp-β2AR. The Mu2 
construct was described previously (Taylor et al., 2011). Briefly, 
mCherry was inserted within the rat Mu2 ORF at residue 236 using 
the BglII and NdeI sites (plasmid 27672; Addgene, Cambridge, MA). </p>

<p>Image analysis </p>

<p>All image analysis was performed in <rs id="software-1" type="software">Matlab</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">MathWorks</rs>, Cambridge, 
United Kingdom) using custom-written software as described previ-
ously (Taylor et al., 2011), with the following modifications. Scripts 
were written in <rs type="software">Matlab</rs> to segment spots using the wavelet-based 
multiscale products as described previously (Olivo-Marin, 2002). 
The coordinates of spots were extracted in <rs type="software">Matlab</rs> and track histo-
ries generated using a <rs type="software">Matlab</rs> version of the IDL nearest-neighbor 
algorithm (www.physics.emory.edu/∼weeks/idl/). To detect the very 
faint mApp-β2AR (+) scission events, the fluorescence of candidate 
spots was quantified using a circle-minus-annulus measurement in 
which segmented spots were excluded from the annulus. This elimi-
nated a major source of noise in the fluorescence measurement and 
allowed a more accurate estimate of fluorescence. </p>



<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We acknowledge funding from Medical Research Council (MRC, 
London, UK) grant MC_U105178789 and Fondation pour la 
Re cherche Medicale (FRM, Paris, France) grant AJE201108. </p>

</text></tei>