<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4921791" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T03:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Objective: A branched-chain amino acid (BCAA)-related metabolic signature is strongly associated with insulin resistance and predictive of 
incident diabetes and intervention outcomes. To better understand the role that this metabolite cluster plays in obesity-related metabolic 
dysfunction, we studied the impact of BCAA restriction in a rodent model of obesity in which BCAA metabolism is perturbed in ways that mirror the 
human condition. 
Methods: Zucker-lean rats (ZLR) and Zucker-fatty rats (ZFR) were fed either a custom control, low fat (LF) diet, or an isonitrogenous, isocaloric 
LF diet in which all three BCAA (Leu, Ile, Val) were reduced by 45% (LF-RES). We performed comprehensive metabolic and physiologic profiling to 
characterize the effects of BCAA restriction on energy balance, insulin sensitivity, and glucose, lipid and amino acid metabolism. 
Results: LF-fed ZFR had higher levels of circulating BCAA and lower levels of glycine compared to LF-fed ZLR. Feeding ZFR with the LF-RES diet 
lowered circulating BCAA to levels found in LF-fed ZLR. Activity of the rate limiting enzyme in the BCAA catabolic pathway, branched chain keto 
acid dehydrogenase (BCKDH), was lower in liver but higher in skeletal muscle of ZFR compared to ZLR and was not responsive to diet in either 
tissue. BCAA restriction had very little impact on metabolites studied in liver of ZFR where BCAA content was low, and BCKDH activity was 
suppressed. However, in skeletal muscle of LF-fed ZFR compared to LF-fed ZLR, where BCAA content and BCKDH activity were increased, 
accumulation of fatty acyl CoAs was completely normalized by dietary BCAA restriction. BCAA restriction also normalized skeletal muscle glycine 
content and increased urinary acetyl glycine excretion in ZFR. These effects were accompanied by lower RER and improved skeletal muscle 
insulin sensitivity in LF-RES fed ZFR as measured by hyperinsulinemic-isoglycemic clamp. 
Conclusions: Our data are consistent with a model wherein elevated circulating BCAA contribute to development of obesity-related insulin 
resistance by interfering with lipid oxidation in skeletal muscle. BCAA-dependent lowering of the skeletal muscle glycine pool appears to 
contribute to this effect by slowing acyl-glycine export to the urine. </p>

<p>Aberrant amino acid metabolism has long been recognized as a feature 
of obesity and accompanying metabolic disease. In 1969 Felig, Mar-
liss, and Cahill [1] made the seminal observation that obese persons 
have higher levels of the branched chain (BCAA; Leucine, isoleucine 
and valine) and aromatic (phenylalanine and tyrosine) amino acids and 
lower levels of glycine in blood compared to lean individuals. More 
recently, unbiased metabolic profiling studies performed by our group </p>

<p>[2e4] and others [5] have revived interest in perturbed amino acid 
metabolism as a potential contributor to development of metabolic 
diseases by revealing that a cluster of circulating metabolites 
comprising these same branched-chain and aromatic amino acids, as 
well as glutamate/glutamine, methionine, alanine, and the C3 and C5 
acylcarnitines is strongly associated with insulin sensitivity [2], car-
diometabolic health [6], future diabetes risk [5], and metabolic out-
comes of weight loss interventions [7,8]. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Sarah W. Stedman Nutrition and Metabolism Center, Duke Molecular Physiology Institute, Departments of Pharmacology &amp; Cancer Biology and Medicine, Duke University 
Medical Center, Durham, NC, 27701, USA </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CV and Metabolic Diseases Research Unit, Pfizer, Cambridge, MA, USA </p>

<p>3 Phillip J. White and Amanda L. Lapworth contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>*Corresponding author. Duke Molecular Physiology Institute, 300 North Duke Street, Durham, NC, 27701, USA. Tel.: þ1 919 668 6059. E-mail: Chris.Newgard@duke.edu 
(C.B. Newgard). </p>

<p>Received April 6, 2016 Revision received April 15, 2016 Accepted April 19, 2016 Available online 22 April 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molmet.2016.04.006 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>538 MOLECULAR METABOLISM 5 (2016) 538e551 Ó 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>

<p>Current evidence suggests that the obesity-related rise in circulating 
BCAA is the product of multiple metabolic perturbations related to their 
synthesis and catabolism, rather than being driven by increased intake 
of these essential amino acids [4,9]. One potential contributing factor 
has emerged from studies of the microbiota from monozygotic twins 
discordant for obesity, which revealed that obesity-driven shifts in 
microbial communities results in higher production and lower catab-
olism of BCAA by the intestinal flora [10]. Indeed, transfer of gut 
microbiota from obese or lean twins to gnotobiotic mice is sufficient to 
raise circulating BCAA in animals that received the microbiota of the 
obese twin by a magnitude similar to that reported for obese versus 
lean humans. 
In addition, hepatic activity of the branched chain keto acid dehydro-
genase (BCKDH) complex, which is responsible for the first irreversible 
and rate limiting step in BCAA metabolism, is low in obese and insulin 
resistant animals [11,12]. This is due to increased expression of the 
BCKDH kinase, BDK, and decreased expression of the BCKDH phos-
phatase, PPM1K, causing BCKDH to be in a hyperphosphorylated and 
inhibited state. Since liver is considered the primary site for catabolism 
of branched chain keto acids (BCKA) this represents a considerable 
systemic impairment. Demonstrating the control strength of this re-
action, hypothalamic insulin and leptin lower circulating BCAA by up to 
50% by reducing the phosphorylation state of hepatic BCKDH [13]. 
Furthermore, expression of BDK and PPM1K is regulated by adipo-
nectin through an AMPK-dependent signal, and adiponectin knockout 
mice have lower PPM1K expression in liver accompanied by higher 
circulating BCAA [12]. Together, these data suggest that obesity-
related changes in the hormonal milieu likely drive the inactivation of 
hepatic BCKDH by influencing the balance of the BDK/PPM1K regu-
latory node. 
In adipose tissue, decreased BCAA metabolism in response to obesity 
appears to occur via global regulation of multiple enzymes in the 
catabolic pathway at a transcriptional level, rather than by post-
translational modification as in liver [14,15]. Interestingly, in-
terventions that reverse obesity-associated metabolic dysregulation, 
including bariatric surgery or treatment with thiazolidinedione drugs, 
restore expression of the BCAA catabolic enzymes in adipose tissue in 
concert with improved glucose homeostasis [11,15]. Remarkably, 
obesity-regulated post-translational or transcriptional regulation of the 
BCAA catabolic pathway has not been reported in skeletal muscle. 
Taken together, these findings highlight tissue-specific differences in 
BCAA catabolism in response to obesity. 
Although our understanding of factors regulating the levels of circu-
lating BCAA in obesity has evolved as described, the role of these 
metabolites in obesity-associated metabolic disorders remains to be 
defined [16]. In healthy humans, acute infusion of a complete amino 
acid mixture results in skeletal muscle and hepatic insulin resistance 
accompanied by activation of the mammalian target of rapamycin/S6 
kinase 1 pathway [17e19]. However, various rodent studies involving 
specific supplementation of BCAA have yielded diverse findings, 
probably due in part to differences in study design. These have ranged 
from supplementation of all three BCAA in HF diets, resulting in 
exacerbation of insulin resistance [2], to addition of leucine alone in the 
drinking water, which is reported to have either no effect [20] or a 
beneficial effect on glucose homeostasis [21,22]. Less studied is the 
impact of BCAA restriction on metabolic control in models in which 
endogenous BCAA metabolism is perturbed in ways that mirror the 
human condition. 
Herein we describe the results of a nutritional intervention study in 
which we restricted BCAA dietary supply by 45% in Zucker-lean 
(ZLR) and Zucker-fatty rats (ZFR), the latter being a model of </p>

<p>insulin resistance and impaired BCAA metabolism [23]. We per-
formed comprehensive metabolic and physiologic profiling to char-
acterize the role of BCAA restriction on energy balance, insulin 
sensitivity, and glucose, lipid, and amino acid metabolism. Our 
findings demonstrate a clear cause and effect relationship between 
BCAA supply and insulin sensitivity and highlight underlying 
biochemical mechanisms. </p>

<p>2. MATERIALS &amp; METHODS </p>

<p>2.1. Animals and diets 
Six week-old male Zucker-lean (ZLR) and Zucker-fatty rats (ZFR) from 
Charles River Laboratories were placed on either a custom control low 
fat (LF) diet (A11072001, Research Diets, New Brunswick, NJ) or a LF 
BCAA restricted diet (LF-RES; A11072002, Research Diets, New 
Brunswick, NJ) in which 45% of the BCAA component of the LF diet 
was removed and replaced by a small increment in all other amino 
acids (except phenylalanine and tyrosine) such that nitrogen content 
was equal in both diets (Table 1). Rats were individually housed in a 
12 h light:dark cycle with ad libitum access to water and food for up to 
15 weeks. Food intake and weight gain were monitored weekly. A non-
fasting blood sample was taken after 9 weeks on the diets at 9AM to 
determine the genotype and dietary effect on circulating amino acid 
concentrations. Plasma and tissue samples used for biochemical 
analysis were derived from rats that were euthanized in the fed state at 
week 15 by exsanguination following intraperitoneal administration of 
Nembutal (80 mg/kg). Tissues were rapidly excised, weighed, and 
freeze clamped in liquid nitrogen and then stored at À80 C until 
further analysis. All animal procedures were approved and carried out 
in accordance with the directions of the Duke University Institutional 
Animal Care and Use Committee. </p>

<p>Table 1 e Diet amino acid content. </p>

<p>% 
LF: Research 
Diets A11072001 </p>

<p>LF-RES: 
Research Diets A11072002 </p>

<p>grams 
kcal 
grams 
kcal </p>

<p>Macronutrients 
Protein 
33.6 
33 
33.6 
33 
Carbohydrate 
49.3 
49 
49.3 
49 
Fat 
8.0 
18 
8.0 
18 
Fiber 
4.0 
0 
4.0 
0 
Total 
90.9 
100 
90.9 
100 
kcal/gm 
4.03 
4.03 </p>

<p>Amino acids 
Isoleucine 
17.88 
72 
9.83 
39 
Leucine 
31.63 
127 
17.40 
70 
Valine 
23.38 
94 
12.86 
51 
Phenylalanine 
17.88 
72 
17.88 
72 
Tyrosine 
12.38 
50 
12.38 
50 
Cysteine 
5.50 
22 
6.29 
25 
Lysine 
24.75 
99 
28.28 
113 
Methionine 
6.88 
28 
7.86 
31 
Tryptophan 
5.50 
22 
5.50 
22 
Histidine 
8.25 
33 
9.43 
38 
Alanine 
12.38 
50 
14.15 
57 
Arginine 
27.50 
110 
31.43 
126 
Aspartic acid 
20.63 
83 
23.58 
94 
Glutamic acid 
37.13 
149 
42.43 
170 
Glycine 
38.50 
154 
44.00 
176 
Proline 
17.88 
72 
20.43 
82 
Serine 
15.13 
61 
17.29 
69 </p>

<p>MOLECULAR METABOLISM 5 (2016) 538e551 Ó 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>



<p>2.2. Glucose tolerance tests 
After 10 weeks on the respective diets, rats were fasted for 16 h with 
free access to water and a 1 g/kg intraperitoneal glucose tolerance test 
was performed. Blood samples were obtained from the tail vein before 
the glucose injection and at the indicated time points after the glucose 
load. Glucose levels were measured with a BD Logic glucose meter 
and insulin concentrations were determined in plasma samples using a 
Millipore EMD Rat insulin ELISA. </p>

<p>2.3. Indirect calorimetry 
Indirect calorimetry was performed in weeks 11 and 12 of feeding 
using an eight-chamber Oxymax system (Columbus Instruments; Co-
lumbus, OH). Rats were acclimatized to the system for 24 h prior to 
measurement. Recordings were made while food and water was freely 
accessible. Urine was also collected from the Oxymax chambers for 
analysis of urinary acetylglycine content. </p>

<p>2.4. Hyperinsulinemic isoglycemic clamps 
A cohort of ZFR was subjected to hyperinsulinemic-isoglycemic clamps 
after 14e15 weeks of LF or LF-RES diet feeding in order to assess 
insulin sensitivity. Seven days prior to clamp experiments, animals 
were anesthetized with 2% isoflurane (Butler Schein, Dublin OH), and 
polyethylene catheters were aseptically placed in the left carotid artery 
(advanced to the aortic arch) or the right jugular vein. Catheters were 
filled with 3% heparinized saline to maintain patency and exteriorized 
in the intrascapular region. Buprenorphine (0.03 mg/kg, s.c.) was 
postsurgically administered for pain control, and animals recovered to 
preoperative weight prior to experiments. Buprenorphine was given to 
all animals in the first 3 days following surgery, and then removed for 4 
days until clamps were carried out on day 7. 
Clamps were performed in conscious unrestrained animals using 
swivels and tethers (Instech) to allow uninterrupted movement of the 
animals without disruption of infusion lines. Hyperinsulinemia was 
achieved by a primed (3 min 60 mU/kg/min) continuous 10 mU/kg/min 
intravenous insulin infusion. Blood was sampled from arterial lines at 
5 min intervals and analyzed with a BD Logic glucose meter. Iso-
glycemia, defined as blood glucose within 10% of individual fasting 
glycemia, was restored and maintained by variable infusion of 30% 
dextrose. Steady state was achieved approximately 90 min after 
initiating hyperinsulinemia and maintained for at least 45 min. Once 
steady state had been maintained for 45 min, a [U-</p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C] glucose </p>

<p>(45 mCi/rat) and [ 
3 H]2-deoxyglucose (67.6 mCi/rat) bolus was admin-</p>

<p>istered to determine tissue glucose uptake and rates of glucose 
incorporation into glycogen. After tracer injection, blood was collected </p>

<p>at 2, 5, 10, 15, 20, 30 and 40 min and 50 mL plasma was transferred 
into tubes containing 1 mL of ZnSO 4 (2.75%w/v). 350 mL of saturated </p>

<p>BaOH was then added to the ZnSO 4 -plasma. Samples were centri-
fuged and total </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>H and </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C in the supernatant was counted in Uniscint 
BD Scintillation fluid in a Beckman Coulter LS6500 liquid scintillation 
counter to determine total tracer disappearance. Immediately following 
the clamp procedure, rats were euthanized with Euthasol, and 
gastrocnemius muscle and epididymal white adipose tissue (eWAT) 
were quickly harvested and freeze clamped. Samples were later pul-
verized under liquid nitrogen and stored at À80 C for further 
biochemical analysis. 
Tissue content of </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>H-2-deoxyglucose-6-phosphate was used to 
determine glucose uptake in gastrocnemius and epididymal adipose 
samples. Briefly, tissue samples were deproteinated, loaded onto 
columns packed with a 0.75 mL AG-1 resin bed (BioRad #140-1453), 
and washed with 4 mL of distilled water. The </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>H-2-DG-6-phosphate 
was then eluted off the column with 4 mL of 1 M ammonium </p>

<p>acetate (Sigma #431311). Specific activity of the eluate was deter-
mined by counting 
3 H in Uniscint BD Scintillation fluid in a Beckman 
Coulter LS6500 liquid scintillation counter. To evaluate 
14 C glucose 
incorporation into glycogen, we extracted glycogen by a modified 
version of the Pfluger method. Briefly, 200 mg of tissue was dissolved 
in 1.5 mL of a 30% KOH solution at 60 C for 1 h. Samples were </p>

<p>vortexed gently, and 250 mL of saturated Na 2 SO 4 and 2 mL of 100% </p>

<p>ethanol were added to each sample. After gentle vortexing, samples 
were incubated at 85 C until boiling point was reached and then 
immediately placed on ice to precipitate glycogen. Samples were 
centrifuged at 2500 RPM at 4 C, and the supernatant was removed. 
The pellet was washed three times by suspension in 2 mL of distilled 
water and precipitation in 100% ethanol. The washed pellet was then 
resuspended in 1 mL of distilled water, and </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C was counted in Uni-
scint BD Scintillation fluid in a Beckman Coulter LS6500 liquid scin-
tillation counter. Rates of glucose uptake and incorporation into 
glycogen were calculated as described [24]. </p>

<p>2.5. Metabolite profiling 
Amino acid profiles were derived from whole blood, liver, and 
gastrocnemius muscle. Organic acid, acylcarnitine and acyl CoA pro-
files were derived from liver and gastrocnemius muscle. Methods of 
sample handling and extraction have been described previously 
[25,26]. Amino acid, acylcarnitine, acyl CoA and acetylglycine profiling 
was performed by tandem mass spectrometry (MS/MS) [2,25e27]. 
Organic acids in liver and gastrocnemius muscle samples were 
analyzed by capillary gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GS-
MS) on a TRACE ISQ instrument (Thermo Electron Corporation) [2]. All 
MS analyses employed stable-isotope-dilution with internal standards 
from Isotec, Cambridge Isotopes Laboratories, and CDN Isotopes. A list 
of all internal standards used in these studies has been published 
previously [2,25]. 
Plasma concentrations of the alpha-keto acids of leucine (a-keto-
isocaproate, KIC), isoleucine (a-keto-b-methylvalerate, KMV) and 
valine (a-keto-isovalerate, KIV) were measured by LC-MS as previ-
ously described [28,29]. Other plasma analytes were measured on a 
Beckman DxC600 autoanalyzer, using reagents for lactate, total 
cholesterol, and triglycerides from Beckman, and non-esterified fatty 
acids (NEFA) and ketones (total and 3-hydroxybutyrate) from Wako 
(Richmond, VA). Glycerol was measured using reagents from TG-B by 
Roche Diagnostics (Indianapolis, IN). </p>

<p>2.6. BCKDH activity assay 
Tissue BCKDH activity was determined as previously described [13]. 
Briefly, frozen tissue samples were pulverized in liquid nitrogen, then 
homogenized using a QIAGEN TissueLyser II in 250 ul of ice cold buffer </p>

<p>I (30 mM KPi pH 7.5, 3 mM EDTA, 5 mM DTT, 1 mM a-ketoisovalerate, 
3% FBS, 5% Triton X-100, 1 mM Leupeptin). Samples were then 
centrifuged for 10 min at 10 000 Âg and 50 mL of supernatant was 
added to 300 mL of buffer II (50 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 30 mM KPi pH 7.5, </p>

<p>0.4 mM CoA, 3 mM NADþ, 5% FBS, 2 mM Thiamine Pyrophosphate, </p>

<p>2 mM MgCl 2 , 7.8 mM a-keto [1-</p>

<p>14 C] isovalerate) in a polystyrene test 
tube containing a raised 1 M NaOH CO 2 trap. Tubes were capped and 
placed in a shaking water bath at 37 C for 30 min. The reaction 
mixture was acidified by injection of 70% perchloric acid followed by 
shaking on an orbital shaker for 1 h. The </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>CO 2 contained in the trap 
was counted in a liquid scintillation counter. </p>

<p>2.7. Statistical analysis 
All data are reported as mean AE the standard error of the mean. 
Statistical outliers determined as 2.5 standard deviations outside of </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>540 MOLECULAR METABOLISM 5 (2016) 538e551 Ó 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>

<p>the mean were excluded prior to statistical analysis. For plasma 
metabolites, there was a single outlier detected for hydroxybutyrate 
and two detected for glycerol. In liver, there was a single outlier 
detected for succinate, phenylalanine, Glx, citrulline, C6, C5-OH/C3-
DC, C10, and C18:1 acylcarnitine; and two detected for leucine/ 
isoleucine. In skeletal muscle there was a single outlier detected for 
pyruvate, glycine, serine, proline, valine, leucine/isoleucine, C4/Ci4, 
C5, C6, and C14 acylcarnitine and two for lactate, succinate, C16, 
C18, and C18:1 acylcarnitine. For studies comparing all four exper-
imental groups, a full factorial analysis of variance (ANOVA) was 
performed in <rs id="software-0" type="software">JMP Pro</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">12</rs> to evaluate diet and genotype effects fol-
lowed by Tukey's HSD post-hoc test for all pairwise multiple com-
parisons. A Pearson's correlation test was performed in <rs id="software-1" type="software">JMP Pro</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">12</rs> 
to assess the association between urinary acetylglycine and skeletal 
muscle glycine levels. For clamp and metabolic cage studies where 
only ZFR fed the two diets were compared, an unpaired two-sided 
student's t-test was performed in excel. In all cases, a P-value 
less than 0.05 was considered significant. </p>

<p>3. RESULTS </p>

<p>3.1. Influence of Zucker-fatty genotype and BCAA restriction on 
circulating amino acids 
In this study, we employed a dietary approach to manipulate BCAA 
availability in Zucker-fatty rats (ZFR), which are hyperphagic due to a 
missense mutation in the leptin receptor (Lepr) gene, and also studied 
Zucker-lean rats (ZLR), which have at least one copy of normal Lepr. 
We fed these animals for 15 weeks with either a standard low fat (LF) 
diet, or a LF diet in which the BCAA content was reduced by 45% (LF-
RES). The LF-RES diet was rendered isocaloric and isonitrogenous to 
the LF diet by increasing the levels of the non-BCAA amino acids 
evenly to offset the decrease in calories and nitrogen caused by BCAA 
restriction (Table 1). We first measured circulating amino acids in the 
two genotypes fed the two diets (Figure 1A). We found that ZFR fed 
the LF diet had approximately 50% higher levels of valine, leucine 
and isoleucine compared to ZLR on the LF diet (P &lt; 0.001; 
Figure 1A). Thus, ZFR have similar increases in circulating BCAA to 
those found in obese and insulin resistant compared to lean and 
insulin sensitive humans [2], suggesting that they are a useful model 
for our studies. Feeding of ZFR with the LF-RES diet lowered circu-
lating BCAA levels to those found in ZLR on the LF diet. Interestingly, 
preventing the rise in circulating BCAA in ZFR via dietary BCAA re-
striction did not lower phenylalanine or tyrosine levels in circulation 
even though these aromatic amino acids are consistently found to be 
increased in obese and insulin resistant humans in concert with the 
rise in BCAA [2,5]. 
While neither diet nor genotype had a significant impact on circulating 
aspartate/asparagine (Asx) or glutamate/glutamine (Glx) (Figure 1A), 
LF-fed ZFR had lower circulating glycine levels than ZLR on the same 
diet (P &lt; 0.05), consistent with differences in lean and obese humans 
[2,30]. Notably, BCAA restriction raised circulating glycine in both ZLR 
and ZFR, revealing for the first time that the obesity-driven decline in 
circulating glycine is related to BCAA availability. In line with the partial 
restoration of the glycine pool in ZFR rats fed the LF-RES diet, we also 
observed higher levels of serine, derived from glycine by the bidirec-
tional serine hydroxymethyltransferase reaction (P &lt; 0.01). 
We also note that circulating alanine was increased approximately 
50% in ZFR compared to ZLR (P &lt; 0.001), and diet did not influence 
this difference. Proline, methionine and histidine were each raised 
modestly by both the ZF genotype and the BCAA restriction diet 
(Figure 1A). </p>

<p>3.2. Dietary BCAA restriction influences food intake and weight 
gain 
We found that feeding an isonitrogenous and isocaloric 45% BCAA 
restriction diet had a small yet significant (p &lt; 0.001) effect on food 
intake in both ZLR and hyperphagic ZFR, with both groups consuming 
approximately 10% less kcal per day (Figure 1B). This decrease in food 
intake had no effect on weight gain over the feeding period or final 
weight at the end of feeding in ZLR but caused an approximate 15% 
decrease in weight gain and 10% decrease in final weight in the ZFR 
setting (Figure 1C). Nonetheless, on both the LF and LF-RES diets, ZFR 
were severely obese, as both groups gained approximately twice the 
weight gained by the ZLR during the 15-week feeding period 
(Figure 1C). 
Furthermore, the livers of ZFR weighed 3.5 fold more than livers of ZLR 
(P &lt; 0.001) and this was not significantly affected by BCAA restriction 
(Figure 1D). However, tissue weight of the eWAT was modestly yet 
significantly lower in the ZFR fed the LF-RES rats compared to the LF 
diet (P &lt; 0.001; Figure 1D). This effect of the BCAA restriction diet was 
not present in ZLR, suggesting that elevated BCAA supply may 
contribute to the expansion of adipose mass in obese states. Notably, 
skeletal muscle and cardiac muscle mass were not significantly 
affected by BCAA restriction (Figure 1E). </p>

<p>3.3. Substrate preference is regulated by dietary BCAA supply 
In order to better understand the metabolic effects of dietary BCAA 
restriction we studied ZFR in metabolic cages. Dietary BCAA restriction 
in ZFR had no effect on ambulation (Figure 1F), heat production 
(Figure 1G), or oxygen consumption (Figure 1H). However, BCAA re-
striction did cause a clear lowering of RER during the transitional 
period between the light and dark cycles (Figure 1I). These data are 
consistent with increased reliance on fatty acid oxidation in ZFR fed the 
BCAA restricted diet and suggest that decreased food intake rather 
than increased energy expenditure accounts for the small reduction in 
weight gain in LF-RES-fed ZFR. 
Notably, the lower RER observed in ZFR fed the BCAA restricted diet 
was not associated with any changes in circulating triglycerides, 
glycerol, NEFA, ketones, or lactate (Figure 1JeN). This suggests that 
lower RER in BCAA restricted ZFR is not due to alterations in substrate 
supply. </p>

<p>3.4. Glucose tolerance is not influenced by BCAA restriction 
After 10 weeks on the diets, ZFR displayed severely impaired glucose 
tolerance that was characterized by elevated fasting glycemia, delayed 
return to fasting glycemia following the intraperitoneal (IP) glucose 
challenge, and extremely high insulin levels that displayed no acute 
response to glucose (Figure 2A and B). Dietary BCAA restriction had no 
significant impact on glucose or insulin responses during IP glucose 
tolerance testing in either ZFR or ZLR. However, there was a trend for 
lower insulin levels at 60 min in ZFR fed the LF-RES diet compared to 
LF feeding (P ¼ 0.065; Figure 2B). </p>

<p>3.5. Skeletal muscle insulin sensitivity and glucose disposal is 
improved by BCAA restriction 
Considering that the glucose-stimulated insulin secretory response 
was entirely absent in ZFR during the GTT and that these obese ani-
mals require pharmacologic concentrations of insulin to elicit effects on 
systemic glucose metabolism [31], we carried out hyperinsulinemic-
isoglycemic clamps using a dose of insulin (10 mU$kg </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>$min </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>) 
found previously to be sufficient to inhibit hepatic glucose production in 
ZFR [31]. Under these conditions, ZFR fed the BCAA restricted diet 
required a higher glucose infusion rate (GIR) than LF-fed ZFR to </p>

<p>MOLECULAR METABOLISM 5 (2016) 538e551 Ó 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>



<p>maintain blood glucose at fasting levels in the steady state (P &lt; 0.05; 
Figure 2C and D). [U-</p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C] glucose and [ </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>H]-2-deoxyglucose were 
provided as a tracer bolus during the clamp experiments, allowing us 
to assess the effect of BCAA restriction on muscle glucose disposal and 
storage as glycogen. Consistent with the higher GIR, we observed a 
more rapid clearance of tracer from circulation after the bolus injection 
(P &lt; 0.05; Figure 2E and F), accompanied by greater accumulation of 
[ </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>H] 2-DG-6-phosphate in muscle (P &lt; 0.05; Figure 2G) and increased 
[ 
14 C] glucose incorporation into muscle glycogen (P &lt; 0.01; Figure 2H) 
in ZFR fed the LF-RES compared to LF diets. These data demonstrate 
improved whole-animal and skeletal muscle insulin sensitivity and </p>

<p>glucose disposal in ZFR fed the BCAA restricted diet. We also observed 
a slight yet significant improvement in accumulation of 
3 H 2-DG-6-
phosphate in the epididymal white adipose tissue (eWAT) of ZFR fed 
the BCAA restricted diet (P &lt; 0.05; data not shown). </p>

<p>3.6. Tissue-specific effects of obesity and BCAA restriction on 
BCKDH activity 
We next measured BCKDH activity in skeletal muscle, adipose tissue, and 
liver. Consistent with previous reports [11,23], we found that ZFR have 
lower hepatic BCKDH activity compared to ZLR (P &lt; 0.001, Figure 3A). 
We also found that BCAA restriction does not relieve this impairment in </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>12:00 
16:00 
20:00 
0:00 
4:00 
8:00 </p>

<p>RER </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>Start 
weight </p>

<p>Final 
Weight </p>

<p>Weight 
gain </p>

<p>grams </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>Food 
intake </p>

<p>Kcal/day </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>Liver eWAT </p>

<p>grams </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>12:00 
16:00 
20:00 
0:00 
4:00 
8:00 </p>

<p>Ambula on </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>12:00 
16:00 
20:00 
0:00 
4:00 
8:00 </p>

<p>Heat (Kcal/kg) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>1400 </p>

<p>12:00 
16:00 
20:00 
0:00 
4:00 
8:00 
VO2 (ml.kg.hr -1 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>1400 </p>

<p>1600 </p>

<p>1800 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>Val Leu/Ile Phe 
Tyr 
Asx 
Glx 
Gly 
Ser 
Ala 
Pro 
Orn 
Cit 
Arg 
Met 
His 
Circula ng amino acids (pmoles) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>Tg's </p>

<p>mg/dL </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>HBUT Ketones </p>

<p>mmol/L </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>NEFA </p>

<p>μmol/L </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Glycerol </p>

<p>mg/dL </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Lactate </p>

<p>μmol/L </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
C 
D 
E </p>

<p>I 
H 
G 
F </p>

<p>N 
M 
L 
K 
J </p>

<p>LF-ZLR 
LF-RES-ZLR 
LF-ZFR 
LF-RES-ZFR </p>

<p>LF-ZFR 
LF-RES-ZFR </p>

<p>LF-ZLR 
LF-RES-ZLR 
LF-ZFR 
LF-RES-ZFR </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Gastroc 
Soleus 
Heart </p>

<p>grams </p>

<p>* * 
* * 
* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>** 
** 
* </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>TG </p>

<p>Figure 1: Effect of Zucker-fatty genotype and BCAA restriction on circulating amino acids and energy balance. Male Zucker-lean rats (ZLR) or Zucker-fatty rats (ZFR) were 
fed a custom low fat (LF) diet or an isonitrogenous isocaloric LF diet in which BCAA were restricted by 45% (LF-RES). (A) Circulating amino acid profiles. (B) Daily food intake (kcal/ 
day). (C) Starting weight, final weight, and total weight gain (grams). (D) Liver and epididymal adipose tissue (eWAT) weights (grams). (E) Gastrocnemius, soleus and heart tissue 
weights (grams). n ¼ 12e28 per group (F) Ambulation (total x and y beam breaks), (G) Heat (kcal/kg), (H) VO2 (mL/kg/hr), and (I) Respiratory exchange ratio (RER) measured hourly 
during a 24 h cycle following a 24 h acclimation period in the metabolic cages, during which the dark period was from 5PM to 5AM as shown by the gray bar, n ¼ 9e12 per group. </p>

<p>(J) Plasma triglycerides (TG; mg/dL), (K) glycerol (mg/dL), (L) non-esterified fatty acids (NEFA; mM/L), (M) hydroxybutyrate and ketones (mmol/L), and (N) lactate (mM/L), n ¼ 9e15 </p>

<p>per group. Data represent mean AE SEM. Statistical differences indicated by: *: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, ***: P &lt; 0.001 comparisons indicated by the connecting lines or in the 
absence of connecting lines vs LF-ZLR, and #: P &lt; 0.05, ##: P &lt; 0.01, ###: P &lt; 0.001 vs LF-ZFR. </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>542 MOLECULAR METABOLISM 5 (2016) 538e551 Ó 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>

<p>ZFR. Interestingly, skeletal muscle and eWAT BCDKH activities were 
increased in ZFR compared to ZLR (P &lt; 0.05), but were unaffected by the 
diet consumed (Figure 3B and C). These data suggest that obesity-
associated decreases in hepatic BCKDH activity are partially compen-
sated by an increase in skeletal muscle and adipose tissue activity, 
although note the differences in scale in Figure 3AeC. 
We next quantified levels of the circulating branched chain keto acids </p>

<p>(BCKA): a-keto-isovalerate (KIV), a-keto-isocaproate (KIC), and a-keto-
b-methylvalerate (KMV; Figure 3D). Here we observed that circulating </p>

<p>BCKA reflect the impairment in hepatic BCKDH activity, with higher 
levels of all three BCKA in plasma of ZFR compared to ZLR (P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>for KIV and KIC, P &lt; 0.01 for KMV). Importantly, despite the near 
complete normalization of circulating BCAA achieved by dietary BCAA 
restriction (Figure 1A), the diet intervention had no significant impact on 
any of the circulating BCKA in ZFR. Thus it appears that the compen-
satory rise in skeletal muscle and adipose tissue BCKDH activity is not 
sufficient to overcome the impairment of hepatic activity in ZFR. </p>

<p>3.7. Divergent effects of obesity and BCAA restriction on liver and 
skeletal muscle amino acid profiles 
In light of the divergent effects of genotype on tissue BCKDH activities, 
we next performed amino acid profiling in liver and muscle by targeted </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>450 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>0 
5 0 
1 0 0 
1 5 0 
2 0 0 </p>

<p>Glucose (mg/dL) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>0 
5 0 
1 0 0 
1 5 0 
2 0 0 </p>

<p>Insulin (ng/mL) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
Glycemia (% basal) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
GIR (mg.kg.min -1 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100000 </p>

<p>200000 </p>

<p>300000 </p>

<p>400000 </p>

<p>500000 </p>

<p>2 5 10 15 20 30 45 </p>

<p>Plasma DPM </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500000 </p>

<p>1000000 </p>

<p>1500000 </p>

<p>2000000 </p>

<p>2500000 </p>

<p>3000000 </p>

<p>3500000 </p>

<p>AUC 
AUC of tracer clearance </p>

<p>LF-ZLR 
LF-RES-ZLR 
LF-ZFR 
LF-RES-ZFR </p>

<p>LF-ZFR 
LF-RES-ZFR </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>E 
D 
C </p>

<p>F 
G 
H </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>Skm 
glycogen 
14C-glucose incorp (μmoles/g ) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* 
* * * * * 
* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>Skm 
3H-2DG uptake (μmoles/g </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Time a er tracer bolus (min) 
Time a er tracer bolus (min) 
Time a er tracer bolus (min) </p>

<p>Figure 2: BCAA restriction improves skeletal muscle insulin sensitivity in Zucker-fatty rats. Male Zucker-lean rats (ZLR) and Zucker-fatty rats (ZFR) were studied on a 
custom low fat (LF) diet or an isonitrogenous, isocaloric LF diet in which BCAA were restricted by 45% (LF-RES). Panels AeB show results of a 1 g/kg intraperitoneal glucose 
tolerance test (IPGTT) performed in week 10 on the diets, whereas panels CeG show results of a hyperinsulinemic-isoglycemic clamp experiment, carried out in weeks 14 and 15, 
during which [U-</p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C] glucose and </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>H 2-deoxyglucose were included as tracers (clamp data shown only for ZFR). (A) Glucose (mg/dL) and (B) insulin (ng/mL) excursions during the 
IPGTT, n ¼ 10e27 per group. (C) Blood glucose during the clamp, expressed as percent of starting value; (D) glucose infusion rate (GIR; mg/kg/min), and (E) tracer disappearance 
(Plasma DPM) during the steady state period following tracer injection of the clamp; n ¼ 5e6 per group. (F) Area under the tracer disappearance curve (from panel E). (G) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>H-2-
deoxyglucose uptake in gastrocnemius muscle (mmoles/g). (H) [U-</p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]-glucose conversion to glycogen in gastrocnemius muscle (mmoles/g). Data represent mean AE SEM, 
statistical differences indicated by: *: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01 vs LF-ZFR. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR METABOLISM 5 (2016) 538e551 Ó 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>



<p>MS/MS. Despite the elevated levels of BCAA found in circulation 
(Figure 1A), livers from LF-fed ZFR had slightly lower concentrations of 
valine and significantly lower levels of leucine and isoleucine compared 
to LF-fed ZLR (P &lt; 0.001; Figure 3E). Dietary BCAA restriction tended 
to further lower hepatic BCAA content in both ZFR and ZLR. In concert 
with lower hepatic BCAA in ZFR we also observed lower hepatic 
content of the transamination product glutamate/glutamine compared 
to ZLR (P &lt; 0.001; Figure 3F). In alignment with our measurements of 
BCKDH activity, we observed that hepatic glutamate/glutamine levels 
were not responsive to BCAA restriction. Interestingly, hepatic 
phenylalanine and tyrosine content was also lower in liver of ZFR 
compared to ZLR (P &lt; 0.001; Figure 3E), and these aromatic amino 
acids were also not responsive to dietary BCAA restriction (Figure 3E). 
One interpretation of these data is that impaired hepatic BCKDH activity 
may be eliciting a feedback signal to inhibit transport of BCAA into the 
liver through the large neutral amino acid transporters (LAT1 and 2) </p>

<p>that are also employed by tyrosine and phenylalanine, contributing to 
accumulation of BCAA, phenylalanine, and tyrosine in the circulation 
(Figure 1A and [2]). 
In contrast to most other amino acids in liver, hepatic glycine levels 
were reflective of circulating glycine (Figure 1A). ZFR had lower hepatic 
glycine levels compared to ZLR (P &lt; 0.001), and dietary BCAA re-
striction raised glycine levels in the ZFR compared to LF-fed ZFR 
(P &lt; 0.05, Figure 3F). However, hepatic serine content was not 
affected by the fatty genotype or the BCAA restricted diet. In light of the 
minimal impact of BCAA restriction on hepatic BCAA metabolism, it is 
likely that changes in liver glycine reflect BCAA-dependent regulation 
of glycine metabolism at an extrahepatic site. 
Hepatic histidine was not affected by the fatty genotype but was 
sensitive to dietary BCAA content in both ZLR and ZFR (Figure 3G). This 
may reflect elevated reliance on the histidine pool to maintain hepatic 
glutamate levels. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>Liver 
KIV oxida on (nmoles/g/min) 
0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Skeletal 
Muscle </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>eWAT </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>KIV 
KIC 
KMV 
Plasma BCKA (μM) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Val Leu/Ile Phe 
Tyr 
Asx 
Skm amino acids (μM) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>Glx 
Gly 
Ser 
Ala </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>Pro Orn Cit 
Arg Met His </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Val Leu/Ile Phe 
Tyr 
Liver amino acids (μM) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>Asx 
Glx Glycine Ser 
Ala </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Pro Orn Cit 
Arg Met His </p>

<p>LF-ZLR 
LF-RES-ZLR 
LF-ZFR 
LF-RES-ZFR </p>

<p>A 
B 
C 
D </p>

<p>E 
F 
G </p>

<p>J 
I 
H </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** 
*** </p>

<p>*** 
** </p>

<p>Figure 3: Effect of Zucker-fatty genotype and BCAA restriction on tissue BCKDH activity and amino acid profiles and on plasma BCKA levels. Tissue branched chain keto 
acid dehydrogenase (BCKDH) activity, plasma branched chain keto acid content (BCKA) and liver and skeletal muscle amino acid profiles were evaluated in ZLR or ZFR fed the LF or 
LF-RES diets. (A) Liver, (B) skeletal muscle, and (C) adipose tissue BCKDH activity measured by 
14 CO 2 produced by tissue extracts incubated with [1-</p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C] a-keto-isovalerate (KIV), 
n ¼ 8e14 per group. (D) Plasma concentration of the branched chain keto acids (BCKA), a-keto-isovalerate (KIV), a-keto-isocaproate (KIC), and a-keto-methylvalerate (KMV), </p>

<p>n ¼ 9e15 per group. (EeG) Liver amino acid levels. (HeJ) Skeletal muscle amino acid levels. n ¼ 9e15 per group. Data represent mean AE SEM. Statistical differences indicated 
by: *: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, ***: P &lt; 0.001 comparisons indicated by the connecting lines or in the absence of connecting lines vs LF-ZLR, and #: P &lt; 0.05, ##: P &lt; 0.01, ###: 
P &lt; 0.001 vs LF-ZFR. </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>544 MOLECULAR METABOLISM 5 (2016) 538e551 Ó 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>

<p>In contrast to our findings in liver, the skeletal muscle amino acid 
profile closely resembled that from circulation. Accordingly, LF-fed ZFR 
had higher levels of valine (P &lt; 0.05), leucine and isoleucine 
(P &lt; 0.001) in skeletal muscle than LF-fed ZLR, and these were almost 
completely normalized by dietary BCAA restriction (Figure 3H). Higher 
skeletal muscle phenylalanine levels in ZFR compared to ZLR were not 
responsive to dietary BCAA restriction (Figure 3H), as was also true in 
the circulation. Also aligned with BCAA supply to skeletal muscle, 
levels of the transamination products aspartate/asparagine (P &lt; 0.05; 
Figure 3H) were higher in LF-fed ZFR compared to LF-fed ZLR, and 
were lowered in response to BCAA restriction. Alanine levels were 
higher in ZFR compared to ZLR (P &lt; 0.001) but the trend for BCAA 
restriction to lower alanine in ZFR did not achieve statistical signifi-
cance (P ¼ 0.13; Figure 3I). 
Skeletal muscle glycine levels were lower in LF-fed ZFR compared to 
ZLR (P &lt; 0.001; Figure 3I) and were almost completely normalized in 
ZFR by BCAA restriction (P &lt; 0.001; Figure 3I). Furthermore, in 
contrast to liver, changes in skeletal muscle glycine were mirrored by 
serine, with lower levels in LF-fed ZFR compared to ZLR (P &lt; 0.01; 
Figure 3I), and a trend for increased serine levels in response to BCAA 
restriction in both genotypes. Arginine levels exhibited a similar pattern 
to glycine but with greater variability (Figure 3J). Skeletal muscle 
proline and ornithine content also resembled circulating levels and 
were raised modestly by both the fatty genotype and BCAA restriction 
(Figure 3J). </p>

<p>3.8. BCAA restriction has minimal effects on liver metabolites in 
ZFR 
We next studied the impact of the fatty genotype and BCAA dietary 
restriction on liver organic acids, acylcarnitines, and acyl CoAs 
measured by targeted GC-MS and MS/MS. Notably, ZFR had lower </p>

<p>levels of the organic acids a-ketoglutarate (a-KG), succinate, fuma-</p>

<p>rate, and malate in liver compared to ZLR, but these metabolites were 
not responsive to dietary BCAA restriction (Figure 4AeE). Levels of C3 
and C5 acylcarnitines, which are derived in part from BCAA catabolism, 
were also lower in ZFR, but were not further reduced by BCAA re-
striction (Figure 4F and G); BCAA restriction did lower C5 acylcarnitine 
in ZLR (P &lt; 0.05; Figure 4G). Interestingly, the most BCAA responsive 
acylcarnitine metabolite in liver was C5-OH/C3-DC acylcarnitine, which 
was lower in LF-fed ZFR compared to LF-fed ZLR (P &lt; 0.05; Figure 4G) 
and further decreased by BCAA restriction in both genetic backgrounds 
(P &lt; 0.001; Figure 4G). 
Hepatic C2 (acetyl) acylcarnitine (Figure 4H) levels were lower in ZFR 
compared to ZLR and not responsive to diet, whereas C4 (Figure 4I) 
and C6 (Figure 4J) acylcarnitine levels were higher in ZFR than in ZLR. 
Similar increases in the C4 and C6 acyl CoA species, butyl CoA and 
hexanoyl CoA, were also observed (Figure 4L); whereas C2 acetyl CoA 
was not different among groups (Figure 4K). There was a trend for 
levels of the long chain C14, C16, C16:1, C18, and C18:1 acylcarni-
tines as well as myristoyl (C14) CoA and palmitoyl (C16) CoA to be 
higher in liver of ZFR compared to ZLR and lower in LF-RES diet-fed 
rats (Figure 4J and L). </p>

<p>3.9. BCAA restriction prevents short and medium even chain acyl 
CoA accumulation in skeletal muscle 
We next studied the impact of the fatty genotype and BCAA restriction 
on skeletal muscle organic acids, acylcarnitines, and acyl CoA's. Di-
etary BCAA restriction tended to raise both lactate and pyruvate levels 
in skeletal muscle of ZFR with P-values for the diet effect of 0.067 and 
0.023, respectively (Figure 5A and B). Dietary BCAA restriction also 
blunted the trend for ZFR to have higher levels of fumarate and malate </p>

<p>in skeletal muscle compared to ZLR (Figure 5G and H). ZFR had clearly </p>

<p>higher levels of citrate (P &lt; 0.05; Figure 5C) and lower levels of a-KG </p>

<p>(P &lt; 0.05; Figure 5D) in skeletal muscle than ZLR, and these differ-
ences were not affected by BCAA restriction. 
Interestingly, skeletal muscle C3 and C5 acylcarnitines were not 
different between genotypes and only C5 was responsive to dietary 
BCAA restriction (P &lt; 0.01 for overall diet effect; Figure 5H). On the 
other hand, the concentration of C5-OH/C3-DC was clearly higher in 
skeletal muscle of LF-fed ZFR compared to LF-fed ZLR (P &lt; 0.001; 
Figure 5I), with this difference completely abrogated by BCAA re-
striction. Taken together, with our findings in liver (Figure 4G), the C5-
OH/C3-DC acylcarnitine metabolite appears to be the best tissue 
biomarker of BCKDH activity and BCAA availability. Importantly, further 
LC-MS/MS analysis identified the BCAA responsive isobar in the C5-
OH/C3-DC peak as C5-OH, representing the leucine metabolite, 3-
hydroxyisovaleryl carnitine, and the isoleucine metabolite, 3-hydroxy-
2-methylbutyryl carnitine (Supplemental Figure 1). 
ZFR had elevated levels of all even chain acylcarnitines from C4/Ci4 to 
C20:1 in skeletal muscle relative to ZLR, and none of these analytes 
was responsive to BCAA restriction in either background (Figure 5K 
and L). LF-fed ZFR also had higher levels of all even chain acyl CoA 
species in skeletal muscle relative to LF-fed ZLR, but in striking 
contrast to the acylcarnitines, BCAA restriction completely prevented 
the accumulation of all short and medium even chain acyl CoA's, 
ranging in chain length from acetyl (C2) to lauroyl (C12) CoA in skeletal 
muscle of ZFR (Figure 5M and N). BCAA restriction also partially 
lowered palmitoyl (C16) CoA (P &lt; 0.05; Figure 5N) and completely 
lowered stearoyl (C18) CoA in skeletal muscle of ZFR (P &lt; 0.01; 
Figure 5N). These data suggest that reduced BCAA intake relieves 
mitochondrial metabolic overload in skeletal muscle to facilitate effi-
cient and complete oxidation of fatty acids, such that even chain acyl 
CoAs no longer accumulate. This interpretation aligns with the lower 
RER observed in response to BCAA restriction in the ZFR background 
(Figure 1I). </p>

<p>3.10. BCAA restriction reverses obesity-associated decreases in 
urinary acetyl-glycine 
Acyl CoA metabolites do not readily cross biological membranes. One 
way of reducing acyl CoA burden in the mitochondria is to conjugate 
acyl groups with glycine to form membrane-permeant acyl-glycines 
that can be excreted in the urine. As an indicator we measured the 
urinary content of the most abundant acyl-glycine, acetylglycine. We 
found that urinary acetylglycine content was lower in LF-fed ZFR 
compared to ZLR (P ¼ 0.084 vs LF-fed ZLR and P &lt; 0.05 vs LF-RES-
fed ZLR; Figure 6A). BCAA restriction in ZFR restored urinary acetyl-
glycine to levels observed in ZLR. Accordingly, we found a significant 
linear association of urinary acetylglycine with skeletal muscle glycine 
levels (R ¼ 0.5779 P ¼ 0.001; Figure 6B). We interpret this to mean 
that BCAA-driven depletion of skeletal muscle glycine contributes to 
accumulation of acyl CoA species in ZFR by limiting the pool of glycine 
available for formation of acyl-glycine adducts that can be exported to 
the urine. </p>

<p>4. DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In an effort to elucidate the role played by circulating BCAA in obesity-
related metabolic dysfunction, we restricted dietary BCAA supply and 
performed comprehensive metabolic and physiologic profiling in a 
rodent model of severe obesity that mirrors human defects in BCAA 
metabolism. Our findings indicate that impaired hepatic BCAA meta-
bolism in obesity is linked to compensatory upregulation of the activity </p>

<p>MOLECULAR METABOLISM 5 (2016) 538e551 Ó 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>



<p>of the rate-limiting enzyme of BCAA oxidation in skeletal muscle. The 
resulting presumed increase in BCAA flux increases substrate load on 
the mitochondria, decreasing the efficiency of skeletal muscle fatty 
acid oxidation and promoting accumulation of lipid-derived short-and 
medium-chain acyl CoAs (Figure 7). Whereas it was previously shown 
that accumulation of incompletely oxidized lipids contributes to skeletal 
muscle insulin resistance [32,33], this is a first demonstration that 
BCAA restriction affects the levels of these lipid mediators. We also 
demonstrate that the obesity-related rise in BCAA is responsible for the 
obesity-associated lowering of glycine levels observed in multiple </p>

<p>human studies [1,2,5,30]. Interestingly, skeletal muscle depletion of 
glycine appears to intersect with fatty acyl CoA accumulation by 
limiting export of acyl groups out of the skeletal muscle in the form of 
acyl-glycine adducts that are excreted in the urine. Consistent with a 
role of this process in regulation of insulin sensitivity, a recent study 
from our group demonstrated increased acyl-glycine levels in urine of 
obese subjects in which an exercise intervention was used to improve 
insulin sensitivity [29]. 
RER was found to be lower in ZFR on the BCAA restricted diet in the 
absence of any change in oxygen consumption, heat production, or </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>Lactate 
Liver organic acids (μM) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Pyruvate 
Citrate 
a-Kg </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>Succinate </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Fumarate </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>Malate </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>C3 
Liver Acylcarni nes (μM) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>C5 
C5-OH/C3-DC </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>C2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>C4/Ci4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>2500 </p>

<p>3000 </p>

<p>acetyl 
Liver Acyl CoAs (pM) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>C6 
C8 
C10 
C12 
C14 
C16 
C16:1 
C18 
C18:1 
C20:1 
Liver Acylcarni nes (μM) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>LF-ZLR 
LF-RES-ZLR 
LF-ZFR 
LF-RES-ZFR </p>

<p>E 
D 
C 
B 
A </p>

<p>H 
G 
F 
I </p>

<p>J </p>

<p>K 
L </p>

<p>*** 
*** 
** </p>

<p>P=0.07 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>* 
** ** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** 
* </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>Figure 4: BCAA restriction has little impact on hepatic metabolites in Zucker-fatty rats. Hepatic metabolites were measured in male ZFR or ZLR fed the LF or LF-Res diets. 
(AeE) Hepatic organic acid levels; (FeI) Hepatic short chain acylcarnitine levels; (J) Hepatic medium-long chain acylcarnitines. (KeL) Hepatic fatty acyl CoA's. n ¼ 9e15 per group. 
Data represent mean AE SEM. Statistical differences indicated by: *: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, ***: P &lt; 0.001 comparisons indicated by the connecting lines or in the absence of 
connecting lines vs LF-ZLR, and ###: P &lt; 0.001 vs LF-ZFR. </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>546 MOLECULAR METABOLISM 5 (2016) 538e551 Ó 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>

<p>activity levels. These findings are consistent with a simple substrate 
supply model wherein increased availability and oxidation of BCAA in 
skeletal muscle of obese rats impedes the oxidation of fatty acids. An 
interesting finding of our study is the increase in a broad array of both 
acylcarnitine and acyl CoA species in muscle of ZFR compared to ZLR, 
but with a selective effect of BCAA restriction to lower the acyl CoA and 
not the acylcarnitine metabolites in the ZFR background. This suggests 
that BCAA restriction has no influence on fatty acid uptake or on the 
CPT1 mitochondrial acylcarnitine transport system for initiating fatty 
acid oxidation but rather relieves a block on oxidation of the inter-</p>

<p>mitochondrial pool of acyl CoAs. These findings are in contrast to a 
recent paper, which proposed that BCAA increase vascular fatty acid 
transport into skeletal muscle through the paracrine actions of a valine 
metabolite, 3-hydroxyisobutyrate (3-HIB) [34]. Such a mechanism 
appears inconsistent with the uniformly high levels of long chain 
acylcarnitines observed in muscle of ZFR fed either the LF or LF-RES 
diets, and the lack of effect of BCAA restriction on circulating NEFA and 
triglycerides, suggesting no differences in lipid supply or uptake. 
BCAA overload in skeletal muscle could conceivably promote the 
accumulation of short-and medium-chain acyl CoAs by competitively </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>Lactate 
Skm organic acids (μM) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Pyruvate </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Citrate </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>a-Kg </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Succinate </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Fumarate </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Malate </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>C3 
C5 
Skm Acylcarni nes (μM) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>C5-OH/C3-DC </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>C2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>C6 
C8 
C10 
C12 
C14 
C16:1 
C16 
C18:1 
C18 
C20:1 
Skm Acylcarni nes (μM) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.12 </p>

<p>C4/Ci4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>acetyl 
Skm Acyl CoAs (pM) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>LF-ZLR 
LF-RES-ZLR 
LF-ZFR 
LF-RES-ZFR </p>

<p>A 
B 
C 
D 
E </p>

<p>J 
I 
H 
K </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>M 
N </p>

<p>F 
G </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.07 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>*** 
** </p>

<p>*** 
*** 
*** 
*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** 
** </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>Figure 5: BCAA restriction abrogates even-chain acyl CoA accumulation in skeletal muscle of Zucker-fatty rats. Metabolites were measured in gastrocnemius muscle 
from male ZFR or ZLR fed LF or LF-Res diets. (AeG) Organic acid levels. (HeK) Short chain acylcarnitine levels. (L) Medium-long chain acylcarnitine levels. (MeN) Fatty acyl CoA 
levels. n ¼ 9e15 per group. Data represent mean AE SEM. Statistical differences indicated by: *: P &lt; 0.05, **: P &lt; 0.01, ***: P &lt; 0.001 comparisons indicated by the connecting 
lines or in the absence of connecting lines vs LF-ZLR, and #: P &lt; 0.05, ##: P &lt; 0.01, ###: P &lt; 0.001 vs LF-ZFR. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR METABOLISM 5 (2016) 538e551 Ó 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>



<p>inhibiting lipid derived acetyl CoA entry into the TCA cycle. Indeed, both 
leucine and isoleucine oxidation can result in acetyl CoA formation. 
However, it is currently unclear what percentage of the total mito-
chondrial acetyl CoA pool of muscle is derived from leucine and 
isoleucine. Nonetheless, a study by Sunny et al. [35] recently 
demonstrated that BCAA infusion lowers TCA cycle flux in liver of 
healthy rats. Hence, it is possible that our data represent the additive 
effect of elevated acetyl CoA synthesis from BCAA and reduced overall 
TCA cycle flux. 
As expected, ZFR rats were severely insulin resistant and glucose 
intolerant compared to ZLR (Figure 2A and B). In line with the strong 
lowering of skeletal muscle acyl CoAs, BCAA restriction caused a 
clear improvement in skeletal muscle insulin sensitivity in ZFR, as 
indicated by a higher glucose infusion rate required to control blood 
glucose during the hyperinsulinemic clamp. This was accompanied by 
enhanced skeletal muscle uptake of radiolabeled glucose and its 
incorporation into glycogen (Figure 2CeH). However, although clearly </p>

<p>significant, the improvement in insulin sensitivity in response to BCAA 
restriction of ZFR rats was only partial relative to the insulin sensitivity 
of ZLR, which display a mean GIR of 37 during a 4 mU$kg </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>$min </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>clamp in our lab (data not shown). Given that BCAA restriction had 
very little effect on hepatic metabolites measured in this study 
(Figures 3 and 4), we assume that insulin sensitivity in liver was not 
improved by BCAA restriction and that this obscured the effects of 
improved muscle glucose disposal on glucose tolerance. Neverthe-
less, our study suggests that BCAA restriction in ZFR promotes non-
oxidative muscle glucose utilization, based on the following obser-
vations: 1) RER was decreased in response to BCAA restriction, 
indicative of an increased reliance on fatty acid oxidation; 2) glucose 
storage as glycogen, a non-oxidative pathway, was increased by 
BCAA restriction; 3) BCAA restriction tended to increase levels of the 
glycolytic intermediates pyruvate and lactate and significantly raised 
serine and glycine without affecting the levels of TCA cycle in-
termediates in skeletal muscle. Thus, increased non-oxidative glucose </p>

<p>Figure 6: Acyl-glycine levels in the urine correlate with skeletal muscle glycine content. We measured acetylglycine content in urine collected from male ZFR or ZLR fed LF 
or LF-RES diets. (A) Urinary acetylglycine (mmol/mol creatinine). (B) Scatterplot showing positive linear correlation between urinary acetylglycine and skeletal muscle glycine 
content. n ¼ 8 per group. Data represent mean AE SEM. Statistical differences indicated by: *: P &lt; 0.05, comparisons indicated by the connecting lines. </p>

<p>Figure 7: Working model of metabolic mechanism of BCAA-driven skeletal muscle insulin resistance. Obesity-driven inhibition of hepatic BCKDH activity lowers hepatic </p>

<p>uptake of BCAA leading to lower tissue levels of BCAA and their metabolic byproducts, particularly C5-OH carnitine, causing BCAA and their a-keto acids (BCKAs) to rise in </p>

<p>circulation and accumulate in skeletal muscle. The obesity-driven increase in skeletal muscle BCKDH activity combined with higher tissue BCAA supply results in higher BCAA 
oxidative flux, reflected by increased C5-OH. This "BCAA overload" in skeletal muscle interferes with the complete oxidation of fatty acids, leading to accumulation of even chain 
fatty acyl CoAs in skeletal muscle. This effect is compounded by BCAA-driven depletion of skeletal muscle glycine levels, which limits acyl CoA excretion as acyl-glycines in the 
urine. BCAA restriction improves muscle insulin sensitivity by relieving substrate pressure and raising glycine levels, leading to normalization of muscle acyl CoA content. </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>548 MOLECULAR METABOLISM 5 (2016) 538e551 Ó 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>

<p>metabolism may contribute to normalization of both skeletal muscle 
fatty acyl CoA and glycine levels in response to BCAA restriction in 
ZFR (Figure 7). 
The approach taken herein focused on the biochemical, metabolic 
changes that underlie BCAA-related insulin resistance rather than 
changes in the canonical pathway of insulin signal transduction. 
However, our observation that BCAA restriction not only lowers skeletal 
muscle BCAA content but also prevents acyl CoA accumulation sug-
gests that lipid and amino acid triggered signals that converge on the 
insulin signaling pathway could have contributed to our findings. Work 
from our group and others has demonstrated that supplementation of 
BCAA, or infusion of a complete mixture of amino acids, activates the 
mTOR/S6K1 pathway leading to inhibitory serine phosphorylation of 
IRS1 [2,17,19]. Indeed, in our prior work, glucose intolerance caused 
by feeding of a BCAA-supplemented high fat diet was lessened by 
infusion of the mTOR inhibitor rapamycin [2]. Thus, altered insulin 
signaling could account for part of the improved skeletal muscle insulin 
sensitivity in ZFR fed the BCAA restricted diet. Furthermore, changes in 
protein acylation states secondary to changes in the acyl CoA pool and/ 
or reduced formation of lipid derivatives such as diacylglycerol and 
ceramide could also have contributed to improved insulin sensitivity in 
BCAA-restricted ZFR [36,37]. Future studies are warranted to delineate 
these and other possible signaling mechanisms linking BCAA to 
skeletal muscle insulin resistance. 
Our comprehensive profiling of liver provides important insight into the 
poorly understood association of BCAA with the aromatic amino acids 
phenylalanine and tyrosine in obese persons [1,2,5]. Surprisingly, 
despite having elevated levels of each of these amino acids in circu-
lation, we observed significantly lower levels of these amino acids in 
liver of ZFR rats. Since BCAA, phenylalanine, and tyrosine are all taken 
into cells by the LAT1/2 transporters [38], this observation suggests 
that impaired hepatic import may contribute to coordinate elevation of 
their levels in circulation. Future studies will investigate the hypothesis 
that accumulation of BCKA or other factors involved in suppression of 
BCDKH activity in ZFR elicit a feedback signal to downregulate activity 
of the LAT1/2 transporter. 
We observed that the BCAA-related metabolite that was most 
responsive to genotype and BCAA restriction was C3-DC/C5-OH 
acylcarnitine. We performed targeted LC-MS/MS analysis to identify 
which isobar was responsible for the differences in the C3-DC/C5-OH 
acylcarnitine peak. Our analysis revealed that C5-OH, which represents 
the leucine intermediate, 3-hydroxyisovaleryl carnitine, and the 
isoleucine intermediate, 3-hydroxy-2-methylbutyryl carnitine, was the 
BCAA responsive metabolite (Supplemental Figure 1). Whereas 3-
hydroxy-2-methylbutyryl carnitine is an intermediate from the clas-
sical isoleucine catabolic pathway, 3-hydroxyisovaleryl carnitine is a </p>

<p>non-canonical leucine metabolite formed from b-methylcrotonyl CoA, </p>

<p>by the actions of enoyl CoA hydratase and carnitine acyltransferase. 3-
hydroxy-2-methylbutyryl carnitine and 3-hydroxyisovaleryl carnitine 
are circulating and urinary markers of 3-hydroxy-2-methylbutyryl-CoA 
dehydrogenase deficiency and 3-methylcrotonyl CoA carboxylase (3-
MCC) deficiency, respectively [39]. Since 3-MCC is a biotin-
dependent enzyme, 3-hydroxyisovaleryl carnitine has also been 
studied as a marker of biotin deficiency [40]. Our data from liver and 
skeletal muscle suggest that C5-OH carnitine levels might also be used 
as a tissue biomarker for BCAA catabolism (Figures 4G and 5I). Given 
the well appreciated role of enoyl CoA hydratase in beta oxidation, 
future studies will be undertaken to determine whether accumulation </p>

<p>of 3-hydroxyisovaleryl carnitine or its precursor b-methylcrotonyl CoA </p>

<p>might contribute to metabolic dysfunction in response to skeletal 
muscle BCAA overload. </p>

<p>We observed a slight but significant reduction in food intake in ZFR rats 
in response to feeding of the BCAA restricted diet, resulting in reduced 
adipose mass. This effect on food intake was unanticipated given our 
previous report that BCAA supplementation of high fat diets decreased 
food intake in normal rats [2] and findings of others that hypothalamic 
activation of mTOR by ICV administration of leucine reduces food intake 
[41]. While it is likely that reduced adipose mass is mostly driven by 
reduced food intake in ZFR fed the BCAA restriction diet, it is note-
worthy that BCAA oxidation was recently shown be induced and 
required for adipocyte differentiation and lipogenesis [42]. Thus, our 
data showing increased BCKDH activity in ZFR compared to ZLR adi-
pose tissues, and the reduction in adipose mass caused by BCAA 
restriction of ZFR, might also support the notion that obesity-
associated elevations in BCAA contribute to adipose tissue expansion. 
We recognize that one interpretation of our findings is that the multiple 
metabolic changes observed in skeletal muscle of ZFR fed the BCAA 
restricted diet are driven by the slightly lesser weight gain in this group 
compared to ZFR fed the BCAA replete diet, even though both groups of 
ZFR rats were massively obese compared to ZLR. Nevertheless, 
several lines of evidence support the idea that the metabolic effects in 
skeletal muscle are in fact regulated by BCAA availability: (1) BCAA 
restriction lowered RER but did not alter circulating levels of glycerol, 
NEFA, triglycerides, ketones, and lactate as one would expect if the 
drop in RER was simply explained by generalized nutrient restriction; 
(2) The metabolic effects of BCAA restriction on lipid accumulation 
were most dramatic in skeletal muscle. Importantly, this tissue-
selective effect does not align with a mechanism for lower RER 
driven by reduced food intake, which would be expected to produce 
more global changes across tissues; (3) BCAA restriction completely 
prevented the accumulation of short and medium chain acyl-CoAs in 
skeletal muscle without modifying even chain acyl-carnitines or the 
long chain palmitoyl CoA. We maintain that this metabolite profile 
speaks to an improvement in clearance or complete oxidation of fatty 
acids in skeletal muscle rather than an alteration in substrate avail-
ability. Indeed, altering lipid availability should coordinately influence 
both acyl-carnitines and acyl-CoAs, as has in fact been observed in 
prior studies from our group [2,32]. (4) In a prior study, we performed 
the opposite manipulation to that described in the current paper-</p>

<p>dnamely, BCAA supplementation. We found that, despite lower food 
consumption and body weight, normal rats fed a HF diet supplemented 
with BCAA accumulated as much or more incompletely oxidized lipids 
in muscle than animals fed the unsupplemented HF diet [2]. This 
finding coupled with the current work appears to demonstrate an effect 
of BCAA to influence lipid oxidation in muscle that is independent of 
body weight and food intake. 
Finally, the current study employed ZFR to model defects present in 
BCAA metabolism in human obesity. While human obesity is not 
commonly caused by a mutation in the leptin receptor, ZFR do replicate 
key metabolic features of the human condition without the requirement 
for dietary manipulation. Most importantly, ZFR display spontaneous 
elevations in circulating BCAA and aromatic amino acids in concert 
with development of obesity as observed for obese humans [1,2,5], 
accompanied by similar perturbations in expression of enzymes 
required for BCAA oxidation in adipose tissue and liver [11,23]. This is 
in contrast to normal rats fed on high-fat diets, which do not exhibit 
increases in circulating BCAA unless supplementation is used [2]. ZFR 
also have lower circulating glycine levels as observed in obese 
humans. Finally, and again in contrast to rodents fed on high fat diets, 
ZFR have an RER of approximately 0.9, similar to that reported for 
obese humans [2]. All of these considerations support the use of ZFR 
for studies of BCAA metabolism. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR METABOLISM 5 (2016) 538e551 Ó 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>



<p>In conclusion, our data support a model in which obesity-driven in-
hibition of hepatic BCAA oxidation drives BCAA, phenylalanine, and 
tyrosine into skeletal muscle, where increases in BCAA oxidation 
interfere with the complete oxidation of lipid, leading to accumulation 
of fatty acyl CoAs, depletion of glycine/serine, and skeletal muscle 
insulin resistance. Our data further suggest that BCAA spillover into 
adipose tissue may promote obesity-related adipose expansion. Future 
studies will be directed at determining the physiological impact of 
restoring hepatic BCKDH activity and raising skeletal muscle glycine on 
obesity-related metabolic dysfunction. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank Huaxia Cui for expert technical assistance. The work was sup-
ported by National Institutes of Health grant NIDDK PO1-DK58398 (to C.B.N.), a 
"Pathways" Initiator Award from the American Diabetes Association (to P.J.W.), and </p>

<p>a sponsored research agreement with Pfizer (to C.B.N.). </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT </p>

<p>C.B.N. is a paid consultant for the CVMED group at Pfizer, and was also the lead 
investigator of a now completed sponsored research agreement with Pfizer that 
supported a portion of the studies described here. </p>

<p>APPENDIX A. SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary data related to this article can be found at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j. 
molmet.2016.04.006. </p>



<p>Original article </p>

<p>550 MOLECULAR METABOLISM 5 (2016) 538e551 Ó 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>



<p>MOLECULAR METABOLISM 5 (2016) 538e551 Ó 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>



</text></tei>