<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4221315" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE: Oral health can affect a patient's general health and quality of life. Given the increase in breast cancer 
survival rates, investigations of factors influencing the quality of life of survivors have gained importance. 
Therefore, the objective of our study was to characterize oral health in postmenopausal breast cancer survivors. 
METHODS: We conducted a matched case-control study. Forty-eight women who survived breast cancer (age 
62.1¡9.1 years) and 48 healthy controls (age 61.8¡8.6 years) were included. For each case and control, a 
complete oral evaluation chart was completed. 
RESULTS: The prevalence of chronic periodontal disease was 98% in breast cancer survivors and 87% in controls. 
The breast cancer survivors had a median of 16 remaining teeth, whereas controls had a median of 22 remaining 
teeth (p = 0.03). The percentage of sites with gingival bleeding was 16.05% (0-100%) in breast cancer survivors 
and 0% (0-72%) in controls (p = 0.04). 
CONCLUSION: Chronic periodontal disease and tooth loss were highly prevalent in postmenopausal breast cancer 
survivors. To improve survivors' quality of life, a preventive oral health evaluation should be available prior to 
cancer treatment. </p>

<p>oral examination. The oral examinations were performed 
after the end of oncological treatment for all breast cancer 
survivors. The data included the following: the total number 
of teeth, full-mouth plaque score (the number of sites with 
detectable dental plaque divided by the total number of 
sites per mouth, multiplied by 100), full-mouth gingival 
bleeding on probing score (the number of sites with gingival 
bleeding on probing divided by the total number of sites per 
mouth, multiplied by 100), full-mouth periodontal lesion 
score (the number of sites with a probing depth $4 mm 
divided by the total number of sites per mouth, multiplied 
by 100) and the mean probing attachment level. </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>The data for each variable were tested using the 
D' Agostino &amp; Pearson normality test. The mean and 
standard deviation or median and range were determined. 
Student's t test or the Mann-Whitney test was performed as 
appropriate. All analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">GraphPad</rs> 
SoftwareH <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0</rs> for Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software Inc</rs>, La 
Jolla, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Ethics </p>

<p>The study was approved by the local institutional review 
board, and all subjects signed a written informed consent 
form. All procedures were in accordance with the Helsinki 
Declaration. </p>

<p>&amp; RESULTS </p>

<p>The medical parameters associated with breast cancer are 
presented in Table 1. The mean age was 62.1¡9.1 years for 
breast cancer survivors and 61.8¡8.6 years for controls. 
Oral health data are presented in Table 2. CPD was 
identified in 98% of breast cancer survivors (mild period-
ontitis: 30 cases; moderate periodontitis: 11 cases; severe 
periodontitis: 6 cases) and 87% of controls (mild period-
ontitis: 23 cases; moderate periodontitis: 12 cases; severe 
periodontitis: 7 cases). 
The median number of teeth was 16 (3-28) for breast 
cancer survivors and 22 (4-31) for controls (p = 0.03, Mann-
Whitney test). The median full-mouth plaque score was 50 
(0-100) for cancer survivors and 36.57 (0-100) for controls 
(p = NS, Mann-Whitney test). The median full-mouth gingi-
val bleeding on probing score was 16.05 (0-100) for the cases 
and 0 (0-72) for the controls (p = 0.04, Mann-Whitney test). </p>

<p>The median full-mouth periodontal lesion score was 3.3 
(0.0-46.7) for breast cancer survivors and 3.6 (0.0-51.6) for 
controls. The probing attachment level was 2.8 (1.3-5.9) in 
breast cancer survivors and 3.1 (1.5-5.2) in controls (p = NS, 
Mann-Whitney test). </p>

<p>&amp; DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We identified a very high prevalence of CPD in post-
menopausal breast cancer survivors; only one of our 
patients did not exhibit signs of the disease. The controls 
also presented a high prevalence of CPD; however, breast 
cancer survivors had significantly higher indices of gingival 
bleeding and tooth loss. These findings are highly relevant 
for the multidisciplinary management of breast cancer. 
The quality of life and long-term survival of breast cancer 
survivors may be affected by lack of oral health care. CPD is 
associated with several unpleasant symptoms that can 
range from mild to severe, including swelling, bluish purple 
discoloration of the gingiva, bleeding after eating or brushing 
and halitosis. CPD can also induce loss of supportive con-
nective tissues, including alveolar bone, thereby resulting 
in loss of attachment of the periodontal ligament to the 
cementum and eventual tooth loss (mainly among older 
individuals) (9). 
The prevalence of CPD increased significantly with age 
and remained constant after the 50-59 age group (10). The 
prevalence of CPD in postmenopausal women not taking 
hormonal replacement is approximately 64.4%, whereas the 
prevalence is 46.3% in postmenopausal women taking 
hormonal replacement (11). Overall, 87% of the individuals 
in our control group had CPD; this prevalence is compar-
able to that observed in Germany (10) and higher than that 
observed in the U.S. (12). The association between breast 
cancer treatment and oral health has not previously been 
explored, but it is well known that ''potentially complicat-
ing oral disease should be identified and corrected as early 
as possible before commencement of anticancer therapy'' 
(13). A comprehensive dental examination performed prior 
to treatment can identify approximately 80% of the patients 
with chronic odontogenic pathology who should receive 
treatment to prevent local exacerbation or systemic spread 
of ongoing infection while avoiding long-term oral compli-
cations, such as tooth loss (14). 
On the other hand, the association between CPD and 
cardiac morbidity is well established. Cardiac complications 
have a serious impact on the life expectancy and quality of 
life of breast cancer survivors. The risk for cardiac disease 
may be increased in breast cancer survivors due to various 
reasons other than CPD. Data from The Late Effects Breast 
Cancer Cohort have revealed that 62.9 excess cases of 
cardiovascular events per 10,000 patient-years are asso-</p>

<p>Table 1 -Medical parameters of breast cancer survivors. </p>

<p>Parameter 
N (%) </p>

<p>Tumor histology 
Ductal 
46 (95.8) 
Lobular 
2 (4.2) 
Tumor stage 
I 
10 (20.8) 
II 
25 (52.1) 
III 
12 (25.0) 
IV 
1 (2.3) 
Chemotherapy 
33 (66.43) 
Radiotherapy 
41 (85.4) 
Tamoxifen 
40 (83.3) 
Aromatase inhibitor 
8 (16.7) 
Surgery 
Radical 
18 (37.5) 
Conservative 
30 62.5) </p>

<p>Table 2 -Oral health parameters in breast cancer survivors 
and controls. </p>

<p>Parameter 
Cases 
Controls 
p </p>

<p>Chronic periodontitis (%) 
47 (98) 
42 (87) 
NS 
Total number of teeth 
16 (3-28) 
22 (4-30) 
0.03 
% of sites with detectable plaque 50 (0-100) 
36.57 (0-100) 
NS 
% of sites with gingival bleeding 16.05 (0-100) 
0 (0-72) 
0.04 
% of sites with a depth $4 mm 
3.3 (0.0-46.7) 3.6 (0.0-51.6) 
NS 
Probing attachment level 
2.8 (1.3-5.9) 
3.1 (1.5-5.2) 
NS </p>

<p>Data are presented as the median (range). </p>

<p>CLINICS 2014;69(10):706-708 
Oral health after breast cancer treatment 
Amó dio J et al. </p>



<p>ciated with long-term breast cancer treatment and the main 
risk factors are associated with radiotherapy of the internal 
mammary chain, radiation with adjuvant chemotherapy 
and smoking (15). After breast conservation treatment for 
early stage disease, the subsequent development of cardiac 
disease is more frequent in women with cancer of the left 
breast (16). Anthracyclines, which are largely used in breast 
cancer chemotherapy, have long been recognized as a cause 
of cardiac dysfunctions, such as cardiomyopathy and heart 
failure. These side effects are dose-dependent (17) and occur 
more frequently in older patients (18). Trastuzumab, a 
monoclonal antibody that blocks the HER-2 receptor and 
improves the survival of women with HER-2-positive breast 
cancer, is also associated with an increased risk of cardiac 
dysfunction (19). 
High-quality management of breast cancer patients should 
include strategies for identifying patients who are at high risk 
for cardiac disease and developing effective interventions to 
prevent the development of late toxicities and minimize 
their effects on quality of life (20). Epidemiological (7)  and experimental (5,21) evidence indicates that periodontal 
disease is linked to an increased risk of cardiovascular 
disease. Despite the limitations of our case-control design 
and a lack of diversity in the therapeutic methods employed, 
our data consistently revealed a high prevalence of period-
ontal disease and tooth loss after breast cancer treatment 
in post-menopausal women. We believe that the current 
evidence warrants the inclusion of a recommendation for a 
comprehensive oral examination and treatment of identified 
lesions in the breast cancer management protocols in the 
public health system. Efforts have been made to screen for 
and reduce or eliminate risk factors for cardiac disease, 
such as smoking, elevated lipid levels and hypertension, in 
patients who have breast cancer after menopause. However, 
these efforts should also include the prevention and treat-
ment of oral diseases. </p>

<p>&amp; AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </p>

<p>Amodio J, Palioto DB and Candido dos Reis FJ conceived and designed 
the study, performed data collection, analyzed data, interpreted data, wrote 
and critically reviewed the manuscript. Carrara HH, Tiezzi DG and 
Andrade JM participated in writing and critically reviewed the manuscript. </p>



<p>Oral health after breast cancer treatment 
Amó dio J et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2014;69(10):706-708 </p>



</text></tei>