<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4793049" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A b s t r a c t </p>

<p>Introduction: Fibroblast growth factor 1 (FGF-1) is a powerful mitogen involved in the stimulation of DNA synthesis 
and the proliferation of a wide variety of cell types. Fibroblast growth factor 1 was genetically modified to improve 
its thermal stability and resistance to protease degradation without losing its biological activity. 
Aim: To study the impact of Q40P/S47I/H93G rFGF-1 on skin cells, its penetration through the skin and the evalu-
ation of the rFGF-1-cosmetic product properties. 
Material and methods: In vitro studies included the examination of primary fibroblast and keratinocyte viability 
after the incubation with rFGF-1. The penetration abilities of rFGF-1 in various formulations and carrier systems 
were examined ex vivo by the Raman spectroscopy. In vivo studies -HF Ultrasound and 3D Imaging System -were 
used to evaluate the anti-aging properties of creams containing rFGF-1. 
Results: In vitro studies demonstrated that rFGF-1 strongly enhanced the viability of the treated cells. The Raman 
Spectroscopy analysis indicated that rFGF-1 encapsulated in lipid spheres penetrate through the stratum corneum 
to the depth of 60 µm, and added to the o/w formulation -could penetrate to a depth of 90 µm. The results 
obtained from Primos revealed the reduction of the volume and the depth of the wrinkles. Changes in the skin 
structure in the analyzed areas were evaluated by HF Ultrasonography. 
Conclusions: Recombinant FGF-1 strongly stimulated fibroblast and keratinocyte proliferation. However, the transi-
tion of this protein through the SC required an appropriate carrier system -lipid spheres. All tests -in vitro, ex vivo 
and in vivo -have proved that rFGF-1 is a substance with a potentially wide spectrum of use. </p>

<p>Aging results mainly in the loss of dermal collagen 
and the accumulation of unorganized collagen and elas-
tin fibers in the dermis, which leads to the appearance of 
the most common signs of aging, i.e. wrinkles, elastosis 
and loss of skin tone. Fibroblasts play the key role in wrin-
kle formation because they produce basic structural skin 
substances: collagen, elastin and hyaluronic acid. These 
substances provide the skin with appropriate elasticity, 
tensile strength, firmness (collagen and elastin fibers) 
and moisturization (hyaluronic acid). During the aging 
process, the proliferative and metabolic activity of fibro-
blasts decreases, the fibers' functions are impaired and </p>

<p>their structure becomes modified and then destroyed. 
Some of the biochemical effects of intrinsic and extrinsic 
skin aging are similar to the formation of a wound [1]. 
Human growth factors (HGF) play the key role in wound 
healing and they are important for proper cell functional-
ity [2]. Human growth factors participate in cell division, 
new cell and blood vessel growth as well as in collagen 
and elastin production and distribution. They are also 
involved in the growth and regeneration of many differ-
ent cells in the body, including fibroblast, liver, vascular, 
thyroid, ovary and pituitary gland cells. Nowadays, a lot 
of research is conducted in order to evaluate the useful-
ness of HGFs in anti-aging treatment. </p>

<p>Postępy Dermatologii i Alergologii 1, February / 2016 </p>

<p>A study of the activity and effectiveness of recombinant fibroblast growth factor (Q40P/S47I/H93G rFGF-1) in anti-aging treatment </p>



<p>Human acidic fibroblast growth factor 1 (FGF-1) be-
longs to a large family of growth factors that bind to 
transmembrane receptors with a cytoplasmic tyrosine 
kinase domain. The FGF-1 is a powerful mitogen involved 
in the stimulation of DNA synthesis and proliferation of 
a wide variety of cell types. It plays important roles in var-
ious stages of development and morphogenesis, as well 
as in angiogenesis and wound healing processes [3, 4]. 
Fibroblast growth factor 1 was genetically modified 
to improve its thermal stability and resistance to pro-
tease degradation without losing its biological activity. 
The triple mutant Q40P/S47I/H93G has changes in the 
sequence localized in the loop between residues Leu89 
and Asn95 (mutation H93G), within residues Thr34-Ile42 
(Q40P) and in strand 4 (S47I) (Figure 1). The obtained 
protein was fully functional and characterized by higher 
mitogenic activity, a longer half-life and much greater re-
sistance to proteolysis than the wild type [5, 6]. </p>

<p>Aim </p>

<p>The aim of this research was to investigate the im-
pact of rFGF-1 on skin cells, its penetration abilities 
through the stratum corneum and to evaluate the anti-
aging properties of cosmetic products containing Q40P/ 
S47I/H93G rFGF-1 as an active compound. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>In vitro study </p>

<p>In vitro studies were carried out on two types of 
skin cells: fibroblasts (human primary fibroblasts from 
donors of different age: 20, 34, 40 and 60 years of age) 
and keratinocytes: KB (ATCC) and HaCaT lines (Deutsches 
Krebsforschungszentrum Stabsstelle Technologietransfer 
Heidelberg, Germany) [7]. </p>

<p>Figure 1. A -Superposition of wild-type FGF-1 (PDB code 1rg8) and the Q40P/S47I/H93G mutant (PDB code 2q9x). Regions 
of mutated residues are shown in (B) (Q40P), (C) (S47I) and (D) (H93G). The wild-type structure is shown in dark grey 
and that of the triple mutant in light grey [6]. Reproduced with permission of the International Union of Crystallography </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>S471 
Gln45 </p>

<p>Lys57 </p>

<p>Q40P </p>

<p>Ser38 </p>

<p>H93G </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Postępy Dermatologii i Alergologii 1, February / 2016 </p>



<p>Justyna Żerańska, Monika Pasikowska, Barbara Szczepanik, Krzysztof Mlosek, Sylwia Malinowska, Renata M. Dębowska, Irena Eris </p>

<p>Fibroblasts and the HaCaT cell lines were grown in 
standard MEM medium (Eagle's), (GIBCO) and the KB 
cells were cultured in RPMI medium. Cells were stimu-
lated by recombinant fibroblast growth factor 1 (rFGF-1) 
[5, 6] in 2 concentrations of 10 ng/ml and 100 ng/ml. 
Cell viability was determined by an MTT assay after 24 h 
of stimulation (KB and HaCaT lines) and after 7 days of 
stimulation (fibroblasts). </p>

<p>Ex vivo study -Raman spectroscopy </p>

<p>Raman measurements were carried out on dried 
samples using a Renishaw inVia Raman system equipped 
with a 100-mW laser emitting a 632.8 nm line used as 
the excitation source. The light from the laser was passed 
through a line filter and focused on a sample mounted 
on an X-Y-Z translation stage with a 50× microscope ob-
jective. The Raman-scattered light was collected by the 
same objective through a holographic notch filter to block 
out Rayleigh scattering. A 1800 groove/mm grating was 
used to provide a spectral resolution of 5 cm 
-1 . The Ra-
man scattering signal was recorded by a 1024 × 256 pixel 
RenCam CCD detector. The beam diameter was approxi-
mately 2.5 µm. Typically, the spectra were acquired for 
10-30 s, either in a static mode, centering at 1200 cm 
-1 , 
or in an extended mode, between 300 and 3400 cm 
-1 , 
with the laser power measured at the sample being 
5 mW. The spectra were normalized by the laser power 
and the collection times. This stage of the research was 
carried out in three phases. Firstly, the determination of 
the fingerprint (reference spectra) for the recombinant 
FGF-1 was done. Then, the evaluation of the penetration 
ability of pure rFGF-1, pure rFGF-1 encapsulated in lipo-
somes and lipid spheres [8], pure rFGF-1 added to stan-
dard o/w and w/o emulsions, and finally the composition 
of rFGF-1 and lipid spheres from o/w and w/o emulsions 
was carried out. Fingerprints of pure substances were 
generated at a depth of 15-25 µm. All samples were ap-
plied on skin explants (10 µl each) from female donors 
(23-26 years of age) and incubated for 72 h on metal 
strainers. Those skin explants were used only to investi-
gate the skin system penetration. </p>

<p>In vivo study </p>

<p>The study sample comprised 25 women in the age 
range between 51 and 59 with visible signs of aging. All 
the volunteers signed the consent to participating in the 
test. The enrolled women applied the anti-wrinkle creams 
day and night for 4 weeks. Both creams included the ac-
tive ingredient -rFGF-1 in lipid spheres. 
The skin evaluation was performed twice -prior to 
and after the 4-week treatment. The High Frequency 
Ultrasound (HFU) device EPISCAN Ultrasound Scanner 
Version 4.0.0.030 (Longport International Ltd., USA), 
equipped with the 50 MHz mechanical probe and Primos 
3D Imaging System (GFMesstechnik GmbH, Germany) </p>

<p>was used for the examinations. All scans and images 
were performed at the same location: the nasolabial fold 
and the wrinkle between the eyebrows, at fixed settings 
of the scanner's and camera's parameters. The following 
parameters were investigated: epidermis echo thickness, 
dermis thickness, dermis echogenicity. Separately, the 
echogenicity of the dermis inferior (reticular) layer (HFU) 
[9] and the depth and volume of measured wrinkles (Pri-
mos) [10] were tested. The study was approved by the 
ethical committee. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The sample distribution was determined by the 
W Shapiro-Wilk test and the statistical significance for de-
pendent samples by the t-Student test, while for the non-
parametric by the Wilcoxon test. α &lt; 0.05 was considered 
statistically significant (<rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistica software</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver 10</rs>). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>In vitro study </p>

<p>The studies carried out on fibroblasts revealed that 
Q40P/S47I/H93G rFGF-1 strongly enhanced the viabil-
ity of cells from each donor. The strength of stimulation 
depended on the cell line. rFGF-1 most effectively stimu-
lated the proliferation of fibroblasts from donors of 34 
and 40 years of age (Figure 2). In almost all samples bet-
ter results were achieved after stimulation with 10 ng/ 
ml rFGF-1. However, in P20 cells higher proliferation was 
observed after stimulation with 100 ng/ml rFGF-1. 
rFGF-1 stimulated the proliferation of keratinocytes 
from the KB line, as from the HaCaT line (Figure 3). In 
the KB line there was a statistically significant increase 
of 25% (10 ng/ml rFGF-1) and of 13% (100 ng/ml rFGF-1) 
in cell viability. In the HaCaT line there was an improve-
ment in cell viability of about 42% after stimulation with 
10 ng/ml rFGF-1, and 11% after stimulation with 100 ng/ 
ml rFGF-1 (Figure 3). </p>

<p>Ex vivo study -Raman spectroscopy </p>

<p>The fingerprint of rFGF-1 was generated. Q40P/S47I/ 
H93G rFGF-1 does not penetrate through the stratum cor-
neum as a pure substance, or from the w/o and o/w for-
mulations (Figure 4). This was evidenced by the lack of 
bands at frequencies: 1063, 1131, 1291, 1440, 2850 and 
2883 cm 
-1 characteristic for rFGF-1. rFGF-1 enclosed in 
liposomes did not penetrate through the stratum cor-
neum either (Figure 5). However, rFGF-1 encapsulated in 
lipid spheres (SLNs) was able to migrate through the skin 
to a depth of 20 μm (Figure 6). Moreover, the rFGF-1 in 
lipid spheres can migrate through the dermis to a depth 
of 60 μm (Figure 7) and it was not present in the deeper 
layers but it can penetrate to a depth of 90 μm from the 
o/w formulation containing 5% of the composition of </p>

<p>Postępy Dermatologii i Alergologii 1, February / 2016 </p>

<p>A study of the activity and effectiveness of recombinant fibroblast growth factor (Q40P/S47I/H93G rFGF-1) in anti-aging treatment </p>



<p>thickness of the dermis (measured on the forehead) was 
2.03 mm. After 4 weeks it increased to 2.23 mm, indicat-
ing a 10.01% improvement in this parameter. However, 
there were no similar results observed at the nasolabial 
fold (Table 1). For the epidermis echo thickness differ-
ences between pre-and post-treatment values were ob-
served in both measured areas (Table 1), but they were 
not statistically significant. There was also a change 
involving the increase in the echogenicity of the dermis 
inferior layer. The pre-and post-treatment values of this 
parameter showed statistically significant differences </p>

<p>Cell line 
Concentration 
of rFGF-1 </p>

<p>Mean value 
(OD, λ = 595 nm) </p>

<p>Standard 
deviation </p>

<p>Difference 
Standard deviation 
of difference </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>P20 
Control 
0.2435 
0.01343 
-0.0835 
0.00919 
0.04946 </p>

<p>10 ng/ml 
0.3270 
0.02263 </p>

<p>Control 
0.2435 
0.01343 
-0.1660 
0.01697 
0.04594 </p>

<p>100 ng/ml 
0.4095 
0.03040 </p>

<p>L34 
Control 
0.1975 
0.00495 
-0.4510 
0.07212 
0.07169 </p>

<p>10 ng/ml 
0.6485 
0.07707 </p>

<p>Control 
0.1975 
0.00495 
-0.3197 
0.00707 
0.00995 </p>

<p>100 ng/ml 
0.5175 
0.01202 </p>

<p>L40 
Control 
0.2223 
0.01817 
-0.3514 
0.07674 
0.01553 </p>

<p>10 ng/ml 
0.5737 
0.07998 </p>

<p>Control 
0.2195 
0.02475 
-0.2805 
0.02616 
0.04193 </p>

<p>100 ng/ml 
0.5000 
0.05091 </p>

<p>A60 
Control 
0.3403 
0.07656 
-0.3422 
0.05840 
0.00956 </p>

<p>10 ng/ml 
0.6827 
0.09903 </p>

<p>Control 
0.3050 
0.06505 
-0.2945 
0.06435 
0.09759 </p>

<p>100 ng/ml 
0.5995 
0.00071 </p>

<p>Figure 2. The mean viability of human primary fibroblasts from 20-(P20), 34-(L34), 40-(L40) and 60-(A60) year-old 
donors (MTT assay) after 7-days' stimulation by rFGF-1 in concentrations of 10 or 100 ng/ml. Untreated cells were used 
as a control. *Statistically significant results (p &lt; 0.05), (Statistica software ver. 10); table contains the RAW data (OD) </p>

<p>Percent of control </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(n = 3) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>134* </p>

<p>258* </p>

<p>201* </p>

<p>168* </p>

<p>262* </p>

<p>228* </p>

<p>197 </p>

<p>328 </p>

<p>(n = 3) </p>

<p>(n = 3) </p>

<p>(n = 2) </p>

<p>(n = 2) </p>

<p>(n = 2) </p>

<p>(n = 2) </p>

<p>(n = 2) </p>

<p>(n = 2) </p>

<p>P20 
L34 
L40 
A60 
P20 
L34 
L40 
A60 
Control 
10 ng/ml rFGF-1 
100 ng/ml rFGF-1 </p>

<p>rFGF-1 and lipid spheres (Figure 7). An analogous test was 
done for the formulation w/o, but there were no bands 
characteristic for the studied active ingredient. </p>

<p>In vivo study </p>

<p>The visual analysis of the collected ultrasound im-
ages was done by three independent researchers sepa-
rately for each individual parameter. The analysis of re-
sults has produced a statistically significant increase in 
dermis thickness in the wrinkle between the eyebrows 
(forehead area). Before applying the cream the average </p>

<p>Postępy Dermatologii i Alergologii 1, February / 2016 </p>



<p>Justyna Żerańska, Monika Pasikowska, Barbara Szczepanik, Krzysztof Mlosek, Sylwia Malinowska, Renata M. Dębowska, Irena Eris </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>125* </p>

<p>113* </p>

<p>142* </p>

<p>111* </p>

<p>Figure 3. The mean viability of keratinocytes: KB and HaCaT lines (MTT assay) after 24 h' stimulation by rFGF-1 in concen-
trations of 10 or 100 ng/ml. Untreated cells were used as a control. *Statistically significant results (p &lt; 0.05) (Statistica 
software ver. 10); table contains the RAW data (OD) </p>

<p>Percent of control </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>(n = 6) </p>

<p>(n = 6) </p>

<p>(n = 6) 
(n = 4) </p>

<p>(n = 4) </p>

<p>Control 
10 ng/ml rFGF-1 
100 ng/ml rFGF-1 </p>

<p>Cell line 
Concentration 
of rFGF-1 </p>

<p>Mean value 
(OD, λ = 595 nm) </p>

<p>Standard deviation 
Difference 
Standard deviation 
of difference </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>KB 
Control 
0.5102 
0.03789 
-0.1255 
0.05470 
0.00242 </p>

<p>10 ng/ml 
0.6357 
0.03049 </p>

<p>Control 
0.4882 
0.02133 
-0.2043 
0.01352 
0.00008 </p>

<p>100 ng/ml 
0.6925 
0.01836 </p>

<p>HaCaT 
Control 
0.1562 
0.00486 
-0.0203 
0.00411 
0.00223 </p>

<p>10 ng/ml 
0.1765 
0.00311 </p>

<p>Control 
0.1587 
0.00532 
-0.0180 
0.00498 
0.00031 </p>

<p>100 ng/ml 
0.1767 
0.00356 </p>

<p>KB line 
HaCaT line 
KB line 
HaCaT line </p>

<p>Figure 4. The spectra of: a) pure rFGF-1 (10 µg/ml) -fin-
gerprint, b) w/o emulsion with pure rFGF-1 (100 ng/ml), 
c) o/w emulsion with pure rFGF-1 (100 ng/ml). Lack of 
bands at frequencies of 1063, 1131, 1291, 1440, 2850 and 
2883 cm 
-1 -characteristic for the rFGF-1 </p>

<p>Raman intensity </p>

<p>Raman shift [cm </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>] </p>

<p>886 </p>

<p>1131 </p>

<p>1297 </p>

<p>1068 </p>

<p>1440 </p>

<p>2850 </p>

<p>2883 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>1440 </p>

<p>Figure 5. Migration of the rFGF-1 enclosed in liposomes. 
The spectra of: a) liposomes, b) rFGF-1 enclosed in lipo-
somes (0.8 µg/ml), c) pure rFGF-1 (10 µg/ml). For spectrum 
b there are mainly bands characteristic for the liposome 
and not for the rFGF-1. No bands at frequencies: 1063, 1131, 
1291, 1440, 2850 and 2883 cm 
-1 which are characteristic for 
that active ingredient show that it cannot migrate through 
the stratum corneum </p>

<p>Raman intensity </p>

<p>Raman shift [cm </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>] </p>

<p>886 </p>

<p>1297 </p>

<p>1440 </p>

<p>1068 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 1400 1600 </p>

<p>Postępy Dermatologii i Alergologii 1, February / 2016 </p>

<p>A study of the activity and effectiveness of recombinant fibroblast growth factor (Q40P/S47I/H93G rFGF-1) in anti-aging treatment </p>



<p>Table 1. Results obtained from HFU </p>

<p>Location 
Parameter 
Before treatment 
(mean value) </p>

<p>After treatment 
(mean value) </p>

<p>Percent 
of improvement </p>

<p>Nasolabial 
fold 
(n = 20) </p>

<p>Epidermis echo thickness [mm] 
0.1050 
0.1185 
+12.86% </p>

<p>Dermis thickness [mm] 
1.8876 
1.8857 
No improvement </p>

<p>Dermis echogenicity [pixels] 
40705 
40023 
No improvement </p>

<p>Echogenicity of dermis inferior layer [pixels] 
15930 
16130 
+1.25%* </p>

<p>The wrinkle 
between the 
eyebrows 
(n = 20) </p>

<p>Epidermis echo thickness [mm] 
0.1273 
0.1387 
+8.96% </p>

<p>Dermis thickness [mm] 
2.0302 
2.2335 
+10.01%* </p>

<p>Dermis echogenicity [pixels] 
40368 
40009 
No improvement </p>

<p>Echogenicity of dermis inferior layer [pixels] 
15741 
15801 
+0.38%* </p>

<p>n -number of women in the test; *statistically significant values. </p>

<p>1440 </p>

<p>2851 
2880 </p>

<p>2850 </p>

<p>2883 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Figure 6. Migration of rFGF-1 encapsulated in lipid spheres 
(SLNs). The spectra of: a) lipid spheres (SLNs), b) rFGF-1 en-
capsulated in lipid spheres (SLNs) (0.8 µg/ml), c) pure rFGF-1. 
The presence of the bands in spectrum b characteristic for 
the test component (at frequencies: 1063, 1131, 1291, 1440, 
2850 and 2883 cm 
-1 ) is a clear indication of its presence in 
the skin sample. rFGF-1 enclosed in lipid spheres passes 
through the stratum corneum into the living layers </p>

<p>Raman intensity </p>

<p>Raman shift [cm </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>] </p>

<p>886 </p>

<p>1297 1440 </p>

<p>2851 
2880 </p>

<p>2850 </p>

<p>2883 </p>

<p>1131 
1068 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>200 
700 
1200 
1700 
2200 
2700 
3200 </p>

<p>1440 </p>

<p>Figure 7. The spectra of: a) pure rFGF-1, b) pure rFGF-1 in lip-
id spheres (10 µg/ml) -presence of the bands characteristic 
for the rFGF-1: 1063, 1131, 1291, 1440, 2850 and 2883 cm </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>at a depth of 60 µm, c) 5% rFGF-1 in lipid spheres in the 
o/w formulation -presence of the bands characteristic for 
the rFGF-1 at a depth of 90 µm, d) empty lipid spheres -
placebo, e) phosphate buffered saline (PBS) </p>

<p>Raman intensity </p>

<p>Raman shift [cm </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>] </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>600 
800 
1000 
1200 
1400 
1600 
1800 </p>

<p>Table 2. Results obtained from Primos </p>

<p>Location 
Parameter 
Before treatment 
(mean value) </p>

<p>After treatment 
(mean value) </p>

<p>The difference 
between pre-and 
post-treatment values </p>

<p>Nasolabial fold 
(n = 20) </p>

<p>The depth of the wrinkle [µm] 
Not available 
Not available 
-75.70 </p>

<p>The volume of the wrinkle [mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>] 
21.20 
18.82 
-2.38 </p>

<p>The wrinkle between 
the eyebrows 
(n = 20) </p>

<p>The depth of the wrinkle [µm] 
Not available 
Not available 
-50.99 </p>

<p>The volume of the wrinkle [mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>] 
6.44 
5.48 
-0.96* </p>

<p>n -number of women in the test, *statistically significant values, "not available" means that the software gives the result as the difference, without before and 
after values. </p>

<p>Postępy Dermatologii i Alergologii 1, February / 2016 </p>



<p>Justyna Żerańska, Monika Pasikowska, Barbara Szczepanik, Krzysztof Mlosek, Sylwia Malinowska, Renata M. Dębowska, Irena Eris </p>

<p>of about 1.25% for the nasolabial location (Table 1). The 
measurement of dermis echogenicity indicated no sta-
tistically significant difference before the application of 
the products and after the 4-week treatment (Table 1). 
The results obtained from Primos revealed differ-
ences for both the depth and the volume of the mea-
sured wrinkles. At the nasolabial fold a decrease by 
75.70 μm (Table 2) in the depth was observed after the 
use of the set of products. Similar results were observed 
in the forehead area, where the depth of the wrinkle be-
tween the eyebrows decreased by 50.99 μm (Table 2). 
The volume of the nasolabial fold was 21.20 mm 
3 before 
the test, and it decreased to 18.82 mm 
3 at the end of the 
treatment (Table 2). A similar tendency was observed for 
the mean value of the volume of the wrinkle between 
the eyebrows, which was 6.44 mm 
3 , whereas after the 
treatment it decreased to 5.48 mm 
3 (Table 2). The differ-
ence of about 0.96 mm 
3 was statistically significant for 
the forehead area, but not for the nasolabial fold, where 
the difference in the volume was 2.38 mm 
3 (Table 2). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The use of growth factors is a novel anti-aging strat-
egy to rejuvenate and reverse the signs of skin photo-
aging. The knowledge and understanding of the role of 
growth factors in wound healing may predict their role 
in remodeling the skin's infrastructure and rejuvenating 
aging skin [2]. </p>

<p>Efficacy of rFGF-1 on human skin cells </p>

<p>The rFGF-1, due to its mitogenic functions, has be-
come a potential active ingredient with a wide range 
of uses in cosmetology directed at skin regeneration. 
There are some studies reporting that growth fac-
tors are a potent antioxidants that inhibits the ag-
ing of skin cells, strengthens its defense processes 
and reduces wrinkles [1]. Some study reports that 
growth factors are critical for the proliferation of 
skin cells like keratinocytes and fibroblasts. Zhang 
et al. tested fibroblast growth factor-peptide (FGF-P) 
as a potential mitigator of radiation effects through the 
proliferation and the barrier function of keratinocytes. 
Proliferation is critical in maintaining a healthy barrier 
layer of keratinocytes. As it was proved, radiation re-
duced MTT activity in a dose-dependent manner, which 
was reversed by treatment with FGF-P [11]. Similar results 
were found by Anitua et al. who tested plasma rich in 
growth factors (PRGF-Endoret) on primary human cells, 
including keratocytes and conjunctival fibroblasts. In 
both cell types, the PRGF-Endoret enhanced prolifera-
tion [12]. The in vitro studies presented in this publication 
have demonstrated similar effects on human keratino-
cytes and fibroblasts. The results showed a strong impact 
of rFGF-1 on the viability of keratinocytes both from KB 
and HaCaT lines (Figure 3) and fibroblasts from donors </p>

<p>of different age. rFGF-1 most strongly stimulated the 
proliferation of L34 and L40 fibroblasts (Figure 2). These 
results suggest that it has strong regenerative properties 
which can be used in cosmetic products. </p>

<p>Penetration through the skin barrier </p>

<p>Small molecules, due to their physico-chemical prop-
erties, have a greater ability to penetrate the skin. In 
the case of large particles, the barrier of percutaneous 
absorption is primarily the stratum corneum. Penetra-
tion of cosmetic ingredients can be accelerated by either 
removing the hydrophilic film from the skin surface by 
surfactants, or by using penetration enhancers like alco-
hols and glycols [13]. 
The skin is the critical surface barrier of the body. The 
structure and lipophilic properties of the outer layer of 
the skin (stratum corneum) cause only lipophilic, non-
polar (non-ionic) and low molecular weight (&lt; 500 Da) 
molecules to migrate to the deeper layers of the skin, 
although penetration of such compounds is often insuf-
ficient to produce the desired effect [14, 15]. Therefore, 
there is a need to increase or even to allow the migration 
of both lipophilic and hydrophilic active substances into 
the skin [15]. For that reason, nowadays the use of nano-
and micro-lipid spheres in cosmetology is growing. The 
lipid-based formulations seem to be the most appropriate 
ones for the topical application of active substances be-
cause they contain physiological and biodegradable lipids 
which have affinity with the stratum corneum. When ap-
plied externally they do not affect its function [16]. 
The rFGF-1 is a large protein of 15.196 kDa. Its isoelec-
tric point is 8.12, and it has a positively charged patch on 
the surface [17]. Due to the large size of this protein there 
was a necessity to check its penetration abilities through 
the stratum corneum. To assess the depth of Q40P/S47I/ 
H93G rFGF-1 penetration, the Raman Spectroscopy was 
used. This method allows the testing of water, NMF, urea, 
lipids, and carotenoids content in the skin. It is also used 
for medical applications like analysing the composition of 
kidney stones, dispensing of medicines, the study of DNA 
damage [18] and analysis of cancer tissues [19]. 
Raman analysis provided evidence that both pure 
rFGF-1, pure rFGF-1 in w/o and o/w formulations and 
rFGF-1 enclosed in liposomes do not penetrate through 
the stratum corneum (Figures 4 and 5). Only rFGF-1 en-
closed in lipid spheres passes through the stratum corne-
um, as evidenced by the presence of bands characteristic 
for the tested component in the generated spectra (Fig-
ure 6). After receiving these results the lipid spheres were 
selected as the dermal transport system for rFGF-1. As 
shown in these data the ingredients of o/w formulation 
could act as enhancers and caused rFGF-1 to penetrate 
deeper (to a depth of 90 μm into the skin) than the com-
position of rFGF-1 and lipid spheres, which migrated to 
a depth of 60 µm (Figure 7), what definitely needs further 
investigation. A feature of lipid particles (lipid spheres) </p>

<p>Postępy Dermatologii i Alergologii 1, February / 2016 </p>

<p>A study of the activity and effectiveness of recombinant fibroblast growth factor (Q40P/S47I/H93G rFGF-1) in anti-aging treatment </p>



<p>particularly important from a cosmetology point of view 
is the creation of a discontinuous occlusive layer on the 
skin's surface. If the particle size is smaller, their adhe-
sion to the skin is stronger and the occlusion is more 
effective. This reduces transepidermal water loss, thereby 
increasing the hydration and elasticity of the skin. Oc-
clusion also has a positive impact on the penetration of 
active substances into the skin. This has been proven 
for the Coenzyme Q10, which was applied in the form of 
a suspension of lipid nanoparticles [20]. 
The rFGF-1 in lipid spheres passes through the stra-
tum corneum presumably on the basis of forming by 
lipid spheres an occlusion layer specific for the active 
substance, which strongly increases its penetrative abili-
ties, and electrostatic interactions between the protein 
molecules and lipid spheres, where lipid spheres act as 
a carrier for cosmetic active ingredients which has an 
affinity with the stratum corneum lipids. On the other 
hand, it has been suggested that growth factors and cy-
tokines can penetrate through hair follicles, sweat glands 
or compromised skin, followed by interaction with cells in 
the epidermis, such as keratinocytes, to produce signal-
ing cytokines that affect cells deeper in the dermis, such 
as fibroblasts [1]. </p>

<p>In vivo efficacy </p>

<p>Several cosmetic products containing human growth 
factors are currently available on the market. For a few 
of them clinical results available indicate that the topical 
application of human growth factors provides beneficial 
effects in reducing the signs of facial skin aging [2, 21-
23]. In the study conducted by Fitzpatrick and Rostan, the 
mixture of growth factors, cytokines and soluble matrix 
proteins secreted by cultured neonatal human fibroblasts 
reduced fine lines, wrinkles and periorbital photodam-
age. Measurements of Grenz-zone collagen and epider-
mal thickness measured from the biopsy showed a 37% 
increase in Grenz-zone collagen and a 30% increase in 
epidermal thickness [21]. Similar results were obtained by 
Gold et al. who tested a proprietary growth factor and cy-
tokine mixture extracted from cultured first trimester fe-
tal human dermal fibroblasts in moisturizing cream on 18 
patients for 60 days. The findings revealed an improve-
ment in the average wrinkle score in periorbital (17%) 
and perioral (13%) areas [23]. The third product contained 
liposome-encapsulated transforming growth factor β1 
(TGF-β1), L-ascorbic acid and black cohosh (Cimicifuga 
racemosa) extract in a silicone base. The study proved an 
improvement in the wrinkle score for TGF-β1-containing 
cream as compared to cream with only L-ascorbic and 
black cohosh extract [22]. All the cited studies are similar 
to the results of our in vivo tests. The instrumental as-
say provided evidence that the 4-week use of 2 products 
with the composition of rFGF-1 and lipid spheres (for day 
and for night) decreases both the volume and the depth 
of the measured wrinkles (Table 2). Moreover, the exami-</p>

<p>nation made by high frequency ultrasound (HFU) demon-
strated changes in the structure of the skin, which may 
be caused by collagen restoration and better hydration 
of the tested areas. However, there were dissimilarities 
depending on the location of measurements. The better 
results obtained at the nasolabial fold may be caused 
by the differences in the thickness of the skin, which is 
thicker on the forehead and thus hinders the penetration 
of active ingredients. 
All the collected data significantly suggest that Q40P/ 
S47I/H93G rFGF-1 has great potential for use in cosmetic 
anti-wrinkle treatment. Its strong effect on cell prolifera-
tion implies that rFGF-1 may have much wider applica-
tions, which inevitably must be further investigated. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Q40P/S47I/H93G rFGF-1 strongly stimulated fibro-
blast and keratinocyte proliferation, which suggests the 
high potential for the use of this protein in anti-aging 
skin care products. However, the transition of this protein 
through the stratum corneum required a suitable carrier 
system -lipid spheres. Only the use of this form of active 
ingredient could provide the desired effect. 
Growth factors play an important role in reversing 
the effects of skin aging mediated both by chronologi-
cal and environmental factors [1]. Active substances such 
as exogenous growth factors may be used as a strategy 
to attenuate the signs of aging. Growth factors may ma-
nipulate the fundamental mechanisms, e.g. reverse the 
activity of fibroblasts and stimulate them to increase pro-
liferation [24], which has been proven in the conducted 
studies. All tests -in vitro, ex vivo and in vivo -confirmed 
that Q40P/S47I/H93G rFGF-1 is a substance with a poten-
tially wide spectrum of use in cosmetology and wound 
healing. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>Postępy Dermatologii i Alergologii 1, February / 2016 </p>





</text></tei>