<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4644610" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Although using the nursing process improves nursing care quality, few studies have evaluated nursing performance in 
accordance with nursing process steps either nationally or internationally. 
Objectives: This study aimed to audit nursing care based on a nursing process model. 
Patients and Methods: This was a cross-sectional descriptive study in which a nursing audit checklist was designed and validated for 
assessing nurses' compliance with nursing process. A total of 300 nurses from various clinical settings of Tehran university of medical 
sciences were selected. Data were analyzed using descriptive and inferential statistics, including frequencies, Pearson correlation 
coefficient and independent samples t-tests. 
Results: The compliance rate of nursing process indicators was 79.71 ± 0.87. Mean compliance scores did not significantly differ by 
education level and gender. However, overall compliance scores were correlated with nurses' age (r = 0.26, P = 0.001) and work experience 
(r = 0.273, P = 0.001). 
Conclusions: Nursing process indicators can be used to audit nursing care. Such audits can be used as quality assurance tools. </p>

<p>Keywords: Nursing Care; Nursing Process; Clinical Audit; Quality of Health Care </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015, Kashan University of Medical Sciences. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non-
Commercial 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial 
usages, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>Audits are a method of evaluating the care process. A 
clinical audit can identify activities that should or should 
not be performed in clinical settings (1). It not only im-
proves care quality but also helps nurses to acquire and 
use the knowledge, skills, and attitudes necessary for cre-
ating a meaningful, productive, and satisfying working 
environment (2). The first step in operationalizing the 
clinical audit is to identify specified indicators of the do-
main. The nursing process can be used as a framework for 
developing auditing indicators. 
Although using the nursing process improves nursing 
care quality, few studies have evaluated nursing perfor-
mance in accordance with nursing process steps either 
nationally or internationally. Most studies on nursing au-
dits evaluated only the quality of nursing records (3-5) to 
assess care quality (6, 7). In Iran, Khosravani et al. found 
that job satisfaction was significantly higher among 
nurses who used the nursing process in their practice 
(8). However, Shoorideh and Ashktorab showed that per-
sonal and management factors are among the barriers to 
implement the nursing process in clinical settings (9). 
Given the importance of evaluation of nursing care, the 
need to develop appropriate criteria for clinical audits </p>

<p>is obvious. However, a review showed that few studies 
have used the nursing process as a framework to evaluate 
nursing care (3-5, 7). </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>This study aimed to audit nursing care on the basis of a 
nursing process model. </p>

<p>3. Patients and Methods </p>

<p>A cross-sectional study was carried out from Febru-
ary 2014 to April 2015 in 16 educational hospitals affili-
ated with Tehran university of medical sciences (TUMS). 
Healthcare providers in these hospitals include resi-
dents, fellows, interns, nurses, and nursing students. In 
this study, we specifically targeted nursing staff. </p>

<p>3.1. Developing the Audit Instrument </p>

<p>First, a nursing audit checklist was designed based on a 
literature review and expert opinions obtained from in-
depth interviews of 10 experts in nursing and accredita-
tion. Interviews included the following question: "what 
indicators should be considered if you want to evaluate </p>

<p>Poortaghi S et al. </p>

<p>Nurs Midwifery Stud. 2015;4(3):e30181 </p>

<p>
clinical nursing services?" Reflective and explorative 
questions were also used (e.g., Why? How? Could you ex-
plain more?). A total of 18 interviews were conducted at 
this stage, with a mean duration of 44 minutes. 
To analyze the data, qualitative content analysis was 
conducted and 354 primary codes were extracted. These 
codes were then reduced into 43 main codes in five main 
categories according to nursing process steps. These sec-
ondary codes were used as the primary items to develop a 
checklist for auditing nursing practice. To assess face and 
content validity qualitatively, the checklist was sent to 15 
experts in clinical nursing and accreditation of nursing 
practice and 10 experienced nurse educators. Some items 
were modified or deleted. 
At this stage, there were 25 items (indicators) in the 
checklist, covering the following domains: assessment 
(5 items), nursing diagnosis and identifying outcomes 
(5 items), planning (5 items), implementation (7 items), 
and evaluation (3 items). Most items were rated on a 
three-point scale (never = 0, sometimes = 50, and always 
= 100) depending on the level of nurses' compliance. 
However, some of the indicators employed a yes/no for-
mat (yes = 100, no = 0) according to the national hos-
pital accreditation audit guide (10). Mean scores were 
calculated for each indicator as well as for each domain 
and for the full checklist. Higher scores indicate better 
performance. 
The external consistency, internal consistency, and inter-
rater reliability of the final version of the checklist were 
assessed. External consistency was assessed through the 
test-retest method with a two-week interval (r = 0.954). 
Internal consistency was confirmed (Cronbach's α = 
0.889). To assess inter-rater reliability, the checklist was 
simultaneously completed by two auditors (first and cor-
responding authors) for 10 care provider. An intraclass 
correlation coefficient of 0.95 was obtained. </p>

<p>3.2. Participants and Sample Size Calculation </p>

<p>Inclusion criteria were working full-time, having at 
least 2 years of clinical experience, and willingness to par-
ticipate in the study. In a previous study, the prevalence of 
quality nursing care was 25% (12). Using Cochran's sample 
size formula and the parameters P = 0.25, q = 0.75, d = 0.05, 
and α = 0.05, we estimated that 288 cases were needed. 
However, we recruited 300 nurses to compensate for pos-
sible attrition. The number of nurses to be recruited each 
hospital was calculated by considering the total number 
of nurses in each. </p>

<p>3.3. Audit Assessment </p>

<p>Data were collected using a demographic questionnaire 
and the audit checklist. The demographic questionnaire 
included questions on nurses' age, gender, work experi-
ence, type of employment, setting, education level, and 
work shift. It was completed along with the checklist. 
Observations, interviews, and document evaluation </p>

<p>were used to audit nursing care (using the audit guide). 
The number of nurses to be audited in each hospital 
was calculated by considering the total number of 
nurses in each. Then, using a random number table, 
the required number of nurses was randomly selected 
from the list of nurses in each hospital. Two auditors, 
who were trained in auditing, performed the audit by 
using a guide designed before the audit process was 
started. To determine the rate of compliance with indi-
cators, all of the nursing activities were observed dur-
ing a single work shift and nursing documents were 
evaluated. Furthermore, in some cases, interviews were 
conducted with nurses as explained in detail in the au-
dit guide. 
Nurses' performance was assessed using the audit 
checklist during a single work shift. Some indicators 
needed to be assessed through a review of documents 
and nursing notes (e.g., recording and reporting). Some 
indicators had to be assessed through observation (e.g., 
collaborating with the client/family in decision mak-
ing for clinical practice). A few indicators were assessed 
through interviews of patients and their families (e.g., 
education about the home care plan). </p>

<p>3.4. Ethical Considerations </p>

<p>This study was approved by the ethics committee of 
Tehran university of medical sciences (approval number: 
92/S/130/1422) on September 28, 2013. The research objec-
tives were explained to all nurses participating in the 
study, and written informed consent was obtained. All 
participants were aware that they would be observed for 
some time but they were not informed about the exact 
time of the audit. All participants were also assured that 
their anonymity would be protected and their personal 
information would be kept confidential. </p>

<p>3.5. Data Analysis </p>

<p>Data were analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13</rs>. The Kol-
mogorov-Smirnov test was used to determine whether 
the quantitative variables were normally distributed. 
Descriptive statistics (frequencies, percentages, means, 
and standard deviations) were calculated for compliance 
with quality indicators. Pearson correlation analysis was 
conducted to examine the relationship between nurses' 
compliance with auditing indicators and their age and 
work experience. Independent-samples t-tests were used 
to compare the mean compliance scores of nurses by di-
chotomous demographic variables. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>The majority of nurses (~ 65%) worked in rotational 
shifts. About 70% had 5 -10 years of experience. Further, 
56% were non-permanently employed and almost 96% 
had a BSc in nursing. The rate of compliance with nurs-
ing process indicators was 79.71 ± 0.87, confirming that </p>

<p>Poortaghi S et al. </p>



<p>Nurs Midwifery Stud. 2015;4(3):e30181 </p>

<p>the majority of nursing care was carried out based on the 
nursing process. A detailed analysis of the compliance 
rate is presented in Table 1. 
The overall compliance score did not significantly dif-
fer by gender (t = -1.07, P = 0.285), nor did domain mean 
compliance scores, except that male nurses scored sig-
nificantly higher on the diagnosis domain (t = -2.25, P = 
0.030). However, mean overall compliance scores signifi-
cantly differed between nurses with a BSc and those with 
an MSc (P = 0.04). This difference was also found in the </p>

<p>mean compliance scores for three domains: diagnosis (P 
= .001), implementation (P = 0.02), and evaluation (P = 
0.01) (Table 2). 
In addition, the overall mean score did not significantly 
differ between nurses with permanent and non-perma-
nent employment (t = 0.123, P = 0.42). However, overall 
compliance scores were correlated with age (r = 0.26, P 
= 0.001) and work experience (r = 0.273, P = 0.001). Table 
3 presents the detailed data on the participants' compli-
ance with the audit items. </p>

<p>Table 1. Compliance Rate With Nursing Process Indicators </p>

<p>Steps 
N 
Minimum 
Maximum 
Values a </p>

<p>Assessment 
300 
50.00 
100.00 
88.13 ± 0.82 </p>

<p>Diagnosis 
300 
43.75 
100.00 
83.86 ± 1.88 </p>

<p>Plan 
300 
66.67 
100.00 
76.33 ± 2.13 </p>

<p>Implementation 
300 
62.50 
100.00 
69.92 ± 0.87 </p>

<p>Evaluation 
300 
66.67 
100.00 
80.33 ± 1.49 </p>

<p>Total 
300 
72.50 
100.00 
79.71 ± 0.87 </p>

<p>a Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>Table 2. Independent-Samples T-Test for Education Level </p>

<p>Education 
Number 
Compliance Rate a 
t 
95% CI 
P (2-Tailed) </p>

<p>Lower 
Upper </p>

<p>Assessment </p>

<p>BSc 
289 
88.09 ± 0.83 
-0.22 
-9.59 
-7.60 
0.820 </p>

<p>MSc 
11 
89.09 ± 3.92 </p>

<p>Diagnosis </p>

<p>BSc 
289 
83.32 ± 1.94 
-5.58 
-20.22 
-9.49 
0.001 </p>

<p>MSc 
11 
98.81 ± 1.81 </p>

<p>Plan </p>

<p>BSc 
289 
76.47 ± 2.17 
0.32 
-18.62 
26.10 
0.74 </p>

<p>MSc 
11 
72.27 ± 11.12 </p>

<p>Implementation </p>

<p>BS 
289 
59.74 ± 5.02 
2.29 
1.49 
19.65 
0.02 </p>

<p>MSc 
11 
70.31 ± 0.87 </p>

<p>Evaluation </p>

<p>BSc 
289 
81.08 ± 1.51 
2.60 
4.98 
35.96 
0.010 </p>

<p>MSc 
11 
60.60 ± 6.46 </p>

<p>Total </p>

<p>BSc 
289 
79.85 ± 0.89 
0.81 
-5.40 
12.98 
0.041 </p>

<p>MSc 
11 
76.06 ± 4.03 </p>

<p>a Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>Poortaghi S et al. </p>

<p>Nurs Midwifery Stud. 2015;4(3):e30181 </p>

<p>
Table 3. Number (Percentage) of Participants With Compliance Scores in Each Category of the Care Quality Indicators a,b </p>

<p>Indicator 
Score </p>

<p>0 
50 
100 </p>

<p>Assessment </p>

<p>Comprehensive nursing assessment of the patient during the first 24 hours of admission 
22 (7.3) 
N/A 
278 (92.7) </p>

<p>Collection and prioritization of data using appropriate techniques, in accordance with patient 
safety and needs </p>

<p>30 (10) 
75 (25) 
195 (65) </p>

<p>Consulting the patient and family/friends (if needed) in data collection 
21 (7) 
N/A 
279 (93) </p>

<p>Re-assessment in case there is any change in the patient's health-related behavior 
39 (13) 
N/A 
261 (87) </p>

<p>Recording and reporting assessment findings in the appropriate form correctly 
15 (5) 
27 (9) 
258 (86) </p>

<p>Diagnosis and Outcome Determination </p>

<p>Extracting a nursing diagnosis from the data by using critical thinking and reasoning skills and 
previous experience </p>

<p>33 (11) 
N/A 
267 (89) </p>

<p>Prioritizing diagnosis based on the interpretation of available data and the complexity and 
severity of a patient's condition </p>

<p>46 (15.3) 
N/A 
254 (84.7) </p>

<p>Extracting and recording expected outcomes from diagnosis 
44 (14.7) 
N/A 
256 (85.3) </p>

<p>Estimating time to reach the target 
54 (18) 
N/A 
246 (82) </p>

<p>Collaborating with families and team members to determine treatment, protection, 
rehabilitation, and palliative outcomes </p>

<p>65 (21.7) 
N/A 
235 (78.3) </p>

<p>Planning </p>

<p>Designing a care plan based on the needs and personal circumstances of patients, assessment 
results, and evidence </p>

<p>57 (19) 
N/A 
243 (81) </p>

<p>Designing and documenting a care plan in collaboration with patients, families, and other 
health care members </p>

<p>59 (19.7) 
N/A 
241 (80.3) </p>

<p>Adjusting daily care according to the patient's condition 
64 (21.3) 
N/A 
236 (78.7) </p>

<p>Designing a discharge care plan to meet the need for follow-up after discharge 
53 (17.7) 
63 (21) 
184 (61.3) </p>

<p>Documenting the care plan in a reliable, understandable way that is accessible to all members of 
the healthcare team, to minimize the possibility of errors </p>

<p>56 (18.7) 
69 (23) 
175 (58.3) </p>

<p>Implementation </p>

<p>Implementing interventions based on the care plan 
57 (19) 
63 (21) 
180 (60) </p>

<p>Implementing interventions in line with the policies and procedures of the treatment center 
and by using existing guidelines and instructions </p>

<p>84 (28) 
N/A 
216 (72) </p>

<p>Collaborating with other healthcare team members to implement the care plan 
98 (32.7) 
N/A 
202 (67.3) </p>

<p>Before performing the clinical intervention, ensuring that the nurse has the necessary expertise 206 (68.7) 
28 (9.3) 
66 (22) </p>

<p>Getting help from the experts and competent colleagues in case of any doubts while performing 
any action or intervention </p>

<p>97 (32.3) 
N/A 
203 (67.7) </p>

<p>Collaborating with the client/family in decision making for clinical practice if necessary 
23 (7.7) 
N/A 
277 (92.3) </p>

<p>Recording actions in reliable way that is understandable to all members of the healthcare team 
63 (21) 
N/A 
237 (79) </p>

<p>Evaluation </p>

<p>Recording patient reaction (response) to the actions taken 
22 (7.3) 
42 (14) 
236 (78.7) </p>

<p>Evaluating the effectiveness of interventions/actions based on relevant outcomes 
56 (18.7) 
N/A 
244 (81.3) </p>

<p>Participating with patients, families, health care providers, and other team members in the 
evaluation process if required </p>

<p>78 (26) 
N/A 
222 (74) </p>

<p>a All data are presented as No. (%). 
b N/A (Not Applicable): these indicators have two modes (yes/no) scored 0 or 100 according to the hospital accreditation audit guide. </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>In the present study, an audit tool was developed and 
used to evaluate nursing activities in accordance with 
nursing process indicators. We also used a combination 
of interviews, observations, and document reviews to 
audit nurses' performance. Mykkanen et al. also audited 
nurse performance but mostly used nursing documenta-</p>

<p>tion as the only data source (7). However, consistent with 
the present study, Fernandez-Sola et al. used a combina-
tion of methods to collect data on implementation of the 
nursing process (11). 
In the present study, nurses obtained a relatively high 
score for compliance with the nursing process indica-</p>

<p>Poortaghi S et al. </p>



<p>Nurs Midwifery Stud. 2015;4(3):e30181 </p>

<p>tors, especially in the domains of assessment, diagnosis, 
and evaluation. Our findings are consistent with those of 
Rivas et al., who investigated the implementation of the 
nursing process in primary healthcare and reported that 
using the nursing process can improve the quality of care 
and people's health (12). Training nurses on the nursing 
process and encouraging them to implement it can sig-
nificantly improve the quality of nursing care (5, 13). 
In the present study, the assessment and diagnosis do-
mains obtained the highest mean scores. This is some-
what consistent with a previous study by Sorensen, where 
assessment and care planning were introduced as the 
main indicators of healthcare system accreditation (3). 
However, Adib-Hajbaghery and Safa investigated nurses' 
evaluation of their use and mastery of health assessment 
skills and reported that nurses use these skills below the 
desired level (14). Nurses' adherence to the nursing pro-
cess differs across settings. Although the nursing culture 
differs across hospitals, previous findings may have been 
influenced by managerial factors or the instruments 
used. However, Munroe et al. found that using a frame-
work for assessment by nurses improved clinical practice 
and patient care outcomes (4). 
The present analysis showed that nurses' experience 
and age had significant positive correlations with imple-
mentation of care indicators. This suggests that nurses 
with more clinical experience are more likely to use the 
nursing process model to provide care and are more com-
mitted to it. This differs from Perez Rivas et al.'s findings 
that younger nurses had better adherence to the nursing 
process than older nurses did (12). In contrast, Akbari Kaji 
found that neither age nor experience was significantly 
associated with commitment to the nursing process (13). 
We did not find a significant association between level 
of education and compliance with the nursing process. 
This is consistent with the findings of Rivas et al. and Ak-
bari Kaji (12, 13). 
Overall, our results showed that nurses' compliance 
with the nursing process is favorable. Implementation 
of the nursing process translates a systematic approach 
into nursing practice. Implementation would not only 
result in quality services but also would improve nurses' 
professional prestige and both patient and nurse satisfac-
tion. Thus, it seems not only necessary to retrain nurses 
through continuing education but also to insist that this 
model be implemented in practice. 
In the present study, the audit sought to have an optimis-
tic view in scoring the nurses' activities. We performed 
the audit only in general units. Our findings might have 
differed if we audit specialized units such as the ICU or 
CCU. Hence, the study should be replicated in specialized 
units. The audit instrument developed should be imple-
mented in different settings. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank the administration and staff of Tehran Univer-</p>

<p>sity of Medical Sciences for their support as well as all of 
the participants. </p>

<p>Authors' Contributions </p>

<p>Conception and design: Sarieh Poortaghi, Mahvash 
Salsali, Abbas Ebadi, and Zahra Rahnavard. Analysis and 
interpretation of the data: Poortaghi and Abbas Ebadi. 
Data collection: Sarieh Poortaghi, Farzaneh Maleki, and 
Zahra Rahnavard. Writing the article: Sarieh Poortaghi, 
Mahvash Salsali, Abbas Ebadi, Farzaneh Maleki, and Zah-
ra Rahnavard. Critical revision of the article: Mahvash 
Salsali, Abbas Ebadi, and Farzaneh Maleki. Final approval 
of the article: Sarieh Poortaghi, Mahvash Salsali, Abbas 
Ebadi, Farzaneh Maleki, and Zahra Rahnavard. Statistical 
analysis: Sarieh Poortaghi and Abbas Ebadi. </p>

<p>Financial Disclosure </p>

<p>This study is part of a PhD dissertation and was con-
ducted with financial support from Tehran university of 
medical sciences. </p>

<p>Funding/Support </p>

<p>This work was supported by the research deputy of Teh-
ran university of medical sciences. </p>



<p>Poortaghi S et al. </p>

<p>Nurs Midwifery Stud. 2015;4(3):e30181 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>