<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4878562" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Various organs that are adversely affected by aging exhibit 
structural changes and are also prone to disease. Thus, disor-
ders of the colon, such as constipation, are more prevalent with 
age (1,2). However, the majority of studies regarding the disrup-
tion of colonic motility have been reported in animals (3). 
Therefore, it is unclear whether the increased prevalence of 
constipation with age in humans is due to confounding factors 
or age-associated abnormalities in the nerves and muscles of 
the colon. 
Neurodegeneration in the enteric nervous system (ENS) 
has been shown to occur with age (4). However, compared 
with the central nervous system (CNS), little is known about 
age-associated changes in the ENS. In the present study, a 
possible underlying mechanism of the aging process in the 
intestinal system was investigated. 
In the CNS, Syn has been linked with the regulation of 
neuronal plasticity, neurotransmission and presynaptic vesicle 
dynamics (5-7). Syn is considered to be a suitable marker for 
identifying the dystrophic features in the ENS of the colon (8). 
Furthermore, fibril formation of Syn results in insoluble 
intracellular aggregates. These aggregates are involved in 
synucleinopathies, which occur predominantly in the elderly 
human brain (9,10). A previous report has demonstrated that 
certain autonomic axons in the wall of the intestinal tract are 
immunopositive for wild-type and phosphorylated Syn (8). 
However, due to the limitation in collecting tissue samples 
from particularly young and elderly subjects, to the best of our 
knowledge, there have been no reports on whether a correla-
tion exists between the expression of Syn and age-associated 
colonic dysfunction. 
Syn has been shown to be phosphorylated (11) or nitrated 
(N) (12) at different residue sites. Previous studies have 
identified that an oligomer-promoting effect of serine 129 
phosphorylation is key in Syn neurotoxicity and inclusion 
formation (13). Furthermore, studies have shown that N-Syn 
is prone to oligomerization (14) and promotes dopaminergic 
loss of neurons in culture (14,15). Therefore, the present study 
hypothesizes that Syn, as well as N-Syn, may participate in 
age-associated colonic neurodegeneration. In addition, it was </p>

<p>Post-translational modifications of α-synuclein contribute 
to neurodegeneration in the colon of elderly individuals </p>

<p>QI XUAN 
1 , YU-XIAN ZHANG </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, DIAN-GANG LIU 
3 , PIU CHAN 
4 , SHENG-LI XU 
4 and YE-QING CUI </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Nutrition, Xuanwu Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing 100053; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Internal Medicine, Beijing Moslem Hospital, Beijing 100054; 
3 Department of General Surgery, Xuanwu Hospital, Capital Medical University; 
4 Department of Neurobiology, Institute of Geriatrics of Beijing, Xuanwu Hospital, Capital Medical University, </p>

<p>Key Laboratory for Neurodegenerative Disease of Ministry of Education, Beijing 100053, P.R. China </p>

<p>Received April 14, 2015; Accepted February 23, 2016 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/mmr.2016.5166 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Professor Dian-Gang Liu, Department of </p>

<p>General Surgery, Xuanwu Hospital, Capital Medical University, 
45 Changchun Street, Beijing 100053, P.R. China 
E-mail: liudiangang@gmail.com </p>

<p>Key words: α-synuclein, nitration, colon, human </p>

<p>XUAN et al: α-SYNUCLEIN MODIFICATIONS IN THE COLON OF THE ELDERLY </p>



<p>hypothesized that neurodegeneration of Syn and N-Syn causes 
functional movement disorders, which commonly occur in 
elderly individuals. In the current study, Syn and its post-trans-
lational modifications (PTMs) were investigated in colonic 
tissue samples obtained from individuals of different ages to 
determine which types are specific to the colon. Furthermore, 
the study aimed to determine whether these PTMs correlate 
with neurodegeneration during normal aging. Thus, these 
results may provide information on the processes underlying 
normal aging, which may in turn be involved in pathological 
aging. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Subjects. Following approval by the local research ethics 
committee and obtaining written informed consent, biopsies 
(at full thickness) were obtained from the normal margin 
(≥5 cm away from the tumor) of 33 adult colorectal cancer 
patients during resection. The biopsies were collected between 
September 2009 and February 2010 at Xuanwi Hospital, 
Capital Medical University (Beijing, China) from the following 
three groups: Young individuals (n=12; 9 men, 3 women) mean 
age, 34.08±5.12 years; middle-aged individuals (n=10; 7 men, 
3 women) mean age, 51.80±3.52 years; and elderly individuals 
(n=11; 5 men, 6 women) mean age 75.82 ± 7.70 years. To 
avoid regional differences in neuron density, all biopsies were 
obtained from the ascending colon. No tumor was present in 
the sections examined. 
Samples were immediately fixed in 10% neutral-buffered 
formalin (OriGene Technologies, Inc., Beijing, China) for 
24 h. For conventional histology, 5-µm thick paraffin (OriGene 
Technologies, Inc.) sections were prepared for hematoxylin 
and eosin (OriGene Technologies, Inc.) staining and immuno-
histochemical studies. The study was approved by the ethics 
committee of Xuanwu Hospital, Capital Medical University 
(Beijing, China). Written informed consent was obtained from 
the patients. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry. Immunohistochemistry was 
performed on the tissue samples using the following primary 
antibodies: Mouse monoclonal anti-Syn 3D5 antibody 
(1:4,000;cat. no. sc-69977; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc., 
Dallas, TX, USA), mouse monoclonal anti-N-Syn anti-
body (1:500; cat. no. sc-32279; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, 
Inc.), and mouse monoclonal anti-NF antibody (1:500; 
cat. no. MAB-0135; Maxim Biotech, Inc., Rockville, MD, 
USA), as previously described (16). The Syn antibody recog-
nizes amino acids 115-121 of human Syn (15,17). 
Immunostaining was conducted using a peroxidase-based 
visualization kit (UltraSensitiveTM SP IHC kit; Maxim 
Biotech, Inc.) according to the manufacturer's instructions 
and 3,3'-diaminobenzidine tetrahydrochloride was used 
as the chromogen. The slides were counterstained with 
Mayer's hematoxylin (OriGene Technologies, Inc.) for 5 sec, 
dehydrated and mounted. The slides were dehydrated with 
sequential ethanol washes of 1 min each starting with 75%, 
followed by 80% and finishing with a 100% ethanol (Sangon 
Biotech Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China). Next, the cover slips were 
mounted on slides with neutral gums (Biogot Technology Co., 
Ltd., Shanghai, China). To account for nonspecific staining, </p>

<p>the sections were subjected to peptides (in normal goat 
serum; OriGene Technologies, Inc.), which blocked polyclonal 
antibody binding, or the sections were incubated without the 
primary antibodies. </p>

<p>Double immunofluorescence. Double-label immunofluores-
cence was used to determine the specific type of Syn present 
in the cells. Sections from an elderly individual were incubated 
with rabbit anti-Syn polyclonal antibody (15) and mouse mono-
clonal anti-NF antibody (1:500), mouse monoclonal anti-S100 
protein antibody (1:500; cat. no. MAB-0697; Maxim Biotech, 
Inc.) or mouse monoclonal anti-N-Syn antibody (1:500) at 4˚C, 
overnight. 
Sections were then incubated for 2 h (at room temperature) 
with biotinylated horse anti-mouse immunoglobulin (Ig) G 
(1:500; cat no. PK-4002; ABC kits; Vector Laboratories, Inc., 
Burlingame, CA, USA), followed by Cy3-conjugated goat 
anti-horse IgG (1:200; Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) 
and fluorescein isothiocyanate-conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG 
(1:200; cat no. ZLI-9021; OriGene Technologies, Inc., China). 
All staining experiments were performed with the 
appropriate positive and negative controls. A series of slides 
containing tissues with a previously established positive reac-
tion with the primary antibodies were used as the positive 
control. To account for nonspecific staining, sections incubated 
without the primary antibody were used as the negative control. 
Sections were analyzed by fluorescence microscopy (Olympus 
BX51; Olympus Corporation, Tokyo, Japan). Colocalization 
of staining was visualized using image analysis software 
(<rs id="software-1" type="software">Image Pro Plus</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">5.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Media Cybernetics, Inc</rs>., Rockville, MD, 
USA) by applying the Boolean operator 'AND'. This operator 
combined individual unmixed images into a novel image that 
consisted solely of colocalized (double-stained) pixels, thus 
representing only double-stained cells (yellow). The relative 
intensities of NF, S-100, Syn, N-Syn within individual cells 
were determined by <rs type="software">Image Pro Plus</rs> software by measuring 
the integral optical densities (IOD) of 80-100 cells that were 
sampled from each subject randomly (16)   Data analysis. All slides were reviewed blindly by two pathol-
ogists. Immunopositive cells were counted on 10 well-stained, 
randomly selected, microscopic fields at x40 magnification 
(Olympus BX51) for each region of interest. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. All data are expressed as the mean ± stan-
dard deviation. The Kruskal-Wallis test by ranks followed by the 
Mann-Whitney test was used to rank the Syn-immunoreactivity 
data. One-way analysis of variance followed by the 
Student-Newman-Keuls test was used for the comparisons 
of NF-positive neurons. Pearson correlations/Spearman's 
rank order correlation was used to evaluate the correlations 
between the neuronal counts and Syn-immunoreactivity cell 
numbers. Data were analyzed with <rs id="software-3" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">20.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">IBM SPSS</rs>, Armonk, NY, USA). P&lt;0.05 was considered to indicate 
a statistically significant difference. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Age-associated neurodegeneration. In young individuals, 
the number of NF-positive neurons in the submucosal plexus </p>

<p>MOLECULAR MEDICINE REPORTS 13: 5077-5083, 2016 </p>



<p>Table I. IODs for each of the groups. </p>

<p>IODs 
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
Region 
Young, n=12 
Middle-aged, n=10 
Elderly, n=11 </p>

<p>NF 
Mucosa 
510.08±6.30 
510.70±7.77 
494.45±12.21 
Submucosa 
1169.67±11.46 
1060.10±24.30 
653.64±29.86 </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>S100 
Mucosa 
1542.08±33.60 
1548.30±42.67 
1658±48.67 
Submucosa 
1569.92±30.95 
1615.00±43.67 
1687.63±51.34 </p>

<p>Syn 
Mucosa 
951.92±45.46 
1101.10±16.00 
1265.45±10.96 </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>Submucosa 
842.83±42.18 
1023.10±21.42 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1083.45±19.67 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>N-Syn 
Mucosa 
212.08±39.32 
396.00±14.16 
762.73±19.62 </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>Submucosa 
79.67±15.06 
129.70±3.78 
216.45±13.37 </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>Syn/NF 
Mucosa 
300.92±12.44 
312.30±7.70 
342.45±10.65 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Submucosa 
114.75±2.83 
120.70±2.51 
127.91±1.77 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Syn/S100 
Mucosa 
481.08±33.15 
658.90±23.33 
874.63±18.36 </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>Submucosa 
331.58±35.38 
386.70±21.61 
402.36±26.25 </p>

<p>N-Syn/NF 
Mucosa 
22.00±1.34 
27.80±1.25 
41.45±3.19 </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>Submucosa 
20.42±1.34 
23.40±1.04 
25.18±1.34 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>N-Syn/S100 
Mucosa 
279.42±22.39 
349.70±15.24 
712.18±16.72 </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>Submucosa 
152.25±14.17 
169.90±11.91 
205.73±10.02 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. young; 
b P&lt;0.05 vs. middle-aged. All values are presented as the mean ± standard deviation. Young, 34.08±5.12 years; middle-aged, 
51.80±3.52 years; elderly, 75.82±7.70 years. IOD, integral optical density; NF, neurofilament; Syn, α-synuclein 3D5; N-Syn, nitrated Syn. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Immunohistochemical staining of neurofilament (brown). Age-associated changes in the submucosal plexus and myenteric plexus in the young, 
middle-aged and elderly groups. The number of neurons was reduced in the elderly group. Magnification, x200. </p>

<p>XUAN et al: α-SYNUCLEIN MODIFICATIONS IN THE COLON OF THE ELDERLY </p>



<p>was 4.63±0.82. These neurons were significantly decreased 
in elderly individuals (2.96±1.77; P&lt;0.01). A loss of 36.07% 
of enteric neurons in the submucosal plexus was observed in 
individuals &gt;65 years when compared with the young indi-
viduals (Fig. 1, top panel). </p>

<p>In the myenteric plexus, the number of NF-positive 
neurons in young individuals was 11.82±3.10. These neurons 
were significantly reduced in the elderly group (4.96±1.59; 
P&lt;0.01) compared with the young and middle-aged groups 
(10.98±2.92). The number of NF-positive neurons in the </p>

<p>Figure 3. Syn inclusions (green) in the submucosa of individuals (top panel). Labeling with N-Syn (green) reveals the presence of pathological inclusions in 
the submucosal plexus (bottom panel). The majority of these structures are immunoreactive for the neuronal marker, NF (red). Submucosal co-localization 
of NF and Syn, and NF and N-Syn (yellow). N-Syn immunoreactivity was not present in the young individuals. The N-Syn first appears in the muscle layer 
and myenteric layer of individuals &gt;50-years-old. Its immunoreactivity to N-Syn increases with age. Immunoreactivity for N-Syn was only present in the 
cytoplasm. Cy3 and fluorescein isothiocyanate were used as stain. Magnification, x200. Syn, α-synuclein; N-Syn, nitrated-Syn; NF, neurofilament. </p>

<p>Figure 2. An immunoperoxidase labeling method was performed to visualize α-synuclein labeled profiles. Syn-positive cells (brown) are located in all 
five layers: the mucosa, submucosa, muscle (inner circular and outer longitudinal), and myenteric plexus, in the young, middle-aged and elderly groups. 
Immunoreactivity for Syn occurs in the nucleus, cytoplasm and neuronal axons. The number of cells that were immunoreactive for Syn was reduced in the 
young and middle-aged groups, but increased in the elderly individuals. Magnification, x200. Syn, α-synuclein. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR MEDICINE REPORTS 13: 5077-5083, 2016 </p>



<p>elderly group was reduced by 58.04% when compared with 
the young group (Fig. 1, bottom panel). </p>

<p>Age-associated accumulation of Syn. In the young, middle-aged, 
and elderly groups, immunoreactivity for Syn was observed in 
all five layers: The mucosa, submucosa, inner circular muscle, 
myenteric plexus, and outer longitudinal muscle (Fig. 2). As the 
expression profile in the inner circular muscle and outer longi-
tudinal muscle was similar, these two groups were combined 
and the cell number was calculated. Double-staining indicated 
that the positively-stained cells were neurons (Fig. 3) or glial 
cells (Fig. 4). Syn was identified in the nucleus, cytoplasm and 
axons (Fig. 3). In young individuals, axons immunoreactive for 
Syn were typically smooth in appearance (Fig. 3). However, 
in the elderly group, axons were densely distributed with a 
swollen appearance along their length (Fig. 3). Furthermore, 
Syn-positive terminals surrounded the colonic glands and 
neurons in the ganglia. The number of Syn-positive cells was 
low in the young (30.50±5.99) and middle-aged (51.00±10.22) 
groups; however, was significantly greater (120.36±31.10; 
P&lt;0.05) in the elderly individuals (Fig. 2). These immunoreac-
tive cells were regionally distributed, with 12.01, 10.13, 56.89, 
and 20.91% located in the mucosa, submucosa, muscle and 
myenteric plexus, respectively. The Spearman's rank order 
correlation analysis indicated a negative correlation between the 
number of submucosa neurons and wild-type Syn in the mucosa 
(r=-0.761) and submucosa (r=-0.713). A negative correlation 
was also identified between the number of myenteric plexus 
neurons and wild-type Syn in the muscle layer (r=-0.742) and 
the myenteric plexus (r=-0.641). Quantitative intensity measure-
ments indicated that the IOD of Syn intensity was significantly 
different between the three age groups (P&lt;0.05). It was higher in 
the elderly group compared with the young group, in the mucosa 
and in the submucosa (Table I). </p>

<p>Age-associated accumulation of N-Syn. Immunoreactivity 
was not present in the majority of the young individuals. Weak 
immunoreactivity for N-Syn was apparent in the muscle layer 
and myenteric layer in individuals aged &gt;50 years (Figs. 3 
and 4). Its presence then increased from young to middle-aged 
to elderly. N-Syn-positive cells were only present in the cyto-
plasm (Figs. 3 and 4). 
The rate of nitration of Syn in elderly subjects was signifi-
cantly higher (36%) when compared with that of the young 
individuals (5%; P&lt;0.05). In 28 out of the 33 subjects (all ages) 
the submucosa was identified to be the most affected region. 
This was followed by the mucosa, with 26 individuals. The 
other regions were found to be less affected. In the affected 
individuals, 48.37% of immunoreactive cells were distributed 
within the mucosa and 19.07% within the submucosa, while 
19.81% was located in the muscle and 12.75% in the myenteric 
plexus N-Syn immunoreactive intensity was increased in the 
elderly group, in the mucosa and in the submucosa. In young 
and middle-aged individuals, there was a significant increase in 
the IOD of N-Syn in the elderly individuals (P&lt;0.05) (Table I). 
The spearman's rank order correlation analysis indicated a 
negative correlation between the number of submucosa neurons 
and N-Syn in the mucosa (r=-0.816) and in the submucosa 
(r=-0.832). A negative correlation was also identified between 
the number of myenteric plexus neurons and N-Syn in the 
muscle layer (r=-0.601) and in the myenteric plexus (r=-0.611). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Colonic function has been shown to significantly deteriorate in 
individuals aged ≥65 years (18). In this age group, the internal 
anal sphincter pressure and pelvic muscle strength is reduced. 
Changes in rectal sensitivity and anal function have also been 
observed in this group (19). Neurodegeneration of the ENS </p>

<p>Figure 4. Syn inclusions (green) in the submucosa of individuals (top panel). Regional specificity of glial cells co-reactive (yellow) with S100 (red) and Syn 
(green) or N-Syn (green). N-Syn immunoreactivity was not present in the young individuals (bottom panel). N-Syn first appears in the muscle layer and 
myenteric layer of individuals aged &gt;50 years. Its immunoreactivity increases with age. Immunoreactivity for N-Syn was only present in the cytoplasm. 
Magnification, x200. Syn, α-synuclein; N-Syn, nitrated-Syn; NF, neurofilament. </p>

<p>XUAN et al: α-SYNUCLEIN MODIFICATIONS IN THE COLON OF THE ELDERLY </p>



<p>may be the key to these functional changes that are observed 
with advancing age. Studies have demonstrated that deficits 
in intestinal function are linked with age-associated loss of 
enteric neurons in rats (20), guinea pigs (21) and humans (22). 
Previous reports indicated that age-associated cell loss in 
the myenteric plexus occurs exclusively in the cholinergic 
(i.e. excitatory) enteric neurons, but not in nitrergic (i.e. inhibi-
tory) neurons (20). However, the majority of studies have not 
investigated the underlying mechanisms of neuronal vulnera-
bility with increasing age. The present study has demonstrated 
age-associated loss of submucosal and myenteric neurons in 
the ascending colon. In addition, the expression pattern of 
wild-type Syn and its PTMs were investigated to elucidate the 
pathogenesis of neurodegeneration. 
In the present study, the expression of wild-type Syn was 
found to be different when compared with its PTM, nitration. 
Wild-type Syn-positive cells were observed in all five layers 
of the colonic tissue sample. Whereas, N-Syn was found in 
only the mucosa and submucosa in the majority of the young 
patients, and its presence in the muscle and myenteric plexus 
did not occur until middle age. Wild-type Syn was present in the 
nucleus, cytoplasm and axons, while N-Syn was only present in 
the cytoplasm. In the cells that were Syn-positive the wildtype 
form was more prevalent than N-Syn. Immunofluorescence 
double-staining revealed that N-Syn was only expressed in 
cells with wild-type Syn. 
Previous studies have shown that Syn increased in 
the gastrointestinal (GI) tract of patients with Parkinson's 
disease (8,23). These upregulated forms have also been shown 
in elderly rats (24). However, to the best of our knowledge, 
they have not been studied in the human colon of elderly 
humans. Although N-Syn has been thoroughly investigated 
in the CNS (15,25), it has not yet been investigated in the GI 
tract. In the present study, it was demonstrated that a small 
quantity of Syn precedes nitration. N-Syn initially appeared 
in individuals that were their late thirties or older. Although 
the cells that were N-Syn-positive were limited in number, 
they were found to be significantly different between the age 
groups. The elderly subjects exhibited the highest frequency 
of nitration. This result was consistent with that of a previous 
study in which age-associated hyper-inflammatory responses 
enhanced Syn nitration in the rat brain (26). 
The present results indicated that Syn and N-Syn were 
significantly greater in the elderly individuals than in the 
younger individuals (Table I). Furthermore, the results 
suggest that during the aging process, nitration of Syn 
initially occurs in the mucosa and submucosa, and subse-
quently in the muscle and myenteric plexus. The common 
characteristic of the various PTM forms of Syn in the 
mucosa was a predominant distribution in the surface layer. 
This layer is in closer contact with environmental toxins in 
the colon lumina. Little or no Syn was observed in the deep 
mucosa. In the elderly group, the staining density intensi-
fied, and axons were swollen, particularly in the wild-type 
Syn. The dendrites became shorter, thicker and twisted. A 
previous study identified that pathological accumulation of 
Syn in neurons may hinder axonal-stromal transport due to 
disturbances in nerve conduction (27). Furthermore, previous 
reports suggest that nerve terminal degeneration may 
precede degeneration of ganglia neurons or even cell death </p>

<p>during these pathological processes (28). Studies have shown 
a significant age-associated loss of submucosal intrinsic 
sensory neurons in the rat distal colon (2,3). Another report 
has suggested that a reduced input to enteric microcircuits 
may result in reduced motility (29). 
Environmental-mediated induction of metabolized 
proteins and reactive oxygen species have been shown to be 
involved in neurodegeneration (30). Based on the results of 
the current study, regarding the temporal and spatial patterns 
of Syn in colonic tissue, it was proposed that age-associated 
infiltration of Syn and its PTM forms through the damaged 
mucosal barrier of the tract allows their access to axons. This 
effect may be due to the marked neuronal innervation in the 
mucosa (31). Reactive oxygen species have been shown to 
facilitate phosphorylation (32,33) and nitration (34), stabilize 
Syn protofibrils and delay their fibrillar formation (35). The 
accumulation of Syn may reduce mitochondrial Complex I 
activity, thus interfering with its function (36), it may also 
lead to further damage from increased oxidative stress and 
free radicals, thereby causing death of neurons (37). Thus, the 
environmental toxins may specifically affect those neurons 
that innervate the mucosa or submucosa, as the terminals of 
these neurons are located in the vicinity of the compromised 
epithelium. In addition, Syn may be continuously transmitted 
from one neural system to another via endocytosis (38); this 
effect may result in the accumulation of Syn, thereby causing 
neurodegeneration. In the elderly population, if the threshold 
of neuronal death in the colon is reached, colonic dysmotility 
and decreased secretory activity may lead to the clinical 
response of constipation. A previous study has indicated that 
the level of accumulated Syn during constipation is markedly 
higher when compared with that of a control group (25). 
Additionally, the current results suggest that neuropathies 
in the ENS may occur in healthy adults. Furthermore, Syn 
and its aggregated PTM forms in the ENS, including its 
peripheral projections, may also be involved in these patho-
logical processes. 
In conclusion, the present findings may facilitate with 
understanding the etiology of aging-mediated dysmotility. 
The current study demonstrates the accumulation of Syn and 
N-Syn in the colonic tissue during aging, this may be linked 
to colonic neuronal degeneration during normal aging, which 
may cause functional deficits. Further research is warranted 
to identify whether the expression of Syn and its nitrated form 
are involved in the pathogenesis of aging-associated disorders, 
including slow transit constipation or inflammatory bowel 
disease. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The present study was supported by grants, awarded to Professor 
Dian-Gang Liu, from the National Natural Science Foundation 
of China (grant no. 81170408), the China Postdoctoral Science 
Special Foundation (grant no. 2013T60386), and the China 
Postdoctoral Science Foundation (grant no. 2012M510094). </p>



<p>MOLECULAR MEDICINE REPORTS 13: 5077-5083, 2016 </p>





</text></tei>