<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4801153" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>O r I g I n a l r e s e a r C h </p>

<p>open access to scientific and medical research </p>

<p>Open access Full Text article </p>

<p>503 </p>

<p>http://dx.Background: Computed tomography (CT) phenotypic characterization helps in understanding 
the clinical diversity of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) patients, but its clinical 
relevance and its relationship with functional features are not clarified. Volumetric capnography 
(VC) uses the principle of gas washout and analyzes the pattern of CO 2 elimination as a function 
of expired volume. The main variables analyzed were end-tidal concentration of carbon dioxide 
(ETCO 2 ), Slope of phase 2 (Slp2), and Slope of phase 3 (Slp3) of capnogram, the curve which 
represents the total amount of CO 2 eliminated by the lungs during each breath. 
Objective: To investigate, in a group of patients with severe COPD, if the phenotypic analysis 
by CT could identify different subsets of patients, and if there was an association of CT findings 
and functional variables. 
Subjects and methods: Sixty-five patients with COPD Gold III-IV were admitted for 
clinical evaluation, high-resolution CT, and functional evaluation (spirometry, 6-minute walk 
test [6MWT], and VC). The presence and profusion of tomography findings were evaluated, 
and later, the patients were identified as having emphysema (EMP) or airway disease (AWD) 
phenotype. EMP and AWD groups were compared; tomography findings scores were evaluated 
versus spirometric, 6MWT, and VC variables. 
Results: Bronchiectasis was found in 33.8% and peribronchial thickening in 69.2% of the 
65 patients. Structural findings of airways had no significant correlation with spirometric 
variables. Air trapping and EMP were strongly correlated with VC variables, but in opposite 
directions. There was some overlap between the EMP and AWD groups, but EMP patients had 
signicantly lower body mass index, worse obstruction, and shorter walked distance on 6MWT. 
Concerning VC, EMP patients had signicantly lower ETCO2, Slp2 and Slp3. Increases in Slp3 
characterize heterogeneous involvement of the distal air spaces, as in AWD. 
Conclusion: Visual assessment and phenotyping of CT in COPD patients is feasible and may 
help identify functional and clinically different subsets of patients. VC may provide useful 
information about the heterogeneous involvement of lung structures in COPD. 
Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is currently defined as a lung disease 
characterized by airflow limitation that is not fully reversible, which is usually progres-
sive and associated with an inflammatory response of the lungs to noxious particles or 
gases, according to the Global initiative for chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) 
guidelines. 
1 The airflow obstruction is usually associated with respiratory symptoms 
such as chronic cough, dyspnea, and presence of sputum. This is a preventable and </p>

<p>Correspondence: Mônica Corso Pereira 
Pneumology service, Department of 
Internal Medicine, school of Medical 
sciences, state University of Campinas 
(UnICaMP), Campinas, são Paulo 
13083970, Brazil 
email moncorso@gmail.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of COPD 
16 March 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>504 </p>

<p>da silva et al </p>

<p>treatable disease that has some systemic effects that interfere 
directly on the severity and prognosis. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Pathologically, COPD is characterized by involvement of 
large and medium, but especially, small airways, those with 
less than 2 mm in diameter. 
2 There is also involvement of the 
lung parenchyma and vasculature, which are most prominent 
findings when there is pulmonary emphysema (EMP). The 
location of predominant structural lesions has a close rela-
tionship with functional manifestations, and this turns out to 
be a key point in the diagnosis of the different phenotypes of 
COPD. The involvement of the small airways, initially by 
inflammatory changes and then followed by fibrotic changes 
(constrictive bronchiolitis caused by scarring of the walls 
of the small airways), is a trademark of airflow limitation 
that occurs in chronic bronchitis. In EMP, it is accepted that 
the main cause of reduced airflow is the loss of lung elastic 
recoil due to reduction of elastic fibers, which occurs when 
the alveolar septa disappear. The relative importance of 
each of these components of the disease in each patient with 
COPD is not clear. 
COPD is a heterogeneous condition with multiple clinical 
and functional profiles. It consists of a number of different 
pathological processes, which are modified by varied host 
susceptibility. Forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV 1 ) 
is not enough to describe this heterogeneity, especially in 
severe COPD patients. But, there is as yet no clear alternative 
to characterize the many faces of COPD. 
High-resolution computed tomography (HRCT) of the 
chest helps determine which structures are more involved 
(airways or lung parenchyma) and to quantify the damage. 
Besides, some authors have been using the method to propose 
a tomography phenotyping of COPD. Quantitative assess-
ment of EMP by CT scanning has a good correlation with 
airflow obstruction. 
3-5 Objective measures of airway wall 
thickening also correlated well with lung function. 
5-7 Whether 
the presence of this specific lung structural abnormalities 
(EMP, airway wall thickening, and/or bronchiectasis) predict 
meaningful clinical outcome is not known. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Some authors compared CT visual assessment of COPD 
patients with quantitative analysis and several physiological 
parameters and found a good correlation. 
9 Besides, 
Kitaguchi et al 
10 used CT visual assessment to phenotype 
COPD patients, and this method allows the recognition 
of subsets of patients with clinical and functional distinct 
characteristics. 
By CT visual assessment, it is possible to establish 
which structural abnormalities prevail in one individual. 
To know how these abnormalities impact the ventilation </p>

<p>in severe COPD patients may provide some insight about 
physiopathologic aspects that are not yet clarified. 
Volumetric capnography (VC) is a technique which 
analyzes the pattern of CO 2 elimination as a function of 
expired volume. It produces a curve, the capnogram, which 
represents the total amount of CO 2 eliminated by the lungs 
during each breath. It has the same shape of the other gas 
elimination curves, with the advantage of being obtained with 
a gas which is normally produced in the body and eliminated 
by the lungs. 
11,12 The main variables analyzed were end-tidal 
concentration of carbon dioxide (ETCO 2 ), Slope of phase 
2 (Slp2), and Slope of phase 3 (Slp3) of capnogram. Slp2 
represents the rapid increase in CO 2 coming from short paths 
to alveoli; it comes immediately after the elimination of the 
air from the dead space. Slp3 is an important feature of gas 
washout curves and contains information about gas transport 
in the alveolated airways of the lung periphery. It varies in 
many pathological conditions of the lungs. </p>

<p>11-16 </p>

<p>The objectives of this study were to investigate if pheno-
typic analysis by CT visual evaluation could identify different 
subsets of patients (EMP or airway disease [AWD] pheno-
type) and if there was an association between CT findings 
and functional variables, especially that from VC. </p>

<p>Subjects and methods 
study design and subjects </p>

<p>We performed a cross-sectional, observational, and retro-
spective study on patients with COPD (GOLD stages III-IV) 
with a smoking history of at least 10 pack-years. All 
patients followed at the Pulmonary Diseases Service of the 
University of Campinas Hospital (UNICAMP Hospital), 
São Paulo, Brazil, between June 2011 and January 2014 
were considered for participation in the study (Figure 1). 
Exclusion criteria were: poor adherence or inability to 
perform the necessary tests; patients with other obstructive 
lung diseases or other causes of bronchiectasis as ciliary 
dyskinesia, cystic fibrosis, immune deficiencies, and 
tuberculosis sequelae. All patients were in a stable clinical 
condition and had not experienced respiratory exacerbations 
in the previous 4 weeks. UNICAMP Medical School's 
Research Ethics Committee approved the study (report 
number 768/2010). All patients signed their informed 
consent forms before participating in the study. 
Initially, we performed an evaluation of symptoms, physi-
cal examination, and assessment of the degree of dyspnea using 
the modified MRC scale. 
17 The Saint George's Respiratory 
Questionnaire (SGRQ) 
18 and the Airways Questionnaire 20 
(AQ20) 
19 were applied. The SGRQ evaluates the quality of </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>505 </p>

<p>COPD phenotypes on CT and correlation with lung function variables </p>

<p>life related to health in three domains (symptoms, activity, 
and impacts) divided into 76 items. The sum of the results of 
the three domains (general domain) is expressed as a percent-
age. The AQ20 consists of 20 questions (score of 0-20), the 
higher the score, the worse the perception of health status. 
Medical records were reviewed to check the frequency 
of exacerbations in the 3 years preceding the beginning 
of the survey. In a previously scheduled visit, pulmonary 
function tests (VC and spirometry) and the 6-minute walk 
test (6MWT) were performed. Subsequently a HRCT was 
scheduled. </p>

<p>Pulmonary function </p>

<p>A complete lung function test was carried out before and 
20 minutes after inhalation of 400 μg of salbutamol using 
a spirometer (EasyOne-PC 
® , NDD Medizintechnik AG, 
Zurich, Switzerland), and the values of forced vital capac-
ity (FVC), FEV 1 , and FEV 1 /FVC ratio were analyzed. The 
test was performed according to the American Thoracic 
Society guidelines, 
20 and reference values for the Brazilian 
population 
21,22,23 were used. FVC and FEV 1 were expressed 
as percent of the predicted value. 
VC was performed using a CO 2 SMOS Plus 8100 Dixtal/ 
Novametrix 
® (Respironics, Murrisville, PA, USA). The sub-
jects remained breathing tidal volume for 4 minutes. During 
this time, the variables were measured and data was stored in 
a computer with the <rs type="software">Analysis Plus</rs> 
® software. At the end of 
data collection, an offline sequence of the respiratory cycles 
of the subjects was selected to accommodate a variation 
of ,15% for expiratory tidal volume and of ,5% for ETCO 2 </p>

<p>tension. Respiratory cycles that had Slp2 and Slp3 equal 
to zero were excluded. The main variables analyzed were 
ETCO 2 , Slp2, Slp3, inspiratory time (T i ), expiratory time 
(T e ), and expiratory volume (V e ). Both slopes are given by 
the <rs type="software">Analysis Plus</rs> 
® software. An example of a capnogram, 
which represents the total amount of CO 2 eliminated by the 
lungs during each breath, can be seen in Figure 1. </p>

<p>six-minute walk test </p>

<p>All patients performed the 6MWT under supervision of the 
same technician according to the American Thoracic Soci-
ety guidelines. 
21 Baseline blood pressure and heart rate were 
measured, and oxygen saturation (SpO 2 ) was determined 
using a finger probe pulse oximeter (Onyx 9500, Nonin 
® , 
Nonin Medical, Inc., Plymouth, MN, USA). The pulse sig-
nal was carefully observed for at least 20 seconds, and the 
most frequent value displayed with a good pulse signal was 
chosen. SpO 2 was measured at rest, in the sixth minute (end 
of the test), and in the ninth minute (recovery). During the 
test, the patients were carefully observed to avoid danger-
ously exceeding their exercise limits. Desaturation was cal-
culated as follows: SpO 2 in the sixth minute -initial SpO 2 . 
The distance was measured in meters and also considered 
as a percentage of the reference values. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>hrCT imaging </p>

<p>The chest CT scans were performed by using a CT 64-channel 
multidetector (Toshiba </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, Toshiba, Tokyo, Japan) with volu-
metric acquisitions with reconstruction 1 mm thick, in high 
spatial resolution algorithm. The scans were performed in 
the supine position with the breath held at full inspiration, 
as well as in maximal expiration. 
The CT assessment was done in a structured chart modi-
fied by the authors from that proposed by Bhalla et al 
24 and 
Tulek et al. 
25 The scoring system proposed by Bhalla et al </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>for evaluating cystic fibrosis patients' CT scans assesses the 
degree and extent of bronchiectasis, mucus plug and peribron-
chial thickening, and the number of bronchial divisions that 
were involved. Abscesses, sacculations, bullae, EMP, areas 
of collapse, and consolidation were also recorded. This scor-
ing system was modified by the addition of an evaluation of 
mosaic perfusion. 
25 In our chart (Table 1), we did an adaptation 
in order to facilitate its use for clinicians: bronchiectasis, bron-
chial wall thickening, air trapping (expiration scan), mucoid 
plugs, tree-in-bud signal, bullae, and EMP were analyzed and 
scored in each lung lobe, so the score ranged from 0 to 77. 
Pulmonary artery/aorta (PA/Ao) ratio was also determined, 
measured at the pulmonary artery branch (#1 or .1). </p>

<p>Figure 1 Illustrative curves constructed with mean values of each group. 
Notes: (A) Control group (eTCO 2 =36 mmhg; slp3=7.3 mmhg/l; V e =693.2±245.9 
ml; (B) airways diseases group (eTCO 2 =39.0±6.7 mmhg; slp3=37.1±15.5 mmhg/l; 
V e =508.5 ml); (C) emphysema group (eTCO 2 =33.7±6.8 mmhg; slp3=28.6±12.7 
mmhg/l; V e =652.1 ml). Data from Veronez et al. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: eTCO 2 , end-tidal CO 2 ; slp3, slope of phase 3; V e , expired volume. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>506 </p>

<p>da silva et al </p>

<p>Two physicians with expertise in reading lung CTs 
analyzed each exam. Before performing individual readings, 
they standardized the process in order to minimize inconsis-
tencies. Any divergences were decided by consensus. 
After analyzing and scoring each CT, patients were clas-
sified in one of three conditions: as having just EMP (no 
AWD), just AWD (no EMP), or both (EMP and airways). 
In this third situation, the predominant pattern was estab-
lished by consensus. </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>Group data were expressed as the mean ± standard devia-
tion for functional data. The comparison between groups for 
categorical variables was performed using the chi-square test 
or Fisher's exact test. The comparison between groups for 
numerical variables was performed using Mann-Whitney 
Utest. The correlation between numerical variables was 
assessed using the Spearman's correlation coefficient. 
A P-value of less than 0.05 was considered significant for the 
results of all statistical analysis. Data analysis was performed 
using the <rs id="software-2" type="software">SAS</rs> System for Windows (Statistical Analysis 
System), <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 9.4</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., Cary, NC, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>We evaluated 250 records of COPD patients followed in the 
Chronic Respiratory Failure clinic. Of these, 115 patients 
were initially included, but 50 did not fulfill all the proposed 
tests, so 65 patients were evaluated. Details of the selection 
process are given in Figure 2. 
Of the 65 patients who completed the study, 21 were 
GOLD III and 44 were GOLD IV. The clinical and functional </p>

<p>characteristics (spirometry, 6MWT, and VC) are shown in 
Table 2. 
Findings related to the airways were present in many 
of HRCT scans of the 65 patients: 33.8% of patients had 
bronchiectasis, 69.2% had some degree of peribronchial 
thickening, and 52.3% of patients who had expiration scans 
(N=44) had air trapping. EMP was present in 69.2% and bul-
lae in 21.5%. In 16.9% of patients, the ratio AP/Ao is greater 
than 1.0, which probably means some degree of pulmonary 
hypertension (Table 3). 
In the process of phenotyping, 15 patients had only EMP 
and 20 patients only airway involvement. Thirty patients had 
CT findings of both EMP and AWD. In this group, it was 
determined by consensus which one was the predominant 
pattern, EMP (N=19) or AWD (N=11). So, the EMP had 34 
patients and the AWD group, 31. CT findings and clinical 
and functional features in patients classified by CT phenotype 
are shown in Table 4. </p>

<p>Table 1 Scoring system for CT findings </p>

<p>Category 
Absent in 
all lobes </p>

<p>RSL LSL ML LIN RIL LIL Total Score 
range </p>

<p>extension of bronchiectasis: 0= absent; 1= until 50% of the lobe; 2= more than 50% 
0-12 
severity of dilatation: 0= absent; 1= mild (lumen slightly greater than the diameter 
of adjacent vessel); 2= moderate (lumen 2-3× . diameter of adjacent vessel); 
3= severe (lumen 3× .diameter of adjacent vessel) </p>

<p>0-18 </p>

<p>Peribronchial thickening: 0= absent; 1= mild (airwall thickness equal to adjacent 
vessel); 2= moderate (airwall thickening . adjacente vessel but #2× the diameter 
of adjacent vessel); 3= severe (airwall thickening .2× diameter of adjacent vessel) </p>

<p>0-18 </p>

<p>Tree-in-bud: 0= absent; 1= present 
0-6 
Mucoid plug: 0= absent; 1= present 
0-6 
air trapping (expiratory scan): 0= absent; 1= present; ne = not evaluated 
0-6 
Fibrotic collapse/consolidation: 0= absent; 1= subsegmentar; 2= segmentar or lobar 
0-2 
Bullae, n: 0= absent; 1= unilateral (,4); 2= bilateral (,4); 3=$4 
0-3 
emphysema: 0= absent; 1= present 
0-6 
Total 
0-77 
Pa/ao ratio: 0#1; 1.1 
0-1 </p>

<p>Notes: The ratio score is zero or one. score zero is equal to Pa/ao ratio #1. score 1 is equal to Pa/ao ratio .1. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CT, computed tomography; rsl, right superior lobe; lsl, left superior lobe; Ml, medium lobe; lIn, lingula; rIl, right inferior lobe; lIl, left inferior lobe; 
Pa, pulmonary artery; ao, aorta. </p>

<p>• </p>

<p>• </p>

<p>• </p>

<p>• </p>

<p>• </p>

<p>Figure 2 Flowchart of patients included in the study. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>507 </p>

<p>COPD phenotypes on CT and correlation with lung function variables </p>

<p>Considering AWD phenotype patients, 45.16% had bron-
chiectasis, 83.9% peribronchial thickening, 9.7% tree-in-bud 
or mucoid plugs, and 76% had air trapping (of those patients 
who had expiratory scans). 
In EMP phenotype, all patients had emphysematous 
lesions (100%), and bullae were found in 38.2% of patients 
versus 3.2% in those with AWD phenotype. Tomography </p>

<p>findings of airways involvement also were seen in EMP 
phenotype: 23.5% had bronchial dilatation, 55.9% had 
peribronchial thickening, 2.9% had tree-in-bud or mucoid 
plugging, and 21.1% of patients who had expiration scans 
had air trapping. 
As can be seen in Table 4, there was no significant dif-
ference between the EMP and AWD groups in terms of age, 
sex distribution, smoking history, SpO 2 at rest, domiciliary 
oxygen, degree of dyspnea (according to the MRC scale), 
frequency of exacerbations per year, cough and expectoration, 
and spirometric classification of GOLD III/IV. Nevertheless, 
there were differences in body mass index (BMI) (lower val-
ues in the EMP group, P=0.0020) and in some spirometric 
variables as post-bronchodilation FEV 1 , FEV 1 /FVC, and 
FEF 25%-75% (forced expiratory flow between 25% and 75% of 
FVC), with P=0.044, P=0.007 and P=0.032, respectively. All 
these values were lower in the EMP group compared to the 
AWD group, indicating a greater degree of obstruction in this 
group. Also the BODE (Body-mass index, airflow Obstruc-
tion, Dyspnea, and Exercise) index had higher values in EMP 
group (P=0.0034). These findings point toward greater sever-
ity and systemic effects of the disease in this group. 
In the 6MWT, only the 6-minute walked distance (6MWD) 
(as % of predicted value) 
22 was different between the groups 
(P=0.039), with lower values in the EMP group. 
Regarding VC, significant differences were observed 
among the AWD and EMP groups in the following variables: 
ETCO 2 (P,0.001), slope of phase 2 (Slp2) (P,0.001), slope 
of phase 3 (Slp3) (P=0.034), and Slp3/V e (P=0.0085). In this 
test, the AWD group had higher values. 
The 44 patients who had full expiration scans were 
evaluated for air trapping; of them, 23 had evidence of air 
trapping and 21 had no signs. Comparing these two groups 
(Table 5), there were no significant differences regarding 
clinical variables, and among the function tests, there were 
differences only in VC variables: ETCO 2 (P=0.046), Slp3 
(P=0.016), and Slp3/V e (P=0.037), with the higher values in 
patients with evidence of air trapping. 
Correlation analysis was carried out between the CT find-
ings (score obtained in each assessed parameter) and func-
tional variables obtained on spirometry, on the 6MWT and 
VC. Complete results of this analysis are shown in Table 6. 
In this analysis, only bullae were negatively correlated with 
spirometric findings, the lower the bullae score, the higher the 
FEV 1 , FEV 1 /FVC, and FEF 25%-75% , with P=0.0087, P=0.0001, 
and P=0.0043, respectively. Spirometric variables were not 
significantly correlated with any of the other CT findings. 
Air trapping and EMP were strongly correlated with 
VC variables, but in opposite directions: the higher the </p>

<p>Table 2 Clinical and functional characteristics of patients (n=65) </p>

<p>age (years) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>64.15±8.45 
sex (M/F) 
43/22 (66.2%/33.8%) 
smoking (pack-years) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>47.4±38.7 
BMI (kg/m 
2 ) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>26.3±6.22 
spO 2 rest (%) 
92.7±3.74 
number of exacerbations/year (last 3 years) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.74±0.44 
BODe </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>4.5±1.86 
MrC </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2.8±0.87 
Cough </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>30 (46%) 
sputum production </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>20 (31%) 
Use of domiciliary oxygen </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>21 (32%) 
Other associated diseases </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>55 (85%) 
hBP 
34 (52%) 
DlP 
10 (15%) 
Pah 
9 (14%) 
DM 
8 (12%) 
Questionnaire sgrQ -general domain (%) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>58.09±15.82 
symptoms score (%) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>55.31±23.48 
activity score (%) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>73.04±16.44 
Impact score (%) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>50.42±17.36 
Questionnaire aQ20 (1-20) 
11.47±3.78 
FVC (l) 
2.07±0.60 
FVC (% predicted) 
56.64±13.98 
FeV 1 (l) 
1.15±0.42 
FeV 1 (% predicted) 
39.75±14.11 
FeV 1 /FVC 
54.83±11.41 
FeF 25%-75% (l) 
0.58±0.29 
FeF 25%-75% (% predicted) 
22.29±11.08 
6MWD (m) 
378.61±89.96 
6MWD (% predicted) </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>76.7 
ΔspO 2 (%) 
4.6±4.04 
ΔBorg 
2.68±2.40 
eTCO 2 
36.22±7.23 
slp2 
246.34±118.18 
slp3 
32.64±14.64 
slp3/eTCO 2 
0.90±0.36 
slp3/V e 
0.07±0.05 
T i /T e (s) 
0.60±0.15 </p>

<p>Notes: all spirometric measurements were obtained after bronchodilator use. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Data expressed as mean ± standard deviation. 
b Categorical variables (yes/no). 
Abbreviations: M, male; F, female; BMI, body mass index; spO 2 , peripheral oxygen 
saturation; BODE, Body mass index, airflow Obstruction, Dyspnea, and Exercise; 
MrC, Medical research Council; hBP, high blood pressure; DlP, dyslipidemia; Pah, 
pulmonary arterial hypertension; DM, diabetes mellitus; sgrQ, saint george's 
respiratory Questionnaire; aQ20, airways Questionnaire 20; FVC, forced vital 
capacity; FeV 1 , forced expiratory volume in 1 second; FeF 25%-75% , forced expiratory 
flow between 25% and 75% of FVC; ΔspO 2 , difference between final and initial 
peripheral oxygen saturation; ΔBorg, difference between final and initial Borg score 
of dyspnea; eTCO 2 , level of carbon dioxide released at the end of expiration; slp2, 
slope of phase 2; slp3, slope of phase 3; V e , expiratory volume; T i , inspiratory time; 
T e , expiratory time. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>508 </p>

<p>da silva et al </p>

<p>air trapping score, the higher the VC variables of ETCO 2 
(P=0.0092) and Slp3 (P=0.0241); the higher the EMP 
score, the lower the VC variables-ETCO 2 (P,0.0001), Slp2 
(P,0.0001), and Slp3/V e (P=0.0370). 
Total score was negatively correlated with Slp2 
(P=0.0310). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>COPD is a greatly heterogeneous condition and includes 
several pathological processes whose clinical manifestations 
and systemic effects vary widely depending on individual 
susceptibility. Grading the severity of COPD solely by the 
FEV 1 is misleading. This heterogeneity impacts on the pattern 
and intensity of patient response to therapeutic measures. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>This study illustrates clearly the great clinical and func-
tional heterogeneity of a group of patients with severe COPD, 
when selected exclusively by spirometric parameters. HRCT 
phenotyping between the EMP and AWD groups allow us 
to identify subsets of patients with distinct clinical and func-
tional characteristics. Although there was some overlapping 
between the EMP and AWD patients, they had different 
functional profiles. </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>HRCT is currently the most sensitive method to detect 
EMP as well as the investigation tool of choice in the diag-
nosis of bronchiectasis. 
In our study, bronchiectasis was found in 33.8% and peri-
bronchial thickening in 69.2% of the 65 patients evaluated. 
These findings are similar to those reported by Martinez-
Garcia et al, 
28 who found peribronchial thickening in 66% 
of COPD patients, and Patel et al 
29 who also found bronchial 
wall thickening in 66% of patients with moderate-to-severe 
COPD. 
Bronchiectasis is frequent in COPD patients, especially in 
severe ones. In Rezende Gonçalves et al's study, 
30 among 37 
severe COPD patients, CT scans showed EMP in 29 (78.4%), </p>

<p>and bronchiectasis in 18 (48.6%) patients. Patel et al </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>evaluated 54 severe COPD patients (mean FEV 1 38.1% of 
predicted) with HRCT and detected bronchiectasis in 50% of 
patients. These authors found that patients with bronchiecta-
sis had higher levels of airway inflammatory cytokines and 
bacterial colonization, but no relationship was seen between 
exacerbation frequency and HRCT findings. 
Martinez-Garcia et al 
28 found bronchiectasis in 57.6% of 
moderate-to-severe COPD patients. These authors identified 
the association between the frequency of bronchiectasis and 
the severity of functional impairment: bronchiectasis was 
present in 72.5% of patients with FEV 1 ,50%, and in 34.7% 
of patients with FEV 1 between 50% and 80% of predicted 
value. Nakano et al 
31 found a good correlation of luminal 
area, with measurements obtained on quantitative assess-
ments with FEV 1 in patients with COPD. 
On the contrary, other authors evaluated 294 COPD 
patients of all grades of severity, and found bronchial dilata-
tion with similar frequency through all categories of severity, 
suggesting limited value of bronchiectasis as severity disease 
marker. </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>In our study, no significant correlation was found between 
CT scores (including airway and EMP) and spirometric 
variables. 
One possible explanation for this result is that bron-
chiectasis is a structural change in the airways that usually 
occurs as a result of a process that begins or exists simultane-
ously in the small airways. Diseases of the small airways may 
be best evaluated by the analysis of the pattern of elimination 
of various gases. Spirometry measures flow, so it is best 
suited for analyzing disease processes that occur in the air-
ways where flow does exist. From the 15th generation down 
to the alveoli, there is no movement of gases by convection 
(difference in pressure) because of the great cross-sectional 
area of the airspaces in this region of the lung. </p>

<p>Table 3 HRCT findings of all patients (N=65) </p>

<p>CT findings 
Patients with the 
CT finding (%) </p>

<p>CT score </p>

<p>Mean ± SD 
Median (min-max) </p>

<p>Bronchiectasis (score range: 0-30) 
22 (33.8) 
7.45±6.25 
5.5 (2-22) 
Peribronchial thickening (score range: 0-18) 
45 (69.2) 
3.60±1.68 
3 (2-8) 
Tree-in-bud/mucoid plugging (score range: 0-12) 
4 (6.15) 
5±3.16 
4.5 (2-6) 
air trapping 
a (score range: 0-6) 
23 (52.3) 
3±1.73 
2 (2-6) 
Bullae (score range: 0-3) 
14 (21.5) 
1.92±0.91 
0-3 
emphysema (score range: 0-6) 
45 (69.2) 
3.15±2.58 
3 (0-6) 
CT total score (score range: 0-77) 
11.47±10.08 
9 (2-50) </p>

<p>Pa/ao .1 
11 (16.9) </p>

<p>Note: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>evaluated in 44 subjects who had expiration scans. 
Abbreviations: Pa, pulmonary artery; ao, aorta; CT, computed tomography; min, minimum; max, maximum; hrCT, high-resolution computed tomography; sD, standard 
deviation. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>509 </p>

<p>COPD phenotypes on CT and correlation with lung function variables </p>

<p>CT and spirometry are tests that assess different aspects 
of pulmonary diseases. CT assesses changes in lung structure, 
and spirometry evaluates the functional variables. CT may 
show small airway signals and the presence of EMP even </p>

<p>when there is no functional compromising. The patients in 
this study were all severely obstructed, and this fact may 
have limited the capacity of spirometry to detect the lung 
function decline. </p>

<p>Table 4 HRCT findings, clinical and functional characteristics of patients according to CT phenotype </p>

<p>Variables 
Emphysema (N=34) 
Airway disease (N=31) 
P-value </p>

<p>n (%) 
n (%) </p>

<p>CT findings 
Bronchiectasis 
8 (23.5) 
14 (45.2) 
0.06 
score: 0-30 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>3.75±1.98 
9.57±6.91 
0.009 
Peribronchial thickening 
19 (55.9) 
26 (83.9) 
0.01 
score: 0-18 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>3.16±1.50 
3.92±1.76 
0.13 
Tree-in-bud/mucoid plug 
1 (2.9) 
3 (9.7) 
0.34 
score: 0-12 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>6 
4.66±3.78 
air trapping (n=44) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>4/19 (21.1) 
19/25 (76) 
,0.001 
score: 0-6 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2.75±2.22 
3.14±1.62 
0.60 
Bullae 
13 (38.2) 
1 (3.2) 
,0.001 
emphysema 
34 (100) 
11 (35.5) 
,0.001 
score: 0-6 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>5.11±1.66 
1.0±1.43 
,0.001 
CT total score (0-77) 
9.76±5.35 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>9.5 (2-29) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>13.35±13.37 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>9 (2-50) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.99 </p>

<p>Pa/ao .1 (Y/n) 
6 (17.7) 
5 (16.1) 
Clinical variables 
age (years) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>64.5±8.4 
63.7±8.7 
0.750 
sex (M/F) </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>24/10 
19/12 
0.430 
smoking (pack-years) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>51.7±42.6 
42.7±34.1 
0.390 
BMI (kg/m 
2 ) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>24.1±6.0 
28.7±5.6 
0.002 
spO 2 (%) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>92.9±3.8 
92.5±3.8 
0.720 
exacerbations/year </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.7±0.4 
0.7±0.5 
0.990 
BODe </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>5.2±1.8 
3.8±1.7 
0.003 
MrC </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2.9±0.8 
2.67±0.9 
0.480 
Cough </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>17 (50) 
13 (41.9) 
0.510 
sputum production </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>9 (26.5) 
11 (35.5) 
0.430 
Use of oxygen </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>11 (32.4) 
10 (32.3) 
0.990 
spirometry post-BD 
FVC (l) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2.1±0.7 
2.1±0.5 
0.710 
FVC (% predicted) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>55.7±15.6 
57.6±12.2 
0.560 
FeV 1 (l) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.1±0.5 
1.2±0.4 
0.059 
FeV 1 (% predicted) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>36.6±13.8 
43.3±13.8 
0.044 
FeV 1 /FVC (%) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>51.1±10.6 
58.9±11.0 
0.007 
FeF 25%-75% (% predicted) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>19.4±9.0 
25.4±12.4 
0.032 
6-minute walk test 
6MWD (m) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>365.2±82.1 
393.4±97.1 
0.140 
6MWD (% predicted) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>73.2±19.4 
80.5±18.1 
0.039 
ΔspO 2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>4.9±3.9 
4.3±4.2 
0.440 
ΔBorg </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2.6±2.3 
2.8±2.5 
0.930 
Volumetric capnography 
eTCO 2 (mmhg) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>33.7±6.8 
39±6.7 
,0.001 
slp2 (mmhg/l) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>192.2±68.1 
305.7±133.2 
,0.001 
slp3 (mmhg/l) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>28.6±12.7 
37.1±15.5 
0.034 
slp3/V e </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.1±0.0 
0.1±0.1 
0.008 
T i /T e (s) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.6±0.1 
0.6±0.2 
0.420 </p>

<p>Notes: all the values (mean) were calculated in patients with tomography sign present. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Values expressed as mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>evaluated in 44 subjects who had 
expiration scans. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Values expressed as median (min-max). </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Categorical variables (yes/no). 
Abbreviations: hrCT, high-resolution computed tomography; Pa, pulmonary artery; ao, aorta; M, male; F, female; BMI, body mass index; spO 2 , peripheral oxygen 
saturation; BODE, Body mass index, airflow Obstruction, Dyspnea, and Exercise; MRC, Medical Research Council; O 2 , oxygen; FVC, forced vital capacity; BD, bronchodilator; 
FeV 1 , forced expiratory volume in 1 second; FeF 25%-75% , forced expiratory flow between 25% and 75% of FVC; 6MWD, 6-minute walked distance; ΔspO 2 , difference between 
final and initial peripheral oxygen saturation; ΔBorg, difference between final and initial Borg score of dyspnea; ETCO 2 , level of carbon dioxide released at the end of 
expiration; slp2, slope of phase 2; slp3, slope of phase 3; V e , expiratory volume; T i , inspiratory time; T e , expiratory time; min, minimum; max, maximum; Y, yes; n, no. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>510 </p>

<p>da silva et al </p>

<p>After analyzing and scoring CT findings, visual evalu-
ation was used to determine which phenotypes (EMP or 
AWD) prevailed, by proceedings described previously in 
this text. 
Han et al 
8 proposed that the use of phenotyping should 
aim to identify, within a given clinical context, patients with 
clinical and functional characteristics in common and that 
this clustering process is meaningful and clinically relevant. 
In this way, it could be useful in customizing the choice of 
therapeutic options and estimating prognosis. Currently, the </p>

<p>most commonly used CT phenotypes are: the emphysematous 
disease and the airway disease. 
The determination of tomography phenotypes may be 
performed by visual or quantitative analysis. The quantitative 
assessment is automatically performed and can identify EMP, 
air trapping, and abnormal airways. 
6,31,33,34 There are evidences 
that CT measurements of EMP or peripheral airways are sig-
nificantly related to airflow obstruction in COPD patients. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>One difficulty for the diffusion of this proceeding and 
its practical applicability is that its use is still restricted to 
research. Visual analysis still has clinical importance and 
greater availability and applicability. 
35 Kim et al 
9 compared 
a visual assessment scheme of CT for COPD using standard 
reference images with quantitative CT and several physi-
ologic parameters. The analysis was performed for each lobe. 
The scheme proposed was reproducible and provides physi-
ologically complementary information to that provided by 
quantitative CT assessment. 
The comparison between the EMP and AWD groups 
showed some overlap of CT findings between the groups, 
with evidence of involvement of airways (bronchiectasis, 
peribronchial thickening, and even air trapping) in EMP 
patients, and vice versa, patients of AWD group showed 
EMP and bullae (Table 4). 
Despite this overlap, the CT phenotyping used here is 
supported by the fact that it identified groups of patients with 
similar clinical and functional characteristics. Comparing the 
EMP and AWD groups, there was no difference in age, sex, 
smoking history, oxygen saturation at rest, number of exac-
erbations per year, or identification of potentially pathogenic 
bacteria in sputum or symptoms. However, patients in the EMP 
group had lower BMI (P=0.002), higher degree of obstruc-
tion in spirometry (FEV 1 , P=0.044, lower FEV 1 /FVC ratio, 
P=0.007), and shorter 6MWD (P=0.039). These factors resulted 
in a higher BODE index in the EMP group (P=0.003). 
These findings were similar to those reported by Kita-
guchi et al. 
10 On performing visual assessment, the authors 
found that the morphological phenotypes of COPD identi-
fied subsets of patients with different clinical and func-
tional characteristics, as the EMP phenotype, which was 
significantly associated with lower BMI, decrease in DlCO 
(diffusing capacity of the lung for carbon monoxide), and 
lower FEV 1 /FVC. 
Patients with EMP have a well-defined clinical phenotype, 
first described in the 1960s. 
36 The mechanical disadvantage 
of EMP patients, who usually have greater hyperinflation and 
more pronounced lowering of the diaphragm, may explain the 
major limitation to physical effort, here shown by reduction </p>

<p>Table 5 Comparison of patients according to the presence or 
absence of air trapping on CT expiratory scans (n=44) </p>

<p>Variables 
With air 
trapping 
(N=23) </p>

<p>Without 
air trapping 
(N=21) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Clinical variables 
age (years) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>64.9±8.1 
65±8.5 
0.970 
sex (M/F) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>13/10 
16/5 
0.170 
smoking (pack-years) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>46.4±37.9 
44.6±40.7 
0.990 
BMI (kg/m 
2 ) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>27.9±5.0 
25.7±6.4 
0.140 
spO 2 (%) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>92±3.9 
93.9±3.6 
0.080 
exacerbations/year </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.8±0.5 
0.7±0.4 
0.270 
BODe </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>4.0±1.7 
4.6±1.9 
0.430 
MrC </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2.6±0.9 
2.8±0.9 
0.790 
Cough (Y/n) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>11/12 
9/12 
0.740 
secretion (Y/n) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>9/14 
3/18 
0.065 
Use of oxygen (Y/n) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>7/16 
5/16 
0.620 
spirometry post-BD 
FVC (l) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2.0±0.6 
2.1±0.6 
0.710 
FVC (% predicted) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>56±13.3 
56.3±15 
0.900 
FeV 1 (l) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.1±0.4 
1.2±0.5 
0.410 
FeV 1 (% predicted) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>40.6±14.1 
41.6±14.9 
0.940 
FeV 1 /FVC (%) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>56.6±10.8 
57.6±11.6 
0.660 
FeF 25%-75% (% predicted) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>23.2±12.5 
23.8±11.5 
0.750 
six-minute walk test (6MWT) 
6MWD (m) 
390.4±92.1 
385.8±87.2 
0.840 
6MWD (% predicted) </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>0.8±0.2 
0.8±0.2 
1.00 </p>

<p>ΔspO 2 
4.8±4.2 
3.2±3.7 
0.250 </p>

<p>ΔBorg 
3.0±2.8 
2.6±2.7 
0.760 
Volumetric capnography 
eTCO 2 (mmhg) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>39.1±7.3 
34.7±6.3 
0.046 
slp2 (mmhg/l) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>286±116.9 
225.5±102 
0.082 
slp3 (mmhg/l) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>37±13.1 
28.4±17.9 
0.016 
slp3/V e </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.1±0.1 
0.1±0.1 
0.037 
T i /T e (s) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.6±0.2 
0.6±0.1 
0.640 </p>

<p>Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Values expressed as mean ± standard deviation. 
b Categorical variables. 
Abbreviations: M, male; F, female; BMI, body mass index; spO 2 , peripheral 
oxygen saturation; BODE, Body mass index, airflow Obstruction, Dyspnea, and 
exercise; MrC, Medical research Council; O 2 , oxygen; FVC, forced vital capacity; 
BD, bronchodilator; FeV 1 , forced expiratory volume in 1 second; FeF 25%-75% , forced 
expiratory flow between 25% and 75% of FVC; 6MWD, 6-minute walked distance; 
ΔspO 2 , difference between final and initial peripheral oxygen saturation; ΔBorg, 
difference between final and initial Borg score of dyspnea; ETCO 2 , level of carbon 
dioxide released at the end of expiration; slp2, slope of phase 2; slp3, slope of phase 
3; V e , expiratory volume; T i , inspiratory time; T e , expiratory time; Y, yes; n, no. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>511 </p>

<p>COPD phenotypes on CT and correlation with lung function variables </p>

<p>in 6MWD. Increased energy spending, major limitation to 
physical activity, and reduced physical activity may explain 
the lower BMI. These findings explain the higher scores on 
the multidimensional BODE score. </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>Considering the findings of VC, EMP patients had lower 
ETCO 2 (P,0.001), lower Slp2 (P,0.001), and lower Slp3 
(P=0.034). 
Slp2 represents the rapid increase in CO 2 coming from 
short paths to alveoli, just after the exhalation of the air from 
the dead space. Steeper Slp2 allows us to suppose that there 
are short branches of the bronchial tree occupying all spaces 
located within short distances from the central axis of the 
tree (the trachea). </p>

<p>Slp3 represents the elimination of CO 2 from most of the 
alveoli, and in normal individuals is almost a plateau with a 
slight upward slope (Figure 1). The Slp3 should therefore be 
small. Increases in Slp3 happen in situations of heterogeneous 
involvement of the distal air spaces, which lead to heteroge-
neous distribution of the air in these regions and reduced contact 
area between CO 2 that crosses the alveolar-capillary membrane 
and the renewed air that arrived through the previous inspiration. 
Larger values of Slp3/V e and Slp3/ETCO 2 in patients suggest 
existence of structural damage to the peripheral lung, which 
promotes this heterogeneous distribution of ventilation. </p>

<p>13,14 </p>

<p>Bronchial tree branching patterns lead to the existence 
of paths of varied lengths from the first bronchial branching </p>

<p>Table 6 Correlation between CT score and spirometric variables, 6MWT and volumetric capnography </p>

<p>Category 
Bronchiectasis 
(0-30) </p>

<p>Peribronchial 
thickening 
(0-18) </p>

<p>Tree-in-bud/ 
mucoid plug 
(0-12) </p>

<p>Air trapping 
(0-6) </p>

<p>Bullae 
(0-3) </p>

<p>Emphysema 
(0-6) </p>

<p>CT total score 
(0-77) </p>

<p>spirometry 
FVC (l) 
r=0.05 
P=0.71 </p>

<p>r=-0.08 
P=0.54 </p>

<p>r=-0.04 
P=0.73 </p>

<p>r=-0.17 
P=0.25 </p>

<p>r=0.06 
P=0.66 </p>

<p>r=-0.01 
P=-0.91 </p>

<p>r=-0.09 
P=0.48 
FVC (% predicted value) r=0.12 
P=321 </p>

<p>r=0.007 
P=0.96 </p>

<p>r=-0.18 
P=0.16 </p>

<p>r=-0.12 
P=0.27 </p>

<p>r=-0.16 
P=0.21 </p>

<p>r=0.04 
P=0.77 </p>

<p>r=-0.01 
P=0.92 
FeV 1 (l) 
r=0.04 
P=0.74 </p>

<p>r=-0.12 
P=0.34 </p>

<p>r=-0.08 
P=0.51 </p>

<p>r=-0.17 
P=0.27 </p>

<p>r=-0.20 
P=0.12 </p>

<p>r=-0.15 
P=0.22 </p>

<p>r=-0.19 
P=0.12 
FeV 1 (% predicted value) r=0.09 
P=0.48 </p>

<p>r=-0.06 
P=0.64 </p>

<p>r=-0.11 
P=0.37 </p>

<p>r=-0.06 
P=0.70 </p>

<p>r=-0.32 
P=0.009 </p>

<p>r=-0.13 
P=0.29 </p>

<p>r=-0.11 
P=0.37 
FeV 1 /FVC 
r=-0.012 
P=0.92 </p>

<p>r=-0.12 
P=0.32 </p>

<p>r=0.04 
P=0.72 </p>

<p>r=-0.02 
P=0.91 </p>

<p>r=-0.46 
P=0.0001 </p>

<p>r=-0.29 
P=0.02 </p>

<p>r=-0.19 
P=0.12 
FeF 25%-75% (l) 
r=0.02 
P=0.84 </p>

<p>r=-0.08 
P=0.53 </p>

<p>r=-0.09 
P=0.47 </p>

<p>r=-0.08 
P=0.60 </p>

<p>r=-0.35 
P=0.004 </p>

<p>r=-0.14 
P=0.27 </p>

<p>r=-0.15 
P=0.24 
ΔFeV 1 
r=0.06 
P=0.66 </p>

<p>r=-0.006 
P=0.96 </p>

<p>r=-0.20 
P=0.11 </p>

<p>r=-0.03 
P=0.85 </p>

<p>r=0.05 
P=0.68 </p>

<p>r=0.03 
P=0.79 </p>

<p>r=0.02 
P=0.89 
Volumetric capnography 
respiratory frequency 
(BPM) </p>

<p>r=0.07 
P=0.56 </p>

<p>r=0.14 
P=0.27 </p>

<p>r=0.14 
P=0.27 </p>

<p>r=0.04 
P=0.80 </p>

<p>r=-0.16 
P=0.21 </p>

<p>r=-0.06 
P=0.63 </p>

<p>r=0.07 
P=0.59 
Vco 2 
r=-0.21 
P=0.09 </p>

<p>r=0.006 
P=0.97 </p>

<p>r=0.14 
P=0.28 </p>

<p>r=-0.01 
P=0.93 </p>

<p>r=-0.002 
P=0.98 </p>

<p>r=-0.02 
P=0.85 </p>

<p>r=-0.09 
P=0.44 
eTCO 2 
r=0.04 
P=0.78 </p>

<p>r=0.09 
P=0.45 </p>

<p>r=0.06 
P=0.65 </p>

<p>r=0.38 
P=0.009 </p>

<p>r=-0.19 
P=0.11 </p>

<p>r=-0.55 
P#0.0001 </p>

<p>r=-0.13 
P=0.29 
slp2 (mmhg/l) 
r=-0.003 
P=0.99 </p>

<p>r=-0.04 
P=0.77 </p>

<p>r=-0.07 
P=0.59 </p>

<p>r=0.24 
P=0.12 </p>

<p>r=-0.36 
P=0.003 </p>

<p>r=-0.55 
P#0.0001 </p>

<p>r=-0.27 
P=0.03 
slp3 (mmhg/l) 
r=0.24 
P=0.05 </p>

<p>r=0.22 
P=0.08 </p>

<p>r=0.05 
P=0.69 </p>

<p>r=0.34 
P=0.02 </p>

<p>r=-0.16 
P=0.22 </p>

<p>r=-0.19 
P=0.14 </p>

<p>r=0.19 
P=0.13 
slp3/V e 
r=0.02 
P=0.13 </p>

<p>r=0.15 
P=0.22 </p>

<p>r=-0.005 
P=0.97 </p>

<p>r=0.23 
P=0.13 </p>

<p>r=-0.23 
P=0.06 </p>

<p>r=-0.26 
P=0.04 </p>

<p>r=0.07 
P=0.59 
T e 
r=-0.06 
P=0.66 </p>

<p>r=-0.12 
P=0.35 </p>

<p>r=-0.17 
P=0.17 </p>

<p>r=0.04 
P=0.81 </p>

<p>r=0.19 
P=0.14 </p>

<p>r=0.09 
P=0.46 </p>

<p>r=-0.03 
P=0.84 
T i /T e 
r=0.05 
P=0.71 </p>

<p>r=-0.02 
P=0.84 </p>

<p>r=0.17 
P=0.18 </p>

<p>r=-0.10 
P=0.50 </p>

<p>r=-0.15 
P=0.24 </p>

<p>r=-0.14 
P=0.26 </p>

<p>r=-0.11 
P=0.36 
Tobin 
r=0.09 
P=0.47 </p>

<p>r=0.13 
P=0.29 </p>

<p>r=0.06 
P=0.65 </p>

<p>r=0.05 
P=0.73 </p>

<p>r=-0.23 
P=0.06 </p>

<p>r=-0.18 
P=0.15 </p>

<p>r=0.009 
P=0.94 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CT, computed tomography; 6MWT, 6-minute walk test; FVC, forced vital capacity; FeV 1 , forced expiratory volume in 1 second; FeF 25%-75% , forced expiratory 
flow between 25% and 75% of FVC; BPM, breaths per minute; ETCO 2 , level of carbon dioxide released at the end of expiration; slp2, slope of phase 2; slp3, slope of phase 
3; V e , expiratory volume; T i , inspiratory time; T e , expiratory time. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>512 </p>

<p>da silva et al </p>

<p>down to the alveolar region. The shortest paths are respon-
sible for the first increases of CO 2 concentration in exhaled 
air and are the cause of sudden rises in CO 2 concentrations 
in Slp2 of the volumetric capnogram. They are more numer-
ous in the apical regions of the lung, which are preferentially 
affected in patients with smoking-related EMP. The decrease 
in these shorter pathways in EMP patients may explain lower 
Slp2 values. 
Another explanation for the decreased Slp2 may come 
from mechanical ventilation of patients with EMP. The dif-
ficulty in exhaling air during expiration caused by reduced lung 
elasticity shifts the point of equal pressure to more peripheral 
airways that have less thick walls and therefore are liable to 
undergo collapse by forced expiration. Although these airways 
are located in outermost regions, they are still out of the lung's 
volumetric region where the smaller 2 mm diameter airways 
are located, too numerous along the long paths to the alveoli of 
the middle fields and lower lung. The collapse of more shorter 
path of the central airways may also decrease Slp2. 
AWD leads to increase in Slp3 compared to normal 
subjects. 
38 In this study, the group with AWD presented Slp3 
with higher values than the group with EMP, a fact which 
must reflect greater heterogeneity of gas distribution in the 
more peripheral airspaces of the lungs of the AWD group. 
The strong correlation found between air trapping with 
VC variables (Table 6) corroborates the role of Slp3 in 
evaluating the volumetric zone. Indeed, the Slp3 of VC or 
phase 3 slopes of the elimination of other test gases reflect 
structural and functional defects of distal airspaces, which 
constitute the volumetric or silent region of the lungs and is 
acknowledged as being poorly evaluated through spirometric 
measurements. On the other hand, HRCT of the thorax gives 
us access to the secondary pulmonary lobule and beyond. In 
fact, a better correlation between the data obtained from gas 
elimination curves and HRCT is not unexpected. 
In AWD, large portions of the parenchyma may have 
reduced ventilation by subocclusion of intralobular bronchi-
oles. The emphysematous process causes destruction of the 
alveoli. The small airways subocclusion, that characterizes 
AWD, causes a greater ventilation/perfusion heterogeneity 
than the loss of alveoli, which happens in the peripheral areas 
of the emphysematous lungs. </p>

<p>Strength and limitations </p>

<p>One strength of this study is that we could demonstrate that 
CT visual analysis is feasible in phenotyping COPD patients. 
Although this is a subjective and observer-dependent method, 
if it is done in a systematic way, it may provide useful </p>

<p>information to manage severe COPD patients with more 
individual basis. Automatic quantitative assessment of EMP 
or airway involvement seems to be more accurate, but this 
software is not available for everyone. Our study has also 
some limitations. First, it is known that air trapping may 
influence results of some functional variables, such as vital 
capacity. So, it would be interesting to have data such as total 
lung capacity, residual volume, and DlCO. Unfortunately, 
such measurements were not performed because we did not 
have this equipment. Second, the choice of evaluating only 
severe COPD patients may pose a bias because these patients 
are more prone to having structural abnormalities in airways 
and lung tissue. On the other hand, these severe COPD 
patients are the most difficult to manage, and spirometry, 
which is the usual exam for evaluating severity of COPD, 
seems to supply limited information about them. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Our study provides further evidence that even visual CT 
analysis for phenotyping COPD patients may help identify 
subsets of individuals with distinct functional profiles. 
Spirometry, as the only means to characterize COPD patients, 
has proven insufficient, especially for severe cases, because 
patients may have a huge function decrease without great 
changes in spirometric values. VC may be a useful tool to 
detect and estimate the magnitude of the heterogeneity of 
disease distribution, which is the main finding in airway 
phenotype of COPD. Using different tools that assess distinct 
dimensions of COPD, such as CT, 6MWT, and VC can help 
us understand the various COPDs and their consequences. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>International Journal of COPD </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-chronic-obstructive-pulmonary-disease-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of COPD is an international, peer-reviewed 
journal of therapeutics and pharmacology focusing on concise rapid 
reporting of clinical studies and reviews in COPD. Special focus is given 
to the pathophysiological processes underlying the disease, intervention 
programs, patient focused education, and self management protocols. </p>

<p>This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, MedLine and CAS. The 
manuscript management system is completely online and includes a 
very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>513 </p>

<p>COPD phenotypes on CT and correlation with lung function variables </p>



</text></tei>