<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4819867" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background/Aims 
To employ an experimental model of opioid-induced bowel dysfunction in healthy human volunteers, and evaluate the impact of 
opioid treatment compared to placebo on gastrointestinal (GI) symptoms and motility assessed by questionnaires and regional GI 
transit times using the 3-dimensional (3D)-Transit system. </p>

<p>Methods 
Twenty-five healthy males were randomly assigned to oxycodone or placebo for 5 days in a double blind, crossover design. Adverse 
GI effects were measured with the bowel function index, gastrointestinal symptom rating scale, patient assessment of constipation 
symptom questionnaire, and Bristol stool form scale. Regional GI transit times were determined using the 3D-Transit system, and 
segmental transit times in the colon were determined using a custom Matlab 
® graphical user interface. </p>

<p>Results 
GI symptom scores increased significantly across all applied GI questionnaires during opioid treatment. Oxycodone increased median 
total GI transit time from 22.2 to 43.9 hours (P &lt; 0.001), segmental transit times in the cecum and ascending colon from 5.7 to 9.9 
hours (P = 0.012), rectosigmoid colon transit from 2.7 to 9.0 hours (P = 0.044), and colorectal transit time from 18.6 to 38.6 hours 
(P = 0.001). No associations between questionnaire scores and segmental transit times were detected. </p>

<p>Conclusions 
Self-assessed GI adverse effects and increased GI transit times in different segments were induced during oxycodone treatment. This 
detailed information about segmental changes in motility has great potential for future interventional head-to-head trials of different 
laxative regimes for prevention and treatment of constipation. 
(J Neurogastroenterol Motil 2016;22:282-291) </p>

<p>Gastrointestinal (GI) adverse effects are common in opioid 
treated patients and collectively referred to as opioid-induced bowel 
dysfunction (OIBD). 
1,2 They result from binding of exogenous opi-</p>

<p>oids to opioid-receptors in the enteric nervous system, consequently 
disturbing normal GI function and manifesting in symptoms 
including gastroesophageal reflux, vomiting, bloating, abdominal 
pain, anorexia, hard stools, constipation, and incomplete evacua-
tion. 
3 Severe adverse effects are often the reason patients discontinue </p>

<p>opioid treatment, which naturally results in inadequate pain man-
agement. 
4,5 As the prescription of opioids has increased several fold </p>

<p>in Europe and the US recent years, an increase in adverse effects to 
opioid treatment has expectedly also developed. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Current assessments of OIBD typically rely on self-assessed 
questionnaires primarily focusing on constipation. 
7,8 The most </p>

<p>commonly used questionnaires include assessment of number of 
spontaneous bowel movements (SBMs), the patient assessment 
of constipation symptoms (PAC-SYM) questionnaire, 
9 the bowel </p>

<p>function index (BFI), 
10 and the Bristol stool form scale (BSFS). </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Despite elaborate focus on constipation, which is often defined 
as a reduction in number of SBMs, infrequent bowel movement 
ranks number 5 in self-assessed constipation symptoms, whereas 
symptoms such as gas, straining, and abdominal discomfort are far 
more prevalent. 
12 This finding strongly emphasizes that focusing </p>

<p>on SBMs is inadequate to describe the complete burden of OIBD. 
Furthermore, other health-related risk factors such as reduced 
mobility, age, low-fiber diet, gender, and different drugs may also 
contribute to the collective GI symptomatology in opioid treated 
patients. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>The clinical presentation of OIBD is the result of decreased 
motility, decreased secretion, and dyscoordination of sphincter func-
tion in the GI tract. 
14 It has previously been shown, using invasive </p>

<p>peroral cecal intubation and serial scintigrams, that subcutaneously 
administered morphine delays cecum and ascending colon transit 
and progression of the geometric center. 
15 However, reliable and </p>

<p>minimally-invasive objective measures of OIBD are warranted in 
order to achieve a better understanding of the underlying mecha-
nisms and evaluate the effect of novel pharmacological treatments 
on motility patterns. An attractive means of quantifying gut motil-
ity is the 3-dimensional (3D)-Transit system. This is a recently 
introduced, minimally-invasive, ambulatory system which--using 
a body-borne detection matrix--simultaneously tracks the precise 
position and general orientation of an electromagnetic capsule from </p>

<p>ingestion to expulsion. 
16-19 Hence, the pan-enteric impact of opioid </p>

<p>treatment can be accurately assessed, providing new insight into 
altered motility patterns. 
20 However, opioid treated patients often </p>

<p>suffer from comorbidities and concomitant drug use, which compli-
cates evaluation of the underlying pathophysiological mechanisms. 
Consequently, an experimental model in healthy volunteers, where 
these limitations are minimized, is highly merited. 
It was hypothesized that an experimental model of OIBD in 
healthy human volunteers could be established through a 5-day opi-
oid treatment. To test this hypothesis the aims were to evaluate how 
orally administered opioid treatment when compared to placebo af-
fected (1) GI symptoms and function assessed by questionnaires, (2) 
regional and segmental GI transit times using the 3D-Transit sys-
tem, and (3) investigate whether there was an association between 
self-assessed symptomatology and transit times. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>The trial was approved by the local scientific ethical committee, 
the Danish Health and Medicines Authority, and conducted in ac-
cordance with the principles of ICH-GCP of the European Union. 
All subjects signed informed written consent according to the Dec-
laration of Helsinki. The experiment was carried out between April 
2014 and February 2015 at the research facilities of Mech-Sense, 
Aalborg University Hospital, Department of Gastroenterology &amp; 
Hepatology and Department of Radiology. The trial was registered 
at www.clinicaltrialsregister.eu (EudraCT number: 2013-001540-
60). </p>

<p>Subjects </p>

<p>Twenty-five healthy, male volunteers (median age 24 years [21 
to 56 years], mean height 182.2 cm [180 to 184.5 cm], mean BMI 
23.9 kg/m 
2 [22.9 to 25.0 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>]), with neither current symptoms 
nor history of GI disease were included in the study. All subjects 
underwent a screening session where the volunteers were informed 
about the study and informed consent was obtained. Hereafter, a 
physician (J.L.P) evaluated their medical history and ensured that 
all inclusion and exclusion criteria were fulfilled, and, if eligible, 
subjects were enrolled in the study. 
Inclusion criteria were (1) signed written informed consent 
declaration, (2) capable of reading and understanding Danish, (3) 
male of Northern European descent, and (4) understanding of 
what the study involved: age 20-60 years, healthy, and opioid naive. 
The exclusion criteria were (1) known allergy towards opioids, (2) 
participation in any other studies within 14 days of enrolment, (3) </p>



<p>Jakob L Poulsen, et al </p>

<p>Journal of Neurogastroenterology and Motility </p>

<p>planned medical/surgical treatment within the study duration, (4) a 
need to operate heavy machinery or motor vehicles during the study, 
(5) any previous or current drug abuse, (6) non-removable pierc-
ings or metal implants, (7) daily alcohol or nicotine consumption, (8) 
any known disease that may influence the results, and (9) the use of 
prescribed medicine and/or herbal medicine. </p>

<p>Study Design </p>

<p>Subjects were treated for 5 days (one period) with oral pro-
longed-release (PR) oxycodone or placebo in a double blind, cross-
over design (Fig. 1). A computer generated block-randomisation 
list (6 blocks of 4 subjects each and 1 subject manually randomised </p>

<p>by study personnel which was not otherwise included in the study) 
was used. The personnel that generated the randomisation list also 
carried out proper concealment of each subject's assigned sequence 
in individually sealed envelopes, which allowed un-blinding of a 
single subject in case of emergencies. To ensure statistical power, 
dropouts were replaced using mirror-randomisation. 
The subjects arrived at the research unit after an overnight 
fast. All periods started on a Monday (Day 1) where baseline GI 
questionnaires and muscle pressure stimulation thresholds were 
obtained. The first dose of PR oxycodone or placebo was admin-
istered to the subject after the baseline measurements and then 
repeated every 12 hours until Friday morning. Following the first </p>

<p>Figure 1. Study enrolment and rando-
misation. </p>

<p>Randomised 
(n = 26) </p>

<p>Allocated to oxycodone treatment (n = 14) 
Allocated to placebo treatment (n = 12) </p>

<p>Drop-out (n = 1) 
-Non-compliance (n = 1) </p>

<p>Cross-over to oxycodone treatment (n = 12) 
Cross-over to placebo treatment (n = 13) </p>

<p>Received both treatments (n = 25) </p>

<p>Analysed (n = 
Excluded from questionnaire analysis 
Excluded from muscle pressure analysis 
Excluded from 3D-Transit data analysis 
Technical issue with recording 
Faulty capsules </p>

<p>25) 
-
( n = 0) 
-
( n = 0) 
-
( n = 6) 
-
( n = 2) 
-
( n = 4) </p>

<p>Responded to recruiting material (N = 80) </p>

<p>Not eligible (n = 54) 
-No reply when contacted 
Not meeting inclusion criteria 
No consent 
Gender 
Medication 
Nicotine consumption 
Disease 
Not opioid naive 
Age 
Ethnic descent 
Hypersensitivity to opioids </p>

<p>(n = 20) 
-
( n = 34) 
-
( n = 9) 
-
( n = 6) 
-
( n = 5) 
-
( n = 4) 
-
( n = 4) 
-
( n = 2) 
-
(n = 2) 
-
( n = 1) 
-
( n = 1) </p>



<p>Impact of Opioid Treatment on Regional GI Transit </p>

<p>Vol. 22, No. 2 April, 2016 (282-291) </p>

<p>dose, a standardized meal (375 kcal, 11.4 g fat, and 1.8 g fiber) 
was ingested and immediately after the meal was finished, the 3D-
Transit capsule was ingested with a glass of water, approximately 15 
minutes after the first dose of study medication. PR oxycodone was 
administered 5 mg twice daily on Monday, 10 mg twice daily on 
Tuesday through Thursday, and 10 mg once Friday morning. 
The data presented here are part of a larger protocol evaluat-
ing experimentally induced OIBD, which also included measures 
of colonic volume with magnetic resonance imaging (Nilsson et al. 
unpublished data). </p>

<p>Questionnaires </p>

<p>The subjects were asked to answer 4 validated GI question-
naires (1) BFI, 
10 (2) gastrointestinal symptom rating scale (GSRS), </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>(3) PAC-SYM, 
9,22 and (4) BSFS. 
11 The BFI and GSRS were </p>

<p>administered on day 1 and day 5, whilst the PAC-SYM and BSFS 
were used to assess the dynamic changes of the general bowel func-
tion of the healthy volunteers and thus assessed daily. </p>

<p>Muscle Pressure Stimulation </p>

<p>To verify that the chosen oxycodone dose regimen was suf-
ficient to provide analgesic effect, pressure algometry was included 
as a measure of analgesic effect. In order to improve consistency, 
stimuli were applied by the same examiner. 
23 Subjects were trained </p>

<p>in assessment of pain using a modified visual analog scale (VAS; a 
continuous scale from 0-10 with anchor words for every increment 
of one). The scale has been described in details previously and used 
extensively to assess pain intensity in several different tissues. </p>

<p>24-26 </p>

<p>Pressure was applied on the dorsal forearm 10 cm distal to the 
elbow corresponding to the extensor digitorum muscle with a hand-
held algometer (Type 2; Somedic Production AB, Hörby, Sweden). 
The force increase rate was 30 kPa/sec adjusted to a probe size of 1 
cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. Two stimulations, separated by 10 seconds, were applied each 
day; corresponding to pain detection threshold and moderate pain 
(VAS = 5 and VAS = 7, respectively on the modified VAS Scale). </p>

<p>3D-Transit System </p>

<p>The technical specifications, performance and use of the 3D-
Transit system is described in detail elsewhere. 
20 After ingestion </p>

<p>of the 3D-Transit capsule, the subjects were instructed to fast for 
6 hours as non-digestible solids are thought to empty with phase 
III of the migrating motor complex, and hence a new meal within 
6 hours of capsule ingestion could delay gastric emptying. 
27 Sub-</p>

<p>jects returned to the research facility on days 2, 3, 4, and 5, so that 
emitted signals from the capsules could be monitored in real-time. </p>

<p>This was done to confirm retention or expulsion of the capsules. 
Subjects were asked to refrain from hard physical work and sports. 
To confirm expulsion of the capsule by loss of signal on the 3D-
Transit recording, subjects were instructed to register the exact time 
of defecation during the study periods. Total GI transit time was 
defined as the time between ingestion and expulsion of the capsule. 
If the capsule was not expelled by day 5, the recording was stopped, 
and the time of the last confirmed signal from the capsule was used 
as the earliest possible expulsion time. Based on previously validated 
principles, regional transit times were determined in the 3D-Transit 
analysis software from changes in contraction frequencies observed 
on the capsule rotation graphs, the time-frequency map for the 
recording, and 2D overview of capsule position. 
18 Gastric empty-</p>

<p>ing was defined as the time from ingestion until pyloric passage, 
the latter identified as a shift from approximately 3 contractions per 
minute (cpm) to 12 cpm, in combination with the characteristic 
2D image of passage through the duodenal arch. As the ingestion 
time for the first dose of oxycodone and ingestion time of the 3D-
Transit capsule was only 15 minutes apart, gastric emptying was 
not analysed in this study, as the short time interval did not allow 
for oxycodone to be sufficiently absorbed and induce OIBD in 
the gastric segment. Small intestinal transit time was defined as the 
time between pyloric passage and ileocecal passage. Ileocecal pas-
sage was identified as a decrease in contraction frequency from 6 
cpm, characteristic of the distal ileum, to 3 cpm, typical of the colon. 
Identification of ileocecal passage was supported by a rapid lateral 
movement in the lower right quadrant. Total colorectal transit time 
was defined as the time between ileocecal passage and expulsion of 
the capsule. 
In order to obtain the segmental transit times of the colon, a 
new method for 3D visualization and determination of the trajectory 
traversed by the magnetic capsule in the colon was developed. The 
raw positional data from the magnetic capsule were pre-processed 
prior to visualization. To enhance visualization of the trajectory, 
samples with considerable noise and artefacts coming from patient 
movement or external noise based on signal strength of the capsule 
and accelerometer data were removed. Additionally, the positional 
data were low-pass filtered using a second order Butterworth filter. 
Samples were then averaged for every 10 minutes providing a more 
uniform trajectory visualization as the capsule may remain in the 
same position within the colon for several hours. 
The algorithms were incorporated into a custom <rs id="software-0" type="software">Matlab</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">R2014b version 8.4.0.150421</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">MathWorks</rs>, Inc, Natick, MA, 
USA) application with a graphical user interface allowing the user 
to visually inspect the trajectory traversed by the capsule and select </p>



<p>Jakob L Poulsen, et al </p>

<p>Journal of Neurogastroenterology and Motility </p>

<p>landmarks corresponding to the hepatic flexure, splenic flexure, and 
descending-sigmoid junction. Hereby, segmental colonic transit 
times could be calculated. In Figure 2, an example of a 3D trajec-
tory visualized in the graphical user interface is shown. 
All regional transit times were determined by the same investi-
gator (J.L.P.). Inter-observer agreement was not done, as it previ-
ously has been shown to be good for both an earlier version of the 
3D-Transit system 
18 and the same version as used in the present </p>

<p>study. 
20 All segmental colonic transit times were determined by the </p>

<p>same investigator (T.H.S.). In case of doubt, regional or segmental 
passage was discussed with another investigator (M.N., J.L.P., or 
T.H.S.). </p>

<p>Data Analysis and Statistics </p>

<p>All data are presented as means (95% confidence interval) 
unless otherwise stated. All data were assessed for normality and 
handled accordingly with parametric or non-parametric statistics. 
Statistical analysis was performed with treatment coded as "treatment 
A" and "treatment B," and un-blinding was not performed until all 
data had been processed. 
Baseline-corrected data from the BFI questionnaire were ana-
lysed with a paired t test. Data from the GSRS questionnaire were </p>

<p>baseline-corrected and analysed in a two-way ANOVA with factors 
treatment (oxycodone and placebo) and questionnaire dimension 
(abdominal pain, reflux, indigestion, diarrhea, and constipation). 
Data from the PAC-SYM and BSFS questionnaires and pain de-
tection thresholds were baseline-corrected and analysed with two-
way ANOVAs with factors treatment (oxycodone and placebo) and 
day (days 2, 3, 4, and 5). For all ANOVAs, Tukey's post hoc test 
was applied where relevant. Transit time data were non-parametric, 
and are presented as medians and ranges. Wilcoxon signed rank 
test was used to compare segmental transit times during the 2 treat-
ments. Spearman's rho was used to identify associations between 
questionnaire scores and transit times. P-values &lt; 0.05 were con-
sidered significant. Statistical analyses were carried out using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Stata</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">Version 13.1</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">StataCorp LP</rs>, College Station, TX, USA) and 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">Version 22</rs>; release 22.0.0.0, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">IBM Corp</rs>, New York, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Twenty-six subjects were enrolled in the study; 1 subject was 
excluded during day 4 in the first period due to non-compliance. 
This allowed a total of 25 subjects to complete the study. </p>

<p>Questionnaires </p>

<p>BFI scores increased 34 points during oxycodone treatment vs 
3 points increase during placebo treatment (P &lt; 0.001) (Fig. 3). 
Total GSRS scores likewise increased during oxycodone treatment 
(P &lt; 0.001) (Fig. 3). The post hoc test revealed increased scores 
during oxycodone treatment for the dimensions abdominal pain (P 
= 0.031) and constipation (P &lt; 0.001). For the PAC-SYM sig-
nificantly higher scores were found during oxycodone treatment on 
day 4 (6.5 vs 1.9 during oxycodone vs placebo, respectively; P &lt; 
0.001) and day 5 (7.0 vs 2.0 during oxycodone vs placebo, respec-
tively; P &lt; 0.001), but also within the oxycodone treatment period 
there were significant increases between day 2 and day 4 (2.0 vs 6.5 
day 2 vs day 4, respectively; P = 0.002) and between day 2 and day 
5 (2.0 vs 7.0 day 2 vs day 5, respectively; P &lt; 0.001). Number of 
bowel movements were lower on day 2 during oxycodone treatment 
compared to placebo, 0.9 vs 1.7 (P = 0.001), but not for other 
days. Stool form scores also decreased significantly during oxyco-
done treatment for all days compared to the placebo (37%, 52%, 
64%, 40%, and 73% lower scores for day 1 through 5; all P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Muscle Pressure Stimulation </p>

<p>The analgesic effect of oxycodone was validated in the pain 
model with an 8% increase in pain detection threshold to muscle </p>

<p>Figure 2. Example of 3-dimensional trajectory of colonic passage of a 
single capsule illustrated in the custom designed interactive graphical 
user interface. "Start" marks the ileocecal passage and "End" marks 
the expulsion of the capsule. A red line represents a progression of 
less than 50 mm the last 10 minutes. A blue line represents a progres-
sion of more than 50 mm during the last 10 minutes. Hepatic flexure, 
splenic flexure, and descending end can be marked in the trajectory in 
order to calculate segmental colonic transits. </p>



<p>Impact of Opioid Treatment on Regional GI Transit </p>

<p>Vol. 22, No. 2 April, 2016 (282-291) </p>

<p>pressure in comparison to 3% decrease during placebo treatment (P 
= 0.021). </p>

<p>Total and Regional Transit Times </p>

<p>Of the 50 capsules ingested (1 per period per subject), full 
recordings were obtained in 44 cases. Technical problems lead to 
insufficient recordings in 2 cases, in whom it was only possible to 
determine the total GI transit. In 4 cases it was not possible to de-
termine any transits due to faulty capsules. This led to 19 subjects 
with full recordings of all regional and colon segment transits in 
both periods, and 21 subjects with total GI transit in both periods. 
Capsule retention on day 5 occurred in 7 recordings (6 during oxy-
codone treatment and 1 during placebo). No adverse events were 
registered. 
Oxycodone treatment increased total GI transit (P &lt; 0.001) 
and colorectal transit (P = 0.001). For the colonic segments, oxy-
codone treatment increased cecum and ascending colon transit time 
(P = 0.012) and rectosigmoid transit time (P = 0.044). No other 
segmental transits were significantly different during oxycodone </p>

<p>treatment compared to placebo (Table). </p>

<p>Correlations </p>

<p>No associations were found between questionnaire scores and 
segmental transit times (all Spearman's rho &lt; ± 0.5; all P &gt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study has shown that the chosen dose regimen induced 
OIBD symptoms verified by increase in subjective symptom 
scores across all GI questionnaires. Furthermore, short term PR 
oxycodone treatment significantly increased the total GI transit 
time, colorectal transit time, and segmental colonic transit times in 
the cecum and ascending colon, as well as the rectosigmoid colon. 
The increase in pain detection thresholds suggests adherence to 
treatment. No associations between questionnaire scores and transit 
times were detected. 
Both the BFI, specifically designed and validated to assess 
opioid-induced constipation, and the more comprehensive GSRS, </p>

<p>Oxycodone 
Placebo </p>

<p>Day 1 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 
Questionnaire scores </p>

<p>BFI </p>

<p>0 
Day 5 
Day 1 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 
Questionnaire scores </p>

<p>GSRS (total score) </p>

<p>1.0 
Day 5 </p>

<p>Oxycodone 
Placebo </p>

<p>Figure 3. Bowel function index (BFI) and total gastrointestinal symptom rating scale (GSRS) results. From the left the first figure depicts the av-
erage BFI scores from day 1 and day 5 for both treatments. The second figure shows the total GSRS. Data are presented as means ± SEM. </p>

<p>Table. Total and Segmental Transit Times (in Hours) During Placebo and Oxycodone Treatment </p>

<p>Placebo 
Oxycodone 
P-value </p>

<p>Small intestinal transit time 
3.7 (1.9 to 10.0) 
5.3 (1.5 to 9.6) 
0.147 
Cecum and ascending colon 
5.7 (0.4 to 21.7) 
9.9 (0.3 to 73.2) 
0.012 
Transverse colon 
4.4 (0.5 to 40.6) 
3.8 (0.8 to 4.4) 
0.872 
Descending colon 
1.4 (0.4 to 15.6) 
4.7 (0.5 to 25.8) 
0.064 
Rectosigmoid colon 
2.7 (0.1 to 19.0) 
9.0 (0.1 to 71.3) 
0.044 
Colorectal transit time 
18.6 (7.0 to 82.2) 
38.6 (5.6 to 88.6) 
0.001 
Total GI transit time 
22.2 (11.0 to 85.6) 
43.9 (7.1 to 92.6) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Data are presented as medians (range). </p>



<p>Jakob L Poulsen, et al </p>

<p>Journal of Neurogastroenterology and Motility </p>

<p>increased significantly during oxycodone treatment, 
10 convincingly </p>

<p>implying the desired constipating effect. Particularly interesting was 
that not only the constipation dimension of the GSRS but also the 
abdominal pain dimension increased. Of special note are the daily 
assessed PAC-SYM scores, revealing a progressively constipat-
ing effect with significant increases on day 4 and 5--both during 
oxycodone treatment when compared to placebo, but also within the 
oxycodone arm when compared to day 2. In agreement, stool form 
score decreased for all days during oxycodone treatment compared 
to placebo, but SBM frequency only decreased on day 2 in the oxy-
codone arm compared to placebo. 
The 3D-Transit system added interesting insights in regional 
transit times during oxycodone treatment. It has previously been 
shown that intravenous morphine increases oro-cecal transit evalu-
ated by breath tests. 
28 The current data is supported by a compre-</p>

<p>hensive study by Kaufman et al, 
15 who showed that subcutane-</p>

<p>ously administered morphine decreases transit in the cecum and 
ascending colon as well as geometric center transit. However, fewer 
subjects underwent a highly invasive method with peroral cecal 
intubation in this study, where only fluid meals were allowed, and 
the subjects were subjected to a series of scintigrapic images, con-
sequently exposing them for radiation. Thus, clinical studies inves-
tigating colonic transit in response to for example, pharmacological 
interventions, necessitate less invasive methods such as the ambula-
tory and minimally-invasive nature of the 3D-Transit system. 
The significantly prolonged transit during opioid treatment 
in the cecum and ascending colon, but not in the transverse and 
descending colon, indicates that the origin of pathophysiological 
motility is in this colonic segment. The analysis software for the 3D-
Transit system is still in its infancy, but the current system is able to 
provide precise anatomical position of ingested capsules, description 
of contractile activity and luminal progression through well-defined 
regions of the GI tract. 
20 An alternative, but invasive, method to </p>

<p>examine colonic motility patterns is high-resolution fiber-optic ma-
nometry. 
29 A recent study employing this technique in slow transit </p>

<p>constipation patients found that the normal increase in the postpran-
dial propagating cyclic motor pattern was absent in patients when 
compared to healthy controls. 
30 Similar studies in slow transit con-</p>

<p>stipation patients have found a reduced daily frequency of high am-
plitude propagating sequences (also recognised as mass movements 
and responsible for a significant proportion of propulsive activity 
in the colon), and that all high amplitude propagating sequences 
originate in the proximal colon. 
29,31,32 It is therefore plausible that </p>

<p>the prolonged colonic transit times during oxycodone treatment in 
this study share-at least partly-pathophysiological characteristics </p>

<p>with slow transit constipation, and that further development of the 
3D-Transit software could elucidate this neglected, yet important 
aspect of GI motility. Along the same line, the increased transit in 
the rectosigmoid colon during oxycodone treatment could indicate 
that not only transit, but possibly also defecation, is affected. This 
may be an indirect consequence of prolonged transit leading to in-
creased passive absorption, resulting in harder, dryer stools, which 
are difficult to pass. In addition, the recto-anal inhibitory reflex has 
also been found to be inhibited during opioid administration further 
complicating defecation. 
33 No difference in small intestinal transit </p>

<p>was observed, but as previous studies have been contradictory, 
methodological refinements are likely needed to report consistent 
findings. 
34-36 Recent in vitro studies in rodents has demonstrated </p>

<p>tolerance to opioids in the upper, but not the lower GI tract. </p>

<p>37,38 </p>

<p>Therefore differences in tolerance may partly explain our findings 
although direct translation to human in vivo physiology is highly 
questionable. </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>No associations between questionnaire scores and transit times 
were found. At first, this may seem surprising, but could reflect 
that the clinical presentation of OIBD is multi-faceted and the 
self-assessed symptoms are highly subjective, and does not always 
correspond with the objective findings. This is underscored in a 
study by Bell et al, 
40 who found that many opioid-treated patients </p>

<p>report normal stool frequency, but still experience symptoms of 
OIBD, and Johanson and Kralstein 
12 who found that infrequent </p>

<p>bowel movement ranks only number 5 in self-assessed constipation 
symptoms. Moreover, stool frequency correlates poorly with both 
measured whole-gut and colonic transit time, and only a mod-
est correlation between GI transit and stool form exists in chronic 
constipated patients. 
41 This strongly accentuates the limitations of </p>

<p>studies using number of SBMs as the primary outcome measure, 
as it may potentially underestimate symptoms regarded more both-
ersome for the patient. Our study supports these results, as SBM 
frequency only changed on day 2, but other OIBD symptoms were 
present throughout the study along with the significant increased 
transit times in the colon. 
A major advantage of our study is the use of healthy volunteers. 
In a clinical setting, factors known to affect bowel function such as 
immobility, concomitant drug use, dehydration, anorexia, previous 
GI surgery, haemorrhoids, but also psychological factors such as 
depression and anxiety can influence the outcome, and hence it can 
be difficult to evaluate the contribution of the variable of interest--
in this case oxycodone. 
42 By applying an experimental model, where </p>

<p>these factors are controlled, this allows us to examine the underlying 
pathophysiology and development of GI symptoms during oxyco-</p>



<p>Impact of Opioid Treatment on Regional GI Transit </p>

<p>Vol. 22, No. 2 April, 2016 (282-291) </p>

<p>done treatment with low risk of confounding and bias. Of course, 
a model like this should be validated in a clinical setting. Due to 
ethical reasons we chose only to treat the volunteers for 5 days. De-
spite this, our results clearly show that significant changes in bowel 
function and GI adverse effects could be induced. It is therefore 
plausible, that a longer treatment and/or higher dose would have 
resulted in even more pronounced symptoms. This scenario would 
also be more similar to the typical opioid treated patient. Moreover, 
a chronic pain condition may also result in a more sedentary life-
style, known to negatively affect bowel function. </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>The lack of gastric emptying data could influence the transit 
time and upper gut function during oxycodone treatment, but due 
to the logistics in study design these were not valid. Furthermore, 
the loss of data due to technical problems and faulty capsules result-
ing in 19 subjects with full recordings for all GI regions was unfor-
tunate, as this, combined with the wide intra-and inter-individual 
variation in transit times, hampers the possibility to detect signifi-
cant differences. Capsule retention on day 5 in 7 recordings affected 
precise calculations of colorectal and total GI transit times. As it oc-
curred in 6 recordings during oxycodone treatment, but only once 
in the placebo period, it has resulted in a systematic underestimation 
of colorectal and total GI transit time during oxycodone treatment. 
Also, one could argue that the use of only male volunteers in our 
study restricts external validity. The reason for this was to avoid 
potential confounding on GI symptoms and function due to the 
female menstrual cycle. 
44-46 As functional constipation is also more </p>

<p>prevalent among women than men, 
47 and if opioid-induced consti-</p>

<p>pation and (slow-transit) functional constipation share pathophysi-
ological mechanisms, it is not unlikely that the prevalence of GI 
adverse effects due to opioid treatment would be equally frequent in 
women. 
In conclusion, OIBD can be experimentally induced through 
5 days of oral PR oxycodone treatment, as subjectively evaluated by 
validated GI questionnaires and objectively by increased total GI 
transit time, colorectal transit time, and segmental colonic transit 
times in the cecum and ascending colon, and rectosigmoid colon. 
Our study highlights the advantage of combined, comprehensive 
subjective and objective evaluation, and the limitation of focusing 
on SBMs as the sole or primary outcome measure when assessing 
OIBD. Accordingly, this experimental model provides a tool for 
detailed investigation of pathophysiological motility in a controlled 
environment, which may be used in comparative studies of treat-
ments against this burdensome condition. </p>

<p>Financial support: This study was funded (1) in part by Inno-</p>

<p>vation Fund Denmark--Individuals, Disease and Society (Grant 
No. 10-092786), (2) in part by The A.P. Møller Foundation for 
the Advancement of Medical Science (Grant No. 14-319), (3) in 
part by Aage og Johanne Louis-Hansens Fond, and (4) in part by 
an unrestricted grant from Mundipharma Research GmbH &amp; Co. 
KG. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest: Asbjørn M Drewes has received financial </p>

<p>support from Mundipharma, AstraZeneca, Shire, Almirall, Grü-
nenthal, and Pfizer. Klaus Krogh has served as an advisory board 
member for Coloplast, Wellspect, Nordic Health Care, Amirall, 
and Shire. </p>

<p>Author contributions: Jakob L Poulsen: data acquisition, data </p>

<p>interpretation, drafting of manuscript, and statistical analysis; Ma-
tias Nilsson: data acquisition, data interpretation, and drafting of 
manuscript; Christina Brock: study supervision, study design, data 
interpretation, statistical analysis, and revision of the manuscript for 
important intellectual content; Thomas H Sandberg: wrote algo-
rithm and graphical user interface for assessment of regional colonic 
transit time, data interpretation, and drafting of manuscript; Klaus 
Krogh: data interpretation and revision of the manuscript for im-
portant intellectual content; Asbjørn M Drewes: obtained funding 
for the study, study supervision, study design, data interpretation, 
and revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content. </p>





<p>Jakob L Poulsen, et al </p>

<p>Journal of Neurogastroenterology and Motility </p>





<p>Impact of Opioid Treatment on Regional GI Transit </p>

<p>Vol. 22, No. 2 April, 2016 (282-291) </p>



</text></tei>