<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4801132" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Bufei Jianpi formula (BJF) has long been used as a therapeutic agent in the treatment 
of COPD. Systems pharmacology identified 145 active compounds and 175 potential targets of 
BJF in a previous study. Additionally, BJF was previously shown to effectively prevent COPD 
and its comorbidities, such as ventricular hypertrophy, by inhibition of inflammatory cytokine 
production, matrix metalloproteinases expression, and other cytokine production, in vivo. 
However, the system-level mechanism of BJF for the treatment of COPD is still unclear. The aim 
of this study was to gain insight into its system-level mechanisms by integrating transcriptomics, 
proteomics, and metabolomics together with systems pharmacology datasets. Using molecular 
function, pathway, and network analyses, the genes and proteins regulated in COPD rats and 
BJF-treated rats could be mainly attributed to oxidoreductase activity, antioxidant activity, focal 
adhesion, tight junction, or adherens junction. Furthermore, a comprehensive analysis of systems 
pharmacology, transcript, protein, and metabolite datasets is performed. The results showed that 
a number of genes, proteins, metabolites regulated in BJF-treated rats and potential target pro-
teins of BJF were involved in lipid metabolism, cell junction, oxidative stress, and inflammatory 
response, which might be the system-level therapeutic mechanism of BJF treatment. 
COPD is a serious health problem characterized primarily by irreversible airflow limi-
tation and systemic inflammation, which represents a substantial economic burden in 
the world. 
1,2 Despite great progress in the treatment of COPD, drug therapies have not 
changed significantly. 
3 Therefore, the development of novel therapeutic drugs and strate-
gies to improve the efficacy in treating this deadly disease is still urgently needed. 
Bufei Jianpi formula (BJF), a traditional Chinese medicine (TCM), has provided 
effective relief of symptoms in patients with COPD. Our clinical study demonstrated 
that BJF had extensive pharmacological effects on patients with COPD, such as alleviat-
ing the clinical symptoms of stable COPD, reducing the exacerbation frequency, delay-
ing acute exacerbation, and improving pulmonary function and exercise capacity. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Increasing evidences demonstrate that, in treating complex illnesses, includ-
ing COPD, treatment formula containing multiple drugs with distinct but related 
mechanisms can usually exert synergistic therapeutic effects and amplify the </p>

<p>Correspondence: Jiansheng li 
henan University of Traditional Chinese 
Medicine, 1 Jinshui road, Zhengzhou 
450046, People's republic of China 
Tel +86 371 6567 6568 
email li_js8@163.com </p>

<p>Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of COPD 
15 March 2016 </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>554 </p>

<p>Zhao et al </p>

<p>therapeutic efficacies of each agent. 
5,6 In the previous 
study, we constructed a systems pharmacological model by 
combining active compound prediction, target prediction, 
and network pharmacology to clarify the active compounds 
and therapeutic mechanism of BJF. Systems pharmacology 
successfully identified 145 bioactive ingredients from BJF 
and predicted 175 potential targets of the active components 
contained in BJF. Moreover, we experimentally demon-
strated that BJF was effective for the treatment of COPD and 
ventricular hypertrophy due to its inhibitory effect on the 
inflammatory cytokine, and hypertrophic factors expression, 
protease-antiprotease imbalance, and collagen deposition, 
in vivo. 
7 Systems pharmacology, as an understanding of 
the function of the biological system, provided a system-
wide view of the therapeutic mechanism of BJF in treating 
COPD rats. However, we should provide more experimental 
evidences to validate the systems pharmacology predictions 
at system level. 
Transcriptomics-proteomics-metabolomics-profiling 
techniques provide holistic approaches to reveal the com-
plex biological processes and function of herbal compound 
recipe. 
8-10 Transcriptomics has been used in many in vivo 
studies to find the whole genome, which, however, cannot 
provide the details of the alternative splicing or even protein 
expression itself. Proteomics is a promising approach to 
directly study the expressed proteins and protein functions 
in a cellular context. Moreover, metabolomics provides the 
metabolic information, that is, the consequence of the tran-
scriptome and proteome. 
11 Thus, comprehensive analyses of 
the transcriptomics, proteomics, and metabolomics datasets 
have the potential to provide a system view of the complex 
biological processes and function of herbal compounds. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>We previously analyzed metabolite changes in lung 
tissues of COPD rats, and identified 30 strongly regulated 
metabolites resulting from intervention by BJF treatment. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>In this study, we further analyzed the molecular effect of BJF 
on COPD rats using the datasets of transcripts and proteins 
derived from lung tissues. Finally, the aim of this study was 
to integrate systems pharmacology, transcriptomics, pro-
teomics, and metabolomics data streams, which provided a 
system picture of molecular mechanisms of BJF in treating 
COPD rats. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Chemicals and animals </p>

<p>Klebsiella pneumoniae (strain ID: 46114) was purchased 
from the National Center for Medical Culture Collection 
(CMCC, Beijing, People's Republic of China). Tobacco </p>

<p>(Hongqi Canal 
® Filter tip cigarette; tobacco type, tar: 
10 mg; nicotine content: 1.0 mg; carbon monoxide: 12 mg) 
was obtained from China Tobacco Henan Industrial Co., 
Ltd (Zhengzhou, People's Republic of China). Thirty-two 
Sprague Dawley rats (16 male and 16 female; 200±20 g) 
were purchased from the Experimental Animal Center of 
Henan Province (Zhengzhou, People's Republic of China). 
The animals were reared in cages with free access to food and 
water under standard laboratory conditions. All animals were 
handled with humane care throughout the experiment. </p>

<p>COPD model, drug administration, and 
lung samples </p>

<p>COPD rat model was prepared as described earlier. Briefly, 
22 rats were placed in a closed box exposed to tobacco and 
repeated K. pneumoniae infections. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>On week 9, COPD rats were randomly divided into two 
groups with ten rats in each group. COPD rats were intra-
gastrically treated with normal saline (2 mL) and BJF at the 
dose of 4.84 g/kg per day. The healthy control rats were also 
administered intragastrically normal saline (2 mL) for the 
same amount of time. All the rats were sacrificed at week 20. 
The lung tissues were shock-frozen in liquid nitrogen and 
stored at -80°C before use. 
The components of BJF were as follows: Astragali Radix 
15 g, Polygonati Rhizoma 15 g, Codonopsis Radix 15 g, 
Atractylodis Macrocephalae Rhizoma 12 g, Poria 12 g, Fritil-
lariae Thunbergii Bulbus 9 g, Magnoliae Officinalis Cortex 
9 g, Citri Reticulatae Pericarpium 9 g, Asteris Tatarici Radix 
9 g, Pheretima 12 g, Ardisiae Japonicae Herba 15 g, and Epi-
medii Herba 6 g. The herbs were identified and prepared in 
fluid extract according to the standard operating procedure. 
The experimental protocol was approved by the Experimental 
Animal Care and Ethics Committee of the First Affiliated 
Hospital, Henan University of Traditional Chinese Medicine. 
The animal experiments were conducted in accordance with 
guidelines of the Committee on the Care and Use of Laboratory 
Animals of the First Affiliated Hospital, Henan University of 
Traditional Chinese Medicine, People's Republic of China. </p>

<p>gene expression analyses with 
microarrays </p>

<p>For microarray analysis, six rats were used for each group 
for microarray study. Total RNA was isolated from lung tis-
sues of six rats from each of the three experimental groups 
by TRIzol reagent (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, 
MA, USA) and purified using a Qiagen RNeasy Micro Kit 
(Qiagen NV, Venlo, the Netherlands). RNA integrity was </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>555 </p>

<p>Chinese herbal Bufei Jianpi formula for COPD </p>

<p>checked using standard agarose gel electrophoresis and 
ethidium bromide staining. 
Purified RNA was polymerase chain reaction amplified 
using a First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Hoffman-La Roche 
Ltd., Basel, Switzerland) and labeled using an Agilent Quick 
Amp Kit (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA). 
Then, RNA was hybridized with Agilent Whole Rat Genome 
Oligo Microarray (4×44 K) and washed. Finally, the slides 
were analyzed using an Agilent DNA microarray scanner 
(part number G2505B). 
The raw microarray data were further analyzed using 
<rs id="software-4" type="software">Agilent GeneSpring GX</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">version 11.0</rs>. Processed 
data were subsequently filtered for significant detection 
(Student's t-test screening, P,0.05) and differential expres-
sion versus COPD model rats (fold change, |log ratio| .1). </p>

<p>Protein expression analysis </p>

<p>Lung tissue protein was isolated from the three experimental 
groups. In each group, six rats were taken out for the analysis 
of protein expression. In brief, the lung tissues were lysed 
using the lysis buffer containing 4% sodium dodecyl sulfate, 
0.1 M dithiothreitol, and 0.1 M Tris pH 8.0 and homogenized 
in a mechanical homogenizer (Retsch Technology, Haan, 
Germany). The lysates were clarified by centrifugation and 
then stored at -80°C. 
For proteolytic digestion, trypsin (Hoffman-La Roche Ltd.) 
solution (protein/trypsin ratio 1:30) was added to the protein 
solution and incubated for 24 hours at 37°C. To label tryptic 
peptides with 8-plex iTRAQ labeling reagents (ABSciex, 
Darmstadt, Germany), each of the samples was reconstituted 
with isopropanol individually, and the labeling procedure was 
performed according to the manufacturer's protocol. 
For strong cation exchange fractionation, buffers A (10 mM 
KH 2 PO 4 in 25% acetonitrile [ACN] at pH 3) and B (10 mM 
KH 2 PO 4 and 2 M KCl in 25% ACN at pH 3) were used as the 
mobile phase. The peptide mixtures were dissolved in buffer A 
and then loaded onto a PolySULFOETHYL A column. Pep-
tides were fractionated using an 86-minute gradient from 0% 
to 100% of buffer B and monitored at optical density 214 nm. 
Fractions were collected every minute from the retention times 
of 8-58 minutes. Then, the fractions were dried, dissolved in 
0.1% formic acid (FA), and used for liquid chromatography-
mass spectrometry (LC-MS) analysis. 
LC-MS/MS analysis was performed on a nano liquid 
chromatograph (Shimadzu, Kyoto, Japan) coupled online 
to a quadrupole time-of-flight mass spectrometer (Bruker 
Daltonics, Bremen, Germany). For the LC-MS/MS analysis, 
water with 0.1% FA and ACN with 0.1% FA were used as the </p>

<p>mobile phase. The peptide sample was injected into a pulled 
tip column (15 cm ×100 μm inner diameter) containing C18 
Reprosil, 5 μm particles (Nikkyo Technos, Tokyo, Japan), 
and separated online using increasing amounts of acetonitrile 
containing 0.1% FA (mobile phase B) at 300 nL/min. Gradi-
ent conditions were as follows: 5%-34% B (0-25 minutes), 
34%-60% B (25-30 minutes), 80% B held for 4 minutes, 
and 5%-80% B (1 minute). 
The identification results were obtained from Mascot. 
The criteria used for protein quantitation were as follows: two 
unique peptide hits, two quantitative peptides, and disabling 
of outlier removal. The reporter ion ratio for each identified 
peptide was determined by <rs type="software">Mascot</rs>. The loess and global 
median normalization were used to process the proteom-
ics data. Data were log 2 transformed and analyzed on both 
peptide and protein level. Statistical significance of observed 
fold-change ratios was determined by one sample t-test. 
P-values ,0.05 were considered statistically significant for 
proteins. Fold change higher than 1.0 is for upregulation or 
lower than 1.0 is for downregulation. </p>

<p>gene/protein set enrichment, network, 
and pathway analyses </p>

<p>The molecular function of transcripts and proteins was 
explored by <rs type="software">BiNGO</rs>, a <rs id="software-7" type="software">Cytoscape</rs> <rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-number">v3.1.1</rs> plugin. 
15 Pathway 
enrichment analysis of transcripts and proteins was per-
formed using the Database for Annotation, Visualization and 
Integrated Discovery and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and 
Genomes database. We considered regulated pathways only 
as statistically significant, if the P-value was #0.05. We 
applied <rs type="software">Metscape</rs> to analyze the integrated pathway of gene, 
protein, and metabolomics data. 
16 We also applied <rs type="software">ClueGO</rs>, 
a <rs type="software">Cytoscape</rs> plugin, to explore the molecular function of the 
proteins. 
17 In the <rs id="software-11" type="software">MetaboAnalyst</rs> <rs corresp="#software-11" type="version-date">3.0</rs>, the pathway analysis 
module combines the results from powerful pathway enrich-
ment analysis with the pathway topology analysis to help us 
identify the most relevant pathways involved in the conditions 
under this study. 
18 Using STRING 10, we generated interaction 
networks based on the overlapping proteins between the targets 
of BJF and proteomic measurements of BJF-treated rats. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Results and discussion 
Transcriptomics analysis results of BJF-
treated COPD rats </p>

<p>In the previous study, systems pharmacology successfully 
identified the bioactive ingredients and revealed the poten-
tial targets of the multiple components contained in BJF. 
Subsequently, we validated that BJF was effective for the </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Zhao et al </p>

<p>treatment of COPD and ventricular hypertrophy due to its 
inhibitory effect on the inflammatory cytokine, and hyper-
trophic factors expression, protease-antiprotease imbalance 
and collagen deposition, in vivo. 
7 In this study, to investigate 
the system-wide mechanism of BJF in treating COPD rats, 
we further examined the effect of BJF on transcriptional 
profiles of lung tissues. 
Using microarray-based RNA expression analysis, we 
detected ~41,000 expressed genes in lung tissues. There 
were 2,463 and 1,012 genes differently expressed at COPD 
model (versus control) and BJF treatment (versus COPD 
model) rats, respectively (Tables S1 and S2). These tran-
scripts regulated in lung tissues of COPD model rats could 
be mapped to various molecular functions such as regulation 
of oxidoreductase activity, nucleic acid binding, channel 
activity, fatty acid binding, glucose, or fatty acid metabolism 
(Figure 1A). However, transcripts regulated only in BJF-
treated rats were mapped to several molecular functions, 
such as kinase binding, protein complex binding, and insulin 
receptor binding (Figure 1B). 
In addition, in the COPD model group, the regulated 
genes were mapped to many different pathways, such as fatty 
acid metabolism, valine, leucine and isoleucine degradation, 
and propanoate metabolism (Table 1). The genes regulated 
in the BJF-treated group could be mapped to adherens junc-
tion, focal adhesion, endocytosis, wnt signaling pathway, 
etc. (Table 2). </p>

<p>Proteomics analysis results of BJF-treated 
COPD rats </p>

<p>To characterize the protein expression profiles of rats, 
expression levels of proteins were detected using LC-MS-
based proteomics. Comparing to those in healthy control 
rats, 192 proteins were identified in the COPD model rats 
(Table S3). After the treatment with BJF, comparing to 
those in the COPD model rats, 191 proteins were detected in 
BJF-treated rats (Table S4). The COPD rats (192 proteins) 
shared 100 common proteins with the BJF-treated rats (191 
proteins). Out of the 100 proteins, expression changes of 
42 proteins in the COPD model were inhibited by the BJF 
treatment (Table S5). These 42 proteins could be attributed 
to various molecular functions, such as oxidoreductase 
activity and antioxidant activity (peroxidase activity, cata-
lase activity, thioredoxin peroxidase activity; Figure 2A), 
which might be involved in the therapeutic mechanism of 
BJF in treating COPD. 
In addition, the 192 proteins regulated in COPD rats 
could be attributed to multiple molecular functions, including </p>

<p>phospholipase A2 inhibitor activity, peroxiredoxin activity, 
and oxidoreductase activity, acting on the aldehyde or oxo 
group of donors, etc. (Figure 2B). In the BJF-treated group, 
191 regulated proteins were mainly related to oxidoreductase 
activity, adrenergic receptor activity, receptor signaling 
protein activity, and extracellular ligand-gated ion channel 
activity (Figure 2C). 
In addition, the proteins regulated in COPD rats and 
BJF-treated rats were mapped to various pathways, such as 
focal adhesion, tight junction, adherens junction, and leuko-
cyte trans-endothelial migration (Tables 3 and 4). 
COPD is known to be accompanied by pulmonary inflam-
mation, oxidative stress, and muscle fiber dysfunction. </p>

<p>20,21 </p>

<p>These results suggested that BJF treatment could improve 
these COPD symptoms probably by regulating multiple 
molecular functions and pathways, such as oxidoreductase 
and antioxidant activity, focal adhesion, tight junction, 
adherens junction, and leukocyte trans-endothelial migra-
tion pathway. </p>

<p>holistic views on gene, protein, and 
metabolite data </p>

<p>In the previous study, we detected 49 and 30 metabolites 
regulated in the COPD model (versus control) and BJF-
treated (versus COPD model) groups, respectively. 
13 These 
metabolites were primarily involved in lipid metabolism 
(Figure 3A and B). In this study, a number of genes and 
proteins were identified, which deserve further attention to 
their system functions. Therefore, we further explored the 
system biological interpretation of the genes, proteins, and 
metabolites by integrating transcriptomics, proteomics, and 
metabolomics data. 
Using the <rs type="software">Metscape</rs> software, we investigated the latent 
relationships of the metabolite, gene, and protein measure-
ments by constructing the correlation network diagram. 
As shown in Figure 4A and B, according to the transcriptom-
ics and metabolomics data of COPD rats and BJF-treated rats, 
we constructed two gene-metabolite networks, which were 
mainly related to lipid metabolism and purine metabolism. 
Interestingly, a number of genes and most of the metabo-
lites were involved in lipid metabolism. Subsequently, we 
constructed two protein-metabolite networks based on the 
metabolomics and proteomics data of COPD rats and BJF-
treated rats. As shown in Figure 4C and D, we observed that 
the protein-metabolite networks could be divided into two 
primary groups: lipid metabolism and purine metabolism, 
and more than half of proteins and almost all of metabolites 
were involved in lipid metabolism. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>557 </p>

<p>Chinese herbal Bufei Jianpi formula for COPD </p>

<p>Figure 1 Molecular functions of regulated genes in lung tissues of rats with COPD and BJF-treated rats. 
Notes: <rs type="software">BingO</rs> mapped the predominant functional themes of the tested gene set on the gO hierarchy and produced an intuitive and a customizable visual representation of the results. The area of a node was proportional to the 
number of genes in the test set annotated to the corresponding gO category. (A) representative molecular function of regulated genes in lung tissues of rats with COPD. (B) representative molecular function of regulated genes in lung 
tissues of BJF-treated rats. 
Abbreviations: BJF, Bufei Jianpi formula; GO, gene ontology; FAD, flavin adenine dinucleotide. </p>

<p>Binding </p>

<p>Protein binding </p>

<p>Nucleic acid 
binding 
Nucleotide 
binding </p>

<p>Cofactor 
binding </p>

<p>Coenzyme 
binding </p>

<p>FAD binding </p>

<p>Acyl-CoA binding 
Fatty acid binding </p>

<p>Monocarboxylic </p>

<p>acid binding 
Carboxylic </p>

<p>acid binding </p>

<p>Fipid 
binding </p>

<p>RNA binding </p>

<p>Chaperone 
binding 
Transcription </p>

<p>repressor binding </p>

<p>Glutamate 
receptor 
binding </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Lonotropic </p>

<p>glutamate receptor 
binding </p>

<p>Receptor 
binding </p>

<p>Transcription </p>

<p>factor 
binding </p>

<p>Transcription 
cofactor 
activity </p>

<p>Transcription 
activator 
activity </p>

<p>Acyl-CoA 
dehydrogenase </p>

<p>activity 
Oxidoreductase activity, </p>

<p>acting on the CH-CH 
group of donors </p>

<p>Aspartate-tRNA </p>

<p>ligase activity 
Aminoacyl-tRNA </p>

<p>ligase activity </p>

<p>Transcription </p>

<p>regulator activity 
Structural molecule 
activity </p>

<p>Structural constituent 
of ribosome </p>

<p>Molecular function </p>

<p>Molecular function </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Binding </p>

<p>Protein binding </p>

<p>Protein C-terminus 
binding </p>

<p>Protein complex 
binding </p>

<p>Insulin receptor 
binding </p>

<p>Enzyme 
binding </p>

<p>Kinase 
binding </p>

<p>Receptor 
binding </p>

<p>Catalytic 
activity </p>

<p>Lyase 
activity </p>

<p>Ligase 
activity </p>

<p>Oxidoreductase </p>

<p>activity 
Ligase activity, forming 
Carbon-oxygen bonds </p>

<p>Ligase activity, forming 
aminoacyl-tRNA and </p>

<p>related compounds </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>558 </p>

<p>Zhao et al </p>

<p>All of the abovementioned results indicated that lipid 
metabolism disorders might play a critical role in the COPD 
development and BJF intervention in a preclinical setting. 
To explore the system relationships of the transcript and 
protein measurements, we compared the significant pathways 
derived from transcriptomics and proteomics data of COPD 
rats, and identified three common pathways including fatty 
acid metabolism, propanoate metabolism, and valine, leucine, 
and isoleucine degradation (Tables 1 and 3). In addition, the 
transcripts and proteins regulated in BJF-treated rats were 
mapped into three common pathways: adherens junction, 
tight junction, regulation of actin cytoskeleton, and dilated 
cardiomyopathy (Tables 2 and 4). </p>

<p>Table 1 analyzed pathways of transcriptomics data regulated in 
lung tissues of rats with COPD </p>

<p>Term 
Count % 
P-value </p>

<p>Valine, leucine, and isoleucine degradation 15 
0.1128 1.43e-06 
Propanoate metabolism 
12 
0.0902 7.33e-06 </p>

<p>ribosome 
19 
0.1429 1.02e-05 </p>

<p>endocytosis 
30 
0.2256 1.06e-04 </p>

<p>Fatty acid metabolism 
11 
0.0827 4.45e-04 </p>

<p>graft-versus-host disease 
12 
0.0902 5.80e-04 </p>

<p>Viral myocarditis 
16 
0.1203 8.03e-04 </p>

<p>antigen processing and presentation 
16 
0.1203 9.08e-04 </p>

<p>Type I diabetes mellitus 
12 
0.0902 0.002375 </p>

<p>allograft rejection 
11 
0.0827 0.002977 </p>

<p>aminoacyl-trna biosynthesis 
9 
0.0677 0.005296 </p>

<p>Butanoate metabolism 
8 
0.0602 0.006394 </p>

<p>autoimmune thyroid disease 
11 
0.0827 0.008398 </p>

<p>Cell cycle 
17 
0.1278 0.012759 </p>

<p>Beta-alanine metabolism 
6 
0.0451 0.015285 </p>

<p>Other glycan degradation 
5 
0.0376 0.021132 </p>

<p>limonene and pinene degradation 
4 
0.0301 0.035787 </p>

<p>p53 signaling pathway 
10 
0.0752 0.036731 </p>

<p>spliceosome 
15 
0.1128 0.038974 
Pyruvate metabolism 
7 
0.0526 0.049506 </p>

<p>Table 2 analyzed pathways of transcriptomics data regulated in 
lung tissues of Bufei-Jianpi-formula-treated rats </p>

<p>Term 
Count 
% 
P-value </p>

<p>renal cell carcinoma 
8 
1.5625 
0.002333 
endocytosis 
14 
2.7344 
0.002719 </p>

<p>adherens junction 
8 
1.5625 
0.003481 </p>

<p>Focal adhesion 
13 
2.5391 
0.00587 </p>

<p>Pathways in cancer 
17 
3.3203 
0.01044 </p>

<p>hedgehog signaling pathway 
6 
1.1719 
0.012268 </p>

<p>huntington's disease 
12 
2.3438 
0.012719 </p>

<p>Protein export 
3 
0.5859 
0.022752 </p>

<p>Wnt signaling pathway 
9 
1.7578 
0.040431 
Type II diabetes mellitus 
5 
0.9766 
0.041517 </p>

<p>Antioxidant activity 
Catalytic activity </p>

<p>Molecular function </p>

<p>Oxidoreductase activity </p>

<p>Protein 
binding </p>

<p>Binding </p>

<p>Guanyl nucleotide 
binding </p>

<p>Guanyl ribonucleotide </p>

<p>binding </p>

<p>Purine ribonucleotide </p>

<p>binding </p>

<p>Ribonucleotide </p>

<p>binding </p>

<p>Purine nucleotide 
binding 
Nucleotide 
binding </p>

<p>Nucleobase binding </p>

<p>GTP binding </p>

<p>Thioredoxin peroxidase 
activity </p>

<p>Catalase activity 
Peroxidase activity </p>

<p>Peroxiredoxin activity 
Flavin reductase 
activity </p>

<p>Trans-1,2-dihydrobenzene-1,2-diol </p>

<p>dehydrogenase activity </p>

<p>Biliverdin reductase 
activity 
3-hydroxy-2-methylbutyryl-CoA </p>

<p>dehydrogenase activity 
Indanol dehydrogenase </p>

<p>activity </p>

<p>Oxidoreductase activity, acting on </p>

<p>the CH-NH group of donors, NAD 
or NADP as acceptor </p>

<p>Oxidoreductase activity, acting on </p>

<p>the CH-CH group of donors, NAD 
or NADP as acceptor </p>

<p>Oxidoreductase activity, acting on </p>

<p>the CH-OH group of donors, NAD 
or NADP as acceptor </p>

<p>Oxidoreductase activity, acting on </p>

<p>the CH-NH group of donors </p>

<p>Oxidoreductase activity, acting on </p>

<p>the CH-OH group of donors 
Oxidoreductase activity, acting on </p>

<p>the CH-CH group of donors </p>

<p>Adenine binding </p>

<p>Actin binding </p>

<p>Chaperone binding 
Virion binding </p>

<p>Misfolded protein 
binding </p>

<p>Unfolded protein 
binding 
ATP-dependent protein 
binding </p>

<p>Protein binding involved in 
protein folding 
Ubiquitin protein ligase 
binding </p>

<p>Monocarboxylic acid 
binding 
Carboxylic acid 
binding 
Cofactor binding </p>

<p>Pyridoxal phosphate 
binding 
Steroid binding </p>

<p>Steroid dehydrogenase </p>

<p>activity </p>

<p>Oxidoreductase activity, acting on </p>

<p>paired donors, with incorporation </p>

<p>or reduction of molecular oxygen </p>

<p>Oxidoreductase activity, acting on 
peroxide as acceptor </p>

<p>Steroid dehydrogenase activity, 
acting on the CH-OH group of 
donors, NAD or NADP as </p>

<p>acceptor </p>

<p>Acetoacetyl-CoA reductase 
activity 
3-alpha-hydroxysteroid </p>

<p>dehydrogenase (B-specific) 
activity 
7-alpha-hydroxysteroid </p>

<p>dehydrogenase activity </p>

<p>20-alpha-hydroxysteroid </p>

<p>dehydrogenase activity </p>

<p>Vitamin D binding </p>

<p>Vitamin B6 binding 
Vitamin binding </p>

<p>Lipid binding </p>

<p>Bile acid 
binding </p>

<p>Enzyme binding 
Cytoskeletal protein 
binding </p>

<p>Purine 
binding </p>

<p>Toxin binding </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>559 </p>

<p>Chinese herbal Bufei Jianpi formula for COPD </p>

<p>Figure 2 Molecular functions of regulated proteins in lung tissues of COPD rats and BJF-treated rats. 
Notes: <rs type="software">BingO</rs> mapped the predominant functional themes of the 42 overlapping proteins between COPD rats and BJF-treated rats and produced an intuitive and a customizable visual representation of the results (A). The molecular 
functions of 192 regulated proteins in COPD rats (B), and 191 regulated proteins in BJF-treated rats (C) were analyzed by <rs type="software">CluegO</rs>: functionally grouped network with terms as nodes linked, and functionally related groups partially 
overlap; the node size represents the term enrichment significance. 
Abbreviation: BJF, Bufei Jianpi formula. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>560 </p>

<p>Zhao et al </p>

<p>Table 3 analyzed pathways of proteomics data regulated in lung 
tissues of rats with COPD </p>

<p>Term 
Count % 
P-value </p>

<p>glycolysis/gluconeogenesis 
10 
0.4179 6.64e-06 
hCM 
9 
0.3761 5.29e-05 
Dilated cardiomyopathy 
9 
0.3761 8.70e-05 
Pyruvate metabolism 
6 
0.2507 3.62e-04 
glyoxylate and dicarboxylate metabolism 4 
0.1672 7.99e-04 
Tight junction 
9 
0.3761 0.001079 
Citrate cycle (TCa cycle) 
5 
0.2089 0.00125 
leukocyte transendothelial migration 
8 
0.3343 0.002374 
Focal adhesion 
10 
0.4179 0.003903 
Tryptophan metabolism 
5 
0.2089 0.004803 
Valine, leucine, and isoleucine degradation 5 
0.2089 0.006122 
adherens junction 
6 
0.2507 0.00651 
Cardiac muscle contraction 
6 
0.2507 0.008115 
Propanoate metabolism 
4 
0.1672 0.015539 
Prion diseases 
4 
0.1672 0.018217 
Fatty acid metabolism 
4 
0.1672 0.029489 
arVC 
5 
0.2089 0.030762 
Purine metabolism 
7 
0.2925 0.03707 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: arVC, arrhythmogenic right ventricular cardiomyopathy; hCM, 
hypertrophic cardiomyopathy; TCa, tricarboxylic acid. </p>

<p>Table 4 analyzed pathways of proteomics data regulated in lung 
tissues of Bufei-Jianpi-formula-treated rats </p>

<p>Term 
Count % 
P-value </p>

<p>Focal adhesion 
16 
9.0395 5.73e-07 
Tight junction 
13 
7.3446 1.26e-06 
adherens junction 
9 
5.0847 2.66e-05 
regulation of actin cytoskeleton 
14 
7.9096 3.54e-05 
leukocyte transendothelial migration 
10 
5.6497 1.09e-04 
hCM 
8 
4.5198 4.49e-04 
Dilated cardiomyopathy 
8 
4.5198 6.83e-04 
eCM-receptor interaction 
7 
3.9548 0.002147 
Prion diseases 
5 
2.8249 0.002534 
glycolysis/gluconeogenesis 
7 
3.9548 0.002584 
arVC 
6 
3.3898 0.007467 
antigen processing and presentation 
6 
3.3898 0.01515 
Cardiac muscle contraction 
5 
2.8249 0.040267 
Valine, leucine, and isoleucine degradation 4 
2.2599 0.040457 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: arVC, arrhythmogenic right ventricular cardiomyopathy; eCM, 
extracellular matrix; hCM, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. </p>

<p>Integrating systems pharmacology, 
transcriptomics, proteomics, and 
metabolomics data </p>

<p>In the previous study, systems pharmacology successfully 
identified 175 targets of the active compounds contained 
in BJF. 
7 To investigate the system mechanism of BJF in 
treating COPD, we integrated transcriptomics, proteomics, 
and metabolomics data streams with systems pharmacology 
to provide a globe view of therapeutic mechanism of BJF 
treatment. </p>

<p>In this article, we first analyzed the overlapping proteins 
between the targets of BJF and transcript measurements of 
BJF-treated rats. As shown in Figure 5A, there were seven 
overlapping proteins (VEGFA, SLC6A2, ADRA2B, gyrB, 
CYCS, ampC, and katA) between them, which were asso-
ciated with various biological functions, such as vascular 
endothelial growth factor receptor 1 binding, chemoattractant 
activity, and G-protein-coupled amine receptor activity. 
Subsequently, we identified eleven overlapping proteins 
(GSTM1, GSTP1, CTSD, MPO, HSPA5, CAT, ampC, kata, 
XDH, SOD1, and gyrB) between the targets of BJF and 
proteomic measurements of BJF-treated rats. Interestingly, 
the molecular functions of eleven overlapping proteins were 
mainly related to oxidoreductase and antioxidant activity 
(Figure 5B). However, no overlapping pathways were 
detected between the potential targets and transcript/protein 
measurements of BJF-treated rats. Finally, we constructed a 
correlation network diagram to investigate the latent relation-
ships of the potential targets and metabolomics measurements 
of BJF-treated rats. In Figure 6, the results show that the 
network mainly consisted of lipid metabolism pathways. 
As discussed earlier, we constructed a system-level 
picture of the therapeutic mechanism of BJF by integrating 
systems pharmacology, transcript, protein, and metabolite 
datasets. As shown in Figure 7, the systems pharmacology 
targets and three-omics data were integrated, and the com-
prehensive picture was mainly consisted of four groups: 
lipid metabolism, inflammatory response, cell junction, and 
oxidative stress. In the previous study, we found that the 
expression levels of interleukin (IL)-1β, IL-6, and tumor 
necrosis factor-α were significantly decreased by BJF treat-
ment. In addition, ERK, p38, JNK, and NF-κB were the 
potential targets of BJF. 
7 These results implied that BJF 
could achieve its ameliorative effect on COPD rats by sup-
pressing inflammatory responses. In this study, upon BJF 
treatment, arachidonic acid metabolism and linoleic acid 
metabolism were the significant deregulated pathways in 
lung tissues. In these pathways, the level of lecithin, linoleate, 
9-OXOODE, γ-linolenate, LXA4, LTB4, and PGE2 were 
suppressed by BJF treatment. Moreover, these metabolites, 
such as LXA4, LTB4, PGE2, and PGF2α, were involved 
in inflammatory processes in the airways of patients with 
COPD. 
22-25 In addition, according to the systems pharmacol-
ogy predictions, ALOX5 PTGS1/2, LTA4H, and AKR1C3, 
the important enzymes involved in these deregulated path-
ways were the potential targets of BJF. Therefore, the results 
indicated that BJF achieved its anti-inflammatory activity 
by suppressing the lipid metabolism and the production of 
pre-inflammatory cytokines. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>561 </p>

<p>Chinese herbal Bufei Jianpi formula for COPD </p>

<p>Figure 3 Pathway analysis of the metabolites regulated in lung tissues of COPD rats and BJF-treated rats. 
Notes: global metabolic disorders of the most relevant pathways were revealed using the <rs type="software">Metaboanalyst</rs>. a google-map style interactive visualization system was 
implemented to facilitate data exploration and generate pathway views. (A) representative pathway analysis of the metabolites in lung tissues of COPD rats. (B) representative 
pathway analysis of the metabolites in lung tissues of BJF-treated rats. 
Abbreviation: BJF, Bufei Jianpi formula. </p>

<p>Figure 4 Correlation networks of the metabolites, genes, and proteins regulated in lung tissues of COPD rats and BJF-treated rats. 
Notes: The compound reaction network with compounds (the pink and red hexagons) and metabolic enzymes (the gray and blue rounds) as nodes and reactions as edges, 
was constructed using <rs type="software">Metscape</rs>. Inputted compounds are shown in red, inputted genes and proteins are shown in blue. existing compounds that populate the <rs type="software">Metscape</rs> 
system were shown in pink. existing genes and proteins were shown in gray. (A) representative metabolites-gene network of COPD model group. (B) representative 
metabolite-gene network of the BJF-treated group. (C) representative metabolites-protein network of the COPD model group. (D) representative metabolite-protein 
network of the BJF-treated group. 
Abbreviation: BJF, Bufei Jianpi formula. </p>

<p>Lipid metabolism 
Lipid metabolism </p>

<p>Lipid metabolism 
Lipid metabolism </p>

<p>Purine metabolism </p>

<p>Purine metabolism </p>

<p>Purine metabolism 
Purine metabolism </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>562 </p>

<p>Zhao et al </p>

<p>Figure 5 Molecular functions of the overlapping proteins. 
Notes: <rs type="software">BingO</rs> mapped the predominant functional themes of the tested protein set on the gO hierarchy and produced an intuitive and customizable visual representation of the results. The area of a node was proportional to the 
number of proteins in the test set annotated to the corresponding gO category. (A) representative molecular function of overlapping proteins between the potential targets and transcript measurements in lung tissues of BJF-treated 
rats. (B) representative molecular function of overlapping proteins between the potential targets and proteome measurements in lung tissues of BJF-treated rats. 
Abbreviation: BJF, Bufei Jianpi formula. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>563 </p>

<p>Chinese herbal Bufei Jianpi formula for COPD </p>

<p>Figure 6 Correlation networks of the metabolites regulated in BJF-treated rats and target proteins. 
Notes: The compound reaction network with compounds (the pink and red hexagons) and metabolic enzymes (the gray and blue rounds) as nodes and reactions as edges, 
was constructed using <rs type="software">Metscape</rs>. Inputted compounds are shown in red, and inputted target proteins are shown in blue. existing compounds that populate the <rs type="software">Metscape</rs> 
system were shown in pink. existing proteins were shown in gray. 
Abbreviation: BJF, Bufei Jianpi formula. </p>

<p>Figure 7 Comprehensive analysis of the potential targets of BJF, transcriptomics, proteomics, and metabolomics regulations in lung tissues of BJF-treated rats. 
Notes: The potential targets, transcriptomics, proteomics, and metabolomics data are presented as rectangles with different colors. red arrow stands for upregulated, blue 
arrow for downregulated, and gray rectangle for unregulated. 
Abbreviation: BJF, Bufei Jianpi formula. </p>

<p>α </p>

<p>α 
β 
κ 
α β </p>

<p>α </p>

<p>β </p>

<p>α </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>564 </p>

<p>Zhao et al </p>

<p>The inflammatory responses associated with COPD 
are believed to be triggered by oxidative stress. 
26,27 In this 
study, we detected eleven overlapping proteins between the 
targets of BJF and proteomic measurements of BJF-treated 
rats, which were mainly involved in oxidative stress. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>For instance, the antioxidant proteins such as SOD1 and 
GSTP1 were involved in the pathogenesis of COPD, </p>

<p>29-31 </p>

<p>which were upregulated by BJF treatment. Additionally, </p>

<p>increased myeloperoxidase levels are associated with rapid 
lung function decline. 
32,33 In proteomic study, we found that 
the expression levels of myeloperoxidase were decreased by 
BJF treatment. These results suggested that BJF achieved 
its anti-inflammatory activity by regulating the oxidative 
stress status. 
Moreover, focal adhesion, the overlapping pathway 
among transcriptomic measurements, proteomic measure-
ments, and the potential targets of BJF were significantly 
regulated by BJF treatment (Table 5). For instance, FAK, 
PI3K, JNK, c-Jun, and ERK1/2, involved in the pathogenesis 
of COPD progression, 
34-36 were the potential targets of BJF. 
Overall, we demonstrated that BJF provided protec-
tive and therapeutic benefits against COPD by regulating 
multiple biological functions, such as lipid metabolism, 
oxidative stress, inflammatory response, and focal adhesion 
pathway. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Three-omics technologies have emerged as the promising 
tools to find the complex mechanism of TCM in the form 
of systems biology. 
37,38 Systems pharmacology is applied to 
conduct a comprehensive analysis of the dynamic interac-
tions between the components of TCM and a biological 
system. Combining systems pharmacology, transcriptomics, 
proteomics, and metabolomics data is becoming more impor-
tant to detect the system-level therapeutic mechanism of 
TCM. However, attempts thus far to integrate system biology 
data streams have been met with limited success. 
In this study, we first characterized the transcriptomic and 
proteomic profiles of the lung tissues derived from COPD rats 
and BJF-treated rats. The regulated transcripts and proteins 
were attributed to multiple functions, such as oxidoreductase 
activity and antioxidant activity. The metabolomics profiles 
of the lung tissues were previously characterized, and the 
regulated metabolites were mainly involved in lipid metabo-
lism. Finally, we sought to obtain a comprehensive picture 
of systems pharmacology, transcriptomics, proteomics, and 
metabolomics data. The potential targets derived from systems 
pharmacology and three-omics data were integrated, and the 
system-level results indicated that BJF achieved its ameliora-
tive effect over COPD via mechanisms that might be dependent 
on its system-wide effects on lipid metabolism, inflammatory 
response, cell junction pathways, and oxidative stress. 
In summary, integrative application of systems phar-
macology, transcriptome, proteome, and metabolome has 
potential implications toward understanding the system 
mechanism of action of TCM. </p>

<p>Table 5 analyzed pathways of the potential target </p>

<p>Term 
Count 
% 
P-value </p>

<p>neuroactive ligand-receptor 
interaction </p>

<p>28 
0.7718 
2.33e-11 </p>

<p>Pathways in cancer 
26 
0.7166 
1.25e-07 
Bladder cancer 
10 
0.2756 
4.18e-07 
Calcium signaling pathway 
18 
0.4961 
6.48e-07 
Prostate cancer 
12 
0.3308 
6.68e-06 
als 
9 
0.2481 
2.95e-05 
non-small-cell lung cancer 
9 
0.2481 
3.39e-05 
glioma 
9 
0.2481 
1.06e-04 
small-cell lung cancer 
10 
0.2756 
1.49e-04 
Colorectal cancer 
10 
0.2756 
1.49e-04 
gap junction 
10 
0.2756 
2.33e-04 
Pancreatic cancer 
9 
0.2481 
2.73e-04 
VegF signaling pathway 
9 
0.2481 
3.63e-04 
Metabolism of xenobiotics by 
cytochrome P450 </p>

<p>8 
0.2205 
4.93e-04 </p>

<p>Drug metabolism 
8 
0.2205 
6.03e-04 
Progesterone-mediated oocyte 
maturation </p>

<p>9 
0.2481 
9.17e-04 </p>

<p>T-cell receptor signaling pathway 
10 
0.2756 
9.80e-04 
Insulin signaling pathway 
11 
0.3032 
0.001285 
Prion diseases 
6 
0.1654 
0.001287 
Melanoma 
8 
0.2205 
0.001367 
gnrh signaling pathway 
9 
0.2481 
0.002145 
Focal adhesion 
13 
0.3583 
0.002765 
nOD-like receptor signaling pathway 
7 
0.1929 
0.003321 
erbB signaling pathway 
8 
0.2205 
0.004394 
Thyroid cancer 
5 
0.1378 
0.004572 
Type II diabetes mellitus 
6 
0.1654 
0.004846 
alzheimer's disease 
11 
0.3032 
0.005136 
endometrial cancer 
6 
0.1654 
0.007473 
arginine and proline metabolism 
6 
0.1654 
0.008098 
neurotrophin signaling pathway 
9 
0.2481 
0.008989 
Toll-like receptor signaling pathway 
8 
0.2205 
0.009847 
arachidonic acid metabolism 
6 
0.1654 
0.010189 
graft-versus-host disease 
5 
0.1378 
0.013197 
Oocyte meiosis 
8 
0.2205 
0.015298 
Vascular smooth muscle contraction 
8 
0.2205 
0.016754 
apoptosis 
7 
0.1929 
0.016888 
p53 signaling pathway 
6 
0.1654 
0.022214 
renal cell carcinoma 
6 
0.1654 
0.024849 
Cell cycle 
8 
0.2205 
0.028683 
glutathione metabolism 
5 
0.1378 
0.030289 
Fc epsilon rI signaling pathway 
6 
0.1654 
0.037359 
MaPK signaling pathway 
12 
0.3308 
0.0418 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: als, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis; nOD, nucleotide 
oligomerization domain; VegF, vascular endothelial growth factor; MaPK, mitogen-
activated protein kinase. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>565 </p>

<p>Chinese herbal Bufei Jianpi formula for COPD </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The research is supported by the National Natural Science 
Fund of China (influence and long-term effects of three 
Tiao-Bu Fei-Shen therapies in rats with COPD on regulation 
of multidimensional molecular network, No 81130062). </p>

<p>Authors contributions </p>

<p>JSL and SYL designed the outline of the study. PZ performed 
experiments, conceived the study, wrote the draft of the 
manuscript, and revised the manuscript. LPY, YGT, and YL 
were involved in performing experiments, acquisition of data, 
and statistical analysis. All authors contributed toward data 
analysis, drafting and critically revising the paper and agree 
to be accountable for all aspects of the work. All the authors 
read and approved the final version of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this study. </p>



<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-chronic-obstructive-pulmonary-disease-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of COPD is an international, peer-reviewed 
journal of therapeutics and pharmacology focusing on concise rapid 
reporting of clinical studies and reviews in COPD. Special focus is given 
to the pathophysiological processes underlying the disease, intervention 
programs, patient focused education, and self management protocols. </p>

<p>This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, MedLine and CAS. The 
manuscript management system is completely online and includes a 
very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>