<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4917775" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Study Design: Retrospective study. 
Purpose: To compare the neurological outcome of transforaminal debridement and interbody fusion with transpedicular decompres-
sion for treatment of thoracic and lumbar spinal tuberculosis. 
Overview of Literature: Few articles have addressed the impact of neurological recovery in patients with tuberculosis who were 
treated by two different operative methods via the posterior-only approach. 
Methods: Clinical and radiographic results of one-stage posterior instrumented spinal fusion for treatment of tuberculous spondylo-
discitis with neurological deficits were reviewed and analyzed from 2009 to 2013. The extensive (E) group consisted of patients who 
received transforaminal debridement and interbody fusion, whereas transpedicular decompression was performed on limited (L) group. 
Rapid recovery was improvement of at least one Frankel grade within 6 weeks after operation. Otherwise, it was slow recovery. 
Results: All 39 patients had improved neurological signs. The median follow-up period was 24 months. Proportionately younger pa-
tients (under 65 years of age) received extensive surgery (15 of 18, 83.3% vs. 11 of 21, 52.4%; p=0.04). The mean operative time and 
blood loss in the group E were higher than in the group L (both p&lt;0.01). With regard to type of procedure, especially at thoracic and 
thoracolumbar spine, patients who underwent extensive surgery had rapid neurological recovery significantly different from those of 
limited surgery (p=0.01; Relative Risk, 3.06; 95% Confidence Interval, 1.13 to 8.29). 
Conclusions: Transforaminal debridement and interbody fusion provides more rapid neurological recovery in patients with thoracic 
and thoracolumbar spinal tuberculosis compared to transpedicular decompression. </p>

<p>Spinal tuberculosis accounts for approximately 50% to </p>

<p>66% of all cases of osteoarticular tuberculosis and imag-
ing is important for characterizing lesions, as osteolytic 
patterns and destructive behaviors likely to produce ky-</p>

<p>Weera Sudprasert et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2016;10(3):543-552 </p>

<p>phosis and instability [1,2]. The response to non-operative 
treatment is occasionally slow and kyphotic deformity is 
likely to progress during the follow-up period [3]. There-
fore, surgery is superior, particularly in cases when non-
operative management has failed or severe kyphosis/ 
instability has developed with or without neurological 
deficit [4,5]. Anterior radical surgery (i.e., the Hong Kong 
operation) for spinal tuberculosis reported by Hodgson 
and Stock has been considered the gold standard [6,7]. 
The most important advantage of the traditional approach 
is that it allows a full radical resection of the infectious 
focus [5]. However, a review of the recent literature shows 
the evidence supporting autofusion of anterior spinal seg-
ment affected by tuberculous (TB) disease can be obtained 
without anterior surgery [8-11]. 
Transforaminal thoracic interbody fusion or transfo-
raminal lumbar interbody fusion has been modified to 
treat spinal tuberculosis in a one-stage posterior transfo-
raminal debridement, interbody fusion plus pedicle screw 
instrumentation [8,10-14]. Moreover, the posterior trans-
pedicular approach has recently become popular as an 
alternative method and a less invasive surgical procedure 
[15-17]. 
In the present study, the difference of the two surgical 
procedures regarding the treatment of TB spondylodiscitis 
by the single-stage posterior approach and instrumented 
stabilization was analyzed in terms of rapidity of neuro-
logical recovery, general surgical outcomes, radiological 
results and postoperative complications. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>The study was approved by the Institutional Review Board 
of Maharat Nakhon Ratchasima hospital. The electronic 
medical records of 40 consecutive patients admitted with 
neurological deficits resulting from TB spondylodiscitis 
during a 48-month time period from January 2009 to 
January 2013 were retrospectively reviewed. Confirmation 
of the diagnosis by histopathology, Mycobacterium tuber-
culosis culture and/or polymerase chain reaction (PCR) 
for tuberculosis from surgical biopsy specimens was avail-
able in all cases. Patients were included in the analysis if 
they had a follow-up of more than 12 months. A 47-year-
old female with alcoholic liver cirrhosis who died of spon-
taneous bacterial peritonitis and gram-negative bacillus 
sepsis 6 months after extensive surgery was excluded from 
the study. A total of 39 cases were included; all were oper-</p>

<p>ated on by a single surgeon (W.S.). 
The extensive (E) group was composed of patients with 
severe destructive vertebral lesions and low anesthetic 
risk. One -stage posterior transforaminal debridement 
and interbody fusion with bone graft was carried out to 
achieve sufficient stability. Laminectomy was done and the 
entire space between the medial walls of the pedicles was 
exposed. Articular process removal and pediculectomy 
on the severely affected side of lesion were performed to 
reach the diseased portion of vertebral bodies. Unilateral 
costotransversectomy was utilized in thoracic spines and 
thoracic nerve roots on the focal level were sacrificed for 
better exposure. In lumbar lesions, sufficient exposure for 
debridement was obtained deliberately by unilateral total 
facetectomy. The location of the lumbar nerve root was 
identified to ensure that postoperative nerve palsy would 
not be encountered from iatrogenic injury. Curettes and 
burr drills were used to remove lesions including the in-
fected vertebral body sequestrum, necrotic intervertebral 
disc, pus and caseous granulation tissue as thoroughly as 
possible. Autogenous corticocancellous chips were placed 
around the anterior two-thirds of the space created by de-
bridement and a tricortical iliac bone graft was inserted to 
reconstruct the anterior column. Finally, posterolateral ar-
throdesis of the instrumented levels with local autologous 
bone was undertaken (Fig. 1). 
The limited (L) group included patients who had less 
vertebral destruction and serious medical condition. This 
group could be treated with single-stage posterior de-
compression by transpedicular curettage and additional 
decompression procedures included hemi-laminectomy 
or complete laminectomy. The paraspinal abscess was 
drained using curettes and the infected bone was removed 
using pituitary forceps. This step was performed on the 
basis of more neurological and radiological signs. The pat-
terns were similar in the thoracic and lumbar regions. No 
attempt at radical debridement was undertaken and no 
anterior reconstruction with a strut graft was carried out. 
Adequate stability and positively influenced the healing of 
bone defect were accomplished via long-segment instru-
mentation in spite of a small dead space often encoun-
tered at the early stage. In the final step, posterolateral fu-
sion using autologous local bone graft of the instrumented 
segments was performed. 
The global standard screw (GSS, GS Medical Co., Ltd, 
Geumcheon-gu, Seoul, Korea) pedicle screw system was 
used in all patients. Screws were inserted in the usual </p>

<p>Transforaminal debridement for spinal tuberculosis </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>



<p>manner and also placed in pathological vertebrae if the 
upper part of the vertebral body and the pedicle was not 
involved. The patients could ambulate with external or-
thotic support comprising thoracolumbar or lumbosacral 
orthosis for at least 3 months postoperatively. All cases 
received isoniazid (I, 5 mg/kg), rifampicin (R, 10 mg/ 
kg), pyrazinamide (Z, 25 mg/kg) and ethambutol (E, 15 
mg/kg) for the first 2 months (2IRZE), then I/R/E for at 
least 10 months later (10IRE) until the abnormal levels of 
C-reactive protein (CRP) and erythrocyte sedimentation 
rate (ESR) as markers of infection returned to normal or 
were significantly decreased after treatment. All patients 
remained in laboratory monitoring for at least 12 months 
postoperatively. Neurological outcome was evaluated by 
the Frankel classification [18]. Rapid recovery represented 
by improvement of at least one Frankel grade within 6 
weeks after the surgery. Otherwise it was slow recovery. 
The visual analogue scale (VAS) score was used to assess 
pain symptoms [19]. Vertebral body loss (VBL) and angle 
of localized spinal deformity were measured as previously 
described [14]. Sagittal alignment was measured for each 
case on plain lateral radiographs by Cobb angle before 
and after the operation and at the final follow-up. The as-</p>

<p>sessment of bony fusion was conducted as previously de-
scribed [20]. Criteria were based on the standard of bone 
fusion: continuity of bony trabeculae bridging across the 
bone graft space, fusion segments not active (&lt;3 degrees) 
on a flexion-extension radiograph and no gap at interface. 
All measurements were done by one of the authors (K.C.) 
who did not participate in the surgeries. 
Baseline characteristics are presented as mean (±stan-
dard deviation) or median (interquartile range, IQR) 
for continuous variables and frequency (percentage) for 
categorical variables. Independent t-test was used for the 
comparison of the mean continuous numerical data and 
Mann-Whitney U test was used for the comparison of the 
medians. Categorical variable presented as percentages 
were analyzed using the chi-square test or Fisher's exact 
test when expected counts were less than five. Statistical 
analysis was performed to compare the outcomes using 
software program <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> for Macintosh <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 12</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Stata-Corp LP</rs>, College Station, TX, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>There were 25 men and 14 women with overall mean age </p>

<p>Fig. 1. (A) Extensive surgery was performed on a 63-year-old male with low back pain and paraplegia for 2 months, with transforaminal de-
bridement and interbody fusion using an autogenous iliac crest bone graft (white arrow), postoperative radiographs showing well-corrected 
sagittal alignment. (B) Preoperative magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the thoracic spine, T2-weighted in the sagittal and axial plane 
show typical pattern of T11-T12 vertebral destruction with intervening disc involvement, and severe vertebral collapse is noted (black ar-
row). Postoperative MRI shows a wide thoracic canal and well-maintained sagittal alignment at the 12-month follow-up. (C) Extension and 
flexion radiographs of the same patient at the 24-month follow-up. </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>Weera Sudprasert et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2016;10(3):543-552 </p>

<p>of 53.8±17.6 years (range, 16 to 82 years). Group E was 
significantly younger than group L with a mean age of 
47.2±19.2 years vs. 59.4±14.4 years (p=0.03). The majority 
of the patients (83.3%) that underwent extensive surgery 
were in the young age group (under 65 years of age), with 
statistical significance (p=0.04). Patients were followed-
up for a median of 24 months (IQR, 18 to 30 months). 
The overall median preoperative CRP and ESR values 
were 78.9 mm/hr (IQR, 63.5 to 95.3 mm/hr) and 77 mg/ 
L (IQR, 64 to 93 mg/L) respectively. Levels of both mark-
ers decreased gradually to normal values at 12 months. 
Significant differences in the mean operative time and 
intraoperative blood loss were observed between both 
operative groups (both p&lt;0.01). No significant differences 
were noted between the two groups for length of stay in 
the hospital and postoperative hospitalizations. The most 
commonly found comorbidity was water-electrolyte im-
balance (53.8%), followed by diabetes mellitus (35.9%) 
and anemia from chronic disease (33.3%). Underlying 
medical illnesses were demonstrated in all 21 (100%) pa-
tients in group L, while medical comorbidities had been 
recorded in 14 (77.8%) patients in group E; the difference 
between the groups was statistically significant (p=0.04). 
At weeks 2 and 6, VAS scores significantly decreased 
in both groups as compared to the preoperative scores 
(all p&lt;0.01). There was a significant difference observed 
between the E and L group at 2 weeks (p=0.02), but no 
significant difference between groups at 6 weeks follow-
up evaluation. Initial VBL was significantly higher in 
group E vs. group L (0.6, IQR 0.5 to 1.1 vs. 0.4, IQR 0.2 
to 0.7; p=0.02). The mean correction of sagittal index and 
the final loss of correction in both groups showed signifi-
cant differences (both p&lt;0.01). Anywise, the differences 
between the groups were not statistically significant. All 
the patients demonstrated solid fusion at the 12-month 
follow-up. The E group had a significantly higher inci-
dence of respiratory complications according to the using 
of postoperative ventilator when compared to the L group 
(61.1% vs. 23.8%, p=0.02), although the incidence of over-
all perioperative complications did not differ significantly 
between the groups. Tables 1 and 2 summarize the results 
of a comparative analysis between the groups. 
In group L, pseudarthrosis was suspected in one case 
due to broken rods which was observed on plain radio-
graph 4 months after surgery. This patient did not com-
plain of any back pain or pain in his legs while postero-
lateral fusion was still achieved radiographically by the </p>

<p>longer time of greater than 12 months of follow-up; three-
dimensional reconstructions of computed tomography 
scan were used to confirm fusion evidence in this 29-year-
old male patient at 24 months postoperatively (Fig. 2). 
Another patient from group L (a 64-year-old male) was 
recommended to undergo repeated operation when a 
kyphotic deformity of adjacent segment abruptly pro-
gressed and the sites of noncontiguous relapse were seen 
on magnetic resonance image (MRI) scan 12 months after 
surgery, but he refused reoperation. Eventually, he was 
treated successfully with anti-TB drugs that extended an 
extra 12 months of therapy. 
At the final follow-up, all 39 patients in both groups ex-
hibited improved neurological function and did not dem-
onstrate any deterioration (Table 3). There were no differ-
ences in the rate of recovery between age group, duration 
of illness, severity according to Frankel grade, operated 
level and operative group (all p&gt;0.05). With regard to type 
of procedure, especially at thoracic and thoracolumbar 
spine, patients who were underwent extensive surgery had 
rapid neurological recovery significantly different from 
those of limited surgery (p=0.01; relative risk, 3.06; 95% 
confidence interval, 1.13 to 8.29) (Table 4). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The diagnosis of spinal tuberculosis can be established on 
indolent onset of clinical symptoms, typical laboratory 
tests and compatible plain radiographic findings [1,2]. 
MRI is an important diagnostic tool for characterizing 
paravertebral and/or intraspinal extension of the disease 
prior to performing a surgical biopsy [21]. The microbio-
logical diagnosis consists of both conventional methods 
(acid-fast microscopy, culture for anti-TB drug-suscep-
tibility testing) and modern molecular techniques such 
as PCR on the biopsy specimens which are also valuable 
means for confirmation of diagnosis [22]. The treatment 
of spinal tuberculosis must be based on the use of effective 
anti-TB drugs, and early surgical decompression plays an 
important role in treating patients who suffer from severe 
pain and/or marked neurological impairment [3-5,22,23]. 
The surgical trend for Pott's paraplegia has constantly 
evolving as modern posterior spinal instrumentation 
which provides immediate stability and allows rapid pa-
tient mobilization [24]. With the minimal risk of anesthe-
sia and with the less invasive spinal techniques, several in-
vestigators have started to report a wide variety of surgical </p>

<p>Transforaminal debridement for spinal tuberculosis </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>



<p>procedures from this posterior approach and fixation to 
the treatment of TB spondylitis [8,10-17]. Moreover, with 
the evidence suggesting that TB lesions that almost always 
affect the anterior column may achieve spontaneous fu-
sion, the posterior approach represents a possible alter-
native surgical procedure in patients with less involved 
spinal tuberculosis [9,10]. Several spinal surgeons have </p>

<p>advocated primary placement of transpedicular instru-
mentation for providing posterior stability and recovering 
activities of daily living after the operation [24]. Addition-
ally, posterior pedicle screw instrumentation with fusion 
may be able to encourage neurological recovery because 
rigid stabilization enhances neurological improvement in 
traumatic spinal cord injury [25]. </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline characteristics of 39 patients </p>

<p>Variable 
Extensive group (n=18) 
Limited group (n=21) 
p-value </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
47.2±19.2 
59.4±14.4 
0.03 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Age 
0.04 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>≥65 yr 
3 (16.7) 
10 (47.6) </p>

<p>&lt;65 yr 
15 (83.3) 
11 (52.4) </p>

<p>Sex 
0.33 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>Male 
13 (72.2) 
12 (57.1) </p>

<p>Female 
5 (27.8) 
9 (42.9) </p>

<p>Bodyweight (kg) 
50.5 (48.8-59.3) 
52 (49.5-60) 
0.64 </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Onset of illness (wk) 
20 (8-36) 
8 (4-34) 
0.07 </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Time of onset of weakness (wk) 
2 (1-8) 
2 (1-4) 
0.73 </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Level of spondylodiscitis 
0.37 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>Lumbar 
6 (33.3) 
10 (47.6) </p>

<p>Thoracic and thoracolumbar 
12 (66.7) 
11 (52.4) </p>

<p>Vertebral body disease 
2 (2-3) 
2 (2-2) 
0.45 </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Vertebral body height loss 
0.6 (0.5-1.1) 
0.4 (0.2-0.7) 
0.02 </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Preoperative Frankel scale 
0.51 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>A: complete motor and sensory loss below the lesion 
1 (5.6) 
3 (14.3) </p>

<p>B: no motor function, but some sensation preserved 
6 (33.3) 
6 (28.6) </p>

<p>C: residual motor function but no practical use 
2 (11.1) 
5 (23.8) </p>

<p>D: useful motor function below the lesion 
9 (50) 
7 (33.3) </p>

<p>E: normal motor and sensory function 
0 
0 </p>

<p>Preoperative VAS 
8 (6-8) 
7 (6-9) 
0.73 </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Incidence of medical comorbidities 
14 (77.8) 
21 (100) 
0.04 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Comorbidities </p>

<p>Water-electrolyte imbalance 
8 (44.4) 
13 (61.9) 
0.28 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>Diabetes 
4 (22.2) 
10 (47.6) 
0.09 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Anemia in chronic disease 
4 (22.2) 
9 (42.9) 
0.15 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Respiratory affection 
6 (33.3) 
4 (19) 
0.26 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Cardiac affection 
2 (11.1) 
3 (14.3) 
0.58 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Liver affection 
0 
3 (14.3) 
0.14 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Renal impairment (CKD stage 4 or 5) 
0 
4 (19) 
0.07 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation, median (interquartile range) or number (%). 
VAS, visual analogue scales; CKD, Chronic kidney disease. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Result of two sample t-test; 
b) Result of Fisher's exact test; </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>Result of chi-square test; </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Result of Mann-Whitney U test. </p>

<p>Weera Sudprasert et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2016;10(3):543-552 </p>

<p>In the past, studies comparing the posterior approach 
with the anterior approach for spinal tuberculosis ob-
served no difference in the outcomes between groups. Pu 
et al. [13], investigated 47 cases of thoracic and lumbar 
tuberculosis patients; 25 cases were treated by posterior </p>

<p>debridement combined with interbody bone grafting and 
instrumentation, and the loss of kyphosis correction was 
also present in both groups (6.1° vs. 4.6° in posterior and 
anterior groups respectively). Lee et al. [15] studied 17 
individuals with established TB on thoracic and thora-</p>

<p>Table 2. Outcomes after surgical treatment </p>

<p>Variable 
Extensive group (n=18) 
Limited group (n=21) 
p-value </p>

<p>Operative time (min) 
173.1±72.6 
120.7±39.7 
0.00 </p>

<p>a),b) </p>

<p>Intraoperative blood loss (mL) 
1166.7±746.8 
409.5±290.1 
0.00 </p>

<p>a),b) </p>

<p>Follow up period (mo) 
25.5 (12.75-37.5) 
24 (18-25) 
0.57 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>Postoperative hospitalization (day) 
11.7±7.1 
16±9.9 
0.14 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Length of stay in the hospital (day) 
26.4±9.9 
32.4±13.9 
0.13 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Fusion level 
5 (4-6.25) 
4 (4-5) 
0.12 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>VAS </p>

<p>VAS at 2 weeks after operation 
3 (1-3) 
1 (1-2) 
0.02 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>VAS at 6 weeks after operation 
2 (1-2) 
1 (1-2) 
0.08 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>CRP (mg/L) </p>

<p>Initial CRP 
86.3 (70.9-96.9) 
74.9 (55.8-89.5) 
0.19 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>CRP at 12 months follow-up 
1.8 (0.8-4.9) 
4.9 (0.9-6.3) 
0.38 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>ESR (mm/hr) </p>

<p>Initial ESR 
81.5 (64.8-95.5) 
74 (63-91) 
0.54 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>ESR at 12 months follow-up 
16 (7-28.3) 
19 (12-30) 
0.51 </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>Sagittal index (°) </p>

<p>Preoperation 
14.4±17.1 
6.7±10.6 
0.09 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Postoperation 
2.7±13.3 
0.1±9.5 
0.48 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Last follow-up 
7.9±12.2 
3.3±9.1 
0.19 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Loss correction 
5.2±3.2 
3.2±2.9 
0.06 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Incidence of complications 
14 (77.8) 
19 (90.5) 
0.39 </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Complications </p>

<p>Postoperative mechanical ventilation 
11 (61.1) 
5 (23.8) 
0.02 </p>

<p>e) </p>

<p>Urinary tract infection 
6 (33.3) 
9 (42.9) 
0.54 </p>

<p>e) </p>

<p>Neurogenic bladder 
5 (27.8) 
9 (42.9) 
0.33 </p>

<p>e) </p>

<p>Hepatitis 
2 (11.1) 
4 (19) 
0.41 </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Pressure sore 
1 (5.6) 
2 (9.5) 
0.56 </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Pneumonia 
1 (5.6) 
1 (4.8) 
0.72 </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Dural tear 
1 (5.6) 
1 (4.8) 
0.72 </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Hematoma 
1 (5.6) 
0 
0.46 </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Implant-related 
0 
1 (4.8) 
0.54 </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Relapse 
0 
1 (4.8) 
0.54 </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation, median (interquartile range) or number (%). 
CRP, C-reactive protein; ESR, erythrocyte sedimentation rate; VAS, visual analogue scales. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Statistically significant with p&lt;0.01; </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Result of two sample t-test; </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>Result of Mann-Whitney U test; </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Result of Fisher's exact test; </p>

<p>e) </p>

<p>Result of chi-
square test. </p>

<p>Transforaminal debridement for spinal tuberculosis </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>



<p>columbar spine and reported that two or more vertebrae 
were involved in 94% of the patients, 10 of whom had 
undergone single-stage transpedicular decompression and 
posterior instrumentation. When the angle of kyphosis 
was &lt;30°, significant kyphosis correction was found. But, 
the loss of correction was considerable in both groups (6.1° 
and 4.5° in posterior and anterior group, respectively). 
In the present study, the loss of correction was similar 
to prior studies [8,13-16]. Zhang et al. [12] studied 14 
patients with upper thoracic tuberculosis; excellent neu-
rological results were observed after one-stage debride-
ment, combined interbody and instrumented fusion via 
posterior-only approach, and there was no significant loss 
of deformity correction at the final follow-up, with loss 
of correction being only 1.3°. The reasons for higher cor-
rection loss in the present study might be that TB lesions 
were not confined to only one segment, and placement 
of pedicle screws were attempted to fix inside the pedicle 
of the pathological vertebral body to reduce the extent 
of fixation, and also preserve more motion segments at 
the lumbar level [10]. The radiographic superiority of 
one-stage circumferential fusion using cage, especially in 
patients with lumbar spinal tuberculosis, might result in </p>

<p>more favorable long-term outcome [26]. Similar findings 
were also published by other researchers, while the total 
operative time was longer, blood loss was higher and the 
titanium mesh cage that was used was more costly in cases 
of circumferential fusion [27,28]. 
We offer several thoughts concerning the current one-
stage posterior surgery performed as follows. The pos-</p>

<p>Fig. 2. (A) Tuberculous spondylitis of T11-T12 (white arrowheads) and L5-S1 (black arrowheads) in a 29-year-old male patient, post-gadolin-
ium T1-weighted magnetic resonance image in sagittal and axial plane show typical pattern of two vertebral bodies destruction, irregular rim 
enhancing intervertebral disc is presented. (B) Anterior-posterior view of plain lumbar spine radiograph at 4 months after limited surgery re-
veals broken rods but he did not complain of any back pain or pain in his legs, while posterolateral fusion was still achieved radiographically 
on lateral extension and flexion view. (C) Three-dimensional computed tomography scan was used to confirm fusion evidence at 24 months 
postoperatively. </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>Table 3. Frankel grade according to procedures </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Frankel scale </p>

<p>A 
B 
C 
D 
E </p>

<p>Extensive group (n=18) </p>

<p>Preoperation 
1 
6 
2 
9 
0 </p>

<p>6 wk follow-up 
1 
2 
1 
6 
8 </p>

<p>12 mo follow-up 
0 
1 
1 
4 
12 </p>

<p>Limited group (n=21) </p>

<p>Preoperation 
3 
6 
5 
7 
0 </p>

<p>6 wk follow-up 
1 
5 
1 
6 
8 </p>

<p>12 mo follow-up 
0 
1 
4 
4 
12 </p>

<p>Values are presented as number. </p>

<p>Weera Sudprasert et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2016;10(3):543-552 </p>

<p>terior approach was relatively uncomplicated. The long-
segment instrumentation and posterolateral fusion could 
be successfully obtained stability in such a way that the 
spinal cord or nerve roots were not irritated and may pro-
mote efficient neurological recovery, thereby increasing 
mobility to hospitalized patients and decreasing compli-
cations of being in bed. The extensive clearance of case-
ous tissues that cause inflammatory response correlated 
with rapidly progressing recovery of function. Finally, the 
abrupt reduction of inflammation of neural elements was 
related to the improvement of disease activity and neuro-
logical grading. 
Results of the two posterior decompressive surgical 
procedures for thoracic and lumbar tuberculosis were 
favorable. The overall incidence of complications in 
the two groups was not statistically different. But, the 
incidence of postoperative mechanical ventilation was </p>

<p>significantly higher in group E compared with group L. 
This difference might be due to more complicated opera-
tive process, longer operative time and higher blood loss. 
Furthermore, the improvement in VAS scores on weeks 2 
after surgery was significantly lesser in the E group. This 
might be because postoperative pain was slowly reduced 
for extensive surgery. The determination according to the 
type of the surgery should be individualized depending 
on the basis of the patient's general condition. Transfo-
raminal approach in combination with internal fixation 
and posterolateral fusion with placement of interbody 
graft procedures were reserved for young (age &lt;65 years) 
patients who could tolerate more complex reconstructive 
surgery. Performed extensively, these surgical procedures 
were suitable with lesions at spinal cord level because of 
wider exposure and more aggressive debridement of all 
infected tissues. So it might be assumed that there is the </p>

<p>Table 4. The comparison of the categorized affecting factors and neurological outcomes </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Recovery 
Relative risk 
(95% confidence 
interval) </p>

<p>p-value 
Rapid (n=24) 
Slow (n=15) </p>

<p>Age 
0.67 (0.35 to 1.27) 
0.16 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>≥65 yr 
6 (25) 
7 (46.7) </p>

<p>&lt;65 yr 
18 (75) 
8 (53.39) </p>

<p>Duration of illness 
1.50 (0.69 to 3.25) 
0.27 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>≥8 wk 
20 (83.3) 
10 (66.7) </p>

<p>&lt;8 wk 
4 (16.7) 
5 (33.3) </p>

<p>Severity 
0.59 (0.32 to 1.09) 
0.06 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Frankel A and B 
7 (29.2) 
9 (60) </p>

<p>Frankel C and D 
17 (70.8) 
6 (40) </p>

<p>Group 
1.38 (0.84 to 2.27) 
0.20 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Extensive surgery 
13 (54.2) 
5 (33.3) </p>

<p>Limited surgery 
11 (45.8) 
10 (66.7) </p>

<p>Level 
0.82 (0.51 to 1.34) 
0.44 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Lumbar 
11 (45.8) 
5 (33.3) </p>

<p>Thoracic and thoracolumbar 
13 (54.2) 
10 (66.7) </p>

<p>Lumbar 
0.63 (0.27 to 1.47) 
0.30 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Extensive surgery 
3 (27.3) 
3 (60) </p>

<p>Limited surgery 
8 (72.7) 
2 (40) </p>

<p>Thoracic and thoracolumbar 
3.06 (1.13 to 8.29) 
0.01 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Extensive surgery 
10 (76.9) 
2 (20) </p>

<p>Limited surgery 
3 (23.1) 
8 (80) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%). </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Result of chi-square test; </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Result of Fisher's exact test. </p>

<p>Transforaminal debridement for spinal tuberculosis </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>



<p>likely benefit of surgery to relieve myelopathy; rapid early 
neurological recovery was presently evident. Limited 
surgery with posterior transpedicular decompression 
in combination with pedicle screw instrumentation and 
posterolateral fusion procedures were better suited to 
less destructive forms of TB in aging adults with multiple 
comorbidities. Lastly and most importantly, completion 
of a full course anti-TB therapy and surgeon's surgical 
experience were the two key points to achieve success in 
reaching the goals of the treatment, regardless of the type 
of operation. 
In the present article, the authors propose that the two 
techniques of the posterior-only approaches can lead to 
improved neurological function and acceptable radio-
graphic results in patients undergoing surgical treatment 
for spinal tuberculosis. Nevertheless, it was an uncon-
trolled retrospective study obtained from a small popula-
tion and relatively short follow-up period. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>A transforaminal debridement, interbody fusion with 
instrumentation may be a viable choice in a relative-
ly healthy young (age &lt;65 years) patients, but postopera-
tive ventilatory support as a complication is too high. 
The combination of extensive resection and stable recon-
struction with interbody autografting via posterior-only 
approach seems to accelerate neurological recovery in 
thoracic and thoracolumbar spinal tuberculosis. Patients 
with poor general medical condition achieve acceptable 
neurological outcomes and kyphosis correction by shorter 
operative time and less blood loss through transpedicular 
decompression with instrumentation techniques. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was 
reported. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors would like to appreciate Assist. Prof. Dr. 
Sudaporn Sudprasert, for her valuable comments while 
revising this manuscript. They also thank Dr. Jithayut 
Sueajui, MD for his considerable assistance with the illus-
trations. </p>



<p>Weera Sudprasert et al. 
 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>