<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4135079" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Introduction-Unwanted drug interactions with ionic currents in the heart can lead to an 
increased proarrhythmic risk to patients in the clinic. It is therefore a priority for safety 
pharmacology teams to detect block of cardiac ion channels, and new technologies have enabled 
the development of automated and high-throughput screening assays using cell lines. As a result of 
screening multiple ion-channels there is a need to integrate information, particularly for 
compounds affecting more than one current, and mathematical electrophysiology in-silico action 
potential models are beginning to be used for this. </p>

<p>Methods-We quantified the variability associated with concentration-effect curves fitted to 
recordings from high-throughput Molecular Devices IonWorks® Quattro™ screens when 
detecting block of I Kr (hERG), I Na (NaV1.5), I CaL (CaV1.2), I Ks (KCNQ1/minK) and I to (Kv4.3/ 
KChIP2.2), and the Molecular Devices FLIPR® Tetra fluorescence screen for I CaL (CaV1.2), for 
control compounds used at AstraZeneca and GlaxoSmithKline. We examined how screening 
variability propagates through in-silico action potential models for whole cell electrical behaviour, 
and how confidence intervals on model predictions can be estimated with repeated simulations. </p>

<p>Results-There are significant levels of variability associated with high-throughput ion channel 
electrophysiology screens. This variability is of a similar magnitude for different cardiac ion 
currents and different compounds. Uncertainty in the Hill coefficients of reported concentration-
effect curves is particularly high. Depending on a compound's ion channel blocking profile, the 
uncertainty introduced into whole-cell predictions can become significant. </p>

<p>Discussion-Our technique allows confidence intervals to be placed on computational model 
predictions that are based on high-throughput ion channel screens. This allows us to suggest when 
repeated screens should be performed to reduce uncertainty in a compound's action to acceptable 
levels, to allow a meaningful interpretation of the data. </p>

<p>Unwanted drug interactions with cardiac ion channels can lead to an increased pro-
arrhythmic risk in the clinic (Roden, 2008). It is therefore a priority for safety pharmacology 
teams to detect these interactions as early as possible during drug development. As such, it is 
now common for pharmaceutical companies to perform high-throughput screening (HTS) on 
large numbers of novel compounds, early in development, to detect whether they block 
cardiac ion channels (Pollard et al., 2010). Discovering that a lead compound carries a high 
cardiac risk at later stages of development is very costly. </p>

<p>At both AstraZeneca (AZ) and GlaxoSmithKline (GSK), results from HTS assays for 
multiple cardiac ion channels inform mathematical models for a compound's action on 
whole-cell electrophysiology (Davies et al., 2012; Mirams et al., 2011). Simulations are run 
to predict whether significant changes to cellular electrophysiology may occur with a given 
compound, and at which concentrations. Development of compounds that are flagged as 
having a significant effect can then be de-prioritised, or they can be referred for further 
safety testing, which is more accurate, but also more expensive. </p>

<p>In this study we characterised the variability associated with the results of HTS assays for 
cardiac ion channels, and examined how that variability affects predictions that are made for 
drug-induced changes to whole-cell electrophysiology. </p>

<p>1.1. High throughput screening </p>

<p>The current 'gold standard' of electrophysiological screening for ion-channel block involves 
manual patch clamping of single cells. This method is resource intensive and technically 
challenging, consequently it has a throughput that is far too low to be of commercial use 
during early drug discovery, when a large number of compounds need to be screened. To 
some extent, this problem has been overcome in recent years with the development of 
dedicated planar array high-throughput electrophysiology platforms. These platforms allow 
high precision recordings of ion-current inhibition by compounds, while being amenable to 
high-throughput screening (HTS). </p>

<p>A number of different planar array electrophysiology platforms have been developed in 
recent years, namely: Qpatch by Sophion Bioscience (Mathes, Friis, Finley, &amp; Liu, 2009), 
PatchXpress by Molecular Devices (Ly, Shyy, &amp; Misner, 2007), PatchLiner by Nanion 
Technologies (Polonchuk, 2012), IonFlux by Fluxion (Golden et al., 2011), CytoPatch by 
Cytocentrics (Stett, Burkhardt, Weber, Van Stiphout, &amp; Knott, 2003) and IonWorks™ HT/ </p>

<p>Elkins et al. 
Page 2 </p>

<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Quattro and Barracuda by Molecular Devices. A recent comparison of hERG IC50 values 
obtained across these platforms with manual patch clamp experiments can be found in 
Gillie, Novick, Donovan, Payne, and Townsend (2013, Table 2). The Molecular Devices 
FLuorometric Imaging Plate Reader (FLIPR® Tetra, Schroeder &amp; Neagle, 1996) assay is 
also used to measure changes in calcium transients (Sullivan, Tucker, &amp; Dale, 1999). </p>

<p>HTS provides a measurement of the concentration-effect curve of ion-channel current 
inhibition, and has established a good record in detecting ion-channel blockade for a wide 
variety of compounds and ion channels. </p>

<p>In this study we consider the Molecular Devices IonWorks® Quattro™ assays for detecting 
block of I Kr (hERG), I Na (NaV1.5), I CaL (CaV1.2), I Ks (KCNQ1/minK) and I to (Kv4.3/ 
KChIP2.2), and the Molecular Devices FLIPR assay for I CaL (CaV1.2). These assays have 
been used routinely at AZ and GSK for novel compound screening for a number of years. </p>

<p>1.2. Concentration-effect curves </p>

<p>Ion-channel current inhibition is commonly described by concentration-effect curves, such 
as those seen in Fig. 1. This curve describes how an 'effect' or 'response' R depends on a 
'dose' or compound 'concentration' [C]. In this case, the peak ionic current following a 
voltage step is recorded repeatedly, and the proportion of this that remains after addition of a 
certain concentration (or dose) of a compound is the recorded effect (or response). Such 
curves are commonly described by a Hill function (Hill, 1910): </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>or equivalently </p>

<p>This function of concentration [C], has two parameters: [IC 50 ], the half-maximal inhibitory 
concentration; and the Hill coefficient n. </p>

<p>In Fig. 1 we present concentration-effect curves that have been fitted to the output of a 
hERG-channel HTS that was performed 120 times (on different screening plates). Only 
those HTS assays that passed quality-control criteria, i.e. ones in which the positive controls 
registered an acceptable positive result, are considered in this study. We are therefore 
considering only the variability in 'acceptable' measurements, not across all the 
measurements that were taken. For discussion of typical quality control criteria used in these 
assays please see Bridgland-Taylor et al. (2006), Harmer et al. (2008), and Davies et al. 
(2012). Whilst the concentration-effect curves consistently detect the compound's blockade 
of I Kr , it is immediately evident that there is substantial variability between individual 
curves shown in Fig. 1. Our use of the term 'variability' is intended to represent the 
variation in IC 50 values and Hill coefficients fitted to concentration-effect curves recorded 
by HTS assays that are carried out on separate occasions. Indeed, HTS is thought to provide </p>

<p>Elkins et al. 
Page 3 </p>

<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>more variable results than the 'gold-standard' of manual patch clamp, and we seek to 
characterise this HTS variability in this study. </p>

<p>1.3. Aims </p>

<p>For most novel compounds that are of interest in drug development, repeats of only N = 1 or 
N = 2 are common. It is therefore difficult to draw any conclusions about the variability 
associated with screening a particular novel compound. Fortunately, a large number of 
repeats exist for those compounds used as controls in the assays. </p>

<p>Since AZ and GSK both run positive controls on each IonWorks Quattro or FLIPR Tetra 
plate, a whole concentration-effect curve is evaluated for a control compound each time any 
compound is screened. This has led to the accumulation of an unprecedented amount of 
information on HTS variability, which we have utilised here to determine the statistical 
distributions of both IC 50 values and Hill coefficients that describe the concentration-effect 
curves. </p>

<p>By using in-silico action potential (AP) simulations, AZ and GSK have begun to integrate 
quantitative information on concentration-effect curves that is gained from a panel of 
cardiac ion channel screens (Davies et al., 2012; Mirams et al., 2013). The aim of these 
simulations is to provide a prediction of how a compound is likely to affect the whole 
cardiac cell, or even the whole heart, early in compound development (Fletcher et al., 2011; 
Mirams &amp; Noble, 2011). For example, in related work, we show how HTS data can be used 
to predict the results of a rabbit left-ventricular wedge assay (Beattie et al., 2013-this issue). 
It has not yet been considered how variability in HTS results, that are taken as inputs into in-
silico models, might affect such simulation outputs. </p>

<p>The aims of this article are therefore two-fold: firstly, to quantify the variability in 
concentration-effect curves produced by HTS, by examining variability in the IC 50 values 
and Hill coefficients that describe them; and secondly, to provide a method for estimating 
the subsequent variability in the output of in-silico action potential simulations based upon 
HTS. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>2.1. Ion-channel screening </p>

<p>Here we describe the IonWorks and FLIPR platforms in general terms. For details of the 
experimental protocols that are used at AZ and GSK, please refer to Supplementary material 
S1. </p>

<p>The IonWorks™ Quattro platform (first described by Schroeder, Neagle, Trezise, and 
Worley (2003)) has been the mainstay of ion channel electrophysiology HTS at AZ and 
GSK in recent years. On this platform, the glass electrodes typical of manual patch clamping 
rigs have been replaced by planar, 96 or 384 well, "chips" (known as the PatchPlate™). 
Each of the wells contains one hole to which one cell is clamped. Briefly, the PatchPlate™ 
is placed on the machine at the interface between two separate fluid compartments. The 
extracellular compartment (above the holes), is loaded with an external solution. The surface </p>

<p>Elkins et al. 
Page 4 </p>

<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>below the PatchPlate™ (the intracellular compartment), is perfused with a second solution. 
A vacuum is used to attach the cells onto the small holes at the base of each well, creating a 
high resistance seal (≈100 MΩ) between the cell and the edge of the PatchPlate™. </p>

<p>Unlike other methods, this suction is not used to break the cell membrane. Instead, a cell 
membrane-perforating agent (Amphotericin-B) is introduced into the intracellular 
compartment allowing access to the intracellular compartment from the underside while the 
high-resistance seal is maintained. This method, known as 'perforated patch', allows many 
of the intracellular components required for ion channel modulation to be retained (Wood, 
Williams, &amp; Waldron, 2004). The cell can then be voltage clamped and currents across the 
membrane are measured by a 48 channel amplifier. Separate measurements can be taken 
from each well using this method. </p>

<p>An updated method, known as population patch clamping (PPC) was developed by Dale, 
Townsend, Hollands, and Trezise (2007). This protocol can be utilised on IonWorks™ 
Quattro and Barracuda machines and allows for more accurate recordings. In PPC mode, 
each PatchPlate™ is perforated by many holes allowing one amplifier to take recordings 
from up to 64 different cells. The recorded current is then the mean current from a number 
of cells. This dramatically improves consistency in the recordings, by helping to overcome 
some of the inter-cell variability that has been observed with the single-hole approach 
(Finkel et al., 2006). All of the data discussed in this study were acquired using the 
IonWorks Quattro in the PPC mode, as described in Supplementary material S1. In brief, 
cells were placed into wells at a concentration of between 1 and 5 million cells/ml 
(depending on the HTS target), cells were incubated in the presence of the test compound 
for 3-5 min before measurements were taken, and compounds were tested up to the limit of 
solubility. </p>

<p>We also consider the FLIPR screen that GSK has been using to detect blockade of CaV1.2 
channels (Sullivan et al., 1999). This screen uses calcium-sensitive dyes to record changes in 
fluorescence. Intracellular calcium transients occur upon the addition of a depolarising 
solution, reductions in these transients relative to control wells are used as a proxy for 
blockade of the L-type calcium current. Details of the protocols that were used are given in 
Supplementary material S1.3. </p>

<p>2.2. pIC 50 and Hill coefficient distributions </p>

<p>Of particular note, in terms of size, is the IonWorks hERG control at AZ, in which the 
compound Cisapride is used. At the time of writing there had been N = 12,638 replications 
of this experiment. We therefore use this example to discuss the fitting of the data to 
particular probability distributions. A histogram of the pIC 50 values that have been recorded 
is shown in Fig. 1. For ease of presentation and intuition we will work with pIC 50 values 
throughout this article. These are calculated from IC 50 values using pIC 50 = −log 10 (IC 50 ) 
with units of Molar for IC 50 and therefore log(Molar) for pIC 50 . Probability plots revealed 
that the logistic distribution is a good descriptor of pIC 50 variability in this dataset, this was 
true for all of the different HTS control assays (please see Supplementary material S2 for 
more detail). </p>

<p>Elkins et al. 
Page 5 </p>

<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>To estimate the parameters of the distribution we used maximum likelihood estimates, 
provided by the MatLab™ statistics toolbox 'mle' function (the datasets and fitting code are 
available to download from http://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/chaste/download). The logistic 
distribution is fitted to the Cisapride hERG control data, and is shown overlaid in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>Throughout this investigation we therefore assume that pIC 50 follows a logistic distribution 
(pIC 50 ~ Logistic(μ, σ), where μ is the centering parameter and σ is the spread parameter). </p>

<p>Note that since the pIC 50 is calculated from the IC 50 using a logarithm, this implies that IC 50 
follows a log-logistic distribution (IC 50 ~ LogLogistic(α, β)), where the two distributions are 
related by α = e μ and β = 1/σ. For the equations of the distributions please see the </p>

<p>Supplementary material S2. </p>

<p>We perform a similar characterisation of the variability in Hill coefficients, that were fitted 
to concentration-effect curves at the same time as pIC 50 values. In this case all Hill 
coefficients appeared to follow a log-logistic distribution, as IC 50 values do (Hill L 
ogLogistic(α, β)). In Fig. 1 we present a histogram of the Hill coefficients that correspond </p>

<p>to the same assay as the pIC 50 values shown in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>The peaks at 1.0 and 1.1 in Fig. 1 may illustrate unconscious 'rounding' by human 
operators, affecting the values that are logged into a database, whereas no such bias exists 
for pIC 50 values. Also of note is the accumulation of Hill coefficients at 5.0, which was the 
maximum allowed Hill coefficient in the fitting process. </p>

<p>2.3. Inferring underlying distributions from limited repeats </p>

<p>In order to simplify this section we discuss pIC 50 values, exactly the same procedure can be 
followed for Hill coefficients by substituting α for μ and β for σ, in the following discussion. </p>

<p>When an HTS assay is performed on a novel compound, we will typically have only a 
limited number of concentration-effect curves, and hence very limited knowledge of the 
distribution of concentration-effect curve parameters (in contrast to the control cases 
discussed above, where we have a very good approximation to the true distribution). </p>

<p>We must therefore make some assumptions about a distribution for the novel compounds: </p>

<p>1. When an HTS is repeated a large number of times, μ is equal to the 'true' pIC 50 
value. This is a reasonable approximation since μ is equal to the mean, median and 
mode of the logistic distribution (and for the Hill coefficient case, with the log-
logistic distribution, α is equal to the median). Note this is only really the 'true </p>

<p>pIC 50 ' if the HTS assay has no systematic bias resulting in under-or over-reporting 
of pIC 50 values. </p>

<p>2. The deviation parameter (σ) is the same as that of the relevant control assays; i.e. if 
we repeated the HTS for the novel compound hundreds of times we would fit a 
distribution with the same deviation (σ) as the relevant control for that HTS assay, 
but with a different median (μ). As we will see in Section 3.1, this is a reasonable 
assumption for most of the assays, as different control compounds tend to share </p>

<p>Elkins et al. </p>

<p>
J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>similar deviation parameters, and for a first approximation we might expect a novel 
compound to do the same. </p>

<p>In Supplementary material S3 we provide details of how these assumptions are used in 
inference calculations to estimate the underlying distribution of the true pIC 50 , from 
individual runs of the assay. Here we discuss an example of the inference procedure, shown 
in Fig. 3. </p>

<p>In Fig. 3 we observe how the incorporation of repeat assay results into our inference 
procedure influences our confidence in the possibilities for the 'true' pIC 50 . If repeat 
experiments yield similar values (as will we see, this is suggested by the results in Section 
3.1), the effect of including them is to reduce the effective spread of the probability 
distribution for μ. We therefore tend to obtain more accurate estimates for the 'true' pIC 50 
values when multiple experiments are performed, as demonstrated in Fig. 3. </p>

<p>2.4. In-silico action potential modelling </p>

<p>2.4.1. Model-In-silico action potential models are based on the Nobel Prize winning work 
of Hodgkin and Huxley (1952). These models describe the evolution through time of voltage 
across a cell membrane that results from differences in intracellular and extracellular ionic 
concentrations, caused by transmembrane ion currents, which are themselves voltage and 
time dependent. The first cardiac action potential models were developed over 50 years ago 
(Noble, 1962), and models now exist for multiple species and types of cardiac myocyte 
(Noble, Garny, &amp; Noble, 2012). These cellular models have also been integrated into models 
of tissue electrophysiology to predict the path of electrical waves up to the whole heart scale 
(Clayton et al., 2011). We have recently reviewed the use of these biophysical cardiac 
electrophysiology models in pro-arrhythmic safety testing (Mirams, Davies, Cui, Kohl, &amp; 
Noble, 2012). </p>

<p>In this study we used the Ten Tusscher and Panfilov (2006) (TT06) human ventricular 
action potential model (epicardial variant). This model was chosen as it has a relatively low 
number of equations, making simulations relatively fast, and appears to be robust under 
multiple-ion-channel drug action (Mirams et al., 2013). We have used a simple conductance-
block model for ion channel blockade, so that the maximal conductance of a given channel, 
g j , is modified under drug block according to </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>where R([C]) is the degree of ion-channel block given by the concentration-effect curve (Eq. 
(1)), and g j control is the maximal conductance of the channel in control (drug free) 
conditions. </p>

<p>The TT06 model includes all of the currents that are screened by the HTS assays we are 
considering, with the exception of an individual fast I to current. Fast I to is molecularly 
distinct from slow I to (Niwa &amp; Nerbonne, 2010), and so models that have separate 
components may provide more realistic simulation predictions for use in pharmaceutical 
safety assessment. However, here we are interested in demonstrating the method, rather than </p>

<p>Elkins et al. </p>

<p>
J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>the quantitative accuracy of the predictions, and so we block the whole TT06 I to current 
according to the concentration-effect curve from the fast I to assays. </p>

<p>2.4.2. Sampling from distributions-In the results section we consider data from a 
screen of a number of marketed reference compounds. This screen was performed once, so 
to emulate the process of repeat HTS experiments we assume the screened values represent 
the 'true' values. If the experiment was to be repeated we assume that the individual sample 
pIC 50 values and Hills would follow the PDF of those HTS screens, assuming true median 
values for μ to be those given in Table 2 and spread parameters to be as in Table 1. The 
Bayesian inference scheme is then applied to 1, 2, 4 or 8 data points, drawn at random from 
these distributions (if one did possess raw data from multiple repeats the Bayesian inference 
scheme should be applied directly to these values). </p>

<p>Having inferred a probability density function for μ, as described in Section 2.3, we can then 
sample an estimate for the 'true' pIC 50 , which is subsequently used to create a sample 
concentration-effect curve R([C]), using Eq. (1). </p>

<p>Then for any drug concentration of interest, the sample concentration-effect curve is used to 
calculate a new maximal channel conductance using the conductance block model (Eq. (2)). 
This process is repeated as required for all channels of interest. </p>

<p>We differentiate between the cases where we allow: only pIC 50 to be sampled (and Hill 
coefficient is assumed to be equal to one) or both pIC 50 and Hill (independently, as 
discussed in Supplementary material S3); and the inclusion of variability on different 
numbers of the ion currents (just hERG, or hERG/NaV/CaV or hERG/NaV/CaV/I Ks /I to ). </p>

<p>2.4.3. Simulations-A pIC 50 and Hill coefficient are selected, for each channel, using the 
sampling method described above in Section 2.4.2. These values define a concentration-
effect curve for each ion current. We modified the Ten Tusscher and Panfilov (2006) model 
to allow scaling of the channel conductances in response to drug block, as described in 
Section 2.4.1 and Eq. (2). We begin with the model in steady state 1 Hz pacing drug-free 
control conditions. The channel conductance scalings are applied, then regular 1 Hz pacing 
continues until the model reaches a new steady state (limit cycle). The action potential 
duration (at 90% repolarization, APD 90 ) is then calculated and recorded. Note that any 
marker of interest could be processed from the simulated action potentials, for example 
upstroke velocity, or triangulation. Here we have restricted the analysis to APD 90 , as this is 
the most widely used marker in computational cardiac safety assessment at present, and has 
been linked to human clinical Torsadogenic risk (Mirams et al., 2011). The process is 
repeated for a range of concentrations for each sample of pIC 50 and Hill coefficient. This 
'workflow' is depicted in schematic form in Fig. 4. </p>

<p>A new pIC 50 and Hill coefficient are sampled, and the process shown in Fig. 4 is repeated 
for the new values. By repeating this process 200 times for each compound, resulting in 200 
distinct APD-response curves, we can build up a probability distribution for the outputs. By 
ignoring the 5 maximum and 5 minimum of the 200 simulated APDs at each concentration, 
the remaining spread of APDs defines an estimate for the 95% credible interval for the </p>

<p>Elkins et al. </p>

<p>
J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>simulated response curve. The simulation takes a few hours on a single processor of a 
modern desktop PC (the time varies depending on the action-potential model used), but 
moving the calculations to parallel evaluation on larger computing resources is trivial. </p>

<p>For the interested reader we have made the following resources available: the full control 
datasets to which distributions were fitted, with the corresponding <rs type="software">MatLab</rs> script; the 
Bayesian sampling code; the action potential modelling software; and the scripts for 
generating the figures presented in this article. These can be downloaded as a 'bolt-on 
project' for the open-source cardiac simulation software <rs id="software-4" type="software">Chaste</rs> (written to work with <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">v3.1</rs>) 
from http://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/chaste/download. </p>

<p>A brief description of the computational techniques follows. We used a machine readable 
version of the Ten Tusscher and Panfilov (2006) model, taken from the CellML repository 
(Lloyd, Lawson, Hunter, &amp; Nielsen, 2008). PyCML was used to convert the CellML format 
into C++ code, the CellML file being tagged with metadata denoting the conductances of 
interest (Cooper, Corrias, Gavaghan, &amp; Noble, 2011; Cooper, Mirams, &amp; Niederer, 2011). 
The equations were solved using the adaptive CVODE solver (Hindmarsh et al., 2005), with 
relative and absolute tolerances of 10 −6 and 10 −8 respectively, in a custom-made program 
based on the open-source Chaste library (Mirams et al., 2013; Pitt-Francis et al., 2009). </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Screening variability </p>

<p>In this section we present the variability associated with fitting concentration-effect curves 
to the output of HTS assays. Each of the compounds we consider has been screened a large 
number of times as a positive control at either AZ or GSK. </p>

<p>Each assay generates a histogram of reported pIC 50 and Hill coefficients, such as those 
shown in Fig. 2 for Cisapride in the hERG IonWorks screen. Analogous figures are 
presented in Supplementary material S4 for each control compound. The probability 
distributions that were fitted to the datasets for each control compound, as discussed in 
Section 2.2, are shown in one figure for each assay (Figs. 5 &amp; 6). The individual fit 
parameters are summarised in Table 1. </p>

<p>Of particular interest in Table 1 is the consistency in the values of the 'spread' parameters σ 
and 1/β for each assay, as we would expect μ and α to vary between different compounds. </p>

<p>Note that the spread of the Hill (log-logistic) distribution shown in Figs. 5 &amp; 6 naturally 
increases as the median α increases, even with an unchanged scaling (1/β) parameter (see </p>

<p>Supplement Fig. S4). The values in Table 1 may therefore be a better representation of the 
differences in the variability associated with the Hill coefficients than Figs. 5 &amp; 6. </p>

<p>Those assays with multiple controls, which are hERG (Fig. 4), CaV1.2 FLIPR (Fig. 4), and 
I Ks (Fig. 5), demonstrate similar levels of variability in both pIC 50 and Hill coefficients for 
all of the compounds considered. These results provide evidence that the second assumption 
we made in Section 2.4.2 about consistency in the spread of pIC 50 and Hill coefficients is 
reasonable for these assays. A possible exception to this is the NaV1.5 IonWorks screen, </p>

<p>Elkins et al. </p>

<p>
J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>



<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>that shows slightly higher variability in the pIC 50 spread associated with different 
compounds. Ideally data would be acquired on additional NaV1.5 control compounds to 
characterise this assay further. In the absence of any further information, we keep the same 
assumption for the CaV1.2 IonWorks and I to screens, for which data were only available for 
one control compound each. </p>

<p>Figs. 5 &amp; 6 and Table 1 show that the variability associated with Hill coefficients fitted to 
HTS results is considerable (but the level of variability is consistent between different 
compounds in a given assay). Such high variability may suggest that there would be less 
error associated with making the assumption that the Hill coefficient is always equal to one, 
than there is in taking the Hill coefficient from an HTS assay. </p>

<p>There did not appear to be a correlation between the pIC 50 and Hill coefficients recorded in 
any of the assays (see Supplementary material Fig. S5). </p>

<p>3.2. Simulation variability </p>

<p>In this section we show how the uncertainty in the 'true' concentration-effect parameters 
propagates through an action potential simulation. We performed HTS at AZ for the ion 
channels of interest for a number of reference compounds, the results are shown in Table 2. </p>

<p>We selected an underlying spread parameter for each assay, shown in Supplementary 
material Table S1, based on the data shown in Table 1. Where there was a choice to be made 
between AZ or GSK spread parameters, we chose the AZ ones, as the experiments for this 
section were performed using those reagents, protocols and machines. We then performed 
the Bayesian inference method to obtain probability distributions for the 'true' pIC 50 value 
and Hill coefficient, as discussed in Section 2.4.2. We sampled from these distributions to 
explore the range of possible concentration-effect curves that are input into the simulations 
(as shown in Fig. 4). In practice to apply this method, you should characterise the variability 
of your own assay as shown above, and use the resulting spread parameters in the inference 
step. </p>

<p>The results consist of concentration-effect curves for action potential duration (APD 90 ), with 
95% confidence limits evaluated from the many trajectories of the individual runs, as shown 
in Tables 3 &amp; 4 and Tables S2-S9. In the following sections we present the variation we 
expect to be associated with simulation outputs, based on the level of variability in the HTS 
ion channel screens, for each of the compounds listed in Table 2. </p>

<p>3.2.1. Alfuzosin case study-Table 3 summarises the findings for Alfuzosin when 
considering the variability associated with pIC 50 measurements, but not Hill coefficients. 
Table 4 summarises the findings when including both sources of variability. </p>

<p>In the Thorough-QT (TQT) study a maximum QTc prolongation of 7.7 ms was observed 
(Gintant, 2011). In Tables 3 &amp; 4 we see that simulations based on single screens could give 
misleading results. In some cases small, and in others very large, prolongation is predicted at 
high concentrations (top right plots in each table), particularly when considering variability 
associated with Hill coefficient measurements (Table 4). </p>

<p>Elkins et al. </p>

<p>
J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>By repeating the ion channel screens we gain more reliable channel block estimates, and the 
lower panels exhibit the correct behaviour -mild/moderate prolongation of repolarization. </p>

<p>3.2.2. Dofetilide case study-The remaining simulated concentration-action potential 
duration (APD 90 ) curves for this section are presented in Supplementary material S5. Tables 
S2 &amp; S3 summarise the findings for Dofetilide. </p>

<p>Dofetilide is a well known QT-prolonging hERG blocker, we see that prolongation occurs at 
low concentrations of 0.01-0.1 μM. Since the hERG IC 50 is in this range, a large amount of 
variability is introduced at these concentrations. When considering only hERG block 
(Tables S2 &amp; S3, left columns) the variability is reduced at high concentrations. This is due 
to the blockade of hERG being close to 100% at 1 μM and above, regardless of the variation 
in IC 50 reported by the HTS assay. In a similar situation, at 100 μM of Quinidine in Fig. 1, 
all 120 assay runs reported at least 90% block. </p>

<p>When we consider the results of the other channel assays, variability is introduced at higher 
concentrations, where those assays' concentration-effect curves become active (Tables S2 &amp; 
S3, centre and right columns). In particular, the next IC 50 to be encountered is that of 
CaV1.2 (Table 2); and as we might expect blockade of the L-type calcium current at 
concentrations close to 100 μM begins to cause significant shortening in some of the runs, 
and correspondingly large confidence intervals on the simulation output. </p>

<p>3.2.3. Lacosamide case study-Lacosamide is an example of a QT-shortening 
compound. It has a very low hERG affinity, and a significant CaV1.2 affinity. In the TQT 
study Lacosamide showed a shortening of around 6.3 ms (Gintant, 2011). </p>

<p>Tables S4 &amp; S5 summarise the simulation results for Lacosamide. As we might expect, 
including assay variability for hERG has almost no effect, as the concentrations we are 
considering (up to 100 μM) are never close to any of the possible 'true' hERG IC 50 values. </p>

<p>The majority of variability is associated with the CaV1.2 IC 50 value, and accordingly the 
additional variability introduced when considering I Ks and I to is negligible. This example 
shows how it is possible, if unlikely, to get very strange behaviour due to HTS variability, in 
0.5-1% of cases with just one assay repeat (N = 1), the simulations predict prolongation 
instead of shortening. In this case we would choose to screen CaV1.2 multiple times, as this 
has the largest benefit in terms of constraining the confidence intervals. </p>

<p>3.2.4. Nilotinib case study-Tables S6 &amp; S7 summarise the findings for Nilotinib. In 
our screens Nilotinib is not a strong blocker of any current, and simulations suggest a mild 
prolongation, or even a possible shortening at high concentrations and low numbers of 
repeats. By increasing the number of assay repeats, we would consistently predict 
prolongation. </p>

<p>In the TQT study Nilotinib was a prolonger with 15.8 ms of QTc prolongation being 
observed (Gintant, 2011). By examining this compound's FDA pharmacology review, 1 we </p>

<p>1 http://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/nda/2007/022068s000_PharmR_P1.pdf. </p>

<p>Elkins et al. </p>

<p>
J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>find that hERG IC 50 =0.13 μM was reported, substantially lower than our screening result 
(Table 2). </p>

<p>3.2.5. Tolterodine case study-The assays suggested that Tolterodine is a strong hERG 
blocker (Table 2) that we might expect to have a similar profile to Dofetilide. Tables S8 &amp; 
S9 summarise the simulation findings for Tolterodine. The difference in the profiles shown 
(ever-longer prolongation at higher concentrations for Tolterodine but not Dofetilide) is 
explained by the fact that there is no CaV1.2 block to stabilise the hERG prolongation at 
higher concentrations, and instead blockade of I Ks and I to can be introduced. </p>

<p>This potentially risky profile would suggest repeating most of the screening panel multiple 
times in order to minimise uncertainty in prolongation predictions. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>The variability that we have observed in the high-throughput screens (HTS) could be caused 
by a large number of factors, including (but not limited to): </p>

<p>• Noise in recording or 'instrument error'. </p>

<p>• Variability in the number and condition of cells in each well. </p>

<p>• Variability in the concentration and differences in the condition/batch of the 
compound added. </p>

<p>• Variability in the temperature at which the recordings were taken; temperature is 
not fixed at a physiological 37° in the screens we have considered. </p>

<p>Firstly, we characterised variability in pIC 50 values and Hill coefficients resulting from HTS 
assays by examining controls that have been repeated a large number of times. pIC 50 values 
fitted to data from an IonWorks or FLIPR screen are described by a logistic distribution, and 
Hill coefficients follow a log-logistic distribution. We observed moderate variability in 
pIC 50 values (Table 1) that is consistent with a ± ½ log 10 unit 'rule of thumb'. There is a 
larger amount of variability associated with Hill coefficients. </p>

<p>There can be such a high level of variability associated with Hill coefficients that it is not 
clear that including the Hill coefficient from a HTS adds useful information: there may be 
less error introduced by assuming that the Hill coefficient associated with each 
concentration-effect curve (n in Eq. (1)) is equal to one. This is something we are 
investigating in parallel work (Beattie et al., 2013-this issue). </p>

<p>The use of in-silico action potential models to integrate information from HTS rests on the 
fact that the average result of a HTS is giving the 'correct answer'. Careful analysis should 
be made to ensure that these screens are not consistently over-or under-reporting ion 
channel blockade, by comparing results with manual patch clamping. </p>

<p>We would like other companies and device manufacturers, that have repeated screens large 
numbers of times, particularly with other machines and for other ion channels, also to 
publish their datasets. The variability that is associated with different assays, reagents and </p>

<p>Elkins et al. </p>

<p>
J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>protocols could then be characterised, and the most reliable screening methods selected for 
use. </p>

<p>We also characterised the resulting uncertainty in whole-cell responses via simulating the 
action potential duration based on the uncertainty in the screening data (that the simulation 
uses as inputs). This was done by performing a Bayesian inference step: inferring the 
distribution of likely 'true' concentration-effect parameters, from a number of sample assay 
runs, by assuming that the variability level for a novel compound is similar to that of the 
relevant control assay compounds. We then sampled possible concentration-effect curves for 
each channel and performed repeated simulations to build up a probability distribution for 
the resulting action-potential-duration vs. concentration curves. </p>

<p>The approach we have proposed does not rule out the consideration of other sources of 
variability, for example due to stochasticity of ion channel gating (Dangerfield, Kay, &amp; 
Burrage, 2012), or inter-individual variability (Davies et al., 2012), and could be considered 
in addition to these. </p>

<p>The choice of number of screening repeats to perform initially depends upon the expense of 
the screen, the level of accuracy that is required, and the time and cost involved in repeating 
screens to reduce uncertainty at a later date. An organisation could decide to perform each 
screen once, analyse uncertainty using the proposed method, and perform additional screens 
as required; whilst another organisation could choose to perform each screen four times, or 
more, to minimise uncertainty from the outset. </p>

<p>Whatever strategy is adopted, our methodology provides a means to determine whether a 
particular screen is introducing large amounts of uncertainty, and whether the uncertainty in 
whole-cell behaviour predictions is at an acceptable level. This is a basic requirement for 
sensible interpretation of simulation results, and therefore a pre-requisite for the possible 
future use of simulation in reduction and replacement of animal-based safety tests. </p>

<p>Supplementary Material </p>

<p>Refer to Web version on PubMed Central for supplementary material. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank Chris Luscombe, Andrew Powell, Metul Patel, Jordi Munoz-Muriedas, Jim Harvey 
and Nick McMahon at GSK; Matthew Bridgland-Taylor, Chris Pollard and Jean-Pierre Valentin from AstraZeneca. 
Also thanks to Denis Noble at the University of Oxford, and Ben Calderhead at UCL, for useful discussions. </p>

<p>GRM and DJG gratefully acknowledge research support from a GlaxoSmithKline Grants &amp; Affiliates award, the 
'2020 Science' programme funded through the EPSRC Cross-Discipline Interface Programme (EP/I017909/1) and 
supported by Microsoft Research, and an NC3Rs/EPSRC Strategic Award in Mathematics and Toxicology (NC/ 
K001337/1). </p>

<p>Abbreviations </p>

<p>AP(D) 
Action Potential (Duration) </p>

<p>AZ 
AstraZeneca </p>

<p>Elkins et al. 
Page 13 </p>

<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>FLIPR </p>

<p>FLuorometric Imaging Plate Reader </p>

<p>GSK 
GlaxoSmithKline </p>

<p>HTS 
High Throughput Screening [assays] </p>

<p>IC 50 
Concentration for 50% Inhibition </p>

<p>I CaL 
L-type calcium current </p>

<p>I Kr 
rapid delayed rectifier potassium current </p>

<p>I Ks 
slow delayed rectifier potassium current </p>

<p>I Na 
fast sodium current </p>

<p>I to 
[fast] transient outward potassium current </p>

<p>PDF 
Probability Density Function </p>

<p>pIC 50 
minus log 10 of IC 50 </p>

<p>PPC 
Population Patch Clamping </p>

<p>QT(c) 
QT interval of the electrocardiogram (corrected for heart rate) </p>

<p>TQT 
Thorough QT, human clinical QT prolongation trial </p>

<p>TT06 
Ten Tusscher and Panfilov (2006) human ventricular cell model </p>



<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>



<p>Elkins et al. </p>

<p>
J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>



<p>Elkins et al. </p>

<p>
J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Fig. 1. </p>

<p>Variability in the concentration-effect curves fitted to results of an IonWorks Quattro™ 
hERG screen using Quinidine. These were recorded as a control at GSK, N = 120 separate 
assay runs. </p>

<p>Elkins et al. 
Page 17 </p>

<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Fig. 2. </p>

<p>Histograms of (a) pIC 50 values and (b) Hill coefficients, from an IonWorks Quattro 
Cisapride hERG assay. These values were fitted to recordings taken at AZ for N = 12,638 
independent assay runs. Solid red lines denote the distributions that have been fitted to these 
data as described in the text. </p>

<p>Elkins et al. 
Page 18 </p>

<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Fig. 3. </p>

<p>An example of how Bayesian inference informs the probability density function (PDF -
solid line) for the 'true pIC 50 ' (dashed line), based on individual samples from the hERG 
Cisapride dataset. In the top left we consider the case where we have run one assay, N = 1, 
observing just one pIC 50 (red cross in blue circle). We plot the inferred probability 
distribution for μ, based on these data. Moving across the top row we have N = 2, then N = 
3; and in the second row N = 4, N = 5 and N = 6. The example assay results were sampled at 
random from the Cisapride dataset shown in Fig. 1, and the Bayesian inference scheme used 
the spread parameter that was fitted to that distribution (σ = 0.1035). </p>

<p>Elkins et al. </p>

<p>
J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Fig. 4. </p>

<p>A schematic of the simulation and processing workflow. Step 1: concentration-effect curves 
are fitted to the result of each HTS assay. Step 2: for a given concentration, percentage 
blocks of the relevant ion channels are calculated from the concentration-effect curves, and 
applied to the mathematical electrophysiology model. Step 3: the model is paced at 1 Hz 
until it reaches a steady state, and the resulting action potential is recorded. Step 4: steps 2 &amp; 
3 are repeated for a range of concentrations, to build up a concentration-APD curve. </p>

<p>Elkins et al. 
Page 20 </p>

<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Fig. 5. </p>

<p>Probability density functions for: (left) pIC 50 values; (right) Hill coefficients, as fitted to the 
distributions resulting from large numbers of repeat screens with control compounds. </p>

<p>Elkins et al. 
Page 21 </p>

<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Fig. 6. </p>

<p>Probability density functions for: (left) pIC 50 values; (right) Hill coefficients, as fitted to the 
distributions resulting from large numbers of repeat screens with control compounds. </p>

<p>Elkins et al. 
Page 22 </p>

<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>



<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Distribution of concentration-effect curves for control compounds. This table lists the fitted parameters for the 
pIC 50 (logistic) and Hill (log-logistic) distributions for each control compound, for each cardiac ion channel </p>

<p>assay. </p>

<p>Ion channel Control compound HTS platform Performed at Repeats 
N </p>

<p>pIC 50 Logistic Hill Log-logistic </p>

<p>μ 
σ 
α </p>

<p>1/β </p>

<p>NaV1.5 
Flecainide 
IonWorks 
AZ 
2307 5.235 0.0760 1.188 
0.0835 </p>

<p>NaV1.5 
Amitryptiline 
IonWorks 
GSK 
362 5.765 0.1388 1.744 
0.1983 </p>

<p>NaV1.5 
Tetracaine 
IonWorks 
GSK 
248 6.060 0.1459 1.530 
0.2089 </p>

<p>NaV1.5 
GSK-A 
IonWorks 
GSK 
121 5.315 0.2044 0.930 
0.1529 </p>

<p>CaV1.2 
Verapamil 
IonWorks 
AZ 
369 5.571 0.1597 0.605 
0.1206 </p>

<p>CaV1.2 
Nicardipine 
FLIPR 
GSK 
395 7.378 0.2216 1.325 
0.2386 </p>

<p>CaV1.2 
Nifedipine 
FLIPR 
GSK 
328 7.248 0.1856 1.179 
0.2213 </p>

<p>CaV1.2 
Diltiazem 
FLIPR 
GSK 
244 5.249 0.1560 0.979 
0.2263 </p>

<p>hERG 
Cisapride 
IonWorks 
AZ 
12638 6.408 0.1034 1.790 
0.1784 </p>

<p>hERG 
Quinidine 
IonWorks 
GSK 
120 5.625 0.1033 1.708 
0.1544 </p>

<p>hERG 
Pimozide 
IonWorks 
GSK 
94 7.321 0.1914 1.586 
0.2486 </p>

<p>hERG 
Haloperidol 
IonWorks 
GSK 
84 6.852 0.1498 1.469 
0.2031 </p>

<p>hERG 
Verapamil 
IonWorks 
GSK 
72 6.169 0.1464 1.429 
0.2025 </p>

<p>I Ks 
XE991 
IonWorks 
AZ 
525 6.217 0.1053 1.127 
0.1510 </p>

<p>I Ks 
XE991 
IonWorks 
GSK 
79 5.927 0.1342 1.011 
0.1837 </p>

<p>I Ks 
GSK-B 
IonWorks 
GSK 
451 7.414 0.1808 1.318 
0.1677 </p>

<p>I to 
Flecainide 
IonWorks 
AZ 
366 4.860 0.0860 1.063 
0.0862 </p>

<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>



<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Results of a screen for a number of compounds with varying ion-channel blocking profiles. These screens 
were performed once for each ion channel at AZ. Where 50% block was not achieved, we have performed a 
least-squares fit of a concentration-effect curve to the original data, with a minimum allowed pIC 50 of 0, a </p>

<p>minimum allowed Hill coefficient of 0.5, and a maximum of 5.00. </p>

<p>Compound hERG 
NaV1.5 
CaV1.2 
KCNQ1/minK Kv4.3/KChIP2.2 </p>

<p>pIC 50 Hill pIC 50 Hill pIC 50 Hill pIC 50 
Hill 
pIC 50 
Hill </p>

<p>Alfuzosin 
4.66 
0.92 3.69 
0.71 3.75 
1.64 3.95 
0.50 
3.04 
0.50 </p>

<p>Dofetilide 
6.85 
1.88 3.46 
0.79 3.77 
5.00 3.65 
0.50 
0.00 
1.00 </p>

<p>Lacosamide 0.00 
1.00 3.34 
0.72 4.33 
0.44 3.62 
0.50 
0.00 
1.00 </p>

<p>Nilotinib 
4.20 
0.53 2.97 
0.71 3.67 
0.67 3.39 
0.50 
2.48 
0.72 </p>

<p>Tolterodine 6.89 
1.58 5.24 
1.08 0.00 
1.00 4.10 
0.60 
4.93 
1.07 </p>

<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Elkins et al. 
Page 25 </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>Uncertainty in concentration-effect curves for action potential duration under the action of Alfuzosin, when 
considering ion-channel assay variability in pIC 50 values (not in Hill coefficients), for various numbers of </p>

<p>repeats. Each plot displays action potential duration, APD 90 , as a function of concentration. Black lines </p>

<p>represent simulation results for each set of sampled concentration-effect inputs, the red line denotes the result 
when using the numbers reported by the assay directly, with 95% credibility intervals imposed as described in 
the text. </p>

<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Europe PMC Funders Author Manuscripts </p>

<p>Elkins et al. 
Page 26 </p>

<p>Table 4 </p>

<p>Uncertainty in concentration-effect curves for action potential duration under the action of Alfuzosin, when 
considering ion-channel assay variability in pIC 50 values and Hill coefficients, for various numbers of repeats. </p>

<p>Each plot displays action potential duration, APD 90 , as a function of concentration. Black lines represent </p>

<p>simulation results for each set of sampled concentration-effect inputs, the red line denotes the result when 
using the numbers reported by the assay directly, with 95% credibility intervals imposed as described in the 
text. </p>

<p>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2014 August 18. </p>

</text></tei>