<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4898854" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Every year millions of dollars are expended to equip and maintain the hospital steri-
lization centers, and our country is not an exception of this matter. According to this, it is important 
to use more effective technologies and methods in health system in order to reach more effectiveness 
and saving in costs. This study was conducted with the aim of evaluating the technology of regional 
sterilization centers. 
Methods: This study was done in four steps. At the first step, safety and effectiveness of technolo-
gy was studied via systematic study of evidence. The next step was done to evaluate the economical 
aspect of off-site sterilization technology using gathered data from systematic review of the texts 
which were related to the technology and costs of off-site and in-site hospital sterilization. Third step 
was conducted to collect experiences of using technology in some selected hospitals around the 
world. And in the last step different aspects of acceptance and use of this technology in Iran were 
evaluated. 
Results: Review of the selected articles indicated that efficacy and effectiveness of this technology 
is Confirmed. The results also showed that using this method is not economical in Iran. 
Conclusion: According to the revealed evidences and also cost analysis, due to shortage of neces-
sary substructures and economical aspect, installing the off-site sterilization health technology in 
hospitals is not possible currently. But this method can be used to provide sterilization services for 
clinics and outpatients centers. </p>

<p>Keywords: Health technology assessment, Off-site sterilization, In-house sterilization. </p>

<p>Cite this article as: Dehnavieh R, Mirshekari N, Ghasemi S, Goudarzi R, Haghdoost AA, Mehrolhassani MH, Moshkani Z, Noori Hekmat </p>

<p>S. Health technology assessment: Off-site sterilization. Med J Islam Repub Iran 2016 (16 March). Vol. 30:345. </p>

<p>Introduction 
Hospital infections have been always one 
of the most important problems of health 
centers. Due to increasing number of hospi-
tals, the rise of new and emerging diseases, 
increasing microbial resistance and need </p>

<p>for various medical services, incidence of 
health care associated infections has be-
come inevitable (1).In addition to death and 
complications, hospital infections increase 
the hospitalization period and consequently 
increase the cost of medical services and </p>

<p>Health technology assessment: off-site sterilization </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Med J Islam Repub Iran 2016 (16 March). Vol. 30:345. </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>patients' dissatisfaction. Of course applying 
effective methods of sterilization will de-
cline hospital infections and consequently 
the infections caused by it (2). In fact, steri-
lization means applying physical and chem-
ical methods to destruction and disruption 
of all germs Endospore-resistant microbes 
(3). 
Every year millions of dollars are ex-
pended to equip and maintain the hospital 
sterilization centers in the word. The hospi-
tal's Central Sterilization Room, which is 
called CSR, is placed in the vicinity of the 
operating rooms or near the surgical ward. 
This place is the center of preparation and 
distribution of sterilized medical and surgi-
cal supplies for the diagnosis, treatment and 
patient care (4). 
Recently, hospital managers, in the pro-
cess of hospitals' development and pro-
gress, have been faced with numerous chal-
lenges which are caused by advances in 
technology, converting the diseases' ap-
pearance, the growing demand for hospital 
services, and consequently increasing the 
cost of maintenance and equipping or re-
construction of the sterilizations centers. In 
response to these pressures, especially fi-
nancial shortages and to reach high effec-
tiveness, hospital managers are looking for 
new solutions and some changes to design 
and apply in their own sterilizations' ser-
vices (5). 
Sterilization of the medical instrument 
out of the hospital which is called in some 
scientific resources as off-site sterilization 
center or outsourcing the sterilization tasks 
is one of the methods which are applied in 
some hospitals to face above mentioned 
problems. There are so many discussions 
about applying this method such as: costs 
reduction, quality increase, and effective-
ness of medical instrument sterilization. For 
the first time, off-site sterilization center 
was used in Glasgow, Scotland. In this 
way, a company, as an" off-site sterilizing 
company", is responsible to deliver sterili-
zation services to several hospitals (6). 
In 2012, in the wake of demographic 
change, technology growth and increasing </p>

<p>demand for surgical services, Ipswich hos-
pital in England, reviewed its sterilization 
unit available options to deliver efficient 
sterilization services and access to the last 
quality standards. Off-site sterilization was 
one of the considered options (7). Also, in 
2013, National Health Service (NHS) was 
reviewed the off-site sterilization method 
among other considered options. The exam-
ining factors in this survey were the initial 
investment, flexibility, Speed and continui-
ty of sterilization services (8). 
Recently, some Iranian hospitals are 
faced with proposals by domestic and for-
eign companies about construction of off-
site sterilization center focusing on the rea-
sons of workload and costs reduction and 
increasing the sterilization quality. Conse-
quently, some questions have been raised 
for officials. These questions are about ef-
ficacy, efficacy costs and possibility of ap-
plying this method for instrument steriliza-
tion in the service provider centers in Iran. 
Health technology assessment is a tech-
nique which can help to answer the raised 
questions about off-site sterilization cen-
ters and to provide scientific evidence 
based on evidences related to this technolo-
gy for policy maker to decision making. In 
this study of health technology assessment, 
researchers tried to compare new off-site 
sterilization technology with the common 
in-house sterilization method. </p>

<p>Methods 
This study was done in four steps. At the 
first step, consequences of using off-sit 
sterilization centers was identified via sys-
tematic study of evidence, and in the next 
step by combining the information provid-
ed by systematic review of literature and 
local data, economic evaluation was done 
via costs minimization approach. In the 
third step the experiences of using off-site 
sterilization methods in some selected hos-
pitals in the world were gathered and in the 
fourth step possibility of using off-site 
sterilization technology in Iran was sur-
veyed via interviews with experts. </p>

<p>R. Dehnavieh, et al. </p>



<p>Med J Islam Repub Iran 2016 (16 March). Vol. 30:345. </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>Systematic review of research question 
What consequences have been off-site 
sterilization centers in terms of efficacy, 
effectiveness and costs for the hospitals ap-
plying this technology? </p>

<p>Data Sources and Search Strategy 
We searched for relevant English lan-
guage articles, based on keywords in title, 
abstract and MeSH terms. We performed 
searches (in June 2015) of the literature 
indexed in PubMed, Scopus and Science 
Direct using a broad set of terms to max-
imize sensitivity. We also searched the 
Cochrane library as the most important 
systematic reviews database, and the 
Google Scholar for other unpublished lit-
eratures; Searching was supplemented by 
scanning bibliographies from identified 
articles; and mined hand-searching per-
sonal libraries by project staff and experts. 
We asked experts to identify unpublished 
literature. The following search strategies 
were used in PubMed: </p>

<p>Search Strategy (PubMed): 
1. "outsourcing of sterile services" 
2. "outsourcing of sterile" 
3. "off-site sterilization" 
4. "Decentralized sterile services " 
5. (1 or 2 or 3 or 4) 
6. "cost effectiveness" 
7. "Efficacy" 
8. (6 or 7) 
9. (5 AND 8) </p>

<p>Inclusion and exclusion criteria for stud-
ies 
Inclusion criteria included of studies con-
ducted about consequences of using off-site 
sterilization compared with in-house sterili-
zation and also studies in English. The ex-
clusion criteria were studies conducted 
about other sterilizations methods, the func-
tion of sterilization devices, and improving 
ways for sterilization methods. </p>

<p>Selection of studies 
At first, the specifications of articles and 
reports which were gathered from data </p>

<p>banks and other resources were entered into 
the Endnote software. Then using the soft-
ware, the duplicate cases were deleted and 
in the next step two people of research team 
individually reviewed the topics and ab-
stracts of the articles and deleted irrelevant 
cases. Then researchers studied the articles 
completely and carefully and selected the 
relevant articles and deleted the irrelevant 
ones. </p>

<p>Assessing the information quality and ex-
traction and analysis of information 
A checklist includes of 6 questions was 
prepared in order to select the articles. The 
questions were about the exact definition of 
research aim, exact definition of variables 
studied, the exact definition of research 
time and place, selecting a prepare method 
to analyze data, appropriateness of data col-
lection and analysis tools with the research 
aim and reliability of data collection tool. 
Each of the criteria was categorized as 
clearly yes or clearly no. The articles quali-
ty was examined via complete review over 
them. Since we didn't aim to perform Me-
ta-analysis of evidences, to reduce the risk 
of subjective quality judgment, we decided 
not to exclude nor weigh studies based on 
quality rating or scales. "While study quali-
ty assessment is important to judge the ef-
fectiveness, the usefulness of excluding 
studies based on quality has been contest-
ed" (9). We used the results of quality as-
sessment to identify potential gaps in the 
evidence on the off-site sterilization tech-
nology and analyzed their results descrip-
tively. 
Every article's data were extracted based 
on article's topic, the first author, year of 
conducting the research, research method 
and consequences of using off-site steriliza-
tion method and in-house sterilization. 
Analyzing the results of the study was done 
in the form of quantitative summarizing of 
data in terms of efficacy and effectiveness 
variables. </p>

<p>Economic evaluation 
Cost minimization analysis (CMA) was </p>

<p>Health technology assessment: off-site sterilization </p>



<p>Med J Islam Repub Iran 2016 (16 March). Vol. 30:345. </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>used in order to economic evaluation of 
off-site sterilization technology. The CMA 
is used in case of the same outcomes and 
results of applying different services and 
technologies in a field. In simple terms, the 
aim of CMA is to find technology and ser-
vices which have the same quality and con-
sequences but impose fewer costs to the 
service delivery system (10,11). From 
health care system perspective costs in-
clude of personnel costs, special and general 
consumable costs, equipment costs, power 
costs, capital cost and amortization cost sepa-
rated according to the cost centers during a 
year (12). 
To calculate CMA, first of all, the cost of 
CSR was extracted from a study which was 
done in the Flashing hospital of New York, 
in 1990 (6). After applying a discount rate 
of 5%, the cost of CSR changed to current 
value. Counting 34600 Rials for every dol-
lar, the annual cost of off-site sterilization 
method was found. After that, with consid-
ering 4500 sterile bags for every year, the 
cost of every sterile bag was calculated. In-
house sterilization cost was extracted from 
a study which was done in 2007 in Iran, 
and its current value was calculated with 
discount rate of 5%. Then, with considering 
20605 sterile bags for every year, the cost 
of every sterile bag was calculated. </p>

<p>Qualitative method 
A qualitative case-study approach was 
used to explore understand cons and pros of 
off-site sterilization technology from the 
experts' point of view and frontline 
healthcare professionals under public set-
tings. A case study is a research methodol-
ogy that focuses on the circumstances, dy-
namics and complexity of a single case or 
small number of cases (13). Semi-
structured interviews were used for qualita-
tive data gendering. </p>

<p>Identification of experts 
The inclusion criteria were: being a hos-
pital manager or sterilisation ward supervi-
sor for at least 5 years in public hospitals or 
being a Health Technology Assessment ex-</p>

<p>pert. Participants with expertise in Health 
Technology Assessment, Health Services 
Management and Health Economics were 
identified through contact with Standardi-
zation and Tariff Management in Deputy of 
curative affairs of Ministry of Health. Hos-
pital managers and sterilisation ward su-
pervisors were identified in public hospitals 
and recruitment continued through snow-
ball sampling. All identified informants ac-
cepted to participant in the study. 
Totally 14 interviews were conducted 
with informants; 5 interviews with health 
economics and Health Technology As-
sessment experts and 9 interviews with 
hospital managers and supervisors and the 
interviews continued until the point of satu-
ration, in which no new relevant data 
seemed to emerge. Eligible participants 
were approached for written consent and 
there were no concerns related to authority 
relationship between interviewer and inter-
viewee. </p>

<p>Semi-structured interview Guide 
A guided set of open-ended questions was 
developed based on literature review and 
expert opinion. The questions have been 
covered the following: (i) current hospital 
sterilization system, (ii) their knowledge 
about off-site sterilization technology, (iii) 
cons and pros of off-site sterilization tech-
nology in Iran. </p>

<p>Data Collection Procedure 
The semi-structured group interviews 
were conducted at the interviewee's work 
place. Each interview took approximately 
30-40 minutes, and the proceedings were 
audio-recorded with the interviewee's con-
sent. Interviews were transcripted and sub-
sequently sent back to participants for veri-
fication. </p>

<p>Data Analysis 
A framework analytical approach, which 
is appropriate for health policymaking stud-
ies (14), was used for data analysis. Initial 
analysis was conducted by NM and SG us-
ing Framework Analysis independently </p>

<p>R. Dehnavieh, et al. </p>



<p>Med J Islam Repub Iran 2016 (16 March). Vol. 30:345. </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>(15) supported by the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Atlas.ti</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">6</rs> Software 
package. These initial concepts were re-
viewed and revised by the chief investiga-
tor (RD) and subsequently applied to the 
remaining transcripts. Interview transcripts 
from informants were read and re-read and 
multiple emerging themes and subthemes 
framework were designed by the research-
ers and each interview transcript was coded 
using this framework (16). </p>

<p>Ethical Approval 
The purpose of the present study was ex-
plained for all interviewees and written in-
formed consents were taken. All discus-
sions were recorded as anonymous and kept 
confidential. </p>

<p>Results 
Systematic review 
Totally 287 studies were found in the sys-
tematic review. After excluding irrelevant 
topics and repeated ones, 19 relevant stud-
ies were found and surveyed in detail for 
further evaluation. 7 out of 19 studies were 
removed due to lack of abstract or complete 
texts and also 7 other studies were removed 
because they didn't have the entrance crite-
ria (including 3 studies in languages other 
than English, two studies about various off-
site sterilization methods, and two studies 
in calculating the cost of in-house steriliza-
tion method.). Finally only 5 studies were 
found completely relevant to the aims of 
the study (6,7,8,17,18) (Table 1). All of 5 
selected studies were in accordance with 
the 6 quality assessment criteria proposed 
by research team. Figure 1 presents the re-</p>

<p>sults of the search and review strategy for 
Systematic Reviews flow diagram. 
Because of the long-time differences be-
tween studies, their results were so differ-
ent. Only one study was done in 1988, 
which has been compared off-site and in-
house sterilization methods in terms of effi-
cacy and effectiveness. The authors has 
mentioned that after three years, using this 
technology has been ceased because of 
some management concerns including not 
suitable weather conditions such as storms 
and delay in delivering equipment to the 
hospital (6). 
Two studies in 2012 and 2013 compared 
the available options to do sterilization ser-
vices in terms of costs and benefits. The 
results has shown that total cost of off-site 
sterilization was more than other options 
and in other hand had the minimum score 
(7,8) while the results of two older studies 
done in 1988 and 1990 have showed that 
off-site sterilization method results in cost 
saving and is a suitable option to do sterili-
zation services (6,17). Some positive and 
negative consequences of off-site steriliza-
tion method compared with in-house steri-
lization method which were extracted from 
each study were expressed in two variables 
of efficacy and effectiveness (6-8,17,18) 
(Table 2). 
Two main criteria to compare these two 
technologies are efficacy and effectiveness. 
Effectiveness of the technology means the 
technology's ability to convert infected 
tools and equipment into sterile, safe and 
secure ones. Review of the results of stud-
ies shows that the possibility of providing </p>

<p>Table 1. Features of the studies included in systematic review 
Reference 
Study Title 
First author 
Year of publication 
Kind of study 
6 
Off-Site Instrument Sterilizing: 
A New Concept 
Dorsey R 
1988 
Case study </p>

<p>12 
In-house versus off-site sterilization. 
Giarraputo D 
1990 
Costing 
13 
A two-phased approach for the centralization 
versus decentralization of the hospital sterili-
zation service department </p>

<p>Tlahig H 
2009 
Modeling </p>

<p>7 
Compliant Sterilization Services Department 
(SSD) 
Business 
Development 
Planning </p>

<p>2012 
Economical 
assessment 
record 
8 
Sterile Services Department Option Appraisal. 
Grimwood J 
2013 
Sectional 
report </p>

<p>Health technology assessment: off-site sterilization </p>



<p>Med J Islam Repub Iran 2016 (16 March). Vol. 30:345. </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>safe and sterile tools in both methods is the 
same. Efficacy means doing sterilization 
services with a minimum of resources and 
in the minimum time. 
In the other hand negative and positive </p>

<p>mentioned consequences of off-site sterili-
zation such as more total cost, less need for 
staff training, more possibility of delay in 
delivering equipment to the surgery room 
in critical conditions, more need for in-</p>

<p>Fig. 1. Selection process of included studies in the systematic review </p>

<p>Table 2. Off-site and in-house sterilization consequences in terms of efficacy and effectiveness criteria 
Effectiveness 
Criteria 
Options 
Efficacy Criteria 
Study Title </p>

<p>Same in Both 
Off-site S 
possibility of delay in delivering 
equipment to the surgery room 
in critical conditions </p>

<p>off-Site Instrument Sterilizing: A New Con-
cept (1988) </p>

<p>In-house S 
need to the personnel in the 
hospital 
Off-site S 
Save in hospital costs 
In-house versus off-site sterilization. Hospital 
Material Management Quarterly (1990) 
Off-site S 
Save in hospital costs 
A two-phased approach for the centralization 
versus decentralization of the hospital sterili-
zation service department (2009) 
Off-site S 
Administrative and control 
problems 
Off-site S 
Final cost 
The Ipswich Hospital Compliant Sterilization 
Services Department (SSD) (2012) 
In-house S 
need for staff training 
Off-site S 
need for investment 
Sterile Services Department Option Apprais-
al. West Suffolk NHS Foundation Trust 
(2013) </p>

<p>R. Dehnavieh, et al. </p>



<p>Med J Islam Repub Iran 2016 (16 March). Vol. 30:345. </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>vestment, less need for personnel in the 
hospital and saving in fuel and supporting 
costs of hospital, all are considered as ef-
fective factors in the hospital efficacy. </p>

<p>Economic evaluation 
In order to calculate CMA, first of all to-
tal cost of CSR was extracted from the 
study which was done in Flashing hospital 
of New York in 1990. Then considering 
discount rate of 5%, the total cost of CSR 
converted to the current value of 47137384 
dollars. Considering the dollar rate of 
34600, annual cost of off-site sterilization 
method was calculated equal to 16309 mil-
lion Rials and considering 4500 sterile bags 
in every year, the cost of each sterile bag 
was calculated equal to 362434. In-house 
sterilization cost was extracted equal to 461 
million Rials from a study which was done 
in Iran in 2007, and with discount rate of 
5% converted to current value of 682 mil-
lion Rials and considering 20605 sterile 
bags for every year, the sterilization cost 
for each bag were calculated equal to 
33116.Finally, it can be mentioned that for 
each sterile bag, new technology (off-site 
sterilization) imposes 329318 Rails more 
than the other method. </p>

<p>The experience of using Off-site Sterilisa-
tion technology in selected hospitals 
After sending emails to the approved 
hospitals and receiving emails, analysing 
some of the received emails showed that 
using these methods is not common in the-
se hospitals. But some hospitals such as 
Mediclinic hospital in Dubai (Emirates) 
have limited use of this method in order to 
support the city's clinics by the sterilization 
unit which is near the hospital. </p>

<p>Possibility of using Off-site Sterilisation 
technology from interviewee's point of view 
After analysing the experts' interviews, 
effective factors for possibility of using 
each sterilization technology were clustered 
in 3 main themes: hospital related factors, 
employer related factors, and contractor 
related factors. </p>

<p>A: The scope of hospital related factors 
In this scope interviewers pointed to some 
cases which directly affect the bargaining 
power of hospital such as the extent of hos-
pital, possibility of coordinated action be-
tween the region hospitals, the number of 
hospital in the city, available resource and 
equipment in the hospital, the extent of 
hospital's budget flexibility to provide the 
contractor's costs and the situation of tech-
nically competent human resources in the 
hospital. One of the hospital managers 
mentioned: 
"Given the fact that in off-site technology 
hospitals will lose all of their sterilization's 
equipment and skilled staffs, hospitals will 
be at a disadvantage because they couldn't 
bargain with contractors over the forms of 
contracts or its price, but will be faced with 
a "take-it-or-leave-it" choice." 
They also mentioned economic aspects of 
the technology, for example a health eco-
nomic expert stated that: 
"Nowadays our hospitals have significant 
investment to equip their central steriliza-
tion units and ceasing them and outsourcing 
sterilization services to out of hospital con-
tractors is not economical." </p>

<p>B: The scope of employer related factors 
In this scope some factors such as tech-
nical competence and the managers' point 
of view about the outsourcing strategy were 
focused. Manager should have necessary 
knowledge, experience, competence and 
ability for outsourcing the sterilization ser-
vices and could find the appropriate pro-
viders. From interviewer's view, manage-
ment changes, some managers' weaknesses 
to find the program deviation and hospital 
services sensitivity in unexpected disasters 
all points out the difficulty of outsourcing 
sensitive services such as sterilization. Here 
is one of the comments: 
"Another reason is that there are lots of 
activities in the hospitals and hospital man-
agers have to find shortest path for critical 
process like sterilisation. Furthermore, most 
of them don't have skills and Knowledge 
for outsourced services quality control." </p>

<p>Health technology assessment: off-site sterilization </p>



<p>Med J Islam Repub Iran 2016 (16 March). Vol. 30:345. </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>C: The scope of contractor related factors 
In this scope the view and the satisfac-
tion's extent of clinical teams with the con-
tractors' performance, mutual trust, and the 
existence of valid institute with technical 
knowledge were the main considered sub-
jects by the interviewers. In the case of 
identifying unacceptable performance for 
the off-site sterilization centres by the hos-
pital's clinical team, it is not possible to 
have an appropriate working relationship. 
Need for too much investment and the im-
portance of security for the investors were 
other concerns mentioned by the experts. 
Sometime medical science universities 
cannot participate in such an investment 
and there is a need for intersectional in-
vestment that it is not possible at least in 
small towns. One participant commented 
the following: 
"The problem is that we cannot rely on 
these contractors, they may suddenly stop 
cooperating with hospital or ask for more 
money." </p>

<p>Discussion 
The subject of outsourcing hospital ser-
vices has been under consideration of many 
managers and policymakers. Sometimes 
successful experiences in order to increase 
efficacy and effectiveness of services, and 
consequently increasing the customers' sat-
isfaction with the quality of hospital ser-
vices have recorded (19-21). In this study 
off-site sterilization technology, that recent-
ly some contractor companies in Iran have 
made widespread propaganda about its 
benefits and it has used in some hospitals of 
other countries, was evaluated. At the first 
chapter of research's findings, efficacy and 
effectiveness of this technology were ana-
lysed in comparison with central in-house 
sterilization technology via assessing the 
result of systematic review of evidence. 
Findings of economical assessment were 
presented in the second chapter by the 
minimization of costs method. In the third 
chapter, the qualitative views of experts, 
about possibility of applying this technolo-
gy in Iran, were analysed. </p>

<p>The systematic review of the available 
evidences revealed that limited studies 
about off-site sterilization method have 
been published. The evidence of effective-
ness, cost of effectiveness and effects of 
this method on equipment's sterilization 
process and also its final consequences are 
so limited and sometimes they are in con-
trast with each other and also have been 
changed during the time. 
Analysing the result of selected articles 
revealed that typically older articles have 
been reported more efficacy, affectivity and 
economical saving for off-site sterilization 
method (6). In contrast newer articles have 
showed opposite results. While effective-
ness, which means providing safe and ster-
ile equipment, is reported the same in both 
methods, efficacy criteria such as capital 
and current costs, time and access are main-
ly reported in favour of in-house steriliza-
tion method (7, 8,18). 
In health technology studies which are 
done on the group of management or sup-
portive technologies, the result are signifi-
cantly affected by social, cultural and or-
ganizational conditions (22,23). In this 
study, according to the experts' point of 
view, the possibility of applying off-site 
sterilization method is different in various 
conditions whereas it is only possible to 
apply off-site sterilization technology in big 
cities that have many hospitals and it is 
more possible to change the contactor. In 
small cities hospitals cannot rely on con-
tractors in order to providing sterile equip-
ment and tools. If this technology is ap-
proved as an applicable technology in Iran, 
it is necessary to identify which cities can 
apply it and new hospitals which are going 
to be established in these cities should 
equip with the assumption of applying off-
site sterilization method. 
Reducing hospital costs, access to the 
new sterilization technology, time saving, 
the possibility of employing professional 
staff and providing continues training for 
them are some cases the mentioned about 
the benefits of using off-site sterilization 
method. In this regard, managers and uni-</p>

<p>R. Dehnavieh, et al. </p>



<p>Med J Islam Repub Iran 2016 (16 March). Vol. 30:345. </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>versity experts should propound the stand-
ards, procedures and policies that the con-
tractor should perform and provide mecha-
nism to enforce them (24,25,26). 
There are also some limitations on out-
sourcing the hospital services. For example, 
contractors may not be able to understand 
the organization's culture and the hospital's 
conditions (27). Always there is a risk of 
contractors' entrance to the market as the 
organization's competitor (28). Some stud-
ies have reported that delivering vital ser-
vices out of the hospitals reduces the hospi-
tal's ability to meet urgent needs in times of 
crisis. If the contractor does not adhere to 
its obligations on the quantity and quality 
of services, due to the specialized nature of 
services and need for considerable invest-
ment, changing the contractor will be really 
difficult for the hospitals (29). So, monopo-
ly on the important issue of providing hos-
pital sterile equipment of a city in the hands 
of a company can be a serious threat (30). </p>

<p>Limitations 
This review revealed severe shortage in 
the published studies to assess off-site steri-
lization technology. The main methodolog-
ical weaknesses identified in these studies 
were the use of largely invalidated instru-
ments to assess off-site sterilization tech-
nology efficacy and effectiveness, and lack 
of details regarding the data analysis meth-
ods. 
Another limitation for this study was that 
there were no study regarding off-site steri-
lization technology in Iran, therefor, some 
participants had not heard anything about 
this technology. To reduce the effect of this 
limitation, we had to explain off-site sterili-
zation technology characteristics to them. 
Since most of health technology assessment 
studies carried out before rising a new 
technology, many experts do not have 
much experience of the performance of the 
technology (31-34). 
Moreover, although we performed a wide 
search of the literature to identify studies 
which estimates cost of sterilization in 
Iran's public hospitals, we couldn't find </p>

<p>any related study to compare our results 
with other studies results. 
Nonetheless, emerged themes show con-
sistencies in the health managers and health 
technology assessment and health econom-
ic expert opinions about main pros and 
cons of off-site sterilization technology in 
Iranian public hospitals. </p>

<p>Conclusion 
Analysing the results of this study sug-
gests that considering the investments made 
in the sterilization wards of Iranian hospi-
tals and shortage of necessary infrastruc-
tures for hospitals, nowadays, delivering 
off-site sterilization services is not econom-
ically possible. It is obvious that after en-
trance of newer technologies and equip-
ment to reduce the sterilization costs, facili-
tation of transporting the sterile equipment 
to the hospitals, appropriate training for the 
staff, and foundation of sterilization major 
in medical science universities in the fu-
ture, off-site sterilization method can be 
revised. However, off-site sterilization 
method is acceptable for clinics and outpa-
tient centres. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment 
This work was done under national insti-
tute of health research contract no. 
241/ки/91292.2013. The funding sources had 
no role in the design, analysis, or interpre-
tation of the study or in the decision to 
submit the manuscript for publication. </p>



<p>Health technology assessment: off-site sterilization </p>





<p>R. Dehnavieh, et al. </p>





</text></tei>