<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4309330" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Objectives: Despite the increasing utilization of in-home services, 
the assessment of in-home services used by those that have certified 
levels of care needs has been limited to the actual changes in indi-
vidual outcomes. The purpose of the present study was to determine 
factors affecting how the utilization of in-home services could have 
sustained and/or improved or deteriorated the care needs levels of 
frail persons. We also examined the effect of in-home services used 
in the lower level of care needs subgroup and the higher level of 
care needs subgroup during a two-year period. 
Subjects and Methods: We used longitudinal data from Izumo 
City of those individuals with certified levels of care needs to ana-
lyze the changes in care need levels in Izumo City between 2002 to 
2004. In 2002, 2,651 persons had certified levels of care needs. All 
permanent residents of care facilities, at care needs level 5 in 2002, 
those who died since 2002 and people who could not be traced dur-
ing the two-year follow-up period were excluded. The remaining 
data from 1,788 frail persons were ultimately analyzed. We arbi-
trarily divided the changes in care needs levels into two categories: 
sustained/improved and deteriorated. The care needs levels were 
also stratified into a lower level of care needs subgroup and a higher 
level of care needs subgroup at the baseline. Simple statistical anal-
ysis and binary logistic regression analysis were used to analyze 
factors that were thought to be related to in-home service utilization 
data to predict changes in care needs levels. 
Results: Approximately 63.3% of the respondents had a sustained 
or improved care needs level, and 36.7% of the respondents showed 
deteriorated of care needs levels. In the lower level of care needs 
subgroup, utilization of home help/bathing (OR=2.59) was associ-
ated with significant sustained/improved care needs levels. In the 
higher level of care needs subgroup, day care service (OR=0.90) 
and short stay services (OR=0.87) were significantly related to de-
teriorated care needs levels, respectively. </p>

<p>Conclusions: This study shows that home help/bathing care in the 
lower level of care needs subgroup was a significant predictor of 
sustained/improved levels of care needs for frail persons but that 
short stay services and day care services in the higher level of care 
needs subgroup have a negative impact on sustained/improved lev-
els of care needs. Our results suggest that utilization of home help 
services can prevent deterioration of these levels of care needs in 
frail persons. </p>

<p>The family's capacity to care for the elderly is weaken-
ing because of a changing household structure, an increas-
ing number of working women and an enhanced social se-
curity system in Japan. There are 4.884 million people in 
Japan certified as eligible for the long-term care insurance 
system. The ratio of those aged 65 and over was 16.9%, 
and the number of home services users was 2.924 million 
people in May 2010 </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>. Disabilities are associated with a loss 
of independence, an increased need for health care services 
and subsequently higher health care costs </p>

<p>2-4) </p>

<p>. In response to 
these problems, the public long-term care insurance system 
(LTCIS) was introduced in 2000 by the Ministry of Health, 
Labour and Welfare, which focuses on providing both in-
home services (home care) and also services at facilities (in-
stitutional care). All persons aged 65 and over are eligible, 
along with people aged 40 to 64 who have a health-related 
disability. In-home services have become the fastest grow-
ing segment of the Japan LTCIS. They are expected to play 
a significant role as an effective tool for not only preventing 
deterioration and improving the disability status for frail 
persons but also decreasing the burden for family caregivers </p>

<p>J Rural Med 2012; 7(1): 6-14 </p>

<p>©2012 The Japanese Association of Rural Medicine </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Jung-Nim Kim, Tokyo University and Graduate 
School of Social Welfare, 2020-1 Sano-cho, Isesaki City, Gunma 372-
0831, Japan 
E-mail: daab2000@gmail.com </p>



<p>and improving the lives of those living in the community 
with certified care needs levels. 
There is an ongoing debate over the effectiveness of in-
home services for the various levels of care needs of frail 
persons. Despite a considerable number of meta-analyses 
and reviews synthesizing the home-visit nursing literature </p>

<p>5) </p>

<p>, 
there have been few reviews examining in-home services 
for those with certified levels of care needs or support needs, 
and the available literature does little to inform us about 
whether the association of in-home services with levels of 
care needs of frail persons has been maintained/improved 
or deteriorated in Japan since the implementation of the na-
tional long-term care insurance system (LTCIS). 
The main objective of the present study was to deter-
mine how the utilization of in-home services could have 
sustained/improved or deteriorated the levels of care needs 
of frail persons. We also examined the effect of in-home 
services used in the lower level of care needs subgroup and 
the higher level of care needs subgroup during a two-year 
period. Studies have been limited by the lack of evidence 
for the effectiveness of in-home services for frail elderly 
on changes in levels of care needs such as lower level of 
care needs and higher level of care needs </p>

<p>6) </p>

<p>. Some studies 
have indicated that in-home services had positive or nega-
tive effects on reductions in functional levels. Kato et al. </p>

<p>7) </p>

<p>found that use of respite stays in a nursing home, and use 
of medical management by a physician were significantly 
related to a deterioration of the user's levels of care needs. 
On the other hand, Ishibashi et al. 
8) demonstrated that the 
risk of decline in functional status was lower for users of 
home help services. Moreover, Fukuma and Shiwaku 
6) indi-
cated that at the end of tracking of two years, improvement 
in the care level was related to either levels of care needs or 
utilization of short stays. A study by Tomita et al. 
9) reported 
that among the types of services, users of respite care and 
rental services for assistive devices were less likely to be 
hospitalized or institutionalized than nonusers. Concerning 
those with relatively light needs, users of day care services 
were also less likely to be hospitalized or institutionalized 
than nonusers. Markle-Reid et al. 
10) found that a variety of 
home visiting interventions carried out by nurses can favor-
ably affect health and functional status and mortality rates. 
However, Stuck et al. 
11) used subgroup analysis to reveal that 
public home-visit nursing can reduce disabilities among el-
derly people at low risk but not among those at high risk 
for functional impairment after three years. Other studies, 
however, indicated that the use of home help services had no 
effect on reducing functional decline </p>

<p>7, 11-13) </p>

<p>. 
Although multidimensional services and levels of care 
needs have been studied, these previous reviews have had 
significant limitations. There is still insufficient evidence </p>

<p>not only regarding the effectiveness of in-home based ser-
vices 
7) but also what kinds of in-home services have a sig-
nificant predictor of sustained/improved level of care needs 
for frail persons in the lower level of care needs subgroup 
and the higher level of care needs subgroup in panel study. 
Given the shortcomings of previous reviews and the lack of 
consistency among their findings, we thought it important to 
undertake a panel analysis to clarify the benefits of in-home 
based services. The results of this study will contribute to 
the discussion concering effective in-home service strate-
gies for frail persons. </p>

<p>Subjects and Methods </p>

<p>Subjects </p>

<p>All subjects were selected from those who had applied 
for LTCI for the first time beginning in April 2002 and had 
been newly certified as community-dwelling frail persons 
in Izumo City, Shimane Prefecture, Japan. The subjects 
in the first wave were 2,625 residents in 2000, those in the 
second wave were 3,435 residents in 2002 and those in the 
third wave were 4,206 residents in 2004. The population in 
the third wave was comprised of residents who were ob-
served by a survey that was subsequently performed every 
two years by the Izumo long-term care insurance union 
in Izumo City. We used second wave and third wave data 
(2002-2004) from those who were certified for long-term 
care insurance by the Izumo LTCI union. Because the care 
insurance system started in 2000 in Japan, the second wave 
data was more stable than the first wave data. 
Of the 2,651 subjects who were certified as "support 
level of care needs" or "care needs levels 1 to 5" in Izumo 
City in 2002, 1,788 completed the entire survey in 2004. The 
subjects of the analysis were calculated by limiting the nu-
merator to those who were certified as "support need" or 
"levels of care needs". First, all permanent residents of care 
facilities were excluded from the analysis. Second, 435 peo-
ple who died and 99 people who could not be traced during 
the two-year follow-up period in 2002 were also excluded. 
Third, 329 people at care needs level 5 in 2002 were exclud-
ed. Because the subjects were limited to those capable of 
living at home in 2004 and the dependent variables include 
the change in the care needs levels, care needs level 5 could 
be identified as sustained or improved but could not be clas-
sified as deteriorated. </p>

<p>Dependent variables </p>

<p>The levels of care needs were determined by Izumo City 
through a predetermined process. A trained local govern-
ment official visits the home to evaluate nursing care needs 
using a questionnaire on current physical and mental status </p>



<p>(73 items) and use of medical procedures (12 items). A com-
puter program classifies each applicant into one of six levels 
of dependency care after the evaluation. The Nursing Care 
Needs Certification Board, consisting of social and health 
services experts appointed by the mayor, determines wheth-
er the initial levels of care needs are appropriate </p>

<p>14) </p>

<p>. Care 
needs level 0 (assistance required) is intended for preventive 
services. The other five levels of care needs (care required) 
range from the lowest (level 1 of care need) to highest (care 
needs level 5) levels of care needs </p>

<p>7) </p>

<p>. We arbitrarily set the 
changes in levels of care needs into two categories: sus-
tained or improved and deteriorated. The changes in the lev-
els of care needs were calculated by subtracting the baseline 
levels of care needs from the levels of care needs in 2004. If 
a subject's change in level of care needs was calculated to be 
0 or -1&gt;, the change in the level of care needs was defined as 
a "sustained" or "improved." If the subject's change in level 
of care needs was calculated to be &lt;1, the change in level of 
care needs was defined as "deteriorated." </p>

<p>Independent variables and controlled variables </p>

<p>In-home services can be provided by nonprofit and for-
profit firms. An eligible person must pay a 10% co-payment 
for each insured service and the municipality pays the rest. 
The independent variables included in-home services of 8 
kinds: home help service, home-visit bathing, home-visit 
nursing, home-visit rehabilitation, day care service, day re-
habilitation service, rental service for equipment, and short 
stay service. The response categories for this question were 
dichotomized (used service or did not used service). There 
were significantly fewer users of home help service and 
home-visit bathing, respectively, so these services were cal-
culated as sum categories 1 and 2 concerning use of home 
help service and home-visit bathing, with category 1 indi-
cating that the home help/bathing was not used. 
The controlled variables included age, gender, and 
household structure. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Descriptive analysis of the following statistical results 
characterize the face sheets of the subjects, levels of care 
needs and in-home service. First, differences in the changes 
in levels of care needs and baseline characteristics were ex-
amined with simple statistical analysis and cross tabulation. 
Second, cross tabulation is the process of creating a contin-
gency table from the multivariate frequency distribution of 
statistical variables, and we tested for the statistical signifi-
cance of values. Third, binary logistic regression analysis 
was used to build a final model for utilization of in-home 
service with the dependent variable divided into two catego-
ries, sustained/improved and deteriorated. </p>

<p>The changes in levels of care needs were stratified into a 
lower level of care needs subgroup and a higher level of care 
needs subgroup based on the baseline levels of care needs. 
The lower level of care needs subgroup included the support 
level and care needs level 1. The higher level of care needs 
subgroup included care needs level 2, 3 and 4. Because the 
LTCI system was amended in April 2006 to include 7 levels 
instead of 6, with eligibility determined through a process 
of care needs certification by the municipality, those eligible 
were 1) persons certified before the revision as "support lev-
el" (support level 1 in the new classification) and 2) persons 
with a higher possibility of maintaining or improving their 
condition among those certified before the revision as care 
needs level 1 (support level 2 in the new classification) </p>

<p>15) </p>

<p>. 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> 18.0J <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Windows</rs> was used for the statistical analy-
sis. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Characteristics of the study population </p>

<p>Table 1 shows the characteristics of the frail persons at 
baseline and during the two-year follow-up period. Overall, 
the data showed that female subjects were nearly 65% and 
68% in 2002 and 2004, respectively. Those 85 years and over 
of the subjects were 37.8% and 43.7% in 2002 and 2004, re-
spectively. In 2002 and 2004, more than 68% and 63% of the 
subjects lived in a two-generation household, respectively. 
In 2002 and 2004, 23% and 30% of the subjects were care 
needs level 1 and 12.4% of the subjects and 9.7% were care 
needs level 5, respectively. There was a difference in utiliza-
tion of home help service, with 29% and 32% of the subjects 
using more day care service in 2002 and 2004, 25.3% and 
24.4% of the subjects used home help service or home-visit 
bathing in 2002 and 2004, respectively. More than 63.3% of 
the subjects had a sustained or improved level of care needs, 
nearly 36.7% of the subjects had a deteriorated level of care 
needs and more than 18.7% of the subjects had died. </p>

<p>Distribution of care needs levels </p>

<p>Table 2 shows the changes in care needs levels of frail 
persons with regard to utilization of in-home services. For 
utilization of in-home services, using of home help/bathing 
and day care service exhibited statistically significant re-
sults and were related to a sustained/improved level of care 
needs, respectively. About 78% of the subjects used home 
help/bathing, 71% of the subjects used day care service and 
58% of the subjects were using day rehabilitation were as-
sociated with significant sustained/improved care needs lev-
els, respectively. In contrast, about 59% of the subjects us-
ing short stays in a facility were associated with significant 
deteriorated care needs levels. Whereas, for 60% of the sub-</p>



<p>jects using home-visit nursing and rental service for equip-
ment was associated with no significant stained/improved 
care needs levels, respectively. 
The care needs level 1 to 4 had a sustained/improved 
care needs level as compare to support level of care needs 
group. There was an insignificant difference between men 
and women in the change in care needs levels. Those young-
er than 65 years and over at baseline had more changes cat-
egorized sustained/improved level of care needs. Household 
size was almost the same in sustain/improved and deterio-
rated level of care needs. 
In the present study, we considered all these confound-
ing factors in order to evaluate the change in the levels of 
care needs in frail persons, and we compared in-home ser-
vices with age and levels of care needs factors. Of the age 
groups, the 65-74-year-old age group used significantly </p>

<p>more home help/bathing (9.7% vs. 7.6%, p &lt; 0.48) and day 
rehabilitation (18.9% vs. 8.6%, p = 0.00), than the 85 years 
and over age group; however, the 85 years and over age 
group used significantly more day care service (31.3% vs. 
22.5%, p &lt; 0.00) and short stays (9.8% vs. 3.5%, p = 0.00) 
than the 65-74-year-old age group. The higher level of care 
needs subgroup used significantly more home help/bathing 
(8.5% vs. 8%, p &lt; 0.00), day rehabilitation (14.2% vs. 9.5%, 
p = 0.00), and short stays (9.7% vs. 2.4%, p = 0.00) than the 
lower level of care needs subgroup, however, the lower level 
of care needs subgroup used significantly more day care ser-
vice (27.9% vs. 27.4%, p &lt; 0.00) than the higher level of care 
needs subgroup. </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of the frail persons of the Izumo in-home cohort study </p>

<p>2002 
2004 
2002 
2004 
Variables 
Response category 
% (N=3,435) % (N=2,322) % (N=2,651) % (N=1,788) 
Stay in place 
In-home 
77.2 (2,651) 
Group home 
0.8 ( 27) 
Special nursing home 
12.0 ( 412) 
Health service facility 
7.1 ( 243) 
Sanatorium type mecical care facility 
3.3 ( 115) 
Death 
18.7 (435) 
Could not track 
4.3 ( 99) 
Gender 
Male 
35.2 ( 934) 31.7 ( 566) 
Female 
64.8 (1,717) 68.3 (1,222) 
Age 
40-64 years 
4.3 ( 114) 
3.2 ( 57) 
65-74 years 
17.5 ( 463) 14.0 ( 251) 
75-84 years 
40.5 (1,073) 39.1 ( 699) 
85 years and over 
37.8 (1,001) 43.7 ( 781) 
Mean±standard deviation 
81.1 ± 8.9 
82.4 ± 8.8 
Household 
Living alone 
13.6 ( 349) 17.4 ( 310) 
Living with spouse 
18.3 ( 401) 17.9 ( 320) 
Lining with 2-generations or more 
68.1 (1,749) 62.7 (1,119) 
Care needs levels 
Support level 
10.6 ( 280) 10.2 ( 183) 
Care level 1 
23.3 ( 618) 29.9 ( 535) 
Care level 2 
20.6 ( 547) 18.7 ( 334) 
Care level 3 
15.9 ( 421) 19.0 ( 340) 
Care level 4 
11.0 ( 292) 12.4 ( 222) 
Care level 5 
12.4 ( 329) 
9.7 ( 174) 
In-home services used 
Home help/bathing 
25.3 ( 671) 24.4 ( 437) 
Home-visit nursing 
9.5 ( 253) 
7.9 ( 141) 
Day care service 
29.0 ( 770) 32.0 ( 572) 
Day rehabilitation 
14.2 ( 376) 13.9 ( 249) 
Short stay 
9.7 ( 257) 11.2 ( 201) 
Rental service for equipment 
21.8 ( 577) 27.3 ( 488) 
Total number of services used in-home 
(mean±SD) 
1.01 ± 1.02 
1.01 ± 1.02 </p>

<p>Changesinf levels of care needs 
Sustaind or improved 
63.3 (1,132) 
Deteriorated 
36.7 ( 656) </p>



<p>Results of logistic regression analysis for changes in the lev-
els of care needs </p>

<p>Table 3 shows the binary logistic regression analysis re-
sults. In Table 3, the changes to sustained/improved in the 
lower level of care needs subgroup are indicated in Model 1, 
and the changes to sustained/improved in the higher level of 
care needs subgroup are indicated in Model 2. 
For the lower level of care needs subgroup in Model 1, 
utilization of home help/bathing service (OR= 2.59; CI, 1.38-
4.87) was significantly higher for the sustained/improved 
level of care needs compared with the group that did not use 
in-home services. For the following types of service, utili-
zation of day care service (OR=1.08; CI, 0.96-1.23), rental 
service for equipment (OR=1.04; CI, 0.95-1.15), home-visit 
nursing (OR=0.69; CI, 0.46-1.02), day care service (OR=0.97; 
CI, 0.87-1.08), and short stays in a facility (OR=0.87; CI, 
0.74-1.02), there was no statistically significant difference 
in sustained/improved level of care needs for frail persons, 
respectively. 
The higher level of care needs subgroup in Model 2 in-
cludes care needs levels 2 to level 4. We observed that the 
utilization of a short stays in a facility (OR=0.87; CI, 0.81-
0.94) was significantly related to a negatively sustained/ 
improved level of care needs. That is, that group was more 
likely to move into a deteriorated level of care needs. Like-
wise, using day care service (OR=0.90; CI, 0.82-0.99) was </p>

<p>significantly related to deterioration of care needs levels as 
compared with subjects who did not use in-home services. 
In contrast, utilization of home help/bathing service (OR= 
1.29; CI, 0.80-2.08), day rehabilitation service (OR= 1.09; 
CI, 1.00-1.19), and rental service for equipment (OR= 1.01; 
CI, 0.94-1.08) resulted in no statically significant differenc-
es in sustained/improved level of care needs in those groups, 
respectively. 
We also observed that the higher level of care needs 
subgroup in Model 2, living with a spouse (OR= 1.87; CI, 
1.08-3.22) among subjects was significantly related to sus-
tained/improved level of care needs. On the other hand, age 
(OR= 0.95; CI, 0.93-0.97; OR= 0.97; CI, 0.95-0.98) of sub-
jects was significantly related to deterioration level of care 
needs in the lower and higher care needs level subgruop, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We studied frail persons based on a cohort study to as-
sess the effects of utilization of in-home services among 
lower level and higher level of care needs subgroups of 
community-dwelling elderly in Japan. 
Differences in utilization of in-home services occurred 
between the lower level of care needs subgroup and higher 
level of care needs subgroup. The use of home help or home-</p>

<p>Table 2 Changes in levels of care needs of frail persons with utlizaiton of in-home services </p>

<p>Variables 
Response category 
Sustained/Improved 
% (N=1,132) </p>

<p>Deteriorated 
% (N=656) </p>

<p>Total 
% (N=1,788) </p>

<p>Gender 
Male 
67.5 
32.5 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>100.0 
Female 
61.3 
38.7 
100.0 </p>

<p>Age 
40-64 years 
84.8 
15.2 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>100.0 
65-74 years 
75.6 
24.4 
100.0 
75-84 years 
67.7 
37.3 
100.0 
85 years and over 
54.0 
46.0 
100.0 </p>

<p>Household 
Living alone 
63.3 
36.7 </p>

<p>n.s. </p>

<p>100.0 
Living with spouse 
63.1 
36.9 
100.0 
Lining with 2-generations or more 
62.5 
37.5 
100.0 </p>

<p>Care needs levels 
Support level 
48.1 
51.9 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>100.0 
Care level 1 
69.2 
30.8 
100.0 
Care level 2 
59.9 
40.1 
100.0 
Care level 3 
67.4 
32.6 
100.0 
Care level 4 
63.3 
36.7 
100.0 </p>

<p>In-home services used Home help/bathing Yes 
78.4 
21.6 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>100.0 
Visit nursing 
Yes 
61.3 
38.7 </p>

<p>n.s. </p>

<p>100.0 
Day care service 
Yes 
71.2 
28.8 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>100.0 
Day rehabilitation Yes 
57.8 
42.5 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>100.0 
Short stay 
Yes 
41.1 
58.9 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>100.0 
Rental service for equipment Yes 
65.1 
34.9 </p>

<p>n.s. </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>* and **; * &lt; 0.05 and ** &lt; 0.01, respectively. </p>



<p>visit bathing services was significantly related to a positive-
ly sustained/improved level of care needs in the lower level 
of care needs subgroup. However, use of short-stay and day 
care service were significantly related to a worsening pre-
dictor of level of care needs of frail persons in the higher 
level of care needs subgroup. In the controlled variables, 
living with a spouse was significantly related to a positively 
sustained/improved level of care needs in the higher level of 
care needs subgroup; however, age of the frail persons was 
significantly related to worsening level of care needs in both 
the lower level of care needs and higher level of care needs 
subgroups. In our study, we took these factors into consider-
ation by adjusting for insured persons obtained from records 
concering certification of needed for long-term care. 
Our study could not identify causal relationships from 
empirical analysis. However, we can explain conjecturally 
why some use of services showed a significant relationship 
with sustain/improved level of care needs or a deteriorating 
level of care needs. 
Based on our conjecture, the subjects who used home 
help service or home-visit bathing had improved or sus-
tained level of care needs in the lower level of care needs 
subgroup but were at far higher risk of ADL (Activity of 
Daily Living) limitations and/ or cognitive impairments 
than others. In the lower care needs subgroup, the reason 
that home helpers are professionals and provides skilled 
care works to frail persons who need care continue to live 
as independently as possible at home. Frail persons can de-
cide who come to their house and provides care and thery 
can set home helpers schedule and determine how and when 
the tasks will be done. Thus, the main focus of long-term 
care services is on primary prevention of disability for frail 
persons, and this need has been met especially for those us-
ing these services. Regarding home visiting services, Elkan 
et al. 
16) indicated that regular home visits for elderly people 
was associated with a significant reduction in mortality and 
admission to long-term institutional care. 
Use of short-term admission to a facility was particu-
larly salient in the higher level of care needs subgroup. The 
users of this services were less likely than nonusers of in-
home services to have a sustained or improved level of care 
needs in the higher level of care needs subgroup. These us-
ers, on average, had more severe ADL or IADL limitations 
and/or cognitive impairments than other. This may also be 
the reason why these services have been focused on fam-
ily caregivers for those with greater burden or for working 
fanilies etc. who do not provide informal care. This is sup-
ported by the fact that numerous publications have evalu-
ated the effect of short-stay service focusing on outcomes 
for caregivers, not care recipients </p>

<p>7, 17) </p>

<p>. Thus, those who used 
respite care were less likely than nonusers to be hospitalized </p>

<p>or institutionalized </p>

<p>9) </p>

<p>. This service may reduce the care bur-
den of family caregivers, allowing them to maintain their 
ability to provide care </p>

<p>9, 18) </p>

<p>, but so far, most of the users are 
at either a sustained or improved level of care needs. Re-
garding effect of program, Brunette et al. 
19) indicated that 
patients in long-term programs had significantly better out-
comes than those in short-term programs. Quality of care 
is fundamentally a multidimensional concept, which in ad-
dition to clinical information, includes quality of life and 
the satisfaction of the frail persons and the caregiver </p>

<p>20) </p>

<p>, that 
needs to be considered, in association with the improvement 
levels of care needs among those who have a higher level of 
care needs, which becomes more pronounced as the popula-
tion continues to age. 
Concerning the impact of day care use on the deteriora-
tion level of needs in the high level of care needs subgroup, 
we should consider that the service users, on average, had 
less risk of ADL limitations and/or cognitive impairments. 
Thus, many day care service centers have not employed spe-
cialists to perform services, which includes programs for 
frail persons like physical therapy, psychological services 
and special programs of recreation according to the needs 
of the frail persons in the high level of care needs subgroup. 
The day service center programs provide basic services to 
frail persons including meals, transportation, bathing and 
simple recreation by care workers. We also consider that the 
number of care workers in day care services is significantly 
less than those in facilities providing care to frail persons. A 
care worker ratio of 1:15 was maintained for subjects deter-
mined to be frail persons by the LTCS, and sufficient care 
could not be provided for frail persons to maintain their 
physical and mental health, especially in the high level of 
care needs subgroup. Thus, users of day care services were 
more likely than nonusers to be independent and more likely 
to be co-performers of activities of daily living with care 
workers. A sufficient ratio of care workers to frail persons 
needs to be established to increase the proportion of frail 
persons who improve or sustain their level of care needs, 
and it is an important public policy issue. 
Concerning the baseline confounding factors for dete-
riorated level of care needs, day care users and short-stay 
service users were older and had a higher level of care needs 
in users with deterioration of physical or mental function. 
However, regarding a sustained/improved level of care 
needs, home help/bathing users were young elderly and had 
a lower level of care needs. It has been suggested that the 
young-old population gains greater benefit from follow-up 
home help/bathing services than the old-old population. 
Therefore, a seemingly baseline higher level of care needs 
was related to a deteriorating of level of care needs even 
though the subjects were using day care and short stay ser-</p>



<p>vices. 
However, there was no evidence of an effect of improve-
ment or sustained level of care needs on users of in-home 
services, home-visit nursing, day rehabilitation services and 
welfare equipment among both the lower level of care needs 
subgroup and higher level of care needs subgroup. Concern-
ing in-home services, a previous study reported the effect of 
improvement level of care needs on some types of in-home 
services </p>

<p>6, 7, 21, 22) </p>

<p>. It may be necessary to focus more investi-
gators on the effect of various types of in-home services on 
changes in the level of care needs of frail persons. A study in 
Saskatchewan, Canada 
23) concluded that persons receiving 
home care were more likely to experience improvement of 
their level of care needs than those not receiving home care. 
Therefore, there exists an urgent need to develop and test the 
effectiveness of in-home services and strategies designed to 
improve the level of care needs, or to at least maintain the 
level of care needs, among frail persons and to determine 
how well in-home services and other strategies work in both 
the lower level of care needs and higher level of care needs 
subgroups. 
Overall, utilization of home help/bathing services in the 
lower level of care needs subgroup was a significant pre-
dictor of improved/maintained levels of care needs for frail 
persons. We consider in-home services to have at least two </p>

<p>main purposes. The first is to provide an alternative to resi-
dential support, enabling people to stay in their communi-
ties, families or homes. The second is to provide respite care 
for family caregivers, often the children or spouse of the 
frail persons who are provided home care. Our findings are 
only preliminary, but they provide further evidence sup-
porting the importance of the effects of the levels of care 
needs for frail persons using in-home services. Given the 
pressures to reduce public spending on care of frail persons 
and a growing desire for in-home services for the elderly, the 
emphasis on caring for elderly people in their own homes 
has gained momentum across social welfare systems in the 
developed world </p>

<p>24-26) </p>

<p>. In-home services for frail persons are 
intended to improve the quality of services for improvement 
or maintenance of the level of care needs, though it is not yet 
known whether frail persons and their families are able to 
be appropriate judges of which providers and which kind of 
in-home services will provide the best type of care. 
Nevertheless, we note several limitations of the present 
study. First, the data did not contain any relevant informa-
tion regarding the socioeconomic situation of frail persons 
or family caregivers or the quality of home care service 
provided. Whether these additional sources of information 
affect the levels of care needs for frail persons and the cat-
egories is an issue that requires further investigation. Sec-</p>

<p>Table 3 Logisitic regression analysis for changes in levels of care needs </p>

<p>Factor Category </p>

<p>Sustained/Improved 
in the lower level 
Odds ratio (95% CI) 
Model 1 </p>

<p>Sustained/Improved 
in the higher level 
Odds ratio (95% CI) 
Model 2 </p>

<p>Gender 
Male 
1.00 reference 
1.00 reference 
Female 
1.166 (0.84-1.63) 
0.74 (0.53-1.01) 
Age 
0.95 (0.93-0.97) </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.97 (0.95-0.98) </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Household 
Living alone 
1.00 reference 
1.00 reference 
Living with spouse 
0.69 (0.43-1.09) 
1.87 (1.08-3.22) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Living with 2 generations or more 
0.91 (0.62-1.33) 
1.48 (0.95-0.98) 
In-home services used 
Nonuse of care sevices 
1.00 reference 
1.00 reference 
Home help/bathing 
2.59 (1.38-4.87) </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>1.29 (0.80-2.08) 
Home-visit nursing 
0.69 (0.46-1.02) 
0.94 (0.74-2.08) 
Day care service 
0.97 (0.87-1.08) 
0.90 (0.82-0.99) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Day rehabilitation 
1.08 (0.96-1.23) 
1.09 (1.00-1.19) 
Short stay 
0.87 (0.74-1.02) 
0.87 (0.81-0.94) </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Rental service of equipment 
1.04 (0.95-1.15) 
1.01 (0.94-1.08) </p>

<p>-2 log Likelihood 
1079.73 
1131.61 
Model Chi-square 
61.52 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>67.86 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>N 
873 
915 </p>

<p>* and **; *&lt; 0.05 and ** &lt; 0.01, respectively. Numbers in parentheses are 95% confidence intervals (CI). Con-
trol variables included gender, age and household in model 1 and model 2. </p>



<p>ond, generalization of our findings is limited because our 
data were derived from data for individuals who had applied 
for LTCI and individuals certified for LTCI among commu-
nity-dwelling frail persons in a single prefecture. Future 
studies are needed from another prefecture to confirm our 
results. Third, our analysis did not have informal services 
data conserning such thing as the private caregiver situation 
and support networks because our dataset did not contain 
these categories. More detailed data on the private services 
of subjects would be helpful to further clarify the changes 
in the levels of care needs in later life. Fourth, our study 
could not identify the effects of using home help service and 
home visit-bathing had a improved or sustained level of care 
needs, respectively. Therefore, in the future, the effect of 
use of a home helper service and home-visit bathing should 
be investigated to determine whether or not frail persons 
who are using home help services or visit bathing can sus-
tain their levels of care needs, respectively. Finally, in-home 
service programs targeting frail persons were not included 
in our study because the goal of our study was to determine 
whether or not individuals sustained/maintained their level 
of care needs, which kinds of home care services were used 
and whether the intervention consisted of less than four vis-
its per year and/or the duration of the intervention program 
was shorter than 12 months. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>The evidence in this investigation points to the impor-
tance of the use of home help or bathing services in main-
taining and improving the level of care needs in the lower 
level of care needs subgroup. Furthermore, in the higher 
level of care needs subgroup, the use of a short stay and day 
care service was significantly associated with a retrograded 
level of care needs. The political and practical problem fac-
ing governments is how to achieve financial savings and in-
crease efficiency without reducing the quality of care. By 
identifying potential ways to maintain or improve level of 
care needs of frail persons and the utilization of in-home 
services that are viable from a policy perspective, the pres-
ent survey should provide a better sense of which in-home 
services might result in more positive changes in levels of 
care needs for frail persons. This knowledge may suggest 
that in-home services contribute to the goal of the long-term 
care system of preventing deterioration but also that these 
services may help make things easier for family caregivers 
in the community and help policy-makers reform in-home 
services. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This study was partly supported by residents certified 
for long-term care insurance by the Izumo LTCI union. </p>







</text></tei>