<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4947724" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective: This study examined whether the presence </p>

<p>of peripheral sensory neuropathy or cardiac autonomic 
deficits is associated with postocclusive reactive 
hyperemia (reflective of microvascular function) in the 
diabetic foot. </p>

<p>Research design and methods: 99 participants </p>

<p>with type 2 diabetes were recruited into this cross-
sectional study. The presence of peripheral sensory 
neuropathy was determined with standard clinical tests 
and cardiac autonomic function was assessed with 
heart rate variation testing. Postocclusive reactive 
hyperemia was measured with laser Doppler in the 
hallux. Multiple hierarchical regression was performed 
to examine relationships between neuropathy and the 
peak perfusion following occlusion and the time to 
reach this peak. </p>

<p>Results: Peripheral sensory neuropathy predicted 22% </p>

<p>of the variance in time to peak following occlusion 
( p&lt;0.05), being associated with a slower time to peak 
but was not associated with the magnitude of the peak. 
Heart rate variation was not associated with the 
postocclusive reactive hyperemia response. </p>

<p>Conclusions: This study found an association between </p>

<p>the presence of peripheral sensory neuropathy in people 
with diabetes and altered microvascular reactivity in the 
lower limb. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>In the foot, autonomic neuropathy results 
in a loss of sympathetic activity in periph-
eral blood vessels causing vasodilation and 
increased arterial flow. 
4 However, the increase 
in blood flow bypasses the cutaneous </p>

<p>structures due to the opening of arterioven-
ous shunts, resulting in local ischemia. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Neuropathy has also been associated with 
reductions in microvascular reactivity that are 
likely to contribute to the development of 
ulceration, impaired healing, and difficulty 
fighting infection. </p>

<p>5 6 </p>

<p>Capacity for vasodilation can be assessed by 
measuring local skin blood flow while introdu-
cing stressors such as heat and iontophoresis 
of chemical substances. This approximates 
the capacity in that individual to mount blood 
flow and inflammatory responses to injury </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>and can also be indicative of early cardio-
vascular disease. 
7 While reduced vasodila-
tion in response to heat and iontophoresis of 
acetylcholine (ACh) has been observed in the 
presence of diabetic neuropathy, 
8-10 the effect 
of neuropathy on postocclusive reactive hyper-
emia (PORH) is less explored. 
PORH is the increase in blood flow that 
occurs in response to a period of arterial 
occlusion (figure 1). Impaired PORH has 
been associated with diabetes 
11 12 and with 
poor blood glucose control 
13 and notably 
has been shown to precede late diabetes 
complications. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>The underlying mechanisms for the 
response are not fully understood, but it is 
thought that prostaglandins 
14 and other meta-
bolic and endothelial dilators, 
15 as well as 
sensory nerves, 
16 play a role. As a relatively 
simple, reliable and non-invasive measure, the 
PORH response represents the sum of endo-
thelial 
dependent 
and 
independent </p>

<p>Key messages </p>

<p>▸ Peripheral sensory neuropathy in diabetes was 
associated with slower reactive hyperaemia 
response to occlusion. 
▸ Peripheral sensory neuropathy in diabetes was 
not associated with the peak reactive hyperaemia 
response to occlusion. 
▸ Cardiac autonomic neuropathy was not asso-
ciated with reactive hyperaemia. </p>

<p>BMJ Open Diabetes Research and Care 2016;4:e000235. doi:10.1136/bmjdrc-2016-000235 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>functions. 
15 If nerves are involved in the response, neur-
opathy may affect the PORH response. This study aimed 
to determine whether neuropathy in diabetes is asso-
ciated with altered microvascular reactivity in the foot. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS 
Participants and procedure 
A volunteer convenience sample was recruited from 
patients attending public and private podiatry clinics for 
general foot care in New South Wales, Australia, as well 
as those responding to poster and newspaper editorial 
advertising. Recruitment took place between March 
2014 and January 2015. All participants were adults with 
type 2 diabetes mellitus and were excluded if they were 
pregnant, took corticosteroids, or hormone replacement 
therapy, had osteoporosis, chronic renal failure, current 
bilateral foot ulceration, neuropathic osteoarthropathy, 
malignancy, endocrine disorders (other than diabetes) 
or a recent history of foot trauma. Ethics was obtained 
from the University of Newcastle Human Research 
Ethics Committee and written informed consent was 
obtained from all participants. Details of glycated hemo-
globin, the presence of retinopathy and other medical 
history, date of diabetes diagnosis, and medication use 
were obtained from medical history supplied by the par-
ticipant's general practitioner. 
Participants refrained from nicotine, caffeine, and 
exercise for 2 hours and lay supine for at least 10 min 
prior to testing while room temperature was controlled 
at 23-24°C. Tests were performed in the following order: 
monofilament detection, vibration perception, sharp/ 
blunt detection, and temperature detection followed by 
PORH and heart rate variation testing. All tests, as 
described below, were performed by a single podiatrist. </p>

<p>Sensory neuropathy assessment 
The presence of large-fiber sensory neuropathy was 
assessed with the four-point monofilament test and 
vibration perception threshold (VPT) 
17 and small-fiber 
sensory neuropathy was assessed with sharp/blunt per-
ception and temperature perception. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>A Bailey Instruments (Chorlton, Manchester, UK) 5.07 
monofilament was used for the four-site monofilament </p>

<p>test. The test was performed three times and an average 
of the three was taken. A score of three or less out 
of four sites correctly identified is indicative of large-
fiber sensory loss in that foot. 
17 VPT was assessed with 
a Horwell Neurothesiometer (Scientific Laboratory 
Supplies, Nottingham, UK) placed on the dorsal hallux. 
The amplitude of the instrument was gradually 
increased until the participant indicated they could feel 
vibration. This voltage was recorded as the VPT. The 
mean of three readings was taken. A value of over 25 V 
was considered abnormal. 
17 Where a participant failed 
both tests, they were classified as having sensory 
neuropathy. 
A Neurotip (Owen Mumford, Oxford, UK) installed 
in a calibrated Neuropen (Owen Mumford) was used to 
assess sharp/blunt perception. After demonstration of 
the instrument on the patient's hand, the sharp or blunt 
end of the instrument was placed randomly on the 
plantar surface of the hallux three times and the partici-
pant was asked to identify which end they perceived. 
This was performed three times with an average of the 
three being taken. A score of one or less out of three 
was considered abnormal. Temperature perception was 
assessed with a Tip-therm device (AXON GmbH, 
Dusseldorf, Germany). The cold or warm end of the 
instrument was placed randomly on the dorsum of the 
foot and the participant was asked to identify which end 
they perceived. A score of one or less out of three was 
considered abnormal. Where participants failed both 
these tests, they were also classified as having sensory 
neuropathy. </p>

<p>Postocclusive reactive hyperemia 
PORH was measured as described in Barwick et al. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Briefly, 
measurements 
were 
made 
with 
a 
moorVMS-LDF2 laser Doppler module and a VHP2 digit 
skin heater probe and needle probe (Moor Instruments, 
Axminster, UK). The laser probe was fixed to the 
plantar surface of the participant's hallux and heated to 
a thermoneutral 33°C. Where access to the right hallux 
was precluded by injury or amputation, the left hallux 
was used. A 2.5 cm pneumatic cuff (Moor Instruments) 
was placed proximal to the probe. The following </p>

<p>Figure 1 Typical PORH 
response measured in perfusion 
units-channel 1 and cuff 
pressure-channel 2. PORH, 
postocclusive reactive hyperemia. </p>



<p>BMJ Open Diabetes Research and Care 2016;4:e000235. doi:10.1136/bmjdrc-2016-000235 </p>

<p>Pathophysiology/complications </p>

<p>automated settings were used with the moorVMS-PRES 
pressure module (Moor Instruments): 3 min of baseline 
flux recording, inflation of the cuff to 220 mm Hg for 
3 min, cuff deflation at maximum speed, and postocclu-
sive flux recording for a further 4 min. All data were pro-
cessed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">moorVMS</rs> recording and analysis software 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.3.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Moor Instruments</rs>). 
The variables of peak expressed as a percentage of 
baseline (P%BL) and time to peak (TtP) were chosen 
due to their representation of the magnitude and tem-
poral representation of the response and their estab-
lished reliability. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Cardiac autonomic function assessment 
A Polar RS800cx heart monitor (Polar Electro Oy, 
Kempele, Finland) was used to assess heart rate variabil-
ity (HRV) as a measure of cardiac autonomic function. 
Participants completed a supine 5 min rest recording. 
The R-R interval tachogram was analyzed with <rs id="software-1" type="software">Kubios 
HRV</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">V.2.1</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Kuopio</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2012</rs>). Ectopic beats were 
removed using linear interpolation of previous and sub-
sequent beats. Time and frequency domain parameters 
were assessed. Time domain measured included the SD 
of the N-N interval (SDNN) and the root mean square 
of the R-R intervals (RMS-SD). Frequency domain mea-
sures were divided by spectral power analysis into high 
(0.15-0.40 Hz), low (0.04-0.15 Hz), and very low-
frequency (0.00-0.04 Hz) powers with total power calcu-
lated as the sum of all powers. 
20 Variables were left con-
tinuous due to a lack of cut-off values established to 
indicate pathology. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Statistical analysis was performed in <rs id="software-2" type="software">Statistical Packages 
for the Social Sciences</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">V.22</rs> for Windows (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SPSS</rs>, 
Chicago, USA). Reliability of sensory neuropathy diagno-
sis was assessed with duplicate tests on a subset of 31 par-
ticipants 7-14 days apart. κ Statistics were calculated and 
interpreted as per Landis and Koch 
21 ≥0.75=excellent 
agreement, 0.4-0.75=fair to good agreement, and 
&lt;0.40=poor agreement. Reliability of continuous mea-
sures (HRV) was assessed with duplicate tests on a subset 
of 29 participants 7-14 days apart. Intraclass correlation 
coefficients were calculated and interpreted in accord-
ance with Portney and Watkins: &gt;0.75=good, 0.50-
0.75=moderate, and &lt;0.50=poor. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Several hierarchical regression models were per-
formed to determine how much the presence of sensory 
neuropathy and HRV predicted the variance in PORH 
variables (P%BL and TtP). One model for each of the 
four neurological variables ( presence of sensory neur-
opathy, RMS-SD, SDNN, and total power) was assessed. 
In each of the models, demographic variables identified 
as confounds (diabetes duration, gender, and age) were 
entered in level 1 and the neurological variable as the 
independent predictor variable in level 2. Non-normally 
distributed data were log transformed. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Ninety-nine participants were recruited; participant 
characteristics are given in table 1. HRV data for three 
participants were unavailable leaving 96 participants for 
analyses of these data. TtP and P%BL were log trans-
formed due to their non-normal distribution. 
The intratester reliability of the diagnosis of sensory 
neuropathy was excellent (large-fiber tests: left foot 1.00; 
right foot 0.93, small-fiber tests: left foot 0.82; right foot 
0.92). The reliability of HRV was moderate for the time 
domains (SDNN 0.70; RMS-SD 0.66) and good for the 
frequency domain (total power 0.94). 
Results of the hierarchical regression are found in 
tables 2 and 3. The presence of sensory neuropathy pre-
dicted 22% of the variance in TtP ( p=0.03) with the 
presence of neuropathy indicating a longer latency to 
peak flux following release of occlusion. None of the 
HRV variables predicted the response. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS 
The relationship between diabetic neuropathy and 
microvascular reactivity is poorly understood. Such infor-
mation is useful in the early diagnosis and </p>

<p>Table 1 Participant characteristics (n=99) </p>

<p>Age (mean, SD) 
68.6 (9.56) 
Gender (male/female) 
64/35 
Toe pressure (mean, SD) 
99.39 (31.45) 
HbA1c (%) (mean, SD) 
7.26 (1.47) 
HcA1c (mmol/mol) (mean, SD) 
55.8 (16.15) 
BMI (mean, SD) 
34 (7.42) 
Retinopathy (past and current) 
(present/absent) </p>

<p>7/92 </p>

<p>Sensory neuropathy (present/absent) 
41/58 
Diabetes duration 
11.72 (9.73) </p>

<p>BMI, body mass index; HbA1c, glycated hemoglobin. </p>

<p>Table 2 Regression analyses of sensory neuropathy with 
PORH </p>

<p>R 
2 change β 
p Value </p>

<p>TtP 
Step 1* 
0.18 
&lt;0.01 
Step 2* 
0.22 
0.03 
Duration 
−0.05 
0.60 
Age 
0.05 
0.58 
Gender* 
−0.44 
0.00 
Sensory neuropathy* 
0.21 
0.03 
P%BL 
Step 1 
0.03 
0.12 
Step 2 
0.02 
0.68 
Duration 
−0.16 
0.12 
Age 
−0.03 
0.76 
Gender 
0.21 
0.06 
Sensory neuropathy 
0.04 
0.41 </p>

<p>*Significant at p&lt;0.05. 
P%BL, peak as a percentage of baseline; PORH, postocclusive 
reactive hyperemia; TtP, time to peak. </p>

<p>BMJ Open Diabetes Research and Care 2016;4:e000235. doi:10.1136/bmjdrc-2016-000235 </p>



<p>Pathophysiology/complications </p>

<p>management of diabetic foot complications. This study 
aimed to investigate relationships between clinically 
detectable peripheral sensory neuropathy, cardiac auto-
nomic deficits, and the PORH response in the periph-
ery. The presence of sensory neuropathy predicted 22% 
of the variance in the timing of the response but did not 
predict its magnitude. Heart rate variation did not 
predict temporal or magnitudinal aspects of the 
response. 
These findings are in keeping with previous studies 
that have shown other microvascular reactivity </p>

<p>parameters to be affected by the presence of neur-
opathy. The role of nerves in the blood flow response to 
heating and ACh iontophoresis and the effect of neur-
opathy on those responses are more established than in 
the PORH response. 
15 23 Numerous studies have demon-
strated that in the presence of diabetic neuropathy, 
there is a reduction in blood flow response to 
heating 
9 10 and iontophoresis of ACh. </p>

<p>8-10 </p>

<p>PORH is thought to be mediated by a mix of meta-
bolic dilators, endothelial dilators, myogenic relaxation, 
and sensory nerve activity. 
16 The work of Larkin and 
Williams 
24 and Lorenzo and Minson 
16 demonstrated the 
role of sensory nerves in PORH by showing a reduction 
in the response following anesthetization. This suggests 
that the presence of neuropathy should also reduce the 
response. In support of this, Yamamoto-Suganuma and 
Aso 
7 showed that a reduction in magnitude of the 
response is associated with slower sensory nerve conduc-
tion speed. 
The observed relationship, the current study, of neur-
opathy with the timing of the response but not the mag-
nitude is in contrast to these previous findings. 
7 The 
PORH response is characterized by a sharp initial peak 
followed by a delayed prolonged hyperemia. A previous 
study showed that a loss of neural responsiveness may be 
compensated by an increase in myogenic activity, </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>which may have resulted in maintenance of the peak in 
the current study. A large proportion of the participants 
in this study had clinically detectable neuropathy sug-
gesting a more advanced state of the condition. It is 
unknown if increases in myogenic activity remain in the 
presence of advanced neuropathy, and therefore, such a 
relationship cannot be assumed in this instance. 
Alternatively, the lack of association with the peak may 
be due to the inability of the clinical testing methods to 
detect early stages of neuropathy. 
The diagnosis of sensory neuropathy in the current 
study was based on unsophisticated clinical testing, 
which may explain the small size of the relationship 
found with TtP perfusion and the fact that there was no 
association with the peak itself. These measures were 
chosen to investigate whether identification of neur-
opathy with non-invasive clinical tests can give informa-
tion on the microvascular status of individuals. 
Another limitation of the current study was the out-
comes used to quantify the PORH response. Other 
parameters of the PORH response such as curve morph-
ology 
26 or an index of the area under the curve postoc-
clusion to preocclusion 
7 may also be useful indicators of 
disease states. Furthermore, the physiological signifi-
cance of a delayed PORH response as observed in the 
current study and whether it is indicative of pathology is 
unknown, limiting interpretation of the result. 
Since macrovascular disease is likely to affect micro-
vascular function, it may affect the PORH response. 
Those with peripheral vascular disease were not 
excluded from participation in the current study, which 
may have affected the results. However, resting toe </p>

<p>Table 3 Regression analyses of autonomic neuropathy 
variables with PORH </p>

<p>R 
2 change 
β 
p Value </p>

<p>TtP 
Step 1* 
0.18 
&lt;0.01 
Step 2 
0.02 
0.15 
Duration 
−0.05 
0.60 
Age* 
−0.41 
&lt;0.01 
Gender 
0.002 
0.98 
RMS-SD 
−0.14 
0.15 
P%BL 
Step 1 
0.06 
0.12 
Step 2 
0.006 
0.45 
Duration 
−0.16 
0.14 
Age* 
0.22 
0.04 
Gender 
−0.03 
0.75 
RMS-SD 
0.08 
0.45 
TtP 
Step 1* 
0.18 
&lt;0.01 
Step 2 
0.02 
0.13 
Duration 
−0.06 
0.56 
Age* 
−0.41 
&lt;0.01 
Gender 
0.01 
0.90 
SDNN 
−0.15 
0.13 
P%BL 
Step 1 
0.06 
0.12 
Step 2 
0.005 
0.48 
Duration 
−0.15 
0.15 
Age* 
0.22 
0.04 
Gender 
−0.04 
0.70 
SDNN 
0.07 
0.48 
TtP 
Step 1* 
0.18 
&lt;0.01 
Step 2 
0.001 
0.76 
Duration 
−0.04 
0.67 
Age* 
−0.41 
&lt;0.01 
Gender 
0.01 
0.89 
Total power 
−0.03 
0.76 
P%BL 
Step 1 
0.06 
0.12 
Step 2 
0.001 
0.83 
Duration 
−0.16 
0.13 
Age* 
0.22 
0.04 
Gender 
−0.04 
0.70 
Total power 
0.02 
0.83 </p>

<p>*Significant at p&lt;0.05. 
P%BL, peak as a percentage of baseline; PORH, postocclusive 
reactive hyperemia; RMS-SD, root mean square of the R-R 
interval; SDNN, SD of the N-N interval; TtP, time to peak. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>BMJ Open Diabetes Research and Care 2016;4:e000235. doi:10.1136/bmjdrc-2016-000235 </p>

<p>Pathophysiology/complications </p>

<p>pressures of participants were &lt;50 mm Hg in only 3 of 
the 99 participants, so severe peripheral arterial disease is 
not likely to have influenced the results. Evidence of 
other microvascular disease (retinopathy) was obtained 
from medical history and strict classification was not 
applied to diagnosis. Given the high prevalence of neur-
opathy in the study cohort, it is likely that the incidence 
of retinopathy was higher than that reported in this study. 
In addition to these concerns, other factors to consider 
in future research include the influence of edema and 
factors affecting blood viscosity on the PORH response. 
A major consideration in this work is that it is unclear 
to what extent the PORH response is reflective of the 
microvascular disease that causes neuropathy. Although 
diabetes-induced alterations in vascular and metabolic 
pathways are implicated in the pathogenesis of neur-
opathy, the disease is considered a microvascular compli-
cation of diabetes due to the predominance of the 
ischemic pathway. 
3 Endoneural blood vessels display cell 
hyperplasia and capillary basement membrane thicken-
ing 
27 causing hypoperfusion and ischemia to the nerves, 
predominating in the lower limbs. 
28 These changes also 
occur to the cutaneous microvasculature. 
28 Owing to the 
cross-sectional nature of the current study, the extent to 
which neuropathy caused the observed changes to PORH 
or microvascular disease affected the changes to PORH 
and neuropathy cannot be determined. 
The literature, however, is suggestive of a contribution 
of nerve function to reduced microvascular reactivity, 
independent of microvascular disease. Arora et al 
8 found 
that the reductions in the response to heating and ionto-
phoresis of ACh seen in those with neuropathy were not 
concurrent with changes to sodium nitroprusside (which 
does not stimulate nerve fibers). This was confirmed by 
Caselli et al. 
29 Furthermore, the temporal relationships 
between microvascular disease and diabetic neuropathy 
have recently been under dispute. 
30 There is likely to be 
a cycle present whereby microvascular disease contri-
butes to neuropathy, which contributes to further micro-
vascular dysfunction. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Microvascular and neural complications of diabetes 
are major contributors to lower limb pathology in dia-
betes. The impact of diabetic neuropathy on microvascu-
lar function is complex and under-researched. This 
study aimed to investigate whether clinically detectable 
peripheral sensory neuropathy or cardiac autonomic 
neuropathy was indicative of a reduction in the capabil-
ity for vasodilation that may be relevant in cases of ulcer-
ation and non-healing. The study found that the 
presence of peripheral sensory neuropathy in diabetes 
was associated with slower TtP dilatory response to ische-
mia. Future research should investigate whether this 
change in the PORH response is relevant for pathology 
as well as the causal link between neuropathy and micro-
vascular dysfunction. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors acknowledge the statistical support of the 
Hunter Medical Research Institute. A subset of the data presented in this </p>

<p>manuscript was published in an abstract in Supplement of the 58th volume of 
Diabetologia. </p>

<p>Contributors ALB contributed to the design of the study, acquisition of data, 
analysis of data, and writing of the manuscript. JWT contributed to the design 
of the study and writing of the manuscript. XJdJ contributed to the design of 
the study and writing of the manuscript. JRI contributed to the acquisition of 
data and writing of the manuscript. VHC oversaw the project and contributed 
to the design of the study, analysis of data, and writing of the manuscript. All 
authors agree on the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding This study was supported by departmental funding of the Faculty of 
Health and Medicine from the University of Newcastle (Australia), 10.13039/ 
501100001771. </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Patient consent Obtained. </p>

<p>Ethics approval University of Newcastle Human Research Ethics Committee. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Pathophysiology/complications </p>





<p>BMJ Open Diabetes Research and Care 2016;4:e000235. doi:10.1136/bmjdrc-2016-000235 </p>

<p>Pathophysiology/complications </p>

</text></tei>