<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4523486" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Adolescence is a transitional stage from childhood to 
adulthood characterized by dramatic physical, emotional, and 
intellectual developments as well as increased intake of various 
nutrients. As optimal development and growth have high 
nutritional requirements, a well-balanced and healthy diet is 
essential [1,2]. However, food consumption analyses have 
shown that intake of rice and fresh foods such as vegetables 
and fruits has dropped in Korean youths, whereas intake of 
processed and convenience foods as well as eating-out have 
increased [3]. A previous study showed that an irregular eating 
schedule combined with inappropriate food selection reduces 
intake of fiber and micronutrients such as iron, calcium, zinc, 
folic acid, and vitamins in youths [4-7]. In particular, the result 
of the 2007 (IV-1) KNHANES (Korea National Health and Nutrition 
Examination Survey) revealed that intake of vegetables 
comprised only 18% of the entire diet in young Koreans [5,8]. 
Vegetables and fruits contain micronutrients such as vitamins 
and minerals as well as phytochemicals, which help to relieve </p>

<p>stress and prevent cancer, obesity, and cardiovascular disease 
[1,5,9-12]. Moreover, the American Institute for Cancer Research 
endorses the '5 a Day for Better Health' program, which promotes 
eating five or more servings of vegetables and fruits daily (more 
than 80 g per serving for a total of 400 g) [13-15]. The nutritional 
section of the third national health promotion plan (2011-2020) 
administered by the Korean government proposes to increase 
the population that consumes more than 500 g of fruits and 
vegetables daily and emphasizes the importance of vegetable 
and fruit intake [16]. 
Studies have shown that consumption of vegetables and 
fruits is crucial in the growth of adolescents and can prevent 
stress related to the university entrance period or chronic 
diseases in adulthood [4,17,18]. Thus, this study examined 
intake of vegetables and fruits among Korean youths using data 
from the Korea Youth Risk Behavior Web-based Survey (2006,  2011), which represents the total youth population of Korea. 
Socio-demographic factors affecting vegetable and fruit intake 
were identified in order to develop basic guidelines on dietary 
education. </p>

<p>This study was supported by the grant from the Cooperative Research Program for Agriculture Science &amp; Technology Development (no. PJ01142701), Rural 
Development Administration, Republic of Korea. 
 § Corresponding Author: Yangsuk Kim, Tel. 82-63-238-3578, Fax. 82-63-238-3842, Email. kagatha@korea.kr </p>

<p>Received: April 1, 2014, Revised: February 14, 2015, Accepted: March 7, 2015 
* These two authors contributed equally to this study. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>



<p>Intake of vegetables and fruits of adolescents </p>

<p>Variables 
n 
% </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>n 
% 
n 
% 
n 
% 
n 
% 
n 
% 
n 
% </p>

<p>2006 (n = 71,404) 
3/day 
2/day 
1/day 
1 per 2-3 days 
1 per 4-5 days 
1 per 6-7 days 
seldom </p>

<p>Vegetables (excluding kimchi) 
11,992 
16.5 
12,572 
17.9 
17,288 
23.8 
13,355 
18.7 
8,619 
12.1 
5,097 
7.4 
2,481 
3.6 </p>

<p>Fruits (excluding fruit juice) 
2,150 
3.2 
5,920 
9.1 
13,433 
19.9 
22,115 
30.8 
12,385 
16.7 
9,307 
12.2 
6,094 
8.0 </p>

<p>2011 (n = 75,643) 
3/day 
2/day 
1/day 
5-6 per week 
3-4 per week 
1-2 per week 
seldom </p>

<p>Vegetables (excluding kimchi) 
13,658 
17.9 
10,969 
14.7 
9,435 
12.7 
10,024 
13.2 
17,488 
23.0 
11,414 
15.1 
2,655 
3.5 </p>

<p>Fruits (excluding fruit juice) 
2,323 
3.2 
4,218 
5.9 
8,121 
11.2 
7,875 
10.7 
22,203 
29.2 
24,028 
30.8 
6,875 
9.0 </p>

<p>1) Weighted percent </p>

<p>Table 1. Frequencies of vegetables and fruits consumption by survey year </p>

<p>SUBJECTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>This study analyzed raw data from the KYRBWS (Korea Youth 
Risk Behavior Web-based Survey) conducted by the Korea 
Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in 2006 and 2011. 
The total number of subjects used in the study was 147,047 
(2006: 71,404, 2011: 75,643). </p>

<p>Vegetable and fruit intake 
This study used frequency of vegetable consumption (F_veg, 
excluding kimchi) and frequency of fruit consumption (F_fruit, 
excluding fruit juice) as variables for analyzing consumption of 
vegetables and fruits. As the items for surveying food 
consumption frequency were different between the surveys in 
2006 and 2011, this study first examined the distribution chart 
(Table 1). The percentages of those who consumed vegetables 
three times a day were 16.5% in 2006 and 17.9% in 2011. The 
percentages of those who consumed fruits three times a day 
were also below 4% in both years. As this distribution was 
considered inadequate to analyze vegetable and fruit 
consumption based on three times a day, this study reclassified 
'1-3 times of food consumption per day' into 'Once or more 
a day (≥ 1/day)' as in the study of Heo et al. [19]. From the 
2006 survey, 'Once in 6-7 days', 'Once in 4-5 days', 'Once in 
2-3 days', and 'Not consumed at all in the past week' were 
re-coded into 'Less than once a day (&lt; 1/day).' From the 2011 
survey, '1-2 times a week', '3-4 times a week', '5-6 times a week', 
and 'no intake in the past week' were all re-coded into 'Less 
than once a day (&lt; 1/day)' variable [19]. </p>

<p>General characteristics, meal, health, and other variables 
Variables used as general characteristics of the subjects were 
gender, school level, residential area, subjective economic 
level/standard of living, and mother's education level. The 
residential area was divided into 'country (Gun area)', 'small and 
middle city', and 'large city'. The subjective economic 
level/standard of living was divided into 'low income', 'middle 
income', and 'high income' levels. Mother's education level was 
re-coded into 'middle school or lower', 'high school', and 
'college or higher'. The meal variable used was frequency of 
breakfast (Variable name: F_BR). From the 2006 survey results, 
'no breakfast in the past 7 days' was recoded into 'less than 
once a week (&lt; 1/week)', and the remaining variables, i.e. '1-2 
days a week', '3-5 days a week', and '6-7 days a week', were 
used from the survey. From the 2011 survey results, '0 day' was 
re-coded into 'less than once a week (&lt; 1/week)'; '1 day' and </p>

<p>'2 days' into '1-2 days a week'; '3 days', '4 days', and '5 days' 
into '3-5 days a week'; and '6 days' and '7 days' into '6-7 days 
a week'. Thus, recoding was performed the same as the 
categories used in the 2006 survey. Moreover, health-related 
and other variables included the presence or absence of 
nutrition education as well as subjective weight status. The 
presence or absence of nutrition education was divided into 
'yes' for those who received education and 'no' for those who 
received no education. For measurement of stress level, 
questions used in preparing the raw data were used (Variable 
name: M_str, 1. feel it very much, 2. feel a lot, 3. feel a little, 
4. do not feel much, 5. do not feel at all). Subjective weight 
status used for the analysis was divided into 'underweight', 
'average', 'overweight', and 'obesity'. </p>

<p>Data analysis 
Multistage stratified cluster sampling method was used for 
the KYRBWS (Korea Youth Risk Behavior Web-based Survey) in 
which clustering, stratification, weight, and finite population 
correction (FPC) were taken into account for the collected data. 
Thus, <rs id="software-0" type="software">SUDAAN</rs> (Survey Data Analysis) Ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">10.01</rs> was used so 
that clustering, stratification, and weight were applicable for the 
total adolescent population of Korea using the obtained sample. 
The general characteristics of the subjects as well as the 
frequencies of vegetable and fruit intake were examined using 
frequency analysis and expressed as frequency (n) and 
percentage (weighted %), after which chi-square (χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-test) was 
used to determine significance. The age was expressed as mean 
and standard error, after which t-test was used to determine 
significance. To identify factors affecting vegetable and fruit 
intake, logistic regression analysis was conducted separately on 
the data from 2006 and 2011 using the frequencies of vegetable 
and fruit intake as the dependent variables, which were recoded 
into 'more than once a day intake' as 1 point and 'less than 
once a day intake' as 0 points. The general characteristics of 
the subjects, their diet, and health-related factors were used 
as independent variables. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>General characteristics of the subjects 
The general characteristics of the subjects were gender, 
school level, average age, residential area, subjective economic 
level/standard of living, mother's education level, nutrition 
education, subjective weight status, and eating or not eating 
breakfast (Table 2). Although there was no significant difference 
in gender, there were slightly more boys (around 53%) </p>

<p>Yang Suk Kim et al. </p>



<p>Variables 
2006 (n = 71,404) 
2011 (n = 75,643) 
P-value </p>

<p>3) </p>

<p>n 
% </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>n 
% </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Boy 
37,204 
53.0 
37,873 
52.7 
0.9996 </p>

<p>Girl 
34,200 
47.0 
37,770 
47.3 </p>

<p>Age 
14.9 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>15.2 ± 0.1 
0.0415 </p>

<p>4) </p>

<p>School level </p>

<p>Middle school students 
37,420 
53.9 
38,474 
49.5 
0.4939 </p>

<p>High school students 
33,984 
46.1 
37,169 
50.5 </p>

<p>Residential area </p>

<p>Country (gun area) 
10,695 
8.0 
9,856 
6.2 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Middle and small city 
26,622 
44.8 
31,095 
48.8 </p>

<p>Large city 
34,087 
47.2 
34,692 
45.0 </p>

<p>Subjective household income level </p>

<p>High 
20,942 
31.1 
22,431 
30.7 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Middle 
33,870 
47.0 
35,762 
46.8 </p>

<p>Low 
16,592 
21.9 
17,450 
22.5 </p>

<p>Mother's education level </p>

<p>Middle school or lower 
7,949 
10.8 
3,790 
5.3 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>High school 
36,973 
59.1 
34,594 
53.4 </p>

<p>College or higher 
16,202 
30.0 
24,745 
41.3 </p>

<p>Nutrition education </p>

<p>Yes 
38,838 
54.4 
47,761 
63.5 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>No 
32,566 
45.6 
27,882 
36.5 </p>

<p>Subjective weight status </p>

<p>Underweight 
20,945 
29.7 
21,382 
29.0 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Normal 
31,936 
44.3 
25,436 
33.5 </p>

<p>Overweight 
14,193 
20.1 
24,642 
32.3 </p>

<p>Obesity 
4,330 
6.0 
4,183 
5.3 </p>

<p>Stress level </p>

<p>Feel it very much 
10,041 
14.1 
9,091 
11.7 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Feel a lot 
22,934 
32.4 
23,026 
30.3 </p>

<p>Feel a little 
27,742 
38.7 
31,482 
41.9 </p>

<p>Do not feel much 
9,107 
12.6 
10,436 
14.0 </p>

<p>Do not feel at all 
1,579 
2.3 
1,608 
2.2 </p>

<p>Breakfast frequency </p>

<p>&lt; 1/week 
9,495 
13.4 
9,349 
12.4 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>1-2 per week 
9,657 
13.3 
9,130 
12.0 </p>

<p>3-5 per week 
13,873 
19.4 
17,082 
22.4 </p>

<p>6-7 per week 
38,378 
53.9 
40,082 
53.2 </p>

<p>1) Weighted percent 
2) Mean ± SE </p>

<p>3) P-value by chi-square test 
4) P-value by t-test </p>

<p>Table 2. General characteristics of study subjects (n = 147,047) </p>

<p>represented in the data from both 2006 and 2011. Regarding 
school level, the most numerous group was middle school 
students, which constituted greater than 50% of the 2006 data. 
The average age in 2006 was 14.9, whereas that in 2011 was 
15.2. On the other hand, more high school students (50.5%) 
than middle school students (49.5%) were observed in the 2011 
data. Regarding residential area, the survey participants from 
the Gun (country) area constituted less than 10% in both survey 
years. The percentages of participants from small and middle 
cities were lower than that from large cities in 2006 but higher </p>

<p>in 2011 (P &lt; 0.0001). Regarding subjective economic level/ 
standard of living, high income level was around 30% in both 
years, middle income level was around 47%, and low income 
level was between 20-25% (P &lt; 0.0001). Regarding mother's 
education level, high school was the most common (more than 
50%) in both years (P &lt; 0.0001). Regarding the presence or 
absence of nutrition education, the percentages of participants 
who received education were higher than 50% in both 2006 
and 2011, and this percentage was approximately 10% higher 
in 2011 (63.5%) than in 2006 (54.4%). In terms of stress level, 
both in 2006 and 2011, groups that identified their stress levels 
as 'feel it a little, (38.7% in 2006 and 41.9% in 2011) and 'feel 
it a lot' (32.4% in 2006 and 30.3% in 2011) constituted the 
highest proportions at above 30%. Regarding subjective weight 
status, the percentage of the normal group was 44.3% in 2006 
but dropped by about 11% to 33.5% in 2011, whereas that of 
the overweight group was 20.1% in 2006 and then increased 
by approximately 12% to 32.3% in 2011 (P &lt; 0.0001). Regarding 
consumption frequency of breakfast, about 53% of respondents 
answered that they ate breakfast six to seven times a week 
in both study years while the rate of respondents that answered 
eating breakfast three to five times a week increased 3% from 
19.4% in 2006 to 22.4% in 2011. </p>

<p>Frequencies of vegetable and fruit intake based on general 
characteristics, diet, and health-related factors </p>

<p>Vegetable intake frequency 
The analysis of vegetable intake frequency based on general 
characteristics, diet, and health-related factors are shown in 
Table 3. Overall, the frequency of eating vegetable side dishes 
'more than once a day' dropped significantly from 58.2% in 
2006 to 45.2% in 2011 (P &lt; 0.0001). Significance determined 
based on specific factors, including gender, school level, 
residential area, subjective economic level/standard of living, 
mother's education level, presence or absence of nutrition 
education, stress level, subjective weight status, and frequency 
of breakfast intake, indicated that the frequency of vegetable 
intake 'more than once a day' was reduced significantly in 2011 
compared to 2006 (P &lt; 0.0001). </p>

<p>Fruit intake frequency 
Table 4 shows the analysis of fruit intake frequency based 
on general characteristics, diet, and health-related factors. 
Overall, intake of fruits 'less than once a day' was higher than 
65% in both years, whereas 'more than once a day' intake was 
32.3% in 2006 but dropped significantly to 20.3% in 2011 (P 
&lt; 0.0001). Regarding specific factors, including gender, school 
level, residential area, subjective economic level/standard of 
living, mother's education level, presence or absence of 
nutrition education, stress level, subjective weight status, and 
frequency of breakfast intake, the frequency of fruit intake 
'more than once a day' was significantly lower in 2011 
compared to 2006 (P &lt; 0.0001). </p>

<p>Vegetable and fruit intake-related factors in youths 
To examine factors related to vegetable and fruit intake in 
youths, logistic regression analysis was conducted on intake of </p>



<p>Intake of vegetables and fruits of adolescents </p>

<p>Variables 
2006 
2011 
P-value </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>n 
% </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>n 
% </p>

<p>Total </p>

<p>≥ 1/day </p>

<p>3) </p>

<p>41,852 58.2 34,062 45.2 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
29,552 41.8 41,581 54.8 </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Boy 
≥ 1/day 
22,564 60.3 17,110 45.5 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
14,640 39.7 20,763 54.5 </p>

<p>Girl 
≥ 1/day 
19,288 55.9 16,952 44.9 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
14,912 44.1 20,818 55.1 </p>

<p>School level </p>

<p>Middle school 
students </p>

<p>≥ 1/day 
22,104 58.6 17,170 44.8 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
15,316 41.4 21,304 55.2 </p>

<p>High school 
students </p>

<p>≥ 1/day 
19,748 57.7 16,892 45.6 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
14,236 42.3 20,277 54.4 </p>

<p>Residential area </p>

<p>Country (gun area) ≥ 1/day 
6,432 
60.4 
4,408 
44.6 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
4,263 
39.6 
5,448 
55.4 </p>

<p>Middle and small city ≥ 1/day 
15,762 58.8 13,915 45.0 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
10,860 41.2 17,180 55.0 </p>

<p>Large city 
≥ 1/day 
19,658 57.3 15,739 45.5 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
14,429 42.7 18,953 54.5 </p>

<p>Subjective household income level </p>

<p>High 
≥ 1/day 
12,954 61.6 11,054 49.4 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
7,988 
38.4 11,377 50.6 </p>

<p>Middle 
≥ 1/day 
19,663 57.6 15,583 43.8 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
14,207 42.4 20,179 56.2 </p>

<p>Low 
≥ 1/day 
9,235 
54.7 
7,425 
42.4 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
7,357 
45.3 10,025 57.6 </p>

<p>Mother's education level </p>

<p>Middle shool or lower ≥ 1/day 
4,601 
56.8 
1,652 
42.6 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
3,348 
43.2 
2,138 
57.4 </p>

<p>High school 
≥ 1/day 
21,669 58.3 15,426 44.6 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
15,304 41.7 19,168 55.4 </p>

<p>College or higher 
≥ 1/day 
9,924 
60.9 12,134 49.2 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
6,278 
39.1 12,611 50.8 </p>

<p>Nutrition education </p>

<p>Yes 
≥ 1/day 
21,934 56.0 20,879 43.9 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
16,904 44.0 26,882 56.1 </p>

<p>No 
≥ 1/day 
19,918 60.9 13,183 47.5 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
12,648 39.1 14,699 52.5 </p>

<p>Subjective weight status </p>

<p>Under weight 
≥ 1/day 
11,859 56.0 
9,203 
43.2 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
9,086 
44.0 12,179 56.8 </p>

<p>Normal 
≥ 1/day 
18,812 58.7 11,587 45.8 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
13,124 41.3 13,849 54.2 </p>

<p>Over weight 
≥ 1/day 
8,532 
59.6 11,330 46.3 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
5,661 
40.4 13,312 53.7 </p>

<p>Obesity 
≥ 1/day 
2,649 
61.2 
1,942 
45.8 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
1,681 
38.8 
2,241 
54.2 </p>

<p>Stress level </p>

<p>Feel it very much 
≥ 1/day 
5,497 
54.1 
3,964 
43.8 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
4,544 
45.9 
5,127 
56.2 </p>

<p>Table 3. Consumption frequency of vegetables according to survey year by each 
variable 
Variables 
2006 
2011 
P-value </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>n 
% </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>n 
% </p>

<p>Feel a lot 
≥ 1/day 
13,108 56.6 10,050 43.6 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
9,826 
43.4 12,976 56.4 </p>

<p>Feel a little 
≥ 1/day 
16,496 59.1 14,032 44.9 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
11,246 40.9 17,450 55.1 </p>

<p>Do not feel much 
≥ 1/day 
5,746 
63.5 
5,142 
49.4 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
3,361 
36.5 
5,294 
50.6 </p>

<p>Do not feel at all 
≥ 1/day 
1,004 
62.2 
874 
55.0 0.0018 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
575 
37.8 
734 
45.0 </p>

<p>Breakfast frequency (per week) </p>

<p>&lt; 1/week 
≥ 1/day 
4,820 
49.9 
3,850 
41.2 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
4,675 
50.1 
5,499 
58.8 </p>

<p>1-2 per week 
≥ 1/day 
5,134 
52.2 
3,356 
36.3 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
4,523 
47.8 
5,774 
63.7 </p>

<p>3-5 per week 
≥ 1/day 
7,657 
54.8 
6,741 
40.0 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
6,216 
45.2 10,341 60.0 </p>

<p>6-7 per week 
≥ 1/day 
24,240 63.0 20,115 50.4 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
14,138 37.0 19,967 49.6 </p>

<p>1) Weighted percent </p>

<p>2) P-value by chi-square test </p>

<p>3) Consumption frequency of vegetables </p>

<p>Table 3. continued </p>

<p>Variables 
2006 
2011 
P-value </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>n 
% </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>n 
% </p>

<p>Total </p>

<p>≥ 1/day </p>

<p>3) </p>

<p>21,503 
32.3 14,662 
20.3 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
49,901 
67.7 60,981 
79.7 </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Boy 
≥ 1/day 
10,813 
31.0 
7,014 
19.2 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
26,391 
69.0 30,856 
80.8 </p>

<p>Girl 
≥ 1/day 
10,690 
33.8 
7,645 
21.5 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
23,510 
66.2 30,125 
78.5 </p>

<p>School level </p>

<p>Middle school 
students </p>

<p>≥ 1/day 
13,298 
37.4 
8,713 
23.7 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
24,122 
62.6 29,761 
76.3 </p>

<p>High school 
students </p>

<p>≥ 1/day 
8,205 
26.3 
5,949 
17.0 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
25,779 
73.7 31,220 
83.0 </p>

<p>Residential area </p>

<p>Country (gun area) ≥ 1/day 
2,580 
25.4 
1,405 
14.2 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
8,115 
74.6 
8,451 
85.8 </p>

<p>Middle and small city ≥ 1/day 
8,084 
32.7 
5,975 
20.3 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
18,538 
67.3 25,120 
79.7 </p>

<p>Large city 
≥ 1/day 
10,839 
33.1 
7,282 
21.2 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
23,248 
66.9 27,410 
78.8 </p>

<p>Subjective household income level </p>

<p>High 
≥ 1/day 
8,581 
43.2 
6,189 
28.6 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
12,361 
56.8 16,242 
71.4 </p>

<p>Middle 
≥ 1/day 
9,735 
30.6 
6,241 
18.3 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
24,135 
69.4 29,521 
81.7 </p>

<p>Low 
≥ 1/day 
3,187 
20.4 
2,232 
13.1 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
13,405 
79.6 15,218 
86.9 </p>

<p>Table 4. Consumption frequency of fruits according to survey year by each 
variable </p>

<p>Yang Suk Kim et al. </p>



<p>Variables 
2006 
2011 
P-value </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>n 
% </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>n 
% </p>

<p>Mother's education level </p>

<p>Middle school or less ≥ 1/day 
1,720 
22.7 
483 
13.4 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
6,229 
77.3 
3,307 
86.6 </p>

<p>High school 
≥ 1/day 
10,547 29.7 
5,794 
17.4 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
26,426 70.3 28,800 
82.6 </p>

<p>College or higher 
≥ 1/day 
6,564 
43.3 
6,527 
27.2 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
9,638 
56.7 18,218 
72.8 </p>

<p>Nutrition education </p>

<p>Yes 
≥ 1/day 
10,699 29.7 
8,677 
19.1 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
28,139 70.3 39,084 
80.9 </p>

<p>No 
≥ 1/day 
10,804 35.4 
5,985 
22.4 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
21,762 64.6 21,897 
77.6 </p>

<p>Subjective weight status </p>

<p>Under weight 
≥ 1/day 
6,486 
32.5 
4,498 
22.1 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
14,459 67.5 16,884 
77.9 </p>

<p>Normal 
≥ 1/day 
9,946 
33.7 
5,112 
21.1 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
21,990 66.3 20,324 
78.9 </p>

<p>Over weight 
≥ 1/day 
3,919 
29.9 
4,418 
18.7 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
10,274 70.1 20,224 
81.3 </p>

<p>Obesity 
≥ 1/day 
1,152 
29.2 
634 
15.5 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
3,178 
70.8 
3,549 
84.5 </p>

<p>Stress level </p>

<p>Feel it very much 
≥ 1/day 
2,732 
28.5 
1,685 
19.4 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
7,309 
71.5 
7,406 
80.6 </p>

<p>Feel a lot 
≥ 1/day 
6,403 
30.5 
4,083 
18.8 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
16,531 69.5 18,943 
81.2 </p>

<p>Feel a little 
≥ 1/day 
8,509 
32.9 
6,059 
20.1 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
19,233 67.1 25,423 
79.9 </p>

<p>Do not feel much ≥ 1/day 
3,168 
36.6 
2,310 
22.9 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
5,939 
63.4 
8,126 
77.1 </p>

<p>Do not feel at all 
≥ 1/day 
690 
47.0 
525 
33.6 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
889 
53.0 
1,083 
66.4 </p>

<p>Breakfast (per week) </p>

<p>&lt; 1/week 
≥ 1/day 
2,086 
23.7 
1,382 
15.0 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
7,409 
76.3 
7,967 
85.0 </p>

<p>1-2 per week 
≥ 1/day 
2,533 
27.8 
1,251 
14.1 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
7,124 
72.2 
7,879 
85.9 </p>

<p>3-5 per week 
≥ 1/day 
3,693 
28.3 
2,780 
17.0 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
10,180 71.7 14,302 
83.0 </p>

<p>6-7 per week 
≥ 1/day 
13,191 37.0 
9,249 
24.3 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>&lt; 1/day 
25,187 63.0 30,833 
75.7 </p>

<p>1) Weighted percent </p>

<p>2) P-value by chi-square test </p>

<p>3) Consumption frequencies of fruits </p>

<p>Table 4. continued </p>

<p>Variables 
2006 
2011 </p>

<p>Gender (ref. = Boy) </p>

<p>Girl 
0.823 (0.787-0.860)*** </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>0.968 (0.932-1.005) </p>

<p>Age 
1.013 (0.988-1.038) 
1.026 (1.015-1.038)*** </p>

<p>School level (ref. = Middle school students) </p>

<p>High school students 
1.057 (1.006-1.112)* 
1.078 (1.034-1.124)*** </p>

<p>Residential area (ref. = Country (gun area)) </p>

<p>Middle and small city 
0.897 (0.833-0.967)** 
0.958 (0.891-1.030) </p>

<p>Large city 
0.851 (0.792-0.914)*** 
0.964 (0.898-1.035) </p>

<p>Subjective household income (ref. = High) </p>

<p>Middle 
0.882 (0.838-0.927)*** 
0.851 (0.816-0.888)*** </p>

<p>Low 
0.819 (0.767-0.875)*** 
0.835 (0.795-0.878)*** </p>

<p>Mother's education level (ref. = Middle school or lower) </p>

<p>High School 
1.021 (0.950-1.097) 
1.065 (0.982-1.155) </p>

<p>College or higher 
1.067 (0.983-1.159) 
1.191 (1.091-1.300)*** </p>

<p>Nutrition education (ref. = Yes) </p>

<p>No 
1.212 (1.160-1.267)*** 
1.154 (1.107-1.203)*** </p>

<p>Subjective weight status (ref. = Normal) </p>

<p>Underweight 
0.894 (0.850-0.940)*** 
0.899 (0.863-0.936)*** </p>

<p>Over weight 
1.037 (0.986-1.091) 
1.018 (0.980-1.057) </p>

<p>Obesity 
1.109 (1.017-1.208)* 
0.998 (0.930-1.071) </p>

<p>Stress level (ref. = Feel it very much) </p>

<p>Feel a lot 
1.098 (1.035-1.165)*** 
0.998 (0.945-1.054) </p>

<p>Feel a little 
1.217 (1.146-1.293)*** 
1.056 (1.002-1.114)*** </p>

<p>Do not feel much 
1.468 (1.361-1.584)*** 
1.280 (1.203-1.363)*** </p>

<p>Do not feel at all 
1.400 (1.186-1.653)*** 
1.599 (1.416-1.807)*** </p>

<p>Breakfast frequency (per week) (ref. =&lt; 1/week) </p>

<p>1-2 per week 
1.039 (0.953-1.133) 
0.823 (0.766-0.883)*** </p>

<p>3-5 per week 
1.194 (1.088-1.310)*** 
0.931 (0.876-0.990)* </p>

<p>6-7 per week 
1.617 (1.501-1.742)*** 
1.401 (1.326-1.481)*** </p>

<p>* P &lt; 0.05, ** P &lt; 0.01, *** P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>1) Odds ratio (95% Confidence Interval) </p>

<p>Table 5. Factors related to vegetable consumption in adolescents </p>

<p>vegetables and fruits 'more than once a day' as dependent 
variables along with general characteristics, diet, and health-
related factors as independent variables according to each year. </p>

<p>Vegetable intake-related factors 
Table 5 shows the analysis of vegetable intake-related factors 
in youths. From the 2006 survey, all factors related to vegetable 
intake 'more than once a day', excluding mother's education </p>

<p>level, showed significant effects. The frequency of vegetable 
intake 'more than once a day' was 17.7% (OR = 0.823) lower 
in female youths than male youths, whereas it was about 1.1 
times (OR = 1.057) higher in high school students than middle 
school students. Regarding residential area, frequencies of 
vegetable intake 'more than once a day' were lower in students 
residing in small and middle city (10.3%, OR = 0.897) as well 
as large city (14.9%, OR = 0.851) compared to those living in 
Gun (country) areas. Regarding subjective economic level/ 
standard of living, frequencies of vegetable intake 'more than 
once a day' were 11.8% lower at the middle income level (OR 
= 0.882) and 18.1% lower at the low income level (OR = 0.819) 
compared to the high income level. Regarding vegetable intake 
based on the presence or absence of nutrition education, 
frequency of vegetable intake 'more than once a day' was 1.2 
times (OR = 1.212) higher in participants who received no 
education compared to those who received education. In terms 
of stress level, the group receiving no stress showed a higher 
frequency of vegetable intake 'more than once a day' compared 
to the group under severe stress. Correlation between subjective 
weight status and vegetable intake showed that the frequency 
of vegetable intake 'more than once a day' was 10.6% (OR = </p>



<p>Intake of vegetables and fruits of adolescents </p>

<p>Variables 
2006 
2011 </p>

<p>Gender (ref. = Boy) </p>

<p>Girl 
1.197 (1.131-1.267)*** </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>1.227 (1.167-1.291)*** </p>

<p>Age 
0.871 (0.854-0.889)*** 
0.903 (0.886-0.920)*** </p>

<p>School level (ref. = Middle school students) </p>

<p>High school students 0.705 (0.661-0.753)*** 
0.742 (0.697-0.790)*** </p>

<p>Residential area (ref. = Country (gun area)) </p>

<p>Middle and small city 1.302 (1.190-1.423)*** 
1.382 (1.249-1.529)*** </p>

<p>Large city 
1.342 (1.232-1.462)*** 
1.402 (1.269-1.548)*** </p>

<p>Subjective household income level (ref. = High) </p>

<p>Middle 
0.651 (0.618-0.686)*** 
0.639 (0.607-0.673)*** </p>

<p>Low 
0.424 (0.393-0.457)*** 
0.492 (0.460-0.525)*** </p>

<p>Mother's education level (ref. = Middle school or lower) </p>

<p>High School 
1.168 (1.075-1.268)*** 
1.168 (1.032-1.321)* </p>

<p>College or higher 
1.740 (1.574-1.923)*** 
1.691 (1.496-1.911)*** </p>

<p>Nutrition education (ref. = Yes) </p>

<p>No 
1.072 (1.024-1.124)** 
1.073 (1.023-1.126)** </p>

<p>Subjective weight status (ref. = Normal) </p>

<p>Underweight 
0.947 (0.901-0.995)* 
1.061 (1.009-1.117)* </p>

<p>Over weight 
0.840 (0.791-0.892)*** 
0.865 (0.826-0.906)*** </p>

<p>Obesity 
0.811 (0.728-0.903)*** 
0.688 (0.622-0.762)*** </p>

<p>Stress level (ref. = Feel it very much) </p>

<p>Feel a lot 
1.090 (1.011-1.175)* 
0.945 (0.884-1.010) </p>

<p>Feel a little 
1.180 (1.101-1.265)*** 
1.016 (0.948-1.089) </p>

<p>Do not feel much 
1.328 (1.229-1.436)*** 
1.164 (1.077-1.258)*** </p>

<p>Do not feel at all 
2,031 (1.723-2.394)*** 
1.939 (1.690-2.225)*** </p>

<p>Breakfast frequency (per week) (ref. =&lt; 1/week) </p>

<p>1-2 per week 
1.149 (1.023-1.291)* 
0.941 (0.852-1.039) </p>

<p>3-5 per week 
1.150 (1.028-1.287)* 
1.079 (0.992-1.174) </p>

<p>6-7 per week 
1.620 (1.475-1.781)*** 
1.565 (1.449-1.690)*** </p>

<p>* P &lt; 0.05, ** P &lt; 0.01, *** P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>1) Odds ratio (95% Confidence Interval) </p>

<p>Table 6. Factors related to frequency of fruit consumption in adolescents </p>

<p>0.894) lower in the underweight awareness group and 1.1 times 
(OR = 1.109) higher in the obese awareness group compared 
to the normal awareness group. Finally, as the frequency of 
eating breakfast increased, the frequency of vegetable intake 
'more than once a day' also increased compared to eating 
breakfast 'less than once a week'. The frequency of vegetable 
intake 'more than once a day' was 1.2 times (OR = 1.194) higher 
than those who ate breakfast '3-5 times a week' and 1.6 times 
(OR = 1.617) higher than those who ate breakfast '6-7 times a 
week'. 
Analysis of factors related to vegetable intake 'more than 
once a day' from the 2011 survey showed that all factors were 
significantly correlated, excluding gender and residential area. As 
age increased by 1 year, intake of vegetables 'more than once 
a day' also increased as much as 1.03 times (OR = 1.026). The 
frequency of vegetable intake 'more than once a day' was 1.1 
times (OR = 1.078) higher in high school students compared to 
middle school students. Regarding subjective economic 
level/standard of living, frequency of vegetable intake 'more 
than once a day' was 14.9% (OR = 0.851) lower at the middle 
income level and 16.5% (OR = 0.835) lower at the low income 
level compared to the high income level. Based on mother's 
education level, frequency of vegetable intake 'more than once 
a day' was 1.2 times (OR = 1.191) higher in the college group 
compared to the middle school or lower education group. The 
frequency of vegetable intake 'more than once a day' was 1.2 
times (OR = 1.151) higher in the group that received no 
education compared to those who received education. In terms 
of stress level, as in 2006, the group receiving no stress showed 
a higher frequency of vegetable intake 'more than once a day' 
compared to the group under severe stress. Regarding 
subjective weight status, the frequency of vegetable intake 
'more than once a day' was 10.1% (OR = 0.899) lower in the 
underweight awareness group compared to the normal aware-
ness group. Regarding frequency of eating breakfast, unlike the 
results of the 2006 survey, the frequency of vegetable intake 
'more than once a day' was 17.7% (OR = 0.823) lower in the 
'1-2 times a week' group and 6.9% (OR = 0.931) lower in the 
'3-5 times a week' group compared to the 'less than once a 
week' group. On the other hand, the frequency of vegetable 
intake 'more than once a day' was 1.4 times (OR = 1.401) higher 
in the '6-7 times a week' group compared to the 'less than 
one time' group. </p>

<p>Fruit intake-related factors 
Table 6 shows the analysis of fruit intake-related factors in 
youths. From the 2006 survey, the frequency of fruit intake 
'more than once a day' showed a significant correlation with 
all factors. Unlike vegetable intake, the frequency of fruit intake 
'more than once a day' was 1.2 times (OR = 1.197) higher in 
girls than in boys as well as 29.5% (OR = 0.705) lower in high 
school students than in middle school students. As age number 
increased by 1 year, fruit intake 'more than once a day' 
decreased by 12.9%. Frequencies of fruit intake 'more than once 
a day' were about 1.3 times higher in small and middle cities 
(OR = 1.302) as well as large cities (OR = 1.342) compared to 
those in the Gun (country) area. Regarding differences accor-
ding to subjective economic level/standard of living, the </p>

<p>frequency of fruit intake 'more than once a day' was 34.9% (OR 
= 0.651) lower in youths at the middle income level and 57.6% 
(OR = 0.424) lower in those at the low income level compared 
to those at the high income level. Regarding the mother's 
education level, the frequency of fruit intake 'more than once 
a day' was 1.2 times (OR = 1.168) higher in youths whose 
mothers had a high school education as well as 1.7 times (OR 
= 1.740) higher in youths whose mothers had a college or 
higher compared to those whose mothers had a middle school 
or lower. The frequency of fruit intake 'more than once a day' 
in youths was 1.1 times (OR = 1.072) higher in those who 
received no education compared to those who received 
nutrition education. In terms of stress level, the group under 
severe stress showed a higher frequency of fruit intake 'more 
than once a day' compared to the group under no stress. 
Regarding subjective weight status, the frequency of fruit intake 
'more than once a day' was 5.3% (OR = 0.947) lower in the 
underweight awareness group, 16% (OR = 0.840) lower in the 
overweight awareness group, and 18.9% (OR = 0.811) lower in 
the obese awareness group compared to youths in the normal 
awareness group. Regarding frequency of eating breakfast, the 
frequency of fruit intake 'more than once a day' was 1.1 times </p>

<p>Yang Suk Kim et al. </p>



<p>(OR = 1.149) higher in the group who ate breakfast '1-2 times 
a week', 1.2 times (OR = 1.150) higher in the group who ate 
breakfast '3-5 times a week', and 1.6 times (OR = 1.620) higher 
in the group who ate breakfast '6-7 times a week' compared 
to the group who ate breakfast 'less than once a week'. 
From the 2011 survey, analysis of factors related to fruit intake 
'more than once a day' in youths showed similar results as the 
2006 survey. All factors were significantly correlated. As age 
increased by 1 year, fruit intake 'more than once a day' 
decreased by 9.7%. The frequency of fruit intake 'more than 
once a day' was 1.2 times (OR = 1.227) higher in female students 
compared to male students as well as 25.8% (OR = 0.742) lower 
in high school students compared to middle school students. 
According to subjective economic level/standard of living, the 
frequency of fruit intake 'more than once a day' in youths was 
36.1% (OR = 0.639) lower in those at the middle income level 
and 51.8% (OR = 0.492) lower in those at the low income level 
compared to those at the high income level. According to 
mother's education level, the frequency of fruit intake 'more 
than once a day' was 1.2 times (OR = 1.168) higher in those 
whose mothers had a high school education and 1.7 times (OR 
= 1.691) higher in those whose mothers had a college 
education or higher compared to those whose mothers had 
a middle school education or lower. The frequency of fruit 
intake 'more than once a day' in youths was 1.1 times (OR = 
1.073) higher in the group that did not receive nutrition 
education compared to the group that received nutrition 
education. In terms of stress level, as in 2006, the group under 
no stress showed a higher frequency of fruit intake 'more than 
once a day' compared to the group under severe stress. Accor-
ding to subjective weight status, the frequency of fruit intake 
'more than once a day' was 1.1 times (OR = 1.061) higher in 
the underweight awareness group, 13.5% (OR = 0.865) lower in 
the overweight awareness group, and 31.2% (OR = 0.688) lower 
in the obese awareness group compared to the normal 
awareness group. Finally, frequency of fruit intake 'more than 
once a day' according to frequency of eating breakfast was 1.6 
times (OR = 1.565) higher in those who ate breakfast '6-7 times 
a week' compared to those who ate breakfast 'less than once 
a week'. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study compared and analyzed consumption frequencies 
of vegetables and fruits, general characteristics, diet, and 
health-related factors in 147,047 youths who participated in the 
KYRBWS (Korea Youth Risk Behavior Web-based Survey) in 2006 
and 2011. When frequencies of vegetable and fruit intake 
according to general characteristics, diet, and health-related 
factors were analyzed, all survey participants, gender, school 
level, residential area, subjective economic level/standard of 
living, mother's education level, presence or absence of 
nutrition education, subjective weight status, and frequency of 
breakfast intake, the frequencies were significantly reduced in 
2011 compared to 2006. Reductions in consumption 
frequencies of vegetables and fruits corroborate the results of 
a previous study by Lee et al. [3] on food consumption in Korean 
youths, which found that consumption of fresh foods, including </p>

<p>vegetables, fish and seafood, and fruits, decreased while 
consumption of processed and convenience foods as well as 
eating out increased in Korean youths. Furthermore, according 
to the 2007 KNHANES (Korea National Health and Nutrition 
Examination Survey), which was conducted within a similar time 
frame as the above study, the average daily vegetable intake 
of the 12-18 year age group was 222.7 g but decreased by 
14.7 g over the past 4 years [20]. According to the 2011 
KNHANES, the average daily vegetable intake was 207.4 g in 
the 10-18 year age group [21]. Regarding fruit intake, the 2007 
KNHANES data showed that the average fruit daily intake was 
138.4 g but decreased by approximately 4 g to 135.5 g in 2011 
[8,20,21]. Based on results of previous studies, the reduced 
intake of vegetables and fruits did not directly affect reduction 
of intake frequency, whereas reduction of intake amount was 
somewhat correlated with reduction of intake frequency. 
Among previous studies that have examined the importance 
of adequate intake of vegetables and fruits, a report from 
Europe demonstrated a close correlation between cancer 
prevention and vegetable or fruit intake as well as a negative 
correlation between sufficient vegetable and fruit intake, 
inflammatory index, and oxidative stress in youths between 
13-17 years of age [22,23]. In another study, sufficient vegetable 
and fruit intake was shown to boost resistance against diseases 
and prevent obesity. Furthermore, it was reported that adequate 
vegetable and fruit intake plays a vital role in boosting 
perseverance and emotional stability as well as relieving various 
forms of stress [1,9,12]. Particularly in Korean youths, increased 
intake of high-fat and high-sugar snacks resulting from emo-
tional instability due to stress from the university entrance 
period, lack of sleep, an unbalanced diet, and irregular eating 
was shown to increase health problems, including increased 
incidence of obesity and various diseases [4,17,24]. Increased 
vegetable and fruit intake in youths will resolve not only health 
problems caused by a bad diet but also problems caused by 
stress. Moreover, more than 500 g of daily intake of vegetables 
and fruits is recommended for nutrition management, preven-
tion of chronic diseases, and promotion of a balanced diet in 
Koreans [16]. However, as mentioned earlier, in the 2011 
KNHANES, average daily vegetable and fruit intake was 342.9 g 
(vegetables: 207.4 g, fruits: 135.5 g) in youths between 10-18 
years of age, which lags behind the recommended amount of 
500 g likely due to snack intake as explained in a previous study 
[21]. Based on the above results, menus favorable to adole-
scents containing vegetables and fruits need to be developed 
to increase intake of vegetables and fruits. 
To identify factors affecting vegetable and fruit intake, logistic 
regression analysis was conducted separately on the data from 
2006 and 2011 based on consumption frequencies of vegetables 
and fruits as the dependent variables. The general chara-
cteristics, diets, and health-related factors of the subjects were 
used as the independent variables. For vegetable and fruit 
intake-related factors from the 2006 and 2011 survey data, as 
the subjective economic level/standard of living decreased, 
intakes were reduced in the group that received nutrition 
education compared to the group that did not. On the other 
hand, vegetable and fruit intake increased with higher 
frequency of eating breakfast as well as mother's education </p>



<p>Intake of vegetables and fruits of adolescents </p>

<p>level. Environmental factors, including household socioe-
conomic level, education level of subject's parents, and family 
structure, along with individual factors such as gender and age 
are known to affect diet in youths [25-29]. Furthermore, as 
income and education levels increase in adult women, consu-
mption frequencies of vegetables and fruits increase [30-33]. 
Another study on vegetable and fruit intake in adults over 30 
years of age showed that the ratio of subjects meeting daily 
intake volumes (more than 400 g) recommended by the World 
Cancer Research Fund (WCRF) increases as education and 
household income levels increase [14]. Thus, mother's educa-
tion level and household income level both affect vegetable 
and fruit intake in Korean youths. Accordingly, national policies 
need to be developed to improve nutrition in low-income 
youths through school foodservice. 
Regarding the presence or absence of nutrition education, 
a study by Lee &amp; Kim [34] found that nutrition education has 
a positive effect on vegetable intake when offered to elemen-
tary school students; however, the results of this study showed 
a decrease in vegetable intake. This discrepancy is due to the 
fact that the study by Lee &amp; Kim evaluated changes in vegetable 
intake after offering education in a selected some group of 
subjects, whereas the data in this study were from the KYRBWS, 
which simply surveyed subjects on nutrition education items. 
Overall, the frequency of vegetable and fruit intake in subjects 
was lower in 2011 compared to 2006. Therefore, policies to 
increase intake of vegetables and fruits should be developed. 
Particularly, sufficient vegetable and fruit intake would help 
relieve various forms of stress in youths, and anti-oxidative 
nutrients from various vitamins and minerals would protect cells 
from oxidative damage [1,4,9,17,18,24]. Furthermore, a previous 
study showed that as vegetable and fruit intake increases, risk 
of cardiovascular disease decreases [12]. Another study by the 
European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition 
(EPIC) reported that diabetics with high intake of vegetables 
and fruits show lower mortality caused by cardiovascular 
disease [14,35]. Thus, we believe that vegetable and fruit intake 
needs to be increased. 
As this study is a survey using items surveying the frequency 
of vegetable and fruit consumption in the KYRBWS, it could 
not estimate the actual amount of vegetable and fruit 
consumption. However, intake frequencies were reduced in 
2011 compared to those in 2006. Thus, future research needs 
to improve dietary guidelines for nutrition education that may 
lead students to recognize the importance of food consumption 
and the necessity of increasing daily serving size of vegetables 
and fruits. </p>



<p>Yang Suk Kim et al. </p>





</text></tei>