<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4716173" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:43+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective: The evidence of an association between </p>

<p>calcium channel blockers (CCBs) and cancer is 
conflicting. The objective of the present study was to 
evaluate the risk of cancer (all, breast, prostate and 
colon cancers) in association with exposure to CCB. </p>

<p>Methods: This is a population-based cohort study in </p>

<p>patients exposed to CCBs from across the UK, using 
two comparison cohorts: (1) patients with no exposure 
to CCB (non-CCB) matched on age and gender and (2) 
unmatched patients unexposed to CCB and at least one 
other antihypertensive (AHT) prescription. Cancer 
incidence rates computed in the exposed and the two 
unexposed groups were compared using HRs and 
95% CIs obtained from multivariate Cox regression 
analyses. </p>

<p>Results: Overall, 150 750, 557 931 and 156 966 </p>

<p>patients were included, respectively, in the CCB, non-
CCB and AHT cohorts. Crude cancer incidence rates 
per 1000 person-years were 16.51, 15.75 and 10.62 
for the three cohorts, respectively. Adjusted HRs (CI) 
for all cancers comparing CCB, non-CCB and AHT 
cohorts were 0.88 (0.86 to 0.89) and 1.01 (0.98 to 
1.04), respectively. Compared to the AHT cohort, 
adjusted HRs (CI) for breast, prostate and colon cancer 
for the CCB cohort were 0.95 (0.87 to 1.04), 1.07 
(0.98 to 1.16) and 0.89 (0.81 to 0.98), respectively. 
Analyses by duration of exposure to CCB did not show 
excess risk. </p>

<p>Conclusions: This large population-based study </p>

<p>provides strong evidence that CCB use is not 
associated with an increased risk of cancer. The 
analyses yielded robust results across all types of 
cancer and different durations of exposure to CCBs. </p>

<p>Europe, hypertension is one of the most 
common interventions in primary care, and 
CCBs are a first-line treatment for this. </p>

<p>2   However, it has been suggested that CCBs 
may interfere with apoptosis, leading to an 
increased potential for abnormal cell prolif-
eration 
and 
tumour 
growth. </p>

<p>3   Epidemiological studies investigating the 
association between CCBs and cancer vary in 
terms of patients' characteristics, design, 
outcome variables and geographic location, 
the compound of which complicates assess-
ment and synthesis of results across studies. 
While several studies showed an association 
between CCB use and an increased risk for 
all forms of cancer 
4 5 and breast cancer, </p>

<p>6-9   others reported no risk. </p>

<p>10-15   Electronic healthcare databases used previ-
ously to investigate potential associations 
between CCB use and cancer can offer 
several advantages over primary data collec-
tion methods, particularly large sampling 
and limiting selection bias. 
16 We used the </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ This is a large-scale population-based study 
investigating differences in cancer risk between 
calcium channel blocker (CCB), non-CCB and 
non-CCB antihypertensive drugs users. 
▪ Extended analyses included specific cancer loca-
tions and cumulative length of exposure. 
▪ The study spanned a 14-year period (1996- 2009) and required patients to have at least 
2 years of follow-up data. 
▪ Exposure variables are unlikely to introduce bias 
considering physicians collected from Clinical 
Practice Research Datalink (CPRD) data while 
unaware of the hypothesis being tested in this 
analysis. 
▪ The results of this study might not apply directly 
to socially and ethnically diverse populations not 
included in the CPRD network of physicians, and 
generalisation therefore must be made 
cautiously. </p>

<p>Grimaldi-Bensouda L, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e009147. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009147 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD; formally 
known as the General Practice Research Database), the 
world's largest database of anonymised clinical records. 
The primary objective of the present study was to investi-
gate the potential association between CCB use and risk 
for all types of cancer, using data compiled from the 
CPRD between 1996 and 2009. Secondary objectives 
were to investigate the association between CCB and 
colon, breast and prostate cancers. This study was part of 
the Pharmacoepidemiological Research on Outcomes 
(PROTECT) project, the main goal of which is to 
strengthen the monitoring of the benefit-risk balance of 
medicines in Europe. </p>

<p>17   METHODS 
Data source 
We conducted a population-based cohort study using 
data from the CPRD. Managed by the British 
Department of Health, the CPRD contains over 5 
million active patient records (over 13 million overall) 
from approximately 650 primary care practices across 
the UK. Sets of CPRD data have been routinely vali-
dated, including diagnosis 
18-20 and drug exposure 
data. 
21 22 This information was linked to data from the 
National Cancer Registration System (NCRS), which cur-
rently includes 11 cancer registries, each with popula-
tions of between 1.65 and 13.8 million patients. 
23 Details 
were collected from a variety of sources including public 
and private hospitals, cancer centres, hospices, cancer 
screening programmes, other cancer registers, general 
practices, nursing homes, death certificates and the 
Hospital Episode Statistics. The NCRS contains data 
from patients across the whole of the UK, but the 
current study only used data from the English and 
Scottish Cancer Registration regions. </p>

<p>Study population 
The study population included all patients aged 18-
79 years in the CPRD-with linkable NCRS data for the 
study period between 1 January 1996 and 31 December 
2009-identified as having visited a general practitioner 
at least once during that period, 2 years of primary care 
history (up to standard) and at least 1 year of compu-
terised prescription history. 
Patients with at least one CCB prescription between 
1996 and 2009 (CCB exposure cohort) were compared 
against those in two comparison cohorts. The first com-
parison cohort included all patients without CCB pre-
scriptions between 1996 and 2009 (non-CCB cohort). 
Patients in the CCB cohort were matched by age and 
sex to a maximum of four patients in the non-CCB 
cohort. The second comparison cohort was a subset of 
the first, including unmatched patients with no CCB 
prescriptions but who had been prescribed at least one 
other AHT drug from 1996 to 2009 (AHT cohort). 
Members of each of the three cohorts were observed 
for the occurrence of cancer starting 6 months after </p>

<p>their index date, defined as the date of first CCB use 
(CCB cohort), the date of first AHT drug use (AHT 
cohort) and, for the non-CCB cohort, the same date as 
first CCB use for their matched CCB user. Patients with 
any record of cancer prior to the index date were 
excluded from all three cohorts. Each patient was fol-
lowed until the earliest date of one of the following was 
reached (whichever came first): cancer diagnosis, 
patient death, 80 years of age, completion of data collec-
tion, or practice left the CPRD database. </p>

<p>Exposure definition 
Drug codes used to identify CCB and AHT drug use 
were based on the British National Formulary (BNF). 
Patients were considered to be exposed to a drug if they 
had been prescribed at least one prescription between 
1996 and 2009. Exposure to CCB drugs was categorised 
into three subgroups: CCBs with direct cardiac effects 
(diltiazem, gallopamil and verapamil; Anatomical 
Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) codes=C08D), non-
selective CCBs (bepridil, fendiline, lidoflazine and per-
hexiline; ATC codes=C08E) and vascular selective CCBs 
(all other CCBs; ATC codes=C08C). Duration of expos-
ure to CCBs was calculated as the total cumulative expos-
ure derived from the total amount resulting from the 
defined daily dose (DDD), the number of prescriptions 
and the period covered by the prescriptions ( package 
size). Exposure to the following AHT drugs was consid-
ered for inclusion into the AHT cohort: diuretics, 
β-blockers, ACE inhibitors, adrenergic neuron blockers, 
α-blockers, AHT vasodilators, centrally acting AHT 
drugs, angiotensin II antagonists and renin inhibitors. 
These were chosen because there is no previous evi-
dence linking them to an increased risk of cancer 
incidence. </p>

<p>Outcome definition 
Information on cancer outcomes was extracted from the 
UK NCRS, which includes 11 regional registries. Cancer 
diagnoses were identified using READ codes and 
International Classification of Diseases, 10th Revision 
(ICD-10) codes, and included all primary and multiple 
sites malignant neoplasms (corresponding to ICD-10 
codes C00-C97), and carcinoma in situ (corresponding 
to ICD-10 codes D00-D09) of a known origin. Specific 
analyses were performed on the following three types of 
cancer, breast (ICD-10 code C50), prostate (ICD-10 
code C61) and colon (ICD-10 code C18). Benign neo-
plasms (corresponding to ICD-10 codes D10-D36) and 
neoplasms of uncertain or unknown origin (correspond-
ing to ICD-10 codes D37-D48) were excluded from the 
analyses. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses 
Crude cancer incidence rates for all three cohorts were 
calculated as the number of cancer occurrences per 
1000 person-years. The CCB cohort was compared to 
both, the non-CCB and AHT cohorts, with regard to </p>



<p>Grimaldi-Bensouda L, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e009147. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009147 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>cancer (all types). Cox regression models were con-
ducted to estimate the crude and multivariable adjusted 
relative risk by calculating HRs and 95% CIs of cancer 
in relation to drug exposure (ever vs never exposed). 
Potential confounding factors in the relation between 
cancer and CCB exposure were accounted for in multi-
variable regression models and included: age at index 
date and sex (matching variables in the comparison with 
the non-CCB cohort), smoking status, body mass index 
(BMI), alcohol consumption, diabetes, hypertension, 
arrhythmia, angina, or heart failure, as well as the use of 
statins or aspirin. These factors were chosen based on 
previous findings linking the variables with an increased 
risk of cancer. For the AHT cohort, separate analyses 
were performed for colon cancer, breast cancer in 
women and prostate cancer in men. Additional analyses 
were also conducted using the AHT cohort to account 
for switching drug exposure, with models stratified 
according to the duration of cumulative exposure to 
drugs (0-5, 5-10 and &gt;10 years). All analyses were con-
ducted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> software V.<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute, Inc</rs>, 
North Carolina, USA). The study protocol was registered 
at the ENCePP electronic register of studies (http:// 
www.encepp.eu/encepp/studiesDatabase.jsp). </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Population characteristics 
A total of 150 750 patients were included in the CCB 
cohort, 557 931 in the non-CCB cohort and 156 966 in 
the AHT cohort. The proportion of males and females 
in the CCB cohort was similar to the non-CCB cohort 
(matching variable) but with slightly more males when 
compared to the AHT cohort (respectively, 49.7% and 
46.0%, table 1). However, participants in the CCB 
cohort were 10 years older than participants in the AHT 
cohort (respectively, 61.5 and 51.4 years), with a higher 
prevalence of overweight people with diabetes, hyperten-
sion or angina than in the non-CCB and AHT cohorts. 
Participants in the CCB cohort were also more likely to 
have been prescribed statins or aspirin than the other 
two cohorts. </p>

<p>CCB and risk of any cancer 
Crude cancer rates were highest in the CCB cohort, with 
16.51/1000 person-years, followed by the non-CCB 
cohort, with 15.75/1000 person-years and the AHT 
cohort, with 10.62/1000 person-years (table 2). In 
adjusted multivariate analyses, CCB exposure was not 
associated with an increased risk for any type of cancer 
when compared to the AHT cohort (HR 1.01; CI 0.98 to 
1.04). This lack of association remained unchanged 
when the analysis was restricted to vascular-selective 
CCBs (HR 1.00; CI 0.98 to 1.03) or CCBs with direct 
cardiac effects (HR 0.96; CI 0.88 to 1.05). The number 
of patients was insufficient to perform a separate analysis 
on non-selective CCBs. Conversely, all types of cancer 
were slightly less frequent in patients who were exposed </p>

<p>to CCBs compared to those in the non-CCB cohort (HR 
0.88; CI 0.86 to 0.89). </p>

<p>Risk of breast, prostate and colon cancer 
Consistent with results for all cancers, breast and pros-
tate cancer rates (crude rates) were higher in the CCB 
cohort than in the AHT cohort-respectively, 3.05 and 
2.32 cases per 1000 person-years for breast cancer, and 
4.10 and 2.50 cases per 1000 person-years for prostate 
cancer (table 3). In adjusted multivariate analyses, no 
differences were found for relative risk of breast cancer 
(HR 0.95; CI 0.87 to 1.04) or prostate cancer (HR 1.07; 
CI 0.98 to 1.16) between the CCB and AHT cohorts. In 
contrast, colon cancer rates were lower for CCB-exposed 
patients compared with those of the AHT cohort (0.92 
compared with 1.41/1000 person-years). CCB exposure 
also showed a small but significant protective effect for 
prostate cancer compared to the AHT cohort (HR 0.89; 
CI 0.81 to 0.89). </p>

<p>Risk of cancer and duration of exposure to CCBs 
Cancer rates were higher in the CCB cohort than in the 
AHT cohort regardless of duration of drug exposure (ie, 
all durations), although the difference between rates 
decreased as the cumulative exposure increased 
(&lt;5 years: 25.9 compared with 13.8; 5-10 years: 10.53 
compared with 8.75; &gt;10 years: 4.59 compared with 3.08; 
table 4). There was no significant evidence of a relation 
between cancer risk and increasing duration of cumula-
tive CCB exposure as opposed to the AHT cohort. In 
fact, patients exposed to CCBs up to 5 years were less 
likely to develop any type of cancer (all cancers) than 
patients exposed to all other AHT drugs for the same 
duration of treatment (HR 0.88; CI 0.85 to 0.91). No dif-
ference in cancer risk between CCB and AHT cohorts 
was found for participants prescribed these drugs for a 
total of 5-10 years (HR 0.98; CI 0.93 to 1.04) or beyond 
10 years (HR 1.11; CI 0.98 to 1.27). Duration of expos-
ure to CCB drugs was also specifically examined in rela-
tion to the risk of breast cancer. These results did not 
differ from those listed above, with HR that decreased 
below unity with increasing duration of exposure. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Summary of findings 
This population-based cohort study among British adults 
found that exposure to CCBs was not associated with an 
increased risk of cancer, all types combined. On the con-
trary, for patients taking CCBs for &lt;5 years, our results 
suggest CCB exposure to be associated with a lower risk 
for any of the types of cancer studied. This study also 
found no difference in cancer risk for patients exposed 
to CCBs compared to those exposed to the most com-
monly used types of AHT drugs. This finding was con-
sistent across all types of cancer, as well as for breast and 
prostate cancers. Patients exposed to CCBs were at lower 
risk of colon cancer than those exposed to other AHT </p>

<p>Grimaldi-Bensouda L, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e009147. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009147 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>drugs. Our study also found no differences between cat-
egories of CCB drugs (vascular and cardiac-selective) 
and no increased risk of cancer with increasing duration 
of exposure to CCBs. </p>

<p>Comparisons with current evidence 
Only a few follow-up studies showed findings different to 
ours, reporting an increased risk for all types of 
cancer 
4 5 24 or breast cancer. 
6 8 9 25 An early cohort 
study by Pahor et al 
5 reported that CCB use was asso-
ciated with an overall twofold increase in cancer risk in </p>

<p>750 elderly individuals with hypertension. A repeated 
analysis using the same cohort, but a different inclusion 
criteria, found that the risk of developing cancer 
increased by approximately 1.7 times for CCB users com-
pared with non-users. 
4 Fitzpatrick et al 
6 found a 2.6-fold 
increased risk for breast cancer in CCB users compared 
with non-CCB users in their study of 3198 women aged 
65 years or older. In the majority of studies, the strength 
of this association appeared to be dependent on daily 
dosage or cumulative dose, ranging from no association 
in users of low dosages to a twofold (or possibly higher) </p>

<p>Table 1 Population characteristics of the calcium channel blocker (CCB), non-CCB and non-CCB antihypertensive (AHT) 
drugs cohorts </p>

<p>Variables 
CCB cohort n (%) 
Non-CCB cohort n (%) 
AHT cohort n (%) </p>

<p>Total sample 
150 750 
557 931 
156 966 
Age (index date, years) 
Mean (SD) 
61.5 (11.5) 
60.1 (12.1) 
51.4 (15.4) 
Gender 
Male 
74 956 (49.7) 
281 575 (50.5) 
72 269 (46.0) 
Female 
75 794 (50.3) 
276 356 (49.5) 
84 697 (54.0) 
BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
≥30 
42 683 (28.3) 
78 158 (14.0) 
32 198 (20.5) 
25-29 
50 251 (33.3) 
149 397 (26.8) 
44 220 (28.2) 
&lt;24 
32 749 (21.7) 
159 215 (28.5) 
45 681 (29.1) 
Missing* 
25 067 (16.6) 
171 161 (30.7) 
34 867 (22.2) 
Smoking 
Ever 
77 220 (51.2) 
243 112 (43.6) 
76 252 (48.6) 
Never 
67 540 (44.8) 
250 893 (45.0) 
70 171 (44.7) 
Missing* 
5990 (4.0) 
63 926 (11.5) 
10 543 (6.7) 
Alcohol use 
Current (high or increasing) 
9723 (6.4) 
22 945 (4.1) 
8767 (5.6) 
Current (low) 
59 050 (39.2) 
199 667 (35.8) 
61 580 (39.2) 
Current (unknown) 
27 290 (18.1) 
85 252 (15.3) 
26 802 (17.1) 
Former drinker 
2438 (1.6) 
6899 (1.2) 
2132 (1.4) 
Non-drinker 
19 887 (13.2) 
57 850 (10.4) 
16 876 (10.8) 
Missing* 
32 362 (21.5) 
185 318 (33.2) 
40 809 (26.0) 
Diagnosis of diabetes before or at baseline 
Yes 
18 287 (12.1) 
28 305 (5.1) 
13 648 (8.7) 
No 
132 463 (87.9) 
529 626 (94.9) 
143 318 (91.3) 
Hypertension before or at baseline 
Yes 
111 022 (73.6) 
74 033 (13.3) 
45 724 (29.1) 
No 
39 728 (26.4) 
483 898 (86.7) 
111 242 (70.9) 
Angina before or at baseline 
Yes 
13 637 (9.0) 
17 531 (3.1) 
4887 (3.1) 
No 
137 113 (91.0) 
540 400 (96.9) 
152 079 (96.9) 
Arrhythmia before or at baseline 
Yes 
6873 (4.6) 
13 144 (2.4) 
5907 (3.8) 
No 
143 877 (95.4) 
544 787 (97.6) 
151 059 (96.2) 
Heart failure before or at baseline 
Yes 
2392 (1.6) 
8322 (1.5) 
2277 (1.5) 
No 
148 358 (98.4) 
549 609 (98.5) 
154 689 (98.5) 
Statin use within 1 year of or at baseline 
Yes 
42 801 (28.4) 
58 417 (10.5) 
26 360 (16.8) 
No 
107 949 (71.6) 
499 514 (89.5) 
130 606 (83.2) 
Aspirin use within 1 year of or at baseline 
Yes 
37 025 (24.6) 
49 949 (9.0) 
24 050 (15.3) 
No 
113 725 (75.4) 
507 982 (91.0) 
132 916 (84.7) </p>

<p>*Information on behavioural risk factors closest to the index date; considered missing if older than 10 years from the index date. </p>



<p>Grimaldi-Bensouda L, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e009147. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009147 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>increased risk when higher dosages were used. Our 
study found no difference in the strength of the associ-
ation when considering the cumulative exposure to 
drugs over time; and an association was also not evident 
until at least 2-3 years after exposure. Furthermore, 
cancer risk was primarily highest for exposure to verap-
amil, 
24 while no such relation was reported for diltiazem, 
and no consistent associations were shown for specific 
cancer sites or histological types. 
25 However, in contrast 
to our study, a paper by Li et al 
8 reported that the use of 
particular types of AHT medicines, including 
immediate-release CCBs and certain diuretics, was asso-
ciated with a modest increased risk of breast cancer 
among 975 women aged 65-79 years. Davis and Mirick </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>also found that breast cancer risk was not associated with 
the use of β-blockers. 
Results from a large number of observational studies 
are consistent with our finding that long-term CCB use 
is not associated with cancer risk. 
11 14 26-30 For example, 
multiple case-control studies investigating the risk of 
developing cancer among patients with hypertension 
treated with CCBs or other AHTs have also found a 
similar risk for malignancy among users and non-users 
of CCBs. 
9 11 12 14 15 26-28 30 Several large-scale, 
population-based cohort studies that took place in 
Denmark, 
10 31 32 the USA, 
13 33 the UK 
34 and Europe, </p>

<p>35   also found no evidence for an association between CCB 
use and cancer. Limitations of these studies included 
the use of self-reported exposure data 
13 35 and lack of 
covariate information on relevant confounders, such as 
smoking, BMI and alcohol use. 
10 31 32 34 Cohen et al </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>carried out three successive interviews in over 3500 indi-
viduals from North Carolina, USA, aged 65-105 years. 
After adjusting for baseline and time-dependent covari-
ates such as race, diabetes, blood pressure, CCB dose, 
CCB class and length of follow-up, cancer risk was 
similar between CCB users and non-users. Our study dif-
fered from the study by Cohen et al 
33 in several respects, 
notably, the ethnic diversity of our study population, the 
time period covered (more recent) and the definition of 
CCB user status (first-time users). González-Pérez et al </p>

<p>34   also used data from the CPRD to investigate the associ-
ation between breast cancer and AHT drugs, specifically 
captopril, and also found that breast cancer incidence 
was similar for users and non-users. They also found that 
captopril was not associated with a reduced risk of breast 
cancer. Trenkwalder et al 
35 investigated the use of CCBs 
and incidence of fatal and non-fatal cancer in a 3-year 
follow-up study of over 1000 elderly patients. Similarly, 
they found that CCB use did not increase the risk of 
fatal or non-fatal cancer in their elderly central 
European population. The findings from the Danish 
cohort studies also agree with our findings related to 
specific cancer types. For example, the study by Fryzek 
et al, 
10 including almost 50 000 Danish women, found 
no evidence that AHT drug use (including CCBs) was 
related to breast cancer. Olsen et al 
31 reported no 
increased risk of colon cancer between CCB users as 
compared to non-users in a Danish study of almost 
18 000 patients. Our findings differ from recently pub-
lished findings by Li et al, 
1 who found that long-term use 
of CCB was particularly associated with breast cancer. </p>

<p>Table 2 Risk of all types of cancer in the calcium channel blocker (CCB) cohort compared to the non-CCB and the non-CCB 
antihypertensive (AHT) drugs cohorts </p>

<p>Cohort </p>

<p>Number of 
cancers </p>

<p>Number of 
person-years </p>

<p>Cancer incidence 
rates (per 1000 
person-years) </p>

<p>CCB vs non-CCB 
CCB vs AHT 
Crude HR 
Adjusted HR </p>

<p>Crude HR 
Adjusted HR 
(95% CI) 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>CCB 
14 588 
883 803 
16.51 
1.03 (1.01 to 1.05) 0.88 (0.86 to 0.89)* 1.56 (1.53 to 1.61) 1.01 (0.98 to 1.04) 
Non-CCB 43 992 
2 792 948 
15.75 
1.00 (reference) 
1.00 (reference) 
-
-
AHT 
9754 
918 801 
10.62 
-
-
1.00 (reference) 
1.00 (reference) </p>

<p>*p&lt;0.001. HR obtained from multivariate Cox proportional hazard analyses including age at index date, gender, smoking status, body mass 
index, alcohol consumption, diagnoses of diabetes, hypertension, arrhythmia, angina or heart failure, and use of statins or aspirin. </p>

<p>Table 3 Risk of breast cancer (women only), prostate cancer (men only) and colon cancer in the calcium channel blocker (CCB) cohort compared to the non-CCB 
antihypertensive (AHT) drugs cohort </p>

<p>Breast cancer (women only) 
Prostate cancer (men only) 
Colon cancer </p>

<p>CCB cohort 
AHT cohort 
CCB cohort 
AHT cohort 
CCB cohort 
AHT cohort </p>

<p>Cancer rates (crude 
per 1000 
person-years) </p>

<p>3.05 
2.32 
4.10 
2.50 
1.41 
0.92 </p>

<p>Number of cancers 
1397 
1194 
1753 
1014 
1249 
849 
Number of 
person-years </p>

<p>457 417 
514 400 
427 654 
404 833 
885 070 
919 233 </p>

<p>Crude HR (95% CI) 
1.33 (1.23 to 1.43) 
1.00 (reference) 
1.64 (1.52 to 1.78) 
1.00 (reference) 
1.54 (1.41 to 1.68) 
1.00 (reference) 
Adjusted HR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>0.95 (0.87 to 1.04) 
1.00 (reference) 
1.07 (0.98 to 1.16) 
1.00 (reference) 
0.89 (0.81 to 0.98)* 
1.00 (reference) </p>

<p>*p=0.02. HR obtained from multivariate Cox proportional hazard analyses including age at index date, gender, smoking status, body mass 
index, alcohol consumption, diagnoses of diabetes, hypertension, arrhythmia, angina or heart failure, and use of statins or aspirin. </p>

<p>Grimaldi-Bensouda L, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e009147. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009147 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations 
To the best of our knowledge, ours is the first large-scale 
population-based study to investigate differences in 
cancer risk between CCB, non-CCB and non-CCB AHT 
drug users. Extended analyses included specific cancer 
locations and cumulative length of exposure. Our study 
spanned a 14-year period (1996-2009) and required 
patients to have at least 2 years of follow-up data. The 
results of this study do not apply directly to populations 
not included in the CPRD network of physicians. 
However, this large, socially and ethnically diverse study 
population is likely to be representative of the British 
population, for the CPRD contains data from primary 
care practices across the whole of the UK. To maximise 
internal validity, we selected two different populations of 
CCB non-users for comparison. We hypothesised that 
patients exposed to AHT drugs other than CCBs repre-
sented the best choice; however, this population turned 
out to be much younger than that of CCB users. 
Multivariate analyses adjusted for these age differences, 
and other potential confounders for the association 
between cancer and CCB use, were performed. This was 
possible due to the breadth of information collected in 
the CPRD. Finally, exposure variables as recorded by 
physicians are unlikely to be biased because CPRD data 
has been shown to be valid and reliable, and collected 
while unaware of the hypothesis being tested in this 
analysis. </p>

<p>22   CONCLUSION 
This large population-based study provides strong evi-
dence that CCB use is not associated with an increased 
risk of cancer when compared to no CCB use or other 
non-CCB AHT drugs. The analyses yielded results across 
all types of cancer and different durations of exposure 
to CCBs. It is likely that different results obtained from 
different countries are due to methodological rather 
than biological issues. </p>

<p>Author affiliations 
1 LA-SER, Paris, France 
2 Conservatoire national des arts et métiers (CNAM), Paris, France 
3 Utrecht Institute for Pharmaceutical Sciences, Utrecht University, Utrecht, 
The Netherlands 
4 European Medicines Agency, London, UK 
5 Pfizer Epidemiology, New York, New York, USA 
6 Tulane University, New Orleans, Louisiana, USA 
7 Department of Epidemiology, Biostatistics and Occupational Health, McGill 
University, Montreal, Canada </p>

<p>Contributors LG-B and OK drafted the protocol and the analyses plan and 
conducted the analyses. MR drafted the manuscript. LG-B supervised all 
operational aspects of the study including recruitment, data collection and 
management. All the authors made substantial contributions to conception or 
design of the work, reviewed the manuscript for important intellectual 
content, approved the final manuscript, and agreed to be accountable for all 
aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or 
integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved. </p>

<p>Funding Innovative Medicine Initiative Joint Undertaking (http://www.imi. 
europa.eu). </p>

<p>Table 4 
Risk of all types of cancer in the calcium channel blocker (CCB) cohort compared to the non-CCB antihypertensive (AHT) drugs cohort, by cumulative duration of </p>

<p>drug exposure </p>

<p>Cumulative duration of drug exposure* </p>

<p>Less than 5 years </p>

<p>5-10 years </p>

<p>More than 10 years </p>

<p>CCB cohort </p>

<p>AHT cohort </p>

<p>CCB cohort </p>

<p>AHT cohort </p>

<p>CCB cohort </p>

<p>AHT cohort </p>

<p>Cancer rates (per 1000 person-years) </p>

<p>25.9 </p>

<p>13.8 </p>

<p>10.53 </p>

<p>8.75 </p>

<p>4.59 </p>

<p>3.08 </p>

<p>Number of cancers </p>

<p>10 449 </p>

<p>6917 </p>

<p>3441 </p>

<p>2400 </p>

<p>705 </p>

<p>437 </p>

<p>Number of person-years </p>

<p>403 881 </p>

<p>502 788 </p>

<p>326 639 </p>

<p>274 173 </p>

<p>153 656 </p>

<p>141 840 </p>

<p>Crude HR (95% CI) </p>

<p>1.85 (1.79 to 1.90) </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) </p>

<p>1.33 (1.27 to 1.40) </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) </p>

<p>1.43 (1.27 to 1.61) </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) </p>

<p>Adjusted HR (95% CI) </p>

<p>0.88 (0.85 to 0.91) † </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) </p>

<p>0.98 (0.93 to 1.04) </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) </p>

<p>1.11 (0.98 to 1.27) </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) </p>

<p>*Duration of CCB exposure estimated using dates of first and last utilisation within the period at risk; same rule applied to the AHT cohort. 
 †p&lt;0.001. HR obtained from multivariate Cox proportional hazard analyses including age at index date, gender, smoking status, body mass index, alcohol consumption, diagnoses of diabetes, 
hypertension, arrhythmia, angina or heart failure, and use of statins or aspirin. </p>



<p>Grimaldi-Bensouda L, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e009147. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009147 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Disclaimer The views expressed in this article are the personal views of the 
authors and should not be understood or quoted as being made on behalf of 
or reflecting the position of their respective organisations. </p>

<p>Competing interests The PROTECT project has received support from the 
Innovative Medicine Initiative Joint Undertaking (http://www.imi.europa.eu) 
under Grant Agreement n°115 004, resources of which are composed of 
financial contribution from the European Union's Seventh Framework 
Programme (FP7/2007-2013) and EFPIA (European Federation of 
Pharmaceutical Industries and Association) companies' in-kind contribution. 
LG-B is currently employed by LA-SER, the company conducting the study. 
OK reports having received a grant from IMI-PROTECT Consortium (http:// 
www.imi-protect.eu) during the conduct of the study. MCHdG reports having 
received a grant from IMI-PROTECT Consortium (http://www.imi-protect.eu) 
during the conduct of the study, and a grant from Top Institute Pharma (NL) 
(http://www.tipharma.com) outside the submitted work. ASMA reports having 
received a grant from IMI-PROTECT Consortium (http://www.imi-protect.eu) 
during the conduct of the study. MLdB reports having received a grant from 
IMI-PROTECT Consortium (http://www.imi-protect.eu) during the conduct of 
the study, and grants from TIPharma-Escher: Improving the EU system for 
marketing authorisation outside the submitted work. XK has no relationship 
with LA-SER that might have an interest in the submitted work in the previous 
3 years. RR is an employee and shareholder of Pfizer, Inc; the views 
expressed are his and not necessarily those of Pfizer, Inc. LA-SER has no 
commercial interests in any of the products studied. Members of the LA-SER 
network have no interest in the drug or other factors studied. Private 
companies or agencies using PGRx for their studies obtain data by 
subscription. The authors consult or currently participate in studies 
sponsored by the following pharmaceutical companies: AstraZeneca, Boiron, 
Laboratoires Expanscience, Laboratoires Genevrier, GSK, Janssen-Cilag, 
Merck/Schering-Plough, Negma/Wockhardt, Novartis, Pfizer and several 
divisions of Sanofi. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>



<p>Grimaldi-Bensouda L, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e009147. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009147 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>