<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4368909" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives: During the past decade, coal-based sponge </p>

<p>iron plants, a highly polluted industry, have grown rapidly 
in Barjora, India. The toxic effects of particulate matters 
and gaseous pollutants include various respiratory 
diseases. Understanding workers' perception of 
respiratory health is essential in people-centred 
healthcare. The aim of the study was to assess their 
respiratory health status and to determine its predictors. </p>

<p>Design: Cross-sectional study. 
Setting: Coal-based sponge iron plants in Barjora, India. 
Participants: 258 coal-based sponge iron plant </p>

<p>workers. </p>

<p>Primary outcome measure: Respiratory health status </p>

<p>was measured using the St. George's respiratory 
questionnaire (SGRQ) total score. 100 and 0 represent 
the worst and best possible respiratory health status, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses: The two-part model (frequency </p>

<p>(any worse respiratory health status) and severity 
(amount of worse respiratory health status)) was 
developed for the score, as the data were positively 
skewed with many zeros. </p>

<p>Results: The mean (SD) SGRQ total score was 7.7 </p>

<p>(14.5), the median (IQR) was 0.9 (9.0), and the observed 
range was 0-86.6. The best possible SGRQ total score 
was reported by 46.9% of workers. Independent 
predictors of worse respiratory health status were cleaner 
domestic cooking fuel (coefficient −0.76, 95% CI −1.46 
to −0.06, p=0.034) and personal history of any 
respiratory disease (1.76, 1.04 to 2.47, p&lt;0.001) in case 
of frequency; and family history of any respiratory 
disease (0.43, 0.02 to 0.83, p=0.039) and personal 
history (1.19, 0.83 to 1.54, p&lt;0.001) in case of severity. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Less than half of the coal-based sponge </p>

<p>iron plant workers in Barjora have the best possible 
respiratory health status. The predictors of worse 
respiratory health status were identified. The study 
findings could be taken into consideration in future 
interventional studies aimed at improving the respiratory 
health status of these workers. </p>

<p>steel. Either coal or natural gas is used in 
sponge iron production. In India, non-coking 
coal is easily available. Thus, the sector 
depends mostly on coal-based sponge iron 
and nearly 80% of the total coal-based 
sponge iron plants are located in India. 1 
About 60% of this production comes from 
small-scale industries in the unorganised 
sector with poor pollution control facilities. 1 
During the past decade, these sponge iron 
plants have rapidly grown in the Barjora block 
of Bankura district, a deprived district in West 
Bengal. 2 These factories are categorised as 
red industries (highly polluted industries) 
and the major pollutants are of three types: 
solid waste heavy metals (cadmium, chro-
mium, lead, mercury and nickel); particulate 
matters (suspended particulate matter and 
respirable particulate matter) and gaseous 
pollutants (oxides of sulfur and nitrogen, and 
hydrocarbons). 1-4 The toxic effects of solid 
waste heavy metals are varied and often take 
several years to manifest. However, the toxic 
effects of particulate matters and gaseous </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ This is the first study to explore respiratory health 
status of coal-based sponge iron plant workers. 
▪ Respiratory health status measurement is subject-
ive to participants, and thus a valid and reliable 
tool, the St. George's respiratory questionnaire 
(SGRQ), was used. 
▪ The response rate was 100%. Missing data 
could lead to bias, but it was extremely low in 
this study. 
▪ Participants who were absent from work on the 
dates of the survey were excluded, and this 
absence from work could be due to poor respira-
tory health status, which could have underesti-
mated the worse respiratory health status. 
▪ As this was a cross-sectional study, it was not 
possible to determine the causal association 
between different variables and respiratory health 
status. </p>

<p>Chattopadhyay K, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e007084. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007084 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>pollutants are often rapid and include respiratory dis-
eases (cough, phlegm, bronchitis, asthma and allergy). 1-4 
The importance of prevention and treatment of these ail-
ments is well acknowledged; however, understanding 
workers' perception of respiratory health is also essential 
in people-centred healthcare. 5 Respiratory health status 
is a complex and multidimensional concept of the well-
being of a person and their perception of respiratory 
health. Respiratory health status is one of the essential 
aspects of respiratory health, which is embedded in the 
physical, mental, social and cultural context. 6 7 Poor 
respiratory health status places a burden on the individ-
ual, family, community and health services, and thus 
respiratory health status is of major public health import-
ance. 6 7 Research has been conducted to explore the 
respiratory health status of the general population and 
other industrial workers in various countries, 8-10 but 
none among coal-based sponge iron plant workers. The 
aim of the study was to assess their respiratory health 
status and to determine factors that independently 
predict their respiratory health status. Knowledge of 
factors associated with the respiratory health status of 
these workers would provide valuable information about 
strategies that professionals and providers of healthcare 
can address to improve their respiratory health status. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Study design, participants, area and inclusion/exclusion 
criteria 
A cross-sectional study was conducted among coal-based 
sponge iron plant workers in Barjora block (Bankura 
district, West Bengal, India) as shown in figure 1. 
Participants who gave written informed consent to par-
ticipate in the study were included, and those who were 
absent from work on the dates of the survey were 
excluded. </p>

<p>Data collection procedure and tool 
A survey was conducted with a quantitative questionnaire 
(available in English, Bengali and Hindi languages) in 
May and June 2013. The questionnaire was either self-
completed by the participant (if literate) or completed 
by the fieldworker (for illiterate participants). In the 
latter case, each question was shown and read to the par-
ticipant who was asked to say and point out the answer. 
Each session lasted for about 30 min and was completed 
in one sitting. Data were entered on the day of collection. 
Section I of the questionnaire included the following 
variables: age (in years), sex, mother tongue ( proxy 
measures for local ethnic origin, culture and lifestyle), 
religion, social caste (general or scheduled caste (SC)/ 
scheduled tribe (ST)/other backward class (OBC)), 
marriage, education (literate or illiterate), work type 
(non-manual or manual), working hours per day (8 
(normal) 11 or more than 8), salary per month (5395 
Indian rupees (INR: minimum monthly wage of an 
unskilled worker) 11 or more, or less than 5395 INR), </p>

<p>total duration of work in this type of factory ( proxy 
measure for exposure time, in years), smoking, smoke-
less tobacco intake, alcohol drinking, house type 
( pucca/semipucca (at least some high-quality construc-
tion materials such as bricks, tiles, cement and concrete) 
or kachcha (low-quality construction materials such as 
mud and thatch)), 12 people living in a room (less than 
3, or 3 or more to indicate crowding), 12 pet animal at 
home, domestic cooking fuel (cleaner fuel (non-
continuous exposure to smoke: charcoal, coal/coke/ 
lignite, kerosene, electricity, petroleum gas and biogas) 
or biomass fuel (continuous exposure to smoke: wood/ 
crop residues and animal dung)), 12 separate room as 
kitchen at home, chimney/exhaust fan for cooking food 
at home, family history ( presence/history of any respira-
tory disease in biological father/mother/siblings), per-
sonal history ( presence/history of any respiratory 
disease) and health insurance. All the variables were 
dichotomous except age and total duration of work in 
this type of factory. Section I was designed in English, 
translated into Bengali and Hindi, reviewed by a local 
primary school teacher and pretested extensively on six 
local similar workers who were not involved in the study. 
Section II included the standardised St. George's 
respiratory questionnaire (SGRQ) to measure the 
respiratory health status. 7 13 14 This questionnaire has 
been widely used in the general population, different 
industrial workers and patients with respiratory dis-
eases. 8-10 15 There are two parts: part 1: questions 1-8 
address participants' recollection of their symptoms over 
the preceding period of 3 months, and part 2: questions 
9-16 address participants' current state (questions 11 
and 15 measure disturbances to participants' daily phys-
ical activity, and questions 9-10, 12-14 and 16-17 cover 
a wide range of disturbances of psychosocial function). 
A total score is calculated that summarises the impact on 
overall respiratory health status. The score is expressed 
as a percentage of impairment where 100 represents the 
worst possible respiratory health status and 0 indicates 
the best possible respiratory health status. The SGRQ is 
available in English, Bengali and Hindi. 7 13-15 </p>

<p>Sample size 
As this was the first study of respiratory health status of 
coal-based sponge iron plant workers, no information 
was available on which to base the sample size calcula-
tion. Instead, a web-based sample size calculator, 
<rs type="software">Creative Research Systems</rs>, 16 was used to calculate the 
sample size, using the following assumptions/informa-
tion: confidence level (95%), margin of error (5%) and 
population size (total 662 coal-based sponge iron plant 
workers, this information was received from the factory 
directors in Barjora). A random sample of 258 such 
workers was required, assuming a response rate of 95%. 
A numbered list of all 662 workers was created (worker 
1, worker 2, worker 3 and so forth). A web-based rando-
miser, <rs type="software">Research Randomizer</rs>, 17 was used to generate 1 </p>



<p>Chattopadhyay K, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e007084. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007084 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>set of 258 unique, sorted numbers with a range from 1 
to 662 (representing the workers' assigned numbers). </p>

<p>Ethics 
Information sheets and consent forms were available in 
English, Bengali and Hindi. 18 The study objectives were 
explained to all the eligible participants and written 
informed consent was taken from those interested in 
participating. Illiterate participants were requested to 
put their left hand thumb impression on the consent 
form. Participants were not compelled and were free to 
participate in the study. They were assured regarding the 
anonymity, privacy, confidentiality and data protection of 
their information. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses 
The SGRQ total score is a continuous variable, and was 
positively skewed with many zeros. Thus, the two-part 
model was developed, which takes advantage of the basic 
rule of probability and splits into two parts-frequency (ie, 
any worse respiratory health status and the estimate 
included all the participants) and severity (ie, amount of 
worse respiratory health status and the estimate was based 
on a subsample of participants with respiratory health 
status greater than zero). 19 20 The two-part model used 
logit regression in the first part, and generalised linear 
model regression with the log link and γ distribution in 
the second part. 20 Both the unadjusted and adjusted (to 
determine independent predictors of the score) models 
were developed, which also included a sample with 
unknown values for the variables (from section I). All the </p>

<p>section I variables were included in the adjusted model. 
Coefficients and their respective 95% CI were calculated. 
The results were considered significant when p values 
were less than or equal to 0.05. All data were analysed 
using STATAV.12 for Windows software. 21 </p>

<p>RESULTS 
The response rate was 100%. Table 1 summarises the vari-
ables from section I. All the participants were men with a 
mean (SD) age of 35 (8) years. Eighty-six per cent, 96% 
and 62% of participants were Bengali, Hindu and 
belonged to the general social caste, respectively. 
Eighty-six per cent and 88% of them were married and lit-
erate, respectively. Seventy-eight per cent and 74% of 
them were manual workers and earned less than 5395 
INR/month, respectively. The mean (SD) total duration 
of work in this type of factory was 10 (14) years. Smokeless 
tobacco was consumed by 50% of participants. Fifty per 
cent of participants had a kachcha type of house, 69% of 
them were living in a room with three or more people, 
52% of them had a pet animal at home, and 91% of them 
had no chimney/exhaust fan for cooking food at home. 
Twenty-six per cent of participants had a personal history 
of respiratory diseases. The mean (SD) SGRQ total score 
was 7.7 (14.5), the median (IQR) was 0.9 (9.0), and the 
observed range was 0-86.6. The best possible SGRQ total 
score was reported by 46.9% of workers. 
Table 2 reports the two-part model to determine 
factors associated with the SGRQ total score. In the 
unadjusted model, a higher SGRQ total score (or worse 
respiratory health status) was associated with cleaner </p>

<p>Figure 1 Location of Barjora, India. </p>

<p>Chattopadhyay K, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e007084. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007084 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>domestic cooking fuel (coefficient −0.53, 95% CI −1.04 
to −0.03, p=0.039) and personal history of any respira-
tory disease (1.66, 0.99 to 2.33, p&lt;0.001) in case of fre-
quency; and family history of any respiratory disease 
(0.47, 0.01 to 0.94, p=0.047) and personal history (1.14, 
0.84 to 1.44, p&lt;0.001) in case of severity. Independent 
predictors of a higher SGRQ total score were cleaner 
domestic cooking fuel (−0.76, −1.46 to −0.06, p=0.034) 
and personal history (1.76, 1.04 to 2.47, p&lt;0.001) in case 
of frequency; and family history (0.43, 0.02 to 0.83, </p>

<p>p=0.039) and personal history (1.19, 0.83 to 1.54, 
p&lt;0.001) in case of severity. McFadden's pseudo R 2 value 
was 0.14 (for the adjusted model). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
The study findings are compared with studies conducted 
among the general population and other industrial 
workers in various countries, 8-10 as respiratory health 
status studies conducted among coal-based sponge iron </p>

<p>Table 1 Section I variables </p>

<p>n total=258 
n (%) 
n (%) </p>

<p>Age 
35.4 (8.2)* 
Alcohol drinking 
Sex 
No 
171 (66.3) 
Male 
258 (100) 
Yes 
85 (33.0) 
Female 
0 
Unknown 
2 (0.8) 
Mother tongue 
House type 
Bengali 
222 (86.1) 
Pucca/semipucca 
127 (49.2) 
Other (Hindi/Oriya) 
29 (11.2) 
Kachcha 
129 (50.0) 
Unknown 
7 (2.7) 
Unknown 
2 (0.8) 
Religion 
People in a room 
Hindu 
247 (95.7) 
&lt;3 
81 (31.4) 
Islam 
11 (4.3) 
≥3 
177 (68.6) 
Social caste 
Pet animal 
General 
161 (62.4) 
No 
123 (47.7) 
SC/ST/OBC 
92 (35.7) 
Yes 
135 (52.3) 
Unknown 
5 (1.9) 
Domestic cooking fuel 
Marital status 
Cleaner fuel 
159 (61.6) 
Yes 
221 (85.7) 
Biomass fuel 
98 (38.0) 
No 
35 (13.5) 
Other 
1 (0.4) 
Unknown 
2 (0.8) 
Kitchen 
Education 
Yes 
190 (73.6) 
Literate 
226 (87.6) 
No 
67 (26.0) 
Illiterate 
31 (12.0) 
Unknown 
1 (0.4) 
Unknown 
1 (0.4) 
Chimney/exhaust fan 
Work type 
Yes 
22 (8.5) 
Non-manual 
57 (22.1) 
No 
234 (90.7) 
Manual 
200 (77.5) 
Unknown 
2 (0.8) 
Unknown 
1 (0.4) 
Family history 
Working hours/day 
No 
182 (70.5) 
8 
233 (90.3) 
Yes 
56 (21.7) 
&gt;8 
23 (8.9) 
Unknown 
20 (7.8) 
Unknown 
2 (0.8) 
Personal history 
Salary/month 
No 
181 (70.2) 
≥5395 INR 
68 (26.4) 
Yes 
66 (25.5) 
&lt;5395 INR 
190 (73.6) 
Unknown 
11 (4.3) 
Total duration of work † 
10.0 (14.1)* 
Health insurance 
Smoking 
No 
49 (19.0) 
No 
158 (61.2) 
Yes 
209 (81.0) 
Yes 
99 (38.4) 
Unknown 
1 (0.4) 
Smokeless tobacco 
No 
128 (49.6) 
Yes 
129 (50.0) 
Unknown 
1 (0.4) </p>

<p>*mean (SD). 
 †n total=252. 
SC, scheduled caste; ST, scheduled tribe; OBC, other backward class; INR, Indian rupees. </p>



<p>Chattopadhyay K, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e007084. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007084 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Table 2 
Two-part model to determine factors associated with the SGRQ total score </p>

<p>Total score </p>

<p>Unadjusted model </p>

<p>Adjusted model </p>

<p>Frequency (n=258)* </p>

<p>Severity (n=137) </p>

<p>Frequency (n=257) </p>

<p>Severity (n=137) </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>Coefficient 95% CI </p>

<p>p 
Value Coefficient 95% CI </p>

<p>p 
Value Coefficient 95% CI </p>

<p>P 
Value 
Coefficient 95% CI </p>

<p>p 
Value </p>

<p>Age </p>

<p>−0.02 
−0.05 to 0.01 </p>

<p>0.314 </p>

<p>0.00 
0.03 to 0.03 0.919 </p>

<p>−0.01 
−0.05 to 0.04 </p>

<p>0.778 </p>

<p>0.01 
−0.01 to 0.04 0.340 </p>

<p>Mother tongue Bengali=1; other=2 </p>

<p>0.09 
−0.68 to 0.87 </p>

<p>0.812 </p>

<p>−0.13 
−0.74 to 0.48 0.678 </p>

<p>−0.13 
−1.15 to 0.89 </p>

<p>0.804 </p>

<p>0.29 
−0.36 to 0.93 0.381 </p>

<p>Religion 
Hindu=1; Islam=2 </p>

<p>−0.71 
−1.97 to 0.54 </p>

<p>0.264 </p>

<p>0.37 
−0.81 to 1.56 0.537 </p>

<p>−0.92 
−2.38 to 0.53 </p>

<p>0.215 </p>

<p>0.67 
−0.37 to 1.70 0.208 </p>

<p>Social caste </p>

<p>General=1; SC/ST/ </p>

<p>OBC=2 </p>

<p>0.21 
−0.30 to 0.73 </p>

<p>0.413 </p>

<p>−0.08 
−0.49 to 0.33 0.696 </p>

<p>0.51 
−0.14 to 1.15 </p>

<p>0.127 </p>

<p>−0.09 
−0.51 to 0.34 0.683 </p>

<p>Marital status Yes=1; no=2 </p>

<p>0.61 
−0.14 to 1.35 </p>

<p>0.111 </p>

<p>0.04 
−0.49 to 0.57 0.891 </p>

<p>0.54 
−0.46 to 1.55 </p>

<p>0.291 </p>

<p>0.28 
−0.31 to 0.87 0.354 </p>

<p>Education </p>

<p>Literate=1; 
illiterate=2 </p>

<p>−0.51 
−1.27 to 0.25 </p>

<p>0.187 </p>

<p>0.17 
−0.50 to 0.85 0.618 </p>

<p>−0.63 
−1.57 to 0.31 </p>

<p>0.187 </p>

<p>0.09 
−0.51 to 0.69 0.758 </p>

<p>Work type </p>

<p>Non-manual=1; </p>

<p>manual=2 </p>

<p>−0.24 
−0.83 to 0.36 </p>

<p>0.432 </p>

<p>−0.03 
−0.50 to 0.43 0.890 </p>

<p>−0.21 
−1.06 to 0.65 </p>

<p>0.637 </p>

<p>−0.20 
−0.71 to 0.31 0.437 </p>

<p>Working 
hours/day </p>

<p>8=1; &gt;8=2 </p>

<p>0.35 
−0.53 to 1.22 </p>

<p>0.436 </p>

<p>−0.38 
−1.02 to 0.27 0.254 </p>

<p>0.46 
−0.60 to 1.52 </p>

<p>0.395 </p>

<p>−0.09 
−0.77 to 0.59 0.804 </p>

<p>Salary/month 
≥5395 INR=1; 
&lt;5395 INR=2 </p>

<p>0.09 
−0.47 to 0.64 </p>

<p>0.754 </p>

<p>0.34 
−0.09 to 0.77 0.122 </p>

<p>0.38 
−0.47 to 1.23 </p>

<p>0.382 </p>

<p>0.07 
−0.47 to 0.61 0.796 </p>

<p>Total duration 
of work </p>

<p>0.01 
−0.01 to 0.03 </p>

<p>0.242 </p>

<p>0.00 
−0.01 to 0.01 0.898 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.00 to 0.05 </p>

<p>0.074 </p>

<p>0.01 
0.00 to 0.02 0.154 </p>

<p>Smoking </p>

<p>No=1; yes=2 </p>

<p>0.36 
−0.15 to 0.87 </p>

<p>0.164 </p>

<p>0.15 
−0.25 to 0.55 0.474 </p>

<p>0.24 
−0.40 to 0.89 </p>

<p>0.456 </p>

<p>0.00 
−0.44 to 0.45 0.985 </p>

<p>Smokeless 
tobacco </p>

<p>No=1; yes=2 </p>

<p>−0.16 
−0.65 to 0.33 </p>

<p>0.533 </p>

<p>0.06 
−0.34 to 0.46 0.767 </p>

<p>−0.3 </p>

<p>−0.90 to 0.31 </p>

<p>0.335 </p>

<p>−0.16 
−0.51 to 0.20 0.388 </p>

<p>Alcohol 
drinking </p>

<p>No=1; yes=2 </p>

<p>0.35 
−0.18 to 0.87 </p>

<p>0.197 </p>

<p>0.19 
−0.22 to 0.59 0.373 </p>

<p>0.39 
−0.29 to 1.07 </p>

<p>0.266 </p>

<p>0.18 
−0.26 to 0.62 0.425 </p>

<p>House type </p>

<p>Pucca/semipucca=1; </p>

<p>kachcha=2 </p>

<p>0.03 
−0.46 to 0.52 </p>

<p>0.901 </p>

<p>0.24 
−0.15 to 0.63 0.226 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>−0.30 to 1.11 </p>

<p>0.266 </p>

<p>0.39 
−0.03 to 0.80 0.068 </p>

<p>People in a 
room </p>

<p>&lt;3=1; </p>

<p>≥3=2 </p>

<p>0.00 
−0.53 to 0.53 </p>

<p>0.998 </p>

<p>0.06 
−0.37 to 0.49 0.783 </p>

<p>−0.1 </p>

<p>−0.74 to 0.54 </p>

<p>0.759 </p>

<p>−0.1 
−0.49 to 0.28 0.591 </p>

<p>Pet animal </p>

<p>No=1; yes=2 </p>

<p>−0.04 
−0.53 to 0.45 </p>

<p>0.864 </p>

<p>0.13 
−0.26 to 0.52 0.524 </p>

<p>0.12 
−0.50 to 0.75 </p>

<p>0.697 </p>

<p>0.01 
−0.36 to 0.39 0.951 </p>

<p>Domestic 
cooking fuel </p>

<p>Cleaner fuel=1; 
biomass fuel=2 </p>

<p>−0.53 </p>

<p>−1.04 to 
−0.03 0.039 </p>

<p>0.26 
−0.14 to 0.67 0.199 </p>

<p>−0.76 </p>

<p>−1.46 to 
−0.06 0.034 </p>

<p>−0.15 
−0.59 to 0.28 0.493 </p>

<p>Kitchen </p>

<p>Yes=1; no=2 </p>

<p>0.12 
−0.44 to 0.67 </p>

<p>0.686 </p>

<p>0.41 
−0.03 to 0.84 0.066 </p>

<p>0.00 
−0.70 to 0.70 </p>

<p>0.999 </p>

<p>0.19 
−0.22 to 0.61 0.357 </p>

<p>Chimney/ 
exhaust fan </p>

<p>Yes=1; no=2 </p>

<p>−0.23 
−1.08 to 0.62 </p>

<p>0.590 </p>

<p>0.35 
−0.29 to 1.00 0.281 </p>

<p>−0.06 
−1.13 to 1.01 </p>

<p>0.913 </p>

<p>0.39 
−0.23 to 1.01 0.214 </p>

<p>Family history No=1; yes=2 </p>

<p>0.40 
−0.21 to 1.00 </p>

<p>0.198 </p>

<p>0.47 
0.01 to 0.94 0.047 </p>

<p>0.08 
−0.62 to 0.78 </p>

<p>0.825 </p>

<p>0.43 
0.02 to 0.83 0.039 </p>

<p>Personal 
history </p>

<p>No=1; yes=2 </p>

<p>1.66 
0.99 to 2.33 &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>1.14 
0.84 to 1.44 &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>1.76 
1.04 to 2.47 &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>1.19 
0.83 to 1.54 &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Health 
insurance </p>

<p>No=1; yes=2 </p>

<p>0.00 
−0.62 to 0.63 </p>

<p>0.995 </p>

<p>0.33 
−0.15 to 0.82 0.181 </p>

<p>−0.06 
−0.82 to 0.69 </p>

<p>0.870 </p>

<p>−0.05 
−0.53 to 0.43 0.846 </p>

<p>*Work type: n=257. 
SC, scheduled caste; ST, scheduled tribe; OBC, other backward class; INR, Indian rupees. </p>

<p>Chattopadhyay K, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e007084. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007084 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>plant workers are lacking. In our study, the SGRQ total 
score distribution was positively skewed-the mean (SD) 
was 7.7 (14.5) and the median (IQR) was 0.9 (9.0). This 
was also found in the Japanese industrial workers study 
(aged above 40 years)-the mean (SD) score was 6.4 
(5.7), and the median score was 5.3. 10 The mean (SD) 
score was 8.4 (11.3) and 7 (7) in studies conducted 
among the Spanish general population aged 40-69 years 
and among British people aged 17-80 years with no 
respiratory diseases, respectively. 8 9 Undesirably, the 
maximum score was high (observed range 0-86.6) in 
our study. This was consistent with the Spanish study 
(observed range 0-83.4). 9 The maximum score was 
better among the Japanese industrial workers (51.5). 10 
The best possible respiratory health status was reported 
by only 46.9% of workers. In the Spanish study, a lower 
percentage of participants (21.1%) reported the best 
possible respiratory health status. This could be due to 
the fact that the Spanish study knowingly included a 
high proportion of individuals with respiratory diseases 
and they were comparatively much older (aged 40-
69 years). 9 In the Japanese study, 8.9% of participants 
reported the best possible respiratory health status, and 
again the participants were comparatively much older 
(aged above 40 years). 10 Although the SGRQ is con-
structed in such a way that a score of zero indicates the 
best possible respiratory health status, even people who 
do not suffer from respiratory diseases will very rarely 
score the minimum on all the items. 9 10 In addition, it is 
assumed that the SGRQ measures specifically the 
respiratory health status impact of respiratory diseases; 
however, it may also reflect the impact of other 
comorbidities. 22 Psychological factors (such as anxiety 
and depression) negatively influence the respiratory 
health status, and previous studies have shown a signifi-
cant association between psychological factors and the 
SGRQ score in people with respiratory diseases. 23 24 
In the unadjusted model, a higher SGRQ total score 
(or worse respiratory health status) was associated with 
cleaner domestic cooking fuel and personal history of 
any respiratory disease in case of frequency; and family 
history of any respiratory disease and personal history in 
case of severity. Independent predictors of worse respira-
tory health status were the same. Considering the points 
that McFadden's pseudo R 2 tends to be smaller than R 2 
and values from 0.20 to 0.40 indicate an excellent model 
fit, 25 McFadden's pseudo R 2 value of 0.14 in our study 
indicates a satisfactory model fit. The Spanish general 
population study found older age, lower education and 
manual work to be associated with worse respiratory 
health status (in unadjusted models). After adjustment, 
this study found respiratory diseases, smoking, older age 
and lower education to be associated with worse respira-
tory health status. 9 In our study, participants with a per-
sonal history had worse respiratory health status. This is 
consistent with another study conducted among the 
same population, where participants with a personal 
history had worse health-related quality-of-life (measured </p>

<p>using the EuroQol-visual analogue scale (EQ-VAS)) as 
compared with those with no such issue. 26 This is also 
consistent with the Japanese industrial workers study 
where they found an association with chronic obstructive 
pulmonary disease. 10 Our study showed the significance 
of personal history and of family history in someone's 
respiratory health status. We found an association 
between cleaner domestic cooking fuel and worse 
respiratory health status. This association is quite con-
flicting, and one would expect the association between 
biomass domestic cooking fuel and worse respiratory 
health status. It is possible that this finding was the result 
of other confounding factors not adjusted for in the 
model. This finding deserves further examination. 
This study has a number of strengths and weaknesses. 
To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to 
explore respiratory health status of coal-based sponge 
iron plant workers. All the workers who were 
approached to participate in the study responded 
(100% response rate and thus no non-respondents). 
This indicates that the data collection methodology was 
appropriate and there is more certainty in the study 
findings (ie, it is more likely that the results are repre-
sentative of the population). In terms of generalisability, 
the study findings could be valid in settings with similar 
populations and healthcare systems (such as in other 
South-Asian countries). The standard steps in question-
naire development (design, translation and pretesting) 
were followed to ensure the validity and reliability of the 
questionnaire (section I). Respiratory health status meas-
urement is subjective to participants, and thus a valid 
and reliable tool (SGRQ in English, Bengali and Hindi) 
was used. The fieldworkers used a standardised protocol 
for data collection. The fieldworkers and the partici-
pants belonged to the same culture, which minimised 
the scope for cultural bias in the study. Missing data 
could lead to bias, but it was extremely low in this study. 
The analyses included a sample with missing values for 
the variables. Participants who were absent from work 
on the dates of the survey were excluded, and this 
absence from work could be due to poor respiratory 
health status, which could have underestimated the 
worse respiratory health status. The response of partici-
pants could have been influenced by the context, and 
individual and contextual psychosocial work factors are 
known to influence the perception of the environment 
at work. 27 28 Most of the data were self-reported, and 
recall error could have been a problem. Medical records 
might be a more reliable measure (for the presence/ 
history of any respiratory disease), but these were not 
available/accessible in the study area. Lung function or 
other diagnostic tests could have been used, but the aim 
of the study was to explore workers' perception of 
respiratory health (respiratory health status) and not to 
diagnose any disease condition. However, these tests 
could be used in future studies, which would cross-check 
our study findings and would provide a complete 
picture of the scenario. The aim of the study was to </p>



<p>Chattopadhyay K, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e007084. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007084 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>explore these workers' respiratory health status, and 
there was no control group in the study. Similar research 
needs to be conducted among coal-based sponge iron 
plant employees working in other parts of India and 
other countries to enhance the generalisability of our 
study results. As this was a cross-sectional study, it was not 
possible to determine the causal association between dif-
ferent variables and respiratory health status. A long-
term, longitudinal study should be conducted among 
these coal-based sponge iron factory workers to assess 
the impact of various factors (these as well as other 
potential factors) on their respiratory health status. 
A good example would be to have a cohort study com-
paring coal-based sponge iron factory workers with 
other types of factory workers (healthy worker effect), 
rather than with the general population. 
In conclusion, less than half of the coal-based sponge 
iron plant workers in Barjora have the best possible 
respiratory health status. The predictors of worse respira-
tory health status were identified. The study findings 
could be taken into consideration in future interven-
tional studies aimed at improving the respiratory health 
status of these workers. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors thank the funding agency, Suresh Chandra 
Chattopadhyay, the fieldworkers, Barjora BDO, the factory directors and the 
participants. </p>

<p>Contributors KC designed the study. KC, CC and EK conducted the study. KC 
wrote the first draft of the manuscript. All authors revised for important 
intellectual content and approved the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding This study was funded by a grant from the Blacksmith Institute, 
USA. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Patient consent Obtained. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Approval was received from the Barjora Block Development 
Office Committee (the committee was based on the Indian Council of Medical 
Research Ethical Guidelines for Biomedical Research on Human Participants, 
2006). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>