<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4754077" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background-Changes in episodic memory are common early in Parkinson's disease (PD) and 
may be a risk factor for future cognitive decline. Although medial temporal lobe (MTL) memory 
and frontostriatal (FS) executive systems are thought to play different roles in distinct components 
of episodic memory impairment in PD, no study has investigated whether different aspects of 
memory functioning are differentially associated with MTL and FS volumes in nondemented 
patients without mild cognitive impairment (PD-woMCI). </p>

<p>Objectives-The present study investigated MRI markers of different facets of memory 
functioning in 48 PD-woMCI patients and 42 controls. </p>

<p>Methods-Regional volumes were measured in structures comprising the MTL and FS systems 
and then correlated with key indices of memory from the California Verbal Learning Test. </p>

<p>Results-In PD-woMCI patients, memory was impaired only for verbal learning, which was not 
associated with executive, attention/working memory, or visuospatial functioning. Despite an 
absence of cortical atrophy, smaller right MTL volumes in patients were associated with poorer 
verbal learning, long delayed free recall, long delayed cued recall, and recognition memory hits 
and false positives. Smaller right pars triangularis (inferior frontal) volumes were also associated 
with poorer long delayed cued recall and recognition memory hits. These relationships were not 
found in controls. </p>

<p>Conclusions-The findings indicate that MTL volumes are sensitive to subtle changes in almost 
all facets of memory in PD-woMCI, whereas FS volumes are sensitive only to memory 
performances in cued-testing formats. </p>

<p>This article is published online with Open Access and distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-
Commercial License. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Deborah L. Harrington, Ph.D., VA San Diego Healthcare System 116A-13, 3350 La Jolla Village Drive, San 
Diego CA 92161, USA. Tel.: +1 858-552-8585/Ext. 7851; dharrington@ucsd.edu. 
CONFLICT OF INTEREST 
The authors have no conflict of interest to report. </p>

<p>U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs </p>

<p>Public Access Author manuscript </p>

<p>J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>Published in final edited form as: 
J Parkinsons Dis. 2015 November 21; 5(4): 971-981. doi:10.3233/JPD-150652. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Keywords </p>

<p>Parkinson's disease; magnetic resonance imaging; memory; neuropsychology; medial temporal 
lobe system; frontostriatal system; cognitive functions </p>

<p>INTRODUCTION </p>

<p>Cognitive impairments are found early in the course of Parkinson's disease (PD), and up to 
80% of patients show dementia 8-years later [1]. Dementia lowers the quality of life for 
patients and caregivers alike, and portends a greater risk of nursing home placement and 
mortality [2, 3]. Markers of cognitive functioning in PD are needed that predate the onset of 
mild cognitive impairment (MCI). Once markers are identified, they can then be studied 
longitudinally to chart the rate of disease progression and determine which markers predict 
risk for dementia. </p>

<p>Episodic memory impairment is common early in PD and may be a risk factor for future 
cognitive decline [4, 5]. However, neuroanatomical substrates of subtle changes in memory 
that predate cognitive impairment have not been comprehensively studied in nondemented 
PD patients without mild cognitive impairment (PD-woMCI) using recent criteria [6]. Most 
investigations have almost solely focused on the relationship of memory to hippocampus 
and entorhinal cortex morphometry, owing to their roles in memory encoding and 
consolidation. Cross-sectional studies of combined samples of PD patients with and without 
cognitive impairment typically report that medial temporal lobe (MTL) volumes correlate 
with various aspects of verbal memory including delayed recall and recognition memory [7- 13]. However, frontostriatal (FS) networks also mediate executive aspects of episodic 
memory, which govern attention and working memory and self-initiated search and 
monitoring strategies at encoding and retrieval [14, 15]. Recently, our group found that 
poorer long delayed free recall in nondemented PD was associated with reduced MTL and 
FS volumes in both hemispheres, suggesting that memory and executive systems are 
associated with early, subtle memory changes [16]. This study may have included some 
patients with MCI, thereby preventing an examination of the systems associated with 
memory functioning before mild cognitive impairment [6]. </p>

<p>In clinical evaluations of PD, different components of verbal memory are typically 
examined including learning, retention, retrieval, and the types of errors during recall. It is 
traditionally believed that impaired learning in nondemented PD is largely due to inefficient 
use of strategies during encoding because of FS dysfunction [17]. For example, one study 
reported that poorer verbal learning in PD patients with and without MCI was not related to 
hippocampal atrophy [7], speculating that verbal encoding deficits, secondary to inefficient 
use of learning strategies, may be related to changes in the FS system, which was not 
examined. To our knowledge, no study has directly tested this hypothesis by correlating 
multiple facets of verbal learning and memory with FS volumes. </p>

<p>Another important distinction is whether a patient has retention or retrieval difficulties. It is 
widely believed that PD patients exhibit retrieval deficits. Indeed, nondemented PD patients 
demonstrate impaired free recall, yet memory performance can improve to normal or near </p>

<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. 
Page 2 </p>

<p>J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>normal levels when cues or yes/no recognition testing formats are used [18-20], which 
decrease retrieval demands. This memory profile is attributed to deficient retrieval rather 
than retention of stored information, ostensibly due to FS dysfunction, which disrupts 
strategies for search and retrieval of information [18]. In contrast, patients with MTL 
damage (e.g., Alzheimer's disease) show rapid rates of forgetting and fail to benefit from 
cueing and recognition testing, owing to impaired consolidation secondary to hippocampal 
atrophy [18, 21]. </p>

<p>However, nondemented PD patients can present with different patterns of memory 
impairment [22-26]. Our group found retrieval deficits (i.e., significantly better recognition 
memory than free recall) in about 1/3 of PD patients [23]. The remaining patients did not 
benefit from recognition memory testing due to increased endorsement of non-list items as 
targets (false positives), presumably related to impaired inhibition secondary to FS 
dysfunction. It is also possible that lack of benefit from recognition memory testing in PD 
was related to impaired encoding/consolidation due to hippocampal dysfunction. This 
demonstrates the importance of assessing multiple components of memory. Moreover, while 
assumptions are frequently made in clinical practice about the different roles of FS and MTL 
systems in distinct components of episodic memory impairment, no study has investigated 
whether various aspects of memory functioning are differentially associated with MTL and 
FS volumes in PD-woMCI. This is an important question because neuroanatomical 
correlates of different facets of memory may suggest MRI markers of future memory 
decline, which could then be studied longitudinally to determine if they are risk factors for 
dementia. </p>

<p>The current study sought to elucidate MRI markers of subtle changes in different aspects of 
episodic verbal memory in PD-woMCI, which was evaluated by a widely used test 
(California Verbal Learning Test II-Short Form) [27]. We focused on measures that are 
routinely used in clinical assessments of PD [27] and are theoretically relevant, namely 
indices of learning, long delay free recall, retention, cued retrieval (cued recall relative to 
free recall), and recognition retrieval (recognition memory relative to free recall). These 
measures were correlated with regional volumes comprising the MTL memory and the FS 
executive systems. We hypothesized that poorer verbal learning would most strongly 
correlate with FS volumes, secondary to difficulties in executive aspects of encoding. We 
also hypothesized that the relative improvement in delayed recall with cued recall and 
recognition memory formats (cued retrieval and recognition retrieval indices) would best 
correlate with FS volumes, since these indices emphasize executive aspects of retrieval. In 
contrast, long delay free recall and retention were predicted to correlate most strongly with 
MTL volumes, owing to their emphasis on memory consolidation. </p>

<p>METHOD </p>

<p>Participants </p>

<p>The University of California San Diego Human Research Protections Program approved this 
study. Study participants included 48 PD-woMCI (see definition for MCI below) and 42 
healthy controls (HC) who were spouses of patients or community volunteers. Participants 
provided written informed consent prior to study procedures. Thirty-eight of the HC </p>

<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. </p>

<p>
J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>participants and 43 of the PD participants partially overlapped with the cohort from our prior 
study that investigated associations between individual differences in volumes of four brain 
systems and performances in five cognitive domains [16]. Exclusion criteria included metal 
in the head, neurological diagnoses other than PD, psychiatric diagnoses, MCI, history of 
alcohol or substance abuse, positive MRI findings (e.g., infarcts, clinically significant 
vascular disease), and use of anticholinergics or cognitive medications (e.g., donepezil). PD 
participants met the PD United Kingdom Brain Bank Criteria. All PD patients were taking 
levodopa or levodopa combination therapy and were tested while on medication. The groups 
did not differ in gender composition, years of education, age, or Mini-Mental Status Exam 
(MMSE) scores (Table 1). Motor symptoms were assessed using Part III of the Unified 
Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS) and the Hoehn and Yahr scale. Motor symptom 
severity and disease duration (Table 1) were similar to other PD-woMCI samples [28-31]. </p>

<p>PD-woMCI criteria </p>

<p>PD participants were excluded if they met criteria for PD-MCI based on a modified (no 
language test) Level 1Movement Disorders Society task force criteria [6], which was 
assessed using four cognitive domains: 1) Executive function: Letter Fluency (number 
correct) from the Delis Kaplan Executive Function System (DKEFS), 2) Verbal memory: 
CLVT long delayed free recall (total correct), 3) Attention/working memory: Digit Span 
Backward (Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale -III; total correct), and 4) Visuospatial 
function: Benton Judgment of Line Orientation test (JLOT; version V, number correct out of 
15 items). Although we did not have a measure of language, as recommended for a Level 1 
PD-MCI diagnosis, language skills are typically spared in patients without deficits in other 
cognitive domains [28]. Owing to the high educational level of our sample, raw scores for 
the cognitive tests were transformed to z-scores based on the HC group mean and standard 
deviation [6]. PD-MCI was diagnosed if a patient demonstrated a z-score ≤−1.5 on at least 2 
neuropsychological measures. Of 56 patients in the original sample, 48 met criteria for PD-
woMCI. There were no significant differences between PD-woMCI and HC groups in 
executive functioning, attention/working memory, visuospatial function, or verbal memory 
(long delay free recall) (Tables 1 and 2). </p>

<p>Memory assessment </p>

<p>The California Verbal Learning Test -Second Edition Short Form (CVLT) [27] was used to 
assess memory. CVLT variables were first normalized to the HC group by calculating z-
scores based on the HC group mean/standard deviation. We then calculated the following 
CVLT indices using the z-scores: 1) learning [number of words recalled on learning trials 
1-4], 2) long delay free recall [number of words recalled on the long delay free recall trial], 
3) retention [number of words recalled on trial 4 -number of words on long delay free 
recall], 4) cued retrieval [cued recall d prime (i.e., a discriminability index) [27] -long 
delay free recall] and 5) recognition retrieval [recognition d prime -long delay free recall] 
[23, 32]. Analyses were also conducted for sub-measures of the retrieval indices. Sub-
measures comprising the cued retrieval index included long delay cued recall [number of 
target words recalled] and cued recall intrusions [number of non-list words recalled]. Sub-
measures comprising the recognition retrieval index included recognition memory hits 
[number of target words recognized] and false positives [number of non-list items endorsed]. </p>

<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. </p>

<p>
J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Higher values on learning, long delayed free recall, long delay cued recall, and hits indicate 
better performance. Higher values on retention, cued retrieval, recognition retrieval, false 
positives, and cued recall intrusions indicate worse performance. </p>

<p>MRI procedures </p>

<p>High resolution T1-weighted anatomic images were acquired on a GE 3T Excite MRI 
system. Automated reconstruction and volumetric segmentation of images were conducted 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">FreeSurfer</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">http://surfer.nmr.mgh.harvard.edu</rs>/), which is widely used and 
provides accurate renderings of regional volumes without rater bias. We used an imaging 
protocol that maximizes differentiation of the white and gray matter boundary (3D spoiled 
gradient-recalled at steady state, TE 3.0 ms, TR 7.8 ms, TI 600, 8° flip angle, NEX 1, 1-mm 
axial slice thickness, FOV 25.6 cm, 256 × 256 matrix). MRIs for each participant were 
motion corrected, normalized for intensity in homogeneities, and transformed to Talairach 
space. Non-brain tissue was removed using a hybrid watershed/surface deformation 
procedure, subcortical structures were segmented, and further intensity normalization was 
conducted. This was followed by white-matter segmentation, tessellation of the gray-white 
matter boundary, and automated topology correction. Finally, surface deformation following 
intensity gradients optimally placed the gray/white and gray/cerebrospinal fluid borders at 
the location where the greatest shift in intensity defines the transition to the other tissue 
class. The cerebral cortex was parcellated into 34 gyral-based regions in each hemisphere 
based on the Desikan-Killiany atlas [33]. Subcortical structures were delineated by an 
algorithm that examines variations in voxel intensities and spatial relationships. Anatomical 
accuracy of the segmentations was manually verified. To account for differences in head 
size, volumes for each region were divided by intracranial volume (ICV). </p>

<p>Regions of interest </p>

<p>Morphometric analyses were conducted on a subset of regions that were the focus of our 
hypotheses (Fig. 1, left panel), namely the FS executive system (frontal cortical regions 
including caudal middle frontal gyrus, rostral middle frontal gyrus, superior frontal gyrus, 
areas of the inferior frontal gyrus including pars triangularis, pars opercularis, pars orbitalis, 
and striatal regions including caudate, putamen) and the MTL memory system (temporal 
pole, entorhinal cortex, parahippocampus, hippocampus) [16]. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Z-scores for memory measures were residualized by calculating the residuals from the 
regression of age and gender onto each brain volume for each group separately. Since 
levodopa dosage and other clinical variables (i.e., disease severity, motor symptom severity 
on the UPDRS Part III) could have an effect on cognition in PD, correlations were 
performed between CVLT variables and clinical variables. The CVLT variables did not 
significantly correlate with the UPDRS or disease duration. (p &gt; 0.05). However, CVLT 
learning (r = −.33, p = 0.011) and retention (r = −.31, p = 0.02) significantly correlated with 
levodopa dosage equivalence, indicating that higher levodopa dosage equivalences were 
associated with poorer learning and retention. Therefore, residuals from the regression of 
levodopa equivalencies, age, and gender onto CVLT learning and CVLT retention were </p>

<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. </p>

<p>
J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>calculated for each group separately. For all other CVLT variables, residuals from the 
regression of age and gender onto these CVLT variables were calculated for each group 
separately. For most variables, Pearson correlations were conducted between the residuals 
for the CVLT variables and regional volumes, separately for each group. Spearman rank 
correlations were conducted for cued recall intrusions and recognition memory hits and false 
positives due to skewed distributions of measures. Owing to our a priori hypotheses, which 
were driven by previous results [16], a more stringent uncorrected statistical threshold of 
p≤0.01 was adopted in lieu of overly conservative adjustments [34]. This threshold was 
chosen in an attempt to strike a balance between Type I and Type II errors. Nonetheless, the 
results should be interpreted with caution. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Memory performance </p>

<p>T tests and Mann-Whitney U tests (cued recall intrusions, recognition memory hits and false 
positives) compared the groups on the CVLT variables (Table 2). The PD-woMCI group 
performed significantly worse than the HC group on learning (p = 0.008). A repeated-
measure ANOVA showed that patients' rate of learning was similar to that of the HC group 
across all 4 learning trials (nonsignificant group X trial interaction; mean (SD) for the slope 
of the learning function was 0.80 (.43) and 0.78 (.38) for the PD-woMCI and HC groups, 
respectively). Thus, verbal learning was poorer in the PD-woMCI group, irrespective of the 
learning trial. In patients, learning was not correlated (p &gt; 0.20) with measures of executive 
functioning, attention, or visuospatial functioning (Table 1). Partial correlations, adjusting 
for levodopa dosage equivalence, also showed no significant associations between learning 
and measures of executive functioning, attention, or visuospatial functioning. Group 
differences were not found on any other memory measures. Importantly, the range of values 
was more restricted for retention, cued retrieval, cued recall intrusions, and recognition 
retrieval relative to all other measures. Additionally, a cued retrieval-deficit profile (z-score 
&gt;1.5 difference between cued recall d prime and long delay free recall) was found in only 
8% (n = 4) of PD-woMCI and 2% (n = 1) controls. A recognition retrieval-deficit profile (z-
score &gt;1.5 difference between recognition memory d prime and long delay free recall) was 
found in 14.5% (n = 7) of PD-woMCI and 5% (n = 2) of controls. </p>

<p>Group differences in regional volumes </p>

<p>Group comparisons (t-tests) showed right putamen volume loss (HC: M= 0.35, SD = 0.05; 
PD-woMCI: M= 0.33, SD = 0.04; p = 0.005) and a nonsignificant trend for left putamen 
volume loss (HC: M= 0.36, SD = 0.06; PD-woMCI: M= 0.34, SD = 0.04; p = 0.02) in the 
PD-woMCI group. No other group differences were found in MTL/FS volumes. </p>

<p>Correlation of regional volumes with different components of memory </p>

<p>Figure 1 (right panel) and Table 3 display the regional maps and significant correlation 
coefficients between brain volumes and performances on CVLT variables for the PD-
woMCI group. Figure 2 shows scatter plots of the significant correlations (age and gender 
adjusted residuals). In the PD-woMCI group, worse learning (trials 1 to 4) correlated with 
smaller right entorhinal, right parahippocampus, right hippocampus, and left temporal pole </p>

<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. </p>

<p>
J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>volumes. Poorer long delayed free recall correlated with smaller right parahippocampus 
volume. Brain volumes did not correlate with retention or the long delayed cued retrieval 
and recognition retrieval indices. As for submeasures of cued retrieval, poorer long delayed 
cued recall correlated with smaller right pars triangularis, parahippocampus, and 
hippocampus volumes. Cued recall intrusions did not correlate with brain volumes. As for 
sub-measures of recognition retrieval, greater hits correlated with larger right pars 
triangularis and hippocampus volumes, whereas more false positives correlated with smaller 
right hippocampus volumes. No significant correlations were found in the HC group. Brain 
volumes for regions that significantly correlated with various memory variables are 
displayed in Table 1. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our results principally linked subtle changes in different components of memory functioning 
in PD-woMCI with volumes of the MTL. This was found even for measures expected to 
emphasize FS functioning, namely learning and recognition memory false positives. Our 
results are compatible with emerging studies that reveal interactions between dopamine 
neurotransmission and hippocampal synaptic plasticity in memory [35]. Memory 
impairments that predate or predict dementia are also associated with a loss of cholinergic 
function and the accumulation of Lewy Bodies, amyloid plaques, and neurofibrillary tangles 
[36, 37]. In contrast, we found that FS volumes were only associated with sub-measures of 
the cued retrieval and recognition indices, namely long delayed cued recall and recognition 
memory hits, which correlated with smaller volumes of the right pars triangularis, an 
element of the right-hemisphere ventral-attention system [38]. This is fitting as the ventral 
prefrontal cortex modulates reorienting responses to task-relevant stimuli [38-40], which is 
elicited by cued memory testing formats. These neurocognitive relationships were not found 
in controls, suggesting that they are related to subtle changes in the disease, rather than 
normal aging. </p>

<p>Episodic memory in PD-woMCI was significantly worse than controls only for learning, 
which was not correlated with executive functioning, as it is in cognitively impaired PD 
[18], nor FS volumes. These findings suggest that poorer learning was not related to 
executive aspects of encoding, but rather diminished encoding functions of the MTL. 
Indeed, poorer learning correlated with smaller right-hemisphere hippocampus, 
parahippocampus, and entorhinal cortex volumes and left-hemisphere temporal pole volume, 
unlike other studies [7]. This result is consistent with right-hemisphere MTL mediation of 
verbal learning and integration of contextual information (e.g., recency, novelty, familiarity) 
for encoding and retrieval [41-43]. Long delayed free recall was also associated with 
smaller right parahippocampal volume. The finding that verbal learning and memory were 
associated with mostly right hemisphere, medial temporal lobe volumes was somewhat 
surprising, but is consistent with a study reporting an association between right, but not left 
hippocampal volumes and verbal learning in PD patients without dementia [7]. Future 
studies in larger samples of PD-woMCI should be conducted to further examine this 
intriguing finding. Previously we reported associations between long delay free recall and 
bilateral MTL (right and left hippocampus and entorhinal cortex; left temporal pole) and 
bilateral FS (right and left pars triangularis and pars orbitalis, left superior frontal, right </p>

<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. </p>

<p>
J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>putamen) volumes in nondemented PD [16]. More pervasive bilateral hemispheric 
associations may have been driven by the inclusion of PD-MCI patients, which underscores 
the importance of characterizing MCI status when studying neurocognitive relationships. </p>

<p>As for other primary memory indices, recognition retrieval, cued retrieval, and retention 
were also not impaired in PD-woMCI, nor did they correlate with MTL or FS volumes. 
These findings may relate to the small proportion of PD-woMCI patients who exhibited a 
cued retrieval-deficit (14.5%) or recognition retrieval-deficit (8%) profile. Indeed, the 
retrieval hypothesis has been questioned more recently, since the magnitude of impairment 
in delayed recall and recognition memory is similar in most nondemented PD patients [22- 24], as we found in PD-woMCI. In prior studies, the absence of a benefit in recognition 
memory testing relative to free recall was due to increased false positives on recognition 
testing [23], presumably owing to FS-based disinhibition. However, recognition memory 
false positives and cued recall intrusions were not elevated in our PD-woMCI group, nor 
were these measures related to FS volumes. Altogether, retrieval impairments in PD-woMCI 
were uncommon, which likely rendered correlations between retrieval indices and regional 
volumes insensitive. </p>

<p>Limitations of our study include the high educational levels of many participants, which 
may limit the generalizability of the results. Although a more stringent uncorrected 
statistical threshold of p≤0.01 was adopted in lieu of overly conservative adjustments, future 
studies are needed to validate our findings. Additionally, our level 1 criteria for MCI did not 
include a language assessment, however language is usually intact in PD patients without 
deficits in other cognitive domains [28]. Level 1 criteria also provide less diagnostic 
certainty than level 2 criteria [6, 31]. Thus, larger studies with comprehensive level 2 PD-
MCI diagnosis should be used in future studies to substantiate these findings. Although 
learning did not correlate with our measures of executive, attention, and visuospatial 
functioning, it is possible that other aspects of functioning in these domains not measured in 
this study (e.g., problem solving, cognitive flexibility, visuoconstruction) could be 
associated with poorer learning in PD-woMCI. Another caveat is that functional changes in 
the FS system may be more broadly associated with changes in different facets of memory 
in PD-woMCI than suggested by our results and possibly precede macrostructural changes 
in grey matter [44]. Indeed, though 18-month increases in gray-matter thinning of the caudal 
middle-frontal cortex in PD-woMCI patients was recently found, cortical thinning was not 
associated with performances on global dementia rating scales [45]. Microstructural changes 
in FS fiber pathways could also affect executive functions that support various components 
of memory [46], as well as changes in other pathological processes that alter dopaminergic 
and non-dopaminergic neurotransmitter systems [47]. Nonetheless, structural MRI will 
remain an important marker of cognitive decline as it is sensitive to changes in cognition and 
has advantages over other imaging methods, including its reliability and validation for use in 
clinical settings. </p>

<p>In summary, subtle changes in several different facets of memory in PD-woMCI were 
predominantly associated with MTL volumes, whereas cued retrieval and recognition 
memory were associated with FS volumes. This was found despite an absence of MTL and 
frontal cortex atrophy. Our results build upon emerging evidence linking structural changes </p>

<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. </p>

<p>
J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>in the MTL with memory function in PD-woMCI [7] and risk for future cognitive decline 
[12]. Longitudinal studies underway will directly determine if these associations are markers 
of future memory decline, which if substantiated may help establish cut-off values (e.g., 
smaller MTL and FS volumes combined with poorer memory) that signify a greater risk for 
memory impairment. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank Gabriel Castillo and Jason Reed for their technical support in acquiring and 
analyzing the structural MRI data, Colleen Takahashi for her technical support in the preparation of figures, 
Christopher Fong for his assistance in data collection, and Dr. David Song for referring patients to the study. This 
research was supported by grants from the Department of Veterans Affairs (DLH: CX000146; JVF: CX12004). </p>



<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. </p>

<p>
J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. </p>

<p>
J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. </p>

<p>
J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Fig. 1. </p>

<p>Regional volumes of interest and their association with memory in Parkinson's patients. 1) 
Left panel: Colored areas designate regions of interest (ROI) in the frontostriatal and medial 
temporal systems. ROIs on sagittal surfaces are displayed for one hemisphere, but were 
analyzed for homologous areas of both hemispheres. The caudate/putamen and the 
hippocampus are respectively shown on axial and coronal views. 2) Right panel: Right 
hemisphere cortical (lateral/medial sagittal surfaces) and hippocampus (coronal view) 
volumes that significantly correlated with various memory measures. For CVLT learning 
(top row), the left hemisphere medial surface displays the significant correlation with the 
temporal pole. The p value for correlation coefficients is designated by the color bar; p≤0.01 
(dark blue) and p≤0.005 (light blue). </p>

<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. 
Page 12 </p>

<p>J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Fig. 2. </p>

<p>Scatter plots showing significant correlations between measures of memory and regional 
volumes in Parkinson's patients. For most variables, age and gender adjusted residuals for 
MRI volumes and CVLT measures are plotted. An exception is CVLT learning, for which 
levodopa dosage equivalence, age, and gender adjusted residuals are plotted. Solid and 
dotted lines display the best-fitting linear regression line and 95% confidence intervals. </p>

<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. 
Page 13 </p>

<p>J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. 
Page 14 </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Demographics, disease characteristics, and neuropsychological test performances of participants </p>

<p>Parkinson's (n = 48) Controls (n = 42) 
F 
p </p>

<p>Demographics </p>

<p>Age (years) 
66.9 (7.9) 
66.7 (8.3) 
2.5 
0.12 </p>

<p>Education (years) 
17.2 (3.0) 
17.1 (2.8) 
0.04 0.85 </p>

<p>Gender (M/F) a 
25/23 
21/21 
0.39 0.84 </p>

<p>Mini-Mental Status Exam 
29.0 (1.4) 
29.1 (0.9) 
2.3 
0.14 </p>

<p>Disease Characteristics </p>

<p>Duration of PD (years) 
6.2 (4.6) </p>

<p>UPDRS III 
27.8 (10.0) </p>

<p>Hoehn &amp; Yahr stage </p>

<p>Stage 1/2/2.5/3 (frequency) 
3/15/17/13 </p>

<p>Levodopa dosage equivalence 
678.7 (570.0) </p>

<p>Neuropsychological Tests </p>

<p>Executive: Letter Fluency 
44.5 (10.6) 
48.1 (11.5) 
2.4 
0.13 </p>

<p>Attention/Working Memory: Digit Span Backward 
7.4 (1.8) 
7.8 (2.3) 
0.63 0.43 </p>

<p>Visuospatial: JLOT 
12.0 (2.1) 
12.7 (1.9) 
2.3 
0.13 </p>

<p>Brain Volumes b </p>

<p>R Pars triangularis 
0.27 (0.05) 
0.27 (0.05) 
0.03 0.86 </p>

<p>R Entorhinal 
0.12 (0.03) 
0.13 (0.02) 
1.2 
0.28 </p>

<p>R Parahippocampus 
0.14 (0.02) 
0.14 (0.02) 
1.2 
0.44 </p>

<p>R Hippocampus 
0.25 (0.03) 
0.26 (0.03) 
0.60 0.28 </p>

<p>L Temporal Pole 
0.16 (0.03) 
0.16 (0.03) 
0.38 0.54 </p>

<p>Demographics, disease characteristics, and neuropsychological test performances are presented as the mean (standard deviation) of raw scores. 
Brain volumes for regions that significantly correlated with memory variables in the Parkinson's group are presented. Frequency counts are 
presented for gender and the Hoehn and Yahr stages. </p>

<p>a Chi-square test for group differences. Test statistic in the F column is a chi-square value. </p>

<p>b Brain volumes (mm 3 /ICV mm 3 ) for regions that were significantly correlated with various CVLT measures. </p>

<p>UPDRS = Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale; JLOT = Judgment of Line Orientation; R= right hemisphere; L = left hemisphere. </p>

<p>J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. 
Page 15 </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Performances on the verbal memory measure (CVLT) </p>

<p>Parkinson's </p>

<p>Controls </p>

<p>CVLT Variables 
Mean (SD) Min, Max Mean (SD) Min, Max </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>Learning </p>

<p>27.5 (3.5) </p>

<p>19,35 </p>

<p>29.4 (3.1) </p>

<p>23,35 </p>

<p>7.4 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>Long Delay Free Recall </p>

<p>7.0 (1.8) </p>

<p>3,9 </p>

<p>7.5 (1.4) </p>

<p>4,9 </p>

<p>2.4 </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>Retention </p>

<p>0.8 (1.4) </p>

<p>−2.0,4.0 </p>

<p>0.6 (1.2) </p>

<p>−2.0,3.0 </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>0.69 </p>

<p>Cued Retrieval a </p>

<p>14 (0.8) </p>

<p>−2.2,1.6 </p>

<p>0.0 (0.6) </p>

<p>−1.3,1.5 </p>

<p>0.88 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>Long Delay Cued Recall </p>

<p>7.4 (1.5) </p>

<p>3,9 </p>

<p>7.8 (1.1) </p>

<p>5,9 </p>

<p>2.3 </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>Cued Recall Intrusions b </p>

<p>0.3 (0.6) </p>

<p>0,2 </p>

<p>0.3 (0.7) </p>

<p>0,3 </p>

<p>0.95 </p>

<p>Recognition Retrieval a </p>

<p>0.1 (1.1) </p>

<p>−2.9,2.3 </p>

<p>0.0 (0.9) </p>

<p>−2.2,2.7 </p>

<p>0.14 </p>

<p>0.71 </p>

<p>Hits b </p>

<p>8.6 (0.6) </p>

<p>7,9 </p>

<p>8.6 (0.7) </p>

<p>6,9 </p>

<p>0.76 </p>

<p>False Positives b </p>

<p>1.4 (1.7) </p>

<p>0,6 </p>

<p>0.9 (1.1) </p>

<p>0,5 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>Note: Memory measures are from the California Verbal Learning Test -Short form (CVLT). </p>

<p>a 
CVLT scores are raw scores, except for cued retrieval and recognition retrieval, which are z-scores, since they involved subtraction of measures using different metrics. </p>

<p>b 
Group comparisons used the Mann-Whitney U test due to the skewed distributions of these variables. </p>

<p>J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>VA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Pirogovsky-Turk et al. 
Page 16 </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>Significant correlations between regional frontostriatal and medial temporal lobe volumes and episodic verbal memory performance in the Parkinson's </p>

<p>group </p>

<p>Regions </p>

<p>Learning Long Delay 
Free Recall </p>

<p>Long Delay 
Cued 
Recall </p>

<p>Recognition 
Memory 
Hits </p>

<p>Recognition 
Memory </p>

<p>False Positives </p>

<p>Frontostriatal System </p>

<p>R Pars triangularis </p>

<p>0.33 a </p>

<p>0.35 a </p>

<p>Medial Temporal System </p>

<p>R Entorhinal </p>

<p>0.39 a </p>

<p>R Parahippocampus </p>

<p>0.44 b </p>

<p>0.34 a </p>

<p>0.33 a </p>

<p>0.33 a </p>

<p>R Hippocampus </p>

<p>0.37 b </p>

<p>0.39 b </p>

<p>−0.40 b </p>

<p>L Temporal Pole </p>

<p>0.36 a </p>

<p>Only memory indices that exhibited significant correlations with brain volumes are displayed. Pearson correlation coefficients are reported, except for recognition memory hits and false positives, which are 
Spearman correlation coefficients. R = right hemisphere; L = left hemisphere. </p>

<p>a 
p≤0.01; </p>

<p>b 
p≤0.005. </p>

<p>J Parkinsons Dis. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 February 15. </p>

</text></tei>