<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4492754" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>CS-917 (MB06322) is a selective small compound inhibitor of fructose 1,6-bis-
phosphatase (FBPase), which is expected to be a novel drug for the treatment of 
type 2 diabetes by inhibiting gluconeogenesis. CS-917 is a bisamidate prodrug 
and activation of CS-917 requires a two-step enzyme catalyzed reaction. The 
first-step enzyme, esterase, catalyzes the conversion of CS-917 into the intermedi-
ate form (R-134450) and the second-step enzyme, phosphoramidase, catalyzes 
the conversion of R-134450 into the active form (R-125338). In this study, we 
biochemically purified the CS-917 esterase activity in monkey small intestine and 
liver. We identified cathepsin A (CTSA) and elastase 3B (ELA3B) as CS-917 
esterases in the small intestine by mass spectrometry, whereas we found CTSA 
and carboxylesterase 1 (CES1) in monkey liver. We also purified R-134450 phos-
phoramidase activity in monkey liver and identified sphingomyelin phosphodies-
terase, acid-like 3A (SMPADL3A), as an R-134450 phosphoramidase, which has 
not been reported to have any enzyme activity. Recombinant human CTSA, 
ELA3B, and CES1 showed CS-917 esterase activity and recombinant human 
SMPDL3A showed R-134450 phosphoramidase activity, which confirmed the 
identification of those enzymes. Identification of metabolic enzymes responsible 
for the activation process is the requisite first step to understanding the activa-
tion process, pharmacodynamics and pharmacokinetics of CS-917 at the molecu-
lar level. This is the first identification of a phosphoramidase other than histidine 
triad nucleotide-binding protein (HINT) family enzymes and SMPDL3A might 
generally contribute to activation of the other bisamidate prodrugs. </p>

<p>CS-917 (MB06322) is a selective small molecule inhibitor 
of fructose 1,6-bisphosphate (FBPase) (Erion et al. 2005; 
van Poelje et al. 2007). Inhibition of FBPase will lead to 
the suppression of gluconeogenesis (Yoshida et al. 2008), 
and thus, CS-917 was expected to be a drug for type 2 
diabetes with a novel mode of action. 
CS-917 is a bisamidate prodrug of R-125338, which 
inhibits FBPase in the human liver in a low nano-molar 
range (IC50: 16 nmol/L) (Erion et al. 2005). R-125338 
was designed to target the adenosine monophosphate 
(AMP)-binding site of FBPase using a structure-based 
drug design (Erion et al. 2007). Although R-125338 
showed good FBPase inhibition, its oral bioavailability 
was not sufficient. To improve the oral bioavailability of 
R-125338, CS-917 was designed as a bisamidate prodrug 
of R-125338, which gave us sufficient bioavailability and 
FBPase inhibition in vivo (Dang et al. 2007). 
After oral administration, CS-917 is converted into the 
active form, R-125338, by a two-step enzyme-catalyzed 
reaction (Fig. 1) in rat hepatocytes (Dang et al. 2007) and 
primary human hepatocytes (Erion et al. 2005). In the 
first step, CS-917 is hydrolyzed by an esterase and the 
resultant monoester is spontaneously hydrolyzed to form 
a monoamidate intermediate (R-134450), mainly in the 
first-pass metabolism in the small intestine and liver. 
Then in the second step, the P-N bond of the intermedi-
ate is hydrolyzed by a phosphoramidase to generate the 
active form, R-125338, mainly in the liver. Investigation </p>

<p>of the conversion rate using rat, monkey, and human 
liver homogenates demonstrated that the first esterase-cat-
alyzed step was fast and that the second phosphorami-
dase-catalyzed step was slow and rate-limiting, analogous 
to other phosphoramidase prodrugs (Saboulard et al. 
1999; Beltran et al. 2001). 
Clinical studies showed a good maximum plasma con-
centration and total exposure of R-125338 indicating effi-
cient conversion in humans as expected, although 
bioavailability in humans cannot be calculated due to the 
lack of pharmacokinetic data of intravenous administra-
tion of R-125338 (Walker et al. 2006). A large variability 
in the plasma concentration of CS-917 and R-125338 was 
also observed. Since CS-917 esterase activity in human 
plasma was relatively weak compared to that in the small 
intestine and liver (data not shown), the plasma concen-
tration of CS-917 would be determined by the degree of 
CS-917 hydrolysis in the first-pass metabolism and phos-
phoramidase of the intermediate R-134450 could contrib-
ute to R-125338 variation. 
Phosphoramidate prodrugs have been exploited for the 
delivery of nucleoside monophosphate antiviral and anti-
cancer agents (Abraham et al. 1996; Saboulard et al. 1999; 
Freel Meyers and Borch 2000; Freel Meyers et al. 2000; 
Beltran et al. 2001; Egron et al. 2003), and molecular 
characterization of the activation process of nucleotide 
bisamidate prodrugs has been described recently. Birkus 
et al. (2007) identified cathepsin A (CTSA) as the 
first hydrolysis esterase by biochemical purification 
for GS-7340 and GS-9131, anti-retroviral nucleotide </p>

<p>Intermediate 
CS-917 
(R-134450) </p>

<p>Active form 
(R-125338) </p>

<p>Esterase 
in small intestine and liver 
Non-enzymatic </p>

<p>Phosphoramidase 
in liver </p>

<p>O 
S </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>O 
NH </p>

<p>HN </p>

<p>NH2 </p>

<p>O 
O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O 
S </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>O 
NH </p>

<p>HN </p>

<p>NH2 </p>

<p>OH 
O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O 
S </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>O 
NH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>NH2 </p>

<p>OH 
O </p>

<p>O 
S </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>O 
OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>NH2 </p>

<p>w 
o 
l 
S 
t 
s 
a 
F </p>

<p>FBPase inhibition </p>

<p>Figure 1. Two-step activation of bisamidate prodrug CS-917 to the active form, R-125338. CS-917 is activated into the active form (R-125338) 
by a two-step enzyme-catalyzed reaction after oral administration. In the first step, CS-917 is hydrolyzed by an esterase and the resultant 
monoester is spontaneously hydrolyzed to form a monoamidate intermediate (R-134450) in the small intestine and the liver. In the second step, 
the P-N bond of the R-134450 is hydrolyzed by a phosphoramidase to generate R-125338 in the liver. The first step is observed to be fast and 
the second step is observed to be slow and rate-limiting. </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 2 </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes 
K. Kubota et al. </p>

<p>phosphoramidate prodrugs. In the study of GS-9191, a 
prodrug for human papillomavirus treatment, they also 
found CTSA for the first esterase and contribution of 
both the unidentified enzyme and acid-driven hydrolysis 
for the second P-N bond cleavage (Birkus et al. 2011). 
Murakami et al. demonstrated carboxylesterase 1 (CES1) 
and CTSA involvement for the first ester hydrolysis and 
histidine triad nucleotide-binding protein 1 (HINT1) for 
the second phosphoramidase hydrolysis for PSI-7851, an 
anti-hepatitis C virus nucleotide prodrug (Murakami 
et al. 2010). They also reported CES1, CES2, and CTSA 
for the first hydrolysis and HINT1 for the second hydro-
lysis for the related drug, GS-6620 (Murakami et al. 
2014). These previous studies showed that different 
enzymes were involved from compound to compound. 
To understand the pharmacodynamics/pharmacokinet-
ics of CS-917, including the variability of the plasma con-
centration of R-125338, identification of CS-917 esterase 
and R-134450 phosphoramidase at a molecular level was 
necessary. The structure of CS-917 is different from that 
of those nucleotide bisamidate prodrugs for anti-viral 
treatment, thus there is a possibility of unexpected 
enzymes which contribute to the activation process, 
although these studies provided candidate enzymes. Here, 
we describe successful identifications of both CS-917 
esterase in the small intestine and liver and R-134450 
phosphoramidase in the liver by biochemical purification 
to identify unexpected enzymes. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>CS-917, R-134450, and R-125338 were provided by Drug 
Metabolism and Pharmacokinetics Research Laboratories, 
Sankyo Co. Ltd., and cynomolgus monkey livers and 
small intestines were provided by Pharmacodynamics 
Research Laboratories and Medicinal Safety Research Lab-
oratories, Sankyo Co., Ltd. All experimental procedures 
were performed in accordance with the in-house guideline 
of the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of 
Sankyo Co., Ltd. </p>

<p>Purification of small intestine CS-917 
esterase </p>

<p>All purification procedures were conducted at 4°C and 
the small intestines from 5 monkeys (monkey #1 to #5) 
were separately investigated. Each cynomolgus monkey 
small intestine was minced and homogenized in nine vol-
umes of 10 mmol/L 4-(2-hydroxyethyl)-1-piperazinee-
thanesulfonic acid (HEPES), pH 7.0, containing 0.25 mol/ 
L sucrose and a protease inhibitor cocktail (complete </p>

<p>tablet; Roche Applied Science, Indianapolis, IN, USA) 
using a polytron homogenizer (Kinematica, Luzern, 
Switzerland). The homogenate was filtrated by a few 
sheets of gauze, the filtrate was sonicated by a Bioruptor 
(COSMO BIO, Tokyo, Japan), and the suspension was 
centrifuged at 25,000g for 1 h. To the supernatant, 
ammonium sulfate was added to 20% saturation, which 
was then stirred for 3 h and centrifuged at 18,000g for 
30 min. To the collected supernatant, ammonium sulfate 
was further added to 70% saturation, which was then stir-
red for 12 h and centrifuged at 18,000g for 30 min. The 
collected 
20-70% saturated ammonium sulfate precipitate was 
stored at À80°C until use. 
Ammonium sulfate precipitate equivalent to 12 g of 
monkey small intestines was dissolved in 80 mL of 
20 mmol/L HEPES, pH 7.0, containing 1 mol/L ammo-
nium sulfate, and dialyzed against 2 L of the same buffer. 
The dialyzed sample was centrifuged at 15,000g for 
10 min, and the supernatant was filtrated and loaded 
onto a hydrophobic interaction chromatography (HIC) 
column (HiPrep Butyl 4 FF; GE Healthcare, Pittsburgh, 
PA, USA). The bound proteins were eluted with a linear 
gradient from 1 to 0 mol/L ammonium sulfate in 
20 mmol/L HEPES, pH 7.0. Each fraction was tested for 
CS-917 esterase activity. The CS-917 esterase activity 
formed two peaks (the first active peak and the second 
active peak) in the case of the small intestine from mon-
key #1. 
For the first active peak purification, the active frac-
tions (20 mL) were dialyzed against 2 L of HC buffer 
(20 mmol/L HEPES, pH 7.0, containing 0.1% [w/v] 3-
[(3-cholamidopropyl) dimethylammonio] propanesulfon-
ic acid [CHAPS]). The dialyzed sample was loaded onto 
a dye-affinity column (HiTrap Blue HP 1 mL; GE 
Healthcare) and the bound proteins were eluted with a 
linear gradient of 0-2 mol/L NaCl in HC buffer. The 
active fractions (2 mL) were dialyzed against 1 L of HC 
buffer. The dialyzed sample was loaded onto an anion 
exchange column (Mini Q PC 3.2/3; GE Healthcare), 
and the bound proteins were eluted with a linear gradi-
ent of 0-350 mmol/L NaCl in HC buffer. A portion of 
the active fraction (50 lL) from the Mini Q column 
was loaded onto a gel filtration column (Superdex 200 
PC 3.2/30; GE Healthcare) equilibrated with 20 mmol/L 
HEPES, pH 7.0, containing 150 mmol/L NaCl and 0.1% 
CHAPS. 
For the second active peak purification, the active frac-
tions (20 mL) were dialyzed against 10 mmol/L sodium 
phosphate, pH 6.8, containing 0.1% CHAPS. The dialyzed 
sample was loaded onto a hydroxylapatite column 
(CHT2-I; Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA) and 
the bound proteins were eluted with a linear gradient of </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 3 </p>

<p>K. Kubota et al. 
Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes </p>

<p>10-500 mmol/L sodium phosphate, pH 6.8, containing 
0.1% CHAPS. The active fractions (2 mL) were dialyzed 
against 1 L of HC buffer. The dialyzed sample was loaded 
onto an anion exchange column (Mini Q PC 3.2/3) and 
the bound proteins were eluted with a linear gradient of 
0-350 mmol/L NaCl in HC buffer. A portion of the 
active fraction (50 lL) from the Mini Q column was 
loaded onto a gel filtration column (Superdex 200 PC 
3.2/30; GE Healthcare) equilibrated with 20 mmol/L HE-
PES, pH 7.0, containing 150 mmol/L NaCl and 0.1% 
CHAPS. 
Ten microliters of the fractions around the active frac-
tions were loaded onto sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacryl-
amide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) gel (5-20% gel; 
Bio-Rad Laboratories) under reducing conditions, and the 
gel was stained with a fluorescent dye (Flamingo gel stain; 
Bio-Rad Laboratories). The band intensity on the stained 
gel was quantified using a fluorescent scanner (Molecular 
Imager FX; Bio-Rad Laboratories). </p>

<p>Purification of liver CS-917 esterase </p>

<p>All purification procedures were conducted at 4°C. A 
monkey liver homogenate was prepared as described 
above, as a small intestine homogenate. Twenty to seventy 
percent saturated ammonium sulfate precipitation of the 
cytosolic fraction was collected and stored at À80°C until 
use. Ammonium sulfate precipitate equivalent to 11 g of 
monkey liver was dissolved in 80 mL of 20 mmol/L 
HEPES, pH 7.0, containing 1 mol/L ammonium sulfate, 
and dialyzed against 2 L of the same buffer. The dialyzed 
sample was centrifuged at 15,000g for 10 min, and the 
supernatant was filtrated and loaded onto an HIC column 
(HiPrep Butyl 4 FF; GE Healthcare). The bound proteins 
were eluted with a linear gradient from 1 to 0 mol/L 
ammonium sulfate in 20 mmol/L HEPES, pH 7.0. Each 
fraction was tested for CS-917 esterase activity. The 
CS-917 esterase activity formed two peaks (the first active 
peak and the second active peak). 
Each active peak was separately purified further using 
the same purification procedures. The active fractions 
(20 mL) were dialyzed against 20 mmol/L HEPES, pH 
7.0. The dialyzed sample was loaded onto a dye-affinity 
column (HiTrap Blue HP 1 mL; GE Healthcare), and the 
bound proteins were eluted with a linear gradient of 
0-1 mol/L NaCl in 20 mmol/L HEPES, pH 7.0. The 
active fractions (4 mL) were dialyzed against 2 L of 
20 mmol/L HEPES, pH 7.0. The dialyzed sample was 
loaded onto an anion exchange column (Mono Q 5/50 
GL; GE Healthcare), and the bound proteins were eluted 
with a linear gradient of 0-500 mmol/L NaCl in 
20 mmol/L HEPES, pH 7.0. Ten microliters of the frac-
tions around the active fractions was loaded onto SDS-</p>

<p>PAGE gel. The gel was stained with the fluorescent dye 
and analyzed by the fluorescent scanner as described 
above. </p>

<p>Purification of R-134450 phosphoramidase 
from the liver </p>

<p>All purification procedures were conducted at 4°C. A 
monkey liver homogenate was prepared as described 
above. Twenty to seventy percent saturated ammonium 
sulfate precipitation of the cytosolic fraction was collected 
and stored at À80°C until use. Ammonium sulfate pre-
cipitate equivalent to 30 g of monkey liver was dissolved 
in 50 mL of CEX buffer (20 mmol/L CH 3 COONa, pH 
4.0, containing 0.1% CHAPS, 5 mmol/L MgCl 2 and 
1 mmol/L dithiothreitol [DTT]) and dialyzed against 2 L 
of CEX buffer. The dialyzed sample was centrifuged at 
3000g for 5 min and the supernatant was filtrated and 
loaded onto a cation exchange column (HiPrep SP 16/10 
XL; GE Healthcare). The bound proteins were eluted with 
a linear gradient of 0-1 mol/L NaCl in CEX buffer. The 
active fractions (20 mL) were dialyzed against CEX buffer, 
and loaded onto another cation exchange column (Mono 
S HR 5/5; GE Healthcare). The bound proteins were 
eluted with a linear gradient of 0-300 mmol/L NaCl in 
CEX buffer. The active fractions (3 mL) were dialyzed 
against AEX buffer (20 mmol/L Tris, pH 10.0, containing 
0.1% CHAPS, 5 mmol/L MgCl 2 , and loaded onto an 
anion exchange column (Mini Q PC 3.2/3; GE Health-
care). The bound proteins were eluted with a linear gradi-
ent of 0-300 mmol/L NaCl in AEX buffer. A portion of 
the active fraction (50 lL) from the Mini Q column was 
loaded onto a gel filtration column (Superdex 75 PC 3.2/ 
30; GE Healthcare) equilibrated with 20 mmol/L HEPES, 
pH 7.0, containing 150 mmol/L NaCl, 0.1% CHAPS, 
5 mmol/L MgCl 2 , and 1 mmol/L DTT. Ten microliters of 
the fractions around the active fractions were loaded onto 
SDS-PAGE gel. The gel was stained with the fluorescent 
dye, and analyzed by the fluorescent scanner as described 
above. </p>

<p>Protein identification and quantitation by 
mass spectrometry </p>

<p>To identify proteins from the gel, the bands on the gel 
were excised, digested in gel, and subjected to liquid 
chromatography equipped with tandem mass spectrome-
try (LC-MS/MS) as described previously (Ishizuka et al. 
2010). In the case of identification from the solution for 
shotgun proteomics, the proteins were digested in solu-
tion, and subjected to LC-MS/MS as described previously 
(Kubota et al. 2009). The MS/MS spectra were searched 
against the GenBank nonredundant protein database </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 4 </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes 
K. Kubota et al. </p>

<p>compiled by the National Center for Biotechnology 
Information using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Mascot</rs> program (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Matrix Sciences</rs>, 
London, UK). A label-free spectral counting method, 
emPAI (Ishihama et al. 2005), was used to quantify iden-
tified proteins in shotgun proteomics. </p>

<p>Molecular cloning and expression vector 
construction </p>

<p>Human genes of CES1, CES2, elastase 2A (ELA2A), 
ELA2B, ELA3A, ELA3B, HINT3, aprataxin (APTX) 
and sphingomyelin phosphodiesterase, and acid-like 
(SMPDL3A) were amplified by a polymerase chain reac-
tion (PCR) from human brains, livers, pancreas, skeletal 
muscle, prostates, or their mixed cDNA library. HINT1 
and HINT3 were amplified from a commercially available 
cDNA clone (Ultimate clone; Invitrogen, Tokyo, Japan). 
The resulting PCR products were purified and cloned into 
a pDONR221 entry vector (Invitrogen) by a Gateway BP 
reaction. The sequences were confirmed by DNA sequenc-
ing. In the case of proteins with secretion signal sequences 
(CES1, CES2, ELA2A, ELA2B, ELA3A, ELA3B, and 
SMPDL3A), an entry clone was recombined with a 
pFLAG-CMV-5.1GW destination vector, in which the gene 
was fused with a C-terminal FLAG-tag by a Gateway LR 
reaction. In other cases (HINT1, HINT2, HINT3, APTX), 
each entry clone was recombined with pFLAG-CMV-2GW 
in which the gene was fused with an N-terminal FLAG-tag. 
The construction of the expression vectors was confirmed 
by the insert length and DNA sequencing. The expression 
vector of the N-terminal FLAG-tagged enhanced green 
fluorescent protein (EGFP) was kindly provided by Dr. 
Keisuke Fukuchi from Daiichi Sankyo Co., Ltd. </p>

<p>Expression and purification of recombinant 
proteins </p>

<p>Each expression vector (30 lg) was transfected into 
human embryonic kidney 293-F cells (3 9 10 
7 cells; Invi-
trogen), using 293-fectin according to the manufacturer's 
protocol. The transfected cells were cultured for 72 h. 
The cell culture was centrifuged and the supernatant was 
filtered and used as a conditioned medium. The collected 
cells were suspended for 5 min on ice in Cellytic-M 
(Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) containing 1 mmol/ 
L DTT. The cell extracts were centrifuged and the super-
natant was used as a cell lysate. 
Proteins were purified using their FLAG-tag by affinity 
chromatography. In the case of purification from a condi-
tioned medium (ELA2A, ELA2B, ELA3A, ELA3B, and 
SMPDL3A), the conditioned medium was adjusted to 
have a 0.1% dodecyl-b-maltoside (DM), and 20-25 lL of 
anti-FLAG M2 agarose (Sigma-Aldrich) was added. In the </p>

<p>case of purification from a lysate (CES1, CES2, EGFP, 
HINT1, HINT2, HINT3, and APTX), 5 lL of anti-FLAG 
M2 agarose was added to the lysate. After 12 h incubation 
at 4°C, the resin was collected by centrifuge and washed 
five times with 500 lL of wash buffer (20 mmol/L Tris-
Cl, pH 7.5, containing 500 mmol/L NaCl, 1% DM) and 
once with 200 lL (for the conditioned medium samples) 
or 100 lL (for the lysate samples) of wash buffer contain-
ing 0.1 lg/mL FLAG peptide (Sigma-Aldrich). Proteins 
bound to the gel were eluted with 200 lL (for the condi-
tioned medium samples) or 100 lL (for the lysate sam-
ples) of wash buffer containing 100 lg/mL FLAG peptide. 
Confirmation of protein expression and quantitation of 
the purified proteins were accomplished by Western blot 
analysis. Proteins were loaded onto SDS-PAGE gel 
(5-20% gradient) and then electro-transferred onto a 
polyvinylidene difluoride membrane (Millipore, Teme-
cula, CA, USA). After blocking with an ECL blocking 
agent (GE Healthcare), the membrane was incubated with 
an anti-FLAG M2 antibody conjugated with horse radish 
peroxidase (Sigma-Aldrich) followed by an ECL Western 
blotting detection system (GE Healthcare). The band 
intensity on the X-ray film was scanned by an optical 
scanner (GT-9700F, EPSON) and quantified using C-ter-
minal FLAG-bacterial alkaline phosphatase (Sigma-
Aldrich) as a standard protein. 
Elastase purified from human leukocytes was purchased 
from Sigma-Aldrich and we confirmed by mass spectrom-
etry that this elastase was human ELA2 without any con-
tamination by other elastases or esterases. The total 
protein concentration of the sample was regarded as the 
concentration of the activated ELA2. </p>

<p>Activation of recombinant enzymes </p>

<p>In the case of the recombinant elastases (ELA2A, ELA2B, 
ELA3A and ELA3B), 1 ng/lL trypsin was added after 
purification and incubated at 37°C for 15 min. The acti-
vated elastases were tested for CS-917 esterase activity 
without inactivation of trypsin because trypsin alone did 
not show any CS-917 esterase activity (data not shown) 
and most trypsin inhibitors are known to inhibit elastases 
as well. A part of the activated elastases was loaded onto 
SDS-PAGE gel and the gel was stained by a fluorescent 
dye (Flamingo gel stain; Bio-Rad Laboratories). The band 
intensity corresponding to the predicted molecular weight 
was quantified using a fluorescent scanner (Molecular 
Imager FX; Bio-Rad Laboratories). 
Human recombinant CTSA and cathepsin L were pur-
chased from R&amp;D Systems (Minneapolis, MN, USA). To 
activate cathepsin L, it was incubated on ice for 15 min in 
50 mmol/L 2-(N-morpholino)ethanesulfonic acid (MES), 
pH 6.0, containing 5 mmol/L DTT. To activate CTSA, </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 5 </p>

<p>K. Kubota et al. 
Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes </p>

<p>1 lg/mL cathepsin L was added to 10 lg/mL CTSA in 
25 mmol/L MES, pH 6.0, containing 5 mmol/L DTT and 
incubated at 37°C for 30 min. After the activation of CTSA, 
cathepsin L was inactivated by adding 10 lmol/L E-64 
(Sigma-Aldrich). </p>

<p>CS-917 esterase assay </p>

<p>The sample was incubated at 37°C for 1 h with 300 lg/mL 
CS-917 in 50 lL of 100 mmol/L HEPES, pH 7.0, contain-
ing 500 mmol/L NaCl and 200 lg/mL bovine serum albu-
min (BSA). Regarding investigation of the CES specific 
inhibitor, bis(4-nitrophenyl) phosphate (BNPP; Sigma-
Aldrich), BNPP dissolved with dimethyl sulfoxide at 
50 mmol/L was added to the sample before the addition of 
CS-917, and after 5 min preincubation at 37°C, CS-917 
was added to the reaction mixture. The concentration of 
BNPP in the reaction mixture was 1 mmol/L in the case 
where there was no explicit description. To stop the reac-
tion, the sample was mixed with 100 lL of methanol, and 
10 lL of the filtrate (0.45 lm; Millipore) was subjected to 
a reversed-phase chromatography column (ZORBAX SB 
C18, 2.1 mm ID 9 0 mm length, 1.8 lm; Agilent Tech-
nologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA), which was conditioned at 
40°C and pre-equilibrated with 20 mmol/L triethylamine 
acetate (TEAA), pH 7.0, containing 5% acetonitrile. The 
compounds were eluted with a linear gradient of 5-95% 
acetonitrile in 20 mmol/L TEAA, pH 7.0, over 2.5 min at a 
flow rate of 0.5 mL/min. Absorbance at 303 nm was moni-
tored, and CS-917 esterase activity was determined by mea-
suring the peak area of the produced R-134450 using a 
known amount of a synthesized R-134450 as the standards. 
One unit of CS-917 esterase activity was defined as the 
activity required for 1 lg/mL production of R-134450 
under these experimental conditions. </p>

<p>R-134450 phosphoramidase assay </p>

<p>To the 35 lL of the sample was added 5 lL of 1 mol/L 
HEPES, pH 7.0, 5 lL of 2 mg/mL BSA and 5 lL of 
10 mmol/L R-134450 dissolved in 5% dimethyl sulfoxide, 
and this was incubated at 37°C for 1 h. After the reaction, 
the sample was mixed with 100 lL of methanol to inacti-
vate the enzyme and 10 lL of the filtrate (0.45 lm) was 
subjected to a reversed-phase chromatography column 
(XTerra MS C18 5 lm, 4.6 mm ID 9 150 mm length; 
Waters, Milford, MA, USA) with a guard column of the 
same material (3.9 mm ID 9 20 mm length, Waters), 
then analyzed with isocratic elution in 10 mmol/L TEAA, 
pH 7.0, containing 16% acetonitrile. Absorbance at 
260 nm was monitored, and R-134450 phosphoramidase 
activity was determined by measuring the peak area of 
produced R-125338, using a known amount of synthesized </p>

<p>R-125338 as the standard. One unit/mL R-134450 phos-
phoramidase activity was defined as the concentration 
required for 1 lmol/L production of R-125338 under 
these experimental conditions. </p>

<p>Protein assay </p>

<p>The total protein concentration was determined by a 
modified Bradford assay (Coomassie Plus Protein Assay; 
Pierce, Tokyo, Japan), using BSA as a standard protein. </p>

<p>Compliance with design and statistical 
analysis requirements </p>

<p>All experiments were independently conducted more than 
once to confirm reproducibility except Figure 4, where we 
show all of the data from individual animals. A represen-
tation of those independent experiments is shown in each 
figure and table, and the number of independent experi-
ments is described in each figure and table legend. There-
fore, replicates in the Figures were 'used only to test the 
precision of n = 1' in this study. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Purification and identification of ELA3B and 
CTSA as CS-917 esterases in monkey small 
intestines </p>

<p>To identify the enzyme responsible for CS-917 esterase 
activity in the small intestine, we used cynomolgus mon-
keys as a purification source because of the abundant sam-
ple availability and their similarity to humans. The monkey 
small intestine was homogenized and separated to nuclear, 
mitochondrial, microsomal, and cytosolic fractions by cen-
trifugation and the activity was found to be mostly local-
ized in the cytosolic and soluble fraction (Fig. S1). The 
observed molecular weight of the activity was 60-70 kDa 
determined by gel filtration chromatography, and interest-
ingly, the activity from one out of the five monkeys 
(monkey #1) was bound to an HIC column and formed 
two almost equivalent peaks (Fig. 2A). 
The active peaks purified with the HIC column were 
further characterized. The first active peak was bound to 
a blue dye affinity column at pH 7 and was also weakly 
bound to a heparin affinity column. On the other hand, 
the second peak was not bound to either the blue dye or 
the heparin affinity columns, but was bound to a hydrox-
ylapatite column. Based on their characters, we purified 
CS-917 esterase activity from the small intestine from 
monkey #1. We used the HIC column for the first 
column and the first and the second active peaks were 
purified separately afterwards. As a result of successive </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 6 </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes 
K. Kubota et al. </p>

<p>five-step purification, the first and the second active peaks 
were purified more than 4000-fold (Table 1) and 8000-
fold (Table 2), respectively. In the fourth (Fig. S2A and 
B) and final (Fig. 2B and C) purification step of the first 
active peak, we found bands of 30, 17, and 15 kDa on 
SDS-PAGE gels which correlated well with the CS-917 
esterase activity. Therefore, we analyzed the proteins in 
these three bands by mass spectrometry and identified 
monkey elastase 3B (NCBI gene identifier: 62510667, 
human homologous gene symbol: ELA3B) from all three 
bands. Similarly, in the fourth (Fig. S2C and D) and final 
(Fig. 2D and E) purification step of the second active 
peak, we found bands of 26 and 17 kDa on SDS-PAGE 
gels which correlated well with the enzyme activity, and 
we identified the protein in these bands as monkey 
cathepsin A (NCBI gene identifier: 109091751, human 
homologous gene symbol: CTSA) by mass spectrometry. </p>

<p>Confirmation of CS-917 esterase activity of 
candidate genes in the small intestine </p>

<p>To confirm that CTSA and ELA3B have CS-917 esterase 
activity and to determine whether other possible candi-
date genes have CS-917 esterase activity, we compared the 
specific activity of the candidate genes for CS-917 ester-
ase. We cloned human homologous genes because our 
final goal is to identify CS-917 esterase in humans. Con-
sidering the differences between species, we regarded 
other human pancreatic elastases (ELA2A, ELA2B and 
ELA3A) as candidates for CS-917 esterase in addition to 
ELA3B. We produced the recombinant proteins in human 
cells, purified them using FLAG-tag fused with their car-
boxyl-terminal, activated them if necessary, and tested 
their specific activity. In addition to pancreatic elastases, 
we also tested ELA2. Fortunately, active ELA2 purified 
from human leukocytes was commercially available. With 
regard to CTSA, we obtained commercially available 
human CTSA and activated them with cathepsin L as 
described in Materials and Methods. 
As shown in Figure 3, CTSA demonstrated the highest 
specific activity as CS-917 esterase while ELA2 and ELA3B 
exhibited moderate specific activity, and ELA3A showed 
weak specific activity. ELA2A and ELA2B did not hydrolase 
CS-917. In parallel, we tested ELA2A and ELA2B's elastase 
activity using synthetic peptide substrates. The results 
revealed ELA2A had elastase activity but ELA2B did not 
(Fig. S3), indicating that our ELA2A was certainly active but 
did not have CS-917 esterase activity. With regard to ELA2B, 
a recent report showed ELA2B was devoid of proteolytic 
activity (Szepessy and Sahin Toth 2006). Thus, our ELA2B 
was supposed to be inactive due to its intrinsic character. 
Phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (PMSF) is an inhibitor 
for a broad range of serine proteases. Since both ELA3B </p>

<p>and CTSA are serine proteases, we tested its inhibitory 
effect on the elastases and CTSA. CS-917 esterase activity 
of the elastases was almost completely inhibited with 
1 mmol/L PMSF, whereas CTSA was relatively insensitive 
to PMSF (Fig. S4). Next, we investigated the PMSF effect 
on CS-917 esterase activity separated with an HIC column 
in monkey small intestine homogenates. Interestingly, we 
found that all 4 homogenates prepared from monkeys 
(monkey #2 to #5) other than monkey #1 formed a single 
active peak after HIC column separation and that the 
activity was relatively insensitive to 1 mmol/L PMSF 
(Fig. 4). These observations strongly suggested that CTSA 
was the major CS-917 esterase in monkey small intestine 
homogenates and that monkey #1 was exceptional for 
unknown reasons, probably insufficient washing of the 
inside of the small intestine. </p>

<p>Purification and identification of CES1 and 
CTSA as CS-917 esterases in monkey liver </p>

<p>The CS-917 esterase activity of human liver S9 was par-
tially removed by CTSA immunodepletion, whereas that 
of the human small intestine was almost completely 
removed (Fig. S5). These results strongly suggested that 
there was an enzyme(s) which had CS-917 esterase activ-
ity other than CTSA in the human liver. 
CES is well known as an activating enzyme for many 
prodrugs, including bisamidate prodrugs and is supposed 
to be a good candidate for an additional CS-917 esterase 
in the liver (Imai 2006; Liederer and Borchardt 2006; 
Satoh and Hosokawa 2006; Murakami et al. 2010). To 
test this hypothesis, we investigated the effects of a CES-
specific inhibitor, BNPP, on human liver S9 and observed 
that the high concentration of BNPP (10 mmol/L) did 
not show an inhibitory effect on human liver S9, but it 
did show significant inhibition on dialyzed human liver 
S9 (Fig. S6). These data indicated that BNPP could not 
inhibit CS-917 esterase activity in a crude sample for 
some reason. Therefore, we separated 20-70% ammo-
nium sulfate precipitate of monkey liver homogenates by 
HIC, and tested the BNPP effect on its fractions. Consid-
ering the possibility of the purification of liver CS-917 
esterase, we used cynomolgus monkey liver for the same 
reasons we used the monkey small intestine. As shown in 
Figure 5A, the CS-917 esterase activity formed two active 
peaks and the first active peak was strongly inhibited by 
BNPP, which suggested that the first active peak was con-
tributed by CES and that the second active peak was con-
tributed by CTSA. 
Among the two major CES in humans, CES1 is highly 
expressed in the liver but is hardly expressed in the small 
intestine and contributes 80-95% CES activity in the 
human liver (Imai 2006), indicating CES1 is the enzyme </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 7 </p>

<p>K. Kubota et al. 
Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes </p>

<p>CS-917 esterase activity 
SDS-PAGE band intensity </p>

<p>26 kDa </p>

<p>17 kDa </p>

<p>150 
100 
75 </p>

<p>50 
37 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>kDa </p>

<p>12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 
11 </p>

<p>CS-917 esterase activity 
SDS-PAGE band intensity </p>

<p>150 
100 
75 </p>

<p>50 
37 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>kDa </p>

<p>12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 
11 </p>

<p>30 kDa </p>

<p>17 kDa 
15 kDa </p>

<p>First 
peak </p>

<p>Second 
peak </p>

<p>80,000 </p>

<p>70,000 </p>

<p>60,000 </p>

<p>50,000 </p>

<p>40,000 </p>

<p>30,000 </p>

<p>20,000 </p>

<p>10,000 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>(B) 
(C) </p>

<p>(E) 
(D) </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 8 </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes 
K. Kubota et al. </p>

<p>responsible for the BNPP sensitive CS-917 esterase activ-
ity. To examine this, we partially purified CS-917 esterase 
activity and analyzed it by mass spectrometry. We sepa-
rated the activity from the ammonium sulfate precipitate 
monkey liver using an HIC column. Afterward, the first 
and the second active peaks were purified separately by </p>

<p>two successive columns, a dye-affinity column and an 
anion exchange column. CS-917 esterase activities sepa-
rated by the final anion exchange chromatography are 
shown in Figure 5B (the first active peak) and D (the sec-
ond active peak). The fractions which showed CS-917 
esterase activity were tested to determine whether their </p>

<p>Figure 2. Purification and identification of CS-917 esterase activity from the small intestine of monkey #1. (A) The CS-917 esterase activity 
precipitated by ammonium sulfate from monkey #1 was subjected to a hydrophobic interaction chromatography (HIC) column. The activity was 
bound to a column and formed two active peaks by a linear gradient elution of 1-0 mol/L ammonium sulfate. CS-917 esterase activity of each 
active peak in the HIC was separately purified by successive chromatography. (B) Fractions of the final purification step of the first active peak 
were subjected to SDS-PAGE and the gel was stained by a fluorescent dye. Bands of 30, 17, and 15 kDa correlating well with the enzyme activity 
are indicated by arrowheads. (C) The enzyme activity of the fractions (solid line) and the intensity of arrowed bands of 30 kDa in (B) are shown 
as bars, respectively. (D) Fractions of the final purification step of the second active peak were subjected to SDS-PAGE and the gel was stained by 
a fluorescent dye. Bands of 26 and 17 kDa correlating well with the enzyme activity are indicated by arrowheads. (E) The enzyme activity of the 
fractions (solid line) and the intensity of the arrowed bands of 26 kDa in (D) are shown as bars, respectively. Three independent experiments were 
conducted, and the average of technical duplicates from a representative single experiment is shown with error bars representing the higher 
value. SDS-PAGE, sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. </p>

<p>Table 1. Purification of the first active peak in hydrophobic interaction chromatography. </p>

<p>Step </p>

<p>Protein 
concentration 
(lg/mL) </p>

<p>Activity </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(U/mL) </p>

<p>Volume 
(mL) </p>

<p>Total 
protein 
(mg) </p>

<p>Total 
activity 
(U) </p>

<p>Specific 
activity 
(U/mg) </p>

<p>Step 
fold 
change </p>

<p>Overall 
fold 
change </p>

<p>Step 
recovery 
(%) </p>

<p>Overall 
recovery 
(%) </p>

<p>Monkey small intestine 
homogenate </p>

<p>14,000 
330 
430 
6000 
140,000 
23 
-
1 
-
100 </p>

<p>1. Ammonium sulfate 
precipitation </p>

<p>20,000 
17,000 
80 
1600 
1,400,000 
85 37 
37 
970 
970 </p>

<p>2. Hydrophobic interaction 
(HiPrep Butyl) </p>

<p>390 
1700 
20 
7.8 
35,000 
4500 
5.2 
190 
2.6 
25 </p>

<p>3. Dye affinity (HiTrap Blue) 
130 
5700 
2.0 
0.26 
11,000 
44,000 
9.8 
1900 
33 
8.2 
4. Anion exchange (Mini Q) 
58 
4600 
0.24 
0.014 
1100 
79,000 
1.8 
3400 
10 
0.8 
5. Gel filtration (Superdex 75) 
15 
1600 
0.10 
0.0015 
160 110,000 
1.4 
4700 
14 
0.11 </p>

<p>Three independent experiments were conducted, and a representative purification table from a single experiment is shown. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>One unit of CS-917 esterase activity is defined as the activity required of 1 lg/mL R-134450 production in our assay condition described in Mate-
rials and Methods. </p>

<p>Table 2. Purification of the second active peak in hydrophobic interaction chromatography. </p>

<p>Step </p>

<p>Protein 
concentration 
(lg/mL) </p>

<p>Activity </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(U/mL) </p>

<p>Volume 
(mL) </p>

<p>Total 
protein 
(mg) </p>

<p>Total 
activity p(U) </p>

<p>Specific 
activity 
(U/mg) </p>

<p>Step 
fold 
change </p>

<p>Overall 
fold 
change </p>

<p>Step 
recovery 
(%) </p>

<p>Overall 
recovery 
(%) </p>

<p>Monkey small intestine 
homogenate </p>

<p>14,000 
327 
430 
6000 
140,000 
23 
-
1 
-
100 </p>

<p>1. Ammonium sulfate 
precipitation </p>

<p>20,000 
17,000 
80 
1600 
1,400,000 
850 37 
37 
967 
967 </p>

<p>2. Hydrophobic interaction 
(HiPrep Butyl) </p>

<p>160 
2700 
20 
3.2 
53,000 
17,000 20 
700 
3.9 
38 </p>

<p>3. Hydroxylapatite (CHT2-I) 
88 
2800 
2.0 
0.18 
5700 
32,000 
1.9 
1400 
11 
4.1 
4. Anion exchange (Mini Q) 
34 
3700 
0.24 
0.008 
900 
110,000 
3.4 
4700 
16 
0.6 
5. Gel filtration (Superdex 75) 
3.4 
630 
0.10 
0.0003 
63 
190,000 
1.7 
8000 
7 
0.04 </p>

<p>Three independent experiments were conducted, and a representative purification table from a single experiment is shown. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>One unit of CS-917 esterase activity is defined as the activity required of 1 lg/mL R-134450 production in our assay condition described in Mate-
rials and Methods. </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 9 </p>

<p>K. Kubota et al. 
Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>(D) 
(C) </p>

<p>Figure 4. CS-917 esterase activity in the small intestine from different monkeys. The CS-917 esterase activity precipitated by ammonium sulfate 
from monkeys other than monkey #1 was subjected to a hydrophobic interaction chromatography column. In all of the cases, the activity formed 
a single active peak by a linear gradient elution of 1-0 mol/L ammonium sulfate. The activity was tested in the presence or absence of 1 mmol/L 
PMSF, a protease inhibitor for serine proteases including elastases. (A) Monkey #2, (B) monkey #3, (C) monkey #4 and (D) monkey #5. The data 
are shown as the average of technical duplicates from a single experiment with error bars representing the higher value. PMSF, 
phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Specific CS-917 esterase activity of candidate genes. Specific activities of human candidate genes as CS-917 esterase were compared. 
Carboxylesterases (CES1 and CES2) were cloned, expressed in human cells, and purified from the lysate. Activated ELA2 purified from human 
leukocytes was commercially available. Pancreatic elastases (ELA2A, ELA2B, ELA3A, and ELA3B) were cloned, expressed in human cells, purified 
from the conditioned medium, and activated with trypsin. Purified CTSA expressed in E. coli. was obtained from a commercial source, and 
activated with cathepsin L. Two to five independent experiments were conducted (2 for ELA2, 3 for CES1, CES2, ELA2A, and ELA3B, and 5 for 
ELA3A, ELA3B, and CTSA), and the average of technical duplicates from a representative single experiment is shown with error bars representing 
the higher value. CTSA, cathepsin A; ELA, elastase. </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 10 </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes 
K. Kubota et al. </p>

<p>activities were inhibited by BNPP. Expectedly, the frac-
tions from the first active peak were well inhibited by 
BNPP, indicating CES1 as a responsible enzyme (Fig. 5C), 
whereas the fractions from the second active peak were </p>

<p>not inhibited by BNPP indicating another enzyme was 
involved (Fig. 5E). Then we attempted to identify pro-
teins in the active fractions by shotgun proteomics, where 
total proteins are digested as a mixture and the digested </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>(D) 
(E) </p>

<p>(C) </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>Figure 5. Purification and identification of CS-917 esterase activity from the monkey liver. (A) The CS-917 esterase activity precipitated by 
ammonium sulfate from monkey liver was subjected to a hydrophobic interaction (HIC). The activity was tested in the absence (gray bars) or 
presence (hatched bars) of 1 mmol/L BNPP, a CES specific inhibitor. CS-917 esterase activity of each active peak in the HIC was separately 
purified by successive chromatography. The CS-917 esterase activities were separated by the final anion exchange column purified from the first 
(B) or the second (D) active peak. The BNPP inhibitory effect was further tested on the active fractions from the first (C) or the second (E) active 
peak (gray and hatched bars). Quantitation of CES1 (C) and CTSA (E) by mass spectrometry using emPAI (closed and open box lines) correlated 
well with the enzyme activity. Four independent experiments were conducted, and the average of technical duplicates from a representative 
single experiment is shown with error bars representing the higher value. CTSA, cathepsin A; BNPP, bis(4-nitrophenyl) phosphate. </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 11 </p>

<p>K. Kubota et al. 
Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes </p>

<p>peptides are analyzed by LC-MS/MS (Hunt et al. 1992; 
Dongre et al. 1997; McCormack et al. 1997; Kubota et al. 
2009). As expected, CES1 was identified in the fractions 
from the first active peak, and CTSA was identified in 
those from the second active peak. We quantified the rel-
ative abundance of CES1 and CTSA using a label-free 
spectral count method and found that the CES1 amount 
correlated well with CS-917 esterase activity purified from 
the first active peak and that the CTSA amount correlated 
well with the activity purified from the second active peak 
in the presence of 1 mmol/L BNPP (Fig. 5C and E). 
These results suggested that CES1 was the enzyme which 
was inhibited by BNPP and that CTSA and CES1 were 
the major CS-917 esterases in monkey liver. </p>

<p>Confirmation of CS-917 esterase activity of 
CES1 </p>

<p>We prepared recombinant human CES1 and CES2 to 
confirm that CES1 has CS-917 esterase activity. Although 
contribution of CES2 is 5-15% in the human liver, CES2 
is known to be the major CES in the small intestine (Imai 
2006). CES2 was not identified as CS-917 esterase in the 
small intestine, therefore CES2 was not supposed to have 
CS-917 esterase activity, but we included CES2 as a good 
negative control. Both recombinant CES1 and CES2 
showed CES activity on a typical CES substrate, 
p-nitrophenylacetate, and the only CES1 demonstrated 
CS-917 esterase activity as expected (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Purification and identification of SMPDL3A 
as the intermediate (R-134450) 
phosphoramidase in monkey liver </p>

<p>To identify the second and rate-limiting enzyme of CS-
917 activation, we attempted to purify the intermediate </p>

<p>(R-134450) phosphoramidase from monkey liver. We 
chose the liver as a purification source because the liver is 
the target organ of the FBPase inhibitor. As a result of 
preliminary experiments, R-134450 phosphoramidase 
activity was localized in the cytosolic fraction (Fig. S7) 
and the observed molecular weight was 65-83 kDa by gel 
filtration chromatography (Fig. S8). 
We purified R-134450 phosphoramidase activity from 
monkey liver by successive five-step purification after 
ammonium sulfate precipitation. The enzyme activity was 
concentrated more than 9000-fold (Table 3). The enzyme 
activity formed a single peak in all chromatography steps, 
which indicated the enzyme was single. After the third 
purification step, we found that bands of 50 kDa on SDS-
PAGE gels were correlating well with the enzyme activity 
(Fig. 6). We identified the protein of these 50 kDa bands 
by mass spectrometry as sphingomyelin phosphodiester-
ase, acid-like 3A (Human homologous gene symbol: 
SMPDL3A). </p>

<p>Confirmation and comparison of candidate 
genes for R-134450 phosphoramidase </p>

<p>As far as we know, only two genes were reported as phos-
phoramidases in the literature (Bieganowski et al. 2002; 
Seidle et al. 2005). These two genes, HINT1 and APTX, 
belong to the same HINT enzyme family, and this HINT 
enzyme family consists of four genes (HINT1, HINT2, 
HINT3, and APTX) in humans. HINT1 could hydrolyze 
the phosphoramide bond of AMP-lysine (Bieganowski 
et al. 2002) and moreover the bisamidate nucleotide pro-
drug PSI-7851 (Murakami et al. 2010). In addition, APTX 
was also found to have the same AMP-lysine phospho-
ramidase activity (Seidle et al. 2005). Therefore, we 
included these four HINT family genes as candidate genes 
for R-134450 in addition to SMPDL3A, although none of </p>

<p>Table 3. Purification of R-134450 phosphoramidase from the monkey liver. </p>

<p>Step </p>

<p>Protein 
concentration 
(lg/mL) </p>

<p>Activity </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(U/mL) </p>

<p>Volume 
(mL) </p>

<p>Total 
protein 
(mg) </p>

<p>Total 
activity 
(U) </p>

<p>Specific 
activity 
(U/mg) </p>

<p>Step 
fold 
change </p>

<p>Overall 
fold 
change </p>

<p>Step 
recovery 
(%) </p>

<p>Overall 
recovery 
(%) </p>

<p>Monkey liver homogenate 
7000 
71 
200 
1400 
14,000 
10 
1.0 
1.0 
-
100 
1. Ammonium sulfate 
precipitation </p>

<p>1400 
320 
50 
72 
16,000 
224 
22 
22 
110 
110 </p>

<p>2. Cation exchange 
(HiPrep SP XL) </p>

<p>13 
680 
30 
0.40 
20,000 53,000 240 
5300 
130 
140 </p>

<p>3. Cation exchange (Mono S) 
18 
300 
3.0 
0.054 
890 16,000 
0.31 1600 
4.4 
6.2 
4. Anion exchange (Mini Q) 
8.3 
160 
0.24 
0.0020 
37 19,000 
1.2 
1900 
4.2 
0.26 
5. Gel filtration (Superdex 75) 
2.1 
190 
0.10 
0.00021 
19 92,000 
4.9 
9100 
52 
0.14 </p>

<p>Three independent experiments were conducted, and a representative purification table from a single experiment is shown. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>One unit of R-134450 phosphoramidase activity is defined as the activity required of 1 lmol/L R-125338 production in our assay condition 
described in Materials and Methods. </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 12 </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes 
K. Kubota et al. </p>

<p>them was identified in the purification of the enzyme 
activity from monkey liver. 
We cloned the human genes of SMPDL3A, HINT1, 
HINT2, HINT3, and APTX, produced recombinant pro-
teins in human cells, purified them using FLAG-tag fused 
with the protein, and tested their R-134450 phosphorami-
dase activity. As shown in Figure 7, SMPDL3A showed 
remarkable R-134450 phosphoramidase activity while 
HINT1, HINT2, and APTX had much weaker specific 
activity than SMPDL3A. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we molecularly identified the enzymes that 
can catalyze the activation process of a bisamidate pro-
drug, CS-917. As activating enzymes in the first step, we 
purified and identified CTSA and ELA3B from the mon-
key small intestine. We also found ELA2 had relatively 
weak CS-917 esterase activity. Based on the fact that ho-
mogenates from only one specific monkey showed high </p>

<p>CS-917 esterase activity derived from ELA3B (Figs. 2, 4) 
and the immunodepletion experiment (Fig. S5), CTSA 
was probably the major responsible enzyme for CS-917 
esterase activity in the small intestine. In addition, we 
have revealed that CES1 could contribute as CS-917 ester-
ase as well as CTSA in the liver. 
Orally administrated CS-917 would be partially hydro-
lyzed by pancreatic elastases, mainly ELA3B, in the lumen 
of the small intestine and would be further hydrolyzed by 
CTSA in the small intestine. CS-917 that escaped from 
those enzymes in the small intestine would be hydrolyzed 
by CTSA and CES1 in the liver, which is the target organ 
of CS-917. CS-917 hydrolyzed before reaching the liver 
would hardly contribute to the drug action of CS-917, 
because R-134450 is hydrophilic and has a low transition 
between organs due to its low membrane permeability. 
CS-917 esterase activity in human plasma was very weak 
compared to that in the small intestine or liver (data not 
shown), which indicated ELA2 was a minor factor in CS-
917 metabolism. Taken together, ELA3B and CTSA, not </p>

<p>(A) 
(B) 
(C) </p>

<p>(F) 
(E) 
(D) </p>

<p>Figure 6. Purification and identification or R-134450 phosphoramidase activity from monkey liver. R-134450 phosphoramidase activity was 
purified from monkey liver by ammonium sulfate precipitation and successive five-step chromatography. Fractions of the third (A), fourth (B) and 
final (C) purification step were subjected to SDS-PAGE and the gel was stained by a fluorescent dye. Bands of 50 kDa correlating well with the 
enzyme activity are indicated by arrowheads. The bands indicated by open arrowheads were cut and analyzed by mass spectrometry. Enzyme 
activity of the fractions (solid line) and the intensities of the arrowed bands in the above panel (bars) are shown in the third (D), fourth (E) and 
final (F) purification step. Boxed fractions were subjected to the next purification step. Three independent experiments were conducted, and the 
average of technical duplicates from a representative single experiment is shown with error bars representing the higher value. SDS-PAGE, sodium 
dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 13 </p>

<p>K. Kubota et al. 
Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes </p>

<p>ELA2, should play an important role in determining the 
CS-917 amount in the liver, and CTSA and CES1 would 
be an important factor for R-125338 concentration in the 
liver. 
Elastases belong to the serine protease family. In 
humans, six elastase genes (elastase 1 (ELA1), ELA2, 
ELA2A, ELA2B, ELA3A, and ELA3B) are known. ELA1 is 
expressed in skin keratinocytes (Kawashima et al. 1992; 
Talas et al. 2000). ELA2, also known as neutrophil elas-
tase or leukocyte elastase, is expressed in bone marrow 
myelocytic precursor cells, mostly promyelocytes (Fouret 
et al. 1989; Lee and Downey 2001). ELA2A, ELA2B, 
ELA3A, and ELA3B are known as pancreatic elastases, 
which are expressed and stored as an inactive zymogen in 
the pancreas, secreted into the intestine, activated by tryp-
sin and participate in food digestion (Hartley and Shot-
ton 1971; Shen et al. 1987; Tani et al. 1988; Fouret et al. 
1989). Although the elastase was defined as a protease 
which degrades elastin, ELA3A and ELA3B are known to 
have a slight elastolytic activity but do have protease 
activity with preferential cleavage after alanine (Bode 
et al. 1989). The partial structure around the hydrolyzed 
ester of CS-917 was alanine ethyl ester, which supported 
ELA3B as the CS-917 esterase. It was reported that 
mature ELA3A/ELA3B had a molecular weight of 30 kDa 
and highly concentrated ELA3A/ELA3B showed rapid 
autolysis (Mallory and Travis 1975), which suggested that 
the 17 and 15 kDa identified as ELA3B by mass spec-
trometry would be its autodigested products (Fig. 2B). All 
of the data were consistent with ELA3B as one of the CS-
917 esterases in the small intestine. 
CTSA, also known as a lysosomal protective protein or 
lysosomal carboxypeptidase A, is a serine protease 
expressed ubiquitously (Hiraiwa 1999). This enzyme has </p>

<p>three distinctive enzymatic activities: (1) peptidase activity 
optimal at pH 5.0 and (2) esterase and (3) deamidase 
activity optimal at pH 7.0 (Jackman et al. 1990). Besides 
its catalytic activities, it plays an important role in stabiliz-
ing lysosomal b-galactosidase and neuraminidase by its 
association. Interestingly, this protective function is inde-
pendent of its catalytic activities (Galjart et al. 1991). 
CTSA is synthesized as a precursor of 54 kDa which is 
proteolytically processed into a mature two-chain form of 
32 and 20 kDa polypeptides linked by disulfide bridges. 
This agrees well with the observations that the 26 and 
17 kDa bands under a reducing condition (Fig. 2D) corre-
lated well with CS-917 esterase activity on SDS-PAGE gels 
and were all identified as CTSA by mass spectrometry. 
SMPDL3A, also referred to as acid sphingomyelinase-
like phosphodiesterase 3a (ASML3a), is a protein whose 
biological or enzymatic function is mostly unknown. One 
study using a yeast 2-hybrid system reported that 
SMPDL3A interacts with the tumor suppressor gene 
deleted in the bladder cancer chromosome region 1 
(DBCCR1) (Wright et al. 2002), and another study dem-
onstrated SMPDL3A expression is regulated by liver X 
receptors (LXRs) (Noto et al. 2012). We found that the 
protein has one predicted phosphohydrolase domain 
(COG1409, NCBI), where the phosphoramidase reaction 
is similar to the phosphohydrolase reaction. mRNA 
expression of human SMPDL3A was high in the skin, 
small intestine, colon, rectum, liver, kidney, and prostate 
but low in other tissues, including blood vessels, which 
was consistent with the observation of the R-134450 
phosphoramidase activity profile (data not shown). All 
experimental data supported that SMPDL3A was the 
enzyme responsible for R-134450 phosphoramidase activ-
ity. </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>L fmol protein) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>R-134450 phosphoramidasep </p>

<p>specific activity (U/m </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>EGFP 
SMPDL3A 
Hint1 
Hint2 
Hint3 
APTX </p>

<p>Figure 7. Specific R-134450 phosphoramidase activity of candidate genes. Candidate genes (SMPDL3A, HINT1, HINT2, HINT3, and APTX) and the 
negative control (EGFP) were expressed in the human cell line, the recombinant proteins were purified using fused FLAG-tag, and the R-134450 
phosphoramidase activity was tested. The purified proteins were quantified by Western blotting, and the specific activity was calculated. Four to 
seven independent experiments were conducted (4 for HINT1, HINT2, HINT3, and APTX, and 7 for EGFP and SMPDL3A). The results are expressed 
as the means AE SD (three technical replicates from a single experiment). EGFP, enhanced green fluorescent protein. </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 14 </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes 
K. Kubota et al. </p>

<p>We have identified SMPDL3A as an R-134450 phos-
phoramidase, which is thought to be a rate-limiting 
enzyme for CS-917 activation (Erion et al. 2005; Dang 
et al. 2007). We deduced that SMPDL3A, not HINT1, is 
the major R-134450 phosphoramidase in vivo because of 
the reasons below: (1) The enzyme activity formed a sin-
gle peak in all purification steps, which suggested the 
enzyme in the monkey liver was unique; (2) Only 
SMPDL3A showed relatively strong specific activity com-
pared to HINT family proteins; (3) We tested the R-
134450 phosphoramidase activity of two isoforms of 
SMPDL3B, the most homologous protein to SMPDL3A, 
but they did not show any R-134450 phosphoramidase 
activity (data not shown) because homologous drug 
metabolism enzymes often have similar enzyme activity. 
To determine whether SMPDL3A is the major enzyme 
responsible for R-134450 phosphoramidase activity, fur-
ther studies are needed. For example, a neutralizing anti-
body against SMPDL3A can be used for such 
experiments. Moreover, investigation of the relationship 
between SMPDL3A and pharmacokinetic and pharmaco-
dynamic analysis of CS-917 will reveal the importance of 
SMPDL3A in CS-917 activation. 
In previous literatures, contribution of CTSA for the 
first ester hydrolysis of nucleotide bisamidate prodrugs 
was reported for GS-7340 and GS-9131 (Birkus et al. 
2007), PSI-7851 (Murakami et al. 2010), GS-9191 (Birkus 
et al. 2011) and GS-6620 (Murakami et al. 2014), whereas 
CES1 was partially involved, such as with PSI-7851 
(Murakami et al. 2010) and GS-6620 (Murakami et al. 
2014). Neutrophil elastase (ELA2) was also described to 
have the esterase activity for PSI-7851 (Murakami et al. 
2010) and we identified ELA3B as CS-917 esterase. There-
fore, the first step reaction of CS-917 was found to be 
similar to those nucleotide prodrugs. On the other hand, 
HINT1 (Murakami et al. 2010, 2014) or an unidentified 
enzyme (Saboulard et al. 1999; Birkus et al. 2011) or 
acid-driven hydrolysis (Birkus et al. 2011) was described 
for the second hydrolysis of the P-N bond for prodrugs, 
which was different from SMPDL3A in CS-917. Thus, 
SMPDL3A would be the first identified phosphoramidase 
other than the HINT family enzymes. Saboulard et al. 
(1999) reported that anti-HIV prodrug phosphoramidase 
from rat liver was enriched in a cytosolic fraction and 
that its observed molecular weight was 50-100 kDa. These 
data agree well with the characteristics of SMPDL3A, but 
not with HINT1 or APTX. Thus, SMPDL3A might be the 
unreported phosphoramidase for the anti-HIV prodrug. 
Identification of an enzyme based on biochemical puri-
fication is sometimes regarded as a classic and conserva-
tive approach. In this study, we purified ELA3B and 
CTSA from monkey small intestine (Fig. 2, Tables 1, 2) 
and SMPDL3A from monkey liver (Fig. 6 and Table 3). </p>

<p>Technical limitations of this study were to use monkey 
tissue as starting materials for purification, and the poten-
tial to bias activities observed toward a more stable 
enzyme by a biochemical purification approach. However, 
many enzymes were discovered through this approach, 
especially the discovery of unforeseen enzymes, and once 
we identify the candidates, we could validate the candi-
dates by the following experiments using human samples. 
Human recombinant protein experiments (Figs. 3, 7) in 
this study are the initial step, and correlation analysis 
between inter-individual enzyme activity and candidate 
proteins, a selective inhibitor experiment and gene knock-
out animal experiment would follow for the purpose. In 
the purification scheme, recovery of enzyme activities at 
the early purification steps showed more than 100%. This 
is not an uncommon observation as we reported previ-
ously (Yonesu et al. 2011) and as written by others (Ryan 
1996), indicating a presence of inhibitors of the enzyme 
reaction in crude samples. With regard to identification 
strategy, CES1 and CTSA can be expected as a CS-917 
esterase, ELA3B could be speculated based on the activity 
of ELA2 for PSI-7851 (Murakami et al. 2010), however 
identification of SMPDL3A as an R-134450 phosphorami-
dase was completely unexpected because SMPDL3A was 
very far from the HINT family proteins which have only 
been reported as having phosphoramidase activity. Recent 
advancement of proteomics technology has made the 
requirements to identify candidate proteins much lower 
than before. We did not have to purify candidate proteins 
to homogeneity. Instead, in this study, we identified can-
didate proteins from faint bands of a nanogram level 
which correlated with enzyme activity (Figs. 2, 6) or even 
without SDS-PAGE (Fig. 5) by using a quantitation 
method by mass spectrometry. Recently, we reported the 
carboxymethylene butenolidase homolog (CMBL) as a 
hydrolase of a new antihypertensive drug, olmesartan me-
doxomil, by the same strategy (Ishizuka et al. 2010), 
where the identified protein was also completely unex-
pected. The classical biochemical approach with cutting-
edge proteomics technology could contribute to identify 
enzymes beyond our limited imagination. 
In conclusion, we identified the enzymes involved in 
both two-step activation processes of the novel phospho-
ramidate prodrug, CS-917, at the molecular level. All of 
the observations presented here were obtained through 
in vitro experiments, thus the next challenge would be to 
determine the contribution of enzymes identified in this 
study in vivo, as other enzymes or even nonenzymatic 
lysosomal hydrolysis could be involved. Nevertheless, this 
study would be an important, initial, and necessary step 
for a better understanding of the activation mechanism, 
pharmacodynamics, and pharmacokinetics of this new 
drug candidate and possibly other phosphoramidate pro-</p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 15 </p>

<p>K. Kubota et al. 
Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes </p>

<p>drugs. Novel identification of new phosphoramidase, 
which could be responsible for the activation process of 
other bisamidate drugs, would contribute to research and 
development of this class of prodrugs in the future. In 
addition, this study would be another good example 
showing that our biochemical approach with proteomics 
technology is an efficient strategy to identify unexpected 
metabolic enzymes, which are supposed to be necessary 
in the personalized medicine era. </p>

<p>Acknowledgement </p>

<p>We thank K. Yoshida for technical support for purifica-
tion of the enzymes. We also appreciate M. Kato for 
informatics support, Brad Weier, and Charmaine Yeoh 
for English editing, and the advice and encouragement of 
H. Furukawa, T. Kosaka, and M. Kubota. </p>

<p>Authors Contribution </p>

<p>Kubota, Inaba, Ichikawa, Takahashi, Izumi, and Shinagawa 
participated in research design. Kubota, Nakano, Watanabe, 
Sakurai, and Fukushima conducted experiments. Kubota, 
Nakano, Watanabe, Sakurai, and Fukushima performed 
data analysis. Kubota, Inaba, Izumi, and Shinagawa wrote 
or contributed to the writing of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Disclosures </p>

<p>All of the authors are employee of Daiichi Sankyo group 
who co-developed CS-917. </p>



<p>Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes 
K. Kubota et al. </p>

<p> </p>

<p>
K. Kubota et al. 
Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes </p>

<p>Supporting Information </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the 
online version of this article: </p>

<p>Figure S1. Organelle fractionation of CS-917 esterase 
activity in monkey small intestine. The monkey small 
intestine was minced and homogenized in 9 volumes of 
10 mmol/L HEPES, pH 7.0, including 0.25 mol/L sucrose 
(homogenate buffer). The homogenate was centrifuged at 
600g for 10 min and the pellet was resuspended in the 
same volume of the homogenate with homogenate buffer 
(nucleus). The supernatant was centrifuged at 8000g for 
10 min and the pellet was resuspended in the same vol-
ume of the supernatant with homogenate buffer (mito-
chondria). The supernatant was centrifuged at 105,000g 
for 60 min and the pellet was resuspended in the same 
volume of the supernatant with homogenate buffer 
(microsome). The supernatant was collected as cytosol. In 
addition, a part of the homogenate was sonicated and 
centrifuged at 105,000g for 60 min. The supernatant was 
collected as soluble fraction and the pellet was resus-
pended in the same volume of the homogenate with 
homogenate buffer (insoluble fraction). The data are 
shown as the average of duplicates with error bars repre-
senting the minimum and maximum values. 
Figure S2. Purification and identification of CS-917 ester-
ase activity from the small intestine of monkey #1. (A) 
Fractions of the fourth purification step of the first active 
peak were subjected to SDS-PAGE and the gel was stained 
by a florescent dye. Bands of 30 kDa, 17 and 15 kDa cor-
relating well with the enzyme activity are indicated by 
arrowheads. (B) The enzyme activity of the fractions 
(solid line) and the intensity of the arrowed bands of 
30 kDa in (A) are shown as bars, respectively. (C) Frac-
tions of the fourth purification step of the second active 
peak were subjected to SDS-PAGE and the gel was stained 
by a florescent dye. Bands of 26 and 17 kDa correlating 
well with the enzyme activity are indicated by arrowheads. 
(D) The enzyme activity of the fractions (solid line) and 
the intensity of the arrowed bands of 26 kDa in (C) are 
shown as bars, respectively. The data are shown as the 
average of duplicates with error bars representing higher 
value. 
Figure S3. Esterase activity of ELA2A and ELA2B. 
Recombinant human ELA2A and ELA2B were purified 
and subjected to esterase assay using Suc-AAPL-PNA as 
substrate with or without prior activation by trypsin. Sub-
strate (300 lg/mL) was incubated with enzymes or buffer 
in 100 mmol/L HEPES, pH 7.0, 200 lg/mL BSA, and 
500 mmol/L NaCl for 1 h and OD 405 nm was mea-
sured. </p>

<p>Figure S4. PMSF inhibition on CS-917 esterase activity of 
recombinant human CTSA. Recombinant human CTSA 
activated and pre-incubated with PMSF at 37°C for 
5 min. PMSF treated CTSA was subjected to CS-917 
esterase assay. CS-917 esterase activity was normalized the 
activity without PMSF treatment. The data are shown as 
the average of duplicates with error bars representing the 
minimum and maximum values. 
Figure S5. Immunodepletion of CTSA in human jejunal 
and liver S9. Human jejunal S9, human liver S9 or 
human recombinant CTSA (1 lg/mL) was mixed with 
anti-CTSA antibody (MAB1049; R&amp;D systems) with the 
indicated concentration and protein G beads at 4°C for 
2 h. The mixture was centrifuged and the supernatant 
was subjected to CS-917 esterase activity. CS-917 esterase 
activity was normalized by the activity without immuno-
precipitation (No-IP). The data are shown as the average 
of duplicates with error bars representing the minimum 
and maximum values. 
Figure S6. BNPP inhibition on CS-917 esterase activity in 
human liver S9. Human liver S9 with or without dialysis 
was pre-incubated with DMSO (negative control) or 
BNPP dissolved in DMSO with indicated concentration 
at 37°C for 5 min, and was subjected to CS-917 esterase 
assay. CS-917 esterase activity was normalized by the 
activity of DMSO-treated. The data are shown as the 
average of duplicates with error bars representing higher 
value. 
Figure S7. Organelle fractionation of R-134450 phospho-
ramidase activity in monkey liver. The monkey liver was 
minced and homogenized in 9 volumes of 10 mmol/L 
HEPES, pH 7.0, including 0.25 mol/L sucrose (homoge-
nate buffer). The homogenate was centrifuged at 600g for 
10 min and the pellet was resuspended in the same vol-
ume of the homogenate with homogenate buffer 
(nucleus). The supernatant was centrifuged at 8000g for 
10 min and the pellet was resuspended in the same vol-
ume of the supernatant with homogenate buffer (mito-
chondria). The supernatant was centrifuged at 105,000g 
for 60 min and the pellet was resuspended in the same 
volume of the supernatant with homogenate buffer 
(microsome). The supernatant was collected as cytosol. In 
addition, a part of the homogenate was sonicated and 
centrifuged at 105,000g for 60 min. The supernatant was 
collected as soluble fraction and the pellet was resus-
pended in the same volume of the homogenate with 
homogenate buffer (insoluble fraction). The data are 
shown as the average of duplicates with error bars repre-
senting the minimum and maximum values. 
Figure S8. Gel filtration chromatography (GFC) fraction-
ation of R-134450 phosphoramidase activity in monkey </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 18 </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes 
K. Kubota et al. </p>

<p>liver. Twenty to seventy percent saturated ammonium 
sulfate precipitation of the cytosolic fraction of monkey 
liver was dissolved in 50 mmol/L HEPES, pH 7.0, 
150 mmol/L NaCl, 0.1% CHAPS, 5 mmol/L MgCl 2 and 
1 mmol/L DTT, and subjected to gel filtration column 
(Superdex 75 10/300 GL; GE Healthcare). A part of frac-</p>

<p>tion was sampled and assessed by R-134450 phospho-
ramidase assay. Estimated molecular weight based on gel 
filtration standard was indicated by arrows with molecu-
lar weight. The data are shown as the average of dupli-
cates with error bars representing higher value. </p>

<p>ª 2015 Daiichi Sankyo RD Novare Co., LTD. Pharmacology Research &amp; Perspectives published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, 
British Pharmacological Society and American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. </p>

<p>2015 | Vol. 3 | Iss. 3 | e00138 
Page 19 </p>

<p>K. Kubota et al. 
Identification of CS-917 Activating Enzymes </p>

</text></tei>