<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4634622" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Development an effective vaccine against Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) 
is urgent and limited information is available on vaccination in nonhuman primate (NHP) model. We herein report 
of evaluating a recombinant receptor-binding domain (rRBD) protein vaccine in a rhesus macaque model. 
Methods: Nine monkeys were randomly assigned to high-dose, low-dose and mock groups,which were immunized 
with different doses of rRBD plus alum adjuvant or adjuvant alone at different time points (0, 8, 25 weeks). Immu-
nological analysis was conducted after each immunisation. Monkeys were challenged with MERS-CoV at 14 days 
after the final immunisation followed by observation for clinical signs and chest X-rays. Nasal, oropharyngeal and 
rectal swabs were also collected for analyses. Monkeys were euthanized 3 days after challenge and multiple speci-
mens from tissues were collected for pathological, virological and immunological tests. 
Conclusion: Robust and sustained immunological responses (including neutralisation antibody) were elicited by the 
rRBD vaccination. Besides, rRBD vaccination alleviated pneumonia with evidence of reduced tissue impairment and 
clinical manifestation in monkeys. Furthermore, the rRBD vaccine decreased viral load of lung, trachea and oropha-
ryngeal swabs of monkeys. These data in NHP paves a way for further development of an effective human vaccine 
against MERS-CoV infection. 
The Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) is the 
only lineage C betacoronavirus known to infect humans (Annan et al., 
2013; Anthony et al., 2013; van Boheemen et al., 2012). Similarly to se-
vere acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV), MERS-CoV in-
fection can result in acute respiratory distress syndrome and organ 
dysfunction, including progressive renal function impairment (Zaki 
et al., 2012). According to the World Health Organization, by the end of 
12 August 2015, a total of 1401 cases had been laboratory confirmed, </p>

<p>with at least 500 deaths following MERS-CoV infection. Among them, 
186 MERS-CoV infection cases, including 36 deaths, had been reported 
by the Republic of Korea (http://www.who.int/csr/don/12-august-2015-
mers-saudi-arabia/en/). These recent clustered cases firstly sprang up 
outside the Arabian Peninsula, indicating the potential human-to-
human transmission of MERS-CoV. To date, no specific antiviral drug 
exists for MERS-CoV infection and supportive treatment is the mainstay 
of management (Zumla et al., 2015). Ribavirin and interferon alfa-2b 
exhibited potential in a rhesus macaque model (Falzarano et al., 2013a, 
b), but in a retrospective cohort study, ribavirin and interferon alfa-2a 
therapy was associated with significantly improved survival at 14 days, 
but not at 28 days in patients with severe MERS-CoV infection (Omrani 
et al., 2014). Besides, specific peptide fusion inhibitors of MERS-CoV (Lu 
et al., 2014), convalescent sera from recovered patient and human mono-
clonal neutralising antibodies (Jiang et al., 2014; Tang et al., 2014; Ying 
et al., 2014) provided a novel approach to MERS-CoV treatment. Howev-
er, more data are needed from animal studies and carefully done clinical 
studies (Zumla et al., 2015). Therefore, developing a prophylactic vaccine 
against MERS-CoV infection remains a priority (Papaneri et al., 2015). </p>

<p>EBioMedicine 2 (2015) 1438-1446 </p>

<p>☆ One sentence summary: Protective immunity of the MERS-CoV RBD vaccine in 
monkeys. 
⁎ Correspondence to: C. Qin, Institute of Laboratory Animal Sciences, Chinese Academy 
of Medical Sciences, No. 5, Panjiayuan Nanli, Chaoyang District, Beijing, China. 
⁎⁎ Correspondence to: W. Tan, Key Laboratory of Medical Virology, Ministry of Health, 
National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, China CDC, 155 Changbai 
Road, ChangPing District, Beijing 102206, China. 
E-mail addresses: qinchuan@pumc.edu.cn (C. Qin), tanwj28@163.com (W. Tan). 
1 Co-first authors. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ebiom.2015.08.031 
2352-3964/© 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>EBioMedicine </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e b i o m e d i c i n e . c o m </p>

<p>Considerable evidence has proved that recombinant receptor bind-
ing domain (rRBD)-based subunit vaccine is a promising candidate vac-
cine against the SARS-CoV infection. As rRBD of SARS-CoV Spike protein 
induced strong neutralisation antibody and long-term protective im-
munity in rabbits and mice and completely protected immunized 
mice from SARS-CoV infection (Zhu et al., 2013). Furthermore, high ti-
tres of neutralisation antibodies in non-human primates (NHP) were in-
duced by vaccination with the rRBD of SARS-CoV (Wang et al., 2012). 
Experience using rRBD-based subunit vaccines against SARS could in-
form the design of a rRBD-based MERS vaccine. Several human 
neutralising antibodies targeting the RBD of the MERS-CoV spike pro-
tein, have been identified from the naïve-antibody library (Tang et al., 
2014; Ying et al., 2014), suggesting that RBD contains epitopes that 
can induce nAbs and therefore may represent a target antigen against 
MERS-CoV. Our group and others have confirmed rRBD protein 
induced strong neutralising antibody responses against MERS-CoV 
infection in mice and rabbits (Du et al., 2013; Lan et al., 2014; Ma 
et al., 2014; Mou et al., 2013; Zhang et al., 2015). Although the rRBD sub-
unit vaccine is a highly potent neutraliser of antibodies and T-cell im-
mune responses, no formulation has been tested on a higher animal 
model with MERS-CoV challenge to verify its prophylactic efficacy 
(Gretebeck and Subbarao, 2015). Recently, MERS-CoV infection and 
disease animal models have been developed (Agrawal et al., 2015; de 
Wit et al., 2013a,b; Falzarano et al., 2014; Munster et al., 2013; Pascal 
et al., 2015; Yao et al., 2013; Zhao et al., 2014), including a rhesus ma-
caque model of naturally permissive MERS-CoV disease (de Wit et al., 
2013a,b; Munster et al., 2013; Yao et al., 2013). We herein evaluate a 
rRBD subunit vaccine in a rhesus macaque model, to identify a prophy-
lactic approach that could be used in humans to prevent MERS-CoV 
infection. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>2.1. Ethics Statement </p>

<p>Animal studies were conducted in strict accordance with the Guide 
for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the People's Republic of 
China. The study protocol was approved by the Committee on the Ethics 
of Animal Experiments of the Chinese Centre for Disease Control and 
Prevention. The approved registration number is 20140609015. To 
comply with 3R (reduction, replacement, refinement) animal experi-
ment principles, a total of 9 rhesus macaques were used. 
During experiments, all procedures were performed under ethyl 
ether anaesthesia, and every effort was made to minimise suffering. Fol-
lowing inoculation with MERS-CoV, all experiments were conducted 
within an animal biosafety level 3 (ABSL-3) facilities. </p>

<p>2.2. Virus and Cell Culture </p>

<p>MERS-CoV strain (hCoV-EMC/2012) was kindly provided by 
Professor Fouchier (Erasmus Medical Centre, Netherlands). MERS-CoV 
seed stocks were propagated in Vero cells (ATCC Number: CCL-81) 
without mycoplasma contamination maintained in Dulbecco's Modified 
Eagle Medium (DMEM, Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% foetal 
bovine serum (FBS), 100 international units (IU)/mL penicillin, and 
100 μg/mL streptomycin, cultured at 37°C in 5% CO 2 . Seed stocks were 
diluted to the desired titre and used to determine the MERS-CoV 50% 
tissue culture infection dose (TCID 50 ), and for neutralising antibody 
and virus inoculation assays. </p>

<p>2.3. Vaccine Formulation </p>

<p>MERS-CoV rRBD protein, containing a 240-amino-acid fragment 
spanning residues 367-606, was prepared using a baculovirus expres-
sion vector system and purified through a HisTrap HP and Superdex 
200 column (GE Healthcare, Bucks, UK) as described previously (Lan </p>

<p>et al., 2014; Lu et al., 2013). The rRBD protein was admixed with alumin-
ium hydroxide (alum) adjuvant 1 day before immunisation. </p>

<p>2.4. Animal Immunisation and MERS-CoV Challenge </p>

<p>Nine monkeys were randomly assigned to high-dose (H), low-dose 
(L), and mock (M) groups (Table 1). High-dose animals were primed 
with 200 μg rRBD and boosted with 100-μg rRBD admixed with 1 mg 
of alum adjuvant. The three low-dose animals were primed with 50 μg 
rRBD and boosted with 25 μg rRBD admixed with 1 mg of alum adju-
vant; control animals were immunised with PBS with 1 mg of alum 
adjuvant. Animals received their second immunisation 8 weeks subse-
quent to their first. To assess long-term immunological responses, the 
interval between the second and third immunisations was 17 weeks. 
Each vaccine formulation was administered intramuscularly (i.m.). 
Two weeks after each immunisation, animals were bled periodically to 
obtain serum and peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) for im-
munological analysis. 
One week after the final immunisation, animals were transferred to 
an ABSL-3 laboratory. Following an adaptive phase of 1 week, nine 
immunised monkeys were anaesthetised and inoculated intratracheally 
with MERS-CoV of the hCoV-EMC strain at a dosage of 6.5 × 10 
7 TCID 50 , </p>

<p>diluted in 1-mL DMEM. After the challenge with MERS-CoV, monkeys 
were observed twice daily, with detailed recording of clinical signs 
and symptoms, morbidity and mortality, including the nature, onset, se-
verity and duration of all gross or visible changes. Chest X-rays were 
performed 1 day pre-and 1 and 3 days post-inoculation (dpi) with 
MERS-CoV. Nasal, oropharyngeal and rectal swabs were collected at 
the same time points. Three days after challenge with MERS-CoV, mon-
keys were euthanized and tissue specimens, including lungs, trachea, 
spleen and kidney, were collected for various pathological, virological, 
and immunological tests. The schematic of the vaccination schedule 
and biological specimen collection timeline are displayed in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>2.5. IgG Antibody Analyses Using Enzyme-linked Immunosorbent Assay 
(ELISA) </p>

<p>Animals were bled periodically throughout the study (Fig. 1) to de-
rive serum for antibody detection. Endpoint anti-RBD IgG antibody ti-
tres were determined by ELISA as described previously (Lan et al., 
2014). </p>

<p>2.6. Pseudovirus Neutralisation Assay </p>

<p>A MERS-CoV pseudovirus system was conducted within biosafety 
level-2 facilities as reported previously (Lan et al., 2014). Relative 
light units were determined immediately using a Gaomax lumino-
meter (Promega). All experiments were performed in triplicate. The 
pseudovirus inhibition (PI) rate was calculated as follows: </p>

<p>ðRelative luciferase units of mock sera -Relative luciferase units of 
immune serum for a given dilutionÞ = Relative luciferase units of 
mock sera: </p>

<p>2.7. Neutralising Antibody to hCoV-EMC </p>

<p>The virus neutralisation assay was conducted on Vero Cells. Briefly, 
sera were diluted twofold and mixed with 50 μL of 2 × 10 
3 TCID 50 /mL </p>

<p>virus, incubated at 37°C for 1 h in quadruplicate. Thereafter, 100-μL 
virus-serum mixture was added to Vero cells previously seeded at 
1.5 × 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>/well. Inoculated plates were incubated in a CO 2 incubator at 
37°C for 3 days, following which the cytopathic effects (CPEs) of the 
virus were observed microscopically at 40 × magnification. All tests 
were repeated twice independently. </p>

<p>1439 
J. Lan et al. / EBioMedicine 2 (2015) 1438-1446 </p>

<p>2.8. Enzyme-linked Immunospot Assay (ELISpot) </p>

<p>To evaluate the antigen-specific T-cell response induced by rRBD 
protein in immunised monkeys, an IFN-γ ELISpot assay was performed 
as described previously (Wen et al., 2013). After PBMCs were isolated 
from EDTA-treated blood, IFN-γ ELISpot assay was carried out according 
to the manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, 2.5 × 10 
5 cells per well were </p>

<p>stimulated with pools of 15-mer peptides overlapping by 11 amino 
acids spanning the RBD protein of MERS-CoV at a final concentration 
of 4 μg/mL into a PVDF membrane-bottomed plate pre-coated with 
anti-monkey IFN-γ capture antibody. A set of negative control wells 
comprising media only were included on each plate. After stimulation 
for 20-24 h, IFN-γ-spot-forming cells were detected by staining 
membranes with the detection antibody (7-B6-1-biotin) followed 
by streptavidin-horseradish peroxidase and development with TMB 
(3, 3′, 5, 5′-tetramethylbenzidine) substrate solution. Results are pre-
sented as spot-forming cells per 10 
6 PBMCs. Values were reported as </p>

<p>the mean of the test wells minus the mean of all negative-control wells. </p>

<p>2.9. RNA Extraction and Quantification Real-time Polymerase Chain Reac-
tion (qRT-PCR) </p>

<p>Total RNA was isolated from individual samples using the RNeasy 
Mini Kit (Qiagen) and reverse transcription reactions were performed 
using the Superscript III First Strand Synthesis Kit (Invitrogen), as de-
scribed previously (Yao et al., 2013), to derive complementary DNA 
(cDNA). All cDNA samples were stored at −20°C until use in the qRT-
PCR, targeted to upE as described previously (Corman et al., 2012). </p>

<p>2.10. Viral Isolation From Tissue and Swab Samples </p>

<p>Even though the qRT-PCR is considered as a highly sensitive assay 
for detection the viral nucleic acid, an assay of viral isolation is absolute 
necessity to detect the real viral replication. To this end, all tissues were 
homogenised to a final 10% suspension in DMEM and clarified by low-</p>

<p>speed centrifugation at 4500 g for 30 min at 4°C. Swab samples were 
immersed in 1-mL DMEM, vortexed, and clarified by low-speed centri-
fugation at 5000 g for 10 min at 4°C. Virus titres were determined in 
Vero cell monolayers grown in 96-well plates as described previously 
(Yao et al., 2013). In brief, 1.5 × 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>/well of Vero cells were seeded in 
a 96-well plate and incubated overnight at 37°C in a CO 2 incubator. 
One-hundred microliters of 10-fold serially diluted suspension was 
then added to each well in quadruplicate. The virus was allowed to ad-
sorb to the cells at 37°C for 1 h. After adsorption, viral inocula were re-
moved, and 100 μL of DMEM (2% FBS) was added to each well. Plates 
were incubated in a CO 2 incubator at 37°C for 3 days, following which 
CPEs were observed microscopically at 40× magnification. The virus ti-
tres expressed as the TCID 50 of each specimen were calculated by the 
Reed-Muench method. </p>

<p>2.11. Histopathology and Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Necropsy was performed on all animals according to the standard 
protocol. Lung, trachea, spleen and kidney tissue samples were collected 
for histopathological and immunohistochemical examination. Proce-
dures were performed using fixed 10% neutral buffered formalin, em-
bedded in paraffin, sequential sectioned to 4-μm thickness, and 
stained with haematoxylin and eosin (HE) prior to examination 
by light microscopy. For immunohistochemistry analysis, staining 
methods included antigen retrieval with citrate buffer. A rabbit-
serum-derived polyclonal antibody against nucleoprotein (Sino Biolog-
ical Inc., cat: 100213-RP02) at 1:1000 dilution, was then incubated with 
the sections. The secondary antibody used was goat anti-rabbit (ZSGB-
Bio, cat: pv-9001) at 1:2000. Finally, results were evaluated using light 
microscopy. To acquire a subject result, different and multiple sites of 
the lung, trachea, spleen and kidney tissue samples were collected for 
the histopathology and immunohistochemistry analysis. Finally, quanti-
tation of 4-5 slides per animal was used to assess the effect and impact 
of the immunized animals. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Schematic diagram of the rRBD vaccination and MERS-CoV challenge schedule. Monkeys were immunised three times intramuscularly (i.m.), at intervals of 8 or 17 weeks, and in-
oculated intratracheally with hCoV-EMC at a dosage of 6.5 × 10 
7 TCID 50 (red arrow). Monkeys were bled periodically at 2, 10, and 25 weeks (−14 days), and at −1 day, 1 day and 3 days. </p>

<p>Additionally, nasal, oral and rectal swabs were collected at −1 day, 1 day and 3 days. Chest X-rays were performed 1 day before inoculation, and at 1 and 3 dpi. Following euthanasia, lung, 
trachea, spleen and kidney specimens of challenged monkeys were acquired at 3 dpi for detection. </p>

<p>Table 1 
Rhesus macaque vaccination group. </p>

<p>Group 
Code 
Gender 
Age 
Vaccine 
Immunisation (i.m.) 
Challenge (i.t.) with 
MERS-CoV (TCID 50 ) 
1st 
2nd 
3rd </p>

<p>M (mock) 
6# 
M 
6 
PBS 
100 μL 
100 μL 
100 μL 
6.5 × 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>4# 
M 
7 
12# 
F 
5 
H (high-dose) 
B# 
M 
6 
rRBD 
200 μg 
100 μg 
100 μg 
6.5 × 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>F# 
F 
5 
G# 
F 
7 
L (low-dose) 
A# 
M 
5 
rRBD 
50 μg 
2 5 μg 
2 5 μg 
6.5 × 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>D# 
M 
7 
H# 
F 
7 </p>

<p> 
J. Lan et al. / EBioMedicine 2 (2015) 1438-1446 </p>

<p>2.12. Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were conducted using one-way ANOVA with 
Bonferroni post-test via the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> for Windows software package (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 17</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). Unpaired two-tailed Student's t test 
was used to compare means between different groups. A value of 
p b 0.05 was taken to indicate statistical significance. Results are 
expressed as mean ± SD. All figures were rendered using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">5</rs> 
software package (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>, CA, USA). </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. rRBD Vaccination Induced Sustained and Robust Immunity in the 
Rhesus Macaque </p>

<p>To assess the humoral immune response to the rRBD vaccine in 
rhesus macaques, total anti-MERS-CoV RBD IgG antibody titres were de-
termined by ELISA. Low titres of IgG in serum samples before prime vac-
cination were detected, possibly due to non-specific responses. IgG 
titres in the high-dose group increased significantly (p b 0.05) after </p>

<p>the first vaccination (Fig. 2a), and achieved the highest titre of RBD-
specific IgG 2 weeks after the second immunisation. Sera IgG titre in 
the low-dose group increased (p b 0.05) only after the second 
immunisation, to almost the same level as that of the high-dose group. 
RBD-specific IgG in the sera of immunised rhesus macaques was pre-
served for at least 17 weeks without obvious decline. In addition, IgG 
titre increased rapidly after a subsequent boost. Increased IgG titre 
was particularly marked in the low-dose group. 
Circulating neutralising antibody titres were monitored simulta-
neously in a pseudovirus system. Neutralisation antibodies were detect-
ed only after the second vaccination. When the pseudovirus inhibition 
rate was at 50% (PI 50 ), the neutralisation antibody titres of sera 
2 weeks after the second vaccination were 1:800 and 1:1600, in the 
low-and high-dose groups, respectively (Fig. 2b). Non-specific 
neutralisation antibody titres in the mock group were at 1:300. Detec-
tion of neutralisation antibodies in rRBD immunised monkeys persisted 
for at least 17 weeks. Neutralisation antibody titres (PI 50 ) of the sera 
were at 1:400 and 1:700 in the low-and high-dose groups, respectively 
(Fig. 2c). Encouragingly, following the next boost, immunisation 
neutralisation antibody titres (PI 50 ) were as high as 1:800 and 1:1200 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Humoral and cellular immune responses induced by rRBD vaccination. a. RBD-specific IgG antibody titres at the indicated time points after vaccine inoculation were monitored 
by ELISA. b-d. Neutralisation antibody titres in the sera of immunised rhesus macaques 2 weeks after the second vaccination; long-term observation (17-weeks) and the subsequent 
(i.e. third) vaccination booster were detected using a pseudovirus neutralisation system. e. Sera neutralisation antibodies were detected on Vero cells. f. ELISpot analysis of rhesus ma-
caques PBMCs derived at the indicated time points after rRBD immunisation. All of the detections were replicated for three times. *p b 0.01 and **p b 0.01. </p>

<p> 
J. Lan et al. / EBioMedicine 2 (2015) 1438-1446 </p>

<p>(Fig. 2d) which were almost identical to those 2 weeks after the second 
vaccination at week 10. At all detection time points, high-dose rRBD in-
duced higher neutralisation antibody titres in the pseudovirus system. 
Neutralisation antibody titres in sera following rRBD vaccination 
were also detected in Vero cells by the hCoV-EMC strain of MERS-CoV. 
Neutralisation antibody titres in the sera of rRBD immunised monkeys 
at week 10 were at 1:269 and 1:363 in the low-and high-dose groups, 
respectively (Fig. 2e). After 17 weeks, neutralisation antibody titres 
decreased slightly. Following a subsequent immunisation boost, 
neutralisation antibodies 1 day pre-MERS-CoV challenge were almost 
as high as at week 10. At all detection time points, non-specific 
neutralisation antibody titres in the mock group were lower or equal 
to 1:10. 
To assess the T-cell immune response, rhesus macaque PBMCs de-
rived at different times following rRBD immunisation were stimulated 
with overlapping synthetic peptides of RBD; ELISpot analyses were 
then conducted. Immunisation with rRBD proteins induced antigen spe-
cific IFN-γ-secreting T-cells. In addition, high-dose rRBD induced signif-
icantly higher levels of IFN-γ-secreting T-cells (Fig. 2f). </p>

<p>3.2. rRBD Vaccination Alleviated Pneumonia in the Rhesus Macaque Upon 
Challenge With MERS-CoV </p>

<p>Following MERS-CoV challenge, all monkeys were observed twice 
daily, with detailed recording of clinical signs, symptoms, morbidity, 
and mortality, including the nature, onset, severity, and duration of all 
gross or visible changes. After challenge, all monkeys, including rRBD-
immunised animals, drastically decreased their water intake. No infected 
monkeys exhibited excessive weight loss or died during the experiment. 
To monitor signs of pneumonia in MERS-CoV challenged animals, X-
ray examination was performed 1 day pre-, 1 and 3 days after MERS-
CoV inoculation. Radiography revealed that all monkeys were negative 
for pneumonia before MERS-CoV challenge (−1 day). In mock group </p>

<p>animals, local interstitial inflammation was detected at 1 dpi, with 
pneumonia diffused to adjacent pulmonary lobes at 3 dpi. Pneumonia 
generated in the high-dose group was delayed to 3 dpi, with infiltration 
confined to a single lobe (Fig. 3a). Although pneumonia was detected in 
low-dose monkeys at 1 dpi, infiltration and interstitial inflammation 
was less severe compared with the mock group. 
The gross pathology of challenged animals was investigated and 
necropsies were performed at 3 dpi following euthanasia. The lungs of 
mock group animals were congested with palpable nodules (Fig. 3b). 
Dark red discolouration and multifocal consolidation was consistent 
with the interstitial pneumonia indicated by X-ray examination. In con-
trast, haemorrhage and necrosis shown by black circle in the rRBD-
groups were smaller in both high and low dose immunization (Fig. 3b). 
To investigate pneumonia following MERS-CoV infection, histopath-
ological and immunohistochemical analyses were conducted to eluci-
date the effect of rRBD vaccination. Control monkey lung tissues 
exhibited moderate lesions (Fig. 4a) with abundant alveolar oedema, fi-
brin formation in the hyaline member and a small-to-moderate degree 
of macrophage fibrous infiltration (Fig. 4b). In contrast, a mild-to-
moderate-sized lesion was observed in the lung tissue of rRBD-
immunised monkeys (Fig. 4c-f). Infiltration of inflammatory cells was 
also detected in the tracheas of mock group monkeys (Fig. 4g). Although 
inflammatory cell infiltration and impaired epithelium in the tunica 
mucosa bronchiorum were also found in the rRBD vaccination group 
(Fig. 4h-i), all of the lesion were alleviated compared to the control 
group. Glomerular capsule expansion was observed in the kidneys of 
all challenge monkeys (data not shown), but this was considered an in-
cidental, clinically non-significant finding. No specific pathological 
changes were observed in the spleens of immunised monkeys (data 
not shown). Viral antigen, using a polyclonal antibody against nucleo-
protein, was found by IHC in the lungs (Fig. 5a-c) and tracheas 
(Fig. 5d−f) of all monkeys. No specific antigen was detected in the kid-
neys of challenged monkeys (data not shown). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Radiographic alterations and lung pathology. a. X-rays from rhesus macaques imaged prior to (−1 day) and post-MERS-CoV inoculation (1 day and 3 days). Areas of interstitial 
infiltration, indicative of pneumonia, are highlighted (circle). b. Gross pathology of the lungs from necropsied animals at 3 dpi. Haemorrhage and necrosis indicated by the black circle 
in both high and low dose immunisation groups were small and local, which happened in the mock group were large and disperse. M, H and L represent the mock, high-and low-
dose groups, respectively. </p>

<p> 
J. Lan et al. / EBioMedicine 2 (2015) 1438-1446 </p>

<p>3.3. rRBD Vaccination Decreased Viral Load in the Rhesus Macaque Upon 
Challenge </p>

<p>qRT-PCR, using upE gene primers specific for MERS-CoV, was con-
ducted to determine viral loads in serum, swabs and tissues, including 
lung, trachea and kidney. Viral RNA was detected in throat, nasal and 
rectal swabs (Fig. 6a) at 1 dpi and 3 dpi. Similarly, viral RNA in lung 
and tracheal tissue homogenate were detected at 3 dpi (Fig. 6b). Com-
pared with control monkeys, the rRBD vaccine decreased (p b 0.05) 
viral loads in the oronasopharynx swab, lungs and trachea. No viral 
RNA was detected in the kidney or serum of challenged monkeys. 
Virus titres of various tissues and swabs of immunised animals were 
determined by end-point titration in Vero cells. Viral loads in the lungs 
and trachea of control monkeys were as high as 50 and 100 TCID 50 /mL, 
respectively (Table 2), but rRBD-immunised monkeys could not isolate 
MERS-CoV from the lungs. Although MERS-CoV could be isolated from 
two of the six rRBD-immunised monkeys, virus titres were lower vs. 
the mock group. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>The MERS virus, which emerged in 2012, is now considered a threat 
to global public health. Developing an effective vaccine is important to 
control MERS-CoV infection. To date, virus-vector vaccines, such 
as recombinant modified vaccinia virus Ankara (MVA), which ex-
presses full-length MERS-CoV spike protein (MVA-MERS-S), and </p>

<p>recombinant adenoviral vectors encoding the full-length MERS-CoV S 
protein (Ad5.MERS-S) and the S1 extracellular domain of S protein 
(Ad5.MERS-S1), have been developed and tested for their ability to in-
duce virus-neutralising antibodies in mice (Kim et al., 2014; Song 
et al., 2013; Volz et al., 2015). Besides, the rRBD subunit vaccine confers 
a highly potent neutralising antibody and T-cell immune response in 
mice (Zhang et al., 2014). However, few studies have been assessed in 
response to MERS-CoV challenge to verify their efficacy, due to a lack 
of animal models. For example, mice (Coleman et al., 2014; Scobey 
et al., 2013), hamsters (de Wit et al., 2013a,b) and ferrets (Raj et al., 
2014) had not been proved to infect with MERS-CoV naturally. Recently, 
a small animal model of MERS-CoV infection was developed by trans-
ducing mice with an adenovirus vector expressing human DPP4 (Zhao 
et al., 2014). However, MERS-CoV infection in this model is highly de-
pendent on the transduction of cells and the level of DPP4 expression 
from the adenovirus vector, and therefore does not necessarily reflect 
the natural disease process (Falzarano et al., 2014). More recently a 
transgenic mouse model of MERS-CoV has been published (Agrawal 
et al., 2015). However, in this model, all cells of the mouse express 
human DPP4. This kind of non-physiological expression patterns result-
ed in extensive brain infection of MERS-CoV and rapidly succumbs to in-
fection in mice. Moreover, a novel humanized mouse model of MERS-
CoV infection was developed, though the mice were not acquired by 
routine technology (Pascal et al., 2015). Encouragingly, rhesus macaque 
models are naturally permissive to MERS-CoV disease, and more closely 
mimic the disease course in human patients (de Wit et al., 2013a,b; 
Munster et al., 2013; Yao et al., 2013). Furthermore, the effects of </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Histopathological changes in the lungs and tracheas of immunised rhesus macaques following MERS-CoV challenge. Three days after MERS-CoV inoculation, all monkeys were 
euthanised. Tissues were collected and stained with haematoxylin and eosin (H &amp; E). a-f. Pathological changes in the lungs of immunised monkeys. The black triangle indicates acute 
interstitial pneumonia diffused in lung tissue. The unfilled arrow indicates the hyaline member resulting from effusion of fibrin. The black arrow indicates the influx of inflammatory 
cells. g-i. Pathological findings of tracheas in immunised rhesus macaques. The black arrow highlights the infiltration of inflammatory cells in the tunica mucosa bronchiorum. The unfilled 
arrow indicates epithelium impairment in tunica mucosa bronchiorum. M, H and L represent the mock, high-and low-dose groups, respectively. </p>

<p> 
J. Lan et al. / EBioMedicine 2 (2015) 1438-1446 </p>

<p>interferon-α2b and ribavirin treatment have been evaluated in these 
models (Falzarano et al., 2013a,b). Therefore, we herein assessed rRBD 
vaccine efficacy in a NHP model. 
Similar as the rRBD protein of SARS-CoV which induced high titres of 
protective anti-RBD antibody responses in NHPs (Wang et al., 2012), the 
rRBD vaccination of MERS-CoV induced effective IgG and neutralisation 
antibodies in our rhesus macaque model. Besides, the induced IgG and 
neutralisation antibodies maintained for at least 17 weeks without obvi-
ous attenuation. Following a subsequent boost, antibody titres reached 
almost their previous peak level. There was no evident difference for in-
duction of the humoral immunity between high and low dose groups. 
However, high-dose vaccination induced a stronger T-cell response </p>

<p>than the low-dose vaccination. Following MERS-CoV challenge, rhesus 
macaques exhibited a transient lower respiratory tract infection, in ac-
cordance with previous reports (de Wit et al., 2013a,b; Munster et al., 
2013; Yao et al., 2013). Although infection was also detected in rRBD-
immunised animals, clinical signs were alleviated. Pathological changes 
in the lungs and tracheas of rRBD-immunised animals indicated re-
duced, but not fully absent lesions. Using qRT-PCR assay, viral loads in 
the lungs, trachea and oropharyngeal swabs of the rRBD vaccination 
groups were decreased. Furthermore, rRBD-immunised monkeys could 
not isolate MERS-CoV from the lungs while viral loads in the lungs and 
trachea of mock monkeys were as high as 50 and 100 TCID 50 /mL, respec-
tively. Consistent with the results of immunity elicited by high and low </p>

<p>Fig. 5. IHC staining of immunised rhesus macaque lung and trachea 3 days after MERS-CoV infection by a polyclonal antibody against nucleoprotein. a-c. IHC analysis of lung tissue. d-f. IHC 
staining of trachea tissue. Black arrows indicate the distribution of viral antigen. M, H and L represent mock, high-and low-dose groups, respectively. </p>

<p>Fig. 6. MERS-CoV loads in the swabs and tissues of immunised rhesus macaques following MERS-CoV infection detected by Real-time-PCR. a. Viral loads in swab samples at 1 dpi and 3 dpi. 
b. The viral loads in lung and trachea tissue 3 days after MERS-CoV infection. All of the detections were replicated for three times. M, H and L represent mock, high-and low-dose groups, 
respectively. *p b 0.05. </p>

<p> 
J. Lan et al. / EBioMedicine 2 (2015) 1438-1446 </p>

<p>dose of rRBD vaccine, the protection against MERS-CoV infection in 
monkey could be contributed to the humoral immune especially the 
neutralising antibodies rather than the cellular mediated immunity. 
Although rRBD vaccination alleviated pneumonia and decreased 
viral load in the rhesus macaque upon challenge with MERS-CoV in 
this study, it did not prevent the infection of MERS-CoV completely. 
The data should be interpreted with some cautions. First, the rhesus ma-
caque models to mimic MERS-CoV infection had inevitable limitations. 
In both the present and previous reports, MERS-CoV challenge in the 
rhesus macaque models resulted in transient infection of the lower re-
spiratory tract (de Wit et al., 2013a,b; Munster et al., 2013; Yao et al., 
2013) and the more severe or even lethal disease course frequently as-
sociated with human cases was not observed herein (van den Brand 
et al., 2015). Therefore, the prophylactic effects of the rRBD vaccine 
were not fully demonstrated in this model. Second, MERS-CoV chal-
lenge in the trachea bypasses the natural entry sites, such as nasal mu-
cosa and laryngeal areas of the pharynx which show as crucial regions of 
mucosal immunity (Sato and Kiyono, 2012), while, the bypassed muco-
sal immunity is the first defence against lots of infectious diseases, in-
cluding MERS-CoV (Neutra and K. P., 2006). Third, the challenge dose 
of 6.5 × 10 
7 TCID 50 , was markedly greater than typical MERS-CoV </p>

<p>exposure in humans. More recently, a progressive and lethal pneumonia 
was observed in a MERS-CoV challenged common marmoset model 
(Falzarano et al., 2014), in which the infected animals developed vire-
mia, and total RNA sequencing demonstrated the induction of immune 
and inflammatory pathways (Falzarano et al., 2014). Therefore, the 
marmoset model corresponds closely to the disease course in humans 
and allows for clearer discrimination between successfully treated and 
control animals. Therefore, the protective efficacy of this vaccine candi-
date remains to be tested in a more suitable disease model (e.g. com-
mon marmoset) or humans. 
To our knowledge, this study represents the first evaluation of the 
protective efficacy of a candidate subunit antigen against MERS-CoV in 
nonhuman primates. We observed sustained and significant antibody 
neutralisation and T-cell immunity in rhesus macaques in response to 
rRBD of MERS-CoV. Besides, the rRBD vaccination alleviated pneumonia 
and decreased viral load in the rhesus macaque upon challenge with 
MERS-CoV. In summary, our results provide insight into the immunoge-
nicity of an rRBD subunit vaccine against MERS-CoV. All these data indi-
cate that the subunit rRBD vaccine confers partial protection against 
MERS-CoV challenge in rhesus macaques, which could be useful for fu-
ture MERS-CoV vaccine trials and prevention strategies. </p>

<p>Competing Interests </p>

<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </p>

<p>Author Contributions </p>

<p>WJT, GFG and CQ conceived the project and design the research; JML, 
YD,HC and WW conducted the majority of the vaccination experiments; 
GWL and GFG provided the RBD protein and final editing of the manu-
script; YFY, WD, LLB and QW assisted with the MERS-CoV challenge and 
the protection studies in the ABSL-3 facility. JML, YFY, CQ and WJT wrote 
the manuscript; and all authors review and approved the manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by grants from the Megaproject 
for Infectious Disease Research of China (2014ZX10004001-002, 
2012ZX10004501-004, and 2013ZX10004601), the Megaproject for 
Novel Drug Discovery of China (2014ZX09102-044-003), National Nat-
ural Sciences Fund of China (81302607) and National 973 Program of 
China (2011CB504704). The funders had no role in study design, data 
collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the 
manuscript. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank Drs. Bart L.Haagmans and Ron 
A.M.Fouchier (Erasmus MC, Rotterdam, The Netherlands) for providing 
MERS-CoV (isolate hCoV-EMC/2012). </p>



<p>Table 2 
Virus isolation in rhesus macaque tissues inoculated with MERS-CoV at 1 or 3 dpi (logTCID 50 /mL). </p>

<p>Group 
Nasal swab 
Throat swab 
Anal swab 
Lung 
Trachea 
Kidney 
Spleen 
Serum </p>

<p>1 day 
3 days 
1 day 
3 days 
1 day 
3 days 
3 days 
3 days 
3 days 
3 days 
3 days </p>

<p>M 
-
-
-
-
-
-
1.67 
2 
-
-
-
H 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
b1 
-
-
-
L 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
1 
-
-
-</p>

<p> 
J. Lan et al. / EBioMedicine 2 (2015) 1438-1446 </p>



<p> 
J. Lan et al. / EBioMedicine 2 (2015) 1438-1446 </p>

</text></tei>