<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4150213" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:46+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>MUC1 interacts with b-catenin and p120 catenin to modulate WNT signaling. We investigated the effect of overexpressing MUC1 on 
the regulation of cyclin D1, a downstream target for the WNT/b-catenin signaling pathway, in two human pancreatic cancer cell 
lines, Panc-1 and S2-013. We observed a significant enhancement in the activation of cyclin D1 promoter-reporter activity in poorly 
differentiated Panc1.MUC1F cells that overexpress recombinant MUC1 relative to Panc-1.NEO cells, which express very low levels of 
endogenous MUC1. In stark contrast, cyclin D1 promoter activity was not affected in moderately differentiated S2-013.MUC1F cells 
that overexpressed recombinant MUC1 relative to S2-013.NEO cells that expressed low levels of endogenous MUC1. The S2-013 cell 
line was recently shown to be deficient in p120 catenin. MUC1 is known to interact with P120 catenin. We show here that re-
expression of different isoforms of p120 catenin restored cyclin D1 promoter activity. Further, MUC1 affected subcellular localization 
of p120 catenin in association with one of the main effectors of P120 catenin, the transcriptional repressor Kaiso, supporting the 
hypothesis that p120 catenin relieved transcriptional repression by Kaiso. Thus, full activation of cyclin D1 promoter activity requires 
b-catenin activation of TCF-lef and stabilization of specific p120 catenin isoforms to relieve the repression of KAISO. Our data show 
MUC1 enhances the activities of both b-catenin and p120 catenin. </p>

<p>4,5   b-catenin 
6,7 or Grb2/SOS, 
8 following phosphorylation by GSK-
3b, 
9 c-Src, 
10 EGFR, 
11 PKC-d, 
12 Lyn 
13 or ZAP-70. 
14 MUC1 CT 
modulates signaling in other pathways including those that 
affect cell proliferation, migration and invasion. </p>

<p>15,16   MUC1 is overexpressed by different adenocarcinomas including 
pancreatic cancer. 
17 Previously, we reported that under conditions 
of MUC1 expression, fragments of the MUC1 CT were detected in 
the cytosol and nucleus of human pancreatic cancer cell lines, 
Panc-1.MUC1F and S2-013.MUC1F, and that the MUC1 CT 
associated with and stabilized the steady-state level of nuclear 
b-catenin. 
18 A well-documented functional consequence of the 
nuclear translocation and accumulation of b-catenin during WNT 
signaling is that nuclear b-catenin binds to LEF/Tcf-4 transcription 
factors and changes the architectural conformation of DNA, 
resulting in the transcriptional activation of several genes </p>

<p>including cyclin D1, c-myc, connexin 43 and c-jun. 
19-21 Recent 
reports suggest that MUC1/b-catenin complexes influence the 
transcription of WNT target genes associated with carcinogenesis, 
including cyclin D1. </p>

<p>22   We previously observed that MUC1 expression stabilized 
b-catenin and obtained preliminary results showing that this 
significantly enhanced cyclin D1 promoter activity in one 
pancreatic cancer cell line, Panc1; however, a second pancreatic 
cancer cell line that was evaluated (S2-013) did not show any 
effects by MUC1 on cyclin D1 transcription. We therefore 
investigated further the deficiency of activity in the second cell 
line and discovered that this line lacked expression of p120 
catenin. Re-expression of p120 catenin in these cells restored 
cyclin D1 promoter activity and responsiveness to modulation by 
MUC1. Thus, this study provides insights into multiple aspects of 
molecular mechanisms whereby MUC1, P120 catenin and Kaiso 
modulate the activity of WNT signaling, and consequent effects on 
cellular proliferation of pancreatic cancer cells. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Expression of MUC1 promotes cyclin D1 gene promoter activity in 
some but not all pancreatic cancer cell lines 
Expression of MUC1 stabilizes b-catenin and enhances its steady-
state nuclear levels 
18 in pancreatic cancer cells including those 
used in the studies reported here. We explored the functional 
influence of MUC1 expression and association with nuclear 
b-catenin on the regulation of cyclin D1, a gene known to be 
regulated by b-catenin and LEF/Tcf-4. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Eppley Institute for Research in Cancer and Allied Diseases, University of Nebraska Medical Center, Omaha, NE, USA; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Gynecologic Oncology and Cancer Biology, 
University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX, USA and </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, University of Nebraska Medical Center, Omaha, NE, 
USA. Correspondence: Dr MA Hollingsworth, Eppley Institute for Research in Cancer and Allied Diseases, University of Nebraska Medical Center, 985950 Nebraska Medical Center, 
Omaha, NE 68198-5950, USA. 
E-mail: mahollin@unmc.edu </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Investigators from the laboratories of YW and MAH were responsible for the design and conduct of this work. 
Received 26 March 2014; revised 1 May 2014; accepted 6 May 2014 </p>

<p>Citation: Oncogenesis (2014) 3, e107; doi:10.1038/oncsis.2014.19 
&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 2157-9024/14 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/oncsis </p>

<p>As b-catenin functions in transcriptional regulation by providing 
a transactivation domain for forming bipartite complexes with 
other factors such as LEF/Tcf-4, which together serve as 
transcriptional coactivators, 
23 we initially evaluated the steady-
state levels of LEF/Tcf-4 protein in two human pancreatic cancer 
cell lines and confirmed that there were equivalent levels of 
expression of LEF/TCF4 in these cell lines (Supplementary 
Figure 1). Western blots of membrane/cytoplasmic and nuclear 
extracts of Panc-1 and S2-013 subclones expressing either high 
levels of recombinant MUC1 (MUC1F) or very low (Panc1.NEO) to 
low (S2-013.NEO) levels of endogenous MUC1 were probed with a 
monoclonal antibody (mAb) to Tcf-4. Irrespective of the levels of 
MUC1, nuclear Tcf-4 protein was expressed at relatively constant 
levels in each of the Panc-1 and S2-013 cell lines. 
Cyclin D1-promoter/luciferase-reporter assays were used to 
evaluate the effect of MUC1 expression on activation of cyclin 
D1 gene transcription. TCF/LEF-driven promoter activity was 
evaluated by using a TOPFLASH construct, which contains a 
1745-bp sequence of the human cyclin D1 promoter that includes 
a wild-type LEF/Tcf-4-binding site followed by a luciferase reporter 
gene. A construct that encoded the same cyclin D1 promoter 
region with a mutated LEF/Tcf-4-binding site (FOPFLASH) was 
used as a control. Each promoter/reporter construct was </p>

<p>transiently transfected into matched sets of two different 
pancreatic cancer cell lines expressing high levels of MUC1 and 
low or no detectable expression of MUC1-Panc-1 and -S2-013 
(Panc-1.MUC1F and S2-013.MUC1F expressed high levels of 
recombinant MUC1, and controls included S2-013.NEO (low levels 
of endogenous MUC1) and Panc-1.NEO cells (very low levels of 
endogenous MUC1)). 
There was no activity of cyclin D1 promoters with mutated 
LEF/Tcf-4-binding sites in NEO control and MUC1-expressing cells 
(Figure 1). In contrast, for the construct containing wild-type 
sequences, there was low cyclin D1 promoter activity in NEO 
control cells, but there was a significant enhancement (approxi-
mately 100-fold) for cyclin D1 promoter activity in Panc-1.MUC1F 
(Figure 1). This supported the hypothesis that WNT signaling 
through b-catenin-activated TCF/LEF in these cells and that 
MUC1 stabilization of b-catenin dramatically increased cyclin D1 
promoter activity. Curiously, however, we found that cyclin D1 
promoter activity in S2-013 cells was low and unresponsive to 
alterations in MUC1 expression (Figure 1), either in S2-013 cells 
expressing high levels of MUC1 or in cells in which the low levels 
of endogenous MUC1 was knocked down by RNA interference. 
This negative result indicated that MUC1 stabilization of b-catenin 
is not sufficient to activate or influence cyclin D1 promoter activity 
and that transactivation of the cyclin D1 gene promoter in this cell 
line is affected by other factors. 
We confirmed the consequences of expressing MUC1 on 
steady-state levels of endogenous cyclin D1 in the Panc1 and 
S2-013 pancreatic cancer cell lines. Consistent with the promoter-
reporter assay results, expression of MUC1 elevated the steady-
state level of cyclin D1 transcripts (data not shown) and cyclin 
D1 protein in Panc-1 cells, but not in S2-013 cells (Figure 2). These 
results suggest that expression of MUC1 contributes to the 
increase in cyclin D1 transcripts in the Panc-1 cells, but not in 
S2-013 cells. Previous studies reported that expression of MUC1 
co-activated the cyclin D1 gene by transactivation in human 
HCT116 colon carcinoma cells. 
24 A recent report suggests that 
MUC1 induces TCF7L2 transcription factor activation and promotes 
cyclin D1 expression in human breast cancer cells. 
22 Taken together, 
these results indicate that the effects of MUC1 expression on cyclin 
D1 gene expression vary among different cell types. </p>

<p>Re-expression of specific p120 catenin isoforms in S2-013 cells 
restore cyclin D1 promoter activity 
We recently reported that the S2-013 cell line is deficient in 
expression of p120 catenin, and that re-expression of p120 catenin 
in these cells stabilized and enhanced steady-state levels of 
b-catenin. 
15 P120 catenin is a member of the Armadillo repeat 
protein family that has multiple isoforms whose expression and 
localization varies depending on tissues and cell types. 
15 P120 
catenin stabilizes the cadherin-catenin adhesion complex at the 
plasma membrane, but also has additional roles in the cytoplasm 
and nucleus, where it has been reported to modulate transcription 
by associating with the transcriptional repressor Kaiso. 
25,26 We 
therefore examined p120 catenin expression in the Panc1 utilized 
here and sought to further investigate the effects of p120 catenin 
re-expression in S2-013 cells on MUC1 modulation of cyclin D1 
promoter activity. The western blot from Figure 3a confirms that 
S2-013 cells do not express p120 catenin and reveal that Panc-1 
cells express different isoforms of p120 catenin. Isoforms of p120 
catenin differ in amino termini because of alternative splicing and 
usage of alternate translation-initiating codons, each of which has 
a distinct start codon in the N-terminal region. 
27-30 Isoform 1 
contains a coiled-coil domain at the N-terminus; isoform 2 
contains the entire 'regulatory region'; isoform 3 has most of 
regulatory region; isoform 4 lacks the majority of the regulatory 
region. Panc-1 Neo cells expressed p120 isoform 3 and low levels 
of isoform 1. Expression of MUC1 in Panc-1 cells stabilized and </p>

<p>Figure 1. Luciferase assay detecting effect of MUC1 on cyclin 
D1 promoter activity. Cells were transfected with 300 or 600 ng of 
the reporter plasmids containing 1745 bp of the cyclin D1 gene 
promoter ( À 1745CD1Luc, TOPFLASH) consists of wild-type 
LEF-1/Tcf-4-binding site or reporter plasmids containing mutated 
LEF-1/Tcf-4-binding site in the cyclin D1 gene promoter (FOPFLASH), 
together with 400 ng of a synthetic Renilla luciferase reporter 
plasmids SV40 as transfection control. Each transfection was carried 
out in duplicate plates, and the data (relative lumenescence 
units-RLU) shown here are representative of three independent 
experiments. (a) Panc-1.MUC1F or Panc-1.Neo (95% confluence). 
(b) S2-013.MUC1F cells, S2-013.NEO cells, S2-013 GFP-NEO, 
two clones of S2-013 cells in which MUC1 was knocked down by 
MUC1-siRNA-S2-013.MTII.C1 and S2-013.MTII.C2 (95% confluence). </p>

<p>Activation of cyclin D1 gene transcription by expression of MUC1 
X Liu et al </p>



<p>Oncogenesis (2014), 1 -9 
&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>increased expression of different isoforms of p120 catenin, 
especially isoforms 1 and 4. 
Given the deficiency of p120 catenin expression in S2-013 cells, 
and the possibility p120 catenin could also influence WNT 
signaling through b-catenin, we elected to examine cyclin D1 
promoter activity in S2-013 cells that expressed different p120 
catenin isoforms in the presence of high-level and low-level 
expression of MUC1 (Figure 3b). Interestingly, different isoforms of 
p120 catenin expressed in S2-013 cells showed distinct subcellular 
localizations. P120 catenin 1A was mainly present on the cell 
membrane and cytoplasm. P120 catenin 3A showed greater </p>

<p>localization to the nucleus compared with other isoforms. P120 
catenin 4A was mostly distributed at the cell surface with a small 
amount detected in the cytoplasm (Figure 3c). Upon MUC1 
expression, the nuclear localizations of p120 catenin 1A and 3A 
were slightly increased. P120 catenin 4A was mostly localized on 
the cell membrane in the presence of MUC1 (Figure 3d). The 
distinct subcellular localizations of different p120 catenin isoforms 
is partly associated with distinct functions related to cell adhesion, 
motility and metastasis. </p>

<p>15   The differences in subcellular 
localization and functional domains in the different p120 catenin 
isoforms were also predicted to affect WNT signaling and </p>

<p>Panc-1.MUC1F 
Panc-1.NEO </p>

<p>Membrane/ 
cytoplasmic 
Extract </p>

<p>Nuclear 
Extract </p>

<p>35KD 
Cyclin D1 </p>

<p>-actin 
42KD </p>

<p>Membrane/ 
cytoplasmic 
Extract </p>

<p>Nuclear 
Extract </p>

<p>S2-013. 
MUC1F </p>

<p>S2-013. 
NEO </p>

<p>S2-013 
GFP-NEO </p>

<p>S2-013 MUC1-
siRNA#1 </p>

<p>S2-013 MUC1-
siRNA#2 </p>

<p>Membrane/ 
cytoplasmic 
Extract </p>

<p>Nuclear 
Extract </p>

<p>Membrane/ 
cytoplasmic 
Extract </p>

<p>Nuclear 
Extract </p>

<p>Membrane/ 
cytoplasmic 
Extract </p>

<p>Nuclear 
Extract </p>

<p>Membrane/ 
cytoplasmic 
Extract </p>

<p>Nuclear 
Extract </p>

<p>Membrane/ 
cytoplasmic 
Extract </p>

<p>Nuclear 
Extract </p>

<p>Cyclin D1 
35KD </p>

<p>42KD </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>DIC 
DIC </p>

<p>Mouse IgG 
Cyclin D1 </p>

<p>Panc-1.MUC1F </p>

<p>DIC </p>

<p>Cyclin D1 </p>

<p>Panc-1.NEO </p>

<p>DIC </p>

<p>Mouse IgG </p>

<p>=20 m </p>

<p>-actin </p>

<p>Figure 2. Western blot protein levels of cyclin D1 in pancreatic cancer cell lines. (a, b) Membrane/cytoplasmic extracts and nuclear extracts 
from Panc-1.MUC1F, Panc-1.NEO, S2-013.MUC1F, S2-013.NEO, S2-013 GFP-NEO, two clones of MUC1-siRNA S2-013 cells were subjected to 
4-20% SDS-PAGE and analyzed by immunoblot (IB) with an anti-cyclin D1 mAb and b-actin as a loading control. Right panel in a shows 
densitometry analysis of the signal for nuclear cyclin D1 normalized to the signal for b-actin. *Po0.01, significant difference. (c) Cyclin D1 
protein expression is enhanced by expression of MUC1 in Panc-1.MUC1F cells as compared with Panc-1.NEO cells. Confocal microscopy was used 
to determine the cyclin D1 protein expression in Panc-1.MUC1F and Panc-1.NEO cells. Cells grown above 90% confluence on coverslips were 
fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde and permeablized with Trixton X-100 before incubation with mAb anti-cyclin D1, which was identified with 
fluorescein isothiocyanate-conjugated secondary antibody and visualized as green color. Images were examined with a Zeiss LSM 410 laser 
scanning microscope (Bar ¼ 20 mM; Â 100 magnification; results shown here represent three or four individual cell scanning observations.). </p>

<p>Activation of cyclin D1 gene transcription by expression of MUC1 
X Liu et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
Oncogenesis (2014), 1 -9 </p>

<p>downstream transcriptional regulation, including cyclin D1 
promoter activity. Thus, we performed luciferase assays with 
S2-013 cell lines expressing the different p120 catenin isoforms 
with and without expression of MUC1. Strikingly, re-expression of 
p120 catenin 1A or 4A (but not 3A) significantly increased the 
cyclin D1 promoter activity in S2-013 cells compared with NEO 
control. Interestingly, superimposing MUC1 expression in this 
system significantly increased cyclin D1 activity only when co-
expressed with p120 catenin isoform 4A (Figure 4a). The effects of 
MUC1 and p120 catenin on cyclin D1 promoter activity were also 
reflected in levels of protein expression (Figure 4b). 
These data suggest that full activation of cyclin D1 promoter 
activity requires b-catenin activation of TCF-lef and stabilization of 
specific p120 catenin isoforms. Our data show that MUC1 
enhances the activities of both b-catenin and isoform 4A of 
p120 catenin in this system. </p>

<p>Different p120 catenin isoforms association with Kaiso 
We sought to investigate the mechanism by which p120 catenin 
was enhancing TCF/Lef activity on the cyclin D1 promoter. The 
transcriptional repressor Kaiso has been shown to bind to the 
cyclin D1 promoter and repress transcription in both a sequence-
specific and methylation-dependent manner, 
31 and it has been 
reported that p120 catenin can bind to Kaiso and de-repress its 
effects on transcription. 
25,26 We investigated the possibility that </p>

<p>specific isoforms of p120 catenin physically associate with Kaiso 
and sought to establish the precise subcellular localization of 
these complexes, given that binding in different subcellular 
locales might be associated with different types of activities. 
Result from proximity ligation assays revealed that Kaiso was 
highly associated with p120 catenin 3A in the nucleus (Figure 5) 
with less seen in the cytoplasm. P120 catenin isoform1A showed 
moderate and equivalent levels of interaction with Kaiso in both 
the nucleus and cytoplasm (Figure 5). P120 catenin isoform 4A 
showed higher levels of interaction with Kaiso in the cytoplasm 
(Figure 5). These differences in localization may explain in part the 
observed effects of different isoforms on cyclin D1 promoter 
activity. The high levels of interaction of p120 catenin isoform 3A 
with Kaiso in the nucleus (Figure 5) together with the results of 
cyclin D1 promoter activity (Figure 4) suggest that this isoform 
may not relieve Kaiso repression, whereas sequestration of Kaiso 
in the cytoplasm by p120 catenin isoforms 1A and 4A may enable 
de-repression of Kasio at the cyclin D1 promoter. </p>

<p>MUC1 expression or p120 catenin re-expression affects cell growth 
properties 
We evaluated growth rates of Panc-1 and S2-013 cells to 
investigate the functional consequences of cyclin D1 gene 
transcriptional activation and elevation of cyclin D1 protein in 
response to MUC1 expression and p120 catenin re-expression. 
There were dramatic and significant differences in the in vitro </p>

<p>-MUC1 
+ MUC1 </p>

<p>S2-013.Neo 
S2-013.p120.1A 
S2-013.p120.3A 
S2-013.p120.4A 
S2-013.MUC1 
S2-013.M.p120.1A 
S2-013.M.p120.3A 
S2-013.M.p120.4A </p>

<p>p120 catenin 
(PP120 ab) </p>

<p>MUC1.CT 
(CT2 ab) </p>

<p>Beta-actin </p>

<p>P120 .3A 
S2013 MUC1 Cyto 
S2013 Neo Cyto 
S2013 MUC1 Nu 
S2013 Neo Nu 
Panc1 MUC1 Cyto 
Panc1 Neo Cyto 
Panc1 MUC1 Nu 
Panc1 Neo Nu </p>

<p>IB: MUC1 
(CT2 ab) </p>

<p>IB: beta-actin </p>

<p>P120. 1A </p>

<p>P120 .4A </p>

<p>S2013 Neo </p>

<p>S2013. 1A </p>

<p>S2013. 3A </p>

<p>S2013. 4A </p>

<p>S2013 MUC1F </p>

<p>S2013. M.1A </p>

<p>S2013.M. 3A </p>

<p>S2013.M. 4A </p>

<p>DNA 
DIC 
Merge 
P120 ctn 
DNA 
DIC 
Merge 
P120 ctn </p>

<p>IB: p120 ctn 
(PP120 ab) </p>

<p>Figure 3. P120 catenin was not detected in S2-013 cells and re-expression of different p120 catenin isoforms in this cells showed distinct 
subcellular localization. (a) Membrane/cytoplasmic extracts and nuclear extracts from S2-013.NEO, S2-013.MUC1F, Panc-1.NEO, Panc-1.MUC1F 
were subjected to 10% SDS-PAGE and analyzed by immunoblot (IB) with an anti-p120 catenin mAb. The same blot was striped and reprobed 
with anti-MUC1.CT antibody. (b) Re-expression of different p120 catenin isoforms were confirmed by western blot using the same p120 
catenin antibody and MUC1 antibody. (c and d) Immunofluorescence analysis of re-expression of p120 catenin in S2-013 cells. The green color 
indicates stains for p120 catenin. Blue indicates 4 
0 -6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) staining for nuclei. The arrowhead indicates subcellular 
localization of p120 catenin in the nucleus. </p>

<p>Activation of cyclin D1 gene transcription by expression of MUC1 
X Liu et al </p>



<p>Oncogenesis (2014), 1 -9 
&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>growth rates of Panc1.MUC1F and Panc1.NEO cells (***Po0.0001), 
suggesting that expression of MUC1 and concomitant increases in 
cyclin D1 expression significantly enhance proliferation of Panc-1 
cells (Figure 6a). The growth rate of S2013 cells expressing 
different isoforms of p120 catenin (S2-013.1A, S2-013.3A, 
S2-013.4A) were slightly but statistically significantly higher than 
the S2-013.Neo (**Po0.05; Figure 6b). In addition, the growth rate 
of S2013 cells expressing MUC1 Flag (S2-013.MUC1F, S2-013.M.1A, 
S2-013.M.3A, S2-013.M.4A) were also significantly higher than 
S2-013.Neo (**Po0.05; Figure 6c). There were no significant 
differences among S2-013.MUC1F, S2-013.M.1A, S2-013.M.3A and 
S2-013.M.4A. These results suggest that enhanced levels of cyclin 
D1 following MUC1 expression or p120 catenin re-expression 
enhanced the growth rate of Panc-1 and S2-013 pancreatic cancer 
cell lines. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
MUC1 engages cytoplasmic signaling proteins that also engage in 
transcriptional regulation, such as b-catenin, directly influencing 
transcription of genes associated with malignant progression. The 
MUC1 CT associates with and stabilizes steady-state levels of 
b-catenin in the cytosol and nucleus. 
18 One functional con-
sequence of the cytoplasm-to-nucleus translocation of b-catenin 
during canonical WNT-signaling is the association of b-catenin and 
LEF/Tcf-4, which functions as part of a transcription factor complex 
that initiates expression of cyclin D1, c-Myc, connexin-43, c-Jun 
and other genes. 
19-21,23 It has been reported that LEF/Tcf-4 
complexes serve as architectural transcription factors that induce 
DNA conformational changes by binding to their target sequence 
via the HMG box. 
32 However, this protein-DNA interaction is not 
sufficient to initiate gene transcription, 
33 and requires association </p>

<p>with other transcription factors, such as b-catenin, which provide a 
transactivation domain and affect DNA-binding properties. </p>

<p>23   Studies have indicated that nuclear b-catenin and LEF/Tcf-4 
complexes were not sufficient for activation of gene expression, 
which suggested that at least one other component is required to 
activate gene expression and that this third component may vary 
with cell type. </p>

<p>34   We initially examined the capacity of MUC1 expression to 
influence cyclin D1 gene promoter activity by using cyclin D1 
gene-promoter-reporter assays. Two pancreatic tumor cell lines were 
investigated: Panc-1, a poorly differentiated pancreatic tumor cell 
line that expresses very low or undetectable levels of MUC1 mRNA 
and protein; the S2-013 pancreatic tumor cell line, a moderately 
differentiated tumor cell line that expresses low levels of endogen-
ous MUC1. Expression of MUC1 significantly enhanced cyclin D1 
promoter activity in Panc-1 cells, but not in S2-013. RNA interference-
mediated knockdown of endogenous MUC1 in S2-013 cells did not 
dramatically affect the activity of the cyclin D1 promoter. 
Expressing MUC1 in Panc-1, a cell line with little or no 
endogenous MUC1, enhanced the transcriptional co-activator 
status of b-catenin in association with LEF/Tcf-4, perhaps through 
increasing the steady-state nuclear levels of b-catenin. 
18 This 
interpretation was supported by the detection of protein-DNA 
interactions between nuclear b-catenin, LEF/Tcf-4 proteins 
and oligonucleotides based on the cyclin D1 promoter, in both 
Panc-1.MUC1F and Panc-1.NEO cells, and the finding of enhanced 
binding of b-catenin and LEF/Tcf-4 proteins to cyclin D1-promoter-
derived oligonucleotides in Panc-1.MUC1F cells as compared with 
Panc-1.NEO cells (data not shown). 
Steady-state levels of endogenous cyclin D1 transcripts and 
protein were affected by MUC1 expression as evidenced by results 
of northern blots (data not shown) and western blots (Figure 2). </p>

<p>Neo 
p120.1A 
p120.3A 
p120.4A 
MUC1 
M.p120.1A 
M.p120.3A 
M.p120.4A </p>

<p>CyclinD1 </p>

<p>-MUC1 
+ MUC1 </p>

<p>-tubulin </p>

<p>Figure 4. Re-expression of specific p120 catenin isoform restores cyclin D1 promoter activity and increases its protein expression level. 
(a) Luciferase reporter assay of cyclin D1 promoter. S2-013 cells with re-expression of different p120 catenin isoforms (with/without MUC1 
expression) were transfected with wild-type cyclin D1 reporter construct, which contains wild-type LEF-1/Tcf-4-binding site or reporter 
plasmids containing mutated LEF-1/Tcf-4-binding site in the cyclin D1 gene promoter (FOPFLASH), together with Renilla luciferase reporter 
plasmids SV40 as transfection control. Each transfection was carried out in duplicate plates, and the data shown here are relative 
luminescence units (RLUs) derived from luminescence assays on cell extracts that are representative of three independent experiments. 
(b) Nuclear extracts from S2-013 cells with re-expression of different p120 catenin isoforms with or without MUC1 expression were subjected 
to 10% SDS-PAGE and analyzed by immunoblot (IB) with an anti-cyclin D1 catenin mAb or b-tubulin as a loading control. Right panel shows 
densitometry analysis of the signal for cyclin D1 normalized to the signal for b-tubulin. </p>

<p>Activation of cyclin D1 gene transcription by expression of MUC1 
X Liu et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
Oncogenesis (2014), 1 -9 </p>

<p>Significantly higher levels of cyclin D1 mRNA transcripts and 
protein were detected in Panc-1.MUC1F cells overexpressing full-
length MUC1F relative to Panc-1.NEO. We also investigated 
subcellular expression patterns of the cyclin D1 protein under 
conditions of expression of MUC1. Nuclear levels of cyclin D1 were 
much higher in Panc-1.MUC1F cells overexpressing recombinant 
MUC1 than Panc-1.NEO cells. Our results are consistent with a 
report that evaluated a pancreatic intraepithelial neoplasia tissue 
microarray and reported correlated expression of MUC1 and cyclin 
D1. 
35 This result further supports the hypothesis that the CT of 
MUC1 contributed to elevated levels of steady-state cyclin D1 
gene transcripts in Panc-1 cells. However, steady-state levels of 
cyclin D1 transcripts (data not shown) and protein (Figure 2) were 
not significantly altered in S2-013 cells with or without high levels 
of MUC1. Moreover, knockdown of MUC1 in S2-013 cells by the 
small interfering RNA (siRNA) strategy did not affect levels of cyclin </p>

<p>D1 mRNA as compared with S2-013.MUC1F cells overexpressing 
MUC1F. A published finding with human HCT 116 colon carcinoma 
cells reported that expression of MUC1 cytoplasmic domain co-
activated WNT-target gene transcription, 
24 which is similar to our 
findings with Panc-1. Taken together, these results support the 
hypothesis that nuclear MUC1 CT can serve as co-factors for 
activation of cyclin D1 gene expression during the canonical 
b-catenin/WNT signal pathway in some cancer cells, but clearly 
shows that these pathways are not operative in all tumor cell lines. 
The fact that MUC1 expression contributes to cyclin D1 gene 
regulation in some of the human pancreatic cancer cells but not 
others suggested that another undefined factor was required to 
activate reporter gene expression. We recently reported that a 
major difference between S2-013 cell and Panc1 cell is the 
absence of detectable P120 catenin in S2-013 cells, 
15 and 
therefore hypothesized that functional p120 catenin was </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>Neo 
4A </p>

<p>MUC1+4A 
MUC1+3A 
MUC1+1A 
MUC1 </p>

<p>1A 
3A </p>

<p>Figure 5. Different p120 catenin isoforms associate with Kaiso. (a) Proximity ligation assay (PLA) was used to detect interactions between p120 
catenin and Kaiso in S2-013 cells with re-expression of different p120 catenin isoforms with or without MUC1. The red dots indicate 
interactions between p120 catenin and Kaiso. Blue (4 
0 -6-diamidino-2-phenylindole, DAPI) staining indicates nuclei. The green indicates 
a-tubulin. (b-d) Quantification of results from PLAs. Results were compiled from three independent experiments. </p>

<p>Activation of cyclin D1 gene transcription by expression of MUC1 
X Liu et al </p>



<p>Oncogenesis (2014), 1 -9 
&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>required to fully activate cyclin D1 promoter activity. We evaluated 
S2-013 cells that re-expressed different p120 catenin isoforms for 
cyclin D1 promoter activity. The results showed that re-expression 
of p120 1A or 4A significantly increased the cyclin D1 promoter 
activity in S2-013 cells compared with NEO controls. Furthermore, 
p120 catenin isoform 4A plus MUC1 expression in S2-013 cells 
dramatically and significantly increased cyclin D1 promoter 
activity. The effects of MUC1 and p120 catenin on cyclin D1 
promoter activity were also reflected in levels of protein 
expression. Thus, re-expressing isoforms 1A and 4A of p120 
catenin restored responsiveness of the cyclin D1 promoter in 
these cells. Consistent with these findings, we note that 
expression of MUC1 in Panc1 cells also stabilized and enhanced 
expression of p120 catenin isoforms 1A and 4A (Figure 3a). 
Published evidence that P120 catenin can associate with and 
inhibit activity of the transcriptional repressor Kasio 
25 led us to 
hypothesize that p120 catenin activity on the cyclin D1 promoter 
was in part due to de-repression of Kaiso. Kaiso is a BTB/POZ-zinc 
finger transcription factor implicated in the development of 
cancer that was first identified as a specific binding partner for 
P120 catenin. 
36 Kaiso binds to the promoter of cyclin D1 and 
represses gene expression. 
31 An independent study reported that 
Kaiso/p120-catenin and TCF/b-catenin coordinately regulate </p>

<p>canonical the WNT gene targets Siamois, cyclin D1. 
26 Our results 
demonstrate that there are high levels of complexes in which 
Kaiso associates with p120 catenin (Figure 5). Interestingly, MUC1 
expression enhances the cytoplasmic distribution of p120 catenin/ 
Kaiso complexes (especially isoform 4A in S2-013 cells). This is 
consistent with the concept that sequestration of Kasio by p120 
catenin in the cytoplasm contributes to its functional de-
repression activity. Further evidence in support of this hypothesis 
will require investigation of transcription factor occupancy of the 
cylin D1 promoter in these and other cell types. 
In dividing cells, the cyclin D1 protein helps to regulate 
cell cycle transition from G1 to S phase. 
37 The functional 
consequences of increased cyclin D1 protein expression under 
conditions of expression of MUC1 were investigated by analyzing 
the in vitro growth rate of each cell line. Results indicated that 
high activity of the cyclin D1 promoter and elevated cyclin D1 
protein in Panc-1.MUC1F cells significantly increased cell 
proliferation as compared with Panc-1.NEO cells. Growth rates of 
S2-013 cells that re-expressed p120 catenin isoforms were 
statistically significantly higher than the S2-013.Neo (**Po0.05). 
The growth rates of cells expressing MUC1 Flag (S2-013.MUC1F, 
S2-013.M.1A, S2-013.M.3A, S2-013.M.4A) were significantly greater 
than S2-013.Neo (**Po0.05). Thus, the effect of increased cyclin 
D1 promoter activity and protein expression in S2-013 cells was 
modest but statistically significant. 
In summary, results from our study demonstrate that full 
activation of cyclin D1 promoter activity in pancreatic cancer cell 
lines requires b-catenin activation of TCF-lef and stabilization of 
specific p120 catenin isoforms. We propose that the role of p120 
catenin is to relieve repression by KAISO, a hypothesis that 
requires further investigation. MUC1 enhances the activities of 
both b-catenin and p120 catenin in this system, which results in 
elevation of cyclin D1 protein in human pancreatic cancer cells. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Materials </p>

<p>The human pancreatic cancer cell line Panc-1 was obtained from the 
American Type Culture Collections (Rockville, MD, USA). The S2-013 cell 
line is a cloned sub-line of a human pancreatic tumor cell line (SUIT-2), 
which was derived from a liver metastasis. 
38 Armenian hamster mAb CT-2 
against the MUC1 CT was kindly provided by Dr Sandra Gendler, Mayo 
Clinic Scottsdale, AZ, USA. Antibodies used were Ab anti-cyclin D1 (72-13G; 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Dallas, TX, USA); mAb anti-TCF-4 (Upstate 
Biotechnology Inc., Lake Placid, NY, USA); anti-b-catenin (BD Transduction 
Laboratories, San Jose, CA, USA). Secondary antibodies used in confocal 
microscopy were fluorescein isothiocyanate-conjugated goat anti-mouse 
IgG1, goat anti-Armenian hamster IgG(H þ L) and Cy </p>

<p>TM5 </p>

<p>-conjugated 
Affinipure goat anti-Armenian hamster IgG(H þ L), purchased from 
Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories Inc., West Grove, PA, USA. </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>Panc-1 and S2-013 cell lines were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's 
medium (DMEM) containing 5% fetal bovine serum at 37 1C in 5% CO 2 , and 
passaged at 80-90% confluence using 0.05% trypsin with 0.53 mM EDTA 
(Gibco BRL, Gaithersburg, MD, USA). </p>

<p>Expression of epitope-tagged MUC1 deletion constructs and 
generation of transfectant cell lines </p>

<p>Constructs encoding a full-length, FLAG epitope-tagged MUC1 cDNA 
(MUC1F) were previously described. 
39 Panc-1 and S2-013 cells were stably 
transfected with plasmid DNA using lipofectin and appropriate protocols 
(Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY, USA). Cells carrying integrated 
constructs and expressing MUC1 were selected by culture in 600 mg/ml 
G418 (Life Technologies Inc, Invitrogen, Grand Island, NY USA), selected 
with cloning cylinders and expanded for screening. Expression of FLAG 
epitope-tagged MUC1 isoforms confirmed by immunofluorescence with 
anti-Flag mAb M2 and by immunoblotting with M2 (data not shown). </p>

<p>Figure 6. Effect of MUC1 expression and p120 catenin re-expression 
on in vitro cell growth in Panc-1 and S2-013 cells. (a) In vitro growth 
rate of Panc-1.MUC1F and Panc-1.NEO cells were evaluated by 
counting cells as described in the Materials and methods. (b and c) 
Cell growth assay using a methylene blue cell dye to measure the 
in vitro growth rate of S2-013 cells with re-expression of different 
p120 catenin isoforms with or without MUC1 expression. </p>

<p>Activation of cyclin D1 gene transcription by expression of MUC1 
X Liu et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
Oncogenesis (2014), 1 -9 </p>

<p>Subcellular fractionation </p>

<p>Preparation of membrane/cytoplasmic extracts and nuclear extracts was 
as previously described. 
18 Protein concentrations were determined with a 
Coomassie Protein Assay kit (Pierce, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Rockford, IL, 
USA) and bovine serum albumin as a standard. </p>

<p>Immunoprecipitation and immunoblot analysis </p>

<p>Equal amounts of protein from cytoplasmic or nuclear extracts were 
incubated with the following mAbs: anti-b-catenin (Transduction Labora-
tory Co.), anti-TCF-4 (Upstate Biotechnology, EMD Millipore Corp, Chicago, 
IL, USA) or anti-cyclin D1 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology), or an IgG control. The 
immune complexes were precipitated with protein G-agarose beads 
(Sigma Aldrich Inc, Atlanta, GA, USA) overnight at 4 1C. After washing three 
times with dialyzed Nuclear Lysis Buffer containing 20 mM HEPES pH 7.9, 
25% glycerol, 420 mM NaCl, 1.5 mM MgCl 2 , 0.2 mM EDTA, 0.5 mM dithio-
threitol, 0.5 mM phenylmethanesulfonyl fluoride, 10 mg/ml leupeptin, 10 mg/ 
ml pepstatin, 1 mg/ml Pefabloe SC and 1 mg/ml aprotinin, bound material 
were eluted from the immunoprecipitates in reducing SDS-PAGE loading 
buffer containing 10% SDS, 1 M Tris-HCl (pH 6.8), 50% glycerol, 10% b-
mercaptoethanol (2-ME), 2% bromophenol blue at 100 1C for 5 min. 
Subcellular extracts or immunoprecipitated proteins were resolved by 
electrophoresis on 6 or 10% denaturing polyacrylamide gels (with 3% 
polyacrylamide stacking gels), transferred to polyvinylidene difluoride 
membranes electrophoretically and blocked in 5% dry milk in Tris-buffered 
saline (TBS; 0.9% NaCl, 10 mM Tris, pH 7.4, 0.5% MgCl 2 ) at 4 1C overnight. 
Primary antibodies were diluted to 1:1000 or 1:500 in blotto (5% nonfat dry 
milk in TBS). Incubations were for 1 h at room temperature and were 
followed by three 10-min washes with TBS. Horseradish peroxidase-
conjugated secondary antibodies were diluted to 1:20 000 in TBS, and 
incubated for 1 h at room temperature. Secondary antibody incubations 
were followed by three 10-min washes in TBS. Chemiluminescent reagents 
(Pierce, Thermo Fisher Scientific) were applied as per the manufacturer's 
instructions, and the membranes were exposed to film (Pierce, Thermo 
Fisher Scientific). 
39 Film images were analyzed by densitometry in cases 
where relative quantification was performed and there were substantial 
differences in signals for loading controls. </p>

<p>Plasmids, transient transfections and luciferase assays </p>

<p>The cyclin D1 promoter-reporter constructs are based on the pA3-luc 
backbone and contain a 1745-bp fragment of the human cyclin D1 
promoter. 
21 One promoter construct, TOPFLASH, has a wild-type LEF/Tcf-4-
binding site ( 
À 81 GCTTTGATCTT </p>

<p>À 73 </p>

<p>), and the other, FOPFLASH, has a 
mutated LEF/Tcf-4-binding site ( 
À 81 GCTTTGGCCTT </p>

<p>À 73 </p>

<p>). Both constructs 
were generously provided by Dr Richard G Pestell, Department of 
Oncology, Lombardi Cancer Center, Georgetown University, Washington, 
DC, USA. A dual-luciferase reporter assay (Promega, Thermo Fisher 
Scientific) was used to detect promoter activity in this study. A synthetic 
renilla luciferase reporter plasmid Phrl-SV40 (Promega, Thermo Fisher 
Scientific) was used as a control for transfection efficiency. Panc-1 cells 
expressing different MUC1 constructs were cultured in DMEM plus 5% fetal 
bovine serum, and 10 000 cells/well were seeded into a 48-well plate and 
grown to B95% confluence. Each well was washed twice with PBS and 
transfected with 300 or 600 ng plasmid DNA using 2 ml Lipofectin 
(Invitrogen) in 200 ml Optimem (Life Technologies), respectively. After 
24 h, cells were washed twice with PBS, fed with 3 ml DMEM plus 10% fetal 
bovine serum and cultured for another 2 days. The cells were then washed 
twice with PBS and harvested with 200 ml Passive Lysis buffer (Promega, 
Thermo Fisher Scientific). To detect firefly luciferase activity (from pA3 
plasmids with cyclin D1 promoter), 20 ml of each lysate was reacted with 
100 ml LARII buffer (Promega, Thermo Fisher Scientific) on ice. Relative light 
emission was detected using an Optocomp1 luminometer (MGM Instruments 
Inc, Hamden, CT, USA) reading 10 s with a 2-s delay. Subsequently, to detect 
the renilla luciferase activity (from SV-40 plasmids as transfection efficiency 
control), 100 ml Stop&amp;Glo Reagent (Promega, Thermo Fisher Scientific) was 
added into each well. The solution was vortexed for five seconds, and read 
again with the Optocomp1 luminometer. Light emission data (mean of 
triplicates) were presented as relative lumenescence units for each cell line 
and analyzed for statistical significance using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs> and InStat software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software, Inc</rs>., La Jolla, CA, USA). Each experiment shown is 
representative of three independent replicates. </p>

<p>Generation of siRNAs for knockdown of MUC1 </p>

<p>The mammalian pSUPER-RNA interference system was applied to construct 
the MUC1-siRNA. pSuper siRNA-human MUC1 plasmids were generated to </p>

<p>target the sequence 5 
0 -ACCTCCAGTTTAATTCCTC-3 
0 in the CT. In brief, a 
19-mer oligonucleotide was selected and inserted into pSUPER gfp-neo 
vector using BglII and HindIII sites. pSUPER-GFP without inserts was used as 
a control. Cells were selected by FACS sorting. Cells transfected with 
pSUPER GFP-siRNA-MUC1 or GFP-neo using the Lipofectin method were 
plated in six-well culture plates and selected with 10% fetal bovine 
serum þ RPMI with 600 mg/ml G418. Individual clones were selected by 
using cloning cylinders. Two independent clones, named S2-013.MTII.C1 
and S2-013.MTII.C2, were examined. Western blotting using mAb CT-2 
anti-MUC1 CT was performed to confirm knockdown of MUC1 protein 
expression (data not shown). </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence </p>

<p>Cells were cultured on glass coverslips (Fisherbrand Microscope cover 
glass, Thermo Fisher Scientific: 12-545-100 18CIR-1) at 4.5 Â 105/well for 
12 h. Cells were washed once in serum-free DMEM for 5 min followed by 
fixation for 15 min in PBS with 4% paraformaldehyde and 120 mM sucrose. 
Residual paraformaldehyde was neutralized with 0.1 M glycine in PBS for 
15 min. For immunofluorescence, cells were permeabilized for 15 min by 
incubation in PBS with 0.1% Triton X-100. After washing with PBS, cells 
were incubated for 2 h with primary antibodies diluted in DMEM media. 
Cells were washed three times with PBS and then incubated with 
fluorescein isothiocyanate-conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG 1 (Southern 
Biotech, Birmingham, AL, USA) or indodicarbocyanine (Cy5)-conjugated 
goat-anti-Armenian hamster IgG (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories 
Inc.) for 1 h. Propidium iodide was used as the nuclear dye at a 1:500 
dilution with 0.1 mM RNAase for triple-color confocal laser scanning 
microscopy analysis. 
40 After washing, cells were mounted in fluoromount-
G (Southern Biotech). Isotype controls included mouse myeloma IgG 1 
(Zymed, Life Technologies Inc), and CT-2 antibody blocked with CT-1 
peptide (SSLSYTNPAVAATSANL, Dr Gendler, Mayo Clinic, AZ, USA) to 
confirm binding specificity. Cells were analyzed on a Zeiss LSM 410 dual 
beam laser confocal scanning microscope (Carl Zeiss, Inc., Thornwood, NY, 
USA). </p>

<p>Cell growth assays </p>

<p>One thousand cells/well were placed separately in 48-well culture plates, 
and after 2, 24, 48 and 72 h, the cells were harvested with trypsin digestion 
and counted using Z1 Series COULTER COUNTER Cell and Particle Counter 
(Beckman Coulter, Inc., Brea, CA, USA). A growth curve of each cell line was 
formulated from six independent replicates. Other methods in this study 
were performed as described previously. </p>

<p>41,42   Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Two-way ANOVA was used to analyze the statistical difference between 
the groups. Turkey methods and spline regression were also used as 
alternative statistical method. A P value of less than 0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. </p>

<p>Proximity ligation assay </p>

<p>Proximity ligation assay methods in this study were performed as 
described previously. </p>

<p>15   ABBREVIATIONS 
GSK-3b, glycogen synthase kinase 3b; LEF-1, lymphoid-enhancing 
factor I; MUC1 CT, MUC1 cytoplasmic tail; SEA, sea-urchin sperm 
protein, enterokinase and agrin; Tcf-4, T-cell transcriptional factor 4. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interests. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We gratefully thank Dr Sandra Gendler, Mayo Clinic Scottsdale, AZ, USA, for mAb 
CT-2, Dr Richard G Pestell, Lombardi Cancer Center, Georgetown University, 
Washington, DC, USA, for pA3 TOPFLASH plasmids, and their technical support. We 
also thank the Confocal Laser Scanning Microscopy Core Facility for providing 
assistance with confocal microscopy, and Dr Jane L Meza at Department of 
Preventive and Societal Medicine, Biostatistics Section of University of Nebraska 
Medical Center for data analysis. We thank Fang Yu for her help with the statistical 
analysis. This work was supported in part by the following grants from the NIH: </p>

<p>Activation of cyclin D1 gene transcription by expression of MUC1 
X Liu et al </p>



<p>Oncogenesis (2014), 1 -9 
&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>CA57362, CA127297, CA111294, CA72712, CA116199, CA098258, CA36727, CA09476, 
Fellowships from the Graduate Studies Office of the University of Nebraska Medical 
Center, a pilot project from the Marsha Rivkin Center Pilot Grant, Amgen scholar 
grant from the Foundation for Women's Cancer, and a research grant from Blanton-
Davis Ovarian Cancer Research Program. </p>



<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on the Oncogenesis website (http://www.nature.com/oncsis). </p>

<p>Activation of cyclin D1 gene transcription by expression of MUC1 
X Liu et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
Oncogenesis (2014), 1 -9 </p>

</text></tei>