<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4267110" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective: To describe the evolution of clinical </p>

<p>characteristics, in-hospital management and early 
outcome of elderly patients with non-ST elevation 
myocardial infarction (NSTEMI). </p>

<p>Methods: We analysed data from five consecutive </p>

<p>Italian nationwide registries, conducted between 2001 
and 2010, including patients with acute coronary 
syndromes admitted to cardiac care units (CCUs). </p>

<p>Results: Of 10 983 patients with NSTEMI enrolled in </p>

<p>the 5 surveys, 4350 (39.6%) were ≥75 years old 
(mean age 81±5 years). Some clinical characteristics 
such as diabetes mellitus, hypertension, renal 
dysfunction and previous percutaneous coronary 
intervention increased significantly, whereas a history 
of stroke, myocardial infarction and heart failure 
decreased over time. An invasive approach increased 
from 26.6% in 2001 to 68.4% in 2010 ( p&lt;0.0001) and 
revascularisation rates increased from 9.9% to 51.7% 
( p&lt;0.0001). Early use and prescription at discharge of 
β-blockers, statins and dual antiplatelet treatment 
increased significantly ( p&lt;0.0001). Thirty-day observed 
mortality decreased from 14.6% (95% CI 9.9 to 20.4) 
to 9.5% (95% CI 7.7 to 11.6). At the multivariate 
logistic regression analyses adjusted for baseline 
characteristics, compared with 2001, the risk of death 
was significantly lower in all the other studies 
performed at different times with reductions in 
adjusted mortality between 66% and 45%. </p>

<p>past decade with the development of new 
therapeutics and strategies of care that have 
been shown to improve outcomes in clinical 
trials. 1 2 However, the extent to which this 
new evidence is applied in clinical practice 
and whether such changes are associated with 
favourable outcomes requires continuous 
assessment, particularly in patients scarcely 
represented in large randomised studies. The 
elderly are a subgroup known to be at high 
risk; they are under-represented in guideline-
generating clinical trials, and real-world regis-
tries continue to demonstrate less use of 
cardiac medications and invasive care, even 
among those who are likely to derive 
benefit. 3 4 Within the whole spectrum of ACS, </p>

<p>KEY QUESTIONS </p>

<p>What is already known about this subject? </p>

<p>▸ The elderly are a subgroup known to be at high 
risk; they are under-represented in guideline-
generating clinical trials, and real-world registries 
continue to demonstrate less use of cardiac medi-
cations and invasive care, even among those who 
are likely to derive benefit. </p>

<p>What does this study add? </p>

<p>▸ We demonstrated that substantial changes 
occurred in the clinical characteristics and man-
agement of elderly patients admitted with a diag-
nosis of NSTEMI over the past decade. These 
changes have been associated with a reduction in 
the adjusted early mortality rate. </p>

<p>How might this impact on clinical practice? </p>

<p>▸ These data might encourage the use of recom-
mended interventional and pharmacological strat-
egies, including anti-thrombotic drugs during 
hospitalisation and life-saving therapies prescribed 
at discharge, in this high-risk population. </p>

<p>De Luca L, Olivari Z, Bolognese L, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000148. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000148 </p>



<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>older patients admitted to cardiac care units (CCUs) 
present more frequently without ST-segment elevation 3-6 
and especially those with elevated biomarkers on admis-
sion seem to benefit from early invasive management. 7 8 
The aim of the present study was to describe the evo-
lution of clinical characteristics, in-hospital management 
and early mortality of elderly patients admitted to CCUs 
with a diagnosis of non-ST elevation myocardial infarc-
tion (NSTEMI) by analysing data from nationwide 
Italian registries conducted between 2001 and 2010. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Five consecutive nationwide registries designed by the 
Italian Hospital Cardiology Association (ANMCO) on 
patients with ACS were conducted in Italy between 2001 
and 2010: BLITZ in 2001, 9 BLITZ-2 in 2003, 10 IN-ACS 
OUTCOME (Italian Network on Acute Coronary 
Syndromes Outcome) in 2006-2007, 11 BLITZ-4 in 2009 
and 2010 12 and MANTRA (Management of patients with 
ACS in the real-world practice in Italy: an outcome 
research study focused on the use of ANTithRombotic 
Agents) in 2009-2010. 13 All surveys included patients 
with ACS consecutively admitted alive to the participat-
ing CCUs during a prespecified period (few weeks for 
the BLITZ registries and 1 year for the IN-ACS 
OUTCOME and MANTRA registries; table 1). The 
methods used for each registry have been described pre-
viously. 9-13 Briefly, their primary objectives were to evalu-
ate the characteristics, management and outcomes of 
consecutive patients with ACS admitted to Italian CCUs, 
using a catchment broad enough to provide data </p>

<p>representative of the entire country. Participation in the 
study was offered to all institutions, including university 
teaching hospitals, general and regional hospitals, and 
private clinics with CCUs receiving patients with ACS. 
Physicians were instructed that participation in the study 
should not affect clinical care or management. 
All patients were informed of the nature and aims of 
the surveys and were asked to sign an informed consent 
form for the anonymous management of their individ-
ual data. Local Institutional Review Boards were 
informed of the study, according to the Italian rules. 
For the present analysis, only patients aged ≥75 years 
presenting with elevated troponin and/or creatine 
kinase (CK)-MB fraction levels, and without persistent 
ST segment elevation and/or new onset Q waves or left-
bundle branch block, were considered. </p>

<p>Data collection 
Data on baseline characteristics including demographics, 
risk factors and medical history were collected as previ-
ously described. 9-13 Information on the use of cardiac 
procedures, including coronary angiography, type and 
timing of revascularisation therapy (if any), use of medi-
cations during hospitalisation and at hospital discharge, 
and in-hospital major clinical events, were recorded. In 
all surveys, clinical events were also assessed at 30 days. 
Clinical reinfarction during initial hospitalisation was 
diagnosed in the presence of new ischaemic symptoms 
and a re-elevation of biochemical myocardial necrosis 
markers with or without concurrent ECG changes. In all 
studies, major bleeding was classified according to the </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of the 5 Italian Surveys </p>

<p>Study </p>

<p>Enrolment 
period </p>

<p>Number of 
participating 
centres </p>

<p>Percentage of 
centres with 
catheterisation 
laboratory </p>

<p>Target 
population </p>

<p>Number of 
patients with 
NSTEMI 
enrolled </p>

<p>Percentage of 
patients with 
NSTEMI 
≥75 years old </p>

<p>BLITZ 
15-29 October 
2001 </p>

<p>296 
44.6 
Consecutive 
patients with 
STEMI and 
NSTEMI </p>

<p>580 
33.1 </p>

<p>BLITZ-2 
6-27 May 2003 
275 
41.2 
Consecutive 
patients with 
NSTEACS </p>

<p>1059 
32.8 </p>

<p>IN-ACS 
OUTCOME </p>

<p>2 December 
2005-8 February 
2008 </p>

<p>38 
47.4 
Consecutive 
patients with 
ACS </p>

<p>2327 
39.7 </p>

<p>BLITZ-4 
15 September-
30 November 
2009 and 15 
February-30 
April 2010 </p>

<p>163 
83.0 
Consecutive 
patients with 
ACS </p>

<p>4511 
43.0 </p>

<p>MANTRA 
22 April 2009-29 
December 2010 </p>

<p>52 
65.4 
Consecutive 
patients with 
ACS </p>

<p>2506 
37.8 </p>

<p>ACS, acute coronary syndrome; CCUs, cardiac care units; NSTEACS, non-ST elevation ACS; NSTEMI, non-ST elevation myocardial 
infarction; STEMI, ST elevation myocardial infarction. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>De Luca L, Olivari Z, Bolognese L, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000148. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000148 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>thrombolysis in MI (TIMI) criteria. 14 Heart failure was 
defined as the presence of signs and/or symptoms of 
pulmonary congestion in the absence of a non-cardiac 
cause. Stroke was identified as an acute neurological 
deficit that lasted &gt;24 h and affected the ability to 
perform daily activities with or without confirmation by 
imaging techniques. 
All data were collected using a case report form at the 
participating centres and entered in a centralised data-
base located at the ANMCO Research Center in 
Florence. By using a validation plan, integrated in the 
data entry software, data were checked for missing or 
contradictory entries and values out of the normal range. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Categorical variables were reported as percentages and 
compared by χ 2 test, whereas continuous variables 
were reported as means and SDs and compared by ana-
lysis of variance, if normally distributed, or by the 
Kruskal-Wallis test, if not. Temporal trends were tested 
using the Cochran-Armitage test for binary variables 
and the Kendall Tau rank correlation coefficient with 
the Jonckheere-Terpstra test for continuous variables. 
The 95% CIs of the difference of percentage changes 
were evaluated using the R package proCIs. Since the 
baseline patient characteristics showed significant 
changes in the five registries, we calculated a risk score 
for the 2010 MANTRA population using a logistic regres-
sion model resulting statistically significant at univariate 
analysis or considered of clinical interest. These variables 
included gender, age, diabetes, history of heart failure, 
prior stroke/transient ischaemic attacks (TIA), periph-
eral vascular disease, prior renal failure, systolic blood 
pressure, heart rate, Killip class and atrial fibrillation at 
admission. This score, evaluated on the 2010 MANTRA 
population, was also used to standardise the death rates 
for each of the previous surveys. The standardised death 
rates therefore represent the rates that would have been 
expected if the distribution of the baseline characteristics 
of each of the first four surveys had been similar to that 
of the most recent one. 
Finally, a multivariate analysis (logistic model) was 
conducted to identify the independent predictors of use 
of coronary angiography during index hospitalisation; 
variables statistically significant at univariate analysis 
were also inserted in the model: gender, age, smoking 
habits, prior acute myocardial infarction (AMI), prior 
revascularisation, history of heart failure, prior stroke/ 
TIA, prior renal failure, systolic blood pressure, heart 
rate, Killip class and atrial fibrillation at entry, admission 
to a hospital with catheterisation laboratory facilities, as 
well as study cohort (2001 as referral). 
All tests were two-sided; a p value &lt;0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. All analyses were conducted with 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">SAS</rs> system software <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">V.9.2</rs> and with the 'R' Development 
Core Team 2012. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Baseline characteristics 
Of the 10 983 patients with NSTEMI enrolled in the five 
surveys, 4350 (39.6%) were ≥75 years old. The percen-
tages of these patients enrolled in the individual studies 
are reported in table 1. The mean age of the populations 
included in the analysis was similar ( p for trend=0.74). 
During this 10-year period, the rates of elderly patients 
with prior cerebrovascular accidents, history of angina, 
myocardial infarction (MI) and heart failure declined, 
whereas the proportions of patients with diabetes melli-
tus, hypertension, renal dysfunction, previous percutan-
eous coronary intervention (PCI) and on β-blocker and 
statin therapy significantly increased (table 2). </p>

<p>Hospital management 
The percentage of patients admitted to hospitals with 
catheterisation laboratory facilities increased substan-
tially from 48% in 2001 to 71% in 2010 ( percentage 
change 23 (95% CI 15 to 30)) and those undergoing 
coronary angiography at any time during index admis-
sion increased from 27% in 2001 to 68% in 2010 ( per-
centage change, 42 (95% CI 35 to 48); figure 1), with a 
significant reduction in the time delay from hospital 
admission to angiography (figure 2). During the whole 
10-year period, an invasive strategy was adopted in 74% 
of the patients admitted to hospitals with a catheterisa-
tion laboratory versus 42% of those admitted to hospitals 
without catheterisation laboratory ( p&lt;0.0001). At multi-
variate analysis, the presence of catheterisation labora-
tory was the strongest independent predictor of use of 
coronary angiography, followed by the year of the regis-
try (the most recent being associated with higher prob-
ability). On the other hand, older age, haemodynamic 
deterioration (as identified by blood pressure, heart rate 
and Killip class), chronic kidney dysfunction and female 
gender were the strongest negative predictors of coron-
ary angiography (figure 3). 
Accordingly, the use of revascularisation therapy 
increased from 9.9% to 51.7% ( percentage change from 
2001 to 2010, 42 (95% CI 36 to 47)), with a more fre-
quent use of PCI (9.4% to 47%; percentage change, 37 
(95% CI 31 to 42)) and coronary artery bypass grafting 
(CABG; 0.5-5.6%; percentage change, 5.1 (95% CI 2.5 
to 6.9); figure 1). In general, among patients who under-
went coronary angiography, myocardial revascularisation 
(PCI or CABG) was performed in 37% in 2001, 55% in 
2003, 68% in 2006 and 75% in 2010 ( p for trend 
&lt;0.0001; percentage change from 2001 to 2010, 38 (95% 
CI 24 to 51)). 
Antithrombotic medications used during hospitalisa-
tion changed markedly with increasing use of dual anti-
platelet therapy from 17% in 2001 to 85% in 2010 
( p for trend &lt;0.0001; percentage change, 68 (95% CI 62 
to 73)) and fondaparinux (15% in 2009 and 21% in 
2010, p&lt;0.0001; figure 4). On the other hand, the use of 
low-molecular-weight heparins (from 66% in 2001 to 
48% in 2010, percentage change, −19 (95% CI −26 </p>

<p>De Luca L, Olivari Z, Bolognese L, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000148. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000148 </p>



<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>to −11)) decreased over the years. It is noteworthy that 
the use of unfractionated heparin (from 46% to 34%, 
percentage change, −12 (95% CI −20 to −4.3)), oral 
anticoagulation therapy (from 8.3% to 4.3%, percentage 
change, −4.0 (95% CI −8.9 to −0.5)) and intravenous 
glycoprotein IIb/IIIa inhibitors (from 14% to 17%, per-
centage change, 3.1 (95% CI −2.9 to 8.1)) did not 
change significantly (figure 4). At the time of the 
studies, the use of bivalirudin in NSTEMI was very 
limited in Italy (0.6% in BLITZ 4, 2009). 
The use of evidence-based treatments at discharge 
increased gradually over the 10-year period. Dual anti-
platelet treatment was prescribed in 9.3% of elderly 
patients discharged alive in 2001 and 75% in 2010 ( per-
centage change, 66 (95% CI 60 to 70)); β-blockers in 
47% in 2001 and 71% in 2010 ( percentage change, 24 
(95% CI 16 to 32)); and statins in 37% in 2001 and 82% 
in 2010 ( percentage change, 45 (95% CI 37 to 52); 
figure 5). 
As shown in figure 2, the mean length of hospital stay 
decreased significantly over the 10-year period, and the </p>

<p>percentage of patients directly discharged home 
decreased significantly from 87% in 2001 to 83% in 
2003, 77% in 2006, 72% in 2009 and 78% in 2010 ( p for 
trend=0.0006; percentage change from 2001 to 2010, 
−9.0 (95% CI −2.6 to −14.2)) in favour of transfers to 
rehabilitation or other structures. </p>

<p>Clinical outcomes 
The crude rates of in-hospital major clinical events, 
including death, heart failure, stroke and major bleed-
ing, did not show a significant trend during the decade 
of analysis (table 3). However, the incidence of reinfarc-
tion (from 1.6% in 2001 to 3.0% in 2010, percentage 
change, 1.4 (95% CI −1.6 to 3.1)) showed an important 
difference between studies, though without a clear 
trend. At 30-day follow-up, the cumulative incidence of 
clinical events did not show any significant time trend 
over the 10-year period, despite remarkable differences 
in event rates between the studies (table 3). 
Crude 30-day mortality decreased from 14.6% in 2001 
to 9.5% in 2010 ( percentage change, −5.1 (95% CI </p>

<p>Table 2 Baseline characteristics of elderly patients with NSTEMI from 2001 to 2010 </p>

<p>BLITZ, 
2001 
n=192 </p>

<p>BLITZ-2, 
2003 
n=347 </p>

<p>IN-ACS 
OUTCOME, 
2006-2007 
n=923 </p>

<p>BLITZ-4, 
2009 &amp; 2010 
n=1941 </p>

<p>MANTRA, 
2009-2010 
n=947 </p>

<p>p for 
trend </p>

<p>Age, years (mean±SD) 
81±5 
81±5 
81±5 
82±5 
81±5 
0.74 
Female, % 
45.3 
49.6 
45.5 
45.0 
43.8 
0.17 
Risk factors and comorbidities, % 
Active smokers 
7.8 
8.1 
7.7 
8.5 
9.4 
0.26 
Dyslipidaemia 
n/a 
38.0 
42.7 
32.8 
42.3 
0.80 
Diabetes mellitus 
24.5 
32.0 
29.3 
35.2 
36.1 
&lt;0.0001 
Hypertension 
69.8 
71.8 
70.7 
76.6 
77.4 
0.0001 
Renal dysfunction 
8.3 
13.0 
16.4 
20.6 
21.2 
&lt;0.0001 
Cardiovascular history, % 
Peripheral artery disease 
20.3 
23.6 
20.8 
17.5 
20.0 
0.11 
Previous stroke/TIA 
16.7 
18.4 
11.2 
8.7 
10.4 
&lt;0.0001 
History of angina 
42.7 
23.0 
23.7 
25.5 
17.4 
&lt;0.0001 
Heart failure 
16.7 
11.5 
8.1 
7.0 
8.8 
0.001 
Previous MI 
32.8 
39.4 
30.8 
19.1 
27.3 
&lt;0.0001 
Previous PCI 
6.3 
9.6 
11.6 
16.4 
17.0 
&lt;0.0001 
Previous CABG 
6.8 
7.4 
8.7 
9.5 
9.8 
0.08 
Variables at admission 
Killip class III-IV, % 
17.7 
13.0 
10.4 
11.5 
11.5 
0.12 
SBP, mm Hg (mean±SD) 
143±30 
147±27 
142±28 
139±26 
140±28 
0.007 
HR, bpm (mean±SD) 
86±24 
84±22 
83±22 
82±19 
84±22 
0.68 
Ejection fraction, % (mean±SD) 
52±12 
47±10 
47±11 
47±11 
48±11 
0.38 
Atrial fibrillation, % 
16.2 
13.0 
12.2 
13.2 
12.0 
0.34 
ECG changes, % 
100.0 
88.2 
63.4 
73.8 
73.4 
&lt;0.0001 
Medication before admission, % 
Antiplatelet agents 
45.3 
57.6 
54.0 
54.2 
55.2 
0.24 
Oral anticoagulant agents 
3.1 
3.8 
5.7 
6.4 
5.2 
0.16 
ACE-I/ARB 
44.8 
49.6 
53.7 
58.4 
52.7 
0.01 
β-blockers 
17.2 
19.9 
28.6 
31.9 
29.7 
&lt;0.0001 
Statins 
13.5 
14.7 
23.0 
32.5 
31.6 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>ACE-I/ARB, ACE inhibitors/angiotensin receptor blockers; CABG, coronary artery bypass grafting; CAD, coronary artery disease; HR, heart 
rate; MI, myocardial infarction; NSTEMI, non-ST elevation MI; PCI, percutaneous coronary intervention; SBP, systolic blood pressure; TIA, 
transient ischaemic attacks. </p>



<p>De Luca L, Olivari Z, Bolognese L, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000148. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000148 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>−11.0 to −0.3)), though without a statistically significant 
time trend ( p=0.36). As shown in figure 6, when the 
death rates were standardised for the 2010 risk score 
(representing the expected rates, standardised on the 
risk distribution profile of 2010 MANTRA population), 
estimated mortality was fairly stable over time (8.9% in 
2001, 7.8% in 2003, 8.8% in 2006, 9.7% in 2009 and 
9.5% in 2010), but these were quite different from the 
observed rates (14.6%, 7.5%, 7.0%, 6.2% and 9.5%, 
respectively). Moreover, after multivariate adjustments 
for the differences in baseline characteristics, the risk of 
death was significantly lower in all of the registries as 
compared to BLITZ, with reductions in adjusted mortal-
ity of between 66% (BLITZ-4) and 45% (MANTRA). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
The main findings of this study are as follows: (1) 
elderly patients account for approximately 40% of the </p>

<p>NSTEMI population admitted to Italian CCUs and this 
proportion is increasing slightly over the years; (2) the 
clinical characteristics of elderly patients admitted to the 
CCUs in Italy have changed, with increasing rates of 
patients with diabetes, renal dysfunction and prior revas-
cularisations; (3) the use of coronary angiography, myo-
cardial revascularisation (mainly PCI) and adjunctive 
evidence-based therapies in this high-risk population has 
increased dramatically and (4) after adjustment for the 
changing baseline characteristics, these advances in care 
seem to be associated with a reduction in the rate of 
early mortality. 
Although patients aged ≥75 years represent up to 40% 
of CCU admissions with NSTEACS, they account for 
only 10% of patients enrolled in clinical trials. 15 
Moreover, elderly patients with ACS in the community 
are at a higher disease-related risk than those rando-
mised in trials and have more comorbidities. 15 Indeed, 
during the 10-year period of our analysis, the rate of </p>

<p>Figure 1 In-hospital use of 
coronary angiography, 
percutaneous coronary 
intervention (PCI), coronary artery 
bypass grafting (CABG) or 
coronary revascularisation (PCI/ 
CABG) from 2001 to 2010. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Mean delay between 
admission and coronary 
angiography; and mean length of 
hospital stay in the various 
studies between 2001 and 2010. </p>

<p>De Luca L, Olivari Z, Bolognese L, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000148. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000148 </p>



<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>elderly patients with traditional risk factors such as previ-
ous cerebrovascular accident, history of angina, MI and 
heart failure declined, suggesting more effective prevent-
ive strategies and/or favourable impact of previous revas-
cularisations. On the other hand, the number of elderly 
patients with comorbidities such as diabetes mellitus and 
renal dysfunction increased consistently, suggesting a 
growing availability of the CCU cardiologist to treat this 
complex population aggressively. 
Lack of randomised clinical trial data to guide acute 
care in elderly patients and in patients with comorbidities 
might explain the lower use of evidence-based therapies 
among elderly patients with ACS. 3 4 The Euro Heart 
survey, an international cohort study including patients 
with ACS from 25 European countries, showed that elderly 
patients were less intensively treated than younger patients 
and had a higher in-hospital mortality. 4 Nevertheless, 
patients ≥75 years old seem to benefit from potent 
adjunctive evidence-based therapies together with an early 
invasive approach, particularly those with ST elevation MI 
(STEMI) or NSTEACS with elevated biomarkers. 7 16 17 In 
the Italian Elderly ACS study, the first randomised trial 
comparing treatment strategies in elderly patients with 
NSTEACS, patients with elevated troponin levels on admis-
sion randomised to an early aggressive approach had a sig-
nificant 57% reduction in the rate of the primary end 
point (a composite of ischaemic and bleeding events) at 
1 year. 7 In the present analysis, the remarkable increase 
over time in the use of life-saving pharmacological therap-
ies, coronary angiography and PCI as revascularisation 
modality was not paralleled by a significant trend towards </p>

<p>the reduction of 30-day mortality, which, however, became 
evident, and statistically highly significant after adjustment 
for other powerful predictors of death such as diabetes, 
chronic kidney dysfunction, 18 19 and markers of ventricu-
lar dysfunction such as prior heart failure, low blood pres-
sure, high baseline heart rate and Killip class. 
A further possible explanation for comparable crude 
mortality rates recorded after the year 2003 is the short-
term follow-up available in our surveys. In another regis-
try that showed a significant increase in the use of 
guidelines-recommended treatments including PCI 
among more than 900 elderly patients admitted for MI 
between 2000 and 2006, a difference in mortality at 
1 month was evident in case of STEMI, whereas there was 
only a non-significant trend towards reduction in mortal-
ity in patients with NSTEMI, despite a fourfold increase 
in the rate of invasive strategy during index admission. 20 
Indeed, in the pivotal randomised clinical trials comparing 
an early invasive and an initially conservative treatment in 
NSTEACS, the clinical benefit in terms of death and/or MI 
after an invasive strategy in NSTEACS are usually observed 
after 6 months to 1 year of admission. 8 21 This is particularly 
evident in some patient populations with ACS, such as the 
elderly, in whom most deaths have a cardiac ischaemic 
origin, and the higher risk rises from 30 days to 1 year, espe-
cially after revascularisation. 22 Accordingly, the 5-year 
follow-up from the RITA-3 trial demonstrated that the 
benefit of invasive treatment over conservative care contin-
ued to widen after the first year, demonstrating the greatest 
benefits in those in high-risk quartiles, with age being the 
strongest predictor of risk. 23 </p>

<p>Figure 3 Independent predictors of coronary angiography during index admission at logistic regression analysis. </p>



<p>De Luca L, Olivari Z, Bolognese L, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000148. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000148 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>Beyond mortality, all other outcomes did not present a 
significant trend over the decade, both during hospital-
isation and at 30-day follow-up, with the exception of an 
increase in reinfarction during hospital stay, probably 
due to more accurate and sensitive diagnostic methods 
that have been recently developed. In this regard, it 
should be appreciated that the increasing accuracy of 
detecting NSTEMI developed over the years may have 
led to a selection of patients at lower risk and could par-
tially explain the reduction in the rate of adverse events 
observed in our series. 
Increased age is associated with an increased risk of 
drug-related adverse events, such as bleeding, frequently 
caused by excess dosing of antithrombolytic drugs. 24 At 
variance with previous reports showing a high risk of 
major bleeding in elderly patients treated invasively (eg, 
17% of patients ≥75 years of age in the invasive arm of </p>

<p>the TACTICS TIMI-18 trial), 14 15 the cumulative rate of 
major bleeding remained consistently low over time 
(approximately 2% at 1 month) in the Italian registries 
reported in this study, and consistently with the results 
of the recent Italian Elderly ACS study. 7 This finding is 
most likely attributable to the moderate use of glycopro-
tein IIb/IIIa inhibitors, with a selective and decreasing 
use of low-molecular-weight heparin and with increasing 
use of the radial approach to PCI that accounts for 
approximately 35% in recent registries and as high as 
70% in high-volume centres. 7 </p>

<p>Limitations 
There are some limitations to our analysis. Although 
every effort was made in each survey to capture the 
greatest possible proportion of hospitals with CCU in 
the entire country, the ratio between the invited and </p>

<p>Figure 4 In-hospital use of antiplatelet agents (A) and anticoagulant drugs (B) in the decade of analysis. </p>

<p>De Luca L, Olivari Z, Bolognese L, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000148. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000148 </p>



<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>Table 3 In-hospital and 30-day clinical events of elderly patients admitted with NSTEMI from 2001 to 2010 </p>

<p>BLITZ, 
2001 
n=192 </p>

<p>BLITZ-2, 
2003 
n=347 </p>

<p>IN-ACS 
OUTCOME, 
2006-2007 
n=923 </p>

<p>BLITZ-4, 
2009 &amp; 2010 
n=1941 </p>

<p>MANTRA, 
2009-2010 
n=947 </p>

<p>p for 
trend </p>

<p>In-hospital events, n (%) 
Death 
19 (9.9) 
13 (3.8) 
40 (4.3) 
81 (4.2) 
63 (6.7) 
0.90 
Heart failure 
62 (32.3) 
25 (7.2) 
137 (14.8) 
370 (19.1) 
165 (17.4) 
0.72 
Reinfarction 
3 (1.6) 
1 (0.3) 
19 (2.1) 
27 (1.4) 
28 (3.0) 
0.02 
Stroke 
2 (1.0) 
2 (0.6) 
10 (1.1) 
15 (0.8) 
10 (1.1) 
0.86 
Major bleeding 
4 (2.1) 
8 (2.3) 
9 (1.0) 
58 (3.0) 
17 (1.8) 
0.45 
30-day events, n (%) 
Death 
28 (14.6) 
26 (7.5) 
65 (7.0) 
121 (6.2) 
90 (9.5) 
0.36 
Heart failure 
65 (33.9) 
35 (10.1) 
141 (15.3) 
378 (19.5) 
177 (18.7) 
0.97 
Reinfarction 
8 (4.2) 
13 (3.8) 
27 (2.9) 
31 (1.6) 
34 (3.6) 
0.33 
Stroke 
5 (2.6) 
4 (1.2) 
11 (1.2) 
19 (1.0) 
13 (1.4) 
0.41 
Major bleeding 
4 (2.1) 
8 (2.3) 
11 (1.2) 
60 (3.1) 
20 (2.1) 
0.31 </p>

<p>NSTEMI, non-ST elevation myocardial infarction; </p>

<p>Figure 5 Drugs prescribed from 
2001 to 2010 in elderly patients 
discharged alive. </p>

<p>Figure 6 Observed and standardised all-cause mortality at 30 days. </p>



<p>De Luca L, Olivari Z, Bolognese L, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000148. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000148 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>participating centres varies across registries from 0.7 to 
0.3. However, the geographical distribution and the 
availability of facilities of CCUs participating in different 
registries may be considered representative of the entire 
country. The duration of the surveys, clinical end points 
and programmed follow-up visits were not homoge-
neous. The short duration of follow-up (1 month) might 
have led to an underestimation of the benefits of imple-
mentation of care in terms of clinical events. In add-
ition, the lack of central event adjudication might have 
amended the actual rate of adverse clinical outcomes. 
We did not record specific contraindications to any 
medication; in an elderly population, this may have influ-
enced the rate of use of certain drugs, and may have been 
an unrecognised confounder, but we would not expect the 
prevalence of contraindications to specific therapies, par-
ticularly antithrombotic therapies, to change markedly 
with time. In addition, we did not collect some variables 
such as frailty and functional status that are particularly 
important in elderly patients. Finally, analysing only 
patients admitted to CCUs may imply a selection bias. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS 
In the past decade, substantial changes have occurred in 
the clinical characteristics and management of elderly 
patients admitted with a diagnosis of NSTEMI in Italian 
CCUs. We observed a marked increase in the use of 
recommended interventional and pharmacological strat-
egies, including antithrombotic drugs used during hospi-
talisation and life-saving therapies prescribed at 
discharge, and these changes have been associated with 
a reduction in the adjusted early mortality rate. </p>

<p>Author affiliations </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Cardiovascular Sciences, European Hospital, Rome, Italy </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Cardiology, Ca' Foncello Hospital, Treviso, Italy </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Cardiovascular and Neurologic Department, San Donato Hospital, Arezzo, 
Italy </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>ANMCO Research Center, Florence, Italy </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Division of Cardiology, Ospedale San Antonio Abate, Tolmezzo, Italy </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Department of Cardiology, Maggiore Hospital, Bologna, Italy </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Division of Cardiology, IRCCS Ospedale S. Martino, Genova, Italy </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Department of Cardiovascular Diseases, S. Giovanni-Addolorata Hospital, 
Rome, Italy </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Cardiology Division, Campo di Marte Hospital, Lucca, Italy </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Division of Cardiology, Ospedale A. Manzoni, Lecco, Italy </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors thank all the patients and investigators from 
all participating centres of the studies, as well as dedicated staff from the 
ANMCO Research Center. </p>

<p>Contributors DL and SS participated in the conception, design and conduct 
of the studies' analysis, drafted and revised the paper. DL and LG statistically 
analysed the data and revised the final manuscript. ZO, FC, AB and GDP were 
the principal investigators of the individual studies and made a critical 
revision of the final manuscript. LB, ADC, GC and FMB made a critical 
revision of the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding The studies included in this manuscript were funded by unrestricted 
grants as follows: BLITZ (Boehringer Ingelheim, Italy), BLITZ-2 (Merck, 
Sharp&amp;Dohme, Italy), IN-ACS Outcome (Sanofi-Aventis and Bristol-Myers 
Squibb, Italy), BLITZ-4 (Merck, Sharp&amp;Dohme, Italy) and MANTRA (Glaxo 
SmithKline, Italy). The sponsor of the studies was the Heart Care Foundation, </p>

<p>a non-profit independent institution which is also the owner of the databases. 
Database management and quality control of the data were under the 
responsibility of the Research Centre of the Italian Association of Hospital 
Cardiologists (ANMCO). The Steering Committees of the studies had full 
access to all of the data in the studies and take complete responsibility for the 
integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. </p>

<p>Competing interests DL and LG, employees of Heart Care Foundation which 
conducted the studies, report Institutional grants from Glaxo SmithKline, Italy 
and grants from Merck, Sharp&amp;Dohme, Italy outside the submitted work. SS 
reports grants and personal fees from ELI LILLY, grants from NOVARTIS, 
grants and personal fees from IROKO, and personal fees from DAIICHI 
SANKYO, ROCHE, BAYER and ASTRA ZENECA outside the submitted work. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Local Italian Institutional Review Boards (IRBs). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Coronary artery disease </p>





<p>De Luca L, Olivari Z, Bolognese L, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000148. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000148 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

</text></tei>