<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4345725" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Nuclear factor-erythroid 2 (NF-E2)-related factor 2 (Nrf2) is a transcription factor that regulates the 
expression of antioxidant genes by activating Nrf2-antioxidant response element (ARE) pathway. This study 
aimed to investigate association of Nrf2 gene single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), rs35652124 (A→G) 
and rs6721961 (C→A), with various laboratory data in 464 health evaluation examinees. The genotyping of 
these SNPs was performed using polymerase chain reaction with confronting two-pair primers (PCR-CTPP) 
assay. The genotype frequencies of rs35652124 SNP were 21.1% for AA, 44.0% for AG, and 34.9% for 
GG. The frequency of A allele was 0.431. In male subjects, cholinesterase was significantly high, and HDL 
cholesterol was significantly low in (AG+GG) carriers. In female subjects, diastolic blood pressure (BP) 
was significantly low in (AG+GG) carriers. The genotype frequencies of rs6721961 SNP were 55.2% for 
CC, 34.7% for CA, and 10.1% for AA. The frequency of A allele was 0.275. In male subjects, systolic 
BP, diastolic BP and cholinesterase were significantly low, and iron was significantly high in (CA+AA) 
carriers. In female subjects, cholinesterase was significantly high in (CA+AA) carriers, and diastolic BP was 
significantly high in AA carriers. In conclusion, Nrf2 polymorphisms are associated with BP in Japanese. </p>

<p>Nuclear factor-erythroid 2 (NF-E2)-related factor 2 (Nrf2) is a member of the cap'n'collar 
family of basic leucine zipper transcription factors that regulate the expression of many anti-
oxidant pathway genes. 
1) Nrf2 is maintained at basal levels in cells by binding to its inhibitor 
protein, Kelch-like erythroid-cell-derived protein with CNC homology (ECH)-associated protein 
1 (Keap1). </p>

<p>2,3) </p>

<p>A large number of studies revealed that Nrf2 protects many cell types and organ systems 
from a broad spectrum of toxic insults and disease pathogenesis. For example, Nrf2 protects lung 
from butylated hydroxytoluene-induced acute respiratory distress syndrome, 
4) hyperoxic injury, </p>

<p>5) </p>

<p>Received: December 25, 2013; accepted: January 24, 2014 
Corresponding author: Toshimitsu Niwa, MD 
Department of Advanced Medicine for Uremia, Nagoya University Graduate School of Medicine, 
65 Tsurumai-cho, Showa-ku, Nagoya 466-8550, Japan 
Tel: +81-52-744-1980, Fax: +81-52-744-1954, E-mail: tniwa@med.nagoya-u.ac.jp </p>



<p>Yasuhiko Shimoyama et al. </p>

<p>and bleomycin-mediated pulmonary fibrosis. 
6) Nrf2 increased sensitivity to acetaminophen-induced 
centrilobular hepatocellular necrosis and hepatotoxicity. 
7,8) Nrf2 also contributes to neuro-
protection. Activation of the Nrf2-antioxidant response element pathway protects neuroblastoma 
cells from oxidative glutamate toxicity 
9) and H 2 O 2 -induced apoptosis. 
10) Thus, Nrf2 is called the 
"multi-organ protector". </p>

<p>11) </p>

<p>Many single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) have been identified in the Nrf2 gene. </p>

<p>12-14) </p>

<p>Of special relevance are the rs35652124 (A→G) polymorphism and the rs6721961 (C→A) 
polymorphism, which are located in the promotor region of the gene. Both SNPs were found 
to reduce the transcription activity of Nrf2, 
12) presumably resulting in decreased Nrf2-dependent 
gene transcription. Furthermore, a correlation between individuals carrying the rs6721961CA 
genotype and increased incidence of acute lung injury, has been reported. 
12) This study aimed to 
investigate the relationship between these Nrf2 SNPs and laboratory data in Japanese subjects. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study subjects 
This study included 464 Japanese subjects who underwent health evaluation at Nagoya 
University Hospital. The general characteristics of the subjects were as follows: The subjects 
included 285 men and 179 women. The mean age was 49.7±12.7 (SD) years. Almost all the 
laboratory parameters were within the normal range for Japanese (Table 1). Written informed 
consent was obtained from all the subjects, and the procedures followed were in accordance 
with the ethical standards of the responsible committee on human experimentation and with the 
Helsinki Declaration of 1975, as revised in 1983. The subject enrollment was approved by Ethics 
Committee of Nagoya University School of Medicine in 2004 for Nagoya University Hospital. </p>

<p>Anthropometric, laboratory measurement 
Height, weight, systolic blood pressure (BP) and diastolic BP were measured for all partici-
pants. Body mass index (BMI) was calculated by dividing the weight (kg) with the square of 
height (m). The body fat percentage was measured by an electrical body-fat-percentage measuring 
instrument (Tanita Inc., Tokyo, Japan). Blood samples were obtained after fasting for 12 h. 
The following biochemical parameters were determined by standard laboratory methods based 
on Japan Society of Clinical Chemistry: red blood cell, hemoglobin, white blood cell, platelet, 
creatinine, aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), alkaline phosphatase 
(ALP), g-glutamyl transpeptidase (g-GTP), total protein, albumin, cholinesterase, total bilirubin, 
amylase, fasting glucose, total cholesterol, triglyceride, high-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol, 
low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol, uric acid, iron and C-reactive protein. </p>

<p>Genotyping of Nrf2 SNPs 
Nrf2 SNPs, rs35652124 and rs6721961, located in the promoter were selected from the Hap-
Map database. The genotyping was performed using polymerase chain reaction with confronting 
two-pair primers (PCR-CTPP) assay. 
15) Confronting pairs of primers (four primers in all) are as 
follows: </p>

<p>rs35652124 
Forward primer 1: CTTTTATCTCACTTTACCGCCCGAG 
Forward primer 2: GCAGTCACCCTGAACGCCCT 
Reverse primer 1: GACACGTGGGAGTTCAGAGGG </p>



<p>NRF2 and BLOOD PRESSURE </p>

<p>Table 1 General characteristics of subjects </p>

<p>Total 
Male 
Female </p>

<p>n 
464 
285 
179 </p>

<p>Age 
(year) 
49.7±12.7 
50.6±12.9 
48.2±12.3 </p>

<p>Height 
(cm) 
164.6±8.6 
169.5±6.1 
156.7±5.8 </p>

<p>Body weight 
(kg) 
61.9±11.4 
67.6±9.2 
52.8±8.1 </p>

<p>BMI 
(kg/m 
2 ) 
22.7±3.1 
23.5±2.7 
21.5±3.3 </p>

<p>Body fat percentage 
(%) 
20.7±6.4 
18.8±5.7 
23.8±6.2 </p>

<p>Waist circumference 
(cm) 
77.3±10.2 
82.2±8.1 
69.6±8.1 </p>

<p>Bone mineral density 
(g/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
0.729±0.092 
0.773±0.062 
0.658±0.087 </p>

<p>Systolic BP 
(mmHg) 
122.9±17.4 
125.0±15.8 
119.7±19.3 </p>

<p>Diastolic BP 
(mmHg) 
78.0±11.8 
80.8±11.1 
73.5±11.6 </p>

<p>%vital capacity 
(%) 
112.3±16.0 
113.4±16.1 
110.6±15.7 </p>

<p>Forced expiratory volume 1.0sec % (%) 
90.2±7.0 
89.9±6.7 
90.7±7.4 </p>

<p>Red blood cell 
(×10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>/μl) 
4.56±0.45 
4.71±0.46 
4.33±0.32 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin 
(g/dl) 
14.1±1.4 
14.8±1.0 
12.9±1.2 </p>

<p>White blood cell 
(×10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>/μl) 
5.13±1.45 
5.25±1.50 
4.95±1.36 </p>

<p>Platelet 
(×10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>/μl) 
232±53 
222±51 
247±54 </p>

<p>Creatinine 
(mg/dl) 
0.78±0.16 
0.87±0.13 
0.65±0.11 </p>

<p>AST 
(IU/l) 
22.2±8.8 
23.7±9.4 
19.9±7.1 </p>

<p>ALT 
(IU/l) 
23.4±17.8 
27.4±19.9 
17.0±11.1 </p>

<p>ALP 
(IU/l) 
210.5±62.9 
213.4±59.9 
205.9±67.3 </p>

<p>g-GTP 
(IU/l) 
42.0±44.9 
53.1±52.6 
24.5±18.0 </p>

<p>Total protein 
(g/dl) 
7.29±0.42 
7.28±0.42 
7.31±0.42 </p>

<p>Albumin 
(g/dl) 
4.41±0.22 
4.44±0.22 
4.36±0.21 </p>

<p>Cholinesterase 
(ΔpH) 
1.04±0.23 
1.06±0.20 
0.99±0.27 </p>

<p>Total bilirubin 
(mg/dl) 
0.95±0.51 
1.00±0.37 
0.88±0.67 </p>

<p>Amylase 
(IU/l) 
87.4±31.2 
83.5±26.5 
93.4±36.7 </p>

<p>Fasting glucose 
(mg/dl) 
91.7±13.9 
94.3±14.7 
87.6±11.5 </p>

<p>Total cholesterol 
(mg/dl) 
202.8±36.4 
203.9±34.8 
201.0±38.7 </p>

<p>Triglyceride 
(mg/dl) 
108.8±77.2 
121.0±89.0 
89.3±47.1 </p>

<p>HDL cholesterol 
(mg/dl) 
55.9±14.0 
52.9±13.7 
60.7±13.1 </p>

<p>LDL cholesterol 
(mg/dl) 
125.2±33.9 
126.9±33.4 
122.6±34.5 </p>

<p>Uric acid 
(mg/dl) 
5.62±1.37 
6.24±1.21 
4.64±0.99 </p>

<p>Iron 
(μg/dl) 
114.9±41.6 
123.1±39.4 
102.0±41.7 </p>

<p>C-reactive protein 
(mg/dl) 
0.100±0.239 
0.110±0.265 
0.084±0.190 </p>

<p>Data are expressed as mean±SD </p>



<p>Yasuhiko Shimoyama et al. </p>

<p>Reverse primer 2: GGGGTTCCCGTTTTTCTCCC 
The region containing this polymorphism was amplified by PCR with these primers with the 
initial denature at 95°C for 10 min followed by PCR with these primers with the initial denature 
at 95°C for 10 min followed by 30 cycles at 95°C for 1 min, at 66°C for 1 min, at 72°C for 
1 min and additionally at 72°C for 5 min. PCR products were visualized on a 2% agarose gel 
with ethidium bromide staining. Genotyping was performed as follows; 317, 145 bp for AA 
genotype, 317, 212, 145 bp for AG genotype, and 317, 212 bp for GG genotype. </p>

<p>rs6721961 
Forward primer 1: CCCTGATTTGGAGGTGCAGAACC 
Forward primer 2: GGGGAGATGTGGACAGCG 
Reverse primer 1: GCGAACACGAGCTGCCGGA 
Reverse primer 2: CTCCGTTTGCCTTTGACGAC 
The region containing this polymorphism was amplified by PCR with these primers with the 
initial denature at 95°C for 10 min followed by PCR with these primers with the initial denature 
at 95°C for 10 min followed by 30 cycles at 95°C for 1 min, at 58°C for 1 min, at 72°C for 
1 min and additionally at 72°C for 5 min. PCR products were visualized on a 2% agarose gel 
with ethidium bromide staining. Genotyping was performed as follows; 282, 113 bp for CC 
genotype, 282, 205, 113 bp for CA genotype, and 282, 205 bp for AA genotype. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
All results are expressed as mean±SD, and significance was defined as a p value of &lt;0.05. 
The analysis was done by using PASW statistics <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18</rs> (SPSS Japan Inc., Tokyo, Japan). Hardy-
Weinberg equilibrium testing was performed by using the X 
2 test. Student's t test and multivariate 
analysis adjusted for age were performed in comparison of the mean values between the different 
genotype groups. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Incidence of Nrf2 SNPs 
Table 1 shows general characteristic of subjects. In this study, the genotype frequencies of the 
rs35652124 polymorphism were 21.1% for AA (n=98), 44.0% for AG (n=204), and 34.9% for 
GG (n=162). The frequency of A allele was 0.431, which was not in compliance with Hardy-
Weinberg equilibrium (p=0.026). The genotype frequencies of the rs6721961 polymorphism were 
55.2% for CC (n=256), 34.7% for CA (n=161), and 10.1% for AA (n=47). The frequency of A 
allele was 0.275, which was not in compliance with Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (p=0.005). We 
consider that the difference between the observed and expected values could happen by accident. 
Table 2 shows genotype frequencies of Nrf2 gene. A strong linkage was observed between 
these two SNPs (D´=0.944, r 
2 =0.445). AA genotype of rs35652124 and AA genotype of 
rs6721961 had more cases (43 cases) than expected (32.8 cases). </p>

<p>Association of Nrf2 gene SNPs with various variables 
Table 3 shows association of SNP rs35652124 with several variables. In male subjects, 
cholinesterase was significantly high, and HDL cholesterol was significantly low in (AG+GG) 
carriers. In female subjects, diastolic BP was significantly low in (AG+GG) and GG carriers, 
and total cholesterol was significantly low in GG carriers. The other variables did not show any 
significant association. </p>



<p>NRF2 and BLOOD PRESSURE </p>

<p>Table 4 shows multivariate analysis of rs35652124 adjusted for age. In male subjects, cholin-
esterase was significantly high, and HDL cholesterol was significantly low in (AG+GG) carriers. 
In female subjects, diastolic BP was significantly low in (AG+GG) carriers. 
Table 5 shows association of SNP rs6721961 with several variables. In male subjects, systolic 
BP, diastolic BP and cholinesterase were significantly low in (CA+AA) carriers, and iron was </p>

<p>Table 2 Genotype frequencies of Nrf2 gene </p>

<p>rs6721961 </p>

<p>CC 
CA 
AA 
Total </p>

<p>rs35652124 
AA 
18 
37 
43 
98 </p>

<p>AG 
79 
121 
4 
204 </p>

<p>GG 
159 
3 
0 
162 </p>

<p>Total 
256 
161 
47 
464 </p>

<p>Table 3 Variables according to polymorphism rs35652124 in Nrf2 gene </p>

<p>rs35652124 </p>

<p>AA 
AG+GG 
p value 
AA+AG 
GG 
p value </p>

<p>Male </p>

<p>n 
59 
226 </p>

<p>Cholinesterase 
(ΔpH) 
1.01±0.20 1.08±0.20 
0.028 </p>

<p>HDL cholesterol (mg/dl) 56.3±16.2 52.1±12.9 
0.033 </p>

<p>Female </p>

<p>n 
39 
140 
116 
63 </p>

<p>Diastolic BP 
(mmHg) 77.3±12.5 72.4±11.2 
0.017 
74.9±11.7 70.9±11.2 
0.026 </p>

<p>Total cholesterol (mg/dl) 
206.0±39.5 191.8±35.7 0.019 </p>

<p>Table 4 Multivariate analysis of polymorphism rs35652124 in Nrf2 gene (adjusted for age) </p>

<p>rs35652124 </p>

<p>AA vs AG+GG 
AA+AG vs GG </p>

<p>p value 
p value </p>

<p>Male </p>

<p>Cholinesterase 
0.037 
ns </p>

<p>HDL cholesterol 
0.036 
ns </p>

<p>Female </p>

<p>Diastolic BP 
0.050 
ns </p>

<p>Total cholesterol 
ns 
ns </p>



<p>Yasuhiko Shimoyama et al. </p>

<p>significantly high in (CA+AA) carriers. In female subjects, cholinesterase was significantly high 
in (CA+AA) carriers, and diastolic BP was significantly high in AA carriers. The other variables 
did not show any significant association. 
Table 6 shows multivariate analysis of rs6721961 adjusted for age. In male subjects, systolic 
BP, diastolic BP and cholinesterase were significantly low, and iron was significantly high in 
(CA+AA) carriers. In female subjects, cholinesterase was significantly high in (CA+AA) carriers, 
and diastolic BP was significantly high in AA carriers. </p>

<p>Table 6 Multivariate analysis of polymorphism rs6721961 in Nrf2 gene (adjusted for age) </p>

<p>rs6721961 </p>

<p>CC vs CA+AA 
CC+CA vs AA </p>

<p>p value 
p value </p>

<p>Male </p>

<p>Systolic BP 
0.008 
ns </p>

<p>Diastolic BP 
0.013 
ns </p>

<p>Cholinesterase 
0.044 
ns </p>

<p>Iron 
0.025 
ns </p>

<p>Female </p>

<p>Cholinesterase 
0.030 
ns </p>

<p>Diastolic BP 
ns 
0.040 </p>

<p>Table 5 Variables according to polymorphism rs6721961 in Nrf2 gene </p>

<p>rs6721961 </p>

<p>CC 
CA+AA 
p value 
CC+CA 
AA 
p value </p>

<p>Male </p>

<p>n 
154 
131 </p>

<p>Systolic BP 
(mmHg) 126.9±17.8 122.6±12.8 0.019 </p>

<p>Diastolic BP 
(mmHg) 82.2±12.4 
79.3±9.1 
0.024 </p>

<p>Cholinesterase 
(ΔpH) 
1.09±0.21 1.04±0.19 
0.024 </p>

<p>Iron 
(μg/dl) 118.4±39.3 128.5±39.1 0.033 </p>

<p>Female </p>

<p>n 
102 
77 
160 
19 </p>

<p>Cholinesterase 
(ΔpH) 
0.96±0.29 1.05±0.22 
0.024 </p>

<p>Diastolic BP 
(mmHg) 
72.9±11.0 78.5±15.5 
0.045 </p>



<p>NRF2 and BLOOD PRESSURE </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Nrf2 is a member of the cap'n'collar family of basic leucine zipper transcription factors that 
regulate the expression of many antioxidant pathway genes in the so-called phase 2 response. </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>Under oxidative stress, phase 2 enzymes such as NAD(P)H: quinone oxidoreductase-1 (NQO1), 
glutathione peroxidase 2 (GPX2), and heme oxygenase-1 (HO-1), are induced to provide anti-
oxidant and anti-inflammatory effects. 
16) This process is mediated by activating the Nrf2-ARE 
pathway. 
1) Therefore, Nrf2 protects cells from oxidative stress. 
This study first demonstrated that Nrf2 polymorphisms are associated with BP in Japanese 
subjects. In male subjects, systolic BP and diastolic BP were significantly low in rs6721961 
(CA+AA) carriers. In female subjects, diastolic BP was significantly low in rs35652124 (AG+GG) 
carriers. Nitric oxide can be degraded by superoxide free radicals, and oxidative stress can thus 
increase BP. 
17) Nrf2 may be involved in the regulation of anti-oxidative gene expression or anti-
oxidant enzyme activities in the vessels. Marzec et al. 
12) reported that Nrf2 gene transcription 
activity was significantly high in rs6721961 C wild-type compared to promoter constructs bearing 
rs35652124 G and rs6721961 A variants. These promoter polymorphisms were predicted to have 
functional significance, and rs6721961 affects basal Nrf2 expression and function. 
12) Thus, different 
transcription activity due to Nrf2 gene polymorphisms might affect BP by modulating protection 
against vascular oxidative stress. 
In male subjects, cholinesterase was significantly high in rs35652124 (AG+GG) carriers. 
HDL cholesterol was significantly low in rs35652124 (AG+GG) carriers. Cholinesterase was 
significantly low in rs6721961 (CA+AA) carriers. Because cholinesterase has been related 
with fatty liver, the Nrf2 polymorphism might be associated with lipid metabolism. Iron was 
significantly high in rs6721961 (CA+AA) carriers. Nrf2 participates in the expression of HO-1. </p>

<p>18) </p>

<p>HO-1 degrades heme into biliverdin, carbon monoxide and iron. Thus, Nrf2 polymorphism may 
also be related with this metabolic pathway with HO-1. 
In the present study, Nrf2 rs35652124 G allele frequency was 0.571, and rs6721961 A allele 
frequency was 0.276. These alleles may decrease Nrf2 transcriptional activity. 
12) Hapmap database 
reported that rs35652124 G allele frequency was about 0.3, and rs6721961 A allele frequency 
was 0.1 in European descent. Japanese seem to have higher frequencies of low-Nrf2-activity 
alleles. In fact, rs35652124 AA genotype and rs6721961 CC genotype were observed only in 
18 per 464 cases (Table 2). 
In conclusion, the novel finding of the present study is that Nrf2 polymorphisms are associated 
with BP in Japanese subjects. Antioxidative activity of Nrf2 might be involved in the regulatory 
mechanism of BP. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>None has anything to declare conflicts of interest. </p>





<p>Yasuhiko Shimoyama et al. </p>



</text></tei>