<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4966572" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: To examine the effect of sodium copper chlorophyllin complex on the expression of </p>

<p>biomarkers of photoaged dermal extracellular matrix indicative of skin repair. 
Patients and methods: Following a previously published 12-day clinical assessment model, </p>

<p>skin biopsy samples from the forearms of four healthy females with signs of photoaged skin 
were obtained and samples were analyzed by immunohistochemistry for key biomarkers of aging 
skin after each subject was treated with a test material consisting of a gel containing a liposomal 
dispersion of sodium copper chlorophyllin complex 0.05%, a positive control of tretinoin cream 
0.025%, and an untreated negative control. 
Results: There was a statistically significantly greater amount of fibrillin/amyloid P and epi-</p>

<p>dermal mucins found for skin treated with the test material containing 0.05% sodium copper 
chlorophyllin complex and the reference control tretinoin 0.025% cream compared to the negative 
control (untreated site). Expression of procollagen 1 and dermal mucin also showed a greater 
presence in the samples treated with the test material and the reference control compared to 
the negative control, though the differences were not statistically significant. No adverse events 
were observed or reported by the subjects during the course of the study. 
Conclusion: The results of this human biopsy study suggest that both retinoids and sodium </p>

<p>copper chlorophyllin complex have beneficial effects on biomarkers of photoaged skin. Prod-
ucts containing both sodium copper chlorophyllin complex and retinols may provide a dual 
approach to reversing age-related decreases in hyaluronic acid (HA) in the skin: inhibition of 
the breakdown of HA via sodium copper chlorophyllin complex by inhibition of hyaluronidase, 
and stimulation of HA synthases by retinol. 
The extracellular matrix (ECM) is composed of two main classes of macromolecules: 
proteoglycans, which includes glycosaminoglycan (GAG) chains, primarily hyaluronic 
acid (HA; hyaluronan); and fibrous proteins, which include collagens, elastins, fibro-
nectins, and laminins. HA is the predominant GAG of human skin, constituting more 
than 50% of the total HA in the body. 1 Because of its negative charge, HA is highly 
hydrating and serves as an extracellular reservoir that holds large amounts of cations 
and water, a mechanism for maintaining normal hydration of the skin. With advancing 
age, HA polymers become more tissue associated, presumably through HA-binding 
proteins such as fibrinogen, collagen, CD44, and hyaluronidase, which may underlie 
some of the changes in human skin that occur with aging. 2 The normal process of </p>

<p>Correspondence: John P McCook 
Discovery Partners, LLC, 4913 Southern 
Hills Drive, Frisco, TX 75034, USA 
Tel +1 214 448 6513 
Email johnmccook@att.net </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 
25 July 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>168 </p>

<p>McCook et al </p>

<p>aging, as well as premature aging caused by sun damage, 
involve similar mechanisms that cause loss of moisture and 
changes in HA distribution. 3 Degradation of HA in the ECM 
by hyaluronidases results in a breakdown of structural integ-
rity and an increase in tissue permeability, 4 thus inhibition of 
hyaluronidase activity prevents rapid degradation of HA and 
helps in maintaining structural integrity. As agents that main-
tain HA homeostasis, hyaluronidase inhibitors may serve 
as antiaging, anti-inflammatory, and antimicrobial agents. 5 
Sodium copper chlorophyllin complex is a semisyn-
thetic mixture of the water-soluble sodium salt of copper 
chlorophyllin and small molecule analogs derived from 
plant chlorophyll that possesses a unique combination of 
anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, and antioxidant activi-
ties. 6 Sodium copper chlorophyllin complex has been used 
topically for many years to aid in wound healing 7-9 but the 
ingredient has not been used until recently as an antiaging 
cosmeceutical in topical products. Sodium copper chloro-
phyllin complex has demonstrated inhibition of hyaluronidase 
activity in vitro, supporting the concept that topical applica-
tion of sodium copper chlorophyllin complex may be useful 
in the regulation of HA in the skin, thereby acting to enhance 
the improvement in the appearance of facial skin. 10 
Topical formulations containing a liposomal dispersion of 
sodium copper chlorophyllin complex have shown promise 
in the clinical treatment of various dermatologic conditions. 
A pilot study demonstrated that sodium copper chlorophyl-
lin complex was clinically effective and well tolerated for 
the treatment of mild-to-moderate photodamage and solar 
lentigines when used for 8 weeks. 11 Another study demon-
strated that topical sodium copper chlorophyllin complex 
was clinically effective and well tolerated for the treatment of 
mild-to-moderate acne and large, visible pores when used for 
3 weeks. 12 In uncontrolled case studies, topical application of 
formulations containing sodium copper chlorophyllin com-
plex demonstrated a reduction in facial redness, decreased 
pore size, and improved skin texture. 13 
The present study was conducted to examine the effect 
of sodium copper chlorophyllin complex on the expression 
of biomarkers of photoaged dermal ECM indicative of skin 
repair. In this study, skin biopsy samples from the forearms 
of four healthy females with signs of photoaged skin were 
obtained and samples were analyzed for key biomarkers of 
aging skin after each subject was treated with a test mate-
rial consisting of a treatment gel containing a liposomal 
dispersion of sodium copper chlorophyllin complex, 0.05% 
(Phytochromatic MD ® Complex; MDRejuvena, Inc., San 
Diego, CA, USA), a positive control of tretinoin cream, </p>

<p>0.025%, and a no treatment control. Tretinoin (retinoic acid) 
can repair photoaged dermal matrix and is regarded as the 
"gold standard" against which repair agents are judged. 14 </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Subjects </p>

<p>Females aged between 45 and 55 years were eligible to be 
screened for the study. Prospective subjects completed an 
eligibility and health questionnaire and were evaluated for 
eligibility criteria. To qualify for enrollment, subjects were 
required to have Fitzpatrick skin type II or III, with clini-
cally determined photoaged skin on the extensor surfaces 
of the forearms. </p>

<p>Study design </p>

<p>This was a single-center, randomized, controlled clinical 
trial (clinical trial #C15-D145) conducted over the course of 
12 days to evaluate the ability of a topical formula contain-
ing 0.05% sodium copper chlorophyllin complex to repair 
photoaged dermal matrix by monitoring changes in reported 
biomarkers from skin biopsy specimens taken from the outer 
forearms of subjects. Prior to study enrollment, the proto-
col, informed consent form, and recruitment materials were 
approved by the IntegReview Institutional Review Board. 
Testing was conducted between August 15, 2015, and Sep-
tember 2, 2015, by Thomas J Stephens &amp; Associates, Inc., 
Richardson, TX, USA; Stephens Study Number C15-D145. </p>

<p>Test material </p>

<p>The test material was gel formula DR198-02 containing 
an aqueous liposomal dispersion of 0.05% sodium copper 
chlorophyllin complex. 
The cosmetic ingredient declaration to qualitatively 
describe the gel formula DR198-02 is as follows: </p>

<p>Water (aqua) 
Pentylene glycol 
Sodium lactate 
Butylene glycol 
Carbomer 
Chlorophyllin-copper complex 
Phosphatidylcholine 
Phenoxyethanol 
Glycerin 
Camellia sinensis (green tea) leaf extract 
Sodium hydroxide 
Sodium ascorbate* (*antioxidant preservative present 
at &lt;1 ppm) </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>169 </p>

<p>Repair of skin photoaging by sodium copper chlorophyllin complex </p>

<p>Study procedures </p>

<p>The study design used for this trial was modeled after 
Watson et al, 14 in which retinoic acid was used as a posi-
tive control against which to test the activity of a variety of 
antiaging products to repair photoaged skin as assessed by 
the expression of key biomarkers. Qualified subjects had 
three 4×5 cm patch sites marked on the extensor surface 
of the left or right forearm according to a predetermined 
randomization. On days 1, 4, 6, 8, and 10, 50 µL of the 
test material (formula DR198-02 containing 0.05% sodium 
copper chlorophyllin complex) was dosed directly onto 
one of the randomized marked patch sites, for 12 days of 
exposure. On day 8, 50 µL of the reference control mate-
rial (tretinoin 0.025% cream) was dosed directly onto 
an assigned patch site, for 4 days of exposure only (to 
minimize the potential for skin irritation) as described by 
Watson et al. 14 The remaining site was untreated during 
the course of the study to serve as a negative control. All 
three test sites were covered with Finn Chambers (Aller-
derm Laboratories, Inc., Mill Valley, CA, USA) 12 mm 
inner diameter aluminum chambers affixed to Scanpore 
Tape (Norgesplaster A/S, Kristiansand, Norway) on each 
application day. 
Clinical evaluations were conducted at visit 2 (day 4), visit 
3 (day 6), visit 4 (day 8), visit 5 (day 10), and visit 6 (day 12) 
for reaction grading and scoring of test sites. </p>

<p>Biopsy procedures and scoring </p>

<p>Selected subjects had a 3 mm punch biopsy collected from 
each of the three test sites at day 12. Biopsies were trans-
ferred immediately after collection into 10% neutral buffered 
formalin solution and stored at room temperature overnight. 
Samples were shipped to Pro Path (Dallas, TX, USA) the 
next day for processing by paraffin embedding. Tissue sec-
tions were processed for immunohistochemistry staining 
for procollagen 1, fibrillin 1 surrogate stain amyloid P, and 
mucins (dermal and epidermal; by both colloidal iron and 
Alcian blue staining methods). Expression of these markers 
was graded by an expert grader using the following scale 
(half-points were acceptable): </p>

<p>Procollagen 1: cytoplasmic stain in dermal fibroblastic 
cells, scale refers to % of cells with positive staining: 
1 =&lt;5% cells 
2 =5%-10% cells 
3 =10%-20% cells 
4 =20%-30% cells 
5 =&gt;30% cells </p>

<p>Fibrillin 1 surrogate staining using amyloid P: 
0 =within normal limits 
1 =mild increase in reticulin fibers 
2 =moderate increase in reticulin fibers 
3 =marked, diffuse increase in dermal reticulin fibers </p>

<p>Mucin: 
0 =normal 
1 =mild increase in interstitial mucin 
2 =moderate increase in interstitial mucin 
3 =marked mucin deposition </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Procollagen 1 </p>

<p>Sample slides were processed for immunohistochemistry 
staining for procollagen type 1 performed using MAB1912 
anti-procollagen type I antibody, N-terminus, clone M-58 
from EMD Millipore (Billerica, MA, USA), according to 
the manufacturer's directions. Antibody dilutions of 1:100 
to 1:1,000 were used, after treatment with 1% trypsin, 20 
minutes at room temperature. </p>

<p>Fibrillin 1 </p>

<p>Sample slides were processed for immunohistochemistry 
staining for fibrillin 1 surrogate stain amyloid P using anti-
serum amyloid P antibody [EP1018Y] (ab45151), a rabbit 
monoclonal antibody to serum amyloid P, from Abcam (Cam-
bridge, MA, USA) according to the manufacturer's directions. 
Antibody dilutions of 1:100 to 1:250 were used. Heat mediated 
antigen retrieval with citrate buffer pH 6 was performed before 
commencing with immunohistochemistry staining protocol. </p>

<p>Mucins </p>

<p>Two different histology methods were employed for epider-
mal and dermal mucin staining, colloidal iron staining and 
Alcian blue staining before and after digestion with hyal-
uronidase; the latter method was used to confirm the results 
of the colloidal iron staining method after the removal of 
HA-related proteoglycans with hyaluronidase. </p>

<p>Colloidal iron staining </p>

<p>Skin biopsy samples were fixed in 10% formalin for 20-24 
hours prior to embedding in paraffin. Fixed tissue was cut 
at 4 microns onto positively charged slides and the sections 
deparaffinized and rehydrated in distilled water. Slides were 
rinsed briefly in 12% acetic acid solution and placed in work-
ing colloidal iron solution for 1 hour (Muller's colloidal iron 
solution + glacial acetic acid + deionized water). Slides were </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>170 </p>

<p>McCook et al </p>

<p>then immersed in ferrocyanide-hydrochloric acid solution 
for 20 minutes at room temperature. Following a rinse in 
tap water, the slides were counterstained with nuclear fast 
red solution for 5 minutes. Slides were then rinsed again in 
tap water, dehydrated in 95% alcohol and absolute alcohol, 
cleared in xylene (×2), and coverslipped. Slides were visual-
ized via conventional light microscopy for mucin deposition 
within the epidermis and dermis (stringy-blue hue), and 
graded on the aforementioned semiquantitative scale. </p>

<p>Alcian blue staining before and after digestion with 
hyaluronidase </p>

<p>Skin biopsy samples were fixed in 10% formalin for 20-24 
hours prior to embedding in paraffin. Fixed tissue was cut 
at 4 microns onto positively charged slides and the sections 
deparaffinized and rehydrated in distilled water. Slides were 
placed in 3% acetic acid solution for 3 minutes, and then in 
Alcian blue solution (pH 2.5, 1% Alcian blue 8GX, 3% acetic 
acid, thymol) for 30 minutes. Following a tap water rinse, slides 
were incubated in 0.5% periodic acid for 10 minutes, rinsed, 
and then placed in Schiff's reagent for 10 minutes. Slides were 
then rinsed again in tap water, dehydrated in 95% alcohol and 
absolute alcohol, cleared in xylene (×2), and coverslipped. 
Slides were visualized via conventional light microscopy for 
mucin deposition within the epidermis and dermis (stringy-blue 
hue), and graded on the aforementioned semiquantitative scale. 
For hyaluronidase treatment, deparaffinized slides 
(4 microns) were treated with hyaluronidase solution (0.05 g 
lyophilized hyaluronidase in 100 mL of 0.1 M hyaluronidase 
buffer) for 1 hour at 37°C. Following a tap water rinse, slides 
were stained per Alcian blue protocol and visualized/graded 
accordingly. 
The difference between before digest and after digest 
was the final score for analysis (all postdigest scores were 0). </p>

<p>Statistical considerations </p>

<p>The per-protocol population was the primary population for 
all statistical analyses. The per-protocol population included 
all subjects who received treatment and completed the study 
in general accordance with the protocol. Only the data of 
completed subjects were analyzed. 
A mixed effect model was built at each available post-
baseline visit for biopsy grading scores. In the model, score 
is the response measurement, test site is the fixed effect, and 
subject is the random effect. Tukey's honestly significant 
difference test was used for pairwise site comparison to find 
which sites' means were different from one another. 
All statistical tests were two-sided at significance level alpha 
=0.05. P-values were reported to three decimal places (0.000). </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> software version 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.30</rs> series (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Statistical Institute</rs>, Cary, NC, USA). </p>

<p>Results 
Subject disposition and demographics </p>

<p>Five subjects were enrolled and completed the study. Biopsy 
samples were obtained from the first four subjects who 
returned for the biopsy visit. Subject disposition and demo-
graphics are shown in Table 1. All five subjects enrolled 
were Caucasian females, median age of 49 years (median 
age 51 years for the four biopsy subjects). Four of the five 
subjects (three of the four biopsy subjects) had Fitzpatrick 
skin type II and one subject had Fitzpatrick skin type III. </p>

<p>Biopsy analysis results </p>

<p>Biopsy analyses results are presented in Tables 2 and 3. 
Biopsy results for the presence of fibrillin/amyloid P 
indicate a statistically significant difference in favor of the 
test material (mean score of 1.25) and the reference control 
(mean score of 1.50), when compared to the negative control 
(mean score of 0.25). 
Biopsy results for presence of epidermal mucins (colloidal 
iron and Alcian blue/hyaluronidase staining methods) indicate 
a statistically significant difference in favor of the test material 
(mean score of 1.25) and the reference control (mean score of 
1.50), when compared to the negative control (mean score of 0.50). 
Biopsy results for presence of procollagen I indicate a 
greater percentage of cells with positive staining for the test 
material (mean score of 1.25) and the reference control (mean 
score of 1.50), compared to the negative control (mean score of 
1.00), though the differences were not statistically significant. 
Biopsy results for presence of dermal mucin indicate a 
greater presence for the test material (mean score of 1.75) 
and the reference control (mean score of 1.25), compared to 
the negative control (mean score of 1.00), though the differ-
ence was not statistically significant. </p>

<p>Table 1 Subject disposition and demographics </p>

<p>All subjects 
(N=5) </p>

<p>Biopsy subjects 
(N=4) </p>

<p>Age (years) 
Mean (SD) 
Median (min, max) </p>

<p>50 (3.9) 
49 (46, 55) </p>

<p>51 (3.7) 
51 (47, 55) 
Sex, n (%) 
Female 
5 (100) 
4 (100) 
Ethnicity/race, n (%) 
Caucasian 
5 (100) 
4 (100) 
Fitzpatrick skin type, n (%) 
II 
III </p>

<p>4 (80) 
1 (20) </p>

<p>3 (75) 
1 (25) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: SD, standard deviation; min, minimum; max, maximum. </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>171 </p>

<p>Repair of skin photoaging by sodium copper chlorophyllin complex </p>

<p>Table 2 Descriptive statistics for biopsy results at day 12 (N=4 subjects) </p>

<p>Parameter 
Treatment </p>

<p>Mean 
Standard deviation 
Minimum 
Median 
Maximum </p>

<p>Procollagen I 
Test material 
1.25 
0.50 
1.00 
1.00 
2.00 
Reference control 
1.50 
0.58 
1.00 
1.50 
2.00 
Negative control 
1.00 
0.00 
1.00 
1.00 
1.00 
Fibrillin/amyloid P 
Test material 
1.25 
0.50 
1.00 
1.00 
2.00 
Reference control 
1.50 
0.58 
1.00 
1.50 
2.00 
Negative control 
0.25 
0.50 
0.00 
0.00 
1.00 
Epidermal mucins (colloidal iron) 
Test material 
1.25 
0.50 
1.00 
1.00 
2.00 
Reference control 
1.50 
0.58 
1.00 
1.50 
2.00 
Negative control 
0.50 
0.58 
0.00 
0.50 
1.00 
Dermal mucin 
Test material 
1.75 
0.96 
1.00 
1.50 
3.00 
Reference control 
1.25 
0.50 
1.00 
1.00 
2.00 
Negative control 
1.00 
0.00 
1.00 
1.00 
1.00 </p>

<p>Notes: Fibrillin, epidermal and dermal mucin are rated on four point (0-3) scale: 0 =normal, 3 =marked increased staining. Procollagen is rated on a 5 point (1-5) scale: 1 
=&lt;5% cells positive, 5 =&gt;30% cells positive. </p>

<p>Table 3 Comparison details between test products for biopsies at day 12 </p>

<p>Parameter 
Overall 
P-value a </p>

<p>Comparison 
Estimated mean 
difference </p>

<p>Standard 
error </p>

<p>Pairwise 
P-value a </p>

<p>Procollagen I 
0.244 
Test material vs reference control 
−0.25 
0.26 
0.632 
Test material vs negative control 
0.25 
0.26 
0.632 
Reference control vs negative control 0.50 
0.26 
0.220 
Fibrillin/amyloid P 
0.002 
Test material vs reference control 
−0.25 
0.20 
0.483 
Test material vs negative control 
1.00 
0.20 
0.006 
Reference control vs negative control 1.25 
0.20 
0.002 
Epidermal mucins 
0.007 
Test material vs reference control 
−0.25 
0.20 
0.483 
(Colloidal iron or Alcian blue/hyaluronidase) 
Test material vs negative control 
0.75 
0.20 
0.024 
Reference control vs negative control 1.00 
0.20 
0.006 
Dermal mucin 
0.178 
Test material vs reference control 
0.50 
0.35 
0.392 
(Colloidal iron or Alcian blue/hyaluronidase) 
Test material vs negative control 
0.75 
0.35 
0.165 
Reference control vs negative control 0.25 
0.35 
0.768 </p>

<p>Notes: a P-value was calculated using a mixed effect model where test product is a fixed effect and subject is a random effect. Tukey's honestly significant difference test was 
used for pairwise treatment comparison. The null hypothesis is that the mean scores are equal between treatments. </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>Figure 1 Procollagen 1 dermal histology. 
Notes: Immunohistochemical staining for procollagen I, showing an increased level of staining in both the test material (A) (subject 4_site 1_procollagen a) and reference 
control (B) (subject 4_site 2_procollagen b), when compared to negative control (C) (subject 4_site 3_procollagen c). Scale bar =200 μm. </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>172 </p>

<p>McCook et al </p>

<p>Safety results </p>

<p>No adverse events were observed or reported by subjects 
during the course of the study, including 10 days postbiopsy 
at the time of removal of biopsy stitches. 
Under the exposure conditions of this test, the test mate-
rial, reference control, and untreated negative control were 
all classified as "questionable/weak skin irritant," the low-
est classification allowed by the test site protocol, and there 
was no statistically significant difference (P&gt;0.05) among 
the three sites. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study was conducted to extend the findings of in vitro 
and pilot clinical studies using sodium copper chlorophyllin 
complex and to further investigate the mechanism of action 
of the complex in the ECM. 
A previous study demonstrated inhibition of hyal-
uronidase activity in vitro by sodium copper chlorophyllin 
complex. 10 Pilot clinical studies demonstrated that a topical 
formulation containing a liposomal dispersion of sodium cop-
per chlorophyllin complex was clinically effective and well 
tolerated for the treatment of mild-to-moderate photodamage </p>

<p>and solar lentigines, 11 mild-to-moderate acne and large vis-
ible pores, 12 and demonstrated a reduction in facial redness, 
decreased pore size, and improved skin texture. 13 
In the present study, overall results from this single center, 
randomized, controlled, 12-day clinical trial indicate that both 
the test material Formula DR198-02 containing 0.05% sodium 
copper chlorophyllin complex and the positive control, treti-
noin cream 0.025%, increased the presence of procollagen 1, 
fibrillin 1, and epidermal and dermal mucins, which are bio-
markers of dermal repair, compared to the negative control. The 
changes in fibrillin 1 and epidermal mucins for both the test 
material and the positive control were statistically significant 
(P&lt;0.05) when compared to no treatment. It was not possible to 
directly assess HA content in the biopsy specimens; therefore, 
the results reflect the effects of the test material on GAGs and 
fibrous proteins in general and are not specific to HA. How-
ever, assessments of changes in epidermal and dermal mucins 
were used as a surrogate method for measuring changes in 
hyaluronan in this study. Since hyaluronidase digestion in the 
Alcian blue staining method removed all increases observed for 
mucins, this would suggest that the changes observed before 
digestion were from HA, and not other GAGs or protein-bound </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>Figure 3 Epidermal and dermal mucin histology. 
Notes: Histochemical staining for mucin via colloidal iron to highlight both epidermal and dermal mucins. An increased amount of mucin is seen in both compartments in both 
the test (A) (subject4_site1_colfe_orig a) and reference material (B) (subject4_site2_colfe_orig b) compared to the negative control (C) (subject4_site3_colfe_orig c). Scale 
bar =200 μm. </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>Figure 2 Fibrillin 1 dermal histology. 
Notes: Immunohistochemical staining for amyloid P (fibrillin surrogate marker), showing increased fibrillin signal in both the test material (A) (subject 4_site1_fibrillin_amyp 
a), and reference control (B) (subject4_site2_fibrillin_amyp b), when compared to the negative control (C) (subject4_site3_fibrillin_amyp c). Scale bar =200 μm. </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>173 </p>

<p>Repair of skin photoaging by sodium copper chlorophyllin complex </p>

<p>mucopolysaccharides. The increases in epidermal and dermal 
mucins demonstrated by the 0.05% sodium copper chlorophyl-
lin gives in vivo support to the hyaluronidase inhibitory activity 
of this compound that has previously demonstrated strong in 
vitro anti-hyaluronidase activity. 10 
Analyses of the biopsy samples showed a statistically sig-
nificant difference in favor of the test material and reference 
control for the presence of fibrillin/amyloid P and presence 
of epidermal mucins (Col/FE) when compared to the nega-
tive control (untreated). There was no statistical difference 
between the test material and reference control for any of the 
increases in the measured biomarkers. 
Tretinoin (retinoic acid) was used as the positive control in 
this study. Retinoic acid is a widely used treatment and consid-
ered the gold standard for photoaged skin. 14,15 It has been dem-
onstrated that all-trans-retinoic acid increases the synthesis of 
hyaluronan and upregulates hyaluronan synthase 2 (Has2) and 
hyaluronan synthase 3 (Has3) gene expression in cultured rat 
epidermal keratinocytes, and appears to be mediated by epider-
mal growth factor. 16,17 A recent publication describes a topically 
applied antiaging product that improved the appearance of fine 
lines/wrinkles and skin hydration, presumably by promoting 
restoration of endogenous epidermal HA homeostasis. 18 
Two products, Rejuvaphyl Rejuvenating Complex LS and 
Rejuvaphyl Rejuvenating Complex HS from MDRejuvena, 
contain both sodium copper chlorophyllin complex and reti-
nol, thereby providing the potential for a dual approach to 
reversing age-related decreases in HA in the skin: inhibition 
of the breakdown of HA by sodium copper chlorophyllin 
complex by inhibition of hyaluronidase, and stimulation of 
HA synthases by retinol. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>This clinical study demonstrates a statistically significant 
improvement in repair of photoaged skin by topical treatment 
with a test formulation containing a liposomal dispersion of 
0.05% sodium copper chlorophyllin, based on changes in 
key epidermal and dermal biomarkers. The degree of repair 
seen with the sodium copper chlorophyllin complex and the 
positive control (tretinoin cream, United States Pharmacopeia 
0.025%), based on immunohistological analysis, was not sta-
tistically different. The results support and validate recently 
published in vitro antihyaluronidase activity for sodium 
copper chlorophyllin complex. Topical retinoid and sodium 
copper chlorophyllin complex for repair of photoaged skin 
should be evaluated further in this biopsy model to quantify 
whether there is an additive or synergistic response with this 
unique combination of topical agents. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Medical writing assistance was provided by Georgia Theo-
fan, PhD of ProPharmaCon LLC, San Diego, CA, USA. 
MDRejuvena, Inc. (San Diego, CA) sponsored the clinical 
study described in this paper. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The first author, John P McCook, is Managing Partner of 
CHL Industries, LLC, the developer and licensor of topical 
sodium copper chlorophyllin complex technology described 
in this paper. The authors report no other conflicts of interest 
in this work. </p>



<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: https://www.dovepress.com/clinical-cosmetic-and-investigational-dermatology-journal </p>

<p>Clinical, Cosmetic and Investigational Dermatology is an interna-
tional, peer-reviewed, open access, online journal that focuses on 
the latest clinical and experimental research in all aspects of skin 
disease and cosmetic interventions. This journal is included 
on PubMed. The manuscript management system is completely online </p>

<p>and includes a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy 
to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real 
quotes from published authors </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>McCook et al </p>

</text></tei>