<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4781901" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>BACKGROUND/OBJECTIVES: Insects have been the subject of recent attention as a potentially environmentally sustainable and 
nutritious alternative to traditional protein sources. The purpose of this paper is to test the hypothesis that insects are nutritionally 
preferable to meat, using two evaluative tools that are designed to combat over-and under-nutrition. 
SUBJECTS/METHODS: We selected 183 datalines of publicly available data on the nutrient composition of raw cuts and offal of 
three commonly consumed meats (beef, pork and chicken), and six commercially available insect species, for energy and 12 
relevant nutrients. We applied two nutrient profiling tools to this data: The Ofcom model, which is used in the United Kingdom, and 
the Nutrient Value Score (NVS), which has been used in East Africa. We compared the median nutrient profile scores of different 
insect species and meat types using non-parametric tests and applied Bonferroni adjustments to assess for statistical significance in 
differences. 
RESULTS: Insect nutritional composition showed high diversity between species. According to the Ofcom model, no insects were 
significantly 'healthier' than meat products. The NVS assigned crickets, palm weevil larvae and mealworm a significantly healthier 
score than beef (P o0.001) and chicken (P o 0.001). No insects were statistically less healthy than meat. 
CONCLUSIONS: Insect nutritional composition is highly diverse in comparison with commonly consumed meats. The food category 
'insects' contains some foods that could potentially exacerbate diet-related public health problems related to over-nutrition, but 
may be effective in combating under-nutrition. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>However, in order to combat this problem, an international 
consortium known as IPIFF (International Platform for Insects as 
Food and Feed) is currently working to change EU laws in favour 
of greater freedom in marketing insects as food. This indicates 
that insect foods are reaching EU (European Union) markets, but </p>

<p>also highlights the importance of systematic research into the 
nutritional content and safety of commercially available insects for 
human consumption. 
Insects are not a new food, although they have not been farmed 
on a commercial scale for use as human food until fairly recently. 
Instead, the majority of edible insects are harvested from the wild, 
particularly in remote rural regions and in tropical countries with 
high biodiversity, where insects have been an important wild 
source of protein and micronutrients for millennia. 
6 However, 
insects are also a farmed or semi-farmed resource across the 
world. European honeybees are thought to have been domes-
ticated for 7000 years, 
7 and the domestic silkworm, Bombyx mori, 
has been farmed for at least 5000 years. 
8 Silkworm pupae, 
a by-product of the silk-making process, are used as human food 
in many areas of Asia. 
9 A relative of the silkworm, the mopane 
caterpillar (Imbrasia belina), is sold widely in markets and 
supermarkets across southern Africa, and the mopane trade is 
estimated to be worth millions of US dollars. 
10 In recent years, 
there have been systematic attempts to farm mopane worms in 
intentionally planted mopane forests, to meet increasing demand 
and to give rural women control over this important source of 
income, and these have met with varying success. 
11 This is part 
of a larger pattern: in many other areas of the world, NGOs 
(Non-government organisations), government-funded research 
teams, private companies and individual entrepreneurs are </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Intercultural Studies, Rikkyo University, Tokyo, Japan and </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Nuffield Department of Population Health, The British Heart Foundation Centre on Population 
Approaches for Non-Communicable Disease Prevention, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK. Correspondence: CLR Payne, Nuffield Department of Population Health, BHF CPNP, 
University of Oxford, Rosemary Rue Building, Old Road Campus, Headington, OX3 7LF Oxford, UK. 
E-mail: charlotte.payne@gmail.com 
Received 27 May 2015; revised 7 July 2015; accepted 10 July 2015; published online 16 September 2015 </p>

<p>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition (2016) 70, 285-291 
© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 0954-3007/16 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/ejcn </p>

<p>attempting to semi-farm insects that were traditionally wild 
harvested. For example, insect-farming initiatives in Thailand now 
produce palm weevils and crickets on a commercial scale, 
12 and 
similar farming methods are currently being developed for the 
African palm weevil 
13 and Mexican grasshopper, both of which are 
highly valued foods in the regions in which they are harvested 
from the wild. 
14 This shows an increasing interest in a fairly recent 
phenomenon: insect farming for human food on a commercial 
scale originated in Southeast Asia in the late 1990s. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>There are many advantages to farming insects. Crickets 
15 and 
weaver ants 
16 have a high feed conversion efficiency compared 
with traditional livestock. The greenhouse gas and ammonia 
emissions of five edible insects are lower or comparable to 
emissions from pig farming and far lower than published figures 
for cattle farming, 
17 and a complete life cycle analysis of 
mealworm production has shown that mealworms require less 
land, comparable energy input and emit fewer greenhouse gases, 
than milk, chicken, pork or beef. 
18 According to current research, 
therefore, insects are a cheaper and more environmentally 
sustainable to conventional livestock. 
The health consequences of insect consumption are less clear. 
The nutritional composition of many edible insects has been 
tested, and many have favourable nutrient profiles, particularly in 
the context of a locally-sourced traditional diet. For example, we 
know that that the palm weevil larvae consumed in some parts of 
Africa are high in lysine and leucine, both of which are found in 
insufficient quantities in tubers, the traditional staple food in the 
same regions. 
19 However, there is little experimental evidence to 
suggest that insects are nutritionally preferable to other plant-or 
animal-based protein sources. Insects have been considered as a 
potential source of nutrients for human complementary feeding, </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>but the results of human trials on health indicators are yet to be 
published. 
To address this lack of data linking health impacts with 
increased insect consumption, in the present study we chose to 
use evaluative tools developed 'to classify foods based on their 
nutritional composition'. 
21 These are known as nutrient profiling 
models, and can be used to derive a 'healthiness' score for foods 
based solely on their nutritional composition. A wide range of 
approaches have been used towards the development of such 
models, and opinion is divided over which approach is most 
scientifically robust. 
22 The scores produced by nutrient profile 
models have been validated against food-based dietary 
guidelines, 
23,24 the opinions of nutrition experts, 
25 theoretically 
constructed healthy diets, 
26 healthy diets achieved in populations </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>and (most importantly) prospective health outcomes. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>In this study, we wish to understand the relative nutritional 
value of commercially available insects and commonly consumed 
meats in two scenarios tackling two different causes of diet-
related ill health, under-nutrition and over-nutrition. For our model 
developed to target over-nutrition, we chose the Ofcom model, 
which is currently in use in the United Kingdom to regulate 
broadcast advertising of foods to children, 
27 and is the basis of 
regulation in Australia and New Zealand to both regulate health 
and nutrition claims and support the 'healthy stars' voluntary 
front-of-pack labelling scheme. 
28,29 We used the 'Nutrient Value 
Score' (NVS) as a model that targets under-nutrition. The NVS is a 
tool developed by the United Nations World Food Programme to 
inform the composition of food baskets and commodity vouchers, 
classifies individual foods on a continuous scale based on their 
nutrient composition, with an emphasis on micronutrient content. </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Table 1. Median and inter-quartile range for nutrients associated with over-nutrition, including those used in the Ofcom model, in 100 g of </p>

<p>commonly consumed meats, meat by-products (offal) and insects </p>

<p>Daily value </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>N 
Energy (Kcal) 
2000 </p>

<p>Nutrient content per 100 g edible portion </p>

<p>Protein (g) 
Fat (g) 
Saturated fat (g) 
Sodium (mg) 
50 
65 
20 
2400 </p>

<p>Beef 
42 
169 
20.6 
9.3 
3.8 
60 
139-218 
19.2-21.6 
5.1-15 
2.48-6.1 
52.5-66.5 
Chicken 
25 
152 
19.9 
7.2 
1.81 
80 
127-198 
18-22 
4-13.9 
0.8-4 
6 9 -89.5 
Pork 
10 
186 
20.1 
12.4 
3.5 
62 
123-218 
18.6-21.5 
4-16.2 
1.4-5.45 
55.5-67.5 
Offal (beef) 
8 
108 
16.9 
3.45 
1 
71 
92-126 
15.6-18.6 
2.18-5.38 
28-114 
Offal (chicken) 
10 
133 
16.8 
6.8 
12.1 
66 
110-250 
10.5-18.1 
3.75-19 
6.4-12.9 
50.5-79.5 
Offal (pork) 
13 
108 
16.9 
4.15 
1.2 
132 
97.3-125 
15.3-18.2 
3.13-8.3 
1.05-2.39 
119-140 
Cricket (adult) 
8 
153 
20.1 
5.06 
2.28 
152 
147-159 
13.2-20.3 
3.51-6.05 
143-178 
Honeybee (brood) 
5 
499 
15.2 
3.64 
2.75 
19.4 
12.3-18.1 
3.27-4.52 
Silkworm (pupae) 
3 
128 
14.8 
8.26 
3.45 
14 
126-131 
13.5-20.8 
7.63-11.9 
2.94-3.95 
Mopane caterpillar (final instar) 
3 
409 
35.2 
15.2 
5.74 
35.2-44.6 
14.5-15.2 
Palm weevil (larvae) 
15 
479 
9.96 
25.3 
9.84 
11 
452-582 
8.38-20.7 
24.7-38 
8.31-32.3 
1.2-109 
Mealworm (larvae) 
26 
247 
19.4 
12.3 
2.93 
53.7 
215-268 
18.1-22.1 
11.2-15.4 
2.59-4.17 
46.9-54.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Daily values from the US Food Labelling Guide. 
43 All are daily reference values (DRVs) with the exception of sodium, which is a recommended daily intake 
(RDI) value. </p>

<p>A comparison using two nutrient profiling models 
CLR Payne et al </p>



<p>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition (2016) 285 -291 
© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Meat and insect nutrient composition data </p>

<p>For a broad geographical spread of meat nutrient composition data, we 
selected one database per continent from the FAO INFOODS website, with 
the exception of South America where no English language databases 
were available: </p>

<p>1. Asia: The Concise ASEAN Food Composition Tables. 
2. Africa: Food Composition tables for Africa. 
3. Europe: UK COFIDS tables. </p>

<p>4. North America: USDA Food tables for standard reference (abridged list). 
5. Oceania: The Pacific Islands Food Composition Tables. </p>

<p>For chicken, pork and beef products in each database, we included 
every dataline with the keywords: '[Meat name]'; 'raw'. We excluded 
processed meats (for example, cured, dried, smoked, minced and 
enhanced) and any meats that were described as 'weighed with bone'. 
Offal and meat by-products are traditional foods that, similarly to insects, 
are rejected in contemporary 'Western' diets. 
31,32 Therefore, in order to 
evaluate these under-utilized meat products separately, any foods that 
fulfilled the above criteria but were not a specific cut of meat or a whole </p>

<p>Table 2. Median and inter-quartile range for the eight micro-nutrients used to calculate the Nutrient Value Score (NVS), in 100 g of commonly </p>

<p>consumed meats, meat by-products (offal) and insects </p>

<p>Daily value </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>N 
Micronutrient content per 100 g edible portion </p>

<p>Calcium (mg) Iron (mg) Iodine (mg) Vitamin C (mg) Thiamin (mg) Vitamin A (mg) Riboflavin (mg) Niacin (mg) 
1000 
18 
0.095 
60 
1.5 
1.5 
1.7 
20 </p>

<p>Beef 
42 
5 
1.95 
10 
0 
0.08 
0 
0.23 
4.7 
5-8.25 
1.54-2.31 
9-11 
0.07-0.07 
0-2 
0.17-0.25 
4.05-5.25 
Chicken 
25 
8 
0.88 
6 
1.1 
0.075 
0 
0.16 
6.5 
6.75-12 
0.7-1 
5 -7.5 
0-2 
0.0675-0.12 
0-16.5 
0.125-0.22 
4.87-7.65 
Pork 
10 
7 
0.8 
5 
0 
0.77 
0 
0.235 
5.6 
6-10 
0.7-0.8 
0-0.25 
0.635-0.928 
0.18-0.28 
4.85-6.86 
Offal (beef) 
8 
15 
7.3 
16 
1 
0.175 
249 
0.355 
4.6 
11.3-23.5 
3.8-10.5 
0-5.5 
0.11-0.28 
128 
0.185-1.13 
3.48-6.65 
Offal (chicken) 
10 
10 
2.45 
16 
6 
0.09 
39.5 
0.375 
3.85 
7.75-13.3 
1.25-6.07 
1-14 
0.05-0.125 
0.123-0.578 
2.25-6.45 
Offal (pork) 
13 
10.5 
4.8 
7 
6 
0.27 
5.5 
0.47 
4.18 
7.75-11.8 
2.55-6.35 
0-10.5 
0.12-0.32 
0-27.5 
0.368-1.44 
2.53-8.65 
Cricket 
8 
104 
5.46 
0.021 
3 
0.04 
6.53 
3.41 
3.84 
49.8 -287 
2.47-8.01 
6.44-24.4 
Honeybee 
5 
30 
18.5 
10.25 
25.7 
3.24 
22.7-37.3 
15.2-21.9 
19.1-27.4 
Silkworm 
3 
42 
1.8 
0.12 
1.05 
0.9 
Mopane caterpillar 
3 
700 
Palm weevil larvae 15 
39.6 
2.58 
0.00425 
11.3 
2.21 
0.028-48 
0.528-8.4 
Mealworm 
26 
42.9 
1.87 
0.017 
1.2 
0.24 
9.59 
0.81 
4.07 
30 
1.6-2.45 
5.7-20.5 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Daily values from the US Food Labelling Guide. 
43 All are daily reference values (DRV) with the exception of vitamins and minerals, which are recommended 
daily intake (RDI) values. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Bar graph showing the median values and inter-quartile range of Ofcom (adjusted) scores for insects (light grey), meat (medium 
grey) and offal (dark grey). Higher scores indicate healthier foods. </p>

<p>A comparison using two nutrient profiling models 
CLR Payne et al </p>



<p>© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
European Journal of Clinical Nutrition (2016) 285 -291 </p>

<p>carcass (for example, organs, skin and blood) were grouped as 'offal'. 
Where a range of values was provided, only the single best estimate 
(mean/median) was used. Where a value was listed as 'Tr' (trace), we 
replaced this with '0'. 
We also extracted datalines for six commercially available edible insect 
species that are currently produced using intensive or non-intensive 
farming: Cricket (Acheta domesticus), honeybee (Apis mellifera), domes-
ticated silkworm (Bombyx mori), mopane caterpillar (Imbrasia belina), 
African palm weevil larvae (Rhynchophorus phoenicis) and yellow meal-
worm (Tenebrio molitor). These data were taken from all English language 
FAO INFOODS databases and from a systematic review of published 
literature, and the datalines describe the nutrient composition of fresh 
insects in their raw, unprocessed state. Full details of methods and 
selection criteria are currently in review. </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>For all the foods described above, we extracted data for energy and the 
12 macro-and micronutrients relevant to calculating Ofcom Scores and 
NVSs. The final database contained 128 datalines for meat (42 for beef, 25 
for chicken, 31 for pork and 30 for offal) and 55 for insects. Many datalines 
had missing values for certain nutrients. In such cases, we replaced missing 
values with the median value for that category. </p>

<p>Nutrient profile models </p>

<p>First, we chose the Ofcom model, which scores foods on the basis of their 
nutritional content per 100 g of the following nutrients to limit: energy, 
total sugars, sodium and saturated fat; and balances this against 
constituent elements considered conducive to health -fruit, nuts and 
vegetables, fibre and protein. Full details on how the Ofcom model is 
applied are available here. </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>We used <rs type="software">Stata</rs> syntax (freely available on request) to generate Ofcom 
Scores for each food in the database, and adjusted the scores to fall on a 
scale from 1 to 100 where 1 is the least healthy and 100 is the most 
healthy. 
Second, we chose the NVS, which was developed to inform food 
assistance programmes for populations who are at high risk of under-
nutrition and micronutrient deficiencies. The NVSs are based on quantities 
of energy, protein, fat and eight micronutrients measured per 100 g (or 
relevant, food basket-specific quantity) of food to evaluate the relative 
nutritional quality of foods. We calculated the scores for each food in the 
database using an Excel file (freely available on request). 
We ran pair-wise non-parametric Mann-Whitney U comparisons for the 
scores (both Ofcom and NVS) of each category of food, using <rs type="software">Stata</rs> 
software. We applied the Bonferroni adjustment to determine the 
appropriate P-value indicating the significance of our results. Since we 
ran 132 pair-wise comparisons for 12 categories of food, the original 
P-value of 0.05 was reduced to 0.000378, and only the comparisons with 
P-values lower than this were considered as significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Table 1 shows the median and interquartile range of values in 
each food category for the nutrients used to calculate the Ofcom 
model. Saturated fat and sodium are the major parameters in this 
model that are relevant to animal products. Of the meat products, 
chicken offal is notably high in saturated fat (12.1 g per 100 g) but 
others have a relatively low median value (range = 1-3.8 g per 
100 g) considering that the recommended daily allowance is 20 g. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Insects, however, have a far greater range of median values, from 
2.28 to 9.84 g of saturated fat per 100 g. Median values for the 
sodium content of insects (range = 0-152 mg per 100 g) also show 
a greater range than for meat (range = 60-132 mg per 100 g). 
Values for protein content show the same pattern, with insects 
containing median values of between 9.96 g and 35.2 g of protein 
per 100 g, compared with 16.8-20.6 g for meat. 
Table 2 shows the median and interquartile range of values in 
each food category for the additional nutrients used to calculate 
the NVSs. Complete information is missing for all but two of the six 
insect species. The median iron content of crickets and honeybees 
is 180 and 850% greater (respectively) than for beef, which has the 
highest iron content of the three meats. However, iron content of 
beef offal is higher than crickets. All of the insects had higher 
calcium and riboflavin levels than any of the meats or meat offals. </p>

<p>Table 3. P-values </p>

<p>(Mann-Whitney U 
rank-sum test) indicating the significance of differences in Ofcom scores and Nutrient Value Scores of insects, meat and meat by-products (offal) </p>

<p>Ofcom score </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>Cricket 
Honeybee Silkworm Mopane caterpillar </p>

<p>Nutrient Value Score </p>

<p>Chicken </p>

<p>Pork 
Beef offal Chicken offal Pork offal </p>

<p>Palm weevil larvae Mealworm </p>

<p>Beef </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Cricket </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>0.143 </p>

<p>0.0143 </p>

<p>0.0134 </p>

<p>0.0092 </p>

<p>0.005 
o 0.0001 </p>

<p>o0.0001 </p>

<p>0.0149 </p>

<p>0.248 </p>

<p>0.105 </p>

<p>0.328 </p>

<p>Honeybee </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0.196 </p>

<p>0.0253 </p>

<p>0.0219 </p>

<p>0.0012 </p>

<p>0.0004 </p>

<p>0.0004 </p>

<p>0.0005 </p>

<p>0.0004 </p>

<p>0.143 </p>

<p>0.114 </p>

<p>0.221 </p>

<p>Silkworm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>0.422 </p>

<p>0.0253 </p>

<p>0.0369 </p>

<p>0.0066 </p>

<p>0.0038 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.0084 </p>

<p>0.0419 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.665 </p>

<p>0.128 </p>

<p>Mopane caterpillar </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>0.324 </p>

<p>0.334 </p>

<p>0.825 </p>

<p>0.0065 </p>

<p>0.0038 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.0053 </p>

<p>0.0557 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.664 </p>

<p>0.126 </p>

<p>Palm weevil larvae 15 </p>

<p>o 0.0001 </p>

<p>0.0006 </p>

<p>0.0373 </p>

<p>0.0063 </p>

<p>0.0197 
o 0.0001 </p>

<p>o0.0001 </p>

<p>0.236 </p>

<p>0.696 </p>

<p>0.128 </p>

<p>0.956 </p>

<p>Mealworm </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>0.401 </p>

<p>0.188 </p>

<p>0.526 </p>

<p>0.463 </p>

<p>o 0.0001 </p>

<p>o 0.0001 </p>

<p>o0.0001 </p>

<p>0.307 </p>

<p>0.452 </p>

<p>0.0181 </p>

<p>0.437 </p>

<p>Beef </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>0.859 </p>

<p>0.126 </p>

<p>0.359 </p>

<p>0.252 </p>

<p>o 0.0001 </p>

<p>0.251 </p>

<p>0.688 </p>

<p>o0.0001 </p>

<p>0.146 </p>

<p>0.0398 </p>

<p>0.0019 </p>

<p>Chicken </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>0.0028 </p>

<p>0.0155 </p>

<p>0.105 </p>

<p>0.0708 </p>

<p>o 0.0001 </p>

<p>0.0004 </p>

<p>0.0059 </p>

<p>o0.0001 </p>

<p>0.166 </p>

<p>0.0379 </p>

<p>0.0017 </p>

<p>Pork </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0.902 </p>

<p>0.123 </p>

<p>0.299 </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>o 0.0001 </p>

<p>0.579 </p>

<p>0.991 </p>

<p>0.0129 </p>

<p>0.602 </p>

<p>0.11 </p>

<p>0.903 </p>

<p>Beef offal </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>0.0001 </p>

<p>0.0021 </p>

<p>0.0095 </p>

<p>0.0093 </p>

<p>0.0001 </p>

<p>o0.0001 
o 0.0001 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>0.0001 </p>

<p>0.817 </p>

<p>0.79 </p>

<p>Chicken offal </p>

<p>0.0283 </p>

<p>0.913 </p>

<p>0.823 </p>

<p>0.652 </p>

<p>0.0001 </p>

<p>0.0058 </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>0.0017 </p>

<p>0.0217 </p>

<p>0.0007 </p>

<p>0.468 </p>

<p>Pork offal </p>

<p>0.11 </p>

<p>0.0132 </p>

<p>0.148 </p>

<p>0.0429 </p>

<p>0.0003 </p>

<p>0.0026 </p>

<p>0.136 </p>

<p>0.327 </p>

<p>0.187 </p>

<p>0.0003 </p>

<p>0.0075 </p>

<p>Numerical values in bold text indicate that the score of the food on the top row of the table was significantly (Po 0.000378) greater than the score of the food on the left column; Values in italicised text indicate </p>

<p>that the score of the food on the left column of the table was significantly (Po0.000378) greater than the score of the food on the top row. Standard text indicates no significant difference (P40.000378; the 
P-value 
was adjusted from 0.05 using the Bonferroni correction). </p>

<p>A comparison using two nutrient profiling models 
CLR Payne et al </p>



<p>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition (2016) 285 -291 
© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Figure 1 shows the median and inter-quartile range of Ofcom 
scores for each food, and Table 3 shows the P-values for pair-wise 
comparisons of these scores using the Mann-Whitney U test and 
the Bonferroni correction. There is no indication that any insect 
used in this analysis is a significantly 'healthier' alternative to meat 
using this model; instead, beef offal is classified as 'healthier' than 
three insects: crickets, palm weevil larvae and mealworms 
(P = 0.0001; P = 0.0001; P o 0.0001); and all meat and offal products 
are 'healthier' than palm weevil larvae. However, there is also 
significant variation between insect species: both crickets 
(P o 0.0001) and mealworms (P o 0.0001) are 'healthier' than palm 
weevil larvae. 
Figure 2 shows the median and inter-quartile range of NVSs for 
each food, and Table 3 also shows the P-values for pair-wise 
comparisons between these scores. Using this model, there is no 
significant variation between insect species. Crickets (P o 0.0001), 
palm weevil larvae (P o 0.0001) and mealworm (P o0.0001) have a 
significantly higher score than beef and chicken, but the only 
other pair-wise comparisons with any significant difference are 
those showing that pork products are more nutritious than beef 
(P o 0.0001) and chicken (P o0.0001). However, of the insect 
species, only crickets and mealworm had nutritional information 
for every nutrient used to calculate this model; all the others had 
missing values. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
The results presented here are the first systematic comparison of 
the nutritional composition of insects and meat, and their relative 
healthiness according to contemporary nutrient profiling models. 
Our first key finding from these analyses is that insects vary 
widely between species in terms of nutrient content and 
consequently their potential for combating crucial public health 
problems. Due to this variation, we suggest that the term 'insects' 
is not a useful food category in discussions of health and nutrition. 
Second, we find that many insect foods have a higher content of 
energy, sodium and saturated fat than conventional livestock. On 
the one hand, this suggests that these species are not suitable for 
promotion as alternatives to meat if the main priority is to combat 
diseases linked to over-nutrition, particularly since reducing 
dietary intake of sodium and replacing saturated fat with 
unsaturated fat is thought to reduce risk of heart disease. </p>

<p>34,35 </p>

<p>Although the associations between saturated fat consumption </p>

<p>and diet-related disease are controversial there remains strong 
evidence supporting the relationship between substituting 
saturated fats with unsaturated fats and reduced blood 
cholesterol. 
34 Similarly there is evidence for associations between 
blood cholesterol levels and coronary heart disease, 
34 and directly 
between fatty acid consumption on coronary heart disease. </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>Third, we find that insects tend to have very high micronutrient 
content, particularly in the case of micronutrients that are known 
to be deficient in many areas where food insecurity is high. 
Therefore, these species may be good candidate foods to promote 
in areas of food insecurity and malnutrition. 
Overall, the data presented here shows no evidence that any 
commercially available insect evaluated in the current study is 
significantly preferable to meat for the purpose of combating diet-
related disease caused by over-nutrition. Offal and meat by-
products, on the other hand, are potentially healthier alternatives 
to commonly consumed cuts of meat, yet offal and meat by-
products are not popular foods in Europe. In the United Kingdom, 
for example, offal has declined in popularity in recent decades </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>and in Italy it is still seen as the 'food of the poor'. 
38 Therefore, 
although the promotion of insects does seem to be justifiable on 
environmental grounds, when considering health in situations of 
over-nutrition some meat by-products may be a more appropriate 
alternative to commonly consumed livestock products. Further-
more, the current study also shows that only a single insect -palm 
weevil larvae -is significantly inferior to meat using a model 
designed to combat over-nutrition. 
However, analyses of nutrient composition using the NVSs tell a 
different story. According to the parameters set by this model, at 
least three insects do have a significantly higher nutritional value 
than the commonly consumed meats beef and chicken, and not a 
single comparison shows insects to be nutritionally inferior to 
meat. Insects as a commodity have many non-health-related 
positive benefits compared with livestock in terms of both 
financial and environmental cost, particularly in developing 
countries where under-nutrition is a key problem. The finding 
that insects and meat do not show significant divergence in 
nutritional composition suggests that there is no health-related 
trade-off in promoting insect foods over meat. 
Elsewhere, data on the dry weight nutrient composition of a 
broad range of insect species are available, 
4 and other research 
has compared the nutritional composition of meat and 
other protein sources. Quorn products, which are made using </p>

<p>Figure 2. Bar graph showing the median values and inter-quartile range of Nutrient Value Scores (a higher score indicates a more nutritious 
food) for insects (light grey), meat (medium grey) and offal (dark grey). Higher scores indicate healthier foods. </p>

<p>A comparison using two nutrient profiling models 
CLR Payne et al </p>



<p>© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
European Journal of Clinical Nutrition (2016) 285 -291 </p>

<p>myco-protein and marketed as alternatives to meat, have 
macronutrient composition profiles that are comparable to the 
meat products upon which they are based. 
39 Non-traditional, wild 
meat species have lower levels of nutrients to limit such as 
cholesterol, sodium, saturated fat and polyunsaturated fatty acids 
compared with farmed livestock, and also have a higher iron 
content. 
40 Insects offer yet another alternative to traditional 
meats, and as shown in this study, some do have favourable 
nutrient profiles compared with meat. 
However, nutrient composition is only a proxy for effects on 
human health, and this is a significant limitation of the present 
study. There have been few trials with human subjects showing 
the effects of insect consumption, and to date, the results of such 
trials are inconclusive. Two insect-based products fed to infants, 
containing caterpillars 
41 and termites, 
42 had a positive effect on 
blood haemoglobin levels and bodily iron stores compared with 
control groups. However, in both cases there was no observable 
effect on growth rates or prevalence of stunting. Therefore, the 
link between nutritionally favourable insect foods and health 
outcomes requires further research. The results of the present 
study can be used to inform the choice of candidate species for 
future human trials. 
A further limitation of our study is the lack of fresh weight data 
on the micronutrient content of several commercially available 
insects. As a result, we have substituted missing data with 
category medians, inflating the units of analyses for our statistical 
tests, and biasing our results away from the null hypothesis. 
Therefore, comparisons between meat and insects with missing 
values using the NVS nutrient profile model, which places 
emphasis on micronutrient content, are not conclusive at this 
stage, and should therefore be treated with caution. 
Overall, in this paper we present systematically collected 
nutritional information on a range of commercially available and 
commonly consumed insects, meats and meat by-products. We 
use relevant nutrient profiling models to combine this information 
into a single measure of 'healthiness', enabling a direct 
comparison of insect and meat products. Our key findings are 
that the nutritional profiles of insects show great variation; meat 
products may be nutritionally preferable to certain insects in the 
context of overnutrition; and several insects are potentially 
superior to meat in situations of undernutrition. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>All authors contributed to research design; CP conducted the analyses and wrote the 
initial draft of the manuscript; all authors commented on, edited and approved the 
final manuscript. We would like to thank the Daiwa Anglo-Japanese Foundation and 
the Great Britain Sasakawa Foundation for directly funding this research project. As 
individual researchers we would like to thank the Japanese Ministry for Education, 
Culture, Sports, Science and Technology (MECT), the British Heart Foundation, the 
University of Oxford, UK, Rikkyo University, Tokyo, and the Japanese Society for the 
Promotion of Science (JSPS) (Japanese Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research, Projects 
No. 22251002 and 26310314), for ongoing financial support. We would also like to 
acknowledge the contribution of the following individuals and organisations for their 
inspiration, encouragement and support in the course of this research project: 
Professor WC McGrew, Kushihara Agroforestry, the Oxford Food Forum and the Japan 
Vespula Society. </p>



<p>A comparison using two nutrient profiling models 
CLR Payne et al </p>



<p>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition (2016) 285 -291 
© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>



<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or 
other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons 
license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under 
the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license 
holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>A comparison using two nutrient profiling models 
CLR Payne et al </p>



<p>© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
European Journal of Clinical Nutrition (2016) 285 -291 </p>

</text></tei>