<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4632117" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Aims: We compared the efficacy of macitentan, a novel </p>

<p>dual endothelin A/endothelin B receptor antagonist, with 
that of another dual endothelin receptor antagonist, bosentan, 
in a rat model of non-vasoreactive pulmonary hypertension (PH) 
with particular emphasis on right ventricular (RV) remodeling. </p>

<p>Methods and Results: Unlike monocrotaline or hypoxic/ </p>

<p>sugen rats, bleomycin-treated rats presented a non-vasoreactive 
PH characterized by the absence of pulmonary dilatation to 
adenosine. We therefore chose the bleomycin rat model to 
compare the effects of the maximally effective doses of 
macitentan and bosentan on pulmonary vascular and RV 
remodeling. Macitentan (100 mg$kg 21 $d 21 ), but not bosentan 
(300 mg$kg 21 $d 21 ), significantly prevented pulmonary vascular 
remodeling, RV hypertrophy, and cardiomyocyte diameter 
increase. Cardiac protection by macitentan was associated with 
a significant attenuation of genes related to cell hypertrophy and 
extracellular matrix remodeling. Microautoradiography and high 
performance liquid chromatography analysis showed greater 
distribution of macitentan than bosentan in the RV and pulmo-
nary tissue. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Macitentan was more efficacious than bosentan in </p>

<p>preventing the development of pulmonary and RV hypertrophies in 
a model of non-vasoreactive PH. Greater ability to distribute into the </p>

<p>tissue could contribute to the greater structural improvement by 
macitentan compared with bosentan. </p>

<p>Endothelins are vasoactive peptides of which endothelin-1 
(ET-1) is the most abundant in the lung. ET-1 responses are 
mediated via activation of 2 homologous G protein-coupled 
receptor subtypes, endothelin A receptor (ET A ) and endothelin 
B receptor (ET B ). Beyond its vasoconstrictive action, ET-1 is 
involved in deleterious processes affecting vascular and organ 
remodeling, such as hypertrophy, fibrosis, and inflammation. 1 
Organ-selective upregulation of the ET system in cardiovascular 
diseases, including pulmonary hypertension (PH), 2,3 and its local 
autocrine/paracrine activity associated with a high tissue receptor 
density 4,5 suggest that the ET system can act as a key player on 
long-term disease progression by contributing to target organ 
remodeling. PH is a progressive disease leading to right ventric-
ular (RV) failure and ultimately death, even on currently avail-
able therapy. ET receptor antagonism is an attractive approach to 
protect cardiac cells from hypertrophy as it provides, beyond 
direct inhibition of ET signaling, neurohormonal blockade. 
Indeed, ET receptor antagonists were shown to be sympatholytic 
and to decrease aldosterone levels in patients with heart failure. 6 
The involvement of ET-1 in the pathophysiology of PH has 
been confirmed by the efficacy of first-generation ET receptor 
antagonists, which improved symptoms and delayed time to 
clinical worsening in patients with group 1 PH. 7,8 Recently, in 
the event-driven SERAPHIN trial, macitentan (10 mg) met its 
primary endpoint by significantly reducing the risk of morbidity 
and mortality by 45% in these patients. 9 
Macitentan is a novel dual ET A and ET B receptor antag-
onist with physicochemical properties favoring sustained 
receptor binding and high tissue distribution. 10,11 It was 
selected for development based on its oral efficacy in vivo 
in animal models of systemic and PH. 11-13 In the 
monocrotaline-treated rat model of PH, macitentan dose </p>

<p>Received for publication January 5, 2015; accepted July 2, 2015. 
From the *Drug Discovery Department, Actelion Pharmaceuticals Ltd, 
Allschwil, Switzerland; and  †Covance Laboratories Ltd, Harrogate, North 
Yorkshire, England. 
All authors except B. R. Whitby are employees of Actelion Pharmaceuticals 
Ltd. Dr. Landskroner is now with Novartis AG, Basel, Switzerland. The 
remaining authors report no conflicts of interest. 
Supplemental digital content is available for this article. Direct URL citations 
appear in the printed text and are provided in the HTML and PDF 
versions of this article on the journal's Web site (www.jcvp.org). 
Reprints: Marc Iglarz, PharmD, PhD, Drug Discovery Department, Actelion 
Pharmaceuticals Ltd, Gewerbestrasse 16, CH-4123 Allschwil, Switzer-
land (e-mail: marc.iglarz@actelion.com). 
Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. This is an 
open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License 4.0 (CC BY-NC-ND), 
which permits downloading and sharing the work provided it is properly 
cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially. </p>

<p>J Cardiovasc Pharmacol ä Volume 66, Number 5, November 2015 </p>

<p>www.jcvp.org | 457 </p>

<p>dependently prevented the development of PH, decreased RV 
hypertrophy, and increased survival. 11 
PH patients who respond acutely to vasodilators (ie, 
vasoreactive PH) represent a form of disease associated with 
exaggerated pulmonary vasoconstriction and/or at an early stage 
of the disease before development of established vascular lesions 
because of remodeling. These patients are amenable for long-
term treatment with calcium channel antagonists, whereas 
nonresponders (ie, non-vasoreactive PH) are considered for 
other pharmacological options: phosphodiesterase type 5 inhib-
itors, ET receptor antagonists, prostacyclin receptor agonists, or 
guanylyl cyclase activators. 14 In non-vasoreactive PH, vascular 
remodeling associated with cell proliferation contributes to the 
maintenance of elevated pulmonary vascular resistance leading 
to RV remodeling and ultimately to a decompensated heart 
failure. Therefore, to compare the efficacy of macitentan versus 
another dual ET receptor antagonist, bosentan, on RV remodel-
ing, we searched for a model of non-vasoreactive PH to focus on 
anti-remodeling effects beyond pulmonary vasodilation. The 
question whether animal models reflect vasoreactive or non-
vasoreactive PH remains unknown. In this study, we first 
screened several PH rat models for acute response to vasodila-
tors and then compared the disease-modifying efficacy of maci-
tentan and bosentan with particular emphasis on RV remodeling. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Animals and Characterization of the Non-
vasoreactive PH Bleomycin Rat Model </p>

<p>This study was conducted in accordance with both 
Swiss Animal Protection Laws and Directive 2010/63/EU of 
the European Parliament on the protection of animals under 
scientific purposes and was specifically approved by Basel-
Landschaft Cantonal Veterinary Office under license 371. 
Male Wistar rats (180-220 g body weight) were purchased 
from Harlan Laboratories B.V. (Venray, NL). All animals 
were housed in climate-controlled conditions with 12 hours 
of light/dark, maintained under identical conditions, and had 
free access to normal pelleted rat chow and drinking water. 
Saline or bleomycin was instilled through an intratracheal 
microsprayer (Model IA-1B-R; Penn-Century Inc, Wynd-
moor, PN). Control animals received 1 mL/kg of sterile saline 
followed by 1 mL/kg of air. Bleomycin-treated rats received 
a single dose of sterile bleomycin sulfate (1.5 mg/kg) dis-
solved in 1 mL/kg of saline, also followed by 1 mL/kg of 
air to distribute the drug equally throughout the lungs. Gen-
eration of other animal models of PH and characterization of 
the presence or absence of vasoreactive PH are described in 
the Supplemental Digital Content 1 (see Supplementary 
Material S1, http://links.lww.com/JCVP/A207). </p>

<p>Measurements of Pulmonary Pressures in 
Bleomycin Rat Model by Means of Telemetry </p>

<p>Conscious rats were equipped with telemetry transmitters 
to measure mean pulmonary arterial pressure (mPAP) as 
previously described. 15 Briefly, rats were anesthetized by inha-
lation of 2.5% isoflurane and were mechanically ventilated. 
After abdominal laparotomy and right thoracotomy, the </p>

<p>transmitter was sutured into the abdominal cavity and the sens-
ing catheter was positioned into the thorax via a trocar. The 
sensing catheter was then inserted into the RV and pushed into 
the pulmonary artery (PA). Tracings of the pulmonary signals 
were monitored continuously to verify the proper position in 
the PA during the surgery. The catheter was sutured onto the 
RV and the chest closed. During the surgery and throughout 
the next 5 days, rats received 0.03 mg/kg buprenorphine for 
analgesia. Seven to 9 days after instillation of bleomycin, rats 
developed PH and were orally treated with single doses of 
vehicle, macitentan, or bosentan and mPAP was measured. </p>

<p>Study Design for Comparison of Macitentan 
Versus Bosentan Chronic Treatment </p>

<p>Rats were treated orally by gavage with vehicle (n = 
18), 100 mg$kg 21 $d 21 macitentan (n = 18), or 300 
mg$kg 21 $d 21 bosentan (n = 16) 1 day before intratracheal 
bleomycin instillation. Treatment was continued for 4 weeks. 
At the end of the study, rats underwent echocardiographic 
analysis and then were euthanized and organs were collected 
for assessment of RV hypertrophy and lung morphometric 
analysis, as described below. </p>

<p>RV Hypertrophy and Echocardiography </p>

<p>Transthoracic 2D, M-mode, and Doppler imaging were 
performed in 8 animals per group using a Vivid 7 Ultrasound 
(GE Healthcare, Aurora, OH) echograph with linear and 
sectorial probes operated at 14 and 10 MHz, respectively, and 
data were analyzed using <rs type="software">Echopac</rs> PC software. Animals 
were examined 28 days post-bleomycin instillation under 
isofluran-induced narcosis (2.5%, inhalation). Measurements, 
performed by 2 sonographers blinded to the treatment groups, 
were made in accordance with the conventions of the 
American Society of Echocardiography. M-mode measure-
ments of RV free wall thickness and end-diastolic cavity 
dimension (left ventricle: LV and RV areas) were measured in 
the parasternal short axis view, just below the level of the 
aortic valve, and their ratio was calculated. Pulsed wave 
Doppler of pulmonary outflow was recorded in the para-
sternal short axis view at the level of the aortic valve. The 
sample volume was placed proximal to the pulmonary valve 
leaflets and aligned to maximize laminar flow. In addition, the 
PA acceleration time, velocity time integral, and ejection time 
(ET) were measured. By combining PA velocity time integral, 
PA area, and heart rate, echographic cardiac output was 
determined. The tricuspid valve was also evaluated for the 
presence of tricuspid regurgitation with color and continuous-
wave Doppler in the apical 4-chamber view; no alteration was 
detected. At the time of killing, that is, after echocardiography, 
a rapid excision of the lungs and heart was performed through 
a ventral thoracotomy, and each organ was weighed. After 
removal of the atria to the plane of the atrial-ventricular valves, 
the RV free wall was dissected from the LV and septum. The 
RV and LV + septum were weighed, and the RV-to-LV + 
septum ratio (Fulton index) was calculated. Tibia lengths were 
measured to normalize read outs because animals presented 
body weight differences between the groups at the end of 
study. Eight RVs from each group were then processed for </p>

<p>Iglarz et al 
J Cardiovasc Pharmacol ä Volume 66, Number 5, November 2015 </p>

<p>458 | www.jcvp.org </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>quantitative polymerase chain reaction, whereas the remaining 
samples were used for histological analysis. </p>

<p>Histology and Morphometry </p>

<p>Pulmonary arterial wall thickness measurement was 
adapted from Mouchaers et al 16 to assess pulmonary vascular 
hypertrophy. Lungs (left lobe) and hearts (RV) were cut sag-
ittally, fixed in 10% neutral buffered formalin solution (4% 
formaldehyde), embedded in paraffin, sectioned at 4 mm, and 
stained with hematoxylin-eosin, sirius red, and Orcein (lungs 
only). Slides were examined with Olympus BX46 micro-
scope, DP25 digital camera, and <rs id="software-1" type="software">CellSens Standard</rs> software 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 1.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Olympus Corporation</rs>, Tokyo, Japan). For each 
group, 24 transversely cut muscular pulmonary arterioles, 
ranging from 15 to 100 mm in diameter, were randomly 
selected, depicted at high-power field (objective ·40), and 
measured in a blinded fashion. The internal lamina elastic 
was considered as inner perimeter; therefore, the real caliber 
was extrapolated independently from the contraction status of 
the arteries, and then the relative pulmonary arterial wall 
thickness (RPAWT) was calculated as follows: </p>

<p>RPAWT ¼ medial wall thickness=outer radius: 
Medial wall thickness ¼ outer radius 2 inner radius: 
Outer radius ¼ 
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
ðouter area=pÞ 
p 
: 
Inner radius ¼ inner perimeter=2p: </p>

<p>Mean values per animal and then per group were 
calculated. 
Cardiomyocyte diameter was measured using a method 
adapted from Henkens et al 17 to assess cardiomyocyte hyper-
trophy. For each animal, 40 transversely cut cardiomyocytes, 
taken from areas not affected by cardiomyopathy, were ran-
domly selected, depicted at medium power fields (objective 
·20), and analyzed in a blinded fashion. Cardiomyocyte di-
ameters, chosen parallel to minimize the standard error at 
selection, were measured in microns. Mean values per animal 
and then per group were calculated. </p>

<p>Vascular Reactivity </p>

<p>Left PAs (2 mm in length) were mounted in organ 
baths under isometric conditions and bubbled with the 
following gas mixture: 5% CO 2 , 16% O 2 , and 79% N 2 . After 
a recovery period, vessels were stretched (2 · 0.5 g) and 
depolarized twice with 60 mM KCl. Endothelium-dependent 
relaxations were obtained with cumulative doses of acetyl-
choline (10 29 to 10 25 M) after precontraction with norepi-
nephrine corresponding to approximately 80% of the 
contraction to 60 mM KCl. After a 45-minute recovery 
period, endothelium-independent relaxations were achieved 
with cumulative doses of sodium nitroprusside (10 210 to 
10 26 M). After another 45-minute recovery period, 10 mM 
serotonin was applied to the vessel. </p>

<p>Gene Expression </p>

<p>Right heart ventricles (8 animals per group) were 
collected in RNAlater (Ambion, Austin, TX). Total RNA 
was isolated using MagMAX 96 kit (AM1839; Ambion) </p>

<p>according to the manufacturer's instructions or the 
RNeasy mini fibrous tissue kit, including the DNAase treat-
ment according to the manufacturer's protocol (QIAGEN, 
Hilden, Germany). The quantity of RNA was measured using 
a Nanodrop spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher, Suwanee, 
GA), and RNA quality was assessed using a Bioanalyzer 
2100 (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA). Total RNA was reverse 
transcribed with the high-capacity complementary DNA 
archive kit and subsequently preamplified using the 
TaqMan PreAmp Master Mix according to the manufacturer's 
protocols (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA) and quantified 
in real time using an ABI PRISM 7900 Sequence Detection 
System (Applied Biosystems/Life Technologies, Carlsbad, 
CA) or a BIOMARK HD system (Fluidigm, San Francisco, 
CA). The following commercial TaqMan assays from 
Applied Biosystems were used for messenger RNA detection: 
Col1a1 Rn01463848_m1, Fn1 Rn00569575_m1, Lgals3 
Rn00582910_m1, Lox Rn00566984_m1, Nppa Rn00664637_ 
g1, Nppb Rn00676450_g1, Timp1 Rn01430873_g1, Fst 
Rn00561225_m1, and Inhba Rn01538592_m1; and for nor-
malization: Ppia Rn00690933_m1, Pgk1 Rn00821429_g1, 
and Hprt1 Rn01527840 for the Fluidigm platform or 
B2m Rn00560865_m1, Gusb Rn00566655_m1, Ppia 
Rn00690933_m1, 
Ppib 
Rn003302274_m1, 
Rock1 
Rn00579490_m1, and Tor2a Rn04218104_m1 for analysis 
on ABI PRISM 7900. Results were calculated using the delta 
Ct method and expressed as fold changes between treated and 
vehicle animals. </p>

<p>Lung Microautoradiography Study </p>

<p>Nineteen days after bleomycin or saline instillation, rats 
were administered a single oral dose of 3 mg/kg radiolabeled 
14 C-macitentan (240 mCi/kg) or 15 mg/kg 14 C-bosentan (585 
mCi/kg) and were euthanized under isofluran-induced narcosis 
(2.5%, inhalation) at a time point corresponding to the respec-
tive plasma T max of the compounds (ie, 8 hours for macitentan 
and 2 hours for bosentan) and T max + 6 hours. These doses 
were selected based on their ability to reach similar plasma 
concentrations of the drug at T max . After perfusion of the lung 
with saline, right middle lobe sections from each animal were 
cut into small pieces and frozen in isopentane precooled with 
dry ice and processed for microautoradiography. For structure 
identification, hematoxylin and eosin or modified Masson's 
trichrome co-staining was used with the following procedure: 
samples were placed in a cryo-microtome (Leica CM3050; 
Leica, Nussloch, Germany) and replicate 5 mm sections cut. 
These sections were thaw mounted onto microscope slides that 
were pre-coated with nuclear photographic emulsion. Radioac-
tive carbon-14 standards were also prepared in water in the 
nominal ranges of 0.093-555 kBq/g. These standards were 
freeze embedded and cryosectioned in a similar manner to 
the lung tissues described above. After autoradiographic expo-
sure for 67 days, the slides were photographically processed 
and histologically evaluated. </p>

<p>Pulmonary and Cardiac Drug Concentrations </p>

<p>The pharmacokinetic study of drug concentrations in 
lung and RV was performed in separate animals. Nineteen 
days after bleomycin instillation, rats (n = 6 per group) were </p>

<p>J Cardiovasc Pharmacol ä Volume 66, Number 5, November 2015 
Macitentan Vs Bosentan in Pulmonary Hypertension </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.jcvp.org | 459 </p>

<p>acutely treated by oral gavage with either macitentan (3 mg/ 
kg) or bosentan (15 mg/kg). These doses were identical to 
those used in the microautoradiography study. At the respec-
tive T max of each drug, sublingual vein blood was collected 
under isoflurane anesthesia. At T max + 6 hours of each drug, 
all rats were anesthetized under isofluran-induced narcosis 
(2.5%, inhalation) and killed by retrograde perfusion via the 
abdominal aorta (perfusion pressure, 90 mm Hg), with a pre-
warmed phosphate buffer solution. The vena cava was 
dissected to prevent the recirculation of perfusate. After per-
fusion, the lung and RV were harvested, dissected, weighed, 
snap frozen, and stored at 2808C. Plasma and organ 
concentrations of macitentan, its active metabolite ACT-
132577, and bosentan were measured by liquid chromatog-
raphy coupled to mass spectrometry (LC-MS), as previously 
described. 11 A similar study using the same doses of drugs 
was performed in monocrotaline rats (see Supplementary 
Material S1, Supplemental Digital Content, http://links. 
lww.com/JCVP/A207, for animal preparation) to confirm </p>

<p>the pattern of distribution of macitentan and bosentan in 
another model of PH. </p>

<p>Expression of Results and Statistical Analyses </p>

<p>Results are expressed as means 6 SEM. Analysis of 
variance for repeated measures followed by the Newman-
Keuls procedure for multiple comparisons was used for 
between-group comparisons. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Evaluation of Vascular Reactivity and Search 
for a Non-vasoreactive PH Model </p>

<p>Rats treated with bleomycin or monocrotaline or 
animals receiving a single administration of Sugen 5416, 
combined with exposure of 3 weeks of chronic hypoxia (10% 
O 2 ), followed by 2 weeks of reexposure to normoxia (SU/ 
HYP), developed different grades of PH with increased 
mPAP of 33 6 3, 52 6 6, and 86 6 5 mm Hg, respectively, </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Characterization of the non-vasoreactive bleomycin-induced PH model. A, Dose-response curve for adenosine 
(intravenous) on mPAP in anesthetized rats without (controls) or with PH; n = 6-7 per group. B, Representative pictures of 
pulmonary arterial remodeling in control (left) and bleomycin-instilled rats (right). Hypertrophied pulmonary arterioles of bleo-
mycin rats are surrounded by stromal changes, such as fibrotic foci and edema. Staining: hematoxylin and eosin (scale bar 
represents 50 mm). C, Representative M-mode measurements of RV free wall thickness (RVWT) as observed in the parasternal short 
axis view. </p>

<p>Iglarz et al 
J Cardiovasc Pharmacol ä Volume 66, Number 5, November 2015 </p>

<p>460 | www.jcvp.org </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>compared with an mPAP of 21 6 1 mm Hg in healthy control 
animals. Intravenous infusion of adenosine decreased pulmo-
nary pressure by approximately 15% in monocrotaline and 
SU/HYP rats, but not in bleomycin-instilled rats (Fig. 1A), 
despite a lower baseline mPAP in this latter model. A similar 
response pattern was observed after acute amlodipine admin-
istration (data not shown). Therefore, the bleomycin-instilled 
rat was identified as a non-vasoreactive PH model. This PH 
model is not solely because of fibrotic lung disease as path-
ological vascular lesions in the lung of bleomycin rats reca-
pitulate most of the lesions described in group 1 PH 
patients 18 : medial hypertrophy, intimal proliferative and 
fibrotic changes, and adventitial thickening with moderate 
perivascular inflammatory infiltrate (Fig. 1B). However, no 
complex or thrombotic lesions were found. 
We next assessed the temporal development of 
bleomycin-induced PH in conscious freely moving rats that 
were implanted with telemetry pressure transmitters. As 
shown in Figure 2A, mPAP started to increase 2-3 days after 
intratracheal instillation of bleomycin, reaching a plateau of 
+13 mm Hg versus control rats at day 7, and this elevated 
mPAP level remained unchanged until day 28. </p>

<p>Superior Long-term Efficacy of Macitentan in 
the Prevention of RV Remodeling </p>

<p>We next performed a dose-response experiment in 
bleomycin-treated rats to determine the maximal effective 
dose on mPAP (Fig. 2B). Maximal effective doses on pulmo-
nary hemodynamics were selected to assess optimally the 
potential of each drug on vascular and cardiac remodeling. 
Although 10 and 30 mg/kg seemed to be the first maximal 
effective doses on hemodynamics for macitentan and bosen-
tan, respectively, we decided to select 10 times higher doses 
to ensure a positive effect of remodeling. Therefore, the 100 
mg/kg dose of macitentan was selected for a direct compar-
ison study with bosentan, which was used at 300 mg/kg, as </p>

<p>this was previously shown to be the maximal effective dose 
on RV remodeling 11 and hemodynamics 13 in PH animal 
models. 
In the absence of compound treatment, bleomycin-
instilled rats displayed a marked decrease in body weight and 
a significant increase of RV free wall thickness versus saline-
instilled control animals after 4 weeks (Table 1, Fig. 1C). 
However, bleomycin-instilled rats showed neither significant 
RV dysfunction, as assessed by echocardiography (Table 1), 
nor development of RV fibrosis (data not shown). RV remod-
eling in bleomycin-induced PH animals was characterized by 
a 51% increase of RV/(LV + S) ratio and a 14% increase of 
cardiomyocyte diameter compared with saline-instilled con-
trol animals (Figs. 3A, B). Bleomycin-induced lung fibrosis 
was observed (Fig. 1B) and pulmonary arterial walls thick-
ened in bleomycin-treated animals by 53% relative to saline-
instilled controls (Fig. 4). Both macitentan and bosentan 
consistently and significantly prevented body weight loss in 
bleomycin-instilled animals (both P , 0.01 vs. bleomycin + 
vehicle) (Table 1). However, only macitentan consistently 
and significantly reduced the development of RV hypertrophy 
(Fulton index) and cardiomyocyte size increase, by 82% and 
100%, respectively (both P , 0.01 vs. bleomycin + vehicle, 
Figs. 3A, B), whereas bosentan, despite a tendency of 
decrease, had no significant effect. Macitentan, but not bo-
sentan, significantly reduced pulmonary arterial wall thicken-
ing by 260% (P , 0.05 vs. bleomycin + vehicle) (Figs. 4A, 
B). Both macitentan and bosentan partially prevented the 
development of lung fibrosis (data not shown). </p>

<p>Macitentan Attenuates Bleomycin-induced 
RV Gene Expression Changes </p>

<p>To further characterize the better efficacy of macitentan 
in comparison with bosentan in the prevention of RV 
remodeling at a molecular level, gene expression analysis 
was performed on isolated right heart ventricles that were </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Changes in mPAP of 
bleomycin-treated rats equipped 
with telemeters and dose-response 
curves for ET receptor antagonists. A, 
Time course development of PH in 
the bleomycin-treated rat. n = 9 per 
group. B, Dose-dependent reduction 
of mPAP by acute oral administration 
of bosentan (3-300 mg/kg) or 
macitentan (0.3-100 mg/kg) in 
bleomycin-treated rats; *P , 0.05, 
**P , 0.01, ***P , 0.001 versus 
vehicle; n = 4-7 per group. </p>

<p>J Cardiovasc Pharmacol ä Volume 66, Number 5, November 2015 
Macitentan Vs Bosentan in Pulmonary Hypertension </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.jcvp.org | 461 </p>

<p>isolated from compound-treated and vehicle-treated bleomy-
cin-instilled animals or saline-instilled control animals. The 
genes that were used in this investigation were selected on the 
basis of known contribution in remodeling/extracellular 
matrix deposition, that is, collagen1a1 (Col1a1), fibronectin 
(Fn1), lysyl oxidase (Lox), tissue inhibitor of metalloprotei-
nase 1 (Timp1), follistatin (Fst), inhibin A (Inhba), and 
galectin-3 (Lgals3), or cardiac function, that is, natriuretic 
peptide A (Nppa) and natriuretic peptide B (Nppb). Gene 
expression analysis revealed that macitentan normalized the 
expression of all investigated genes, in the case of natriuretic 
peptide A (Nppa) even to baseline (Fig. 5), whereas bosentan, 
despite a tendency of decrease, had no significant effect on 
bleomycin-induced gene expression changes with the 
exception of fibronectin 1 (Fn1) and galectin-3 (Lgals3). 
Therefore, at the level of gene expression normalization in 
the RV, macitentan also showed superiority in comparison 
with bosentan. </p>

<p>Efficacy on Smooth Muscle Cell Dysfunction </p>

<p>Vascular reactivity was tested in left PAs, which were 
isolated after 4 weeks from compound-treated and vehicle-</p>

<p>treated bleomycin-instilled animals or saline-instilled control 
animals, using organ baths under isometric conditions. In 
vessels from bleomycin-instilled rats, no obvious endothelial 
dysfunction was observed in response to acetylcholine but 
smooth muscle cell dysfunction was suggested by the right-
ward shift (although nonsignificant) of the response to sodium 
nitroprusside and the significantly increased response to 
serotonin (5-HT) (Figs. 6A, B, C). Bosentan and macitentan 
partially reduced response to 5-HT to a similar extent (258% 
and 262%, respectively, P , 0.05 vs. bleomycin + vehicle) 
(Fig. 6C), suggesting that both compounds had similar effi-
cacy to preserve vascular reactivity. </p>

<p>Increased Tissue Penetration of Macitentan 
Versus Bosentan </p>

<p>Based on our investigations described in the previous 
sections, only macitentan displayed significant prevention of 
RV and PA remodeling in bleomycin-induced PH model. We 
thus explored the possibility of different tissue penetration 
capacity as one of the possible contributors for the improved 
efficacy of macitentan. To this end, 14 C-labeled macitentan 
and bosentan were used to investigate the tissue penetration </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Effects of 4-week treatment with macitentan (100 mg$kg 21 $d 21 ) and bosentan (300 mg$kg 21 $d 21 ) in bleomycin-
instilled rats. A, RV hypertrophy. B, RV cardiomyocyte size. + P , 0.05, +++ P , 0.001 versus rats instilled with saline (control), **P , 
0.01 versus rats instilled with bleomycin and treated with vehicle; n = 8 per group. </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Effect of 4-week Treatment With Macitentan (100 mg$kg 21 $d 21 ), Bosentan (300 mg$kg 21 $d 21 ), and Vehicle on 
Echocardiographic Parameters in Bleomycin-instilled Rats Versus Saline </p>



<p>All data are presented as means 6 SEM. n = 8 rats per group. 
+ P , 0.05, +++ P , 0.001 versus saline; *P , 0.05, **P , 0.01 versus bleomycin rats. 
CL, cardiac length (ms); CO, cardiac output; ET, ejection time (ms); PAAT, PA acceleration time (ms); RVWT, RV free wall thickness; VTI, velocity time integral (ms). </p>

<p>Iglarz et al 
J Cardiovasc Pharmacol ä Volume 66, Number 5, November 2015 </p>

<p>462 | www.jcvp.org </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>properties of both compounds in vivo in lung and heart. 
Microautoradiography revealed that at T max after 14 C-drug 
administration, general lung tissue radioactivity was higher 
in rats treated with macitentan than with bosentan (Fig. 7A). 
For comparable plasma exposures, higher levels of radioac-
tivity were present in the walls and the adventitia of the 
blood vessels in the cuboidal cells and in the smooth mus-
cle/collagen region of the bronchioles of rats treated with 
macitentan, whereas in animals treated with bosentan, mod-
erate levels of radioactivity were present in the same struc-
tures. At T max + 6 hours after drug administration, high 
levels of radioactivity were maintained in the general lung 
tissue of macitentan-treated rats, although the intensity was 
lower than at T max as observed in structures, such as cuboi-
dal cells and blood vessels. In bosentan-treated rats, higher 
radioactivity was observed in the cuboidal cells and bron-
chiole smooth muscles compared with levels observed at 
T max (Fig. 7A), but general lung tissue radioactivity was 
lower in the bosentan-treated than in the macitentan-
treated group. Of note, after single oral administration of 
radiolabeled macitentan, more radioactivity was apparent 
in the lung substructures, particularly the cuboidal cells 
and smooth muscle/collagen regions of the bronchioles, 
when the animals had been pretreated with bleomycin com-
pared with control animals (Fig. 7B). Quantification of drug 
concentration by LC-MS in the lung at T max + 6 hours 
confirmed the microautoradiography findings as total lung 
contents of macitentan and its active major metabolite were 
approximately 4 times higher than that of bosentan for com-
parable plasma exposures as reflected by respective plasma 
concentrations at estimated T max (bosentan: 1625 ng/mL; </p>

<p>macitentan + metabolite: 2222 ng/mL). Moreover, the quan-
tification of macitentan and its metabolite in the RV indi-
cated a higher concentration than bosentan (Fig. 7C). This 
greater distribution of macitentan versus bosentan in lung 
and RV was confirmed in another model of PH (monocrota-
line rats, Fig. 7C). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Macitentan is a potent, novel dual ET receptor 
antagonist with superior in vivo pharmacological efficacy 
compared with existing ET receptor antagonists. 12 This was 
originally demonstrated by its remarkable activity in hyper-
tensive rats after oral administration, in which macitentan 
achieved a superior blood pressure reduction compared 
with other ET receptor antagonists, such as ambrisentan 
and bosentan. 11,12,19 In the present study, using a rat 
model of non-vasoreactive PH, we demonstrated that 
macitentan has superior anti-remodeling effects on pulmo-
nary arterial and RV hypertrophies than bosentan. In addi-
tion, macitentan showed higher RV and lung distribution 
than bosentan. 
We conducted our studies in bleomycin-treated rats 
known to develop PH. 20,21 ET-1 and its receptors have been 
proposed to drive disease progression in this model. 22-24 Orig-
inally used as an antitumor agent, bleomycin is a glycopepti-
dic antibiotic known to induce pulmonary fibrosis through an 
early phase of epithelial/endothelial damage, followed by 
inflammation and ultimately fibrosis. 25 Although this model 
has been primarily used to investigate pulmonary fibrosis, the 
animals administered with bleomycin also develop PH 20,21 </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Effects of 4-week treatment with macitentan (100 mg$kg 21 $d 21 ) or bosentan (300 mg$kg 21 $d 21 ) on pulmonary 
arterial remodeling in bleomycin-instilled rats. A, Pulmonary arterial wall thickness; ++ P , 0.01 versus rats instilled with saline 
(control), *P , 0.05 versus rats instilled with bleomycin and treated with; n = 16-18 per group. B, Representative pictures of PAs 
stained with Orcein, ·20 magnification (scale bar represents 20 mm). </p>

<p>J Cardiovasc Pharmacol ä Volume 66, Number 5, November 2015 
Macitentan Vs Bosentan in Pulmonary Hypertension </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.jcvp.org | 463 </p>

<p>associated with epithelial activation of ET-1. 23 Unlike the 
monocrotaline rats that develop rapid progressive and tran-
sient PH leading to death, the bleomycin-treated rats develop 
moderate and sustained increase in pulmonary pressure, 
which makes it suitable to study compensatory mechanisms, 
such as RV hypertrophy. 17,26,27 We report here, for the first 
time, in conscious freely moving bleomycin-treated rats, the 
temporal development of pulmonary pressure elevation using 
telemetry. Although moderate when compared with other PH 
models, the increased mPAP remained elevated over the 
study period and was accompanied by mild RV hypertrophy 
with preserved function and pulmonary vascular hypertrophy. 
Unlike the monocrotaline and sugen/hypoxia rat models of 
PH, the bleomycin rat presented a non-vasoreactive PH char-
acterized by the absence of an acute vasodilatory response to 
adenosine infusion and hypertrophic vascular remodeling. 
To directly compare the differences of macitentan and 
bosentan in this novel model of non-vasoreactive PH, we 
aimed to use the highest efficacious dose of each compound. 
An off-target effect can be discarded as macitentan was 
shown to be selective for ET A and ET B receptors when 
screened at a concentration of 10 mM in a panel of 63 </p>

<p>radioligand binding assays. 11 Compared with the monocrota-
line rat model in which both compounds were efficacious at 
lower doses, 11 the bleomycin rat model seemed less sensitive 
to ET receptor antagonism. This observation is confirmed by 
other studies demonstrating efficacy of bosentan on cardiac 
remodeling in hypoxic 28 and hypoxia/sugen 29 rats, whereas 
bosentan had no effect on this read out in our study. This 
suggests that the efficacy of compounds might be reduced in 
models on non-vasoreactive (eg, bleomycin) versus reactive 
PH (monocrotaline, hypoxia/sugen). 
We recently presented evidence that macitentan had 
a greater pharmacological activity versus bosentan in vivo: in 
bleomycin-treated rats, the maximal efficacious dose of 
macitentan was able to further decrease mPAP when 
administered on top of the maximal efficacious dose of 
bosentan. 13 Together with the findings of the present study, 
showing a superiority of macitentan over bosentan on RV and 
pulmonary vessel remodeling, our data suggest that maciten-
tan can achieve a more complete inhibition of the ET system 
in vivo. In addition to a longer effective half-life because of 
the presence of an active metabolite, macitentan differs from 
bosentan by its receptor-binding properties and its ability to </p>

<p>FIGURE 5. Effects of 4-week treatment with macitentan (100 mg$kg 21 $d 21 ) and bosentan (300 mg$kg 21 $d 21 ) on a panel of 
genes involved in RV remodeling. + P , 0.05, ++ P , 0.01, +++ P , 0.001 versus rats instilled with saline (control), *P , 0.05, **P , 
0.01, ***P , 0.001 versus rats instilled with bleomycin and treated with vehicle; n = 8 per group. </p>

<p>Iglarz et al 
J Cardiovasc Pharmacol ä Volume 66, Number 5, November 2015 </p>

<p>464 | www.jcvp.org </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>distribute into tissues. Macitentan is a competitive antagonist 
with a prolonged receptor occupancy half-life. Macitentan 
thus displays insurmountable antagonism, that is, it is capable 
of efficient receptor blockade irrespective of the ET-1 con-
centration. 10,30 In diseased tissues, where local ET-1 concen-
trations are elevated, such a binding mode together with the 
higher local concentration of the compound might confer 
superior blockade of downstream signaling induced by 
ET-1. In addition to the binding kinetics, we also hypothe-
sized that macitentan could have differential tissue distribu-
tion compared with bosentan, which we thought could be 
because of differences in their physiochemical properties 
(eg, pKa, lipophilicity). 11 Using microautoradiography and 
tissue quantification by LC-MS, we were able to demonstrate 
(1) differential tissue distribution of macitentan in normal 
versus diseased lung and (2) increased lung and RV concen-
tration of macitentan versus bosentan in 2 models of PH, 
suggesting that these findings are not limited to the bleomycin 
rat model but could apply to other models of PH. The use of 
radiolabeled material enabled us to study the distribution of 
both macitentan and its active metabolite. We previously re-
ported that oral administration of macitentan leads to the 
formation of metabolite ACT-132577, a dual ET A /ET B antag-
onist. Although its overall potency on ET receptors is 5-10 
times less than that of macitentan, ACT-132577 has a longer 
half-life than macitentan, accumulates with time, and is 
expected to contribute to the pharmacological effects 
observed after oral administration of macitentan. 11,31 The mi-
croautoradiography studies revealed increased distribution of 
macitentan-derived radioactivity in diseased lung tissue com-
pared with healthy lungs. This latter observation, which might 
not be specific to macitentan and could apply to other ET 
receptor antagonists, may be because of an increased perme-
ability of the damaged tissue and/or an upregulation of the ET 
binding sites in bleomycin rats. </p>

<p>Although macitentan showed greater effect on RV and 
pulmonary remodeling than bosentan, both drugs had similar 
efficacy on lung fibrosis. This discrepancy could be explained 
by 2 factors: first, as we used maximal effective doses of each 
compound to ensure maximal effect on the remodeling, one 
cannot rule out that a slight greater effect on mPAP obtained 
with macitentan (Fig. 2), possibly because of its ability to 
block more receptors than bosentan, could be responsible 
for its superior efficacy on RV and pulmonary remodeling 
compared with bosentan. Second, our results on lung fibrosis 
suggest that the ET system, although important, is not the sole 
driver in lung fibrosis and that a plateau effect has been 
reached with the 2 drugs. Of note, both clinical trials in 
patients with pulmonary fibrosis involving macitentan and 
bosentan did not reach their primary efficacy endpoints indi-
cating that targeting the ET system alone may not be suffi-
cient in this indication. 
The superior efficacy of macitentan on RV remodeling, 
a known predictive marker of mortality, 32 associated with 
a greater distribution in the RV suggests that macitentan may 
have potential for superior long-term benefit on clinical out-
come compared with bosentan. Although no clinical direct 
comparison was made, macitentan (10 mg) is currently the 
only ET receptor antagonist that demonstrated a dose-
dependent effect on a composite hard endpoint (mortality/mor-
bidity) in a clinical trial and a sustained 50% risk reduction in 
death or hospitalization because of PH during treatment. 9 In 
our study, RV protection was associated with a greater atten-
uation by macitentan of the expression of genes involved in 
extracellular matrix/cardiac remodeling (Col1a1, Lox, Timp1). 
Expression of genes encoding mediators of fibrosis, such as 
fibronectin (Fn1) 33 and galectin-3 (Lgal3), 34 was similarly cor-
rected by both drugs. In contrast to bosentan, macitentan sig-
nificantly decreased Inhba and Fst genes. The Inhba gene 
encodes activin A, a homodimer of inhibin beta subunit, related </p>

<p>FIGURE 6. Effects of 4-week treat-
ment 
with 
macitentan 
(100 
mg$kg 21 $d 21 ) or bosentan (300 
mg$kg 21 $d 21 ) on PA function. A, 
Dose-response curve to acetylcho-
line (ACh). B, Dose-response curve 
to sodium nitroprusside (SNP). C, 
Contraction to 10 mM serotonin (5-
HT). ++ P , 0.01 versus rats instilled 
with saline (control). *P , 0.05 ver-
sus rats instilled with bleomycin and 
treated with vehicle; n = 6-7 per 
group. </p>

<p>J Cardiovasc Pharmacol ä Volume 66, Number 5, November 2015 
Macitentan Vs Bosentan in Pulmonary Hypertension </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.jcvp.org | 465 </p>

<p>to the transforming growth factor b superfamily and involved </p>

<p>in cardiac remodeling and inflammation. 35,36 The Fst gene enc-
odes follistatin, a negative regulator of activin that removes 
activin A from the circulation. 37 Follistatin is upregulated in 
patients with PH, and its plasma levels are correlated with 
increased mortality. 38 In our study, increase of follistatin was 
observed in parallel to activin A activation in bleomycin-
treated rats, as a possible counterregulatory mechanism. Our 
data suggest that macitentan can blunt the activin A/follistatin 
axis to protect against the development of cardiac remodeling. 
Furthermore, the consistent and more pronounced attenuation 
of gene expression changes that are associated with heart re-
modeling could suggest improved local activity of macitentan 
in comparison with bosentan, also in the heart. 
As a study limitation, we did not measure pulmonary 
pressures in bleomycin-instilled rats at the end of the chronic 
treatment with vehicle, macitentan, or bosentan. The reason 
for this is that, in contrast to telemetry, we could not detect an 
increase in mPAP in anesthetized bleomycin-instilled rats 
versus healthy animals probably because of an effect of 
anesthesia on hemodynamics. 
In conclusion, our data show that the efficacy of 
macitentan is higher than that of bosentan in treating PH 
and RV hypertrophy in a rat model of non-vasoreactive PH 
induced by bleomycin. This may be because of the improve-
ment of binding mode and pharmacokinetic profile (tissue 
distribution, long half-life). A more complete blockade of ET </p>

<p>receptors, achieved by macitentan, is a promising approach to 
treat diseases where local tissue ET-1 represents a significant 
component of the pathophysiology. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS 
We are grateful to Odette Birko, Eric Soubieux, and 
Aude Weigel for expert technical assistance. </p>



<p>Iglarz et al 
J Cardiovasc Pharmacol ä Volume 66, Number 5, November 2015 </p>

<p>466 | www.jcvp.org </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>



<p>J Cardiovasc Pharmacol ä Volume 66, Number 5, November 2015 
Macitentan Vs Bosentan in Pulmonary Hypertension </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.jcvp.org | 467 </p>

</text></tei>