<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4496436" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Minimally invasive laparoscopic gastrectomy offers several </p>

<p>advantages, including less postoperative pain, better cosmesis, less </p>

<p>inflammatory reaction, more rapid recovery of bowel function, </p>

<p>and faster recovery compared with conventional open surgery. </p>

<p>1-3 </p>

<p>Single-incision laparoscopic surgery is expected to be the next step </p>

<p>in minimally invasive surgery owing to the development of laparo-</p>

<p>scopic techniques and instruments, and several studies have already </p>

<p>reported that this technique is a feasible alternative treatment for </p>

<p>appendectomy or cholecystectomy. 
4,5 For gastric cancer, single-</p>

<p>incision distal gastrectomy (SIDG) was first reported in 2011. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>However, unlike appendectomy or cholecystectomy, only limited </p>

<p>experiences with SIDG have been published to date because of </p>

<p>several technical difficulties, in particular, the intracorporeal anas-</p>

<p>tomosis technique. 
7-9 Compared with Billroth II or Roux-en-Y </p>

<p>anastomosis (RY), Billroth I anastomosis offers advantages such as </p>

<p>pISSN : 2093-582X, eISSN : 2093-5641 </p>

<p>Unaided Stapling Technique for Pure Single-Incision 
Distal Gastrectomy in Early Gastric Cancer: Unaided 
Delta-Shaped Anastomosis and Uncut Roux-en-Y Anastomosis </p>

<p>Yun-Suhk Suh </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Ji-Ho Park </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Tae Han Kim </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Yeon-Ju Huh </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Young Gil Son </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, 
Jun-Young Yang </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Seong-Ho Kong </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Hyuk-Joon Lee </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, and Han-Kwang Yang </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Surgery and </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cancer Research Institute, Seoul National University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea </p>

<p>Purpose: Intracorporeal anastomosis is the most difficult procedure during pure single-incision distal gastrectomy (SIDG) that affects its 
generalization. We introduced unaided delta-shaped anastomosis (uDelta), a novel anastomosis technique, for gastroduodenostomy after 
pure SIDG, and compared the results with those of previously reported Roux-en-Y anastomosis (RY). 
Materials and Methods: Between March 2014 and March 2015, SIDG with D1+ lymph node dissection was performed for early gas-
tric cancer through a 2.5-cm transumbilical incision without any additional port. uDelta was performed by the operator alone, without 
any intracorporeal assistance. 
Results: uDelta was performed on 11 patents, and uncut RY was performed on 5-patients without open or multiport conversion. R0 
resection was performed in all cases. No significant differences were observed in mean age and body mass index between patients who 
underwent uDelta or RY. Mean operation times were 214.5±36.2 minutes for uDelta and 240.8±65.9 minutes for RY, which was 
not significantly different. Reconstruction time for uDelta was shorter than that for RY, with marginal statistical significance (26.1±8.3 
minutes vs. 38.0±9.1 minutes, P=0.05). There were no intraoperative transfusions, 30-day mortality, or anastomosis-related com-
plications in either group. Average length of hospital stay was 8.2±1.9 days in the uDelta group and 7.2±0.8 days in the RY group 
(P=0.320). 
Conclusions: After carefully considering indications, uDelta can be a feasible and can be a reproducible reconstruction method after 
SIDG in early gastric cancer. </p>

<p>Key Words: Billroth I; Gastrectomy; Laparoscopy; Roux-en-Y anastomosis; Stomach neoplasm </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Han-Kwang Yang 
Department of Surgery and Cancer Research Institute, Seoul National 
University College of Medicine, 101 Daehak-ro, Jongno-gu, Seoul 110-
744, Korea 
Tel: +82-2-2072-3797, Fax: +82-2-3672-0047 
E-mail: hkyang@snu.ac.kr 
Received April 27, 2015 
Revised May 13, 2015 
Accepted May 15, 2015 </p>

<p>Suh YS, et al. </p>

<p>106 </p>

<p>it is simpler to perform, leads to less anatomical change after anas-</p>

<p>tomosis, allows for more physiological food passage, and confers a </p>

<p>lower incidence of internal hernia or adhesion. Consequently, Bill-</p>

<p>roth I is the most common anastomosis technique used after distal </p>

<p>gastrectomy in Korea and Japan, even among expert groups. </p>

<p>10,11 </p>

<p>To achieve intracorporeal Billroth I anastomosis in laparoscopic </p>

<p>surgery, delta-shaped anastomosis for gastroduodenostomy us-</p>

<p>ing linear staplers was introduced. Since then, this has become the </p>

<p>most popular technique for intracorporeal gastroduodenostomy, </p>

<p>and has shown acceptable postoperative results. 
12,13 However, to </p>

<p>perform this type of anastomosis, advanced laparoscopic coop-</p>

<p>eration between the operator and the assistant is essential. When </p>

<p>performing pure SIDG, such advanced cooperation is nearly im-</p>

<p>possible because of the absence of additional ports, the collision of </p>

<p>instruments, and narrow working space. To date, only two authors </p>

<p>have reported their initial experience with or modification of Bill-</p>

<p>roth I anastomosis after SIDG, and the reproducibility or general-</p>

<p>ization of gastroduodenostomy in pure SIDG has been controver-</p>

<p>sial until recently. 
7,14,15 On the basis of our experience with SIDG, </p>

<p>we introduced unaided delta-shaped anastomosis (uDelta), a novel </p>

<p>technique for gastroduodenostomy, without any additional port or </p>

<p>intracorporeal assistance for pure SIDG, and compared the results </p>

<p>with those of previously reported RY technique. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>1. Patients </p>

<p>We retrospectively reviewed the clinicopathological data of pa-</p>

<p>tients who had been treated with pure SIDG between March 2014 </p>

<p>and March 2015. The indication was cT1N0M0 adenocarcinoma of </p>

<p>the distal one-third of the stomach, in patients without any signifi-</p>

<p>cant systemic morbidity or obesity. Reconstruction was performed </p>

<p>using either uDelta or RY. For tumors located in the distal one-</p>

<p>third stomach, uDelta was the preferred technique. If the tumor lo-</p>

<p>cated above the angle of the stomach or the distal resection margin </p>

<p>of the tumor was too close to the pylorus, RY was considered as an </p>

<p>alternative technique. Morbidity and mortality was evaluated for 30 </p>

<p>days after the operation. Statistical analyses were performed using </p>

<p>the Mann-Whitney U-test and the c 
2 test with <rs id="software-0" type="software">IBM SPSS</rs> Statistics </p>

<p><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 19.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Co.</rs>., Armonk, NY, USA). This study was approved </p>

<p>by the Seoul National University Hospital Institutional Review </p>

<p>Board (IRB No: 1504-063-664). </p>

<p>2. Unaided delta-shaped anastomosis surgical technique </p>

<p>The patient is placed supine, and both legs are spread. Surgeons </p>

<p>are placed between the patient's legs, and a scopist usually stands </p>

<p>at the right side of the patient. A vertical 2.5 cm-long transumbili-</p>

<p>cal incision is made, and a commercially available 4-hole single </p>

<p>port (Glove Port </p>

<p>Ⓡ </p>

<p>; Nelis, Bucheon, Korea) is inserted without any </p>

<p>additional port. Pneumoperitoneum is achieved using 12 mmHg </p>

<p>pressure in the reverse Trendelenburg position. A flexible laparo-</p>

<p>scope (ENDOEYE FLEX HD 10 mm; Olympus Medical Systems, </p>

<p>Tokyo, Japan) is essential because it offers unparalleled viewing </p>

<p>among laparoscopic instruments. The operator uses a 45-cm-long </p>

<p>energy device (HARMONIC scalpel; Ethicon Endo-Surgery Inc., </p>

<p>Cincinnati, OH, USA or THUNDERBEAT; Olympus Medical </p>

<p>Systems). A 43-cm-long straight Clickline Croce-Olmi grasping </p>

<p>forcep (Karl Storz, Tuttlingen, Germany) is the main instrument, </p>

<p>and HiQ LS curved hand instrument (5×350 mm, Olympus Medi-</p>

<p>cal Systems) is used as an alternative. </p>

<p>Using a single incision site without any additional port or as-</p>

<p>sistance, laparoscopic distal gastrectomy with D1+ lymph node </p>

<p>dissection is performed according to the Japanese gastric cancer </p>

<p>treatment guidelines. 
16 For Billroth I anastomosis, after full mo-</p>

<p>bilization around the first part of the duodenum, the duodenum </p>

<p>is rotated 90 degrees and transected with a 60 mm linear stapler </p>

<p>(Endo GIA 
TM purple or tan; Covidien, Mansfield, MA, USA), </p>

<p>which creates a duodenal transection in the ventrodorsal direction </p>

<p>(supplementary video). This duodenal transection was occasion-</p>

<p>ally performed before ligation of the right gastric artery in totally </p>

<p>laparoscopic distal gastrectomy (TLDG). However, in SIDG with </p>

<p>uDelta, we performed duodenal transection after ligation of the </p>

<p>right gastric artery to ensure sufficient mobilization and rotation of </p>

<p>the duodenal first portion without any other assistance. After distal </p>

<p>gastrectomy with lymph node dissection is completed, an en bloc </p>

<p>resected specimen with lymph nodes wrapped in a plastic bag is </p>

<p>harvested through a single umbilical incision site. To perform an </p>

<p>intracorporeal gastroduodenostomy, a small incision is created in </p>

<p>the previous stapled line at the corner of the greater curvature side </p>

<p>of the remnant stomach and the dorsal side of the duodenum in </p>

<p>order to insert a linear stapler. To achieve adequate traction with-</p>

<p>out assistance inside the peritoneal cavity, a traction suture with </p>

<p>a 3/0 monofilament thread is added at the posterior wall of the </p>

<p>small incision hole of the remnant stomach and pulled out through </p>

<p>a single umbilical port (Fig. 1A). After inserting a 45 mm linear </p>

<p>stapler (Endo GIA 
TM purple) into the remnant stomach, an opened </p>

<p>linear stapler with a traction suture at the remnant stomach is easily </p>

<p>Unaided Delta-Shaped Anastomosis </p>

<p>107 </p>

<p>maintained by the operator's right hand, allowing for simultaneous </p>

<p>unaided manipulation of the stapler and remnant stomach. A linear </p>

<p>stapler gently holding the posterior wall of the remnant stomach </p>

<p>is rotated clockwise to the duodenal side, which is then ready for </p>

<p>gastroduodenostomy (Fig. 1B). The other jaw of the stapler is in-</p>

<p>serted at the incision site of the duodenal stump, which is simply </p>

<p>controlled by the operator himself. The posterior wall of the stom-</p>

<p>ach and cranial side of the duodenum are approximated and anas-</p>

<p>tomosed (Fig. 1C). To close the common entry hole, one traction </p>

<p>suture at the lesser curvature side of the common entry hole (which </p>

<p>occasionally can be replaced by a previous traction suture at the </p>

<p>remnant stomach) is simply pulled up with the operator's left hand </p>

<p>inside the abdominal cavity. The newly added suture at the greater </p>

<p>curvature side of the common entry hole is pulled out through the </p>

<p>single port and simultaneously manipulated outside the abdominal </p>

<p>cavity with a linear stapler by the operator's right hand (Fig. 1D). </p>

<p>Under the gentle traction of 2 traction sutures inside and outside the </p>

<p>abdominal cavity, the common entry hole can be closed up with a </p>

<p>single application of a 60 mm linear stapler (Endo GIA 
TM purple) </p>

<p>(Fig. 1E). </p>

<p>3. Uncut Roux-en-Y anastomosis surgical technique </p>

<p>The proximal jejunum, 20 cm below the ligament of Treitz, </p>

<p>is harvested extracorporeally through a single incision site. This </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>D 
E 
F </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Unaided delta-shaped anas-
tomosis. (A) A traction suture with 
3/0 monofilament thread is added at 
the posterior wall of the small inci-
sion hole of the remnant stomach and 
pulled out through a single umbilical 
port. (B) An opened 45-mm linear 
stapler inserted at the remnant stom-
ach is manipulated by the operator 
with one hand. (C) The other jaw of 
the stapler is inserted at the incision 
site of the duodenal stump, which 
is easily controlled by the operator 
alone. (D) After the first stapling of 
the gastroduodenostomy, one traction 
suture at the lesser curvature side of 
the common entry hole is pulled up 
by the operator's left hand. This suture 
can be replaced by the previous suture 
at the posterior wall of the remnant 
stomach. An additional traction su-
ture at the greater curvature side of 
the common entry hole is pulled out 
through the single port and simul-
taneously manipulated outside the 
abdominal cavity with a linear stapler. 
(E) The common entry hole can be 
easily closed with a single application 
of a 60-mm linear stapler under gentle 
traction with 2 traction sutures inside 
and outside the abdominal cavity. (F) 
The unaided delta-shaped gastroduo-
denostomy is completed. </p>

<p>Suh YS, et al. </p>



<p>proximal jejunum is anastomosed side to side with the distal jeju-</p>

<p>num, which is approximately 35 cm distal from the jejunojejunos-</p>

<p>tomy. After anastomosis, the proximal afferent jejunum is stapled at </p>

<p>5 cm distal from the jejunojejunostomy, using a linear stapler with-</p>

<p>out knife (TA 
TM 30 mm stapler, vascular; Covidien). A small hole </p>

<p>is made 5 cm distal from the previous nonknife stapled line, and </p>

<p>the entire jejunum is restored into the peritoneal cavity. Another </p>

<p>small hole is then made at the corner of the greater curvature side </p>

<p>of the remnant stomach, and antiperistaltic gastrojejunostomy is </p>

<p>performed using two 60 mm linear staplers (Endo GIA 
TM purple) in </p>

<p>the same manner as previously reported. 
8 After gastrojejunostomy, </p>

<p>Peterson's space is closed using a barbed suture. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The uDelta procedure was performed in 11 patients, and RY was </p>

<p>performed in 5 patients (Table 1). None of the patients required open </p>

<p>or multiport conversion, and the procedure was completed without </p>

<p>any intraoperative complications or transfusions. R0 resection with a </p>

<p>negative resection margin was achieved in all patients. Based on the </p>

<p>7th AJCC TNM staging system, postoperative pathology revealed </p>

<p>stage I gastric adenocarcinoma in 13 patients, neuroendocrine tumor </p>

<p>without lymph node metastasis in 1 patient, and mixed adenoneuro-</p>

<p>endocrine carcinoma in 2 patients. 
17 There was no significant differ-</p>

<p>ence in age, sex, and body mass index between the uDelta and RY </p>

<p>groups. Fig. 2 shows the number of examined lymph nodes at each </p>

<p>lymph node station after total 16 cases of SIDG with D1+ lymph </p>

<p>node dissection. Fig. 3 shows a series of average operation times for </p>

<p>Table 1. Patient information for single incision distal gastrectomy </p>

<p>Variable 
Unaided delta-shaped anastomosis (n=11) 
Roux-en Y anastomosis (n=5) 
P-value </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
64.9±8.4 
61.0±24.5 
0.510 </p>

<p>Sex (male:female) 
6:5 
4:1 
1.000 </p>

<p>Body mass index (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
23.2±3.0 
24.5±3.5 
0.320 </p>

<p>Combined resection 
0 ( 
1 (cholecystectomy) 
-</p>

<p>Tumor size (cm) 
1.9±0.7 
2.4±0.9 
0.518 </p>

<p>Proximal resection margin (cm) 
4.5±2.1 
3.1±2.4 
0.513 </p>

<p>Distal resection margin (cm) 
3.8±2.2 
6.5±1.0 
0.019 </p>

<p>Differentiation </p>

<p>Moderately differentiated 
4 (36.4) 
2 (40.0) 
0.869 </p>

<p>Poorly differentiated 
3 (27.3) 
1 (20.0) 
-</p>

<p>Poorly cohesive 
3 (27.3) 
2 (40.0) 
-</p>

<p>Other 
1* (9.1) 
0 (0.0) 
-</p>

<p>Lauren </p>

<p>Intestinal 
5 (45.5) 
2 (40.0) 
0.288 </p>

<p>Diffuse 
3 (27.3) 
2 (40.0) 
-</p>

<p>Mixed 
0 (0.0) 
1 (20.0) 
-</p>

<p>Unclassified 
3 
 † (27.3) 
0 (0.0) 
-</p>

<p>T stage </p>

<p>T1 
11 (100.0) 
4 (80.0) 
0.333 </p>

<p>T2 
0 (0.0) 
1 (20.0) 
-</p>

<p>N stage 
-</p>

<p>N0 
10 (90.9) 
5 (100.0) 
1.000 </p>

<p>N1 
1 (9.1) 
0 (0.0) 
-</p>

<p>No. of examined lymph nodes 
42.2±15.5 
37.4±5.8 
0.827 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation, number only, or number (%). *One patient with neuroendocrine tumor. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Each patient with 
neuroendocrine tumor, mixed adenoneuroendocrine carcinoma and no residual tumor after endoscopic biopsy, relatively. </p>

<p>Unaided Delta-Shaped Anastomosis </p>



<p>each SIDG case, along with each patient's body mass index. Table 2 </p>

<p>shows that the operation time for the uDelta procedure was shorter </p>

<p>than that for the RY procedure (214.5±36.2 minutes vs. 240.8±65.9 </p>

<p>minutes), although the difference was not statistically significant </p>

<p>(P=0.661). In addition, reconstruction time for uDelta was signifi-</p>

<p>cantly shorter than that for RY (26.1±8.3 minutes vs. 38.0±9.1 </p>

<p>minutes), and this difference was marginally significant (P=0.05). </p>

<p>Regarding perioperative outcomes in both groups, no mortal-</p>

<p>ity or complications occurred, including leakage, stenosis, ileus, or </p>

<p>bleeding related to the anastomosis. In terms of other morbidity, </p>

<p>one patient had intra-abdominal fluid collection; however, it was </p>

<p>unrelated to anastomosis leakage and was managed by 1 applica-</p>

<p>tion of ultrasonography-guided simple aspiration. The other pa-</p>

<p>tient, who had been discharged at postoperative day 7 without any </p>

<p>complications, was readmitted at postoperative day 11 owing to </p>

<p>an intra-abdominal pseudoaneurysm. That patient recovered after </p>

<p>radiological embolization of the pseudoaneurysm, reoperation to </p>

<p>perform remnant total gastrectomy, and intensive care. No signifi-</p>

<p>cant differences in postoperative recovery, including day of first </p>

<p>flatus and length of stay, were observed between the uDelta and </p>

<p>RY groups. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In order to generalize a new procedure such as SIDG, the </p>

<p>simplicity, safety, and reproducibility of the whole procedure in-</p>

<p>cluding reconstruction should be evaluated and compared with a </p>

<p>conventional one. Therefore, to consider procedure generalization, </p>

<p>gastroduodenostomy or gastrojejunostomy should be evaluated </p>

<p>equivocally, not only after conventional open surgery or TLDG </p>

<p>but also after SIDG. Compared with gastroduodenostomy, gastro-</p>

<p>jejunostomy can be relatively easily performed, and most studies </p>

<p>describing the initial experience with SIDG had used gastojejunos-</p>

<p>tomy. 
8,18,19 A recent retrospective comparative study reported that </p>

<p>SIDG with RY resulted in better short-term outcomes than TLDG </p>

<p>in terms of postoperative pain, estimated blood loss, inflammatory </p>

<p>reaction, and cosmetic results. 
9 However, unlike in open surgery, </p>

<p>gastroduodenostomy was usually considered a more difficult tech-</p>

<p>nique in TLDG because of the limitations of an intracorporeal ap-</p>

<p>proach with a circular stapler as well as the narrow working space </p>

<p>around the duodenal stump. To overcome these limitations, delta-</p>

<p>shaped anastomosis has been successfully introduced for Billroth I </p>

<p>anastomosis after TLDG. 
20 However, delta-shaped anastomosis still </p>

<p>requires advanced cooperation between the operator and assistant </p>

<p>because all manipulations related to the linear stapler and remnant </p>

<p>stomach should be conducted by the assistant. Such an advanced </p>

<p>assistant-dependent procedure cannot be expected for SIDG. In </p>

<p>addition, it would be much more challenging if even one more as-</p>

<p>L N </p>

<p># 1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>The median number of examined </p>

<p>lymph </p>

<p>nodes with 95.0% confidence interval </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>L N </p>

<p># 3 </p>

<p>L N 
# 4 S b 
L N 
# 4 d 
L N </p>

<p># 5 
L N </p>

<p># 6 
L N </p>

<p># 7 
L N 
# 8 a 
L N 
# 1 1 p 
L N 
# 1 2 a 
L N </p>

<p># 9 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Median number of estimated lymph nodes (LNs) at each lymph 
node station after total cases of single-incision distal gastrectomy with 
D1+ lymph node dissection. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Operation time of single-inci-
sion distal gastrectomy. BI indicates 
unaided delta-shaped anastomosis, 
and RY indicates Roux-en-Y anasto-
mosis. </p>

<p>Case number </p>

<p>Operation time 
Body mass index </p>

<p>RY 
1 </p>

<p>35.0 </p>

<p>(kg/m ) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>30.0 </p>

<p>25.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>15.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>(min) </p>

<p>BI 
16 </p>

<p>360 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>240 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>0 
BI 
2 </p>

<p>BI 
3 </p>

<p>RY 
4 </p>

<p>BI 
5 </p>

<p>RY 
6 </p>

<p>RY 
7 </p>

<p>BI 
8 </p>

<p>BI 
9 </p>

<p>RY 
15 </p>

<p>BI 
10 </p>

<p>BI 
11 </p>

<p>BI 
12 </p>

<p>BI 
13 </p>

<p>BI 
14 </p>

<p>Suh YS, et al. </p>



<p>sistance grasper were added through a single port because of the </p>

<p>narrow port space and severe collision among surgical instruments. </p>

<p>This limitation of reconstruction may prohibit the generalization of </p>

<p>SIDG, especially in terms of a reconstruction such as gastroduode-</p>

<p>nostomy. </p>

<p>We introduced the uDelta anastomosis under the direct visuali-</p>

<p>zation of a flexible scope and without any additional port or intra-</p>

<p>corporeal assistance grasper. In short, our novel method is a modi-</p>

<p>fication of the way how delta-shaped anastomosis is performed </p>

<p>which is optimized for SIDG, and the anatomical results after </p>

<p>anastomosis are similar to those following the original delta-shaped </p>

<p>anastomosis procedure. Therefore, postoperative outcomes would </p>

<p>be easily expected based on several previous reports. </p>

<p>13,21 </p>

<p>Our method is characterized by 1) appropriate 'aiding' stitches </p>

<p>as assistance through the single port, and 2) simultaneous manipu-</p>

<p>lation of the linear stapler and those stitches. In single-port surgery, </p>

<p>intracorporeal suturing and knot-tying is usually considered a more </p>

<p>complicated technique than in converntional laparoscopic surgery. </p>

<p>However, our technique requires only simple suturing at appropri-</p>

<p>ate points without intracorporeal tying. Here, the simultaneous </p>

<p>manipulation of the linear stapler using aiding stitches substitute </p>

<p>the role of advanced assistance in TLDG. Finally, the operator can </p>

<p>control the whole anastomosis procedure himself without further </p>

<p>collision among instruments or obstacles to the laparoscopic view. </p>

<p>This 'unaided procedure' leads to a simple and easily reproducible </p>

<p>technique. In addition, this procedure can be effectively applied to </p>

<p>multiport TLDG, especially when advanced assistance is not avail-</p>

<p>able. Whether the surgical team is expert or not, the application of </p>

<p>our procedure to SIDG as well as TLDG can be expected to result </p>

<p>in consistent anastomosis outcomes as well as a more standardized </p>

<p>laparoscopic procedure. </p>

<p>In our early experience, one patient was readmitted to the </p>

<p>hospital because of splenic artery pseudoaneurysm and required </p>

<p>reoperation with intensive care. This type of unique complication </p>

<p>might result from thermal damage by an ultrasonic energy device, </p>

<p>and was previously reported at the same vessel (splenic artery) in </p>

<p>a large-scale study of laparoscopic distal gastrectomy with lymph </p>

<p>node dissection. 
22 In particular, the use of an energy-based device </p>

<p>should be considered much more cautiously in SIDG because no </p>

<p>effective assistance is available to avoid possible thermal injury to </p>

<p>adjacent tissues, including major vessels. According to Japanese </p>

<p>treatment guidelines for performing distal gastrectomy, dissection </p>

<p>Table 2. Perioperative outcome after single incision distal gastrectomy </p>

<p>Variable 
Unaided delta-shaped anastomosis (n=11) 
Roux-en Y anastomosis (n=5) 
P-value </p>

<p>Operation time (min) 
214.5±36.2 
240.8±65.9 
0.661 </p>

<p>Reconstruction time (min) 
26.1±8.3 
38.0±9.1 
0.05 </p>

<p>Intraoperative transfusion (pint) 
0 
0 
-</p>

<p>Open or multiport conversion 
0 
0 
-</p>

<p>Mortality 
0 
0 
-</p>

<p>Morbidity </p>

<p>Related to anastomosis </p>

<p>Leakage/fistula 
0 
0 
-</p>

<p>Luminal stenosis/delayed gastric emptying 
0 
0 
-</p>

<p>Ilus 
0 
0 
-</p>

<p>Intraluminal bleeding 
0 
0 
-</p>

<p>Other morbidity </p>

<p>Wound 
0 
1 
-</p>

<p>Peripheral phlebitis 
2 
0 
-</p>

<p>Intraabdominal fluid collection 
2* 
0 
-</p>

<p>Intraabdominal bleeding 
1 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0 
-</p>

<p>First flatus (postoperative days) 
4.5±0.8 
5.0±1.7 
0.827 </p>

<p>Length of stay (postoperative days) 
8.2±1.9 
7.2±0.8 
0.320 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation or number only . *One patient was managed by simple observation, and the other patient by 
ultrasonography-guided percutaneous aspiration (single aspiration). </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Pseudoaneurysmal bleeding at splenic artery. </p>

<p>Unaided Delta-Shaped Anastomosis </p>



<p>around the splenic artery is not mandatory. 
16 Therefore, if we paid </p>

<p>strict attention to such guidelines, serious complications related to </p>

<p>pseudoaneurysm around the splenic artery could be prevented. </p>

<p>This study has several limitations. First, it was retrospective and </p>

<p>examined only a small number of cases. However, we believe that </p>

<p>our study has introduced a new alternative and comparable recon-</p>

<p>struction method for SIDG, and that it represents an important step </p>

<p>toward experience with SIDG. Second, SIDG may have limited </p>

<p>utility for obese patients because it is more difficult to create a good </p>

<p>surgical field in these patients. Third, because no assistance is avail-</p>

<p>able during the operation, SIDG may have serious disadvantages </p>

<p>when unexpected intraoperative complications, such as a major </p>

<p>vessel injury, occur. Therefore, SIDG should be performed only by </p>

<p>an experienced laparoscopic surgeon, and larger-scale studies are </p>

<p>necessary to validate the clinical implications and safety of SIDG. </p>

<p>We introduced a novel anastomosis technique, uDelta, for </p>

<p>gastroduodenostomy after pure SIDG. After carefully consider-</p>

<p>ing indications, uDelta can become a feasible and reproducible </p>

<p>reconstruction option after SIDG for early gastric cancer. It is also </p>

<p>expected to become a useful technique for multiport TLDG with </p>

<p>Billroth I anastomosis. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant (1320270) from the Na-</p>

<p>tional R&amp;D Program for Cancer Control, Ministry of Health &amp; </p>

<p>Welfare, Republic of Korea. </p>



</text></tei>