<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4017532" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Metabonomics and other "omics" fields are essential science in analytical chemistry. Modern analytical instruments 
such as proton nuclear magnetic resonance ( 
1 H NMR) can be provided the great quantity of analytical information. In 
order to assign unknown samples, chemometrics methods recognition build classification model based on experimental 
data. Firstly some current strategies for regarding disease diagnosis are exhibited in metabonomics studies. Some 
disease such as crohn's disease can be difficult to diagnosis since its signs and symptoms may be similar to other 
medical problems or often mimic other symptoms. Applications of NMR and supervised pattern recognition in the field 
of metabonomics are also reviewed in recent years. The aim of present study was to review the assessment of 
1 HNMR to 
investigate a metabolic profile of crohn's disease. </p>

<p>1 A revolution has created in the practice of </p>

<p>biological research in the last decade (1). These 
changes can develop of techniques that are 
valuable to profile levels of molecular 
organization at body. 'Omics' informally refers 
to this wide coverage of techniques that can 
perform metabolic profiling studies such as 
metabonomics or metabolomics (2, 3). In this 
viewpoint, there is a particular emphasis on how 
the levels of metabolites change in response to </p>

<p>Received: 11 July 2013 Accepted: 5 September 2013 
Reprint or Correspondence: Hamid Asadzadeh Aghdaie MD. 
Basic and Molecular Epidemiology of Gastroenterology 
Disorder Research Center, Shahid Beheshti University of 
Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran 
E-mail: hamid.asadzadeh@gmail.com </p>

<p>pathophysiological stimuli or genetic modification 
in living systems because of many molecules with 
small molecular weight involved in metabolism 
(4). Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis are the 
two main types of chronic inflammatory bowel 
disease. Crohn's disease is called regional enteritis 
that affects the gastrointestinal tract. The disorder 
usually affects the colon and rectum, however, 
may influence in each area of the mouth to the 
anus. In some cases the correct diagnosis of 
crohn's disease may be difficult because this 
disease often imitates other symptoms. To make 
correct diagnosis in many areas, metabonomics 
field is to achieve improvements in understanding 
of metabolic processes that occur while a person is </p>

<p>REVIEW ARTICLE </p>

<p>S20 Metabonomics exposes metabolic biomarkers of Crohn's disease by 1HNMR </p>

<p>Gastroenterol Hepatol Bed Bench 2013;6(Suppl.1):S19-S22 </p>

<p>suffering from a disease (5). There are several 
available methods for metabolite profiling. One of 
them is proton nuclear magnetic resonance ( 
1 H-</p>

<p>NMR) that has been utilized as an analytical tool 
in studies of metabolism for many years (6-8). 
NMR spectroscopy technique is non-selective in 
the analytical studied and obtained vital 
information in a short time. Also it is non-
destructive and highly reproducible with minimal 
sample preparation. 
Statistical modeling in metabolic profiling has goals; 
one of them is to visualize the overall similarities 
and differences between samples and variables. The 
main focus in this review is to provide general 
knowledge of data preprocessing in </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HNMR 
approach and the use of chemometrics techniques. 
For reach to this purpose, we have focused on 
studies on crohn's disease using a metabonomics. </p>

<p>Sample and data preprocessing </p>

<p>To convert the NMR data into a form that can be 
useable in statistical procedures firstly the FIDs -
already have been fourier transformed to the 
frequency domain-manually phased and baseline-
corrected applying <rs type="software">XWINNMR</rs> or other 
software(1). Then the NMR data are usually 
transformed into a matrix in which a sample and a 
metabolic signal pertain to a row and a column, 
respectively. The spectral intensity at a particular 
chemical shift corresponds to the estimated level of 
a particular metabolite. The Carr-Pucell-
Meiboom-Gill (CPMG) spin-echo pulse sequence, 
π/2-t D -π-t D , was used for serum samples (9). CPMG 
experiment can enhances visualization of the low 
molecular weight metabolites and to suppress the 
broad signal from the protein (9). Spectral regions 
within the range of 0.2 to 10 ppm were used after 
deleting the region containing residual water and 
urea signals (4.5 to 6.0 ppm) (10). Biological fluids 
such as serum, plasma and urine have been used for 
studies of crohn's disease. Serum and plasma are 
the most common fluids in metabonomics surveys. 
These samples are also relatively easy to obtain. </p>

<p>The human metabolome database (HMDB) is a 
freely available electronic database containing 
detailed information about metabolites found in the 
body. Urine is one of the simplest fluids physical 
that frequently used as a bio-fluid for human and 
animal metabolic studies. Schicho and co-authors 
performed quantitative metabolomic profiling of 
serum, plasma and urine by </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HNMR spectroscopy 
on patients with inflammatory bowel disease 
(crohn's disease and active ulcerative colitis) (11). 
In other survey, Stephens et al. highlighted the 
potential for metabolomics to distinguish 
inflammatory bowel disease from the healthy state 
in urine sample (12). They build a metabolic profile 
applying NMR spectroscopy to distinguish patients 
with inflammatory bowel disease from healthy 
individuals (12). Fathi and colleagues reveal new 
differentiating metabolites for crohn's disease by 
examining on serum of Iranian samples (13). 
Murdoch and colleagues correlated the progress of 
inflammatory bowel disease with specific changes 
in a mouse urinary metabolic fingerprint applying 
metabolomics (14). Marchesi and colleagues 
displayed the first classification of fecal extracts 
acquired from patients with ulcerative colitis and 
crohn's disease using a metabonomics technique. 
This approach combines multivariate pattern 
recognition analysis and high resolution </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HNMR 
spectroscopy (15). </p>

<p>Scaling in metabonomics </p>

<p>In some researches, for each samples 4,4-dimethyl-
4-silapentane-1-sulfonic acid (DSS) was added as 
internal reference substance (δ=0 ppm). Also peak 
of the lactate methyl doublet (δ=1.33 ppm) or other 
metabolites are referenced within <rs type="software">XWINNMR</rs> for 
spectra (16). Scaling is a column-each spectral 
intensity across all samples-operation that 
including mean center, auto scaling, pareto scaling 
etc. Mean centering includes subtracting the 
column mean from each value in the column and 
given a mean of zero. Second scaling is auto 
scaling also called unit or unit variance scaling; in </p>

<p>Fathi F. et al S21 </p>

<p>which each value in the column is divided by the 
standard deviation of the column (17). Pareto 
scaling is other forms of scaling that is very similar 
to auto scaling. Here, each variable is divided by 
the square root of the standard deviation of the 
column (18). 
Rezaei-Tavirani et al. stated that preprocessing the 
spectroscopic data is essential (19). They showed 
scaling effects in metabonomics investigation of 
patients diagnosed with crohn's disease by applying 
two techniques of scaling including: mean 
centering and auto scaling (19). Results of recent 
study reveal that the mean centering is more useful 
to segregate patients from healthy subjects in the 
data set of crohn's disease. They showed that the 
mean centering option is more effective at 
eliminating correlation from the principal 
component analysis (PCA) residuals than the auto 
scaling in this situation. In survey of Fathi et al. the 
data were scaled to pareto scaling preceding 
multivariate analysis (13). 
Regarding the published studies in this field, it can 
be suggested that the goal of scaling is to regulate 
for the distinctions in fold differences between the 
different metabolites and improving their biological 
interpretability. </p>

<p>Classification methods </p>

<p>Classification methods are widely used in order to 
diagnosis crohn's disease from healthy subjects and 
to seek the metabolic biomarkers causes of crohn's 
disease compare to control group. Methods applied 
in crohn's literatures include the following: 
classification and regression tree (CART) and 
orthogonal projections to latent structures 
discriminated analysis (OPLS-DA). 
Breiman et al. in 1984 develop CART as non-
parametric statistical technique (20). This method is 
able both classification and regression. A decision 
tree is built in both cases and describes a response Y 
by selecting some independent variables X from a 
larger set of X values. Fathi and colleagues utilized 
CART in order to classification of crohn's disease </p>

<p>and healthy subjects (13). They obtained 
classification model showed 89% correct 
classification of crohn's disease and healthy subject 
for the external test set. According to CART 
diagram, they concluded that just using one 
descriptor (lipid) crohn's disease and control group 
could be classified separately. Based on CART 
diagram, lipid level reduces in blood serum of 
patients compared to healthy individuals. The 
parameters of classification in last research showed 
that CART classification model has great chance in 
diagnosis of crohn's disease. 
OPLS-DA as regression technique is frequently 
used for classification method (11). Using this 
method, those metabolites which show a 
discrepancy between diagnostic groups can be 
identified. In order to divide the systematic 
variation into two model parts in the metabolite 
levels, OPLS-DA is used (21). These two parts are 
including co-variation between metabolite levels 
and the class of each sample and captures 
systematic variation in metabolite levels orthogonal 
to the class of each sample (11). 
Schicho et al. used hierarchical OPLS-DA for 
comparing several blocks derived from the same 
subject to examine differences in metabolites. 
Based on recent research, methanol, mannose, 
formate, 3-methyl-2-oxovalerate, and amino acids 
increased in serum and plasma and mannitol, 
allantoin, xylose, and carnitine increase in urine of 
IBD patients (11). Quantitative metabolomic 
profiling of serum, plasma and urine discriminated 
healthy subjects and IBD patients. However, they 
showed that the metabolic differences between the 
ulcerative colitis and crohn's disease cohorts are 
less pronounced (11). Stephens et al. performed 
OPLS-DA in order to examine which metabolites 
were contributing to the separation crohn's disease 
and healthy cohorts (12). In this study IBD patients 
could be differentiated from healthy according to 
urinary metabolomics. TCA cycle intermediates, 
amino acids and gut microflora metabolites have </p>

<p>S22 Metabonomics exposes metabolic biomarkers of Crohn's disease by 1HNMR </p>

<p>Gastroenterol Hepatol Bed Bench 2013;6(Suppl.1):S19-S22 </p>

<p>main differences between inflammatory bowel 
disease patients and healthy cohorts. (12). </p>

<p>Conclusions and future prospects </p>

<p>In this review, we evaluated the use of classification 
method to build an easily interpretable predictive 
model to distinguish between crohn's disease and 
healthy controls. It is clear that statistical model and 
bioinformatics 
methods 
are 
valuable 
in 
metabonomics investigation. The aim of these 
"omics" science is to enable the maximum useful 
information to be gleaned from this rich and 
complex data. We suggest using metabonomics to 
identify other patients in the future. </p>



</text></tei>