<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4495456" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Systemic Arterial Hypertension (SAH) is one of the main risk factors for Coronary Artery Disease (CAD), in 
addition to male gender. Differences in coronary artery lesions between hypertensive and normotensive individuals of 
both genders at the Coronary Computed Tomography Angiography (CCTA) have not been clearly determined. </p>

<p>Objective: To Investigate the calcium score (CS), CAD extent and characteristics of coronary plaques at CCTA in men 
and women with and without SAH. </p>

<p>Methods: Prospective cross-sectional study of 509 patients undergoing CCTA for CAD diagnosis and risk stratification, 
from November 2011 to December 2012, at Instituto de Cardiologia Dante Pazzanese. Individuals were stratified 
according to gender and subdivided according to the presence (HT +) or absence (HT-) of SAH. </p>

<p>Results: HT+ women were older (62.3 ± 10.2 vs 57.8 ± 12.8, p = 0.01). As for the assessment of CAD extent, 
the HT+ individuals of both genders had significant CAD, although multivessel disease is more frequent in HT + 
men. The regression analysis for significant CAD showed that age and male gender were the determinant factors of 
multivessel disease and CS ≥ 100. Plaque type analysis showed that SAH was a predictive risk factor for partially 
calcified plaques (OR = 3.9). </p>

<p>Conclusion: Hypertensive men had multivessel disease more often than women. Male gender was a determinant 
factor of significant CAD, multivessel disease, CS ≥ 100 and calcified and partially calcified plaques, whereas SAH was 
predictive of partially calcified plaques. (Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(5):409-416) </p>

<p>Keywords: Coronary Artery Disease; Hypertension; Plaque, Atherosclerotic; Mens. </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Cardiovascular disease (CVD) has been considered a 
major risk to global health and, therefore it requires many 
economic and technological investments from governments 
around the world. The combined efforts of different 
countries aim to reduce 25% of the world CVD mortality by 
2025. In most current programs, special attention is given to 
patients with risk factors for coronary artery disease (CAD), 
particularly those with diabetes mellitus (DM) dyslipidemia 
and systemic arterial hypertension (SAH) 
1,2 . </p>

<p>SAH is an important risk factor for the onset of Major 
Cardiac Events (MACE), and its control is indicated in 
an attempt to improve prognosis in the middle and long </p>

<p>term 
3 . Regarding gender, the prevalence of SAH between 
men and women is similar; however, a higher rate is 
observed in men up to 50 years, which reverses after the 
fifth decade of life 
4 . </p>

<p>The Coronary Computed Tomography Angiography 
(CCTA) is a noninvasive technique that allows the 
identification of CAD and of subclinical lesions in the 
coronary arteries, thus improving the diagnosis and risk 
stratification of patients with suspected CAD or established 
disease 
5-7 , with or without SAH. The differences in 
coronary artery lesions between hypertensive and 
normotensive individuals of both genders at the CCTA 
have not yet been clearly determined. The study aims to 
investigate Calcium Score (CS), coronary artery disease 
extent and the characteristics of coronary plaques at the 
CCTA in male and female patients, with and without 
arterial hypertension. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>This is an observational, analytical, prospective study 
with 509 patients undergoing CCTA for CAD diagnosis and 
risk stratification. </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira et al. 
Plaque Predictors at Coronary CT Angiography </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(5):409-416 </p>

<p>Patients aged &lt; 30 years were excluded, as well as 
those with malignant arrhythmias, pregnancy, renal failure, 
contraindication to beta-blocker or iodinated contrast 
use, cancer, decompensated heart failure, resistant SAH, 
cardiomyopathy and severe valvular heart diseases. The ethical 
principles governing human experimentation were followed, 
and all patients signed the free and informed consent form. 
The study was approved by the Ethics and Research Committee 
of Instituto de Cardiologia Dante Pazzanese. </p>

<p>The CS and the CCTA were performed. Lesion size and 
characterization of atherosclerotic plaques were analyzed. 
The 17 arterial segment model described in the American 
Heart Association classification was used to analyze lesion 
size and a reduced 12-segment segmentation was used to 
characterize plaques </p>

<p>8   . </p>

<p>Clinical, sociodemographic and anthropometric 
characteristics, habits/addictions, comorbidities, presence 
of symptoms such as typical and atypical angina, risk factors 
for CAD, medication use and laboratory data were analyzed. </p>

<p>Hypercholesterolemia was defined as total serum cholesterol 
&gt; 200 mg/dL (after a 12-hour fasting) and hypertriglyceridemia 
as serum triglycerides &gt; 150 mg/dL (after a 12-hour fasting) 
or by the use of lipid-lowering agents (statins and/or fibrates). 
SAH was defined when the measurement of blood pressure 
at rest, in the sitting position, was ≥ 140 x 90 mmHg or by 
the use of antihypertensive drugs. Diabetes mellitus (DM) was 
defined as fasting glucose levels &gt; 126 mg/dL or use of insulin 
or oral hypoglycemic agents. Laboratory tests were performed 
at the Laboratory of Instituto de Cardiologia Dante Pazzanese. </p>

<p>The heart rate of all patients was measured one 
hour before the test. If it was &gt; 65 beats/min, patients 
received 50-100 mg oral atenolol (atenolol 50 mg/tablet), 
or intravenous administration of metoprolol. In case of 
contraindications to the use of beta blockers, diltiazem was 
used, at a loading dose of 0.25 mg/kg and after 15 minutes, 
a maintenance dose of 0.35 mg/kg. </p>

<p>Coronary computed tomography angiography (CCTA). 
The CS protocol was performed through CCTA using 
a 64-channel multidetector tomograph manufactured 
by Toshiba Medical Systems, Otawara, Japan MDCT 
(Aquilion 64) using a 64_0.5 mm collimator; 9.8 to 11.2 
detector; 0.39_0.39 mm pixel; rotation time of 350, 375 
or 400 ms; 400 or 450 mA current and voltage of 100 or 
120 kV (depending on the patient's body mass index). 
For plaque detection, the images were reformatted with 
multiplanar and cross-sectional curves. The protocol 
included 03-mm thick sec tions to a ssess the CS. 
Then, 0.5 mm sections were obtained to allow coronary 
assessment. Electrocardiogram modulation (60%-80% of 
the cardiac cycle) was used to minimize radiation exposure 
and voltage of 100 or 120 kV according to the patient's 
BMI. After the acquisition, the images were transferred to 
a station for CS and coronary analysis. </p>

<p>The analysis started with the CS calculation according 
to the method described by Agatston et al 
9 . At each 
03 mm of thickness, the operator searched for areas 
with attenuation factor ≥ 130 HU (Hounsfield units), </p>

<p>considering the lesions to be calcified if they had an 
area of at least 1 mm 
2 . The total score was calculated by 
adding the lesions. The result was adjusted for gender, 
ethnicity and age of the patient for classification in risk 
percentiles 
10 . The CS was stratified into four groups: score 
zero (none), score 1-99 (light), score 100-399 (moderate), 
score ≥ 400 (severe). CS was not performed in patients 
submitted to coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG) and 
percutaneous angioplasty. </p>

<p>Using a multiplanar curve format, the operator assessed 
the coronary tree based on a computerized semi-objective 
analysis and described the presence or absence of lesions 
in each of the 17 arterial segments described in the 
American Heart Association classification 
8 . Plaques were 
considered hemodynamically significant if they resulted 
in a reduction ≥ 50% of the sectional area of the vessel 
lumen or if they were highly calcified and did not allow 
adequate lumen visualization. </p>

<p>The plaques were divided according to their composition: 
noncalcified, if they were homogeneous and had an 
attenuation coefficient &lt; 70UH; partially calcified, if the 
attenuation coefficient ranged from 71 to 200 UH; and 
calcified, if the attenuation coefficient was &gt; 200 UH 
11 . 
When it was impossible to reduce the fluorescent artifact for 
a calcified plaque, it was interpreted as being a significant 
stenotic lesion. In case of multiple lesions, the segment 
analyzed was the one with the worst luminal narrowing. </p>

<p>Imaging Analysis </p>

<p>The CS of the coronary arteries was measured for each 
calcified plaque using a software program (<rs id="software-0" type="software">Vitrea</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">2</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Vital Images</rs>, Minneapolis, MN, USA). Image processing, including 
vessel segmentation, was performed to create multiplanar 
images and to visualize the entire vessel segment with the 
narrowed lumen. The cross-sectional images of the vessels 
could be obtained from any point throughout its length by 
moving the mouse cursor. The quantitative evaluation of 
stenosis was based on the ratio between the lumen with 
minimum contrast and the unaffected proximal and distal 
lumens with the normal reference. </p>

<p>Coronary stenosis was classified as follows: minimum 
stenosis: luminal diameter reduced by less than 25%; mild 
stenosis: luminal diameter reduced by less than 50%; 
moderate stenosis: luminal diameter reduced by ≥ 50% and 
&lt; 70%; severe stenosis: luminal diameter reduced by ≥ 70%. 
A significant reduction of the arterial lumen was considered 
moderate or severe. For the analysis of the 17 arterial segments, 
atherosclerotic coronary lesions were further classified into two 
groups: significant stenosis (&gt; 50% diameter reduction) and 
non-significant stenosis (&lt; 50% diameter reduction). </p>

<p>The analysis of plaque configuration was performed 
primarily at the cross-sectional view, classifying them 
according to the composition: noncalcified plaques 
(plaques with low attenuation on CT compared with the 
contrasted lumen with no calcification); partially calcified 
(calcified and noncalcified elements in the same plate); 
and calcified plaques (plates with high attenuation on CT 
compared with the contrasted lumen). </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira et al. 
Plaque Predictors at Coronary CT Angiography </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(5):409-416 </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was carried out using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">17.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS</rs>, 
Chicago, IL, USA). Results were expressed as mean and 
standard deviation. Differences in continuous variables 
between groups were compared using the unpaired t-test 
when the variable had a normal distribution and the 
Mann-Whitney test when distribution was not normal. 
Categorical variables were summarized as percentages and 
comparisons between groups were carried out using the 
chi-square test. Statistical significance was set at p &lt; 0.05. 
The logistic regression models were used to study the 
association between significant coronary lesions, multivessel 
involvement, CS ≥ 100, plaque types and risk factors for 
CAD. The analysis was adjusted for age, gender, DM, SAH, 
dyslipidemia, sedentary lifestyle, obesity, smoking and 
family history of CAD. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Of the 509 patients, 369 (72.5%) were hypertensive 
(HT +), of which 41.7% were males. Among the normotensive 
patients (HT-) (27.5%), 15.5% were males. The mean age in 
the HT + group was 61.2 ± 10 years, while in the HT-was 
58.9 ± 12 years (p = 0.051) (Table 1). </p>

<p>After the classification by gender, which showed that 
291 patients of 509 (57.2%) were males, new subgroups 
with and without SAH were defined. The mean age was </p>

<p>higher among hypertensive women. As for anthropometric 
measurements, hypertensive individuals had higher body 
mass index and waist circumference in both genders. 
Dyslipidemia was more frequent in hypertensive individuals 
of both genders, while triglycerides were higher in 
hypertensive men and HDL was higher in normotensive 
ones. The presence of DM in the sample was 24.5%, being 
more frequent in male hypertensive patients, as well as 
family history of CAD. </p>

<p>Hypertensive men are more sedentary, while athletes of 
both sexes are more normotensive. The women smokers are 
more hypertensive. </p>

<p>As for symptoms, there was no difference between typical 
and atypical chest pain, and dyspnea between groups. 
However, asymptomatic individuals were more frequently 
observed in the group of normotensive patients of both genders. 
Acute Myocardial Infarction (AMI) was more frequent among 
hypertensive patients of both genders, as well as medication 
use. However, there was no difference between the groups 
regarding prior percutaneous angioplasty, but CABG was more 
frequent in hypertensive men (Tables 1 and 2). </p>

<p>The CS was studied in 386 patients without previous 
CAD. Moderate (≥ 100 and ≤ 399) and severe CS (≥ 400) 
showed no differences between the HT+ and HT-, even 
when stratified by gender. The frequency of mild CS (≥ 1 </p>

<p>Table 1 -Comparison of clinical and biochemical characteristics according to SAH </p>

<p>Characteristics </p>

<p>HT+ Group 
HT-Group </p>

<p>n = 369 (72.5%) 
n = 140 (27.5%) </p>

<p>Male gender 
212 (41.7%) 
79 (15.5%) </p>

<p>Age 
61.2 ± 10.3 
58.9 ± 12.6 </p>

<p>Body mass index (kg/m 
2 ) 
28.3 ± 4.7 
26.0 ± 3.7 </p>

<p>Abdominal circumference (cm) 
97.6 ± 10.7 
90.6 ± 11.4 </p>

<p>Glycemia (mg/dL) 
112.1 ± 64.1 
94.8 ± 19.9 </p>

<p>Total cholesterol (mg/dL) 
175.4 ± 48.3 
181.4 ± 51.8 </p>

<p>HDLc (mg/dL) 
48.3 ± 13.2 
55.8 ± 24.9 </p>

<p>LDLc (mg/dL) 
100.8 ± 35.6 
107.2 ± 43.6 </p>

<p>Triglycerides (mg/dL) 
154.7 ± 168.2 
111.5 ± 63.9 </p>

<p>Serum creatinine (mg/dL) 
1.30 ± 6.2 
1.0 ± 0.70 </p>

<p>DM 
105 (21.3%) 
16 (3.2%) </p>

<p>Dyslipidemia 
255 (51.8%) 
60 (1.2%) </p>

<p>Family history of CAD 
200 (42.6%) 
64 (13.6%) </p>

<p>Sedentary life style 
256 (55.5%) 
86 (18.7%) </p>

<p>Previous AMI 
68 (14.3%) 
11 (2.4%) </p>

<p>Angioplasty and stent 
28 (5.5%) 
6 (1.2%) </p>

<p>CABG 
60 (11.8%) 
12 (2.4%) </p>

<p>HDL-C: high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDLc: low density lipoprotein cholesterol; DM: diabetes mellitus; CAD: coronary artery disease; AMI: acute myocardial 
infarction; CABG: coronary artery bypass grafting. </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira et al. 
Plaque Predictors at Coronary CT Angiography </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(5):409-416 </p>

<p>and ≤ 99) was higher in the HT + group in both genders, 
but without statistical significance. However, it was observed 
that the male normotensive individuals more frequently had 
a CS = 0 (Table 3). </p>

<p>CCTA results were normal in 26% of hypertensive patients 
versus 45% of normotensive individuals. The calculated CS 
percentages were higher and the presence of significant 
lesions was more frequent in hypertensive patients, of both 
genders. The presence of triple-vessel disease and the number 
of segments with atherosclerotic plaques showed higher 
frequency in hypertensive men (Table 4). </p>

<p>As for the multivariate logistic regression, the factors 
associated with significant lesions were dyslipidemia, male 
gender and age. Regarding disease involvement in two 
vessels, the factors were dyslipidemia, male gender and age. 
On the other hand, multivessel involvement (three vessels) 
was associated with dyslipidemia, male gender and age. 
Hypertensive men had a higher probability (OR = 2.3) for 
lesions in three vessels, but without statistical significance. 
CAD extent was independently associated with dyslipidemia 
(OR = 6.01), male gender (OR = 2.73) and age (OR = 1.03). 
High CS was associated with male gender and age (Table 5). </p>

<p>The presence of calcified plaque was independently 
associated with DM (OR = 2.33), dyslipidemia (OR = 2.05), 
male gender (OR = 2.01) and age (OR = 1.08). For non-calcified 
plaque, age was the only associated factor (OR = 1.05). Male 
gender and dyslipidemia had a higher probability, but without </p>

<p>statistical significance. SAH was a predictive risk factor for the 
presence of partially calcified plaques (OR = 3.9), as well as 
male gender (OR = 1.72) and age (OR = 1.08) (Table 6). 
Figure 1 shows plaque composition at the CCTA. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, the extent of CAD was assessed by 
high CS, presence of significant lesion and multivessel 
involvement. The main risk factors predictors of CAD 
were dyslipidemia and male gender. However, SAH 
was associated with the presence of partially calcified 
plaque (OR = 3.9). We emphasize the lack of difference 
between the groups with all levels of the CS, except for 
the important contribution of zero CS, more frequent in 
normotensive men. </p>

<p>An association was observed between partially calcified 
plaque and SAH, male gender and age; moreover, the calcified 
plaque was associated with DM, dyslipidemia, male gender 
and age. Rivera et al. </p>

<p>12   , in a multivariate analysis, showed that 
SAH was predictive of any type of plaque in asymptomatic 
individuals, and as for the partially calcified plaque, they 
obtained similar results to those found in the present study, 
in which SAH (OR = 2.33; 95% CI = 1.10 to 4.95) and male 
gender (OR = 5.54; 95% CI = 1.84 to 16.68) were predictors 
of this type of plaque. However, the study population was 
different from the sample by excluding previous DAC. </p>

<p>Table 2 -Comparison of clinical and biochemical characteristics according to SAH and gender </p>

<p>Characteristics </p>

<p>Men 
n = 291 (57.2%) 
HT-
n = 61 (12%) </p>

<p>HT+ 
n = 157 (30.8%) 
HT-
n = 79 (15.5%) </p>

<p>HT+ 
n = 212 (41.7%) 
p </p>

<p>Age 
59.7 ± 12.5 
60.4 ± 10.4 
0.64 
57.8 ± 12.8 
62.3 ± 10.2 </p>

<p>Body mass index (Kg/m²) 
26.3 ± 3.8 
27.8 ± 4.1 
0.01 
25.7 ± 3.78 
29.1 ± 5.41 </p>

<p>Abdominal circumference (cm) 
94.6 ± 10.9 
98.9 ± 10.2 
0.05 
85.04 ± 9.18 
96 ± 11.4 </p>

<p>Glycemia (mg/dL) 
98.6 ± 22.4 
114.8 ± 77 
0.17 
89.0 ± 10.89 
108.2 ± 38.54 </p>

<p>Cholesterol total (mg/dL) 
172.1 ± 43 
170.5 ± 51.1 
0.85 
196.2 ± 61.2 
182.5 ± 43.2 </p>

<p>HDLc (mg/dL) 
54.4 ± 29.8 
44.2 ± 10.4 
0.01 
58.1 ± 14.5 
54.2 ± 14.5 </p>

<p>LDLc (mg/dL) 
102.4 ± 34 
99.5 ± 37 
0.65 
114.7 ± 55.5 
102.6 ± 33.7 </p>

<p>Triglycerides (mg/dL) 
110.9 ± 62.9 
15.5 ± 115.3 
&lt; 0.01 
112.6 ± 66.9 
125.7 ± 56.9 </p>

<p>Serum creatinine (mg/dL) 
1.0 ± 0.2 
1.7 ± 8.3 
0.56 
0.98 ± 1.1 
0.81 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>DM 
7 (9%) 
65 (31.0%) 
&lt; 0.01 
9 (15%) 
40 (26.3%) </p>

<p>Dyslipidemia 
32 (41%) 
151 (75. 5%) 
&lt; 0.01 
28 (46.7%) 
104 (67.5%) </p>

<p>Family history of CAD 
35 (45.5%) 
144 (62. 6%) 
0.01 
29 (49.2%) 
86 (57%) </p>

<p>Sedentary life style 
41 (53.9%) 
138 (75%) 
&lt; 0.01 
45 (78.9%) 
118 (81.9%) </p>

<p>Previous AMI 
8 (11%) 
47 (25. 4%) 
0.01 
3 (5.2%) 
21 (15%) </p>

<p>Angioplasty and stent 
3 (3.8%) 
19 (9%) 
0.14 
3 (4.9%) 
9 (5.7%) </p>

<p>CABG 
8 (10.1%) 
41 (19.3%) 
0.06 
4 (6.6%) 
19 (12.1%) </p>

<p>HDL-C: high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDLc: low density lipoprotein cholesterol; DM: diabetes mellitus; CAD: coronary artery disease; AMI: acute myocardial 
infarction; CABG: coronary artery bypass grafting. </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira et al. 
Plaque Predictors at Coronary CT Angiography </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(5):409-416 </p>

<p>Table 3 -Comparison of CS according to SAH and gender </p>

<p>CS </p>

<p>Men 
n = 209 (54.15%) 
HT-
n = 54 (13.98%) </p>

<p>HT+ 
n = 123 (31.89%) 
HT-
n = 67 (17.35%) </p>

<p>HT+ 
n = 142 (36.78%) 
p </p>

<p>None 
31 (43.6%) 
43 (30.3%) 
0.02 
32 (59.3%) 
56 (45.5%) </p>

<p>Mild 
17 (25.4%) 
50 (35.2%) 
0.16 
14 (25.9%) 
43 (35%) </p>

<p>Moderate 
9 (13.4%) 
24 (16.9%) 
0.52 
6 (11.1%) 
14 (11.4%) </p>

<p>Severe 
10 (14.9%) 
25 (17.6%) 
0.63 
2 (3.7%) 
10 (8.1%) </p>

<p>CS: calcium score. </p>

<p>Table 4 -Comparison of CCTA findings according to SAH and gender </p>

<p>Findings </p>

<p>Men 
n = 291 (57.2%) 
HT-
n = 61 
(12%) </p>

<p>HT+ 
n = 157 
(30. 8%) 
HT-
n = 79 
(15.5%) </p>

<p>HT+ 
n = 212 
(41.7%) </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>Normal results 
29 (36.7%) 
35 (83.5%) 
&lt; 0.01 
34 (55.7%) 
61 (38.9%) </p>

<p>Percentiles 
33.3 ± 35.8 
47.6 ± 37.6 
0.01 
26.8 ± 37.6 
41.7 ± 40.36 </p>

<p>Significant CAD 
26 (32.9%) 
107 (50.5%) 
0.01 
9 (14.8%) 
45% (28.7%) </p>

<p>Multivessel (3 vessels) 
6 (7.6%) 
46 (21.7%) 
&lt; 0.01 
1 (1.6%) 
11 (7%) </p>

<p>Number of normal 
segments 
13.0 ± 2.0 
11.4 ± 2.9 
&lt; 0.0001 
13.0 ± 1.9 
12.9 ± 2.5 </p>

<p>Number of 
atherosclerotic segments 
2.3 ± 1.7 
3.7 ± 2.7 
&lt; 0.0001 
1.95 ± 1.52 
2.24 ± 1.83 </p>

<p>CAD: coronary artery disease. </p>

<p>Table 5 -*Multivariate logistic regression for variables associated with coronary artery lesions </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Significant stenosis 
Multivessel involvement 
(2 vessels) </p>

<p>Multivessel 
involvement 
(3 vessels) 
p 
Odds Ratio </p>

<p>Odds Ratio 
p 
Odds Ratio 
p 
Odds Ratio </p>

<p>Age 
1.052 
(1.027-1.076) 
&lt; 0.001 
1.039 
(1.012-1.066) 
0.004 
1.048 
(1.014-1.084) 
0.004 
1.087 
(1.56-1.118) </p>

<p>Male gender 
2. 883 
(1.763-4.714) 
&lt; 0.001 
2.732 
(1.583-4.715) 
&lt; 0.001 
4.270 
(2.011-9.069) 
&lt; 0.001 
2.840 
(1.612-5.002) </p>

<p>Dyslipidemia 
2.829 
(1.661-4.816) 
&lt; 0.001 
6.017 
(2.882-12.562) 
&lt; 0.001 
5.822 
(1.994-16.997) 
&lt; 0.001 
1.635 
(0.929-2.878) </p>

<p>Obesity 
1.996 
(1.149-3.468) 
0.014 
-
-
-
-
-</p>

<p>HT+ 
-
-
-
-
2.317 
(0.963-5.577) 
0.061 </p>

<p>(*)Adjusted for age, gender, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, dyslipidemia, obesity, family history of CAD, physical activity and smoking; SAH: systemic arterial 
hypertension; DM: diabetes mellitus; CAD: coronary artery disease. </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira et al. 
Plaque Predictors at Coronary CT Angiography </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(5):409-416 </p>

<p>Figure 1 -Coronary Computed Tomography Angiography. (A) Calcified plaque; (B) Partially calcified plaque. </p>

<p>Table 6 -*Logistic regression for variables associated with the types of plaques </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Calcified Plaque 
Non-Calcified Plaque 
Odds Ratio 
Odds Ratio 
p 
Odds Ratio 
p </p>

<p>Age 
1.091 (1.059-1.125) 
0.001 
1.058 (1.023-1.095) 
0.001 
1.085 (1.047-1.125) </p>

<p>Male gender 
2.015 (1.146-3.544) 
0.015 
1.951 (0.963-3.952) 
0.064 
1.712 (1.03-2.84) </p>

<p>Dyslipidemia 
2.058 (1.159-3.655) 
0.014 
1.881 (0.904-3.914) 
0.091 
-</p>

<p>DM 
2.332 (1.194-4.557) 
0.013 
-
-
-</p>

<p>HT+ 
-
-
-
-
3.979 (1.486-10.654) </p>

<p>(*) Adjusted for age, gender, SAH, DM, dyslipidemia, obesity, family history of CAD, physical activity and smoking; SAH: systemic arterial hypertension; DM: diabetes 
mellitus; CAD: coronary artery disease. </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira et al. 
Plaque Predictors at Coronary CT Angiography </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(5):409-416 </p>

<p>In a study that analyzed the type of plaque at CCTA between 
the group with and without metabolic syndrome (MS) </p>

<p>13   , it was 
observed that among the types of plaque, the highest frequency 
of partially calcified plaque was found in patients with MS. Older 
age and male gender were associated with both the presence of 
calcified and noncalcified plaque. At the adjusted analysis, MS 
was associated with partially calcified plaque, as well as male 
gender and age, data consistent with our results. </p>

<p>In a study carried out in 2008 with a population with no 
prior CAD at CCTA </p>

<p>14   , there were similarities in the results in 
comparison with this study, as the partially calcified plaque 
was associated to SAH and age. </p>

<p>Additionally, the multivariate analysis showed the highest 
association of partially calcified plaque with SAH, followed 
by male gender and age. </p>

<p>In this study, the calcified plaque was associated with 
DM, dyslipidemia and male gender, with similar odds ratio. 
Studies have shown that calcification of the coronary arteries is 
associated with increased cardiovascular risk. Most significant 
stenotic lesions are calcified and 90% of CAD patients have 
calcification </p>

<p>15,16   . It can be inferred that these risk factors such as 
diabetes mellitus, dyslipidemia and male gender are important 
for the presence of CAD and increased cardiovascular risk. </p>

<p>In the classical literature, SAH is shown as an important 
cardiovascular risk factor. There are, however, recent studies 
showing this association of SAH and coronary heart disease, but 
with questionable impact on clinical practice. A follow-up study </p>

<p>17   showed that there was no significant difference in MACE rates 
between normotensive and hypertensive patients, although the 
hypertensive patients submitted to CCTA had a higher prevalence 
of obstructive CAD and more extensive atherosclerotic lesions. 
It thus suggests that patients without obstructive CAD have an 
excellent prognosis, regardless of the presence of SAH. </p>

<p>In this study, male gender was associated with the presence 
of calcified and partially calcified plaques, in addition to 
CAD extent as demonstrated by the high CS and presence 
of triple-vessel disease, and the number of segments with 
atherosclerotic plaques with greater frequency in the male 
HT + group. In Brazil, CAD is the leading cause of death in 
both genders, in all regions of the country </p>

<p>18   , and is the first 
cause of morbidity and mortality in hypertensive patients </p>

<p>19   . </p>

<p>The difference between the CAD mortality rates between 
men and women in Brazil is one of the lowest in the world, 
both due to high rates of death among women as well as a 
steeper decline in mortality rates and risk factors among men </p>

<p>18   . </p>

<p>By the age of 40 women have lower risk of CAD compared 
to men. The male gender has a 49% chance, whereas females 
have 32%. In men, the first event occurs around age 65; 
while in women the first event usually occurs five to ten years 
later. However, this increase occurs in different ways for both 
sexes, with the female gender showing a remarkable increase 
at older ages, thus decreasing the difference between the 
genders 
20 . These data corroborate those of present study, 
as the mean age of the sample was not advanced age; 
among hypertensive patients it was 61.2 ± 10.3 and for 
normotensive patients, 58.9 ± 12.6 years, with men showing 
a higher frequency of CAD at this age range. This showed 
an association with CAD extent assessed by the presence of </p>

<p>significant lesion, multivessel involvement and high CS, and 
with calcified and partially calcified plaques. </p>

<p>In a multicenter study </p>

<p>19   , the data analysis of 8,737 patients 
with suspected or known CAD, followed for a mean of 25 months 
for the occurrence of all-cause mortality or nonfatal myocardial 
infarction, in the subgroup of female patients with known CAD 
and positive test for myocardial ischemia, the event rate was higher 
in women (p = 0.01) and no gender differences were observed in 
patients with negative test for induced ischemia (p = 0.3). In the 
group of non-ischemic individuals, the annual event rate was 
worse in men than in women aged less than 65 years (p &lt; 0.0001) 
and older than 65 years (p = 0.04). One can infer that the data 
related to the study are similar to this one, as it shows the male 
gender as a predictor of major cardiac events and death, since in 
this research it is associated with CAD extension. However, these 
data suggest analyzing a cohort of our population for assessment 
of cardiac outcomes aiming at more precise comparisons. </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>This study has internal validity, as all patients undergoing this 
methodology at IDPC, from November 2011 to December 2012 
were included; due to limited availability of coronary angiography 
method in most public hospitals in the country to date, it has a low 
external validity. Additionally, CCTA findings were not compared 
with other methods such as coronary ultrasound for validation </p>

<p>21   . </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Hypertensive men more frequently have multivessel 
disease. Male gender was the determining factor of significant 
CAD, multivessel disease, high calcium score and calcified and 
partially calcified plaques, while SAH was a predictor of the 
presence of partially calcified plaque. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>Conception and design of the research: Oliveira JLM, 
Hirata MH, Tavares IS, Pinto IMF. Acquisition of data: Oliveira 
JLM, Gabriel FS, Hirata TDC, Tavares IS, Melo LD, Dória FS. 
Analysis and interpretation of the data: Oliveira JLM, Gabriel 
FS, Tavares IS, Melo LD, Dória FS. Statistical analysis: Oliveira 
JLM, Sousa ACS, Pinto IMF. Obtaining financing: Oliveira JLM, 
Hirata MH, Pinto IMF. Writing of the manuscript: Oliveira 
JLM, Hirata MH, Tavares IS, Pinto IMF. Critical revision of the 
manuscript for intellectual content: Oliveira JLM, Hirata MH, 
Sousa AGMR, Tavares IS, Sousa ACS, Pinto IMF. </p>

<p>Potential Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article 
was reported. </p>

<p>Sources of Funding </p>

<p>This study was funded by CNPq. </p>

<p>Study Association </p>

<p>This article is part of the thesis of Post-Doctoral submitted 
by Joselina Luzia Menezes Oliveira, from Instituto Dante 
Pazzanese de Cardiologia. </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira et al. 
Plaque Predictors at Coronary CT Angiography </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(5):409-416 </p>





</text></tei>