<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4437485" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>SUMMARY </p>

<p>Glial cells can be in vivo reprogrammed into functional neurons in the adult CNS; however, the process by which this reprogramming 
occurs is unclear. Here, we show that a distinct cellular sequence is involved in SOX2-driven in situ conversion of adult astrocytes to 
neurons. This includes ASCL1 
+ neural progenitors and DCX 
+ adult neuroblasts (iANBs) as intermediates. Importantly, ASCL1 is required, </p>

<p>but not sufficient, for the robust generation of iANBs in the adult striatum. These progenitor-derived iANBs predominantly give rise to 
calretinin 
+ interneurons when supplied with neurotrophic factors or the small-molecule valproic acid. Patch-clamp recordings from the </p>

<p>induced neurons reveal subtype heterogeneity, though all are functionally mature, fire repetitive action potentials, and receive synaptic 
inputs. Together, these results show that SOX2-mediated in vivo reprogramming of astrocytes to neurons passes through proliferative 
intermediate progenitors, which may be exploited for regenerative medicine. </p>

<p>Neurons in the CNS are particularly sensitive to injury and 
degenerative conditions that frequently result in cell death. 
Although adult neurogenesis persists in restricted brain 
areas (Gage, 2000; Hsieh, 2012; Kriegstein and Alvarez- Buylla, 2009; Lie et al., 2004), neurons do not regenerate 
in most regions of the adult CNS. An unmet challenge in 
neural injury and degeneration repair is how to replenish 
lost neurons for functional recovery. 
Cell fate reprogramming provides new means for regener-
ating damaged or dead neurons (Arlotta and Berninger,  2014; Cherry and Daley, 2012; Matsui et al., 2014). Not 
only can cells in culture be reprogrammed into pluripotent 
stem cells (Takahashi and Yamanaka, 2006), lineage-
restricted stem cells (Kim et al., 2011a; Ring et al., 2012), 
and different postmitotic cell fates (Heinrich et al., 2010,  2011; Karow et al., 2012; Liu et al., 2013; Vierbuchen  et al., 2010), but they are also amenable to in vivo fate con-
version (Guo et al., 2014; Heinrich et al., 2014; Niu et al.,  2013; Qian et al., 2012; Song et al., 2012; Su et al., 2014a,  b; Torper et al., 2013; Zhou et al., 2008). In regards to the 
CNS, resident glial cells have been directly or indirectly con-
verted into functional neurons in the adult brain and spinal 
cord (Guo et al., 2014; Heinrich et al., 2014; Niu et al., 2013;  Su et al., 2014a, b; Torper et al., 2013). Glial cells are broadly 
distributed and comprise nearly half of the cells in the 
mammalian CNS. These cells become reactive, proliferate, 
and form glial scars in response to neural injuries and degen-</p>

<p>eration (Karimi-Abdolrezaee and Billakanti, 2012; Sofro- niew, 2009). These reactive responses are initially beneficial, 
restricting the spread of damage, but ultimately are delete-
rious, acting as both a physical and chemical barrier to 
neuronal regeneration (Karimi-Abdolrezaee and Billakanti,  2012; Sofroniew, 2009). Reprogramming some of these glial 
cells to functional neurons may constitute a novel thera-
peutic strategy for diseases associated with the CNS. 
Through in vivo screens of candidate factors that are able 
to induce neurogenesis in non-neurogenic regions of the 
adult brain and spinal cord, we previously showed that 
the ectopic expression of SOX2 is sufficient to reprogram 
resident astrocytes to DCX 
+ induced adult neuroblasts </p>

<p>(iANBs) (Niu et al., 2013; Su et al., 2014a). These iANBs 
pass through a proliferative state and generate mature neu-
rons when supplied with neurotrophic factors. This SOX2-
driven in vivo reprogramming process sharply contrasts 
direct lineage conversion strategies (Guo et al., 2014;  Qian et al., 2012; Song et al., 2012; Su et al., 2014b; Torper  et al., 2013; Zhou et al., 2008), which change cell fate in a 
linear fashion without amplification of the induced cell 
population. However, the cellular mechanism underlying 
SOX2-dependent in vivo reprogramming of astrocytes 
was unclear. Furthermore, the subtypes of iANB-derived 
neurons were not well characterized. In this study, we 
reveal that SOX2-driven reprogramming of astrocytes tran-
sits through intermediate neural progenitor states before 
the adoption of a mature neuron fate. Immunohistochem-
istry and electrophysiology further show that induced </p>



<p>neurons are functionally mature and predominantly ex-
press the marker calretinin. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Ectopic Expression of SOX2, but Not the Other SOXB1 
Factors, Results in iANBs 
SOX2 belongs to the SOXB1 subfamily of high-mobility 
group-box transcription factors, which also includes SOX1 
and SOX3 (Sarkar and Hochedlinger, 2013). These factors 
are critical for specifying and maintaining the undifferenti-
ated state of neural precursors. The expression of SOXB1 fac-
tors during SOX2-mediated in vivo reprogramming were 
investigated using immunohistochemistry (Niu et al.,  2013). The adult mouse striatum was injected with lentivirus 
expressing SOX2 under the human GFAP promoter. When 
analyzed 4 weeks post-injection (wpi), DCX 
+ iANBs were </p>

<p>robustly detected in the virus-injected regions, confirming 
our previous results (Niu et al., 2013). Interestingly, SOX1 
can also be detected in striatal regions with iANBs, especially 
in DCX 
+ cell clusters (Figure 1A). However, SOX1 expression </p>

<p>is lower in iANBs than neighboring DCX 
À cells, which is </p>

<p>consistent with previous findings that the continued high-
level expression of SOXB1 factors prohibits neuronal differ-
entiation (Bylund et al., 2003; Niu et al., 2013). In contrast, 
SOX3 is only sporadically distributed in the adult striatum 
and is not detectable in DCX 
+ iANBs (Figure 1A). Due to </p>

<p>sequence and potential functional similarity (Bylund et al.,  2003), we investigated whether the SOXB1 proteins can 
similarly induce DCX 
+ cells. Lentiviruses expressing SOX1 </p>

<p>or SOX3 under the GFAP promoter were individually in-
jected into the adult striatum. However, when examined at 
4 or 5 wpi, no DCX 
+ cells were detected in striatal regions </p>

<p>with ectopic SOX1 or SOX3 expression, in sharp contrast 
to areas injected with SOX2-expressing virus that contain 
DCX 
+ cells (Figure 1B). Together, these data indicate </p>

<p>that SOX2 has a unique property among the SOXB1 
factors, enabling the reprogramming of resident astrocytes 
to iANBs. 
SOX2-dependent iANBs in the adult striatum were 
further examined by injections of lentivirus expressing 
GFP-T2A-SOX2 under the GFAP promoter (Figure S1). The 
co-expressed stable GFP marked virus-transduced cells. 
Immunohistochemical analysis showed that about 23.2% 
± 5.3% of GFP 
+ cells (mean ± SD; n = 17,841 GFP 
+ cells </p>

<p>counted in sections from three mice) stained positive for 
DCX (Figure S1). This suggests a relatively efficient 
induction of iANBs from SOX2-expressing cells. </p>

<p>SOX1 </p>

<p>SOX2 </p>

<p>SOX3 </p>

<p>SOX 
DCX 
SOX/DCX/Hst </p>

<p>SOX1 </p>

<p>SOX2 </p>

<p>SOX3 </p>

<p>SOX 
DCX 
SOX/DCX </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>IHC 
5 wk </p>

<p>SOX2 virus </p>

<p>IHC 
4 -5 wk </p>

<p>SOX virus </p>

<p>Figure 1. Expression and Reprogramming Ability of SOXB1 
Factors 
(A) Immunohistochemistry (IHC) showing expression of SOXB1 
factors in striatal regions with iANBs at 5 weeks post-injection 
(wpi) of SOX2 virus. SOX1 and SOX2, but not SOX3, can be iden-
tified in some of the induced DCX 
+ cells (right panels at higher 
magnifications). Hst, Hoechst 33342. The scale bars represent 
20 mm. 
(B) Ectopic SOX2, but not the other SOXB1 factors, induce striatal 
DCX 
+ cells. Lentivirus expressing individual SOXB1 factors was </p>

<p>injected into the adult mouse striatum and examined 4 or 5 weeks 
(wk) later. The scale bars represent 20 mm. 
See also Figure S1. </p>

<p>Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 4 j 780-794 j May 12, 2015 j ª2015 The Authors 781 </p>

<p>iANBs Are Not the Progeny of Induced Neural Stem 
Cells 
Adult neurogenesis is a multistep process that starts with 
multipotent neural stem cells (NSCs) that gradually transi-
tion into DCX 
+ neuroblasts (Hsieh, 2012; Kempermann   et al., 2004; Kriegstein and Alvarez-Buylla, 2009; Ma  et al., 2009). Both SOX1 and SOX2 are expressed in NSCs 
that can give rise to neurons and glia (Suh et al., 2007; Ve- nere et al., 2012). The residual expression of these factors in 
DCX 
+ iANBs suggests that ectopic SOX2 might reprogram </p>

<p>astrocytes into a multipotent NSC state. We surveyed the 
expression of several additional markers for NSCs sur-
rounding striatal regions injected with SOX2-expressing 
virus at 4 wpi. Nestin (NES), an intermediate filament 
protein highly enriched in embryonic and adult NSCs (La- gace et al., 2007), can be sparsely detected in neighboring 
regions with iANBs (Figure S2). Similarly, cells expressing 
brain-lipid-binding protein, a marker for radial glia in 
developing brain and type-1 and type-2 neural precursors 
of the adult dentate gyrus (DG) (Feng et al., 1994; Steiner  et al., 2006), are intermingled with iANBs in the adult stria-
tum. GFAP 
+ cells are also found in the vicinity of iANBs </p>

<p>(Figure S2). GFAP is robustly induced in reactive astrocytes 
and also labels NSCs in the adult lateral ventricle (LV) and 
DG (Doetsch, 2003; Kriegstein and Alvarez-Buylla, 2009;  Lie et al., 2004). Although the above markers were not 
detected in DCX 
+ cells, these data support a hypothesis </p>

<p>that iANBs might be derived from SOX2-induced NSCs in 
the striatum. 
We directly examined this hypothesis using a lineage-
tracing strategy. When adult Nes-CreER 
TM ;Rosa-YFP mice </p>

<p>were treated with tamoxifen for 7 days and examined 
3 weeks later, DCX 
+ cells in the LV and DG were robustly </p>

<p>labeled with the YFP reporter (Figures 2A and 2B). This 
result confirms that neuroblasts from endogenous NSCs 
can be specifically traced in this transgenic mouse line 
(Kuo et al., 2006; Niu et al., 2013). We then injected 
SOX2-expressing lentivirus into the striatum of adult 
Nes-CreER 
TM ;Rosa-YFP mice, administered tamoxifen at 2 </p>

<p>or 3 wpi, and performed immunohistochemistry after 
another 3 weeks. As internal controls, endogenous neuro-
blasts in the LV were traced with the marker YFP. In sharp 
contrast, none of the SOX2-induced DCX 
+ cells in the stria-</p>

<p>tum were YFP labeled, indicating that ectopic SOX2 does 
not reprogram astrocytes into a NSC-like state (Figures 2C 
and 2D). </p>

<p>SOX2 Induces ASCL1 
+ Neural Progenitors </p>

<p>ASCL1 
+ neural progenitors precede the development of </p>

<p>DCX 
+ neuroblasts during adult neurogenesis (Kim et al., </p>

<p>2011a; Lugert et al., 2012). Very interestingly, ASCL1 
+ cells </p>

<p>can be specifically detected in the striatal regions around 
DCX 
+ iANBs when injected with SOX2, but not a control </p>

<p>virus, at 5 wpi (Figure 3A). A time course analysis further 
showed that the number of ASCL 
+ cells gradually increases </p>

<p>post-injection of SOX2 virus, reaches a peak level around 5 
wpi, and persists beyond 14 wpi (Figure 3B). We used the 
GFAP-GFP marker to label virus-transduced astrocytes in 
the adult striatum and revealed specific ASCL1 expression 
in these GFP 
+ cells, which clustered with SOX2-induced </p>

<p>DCX 
+ cells (Figure 3C). </p>

<p>The above results suggest that ASCL1 
+ cells might be the </p>

<p>precursors of iANBs during SOX2-driven in vivo astrocyte 
reprogramming. We examined this possibility using 
Ascl1-CreER 
T2 mice, in which the tamoxifen-inducible </p>

<p>CreER 
T2 was knocked into the endogenous Ascl1 locus </p>

<p>(Kim et al., 2011b). After crossing to mice harboring the 
Cre-activity-dependent Rosa-tdTomato (tdT) reporter (Mad-
isen et al., 2010), ASCL1 
+ cells and their progeny can be </p>

<p>uniquely traced. These adult mice were injected with a 
SOX2-expressing or control virus, administered tamoxifen 
for 7 days starting at 2 wpi, and examined at 6 wpi (Fig-
ure 3D). Whereas no tdT 
+ cells were detected in striatal </p>

<p>regions injected with the control virus, these cells were 
robustly distributed in regions injected with the SOX2 
virus (Figure 3E). Consistent with the hypothesis that 
iANBs are derived from ASCL1 
+ neural progenitors, over </p>

<p>90% of SOX2-induced DCX 
+ cells could be labeled by tdT. </p>

<p>Together, these data show that ectopic SOX2 reprograms 
striatal astrocytes to ASCL1 
+ neural progenitors, which sub-</p>

<p>sequently give rise to DCX 
+ iANBs. </p>

<p>ASCL1 Is Required, but Not Sufficient, for Generation 
of iANBs 
ASCL1 is a neural specific basic helix-loop-helix transcrip-
tion factor and essential for neurogenesis during early ner-
vous system development (Casarosa et al., 1999; Nieto  et al., 2001; Torii et al., 1999). The induction of ASCL1 in 
the adult striatum suggests that it may be critical for 
SOX2-driven in vivo reprogramming of astrocytes. To 
examine this possibility, we used genetically modified 
mice that contain conditional alleles of Ascl1 (Ascl1 
f/f ; </p>

<p>Pacary et al., 2011) and a tamoxifen-inducible CreER </p>

<p>T2 </p>

<p>transgene under the astrocyte-specific Cst3 promoter (Fig-
ure 4A) (Niu et al., 2013). These adult mice were treated 
with tamoxifen or vehicle for 7 days and then injected 
with SOX2-expressing lentivirus. Immunohistochemistry 
was performed 5 wpi and revealed a dramatic reduction 
in the population of DCX 
+ iANBs upon inducible deletion </p>

<p>of Ascl1 (Figures 4B and 4C). The few residual DCX 
+ cells </p>

<p>might be due to an incomplete deletion of Ascl1 in all the 
SOX2 virus-infected astrocytes. These data indicate that 
ASCL1 plays a critical role in SOX2-driven reprogramming. 
Ectopic ASCL1 is sufficient to promote the neuronal dif-
ferentiation of embryonic stem cells and NSCs (Berninger 
et al., 2007; Chanda et al., 2014), as well as reprogram </p>



<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D 
C </p>

<p>YFP/DCX 
YFP/DCX 
YFP/DCX 
YFP/DCX </p>

<p>YFP 
DCX 
YFP/DCX 
YFP/DCX </p>

<p>Rosa </p>

<p>Nes 
CreER TM </p>

<p>STOP 
YFP </p>

<p>Rosa 
Tam </p>

<p>YFP </p>

<p>LV </p>

<p>DG </p>

<p>m 
u 
t 
a 
i 
r 
t 
S 
m 
u 
t 
a 
i 
r 
t 
S 
V 
L 
L V </p>

<p>IHC 
4 wk </p>

<p>Tam </p>

<p>Virus 
3 wk 
4 wk </p>

<p>IHC 
Tam 
Virus 
IHC 
2 wk </p>

<p>Tam 
4 wk </p>

<p>Figure 2. SOX2-Driven Reprogramming Does Not Pass through a NSC Stage 
(A) A genetic approach to trace NSCs and their progeny. Adult Nes-CreER </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>;Rosa-YFP mice were injected with tamoxifen (Tam) for 7 days 
and examined 3 wk later. 
(B) Endogenous NSCs and DCX 
+ cells in the lateral ventricle (LV) and dentate gyrus (DG) are genetically traced. The scale bars represent 
20 mm. 
(C and D) iANBs do not pass through a nestin 
+ NSC stage. Adult mutant mice were treated with Tam 2 (C) or 3 (D) wpi of SOX2-expressing 
virus and examined at the indicated time points. DCX 
+ cells in the LV were used as endogenous controls. The scale bars represent 20 mm. 
See also Figure S2. </p>

<p>Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 4 j 780-794 j May 12, 2015 j ª2015 The Authors 783 </p>

<p>cultured fibroblasts and early postnatal astroglia to neurons 
(Chanda et al., 2014; Heinrich et al., 2011), demonstrating 
a dominant role for ASCL1 in cell fate specification. To 
investigate whether ASCL1 itself is also able to induce 
DCX 
+ neuroblasts in the adult striatum, we injected lenti-</p>

<p>virus expressing ASCL1 under the GFAP promoter and 
analyzed 1, 2, 3, and 5 wpi (Figure 4D). Unexpectedly, 
DCX 
+ cells were not observed in regions with robust </p>

<p>expression of exogenous ASCL1 (Figure 4E). These results 
suggest that ASCL1 has important roles in the SOX2-driven </p>

<p>reprogramming process but is not itself sufficient to induce 
cell fate switch in the adult striatum. </p>

<p>iANBs Mostly Generate Calretinin 
+ Interneurons </p>

<p>We previously showed that iANBs can give rise to function-
ally mature neurons upon treatment with brain-derived 
neurotrophic factor (BDNF) and noggin or with the small 
molecule valproic acid (VPA) (Niu et al., 2013). However, 
the subtype of neurons generated by these treatments 
was unclear. We surveyed the expression of markers for </p>

<p>DCX 
ASCL1 
DCX/ASCL1 
DCX/ASCL1/Hst </p>

<p>GFP 
ASCL1 </p>

<p>DCX 
Hst </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
14 
wpi : </p>

<p>ASCL1 + </p>

<p>cells/section </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C 
B </p>

<p>SOX2 + GFP </p>

<p>GFP </p>

<p>GFP/ASCL1 </p>

<p>GFP/ASCL1/DCX/Hst </p>

<p>ASCL1 </p>

<p>: </p>

<p>DCX/tdT 
DCX/tdT </p>

<p>Rosa </p>

<p>Ascl1 
CreER T2 </p>

<p>STOP 
tdT </p>

<p>Rosa 
Tam 
tdT </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>IHC 
4 wk 
2 wk </p>

<p>Tam 
Virus </p>

<p>Figure 3. SOX2 Induces ASCL1 
+ Neural 
Progenitors 
(A) The expression of ASCL1 
+ cells in striatal 
regions with DCX 
+ iANBs at 5 wpi. The scale 
bar represents 20 mm. 
(B) A time course analysis of ASCL1 
+ cells in 
the reprogramming area (mean ± SD; n = 3 
mice at each time point). 
(C) ASCL1 is detected in astrocytes trans-
duced with SOX2 lentivirus. The co-ex-
pressed GFP marker is under the control of 
the human GFAP promoter. The scale bar 
represents 20 mm. 
(D) A genetic approach to trace deriva-
tives of ASCL1 
+ progenitors. SOX2-driven 
reprogramming was induced in adult 
Ascl1-CreER 
T2 ;Rosa-tdTomato (tdT) mice. 
(E) SOX2-induced DCX 
+ cells pass through an 
ASCL1 
+ progenitor stage. Confocal images 
show genetic labeling of iANBs. An 
orthogonal view is shown in the right panel. 
The scale bar represents 20 mm. </p>



<p>striatal neurons by immunohistochemistry in regions 
injected with SOX2 virus at 8 wpi. To promote neuron sur-
vival and maturation, some of these mice were also injected 
with virus expressing BDNF or BDNF-noggin or were 
treated with VPA for 4 weeks starting at 4 wpi (Figures 
S3A and S3B). Among all these treatment groups, we did 
not notice any major change in the populations of neurons 
expressing parvalbumin, somatostatin, choline acetyl-
transferase, tyrosine hydroxylase, or DARPP32 (Figure S3C; 
data not shown). In sharp contrast, we observed a dramatic </p>

<p>induction of calretinin neurons in striatal regions of mice 
injected with SOX2 virus and treated with the neurotro-
phic factors or small molecule (Figures S3C and S3D). 
This combination treatment was essential for the induc-
tion of calretinin neurons, as they were not observed in 
mice injected with only virus or treated with only VPA. 
We performed bromodeoxyuridine (BrdU) tracing to 
confirm these calretinin neurons were indeed newly 
induced. Adult mice were injected singularly or in combi-
nation with viruses expressing SOX2, BDNF, noggin, or </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>C 
B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>DCX + </p>

<p>cells/animal </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>3000 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>Tam: </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>_ 
+ 
IHC </p>

<p>1, 2, 3, or 5 wk </p>

<p>ASCL1 virus </p>

<p>Cst3 
CreER T2 </p>

<p>Tam </p>

<p>Ascl1 f/f </p>

<p>Neo 
Venus </p>

<p>ASCL1/DCX 
ASCL1 
DCX </p>

<p>SOX2/DCX 
SOX2 
DCX </p>

<p>Neo 
Venus </p>

<p>IHC </p>

<p>Ascl1 f/f </p>

<p>5 wk 
4 wk </p>

<p>SOX2 
virus 
Tam </p>

<p>Figure 4. ASCL1 Is Required, but Not Sufficient, for SOX2-Driven Reprogramming 
(A and B) Schematic diagrams show experimental designs. Ascl1 is deleted in the adult astrocytes after Tam treatment of Ascl1 </p>

<p>f/f </p>

<p>; 
Cst3-CreER 
T2 mice. Four weeks later, in vivo reprogramming was initiated by injection of SOX2-expressing lentivirus and examined at 5 wpi. 
(C) Deletion of Ascl1 dramatically reduces the induction of DCX 
+ cells (mean ± SD; n = 6 for vehicle-treated and n = 4 for Tam-treated mice; 
**p = 0.0013 by Student's t test). 
(D) The experimental design for examining ASCL1 reprogramming ability. 
(E) DCX 
+ cells were not detected in striatal regions with ectopic ASCL1 when examined at 1, 2, 3, or 5 weeks post virus injection. SOX2-
induced DCX 
+ cells were used as positive controls. The scale bar represents 20 mm. </p>

<p>Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 4 j 780-794 j May 12, 2015 j ª2015 The Authors 785 </p>

<p>Tam 
3 wk </p>

<p>VPA 
twice/day 
IHC 
Virus 
5 wk 
4 wk 
1 wk 
(0 wpi) 
(5 wpi) 
(9 wpi) </p>

<p>Virus 
4 wk </p>

<p>BrdU 
twice/day </p>

<p>4 wk </p>

<p>IHC </p>

<p>VPA </p>

<p>YFP </p>

<p>tdT </p>

<p>Calretinin </p>

<p>Calretinin </p>

<p>YFP/Calretinin </p>

<p>tdT/Calretinin </p>

<p>SOX2 + BDNF-Nog </p>

<p>BrdU 
Calretinin 
BrdU/Calretinin/NEUN </p>

<p>Rosa </p>

<p>Cst3 
CreER T2 </p>

<p>STOP YFP </p>

<p>Tam Rosa 
YFP </p>

<p>S O </p>

<p>X 2 
B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>F 
N 
o g B 
D </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>-N </p>

<p>o g 
V P A B 
D </p>

<p>N 
F B 
D </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>-N 
o g V P A </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 
+SOX2 </p>

<p>BrdU + </p>

<p>CR + 
/CR + </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>IHC 
VPA 
8 wk 
2 wk 
2 wk </p>

<p>Tam 
Virus </p>

<p>Rosa </p>

<p>Ascl1 
CreER T2 </p>

<p>STOP 
tdT </p>

<p>Rosa 
Tam 
tdT </p>

<p>(legend on next page) </p>

<p>786 Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 4 j 780-794 j May 12, 2015 j ª2015 The Authors </p>

<p>BDNF-noggin. A cohort of SOX2 virus-injected mice was 
also treated with VPA in drinking water for 4 weeks begin-
ning at 4 wpi. All mice were administered BrdU for 4 weeks 
to label newly generated cells (Figure 5A). When analyzed 
at 8 wpi, 30%-70% of calretinin cells could be traced by 
BrdU in striatal regions injected with SOX2 virus and 
treated with either neurotropic factors or VPA (Figure 5B). 
A majority of these BrdU 
+ calretinin 
+ neurons were also </p>

<p>NEUN 
+ , a marker for mature neurons (Figure 5C). These </p>

<p>neurons were not detectable in any of the control groups, 
confirming that the long-term survival and maturation of 
SOX2-induced neurons requires neurotrophic factors (Niu  et al., 2013). 
Cell-of-origin tracing was used to map the lineage of 
induced calretinin 
+ neurons in transgenic mice. Astrocytes </p>

<p>were specifically labeled by tamoxifen-inducible expres-
sion of YFP in adult Cst3-CreER 
T2 ;Rosa-YFP mice (Figure 5D) </p>

<p>(Niu et al., 2013). Three weeks later, these mice received 
striatal injections of SOX2-expressing lentivirus and were 
treated with VPA for 4 weeks starting at 5 wpi. When 
analyzed at 10 wpi, calretinin 
+ neurons were uniquely </p>

<p>traced by YFP, indicating an origin from adult striatal astro-
cytes (Figure 5E). However, not all calretinin 
+ neurons were </p>

<p>YFP 
+ , a result that might be due to the incomplete labeling </p>

<p>of striatal astrocytes by the inducible approach and a few 
preexisting endogenous calretinin 
+ neurons. </p>

<p>Ascl1-CreER 
T2 ;Rosa-tdT mice were employed to further </p>

<p>examine whether SOX2-induced calretinin 
+ neurons pass </p>

<p>through an ASCL1 
+ intermediate progenitor stage (Fig-</p>

<p>ure 5F). These adult mice were first injected with SOX2-ex-
pressing lentivirus to induce reprogramming and treated 
with tamoxifen at 2 wpi to label cells derived from 
ASCL1 
+ progenitors. When examined at 6 wpi, many of </p>

<p>the calretinin 
+ interneurons were tdT 
+ (Figure 5G), indi-</p>

<p>cating that they were indeed derived from SOX2-induced 
ASCL1 
+ progenitors. As controls, calretinin 
+ tdT 
+ cells </p>

<p>were not detectable in striatal regions injected with GFP-ex-</p>

<p>pressing lentivirus. The long-term survival of SOX2-
induced neurons was determined at 36 wpi (Figure S3E). 
About 94.6% ± 0.9% tdT 
+ cells (mean ± SD; n = 369 tdT </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>cells from three mice) were NeuN 
+ , indicating that a major-</p>

<p>ity of the induced neurons become mature and exhibit 
long-term survival in the endogenous environment 
(Figure S3F). </p>

<p>Functional Heterogeneity of Induced Neurons 
We conducted whole-cell patch clamp recordings on re-
programmed striatal neurons using live brain slices from 
adult Ascl1-CreER 
T2 ;Rosa-tdT mice. Mice at 2-4 months of </p>

<p>age were injected with SOX2-expressing lentivirus to 
initiate the reprogramming of astrocytes and 2 weeks later 
treated with tamoxifen for 7 days to trace induced neurons. 
To promote the survival and maturation of induced neu-
rons, mice were also treated with VPA for at least 4 weeks 
starting at 4 wpi. Electrophysiology was performed from 
8 to 40 wpi. The morphology of recorded cells was visual-
ized by the infusion of biocytin through recording pipettes 
(Figure 6A). 
Based on resting membrane potential and input resis-
tance, the induced neurons can be broadly grouped into 
four subtypes (Figures 6B-6D). The vast majority of the 
induced neurons (type I; n = 20/27) exhibit hyperpolarized 
resting membrane potential at À80 mV and have a lower 
input resistance (30-80 MU). Type II neurons (n = 2/27) 
are similarly hyperpolarized around À80 mV but show a 
much-higher input resistance (200-1,000 MU). The resting 
membrane potential of type III (n = 2/27) and type IV (n = 
3/27) neurons is À60 mV; however, the respective input 
resistances differ widely, $150 MU and $2,000 MU. Cell 
capacitance, which usually serves as an indicator of cell 
size and channel abundance on the membrane, varies 
broadly among these recorded neurons (Figure 6E). 
Functional maturity was examined by the ability to fire 
action potentials (APs), which were elicited by a series of </p>

<p>Figure 5. Reprogramming of Resident Astrocytes to Calretinin 
+ Neurons 
(A) Experimental schemes. Newly generated cells were labeled by BrdU incorporation. Neuronal survival and maturation were promoted by 
valproic acid (VPA) or neurotrophic factors. 
(B) Quantification of newly generated calretinin (CR) 
+ neurons under the indicated conditions (mean ± SD; n = 3 mice at each condition). 
BDNF, brain-derived neurotrophic factor; Nog, noggin. 
(C) Confocal images showing BrdU-labeled CR 
+ neurons that were induced by SOX2. An orthogonal view of the boxed region is also shown. 
The scale bar represents 20 mm. 
(D and E) SOX2-induced CR 
+ neurons originate from resident astrocytes. Adult resident astrocytes were genetically traced in Cst3-
CreER 
T2 ;Rosa-YFP mice after Tam treatment. These cells were then in vivo reprogrammed by ectopic SOX2 and analyzed 10 weeks later. Soma 
and processes of the astrocyte-converted CR 
+ neurons are indicated by arrows and arrowheads, respectively. The scale bar represents 
20 mm. 
(F and G) SOX2-induced CR 
+ neurons pass through an ASCL1 progenitor stage. The descendants of ASCL1 
+ progenitors were genetically 
traced in Ascl1-CreER 
T2 ;Rosa-tdT mice. A majority of the reprogrammed CR 
+ neurons were traced by the marker tdT. The scale bar represents 
20 mm. 
See also Figure S3. </p>

<p>Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 4 j 780-794 j May 12, 2015 j ª2015 The Authors 787 </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>II III IV </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Capacitance (pF) </p>

<p>I 
II III IV </p>

<p>-100 </p>

<p>-80 </p>

<p>-60 </p>

<p>-40 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>V 
0 (mV) </p>

<p>I 
II 
III 
IV </p>

<p>R 
in (MΩ) </p>

<p>V 0 (mV) </p>

<p>-100 -80 -60 -40 -20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>10000 </p>

<p>I 
III </p>

<p>100ms </p>

<p>20mV </p>

<p>IV </p>

<p>I 
II III IV </p>

<p>-60 </p>

<p>-40 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>AP threshold (mV) </p>

<p>10pA 
1s </p>

<p>10pA 
10ms </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>II </p>

<p>IV </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>I 
II III IV </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>n.a. 
sPSC amplitude (pA) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>E 
D 
C 
B </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>J 
I 
H 
G </p>

<p>M 
L 
K </p>

<p>Type I 
Type II </p>

<p>Biocytin/tdT </p>

<p>Type III 
Type IV </p>

<p>R 
in (MΩ) </p>

<p>I 
II III IV </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>10000 </p>

<p>AP amplitude (pA) 
I 
II III IV </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>I 
II III IV </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>AP half-width (ms) </p>

<p>I 
II III IV </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>AP frequency (Hz) </p>

<p>I 
II III IV </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>sPSC frequency (Hz) 
n.a. </p>

<p>II </p>

<p>Figure 6. Functional Properties of SOX2-Induced Neurons 
(A) Representative confocal images of the four types of induced neurons traced in the striatum of adult Ascl1-CreER 
T2 ;Rosa-tdT mice and 
infused with biocytin. The scale bars represent 10 mm. 
(B-D) Characterization of the four types of induced neurons based on input resistance (R in ) and resting membrane potentials (V 0 ). 
(E) A majority of the recorded neurons have a capacitance around 30 pF. 
(legend continued on next page) </p>



<p>current-step injections. All induced neurons fired repetitive 
APs when depolarized beyond the AP threshold (n = 27/27; 
Figures 6F and S4A). Although the AP threshold (Figure 6G) 
and delay of the first AP spike (Figure S4B) were within a 
broad range, type I neurons exhibited larger amplitudes 
and higher firing frequencies (n = 20; Figures 6H and 6I). 
On the other hand, type IV induced neurons had a wider 
AP half-width (Figure 6J) and slower velocity of AP rise 
and decay (n = 3; Figures S4C and S4D). Interestingly, 
type III induced neurons spontaneously fired APs at their 
resting membrane potential (Figures S3E and S4F), a phe-
nomenon widely observed in many CNS neurons. These 
neurons might function in the synchronization of circuit 
activity or sustain modulatory inputs onto postsynaptic 
neurons (Häusser et al., 2004; Maccaferri and McBain,  1996). 
By depolarizing the induced neurons from À60 mV 
to +60 mV in 10-mV increments, we further examined 
the behaviors of sodium and potassium channels (Fig-
ure S4G). The large inward current from voltage-gated so-
dium channels was completely blocked by the application 
of tetrodotoxin (Figure S4H). These sodium currents (I Na ) 
varied broadly and were not considerably different 
between subtypes of induced neurons (Figure S4I). The out-
ward currents in the plateau phase of the voltage step repre-
sent delayed rectifier potassium currents (I d ; Figure S4G), 
which were much lower in type IV induced neurons (Fig- ure S4J). The approximate summation of fast potassium 
current (I A ) and I d collectively represent the outward cur-
rent immediately following the inward sodium current. I A 
was smaller in type IV induced neurons than the other 
three types (Figure S4K). These data suggest that ion chan-
nel distributions in type IV induced neurons are different 
from the other three types. </p>

<p>Neuron connectivity within the local circuitry was inves-
tigated by recording spontaneous postsynaptic currents 
(sPSCs). All of the analyzed neurons showed robust sPSCs 
with comparable average amplitudes, although the 
frequency was lower in type IV induced neurons (Figures 
6K-6M). These results indicate that all of the induced 
neurons have efficiently integrated into the local neuronal 
networks and received inputs from presynaptic neurons. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study used genetic fate mapping to reveal that SOX2-
driven in vivo reprogramming of adult astrocytes passes 
through a sequence of distinct cell states (Figure 7), which 
mimics aspects of endogenous neurogenesis. Ectopic SOX2 
converts astrocytes to ASCL1 
+ intermediate progenitors, </p>

<p>which proliferate and generate DCX 
+ neuroblasts. These </p>

<p>early neuroblasts can expand and eventually generate 
mature neurons when supplied with neurotrophic factors. 
Expansion through the intermediate progenitors and 
neuroblasts enable one reprogrammed astrocyte to make 
multiple functional neurons, which might be therapeuti-
cally beneficial for regenerative medicine in treating neural 
injuries or degeneration. 
Although previous work showed that SOX2 is sufficient 
to convert fibroblasts into NES 
+ multipotent NSCs under a </p>

<p>unique culture condition (Ring et al., 2012), our genetic 
approach using Nes-CreER 
T2 ;Rosa-YFP mice failed to detect </p>

<p>a stable NSC state during the in vivo reprogramming pro-
cess. This difference highlights the critical importance of 
the microenvironment in cell fate reprogramming and sug-
gests that additional factors are required to enable SOX2 to 
convert glial cells into multipotent stem cells in the adult </p>

<p>(F) Representative action potential traces from each type of reprogrammed neurons. 
(G) All the induced neurons have a similar action potential (AP) threshold. 
(H and I) A majority of the induced neurons have higher AP amplitudes and frequencies. 
(J) Type IV induced neurons have wider AP half-width. 
(K-M) Properties of spontaneous postsynaptic currents (sPSCs). Whereas there is a broader range of sPSC frequencies, their amplitude is 
rather similar (n.a., not available). 
For all panels, n = 20 cells from 11 mice for type I neurons, n = 2 cells from two mice for type II neurons, n = 2 cells from one mouse for type 
III neurons, and n = 3 cells from three mice for type IV neurons. 
See also Figure S4. </p>

<p>Astrocytes 
(GFAP) </p>

<p>Neuroblasts 
(DCX) </p>

<p>Progenitors 
(ASCL1) </p>

<p>SOX2 </p>

<p>Neurotrophic 
factors or 
valproic acid </p>

<p>Virus </p>

<p>Neurons 
(NeuN) </p>

<p>Figure 7. Stepwise Reprogramming of 
Resident Astrocytes to Functional Neu-
rons in the Adult Brain </p>

<p>Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 4 j 780-794 j May 12, 2015 j ª2015 The Authors 789 </p>

<p>CNS. Our initial in vivo screens for reprogramming factors 
included the four factors for induced pluripotent stem cells 
(Niu et al., 2013); however, this combination of factors has 
been subsequently shown to induce tumorigenesis in vivo 
(Abad et al., 2013; Ohnishi et al., 2014) and raised serious 
concerns about the therapeutic value of in vivo induced 
pluripotent stem cells. In contrast, we have not observed 
any histological signs of tumorigenesis in brains or spinal 
cords with ectopic SOX2 expression when examined up to 
1 year post virus injection. This is consistent with a recent 
study showing that multiple key transcription factors are 
required to initiate brain tumors in vivo (Suvà et al., 2014). 
Adult neurogenesis is a multistep process beginning with 
multipotent NSCs that yield transient amplifying neural 
progenitors and then mature neurons (Gage, 2000; Hsieh,  2012; Kriegstein and Alvarez-Buylla, 2009; Lie et al.,  2004). Our immunohistochemistry and genetic fate-map-
ping experiments demonstrate that SOX2-driven in vivo 
reprogramming passes through an ASCL1 
+ intermediate </p>

<p>progenitor stage. These progenitors give rise to DCX 
+ neu-</p>

<p>roblasts, which can further proliferate and expand the 
neuronal lineage (Niu et al., 2013). This sequential and 
multistage amplification process is consistent with what 
has been observed in the adult neurogenic niches, suggest-
ing that the reprogrammed glial cells have adopted the 
behavior of endogenous progenitors (Kim et al., 2011b; Lu- gert et al., 2012). ASCL1 serves as a molecular marker of 
neural progenitors and also controls their activity, 
including proliferation and differentiation (Andersen  et al., 2014; Battiste et al., 2007; Jessberger et al., 2008;  Kim et al., 2007, 2008). Consistently, our conditional dele-
tion of Ascl1 in astrocytes shows that it is critically 
important for robust in vivo reprogramming. Nonetheless, 
ASCL1 cannot replace SOX2 in the induction of neurogen-
esis from adult astrocytes, as DCX 
+ iANBs are rarely </p>

<p>detected in striatal regions with ectopic ASCL1 during a se-
ries of time course analyses. This result agrees with a recent 
in vivo study (Heinrich et al., 2014) and suggests that addi-
tional factors are also required in combination with ASCL1 
to mediate SOX2 function in cell fate reprograming in the 
adult brain. In contrast, ASCL1 alone is able to transdiffer-
entiate early postnatal astroglia (Heinrich et al., 2010,  2012), fibroblasts (Chanda et al., 2014), and embryonic 
stem cells (Chanda et al., 2014) into functional neurons 
in culture. This discrepancy between results from in vitro 
and in vivo studies once again highlights the importance 
of the cellular milieu in cell fate specification, determina-
tion, and reprogramming. 
A survey of markers for neuronal subtypes reveals that a 
larger population of SOX2-induced neurons expresses calre-
tinin, a calcium-binding protein in GABAergic interneu-
rons (Tepper et al., 2010). Interestingly, calretinin was 
shown to be transiently co-expressed with DCX during </p>

<p>the early stage of adult hippocampal neurogenesis and 
subsequently downregulated once newly born neurons 
become mature 6 weeks later (Brandt et al., 2003). In 
contrast, calretinin is rarely detectable in iANBs but contin-
uously expressed once they develop into mature neurons 
by 8 wpi, suggesting the stable generation of this neuronal 
subtype. The preferential reprogramming of striatal 
astrocytes by SOX2 to calretinin 
+ neurons was unexpected </p>

<p>but is most likely due to signaling cues present in the 
adult striatum or intrinsic factors residing in the striatal 
astrocytes. It will be interesting in the future to tease out 
these instructive factors for the generation of specific 
neuron subtypes. 
Endogenous calretinin 
+ interneurons make up 0.5% of </p>

<p>striatal neurons in the rodent but are more prevalent in 
humans (Rymar et al., 2004; Wu and Parent, 2000). These 
neurons are diverse in morphology with limited electro-
physiological characterization (Tepper et al., 2010). Electro-
physiological analyses show that the induced neurons are 
heterogeneous, although the majority is hyperpolarized 
with lower input resistance and higher AP amplitude and 
frequency. This heterogeneity may reflect functional diver-
sity and/or the progressive nature of neuronal maturation 
and integration into the local circuits. Interestingly, a 
minority of the recorded neurons exhibit pacemaker-like 
activity and fire spontaneous APs at resting membrane 
potential. This activity is prevalent in striatal cholinergic 
neurons, subthalamic nucleus neurons, midbrain dopami-
nergic neurons, cerebellar Purkinje and Golgi neurons, and 
low-threshold spike interneurons of the striatum (Beatty  et al., 2012; Reynolds and Wickens, 2004; Sharott et al.,  2012). The pace-making activity of these neurons can syn-
chronize neuronal networks for higher-order brain func-
tions (Ramirez et al., 2004). 
The ability to reprogram glial cells into functional neu-
rons in the adult CNS has reshaped our knowledge of cell 
fate maintenance and brought a new perspective to cell-
based regenerative medicine for neurological diseases. 
The results of this study provide new insights into the 
cellular processes of SOX2-driven in vivo reprogramming, 
which may be useful for future strategies aimed at 
improving reprogramming efficiency and the derivation 
of disease-relevant neuron subtypes. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>The following mutant mouse lines were used in this study: 
Cst3-CreER 
T2 (Niu et al., 2013), Nes-CreER 
TM (Kuo et al., 2006), </p>

<p>Ascl1-CreER 
T2 (Kim et al., 2011b), Ascl1 
neoflox/neoflox (floxed </p>

<p>allele of Ascl1 mutant mice with the neo cassette, here referred 
to as Ascl1 
f/f ; Pacary et al., 2011), Rosa-YFP (Srinivas et al., </p>

<p>2001), and Rosa-tdTomato (Ai14; Rosa-tdT; Madisen et al., 2010). </p>



<p>Adult male and female mice at 2-6 months of age were used un-
less otherwise stated. All mice were housed under a 12 hr light/ 
dark cycle and had ad libitum access to food and water in a 
controlled animal facility. Experimental protocols were approved 
by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at UT 
Southwestern. </p>

<p>Tamoxifen, VPA, and BrdU Administration </p>

<p>Tamoxifen (T5648; Sigma) was dissolved in a mixture of ethanol 
and sesame oil (10:90 by volume) at a concentration of 
40 mg/ml and stored at 4 
C. It was intraperitoneally injected at a </p>

<p>daily dose of 4 mg/40 g body weight daily for 5-7 days. VPA 
(P4543; Sigma) in drinking water (4 g/l) was administered for 
4 weeks. BrdU (B5002; Sigma; 10 mg/kg body weight in PBS) was 
applied by daily intraperitoneal injection for 4 weeks. </p>

<p>Virus Preparation and Intracerebral Injections </p>

<p>The lentiviral vectors GFAP-GFP, GFAP-SOX2, GFAP-GFP-T2A-
SOX2, GFAP-GFP-T2A-Bdnf, and GFAP-GFP-T2A-Noggin were 
generated as previously described (Niu et al., 2013). A final volume 
of 2 ml virus with an original titer of 0.5-1 3 10 
9 colony-forming </p>

<p>units per ml was stereotactically injected into the striatum of adult 
mice with a coordinate of anterior/posterior, +1.0 mm; medial/ 
lateral, ±2 mm; and dorsal/ventral from skull, À3.0 mm. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Adult mice were euthanized with CO 2 overdose and sequentially 
perfused with ice-cold PBS and 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) in 
PBS. Brains were collected and postfixed with 4% PFA for 4-6 hr 
or overnight at 4 
C. Postfixed brains were cryoprotected with </p>

<p>30% sucrose solution in PBS for 24 hr and cut into 40-mm-thick sec-
tions with a sliding microtome (Leica). Brain sections were serially 
collected and stored in antifreezing solution at À20 
C. Immuno-</p>

<p>histochemistry was performed essentially as previously described 
(Niu et al., 2011). Briefly, free-floating sections were rinsed with 
PBS and blocked with blocking solution (3% BSA and 0.2% Triton 
X-100 in PBS) for 1 hr at room temperature. These sections were 
incubated with primary antibodies diluted in blocking solution 
for at least 24 hr at 4 
C followed by three rinses with PBST buffer </p>

<p>(0.2% Triton X-100 in PBS). They were subsequently incubated 
with respective secondary antibodies diluted in blocking solution 
for over 2 hr at room temperature. Nuclei were counterstained 
with Hoechst 33342 when appropriate. After extensive rinsing 
with PBST buffer, sections were mounted onto glass slides for 
microscopy. The following primary antibodies were used: GFP 
(A-11122, rabbit, 1:500, Invitrogen; GFP, chick, 1:1,000, Aves 
Labs), GFAP (G3893; mouse; 1:500; Sigma), BrdU (OBT0030; rat 
BU1/75; 1:500; Accurate Chemical), NEUN (MAB377; mouse; 
1:500; Millipore), SOX1 (4194S; rabbit; 1:500; Cell Signaling Tech-
nology), SOX2 (AB5603; rabbit; 1:500; Millipore), SOX3 (rabbit; 
1:200; a gift from M. Klymkowsky; Wang et al., 2006), BLBP 
(AB9558; rabbit; 1:500; Millipore), NES (556309; mouse; 1:200; 
BD PharMingen), KI-67 (NCL-Ki67; rabbit; 1:500; Novocastra), 
DCX (sc-8066; goat; 1:150; Santa Cruz Biotechnology), OLIG2 
(AB9610; rabbit; 1:500; Millipore), glutamine synthetase 
(MAB302; mouse; 1:500; Chemicon), PSA-NCAM (5A5-a; mouse; 
1:250; Hybridoma bank), NG2 (MAB5384; mouse; 1:500; Milli-</p>

<p>pore), IBA1 (019-19741; rabbit; 1:1,000; Waco), Parvalbumin 
(P3088; mouse; 1:1,000; Sigma), somatostatin (AB5494; rabbit; 
1:500; Chemicon), CHAT (CAT; chick; 1:1,000; Aves), Calretinin 
(AB702; rabbit; 1:200; Novus), DARPP32 (2302; rabbit; 1:500; 
Cell Signaling Technology), CC-1 (OP80; mouse; 1:500; Calbio-
chem), and ASCL1 (TX-518; guinea pig; 1:10,000; Jane Johnson). 
Alexa-488-, Alexa-Fluor-594-, or Alexa-Fluor-647-conjugated cor-
responding secondary antibodies from Jackson ImmunoResearch 
were used for indirect fluorescence. Images were taken using a Zeiss 
LSM510 confocal microscope. A <rs type="software">Cell Counter</rs> software plugin in 
the <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> program was used to count cells. Data were obtained 
from 12 random sections from three to five mice in each group. </p>

<p>Electrophysiology </p>

<p>Adult mice were deeply anesthetized and transcardially perfused 
with chilled (4 
C) artificial cerebrospinal fluid (ACSF) (119 mM </p>

<p>NaCl, 2.5 mM KCl, 26 mM NaHCO 3 , 1 mM NaH 2 PO 4 , 11 mM 
D-glucose at pH 7.4, 300 mOsm, and aerated with 95% O 2 /5% 
CO 2 ), including 0.5 mM CaCl 2 , 5 mM MgCl 2 , and 1% kynurenate 
acid. The striatum with overlying neocortex was then dissected 
out. Acute sagittal slices (250 mm thickness) were collected 
between +2 mm and À2 mm from bregma on a Leica VT1200S 
slicer. They were then incubated in aerated ACSF with 3 mM 
CaCl 2 and 2 mM MgCl 2 to recover for 30 min at 35 
C followed </p>

<p>by additional incubation for over 1 hr at room temperature. A 
single slice was then transferred to a submersion chamber and 
perfused at 3 ml/min with aerated ACSF at 30 
C. Lineage-traced </p>

<p>cells in the striatum were identified under visual guidance using 
IR-DIC optics and tdTomato fluorescence. Whole-cell current-
clamp and voltage-clamp recordings were performed using glass 
pipettes ($6-9 MU) filled with intracellular solution (0.2 mM 
EGTA, 130 mM K-gluconate, 6 mM KCl, 3 mM NaCl, 10 mM 
HEPES, 4 mM ATP-Mg, 0.4 mM GTP-Na, and 14 mM phosphocre-
atine-Tris at pH 7.2 and 285 mOsm). Intracellular solution was 
supplemented with 0.5% biocytin (B4261; Sigma) for biocytin 
labeling. All recordings were obtained with a MultiClamp 700B 
amplifier. Currents were filtered at 2 kHz, acquired, and digitized 
at 10 kHz using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Clampex</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">10.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Molecular Devices</rs>). APs were 
recorded in current clamp mode and elicited by a series of current 
injections starting from À160 pA with 20-, 40-, 80-, or 160-pA in-
crements and 800 ms duration. Sodium and potassium currents 
were recorded in voltage-clamp mode in response to a series of 
voltage steps ranging from À60 mV to +60 mV at 10-mV incre-
ments and 100 ms duration. Delayed rectifier potassium currents 
(K d ) were measured 50 ms prior to the end of current step. 
Spontaneous synaptic currents were recorded in voltage-clamp 
mode. In all voltage-clamp recordings, cells were clamped 
at À60 mV or À80 mV, whichever is close to the resting mem-
brane potential of the cell except during the voltage-step proto-
col. In all current-clamp recordings, recordings were made at 
the resting membrane potential or without any current injection. 
Series and input resistance were measured in voltage-clamp mode 
with a 400 ms, À10 mV step from a À60 mV holding potential 
(filtered by 10 kHz, sampled at 50 kHz). Cells were accepted 
only if the series resistance was less than 30 MU and stable 
throughout the experiment. Data analysis was performed in 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">Clampfit</rs><rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">10.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Molecular Devices</rs>). </p>

<p>Stem Cell Reports j Vol. 4 j 780-794 j May 12, 2015 j ª2015 The Authors 791 </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION </p>

<p>Supplemental Information includes four figures and can be found 
with this article online at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.stemcr.2015. 
03.006. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </p>

<p>W.N., T.Z., and C.-L.Z. conceived and designed the experiments. 
W.N. and T.Z. performed the experiments. Y.Z. maintained mouse 
colonies. D.K.S., T.Y.V., R.B., and J.E.J. provided critical reagents 
and comments. W.N., T.Z., and C.-L.Z. analyzed data and prepared 
the manuscript. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank members of the C.-L.Z. laboratory for discussions and re-
agents, Dr. F. Guillemot for sharing the Ascl1 
f/f mice, and Dr. M. </p>

<p>Klymkowsky for SOX3 antibody. C-.L.Z. is a W. W. Caruth, Jr. 
Scholar in Biomedical Research. This work was supported by the 
Welch Foundation Award (I-1724), the Ellison Medical Foundation 
Award (AG-NS-0753-11), Texas Institute for Brain Injury and 
Repair, the Decherd Foundation, and NIH grants (NS070981 and 
NS088095 to C.-L.Z. and NS032817 to J.E.J.). </p>

<p>Received: January 20, 2015 
Revised: March 24, 2015 
Accepted: March 26, 2015 
Published: April 23, 2015 </p>









</text></tei>