<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4188109" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Aims/Introduction: Type 2 diabetes is characterized by progressive deterioration of b-
cell function. Recently, it was suggested that the C-peptide-to-glucose ratio after oral glu-
cose ingestion is a better predictor of b-cell mass than that during fasting. We investi-
gated whether postprandial C-peptide-to-glucose ratio (PCGR) reflects b-cell function, and 
its clinical application for management of type 2 diabetes. 
Materials and Methods: We carried out a two-step retrospective study of 919 Korean 
participants with type 2 diabetes. In the first step, we evaluated the correlation of PCGR 
level with various markers for b-cell function in newly diagnosed and drug-na€ ıve patients 
after a mixed meal test. In the second step, participants with well-controlled diabetes 
(glycated hemoglobin &lt;7%) were divided into four groups according to treatment 
modality (group I: insulin, group II: sulfonylurea and/or dipeptityl peptidase IV inhibitor, 
group III: metformin and/or thiazolidinedione and group IV: diet and exercise group). 
Results: In the first step, PCGR was significantly correlated with various insulin secretory 
indices. Furthermore, PCGR showed better correlation with glycemic indices than homeo-
static model assessment of b-cell function (HOMA-b). In the second step, the PCGR value 
significantly increased according to the following order: group I, II, III, and IV after adjusting 
for age, sex, body mass index and duration of diabetes. The cut-off values of PCGR for 
separating each group were 1.457, 2.870 and 3.790, respectively (P &lt; 0.001). 
Conclusions: We suggest that PCGR might be a useful marker for b-cell function and 
an ancillary parameter in the choice of antidiabetic medication in type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p>1-3 </p>

<p>. It remains controver-
sial to select first-line drugs to treat diabetic patients, even 
though metformin is a preferred first-line drug. In addition, 
there is no consensus to approach the most effective treatment </p>

<p>for an individual patient. Because most patients have already 
experienced substantial loss of b-cell function at the time of 
diagnosis of type 2 diabetes </p>

<p>4,5 </p>

<p>, it is more reasonable to select 
initial antidiabetic medications or modify drugs with consider-
ation for b-cell function of individual patients. 
Type 2 diabetes is characterized by insulin resistance and 
impaired insulin secretion </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>. Although insulin resistance shows lit-
tle variation among patients with type 2 diabetes, pancreatic 
b-cell function declines progressively over time. The United 
Kingdom Prospective Diabetes Study (UKPDS) and the Belfast 
Diet Study have shown that progressive loss of b-cell function is 
a major cause of hyperglycemia and is also related to treatment 
failure of diabetes </p>

<p>7,8 </p>

<p>. In this regard, not only the evaluation of 
secular changes in insulin secretion, but also accurate methods to </p>

<p> †These authors contributed equally as first authors. 
Received 28 June 2013; revised 24 September 2013; accepted 20 October 2013 </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by Asian Association for the Study of Diabetes (AASD) and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd 
J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 5 September 2014 </p>

<p>517 </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License, which permits use, distribution and 
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes. </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E </p>

<p>evaluate b-cell function are important for management of diabe-
tes </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>. C-peptide, which is cleaved from insulin in secretory gran-
ules, is a well-known marker for b-cell function </p>

<p>10,11 </p>

<p>. In contrast 
to other indices for insulin secretion, C-peptide evaluation is able 
to assess b-cell function even in patients undergoing insulin ther-
apy. Recently, it was suggested that the C-peptide-to-glucose ratio 
after oral glucose ingestion might be a better marker for pancre-
atic b-cell mass than fasting measures, such as the homeostatic 
model assessment of b-cell function (HOMA-b) </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>. 
Thus, we investigated the clinical significance of serum post-
prandial C-peptide-to-glucose ratio (PCGR) measurements in 
providing indices for insulin secretion and in discriminating 
treatment modalities for patients with type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients and Study Design 
Patients in the diabetes registry of Severance Diabetes Center 
between June 2009 and April 2011 were investigated in the 
present study. Type 2 diabetic patients aged older than 
20 years were included. The exclusion criteria were severe liver 
or kidney disease, thyroid disorders, pregnancy, glucocorticoid 
therapy, heavy alcoholics and any malignancy including hema-
tological disorders. Our investigation was a retrospective two-
step study. In the first step, we investigated whether PCGR 
showed a significant correlation with indices for insulin secre-
tion function, such as HOMA-b, as well as with indices for 
glycemic control. We analyzed 361 newly diagnosed type 2 dia-
betes patients who were drug-na€ ıve, and had undergone a 
mixed meal test between June 2009 and April 2011. These 
participants included most of the patients described in our pre-
vious study </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>. The test was a standardized liquid meal test 
(Ensure; Meiji Dairies Corporation, Tokyo, Japan; 500 kcal, 
17.5 g fat [31.5%], 68.5 g carbohydrate [54.5%] and 17.5 g pro-
tein [14.0%]) after overnight fasting. Blood samples were 
collected at 0 and 90 min (basal and stimulated levels, respec-
tively) for glucose, insulin and C-peptide analyses. We used 
fasting glucose, postprandial glucose, glycated albumin (GA) 
and HbA1c as the glycemic indices. For the insulin secretory 
indices, we used fasting or postprandial C-peptide (FCP or 
PCP), delta C-peptide (DCP), fasting C-peptide-to-glucose ratio 
(FCGR) or PCGR, insulinogenic index (IGI), index for C-pep-
tide (ICI) and HOMA-b. 
In the second step, we assessed the validity of PCGR as a 
predictor in the choice of antidiabetic therapy. For this, we ana-
lyzed 558 type 2 diabetic patients who achieved target glycemic 
control (HbA1c &lt;7.0%), and had constant antidiabetic medica-
tion for at least 3 months between November 2009 and April 
2011. The patients were analyzed retrospectively and divided 
into four groups according to their treatment modality 
(group I: exogenous insulin, group II: insulin secretagogues 
[sulfonylurea (SU) and/or dipeptidyl dipeptidase IV inhibitor 
(DPPIVi)], group III: insulin sensitizer [metformin (Met) and/ 
or thiazolidinedione (TZD)], and group IV: lifestyle modifica-
tion [diet and exercise (D&amp;E)]), based on the treatments' </p>

<p>strength and differential function on glycemic reduction. We 
first evaluated whether PCGR levels were significantly different 
among the groups. Subsequently, we investigated the cut-off 
values of PCGR for discriminating each medication group. To 
evaluate the validity of the cut-off values of PCGR, a training 
set comprising of randomly selected cases (70% of the partici-
pants) was used to select an optimal cut-off, which was then 
tested on the independent left-out validation set (30% of the 
participants). The blood samples for plasma glucose and C-pep-
tide were obtained after an overnight fasting and 2 h after an 
individually composed breakfast. The study protocol was 
approved by the ethics committee of the Severance Hospital. 
According to the International Conference on Harmonization 
Good Clinical Practice (ICH GCP) guidelines </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>, all information 
was recorded in a manner so that participants could not be 
identified and kept in a locked computer. </p>

<p>Biochemical Test 
Plasma glucose levels were measured using the glucose oxidase 
method and a Hitachi 747 automatic analyzer (Hitachi Instru-
ments Service, Tokyo, Japan). Serum GA levels were measured 
using the enzymatic method and a Hitachi 7699 P module 
autoanalyzer (Hitachi Instruments Service, Tokyo, Japan). 
HbA1c levels were measured by high-performance liquid chro-
matography using a Variant II Turbo (Bio-Rad Laboratories, 
Hercules, CA, USA). Serum insulin and C-peptide levels were 
measured in duplicate by immunoradiometric assay (Beckman 
Coulter, Fullerton, CA, USA). DCP was calculated as (C-peptide 
90 min -C-peptide 0 min). HOMA-b was calculated as fasting 
insulin (lIU/mL) 9 20 / fasting glucose (mmol/L) -3.5. 
The IGI was calculated as (insulin 90 min -insulin 
0 min) / (glucose 90 min -glucose 0 min), while the corre-
sponding 
ICI 
was 
(C-peptide 
90 min -C-peptide 
0 min) / (glucose 90 min -glucose 0 min). FCGR and PCGR 
were calculated as (fasting or postprandial C-peptide level [ng/ 
mL] / fasting or postprandial glucose level [mg/dL] 9 100). </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
Analysis of variance (ANOVA) or analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) 
tests was used to compare variables. All continuous variables 
are shown as the mean -standard deviation except for ANCOVA 
analysis (mean -standard error). To compare the relationship 
among HbA1c, GA and other variables, Pearson's correlation 
coefficients were used to assess the associations between clinical 
and laboratory variables. We analyzed the differences in the 
correlated coefficients between PCGR or HOMA-b and glyce-
mic indices using Steiger's Z-test. The receiver operating char-
acteristic (ROC) curve of PCGR was shown, and the area 
under the curve (AUC) was calculated for separating each med-
ication group. To determine the optimal cut-off value, the point 
on the ROC curve with maximum Youden index (sensitiv-
ity + specificity -1) was calculated. Statistical analyses were 
carried out using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, NC, 
USA). A P-value &lt;0.05 was considered significant. </p>



<p>J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 5 September 2014 
ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
Lee et al. 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Correlations Between Variable Indices of b-Cell Function 
The baseline characteristics of the newly diagnosed type 2 dia-
betic patients are shown in Table 1. From the first step analysis, 
the correlation between PCGR and insulin secretory indices 
widely accepted as predictors for b-cell function was investi-
gated in 361 drug-na€ ıve patients with newly presenting type 2 
diabetes (Table 2). Among these indices, PCP, DCP and PCGR 
showed a significant correlation with previously established 
insulin secretory indices, such as IGI, ICI and HOMA-b. The 
PCGR showed a stronger correlation with HOMA-b 
(r = 0.552, P &lt; 0.001) than PCP and DCP (r = 0.370, 
r = 0.307, respectively, all P &lt; 0.001). Although FCGR had a 
moderately strong correlation (0.6-0.8) with HOMA-b 
(r = 0.705, P &lt; 0.001), FCGR did not have any correlation 
with IGI or ICI. As expected, IGI showed a very strong correla-
tion (at least 0.8) with ICI (r = 0.928, P &lt; 0.001). However, 
neither IGI nor ICI showed any correlation with HOMA-b. A 
partial correlation adjusted for age, sex and body mass index 
(BMI) showed similar results among various insulin secretory 
indices. </p>

<p>Correlations of PCGR and HOMA-b with Glycemic Indices 
During the first step analysis to find an effective insulin secre-
tory index predicting well-controlled glycemia, we compared 
the correlations of indices for insulin secretion, such as 
PCGR or HOMA-b, with various glycemic indices, such as fast-
ing and postprandial glucose, glycated albumin and HbA1c. </p>

<p>Overall, both indices showed a good correlation with glycemic 
indices (Figure 1). Although PCGR was calculated using post-
prandial indices, including C-peptide and glucose level, PCGR 
(r = -0.558, P &lt; 0.001) showed a strong correlation with fast-
ing glucose levels, which was shown in HOMA-b (r = -0.587, 
P &lt; 0.001). Additionally, PCGR showed significantly stronger 
correlations with GA and HbA1c (r = -0.602 with GA and 
r = -0.591 with HbA1c, all P &lt; 0.001) than HOMA-b did 
(r = -0.521 with GA, and r = -0.471 with HbA1c, all 
P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Clinical Characteristics of Participants According to 
Antidiabetic Medications 
In the second step analysis, we hypothesized that the patients 
who had achieved target glycemic control (HbA1c &lt;7%) might 
have received appropriate antidiabetic therapy according to 
their b-cell secretory function. To investigate whether PCGR 
can differentiate treatment modalities in type 2 diabetes, we 
analyzed 558 patients with type 2 diabetes under good glycemic 
control (HbA1c &lt;7%). Table 3 shows the significantly different 
fasting and postprandial glucose levels among groups that were 
divided according to treatment modalities. As expected, the 
insulin-treated group I showed lower C-peptide level (both 
FCP and PCP) and longer duration of disease than the other 
medication groups. In contrast to FCGR level, mean PCGR lev-
els were significantly different among groups, and decreased 
according to the following order: group IV (D&amp;E), group III 
(Met/TZD), group II (SU/DPPIVi) and group I (insulin; 
Table 3 and Figure 2). The different PCGR levels among 
groups were still significant after adjusting for age, sex, BMI 
and duration of disease (Figure 2). </p>

<p>Cut-off Values of PCGR for Discriminating Antidiabetic 
Medication groups 
We hypothesized that different types of treatment modalities 
could be differentiated by PCGR levels in patients with good 
glycemic control, and determined the cut-off values of PCGR 
for distinguishing between treatment modalities, such as 
SU/DPPIVi, Met/TZD and D&amp;E. From the training set (70% 
of the participants), the PCGR cut-off value for discriminating 
between group I (insulin) and group II (SU/DPPIVi) was 1.457 
(AUC 0.763, 95% confidence interval [CI] 0.67-0.86) with 
92.6% sensitivity and 60.0% specificity; between group II (SU/ 
DPPIVi) and group III (Met/TZD) was 2.870 (AUC 0.634, 
95% CI 0.58-0.69) with 75.5% sensitivity and 51.4% specificity; 
between group III (Met/TZD) and group IV (D&amp;E) was 3.790 
(AUC 0.593, 95% CI 0.53-0.66) with 69.5% sensitivity and 
49.1% specificity (Figure 3 and Supplementary Table 1). In the 
validation set (the remaining 30% of the participants), the sen-
sitivity and specificity of PCGR cut-off value were 81.0% and 
41.7% between group I (insulin) and group II (SU/DPPIVi), 
73.9% and 44.4% between group II (SU/DPPIVi) and group III 
(Met/TZD), and 70.5% and 52.2% between group III (Met/ 
TZD) and group IV (D&amp;E), respectively. </p>

<p>Table 1 | Characteristics of 361 newly diagnosed, drug-n€ aive type 2 
diabetic patients </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>Male:female 
140:221 
Age (years) 
55.3 -11.0 
BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
2 5 . 2 4 -3.39 
HbA1c (%) 
7.3 -1.8 
Glycated albumin (%) 
17.8 -7.3 
FPG (mg/dL) 
127.3 -42.4 
PPG (mg/dL) 
197.1 -86.5 
FCP (ng/mL) 
2.23 -0.82 
PCP (ng/mL) 
6.78 -3.11 
DCP 
4.57 -2.88 
FCGR 
1.86 -0.75 
PCGR 
3.99 -2.14 
IGI 
1.14 -3.16 
ICI 
0.11 -0.31 
HOMA-b 
59.35 -31.82 </p>

<p>DCP, postprandial C-peptide; BMI, body mass index; FCGR, fasting 
C-peptide-to-glucose ratio; FCP, fasting C-peptide; FPG, fasting plasma 
glucose; HbA1c, glycated hemoglobin; HOMA-b, homeostasis model 
assessment of b-cell function; ICI, C-peptide-genic index; IGI, insulino-
genic index; PCGR, postprandial C-peptide-to-glucose ratio; PCP, post-
prandial C-peptide; PPG, postprandial plasma glucose. </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd 
J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 5 September 2014 </p>



<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi 
Postprandial C-peptide to glucose ratio </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Insulin resistance is observed in more than 80% of type 2 dia-
betes patients with little variation </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>. In contrast, pancreatic b-
cell mass decreases progressively during the course of diabetes, 
which results in significantly decreased insulin secretory capac-
ity </p>

<p>7,15,16 </p>

<p>. Because glucose control in diabetes is closely associated 
with pancreatic b-cell mass, it is important to identify predic-
tors of pancreatic b-cell function in patients with type 2 diabe-
tes. In Asian populations, inadequate b-cell response to 
increasing insulin resistance is considered as the cause of loss 
of glycemic control and increased risk of diabetes, even with </p>

<p>relatively little weight gain </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>. For this reason, the typical charac-
teristic of Korean patients with type 2 diabetes in the develop-
ment and aggravation of hyperglycemia is secretory b-cell 
dysfunction </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>. The oral glucose tolerance test and HOMA indi-
ces have been commonly applied as functional tests for insulin 
secretion </p>

<p>19,20 </p>

<p>. However, the interpretation of insulin concentra-
tions is complicated, because insulin levels should be not only 
matched with glucose concentrations, but also borne in mind 
in the situation of insulin use. Although HOMA is often used 
in large clinical and epidemiological studies, it is not suitable 
for some diabetic patients because of hyperglycemic state or </p>

<p>Table 2 | Correlation between postprandial C-peptide-to-glucose ratio and insulin secretory indices </p>

<p>FCP 
PCP 
DCP 
FCGR 
PCGR 
IGI 
ICI 
HOMA-b </p>

<p>FCP 
-
0.419** 
0.169* 
0.788** 
0.198** 
0.085 
0.037 
0.319** 
PCP 
-
0.967** 
0.506** 
0.732** 
0.218** 
0.180** 
0.370** 
DCP 
-
0.313** 
0.742** 
0.212** 
0.181** 
0.307** 
FCGR 
-
0.538** 
0.103 
0.080 
0.705** 
PCGR 
-
0.277** 
0.256** 
0.552** 
IGI 
-
0.928** 
0.082 
ICI 
-
0.094 
HOMA-b 
-
FCP † 
-
0.392** 
0.155* 
0.757** 
0.196** 
0.047 
0.014 
0.280** 
PCP † 
-
0.970** 
0.489** 
0.738** 
0.212** 
0.171* 
0.357** 
DCP † 
-
0.324** 
0.740** 
0.215** 
0.180* 
0.309** 
FCGR † 
-
0.557** 
0.075 
0.062 
0.706** 
PCGR † 
-
0.276** 
0.256** 
0.561** 
IGI † 
-
0.929** 
0.064 
ICI † 
-
0.085 
HOMA-b † 
-</p>

<p>*P &lt; 0.01, **P &lt; 0.001, derived from Pearson's correlation.  †Pearson's partial correlation adjusted for age, sex and body mass index. DCP, postpran-
dial C-peptide; FCGR, fasting C-peptide-to-glucose ratio; FCP, fasting C-peptide; HOMA-b, homeostasis model assessment of b-cell function; ICI, 
C-peptide-genic index; IGI, insulinogenic index; PCGR, postprandial C-peptide-to-glucose ratio; PCP, postprandial C-peptide. </p>

<p>HOMA-B </p>

<p>PCGR </p>

<p>250 
=-0.587 
P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>=-0.558 
P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>=-0.587 
P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>=-0.602 
P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>=-0.591 
P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>=-0.497 
P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>=-0.521 
P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>=-0.471 
P&lt;0.001 
200 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
12.0 
10.0 </p>

<p>8.0 
6.0 
4.0 
2.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>50 100150 </p>

<p>Fasting glucose 
Postprandial glucose 
Glycated albumin 
HbA1c </p>

<p>200 
200 
100 
300 
250 </p>

<p>4005006000 10 20 30 40 50 5.0 7.5 10.0 12.515.0 </p>

<p>300350 0 </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Correlations between postprandial C-peptide-to-glucose ratio (PCGR) or homeostatic model assessment of b-cell function (HOMA-b) and 
glycemic indices. HbA1c, glycated hemoglobin. </p>



<p>J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 5 September 2014 
ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
Lee et al. 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi </p>

<p>insulin use. In addition, a recent study measuring b-cell area in 
humans showed that there was no relationship between 
HOMA-b and b-cell area </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>. 
Postprandial insulin deficiency is regarded as the main 
explanatory factor of deteriorating glucose control in newly 
developed type 2 diabetes </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>. A study showed that the reduc-
tion of postprandial insulin secretion is more prominent than 
that of fasting insulin secretion in the progression of type 2 
diabetes </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>. It was thus suggested that postprandial b-cell func-
tion might be a more important factor for glycemic control 
than fasting b-cell function. Although there are many studies 
on indices for insulin secretory function, only a few studies 
have investigated staged management of type 2 diabetes based 
on insulin secretory function using these indices. Furthermore, 
the studies were only able to distinguish which patients 
require insulin therapy based on the indices </p>

<p>23,24 </p>

<p>. Recently, 
PCGR after oral glucose ingestion was suggested to be a bet-
ter predictor for the b-cell area, the region responsible for b-
cell function, than fasting measures </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>. Therefore, we used a 
new, expanded practical index, PCGR, for assessing insulin 
secretion as part of a new therapeutic strategy for individu-
alized treatment for type 2 diabetes. To precisely analyze 
the relationship between endogenous insulin secretion and 
the various markers, we carried out a standardized mixed 
meal test in newly diagnosed, drug-na€ ıve type 2 diabetic 
patients. PCGR values were correlated with other insulin 
secretory indices, such as HOMA-b, IGI and ICI (Table 2). 
Additionally, PCGR showed a strong correlation with glyce-
mic indices including plasma glucose level and glycated 
index for glycemic control (HbA1c and GA) than HOMA-
b (Figure 1). These results suggest that PCGR might be 
used as an index for insulin secretion in practical fields. In 
addition, PCGR is easily calculated using postprandial </p>

<p>C-peptide and glucose levels measured at the time of diag-
nosis for type 2 diabetic patients. 
In the present study, we categorized diabetic patients with 
good glycemic control based on their maintained antidiabetic 
medication. As shown in Figure 2, PCGR levels after adjusting 
for age, sex, BMI and duration of disease were different accord-
ing to the medication group (2.27 -0.28, 3.32 -0.11, 
3.89 -0.13, 4.53 -0.14 for group I (insulin), group II (SU/ 
DPPIVi), group III (Met/TZD) and group IV (D&amp;E), respec-
tively, P &lt; 0.001 for ANCOVA). We also obtained the cut-off 
values of PCGR to distinguish each treatment group in patients 
with well-controlled glycemic level from the training set and ver-
ified that in the validation set. From the analysis of the training 
set, the cut-off values of PCGR for discriminating between 
treatment groups were 1.457, 2.870 and 3.790, respectively (all 
P &lt; 0.001; Figure 3). In the validation set, the sensitivity of the 
PCGR cut-off value was maintained as relatively constant, 
although the specificity of that was low. We suggest that these 
cut-off values could be applied when choosing antidiabetic 
agents for patients with type 2 diabetes. In accordance with the 
present results, recent studies have shown that PCGR is also a 
better predictor of future insulin therapy than fasting C-peptide 
index </p>

<p>25,26 </p>

<p>. PCGR is a simple and practical marker for insulin 
secretion, and it can be helpful in determining appropriate 
treatment modalities, such as insulin, insulin secretagogues (SU 
and/or DPPIVi), insulin sensitizer (Met and/or TZD) and life-
style modification. As plasma glucose is the most potent stimu-
lator of insulin secretion, it is presumed that PCGR level 
reflects b-cell function more precisely than FCGR or plasma C-
peptide level itself does. Furthermore, insulin secretion is more 
impaired in the postprandial state than in the fasting state </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>, 
and it is stimulated by high plasma glucose level and incretin 
hormone </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>. Thus, PCGR index might be a more useful </p>

<p>Table 3 | Characteristics of 558 patients with well controlled glycemia according to medication groups </p>

<p>Group I (Insulin) 
Group II (SU/DPPIVi) 
Group III (Met/TZD) 
Group IV (D&amp;E) 
P-value † </p>

<p>n 
42 
211 
156 
149 
Male : female 
32:10 
105:106* 
86:70* 
86:63* 
0.016 
Age (years) 
60.0 -13.5 
65.7 -9.8* 
63.0 -10.2 § 
58.5 -10.3 §-
&lt;0.001 
BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
2 3 . 2 2-2.90 
24.37 -2.94* 
24.91 -3.03* 
24.21 -3.37 
0.021 
Duration 
8.8 -1.5 
7.2 -0.6* 
6.4 -0.5* § 
4.1 -0.3* §-
&lt;0.001 
HbA1c (%) 
8.02 -2.05 
7.12 -1.46* 
6.73 -0.86* § 
6.17 -0.48* §-
&lt;0.001 
HbA1c (%) ‡ 
6.5 -0.4 
6.4 -0.4 
6.5 -0.3 
6.3 -0.4* §-
&lt;0.001 
FPG (mg/dL) 
140.8 -69.1 
128.4 -38.7* 
119.5 -25.0* § 
112.6 -18.8* § 
&lt;0.001 
PPG (mg/dL) 
238.6 -116.2 
209.5 -69.7* 
174.1 -49.0* § 
154.1 -47.1* §-
&lt;0.001 
FCP (ng/mL) 
1.34 -1.23 
2.17 -0.93* 
2.20 -1.14* 
2.06 -0.83* 
&lt;0.001 
PCP (ng/mL) 
3.32 -1.99 
6.03 -2.62* 
6.75 -2.69* § 
6.91 -2.45* § 
&lt;0.001 
FCGR 
1.12 -1.27 
1.82 -0.92* 
1.94 -1.32* 
1.85 -0.77* 
&lt;0.001 
PCGR 
1.63 -1.25 
3.17 -1.61* 
4.05 -1.61* § 
4.71 -1.67* §-
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>*P &lt; 0.05 vs insulin group.  †P-values by v </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-test or ANOVA are provided for the four-group comparisons.  ‡Glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c) when 
achieved target glycemic control (HbA1c &lt;7%).  §P &lt; 0.05 vs sulfonylurea/dipeptidyl peptidase IV inhibitor (SU/DPPIVi) group, -P &lt; 0.05 vs metfor-
min/thiazolidinedione (Met/TZD) group. CGR, fasting C-peptide-to-glucose ratio; D&amp;E, diet and exercise; F/U, follow up; FCP, fasting C-peptide; FPG, 
fasting plasma glucose; PCGR, postprandial C-peptide-to-glucose ratio; PCP, postprandial C-peptide; PPG, postprandial plasma glucose. </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd 
J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 5 September 2014 </p>



<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi 
Postprandial C-peptide to glucose ratio </p>

<p>predictor of b-cell function than other indices measured during 
the fasting state. 
The limitations of the present study were as follows. First, 
the study was based on retrospective analysis. Based on the 
results from the present study, a prospective study is in 
progress. Second, we did not examine glucagon-stimulated 
C-peptide levels, which is one of the most widely used meth-
ods for insulin secretory functions of diabetic patients </p>

<p>28,29 </p>

<p>. In 
addition, the C-peptide levels could have been influenced or 
modified by the medications in the second step analysis. For 
instance, prolonged treatment with sulfonylurea could have 
reduced C-peptide, whereas prolonged treatment with TZD 
could have increased b-cell mass. For this reason, a prospec-
tive study of drug-na€ ıve patients is in progress, based on 
PCGR value. Third, we did not include meglitinide in the 
present study, although we suggest the use of similar cut-off 
values of PCGR as in group II (SU/DPPIVi), especially for 
patients with high postprandial glucose. Fourth, we could not </p>

<p>separately assess the additional effects of insulin sensitizer 
(Met or TZD) in group I (insulin) or group II (SU/DPPIVi), 
although 76.4% of patients in the present study had already 
been treated with additional insulin sensitizers, such as Met 
or TZD. Finally, the different cut-off values of PCGR should 
be investigated in different ethnic populations. Despite these 
limitations, we were able to differentiate treatment modalities 
of well-controlled type 2 diabetic patients with PCGR, and 
this value can be a useful marker in the determination of 
antidiabetic therapy. 
In conclusion, the PCGR index might be used as a marker of 
insulin secretion and be used as an ancillary parameter for select-
ing antidiabetic medication, as well as insulin therapy in type 2 
diabetic patients, based on their individual b-cell functions. 
Further prospective study will be warranted to assess the useful-
ness of the PCGR index for staged diabetic management. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS 
The authors report no conflicts of interest. The authors alone 
are responsible for the content and writing of the paper. We 
are very grateful to Hye Sun Lee and Myo Jeong Kim from the 
Biostatistics Collaboration Unit, Yonsei University College of </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* † </p>

<p>* † </p>

<p>* † ‡ </p>

<p>* † ‡ </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>PCGR </p>

<p>PCGR </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 
Insulin 
SU/DPPIVi 
Met/TZD 
D&amp;E </p>

<p>Insulin 
SU/DPPIVi 
Met/TZD 
D&amp;E </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Mean postprandial C-peptide-to-glucose ratio (PCGR) levels 
in the patients according to medication groups (a) before and (b) after 
adjusting for age, body mass index, and duration of diabetes. *P &lt; 0.05 
vs insulin group;  †P &lt; 0.05 vs sulfonylurea/dipeptidyl peptidase IV 
inhibitor (SU/DPPIVi) group;  ‡P &lt; 0.05 vs metformin/thiazolidinedione 
(Met/TZD) group. D&amp;E, diet and exercise. </p>

<p>Sensitivity </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>Insulin vs.SU/DPPIVi 
SU/DPPIVi vs. Met/TZD 
Met/TZD vs. D&amp;E </p>

<p>0.8 
1.0 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>1-Specificity </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves of 
postprandial C-peptide-to-glucose ratio (PCGR) for classifying each 
medication group. Area under the curve (AUC) of 0.763 (95% 
confidence interval [CI] 0.671-0.855) for group I (insulin) vs group II 
(sulfonylurea/dipeptidyl peptidase IV inhibitor [SU/DPPIVi]), 0.634 (95% 
CI 0.577-0.691) for group II (SU/DPPIVi) vs group III (metformin/ 
thiazolidinedione [Met/TZD]) and 0.593 (95% CI 0.529-0.658) for 
group III (Met/TZD) vs group IV (diet and exercise [D&amp;E]). The cut-off 
values of PCGR were 1.457 with 92.6% sensitivity and 60.0% specificity 
for group I (insulin) vs group II (SU/DPPIVi), 2.870 with 75.5% sensitivity 
and 51.4% specificity for group II (SU/DPPIVi) vs group III (Met/TZD), 
and 3.790 with 69.5% sensitivity and 49.1% specificity for group III (Met/ 
TZD) vs group IV (D&amp;E). </p>



<p>J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 5 September 2014 
ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
Lee et al. 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi </p>

<p>Medicine for providing statistical support to the analysis of data 
for this research. </p>





<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi 
Postprandial C-peptide to glucose ratio </p>

<p>29. Scheen AJ, Castillo MJ, Lef ebvre PJ. Assessment of residual 
insulin secretion in diabetic patients using the intravenous </p>

<p>glucagon stimulatory test: methodological aspects and 
clinical applications. Diabetes Metab 1996; 22: 397-406. </p>

<p>SUPPORTING INFORMATION 
Additional Supporting Information may be found in the online version of this article: </p>

<p>Appendix S1 | Cut-off values of postprandial C-peptide-to-glucose ratio (PCGR) for discriminating each medication group in the 
training (randomly selected 70% of the participants) and validation (the remaining 30% of the participants) set. </p>



<p>J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 5 September 2014 
ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
Lee et al. 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi </p>

</text></tei>