<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4938145" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: A thorough understanding of interactions occurring at the interface between </p>

<p>nanocarriers and biological systems is crucial to predict and interpret their biodistribution, 
targeting, and efficacy, and thus design more effective drug delivery systems. Upon intravenous 
injection, nanoparticles are coated by a protein corona (PC). This confers a new biological 
identity on the particles that largely determines their biological fate. Liposomes have great 
pharmaceutical versatility, so, as proof of concept, their PC has recently been implicated in the 
mechanism and efficiency of their internalization into the cell. In an attempt to better understand 
the interactions between nanocarriers and biological systems, we analyzed the plasma proteins 
adsorbed on the surface of multicomponent liposomes. Specifically, we analyzed the physical 
properties and ultrastructure of liposome/PC complexes and the aggregation process that occurs 
when liposomes are dispersed in plasma. The results of combined confocal microscopy and 
flow cytometry experiments demonstrated that the PC favors liposome internalization by both 
macrophages and tumor cells. This work provides insights into the effects of the PC on liposomes' 
physical properties and, consequently, liposome-liposome and liposome-cell interactions. 
In the last few decades, nanoparticle (NP)-based delivery platforms have improved the 
therapeutic index of many drugs. In fact, by increasing their pharmaceutical bioavail-
ability and targeting, NPs avoid systemic toxicity while retaining pharmacological 
activity. 1 After intravenous injection, NPs adsorb a multitude of biological molecules 
(proteins, lipids, glycans, and metabolites) from plasma on their surface. These 
biomole cules continuously recycle 2,3 on the NP surface, thereby forming a dynamic 
shell known as a "biomolecular corona." 4 Most research studying the biomolecular 
corona has focused on protein composition characterization: 5,6 therefore, the biomo-
lecular corona is generally called the "protein corona" (PC). 7,8 This natural coating 
provides NPs with a new biological identity and significantly affects their fate, phar-
macokinetics, and cellular interactions. 
In terms of NP targeting abilities, the PC can 1) hinder the function of targeting 
ligands attached to the NP surface, thereby reducing their accumulation in the targeted 
tissue, 3,9,10 and 2) modify the carrier surface, facilitating cell internalization. 11 The PC 
can also modulate immune response. 12 Several studies have characterized PC structure, 
function, and formation dynamics. 13,14 Structurally, proteins that are weakly bound to 
the NP surface form the "soft corona," while proteins strongly bound to the NP surface 
form the "hard corona." 15,16 Functionally, the PC is characterized by the presence of 
opsonins (complement proteins), immunoglobulins, and lectins, 17 which match to </p>

<p>correspondence: ennio Tasciotti; 
claudia corbo 
center for Biomimetic Medicine, 
houston Methodist research Institute, 
6670 Bertner avenue, houston, 
TX 77030, Usa 
Tel +1 713 441 7319; +1 713 363 9763 
email etasciotti@houstonmethodist.org; 
corbo@ceinge.unina.it </p>

<p>Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of Nanomedicine 
4 July 2016 </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3050 </p>

<p>corbo et al </p>

<p>specific receptors on leukocyte membranes. Until recently, 
NP opsonization was considered part of the body's defense 
mechanism by inducing NP clearance from circulation and 
consequent accumulation in the organs of the mononuclear 
phagocytic system (mainly spleen and liver). 18 However, in 
a recent study, unfolded proteins that promote macrophage 
uptake or their shielding by other proteins in the PC were 
found to reduce in vitro particle uptake by RAW264.7 
macrophages. 19,20 The particular context, therefore, needs to 
be discussed when considering cellular uptake. Although the 
biological identity of NPs largely determines their biologi-
cal fate, their physical identity (ie, shape, size, and surface 
charge) strictly regulates NP-cell interactions. Indeed, large 
NPs (.300 nm) with a higher positive or negative surface 
charge (, -15 mV or . +15 mV) exhibited increased mac-
rophage uptake, in vitro and in vivo. 21,22 
The scope of this work was to shed light on the interactions 
occurring at the interface between nanocarriers and biological 
systems. To this aim, we evaluated liposomes as proof-of-
concept NPs, given their widespread use in the pharmaceuti-
cal field and their high versatility. While most research into 
the PC has studied inorganic NPs, only recently the PC of 
liposomes is emerging as a fundamental entity regulating the 
interactions of liposomes with living systems. 23 The PC is 
believed to have a potentially key impact on targeted delivery 
in nanomedicine, as it could be manipulated by using different 
liposomal formulations. Herein, we selected multicomponent 
choline-based liposomes as a model system to study the PC's 
effects in targeted drug delivery applications. 24 We studied 
the correlation between the biological and physical identity 
of liposomes. To investigate the physical changes occurring 
in liposomes after PC formation, we characterized NP-PC 
complexes and used proteomics to analyze the PC composi-
tion. Lastly, in an attempt to reproduce the environment sur-
rounding NPs upon systemic injection, we investigated the 
interactions between liposome-PC complexes and two cell 
lines in vitro. We studied the impact of the PC composition 
on liposome uptake by the main cell population responsible 
for clearance of foreign materials (macrophages J774 cells) 
and by cancer cells (breast cancer 4T1 cells). </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
liposome assembly </p>

<p>Liposomes were prepared with the thin-layer evaporation 
method. Briefly, dipalmitoylphosphatidylcholine, dio-
leoylphosphatidylcholine, and cholesterol (Avanti Polar 
Lipids, Alabaster, AL, USA) in 6:3:1 molar ratio were dis-
solved in chloroform/methanol (3:1, v/v). This choline-based 
lipid composition provides safe and not immunogenic </p>

<p>liposomes, relevant for drug delivery application. 25 This 
allowed us to study the formation of the PC focusing on 
the physical identity of the particles, reducing the effects of 
secondary factors due to the intrinsic immunogenic features 
of liposome components. A thin lipid film was prepared with 
a rotary evaporator (BUCHI Labortechnik AG, Flawil, Swit-
zerland). The film was then hydrated with ultrapure distilled 
water to obtain a lipid concentration of 20 mM. Liposomes 
were extruded through 200-nm pore cellulose acetate mem-
branes (Whatman, Schleicher &amp; Schuell, Maidstone, UK) 
at 45°C. The unilamellar liposomes obtained were stored 
at 4°C until use. The same procedure was used to assemble 
rhodamine-labeled liposomes for cellular uptake studies. 
For those particles, Rhod-DOPE was also added to the lipid 
mixture; the entire procedure was performed in the dark. </p>

<p>Plasma collection </p>

<p>The study was conducted according to the Guide for the 
Care and Use of Laboratory Animals and was approved by 
the Houston Methodist Institutional Animal Care and Use 
Committee. An aseptic technique was used to withdraw blood 
from healthy BALB/C mice (Charles River Laboratories 
International, Inc., Wilmington, MA, USA) when they were 
sedated. Within 30 minutes after collection, using 50 mM 
ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid as an anticoagulant, plasma 
was isolated by centrifugation for 15 minutes at 1,000× g. 
Plasma was aliquoted and stored at -80°C until use. When 
required, aliquots were thawed at 4°C and then centrifuged 
at room temperature for 5 minutes at 15,000× g to eliminate 
protein aggregates. The blood volume withdrawn from 
the mice was calculated according to the Lee and Blaufox 
equation: </p>

<p>BV 
BW 
= 
× 
+ 
0 06 
077 
. 
. 
(1) </p>

<p>where BV is the blood volume (mL) and BW is the body 
weight (g), and the plasma volume is BV/2. 26 </p>

<p>Formation of liposome-Pc complexes </p>

<p>Liposome-PC complexes were obtained by incubating NPs 
with plasma. Liposome formulation was diluted 20 times 
(1 mM final lipid concentration) with ultrapure water and 
then incubated in plasma at 1:1 liposome/plasma ratio (v/v) in 
order to mimic the protein concentration in vivo (50% plasma 
in blood). 27 The incubation was done in murine plasma for 
1 hour at 37°C under continuous agitation. The liposome-PC 
complexes were recovered after 10 minutes centrifugation 
at 15,000× g, and then washed three times in cold phosphate 
buffered saline to remove unbound proteins. We conducted a </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3051 </p>

<p>liposomes and protein corona </p>

<p>Bradford assay (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA) 
on the washing solution to ensure that no additional proteins 
were eluted from the liposomes. The tubes were changed after 
each washing step to minimize contamination with plasma 
proteins bound to the tubes. A plasma aliquot not incubated 
with liposomes was subjected to the same procedure, as a 
control, to verify the absence of protein precipitation. All 
experiments were performed in triplicate. </p>

<p>size and zeta potential experiment </p>

<p>A <rs id="software-0" type="software">Multisizer 4 Coulter counter</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Beckman Coulter Inc., Miami, FL, USA</rs>) and <rs type="software">ZetaSizer Nano ZS</rs> (Malvern Instru-
ments, Malvern, UK) were employed to measure the size 
and the zeta potential, respectively. Samples were diluted 
50× with distilled water at 25°C. The results are presented 
as the average of five measurements. </p>

<p>cryo-electron microscopy analysis </p>

<p>Lipid vesicles were plunge-frozen on holey film grids 
(R2x2 Quantifoil ® ; Micro Tools GmbH, Jena, Germany). 
A 626 cryo-specimen holder (Gatan, Inc., Pleasanton, CA) 
was used for imaging. Data were collected on a JEOL 
2100 electron microscope (JEOL Ltd., Tokyo, Japan). 
Images were recorded under low electron dose conditions 
(5-20 electrons/Å 2 ) using a 4,096×4,096 pixel CCD camera 
(UltraScan 895, GATAN, Inc., Pleasanton, CA, USA) at a 
nominal magnification of 20,000×. </p>

<p>atomic force microscopy </p>

<p>Atomic force microscopy (AFM) images of the liposome 
and the liposome-PC complex were collected in the Scan 
Asyst ® mode on a Multimode (Bruker Corporation, Santa 
Barbara, CA, USA) microscope using single-beam silicon 
cantilever probes (Bruker MLCT at a resonance frequency of 
10 kHz, a nominal tip curvature radius of 10 nm, and a force 
constant of 0.04 N/m). All measurements were subjected to 
first-order flattening. Particle size was calculated using the 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">Nanoscope 6.13R1</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Digital Instruments, NY, USA</rs>). 
Mean values from 40 random particles in three independent 
experiments are reported. Quantitative AFM force mapping 
analysis was performed to evaluate the relative elasticity of 
particles in order to obtain a complete elastic property map 
of heterogeneous samples. We prepared samples by coating 
the mica surface sample holder with 0.1% (3-Aminopropyl) 
triethoxysilane (APTES) to stabilize the NPs (to prevent 
their collapse on the mica surface), and then performed 
the AFM analysis. Young's modulus was calculated for six 
different samples corresponding to 512×512 force-separation 
curves obtained over a 10×10 μm area. Young's modulus </p>

<p>was calculated using the following equation, as reported 
elsewhere: 28 </p>

<p>F F 
E 
R d d 
− 
= 
− </p>

<p>adh </p>

<p>4 3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>/ * ( 
) 
(2) </p>

<p>where F -F adh is the force on the cantilever relative to the 
adhesion force, R is the tip end radius, d -d 0 is the deforma-
tion of the sample and E* is the reduced modulus. </p>

<p>Protein separation by one-dimensional 
gel electrophoresis and in situ digestion </p>

<p>Proteins adsorbed on the liposomes were separated by one-
dimensional sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel 
electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) and stained by Coomassie 
Brilliant Blue (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, 
USA). Plasma proteins on the surface of liposomes were 
quantified by densitometric analysis with the <rs id="software-7" type="software">ImageJ</rs> software 
<rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-number">Version 1.45</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-7" type="url">imagej.en.softonic.com/</rs>/). The most abundant 
protein bands were cut and treated as previously described. 29,30 
Briefly, each band was de-stained by washing in acetonitrile 
and 50 mM ammonium bicarbonate. Then, cysteine residues 
of the proteins were reduced in 10 mM dithiothreitol for 1 hour 
at 57°C, and alkylated with 55 mM iodoacetamide for 45 min-
utes at room temperature in the dark. Proteins were in situ 
digested using Porcine Trypsin Sequencing Grade (Promega 
Corporation, Fitchburg, WI, USA) overnight at 37°C at an 
enzyme/substrate ratio of 1:50. The next day, the supernatant 
was collected and larger peptides were extracted by adding 
acetonitrile to the bands. Enzyme activity was stopped by add-
ing 0.5% trifluoroacetic acid. Peptides were recovered from 
the supernatant after centrifugation at 18,000× g for 10 min-
utes. The resulting peptides were extracted and identified by 
liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry. </p>

<p>Mass spectrometry and 
identification of proteins </p>

<p>We used a NanoAcquity UPLC system (Waters Corporation, 
Milford, MA, USA) coupled inline with a Synapt HDMS 
(G1) mass spectrometer with an electrospray source to 
analyze proteins. The liquid chromatography system con-
sisted of a 180 μm ×20 mm Symmetry C18 (5 μm particle) 
trapping column, and a 75 μm ×250 mm BEH130 C18 
(1.7 μm particle) analytical column. The peptide mixture was 
resolved as previously described. 31 <rs id="software-2" type="software">The ProteinLynx Global 
Server</rs> (PLGS <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">v2.4</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Waters Corporation</rs>) was used to identify 
proteins. The Uniprot 2013_03 ("reviewed") mouse proteome 
(16,614 entries) served as the target database. Only proteins 
with a minimum of two peptides, 95% confidence interval, 
precursor ion mass error tolerance #5 ppm, and fragment </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3052 </p>

<p>corbo et al </p>

<p>ion mass tolerance #15 ppm were considered. The following 
criteria were used in the database search strategy: one trypsin 
missed cleavage was also allowed, together with oxidation 
of methionines as variable modification. The only allowed 
fixed modification was, instead, the carbamidomethylation 
of cysteines. Quantitative values were normalized using 
100 fmol/sample of yeast alcohol dehydrogenase as internal 
standard and analyzed with the Identity E algorithm. 32 </p>

<p>cell culture </p>

<p>The J774 mouse macrophage cell line (ATCC ® TIB-67™) 
and the 4T1 mouse mammary tumor cell line (ATCC ® 
CRL2539™) were used. Cells were cultured using Dulbecco's 
Modified Eagle's Medium containing 10% (v/v) fetal bovine 
serum and 1% (v/v) penicillin/streptomycin solution. They 
were maintained in humidified incubators under 5% CO 2 , at 
37°C and passaged at 70%-80% of confluence. </p>

<p>Flow cytometry </p>

<p>To evaluate cellular uptake of liposomes by flow cyto metry, 
200,000 cells/well were seeded in a twelve-well tissue cul-
ture plate. After 24 hours of cell culture expansion, cells 
were incubated in serum-free conditions with 0.15 mM of 
rhodamine-labeled bare liposomes and rhodamine-labeled 
liposome-PC complexes. Incubation occurred for 3 hours at 
37°C. After treatment, the cells were washed with phosphate 
buffered saline, harvested using trypsin, and centrifuged for 
10 minutes at 1,500 rpm. A solution of trypan blue (0.01%) 
was added to the tubes before acquisition to quench the 
surface fluorescence. 33 The analysis was performed using 
a Becton Dickinson LSR II instrument equipped with <rs type="software">Diva</rs> 
software. Each sample was evaluated with 10,000 events. 
Untreated cells were used as controls. Results are presented 
as averages of three independent experiments. </p>

<p>Confocal fluorescence microscopy </p>

<p>Cells were seeded onto an eight-well chamber slide (10,000 
cells/well) and treated with the particles as described earlier. 
At the end of the experiment, cells were thoroughly washed 
and fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde solution. Nuclei were 
stained using DAPI (blue), and cell membranes were stained 
using WGA-AlexaFluor 488 conjugate (green). Slides were 
imaged using a Nikon A1 confocal imaging system and 
analyzed via NIS Elements AR. Images are presented as a 
maximum projection or as a 3D side projection of a chosen 
z section. For statistical analysis, images (n=3) were acquired 
for each sample at five different areas. For each micrograph, 
the area fraction for the particles signal (red) was calculated </p>

<p>and divided by the number of nuclei counted (blue). All 
results are presented as mean ± SD in a graph of area fraction/ 
cell in the different treatments. </p>

<p>Results and discussion 
characterization of liposomes before and 
after Pc formation </p>

<p>Liposomes were incubated in plasma for 1 hour to allow 
liposome-PC complex formation. This incubation time was 
chosen because it is known that a stable PC forms over a 
period of 1 hour. 34 Moreover, previous studies reported that 
1 hour is the liposomes' saturation point in terms of proteins 
adsorbed during incubation in plasma. 35 
Samples were analyzed before and after incubation in 
plasma by dynamic light scattering (DLS), zeta potential, 
and cryo-electron microscopy analyses to investigate their 
size (and size homogeneity: polydispersity index, PDI), their 
surface charge, and their structure, respectively. Control 
liposomes had a very low PDI (0.07), which is typical of 
homogeneous formulations, and a hydrodynamic diameter 
(HD) of ~140 nm (Table 1), while the liposome-PC com-
plexes had a wide size distribution (PDI 0.21). In particular, 
three main populations were detected in the liposome-PC 
complexes sample (Table 1): 1) a population of ~60 nm 
in HD attributable to plasma proteins and plasma protein 
aggregates and/or to liposomes that had shrunk due to the 
elastic properties of their lipid bilayer; 36,37 2) a population 
with an HD slightly larger (≈180 nm) than control liposomes 
(ie, liposomes before incubation in plasma) ascribable to PC 
formation; and 3) a population of particles from two to three 
times larger than control liposomes (HD =400 nm), which are 
most likely due to PC-induced liposome aggregation. 
As given in Table 1, control liposomes had a slightly neg-
atively charged surface (ζ-potential =-5 mV). The ζ-potential 
decreased to =-16 mV after the formation of the PC on the 
liposome surface, which is similar to the charge of plasma 
proteins (ζ-potential =-18 mV, data not shown). 
We used cryo-electron microscopy to evaluate the 
morphology of the liposome-PC complex. Single-vesicle </p>

<p>Table 1 Dls analysis of liposomes before and after incubation 
in plasma </p>

<p>Sample 
Size (nm) 
PDI 
Zeta-potential (mV) </p>

<p>liposomes 
148 
0.07 
-5 </p>

<p>liposome/ 
Pc complex </p>

<p>58 
0.21 
-16 
180 
386 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: Dls, dynamic light scattering; PDI, polydispersity index; 
Pc, protein corona. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3053 </p>

<p>liposomes and protein corona </p>

<p>analysis of control liposomes and liposome-PC complexes 
revealed that liposomes preserved their structure and shape 
after incubation in plasma (Figure 1). In addition, unlike 
control liposomes (Figure 1A), additional mass adsorbed 
on liposome surfaces attributable to a compact PC was 
observed (Figure 1B). 
We used AFM to identify changes in the mechanical 
properties of liposomes after PC formation. As shown 
in Figure 2A, liposome-PC complexes were larger than 
control liposomes (142-171 nm), which confirms our DLS 
results. Control liposomes resulted in smaller, homogeneous 
particles, while the liposome-PC complexes are relatively 
larger and heterogeneous. Size distribution analysis showed 
a large variation in particle size ranging from smaller values 
of 180-820 nm. 
Quantitative AFM analysis (Figure 2B) revealed that 
liposomes after incubation with plasma were significantly 
stiffer (P,0.005) than bare liposomes (470 kPa vs 310 kPa). 
The increased elastic modulus is most likely induced by the 
presence of particle aggregates with PC deposition. Bare 
liposomes contained a stiffer central area corresponding 
to the highest particle zone, while a more elastic region 
(the external ring in red) corresponded to the particle edges 
(Figure 2C). The liposome-PC aggregates map, instead, 
showed a heterogeneous elastic modulus variation over the 
large surface (Figure 2D). 
Taken together, these data suggest that the formation of 
particle aggregates could be a two-step process (Figure 2E). 
As mentioned earlier, PC formation is a dynamic process. 38 
Our analysis showed a heterogeneous scenario as a snapshot </p>

<p>of the overall mechanism. The smaller particles found in the 
liposome-PC complex sample represent single particle-PC 
complexes. AFM analysis revealed that these individual 
liposome/PC complexes were stiffer than bare liposomes but 
softer than liposome-PC aggregates (Figure S1). Accord-
ing to this finding, we speculate that once each liposome is 
covered by the first PC layer, it becomes adhesive, thereby 
inducing aggregation into larger clusters. 39 Moreover, the 
analysis of the elastic map revealed another protein adsorp-
tion process on the particle cluster that we call the "outer 
corona" (Figure 2E). In addition, although the cluster itself is 
stiffer than bare liposomes, there are some areas underneath 
the outer corona that are less stiff (Figure S2). However, these 
softer areas remain stiffer than the bare liposomes (green) 
and are, instead, very similar in value to those of single 
liposome-PC complexes (Figure S1). Therefore, we hypoth-
esize a nonhomogeneous presence of the outer corona due to 
this difference in topographical arrangement. We speculate 
that formation of the outer corona might be triggered by the 
size of the PC rather than by its composition (Figure S3). </p>

<p>Identification of proteins in the corona </p>

<p>As reported in the section Characterization of liposomes 
before and after PC formation, liposomes were incubated in 
plasma for 1 hour to allow liposome-PC complex formation. 
Our aim was to define proteins constituting the PC in order 
to understand their potential biological effect on liposomes. 
To this aim, the adsorbed proteins (PCs) were eluted from 
the liposomes, separated by 1D SDS PAGE (Figure 3A), 
and identified by mass spectrometry. The most abundant </p>

<p>Figure 1 liposome and liposome/Pc complex characterization by cryo-electron microscopy. 
Notes: High-magnification cryo-EM images of liposomes before (A) and after incubation in plasma (B). cryo-eM analysis reveals a spherical and unilamellar shape for both 
samples. Liposomes retained their shape and structure after incubation with plasma. Note the significant difference in electron density on the particle surface after plasma 
incubation, which indicates the presence of the PC (B). 
Abbreviations: Pc, protein corona; cryo-eM, cryo-electron microscopy. </p>









<p>
International Journal of Nanomedicine 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3054 </p>

<p>corbo et al </p>

<p>proteins, selected by manual visualization and densitometric 
analysis (Figure 3B), were excised and hydrolyzed with 
trypsin. The 20 most abundant proteins adsorbed on the 
liposome surface after exposure to murine plasma are shown 
in Figure 3C, while the mass spectrometry profiles of the 
identified proteins are listed in Table S1. Overall, most PC 
components were small, negatively charged proteins (.70% 
with molecular weight [MW] ,60 kDa, Figure 4A, and 
.70% with isoeletric point [pI] ,6.5, Figure 4B). A previous 
study showed that negatively charged particles preferentially </p>

<p>attract positively charged proteins. 40,41 Contrary to our 
expectation, negatively charged proteins preferentially 
adsorbed on our negatively charged liposomes. A similar 
trend was reported by others, 42,43 and it supports the idea 
that predictions of PC composition exclusively based on NP 
charge are too simplistic. Electrostatic interactions are not 
the only force that drives NP-PC interactions. Many other 
factors (eg, protein abundance in plasma, the presence of a 
functional group on the NP surface, plasma type, and incuba-
tion time) affect PC composition. On the other hand, neutral </p>

<p>Figure 2 aFM showing the impact of the Pc on the mechanical properties of liposomes. 
Notes: Size distribution of liposomes and liposome-PCs (A). Young's modulus property quantification (B). Young's modulus property map of representative liposome (C) 
and liposome-PC (D) samples with AFM. Schematic representation of liposome aggregation process following exposure to plasma (E). 
Abbreviations: aFM, atomic force microscopy; Pc, protein corona. </p>











































































<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3055 </p>

<p>liposomes and protein corona </p>

<p>and positive proteins are also present in the PC, though in 
small percents (Figure 4B). Considering our observation dis-
cussed above on the formation of a nonhomogenous corona, 
we believe that it is possible that these proteins create small 
positive charges or neutral patches on the particles' surface, </p>

<p>which facilitates aggregation by electrostatic or hydrophobic 
interactions. 
In our study, albumin, apolipoproteins, and IgGs were 
the main PC components (Figure 3C), which confirms data 
obtained with other vesicle types. 35 To better understand the </p>

<p>Figure 3 Proteomic analysis of the Pc of liposomes. 
Notes: liposomes were incubated for 1 hour at 37°C in plasma under agitation (A). NPs were centrifuged and extensively washed, and the Pc was eluted in sDs loading 
buffer. SDS-PAGE (12% acrylamide) was carried out at 120 V for 90 minutes. Plasma was loaded as a control. Gels were Coomassie-stained. Plasma proteins on the surface 
of liposomes were quantified by densitometric analysis. The top five most abundant proteins are labeled by number in the graph (B). The top 20 most abundant proteins in 
the liposomes PC (C). Bands were selected and identified by LC-MS. 
Abbreviations: Pc, protein corona; NP, nanoparticle; sDs-Page, sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis; lc-Ms, liquid chromatography-mass 
spectrometry; MW, molecular weight. </p>











































<p>@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ </p>































<p>
Figure 4 clusterization of proteins in the corona. 
Notes: Classification of proteins according to the MW (A) and pI (B) shows that 73.2% of proteins are smaller than 60 kDa and 71.6% of proteins have a pI ,6.5, indicating 
that their overall charge in plasma (pH 7.4) is negative. Values reported represent molar percentages. 
Abbreviations: MW, molecular weight; pI, isoelectric point. </p>













<p>
International Journal of Nanomedicine 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3056 </p>

<p>corbo et al </p>

<p>biological impact of the PC on particle-cell interactions, we 
investigated liposome and liposome-PC complex uptake by 
macrophages and breast cancer cells. We discuss the results 
in the next section. </p>

<p>Cellular uptake of liposomes before and 
after Pc formation </p>

<p>It is well recognized that the PC affects the fate of particles in 
the bloodstream. 44 Notably, the PC can affect particle clear-
ance by immune cells, 8 thereby affecting their biodistribution 
properties. To obtain an overview of what could happen 
in the context of in vivo cancer therapy when therapeutic 
NPs are systemically injected, we studied their uptake by 
macrophages, which are responsible for particle clearance, 
and their internalization by cancer cells, which is essential for 
pharmacological efficacy. We used mouse J774 macrophages 
(Figure 5A) and mouse 4T1 breast cancer cells (Figure 5B) 
as proof-of-concept models for this in vitro study. We treated 
both cell lines with fluorescent particles, and then examined 
their interactions with NPs using confocal microscopy. The 
uptake of liposomes with a PC was greater than that of </p>

<p>Figure 5 Uptake of liposomes by macrophages and cancer cells in the absence and presence of a PC. 
Notes: Confocal images of J774 (A) and 4T1 (B) treated for 3 hours with bare liposomes and liposomes with PC. Cell membranes are stained by using WGA-Alexa fluor 
488 (green), nuclei are DAPI-stained (blue), and particles are in red. The images reveal that the PC increased liposome uptake by both analyzed cell lines. 
Abbreviation: Pc, protein corona. </p>





















<p>
bare liposomes in both cell lines. Moreover, large particle 
aggregates formed in PC-endowed liposomes but not in bare 
liposomes (white arrows in Figure S4). 
To determine the fraction of particles internalized by J774 
and 4T1 cells, we carried out a flow cytometry analysis, in 
which cells were quenched with trypan blue to obscure the 
fluorescence associated with the cell surface. As shown in 
Figure 6, the quantitative analysis confirmed the increased 
uptake of liposomes with a PC. These results concur with 
studies of NP uptake by immune 45 and tumor cells. 46 
Data on the impact of the PC on the biological fate of NPs 
are controversial. Since PC formation is a highly dynamic 
process, it is difficult to envisage a unique explanation of 
the interfacial events that occur between the PC and bio-
logical components. For several decades, cell opsonization 
was considered the body's first defense mechanism against 
foreign entities, 47 but recent studies have shown that the PC 
can shield particles from the action of adsorbed serum com-
ponents (IgG and complement factors) that normally favor 
particle clearance. 19,20 Here we report increased liposome 
uptake by both J774 and 4T1 cells after plasma incubation. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3057 </p>

<p>liposomes and protein corona </p>

<p>Figure 6 Flow cytometry. 
Notes: Histograms show the average fluorescent values of three experiments ± sD. student's t-test. Liposomes with a PC had a significantly higher uptake by J774 and 4T1 
cells than bare liposomes. Naïve cells were used as controls. 
Abbreviations: aU, arbitrary units; Pc, protein corona; sD, standard deviation. </p>







































<p>We hypothesize that complement factors and apolipoproteins 
present in the PC are mainly responsible for this effect. 
Complement proteins, together with immunoglobulins and 
coagulation factors, mediate particle uptake through inter-
actions with complement Fc and Toll-like receptors on the 
macrophage surface. 47 On the other hand, apolipoproteins 
belong to the family of lipoproteins, which are key players 
in the cholesterol metabolism process, through which they 
stimulate cancer cell growth. 48 Cholesterol availability is 
crucial for the proliferation of rapidly dividing cancer cells. 
Breast cancer cells, like other cancer cells, express B-class 
scavenger receptors on their surface, 49 which are intermediate 
in lipid transfer between lipoproteins and cells. 50 We believe 
that the functional motifs of these proteins are exposed on 
the PC, in the correct orientation to perform their function 
and to be recognized by their specific cell receptors, allowing 
PC-mediated cell internalization. These findings explain the 
impact of the PC, ie, the liposome's new biological identity, 
on cellular uptake. On the other hand, our DLS, cryo-EM, 
and AFM experiments conducted to characterize liposomes 
provide insights into the impact of the PC also on the lipo-
some's new physical identity. We found that PC formation 
induces liposome aggregation, which implies the presence 
of clusters of NPs (Table 1, Figure 2) that coexist with single 
liposome-PC complexes, consistent with what has been 
demonstrated elsewhere. 51,52 This means that cells interact 
not only with single particles surrounded by a PC through a 
receptor-mediated pathway but also with particles in the form 
of larger aggregates. The latter are likely to be internalized 
via phagocytosis, particularly in the case of macrophages, 
which would explain why we observed a major uptake by 
cells (Figure 7). </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In the last decade, the biological components of synthetic 
NPs have attracted the attention of the scientific community 
because of the fundamental role they play in the interaction 
between particles and cells. Several assertions have been 
made to describe the PC's composition and correlate it 
to NP uptake by immune and cancer cells. Thus far, the 
results have been controversial due to the variability of 
the experimental settings (particle chemical composition, 
plasma source, plasma concentration, particle incubation 
time, cell lines, etc). 8 In this study, we reported the struc-
ture, composition, and biological effect of PCs adsorbed 
on multicomponent liposomes. We found that the forma-
tion of a PC on liposomes makes their surface adhesive, 
thus inducing the formation of particle clusters that coexist 
with single vesicles. We also showed that internalization of 
liposome-PC complexes by both macrophages and cancer 
cells was greater than that of control liposomes. The presence 
of a PC strongly affects the NP's biological response. This 
can be due to 1) the presence of molecules (ie, immunoglobu-
lins and apolipoproteins) in the PC that recognize specific 
receptors on the surface of immune and cancer cells, and/or 
2) the formation of NP cluster that induce phagocytosis by 
the cells, or 3) a combination of these effects. 
We shed light on the impact of the PC first on particle-
particle and then on particle-cell interactions. Our observa-
tions suggest that to predict the fate of a NP in vivo, one 
must not only know the PC composition and eventually the 
orientation of proteins, but should also carefully consider 
the physical changes (size, surface, and charge) that the 
NP undergoes when surrounded by a PC and the conse-
quent impact on particle-particle interactions. This study </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3058 </p>

<p>corbo et al </p>

<p>Figure 7 Cellular uptake of liposome/PC complexes. 
Notes: The incubation of liposomes with plasma resulted in liposome/Pc complexes. The latter are heterogeneous and can be single vesicles surrounded by a Pc and clusters 
of up to three vesicles (each of them surrounded by a PC) surrounded also by an outer corona. The cells (macrophage or cancer cells) can interact with single particles 
through a receptor-mediated pathway, and with larger aggregates via phagocytosis. 
Abbreviation: Pc, protein corona. </p>













<p>
@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ </p>



<p>shows that the efficacy of liposomal formulations must 
be reinterpreted, as it is strongly affected by PC forma-
tion in plasma. Classical characterization of nanodelivery 
systems should include studies on PC formation and be 
combined with experiments that simulate the tendency of 
NPs to aggregate after exposure to plasma proteins. We 
believe that such studies will hopefully help us interpret 
and predict in vivo data and to design more effective 
therapeutic carriers. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank Kemi Cui and HMRI 
Advanced Cellular and Tissue Microscope Core Facility for 
traditional confocal scanning services, David Haviland and 
the HMRI Flow Cytometry Core Facility for flow cytometry </p>

<p>setup and acquisition, and DA Engler, RK Matsunami, and 
the HMRI Proteomics Programmatic Core Laboratory for 
mass spectrometry analyses. The authors acknowledge 
the Sealy Center for Structural Biology and Molecular 
Biophysics at the University of Texas Medical Branch 
at Galveston for providing research resources. We thank 
Jean Ann Gilder (Scientific Communication srl. Naples, 
Italy) and Megan Livingston for editing the text. We thank 
Associazione Bianca Garavaglia, Via C Cattaneo 8, 21052 
Busto Arsizio, Varese, Italy. This work was supported 
by grants RF-2010-2318372 and RF-2010-2305526 from 
Italian Ministry of Health, and by grants 1R21CA173579-
01A1 from NIH/NCI, 5U54CA143837 PSOC Pilot project 
from NIH/NCI, W81XWH-12-10414 BCRP Innovator 
Expansion from Department of Defense, William Randolph </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3059 </p>

<p>liposomes and protein corona </p>

<p>Hearst Foundation, and The Regenerative Medicine Program 
Cullen Trust for Health Care to ET and by POR Campania 
FSE 2007-2013 Project DIAINTECH, Italy (to FS). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3061 </p>

<p>liposomes and protein corona </p>

<p>Supplementary materials </p>

<p>Figure S1 aFM elastic map of a single liposome/Pc complex. 
Note: The single liposome/Pc vesicles are stiffer than bare liposomes, but softer than liposome/Pc aggregates. 
Abbreviations: aFM, atomic force microscopy; Pc, protein corona. </p>







<p>Figure S2 aFM analysis of the height of a liposome/Pc complex. 
Notes: Offline image processing of an AFM image of a representative liposome/PC complex. The original scan of this single spherical liposome was obtained in height mode. 
Using offline <rs type="software">Nanoscope</rs> software, the liposome was magnified further, and then a section analysis was performed. Along the whole particle profile, there are regions at 
different heights (differences =5 nm). 
Abbreviations: aFM, atomic force microscopy; Pc, protein corona. </p>













<p>
Figure S3 aFM elastic map of another area of the liposome/Pc samples. 
Notes: The image reveals a more complete picture of the mechanical properties of the particle aggregates. In detail, the image shows three different regions imputed to the 
presence of a cluster of three particles (yellow dotted line). 
Abbreviations: aFM, atomic force microscopy; Pc, protein corona. </p>







<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3062 </p>

<p>corbo et al </p>

<p>Table S1 Mass spectrometry details of the proteins identified in the corona </p>

<p>Uniprot 
accession # </p>

<p>Description 
MW 
(Da) </p>

<p>pI 
PLGS 
score </p>

<p>Error SC (%) 
(ppm) products </p>

<p>Digest 
peptides </p>

<p>Amount 
(ng) </p>

<p>P07724 
serum albumin Os=Mus musculus gN=alb Pe=1 SV=3 68,647 
5.68 11,163 56.74 3.04 748 31 
27.7196586 
P08226 
apolipoprotein e Os=Mus musculus gN=apoe Pe=1 
SV=2 </p>

<p>35,844 
5.42 10,020 39.55 3.62 422 16 
21.6211008 </p>

<p>P01872 
Ig mu chain c region secreted form Os=Mus musculus 
gN=Igh-6 Pe=1 SV=2 </p>

<p>49,940 
6.58 12,623 59.03 3.73 583 21 
15.94776469 </p>

<p>P06728 
Apolipoprotein A-IV OS=Mus musculus gN=apoa4 
Pe=2 SV=3 </p>

<p>45,001 
5.18 5,282 
38.48 3.16 394 20 
7.612684167 </p>

<p>Q7TQJ6 
Myosin-9 Os=Mus musculus gN=Myh9 Pe=1 SV=4 
43,593 
5.38 802 
22.65 2.09 335 39 
6.1941774 
Q61838 
alpha-2-macroglobulin Os=Mus musculus gN=a2m 
Pe=1 SV=3 </p>

<p>165,747 6.23 621 
16.72 2.77 158 19 
5.76277457 </p>

<p>Q921I1 
serotransferrin Os=Mus musculus gN=Tf Pe=1 SV=1 
76,673 
6.85 3,204 
49.64 6.00 388 30 
4.657693068 
Q00623 
apolipoprotein a-I Os=Mus musculus gN=apoa1 
Pe=1 SV=2 </p>

<p>30,596 
5.39 4,085 
38.64 1.49 135 13 
1.590012928 </p>

<p>P55065 
Phospholipid transfer protein Os=Mus musculus 
gN=Pltp Pe=1 SV=1 </p>

<p>54,418 
6.17 1,333 
24.14 2.21 111 10 
1.531132057 </p>

<p>P02088 
hemoglobin subunit beta-1 Os=Mus musculus 
gN=hbb-b1 Pe=1 SV=2 
glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase Os=Mus 
musculus gN=gapdh </p>

<p>15,830 
7.50 6,607 
76.87 2.18 148 7 
0.941123577 </p>

<p>P16858 
Pe=1 SV=2 
complement c1q subcomponent subunit c Os=Mus 
musculus gN=c1qc </p>

<p>35,787 
8.35 1,081 
21.62 1.62 47 
5 
0.753101628 </p>

<p>P02747 
Pe=2 SV=2 
25,974 
8.59 701 
16.26 3.47 38 
3 
1.176765057 
P01837 
Ig kappa chain C region OS=Mus musculus Pe=1 SV=1 
11,770 
5.07 5,034 
70.75 2.31 104 10 
0.575553 
P01592 
Immunoglobulin J chain Os=Mus musculus gN=Igj 
Pe=2 SV=4 </p>

<p>18,001 
4.55 803 
23.90 3.26 20 
3 
0.444183676 </p>

<p>P60710 
actin, cytoplasmic 1 Os=Mus musculus gN=actb 
Pe=1 SV=1 
complement c1q subcomponent subunit a Os=Mus 
musculus gN=c1qa </p>

<p>41,709 
5.14 224 
13.33 1.95 26 
5 
0.438048773 </p>

<p>P98086 
Pe=1 SV=2 
25,958 
9.46 15,695 37.55 4.42 410 9 
0.324475 
P00918 
carbonic anhydrase 2 Os=Mus musculus gN=ca2 
Pe=1 SV=4 </p>

<p>29,014 
6.53 541 
22.31 6.75 28 
5 
0.312103598 </p>

<p>P02089 
hemoglobin subunit beta-2 Os=Mus musculus 
gN=hbb-b2 Pe=1 SV=2 </p>

<p>15,870 
7.90 850 
36.73 1.09 26 
4 
0.249436725 </p>

<p>P63101 
14-3-3 protein zeta/delta Os=Mus musculus 
gN=Ywhaz Pe=1 SV=1 
complement c1q subcomponent subunit B Os=Mus 
musculus gN=c1qb </p>

<p>27,753 
4.53 196 
17.96 3.49 18 
4 
0.223530988 </p>

<p>P02746 
Pe=1 SV=2 
26,700 
8.24 15,927 45.45 4.23 446 11 
0.16554 
P01786 
Ig heavy chain V region MOPC 47A OS=Mus musculus 
Pe=1 SV=1 </p>

<p>12,966 
9.11 945 
21.37 1.51 13 
2 
0.0985416 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: MW, molecular weight; pI, isoelectric point; sc, sequence coverage. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-nanomedicine-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of Nanomedicine is an international, peer-
reviewed journal focusing on the application of nanotechnology 
in diagnostics, therapeutics, and drug delivery systems throughout 
the biomedical field. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, 
MedLine, CAS, SciSearch®, Current Contents®/Clinical Medicine, </p>

<p>Journal Citation Reports/Science Edition, EMBase, Scopus and the 
Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The manuscript management system 
is completely online and includes a very quick and fair peer-review 
system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/ 
testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2016:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3063 </p>

<p>liposomes and protein corona </p>

<p>Figure S4 confocal images of macrophages and cancer cells treated with liposomes in the absence and presence of a Pc. 
Note: The increased uptake and the presence of particles' cluster (white arrows) in both J774 and 4T1 cells in the liposomes after incubation in plasma. 
Abbreviation: Pc, protein corona. </p>













<p>
</p></text></tei>