<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4935458" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T16:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. Hypertrophy of the ligamentum flavum (LF) is one 
of the key pathomechanisms of lumbar spinal stenosis (LSS). 
Transforming growth factor (TGF)-β1 is abundantly expressed 
in hypertrophied degenerative LF tissues from LSS. However, 
the molecular mechanisms underling the association between 
TGF-β1 and LF hypertrophy have not yet been fully eluci-
dated. In this study, we investigated the important role of the 
mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathway in the 
pathogenesis of LSS by analyzing the expression of connective 
tissue growth factor (CTGF) and extracellular matrix (ECM) 
components (collagen I and collagen III) in TGF-β1-treated LF 
cells. Cell growth assay revealed that TGF-β1, in association 
with CTGF, enhanced the the proliferation of LF cells, and 
we found that TGF-β1 also elevated CTGF expression and 
subsequently enhanced the mRNA expression of collagen I and 
collagen III. The increased mRNA expression levels of CTGF, 
collagen I and collagen III were abolished by p38 inhibitors. 
Lumbar spinal stenosis (LSS) is one of the most common spinal 
disorders affecting the elderly (1). Degenerative changes in the 
posterior structures of the lumbar spine, such as hypertrophy 
of the facet joints and ligamentum flavum (LF), in combina-
tion with degenerative spondylolisthesis, can contribute to the 
development of LSS (2). The hypertrophy of the LF has been 
described in anatomic studies to be 7-to 8-mm-thick in patients 
with central stenosis, as opposed to the usual 4 mm or less (2). 
Although it is agreed that spinal mechanical stress (3) and 
secreted cytokines (4) from the herniated disk accelerate the 
hypertrophy of the LF, which contributes to the development 
of LSS, the detailed underlying mechanisms are not yet fully 
understood. 
Continuous mechanical stress causes degeneration of the 
LF (5,6). Common pathological characteristics in the degenerated 
LF are the loss of elastic fibers and tissue fibrosis, and increased 
collagen in tissues (6-8). Mechanical stress increases the produc-
tion of transforming growth factor (TGF)-β1 in several cell lines, 
including LF cells isolated from surgically resected LF (9,10). 
TGF-β1 is a key factor in the pathogenesis of tissue fibrosis (11) 
and is abundantly expressed in hypertrophied degenerative LF 
tissues from LSS (12-14). TGF-β1 increases collagen expression 
in LF cells (15). These previous studies suggest that TGF-β1 
plays an important role in the hypertrophy of the LF and thus in 
the pathogenesis of LSS. However, the molecular mechanisms 
underling the association between TGF-β1 and LF hypertrophy, 
particularly the mechanisms underlying the TGF-β1-induced 
increase in collagen expression have not yet been fully elucidated. 
Recently, connective tissue growth factor (CTGF) has 
been shown to have an increased expression in hypertrophied 
lumbar LF and to be involved in the hypertrophy of the LF (16). 
CTGF is a pro-fibrotic factor involved in the fibrotic process, 
such as cell proliferation, migration, adhesion and extracel-
lular matrix (ECM) accumulation (17). CTGF has also been 
reported to be involved in the biological activities of TGF-β1. 
For example, TGF-β1, in association with CTGF, has been 
shown to regulate cell proliferation and the synthesis of ECM 
components (16-18). TGF-β1 also induces the mRNA expres-
sion of CTGF in human skin fibroblasts (19). TGF-β1 is also 
a well-known inducer of ECM components, such as collagen </p>

<p>TGF-β1, in association with the increased expression of 
connective tissue growth factor, induce the hypertrophy 
of the ligamentum flavum through the p38 MAPK pathway </p>

<p>YAN-LIN CAO </p>

<p>1* , YANG DUAN 
1* , LI-XIN ZHU 
1 , YE-NAN ZHAN 
2 , SHAO-XIONG MIN </p>

<p>1 and AN-MIN JIN </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Departments of 
1 Orthopaedic Surgery and 
2 Neurosurgery, Zhujiang Hospital, </p>

<p>Southern Medical University, Guangzhou, Guangdong 510282, P.R. China </p>

<p>Received November 20, 2015; Accepted May 26, 2016 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/ijmm.2016.2631 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Dr Anmin Jin, Department of Orthopaedic </p>

<p>Surgery, Zhujiang Hospital, Southern Medical University, 253 Gongye 
Road, Guangzhou, Guangdong 510282, P.R. China 
E-mail: jinanmin2008@163.com; anminjin2014@sina.com </p>

<p>* Contributed equally </p>

<p>Key words: connective tissue growth factor, transforming growth </p>

<p>factor-β1, mitogen-activated protein kinases, ligamentum flavum, 
lumbar spinal stenosis </p>

<p>CAO et al: TGF-β INDUCES HYPERTROPHY OF THE LIGAMENTUM FLAVUM </p>



<p>and fibronectin (20). In the presence of CTGF neutralizing 
antibody (NA), the pro-fibrogenic effects of TGF-β1, such as 
collagen deposition and anchorage-independent growth are 
attenuated in fibroblasts (20). Additionally, mitogen-activated 
protein kinases (MAPKs) have been reported to be involved 
in the regulation of the expression of CTGF (21,22). However, 
whether the expression of CTGF is regulated by TGF-β1 in 
LF cells and whether it is involved in the hypertrophy of the 
LF though the MAPK pathway remains unknown. 
In this study, we examined the viability of cultured human 
LF cells, the roles of TGF-β1/CTGF in the proliferation of LF 
cells and LF hypertrophy, as well as the role of the MAPK 
pathway in the pathogenesis of LSS by measuring the expression 
of CTGF and ECM components (collagen I and collagen III) in 
TGF-β1-treated LF cells obtained from LF tissues of patients 
who treated with posterior pedicle fixation for lumbar fracture 
or with a standard nucleotomy for lumbar disc herniation using 
the Love method. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Samples. Specimens from 13 patients, who were treated with 
posterior pedicle fixation for lumbar fracture or with a stan-
dard nucleotomy for lumbar disc herniation using the Love 
method at Zhujiang Hospital of Southern Medical University, 
Guangzhou, China, were collected. Informed consent was 
obtained from each patient, and this study was approved by 
the Ethics Committee of Southern Medical University. </p>

<p>Cell isolation and culture. The cells were isolated from the 
LF tissues as previously described (23,24). Briefly, the speci-
mens were minced with microdissection scissors under aseptic 
conditions and washed extensively with phosphate-buffered 
saline (PBS) to remove the blood component. The minced 
tissue was digested at 37˚C for 60 min with 0.2% type I 
collagenase (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) in serum-
free Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM; Gibco, 
Sydney, Australia). The collagenase-treated ligament chips 
were washed with serum-containing DMEM to inhibit colla-
genase activity. The cells were then filtered through a sterile 
nylon mesh filter (75 µm pore size), and placed in 35-mm Petri 
dishes at a density of approximately 5x10 
4 cells/ml in DMEM 
supplemented with 10% fetal calf serum (Gibco). The cultures 
were incubated at 37˚C in a humidified atmosphere, air 95% 
and CO 2 5%. The medium was changed at 2-day intervals, 
and the explants were examined daily for cell outgrowth using 
an inverted light microscope (IX83; Olympus, Tokyo, Japan). 
The outgrown cells were harvested before confluence and 
subcultured after trypsinization with 0.2% trypsin/0.02% ethyl-
enediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA). The cells at the third-fifth 
passage were used for the experiments. Immunofluorescence 
staining for collagen I and III, and fibronectin was used to 
identify the phenotype of the cultured LF cells. </p>

<p>Viability of cultured LF cells. The viability of the LF cells was 
evaluated using the 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-y1)-2,5-diphen-
yltetrazolium bromide) (MTT) (Sigma-Aldrich) colorimetric 
assay, that is based on the reduction of formazan crystals by 
living cells (25). Briefly, LF cells at passages 1, 3, and 5 were 
seeded in 96-well tissue culture plates at 2x10 
4 cells/well </p>

<p>and incubated at 37˚C under 5% CO 2 for 0, 24, 48 and 72 h. 
The cells was then washed with PBS and subsequently incu-
bated in 100 µl of 5 mg/ml MTT solution (Invitrogen Life 
Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA) for 3 h. MTT was converted 
into purple colored formazan in living cells, which was then 
solubilized with dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) (Invitrogen) and 
the absorbance of the solution was measured at 450 nm using 
a microplate reader (Thermo Plate; Rayto Life and Analytical 
Science Co., Ltd., Shenzhen, China). </p>

<p>Effect of TGF-β1/CTGF on LF cells. To examine the biological 
response of human LF cells to TGF-β1/CTGF, the LF cell 
cultures were treated with 3 ng/ml TGF-β1 or 50 ng/ml CTGF 
(R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA) in the absence or 
presence of CTGF NAs (1:500) for 24 h. The proliferation of 
the LF cells was first examined by MTT assay, and the mRNA 
expression levels of CTGF, collagen I and collagen III were 
then detected by reverse transcription-quantitative polymerase 
chain reaction (RT-qPCR), and the protein expression of CTGF 
in the cell lysate was detected by western blot analysis. </p>

<p>Determination of the role of the MAPK pathway. To investi-
gate the role of the MAPK pathway in the TGF-β1-induced 
expression of CTGF, collagen I and collagen III, the LF cell 
cultures were treated with various MAPK inhibitors including, 
the JNK inhibitor, SP600125 (10 µΜ), the ERK inhibitor, 
PD985059 (10 µΜ), and the p38 inhibitor, SB203580 (100 µΜ), 
(all from Sigma-Aldrich). The cells were pre-treated with the 
indicated MAPK inhibitors for 1 h, and were then treated with 
3 ng/ml of TGF-β1 for 24 h. The mRNA expression levels 
of CTGF, collagen I and collagen III were then detected by 
RT-qPCR. 
In addition, to further confirm the role of p38, we examined 
the expression of p38 and p-p38 in the cells following treatment 
with 3 ng/ml TGF-β1 for 2, 4, and 6 h by immunofluorescence 
staining, and examined the protein expression of p38 and 
p-p38 in the cells following treatment with 3 ng/ml TGF-β1 for 
30 min, 1, 2, and 3 h by western blot analysis. </p>

<p>Validation of the critical role of p38 using p38 siRNA. The 
involvement of p38 in the TGF-β1-induced expression of 
CTGF, collagen I and collagen III was further examined using 
the siRNA-mediated knockdown of p38. For transfection with 
p38 siRNA or non-targeting negative control (Santa Cruz 
Biotechnology Inc., Santa Cruz, CA, USA), DharmaFECT 
reagent (Invitrogen Life Technologies) was used according to 
the manufacturer's instructions. After 24 h, the culture medium 
was replaced with fresh supplemented medium, and the cells 
were cultivated for an additional 24 h following treatment with 
3 ng/ml TGF-β1 for 6 h. The expression levels of p38 and p-p38 
were detected by immunofluorescence staining, and the trans-
fection efficiency over time (0, 12, 24, 36 h) was also validated 
by RT-PCR (data not shown). The mRNA expression levels of 
CTGF, collagen I, and collagen III were detected by RT-qPCR. 
The protein expression of CTGF was detected by western blot 
analysis. </p>

<p>RT-qPCR. Following the afore-mentioned incubation or treat-
ments, total RNA was extracted from the cells using TRIzol 
reagent (Invitrogen Life Technologies). A total of 2 µg of total </p>

<p>INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF MOLECULAR MEDICINE 38: 391-398, 2016 </p>



<p>RNA was used to synthesize complementary DNA (cDNA) 
using M-MLV Reverse Transcriptase (Takara, Dalian, China), 
and subjected to RT-qPCR using SYBR-Green real-time 
master mix (Toyobo, Osaka, Japan) with the following primers: 
5'-GGAGTGGGTGTGTGACGAG-3' (forward) and 5'-GTC 
TTCCAGTCGGTAAGCCG-3' (reverse) for CTGF; 5'-AGATC 
TGAAGTGTGATGACTCAGG-3' (forward) and 5'-CAGAT 
CACGTCATCGCACAAC-3' (reverse) for collagen I; 5'-ATGT 
TCCACGGAAACACTGG-3' (forward) and 5'-GGAGAG 
AAGTCGAAGGAATGC-3' (reverse) for collagen III; CGTGT 
TGCAGATCCAGACCA (forward) and GCCAGAATGC 
AGCCTACAGA and (reverse) for p38 siRNA; and 5'-ACACCC 
ACTCCTCCACCTTT-3' (forward) and 5'-TTACTCCTTGG 
AGGCCATGT-3' (reverse) for GAPDH. The thermal treatment 
was 15 min at 95˚C, followed by 35 cycles of 15 sec at 95˚C, 
30 sec at 60˚C, and 30 sec at 72˚C. Gene expression was 
normalized to the level of GAPDH within each sample using 
the relative ΔΔCT method. Gene expression is shown as the 
expression relative to the control. The data shown are 
representative of 3 independent experiments. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis. The LF cells were lysed using SDS 
lysis buffer (Beyotime, Shanghai, China) and centrifuged at 
14,000 x g for 10 min at 4˚C. Equal amounts of proteins were 
separated by SDS-PAGE on a 10% gel and then transferred 
onto a nitrocellulose membrane, followed by blocking with 
5% bovine serum albumin (BSA) for 1 h at room tempera-</p>

<p>ture. The membrane was then incubated overnight at 4˚C 
with rabbit monoclonal antibody specific to CTGF (1:400; 
ab6992), p-p38 (1:1,000; ab47363), or p38 (1:400; ab27986). 
All antibodies were purchased from Abcam (Cambridge, MA, 
USA). Following 3 washes, the membrane was incubated with 
anti-rabbit IgG conjugated with horseradish peroxidase (A0208; 
Beyotime) for 1 h at room temperature. Detection was performed 
with luminal chemiluminescent systems. Quantitative data 
were obtained using a computing densitometer and <rs id="software-0" type="software">MultiGauge</rs> 
software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 3.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Fuji Photo Film Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan).</rs>). </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence staining. The LF cells were rapidly washed 
once with PBS and fixed with 2% paraformaldehyde, blocked with 
2% goat serum (GS; C0265; Beyotime) for 30 min, stained with 
rabbit anti-collagen I (1:100; Ab34710; Abcam), anti-collagen III 
(1:100; Ab7778; Abcam), anti-fibronectin (1:100; Ab2413; 
Abcam), p-p38 (1:100), or anti-p38 (1:200) antibodies, and finally 
visualized with Alexa Fluor 488 goat anti-rabbit antibody (1:150; 
#4412; Cell Signaling Technology, Inc., Danvers, MA, USA) for 
30 min at room temperature. Immunofluorescence staining was 
imaged using a Zeiss LSM 510 laser scanning confocal micro-
scope (Zeiss, Jena, Germany) as previously described (26). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. All data are expressed as the means ± stan-
dard error of the mean (SEM). One-way analysis of 
variance (ANOVA) with Fisher's protected LSD post-hoc test 
was performed to test the difference in densitometeric data. 
Non-parametric one sample Wilcoxon test was used for the 
analysis of the results of RT-qPCR. Each experiment was 
repeated at least 3 times. The statistical significance level was 
defined as P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Viability of cultured human lumbar LF cells. Human lumbar 
LF cells were isolated from surgical specimens obtained from 
13 patients and cultured. Immunofluorescence staining was 
used to identify the cell phenotype (Fig. 1). The cultured cells 
had a typical LF cell phenotype, and uniformly expressed 
collagen I collagen and fibronectin in each cell, and very 
few cells expressed type III collagen. Cell proliferation assay 
revealed that there were no significant differences in cell proli-
faration among the LF cell subcultures (passages 1, 3 and 5) at 
any experimental time point (0, 24, 48, or 72 h) (P&gt;0.05; Fig. 2). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Identification of the phenotype of cultured ligamentum flavum (LF) cells using immunofluorescence staining. Immunofluorescence staining for col-
lagen I and III, and fibronectin in cultured cells; n=3 experiments. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Viability of cultured human lumbar ligamentum flavum (LF) cells 
was assessed by MTT assay. Although the proliferation of LF cells was 
enhanced with time, no significant differences among passage (P)1, P3 and P5 
cells at 0, 24, 48 or 72 h were detected. n=5, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>CAO et al: TGF-β INDUCES HYPERTROPHY OF THE LIGAMENTUM FLAVUM </p>



<p>There was no significant difference in cell bioactivities between 
the individual donors (data not shown). During the 72-h time 
period, the proliferation of the LF cells was significantly 
increased with time in each subculture, showing a similar 
viability with the primary cultured LF cells (Fig. 2). </p>

<p>TGF-β1/CTGF enhances the proliferation of human lumbar 
LF cells. Both TGF-β1 and CTGF markedly elevated the prolif-
eration of the LF cells (Fig. 3). Of note, the effects of TGF-β1 
and CTGF on the proliferation of the LF cells were attenuated 
by CTGF NA, suggesting that TGF-β1 associates with CTGF. </p>

<p>TGF-β1/CTGF induce the mRNA expression of CTGF, 
collagen I and collagen III, and the expression of CTGF in cell 
lysate. TGF-β1 increased the mRNA expression of CTGF, and 
this effect was markedly abolished by CTGF NA (Fig. 4A). To 
further evaluate the role of TGF-β1/CTGF in the hypertrophy of 
the LF, we determined the mRNA expression of ECM compo-
nents, such as collagen I (Fig. 4B) and collagen III (Fig. 4C). 
TGF-β1/CTGF significantly increased the mRNA expression 
of collagen I and collagen III. In addition, the presence of 
CTGF NA abrogated the promoting effects of TGF-β1/CTGF 
on the mRNA expression of collagen I and collagen III (Fig. 4B 
and C). We also examined the expression of CTGF in the cell 
lysate (Fig. 4D). CTGF expression in the cell lysate was increased 
in the presence of TGF-β1 and CTGF, and was diminished by 
the addition of CTGF NA. Overall, these findings suggest that 
TGF-β1/CTGF plays an important role in the hypertrophy of 
the LF. 
In addition, it is worthwhile to note that exogenous CTGF 
did not enhance the mRNA expression of CTGF in the LF 
cells (Fig. 4A), but it increased the expression of CTGF in the 
cell lysate (Fig. 4D), indicating that although CTGF was exog-
enously expressed in the LF cells, it did not increase the CTGF 
mRNA level. Importantly, CTGF NA abolished the promoting 
effects of TGF-β1 on CTGF expression. </p>

<p>mRNA expression levels of CTGF, collagen I and collagen III 
in TGF-β1-treated cells are mediated by p38, but not by JNK 
or ERK. The MAPK inhibitors, namely the JNK inhibitor, 
SP600125, and the ERK inhibitor, PD985059, did not influence 
the mRNA expression of CTGF (Fig. 5A), collagen I (Fig. 5B) </p>

<p>Figure 4. mRNA expression of connective tissue growth factor (CTGF), collagen I and collagen III, and the expression of CTGF in cell lysate. TGF-β1 (3 ng/ml) 
and CTGF (50 ng/ml) increased the mRNA expression of (A) CTGF, (B) collagen I A1, and (C) collagen III A1 significantly. The expression of CTGF in the cell 
lysate was also significantly increased after 24 h. n=3, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. control; (D) 
# P&lt;0.05 with CTGF vs. without CTGF neutralizing antibody (NA). </p>

<p>Figure 3. Effects of TGF-β1/connective tissue growth factor (CTGF) on the 
proliferation of human lumbar ligmentum flavum (LF) cells. TGF-β1 (3 ng/ml) 
and CTGF (50 ng/ml) significantly enhanced the proliferation of human lumbar 
LF cells, and these effects were abrogated by the addition of CTGF neutral-
izing antibody (NA; 1:500) for 24 h. n=5 experiments, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. control. </p>

<p>INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF MOLECULAR MEDICINE 38: 391-398, 2016 </p>



<p>or collagen III (Fig. 5C). The p38 MAPK inhibitor, SB203580, 
abolished the promoting effects of TGF-β1 on the mRNA 
expression of CTGF, collagen I and collagen III, returning the 
levels close to the baseline levels (Fig. 5). </p>

<p>Expression levels of p38 and p-p38 in TGF-β1-treated cells. 
The immunofluorescence imaging of p38 and p-p38 revealed </p>

<p>that their expression and activity was directly related to the 
duration of TGF-β1 treatment (Fig. 6A). TGF-β1 gradually 
and slightly increased the expression of p38 in the LF cells as 
time progressed (P&gt;0.05; Fig. 6B). TGF-β1 gradually elevated 
the expression of p-p38 as time progressed and its expression 
reached a significant level at 1 h (Fig. 6B), showing TGF-β1 
activates the p38 MAPK signaling pathway. </p>

<p>Figure 6. Immunofluorescence staining images and expression of p38 and p-p38 in the TGF-β1-treated cells. (A) Immunofluorescence staining for p38 and p-p38 
on cells after treated with 3 ng/ml TGF-β1 for 2, 4, and 6 h were detected. (B) The expression of p38 and p-p38 on cells following treatment with 3 ng/ml TGF-β1 
for 30 min, 1, 2, and 3 h detected by western blot analysis. (C) The densitometeric values of results of western blot analysis. n=3 experiments, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. control. 
These results further suggest the important role of p38 in the TGF-β1-induced hypertrophy of the lumbar ligamentum flavum (LF). </p>

<p>Figure 5. mRNA expressions of connective tissue growth factor (CTGF) collagen I and collagen III in the TGF-β1-treated cells in the presence of MAPK 
inhibitors. Cell were pre-treated with indicated MAPK inhibitors for 1 h, and then with the addition of 3 ng/ml of TGF-β1 for 24 h. TGF-β1-increased the mRNA 
expression of (A) CTGF, (B) collagen I A1, and (C) collagen III A1 and this effect was markedly abrogated by treatment with 100 µΜ of the p38 inhibitor, 
SB203580, but not by 10 µΜ of the JNK inhibitor, SP600125, or by 10 µΜ of the ERK inhibitor, PD985059; n=3 experiments, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. TGF-β1. </p>

<p>CAO et al: TGF-β INDUCES HYPERTROPHY OF THE LIGAMENTUM FLAVUM </p>



<p>Transfection with p38 siRNA abrogates the effects of TGF-β1. 
After silencing the expression of p38 by p38 siRNA in the 
LF cells, the mRNA expression levels of CTGF (Fig. 7A), 
collagen I (Fig. 7B) and collagen III (Fig. 7C) in the presence 
or absence of 3 ng/ml TGF-β1 for 6 h were significantly 
decreased compared with the NC siRNA-transfected cells. 
Similarly, the silencing of the expression of p38 in the LF cells </p>

<p>significantly diminished the expression and phosphorylation 
level of p38, as well as the TGF-β1 (3 ng/ml for 6 h)-induced 
expression and activity of p38 compared with the NC siRNA-
transfected cells (Fig. 8A). The expression of CTGF in the cell 
lysate exhibited a similar trend with its mRNA expression. 
TGF-β1 (3 ng/ml for 6 h) increased the expression of CTGF, 
and this effect was abrogated by the silencing of p38 (Fig. 8B </p>

<p>Figure 8. Transfection with p38 siRNA attenuated the TGF-β1-induced expression of p38, p-p38 and connective tissue growth factor (CTGF). (A) The expression 
of p38 and p-p38 in cells following treatment with 3 ng/ml TGF-β1 for 6 h was detected by immunofluorescence staining. (B) The expression of CTGF was 
detected by western blot analysis. (C) The densitometeric values of results of western blot analysis. n=3, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. non-targeting negative control (NC siRNA); 
# P&lt;0.05 vs. TGF-β1 + NC siRNA. These results have validated that the p38 pathway plays a critical role in TGF-β1-induced hypertrophy of the lumbar liga-
mentum flavum (LF). </p>

<p>Figure 7. Transfection with p38 siRNA attenuated the TGF-β1-induced mRNA expression of connective tissue growth factor (CTGF), collagen I A1, col-
lagen III A1. The mRNA expression of (A) CTGF, (B) collagen I A1, and (C) collagen III A1 detected by RT-qPCR. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. non-targeting negative 
control (NC siRNA); 
# P&lt;0.05 vs. TGF-β1 + NC siRNA. These results have validated that the p38 pathway plays a critical role in TGF-β1-induced hypertrophy 
of the lumbar ligamentum flavum (LF). </p>

<p>INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF MOLECULAR MEDICINE 38: 391-398, 2016 </p>



<p>and C). Overall, the results presented above indicate that the 
p38 MAPK signing pathway plays a critical role in the TGF-β1-
induced hypertrophy of the LF. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Stenotic LF cells can produce a matrix rich in type I and III 
collagen and fibronectin (23), and the cultured cells acquire the 
LF cell phenotype with the uniform expression of collagen I 
and type III collagen, as well as fibronectin in each cell. 
Hypertrophy of the LF plays an important role in the 
development of LSS (2). Spinal mechanical stress (3) and 
secreted cytokines (4) from herniated disk accelerate the 
hypertrophy of the LF. Mechanical stress increases the produc-
tion of TGF-β1 (9,10). The association between TGF-β1 and LF 
hypertrophy has not yet been fully elucidated. In this study, we 
found that TGF-β1 enhanced the expression of CTGF at both 
the mRNA and protein level, further supporting the existence 
of an interaction between CTGF and TGF-β1, as described 
in a previous study (27). Furthermore, TGF-β1 elevated the 
mRNA expression of ECM components, including collagen I 
and III, and this effect was abolished by the CTGF NA, indi-
cating that TGF-β1 contributes to the hypertrophy of the LF in 
association with CTGF. Furthermore, the associations between 
TGF-β1, CTGF and LF hypertrophy are mediated through the 
p38 MAPK pathway. 
Previous studies have demonstrated that TGF-β1, in asso-
ciation with CTGF, regulates cell proliferation (16,18). In this 
study, we found that TGF-β1 enhanced the proliferation of LF 
cells, and this associated with an increase in CTGF expres-
sion. However, with the addition of CTGF NA, the promoting 
effects of TGF-β1 on the proliferation of LF cells were 
abrogated (Fig. 3). Furthermore, TGF-β1, in association with 
CTGF, regulates the synthesis of ECM components (16,18). 
The increased synthesis of collagen is a major characteristic 
of LF hypertrophy (10). LF cells have a typical fibroblast-
like phenotype, as they express type I and type III collagen 
and fibronectin, but do not stain positive for osteonectin (23). 
Normal cells do not synthesize type II collagen (23). Type I 
and type III collagen have been found to be predominant in 
human LF (28). In this study, we also observed that TGF-β1 
increased the mRNA expression of collagen I and collagen III, 
and this effect was abrogated by CTGF NA, indicating that the 
TGF-β1-induced synthesis of ECM components is associated 
with CTGF. TGF-β1 elevated the expression of CTGF at both 
the mRNA and protein level (Fig. 4). Therefore, TGF-β1, in 
association with CTGF, contributed to the hypertrophy of the 
LF. 
In general, the effects of TGF-β are mediated through the 
phosphorylation of cytoplasmic R-Smads (29,30). In addition to 
the activation of Smad signaling, TGF-β1 can activate members 
of the MAPK pathway, as well as other kinases (31,32). Upon 
stimulation with TGF-β, the crosstalk between the ERK, p38, 
JNK and Smad pathways is cell type-specific (33,34). Previous 
studies have shown the pro-fibrotic activities of p38 and ERK 
signaling, and the anti-fibrotic activities of JNK signaling (27). 
The pathway involved in the TGF-β1-induced hypertrophy 
of the LF has not been addressed to date, to the best of our 
knowledge. In this study, among ERK, p38, and JNK, only 
the use of the p38 inhibitor abolished the mRNA expression </p>

<p>of CTGF, and collagen I and III (Fig. 5), indicating the pro-
fibrotic activities of p38 signaling. We further observed that the 
expression and phosphorylation level of p38 were enhanced by 
TGF-β1. Following the silencing of p38 MAPK (its efficiency 
over time was almost the same; data not shown), the expression 
and phosphorylation level of p38, as well as the mRNA expres-
sion of CTGF, collagen I and collagen III were attenuated 
correspondingly, as well as the expression of CTGF (Fig. 6). 
Apparently, the expression of p38 and p-p38 presented in 
Fig. 6A does not match that shown in Fig. 6B. It is worth noting 
that the immunofluorescence staining in this study was focused 
on the cell surface, that should limit the detection of intracel-
lular signaling, but the western blot analysis included all the 
intracellular and cell surface information. These results further 
confirm that p38 MAPK is a key mediator of the effects of 
TGF-β1, and the pro-fibrotic activities of p38 signaling. 
In conclusion, TGF-β1, in association with the increased 
expression of CTGF, induce the hypertrophy of the LF through 
the p38 MAPK pathway. Degenerative changes in the poste-
rior structures of the lumbar spine, such as the hypertrophy 
of the facet joints and LF, in combination with degenerative 
spondylolisthesis, contribute to the development of LSS (2). 
Patients with LSS usually present with the typical symptoms 
of neurogenic claudication and/or lumbar or sacral radiculop-
athy (35,36). Many patients may also complain of pain when 
performing activities requiring the extension of the spine. 
These symptoms may improve with appropriate conserva-
tive treatment, although 60-85% of patients undergo surgical 
treatments (35). Our observations appear to be important for 
evaluating the pathomechanisms of LSS, and may prove to be 
helpful in the diagnosis and prevention of LSS in the early 
stage, and may also provide an effective alternative to surgery. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This study was supported by funds from the Guangdong 
Science and Technology plan project (no. 2011B080701018), 
and the Guangdong Medical Science and Technology Research 
Fund (no. A2012372). </p>



<p>CAO et al: TGF-β INDUCES HYPERTROPHY OF THE LIGAMENTUM FLAVUM </p>





</text></tei>