<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4583706" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Genomics Data </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : h t t p : / / w w w . j o u r n a l s . e l s e v i e r . c o m / g e n o m i c s -d a t a / </p>

<p>from patients diagnosed and treated at Hospital Sant Joan de Déu 
(Barcelona, Spain) were included in the study. Normal fetal brain 
(n = 2) and adrenal gland (n = 2) tissues as well as ganglioneuroma 
samples (n = 2) were used as reference samples. Neuroblastoma 
risk assessment was defined by the International Neuroblastoma 
Staging System (INSS) [8]. Patients' clinical and biological character-
istics are displayed in Table 1. Tumors were evaluated by a patholo-
gist, only samples with more than 70% viable tumor cell content 
were included in the study. This study was approved by the Institu-
tional Review Boards. Informed consent was obtained before collec-
tion of samples. 
Genomic DNA was isolated from samples using Wizard DNA Purifi-
cation Kit (Promega Biotech Ibérica, Spain), following manufactures' 
protocols. </p>

<p>3.2. DNA methylation microarrays </p>

<p>Genomic DNA bisulfite conversion and hybridization to Infinium 
Human Methylation 450k BeadChip (Illumina Inc., San Diego, CA) was 
performed at the Human Genotyping Unit of the Spanish National Can-
cer Center (CEGEN-CNIO, Madrid, Spain), as described previously [9]. </p>

<p>3.3. Quality control </p>

<p>Microarray data was analyzed by <rs type="software">minfi</rs> [10] and <rs type="software">shinyMethyl</rs> [11] 
packages available through <rs type="software">Bioconductor</rs> [12]. </p>

<p>Table 1 
Patients' clinical and biological characteristics. </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Methylation array samples (n = 35) </p>

<p>Age, months 
Median 
17.90 
Range 
0.10-225.28 
INSS, n (%) 
Stages 1-3 
15 
44.12% 
Stage 4 
14 
41.18% 
Stage 4s 
6 
17.65% 
MYCN status, n (%) 
MYCN Amp 
7 
20.59% 
MYCN non-Amp 
28 
82.35% </p>

<p>Fig. 1. A: Raw β-value density plot. B: Raw β-value bean density plot. C: Scatter plot of log median intensity of methylated (Meth) and unmethylated (Unmeth) channels. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Principal component analysis. AG: adrenal gland. GN: ganglioneuroma. FB: fetal 
brain. NB: neuroblastoma. </p>

<p> 
S. Gómez et al. / Genomics Data 5 (2015) 360-363 </p>

<p>Single cytosine methylation values (β-values) in each sample were 
calculated as the ratio of the methylated signal intensity to the sum of 
methylated and unmethylated signals. Methylation values ranged 
from 0, fully unmethylated, to 1, fully methylated cytosine. Raw methyl-
ation β-value plots were performed for all samples to identify possible 
deviant samples (Fig. 1 &amp; B). 
Sample quality was assessed using the log median intensity in both 
the methylated and unmethylated channels (Fig. 1C). 
Principal component analysis (PCA) was performed on the 20,000 
most variable autosomal probes in order to analyze associations be-
tween sample type (adrenal gland, ganglioneuroma, fetal brain or neu-
roblastoma) and methylation levels (Fig. 2). </p>

<p>3.4. Data normalization </p>

<p>Microarray methylation data was normalized by <rs type="software">missMethyl</rs> pack-
age [13] using the SWAN (subset-quantile within array normalization), 
a within-array normalization method for Illumina Human Methylation 
450k BeadChips (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>3.5. Filtering of microarray data </p>

<p>An optimized pipeline with several filters developed at the IDIBAPS 
was used to exclude technical biases, [14,15]. Cytosines with poor detec-
tion P-values (P N 0.01) and those with sex-specific DNA methylation 
(n = 6926) were removed from the initial dataset of 485,512 sites (ex-
cluding probes detecting SNPs). The remaining sites (n = 478,169) 
were used for downstream analyses (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>3.6. Bisulfite pyrosequencing </p>

<p>DNA methylation data were validated by bisulfite pyrosequencing as 
previously described [15,16] (Fig. 5). </p>

<p>4. Data summary </p>

<p>The analysis of the DNA methylome of neuroblastoma patients re-
vealed that: i) most DNA methylation changes take place outside pro-
moters, ii) not only CpGs but also non-CpG sites are targeted, iii) 
methylation changes at these sites are associated with clinicopatholog-
ical features of neuroblastoma, and iv) the identified epigenetic patterns 
provide new insights into the pathogenesis and clinical behavior of this 
pediatric tumor. The analysis of this data has been reported in our re-
cently published study [15]. </p>

<p>Financial disclosure </p>

<p>This work was supported by the NEN association (association of 
families and friends of patients with neuroblastoma) [to S Gómez], Hos-
pital Sant Joan de Déu, Barcelona, Spain [BR201102 to G. Mayol] and 
Spanish Government [PI11/02661 and PI14/00038 Instituto de Salud 
Carlos III grant to C Lavarino and Ramon y Cajal Grant to JI Martín-
Subero]. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors acknowledge G. Garcia-Castellví for the fund raising and 
the "Biobanc de l'Hospital Infantil Sant Joan de Déu per a la Investigació" 
integrated in the National Network Biobanks of ISCIII for tissue samples. 
The authors also thank J. Ríos for statistical advice and S. Sánchez Molina 
for precious technical support. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Density distributions of beta values before and after using SWAN. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Data processing work-flow. </p>

<p> 
S. Gómez et al. / Genomics Data 5 (2015) 360-363 </p>



<p>Fig. 5. Technical DNA methylation validation. (A) Scatter plot of DNA methylation levels obtained by Infinium Human Methylation 450k BeadChip (Illumina Inc., San Diego, CA) (Y-axis) 
and bisulfite pyrosequencing (X-axis) (n = 11). A highly significant correlation (P b 0.001, R 
2 = 0.978 and R 
2 = 0.968, respectably) between microarray and pyrosequencing data was </p>

<p>observed. Example of pyrograms with methylated (B) and unmethylated (C) cytosines. </p>

<p> 
S. Gómez et al. / Genomics Data 5 (2015) 360-363 </p>

</text></tei>