<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4182815" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>About 150,000 patients per year suffer moderate or severe 
traumatic brain injury (TBI) in the USA. All of these are at risk for 
intracranial hematomas including extra-axial hematomas (both 
subdural and epidural), as are some of the 1.35 million patients per 
year who suffer mild traumatic brain injury. Subdural hematomas 
result from bleeding between the arachnoid mater and dura mater, 
while epidural hematomas results from bleeding between the dura 
mater and the skull. Extracranial hematomas are also common in 
TBI patients, but pose less risk compared to intracranial hemato-
mas. All acute neurologic emergencies require rapid identification 
of pathophysiologic processes that are amenable to surgical or 
medical treatment [1-9]. For example, patients with acute 
intracranial hematomas that are sufficiently large to compromise 
cerebral blood flow require emergent surgical drainage in order to </p>

<p>increase the likelihood of an acceptable neurologic outcome. 
Evacuation of acute intracranial hematomas within four hours is 
recommended [3]. 
In general, hematomas are formed by rupture of blood vessels 
and internal bleeding in tissues. Instead of circulating in blood 
vessels, blood accumulates in tissues and can induce damage, in 
particular, damage to brain tissue directly exposed to blood in 
intracranial hematomas [1-4]. Before the advent of computed 
tomography (CT) and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), acute 
intracranial hematomas were diagnosed using physical examination 
and cerebral angiography. The development of CT and MRI 
permitted rapid, high-resolution, noninvasive diagnosis, but could 
not be used until a patient arrived at a major health-care facility. 
However, more rapid, accurate diagnosis before arrival at a major 
facility could reduce the time required before definitive evacuation. 
We proposed to use an optoacoustic technique to detect and 
characterize intracranial and extracranial hematomas. Optoacous-
tics (which is based on absorption contrast) is a promising 
technology for both blood vessels and hematoma detection and 
characterization [10-15] because hemoglobin is a major chromo-
phore in the near-infrared spectral range [16]. In cases of severely 
reduced brain perfusion, more rapid diagnosis and treatment could 
improve outcome. Unlike bulky CT and MRI equipment, an effective 
optoacoustic system can be small, portable and easily transported in </p>

<p>Photoacoustics 2 (2014) 75-80 </p>

<p>A R T I C L E I N F O </p>

<p>Article history: 
Received 9 January 2014 
Received in revised form 31 March 2014 
Accepted 2 April 2014 
Available online 13 April 2014 </p>

<p>Keywords: 
Optoacoustics 
Noninvasive monitoring 
Cerebral blood oxygenation 
Animal model 
Traumatic brain injury 
Hematoma 
blast </p>

<p>A B S T R A C T </p>

<p>Surgical drainage of intracranial hematomas is often required within the first four hours after traumatic 
brain injury (TBI) to avoid death or severe disability. Although CT and MRI permit hematoma diagnosis, 
they can be used only at a major health-care facility. This delays hematoma diagnosis and therapy. We 
proposed to use an optoacoustic technique for rapid, noninvasive diagnosis of hematomas. In this study 
we developed a near-infrared OPO-based optoacoustic system for hematoma diagnosis and cerebral 
venous blood oxygenation monitoring in rats. A specially-designed blast device was used to inflict TBI in 
anesthetized rats. Optoacoustic signals were recorded from the superior sagittal sinus and hematomas 
that allowed for measurements of their oxygenations. These results indicate that the optoacoustic 
technique may be used for early diagnosis of hematomas and may provide important information for 
improving outcomes in patients with TBI. 
ß 2014 Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/). </p>

<p>* Corresponding author: Professor, Director of Laboratory for Optical Sensing and 
Monitoring, Director of High-resolution Ultrasound Imaging Core of UTMB, Center 
for Biomedical Engineering, UTMB Comprehensive Cancer Center, Department of 
Neuroscience and Cell Biology, and Department of Anesthesiology, Research 
Building #21, 301 University Boulevard, University of Texas Medical Branch, 
Galveston, Texas 77555-1156, Tel.: +409 772 8144; fax: +409 772 8144. 
E-mail address: riesenal@utmb.edu (R.O. Esenaliev). </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>Photoacoustics </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / p a c s </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pacs.2014.04.001 
2213-5979/ß 2014 Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/). </p>

<p>an emergency vehicle. Unlike CT or MRI, heavy shielding and 
avoidance of magnetic objects is unnecessary. Although diagnosis of 
delayed intracranial hematomas in hospitalized patients can be 
definitively accomplished using CT or MRI, more rapid optoacoustic 
assessment that does not require transport to the radiology 
department could save time and reduce morbidity in hospitalized 
patients who suffer sudden neurologic deterioration. 
Optoacoustic technology that can detect intracranial hemato-
mas can also recognize abnormalities in overall brain perfusion 
because of associated reductions in oxygen saturation, including 
that in the superior sagittal sinus (SSS) [10-15,17-19]. The same 
pre-hospital device can both diagnose intracranial hematomas and 
document inadequate cerebral perfusion by detecting low SSS 
hemoglobin saturation. 
Patients with mild, moderate or severe traumatic brain injury 
and nontraumatic coma represent a population of at least 
2,000,000 patients who are likely to be emergently transported 
to the hospital and for whom pre-hospital diagnosis of or exclusion 
of intracranial hematomas may dramatically reduce the time 
necessary for definitive diagnosis and therapy after hospital 
arrival. Formulating a preliminary diagnosis during pre-hospital 
transport could provide invaluable information to guide emergen-
cy diagnosis and treatment after hospital admission. For instance, 
if a patient with a deteriorating level of consciousness before 
hospital admission had an optoacoustic diagnosis of epidural 
hematoma, surgeons and other hospital personnel could initiate 
preparations for emergent craniotomy. If that patient were located 
in a rural area remote from a major medical center, evidence of an 
intracranial hematoma could prompt transport by helicopter 
rather than ambulance to speed arrival at a center that could 
provide emergency neurosurgical treatment. 
In the present study, we used a prototype optoacoustic system to 
detect blast-induced extra-and intracranial hematomas in a small 
animal model. The mechanisms of blast injuries in humans can be 
classified into at least 4 types [20]. A primary injury results directly 
from blast over/underpressure. Secondary blast injury results from 
shrapnel (energized fragments from the explosive) or debris 
accelerated by the blast wind. Tertiary injuries result from 
acceleration of the body by the blast wave and/or wind and may 
include tumbling, impact onto hard surfaces, or crushing. Quater-
nary injuries include all other effects, such as burns and poisoning. 
All of these classifications apply to animal models as well. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>In optoacoustics, a short pulse of light (typically, near-infrared 
light for deeper penetration) induces a rapid increase in pressure in 
an absorbing sample due to stress confinement (i.e. the duration of 
the light pulse is significantly shorter than the time required for the 
pressure to dissipate). Given constant pulse energy and duration, 
the magnitude of the pressure depends on the Gruneisen 
parameter (G) of the sample and the absorbed energy density: </p>

<p>PðzÞ ¼ G m a FðzÞ </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>G ¼ bc </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>s =C p 
(2) </p>

<p>Here P(z) is the axial pressure distribution (1-D case), m a is the </p>

<p>optical absorption coefficient of the sample, and F(z) is the depth 
dependence of fluence (light energy delivered per unit area). In 
many biological tissues (e.g. blood), the acoustic properties are </p>

<p>essentially those of water, but m a depends on the concentration of </p>

<p>chromophores (e.g. hemoglobin) and on the excitation wavelength 
(l) [16]. Irradiating a sample with multiple wavelengths will 
produce acoustic signals that can be used for quantitative analysis 
of the sample's absorption spectrum. For blood, we can determine </p>

<p>the oxygen saturation using the m a values obtained from a multi-</p>

<p>wavelength optoacoustic measurement and the spectra of oxy-
and deoxyhemoglobin [10-15]. 
The optoacoustic system used in this study (Fig. 1) was 
designed for continuous monitoring of oxygenation in a variety of 
blood vessels [11,12,15]. An optical parametric oscillator (OPO) 
(Opolette 532 II, Opotek Inc., Carlsbad, CA) outputs short (&lt; 20 ns) 
pulses of near-infrared (NIR) light in the range from 680 to 
2400 nm, with pulse energy &lt; 8 mJ and repetition rate 20 Hz. This 
spectral range includes the 700-1064 nm spectral range which is 
best for accurate oxygenation monitoring in deeper blood vessels 
as shown in our previous studies in large animals (sheep) when we 
validated our noninvasive method using invasive measurements of 
the SSS blood oxygenation (blood sampling followed by Co-
Oximeter measurements) [11,12,15]. As in the previous works, the 
ratio of peak-to-peak optoacoustic amplitudes was used for 
accurate oxygenation measurements. Although direct validation 
of noninvasive oxygenation measurements in small animal studies 
is impossible with the invasive measurements due to the size 
limitations, the high accuracy of SSS blood oxygenation measure-
ments obtained with the system in thicker tissues in our large 
animal studies justified its application in the rat studies. 
The optoacoustic probe is a broadband ultrasonic receiver made </p>

<p>of a 6 cm wide disk of piezoelectric film (110 mm PVDF), with a 1-</p>

<p>mm optical fiber in the center for object irradiation and an 
integrated 20 dB preamplifier [19]. The energy emitted from the 
probe did not exceed 0.5 mJ, so given the circular laser spot with 
diameter 1 mm, the radiant exposure on skin was &lt; 64 mJ/cm 
2 . </p>

<p>The lateral resolution of the probe is 1-2 mm depending on target 
depth, while the axial resolution is limited by the system's 
ultrasound bandwidth and is &lt; 0.2 mm. The probe displacement 
was performed manually, however the peak amplitudes were </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Photo of the optoacoustic system. Laser/OPO block is mounted on the top 
shelf of the cart along with a box containing optical elements that direct light into 1-
mm fiber. OPO controller, amplifier and digitizer are located on the middle shelf, 
whereas OPO cooling tower and UPS occupy the lowest shelf. </p>

<p>A. Petrov et al. / Photoacoustics 2 (2014) 75-80 </p>

<p>
measured and displayed automatically by the system itself. After 
the blast, new peaks appeared indicating to formation of new areas 
with blood. The acoustic signal is amplified by a low-noise 40 dB 
second-stage amplifier and recorded by a high-speed digitizer (NI 
USB-5132, National Instruments, Austin, TX) at 8 bits resolution 
and 50 MS/s. The operator interface is a laptop (Dell Precision 
M4500) running <rs type="software">Windows 7</rs> and custom <rs type="software">LabVIEW</rs> software. The 
software controls the OPO and analyzes signals in real time to 
allow for unattended monitoring once the probe is secured. 
In this study, we attempted to isolate the effects of primary and 
tertiary blast injury while minimizing all other effects. The 
custom-made Vandenberg blast device (Fig. 2) uses nail gun 
cartridges inserted into a detachable barrel [21]. To prevent 
accidental activation, the device only fires when an operator 
simultaneously presses two switches, which requires both hands. 
A solenoid drives a metal bar to strike the firing pin against the 
cartridge (Fig. 2, bottom). In this study we used Ramset/Remington 
nail gun cartridges of .27 caliber with power level 5, which in our 
unpublished study were shown to induce moderate brain injury in 
the animal model. Under these conditions, the Vandenberg blast 
device produces a combined blast over/underpressure that is 
followed by a blunt impact caused by the venting gas jet. 
The rat model is the most commonly used model in the TBI 
research due to the similarities between TBI in humans and rats 
and knowledge obtained in numerous rat TBI studies. To 
demonstrate the feasibility of the blast-induced hematoma 
formation monitoring with this technique, the rat model was 
best because the blast-induced TBI has been studied in rats by 
many groups. Blast-induced TBI in large animals is less reproduc-
ible and practical and is not well established yet. All experimental 
procedures were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and 
Use Committee of the UTMB. Adult, male Sprague-Dawley rats 
(N = 15, weight = 370-520 g) were anesthetized with 4% isoflurane 
in an induction chamber, intubated and mechanically ventilated </p>

<p>with a mixture of 70:30 air:oxygen and 1.5-3% isoflurane (2-3% 
during surgery, 1.5-2% during monitoring). A tail artery was 
cannulated for continuous measurement of arterial blood pressure 
via a Biopac MP-100 system (Biopac Systems, Inc., Goleta, CA). The 
instantaneous blood pressure (with a sampling interval of 50 ms) 
was acquired, displayed and logged by <rs id="software-2" type="software">AcqKnowledge</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">3.9</rs> software 
running on a Macintosh PC. The current mean arterial pressure 
(MAP, averaged over the last 30 sec) was periodically calculated 
and entered in the <rs type="software">AcqKnowledge</rs> journal. Body temperature was 
monitored with a rectal probe. The dorsal surface of the head was 
shaved, and any remaining hair removed with Nair lotion, to 
minimize the attenuation of the blast wave, the laser pulses, and 
the acoustic signals during oxygenation monitoring. 
The optoacoustic probe was placed on the dorsal midline of the 
head with a layer of ultrasound gel for acoustic coupling and 
aligned for maximum SSS signal. The SSS oxygenation (SO 2_SSS ) 
was measured continuously and in real time for 10 min to 
provide a baseline. Then the optoacoustic probe was removed and 
the rat was transferred onto a 5 cm thick foam pad to minimize 
tertiary blast injuries. Using high-speed video recordings, we had 
previously confirmed that the force of the blast presses the rat into 
the foam pad. To block both debris (e.g. unburned powder) and 
heat from reaching the animal, a 1.5 mm thick silicone rubber 
pad was placed on the head over a layer of ultrasound gel (which 
conducted the blast wave). Earplugs were inserted to protect the 
eardrums. The rat was positioned under the Vandenberg device, 
with the opening of the barrel 15 mm above the protective pad and 
directly over the right hemisphere of the brain. A single blast was 
fired, the rat was returned to its original position, and optoacoustic 
monitoring was resumed as quickly as practical (typically within 
5 min). The OA probe was placed as close as possible to its pre-blast 
location, while maximizing the SSS signal. MAP monitoring was 
continued during the blast. Whenever the MAP began to drop 
rapidly, or if it fell below 60 mmHg, the OA probe was lifted, proper 
ventilation was verified, and the arterial catheter was flushed with 
saline. To maintain body temperature in the 37-38 8C range, we 
placed a warm-water blanket under the rat and a 100 W halogen 
lamp above it; the lamp was raised or lowered as needed. 
The blast injury often was followed by the formation of a 
hematoma (intracranial, extracranial, or both) over the right 
hemisphere, close to the SSS, which was revealed upon the 
completion of the experiment and animal euthanasia. Even though 
the probe was aligned over the SSS, in many cases it also picked up an 
optoacoustic signal from the hematoma. This allowed simultaneous </p>

<p>-0.4 
0.0 
0. 4 
0.8 
1. 2 
1.6 
2.0 </p>

<p>-0.6 
0.0 
0. 6 
1.2 
1. 8 
2.4 </p>

<p>-0.8 </p>

<p>-0.6 </p>

<p>-0.4 </p>

<p>-0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>swel lin g </p>

<p>intracran ial 
hematoma 
extracran ial 
hematoma </p>

<p>SSS-</p>

<p>Depth, mm </p>

<p>Energy-normalized OA Signal, a.u. </p>

<p>Time, s </p>

<p>be fore bl ast 
blast + 5 min 
blast + 10 min 
blast + 20 min </p>

<p>SSS+ </p>

<p>skin </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Optoacoustic signals from a rat's head before and after blast injury, acquired 
at a wavelength of 800 nm. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Vandenberg blast device: external appearance (top); internal structure 
(bottom). </p>

<p>A. Petrov et al. / Photoacoustics 2 (2014) 75-80 </p>

<p>
measurement of blood oxygenation in the SSS and in the hematoma, 
as well as monitoring the progression of the hematoma. 
After 60-80 minutes of monitoring, the isoflurane anesthesia 
was increased to 4% for 10 min in preparation for euthanasia. 
Then the rat was decapitated and the skull was opened for gross 
examination. The brain was immediately transferred to dry ice for 
further analysis. </p>

<p>3. Results &amp; discussion </p>

<p>Fig. 3 shows the optoacoustic signals obtained from the intact 
head of one of the rats before the blast and at several time intervals 
after the blast, using the same probe position (except before the 
blast). Each of these waveforms was obtained by averaging 50 
consecutive signals induced by 800 nm laser pulses. During the 
experiment, the operator selected the peaks of interest in the 
displayed signal, and their positions and amplitudes were 
automatically calculated and displayed in real time. The pre-blast 
signal contains only two distinct peaks, from the skin and the SSS. </p>

<p>The very first peak was the signal from skin (at t = 0 ms) because 
the probe was in contact with skin and t = 0 ms corresponded the </p>

<p>probe-skin interface. The SSS signal has a well-defined bipolar 
shape, with an initial maximum pressure (SSS + ) followed by a 
minimum (SSS-). After the blast, a peak from the intracranial 
hematoma was immediately apparent and increased over time. </p>

<p>About 10 min after the blast, another peak appeared near the skin, 
indicating an extracranial (subcutaneous) hematoma. The ultra-
sonic time-of-flight measurements (from the skin peak to each of 
the other peaks) were converted into distance measurements 
using the fact that the speed of sound in most soft tissues is very 
close to the speed in water. The measured distances correlated well 
with the expected anatomical features. Also, the SSS signal was 
maximized when the probe was placed on the midline of the head, 
which is the actual location of the SSS. 
Both hematoma peaks increased in amplitude over time as the 
volume of blood in the hematomas increased. Higher vasculariza-
tion and blood flow in brain compared to that in skin explain faster 
formation of intracranial hematomas compared to extracranial 
hematomas. The amplitude of the SSS peak declined over time 
because more light was absorbed by the intervening hematomas. </p>

<p>d X (t) = thickness of layer X (distance between boundaries) </p>

<p>s X (t) = (d X (t) -d X (t 0 )) / d X (t 0 ) * 100% (% swelling in lay er X) </p>

<p>d X = d X (t end ) -d X (t 0 ) </p>

<p>s X = s X (t end ) -s X (t 0 ) = s X (t end ) </p>

<p>s X / t = s X / (t end -t 0 ) (rate of swell ing) </p>

<p>-20 
-15 
-10 
-5 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>d int (22.9) = 0.837 mm 
d total = 0. 043 mm </p>

<p>s total = 2.38 % </p>

<p>s total / t = 0.23 %/m in </p>

<p>d int = 0.094 mm </p>

<p>s int = 12.7 % </p>

<p>s int / t = 0. 76 %/m in </p>

<p>d scalp (6.2) = .480 mm </p>

<p>d int (6.2) = 0.74 3 mm </p>

<p>d scalp = 0.187 mm </p>

<p>s scalp = 39.0 % </p>

<p>s scalp / t = 2.34 %/min </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>total </p>

<p>(-7) = 1.852 mm </p>

<p>Depth (distan ce fr om skin) of optoac oust ic peak s: 
Extracranial hematoma 
Intracranial he matom a 
SS S </p>

<p>Time fr om blast, min. </p>

<p>Depth, 
mm </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>total </p>

<p>(-17.5) = 1.809 mm </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Depths of the optoacoustic peaks, before and after blast, and definitions of swelling parameters. </p>

<p>Table 1 
Blast-induced swelling rates by layer. d(start) and d(end) refer to the thickness at </p>

<p>the start and end of the monitoring period (either pre-or post-blast). Dd, Ds and Ds/ 
Dt are defined in Fig. 4. </p>

<p>Layer </p>

<p>d(start), mm d(end), mm Dd, mm Ds, % Ds/Dt, %/min </p>

<p>Pre-blast total 
1.809 
1.852 
0.043 
02.4 
0.23 
Post-blast total 2.128 
2.459 
0.331 
15.6 
0.93 
Scalp 
0.480 
0.667 
0.187 
39.0 
2.34 
Skull 
0.905 
0.955 
0.050 
05.5 
0.33 
Intracranial 
0.743 
0.837 
0.094 
12.7 
0.76 </p>

<p>-20 
-15 
-10 
-5 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>MAP (mmHg) and oxygenation (%) </p>

<p>MAP, mmH g 
Oxy gena tions: 
Extracranial he matom a 
Intracranial hematoma 
SSS </p>

<p>Time from bl ast, min . </p>

<p>Fig. 5. MAP and oxygenation of the SSS and hematomas, before and after blast. </p>

<p>A. Petrov et al. / Photoacoustics 2 (2014) 75-80 </p>

<p>
Absorption by the extracranial hematoma also reduced the amount 
of light scattered back to the skin, resulting in lower skin signal 
amplitude. Moreover, it is highly likely that blast-induced trauma 
may result in vasoconstriction and decreased blood flow in skin, 
further reducing the skin signal due to lower hemoglobin content. 
As the blast-induced swelling progressed, the distance from the 
skin to the hematoma and SSS peaks increased steadily (Fig. 4). 
Here we divide the tissue into 3 hypothetical layers, separated by 
the peaks in the optoacoustic signal. Layer ''scalp'' extends from the 
skin peak to the extracranial hematoma, layer ''skull''-from extra-
to intracranial hematoma, and layer ''intracranial''-from intracra-
nial hematoma to SSS. Let d X (t) denote the thickness of layer X, and 
d total -the total thickness of all layers (the distance from the skin to 
the SSS). To calculate d X , we multiply the time difference between 
the optoacoustic peaks by 1.5 mm/ms, the speed of sound in soft 
tissue. (This will underestimate the skull thickness, but will not 
affect the % swelling result.) Let t 0 be the time (in minutes) of the 
start of the monitoring period, and t end -the end of the period. Fig. 4 
defines s X (t) (the percent swelling in layer X, relative to initial </p>

<p>thickness), Dd X (the absolute change in thickness from start to end 
of monitoring), and Ds X (total % swelling). The average rate of 
swelling (in %/min) is given by Ds X /Dt. All results are presented in </p>

<p>Table 1. We can see that the rate of swelling before the blast was 
within measurement error (considering only the total tissue 
thickness since there were no hematomas yet), but after the blast it 
was significant. As expected, the skull layer experienced almost no 
swelling. The intracranial layer did not swell as much as the scalp, 
probably because it was constrained by the cranium. 
Fig. 5 shows the blood oxygenation measured in the SSS, 
intracranial hematoma, and extracranial hematoma of the above 
mentioned rat. Cerebral blood flow, and hence SSS oxygenation, 
increases with cerebral perfusion pressure (CPP = MAP-ICP), 
where ICP is intracranial pressure. Before the blast, the ICP was 
constant but MAP decreased quickly before stabilizing, leading to a 
gradual decrease in SSS oxygenation. It should be noted that even 
before the blast MAP was often unstable in the rats due to 
anesthesia. After the blast, the SSS blood oxygenation gradually 
decreased from 70% to 60%. While the MAP increased gradually, 
the ICP increased greatly due to hematoma formation, leading to 
lower CPP and slowly declining SSS oxygenation. The oxygenation 
of both hematomas started low and rapidly increased (from 40% 
to 68% in the intracranial hematoma, and from 40% to 83% in the 
extracranial hematoma). The decrease of SSS blood oxygenation 
was due to the blast-induced brain injury resulting in insufficient 
cerebral blood flow. The higher increase of oxygenation in the 
extracranial hematoma was due to low oxygen consumption in skin 
tissue compared to that in brain tissue. In general, skin tissues have 
higher oxygenation compared to that of other tissues (including 
brain tissues) because of the lower oxygen consumption. We </p>

<p>speculate that the hematoma oxygenation was low (40%) 
immediately after the blast because: 1) the fresh hematomas 
consisted primarily of venous blood (70% of cerebral blood is 
venous) and 2) the blast may result in rapid and transient 
vasoconstriction within a few minutes after blast. Over time, the 
pressure gradient between arterial and venous blood resulted in 
leakage of more highly saturated arterial and capillary blood into the 
hematoma. The strong correlation between the MAP and the 
oxygenation of each hematoma supports this hypothesis. 
After blast MAP measurements can be resumed quicker (in 
2 minutes) than the optoacoustic measurements (in 5 minutes) 
due to limitations in the animal study. Most likely, that within a 
few minutes after the blast the SSS blood oxygenation closely 
followed the MAP (namely, sharply decreased and then quickly 
recover). The short transition period was followed by the steady 
increase in the MAP, while the SSS blood oxygenation decreased 
due to intracranial pressure rise. 
The presence of extracranial hematoma was visually confirmed 
after the scalp over the blast site was removed (Fig. 6, left). On the 
excised brain, the intracranial hematoma was easily identified 
(Fig. 6, right). Similar hematomas were observed in five other rats. 
The experiments were designed to induce moderate traumatic 
brain injury in rats. In 6 out of 15 rats the blasts resulted in 
hematoma formation. After blasts, the additional peaks were 
detected in all the rats with hematomas and these peaks had 
similar trends in these animals. </p>

<p>4. Conclusions </p>

<p>In this pre-clinical study, we have demonstrated the feasibility 
of optoacoustic detection of blast-induced hematomas in a small 
animal model. Detection of hematomas through an adult human 
skull requires a separate clinical study, which is beyond the scope 
of the present work but is planned for the near future. However, we 
have already measured SSS oxygenation in adult human volunteers 
[17] and TBI patients [18] through intact scalp and skull. The 
penetration depth of our technique in these cases is 2 cm (up to 
1 cm scalp and 1 cm skull). In real clinical settings an optoacoustic 
array may be used to provide real-time, fast data acquisition for 
hematoma detection. 
Our observations have clinical diagnostic significance. Not only 
will the optoacoustic device detect intracranial hematomas, it also 
will provide valuable information regarding hemoglobin saturation 
in the hematoma. Most subdural hematomas result from venous 
bleeding and would be expected to have relatively low hemoglobin 
saturation. In contrast, many epidural hematomas result from 
arterial disruption and would be expected to be associated with 
hemoglobin saturation similar to arterial saturation. Diagnosis of 
hematomas with an apparent arterial source could prompt more </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Extracranial (left) and intracranial (right) blast-induced hematomas on the right side of the brain. The scale bar is 1 cm. </p>

<p>A. Petrov et al. / Photoacoustics 2 (2014) 75-80 </p>

<p>
rapid intervention because arterial bleeding may be more rapidly 
progressive. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest statement </p>

<p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work is supported by the National Institutes of Health 
Grant # U54EB007954 (from the National Institute of Biomedical 
Imaging and Bioengineering) and in part by the DOD (Grant 
#W81XWH-10-1-1048), NIH Grant R01 NS044345 from the 
National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke, Grant 
R41HL10309501 from the National Heart, Lung and Blood 
Institute), and the Moody Center for Brain and Spinal Cord Injury 
Research/Mission Connect of UTMB. The content is solely the 
responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the 
official views of the NIBIB or NIH. Drs. Prough and Esenaliev are co-
owners of Noninvasix, Inc., a UTMB-based startup that has licensed 
the rights to optoacoustic monitoring technology. </p>



<p>A. Petrov et al. / Photoacoustics 2 (2014) 75-80 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>