<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4743607" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>AbstrAct </p>

<p>background. Prospective studies in various cardiovascular populations show that Type D personality predicted impaired 
health-related quality of life (HRQoL) and disease-specific health status. We examined the effect of negative affectivity 
(NA), social inhibition (SI) and their combined effect (Type D personality) on HRQoL and disease-specific health 
status among colorectal cancer (CRC) patients. 
Methods. CRC patients diagnosed between 2000 and 2009, as registered in the Dutch population-based Eindhoven 
Cancer Registry, received questionnaires on Type D personality (DS14), HRQoL (EORTC QLQ-C30) and disease-
specific health status (EORTC QLQ-CR38) in 2010, 2011 and 2012. 
results. Response rates were 73% (n  2625), 83% (n  1643) and 82% (n  1458), respectively. Analyses were done 
on those completing at least two questionnaires (n  1735). Individuals with Type D (NA/SI; 19%) and high NA 
(NA/SI-; 11%) reported a significantly worse HRQoL and disease-specific health status compared to NA-/SI and 
NA-/SI-. Differences were stable over time. Linear mixed effects models showed that Type Ds had a lower quality of 
life, cognitive and emotional functioning, more insomnia, diarrhea, gastrointestinal, defecation and stoma-related prob-
lems and poor body image and future perspective compared to the reference group (NA-/SI-), even after controlling for 
sociodemographic and clinical variables. High NA individuals (NA/SI-) reported similar poor health outcomes as Type 
Ds. However, they also reported lower social functioning and more fatigue, pain, micturition-and financial problems, 
while Type Ds reported more constipation, sexual problems and less sexual enjoyment. 
conclusions. Type D personality and high NA both have a significant negative stable impact on HRQoL and disease-
specific health status among CRC patients. </p>

<p>Colorectal cancer (CRC) is the second most prevalent 
cancer in the Netherlands. There were about 45 000 
CRC survivors in 2000, while in 2020 the total num-
ber is expected to have doubled [1]. Most research 
among CRC survivors focusses on the role of clinical 
variables, like diagnosis and treatment, on health-
related quality of life (HRQoL) and disease-specific 
health status (e.g. side effects and symptoms). How-
ever, the role of individual differences in this matter 
is under exposed. The holy grail of personalized </p>

<p>medicine, which is currently the dominant ambition 
of translational research, will remain elusive unless we 
can find ways to identify those patients that experience 
a healthy cancer survivorship, and those patients who 
do not. In addition to clinical and demographic char-
acteristics, individual differences in personality can 
probably help to identify those patients [2]. 
Type D personality has been shown to be an impor-
tant predictor of HRQoL and disease-specific health 
status in medical and general populations, above and </p>

<p>Acta Oncologica, 2015; 54: 669-677 </p>

<p>ISSN 0284-186X print/ISSN 1651-226X online 
DOI: 10.3109/0284186X.2014.996663 </p>



<p>beyond clinical characteristics [3-5]. Type D is defined 
by the combination of two personality traits; the ten-
dency to experience negative emotions [negative affec-
tivity (Na)] and to inhibit self-expression in social 
interaction [social inhibition (SI)] [6]. as such, Type D 
has been associated with adverse health outcomes, 
impaired health status and HRQoL, more serious ill-
ness perceptions and an increased health care utiliza-
tion [2,4,5,7,8]. Overall, the Na component of Type D 
plays a more important role than the SI component in 
terms of general HRQoL, while the specific combina-
tion of Na and SI in Type D has been related to symp-
toms of anhedonia, mental fatigue and decreased 
motivation [9]. There are a number of potential path-
ways that could explain the relationship between per-
sonality and worse self-reported health and HRQoL. 
For example, patients with Type D and high Na may 
be more likely to perceive and attend to somatic symp-
toms and to interpret them as potentially pathological 
[8]. In addition, Type D personality has been associated 
with an unhealthy lifestyle and poor treatment adher-
ence, which, in turn, may have an adverse effect on 
perceived health [8]. 
Research on the association of personality and 
HRQoL among CRC cancer patients is scarce but 
rising. a recent cross-sectional study among 162 CRC 
patients reported that personality was associated with 
HRQoL, independent of disease severity and psycho-
logical distress [10]. Furthermore, a prospective study 
among 144 CRC patients stated that personality vari-
ables can predict a decrease in HRQoL over a one-
year period [11]. also, Type D personality was 
associated with poor quality of life and mental health 
among CRC and other cancer survivors in a cross-
sectional population-based study (n  3080) [7]. 
a recent review stated that "more well-designed 
prospective investigations are necessary to establish 
the contributory role of personality dimensions for 
the development of and protection from distress 
and impairment in the HRQoL of CRC patients" 
[8]. In order to predict which CRC patients will 
experience a self-reported healthy cancer survivor-
ship, we will investigate the degree to which HRQoL 
and disease-specific health status can be explained 
by individual differences in the personality (e.g. 
Na, SI and Type D personality), while controlling 
for clinical characteristics. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Setting and participants </p>

<p>Data from the first three waves (2010, 2011 and 
2012) of a prospective population-based yearly 
survey among CRC survivors from the Eindhoven 
Cancer Registry (ECR) was used. The ECR </p>

<p>compiles data of all individuals newly diagnosed with 
cancer in the southern part of the Netherlands, an 
area with 10 hospitals serving 2.3 million inhabitants 
[12]. Everyone diagnosed with CRC from 2000 to 
2009 as registered in the ECR was eligible for par-
ticipation. Those with unverifiable addresses, with 
cognitive impairment, who died prior to the start of 
study or were terminally ill, with stage 0/carcinoma 
in situ, and those already included in our 2009 study 
or another study (n  169) were excluded. a com-
plete overview of the selection of patients can be 
found on our website http://www.profilesregistry.nl/ 
dataarchive/study_units/view/22 under 'data &amp; docu-
mentation'. This study was approved by the certified 
Medical Ethics Committee of the Maxima Medical 
Centre, Veldhoven, The Netherlands. 
Data collection was done within PROFILES [13]. 
Data from the PROFILES registry is freely available 
for non-commercial scientific research, subject to 
study question, privacy and confidentiality restric-
tions, and registration (www.profilesregistry.nl). </p>

<p>Data collection </p>

<p>Survivors were informed of the study via a letter from 
their (ex-)attending specialist. The letter included a 
link to a secure website, a login name, and a pass-
word, so that interested patients could provide 
informed consent and complete questionnaires 
online. If the patient preferred written rather than 
digital communication, (s)he could return our post-
card by mail after which (s)he received our paper-
and-pencil informed consent form and questionnaire. 
Non-respondents were sent a reminder letter and 
paper-and-pencil questionnaire within two months. 
Survivors' sociodemographic and clinical informa-
tion were available from the ECR. Comorbidity at the 
time of the study was assessed with the adapted Self-
administered Comorbidity Questionnaire [14]. Ques-
tions on marital status, educational level, and current 
occupation were included in the questionnaire. </p>

<p>NA, SI and Type D personality. Na, SI, and the Type 
D personality construct were assessed with the Type 
D Personality Scale (DS14) [6]. The 14 items are 
answered on a five-point response scale ranging from 
0 (false) to 4 (true). The DS14 has good measure-
ment properties; the subscales have high reliability 
(Cronbach's alpha 0.88/0.86) and good test-retest 
reliability over a three-month period of r  0.72/0.82 
for the two subscales, respectively, and the DS14 dis-
criminates well between Type D and non-Type per-
sonality [6,15]. To compare the separate and 
combined effects of high and low trait levels, the 
standard cut-off score  10 on the Na and SI sub-
scales of the DS14 [6] was used to classify patients </p>

<p>Personality, quality of life and disease-specific health status 671 </p>

<p>in four personality groups based on their scores at 
T1: Na  10 and SI  10 (Na/SI; the 'Type D' 
group), Na  10 but SI  9 (Na/SI-; the 'Na only' 
group), SI  10 but Na  9 (Na-/SI; the 'SI only' 
group), and both Na  9 and SI  9 (Na-/SI-; the 
'reference' group). </p>

<p>Quality of life. The EORTC QLQ-C30 (Version 3.0) 
was used to assess cancer-specific QoL [16]. It con-
tains five functional scales, a global health status/ 
QoL scale, three symptoms scales, and six single 
items. Each item is scored on a four-point Likert-
scale, except the global QoL scale, which has a seven-
point Likert-scale. Scores were linear transformed to 
a 0-100 scale [17]. a higher score on the functional 
scales and global QoL scale means better functioning 
and QoL. a higher score on the symptom scales 
mean more complaints. </p>

<p>Disease-specific health status. Disease-specific health 
status was assessed with the EORTC QLQ-CR38 
[18]. It consists of two multi-item and two single-
item scales, seven symptom scales, and an item on 
weight loss. Items were scored on a four-point Lik-
ert-scale. all scales were linearly converted to a 0-100 
scale. a higher score on the EORTC QLQ-CR38 
functional scales and single items (i.e. body image, 
sexual functioning, sexual enjoyment and future per-
spective) represent a higher level of function. For the 
symptom scales and single items, a higher score rep-
resents a higher level of symptoms. </p>

<p>Depression. Depressive symptoms were assessed with 
the depression subscale of the Hospital anxiety and 
Depression Scale (HaDS) comprising of seven items 
on a four-point Likert-scale [19]. It assesses levels of 
symptoms in the last week. The scale mainly covers 
anhedonia and loss of interest, which are core depres-
sive symptoms. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Differences in sociodemographic and clinical charac-
teristics between respondents, non-respondents or 
patients with unverifiable addresses at T1 and 
between patients who completed one or more ques-
tionnaires were compared with a c 2 , aNOVa or inde-
pendent samples t-test where appropriate. 
all other analyses are based on patients who 
completed at least two questionnaires. Differences 
in sociodemographic and clinical characteristics 
between patients with different personality types 
(Na-/SI-; Na-/SI; Na/SI-; Type D) were com-
pared with a c 2 or aNOVa while differences in 
HRQoL and disease-specific health status were 
determined by aNOVas at each time point. as our </p>

<p>results showed that Na had a large effect on our 
outcomes, the same analyses were performed for 
continuous Na scores divided into quartiles. 
The course of HRQoL and disease-specific health 
status (separate models for each scale) according to 
the four personality groups was analyzed using linear 
mixed effects models (i.e. covariance pattern model 
with an unstructured error variance matrix and max-
imum likelihood estimation). This technique uses 
data efficiently by also including incomplete cases in 
the analyses. as a result of this, bias is limited and 
statistical power is preserved. Time was analyzed as 
a regular categorical predictor with three levels (i.e. 
three time points). Sex, age, time since diagnosis, 
treatment, disease stage, comorbid conditions, part-
nership and educational level and depression levels 
were entered as covariates into the models, based on 
a priori assumptions/hypotheses. Sociodemographic 
and clinical characteristics were analyzed as time-
invariant predictors (i.e. baseline characteristics were 
used). Depression scores were analyzed as continu-
ous time varying predictors. In order to correctly 
interpret all model parameters, all continuous vari-
ables have been grand-mean centered. 
Finally, a sub analyses using linear mixed-effects 
models was performed on the general subscale global 
health status/QoL over time stratified by Na divided 
into quartiles. 
all statistical tests were two-sided and considered 
significant if p  0.05. all analyses were conducted 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 19.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Statistical Package for Social Sciences</rs>, Chicago, IL, USa). Missing items 
from multi-item scales of the EORTC QLQ-C30 
and EORTC QLQ-CR38 were mean-imputed if at 
least half of the items from the scale were answered, 
according to the EORTC guideline. Missing items 
on the DS14 and HaDS scales were mean imputed 
if only one item was missing, otherwise the scale 
score became missing [6,19]. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Sociodemographic and clinical characteristics </p>

<p>The questionnaire was completed by 73% (n  2625) 
at T1, 83% (n  1643) at T2 and 82% (n  1458) at 
T3. Respondents were significantly younger (69.4 vs. 
72.4; p  0.01), more often male (55% vs. 48%; 
p  0.01), were more often diagnosed with stage I 
disease (30% vs. 25%; p  0.02) and were more often 
treated with radiotherapy (31% vs. 24%; p  0.01) 
compared to non-respondents. Respondents signifi-
cantly more often received radiotherapy (31% vs. 
26%; p  0.01) and surgery (99% vs.96%; p  0.01) 
and were more often male (55% vs. 48%; p  0.01) 
compared to patients with unverifiable addresses. </p>



<p>Those who completed one versus those who 
completed  2 questionnaires differed with respect to 
gender (49% vs. 43% female; p  0.01), age (71.3 vs. 
68.4 years; p  0.001), having a partner (71% vs. 
79%; p  0.001), having a job (10% vs. 19%; 
p  0.01), and radiotherapy treatment (27% vs. 32%; 
p  0.01). also, they more often had a lower educa-
tional level (p  0.001), were more often diagnosed 
with stage IV disease (p  0.001) and had worse 
scores on more than half of the subscales of the 
EORTC QLQ-C30 and EORTC QLQ-CR38 (global 
QoL, physical, role emotional and social functioning, 
fatigue, nausea, pain, dyspnea, appetite loss, sexual 
functioning, sexual enjoyment, future perspective, 
chemotherapy side effects and weight loss; data not 
shown). Those who completed  2 questionnaires 
had worse scores on the subscales gastrointestinal 
problems and defecation problems. From this point 
forward, only those who completed  2 question-
naires are described in the analyses. 
at T1, 328 CRC survivors (19%) had a Type D 
personality (Table I). No statistically significant 
differences were observed between those with and with-
out a Type D personality in age, years since diagnosis, 
primary treatment and tumor type. However, CRC 
survivors with a Type D personality were significantly 
more often female, more often diagnosed with stage II 
disease, had a lower educational level and had a partner 
less often compared to those without a Type D person-
ality. Furthermore, those with Na only were younger 
compared to the other three groups. Finally, those with 
Type D and those with Na only had more comorbid 
conditions compared to the other two groups. </p>

<p>HRQoL and disease-specific health status </p>

<p>at T1, patients with Type D and Na only reported 
a significantly worse HRQoL and more disease-
specific symptoms compared to the other two groups 
except for sexual enjoyment which was only worse 
among those with a Type D personality, and female 
sexual problems which showed no differences 
between the groups (Table I). Furthermore, the dif-
ferences in HRQoL scores between the Type D group 
and the reference group, and between the Na only 
group and the reference group, were clinically rele-
vant for all subscales except for nausea (Type D 
group) and constipation (Na only group) [20]. 
These differences in HRQoL and disease-specific 
health status between Type D and Na only groups 
versus the SI only and reference groups were quite 
stable across the three time points, the most relevant 
EORTC QLQ-C30 and EORTC QLQ-CR38 sub-
scales with respect to survivorship [21] are presented 
in Figure 1. However, problems with weight loss and 
female sexual functioning were more prevalent in the </p>

<p>Type D group than in the other three groups at T2, 
and Type D patients also reported more problems 
regarding sexual enjoyment across all time points. 
Type D patients also reported more problems with 
sexual functioning and male sexual functioning at T1, 
but not at T2 or T3 and for female sexual functioning 
at T2 but not T1 or T3 than patients with Na only. 
Linear mixed effects models showed that CRC 
survivors with a Type D personality were at a sig-
nificantly increased risk of an impaired global quality 
of life, more insomnia, less sexual enjoyment, and a 
worse body image and future perspective compared 
to the reference group (Na-/SI-), even after control-
ling for sex, age, time since diagnosis, stage, chemo-
therapy, comorbidity, partner, education, time of 
questionnaire, and depression (Table II). also, CRC 
survivors with a Type D personality were at a sig-
nificantly increased risk of an impaired cognitive 
functioning (Beta -4.7, 95% CI -6.7--2.6), emotional 
functioning (Beta -10.3, 95% CI-11.8--8.7), more 
diarrhea (Beta 3.6, 95% CI 1.2-6.1), constipation 
(Beta 2.3, 95% CI 0.1-4.5), gastrointestinal prob-
lems (Beta 3.2, 95% CI 1.6-4.8), defecation prob-
lems (Beta 3.6, 95% CI 2.0-5.2), stoma-related 
problems (Beta 8.9, 95% CI 3.8-14.0), and female 
sexual problems (Beta 14.8, 95% CI 5.5-24.0) in 
comparison to the reference group. Other important 
determinants of HRQoL and disease-specific symp-
toms were sex, age, time since diagnosis, comorbid 
conditions and depression (data not shown). 
Furthermore, linear mixed effects models showed 
that patients with Na only also reported an impaired 
global quality of life, more insomnia, a worse body 
image, and future perspective compared to the refer-
ence group but moreover, they also reported and 
more fatigue and pain (Table II). additionally, those 
who score high on Na reported more problems 
with cognitive functioning (Beta 25.4, 95% CI 
27.8-22.9), social functioning (Beta 22.7, 95% CI 
25.1-20.3), emotional functioning (Beta 212.6, 
95% CI 214.4-210.7), and more diarrhea (Beta 
3.7, 95% CI 0.8-6.6), gastrointestinal problems 
(Beta 4.4, 95% CI 2.5-6.5), defecation problems 
(Beta 2.9, 95% CI 1.0-4.8), stoma-related problems 
(Beta 8.6, 95% CI 2.7-14.5), micturition problems 
(Beta 3.1, 95% CI 0.8-5.4) and financial problems 
(Beta 3.2, 95% CI 0.7-5.6). 
as patients with Type D and Na only reported 
very similar scores on most outcomes, we performed 
a sub analysis on the general and overarching "global 
health status/QoL" scale over time stratified by Na 
divided into quartiles (Figure 2). Results showed 
that all Na quartiles differed significantly from each 
other at each time point with respect to global 
health status/QoL, except for quartile 1 (lowest) and 
2 which did not differ. </p>

<p>Personality, quality of life and disease-specific health status 673 </p>

<p>Table I. Sociodemographic and clinical characteristics at T1 according to Type D personality. </p>

<p>N (%) 
all (n  1735) </p>

<p>Na-/SI-
(n  911) </p>

<p>Na-/SI 
(n  297) </p>

<p>Na/SI-
(n  199) </p>

<p>Na/SI 
(n  328) 
p-Value a </p>

<p>Sex (Female) 
743 (43%) 
383 (42%) 
110 (37%) 
92 (46%) 
158 (48%) 
0.03 
age [mean (SD)] 
68.4 (9.4) 
68.8 (9.1) 
68.4 (9.2) 
66.6 (10.5) 
68.5 (9.8) 
0.03 
Years since diagnosis [mean (SD)] 
5.1 (2.8) 
5.1 (2.9) 
5.4 (2.8) 
5.1 (2.7) 
5.0 (2.7) 
0.21 
Tumor type 
Colon 
Rectal </p>

<p>1031 (59%) 
704 (41%) </p>

<p>558 (61%) 
353 (34%) </p>

<p>171 (58%) 
126 (42%) </p>

<p>112 (56%) 
87 (44%) </p>

<p>190 (58%) 
138 (42%) </p>

<p>0.42 </p>

<p>Stage 
I 
II 
III 
IV </p>

<p>522 (31%) 
610 (36%) 
503 (30%) 
55 (3%) </p>

<p>267 (30%) 
327 (37%) 
264 (30%) 
30 (3%) </p>

<p>100 (35%) 
93 (32%) 
91 (32%) 
5 (2%) </p>

<p>63 (32%) 
59 (30%) 
60 (31%) 
13 (7%) </p>

<p>92 (29%) 
131 (42%) 
88 (28%) 
7 (2%) </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>Chemotherapy (yes) 
516 (30%) 
265 (29%) 
88 (30%) 
67 (34%) 
96 (29%) 
0.64 
Radiotherapy (yes) 
562 (32%) 
277 (30%) 
107 (36%) 
68 (36%) 
110 (34%) 
0.27 
Number of comorbid conditions 
None 
One 
Two or more </p>

<p>422 (25%) 
501 (30%) 
736 (44%) </p>

<p>239 (28%) 
273 (32%) 
353 (41%) </p>

<p>95 (33%) 
92 (32%) 
99 (35%) </p>

<p>33 (17%) 
51 (27%) 
108 (56%) </p>

<p>55 (17%) 
85 (27%) 
176 (56%) </p>

<p> 0.001 </p>

<p>Partner (yes) 
1357 (79%) 
706 (78%) 
247 (84%) 
158 (81%) 
246 (75%) 
0.05 
Educational level 
Low 
Middle 
High </p>

<p>285 (17%) 
1055 (61%) 
383 (22%) </p>

<p>138 (15%) 
560 (62%) 
206 (23%) </p>

<p>48 (16%) 
169 (57%) 
79 (27%) </p>

<p>29 (15%) 
123 (63%) 
44 (22%) </p>

<p>70 (21%) 
203 (62%) 
54 (17%) </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>Quality of life [mean (SD)] 
global quality of life 
Physical functioning 
Role functioning 
Emotional functioning 
Cognitive functioning 
Social functioning 
Fatigue 
Nausea 
Pain 
Dyspnea 
Insomnia 
appetite loss 
Constipation 
Diarrhea 
Financial problems </p>

<p>78.9 (17.7) 
82.3 (19.0) 
82.0 (26.0) 
86.8 (18.6) 
85.3 (20.3) 
87.1 (21.6) 
20.1 (22.1) 
3.2 (10.5) 
15.6 (23.8) 
12.6 (23.3) 
20.3 (27.8) 
4.2 (13.5) 
8.6 (19.2) 
10.6 (21.5) 
7.0 (19.1) </p>

<p>83.3 (15.4) 
84.7 (17.7) 
85.9 (23.8) 
94.0 (10.4) 
90.1 (15.3) 
91.3 (18.1) 
15.6 (19.6) 
2.3 (9.4) 
12.5 (21.8) 
9.9 (20.8) 
15.9 (24.8) 
2.5 (10.4) 
6.7 (16.8) 
8.5 (19.2) 
5.3 (16.9) </p>

<p>82.0 (15.4) 
84.7 (17.4) 
85.3 (23.0) 
91.6 (13.1) 
87.7 (17.6) 
90.9 (16.7) 
16.0 (18.7) 
2.5 (8.9) 
12.8 (20.6) 
10.5 (21.1) 
15.8 (24.0) 
3.3 (13.5) 
8.7 (18.7) 
9.6 (19.9) 
4.1 (15.0) </p>

<p>70.5 (19.0) b 
77.0 (20.7) b 
73.4 (29.0) b 
71.9 (22.3) b 
75.6 (25.9) b 
79.0 (24.2) b 
31.2 (25.0) b 
5.7 (14.1) b 
22.1 (27.1) b 
19.5 (27.7) b 
32.8 (34.1) b 
8.0 (19.0) b 
11.2 (22.7) 
13.8 (24.6) b 
12.2 (23.9) b </p>

<p>69.1 (19.3) b 
77.0 (21.1) b 
73.3 (29.2) b 
71.3 (23.3) b 
75.6 (25.1) b 
77.0 (27.4) b 
29.9 (24.4) b 
4.7 (11.8) 
22.7 (27.3) b 
18.1 (26.9) b 
29.3 (30.6) b 
7.3 (16.1) b 
11.7 (22.8) b 
15.4 (25.5) b 
11.4 (23.4) b </p>

<p> 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.001 
EORTC QLQ-CR38 [mean (SD)] 
Body image 
Future perspectives 
Sexual functioning 
Sexual enjoyment 
Micturition problems 
Chemotherapy side effects 
gastrointestinal problems 
Male sexual problems c 
Female sexual problems c 
Defecation problems 
Stoma-related problems 
Weight loss </p>

<p>84.7 (21.7) 
72.8 (27.1) 
24.4 (23.1) 
58.7 (27.7) 
21.4 (17.5) 
10.4 (15.5) 
15.4 (14.5) 
43.4 (37.6) 
23.6 (24.8) 
13.2 (12.6) 
23.5 (21.2) 
4.5 (14.1) </p>

<p>89.0 (18.0) 
79.5 (23.3) 
26.0 (23.8) 
61.9 (26.8) 
19.6 (17.0) 
8.3 (13.2) 
12.6 (12.6) 
40.2 (37.4) 
22.6 (25.8) 
11.5 (11.3) 
20.2 (19.7) 
3.6 (12.3) </p>

<p>86.9 (19.3) 
77.6 (23.5) 
23.8 (21.7) 
56.4 (26.4) 
20.2 (17.1) 
8.1 (12.5) 
15.4 (13.8) 
44.7 (36.4) 
20.3 (20.5) 
12.6 (11.9) 
18.0 (17.8) 
4.2 (13.5) </p>

<p>75.5 (27.3) 
58.2 (30.9) 
23.5 (22.7) 
59.4 (29.7) 
26.0 (18.5) 
14.0 (17.3) 
22.1 (15.8) 
45.9 (40.3) 
27.3 (26.3) 
16.7 (13.1) 
30.9 (20.5) 
7.0 (17.3) </p>

<p>76.0 (24.8) 
58.8 (28.8) 
21.0 (22.4) 
50.8 (28.7) 
24.6 (17.8) 
15.9 (20.1) 
19.4 (16.9) 
49.9 (37.4) 
27.5 (24.3) 
16.9 (15.1) 
32.9 (24.4) 
5.9 (16.5) </p>

<p> 0.001 
 0.001 
0.02 
 0.01 
 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.001 
0.04 
0.51 
 0.001 
 0.001 
 0.01 
HaDS [mean (SD)] 
anxiety 
Depression </p>

<p>4.5 (3.7) 
4.0 (3.4) </p>

<p>2.9 (2.6) 
2.7 (2.4) </p>

<p>3.4 (2.6) 
3.2 (2.7) </p>

<p>7.4 (3.7) 
5.8 (3.5) </p>

<p>7.8 (3.8) 
7.0 (4.0) </p>

<p> 0.001 
 0.001 </p>

<p>Only those who completed two or more questionnaires were included in the analyses. 
a higher score on the EORTC QLQ-C30 and EORTC QLQ-CR38 functional scales, global QOL scale and single items (i.e. body image, 
sexual functioning, sexual enjoyment and future perspective) represent a higher level of function. For the symptom scales and single items, 
a higher score represents a higher level of symptoms. 
a p-Value represents the difference between the four personality groups; b Clinically relevant differences between the Type D group (Na SI) 
and the reference group (Na-SI-) and between the Na only group (Na SI-) and the reference group (Na-SI-) according the guidelines 
[20]; c this question was filled out by a small number of patients. </p>



<p>they reported more insomnia, diarrhea, constipa-
tion, gastrointestinal-, defecation-, stoma-related-, 
and female sexual problems, and a worse body 
image and future perspective compared to the refer-
ence group, even after controlling for sociodemo-
graphic and clinical variables. High Na patients 
reported similar poor outcomes as Type Ds. How-
ever, they also reported a lower social functioning 
and more fatigue, pain, micturition-and financial </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>CRC survivors with a Type D personality and those 
with high Na reported a significantly worse HRQoL 
and disease-specific health status and these differ-
ences were quite stable over time. Furthermore, 
linear mixed effects models showed that Type D 
patients had a lower quality of life, cognitive and 
emotional functioning, and sexual enjoyment, and </p>

<p>Figure 1. The most relevant EORTC QLQ-C30 and EORTC QLQ-CR38 subscales regarding survivorship over time stratified by 
personality. Only those who completed two or more questionnaires were included in the analyses. a selection of the EORTC QLQ-C30 
and EORTC QLQ-CR38 subscales that are most relevant with respect to survivorship are included in this figure [21]. </p>

<p>Personality, quality of life and disease-specific health status 675 </p>

<p>problems, while Type D individuals reported more 
sexual problems and less sexual enjoyment. 
To our knowledge, other studies that prospec-
tively describe the influence of Type D personality 
and its components on HRQoL and disease-specific 
health status among cancer patients are lacking. 
However, a prospective study among 144 CRC 
patients showed that personality variables can predict 
a decrease in HRQoL over a one-year period [11]. 
Furthermore, our results confirm those of a cross-
sectional study on Type D personality among 124 
Taiwanese CRC survivors that also reported that 
Type D personality was an important factor associ-
ated with QoL [22]. Finally, prospective studies 
among cardiovascular patients also showed that Type 
D personality has a negative influence on HRQoL 
and disease-specific health status [23-26]. 
Importantly, our study showed that the Na com-
ponent of Type D was more prominent than SI in 
predicting worse patient-reported outcomes. This 
suggests that Na should be the primary focus when 
evaluating personality-related differences in patient-
reported outcomes. Other studies also suggested that </p>

<p>the Na component of Type D is the key predictor of 
subjective health outcomes in both healthy [27] and 
cardiac populations [28]. The specific combination 
of Na and SI in the Type D construct may be more 
important regarding the risk of adverse cardiac 
events. a recent study in 541 patients with coronary 
artery disease showed that Type D personality was 
associated with cardiac death and myocardial infarc-
tion, while patients with high Na or SI alone were 
not at an increased risk [29]. 
The present study has some limitations. although 
we had sociodemographic and clinical information 
of non-respondents, it remains unknown whether 
they declined to participate because of poor health. 
Furthermore, personality traits like neuroticism or a 
low sense of coherence are also known to exert influ-
ence on HRQoL and we did not take them into 
account. Finally, although Type D personality is a 
stable construct [30], and although this is a prospec-
tive study, our analyses limit the determination of 
causal association between personality and patient-
reported outcomes as baseline data on these out-
comes are unknown. The strengths of this study are </p>

<p>Table II. generalized linear mixed model estimating effects of Type D personality on the most relevant EORTC QLQ-C30 and EORTC 
QLQ-CR38 subscales regarding survivorship over time, mutually adjusted for sociodemographic and clinical characteristics. </p>

<p>EORTC-QLQ-C30 
EORTC-QLQ-CR38 </p>

<p>global quality 
of life 
Beta and 95% CI </p>

<p>Fatigue 
Beta and 95% CI </p>

<p>Pain 
Beta and 95% CI </p>

<p>Insomnia 
Beta and 95% CI </p>

<p>Body image 
Beta and 95% CI </p>

<p>Future perspective 
Beta and 95% CI </p>

<p>Sexual enjoyment 
Beta and 95% CI </p>

<p>Sex 
Female 
vs. male </p>

<p>2.0 
0.8-3.1 ** 23.9 25.5-22.3 ** 24.9 26.7-23.1 ** 210.7 212.9-28.6 ** 
0.6 21.2-2.3 
3.7 
1.8-5.7 ** 
11.8 
8.3-15.2 ** </p>

<p>age a 
0.1 
0.1-0.2 ** 20.1 20.2-0.01 * 
20.2 20.3-20.1 ** 20.1 
20.2-20.1 * 
0.3 
0.2-0.3 ** 
0.3 
0.2-0.4 ** 20.4 20.6-20.2 ** 
Time since 
diagnosis a </p>

<p>0.3 
0.1-0.5 ** 20.5 20.7-20.2 ** 20.3 20.6-0.1 
20.4 
20.8-20.1 * 
0.6 
0.3-0.9 ** 
1.0 
0.6-1.3 ** 
0.1 20.4-0.7 </p>

<p>Stage 
Stage I vs. IV 
Stage II vs. IV 
Stage III vs. IV </p>

<p>20.4 
20.5 
0.8 </p>

<p>23.9-3.1 
24.0-2.9 
22.6-4.1 </p>

<p>23.9 
23.6 
24.4 </p>

<p>28.6-0.8 
28.2-1.0 
28.8-0.1 </p>

<p>22.1 
21.4 
20.9 </p>

<p>27.3-3.0 
26.5-3.7 
25.8-4.0 </p>

<p>2.2 
0.9 
2.2 </p>

<p>24.3-8.6 
25.4-7.2 
23.9-8.3 </p>

<p>24.8 
23.9 
23.2 </p>

<p>29.9-0.4 
28.9-1.2 
28.0-1.7 </p>

<p>12.3 
10.7 
9.6 </p>

<p>6.6-18.0 ** 
5.0-16.3 ** 
4.2-15.1 ** </p>

<p>24.1 
22.4 
24.0 </p>

<p>213.5-5.4 
211.6-6.9 
212.9-4.9 
Chemotherapy 
yes vs. no </p>

<p>1.1 20.6-2.7 
21.2 23.4-1.0 
0.9 21.5-3.3 
0.1 
22.9-3.1 
1.7 20.8-4.0 
0.3 
22.4-3.0 
20.6 25.0-3.8 </p>

<p>Comorbid 
conditions a </p>

<p>22.3 22.7-22.0 ** 2.6 
2.2-3.0 ** 
4.0 
3.5-4.5 ** 
1.9 
1.3-2.5 ** 
20.6 21.1-20.2 ** 21.8 
22.4-21.3 ** 
0.1 20.8-1.0 </p>

<p>Partner 
no vs. yes </p>

<p>0.6 20.7-2.0 
21.8 23.6-20.1 * 22.7 24.7-20.6 * 24.6 
27.1-22.2 ** 20.7 22.7-1.3 
0.8 
21.4-3.1 
1.6 22.8-6.0 </p>

<p>Education 
High vs. Middle 
High vs. Low </p>

<p>0.2 
0.1 </p>

<p>21.1-1.5 
21.7-1.9 </p>

<p>0.1 
21.1 </p>

<p>21.7-1.7 
23.4-1.3 </p>

<p>0.6 
1.1 </p>

<p>21.4-2.5 
21.5-3.8 </p>

<p>0.6 
20.1 </p>

<p>21.8-2.9 
23.2-3.2 </p>

<p>1.0 
2.3 </p>

<p>20.8-2.8 
20.1-4.9 </p>

<p>0.8 
1.6 </p>

<p>21.3-3.0 
21.3-4.6 </p>

<p>20.1 
23.7 </p>

<p>23.4-3.3 
28.8-1.5 
Time 
T2 vs. T1 
T3 vs. T1 </p>

<p>21.1 
21.3 </p>

<p>21.9-20.3 ** 
22.2-20.4 ** </p>

<p>0.2 
0.8 </p>

<p>20.8-1.1 
20.3-1.8 </p>

<p>0.7 
0.7 </p>

<p>20.5-1.8 
20.6-1.9 </p>

<p>20.5 
0.7 </p>

<p>21.8-0.7 
20.7-2.2 </p>

<p>1.1 
0.4 </p>

<p>0.1-2.1 * 
20.7-1.5 </p>

<p>1.5 
0.6 </p>

<p>0.2-2.7 * 
20.8-2.0 </p>

<p>0.4 
21.1 </p>

<p>21.8-2.5 
22.5-2.3 
Depression a 
22.2 22.4-22.1 ** 2.5 
2.3-2.7 ** 
1.7 
1.5-1.9 ** 
1.6 
1.3-1.9 ** 
21.8 22.0-21.6 ** 22.2 
22.5-2.0 ** 21.5 22.0-21.1 ** 
Type D 
Na-/SI 
vs. Na-/SI-
Na/SI-
vs. Na-/SI-
Na/SI 
vs. Na-/SI-</p>

<p>20.7 </p>

<p>23.5 </p>

<p>22.3 </p>

<p>22.3-0.8 </p>

<p>25.5-21.6 ** </p>

<p>23.9-20.6 ** </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>5.1 </p>

<p>1.8 </p>

<p>21.9-2.3 </p>

<p>2.5-7.7 ** </p>

<p>20.4-4.0 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>3.3 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>21.9-2.7 </p>

<p>0.5-6.2 * </p>

<p>22.3-2.6 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>8.0 </p>

<p>4.3 </p>

<p>22.8-3.0 </p>

<p>4.5-11.6 ** </p>

<p>1.3-7.3 ** </p>

<p>21.0 </p>

<p>26.2 </p>

<p>24.9 </p>

<p>23.3-1.3 </p>

<p>29.0-23.3 ** </p>

<p>27.3-22.5 ** </p>

<p>20.5 </p>

<p>211.1 </p>

<p>27.5 </p>

<p>23.1-2.1 </p>

<p>214.2-27.9 ** </p>

<p>210.2-24.8 ** </p>

<p>24.7 </p>

<p>3.9 </p>

<p>26.4 </p>

<p>29.0-20.5 * </p>

<p>21.5-9.2 </p>

<p>210.9-22.0 ** </p>

<p>Only those who completed two or more questionnaires were included in the analyses. 
a selection of the EORTC QLQ-C30 and EORTC QLQ-CR38 subscales that are most relevant with respect to survivorship are included 
in this figure [21]. 
a Continuous variables are grand-mean centered; * p  0.05; ** p  0.01. </p>



<p>that we assessed HRQoL and disease-specific health 
status prospectively in a large population-based set-
ting which provides information on the persistence 
of these constructs over time in a representative 
group of CRC patients in daily practice. 
Type D personality and high Na were associated 
with poor HRQoL and disease-specific health status 
among survivors of CRC, even after controlling for 
sociodemographic and clinical variables. By taking a 
patient's personality into account, this study offers a 
different view on personalized medicine. Evaluating 
HRQoL and disease-specific health status according 
to personality is of great value as this informs about 
the disease burden and treatment-related effects 
directly from the patients' perspective. This informa-
tion will help clinicians to inform CRC patients 
about potential late side effects. Furthermore, this 
can possibly lead to the development and evaluation 
of strategies for tailored long-term management and 
support for survivors on the basis of a more indi-
vidualized approach, as a function of stable differ-
ences in coping with chronic medical conditions. For 
example, mindfulness-based stress reduction may 
reduce levels of negative affectivity and social inhibi-
tion [31]. Paying attention to the recognition of Na 
seems warranted as these patients reported a worse 
HRQoL and disease-specific health status. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We would like to thank all patients and their doctors 
for their participation in the study. Special thanks go </p>

<p>to Dr. M. van Bommel, who was willing to function 
as an independent advisor and to answer questions 
of patients. In addition, we want to thank the follow-
ing hospitals for their cooperation: amphia Hospital, 
Breda; Bernhoven Hospital, Veghel and Oss; Catharina 
Hospital, Eindhoven; Elkerliek Hospital, Helmond; 
Jeroen Bosch Hospital, 's Hertogenbosch; Maxima 
Medical Centre, Eindhoven and Veldhoven; Sint anna 
Hospital, geldrop; St. Elisabeth Hospital, Tilburg; 
Twee Steden Hospital, Tilburg and Waalwijk; VieCury 
Hospital, Venlo and Venray. The present research was 
supported by a VENI grant (#451-10-041) from the 
Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research (The 
Hague, The Netherlands) awarded to Floortje Mols. </p>

<p>Declaration of interest: The authors report no 
conflicts of interest. The authors alone are respon-
sible for the content and writing of the paper. </p>



</text></tei>