<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4468934" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 
Dovepress </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2983 </p>

<p>O r i g i n a l r e s e a r c h </p>

<p>open access to scientific and medical research </p>

<p>Open access Full Text article </p>

<p>http://dx.Abstract: Galangin is an active pharmacological ingredient from propolis and Alpinia 
officinarum Hance, and has been reported to have anti-inflammatory and antioxidative prop-
erties. The present study aims to reveal the effect of galangin on Concanavalin A (ConA)-
induced hepatitis (CIH), a well-established animal model of immune-mediated liver injury, 
and to clarify the related mechanism. C57BL/6 mice were pretreated with galangin followed 
by ConA challenge. Results indicated that galangin inhibited ConA-induced liver damage. 
Mice pretreated with galangin showed more reduction of liver damage when compared with 
control mice pretreated with vehicle solution. In galangin-pretreated mice with induced CIH, 
increases in serum levels of several inflammatory cytokines, including tumor necrosis factor-α, 
interferon-γ, and interleukin-12 were dramatically attenuated, and chemokines and adhesion 
molecules like interferon inducible protein-10, macrophage inflammatory protein-1α, and inter-
cellular adhesion molecule-1 messenger RNA expressions in liver were decreased. Moreover, 
CIH mice pretreated with galangin showed less leukocyte infiltration and T-cell activation in 
the liver. Further, the mechanism of the anti-inflammatory effects of galangin may be attributed 
to its modulation of crucial inflammatory signaling pathways, including nuclear factor kappa B 
and interferon-gamma/signal transducer and activator of transcription 1. Collectively, these 
findings suggest the preventive and therapeutic potential of galangin in immune-mediated 
liver injury in vivo. 
Hepatitis, caused by virus infection, autoimmunity, alcoholism, and certain drugs, 
is a serious threat to human health and a worldwide problem. In the pathogenesis of 
various hepatitides, excessive or misdirected immune stimulation is considered to 
play a critical role. 
1-3 Concanavalin A (ConA)-induced hepatitis (CIH) in mice is a 
well-established experimental model for immune-mediated liver injury and has been 
widely used in studies of the pathogenesis and clinical treatment of immune hepatitis 
in humans. In CIH, inflammatory cells, such as T-cells, natural killer T-cells, mac-
rophages, and neutrophils, infiltrate the liver and produce a variety of hepatotoxic 
inflammatory cytokines, including interferon (IFN)-γ, tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α, 
interleukin (IL)-1β, and IL-12, 
4,5 which finally leads to massive apoptosis and necrosis 
of hepatocytes and marked elevation of serum transaminases. 
Galangin (3,5,7-trihydroxyflavone; Figure 1A) is a naturally active flavonoid 
extracted from propolis and the root of Alpinia officinarum Hance, a plant that has been 
used as a spice and as a herbal medicine for various ailments in Asia for centuries. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>The biological activity of galangin includes antimutagenic, anticlastogenic, antioxi-
dative, radical scavenging, metabolic enzyme-modulating, bactericidal, antifibrotic, </p>

<p>correspondence: lili Xu 
Division of gastroenterology, Zhongshan 
hospital, Fudan University, no 180, 
Fenglin road, shanghai 200032, 
People's republic of china 
email xu.lili3@zs-hospital.sh.cn </p>

<p>Fuxiang chen 
Department of clinical immunology, 
shanghai ninth People's hospital, 
shanghai JiaoTong University school 
of Medicine, no 639, Zhizaoju road, 
shanghai 200011, People's republic 
of china 
email chenfx@sjtu.edu.cn </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Drug Design, Development and Therapy 
10 June 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2984 </p>

<p>luo et al </p>

<p>and antitumor effects. 
6-8 There is also some recent evidence 
indicating that galangin has anti-inflammatory activity, which 
has attracted increasing attention. Galangin was shown to 
inhibit mast cell-derived allergic inflammation. 
9 Galangin 
also showed anti-inflammatory effects on collagen-induced 
arthritis via attenuation of RANKL-induced activation of 
Janus kinase, p38, and nuclear factor kappa B (NF-κB) path-
ways. 
10 Moreover, galangin dampened lipopolysaccharide-
induced acute lung injury and inhibited atopic dermatitis-like 
skin lesions. 
11,12 However, the effect of galangin on CIH has 
not yet been studied. </p>

<p>In this study, we demonstrated that pretreatment with 
galangin dramatically inhibited development of CIH in mice. 
In mice with CIH, the increases in serum aminotransferases, 
cytokine production, hepatic necroinflammation, and apopto-
sis were markedly attenuated by administration of galangin. 
Intrahepatic inflammatory cell infiltration and activation 
was also decreased by galangin. We also investigated the 
signaling pathways involved in the anti-inflammatory effects 
of galangin. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Mice </p>

<p>Male C57BL/6 mice aged 8-10 weeks were purchased from 
Shanghai SLAC Laboratory Animal Co Ltd (Shanghai, 
People's Republic of China). The mice were housed in 
the animal care facilities of the Ninth People's Hospital, 
Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine, under 
pathogen-free conditions. Animal welfare and experimental 
procedures were carried out strictly in accordance with 
the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals 
(Ministry of Science and Technology of China, 2006) and 
approved by the hospital's laboratory animal care and use 
committee. </p>

<p>galangin treatment and induction of cih </p>

<p>Galangin (purity $95%, determined by high-performance 
liquid chromatography; Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA) 
was dissolved in dimethyl sulfoxide (Sigma-Aldrich) and 
diluted with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) for use (the 
final concentration of dimethyl sulfoxide in the solution 
was 10%). Mice in the treated group received galangin by 
intraperitoneal injection at a dose of 25 mg/kg or 50 mg/kg. 
Four hours later, the galangin injection was repeated. Control 
mice received equivalent vehicle solution. After the second 
injection of galangin or vehicle, all mice were injected with 
ConA (Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA, USA) dis-
solved in PBS via the tail vein (15 mg/kg). </p>

<p>Measurement of serum aminotransferase 
activity </p>

<p>Blood samples were collected from the mice at different time 
points after ConA injection. Serum alanine aminotransferase 
(ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) activities were 
determined by the velocity method according to the manu-
facturer's instructions using the Siemens Dimension RXL 
MAX Clinical Chemistry Analyzer (Dade Behring Inc., 
Newark, NJ, USA). </p>

<p>Figure 1 effect of galangin on serum aminotransferases. 
Notes: (A) Molecular structure of galangin. (B) c57Bl/6 mice, n=5 per group, 
received vehicle or galangin (25 or 50 mg/kg) by intraperitoneal injection. Four 
hours later, galangin injection was repeated. control mice received equivalent 
vehicle solution accordingly. after the second injection of galangin or vehicle, all 
mice were injected with a single dose (15 mg/kg) of concanavalin a via the tail vein. 
Mice were euthanized at the indicated time points and serum levels of alT and asT 
were measured. The results are shown as the mean ± standard deviation. Data are 
representative of three experiments. *P,0.05, **P,0.01, ***P,0.001. 
Abbreviations: alT, alanine transaminase; asT, aspartate transaminase. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2985 </p>

<p>Protective effect of galangin in cih </p>

<p>liver histology and TUnel staining </p>

<p>Eight hours after ConA injection, mice develop significant 
liver injury. 
5,13 Thus, we chose this time point for examination 
of liver pathology. Livers were removed after perfusion with 
PBS, fixed with 4% phosphate-buffered paraformaldehyde, 
and embedded in paraffin. Tissue sections (5 µm) were 
prepared and stained with hematoxylin-eosin. For TUNEL 
(terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase (TdT)-mediated 
dUTP-biotin nick end labeling) staining, paraffin-embedded 
liver tissues were assayed for DNA fragmentation using a 
TUNEL reaction, according to the instructions provided by 
the manufacturer (Roche Molecular Biochemicals, India-
napolis, IN, USA). All sections were examined under light 
microscopy. A total of ten tissue sections were analyzed for 
each animal. </p>

<p>analysis of serum cytokines </p>

<p>Serum concentrations of TNF-α, IFN-γ, and IL-12p70 were 
determined using a specific enzyme-linked immunosorbent 
assay kit (R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA) accord-
ing to the manufacturer's instructions. As has been reported 
previously, cytokines reach their peak concentrations at dif-
ferent time points. 
14-16 Thus, TNF-α was measured 2 hours 
after ConA injection and the other cytokines were measured 
8 hours after ConA injection. </p>

<p>rna extraction and reverse 
transcription </p>

<p>Total RNA was isolated from the frozen liver tissues using 
TRIzol reagent (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA) 
according to the protocol provided by the manufacturer. 
Genomic DNA was removed from total RNA prior to syn-
thesis of complementary DNA using the RNase-free DNase 
set for DNase digestion during RNA purification (Qiagen, 
Hilden, Germany). RNA was stored at -80°C. First-strand 
complementary DNA synthesis was performed for each RNA 
sample using the Sensiscript RT kit (Qiagen). Random hex-
amers were used to prime complementary DNA synthesis. </p>

<p>real-time polymerase chain reaction </p>

<p>Messenger (m)RNA expression of IFN-inducible protein 
(IP)-10, macrophage inflammatory protein (MIP)-1α, and 
intercellular adhesion molecule (ICAM)-1 was investigated 
by real-time polymerase chain reaction using SYBR Green 
master mix (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). 
Thermocycler conditions comprised an initial holding at 50°C 
for 2 minutes, then 95°C for 10 minutes. This was followed by 
a two-step polymerase chain reaction program consisting of </p>

<p>95°C for 15 seconds and 60°C for 60 seconds for 40 cycles. 
Data were collected and quantitatively analyzed on an ABI 
Prism 7500 sequence detection system (Applied Biosystems). 
The β-actin gene was used as an endogenous control to normal-
ize for differences in the amount of total RNA in each sample. 
All quantities were expressed as number of folds relative to 
the expression of β-actin. Primer sequences were as follows: 
β-actin, sense 5′-TGTCCACCTTCCAGCAGATGT-3′, 
antisense 5′-AGCTCAGTAACAGTCCGCCTAGA-3′; 
MIP-1α, sense 5′-CACCCTCTGTCACCTGCTCAA-3′, 
antisense 5′-ATGGCGCTGAGAAGACTTGGT-3′; 
IP-10, sense 5′-GCCGTCATTTTCTG CCTC-3′, anti-
sense 5′-ATGGCGCTGAGAAGACTTGGT-3′; ICAM-1, 
sense 5′-CCATCACCGTGTATTCGTTTCC-3′, antisense 
5′-CTGGCGGCTCAGTATCTCCTC-3′. </p>

<p>isolation of hepatic leukocytes </p>

<p>Isolation of intrahepatic leukocytes was performed as 
described previously. 
17 Briefly, the mice livers were removed 
and pressed through a 70 µm cell strainer. The liver cells were 
suspended in PBS and centrifuged at 50× g for 5 minutes. 
Supernatants containing mononuclear cells were collected, 
washed in PBS, and resuspended in 40% Percoll. The cell 
suspension was gently overlaid onto 70% Percoll and cen-
trifuged for 30 minutes at 750× g. Mononuclear cells were 
collected from the interphase, washed twice in PBS, and 
resuspended in PBS for analysis by fluorescence-activated 
cell sorting. The intrahepatic leukocytes were also observed 
and counted under a light microscope. </p>

<p>Flow cytometry </p>

<p>Single-cell suspensions of liver or spleen mononuclear cells 
were washed in PBS containing 1% bovine serum albu-
min. The cells were stained with fluorochrome-conjugated 
monoclonal antibody for 30 minutes on ice. The following 
antibodies were used: anti-CD3e, anti-NK1.1, anti-Gr-1, 
anti-CD11b, and anti-CD69 (BD Pharmingen, San Diego, 
CA, USA). Samples were acquired on a FACSCalibur flow 
cytometer (BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA) and 
the data were analyzed by <rs type="software">FlowJo</rs> software. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>Liver homogenates were lysed in RIPA buffer (150 mmol/L 
NaCl, 10 mmol/L Tris-HCl [pH 8.0], 1% Nonidet P-40, 0.5% 
deoxycholic acid, 0.1% sodium dodecyl sulfate, 5 mmol/L 
ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid) containing 0.7% phenyl-
methylsulfonyl fluoride, 0.2% aprotinin, and 0.2% leupeptin 
and sodium metavanadate. Samples containing 100 µg of </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2986 </p>

<p>luo et al </p>

<p>protein were incubated at 100°C for 5 minutes, separated 
by 10% (w/v) sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel 
electrophoresis, and electrophoretically transferred onto 
a polyvinylidene difluoride transfer membrane (Bio-Rad 
Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA). The nonspecific sites 
were blocked with a solution containing 5% non-fat milk 
powder in Tris-buffered saline/Tween 20 (TBST) for 2 hours 
at room temperature. The membrane was incubated with 
antibodies against β-actin (Sigma-Aldrich), IκBα (44D4), 
phospho-IκBα (pIκBα) (Ser32/36, 5A5), signal transducer 
and activator of transcription 1 (STAT1), and pSTAT1 
(Ser727; Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, USA) 
in TBST containing 5% bovine serum albumin overnight at 
4°C, then with horseradish peroxidase-conjugated second 
antibodies (anti-rabbit IgG [Sigma-Aldrich] and anti-mouse 
immunoglobulin G [Cell Signaling Technology], at a dilu-
tion of 1/5,000 and 1/2,000, respectively). Protein bands 
were visualized using chemiluminescence reagent (Thermo 
Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>All results are expressed as the mean ± standard deviation. 
The Student's t-test was used for the statistical analysis. 
P,0.05 was considered to be statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results 
galangin inhibited cona-induced 
aminotransferase release in a dose-
dependent manner </p>

<p>It has been shown that galangin has anti-inflammatory 
activity; 
9,10 however, whether galangin plays a role in CIH 
is not clear. In order to clarify the effect of galangin in CIH, 
we pretreated mice with galangin at two different doses (25 
mg/kg or 50 mg/kg) before injection of ConA. Mice were 
euthanized at different time points after induction of CIH, 
and serum levels of ALT and AST were measured for each 
mouse. As shown in Figure 1B, mice treated with galangin 
showed much lower serum ALT and AST activity in both the 
acute phase and the recovery stage, as compared with mice 
in the vehicle-injected control group. Moreover, galangin 
inhibited ConA-induced aminotransferase release in a 
dose-dependent manner. Mice receiving a 25 mg/kg dose of 
galangin showed more than half the reduction in ALT and 
AST release when compared with control mice, and in mice 
pretreated with 50 mg/kg galangin, the elevation of ALT 
and AST levels induced by ConA was almost completely 
suppressed. These data strongly suggest that the protective 
effect of galangin was permanent in the development of </p>

<p>ConA-induced liver injury. We tried a higher dose of galangin 
(100 mg/kg), but did not observe further inhibition of release 
of ConA-induced aminotransferases (data not shown). Thus, 
the dose of galangin used in the following experiments was 
50 mg/kg. </p>

<p>galangin ameliorated cona-induced liver 
damage </p>

<p>We then examined the effect of galangin on ConA-induced 
liver damage using hematoxylin-eosin and TUNEL stain-
ing. Mice administered ConA suffered severe liver damage, 
indicated by inflammatory infiltration around the central 
veins and large areas of centrilobular necrosis and apoptosis 
of hepatocytes (Figure 2A shows hematoxylin-eosin stain-
ing, Figure 2C shows TUNEL staining). However, mice 
pretreated with galangin (50 mg/kg) showed minimal liver 
damage: in these mice, fewer areas of intralobular necrosis 
or inflammatory infiltration were observed (Figure 2B, 
hematoxylin-eosin staining) and only a few hepatocytes 
exhibited TUNEL-positive nuclei (Figure 2D, TUNEL 
staining), indicating that apoptosis was markedly reduced 
in galangin-pretreated mice. </p>

<p>galangin inhibited release 
of inflammatory cytokines in CIH mice </p>

<p>Previous studies indicate that immune cells are activated 
after ConA injection and that, as a result, a number of cytok-
ines are released that aggravate liver injury. 
4,5 We therefore 
examined the influence of galangin on serum TNF-α, IFN-γ, 
and IL-12 levels, given that these cytokines are reported to 
play an important role in the development of ConA-induced 
liver injury. 
4,5 As shown in Figure 3, production of TNF-α, 
IFN-γ, and IL-12 was inhibited in galangin-pretreated 
mice when compared vehicle-pretreated mice (P,0.01 
for TNF-α and IFN-γ, and P,0.001 for IL-12). These data 
demonstrate that galangin effectively suppressed produc-
tion of various disease-related cytokines, thereby reducing 
the damage to liver tissues caused by these inflammatory 
mediators. </p>

<p>galangin inhibited chemokine and 
adhesion molecule expression in the liver </p>

<p>Upregulated expression of chemokines and adhesion mol-
ecules such as IP-10, MIP-1α, and ICAM-1 has been reported 
to play a critical role in the development of CIH. 
18-20 Thus, we 
further studied the changes in IP-10, MIP-1α and ICAM-1 
mRNA expression in the livers of mice with or without 
galangin pretreatment. Liver tissue RNA was obtained </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2987 </p>

<p>Protective effect of galangin in cih </p>

<p>8 hours after ConA injection, and mRNA expression of IP-10, 
MIP-1α, and ICAM-1 was measured. As shown in Figure 4, 
the mRNA levels of these three genes were all dramatically 
reduced by pretreatment with galangin (P,0.01 for IP-10, 
and P,0.05 for MIP-1α and ICAM-1). </p>

<p>galangin prevented cona-induced 
inflammatory cell recruitment and 
activation in the liver </p>

<p>To further study the profiles of the infiltrated inflammatory 
cells in the liver, we analyzed intrahepatic leukocytes by 
fluorescence-activated cell sorting. CIH mice with or with-
out galangin pretreatment were euthanized 2 hours after 
ConA injection, and intrahepatic leukocytes in the liver </p>

<p>were obtained. The total number of intrahepatic leukocytes 
in galangin pretreated mice was remarkably decreased 
compared with that in mice without galangin administra-
tion (Figure 5A, P,0.01). Neutrophils (Gr-1+CD11b+), 
macrophages (CD11b+Gr-1-), and T-cells (CD3+NK1.1-) 
recruited into the liver were significantly reduced by galangin, 
as shown in Figure 5A. Moreover, galangin significantly 
inhibited T-cell activation in CIH mice, as CD3+CD69+T 
cell percent decreased dramatically (Figure 5B). However, 
there was no significant change in natural killer cells 
(CD3-NK1.1+) or natural killer T-cells (CD3+NK1.1+). 
Taken together, these results indicate that pretreatment with 
galangin influenced ConA-induced intrahepatic inflammatory 
cell infiltration and activation. </p>

<p>Figure 2 liver h&amp;e and TUnel staining. 
Notes: eight hours after concanavalin a injection, liver tissues were obtained and sectioned, then stained by h&amp;e or TUnel. h&amp;e staining for (A) vehicle-pretreated mice 
and (B) galangin-pretreated mice. TUnel staining for (C) vehicle-pretreated mice and (D) galangin-pretreated mice. Ten sections were observed in each animal. results are 
representative of five experiments. (H&amp;E, magnification ×100; TUNEL, magnification ×200). 
Abbreviations: h&amp;e, hematoxylin-eosin; TUnel, terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase (TdT)-mediated dUTP-biotin nick end labeling. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2988 </p>

<p>luo et al </p>

<p>galangin suppressed cona-induced nF-
κB activation and sTaT1 phosphorylation </p>

<p>Since the production of many inflammatory mediators, 
including the cytokines and chemokines mentioned above, 
depends on activation of the NF-κB signaling pathway, we 
analyzed the activation of NF-κB in mice received vehicle 
or galangin pretreatment and ConA injection. As shown in 
Figure 6, galangin significantly inhibited ConA-induced 
phosphorylation of IκBα, which is required for subsequent 
activation of NF-κB because it allows the NF-κB dimer to 
translocate into the nucleus and bind to the κB site. Therefore, 
more NF-κB complexes remained in an inactive state in the 
cytoplasm after pretreatment with galangin, leading to a weak 
response toward ConA stimulation. In addition, transcription 
factor STAT1, which is associated with the IFN-γ signaling 
pathway, is considered to be an important pathogenic media-
tor of T-cell activation in CIH. 
21,22 It has been reported that 
synthesis and activation of STAT1 is increased in the liver of 
the CIH mouse, and that STAT1 deficiency attenuates ConA-
induced liver damage. 
21,22 Therefore, we also investigated </p>

<p>the effect of galangin on activation of STAT1 in CIH. The 
data show that galangin effectively reduced phosphoryla-
tion of STAT1 (Figure 6A and B), suggesting that galangin 
decreased the release of IFN-γ and suppressed the STAT1 
signaling pathway. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In the present study, we showed that galangin was able to pro-
tect against immune-mediated liver injury in mice with CIH. 
Histological staining indicated that liver inflammation and 
apoptosis of hepatocytes were clearly reduced in galangin-
pretreated mice. Galangin also significantly reduced the 
expression and release of various disease-related cytokines 
and chemokines. Moreover, galangin inhibited infiltration 
and activation of intrahepatic inflammatory cells. The protec-
tive effects of galangin may be attributed to its suppression 
of activation of NF-κB and STAT1 signaling pathway. 
Galangin, a member of the flavonol class of flavonoids, 
has multiple pharmacological activities, including anticancer, </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>antioxidative, 
6 antiviral, 
23 antimicrobial, 
24 and vasorelaxant </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>α 
γ </p>

<p>Figure 3 Influence of galangin on serum cytokines. 
Notes: c57Bl/6 mice received vehicle or galangin pretreatment and cona injection. (A) Two hours after injection of cona, serum was obtained and TnF-α was measured 
by elisa. eight hours after cona injection, serum iFn-γ (B) and il-12 (C) were measured by elisa. Data are shown as the mean ± standard deviation. The results are 
representative of three experiments. **P,0.01, ***P,0.001. 
Abbreviations: cona, concanavalin a; elisa, enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay; iFn-γ, interferon gamma; il-12, interleukin-12; TnF-α, tumor necrosis factor alpha. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2989 </p>

<p>Protective effect of galangin in cih </p>

<p>effects. Recently, the anti-inflammatory effect of galangin 
has been attracting increasing attention. Galangin has been 
reported to reduce IL-1β, TNF-α, and IL-17 concentrations 
and to attenuate activation of the Janus kinase, p38, and 
NF-κB pathways, thus reducing the severity of collagen-in-
duced arthritis in mice. 
10 Galangin also abrogated ovalbumin-
induced airway inflammation by modulating the expression 
of several related cytokines, including IL-4, IL-5, and IL-13, 
and chemokines such as monocyte chemoattractant protein-1, 
C-X-C motif chemokine 10, and vascular cell adhesion protein 
1, thereby reducing infiltration and activation of eosinophil. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>In addition, several other groups have demonstrated that 
galangin inhibits atopic dermatitis-like lesions and dampens 
lipopolysaccharide-induced acute lung injury in mice. 
11,12 Our 
observations of the beneficial effects of galangin on CIH are 
consistent with previous reports. In particular, we demon-
strated for the first time that galangin has marked protective 
effects against immune-mediated liver injury. 
Previous studies have reported that TNF-α and IFN-γ play 
a critical role in the pathogenesis of CIH. 
14,27 TNF-α, secreted 
from activated macrophages and T-cells, binds to its receptors 
and induces an apoptotic cascade, thus acting as a major </p>

<p>mediator in inflammation-induced hepatocyte death. 
27 Mice 
pretreated with anti-TNF-α antiserum or a TNF-α inhibitor 
and mice deficient in the TNF-α receptor exhibited obvious 
resistance to CIH. IFN-γ exerts pathogenic effects by syner-
gizing with TNF-α to promote production of various chemo-
kines and adhesion molecules. 
14,28 In addition, IFN-γ induces 
phosphorylation of STAT1, which leads to expression of 
proapoptotic genes and contributes to CIH. 
29 Besides TNF-α 
and IFN-γ, IL-12 has also been found to be important in the 
pathogenesis of CIH. Exogenous IL-12 administration prior 
to ConA injection exacerbated liver damage, and anti-IL-12 
monoclonal antibody pretreatment prevented ConA-induced 
liver injury. 
15 In our study, galangin pretreatment reversed 
the increase in production of these pathogenic inflammatory 
cytokines in CIH, thereby suppressing activation of T-cells 
and alleviating the liver injury. 
We found that galangin was able to inhibit IP-10, 
MIP-1α, and ICAM-1 mRNA expression in the livers of 
CIH mice. During the first few hours after injection of 
ConA, production of proinflammatory cytokines followed 
by expression of chemotactic factors such as IP-10, MIP-1α, 
and ICAM-1, which attract leukocytes to the liver, amplifies </p>

<p>Figure 4 effects of galangin on chemokine and adhesion molecule messenger (m)rna expression. 
Notes: eight hours after injection of concanavalin a, liver rna from mice was obtained and mrna expression levels of (A) IP-10, (B) MIP-1α, and (C) ICAM-1 were 
quantitatively analyzed by real-time polymerase chain reaction. results are representative of three experiments. *P,0.05, **P,0.01. 
Abbreviations: IP-10, iFn-inducible protein-10; MIP-1α, macrophage inflammatory protein-1 alpha; ICAM-1, intercellular adhesion molecule-1. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2990 </p>

<p>luo et al </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>1,000 
800 
600 
400 
200 
1,000 
800 
600 
400 
200 
200 400 600 800 1,000 
200 400 600 800 1,000 </p>

<p>SSC-H 
SSC-H </p>

<p>FSC-H 
FSC-H </p>

<p>Gr-1-PE 
NK1.1-PE 
CD69-APC </p>

<p>Vehicle </p>

<p>Galangin </p>

<p>Vehicle </p>

<p>Galangin </p>

<p>CD11b-FITC 
CD3e-FITC 
CD3e-FITC </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>% gated </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Vehicle </p>

<p>Galangin </p>

<p>60 
40 
20 
0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Cell number (×10 6 ) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>T 
o 
t 
a 
l 
I 
H 
L 
s 
C 
D 
1 
1 
b 
+ 
G 
r 
-
1 
+ 
C 
D 
1 
1 
b 
+ 
G 
r 
-
1 
-
C 
D 
3 
+ 
N 
K 
1 
. 
1 
-
C 
D 
3 
+ 
N 
K 
1 
. 
1 
+ 
C 
D 
3 
-
N 
K 
1 
. 
1 
+ </p>

<p>15 
10 
5 
0 </p>

<p>Vehicle 
Galangin </p>

<p>Figure 5 Influence of galangin on recruitment and activation of inflammatory cells. 
Notes: (A) ihls were isolated from vehicle-pretreated cih mice and galangin-pretreated cih mice (2 hours after injection of concanavalin a). The total number of ihls from each mouse was counted using a cell counting plate. ihls 
were stained with cD3e, cD11b, gr-1, and nK1.1. The number of each cell subset was calculated by multiplying the total number of ihls by the frequency of the subset. (B) ihls were stained with cD3e and cD69, and the percentage 
of activated T-cells was analyzed. Data are shown as the mean 
± standard deviation. The results are representative of three experiments. *P,0.05, **P,0.01. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CIH, Concanavalin A-induced hepatitis; FITC, fluorescein isothiocyanate; APC, allophycocyanin; PE, R-phycoerythrin; SCC-H, side scatter-height; FSC-H, forward scatter-height; IHLs, intrahepatic leukocytes. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2991 </p>

<p>Protective effect of galangin in cih </p>

<p>the local inflammatory damage. 
20,29 IP-10 has been found 
to play an important role in the hepatic neutrophil influx in 
CIH. 
19 MIP-1α is reported to promote recruitment of vari-
ous leukocyte subtypes, including T-cells, macrophages, 
and neutrophils. In mice with MIP-1α deficiency, hepatic 
injury induced by ConA was markedly attenuated. 
18 Fur-
ther, ICAM-1 has been shown to mediate adhesion and 
to support transendothelial migration of lymphocytes in 
the liver. 
20 A previous study demonstrated that ICAM-1 
deficiency significantly inhibited liver injury and T-cell 
recruitment in CIH. In the present study, we report, for 
the first time, that galangin is able to downregulate IP-10, 
MIP-1α, and ICAM-1 mRNA expression in the liver. Such 
downregulation, in turn, inhibited infiltration of leukocytes 
into the liver, thus reducing the severity of liver damage 
in CIH mice. 
We further investigated the mechanisms involved in the 
protective effect of galangin in CIH. One important signaling 
pathway in the regulation of these inflammatory mediators 
is activation of NF-κB. In resting cells, the NF-κB complex 
is retained in the cytoplasm by the inhibitory protein IκBα, 
and nuclear accumulation of NF-κB depends mainly on 
phosphorylation of IκBα and its subsequent degradation. 
Without the inhibitory effect of IκBα, NF-κB translocates 
from the cytoplasm to the nucleus to bind the κB site of </p>

<p>target genes. 
30 In the present study, we found that galangin 
decreased phosphorylation of IκBα, leading to less translo-
calization of NF-κB. Moreover, the pathogenic inflamma-
tory cytokine IFN-γ exerted its effects via activation of the 
Janus kinase-STAT signaling pathway. With the ligation 
of IFN-γ to its receptor, STAT1 was phosphorylated and 
dimerized, and then translocated into the nuclei to activate 
transcription of a number of genes, including those for IFN 
regulatory factor-1, Fas receptor, caspases, inducible nitric 
oxide synthase, cyclo-oxygenase, and intercellular cell adhe-
sion molecules, all of which are critically involved in the 
pathogenesis of CIH. 
29,31 We observed an obvious decrease 
of STAT1 phosphorylation after pretreatment with galangin. 
Therefore, we speculate that the protective effect of galangin 
in CIH is mediated by inhibition of the NF-κB and IFN-γ/ 
STAT1 signaling pathways. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Galangin attenuated ConA-induced liver injury in mice. The 
suppressive effect was attributed to inhibition of NF-κB 
and STAT1 signaling leading to the reduced expression and 
secretion of several inflammatory mediators. The results 
of this study suggest new opportunities to use galangin in 
the prevention and treatment of immune-mediated liver 
disease. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>ConA 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Vehicle 
Galangin 
0 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>-
Galangin </p>

<p>pIκBα </p>

<p>pIκBα </p>

<p>IκBα </p>

<p>STAT1 </p>

<p>pSTAT1 </p>

<p>pSTAT1 </p>

<p>β-actin 
%β-actin expression </p>

<p>%β-actin expression </p>

<p>Figure 6 effect of galangin on nF-κB and sTaT1 activation. 
Notes: Mice received vehicle or galangin pretreatment and cona injection. (A) Two hours after cona injection, iκBα, piκBα, sTaT1, and psTaT1 proteins in liver tissue 
were analyzed by Western blotting. (B) Band intensities of piκBα and pSTAT1 were quantified by <rs id="software-0" type="software">ImageProPlus</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0</rs> software. Densitometry confirms the decrease in IκBα 
and sTaT1 phosphorylation in response to galangin. The results are representative of three experiments. ***P,0.001. 
Abbreviations: cona, concanavalin a; nF-κB, nuclear factor kappa B; sTaT1, signal transducer and activator of transcription 1; p, phosphorylated. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/drug-design-development-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy is an international, peer-
reviewed open-access journal that spans the spectrum of drug design 
and development through to clinical applications. Clinical outcomes, 
patient safety, and programs for the development and effective, safe, 
and sustained use of medicines are a feature of the journal, which </p>

<p>has also been accepted for indexing on PubMed Central. The manu-
script management system is completely online and includes a very 
quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2992 </p>

<p>luo et al </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science 
Foundation of China (81200299 and 81472514) and the 
Medical Guide Program of Shanghai Municipal Science and 
Technology Commission (124119a9302). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



</text></tei>