<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4441238" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Introduction 
Endodontically treated teeth should be restored since there is 
a loss of structure, changes in physical characters, dehydration 
and altered esthetic of remaining tooth structure. Post and 
core with full coronal restoration is a common method to 
restore coronal portion of lost tooth structure. Dowel is a post 
placed in the root of a non-vital tooth to retain core portion. 1 
Endodontic post can be metallic or nan-metallic, custom 
made or prefabricated, esthetic or non-esthetic. Custom and 
metallic post was widely used to strengthen the endodontically 
treated teeth. With increase demand for esthetic and better 
physical quality, various tooth-colored posts such as glass fiber 
reinforced post, carbon fiber post, zirconia post, and composite 
post were developed. 1,2 Modulus of elasticity for stainless steel 
and titanium posts are 20 and 10 times greater than dentine, 
whereas glass fiber reinforced post are bonded to composite 
core and have modulus of elasticity nearly equal to that of 
dentine hence reduces possibility of root fracture. 2 There are 
very few published studies comparing fracture resistance of the 
metal and fiber posts. Hence the present study was aimed to 
compare the fracture resistance of endodontically treated teeth 
restored with different posts such as custom made, metallic, 
fiber reinforced and carbon reinforced posts. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
Totally 40 extracted maxillary incisors free from caries, fracture 
and cervical abrasion were collected for in vitro study and 
stored in normal saline at room temperature (24-28°C). Root 
canal treatment, followed by the obturation was carried out on 
selected specimens. The selected teeth were randomly assigned 
into four experimental groups with ten in each group (Group A: 
Custom post, Group B: Stain less metal post, Group C: Fiber 
reinforced post, Group D: Carbon fiber reinforced post). The 
samples were decoronated at cemento-enamel junction and 
endodontically treated. Post space was prepared and selected 
posts were cemented. </p>

<p>In all groups, post space preparation was done by removing 
the gutta-percha with peeso-reamer and leaving 4 mm of 
gutta-percha apically. In Group A, direct inlay pattern of post 
and core was prepared. The pattern was casted With Type III </p>



<p>Journal of International Oral Health 2015; 7(5):53-55 
Fracture resistance of custom made, metal post, glass fiber reinforced and carbon 
reinforced posts in endodontically treated teeth … Sonkesriya S et al </p>

<p>cast gold alloy. The post space was treated with chelating 
agent (Glyde Germany), and subsequently irrigated with 
5.25% sodium hypochlorite to remove the smear layer. The 
post and core were cemented with dual cure adhesive cement 
(Panvia F, Kuraray, Osaka, Japan). In Group B, C and D after 
post space preparation, selected posts (stainless steel, glass 
fiber reinforced and carbon reinforced posts) were cemented 
with dual cure resin cement and composite core build-up was 
done to the height of 5 mm. </p>

<p>All specimens were mounted on the acrylic block, and 
subjected to the compressive force at 1 mm diameter at an 
angle of 130° to long axis of the tooth using Instron Universal 
Testing Machine. The force at fracture was measured in MPa. 
Data were tabulated and statistically analyzed using analysis of 
variance and t-tests (<rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">21</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM</rs>). </p>

<p>Results 
In the present study carbon fiber reinforced posts and glass 
fiber reinforced posts showed highest fracture resistance as 
compared to custom post and metal posts (Table 1). Table 2 
showed that there was no significant difference between glass 
fiber (Group C) and carbon fiber posts (Group D) and between 
custom post (Group A) and metal posts (Group B, where as 
between other groups it is statistically significant (P &gt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Discussion 
Esthetic, functional, and structural rehabilitation of pulpless 
teeth is critically important for successful endodontic therapy. 1 
Clinically, longevity of post-core-crown system for endodontically 
treated teeth depends on the design, length and diameter of the 
post, ferrule effect, cementation and amount of remaining tooth 
substance. 2 Since many years custom post was used commonly 
for restoring endodontically treated teeth. Use of prefabricated 
posts reduced the laboratory and chair side time. Prefabricated 
posts are as available as metallic or fiber posts. In 1992, glass fiber 
posts were introduced. Fiber posts are strong, improves esthetics, 
reduces corrosion and toxicity. 2,3 Glass fiber posts are composed 
of unidirectional glass fibers embedded in a resin matrix which </p>

<p>increases the post strength without changes in modulus of 
elasticity. In a glass reinforced fiber posts stress is distributed in 
broader surface area, hence reduces the chances of root fracture. 2 </p>

<p>In the present study, carbon fiber reinforced posts and glass 
fiber reinforced posts showed highest fracture resistance as 
compared to custom post and metal posts (Table 1). Table 2 
showed that there was no significant difference between 
glass fiber (Group C) and carbon fiber posts (Group D) and 
between custom post (Group A) and metal posts (Group B, 
where as between other groups it is statistically significant 
(P &gt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Results of our study is in agreement with the study by Dean 
et al. in vitro study, who observed no root fractures with carbon 
post, 50 % of teeth had root fracture with cast post. 4 Similarly 
Fredriksson et al. and Preethi and Kala observed good clinical 
success with carbon posts and glass fiber posts. 2,5 Makade et al. 
concluded that, glass fiber post is better compared to metal 
posts. 1 Our results are consistent with Kantor and Pines, Sirimai 
et al. and Sidoli et al. 6-8 Robbins recommended use of post to 
increase the fracture resistance. 9 </p>

<p>Whereas Martinez-Insua et al. observed significantly higher 
fracture strength with cast post and core as compared to carbon 
fiber posts. 10 Ferrari et al. concluded that composite posts 
systems are superior to cast post and core system, and they 
observed 14% failure with cast post system. 11 Adanir and Belli 
concluded that for clinical success, posts shorter than clinical 
crowns should be avoided 12 Jalalian and Mirzaei concluded 
from their study that, fiber posts with larger diameter adhere 
to the root structure more efficiently. 13 </p>

<p>Makade et al. found that teeth restored with cast post and core 
found to have cervical and middle third root fracture whereas 
glass fiber posts demonstrated only core fracture. 1 Garhnayak 
et al. concluded that incorporation of ferrule offered some 
degree of stress reduction in post restored teeth. 14 Present 
in vitro study helps to know about the physical quality of 
different types of posts which can be useful in post selection 
and clinical successful outcome of endodontic therapy. </p>

<p>Conclusion 
It is concluded that carbon reinforced fiber post and glass fiber 
posts showed good fracture resistance compared to custom 
made and metal posts. This in vitro study helps in the selection 
of posts for successful endodontic therapy. </p>

<p>References 
1. Makade CS, Meshram GK, Warhadpande M, Patil PG. 
A comparative evaluation of fracture resistance of 
endodontically treated teeth restored with different 
post core systems -an in-vitro study. J Adv Prosthodont 
2011;3(2):90-5. 
2. Preethi G, Kala M. Clinical evaluation of carbon fiber </p>

<p>Table 1: Mean, median and standard deviation values for fracture 
resistance in different groups (MPa). </p>

<p>Type of post Sample Mean Median Standard deviation </p>

<p>Group A 
10 
857.4 
848.3 
78.7 
Group B 
10 
1268.7 
1272.6 
90.2 
Group C 
10 
1213.2 
1144.7 
141.2 
Group D 
10 
1245.4 
1254.5 
145.8 </p>

<p>Table 2: Comparative evaluation between experimental groups. </p>

<p>Group comparison 
t-test value 
P value </p>

<p>Group A versus B 
0.8061 
0.4684 
Group A versus C 
14.77 
0.001 
Group A versus D 
18.56 
0.001 
Group B versus C 
11.22 
0.001 
Group B versus D 
13.88 
0.001 
Group C versus D 
0.9061 
0.3834 </p>





</text></tei>