<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4102165" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background/Aims 
To draw a normative database of laryngopharynx pH profile in Chinese subjects. </p>

<p>Methods 
Normal volunteers were recruited from "www.Ganji.com" and People's hospital between May 2008 and December 2009. The 
Restech pH Probes were calibrated in pH 7 and pH 4 buffer solutions according to the manufacturer's instructions. Each volun-
teer was asked to wear the device for a 24-hour period and was encouraged to participate in normal daily activities. </p>

<p>Results 
The healthy volunteers consisted of 20 males and 9 females with a median age of 23 years (interquartile range, 21 to 32 
years). The 95th percentiles for % total times at pH &lt; 4, pH &lt; 4.5, pH &lt; 5.0 and pH &lt; 5.5 for the oropharynx pH catheter 
were 0.06%, 1.01%, 7.23% and 27.34%, respectively. The 95th percentile for number of reflux events within the 24-hour peri-
od at pH &lt; 4, pH &lt; 4.5, pH &lt; 5.0 and pH &lt; 5.5 were 2.0, 18.0, 107.5 and 284.5, respectively. </p>

<p>Conclusions 
This is the first study to systematically assess the degree of reflux detected by the new pH probe in healthy asymptomatic 
Chinese volunteers and to report normative values in Chinese people. Using an oropharyngeal pH catheter to monitor lar-
yngopharyngeal reflux indicated that in healthy Chinese, reflux should be considered normal if the percent time at pH less than 
4.5 is no more than 1%. 
(J Neurogastroenterol Motil 2014;20:347-351) </p>

<p>Gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD) is a condition that 
develops due to reflux of stomach contents into the esophagus, 
oral cavity (including larynx) or lung. 
1 GERD is a common dis-</p>

<p>ease in Western countries and in Asia. 
2 Epidemiologic studies </p>

<p>suggest that close to 50% of the population may have some type of 
GERD symptom during a calendar year. 
3 Wong et al 
4 reported </p>

<p>that approximately 29.8% of the population in China suffers from 
GERD symptoms in an annual period. Ma et al 
5 found that the </p>

<p>prevalence of GERD, defined 
6 as heartburn and/or regurgitation </p>

<p>of any frequency during the previous week, was 6.2% in Shanghai, 
a developed city in China. Laryngopharyngeal reflux (LPR) is 
the backflow of gastric contents (refluxate) to the laryngopharynx 
and upper aerodigestive tract and by a recent definition is a form 
of GERD. 
7 LPR is not always secondary to GERD </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>; however 
the term laryngopharyngeal reflux disease (LPRD) was adopted 
by the American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck 
Surgery in its 2002 Position Statement on LPR. 
9 We presented </p>

<p>our classification of LPRD in a previous conference abstract. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>The diagnosis of LPRD is mainly based on reflux symptom in-
dex, 
11 reflux finding score (RSF) 
12 and laryngopharynx pH </p>

<p>monitoring. The susceptibility of larygopharyngeal epithelium to 
reflux injury differs from that of esophagus 
13 and the normative </p>

<p>data of reflux events may vary by ethnicity or diet. 
Normative LPR data are available for many groups, 
14,15 but </p>

<p>there is no accepted normal larygopharyngeal pH profile for 
healthy Chinese subjects. To determine the normal values of pH 
in healthy Chinese, we used the Dx-pH measurement system 
(Respiratory Technology Corp, San Diego, CA, USA). The 
Dx-pH probe is a sensitive and minimally invasive device for de-
tection of acid reflux in the posterior oropharynx. 
16 It uses a naso-</p>

<p>pharyngeal catheter to measure pH in either liquid or aerosolized 
droplets. Special circuitry monitors each individual reading to as-
sure sufficient sensor hydration. This circuitry prevents the in-
clusion of dry-out related "pseudo-reflux" events. Our study pro-
vides the first normative LPR data for healthy Chinese subjects. </p>

<p>M aterials and M ethods </p>

<p>Study Population </p>

<p>The study protocol was approved by the institutional review 
board for human use at People's Hospital, Peking University </p>

<p>and informed consent was obtained from each participant. 
Normal volunteers were recruited from "www.Ganji.com" and 
People's Hospital between May 2008 and December 2009. Each 
potential subject completed reflux symptom index 
11 and reflux </p>

<p>disease questionnaire. Only volunteers with scores equal to zero 
participated in the study. Subjects with history of GERD or lar-
yngopharyngeal diseases or who had recently used histamine re-
ceptor antagonists, proton pump inhibitors, or other antacids 
were also excluded. Each volunteer underwent laryngoscope ex-
amination, and only those who presented with no abnormalities 
and with RSF 
12 score of zero were studied. Additional exclusion </p>

<p>criteria included ongoing use of alcohol or tobacco, inability to 
comply with the period of monitoring (22-24 hours), recent nasal 
surgery or nasal obstruction, or other significant medical con-
ditions (psychiatric disorders, inability to comprehend the con-
sent form and pregnancy). </p>

<p>Study Design </p>

<p>The Restech pH probes were calibrated in pH 7 and pH 4 
buffer solutions according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
The probe is a 1.5 mm diameter oropharyngeal catheter with a 
wireless digital transmitter worn externally. The catheter employs 
a 3.2 mm teardrop-like tip that contains a colored light emitting 
diode (LED) to aid insertion and to allow visualization of the 
sensor for proper positioning. The standard catheter was placed 
in the oropharynx at the level of the uvula. Each volunteer was 
asked to wear the device for a 24-hour period and was encour-
aged to participate in normal daily activities. Each subject carried 
one transmitter/receiver that wirelessly sent data to a monitor 
worn by the subject. The monitor contains a digital memory card 
to record events such as meal times, position and chief complaint. 
Once the pH study was completed, the volunteer returned to 
have the catheter removed, and the data from the digital recorder 
were downloaded to a password-protected computer. Data were 
analyzed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">DataView</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 3</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">AEMC Instru-ments</rs>, Dover, NH, USA). The software generated a graphical 
tracing of the study events and also created a report of any reflux 
events. The data collected during meal times were excluded from 
analysis. It was considered as reflux event when the time of pH 
reaching to the lowest point was no more than 30 seconds. </p>

<p>Statistical Methods </p>

<p>Data are presented as means or medians depending on data 
distribution, and 25th, 75th and 95th percentiles are provided. 
The percent time spent below pH values of 4.0, 4.5, 5.0 and 5.5 </p>

<p>Draw a Normative Database of Laryngopharynx pH Profile in Chinese </p>

<p>Vol. 20, No. 3 July, 2014 (347-351) </p>



<p>Figure 1. Oropharyngeal pH monitored over the course of 24 hours in 
a healthy volunteer. </p>

<p>Figure 2. An analysis of the data shown in Figure 1. The data collected 
during meals were deleted, and pH 4.5 was selected as baseline pH. The 
time duration for analysis was 22 hours and 51 minutes. The percentile 
for % total time at pH ＜ 4.5 was 0.02, and 2 reflux events. The part of 
the curve marked by red vertical lines is reflux curve. </p>

<p>was determined for each subject. The data were also evaluated 
based on whether the subject was in the upright position, a supine 
position or a combination of the 2 positions (total). The dis-
tributions of percent time were summarized at 25th, 50th 
(median), 75th and 95th quantiles for each pH level and body 
position. All data were visually evaluated for accuracy by one in-
vestigator and subjects were excluded if they were not monitored 
for at least 22 hours. This allowed analysis of both supine and up-
right positions. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Of 90 volunteers initially recruited, 50 subjects were ex-
cluded due to self-report of one or more GERD or LPR symp-
toms or because of treatment with acid suppressive therapy. An 
additional 10 subjects were excluded because of one or more RSF 
signs by laryngoscope. Thirty volunteers began pH monitoring. 
One volunteer withdrew due to dizziness an hour after initial 
placement. Thus a total of 29 healthy volunteers constituted the 
study population and underwent pH monitoring with a Restech 
pH catheter in the oropharynx. The healthy volunteers consisted 
of 20 males and 9 females with a median age of 23 years (inter-
quartile range, 21 to 32 years). No patient reported heartburn, 
cough, globus or throat discomfort during the study period. 
Figure 1 shows a typical tracing of oropharyngeal pH monitoring 
in a healthy volunteer. In Figure 2, the raw data from Figure 1 
has been subjected to analysis. 
A summary of the data obtained using the oropharyngeal pH 
catheter for all 29 subjects is shown in Table. The 95th percen-
tiles for % total time at pH ＜ 4.0, pH ＜ 4.5, pH ＜ 5.0 and 
pH ＜ 5.5 were 0.06%, 1.01%, 7.23% and 27.34%, respectively. </p>

<p>Table also shows the number of reflux events at each pH level for 
total, upright and supine positions. The 95th percentiles for the 
number of reflux events for pH ＜ 4.0, pH ＜ 4.5, pH ＜ 5.0 
and pH ＜ 5.5 were 2.5, 18.0, 107.5 and 284.5, respectively. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Chinese researchers began to study LPR many years ago. In 
1995, Zheng et al. found that abnormal sensations in the pharynx 
were associated with the esophageal pH. 
17 Cheng et al 
18 found </p>

<p>that 17.9% of GERD patients suffered from cough and asthma. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>We previously reported an association of oropharyngeal pH with 
LPR 
19 and analyzed the relationship of GERD and LPR based </p>

<p>on symptoms. 
20 Another researcher determined the clinical value </p>

<p>of 24 h double-probe pH-metry for the diagnosis and treatment 
of LPR. 
21 Despite of the presentation of these studies, normal </p>

<p>values of oropharyngeal pH in the Chinese population have not 
been established. However normal oropharyngeal pH profiles 
have been obtained in other country. 
15 In this previous study, a </p>

<p>distal esophageal catheter was used to ensure that the decrease in 
pH detected by the oropharyngeal pH catheter originated distally 
and was of a gastric source. However, LPR is not always secon-
dary to gastroesophageal reflux and the association between het-
erotopic gastric mucosal patch and LPR has been reported. </p>

<p>22,23 </p>

<p>Here we used an oropharyngeal pH catheter to ensure that all 
LPR events were detected. The volunteers in our study were 
evaluated by laryngoscopy to exclude silent LPR patients. 
Wang et al 
24 performed ambulatory 24-hour multichannel </p>

<p>Guijian Feng, et al </p>

<p>Journal of Neurogastroenterology and Motility </p>



<p>Table. Oropharyngeal pH Parameters Detected by Restech pH Probe (N = 29) </p>

<p>Item 
Posture 
Mean 
25% percentile 
Median 
75% percentile 
95% percentile </p>

<p>% time ＜ pH 4.0 
Upright 
0.01 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.10 
Supine 
0.15 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
2.25 
T o t a l 
0 . 0 4 
0 . 0 0 
0 . 0 0 
0 . 0 0 
0 . 6 4 
% time ＜ pH 4.5 
Upright 
0.04 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.41 
Supine 
0.24 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
3.37 
T o t a l 
0 . 0 9 
0 . 0 0 
0 . 0 0 
0 . 0 3 
1 . 0 1 
% time ＜ pH 5.0 
Upright 
0.27 
0.00 
0.00 
0.07 
3.41 
Supine 
2.41 
0.00 
0.00 
2.27 
19.06 
T o t a l 
0 . 9 8 
0 . 0 0 
0 . 0 5 
0 . 6 9 
7 . 2 3 
% time ＜ pH 5.5 
Upright 
2.28 
0.04 
0.28 
2.10 
18.97 
Supine 
19.68 
0.00 
16.50 
31.91 
58.60 
Total 
8.23 
0.20 
8.66 
13.10 
27.34 
No. of events pH ＜ 4.0 
Upright 
0.8 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
2.0 
Supine 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.5 
Total 
0.2 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
2.5 
No. of events pH ＜ 4.5 
Upright 
0.6 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
5.5 
Supine 
1.1 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
15.5 
Total 
1.7 
0.0 
0.0 
1.0 
18.0 
No. of events pH ＜ 5.0 
Upright 
3.2 
0.0 
0.0 
3.0 
28.0 
Supine 
10.8 
0.0 
0.0 
5.5 
88.0 
Total 
13.7 
0.0 
1.0 
8.0 
107.5 
No. of events pH ＜ 5.5 
Upright 
44.5 
0.0 
5.0 
80.0 
207.0 
Supine 
45.8 
0.0 
44.0 
75.5 
116.0 
Total 
85.8 
7.5 
56.0 
129.5 
284.5 </p>

<p>intraluminal impedance-pH (MII-pH) monitoring in a group of 
healthy Chinese volunteers to define the normative data of LPR. 
A limitation of the Wang study is that the MII-pH probe mon-
itors both pharynx and esophagus, defining LPR as gastro-
esophageal reflux that reaches 1 cm above the upper esophageal 
sphincter. This design may miss LPR events. In another study, 
laryngopharyngeal reflux was studied in 20 volunteers, 
15 pH </p>

<p>monitoring time was from 14 to 24 hours (median 20.5 hours). 
The 95th percentile for percent total times at pH ＜ 4, pH ＜ 5 
and pH ＜ 6 were 0.02%, 2.33% and 21.41%, respectively. The 
95th percentile for number of reflux events at pH ＜ 4, pH ＜ 5 
and pH ＜ 6 were 1.3, 8.1 and 128.0, respectively. The values in 
our study were higher than these when the same pH value was 
used as baseline. In the previous study, the authors did not report 
data of pH values at 4.5 or 5.5 and in some subjects pH monitor-
ing time was less than 22 hours. 
The advantages of our study are mainly derived from the 
probe employed. When a traditional pH sensor is utilized in 
monitoring pharyngeal pH, data are noisy due to mucus accumu-
lation, food interruption and sensor drying; this noise cannot be </p>

<p>completely corrected thereby making data analysis complicated. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>The Restech pH probe used here is specially designed for meas-
urement of pharyngeal pH. Data are collected only when the 
probe is dry, which significantly minimizes artifacts. Moreover, 
the Restech pH probe samples at a frequency of 2 Hz (i.e., once 
every 0.5 second), whereas a traditional probe has a 4-to 5-sec-
ond interval. This high rate of sampling enables the device to 
draw a more accurate profile of pharyngeal environment. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>In our study, volunteers did not undergo esophageal man-
ometry or esophagogram. All the volunteers who had reported 
any discomfort or symptom were not included. Therefore, it is 
unlikely that any of our subjects had abnormal esophageal mo-
tility disease. According to our data, the 95% percentile of per-
cent time at below pH 4.5 was 1.01%. We suggest that pH 4.5 
should be considered as baseline for laryngopharyngeal reflux in 
Chinese subject. Reflux should be considered normal if the per-
cent time at pH less than 4.5 is no more than 1%. 
In conclusion, this study suggested Chinese normal values 
for acid reflux using the Restech oropharyngeal pH probe. 
Further studies are needed to evaluate the utility of the Dx-pH </p>

<p>Draw a Normative Database of Laryngopharynx pH Profile in Chinese </p>

<p>Vol. 20, No. 3 July, 2014 (347-351) </p>



<p>measurement system and to validate the normal values of or-
opharyngeal pH in a larger number of subjects. </p>



</text></tei>