<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4551074" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Protein-protein interactions (PPIs) have been widely studied to understand the bi-
ological processes or molecular functions associated with dif ferent disease systems 
like cancer. While focused studies on individual cancers have generated valuable in-
formation, global and comparative analysis of datasets from dif ferent cancer types 
has not been done. In this work, we carried out bioinformatic analysis of PPIs 
corresponding to dif ferentially expressed genes from microarrays of various tumor 
tissues (belonging to bladder, colon, kidney and thyroid cancers) and compared 
their associated biological processes and molecular functions (based on Gene On-
tology terms). We identif ied a set of processes or functions that are common to all 
these cancers, as well as those that are specif ic to only one or partial cancer types. 
Similarly, protein interaction networks in nucleic acid metabolism were compared 
to identify the common/specif ic clusters of proteins across dif ferent cancer types. 
Our results provide a basis for further experimental investigations to study protein 
interaction networks associated with cancer. The methodology developed in this 
work can also be applied to study similar disease systems. </p>

<p>The vast majority of proteins must interact with other 
proteins to perform their function. The network of 
protein-protein interactions (PPIs), referred to as the 
interactome, plays a vital role in the initiation and 
progression of many disease pathways. Hence, un-
derstanding protein interaction networks is crucial 
for identifying the key functional modulators of tu-
mor progression and metastasis in cancer. Computa-
tional approaches using PPI data have been widely 
employed for the identification of important protein 
networks involved in tumors (1 ) and cancer metas-
tasis (2 ). For instance, estrogen-regulated networks 
in human breast cancer cells were recently identified 
(3 ). Similarly, an earlier study on the interactome-
transcriptome analysis has revealed the high central-
ity of differentially expressed genes in lung cancer tis-
sues (4 ). Studies were also performed on integrated 
analysis of the cancer transcriptome using microarray </p>

<p>data coupled with computational approaches (5 ). A 
recent study introduced a systems biology approach 
to improve the prognosis prediction of breast, lung 
and ovarian cancer patients (6 ), where the authors 
analyzed molecular interactions that are dysregulated 
in specific tumor phenotypes using a large set of mi-
croarray expression data. Likewise, protein interac-
tion networks of brain metastasis were analyzed by 
developing and using a bioinformatics program called 
PIANA (7 ). These studies show the importance of 
computational methods in deducing and understand-
ing protein interaction networks from datasets associ-
ated with cancer gene expression. 
Analysis of microarray expression data to infer 
protein interaction networks has been the subject of 
extensive research aimed at gaining insight into the 
initiation and progression of various diseases like can-
cer. Several studies have been carried out on similar </p>

<p>Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics Vol. 7 No. 1-2 June 2009 </p>

<p>
This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). </p>

<p>Protein-Protein Interactions in Cancer Genes </p>

<p>lines using gene expression data from tumor tissues of 
ovarian cancer (8 ), prostate cancer (9 ), etc. Never-
theless, these studies were primarily focused on cor-
relating gene expression data with PPIs occurring in 
a specific type of cancer. While these studies provide 
valuable information on the significance of a set of 
PPIs in a particular type of cancer, comparing and 
contrasting these interactions across various cancers 
will elucidate comprehensive knowledge on the nature 
of these interactions. 
In the current study, we carried out global 
computational analysis of protein interactions in 
cancer-associated genes, using microarray expression 
datasets from normal and tumor tissues of four dis-
tinct cancer types, including bladder, colon, kidney 
and thyroid cancers. To the best of our knowledge, 
such kind of global computational analysis to com-
pare PPIs across multiple cancer types has not been 
conducted before. The goals of this study are two-
fold: firstly, to identify and characterize PPIs that 
are common to all these cancers as well as those that 
are specific to a particular cancer type, and secondly, 
to infer the functional significance of PPIs by creat-
ing protein interaction networks using Gene Ontology 
(GO) annotations. </p>

<p>Results and Discussion </p>

<p>We implemented a top-down approach to carry out 
global analysis of the PPIs that are potentially in-
volved in the initiation and progression of cancer. Fig-
ure 1 depicts the workflow of our methodology. We 
searched the GEO database (Gene Expression Om-
nibus) to collect datasets from gene expression stud-
ies where a tumor tissue (belonging to bladder, colon, 
kidney or thyroid cancers) was compared against a 
healthy tissue reference (see Materials and Methods 
for more details). To maintain consistency, the data 
for all cancer types analyzed in this study were col-
lected from experiments that used only Affymetrix 
HG-U133 Plus 2.0 GeneChip. Due to a paucity of </p>

<p>tumor-grade-specific datasets on this new Affymetrix 
GeneChip platform for all cancer types, we restricted 
our analysis to the baseline or essential PPIs in 
different cancer tumors (irrespective of the tumor 
grade) compared with normal tissues. </p>

<p>As a result, we identified a total of 6,758 unique 
proteins in the four cancer types, corresponding to 
the genes that are differentially expressed by at least 
two folds. Differentially expressed genes were first 
mapped to corresponding proteins and then to pro-
teins involved in known PPIs. About 54% (3,656) of 
these proteins were mapped to 23,619 unique PPIs 
and were used for further analysis in this study. 
Mapped PPIs for each cancer were annotated us-
ing GO terms that describe their biological processes 
(pathways) and molecular functions. We compared 
PPIs from different cancer types using the frequency 
of common GO terms between two partner proteins in 
an interaction. The rationale is that the common GO 
terms of two partner proteins in an interaction denote 
the common biological process and/or molecular func-
tion associated with that interaction. Hence, based on 
the most frequent common GO terms in the PPIs of 
a particular cancer type, the nature of biological pro-
cesses and/or functions associated with that cancer 
can be inferred. However, the incomplete and unbal-
anced nature of the available PPI datasets resulted in 
unbalanced datasets of mapped PPIs across the four 
cancers used in this study (Table 1). To make a fair 
comparison of GO term frequencies, we normalized 
the raw frequencies against the number of PPIs, show-
ing at least one common GO term under a given GO 
category in a given cancer type. Accordingly, the top 
20 most frequent common GO terms were collected 
from each cancer type and then were combined to ob-
tain 30 unique GO terms from all these cancers, under 
the "biological process" and the "molecular function" 
categories, respectively. These GO terms were then 
used for comparative analysis of biological processes 
and molecular functions associated with the PPIs of 
different cancer types. </p>

<p>Table 1 Statistics on the size of datasets across four dif ferent cancer types </p>

<p>Cancer 
Total proteins 
Unique proteins with Unique proteins Unique PPIs* 
mapped from DEGs* 
known interactions 
having PPIs* </p>

<p>Bladder 
3,704 
3,008 
2,081 
15,522 
Colon 
3,515 
2,922 
1,944 
13,099 
Kidney 
1,257 
1,034 
728 
4,978 
Thyroid 
1,380 
1,124 
715 
4,599 </p>

<p>*DEGs, differentially expressed genes; PPIs, protein-protein interactions. </p>

<p> 
Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics Vol. 7 No. 1-2 June 2009 </p>

<p>Guda et al. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Flow chart showing the methodology used in this study. </p>

<p>Comparative analysis of biological pro-
cesses associated with cancer PPIs </p>

<p>The most frequent biological processes associated 
with differentially expressed genes in the four can-
cers are listed in Table 2. As shown in Figure 2A, 
there are 14 common regulatory processes found in 
the differentially expressed genes of all these cancers. 
We further analyzed the types of PPIs associated with 
only one or two types of cancers (Figure 2B). Note 
that a GO biological process observed in only a partic-
ular cancer does not necessarily mean that such pro-
cess is entirely lacking in other cancer types, rather 
it is not found in the list of experimentally known 
PPI datasets, which are incomplete and unbalanced 
for various types of cancers. Our methodology found 
a number of interesting biological processes that are 
specific to a particular cancer type. For instance, </p>

<p>cell-cell signaling (CCS) and macromolecule catabolic 
process (MCP) were observed only in bladder cancer, 
which are linked to signaling proteins like hormones 
and glycoproteins that are mostly oncogenes (10 ). 
The TEK receptor tyrosine kinase, which is associated 
with angiogenesis (a primary process that establishes 
blood supply for the tumors), is one of the proteins in 
cell signaling process (11 ). Inhibin is another signal-
ing protein whose levels have been shown to reflect 
the size of cell tumors (12 ). However, experimen-
tal evidence suggesting a direct link between these 
proteins and bladder cancer is not available. Protein 
interactions associated with blood coagulation (BC) 
and hemostasis (HE) were observed only in thyroid 
cancer. Literature evidence shows that disturbance of 
hemostasis is a common phenomenon in patients with 
thyroid disease, usually with hyperthyroidism (13 ). 
In these studies, a hyper coagulability state has been </p>

<p>Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics Vol. 7 No. 1-2 June 2009 </p>

<p>
Protein-Protein Interactions in Cancer Genes </p>

<p>Table 2 Gene Ontology terms (biological process) of dif ferentially expressed genes </p>

<p>Processes common to all of the four cancer types </p>

<p>ASM 
anatomical structure morphogenesis 
BMP 
biopolymer metabolic process 
CD 
cell differentiation 
CL 
cellular localization 
CMM 
cellular macromolecule metabolic process 
NNN 
nucleobase, nucleoside, nucleotide and nucleic acid metabolic process 
NRBP negative regulation of biological process 
OD 
organ development 
OOB 
organelle organization and biogenesis 
PP 
phosphorus metabolic process 
PRB 
positive regulation of biological process 
RCM 
regulation of cellular metabolic process 
SD 
system development 
ST 
signal transduction </p>

<p>Processes found only in specific cancers </p>

<p>BC 
blood coagulation 
thyroid 
CBP 
cellular biosynthetic process 
colon, thyroid 
CCS 
cell-cell signaling 
bladder 
CP 
cell cycle process 
bladder, kidney, thyroid 
GPM 
generation of precursor metabolites and energy 
colon 
HE 
hemostasis 
thyroid 
HOP 
homeostatic process 
colon, kidney 
MCP 
macromolecule catabolic process 
bladder 
MOB 
membrane organization and biogenesis 
kidney 
PMP 
protein metabolic process 
colon, thyroid 
PT 
protein transport 
colon 
RMP 
regulation of membrane potential 
kidney 
RST 
regulation of signal transduction 
bladder, kidney 
RW 
response to wounding 
bladder, thyroid 
SEM 
symbiosis, encompassing mutualism through parasitism colon 
VMT 
vesicle-mediated transport 
bladder, kidney </p>

<p>reported in patients with thyroid cancer as a result of 
up-regulation of thrombin, protein S alpha and coagu-
lation factor X. Similarly, PPIs involved in membrane 
organization and biogenesis (MOB) and regulation of 
membrane potential (RMP) were observed only in 
kidney cancer. Proteins associated with these pro-
cesses regulate ionic homeostasis, suggesting the im-
portance of homeostasis in renal cell carcinoma (14 ). 
Moreover, most of these interactions are among mem-
brane proteins that are vital for membrane transport 
to maintain homeostasis (chloride channels, Na 
+ /H </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>exchanger, ferritin, the iron storing protein, Thy-1 
membrane glycoprotein, etc). 
Lastly, PPIs associated with the generation of pre-
cursor metabolites and energy (GPM), symbiosis en-</p>

<p>compassing mutualism through parasitism (SEM) and 
protein transport (PT) were observed only in colon 
cancer. Proteins associated with the GPM process 
are mostly mitochondrial respiratory enzymes and mi-
tochondrial outer membrane proteins. It is reported 
that a quantitative mitochondrial change occurs in 
colon carcinoma patients; in particular, the ratio be-
tween outer membrane enzyme activity and respira-
tory enzyme activity may be altered (15 , 16 ). An-
other process that is regulated only in colon cancer is 
SEM. This is not surprising because the role of bacte-
ria in the development of colorectal tumors was well 
documented (17 ). The involvement of colonic bacte-
ria expressing enzymes in the metabolism of procar-
cinogens and tumor promoters suggests that changes </p>

<p> 
Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics Vol. 7 No. 1-2 June 2009 </p>

<p>Guda et al. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Comparison of the frequency distribution of GO terms describing the common biological processes in the 
PPIs of different cancers including bladder (BLAD), colon (COL), kidney (KID) and thyroid (THY) cancers. A. 
Histogram showing the most frequent processes in at least three types of cancers; processes found only in three types 
of cancer are marked with asterisk. B. Histogram showing the most frequent processes in only one or two types of 
cancers. </p>

<p>in the colonic bacterial population would influence 
cancer risk by altering the activity of these enzymes 
(18 ). Major proteins involved in the SEM process are 
ubiquitin protein ligase and HLA class histocompati-
bility antigen. Proteins associated with the PT pro-
cess are chromatin modifying protein, SH3 and PX 
domain containing protein (sorting nexin-9), which 
are involved in intracellular trafficking. The chro-
matin remodeling enzymes with their role in cancer 
and dysplastic syndromes were previously reported 
(19 ). Studies on sorting of nexin-9 and EG-1 proteins 
that are significantly elevated in colorectal, breast and 
prostate cancer revealed the possible role of nexin-9 
in signaling pathway (20 ). 
Other processes regulated in multiple cancers in-
clude regulation of signal transduction (RST) and 
vesicle-mediated transport (VMT) in bladder and kid-</p>

<p>ney cancers, homeostatic process (HOP) in colon and 
kidney cancers, regulation of protein metabolic pro-
cess (PMP) and cellular biosynthetic process (CBP) 
in colon and thyroid cancers, and response to wound-
ing (RW) in bladder and thyroid cancers. PPIs as-
sociated with the RW process were observed among 
proteins such as thrombin, serine proteinase inhibitor, 
prostaglandin endoperoxidase synthase (aka COX-
2, cyclooxygenase-2), which are all responsible for 
inducing tumor growth, metastasis and angiogene-
sis (21 , 22 ). Nevertheless, we were unable to find 
literature-based explanations for each and every ob-
servation in our study, yet the aforementioned exper-
imental evidence strongly suggests that the method-
ology used in this study is able to identify the true 
biological processes involved in the PPIs of cancer-
associated genes. </p>

<p>Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics Vol. 7 No. 1-2 June 2009 </p>

<p>
Protein-Protein Interactions in Cancer Genes </p>

<p>Comparative analysis of molecular func-
tions associated with cancer PPIs </p>

<p>We also carried out similar analysis of GO terms that 
describe the common "molecular functions" of PPIs 
associated with different cancers. We collected the 
top 20 most frequent GO terms from the PPIs of each 
of the four cancers and then combined them to ob-
tain 30 unique GO terms describing their molecular 
functions. Out of the 30 terms, 12 ones are common 
to all these cancers (Figure 3A), including functions 
related to the binding of protein, ion, carbohydrate 
and nucleic acid, as well as to the catalytic activity 
(listed in Table 3). This result clearly indicates that 
binding and catalytic activities are the most common 
functions associated with all types of cancers. Mean-</p>

<p>while, some functions were found in the PPIs of only 
three cancer types. For instance, two functions, hy-
drolase activity acting on ester bonds (HAE) and pro-
tein binding, bridging (PBB), were regulated in all 
these cancers except in kidney cancer; PPIs associated 
with alpha-type channel activity (ATC), hydrolase ac-
tivity acting on acid anhydrides (HAA) and identical 
protein binding (IPB) were expressed in all these can-
cers except in thyroid cancer; while protein domain 
specific binding (PDSB) function was not found in 
the PPIs of bladder cancer. 
Similar to the biological processes, we have iden-
tified several molecular functions that are specifically 
associated with a particular type of cancer (Figure 
3B). Proteins regulated only in bladder cancer include 
kinases and synthetases that belong to the GO cate-</p>

<p>Figure 3 Comparison of the frequency distribution of GO terms describing the common molecular functions in the 
PPIs of different cancers including bladder (BLAD), colon (COL), kidney (KID) and thyroid (THY) cancers. A. 
Histogram showing the most frequent functions in at least three types of cancers; functions found only in three types 
of cancer are marked with asterisk. B. Histogram showing the most frequent functions in only one or two types of 
cancers. </p>

<p> 
Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics Vol. 7 No. 1-2 June 2009 </p>

<p>Guda et al. </p>

<p>Table 3 Gene Ontology terms (molecular function) of dif ferentially expressed genes </p>

<p>Functions common to all of the four cancer types </p>

<p>CB 
cation binding 
CPB 
cytoskeletal protein binding 
CTA 
cation transport activity 
DNAB DNA binding 
EB 
enzyme binding 
MIB 
metal ion binding 
PA 
peptidase activity 
PDA 
protein dimerization activity 
PNB 
purine nucleotide binding 
PSB 
polysaccharide binding 
RB 
receptor binding 
TRA 
transmembrane receptor activity </p>

<p>Functions found only in specific cancers </p>

<p>AB 
anion binding 
thyroid 
ATC 
alpha-type channel activity 
bladder, colon, kidney 
CEB 
coenzyme binding 
colon 
CNB 
cyclic nucleotide binding 
kidney 
CYB 
cytokine binding 
kidney 
HAA 
hydrolase activity, acting on acid anhydrides 
bladder, colon, kidney 
HAE 
hydrolase activity, acting on ester bonds 
bladder, colon, thyroid 
IPB 
identical protein binding 
bladder, colon, kidney 
PBB 
protein binding, bridging 
bladder, colon, thyroid 
PDSB 
protein domain specific binding 
colon, kidney, thyroid 
PIA 
protease inhibitor activity 
thyroid 
PKRA protein kinase regulator activity 
thyroid 
PLB 
phospholipids binding 
kidney 
PRA 
peptide receptor activity 
bladder, kidney 
RNAB RNA binding 
bladder, colon 
TANB translation factor activity, nucleic acid binding 
thyroid 
TATP 
transferase activity, transferring phosphorus-containing groups bladder 
TFB 
transcription factor binding 
thyroid </p>

<p>gory of transferase activity, transferring phosphorus 
containing groups (TATP). There is concrete evidence 
on the role of these enzymes in tumorigenesis and 
metastasis (23 , 24 ). Likewise, cyclic nucleotide bind-
ing (CNB), cytokine binding (CYB) and phospholipid 
binding (PLB) functions are involved only in the PPIs 
observed from renal cell carcinoma. Proteins reg-
ulated in this cancer include chemokine (a type of 
cytokine) receptors and contactin-1 protein (a phos-
pholipid binding protein). A relationship between cy-
tokine binding and renal cancer cells was reported in 
a previous study (25 ), and the role of contactin-1 was 
found to be essential in tumor invasion and metasta-
sis (26 ). PPIs involved in coenzyme binding (CEB) 
function were regulated only in colon cancer. Pro-</p>

<p>teins with this function are mostly mitochondrial, and 
the relationship between mitochondrial enzymes and 
colon cancer was previously explained in the biologi-
cal process section (15 ). Molecular functions includ-
ing protease inhibitor activity (PIA), anion binding 
(AB), transcription factor binding (TFB), translation 
factor activity, nucleic acid binding (TANB) and pro-
tein kinase regulatory activity (PKRA) were found 
to regulate only in the PPIs of thyroid cancer. Pro-
teins associated with these functions include cathep-
sin, runt-related transcription factor, protein kinase, 
cycline-dependent kinase inhibitor, etc. The regula-
tion of these proteins and their role in tumorigenesis 
was well documented (27-29 ). </p>

<p>We also observed some molecular functions that </p>

<p>Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics Vol. 7 No. 1-2 June 2009 </p>

<p>
Protein-Protein Interactions in Cancer Genes </p>

<p>are seen in only two types of cancers. For in-
stance, peptide receptor activity (PRA) was found 
only in bladder and kidney cancers. Proteins in-
volved in these interactions include signaling recep-
tors like G-protein coupled receptor, interleukin-8 re-
ceptor, chemokine and bradykinin receptors. Expres-
sion and regulation of these proteins was reported in 
bladder cancer (30 , 31 ). </p>

<p>Analysis of protein interaction networks 
in nucleic acid metabolism </p>

<p>To demonstrate the effectiveness of this method in 
identifying networks of genes that have different reg-
ulatory roles in different cellular processes associated 
with cancer, we chose the biological process NNN 
(nucleobase, nucleoside, nucleotide and nucleic acid 
metabolism) for analysis, which is highly up-regulated 
in all the four cancer types used in this study. We 
created protein interaction networks for each cancer 
separately, using PPIs that are associated with the 
NNN process. These networks were compared against 
each other to identify the similarities and differences 
among them. As shown in Figure 4, we found that 
some networks are universal to all these cancers (Fig-
ure 4A), while some are found only in part of these 
cancers (Figure 4B) or only in a specific type of can-
cer such as bladder cancer (Figure 4C) or colon cancer 
(Figure 4D). The observations are elucidated as fol-
lows. </p>

<p>Oncogenic activation of transcription factors is a 
key event in the establishment and progression of hu-
man cancers. Most of the members of the networks 
in Figure 4 are either transcription factors or their 
activators/receptors. Figure 4A shows a network of 
transcription factor activating proteins that are com-
mon to all of the four cancer types. The activity of 
these proteins was shown to increase in multiple hu-
man tumor types, suggesting their pivotal role in tu-
morigenesis (32 ). These activator proteins were rec-
ognized as molecular targets for many antioxidant and 
anti-inflammatory chemopreventive compounds. For 
example, the transcription factor activation protein 1 
(JUN) is associated with progression and recurrence 
of various types of cancers (33 ), and several nuclear 
receptors (NR1P1, NCOA2, NR4A1) play a pivotal 
role in controlling the growth and differentiation in 
many cell types. These proteins are also known to in-
hibit or enhance transcription by recruiting an array 
of co-activator or co-repressor proteins to the tran-
scription complex (34 ). Transcription factors are gen-
erally not suitable as drug targets except the nuclear 
receptors, which are considered as outstanding tar-
gets for developing cancer therapeutics and drug dis-
covery (35 ). Other proteins in this network include 
hypoxia-inducible factor 1 alpha (HIF1A), which, in 
association with other proteins, may be involved in 
angiogenesis and tumor growth (36 ). 
Figure 4B shows the proteins containing WW do-
main (WWTR1) or homeobox domain (NKX2.1) that </p>

<p>Figure 4 Protein interaction networks of nucleic acid pathway. A. NFYA, nuclear transcription factor Y subunit 
alpha; HIF1A, hypoxia inducible factor 1 alpha; NRIP1, nuclear receptor interacting protein 1; JUN, transcription 
factor activator protein 1; NCOA2, nuclear receptor co-activator 2; NR4A1, nuclear receptor subfamily 4 group A 
member 1; ATF4, activating transcription factor 4; C/ATF4, cyclic AMP-dependent transcription factor ATF-4. 
B. WWTR1 (TAZ), WW domain-containing transcription regulator protein; NKX2.1, homeobox protein Nkx-2.1. 
C. Rxra, retinoic acid receptor RXR-alpha; crebbp, CREB binding protein; Thra, thyroid hormone receptor alpha. 
D. NDK, nucleoside diphosphate kinase; Nm23, nucleoside diphosphate kinase, mitochondrial (precursor). </p>

<p> 
Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics Vol. 7 No. 1-2 June 2009 </p>

<p>Guda et al. </p>

<p>are specific to both colon and bladder cancers. 
Though their expression and involvement are not well 
studied in bladder and colon cancers, their critical 
role was reported in breast cancer (37 ) (not included 
in this study due to constraints on HG-U133 plus 
2 GeneChip data availability). The network that is 
specific to bladder cancer (Figure 4C) contains impor-
tant receptor proteins, whose role as biomarkers was 
well studied for developing therapeutic drugs in blad-
der cancer prevention (38 , 39 ). The network in Figure 
4D was found only in colon cancer, which contains two 
nucleoside diphosphate kinases NDK and Nm23. Out 
of them, the mitochondrial precursor protein (Nm23) 
was well studied as a metastasis-associated gene in 
colon cancer (40 ). 
We also looked into the subcellular localization of 
the proteins involved in these networks. The result 
shows that almost all of these proteins are localized in 
the nucleus except those in Figure 4D, where Nm23 
is localized to mitochondria and the localization of 
NDK is unknown. The nuclear localization of these 
proteins is expected owing to their role in the reg-
ulation of transcription. In addition, comparison of 
PPI networks across four cancers and identification of 
experimentally known protein clusters that are com-
mon or specific to different cancer types have demon-
strated the efficacy of our method in studying similar 
interaction networks in other disease systems. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>We performed bioinformatic analysis of differentially 
expressed genes obtained from microarray studies of 
various tumor tissues. Comparative analysis of PPIs 
from different cancer types revealed a number of com-
mon functions or processes across all these cancers, 
as well as those that are specific to partial cancers or 
only to a particular cancer type. The function of a 
protein in a system (such as a tumor) is better under-
stood by studying the function(s) of its interacting 
proteins. The methodology used in this study de-
rives the common functions of protein pairs in PPIs 
from different tumor tissues and uses this formation 
as the basis for cross comparison of similarities and 
differences among various cancer types. Comparison 
of protein interaction networks revealed the group of 
genes that are regulated uniformly across all these 
cancer types as well as those regulated only in a 
specific cancer, indicating their importance in that 
particular cancer. We have provided literature-based </p>

<p>evidence for many observations in this study, yet such 
evidence is not available to support every observation. 
We believe that the similarities and differences ob-
served in the biological processes and molecular func-
tions of PPIs from various cancer types will provide 
the basis for focused experimental investigations in 
cancer therapeutics and drug discovery studies. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Cancer gene expression data </p>

<p>The GEO database (41 ), a central repository for 
differential gene expression data, was used in this 
study. This database offers an extensive collection 
of gene expression data on cancer and compares vari-
ous types and subgroups. We selected only those gene 
expression studies where a tumor tissue was compared 
against a healthy tissue reference. The initial datasets 
were derived for six cancer types including blad-
der (GSE7476), colon (GSE4107), kidney (GSE7023), 
thyroid (GSE3678), breast (GSE6883) and prostate 
(GSE3325) cancers. To maintain consistency, data 
for all cancer types in this study were collected from 
experiments that used only Affymetrix HG-U133 Plus 
2.0 GeneChip. This is a newer chip from Affymetrix 
that covers about 54,000 human genes, but the trade-
off is that this restriction limits the number of avail-
able datasets on a specific tumor grade for a specific 
cancer. Since the goal of our study is to carry out 
comparison of baseline PPIs in different cancer types, 
it requires robust datasets for each cancer type. To 
obtain datasets of reasonable size, we didn't take the 
tumor grade into account; hence heterogeneity some-
what exists in the grade of the tumor tissue sam-
ples used in this study. In brief, bladder, kidney 
and prostate datasets were obtained from low, high 
or metastatic (invasive) tumors, whereas breast, colon 
and thyroid samples originated mostly from low grade 
or early onset tumors. Under this GeneChip, breast 
cancer and prostate cancer were found to have only 34 
and 139 differentially expressed genes, respectively; 
hence these two cancer types were eliminated from 
further analysis. More details on the grade and tu-
mor type used for each cancer are provided in Table 
S1 (see Supporting Online Material). 
Datasets in each series were analyzed by <rs id="software-0" type="software">Gene-
Spring</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v7.3.1</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Agilent</rs>) using GCRMA nor-
malization and with the cross-gene error model acti-
vated. In each case, samples were grouped as nor-
mal or diseased, and a parametric t-test was per-</p>

<p>Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics Vol. 7 No. 1-2 June 2009 </p>

<p>
Protein-Protein Interactions in Cancer Genes </p>

<p>formed to obtain genes with statistically significant 
differences. The p-value cutoff was set at 0.05 and a 
Benjamin Hochberg False Discovery Rate correction 
was included. These restrictions would allow about 
5% of the tested genes on the GeneChip (total 54,675) 
to qualify by random chance. This gene list was fur-
ther filtered to obtain genes that showed at least a 
two-fold differential expression between the normal 
and diseased states, which generated between 1,300 
to 3,700 differentially expressed genes for the four 
cancer datasets (Table 1). Protein sequences corre-
sponding to these genes were obtained from GenBank 
and UniProt databases. </p>

<p>Protein-protein interaction data </p>

<p>We created a comprehensive, non-redundant dataset 
of human interacting protein pairs (PPIs) by com-
bining experimentally derived datasets from five 
major protein interaction databases, including DIP 
(Database of Interacting Proteins; http://dip.doe-
mbi.ucla.edu), IntAct (http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intact), 
BIND (Biomolecular Interaction Network Database; 
http://www.bind.ca), HPRD (Human Protein Ref-
erence Database; http://www.hprd.org) and MINT 
(Molecular Interaction Database; http://mint.bio. 
uniroma2.it/mint). Protein sequences in each of these 
databases are fairly overlapping, but are indexed by 
different identifiers such as SwissProt/UniProt iden-
tifier, GenBank protein identifier, etc, making it 
difficult to identify redundant sequences. To remove 
redundancy, we first created datasets of unique se-
quences (based on full-length protein sequence string 
comparison using Perl scripts) within each database 
and then merged them to create a non-redundant 
dataset of interacting protein sequences, each indexed 
with our internal identifier. Note that this inter-
nal identifier can be used to map all the original 
source identifiers for corresponding sequences in the 
source databases. Finally, we obtained 27,051 unique 
human protein sequences (henceforth referred to as 
P int ) representing 57,307 unique PPIs. The FASTA 
formatted protein sequences and PPI datasets for 
each cancer used in this study can be downloaded at 
http://bioinformatics.albany.edu/gpb/. </p>

<p>Mapping and annotation of interacting 
proteins </p>

<p>To map the interacting proteins with corresponding 
differentially expressed genes, we performed a BLAST </p>

<p>search against the P int dataset described above us-
ing very stringent criteria as following. For each 
query protein, the top hits with a sequence identity 
of ≥ 95% and a sequence length match between 90%-
110% were selected. Functional annotations for the 
selected interacting proteins were obtained from the 
GO database (http://www.geneontology.org). We de-
veloped several Perl scripts to analyze the most fre-
quent common GO terms in PPIs belonging to indi-
vidual cancer types. </p>

<p>Comparative analysis of PPIs based on 
GO term frequency </p>

<p>GO is a hierarchical graph-based annotation system 
where the terms closer to the root describe more gen-
eral information while those away from the root pro-
vide more specific information about a given GO cat-
egory. The root (level 0) describes three main GO 
categories at level 1, which are "biological process", 
"molecular function" and "cellular component". We 
used GO terms only from the "biological process" and 
"molecular function" categories because the data for 
the "cellular component" category are very sparse. 
Ideally, we would have used GO terms that provide 
specific descriptions on the processes or functions; 
however, the more specific the terms get, the less fre-
quent they are, which prohibits meaningful compar-
ison of GO term frequencies across different cancer. 
Hence, we chose the GO terms at level 4 for our anal-
ysis because at this level, GO terms are more specific 
(than those at previous levels), while generic enough 
to cover broader groups of related processes or func-
tions to attain reasonable cumulative frequency for 
analysis. All the GO terms associated with a pro-
tein sequence were obtained from the GO database as 
graph paths, which have an inherent hierarchical or-
der starting from the root (level 0). Since our goal is 
to compare the number of common GO terms across 
different cancer types, these GO terms must be se-
lected at the same level in the graph path (for all 
cancers) to make the comparison meaningful. We de-
veloped a Perl program to store all the graph paths 
for a given protein. Using this program, under each 
GO category (except the "cellular component"), the 
common GO terms for a given pair of PPIs were de-
termined at level 4 to calculate the frequency of com-
mon GO terms in a given cancer. Since the size of 
PPI dataset (Table 1) varies across different cancer 
types, frequencies of common GO terms were normal-
ized against the number of PPIs, showing at least one </p>

<p> 
Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics Vol. 7 No. 1-2 June 2009 </p>

<p>Guda et al. </p>

<p>common GO term in each cancer dataset. This nor-
malization ensures a fair comparison of the common 
GO term frequencies across different cancer types ir-
respective of the size of PPI datasets used. The top 
20 most frequent common terms were selected from 
each cancer, which were combined to obtain a non-
redundant set of GO terms under the biological pro-
cess and the molecular function categories, respec-
tively. </p>

<p>Creation of protein interaction net-
works </p>

<p>PPIs associated with differentially expressed can-
cer genes were used to create networks with the 
application of <rs id="software-2" type="software">Cytoscape</rs> program (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">v2.3.2</rs>) (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">http://www.cytoscape.org</rs>). Semantic similarity provides a 
quantitative measure of how similar a pair of proteins 
are, based on the annotations (GO terms) in a given 
GO category. This method has been proved to be very 
effective in interpreting the functional similarities of 
genes based on gene annotation information from het-
erogeneous data sources (42 , 43 ). In our study, the 
semantic similarity between the molecular functions 
or the biological processes of two proteins involved 
in a PPI was calculated following the literature (43 ) 
and only those PPIs with a high semantic similarity 
value of 4.0 or more (5.5 being the highest) were used 
to create interaction networks under each GO term 
category. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was partly supported by the start-
up funds to CG from SUNY-Albany, and partly 
by the Academic Research Enhancement Award 
(1R15GM080681-01) to CG from NIGMS/NIH. </p>

<p>Authors' contributions </p>

<p>PG carried out this work, analyzed the results and 
drafted the manuscript. SVC created the microarray 
datasets and contributed to the manuscript prepara-
tion and proofreading. CG conceived of the study, 
provided overall conceptual framework for this project 
and contributed to the manuscript preparation. All 
authors read and approved the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Competing interests </p>

<p>The authors have declared that no competing inter-
ests exist. </p>



<p>Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics Vol. 7 No. 1-2 June 2009 </p>

<p>
Protein-Protein Interactions in Cancer Genes </p>



<p> 
Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics Vol. 7 No. 1-2 June 2009 </p>

</text></tei>