<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4723022" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T03:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: The primary aim of this study was to compare the differences in temperament-
character traits, suicide attempts, impulsivity, and functionality levels of patients with bipolar 
disorder I (BD-I) and bipolar disorder II (BD-II). 
Methods: Fifty-two BD-I patients and 49 BD-II patients admitted to Erenköy Mental and 
Neurological Disease Training and Research Hospital psychiatry clinic and fifty age-and sex-
matched healthy control subjects were enrolled in this study. A structured clinical interview for 
Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 4th Edition Axis I Disorders, Tempera-
ment and Character Inventory, Barrett Impulsiveness Scale-11 (BIS-11), Hamilton Depression 
Inventory Scale, Young Mania Rating Scale, and Bipolar Disorder Functioning Questionnaire 
(BDFQ) were administered to patients and to control group. 
Results: No statistically significant difference in sociodemographic features existed between 
the patient and control groups (P.0.05). Thirty-eight subjects (37.62%) in the patient group 
had a suicide attempt. Twenty-three of these subjects (60.52%) had BD-I, and 15 of these 
subjects (39.47%) had BD-II. Suicide attempt rates in BD-I and II patients were 60.52% and 
39.47%, respectively (P,0.05). Comparison of BD-I and II patients with healthy control 
subjects revealed that cooperativeness (C), self-directedness (Sdi), and self-transcendence 
(ST) scores were lower and novelty seeking (NS1 and NS2), harm avoidance (HA4), and 
reward dependence (RD2) subscale scores were higher in patients with BD-I. When BD-I 
patients were compared with BD-II patients, BIS-11 (attention) scores were higher in patients 
with BD-II and BIS-11 (motor and nonplanning impulsivity) scores were higher in patients 
with BD-I. According to BDFQ, relations with friends, participation in social activities, 
daily activities and hobbies, and occupation subscale scores were lower and taking initiative 
subscale scores were higher in patients with BD-I. Social withdrawal subscale scores were 
higher in patients with BD-II. 
Conclusion: In our study, NS, HA, and RD scores that may be found high in suicide attempters 
and Sdi scores that may be found low in suicide attempters were as follows: NS1, NS2, HA4, 
and RD2 subscale scores were high and Sdi scores were low in patients with BD-I, suggesting 
a higher rate of suicide attempts in this group of patients. In addition, C and Sdi scores that 
indicate a predisposition to personality disorder were significantly lower in patients with BD-I 
than patients with BD-II and healthy controls, suggesting a higher rate of personality disorder 
comorbidity in patients with BD-I. Higher impulsivity and suicidality rates and poorer func-
tionality in patients with BD-I also suggest that patients with BD-I may be more impulsive and 
more prone to suicide and have poorer functionality in some areas. 
Bipolar disorder (BD) is a mental disorder characterized by 
manic, depressive, and mixed episodes, and life-expectancy 
has been found to be much shorter in patients, with BD preva-
lence of BD-I and BD-II being 0.8% and 0.5% respectively. </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>BD is divided into BD-I, BD-II, cyclothymic disorder, and 
BD not otherwise specified (NOS) subgroups according to 
Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 4th 
Edition (DSM-IV) classification system. 
3 In a study examining 
Bipolar spectrum disorders among 300 patients, BD rate was 
found to be high and a majority of the BD cases had BD-II. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>The presence of other Axis I disorders, alcohol and substance 
use, rapid cycling, early onset of bipolar, a family history of 
suicide attempts, and severe mixed and depressive episodes 
may constitute risk factors for suicide attempts in patients with 
BD. 
5 Patients with BD have a suicide rate that is 30 times higher 
than the general population, and 15%-25% of bipolar patients 
attempt suicide. Fifteen percent of those who attempted suicide 
succeed in ending their lives. 
6 Although no difference exists 
in attempted suicide rates between BD-I and BD-II patients, 
BD-II patients tend toward more lethal suicide attempts. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Personality disorder comorbidity in patients with 
psychiatric disorders has been reported to increase the risk 
of suicide. 
8,9 Personality traits are among the many predictors 
of suicide in patients with BD. 
10 Cloninger has developed 
a dimensional psychobiological model of personality that 
accounts for two major components of personality: tem-
perament and character traits. Cloninger's psychobiological 
theory of personality contains four temperament dimensions 
including novelty seeking (NS), harm avoidance (HA), 
reward dependence (RD), and persistence (P) along with 
three character dimensions including self-directedness 
(Sdi), cooperativeness (C), and self-transcendence (ST). 
Temperament dimensions reflect biological, hereditary 
aspects of personality. Temperament is distinguished from 
character by individual differences in interpersonal relation-
ships and object relations. Meanwhile, life events, culture, 
and social learning mold character dimensions. 
11-14 BD 
patients have higher novelty-seeking scores and lower persis-
tence scores than depressive patients and normal subjects. </p>

<p>15,16 </p>

<p>Higher NS scores may predict impaired functioning. 
17 In 
addition, current research findings show that specific tem-
perament types (depressive, cyclothymic, hyperthymic, 
irritable, and anxious) are the subsyndromal (trait-related) 
manifestations and commonly the antecedents of minor and 
major mood disorders. Up to 20% of the population has some 
kind of marked temperaments; depressive, cyclothymic, and 
anxious temperament is more frequent in women, whereas 
hyperthymic and irritable temperaments predominate among </p>

<p>men. Premorbid temperament types have an important role 
in the clinical evolution of minor and major mood episodes 
including the direction of the polarity and the symptom 
formation of acute mood episodes. They can also significantly 
affect the long-term course and outcome including suicidality 
and other forms of self-destructive behaviors. 
18 More than 
81% of the patients with prevailing cyclothymic-depressive-
anxious temperament had mild-to-severe suicidal risk on the 
MINI versus only around 42% of the patients with prevailing 
hyperthymic temperament. 
19 Here, we aimed to compare a 
history of attempted suicide, temperament character traits, 
impulsivity, and levels of functionality in BD-I and BD-II 
patients admitted to our outpatient clinic. </p>

<p>Patients and methods 
sample </p>

<p>Fifty-two patients diagnosed with BD-I and 49 patients 
diagnosed with BD-II using a structured interview for 
DSM-IV Axis I Disorders (SCID-I/CV) who were admitted 
to the outpatient psychiatry clinic of the Erenköy Mental 
and Neurological Diseases Training and Research Hospital 
between March 2013 and August 2013 were enrolled in this 
study. Also 50 age-and sex-matched healthy control sub-
jects who met the study criteria and had no history of any 
psychiatric or neurological disease were included. Verbal 
and written informed consent was taken from the patient and 
control group. The study was started after the approval of 
Ethics Committee of Erenköy Psychiatric and Neurological 
Diseases Training and Research Hospital. 
Individuals who were between 18 and 60 years old, literate 
enough to understand written documents, diagnosed with BD 
according to Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Dis-
orders, 4th Edition, Text Revision (DSM-IV-TR), in remission at 
least for 2 months with a Hamilton Rating Score of Depression 
(HRSD) lower than 7, and a Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS) 
score lower than 5 were included. Impulsivity and temperament 
characteristics were evaluated during remission. 
We excluded from the study patients with mental retarda-
tion, alcohol and drug-abuse related disorders, anxiety disor-
ders, schizophrenia and other psychotic disorders, dementia 
and other cognitive disorders, and neurological disorders with 
unique personality traits such as epilepsy, migraine, multiple 
sclerosis, and Parkinson's disease, as well as systemic dis-
orders leading to cognitive impairment or affecting vision, 
hearing, or motor skills. </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>We assessed all patients and controls using a semistructured 
sociodemographic data form based on clinical experience </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2016:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>179 </p>

<p>The differences in temperament-character traits </p>

<p>and an investigation of the literature, structured clinical 
interview for DSM-IV SCID-I, Temperament and Character 
Inventory (TCI), and Barratt Impulsivity Scale 11 (BIS-11). 
Additionally, Hamilton Depression Rating Scale, YMRS, and 
Bipolar Disorder Functioning Questionnaire (BDFQ) were 
administered to the patient group. </p>

<p>Data collection tools </p>

<p>Sociodemographic and clinical information </p>

<p>Sociodemographic and clinical information was collected 
using a questionnaire consisting of some questions regarding 
age, sex, marital status, educational level, and economic sta-
tus, for patients with BD-I, BD-II, and the control group. </p>

<p>structured clinical interview for DsM-iV/clinical Version 
This structured interview was developed by First et al 
20 in 
1995 to determine the presence or absence of DSM-IV Axis I 
disorders. Çorapçıoğlu conducted a validation and reliability 
study for the Turkish version in 1999. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Temperament and character inventory 
The TCI is a 240-item, self-report questionnaire with true-
or-false statements developed to assess personality. The 
TCI consists of seven higher-order scales. The temperament 
dimensions of NS, HA, and RD are each divided into four 
subscales, while the character dimensions of Sdi and coopera-
tiveness (C) are each divided into five subscales. In addition, 
ST is divided into three subscales. 
11 Köse et al 
22 conducted 
the validation and reliability study for the Turkish version 
of the inventory in 2004. </p>

<p>Barratt impulsiveness scale-11 
This is a 30-item self-report measure intended to assess 
impulsivity in which the individual marks the most appro-
priate answers to a series of questions from the alternatives, 
"rarely/never, occasionally, often, and almost always/ 
always." A factor analysis indentified three second-order 
factors: 1) attentional impulsivity, 2) motor impulsivity, 
and 3) nonplanned impulsivity. Higher scores indicate higher 
levels of impulsivity. 
23 Güleç et al 
24 conducted the validation 
and reliability study for the Turkish version in 2008. </p>

<p>Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression 
This is the most widely used scale for assessing depression 
severity and was developed by Williams in 1978. 
25 The sum 
of the scores obtained from each item provide the total score. 
Scores below 7 indicate no depression, scores between 7 and 
17 indicate moderate depression, scores between 18 and 24 
indicate heavy depression, and scores $25 indicate severe </p>

<p>depression. Akdemir et al 
26 conducted the validation and 
reliability study for the Turkish version in 1996. </p>

<p>Young Mania Rating Scale 
Young et al 
27 developed this scale, which is widely used to 
assess the intensity of manic symptoms. The scale consists of 
eleven items. Seven of them have five Likert-type items and 
four of them have nine Likert-type items. The lowest score 
that can be obtained from the scale is 0, while the highest 
score is 44. The validity and reliability of the Turkish version 
has been tested by Karadağ et al. 
28 The cut-off score was not 
calculated during the Turkish version's validity and reliability 
study. Here, we compared both total scores and single-item 
scores according to sex. </p>

<p>Bipolar Disorder Functioning Questionnaire (BDFQ) 
This is a 52-item self-report measure intended to assess the 
functionality of bipolar patients during symptomatic periods 
or recovery. Aydemir et al 
29 developed the questionnaire that 
consists of eleven subscales, including emotional function-
ing, intellectual functioning, sexual functioning, stigma-
tization feelings, social withdrawal, household relations, 
relations with friends, participation in social activities, daily 
activities and hobbies, initiative taking, self-sufficiency, 
and occupation. Because the cut-off score could not be 
calculated, it was recommended for use in comparative 
studies. </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>"<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS for Windows 8.0</rs>" (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) 
was used for data analysis. Chi-square test was used to 
evaluate the relationship between categorical variables. 
After testing for homogeneity and normality of variances, 
Student's t-test was performed to evaluate the difference 
between temperament and impulsivity. One-way analysis of 
variance (ANOVA) and Tukey post hoc test were performed 
to evaluate the patient subgroups. Results were evaluated at 
95% confidence interval and significance was evaluated at 
P,0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Fifty-two patients diagnosed with BD-I and 49 patients 
diagnosed with BD-II according to the DSM-IV-TR and 
50 age-and sex-matched controls were enrolled in this 
study. The mean age in the patient and control groups was 
35.69±12.10 years and 32.00±9.24 years, respectively. There 
was no statistically significant difference between the patient 
and control groups in terms of sociodemographic properties 
(P.0.05; Table 1). Thirty-eight (37.62%) subjects in the </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2016:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>izci et al </p>

<p>patient group had a suicide attempt and 23 (60.52%) of these 
patients were diagnosed with BD-I and 15 (39.47%) were 
diagnosed with BD-II (Table 2). 
Suicide attempt rates of BD-I and BD-II patients were 
60.52% and 39.47%, respectively (P,0.05; Table 2). 
Within temperament dimension, in the comparison of the 
patients with BD-I, BD-II, and healthy controls, there was 
a statistically significant difference between the groups in 
terms of NS (NS1 and NS2; respectively: F=6.17, P,0.05; 
F=16.32, P,0.00), HA4 (F=6.83, P,0.05), and RD (RD2; 
F=8.80, P,0.01). 
Within character dimension, in the comparison of the 
patients with BD-I, BD-II, and healthy controls, there was a 
statistically significant difference between the groups in terms 
of Sdi subgroups (Sdi1, Sdi2, Sdi3, Sdi5; F=11.72, P,0.05; 
F=23.05, P,0.00; F=14.64, P,0.00; F=19.97, P,0.00), total 
Sdi (F=17.55, P,0.00), C subgroups (C1, C2, C3, C4, C5; 
respectively, F=7.36, P,0.05; F=6.68, P,0.05, F=13.13, 
P,0.00; F=6.11, P,0.05, F=12.69, P,0.00), and total C 
scores (C; F=17.55, P,0.00). In the comparison of patients </p>

<p>with BD-I, BD-II, and healthy controls, there was a statisti-
cally significant difference between the groups in terms of ST 
subgroups (ST1, ST2; respectively, F=9.91, P,0.00; F=15.66, 
P,0.00) and total ST scores (F=8.43, P,0.00; Table 3). 
According to the BIS-11, motor impulsiveness and 
nonplanning impulsiveness subgroup scores were found 
to be statistically significantly higher in patients with 
BD-I (respectively, F=21.04, P,0.00; F=23.88, P,0.00). 
However, attentional impulsiveness subgroup score was </p>

<p>Table 1 Sociodemographic characteristics of the patients and 
controls </p>

<p>Patient 
(N=101) </p>

<p>Control 
(N=50) </p>

<p>Statistic </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Age (mean ± SD) 
35.69±12.10 
32.00±9.24 
1.89 
0.06* 
Sex 
Male 
71 (70.3) 
30 (60.0) 
1.60 
0.20* 
Female 
30 (29.7) 
20 (40.0) 
Educational status 
Primary school 
34 (33.6) 
8 (16.0) 
High school 
32 (31.7) 
15 (30.0) 
5.40 
0.06* 
University 
35 (34.7) 
27 (54.0) 
Marital status 
Married 
41 (40.6) 
18 (36.0) 
Single 
60 (59.4) 
32 (64.0) 
1.60 
0.20* 
Occupational status 
employed 
67 (66.3) 
30 (60.0) 
Unemployed 
27 (26.7) 
10 (20.0) 
10.94 
0.06* 
student 
7 (6.90) 
10 (20.0) </p>

<p>Notes: *P.0.05. Data presented as number (%). 
Abbreviation: sD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Table 2 comparison of suicide attempt rates of patients with 
BD-i and BD-ii </p>

<p>The group of 
patients with 
BD-I (N=52) </p>

<p>The group of 
patients with 
BD-II (N=49) </p>

<p>Statistic </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P-value* </p>

<p>Suicide attempt (+), 
(N, %) </p>

<p>23 (60.52) 
15 (39.47) </p>

<p>Suicide attempt (-), 
(N, %) </p>

<p>29 (46.03) 
34 (53.96) 
1.70 0.019 </p>

<p>Note: *P,0.05. 
Abbreviations: BD-i, bipolar disorder i; BD-ii, bipolar disorder ii. </p>

<p>Table 3 comparison of Tci scores of patients with BD-i, BD-ii, 
and healthy controls </p>

<p>BD-I 
(N=52) </p>

<p>BD-II 
(N=49) </p>

<p>Controls 
(N=50) </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Novelty seeking 
Ns1 
6.06±1.76 
5.31±2.11 
6.34±2.03 
6.17 
0.04* 
Ns2 
4.88±2.02 
4.22±2.00 
3.14±1.97 
16.32 
0.00* 
Ns3 
5.48±2.35 
4.46±2.34 
4.88±1.49 
3.68 
0.15 
Ns4 
4.09±1.89 
4.24±1.92 
4.24±1.66 
0.37 
0.82 
Total 
20.51±8.02 
18.23±8.37 
18.60±4.83 
0.82 
0.71 
Harm avoidance 
ha1 
6.18±2.32 
5.09±2.44 
5.02±2.05 
5.20 
0.07 
ha2 
3.75±1.81 
3.72±1.54 
3.64±1.50 
0.39 
0.81 
ha3 
3.42±2.35 
2.81±2.25 
3.08±1.38 
1.51 
0.46 
ha4 
4.65±2.33 
4.26±1.91 
3.48±1.52 
6.83 
0.03* 
Total 
18.00±8.81 
15.88±8.14 
15.22±3.72 
2.73 
0.24 
Reward dependence 
rD1 
6.68±2.16 
7.47±1.72 
7.37±1.66 
3.11 
0.21 
rD2 
4.92±1.79 
4.21±1.65 
3.85±1.68 
8.80 
0.01* 
rD3 
2.80±1.30 
2.45±1.20 
2.27±1.30 
4.41 
0.11 
Total 
14.40±3.69 
14.15±3.08 
13.56±2.66 
1.99 
0.36 
Persistence 
P 
4.81±1.86 
5.41±2.53 
5.16±1.85 
0.82 
0.66 
Self-directedness 
sD1 
4.19±1.86 
4.24±2.27 
5.58±1.73 
11.72 
0.03* 
sD2 
4.86±1.58 
5.25±1.75 
6.58±1.57 
23.50 
0.00* 
sD3 
2.66±1.39 
2.88±1.56 
3.78±1.09 
14.64 
0.00* 
sD4 
5.24±2.81 
5.53±2.23 
5.76±2.55 
0.75 
0.68 
sD5 
6.45±2.06 
6.61±2.38 
8.40±1.93 
19.97 
0.00* 
Total 
22.77±7.43 
24.72±8.16 
30.10±6.22 
17.55 
0.00* 
Cooperativeness 
c1 
5.29±2.00 
6.03±1.51 
6.46±1.40 
7.36 
0.02* 
c2 
3.93±1.22 
4.16±1.26 
4.70±1.32 
6.68 
0.03* 
c3 
4.34±1.45 
5.00±1.23 
5.48±1.18 
13.13 
0.00* 
c4 
6.29±2.54 
7.75±1.64 
6.82±1.99 
6.11 
0.04* 
c5 
6.42±1.58 
6.51±1.73 
7.54±1.03 
12.69 
0.00* 
Total 
26.27±8.79 
29.45±7.37 
31.00±4.12 
6.83 
0.00* 
Self-transcendence 
sT1 
6.30±2.76 
7.03±2.61 
5.26±2.34 
8.91 
0.00* 
sT2 
5.23±2.14 
6.00±2.25 
4.06±1.95 
15.66 
0.00* 
sT3 
7.06±2.66 
8.29±2.97 
7.30±3.11 
3.40 
0.18 
Total 
18.59±7.98 
21.32±7.83 
16.62±6.03 
8.43 
0.00* </p>

<p>Notes: F, aNOVa test value. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Post hoc assessment Tukey test. *P,0.05. Data 
presented as mean ± standard deviation. 
Abbreviations: BD-i, bipolar disorder i; BD-ii, bipolar disorder ii; aNOVa, 
analysis of variance; Tci, temperament and character inventory. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2016:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>181 </p>

<p>The differences in temperament-character traits </p>

<p>found to be statistically significantly higher in patients with 
BD-II (F=15.31, P,0.00; Table 4). 
Patients with BD-I had lower scores than patients with 
BD-II in relations with friends, participation in social 
activities, daily activities and hobbies, and occupation sub-
scales on the BDFQ (P,0.05, P,0.05, P,0.01, P,0.01, 
respectively). While the social withdrawal subscore was 
higher in patients with BD-II (P,0.05), taking initiative and 
self-sufficiency subscores were higher in patients with BD-I 
(P,0.05; Table 5). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The risk of suicide attempts among psychiatric disorders was 
identified as highest in patients with mood disorders (60%). 
Twenty percent of those with BD die by suicide, as com-
pared to 15% of those with major depressive disorder, 18% 
of those with alcoholism, 10% of those with schizophrenia, 
and 5%-10% of those with Axis II disorders. 
30,31 Thirty-
eight (37.62%) patients in our study had attempted suicide. </p>

<p>Of patients who attempted suicide, 23 (60.52%) had BD-I 
and 15 (39.47%) had BD-II. Increased suicide rates may con-
tribute to a lower life expectancy and quality of life. Suicide 
attempt rates are 20-30 times higher in bipolar patients than 
general population. 
32 In a study with bipolar and unipolar 
depressive disorder patients, high suicide risk was found in 
more than 52% of the patients and depressive anxiety symp-
toms, impulsivity, and hostility rates were higher in patients 
with high suicidality risk. </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>The coexistence of a personality disorder is present in 
the majority of the patients who attempted suicide. In a 
controlled study of patients with BD, a personality disorder 
diagnosis according to the DSM IV was present in 48% of 
bipolar patients. 
34 Given that the prevalence of personality 
disorders among the general population is about 5.9%, per-
sonality disorder is significantly higher in patients with BD 
than general population. 
35 Patients with personality disorder 
were more likely to attempt suicide, 
36 both in our study and in 
the literature. 
37 Similarly, character traits are one of the many 
predictors for suicide attempts in patients with BD. 
Studies examining the relationship between suicide 
attempts and temperament and character traits have shown 
that suicide attempters had lower Sdi 
32,33 and higher ST </p>

<p>32-34 </p>

<p>subscale scores within character dimension and higher 
HA, NS, and RD subscale scores 
11,35 within temperament 
dimension. Another study found a relationship between 
higher HA scores and suicide attempts in patients with BD. </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>Consistent with the literature, in our study, NS1, NS2, HA4, 
and RD2 subscale scores are found to be higher and Sdi scores 
are found to be lower in patients with BD-I than BD-II and 
controls. For personality disorders, the rate of completed 
suicide has been identified as 29%-57%. 
39 Slama et al 
40 have 
proposed that low Sdi and C scores could possibly predict the 
development of a personality disorder. In our study, lower Sdi 
and C scores in patients with BD-I than patients with BD-II 
and controls suggest that personality disorder coexistence 
may occur more frequently in patients with BD-I. 
In the literature, suicide risk factors for patients with BD-I 
and BD-II include a family history of suicide attempts, early 
onset of BD, frequent depressive symptoms, alcohol and sub-
stance abuse, social phobia features, antidepressant-induced 
mania, and a history of head trauma. No statistically signifi-
cant differences were found in terms of suicide ideation and 
attempts between patients with BD-I and BD-II. 
41,42 Suicide-
attempt rates were higher in patients with BD compared to 
patients with unipolar depressive disorder. Suicide-attempt 
rates were also higher in patients with BD-II as compared to 
BD-I. 
42 However in our study, 23 (60.52%) of 38 attempters </p>

<p>Table 4 comparison of impulsivity in patients with BD-i and BD-ii </p>

<p>BIS-11 
Patients 
with BD-I 
(mean ± SD) </p>

<p>Patients 
with BD-II 
(mean ± SD) </p>

<p>Controls Statistics </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Total 
70.80±23.24 
65.27±12.32 
57.08±9.56 22.17 0.00* 
Nonplanned 30.69±27.59 
25.02±4.92 
22.66±3.77 23.88 0.00* 
Motor 
23.00±5.36 
22.85±6.43 
18.82±4.66 21.04 0.00* 
attentional 17.11±4.25 
17.40±4.87 
14.38±3.12 15.31 0.00* </p>

<p>Notes: F, aNOVa test value. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Post hoc assessment Tukey test. *P,0.05. 
Abbreviations: BD-i, bipolar disorder i; BD-ii, bipolar disorder ii; aNOVa, analysis 
of variance; Bis-11, Barrett impulsiveness scale-11. </p>

<p>Table 5 Comparison of functioning in patients with BD-I and BD-II </p>

<p>BDFQ 
BD-I 
(N=52) </p>

<p>BD-II 
(N=49) </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>t 
P-value </p>

<p>Emotional functioning 
3.62±1.13 3.85±1.09 -0.9 
0.52 
Intellectual functioning 
4.51±1.07 4.22±1.04 1.22 
0.13 
Sexual functioning 
3.76±1.96 3.97±2.09 -0.46 0.68 
Feelings of stigmatization 
3.19±2.23 3.44±2.32 -0.5 
0.56 
social withdrawal 
2.88±1.61 3.68±1.56 -2.26 0.03* 
household relations 
6.16±2.89 6.42±3.08 -0.38 0.86 
relations with friends 
4.90±2.46 6.75±2.45 -3.39 0.02* 
Participation to social 
activities </p>

<p>7.47±3.50 9.20±4.39 -1.97 0.04* </p>

<p>Daily activities and hobbies 4.34±2.24 6.35±3.70 -2.96 0.01** 
Taking initiative and self 
sufficiency </p>

<p>2.62±1.44 1.67±1.87 2.22 
0.03* </p>

<p>Occupation 
4.42±1.48 5.16±1.67 -2.03 0.01** </p>

<p>Note: *P,0.05, **P,0.01. 
Abbreviations: BDFQ, Bipolar Disorder Functioning Questionnaire; BD-I, bipolar 
disorder i; BD-ii, bipolar disorder ii; sD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2016:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>182 </p>

<p>izci et al </p>

<p>had BD-I, and 15 (39.47%) had BD-II. Other studies of BD 
patients have identified that unipolar patients had higher NS </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>and lower Sdi 
6 scores compared to healthy controls. In a simi-
lar study, patients with BD had higher NS scores than patients 
with unipolar disorder and patients with bipolar and unipolar 
disorder had higher HA scores than healthy controls. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>In our study, within temperament dimension, NS1, NS2, 
HA4, and RD2 subscale scores were significantly higher in 
patients with BD-I than BD-II and healthy controls. Within 
character dimension, total Sdi scores, total C scores, and 
subscale scores for both dimensions were significantly 
lower in patients with BD-I than BD-II and healthy controls. 
In addition, total ST scores and ST subscale scores were 
significantly higher in patients with BD-II than BD-I and 
healthy controls. Because Slama et al 
40 considered C and Sdi 
scores as predictors of personality disorder, low C and Sdi 
scores in patients with BD-I suggest that the coexistence 
of personality disorder with BD could be more frequent in 
patients with BD-I. NS indicates a hereditary predisposition 
to exploratory activity in response to a new stimulus, impul-
sive decision making and irritability. 
12-14,38 Because in our 
study NS scores were higher in patients with BD-I, we may 
think that these patients may be more prone to impulsive 
behaviors like suicide. 
Two main differences emerged in bipolar patients with 
and without a history of attempted suicide. One of these 
differences was that suicide attempters had more subjective 
depression and hopelessness, as well as more seriously sui-
cidal ideations; they also displayed lifelong reactionary and 
aggressive tendencies. Patients who had attempted suicide 
were more impulsive in decision making and interpersonal 
relationships. 
43,44 Lifelong aggression levels were higher in 
patients with suicide attempts, but impulsivity levels were 
similar between the two groups. 
45 In our study, both motor 
and nonplanned impulsivity scores were higher in patients 
with BD-I than BD-II. In the manic phase, impulsivity is 
characterized by unplanned and motor impulsivity, whereas 
in the depressive phase, it is characterized again by unplanned 
impulsivity. Attentional impulsivity is present in BD-II. 
Impulsive behaviors such as suicide attempts usually occur 
in the depressive phase of BD. 
46,47 In our study, in concor-
dance with literature, motor and nonplanned impulsivity was 
pronounced in patients with BD-I and attentional impulsivity 
was pronounced in patients with BD-II. 
In the BDFQ, social withdrawal, relationships with 
friends, participation in social activities, daily activities 
and hobbies and occupation subscale scores were lower in 
patients with BD-I than BD-II, and only initiative-taking </p>

<p>subscale scores were significantly higher in patients with 
BD-I than BD-II. BD adversely affects nearly every area 
of life and reduces overall functionality. 
48 Two studies 
investigating the differences between the psychosocial 
functioning of patients with BD-I and BD-II have shown that 
similar disabilities were present during both their euthymic 
and depressive periods. 
49,50 A recent meta-analysis showed 
similar levels of deterioration in cognitive functioning in 
euthymic patients with BD-I and BD-II. Euthymic patients 
with BD experience cognitive deficits, especially in executive 
functioning, working memory, and attention. 
51 In our study, 
patients with BD-I had a more corrupted functionality in 
social activities and relationships than patients with BD-II. </p>

<p>study limitations </p>

<p>Our study has several limitations, including its cross-
sectional design, the relatively small subject numbers, and 
the exclusive use of self-report questionnaires. Although 
it is not possible to establish direct causal relationships or 
determine predictive factors with these findings, our results 
are noteworthy in terms of being descriptive of the clinical 
characteristics of our patient population. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Suicide attempts in patients with BD-I and -II significantly 
affect individual's life and functionality. Early diagnosis, 
individual assessment of symptomatology, and the establish-
ment of a treatment process are the most important factors. 
Our study has shown that impulsivity and risk of attempting 
suicide are higher in patients with BD-I than BD-II. In addi-
tion, patients with BD-I are found to have poorer function-
ality than patients with BD-II. High NS1, NS2, HA4, RD2 
subscale scores and low Sdi and C scores may be related to 
suicide attempts. Higher motor and nonplanned impulsivity 
scores in patients with BD-I than BD-II suggest that these 
may be facilitating factors for an impulsive behavior like 
suicide. Identifying impulsivity, suicide attempts, tempera-
ment-character traits, and functionality in patients with BD-I 
and BD-II will be useful in the diagnosis and treatment of 
disease progression. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/neuropsychiatric-disease-and-treatment-journal </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment is an international, peer-
reviewed journal of clinical therapeutics and pharmacology focusing 
on concise rapid reporting of clinical or pre-clinical studies on a 
range of neuropsychiatric and neurological disorders. This journal 
is indexed on PubMed Central, the 'PsycINFO' database and CAS, </p>

<p>and is the official journal of The International Neuropsychiatric 
Association (INA). The manuscript management system is completely 
online and includes a very quick and fair peer-review system, which 
is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to 
read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2016:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>