<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4435018" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>SUMMARY </p>

<p>The emergence of zoonotic visceral leishmaniasis (ZVL) in Latin America is a growing public health problem. The urbanization 
of ZVL has been observed in different countries around the world, and there are a growing number of reports drawing attention to 
the emergence of this infection in new locations, as well as its increase in previously established areas of endemicity. In the city of 
Posadas, Misiones province, Northeastern Argentina, the transmission of ZVL associated with canines and Lutzomyia longipalpis was 
first reported in 2006. In the city of Puerto Iguazú, also in Misiones province, the first human case of ZVL was reported in February 
2014. From 209 surveyed dogs, 15 (7.17%) were identified as positive by serological and/or parasitological methods. Amplification 
was observed in 14 samples and in all cases the species implicated was Leishmania infantum. To the authors' knowledge, this is the 
first molecular characterization of L. infantum from dogs in this area. </p>

<p>ACOSTA, L.; DÍAZ, R.; TORRES, P.; SILVA, G.; RAMOS, M.; FATTORE, G.; DESCHUTTER, E.J. &amp; BORNAY-LLINARES, F.J. -Identification of Leishmania infantum in Puerto Iguazú, 
Misiones, Argentina. Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo, 57(2): 175-6, 2015. </p>

<p>176 </p>

<p>IFAT threshold title for positivity was 1/160. From 209 surveyed dogs, 
13 (6.22%) were seropositive by IFI (13/209) and/or by ICT (12/209). </p>

<p>Lymph node samples were washed with 500 µL of PBS and DNA 
was extracted by conventional phenol-chloroform extraction and ethanol 
precipitation </p>

<p>7   , and further eluted in 100 µL sterile distilled water. Purified 
DNA was stored at -80 
o C until further use. Parasite DNA detection was 
done by means of PCR targeting the Leishmania intergenic transcript 
spacer (ITS-1) 
10 . Amplicons were visualized in seven out of 209 
dogs. A total of 15 (7.17%) dogs were positive by serological and/or 
parasitological methods. </p>

<p>Later, those 15 positive dogs were subjected to a nested-PCR with 
outer pair previously used 
7 and inner pair SAC (5´-CATTTTCCGATGAT 
TACACC-3´) and VAN2 (5´-GCGACACGTTATGTG AGCCG-3´) to 
amplify an internal region (280 to 330 bp) of the fragment as described 
by CRUZ et al. in 2013 
6 . Direct sequencing of the PCR products 
was performed with forward and reverse primers; using the Big-
Dye Terminator Cycle Sequencing Ready Reaction Kit V3.1 and the 
automated sequencer "3730 DNA analyzer" (Applied Biosystems, Foster 
City, CA). Sequences obtained were analyzed and edited using <rs id="software-0" type="software">BioEdit</rs> 
v<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">7.2.5</rs>.©1999-2013 software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Tom Hall, Ibis Biosciences</rs>, Carlsbad, CA). 
Amplification was observed in 14 of the 15 samples studied and in all 
cases the species implicated was L. infantum. </p>

<p>In February 2014, the first fatal case of VL in humans was reported 
in the city of Puerto Iguazú 
8 . Although the infecting species in this 
patient is not known, 29 human-VL patients at species level have been 
identified in the following cities; Posadas, Oberá, San Ignacio, Candelaria 
and Apóstoles (Misiones Province), as well as in 52 dogs sampled in 
2006 
5 and 53 dogs in 2010, all from Posadas. L. infantum was the only 
Leishmania species identified infecting humans and dogs (unpublished 
data). </p>

<p>In conclusion, the changes in the urbanization of the vector, the 
existence of susceptible reservoir hosts (dogs), vectors (Lu. Longipalpis) 
and the proximity of the disease to Paraguay, Brazil 
2 and other cities of 
Misiones, may have favored the establishment of ZVL by L. infantum 
in Puerto Iguazú. It is important to highlight the strategic position of the 
city of Puerto Iguazú as a contributing factor to the spread of the disease, 
because of its geographical location (a location at which the Argentine, 
Paraguayan and Brazilian borders meet) and the influx of tourists it 
receives throughout the year due to the nearby Iguazú National Park 
(Iguazú falls). CanL control policies should be established in order to 
prevent further human and canine cases. </p>

<p>RESUMEN </p>

<p>Identificación de Leishmania infantum en Puerto Iguazú, 
Misiones, Argentina </p>

<p>La emergencia de leishmaniosis visceral zoonótica (LVZ) en América 
Latina es problema de salud pública en aumento. La urbanización de 
la LVZ es un fenómeno observado en diferentes países alrededor del 
mundo y hay un número creciente tanto de denuncias respecto a la 
aparición de esta infección en nuevas ubicaciones, como su aumento </p>

<p>en zonas endémicas previamente establecidas. En la ciudad de Posadas, 
provincia de Misiones, nordeste de Argentina, la transmisión de LVZ 
asociada a canes y Lutzomyia longipalpis fue descrita por primera 
vez en 2006. En la ciudad de Puerto Iguazú, provincia de Misiones, 
el primer caso humano de LVZ tuvo lugar en febrero de 2014. De 209 
perros muestreados, 15 (7.17%) resultaron positivos mediante métodos 
serológicos y/o parasitológicos. Se observó amplificación en 14 muestras 
y en todos los casos la especie implicada fue Leishmania infantum. Según 
nuestro conocimiento, esta es la primera caracterización molecular de 
L. infantum en perros procedentes de este área. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors especially acknowledge the essential collaboration of the 
"Mundo Sano" Foundation, the Ministry of Public Health of Misiones 
and the City Land Registry of Puerto Iguazú. </p>

<p>This study was supported by the Agencia Española de Cooperación 
Internacional al Desarrollo (AECID) (A2/037352/11) and Centro de 
Cooperación y Voluntariado of the Universidad Miguel Hernández de 
Elche (UMH), Alicante, Spain. </p>



<p>Received: 26 May 2014 
Accepted: 1 July 2014 </p>

</text></tei>