<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4027853" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Interleukin (IL)-17 has been shown to play an important role in the pathogenesis </p>

<p>of inflammation and cancer. The IL-17A (-197G/A) and IL-17F (7488T/C) polymorphisms 
have been extensively investigated with cancer risk, but individually published results have 
been inconclusive. The aim of this study was to clarify the effects of the IL-17A (-197G/A) and 
IL-17F (7488T/C) polymorphisms on cancer risk in Asian populations. Relevant studies were 
identified by searching databases extensively. The association between the IL-17A (-197G/A) 
and IL-17F (7488T/C) polymorphisms and cancer risk was assessed by odds ratios (ORs) 
together with their 95% confidence intervals (CIs). A total of 12 articles with adequate infor-
mation satisfied our inclusion criteria; these included 12 studies, with 4,540 cases and 5,875 
controls, of IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism and seven studies, with 1,960 cases and 3,226 
controls, of IL-17F (7488T/C) polymorphism. In the overall analysis, the IL-17A (-197G/A) 
polymorphism was significantly associated with increased cancer risk (P,0.05), for all genetic 
models. However, there was no statistically significant association between IL-17F (7488T/C) 
and cancer risk (P.0.05), for any genetic models. Furthermore, stratification by cancer type 
revealed a significant correlation between the IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism and cancer 
risk for all cancer types. When stratified by source of controls, a significant correlation was 
observed between the IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism and cancer risk in the population-
based control subgroup but not in hospital-based control subgroup. In conclusion, our meta-
analysis provides evidence that the IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism might be associated with 
cancer risk, while no evidence suggested a significant association between IL-17F (7488T/C) 
polymorphism and cancer risk. 
Interleukin (IL)-17A, initially termed as cytotoxic T lymphocyte-associated antigen 
(CTLA)-8, is the founding member of IL-17 cytokine family, consisting of six homolo-
gous proteins (from IL-17A to IL-17F). 1 IL-17 is a pleiotropic cytokine that acts on 
multiple cell types to enhance the production of proinflammatory molecules, including 
the induction of IL-6, IL-8, and prostaglandin E 2 , as well as enhancing granulocyte 
colony-stimulating factor and CXC chemokine production. 2,3 In addition, IL-17 induces 
secretion of tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α, IL-1β, and stromelysin, by macrophages, 4,5 
and activates the nuclear factor κB and activator protein 1 transcription factors, which 
may explain its proinflammatory properties. 6,7 
Recently, several studies have shown that IL-17 can have either a protumor or 
antitumor role in different cancer models. 8 Accumulating evidence indicates that IL-17 </p>

<p>Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
13 May 2014 </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2014:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>704 </p>

<p>Dai et al </p>

<p>expression is aberrant in several human tumors, such as 
ovarian cancer, 9 cervical cancer, 10 breast cancer, 11 hepatocel-
lular carcinoma, 12 esophageal cancer, 13 gastric cancer, 14 and 
colorectal cancer. 15 But the underlying mechanism of IL-17 
in tumor initiation and progression is not yet completely 
clear. Of note, Kryczek et al suggested that endogenous 
IL-17 or/and T helper (Th)17 cells may play a protective 
role in tumor immunity. 16 Martin-Orozco et al reported that 
IL-17A-deficient mice were more susceptible to developing 
lung melanoma. 17 These studies showed an opposite role 
of IL-17; specifically, they suggest an antitumor effect, by 
promoting cytotoxic T lymphocyte generation. 
A large number of previous studies have suggested the 
possible correlation between genetic polymorphisms of can-
cer susceptibility genes and higher risk of human malignant 
tumors. There are several single nucleotide polymorphisms 
(SNPs) that are reported for the IL-17 gene, and the IL-17A 
gene polymorphism IL-17A (-197G/A, rs2275913) and IL-17F 
gene polymorphism IL-17F (7488T/C, rs763780) are reported 
to be associated in gastric carcinogenesis. 18 IL-17A (-197G/A), 
located at a position -197 from the starting codon of the IL-17A 
gene, may regulate the expression of messenger ribonucleic 
acid (mRNA). 19 Recently, Kawaguchi et al reported that 
IL-17F (7488T/C) causes a histidine (His)-to-arginine (Arg) 
substitution at amino acid 161 (H161R) variant. 20 To date, 
many studies have been published that assessed the association 
between the IL-17A (-197G/A) and IL-17F (7488T/C) poly-
morphisms and cancer susceptibility, but they have reported 
controversial results. A single case-control study may fail to 
completely demonstrate the complicated genetic relationship 
because of the small sample size. 21 In order to provide strong 
evidence of the effects of the IL-17A (-197G/A) and IL-17F 
(7488T/C) polymorphisms on cancer susceptibility, we per-
formed a meta-analysis, by combining data from numerous 
published studies. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Search strategy </p>

<p>A comprehensive literature search of PubMed, Embase, 
Web of Science, Science Direct, SpringerLink, and the 
Chinese National Knowledge Infrastructure databases 
(up to November 2013) was conducted to identify case-
control studies that investigated the association between IL-17 
polymorphisms and cancer risk. The search strategies were 
based on combinations of the following keywords: "cancer or 
carcinoma or neoplasm or tumor" AND "IL-17 or IL-17A or 
IL-17F or CTLA" AND "polymorphism or variant or muta-
tion or genotype". There was no restriction on time period, </p>

<p>sample size, population, or language, in order to minimize 
potential publication bias. </p>

<p>Selection criteria </p>

<p>Studies were included in the meta-analysis if they satisfied the 
following inclusion criteria: 1) case-control studies focused 
on association between the IL-17A (-197G/A) or IL-17F 
(7844T/C) polymorphism and cancer risk; 2) study design 
that was either retrospective or a nested case-control design; 
3) any diagnoses of patients with cancer had to be confirmed 
by pathological examinations; and 4) sufficient published 
data to estimate the odds ratio (OR) and corresponding 
95% confidence interval (CI). The exclusion criteria of 
the meta-analysis were: 1) case-control studies not focus-
ing on the correlation between the IL-17A (-197G/A) or 
IL-17F (7844T/C) polymorphism and cancer risk; 2) studies 
with duplicate data; 3) studies with incomplete data; and 
4) meta-analyses, letters, reviews, and editorial articles. When 
an individual author published several articles obtained from 
the same patient population, only the newest or most complete 
article was included in the analysis. </p>

<p>Data extraction </p>

<p>Two authors independently extracted data from the included 
studies (Dai and Zhou). For each eligible study, the following 
information was extracted: first author's name, year of 
publication, country, ethnicity, cancer type, numbers of cases 
and controls, source of controls (hospital-based controls or 
population-based controls), genotyping method, and the 
Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium frequency. In cases of discrep-
ancy, a consensus was reached by consulting a third author. </p>

<p>Sensitivity analysis </p>

<p>Sensitivity analysis was employed by sequentially excluding 
a single study each time, in an attempt to identify the potential 
influence of the individual data set to the pooled ORs. 22 </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data management and processing were performed using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Review Manager (RevMan</rs>) <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">The Nordic Cochrane Centre</rs>, Copenhagen) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">11.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Stata Corp</rs>, College 
Station, Texas, USA). The strength of the association between 
the IL-17 gene polymorphisms and cancer risk was measured 
by crude ORs and 95% CIs. The significance of the combined 
ORs was determined by a Z test, and two-sided P-value ,0.05 
was considered significant. The pooled ORs were calculated 
for the allele model (mutation [M] allele versus [vs] wild [W] 
allele), dominant model (WM + MM vs WW), recessive model </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2014:7 </p>

<p>136 potentially relevant studies identified and screened 
through six databases (up to November. 2013) </p>

<p>116 studies were excluded: 
12 studies in animal model 
18 studies in cell line 
31 reviews 
2 case reports 
53 studies not related to IL-17 polymorphism </p>

<p>8 studies were excluded: 
4 studies with incomplete data 
2 studies with duplicate data 
2 studies with other IL-17 SNP </p>

<p>20 studies were retrieved for further analysis </p>

<p>12 studies were finally included (9 English, 3 Chinese) </p>

<p>Figure 1 Flow chart of the literature search and study selection. 
Abbreviations: IL, interleukin; SNP, single nucleotide polymorphism. </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>705 </p>

<p>IL-17A and IL-17F gene polymorphisms and cancer risk </p>

<p>(MM vs WM + WW), homozygote comparison (MM vs WW), 
and heterozygote comparison (WM vs WW), respectively. 
Stratified analyses were conducted with respect to cancer type 
and source of controls. Statistical heterogeneity among the 
studies was evaluated using the chi square-based Q-test, and 
heterogeneity was considered significant when P,0.1 for Q 
statistic. Heterogeneity was quantified by I2 statistics examin-
ing the percentage of heterogeneity (0%-25% = no heterogene-
ity; 25%-50% = moderate heterogeneity; 50%-75% = large 
heterogeneity; and 75%-100% = extreme heterogeneity). 23 
The random effects model was used when heterogeneity was 
significant (I 2 .50% or P#0.10); otherwise, the fixed effects 
model was used. Publication bias was examined with both 
Begg's funnel plot 24 and the Egger's regression method, 25 and 
P,0.05 was considered representative of statistically signifi-
cant publication bias. </p>

<p>Results 
Characteristics of eligible studies </p>

<p>A total of 136 relevant studies were reviewed based on our 
selection strategy. The stepwise selection process is shown 
in Figure 1. After sequential selection, a total of 12 articles 
with adequate information satisfied our inclusion criteria, 
among which were 12 studies, with 4,540 cases and 5,875 
controls, of the IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism 18,26-36 and 
seven studies, with 1,960 cases and 3,226 controls, of the 
IL-17F (7488T/C) polymorphism 18,29,31-34,36 All studies were 
case-control designs, with subjects of Asian ancestry. Out 
of the 12 applicable studies, eight were studies of gastric 
cancer, one was cervical cancer, one was breast cancer, one 
was ovarian cancer, and one was bladder cancer. Population-
based controls were used in seven studies, and hospital-based </p>

<p>controls were used in five studies. The detailed characteristics 
of the eligible studies are listed in Table 1. The genotype 
distribution of IL-17 polymorphisms in the controls was in 
compliance with Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium, except for 
two studies of IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism 18,34 and three 
studies of IL-17F (7488T/C) polymorphism. 30,32,33 </p>

<p>Quantitative data synthesis </p>

<p>IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism </p>

<p>The results of the meta-analysis are presented in detail in 
Table 2. For the IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism, 12 studies 
were combined. In the overall analysis, a significant associa-
tion between IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism and cancer 
risk was found under the allele model (OR =1.23, 95% 
CI =1.10-1.38, P,0.01), dominant model (OR =1.22, 
95% CI =1.08-1.37, P,0.01), recessive model (OR =1.50, 
95% CI =1.17-1.93, P,0.01), homozygous comparison 
(OR =1.62, 95% CI =1.27-2.06, P,0.01), and heterozygous 
comparison (OR =1.11, 95% CI =1.01-1.21, P=0.03). 
Subgroup analysis, stratified by cancer type, also 
suggested a signif icant association between IL-17A 
(-197G/A) polymorphism and cancer risk in the gastric 
cancer subgroup, under the allele model (OR =1.22, 95% 
CI =1.06-1.41, P,0.01), dominant model (OR =1.17, 
95% CI =1.02-1.33, P=0.03), recessive model (OR =1.58, 
95% CI =1.11-2.24, P,0.01), and homozygous compari-
son (OR =1.61, 95% CI =1.17-2.23, P,0.01). Moreover, 
a significant association was observed in the other cancer 
subgroups, under any of the genetic models (P,0.05) 
(Table 2 and Figure 2A). Therefore, no difference was 
observed between the cancer types. 
Stratified analyses by the source of control also sug-
gested that IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism increased 
the cancer risk in the population-based control subgroup, 
under all genetic models (allele model: OR =1.24, 95% 
CI =1.08-1.41, P,0.01; dominant model: OR =1.21, 
95% CI =1.09-1.33, P,0.01; recessive model: OR =1.41, 
95% CI =1.08-1.82, P=0.01; homozygous comparison: 
OR =1.53, 95% CI =1.17-2.01, P,0.01; and heterozygous 
model: OR =1.15, 95% CI =1.02-1.28, P=0.02). In contrast, 
a significant association was only found under homozygous 
comparison (OR =1.65, 95% CI =1.08-2.52, P=0.02) in the 
hospital-based control subgroup (Table 2 and Figure 2B). </p>

<p>IL-17F (7488T/C) polymorphism </p>

<p>For the IL-17F (7488T/C) polymorphism, seven studies 
were combined. When all seven studies were pooled into the 
meta-analysis, there was no significant association between </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2014:7 </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of studies included in the present meta-analysis </p>

<p>Studies 
Year Country Ethnicity Cancer 
type </p>

<p>Source of 
controls </p>

<p>Sample 
size </p>

<p>SNP studied 
Conclusion 
Genotyping 
method </p>

<p>HWE </p>

<p>Arisawa T 19 2012 Japan 
Asian 
Gastric HB 
337/587 
IL-17A (-197G/A) IL-17A (-197G/A) (+) PCR-SSCP 
0.080 
Quan Y 27 
2012 People's 
Republic 
of China </p>

<p>Asian 
Cervical PB 
311/463 
IL-17A (-197G/A) 
IL-17F (7488T/C) </p>

<p>IL-17A (-197G/A) (+) 
IL-17F (7488T/C) (-) </p>

<p>Taqman ® (Applied 
Biosystems, ABI, 
Foster City, CA, USA) </p>

<p>0.433; 
0.064 </p>

<p>Rafiei A 28 
2013 Iran 
Asian 
Gastric PB 
161/171 
IL-17A (-197G/A) IL-17A (-197G/A) (+) PCR-RFLP 
0.491 
Shibata T 18 2009 Japan 
Asian 
Gastric HB 
287/523 
IL-17A (-197G/A) 
IL-17F (7488T/C) </p>

<p>IL-17A (-197G/A) (+) 
IL-17F (7488T/C) (-) </p>

<p>PCR-SSCP 
,0.01; 
0.457 
Wang L 29 
2012 People's 
Republic 
of China </p>

<p>Asian 
Breast 
PB 
491/502 
IL-17A (-197G/A) 
IL-17F (7488T/C) </p>

<p>IL-17A (-197G/A) (-) 
IL-17F (7488T/C) (-) </p>

<p>SNaPshot ® 
SNP assay 
(Applied Biosystems) </p>

<p>0.173; 
0.775 </p>

<p>Wu X 30 
2010 People's 
Republic 
of China </p>

<p>Asian 
Gastric PB 
1,010/1,500 IL-17A (-197G/A) IL-17A (-197G/A) (-) PCR-RFLP 
0.351 </p>

<p>Yuan Y 34 
2012 People's 
Republic 
of China </p>

<p>Asian 
Ovarian HB 
92/38 
IL-17A (-197G/A) IL-17A (-197G/A) (-) PCR-RFLP 
0.028 </p>

<p>Zhou B 31 
2012 People's 
Republic 
of China </p>

<p>Asian 
Bladder HB 
301/446 
IL-17A (-197G/A) 
IL-17F (7488T/C) </p>

<p>IL-17A (-197G/A) (+) 
IL-17F (7488T/C) (-) </p>

<p>Taqman 
0.292; 
0.060 </p>

<p>Chen JJ 35 
2010 People's 
Republic 
of China </p>

<p>Asian 
Gastric PB 
1,042/1,090 IL-17A (-197G/A) IL-17A (-197G/A) (-) Taqman 
0.967 </p>

<p>Luo Y 36 
2010 People's 
Republic 
of China </p>

<p>Asian 
Gastric HB 
24/230 
IL-17A (-197G/A) 
IL-17F (7488T/C) </p>

<p>IL-17A (-197G/A) (+) 
IL-17F (7488T/C) (+) </p>

<p>PCR-RFLP 
0.135; 
0.747 </p>

<p>Zhang X 32 2013 People's 
Republic 
of China </p>

<p>Asian 
Gastric PB 
260/512 
IL-17A (-197G/A) 
IL-17F (7488T/C) </p>

<p>IL-17A (-197G/A) (+) 
IL-17F (7488T/C) (-) </p>

<p>MassARRAY ® 
(Sequenom ® , 
San Diego, CA, USA) </p>

<p>0.057; </p>

<p>,0.01 </p>

<p>Qinghai Z 33 2014 People's 
Republic 
of China </p>

<p>Asian 
Gastric HB 
311/611 
IL-17A (-197G/A) 
IL-17F (7488T/C) </p>

<p>IL-17A (-197G/A) (+) 
IL-17F (7488T/C) (-) </p>

<p>MassARRAY 
0.070; </p>

<p>,0.01 </p>

<p>Notes: (+) denotes there is significant association between IL-17A or IL-17F polymorphism and cancer risk. (-) denotes there is no significant association between IL-17A or 
IL-17F polymorphism and cancer risk. 
Abbreviations: HB, hospital-based controls; IL, interleukin; HWE, Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium; PB, population-based controls; PCR, polymerase chain reaction; 
RFLP, restriction fragment length polymorphism; SNP, single nucleotide polymorphism; SSCP, sequence-specific primers. </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>706 </p>

<p>Dai et al </p>

<p>the IL-17F (7488T/C) polymorphism and cancer suscepti-
bility, under all genetic models (allele model: OR =1.06, 
95% CI =0.89-1.26, P=0.54; dominant model: OR =1.05, 
95% CI =0.85-1.29, P=0.67; recessive model: OR =1.23, 
95% CI =0.87-1.75, P=0.24; homozygous comparison: 
OR =1.24, 95% CI =0.88-1.76, P=0.22; and heterozygous 
model: OR =1.03, 95% CI =0.82-1.29, P=0.82). 
In the stratified analysis by cancer type, only the allele 
model (OR =1.21, 95% CI =1.01-1.44, P=0.04) displayed 
a significant association between IL-17F (7488T/C) poly-
morphism and cancer risk, in the gastric cancer subgroup. 
No significant association was found, under any genetic 
models, in the other cancer subgroup (all P.0.05) (Table 2 
and Figure 3A). 
Next, we performed a subgroup analysis according to the 
source of controls. The results showed that IL-17F (7488T/C) 
polymorphism was not associated with cancer risk, in either the </p>

<p>population-base control subgroup or the hospital-based control 
subgroup (all P.0.05) (Table 2 and Figure 3B). Therefore, dif-
ferences in the controls did not affect the association between 
IL-17F (7488T/C) polymorphism and cancer risk. </p>

<p>Sensitivity analysis </p>

<p>The sensitivity analysis indicated that no single study influenced 
the pooled OR value, either for IL-17A (-197G/A) polymor-
phism or for IL-17F (7488T/C) polymorphism, suggesting that 
the results of this meta-analysis are stable (data not shown). </p>

<p>Publication bias </p>

<p>Publication bias of the selected articles was assessed 
using Begg's funnel plot and Egger's test. The shape of the 
funnel plot did not show an obvious publication bias for 
IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism or IL-17F (7488T/C) 
polymorphism (Figure 4A and B). Similarly, no evidence </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2014:7 </p>

<p>Table 2 Meta-analysis of the IL-17A </p>

<p>(-197G/A) polymorphism and IL-17F 
(7488T/C) polymorphism with risk of cancer </p>

<p>Allele model </p>

<p>Dominant model </p>

<p>Recessive model </p>

<p>Homozygous comparison </p>

<p>Heterozygous comparison </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value 
OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value 
OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value 
OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value 
OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>IL-17A 
(-197G/A) 
A allele vs G allele </p>

<p>AA + 
AG vs GG </p>

<p>AA vs GG + </p>

<p>AG </p>

<p>AA vs GG </p>

<p>AG vs GG </p>

<p>Overall </p>

<p>1.23 (1.10-1.38) </p>

<p>,0.01 
1.22 (1.08-1.37) </p>

<p>,0.01 
1.50 (1.17-1.93) </p>

<p>,0.01 
1.62 (1.27-2.06) </p>

<p>,0.01 
1.11 (1.01-1.21) </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>Gastric cancer </p>

<p>1.22 (1.06-1.41) </p>

<p>,0.01 
1.17 (1.02-1.33) </p>

<p>0.03 
1.58 (1.11-2.24) </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>1.61 (1.17-2.23) </p>

<p>,0.01 
1.06 (0.95-1.18) </p>

<p>0.28 </p>

<p>Other cancers </p>

<p>1.27 (1.09-1.49) </p>

<p>,0.01 
1.37 (1.11-1.69) </p>

<p>,0.01 
1.42 (1.07-1.89) </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>1.69 (1.23-2.33) </p>

<p>,0.01 
1.24 (1.04-1.48) </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>PB subgroup </p>

<p>1.24 (1.08-1.41) </p>

<p>,0.01 
1.21 (1.09-1.33) </p>

<p>,0.01 
1.41 (1.08-1.82) </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>1.53 (1.17-2.01) </p>

<p>,0.01 
1.15 (1.02-1.28) </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>HB subgroup </p>

<p>1.19 (0.97-1.45) </p>

<p>0.09 
1.12 (0.86-1.47) </p>

<p>0.40 
1.52 (0.97-2.38) </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>1.65 (1.08-2.52) </p>

<p>0.02 
1.03 (0.89-1.21) </p>

<p>0.68 </p>

<p>IL-17F 
(7488T/C) 
C allele vs T allele </p>

<p>CC + 
CT vs TT </p>

<p>CC vs CT + </p>

<p>TT </p>

<p>CC vs TT </p>

<p>CT vs TT </p>

<p>Overall </p>

<p>1.06 (0.89-1.26) </p>

<p>0.54 
1.05 (0.85-1.29) </p>

<p>0.67 
1.23 (0.87-1.75) </p>

<p>0.24 </p>

<p>1.24 (0.88-1.76) </p>

<p>0.22 
1.03 (0.82-1.29) </p>

<p>0.82 </p>

<p>Gastric cancer </p>

<p>1.21 (1.01-1.44) </p>

<p>0.04 
1.20 (0.98-1.48) </p>

<p>0.08 
1.30 (0.87-1.94) </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>1.33 (0.89-1.98) </p>

<p>0.17 
1.18 (0.92-1.51) </p>

<p>0.19 </p>

<p>Other cancers </p>

<p>0.91 (0.70-1.18) </p>

<p>0.47 
0.89 (0.64-1.22) </p>

<p>0.46 
1.04 (0.51-2.13) </p>

<p>0.90 </p>

<p>1.02 (0.50-2.08) </p>

<p>0.96 
0.88 (0.62-1.24) </p>

<p>0.46 </p>

<p>PB subgroup </p>

<p>1.10 (0.93-1.30) </p>

<p>0.26 
1.09 (0.90-1.32) </p>

<p>0.37 
1.26 (0.78-2.03) </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>1.28 (0.79-2.06) </p>

<p>0.32 
1.06 (0.87-1.30) </p>

<p>0.54 </p>

<p>HB subgroup </p>

<p>1.04 (0.74-1.44) </p>

<p>0.84 
1.04 (0.69-1.58) </p>

<p>0.84 
1.21 (0.72-2.01) </p>

<p>0.47 </p>

<p>1.21 (0.72-2.01) </p>

<p>0.47 
1.05 (0.66-1.65) </p>

<p>0.85 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; HB, hospital-based controls; IL, interleukin; OR, odds ratio; PB, population-based controls; vs, versus. </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>707 </p>

<p>IL-17A and IL-17F gene polymorphisms and cancer risk </p>

<p>of publication bias was observed by Egger's test, for the 
IL-17A (-197G/A) dominant model (P=0.270) or the IL-17F 
(7488T/C) dominant model (P=0.250). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Large-sample and unbiased, epidemiological studies of 
predisposition genes polymorphisms could provide insight 
to etiology of diseases. However, the findings are gener-
ally inconsistent, probably due to some limitation in these </p>

<p>Figure 2 Meta-analysis to evaluate the association between the IL-17A (-197G/A) 
polymorphism and cancer risk (dominant model: AA + AG vs GG). (A) subgroup 
analysis by cancer type; (B) subgroup analysis by source of control. 
Abbreviations: IL, interleukin ; M-H, Mantel-Hanszel; vs, versus. </p>

<p>Odds ratio 
M-H random, 95% Vl </p>

<p>Odds ratio 
M-H random, 95% Cl 
Weight </p>

<p>1.2.1 Gastric cancer </p>

<p>Chen JJ 2010 35 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: τ 2 =0.01; χ 2 =11.46, df=7 (P=0.12); l 2 =39% </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=3.31 (P= 0.0009) </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=3.59 (P=0.0003) </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: τ 2 =0.02; χ 2 =18.44, df=11 (P=0.07); l 2 =40% </p>

<p>2.2.2. Hospital-based group </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: τ 2 = 0.00; χ 2 =5.02, df=5 (P=0.41); l 2 =0% </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=0.84 (P=0.40) </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=3.31 (P=0.0009) </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: τ 2 =0.06; χ 2 =13.42, df=5 (P=0.02); l 2 =63% </p>

<p>Total events </p>

<p>100% 
1.22 (1.08, 1.37) </p>

<p>Decreased model </p>

<p>0.1 0.2 </p>

<p>Increased model </p>

<p>Decreased risk Increased risk </p>

<p>Total (95% Cl) </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: τ 2 =0.02; χ 2 =18.44, df=11 (P=0.60); l 2 =0% </p>

<p>1.21 (1.09, 1.35) </p>

<p>1.39 (1.03, 1.87) </p>

<p>1.17 (0.94, 1.47) </p>

<p>1.29 (1.00, 1.67) </p>

<p>1.57 (1.01, 2.45) </p>

<p>1.33 (0.98, 1.82) </p>

<p>1.05 (0.87, 1.27) </p>

<p>60.9% </p>

<p>9.1% </p>

<p>12.4% </p>

<p>10.8% </p>

<p>5.4% </p>

<p>8.9% </p>

<p>14.4% </p>

<p>Total events </p>

<p>Subtotal (95% Cl) </p>

<p>Zhang X 2013 32 </p>

<p>Wu X 2010 30 </p>

<p>Total events </p>

<p>Subtotal (95% Cl) </p>

<p>Qinghai Z 2014 33 </p>

<p>Zhou B 2012 31 </p>

<p>Yuan Y 2012 34 </p>

<p>Shibata T 2009 18 </p>

<p>Luo Y 2010 36 </p>

<p>Arisawa T 2012 19 </p>

<p>Wang L 2012 29 </p>

<p>Rafiei A 2013 28 </p>

<p>Quan Y 2012 27 </p>

<p>Chen JJ 2010 35 </p>

<p>2.2.1 Population-based group </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=2.91 (P=0.004) </p>

<p>Test for subgroup differences: χ 2 =1.54, df=1 (P=0.21); l 2 =35.1% </p>

<p>Test for subgroup differences: χ 2 =0.27, df=1 (P=0.60); l 2 =0% </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: τ 2 =0.01; χ 2 =4.14, df=3 (P=0.25); l 2 =27% </p>

<p>Total events </p>

<p>1.37 (1.11, 1.69) </p>

<p>1.63 (1.11, 2.25) </p>

<p>0.37 (0.08, 1.74) </p>

<p>1.29 (1.00, 1.67) </p>

<p>1.33 (0.98, 1.82) </p>

<p>28.6% </p>

<p>8.4% </p>

<p>0.6% </p>

<p>10.8% </p>

<p>8.9% </p>

<p>Subtotal (95% Cl) </p>

<p>Total events </p>

<p>1.22 (1.08, 1.37) 
100.0% 
Total (95% Cl) </p>

<p>Zhou B 2012 31 </p>

<p>Yuan Y 2012 34 </p>

<p>Wang L 2012 29 </p>

<p>Quan Y 2012 27 </p>

<p>1.2.2 Other cancers </p>

<p>1.17 (1.02, 1.33) </p>

<p>1.31 (0.98, 1.74) </p>

<p>1.39 (1.03, 1.87) </p>

<p>1.17 (0.94, 1.47) </p>

<p>1.03 (0.76, 1.40) </p>

<p>1.57 (1.01, 2.45) </p>

<p>0.40 (0.17, 0.94) </p>

<p>1.05 (0.87, 1.27) </p>

<p>1.18 (0.89, 1.56) </p>

<p>71.4% </p>

<p>9.7% </p>

<p>9.1% </p>

<p>12.4% </p>

<p>8.9% </p>

<p>5.4% </p>

<p>1.7% </p>

<p>14.4% </p>

<p>9.8% </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=2.24 (P=0.03) </p>

<p>Qinghai Z 2014 33 </p>

<p>Subtotal (95% Cl) </p>

<p>Zhang X 2013 32 </p>

<p>Wu X 2010 30 </p>

<p>Shibata T 2009 18 </p>

<p>Rafiei A 2013 28 </p>

<p>Luo Y 2010 36 </p>

<p>Arisawa T 2012 19 </p>

<p>Study or subgroup </p>

<p>Odds ratio 
M-H random, 95% Cl </p>

<p>Odds ratio 
M-H random, 95% Cl 
Weight 
Study or subgroup </p>

<p>0.5 
1 
2 
5 10 </p>

<p>0.1 0.2 
0.5 1 
2 
5 10 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>39.1% </p>

<p>9.7% </p>

<p>8.4% </p>

<p>0.6% </p>

<p>8.9% </p>

<p>1.7% </p>

<p>9.8% 
1.18 (0.89, 1.56) 
0.40 (0.17, 0.94) </p>

<p>1.03 (0.76, 1.40) </p>

<p>0.37 (0.08, 1.74) </p>

<p>1.63 (1.19, 2.25) </p>

<p>1.31 (0.98, 1.74) </p>

<p>1.12 (0.86, 1.47) </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2014:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>708 </p>

<p>Dai et al </p>

<p>Study or subgroup </p>

<p>4.2.1 Gastric cancer </p>

<p>4.2.2 Other cancers </p>

<p>Luo Y 2010 36 
4.9% 
2.33 (0.98, 5.54) 
1.08 (0.75, 1.54) </p>

<p>1.26 (0.86, 1.86) </p>

<p>1.15 (0.79, 1.67) </p>

<p>1.20 (0.98, 1.48) </p>

<p>15.4% </p>

<p>14.4% </p>

<p>14.7% </p>

<p>49.4% </p>

<p>17.0% 
Quan Y 2012 27 
Wang L 2012 29 </p>

<p>Zhou B 2012 31 </p>

<p>Subtotal (95% CI) </p>

<p>Total events </p>

<p>Total (95% CI) </p>

<p>Total events </p>

<p>100.0% 
1.05 (0.85, 1.29) </p>

<p>0.89 (0.64, 1.22) </p>

<p>0.1 0.2 
0.5 
2 
5 10 
1 </p>

<p>0.62 (0.44, 0.88) </p>

<p>1.02 (0.74, 1.40) </p>

<p>1.07 (0.79, 1.44) 
17.7% </p>

<p>15.8% </p>

<p>50.6% </p>

<p>Shibata T 2009 18 </p>

<p>Zhang X 2013 32 </p>

<p>Qinghai Z 2014 33 </p>

<p>Subtotal (95% CI) </p>

<p>Total events 
Heterogeneity: τ 2 =0.00; χ 2 =2.72, df=3 (P=0.44); I 2 =0% </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: τ 2 =0.05; χ 2 =6.01, df=2 (P=0.05); I 2 =67% </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: τ 2 =0.04; χ 2 =12.84, df=6 (P=0.05): I 2 =53% </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=1.73 (P=0.08) </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=0.74 (P=0.46) </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=0.42 (P=0.67) </p>

<p>Test for subgroup differences: Chi 2 =2.44 df=1 (P=0.12). I 2 =58.9% 
Decreased risk Increased risk </p>

<p>Weight </p>

<p>Odds ratio 
M-H, random, 95% CI </p>

<p>Odds ratio 
M-H, random, 95% CI </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Study or subgroup </p>

<p>5.2.1. Population-based group </p>

<p>5.2.2 Hospital-based group </p>

<p>17.0% 
1.02 (0.74, 1.40) </p>

<p>1.07 (0.79, 1.44) </p>

<p>1.26 (0.86, 1.86) </p>

<p>1.09 (0.90, 1.32) </p>

<p>17.7% </p>

<p>14.4% </p>

<p>49.2% </p>

<p>15.4% </p>

<p>Wang L 2012 29 </p>

<p>Zhou B 2012 31 </p>

<p>Subtotal (95% CI) </p>

<p>Total events </p>

<p>Total (95% CI) </p>

<p>Total events </p>

<p>100.0% 
1.05 (0.85, 1.29) </p>

<p>0.62 (0.44, 0.88) </p>

<p>1.15, (0.79, 1.67) </p>

<p>2.33 (0.98, 5.54) </p>

<p>1.08 (0.75, 1.54) </p>

<p>1.04 (0.69, 1.58) </p>

<p>15.8% </p>

<p>4.9% </p>

<p>14.7% </p>

<p>50.8% </p>

<p>Quan Y 2012 27 </p>

<p>Luo Y 2010 36 </p>

<p>Shibata T 2009 18 </p>

<p>Zhang X 2013 32 </p>

<p>Qinghai Z 2014 33 </p>

<p>Subtotal (95% CI) </p>

<p>Total events </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: τ 2 =0.00; χ 2 =0.76, df=2 (P=0.68); I 2 =0% </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: τ 2 =0.12; χ 2 =11.14, df=3 (P=0.01); I 2 =73% </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: τ 2 =0.04; χ 2 =12.84, df=6 (P=0.05); I 2 =53% </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=0.90 (P=0.37) </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=0.20 (P=0.84) </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z=0.42 (P=0.67) 
Test for subgroup differences: χ 2 =0.04, df=1 (P=0.85); I 2 =0% </p>

<p>Weight </p>

<p>Odds ratio 
M-H, random, 95% CI </p>

<p>Odds ratio 
M-H, random, 95% CI </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0.1 0.2 
0.5 
2 
5 1 0 
1 </p>

<p>Decreased model Increased model </p>

<p>Figure 3 Meta-analysis to evaluate the association between the IL-17F (7488T/C) 
polymorphism and cancer risk (dominant model: CC + CT vs TT). (A) subgroup 
analysis by cancer type; (B) subgroup analysis by source of control. 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; IL, interleukin; vs, versus. </p>

<p>studies, such as small sample size, and mix of ethnicities 
and cancer types. Meta-analysis is considered a powerful 
tool for combining the contradicting results from different 
studies to achieve greater statistical power and obtain more 
reliable results than with a single study. 37 In this meta-
analysis, we investigated the association between IL-17A 
(-197G/A) (rs2275913) and IL-17F (7488T/C) (rs763780) 
and cancer risk. Overall, our study provided evidence that 
IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism was associated with cancer 
susceptibility. However, no association was detected between 
IL-17F (7488T/C) polymorphism and cancer susceptibility. 
Sensitivity analysis and publication bias further strengthened 
the validity of these results. 
IL-17 family members belong to a distinct category 
of cytokine and are involved in coordinating local tissue </p>

<p>inflammation, through release of proinflammatory and 
neutrophil-mobilizing cytokines. 20 To date, investigation into 
the function of the IL-17 cytokine family has been extensive, 
but the majority of the effort has focused on the role of two 
members, IL-17A and IL-17F. The IL-17A and IL-17F genes 
are both located at 6p12. In addition, among the IL-17 fam-
ily, from the alignment of the amino acid sequences, IL-17A 
and IL-17F have the highest overall amino acid sequence 
identity and share similar functions in terms of their ability 
to induce chemokines, which are important in neutrophil 
recruitment and activation. 31 IL-17A and IL-17F cytokines 
are both expressed by Th17 cells, which mediate chronic 
inflammation and cancer. 9 Although the significance of 
IL-17A and -17F in the pathogenesis of the cancer has still 
remained unclear, we hypothesized that both the cytokines 
may affect the development of chronic inflammation fol-
lowed by malignancy, coordinately or independently. Over 
the last several years, many studies have identified a variety 
of environmental, host immune status, and host genetic fac-
tors that play important roles in carcinogenesis. Moreover, 
Espinoza et al reported that IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism 
influences the response of the IL-17 gene promoter to factors 
released in response to T cell activation, thus leading to a 
differential IL-17 production. 38 Kawaguchi et al revealed that 
IL-17F (7488T/C), which causes a His-to-Arg substitution 
at amino acid 161 (H161R) of IL-17F, lacked the ability 
to activate the mitogen-activated protein kinase pathway, 
cytokine production, and chemokine production, and blocked 
induction of IL-8 expression by wild type IL-17F in in vitro 
functional experiments. 39 Therefore, we evaluated the effect 
of the polymorphisms of two cytokines on cancer risk. Our 
investigation suggests that IL-17A (-197G/A), but not IL-17F 
(7488T/C), contributes to cancer susceptibility. 
Subgroup analyses stratified by source of controls and 
cancer types were also performed. For IL-17A (-197G/A) 
polymorphism, a significant increased cancer risk was 
observed in gastric cancer and other cancers, suggesting that 
cancer type may not affect cancer susceptibility. Moreover, 
stratified analysis by source of controls suggested that IL-17A 
(-197G/A) polymorphism was associated with increased risk 
of cancer in the population-based control subgroup, but not in 
the hospital-based control subgroup. This may have been due 
to some selection biases existing in the hospital-based studies 
because such controls may have come from a population with 
a related disease and may not have been representative of the 
general population. For IL-17F (7488T/C) polymorphism, 
we found little association between IL-17F (7488T/C) poly-
morphism and cancer risk in subgroups analysis. This result </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2014:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>709 </p>

<p>IL-17A and IL-17F gene polymorphisms and cancer risk </p>

<p>indicates that the differences in cancer types and sources of 
controls do not affect cancer susceptibility. 
Several potential limitations of the present meta-analysis 
should be acknowledged. First, significant heterogeneity was 
observed in the overall and subgroup analyses. Although 
two potential sources of the heterogeneity were investi-
gated, including the source of controls and cancer types, 
neither of them sufficiently explained the between-study </p>

<p>heterogeneity. Second, the sample size is not large enough, 
especially for subgroup analysis. Thus, we do not have 
adequate power to evaluate the possible association for 
both polymorphisms, and the observed significant asso-
ciations in some subgroup analysis may be not accurate. 
Third, the lack of observations concerning gene-gene and 
gene-environment interactions could have influenced our 
results. Fourth, only published studies were included in the </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
0.1 
0.2 
0.3 
0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>SE of: logor </p>

<p>SE of: logor </p>

<p>Logor </p>

<p>Logor </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>−0.5 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>−0.5 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>A 
Begg's funnel plot with pseudo 95% confidence limits </p>

<p>Begg's funnel plot with pseudo 95% confidence limits 
B </p>

<p>Figure 4 Funnel plots of IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism and IL-17F (7488T/C) polymorphism in the dominant model. (A) IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism; (B) IL-17F 
(7488T/C) polymorphism. 
Abbreviations: IL, interleukin; SE, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2014:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>710 </p>

<p>Dai et al </p>

<p>meta-analysis, and nonsignificant or negative findings may 
be unpublished. Hence, some inevitable publication biases 
might exist in the results. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In conclusion, our meta-analysis provides evidences that the 
IL-17A (-197G/A) polymorphism might be associated with 
cancer risk in the Asian populations, while no evidence sug-
gested a significant association between the IL-17F (7488T/C) 
polymorphism and cancer risk. However, large-sample studies 
are warranted to validate our findings, especially in some types 
of cancer. More studies on gene-gene and gene-environment 
interactions should also be considered in the future, to obtain 
a more comprehensive understanding of the association 
between IL-17 polymorphisms and cancer risk. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work has been supported by Grants from the National 
Natural Science Foundation of China (No 81301835). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>

<p>References </p>



<p>OncoTargets and Therapy </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open access 
journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2014:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>711 </p>



</text></tei>