<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4801097" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">


<p>AIM </p>

<p>Despite extensive research into keloid scarring 
etiopathogenesis, no biomarker has led to an effec-
tive therapy. Retinoic acid (RA) has been implicat-
ed in key functions including cell cycle regulation, 
apoptosis, and cell differentiation and shown to 
affect profibrotic factors, including Transform-
ing growth factor β. However, confirmation of 
the genetic expression and manipulation of this 
molecular target have not yet been explored in 
keloids. The aim, here, was to develop and test 
new hypotheses underlying keloids by taking the 
novel approach of examining this entity from both 
site-specific and dermoepidermal perspectives, 
leading to targeted potential therapies. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Normal skin and keloid biopsies, harvested from 
the centre and margin of the lesion, were cryosec-
tioned and laser capture microdissected, where the 
epidermis and dermis were separately collected and </p>

<p>microarrayed (whole genome array). Data were ana-
lyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Array Studio</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v7.2</rs> and filtered (criteria: 
p value &lt; 0.05, q value &lt; 0.05, and fold change ≥2). 
The resultant list of genes was enriched using ingenu-
ity pathway analysis and key pathways identified then 
validated with qPCR and protein studies (western blot 
and immunohistochemistry/immunocytochemistry). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The keloid epidermis revealed the reductase 
enzyme AKR1B10 to be significantly upregulated 
(p value, 1.19E − 06; fold change, 75). Quanti-
tative real-time polymerase chain reaction con-
firmed this and dysregulation of other members 
of the RA pathway. Aldo-keto reductase family 1, 
member B10 overexpression through transfec-
tion of normal keratinocytes changes RA recep-
tor activity and fibrotic gene expression. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>The manipulation of AKR1B10 to ascertain its 
effect on RA activity and the consequent down-
stream events in keloid with regard to regulation 
of fibrosis represents compelling therapeutic 
potential. </p>

</text></tei>