<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4025442" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>medical advances of the 20th century. 
1 For 
some cancers, cytotoxic chemotherapy is 
curative, even in the setting of metastatic 
disease, and the promise of long-term sur-
vival makes the risk of adverse events and 
financial costs worthwhile. 
2 Adjuvant chemo-
therapy for breast, colorectal or lung cancer 
offers significant survival gains beyond 
surgery alone. For patients with incurable 
disease, chemotherapy can also lengthen sur-
vival. The prospects for patients with cancer 
have improved further by the recent develop-
ment of molecular profiling of tumour cells. 
This technology has facilitated the identifica-
tion of 'novel, druggable targets' that can be 
modulated to control or cure cancer. </p>

<p>3   Moreover, 'personalised medicine' has the 
potential to optimise treatment efficacy and 
minimise the toxicity of therapeutic agents. </p>

<p>3   Drug regulatory bodies and funding agen-
cies play an important role in translating 
current evidence into policy and clinical prac-
tice. Data generated in clinical trials form the 
basis for regulatory approval because licensing 
organisations such as the US Food and 
Drug Administration (FDA) and Australia's 
Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA) 
request that manufacturers demonstrate new 
medicines are safe and efficacious before 
approval for marketing. After market approval, 
governments and other third party payers have 
developed subsidy systems to achieve greater 
access to pharmaceuticals. These systems 
involve a delicate balance between providing 
access to effective treatments while ensuring 
long-term fiscal sustainability. 
4 Worldwide, 
many third party payers now require that 
healthcare technology manufacturers provide 
evidence of a product's cost-effectiveness, 
based mostly on clinical trial evidence, to 
support subsidy applications. 
However, regulatory approval and subsidy 
decisions are based on the assumption that </p>

<p>Pearson S-A, Schaffer A. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004099. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004099 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Protocol </p>

<p>clinical trial outcomes can be extrapolated to the 
general population. While clinical trials are the indisput-
able gold standard for demonstrating drug safety and 
efficacy, they have significant limitations as an evidence 
base for regulatory and subsidy decisions. 
5 6 Some of 
these drawbacks include: small sample size, short dur-
ation, use of surrogate endpoints, early stopping rules 
that permit cross-over to experimental therapy, lack of 
measurement of real clinical effects, bias towards 
younger patients and under-representation of patients 
with complex health problems. </p>

<p>7   To add to these well-established limitations, the uncer-
tainties for decision-makers have increased due to stake-
holder demand for faster access to potentially life-saving 
medicines. While fast-track initiatives show commend-
able responsiveness to stakeholder concerns, the end 
result is that the premarket approval evidence base is 
becoming increasingly limited and medicines are reach-
ing the marketplace earlier than ever before. Clearly, no 
clinical trial could ever be large enough or long enough 
to quantify all clinical outcomes, risks or otherwise; 
however, the current situation has created an urgent 
need to better understand how cancer medicines are 
prescribed in routine clinical care. 
Australians receive subsidised access to a broad range of 
cancer therapies, including conventional cytotoxics as well 
as the newer biological agents. Australia is unusual among 
developed countries as it operates under a National 
Medicines Policy and a Quality Use of Medicines (QUM) 
framework. 
8 We have comprehensive policies guiding the 
production, licensing, subsidy and use of medicines. A sig-
nificant feature of our QUM framework is the internation-
ally recognised cost-effectiveness analysis model, employed 
by the Pharmaceutical Benefits Advisory Committee 
(PBAC) and the Repatriation Pharmaceutical Reference 
Committee to make recommendations for medicines 
subsidy on the Pharmaceutical Benefits and Repatriation 
Pharmaceutical Benefits Schemes (PBS and RPBS), 
respectively. 
After medicines have been subsidised for use in 
Australia we know little about the way in which they are 
used in clinical practice, their impact on resource utilisa-
tion and whether the people who will derive the most 
benefit from their use are gaining access to them. This 
situation persists despite the existence of good quality, 
routinely collected administrative health data. Australia 
is in a unique position to undertake population-based 
pharmacoepidemiological research due to its universal 
healthcare arrangement and drug coverage for all 
Australians. 
However, health data linkage initiatives have been 
impeded by privacy concerns and legislation. Moreover, 
there have been a range of cross-jurisdictional barriers 
to linking dispensing data (under the custodianship of 
the Commonwealth) and outcomes data such as hospita-
lisations (under the custodianship of individual states 
and territories). Some of the major barriers include the 
variation in privacy legislation across jurisdictions, lack </p>

<p>of transparency and variability about the requirements 
of jurisdictional ethics committees and the different 
data release policies of data custodians. 
To demonstrate the consequences of this situation we 
have been undertaking a comprehensive review of all 
peer-reviewed literature of pharmacoepidemiological 
research undertaken in Australia using PBS or RPBS dis-
pensing data over a 25-year period (1987-2012). We 
identified 196 studies, 110 of which were published 
between 2007 and 2012. Approximately one-third of all 
published studies (n=70) were based on aggregated 
claims level data reporting the volume of medicines dis-
pensed over designated time periods. These studies 
provide little evidence on the way in which medicines 
are prescribed and used in the Australian population. 
Another third of all studies (n=91) examined clinician 
or patient behaviour around a particular medication 
(coprescribing, potential drug interactions, switching 
behaviours or patient adherence to therapy). Only 13% 
of studies linked individual-level medicines use to a 
health outcome. Moreover, there have only been six 
studies with a cancer medicines focus. 
9-14 As such, phar-
macoepidemiological research has no systematic frame-
work for undertaking timely studies of medicines use 
and health outcomes in real-world settings. In direct 
contrast, the Nordic countries have had long-standing 
and robust approaches to accessing routinely collected 
data for pharmacoepidemiological research. In a recent 
publication, they showcased their pharmacoepidemiolo-
gical research with an output of 515 research papers in 
a period of only 6 years (2005-2010). </p>

<p>15   There has been a notable exception in terms of advan-
cing pharmacoepidemiological research in Australia. 
The Australian Government Department of Veterans' 
Affairs (DVA) subsidises healthcare and pharmaceuticals 
for eligible veterans and their dependants, with the col-
lected health claims data available for use in pharmacoe-
pidemiological research. </p>

<p>16-27   Since the DVA are 
responsible for all aspects of hospital and community 
care for their clients they have both exposure and out-
comes data under their custodianship. More than 
one-third of all studies included in our review above 
used RPBS data. Moreover, more than two-thirds of all 
studies examining individual level medicines use in our 
review used RPBS data. To date, the vast majority of the 
DVA's pharmacoepidemiological research has been con-
ducted under the auspices of the Veterans' Medicines 
Advice and Therapeutics Education Services (Veterans' 
MATES) program. 
28 However, cancer pharmacoepide-
miology has not been a focus of the Veterans' MATES 
program. 
The programme of work outlined in this protocol 
brings together cross-jurisdictional data collections to 
link medicines exposure to real-world outcomes for a 
subset of elderly Australians residing in New South 
Wales (NSW), Australia's most populous state. The 
overall objective of the research programme is to evalu-
ate the use and impact of cancer medicines in the real-</p>



<p>Pearson S-A, Schaffer A. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004099. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004099 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>world clinical setting. Specifically, we will investigate the 
trends in utilisation of chemotherapeutic and biological 
agents by cancer type, patterns of care following cancer 
diagnoses and outcomes associated with cancer medi-
cines use. </p>

<p>METHODS AND ANALYSIS 
Setting 
Australia has a publicly funded universal healthcare 
system entitling all Australian citizens and permanent 
residents to a range of subsidised health services. This 
includes free treatment in public hospitals (funded 
jointly by the Commonwealth and State/Territory gov-
ernments) and subsidised treatment in private hospitals 
(funded jointly by the Commonwealth and private 
health insurance). It also includes a range of subsidised 
outpatient services including consultations with clini-
cians (funded by the Commonwealth's Medicare 
Benefits Scheme, MBS) and medicines prescribed in 
hospitals and in the community (funded by the 
Commonwealth's PBS; medicines prescribed to public 
hospital inpatients are covered primarily by the hospital 
budget). 
The DVA funds the healthcare of eligible veterans, war 
widows, war widowers and their dependants. 
29 In add-
ition to the coverage received by the general population 
via the MBS and PBS, Repatriation Gold Card holders 
(ex-prisoners of war, World War I and II veterans and 
mariners, and their war widows/widowers) are also 
entitled to additional DVA-approved services and 
pharmaceutical items not available to the general popu-
lation. White Card holders (other veterans or mariners 
who do not qualify for a Gold Card) are entitled to treat-
ment for specific conditions approved by the DVA 
including a war-related or service-related injury, any 
malignant cancer and/or tuberculosis. All other condi-
tions are treated and subsidised based on the same </p>

<p>entitlements as the Australian general population. The 
Orange Card provides eligible veterans and mariners of 
British Commonwealth and allied countries who are 
70 years of age or older and Australian residents subsi-
dised access to approved pharmaceuticals according to 
clinical need. 
30 Clients can hold both White and 
Orange cards simultaneously. 
DVA clients are a major subgroup of the Australian 
population. In December 2010, they constituted approxi-
mately 6% of Australians aged 65 years and older and 
27% of Australians aged at least 85 years. 
31 Our research 
programme is limited to all DVA clients residing in the 
largest Australian state (NSW). DVA clients residing in 
NSW account for approximately one-third of the 
Australian DVA population and have a similar and 
gender profile to clients residing in other Australian 
states. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>Study design 
This ongoing research programme comprises a series of 
retrospective cohort studies of DVA clients diagnosed 
with specific cancers. It involves the linkage of eight 
health administrative databases under the custodianship 
of the DVA and the NSW Ministry of Health (table 1). 
Data linkages of this kind have not occurred routinely in 
other research programmes using DVA claims data. </p>

<p>Data sources 
The linked databases are described below and in table 1. </p>

<p>DVA client database 
The DVA provide data on clients' sex, dates of birth and 
death, level of healthcare entitlement history (Gold, 
White, Orange) and postcode of residence history 
mapped to statistical local areas (SLAs) and local govern-
ment areas (LGAs). 
32 The SLAs and LGAs form part of 
the Australian Standard Geographical Classification, </p>

<p>33   Table 1 Description of linked data sets </p>

<p>Data set 
Description </p>

<p>Dates available for 
current data holdings </p>

<p>Department of Veterans' Affairs (DVA) data collections 
Client file 
Demographics and level of benefits for all DVA clients 
2004-2012 
Repatriation Pharmaceutical 
Benefits Scheme </p>

<p>Pharmaceutical items paid for by the DVA dispensed anywhere 
in Australia </p>

<p>2004-2012 </p>

<p>DVA health services 
All medical and allied health services in the Australian Medicare 
Benefits Schedule and extra items paid for by the DVA </p>

<p>2004-2012 </p>

<p>Hospital episodes 
All hospital episodes in public and private hospitals in Australia 
2005-2012 
New South Wales (NSW) data collections 
Central Cancer Registry 
All notifications of cancers diagnosed in NSW 
1994-2009 
Register of Births, Deaths 
and Marriages </p>

<p>All deaths that occurred in NSW 
1994-2012 </p>

<p>Admitted Patients Data 
Collection </p>

<p>All inpatient separations from public and private hospitals in 
NSW </p>

<p>2000-2012 </p>

<p>Emergency Department 
Data Collection </p>

<p>All emergency department visits to a subset of public hospitals 
in NSW </p>

<p>2005-2012 </p>

<p>Pearson S-A, Schaffer A. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004099. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004099 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>established to enable the development of geography-
specific statistics and classification of areas according to 
socioeconomic profile and remoteness. We did not 
obtain individual-level data on the service history of the 
clients in our cohort; however, almost all male DVA 
clients are veterans of the Australian forces and almost 
all female clients are war widows. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>PBS and RPBS 
The PBS is a national programme subsidising prescrip-
tion medicines for all Australians, while the RPBS subsi-
dises additional items for DVA clients. It contains data 
on all dispensed pharmaceutical items (item name and 
strength, date of supply, quantity supplied and number 
of repeats) that were subsidised in whole or in part by 
the DVA and dispensed in the community or in a private 
hospital anywhere in Australia. </p>

<p>DVA hospital episodes 
The DVA collects information on all hospitalisations to 
public and private hospitals across Australia where the 
hospital stay was subsidised by the DVA, including dates 
of stay, primary diagnosis and primary procedure. 
Claims from public and private hospitals are processed 
differently and there is a significant lag in the capture of 
public hospital claims (up to 1 year from the date of 
service in some instances). </p>

<p>DVA health services 
These data contain all billed medical and allied health 
services performed anywhere in Australia both 
in-hospital and out-of-hospital that are covered under 
Australia's national MBS, as well as additional items 
covered by the DVA. MBS items include physician visits, 
diagnostic and therapeutic procedures and pathology 
tests and additional DVA items including services pro-
vided by dentists, podiatrists, chiropractors and 
dieticians. </p>

<p>NSW Central Cancer Registry 
The Central Cancer Registry (CCR) records all cancer 
cases diagnosed in NSW residents. The registry is run 
according to the International Association of Cancer 
Registries' rules </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>and records the cancer type 
(ICD-O-3), date of diagnosis, degree of spread at the 
time of first diagnosis for solid tumours and the date 
and cause of death (cancer or non-cancer). </p>

<p>35   NSW Admitted Patients Data Collection 
The Admitted Patients Data Collection (APDC) is a 
census of all inpatient separations (ie, discharges, trans-
fers, deaths) from all public, private and repatriation 
hospitals, private day procedures centres and public 
nursing homes in NSW and collects data on the dates of 
admission and separation, and up to 50 diagnoses and 
procedures. </p>

<p>Emergency Department Data Collection 
The Emergency Department Data Collection (EDDC) 
records the date, the reason for the visit and the visit 
outcome (eg, admission to hospital, death or discharge) 
for all ED visits to 90 public EDs across NSW. There are 
150 EDs in NSW, two of which are located in private hos-
pitals. All of the larger EDs contribute data to the EDDC 
so the data set includes the majority of ED atten-
dances. 
36 Moreover, using the APDC, it is possible to 
identify ED presentations which resulted in an admission 
to hospital. </p>

<p>NSW Register of Births, Deaths and Marriages (RBDM) plus 
Australian Bureau of Statistics Cause of Death 
The RBDM records all births and deaths in NSW. Details 
of all registered deaths are forwarded to the ABS where 
causes of death codes (ICD-10) are applied to each 
record. The coded data then form part of the registered 
death information. However, there is often a significant 
lag between fact and cause of death data due to the 
time taken to process cause of death information. </p>

<p>Data linkage 
The first linked data were obtained in 2011. The data 
linkage was performed by the Centre for Health Record 
Linkage (CHeReL) which maintains a record linkage 
system for health-related data in NSW and the Australian 
Capital Territory in accordance with all ethical, legal, 
privacy and confidentiality requirements. The CHeReL 
keeps a Master Linkage Key that consists of continuously 
updated links between most NSW data sets. 
The DVA provided the CHeReL with an encrypted 
client number and personal information for all clients. 
The CHeReL then assigned a project person number 
(PPN) to each DVA client. A 'project key' containing the 
PPN and encrypted client number for each respective 
database is sent to the various data custodians who 
decrypted the client number and attached the PPNs and 
requested content variables. These were subsequently 
sent to the researchers stripped of personally identifying 
information such as name and address. All the data sets 
were joined by the researchers using the PPNs. This 
process is outlined in figure 1. 
The linkage used probabilistic matching 
37 using the 
record linkage software <rs type="software">ChoiceMaker</rs>, 
38 together with 
clerical review of possible matches. Probabilistic match-
ing assigns a weight to pairs of records based on how 
likely they are to be a true match based on a comparison 
of name, date of birth and address. Records with high 
weights are considered a true match while those with 
low weights are false matches; uncertain matches 
undergo clerical review. The cut-off for determining 
whether a match is true or false is chosen as to minimise 
the number of false positives, false negatives and the 
number of clerical reviews. 
39 The linkage algorithms 
take into account name reversals, name shortenings and 
a limited number of keystroke errors in date of birth. 
The CHeReL routinely performs these linkages, and </p>



<p>Pearson S-A, Schaffer A. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004099. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004099 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>standard operating procedures exist to fine tune the 
linkage sensitivity and specificity depending on the 
cohort data being linked. CHeReL follows established 
quality assurance processes for their master linkage key, 
linkage procedures and linkage staff. In general, these 
processes achieve false positive rates of 0-5/1000 and 
false negative rates of &lt;1/1000. However, the quality of 
the probabilistic matching process is highly dependent 
on the quality of the data provided, and in the case of 
DVA clients, important linkage variables such as name, 
date of birth and death and address histories are well 
documented. For example, an audit of the first CCR, 
APDC and EDDC linkages found a false positive rate of 
0.4% and a false negative rate of &lt;0.5%. Moreover, indi-
vidual research projects conducted under the auspices 
of this programme start with a comprehensive review of 
the cohort to minimise the inclusion of false positive 
cases. This is carried out by identifying and excluding 
cases where there are discrepancies between dates of 
birth and death across different databases or in circum-
stances where a client has observations of health 
resource use after their date of death. </p>

<p>Study population 
As this is an ongoing study, the characteristics of the 
population change over time. Characteristics of the 
study population as described below are summarised for 
each client at 1 July 2004 or the date of their first health-
care entitlement, whichever occurred later. There were 
104 635 DVA clients who resided in NSW, were aged 
65 years or older and received full or partial funding of 
medicines and/or health services. Figure 2 shows the 
proportion of the NSW population represented by DVA 
clients. </p>

<p>The vast majority of these DVA clients (89%) received 
full healthcare entitlements (Gold Card holders). For 
these individuals there will be almost complete ascertain-
ment of subsidised healthcare utilisation by combining 
DVA and NSW databases; it is this subpopulation that we 
will generally use for analysis of health services utilisa-
tion and medicines use. An additional 5% received sub-
sidised pharmaceuticals only (Orange Card holders). 
Inclusion of this cohort in analyses would be appropriate 
to answer research questions that require pharmaceut-
ical claims data only. Finally, 6% of DVA clients received 
subsidies for health services and pharmaceuticals related 
to the treatment of specific conditions related to service 
or any malignancy (White Card holders). Inclusion of 
this cohort would be appropriate for research questions 
about the medicines and health service use of clients 
with cancer. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Data linkage process. CHeReL, Centre for Health Record Linkage; DVA, Department of Veterans' Affairs; NSW, New 
South Wales. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Age distribution of New South Wales population 
and Department of Veterans' Affairs population, July 2004. </p>

<p>Pearson S-A, Schaffer A. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004099. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004099 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Over half (52%) of Gold Card holders were women, 
while men were the vast majority of White and Orange 
Card holders (table 2). The gender disparity at different 
levels of entitlement reflects the fact that the majority of 
female DVA clients are war widows, 
31 who are not eligible 
for White or Orange Cards. Most clients were aged 
between 80 and 84 years. Given the older age of this 
population, attrition was high with approximately 7% 
dying every year of follow-up. A quarter of clients (26%) 
had been diagnosed with cancer, with prostate, skin and 
colorectal cancers being the most common. White and 
Orange Card holders were less likely to have breast 
cancer given the fewer number of women with these enti-
tlements. In a 1-year period, 54% of all DVA clients had 
no hospitalisations. Among those hospitalised, the 
comorbidity burden as measured by the Charlson 
index 
40 was low, with most having an index of 0 (table 2). 
Since the collection of hospital separation data is pro-
vided by the NSW Ministry of Health, it is not dependent 
on DVA subsidy, so there was little variation by level of 
DVA healthcare entitlement. In contrast, given the 
limited subsidy of pharmaceutical items among White 
Card holders, this group was more likely to have had no 
dispensing records in a 1-year period. When comorbid-
ities are defined using the RxRisk, 
41 approximately 
one quarter of clients had seven or more comorbidities 
(table 2). Nearly two-thirds of clients lived in major cities 
(defined by the Accessibility/Remoteness Index of 
Australia), 
42 and nearly one-third resided in areas classi-
fied as the least disadvantaged (defined by the Index of 
Relative Socio-Economic Disadvantage 
43 ; table 2). 
Statins were the most common class of medicines dis-
pensed, representing between 7% and 8% of all dispens-
ing records in a 1-year period, followed closely by proton 
pump inhibitors (6-7%; table 3). Among Gold Card 
holders, 43% of patients were ever dispensed paraceta-
mol and 37% were ever dispensed a statin over a 1-year 
period. Among White and Orange Card holders, 19% 
and 34%, respectively, were ever dispensed a statin 
(table 3). The lower percentage among White Card 
holders likely reflects their lower rate of subsidy for 
pharmaceuticals. Cancer medicine use, including 
chemotherapy and hormone therapy, represented only 
0.5% of dispensing records. Over a 1-year period the 
most commonly dispensed antineoplastics were 
gonadotropin-releasing hormone analogues, such as 
goserelin, and pyrimidine analogues, such as capecita-
bine, reflecting the high rates of prostate and colorectal 
cancers (table 4). 
DVA clients were high users of health services, with 64 
health services per person-year. The majority of these 
were consultations and visits with healthcare profes-
sionals (41%), followed by pathology services (25%) and 
diagnostic and therapeutic procedures (14%; table 5). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
We will use a range of pharmacoepidemiological ana-
lyses to explore cancer medicines use and outcomes </p>

<p>across our programme of work. We will identify patients 
diagnosed with cancer using cancer registry data, while 
we will identify users of cancer medicines based on 
pharmaceutical dispensing data. When determining spe-
cific research questions we will account for the availabil-
ity and quality of the various data sources, the presence 
of secular trends and geographical variation that may 
affect the outcomes of the study. Importantly, the most 
contemporary cancer notification data are only available 
to Australian researchers until 2009, but outcomes that 
result in hospitalisation can be ascertained up until 
2012. The predominant approaches are outlined below. </p>

<p>Cancer medicines use 
We will ascertain use of cancer medicines using the 
pharmaceutical dispensing data. We will map all medi-
cines to their WHO Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical 
(ATC) classification; medicines in the ATC categories 
L01 ('antineoplastic agents') and L02 ('endocrine 
therapy') will be the primary medicines of interest. 
Since the dispensing data do not contain information 
on the daily dose, we will develop an algorithm for each 
medicine of interest based on the amount dispensed, 
the number of repeats, the average time between refills 
by person and typical dosage, as we have carried out pre-
viously. 
10-12 Where this is not practicable we will use the 
WHO's 'defined daily dose'. Using the hospital episode 
data we will also identify the administration of antineo-
plastic agents to public hospital inpatients, as medicines 
dispensed to these patients do not appear in the dis-
pensing data. </p>

<p>Patterns of use 
We will examine the trends in cancer medicines use 
using the following measures: cumulative incidence by 
medicine type over time, prevalence of use by medicine 
type by age group and by year, duration of use, average 
daily dose and the concomitant use of multiple cancer 
medicines. We will also estimate 'off-label' use of cancer 
medicines by using information about concomitant use 
of specific cancer medicines. We will report the 
characteristics of patients dispensed cancer medicines, 
specifically age, sex, geographical remoteness and area 
of socieconomic disadvantage, cancer type, disease 
spread and presence of comorbidities, and whether this 
changes over time. Age, sex, geographical remoteness 
and area of socieconomic disadvantage will be ascer-
tained from the DVA client database, while cancer type 
and spread is available from the cancer registry. We will 
identify comorbidities using the Charlson index, 
44 and/ 
or the Elixhauser index 
45 ; both indexes use diagnosis 
information from hospital separation data to identify 
comorbidities, and therefore clients who are not hospita-
lised will not be captured by these indices. Therefore, 
the RxRisk 
41 will also be used; this index uses dispensed 
medicines to identify 41 comorbidities. </p>



<p>Pearson S-A, Schaffer A. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004099. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004099 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Patterns of care 
After identifying patients with cancer, we will describe the 
treatment pathway for specific cancer types after </p>

<p>diagnosis. We will identify the receipt of cancer-related 
surgery, radiation therapy and chemotherapy using: (1)  hospital separation data to identify in-hospital surgery, </p>

<p>Table 2 Demographics of those alive, living in New South Wales and ≥65 years of age at 1 July 2004 or date of first 
healthcare entitlement </p>

<p>Department of Veterans' Affairs healthcare entitlement level 
Total 
n (%) </p>

<p>Gold 
n (%) </p>

<p>White* 
n (%) </p>

<p>Orange * 
n (%) </p>

<p>Sex 
Male 
44 480 
(47.6) 
5921 
(83.8) 
4928 
(98.0) 
54 508 
(52.1) 
Female 
48 890 
(52.4) 
1143 
(16.2) 
100 
(2.0) 
50 127 
(47.9) 
Age in years 
65-74 
9363 
(10.0) 
855 
(12.1) 
18 
(0.4) 
10 230 
(9.8) 
75-79 
20 632 
(22.1) 
1972 
(27.9) 
1104 
(22.0) 
23 539 
(22.5) 
80-84 
39 983 
(42.8) 
2850 
(40.4) 
2879 
(57.3) 
45 234 
(43.2) 
85-89 
17 884 
(19.2) 
1069 
(15.1) 
881 
(17.5) 
19 682 
(18.8) 
90+ 
5508 
(5.9) 
318 
(4.5) 
146 
(2.9) 
5950 
(5.7) 
Alive at † (year) 
1 
88 781 
(96.2) 
6773 
(96.6) 
4837 
(96.3) 
99 600 
(96.3) 
2 
80 812 
(89.3) 
6162 
(89.7) 
4440 
(88.6) 
90 687 
(89.3) 
3 
73 134 
(82.4) 
5353 
(81.8) 
4022 
(80.8) 
81 868 
(82.3) 
4 
65 286 
(75.1) 
4689 
(75.3) 
3575 
(72.7) 
72 985 
(75.1) 
5 
57 601 
(67.9) 
4079 
(68.8) 
2802 
(63.8) 
63 991 
(67.8) 
Cancer diagnosis (since 1994) 
Any cancer 
23 993 
(25.7) 
2515 
(35.6) 
1396 
(27.8) 
27 651 
(26.4) 
Prostate (C61) 
6122 
(6.6) 
895 
(12.7) 
527 
(10.5) 
7452 
(7.1) 
Skin (C44) 
5432 
(5.8) 
615 
(8.7) 
165 
(3.3) 
6162 
(5.9) 
Colorectal (C18-C20) 
4109 
(4.4) 
389 
(5.5) 
203 
(4.0) 
4661 
(4.5) 
Breast (C50) 
2342 
(2.5) 
137 
(1.9) 
7 
(0.1) 
2485 
(2.4) 
Bronchus and lung (C34) 
1899 
(2.0) 
179 
(2.5) 
151 
(3.0) 
2204 
(2.1) 
Other 
8291 
(8.9) 
559 
(7.9) 
850 
(16.9) 
9617 
(9.2) 
Charlson index ‡ 
0 
28 746 
(30.8) 
2156 
(30.5) 
1320 
(26.3) 
31 970 
(30.6) 
1-2 
9655 
(10.3) 
743 
(10.5) 
572 
(11.4) 
10 876 
(10.4) 
3+ 
4713 
(5.1) 
448 
(6.3) 
328 
(6.5) 
5430 
(5.2) 
No hospitalisations 
50 256 
(53.8) 
3717 
(52.6) 
2808 
(55.9) 
56 359 
(53.9) 
RxRisk † ‡ 
0-2 comorbidities 
17 255 
(18.7) 
1253 
(17.9) 
1018 
(20.3) 
19 348 
(18.7) 
3-4 comorbidities 
23 016 
(25.0) 
1572 
(22.4) 
1208 
(24.0) 
25 578 
(24.7) 
5-6 comorbidities 
22 151 
(24.0) 
1550 
(22.1) 
1172 
(23.3) 
24 657 
(23.8) 
7+ comorbidities 
24 230 
(26.3) 
1635 
(23.3) 
1176 
(23.4) 
26 841 
(25.9) 
No dispensing records 
5608 
(6.1) 
1002 
(14.3) 
450 
(9.0) 
7045 
(6.8) 
Accessibility/Remoteness Index of Australia category 
Major cities of Australia 
57 681 
(61.8) 
4378 
(62.0) 
3617 
(71.9) 
65 106 
(62.2) 
Inner regional Australia 
26 314 
(28.2) 
2012 
(28.5) 
1147 
(22.8) 
29 260 
(28.0) 
Outer regional Australia 
8324 
(8.9) 
573 
(8.1) 
232 
(4.6) 
9093 
(8.7) 
Remote/very remote Australia 
470 
(0.5) 
23 
(0.3) 
8 
(0.1) 
499 
(0.5) 
Unknown 
581 
(0.6) 
78 
(1.1) 
24 
(0.5) 
677 
(0.7) 
Index of Relative Socio-Economic Disadvantage 
Most disadvantaged 
12 647 
(13.6) 
823 
(11.7) 
556 
(11.1) 
13 949 
(13.3) 
Second quintile 
12 622 
(13.5) 
1013 
(14.3) 
661 
(13.2) 
14 156 
(13.5) 
Third quintile 
20 984 
(22.5) 
1563 
(22.1) 
1175 
(23.4) 
23 548 
(22.5) 
Fourth quintile 
18 663 
(20.0) 
1342 
(19.0) 
1057 
(21.0) 
20 906 
(20.0) 
Least disadvantaged 
27 873 
(29.9) 
2245 
(31.8) 
1555 
(30.9) 
31 399 
(30.0) 
Unknown 
581 
(0.6) 
78 
(1.1) 
24 
(0.5) 
677 
(0.7) 
Total 
93 370 
(100.00) 
7064 
(100.0) 
5028 
(100.0) 
104 635 
(100.0) </p>

<p>*Includes n=827 who have both White and Orange Cards. 
 †Denominator restricted to those with the necessary length of follow-up. 
 ‡Based on first year of hospital separation/dispensing data. </p>

<p>Pearson S-A, Schaffer A. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004099. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004099 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>radiation therapy and chemotherapy; (2) pharmaceutical 
dispensing data to identify the dispensing of antineoplas-
tic medicines in-hospital and out-of-hospital and (3) 
health services data to identify in-hospital and 
out-of-hospital surgery, radiation therapy and chemother-
apy. We will further examine the temporal relationship 
between date of diagnosis and the receipt of different 
treatment types; where treatment is identified from mul-
tiple data sources, we will compare dates to avoid double 
counting. 
In addition, where relevant, we will ascertain that 
appropriate monitoring is being performed for known 
side effects of cancer medicines using procedures and 
tests identified in health services data. </p>

<p>Health services utilisation 
We will quantify the use of health services in the period 
prior to diagnosis. These include: the number of hos-
pital separations and days spent in hospital, identified 
using the hospital separation data; the number of </p>

<p>general practitioner consultations, specialist consulta-
tions and allied health consultations, identified using 
the health services data and the number of ED visits, 
identified using the ED data. </p>

<p>Predictors of health outcomes 
We will identify predictors of the receipt of any treat-
ment, and type of treatment, using logistic regression 
models. We will also examine predictors of time to 
therapy and time to death (both cancer death and all-
cause mortality) using Kaplan-Meier curves and Cox pro-
portional hazards models. Date of death will be ascer-
tained using the DVA client database, while cause of 
death (cancer vs non-cancer) is provided by the cancer 
registry data. We will identify predictors of the rate of 
health service utilisation using Poisson regression or 
negative binomial regression, as appropriate. In all 
models the predictors we will consider include age at 
diagnosis, sex, geographical remoteness and area of </p>

<p>Table 3 Most common Repatriation Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme medicines dispensed in a 1-year period </p>

<p>Drug category 
Examples </p>

<p>Level of Department of Veterans' Affairs 
entitlement 
Gold 
n (%) </p>

<p>White 
n (%) </p>

<p>Orange 
n (%) </p>

<p>By number of dispensing records 
HMG-coenzymeA reductase 
inhibitors (C10AA) </p>

<p>Atorvastatin, simvastatin 
326 897 (6.8) 
10 007 (7.2) 
14 551 (8.2) </p>

<p>Proton pump inhibitors (A02BC) 
Omeprazole, pantoprazole 
295 844 (6.1) 
9146 (6.5) 
10 385 (5.9) 
ACE inhibitors, plain (C09AA) 
Perindopril, ramipril 
234 476 (4.8) 
7275 (5.2) 
10 722 (6.1) 
Anilides (N02BE) 
Paracetamol 
187 639 (3.9) 
4723 (3.4) 
5691 (3.2) 
Platelet aggregation inhibitors 
excluding heparin (B01AC) </p>

<p>Clopidogrel, aspirin 
173 264 (3.6) 
5070 (3.6) 
6256 (3.5) </p>

<p>Dihydropyridine derivatives (C08CA) Amlodipine, nifedipine 
142 419 (2.9) 
4044 (2.9) 
5955 (3.4) 
Angiotensin II antagonists, plain 
(C09CA) </p>

<p>Irbesartan, candesartan 
130 240 (2.7) 
3809 (2.7) 
4655 (2.6) </p>

<p>Organic nitrates (C01DA) 
Isosorbide mononitrate, 
glyceryl trinitrate </p>

<p>114 774 (2.4) 
3480 (2.5) 
5205 (3.0) </p>

<p>β-Blocking agents, selective (C07AB) Atenolol, metoprolol 
114 395 (2.4) 
3253 (2.3) 
4373 (2.5) 
Benzodiazepine derivatives (N05CD) Temazepam, nitrazepam 
114 964 (2.4) 
3230 (2.3) 
3880 (2.2) 
Total number of dispensing records 
5 025 507 (100.0) 144 644 (100.0) 181 444 (100.0) 
By number of people with ≥1 dispensing record 
Anilides (N02BE) 
Paracetamol 
39 766 (43.1) 
1238 (17.7) 
1443 (28.7) 
HMG-coenzymeA reductase 
inhibitors (C10AA) </p>

<p>Atorvastatin, simvastatin 
34 382 (37.3) 
1344 (19.2) 
1702 (33.9) </p>

<p>Proton pump inhibitors (A02BC) 
Omeprazole, pantoprazole 
33 905 (36.7) 
1322 (18.9) 
1369 (27.2) 
Platelet aggregation inhibitors 
excluding heparin (B01AC) </p>

<p>Clopidogrel, aspirin 
32 526 (35.3) 
1092 (15.6) 
1283 (25.5) </p>

<p>First-generation cephalosporins 
( J01DB) </p>

<p>Cephalexin, cephalotin 
26 707 (28.9) 
896 (12.8) 
911 (18.1) </p>

<p>ACE inhibitors, plain (C09AA) 
Perindopril, ramipril 
25 985 (28.2) 
998 (14.2) 
1305 (26.0) 
Other opthalmologicals (S01XA) 
Eye drops 
20 666 (22.4) 
574 (8.2) 
566 (11.3) 
Sulfonamides, plain (C03CA) 
Frusemide, bumetanide 
18 850 (20.4) 
590 (8.4) 
780 (15.5) 
Benzodiazepine derivatives (N05CD) Temazepam, nitrazepam 
18 798 (20.4) 
673 (9.6) 
719 (14.3) 
Corticosteroids, potent (group III) 
(D07AC) </p>

<p>β-Methasone, mometasone 
18 566 (20.1) 
674 (9.6) 
768 (15.3) </p>

<p>Total number of people with 1 year of dispensing data 
92 260 (100.0) 
7012 (100.0) 
5024 (100.0) </p>



<p>Pearson S-A, Schaffer A. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004099. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004099 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>socieconomic disadvantage, cancer type, disease spread 
at diagnosis and comorbidities. 
We will also investigate the risk of specific adverse out-
comes in clients with cancer who are taking a particular 
medicine, compared to a similar group of patients naive 
to the medicine of interest. Adverse outcomes will be 
identified using information such as: the dispensing of a 
new medicine that indicates the development of a new 
disease, a hospital separation with a diagnosis of the 
outcome of interest a new notified cancer and mortality. 
Care will be taken when selecting the comparison group 
to avoid confounding by indication; where practicable, 
we will apply high-dimensional propensity score ana-
lysis 
46 using the following dimensions: dispensed medi-
cines, hospital diagnoses, hospital procedures and 
physician visit procedures. We will investigate the rela-
tionship between the timing of the adverse event and </p>

<p>use of the medicine of interest using time-dependent 
Cox proportional hazard models. 
47 To best describe the 
relationship between the medicine of interest and the 
outcome, we will define medicine use in several different 
ways, using the daily dose information as described 
above, that is, any use, total cumulative dose, current 
dose, cumulative dose in the past 30 days, and recent ini-
tiation and/or discontinuation. Using different measures 
of medicine use will also allow us to perform sensitivity 
analyses to assess the robustness of our results. 
Analyses will be performed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SAS</rs> Version <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">9.3</rs>, 
<rs id="software-3" type="software">Stata</rs> Version <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">12</rs> and R Version 3.1.0. </p>

<p>Validation and feasibility 
As in any epidemiological study we must consider the 
potential biases in our research. Some of the concerns 
raised in relation to administrative database research </p>

<p>Table 4 Most common Repatriation Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme cancer medicines (ie, cytotoxic and hormone therapy) 
dispensed in a 1-year period </p>

<p>Drug category 
Examples </p>

<p>Level of Department of Veterans' Affairs 
entitlement 
Gold 
n (%) </p>

<p>White 
n (%) </p>

<p>Orange 
n (%) </p>

<p>By number of dispensing records 
Gonadotropin-releasing hormone analogues 
(L02AE) </p>

<p>Leuprorelin, goserelin 
7184 (27.3) 
723 (39.3) 
531 (44.3) </p>

<p>Pyrimidine analogues (L01BC) 
Fluorouracil, 
capecitabine </p>

<p>3370 (12.8) 
243 (13.2) 
73 (6.1) </p>

<p>Antiandrogens (L02BB) 
Flutamide, bicalutamide 
2898 (11.0) 
240 (13.0) 
217 (18.1) 
Antiestrogens (L02BA) 
Tamoxifen, toremifene 
3191 (12.1) 
89 (4.8) 
57 (4.8) 
Folic acid analogues (L01BA) 
Methotrexate, raltitrexed 
2211 (8.4) 
57 (3.1) 
16 (1.3) 
Total number of cancer medicine dispensing records 
26 290 (100.0) 1840 (100.0) 1200 (100.0) 
By number of people with ≥1 dispensing record 
Pyrimidine analogues (L01BC) 
Fluorouracil, 
capecitabine </p>

<p>2267 (2.5) 
145 (2.1) 
49 (1.0) </p>

<p>Gonadotropin-releasing hormone analogues 
(L02AE) </p>

<p>Leuprorelin, goserelin 
1854 (2.0) 
184 (2.6) 
145 (2.9) </p>

<p>Antiestrogens (L02BA) 
Tamoxifen, toremifene 
664 (0.7) 
24 (0.3) 
6 (0.1) 
Folic acid analogues (L01BA) 
Methotrexate, raltitrexed 
641 (0.7) 
28 (0.4) 
24 (4.8) 
Antiandrogens (L02BB) 
Flutamide, bicalutamide 
472 (0.5) 
41 (0.6) 
37 (0.7) 
Total number of people with 1 year of dispensing data 
92 260 (100.0) 7012 (100.0) 5024 (100.0) </p>

<p>Table 5 Number of health service records by type over a 1-year period </p>

<p>Level of Department of Veterans' Affairs entitlement 
Gold 
n (%) </p>

<p>White 
n (%) </p>

<p>Orange 
n (%) </p>

<p>Attendances/consults/visits 
2 380 445 (40.7) 
160 087 (40.0) 
111 923 (40.2) 
General practitioner 
1 092 432 (18.7) 
72 918 (18.2) 
50 970 (18.3) 
Specialist 
456 327 (7.8) 
31 967 (8.0) 
22 980 (8.3) 
Pathology services 
1 461 671 (25.0) 
102 413 (25.6) 
68 656 (24.7) 
Procedures 
820 958 (14.1) 
58 760 (14.7) 
42 597 (15.3) 
Diagnostic 
358 825 (6.1) 
24 740 (6.2) 
18 064 (6.5) 
Therapeutic 
462 133 (7.9) 
34 020 (8.5) 
24 533 (8.8) 
Miscellaneous (eg, administrative, medical supplies) 
1 181 775 (20.2) 
79 130 (19.8) 
55 157 (19.8) 
Total number of health services 
5 844 856 (100.0) 
400 390 (100.0) 
278 337 (100.0) </p>

<p>Pearson S-A, Schaffer A. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004099. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004099 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>and the conduct of pharmacoepidemiological research 
in Australia are described below. </p>

<p>Medicine exposure 
Electronic pharmacy dispensing records are considered 
the gold standard of prescribed medicines exposure 
information, compared with patient notes and self-
reported information. 
48 49 In addition, undertaking 
studies in the DVA client population have the distinct 
advantages of having good ascertainment of prescribed 
medicines use, even relatively cheap medicines that are 
not always captured in the general population. In 
Australia, we have comprehensive pharmaceutical claims 
data collections for prescribed medicines dispensed in 
community and private hospitals, but not for public hos-
pital inpatients. Given the vast majority of oncology pro-
tocols are administered in the outpatient setting or to 
private hospital inpatients (both of which are captured 
in the R/PBS data), we believe this issue will not impact 
significantly on the outcomes of our analyses. However, 
if in the unlikely event that chemotherapy is adminis-
tered to public hospital inpatients, it is indicated as a 
procedure code in the public hospital separation record. 
While we will not know the nature of the chemotherapy 
we can identify an episode when chemotherapy was 
administered in hospital, allowing us to estimate the 
chemotherapy use that was not identified in the R/PBS 
dispensing data. While there are clear limitations in 
terms of complete ascertainment of cancer medicines 
dispensing claims, our approach remains the best way of 
defining medicines exposure in whole of population 
studies. Since it is highly unlikely that we would miss 
every administration of a cancer medicine over the 
course of a chemotherapy protocol, we will almost cer-
tainly identify most patients who had received some type 
of cancer drug treatment. </p>

<p>Diagnosis, outcome and covariate misclassification 
As the health administrative data sets lack detailed clin-
ical information, one needs to assess the impact of mis-
classifying diagnoses and outcomes of interest. The 
accuracy of cancer incidence in DVA clients depends on 
the completeness and accuracy of the NSW CCR. 
Routine indicators of data quality and completeness 
show the Australian State and Territory cancer registries 
are operating in accordance with international stan-
dards. 
50 In terms of outcomes of interest, poor sensitivity 
may be an issue as we commonly identify outcomes that 
result in hospitalisation before we can identify potential 
outcomes of interest and the health service records 
contain no diagnostic information. However, poor speci-
ficity of the outcome is worse than a lack of sensitivity in 
most situations. 
51 If the specificity of the outcome is 
100% then relative risk estimates are unbiased. A recent 
comprehensive study on the misclassification of claims 
data diagnoses using medical record chart review as the 
gold standard revealed the sensitivity of claims diagnoses 
is often less than moderate whereas specificity is usually </p>

<p>95% or greater. A high specificity of diagnostic coding in 
claims data can be expected because if a diagnosis is 
coded and recorded it is likely the diagnosis was made. </p>

<p>52   The data also lack certain important covariates, includ-
ing health behaviours such as smoking, drinking habits 
and obesity. Further, our data set is not linked to DVA mili-
tary service records. In hospital separation data, comorbid-
ities are only recorded if they are directly related to the 
reason for admission. As a result, there have been several 
algorithms developed to identify the presence of import-
ant comorbidities using administrative claims data, includ-
ing in hospitalisation data (such as the Charlson index </p>

<p>53   ) 
and in dispensing data (such as the RxRisk </p>

<p>54   ). 
In the general population, recording of services pro-
vided by Medicare Australia (ie, health services and dis-
pensed medicines) is tied to those subsidised (in part or 
in full) by the government; therefore the record of their 
healthcare utilisation is incomplete, limiting the sorts of 
analyses that can be conducted. In contrast, the utilisa-
tion of health services by Australian veterans is nearly 
totally subsidised by the DVA, meaning there is near-
complete capture of health services and hospital visits, 
creating a unique opportunity for study. The availability 
of data across multiple sources allows for validation of 
important endpoints such as death, for which we will 
have date of death information from a minimum of 
three sources and cause of death from a minimum of 
two sources (table 6). </p>

<p>Multiple data sources and observations 
One of the greatest strengths of the DVA/NSW data 
linkage is the multiple data sources for the key analysis 
variables (table 2). For example, we will use hospital sep-
aration data from both NSW and DVA data sets. While 
some of this information is clearly duplicated, each data 
set brings its own unique benefits. The NSW APDC will 
contain hospital separations for DVA clients in NSW, and 
the DVA hospital episodes will record any hospital separ-
ation (as a DVA client) regardless of where it occurred 
in Australia. </p>

<p>External validity of research findings 
One potential limitation of this research programme is 
that the health seeking behaviour and health outcomes 
of the veterans' population may not be representative of 
older Australians. However, when compared with 
Australians of similar age, DVA clients have been shown 
to have very similar rates of health service and medicine 
use. </p>

<p>55   Ethics and dissemination 
The work outlined in this protocol describes a pro-
gramme of research examining the real-world use and 
impacts of cancer medicines in a population of elderly 
Australians. The first linkages and data access occurred 
in 2011 and we have ongoing human research ethics 
approval until 2015. </p>



<p>Pearson S-A, Schaffer A. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004099. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004099 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>The original proposals were submitted in two phases, 
the first of which approved the linkage of the DVA client 
data with NSW CCR and the RPBS data (approval 
numbers: 2008/02/060 and, E008/003). The second 
phase approved the linkage of the remaining data sets 
(approval numbers: 2010/03/217 and E010/009). The 
two-phased approach was developed after discussions 
with the DVA and NSW Ministry of Health data custo-
dians. Given the novelty of the linkage, it was deter-
mined that the first linkage should be used to 
demonstrate the feasibility of the linkage after which 
time the additional data would be linked. Despite this, 
there was a 3-year delay between the first ethics 
approval and delivery of the data. The primary impedi-
ments related to a lack of capacity within the various 
agencies to extract the data and due to challenges in 
negotiating and signing a data service agreement 
between the DVA (a Commonwealth agency) and an 
academic institution. 
The data for the research programme were released 
without individual consent. Therefore, the ethical and 
privacy issues related to the use and disclosure of infor-
mation for a secondary purpose, and waiving informed 
consent. The use and disclosure of Commonwealth and 
state data are governed under the Privacy Act 1988 and 
Health Records and Information Privacy (HRIP) Act 
2003, respectively. Information Privacy Principle (IPP) 2 
under the Privacy Act 1988 (Commonwealth) provides 
that personal information should not be used or dis-
closed for any purpose other than the primary purpose 
of the collection. Further, Health Privacy Principles 10 
and 11 of the HRIP Act provide that an organisation can 
only use and disclose health information for the 
purpose for which it was collected, or a directly related 
purpose. 
We sought approval to use of data for a secondary 
purpose, that of research involving data linkage. 
▸ Under IPP2.1(d) use or disclosure for another 
purpose is permitted if (1) it is necessary for research </p>

<p>and it is impracticable to gain consent and (2) the 
use is in accordance with the section 95A guidelines 
(which provides a process to resolve the conflict that 
may arise between the public interest in privacy and 
the public interest in medical research). 
▸ The statutory guidelines under the HRIP Act define 
the scope of particular exemptions in the health 
privacy principles. Under this act, data can be disclosed 
for a secondary purpose, such as research using the 'research 
exemption'. 
As such, we applied for these exemptions to the 
current research programme. 
We sought to waive individual consent for the release of 
data because: 
▸ It is not possible or practical to obtain consent 
because of the large study population (more than 
100 000 DVA clients) and a large proportion of DVA 
clients were likely to be deceased. 
▸ Obtaining consent would prejudice the scientific 
value of the research due to the high participation 
rates required for unbiased samples (at least 90%) </p>

<p>56   and the Australian evidence about the sociodemo-
graphic differences between participants who consent 
to data linkage research and those that do not. </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>▸ The public interest in the research outweighs the 
public interest in privacy protection. This is because 
we know little about the way in which medicines are 
used in the real-world marketplace. Our research has 
the potential to address key issues such as the risks 
and benefits of specific cancer medicines in a sub-
group of Australians. 
We minimised the risk to personal privacy by: 
▸ A third party, the CHeReL, undertaking the record 
linkage, ensuring the smallest number of people have 
access to the identifiable data. 
▸ Ensuring data are stored securely. 
▸ Restricting access to identified data to officers in the 
CHeReL, whose access is password protected and 
subject to the signing of a confidentiality agreement. </p>

<p>Table 6 Data sources containing key analysis variables </p>

<p>Department of Veterans' Affairs 
New South Wales 
Client 
data 
RPBS </p>

<p>Medical 
services </p>

<p>Hospital 
episodes 
CCR 
APDC 
RBDM 
EDDC </p>

<p>Cancer diagnoses 
✓ 
✓ 
Hospitalisations 
✓ 
✓ 
Prescribed medicines use 
✓ 
✓ * 
Health service use 
✓ 
✓ 
Emergency department 
visits </p>

<p>✓ </p>

<p>Date of death 
✓ 
✓ 
✓  † 
✓ 
✓  ‡ 
Cause of death 
✓ § 
✓ † 
✓ 
✓  ‡ </p>

<p>*Absence or presence of chemotherapy. 
 †If death occurred in hospital. 
 ‡If death occurred in emergency department. 
 §Cancer related or non-cancer related. 
APDC, Admitted Patients Data Collection; CCR, Central Cancer Registry; EDDC, Emergency Department Data Collection; RBDM, Register 
of Births, Deaths and Marriages; RPBS, Repatriation Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme. </p>

<p>Pearson S-A, Schaffer A. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004099. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004099 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>▸ Separating the data linkage process (where access to 
personally identified data is necessary), from the data 
analysis, so that personal information and health 
information are separated. 
▸ Ensuring researchers will not be in possession of any 
personal identifying information. The identifiable 
information (such as name and address) will be 
removed from the content data by linkage staff after 
record linkage has taken place. 
▸ Ensuring the files released to researchers will not 
contain DVA clients' actual enrolment number, rather 
a unique project number generated by CHeReL staff. 
▸ Ensuring identifiable information will not be 
published. </p>

<p>Dissemination plan 
The outcomes of this research will be submitted to inter-
national peer-reviewed journals; in particular oncology, 
general medical and pharmacoepidemiology journals. 
Furthermore, results will be presented at national and 
international oncology and pharmacoepidemiology con-
ferences. We will also develop lay summaries of research 
findings for communication to consumer groups and 
policy makers where appropriate. As stipulated in our DVA 
data agreement we will submit all data that will be commu-
nicated in the public domain to the DVA for review and 
approval. Authorship will be based on the International 
Committee of Medical Journal Editors guidelines. 
Outcomes will also be posted on the University of Sydney 
webpage of the lead investigator and the Centre for 
Research Excellence in Medicines and Ageing website 
(under development). Direct access to the data and analyt-
ical files to other individuals or authorities is not permitted 
without the express permission of the approving human 
research ethics committees and data custodians. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
The programme outlined in this protocol will form a 
solid foundation for cancer pharmacoepidemiology 
research and will allow Australian researchers to capital-
ise on the evidence derived and learning gained from 
this programme of work. Observational studies of the 
kind described in this protocol are particularly import-
ant as the elderly are under-represented in clinical trials 
but are the subpopulation with the highest rates of 
medicine use 
58 and are at the most at risk of adverse 
events. 
59 60 The DVA have a strong tradition of making 
data available for research purposes and this programme 
will establish a long-term programme in cancer 
pharmacoepidemiology. 
Moreover, there have been encouraging developments 
in Australia in recent years that will increase the opportun-
ities for Australian researchers to undertake whole of 
population, pharmacoepidemiology research. At the 
national level, the Department of Human Services (custo-
dians of Medicare and PBS data) now provides timely 
access to person-level medicines dispensing data. At the </p>

<p>state level, major linked data resources incorporating hos-
pital separations, ED visits, cancer registrations, mental 
health service use and fact and cause of death data have 
been available for nearly two decades via the Western 
Australian Data Linkage System (WADLS) and the NSW 
CHeReL since 2006. A similar service has been recently 
established in South Australia and the Northern Territory 
via SA-NT Datalink. Other states will follow in the near 
future due to the injection of more than $A60 million by 
the National Collaborative Research Infrastructure 
Strategy (NCRIS). Moreover, there is a strong commitment 
from government for linked Commonwealth and State 
data through Integrating Authorities, which have become 
operational in 2012. With these advances cancer pharma-
coepidemiology research in Australia has a bright future. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors would like to thank the Australian 
Government Department of Veterans' Affairs (DVA) and the New South Wales 
(NSW) Ministry of Health for data provision and the Centre for Health Record 
Linkage for undertaking the data linkage process. </p>

<p>Contributors S-AP and AS drafted and approved the final manuscript. AS 
conducted the data analysis. </p>

<p>Funding This data linkage was funded by a Cancer Australia Project Grant 
(Number 568773). From 2014, the programme will be partly funded by the 
NHMRC Centre of Research Excellence in Medicines and Ageing (1060407). </p>

<p>Competing interests Sallie Pearson is a Cancer Institute NSW Career 
Development Fellow (12/CDF/2-25). Sallie Pearson was based at the 
University of NSW at the time she established the research programme. She is 
now at the University of Sydney. </p>

<p>Ethics approval The research programme was approved by the New South 
Wales Population and Health Services and DVA Human Research Ethics 
Committees </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>





<p>Pearson S-A, Schaffer A. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004099. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004099 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>



<p>Pearson S-A, Schaffer A. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004099. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004099 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>