<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4027884" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A massive amount of radioactive materials has been released into the environment by the Fukushima 
Dai-ichi Nuclear Power Plant accident, but its biological impacts have rarely been examined. Here, we have 
quantitatively evaluated the relationship between the dose of ingested radioactive cesium and mortality and 
abnormality rates using the pale grass blue butterfly, Zizeeria maha. When larvae from Okinawa, which is 
likely the least polluted locality in Japan, were fed leaves collected from polluted localities, mortality and 
abnormality rates increased sharply at low doses in response to the ingested cesium dose. This dose-response 
relationship was best fitted by power function models, which indicated that the half lethal and abnormal 
doses were 1.9 and 0.76 Bq per larva, corresponding to 54,000 and 22,000 Bq per kilogram body weight, 
respectively. Both the retention of radioactive cesium in a pupa relative to the ingested dose throughout the 
larval stage and the accumulation of radioactive cesium in a pupa relative to the activity concentration in a 
diet were highest at the lowest level of cesium ingested. We conclude that the risk of ingesting a polluted diet 
is realistic, at least for this butterfly, and likely for certain other organisms living in the polluted area. </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>nvironmental pollution by artificial radionuclides released from the collapsed Fukushima Dai-ichi Nuclear 
Power Plant (NPP) has often been evaluated based on radioactivity concentrations in environmental 
samples collected from the polluted area, such as soil and forest litter </p>

<p>1-3 </p>

<p>. The accumulation of radionuclides 
in the bodies of wild and domesticated organisms and in agricultural products has also been documented </p>

<p>4-11 </p>

<p>. 
However, the biological impacts of this pollution on the health and disease of wild organisms have not been 
examined sufficiently. 
A field study indicated that the abundance of insects, especially butterflies, has decreased </p>

<p>12,13 </p>

<p>, suggesting that 
the pollution might have had a fatal effect on butterflies. Another study indicated a high incidence of morpho-
logical abnormality in gall-forming aphids 
14 . Consistent with these studies, we have demonstrated that the 
Japanese pale grass blue butterfly, Zizeeria maha (Yamato shijimi in Japanese), was affected physiologically 
and genetically in the polluted area, likely due to the artificial radionuclides released from the Fukushima Dai-
ichi NPP </p>

<p>15,16 </p>

<p>. In one of a series of experiments, we have shown a decrease in the survival rate of this butterfly in 
accordance with the level of radioactivity of cesium in the diet (i.e., the leaves of the host plant, Oxalis cornicu-
lata) 
15,16 under our standard rearing conditions 
17 . In this experiment, host plant leaves were collected from 5 
different localities with different pollution levels (Ube, Hirono, Fukushima, Iitate-flatland, and Iitate-montane) 
(Table 1) and were given to larvae that were obtained in the laboratory from field-caught females from Okinawa </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>, 
which is likely the least polluted locality in Japan. However, the amount of food and the dose of artificial 
radioactive cesium ingested by these larvae remain to be determined. Furthermore, the amount of radioactivity 
retained and accumulated by pupae has not been examined. 
In the present study, we quantified the amount of radioactive cesium consumed by larvae over their lifetimes. 
Based on these data, simple mathematical models were employed to obtain the radioactive cesium doses resulting 
in a 50% mortality rate and a 50% abnormality rate. We also quantified how much radioactive cesium was 
retained and accumulated in pupae. Finally, we discussed the possible risks of a polluted diet for butterflies and 
other organisms living in the polluted area. </p>

<p>Results 
Quantification of ingested doses. We first investigated the leaf weight consumed by larvae in the larval stage 
(Fig. 1). Dietary consumption curves for 5 larvae were largely sigmoidal: approximately 4 days before reaching the </p>

<p>OPEN </p>

<p>SUBJECT AREAS: </p>

<p>ENVIRONMENTAL 
SCIENCES </p>

<p>RISK FACTORS </p>

<p>ENVIRONMENTAL HEALTH </p>

<p>100% consumption level, the amount of ingested leaves increased 
dramatically. There was variability in the total amount ingested 
among the 5 individuals; we recorded 0.304, 0.342, 0.391, 0.318, 
and 0.279 g (mean 6 SD 5 0.327 6 0.038 g; n 5 5) for the total 
weight of host plant leaves eaten by each larva (Fig. 1). However, the 
shapes of these dietary consumption curves were essentially similar 
to one another, indicating that our feeding process in which we 
quantified the weight of ingested leaves did not considerably </p>

<p>disrupt the overall growth patterns of the larvae. Within 24 hours 
after pupation, the weights of all 5 pupae were also recorded; we 
recorded 0.023, 0.028, 0.033, 0.035, and 0.026 g pupal weight 
(mean 6 SD 5 0.029 6 0.004 g; n 5 5). These 5 pupae were 
smaller than other pupae reared under standard conditions using 
leaves from Ube, a control locality (mean 6 SD 5 0.035 6 
0.005 g; n 5 154). This difference is most likely due to larval stress 
resulting from the above rearing conditions, which were necessary to 
quantify the ingested leaves. Only one piece of leaf was given at a time 
and replaced daily, and each larva was confined to a small airtight 
container (see Methods). The leaf weight ingested by an average larva 
reared under the standard conditions was calculated to be 0.389 g per 
larva based on a linear adjustment according to the mean pupal 
weight under the standard conditions, 0.035 g. 
Using the summation of the radioactivity of </p>

<p>137 </p>

<p>Cs and </p>

<p>134 </p>

<p>Cs 
detected in host plant samples from 5 localities </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>, we calculated the 
cumulative radioactive cesium doses ingested by larvae throughout 
the larval stage; 0.00038 (Ube), 0.58 (Hirono), 2.8 (Fukushima), 3.3 
(Iitate-flatland), and 16 (Iitate-montane) Bq (Table 1). Averaged 
over 5 individuals, the larva in this experiment ate a small amount 
of non-contaminated leaves (2.8% of the total weight of leaves) 
before eating contaminated leaves, which was taken into account 
to calculate the cumulative doses above. The average dose rates per 
day per larva were also calculated, given that the average larva began 
ingesting contaminated leaves on day 6 and required 12 additional 
days to reach 100% consumption (Table 1). </p>

<p>Table 1 | Summary of data for the internal exposure experiment* </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Ube 
Hirono 
Fukushima 
Iitate-flatland 
Iitate-montane </p>

<p>Distance from the NPP [km] 
966.0 
20.7 
61.1 
40.0 
33.7 
Collection site for the host 
plant </p>

<p>Higashisue, Oaza 
(Kounan-kita) </p>

<p>Futatsunuma Park 
Takahata (Okabe); 
Hanamiyama </p>

<p>Ainosawa Campsite; 
Omori Fukaya; Onishi Iitoi </p>

<p>Nagadoro </p>

<p>Collection prefecture for 
the host plant </p>

<p>Yamaguchi Prefecture 
Fukushima Prefecture </p>

<p>Collection site for the pale 
grass blue butterfly </p>

<p>Nishihara, Okinawa Island, Okinawa Prefecture </p>

<p>Ground radiation 
dose [mSv/h] </p>

<p>0.18 
1.06 
3.57 
6.22 
18.9 </p>

<p>Activity of 
137 Cs in the host 
plant [Bq/kg]* </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>5.4 (60.2) 3 10 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>7.79 (60.08) 3 10 
2 4.21 (60.04) 3 10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>5.47 (60.05) 3 10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2.33 (60.01) 3 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Activity of 
134 Cs in the host 
plant [Bq/kg]* </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4.5 (60.1) 3 10 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>6.73 (60.07) 3 10 
2 3.65 (60.03) 3 10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4.70 (60.05) 3 10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2.02 (60.01) 3 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Summation of cesium 
activity in the host plant 
[Bq/kg] </p>

<p>0.99 
1,452 
7,860 
10,170 
43,500 </p>

<p>Number of larvae reared 
146* </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>85 
108 
100 
103 
Number of pupae 
obtained </p>

<p>154 
58 
70 
67 
81 </p>

<p>Number of adults eclosed 
139 
62 
53 
41 
56 
Average pupal weight 6 
SD [g]* </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0.035 6 0.005 
0.037 6 0.006 
0.033 6 0.006 
0.029 6 0.007 
0.033 6 0.008 </p>

<p>Total leaves ingested per 
larva [g] </p>

<p>0.39 
0.42 
0.37 
0.33 
0.37 </p>

<p>Contaminated leaves 
ingested per larva [g]* </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0.38 
0.40 
0.36 
0.32 
0.36 </p>

<p>Radiation dose ingested 
per larva [Bq] </p>

<p>0.00038 
0.58 
2.8 
3.3 
16 </p>

<p>Dose rate of ingestion per 
day per larva [Bq/d] </p>

<p>3.2 3 10 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>0.048 
0.23 
0.28 
1.3 </p>

<p>Mortality rate [%] 
4.8 
31.8 
58.3 
63.0 
46.6 
Abnormality rate [%] 
6.2 
45.9 
73.1 
75.0 
72.8 </p>

<p>*1. Part of this information is also available in Supplementary Table 8 in Hiyama et al. (2012) 15 . 
*2. Activity values at the time of larval ingestion (fixed at 22 July 2011 for simplicity) were calculated based on measured values obtained on 26 December 2011 as shown in Hiyama et al. (2012) 15 , 
assuming that 137 Cs and 134 Cs were released at a 151 activity ratio on 15 March 2011 in a single burst from the Fukushima Dai-ichi NPP. 
*3. This number was underestimated because larvae not counted at the earlier stage were found later. 
*4. Pupal weight was measured within 24 hours postpupation. 
*5. Because leaves from the 5 localities were given from the 6th day post-hatching, the ingested contaminated leaves correspond to 97.16% of the total amount of leaves ingested. </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Cumulative amount of leaves ingested over time for 5 larvae. </p>

<p>Each curve represents an individual larva. The day when a hatched larva 
was detected was defined as day 1. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4946 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04946 </p>

<p>
Ingested doses, mortality rates, and abnormality rates. In reference 
to mortality rates and abnormality rates of 5 groups that ingested 
leaves from Ube (n 5 154), Hirono (n 5 85), Fukushima (n 5 108), 
Iitate-flatland (n 5 100), and Iitate-montane (n 5 103) (Table 1), we 
next examined possible relationships between the dose of ingested 
cesium per larva and the mortality and abnormality rates (Fig. 2). 
Both the mortality and abnormality rates increased sharply, 
especially at low doses, until the ingested cesium dose reached 
approximately 3 Bq, above which rates did not change notably. 
Because the plot for the Iitate-montane group was located in the 
plateau phase, we tentatively excluded it to obtain a mathematical 
model. Indeed, inclusion of the Iitate-montane plot made any models 
examined less fit (data not shown). The remaining plots were 
approximated very well using power functions: y 5 42x 
0.28 or Y 5 
0.28 (60.01) X 1 1.6 (60.03) on logarithmic scales with R 
2 5 0.9945, 
RMSE (root-mean-square error) 5 0.047, F 5 3.6 3 10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, df 5 3 (also 
in all other models examined hereafter), and p 5 0.0027 for the 
mortality rate, and y 5 54x 
0.28 or Y 5 0.28 (60.002) X 1 1.7 
(60.003) on logarithmic scales with R 
2 5 0.9999, RMSE 5 0.0068, 
F 5 1.73 3 10 
4 , and p , 0.0001 for the abnormality rate. 
The power functions above were compared with simple linear 
models. For the mortality rate, we obtained y 5 16x 1 13 with R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>5 0.9236, RMSE 5 9.1, F 5 24, and p 5 0.039, using the 4 data points 
excluding the Iitate-montane data. For the abnormality rate, we 
obtained y 5 18x 1 20 with R 
2 5 0.8527, RMSE 5 15, F 5 12, 
and p 5 0.077, using the 4 data points. These results indicate that 
the simple linear models were poorer fits than the power function 
models. Similarly, we examined logarithmic models, obtaining y 5 
5.9 ln(x) 1 49 with R 
2 5 0.8806, RMSE 5 11, F 5 15, and p 5 0.062 
for the mortality rate, and y 5 7.3 ln(x) 1 61 with R 
2 5 0.9420, RMSE 
5 9.5, F 5 33, and p 5 0.029 for the abnormality rate. These log-
arithmic models appeared to be better than the linear models but still 
inferior to the power function models. We examined other major 
models, all of which were less fit than the power function models (see 
Methods). 
Therefore, based on the power function equations, the half lethal 
dose and the half abnormal dose (y 5 50) were calculated to be 1.9 
(60.02) and 0.76 (60.02) Bq per larva, respectively. Using the mean 
pupal weight under standard conditions (0.035 g), these half doses of 
cesium corresponded to 5.4 (60.06) 3 10 
4 and 2.2 (60.06) 3 10 
4 Bq 
per kilogram body weight, respectively. Similar calculations yielded 
the half lethal dose rate (daily dose) and the half abnormal dose rate 
(daily dose) of cesium ingestion, assuming that a larva consumed 
contaminated leaves over 12 days, which were 0.16 (60.002) and 
0.063 (60.002) Bq/d per larva, respectively. These half dose rates 
corresponded to 4.6 (60.06) 3 10 
3 and 1.8 (60.06) 3 10 
3 Bq/d 
per kilogram body weight, respectively. 
Assuming that larvae eat leaves with a constant contamination 
level throughout life, we calculated the critical contamination levels </p>

<p>of leaves to attain the half lethal and abnormal doses when ingested. 
These critical concentrations were obtained simply by dividing the 
half lethal and abnormal doses by the amount of leaves consumed 
throughout life, 0.389 g, yielding 4.9 (60.05) 3 10 
3 and 2.0 (60.05) 
3 10 
3 Bq per kilogram leaf, respectively. </p>

<p>Cesium radioactivity in pupae. To examine how much radioactive 
cesium was retained in the body of the pupae, we measured the 
cesium radioactivity of dead pupae that never eclosed under our 
standard rearing conditions (Table 2). The summation of </p>

<p>137 </p>

<p>Cs and </p>

<p>134 </p>

<p>Cs activity concentrations per pupa showed that the pupae that ate 
Hirono leaves (1.32 mBq) had higher values than the pupae that ate 
Fukushima leaves (1.03 mBq), although the dose ingested by the 
Hirono pupae (0.58 Bq) was lower than that ingested by the 
Fukushima pupae (2.8 Bq). Furthermore, the Iitate-flatland pupae 
had the highest radioactivity (2.36 mBq), which was roughly twice as 
much as those of the Hirono and Fukushima pupae. Surprisingly, the 
Iitate-montane pupae showed the lowest radioactivity (0.61 mBq) 
among the examined pupae, except for the control Ube sample 
(Table 2). 
Possible relationships between the cesium radioactivity per pupa 
and mortality and abnormality rates were examined in scatter plots 
(Fig. 3). The scattering patterns were different from those found in 
the ingested dose shown in Fig. 2. As discussed above, the Hirono 
pupae may be expected to have a lower value than the measured 
value, and the Iitate-montane pupae may be expected to have a 
higher value than the measured values, if the cesium activity in a 
pupa linearly reflects the ingested cesium dose. Deviations from the 
linear expectations suggest nonlinear biological responses to the 
ingested radioactive cesium. When a linear model was fitted, we 
obtained R 
2 5 0.56 and p 5 0.15 for the mortality rate, and R 
2 5 
0.41 with p 5 0.24 for the abnormality rate, assuming that the Ube 
sample had no cesium activity. Conclusive interpretation of these 
data was not possible, as indicated by low R 
2 values and high p-values. 
To assess the amount of radioactive cesium retained and accumu-
lated in pupae, we calculated both the percentage of cesium radio-
activity retained in pupae (Bq) relative to the cesium dose ingested by 
larvae throughout the larval stage (Bq) and the percentage of cesium 
radioactivity accumulated in pupae (Bq/kg) relative to the cesium 
radioactivity of the host plant leaves (Bq/kg) (Table 2). Both reten-
tion and accumulation percentages were highest in the Hirono pupae 
(0.23% and 2.6%, respectively), which ingested the least contami-
nated leaves, except for the control Ube sample (Table 2). </p>

<p>Discussion 
In this paper, we focused on the biological effects of ingested materi-
als containing radioactive cesium species released by the Fukushima 
Dai-ichi NPP accident. We found that the levels of ingested cesium 
from the 4 localities (i.e., Hirono, Fukushima, Iitate-flatland, and </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Mortality rate (a) and abnormality rate (b) in response to the radioactive cesium dose ingested per larva. Insets are plots of four localities that </p>

<p>were fitted by power functions (red broken lines). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4946 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04946 </p>

<p>
Iitate-montane) were much higher than that from Ube, a control 
locality; thus, it is not surprising that harmful biological effects were 
clearly detected in previous studies </p>

<p>15,16 </p>

<p>. However, we do not know if 
our results can be directly compared to other studies on natural 
radiation or other nuclear accidents. We measured the amount of 
cesium radioactivity retained in pupae, which could affect meta-
morphosis, resulting in morphological abnormalities and death </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>. 
However, it should be noted that the activity concentrations of 
cesium in pupae may not be proportional to the degrees of physio-
logical and genetic damage of those pupae. The cesium radioactivity 
concentration in pupae was much lower than that in the host plant, 
showing that no bioaccumulation took place in this producer-con-
sumer system that plays a role in an ecological food chain. 
We found that changes in the overall mortality and abnormality 
rates in response to amounts of ingested radioactivity were not linear. 
Rather, the mortality and abnormality rates increased sharply, espe-
cially at low doses. Additionally, there seemed to be no threshold 
level below which no biological response could be detected. These 
results are consistent with the linear no-threshold (LNT) model, 
which is relatively widely accepted at low doses </p>

<p>18,19 </p>

<p>, in that there 
was no threshold detected in our system. However, the results may 
be inconsistent with the LNT model in that a linear model may not be 
appropriate for our system. More precisely, the power function fit for 
the dose-response data suggests that the relatively small level of 
artificial cesium from the Fukushima Dai-ichi NPP may be signifi-
cantly toxic to some individuals in butterfly populations, although we 
do not know whether the relatively ''low-level'' radiation in our 
experimental system is in the range of the levels safely applicable 
to the LNT model. </p>

<p>Nevertheless, we assert that the half lethal and abnormal doses we 
obtained were quite high. Moreover, the critical concentrations of 
cesium resulting in the half lethal and abnormal doses, 4.9 (60.05) 3 
10 
3 and 2.0 (60.05) 3 10 
3 Bq per kilogram leaf, respectively, 
appeared to be very high compared to naturally occurring radioactiv-
ity levels. These results can be interpreted to suggest that the pale 
grass blue butterfly is generally resistant to internal radiation expo-
sure. The possible biological impacts of much lower radiation levels 
will be the subject of future investigations. 
The relevance of our results to humans remains undetermined and 
will remain so because of the impossibility of controlled experiments 
in humans. However, it should be noted that we sampled contami-
nated leaves from Fukushima City, which many people inhabit as 
though nothing had happened, and from Hirono Town, which some 
people returned to inhabit. Moreover, our results are consistent with 
the previous human results after the Chernobyl accident, in which 
infant mortality rate increased sharply in West Germany 
20 and in the 
United States 
21 . Gould and Sternglass (1989) 
21 speculated that the 
increased infant mortality rate immediately after the Chernobyl acci-
dent may have been caused by the ingestion of radioactive iodine. 
Although they used a logarithmic model rather than a power func-
tion model to fit their dose-response relationship, both models share 
a sharp non-linear increase at low doses. Implications of the half 
lethal and abnormal doses we obtained in the present study will 
impact future discussions on the effects of radioactive exposure on 
other organisms, including humans. 
We found that cesium radioactivity in Hirono pupae was relatively 
high, despite Hirono leaves having the lowest level of contamination 
among those examined. Interestingly, cesium activity in the Iitate-</p>

<p>Table 2 | Cesium radioactivity in pupae that ingested contaminated leaves at the larval stage </p>

<p>Ube 
Hirono 
Fukushima Iitate-flatland Iitate-montane </p>

<p>Number of dead pupae measured 
8 
6 
11 
10 
22 
Activity of 
137 Cs per pupa [mBq]* </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Lower than detection limit 0.71 6 0.06 0.55 6 0.04 1.27 6 0.05 0.33 6 0.01 
Activity of 
134 Cs per pupa [mBq]* </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Lower than detection limit 0.61 6 0.05 0.48 6 0.04 1.09 6 0.05 0.28 6 0.01 
Summation of cesium activity per pupa [mBq] 
Not applicable 
1.32 
1.03 
2.36 
0.61 
Summation of cesium activity per pupa [Bq/kg]* </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Not applicable 
35.7 
31.2 
81.4 
18.5 
Cesium activity retained per pupa (Bq) relative 
to the ingested dose (Bq) [%]* </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Not applicable 
0.23 
0.037 
0.072 
0.0038 </p>

<p>Cesium activity (Bq/kg) accumulated per pupa 
relative to the host plant activity (Bq/kg) [%]* </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Not applicable 
2.6 
0.40 
0.80 
0.043 </p>

<p>*1.Activity values of 137 Cs at the time of larval ingestion (fixed at 22 July 2011) were calculated based on measured values obtained on 15 February 2014, assuming that 137 Cs and 134 Cs were released at a 
151 activity ratio on 15 March 2011 in a single burst from the Fukushima Dai-ichi NPP. 
*2. Activity values of 134 Cs at the time of larval ingestion (fixed at 22 July 2011) were calculated based on the calculated values of 137 Cs using the 137 Cs5 134 Cs activity ratio at the time of ingestion, which was 
obtained from Table 1. 
*3. Calculated based on the average pupal weight of each group shown in Table 1. 
*4. Calculated based on the ingested doses shown in Table 1. 
*5. Calculated based on the host plant cesium activity concentrations shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Mortality rate (a) and abnormality rate (b) in relation to the cesium radioactivity in pupae. The Ube sample was considered to have a cesium </p>

<p>activity of 0. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4946 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04946 </p>

<p>
montane pupae was the lowest observed, except for the control Ube 
pupae, despite consuming leaves with the highest level of contamina-
tion observed. The Hirono pupae, which ate leaves with relatively 
low-level contamination among those sampled, had the highest 
retention and accumulation values. One possibility is that the epithe-
lial cells of the digestive tract of larvae that ate the highly contami-
nated Iitate-montane leaves became damaged, preventing the 
absorption of radioactive cesium. Alternatively, the digestive tract 
may have effectively expelled the excessively high dose of cesium, 
resulting in the absorption of a limited amount. The latter possibility 
is more likely, as no systematic reduction of body weight or wing size, 
which might result from digestive tract damage, was observed in the 
Iitate-montane group </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>. Indeed, the latter possibility may be likely if 
cesium was ingested as microparticles 
22 adsorbed onto the surface of 
host plant leaves. In contrast to the Iitate-montane group, the larvae 
that ate Hirono leaves appeared to have effectively absorbed the 
radioactive cesium. This scenario explains not only the sharp increase 
of the mortality and abnormality rates at low doses but also the 
saturated mortality and abnormality rates at high doses. The satura-
tion of the mortality and abnormality rates may also be explained by 
a possible exhaustion of relevant targets such as functional genes that 
cause immediate lethal or abnormal effects when damaged. Such 
genes may be limited in number, and further hits at these genes do 
not contribute to an increase in the mortality and abnormality rates. 
The biological impacts of internal radiation exposure on larvae 
may be relatively high, considering the fact that the artificial cesium 
emits not only c-rays but b-rays </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>. Additionally, the radioactive 
plume may have been ingested as microparticles </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>, causing immune 
responses (or other physiological responses) independent of radi-
ation, eventually leading to pathological outcomes. There is also 
the possibility that other radioactive (and even non-radioactive) 
materials from the Fukushima Dai-ichi NPP, other than cesium, 
could contribute additively to butterfly mortality and abnormality. 
Few available studies have evaluated the biological effects of 
internal radiation exposure in various organisms </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>, but it has been 
shown that different species have different sensitivities to radiation 
exposure </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>. We speculate that sensitivity likely varies widely under 
different genetic and environmental conditions, even within a single 
species. In this internal exposure experiment, we observed that even 
under the dosage conditions where many individuals died, other 
individuals survived normally. That is, the mortality and abnormality 
rates never reached 100%, indicating individual variability of sens-
itivity within a species. Because such intraspecies variation likely 
exists in humans as well as in other organisms, setting a single thresh-
old for a ''safe exposure level'' requires clearly stated confidence inter-
vals along with other relevant information on the system of interest. 
One recent study reported no detectable effect of radioactive 
cesium on bull testes </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>. However, it is premature to draw conclusions 
from that study, primarily because only two individuals were exam-
ined. Furthermore, sperm morphology was shown to be normal by 
images of only a few sperm nuclei and acrosomes, and the number of 
germ cells examined was not presented. Above all, negative data 
should generally be treated carefully, because careful definition of 
the experimental system and a large number of samples are required 
to demonstrate a null hypothesis </p>

<p>27,28 </p>

<p>. 
In conclusion, it is important to recognize the risk of internal 
radiation exposure due to ingested radioactive cesium, at least for 
the pale grass blue butterfly, and likely for certain other organisms 
living in the polluted area, possibly including humans. More studies 
at low doses are required in the near future to confirm and expand 
the findings of the present study. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Internal exposure experiment. To harvest eggs, 6 females and 6 males caught in the 
field in Okinawa Island were confined to a 300-mm cubic container for 6-10 days 
as described previously </p>

<p>15,16 </p>

<p>. During this period, dead adults were replaced with live 
ones to keep the number of adults unchanged. The obtained eggs, larvae, and pupae </p>

<p>were reared in the laboratory under standard conditions </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>. The diet from Okinawa 
(i.e., the non-contaminated leaves of the host plant, Oxalis corniculata) was given to 
all larvae initially, and on the 6th day after hatching, the initial larval population was 
randomly divided into 5 groups. Therefore, these groups were genetically identical to 
one another. Each group of larvae was fed a diet collected from one of the 5 localities 
(Ube, Hirono, Fukushima, Iitate-flatland, and Iitate-montane) from the 6th day after 
hatching </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>. Non-polluted leaves from Ube, Yamaguchi Prefecture, were fed to a group 
of larvae. This group of larvae served as a control for the internal exposure 
experiment. </p>

<p>Quantification of consumed diet. Eggs were harvested from females caught in the 
field in Okinawa as above, and 5 larvae were randomly chosen and reared at ambient 
temperature (approximately 27uC), each in a plastic columnar centrifuge tube with an 
airtight screw cap (10 mm in diameter and 50 mm in height) to prevent leaves from 
drying. The quantity of leaves eaten by each larva was monitored every day. One piece 
of leaf removed from the stalk was supplied at a time. Before being given to a larva, the 
leaf piece was weighed. Additionally, its image was taken by an image scanner, and its 
area was measured using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">ImageJ</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">1.44p</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">U. S. National Institutes of Health</rs>, Bethesda, Maryland, USA, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">http://imagej.nih.gov/ij</rs>/, 1997-2012). After being 
eaten, the remaining leaf was replaced every day with a fresh leaf. The area of the 
remaining leaf was measured every day, and its value was converted into weight, based 
on the proportion of the original leaf represented by the remnant. This process 
ensured that the weight eaten each day was recorded as the weight of the fresh leaf. </p>

<p>Radioactivity measurements and calculations. Cesium radioactivity (both </p>

<p>137 </p>

<p>Cs and </p>

<p>134 </p>

<p>Cs) in leaf samples was measured with a germanium semiconductor radiation well-
type detector Canberra GCW-4023 (Meriden, CT, USA) with a heavy shield of lead 
after ashing the samples as described previously </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>.Using cesium radioactivity values of 
the leaves at the time of measurement (26 December 2011), presented in 
Supplementary Table 8 in Hiyama et al. (2012) </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>, we recalculated the values at the time 
of larval consumption (fixed at 22 July 2011 for simplicity), assuming that </p>

<p>137 </p>

<p>Cs and </p>

<p>134 </p>

<p>Cs were released at a 151 activity ratio in a single burst on 15 March 2011 from the 
Fukushima Dai-ichi NPP. The Hirono </p>

<p>134 </p>

<p>Cs value, 5.38 (60.06) 3 10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, was amended 
due to a typing error in the original paper </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>. The same detector was used to measure 
cesium activity ( </p>

<p>137 </p>

<p>Cs only) in pupae. This well-type detector provides maximum 
efficiency for small samples, because samples can be inserted into a well. Before 
measurement, dead pupae were air-dried for several months and placed in a columnar 
plastic container (14 mm in diameter). The detector was calibrated with a standard 
prepared from the NBL powder standard (New Brunswick Laboratory, U.S. 
Department of Energy, Argonne, IL, USA). Measurements were performed until the 
error rate scored less than 10%. Measurements were assumed to be made 
simultaneously on 15 February 2014 for simplicity, although several days were required 
to obtain reliable levels of radioactive signals from the pupae. Radioactivity per pupa at 
the time of ingestion was calculated, assuming that </p>

<p>137 </p>

<p>Cs and </p>

<p>134 </p>

<p>Cs were released in a 
single burst on 15 March 2011 at a 151 activity ratio and that all leaves were eaten 
simultaneously at once on 22 July 2012. </p>

<p>134 </p>

<p>Cs activity was calculated based on a </p>

<p>134 </p>

<p>Cs5 </p>

<p>137 </p>

<p>Cs activity ratio at the time of ingestion, fixed at 22 July 2011 for simplicity. </p>

<p>Mortality and abnormality rates. The mortality rate was defined as the percentage of 
dead individuals at all stages relative to the total number of individuals reared. Thus, 
the mortality rate excluded only normal adults. In contrast, the abnormality rate 
reported here could be more accurately called the total abnormality rate. This rate was 
the percentage of dead individuals at the larval, prepupal, and pupal stages plus the 
adults that had morphological abnormalities relative to the total number of 
individuals reared. Thus, the abnormality rate excluded only normal adults that 
lacked any morphological abnormalities. Correlation analysis was performed using 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2013</rs>) and <rs id="software-2" type="software">JSTAT</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">13.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-date">2012</rs>) (Yokohama, Japan). </p>

<p>Mathematical modeling. We first used the built-in mathematical fit function of 
<rs id="software-3" type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-date">2013</rs>) to obtain the best-fit curves among available models. All 
possible models were examined including linear, exponential, logarithmic, 
polynomial, and power function models, and the best possible fit in terms of R 
2 values 
and biological justification was considered to be the most appropriate. Based on 
equations obtained in this way, we manually calculated the half lethal dose and the 
half abnormal dose by setting y 5 50(%). Additionally, linear and nonlinear models 
were examined using the model analysis software <rs id="software-4" type="software">JMP</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">11.0.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-date">2013</rs>) (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, 
Cary, NC, USA). We reasoned that the simplest mathematical equation with the 
highest R 
2 value, the lowest RMSE, or the lowest information criterion, such as AIC, 
BIC, and MDL, would be accepted. We examined linear models (including 
logarithmic scales for power function) and nonlinear models (including logarithmic, 
square root, quadratic, polynomial, logistic, and exponential equations). Among the 
model fits performed, logistic 4 P models also showed high R 
2 values (R 
2 5 0.9972 
and BIC 5 19.93 for mortality rate; R 
2 5 0.9997 and BIC 5 12.31 for abnormality 
rate) in addition to the power function models, but the complicated equations with 
relatively high BIC values discouraged the use of these equations for further analysis. 
The numerical values associated with the models and calculations are shown together 
with standard errors (SE) in the main text. </p>

<p>1. Hashimoto, S., Ugawa, S., Nanko, K. &amp; Shichi, K. The total amounts of 
radioactively contaminated materials in forests in Fukushima, Japan. Sci. Rep. 2, 
416 (2012). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4946 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04946 </p>



<p>
Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank J. Nohara (Tokyo), M. Hatta (Ube), J. Ishida (Okuma), N. Itou (Iitate), K. Yoshida 
(Minami-soma), and K. Nakanome (Minami-soma) for their help in collecting host plant 
leaves, and S. Gima (University of the Ryukyus) for technical help. This work was supported 
in part by the Grant for Environmental Research Projects from The Sumitomo Foundation, 
Tokyo, Japan, and by the Incentive Project from the University of the Ryukyus. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>J.M.O. designed and coordinated the study and performed mathematical modeling; C.N., 
A.H., W.T. and A.T. performed experiments; C.N., A.H., W.T., A.T. and J.M.O. analyzed 
data; and J.M.O. wrote the paper. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Nohara, C., Hiyama, A., Taira, W., Tanahara, A. &amp; Otaki, J.M. The 
biological impacts of ingested radioactive materials on the pale grass blue butterfly. Sci. Rep. 
4, 4946; DOI:10.1038/srep04946 (2014). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. The images in this article are included in the 
article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the image credit; 
if the image is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to 
obtain permission from the license holder in order to reproduce the image. To view a 
copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/ </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4946 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04946 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>