<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4871932" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Obesity has become an important global health concern, and 
the increasing rate of obesity among women of reproduc-
tive age has a significant impact on the outcomes of their 
pregnancies [1]. In 2012, 29.7% of Korean women &gt;18 years 
old had a body mass index (BMI) &gt;25 kg/m², and 21.9% of 
women of reproductive age (19 to 49 years old) were consid-
ered overweight [2]. Unfortunately, obesity during pregnancy 
is associated with adverse pregnancy outcomes, including </p>

<p>The risk of emergency cesarean section after failure 
of vaginal delivery according to prepregnancy body 
mass index or gestational weight gain by the 2009 
Institute of Medicine guidelines </p>

<p>Ha Yan Kwon </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, Ja-Young Kwon </p>

<p>2,3 </p>

<p>, Yong Won Park </p>

<p>2,3 </p>

<p>, Young-Han Kim </p>

<p>2,3 </p>

<p>1 Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Dongguk University Ilsan Hospital, Goyang; 
2 Institute of Women's Life Medical Science, Yonsei University 
College of Medicine, Seoul; </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Division of Maternal-Fetal Medicine, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Severance Hospital, Yonsei University College 
of Medicine, Seoul, Korea </p>

<p>Objective 
To evaluate the risk of emergency cesarean section according to the prepregnancy body mass index (BMI) and 
gestational weight gain per the 2009 Institute of Medicine guidelines. </p>

<p>Methods 
A retrospective analysis of data from 2,765 women with singleton full-term births (2009 to 2012) who attempted a vaginal 
delivery was conducted. Pregnancies with preeclampsia, chronic hypertension, diabetes, planned cesarean section, placenta previa, 
or cesarean section due to fetal anomalies or intrauterine growth restriction were excluded. Odds ratios (ORs) and confidence 
intervals (CIs) for emergency cesarean section were calculated after adjusting for prepregnancy BMI or gestational weight gain. </p>

<p>Results 
Three-hundred and fifty nine (13.0%) women underwent emergency cesarean section. The adjusted OR for overweight, 
obese, and extremely obese women indicated a significantly increased risk of cesarean delivery. Gestational weight gain 
by Institute of Medicine guidelines was not associated with an increased risk of cesarean delivery. However, inadequate 
and excessive weight gain in obese women was highly associated with an increased risk of emergency cesarean section, 
compared to these in normal BMI (OR, 5.56; 95% CI, 1.36 to 22.72; OR, 3.63; 95% CI, 1.05 to 12.54; respectively), while 
there was no significant difference between normal BMI and obese women with adequate weight gain. </p>

<p>Conclusion 
Obese women should be provided special advice before and during pregnancy for controlling weight and careful 
consideration should be needed at the time of vaginal delivery to avoid emergency cesarean section. </p>

<p>Keywords: Body mass index; Cesarean section; Emergency; Pregnancy; Weight gain </p>

<p>Articles published in Obstet Gynecol Sci are open-access, distributed under the terms of 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons. 
org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, 
and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016 Korean Society of Obstetrics and Gynecology </p>

<p>Received: 2015.7.21. Revised: 2015.12.7. Accepted: 2015.12.29. 
Corresponding author: Young-Han Kim 
Division of Maternal-Fetal Medicine, Department of Obstetrics and 
Gynecology, Severance Hospital, Yonsei University College of Medicine, 
50-1 Yonsei-ro, Seodaemun-gu, Seoul 03722, Korea 
Tel: +82-2-2228-2230 Fax: +82-2-313-8357 
E-mail: yhkim522@yuhs.ac 
http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0645-6028 </p>

<p>www.ogscience.org </p>

<p>
Vol. 59, No. 3, 2016 </p>

<p>miscarriage, preeclampsia, gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM), 
thrombophlebitis, congenital anomalies, macrosomia, pre-
term delivery, and an increased risk of cesarean section [3]. 
Compared to vaginal delivery, cesarean section is known to 
be associated with prolonged hospitalization, longer recovery 
time, increased risk of wound infection, and higher blood loss. 
In addition, cesarean deliveries that occur in critical situations 
(e.g., cephalopelvic disproportion or fetal distress) are at an 
increased risk of intraoperative complications, postoperative 
morbidity, and neonatal complications [4,5]. Excessive weight 
gain during pregnancy is also associated with complications 
that are related to maternal obesity and cesarean delivery 
[6]. Therefore, there is a need for more detailed knowledge 
regarding the impact elevated prepregnancy BMI and gesta-
tional weight gain on the outcomes that are associated with 
emergency cesarean section. Hence, the purpose of this study 
was to estimate the effect of obesity (using the World Health 
Organization criteria) and gestational weight gain (using the 
2009 Institute of Medicine [IOM] guidelines) on the risk of 
emergency cesarean section during labor. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>We retrospectively analyzed data from 2,765 pregnancies 
who delivered at the obstetrics and gynecology department 
of Severance Hospital in Korea between June 2009 and De-
cember 2012. The study was approved by the Ethics Commit-
tee of Yonsei University Health System. The inclusion criteria 
were singleton pregnancies with cephalic presentation, term 
pregnancies (≥37 gestational weeks), and women who began 
labor and initially attempted a vaginal delivery. Women with 
preeclampsia, eclampsia, chronic hypertension, diabetes, pla-
centa previa, planned cesarean section due to prior cesarean 
delivery and full-thickness myomectomy, or cesarean section 
due to fetal anomalies or intrauterine growth restriction de-
fined as a fetus whose estimated weight is below the 10th 
percentile for its gestational age, were excluded from our 
analysis. The included subjects were then grouped according 
to their vaginal delivery or emergency cesarean section after 
an attempted vaginal delivery. 
Prepregnancy body weight and height were reported at first 
visit, and we calculated the BMI as weight (kg)/height² (m²). 
BMI was considered a categorical variable, and subjects were 
grouped according to the World Health Organization cat-</p>

<p>egories: underweight (&lt;18.5 kg/m²), normal (18.5-24.9 kg/ 
m²), overweight (25.0-29.9 kg/m²), obese (30.0-34.9 kg/m²), 
and extremely obese (≥35.0 kg/m²) [7]. Weight gain during 
pregnancy was also categorized into three groups based on 
the 2009 revision of IOM gestational weight gain guidelines 
(adequate, excessive, and inadequate weight gain) [8]. Infants 
who were small for their gestational age (SGA) or large for 
their gestational age (LGA) were defined as those that were in 
the &lt;10% and &gt;90%, respectively, of the 1999 Korean birth 
weight percentiles [9]. Data regarding other variables (e.g., 
maternal age, gestational age at delivery, parity, birth weight, 
and neonatal information) were obtained from the subjects' 
medical records. 
The primary outcome for this study was the rate of emer-
gency cesarean section, which we compared across the 
prepregnancy BMI and gestational weight gain categories. 
The secondary outcome was the risk of emergency cesar-
ean section among the prepregnancy BMI and gestational 
weight gain categories. For an inter-group comparison of 
age, prepregnancy weight and BMI, gestational weight gain, 
gestational age at delivery and neonate birth weight, we used 
an independent t-test. For a comparison of parity, GDM, the 
incidence of LGA infants, each BMI status and each gesta-
tional weight gain status based on the 2009 IOM guidelines, 
a chi-square test was used. To evaluate the crude association 
between prepregnancy BMI or gestational weight gain and 
emergency cesarean section, logistic regression analysis was 
used to calculate the unadjusted odds ratios (ORs) and 95% 
confidence intervals (CIs). We also calculated the adjusted 
ORs after adjusting for potential confounding factors, includ-
ing maternal age, parity, gestational age at delivery, birth 
weight, labor induction, LGA, fetal sex, and GDM. Additional 
regression models included prepregnancy BMI and gestational 
weight gain with the other confounders to evaluate the inde-
pendent effect of prepregnancy BMI and gestational weight 
gain on the risk of emergency cesarean section. To further 
investigate the difference gestational weight gain-emergency 
cesarean section association stratified by maternal prepreg-
nancy BMI, we calculated the adjusted ORs after adjusting for 
confounders with gestational weight gain in each prepreg-
nancy BMI group. P-value of &lt;0.05 was considered statistically 
significant. All analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">IBM SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver.20.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corp.</rs>., Armonk, NY, USA). </p>

<p>www.ogscience.org </p>



<p>Ha Yan Kwon, et al. Obesity and emergency cesarean section </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Among the 2,765 women we analyzed, 2,406 (87.0%) had a 
vaginal delivery and 359 (13.0%) had an emergency cesarean 
section. The subjects' demographic characteristics are listed 
in Table 1. Women who underwent emergency cesarean sec-
tion had significantly greater prepregnancy weight and BMI 
(P=0.001 and P&lt;0.0001, respectively). Gestational weight 
gain was also significantly greater among women who un-
derwent an emergency cesarean section compared to those 
who experienced a vaginal delivery (13.4±4.9 vs. 12.8±4.1 
kg, P=0.018), although there was no significant differences 
between the two groups when the gestational weight gain 
categories were compared (P=0.36). 
The prevalence of nulliparity and GDM was higher in the 
emergency cesarean section group compared to those in 
the vaginal delivery group (88.0% vs. 54.2%, P&lt;0.0001 and 
10.5% vs. 4.6%, P&lt;0.0001, respectively). There were no other </p>

<p>significant differences between the two groups regarding any 
of the other demographic characteristics. 
Table 2 lists the neonatal characteristics for the study 
groups. There was significant differences in the birth weight 
when emergency cesarean section was compared to vaginal 
delivery (3,275.3±382.4 vs. 3,396.3±536.7 g, P=0.0001). In 
addition, the prevalence of LGA was higher in the emergency 
cesarean section group compared to that in the vaginal deliv-
ery group (21.5% vs. 8.3%, P&lt;0.0001). The incidences of a 
low neonatal Apgar score (&lt;7 at 5 minutes) and admission to 
the neonatal intensive care unit were higher in the emergency 
cesarean section group compared to those in vaginal delivery 
(3.6% vs. 1.6%, P=0.007 and 23.4% vs. 11.2%, P&lt;0.0001, 
respectively). The most common cause for an emergency 
cesarean section was cervical dilatation disorder such as a pro-
tracted of dilatation or arrest of dilatation (52.1%), followed 
by prolonged latent phase (31.2%), non-reassuring fetal heart 
rate pattern (9.8%), and arrest of descent (4.9%). Emergency </p>

<p>Table 1. The maternal characteristics of the study groups </p>

<p>Variable 
Vaginal delivery 
(n=2,406) </p>

<p>Emergency cesarean delivery 
(n=359) 
P-value </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
31.8±3.4 
32.2±3.8 
0.11 </p>

<p>Prepregnancy weight (kg) 
54.8±7.5 
56.6±9.9 
0.001 </p>

<p>Prepregnancy BMI (kg/m²) 
20.8±2.7 
22.0±3.8 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>Underweight (&lt;18.5) 
405 (16.8) 
48 (13.4) 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>Normal (18.5-24.9) 
1828 (76.0) 
244 (68.0) </p>

<p>Overweight (25.0-29.9) 
142 (5.9) 
51 (14.2) </p>

<p>Obese (30.0-34.9) 
28 (1.2) 
14 (3.9) </p>

<p>Extremely obese (≥35.0) 
3 (0.1) 
2 (0.6) </p>

<p>Nulliparous 
1,305 (54.2) 
316 (88.0) 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>Parity 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>1 
918 (38.2) 
40 (11.1) </p>

<p>2 
164 (6.8) 
1 (0.3) </p>

<p>≥3 
19 (0.8) 
2 (0.6) </p>

<p>Gestational weight gain (kg) 
12.8±4.1 
13.4±4.9 
0.018 </p>

<p>Inadequate </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>922 (38.3) 
133 (37.0) 
0.36 </p>

<p>Adequate </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>910 (37.8) 
131 (36.5) </p>

<p>Excessive </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>574 (23.9) 
95 (26.5) </p>

<p>GDM 
110 (4.6) 
36 (10.6) 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>Labor induction 
558 (23.2) 
94 (26.2) 
0.23 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation or number (%). 
BMI, body mass index; GDM, gestational diabetes mellitus. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>P-values are based on t-tests for continuous variables and on chi-square test for categorical variables; </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Gestational weight gain below Institute 
of Medicine (IOM) guidelines; </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>Gestational weight gain within IOM guidelines; </p>

<p>d) </p>

<p>Gestational weight gain above IOM guidelines. </p>

<p>www.ogscience.org </p>

<p>
Vol. 59, No. 3, 2016 </p>

<p>cesarean section was more frequent among overweight and 
obese women, compared to among those of normal weight, 
and the risk of emergency cesarean section increased with 
increasing prepregnancy BMI (Fig. 1). Women with excessive 
gestational weight gain were likely to undergo emergency 
cesarean section, compared with women with inadequate or 
normal weight gain, although there were no significant differ-
ences among the gestational weight gain categories (Fig. 2). 
However, women with gestational weight gain of ≥18 kg had 
a significantly increased risk of cesarean section, compared </p>

<p>with women with gestational weight gain &lt;18 kg (Fig. 3). 
Table 3 lists the risk of emergency cesarean section accord-
ing to obesity and gestational weight gain, before and after 
adjusting for the various confounders. Overweight, obese, 
and extremely obese women had a significantly increased 
risk of emergency cesarean delivery, and this increased risk 
was still observed after adjusting for maternal age, parity, 
gestational age at delivery, GDM, birth weight, and sex. In 
particular, extremely obese women had the greatest risk of 
cesarean section (OR, 5.00; 95% CI, 0.83 to 30.04), and this </p>

<p>Table 2. The neonatal characteristics of the study groups </p>

<p>Variable 
Vaginal delivery 
(n=2,406) </p>

<p>Emergency cesarean delivery 
(n=359) 
P-value </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Gestational age at delivery (wk) 
39.5±1.0 
39.4±1.1 
0.11 </p>

<p>Sex 
0.15 </p>

<p>Male 
1,262 (52.5) 
203 (56.5) </p>

<p>Female 
1,144 (47.5) 
156 (43.5) </p>

<p>Birth weight (g) 
3,275.3±382.4 
3,396.3±536.7 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>SGA 
244 (10.1) 
40 (11.2) 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>AGA 
1,962 (81.5) 
241 (67.3) </p>

<p>LGA 
200 (8.3) 
77 (21.5) </p>

<p>NICU admission 
270 (11.2) 
84 (23.4) 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>Apgar score &lt;7 at 5 min 
38 (1.6) 
13 (3.6) 
0.007 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation or number (%). 
SGA, small for gestational age; AGA, appropriate for gestational age; LGA, large for gestational age; NICU, neonatal intensive care unit. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Based on t-tests for continuous variables and on chi-square test for categorical variables. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. The percentage of women who had a emergency cesarean 
section, stratified according to gestational weight gain ≥18 and 
&lt;18 kg (emergency cesarean section vs. vaginal delivery): &lt;18 kg 
(12.3 vs. 87.7), ≥18 kg (17.8 vs. 82.2). The women with weight 
gain ≥18 kg had a significantly increased risk of emergency cesar-
ean section (P=0.005). BMI, body mass index. </p>

<p>Percentage (%) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>T o t a l </p>

<p>U n d e r w </p>

<p>e i g h t 
N o r m </p>

<p>a l </p>

<p>U n d e r w </p>

<p>e i g h t 
O b e s e I 
O b e s e I I </p>

<p>Prepregnancy BMI group </p>

<p>Emergency 
cesarean 
section </p>

<p>Vaginal 
delivery </p>

<p>Fig. 2. The percentage of women who had emergency cesarean 
section, stratified according to gestational weight gain (emergency 
cesarean section vs. vaginal delivery): total (13 vs. 87), inadequate 
(12.6 vs. 87.4), adequate (12.6 vs. 87.4), excessive (14.2 vs. 85.8). 
The risk of emergency cesarean section had no significant differ-
ences between each groups (P=0.36). IOM, Institute of Medicine. </p>

<p>Percentage (%) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>T o t a l </p>

<p>I n a d e q u a t e 
A d e q u a t e 
E x c e s s i v e </p>

<p>Gestational weight gain group by IOM guideline </p>

<p>Emergency 
cesarean section </p>

<p>Vaginal delivery </p>

<p>www.ogscience.org </p>



<p>Ha Yan Kwon, et al. Obesity and emergency cesarean section </p>

<p>risk increased after adjusting for the confounders (adjusted 
OR, 12.66; 95% CI, 1.14 to 140.66). Women who were 
overweight, obese, and extremely obese also had a signifi-
cantly increased risk of emergency cesarean section, indepen-
dent of their gestational weight gain (OR, 2.51; 95% CI, 1.68 
to 3.73; OR, 2.50; 95% CI, 1.17 to 5.35; OR, 12.43; 95% CI, 
1.11 to 138.68; respectively). In contrast, there was no sig-
nificant interaction between emergency cesarean section and 
gestational weight gain categories. Women with inadequate 
and excessive gestational weight gain had a similar risk of 
emergency cesarean section, after adjusting for the con-
founding factors (OR, 0.94; 95% CI, 0.71 to 1.24; OR, 1.01; 
95% CI, 0.74 to 1.38; respectively). However, when adjusted 
gestational weight gain-emergency cesarean section associa-
tion stratified by prepregnancy BMI was different. Among 
women with inadequate gestational weight gain, overweight </p>

<p>Table 3. ORs for emergency cesarean delivery versus vaginal delivery according to prepregnancy body mass index and gestational weight 
gain </p>

<p>Variable 
Crude OR (95% CI) 
Adjusted OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Model 1 </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Model 2 </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Prepregnancy BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Underweight (&lt;18.5) 
0.89 (0.64-1.23) 
0.88 (0.62-1.24) 
0.88 (0.62-1.24) </p>

<p>Normal (18.5-24.9) 
Reference value 
Reference value 
Reference value </p>

<p>Overweight (25.0-29.9) 
2.69 (1.90-3.81) 
2.51 (1.69-3.74) 
2.51 (1.68-3.73) </p>

<p>Obese I (30.0-34.9) 
3.74 (1.95-7.21) 
2.51 (1.17-5.38) 
2.50 (1.17-5.35) </p>

<p>Obese II (≥35.0) 
5.00 (0.83-30.04) 
12.66 (1.14-140.66) 
12.43 (1.11-138.68) </p>

<p>Gestational weight gain </p>

<p>Inadequate (below IOM guidelines) 
1.00 (0.77-1.30) 
0.93 (0.71-1.24) 
0.94 (0.71-1.24) </p>

<p>Adequate (within IOM guidelines) 
Reference value 
Reference value 
Reference value </p>

<p>Excessive (above IOM guidelines) 
1.15 (0.87-1.53) 
1.06 (0.78-1.44) 
1.01 (0.74-1.38) </p>

<p>OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval; BMI, body mass index; IOM, Institute of Medicine. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Adjusted for maternal age, gestational age at delivery, parity, gestational diabetes mellitus, labor induction, birth weight, neonate for large 
gestational age and gender; </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Adjusted for prepregnancy BMI and gestational weight gain, according to the 2009 IOM guidelines. </p>

<p>Table 4. Adjusted odds ratios and 95% confidence intervals for the risk of emergency cesarean delivery due to gestational weight gain, 
stratified according to prepregnancy body mass index </p>

<p>Gestational weight 
gain </p>

<p>Underweight 
(n=453, 16.4%) </p>

<p>Normal 
(n=2,072, 74.9%) </p>

<p>Overweight 
(n=193, 7.0%) </p>

<p>Obese 
(n=47, 1.7%) </p>

<p>Inadequate </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>0.72 (0.40-1.31) 
Reference value 
3.34 (1.73-6.47) 
5.56 (1.36-22.72) </p>

<p>Adequate </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>1.04 (0.62-1.74) 
Reference value 
2.56 (1.29-5.10) 
1.15 (0.24-5.60) </p>

<p>Excessive </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>0.83 (0.39-1.80) 
Reference value 
1.76 (0.84-3.68) 
3.63 (1.05-12.54) </p>

<p>Adjusted for maternal age, gestational age at delivery, parity, gestational diabetes mellitus, labor induction, birth weight, gender, and weight gain. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Gestational weight gain below Institute of Medicine (IOM) guidelines; </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>Gestational weight gain within IOM guidelines; </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>Gestational weight 
gain above IOM guidelines. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. The percentage of women who had a emergency cesarean 
section, stratified according to gestational weight gain ≥18 and 
&lt;18 kg (emergency cesarean section vs. vaginal delivery): &lt;18 kg 
(12.3 vs. 87.7), ≥18 kg (17.8 vs. 82.2). The women with weight 
gain ≥18 kg had a significantly increased risk of emergency cesar-
ean section (P=0.005). </p>

<p>Percentage (%) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
&lt;18 
≥18 </p>

<p>Gestational weight gain (kg) </p>

<p>Emergency 
cesarean section </p>

<p>Vaginal delivery </p>

<p>www.ogscience.org </p>

<p>
Vol. 59, No. 3, 2016 </p>

<p>or obese women were related with increased risk of emer-
gency cesarean section, compared to normal BMI women 
(Table 4). A similar result was observed among women with 
excessive gestational weight gain; OR of emergency cesarean 
section in obese women was 3.63 (1.05 to 12.54), compared 
to these with normal BMIs. Among obese women stratified 
by gestational weight gain, the risk of emergency cesarean 
section tend to increased 7.2-fold among women with inad-
equate weight gain and 5.7-fold among women with exces-
sive weight gain, compared to women with adequate weight 
gain, although these were not statistically significant differ-
ence (OR, 7.28; 95% CI, 0.56 to 61.53; OR, 5.70; 95% CI, 0.69 
to 46.81; respectively). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Cesarean section is known to be associated with an increased 
risk of adverse maternal and neonatal outcomes, and several 
factors (e.g., low and high birth weight, advanced maternal 
age, high prepregnancy BMI, excessive gestational weight 
gain, and &gt;40 weeks of gestation) are known to increase the 
risk of emergency cesarean section [5]. However, as prepreg-
nancy BMI, gestational weight gain, and maternal weight at 
delivery may be controlled by the mother, they are important 
factors for reducing the prevalence of emergency cesarean 
section and the related complications. 
Our results indicate that overweight and obese women, 
particularly those with extreme obesity, have a considerably 
increased risk of failed labor and emergency cesarean section 
compared to women of normal weight. This result remained 
significant even after we adjusted for maternal age, parity, 
GDM, gestational age at delivery, birth weight, and sex. In 
addition, prepregnancy BMI and emergency cesarean section 
were significantly associated after adjusting for gestational 
weight gain and the other confounders. Although women 
with excessive gestational weight gain were likely to undergo 
emergency cesarean section, inadequate or excessive ges-
tational weight gain did not appear to significant affect the 
increased rates of emergency cesarean delivery (compared 
to those among women with adequate gestational weight 
gain). 
Our results are consistent with those of previous studies, 
such as that by Crane et al. [10], who reported that the risk 
of cesarean section increased 1.6-fold among women who </p>

<p>were obese before pregnancy, compared to that among 
women who were not obese before pregnancy. Similar re-
sults have been reported by Kerrigan and Kingdon [11], who 
observed a significantly higher rate of emergency cesarean 
delivery among obese women (16.7%), compared to that 
among non-obese women (10.9%) (P&lt;0.001). Similarly, 
Wolfe et al. [12] have compared the rates of failed induc-
tion of labor (defined as delivery by cesarean delivery after 
an attempted induction) among obese and normal-weight 
women. They reported that failed induction followed by 
cesarean delivery was more common among obese women 
compared to among normal-weight women, and that the 
risk of cesarean delivery increased with increasing BMI. There 
are two possible explanations for this phenomenon. First, a 
relatively narrow pelvis (due to the mechanical pressure of 
the adipose tissue within the abdomen and pelvis) combined 
with a relatively large fetus could disturb the descent of the 
fetus, leading to cephalopelvic disproportion and prolong-
ing the second stage of labor, thereby necessitating cesarean 
delivery. Second, it is possible that obese women experience 
inefficient uterine contractions, due to the release of inflam-
matory mediators from their abdominal and pelvic adipose 
tissue, as weak contractility can lead to labor arrest [10,13,14]. 
In our study, the major causes of emergency cesarean delivery 
were cervical dilatation disorder, prolonged latent phase, and 
arrest of descent, which would appear to support the theory. 
Few studies have evaluated whether gestational weight 
gain, combined with prepregnancy BMI, is associated with 
cesarean section. Morken et al. [13] reported that women 
with gestational weight gain of ≥16 kg had a significantly 
increased risk of cesarean section. In contrast, we found 
that women with gestational weight gain above the IOM 
recommendations were not at a significantly increased risk 
of emergency cesarean section. This discrepancy may be ex-
plained by the fact that Morken et al. [13] used gestational 
weight gain categories based on weight alone (&lt;8, 8-16, 
and &lt;16 kg), while we categorized gestational weight gain 
according to the 2009 IOM guidelines. Similar to our results, 
Tanaka et al. [15] reported that gestational weight gain ac-
cording to the IOM guidelines did not significantly influence 
to the rate of emergency cesarean delivery among Japanese 
women. Interestingly, Jang et al. [16] evaluated the effects 
of prepregnancy BMI and gestational weight gain based on 
the IOM guidelines on the risk of emergency cesarean de-
livery among 1,024 nulliparous women, and reported that </p>

<p>www.ogscience.org </p>



<p>Ha Yan Kwon, et al. Obesity and emergency cesarean section </p>

<p>although the frequency of cesarean delivery was significantly 
increased among women with gestational weight gain &gt;18 
kg, gestational weight gain above IOM guidelines did not 
independently affect the frequency of emergency cesarean 
delivery. These results suggest that inappropriate gestational 
weight gain based on IOM guideline is less associated with 
the risk of emergency cesarean section, and that the absolute 
degree of gestational weight gain regardless of prepregnancy 
BMI affects the risk of emergency cesarean delivery more 
than the relative degree of gestational weight gain stratified 
by prepregnancy BMI. 
In addition, prepregnancy BMI was increased, as was the 
risk of emergency cesarean section among our subjects with 
inadequate and excessive gestational weight gain, compared 
those with normal BMI. Particularly, even though obese wom-
en had gestation weight gain below IOM guidelines, they 
had a higher risk of emergency cesarean section. Similar to 
our study, Graham et al. [3] reported that obese women with 
low maternal weight gain had nearly a three-fold increased 
odds of cesarean delivery (OR, 2.58; 95% CI, 1.71 to 3.37). Li 
et al. [17] also reported that low gestational weight gain was 
associated with moderate-to-strong evidence of increased 
risk of cesarean section (OR, 1.6; 95% CI, 1.4 to 1.7). These 
suggest that prepregnancy obesity is highly associated with 
the risk of emergency cesarean section rather than gestation-
al weight gain. In subgroup analysis among obese women 
stratified by gestational weight gain, the risk of emergency 
cesarean section tend to increased, compared to women 
with adequate weight gain, however these results were not 
statistically significant difference. In our study, obese women 
who had undergone emergency cesarean section was too 
small to calculate the OR and 95% CI, so the results may 
undergo profound impact by confounders. Actually, the rate 
of GDM women or LGA infants was higher in women with 
inadequate weight gain compared to those with adequate 
weight gain, although there were no significant differences 
among study groups. Fetal distress was also more common in 
women who had gestational weight gain below IOM guide-
lines. These results suggest that the mechanisms by which 
obesity increases the risk of cesarean section are not simply 
based on excess weight gain, but it could be related various 
types of complication due to maternal obesity such as GDM 
or preeclampsia. Obesity causes practical difficulties including 
inaccuracies of abdominal palpation of the pregnant abdo-
men to assess the growth, lie, or presentation of the fetus, </p>

<p>potential errors in sonographic prenatal diagnosis and errors 
in blood pressure measurement. Maternal obesity also has 
been associated with fetal distress and an increased risk of 
fetal meconium aspiration and has been reported to more 
than double the risk of stillbirth and neonatal death [18-20]. 
Therefore, it is important to appropriate weight gain in obese 
women regarding suspected complications and further study 
is needed to investigate the difference gestational weight 
gain-emergency cesarean section association stratified by 
maternal prepregnancy BMI. 
A significant strength of our study was the large popula-
tion-based sample of pregnant women who attempted vagi-
nal delivery. In addition, we excluded women with chronic 
hypertension, preeclampsia, diabetes, intrauterine growth 
restriction, and women who required cesarean delivery due 
to maternal or fetal conditions, thereby reducing the poten-
tial for bias. In addition, all women were screened for gesta-
tional diabetes, and our analyses were adjusted for potential 
confounding factors to evaluate the independent effects of 
prepregnancy BMI and gestational weight gain. 
Despite these strengths, the study has several limitations. For 
example, we used a self-reported prepregnancy weight and 
the study groups consisted of predominantly Korean women. 
In our study, only 8.6% of the population was overweight 
or obese, which is significantly lower than the prevalence in 
developed countries and the rate of women with excessive 
gestational weight gain was relatively low, compared to that 
in previous other studies [21]. This may be due to differences 
in Asian versus Western populations. Thus, the relevance of 
our findings may be limited to similar Asian populations, and 
it may be difficult to generalize our results to Western popula-
tions. 
The global incidence of cesarean delivery is increasing, al-
though cesarean delivery is considered a safe procedure in 
developed countries. However, the prevalence of emergency 
cesarean section should be reduced, as it is associated with 
adverse effects, including bladder injury, longer recovery 
times, increased blood loss, postpartum hemorrhage, in-
creased risk of infection, and higher medical costs. In ad-
dition, primary cesarean section is a major cause of repeat 
cesarean delivery. Therefore, it is important to identify the 
risk factors for emergency cesarean delivery, thereby reduc-
ing its incidence. In this study, women who were overweight 
or obese prepregnancy had an increased risk of emergency 
cesarean section compared to women with normal prepreg-</p>

<p>www.ogscience.org </p>

<p>
Vol. 59, No. 3, 2016 </p>

<p>nancy BMI. In addition, although there was no association 
between gestational weight gain (based on the 2009 revised 
IOM guidelines) and the risk of emergency cesarean delivery, 
obese women with inappropriate gestational weight gain 
could have a high risk of emergency cesarean section com-
bined with other complications due to maternal obesity, such 
as GDM or fetal distress. Therefore, overweight and obese 
women should be advised to modify their lifestyle (e.g., diet 
and exercise) to achieve and maintain a normal body weight 
before and during pregnancy, as this may increase their 
chance of a successful vaginal delivery. Furthermore, obese 
women should be counseled suspected complication regard-
ing appropriate gestational weight gain, as it may affect their 
mode of delivery. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was 
reported. </p>



<p>www.ogscience.org </p>





</text></tei>