<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4807949" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:43+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Phospholipase C, β1 (PLCB1) plays critical roles in intracellular transduction 
and regulating signal activation which are important to tumorigenesis. However, the mechanism 
of PLCB1 in hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is still unknown. This study aims to investigate 
whether its expression is associated with the clinicopathological parameters and prognosis of 
the patients with HCC. 
Methods: Immunohistochemistry on two tissue microarrays containing 141 cases of HCC 
tissues and adjacent non-tumorous tissues were performed to analyze the correlation between 
PLCB1 expression and clinicopathological features. Kaplan-Meier analysis and Cox multivariate 
analysis were performed to determine the PLCB1 expression in HCC prognosis. Furthermore, 
effects of PLCB1 on proliferation of HCC cells were explored using a colony formation assay 
and apoptosis assay. 
Results: We identified that PLCB1 expression was significantly higher in tumor tissues than 
that in adjacent non-tumorous tissues and associated with advanced tumor stage. Kaplan-Meier 
survival analysis showed that patients with PLCB1-positive tumors had poorer survival than 
the patients with PLCB1-negative tumors. In multivariate analyses, PLCB1 expression was an 
independent prognostic factor. Moreover, overexpression of PLCB1 in HCC cells promoted 
cell proliferation and inhibited apoptosis, while knocking down PLCB1 reduced cell viability 
in vitro. Further investigation found that activation of ERK signaling might involve in PLCB1-
mediated cell growth. 
Conclusion: Our study suggests that PLCB1 promotes the progression of HCC and can be 
served as an independent prognostic factor and a promising therapeutic target in HCC. 
Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is one of the leading cause of cancer-related death 
and the fifth most common malignancy worldwide. Despite the facts that current clini-
cal treatments such as hepatectomy and liver transplantation have made significant 
achievements for combating this disease, the long-term prognosis of HCC remains 
unfavorable, and the 5-year survival rate was approximately 12% due to the tumor 
aggressive metastasis and recurrence. 
1,2 Studies on revealing the mechanisms underly-
ing HCC progression have found important oncogenes and pathways which promoted 
tumor development. 
3 However, HCC is a systemic disease, which involves alternations 
of genes, cells, and tissues which are all deregulated. Thus, aiming to improve the 
outcome of the patients with HCC, it is necessary to identify novel molecular targets, 
which play key regulatory roles in tumor cell proliferation and metastasis. </p>

<p>correspondence: Kaijian luo 
guiZhou cancer hospital, cancer 
hospital of guizhou Medical University, 
no 1 West Beijing road, guiyang 
550004, People's republic of china 
Tel +86 851 681 2999 
email drkjluo@sina.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
21 March 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1698 </p>

<p>li et al </p>

<p>Phospholipase C, β1 (PLCB1) is encoded by the PLCB1 
gene which is located at chromosome 20p12. It is originally 
identified as a member of GPCR (G-protein-coupled receptor)-
associated PLC-β isoforms that catalyze the formation of 
inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate (IP3) and diacylglycerol (DAG) 
from phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate (PIP2). 
4 This reac-
tion plays an important role in the intracellular transduction. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Deregulation of signal transduction pathways frequently elicits 
survival advantages to tumors. The PLCB1 is activated by Gα 
and triggers a series of events, which lead to an increase in 
intracellular calcium. 
6 One consequence involved of this acti-
vation would be aberrant proliferative changes in the cell. 
The PLCB1 has reported to be involved in several kinds 
of disease. Abnormal expression pattern of PLCB1 was 
observed in the brains of the patients with schizophrenia. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>The PLCB1 knockout mice displayed behaviors relevant to 
the cognitive symptoms of schizophrenia. 
8 The PLCB1 also 
acts as a key regulator in myoblast differentiation, func-
tioning as a positive regulator in the correction of delayed 
differentiation of skeletal muscle in myotonic dystrophy 
myoblasts. 
9 In addition, PLCB1 could reduce cell damage 
under oxidative stress and prevent α-synuclein aggregation. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>It has demonstrated that amplification of PLCB1 conferred a 
real advantage to K562 cell viability and protected cells from 
apoptosis. 
11,12 In addition, PLCB1 positively targets cyclin 
D3 and regulates cell cycle and cell proliferation through 
PKCα-mediated pathways. 
13 Overexpression of PLCB1 is 
found to be sufficient to drive Swiss 3T3 cell in S phase of 
the cell cycle. 
14 More importantly, elevated level of PLCB1 
in carcinogenesis has also been recently reported. 
15 Molinari 
et al 
16 demonstrated that PLCB1 gene copy number altered in 
breast cancer and the overexpression of PLCB1 was associ-
ated with histological grade and proliferative index. 
In this study, we showed that the expression of PLCB1 
was elevated in HCC samples. Then, we analyzed the cor-
relation between PLCB1 expression and clinicopathological 
parameters, aiming to investigate the role of PLCB1 in 
carcinogenesis and prognosis. Exogenous expression of 
PLCB1 in HCC cells promoted cell growth and migration, 
while knocking down PLCB1 retarded the cell proliferation. 
Furthermore, ERK signal was involved in PLCB1-mediated 
cell growth. Taken together, we found that PLCB1 could act 
as a prognostic factor in HCC. </p>

<p>Patients and methods 
cell culture </p>

<p>HEK293T cells, human immortalized hepatic cell line LO2 
and HCC cell lines HepG2, Hep3B, LM3, Huh7, and H7402 
were purchased from Cell Bank at the Chinese Academy of </p>

<p>Sciences and American Type Culture Collection (ATCC). 
Cells were cultured in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium 
(Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) supple-
mented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS, Thermo Fisher 
Scientific), 10 U/mL penicillin, and 10 mg/mL streptomycin. 
All cells were incubated at 37°C in a humidified incubator 
containing 5% CO 2 . </p>

<p>immunohistochemical staining </p>

<p>Two tissue microarrays (TMAs) were used to analyze the 
expression of PLCB1. The study was approved by the Ethical 
Review Committee of the GuiZhou Cancer Hospital. The 
informed consent was provided and all the patients agreed 
with this study. The TMA1 and TMA2, which contained 
51 cases and 90 cases of paired tumors and non-tumorous 
tissues, respectively were purchased from Shanghai Outdo 
Biotech Inc (Shanghai, People's Republic of China). The 
microarrays were deparaffinized in xylene and rehydrated 
through graded alcohol. After antigen recovery in citrate 
buffer and neutralization of endogenous peroxidase, slides 
were blocked with 10% goat serum to decrease nonspecific 
staining. Then tissues sections were incubated with anti-
PLCB1 antibody (1:200, sc-205, Santa Cruz Biotechnology 
Inc., Dallas, TX, USA) at 4°C overnight. After washing in 
phosphate buffered saline (PBS), the slides were performed 
by horseradish peroxidase-labeled second antibody for 
30 minutes and again washed in PBS. The sections were 
then visualized using diaminobenzidine solution and coun-
terstained with hematoxylin. 
Each slide was evaluated using a semi-quantitative score 
system for both the intensity and the percentage of positive 
staining. Briefly, the intensity of staining was scored as: 0, 
1, 2, 3 and the percentage was scored as: 0, 1, 2, 3. Then, the 
final score was calculated by multiplying the two scores and 
classified them into two groups which were low expression 
and high expression as described earlier. </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time Pcr </p>

<p>Total RNA was isolated from cells using TRIzol reagent 
(Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) as the 
manufacture's recommendation. First-strand cDNA was 
synthesized using PrimeScript RT-PCR kit (Takara). The 
mRNA level of PLCB1 was detected using ABI 7500 
Sequence Detection system with SYBR Green methods. 
β-Actin was used as the internal control. The primer pair used 
for amplification of the human PLCB1 gene was as follows: 
forward primer, 5′-GATGAGCCCAGATGGCCG-3′, and 
reverse primer, 5′-AGTTGAGTCATCATCCCACTTGA-3′. 
The primers for β-actin were as followed: forward primer, </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1699 </p>

<p>Up-regulated expression of phospholipase c, β1 </p>

<p>5′-CATGTACGTTGCTATCCAGGC-3′, and reverse primer, 
5′-CTCCTTAATGTCACGCACGAT-3′. </p>

<p>Western blot </p>

<p>Cells were lysed in radioimmunoprecipitation assay (RIPA) 
buffer (Sigma, Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA) con-
taining a cocktail of proteinase inhibitors and phosphatase 
inhibitors according to the manufacture's recommendation. 
The total protein concentration was determined by bicin-
choninic acid method. A total of 60 µg of total protein was 
separated in 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide 
gel electropheresis. Then proteins were transferred to poly-
vinylidene fluoride membranes (Millipore). The membranes 
were blocked with fat-free milk and incubated with primary 
antibodies overnight. After washing with tris buffer saline 
Tween 20, the membranes were incubated with horserad-
ish peroxidase-labeled secondary antibody and visualized 
by enhanced chemiluminescence. Anti-phospho-ERK1/2 
(#4376), anti-ERK1/2 (#9102) were from Cell Signaling 
Technology Co (CST). Anti-PLCB1, anti-dual specificity 
phosphatase 1(DUSP1) (sc-370), and anti-β-actin (sc-47778) 
were from Santa Cruz Co (Santa Cruz Biotechnology). </p>

<p>Overexpression and rnai-mediated 
knockdown of PlcB1 </p>

<p>The PLCB1 cDNA was cloned into lentiviral vector pLKO.1 
TRC. psPAX2 and pMD2G were used to construct recom-
binant lentivirus to establish the cell lines with stable over-
expression of PLCB1. The short hairpin RNAs (shRNAs) 
targeting PLCB1 were obtained from Santa Cruz Co (Santa 
Cruz Biotechnology). A scrambled sequence was used 
as a control. Cell transfection was performed using the 
lipofectamine 2000 reagent (Thermo Fisher Scientific) as 
protocol described. </p>

<p>cell viability and caspase-3/7 activity assay </p>

<p>For analyzing the viability of these kinds of cells, 2×10 
3 cells/ 
well were seeded in 96-well plates. Cell Counting Kit-8 
(CCK-8, Dojindo, Shanghai, People's Republic of China) 
was used to evaluate the cell viability following the manufac-
turer's protocols at 24, 48, 72, and 96 hours. The absorbance 
was measured at 450 nm. The caspase-3/7 activity assay was 
performed at 72 hours under serum deprivation according 
to the protocol. All the experiments were repeated at least 
three times. </p>

<p>colony formation assay </p>

<p>Cells were seeded into 6-well plates (2×10 
4 cells/well) and 
incubated for 10 days to form colonies. At the indicated time </p>

<p>point, cells were washed twice with PBS, treated with crystal 
violet for 10 minutes, washed, then counted, and measured. 
All the experiments were performed at least three times. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data were presented as the mean ± standard error of the mean 
(SEM) of three independent in vitro experiments. Statistical 
analysis and graphical representations were performed with 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">21.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>, Armonk, NY, USA) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">Graph-
Pad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">5</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">GraphPad Software, Inc.</rs>., La Jolla, CA, 
USA). The relations between clinical features and the PLCB1 
expression were analyzed using chi-squared test and in vitro 
studies were evaluated with the Student's t-test. The Kaplan-
Meier method was used to estimate overall survival (OS) and 
Cox regression model was applied to calculate univariate and 
multivariate hazard ratios for the study variables. A P-value 
less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results 
Up-regulated expression of PlcB1 
indicates a poor prognosis in hcc </p>

<p>To explore the expression pattern of PLCB1 in HCC, two 
different TMAs were analyzed using immunohistochemical 
staining. The PLCB1 protein was detected both in the cyto-
plasm and nuclear of the HCC specimens. Indeed, PLCB1 
was significantly overexpressed in HCC tissues than that 
in the adjacent non-tumorous tissues (Figure 1A and B). 
Moreover, the mRNA level of PLCB1 was notably elevated 
in liver cancer tissues of GSE14520 containing 221-patient 
cohort according from the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) 
(http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo) (Figure 1C). 
Among the 141 HCC specimens, a high expression of 
PLCB1 was detected in 80 samples (56.73%). The relation-
ship between PLCB1 protein expression and clinicopatholog-
ical features of HCC was analyzed (Table 1). The expression 
of PLCB1 correlated with T stage (P=0.0145), while no 
significant relationship with other features was found. 
To further assess the possible association between HCC 
PLCB1 expression and patient survival, Kaplan-Meier curves 
with a log-rank test for OS were performed in 141 cases. As 
shown in Figure 1D, the patients with positive tumor PLCB1 
expression had a lower OS rate than the patients with negative 
PLCB1 expression. The estimated mean OS time was signifi-
cantly different between the patients with PLCB1-positive and 
PLCB1-negative tumors (P=0.001). These results indicated 
that PLCB1 expression is significantly related to the OS. 
Cox regression analysis was undertaken to analyze the 
prognostic factors for the 141 patients with HCC. Using a 
univariate analysis, OS was significantly associated with </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1700 </p>

<p>li et al </p>

<p>β </p>

<p>Figure 1 PlcB1 is overexpressed in hcc tissues and indicates a poor prognosis. 
Notes: (A) Representative images of the PLCB1 expression in paired adjacent non-tumorous tissues and HCC tissues (magnification, </p>

<p>×200). (B) immunohistochemical analysis of PlcB1 expression in two tissue microarrays. (C) Data </p>

<p>from geO database indicated the relative mrna levels in hcc samples. (D) Kaplan-Meier analysis for HCC 141 patients according to high and low PLCB1 expression. Log-rank regression was used to test the significance. The mRNA 
levels (E) and protein levels (F) of PlcB1 in immortalized hepatic cell line (lO2) and hcc cell lines (h7402, hepg2, hep3B, lM3, huh7). Data were representative as the mean </p>

<p>± seM of triplicated independent experiments. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: geO, gene expression Omnibus; hcc, hepatocellular carcinoma; PlcB1, phospholipase c, </p>

<p>β1; seM, standard error of the mean; n, non-tumorous tissues; T, tumor tissues. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1701 </p>

<p>Up-regulated expression of phospholipase c, β1 </p>

<p>tumor differentiation, tumor size, T stage, and PLCB1 
expression. Multivariate analysis demonstrated that posi-
tive PLCB1 expression remained a significant independent 
prognostic factor for HCC survival (Table 2). </p>

<p>PlcB1 promotes cell proliferation and 
inhibits cell apoptosis </p>

<p>To further investigate the function of PLCB1 in HCC cells, 
PLCB1 expression in HCC cell lines was examined by qRT-
PCR and Western blot, and the results showed that mRNA </p>

<p>(Figure 1E) and protein (Figure 1F) expression levels of 
PLCB1 were higher in the HCC cell lines than the immor-
talized liver cell LO2. Then we constructed PLCB1 stably 
overexpressed HepG2 and Huh7 cells using lentivirus infec-
tion. The exogenous of PLCB1 was confirmed using Western 
blot (Figure 2A). For CCK-8 assay, the results indicated that 
overexpression of PLCB1 exhibited markedly increased cell 
viability in relation to the control cells (Figure 2B). Consistent 
with the CCK-8 assay, we performed the colony formation 
assay, and the crystal violet staining showed that upregulation 
of PLCB1 in HepG2 and Huh7 cells significantly increased 
their growth compared with control cells (Figure 2C). 
Moreover, the apoptosis assay was undertaken when cells 
were starved for 72 hours. The data showed that caspase-
3/7 activity, which was an index of apoptosis, was notably 
reduced after PLCB1 overexpressed (Figure 2D). Collec-
tively, these results suggested that PLCB1 overexpression 
could promote cell growth and inhibit apoptosis. 
To further confirm the biofunction of PLCB1, we 
knocked down the endogenously expressed PLCB1 via 
lentivirus-delivered shRNA (sh-1 and sh-2). As shown in 
Figure 3A, both of the PLCB1-targeting shRNAs decreased 
the expression of PLCB1 in Hep3B and LM3 effectively 
compared to control shRNA (shcon). In the in vitro cell 
viability and colony formation assays, it was observed that 
downregulation of PLCB1 significantly abrogated cell prolif-
eration (Figure 3B and C). In addition, caspase-3/7 activities 
of knocked down cells were also higher than control cells 
(Figure 3D). Taken together, downregulation of PLCB1 
inhibited the malignant phenotypes of HCC cells. </p>

<p>erK signaling activation involves in the 
oncogenic properties of PlcB1 </p>

<p>In HCC, the mechanism of PLCB1 function remains 
unknown. The ERK signaling is a critical survival signal and </p>

<p>Table 1 correlation between PlcB1 expression and 
clinicopathologic parameters of hcc </p>

<p>Parameters 
Case 
number </p>

<p>PLCB1 
expression </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Low High </p>

<p>Overall 
141 
61 
80 
sex 
Male 
126 
54 
72 
0.079 0.778 
Female 
15 
7 
8 
age (years) 
,60 
108 
46 
62 
0.084 0.771 </p>

<p>$60 
33 
15 
18 
Tumor size (cm) 
,5 
77 
37 
40 
1.585 0.208 </p>

<p>$5 
64 
24 
40 
cirrhosis 
Yes 
89 
38 
51 
0.031 0.859 
no 
52 
23 
29 
Tumor differentiation 
Well 
16 
7 
9 
1.873 0.392 
Moderate 
102 
47 
55 
Poor 
23 
7 
16 
clinical stage (T stage) 
i 
22 
15 
7 
6.69 
0.0352* 
ii 
47 
19 
28 
iii+iV 
72 
27 
45 </p>

<p>Note: *P,0.05. 
Abbreviations: hcc, hepatocellular carcinoma; PlcB1, phospholipase c, β1. </p>

<p>Table 2 Univariate and multivariate analysis for overall survival (cox regression analysis) </p>

<p>Parameters 
Univariate analysis 
Multivariate analysis </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>RR 
95% CI 
P-value 
RR 
95% CI 
P-value </p>

<p>age (years) 
0.753 
0.447-1.268 
0.286 
-
-
-
sex 
0.925 
0.463-1.848 
0.826 
-
-
-
histological 
differentiation </p>

<p>2.310 
1.504-3.546 
,0.0001* 
1.945 
1.273-2.972 
0.002* </p>

<p>cirrhosis 
1.032 
0.663-1.606 
0.891 
-
-
-
Tumor size 
1.932 
1.253-2.979 
0.003* 
1.308 
0.806-2.121 
0.277 
clinical stage (T stage) 
2.435 
1.673-3.544 
,0.0001* 
2.038 
1.347-3.084 
0.001* 
PlcB1 expression 
2.096 
1.317-3.336 
0.002* 
1.706 
1.039-2.801 
0.035* </p>

<p>Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Final multivariate analysis include only those covariates that were significantly associated with survival (P,0.05); *P,0.05; -indicates data not available. 
Abbreviations: PlcB1, phospholipase c, β1; RR, relative risk; CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1702 </p>

<p>li et al </p>

<p>Figure 2 exogenous expression of PlcB1 promotes proliferation and inhibits apoptosis of hepg2 and huh7 cells. 
Notes: (A) The HepG2 and Huh7 cells were stably transfected with either control vector or PLCB1 expression vector and the exogenous expression was confirmed by Western blot. (B) cell viability of hepg2 and huh7 cells after 
PlcB1 overexpression was measured by ccK-8. Data were representative as the mean 
± seM of triplicated independent experiments. (C) The effects of PlcB1 on the growth of hepg2 and huh7 cells were measured by colony </p>

<p>formation assay. Results were described as the relative number from five randomly selected fields. The data were representative as the mean </p>

<p>± seM of triplicated independent experiments. (D) caspase-3/7 activity of hepg2 and huh7 </p>

<p>cells after PlcB1 overexpression were detected. The data were representative as the mean </p>

<p>± seM of triplicated independent experiments. (*P,0.05, **P,0.01). </p>

<p>Abbreviations: PlcB1, phospholipase c, 
β1; ccK-8, cell counting kit-8; seM, standard error of the mean; h, hours. </p>

<p>β </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1703 </p>

<p>Up-regulated expression of phospholipase c, β1 </p>

<p>β </p>

<p>Figure 3 Knocking down the expression of PlcB1 inhibits the growth and increases apoptosis of hep3B and lM3 cells. 
Notes: (A) Knocking down the expression of PLCB1 in Hep3B and LM3 was confirmed via Western blot. (B) cell viability of hep3B and lM3 cells with PlcB1 knocking down was measured by ccK-8. Data were representative as the 
mean 
± seM of triplicated independent experiments. (C) The effects of PLCB1 on the growth of Hep3B and LM3 cells were measured by colony formation assay. Results were described as the relative number from five randomly selected 
fields. The data were representative as the mean 
± seM of triplicated independent experiments. (D) caspase-3/7 activity of hep3B and lM3 cells after knocking down PlcB1 was detected. The data were representative as the mean </p>

<p>± </p>

<p>seM of triplicated independent experiments (*represents sh-1 compared to shcon, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>represents sh-2 compared to shcon, *P,0.05, **P,0.01, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P,0.05, </p>

<p>## </p>

<p>P,0.01). </p>

<p>Abbreviations: PlcB1, phospholipase c, 
β1; ccK, cell counting kit; shrnas, short hairpin rnas; sh-1 and sh-2, lentivirus-delivered shrnas; shcon, control shrna; h, hours; seM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1704 </p>

<p>li et al </p>

<p>controls cell proliferation and death. To investigate possible 
mechanisms related to PLCB1-induced proliferation and 
apoptosis, ERK activation status was examined via Western 
blot. The results indicated that exogenous expression of 
PLCB1 in HepG2 and Huh7 cells significantly stimulated 
the phosphorylation of ERK 1/2, while knocking down 
of PLCB1 in Hep3B cells effectively downregulated the 
phosphorylation level (Figure 4A and B). We also examined 
the expression of DUSP1, however, there were no changes. 
These results suggested the PLCB1 could modulate the acti-
vation of ERK signaling in HCC cells. Functionally, using 
ERK signaling inhibitor U0126 abolished the promoting 
effects of PLCB1 on the growth of HCC cells (Figure 4C), 
indicating that ERK activation involved in the oncogenic 
properties of PLCB1. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Oncogenes deregulation and abnormal activation of key 
pathways are always required to maintain the proliferation 
advantage of malignant diseases and might be essential for 
non-tumorous cells to acquire tumor-initiating capacity. </p>

<p>17,18 </p>

<p>Dysregulation of PLCB1 has been observed in several 
diseases, including hematopoietic system and breast cancer. 
However, the expression profile and the function of PLCB1 
in HCC remain largely unclear. Here, we identified PLCB1 
as a novel oncogene and independent prognostic marker of 
HCC. The in vitro experiments revealed that overexpres-
sion of PLCB1 promoted cell growth, while knocking down 
inhibited the growth. Besides, we found that ERK signaling 
aberrant activation might be involved in PLCB1-mediated 
cell growth. More importantly, in clinical specimens, posi-
tive correlations between PLCB1 expression and advanced 
tumor stage suggested that the elevated expression of PLCB1 
might contribute to the progression of HCC. 
Signal transduction networks could transmit informa-
tion about the external environment of the cell and integrate 
these stimulations to trigger the activation of cellular internal 
pathways. The PLCB1 encodes the phosphoinositide-specific 
enzyme, PLCB1, which could be activated by G-proteins 
and catalyzes the formation of second messengers, initiat-
ing the signal cascade. 
19 Several studies have demonstrated 
that PLCB1 played important roles in modulating various </p>

<p>β 
β </p>

<p>Figure 4 erK signaling activation mediates the oncogenic activity of PlcB1. 
Notes: (A) Overexpression of PlcB1 stimulated the phosphorylation of erK1/2 in hepg2 and huh7 cells. (B) Knocking down the endogenous PlcB1 inhibited the 
phosphorylation of erK1/2 in hep3B cells. (C) colony formation assays showed that U0126 could inhibit PlcB1-induced cell growth. 
Abbreviation: PlcB1, phospholipase c, β1. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1705 </p>

<p>Up-regulated expression of phospholipase c, β1 </p>

<p>functional aspects of diseases. 
10,20 In the murine model, 
PLCB1 knock out results in an epileptic phenotype. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>In addition, PLCB1 was involved in the generation of 
IP3 production evoked by histamine stimulation in HeLa 
cells. 
21 In breast cancer, gain of PLCB1 closely related to 
histological grade and proliferative index, and low expres-
sion of PLCB1 in luminal-like A type tumors which had a 
relatively good prognosis. 
16 An earlier study found that a 
role for gains on chromosomes 8q and 20 as predictors of 
poor outcome in hepatoblastomas. 
22 The PLCB1 gene is 
located at chromosome 20p12, which makes us concern its 
up-regulated status. 
Up to now, no reports on the possible association between 
PLCB1 expression and the clinicopathological features of 
HCC were published. Our results revealed significant cor-
relations between the overexpression of PLCB1 and tumor T 
stage. While there were no significant correlations between 
PLCB1 and tumor differentiation, tumor size, and cirrhosis, 
it implicated that PLCB1 was involved in the complicated 
mechanisms on tumor initiation. Furthermore, it could be 
possibly used as a biomarker to identify subsets of HCC 
with the aggressive phenotype. In addition, the patients with 
positive PLCB1 exhibited a lower 5-year OS. Multivariate 
analyses indicated that PLCB1 expression in HCC was an 
independent prognostic factor for survival as well as histo-
logical differentiation and T stage. 
The mechanism by which PLCB1 contributes to HCC 
progression is not well elucidated. We performed in vitro 
experiments to demonstrate that overexpression of PLCB1 
could promote cell proliferation and inhibit apoptosis. More-
over, in our study, PLCB1 was observed to activate ERK 
signaling, which has been proved to affect cell growth and 
apoptosis. Also, it has been reported that ERK activation 
could be regulated by dual-specificity phosphatase DUSP1 
which dephosphorylated ERK. 
23 However, there were slightly 
changes on DUSP1 expression when we affected PLCB1 
expression, suggesting alternative mechanisms underlying 
regulation of ERK activation. Moreover, it has been reported 
that insulin-like growth factor I (IGF-I) could cause rapid 
nuclear translocation of activated ERK and concurrently 
induce phosphorylation of nuclear PLCB1, initiating the 
phosphoinositide cycle. 
24 These might be a positive regula-
tory loop between PLCB1 and ERK signaling. In recent 
years, compounds inhibiting the kinase activity of ERK have 
yielded preclinical results and made some progress in cancer 
treatment. 
25 As shown in Figure 4C, the proliferation accel-
eration effect mediated by overexpression of PLCB1 was par-
tially abolished by ERK inhibitor. It has been demonstrated </p>

<p>that the antiproliferative efficacy of inhibitors aimed at ERK 
signals depends on the driver oncogenic lesion. At the next 
stage of the cascade, expression levels of effectors such as 
Fra-1 and c-Myc were controlled by ERK activation through 
an integrative process. 
25 In further studies, more experimenta-
tion will be required to explore the molecular mechanisms of 
PLCB1 in HCC pathogenesis and metastasis. In addition, we 
would also study the role of PLCB1 in a variety of cancers 
such as colorectal cancer and prostate cancer. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>A specific upregulation of PLCB1 in the patients with HCC 
has been identified in this work. This overexpression might 
possess a crucial role in promoting tumorigenesis, and 
moreover, it is closely correlated with aggressive malignant 
behavior and could predict poor prognosis. All these results 
from both clinical specimens and in vitro experiments sup-
ported a role of PLCB1 in HCC development and provided 
a potential molecular target for detection and treatment of 
HCC. We proposed that inhibition of PLCB1-mediated 
pathway might give insight to the novel therapeutic strategy 
for controlling tumor progression in HCC. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open 
access journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>