<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4934460" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Cost-effectiveness models for the treatment of long-term conditions often require 
information on survival beyond the period of available data. 
Objectives: This paper aims to identify a robust and reliable method for the extrapolation 
of overall survival (OS) in patients with radioiodine-refractory differentiated thyroid cancer 
receiving lenvatinib or placebo. 
Methods: Data from 392 patients (lenvatinib: 261, placebo: 131) from the SELECT trial are 
used over a 34-month period of follow-up. A previously published criterion-based approach is 
employed to ascertain credible estimates of OS beyond the trial data. Parametric models with and 
without a treatment covariate and piecewise models are used to extrapolate OS, and a holistic 
approach, where a series of statistical and visual tests are considered collectively, is taken in 
determining the most appropriate extrapolation model. 
Results: A piecewise model, in which the Kaplan-Meier survivor function is used over the 
trial period and an extrapolated tail is based on the Exponential distribution, is identified as 
the optimal model. 
Conclusion: In the absence of long-term survival estimates from clinical trials, survival esti-
mates often need to be extrapolated from the available data. The use of a systematic method 
based on a priori determined selection criteria provides a transparent approach and reduces the 
risk of bias. The extrapolated OS estimates will be used to investigate the potential long-term 
benefits of lenvatinib in the treatment of radioiodine-refractory differentiated thyroid cancer 
patients and populate future cost-effectiveness analyses. 
ClinicoEconomics and Outcomes Research 2016:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>324 </p>

<p>Tremblay et al </p>

<p>Lenvatinib is a multiple receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitor 
that selectively inhibits multiple angiogenic and oncogenic 
signaling pathways 
10 and is indicated for the treatment of adult 
patients with progressive, locally advanced, or metastatic, dif-
ferentiated (papillary/follicular/Hürthle cell) RR-DTC. 
10 The 
key clinical evidence for lenvatinib is derived from a Phase III 
multicenter, double-blind, randomized (2:1), placebo-controlled 
trial (SELECT) comparing the efficacy and safety of lenva-
tinib and placebo in patients with progressive RR-DTC. 
11 The 
primary end point of SELECT was progression-free survival 
(PFS), with overall survival (OS) measured as a secondary end 
point. The trial was designed to allow patients randomized to 
the placebo group to receive optional open-label lenvatinib at 
the time of confirmed disease progression. Over the 34-month 
period of follow-up of the SELECT, lenvatinib was found to 
prolong PFS by almost 15 months compared with placebo 
(hazard ratio =0.21; 95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.14-0.31). </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>While PFS is an important and significant measure of 
treatment success, OS is a key outcome for patients and 
health care providers. A high value is placed on OS by health 
technology assessment bodies, and it is a key component of 
cost-effectiveness models for long-term conditions. However, 
benefits in OS often prove difficult to demonstrate, particularly 
due to the limited duration of clinical trials, whereas PFS clinical 
trial data are often more complete. Although PFS at 34 months 
of follow-up for the placebo and lenvatinib arms in SELECT 
was 0% and 33%, respectively, median OS was not reached in 
either treatment group, meaning that &gt;50% of patients remained 
alive. 
12 Therefore, extrapolation of OS was considered more 
critical than that of PFS and is the focus of this manuscript. 
Increasing trial time-horizons to capture reliable OS 
data would be prohibitively expensive, with results often 
not available for many years, thus delaying patient access to 
potentially beneficial new treatments. A method of obtaining 
estimates of long-term survival is by extrapolation from the 
available data. In cases where treatment effects on survival 
extend beyond the period investigated in clinical trials, 
extrapolation could reveal longer term treatment benefits that 
would have been missed by restricting the investigation to a 
shorter period. 
13 The purpose of this analysis is to identify 
the most appropriate extrapolation method for SELECT OS 
data in order to estimate the potential long-term benefit of 
lenvatinib in slowly evolving RR-DTC and for potential use 
in future cost-effectiveness evaluations. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>The following sections describe the SELECT and the deriva-
tion of OS data, including the construction of Kaplan-Meier </p>

<p>(KM) plots for adjusting OS data for potential bias due to 
the crossover design of the SELECT. These methods have 
been described in the previous literature 
14 and are important 
to the understanding of the current approach. </p>

<p>SELECT </p>

<p>The SELECT was a Phase III, randomized, double-blind, 
placebo-controlled, multicenter, crossover trial. Patients 
aged 18 years or older were eligible for enrollment and were 
recruited from the Americas, Europe, Asia, and Australia. 
In total, 392 patients were randomly assigned (block ran-
domization) in a 2:1 ratio to receive 24 mg once-daily oral 
lenvatinib (261 patients) or placebo (131 patients) in 28-day 
cycles. Trial follow-up was 34 months (cutoff point June 15, 
2014). Primary and secondary analyses were conducted in 
the intention-to-treat population. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>OS data from the SELECT -crossover correction 
and production of KM plots </p>

<p>Due to the crossover design of SELECT, where patients 
randomized to placebo were eligible to receive open-label 
lenvatinib on confirmed disease progression, 
11 87.8% of 
placebo-treated patients switched to lenvatinib. As a conse-
quence, although PFS data were unaffected by the crossover 
design of SELECT, OS survival for the placebo arm was 
biased, with placebo demonstrating a higher survival than 
what would have been observed without treatment switching 
due to the use of open-label lenvatinib. To adjust for this bias, 
a rank-preserving structural failure time (RPSFT) model was 
used. 
12,14 Table 1 shows the unadjusted and RPSFT-corrected 
median OS times for the lenvatinib and placebo arms of the 
SELECT. KM plots for both trial arms have been published 
by Schlumberger et al. 
11 In the current analysis, long-term 
OS is obtained by extrapolation from the RPSFT-corrected 
data over the trial period. </p>

<p>Lenvatinib 
Placebo </p>

<p>Deaths, n (%) 
93 (35.6) 
55 (42.0) 
Unadjusted 
Median OS, months (95% CI) 
NE (30.9, NE) 
NE (21.7, NE) 
Unadjusted HR (95% CI) 
0.80 (0.57, 1.12), nominal P=0.1993 
RPSFT corrected 
Median OS, months (95% CI) 
NE (30.9, NE) 
19.1 (14.3, NE) 
RPSFT-adjusted HR (95% CI) 
0.53 (0.34, 0.82), nominal P=0.0051 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; HR, hazard ratio; NE, not estimable; OS, 
overall survival; RPSFT, rank-preserving structural failure time. </p>

<p>ClinicoEconomics and Outcomes Research 2016:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>325 </p>

<p>Extrapolating OS for RR-DTC from placebo-controlled trial </p>

<p>Current analysis </p>

<p>Time-horizon 
A 120-month (10-year) time-horizon was chosen in order to 
mitigate inherent uncertainty in the extrapolation of 34-month 
OS data over a lifetime-horizon. The 10-year time-horizon 
was deemed both sufficient to capture meaningful differences 
in OS and appropriate from an economic perspective since, 
according to published data, only 10% of patients with RR-
DCT survive at 10 years. 
1 The restricted mean, truncated at 
the 10-year time-horizon, was used to facilitate estimates of 
OS before and after the empirical data cutoff (at 34 months), 
while the extended mean was used to estimate CIs around the 
marginal OS difference. The uncertainty around the estimates 
was measured using the bootstrap method 
15 to evaluate the 
CIs. All statistical analyses were performed in <rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA Version 
13</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StataCorp LP, College Station, TX, USA</rs>). </p>

<p>Selection of most appropriate extrapolation method 
A peer-reviewed, five-criterion framework for the robust 
extrapolation of survival data (presented by Tremblay et al </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>) 
was applied to the RPSFT-adjusted SELECT data set in order 
to help identify the most plausible extrapolation for OS. </p>

<p>Criterion 1 -proportional treatment (PT) assumption testing: 
the PT assumption must be supported by the log-cumulative 
hazard plot (which would be parallel in the case of a PT effect) 
and the PT global test. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Criterion 2 -extrapolated hazard function fitting in time and 
between trial arms: the hazard rates should have a similar 
time relation pattern between the extrapolation function and 
the KM survivor function. The characteristic of the relation 
between the hazard rates of both arms should be replicated by 
the modeling technique selected, for example, crossing lines 
would advocate a separate parametric model for each arm. </p>

<p>Criterion 3 -minimal Akaike information criterion (AIC) and 
Bayesian information criterion (BIC): for parametric models, 
the selected model must have a low AIC/BIC to demonstrate 
goodness-of-fit to the clinical data. </p>

<p>Criterion 4 -uncertainty in the results: uncertainty in 
model parameters should be considered when selecting the 
best model, as a high uncertainty would be a sign of low 
robustness. </p>

<p>Criterion 5 -similitude of pre-extrapolation marginal gain 
and realism of the extrapolated marginal gain: the realism 
of the marginal gain should be accounted for when selecting 
the best model as an unrealistic marginal gain would create 
bias in the economic analysis. </p>

<p>Although these five criteria provide a systematic approach 
for the identification of the model that most accurately 
extrapolates OS, they should be used as a theoretical guide 
only as it is often the case that not all of these criteria can be 
satisfied simultaneously when applied to real data. 
Five model "classes" were considered for the extrapola-
tion of OS: PT models with a treatment covariate, acceler-
ated failure time (AFT) models with a treatment covariate, 
individual models (where the extrapolation for each arm is 
estimated separately, ie, no treatment covariate is used), KM 
survival function with parametric extrapolation, and Royston 
and Parmar spline technique. The Exponential, Weibull, 
Gompertz, Log-Normal, Log-Logistic, and Gamma distri-
butions were considered, where appropriate, in the model 
classes outlined earlier. 
For the purposes of the current analysis, the selected 
extrapolation model needs to be compatible with a 10-year 
time-horizon. The Royston and Parmar technique is a flexible 
piecewise technique that uses segmental parameter partition-
ing. 
17 Although this allows for a better fit of the parametric 
function to the pre-34-month cutoff data, credibility for the 
tail extrapolation is lost. Therefore, the Royston and Parmar 
technique was deemed inappropriate for extrapolating data 
to 10 years in the current analysis. The models used in the 
current analysis were parametric (PT and AFT), individual 
(separate models for each arm of the SELECT), and piece-
wise (KM + extrapolated tail). </p>

<p>Results 
Extrapolation of OS data from SELECT </p>

<p>Criterion 1 -PT assumption testing 
PT assumption testing (Criterion 1) was performed by visual 
inspection of the log-cumulative hazard plot (Figure 1) and 
the PT global test (Schoenfeld residual test). 
18 The visual 
inspection revealed relatively straight but not parallel log-
cumulative plots. The PT global test yielded a P-value of 
0.7270, which did not indicate a significant deviation from 
the PT assumption. Due to the contradictory nature of the 
global test for a PT effect and the visual inspection of the 
log-cumulative hazard OS plot, the validity of the PT assump-
tion was ambiguous. </p>

<p>Criterion 2 -extrapolated hazard function fitting in time 
and between trial arms 
A visual evaluation of the extrapolated hazard function fitting 
to the KM hazard function was performed. Inspection of the 
log-cumulative hazard plot (Figure 1) indicated that using fully 
parametric models with a treatment covariate (PT and AFT) </p>

<p>ClinicoEconomics and Outcomes Research 2016:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>326 </p>

<p>Tremblay et al </p>

<p>would, by definition, not adequately capture the crossing of 
hazards. Fitted and observed log-cumulative hazard functions 
were overlaid for both the PT (Figure S1) and individual mod-
els (Figure S2). Figure S1 shows that the Weibull (PT and AFT 
models) and Gamma (AFT model) have similar hazard patterns 
to the KM of empirical data after the plots have diverged. The </p>

<p>fitting of individual models negates the PT assumption and may 
therefore better reflect the change in hazard at earlier points in 
time. The log-cumulative hazard plots for individual models 
(Figure S2) indicated that the Weibull, Gamma, and the Log-
Logistic distributions can be considered to have approximately 
similar hazard patterns to the KM of empirical data. </p>

<p>Criterion 3 -minimal AIC and BIC and Criterion 4 -
uncertainty in the results 
The difference in mean OS survival estimates between the 
lenvatinib and placebo arms of SELECT, summary statistics 
(based on the extended mean), CIs of the marginal difference, 
and AIC/BIC criteria are provided in Table 2 for models based 
on the PT assumption, individual models, and piecewise 
models. The different classes display similar findings in terms 
of ranking the best fitted models to the empirical data. The 
Log-Logistic, Gompertz, Gamma, and Log-Normal extrapo-
lations are ranked third, fourth, fifth, and sixth, respectively, in 
each of the model classes when evaluating the AIC statistics. 
This result is closely matched in the BIC statistics; however, 
in each class, the Log-Normal extrapolation is ranked fifth 
and the Gamma sixth. In the case of the individual models, </p>

<p>Figure 1 Log-cumulative hazard plot for OS. 
Abbreviation: OS, overall survival. </p>

<p>ClinicoEconomics and Outcomes Research 2016:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>327 </p>

<p>Extrapolating OS for RR-DTC from placebo-controlled trial </p>

<p>the Exponential extrapolation would be ranked first from 
the perspective of both the AIC and the BIC. This ranking 
is repeated in the BIC results for the PT models; however, 
the AIC statistics show the Weibull to be a better fit than 
the Exponential. The CIs do not go below 0 for any of the 
extrapolations in the PT and piecewise model classes. In the 
individual model class, both the Log-Logistic and Gamma 
extrapolations have lower bounds crossing 0. In each of the 
model classes, the Log-Normal and Log-Logistic extrapola-
tions exhibit the highest levels of uncertainty (widest CIs). </p>

<p>Criterion 5 -similitude of pre-extrapolation marginal gain 
and realism of the extrapolated marginal gain 
Criterion 5 is a "rule of thumb" designed to evaluate the 
robustness of the marginal survival gain of the extrapolation 
in comparison with that shown in the pre-extrapolation KM. 
The marginal survival gain prior or post the trial cutoff is 
divided by the time prior or post the trial cutoff, respectively. 
The resulting ratio in the post-trial period should be equal or 
inferior to the ratio in the pre-extrapolation period, that is, 
if the ratio is much higher after the cutoff, it suggests that 
the marginal gain is exaggerated in the post-cutoff period 
(resulting in a "long" and/or "thick" tail). The ratios that serve 
as the basis for evaluating Criterion 5 are shown in Table 3. 
Of the PT models, the Log-Normal, Log-Logistic, and 
Gompertz distributions satisfied Criterion 5 in terms of the 
comparison of the KM rate of survival gain against the post-
extrapolation rate of survival gain. However, of these, only 
the Log-Normal distribution satisfied Criterion 5 in terms 
of comparison between the pre-and post-extrapolation rate 
of gain. The Weibull and Gamma distributions both satisfied 
Criterion 5 in terms of the comparison between pre-and 
post-extrapolation rate of gain; however, in both instances, 
the extrapolated rate of gain in the pre-extrapolation period 
was greater than the KM rate of survival gain. 
All the individual models failed to satisfy Criterion 5 
in terms of the comparison of the KM rate of survival gain </p>

<p>against the post-extrapolation rate of survival gain. The 
Weibull, Exponential, Gamma, and Gompertz distributions 
all satisfied the criterion in terms of the comparison between 
pre-and postextrapolated rate of survival gain. Neither the 
Log-Normal nor the Log-Logistic distributions satisfied 
the criterion when either the KM or pre-extrapolation rate 
was compared against the postextrapolation rate. For both 
distributions, the postextrapolation rate of survival gain is 
noticeably higher than the KM rate of survival gain, a result 
indicative of both distributions being characterized by "long" 
tails. Using the KM survival function with extrapolated tail, 
all evaluated distributions satisfied Criterion 5. 
The individual results for the application of each of the five 
criteria in the model selection framework are presented in Table 4. </p>

<p>Extrapolation using the most appropriate model </p>

<p>The results indicate that a piecewise model appears to be the 
most appropriate for extrapolating the RPSFT-adjusted OS 
trial data. Deviance under the PT assumption is inconsistent, 
and data are unfavorable for Log-Normal and Log-Logistic 
distributions in all the evaluated model types. 
The best fitting functional forms (in descending order 
of fit) were: </p>

<p>1. OS extrapolation result, using a piecewise model. 
Abbreviation: OS, overall survival. </p>

<p>ClinicoEconomics and Outcomes Research 2016:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>329 </p>

<p>Extrapolating OS for RR-DTC from placebo-controlled trial </p>

<p>Using the KM + exponentially extrapolated tail, the 
benefit associated with lenvatinib, relative to placebo, was 
4.45 months pre-extrapolation and estimated at 11.13 months 
postextrapolation -giving a total OS benefit of 15.58 months 
with lenvatinib treatment over the 120-month (10-year) 
time-horizon. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>OS is a key outcome in determining the efficacy of cancer thera-
pies in clinical trial settings. 
19 An OS benefit can be difficult to 
demonstrate due to the limited duration of clinical trials and 
the potential confounding due to subsequent treatments that 
patients may receive. 
11 This was the case in the SELECT, in 
which ~50% of patients remained alive at the 34-month data 
cutoff point, and 87.8% of patients originally randomized to 
receive placebo had switched over to lenvatinib following docu-
mented disease progression. The purpose of this analysis was 
to extrapolate OS data from the SELECT, in order to estimate 
the potential long-term benefits of lenvatinib for use in future 
cost-effectiveness evaluations. Our work is novel in that it uses 
a holistic approach in the selection of the most appropriate 
model for the long-term extrapolation of survival when a high 
percentage of individuals are still alive at the end of follow-up. 
The extrapolation of OS data used an RPSFT model to cor-
rect for potential confounding due to crossover 
14 and followed </p>

<p>a previously published, systematic method to determine the 
most suitable approach to extrapolate OS data. 
13 The use of this 
systematic method (involving five criteria) 
13 was considered a 
strength of this analysis. Testing of Criterion 1 regarding the 
PT assumption was inconclusive as the log-cumulative hazard 
OS plots from SELECT were relatively straight but not paral-
lel, while the global test for a PT effect was not significant. 
While some researchers would not consider the evidence 
regarding the use of the PT assumption to be prohibitive, it 
is the opinion of the authors that, if using a PT assumption, 
proof should be presented that individual models and piece-
wise models (such as the KM model + extrapolated tail) are 
inferior. Piecewise models use the observed hazard from the 
clinical trial data by applying the KM survivor estimator over 
the trial period; thus, they can be superior to parametric mod-
els and individual models when their underlying assumptions 
are inappropriate. Therefore, a piecewise model (ie, KM + 
extrapolated tail) appeared to be a suitable alternative. 
A potential limitation of this analysis is that OS for the 
placebo arm of the SELECT was obtained by fitting an 
RPSFT model. Although this approach can be used to correct 
for potential confounding due to the crossover design of the 
SELECT, a key assumption in RPSFT models is that the treat-
ment is acting by multiplying survival time by a given factor 
once patients start receiving active treatment. Therefore, OS </p>

<p>Table 5 Summary statistics of pre-and post-cutoff OS (120-month time-horizon) -survival difference (months) </p>

<p>This analysis and publication were funded by Eisai Inc. 
We thank Brigitte Moore (DRG Abacus) for help with the 
preparation of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>GT is an employee of Eisai Inc. AB received an honorarium 
for his validation of the analysis. There are no other conflicts 
of interest in this work. </p>



<p>ClinicoEconomics and Outcomes Research 2016:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>332 </p>

<p>Tremblay et al </p>

<p>Supplementary materials </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>-3 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-8 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-3 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>-1 
0 
1 
2 
ln(time) </p>

<p>Exponential </p>

<p>Log-Logistic 
Log-Normal </p>

<p>Log-cumulative hazard -proportional treatment models </p>

<p>Weibull </p>

<p>Gamma 
Gompertz </p>

<p>3 
4 </p>

<p>-1 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>ln(time) </p>

<p>Placebo Kaplan-Meier 
Lenvatinib Kaplan-Meier 
Placebo fitted model 
Lenvima fitted model </p>

<p>3 
4 
-1 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>ln(time) </p>

<p>3 
4 
-1 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>ln(time) </p>

<p>3 
4 </p>

<p>-1 
0 
1 
2 
ln(time) </p>

<p>3 
4 
-1 
0 
1 
2 
ln(time) </p>

<p>3 
4 
ln[-ln(survival probability)] 
ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>ln[-ln(survival probability)] 
ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>Figure S1 Log-cumulative hazard plots for OS comparing observed (KM) with fitted estimates obtained from PT models. 
Abbreviations: KM, Kaplan-Meier; OS, overall survival; PT, proportional treatment. </p>

<p>ClinicoEconomics and Outcomes Research 2016:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>ClinicoEconomics and Outcomes Research </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: https://www.dovepress.com/clinicoeconomics-and-outcomes-research-journal </p>

<p>ClinicoEconomics and Outcomes Research is an international, peer-
reviewed open-access journal focusing on health technology assess-
ment, pharmacoeconomics and outcomes research in the areas of 
diagnosis, medical devices, and clinical, surgical and pharmacological 
intervention. The economic impact of health policy and health systems </p>

<p>organization also constitute important areas of coverage. The manu-
script management system is completely online and includes a very 
quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>333 </p>

<p>Extrapolating OS for RR-DTC from placebo-controlled trial </p>

<p>Log-cumulative hazard -individual models </p>

<p>Exponential </p>

<p>Log-Logistic </p>

<p>Gamma 
Gompertz </p>

<p>ln(time) 
ln(time) 
ln(time) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>-1 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
-1 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
-1 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>Log-Normal 
Weibull </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>-1 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>ln(time) </p>

<p>3 
4 
-1 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>ln(time) </p>

<p>3 
4 
-1 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>ln(time) </p>

<p>3 
4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-8 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>Placebo Kaplan-Meier 
Lenvatinib Kaplan-Meier 
Placebo fitted model 
Lenvima fitted model </p>

<p>ln[-ln(survival probability)] 
ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>ln[-ln(survival probability)] 
ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>Figure S2 Log-cumulative hazard plots for OS comparing observed (KM) with fitted estimates obtained from individual models. 
Abbreviations: KM, Kaplan-Meier; OS, overall survival. </p>

</text></tei>