<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4792979" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:41+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. [Purpose] Respiratory function is important for patients including athletes who require physical thera-
py for respiratory dysfunction. The purpose of the present study was to analyze the differences in the respirograms 
between Korean wrestling athletes and nonathletes according to phase for the study of sports physiotherapy. [Sub-
jects and Methods] Respiratory function was measured using spirometry in both the athletes and nonathletes while 
they were in a sitting position. [Results] Spirometry parameters in the athletes were significantly higher than in the 
nonathletes. In respirogram phasic analysis, the expiratory area and total area of forced vital capacity were signifi-
cantly increased in the athletes compared with the nonathletes. The slopes of the forced vital capacity for athletes 
at slopes 1, 2, and 3 of the A area were significantly increased. In correlative analysis, chest circumference was 
significantly correlated with slope 3 of the A area of the forced vital capacity. [Conclusion] The results suggest that 
the differences in changes in the phases of the respirogram between the Korean wrestling athletes and nonathletes 
may in part contribute to our understanding of respiratory function in sports physiotherapy research. 
Respiratory physiotherapy is an important way to potentially improve lung function in patients including athletes with 
respiratory dysfunction caused by genetically determined neuropathy, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, asthma, or 
sports injury of the chest 1-4) . In particular, sports injury in coastal areas is directly or indirectly related to maintenance of 
athletes' performance 5-8) . Korean wrestling, also called ssireum, is unique to the traditional culture and folklore of Korean 
spectator sports 9-11) . The rules for matches are simple, and the outcome is clear to young and old observers alike. A Korean 
wrestling match is a gentlemanly sport focused on manners in which the participants do not hit each other 9-11) . Male athletes 
are categorized into seven divisions according to body weight, while female athletes compete in two weight divisions. The 
objective of Korean wrestling is to overcome the opponent by utilizing the muscles of the whole body based on fitness 
and skill 9-11) . Therefore, participation in Korean wrestling results in balanced development of the whole body. In Korean 
wrestling, the participants hold onto each other's belt (satba) and try to cause part of their opponent's body above the knee 
to touch the ground 9-11) . Ultimately, the body movements used in the attempt to knock over opponents cause development of 
muscle strength and endurance 9-11) . We selected a pulmonary function test to characterize the exercise of Korean wrestling. 
Cardiorespiratory fitness represents a human health condition of the entire body 12-14) . In contrast, pulmonary function testing 
provides a quantitative assessment of lung function, which is important for estimating an individual's health 15) . Respiratory 
function is influenced by exercise and training 15, 16) . As a result, lung function may change depending on the frequency 
of the sport activity 17, 18) . To date, however, no study has analyzed the respiratory function of Korean wrestling athletes. 
Therefore, the objectives of this research were to analyze and compare the respiratory function of Korean wrestling athletes 
and nonathletes for the study of sports rehabilitation. </p>

<p>SUBJECTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>The present study consisted of 16 elite Korean wrestling athletes and 95 nonathletes. Measurements were performed from 
March 2015 to August 2015. One hundred and eleven volunteers who had no abnormal physical or psychological conditions 
provided written informed consent to participation in this study 9) . Participants were asked to complete a questionnaire via 
individual in-depth interviews, which took 30 minutes per person 9) . There were seven weight categories: gyungjang (less 
than 75 kg), sojang (less than 80 kg), chungjang (less than 85 kg), yongjang (less than 90 kg), yongsa (less than 95 kg), 
yeoksa (less than 110 kg), and jangsa (less than 150 kg) 9, 10) . The criteria for the inclusion of participants in the study were 
as follows: (1) 20-23 years of age, (2) male, (3) history of respiratory disease, (4) experience of stress during exercise, (5) 
psychological factors, (6) history of injuries, and (7) primary technology used. Before measurement, all participants rested 
for 30 minutes 9) . Chest and abdominal circumference were measured at rest under expiratory and inspiratory conditions 2) . 
Chest circumference was measured at the height of the axilla, and abdominal circumference was measured at the height of 
the navel. The respiration ability of participants was measured. The participants were measured by lung function testing using 
the SCHILLER SP-260 spirometer (SCHILLER AG, Baar, Switzerland). Spirometric parameters, including forced vital 
capacity (FVC), forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1), FEV1/FVC, peak expiratory flow (PEF), peak inspiratory 
flow (PIF), slow vital capacity (SVC), inspiratory reserve volume (IRV), expiratory reserve volume (ERV), tidal volume 
(TV), maximum voluntary ventilation (MVV), minute or expired ventilation (MV), and respiratory rate (RR) were recorded 
and analyzed by methods of resting breathing and forced breathing. Measurement was focused on the FVC graph, which 
was divided into the expiratory area (ExA) and the inspiratory area (InsA) 2) . The pixel values were measured using <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Adobe</rs> 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Photoshop</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">7.0.1</rs>. The ExA was divided into A and B sections based on the PEF. Analogously, the InsA was divided into C and 
D sections based on the PIF. Each A, B, C, and D section was further subdivided to four areas (Fig. 1A). From left to right, 
the connections between each of the divided points of the A area were designated as the first slope (AS1), the second slope 
(AS2), and the third slope (AS3). Correspondingly, from left to right, the first, second, and third slopes defining the B area 
were designated BS1, BS2, and BS3, respectively; the first, second, and third slopes defining the C area were designated CS1, 
CS2, and CS3, respectively; and the first, second, and third slopes defining the D area were designated DS1, DS2, and DS3, 
respectively (Fig. 1A) 2) . After creating these subdivisions, the tangent and angle of each point were measured. The angle of 
each point and the respiratory area of the FVC were each measured in triplicate at each measurement time, and the mean 
values were calculated 2, 19) . The formula for the tangent is given in Equation 1, where r is the radius of a circle composed of 
the coordinates of the x and y axes. The cos θ is the value obtained by dividing x by r; sin θ is the value obtained by dividing 
y by r. The tan θ is equivalent to the ratio of the sin θ to the cos θ 2, 20) . </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>The angle was determined (Equation 2) using the arctangent in order to verify the tangent θ 2, 21) . In Equation 2, x repre-
sents the unknown quantity, and i represents an imaginary quantity. </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 28, No. 2, 2016 </p>



<p>3 
5 
7 
n 2n 1 </p>

<p>n 0 </p>

<p>( 1) 
arctan 
; 
1, 
, 
3 
5 
7 
2n 1 </p>

<p>x 
x 
x 
x x 
x 
x i 
x 
i </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>− 
= − 
+ 
− 
+ = 
≤ 
≠ − 
+ </p>

<p>∑ </p>

<p> 
(2) </p>

<p>The IBM <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> Statistics software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">Version 22.0</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM Corp.</rs>., Armonk, NY, USA) was used for the statistical analysis. 
The significance level was set to α=0.05, and all data are presented as the mean ± standard error (SE) of the measurements. 
One-way ANOVA was conducted to compare the significance between the groups. The Pearson correlation coefficient test 
was performed to identify correlations between the variables. The protocol for this study was approved by the Committee of 
Ethics in Research of Yong In University in accordance with the terms of Resolution 5-1-20. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Table 1 shows the general characteristics of the Korean wrestling athletes compared with those of the nonathletes. Spirom-
etry parameters in the athletes group were significantly higher than in the nonathletes, but not ERV, IRV, and MVV (Table 2). 
Respirogram phasic analysis revealed that the expiratory (ExA) and total area (Total) of the FVC were significantly increased 
in the athletes compared with the nonathletes (Table 3 and Fig. 1B). The slopes of respirogram phases, such as the tangent 
angles, of the FVC were compared between nonathletes and athletes (Table 3, Fig. 1B). The tangents for athletes at slopes 1, 
2, and 3 of the A area (AS1, AS2, and AS3) were significantly increased (Table 3, Fig. 1B). Furthermore, in the correlative 
analysis, chest and abdominal circumference were not correlated with the area of the FVC (Table 4). The correlation coef-
ficients for the chest circumference and tangent are shown in Table 5, with slope 3 of the A area (AS3) showing significant 
correlation. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Respiratory exercise is a factor that affects balance and postural stability 22) . Balance is very important in ssireum, which 
is also called Korean wrestling 9, 10) . Regular physical training improves respiratory functions 23) . Therefore, the respiratory 
function of Korean wrestling athletes is better than that of nonathletes, as were other physical parameters such as height, 
weight, body mass index, chest circumference, and abdominal circumference. Analysis of the FVC graph revealed that the 
ExAs of the Korean wrestling athletes and the nonathletes were significantly different. The AS1, AS2, and AS3 values were 
also significantly different. The respiratory muscles of the ssireum athletes were anticipated to be better than those of the 
nonathletes. According to other studies, ssireum athletes have more muscle and fat mass compared with nonathletes 9-11) . 
Examination of the reasons for this development in ssireum athletes prompted respiratory analyses in this study. The primary 
techniques of the ssireum athletes were considered, including hand techniques, leg techniques, trunk techniques, and mixed 
techniques 9-11) . The preferred technique for ssireum athletes is the "Deul-baejigi"-one of the trunk techniques. Ssireum 
athletes are overweight compared with normal people 9-11) . Therefore, use of the "Deul-baejigi" technique is an advantageous. 
Muscle strength and respiratory function are closely related to each other, because poor respiratory function is an indicator 
of muscle weakness 24) . The interaction between respiratory and motor functions can be observed from normal functions, 
such as simple limb movements and muscle strength 25-28) . Korean wrestling is similar to another sport-Sumo wrestling in </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Differences in FVC and respirogram phase between the Korean wrestling athletes and nonathletes 2, 9, 10) 
Area and slope of the FVC and respiratory parameters were determined, as described in the Subjects and Meth-
ods section. FVC, forced vital capacity; AS1-3, first, second, and third slopes of the A area; BS1-3, first, second, 
and third slopes of the B area; CS1-3, first, second, and third slopes of the C area; DS1-3, first, second, and third 
slopes of the D area; ExA, expiratory area; InsA, inspiratory area 
Weight classes of Korean wrestling athletes: GJ, gyungjang; SJ, sojang; CJ, chungjang; YJ, yongjang; YS, 
yongsa; YeS, yeoksa </p>



<p>Japan. Sumo has a simple match style and provides anaerobic training. Most matches end within one minute. Therefore, the 
aerobic energy system is affected by sumo matches and training 29) . Korean wrestling matches also end within less than one 
minute. Therefore, Korean wrestling athletes can expect type II muscle development to be enhanced by anaerobic exercise. 
Features of the type II muscles are used to demonstrate instantaneous power rather than endurance 28, 30) . This can be observed 
in the AS1, AS2, and AS3 sections of the graph. Therefore, instantaneous power, as opposed to endurance, is relatively weak, 
because the decrease in the B section of the PEF area has the same slope in athletes and nonathletes. Other sports similar 
to Korean wrestling are found throughout the world-Buh in Mongolia, Sambo in Russia, Kara Kucak and Yagli Gures in 
Turkey, Das Schwingen in Switzerland, Fang in Iceland, and Lucha Canaria in Spain 31) . In addition, these same athletes can 
anticipate similar development of the Type II muscles as a result of anaerobic exercise 31) . However, further systematic and 
scientific studies in the area of sports physiotherapy research and therapy, especially for chest injuries related to various 
sports, are needed 32-35) . </p>

<p>Table 1. General characteristics of the participants </p>

<p>Nonathletes 
Korean Wrestling Athletes 
Age (yrs) 
24.9 ± 2.8 
21.3 ± 1.0 * 
Height (cm) 
174.1 ± 4.7 
178.6 ± 4.3 * 
Weight (kg) 
75.9 ± 10.1 
94.6 ± 12.9 * 
BMI (kg/m 2 ) 
24.9 ± 2.8 
29.6 ± 3.8 * 
Career (yrs) 
-
9.5 ± 0.5 
Training frequency 
-
3/day (18/week) 
Training time 
-
5.7 ± 0.3 h/day (34.2 ± 1.8 h/week) 
Aerobic exercise 
-
2.2 ± 0.2 h/day (13.2 ± 1.2 h/week) 
Anaerobic exercise 
-
3.1 ± 0.5 h/day (18.6 ± 3.0 h/week) </p>

<p>Ches Cir (cm) </p>

<p>Rest 
96.1 ± 6.3 
113.1 ± 13.8 * 
Exp 
94.0 ± 6.5 
110.6 ± 16.9 * 
Insp 
100.3 ± 6.1 
115.4 ± 12.1 * 
DER 
1.6 ± 1.4 
2.4 ± 3.1 
DIR 
3.3 ± 2.2 
2.4 ± 1.9 </p>

<p>Abd Cir (cm) </p>

<p>Rest 
86.8 ± 7.5 
101.5 ± 13.9 * 
Exp 
84.5 ± 8.0 
98.1 ± 13.6 * 
Insp 
89.4 ± 7.9 
104.1 ± 13.3 * 
DER 
2.1 ± 2.0 
3.5 ± 2.0 
DIR 
2.2 ± 1.8 
2.6 ± 2.4 </p>

<p>Weight category (%) </p>

<p>Gyungjang/Sojang 
-
2 (12.5)/2 (12.5) 
Chungjang/Yongjang 
-
3 (18.8)/2 (12.5) 
Yongsa/Yeoksa 
-
4 (25.0)/3 (18.8) 
Jangsa 
-
-</p>

<p>Hand technique (%) </p>

<p>AM-C/DM-C 
-
1 (6.3)/-(-) 
O-C/YM-C 
-
2 (12.5)/-(-) 
G-D/DS-J 
-
1 (6.3)/1 (6.3) </p>

<p>Leg technique (%) </p>

<p>AD-G/BD-G 
-
8 (50.0)/5 (31.3) 
H-G/BB-G 
-
1 (6.3)/4 (25.0) 
B-G/C-D 
-
1 (6.3)/-(-) 
D-G 
-
4 (25.0) </p>

<p>Trunk technique (%) 
J-C/Oe-B 
-
6 (37.5)/5 (31.3) 
D-B/G-C 
-
14 (87.5)/-(-) </p>

<p>Mixed technique (%) 
Or-D/Oe-D 
-
2 (12.5)/1 (6.3) 
D-D 
-
1 (6.3) </p>

<p>All data are presented as the mean±SE. BMI: body mass index; Ches Cir: chest circumference; Abd Cir: abdominal circum-
ference; Exp: expiration; Insp: inspiration; DER: differences between expiration and rest; DIR: differences between inspira-
tion and rest; AM-C: Ap Mureup-Chigi; DM-C: Dwit Mureup-Chigi; O-C: Oguem-Chaegi; YM-C: Yeop Mureup-Chigi; 
G-D: Ggok-Dwijypgi; DS-J: Deung Satba-Jabachaegi; AD-G: Ahn Dari-Geolgi; BD-G: Bat Dari-Geolgi; H-G: Homi-Geoli; 
BB-G: Balmok Bitjang-Geoli; B-G: Baldeung-Geoli; C-D: Cha-Dolrigi; D-G: Deot-Geoli; J-C: Jab-Chaegi; Oe-B: Oen-
Baejigi; D-B: Deul-Baejigi; G-C: Ggatdan-Chigi; Or-D: Oreun-Dwijypgi; Oe-D: Oen-Dwijypgi; D-D: Dwiro-Dwijypgi. 
*Significantly different from nonathletes, p &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 28, No. 2, 2016 </p>



<p>Table 2. Differences in respiratory function between the nonathletes and Korean wrestling athletes </p>

<p>Variable 
Nonathletes 
Korean Wrestling Athletes 
FVC (L) 
4.9 ± 0.5 
5.2 ± 0.4 * 
FEV1.0 (L) 
4.1 ± 0.4 
4.6 ± 0.4 * 
FEV1.0/FVC (%) 
84.1 ± 6.1 
87.8 ± 4.5 * 
PEF (L/s) 
9.2 ± 1.4 
10.5 ± 1.4 * 
PIF (L/s) 
6.4 ± 1.2 
7.3 ± 1.7 * 
SVC (L) 
4.8 ± 0.6 
5.2 ± 0.6 * 
ERV (L) 
1.5 ± 0.4 
1.5 ± 0.5 
IRV (L) 
2.4 ± 0.6 
2.6 ± 0.5 
TV (L) 
0.7 ± 0.3 
1.2 ± 0.6 * 
MVV (L/min) 
161.5 ± 30.5 
171.6 ± 33.3 
RR (L/min) 
94.5 ± 17.9 
91.1 ± 32.7 
TV (L/min) 
1.7 ± 0.4 
1.9 ± 0.5 
MV (L/min) 
12.8 ± 6.0 
19.0 ± 6.2 * 
RR (L/min) 
27.1 ± 6.8 
21.6 ± 7.3 * 
TV (L/min) 
0.5 ± 0.3 
0.9 ± 0.3 * </p>

<p>All data are presented as the mean±SE. FVC: forced vital capacity; FEV1.0: forced expiratory volume 
in one second; FEV1.0/FVC: FEV1.0/FVC ratio, PEF: peak expiratory flow; PIF: peak inspiratory 
flow; SVC: slow vital capacity; IRV: inspiratory reserve volume; ERV: expiratory reserve volume; TV: 
tidal volume; MVV: maximum voluntary ventilation; MV: minute ventilation; RR: respiratory rate 
*Significantly different from nonathletes, p &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>Table 3. Differences in respirogram phases of forced vital capacity between the nonathletes and Korean 
wrestling athletes </p>

<p>Variable 
Nonathletes 
Korean Wrestling Athletes </p>

<p>aFVC 
ExA 
20,026.3 ± 2,966.2 
24,429.5 ± 10,269.5 * 
InsA 
22,449.5 ± 6,610.4 
25,101.1 ± 16,417.0 
Total 
42,475.8 ± 8,039.3 
49,530.6 ± 21,591.9 * 
sFVC 
AS1 
10.3 ± 3.1 
12.1 ± 4.0 * 
AS2 
5.6 ± 2.4 
7.1 ± 3.3 * 
AS3 
1.9 ± 1.0 
2.6 ± 1.4 * 
BS1 
−1.4 ± 0.8 
−1.5 ± 0.8 
BS2 
−1.4 ± 0.6 
−1.3 ± 0.4 
BS3 
−1.4 ± 0.5 
−1.2 ± 0.4 
CS1 
2.7 ± 1.7 
2.5 ± 1.0 
CS2 
0.5 ± 4.4 
1.0 ± 0.4 
CS3 
0.5 ± 0.4 
0.5 ± 0.3 
DS1 
−0.3 ± 0.3 
−0.4 ± 0.3 
DS2 
−0.7 ± 0.5 
−0.6 ± 0.4 
DS3 
−1.7 ± 1.1 
−1.8 ± 1.0 </p>

<p>All data are presented as the mean±SE. aFVC: area of forced vital capacity; ExA: expiratory area; InsA: inspi-
ratory area; Total: total area; sFVC: slope of forced vital capacity; AS1: first slope of the A area; AS2: second 
slope of the A area; AS3: third slope of the A area; BS1: first slope of the B area; BS2: second slope of the B 
area; BS3: third slope of the B area; CS1: first slope of the C area; CS2: second slope of the C area; CS3: third 
slope of the C area; DS1: first slope of the D area; DS2: second slope of the D area; DS3: third slope of the D 
area. *Significantly different from nonathletes, p &lt; 0.05 </p>





<p>Table 5. Correlation coefficients of the circumference and slope of forced vital capacity </p>

<p>sFVC 
Chest circumference 
Abdominal circumference 
Rest 
ExP 
InsP 
DER 
DIR 
Rest 
ExP 
InsP 
DER 
DIR </p>

<p>AS1 
−0.247 
−0.262 
−0.192 
0.080 
0.156 
−0.229 
−0.212 
−0.197 
−0.301 
0.174 
AS2 
0.025 
−0.017 
0.063 
0.280 
0.202 
0.093 
0.084 
0.120 
0.128 
0.297 
AS3 
−0.571 * 
−0.600 * 
−0.588 * 
0.463 
0.069 
−0.464 
−0.451 
−0.470 
−0.109 
0.012 
BS1 
0.058 
0.010 
0.138 
0.335 
0.427 
0.106 
0.098 
0.076 
0.173 
−0.143 
BS2 
0.081 
0.042 
0.137 
0.059 
0.071 
0.064 
0.035 
0.113 
0.084 
0.269 
BS3 
−0.310 
−0.365 
−0.301 
0.549 * 
0.305 
−0.128 
−0.154 
−0.096 
0.371 
0.465 
CS1 
0.062 
0.087 
−0.001 
0.036 
−0.031 
0.022 
0.045 
0.010 
0.046 
0.125 
CS2 
0.313 
0.334 
0.317 
−0.305 
−0.075 
0.081 
0.114 
0.062 
−0.333 
−0.264 
CS3 
0.295 
0.266 
0.322 
−0.093 
−0.102 
0.163 
0.180 
0.166 
−0.268 
−0.157 
DS1 
−0.063 
0.038 
−0.019 
−0.578 * 
0.196 
−0.110 
−0.114 
−0.128 
−0.003 
−0.175 
DS2 
−0.014 
0.051 
0.020 
−0.016 
0.516 * 
−0.080 
−0.082 
−0.081 
0.328 
0.339 
DS3 
0.340 
0.374 
0.366 
−0.018 
0.428 
0.342 
0.333 
0.330 
0.444 
0.245 </p>

<p>sFVC: slope of forced vital capacity; ExP: expiration condition; InsP: inspiration condition; DER: differences between expiration and 
rest; DIR: differences between inspiration and rest; AS1-3: first, second, and third slopes of the A area; BS1-3: first, second, and third 
slopes of the B area; CS1-3: first, second, and third slopes of the C area; DS1-3: first, second, and third slopes of the D area. *p&lt;0.05 </p>

<p>Table 4. Correlation coefficients of the circumference and area of forced vital capacity </p>

<p>aFVC 
Chest circumference 
Abdominal circumference 
Rest 
ExP 
InsP 
DER 
DIR 
Rest 
ExP 
InsP 
DER 
DIR 
ExA 
0.038 
0.038 
0.073 
−0.084 
0.066 
−0.256 
−0.245 
−0.261 
−0.242 
−0.177 
InsA 
−0.161 
−0.156 
−0.167 
0.030 
−0.008 
−0.234 
−0.261 
−0.180 
0.152 
0.467 
Total 
−0.115 
−0.111 
−0.103 
−0.015 
0.024 
−0.311 
−0.329 
−0.269 
0.007 
0.284 </p>

<p>aFVC: area of forced vital capacity; ExP: expiratory condition; InsP: inspiratory condition; DER: differences between expiration and 
rest; DIR: differences between inspiration and rest; ExA: expiratory area; InsA: inspiratory area; Total: total area </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 28, No. 2, 2016 </p>





</text></tei>