<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4713128" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT Genes occupy preferred spatial positions within interphase cell nuclei. However, 
positioning patterns are not an innate feature of a locus, and genes can alter their localization 
in response to physiological and pathological changes. Here we screen the radial positioning 
patterns of 40 genes in normal, hyperplasic, and malignant human prostate tissues. We find 
that the overall spatial organization of the genome in prostate tissue is largely conserved 
among individuals. We identify three genes whose nuclear positions are robustly altered in 
neoplastic prostate tissues. FLI1 and MMP9 position differently in prostate cancer than in 
normal tissue and prostate hyperplasia, whereas MMP2 is repositioned in both prostate can-
cer and hyperplasia. Our data point to locus-specific reorganization of the genome during 
prostate disease. </p>

<p>The interphase nucleus is a highly organized organelle, with genes 
and chromosomes occupying preferred locations within the cell 
nucleus (Ferrai et al., 2010; Meaburn et al., 2016). Although the spa-
tial organization of the genome is largely conserved among indi-
viduals (Borden and Manuelidis, 1988; Wiech et al., 2005; Murata 
et al., 2007; Meaburn et al., 2009; Timme et al., 2011), nuclear loca-
tion is not an inherent feature of a locus, since gene loci can occupy 
distinct positions depending on context or conditions. For example, 
gene positions may differ among tissue types during differentiation 
or as cells become quiescent or senescent (Bridger et al., 2000; 
Boyle et al., 2001; Kosak et al., 2002; Parada et al., 2004; Meaburn 
and Misteli, 2008; Meaburn et al., 2016; Takizawa et al., 2008a; 
Ferrai et al., 2010; Peric-Hupkes et al., 2010; Foster et al., 2012). </p>

<p>Although the molecular mechanisms that govern the nuclear posi-
tion of a gene are unknown, changes in gene positioning are some-
times, but not always, correlated with functional changes, such as 
altered transcription levels or replication timing or with epigenetic 
changes to chromatin (Kosak et al., 2002; Williams et al., 2006; 
Hiratani et al., 2008; Meaburn and Misteli, 2008; Meaburn et al., 
2016; Takizawa et al., 2008a; Morey et al., 2009; Ferrai et al., 2010; 
Peric-Hupkes et al., 2010; Towbin et al., 2012; Kind et al., 2013; 
Therizols et al., 2014; Rafique et al., 2015). 
There is accumulating evidence that spatial reorganization of the 
genome is a pathological feature, with repositioning of individual 
genes or genomic regions detected in a wide range of diseases, 
including epilepsy (Borden and Manuelidis, 1988), laminopathies 
(Meaburn et al., 2007; Mewborn et al., 2010; Mehta et al., 2011), 
parasitic or viral infection (Li et al., 2010; Knight et al., 2011; Arican-
Goktas et al., 2014), Down syndrome (Paz et al., 2015), endometrio-
sis (Mikelsaar et al., 2014), and cancer (Cremer et al., 2003; Murata 
et al., 2007; Meaburn and Misteli, 2008; Meaburn et al., 2009; Zeitz 
et al., 2013). For example, in cultured fibroblasts from laminopathy 
patients, some chromosomes, such as chromosomes (HSAs) 13 and 
18, occupy altered nuclear positions, although others, including 
HSAX and HSA4, are unaffected (Meaburn et al., 2007; Mewborn 
et al., 2010; Mehta et al., 2011). Similarly, in brain tissue from epi-
lepsy patients, the centromere of HSAX is relocated but 1q12, 9q12, 
and Y12 are not (Borden and Manuelidis, 1988). 
Spatial genome reorganization has been associated with cancer. 
HSA18 and HSA19, which in many cell types are peripherally and </p>

<p>Monitoring Editor 
Orna Cohen-Fix 
National Institutes of Health </p>

<p>Received: May 22, 2015 
Revised: Sep 28, 2015 
Accepted: Nov 5, 2015 </p>

<p>This article was published online ahead of print in MBoC in Press (http://www 
.molbiolcell.org/cgi/doi/10.1091/mbc.E15-05-0280) on November 12, 2015. 
Address correspondence to: Tom Misteli (mistelit@mail.nih.gov), Karen J. 
Meaburn (meaburnk@mail.nih.gov). </p>

<p>© 2016 Leshner et al. This article is distributed by The American Society for Cell 
Biology under license from the author(s). Two months after publication it is avail-
able to the public under an Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unport-
ed Creative Commons License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc 
-sa/3.0). 
"ASCB </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>," "The American Society for Cell Biology </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>," and "Molecular Biology of 
the Cell 
® " are registered trademarks of The American Society for Cell Biology. </p>

<p>Abbreviations used: EDT, Euclidean distance transform; FFPE, Formalin-fixed, 
paraffin-embedded; FISH, fluorescence in situ hybridization; HSA, human chro-
mosome; KS, Kolmogorov-Smirnov; NAT, normal adjacent to tumor; PND, 
pooled normal distribution; RRD, relative radial distribution. </p>

<p>Marc Leshner </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, Michelle Devine </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, Gregory W. Roloff </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, Lawrence D. True </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>, Tom Misteli </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, 
and Karen J. Meaburn </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD 20892; </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Department of Pathology, University of 
Washington, Seattle, WA 98195 </p>

<p>Volume 27 January 15, 2016 </p>

<p>Gene repositioning in prostate cancer | 237 </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Comprehensive mapping of gene positioning 
in prostate tissue </p>

<p>Analogous to our approach with regard to breast cancer (Meaburn 
et al., 2009), we screened the positioning patterns of 40 genes (Sup-
plemental Table S1) in prostate specimens to identify genes that 
reposition in prostate cancer. To this end, to map comprehensively 
the spatial position of genes in normal and malignant prostate tis-
sue, we combined fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) with 
quantitative imaging to map the nuclear positions of our set of 
genes in 4-to 5-μm-thick FFPE human prostate tissues (Supplemen-
tal Table S2). The panel of tissues used includes 30 prostate carcino-
mas, five hyperplasic (nonmalignant abnormality) tissues, and 29 
normal or normal adjacent to tumor (NAT) tissues (Supplemental 
Table S2). The eight genes previously identified to reposition in 
breast cancer tissues (Meaburn et al., 2009), do not reposition in 
prostate (unpublished data), and we were unable to identify any par-
ticular characteristics of repositioning genes in breast cancer that 
predicted repositioning potential (Meaburn et al., 2009). Therefore 
we screened a wide range of genes in prostate tissues, which in-
cluded many of the most important genes related to prostate can-
cer, such as genes reported to be misregulated in prostate cancer or 
to participate in translocations, as well as a set of randomly selected 
genes, which were selected independently of known changes in ac-
tivity or involvement in prostate cancer development or progres-
sion. The test set included genes from 21 different chromosomes 
(Supplemental Table S1). To map the nuclear locations of individual 
genes in a given tissue, we determined the radial position of each 
allele in typically 100-200 randomly selected epithelial nuclei on 
projections of three-dimensional image stacks using Euclidean dis-
tance transform (EDT) after automated FISH signal detection, as pre-
viously described (Meaburn et al., 2009; see Materials and Methods 
for details). For each candidate gene, the positions, normalized to 
the nuclear radius to eliminate nuclear size effects, of all measured 
alleles in a tissue were combined and represented as a cumulative 
relative radial distribution (RRD). Statistical difference between the 
cumulative RRDs of different samples was assessed using the non-
parametric two-sample one-dimensional (1D) Kolmogorov-Smirnov 
(KS) test as previously described (Meaburn et al., 2009; see Materials 
and Methods). 
To screen for genes that specifically reposition in prostate cancer, 
we used a previously described screening strategy (Meaburn et al., 
2009). Briefly, gene positions were first compared in at least three 
normal and three cancerous prostate tissues (Table 1 and Supple-
mental Figure 1A). Genes that repositioned in the majority of can-
cers, in the absence of a large variability among normal tissues, were 
then screened in a larger number of tissues (Table 1 and Supplemen-
tal Figure 1A). Finally, the sensitivity and specificity of the reposition-
ing events of the top hits were assessed by positioning these genes 
in hyperplasic tissues and determining false-positive and false-neg-
ative rates (Supplemental Figure 1A; see later discussion for 
details). </p>

<p>Conservation of positioning patterns in morphologically 
normal prostate tissues </p>

<p>It is unknown how similar positioning patterns are between pros-
tates from different individuals, yet knowing the level of interindi-
vidual variability in the positioning pattern of a given gene is critical 
in determining whether any repositioning detected in cancer tissues 
is specific to cancer or simply a product of interindividual variability. 
Potential variability of positioning patterns is particularly relevant in 
the prostate, since the position of several genes has been shown to </p>

<p>internally located, respectively, broadly maintained their positions in 
cell lines derived from various cancers, including colon and cervical 
cancer, melanoma, and Hodgkin's disease, although they tend to be 
in closer proximity, and a small fraction of nuclei have inverted the 
locations of these two chromosomes (Boyle et al., 2001; Cremer 
et al., 2003; Meaburn et al., 2007). Similarly, HSA19 is also shifted to 
a more peripheral position in tumors of a subset of thyroid cancer 
patients (Murata et al., 2007). Moreover, HSA18 and the BCL2 gene 
are shifted to a more peripheral position in invasive cervical squa-
mous carcinoma compared with the apical, but not basal, layer of 
nonneoplastic squamous epithelium (Wiech et al., 2009). In both an 
in vitro model of breast cancer and breast cancer tissues, ∼40% of 
the tested genes were in altered locations (Meaburn and Misteli, 
2008; Meaburn et al., 2009). Of importance, most of these gene-
repositioning events are specific to the oncogenic state and do not 
occur in benign breast disease (Meaburn et al., 2009). Not only 
might the position of a genomic region change in relation to the 
nuclear edge or center (radial positioning) in cancer, but its position 
relative to its neighbors might also be affected. For instance, the 
group of loci that are in close spatial proximity to the IGFBP3 locus 
is significantly changed in breast cancer cell lines compared with a 
normal control (Zeitz et al., 2013). 
Spatial genome reorganization in cancer, however, is not a 
global event. The positions of many genomic regions remain con-
served in cancer (Kozubek et al., 2002; Parada et al., 2002; Wiech 
et al., 2005; Meaburn and Misteli, 2008; Meaburn et al., 2009; 
Timme et al., 2011). For example, the radial position of HSA8 in 
pancreatic cancer (Timme et al., 2011) and HSA10 in most thyroid 
cancers (Murata et al., 2007) is similar to that in normal tissue, and 
the position of the majority of genes analyzed in breast cancer 
(Wiech et al., 2005; Meaburn and Misteli, 2008; Meaburn et al., 
2009) and leukemia (Kozubek et al., 2002) are unaffected. Similarly, 
the preferred clustering of chromosomes 12, 14, and 15 is main-
tained in a mouse lymphoma cell line compared with cultured 
spleenocytes (Parada et al., 2002). 
Prostate cancer is highly prevalent. In the United States alone, 
&gt;220,000 new cases are diagnosed each year, with one in seven 
men developing prostate cancer during their lifetime, and there 
are &gt;27,500 deaths from it annually, accounting for 9% of all male 
cancer deaths (Siegel et al., 2015). A major challenge in the treat-
ment of prostate cancer patients is the difficulty of distinguishing 
indolent from aggressive cancer. As a result, a large number of 
patients receive unnecessary treatment for cancers that will likely 
remain asymptomatic during their lifetime (Draisma et al., 2009; 
Cooperberg et al., 2010). There is also a subset of patients with 
high-risk prostate cancer who are undertreated and are not receiv-
ing the treatment their cancer requires to ensure disease-free sur-
vival (Cooperberg et al., 2010). Emerging evidence suggests that 
changes in nuclear architecture features, such as nuclear shape or 
global levels and patterns of histone modifications and nuclear 
lamin proteins, may have a clinical value for prostate cancer detec-
tion and prognosis (Veltri and Christudass, 2014). However, 
whereas spatial (re)organization of the genome has been proposed 
to have diagnostic potential for breast cancer (Meaburn and 
Misteli, 2008; Meaburn et al., 2009), little is known about spatial 
genome organization in prostate cancer. 
We performed an unbiased screen of the position of 40 genes in 
Formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded (FFPE) human prostate tissues. 
Although we find limited variability in gene positioning patterns 
among individuals and general conservation of positioning patterns 
in cancer, we identified three genes that undergo disease-specific 
repositioning in prostate cancer. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>be sensitive to androgen (Lin et al., 2009; Mani et al., 2009). To de-
termine the degree of variability in gene localization among indi-
viduals, we compared the positioning pattern of our set of 40 genes 
among morphologically normal prostate tissues. For most of the 
genes analyzed, the radial distribution of the gene among normal 
prostate tissues was similar (Table 1, Figures 1 and 2, and Supple-
mental Figures S1 and S2). For 12 of 40 (30.0%) genes, the RRDs 
were statistically identical among all individuals (p &gt; 0.01; Table 1, 
Figures 1 and 2, and Supplemental Figures S1 and S2). An addi-
tional 20 genes (50.0%), although not identical among all compari-
sons, were very similarly positioned among most individuals, with 
&lt;33.4% of cross-comparisons being statistically significantly differ-
ent (p &lt; 0.01; Table 1, Figures 1 and 2, and Supplemental Figures S1 
and S2). The position of 20% of genes (8 of 40; CCND1 [3 of 6 cross-
comparisons], ERG [5 of 10], LMNA [3 of 6], TGFB1 [3 of 6], TIMP2 
[8 of 15], TIMP3 [9 of 15], TMPRSS2 [9 of 15] and VIM [7of 10]) were 
highly variable among individuals, with 50-70% of the cross-com-
parisons among normal tissues being significantly different (Table 1, 
Figures 1 and 2, and Supplemental Figures S1 and S2). 
Because the position of a gene in a given tissue can be signifi-
cantly different from some but not all other tissues, as an additional 
measure of conservation in positioning patterns among individuals, 
we compared the RRD of each gene in each normal tissue to a 
pooled normal distribution (PND). The PND is used as a standard-
ized "average" position of a gene within normal tissues and was 
generated by combining the RRDs from all normal tissues analyzed 
into a single distribution for each gene, as previously described 
(Meaburn et al., 2009; see Materials and Methods). Again we found 
a high level of similarity among individuals (Table 2, Figures 1 and 2, 
and Supplemental Figures S1 and S2). For 26 of the 40 (65.0%) 
genes, no individual's normal tissue was significantly different from 
the PND, and an additional eight (20.0%) genes had only a single 
normal tissue significantly different to the PND (7.7-25% of normal 
tissues; Table 2, Figures 1 and 2, and Supplemental Figures S1 and 
S2). On the other hand, three genes (3 of 40; 7.5%)-FGFR1 (2 of 7 
normal tissues), TMPRSS2 (2 of 6), and RAF1 (3 of 8)-had approxi-
mately one-third (28.6-37.5%) of normal tissues significantly differ-
ent from the PND, and an additional three genes (CCND1 [2 of 4], 
TIMP2 [3 of 6], and TIMP3 [4 of 6]) were significantly different from 
the PND in 50.0-66.7% of normal tissues (Table 2 and Supplemental 
Figures S1 and S2). Taken together, these data demonstrate that the 
radial positions of most genes are conserved among prostate tissue 
from different individuals. However, the position of a subset of 
genes is variable among individuals. </p>

<p>Identification of repositioned genes in prostate cancer </p>

<p>Having established limited variability in gene positioning among in-
dividuals, we screened for genes that reposition in prostate cancer. 
We compared the RRDs of 39 genes in multiple cancer tissues to 
individual normal tissues and to the PND (Tables 1 and 2, Figures 1 
and 2, and Supplemental Figures S1 and S2). The position of nine 
genes (23.1%) was indistinguishable in all cross-comparisons among 
individual normal and cancer tissues, and an additional 19 genes 
(48.7%) had only limited variability between normal and cancer tis-
sues, with 5.0-33.3% of cross-comparisons reaching significance. 
Nine genes (23.1%; CCND1 [6 of 16 comparisons], ERG [6 of 15], 
VIM [43 of 91], FGFR2 [10 of 24], MMP9 [84 of 190], MMP14 [4 of 9], 
VEGFA [43 of 91], MMP2 [62 of 128], and TMPRSS2 [12 of 24]) were 
differently positioned in 37.5-50.0% of cross-comparisons. Two 
genes (5.1%; TIMP3 [14 of 24] and FLI1 [68 of 112]) were reposi-
tioned in ∼60% of cross-comparisons between normal and malig-
nant prostate tissues (Table 1, Figures 1 and 2, and Supplemental </p>

<p>Gene </p>

<p>Number of 
tissues </p>

<p>Percentage (number) of SD 
cross-comparisons among: </p>

<p>Normal Cancer </p>

<p>Individual 
normal tissues </p>

<p>Individual 
normal and 
cancer tissues </p>

<p>AR 
7 
6 
9.5 (2/21) 
16.7 (7/42) </p>

<p>BCL2 
4 
4 
0.0 (0/6) 
0.0 (0/16) </p>

<p>BRCA2 
4 
3 
0.0 (0/6) 
0.0 (0/12) </p>

<p>CCND1 
4 
4 
50.0 (3/6) 
37.5 (6/16) </p>

<p>DCN 
5 
3 
20.0 (2/10) 
0.0 (0/15) </p>

<p>EGFR 
6 
4 
0.0 (0/15) 
0.0 (0/24) </p>

<p>ERG 
5 
3 
50.0 (5/10) 
40.0 (6/15) </p>

<p>ESR2 
5 
4 
0.0 (0/10) 
0.0 (0/20) </p>

<p>ETV1 
5 
3 
0.0 (0/10) 
0.0 (0/15) </p>

<p>FGFR1 
7 
5 
28.6 (6/21) 
22.9 (8/35) </p>

<p>FGFR2 
6 
4 
33.3 (5/15) 
41.7 (10/24) </p>

<p>FLI1 
8 
14 
7.1 (2/28) 
60.7 (68/112) </p>

<p>FOXA1 
4 
4 
0.0 (0/6) 
0.0 (0/16) </p>

<p>FUT4 
4 
3 
0.0 (0/6) 
0.0 (0/12) </p>

<p>GREB1 
4 
3 
16.7 (1/6) 
25.0 (3/12) </p>

<p>HOXA9 
4 
3 
0.0 (0/6) 
8.3 (1/12) </p>

<p>KLK3 
5 
4 
20.0 (2/10) 
30 (6/20) </p>

<p>LMNA 
4 
3 
50.0 (3/6) 
16.7 (2/12) </p>

<p>MATR3 
4 
3 
33.3 (2/6) 
0.0 (0/12) </p>

<p>MMP1 
3 
3 
33.3 (1/3) 
11.1 (1/9) </p>

<p>MMP14 
3 
3 
33.3 (1/3) 
44.4 (4/9) </p>

<p>MMP2 
8 
16 
7.1 (2/28) 
48.4 (62/128) </p>

<p>MMP9 
10 
19 
17.8 (8/45) 
44.2 (84/190) </p>

<p>NPM1 
3 
3 
33.3 (1/3) 
33.3 (3/9) </p>

<p>NUMA1 
4 
4 
0.0 (0/6) 
12.5 (2/16) </p>

<p>PADI4/6 
6 
6 
13.3 (2/15) 
5.6 (2/36) </p>

<p>PTEN 
3 
3 
0.0 (0/3) 
22.2 (2/9) </p>

<p>RAF1 
8 
5 
32.1 (9/28) 
30.0 (12/40) </p>

<p>SATB1 
5 
4 
20.0 (2/10) 
15.0 (3/20) </p>

<p>SERPINB2 
4 
4 
16.7 (1/6) 
6.3 (1/16) </p>

<p>SLC45A3 
5 
0 
0.0 (0/10) 
ND </p>

<p>SP100 
5 
4 
0.0 (0/10) 
20.0 (4/20) </p>

<p>SPDEF 
5 
4 
10.0 (1/10) 
5.0 (1/20) </p>

<p>TGFB1 
4 
4 
50.0 (3/6) 
30.0 (5/16) </p>

<p>THBS1 
5 
4 
20.0 (2/10) 
30.0 (6/20) </p>

<p>TIMP2 
6 
7 
53.3 (8/15) 
33.3 (14/42) </p>

<p>TIMP3 
6 
4 
60.0 (9/15) 
58.3 (14/24) </p>

<p>TMPRSS2 
6 
4 
60.0 (9/15) 
50.0 (12/24) </p>

<p>VEGFA 
13 
7 
24.4 (19/78) 
47.3 (43/91) </p>

<p>VIM 
5 
4 
70.0 (7/10) 
40.0 (8/20) </p>

<p>SD, significantly different, based on a KS test, p &lt; 0.01. ND, not determined. </p>

<p>TABLE 1: Cross-comparisons among individual tissues. </p>

<p>Volume 27 January 15, 2016 </p>

<p>Gene repositioning in prostate cancer | 239 </p>

<p>mal and cancer tissues, 60.0% (9 of 15) of cross-comparisons were 
statistically different when normal tissues were cross-compared with 
each other (Table 1 and Supplemental Figure S2). Taking into con-
sideration the degree of positioning changes in all cross-compari-
sons and the interindividual variability of candidates, we identified 
three genes-MMP2, MMP9, and FLI1-that exhibited robust </p>

<p>Figures S1 and S2). For most genes, the number of significantly dif-
ferent cross-comparisons between normal and cancer specimens 
was not greater than that of the cross-comparisons among normal 
tissues, suggesting that the repositioning was not cancer specific 
(Table 1). For example, whereas TIMP3 was differently positioned in 
58.3% (14 of 24) of the cross-comparisons between individual nor-</p>

<p>FIGURE 1: Gene-specific spatial reorganization of the genome in prostate cancer. (A, B) Gene loci were detected by 
FISH in FFPE prostate tissue sections. Blue, 4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole nuclear counterstain. Projected image stacks. 
(A) EGFR (red) and SPDEF (green) gene loci, in a malignant prostate tissue. Bar, 10 μm. (B) FLI1, MMP9, and MMP2 gene 
loci (red) in normal and cancer tissues. Bar, 5 μm. (C) Cumulative RRDs for the indicated genes in prostate cancer (red), 
normal prostate tissues (black), and the pooled normal distribution (PND, blue). The positioning patterns of some but 
not all genes are different in prostate cancer compared with normal tissues. RRP, relative radial position. </p>

<p>MMP9 </p>

<p>FOXA1 </p>

<p>y 
c 
n 
e 
u 
q 
e 
r 
f 
e 
v 
i 
t 
a 
l 
u 
m 
u 
C </p>

<p>Periphery 
Center 
RRP </p>

<p>0 0 
0.4 
1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>FLI1 </p>

<p>0 0 
0.4 
1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0 0 
0.4 
1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>ETV1 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>0 0 
0.4 
1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>RRP </p>

<p>RRP 
RRP </p>

<p>y 
c 
n 
e 
u 
q 
e 
r 
f 
e 
v 
i 
t 
a 
l 
u 
m 
u 
C </p>

<p>MMP2 </p>

<p>KLK3 </p>

<p>0 0 
0.4 
1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0 0 
0.4 
1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>RRP </p>

<p>RRP </p>

<p>TGFB1 </p>

<p>0 0 
0.4 
1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>SPDEF </p>

<p>0 0 
0.4 
1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>RRP 
RRP </p>

<p>y 
c 
n 
e 
u 
q 
e 
r 
f 
e 
v 
i 
t 
a 
l 
u 
m 
u 
C </p>

<p>Pooled normal 
Normal 
Cancer </p>

<p>A 
B 
MMP9 
FLI1 
MMP2 </p>

<p>Normal </p>

<p>Cancer </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>differential radial positioning between nor-
mal and cancer tissues. For these genes, the 
percentage of cross-comparisons between 
normal and cancer tissues was higher by 
&gt;25% than when normal tissues were com-
pared with each other (48.4 vs. 7.1%, 44.2 
vs. 17.8%, and 60.7 vs. 7.1%, respectively; 
Table 1 and Figure 2). 
Repositioning of FLI1, MMP9, and MMP2 
in prostate cancers was confirmed by analy-
sis of their distributions in individual cancer 
samples to their PNDs. Most genes in the 
test set displayed limited repositioning in 
prostate cancer tissues compared with their 
PNDs. Two-thirds (26) of genes were reposi-
tioned in 0-33.3% of cancer tissues com-
pared with the PND, and six genes reposi-
tioned in 40-50% of cancers (Table 2, 
Figures 1 and 2, and Supplemental Figures 
S1 and S2). As observed in the cross-com-
parison analysis, FLI1, MMP9, and MMP2 
showed robust repositioning in prostate 
cancer, and their distributions were distinct 
from their PNDs in 92.9% (13 of 14 of cancer 
tissues), 68.4% (13 of 19), and 56.3% (9 of 
16) of cancers, respectively (Table 2 and 
Figures 1 and 2). Although an additional 
four genes were also repositioned in &gt;50% 
of cancers compared with the PND (VEGF, 
57.1% [4 of 7]; MMP14, 66.7% [2 of 3]; 
NPM1, 66.7% [2 of 3]; and TMPRSS2, 75% 
[3 of 4]; Table 2 and Supplemental Figures 
S1 and S2), we classified these genes as 
low-priority hits and did not pursue them 
further because the percentage of cross-
comparisons between normal and cancer 
tissues was not significantly higher than the 
variability detected among normal tissues 
and visual inspection of the cumulative fre-
quency distribution plots revealed that only 
a small number of the distributions in cancer 
tissues fell outside the range of the normal 
tissues (Supplemental Figure S1). 
In the vast majority (96 of 125; 76.8%) of 
cases, there was a similar repositioning be-
havior when a cancer was compared with its 
matched NAT or with the PND (Figure 2 and 
Supplemental Figure S2). This observation 
suggests that repositioning, if present in a 
patient, is limited to the cancer tissue itself 
and that comparison to the PND is suitable 
to assess whether a gene is repositioned in 
cancer, even when no normal tissue from 
the same individual is available. 
We were unable to define any feature of 
a prostate cancer that predicted the likeli-
hood of a gene repositioning within it. The 
propensity of the three marker genes to re-
position in a given cancer was not linked to 
changes in copy number (Supplemental 
Table S3), nor was the variation in their 
positioning patterns correlated with the </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Gene-specific repositioning in prostate cancer. Heat maps representing the pairwise 
statistical comparisons of radial positioning patterns of indicated genes among tissues using the 
two-sample 1D KS test. Although positioning patterns are statistically similar (blue, brown) 
among most normal tissues (N1-N28; see Supplemental Table S2), they can be divergent (red, 
orange, yellow) in cancer tissues (C1-C24; see Supplemental Table S2). Black and white asterisks 
indicate a cross-comparison between a normal and cancer specimens from the same individual. 
PND, pooled normal distribution. </p>

<p>N1 
N2 
N3 
N4 
N5 
N12 
N13 
N15 </p>

<p>FLI1 </p>

<p>N2 
N3 
N4 
N5 
N12 
N13 
N15 
C1 
C2 
C3 
C4 
C5 
C6 
C7 
C8 
C9 
C10 
C11 
C12 
C13 
C14 </p>

<p>* 
* * </p>

<p>N7 
N8 
N14 
N15 
N16 
N19 
N20 
N21 
N22 
N23 </p>

<p>MMP9 </p>

<p>N8 
N14 
N15 
N16 
N19 
N20 
N21 
N22 
N23 
C3 
C4 
C5 
C6 
C7 
C8 
C10 
C11 
C12 
C13 
C14 
C15 
C16 
C17 
C18 
C19 
C20 
C21 
C22 </p>

<p>N5 
N7 
N15 
N16 
N21 
N22 
N24 
N25 </p>

<p>MMP2 </p>

<p>N7 
N15 
N16 
N21 
N22 
N24 
N25 
C3 
C4 
C5 
C6 
C7 
C8 
C10 
C11 
C12 
C13 
C14 
C15 
C16 
C17 
C23 
C24 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* 
* * 
* * * </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>N8 
N9 
N19 
N20 
N22 </p>

<p>N9 
N19 
N20 
N22 </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>ETV1 </p>

<p>C18 
C19 
C21 </p>

<p>N5 
N14 
N23 
N28 </p>

<p>N14 
N23 
N28 </p>

<p>* * </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>FOXA1 </p>

<p>C4 
C22 
C26 
C28 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>N5 
N15 
N22 
N24 
N25 </p>

<p>N15 
N22 
N24 
N25 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>KLK3 </p>

<p>C4 
C22 
C26 
C28 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>N5 
N14 
N21 
N24 
N25 </p>

<p>N14 
N21 
N24 
N25 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>SPDEF </p>

<p>C4 
C20 
C23 
C24 </p>

<p>* 
* * </p>

<p>N5 
N12 
N16 
N28 </p>

<p>N12 
N16 
N28 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>PND </p>

<p>TGFB1 </p>

<p>C3 
C15 
C28 
C29 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P &gt; 0.05 
P &lt; 0.05 
P &lt; 0.01 
P &lt; 0.001 
P &lt; </p>

<p>Volume 27 January 15, 2016 </p>

<p>Gene repositioning in prostate cancer | 241 </p>

<p>clinicopathologically defined aggressiveness of the cancer (Supple-
mental Table S2 and Figure 3). </p>

<p>Cancer specificity of FLI1 and MMP9 repositioning </p>

<p>Given that loci can alter their nuclear location in diseases other than 
cancer (Borden and Manuelidis, 1988; Meaburn et al., 2007, 2009), 
we sought to determine whether the repositioning of FLI1, MMP9, 
and MMP2 was specific to cancer or was a more general feature of 
prostate disease. We compared the radial positioning patterns of </p>

<p>Gene </p>

<p>Percentage (number) of SD 
cross-comparisons between: </p>

<p>Individual normal 
tissues and pooled 
normal </p>

<p>Individual cancer 
tissues and pooled 
normal </p>

<p>AR 
0.0 (0/7) 
33.3 (2/6) </p>

<p>BCL2 
0.0 (0/4) 
0.0 (0/4) </p>

<p>BRCA2 
0.0 (0/4) 
33.3 (1/3) </p>

<p>CCND1 
50.0 (2/4) 
25.0 (1/4) </p>

<p>DCN 
0.0 (0/5) 
0.0 (0/3) </p>

<p>EGFR 
0.0 (0/6) 
0.0 (0/4) </p>

<p>ERG 
20.0 (1/5) 
33.3 (1/3) </p>

<p>ESR2 
0.0 (0/5) 
0.0 (0/4) </p>

<p>ETV1 
0.0 (0/5) 
0.0 (0/3) </p>

<p>FGFR1 
28.6 (2/7) 
40.0 (2/5) </p>

<p>FGFR2 
16.7 (1/6) 
50.0 (2/4) </p>

<p>FLI1 
12.5 (1/8) 
92.9 (13/14) </p>

<p>FOXA1 
0.0 (0/4) 
0.0 (0/4) </p>

<p>FUT4 
0.0 (0/4) 
0.0 (0/3) </p>

<p>GREB1 
25.0 (1/4) 
0.0 (0/3) </p>

<p>HOXA9 
0.0 (0/4) 
33.3 (1/3) </p>

<p>KLK3 
20.0 (1/5) 
25.0 (1/4) </p>

<p>LMNA 
0.0 (0/4) 
33.3 (1/3) </p>

<p>MATR3 
0.0 (0/4) 
0.0 (0/3) </p>

<p>MMP1 
0.0 (0/3) 
0.0 (0/3) </p>

<p>MMP14 
0.0 (0/3) 
66.7 (2/3) </p>

<p>MMP2 
0.0 (0/8) 
56.3 (9/16) </p>

<p>MMP9 
10.0 (1/10) 
68.4 (13/19) </p>

<p>NPM1 
0.0 (0/3) 
66.7 (2/3) </p>

<p>NUMA1 
0.0 (0/4) 
50.0 (2/4) </p>

<p>PADI4/6 
0.0 (0/6) 
16.7 (1/6) </p>

<p>PTEN 
0.0 (0/3) 
0.0 (0/3) </p>

<p>RAF1 
37.5 (3/8) 
40.0 (2/5) </p>

<p>SATB1 
0.0 (0/5) 
25.0 (1/4) </p>

<p>SERPINB2 
0.0 (0/4) 
0.0 (0/4) </p>

<p>SLC45A3 
0.0 (0/5) 
ND </p>

<p>SP100 
0.0 (0/5) 
25.0 (1/4) </p>

<p>SPDEF 
0.0 (0/5) 
0.0 (0/4) </p>

<p>TGFB1 
25.0 (1/4) 
0.0 (0/4) </p>

<p>THBS1 
0.0 (0/5) 
50.0 (2/4) </p>

<p>TIMP2 
50.0 (3/6) 
28.6 (2/7) </p>

<p>TIMP3 
66.7 (4/6) 
50.0 (2/4) </p>

<p>TMPRSS2 
33.3 (2/6) 
75.0 (3/4) </p>

<p>VEGFA 
7.7 (1/13) 
57.1 (4/7) </p>

<p>VIM 
0.0 (0/5) 
25.0 (1/4) </p>

<p>SD, significantly different, based on a KS test, p &lt; 0.01. ND, not determined. </p>

<p>TABLE 2: Comparison of individual tissues to a pooled normal 
distribution. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: Gene repositioning in prostate cancer is not linked to 
prognostic status. Cumulative RRDs are color coded according to the 
prognostic status of the cancer: blue, indolent prostate cancers 
(Gleason score ≤6, without metastasis); green, intermediate cancers 
(Gleason score 7, without metastasis); red, aggressive cancers 
(Gleason score ≥8, and/or metastasis). The pooled normal distribution 
(black) is included for comparison. RRP, relative radial position. </p>

<p>y 
c 
n 
e 
u 
q 
e 
r 
f 
e 
v 
i 
t 
a 
l 
u 
m 
u 
C </p>

<p>Periphery </p>

<p>RRP </p>

<p>0 
0 
0.4 
1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>FLI1 </p>

<p>0 
0 
0.4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>MMP9 </p>

<p>0 
0 
0.4 
1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>MMP2 </p>

<p>RRP 
Center </p>

<p>Pooled normal 
Indolent 
Intermediate 
Aggressive </p>

<p>RRP </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>y 
c 
n 
e 
u 
q 
e 
r 
f 
e 
v 
i 
t 
a 
l 
u 
m 
u 
C </p>

<p>y 
c 
n 
e 
u 
q 
e 
r 
f 
e 
v 
i 
t 
a 
l 
u 
m 
u 
C </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>only a single cross-comparison reaching significance (1 of 10; Table 
3 and Figure 4). FLI1 and MMP9 did not reposition in hyperplasia 
compared with normal tissues, since the positioning of both genes 
was indistinguishable from the PND in all five hyperplasia tissues 
(Table 3 and Figure 4), and only 10% (4 of 40) and 12% (6 of 50) of 
the cross-comparisons among individual normal tissues reached sig-
nificance, respectively. These findings, combined with the low repo-
sitioning rate in normal tissue, suggests that FLI1 and MMP9 reposi-
tioning is specific to cancer. In contrast, compared with normal 
tissues, MMP2 was repositioned in both prostate cancer and hyper-
plasia. MMP2 was in a significantly different position in 80% (4 of 5) 
of the hyperplastic tissues compared with the PND and in 45% (18 
of 40) of cross-comparisons between hyperplasic and normal tissues 
(Table 3 and Figure 4), suggesting that the repositioning of MMP2 is 
common in prostate disease and not limited to malignancy. We had 
access to both hyperplastic and cancer tissue from the same pros-
tate (B1 and C3, respectively; Supplemental Table S2). In keeping 
with the comparisons between hyperplasia and normal tissue, FLI1 
and MMP9 occupied significantly different positions in the cancer 
and hyperplasic tissue (p = 0.004 and 0.002, respectively), whereas </p>

<p>these genes in five benign hyperplastic tissues with the positioning 
patterns of normal prostate tissues and among multiple hyperplasia 
tissues (Table 3 and Figure 4). MMP9 and MMP2 were positioned 
identically in all hyperplastic tissues (Table 3 and Figure 4). The posi-
tion of FLI1 is similarly conserved among hyperplastic tissues, with </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: Gene positioning in benign disease. Positions of indicated genes were compared between hyperplasia 
(B1-B5) and normal prostate tissue (N1-N25). (A) Cumulative RRDs for the indicated genes in hyperplasia (red), normal 
tissues (black), and the pooled normal distribution (PND; blue). (B) Pairwise statistical comparisons of RRDs between 
hyperplasic tissues and normal tissues and among hyperplasic tissues, using the two-sample 1D KS test. All three genes 
are similarly positioned between hyperplasic tissues and only MMP2 repositions in hyperplasic compared with normal 
tissues. RRP, relative radial position. </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>B1 </p>

<p>B2 </p>

<p>B3 </p>

<p>B4 </p>

<p>B5 </p>

<p>B2 
B3 
B4 
B5 </p>

<p>FLI1 </p>

<p>PND 
N1 
N2 
N3 
N4 
N5 
N12 
N13 
N15 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B1 </p>

<p>B2 </p>

<p>B3 </p>

<p>B4 </p>

<p>B5 </p>

<p>B2 
B3 
B4 
B5 </p>

<p>MMP9 </p>

<p>PND 
N7 
N8 
N14 
N15 
N16 
N19 
N20 
N21 
N22 
N23 </p>

<p>B1 </p>

<p>B2 </p>

<p>B3 </p>

<p>B4 </p>

<p>B5 </p>

<p>B2 
B3 
B4 
B5 </p>

<p>MMP2 </p>

<p>PND 
N5 
N7 
N15 
N16 
N21 
N22 
N24 
N25 </p>

<p>P &gt; 0.05 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>0 
0 
0.4 
1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0 
0 
0.4 
1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>y 
c 
n 
e 
u 
q 
e 
r 
f 
e 
v 
i 
t 
a 
l 
u 
m 
u 
C y </p>

<p>c 
n 
e 
u 
q 
e 
r 
f 
e 
v 
i 
t 
a 
l 
u 
m 
u 
C </p>

<p>FLI1 </p>

<p>RRP </p>

<p>MMP9 </p>

<p>RRP 
Periphery 
Center </p>

<p>0 
0 
0.4 
1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>y 
c 
n 
e 
u 
q 
e 
r 
f 
e 
v 
i 
t 
a 
l 
u 
m 
u 
C </p>

<p>MMP2 </p>

<p>RRP </p>

<p>PND 
Normal 
Hyperplasia </p>

<p>Gene </p>

<p>Percentage (number) of SD 
cross-comparison among: </p>

<p>Individual 
hyperplasia 
tissues </p>

<p>Individual 
normal and 
hyperplasia 
tissues </p>

<p>Individual 
hyperplasia 
tissues and 
pooled normal </p>

<p>FLI1 
10.0 (1/10) 
10.0 (4/40) 
0.0 (0/5) </p>

<p>MMP9 
0.0 (0/10) 
12.0 (6/50) 
0.0 (0/5) </p>

<p>MMP2 
0.0 (0/10) 
45.0 (18/40) 
80.0 (4/5) </p>

<p>SD, significantly different, based on a two-sample 1D KS test, p &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>TABLE 3: Comparison of gene positioning in benign tissues. </p>

<p>Volume 27 January 15, 2016 </p>

<p>Gene repositioning in prostate cancer | 243 </p>

<p>breast (Wiech et al., 2005; Meaburn et al., 2009), we find that the 
spatial positioning of most genes tested in normal prostate tissue is 
generally well conserved among individuals. Of 40 genes analyzed, 
only three (CCND1, TIMP2, and TIMP3) were highly variable among 
individuals. A prerequisite of a useful cancer biomarker is conserva-
tion among individuals in nonmalignant tissues because such vari-
ability leads to low sensitivity and specificity of the marker. There-
fore some genes will not be suitable for diagnostic purposes due to 
variable positioning patterns among individuals. The variability in 
the position of some genes in normal prostate tissue is higher than 
previously detected for 15 genes in morphologically normal breast 
tissue (Meaburn et al., 2009). The reasons for this difference be-
tween the two tissue types are not known. One possibility is that 
some glands within normal prostate tissues have preneoplastic fea-
tures. For example, proliferative inflammatory atrophy, which is re-
garded as a histologically distinctive pattern of benign glands, has 
some of the molecular features of prostate neoplasia (De Marzo 
et al., 1999). In contrast, there is no reported counterpart lesion of 
mammary glands. Another possibility is that these prostate glands 
could have included low-grade prostatic intraepithelial neoplasia, 
which is challenging to recognize in dark-field FISH preparations. In 
addition, some genes could be more susceptible to interindividual 
variations in their positioning patterns, which could be either a gen-
eral feature of the locus or tissue specific. For example, the position 
of CCND1 was similar among normal breast tissues (Meaburn et al., 
2009) but varied among individuals in the prostate, pointing to a 
potential tissue-specific driver to interindividual positioning pat-
terns. Because CCND1 is a cell cycle regulator and epithelial cells 
are largely quiescent in normal breast and prostate tissues, a direct 
link between CCND1 function and tissue specificity seems unlikely. 
We identified three genes that consistently reposition in prostate 
cancer. The repositioning of FLI1 and MMP9 was specific to cancer, 
as it did not occur in benign disease, in line with earlier observations 
in breast, where gene repositioning was generally limited to cancer-
ous tissue (Meaburn et al., 2009). In contrast, MMP2 repositioned in 
cancer as well as in hyperplasic prostate tissue. Our findings are in 
line with previous studies in other types of cancer, for which reposi-
tioning of some loci and concurrent conservation in the positioning 
patterns of others have been reported (Croft et al., 1999; Parada 
et al., 2002; Cremer et al., 2003; Wiech et al., 2005, 2009; Murata 
et al., 2007; Meaburn and Misteli, 2008; Meaburn et al., 2009; </p>

<p>MMP2 was in a similar position in the two disease states (p = 0.516) 
for this individual. </p>

<p>High-confidence detection of prostate cancers using 
multiplexed positioning biomarkers </p>

<p>Because FLI1 and MMP9 repositioning occurs predominantly in can-
cer tissues, we determined their false-positive and false-negative 
rates as a preliminary step toward assessing their potential as bio-
markers for prostate cancer. A false positive was defined as reposi-
tioning (p &gt; 0.01; KS test) of the marker gene in a nonmalignant 
(normal or hyperplastic) tissue compared with the PND, thus incor-
rectly classifying the tissue as cancer. Conversely, a false negative 
was defined as lack of repositioning (p &lt; 0.01) of the marker gene in 
a cancer, leading to incorrect classification of the tissue as nonmalig-
nant. As expected due to its high rate of repositioning in hyperplasia, 
MMP2 had a high false-positive rate (30.8% [4 of 13 nonmalignant 
tissues]; Figures 2 and 4 and Table 4). This finding, combined with its 
high false-negative rate (43.8% [7 of 16 cancer tissues]; Figure 2 and 
Table 5), suggests that MMP2 would not be a useful biomarker for 
prostate cancer. In contrast, FLI1 had low false-negative and false-
positive rates (7.1% [1 of 14 cancer tissues] and 7.7% [1 of 13 nonma-
lignant tissues], respectively; Figures 2 and 4 and Tables 4 and 5). 
MMP9 had a fairly high false-negative rate (31.6% [6 of 19 cancer 
tissues]; Figure 2 and Table 5) but a low false-positive rate (6.7% [1 of 
15 nonmalignant tissues]; Figures 2 and 4 and Table 4). 
None of the genes we tested repositioned in all prostate cancer 
tissues. However, at least one repositioned gene was present in ev-
ery prostate cancer tissue analyzed (30 of 30 cancers; Figure 2 and 
Supplemental Figure S2). Given the low false-positive rate of FLI1 
and MMP9, we explored the possibility of using these two genes in 
a multiplex format for the detection of cancer samples. When ana-
lyzed together, FLI1 or MMP9, or both, repositioned in all (11 of 11) 
cancers (Figure 2 and Supplemental Table S4). Consequently, multi-
plexing FLI1 and MMP9 reduced the false-negative rate to 0% (0 of 
11; Table 5). We conclude that in combination, FLI1 and MMP9 are 
strong potential biomarkers for prostate cancer. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study was designed to identify gene loci that undergo reposi-
tioning during prostate carcinogenesis. Spatial mapping of the ra-
dial position of 40 genes by FISH identified two genes that robustly 
reposition in prostate cancer and a third gene that repositions in 
both prostate cancer and benign prostate disease. The vast majority 
of analyzed genes, however, did not undergo significant cancer-
specific repositioning, pointing to considerable conservation of spa-
tial genome organization in prostate cancer. 
In keeping with previous studies on positioning of select genes 
and of whole chromosomes in brain (Borden and Manuelidis, 1988), 
pancreas (Timme et al., 2011), thyroid (Murata et al., 2007), and </p>

<p>Gene </p>

<p>Normal-tissue 
false positives </p>

<p>Benign-tissue 
false positives </p>

<p>Total false 
positives </p>

<p>FLI1 
12.5% (1/8) 
0.0% (0/5) 
7.7% (1/13) </p>

<p>MMP9 
10.0% (1/10) 
0.0% (0/5) 
6.7% (1/15) </p>

<p>MMP2 
0.0% (0/8) 
80.0% (4/5) 
30.8% (4/13) </p>

<p>The percentage (number) of tissues that give a false-positive result. A false 
positive is scored when a gene has a statistically significant different RRD in a 
normal or hyperplastic tissue compared with the pooled normal (p &lt; 0.01; KS 
test). </p>

<p>TABLE 4: False-positive rates. </p>

<p>Gene(s) 
False-negative rate </p>

<p>Single gene </p>

<p>FLI1 
7.1% (1/14) </p>

<p>MMP9 
31.6% (6/19) </p>

<p>MMP2 
43.8% (7/16) </p>

<p>Multiplexed genes </p>

<p>FLI1 and MMP9 
0.0% (0/11) </p>

<p>FLI1 and MMP2 
9.1% (1/11) </p>

<p>MMP9 and MMP2 
28.6% (4/14) </p>

<p>The percentage (number) of tissues that give a false-negative result. A false 
negative is scored when the RRD of a gene in a cancer tissue is similar to that 
of the pooled normal distribution (KS test, p &gt; 0.01). For multiplexed genes, a 
false positive is scored when neither gene in the pair is repositioned compared 
with the pooled normal distribution (p &gt; 0.01, KS test). Only tissues in which 
both genes of the pair were positioned are included. </p>

<p>TABLE 5: False-negative rates for single and multiplexed genes. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>detection of cancer with high accuracy. Whereas neither MMP9 nor 
FLI1 alone was repositioned in all prostate tumor samples, at least 
one of the two was repositioned in all cancer samples analyzed. Our 
observation of cancer-specific repositioning of these two genes, 
combined with their relatively low false-positive detection rate, 
makes MMP9 and FLI1 strong candidates for combinatorial use in 
cancer diagnosis. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Tissues </p>

<p>To detect individual genes, FISH was performed on a panel of 4-to 
5-μm-thick FFPE human prostate tissue sections, which consisted of 
30 prostate cancers, 29 normal and NAT prostate tissues, and five 
hyperplasic tissues (Supplemental Table S2). Prostate tissues were ob-
tained from the University of Washington (Seattle, WA) under the 
guidelines and approval of the Institutional Review Board of the 
University of Washington (#00-3449). These specimens were reviewed 
by a single genitourinary pathologist (L.D.T.). Additional tissues were 
purchased from US Biomax (Rockville, MD) and Imgenex (San Diego, 
CA; Supplemental Table S2). All specimens were deidentified. </p>

<p>FISH </p>

<p>FISH probes were produced by using nick translation to label DNA 
purified from bacterial artificial chromosome clones (BACPAC 
Resources Center [Oakland, CA]; Supplemental Table S1) with either 
biotin-or digoxigenin-conjugated dUTPs (Roche, Indianapolis, IN), 
as detailed in Meaburn (2010). An identical dual-probe FISH proce-
dure was performed on all specimens as previously described 
(Meaburn et al., 2009), with the exceptions that 1) the 60°C slide 
baking step, before xylene (Avantor Performance Materials, Center 
Valley, PA) treatment, was omitted, 2) the time the tissue sections 
were incubated in 0.25 mg/ml Proteinase K (Sigma-Aldrich, St. 
Louis, MO) was increased to 15-20 min, and 3) 0.5 mg/ml Protein-
ase K was often required for single-tissues slides obtained from Bio-
max (but not tissue microarray slides). </p>

<p>Image acquisition and FISH analysis </p>

<p>Image accusation was performed essentially as described in 
Meaburn et al. (2009). Briefly, tissue sections were imaged with an 
IX70 (Olympus, Waltham, MA) DeltaVision (Applied Precision-GE 
Healthcare Bio-Sciences, Pittsburgh, PA) system, using a 60×/1.42 
numerical aperture oil objective lens (Olympus) and an auxiliary 
magnification of 1.5. Image stacks were acquired with a 0.5-μm step 
interval along the z-axis. If mixed morphologies were present in a 
tissue section, before imaging, the tissue was visually inspected at 
low resolution (10× lens; Olympus) to identify malignant, normal, or 
hyperplastic regions. In these cases, hematoxylin and eosin-stained 
tissue slides that had been marked by a pathologist (L.D.T.) were 
used as a guide to ensure correct classification of different regions 
of a tissue. Image stacks were deconvolved and converted into max-
imum intensity projections using SoftWoRx (Applied Precision). 
Image analysis was performed as previously described (Meaburn 
et al., 2009). Images were contrast enhanced based on visual inspec-
tion, and individual nuclei were manually delineated in <rs id="software-0" type="software">Photoshop</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">7.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Adobe</rs>, San Jose, CA), with each nucleus saved in a separate 
image file. To determine the relative radial positioning of a gene in a 
given tissue, 91-263 randomly selected interphase epithelial nuclei 
were run though a custom-made image analysis software package 
(P. Gudla and S. Lockett, National Cancer Institute, Bethesda, MD; 
Meaburn et al., 2009) in <rs id="software-1" type="software">MATLAB</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">MathWorks</rs>, Natick, MA) using the 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">PRTools</rs> and <rs type="software">DIPImage</rs> toolboxes (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Delft University of Technology</rs>, 
Delft, Netherlands). The software automatically identified FISH </p>

<p>Harewood et al., 2010). Of interest, FLI1 and MMP9 also reposition 
in breast cancer (unpublished data), suggesting that they are multi-
tissue markers of cancer. Not all genes that reposition in cancer are 
general markers of a malignant state, however, since an additional 
eight genes that reposition in breast cancer (Meaburn et al., 2009) 
do not reposition in prostate cancer (unpublished data). 
We did not identify any common features shared among reposi-
tioning genes in prostate cancer. For example, the genes that repo-
sition map to different chromosomes (FLI1, HSA11; MMP9, HSA20; 
and MMP2, HSA16). The repositioning of FLI1, at least, is unlikely to 
reflect whole-chromosome movements, since of five genes located 
on HSA11 (FLI1, CCND1, FUT4, MMP1, and NUMA1), only FLI1 ro-
bustly repositioned in prostate cancer. In addition, biological func-
tion or known relevance to tumorigenesis of genes does not predict 
repositioning behavior. Many of the genes we positioned that are 
commonly implicated in prostate cancer, such as KLK3 (prostate-
specific antigen), AR, PTEN, TGFB1, VEGFA, and BCL2 (Bok and 
Small, 2002; Ferte et al., 2010; Lawrence et al., 2010; Shen and 
Abate-Shen, 2010), and the commonly translocated genes in pros-
tate cancer, the androgen-regulated TMPRSS2 and the ETS tran-
scription factors ERG and ETV1 (Tomlins et al., 2005), do not spa-
tially reposition in prostate cancers. Yet the ETS transcription factor 
FLI1, which forms rare translocations in prostate cancer (Paulo et al., 
2012), does. MMP9 and MMP2, which belong to the same class of 
matrix metallopeptidases (MMPs) and are involved in the break-
down of extracellular matrix, which is important to cancer-associ-
ated processes such as angiogenesis and metastasis (Egeblad and 
Werb, 2002), reposition in prostate cancer, and yet the potential 
functional relevance of the cancer-association gene repositioning is 
unclear. Although an increase in MMP9 and MMP2 expression has 
been linked to poor prognosis in prostate cancer, both genes are 
predominantly expressed by the stromal cells and not by the tumor 
cells (Egeblad and Werb, 2002). Other MMP family members, such 
as MMP14, and the genomic loci containing a cluster of MMP 
genes, including MMP1, did not reposition. Moreover, genes cod-
ing the MMP-regulating proteins TIMP2, TIMP3 (Egeblad and Werb, 
2002), and SPDEF (Johnson et al., 2010), another ETS transcription 
factor, do not reposition in prostate cancer, further reducing a link 
between function and cancer-associated gene repositioning. A lack 
of a link between gene function and an altered radial position in 
cancer is in line with multiple studies that find no correlation be-
tween changes in gene expression and changes in radial positioning 
patterns, including a cell culture model of early breast cancer 
(Williams et al., 2006; Meaburn and Misteli, 2008; Takizawa et al., 
2008b; Morey et al., 2009; Harewood et al., 2010; Shachar et al., 
2015). Although we focused on radial positioning patterns to iden-
tify cancer-specific spatial genome-repositioning events, relative 
positioning of loci to other genomic loci or nuclear landmarks, such 
as nuclear bodies, may be a promising alternative parameter to 
characterize the spatial reorganization of gene loci in cancer. 
Repositioning did not correlate with gene copy number or the 
presence of translocations. For example, FLI1 repositioned in both 
cancers with and without amplified FLI1, and we found FLI1 reposi-
tioning in 13 of 14 prostate cancers, yet the SLC45A3-FLI1 translo-
cation occurs in only 1 in 200 prostate cancers (Paulo et al., 2012). 
Although it is possible that translocations could affect the position 
of genomic regions beyond the translocating region, even on chro-
mosomes not involved in the translocation, our data demonstrate 
that in the background of genetic instability, it is still possible to use 
gene positioning for cancer diagnostics. 
As previously observed for breast cancer (Meaburn et al., 2009), 
we find that combinatorial analysis of multiple genes results in </p>

<p>Volume 27 January 15, 2016 </p>

<p>Gene repositioning in prostate cancer | 245 </p>

<p>signals (&gt;99% of FISH signals detected, with a false-positive rate of 
&lt;1%; Takizawa et al., 2008a) and determined both the binary EDT of 
the geometric gravity center of each FISH signal and the number of 
FISH signals in a nucleus for both genes visualized by FISH. In EDT, 
each pixel in a nucleus is assigned a value that equals the shortest 
distance to the nuclear edge. EDT values are then normalized to the 
maximum EDT value of a given nucleus to account for variations in 
nuclear size. Using this method, no assumption regarding nuclear 
shape or size is made when determining the radial position of a 
gene, allowing accurate comparisons between tissues even if there 
are differences or irregularities in nuclear shape or size. The relative 
radial positions of individual nuclei from the same specimen for each 
histologic entity were combined to generate a RRD for a gene. All 
alleles in a nucleus were included for analysis, and nuclei were ana-
lyzed regardless of the number of alleles present, unless there were 
no signals for either gene. Because some nuclei contained FISH sig-
nals for only one gene, when the number of nuclei analyzed is indi-
cated, only nuclei containing FISH signals for the indicated gene are 
included. To generate PNDs, normalized EDTs from all nuclei from all 
normal tissues analyzed for a given gene were combined into a sin-
gle data set (see Table 1 for the number of normal tissues analyzed 
for each gene and Supplemental Table S1 for the number of nuclei 
used to generate each gene's PND). Finally, cumulative RRDs from 
different samples were statistically compared using the nonparamet-
ric two-sample 1D KS test. The null hypothesis that the samples are 
from the same distribution was rejected if p &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Prabhakar Gudla and Stephen Lockett for help with image 
analysis; Olufunmilayo Agunloye for technical assistance; Delft 
University of Technology for providing the DIPImage and PRTools 
toolboxes; and Tatiana Karpova for microscopy support. We also 
thank Kathy Doan for help in identifying and obtaining tissue used 
for this study. Fluorescence imaging was performed at the National 
Cancer Institute Fluorescence Imaging Facility (Bethesda, MD). This 
work was supported by Department of Defense Idea Award 
W81XWH-12-1-0224, the National Cancer Institute, National Insti-
tutes of Health, under Pacific Northwest Prostate Cancer SPORE 
Grant P50CA097186, and, in part, by the Intramural Research Pro-
gram of the National Institutes of Health, National Cancer Institute, 
Center for Cancer Research. </p>





<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>



</text></tei>