<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4283627" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs type="software">STRUCTURE</rs><rs type="software">STRUCTURE</rs><rs type="software">GENALEX</rs>subpopulations is a measure of the number of population sub-
groups in the data set. Analyses were run as described (Mellanby 
and others 2013) using the results for 15 microsatellite markers, 
and both South African dogs and the UK dogs previously 
reported by Mellanby and others (2013) were included. Fig 1 
shows the outcome of this analysis when K (number of contrib-
uting subpopulations) was set at 6. The result was the same 
with higher values of K. This analysis showed that within a 
breed the dogs were genetically very similar regardless of the 
country. Jack Russell terriers showed equal contributions from 
different subpopulations, whereas labrador retrievers and 
German shepherd dogs each showed 90 per cent contribution 
from a single subpopulation. Jack Russell terriers had very little 
contribution from either of the subpopulations predominant in </p>

<p>the labrador retrievers or German shepherd dogs, as might be 
expected given the very different phenotype and ancestry of 
these dogs. The admixture of subpopulations within a breed was 
the same regardless of country, showing that the breeds have not 
diverged greatly. To further test this, each breed was subjected 
individually to <rs type="software">STRUCTURE</rs> analysis. There was no evidence of 
stratification based on country of origin at K=2 or higher 
K values (Fig 2). As previously reported (Mellanby and others 
2013), misclassification of dog breed was common with four of 
the South African labrador retrievers and one of the German 
shepherd dogs showing mixed breed ancestry, whereas several 
others had a 50 per cent contribution from one subpopulation 
suggesting a one parent of the associated breed and one of 
another breed or mixed breed background. </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>80% </p>

<p>60% </p>

<p>40% </p>

<p>20% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>K=6 
German shepherd Dog 
Labrador Retriever 
Jack Russell Terrier </p>

<p>Percent membership of cluster </p>

<p>United Kingdom 
South Africa 
South Africa 
South Africa 
United Kingdom 
United Kingdom </p>

<p>FIG 1: STRUCTURE analysis of three dog breeds from the UK and South Africa. Genotypes for 15 microsatellites for dogs of all three breeds 
from South Africa and the UK were entered into the program <rs type="software">STRUCTURE</rs> and the analysis run with a burn-in period of 100,000 replications 
and a run of 500,000 replications (Mellanby and others 2013). Runs were repeated between two and five times for each value of K to assess 
the stability of the population structure detected. The results are shown for a typical run with K=6. Each vertical column represents a different 
dog, whereas the shades of grey represent six different subpopulations in the admixture. The y axis shows the proportional of the genotype 
attributed to each subpopulation for each dog </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>80% </p>

<p>80% </p>

<p>80% </p>

<p>80% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>80% </p>

<p>60% </p>

<p>40% </p>

<p>20% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>80% </p>

<p>60% </p>

<p>40% </p>

<p>20% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>German 
Shepherd Dog </p>

<p>Labrador Retriever </p>

<p>Jack Russell Terrier </p>

<p>United Kingdom 
South Africa </p>

<p>FIG 2: <rs type="software">STRUCTURE</rs> analysis within dog breeds from the UK and South Africa. The input data were the same as for Fig 1, but the input 
contained only the results for a single breed. Burn-in, run and replications were the same as for Fig 1. Results are shown for K=2. The relative 
proportion of each population in each dog is shown in dark and light grey.; the outcome was similar for higher values of K </p>

<p>Veterinary Record | December 6, 2014 </p>

<p>Short Communication </p>

<p>This analysis shows that the assignment of dogs to pedigree 
classes on the basis of genotype is robust across the two coun-
tries and there is little evidence for genetic drift within breeds, 
reflecting the similarity of the breed standards between the two 
countries. This may be maintained by the import of dogs from 
other countries and the exchange of semen for artificial insemin-
ation. Artificial insemination from cryopreserved domestic dog 
semen has been available since the 1960s (Thomassen and 
Farstad 2009) and use of artificial insemination has increased 
among pedigree dog breeders as technologies have developed to 
preserve and transport semen. Although this could benefit the 
breed and enhance genetic diversity by varying the sires used by 
a breeder, it is also seen as a cost-effective method to maximise 
the number of progeny of popular sires (Thomassen and Farstad 
2009), hence restricting the gene pool. Worldwide use of semen 
from a small number of sires may have the effect of maintaining 
the homogeneity of the breed across geographically separated 
regions. The heterozygosity of the Jack Russell has been main-
tained in South Africa, indicating that registration as a breed and 
the need to conform to breed standard has not reduced genetic 
diversity at this point. 
Thus, the geographical isolation of the two countries has not 
apparently led to genetic divergence within the breeds examined, 
suggesting that there is minimal reproductive isolation and con-
siderable genetic exchange. Consequently, an important implica-
tion of this study is that genetic diseases detected in a breed 
(Asher and others 2009, Summers and others 2010) are likely to 
be found in both countries and could be transmitted from foun-
ders in either country, exacerbated by the use of artificial insem-
ination, limiting the number of sires. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank the owners of the dogs 
included in this study for agreeing to participate. This study was 
partly funded by a Clinical Pump Priming Grant from the Roslin 
Institute to DNC, RJM, KMS, JPS, Mark Bronsvoort and 
Andreas Lengeling, a grant from Petsavers to RJM and DNC and 
a Genesis-Faraday SPARK award to RO, RJM, DNC and Ross 
McEwing. The Roslin Institute is supported by BBSRC Institute 
Strategic Grant funding. </p>



</text></tei>