<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4651396" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: To evaluate the diagnostic performance of 
ultrasound, MRI and fluorine-18 fludeoxyglucose positron 
emission tomography ( </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>F-FDG PET)/CT for the diagno-
sis of metastatic axillary lymph node (ALN) after neo-
adjuvant chemotherapy (NAC) and to find out 
histopathological factors affecting the diagnostic perfor-
mance of these imaging modalities. 
Methods: From January 2012 to November 2014, 191 
consecutive patients with breast cancer who underwent 
NAC before surgery were retrospectively reviewed. We 
included 139 patients with ALN metastasis that was 
confirmed on fine needle aspiration or core needle biopsy 
at initial diagnosis. 
Results: After NAC, 39 (28%) patients showed negative 
conversion of ALN on surgical specimens of sentinel 
lymph node (LN) or ALN. The sensitivity of ultrasound, 
MRI and PET/CT was 50% (48/96), 72% (70/97) and 22% 
(16/73), respectively. The specificity of ultrasound, MRI 
and PET/CT was 77% (30/39), 54% (21/39) and 85% (22/ 
26), respectively. The Az value of combination of 
ultrasound and PET/CT was the highest (0.634) followed 
by ultrasound (0.626) and combination of ultrasound, 
MRI and PET/CT (0.617). The size of tumour deposit in LN 
and oestrogen receptor was significantly associated with 
the diagnostic performance of ultrasound (p , 0.001 and 
p 5 0.009, respectively) and MRI (p 5 0.045 and </p>

<p>p 5 0.036, respectively). The percentage diameter de-
crease, size of tumour deposit in LN, progesterone 
receptor, HER2 and histological grade were significantly 
associated with the diagnostic performance of PET/CT 
(p 5 0.023, 
p 5 0.002, 
p 5 0.036, 
p 5 0.044 
and 
p 5 0.008, respectively). On multivariate logistic regres-
sion analysis, size of tumour deposit within LN was 
identified as being independently associated with di-
agnostic performance of ultrasound [odds ratio, 13.07; 
95% confidence interval (CI), 2.95-57.96] and PET/CT 
(odds ratio, 6.47; 95% CI, 1.407-29.737). 
Conclusion: Combination of three imaging modalities 
showed the highest sensitivity, and PET/CT showed the 
highest specificity for the evaluation of ALN metastasis 
after NAC. Ultrasound alone or combination of ultrasound 
and PET/CT showed the highest positive-predictive 
value. The size of tumour deposit within ALN was 
significantly associated with diagnostic performance of 
ultrasound and PET/CT. 
Advances in knowledge: This study is about the di-
agnostic performance of ultrasound, MRI, PET/CT and 
combination of each imaging modality for the evaluation 
of metastatic ALN after NAC. Of many histopathological 
factors, only the size of tumour deposit within ALN was 
an independent factor associated with the diagnostic 
performance of ultrasound and PET/CT. </p>

<p>Axillary lymph node (ALN) metastasis is one of the most 
significant prognostic factors in patients with breast cancer. As 
the management of axillary lesions has been diverse, the de-
tection of axillary nodal lesion has been more important. The 
diagnostic accuracy of ultrasound and MRI for the detection 
of metastatic ALNs has been studied by many researchers. 
Sensitivity and specificity of ultrasound for the detection of </p>

<p>metastatic ALNs have been reported as 41.2-70.8% and 
54.5-93.7%. 
1-4 Sensitivity and specificity of MRI have been 
reported as 36-79% and 93-100%, respectively. </p>

<p>4-6 </p>

<p>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy (NAC) has become the stan-
dard treatment not only in patients with locally advanced 
breast cancer but also in early invasive breast cancer in an </p>

<p>attempt to downstage the primary cancer and to reduce 
micrometastasis. If the ALN metastasis is confirmed on fine 
needle aspiration biopsy (FNAB) or core needle biopsy (CNB) at 
initial diagnosis, ALN dissection (ALND) is usually performed, 
regardless of the responsiveness of ALN. Residual metastatic 
lesion of ALNs after NAC is an important prognostic factor of 
disease-free survival. </p>

<p>7,8 </p>

<p>In ACOSOG Z1071 trial, in patients with breast cancer with 
clinical N1 stage receiving NAC, if two or more sentinel lymph 
nodes (SLNs) were removed, the false-negative rate of SLN bi-
opsy (SLNB) was relatively low, 12.6%. Therefore, the role of 
axillary imaging in NAC setting should be to find out metastatic 
lymph nodes (LNs) for surgeons to proceed directly to ALND. 
Another role could be to correctly diagnose negative LN to safely </p>

<p>omit SLNB. Despite the importance of restaging of nodal status, 
there have been few studies about diagnostic accuracy of im-
aging modalities for detection of metastatic ALNs after NAC. </p>

<p>The purpose of our study was to evaluate the diagnostic per-
formance of ultrasound, MRI and fluorine-18 fludeoxyglucose 
positron emission tomography ( 
18 F-FDG PET)/CT for the di-
agnosis of metastatic ALNs after NAC and to find out histo-
pathological factors affecting the diagnostic accuracy of these 
imaging modalities. </p>

<p>METHODS AND MATERIALS 
Patients 
The institutional review board of Ajou University approved this 
retrospective study. From January 2012 to November 2014, 191 </p>

<p>Table 1. Patient characteristics </p>

<p>Characteristics 
All (n 5 139) 
Patients for ultrasound 
analysis (n 5 135) </p>

<p>Patients for MRI 
analysis (n 5 136) </p>

<p>Patients for positron 
emission tomography/ 
CT analysis (n 5 99) </p>

<p>Age (years) 
(mean 6 standard deviation) 
46.4 6 10.0 
46.3 6 9.1 
46.3 6 9.2 
45.7 6 8.9 </p>

<p>Tumour size (cm) 
(mean 6 standard deviation) 
3.8 6 2.2 
3.8 6 2.2 
3.8 6 2.2 
4.0 6 2.1 </p>

<p>T stage </p>

<p>T1 
23 
23 
23 
9 </p>

<p>T2 
79 
76 
78 
62 </p>

<p>T3 
16 
16 
14 
13 </p>

<p>T4 
21 
20 
21 
15 </p>

<p>Tumour histology </p>

<p>Infiltrating ductal 
131 
127 
128 
91 </p>

<p>Infiltrating lobular 
3 
3 
3 
3 </p>

<p>Other 
5 
5 
5 
5 </p>

<p>Nuclear grade </p>

<p>Low 
56 
54 
55 
37 </p>

<p>High 
57 
55 
55 
44 </p>

<p>Histological grade </p>

<p>Low 
72 
70 
71 
50 </p>

<p>High 
42 
40 
40 
32 </p>

<p>Oestrogen receptor </p>

<p>Negative 
41 
40 
40 
30 </p>

<p>Positive 
98 
95 
96 
69 </p>

<p>Progesterone receptor </p>

<p>Negative 
68 
66 
67 
48 </p>

<p>Positive 
71 
69 
69 
51 </p>

<p>HER2 </p>

<p>Negative 
98 
96 
97 
72 </p>

<p>Positive 
41 
39 
39 
27 </p>

<p>BJR 
S You et al </p>

<p>2 of 9 birpublications.org/bjr 
Br J Radiol;88:20150143 </p>

<p>consecutive patients with breast cancer who underwent ul-
trasound and MRI with/without PET/CT for assessment of 
tumour response after NAC were retrospectively reviewed. We 
included 139 patients with ALN metastases that were con-
firmed on FNAB or CNB at initial diagnosis. Of 139 patients, 
4 patients did not undergo follow-up ultrasound, 3 patients 
did not undergo follow-up MRI and 40 patients did not 
undergo follow-up PET/CT. Therefore, 135 patients were 
included for the ultrasound analysis, 136 patients were in-
cluded for the MRI analysis and 99 patients were included for 
the PET-CT analysis. Patient characteristics are summarized 
in Table 1. </p>

<p>Ultrasound technique and interpretation 
Ultrasound examinations had been performed in all patients 
by one of two radiologists with 7 years' and 12 years' ex-
perience in breast imaging. Each patient was evaluated with 
real-time ultrasound using a Siemens Acuson S2000 Ultra-
sound system (Siemens Healthcare, Mountain View, CA) or 
Hi Vision Ascendus system (Hitachi Medical, Tokyo, Japan) 
with a 15-MHz linear array transducer. </p>

<p>ALN metastasis was suspected if the LN had any of the following 
morphologic characteristics: eccentric or concentric cortical 
thickening .3 mm, absent fatty hilum, a transverse axis-to-
longitudinal axis ratio more than two or increased blood flow in 
the thickened cortex on Doppler image. </p>

<p>FNAB was performed without local anaesthesia. The needle was 
inserted into the area to be sampled and repeatedly redirected 
within the cortex and subcapsular area while suction was applied. </p>

<p>MRI technique and interpretation 
All MR examinations were performed using a 1.5-T system 
(Signa HDxt; GE Healthcare, Milwaukee, WI) with a dedicated 
breast coil (8-channel HD breast array, GE Healthcare). Gado-
butrol (Gadovist®; Bayer Schering Pharma, Berlin, Germany) 
was injected into an antecubital vein at a dose of 0.1 mmol kg </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>of body weight and at a rate of 3 ml s 
-1 , followed by a 20-ml 
saline flush for all patients. </p>

<p>The imaging protocol of a 1.5-T scanner consisted of fat sup-
pressed axial fast spin echo T 2 weighted images (repetition time/ </p>

<p>Table 2. Sensitivity, specificity, positive-predictive value (PPV) and negative-predictive value (NPV) of ultrasound, MRI and positron 
emission tomography (PET)/CT after neoadjuvant chemotherapy </p>

<p>Diagnostic 
performance 
Ultrasound 
MRI 
PET/CT 
Ultrasound 1 
MRI </p>

<p>Ultrasound 1 
PET/CT </p>

<p>MRI 1 
PET/CT </p>

<p>Ultrasound 1 
MRI 1 
PET/CT </p>

<p>Sensitivity 
50% (48/96) 
72% (70/97) 
22% (16/73) 
77% (72/94) 
54% (38/71) 
77% (54/70) 
81% (56/69) </p>

<p>Specificity 
77% (30/39) 
54% (21/39) 
85% (22/26) 
51% (20/39) 
73% (19/26) 
42% (11/26) 
42% (11/26) </p>

<p>PPV 
84% (48/57) 
80% (70/88) 
80% (16/20) 
79% (72/91) 
84% (38/45) 
78% (54/69) 
79% (56/71) </p>

<p>NPV 
38% (30/78) 
44% (21/48) 
28% (22/79) 
48% (20/42) 
37% (19/52) 
41% (11/27) 
46% (11/24) </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparison of diagnostic abilities among imaging modalities </p>

<p>Imaging 
Az 
value </p>

<p>p-value* vs </p>

<p>Ultrasound 
MRI 
PET/CT 
Ultrasound 1 
MRI </p>

<p>Ultrasound 1 
PET/CT </p>

<p>MRI 1 
PET/CT </p>

<p>Ultrasound 1 
MRI 1 
PET/CT </p>

<p>Ultrasound 
0.626 
-
0.496 
0.03* 
0.763 
0.317 
0.584 
0.868 </p>

<p>MRI 
0.588 
0.496 
-
0.336 
0.079 
0.424 
0.317 
0.041* </p>

<p>PET/CT 
0.532 
0.030* 
0.336 
-
0.182 
0.017* 
0.27 
0.138 </p>

<p>Ultrasound 1 
MRI 
0.610 
0.763 
0.079 
0.182 
-
0.666 
0.317 
0.317 </p>

<p>Ultrasound 1 
PET/CT 
0.634 
0.317 
0.424 
0.017* 
0.666 
-
0.496 
0.763 </p>

<p>MRI 1 
PET/CT 
0.596 
0.584 
0.317 
0.27 
0.317 
0.496 
-
0.079 </p>

<p>Ultrasound 1 
MRI 1 
PET/CT </p>

<p>0.617 
0.868 
0.041* 
0.138 
0.317 
0.763 
0.079 
-</p>

<p>PET, positron emission tomography. 
*p , 0.05. </p>

<p>Full paper: Comparison of diagnostic performance of ultrasound, MRI and PET/CT 
BJR </p>

<p>3 of 9 birpublications.org/bjr 
Br J Radiol;88:20150143 </p>

<p>echo time, 4000/74 ms; slice thickness, 3 mm) and dynamic 
unenhanced and contrast-enhanced fat-saturated three-
dimensional (3D) gradient-echo T 1 weighted imaging (5.1/2.4; 
flip angle, 10°; image matrix, 300 3 300 pixels; field of view, 300 
3300 mm; section thickness, 1.5 mm; and section gap, 0 mm). 
Sagittal and coronal reformatted images were obtained using raw 
data. Standard subtraction images were obtained by subtracting 
the pre-contrast images from the early peak post-contrast image 
(obtained at 80 s after contrast injection) on a pixel-by-pixel 
basis. In addition, maximum intensity projection recon-
structions were applied to the subtraction images. ALN metas-
tasis was suspected if the LN had any of the following 
morphologic characteristics: eccentric or concentric cortical 
thickening .3 mm, absent fatty hilum, a transverse axis-to-
longitudinal axis ratio more than two on T 2 weighted image. </p>

<p>Positron emission tomography CT technique 
and interpretation 
After fasting for least 6 h, patients were administered 370 MBq of 
18 F-FDG intravenously. All patients were instructed to rest 
comfortably for 60 min and to urinate before scanning. Whole-
body PET-CT images were obtained with a Discovery ST scanner 
(GE Healthcare, Milwaukee, WI). Seven to eight frames (3 min 
per frame) of emission PET data were acquired in 3D mode after 
a non-contrast CT scan from the base of the skull to the upper 
thigh (tube rotation time of 1 s per revolution, 120 kV, 60 mA, 
7.5 mm per rotation and an acquisition time of 60.9 s for a scan 
length of 867 mm). Emission PET images were reconstructed 
using an iterative method (ordered-subsets expectation maxi-
mization with 2 iterations and 30 subsets; field of view, 600 mm; 
slice thickness, 3.27 mm) and attenuation corrected with non-
contrast CT. Two nuclear medicine physicians reviewed 
18 F-FDG 
PET-CT images on an <rs id="software-0" type="software">AW workstation</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v. 4.4</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GE Healthcare,Milwaukee</rs>, WI) by consensus. Focal 
18 F-FDG uptake with in-
tensity higher than that of normal background soft tissue on 
PET image was considered to be positive for metastasis. CT </p>

<p>images were used for anatomic localization, but not for decision 
making. For the semi-quantitative analysis of 
18 F-FDG uptake, 
standardized uptake values (SUVs) were calculated based on 
injected dose and body weight. Circular regions of interest were 
placed on the ALN and maximum SUVs (SUV max ) were recor-
ded. When the lesion could not be visualized owing to a lack of 
18 F-FDG uptake, an SUV of zero was recorded. </p>

<p>Histopathological evaluation 
All patients underwent surgical resection for breast cancer with 
SLNB and/or ALND. The routinely formalin-fixed, paraffin-
embedded tissue blocks of tumours and ALNs were sectioned to 
4-mm thickness and stained with haematoxylin-eosin. The 
specimens of tumour and ALNs were evaluated according to the 
following histopathological features: tumour size, histological 
type of carcinoma, perinodal extension of tumour in ALN, size 
of tumour deposit in ALN, Black nuclear grade (nuclear grade 1, 
poorly differentiated; grade 2, moderately differentiated; and 
grade 3, well differentiated) and modified Bloom-Richardson 
histological grade (histological grade 1, well differentiated; grade 2, 
moderately differentiated; and grade 3, poorly differentiated). For 
dichotomous-dependent variables, nuclear grade was classified as 
high (grade 1) vs low (grades 2 and 3) and histological grade as low 
(grades 1 and 2) vs high (grade 3). </p>

<p>If no metastasis was detected in SLN or ALN, immunohistochemical 
(IHC) staining was performed. Each node was recorded as benign 
(stage pN0), isolated tumour cells [stage pN0 (i1); #0.2 mm], 
micrometastasis (stage pN1mi; 0.2 # 2.0 mm) or macrometastasis 
(stage pN1-3; .2.0 mm). We classified micrometastasis as positive 
LN. There was no case of isolated tumour cells in our study. </p>

<p>Expression of estrogen receptor (ER), progesterone receptor 
(PR) and HER2 was evaluated in the surgically removed speci-
mens using standard avidin-biotin complex IHC staining 
methods. The ER and PR status was assessed using the Allred score, </p>

<p>Figure 1. Receiver operating characteristic analysis curves for the diagnosis of axillary lymph node metastasis after neoadjuvant 
chemotherapy (NAC). PET, positron emission tomography; US, ultrasound. </p>

<p>BJR 
S You et al </p>

<p>4 of 9 birpublications.org/bjr 
Br J Radiol;88:20150143 </p>

<p>Table 4. Association of diagnostic performance of ultrasound, MRI and positron </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>emission tomography (PET)/CT with histopathological factors </p>

<p>Histological factor </p>

<p>Ultrasound </p>

<p>p-value </p>

<p>MRI </p>

<p>p-value </p>

<p>PET/CT </p>

<p>p-value </p>

<p>Correct 
diagnosis </p>

<p>Incorrect 
diagnosis </p>

<p>Correct 
diagnosis </p>

<p>Incorrect 
diagnosis </p>

<p>Correct 
diagnosis </p>

<p>Incorrect 
diagnosis </p>

<p>Initial tumour size </p>

<p>3.75 
6 2.19 </p>

<p>3.86 
6 2.27 </p>

<p>0.792 </p>

<p>3.6 
6 2.24 </p>

<p>4.18 
6 2.17 </p>

<p>0.153 </p>

<p>4.3 
6 2.3 </p>

<p>3.89 
6 2.15 </p>

<p>0.371 </p>

<p>Tumour size after neoadjuvant 
chemotherapy </p>

<p>1.65 
6 1.81 </p>

<p>2.17 
6 2.21 </p>

<p>0.133 </p>

<p>1.74 
6 1.83 </p>

<p>2.17 
6 2.3 </p>

<p>0.24 </p>

<p>1.95 
6 2.35 </p>

<p>2.37 
6 2.04 </p>

<p>0.343 </p>

<p>Percentage diameter decrease </p>

<p>53.9 
6 39.48 </p>

<p>45.8 
6 35.35 </p>

<p>0.224 </p>

<p>50.28 
6 38.96 </p>

<p>49.12 
6 37.44 </p>

<p>0.869 </p>

<p>57.16 
6 42.92 </p>

<p>37.85 
6 38.79 </p>

<p>0.023* </p>

<p>Size of tumour deposit in 
lymph node </p>

<p>0.97 
6 0.63 </p>

<p>0.5 
6 0.31 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001* </p>

<p>0.84 
6 0.61 </p>

<p>0.57 
6 0.42 </p>

<p>0.045* </p>

<p>1.09 
6 0.6 </p>

<p>0.61 
6 0.49 </p>

<p>0.002* </p>

<p>Perinodal tumour extension </p>

<p>0.709 </p>

<p>0.329 </p>

<p>0.904 </p>

<p>Negative </p>

<p>16 (35.6%) </p>

<p>14 (31.8%) </p>

<p>19 (30.2%) </p>

<p>11 (40.7%) </p>

<p>7 (36.8%) </p>

<p>18 (35.3%) </p>

<p>Positive </p>

<p>29 (64.4%) </p>

<p>30 (68.2%) </p>

<p>44 (69.8%) </p>

<p>16 (59.3%) </p>

<p>12 (63.2%) </p>

<p>33 (64.7%) </p>

<p>Oestrogen receptor </p>

<p>0.009* </p>

<p>0.036* </p>

<p>0.061 </p>

<p>Negative </p>

<p>30 (38.5%) </p>

<p>10 (17.5%) </p>

<p>32 (35.2%) </p>

<p>8 (17.8%) </p>

<p>16 (41%) </p>

<p>14 (23.3%) </p>

<p>Positive </p>

<p>48 (61.5%) </p>

<p>47 (82.5%) </p>

<p>59 (64.8%) </p>

<p>37 (82.2%) </p>

<p>23 (59%) </p>

<p>46 (76.7%) </p>

<p>Progesterone receptor </p>

<p>0.318 </p>

<p>0.248 </p>

<p>0.036* </p>

<p>Negative </p>

<p>41 (52.6%) </p>

<p>25 (43.9%) </p>

<p>48 (52.7%) </p>

<p>19 (42.2%) </p>

<p>24 (61.5%) </p>

<p>24 (40%) </p>

<p>Positive </p>

<p>37 (47.4%) </p>

<p>32 (56.1%) </p>

<p>43 (47.3%) </p>

<p>26 (57.8%) </p>

<p>15 (38.5%) </p>

<p>36 (60%) </p>

<p>HER2 </p>

<p>0.183 </p>

<p>0.716 </p>

<p>0.044* </p>

<p>Negative </p>

<p>52 (66.7%) </p>

<p>44 (77.2%) </p>

<p>64 (70.3%) </p>

<p>33 (73.3%) </p>

<p>24 (61.5%) </p>

<p>48 (80%) </p>

<p>Positive </p>

<p>26 (33.3%) </p>

<p>13 (22.8%) </p>

<p>27 (29.7%) </p>

<p>12 (26.7%) </p>

<p>15 (38.5%) </p>

<p>12 (20%) </p>

<p>Nuclear grade </p>

<p>0.778 </p>

<p>0.313 </p>

<p>0.37 </p>

<p>Low </p>

<p>28 (48.3%) </p>

<p>26 (51%) </p>

<p>34 (46.6%) </p>

<p>21 (56.8%) </p>

<p>10 (38.5%) </p>

<p>27 (49.1%) </p>

<p>High </p>

<p>30 (51.7%) </p>

<p>25 (49%) </p>

<p>39 (53.4%) </p>

<p>16 (43.2%) </p>

<p>16 (61.5%) </p>

<p>28 (50.9%) </p>

<p>Histological grade </p>

<p>0.071 </p>

<p>0.262 </p>

<p>0.008* </p>

<p>Low </p>

<p>33 (55.9%) </p>

<p>37 (72.5%) </p>

<p>44 (60.3%) </p>

<p>27 (71.1%) </p>

<p>11 (40.7%) </p>

<p>39 (70.9%) </p>

<p>High </p>

<p>26 (44.1%) </p>

<p>14 (27.5%) </p>

<p>29 (39.7%) </p>

<p>11 (28.9%) </p>

<p>16 (59.3%) </p>

<p>16 (29.1%) </p>

<p>*p 
, 0.05. </p>

<p>Full paper: Comparison of diagnostic performance of ultrasound, MRI and PET/CT 
BJR </p>

<p>5 of 9 birpublications.org/bjr 
Br J Radiol;88:20150143 </p>

<p>which was expressed as the sum of the proportion score and the 
intensity score of positively stained tumour cells. Tumours with an 
Allred score of at least three were regarded as positive. The intensity 
of HER2 staining was scored as 0, 11, 21 or 31. Tumours with 
a 31 score were classified as HER2 positive, and tumours with 
a 0 or 11 score were classified as negative. In tumours with a 21 
score, gene amplification by using fluorescence in situ hybridization 
was used to determine HER2 status. All specimens were reviewed 
by a pathologist with 16 years' experience. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
The diagnostic performance of ultrasound, MRI and PET/CT for the 
evaluation of ALN after NAC was evaluated with receiver operating 
characteristic (ROC) curve analysis. The diagnostic accuracy was 
estimated by calculating the area under the ROC curve (Az value). </p>

<p>Univariate analysis was performed using x 
2 test for the evaluation 
of relationships between the rate of correct diagnosis of ultrasound, 
MRI and PET/CT with histopathological factors (initial tumour 
size, tumour size after NAC, percentage diameter decrease, size of 
tumour deposit in LN, perinodal tumour extension, oestrogen re-
ceptor, progesterone receptor, HER2, nuclear grade and histological 
grade). The definition of correct diagnosis was that the imaging 
findings and final pathological results were concordant, and the 
definition of incorrect diagnosis was that they were discordant. </p>

<p>Multivariate analysis was performed using logistical regression of 
the variables that were found to be statistically significant on 
univariate analyses. Analyses were performed using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs>® 
v. <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">19.0</rs> statistical software package (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL), with 
a value of p , 0.05 considered to be significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
For 139 patients with ALN metastasis at the time of initial di-
agnosis, the sensitivity of ultrasound, MRI and PET/CT was 88% 
(123/139), 93% (128/137) and 89% (118/133), respectively. </p>

<p>After NAC, 39 (28%) patients showed negative conversion of 
ALN on surgical specimens of sentinel LN or ALN. The sensi-
tivity of ultrasound, MRI and PET/CT was 50% (48/96), 72% 
(70/97) and 22% (16/73), respectively. The specificity of ultra-
sound, MRI and PET-CT was 77% (30/39), 54% (21/39) and 
85% (22/26), respectively. The positive-predictive value (PPV) 
was 84% (48/57), 80% (70/88) and 80% (16/20) and the 
negative-predictive value (NPV) was 38% (30/78), 44% (21/48) 
and 28% (22/79), respectively (Table 2). </p>

<p>According to the combined imaging modalities, the sensitivity, 
specificity, PPV and NPV for detecting axillary nodal metastasis 
were 77%, 51%, 79% and 48% for ultrasound combined with 
MRI; 54%, 73%, 84% and 37% for ultrasound combined with 
PET/CT; 77%, 42%, 78% and 41% for MRI combined with 
PET/CT; and 81%, 42%, 79% and 46% for all three imaging 
modalities combined, respectively (Table 2). </p>

<p>The area under the ROC curve (Az) of each imaging modality 
and comparison of ROC curves between imaging modalities are 
summarized in Table 3 and Figure 1. The Az value of combi-
nation of ultrasound and PET/CT was the highest (0.634) fol-
lowed by ultrasound (0.626), combination of ultrasound, MRI 
and PET/CT (0.617) and combination of ultrasound and MRI 
(0.610). </p>

<p>The Az value of ultrasound was significantly greater than that of 
PET/CT (p 5 0.03), the Az value of combination of ultrasound 
and PET/CT was greater than that of PET/CT alone (p 5 0.017) 
and the Az value of combination of all imaging modalities was 
greater than that of MRI alone (p 5 0.041). </p>

<p>Univariate analysis was performed for the evaluation of rela-
tionships between the rate of correct diagnosis of ultrasound, 
MRI and PET/CT with histopathological factors (Table 4). The 
size of tumour deposit in LN and oestrogen receptor was </p>

<p>Table 5. Logistic regression analysis for variables associated with diagnostic performance of ultrasound, MRI and positron emission 
tomography (PET)/CT </p>

<p>Variables 
b 
Standard error 
Odds ratio 
95% confidence interval 
p-value </p>

<p>Ultrasound </p>

<p>Size of tumour deposition within LN 
2.571 
0.760 
13.073 
2.949-57.964 
0.001* </p>

<p>Oestrogen receptor 
20.981 
0.599 
0.375 
0.116-1.213 
0.101 </p>

<p>MRI </p>

<p>Size of tumour deposition within LN 
1.127 
0.579 
3.085 
0.992-9.592 
0.052 </p>

<p>Oestrogen receptor 
20.333 
0.599 
0.717 
0.221-2.320 
0.578 </p>

<p>PET/CT </p>

<p>Size of tumour deposition within LN 
1.867 
0.778 
6.468 
1.407-29.737 
0.016* </p>

<p>Percentage diameter decrease 
20.002 
0.010 
0.998 
0.978-1.018 
0.812 </p>

<p>Progesterone receptor 
21.363 
0.879 
0.256 
0.046-1.434 
0.121 </p>

<p>HER2 
20.342 
1.036 
0.710 
0.093-5.411 
0.741 </p>

<p>Histological grade 
1.808 
0.926 
6.101 
0.994-37.46 
0.051 </p>

<p>LN, lymph node. </p>

<p>BJR 
S You et al </p>

<p>6 of 9 birpublications.org/bjr 
Br J Radiol;88:20150143 </p>

<p>significantly associated with the rate of correct diagnosis of ul-
trasound (p , 0.001 and p 5 0.009, respectively) and MRI 
(p 5 0.045 and 0.036, respectively). The percentage diameter 
decrease, size of tumour deposit in LN, progesterone receptor, 
HER2 and histological grade were significantly associated with 
the rate of correct diagnosis of PET/CT (p 5 0.023, p 5 0.002, 
p 5 0.036, p 5 0.044 and p 5 0.008, respectively). </p>

<p>Multivariate logistic regression analysis was performed with the 
variables associated with diagnostic performance of imaging 
modalities through univariate analysis (Table 5). Size of tumour 
deposit within LN was identified as being independently asso-
ciated with diagnostic performance of ultrasound [odds ratio, 
13.07; 95% confidence interval (CI), 2.95-57.96] and PET/CT 
[odds ratio, 6.47; 95% CI, 1.407-29.737]. Oestrogen receptor, 
percentage diameter decrease, progesterone receptor, HER2 
and histological grade were not significant independent factors 
for diagnostic performance. A representative case is shown in 
Figure 2. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
About 20-40% of patients underwent negative node conversion 
after NAC, and the best surgical management of ALN is un-
clear. 
9,10 In our results, 39 (28%) patients showed negative conver-
sion of ALN on surgical specimens of sentinel LN or ALN after NAC. 
A previous study reported that involvement of LNs at the time of 
surgery, not the initial axillary node stage, was significantly associated 
with distant disease-free survival. 
11 In ACOSOG Z1071 trial, 
12 in 
patients with breast cancer with clinical N1 stage receiving NAC, if 
two or more sentinel LNs were removed, the false-negative rate of 
sentinel node biopsy was 12.6%. The false-negative rate was signif-
icantly higher in patients with only one sentinel node dissection or 
when SLNs were mapped with a single agent (dye or isotope) than 
dual agents. In another prospective multicentre trial SENTINA, 
13 the 
detection rate of SLNB before NAC was 99.1%. However, in patients 
with LN conversion after NAC, the detection rate of SLNB was 
80.1% and the false-negative rate was 14.2%. Thus, the accuracy of 
SLNB was less favourable in patients after NAC than in patients who 
underwent SLNB without NAC. However, .50% of patients who </p>

<p>Figure 2. A 44-year-old female who had invasive ductal carcinoma with negative estrogen receptor and positive HER2 in the right 
breast and biopsy confirmed metastatic lymph node in right axilla. Initial ultrasound (a) and MRI (b) showed the axillary lymph node 
(ALN) showing eccentric cortical thickening .3 mm. Initial positron emission tomography (PET)-CT (c) also showed increased 
fluorine-18 fludeoxyglucose uptake in the right ALN (peak standardized uptake value 5 2.8). After neoadjuvant chemotherapy 
(NAC) treatment, ultrasound (d) and PET-CT (f) showed no evidence of metastasis in right ALN. However, MRI (e) after NAC showed 
ALN showing 3-mm eccentric cortical thickening suggesting remaining metastasis. </p>

<p>Full paper: Comparison of diagnostic performance of ultrasound, MRI and PET/CT 
BJR </p>

<p>7 of 9 birpublications.org/bjr 
Br J Radiol;88:20150143 </p>

<p>had negative conversion after NAC could be spared from further 
ALND or regional treatment such as radiation therapy. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>A previous study reported that sensitivity, specificity, PPV and 
NPV of MRI for ALN evaluation after NAC were 85.7%, 89%, 
92% and 80.9%, respectively. 
14 In a recent study analysing the 
diagnostic performance of ultrasound, MRI and PET-CT for 
metastatic LN after NAC, 
15 the sensitivity was 70%, 61% and 
63% and the specificity was 58%, 59% and 85%, respectively. In 
a recent review article, 
16 the sensitivity of ultrasound, MRI and 
PET-CT was 58-86%, 59% and 48-85%, respectively, for the 
detection of pathological complete remission of ALN. </p>

<p>In our study, the sensitivity of ultrasound, MRI and PET/CT was 
50%, 72% and 22% and the specificity was 77%, 54% and 85%, 
respectively. We think that the reason why MRI showed the 
highest sensitivity compared with ultrasound and PET-CT is 
that we could perform side-by-side analyses of the individual 
pairs of MR studies before and after NAC treatment concen-
trating on the changes of initially metastatic LNs. We could 
detect more remaining metastatic LNs with subtle eccentric 
cortical thickening of 3 mm on MRI than on ultrasound. Our 
results also revealed that the combination of ultrasound, MRI 
and PET/CT showed the highest sensitivity (81%) and PET/CT 
alone showed the highest specificity (85%). </p>

<p>The PPV of imaging modalities in our study ranged from 78% to 
84% with the highest PPV in ultrasound and combination of 
ultrasound and PET/CT. However, NPV was relatively low 
ranging from 28% to 48%. Combination of ultrasound and MRI 
showed the highest NPV (48%). Therefore, it cannot be con-
sidered a substitute for the SLNB procedure for the diagnosis of 
negative conversion of ALN. Relatively high PPV of ultrasound 
and combination of ultrasound and PET/CT could help sur-
geons to proceed directly to ALND without prior SLNB. </p>

<p>In the study of Park et al, 
17 higher T stage ($T2) and lympho-
vascular invasion were significantly associated with false-negative 
ALN on ultrasound and ultrasound-guided FNAB in patients who 
underwent primary surgery without NAC. In the study of Kim 
et al, 
18 SUV max on </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>F-FDG PET/CT was effective for the ALN 
evaluation in ER-positive/HER2-negative subtypes and in HER2-
positive subtypes. However, it was not effective in triple-negative 
subtypes. However, these studies are about the cases of primary 
surgery without NAC. Breast cancer is a heterogeneous disease with 
biologically different phenotypes. Molecular subtype classification 
by gene expression profiling has led to a better understanding of 
tumour biology and behaviour. However, because of the high cost </p>

<p>and technical complexity, IHC classification based on the expres-
sion of ER, PR and HER2 has been investigated as a substitute for 
the molecular gene profiling. This IHC classification showed good 
correlation with intrinsic molecular subtypes of luminal, HER2-
positive and basal-like forms. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Univariate analysis of our study demonstrated that the positive 
oestrogen receptor and positive progesterone receptor were asso-
ciated with incorrect diagnosis rate of ultrasound, MRI and PET/ 
CT. This result is somewhat different from the previous study that 
demonstrated PET/CT was effective in ER-positive/HER2-negative 
subtype. 
18 There have been many studies about the variable che-
moresponsiveness according to the subtypes of breast cancers. 
Luminal type has been shown to be less sensitive to NAC and had 
the least likelihood of pathological complete remission, whereas 
HER2-positive and triple-negative subtypes showed better che-
mosensitivity to NAC. 
20-23 Our univariate analysis showed that 
breast cancers with positive hormone receptor were associated 
with higher rate of incorrect diagnosis of ALN statue after NAC. 
Because of worse responsiveness to NAC in hormone receptor-
positive cancers, there may be higher probability of residual cancer 
cells in the ALN compared with hormone receptor-negative sub-
types, regardless of negative imaging findings. </p>

<p>However, multivariate logistic analysis showed that hormone 
receptor status and HER2 status did not affect the diagnostic 
performance of all imaging modalities. Only the size of tumour 
deposit in LN was a significant independent factor associated 
with diagnostic performance of ultrasound and PET/CT. </p>

<p>Our result demonstrated that ultrasound alone and combination 
of ultrasound and PET/CT showed the highest PPV (84%). 
Therefore, if there is suspicious ALN on ultrasound, we could 
help surgeons to proceed directly to ALND. </p>

<p>There are several limitations in our study. First, total number of 
patients was relatively small. Further prospective larger multi-
centre studies are needed to validate our results. Second, this 
study was performed retrospectively from a single centre, and it 
could cause selection bias. </p>

<p>In conclusion, combination of three imaging modalities showed 
the highest sensitivity and PET/CT showed the highest specificity 
for the evaluation of ALN metastasis after NAC. Ultrasound 
alone or combination of ultrasound and PET/CT showed the 
highest PPV. The size of tumour deposit within ALN was sig-
nificantly associated with diagnostic performance of ultrasound 
and PET/CT. </p>



<p>BJR 
S You et al </p>

<p>8 of 9 birpublications.org/bjr 
Br J Radiol;88:20150143 </p>



<p>Full paper: Comparison of diagnostic performance of ultrasound, MRI and PET/CT 
BJR </p>

<p>9 of 9 birpublications.org/bjr 
Br J Radiol;88:20150143 </p>

</text></tei>