<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4280422" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A b s t r a c t </p>

<p>Introduction: Currently, the predominant question is whether a laparoscopic approach is comparatively radical in 
comparison with an open access approach, especially in the circumferential resection margin and quality of the com-
pleteness of total mesorectal excision. These factors are important in determining the quality of surgical care as well 
as long-term results of the treatment. 
Aim: This article focuses on the evaluation of circumferential resection margins and on the quality of mesorectal 
excision of middle and lower rectum tumors. In addition, laparoscopic and open techniques are compared. 
Material and methods: Data were collected prospectively and stored in a rectal cancer registry over a 3-year period. 
The parameters studied were age, sex, body mass index, localization and topography of the tumor, clinical stage, 
neoadjuvant chemotherapy and its response, the type of surgery, character of the circumferential and distal margins, 
quality of the mesorectal excision, pT and pN. 
Results: One hundred and twenty-five patients were chosen for our study. Laparoscopy was performed in 53 opera-
tions and a conventional approach was performed in 72 operations. Complete mesorectal excision was achieved in 
54.7% of laparoscopic operations versus 44.4% in the conventional technique; partially complete excision was per-
formed in 20.8 and 12.5%, respectively. Incomplete excisions were described in 24.5 and 43.1% (p = 0.085). Positive 
circumferential margin occurred during laparoscopic surgery in 11 (20.8%) patients, and in the case of conventional 
resection in 27 (37.5%) patients (p = 0.044). 
Conclusions: Our study showed comparable results between laparoscopic and open access procedures during rectal 
resection. The results achieved, in particular in the quality of the mesorectal excision and negative circumferential 
resection margin, show that the laparoscopic approach is comparable to conventional surgical techniques, with an 
adequate surgical outcome, in the treatment of rectal cancer. </p>

<p>Key words: colorectal cancer, total mesorectal excision, circumferential resection margin. </p>

<p>Alexander Ferko, Julius Orhalmi, Tomas Dusek, Milan Chobola, Eva Hovorkova, Dimitar Hadzi Nikolov </p>

<p>Videosurgery and Other Miniinvasive Techniques 4, December/2014 </p>



<p>cumferential margin (pCRM) can be used as a direct 
indicator of oncological radicality, which significantly 
affects the outcome of treatment [1, 3]. According to 
some, a positive pathological circumferential margin 
is a more significant independent predictive factor 
than the actual pT stage of the tumor [3]. 
The laparoscopic approach for resection of the 
rectum has been repeatedly analyzed for many 
years. Currently, the predominant question is wheth-
er a laparoscopic approach is comparatively radical 
in comparison with an open access approach, espe-
cially in the circumferential resection margin. 
Our study is focused on the results of rectal re-
section of the aboral 10 cm. One such study pub-
lished on this subject was unfortunately hindered by 
methodological shortcomings. For example, patients 
with cancer of the upper rectum were included [4, 5], 
while amputation procedures for cancer of the distal 
third of the rectum were excluded [6]. In addition, 
overall patient selection was questionable [7, 8]. </p>

<p>Aim </p>

<p>This article focuses on the evaluation of circum-
ferential resection margins and on the quality of 
mesorectal excision of middle and lower rectum tu-
mors. In addition, laparoscopic and open techniques 
are compared. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Our study includes patients with carcinoma of 
the middle and lower rectum who underwent sur-
gery at the Department of Surgery at the Univer-
sity Hospital in Hradec Kralove in the period from 
January the 1 st 2010 to December the 31 st , 2012. 
Rectal cancer diagnosis was performed by standard 
procedures (colonoscopy, biopsy). Preoperative TNM 
staging was determined by abdominal computed to-
mography (CT). Almost all patients underwent a pre-
treatment pelvic nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), 
and in some cases endorectal endosonography was 
also provided. The height of the lower edge of the 
tumor in all patients was based on clinical examina-
tion, including digital rectal or endorectal sonogra-
phy and MRI measurement. </p>

<p>Monitored data </p>

<p>All observed data were prospectively entered into 
the registry for rectal cancer -ProMED. The factors 
investigated in the laparoscopic group and in the </p>

<p>classic procedures were age, sex, body mass index, 
tumor location and its location in the rectal circum-
ference, clinical stage, type of preoperative therapy 
and response to it, the type of surgery, tumor dis-
tance from the distal resection margins, quality of 
the total mesorectal excision, pathological tumor in-
vasion and pathological evaluation of lymph nodes. 
Patients in whom the lower tumor margin was 
higher than 10 cm from the anal verge were exclud-
ed. Compliance with this condition guaranteed the 
possibility of performing a total mesorectal excision. 
In addition, patients who have not undergone resec-
tion but only palliative derivative stoma were also 
excluded. Patients in whom the laparoscopic oper-
ations were converted were also excluded from the 
study. The last exclusion criterion was a complete 
pathological response (ypT0) or if the tumor was 
not histologically found after non-radical endoscopic 
polypectomy. In these cases it was not possible to 
assess the circumferential margins. 
The treatment strategy for each patient was de-
termined by the decision of the oncosurgical multi-
disciplinary committee. 
Preoperative oncological treatment was indicat-
ed in patients with locally advanced tumors (T2N+, 
T3N+, T4 regardless of N+). After the treatment was 
carried out, NMR re-staging took place and patients 
were operated on at least 8 weeks after completing 
the neoadjuvant cancer treatment. 
Either a conventional or laparoscopic technique 
was employed for each operation. Abdominoperine-
al excision of the rectum and Hartmann's operation 
were also carried out. Since 2012, intersphincteric 
resection and extralevator abdominoperineal exci-
sion of the rectum has been performed at our insti-
tution. Adjuvant chemotherapy was indicated again 
on the basis of the conclusions of the oncosurgical 
committee, especially for patients with tumors of 
stage III and IV and high-risk patients in stage II. </p>

<p>Histopathological evaluation of rectal 
resection </p>

<p>A fresh specimen of the rectum was sent for his-
topathological examination immediately after ter-
minating the resection phase of the operation. The 
histopathological evaluation was done by a knowl-
edgeable pathologist in accordance with the "Histo-
pathological Protocol for Rectal Cancer", which has 
been a standard part of our institutional evaluation </p>

<p>Videosurgery and Other Miniinvasive Techniques 4, December/2014 </p>

<p>Higher risk of incomplete mesorectal excision and positive circumferential margin in low rectal cancer regardless of surgical technique </p>



<p>for surgical treatment of rectal cancer since 2008. 
The quality of the mesorectal excision was assessed 
by Quirke [1]. A positive circumferential resection 
margin is evaluated as a tumor or tumor-affected 
lymph nodes less than or equal to 1 mm. A distance 
greater than 1 mm is considered negative. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>For statistical evaluation the software <rs id="software-0" type="software">NCSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">8</rs> 
was used. For comparing the quantitative data we 
used either the two-sided t-test or the nonparamet-
ric Mann-Whitney, or the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. 
To evaluate the qualitative data we used the c 2 test 
of independence in a contingency table or Fisher's 
exact test. Values of p were obtained with the likeli-
hood-ratio test and considered significance if &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>In the period from January the 1 st 2010 to Decem-
ber 31 st 2012 a total of 229 patients were operated 
on for rectal cancer at the Department of Surgery at 
the Faculty Hospital in Hradec Králové. Sixty-seven 
(29.3%) patients with carcinoma of the upper rec-
tum were excluded based on the given exclusion cri-</p>

<p>teria. From the remaining group of 162 patients with 
carcinoma of the middle and lower rectum, 11 fur-
ther patients were excluded: 10 (6.2%) who under-
went only palliative stoma and 1 patient on whom 
transanal local surgery was performed. In addition, 
from the remaining 151 patients, 11 (7.3%) patients 
with tumors of the middle and lower rectum were 
excluded (Figure 1). These patients had achieved 
a pathologically complete response following neoad-
juvant chemoradiotherapy. Ten patients (6.2%) were 
excluded due to converted surgery. The main reason 
was to achieve homogeneous groups. Five (3.3%) 
other patients were not be intended quality of the 
mesorectal excision were also excluded. The total 
number of enrolled patients was 125: 76 men and 
49 women, with an age range of 38-86 years. 
Laparoscopy was performed in 53 cases, while 
a conventional approach was used in 72 cases (Fig-
ure 2). A diverting ileostomy was performed in 49 
(36.3%). 
These two groups, the laparoscopic and conven-
tional groups, differed significantly in body mass 
index (BMI, median 26.2 kg/m 2 vs. 27.9 kg/m 2 ) (p = 
0.021). In both groups there was a higher number of 
men than women (64.2% in the laparoscopic group 
and 58.3% in the conventional group). In the group 
of laparoscopic procedures, middle rectal carcinoma 
represented 52.8% of the procedures, tumors of the 
lower rectum 47.2%. A conventional operation was </p>

<p>Figure 1. Study profile </p>

<p>229 patients with rectal cancer had 
operations in the period 
January 2010 -December 2012 </p>

<p>67 patients with upper rectal carcinoma 
were excluded </p>

<p>162 patients with middle 
and lower rectal carcinoma </p>

<p>Excluded: 
-10 patients with palliative stoma 
-1 patient with transanal miniinvasive 
surgery </p>

<p>151 patients with rectal resection 
were included </p>

<p>Excluded: 
-11 patients with ypT0 
-5 patients with unidentified TME 
-10 patients with converted surgery </p>

<p>125 patients were included 
in the study </p>

<p>Figure 2. Low and mid third rectal cancer. Num-
ber of resection procedures in successive years </p>

<p>Number of patients </p>

<p>2010 
2011 
2012 </p>

<p>Year </p>

<p>Laparoscopy 
Open </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Alexander Ferko, Julius Orhalmi, Tomas Dusek, Milan Chobola, Eva Hovorkova, Dimitar Hadzi Nikolov </p>

<p>Videosurgery and Other Miniinvasive Techniques 4, December/2014 </p>



<p>performed for middle rectal tumors in 47.2% of the 
cases and lower rectum in 52.8%. In the group of 
middle rectal tumors there were 14 patients (22.2%) 
with tumor localization within 9-10 cm from the anal 
verge. 
Distribution based on clinical stage and type of 
surgery was not statistically significant (stage I -
43.4%. vs. 29.2%, stage II -15.1% vs. 29.2%, stage 
III -28.3% vs. 23.6% and stage IV -13.2% vs. 18.1%) 
(Table I). </p>

<p>Ninety-seven (77.6%) patients underwent total 
preoperative oncologic treatment, while 60.4% of the 
patients underwent chemoradiotherapy before the 
laparoscopic procedure, and 52.8% before convention-
al resection. Eight patients (2 vs. 6) were irradiated in 
long mode, and 19 patients (5 vs. 14) in short mode. 
Twenty-eight patients received no preoperative onco-
logical treatment. No statistically significant difference 
was found in response to neoadjuvant therapy (p = 
0.098), where a partial pathological response in the </p>

<p>Table I. Comparison of the laparoscopic and open group. Demographic and basic oncologic data </p>

<p>Parameter 
Laparoscopic 
Open 
Value of p </p>

<p>n 
% 
n 
% </p>

<p>Number of patients 
53 
72 </p>

<p>Age [years]: 
0.63 </p>

<p>Mean 
65.4 
66.4 </p>

<p>Median 
65 
66 </p>

<p>Range 
40-85 
38-86 </p>

<p>Gender: 
0.51 </p>

<p>Male 
34 
64.2 
42 
58.3 </p>

<p>Female 
19 
35.8 
30 
41.7 </p>

<p>BMI [kg/m²]: 
0.021 </p>

<p>Mean 
26.6 
28.4 </p>

<p>Median 
26.2 
27.9 </p>

<p>Range 
19.4-38.2 
19.9-41.9 </p>

<p>Tumor location: 
0.54 </p>

<p>Middle rectum (5-10 cm) 
28 
52.8 
34 
47.2 </p>

<p>Lower rectum (0-5 cm) 
25 
47.2 
38 
52.8 </p>

<p>Tumor topography: 
0.19 </p>

<p>Circular 
11 
20.8 
24 
34.2 </p>

<p>Anterior 
10 
18.9 
19 
27.1 </p>

<p>Dorsal 
13 
24.5 
9 
12.9 </p>

<p>Lateral on the right 
9 
17 
9 
12.9 </p>

<p>Lateral on the left 
10 
18.9 
9 
12.9 </p>

<p>Clinical stage: 
0.17 </p>

<p>I 
23 
43.4 
21 
29.2 </p>

<p>II 
8 
15.1 
21 
29.2 </p>

<p>III 
15 
28.3 
17 
23.6 </p>

<p>IV 
7 
13.2 
13 
18.1 </p>

<p>Videosurgery and Other Miniinvasive Techniques 4, December/2014 </p>

<p>Higher risk of incomplete mesorectal excision and positive circumferential margin in low rectal cancer regardless of surgical technique </p>



<p>laparoscopic group occurred in 45.3% of the patients, 
in contrast to 30.6% in the group with open surgery. 
Laparoscopy was performed in 43 patients 
(81.1%) by means of low anterior resection, includ-
ing 4 intersphincteric resections. An abdominoper-
ineal amputation was performed in 9 patients of 
this group (17%), along with 1 (1.9%) Hartmann's 
operation. In the group of open surgery 26 (36.1%) 
low anterior resections were performed, 39 (54.2%) 
abdominoperineal amputations and 7 (9.7%) Hart-
mann's resections. A statistically significant differ-
ence (p = 0.000001) was observed between these 
groups. The difference was mainly due to the high 
number of low anterior resections in the laparo-
scopic group and more than 50% share of amputa-
tion procedures in the open surgery group (Table II). </p>

<p>Histopathological aspects </p>

<p>The first quality of TME, namely complete me-
sorectal excision, was achieved in 54.7% of patients 
in the laparoscopic group, compared with 44.4% in 
the group of patients operated on conventionally. 
Partially complete excision was performed in 20.8% 
and 12.5%, respectively. Incomplete excision was de-
scribed in 24.5% and 43.1%, respectively. Differenc-</p>

<p>es in mesorectal excision in both surgical approach-
es were not statistically significant. 
A positive circumferential margin was described 
in the laparoscopic procedure in 11 (20.8%) patients. 
In the case of an open resection, the number was 
27 (37.5%). The results between groups were statis-
tically significant (p = 0.044) (Table III). 
The ypCRM (after neoadjuvant oncologic treat-
ment) was evaluated and compared in selected 
group of patients treated preoperatively with the 
laparoscopic or conventional technique (Table IV). 
The results were not statistically significant (Fisher 
p = 0.11). We suppose that a relatively small group 
of patients has been included in our study to demon-
strate the difference between laparoscopic and con-
ventional groups. The distance from the distal tumor 
resection margin was not statistically significant, but 
it was in favor of the open method (median 20.7 mm 
in laparoscopy, 24.2 mm in the conventional proce-
dure) (p = 0.45). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The benefits of laparoscopic resection of the rec-
tum, which include reduced postoperative pain and </p>

<p>Table II. Comparison of the laparoscopic and open group. Factors connected with treatment </p>

<p>Parameter 
Laparoscopic 
Open 
Value of p </p>

<p>n 
% 
n 
% </p>

<p>Neoadjuvant therapy: 
0.28 </p>

<p>Without 
14 
26.4 
14 
19.4 </p>

<p>Chemoradiotherapy 
32 
60.4 
38 
52.8 </p>

<p>Radiotherapy -long course 
2 
3.8 
6 
8.4 </p>

<p>Radiotherapy -short course 
5 
9.4 
14 
19.4 </p>

<p>Response to therapy: 
0.098 </p>

<p>Partial pathological response 
24 
45.3 
22 
30.6 </p>

<p>Stable disease 
9 
16.9 
23 
31.9 </p>

<p>Progressive disease 
3 
5.7 
4 
5.6 </p>

<p>Not available 
17 
32.1 
23 
31.9 </p>

<p>Type of procedure: 
0.000001 </p>

<p>Low anterior resection 
43 
81.1 
26 
36.1 </p>

<p>Abdominoperineal amputation 
9 
17 
39 
54.2 </p>

<p>Hartmann's procedure 
1 
1.9 
7 
9.7 </p>

<p>Alexander Ferko, Julius Orhalmi, Tomas Dusek, Milan Chobola, Eva Hovorkova, Dimitar Hadzi Nikolov </p>

<p>Videosurgery and Other Miniinvasive Techniques 4, December/2014 </p>



<p>faster recovery, with both early resumption of bowel 
function and shortened hospitalization, are very well 
known and confirmed by prospective clinical studies </p>

<p>[5, 7-11]. An important and strictly monitored pa-
rameter is the oncological aspects of laparoscopic 
procedures. When comparing the results of surgical </p>

<p>Table III. Comparison of the laparoscopic and open group. Results of the pathological examination </p>

<p>Parameter 
Laparoscopic 
Open 
Value of p </p>

<p>n 
% 
n 
% </p>

<p>Character of distal resection margin: 
0.23 </p>

<p>Positive 
3 
5.7 
10 
13.9 </p>

<p>Negative 
50 
94.3 
62 
86.1 </p>

<p>Distance from distal resection margin to tumor [mm]: 
0.45 </p>

<p>Mean 
20.7 
24.2 </p>

<p>Median 
15 
20 </p>

<p>Range 
0-60 
0-99.9 </p>

<p>Circumferential margin [mm]: 
0.20 </p>

<p>Mean 
7.2 
6.2 </p>

<p>Median 
5 
2.8 </p>

<p>Range 
0-40 
0-45 </p>

<p>Character of circumferential margin: 
0.044 </p>

<p>≤ 1 mm 
11 
20.8 
27 
37.5 </p>

<p>&gt; 1 mm 
42 
79.2 
45 
62.5 </p>

<p>Total mesorectal excision quality: 
0.085 </p>

<p>Complete 
29 
54.7 
32 
44.4 </p>

<p>Nearly complete 
11 
20.8 
9 
12.5 </p>

<p>Incomplete 
13 
24.5 
31 
43.1 </p>

<p>pT stage </p>

<p>Middle rectum: 
0.074 </p>

<p>pT1 
2 
7.1 
1 
2.9 </p>

<p>pT2 
17 
60.8 
12 
35.3 </p>

<p>pT3 
9 
32.1 
19 
55.9 </p>

<p>pT4 
0 
0 
2 
5.9 </p>

<p>Low rectum: 
0.068 </p>

<p>pT1 
5 
20.0 
3 
7.9 </p>

<p>pT2 
10 
40.0 
9 
23.7 </p>

<p>pT3 
9 
36.0 
17 
44.7 </p>

<p>pT4 
1 
4.0 
9 
23.7 </p>

<p>Number of harvested lymphatic nodes: 
0.26 </p>

<p>Mean 
17.2 
19.0 </p>

<p>Median 
14 
16 </p>

<p>Range 
2-55 
6-55 </p>

<p>pN stage: 
0.85 </p>

<p>N0 
31 
58.5 
44 
61.1 </p>

<p>N+ 
22 
41.5 
28 
38.9 </p>

<p>Videosurgery and Other Miniinvasive Techniques 4, December/2014 </p>

<p>Higher risk of incomplete mesorectal excision and positive circumferential margin in low rectal cancer regardless of surgical technique </p>



<p>treatment of rectal cancer, particular attention must 
be given to the varying anatomy and principles of 
surgical treatment, especially in tumors of the lower 
third. Unfortunately, many studies do not reflect the 
view of the divergent results of TME and CRM tumors 
above and below 10 cm from the anus. Incorporating 
upper rectum resections into procedures has led to 
an "improvement" in the results and thus distorted 
the results of many studies. It has been shown that 
while the prognosis of rectal cancer depends princi-
pally on the stage of disease at diagnosis, the inci-
dence of local recurrence after resection of the rec-
tum reflects the quality of the surgeon [8, 12-16]. 
Traction using laparoscopic instrumentation is 
difficult and can lead to tears in the mesorectum, 
which can also be the cause of the poor quality of 
the mesorectal excision. On the other hand, lapa-
roscopy provides a detailed view of the pelvis and 
greater control over the management of the identi-
fication of the resection line, essential for the high 
quality of the oncologic outcome. Capnoperitoneum 
plays a role, which helps separate the avascular tis-
sue layers [16, 17]. The open operation is facilitated 
by hand traction, which does not damage fat me-
sorectal tissue. It has been repeatedly demonstrated 
that total mesorectal excision is a significant mile-
stone in reducing local recurrence [2]. 
Obese patients have larger mesorectal fat tis-
sue, so handling and dissecting in tighter spaces 
makes identifying the avascular layer difficult. Iden-
tifying the layers also poses problems even in thin 
patients. The layer of perirectal fat is low, and dis-
section is closer to the intestinal wall and thus to 
the tumor, making it difficult to prevent tearing the 
mesorectum [4]. The BMI difference between these 
two groups was evaluated in our study and showed 
statistical significance, probably due to the fact that 
patients with a lower BMI were previously operated 
on laparoscopically. Some studies take into account 
the distribution of "internal" fat and pelvic propor-
tions as factors to be considered in terms of surgical 
tactics [18]. Also sex of the patient plays an import-</p>

<p>ant role. A woman and a man carry the risk of injury 
of the mesorectum and pCRM disruption. Injury of 
the mesorectum can be caused by a thin fat layer, 
especially in the ventral part of the mesorectum in 
a woman. However, the combination of a narrow 
small pelvis with bulky mesorectal tissue in a man 
can be the cause of worse results of TME. 
The quality of mesorectal excision and pCRM are 
related yet independent prognostic factors. The rela-
tionship between pCRM+ and the completeness of 
the mesorectal excision has been documented by 
Nagtegaal. In 44% of patients with pCRM+ a torn 
mesorectum was observed, while patients with an 
intact mesorectum exhibited pCRM positivity in 11% 
of cases [13]. 
The study COLOR II, which prospectively com-
pared the laparoscopic and open technique for rectal 
resection, showed no statistically significant differ-
ence in the frequency of pCRM+ between these two 
groups (93% of laparoscopically operated patients 
had negative pCRM vs. 91% of patients in the open 
surgery group). Conversely, a difference was ob-
served in the positivity of the pCRM in carcinoma of 
the lower rectum. A significantly lower number was 
found in the laparoscopic than in the open approach 
(the difference was 12.4%). The difference in pCRM 
positivity was even more pronounced in the case of 
abdominoperineal amputation. A positive pCRM was 
found in 25% of open procedures, but only in 8% 
during laparoscopic procedures [17]. 
Similar results have also been obtained by the 
prospective multicenter study COREAN, dealing with 
the results of the treatment of rectal cancer within 
9 cm. Positive pCRM was exhibited in 2.9% of pa-
tients in the laparoscopic resection group, and in the 
open technique group the figure was 4.1%. Even from 
other studies comparing the influence of the chosen 
surgical techniques to pCRM it is obvious that the 
results in this category are identical [14, 16, 19, 20]. 
In a study by Laurent, which included more than 
80% of patients with lesions of the middle and low-
er rectum, there were no differences in the number </p>

<p>Table IV. ypT results in laparoscopic and open group with regard to CRM </p>

<p>CRM 
Laparoscopic 
Open 
Value of p </p>

<p>n 
% 
n 
% </p>

<p>Negative 
32 
82.1 
39 
67.2 
0.11 </p>

<p>Positive 
7 
17.9 
19 
32.8 </p>

<p>Alexander Ferko, Julius Orhalmi, Tomas Dusek, Milan Chobola, Eva Hovorkova, Dimitar Hadzi Nikolov </p>

<p>Videosurgery and Other Miniinvasive Techniques 4, December/2014 </p>



<p>of positive CRM for both techniques (7% vs. 6%), 
and thus no differences in local recurrence in both 
groups (3.9% vs. 5.5%). These results were probably 
achieved due to the high number of R0 resections 
(92% vs. 95%) [21]. However, the results may be 
affected by including in the overall group patients 
(12%) with tumors of the upper rectum. The differ-
ence we found between ypCRM+ after laparoscopic 
and conventional resection of the rectum for cancer 
within 10 cm (12.5% and 27.8%, respectively) was 
not statistically significant. There is, however, the 
assumption that increasing the number of patients 
in the study resulted in a statistically significant dif-
ference in favor of laparoscopic resection. Partial se-
lection of the patients who are candidates for lapa-
roscopic resection (patients with a positive response 
in tumor size on preoperative treatment, no tumor 
infiltration of surrounding organs and patients in 
whom bulky tumors were not found) probably af-
fects the outcome of this study. 
Achieving complete mesorectal excision is very 
important in the case of obtaining a negative cir-
cumferential resection margin with all consequenc-
es of treatment for the patient [22]. 
Another factor to consider is the impact of posi-
tive lymph nodes and radial spread of tumor through 
the mesorectal tissue on positive pCRM. Patients 
with pN+ and in whom positive CRM was observed 
had a damaged mesorectum in 44% of cases. This is 
compared to patients with mesorectal excision qual-
ity of the third degree and pN-, where a positive cir-
cumferential margin was found in 24% of cases [13]. 
In the COREAN study positive CRM after conven-
tional abdominoperineal amputation was described 
in 8.3% and 5.3% for the laparoscopic procedure [7]. 
In our study we observed positive CRM in the lapa-
roscopically assisted APR in 33.3%, and in the open 
procedure in 47.6%. Such a high rate of non-radical 
performance can be attributed to the relatively small 
group of patients with amputation. 
A higher frequency of positive pCRM has been 
found in patients with abdominoperineal amputa-
tion (10.2% to 13.9%) compared to low anterior re-
section (3.6% to 8.7%) [23, 24]. 
Positive CRM contributes to the increased inci-
dence of local recurrence (36.5% vs. 22.3%) and 
a shorter overall survival rate (52.3% vs. 65.8%) [22, 
24]. In our group similar results were confirmed and 
led to a change in surgical technique for AP ampu-
tation. </p>

<p>The distance of the tumor from the anal verge is 
closely related to the quality of the removed mesorec-
tum. Low anterior resections for tumors of the distal 
rectum achieve complete excision only in 39% of cas-
es, compared with 67% in cases where tumors are 
located at distances more than 10 cm from the anus. 
Similar results were observed in amputation proce-
dures. The APR group had a complete mesorectum in 
only 34% of patients. Compare that with low anterior 
resections, where complete excision was achieved in 
73% of patients. No difference was observed between 
the genders and age of the patients [13]. 
Problems during dissection in the perineal phase 
of the Miles operation can be tumor infiltration of 
the levator muscle, which can lead to nonradical 
surgery with pCRM+. Specimen perforation during 
resection is in even more aboral localisation due to 
poor orientation of the surgeon in the case of a bulky 
tumor with a close relationship to nearby organs -
vagina, prostate, urethra or urinary bladder. 
Subsequently, the result is low quality mesorec-
tal excision together with more positive CRM. The 
solution of this problem may be cylindrical excision 
of the rectum. Laurent compared the long-term on-
cological outcome between laparoscopic and con-
ventional resection of the rectum and found that, 
over a 5-year period, the incidence of local recur-
rence was not significantly different (3.9% vs. 5.5%). 
Furthermore, the long-term disease-free survival re-
sults are comparable for the two methods [21, 25]. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Our study showed no differences between laparo-
scopic and open access with regard to oncological out-
comes in rectal resections. Evaluating both pCRM and 
the quality of excision confirmed the legitimacy of the 
laparoscopic approach. To confirm these results, fur-
ther studies on a larger cohort of patients is necessary. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This article was supported by MH CZ -DRO (UHHK, 
00179906). </p>



<p>Videosurgery and Other Miniinvasive Techniques 4, December/2014 </p>

<p>Higher risk of incomplete mesorectal excision and positive circumferential margin in low rectal cancer regardless of surgical technique </p>





<p>Received: 19.01.2014, accepted: 14.09.2014. </p>

</text></tei>