<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4508259" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A worldwide epidemic of chronic disease, and complications thereof, is underway, with no sign of abatement. Healthcare costs 
have increased tremendously, principally because of the need to treat chronic complications of non-communicable diseases in-
cluding cardiovascular disease, blindness, end-stage renal disease, and amputation of extremities. Current healthcare systems fail 
to provide an appropriate quality of care to prevent the development of chronic complications without additional healthcare costs. 
A new paradigm for prevention and treatment of chronic disease and the complications thereof is urgently required. Several clini-
cal studies have clearly shown that frequent communication between physicians and patients, based on electronic data transmis-
sion from medical devices, greatly assists in the management of chronic disease. However, for various reasons, these advantages 
have not translated effectively into real clinical practice. In the present review, we describe current relevant studies, and trends in 
the use of information technology for chronic disease management. We also discuss limitations and future directions. </p>

<p>The incidence of chronic disease, including diabetes mellitus, 
hypertension, dyslipidemia, and cardiovascular disease, has 
increased rapidly as industrialization becomes ubiquitous 
[1,2]. The worldwide diabetic population is projected to in-
crease from 366 million in 2011 to 552 million in 2030 [3]. 
Diabetes is already a major healthcare burden; the annual mor-
tality is estimated to be 4.6 million [4]. In South Korea, the 
prevalence of diabetes among adults aged 30 years or over is 
about 12.4%, and the estimated number of diabetic subjects 4 
million [5]. It is essential to improve medical services to en-
sure effective high-quality medical treatment; this obviously 
increases both demand and cost. Further increases in the inci-
dence of chronic disease and accompanying complications are </p>

<p>inevitable unless the current system is changed. The social and 
economic expense of change must be accepted. 
In patients with chronic diseases, prevention of various 
complications is generally more important than treating the 
disease per se. However, this is extraordinarily expensive. For 
example, the annual cost of treating diabetic complications in 
the United States is 45 billion US dollar (USD) [6,7]. Compli-
cations can be prevented if chronically diseased patients main-
tain healthy lifestyles. Thus, an ideal management system 
would allow remote 24-hour communication between the pa-
tient and a medical support team, to jointly plan lifestyle be-
havior and to monitor aspects of the disease. However, this is 
currently impossible. 
Current healthcare systems focus on treatment-based care. 
A new focus on the prevention of chronic diseases is essential. </p>

<p>Received: 19 May 2015, Revised: 26 May 2015, 
Accepted: 29 May 2015 
Corresponding author: Kun-Ho Yoon 
Department of Endocrinology and Metabolism, Seoul St. Mary's Hospital, 
College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, 222 Banpo-daero, 
Seocho-gu, Seoul 137-701, Korea 
Tel: +82-2-2258-8262, Fax: +82-2-2258-8297, E-mail: yoonk@catholic.ac.kr </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Korean Endocrine Society 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Com-
mons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribu-
tion, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly 
cited. </p>

<p>Kim HS, et al. </p>

<p>160 www.e-enm.org </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Korean Endocrine Society </p>

<p>Healthy high-risk subjects must be taught how to manage their 
lifestyles; they need information on diet and exercise. Current 
medical systems lack the resources to focus on lifestyles, be-
ing restricted in time, by place, and by cost. Diet and exercise 
interventions must be integrated into the daily lives of all dia-
betic patients. In South Korea, only 29.5% of such patients at-
tain the target glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c) level (below 
6.5%); diabetes management is thus generally unsuccessful. 
Driven by such needs, various U-healthcare systems have 
been developed and their clinical benefits assessed [8-14]. The 
widely used expression "ubiquitous healthcare" (U-healthcare) 
combines the word "ubiquitous" (simultaneously present any-
time, anywhere)" with "healthcare." U-healthcare uses fixed 
or mobile networking to ensure access to healthcare or medi-
cal services anywhere, at any time. U-healthcare has attracted 
increasing interest; it is recognized that chronic diseases re-
quire continuous management, integrated into daily life. Such 
diseases cannot be efficiently managed using hospital-centered 
treatment methods. </p>

<p>HOW CAN WE MINIMIZE THE 
COMPLICATIONS OF CHRONIC DISEASE 
AND IMPROVE THE QUALITY OF CARE? </p>

<p>It is essential to reduce healthcare expenditure but maintain 
healthcare quality. Diabetic patients are at high risk of the de-
velopment of various complications and are thus in need of 
constant management. Diabetic complications, such as cardio-
vascular disease, account for the major proportion of treatment 
costs, which can obviously be reduced by preventing the de-
velopment of complications [15]. Many reports have shown 
that aggressive diabetes management saves medical costs 
[16,17] and need not affect the quality of care. Prevention of 
complications, early treatment triggered by close monitoring 
of blood glucose levels, proactive education on diet and exer-
cise, and regular monitoring, are all essential to manage diabe-
tes effectively and at minimal cost. Also, detection and inten-
sive treatment of early-stage diabetes greatly contribute to re-
ducing the incidence and cost of long-term complications [18]. 
In the United States, it has been estimated that U-healthcare 
could save over 457 million USD annually if the model be-
came widely accepted [19,20]. U-healthcare cannot currently 
replace direct consultation and treatment, but a telemonitoring 
or telecoaching approach to the treatment of chronic disease 
[21-23] such as diabetes mellitus would be very helpful for 
patients who have already been diagnosed and treated in hos-</p>

<p>pital. Regular hospital visits would continue, but health at 
home would be managed via telemonitoring or telecoaching 
using simple electronic devices. Patients remain connected to 
their physicians and receive medical assistance as needed. 
Such a system would be useful when lifestyle management is 
important, as is true of patients with diabetes mellitus. 
The clinical guidelines for the treatment and management 
of diabetes are well established. Prescriptions, and lifestyle-
related health management (diet and/or exercise) can be en-
trusted to nurses without compromising the quality of care. 
Patient compliance with chronic disease management is essen-
tial [24]; customized treatment plans focusing on prevention 
and management rather than treatment are required. Frequent 
contact with a readily available management team, which may 
include physicians, nurses, dietitians, exercise specialists, and 
professionals in related fields, enhances psychological stabili-
ty; this is the rationale behind "humanistic" or "whole-person" 
treatment. A team effort improves education and monitoring. 
Again, frequent communication is important, as is access to 
information from both the hospital and the patient's home. The 
patient can report frequently on his/her condition. </p>

<p>CLINICAL APPLICATIONS OF 
U-HEALTHCARE </p>

<p>Medical care needs to change from uni-to bi-directional. De-
velopments in information technology (IT) and the develop-
ment of many new medical devices have encouraged recent 
research projects on healthcare communication [25-30]. U-
healthcare combines IT and medicine, allows contact anytime 
with health management and medical services, and is being 
introduced both domestically and internationally (primarily 
targeting diabetics) [31-37]. Patients with chronic diseases, 
such as diabetes or hypertension, are still required to visit 
medical professionals every 3 to 4 months, but U-healthcare 
aids in management between hospital visits. Via a mobile 
phone or the Internet, patient places personal information 
(blood sugar level, drug use, and hypoglycemic status) onto a 
server, and the data are then delivered to a U-healthcare center. 
A medical team next reads and analyzes the information, and a 
medical team member responds if a problem is apparent (Fig. 
1) [35-38]. Many patients have already expressed the desire to 
participate in U-healthcare [35], and an Internet-based glucose 
monitoring (IBGM) system has been developed. In one study, 
a significant decrease in the level of HbA1c was evident in di-
abetic patients who used the system for 3 months; indeed, </p>

<p>Current and Future Status of U-Healthcare </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Korean Endocrine Society </p>

<p>www.e-enm.org 161 </p>

<p>those with higher baseline HbA1c levels benefitted particular-
ly [39]. Furthermore, a 3-month trial yielded benefits that last-
ed for up to 30 months [40]. Thus, IBGM not only reduced 
HbA1c levels but caused such levels to become stabilized. It 
appears that the program motivated patients to manage blood 
sugar levels continuously. Thus, U-healthcare was successful. 
Similar results have been obtained in other studies [25-40]. 
To participate in IBGM, a patient must have access to a 
computer with an Internet connection. Thus, patients in rural 
areas where the Internet is not accessible, or elderly patients 
unfamiliar with computers or the Internet, are unable to access 
U-healthcare. IBGM can be performed only in urban areas 
with readily available Internet connections. In addition, this 
U-healthcare is accompanied by continual direct, personal 
treatment, including visits to medical professionals. Therefore, 
patients with poor accessibility to specialized medical institu-
tions cannot use U-healthcare. Flexibility and accessibility 
must be improved to support systematic diabetes management 
more effectively. A new system featuring personal data assis-
tants with inbuilt blood sugar-monitoring capacities was tri-
alled at a public health center in a farming community with 
limited access to medical professionals and treatment. HbA1c </p>

<p>levels improved significantly [41], confirming that IBGM was 
indeed effective at managing diabetes in a rural area with only 
a public health clinic. This illustrates the benefits of linking 
medical care to a mobile device. </p>

<p>HEALTH ECONOMICS: HOW CAN WE 
REDUCE THE COST OF MEDICAL CARE? </p>

<p>The economic benefit of a U-healthcare system must become 
clear if the system is to be widely accepted. In other words, it 
must be shown that the medical and social cost reductions 
achieved are greater than the expenses associated with estab-
lishment, application, and maintenance of the system. Such 
costs include commercialization, provision of new devices, 
the labor of medical teams, systems maintenance, and server 
management. Any measure enhancing patient care and satis-
faction, while minimizing personal expense, must be cost-ef-
fective [42]. Artificial intelligence systems minimizing the 
medical manpower necessary for effective patient manage-
ment are required. Such software would maximally reduce so-
cial and medical expenses. In fact, such a program (System for 
Automatic Verification, or <rs type="software">SAVE</rs>) was recently applied in </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Scheme of the ubiquitous healthcare system. </p>

<p>Kim HS, et al. </p>



<p>Copyright © 2015 Korean Endocrine Society </p>

<p>clinical research, and reduced physician labor by 50%, thus af-
fording efficiency, stability, and economic benefit. <rs type="software">SAVE</rs> will 
contribute to commercialization of U-healthcare systems by 
reducing labor costs [43]. </p>

<p>WHAT ARE THE LIMITATIONS OF 
U-HEALTHCARE? </p>

<p>Provision of medical services 
Low compliance by medical institutions and physicians 
Many medical institutions and their affiliated physicians lack 
an awareness of U-healthcare, and distrust it. Many will view 
a new technology such as U-healthcare negatively, particularly 
when this is not profitable. Incentives are required. Also, cur-
rently, a physician would be absolutely liable for any medical 
accident associated with U-healthcare. </p>

<p>Lack of clinical trust, experience, and knowledge 
Physicians are accustomed to treating patients in their offices 
or hospitals. Currently, most doctors lack the experience and 
knowledge necessary for management of patients outside a 
hospital. This is particularly so when medical services are ex-
panded to include lifestyle management (e.g., diet and exer-
cise) and encouragement of patient compliance (e.g., with ad-
ministrative requests and disease management). Doctors lack-
ing the necessary experience will require expert medical and 
systems support. </p>

<p>Medical service customers 
A patient may be reluctant to entrust private health-related in-
formation and health status reports to a U-healthcare system in 
the absence of legal standards and/or institutional support. U-
healthcare credibility must be established by providing empiri-
cal evidence that engenders trust, defines any personal costs, 
and establishes a financial system both allowing and compel-
ling a patient to pay reasonable costs. Investment by leading 
companies, and governmental promotion, are necessary. </p>

<p>THE ROLE OF POLICYMAKERS </p>

<p>Policymakers create legal and institutional acceptance, pro-
vide essential support, and make the changes necessary for es-
tablishment of U-healthcare. The current boundaries of tele-
medicine must be broadened. Today, U-healthcare focuses 
principally on lifestyle management. The training of, and the 
roles played by, healthcare workers who are not physicians </p>

<p>but, rather, nutritionists and exercise specialists, must be regu-
lated. In addition, new specialists, such as U-healthcare nurs-
es, must be trained, and the rules of in-house treatment, in-
cluding that performed by visiting nurses, must be relaxed, 
particularly on military bases and in remote or medically un-
derdeveloped areas. </p>

<p>Who is liable? 
Liability is ambiguous if a medical accident not associated 
with diagnosis or treatment (e.g., equipment failure or a com-
munication problem) occurs during U-healthcare. Medical 
professionals will refuse to engage in such care unless the law 
clearly places any liability elsewhere. </p>

<p>Acceptance of U-healthcare by health insurance providers 
Currently, U-healthcare is not covered by many medical insur-
ers, including the Korean national health indemnity provider. 
Therefore, costs fall on consumers and (some) local govern-
ments. Telemedicine will not become readily available or ac-
cepted if the care remains unrecognized by medical insurers. </p>

<p>Incentives for healthcare institutions are low 
Although prevention of complications greatly aids in chronic 
disease management, the incentives for hospitals to prioritize 
such practices are low. Any emphasis on prevention and man-
agement of complications is often insignificant, except in pub-
lic health programs. In some developed countries, including 
the United States, the United Kingdom, and Germany, the 
newer approach is becoming a focus of standard medical ser-
vices, driven by incentives offered to medical institutions and 
physicians who reduce medical expenses by practicing pre-
ventative methods [44-47]. </p>

<p>Protection of personal health information 
U-healthcare is possible only if health information is secure 
but also available outside of medical institutions. The collec-
tion, handling, distribution, and use of personal health infor-
mation gathered via the Internet must be safeguarded; urgent 
research is needed. </p>

<p>HOW DO WE START? </p>

<p>The amount of time a patient spends with medical professional(s) 
is currently extremely limited. Can both lifestyle and medical 
needs be managed via one consultation every 3 months with a 
medical professional? A diabetic patient has a primary need to be </p>

<p>Current and Future Status of U-Healthcare </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Korean Endocrine Society </p>

<p>www.e-enm.org 163 </p>

<p>healthy, and a secondary desire to make lifestyle changes after di-
agnosis. Demands form when financial conditions allow and the 
will to take action develops. As disease management changes fo-
cus from treatment of acute disease to a management-based treat-
ment plan [1,2], the demand for health management may expo-
nentially increase, but the systems in place to support the de-
mands are inadequate. If a "low-cost" lifestyle management sys-
tem were available, this would afford the opportunity to maintain 
and improve life, and would reduce the enormous social and eco-
nomic costs of healthcare. 
How can U-healthcare be developed and implemented? 
This form of care, the new paradigm of chronic disease man-
agement, will require extensive innovations in medical equip-
ment, wireless communications, computer databases, and soft-
ware processing large amounts of data. The U-healthcare sys-
tem has three particular requirements (Fig. 1): monitoring de-
vices and sensors that measure biometric data; networks that 
transmit data; and medical analyses of, and responses to, the 
data. U-healthcare will be in increasing demand when all three 
requirements are met. Mobile devices like Smartphones and 
tablets are becoming ubiquitous and increasingly powerful. 
Sensing devices and networks will become more sophisticat-
ed, enhancing medical applications in chronic disease man-
agement. Currently, both the necessary sensing devices and 
networking facilities are inadequate. Evidence-based improve-
ments and proof of successful clinical application are essen-
tial. Governments should financially support commercial con-
cerns and hospitals that combine to empirically demonstrate 
the effectiveness of U-healthcare. Simultaneously, a large 
clinical research team should be formed. The team should in-
clude representatives of government; corporations producing 
and developing the necessary equipment, services, and sys-
tems; and hospitals and clinics supporting U-healthcare. Com-
mitted long-term governmental support is essential to ensure 
the immediate application of programs that are demonstrably 
effective and stable. 
Since we are bringing in a new system, we shouldn't expect 
that everything will go well. The process should start small 
and then grow rapidly. There must be more clinical trials to 
have definite clinical evidence. Medical staffs in hospitals 
have to be in charge of the clinical research and provide tech-
nical supports and patents. The government and Insurance 
companies should build a guideline and reward of the new 
system and apply them to local clinics. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>Although non-trivial problems remain, it is clear that U-
healthcare is very attractive when diabetes is to be treated. Al-
though not all required changes can be simultaneously intro-
duced, it appears that some such changes will undergo clinical 
testing and implementation in the near future. After U-health-
care treating diabetes has pioneered, other various conditions 
or diseases such as hypertension [48,49], obesity [50-52], car-
diac patients [53-56], and cancer [57-59] can be similarly 
managed. Such initiatives will be rapidly introduced when the 
benefits of U-healthcare in diabetes treatment become evident. 
New forms of management of chronic disease are under de-
velopment. These exploit cellular and social networks, analyze 
large amounts of data, and feature genomic sequencing. The 
entry of IT into medical treatment is inevitable; many coun-
tries are already competing to be the leader. 
Excellence and innovation are required to become globally 
competitive. South Korea, which has excellent IT infrastruc-
ture, can become a world leader in the field, adding to the na-
tion's international reputation. Also, the technology may allow 
early diagnosis of chronic diseases, which can then be treated 
promptly, reducing the risk of later complications. U-health-
care and the associated technology will be commercially very 
valuable, and innovations in equipment, sensors, and commu-
nications infrastructure may be expected. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was re-
ported. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This research was supported by the R&amp;D Program for Society 
of the National Research Foundation (NRF) funded by the Min-
istry of Science, ICT &amp; Future Planning (NRF-2013M3C8A2A0 
2078507). </p>



</text></tei>