<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4766201" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Purpose The aim of this study is to characterize the patterns of 
medication use by early-stage breast cancer (ESBC) survivors 
from diagnosis to 1 year post-chemotherapy. 
Methods A single-center longitudinal study was conducted 
with ESBC patients diagnosed between December 2011 and 
June 2014. Data on the medication use of individual patients 
were retrieved from prescription databases, supplemented by 
records from the National Electronic Health Records. The data 
covered the period from ESBC diagnosis to 1 year post-che-
motherapy. Medication types were classified according to the 
World Health Organization's Anatomical Therapeutic 
Chemical classification system, and medication for chronic 
diseases was created by adapting a list of 20 chronic diseases 
provided by the U.S. Department of Human and Health 
Services. 
Results Of the 107 patients involved in the study (mean 
age 51.1±8.4 years; 78.5 % Chinese), 46.7 % manifested 
non-cancer comorbidities, of which hypertension (24.3 %) 
was the most prevalent, followed by hyperlipidemia 
(13.1 %) and diabetes (5.6 %). Calcium channel blockers </p>

<p>(12.1 %) and lipid-modifying agents (11.2 %) were the 
most common chronic medication types used before che-
motherapy, and their use persisted during chemotherapy 
(10.3 and 11.2 %, respectively) and after chemotherapy 
(11.2 and 13.1 %, respectively). Hormonal therapy was 
the predominant post-chemotherapy medication (77.6 %). 
A statistically significant increase (p&lt;0.0001) was ob-
served in the mean number of chronic disease medication 
classes prescribed to patients between the pre-
chemotherapy (0.53±1.04) and chemotherapy (0.62±1.08) 
periods and between the chemotherapy and post-
chemotherapy (1.63±1.35) periods. 
Conclusions There is an increase in trend of chronic medica-
tion usage in breast cancer survivors after cancer treatment. 
This study provides important insights into the design of med-
ication management programs tailored to this population. 
Future studies should incorporate a control population to im-
prove the interpretation of study results. </p>

<p>According to the World Health Organization (WHO), 32.6 mil-
lion people worldwide were living with cancer in 2012. 
Globally, breast cancer is the second most common form of 
cancer, exhibited by approximately 19.2 % of all cancer patients 
[1]. Early-stage breast cancer (ESBC) survival rates have in-
creased in the last decade. There are numerous possible expla-
nations for the increased likelihood of survival, such as the early 
detection of cancer [2] and the development of more effective 
systemic therapies in the form of cytotoxic chemotherapy, hor-
monal therapy, and targeted therapies [3, 4]. Due to the ageing </p>

<p>Presented as a poster at the MASCC 2015 Annual Meeting, Copenhagen, 
Denmark </p>

<p>* Alexandre Chan 
phaac@nus.edu.sg </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Pharmacy, National Cancer Centre 
Singapore, Singapore </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Pharmacy, Faculty of Science, National University of 
Singapore Block S4, 18 Science Drive 4, Singapore 117543, 
Singapore </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Division of Medical Oncology, National Cancer Centre Singapore 
Singapore, Singapore </p>

<p>Support Care Cancer (2016) 24:1639-1647 
DOI 10.1007/s00520-015-2950-z </p>

<p>population and the expected increase in breast cancer incidence, 
the pool of ESBC survivors is likely to become considerably 
larger in the coming decades [5, 6]. 
Numerous studies have shown that both the disease 
and its treatment have physical and psychosocial conse-
quences for ESBC survivors [7, 8]. These may manifest 
as long-term effects during active therapy or late effects 
that persist for months to years after active treatment. 
These effects may be temporary, progressive, or perma-
nent and range from mild to severe, debilitating, and 
even life threatening. Complications may arise from sur-
gery (pain, numbness, weakness, lymphedema), chemo-
therapy (cognitive dysfunction, neuropathy, sexual dys-
function, cardiac dysfunction), radiotherapy (pain, atro-
phy, fibrosis, late cardiac effects of left breast radiation), 
and the disease itself (psychosocial problems, fatigue, 
pain, sleep disorder, depression/anxiety) [5, 9]. The use 
of adjuvant hormonal therapy in the form of tamoxifen 
has been associated with menopause-like side effects 
such as hot flushes, sleep disturbance, anxiety, and an 
increased risk of uterine cancer and thromboembolic 
events. The use of aromatase inhibitors (AIs) is associ-
ated with vaginal dryness, arthralgia, and an increased 
risk of osteoporosis and fractures. Therefore, survivors 
of ESBC are likely to require different types of medi-
cation throughout their treatment journeys, primarily to 
manage changes in treatment-related complications. 
The majority of ESBC patients are 45-64 years old. 
Therefore, most patients diagnosed with breast cancer 
belong to a subset of a larger population of mid-life 
women with chronic conditions such as hypertension, 
dyslipidemia, diabetes mellitus, and coronary artery dis-
ease [10-12]. Otte et al. reported that the majority of 
breast cancer survivors exhibit at least two non-cancer-
related comorbidities [10]. This observation is consistent 
with the findings of another study, in which more than 
60 % of the sampled breast cancer survivors were pre-
scribed medication for comorbidities, and 53 % reported 
using non-prescription therapies concurrently [13]. 
Therefore, it is vital that the use of medication by breast 
cancer survivors is effectively managed to facilitate 
medication adherence, prevent drug-drug interaction, 
and ensure the efficacy of cancer treatment and chronic 
medication [10, 14]. 
To the best of our knowledge, few researchers have taken a 
longitudinal approach to the medication use of ESBC survi-
vors. Therefore, this study was designed to characterize the 
medication use of ESBC survivors by (i) identifying the prev-
alence of therapeutic classes of medication used before che-
motherapy, during chemotherapy and in the 1 year post-
chemotherapy period, and (ii) comparing the numbers of 
chronic disease medication classes used by patients before, 
during, and after chemotherapy. </p>

<p>Methodology </p>

<p>Study design and population </p>

<p>This is a single-center, retrospective study conducted at the 
National Cancer Centre Singapore (NCCS). NCCS is a lead-
ing regional center for cancer research and treatment, serving 
approximately 70 % of all cancer patients in Singapore. The 
study participants were drawn from a patient cohort recruited 
between December 2011 and June 2014 to participate in a 
prospective longitudinal study designed to investigate the cog-
nitive effects of chemotherapy on ESBC patients [15]. The 
current study was approved by the SingHealth Institutional 
Review Board, and written informed consent was provided 
by all of the study subjects. 
Patients were eligible to participate in the study if they had 
completed at least 1 year of follow-up treatment, dated from 
the last day of their final chemotherapy cycle. The patients in 
the original cohort met the following criteria for eligibility: (i) 
they were aged 21 years or above, (ii) they were able to read 
and understand either English or Mandarin, (iii) they had re-
ceived a diagnosis of ESBC from a medical oncologist, and 
(iv) they had received either anthracycline-based or taxane-
based chemotherapy without a previous history of chemother-
apy or radiotherapy. </p>

<p>Data collection </p>

<p>A data collection form was created to obtain information on 
the patients' sociodemographic characteristics and clinical and 
medication histories. The patients' sociodemographic charac-
teristics (age, body mass index, race, comorbidities, and mar-
ital, menopausal, smoking, and alcohol status) and clinical 
characteristics (estrogen/progesterone receptor status, HER-2 
status, breast cancer staging, histology, and comorbidities) 
were obtained from their electronic medical records. Data on 
the patients' medication use were collected from their elec-
tronic prescription records, covering the period from the date 
of diagnosis (biopsy results) to 1 year post-chemotherapy. As 
the data were collected from electronic records held by public 
institutions, neither the patients' clinical/prescription records 
from private practices nor their non-prescribed medication 
were included. </p>

<p>Medicine classification and definitions </p>

<p>The medication types were classified according to the WHO's 
Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) classification sys-
tem [16]. Each medication was classified at the first 
(anatomical) and second (therapeutic/pharmacological) levels 
of the ATC classification system. The therapeutic drug cate-
gories were further classified as "medications for chronic dis-
eases" or "other medications" according to an adapted list of </p>

<p> 
Support Care Cancer (2016) 24:1639-1647 </p>

<p>20 chronic diseases generated by the Office of the Secretary of 
Health, US Department of Human and Health Services 
(OASH) [17]. The OASH's list was modified to include thy-
roid disorders. 
"Before chemotherapy" was defined as the period between </p>

<p>the date of disease diagnosis (inclusive) and the first day of the 
first cycle of chemotherapy (exclusive). "During chemothera-
py" was defined as the period from the first day of the first 
cytotoxic chemotherapy cycle to the last day of the final cy-
totoxic chemotherapy cycle. "Post-chemotherapy" was de-
fined as the 1-year period beginning on the last day of the 
final cytotoxic chemotherapy cycle (including a 1-year 
trastuzumab maintenance period) (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Descriptive statistics were used to summarize both categorical 
data (frequencies and percentages) and continuous data 
(means and standard deviations). Post hoc Bonferroni tests 
and repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) with 
Greenhouse-Geisser correction were used to assess the signif-
icance of the differences between the numbers of chronic dis-
ease medication classes taken before, during. and after che-
motherapy. All of the data analysis was performed using the 
<rs type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences</rs> program (version 
16.0). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Demographics (Table 1) </p>

<p>A total of 107 patients met the criteria for participation in 
the study; all of whose data were included in the final analysis. 
The mean (± SD) age of the population was 51.1 (±8.4), and 
the majority of the patients [83 (77.6 %)] were 45 years old 
and above. The mean (± SD) body mass index of the popula-
tion was 24.6 (±4.3) kg/m 2 , and 36 (33.6 %) and 23 (21.5 %) 
patients were overweight and obese, respectively. Most of the 
patients were Chinese [84 (78.5 %)], married [81 (75.6 %)], 
non-smokers [92 (86.0 %)], and non-drinkers [99 (92.5 %)]. 
The majority of the patients had been diagnosed with stage 
II breast cancer [49 (45.8 %)] and presented with invasive </p>

<p>ductal carcinoma (IDC) [92 (86.0 %)]. Significant proportions 
of the sample had estrogen receptor-positive [82 (76.6 %)] and 
progesterone receptor-positive [74 (69.2 %)] breast cancer. 
Almost half of the patients [50 (46.7 %)] manifested comor-
bidities. Hypertension was the most common comorbidity [26 
(24.3 %)], followed by hyperlipidemia [14 (13.1 %)] and di-
abetes mellitus [6 (5.6 %)]. Thirty patients (28.0 %) manifest-
ed one comorbidity, and 13 (12.2 %) manifested two 
comorbidities. </p>

<p>Prevalence of therapeutic medication classes before, 
during, and after chemotherapy (Table 2) </p>

<p>Prior to chemotherapy, the chronic disease medication 
types most commonly used by the sampled patients were in 
the cardiovascular anatomical class: calcium channel blockers 
[13 (12.1 %)], lipid-lowering medications [12 (11.2 %)], and 
agents acting on the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone-system 
(RAAS) [7 (6.5 %)]. The main therapeutic classes used were 
analgesics [83 (77.6 %)], medications for acid-related disor-
ders [44 (44.1 %)], and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs 
(NSAIDs) [46 (43.0 %)]. 
Cardiovascular medication types remained the most com-
mon anatomical class of chronic disease medication during 
chemotherapy: lipid-lowering medications [12 (11.2 %)], cal-
cium channel blockers [11 (10.3 %)], and agents acting on the 
RAAS [9 (8.4 %)]. The use of other medication during che-
motherapy was limited to the following three main anatomical 
classes: (i) alimentary tract and metabolism: anti-emetics and 
anti-nauseants [107 (100 %)], drugs for acid-related disorders 
[45 (42.1 %)], drugs for constipation [44 (41.1 %)], and 
stomatological preparations [29 (27.1 %)]; (ii) nervous sys-
tem: analgesics [83 (77.6 %)] and psycholeptics [24 
(22.4 %)]; and (iii) dermatologicals: topical corticosteroids 
[31 (29.0 %)], emollients, and protectives [25 (23.4 %)]. 
Hormonal therapy was the most prevalent therapeutic class 
of chronic disease medication during the 1-year post-chemo-
therapy period [83 (77.6 %)]. There was a noteworthy increase 
in the use of chronic medication from the musculoskeletal 
anatomical class, specifically bone disease medication [13 
(12.1 %)] and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs [28 
(26.2 %)]. An increase was also observed in the use of 
psychoanaleptics [4 (3.7 %)]. Other significant therapeutic </p>

<p>Diagnosis </p>

<p>First day of first 
cycle of cytotoxic 
chemotherapy </p>

<p>Last day of final 
cycle of cytotoxic 
chemotherapy </p>

<p>Before 
chemotherapy </p>

<p>During 
chemotherapy </p>

<p>1 year post-chemotherapy </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Description of the stages 
of patients' treatment journey </p>

<p>Support Care Cancer (2016) 24:1639-1647 </p>

<p>
classes of medication used after chemotherapy were vitamins 
[77 (72.0 %)], analgesics [48 (44.9 %)], emollients and pro-
tectives [38 (35.5 %)], topical corticosteroids [27 (25.2 %)], 
and muscle relaxants [18 (16.8 %)]. </p>

<p>Numbers of chronic disease medication classes before, 
during, and after chemotherapy </p>

<p>Before chemotherapy, 33 (30.9 %) patients received medica-
tion for chronic diseases. During chemotherapy, the number of 
patients [37 (34.6 %)] receiving medication for chronic dis-
eases increased. This number increased further during the 
post-chemotherapy period [92 (86.0 %)] (Table 3). In addi-
tion, the mean number (± SD) of chronic disease medication 
classes increased between the pre-chemotherapy and post-
chemotherapy periods: from 0.53 (±1.04) (before chemother-
apy) to 0.62 (±1.08) (during chemotherapy) and to 1.63 
(±1.35) (post-chemotherapy). A statistically significant in-
crease was observed in the number of medication classes pre-
scribed for chronic diseases as treatment progressed through </p>

<p>Table 1 Demographics (N=107) </p>

<p>Characteristics 
N 
% </p>

<p>Age (±SD) (year) at diagnosis </p>

<p>Mean 51.1±8.4 </p>

<p>&lt;35 
4 
3.7 
35-44 
20 
18.7 </p>

<p>45-54 
40 
37.5 
55-64 
39 
36.4 </p>

<p>65 and above 
4 
3.7 </p>

<p>Body mass index (± SD) (kg/m 2 ) at diagnosis 
Mean 24.6±4.6 
Underweight (&lt;18.5) 
4 
3.7 </p>

<p>Normal (18.5-22.9) 
44 
41.2 
Overweight (23.0-27.4) 
36 
33.6 </p>

<p>Obese (≥27.5) 
23 
21.5 </p>

<p>Race 
Chinese 
84 
78.5 </p>

<p>Malay 
14 
13.1 
Indian 
2 
1.9 </p>

<p>Other a 
7 
6 . 5 
Marital status 
Married 
81 
75.6 </p>

<p>Single 
19 
17.8 
Divorced 
5 
4.7 
Widowed 
2 
1.9 
Menopausal status 
Pre-menopausal 
46 
43.0 </p>

<p>Peri-menopausal 
2 
1.9 
Post-menopausal 
59 
55.1 
Smoking status 
Smoker 
7 
6.5 
Non-smoker 
92 
86.0 </p>

<p>Missing data 
8 
7.5 
Alcohol status 
Yes 
8 
7.5 
No 
99 
92.5 </p>

<p>Estrogen receptor status </p>

<p>Positive 
82 
76.6 </p>

<p>Negative 
25 
23.4 
Progesterone receptor status </p>

<p>Positive 
74 
69.2 </p>

<p>Negative 
33 
30.8 </p>

<p>HER-2 status 
Positive 
50 
46.7 
Negative 
57 
53.3 </p>

<p>Staging </p>

<p>I 
2 7 
2 5 . 2 </p>

<p>II 
49 
45.8 
III 
31 
29.0 
Histology </p>

<p>Invasive ductal carcinoma (IDC) 
92 
86.0 </p>

<p>Table 1 (continued) </p>

<p>Characteristics 
N 
% </p>

<p>Invasive lobular carcinoma (ILC) 
5 
4.7 
IDC + ILC 
3 
2.8 </p>

<p>Others 
7 
6.5 </p>

<p>Comorbidities 
No significant comorbidities 
57 
53.3 </p>

<p>Hypertension 
26 
24.3 </p>

<p>Hyperlipidemia 
14 
13.1 
Diabetes mellitus 
6 
5.6 </p>

<p>Thyroid disorders 
5 
4.7 
Hepatobiliary disorders 
5 
4.7 </p>

<p>Cardiac disorders 
4 
3.7 </p>

<p>Migraine 
3 
2.8 
Eczema 
3 
2.8 </p>

<p>Asthma 
2 
1.9 
Musculoskeletal disorders 
2 
1.9 
Depression 
2 
1.9 </p>

<p>Gastrointestinal disorders 
2 
1.9 
Other b 
4 
3 . 7 
Number of comorbidities (±SD) 
Mean 0.75±1.00 </p>

<p>0 
5 7 
5 3 . 3 </p>

<p>1 
3 0 
2 8 . 0 
2 
1 3 
1 2 . 2 
3 
4 
3.7 
4 
3 
2.8 </p>

<p>a Filipinos, Sikh, Myanmese </p>

<p>b Acute myeloid leukemia, thalassemia, neurofibromatosis type 1, 
endometriosis </p>

<p> 
Support Care Cancer (2016) 24:1639-1647 </p>

<p>Table 2 Medication use before, during, and after chemotherapy (N=107) </p>

<p>Anatomical class 
Therapeutic class b 
For 
managing 
chronic 
disease a </p>

<p>Number of patients (%) </p>

<p>Before 
chemotherapy </p>

<p>During 
chemotherapy </p>

<p>Post-
chemotherapy </p>

<p>Alimentary tract and metabolism 
Drugs used in diabetes 
✓ 
4 (3.7) 
4 (3.7) 
4 (3.7) </p>

<p>Stomatological preparations 
1 (0.9) 
29 (27.1) 
5 (4.7) </p>

<p>Drugs for acid-related disorders 
44 (41.1) 
45 (42.1) 
25 (23.4) 
Drugs for functional gastrointestinal 
disorders </p>

<p>0 
6 (5.6) 
1 (0.9) </p>

<p>Anti-emetics and anti-nauseants 
20 (18.7) 
107 (100.0) 
16 (15.0) </p>

<p>Drugs for constipation 
8 (7.5) 
44 (41.1) 
14 (13.1) 
Antidiarrheal, intestinal anti-inflammatories/ 
anti-infectives </p>

<p>1 (0.9) 
18 (16.8) 
9 (8.4) </p>

<p>Vitamins c 
13 (12.1) 
12 (11.2) 
77 (72.0) </p>

<p>Vitamin B-containing 
3 (2.8) 
14 (13.1) 
33 (30.8) 
Vitamin C 
9 (8.4) 
1 (0.9) 
3 (2.8) </p>

<p>Vitamin D/calcium-containing 
3 (2.8) 
11 (10.3) 
66 (61.7) 
Multivitamins 
1 (0.9) 
5 (4.7) 
2 (1.9) 
Mineral supplements 
2 (1.9) 
1 (0.9) 
0 
Blood and blood-forming organs 
Antithrombotic agents 
✓ 
2 (1.9) 
2 (1.9) 
2 (1.9) 
Anti-anemic preparations 
4 (3.7) 
11 (10.3) 
6 (5.6) </p>

<p>Cardiovascular 
Cardiac therapy 
✓ 
1 (0.9) 
1 (0.9) 
1 (0.9) 
Diuretics 
✓ 
3 (2.8) 
3 (2.8) 
2 (1.9) 
Beta-blocking agents 
✓ 
7 (6.5) 
7 (6.5) 
12 (11.2) 
Calcium channel blockers 
✓ 
13 (12.1) 
11 (10.3) 
12 (11.2) 
Agents acting on RAAS system 
✓ 
7 (6.5) 
9 (8.4) 
11 (10.3) </p>

<p>Lipid-modifying agents 
✓ 
12 (11.2) 
12 (11.2) 
14 (13.1) 
Vasoprotectives 
0 
6 (5.6) 
4 (3.7) </p>

<p>Dermatologicals 
Antifungals 
2 (1.9) 
9 (8.4) 
10 (9.3) 
Emollients and protectives 
1 (0.9) 
25 (23.4) 
38 (35.5) </p>

<p>Antibiotics and chemotherapeutics 
5 (4.7) 
10 (9.3) 
13 (12.1) 
Corticosteroids 
4 (3.7) 
31 (29.0) 
27 (25.2) </p>

<p>Antiseptics and disinfectants 
3 (2.8) 
6 (5.6) 
5 (4.7) 
Genitourinary system and sex 
hormones </p>

<p>Gynecological anti-infectives and antiseptics 
1 (0.9) 
1 (0.9) 
3 (2.8) 
Other gynecological 
2 (1.9) 
1 (0.9) 
0 </p>

<p>Systemic hormonal preparations 
Thyroid therapy 
✓ 
2 (1.9) 
2 (1.9) 
3 (2.8) 
Corticosteroids 
0 
10 (9.3) 
2 (1.9) </p>

<p>Anti-infectives for systemic use 
Antivirals for hepatitis (ribavirin, entecavir) ✓ 
2 (1.9) 
2 (1.9) 
3 (2.8) </p>

<p>Antibacterials 
40 (37.4) 
37 (34.6) 
38 (35.5) </p>

<p>Antimycotics 
0 
1 (0.9) 
2 (1.9) 
Antivirals (aciclovir) 
0 
7 (6.5) 
5 (4.7) 
Antineoplastic and 
immunomodulating agents </p>

<p>Endocrine therapy 
✓ 
0 
5 ( 4 . 7 ) 
8 3 ( 7 7 . 6 ) d 
AIs 
0 
1 (0.9) 
34 (31.8) </p>

<p>Tamoxifen 
0 
3 (2.8) 
53 (49.5) 
Goserelin 
0 
1 (0.9) 
1 (0.9) </p>

<p>Granulocyte colony-stimulating factors 
0 
44 (41.1) 
0 
Musculoskeletal system 
Glucosamine products 
✓ 
2 (1.9) 
1 (0.9) 
1 (0.9) </p>

<p>Anti-gout preparations 
✓ 
0 
0 
1 ( 0 . 9 ) 
Drugs used for treatment of bone diseases 
✓ 
1 (0.9) 
3 (2.8) 
13 (12.1) </p>

<p>Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs 
46 (43.0) 
14 (13.1) 
28 (26.2) 
Muscle relaxants 
1 (0.9) 
8 (7.5) 
18 (16.8) </p>

<p>Support Care Cancer (2016) 24:1639-1647 </p>

<p>
the three periods (p&lt;0.0001). Post hoc analysis revealed a 
significant difference between the numbers of chronic disease 
medication classes used pre-chemotherapy and post-
chemotherapy (p&lt;0.0001) and between the numbers used 
during and after chemotherapy (p&lt;0.0001). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study has successfully characterized the changes in med-
ication use by survivors of ESBC during their treatment jour-
neys until 1 year post-chemotherapy. In summary, cardiovas-
cular medication was the most common class of medication 
prescribed for chronic diseases, with a significant increase in 
the use of hormonal therapies, bone disease medication, and 
psychoanaleptics during the post-chemotherapy period. The 
number of medication classes prescribed for chronic disease 
management also increased during the post-chemotherapy pe-
riod, in comparison with the periods before and during che-
motherapy. Dermatologicals and medication associated with 
the alimentary tract, the metabolism, and the nervous system 
were the most prevalent forms of non-chronic disease medi-
cation during chemotherapy. In contrast, vitamins, dermato-
logicals, musculoskeletal medication, and analgesics were 
predominant during the post-chemotherapy period. The re-
sults of this study make an important contribution to the liter-
ature on the numerous treatment-related complications [7, 8, </p>

<p>18, 19] and chronic disease management needs associated 
with breast cancer. 
The characterization of medication use offers invaluable 
insights into the medication management needs of a popula-
tion of breast cancer survivors, potentially facilitating the de-
velopment of dedicated medicine management services for 
women who have achieved complete remission after treat-
ment. Between ESBC diagnosis and the beginning of chemo-
therapy, changes to the participants' medication were made 
primarily to manage treatment-related complications. The 
trend in medication use during chemotherapy suggests that 
the patients experienced treatment-related complications in 
the following forms: gastrointestinal side effects (mucositis, 
nausea, vomiting, constipation, dyspepsia), which are com-
monly exhibited by patients receiving taxanes and 
anthracycline-containing regimens; neurological effects (anx-
iety, insomnia); and dermatological side effects (probably sec-
ondary to taxanes). 
In contrast, most of the changes in medication post-
chemotherapy reflected the introduction of adjuvant hormonal 
therapies and medication to manage the long-term psychoso-
cial effects of cancer and its treatment. Long-term hormonal 
therapy in the form of AIs or tamoxifen causes side effects that 
must be managed. This explains the prevalence of medication 
for osteoporosis (bisphosphonates, calcium/vitamin D supple-
ments) and musculoskeletal symptoms (NSAIDs, analgesics, 
muscle relaxants, glucosamine), to manage AI-associated 
musculoskeletal effects, and the increased use of </p>

<p>Table 2 (continued) </p>

<p>Anatomical class 
Therapeutic class b 
For 
managing 
chronic 
disease a </p>

<p>Number of patients (%) </p>

<p>Before 
chemotherapy </p>

<p>During 
chemotherapy </p>

<p>Post-
chemotherapy </p>

<p>Nervous system 
Psychoanaleptics 
✓ 
0 
1 (0.9) 
4 (3.7) </p>

<p>Analgesics 
83 (77.6) 
43 (40.2) 
48 (44.9) 
Anti-epileptics 
0 
1 (0.9) 
4 (3.7) </p>

<p>Psycholeptics 
6 (8.6) 
24 (22.4) 
11 (10.3) 
Other nervous system drugs 
2 (1.9) 
0 
3 (2.8) </p>

<p>Respiratory system 
Drugs for obstructive airway diseases 
✓ 
2 (1.9) 
2 (1.9) 
2 (1.9) 
Sore throat preparations 
10 (9.3) 
36 (33.6) 
32 (29.9) 
Cough and cold preparations 
10 (9.3) 
31 (29.0) 
46 (43.0) </p>

<p>Antihistamines for systemic use 
4 (3.7) 
47 (43.9) 
43 (40.2) </p>

<p>Sensory organs 
Ophthalmological anti-infectives 
0 
7 (6.5) 
7 (6.5) 
Ophthalmological lubricants 
1 (0.9) 
10 (9.3) 
10 (9.3) </p>

<p>Ophthalmological anti-inflammatories 
1 (0.9) 
0 
2 (1.9) </p>

<p>a OASH list of 20 chronic diseases (with modifications) [17] </p>

<p>b WHO ATC classification system [16] </p>

<p>c The number of patients does not add up to 107 (N) because some patients were using different vitamins concurrently </p>

<p>d The number of patients does not add up to 107 (N) because some patients switched endocrine therapy types or received multiple therapies </p>

<p> 
Support Care Cancer (2016) 24:1639-1647 </p>

<p>psychoanaleptics (antidepressants) to manage menopausal 
symptoms associated with tamoxifen (hot flushes, anxiety, 
sleep disturbance). It is important to note that the effects of 
estrogen deprivation were not solely due to hormonal therapy 
but were probably compounded by the significant reduction in 
estrogen levels in peri-and post-menopausal women, who 
made up more than half of the sample population [40 
(57.1 %)]. In addition, glucosamine, analgesics, and 
NSAIDs may have been used to manage osteoarthritis, as 
the majority of the population exhibited osteoarthritis risk fac-
tors [20-22] associated with gender (female), weight (over-
weight/obese), and age (elderly). The use of psychoanaleptics 
probably reflects the need to manage the long-term psychoso-
cial effects of cancer and its treatment [18, 19]. 
The significant increase in the burden of medication for 
chronic diseases from the periods before and during chemo-
therapy to the post-chemotherapy period was primarily due to 
the introduction of hormonal therapies in addition to pre-
existing cardiovascular medication. Therefore, the breast can-
cer survivors in our population are likely to face medication 
management problems such as reduced adherence and adverse 
effects. In a recent systematic review, breast cancer survivors 
were found to show suboptimal adherence and persistence 
rates in response to adjuvant hormonal therapy (31-73 % dis-
continuation rates) [23], which may compromise the long-
term survival benefits of such therapy. Adherence was posi-
tively associated with the number of medication types taken at 
baseline, referral to an oncologist and earlier diagnosis, and 
negatively associated with treatment side effects and follow-
up with a general practitioner (as compared with an oncolo-
gist) [23]. This demonstrates the importance of ongoing 
follow-up in the oncology setting and the need to manage 
adverse effects to facilitate adherence to adjuvant hormonal 
therapy. These imperatives are especially important for our 
breast cancer survivor population, as only a minority had re-
ceived long-term medication for chronic diseases before 
starting hormonal therapy. It is also essential to </p>

<p>simultaneously monitor and manage the use of medication 
for other pre-existing chronic diseases such as hypertension 
and hyperlipidemia. Middle-aged non-cancer patients have 
been reported to show suboptimal adherence to antihyperten-
sives [24] and cardiovascular medication such as lipid-
lowering medications for primary or secondary prevention, 
potentially compromising their cardiovascular-associated 
mortality and morbidity benefits. Such information contains 
major implications to our breast cancer survivors. In this 
study, our patients tend to be young (average of 50 years) 
and diagnosed with few comorbidities; such demographics 
are very similar to the national average among 
Singaporeans. For example, the prevalence of hypertension 
is 24 % in our study which is similar to the national survey 
(23.5 %) [25]. Hence, medication compliance remains an im-
portant issue, and clinicians must ensure that these survivors 
adhere to their prescribed adjuvant hormonal therapies and 
chronic medications. 
Primary care is likely to become vital to ESBC survivors' 
long-term follow-up treatment and management, due to the 
growth of this population and their diverse medication man-
agement needs, such as the long-term monitoring of hormonal 
therapy, chronic disease management, and the management of 
long-term treatment/disease-related complications after che-
motherapy. Although oncology specialists continue to play 
critical roles in diagnosis and initial treatment, the activities 
of primary care providers (general practitioners and commu-
nity pharmacists) have been expanded to cover early cancer 
screening, post-treatment follow-up and surveillance for can-
cer recurrence, screening and management of the long-term 
effects of cancer, and its treatment, medication management, 
health promotion, and chronic disease management [9, 26]. 
As a result, numerous models of cancer survivorship care have 
been developed and discussed in the literature [27-29], with 
the aim of establishing a coordinated care partnership between 
oncology specialists and primary care providers. Primary care 
providers are likely to become responsible for managing the </p>

<p>Table 3 Number of medication 
classes for chronic diseases taken 
by each patient before, during, 
and after chemotherapy (N=107) </p>

<p>Number of medication classes 
for chronic diseases </p>

<p>Number of patients (%) </p>

<p>Before chemotherapy 
During chemotherapy 
Post-chemotherapy </p>

<p>0 
74 (69.1) 
70 (65.4) 
15 (14.0) </p>

<p>1 
22 (20.6) 
21 (19.6) 
49 (45.7) 
2 
3 (2.8) 
8 (7.5) 
22 (20.6) 
3 
5 (4.7) 
5 (4.7) 
11 (10.3) </p>

<p>4 
1 (0.9) 
1 (0.9) 
5 (4.7) 
≥5 
2 (1.9) 
2 (1.9) 
5 (4.7) </p>

<p>Mean number of medication 
classes for chronic diseases±SD* </p>

<p>0.53±1.04 
0.62±1.08 
1.63±1.35 </p>

<p>*p&lt;0.0001, obtained by repeated measures ANOVA with Greenhouse-Geisser correction </p>

<p>Support Care Cancer (2016) 24:1639-1647 </p>

<p>
medication of breast cancer survivors during the post-
chemotherapy phase. Furthermore, rising health costs demand 
that the long-term management of breast cancer survivors is 
delegated to the primary setting and that medication manage-
ment is effective. 
Although primary care may have an increasingly large part 
to play in the management of cancer survivors, the roles of 
healthcare workers in the tertiary setting remain crucial, as the 
majority of breast cancer survivors follow-up with their on-
cologists in their first year after chemotherapy. Oncology 
pharmacists are in the best position to understand these pa-
tients' diverse medication management needs (both cancer-
related and non-cancer-related), and they need to be part of 
the multidisciplinary team to manage the long-term complica-
tions experienced by this group of patients. A more concrete 
understanding of the needs of breast cancer survivors will aid 
the development of individualized cancer survivorship plans 
in our setting to improve the coordination of care and make 
effective use of our pharmacists' diverse skill sets in the mul-
tidisciplinary management of breast cancer survivors. 
This study has several limitations. The extent of the pa-
tients' adherence to the prescribed medications was unknown. 
However, compared with interviews or questionnaires, this 
method of data collection minimized the risk of self-
reporting errors and interviewer bias. We were also able to 
track changes in medication throughout the patients' treatment 
journeys, enabling us to identify trends in medication use at 
different stages of treatment. The study was also limited by the 
small size of the sample and the lack of a control population 
with which to compare medication use. However, this sample 
size was reasonable, as it captured the demographic character-
istics of the majority of patients diagnosed with ESBC. Lastly, 
as the study was retrospective, causal relationships could not 
be definitively established. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Given the increasing global population of ESBC survivors 
and the extensive literature on the prevalence of chronic dis-
eases and disease-/treatment-related complications experi-
enced by these patients, ESBC survivors' medication manage-
ment can no longer be overlooked. Our findings suggest that 
ESBC survivors are likely to receive numerous forms of long-
term medication, of which the most common are hormonal 
therapy and pre-existing cardiovascular medication. In addi-
tion, we show that the medication use of breast cancer survi-
vors undergoes several changes from the pre-to post-
chemotherapy periods. These changes are usually made to 
manage treatment-related complications. These findings pro-
vide preliminary insights into the treatment-related complica-
tions experienced by breast cancer survivors in our local pop-
ulation and their chronic disease management needs. These </p>

<p>insights will help both oncology specialists and primary care 
providers to assess patients' needs during long-term follow-up 
treatment, as well as guiding the development of dedicated 
medication management services for ESBC survivors. 
Future researchers should compare the medication use of 
ESBC survivors with that of a healthy population to obtain 
clearer information on the trends in medication use and, more 
importantly, the medication management needs of breast can-
cer survivors. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments This study was financed by research grants 
awarded by the National University of Singapore (R-148-000-166-112), 
the National Cancer Centre Singapore (NRFCB12131), and the National 
Medical Research Council Singapore (NMRC/CIRG/1386/2014). We 
would like to thank Mr. Mark Ryan De Guzman Langit for his assistance 
on this study. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest The authors declare that they have no competing 
interests. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits any noncom-
mercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided 
you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, pro-
vide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were 
made. </p>



<p> 
Support Care Cancer (2016) 24:1639-1647 </p>



<p>Support Care Cancer (2016) 24:1639-1647 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>