<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4564743" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Anterior cervical discectomy and fusion (ACDF) with autolo-
gous bone graft and anterior plating has been the standard pro-
cedure for single level cervical disc disease </p>

<p>12,15,22) </p>

<p>. To reduce post-
operative complications, such as post-operative iliac pain and 
dysphagia, the stand-alone cage was developed </p>

<p>2-4,11,27) </p>

<p>. Compared 
to the traditional procedure, multiple studies have argued that 
the stand-alone cage produces more subsidence and local ky-
phosis at the index level, however no difference in clinical out-
come has been proven </p>

<p>2,4,6,11,21,27) </p>

<p>. Because of its advantages (con-
venience of use and decreased complications, as noted above) 
and less evidence of disadvantages relative to the standard pro-
cedure, the stand-alone cage is widely used for ACDF. </p>

<p>Cervical Stand-Alone Polyetheretherketone Cage versus 
Zero-Profile Anchored Spacer in Single-Level Anterior 
Cervical Discectomy and Fusion : Minimum 2-Year 
Assessment of Radiographic and Clinical Outcome </p>

<p>Hyun-Jun Cho, M.D., Junseok W. Hur, M.D., Ph.D., Jang-Bo Lee, M.D., Ph.D., Jin-Sol Han, M.D., Tai-Hyoung Cho, M.D., Ph.D., 
Jung-Yul Park, M.D., Ph.D. </p>

<p>Department of Neurosurgery, Korea University Anam Hospital, College of Medicine, Korea University, Seoul, Korea </p>

<p>Objective : We compared the clinical and radiographic outcomes of stand-alone polyetheretherketone (PEEK) cage and Zero-Profile anchored 
spacer (Zero-P) for single level anterior cervical discectomy and fusion (ACDF). 
Methods : We retrospectively reviewed 121 patients who underwent single level ACDF within 2 years (Jan 2011-Jan 2013) in a single institute. To-
tal 50 patients were included for the analysis who were evaluated more than 2-year follow-up. Twenty-nine patients were allocated to the cage 
group (m : f=19 : 10) and 21 for Zero-P group (m : f=12 : 9). Clinical (neck disability index, visual analogue scale arm and neck) and radiographic 
(Cobb angle-segmental and global cervical, disc height, vertebral height) assessments were followed at pre-operative, immediate post-operative, 
post-3, 6, 12, and 24 month periods. 
Results : Demographic features and the clinical outcome showed no difference between two groups. The change between final follow-up (24 
months) and immediate post-op of Cobb-segmental angle (p=0.027), disc height (p=0.002), vertebral body height (p=0.033) showed statistically 
better outcome for the Zero-P group than the cage group, respectively. 
Conclusion : The Zero-Profile anchored spacer has some advantage after cage for maintaining segmental lordosis and lowering subsidence rate 
after single level anterior cervical discectomy and fusion. </p>

<p>Key Words : Zero-profile · Anterior cervical discectomy and fusion · Stand-alone cage · Kyphosis · Subsidence. </p>

<p>Clinical Article </p>

<p>• Received : April 2, 2015 • Revised : June 24, 2015 • Accepted : June 24, 2015 
• Address for reprints : Jang-Bo Lee, M.D., Ph.D. 
Department of Neurosurgery, Korea University Anam Hospital, College of Medicine, Korea University, 73 Inchon-ro, Seongbuk-gu, Seoul 02841, Korea 
Tel : +82-2-920-5729, Fax : +82-2-929-0629, E-mail : jblee42@gmail.com 
• This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>J Korean Neurosurg Soc 58 (2) : 119-124, 2015 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3340/jkns.2015.58.2.119 </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 The Korean Neurosurgical Society </p>

<p>Print ISSN 2005-3711 On-line ISSN 1598-7876 </p>

<p>www.jkns.or.kr </p>



<p>J Korean Neurosurg Soc 58 | August 2015 </p>

<p>were immediately post-operative, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months, 
and 24 months. We measured the Cobb angle of segmental area 
(Cobb-s) and Cobb angle of global cervical spine (Cobb-c) in 
the cervical spine plain X-ray lateral view to evaluate the aggra-
vation of kyphosis (Fig. 1). Initially, we planned to evaluate 
bone fusion, but because of a lack of CT data (post-operative 
CT is not a standard procedure because of radiation hazard), 
we evaluated bone fusion through X-ray lateral view. Bone fu-
sion was judged by 2 spine surgeons on radiographs by 1) less 
than 10 degree movement on lateral flexion/extension views, 2) 
presence of bridging trabecular bone between the endplates on 
anteroposterior and lateral views, 3) less than 50% radiolucency 
in the perimeter surrounding the cage, and 4) no evidence of 
pull out of the device. We compared the bone fusion rate of the 
each group on post-operative 3 months, 6 months, 12 months, 
and 24 months. The kappa coefficients for hinge status at each 
observation were 0.69, 0.71, 0.68, and 0.77, respectively. Kappa 
coefficients of 0.68-0.77 suggest good agreement among the 
observers. Also, we compared pre-and post-operative disc 
height (DH) and vertebral height (VH) in the plain X-ray imag-
es to evaluate the degree of subsidence to estimate the spinal 
alignment state indirectly. We measured the anterior-posterior 
length of the superior vertebrae at operation level in the X-ray </p>

<p>18) </p>

<p>and in the pre-operative CT scan or MRI, which demonstrate 
actual length (aAP). These data were used for the calculation of 
actual length of DH (aDH; DH×aAP/AP) and VH (aVH; 
VH×aAP/AP) </p>

<p>11) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Clinical outcomes </p>

<p>Clinical outcomes were evaluated with the neck disability in-
dex (NDI) and the visual analogue scale of the patients' necks 
(VASn) and arms (VASa). These indexes were checked pre-op-</p>

<p>Clarifying the efficacy of Zero-P compared with the stand-
alone cage is important to the practice of spine surgery overall. 
Spine surgeons commonly use the stand-alone cage to avoid the 
discomfort of the anterior plate and autologous bone graft. How-
ever, if the Zero-P shows a superior outcome over the stand-
alone cage and a similar outcome to the anterior plate system, this 
technique could be a good alternative. In this study, we followed 
patients for more than 2 years to compare radiographic and clini-
cal outcomes of the Zero-P and the stand-alone polyetheretherk-
etone (PEEK) cage (Cervios; Synthes GmbH, Oberdorf, Switzerland) 
packed with demineralized bone matrix (DBM; Musculoskeletal 
Transplant Foundation, Edison, NJ, USA). </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>Total 121 patients underwent single-level ACDF for cervical 
disc herniation accompanied by radiculopathy or myelopathy 
between January 2011 and January 2013 in our hospital. Among 
them, we excluded the patients who had any history of 1) previ-
ous cervical spine surgery, 2) other cervical disease including 
ossification of posterior longitudinal ligament, 3) systemic in-
fection or malignancy, and 4) a follow-up period shorter than 2 
years. We finally reviewed 50 patients retrospectively. 
All operations were performed by one neurosurgeon. Twen-
ty-nine of these procedures were performed with the stand-
alone PEEK cage (cage group) packed with DBM, and the other 
21 were performed with Zero-P (Zero-P group), within the same 
period. All patients were performed ACDF under the same op-
eration indication and the device used for the operation was se-
lected randomly. </p>

<p>Operative techniques </p>

<p>A standard anterior Smith-Robinson approach was per-
formed in both groups. The discectomy was performed with pi-
tuitary forceps after confirmation of the surgical level. The mar-
ginal areas of each vertebral body were prepared with a high 
speed drill and curettes. Subsequently, the posterior longitudinal 
ligament was removed, and neural decompression was con-
firmed. A stand-alone PEEK cage packed with DBM was insert-
ed for the cage group, and Zero-P packed with the same DBM 
was inserted for the Zero-P group. Four screws were inserted for 
the Zero-P group under C-arm guidance. Then, the wound was 
closed in a layer-by-layer fashion after drainage insertion. </p>

<p>Radiographic evaluations </p>

<p>All patients were routinely examined with cervical spine plain 
X-ray images with an antero-posterior, lateral, both obliques, and 
excessive flexion and extension series. Additionally, the cases 
included pre-operative computed tomography (CT) or magnet-
ic resonance imaging (MRI). All patients were followed with 
cervical spine plain X-ray images with antero-posterior and lat-
eral views at the outpatient clinic. The follow-up time points </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Simple X-ray lateral view of patient operated with Zero-P an-
chored spacer. Cobb-c indicates the angle (°) between the lower margin 
of C2 and C7 vertebral bodies, Cobb-s indicates the angle (°) between 
upper margin of cranial vertebral body and the lower margin of caudal 
vertebral body of operated level, VH indicates the length (mm) between 
the midline of upper margin of cranial vertebral body and the lower mar-
gin of caudal vertebral body of operated level, DH indicates the length 
(mm) between the midline of upper and lower margin of disc space at 
operated level, and AP indicates the length (mm) of upper margin at the 
cranial vertebral body for operated level. Zero-P : Zero-Profile, VH : ver-
tebral height, DH : disc height, AP : anterior-posterior. </p>



<p>Zero-P versus Stand-Alone Cage | HJ Cho, et al. </p>

<p>eratively and at 24 months post-operatively. The operation time 
and estimated blood loss (EBL) were also checked. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">21.0</rs> statis-
tical software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). The radiological 
and clinical values were expressed as means±standard devia-
tions. The data were analyzed using the Mann-Whitney U test 
for the quantitative data and the chi-squared test for the qualita-
tive data. A p-value&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Demographics </p>

<p>The number of patients in each group was 29 in the cage 
group and 21 in the Zero-P group. The age (p=0.821) and sex 
(p=0.547) were not significantly different between the two 
groups. The surgical level was evaluated as C6-7 or not, with no 
significant difference between the groups (p=0.991) </p>

<p>2,11,24) </p>

<p>. The 
pre-operative Cobb-c and the pre-operative Cobb-s were not 
statistically significant (p=0.242 and p=0.431, respectively). The 
aDH (p=0.929) and aVH (p=0.406) also did not differ signifi-
cantly between groups. The data are shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>Clinical outcomes </p>

<p>Pre-operative NDI, VASn, and VASa showed no significant 
difference between the two groups (p&gt;0.05). These results did 
not change after 24 months (p&gt;0.05). Further, the group differ-
ences between pre-operative and 24 months post-operative 
were estimated, and the results showed no significant difference 
between the two groups (p&gt;0.05). Finally, the average operation 
time (p=0.296) and the EBL (p=0.420) were not significantly 
different between the two groups. Details are shown in Table 2. </p>

<p>Radiographic outcomes </p>

<p>The Cobb-c scores at the immediate post-operative time point </p>

<p>were 12.2±9.1 for the cage group and 12.0±9.1 for the Zero-P 
group (p=0.906). Both groups showed loss of lordosis in the 24 
month follow-up X-ray without significant differences between 
the two groups (p=0.937). The difference between the immedi-
ate post-operative Cobb-c and pre-operative Cobb-c, post-op-
erative 24-month and immediate post-operative, and difference 
cage group and -2.1±2.8 at the Zero-P group (p=0.765). Addi-
tional data are shown in Table 3. 
The Cobb-s immediately after the surgery was 3.7±2.8 for the 
cage group and 2.4±3.4 for the Zero-P group (p=0.221). These 
values worsened gradually, and the 24-month follow-up values 
were 0.2±2.5 and 0.3±3.2, respectively (p=0.812) (Fig. 2). The 
changes in Cobb-s between the immediately post-operative and 
pre-operative time points and between the 24-month post-op-
erative and pre-operative time points were not significantly dif-
ferent between the groups (p&gt;0.05). However, the difference be-
tween the 24-month post-operative and the immediately post-
operative Cobb-s was significantly different between the two 
groups (p=0.027) (Table 4). Comparing the bone fusion rate, 
there were no statistical differences between two groups at any 
periods (p&gt;0.05) (Table 5). 
The aDH was improved immediately after surgery for both </p>

<p>Table 1. Patients' demographics </p>

<p>Cage 
Zero-P 
p-value 
No. 
29 
21 
Sex (m : f) 
19 : 10 
12 : 9 
0.547 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Age (years) 
55.2±10.4 
56.1±12.0 
0.821* 
T-score 
-1.54±1.4 
-1.3±1.5 
0.589* 
Location </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.991 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>C3-4 
3 
3 
C4-5 
7 
3 
C5-6 
9 
6 
C6-7 
10 
9 
Pre-op Cobb-c (°) 
11.2±11.3 
8.85±10.5 
0.242* 
Pre-op Cobb-s (°) 
0.01±3.08 
-0.93±3.85 
0.431* 
Pre-op aDH (mm) 
6.11±1.78 
6.19±1.63 
0.929* 
Pre-op aVH (mm) 
35.4±4.12 
36.4±3.42 
0.406* </p>

<p>*Mann-Whitney U test, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Chi-square test, </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>C6-7 or not. Zero-P : Zero-Profile, aDH : 
actual length of disc height, aVH : actual length of vertebral height </p>

<p>Table 2. Clinical parameters </p>

<p>Cage 
Zero-P 
p-value* 
NDI 
Pre-op 
21.1±6.0 
18.0±4.2 
0.072 
24 mo 
9.6±5.0 
7.9±3.2 
0.320 
Pre-24 mo 
11.4±5.9 
10.1±4.2 
0.574 
VASn 
Pre-op 
5.6±1.4 
5.9±1.6 
0.623 
24 mo 
2.5±1.7 
3.0±1.4 
0.164 
Pre-24 mo 
3.1±2.0 
3.0±1.9 
0.484 
VASa 
Pre-op 
5.6±1.9 
5.3±1.3 
0.653 
24 mo 
2.5±1.5 
2.7±1.3 
0.298 
Pre-24 mo 
3.1±2.1 
2.6±1.8 
0.374 
Operation time (min) 
138.3±37.3 142.5±40.2 
0.296 
Estimated blood loss (mL) 
85±95.7 
88±87.3 
0.420 </p>

<p>dA-B=the difference between the value of A and B. For example, dPre-24 mo 
NDI means the difference between the value of pre-operative and post-operative 
24 month NDI. *Mann-Whitney U test. Zero-P : Zero-Profile, NDI : neck disability 
index, VASn : visual analogue scale of the patients' necks, VASa : visual analogue 
scale of the patients' arms </p>

<p>Table 3. Global Cobb-cervical angle (°) </p>

<p>Cage 
Zero-P 
p-value* 
Pre-op 
11.2±11.3 
8.85±10.5 
0.242 
Post-op </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>12.2±9.1 
12.0±9.1 
0.906 
24 mo 
9.4±10.0 
9.9±8.4 
0.937 
dPost-Pre 
1.0±5.0 
3.2±5.9 
0.169 
d24 mo-Pre 
-1.8±5.3 
1.1±5.0 
0.123 
d24 mo-Post 
-2.8±3.1 
-2.1±2.8 
0.765 </p>

<p>dA-B=the difference between the value of A and B. *Mann-Whitney U test, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Im-
mediate post-op. Zero-P : Zero-Profile </p>



<p>J Korean Neurosurg Soc 58 | August 2015 </p>

<p>groups; 8.1±1.3 in the cage group and 8.3±1.3 in the Zero-P group. 
The post-operative aDH of each group worsened to 6.5±1.5 and 
7.1±1.5 at the 12 month follow-up, respectively (p=0.061). At 
the final follow-up, the two groups showed a significant differ-
ence (5.5±1.3 and 6.8±1.5, respectively, p=0.001), and the cage 
group was even worse than at the pre-operative evaluation. 
Compared to the immediately post-operative examination, 
aDH worsened over time for both groups. At the final follow-
up, the differences between the immediately post-operative fol-
low-up and 24 month post-operative aDH significantly differ-
ent between the two groups, with the Zero-P group showing a 
better result (p=0.002) (Table 6, Fig. 3, 4). 
The aVH measure had a similar tendency to the aDH scores. 
The VH was also improved right after the surgery; 38.4±3.6 in 
the cage group and 39.0±2.7 in the Zero-P group (p=0.442). 
These scores also worsened over time : 35.4±3.8 and 36.8±2.2 at </p>

<p>the 12-month follow-up (p=0.165), respectively, and 34.7±4.3 
and 36.0±2.3 at the 24 month follow-up (p=0.070), respectively. 
The difference between the immediate post-operative time 
point and the later follow-up results revealed a gradual worsen-
ing. Similar to aDH, the gap between the two groups widened 
as time passed, and the results of the last follow-up (the differ-
ence between the immediate post-operative and 24 month 
post-operative follow-ups) showed significant differences be-
tween the two groups, with a better outcome for the Zero-P 
group (p=0.033) (Table 6). </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>mm </p>

<p>aDH </p>

<p>Pre-op Post-op 
3 mo 
6 mo 
12 mo 
24 mo </p>

<p>Cage 
Zero-P </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Serial follow up graph for aDH. The aDH shows immediate im-
proval after surgery but aggravates as follow up. At final follow up, cage 
group showed significantly shorter aDH than Zero-P group (*p=0.001). 
Zero-P : Zero-Profile, aVH : actual length of vertebral height. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>Angle (°) </p>

<p>Cobb-s </p>

<p>*d24 mo-post 
p=0.027 </p>

<p>Pre-op Post-op 3 mo 6 mo 12 mo 24 mo </p>

<p>Cage 
Zero-P </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Serial follow up graph for Cobb-s angle (°). The Cobb-s angle 
shows improvement after immediate post-op and declines as time pass 
for both group. Change after immediate post-op and post-op 24-month 
shows significant difference between two groups (*p=0.027), the Zero-P 
group has lesser decline. Zero-P : Zero-Profile. </p>

<p>Table 4. Change of Cobb-segmental angle between pre-op, post-op, and 
24months </p>

<p>Cage 
Zero-P 
p-value* </p>

<p>dPost-Pre 
3.7±2.9 
3.4±2.5 
0.630 
d24 mo-Pre 
0.2±2.5 
1.2±2.4 
0.174 
d24 mo-Post 
-3.5±2.2 
-2.1±1.4 
0.027 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>dA-B=the difference between the value of A and B. *Mann-Whitney U test, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05. Zero-P : Zero-Profile </p>

<p>Table 6. Change of aDH and aVH between post-op and serial follow-up 
periods </p>

<p>Cage 
Zero-P 
p-value* </p>

<p>aDH </p>

<p>d3 mo-Post 
0.9±0.8 
0.6±0.7 
0.497 </p>

<p>d6 mo-Post 
1.4±1.0 
0.9±1.0 
0.133 </p>

<p>d12 mo-Post 
1.7±1.1 
1.2±1.1 
0.094 </p>

<p>d24 mo-Post 
2.7±1.2 
1.5±1.1 
0.002 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>aVH </p>

<p>d3 mo-Post 
1.6±1.1 
1.4±1.6 
0.656 </p>

<p>d6 mo-Post 
2.3±1.5 
1.8±1.2 
0.273 </p>

<p>d12 mo-Post 
2.9±1.8 
2.2±1.8 
0.063 </p>

<p>d24 mo-Post 
3.6±2.6 
2.9±2.1 
0.033 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>dA-B=the difference between the value of A and B. *Mann-Whitney U test, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05. Zero-P : Zero-Profile, aDH : actual length of disc height, aVH : actual 
length of vertebral height </p>

<p>Table 5. Bone fusion rate of the groups at each follow-up period </p>

<p>Cage (%) 
Zero-P (%) 
p-value* </p>

<p>3 month 
62.1 (18/29) 
61.9 (13/21) 
0.520 
6 month 
72.4 (21/29) 
76.2 (16/21) 
0.273 </p>

<p>12 month 
75.9 (22/29) 
76.2 (16/21) 
0.395 
24 month 
79.7 (23/29) 
80.9 (17/21) 
0.326 </p>

<p>*Mann-Whitney U test, p&lt;0.05. Zero-P : Zero-Profile </p>



<p>Zero-P versus Stand-Alone Cage | HJ Cho, et al. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Cervical degenerative disease is defined as a chronic degen-
erative process of the cervical spine </p>

<p>23) </p>

<p>. The category includes 
clinical syndromes such as radiculopathy or myelopathy, and 
sometimes requires surgical intervention </p>

<p>23) </p>

<p>. ACDF is one of the 
most common surgical interventions performed by neurosur-
geons. Overall complication rates reported for ACDF vary from 
5% to 15% according to published studies </p>

<p>5,13) </p>

<p>. ACDF with autol-
ogous bone graft and anterior plating has been the gold-stan-
dard operation for cervical degenerative spondylosis, including 
herniated nucleus pulposus </p>

<p>12,15,22) </p>

<p>. Because of problems associat-
ed with the operation, such as autologous bone graft subsid-
ence, donor site pain, dysphagia due to anterior plate and screw 
failure, stand-alone cages were developed </p>

<p>2-4,11,27) </p>

<p>. The Cervios 
cage is one of these devices; it is designed to provide a scaffold 
for bony fusion and stability. The apparatus also restores the 
height of the disc space </p>

<p>2,4,6,9,11,27) </p>

<p>. According to recent studies, 
stand-alone cages have shown equally good clinical output as 
the previous method </p>

<p>6,9,19,21) </p>

<p>. 
However, the stand-alone cages have issues of subsidence and 
local kyphosis at the index level </p>

<p>2,6,11) </p>

<p>. The kyphosis at the index 
level may aggravate the degenerative change in adjacent lev-
els </p>

<p>10,11) </p>

<p>. Kim et al. 
11) reported that even though the subsidence 
does not affect short-term outcome, it may be associated with 
the acceleration of the degenerative change. 77% of the patients 
with kyphosis at the fused segment showed a degenerative 
change in a long-term study. To minimize these problems, the 
Zero-P was produced. This method reduces the volume of the 
anterior plate so that it can decrease dysphagia while maintain-
ing the benefits of anterior cervical plating. </p>

<p>In this study, we compared the bone fusion rate of the both 
groups; it was not significantly different between the two groups. 
Then we compared the Cobb's angle of the whole cervical spine 
and the segmental area between the stand-alone cage group and 
the Zero-P group. The initial Cobb-c was not significantly dif-
ferent. The immediately post-operative Cobb-c was improved 
in both groups, showing no significant difference between the 
groups. The lordotic curve of both groups was improved tem-
porarily, but it worsened as time passed. The 24 month post-
operative Cobb-c of the cage group was even worse than the 
pre-operative Cobb-c, while the Zero-P group maintained a 
somewhat improved value compared the pre-operative Cobb-c 
value. However, the two groups were not statistically different. 
When we compared the tendency of the Cobb-s between the 
two groups, it showed similar results to the Cobb-c : lordosis 
was improved temporarily and then gradually worsened. The 
difference between the 24 month post-operative and the imme-
diately post-operative time points were significant, representing 
that the Zero-P group displayed significantly less aggravation of 
the segmental Cobb-s angle than the cage group. In some long-
term studies, degenerative changes of adjacent levels were ob-
served in 77% of the patients with kyphosis </p>

<p>10,11) </p>

<p>. Taking this into 
consideration, the restoration of the lordotic angle may be ben-
eficial to prevent the aggravation of degenerative changes. In 
this aspect, Zero-P seems to better maintain the normal curva-
ture of the cervical spine than the stand-alone cage. 
From these results, we can suppose that if we follow the pa-
tients for a longer time or study a larger population, the global 
lordosis may also show a statistically significant value. As noted 
earlier, the kyphosis of the segmental area affects the degenera-
tive change of the whole cervical spine according to several pre-
vious studies. In our study, even though the Cobb-s showed sta-
tistically similar results in both groups, the groups became more 
different as time passed. Combining these studies, a longer follow-
up time may show a statistically significant result in the Cobb-s 
measure. 
We measured aDH and aVH to evaluate the subsidence rate 
and post-operative spinal alignment for the groups. Both aDH 
and aVH showed similar results; the difference between the 24 
month post-operative and the immediately post-operative ex-
aminations was significantly higher in the cage group. We in-
ferred from these results that the subsidence of the cage group 
was higher than that of the Zero-P group. Although these re-
sults were not directly related to the clinical outcomes, higher 
subsidence could worsen degenerative changes of the cervical 
spine, which might eventually affect cervical spondylotic symp-
toms. 
This study is the first long-term study (more than 2 years) to 
compare the clinical and radiological outcomes of the Zero-P 
and the stand-alone cage. The results were mostly similar to 
those of the previous short-term studies; however, we found 
that longer-follow-up study could reveal more statistically sig-
nificant results. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Serial follow up graph for aVH. The aVH shows improvement after 
operation but declines as time. Though the statistic difference are not 
proved, the gap between two groups get larger as time pass. Zero-P : 
Zero-Profile, aVH : actual length of vertebral height. </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>mm </p>

<p>aVH </p>

<p>Pre-op 
Post-op 
3 mo 
6 mo 
12 mo 
24 mo </p>

<p>Cage 
Zero-P </p>



<p>J Korean Neurosurg Soc 58 | August 2015 </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>For one-level anterior cervical discectomy and fusion surgery, 
the Zero-Profile anchored spacer has advantages for maintain-
ing segmental lordosis and lowering the subsidence rate in long-
term follow-up, compared to the stand-alone PEEK cage. The 
clinical outcomes between the two devices are similar. We sug-
gest the Zero-P anchored spacer as a good substitute for the 
stand-alone cage in one-level anterior cervical discectomy and 
fusion. </p>



</text></tei>