<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4068285" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:46+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>L </p>

<p>isteria monocytogenes (LM) is a bacterial pathogen with 
tropism for human nervous tissue. Listeriosis can be a 
life-threatening disease causing severe meningitis, encephalitis, 
and brain abscess in pregnant women, neonates, elderly, and 
immunocompromised individuals. Some murine models have 
shown that invasion of the central nervous system (CNS) by 
LM is facilitated by infected bone-marrow-derived monocytes 
that adhere to activated brain endothelial cells and accumulate </p>

<p>in brain vessels to invade the brain parenchyma (Join-Lam- bert et al., 2005; Oeverman et al., 2010). 
Several cell types have been identified as potential targets 
of LM in the brain, for example, epithelial cells from choroid 
plexus, ependymal cells, macrophages, microglia, and neurons 
(Schl€ uter et al., 1999). Acute cerebral listeriosis is accompanied 
by hippocampal neuronal apoptosis (Schl€ uter et al., 1998). It 
is known that virulence factors participating in nonlethal 
infection models also contribute to fatal CNS infection </p>

<p>View this article online at wileyonlinelibrary.com. DOI: 10.1002/glia.22602 </p>

<p>Published online December 6, 2013 in Wiley Online Library (wileyonlinelibrary.com). Received Feb 10, 2013, Accepted for publication Nov 5, 2013. </p>

<p>Address correspondence to Carmen Alvarez-Dominguez, Grupo de Gen omica, Prote omica y Vacunas, Instituto de Formaci on e Investigaci on Marqu es de Valdecilla 
(IFIMAV), Avda. Cardenal Herrera Oria, s/n. 39011 Santander, Spain. E-mail: calvarez@humv.es </p>

<p>From the </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Grupo de Gen omica, Prote omica y vacunas, Instituto de Investigaci on y Formaci on Marqu es de Valdecilla (IFIMAV), Primera Planta-Laboratorio 124, 
Avda. de Cardenal Herrera Oria, s/n, 39011, Santander, Spain; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Departamento de Biolog ıa Molecular, Facultad de Medicina, Universidad de Cantabria-IFIMAV, 
39008, Santander, Spain; </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Servicio de Dermatolog ıa, Hospital Universitario Marqu es de Valdecilla, 39008, Santander, Spain. </p>

<p>Elisabet Frande-Cabanes and Lorena Fernandez-Prieto contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the online version of this article. </p>

<p>V C 2013 The Authors Glia Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. 
This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial License, which permits use, distribution and 
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes 
233 </p>

<p>(Schl€ uter et al., 1998, 1999). In this regard, the hly-encoded 
listeriolysin O (LLO) is a pore-forming toxin and the main vir-
ulence factor that allows LM to escape from phagosomes. 
Another virulence factor is the protein encoded by actA gen, 
ActA, a polarized cell-surface protein responsible for LM intra-
cellular motility through interactions with components of the 
actin cytoskeleton and also involved in LM cell-to-cell dissemi-
nation. Finally, two additional virulence factors participate in 
the intracellular stage of LM, plcA, and plcB (Schl€ uter et al.,  1998), two phospholipases C encoded by plcA and plcB genes, 
respectively, that support LLO to dissolve the phagosomes. 
However, the effect of all these LM virulence factors in bacte-
rial proliferation differs among cell types being used. 
Here, we present a new in vitro model for LM infection 
based on mixed cultures of neurons and glia including micro-
glia, the highly specialized brain resident macrophages. In 
response to injury, pathogen invasion, or stressful conditions, 
microglia transform into proliferating cells that migrate and 
behave as macrophages, producing pro-and anti-
inflammatory factors that promote protection and repair 
functions (Greter and Merad, 2013; Hanisch, 2002). How-
ever, microglial activation is also a source of soluble and neu-
rotoxic inflammatory mediators, such as tumor necrosis factor 
(TNF)-a, nitric oxide (NO), or Type I interferons (IFN-ab), 
that cause negative effects on neuronal plasticity, neurogenesis, 
and contribute to neurodegenerative disorders such as Parkin-
son's and Alzheimer's diseases (Block et al., 2007; Burguillos  et al., 2011; Chao et al., 1992; Kaur et al., 2001), disrupting 
the delicate balance in the CNS. It is still unclear how sub-</p>

<p>clinical microbiological infections can also interfere with the 
microglial-neuronal equilibrium and contribute to these neu-
rodegenerative pathologies. 
This study investigated a relevant cell target for LM infec-
tion, microglia, and its putative role in neuronal apoptosis by 
using primary microglia. We also performed phagocytosis assays 
by using the murine microglial cell line BV2 and the murine 
macrophage cell line J774 and four different LM strains: the 
pathogenic LM 
WT and the mutant strains LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>, 
and LM </p>

<p>DplcADplcB </p>

<p>. Our phagocytic functional studies included 
analysis of cell surface markers, transcriptional responses with 
differential displayed microarrays, cytokine measurements, 
microbicidal mechanisms, and protein composition of isolated 
phagosomes or postnuclear supernatants (PNS). </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>We used C57BL/6 mice from our animal facilities at the University 
of Cantabria. Bone marrow-derived macrophages (BMDMs) were 
obtained from femurs of 8-to 12-week-old female mice, cultured, 
and differentiated in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium supple-
mented with 20% fetal calf serum, 1 mM glutamine, 1 mM NEAA, 
25 ng/mL macrophage colony-stimulating factor, 50 mg/mL genta-
micin, and 30 mg/mL vancomycin for 7 days. Newborn C57BL/6 
pups were used to obtain cerebellum for preparation of mixed 
microglia and subsequent isolation of primary microglial cultures. </p>

<p>Mixed Microglial Cell Cultures, Purified Primary 
Microglia, and Cell Lines </p>

<p>Microglial cultures have been described previously (Lopez-Fanarraga  et al., 2007; Ribes et al., 2010; Scheffel et al., 2012). Detailed pro-
cedures for obtaining mixed microglial cell cultures, purified primary 
microglia, the microglial cell line BV2, and the murine macrophage 
cell line J774 are described in Supporting Information. </p>

<p>Bacteria </p>

<p>Prof. D.A. Portnoy (University of California. Berkeley, CA) provided 
L. monocytogenes 10403S pathogenic strain (LM 
WT ) and the mutant </p>

<p>strains LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>, and LM 
DplcADplcB . GFP-LM DH-L1039 </p>

<p>(GFP-LM) derived from the 10403S LM strain was a gift from Prof. 
D.E. Higgins (Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA). </p>

<p>Kinetic Infection Assays </p>

<p>Cell lines, mixed microglial cultures, BMDMs, and purified primary 
microglia were infected as described in Supporting Information and previ-
ously (Carrasco-Marin et al., 2009, 2011). Replication indexes (RIs) were 
calculated as previously reported (Alvarez-Dominguez and Stahl, 1999;  Alvarez-Dominguez et al., 2000; Carrasco-Marin et al., 2009, 2012; Del  Cerro-Vadillo et al., 2006; Prada-Delgado et al., 2001). </p>

<p>Phagosome and Endosome Isolation and Protein 
Composition Analysis </p>

<p>BV2 and J-774 cells were infected with LM strains (LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, 
LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>, or LM 
DplcADplcB mutants) for 20 min (10:1; </p>

<p>Abbreviations </p>

<p>actA 
LM gene coding for ActA, a LM protein responsible for actin 
polymerization 
BMDM 
bone-marrow derived macrophage 
CCL 
chemokine CC ligand 
CFU 
colony forming units 
CNS 
central nervous system 
FITC 
fluorescein isothiocyanate 
HBE 
HEPES buffer with EDTA 
hly 
LM gene coding for listeriolysin O 
H 2 O 2 
hydrogen peroxide 
IFN 
interferon 
IL 
interleukin 
i.p. 
intra-peritoneal 
LLO 
listeriolysin O protein 
LM 
Listeria monocytogenes 
LPS 
lipopolysaccharide 
MCP 
monocyte chemotactic protein 
MHC-II major histocompatibility class II molecules 
NEEA 
nonessential amino acids 
NO 
nitric oxide 
NOD 
nucleotide-binding and oligomerization domain receptor 
PI3K 
phosphatidylinositol 3 kinase 
PE 
phycoerithrin 
PNS 
postnuclear supernatants 
TLR 
Toll-like receptor 
TRITC 
tetramethylrodamine B isothiocyanate </p>

<p>234 
Volume 62, No. 2 </p>

<p>bacteria:cell ratio) and phagosomal fractions were isolated from 
thawed PNSs as previously described (Alvarez-Dominguez et al.,  1999; Carrasco-Marin et al., 2009, 2011, 2012; Del Cerro-Vadillo  et al., 2006; Prada-Delgado et al., 2001). Endosomes form nonin-
fected BV2 and J-774 cells were obtained as described (Del Cerro- Vadillo et al., 2006; Prada-Delgado et al., 2001; Rodriguez-Del Rio  et al., 2011) and detailed in Supporting Information. Endosomal 
fractions were used as control vesicles to standardize basal levels for 
protein composition analysis (CONT) (Rodriguez-Del Rio et al.,  2011). </p>

<p>Comparative Analysis of Phagosomal and Cytosolic 
Bacteria </p>

<p>J-774 and BV2 cells were infected with LM, and phagosomes were 
isolated as described above. Cytosol was prepared (Carrasco-Marin  et al., 2009, 2011) and percentages of phagosomal and cytosolic bac-
teria were calculated as described in Supporting Information. </p>

<p>Fluorescence Label, Confocal Microscopy, and 
Apoptosis </p>

<p>Cells used for immunocytochemistry were fixed in 3% paraformalde-
hyde. Fluorescence labeling, confocal microscopy, and apoptosis 
studies of HN9 neurons were performed as previously described 
(Carrasco-Marin et al., 2011). </p>

<p>Measurement of NO and Hydrogen Peroxide 
(H 2 O 2 ) Production </p>

<p>J-774 cells, BV2 cells, BMDMs, or purified primary microglia were 
infected with LM and assayed for NO production or H 2 O 2 as previ-
ously reported (Alvarez-Dominguez and Stahl, 1999; Alvarez- Dominguez et al., 2000). </p>

<p>Flow Cytometry Analysis </p>

<p>After infection with different LM mutants, proinflammatory cyto-
kine production was measured in cultured supernatants of J-774 
cells, BV2 cells, BMDMs, or purified primary microglia by using a 
CBA proinflammatory kit (BD Life Sciences) (Carrasco-Marin et al.,  2009, 2011; Del Cerro-Vadillo et al., 2006). J-774 cells, BV2 cells, 
BMDMs, or purified primary microglia were incubated in microtiter 
plates at a density of 2 3 10 
6 cells/mL with medium alone or with </p>

<p>medium containing 2 3 10 
7 CFU/mL of LM for 1 h without anti-</p>

<p>biotics, followed by 24 h incubation in complete medium. Cells 
were centrifuged and half of the supernatant volume was harvested 
and stored at -80 
C until fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) </p>

<p>analysis was performed. Samples were analyzed in triplicate and 
results are shown as mean 6 SD of two separate experiments. We 
also used FACS analysis for evaluation of cell surface markers in 
J-774 cells, BV2 cells, BMDMs, or purified primary microglia: 
CD45-fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC), CD14-FITC, F4/80-PE, 
IA 
d -APC (MHC-II in J-774 cells), or IA 
b -APC (MHC-II of in BV2 </p>

<p>cells, BMDMs, and primary microglia), and CD11b-APC. </p>

<p>Transcriptional Expression of Microglial Cells </p>

<p>BV-2 cells were infected with different LM strains and after RNA 
isolation we performed differential microarrays using the Affimetrix 
GeneChip MOE430A2.0 that evaluates 22.626 mouse genes </p>

<p>(Carrasco-Marin et al., 2012). Microarray analyses were deposited in 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">NCBI</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">Gene Expression Omnibus</rs> (Alvarez, 2011) and accessible 
through GEO Series accession number GSE32505 (http:// 
www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE32505). Results of 
the differential microarrays are expressed as signal log ratio (SLR). 
All final values were subtracted from values of basal controls that 
corresponded to noninfected cells (NI) detailed in Supporting Infor-
mation as reported (Carrasco-Marin et al., 2012). </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>For statistical analysis, the Student's t test was applied. P 0.05 was 
considered significant using <rs type="software">GraphPad</rs> for graphic presentation. </p>

<p>Ethics Statement </p>

<p>This study was carried out in strict accordance with the recommen-
dations in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of 
the Spanish Ministry of Science, Research and Innovation. The Ethi-
cal Committee of Animal Experiments of the University of Canta-
bria approved this protocol (Permit Number: 2009/12) that follows 
the Spanish legislation (RD 1201/2005). All surgery was performed 
under sodium pentobarbital anesthesia and all efforts were performed 
to minimize suffering. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>LM Invades Mainly Microglial Cells 
We first investigated two potential cell targets of LM 
WT in </p>

<p>the CNS by establishing an in vitro infection model based on 
primary cultures of murine neurons that contained 95% 
neurons, 2% microglial cells, and some other types of glia 
(Lopez-Fanarraga et al., 2007). This mixed culture system 
allowed us to analyze the interactions between these two cell 
populations. As shown in Fig. 1A,B, LM 
WT (green channel) </p>

<p>effectively infected primary microglia (red channel), but it 
was virtually absent in neurons (blue channel). We also 
observed viable bacteria in the cytosol nucleating actin comet 
tails (Fig. 1A inset). Infected microglia exhibited a highly 
reactive morphology visualized with TRITC-phalloidin that 
stains actin filaments (Fig. 1A) and expressing macrophagic 
markers such as F4/80 (red channel) (Fig. 1B). We found vir-
tually no bacteria outside the microglia (inset in Fig. 1B 
shows a lower magnification image). Therefore, this hippo-
campal mixed culture system strongly suggested that microglia 
were the primary cells for LM 
WT infection because they were </p>

<p>more active capturing bacteria than neurons. Quantification 
of the percentages of infected microglia over 10 different 
experiments performed in triplicate showed that 99% of 
microglia were infected with LM and barely 0.01% neurons 
contained bacteria (Fig. 1A,B). </p>

<p>Microglia Control LM Infection Different from 
Macrophages 
Next, we performed growth kinetic analysis of LM 
WT within </p>

<p>these hippocampal mixed cultures (Mixed-MG in Fig. 1D) </p>

<p>Frande-Cabanes et al.: Microglia, the Innate Immune Cells </p>

<p>February 2014 
235 </p>

<p>and observed a characteristic exponential proliferation of 4 h 
duration that ended in a plateau phase of growth at 16 h post-
infection, similar to LM 
WT kinetics in bone-marrow macro-</p>

<p>phages (BMDMs) (LM 
WT plots in Fig. 1D) (Alvarez-</p>

<p>Dominguez and Stahl, 1999; Carrasco-Marin et al., 2009, 
2011, 2012; Del Cerro-Vadillo et al., 2006; Prada-Delgado 
et al., 2001). We also used different LM mutant strains with </p>

<p>known gene deletions relevant for specific LM intracellular 
stages: hly-deficient (LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>), actA-deficient (LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>), or 
plcA and plcB-deficient mutants (LM </p>

<p>DplcADplcB </p>

<p>) to analyze their 
role in LM growth in microglia. Although LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, 
and LM 
DActA showed characteristic exponential growth, the </p>

<p>LM 
DplcADplcB strain did not replicate in microglial mixed cul-</p>

<p>tures (Fig. 1D). Next, we purified primary microglia from our </p>

<p>FIGURE 1: Listeria monocytogenes invade mainly microglia. (A) Confocal microscopy projection image of mixed microglial cultures infected 
with LM. GFP-LM (green channel) invaded microglial cells showing actin filaments (red channel). Inset represents single confocal Z-plane 
images that showed actin (red channel) encapsulation of GPF-LM in murine microglia. Colocalization of GFP-LM and actin (yellow fluores-
cence) showed actin-comet tails. (B) Confocal microscopy projection image of murine mixed microglial cultures infected with GFP-LM. 
Microglial cells labeled with F4/80 (red channel) were massively infected with GFP-LM (green channel) while surrounding neurons labeled 
with antitubulin b3 antibody (blue channel) did not show intracellular bacteria. Inset corresponds to a lower magnification field. (C) Purified 
primary microglia were isolated from mixed microglial cultures at day 7 by shaking at 200 times/min for 30 min and cells in supernatants 
replated in 24-well with cover-slips for confocal images. Quality of the microglia preparation was observed (lower image) by confocal 
microscopy staining actin filaments with TRITC-phalloidin (red channel) and tubulin (green channel), intracellular colocalization of red and 
green fluorescences is a feature of microglia, while in neurons actin and microtubule filaments do not colocalize. All these microglia prepa-
rations were CD11b </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>F4/80 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>IA </p>

<p>b1 </p>

<p>CD45 
1 with 90% double positive CD11b </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD45 
1 by FACS, reflecting their microglia origin and purity. 
Next, we infected these microglia with GPF-LM 
WT (upper images) for 2 h and stained actin filaments with TRITC-phalloidin and nuclei with 
Hoechst. Bars scale were 10 mm for left upper, 50 mm for right upper, and 25 mm for lower images. Colocalization of GFP-LM 
WT and actin 
(yellow fluorescence) showed actin-comet tails in the cytosol (inset represents an enlarged image of actin-comet tails) (lower right image). 
(D) Kinetic analysis of murine mixed microglial primary cultures, BMDMs, primary purified microglia, BV2 and J-774 cells infected with dif-
ferent LM strains (LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>, or LM </p>

<p>DplcADplcB </p>

<p>). Results are expressed as CFU (mean 6 SD) obtained with triplicate samples 
from three independent experiments (main differences are always observed between LM 
WT and LM 
DLLO and LM 
DplcADplcB results, P &lt; 0.05). 
(E) Primary purified microglia or BMDMs were infected with different LM strains (ratio 10:1 of bacteria: cell) or noninfected (NI) for 2 h, 
detached from plates, washed several times and surface stained with the following FITC or PE-labeled antibodies: CD45-FITC, CD14-FITC, 
F4/80-PE, and anti-IA </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>-APC or anti-IA </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>-APC. Samples were acquired using FACSCanto flow cytometer and percentages of positive cells for 
each antibody are shown. Results are expressed as the mean 6 SD of triplicates (P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>236 
Volume 62, No. 2 </p>

<p>microglial mixed cultures and compared the data with 
BMDMs (Carrasco-Marin et al., 2011, 2013). Quality of the 
microglia preparation was observed by confocal microscopy 
staining of actin filaments with TRITC-phalloidin (red chan-
nel) that colocalize with tubuline (green channel) (lower left 
image in Fig. 1C). Intracellular colocalization of actin and 
tubuline is a feature of microglia, while neurons actin and 
microtubule filaments do not colocalize. Purified primary 
microglia infected with LM 
WT present high numbers of bacte-</p>

<p>ria in the cytosol (upper images in Fig. 1C), nucleate actin fila-
ments (lower right image in Fig. 1C and inset) and show 
robust exponential growth of LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, or LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>strains (Microglia plot in Fig. 1D). All microglia preparations 
were CD11b </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>F4/80 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>IA </p>

<p>b1 </p>

<p>CD45 
1 before LM infection (NI </p>

<p>bars in Fig. 1E) with 90% double positive CD11b </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD45 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>cells by FACS, reflecting their microglia origin and purity 
(Greter and Merad, 2013; Scheffel et al., 2012). Interestingly, 
microglia decreased significantly CD11b 
1 expression after LM </p>

<p>infection and showed no modification on F4/80 and IA </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>markers (MG bars in Fig. 1E). BMDMs preparations were 
CD11b 
1 CD45 
1 and become double positive F4/80 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>IA </p>

<p>b1 </p>

<p>cells only after LM infection (BMDMs bars in Fig. 1E). 
Detailed analysis of phagocytic functions indicated that 
microglia internalized three-fold higher numbers of bacteria 
than BMDMs (Uptake data in Table 1). We also examined the 
intracellular bactericidal capacities of microglia and BMDMs 
(Carrasco-Marin et al., 2009, 2012; Del Cerro-Vadillo et al.,  2006). In BMDMs (Table 1), LM 
WT and LM 
DActA showed </p>

<p>bacterial RI &gt;25, indicating rapid LM proliferation (Alvarez-
Dominguez et al., 2000; Carrasco-Mar ın et al., 2011, 2013). 
BMDMs infected with LM 
DLLO or LM 
DplcADplcB strains </p>

<p>showed RI 1. In microglia, LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, and LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>showed RI &gt;25 and only LM 
DplcADplcB mutants showed RI 5 </p>

<p>1. LM 
DLLO behaved as a virulent strain in microglia, suggesting </p>

<p>that LLO might not be required for phagosomal disruption. 
We observed similar results as above using the microglial 
cell line BV2 (Blasi et al., 1990; Pokock and Liddel, 2001) 
and the macrophage cell line J774 (Carrasco-Marin et al.,  2009, 2011, 2012; Prada-Delagado et al., 2001). BV2 and 
J774 cells were double positive CD11b 
1 CD45 
1 cells and </p>

<p>show same differences in F4/80 and IA </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>/IA 
d markers as micro-</p>

<p>glia and BMDMs (Fig. S1, panel A in Supp. Info.). BV2 cells 
also showed decreased CD11b 
1 expression and no modifica-</p>

<p>tion of F4/80 and IA 
b markers after LM infection. Wild-type </p>

<p>LM and hly-and actA-deficient mutants (LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, 
and LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>, respectively) showed exponential growth in BV2 
cells (BV2 plot in Fig. 1D). However, LM 
DLLO strain showed </p>

<p>no intracellular growth in J774 cells (J774 plot in Fig. 1D) 
(Carrasco-Marin et al., 2009; Join-Lambert et al., 2005). Simi-
larly, uptake of different LM strains in BV2 was three-fold 
higher than in J774 cells. We also observed that in BV2, 
LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, and LM 
DActA showed bacterial RI &gt;25 (Fig. </p>

<p>S1, panel B and C, respectively, in Supp. Info.). Therefore, we 
concluded that LLO and ActA proteins encoded by hly and 
actA genes, were not relevant for LM intracellular growth in all 
sources of microglia, despite being required for LM prolifera-
tion in different macrophages (Carrasco-Marin et al., 2009,  2011, 2012; Del Cerro-Vadillo et al., 2006; Join-Lambert  et al., 2005). All together, these data suggested that microglia 
had a lower bactericidal potential than macrophages. 
We next examined the intracellular distribution of LM in 
BV2 cells by using a technique, described in J774 cells, that 
quantified viable bacteria in isolated phagosomal and cytosolic 
fractions (Alvarez-Dominguez et al., 1999; Carrasco-Marin  et al., 2009, 2011, 2012). LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, and LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>mutants in BV2 cells showed a dominant cytosolic localization </p>

<p>TABLE 1: Phagocytic Functions of Microglia and Macrophages </p>

<p>Uptake </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Replication indexes </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Bacteria </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Microglia 
BMDM 
Microglia 
BMDM 
LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>18130 6 359 
6020 6 113 
80 6 6 
4 8 6 6 </p>

<p>LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>18100 6 521 
6038 6 151 
32 6 4 
0.1 6 0.05 </p>

<p>LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>18230 6 389 
6025 6 132 
38 6 6 
3 0 6 2 </p>

<p>LM </p>

<p>DplcADplcB </p>

<p>18175 6 428 
6090 6 144 
1 6 0.04 
0.5 6 0.5 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Different LM strains were used for infection of microglia and BMDM as described in Methods. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Cells were infected with [ 
35 S]-labeled LM strains for 45 min. Cells were washed and radioactivity associated with cell lysates (CPM) was 
quantified in a b2counter as the amount of bacterial uptake by microglia. Results are expressed as cpm of internalized bacteria (mean 6 
SD) (mean differences are observed between BMDM and microglia results, P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>RIs were calculated as the ratio of the number of CFU at 16 h divided by the amount of CFU at 0 h. This parameter was considered as 
an indicator of bacterial growth. Results are expressed as CFU (mean 6 SD) (main differences are always observed between LM 
WT and 
LM 
DLLO and LM 
DplcADplcB results, P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Frande-Cabanes et al.: Microglia, the Innate Immune Cells </p>

<p>February 2014 </p>

<p>
with only 20-38% of bacteria in phagosomes (Table 2), 
whereas the LM 
DplcADplcB mutant showed a dominant phagoso-</p>

<p>mal distribution. We also confirmed the intracellular distribu-
tion of the different LM strains (Supp. Info. Fig. S2) and the 
colocalization of actin filaments with cytosolic LM using con-
focal microscopy (Arrows in Fig. S3 of Supp. Info.). </p>

<p>LM actA Gene Regulates TNF-Induced Immune 
Gene Expression in Microglia that Transforms 
Phagosomes into Deficient Innate Immune 
Platforms 
Only cytosolic LM induces innate immune transcriptional 
responses in macrophages (Carrasco-Marin et al., 2011; 
Herskovits et al., 2007; Leber et al., 2008; MacCaffrey et al.,  2004). Here, we analyzed the differential expression of genes 
included on the Affimetrix GeneChip MOE430A2.0 in BV2 
cells after infection with cytosolic LM strains (pathogenic 
LM 
WT as well as the attenuated LM 
DLLO and LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>) as 
compared with basal levels of noninfected cells. We used BV2 
cells using a previously reported strategy for J774 cells 
infected with LM that combines transcriptional analysis and 
protein composition of the phagosomal platform (Carrasco- Marin et al., 2012). We analyzed the transcriptional data 
using an approach focused on functional clusters involved in 
macrophages innate immunity (Fig. 2A) (Carrasco-Marin  et al., 2012; Herskovits et al., 2007; Leber et al., 2008;  McCaffrey et al., 2004) (the complete bioinformatics 
approach is described in Fig. S4, panels A and B of Supp. 
Info.). Our approach selected the 20 highest differentially 
expressed genes in microglia, sorting them in two transcrip-
tional patterns: a pattern common to macrophages and a pat-
tern specific for microglial immune response (Fig. 2A and 
Supp. Info. Table S1). The gene expression pattern shared by 
macrophages involved Toll-like receptor (TLR), TNF, phos-</p>

<p>phoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K), and nuclear factor (NF)-jB sig-
naling routes (Carrasco-Marin et al., 2012; Herskovits et al.,  2007; Leber et al., 2008; McCaffrey et al., 2004; Scheffel  et al., 2012). The actA gene of LM appeared to induce the 
expression of chemokines/cytokines genes cxcl2, ccl4, and tnf-
a, the transcriptional factor NfkB, and the TLR-associated 
gene cd14 (Fig. 2A). The hly gene of LM might be important 
for a minimal part of this signaling route involving the pi3k 
catalytic polypeptide gene (Figs. 2A and S4, Panel C in Supp. 
Info.). Microglia-specific repression included trafficking regu-
latory genes of phagosomes (Carrasco-Marin et al., 2012), a 
lysosomal-autophagy gene and IFN-responsive genes. The 
actA gene of LM was involved in repression of trafficking reg-
ulatory genes of phagosomes as rab14, lysosomal components 
as smpd1, vps16, scarb2, and rilp12 (Carrasco-Marin et al., 
2012) and the lysosomal-autophagy gene, atg4b (Supp. Info. 
Table S1). While the hly gene of LM might be involved in 
repression of the IFN-responsive genes, the chemokine ccl5, 
the kinase associated with IFN receptors jak1 and upregula-
tion of the IFN signaling repressor, socs3 gene. We confirmed 
most of these transcriptional results by performing a detailed 
protein composition analysis on highly purified LM phago-
somes isolated from microglia and based on the signaling 
components that were highlighted in the transcriptional 
response (Fig. 2C). We used the innate immune LM phago-
somal platforms recently reported for J774 cells as templates 
and as protein basal controls, endosomes from noninfected 
BV2 and J774 cells (CONT lanes in Fig. 2C) (Carrasco- Marin et al., 2012). We included RNA contamination con-
trols that might influence signaling inside the phagosomes 
and an internal protein loading control in all our phagosomal 
preparations to verify the quality of microglial phagosomes. 
Quality of purified microglial phagosomes was as follows: 
protein yields of 1 mg/mL from 1 3 10 
9 starting cells </p>

<p>TABLE 2: Subcellular Compartments for Pathogenic and Mutants Strains of LM in BV2 and J-774 cells </p>

<p>Phagosomal (%) 
Cytosolic (%) </p>

<p>Bacteria </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>BV2-microglia 
J-774-MØ 
BV2-microglia 
J-774-MØ </p>

<p>LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>20 6 1 
3 0 6 3 
8 0 6 6 
7 0 6 6 </p>

<p>LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>38 6 5 
100 6 5 
6 2 6 4 
0 6 0.5 </p>

<p>LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>20 6 3 
3 0 6 3 
8 0 6 6 
7 0 6 2 </p>

<p>LM </p>

<p>DplcADplcB </p>

<p>90 6 4 
7 5 6 4 
1 0 6 4 
2 5 6 0.5 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>BV2 and J-774 cells were infected for 2 h with pathogenic LM 
WT and LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, LM 
DActA or LM 
DplcADplcB at a 10:1 (cell:bacteria) ratio. 
Phagosomal and cytsolic fractions were purified from PNS (30 mg), and solubilized. Viable LM was quantified (CFU) to calculate the 
percentages of phagosomal and cytosolic bacteria. Results are expressed as percentages of total internalized CFU in PNS (mean 6 SD). 
CFU values for PNS at 0 h were in J-774: 6.5 6 0.03 for LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, 32.5 6 0.1 for LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, 63.7 6 0.01 for LM 
DActA and 7.0 6 0.03 for 
LM 
DplcADplcB . CFU values for PNS at 0 h were in BV2: 6.5 6 0.03 for LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, 32.5 6 0.1 for LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, 63.7 6 0.01 for LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>, and 
7.0 6 0.03 for LM 
DplcADplcB . </p>

<p>238 
Volume 62, No. 2 </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: LM actA gene regulates TNF-mediated immune gene expression in microglia, which transforms phagosomes into deficient 
innate immune platforms. (A) Noninfected (NT) or LM-infected (LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, or LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>) BV2 cells were used for RNA isolation and dif-
ferential microarrays. Heat Map presentation of the 20 highest differentially expressed genes representing the LM innate immunity clus-
ter (see Supp. Info. Fig. S3). Colored rows represent expression ratios from £ -1.2-fold-change (FC)-repressed genes shown in green to 
1.2 FC-induced genes shown in red. Black boxes correspond to nondifferentially-expressed genes. (B) Examination of RNA quality in 
phagosomal preparations. By using 1% agarose gel, RNA major bands, a small 2 kb and a large 5 kb band, and no fragmented RNA 
were visualized. In PNSs we observed rRNA (lanes 1, 3, 5, and 7), although no detectable rRNA was observed in phagosomes (lanes 2, 
4, 6, and 8). J-774 and BV2 phagosomes usually contain yields of proteins ranging from 1 mg/mL and 1-3% of RNA contamination. 
(C) Protein and functional analysis of phagosomes and endosomes as basal controls. Western blots of 30 mg per lane of J-774 or BV2 
isolated phagosomes containing LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>, or LM 
DplcADplcB or endosomes from noninfected J-774 or BV2 (CONT lanes) 
showed different relevant proteins, TLR-2, Pi3kp110, NFkB, Jak1, Socs3, Arf-1, Arf-6, and Rab5a, as well as lysosomal markers, Scarb2, 
and Smpd1. Rab5c was selected as an internal control marker because it showed no variation in J-774 phagosomes and it is also found 
in endosomes. CFU numbers under western-blot lanes reflected the amount of live bacteria within the phagosomes. [Color figure can be 
viewed in the online issue, which is available at wileyonlinelibrary.com.] </p>



<p>February 2014 </p>

<p>
similar to standard phagosomal purifications in macrophages 
(Alvarez-Dominguez and Stahl, 1999; Carrasco-Marin et al.,  2009, 2011, 2012; Del Cerro-Vadillo et al., 2006; Prada- Delgado et al., 2001), and similar levels of the internal load-
ing control Rab5c (Fig. 2C) (Carrasco-Marin et al., 2012). 
RNA ranges were lower than those reported in macrophages 
(Carrasco-Marin et al., 2012) with 1-2% RNA contamina-
tion (Supp. Info. Table S2) and a lack of the two rRNA 
forms, the small 2 kb and large 5 kb bands as compared 
with nonpurified fractions (Fig. 2B). Next, we verified TLR 
signaling by studying TLR2 protein levels because LM signals 
through this TLR (Herskovits et al., 2007; Leber et al., 2008;  McCaffrey et al., 2004). We observed similar TLR2 levels in 
microglia and macrophage phagosomes containing the differ-
ent LM strains, while TLR2 was not detected in endosomes 
as expected (Fig. 2C). CD14 surface expression in microglia 
and macrophages infected with LM 
WT or LM mutants was </p>

<p>also comparable (Figs. 1E and S1, panel A in Supp. Info.). 
We next analyzed PI3K signaling upon protein expression of 
its p110 catalytic subunit and two components of this path-
way: Rab5a that acts upstream and activates the phagosomal 
oxidase (Carrasco-Marin et al., 2011, 2012; Prada-Delgado  et al., 2001), and Arf-1 that acts downstream in the phago-
cytic cups (Beemiller et al., 2006). LM blocked PI3K signal-
ing in microglia, which involved the LM hly gene (Supp. 
Info. Fig. S4C). However, LM did not inhibit PI3K but acti-
vated this kinase signaling in macrophages (Carrasco-Marin  et al., 2012; Herskovits et al., 2007; Leber et al., 2008; Mac- Caffrey et al., 2004). Accordingly, microglial phagosomes 
containing LM 
WT and LM 
DActA showed low levels of PI3K </p>

<p>p110 catalytic subunit, Arf-1, and lower levels of Rab5a than 
macrophage phagosomes (Fig. 2C). In contrast, microglial 
phagosomes containing LM 
DLLO presented high levels of </p>

<p>PI3K p110 and Arf-1 and normal levels of Rab5a. We con-
cluded that microglial phagosomes loaded with LM 
WT and </p>

<p>LM 
DActA strains contained an inactivated PI3K pathway with </p>

<p>LM hly gene being involved in PI3K inactivation. LM acti-
vates NFkB signaling, which in microglia involved LM actA 
gene. Accordingly, microglia phagosomes containing LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>strains showed no detectable NFkB levels (NFkB lane in Fig. 
2C). We also examined the IFN receptor associated kinase 
Jak1 and the IFN repressor Socs3. Similar to the IFN tran-
scriptional response in macrophages, LM phagosomes show 
high levels of Jak1 and very low levels of Socs3 (Jak1 and 
Socs3 lanes in Fig. 2C). LM inactivates IFN transcriptional 
routes in microglia, which involved LM hly gen. Conse-
quently, phagosomes of BV2 cells containing LM 
WT and </p>

<p>LM 
DLLO strains, showed low or undetectable levels of Jak1 </p>

<p>and very high levels of Socs3. Next, we analyzed the lysoso-
mal components repressed in microglia by LM actA gene. 
Similar to the transcriptional response analysis, we observed </p>

<p>low levels of two lysosomal components involved in LM 
innate immunity, Scarb2, and Smpd1 (Fig. 2C) (Carrasco- Marin et al., 2011; Schramm et al., 2008; Uterm€ ohler et al.,  2003). Other phagosomal trafficking components such as 
Arf-6, the PLD-activator, showed normal levels in LM phago-
somes from microglia and macrophages (Fig. 2C). Endosomal 
protein composition validated our analysis since endosomes 
only contain detectable levels of the trafficking components 
Rab5a, Rab5c, Pi3Kp110, Arf-6, or Arf-1, as expected. We 
also verified this complete protein analysis using PNS from 
purified microglia (data not shown) and obtained same results 
as with phagosomes of BV2 cells (Fig. 2C). Phagosome com-
position suggested that LM phagosomes in microglia might 
not be considered innate immune platforms controlling bacte-
rial viability as in macrophages (Carrasco-Marin et al., 2012). 
In fact, CFU count inside LM phagosomes from microglia 
was higher than that observed in LM phagosomes from mac-
rophages (CFU percentages under protein lanes in Fig. 2C). </p>

<p>LM Infection of Microglial Cells Dissociates TNF 
from IFN Function 
Two innate immune signals control LM infection, TNF-
mediated genes, and IFN-regulated genes (Carrasco-Marin  et al., 2012; Herskovits et al., 2007; Leber et al., 2008;  McCaffrey et al., 2004). First, we observed that after LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>infection, purified primary microglia produced 10-fold higher 
levels of TNF and 3.5-fold higher levels of the TNF-
regulated chemokine CC ligand (CCL)2/monocyte chemotac-
tic protein (MCP)-1 than BMDMs did (Fig. 3A,B). Infection 
with LM 
DActA induced production of basal levels of both </p>

<p>cytokines/chemokines in microglia as compared with normal 
levels in macrophages. Therefore, LM actA gene might be 
involved in TNF production in microglia. Other proinflam-
matory cytokines such as interleukin (IL)-6 or IL-12 were 
produced at similar levels in microglia and macrophages 
infected with LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, or LM 
DActA strains. IFN-ab </p>

<p>production was undetectable in microglia infected with path-
ogenic LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, or LM 
DActA and at least 100-times </p>

<p>lower than in BMDMs. Interestingly, LPS induced similar 
levels of this cytokine in microglia and BMDMs (white bars 
in Fig. 3A,B) (Hanisch, 2002; Ribes et al., 2013; Scheffel  et al., 2012). Similar results were observed using BV2 and 
J774 cells (Supp. Info. Table S3). 
In macrophages, IFN-mediated genes regulate NO and 
H 2 O 2 production, while TNF signaling controls only NO 
release (Carrasco-Mar ın et al., 2012; Cohen et al., 2000; Jun  et al., 1993; MacMicking et al., 1997; Prada-Delgado et al.,  2001). NO and H 2 O 2 are the main microbicidal mechanisms 
acting in macrophages (Alvarez-Dominguez et al., 2000; Mac- Micking et al., 1997) and in microglia (Block et al., 2007;  Burguillos et al., 2011; Chao et al., 1992; Ribes et al., 2010;   240  Volume 62, No. 2 </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: Purified primary microglia produces low neurotoxic and microbicidal compounds and limit neuronal apoptosis. (A) Purified primary 
microglia and (B) bone-marrow derived macrophages (BMDM) were infected with different mutants or pathogenic LM strains at a ratio of 10: 
(bacteria: cells). We also included samples incubated with LPS (10 ng/mL). Culture supernatants were collected after 24 h infection in medium 
containing 50 mg/mL gentamicin to kill extracellular bacteria. Supernatants were filtered before storage at -80 
C. Levels of proinflammatory 
cytokines (MCP-1, TNF-a, IFN-ab, IL-6, and IL-12) were analyzed by using the CBA kit (Becton Dickinson) and flow cytometry. Results were 
expressed as cytokine concentration (pg/mL of mean 6 SD, P &lt; 0.05). (C) NO production of BMDMs (black bars) and purified primary micro-
glia (white bars) infected with LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, or LM 
DActA measured in cell supernatants. Results are expressed as nmol of NO produced by 
10 
5 cells (mean 6 SD, P &lt; 0.05) obtained with triplicate samples (main differences are always observed between LM 
WT and LM 
DLLO results). 
(D) H 2 O 2 production in BMDMs (black bars) and purified primary microglia (white bars) infected with LM </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>, LM </p>

<p>DLLO </p>

<p>, or LM </p>

<p>DActA </p>

<p>. Results are 
expressed as nmol of H 2 O 2 produced per cell (mean 6 SD, P &lt; 0.05). (E) Diagram of the experiment using purified primary microglia (MG) 
and isolated neurons. Purified primary microglia (MG) were infected with different LM strains for 1 h followed by overnight incubation with 
complete medium with gentamicin to kill extracellular bacteria. Supernatants were collected and filtered by 0.22 mm filters. (F) Isolated neu-
rons were cultured together with a 1/10 dilution of these supernatants for 16 h. In figure, plots of apoptotic neurons are shown after staining 
and counting using an optical microscope. 50 fields were examined per condition. Results are expressed as percentages (mean 6 SD) (mean 
6 SD, P &lt; 0.05) obtained with triplicate samples. [Color figure can be viewed in the online issue, which is available at wileyonlinelibrary.com.] </p>

<p>Schl€ uter et al., 1999), therefore, we compared the production 
of these toxic compounds in both cell types. Primary purified 
microglia infected with LM 
WT produced lower NO levels </p>

<p>than BMDMs did (P &lt; 0.05), while infection of microglia 
with LM 
DLLO or LM 
DActA caused even lower levels (P &lt; </p>

<p>0.05) (Fig. 3C). Conversely, BMDMs infected with LM 
WT or </p>

<p>LM 
DActA caused high production of NO, and only the </p>

<p>LM 
DLLO strain produced low levels of NO as expected (Bol-  drick et al., 2001; Cohen et al., 2000; Corr and O'Neil,  2010; Jun et al., 1993; MacMicking et al., 1991; Myers  et al., 2003) (Fig. 3C). Moreover, H 2 O 2 was undetectable in 
microglia infected with LM, while macrophages showed high 
levels after infection with LM mutants (Fig. 3D). Addition of 
a TLR4 ligand such as lipopolysaccharide (LPS) induced high 
levels of NO and H 2 O 2 in microglia and BMDMs (LPS bars 
in Fig. 3C,D) (Ribes et al., 2013; Scheffel et al., 2012). BV2 
and J774 cells showed similar results (Fig. S5 panel A and B  in Supp. Info.). We concluded that TNF and IFN signaling 
routes regulating NO and H 2 O 2 production were dissociated 
in microglia infected with LM, although not in resting micro-
glia (Hanisch, 2002). However, it is also possible that phago-
somes from microglia were not equipped for H 2 O 2 
production. 
In macrophages, expression of MHC-II, F4/80 and 
CD11b molecules is linked and modulated by IFN genes 
upon LM infection (Carrasco-Marin et al., 2012; Herskovits  et al., 2007; Leber et al., 2008; MacCaffrey et al., 2004). 
Therefore, dissociation of TNF and IFN mediated responses 
in microglia such as production of cytokines, NO and H 2 O 2 
might also correlate with the decrease in the expression of 
CD11b integrin and the lack of modification in F4/80 and 
MHC-II levels after LM infection (Figs. 1E and S1, panel A  in Supp. Info.). These data also correlates with the induction 
of a particular subset of microglia after LM infection as 
reported for TLR-4 activation (Scheffel et al., 2012). </p>

<p>LM-Infected Microglia Avoid Generalized 
Neuronal Damage 
We tested the hypothesis that the microglial strategy after LM 
infection was focused on reducing neuronal damage. We 
examined neuronal apoptosis mediated by the products 
released by microglia infected with LM but without direct 
contact of neurons with pathogenic LM (Fig. 3E,F). We 
infected primary purified microglia with pathogenic or LM 
mutants and collected and filtered the supernatants to elimi-
nate bacteria (Lopez-Fanarraga et al., 2007). Isolated hippo-
campal neurons were coincubated with a 1/10 dilution of 2 h 
supernatants for 16 h. We measured nuclear fragmentation as 
the percentage of apoptotic cells by using either confocal 
microscopy (Fig. 3E,F) or apoptosis of murine HN9 neurons 
using FACS analysis with DAPI (Fig. S5, panel D in Supp. </p>

<p>Info.). We included two negative controls consisting of cul-
ture medium alone (medium bars in Fig. 3F) and cell media 
with noninfected microglia or BMDMs (NI bars in Fig. 3F). 
We observed a three-fold increase in apoptosis of primary 
neurons after incubation with the filtered supernatant of 
microglia infected with pathogenic LM 
WT (white bars in Fig. </p>

<p>3F). These apoptotic levels were reverted to basal levels with 
an anti-TNF antibody and with the supernatant of microglia 
infected with LM 
DActA strain that was unresponsive to TNF </p>

<p>antibody (anti-TNF/LMDActA bars in Fig. 3F). However, 
neuronal apoptosis increased up to 45-47% after using 
supernatants of microglia incubated with IFN-c or with LPS 
(IFN-g and LPS bars in Fig. 3F). Supernatants from BMDMs 
infected with LM (black bars in Fig. 3F) showed higher apo-
ptosis (26-38%) than microglia infected with LM (17%). We 
observed similar results using BV2 and J774 cells (Fig. S5,  panel C and D in Supp. Info.). 
In summary, these results strongly indicated that the 
high levels of TNF induced in microglial after LM infection 
were regulated by the LM actA gene and appeared to cause 
only limited neuronal apoptosis as compared with the apo-
ptosis induced by other stimuli such as LPS or IFN-c. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Microglia are important in cerebral listeriosis to avoid patho-
gen dissemination into the CNS and preserve brain homeo-
stasis (Dramsi et al., 1998; Drevets et al., 2008; Schl€ uter  et al., 1998, 1999; Sonje et al., 2010; Virna et al., 2006). An 
excessive inflammatory reaction upon bacterial infection 
might cause bystander damage, therefore, microglia might 
count with especial regulatory mechanisms, which may not 
be necessarily identical to those triggered in innate immune 
cells such as macrophages (Herskovits et al., 2007; Leber  et al., 2008; MacCaffrey et al., 2004). 
The present study shows that microglia are relevant target 
cells for LM in the CNS, and that microglia and macrophages 
control LM infection differently. Our analysis of the transcrip-
tional response induced by LM indicated that microglial cells 
triggered a limited innate immune response dominated by two 
transcriptional programmes. The first expression programme is 
common to macrophages and microglia and involves TLR, 
TNF, PI3K, and NF-jB signaling pathways. LM actA gene 
seems to be involved in gene induction of the TLR2-associated 
molecule involved in LM adhesion cd14 (Corr and O'Neil,  2010; Herskovits et al., 2007; Leber et al., 2008; MacCaffrey  et al., 2004), NfjB, tnf-a and the chemokines/cytokines genes 
cxcl2 and ccl4, which are involved in recruiting monocytes. 
However, we observed similar phagosomal TLR2 levels and 
CD14 surface expression in microglia and macrophages 
infected with LM. LM also activates NFkB signaling and bac-
terial actA gene seems to control phagosomal NFkB levels in </p>

<p>242  Volume 62, No. 2 </p>

<p>microglia. We concluded that bacterial receptor expression or 
initial steps on phagosomal signaling did not explain the differ-
ences between microglia and macrophages. 
Measurements of cytokines/chemokines indicated that 
actA gene of LM was responsible for an overproduction of 
TNF-a and MCP-1/CCL2 in LM-infected microglia. This 
high production of TNF-a and MCP-1 might recruit other 
monocytes to the infection site and control pathogen propa-
gation to other cells. These results are in accordance with LM 
infection of hippocampal mixed cultures, which show bacte-
rial growth only in microglia. Down regulation of migratory 
markers such as CD11b in microglia infected with LM might 
also avoid this pathogen dissemination. 
The hly gene of LM controls part of this early response 
repressing pi3kcg, the catalytic polypeptide gene of PI3K 
kinase. Consequently, microglial LM phagosomes are defi-
cient in oxidative microbicidal components regulated by 
PI3K signaling such as PI3K p110, Rab5a, and Arf-1, which </p>

<p>might down-regulate the phagosomal oxidase and explain the 
low levels of microbicidal H 2 O 2 that microglia produced 
after LM infection (Beemiller et al., 2006; Cohen et al.,  2000; Jun et al., 1993; Prada-Delgado et al., 2001). The 
functional analysis indicated that microglia had higher bacte-
rial phagocytic rates but a lower microbicidal potential as 
compared with macrophages. In fact, LM phagosomes in 
microglia show much higher CFU values than macrophages 
suggesting a defective compartment for degradation of 
bacteria. 
This inducible expression programme highlighted two 
relevant functions of these cells, recruitment of other phago-
cytes, and activation of innate immune responses to combat 
intracellular pathogens (Herskovits et al., 2007; Leber et al.,  2008; McCaffrey et al., 2004). In contrast, this transcriptional 
early response in macrophages is induced by phagosome-
degraded bacteria and controlled by LM hly gene and not by 
actA gene (Herskovits et al., 2007; Leber et al., 2008). </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: Hypothetical model of LM infection in microglia. Pathogenic LM seems to induce in microglia the dissociation of a transcrip-
tional response dominated by innate immunity using three events regulated by the actA gene and partially by the hly gene: (i) the actA 
gene appears relevant for the induction of early innate responses compiled in three signaling pathways: TLR, TNF, and NF-jB. After bac-
teria bound to TLR2, induction of mitogen-activated kinase and PI3K seemed to occur with participation of CD14. Subsequent activation 
of the NF-jB might induce high levels of TNF-a (GOOD TNF-a production in the model) and MCP-1, and CXCL2 and CCL4 chemokines 
that recruited other monocytes (1 routes). (ii) The actA gene also repressed a degradation cluster belonging to late innate responses 
and characterized by lysosomal genes smpd1 and scarb2 (-routes). (iii) The hly gene seemed to repress the IFN-responsive gene cluster 
belonging to late innate responses involving high induction of repressor Socs3 (1 arrow) that blocked the IFN pathway and repressed 
Jak1, the kinase associated with IFN receptor (-routes). Therefore, production of type I IFNs (i.e., IFN-ab: and NO was decreased (BAD 
IFN-ab and NO production in the model) because activation of the iNOS genes appeared compromised. The hly gene seemed also 
important for inhibition of the pi3kcg gene that might avoid activation of the phagosomal oxidase (known as phox) and block H 2 O 2 pro-
duction. [Color figure can be viewed in the online issue, which is available at wileyonlinelibrary.com.] </p>

<p>Frande-Cabanes et al.: Microglia, the Innate Immune Cells </p>

<p>February 2014 
243 </p>

<p>The second gene expression programme is specific for 
microglia and involves the repression of late innate immune 
genes classified according to the literature in two functional 
clusters highly induced in macrophages (Carrasco-Marin et al., 
2012; Herskovits et al., 2007; Leber et al., 2008). The first is a 
degradation cluster mainly characterized by lysosomal traffick-
ing genes and autophagy. The second is a listericidal cluster 
characterized by IFN-responsive genes involved in production 
of type I IFN, H 2 O 2 , and NO (Carrasco-Marin et al., 2012; 
MacMicking et al., 1997; Myers et al., 2003; Jun et al., 1993). 
LM actA gene seems to be important in the inhibition of the 
degradation cluster genes participating in organelle fusion, such 
as syntaxin-3 and syntaxin-8; the specific autophagy gene 
atg4b, which might participate in LM cytosolic degradation 
(Mostowy et al., 2011; Yin et al., 2009), the lysosomal genes 
vps16, lamp-1, and rilp2 and specially repression of two lysoso-
mal genes involved in LM innate immunity, scarb2 (Carrasco-
Marin et al., 2011) and smpd1 (Del Cerro-Vadillo et al., 2006; 
Schramm et al., 2008; Uterm€ ohlen et al., 2003). Therefore, it 
seems that LM actA gene is mandatory in microglia to avoid 
phagosomal and cytosolic degradation of LM, control late 
fusion events as well as to up-regulate TNF production (Dre-
vets et al., 2008). We verified that phagosome fusion with late 
compartments was impaired in microglia but not in macro-
phages (data not shown). We also confirmed that microglia 
phagosomes lacked the nonoxidative listericidal components 
Scarb2 and Smpd1, which are involved in confining LM 
within the phagosomes (Carrasco-Mar ın et al., 2011; Schramm 
et al., 2008; Uterm€ ohlen et al., 2003). Moreover, cytosolic 
destruction of LM seems to be also partially blocked in micro-
glia, showing a high number of cytosolic bacteria that escaped 
from phagosomes. 
The LM hly gene appeared to be relevant for the micro-
glial specific expression programme that represses IFN-
responsive genes cluster and avoids amplification of the LM 
proinflammatory immune response. In fact, IFN-ab produc-
tion is very low in microglia infected with LM. Induction of 
socs3 gene in microglia blocked the activation of late immune 
responses because it is an inhibitor of Type I IFN production 
(Jun et al., 1993; Herskovits et al., 2007; Leber et al., 2008; 
MacMicking et al., 1997; McCaffrey et al., 2004; Myers 
et al., 2003; Uterm€ ohlen et al., 2003). This expression pro-
gramme also represses jak1 gene, the kinase associated with 
IFN receptors. In fact, LM microglial phagosomes showed an 
inactive IFN pathway since they lack Jak1 and contain high 
levels of Socs3. These entire genes act as feedback mecha-
nisms to increase the microbicidal machinery of macrophages 
(Dedoni et al., 2010; Herskovits et al., 2007; Leber et al., 
2008; McCaffrey et al., 2004), thus, their repression in 
microglia after LM infection seemed to favor low levels of 
toxic H 2 O 2 . IFN signaling also controls the production of </p>

<p>NO in macrophages. Microglia infected with LM released 
low levels of NO that might not be sufficient to eliminate all 
cytosolic bacteria. In summary, microglia have poor microbi-
cidal compartments such as phagosomes and cytosol, there-
fore, it might be difficult for them to generate bacterial 
ligands for NOD receptors and induce a powerful inflamma-
tory respons(Herskovits et al., 2007; Leber et al., 2008). 
This entire transcriptional programme induced by LM 
infection in microglia seems to dissociate TNF-from IFN-
mediated responses (Fig. 4). Cytokine measurements con-
firmed this hypothesis with an overproduction of TNF-a and 
MCP-1/CCL2 in LM-infected microglia, but reduced pro-
duction of Type I IFNs and bactericidal compounds such as 
H 2 O 2 and NO. This dissociation also aims to limit neuronal 
damage up to a maximum of 17%, because LPS or IFN-c 
signals that do not cause this dissociation are more neuro-
toxic. LM actA gene controlled this limited neuronal apopto-
sis that seems attributed only to microglia TNF-a 
production. The lack of production of Type I IFNs also lim-
its the acute inflammatory response not recruiting other leu-
kocytes and reduces brain damage (Dedoni et al., 2010; 
Sonje et al., 2010; Virna et al., 2006; Yin et al., 2009). Our 
results are contradictory to those reported with a strain of Lis-
teria, not previously reported or deposited in data banks, that 
uses a nervous system model of mixed rat neuronal cultures 
(Remuzgo-Martinez et al., 2013). Cytokines and gene expres-
sion patterns reported by these authors cannot be assigned to 
microglia since they do not use purified microglia or micro-
glial homogeneous cell lines. The dissociation of LM innate 
immune responses in microglia that we report in this study 
seems to correlate with the heterogenicity of microglia 
responses since LM infection might select a specific microglia 
population (Scheffel et al., 2012). Moreover, this microglia 
strategy after infection with LM seems to preserve the 
delicate brain balance and highlights the role of microglia in 
preventing microbiological infections that might exacerbate 
neurodegenerative processes (Dedoni et al., 2010; Dramsi 
et al., 1998). </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>Grant sponsor: Spanish Secretary of State for Research and 
Innovation; Grant number: BIO2002-0628, SAF2006-08968, 
SAF2009-08695, SAF2012-34203; Grant sponsor: IFIMAV; 
Grant number: API2010/03/SAF2009-08695. 
The authors thank M. Garcia-Gil for providing the murine 
neuron HN9 cells. They are indebted to D. Fernandez (Pro-
genika S.A. Bilbao. Spain) for gene expression analysis and R. 
Tobes and E. Pareja (Era7 Information Technologies SL. 
Granada. Spain) for the design of bioinformatics models. 
They also acknowledge A. San Nicolas-Gomez, L. Bronchalo-</p>

<p>244 
Volume 62, No. 2 </p>

<p>Vicente, and L. Alvarez-Montes for excellent technical assis-
tance and J.C. Zabala (UC Santander) for laboratory support. 
They also thank S. Ribes, JP Gorvel, and M. Fresno for criti-
cal comments on the manuscript, and appreciate A. Tenner's 
interest in our study. </p>



<p>Frande-Cabanes et al.: Microglia, the Innate Immune Cells </p>

<p>February 2014 </p>



<p>
246 
Volume 62, No. 2 </p>

</text></tei>