<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4574835" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>AIM </p>

<p>Dolutegravir is the newest integrase inhibitor approved for HIV 
treatment and has demonstrated potent antiviral activity in patient 
populations with a broad range of treatment experience. This analysis 
aimed to characterize the population pharmacokinetics of dolutegravir 
in treatment-naive patients and to evaluate the influence of patient 
covariates. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>A population pharmacokinetic model was developed using a non-
linear mixed effect modelling approach based on data from 563 HIV-
infected, treatment-naive adult patients in three phase 2/3 trials who 
received dolutegravir (ranging from 10-50 mg once daily) alone or in 
combination with abacavir/lamivudine or tenofovir/emtricitabine. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The pharmacokinetics of dolutegravir were adequately described by a 
linear one compartment model with first order absorption, absorption 
lag time and first order elimination. Population estimates for apparent 
clearance, apparent volume of distribution, absorption rate constant 
and absorption lag time were 0.901 l h 
-1 , 17.4 l, 2.24 h 
À1 , and 0.263 h, 
respectively. Weight, smoking status, age and total bilirubin were 
predictors of clearance, weight was a predictor of volume of 
distribution and gender was a predictor of bioavailability. However, the 
magnitude of the effects of these covariates on steady-state 
dolutegravir plasma exposure was relatively small (&lt;32%) and was not 
considered clinically significant. Race/ethnicity, HBV/HCV co-infection, 
CDC classification, albumin, creatinine clearance, alanine aminotrans-
ferase or aspartate aminotransferase did not influence the pharmaco-
kinetics of dolutegravir in this analysis. </p>

<p>Dolutegravir (DTG; Tivicay®, ViiV Healthcare, Research Trian-
gle Park, NC, USA) is an HIV integrase strand transfer inhib-
itor (INSTI) that has been approved by the Food and Drug 
Administration (FDA) and the European Medicines Agency 
(EMA) for the treatment of HIV infection in a broad patient 
population [1, 2]. Phase 3 studies in treatment-naive and 
treatment-experienced subjects demonstrated that DTG 
has sustained antiviral activity and desirable safety profiles 
in combination with various background therapies in 
HIV-infected adults [3, 4]. Furthermore, in vitro experi-
ments suggest that DTG retains activity against viral strains 
harboring major integrase resistance mutations selected 
for by both raltegravir (RAL) and elvitegravir (EVG) [5], two 
previously approved integrase inhibitors. These findings 
have been confirmed in clinical studies demonstrating 
DTG's activity in subjects with resistance to RAL [6]. 
The pharmacokinetics (PK) of DTG have been evaluated 
in both healthy and HIV-1 infected adult subjects. The pri-
mary objectives of evaluating DTG PK in healthy subjects 
were to understand the disposition of DTG after oral ad-
ministration and to assess the effect of formulations, food, 
drug-drug interactions and enzyme polymorphisms on 
DTG PK. Effects of intrinsic factors, including age, gender, 
body size, and race/ethnicity and extrinsic factors, including 
smoking, hepatitis B virus/hepatitis C virus (HBV/HCV) co-
infection and disease status, were primarily evaluated in 
HIV-infected subjects using sparse PK samples collected in 
phase 2/3 trials and a population PK modelling approach. 
Based on in vitro studies and phase 1 studies, DTG is 
highly bound (≥98.9%) to human plasma proteins, is 
eliminated primarily through hepatic metabolism with 
minimal renal excretion (&lt;1% of dose administered 
orally), is metabolized primarily through uridine diphos-
phate glucuronosyltransferase (UGT) 1A1 with some con-
tribution from cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A4, and is a 
substrate of P-glycoprotein (Pgp) and breast cancer resis-
tance protein (BCRP) [1, 2]. DTG has demonstrated low to 
moderate between subject and within subject PK vari-
ability. In phase 1 studies in healthy subjects, between-
subject variability (%BSV) for area under the plasma 
concentration-time curve (AUC) and maximum plasma 
concentration (C max ) ranged from~20% to 40%, and for 
concentration at the end of the dosing interval (C τ ) from 
30% to 65%. The variability seemed higher in HIV-
infected subjects than healthy subjects. 
The current population PK analysis combines the data 
from clinical trials in treatment-naive populations from a 
proof-of-concept study (ING111521[7]), a phase 2b study 
(SPRING-1 [8]) and a phase 3 study (SPRING-2 [3]). The 
aims of the analysis were to build a population PK model 
of DTG following once daily oral administration in HIV-
infected treatment-naive patients, to identify co-factors 
that contribute to inter-individual variability (IIV) and to 
assess inter-occasion variability (IOV) in DTG PK. This </p>

<p>model was subsequently used to explore the PK/ 
pharmacodynamic (PD) relationship between DTG expo-
sure and efficacy/safety endpoints. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study design, dosing regimens and subjects </p>

<p>The population analysis was conducted using data from 
three studies primarily in HIV-1 infected antiretroviral 
(ART) treatment-naive adults. The number of subjects, 
doses, and populations for each study are presented in 
Table 1. 
Study ING111521 was a phase 2a, multicentre, ran-
domized, parallel, double-blind, dose-ranging, placebo-
controlled study to compare antiviral effect, safety, 
tolerability and PK of DTG monotherapy vs. placebo 
over 10 days in treatment-naive and/or treatment-
experienced INSTI-naive HIV-1 infected adults who were 
not currently receiving antiretroviral therapy. Eligible 
HIV-1 infected subjects were randomized to receive one 
of three blinded treatments (2 mg, 10 mg or 50 mg 
every 24 h) or placebo for 10 days. Data for the 2 mg dose 
(2 × 1mg tablets) were not included in the population PK 
analysis as this dose has been previously shown to have 
different PK to higher doses and is not intended for 
commercial use. SPRING-1 was a phase 2b randomized, 
multicentre, parallel group, dose ranging study 
conducted in HIV-1 infected treatment-naive adults. Sub-
jects were randomized 1: 1: 1: 1 to one of three DTG 
doses (10 mg, 25 mg or 50 mg once daily) or a control 
regimen containing efavirenz (EFV). The background 
nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NRTIs) co-
administered with DTG or EFV were selected by investi-
gators and were either abacavir/lamivudine (ABC/3TC) 
or tenofovir/emtricitabine (TDF/FTC) fixed dose combi-
nation (FDC) tablets. SPRING-2 was a phase 3 random-
ized, double-blind, double-dummy, active-controlled, 
multicentre, parallel group, fully-powered non-inferiority 
study conducted in HIV-1 infected treatment-naive 
adults. Subjects were randomized 1: 1 to receive DTG 
50 mg once daily or RAL 400 mg twice daily, both in com-
bination with investigator-selected fixed-dose dual NRTI 
therapy (either ABC/3TC or TDF/FTC). 
All protocols and consent forms were reviewed and ap-
proved by the institutional review boards (IRB) or ethics 
committees for each of the study sites, and all subjects 
provided signed consent. All studies were conducted in 
accordance with the ethical standards of the Declaration 
of Helsinki and its amendments, consistent with good 
clinical practices and local regulatory requirements. </p>

<p>Pharmacokinetic sampling </p>

<p>PK sampling times for each study are presented in 
Table 1. Briefly, in study ING111521, serial PK samples 
were collected on days 1 and 10. In addition, pre-dose </p>

<p>Population pharmacokinetics of dolutegravir in treatment-naive population </p>

<p>Br J Clin Pharmacol / 80:3 / 503 </p>

<p>PK samples were collected on days 3, 4, 7, 8 and 9. In 
SPRING-1, serial PK samples at week 2 were collected in 
a subgroup of subjects receiving DTG treatment (n = 15 
per DTG dose arm). Sparse PK samples at weeks 2, 12 
and 24 were collected in most subjects receiving DTG. 
In SPRING-2, sparse PK samples at weeks 4, 24 and 48 
were collected in most subjects receiving DTG. </p>

<p>Bioanalytical methods </p>

<p>Plasma samples were analyzed for DTG using a validated 
analytical method [9]. DTG was extracted from human 
plasma by protein precipitation using acetonitrile con-
taining [ 
15 N 
2 H 7 ]-DTG as an internal standard. Extracts 
were analyzed by liquid chromatography-tandem mass 
spectroscopy using a TurboIonSpray® (AB Sciex, 
Framingham, MA, USA) interface with positive ion 
multiple reaction monitoring. The lower limit of the assay 
was 5 ng ml 
-1 or 20 ng ml 
-1 depending on the study, with 
a within-and between-run precision of ≤8.0% and 
≤7.5%, respectively. </p>

<p>Population pharmacokinetic modelling </p>

<p>The population PK models were developed via a non-
linear mixed effects modelling approach using the first 
order conditional estimation method with interaction 
(FOCEI) of <rs type="software">NONMEM</rs> software (version VII Level 1.2) [10]. 
Structural model selection was driven by the data and </p>

<p>was based on evaluation of goodness-of-fit plots (ob-
served vs. predicted concentrations, weighted residuals 
vs. predicted values or time, histograms of individual ran-
dom effects etc.), successful convergence, plausibility 
and precision of parameter estimates and the minimum 
objective function value (OFV). 
The population PK model of DTG was developed with 
3357 plasma concentrations from 563 subjects. Records 
with concentrations below the limit of quantification 
(BLQ) represented a very small percentage of the data 
(1%) and were excluded from the analysis. Various 
models were considered and tested to describe the 
absorption/disposition kinetics of DTG. 
Distributions of inter-individual random effects were 
assumed to be log-normal and were described by an ex-
ponential error model. The residual errors were de-
scribed by a combined additive and proportional 
model. IOV was also investigated and distributions of 
IOV were assumed to be normal. The occasion in this 
analysis was defined by PK sampling week, except for 
study ING111521, in which day 1 through day 10 were 
treated as a single occasion. The inclusion of IOV in the 
model was based on OFV, individual predictions and 
the extent of IOV (CV%) relative to IIV. 
Investigation of covariate-parameter relationships 
was based on the range of covariate values in the data 
set, scientific interest, mechanistic plausibility and </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Overview of clinical trials included in dolutegravir population PK analysis </p>

<p>Study/Phase 
Population 
n 
Dose/Treatment duration 
Planned PK data </p>

<p>ING111521 
(Proof of concept) </p>

<p>Treatment-naive or treatment-experienced 
(integrase inhibitor naive) HIV-infected 
patients, not currently receiving 
antiretroviral therapy </p>

<p>19 
2, 10 and 50 mg once daily orally 
(data for the 2 mg dose were not 
included in this population PK 
analysis as this dose has been 
previously shown to have different 
PK to higher doses and there is no 
intention to commercialize the 
1 mg tablet) </p>

<p>Days 1 and 10 at pre-dose, 
0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12 
and 24 h post-dose </p>

<p>10 days </p>

<p>Days 3, 4, 7, 8 and 9 at 
pre-dose </p>

<p>SPRING-1 (Phase 2b) 
HIV-infected treatment-naive patients 
141 
10, 25 and 50 mg DTG once daily 
orally with either ABC/3TC 
(600 mg/300 mg) or TDF/FTC 
(300 mg/200 mg) fixed-dose 
combination (FDC) </p>

<p>Intensive PK (n = 45): Week 2 at 
pre-dose, 2, 3, 4, 8 and 24 h 
post-dose; Week 12 and 24 at 
pre-dose and 2-4 h post-dose </p>

<p>96 weeks 
Limited PK (n = 96): Weeks 2, 12, 
and 24 at pre-dose and 2-4 h 
post-dose </p>

<p>SPRING-2 (Phase 3) 
HIV-infected treatment-naive patients 
403 
50 mg DTG once daily with either 
ABC/3TC (600 mg/300 mg) or 
TDF/FTC (300 mg/200 mg) 
fixed-dose combination (FDC) </p>

<p>Week 4: pre-dose and 1-3 h or 
4-12 h post-dose; </p>

<p>96 weeks </p>

<p>Week 24: pre-dose; </p>

<p>Week 48: pre-dose and 1-3 h or 
4-12 h post-dose </p>

<p>ABC, abacavir; DTG, dolutegravir; FTC, emtricitabine; PK, pharmacokinetics; 3TC, lamivudine; TDF, tenofovir disoproxil fumarate. </p>

<p>J. Zhang et al. </p>

<p>504 / 80:3 / Br J Clin Pharmacol </p>

<p>exploratory graphics. The covariates evaluated are identi-
fied in Table 2. A full model approach [11, 12] was imple-
mented, where all covariate-parameter relationships of 
interest were entered in the model and parameters were 
estimated. Insignificant or poorly estimated covariates (less 
than 10.83 point increase of OFV for one parameter, and/or </p>

<p>confidence intervals (CI) including the null value and/or 
high relative standard error (RSE &gt;50%)) were then ex-
cluded from the model during the backward elimination 
process. The full model did not simultaneously include 
highly correlated covariates, such as body weight vs. body 
mass index (BMI) or gender vs. body weight. Therefore </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Subject characteristics and demographics by study </p>

<p>Covariate 
Statistic or category 
ING111521 
SPRING-1 
SPRING-2 
All studies </p>

<p>Total number 
19 
141 
403 
563 </p>

<p>Age (years) at baseline 
Median [min-max] 
40 [22-53] 
35 [20-64] 
37 [18-68] 
37 [18-68] </p>

<p>Weight (kg) at baseline 
Median [min-max] 
78.1 [60.5-106] 
76.4 [49-120] 
74.0 [39.0-135]* 
74.5 [39.0-135]* </p>

<p>Body mass index (kg m 
-2 ) at baseline 
Median [min-max] 
25.5 [21.7-32.7] 
24.3 [17.6-38.7] 
24.1 [14.7-47.9]* 
24.2 [14.7-47.9]* </p>

<p>Body surface area (m 
2 ) at baseline 
Median [min-max] 
1.95 [1.68-2.33] 
1.94 [1.46-2.49] 
1.90 [1.27-2.69]* 
1.92 [1.27-2.69]* </p>

<p>Total bilirubin (μmol l 
-1 ) at baseline 
Median [min-max] 
8.55 [5.13-18.8] 
10.0 [4.00-38.0] 
9.00 [3.00-31.0] 
9.00 [3.00-38.0] </p>

<p>Albumin (g l 
-1 ) at baseline 
Median [min-max] 
42.0 [38.0-47.0] 
44.0 [34.0-51.0] 
45.0 [30.0-54.0] 
45.0 [30.0-54.0] </p>

<p>Aspartate aminotransferase (IU l 
-1 ) at baseline 
Median [min-max] 
25.0 [15.0-42.0] 
24.0 [11.0-180] 
24.0 [12.0-133] 
24.0 [11.0-180] </p>

<p>Alanine aminotransferase (IU l 
-1 ) at baseline 
Median [min-max] 
22.0 [12.0-41.0] 
20.0 [8.00-260] 
21.0 [5.00-158] 
21.0 [5.00-260] </p>

<p>Creatinine clearance (ml min 
-1 ) at baseline 
Median [min-max] 
119 [86.0-190] 
116 [54.6-231] 
123 [64.4-239] 
121 [54.6-239] </p>

<p>Gender, n (%) 
Male 
19 (100) 
122 (87) 
340 (84) 
481 (85) </p>

<p>Female 
0 (0) 
19 (13) 
63 (16) 
82 (15) </p>

<p>Race, n (%) 
Caucasian 
16 (84) 
113 (80) 
341 (85) 
470 (83) </p>

<p>Black 
3 (16) 
16 (11) 
47 (12) 
66 (12) </p>

<p>Asian 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
6 (1) 
6 (1) </p>

<p>Other 
0 (0) 
12 (9) 
9 (2) 
21 (4) </p>

<p>Ethnicity, n (%) 
Non-Hispanic or Latino 
18 (95) 
118 (84) 
361 (90) 
497 (88) </p>

<p>Hispanic or Latino 
1 (5) 
23 (16) 
42 (10) 
66 (12) </p>

<p>Smoking, n (%) 
Never 
0 (0) 
72 (51) 
163 (40) 
235 (42) </p>

<p>Current 
0 (0) 
54 (38) 
182 (45) 
236 (42) </p>

<p>Former 
0 (0) 
15 (11) 
58 (14) 
73 (13) </p>

<p>Unknown 
19 (100) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
19 (3) </p>

<p>HCV co-infection at baseline, n (%) 
No 
19 (100) 
129 (91) 
359 (89) 
507 (90) </p>

<p>Yes 
0 (0) 
11 (8) 
41 (10) 
52 (9) </p>

<p>Unknown 
0 (0) 
1 (1) 
3 (1) 
4 (1) </p>

<p>HBV co-infection at baseline, n (%) 
No 
19 (100) 
140 (99) 
396 (98) 
555 (99) </p>

<p>Yes 
0 (0) 
1 (1) 
7 (2) 
8 (1) </p>

<p>CDC classification of HIV infection at baseline, n (%) 
A 
17 (89) 
120 (85) 
353 (88) 
490 (87) </p>

<p>B 
1 (5) 
20 (14) 
41 (10) 
62 (11) </p>

<p>C 
1 (5) 
1 (1) 
9 (2) 
11 (2) </p>

<p>Metal-cation containing products †, n (%) 
No 
19 (100) 
124 (88) 
366 (91) 
509 (90) </p>

<p>Yes 
0 (0) 
17 (12) 
37 (9) 
54 (10) </p>

<p>Formulation, n (%) 
AL 
19 (100) 
49 (35) 
0 (0) 
68 (12) </p>

<p>AP 
0 (0) 
92 (65) 
0 (0) 
92 (16) </p>

<p>AW 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
403 (100) 
403 (72) </p>

<p>Dose (mg), n (%) 
10 
9 (47) 
49 (35) 
0 (0) 
58 (10) </p>

<p>25 
0 (0) 
46 (33) 
0 (0) 
46 (8) </p>

<p>50 
10 (53) 
46 (33) 
403 (100) 
459 (82) </p>

<p>Total number of samples, n (%) 
493 (15) 
985 (29) 
1879 (56) 
3357 </p>

<p>CDC, Centres for Disease Control and Prevention; CYP, cytochrome P450; HBV, hepatitis B virus; HCV, hepatitis C virus; PGP, P-glycoprotein, UGT, uridine diphosphate 
glucuronosyltransferase.*Imputed values included in summary statistics. †Use of metal cation containing products was the only concomitant medication group involving 10% 
or more of the population. The number of subjects taking other concomitant medications (Ginkgo biloba, CYP34A inhibitors/inducers, PGP inhibitors/inducers, UGT1A1 inhibi-
tors/inducers and UGT1A3 inhibitors/inducers) of interest was 3% or less apart from UGT1A1 inhibitors where 6% of patients were taking this concomitant medication. No sub-
jects were taking moderate to strong CYP3A4 or PGP inducers. </p>

<p>Population pharmacokinetics of dolutegravir in treatment-naive population </p>

<p>Br J Clin Pharmacol / 80:3 / 505 </p>

<p>several semi-final models (with one of the competing 
correlated covariates) were investigated. For continuous 
covariates, a power function was utilized. For categorical 
covariates, the fractional change in the typical parameter 
value was determined. </p>

<p>Model evaluation </p>

<p>A prediction corrected visual predictive check [13] (PC-VPC) 
was performed for the final PK model. Five hundred 
data sets were simulated using the final model parameters, 
covariates, sampling times and dosing histories. Both the 
observed and the model predicted individual concentra-
tion values were normalized by the population prediction 
of the same time point. Non-parametric bootstrap analysis 
was also performed by generating 1000 data sets through 
random sampling with replacement from the original data 
using the individual as the sampling unit. No stratification 
was implemented during the random sampling. Population 
parameters of the final model for each data set were 
estimated using <rs type="software">NONMEM</rs> and empirical 95% CIs were 
constructed. </p>

<p>Individual predicted pharmacokinetic 
parameters </p>

<p>The final model was used to compute individual esti-
mates of steady-state AUC(0-τ), C max , t max (time to C max ) 
and C τ for all subjects included in the population PK anal-
ysis following repeat dosing of the actual DTG dose ad-
ministered to each subject in the study. The individual 
estimates of all model parameters were obtained from 
the final model by an empirical Bayes estimation 
method. Individual estimates of AUC(0-τ) were obtained 
as AUC(0-τ) = Dose/([CL/F i ]/F), where Dose was the actual 
dose administered to each subject in study, CL/F i was the 
individual estimate of oral clearance and F was the esti-
mated oral bioavailability in subpopulations identified 
by the model relative to the reference population. Indi-
vidual estimates of C max , t max and C τ were obtained by 
simulation of the concentration-time profiles following 
a steady-state dose for all individuals using their individ-
ual parameter values assuming no IOV and zero values 
for residual variability. Summary statistics for parameter 
estimates were computed. </p>

<p>Simulation </p>

<p>A simulation was performed to predict the impact of co-
variates on DTG exposure. The final PK model was used 
to simulate plasma PK profiles for the treatment-naive 
population following a steady-state once daily dose of 
50 mg DTG. The PK parameters AUC(0-τ), C max , t max and 
C τ were summarized by covariate categories. Forest plots 
[14-16] were created for comparison of steady-state 
C max , AUC(0-τ) and C τ among various subpopulations. In 
this analysis, each PK parameter was first averaged by co-
variate categories of interest and normalized by the aver-
age of reference categories in order to express the results </p>

<p>as the PK parameter fold change for a given covariate 
category from the reference category. These PK 
parameter fold changes were then summarized from 
100 simulations to obtain the median and the corre-
sponding 90% CI. </p>

<p>Exploratory PK-PD relationship </p>

<p>An exploratory graphical analysis of potential exposure-
response relationships was performed using individual 
predicted DTG exposure (steady-state C τ , C max and 
AUC(0-τ)) obtained from the final population PK model 
with actual doses administered in each study assuming 
no IOV. The following efficacy endpoints were explored: 
plasma HIV-1 RNA &lt;50 copies ml 
-1 at week 48 using 
the missing, switch or discontinuation equals failure 
(MSDF) algorithm (categorical variable) (SPRING-2 only), 
protocol-defined virological failure (PDVF) at week 48 
(categorical variable) (SPRING-1 only); CD4+ cell count 
change from baseline both at week 48 and maximal 
change over 48 weeks (continuous variable) (SPRING-1 
and SPRING-2 combined and SPRING-2 alone). The 
following safety endpoints were explored: change from 
baseline in serum creatinine concentration, creatinine 
clearance (CRCL), urine albumin: creatinine ratio, alanine 
aminotransferase (ALT), and total bilirubin (maximal 
change over 48 weeks and change at week 48 visit 
[continuous variable]); presence of the top three most 
common adverse events (AEs) including nausea, diarrhoea 
and headache (categorical variable), for both SPRING-1 
and SPRING-2 combined apart from urine albumin: creati-
nine ratio which was not collected before week 48 in 
SPRING-1, and consequently was only explored for 
SPRING-2. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Data, demographics, and baseline 
characteristics </p>

<p>The basic distribution of covariates and number of 
concentrations by study are described in Table 2. </p>

<p>Population PK analysis </p>

<p>The PK of DTG following oral administration were ade-
quately described by a one compartment model with ab-
sorption lag time (t lag ) and first order absorption and 
elimination as the final base model, with IIV in apparent 
clearance (CL/F), apparent volume of distribution (V/F), 
and first order absorption rate (k a ), correlation between 
CL/F and V/F, IOV on CL/F, weight on CL/F and V/F, 
increase in CL/F for study ING111521, and increase in 
bioavailability (F) for the 10 mg dose. No improvement 
was found with the two compartment model and the ad-
ditive residual error was not significant. Dose was tested 
as a continuous covariate on F but was not significant. 
The final model showed that weight, smoking status, </p>

<p>J. Zhang et al. </p>



<p>age and total bilirubin were predictors of CL/F, weight 
was a predictor of V/F and gender was a predictor of F. 
The correlation between CL/F and V/F was low (correla-
tion = 0.375, %RSE = 33%) in the final model and removed 
(11 point increase in OFV). 
The parameter estimates of the final PK model are 
presented in Table 3. The reference population was a 
40-year-old, 70 kg male, non-current smoker, with total 
bilirubin of 9 μmol l 
-1 administered &gt;10 mg dose. The 
estimated typical (95% CI) parameter values were: 
CL/F = 0.901 (0.864, 0.938) l h 
-1 , V/F = 17.4 (16.5, 18.3) l, 
k a = 2.24 (1.56, 2.92) h 
-1 and absorption t lag = 0.263 
(0.0942, 0.432) h. There was a 35% increase in CL/F 
for study ING111521 compared with SPRING-1 and 
SPRING-2. There was a 24% increase in oral bioavailability 
for the 10 mg dose compared with the 25 and 50 mg 
doses. Apparent clearance of DTG was, on average, 16% 
(95% CI: 10%, 22%) higher in current smokers than non-
current smokers. Oral bioavailability (F) was, on average, 
21% (95% CI: 13%, 29%) higher in female subjects 
compared with males. Apparent clearance and volume 
of distribution increased with weight with a power coef-
ficient of 0.438 and 0.768, respectively (i.e. as (WT/70) </p>

<p>0.438 </p>

<p>and (WT/70) 
0.768 , respectively). For the range of weights 
in the analysis population (39-135 kg), CL/F ranged from 
0.697-1.20 l h 
-1 , which was 23% lower to 33% higher 
compared with a 70 kg subject and V/F ranged from 
11.1-28.8 l, which was 36% lower to 66% higher 
compared with a 70 kg subject. Apparent clearance 
increased with age with a power coefficient of 0.193 
(i.e. as (AGE/40) 
0.193 ), and for the range of age in the 
analysis population (18-68 years), CL/F ranged from 
0.772-0.998 l h 
-1 . Apparent clearance decreased with 
increasing total bilirubin with a power coefficient of À0.211 
(i.e. as (BILI/9) 
À0.211 ), and for the range of total bilirubin 
in the analysis population (3-38 μmol l 
-1 ), CL/F ranged 
from 1.14-0.665 l h 
-1 . Race, ethnicity, HCV co-infection, 
CDC classification, albumin, CRCL, ALT or aspartate 
aminotransferase (AST) did not influence the PK of DTG 
in this analysis. 
All of the fixed effect parameters were estimated with 
good precision (%RSE &lt;24%) apart from absorption t lag 
(%RSE = 32.7%). The inter-individual random effects were 
also estimated with reasonable precision (%RSE &lt;40%). 
IOV was tested in all PK parameters, of which an inclusion 
of IOV on CL/F was significant with a reduction of OFV by </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>Parameter estimates of final dolutegravir population PK model </p>

<p>Parameter 
NONMEM estimates 
Bootstrap estimates* </p>

<p>(units) 
Point estimate 
%RSE 
95% CI 
Median 
95% CI </p>

<p>CL/F (l h 
-1 ) † 
0.901 
2.11 
0.864, 0.938 
0.901 
0.866, 0.940 </p>

<p>V/F (l) ‡ 
17.4 
2.49 
16.5, 18.3 
17.4 
16.6, 18.2 </p>

<p>k a (h 
-1 ) 
2.24 
15.4 
1.56, 2.92 
2.21 
1.73, 3.10 </p>

<p>ALAG (h) 
0.263 
32.7 
0.0942, 0.432 
0.262 
0.0833, 0.393 </p>

<p>CL/F~proof-of-concept 
1.35 
4.83 
1.22, 1.48 
1.35 
1.24, 1.51 </p>

<p>F~10 mg § 
1.24 
2.92 
1.17, 1.31 
1.24 
1.17, 1.31 </p>

<p>CL/F~WT 
0.438 
16.9 
0.293, 0.583 
0.440 
0.290, 0.582 </p>

<p>V/F~WT 
0.768 
10.8 
0.605, 0.931 
0.774 
0.616, 0.944 </p>

<p>F~GENDER § 
1.21 
3.27 
1.13, 1.29 
1.21 
1.13, 1.30 </p>

<p>CL~SMOKING 
1.16 
2.45 
1.10, 1.22 
1.16 
1.10, 1.22 </p>

<p>CL~AGE 
0.193 
23.7 
0.103, 0.283 
0.195 
0.105, 0.283 </p>

<p>CL~BILIRUBIN 
-0.211 
14.0 
-0.269, -0.153 
-0.212 
-0.267, -0.152 </p>

<p>Inter-individual or inter-occasion variability 
CV% </p>

<p>‖ </p>

<p>ω </p>

<p>2 
CL </p>

<p>0.0551 
9.27 
0.0451, 0.0651 
23.5 
0.0539 
0.0449, 0.0652 </p>

<p>ω </p>

<p>2 
V </p>

<p>0.0188 
29.5 
0.00794, 0.0297 
13.7 
0.0182 
0.00714, 0.0295 </p>

<p>ω </p>

<p>2 
ka </p>

<p>0.224 
38.8 
0.0535, 0.395 
50.1 
0.217 
0.0613, 1.11 </p>

<p>ω </p>

<p>2 
IOV-CL </p>

<p>0.0296 
15.6 
0.0205, 0.0387 
17.2 
0.0300 
0.0184, 0.0407 </p>

<p>Residual variability 
CV% 
Median 
95% CI </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>2 
prop </p>

<p>0.0704 
7.41 
0.0602, 0.0806 
26.5 
0.0698 
0.0555, 0.0830 </p>

<p>%RSE: percent relative standard error of the estimate = SE/parameter estimate × 100; 95% CI = 95% confidence interval on the parameter; ALAG, absorption lag-time; CL/F, ap-
parent clearance; CV, coefficient of variation of proportional error (=[σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>prop ] 
0.5 *100); IOV, inter-occasion variability; k a , absorption rate constant; PK, pharmacokinetics; σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>prop , 
proportional component of the residual error model; V/F, volume of central compartment; ω </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CL , ω </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>V , and ω </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ka , variance of random effect of CL/F, V/F and k a , respectively.The 
reference population for PK parameters CL/F and V/F are 40-year-old, 70 kg male, non-current smoker, with total bilirubin of 9 μmol l 
-1 . *From 1000 completed bootstrap runs; </p>

<p> †CL/F = 0.901 × 1.16 
SMOK × 1.35 
POC × (WT/70) 
0.438 × (AGE/40) 
0.193 × (BILI/9) 
-0.211 (SMOK = 1 for smoking subjects and = 0 for non-smoking subjects; POC = 1 for study </p>

<p>ING111521 and = 0 for other studies);  ‡V/F = 17.4 × (WT/70) 
0.768 ;  §F = 1.21 
GEND × 1.24 
DOSE (GEND = 1 for females and = 0 for males; DOSE = 1 for 10 mg dose and = 0 for other </p>

<p>doses) 
‖ CVTV P ¼ 
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
e </p>

<p>ω 2 </p>

<p>P À 1 </p>

<p>p 
when ω </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P exceeds 0.15 </p>

<p>Population pharmacokinetics of dolutegravir in treatment-naive population </p>

<p>Br J Clin Pharmacol / 80:3 / 507 </p>

<p>&gt;100 points and good precision (%RSE = 15.6). As a 
result, IOV for CL/F (17.2%) was retained in the model. 
The diagnostic plots for the final model (Figure 1) 
indicated that the model adequately described the data. 
The distributions of the random effects were close to 
normal, and they were not correlated. No strong 
unexplained covariate-parameter relationships were 
noticeable. 
Figure 2 presents the results of the PC-VPC for the 
final model. The results of the PC-VPC indicate that the 
final PK model provided a good description of the data. 
The bootstrap results were very similar to the 
NONMEM estimates from the final PK model (Table 3), 
supporting the stability of the population PK model and 
the good precision of NONMEM parameter estimates. 
Steady-state AUC(0-τ), C max , t max and C τ of DTG were 
derived from the final model by an empirical Bayes esti-
mation method (Table 4). Consistent with the final PK 
model, DTG exposure (AUC(0-τ) and C max ) was 20% to 
50% lower in study ING111521 compared with the same 
doses in SPRING-1 (10 mg and 50 mg) and SPRING-2 
(50 mg), which is in agreement with the 35% higher </p>

<p>CL/F in study ING111521 as described by the final PK 
model. Dose-proportional PK were seen between the 25 
and 50 mg doses. However, slightly higher than dose-
proportional PK were observed at the 10 mg dose, in 
agreement with the model that the relative oral bioavail-
ability of the 10 mg dose is approximately 24% higher 
than the 25 and 50 mg doses. The average t max was 
approximately 2 h across all studies and doses. For sub-
jects receiving DTG 50 mg once daily in the three studies 
(n = 449), the geometric mean (CV%) [5 
th %, 95 
th %] of es-
timated DTG AUC(0-τ), C max and C τ were 53.6 μg ml 
-1 h 
(26.9%) [35.1, 84.9 μg ml 
-1 h], 3.67 μg ml 
-1 (19.7%) 
[2.74, 5.19 μg ml 
-1 ] and 1.11 μg ml 
-1 (46.3%) [0.532, 
2.24 μg ml </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>], respectively. </p>

<p>Simulation </p>

<p>Forest plots for the comparison of steady-state DTG C max , 
AUC(0-τ) and C τ among various subpopulations are pre-
sented in Figure 3 to illustrate and confirm the PK model 
findings of covariate effect on DTG PK in terms of sys-
temic exposure. On average, DTG C max , AUC(0-τ) and C τ 
were 32%, 26% and 15% higher in females, respectively. </p>

<p>Figure 1 </p>

<p>Goodness-of-fit and diagnostic plots. Each plot shows the line of unity (solid line) and Loess line (dashed line) </p>

<p>J. Zhang et al. </p>



<p>DTG C max , AUC(0-τ) and C τ were 7%, 13% and 22% lower 
in current smokers, respectively. Exposure decreased 
with increasing weight. For the weight groups (based 
on quartiles) 66-75 kg, 75-84 kg and &gt;84 kg, C max was 
14%, 20% and 28% lower, AUC(0-τ) was 12%, 17% and 
24% lower and C τ was 7%, 8% and 15% lower 
compared with the ≤66 kg group, respectively. Exposure 
decreased with increasing age. For elderly subjects 
&gt;55 years, C max , AUC(0-τ) and C τ was 10%, 14% and 
18% lower compared with subjects ≤55 years. Subjects </p>

<p>with background therapy TDF/FTC had 6%, 5% and 4% 
lower C max , AUC(0-τ) and C τ than those with background 
therapy of ABC/3TC, respectively, which is of no clinical 
significance. For total bilirubin (based on quartiles), 
C max , AUC(0-τ) and C τ were comparable for the ≤7 and 
7-9 μmol l 
-1 groups. For the 9-12 and &gt;12 μmol l </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>groups, C max was 2% and 18% higher, AUC(0-τ) was 
7% and 17% higher and C τ was 17% and 38% higher, 
respectively, compared with the ≤7 μmol l 
-1 group. 
Covariates HBV/HCV co-infection, race and ethnicity were 
not significant covariates in the models, and very little 
difference was found in C max , AUC(0-τ) and C τ within 
these covariates. </p>

<p>Exploratory PK-PD relationship </p>

<p>The PK-PD exploratory graphical analysis showed no re-
lationship between any of the efficacy endpoints (antivi-
ral response and CD4+ increase) and DTG exposure 
(steady-state AUC(0-τ), C max and C τ ) in treatment-naive 
subjects. No relationship between DTG exposure and 
the safety endpoints was observed, except that serum 
creatinine (Figures 4 and 5) and CRCL (Figures 6 and 7) 
appeared to be slightly correlated with DTG exposure. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The PK of DTG were described by a linear one compart-
ment model with absorption t lag , first order absorption 
and elimination. Lower body weight, non-smoking sta-
tus, lower age, higher total bilirubin at baseline and fe-
male gender were associated with higher plasma DTG 
exposure, either through effects on CL or F. The magni-
tude of effect of each covariate on CL or F was relatively </p>

<p>Figure 2 </p>

<p>Prediction-corrected visual predictive check. Open circles: observed 
data, red lines: observed median (solid), 5th and 95th percentiles 
(dashed), shaded areas: 90% confidence intervals for median (red) 5th 
and 95th percentiles (blue) of simulated data </p>

<p>Table 4 </p>

<p>Summary of steady-state C max , t max , C τ and AUC(0-τ) following actual dose of dolutegravir administered in the studies </p>

<p>Study 
Dose (mg) 
Statistic </p>

<p>AUC(0-τ) 
C max 
t max 
C τ </p>

<p>(μg ml 
-1 h) 
(μg ml 
-1 ) 
( h ) 
( μg ml 
-1 ) </p>

<p>ING111521 
10 
n* 
9 
9 
9 
9 </p>

<p>Geometric mean (95% CI) 
9.33 (8.16, 10.7) 
0.691 (0.606, 0.788) 
1.66 (1.17, 2.35) 
0.168 (0.136, 0.208) </p>

<p>50 
n 
10 
10 
10 
10 </p>

<p>Geometric mean (95% CI) 
41.3 (38.4, 44.4) 
2.94 (2.65, 3.27) 
1.94 (1.65, 2.29) 
0.785 (0.689, 0.895) </p>

<p>SPRING-1 
10 
n 
49 
49 
49 
49 </p>

<p>Geometric mean (95% CI) 
14.3 (13.4, 15.3) 
0.957 (0.908, 1.01) 
2.00 (2.00, 2.00) 
0.311 (0.281, 0.345) </p>

<p>25 
n 
46 
46 
46 
46 </p>

<p>Geometric mean (95% CI) 
25.7 (23.6, 28.1) 
1.77 (1.66, 1.89) 
2.00 (2.00, 2.00) 
0.530 (0.462, 0.609) </p>

<p>50 
n 
46 
46 
46 
46 </p>

<p>Geometric mean (95% CI) 
53.8 (49.6, 58.2) 
3.58 (3.37, 3.80) 
2.00 (2.00, 2.00) 
1.17 (1.04, 1.33) </p>

<p>SPRING-2 
50 
n 
403 
403 
403 
403 </p>

<p>Geometric mean (95% CI) 
53.6 (52.3, 55.0) 
3.69 (3.62, 3.76) 
2.00 (2.00, 2.00) 
1.10 (1.05, 1.15) </p>

<p>AUC(0-τ), steady state area under the plasma concentration-time curve over the dosing interval (τ); CI, confidence interval; C max , maximum plasma concentration at steady-state; 
C τ , concentration at time τ; t max , time to C max .*95% CI = 95% confidence interval for geometric mean. </p>

<p>Population pharmacokinetics of dolutegravir in treatment-naive population </p>

<p>Br J Clin Pharmacol / 80:3 / 509 </p>

<p>small (all less than 30%, Table 3), and the magnitude of 
effect on steady-state AUC(0-τ), C max and C τ of DTG was 
&lt;32% (Figure 3). Based on the known safety profile and 
PK/PD relationships for the antiviral activity of DTG, the 
likely range of DTG therapeutic effect encompasses 
these changes. Subgroup analysis on week 48 antiviral 
response in SPRING-2 demonstrated that there were no 
effects of gender and age on response [17]. Thus, the ef-
fects of these covariates are not considered clinically sig-
nificant. Therefore, no DTG dose adjustment by these 
covariates is necessary. 
The final PK model indicated that mean (95% CI) CL/F 
was 16% (10%, 22%) higher in current smokers compared 
with non-smokers/former smokers. DTG is metabolized 
primarily by UGT1A1 with CYP3A4 as a secondary path-
way. Tobacco smoking has been shown to induce he-
patic CYP isozymes including 1A1, 1A2, 2B6, 3A4 and 
possibly 2E1 [18-22], and it may also have the potential 
to induce UGT1A1 activity [22, 23]. The reason for the 
higher CL/F of DTG seen in current smokers in this analy-
sis may be related to the enzyme induction effect of to-
bacco smoking. 
The final PK model also indicated that there was a 
21% (13%, 29%) increase in mean (95% CI) oral bio-
availability in women compared with men. DTG is a 
known substrate of drug transporters Pgp and BCRP. 
It has been suggested [24] that gender may play a role 
in the expression of drug transporters, which could in-
fluence the drug disposition and may partly explain 
gender differences in oral bioavailability. Nevertheless, 
the actual mechanism that contributed to the gender 
difference in oral bioavailability of DTG merits further 
investigation. 
Apparent clearance unexpectedly increased with age 
with a positive power coefficient of 0.193 (95% CI: 0.103, 
0.283) (i.e. as (AGE/40) 
0.193 ). Clearance is often lower in 
elderly people. The reason for the unexpected effect of 
age on DTG CL/F may be associated with decreased 
absorption of DTG with age. For highly protein bound 
molecules like DTG, reduction in protein binding capacity 
and decrease in plasma albumin concentrations, as 
commonly seen in the elderly, may have contributed 
to the increased CL/F with age [25]. In the current 
analysis, age was slightly but inversely correlated with 
baseline albumin. However, age in the model had a 
lower OFV than baseline albumin in the model, sug-
gesting that the increase in CL/F with age cannot be 
fully attributed to the decrease in plasma albumin 
concentrations. Since the data in elderly subjects were 
limited in the current analysis (17 [3%] aged &gt;55 years 
and 1 aged &gt;65 years), additional data from elderly 
subjects may be warranted to understand further the 
PK of DTG in this population. 
Apparent clearance also decreased with total bilirubin 
with a negative power coefficient of À0.211 (95% CI: À0.269, 
À0.153). For the range of total bilirubin in the analysis </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Figure 3 </p>

<p>Predicted fold change in steady-state (A) C max , (B) AUC(0-τ) and (C) C τ of 
dolutegravir relative to reference covariate category (fold change in 
median and 90% confidence interval). Reference categories: male, 
non-current smoker, no HBV/HCV co-infection, Caucasian, non-
Hispanic/Latino, CDC A, ABC/3TC for gender, smoking status, HBV/ 
HCV co-infection, race, ethnicity, CDC, and background therapy, respec-
tively. For continuous covariates, the overall median was used to nor-
malize the C max , AUC(0-τ) and C τ of each category (i.e., 4.43 μg ml 
-1 , </p>

<p>52.8 μg ml 
-1 h, and 1.12 μg ml 
-1 for C max , AUC(0-τ) and C τ , respectively). </p>

<p>ABC/3TC, abacavir/lamivudine; AUC(0-τ), steady-state area under the 
plasma concentration-time curve over the dosing interval (τ); CDC, 
Centres for Disease Control and Prevention; C max , maximum plasma 
concentration at steady-state; C τ , concentration at time τ; HBV, hepatitis 
B virus; HCV, hepatitis C virus; ss, steady state; TDF/FTC, tenofovir 
disoproxil fumarate/emtricitabine </p>

<p>J. Zhang et al. </p>



<p>(3-38 μmol l 
-1 ), CL/F would range from 26% higher to 26% 
lower compared with a subject with total bilirubin of 
9 μmol l </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>. The relationship between DTG CL/F and total 
bilirubin is likely attributable to competition between 
DTG and bilirubin for the same metabolic pathway 
(UGT1A1). 
There was a 35% higher CL/F for study ING111521 
compared with the other two studies. The reason behind 
such a study difference is not fully understood. There 
may be factors in these studies that are not accounted 
for with the available covariates to explain this differ-
ence. Although study ING111521 was a DTG monother-
apy study, and SPRING-1 and SPRING-2 were combination 
treatment studies, no difference in DTG PK was expected 
between subjects receiving monotherapy vs. combination </p>

<p>therapy with ABC/3TC or TDF/FTC, as these NRTIs do not 
share and have no effect on the elimination pathways of 
DTG (UGT1A1 and CYP3A). A smaller sample size and 
thus less diverse patient population in study ING111521 
vs. SPRING-1 and SPRING-2 may potentially account for 
the difference in the estimated CL/F between these studies. 
There was a difference in bioavailability by dose, 24% 
higher bioavailability for the 10 mg dose compared with 
the 25 and 50 mg doses. Dose as a continuous covariate 
was investigated but was not significant, and no differ-
ence was found when separate bioavailability was esti-
mated for the 25 mg dose compared with the 50 mg 
dose. The reason for a higher oral bioavailability at the 
lower dose is possibly due to better dispersion of the 
tablet at lower tablet strength. </p>

<p>Figure 4 </p>

<p>Serum creatinine change from baseline at week 48 vs. dolutegravir exposure (C max and AUC(0-τ))-SPRING-1 and SPRING-2. Each plot shows the individ-
ual observed data (open circle) and the Loess line (dashed line). AUC(0,τ), steady-state area under the plasma concentration-time curve over the dosing 
interval (τ); C max , maximum plasma concentration at steady-state; ss, steady-state </p>

<p>Figure 5 </p>

<p>Serum creatinine maximum change from baseline vs. dolutegravir exposure (C max and AUC(0-τ))-SPRING-1 and SPRING-2. Each plot shows the individual 
observed data (open circle) and the Loess line (dashed line). AUC(0-τ), steady-state area under the plasma concentration-time curve over the dosing 
interval (τ); C max , maximum plasma concentration at steady state; ss, steady state </p>

<p>Population pharmacokinetics of dolutegravir in treatment-naive population </p>

<p>Br J Clin Pharmacol / 80:3 / 511 </p>

<p>IOV was assessed in the model which improved individ-
ual predictions. The estimated IOV on CL/F was 17%, which 
is quite similar to the estimated intra-subject variability 
based on phase 1 studies in healthy adult subjects. The 
IOV is probably due to variation in absorption, although 
day-to-day variability in metabolic enzyme activity (such 
as UGT1A1 or CYP3A4) may also contribute to the esti-
mated IOV. Compared with the residual variability esti-
mated from this analysis (26.5%), the magnitude of IOV is 
not considered significant and therefore of little clinical 
relevance. This also provided the reasonable justification 
for not including IOV in simulation, given the main focus 
of simulation in this analysis was the central tendency of 
DTG exposure among various subpopulations. </p>

<p>DTG PK were similar between healthy and HIV-1 in-
fected subjects. Based on analysis using pooled PK data 
following DTG 50 mg once daily (fasted and fed) in phase 
1 studies, geometric means (CV%) of DTG AUC(0-τ), 
C max and C τ were estimated at 49.1 μg ml 
-1 h (41%), 
3.62 μg ml 
-1 (35%) and 1.05 μg ml 
-1 (56%), respectively 
(internal data). These values were comparable with those 
presented in Table 4 based on the population PK 
analysis. 
The PK-PD exploratory graphical analysis showed no 
relationship between any of the efficacy endpoints 
(antiviral response and CD4+ increase) and DTG expo-
sure (steady-state AUC(0-τ), C max and C τ ) in treatment-
naive subjects, which is likely due to the high potency </p>

<p>Figure 6 </p>

<p>Creatinine clearance change from baseline at week 48 vs. dolutegravir exposure (C max and AUC(0-τ))-SPRING-1 and SPRING-2. Each plot shows the 
individual observed data (open circle) and the Loess line (dashed line). AUC(0-τ), steady state area under the plasma concentration-time curve over 
the dosing interval (τ); C max , maximum plasma concentration at steady state; CL cr , creatinine clearance; ss, steady-state </p>

<p>Figure 7 </p>

<p>Creatinine clearance maximum change from baseline vs. dolutegravir exposure (C max and AUC(0-τ))-SPRING-1 and SPRING-2. Each plot shows the indi-
vidual observed data (open circle) and the Loess line (dashed line). AUC(0-τ), steady-state area under the plasma concentration-time curve over the 
dosing interval (τ); C max , maximum plasma concentration at steady-state; CL cr , creatinine clearance; ss, steady-state </p>

<p>J. Zhang et al. </p>



<p>of the combination of DTG at 10 to 50 mg once daily with 
two active NRTIs. The lack of PK/PD relationship also indi-
cates that the antiviral effect of DTG (when in combina-
tion with two active NRTIs) is at maximum at doses of 
10 mg once daily or higher. No relationship between 
DTG exposure (AUC(0-τ), C max and C τ ) and the safety 
endpoints was observed, except for serum creatinine 
and CRCL, which appeared to be correlated with DTG 
exposure. DTG is known to inhibit organic cation 
transporter, OCT2, which mediates the tubular secre-
tion of creatinine in the proximal renal tubules [26]. 
The observed correlation between DTG exposure and 
serum creatinine/CRCL would be an expected finding 
based on OCT2 inhibition by DTG. However, given 
the magnitude of changes in these safety parameters, 
none of them was considered to be clinically significant, 
and therefore DTG dose adjustment by patient character-
istics is not necessary in HIV-infected treatment-naive 
adult patients. </p>

<p>Competing Interests </p>

<p>All authors have completed the Unified Competing 
Interest form at www.icmje.org/coi_disclosure.pdf (avail-
able on request from the corresponding author) and 
declare the submitted work was supported by ViiV 
Healthcare, JZ, IM, SP, SM and IS are employees of 
GlaxoSmithKline and hold stock options and SH and BS 
are employees of ICON. There are no other relationships 
or activities that could appear to have influenced the 
submitted work. 
Funding for this work was provided by ViiV Healthcare. 
All listed authors meet the criteria for authorship set forth 
by the International Committee for Medical Journal Editors. 
The authors attest that the funding source did not have an 
influence on the analysis and reporting of results. The au-
thors wish to acknowledge the following individual for ed-
itorial assistance during the development of this 
manuscript: Jian Zong. </p>

<p>Contributors </p>

<p>Ivy H. Song designed and reviewed the analysis and 
prepared the manuscript. Jianping Zhang reviewed 
the data quality and analysis and prepared the manu-
script. Siobhán Hayes and Brian Sadler performed the 
analysis and prepared the manuscript. Ilisse Minto 
oversaw the data quality and reviewed the manuscript. 
Steve Piscitelli and Sherene Min were involved in the 
design of the clinical studies in which PK data used 
in this analysis were generated, and reviewed and 
contributed to interpretation of the analysis and devel-
opment of the manuscript. </p>

<p>PI statement </p>

<p>None of the authors is the principal investigator as this 
manuscript presents results from a meta-analysis using 
pooled pharmacokinetic data from multiple studies. </p>



<p>Population pharmacokinetics of dolutegravir in treatment-naive population </p>

<p>Br J Clin Pharmacol / 80:3 / 513 </p>



<p>J. Zhang et al. </p>

<p>514 / 80:3 / Br J Clin Pharmacol </p>

</text></tei>