<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4816035" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVES: Soluble CD163 (sCD163), a marker of Kupffer cell activation detectable in serum, correlates with inflammation and 
fibrosis in chronic viral hepatitis, but its role in nonalcoholic fatty liver disease is unknown. We hypothesized that sCD163 would 
correlate with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease activity and fibrosis. 
METHODS: Liver biopsies and serum were obtained from 145 obese subjects undergoing gastric bypass surgery. Subjects were 
divided into four groups based on fibrosis stage and nonalcoholic fatty liver disease activity score (NAS); Group 1: F0, NAS = 0; 
Group 2: Fo2, 0oNASo5; Group 3: NAS ≥ 5, Fo3; or Group 4: F ≥ 3, any NAS. Serum sCD163 and the monocyte/macrophage 
marker sCD14 were measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. Relationships between sCD163, sCD14, fibrosis stage, and 
NAS were examined. Area under the receiver operating charateristic for the diagnosis of nonalcoholic steatohepatitis based on the 
Clinical Research Network definition was calculated. 
RESULTS: sCD163 increased with progressive liver histology, with lowest values in normal histology and highest levels in those 
with nonalcoholic steatohepatitis and advanced fibrosis (Group 1: 552 ng/ml, Group 2: 721 ng/ml, Group 3: 803 ng/ml, and Group 
4:1,031; P = 0.001). sCD14 also differed significantly across groups (Group 1: 1,877 ng/ml, Group 2: 1632 ng/ml, Group 3: 1,706 
ng/ml, and Group 4: 2111; P = 0.008, respectively). sCD163 correlated with steatosis grade (Po0.001), lobular inflammation 
(P = 0.033), and hepatocyte ballooning (Po0.001). In a multivariable ordered logistic regression model, there was a significant 
association between every 100 ng/ml increase in sCD163 and higher fibrosis stage, with an odds ratio of 1.16 (95% confidence 
interval 1.02-1.31), P = 0.020. The odds ratios of the association between every 100 ng/ml increase in sCD163 and higher NAS was 
1.17 (95% confidence interval 1.04-1.32), P = 0.010. A sCD163-based predictive score demonstrated an area under the receiver 
operating charateristic of 0.70 (95% confidence interval: 0.58-0.82) for the diagnosis of nonalcoholic steatohepatitis. Soluble CD14 
did not correlate with fibrosis stage or NAS. 
CONCLUSIONS: In obese subjects, serum sCD163, but not sCD14, correlated with fibrosis stage and NAS. These data support a 
role for activated Kupffer cells in the pathogenesis of nonalcoholic steatohepatitis and fibrosis, and suggest potential clinical 
utility for assessment of sCD163 levels. 
In the United States, nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) 
afflicts~30% of the general population and is the leading cause 
of chronic liver disease. 
1 NAFLD encompasses a broad 
spectrum of disorders, ranging from simple steatosis to 
nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH), the progressive form of 
NAFLD that can lead to cirrhosis, 
2 hepatocellular carcinoma, 
and the need for transplantation. 
3-5 Distinguishing between 
simple steatosis and NASH, as well as the staging of NASH 
fibrosis requires histologic diagnosis via liver biopsy. Biopsies </p>

<p>are invasive, expensive, and can result in serious 
complications. 
6 Furthermore, they are subject to sampling error 
and interobserver variability. Therefore, there exists a need for 
accurate, non-invasive, and cost-effective testing to assist in 
risk stratification of NASH. 
Although hepatic steatosis is a hallmark of NAFLD, hepatic 
inflammation has a key role in the pathophysiology of NASH 
and fibrosis. 
7 The cause of this inflammation has long been 
debated, and may be directly due to free fatty acid or cholesterol 
accumulation within hepatocytes, 
8 microbial translocation from 
the gastrointestinal tract leading to intrahepatic immune cell </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Division of Gastroenterology, Department of Medicine, Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston, Massauchusetts, USA; 
2 Harvard Medical School, Boston, 
Massauchusetts, USA; 
3 School of Medicine and Medical Sciences, University College Dublin, Ireland; </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Biostatistics Center, Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston, 
Massauchusetts, USA; 
5 Department of Pathology, Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston, Massauchusetts, USA and 
6 Bon Secours Health Care System, Richmond, 
Virginia, USA 
Correspondence: Raymond T. Chung, MD, Liver Center, Division of Gastroenterology, Massachusetts General Hospital, 55 Fruit Street, Boston, Massauchusetts 02114, 
USA. E-mail: rtchung@partners.org </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>These authors contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>These authors contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>Received 31 March 2015; accepted 4 August 2015 </p>

<p>Citation: Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology (2015) 6, e114; doi:10.1038/ctg.2015.36 </p>

<p>&amp; 2015 the American College of Gastroenterology All rights reserved 2155-384X/15 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/ctg </p>

<p>activation, 
9 or alterations in gut microbiota. 
10 The ability to 
detect hepatic inflammation and distinguish steatosis from 
NASH non-invasively would allow for rapid diagnosis of NASH 
and monitoring of disease progression and response to therapy 
without the need for serial liver biopsies. Circulating monocyte-
macrophage associated proteins might serve as biomarkers for 
NASH. CD163 is a hemoglobin scavenger receptor that is 
expressed by cells of the monocyte-macrophage lineage. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>During cellular activation and inflammation, its soluble form 
(sCD163) is shed via proteolytic cleavage at the cell surface </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>and can be detected within serum or plasma. Kupffer cells, 
hepatic macrophages that have a key role in liver inflammation 
and fibrosis, express high levels of CD163 and represent over 
80% of tissue macrophages, 
13 raising the possibility that serum 
levels of sCD163 disproportionately reflect chronic hepatic 
inflammation. Indeed sCD163 has been examined in various 
liver conditions, including hepatitis C virus (HCV) and hepatitis 
B virus (HBV) infection. Recent work has shown sCD163 levels 
are elevated in patients with HCV-related cirrhosis compared 
with those with minimal or no fibrosis. 
14 Soluble CD163 has also 
been shown to correlate with inflammation, specifically hepatic 
activity index, and fibrosis among patients with chronic hepatitis 
B and C. 
15 In addition, in patients with cirrhosis of varying 
etiologies, elevated sCD163 levels are significantly associated 
with portal hypertension, Child-Pugh score, and model for end-
stage liver disease score. 
16,17 There is a paucity of data on 
sCD163 in NAFLD. One study of liver biopsies from children 
with NAFLD found an association between CD163 staining and 
the severity of steatosis and fibrosis. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Soluble CD14 (sCD14) is another more general marker of 
monocyte activation, lipopolysaccharide, and bacterial translo-
cation. CD14 is expressed on Kupffer cells and 
hepatocytes, 
19,20 and serum sCD14 is elevated in cirrhotic 
subjects with ascites and evidence of bacterial translocation. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>In a recent study of 113 subjects with NAFLD sCD14 correlated 
with histologic evidence of inflammation and fibrosis. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>To our knowledge, the roles of sCD163 and sCD14 have not 
been compared in liver disease, and more specifically have 
not been explored in NASH. We hypothesized that both 
sCD163 and sCD14 would correlate with hepatic inflammation 
and fibrosis, but sCD163 would have a stronger correlation 
with fibrosis and inflammation because of its relative specificity 
for the activation of Kupffer cells, which have a key role in liver 
injury and inflammation. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Cohort Selection. We performed a cross-sectional analysis 
of serum sCD163, sCD14, and hepatic histology. Liver 
biopsies and serum samples were obtained from patients 
undergoing gastric bypass surgery at Bon Secours Health 
System in Richmond, VA. This study was approved by the 
Bon Secours Health System and Partners Institutional 
Review Boards, and all patients gave written consent before 
participation. Standard of care core liver biopsies and serum 
samples were obtained at time of gastrbypass surgery. 
Inclusion criteria included age ≥ 18 years of age, liver biopsy 
at the time of surgery and ability to provide informed consent. 
Exclusion criteria included infection with HBV, HCV or HIV, or </p>

<p>other causes of chronic liver disease and significant alcohol 
consumption (defined by 41 drink/day in women or 2 drinks/ 
day in men). 
Liver biopsies were reviewed by a single blinded pathologist 
at Massachusetts General Hospital and scored for presence 
of fibrosis (modified Brunt stage, F0-F4) and assigned scores 
for grade of steatosis (grade 0 = o5% steatosis; 1 = 5-33%; 
2 = 34-66%; 3 = 466%), hepatocyte ballooning (0 = no bal-
looning; 1 = few; 2 = many), and lobular inflammation per 
200 × (0 = no foci; 1 = o2 foci; 2 = 2-4 foci; 3 = 44 foci). </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Biopsies considered insufficient (o15 mm in length or o10 
portal tracts) were excluded. NAFLD activity score (NAS) 
ranges from 0 to 8 and is a sum of the scores for steatosis 
grade, lobular inflammation, and hepatocyte ballooning. 
Baseline demographics, including age, gender, and race, as 
well as baseline clinical and laboratory values were collected 
on all patients. 
Subjects were divided into four groups: Group 1, normal 
histology with NAS = 0 and F = 0, Group 2 (0oNASo5, Fo3); 
Group 3, (NAS ≥ 5, Fo3); and Group 4, advanced fibrosis 
(F ≥ 3, any NAS). 
NASH was defined based on the Clinical Research Network 
recommendations as having a score of 1 or greater in each of 
the three components of the NAS score: steatosis, hepatocyte 
ballooning, and lobular inflammation. 
24 This definition pro-
vides similar categorization as the recently described FLIP 
algorithm, 
25 but the decision tree was not used by pathologists 
during specimen analysis. Subjects were divided into three 
groups based on NASH: Group 1, normal, obese subjects 
(steatosis, lobular inflammation and hepatocyte ballooning all 
= 0); Group 2, simple steatosis (steatosis score ≥ 1 with 
ballooning and/or lobular inflammation score o1) and group ; 
Group 3, NASH (steatosis score ≥ 1, hepatocyte ballooning 
≥ 1, and lobular inflammation ≥ 1). </p>

<p>Biochemical analysis. For all but eight patients, blood 
draws occurred on the day of gastric bypass surgery when 
liver tissue was obtained; seven patients had blood drawn 
within six months before surgery and one patient had blood 
drawn within one year before surgery. Blood from one 10-ml 
EDTA-coated tube was separated by centrifugation and 
serum was stored at − 80°C. Samples were thawed and 
serum sCD163 and sCD14 levels were batch analyzed in 
duplicate using the Quantikine enzyme-linked immunosor-
bent assay system (R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN). The 
mean assay coefficient of variance was 3.3% and 4.8% for 
sCD163 and sCD14, respectively. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Data are distributed normally and are 
therefore presented as mean ± s.d. Differences between 
multiple groups were compared using one-way analysis of 
variance (or χ 
2 test, and differences between two specific 
groups were compared using unpaired Student's t-tests. 
Spearman's rank correlation was used to assess the relation-
ship between sCD163 or sCD14 levels and histological fibrosis 
stage or NAS, whereas Pearson's correlation was used to 
assess the relationship between continuous variables. 
Univariate and multivariate ordered logistic regression 
analyses were performed with NAS or fibrosis stage as 
dependent variables and sCD163 or sCD14 as explanatory </p>

<p>CD163, Fibrosis and Disease Activity in NAFLD 
Mueller et al. </p>



<p>Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology </p>

<p>variables. These models generated odds ratios for a given 
fibrosis stage or NAS corresponding to specific increases in 
sCD163 or sCD14. These models included age, gender, race, 
diabetes, alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate amino-
transferase (AST), and bilirubin as covariates. 
We evaluated the prediction power of sCD163 plus ALT by 
calculating the receiver-operator characteristics (ROC) 
curves. We randomly partitioned the sample into two half-
samples, each containing 50% of the cases (Group 3) and 
50% of controls (Group 2). The first-half sample was used as 
the training set on which we fitted a logistic regression model 
and estimated the coefficients on sCD163 and ALT. 
26 We used 
the second half-sample as the validation set and calculated 
the ROC curve of the score based on the coefficients 
estimated from the training set. We calculated the area under 
the ROC curve (AUROC) for both the training and validation 
sets. The software <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., Cary, 
NC) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 17.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL) were 
used for the analyses. P values o0.05 were considered 
significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>In this cohort, 145 patients who underwent gastric bypass 
surgery had samples available and were included in the 
analyses. There were 20 patients with normal liver histology 
(Group 1), 78 patients with NAS o5, Fo3 (Group 2), 37 
patients with NAS ≥ 5, Fo3 (Group 3), and 10 patients with 
advanced fibrosis or cirrhosis (Group 4). Subjects had NAS 
ranging from 0 to 7 and fibrosis stages ranging from 0 to 4. 
The characteristics of the 145 patients and their respective 
groups are shown in Table 1. Patients with advanced fibrosis 
(Group 4) were more likely to be male, older, white, diabetic, 
and had significantly elevated ALT, AST, and total bilirubin 
compared with those with normal histology (Group 1). 
Differences in sCD163 and sCD14 levels between two groups 
are shown in Supplementary Table 1 online. 
In a univariate ordered logistic regression model, age, male 
gender, white race, diabetes status, ALT, AST, sCD163 levels, 
and sCD14 levels all predicted increasing fibrosis stage 
(Po0.05 for all analyses; results not shown). Similarly, </p>

<p>diabetes status, male gender, white race, ALT, AST, and 
sCD163 levels predicted increasing NAS (Po0.05 for all 
analyses; results not shown). </p>

<p>sCD163. Mean levels of sCD163 in Group 2 (Figure 1; 721 g/ml 
[261]), Group 3, (803 ng/ml [350]), and Group 4 (1031ng/ml 
[529]) differed significantly from controls (Table 2; Group 1, 
552 ng/ml [206]; P = 0.009, P = 0.005, and P = 0.001, </p>

<p>Table 1 Baseline characteristics of subjects </p>

<p>Group 1 NAS = 0, F = 0 
(n = 20) </p>

<p>Group 2 0oNASo5, Fo3 
(n = 78) </p>

<p>Group 3 NAS ≥ 5, Fo3 
(n = 37) </p>

<p>Group 4 Any NAS, F ≥ 3 
(n = 10) </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>Diabetes (n, %) 
1 (5.0) 
29 (37.2) 
17 (45.9) 
8 (80.0) 
o0.001 
Male (n, %) 
1 (5.0) 
14 (17.9) 
9 (24.3) 
5 (50.0) 
0.028 
Smoker (n, %) 
2 (10.0) 
7 (9.0) 
3 (8.1) 
2 (20.0) 
0.089 
White (n, %) 
7 (35.0) 
57 (75.0) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>30 (81.1) 
10 (100.0) 
0.001 
Age (years) 
39.6 (9.0) 
46.3 (11.4) 
43.6 (11.6) 
55.7 (9.1) 
0.002 
BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
46.3 (5.7) 
45.8 (6.8) 
49.1 (7.9) 
47.0 (4.2) 
0.117 
ALT (IU/l) 
40 (29) 
41 (17) 
65 (31) 
97 (86) 
o0.001 
AST (IU/l) 
17 (10) 
23 (14) 
38 (26) 
66 (57) 
o0.001 
Total billirubin 
(mg/dl) </p>

<p>0.44 (0.25) 
0.48 (0.23) 
0.49 (0.24) 
0.65 (0.28) 
0.139 </p>

<p>sCD163 ng/ml 
552 (206) 
721 (261) 
803 (350) 
1031 (529) 
0.001 
sCD14 ng/ml 
1877 (336) 
1632 (497) 
1706 (491) 
2111 (262) 
0.008 </p>

<p>AST, aspartate aminotransferase; BMI, body mass index; F, modified brunt fibrosis score; NAS, Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease activity score. Data are mean (s.d.). </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Two subjects missing race information. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Differences in soluble CD163 (sCD163) and sCD14 (sCD14) across all 
four groups. Although both sCD163 and sCD14 were significantly different across 
groups, only sCD163 increased across Group 1 to Group 4 and was significantly 
higher in all groups compared with controls. P values are for ANOVA. ANOVA, 
analysis of variance. </p>

<p>CD163, Fibrosis and Disease Activity in NAFLD 
Mueller et al. </p>



<p>Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology </p>

<p>respectively) and across all groups (P = 0.001). In addition, 
mean sCD163 levels were significantly elevated in the 
advanced fibrosis group vs. the steatosis group (P = 0.003). 
In the univariate analysis, sCD163 correlated with both 
fibrosis stage and NAS (Figure 2a; ρ = 0.277, P = 0.001 and 
ρ = 0.309, Po0.001, respectively) and also correlated with 
each of the components of NAS, including steatosis 
(ρ = 0.307, Po0.001), lobular inflammation (ρ = 0.177, 
P = 0.033), and hepatocyte ballooning (ρ = 0.296, Po0.001, 
Figure 3). sCD163 also correlated with traditional biochemical </p>

<p>markers of inflammation such as AST and ALT (r = 0.295 and 
0.356, respectively, Po0.0001). 
In a multivariable ordered logistic regression model of 
fibrosis that included age, gender, race, diabetes status, body 
mass index, ALT, AST, bilirubin, and sCD163, for every 100 ng/ 
ml increase in sCD163 the odds ratiofor increasing fibrosis 
score was 1.16 (95% confidence interval (CI) 1.03-1.32, 
P = 0.018). In this model, race and diabetes status also 
independently predicted increasing fibrosis (Supplementary 
Table 2). Similarly, for every 100ng/ml increase in sCD163 the </p>

<p>Table 2 Baseline characteristics of subjects </p>

<p>Group 5 Normal (n = 21) 
Group 6 NAFLD (n = 49) 
Group 7 NASH (n = 75) 
P value </p>

<p>Diabetes (n, %) 
2 (9.5) 
14 (28.6) 
39 (52.0) 
o0.001 
Male (n, %) 
1 (4.8) 
8 (16.3) 
20 (26.7) 
0.063 
Smoker (n, %) 
3 (14.3) 
4 (8.2) 
7 (9.3) 
0.772 
White (n, %) 
8 (38.1) 
38 (77.6)* 
58 (77.3) 
0.003 
Age (years) 
40.9 (10.7) 
46.9 (12.0) 
45.5 (11.1) 
0.130 
BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
46.4 (5.6) 
45.0 (6.6) 
49.1 (7.9) 
0.048 
ALT (IU/l) 
39 (29) 
42 (26) 
60 (40) 
0.006 
AST (IU/l) 
18 (10) 
24 (20) 
35 (29) 
0.006 
Total billirubin (mg/dl) 
0.46 (0.26) 
0.47 (0.20) 
0.50 (0.26) 
0.675 
sCD163 ng/ml 
555 (201) 
691 (270) 
824 (350) 
0.001 
sCD14 ng/ml 
1901 (347) 
1554 (411) 
1773 (524) 
0.007 </p>

<p>ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; BMI, body mass index. Data are mean (s.d.). P values are for χ 
2 test or unpaired t-test. </p>

<p>Figure 2 (a) Soluble CD163 (sCD163) and (b) soluble CD14 (sCD14) compared with fibrosis stage and NAFLD Activity Score (NAS) score. Serum sCD163 correlated with 
both fibrosis stage and NAS score, whereas sCD14 did not. P values are for Spearman's rank correlation. NAFLD, nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. </p>

<p>CD163, Fibrosis and Disease Activity in NAFLD 
Mueller et al. </p>



<p>Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology </p>

<p>odds ratio for increasing NAS was 1.17 (1.04-1.32), P = 0.010, 
and race, diabetes status, and body mass index also predicted 
increasing NAFLD activity (Supplementary Table 3). 
Moreover, sCD163 was an independent predictor of NAS 
≥ 5 among patients without advanced fibrosis, as our sCD163-
based predictive score (which included sCD163 and ALT </p>

<p>levels) demonstrated an area under the receiver operating 
characteristic curve (AUROC) of 0.75 (95% CI: 0.61-0.88). 
The area under the ROC curve (AUROC) in the validation set 
was not different from the AUROC in the training set. Figure 4a 
and b show the ROC curves in the training set and the 
validation set, respectively. Only two variables, sCD163 and 
ALT were included in the model due to a limited sample size. 
When those with advanced fibrosis were included in the 
analysis, our sCD163-based predictive score demonstrated 
an AUROC of 0.76 (95% CI: 0.68-0.85) for NAS ≥ 5. 
In a second analysis, there were 21 patients with normal 
liver histology (Group 5), 49 patients with steatosis (Group 6), 
and 75 patients with NASH (Group 7). The characteristics of </p>

<p>Figure 3 Association of soluble CD163 (sCD163) with each component of the 
nonalcoholic fatty liver disease Activity Score (NAS). Serum sCD163 correlated with 
all three individual components of the NAS-steatosis, lobular inflammation and 
ballooning. sCD14 did not (data not shown). P values are for Spearman's rank 
correlation. </p>

<p>Training Set ROC Curve </p>

<p>Area Under the Curve = 0.7465 </p>

<p>Validation Set ROC Curve </p>

<p>Area Under the Curve = 0.7764 </p>

<p>Figure 4 Training and validation receiver-operator characteristic (ROC) curves 
for model using sCD163 and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) as a predictor for 
nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH). Receiver-operator characteristic (ROC) curves 
were obtained using sCD163 and ALTas a predictor for the presence of NASH in both 
a training (4A) and validation (4B) selection of patients from the cohort.sCD163, 
soluble CD163. </p>

<p>CD163, Fibrosis and Disease Activity in NAFLD 
Mueller et al. </p>



<p>Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology </p>

<p>the 145 patients and their respective groups are shown in 
Table 2. Diabetes status, gender, age, race, ALT, AST, 
sCD163, and sCD14 levels were significantly different 
between groups. Levels of sCD163 were significantly different 
between each group and are shown in Figure 5. Soluble 
CD163 levels were lower in normal individuals (mean 555 
[201] ng/ml) compared with those with NAFLD (mean 691 
[270] ng/ml, P = 0.043) and NASH (mean 824 [350] ng/ml, 
P = 0.001). Furthermore, sCD163 levels were significantly 
different between NASH subjects and those with steatosis 
(P = 0.026). Our sCD163-based predictive score (which 
included sCD163 and ALT levels) demonstrated an area 
under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUROC) of 
0.70 (95% CI: 0.58-0.82) for the diagnosis of NASH (NASH 
vs. non NASH) and an AUROC of 0.66 (95% CI: 0.52-0.80) in 
a NASH vs. steatosis analysis. Furthermore, when the eight 
patients that did not have their blood drawn on day of gastric 
bypass were excluded, the NASH vs. non-NASH and NASH 
vs. steatosis AUROC improved to 0.73 (95% CI: 0.61-0.85) 
and 0.73 (95% CI: 0.60-0.86), respectively. </p>

<p>sCD14. Mean sCD14 levels were elevated in Group 4 
(Figure 1; 2111 ng/ml [562]) when compared with Groups 1 
(1877 ng/ml [336]), 2 (1632 ng/ml [497]), and 3 (1706 ng/ml 
[491) (Supplementary Table 1; P = 0.065, P = 0.004, and 
P = 0.016, respectively). sCD14 levels differed significantly 
between the steatosis group and controls (P = 0.040). In 
univariate analysis sCD14 differed significantly across groups 
(Figure 1, P = 0.008, respectively). 
In contrast to sCD163, sCD14 levels did not correlate with 
fibrosis stage or NAS (Figure 2b; ρ = 0.139, P = 0.095 and 
ρ = 0.079, P = 0.346, respectively) and did not predict increas-
ing fibrosis stage or NAS in the ordered logistic regression 
model (results not shown). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we found a significant association between 
sCD163, NASH, and fibrosis. This association remained </p>

<p>significant after adjustment for age, gender, race, presence 
of diabetes, and aminotransferase levels; indeed, in a multi-
variate logistic regression model only sCD163, white race, and 
presence of diabetes were significantly associated with both 
NAS and fibrosis stage. In contrast another widely used 
circulating marker of macrophage activation, sCD14, was not 
associated with NAS or fibrosis stage, consistent with its 
reflection of overall macrophage status rather than liver 
specific status. 
These data have significance for the understanding of the 
pathophysiology of NAFLD and fibrosis. First, the cohort of 
patients with NAS o5 (Group 2) had significantly higher 
sCD163 than controls (Group 1), suggesting that early hepatic 
lipid accumulation may be associated with Kupffer cell 
activation and inflammation, even potentially before it is visible 
histologically. Second, the level of sCD163 was even higher in 
those with NAS ≥ 5 and higher yet in those with advanced 
fibrosis, suggesting ongoing and increasing Kupffer cell/ 
macrophage activation throughout all stages of NAFLD. This 
activation persists even in those with advanced fibrosis. This 
confirms the recent study by Kazankov et al. 
27 who also found 
sCD163 to be elevated in NAS ≥ 5 compared with those with 
NASo5 as well as in patients with bridging fibrosis compared 
with lower fibrosis stages. Therefore, preventing or inhibiting 
Kupffer cell activation may be a rational therapeutic strategy 
for all stages of NAFLD. 
The specific relationship between sCD163, fibrosis and 
NAS as compared with sCD14 is striking. Both are markers of 
macrophage activation, and both have been associated with 
tissue inflammation (e.g., carotid artery disease in HIV-HCV 
coinfection). 
28 Although sCD14 has been associated with 
disease progression in HBV/HCV, 
29 only sCD163 has been 
associated with fibrosis in HBV, HCV and HIV/HCV 
coinfection 
14,15,30 as well as acute liver failure 
31 and portal 
hypertension. 
32 CD14 is a co-receptor for lipopolysaccharide 
along with toll-like receptor 4, and is expressed primarily on 
macrophages, but also neutrophils and dendritic cells. Its shed 
form, sCD14, appears to be a general marker of inflammation. 
In contrast, CD163 is highly expressed on Kupffer cells, and 
sCD163 is significantly higher in the hepatic veins compared 
with the portal veins. 
17 Taken together these findings suggest 
that sCD163 is a marker of macrophage activation with a 
higher sensitivity for liver injury compared with other soluble 
markers. Soluble CD163 is not uniquely specific for the liver, 
however; elevated sCD163 is also associated with many 
conditions of immune activation: coronary plaque burden in 
HIV infection, 
33 rheumatoid arthritis activity, 
34 and, most 
interestingly in obesity. 
35,36 The fact that in our study of obese 
patients sCD163 was further increased in those with 
significant liver disease demonstrates the potential utility of 
sCD163 in this population, and underlines the role of 
inflammation in the pathogenesis of NAFLD. 
Although sCD163 alone cannot be used as a definitive 
diagnostic test for NASH, as part of a panel with other 
predictors of steatohepatitis, it may serve as a useful screen-
ing tool. Currently the American Association for the Study of 
Liver Disease practice guidelines suggest considering biopsy 
for NAFLD patients at the highest risk of developing NASH, 
based on the presence of metabolic syndrome and the NAFLD 
fibrosis score. 
37 Another biomarker, circulating cytokeratin 18, </p>

<p>Figure 5 Mean sCD163 levels across normal, steatosis, and NASH groups. 
P = 0.001. NASH, nonalcoholic steatohepatitis. </p>

<p>CD163, Fibrosis and Disease Activity in NAFLD 
Mueller et al. </p>



<p>Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology </p>

<p>has been suggested in one study to be markedly increased in 
NASH patients when compared with patients with simple 
steatosis (AUROC = 0.82, 95% CI: 0.78-0.88), 
4 but other 
studies have not corroborated its predictive value. </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>There are some limitations to this study. The data are cross-
sectional, and therefore exploratory, as individuals were not 
followed after gastric bypass surgery. Further longitudinal data 
are required to determine whether sCD163 levels change with 
disease regression or progression. Our cohort was limited to 
those with obesity warranting weight loss surgery and further 
exploration of the value of sCD163 in non-obese individuals with 
NAFLD as well as in the general NAFLD population is needed. 
Nonetheless, levels of serum sCD163 in those with NAS = 0 
(Group 5) are similar to those reported in other "healthy control" 
groups, 
39 supporting the role of sCD163 as a specific marker of 
hepatic inflammation. The use of obese controls in this study 
and including body mass index as a covariate aims to eliminate 
obesity as a potential confounder. Finally, only 10 subjects had 
advanced fibrosis, and 5 of these had NAS scores consistent 
with NASH, suggesting that the association of sCD163 and 
fibrosis scores may be confounded by concomitant steatohe-
patitis. However, previous studies 
14,15 have reported a correla-
tion between sCD163 and advanced fibrosis or cirrhosis. 
Furthermore, although random division of the original cohort 
into a training and validation set for the AUROC analysis is a 
popular strategy when a true validation cohort is unavailable, </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>this method does not replace an independent validation 
cohort. Unfortunately, a true validation cohort was unavailable, 
so this strategy is our best attempt to reduce the bias 
associated with a single study cohort. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>In summary, serum sCD163, but not sCD14, correlated with 
overall NAS score, histologic elements of steatohepatitis, and 
fibrosis stage in patients with NAFLD. The assay for sCD163 is 
rapid, inexpensive, and highly reproducible. Measurement of 
sCD163 may have a role, together with other assessments, in 
the diagnosis and staging of NAFLD/NASH. Further studies 
addressing its prognostic value in other patient populations as 
well as the effect of therapeutic interventions (such as weight 
loss) are needed. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>Guarantor of the article: Raymond T. Chung, MD. 
Specific author contributions: J.L.M. performed the 
experiments, analyzed the data and wrote the manuscript. E. 
R.F. performed the experiments, analyzed the data and wrote 
the manuscript. H.Z. analyzed the data and wrote the 
manuscript. J.M. performed the experiments and analyzed the 
data. A.K. performed the experiments and analyzed the data. 
N.A. performed the experiments and analyzed the data. L.Y.K. 
performed the experiments and analyzed the data. L.G. 
performed the experiments. K.E.C. planned the study, 
analyzed the data and wrote the manuscript. R.T.C. planned 
the study, analyzed the data and wrote the manuscript. 
Financial support: The following authors would like to 
acknowledge NIH grants; these grants were not connected 
specifically to this project but contributed to the work. </p>

<p>Raymond T. Chung NIH K24 DK078772. Kathleen E Corey: 
NIH K23DK099422. Jessica L. Mueller: NIH T32 DK007191. 
Eoin R. Feeney: NIH/NIAID 5P30AI060354-09. Lindsay Y. 
King: NIH T32 DK007191. 
Potential competing interests: None. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments. We would like to thank the patients and staff at the Bons </p>

<p>Secours Health System in Ricmond, VA. </p>

<p>Study Highlights </p>

<p>WHAT IS CURRENT KNOWLEDGE </p>

<p>✓ Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease is the leading cause of 
chronic liver disease. </p>

<p>✓ Diagnosis and staging usually requires a liver biopsy. </p>

<p>WHAT IS NEW HERE </p>

<p>✓ Soluble CD163 (sCD163) is a macrophage marker 
associated with steatohepatitis and fibrosis in nonalcoholic 
fatty liver disease. 
✓ Another macrophage marker sCD14 was not associated 
with fibrosis or steatohepatitis. 
✓ sCD163 could be used to help stage nonalcoholic fatty liver 
disease without a biopsy. </p>





<p>Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology </p>



<p>Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology is an open-
access journal published by Nature Publishing Group. 
This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or 
other third party material in this article are included in the article's 
Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; 
if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, 
users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to 
reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on the Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology website (http://www.nature.com/ctg) </p>

<p>CD163, Fibrosis and Disease Activity in NAFLD 
Mueller et al. </p>



<p>Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology </p>

</text></tei>