<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4915762" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Concussive events frequently occur in high impact sports such as North American football. The long term </p>

<p>effects of concussive events on physical and psychological wellbeing are the focus of ongoing research. The purpose of </p>

<p>this study was to determine if concussive events increase the incidence of depression in active semi-professional and </p>

<p>professional North American football players. </p>

<p>Methods: An anonymous online survey was sent to 200 players to collect the following self-reported data: position played, </p>

<p>years played, number of concussions sustained and subsequent depressive symptoms using the Center for Epidemiologic </p>

<p>Studies Depression (CESD-R) scale. An independent T-test was used to determine differences in the number of con-</p>

<p>cussive events in those with CESD-R scores ＜16 vs. ≥16, where scores ≥16 are indicative of a depressed state. Likewise, </p>

<p>an independent T-test was used to compare CESD-R scores between players with ≥3 concussions vs. ≤2. </p>

<p>Results: Individuals with a CESD-R score ≥16, sustained a significantly greater number of concussions (3.8 vs. 1.6) </p>

<p>than those who scored ＜16 (p ＜ 0.001). Further analysis also revealed significantly higher CESD-R scores in players </p>

<p>who had sustained ≥3 concussions (24.0 vs. 15.6) than those with ≤2 (p ＜ 0.05). </p>

<p>Conclusion: Within the parameters of this study, players that were classified as depressed had sustained significantly </p>

<p>more concussions compared to those who were not classified as depressed. Further, multiple concussive events (≥3) </p>

<p>appears to increase symptoms of depression. </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/4.0) which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, dis-
tribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is 
properly cited. </p>

<p>In the sporting community, and especially North American </p>

<p>football (football), a new importance has been placed on </p>

<p>properly diagnosing and treating concussion injuries as a re-</p>

<p>sult of evidence indicating that these mild traumatic brain </p>

<p>injuries can have lasting neurological effects which may lead </p>

<p>to degenerative diseases such as early Alzheimers and </p>

<p>Parkinson's syndrome as well as symptoms of depression </p>

<p>[1,2]. On an annual basis football-related concussions alone </p>

<p>occur to an estimated 43,200 to 67,200 athletes [3]. </p>

<p>Professional football players in the National Football League </p>

<p>(NFL) sustained a total of 758 concussions during the </p>

<p>2002-2007 seasons [4] with 152 players having sustained </p>

<p>multiple concussions [5]. Recently Baron et al. [6] observed </p>

<p>Journal of </p>

<p>Lifestyle 
Medicine </p>



<p>Journal of Lifestyle Medicine Vol. 6, No. 1, March 2016 </p>

<p>in retired NFL football players (n = 2,552), a 5-fold increase </p>

<p>in prevalence of mild cognitive disorders and a threefold in-</p>

<p>crease in prevalence of significant memory problems in play-</p>

<p>ers who experienced three or more concussions verses those </p>

<p>who sustain fewer than three concussions [6]. Although un-</p>

<p>able to establish cause-effect, Baron et al. [6] did provide </p>

<p>additional evidence supporting the association between multi-</p>

<p>ple concussions and increased risk of neurodegenerative </p>

<p>diseases. </p>

<p>Casson et al. [7] recently found from a sample of retired </p>

<p>NFL players (n = 45) that 32 had sustained three or more </p>

<p>concussions and of these players, 13 were found to have </p>

<p>suffered from depression. In a similar study Didenbani et </p>

<p>al. [8] examined depression symptoms and concussions in re-</p>

<p>tired NFL players. The results indicated that there was a </p>

<p>significant positive relation between number of sustained </p>

<p>player concussions and cognitive depressive symptoms. It </p>

<p>should be noted, in the two aforementioned studies [7,8] </p>

<p>that the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II) was used to as-</p>

<p>sess depression at the time of the study, hence reflecting </p>

<p>current state or symptoms of depression, providing little </p>

<p>temporal information regarding the relationship of depres-</p>

<p>sion and concussion. </p>

<p>Schwenk et al. [9] examined depression and pain in re-</p>

<p>tired NFL players. The results indicated that retired NFL </p>

<p>players experienced symptoms of depression at levels con-</p>

<p>sistent with the general population. The instrument used to </p>

<p>assess depressive symptoms at the time of the study was the </p>

<p>PHQ-9, a screening questionnaire known for a significant </p>

<p>rate of false positives [10,11]. </p>

<p>An additional pair of recent studies have focused on con-</p>

<p>cussion and depression symptoms in retired NFL players </p>

<p>[1,12]. The initial study by Guskiewicz at al. [1] focused </p>

<p>on the relationship of concussion and being diagnosed with </p>

<p>depression in retired NFL players (n = 2552). The results </p>

<p>of the study indicated that players who had sustained 1-2 </p>

<p>concussions were 1.5 times more likely to be diagnosed with </p>

<p>depression than players who had not sustained a concussion. </p>

<p>Further, players who reported ≥3 concussion were 3 times </p>

<p>more likely to be diagnosed with depression then players </p>

<p>who had not sustained a concussion. The purpose of the sec-</p>

<p>ond study by Kerr et al. [12] was a nine-year follow up </p>

<p>to the Guskiewicz at al. [1] report which attempted to pro-</p>

<p>spectively determine the effects of concussion occurrence on </p>

<p>clinical diagnosis of depression in retired NFL players (n = </p>

<p>1044). During the 9-year study period 106 players reported </p>

<p>being diagnosed as clinically depressed. Additionally, the re-</p>

<p>sults of the study indicated that there was a strong dose re-</p>

<p>sponse relationship between the number of self-reported </p>

<p>concussions and 9-year clinical diagnosis of depression. </p>

<p>It should be noted that in the two aforementioned studies </p>

<p>[1,12] that the method of determining depression occur-</p>

<p>rence was based on the investigators asking the players </p>

<p>"Have you ever been told by a physician or health care pro-</p>

<p>fessional that you had/have any of the following con-</p>

<p>ditions?" Where one of the conditions enquired about was </p>

<p>depression [12]. The researchers in these studies did not </p>

<p>state who the health care professional was (general practi-</p>

<p>tioner or psychiatrist, etc.). There is lack of consensus be-</p>

<p>tween how psychiatrists and general practice (GP) physi-</p>

<p>cians diagnose depression [13] where the majority of pa-</p>

<p>tients with depression are treated by GP physicians [14]. </p>

<p>The lack of shared understanding between psychiatrists and </p>

<p>GP physicians regarding the diagnosis of depression is be-</p>

<p>yond the scope of this manuscript. However what is im-</p>

<p>portant is that there is a clear lack of inter-rater reliability </p>

<p>regarding the diagnosis of depression and an issue that must </p>

<p>be kept in mind when attempting to interpret the results of </p>

<p>the studies in question [1,12]. Further confounding the issue </p>

<p>of clinical depression diagnosis has to do with the explosion </p>

<p>of individuals diagnosed with depression during the time </p>

<p>frame of the Guskiewicz at al. [1] and Kerr et al. [12] stud-</p>

<p>ies [15]. The clinical diagnosis of depression among </p>

<p>Medicare patients increased by 100% between 1992-95 and </p>

<p>2002-05 [16]. According to Dowrick [15], this increase in </p>

<p>depression diagnosis rates is not due to GP's improved abil-</p>

<p>ity to identify depression disorders but rather a result of </p>

<p>"medicalising of unhappiness", a likely outcome of the </p>

<p>broadening of depressive disorders introduced by the </p>

<p>DSM-IV [17]. </p>

<p>Psychology based research has fallen under considerable </p>

<p>scrutiny given the poor rate of reproducibility, a "defining </p>

<p>feature of science" [18]. A study published in Science in </p>

<p>august of 2015 [18] indicated that in attempt to replicate </p>

<p>100 experimental and correlational psychology studies that </p>

<p>only 36% of the replicant studies demonstrated significant </p>



<p>James Pryor, et al : Depression and Concussions in Football Players </p>

<p>results compared to 97% of the original studies that had re-</p>

<p>ported significant results. Given the limitations of the stud-</p>

<p>ies expressed above and concerns of poor replication of psy-</p>

<p>chology research in general, we felt that the potential rela-</p>

<p>tionship between concussions and depression in professional </p>

<p>football players warrants continued investigation. </p>

<p>Therefore, the purpose of this study was to assess the dif-</p>

<p>ference in average number of concussive events among ac-</p>

<p>tive professional and semi-professional football players </p>

<p>meeting criteria for clinically significant depression vs </p>

<p>non-clinically significant depression using the Center for </p>

<p>Epidemiologic Studies Depression scale (CESD-R) [19]. </p>

<p>Where depression is defined as a CESD-R score of 16 or </p>

<p>greater. Further, a secondary purpose was to investigate the </p>

<p>CESD-R scores between players with ≥3 concussions with </p>

<p>those having sustained ≤2 concussions. It was hypothesized </p>

<p>that if the relationship between concussion and depression </p>

<p>suggested by prior research robustly exits [1,7,8,12], then </p>

<p>it would be supported by the results of the current study. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>1. Participants </p>

<p>The sample population for this study was active semi-pro-</p>

<p>fessional and professional football players. All participation </p>

<p>was voluntary and all participants read the informed consent </p>

<p>prior to answering any research questions. The recruitment </p>

<p>of semi-professional player-participants was conducted in </p>

<p>two leagues: The Western Washington Football Alliance </p>

<p>(WWFA) and Pacific Football League (PFL). Professional </p>

<p>player-participants were recruited from various NFL teams. </p>

<p>Only current football players were recruited. </p>

<p>1) Instruments </p>

<p>A web-based Qualtrics Survey was used to question par-</p>

<p>ticipants on the following: league (Professional or </p>

<p>Semi-Professional), position played, years played, if a con-</p>

<p>cussion has ever been sustained and if so, and how many. </p>

<p>If the participant answered "no" to having ever received a </p>

<p>concussion, the survey was terminated and the participant </p>

<p>was excluded from further questioning and subsequent data </p>

<p>analysis. If the participant responded "yes", they were then </p>

<p>asked to answer a number of questions from the Center for </p>

<p>Epidemiologic Studies Depression (CESD-R) Scale [19], </p>

<p>which consists of 20 closed-ended survey questions in which </p>

<p>participants answer questions by choosing one of four re-</p>

<p>sponse options: 0) rarely or none, 1) some or little of the </p>

<p>time, 2) occasionally or a moderate amount, 3) most or all </p>

<p>of the time. Example questions include: "I felt depressed" </p>

<p>or "I felt happy". Results are calculated using a 0-3 scoring </p>

<p>system and individual question scores are totaled (0-60 pos-</p>

<p>sible). Score classifications are as follows: 0 no depression </p>

<p>exists; 1-16 little or no depression and not clinically sig-</p>

<p>nificant; 17-49 mild depression; 50-60 major depression. </p>

<p>CESD-R questions were asked within the context of how </p>

<p>the participant felt in the days and weeks after a concussive </p>

<p>event. The CESD-R scale has been reported to be a valid </p>

<p>instrument, with high reliability (0.85-0.95), when com-</p>

<p>pared to other measures of depression [20]. </p>

<p>2. Procedures </p>

<p>The current study and the participant informed consent </p>

<p>document were approved by the University Institutional </p>

<p>Review Board (IRB) as being in accordance with the ethical </p>

<p>standards of human experimentation (institutional and na-</p>

<p>tional) and with the Helsinki Declaration of 1975 (as re-</p>

<p>vised in 2008). All participants read the IRB approved elec-</p>

<p>tronic informed consent document; consent was given by </p>

<p>clicking an "agree" tab which then linked the participant </p>

<p>to the survey. All responses were anonymous with no identi-</p>

<p>fying information attached to any portion of the survey </p>

<p>results. Semi-Professional and Professional football players </p>

<p>were recruited via two methods. Semi-Professional players </p>

<p>were contacted through a social media site with a letter con-</p>

<p>taining information about the topic, the research procedures </p>

<p>and information regarding the voluntary and anonymous </p>

<p>nature of study participation. Professional players were con-</p>

<p>tacted via personal connections of the Principle Investigator </p>

<p>(PI). The PI contacted former or current NFL players </p>

<p>whom he had a personal connection/acquaintance with. </p>

<p>These individuals were given informative recruitment letters </p>

<p>to hand out to interested current NFL players. In order to </p>

<p>participate in the study, players must have sustained at least </p>

<p>one concussion. Within the context of the present study the </p>

<p>term "concussion", is defined as a direct blow to the head, </p>

<p>face, or neck with an "impulsive force transmitted to the </p>



<p>Journal of Lifestyle Medicine Vol. 6, No. 1, March 2016 </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographics of participants by group </p>

<p>Professional Semi-Professional </p>

<p>Participants 
Participants with Concussion 
Age (Years) 
Concussion Range 
Years Playing 
Offense 
Wide Receiver 
Running Back 
Quarterback 
Defense 
Defensive Line 
Linebacker 
Safety </p>

<p>5 
2 
26.6 ± 3.3 
4 ± 2 
10 </p>

<p>1 
0 
0 </p>

<p>1 
0 
0 </p>

<p>46 
25 
25.9 ± 5.1 
2.6 ± 4.1 
10.9 ± 8.1 </p>

<p>7 
4 
4 </p>

<p>9 
7 
5 </p>

<p>Note </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>: Professional football player, Semi-Professional football 
player. 
Note </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>: Some Semi-Professional football players were multi-position. </p>

<p>Table 2. CESD-R scores: 2 or fewer concussions vs. 3 or more 
concussions </p>

<p>2 or fewer 
concussions 
(n = 16) </p>

<p>3 or more 
concussions 
(n = 11) </p>

<p>Average CESD-R Score 
N scoring CESD-R ≥16 </p>

<p>15.6 
5 </p>

<p>24.0* 
11 </p>

<p>Note: CESD-R score ≥16 is criteria for clinical depression, 
*Significantly greater: p = 0.03. </p>

<p>Table 3. Average number of Concussions: CESD-R Score 16 or 
greater vs. less than 16 </p>

<p>CESD-R score 
≥16 (n = 16) </p>

<p>CESD-R score 
＜16 (n = 11) </p>

<p>Average number of concussions 
3.8* 
1.6 </p>

<p>*Significantly greater: p = 0.0004. </p>

<p>head that may result in neuropathological changes and may </p>

<p>or may not involve a loss of consciousness" [21]. Players </p>

<p>that chose to participate were given a link to the Qualtrics </p>

<p>Survey regarding their past concussion history and the </p>

<p>CESD-R scale. </p>

<p>3. Statistical analyses </p>

<p>An independent t-test was used to find if players who </p>

<p>scored ≥16 on the CESD-R test had incurred a greater </p>

<p>number of concussions compared with those who scored </p>

<p>＜16. An independent t-test was also used to determine if </p>

<p>those who have a history of three or more concussions scor-</p>

<p>ed higher on the CESD-R survey compared to players who </p>

<p>have sustained two or fewer concussions. Level of sig-</p>

<p>nificance for all tests was set at p ＜ 0.05. Descriptive sta-</p>

<p>tistics and frequency tables were calculated and generated </p>

<p>via <rs type="software">Qualtrics</rs> software program, all inferential statistical cal-</p>

<p>culations were conducted using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2013</rs>. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>A total of 51 participants agreed to take the survey. </p>

<p>However, do to the inclusion criteria (∼a concussive event), </p>

<p>only 35 of the 51 willing participants were eligible to take </p>

<p>the surveys. Eight of the 35 eligible participants did not fin-</p>

<p>ish the surveys. Hence the data provided below is based on </p>

<p>a participant pool of n = 27. Participant demographics and </p>

<p>position played can be found in Table 1. </p>

<p>The 27 participants who previously sustained one or more </p>

<p>concussion(s) were asked to complete the 20 question </p>

<p>CESD-R form. Of the 27 participants, the mean CESD-R </p>

<p>scores can be found in Table 2. Players who scored ≥16 </p>

<p>(n = 16) on the CESD-R survey incurred a significantly </p>

<p>greater number of concussions compared with those who </p>

<p>scored ＜16 (n = 11) (p = 0.0004). Players with a history </p>

<p>of three or more concussions scored significantly higher on </p>

<p>the CESD-R survey when compared to players that had a </p>

<p>history of two or less (p = 0.03), see Tables 2 and 3. </p>

<p>After reviewing the data (histograms), we were con-</p>

<p>cerned that the assumptions of normality and equal variance </p>

<p>might be in question, noting that the independent t-test is </p>

<p>robust in regards to these assumptions [22]. As such, addi-</p>

<p>tional statistical analyses (Welch's t-test) that accommodate </p>

<p>for the aforementioned violation of assumptions were car-</p>

<p>ried out as recommended by McDonald [22]. The results of </p>

<p>the Welch's t-tests were as follows: the players who scored </p>

<p>≥16 (n = 16) on the CESD-R survey incurred a sig-</p>

<p>nificantly greater number of concussions compared with </p>

<p>those who scored ＜16 (n = 11) (p ＜ 0.001), and the play-</p>

<p>ers with a history of three or more concussions scored sig-</p>

<p>nificantly higher on the CESD-R survey when compared to </p>

<p>players that had a history of two or less (p ＜ 0.001). </p>

<p>Hence, confirming is initial statistical analysis. </p>



<p>James Pryor, et al : Depression and Concussions in Football Players </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The purpose of this study was to investigate if the number </p>

<p>of concussive events leads to an increased prevalence of de-</p>

<p>pression in active professional and semi-professional North </p>

<p>American football players. The results of the studied sample </p>

<p>indicate that professional and semi-professional football </p>

<p>players who experience a greater number of depressive </p>

<p>symptoms have also suffered a greater number of con-</p>

<p>cussive events. This is evidenced in our study in that those </p>

<p>who met the CESD-R criteria for clinical depression had </p>

<p>sustained a significantly greater number of concussive </p>

<p>events. Furthermore, players that had a concussion history </p>

<p>of three or more also scored significantly higher on the </p>

<p>CESD-R survey. We also explored the direct relationship </p>

<p>between concussive events and the CESD-R survey score </p>

<p>(Pearson correlation ∼r) which yielded a significant pos-</p>

<p>itive moderate relationship (r = 0.37, p ＜ 0.05) [23]. This </p>

<p>moderate positive relationship between concussive events in-</p>

<p>curred and the CESD-R survey score was independent of </p>

<p>years played. Of particular concern is the fact that 100% </p>

<p>of the participants that experienced 3 or more concussive </p>

<p>events were assessed as clinically depressed per the CESD-R </p>

<p>survey. In contrast, the lifetime prevalence of major depres-</p>

<p>sion among US male adults has been estimated to be 12.7% </p>

<p>[24]. </p>

<p>Previous results corroborate the present findings. </p>

<p>Guskiewicz et al. [1] reported that NFL players with a his-</p>

<p>tory of three or more previous concussions were three times </p>

<p>more likely to be diagnosed with depression, and those with </p>

<p>a history of one or two previous concussions were 1.5 times </p>

<p>more likely to have been diagnosed with depression, com-</p>

<p>pared to those who reported no concussive events. Results </p>

<p>of the Guskiewicz et al. study [1] as well as the present sug-</p>

<p>gest that football players with three or more concussions are </p>

<p>at a significantly increased risk of being diagnosed with </p>

<p>clinical depression compared to those with limited or no pri-</p>

<p>or concussion history. In a 9-year follow-up study to the </p>

<p>Guskiewicz et al. [1] report, Kerr et al. [12] documented </p>

<p>a strong dose-response relationship between depression diag-</p>

<p>nosis and self-reported concussions in retired NFL players. </p>

<p>Didehbani et al. [8] also reported a positive significant asso-</p>

<p>ciation between the number of self-reported lifetime con-</p>

<p>cussions and depression in retired NFL players as measured </p>

<p>by the BDI-II total scores (r = 0.43, p ＜ 0.05), a statistic </p>

<p>closely matching the results of the current study. </p>

<p>Casson et al. [7] examined chronic brain damage in re-</p>

<p>tired NFL players which included the BDI-II inventory in </p>

<p>order to evaluate if there was a relationship between depres-</p>

<p>sion and concussions. The results indicated that of the n = </p>

<p>45 players who participated in the study, 32 of 45 (≈71%) </p>

<p>had experienced ≥3 concussions. Thirteen of the 32 (≈ </p>

<p>41%) were assessed with some level of depression per BDI-II </p>

<p>inventory criteria (BDI-II ≥14). According to the authors </p>

<p>[7], "evidence in this study does not support the contention </p>

<p>that a career in the NFL is causally related to later-life de-</p>

<p>pression". With that said, consider the following. According </p>

<p>to the author's presented data, of the n = 45 NFL retired </p>

<p>participants, only 7 did not report having sustained a con-</p>

<p>cussion, in other words ≈84% had sustained at least one </p>

<p>concussion. From a biomechanical perspective, the hits de-</p>

<p>livered and/or received by players during the course of a </p>

<p>football game can and do cause concussions; playing in the </p>

<p>NFL does cause concussions. Further, per their presented </p>

<p>data there is a positive moderate relationship between BDI-II </p>

<p>inventory depression symptoms and number of sustained </p>

<p>concussions (r = 0.35, p ＜ 0.05) [23]. Interestingly, almost </p>

<p>precisely the statistical relationship found in the current </p>

<p>study between the number of sustained concussions and de-</p>

<p>pressive symptoms as assessed by the CESD-R inventory. It </p>

<p>should also be noted that Kerr et al. [12] provided evidence </p>

<p>from a prospective study that there is a possible causal rela-</p>

<p>tionship between concussive episodes and depression in re-</p>

<p>tired professional football players. </p>

<p>A study by Schwenk et al. [9] reported that retired NFL </p>

<p>players (n = 1617) experienced depressive symptoms com-</p>

<p>parable to the general population. However, the Schwenk </p>

<p>[9] study did not examine subpopulations on NFL players </p>

<p>such as those having sustained at least one concussive event. </p>

<p>With that said, we were unable to make a direct comparison </p>

<p>between the Schwenk [9] study and the current </p>

<p>investigation. However, it should be noted that in the cur-</p>

<p>rent study that the CSED-R criteria for depression was met </p>

<p>by 31% of the participants who sustained 1 or 2 concussive </p>

<p>events, far greater than the depressive symptoms reported </p>

<p>in the Schwenk [9] study. </p>



<p>Journal of Lifestyle Medicine Vol. 6, No. 1, March 2016 </p>

<p>The results of the current study also agree with results </p>

<p>of prior studies in different sub-populations regarding the </p>

<p>relationship of concussion and subsequent depression. </p>

<p>Specifically, Chrisman et al. [25] (n = 36,060) and Barker </p>

<p>et al. [26] (n = 14,082) both found elevated risk of depres-</p>

<p>sion diagnosis in adolescents with a history of concussion. </p>

<p>Holsinger et al. [27] reported an increased lifetime risk of </p>

<p>depression in head injured US World War II veterans (n = </p>

<p>520) and the risk was greatest for those who sustained se-</p>

<p>vere head injuries. Finally, Kerr et al. [28] recorded an asso-</p>

<p>ciation between sustained concussions and severe depression </p>

<p>in former collegiate athletes (n = 797). </p>

<p>Also of interest and an area for future study is the poten-</p>

<p>tial relationship between player position and likelihood of </p>

<p>incurring multiple head injuries. Of the twenty participants </p>

<p>that scored within 3 points or above the set criteria for mild </p>

<p>depression (CESD-R score ≥16) there appeared a trend </p>

<p>(although statistically insignificant due to small sample size) </p>

<p>related to position played and the number of concussion(s) </p>

<p>sustained; offensive wide receivers (n = 8) had more </p>

<p>post-concussion depressive symptoms compared to other of-</p>

<p>fensive players, as did defensive linebackers (n = 7) when </p>

<p>compared to players in other defensive positions. Casson et </p>

<p>al. [5] reported similar findings suggesting that defensive </p>

<p>secondary, kick squads, offensive running backs and de-</p>

<p>fensive line backers had the highest incidence of repeat </p>

<p>concussions. </p>

<p>Several investigations have used medical imaging techni-</p>

<p>ques to attempt to identify clinical abnormalities of the brain </p>

<p>in retired NFL players [7,29,30]. Hart et al. [29] utilized </p>

<p>neuroimaging to examine depression and cognitive impair-</p>

<p>ment in retired NFL players (n = 34). The results of the </p>

<p>study suggested that retired "NFL players may be more likely </p>

<p>to develop depression and cognitive impairments as they age </p>

<p>when compared to the general population". With these cogni-</p>

<p>tive impairments being correlated with abnormalities in white </p>

<p>matter and cerebral blood flow patterns. Strain et al. [30] </p>

<p>used diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) to examine the relation-</p>

<p>ship between depression and white matter dysfunction in re-</p>

<p>tired NFL players (n = 26). The results demonstrated that </p>

<p>DTI techniques (fractional anisotropy maps) were 100% sen-</p>

<p>sitivity and 95% specificity with respect to identifying de-</p>

<p>pressed and non-depressed participants. Casson et al. [7] used </p>

<p>a host of magnetic imaging techniques to examine if there </p>

<p>is chronic brain damage in retired NFL players (n = 45) </p>

<p>and if so, was the damage somehow related to depression </p>

<p>symptoms. The results of the study indicated that up to 13% </p>

<p>of the players had chronic brain injury likely related to </p>

<p>football. The author's further stated that there was no clear </p>

<p>link of chronic brain damage on depression in the retired </p>

<p>players. </p>

<p>Other researchers have examined potential contributing </p>

<p>factors associated with the difficulties attached to retirement </p>

<p>from the NFL [9]. Schwenk et al. [9] noted the most com-</p>

<p>mon problems attached to retirement as reported by retired </p>

<p>NFL players as: as difficulty with pain, loss of fitness/lack </p>

<p>of exercise, weight gain, trouble sleeping, difficulty with ag-</p>

<p>ing, and transition to life after professional football. It </p>

<p>should be noted here that many of the aforementioned dif-</p>

<p>ficulties have been reported to be associated with depressive </p>

<p>symptoms in the general population [31-35]. The combina-</p>

<p>tion of loss of fitness and weight gain are of particular con-</p>

<p>cern as these issues are related to a host of other medical </p>

<p>conditions (metabolic syndrome, hyper-lipedema, cardio </p>

<p>vascular disease, high blood pressure, diabetes, and certain </p>

<p>cancers, etc.). Interestingly, active NFL players are often </p>

<p>classified as obese by body mass index (BMI-body mass </p>

<p>kg/height meters squared) criteria where BMI ≥ 30 is con-</p>

<p>sidered obese [36]. A BMI analysis of active NFL players </p>

<p>for the Detroit Lions [37] yielded a team average BMI of </p>

<p>32.2 ± 4.7, considered obese. However, it should be noted </p>

<p>that in this population there is a high amount of muscle </p>

<p>mass contributing to the total body mass. After NFL retire-</p>

<p>ment, data from previous research [12] has shown that BMI </p>

<p>is relatively consistent with active playing days. Kerr et al. </p>

<p>[12] reported the BMI of the retired NFL players as BMI </p>

<p>= 30.3 ± 4.1, a value consistent with the reported BMI of </p>

<p>the current NFL team reported above. What is likely occur-</p>

<p>ring in this population is a "BMI shift". A condition much </p>

<p>like what others [38] have referred to as sarcopenic obesity. </p>

<p>A physiologic process where muscle mass is lost with age </p>

<p>while there is a concurrent accumulation of body fat. </p>

<p>Hence, total BMI is unaffected, but the individual is now </p>

<p>predisposed to the myriad of health conditions associated </p>

<p>with obesity. The difference between the "BMI shift" and </p>

<p>sarcopenic obesity is that the population of NFL players are </p>



<p>James Pryor, et al : Depression and Concussions in Football Players </p>

<p>initially younger adults and obese as per BMI classification </p>

<p>but with an extreme amount of muscle mass as compared </p>

<p>to the general population. Then after retirement, and as the </p>

<p>years pass, muscle mass is lost at that same time as fat mass </p>

<p>is gained. This accumulation of body fat is likely a potential </p>

<p>trigger of depressive symptoms. </p>

<p>Furthering the importance of loss of fitness, Kerr et al. </p>

<p>[12] suggested that reduced physical ability in previously </p>

<p>elite athletes (NFL retirees) could lead to an increasing </p>

<p>sense of "hopelessness and less physical independence", </p>

<p>hence a potential trigger for depression onset. Additionally, </p>

<p>Kerr et al. [12] postulated that retired NFL players who </p>

<p>have been forced into retirement (injury, loss of ability, </p>

<p>etc.) might feel a sense of un-fulfilled ambitions as well as </p>

<p>facing financial troubles, both potentially leading to </p>

<p>depression. </p>

<p>The primary limitation to the present study was a small </p>

<p>sample size. Many players still do not want to share all their </p>

<p>health information, especially something as sensitive as men-</p>

<p>tal health information. Of the 200 invitations sent to </p>

<p>Semi-Professional and Professional football players, only 51 </p>

<p>responded and only 27 had actually sustained at least one </p>

<p>concussion. The NFL has a clause in player's contracts that </p>

<p>restricts the player from participating in medical surveys out-</p>

<p>side of the NFL. Another limitation was the exclusion of </p>

<p>participants who had reported no concussive events from tak-</p>

<p>ing the CESD-R survey. In retrospect the CESD-R survey </p>

<p>could have been administered to all respondents regardless </p>

<p>of prior concussion status, albeit not a primary purpose of </p>

<p>the current study. Concussion recall is also a potential limi-</p>

<p>tation of the current study. Kerr et al. [39] reported a sub-</p>

<p>stantial lack of agreement between clinically documented and </p>

<p>self-recalled concussion history. Likewise, we did not attempt </p>

<p>to determine concussion history occurring prior to the play-</p>

<p>er's professional or semi-professional careers, a potential con-</p>

<p>tributing factor to current depression state/symptoms. </p>

<p>In summary, our data suggests that concussions are asso-</p>

<p>ciated with depression in active North American semi-pro-</p>

<p>fessional and professional football players. We have also </p>

<p>compared and contrasted the results of the current study </p>

<p>with others who have examined concussion and depression </p>

<p>in retired NFL players, adolescence, collegiate athletes, and </p>

<p>young adults [1,7,8,12,25-28]. Likewise, we have reviewed </p>

<p>additional sources of stressors that could contribute to de-</p>

<p>pression in retired NFL players. The preponderance of the </p>

<p>evidence strongly suggests that concussions are linked to de-</p>

<p>pression in NFL players active and retired. </p>

<p>Untreated depression can lead to suicide [40]. Approximately </p>

<p>1/3 
rd of the retired NFL players in the Schwenk et al. [9] </p>

<p>study were unaware that the depressive symptoms they were </p>

<p>experiencing were even important. With that said, how would </p>

<p>these individuals know to seek out treatment? We suggest </p>

<p>the following three straightforward strategies: </p>

<p>• The social and professional structures surrounding these </p>

<p>athletes need to be made aware of the increased risk </p>

<p>of depression and help the athletes monitor for symp-</p>

<p>toms so that appropriate treatment can be sought if </p>

<p>warranted. This would include friends, family, coaches, </p>

<p>athletic trainers, team and personal physicians all of </p>

<p>whom could be in a vantage to help the players monitor </p>

<p>for depressive symptoms such as anger, irritability, sub-</p>

<p>stance abuse or overtraining [41]. </p>

<p>• The CESD-R is available on the web [42] and can read-</p>

<p>ily allow for self-monitoring of depressive symptoms </p>

<p>and condition. Retired and active football players </p>

<p>should periodically use an instrument such as the </p>

<p>CESD-R in order to self-monitor for depressive </p>

<p>symptoms. The CESD-R website also has crisis hotlines </p>

<p>in the event that an individual needs immediate help. </p>

<p>• Physical activity has been found to be an effective </p>

<p>treatment against depression [33]. Further, vigorous </p>

<p>physical activity has been shown to be protective in re-</p>

<p>gards to preventing depression in aging retired athletes </p>

<p>[43]. Retired football players should maintain a highly </p>

<p>physical active life style as a countermeasure to help </p>

<p>offset the risk of depression. In fact, these retired ath-</p>

<p>letes might consider competing in master's athletic </p>

<p>games where participants have reported positive social, </p>

<p>psychological, and physical health benefits [44-50]. </p>

<p>We believe these three simple strategies may provide an </p>

<p>effective front line defense against the development and/or </p>

<p>progression of depression in active and retired football </p>

<p>players. Given that there is a lack of understanding as to </p>

<p>the ideal assessment of depression in athletes [41], it would </p>

<p>seem prudent that a multifaceted approach be employed </p>

<p>where the social and professional structures surrounding </p>



<p>Journal of Lifestyle Medicine Vol. 6, No. 1, March 2016 </p>

<p>these athletes stand vigilant and collectively monitor these </p>

<p>athletes. </p>





<p>James Pryor, et al : Depression and Concussions in Football Players </p>



</text></tei>