<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4147369" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The mechanical property of extracellular matrix and cell-supporting substrates is known to modulate 
neuronal growth, differentiation, extension and branching. Here we show that substrate stiffness is an 
important microenvironmental cue, to which mouse hippocampal neurons respond and integrate into 
synapse formation and transmission in cultured neuronal network. Hippocampal neurons were cultured on 
polydimethylsiloxane substrates fabricated to have similar surface properties but a 10-fold difference in 
Young's modulus. Voltage-gated Ca 
21 channel currents determined by patch-clamp recording were greater 
in neurons on stiff substrates than on soft substrates. Ca 
21 oscillations in cultured neuronal network 
monitored using time-lapse single cell imaging increased in both amplitude and frequency among neurons 
on stiff substrates. Consistently, synaptic connectivity recorded by paired recording was enhanced between 
neurons on stiff substrates. Furthermore, spontaneous excitatory postsynaptic activity became greater and 
more frequent in neurons on stiff substrates. Evoked excitatory transmitter release and excitatory 
postsynaptic currents also were heightened at synapses between neurons on stiff substrates. Taken together, 
our results provide compelling evidence to show that substrate stiffness is an important biophysical factor 
modulating synapse connectivity and transmission in cultured hippocampal neuronal network. Such 
information is useful in designing instructive scaffolds or supporting substrates for neural tissue engineering. </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>t is well-known that all types of cells are able to detect and respond to extracellular and intracellular chemical 
signals. Recent studies have evidence to suggest many cells including neurons in the brain are also equipped to 
sense mechanical cues from their microenvironments such as the stiffness or rigidity of extracellular matrix or 
cell-supporting substrates, and result in profound effects on their morphology and function </p>

<p>1-14 </p>

<p>. For instance, 
substrates with stiffness similar to brain tissues prefer to stimulate neuronal over glial growth in cortical neuronal 
cultures 
2 . The mechanical property of neuron-supporting substrates also exerts considerable influence on 
important neuronal behaviors; taking hippocampal neurons for example, stiff substrates promote dendrite 
arborization and, by contrast, soft substrates render weak adhesion that assists neurite outgrowth and/or retrac-
tion and thereby increase the frequency of extension-retraction events and neuronal dynamics </p>

<p>4,5,8 </p>

<p>. Furthermore, 
there is increasing evidence to suggest that the physical properties of substrates can tune synapse formation and 
strength in cultured neuronal network although the underlying mechanisms are not fully understood </p>

<p>4-7,9,13,14 </p>

<p>. 
Brain injury or neurodegenerative disease can change local or global stiffness of the brain tissues, for example, 
local tissue stiffness is likely to increase after injury, as a result of formation of structures such as glial scars, and 
decrease in the brain tissues of patients with Alzheimer's disease and multiple sclerosis </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>. These and other studies 
have led to recognition of the mechanical property as an important factor in designing instructive scaffolds for 
neural tissue engineering </p>

<p>10-12 </p>

<p>. A clear understanding of how the mechanical property of neuron-supporting 
substrates influences neuronal function is still lacking but important in inspiring a full insight into brain function 
and in particular development of novel neuron-supporting scaffolds for neural tissue engineering or regenera-
tion 
7,10,12-15 . We carried out the present study to investigate the effects of substrate stiffness on Ca 
21 signaling, 
synapse connectivity and transmission in cultured hippocampal neuronal network. </p>

<p>Results 
Polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS) substrates were used in the present study as have been recently shown to have a 
wide range of elasticity or mechanical strength independently of surface properties and thus are highly appro-</p>

<p>OPEN </p>

<p>SUBJECT AREAS: </p>

<p>NEURAL CIRCUIT </p>

<p>TISSUE ENGINEERING </p>

<p>priate for study of the mechano-sensitivity of cellular processes </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>. 
Indeed, our two types of PDMS substrate preparations had similar 
surface roughness or topography as revealed using atomic force 
microscopy (Fig. 1a), but a 10-fold difference in Young's modulus 
(46 6 11 kPa versus 457 6 39 kPa; n 5 6) as determined using the 
spherical indentation method (see Materials and Methods). We 
referred to them from here onwards as the soft and stiff substrates, 
respectively. Hippocampal neurons cultured on such substrates over 
a period of 14-18 days showed the typical size of cell body, morpho-
logy, neurite growth and extension. Neurites grew in all directions 
and with varying distances, and a high proportion of them made 
contacts with each other in the later stage (Fig. 1b-d). Further char-
acterization by immunofluorescent confocal microscopy using anti-
bodies that recognize MAP2 (a neuronal marker), vesicular 
glutamate transporter (vGLUT1) (a marker of excitatory neurons 
using glutamate) or GAD67 (a maker for inhibitory neurons using 
c-aminobutyric acid or GABA) shows no difference in neuron den-
sity, soma size, and percentage of excitatory and inhibitory neurons 
on stiff and soft substrates (Fig. 1c-e). 
Cytosolic Ca 
21 is a ubiquitous signaling molecule, and neurons 
express numerous Ca 
21 signaling mechanisms that play a crucial role </p>

<p>in determining and regulating their functional roles </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>. Voltage-gated 
Ca 
21 channels mediating Ca 
21 influx into the presynaptic terminals are 
particularly important for synaptic transmission </p>

<p>17,18 </p>

<p>. Thus, we firstly 
examined the effect of substrate stiffness on voltage-gated Ca 
21 chan-
nels in hippocampal neurons in culture for 8-10 days in vitro (DIV8-
10), using whole-cell patch-clamp recording and Ba 
21 as the charge 
carrier to avoid perturbance of Ca </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>-dependent mechanisms. Neurons 
cultured on both substrates responded to depolarization pulses with 
non-inactivating currents (Fig. 2a). The current-voltage (I-V) relation-
ship curves were bell-shaped; the inward currents began to appear 
approximately at 230 mV, reached the maximum at 25 mV and 
reversed at 150 mV (Fig. 2b). The amplitude of inward currents in 
the voltage range from 215 mV to 115 mV was significantly greater 
in neurons on stiff substrates as compared to that in neurons on soft 
substrates (Fig. 2b). Similar increases in voltage-gated Ca 
21 channel 
currents in nerve growth factor-differentiated PC12 pheochromocy-
toma cells (Fig. 2c-d), a cell model for neuronal function. Taken 
together, these results suggest up-regulation of neuronal voltage-gated 
Ca 
21 channels by stiff substrates. 
Hippocampal neurons as they mature in vivo or in vitro develop 
spontaneous oscillations in the cytosolic Ca 
21 concentrations </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Surface topography of PDMS substrates and effect of substrate stiffness on neuronal cultures. (a) Representative AFM images showing </p>

<p>similar surface topography of soft and stiff substrates. (b) Representative optical microscopic photos showing DIV14 neurons on soft and stiff substrates. 
(c) Left: representative fluorescent confocal images showing neurons stained with MAP2. Right: summary of neurons density (top) and soma size 
(bottom), determined from images like the one shown on the left. (d) Representative MAP2 staining, GAD67 staining and merged fluorescent images 
(top), or MAP2 staining and vGLUT1 staining and merged fluorescent images (bottom), on soft substrates. The arrows in the merged images highlight 
example neurons with positive (filled) and negative (empty) co-staining. (e) Percentage of vGLUT1-positive (top) and GAD67-positive neurons 
(bottom). The numbers shown in parenthesis indicate images (cell density in (c) and (e)) or neurons (soma area in (c)) examined in each case. Similar 
results were observed in four independent experiments. NS denotes no significant difference. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 6215 | DOI: 10.1038/srep06215 </p>

<p>
([Ca 
21 ] c ), or Ca 
21 oscillation as a result of synapse formation in 
neuronal network </p>

<p>19-24 </p>

<p>. We combined time lapse microscopy and 
Fura-2 ratiometry to investigate the effect of substrate stiffness on 
basal [Ca 
21 ] c and Ca 
21 oscillation in DIV14-18 neurons (Fig. 3a-c). 
The basal [Ca 
21 ] c were similar in neurons cultured on soft and stiff 
substrates (Fig. 3d). Ca 
21 oscillations were observed in a majority of 
neurons but neurons on stiff substrates exhibited significant 
increases in both frequency and amplitude (Fig. 3e-f) with no dis-
cernible change in synchronization (Fig. 3g). 
Ca 
21 oscillations have been shown to be mediated by excitatory 
and inhibitory neurons or synapses in the neuronal networks </p>

<p>19-22 </p>

<p>. To 
further study the effects of substrate stiffness on synapse formation 
and function, we recorded spontaneous excitatory and inhibitory 
postsynaptic currents (sEPSC and sIPSC) from DIV14-18 neurons. 
The results are summarized in Fig. 4. There were significant increases 
in both amplitude and frequency of sEPSC in neurons on stiff sub-
strates (Fig. 4b-c) and by contrast no effect on sIPSC was detected 
(Fig. 4e-f). We also determined the synaptic connectivity directly by 
paired recording (Fig. 5a) on the basis that action potentials (APs), 
induced by injecting currents into one (or presynaptic) neuron, 
evoke neurotransmitter release and subsequent postsynaptic cur-
rents in another synaptically coupled (postsynaptic) neuron. The 
average percentage of synaptic connectivity among neurons on stiff 
substrates was significantly greater than that among neurons on soft 
substrates (Fig. 5b). More specifically, stiff substrates increased both 
excitatory and inhibitory synaptic connectivity (Fig. 5c). All the syn-
aptic connectivity was completely abolished in extracellular Ca </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>free solutions (data not shown), consistent with a critical role of Ca </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>influx in inducing synaptic transmission. We also examined the 
electrical coupling between neurons. The prevalence of electrical 
coupling and the coupling coefficient were not altered by substrate 
stiffness (Fig. 5d-f). Finally, we compared AP-evoked excitatory 
postsynaptic currents (EPSC) and inhibitory postsynaptic currents 
(IPSC), and also paired-pulse facilitation (PPF) or depression (PPD) 
that are often indicative of vesicular release probability (Pr) of neu-
rotransmitters with a lower Pr resulting in a greater PPF or PPD 
value </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>. The cumulative distribution of postsynaptic currents shows 
that the size of evoked EPSC was increased significantly in neurons 
on stiff substrates relative to that in neurons on soft substrates 
(Fig. 5g). The PPF value was, as expected, significantly lower for 
neurons on stiff substrates (1.12 6 0.07) than on soft substrates 
(1.38 6 0.08; p , 0.05) (Fig. 5h), consistent with enhanced excitatory 
synaptic transmission. In contrast, there was no change in evoked 
IPSC and PPD value (Fig. 5i-j). Collectively, these results provide 
consistent evidence to show that stiff substrates preferentially 
enhance the excitatory synaptic connectivity and transmission in 
cultured hippocampal neuronal network. </p>

<p>Discussion 
The present study provides evidence to show that substrate stiffness 
strongly enhances voltage-gated Ca 
21 channel currents, Ca 
21 oscilla-
tions, synaptic connectivity, and excitatory neurotransmission in 
cultured hippocampal neuronal networks. </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Stiff substrate enhances voltage-gated Ca </p>

<p>21 channel currents in hippocampal neurons and PC12 cells. (a) Representative whole-cell Ba </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>current recordings from DIV8-10 neurons on soft and stiff substrates. (b) Mean I-V relationship curves from recordings of 10 neurons from three 
preparations. (c) Representative whole-cell Ba 
21 current recordings from PC12 neurons cultured for 8-10 days on soft and stiff substrates. (d) Mean I-V 
relationship curves. The number of cells recorded in each case is shown in parenthesis. *, p , 0.05 denotes difference in the current density at the same 
membrane potential. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 6215 | DOI: 10.1038/srep06215 </p>

<p>
As mentioned above, neurons express a diversity of Ca 
21 signaling 
mechanisms that are important for brain functions </p>

<p>17,18,25-27 </p>

<p>, including 
presynaptic voltage-gated Ca 
21 channels to mediate transmission at 
synapses, and synchronized Ca 
21 oscillations in neuronal networks 
to determine neuronal plasticity. Diverse extrinsic chemical signals 
and intrinsic mechanisms exist at both presynaptic and postsynaptic 
sites to determine or modulate synaptic formation and transmis-
sion </p>

<p>17,22-28 </p>

<p>. For example, expression of cadherin-9 is crucial for syn-
apse formation between dentate gyrus and CA3 neurons in 
hippocampus 
28 and neuropeptides via activation of distinctive G-
protein-coupled receptors can alter the amplitude and/or frequency 
of Ca 
21 oscillations and thereby neuronal plasticity </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>. Emergent evid-
ence suggests that the physical properties of neuron-supporting 
substrates are also influential. Thus, culturing neuronal stem cell-
differentiated neurospheres on graphene, as opposed to tissue culture 
plastic surface, enhanced synchronized spontaneous Ca 
21 oscilla-
tions and postsynaptic currents </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>. Stretching the membranes which 
supported cortical neurons significantly reduced spontaneous Ca </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>oscillations and excitatory postsynaptic currents </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>. The present study 
examined hippocampal neurons cultured on substrates with differ-
ent stiffness, and revealed that the stiff substrates significantly up-
regulated Ca 
21 signaling mechanisms, including voltage-gated Ca </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>channels (Fig. 2) and synchronized spontaneous Ca 
21 oscillations 
(Figs. 3). More importantly, our study has shown that the stiff sub-
strates enhanced synaptic connectivity and excitatory synaptic trans-</p>

<p>mission (Figs. 4-5). To our best knowledge, this is the first study to 
show that neurons can sense mechanical cues from their microenvir-
onments and integrate into synapse connectivity and transmission. 
The increases in both Ca 
21 channel activity (Fig. 2) and synaptic 
connectivity induced by the stiff substrates (Fig. 5b), and no detect-
able synaptic connectivity in extracellular Ca </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>-free solutions sup-
port the importance of Ca 
21 signalling or presynaptic Ca 
21 influx 
through voltage-gated Ca 
21 channels. The stiff substrates also stimu-
lated synchronized spontaneous Ca 
21 oscillations in cultured neur-
onal network (Fig. 3), and facilitated excitatory synaptic connectivity 
and transmission (Fig. 4a-c, Fig. 5c and Fig. 5g-h). These findings 
are consistent with the notion that the Ca 
21 oscillations result from 
periodic burst firing of APs engaging excitatory synaptic transmis-
sion via activation of L-type voltage-gated Ca 
21 channels and excit-
atory NMDA receptors </p>

<p>19,22,23,30 </p>

<p>. The excitatory GABA A receptors in 
the neonatal hippocampus have been reported to mediate the Ca </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>oscillations in synergy with NMDA receptors </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>. This study has 
shown that the stiff substrates also enhanced the inhibitory synaptic 
connectivity (Fig. 5c) but did not alter the inhibitory synaptic trans-
mission (Fig. 4d-f and Fig. 5i-j). Further investigations are required 
to determine the contribution of the excitatory and inhibitory recep-
tors in mediating the increases in the Ca 
21 oscillations and the dis-
criminating effects on the excitatory versus inhibitory synaptic 
transmission. The increases in spontaneous Ca 
21 oscillations on stiff 
substrates have also been documented in other cell types; for </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Stiff substrate increases synchronized spontaneous cytosolic Ca </p>

<p>21 oscillations in cultured neural networks of hippocampal neurons. (a) 
Representative single cell images showing Ca 
21 fluorescence in DIV14-18 neurons on stiff substrates. (b) Representative single cell images showing Ca </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>fluorescence intensity at given time points from one neuron on soft substrate and another neuron on stiff substrate. (c) Representative time elapse 
recordings of Ca 
21 oscillations from neurons on soft and stiff substrates. (d) Summary of the basal cytosolic Ca 
21 concentrations (left), and the magnitude 
(middle) and frequency (right) of Ca 
21 oscillations in 58 neurons on soft and stiff substrates from three preparations. *, p , 0.05 denotes significant 
difference, and NS, no significant difference. (g) Left: representative single cell images showing Ca 
21 fluorescence in DIV14-18 neurons on soft and stiff 
substrates. Right: time elapse recordings of Ca 
21 oscillations from four neurons as denoted by circles in the left images. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 6215 | DOI: 10.1038/srep06215 </p>

<p>
example, spontaneous cytosolic Ca 
21 oscillations became more fre-
quent in human mesenchymal stem cells when cultured on stiff 
polyacrylamide gel substrates or were amplified in endothelial cells 
when migrating from soft to stiff region of the substrates </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>. It is thus 
attractive to propose tuning the frequency and/or amplitude of cyto-
solic Ca 
21 oscillations as a common intrinsic mechanism which cells 
use to encode the difference and/or change in the mechanical prop-
erty of their microenvironments. Neurons examined in the present 
study were supported directly by the substrates based on visual exam-
ination (Fig. 1b). The stiff substrates increased the voltage-gated Ca </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>channel currents in cultured hippocampal neurons (Fig. 2a-b) and 
similarly in nerve growth factor-differentiated PC12 cells (Fig. 2c-d). 
Taken together, these results support expression of intrinsic 
mechano-sensing mechanisms in neurons. Nevertheless, it is worth 
pointing out that our hippocampal neuronal preparations like those 
used in many previous studies contained glial cells, and thus we 
cannot exclude the intriguing possibility that the glial cells have a 
role in sensing the mechanical cues and relaying to co-existing neu-
rons. The PDMS substrates used in this present study are similar to 
those in previous studies, particularly those focusing on tissue engin-
eering, and the substrate stiffness is much higher than the overall 
stiffness of brain tissues </p>

<p>2,15,16 </p>

<p>. While it is important to determine the 
effects of changing the substrate stiffness occurring to the brain 
tissues on synaptic formation and function, the interesting finding 
reported in the present study is useful for the development of novel 
instructive scaffolds for neural tissue engineering. 
The mechano-sensing mechanisms are currently still poorly 
understood, despite several cytoskeletal and signaling proteins have 
been identified in various cell types, including receptor-like protein </p>

<p>tyrosine phosphatase 
4 , integrins </p>

<p>7,31-33 </p>

<p>, RhoA 
34 and GAP-43 
35 as well 
as mechano-sensitive ion channels </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>. In addition, there is evidence 
suggesting that the effect of substrate stiffness on dendrite arboriza-
tion is mediated by glutamate receptors 
30 . More investigations are 
clearly required to identify the neuronal voltage-gated Ca 
21 channels 
that are up-regulated by stiff substrates, and particularly elucidate the 
mechano-sensing mechanisms that enhance voltage-gated Ca </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>channel function, synaptic connectivity, excitatory synaptic trans-
mission, and synchronized spontaneous Ca 
21 oscillations we have 
reported here in cultured hippocampal neuronal network. 
In summary, we have shown stiffness of cell-supporting substrates 
can strongly modulate excitatory synaptic connectivity and trans-
mission in cultured hippocampal neuronal network. Such findings 
are useful for design of instructive scaffolds to be used in neural tissue 
engineering as well as to inspire a new insight into brain functions 
and mechanisms of diseases that change extracellular matrix 
compliance. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Preparation and characterization of PDMS substrates. PDMS curing agent 
(sylgard184; Dow corning Corp) were mixed with base agent in a mass ratio of 1051 
or 5051 in 15-ml centrifugal tubes, and centrifuged in a bench-top centrifuge to 
remove air bubbles. The mixture of ,100 ml was transferred using a pipette onto the 
top of four 12-mm coverslips in a 35-mm petri dish and left at 65uC for 12 hrs; the 
resulting PDMS substrates were oxidized in an oxygen plasma cleaner, which 
generated silanol group (Si-OH) on the surface of the PDMS, then sterilized by UV 
radiation for 2 hrs, coated with fibronectin and left in a laminar flow cabinet for at 
least 2 hrs. The PDMS-coverslips were washed extensively with sterile water and 
dried before being used to culture hippocampal neurons as described previously 
37 . 
The substrate surface topography was examined using atomic force microscopy 
(AFM) (Nanoscope IIIa system, Digital Instruments, Santa Barbara, CA, USA) in a </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Effects of substrate stiffness on spontaneous EPSC and IPSC. (a) Representative recordings of spontaneous EPSC from DIV14-18 neurons in </p>

<p>soft and stiff substrates. (b) Cumulative distribution and amplitude of spontaneous EPSC. (c) Cumulative distribution of inter-event intervals and 
frequency of spontaneous EPSC. (d) Representative recordings of spontaneous IPSC from DIV14-18 neurons in soft and stiff substrates. (e) Cumulative 
distribution and amplitude of spontaneous IPSC. (f) Cumulative distribution of inter-event intervals and frequency of spontaneous IPSC. *, p , 0.05 
denote significant difference, and NS, no significant difference. The numbers shown in parenthesis indicate neurons examined in each case. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 6215 | DOI: 10.1038/srep06215 </p>

<p>
tapping mode with 512 3 512 pixel data acquisition and 1 Hz scan speed. The AFM 
images were recorded with a standard silicon tip on a cantilever beam. The cantilever 
had a spring constant of 50 pN/nm, and was 125 mm long with a resonant frequency 
of 300 kHz. 
The Young's modulus of the substrates was determined using the spherical 
indentation method and ElectroForceH3100 test instrument (Bose, Shanghai, China) 
as described previously </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>. In brief, the samples had a diameter of 55 mm and a height 
of 15 mm. The spherical indenter of 3-mm radius was used. The loading procedures 
were undertaken with controlled displacement, and the loading rate was set at 2 mm/ 
s and the maximum indentation depth at 3 mm. Measurements were undertaken at 
six different positions of the sample, and the depth-indentation load curves were 
recorded. The initial shear modulus was determined by fitting the load curves up to </p>

<p>different ratios of h/R using the following equation: P~1 
6 
9 
E 
ffiffiffiffiffi ffi 
Rh 
p 
h 1{0:15 
h 
R </p>



<p>
, </p>

<p>where P represents indentation load, E Young's modulus, h indentation depth and R 
indenter radius </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Hippocampal neuron culture preparation and PC12 cell culture. All animal 
procedures were in accordance with the guidelines approved by Tsinghua University. 
Mouse hippocampal neurons were isolated from one day old pups as previously 
described </p>

<p>18,39 </p>

<p>. In brief, after the blood vessels and meninges were removed, the 
hippocampus was collected into tubes in cold Hank's balanced salt solution (HBSS), 
and rinsed twice with HBSS solutions. Tissues were digested in TrypIE (Sigma) for 
15 min at 37uC and gently triturated using pipette tips to cell suspension in DMEM 
medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and 2% B-27 (Life 
Technologies). Cells were seeded approximately 6000 cells/cm 
2 and were maintained 
at 37uC in humidified atmosphere with 5% CO 2 . Arabinofuranosyl cysteine at 1 mg/ </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Stiff substrate facilitates excitatory synaptic connectivity and transmission in the neural networks of hippocampal neurons. (a) Experimental </p>

<p>setting of paired recording; one (presynaptic) neuron was stimulated by the electrode in current-clamp configuration to evoke APs and the unitary 
postsynaptic currents in the other (postsynaptic) neuron were detected by the electrode in voltage-clamp configuration. Example unitary EPSC and IPSC 
with distinct kinetics are illustrated at the bottom. (b) Summary of percentage of pairs of neurons that exhibited synaptic connectivity or transmission on 
soft and stiff substrates. In total, 181 pairs of neurons on soft and stiff substrates each from three independent preparations respectively were examined. (c) 
Summary of the percentage of pairs of neurons on soft and stiff substrates that showed excitatory and inhibitory synaptic connectivity (from (b)). (d) 
Paired recording from a pair of electrically coupled neurons. The experimental protocol is illustrated on top: a hyperpolarizing step current was injected to 
the presynaptic neuron C1, and changes in membrane potential were recorded from both presynaptic neuron and postsynaptic neuron (C2). 
Representative recordings of changes in membrane potential in C1 and C2 cells are shown below. (e) Summary of the percentage of electrically coupled 
neurons on soft and stiff substrates. In total, 54 pairs of neurons on soft substrates and 46 pairs of neurons on stiff substrates from 8 independent 
preparations were examined. (f) Summary of the coupling coefficient values for electrically coupled neurons. (g) The cumulative distribution of AP-
evoked EPSC recorded in 18 neurons from seven independent preparations in each case. Insert: evoked EPSC traces from neurons on soft and stiff 
substrates. (h) Mean PPF value for 18 neurons on soft and stiff substrates from seven independent preparations. (i) The cumulative distribution of AP-
evoked IPSC recorded in 16 neurons from seven independent preparations. Insert: evoked IPSC traces in neurons on soft and stiff substrates. (j) Mean 
PPD value for 16 neurons on soft and stiff substrates each from seven independent preparations. The numbers shown in parenthesis indicate neuron 
preparations (b-c and e) or neurons examined (f-j) in each case. *, p , 0.05 denotes significant difference, and NS, no significant difference. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 6215 | DOI: 10.1038/srep06215 </p>

<p>
ml was added to culture medium 2-3 days after initial seeding to inhibit glial 
proliferation. PC12 cells were seeded on substrates and culture in DMEM medium 
supplemented with 10% FBS and 50 ng/ml nerve growth factor (Sigma) for 8-10 days 
before use. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence staining and confocal imaging. This was performed at room 
temperature except incubation with the primary antibody at 4uC. DIV14 cells were 
washed with phosphate buffered solutions (PBS), fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde in 
PBS for 15 min and then permeabilized with 0.2% Triton X-100 (Sigma) in PBS for 
5 min. After extensive washing with PBS, cells were blocked with 5% bovine serum 
albumin in PBS for 60 min, and incubated with primary rabbit polyclonal MAP2 
antibody (Abcam) at a dilution of 15500 alone, or together with mouse monoclonal 
GAD67 antibody (Millipore) at 15200 or mouse monoclonal vGLUT1 (Millipore) at 
15200 overnight. After extensive wash with PBS, cells were incubated with secondary 
Alexa Fluor568 goat anti-rabbit IgG antibody (Molecular Probes) at 151000 alone or 
with Alexa Fluor488 goat anti-mouse IgG antibody (Molecular Probes) at 151000 for 
60 min. Fluorescence images were captured using a fluorescence microscope (TCS 
SP5, Leica Microsystems). </p>

<p>Patch-clamp recording. Whole-cell currents were recorded from DIV8-10 neurons 
at room temperature, using an Axopatch 200B amplifier and <rs id="software-0" type="software">pClamp</rs> software 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 10.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Axon Instruments</rs>). The patched cells were perfused at 0.5 ml/min in 
extracellular solution containing (in mM): 140 tetraethylammonium (TEA)-Cl, 10 
BaCl 2 , 10 HEPES and 20 glucose, pH 7.3 with TEA-OH, 310 mOsm. The pipette 
solution contained (in mM): 110 CsCl, 10 EGTA, 4 Mg-ATP, 0.3 Na-GTP, 25 HEPES, 
10 Tris-phosphocreatine and 20 U/ml creatine phosphokinase, pH 7.3 with CsOH, 
290 mOsm. The resistance of recording pipettes in extracellular solution was 3.0-
4.0 MV. The membrane potential was held at 280 mV and series resistance 
compensated by 80%. Currents were evoked by applying test pulses of 275 mV to 
1100 mV with 40-s duration and an increment of 5 mV at 10-s intervals. The cell 
capacitance (32 6 12 pF) and series resistance (,20 MV) were monitored 
throughout the recording. Signals were filtered at 1 kHz and digitized at 10 kHz. The 
leak currents were corrected using the online P/6 trace subtraction. </p>

<p>Cytosolic Ca 
21 measurement. Cytosolic Ca 
21 concentrations in DIV14-18 neurons 
were measured at room temperature using Fura-2 ratiometric method. In brief, 
neurons were incubated with 2 mM Fura-2/acetoxymethyl ester (Life Technologies) 
in DMEM culture medium at 37uC for 30 min, followed by washing three times with 
phosphate buffer saline. Cells bathed in MEM with 2% FBS were placed on the stage of 
an Olympus IX71 inverted microscope equipped with a Xenon illumination system 
and an IMAGO CCD camera (Till Photonics, Germany). The fluorescence, excited 
alternatively with 340 nm and 380 nm and emitted at 510 nm, were recorded, stored 
digitally and analyzed by <rs id="software-1" type="software">TILLvisION</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">4.0</rs> program. </p>

<p>Spontaneous and AP-evoked postsynaptic current recordings. Postsynaptic 
current recordings were made from DIV14-18 neurons. The recording chamber was 
perfused at 0.5 ml/min with extracellular Tyrode's solution containing (in mM): 125 
NaCl, 2 KCl, 4 CaCl 2 , 4 MgCl 2 , 25 HEPES and 30 glucose, pH 7.3 with NaOH, 
310 mOsm. The pipette solution contained (in mM): 100 KCl, 2 EGTA, 4 Mg-ATP, 
0.3 Na-GTP, 30 HEPES, 10 Tris-phosphocreatine and 20 U/ml creatine 
phosphokinase, pH 7.3 with KOH, 290 mOsm. Spontaneous and evoked inhibitory 
postsynaptic currents (IPSC) were recorded in extracellular solutions containing 
20 mM NBQX, and spontaneous and evoked excitatory postsynaptic currents (EPSC) 
in extracellular solutions containing 10 mM bicuculline. In some experiments, 
extracellular solutions without CaCl 2 were used. Spontaneous postsynaptic currents 
were recorded with the membrane potential held at 270 mV for 5 min. AP-evoked 
postsynaptic currents and paired-pulse facilitation (PPF) or depression (PPD) were 
determined by paired recording without capacitance compensation as previously 
described </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>. The presynaptic neurons were depolarized to 0 mV for 1 ms to elicit APs 
at 10-s intervals. The unitary postsynaptic currents were recorded from the paired 
postsynaptic neurons at a holding potential of 270 mV. 30 AP-evoked EPSC and 
IPSC were recorded from each neuron. Evoked EPSC and IPSC exhibited different 
decay kinetics, with average rise and decay times of 3 6 0.3 ms and 24 6 2.6 ms for 
EPSC (n 5 18), and 4 6 0.4 ms and 184 6 12.4 ms for IPSC (n 5 16), respectively. 
PPF was determined by evoking two EPSC at a 50-ms interval and PPD by evoking 
two IPSC at a 200-ms interval. To minimize the potential effects of spatial proximity 
on synaptic connectivity, paired recordings were made from a pair of neurons in the 
distance of 100-150 mm. </p>

<p>Electrical coupling. The electrical coupling between neurons was examined using the 
protocols described previously by Lefler et al 
40 . A hyperpolarizing current of 300 or 
500 pA was delivered to the presynaptic neuron and measured the ensuing changes in 
membrane potential in both neurons. The ratio of the steady-state change in 
membrane potential in the presynaptic neuron to that in the postsynaptic neuron was 
calculated as the electrical coupling coefficient (CC). The CC value of ,0.002 is 
indicative of no electrical coupling. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. The data were presented as mean 6 s.e.m., where appropriate. 
The neuron density was derived from MAP2-positive cells that were counted in 
fluorescent images and converted to the number of neurons per mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, and the soma 
area of individual MAP2-positive cells was estimated, using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs>. The percentage 
of excitatory and inhibitory neurons was obtained by visually identifying the number </p>

<p>of MAP2-positive and vGLUT1-positive neurons or MAP2-positive and GAD67-
positive neurons, and divided by the number of MAP2-positive neurons examined. 
The peak Ba 
21 currents were normalized to the cell membrane capacitance and 
presented as current density. To determine the basal Ca 
21 level and cytosolic Ca </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>oscillations, cells with the basal F340/F380 value within the average 6 2 3 standard 
deviation were included in analysis, and a Ca 
21 spike was defined with its amplitude 
being .1.2 times of the basal level. The number of Ca 
21 oscillation per minute and the 
changes in F340/F380 were used to calculate the frequency and amplitude. 
Spontaneous postsynaptic currents were analyzed using <rs id="software-3" type="software">Clampfit</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Molecular Devices</rs>) and <rs id="software-4" type="software">Mini Analysis Progrom</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Synaptosoft</rs>). The last 10 AP-evoked EPSCs 
and IPSCs were averaged to obtain the postsynaptic current amplitude which was 
used to construct the cumulative distribution as described previously </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>. PPF value was 
derived by the ratio of the second EPSC over the first EPSC and PPD value by the ratio 
of the second IPSC over the first IPSC. Statistical analysis was conducted using 
Student's t-test for the mean data and using Kolmogorov-Smirnov for the cumulative 
distribution of spontaneous and evoked EPSC and IPSC, with the difference to be 
considered significant at p , 0.05. </p>

<p> </p>



<p>
Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was support by research grants (No.11072132 and No.11272184) from National 
Natural Science Foundation of China. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>H.C.Z., L.H.J. and Q.Y.Z. conceived the research, designed the experiments, prepared and 
revised the manuscript. Q.Y.Z. and J.X. performed the experiments. Y.Y.Z. and B.L.L. 
analyzed the data. S.N.L., B.H., C.X.L. and W.Y.C. provided technical support. All authors 
discussed the results and commented on the manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Zhang, Q.-Y. et al. Stiff substrates enhance cultured neuronal 
network activity. Sci. Rep. 4, 6215; DOI:10.1038/srep06215 (2014). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
ShareAlike 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this 
article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated 
otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative 
Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder 
in order to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 6215 | DOI: 10.1038/srep06215 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>