<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4453652" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: There are limited data on surgical outcomes in gynaecological oncology. We report on predictors of complications 
in a multicentre prospective study. </p>

<p>Methods: Data on surgical procedures and resulting complications were contemporaneously recorded on consented patients 
in 10 participating UK gynaecological cancer centres. Patients were sent follow-up letters to capture any further complications. 
Post-operative (Post-op) complications were graded (I-V) in increasing severity using the Clavien-Dindo system. Grade I 
complications were excluded from the analysis. Univariable and multivariable regression was used to identify predictors of 
complications using all surgery for intra-operative (Intra-op) and only those with both hospital and patient-reported data for 
Post-op complications. </p>

<p>Results: Prospective data were available on 2948 major operations undertaken between April 2010 and February 2012. Median 
age was 62 years, with 35% obese and 20.4% ASA grade X3. Consultant gynaecological oncologists performed 74.3% of 
operations. Intra-op complications were reported in 139 of 2948 and Grade II-V Post-op complications in 379 of 1462 surgeries. </p>

<p>*Correspondence: Professor U Menon; E-mail: u.menon@ucl.ac.uk </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>These authors contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>Received 29 July 2014; revised 16 November 2014; accepted 30 November 2014; published online 23 December 2014 </p>

<p>&amp; 2015 Cancer Research UK. All rights reserved 0007 -0920/15 </p>

<p>FULL PAPER </p>

<p>Keywords: UKGOSOC; complications; surgery; gynaecological oncology; predictors; Intra-op; Post-op </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2015) 112, 475-484 | doi: 10.1038/bjc.2014.630 </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.630 </p>

<p>
The predictors of risk were different for Intra-op and Post-op complications. For Intra-op complications, previous abdominal 
surgery, metabolic/endocrine disorders (excluding diabetes), surgical complexity and final diagnosis were significant in univariable 
and multivariable regression (Po0.05), with diabetes only in multivariable regression (P ¼ 0.006). For Post-op complications, age, 
comorbidity status, diabetes, surgical approach, duration of surgery, and final diagnosis were significant in both univariable and 
multivariable regression (Po0.05). </p>

<p>Conclusions: This multicentre prospective audit benchmarks the considerable morbidity associated with gynaecological oncology 
surgery. There are significant patient and surgical factors that influence this risk. </p>

<p>Treatment outcomes are increasingly used by commissioners and 
consumers of health care to evaluate the performance of individual 
clinicians and institutions. This has led to some specialities 
developing clinician led national databases such as the National 
Surgical Quality Improvement Programme (NSQIP) in the United 
States (Khuri, 1998) and the national audits in cardiac surgery in 
England (Bridgewater, 2010). The hallmark of such initiatives is 
collection of comparable accurate data by clinical teams across 
hospitals, which make the calculation of risk-adjusted morbidity 
and mortality rates for surgical procedures possible. In gynaeco-
logical oncology, there is little such data available, with studies on 
surgical outcomes limited to single centre reports from United 
Kingdom (Das et al, 2006) and Australia (Kondalsamy 
Chennakesavan et al, 2009) and a three centre US ovarian cancer 
study (Aletti et al, 2007b) 
In England, the outcome data for gynaecological oncology 
procedures undertaken in the National Health Service (NHS) are 
limited to a few procedures such as hysterectomy and includes both 
benign and malignant disease. Surrogate markers of surgical 
performance such as duration of hospital admission ('length of stay'), 
readmission and repeat surgery ('return to theatre') rates collected as 
part of Hospital Episode Statistics (www.hesonline.nhs.uk) are used. 
The latter is an administrative national data repository containing 
details of all admissions, outpatient appointments and accident/ 
emergency attendances at NHS hospitals in England. It was initially 
established to evaluate/monitor resource allocation but is now 
increasingly being used to compare the quality of care provided by 
NHS hospitals, with summary data accessible to the public on the web 
(e.g., www.drfosterhealth.co.uk). However, studies comparing HES 
outcome data with clinician databases have shown that it is prone to 
error, omissions and inconsistencies (Westaby et al, 2007; Cockbain 
et al, 2012). One of the reasons for this is that there is little clinical 
input into data collection with coding officers capturing data from 
clinical notes, which are not uniformly standardised or structured 
across hospitals. 
To address this lack of high quality outcome data in 
gynaecological oncology, the United Kingdom Gynaecological 
Oncology Surgical Outcomes and Complications (UKGOSOC) 
study was undertaken to contemporaneously capture relevant data 
from participating gynaecological oncology centres. Here, we 
report on the type and incidence of intra-and post-operative 
complications in gynaecological oncology surgery and significant 
predictors of risk. </p>

<p>STUDY DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Certain aspects of the study design have been previously described 
(Iyer et al, 2013). A web-based custom built database was designed 
to capture data at various stages during the patient's surgical 
pathway, hosted on a secure server at the Trent Cancer Registry. 
The website was accessible only through N3 (N3.nhs.uk), which is 
a secure private network service used by NHS hospitals in England, 
Wales and Scotland. Advice was sought from the Joint UCL/UCLH 
Committees on the Ethics of Human Research in June 2008, which </p>

<p>confirmed that the study was similar to an audit and did not 
require formal ethical review. However, because patients were sent 
a follow-up letter (FUL) from the co-ordinating centre (CC) at 
University College London (UCL), informed consent was obtained 
(Supplementary File). Patients were given the option of providing 
either identifiable or anonymised data as per their preference. </p>

<p>Data collection. Training in the use of the web-based programme 
was provided by one of the CC team members either in person or 
remotely via web conferencing. Each centre user had a unique 
username and password. Clerical staff entered details of 
consecutive surgical patients (who had given prior consent) listed 
on the participating surgeon's list. Clinical staff entered data on 
surgery, Intra-op complications and the Post-op course (including 
any complications) contemporaneously online from the theatre 
and ward respectively. Once entered and saved, data could not be 
deleted or changed unless the clinical teams contacted the CC. 
All major surgical procedures performed on a gynaecological 
oncology theatre list were included in the study. In addition to surgery 
for malignancy, the procedures included surgery for benign conditions 
where there was a high pre-operative suspicion of cancer, cases with a 
complex surgical history which had been referred to the gynaecological 
oncology team and risk-reducing surgery. Minor diagnostic procedures 
and repeat surgery for complications were excluded. </p>

<p>Comorbidity. Pre-operative information on patients included age, 
comorbidity, American Society of Anaesthesiologists (ASA) grade 
(1-4) (Soliani, 1963), body mass index (BMI) and details of any 
previous surgery. Comorbidity (yes/no) was captured under the 
following categories: cardiac, coagulation/thrombosis, diabetes, 
gastrointestinal, hypertension, integumentary/dermatology, infec-
tions, low albumin (o30 g l 
À 1 ), metabolic/endocrine, neurological, 
psychiatric, respiratory, smoking, vascular and other neoplasms. </p>

<p>Surgery. Surgical procedures were captured using the relevant 
Office of the Population Censuses and Surveys (OPCS) Classifica-
tion of Interventions and Procedures version 4.5 and 4.6 codes. 
Surgical complexity was classified using a modification of the 
surgical scoring system (Supplementary Table 1) developed by 
Aletti et al (2007a) for ovarian cancer. Each individual procedure 
was given a score and the total score for the surgery was the sum of 
the individual scores. For example, if adhesiolysis (score 1) and 
ureterolysis (score 1) were performed along with a total abdominal 
hysterectomy (TAH, score 1), the surgical complexity score was 3. 
Surgeries were categorised into five groups of increasing complex-
ity based on the overall score (surgical complexity score 1 and 2: 
Group 1; 3 and 4: Group 2; 5 and 6: Group 3; 7 and 8: Group 4; 
48: Group 5). In addition to the procedure, the grade of operating 
surgeon, duration of surgery, the surgical approach (open/ 
laparoscopic/vulval-vaginal) and estimated blood loss (EBL) were 
also recorded. </p>

<p>Diagnosis. The diagnosis was recorded using the International 
Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems 
codes (ICD-10) (WHO, 1990). For the analysis, the final </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Predictors of complications in gynaecological oncological surgery </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.630 </p>

<p>histological diagnosis post-surgery was grouped into five cate-
gories: (1) ovarian which included primary ovarian/fallopian tube/ 
peritoneal, non-gynae primary and unknown primary cancers 
(where the preoperative diagnosis had been suspected to be an 
ovarian primary); (2) uterine which included primary endometrial 
cancer, carcinosarcoma and sarcomas of the uterus; (3) cervix 
(primary cervical cancer); (4) vulva which included primary vulval 
and vaginal cancers; and (5) benign. </p>

<p>Complications. A surgical complication was defined as 'an 
undesirable and unintended result of an operation affecting 
the patient that occurs as a direct result of the operation' (Sokol 
and Wilson, 2008). Post-op complications were defined as 
those complications occurring post-operatively up to 8 weeks 
after surgery. To capture Intra-op and Post-op complications, a 
pre-determined list of complications was compiled following 
literature review and several group discussions involving the 
participating surgeons (Supplementary Table 2). Intra-op compli-
cations were recorded by the surgeons in theatre. Estimated blood 
loss of 42.5 l was documented as Intra-op haemorrhage, 
regardless of whether haemorrhage was specifically identified as 
a complication by the operating surgeon. Completeness of Post-op 
complications was ensured by including both hospital-reported 
and patient-reported (via FULs) data as previously detailed (Iyer 
et al, 2013). Post-op complications were graded I-V using the 
Clavien and Dindo system based on the severity and intervention 
required (Dindo et al, 2004) (Supplementary Table 3). Only Grade 
II-V Post-op complications were included in the analysis. Grade 1 
complications were excluded as they were by definition 'any 
deviation from the normal post-operative course not requiring any 
pharmacological/surgical/radiological intervention' and therefore 
likely to be subject to individual variation and to have minimal 
impact on the post-operative course (Iyer et al, 2013). </p>

<p>Data cleaning. The database was checked on a weekly basis by the 
clinical research fellow (RI) at the CC and the centres were 
contacted for any missing data or for clarification/correction of 
erroneous data. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Statistical analysis was performed using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 12.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StataCorp</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">2012</rs>; StataCorp LP, College 
Station, TX, USA). Descriptive statistics were used to characterise 
the cohort. Surgery was used as the denominator for all the 
analyses as there were 38 women who had undergone two separate 
procedures as part of their treatment (repeat surgeries for 
complications were excluded). In addition, it was possible that 
age, comorbidity and ASA grade could change over time in an 
individual woman. All eligible surgeries were included to calculate 
the crude or unadjusted Intra-op complication rate (CR) and for 
the Post-op CR analysis was limited to those with both hospital-
and patient-reported data. To assess how each potential predictor 
affected the CR individually, univariable logistic regressions were 
performed separately for all predictors. For Intra-op complications, 
the independent variables included age, the presence of comorbid-
ities (yes/no), type of comorbidities, BMI (continuous variable and 
categorical-underweight, normal, overweight, obese and morbidly 
obese), ASA grade (1-4), previous abdominal surgery (yes/no), 
grade of operating surgeon (consultant, sub-specialty trainee, 
general obstetrics and gynaecology trainee), surgical approach 
(laparotomy/laparoscopy), surgical complexity (1-5) and final 
diagnosis (ovarian, uterine, cervix, vulva and benign). For Post-op 
complications, two additional variables-duration of surgery (in 
hours) and EBL (o500 mls, 500-1000 mls, 41000-2500 mls, 
42500 mls) were included. 
To create a risk prediction model for both the Intra-op and 
Post-op CRs, useful predictors were identified in a multivariable 
logistic regression model by running a stepwise regression with </p>

<p>backward elimination, with P (removal) ¼ 0.05. Significant cate-
gorical predictors with more than two categories were retained 
complete rather than dropping any insignificant categories. 
Goodness of fit was assessed using the Hosmer-Lemeshow test 
(with the data split into 10 groups based on estimated 
probabilities). Since 38 women had repeated outcomes, the data 
should formally be considered longitudinal (with very short 
panels). Another possible source of correlated errors was through 
clustering at each hospital. Hence, cluster robust standard errors 
were used and additionally, a random effects logistic regression 
model was fitted using the identified predictors to test the null 
hypothesis that the possible clustering factors were not significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>During the prospective UKGOSOC audit, undertaken between 1st 
April 2010 and 29th February 2012, 10 centres submitted a total of 
3026 operations. In all, 78 operations were excluded as they were 
minor diagnostic procedures (54) and surgeries for complications 
(24). The remaining 2948 operations involving 2910 women 
(38 had two surgeries each) were included in the analysis. Patient-
reported complications were available for 1462 (68%) of the 
surgeries and the CONSORT diagram for the latter has been 
detailed previously (Iyer et al, 2013). </p>

<p>Patients. The baseline characteristics of the women are detailed in 
Table 1 and the overall surgery details are described in Table 2. 
Overall, 33.5% (989) of the surgeries were for ovarian, 27.8% (820) 
for uterine, 7% (207) for cervical, 6% (176) for vulval cancer and 
25.6% (756) for benign pathologies. </p>

<p>Surgery for individual diagnostic categories. For ovarian can-
cers, 93.4% (924 out of 989) of the operations were open 
procedures and 6.6% (65 out of 989) were laparoscopic. In all, 
8.2% (81) of the procedures required a bowel resection and 5.8% 
(57) required upper abdominal debulking involving the diaphragm, 
spleen, liver, etc. 
For uterine cancers, 90% (738 out of 820) of the procedures 
were total hysterectomies ( ± lymphadenectomy) of which 58.4% 
(431 out of 738) were open procedures in which lymphadenectomy 
had been performed in 38.5% (166 out of 431). In all, 41.6% (307 
out of 738) of the hysterectomies were performed via the 
laparoscopic approach in which lymphadenectomy was performed 
in 26.8% (82 out of 307). The median BMI of women undergoing 
the open vs laparoscopic hysterectomy was similar (30.1; IQR 25.7-
35.3 vs 31.3; IQR 26.1-36.2, respectively). 
For cervical cancers, 26.6% (55 out of 207) of the procedures 
were open radical hysterectomies in which lymphadenectomy had 
been performed in 76.6% (42). In all, 24.2% (50 out of 207) were 
laparoscopic radical hysterectomies which included lymphadenect-
omy in 94% (47). The median BMI for the two approaches was 
similar, 26.3 (IQR 23.2-31.6) for open and 25 for laparoscopic 
(IQR 22.4-30.7). 
For vulval cancer, vulvectomy was the commonest procedure 
(95 out of 176, 54%), followed by vulvectomy with inguinofemoral 
lymphadenectomy (46 out of 176, 26.1%). 
For benign pathology, total abdominal hysterectomy (TAH) with 
bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy (BSO) þ omentectomy/lymphade-
nectomy/appendicectomy (318 out of 756, 42.1%) was the commonest 
procedure followed by simple TAH with BSO (178 out of 756, 23.5%). </p>

<p>Intra-operative complications. In total, 139 of 2948 surgeries had 
an Intra-op complication giving an overall Intra-op CR of 4.7% 
(95% CI 4.0-5.6). This included 143 individual Intra-op complica-
tions (i.e., four surgeries had two complications each) (Table 3). 
Intra-op haemorrhage (28.7%; 41 out of 143) followed by bladder 
(15.4%; 22 out of 143) and small bowel (15.4%; 22 out of 143) </p>

<p>Predictors of complications in gynaecological oncological surgery 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.630 </p>

<p>
injury were the most frequently occurring Intra-op complications. 
In the 2192 operations with a cancer diagnosis, 118 had an Intra-
op complication resulting in an Intra-op CR for cancer surgery of 
5.4% (95% CI 4.5-6.4) and this included 121 individual Intra-op 
complications. 
The highest Intra-op CR was for ovarian cancer surgery (78 out 
of 989; 7.9%, 95% CI 6.4-9.7). Two out of the three exenterations 
had an Intra-op complication (66.8%). The Intra-op CR was 19.8% 
(16 out of 81) for procedures with bowel resection and 14% (8 out 
of 57) for procedures involving upper abdominal surgery. 
Cervical cancer surgery had the second highest Intra-op CR (10 
out of 207, 4.8%; 95% CI 2.6-8.7). The Intra-op CR for the subset 
of open radical hysterectomies was 5.5% (3 out of 55) and was 
almost double (10%, 5 out of 50) for laparoscopic radical 
hysterectomies. Emergency laparotomy was required for only one 
(2%; 1 out of 50) of the laparoscopic radical hysterectomies. 
For uterine cancer surgery, the overall Intra-op CR was 3.4% (28 
out of 820, 95% CI 2.4-4.9). Where hysterectomy was undertaken, 
the Intra-op CR was 2.6% (11 out of 431) for the open approach 
and 3.6% (11 out of 307) for the laparoscopic approach. The Intra-
op CR for the subgroup of hysterectomies with lymphadenectomy 
was 1.8% (3 out of 166) for open and 7.3% (6 out of 82) for 
laparoscopic surgery. The unscheduled laparotomy rate for the 
laparoscopic approach was 1.6% (5 out of 307). 
Intra-op haemorrhage was the most common complication for 
ovarian, uterine and cervical cancer surgery (Table 3). </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline characteristics </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics (n ¼ 2948) </p>

<p>Age (in years, median, IQR) 
62 (50-71) </p>

<p>BMI </p>

<p>BMI (median, IQR) 
27.4 (23.8-32.4) </p>

<p>BMI category 
n (%) </p>

<p>Underweight (o18.5) 
41 (1.4) 
Normal (18.5-24.9) 
897 (30.4) 
Overweight (25-29.9) 
895 (30.4) 
Obese (30-39.9) 
805 (27.3) 
Morbidly obese (X40) 
236 (8) 
Missing 
74 (2.5) </p>

<p>ASA grade </p>

<p>1 and 2 
2341 (79.4) 
X3 
600 (20.4) 
Missing 
7 (0.2) </p>

<p>Comorbidity </p>

<p>0 
1105 (37.5) 
1-3 
1716 (58.2) 
43 
127 (4.3%) </p>

<p>Type of comorbidity </p>

<p>Hypertension 
973 (33) 
Cardiac 
308 (10) 
Diabetes 
298 (10) 
Respiratory 
287 (10) 
Musculoskeletal 
261 (9) 
Neurology/psychiatric 
208 (7) 
Other neoplasms 
148 (5) 
Coagulation/thrombosis 
116 (4) 
Gastrointestinal 
104 (4) 
Smoking 
95 (3) 
Vascular 
86 (3) 
Genitourinary 
52 (2) 
Autoimmune 
37 (1) 
Integumentary/Dermatology 
30 (1) 
Infections 
13 (0.4) 
Low albumin 
11 (0.4) </p>

<p>Previous abdominal surgery 
1025 (34.7) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ASA ¼ American Society of Anaesthesiologists; BMI ¼ body mass index; 
IQR ¼ interquartile range. </p>

<p>Table 2. Surgery details </p>

<p>Grade of operating surgeon 
n (%) </p>

<p>Consultant 
2191 (74.3) </p>

<p>Sub-specialty trainee 
573 (19.4) </p>

<p>General Obstetrics and Gynaecology Trainee 
108 (3.7) </p>

<p>Missing 
76 (2.6) </p>

<p>Diagnosis 
n (%) </p>

<p>Ovarian </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>989 (33.5) </p>

<p>Uterine </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>820 (27.8) </p>

<p>Cervical 
207 (7.0) </p>

<p>Vulval </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>176 (6.0) </p>

<p>Benign 
756 (25.7) </p>

<p>Surgical approach 
n (%) </p>

<p>Open 
2001 (67.9) </p>

<p>Laparoscopic elective proceed to laparotomy 
68 (2.3) </p>

<p>Laparoscopic emergency proceed to laparotomy 
11 (0.3) </p>

<p>Laparoscopic </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>670 (22.7) </p>

<p>Vulval/vaginal procedures 
198 (6.7) </p>

<p>Duration of surgery (minutes) 
Median, IQR </p>

<p>Open procedures 
120 (90-167) </p>

<p>Laparoscopic procedures 
120 (85-170) </p>

<p>Vulval/vaginal procedures 
87 (50-148) </p>

<p>Surgical complexity 
n (%) </p>

<p>Group 1 (complexity score 1 and 2) 
1398 (47) </p>

<p>Group 2 (complexity score 3 and 4) 
982 (33) </p>

<p>Group 3 (Complexity score 5 and 6) 
430 (15) </p>

<p>Group 4 (complexity score 7 and 8) 
93 (3) </p>

<p>Group 5 (complexity score 48) 
45 (2) </p>

<p>Surgical procedures 
n (%) </p>

<p>TAH ± BSO þ omentectomy /appendicectomy/ 
lymphadenectomy/peritonectomy </p>

<p>1202 (40.8) </p>

<p>TAH ± BSO/USO 
448 (15.2) </p>

<p>Radical hysterectomy ± BSO ± lymphadenectomy 
106 (3.6) </p>

<p>TAH/BSO/omentectomy þ bowel resection 
94 (3.2) </p>

<p>TAH þ BSO þ omentectomy þ upper abdominal 
surgery </p>

<p>58 (2.0) </p>

<p>Exenterations±conduits 
16 (0.5) </p>

<p>Open lymphadenectomy 
14 (0.5) </p>

<p>Exploratory/abandoned procedure 
29 (1.0) </p>

<p>Other open procedures 
105 (3.6) </p>

<p>TLH/LAVH þ BSO 
306 (10.4) </p>

<p>TLH or LAVH ± omental biopsy þ lymphadenectomy 
262 (8.9) </p>

<p>Laparoscopic radical hysterectomy 
±lymphadenectomy </p>

<p>65 (2.2) </p>

<p>Laparoscopic lymphadenectomy 
30 (1.0) </p>

<p>Other laparoscopic procedures 
18 (0.6) </p>

<p>Vulvectomy (radical/simple) 
113 (3.8) </p>

<p>Vulvectomy þ Inguinofemoral lymphadenectomy 
46 (1.6) </p>

<p>Inguinofemoral lymphadenectomy 
18 (0.6) </p>

<p>Vaginectomy 
12 (0.4) </p>

<p>Other vulval/vaginal procedures 
6 (0.2) </p>

<p>Length of stay 
Days, median 
(IQR) </p>

<p>Open procedures 
4 (3-6) </p>

<p>Laparoscopic 
2 (1-2) </p>

<p>Vulval/vaginal procedures 
4 (2-7) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: BSO ¼ bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy; LAVH ¼ laparoscopic assisted 
vaginal hysterectomy; TAH ¼ total abdominal hysterectomy; TLH ¼ total laparoscopic 
hysterectomy; USO ¼ unilateral salpingo-oophorectomy. 
a Includes primary ovarian, fallopian tube, primary peritoneal, synchronous, non-gynae </p>

<p>primary cancers. 
b Includes primary endometrial cancer, carcinosarcoma and sarcoma of the uterus. 
c Includes primary vulval and vaginal cancers. 
d Includes total laparoscopic and laparoscopic assisted vaginal procedures. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Predictors of complications in gynaecological oncological surgery </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.630 </p>

<p>There were only two surgeries with an Intra-op complication for 
vulval cancer (2 out of 176, 1.1%; 95% CI 3.1-4.1) and both were 
bladder injuries. The Intra-op CR (21 out of 756, 2.8%; 95% CI 1.8-
4.2) was lower for benign conditions when compared with ovarian, 
uterine and cervix cancer surgery. Bladder and large bowel injuries 
were the most commonly occurring complications (4 out of 756, 0.5%). 
The Intra-op CR increased with increasing surgical complexity 
with rates of 2.9% (41 out of 1398) for a surgical score of o3, 4.4% 
(43 out of 982) for a score of 3-4, 7.9% (34 out of 430) for a score 
of 5-6, 12.9% (12 out of 93) for a score of 7-8 and 20% (9 out of 
45) for a score of 48. Overall, the highest Intra-op CR was seen 
for procedures with bowel resection (18 out of 94, 19.1%) and 
exenterations (3 out of 16, 18.8%) followed by debulking surgery 
requiring upper abdominal resection (8 out of 58, 13.8%). </p>

<p>Post-operative complications. Both hospital and patient reported 
data on Post-op complications were available for 1462 surgeries. 
There were 200 hospital-reported and 252 patient-reported Grade 
II-V complications in 379 surgeries resulting in an overall Post-op 
CR of 25.9% (95% CI 23.7-28.2) as previously reported (Iyer et al, 
2013). Out of the total 452 Grade II-V complications, wound 
(140 out of 452, 30.9%) and other infections (126 out of 452, 27.8%) 
were the most common (Table 4). In the 1067 operations leading to a 
cancer diagnosis, 289 had a Post-op complication resulting in a Post-
op CR for cancer surgery of 27.1% (95% CI 24.5-29.8). 
Surgery for vulval cancer had the highest Post-op CR (33 out of 79, 
41.8% 95% CI 31.5-52.8). Wound breakdown/infection (26 out of 79, 
32.9%) was the most common complication. In over one in three 
procedures with inguinofemoral lymphadenectomy, the main com-
plication was lymphocysts/lymphoedema (15 out of 42, 35.7%). 
Cervical cancer surgery had a similar Post-op CR (32 out of 
80, 40%; 95% CI 29.9-50.9) to vulval cancer surgery with similar 
rates for open (11 out of 27, 40.7%) vs laparoscopic radical </p>

<p>hysterectomy ± lymphadenectomy (8 out of 20, 40%). Infections 
(excluding wound) were the most common complication 
(7 out of 80, 8.8%). When compared with vulval cancer surgery, 
the incidence of lymphocysts/lymphoedema was lower at 12.7% 
(7 out of 55 procedures with lymphadenectomy). 
Ovarian cancer surgery had a significantly lower Post-op CR 
(128 out of 481, 26.6%, 95% CI 22.9-30.7) when compared with 
vulval and cervical cancer surgery. Exenterations (one out of two; 
50%), procedures including upper abdominal surgery (11 out of 
26, 42.3%) and bowel resection (11 out of 35, 31.4%) had the 
highest rates. Infections (excluding wound) remained the most 
common (8.5%; 41 out of 481) complication. 
The Post-op CR for uterine cancer surgery was 22.5% (96 out 
of 427, 22.5%; 95% CI 18.8-26.7). The Post-op CR for 
hysterectomies ± lymphadenectomy was 26.8% (63 out of 235) 
for the open and 16.2% (25 out of 154) for the laparoscopic 
approach. For the subset of hysterectomies with lymphadenect-
omy, the Post-op CR was 37.9% (36 out of 95) for the open and 
19.6% (10 out of 51) for the laparoscopic approach. The incidence 
of lymphocysts/lymphoedema was 7.1% (11 out of 156) for 
procedures with lymphadenectomy, a lower rate than that for 
cervical and vulval cancers. 
For benign pathology, the Post-op CR was 22.8% (90 out of 395; 
95% CI 18.9-27.2). TAH with BSO had the highest Post-op CR 
(29 out of 96, 30.2%) followed by Total Laparoscopic Hysterectomy 
( ± BSO) (10 out of 38, 26.3%). Wound breakdown (38 out of 395, 
9.6%) and infections (excluding wound) (33 out of 395, 8.4%) were 
the most common type of complications (Table 4). </p>

<p>Grade of complications. In total, 402 (88.9%) out of the 452 
complications in this cohort of 1462 surgeries were Grade II and 50 
(11.1%) were Grade III or worse (8 Grade IIIa, 30 Grade IIIb, 10 
Grade IVa and 2 Grade V) (Supplementary Table 4). </p>

<p>Table 3. Intra-operative complications </p>

<p>Intra-operative complications (no. of surgery ¼ 2948) </p>

<p>Primary cancer site </p>

<p>Complication category 
Total no. (% with complication) 
Ovary </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Uterine </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Cervix 
Vulva </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Benign </p>

<p>Intra-operative haemorrhage 
41 (28.7) 
27 
8 
3 
3 </p>

<p>Bladder injury 
22 (15.4) 
11 
3 
2 
2 
4 </p>

<p>GI tract injury-small bowel 
22 (15.4) 
16 
4 
2 </p>

<p>GI tract injury-large bowel 
11 (7.7) 
4 
2 
1 
4 </p>

<p>Vascular injury 
13 (9.1) 
7 
2 
1 
3 </p>

<p>Vaginal tear 
7 (4.9) 
5 
2 </p>

<p>Cardiac 
6 (4.2) 
2 
1 
3 </p>

<p>Diaphragmatic injury 
5 (3.5) 
5 </p>

<p>Ureteric injury 
5 (3.5) 
1 
2 
1 
1 </p>

<p>Splenic injury 
3 (2.1) 
3 </p>

<p>Gall bladder injury 
1 (0.7) 
1 </p>

<p>Liver laceration 
1 (0.7) 
1 </p>

<p>Nerve injury 
1 (0.7 
1 </p>

<p>Respiratory 
1 (0.7) 
1 </p>

<p>Uterine perforation 
1 (0.7) 
1 </p>

<p>Anaphylaxis 
1 (0.7) 
1 </p>

<p>Other 
2 (1.4) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>Total no. of intra-op complications (% of total surgery) 
143 (4.9%) 
79 (7.9%) 
30 (3.4%) 
10 (4.8%) 2 (1.1%) 22 (2.8%) </p>

<p>Total no. of surgeries 
2948 
989 
820 
207 
176 
756 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Includes primary ovarian, fallopian tube, primary peritoneal, synchronous, non-gynae primary cancers. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Includes primary endometrial cancer, carcinosarcoma and sarcoma of the uterus. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Includes primary vulval and vaginal cancers. </p>

<p>Predictors of complications in gynaecological oncological surgery 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.630 </p>

<p>
There were 48 re-admissions (48 out of 1462, 3.6%), 34 returns 
to theatre (30 Grade IIIb and 4 Grade IVa; 2.3%) and 10 (2.2%) 
unscheduled admissions to intensive care. There were two (0.14%) 
peri-operative deaths reported in this cohort, one due to cardiac 
failure and the other secondary to bowel perforation. </p>

<p>Predictors of complications </p>

<p>Intra-op CR. In univariable analysis, the significant predictors of 
Intra-op complications were previous abdominal surgery, 
metabolic/endocrine conditions excluding diabetes (patient 
factors), surgical complexity and final diagnosis (Table 5, 
Supplementary Table 5). In multivariable regression, all four 
factors continued to be significant with previous abdominal 
surgery (OR ¼ 1.6), increasing surgical complexity (Po0.0005) 
and ovarian cancer diagnosis (Po0.0005) increasing risk along 
with diabetes (OR ¼ 2) and the presence of metabolic/endocrine 
disorders (excluding diabetes) (OR ¼ 0.35) associated with 
decreased risk of Intra-op complication (Table 5). </p>

<p>Post-op-CR. In univariable regression, the significant patient 
factors associated with increased risk of Post-op complications 
were diabetes, the presence of any comorbidity, previous 
abdominal surgery and increasing ASA grade, age and BMI 
(Table 6, Supplementary Table 6). Among the Intra-op factors, 
surgical complexity, surgery duration and EBL increased risk </p>

<p>whereas laparoscopic compared with open approach reduced 
the likelihood of a Post-op complication. As with Intra-
op complications, final diagnosis was a significant predictor. In 
multivariate regression, the only patient factors that increased risk 
were the presence of comorbidity (OR ¼ 1.3) and diabetes 
(OR ¼ 1.6). Significant Intra-op variables were laparoscopic 
approach that was associated with decreased risk of Post-op 
complications (OR ¼ 0.65) and duration of surgery in hours that 
increased risk (OR ¼ 1.3). Unlike for Intra-op complications, 
increased risk was associated with a diagnosis of vulval/vaginal 
(OR ¼ 2.4) and cervical cancer (OR ¼ 1.7). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This prospective multicentre UK study is the largest published 
study that we are aware of which reports on the morbidity 
associated with surgery undertaken in gynaecological oncology 
centres. Whilst the overall Intra-op CR was 4.7%, it was 5.4% when 
limited to confirmed malignancies. Previous abdominal surgery, 
diabetes, surgical complexity and final diagnosis were significant 
predictors of increased risk. The Post-op CR was similar for overall 
(26%) and for confirmed malignancies (27%). The only common 
predictors of both Intra-op and Post-op complications were 
diabetes and final diagnosis. Other significant associations with 
Post-op complications were age, the presence of comorbidity, </p>

<p>Table 4. Hospital and patient-reported post-operative complications </p>

<p>Grade II-V hospital-and patient-reported post-operative complications (no. of surgery ¼ 1462) </p>

<p>Primary cancer site </p>

<p>Complication category 
Total no. (% with complication) 
Ovary </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Uterine </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Cervix 
Vulva </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Benign </p>

<p>Wound breakdown 
140 (30.1) 
37 
35 
4 
26 
38 </p>

<p>Infection 
126 (27.8) 
41 
30 
17 
5 
33 </p>

<p>Lymphocyst/lymphoedema 
39 (8.6) 
6 
11 
7 
15 </p>

<p>Bladder 
17 (3.8) 
2 
7 
2 
6 </p>

<p>Abscess/haematoma 
14 (3.1) 
6 
2 
2 
4 </p>

<p>Ileus 
16 (3.5) 
11 
3 
2 </p>

<p>Bowel obstruction 
7 (1.5) 
5 
1 
1 </p>

<p>Bowel perforation 
2 (0.4) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>Bowel-other 
11 (2.4) 
5 
1 
1 
4 </p>

<p>Primary haemorrhage 
5 (1.1) 
2 
2 
1 </p>

<p>Secondary haemorrhage 
10 (2.2) 
2 
3 
1 
4 </p>

<p>Fistula 
7 (1.5) 
4 
1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>Anastomotic leak 
2 (0.4) 
2 </p>

<p>Cardiac 
7 (1.5) 
4 
2 
1 </p>

<p>Pulmonary embolism 
5 (1.1) 
3 
2 </p>

<p>Deep vein thrombosis 
5 (1.1) 
2 
1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>Respiratory 
6 (1.3) 
3 
2 
1 </p>

<p>Neurological 
4 (0.9) 
1 
3 </p>

<p>Psychiatric 
2 (0.4) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>Hernia 
4 (0.9) 
3 
1 </p>

<p>Ureteric obstruction 
1 (0.2) 
1 </p>

<p>Other 
22 (4.9) 
8 
5 
2 
1 
6 </p>

<p>Total no. of post-operative complications 
(% of total surgery) </p>

<p>452 
(30.9) </p>

<p>148 
(30.7) </p>

<p>112 
(26.2) </p>

<p>38 
(47.5) </p>

<p>47 
(59.5) </p>

<p>107 
(27.1) </p>

<p>Total no. of surgeries 
1462 
481 
427 
80 
79 
395 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Includes primary ovarian, fallopian tube, primary peritoneal, synchronous, non-gynae primary cancers. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Includes primary endometrial cancer, carcinosarcoma and sarcoma of the uterus. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Includes primary vulval and vaginal cancers. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Predictors of complications in gynaecological oncological surgery </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.630 </p>

<p>surgical approach and duration of surgery. Gynaecological 
oncology surgery is associated with considerable morbidity and 
our study provides much needed estimates of complication risk 
associated with procedures for specific cancers to counsel patients 
and benchmark surgical performance. 
Strengths of UKGOSOC include prospective data collection 
using standard forms, large sample size and multicentre design 
with 10 participating gynaecological cancer centres. Data capture 
from both clinicians and patients ensured completeness of Post-op 
complications. An online database, accessible to the clinical team 
whether they were in theatre, wards or outpatient departments 
facilitated capture of surgical data and complication events 
contemporaneously. Validity of the data was ensured by weekly 
review by an independent clinician at the CC, who contacted the 
teams on a regular basis to retrieve missing data and 'clean' 
erroneous entries. While clinician-led databases collect more 
accurate and complete information compared with administrative 
databases like HES (RCOG, 2012), this was a very resource 
intensive process. The heavy reliance of UKGOSOC on the clinical 
teams was a limitation. Most centres, especially those relying on 
junior trainees on four to six monthly rotations, struggled with 
prospective data entry. 
As this was a prospective study rather than an audit, patient 
consent was required. In keeping with majority of clinical studies, 
we are unable to provide an accurate number of women who were 
approached. Therefore, it is likely that all consecutive patients on 
operating lists have not been included. In 10% of surgeries, patients </p>

<p>had Metabolic/Endocrine disorders other than diabetes. This 
mainly included hypercholesterolaemia and thyroid dysfunction 
and was a predictor of reduced intra-operative CR. We are unable 
to explain this and as previous studies have not looked at this 
separately, there is no data for comparison. Some pre-operative 
biochemical markers such as serum albumin and liver enzymes 
that have been reported to be predictors of surgical complications 
(Khuri, 1998; Copeland, 2002; Aletti et al, 2007b; Kondalsamy 
Chennakesavan et al, 2009) could not be included in our study as 
they are not routinely assayed in all patient undergoing 
gynaecological oncology surgery in United Kingdom. 
Our overall Intra-op CR of 4.7% was lower than the 8% reported 
from a tertiary gynaecological oncology centre in Australia 
(Kondalsamy Chennakesavan et al, 2009), which we feel was 
probably influenced by the small sample size of 381 women in their 
study compared with nearly 3000 in ours (Kondalsamy 
Chennakesavan et al, 2009). No other comparable figures were 
available in the published literature. Rates for gynaecological 
malignancy alone were lower than Intra-op CRs in women 
undergoing pelvic surgery for rectal cancer surgery (12%) (van 
der Pas et al, 2013). The lower incidence of Intra-op complications 
was paralleled by the lower (1.6%) laparoscopic to emergency 
laparotomy conversion rates compared with the Australian 
study (2.4%) and the rectal cancer surgery multicentre trial 
(16%) (van der Pas et al, 2013). Lower CRs in surgeries for 
gynaecological compared with colorectal cancer are likely to be 
related to the lower rates of bowel resection and possible </p>

<p>Table 5. Significant predictors of intra-operative complications in univariable and multivariable regression </p>

<p>Variable 
Odds ratio 
95% Confidence interval 
Standard error 
P-value </p>

<p>Univariable analysis of risk factors for intra-operative complications as the outcome </p>

<p>Previous abdominal surgery 
1.74 
1.239-2.455 
0.304 
0.001 </p>

<p>Metabolic/endocrine (excluding diabetes) 
0.383 
0.168-0.876 
0.162 
0.023 </p>

<p>Surgical complexity group </p>

<p>1 
1 
2 
1.516 
0.980-2.344 
0.337 
0.061 
3 
2.841 
1.779-4.539 
0.679 
0.000 
4 
4.903 
2.481-9.690 
1.704 
0.000 
5 
8.274 
3.741-18.301 
3.351 
0.000 </p>

<p>Joint significance for all the categories in surgical complexity 
0.000 </p>

<p>Final diagnosis </p>

<p>Ovary 
1 </p>

<p>Uterine 
0.413 
0.265-0.643 
0.093 
0.000 </p>

<p>Benign 
0.334 
0.204-0.546 
0.084 
0.000 </p>

<p>Vulva 
0.134 
0.033-0.551 
0.097 
0.005 </p>

<p>Cervix 
0.593 
0.302-1.166 
0.205 
0.130 </p>

<p>Joint significance for all the categories in final diagnosis 
0.000 </p>

<p>Multivariable logistic regression model for intra-operative complication as the outcome </p>

<p>Diabetes 
2.015 
1.223-3.324 
0.514 
0.006 </p>

<p>Metabolic/endocrine disorders (excluding diabetes) 
0.351 
0.152-0.809 
0.150 
0.014 </p>

<p>Previous abdominal surgery 
1.561 
1.099-2.219 
0.280 
0.013 </p>

<p>Surgical complexity group </p>

<p>1 
1 
2 
1.302 
0.834-2.033 
0.296 
0.246 
3 
2.311 
1.396-3.826 
0.594 
0.001 
4 
3.397 
1.660-6.951 
1.241 
0.001 
5 
5.399 
2.335-12.48 
2.309 
0.000 </p>

<p>Final diagnosis </p>

<p>Ovary 
1 
Uterine 
0.555 
0.348-0.887 
0.133 
0.014 
Cervix 
0.599 
0.296-1.212 
0.215 
0.154 
Vulva 
0.193 
0.046-0.805 
0.141 
0.024 
Benign 
0.468 
0.278-0.787 
0.124 
0.004 </p>

<p>Predictors of complications in gynaecological oncological surgery 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.630 </p>

<p>
anastomosis and resultant lower incidence of anastomotic leaks, 
peritonitis or other bowel complications. In UKGOSOC, only 4.2% 
(91 out of 2192) of the cancer surgeries required a bowel resection. 
Previous abdominal surgery was a significant predictor of Intra-
op complications probably due to intra-abdominal adhesions 
following the previous surgery. This is in keeping with results of a </p>

<p>prospective multicentre Finnish study (FINHYST) of over 5000 
hysterectomies for benign indications (Brummer et al, 2011), 
which found that prior laparotomy (OR ¼ 1.1) but not caesarean 
section or laparoscopy increased the risk of major complications. 
In the latter study, adhesiolysis during surgery was the strongest 
single risk factor (OR ¼ 2.4). In bowel surgery, previous three or </p>

<p>Table 6. Significant predictors of post-operative complications in univariable and multivariable regression </p>

<p>Variable 
Odds ratio 
95% Confidence interval 
Standard error 
P-value </p>

<p>Univariable analysis for post-operative complications as the outcome </p>

<p>Age 
1.014 
1.002-1.026 
0.006 
0.027 
Comorbidity status (yes/no) 
1.477 
1.049-2.077 
0.257 
0.025 
Diabetes 
1.916 
1.233-2.977 
0.431 
0.004 
Previous abdominal surgery 
1.465 
1.068-2.011 
0.237 
0.018 
Body mass index (continuous variable) 
1.023 
1.001-1.045 
0.011 
0.039 </p>

<p>Body mass index (categorical variable) </p>

<p>Underweight (o19.9) 
1 
Normal (19.9-24.9) 
0.709 
0.156-3.231 
0.549 
0.657 
Overweight (25-29.9) 
0.888 
0.196-4.017 
0.684 
0.877 
Obese (30-39.9) 
1.359 
0.302-6.120 
1.044 
0.689 
Morbidly obese (440) 
0.948 
0.193-4.652 
0.769 
0.947 </p>

<p>Joint significance for all the categories in BMI 
0.037 </p>

<p>ASA grade (1-3) </p>

<p>ASA grade 1 
1 
ASA grade 2 
1.623 
1.0422-2.527 
0.367 
0.032 
ASA grade X3 
2.178 
1.315-3.608 
0.561 
0.002 </p>

<p>Joint significance for all the categories in ASA grade 
0.008 </p>

<p>Duration of surgery 
1.496 
1.324-1.690 
0.093 
0.000 </p>

<p>Approach for surgery </p>

<p>Open 
1 
Laparoscopic 
0.506 
0.326-0.787 
0.114 
0.002 </p>

<p>Surgical complexity group </p>

<p>1 
1 
2 
1.719 
1.196-2.469 
0.318 
0.003 
3 
1.896 
1.198-3.003 
0.445 
0.006 
4 
2.652 
1.218-5.774 
1.053 
0.014 
5 
6.562 
2.454-17.543 
3.292 
0.000 </p>

<p>Joint significance for all the categories in surgical complexity 
0.000 </p>

<p>Estimated blood loss (EBL) </p>

<p>o500 mls 
1 
500-1000 mls 
2.554 
1.737-3.756 
0.502 
0.000 
41000-2500 mls 
2.443 
1.381-4.319 
0.710 
0.002 
42500 mls 
0.797 
0.102-6.226 
0.710 
0.829 </p>

<p>Joint significance for all the categories in EBL 
0.000 </p>

<p>Final diagnosis </p>

<p>Ovary 
1 
Uterine 
0.609 
0.407-0.914 
0.126 
0.016 
Cervix 
1.623 
0.908-2.901 
0.481 
0.102 
Vulva 
2.024 
1.158-3.535 
0.576 
0.013 
Benign 
0.41 
0.258-0.652 
0.097 
0.000 </p>

<p>Joint significance for all the categories in final diagnosis 
0.000 </p>

<p>Multivariable logistic regression model for post-operative complication as the outcome </p>

<p>Comorbidity status (Yes/No) 
1.338 
1.012-1.769 
0.191 
0.041 
Diabetes 
1.642 
1.113-2.421 
0.325 
0.012 
Age 
0.989 
0.979-1.000 
0.005 
0.052 
Laparoscopic approach 
0.653 
0.469-0.909 
0.110 
0.012 
Duration of surgery 
1.285 
1.149-1.439 
0.074 
0.000 </p>

<p>Final diagnosis </p>

<p>Ovary 
1 
Uterine 
0.998 
0.716-1.392 
0.169 
0.992 
Cervix 
1.664 
0.958-2.891 
0.469 
0.071 
Vulva 
2.398 
1.438-3.999 
0.626 
0.001 
Benign 
1.046 
0.738-1.481 
0.186 
0.802 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ASA ¼ American Society of Anaesthesiologists; BMI ¼ body mass index. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Predictors of complications in gynaecological oncological surgery </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.630 </p>

<p>more laparotomies have been found to increase risk of enterotomy 
by tenfold (OR ¼ 10.4) (Van Der Krabben et al, 2000). The other 
comorbidity that significantly increased Intra-op complication risk 
was diabetes (OR ¼ 2). While several studies have demonstrated 
the association of diabetes with increased Post-op morbidity 
(Pull et al, 2012; Gimenes et al, 2013; Fischer et al, 2014) this is the 
first study to demonstrate its effect specifically on Intra-op 
complications. 
Intra-op CRs increased with surgical complexity with the 
highest rates for those procedures with an overall surgical 
complexity score of 48. In Aletti's study on ovarian cancer 
surgery as well as in the Australian study (Kondalsamy 
Chennakesavan et al, 2009), surgical complexity was found to be 
a significant predictor of overall morbidity. To capture complexity 
accurately in UKGOSOC, the surgical complexity scoring system 
for ovarian cancer developed by Aletti et al (2007a,b) was modified 
to include procedures for all gynaecological cancers and stratified 
into five rather than the three originally described (low, 
intermediate and high) groups as preliminary analysis had 
demonstrated it to be a key predictor. Although a higher 
proportion of procedures were of low complexity in UKGOSOC, 
we feel that direct comparisons with the Australian study are 
difficult to make as surgical complexity was defined differently in 
the two studies. Surgery for ovarian cancer had the highest crude 
Intra-op CR at 8% which was double of that seen for the 
other gynaecological cancers. This is mainly influenced by the 
complexity of ovarian cancer surgery when compared with that for 
the others (11% of ovarian cancer surgery had an overall 
complexity score of 45 when compared with 1-3% of the 
procedures for the other gynaecological malignancies). 
When compared with Intra-op-CR, the Post-op-CR was much 
higher with approximately one in four surgeries having a Post-op 
complication. However, most of the complications were Grade II, 
which required medical therapy only as previously reported (Iyer 
et al, 2013). Vulval cancer (OR ¼ 2.4) when compared with other 
cancers and benign diagnosis posed the highest risk of developing a 
Post-op complication. Vulval cancer surgery also had the highest 
crude Post-op-CR (41.8%) with wound infection/breakdown the 
commonest complication (32.9%) followed by lymphocysts/lym-
phoedema (18.9%). These rates were comparable to that reported in 
a recent review of complications of vulval cancer surgery where 
wound infection rates ranged from 17% to 39% and lymphoedema 
rates between 14% and 48% (Wills and Obermair, 2013). The 
incidence of intra-operative ureteric and bladder injury and post-
operative bladder complications was highest for cervical cancer 
surgery when compared with other gynaecological cancers. How-
ever, this difference was not statistically significant (Supplementary 
Tables 7 and 8). This is likely to be related to the higher proportion 
of radical hysterectomies undertaken for cervical cancer. Overall, 
however, the rates are lower than those reported elsewhere, as in the 
United Kingdom, majority of radical hysterectomies are Type II 
rather than Type III as they are undertaken in patients with smaller 
tumours (Mota et al, 2008). Tumours of 44 cm are more likely to be 
treated with chemo-radiation. 
As previously reported, in studies comparing open vs laparo-
scopic approaches for endometrial and cervical cancer surgery 
(Walker et al, 2009; Park et al, 2013), the latter reduced the 
likelihood of a Post-op complication in our series too. This is 
probably one of the main drivers for the increasing use of 
laparoscopic surgery in gynaecological oncology. Surgical complex-
ity however was not a significant predictor of Post-op unlike Intra-
op complications. Instead, duration of surgery (OR ¼ 1.3) was 
significant. This has also been noted to increase the risk of Post-
operative infections following total knee arthroplasty (Peersman 
et al, 2006). 
In addition to being a significant predictor of Intra-op 
complications, diabetes (OR ¼ 1.6) was also found to be significant </p>

<p>in predicting Post-op complications. In the Australian study, while 
diabetes was significant in univariable analysis, it was not found to 
be so in multivariable analysis (Kondalsamy Chennakesavan et al, 
2009). However, studies in other specialties such as plastic surgery 
(breast reconstruction surgery) and orthopaedic surgery have 
shown diabetes to be a significant predictor of surgical complica-
tions, particularly wound infections (Pull et al, 2012; Liang et al, 
2013; Fischer et al, 2014). Diabetes has also been found to increase 
the risk of Post-op complications following coronary artery bypass 
surgery (Gimenes et al, 2013). Our data indicate that the presence 
of any comorbidity (OR ¼ 1.3) predicted Post-op complications 
on multivariable analysis. Performance status as measured by ASA 
grade was significant only on univariable analysis. This is in 
contrast to the Australian study and Aletti's study where ASA 
grade was a significant independent predictor for overall morbidity 
(Aletti et al, 2007a; Kondalsamy Chennakesavan et al, 2009). 
The 18-month prospective study was driven by the determina-
tion and desire of those involved to obtain robust data. National 
data collection in this manner without dedicated administrative 
support would not be feasible. For such data to be collected on a 
national scale, one of the options would be to incorporate some of 
the key audit fields into existing data sources coupled with routine 
central follow-up of patients using validated questionnaires. 
Despite the logistical issues, internal auditing using the system of 
clinician led data capture adopted in this study might still be 
preferable and acceptable to clinicians rather than external 
regulations that might be imposed in the foreseeable future 
(Hacker, 2011). </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>This the first large multicentre prospective study to investigate the 
morbidity associated with gynaecological oncology surgery. 
A set of robust complications data has been generated, which 
can be utilised for future benchmarking surgical practice. There are 
significant patient and surgical factors that influence risk, raising 
the need for risk-adjusted rates to compare outcomes. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The study was supported by researchers at the National Institute 
for Health Research, University College London Hospitals 
Biomedical Research Centre. We would like to thank the Eve 
appeal for their support of the study. We are very grateful to all the 
women who participated in this study and to all the medical, 
nursing and administrative staff who worked on UKGOSOC. In 
addition, we would like to thank the following members of the 
hospital teams who contributed to data collection: Sara Roberts, 
Philip Toon, Richard Peevor (Betsi Cadwaladr University Health 
Board), Charlie Chan, Janos Balega, Kavita Singh, Sudha Sundar, 
Ahmed Elattar, Esther Moss, Mary Wright (City Hospital 
Birmingham), Alta Viljoen (Cheltenham General Hospital), 
Branislav Potancok, Mohamed Ismail, Vivek Nama, Ruth Lomas, 
Cheryl Walke (East Kent University Hospital NHS Foundation 
Trust), Deborah Woods, Alison Garnham (Ipswich General 
Hospital), Ketan Gajjar, Deborah Parkinson (Royal Preston 
Hospital), Emma Arthur, Arnold Kruse (Royal Cornwall Hospital), 
and Kostas Doufekas (University College London Hospital). </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Predictors of complications in gynaecological oncological surgery 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.630 </p>



<p>
This work is published under the standard license to publish agree-
ment. After 12 months the work will become freely available and 
the license terms will switch to a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on British Journal of Cancer website (http://www.nature.com/bjc) </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Predictors of complications in gynaecological oncological surgery </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.630 </p>

</text></tei>