<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4515454" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Internal snapping hip syndrome is a condition produced 
by the iliopsoas tendon snapping over the iliopectineal 
eminence or the femoral head. This condition is caused by 
hypertrophy or hyperactivity of the iliocapsularis, chronic 
inflammation of the iliopsoas tendon and bursa, overhang-
ing acetabular cup, abnormal angulation of the tendon, a 
large femoral head, and high femoral anteversion. </p>

<p>outcomes of arthroscopic iliopsoas tendon release for painful internal snapping hip with concomitant hip pathologies. </p>

<p>Methods: Between January 2009 and December 2011, we performed arthroscopic iliopsoas tendon release and related surgeries </p>

<p>in 25 patients (20 men and 5 women; mean age, 32 years; range, 17 to 53 years) with combined intraarticular hip pathologies. The </p>

<p>patients were followed for a minimum of 2 years postoperatively. Clinical and radiological evaluations were performed. </p>

<p>Results: Snapping sounds had disappeared by the 2-year follow-up in 24 of the 25 patients. All patients who had presented with </p>

<p>loss of flexion strength postoperatively showed recovery at postoperative week 6 to 10. Harris hip score improved from 65 points </p>

<p>(range, 46 to 86 points) preoperatively to 84 points (range, 67 to 98 points) postoperatively (p &lt; 0.001). Seven hips (28%) had an </p>

<p>excellent score, 15 hips (60%) a good score, 2 hips (8%) a fair score, and one hip (4%) a poor score (p &lt; 0.001). The Tonnis grade of </p>

<p>osteoarthritis did not change in any of the patients at the last follow-up. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Patients with painful internal snapping hip have combined hip pathologies. Therefore, the surgeon should keep in </p>

<p>mind that painful internal snapping hips are frequently combined with concomitant intraarticular pathologies. </p>

<p>Keywords: Internal snapping hip syndrome, Femoroacetabular impingement, Arthroscopy, Iliopsoas tendon tenotomy </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 by The Korean Orthopaedic Association </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • pISSN 2005-291X eISSN 2005-4408 </p>

<p>Received July 20, 2014; Accepted December 8, 2014 
Correspondence to: Yong-Chan Ha, MD 
Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Chung-Ang University College of 
Medicine, 102 Heukseok-ro, Dongjak-gu, Seoul 156-755, Korea 
Tel: +82-2-6299-1577, Fax: +82-2-822-1710 
E-mail: hayongch@naver.com </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery 2015;7:158-163 • http://dx.doi.org/10.4055/cios.2015.7.2.158 </p>



<p>Hwang et al. Arthroscopic Treatment of Symptomatic Internal Snapping Hip </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • Vol. 7, No. 2, 2015 • www.ecios.org </p>

<p>intracapsular hip pathologies. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Between January 2009 and December 2011, we performed 
arthroscopic iliopsoas tendon release in 25 patients fol-
lowed up for a minimum of 2 years postoperatively. The 
indications for surgery were an audible and painful pop-
ping sound of the iliopsoas attachment area and intrac-
table pain after preoperative conservative treatment, mani-
fest as limitation of patient's activity, physical therapy, and/ 
or the need for medications and injections for at least 12 
weeks. On physical examination, all patients had a painful 
range of motion and a positive impingement test (flexion, 
adduction, and internal rotation). Preoperative imaging 
included plain radiographs (pelvis anteroposterior and 
frog leg) and computed tomography arthrogram or mag-
netic resonance arthrogram to detect bony impingement 
and labral lesons. Patients who had undergone previous 
hip surgery, and who had avascular necrosis, rheumato-
logic disorder, and arthritis more severe than Tonnis grade 
2 were excluded. 
The 25 patients comprised 20 men and 5 women, 
with a mean age of 32 years (range, 17 to 53 years). Pre-
operative diagnoses included internal snapping hip with 
isolated labral tear in 6 hips, cam-type impingement in 14 
hips, pincer-type impingement in 3 hips, and mixed type 
in 2 hips. Preoperative radiographs revealed Tonnis grade 
0 to 1 changes in 23 hips and grade 2 changes in 2 hips 
(Table 1). During surgery, all patients had ilipsoas tendon 
release combined with another procedure; arthroscopic 
femoroplasty with labral repair was performed in 16 pa-
tients, chondroplasty in 3 patients, and labral repair or 
debridement in 6 patients. 
Arthroscopy was performed with the patient supine 
on a fracture table, with the post for counter-traction in 
the central position and a well-padded foam cushion in 
place to protect against any nerve compression. The ar-
throscope was initially inserted through a posterolateral 
portal in all cases. Anterior and anterolateral portals were 
used as necessary. Complete inspection of the central 
compartment was performed, with care to evaluate for the 
presence of injury to any part of the labrum, articular car-
tilage damage, or pincer lesion. In cases with a tear of the 
labrum, the torn portion was debrided using the shaver or 
reattached using suture anchors. The traction was released 
and the peripheral compartment entered via anterolateral 
and anterior portals with the hip in 30° flexion to open 
the space anteriorly over the hip. For exposure of the 
tendinous portion of the iliopsoas, further capsulotomy </p>

<p>was made anterior to the labral injury using the shaver or 
radiofrequency ablation device. A 30° arthroscope was 
introduced into the anterolateral portal aiming caudally 
and set on the femoral head-neck junction. With the ar-
throscope pointing toward the anterior capsule, an elec-
trocautery device was introduced from the anterior portal. 
An 8-mm transverse capsulotomy was made just lateral to 
the medial synovial fold and just proximal to the zona or-
bicularis anteriorly, directly under the iliopsoas tendon. </p>

<p>13) </p>

<p>Through this capsular window, the tendinous portion of 
the iliopsoas could be visualized (Fig. 1). The shaver was 
used to peel any adherent portions of the iliopsoas off of 
the capsule. The tendinous portion of the iliopsoas was 
then incised through an anterior portal from medial to 
lateral using arthroscopic electrocautery (Fig. 2). Careful 
attention was paid to avoid damage to any of the nearby 
neurovascular structures (Supplement 1 ). The surgery 
was completed with a thorough inspection of the periph-
eral compartment with care to note the presence of a cam 
lesion or capsular-sided labral abnormality. The operation 
was completed by joint lavage and injection with a local 
anesthetic. Postoperatively, all patients followed a stan-
dardized rehabilitation program. 
Clinical and radiographic follow-up evaluations 
were performed at 6 weeks, 3, 6, and 12 months, and every 
6 months thereafter. Patients that did not attend regularly </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic Data </p>

<p>Variable 
Value </p>

<p>No. of patients (hip) 
25 (25) </p>

<p>Sex (male:female) 
20:5 </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
32 (range, 21 to 57) </p>

<p>Primary diagnosis (no. of hips) </p>

<p>Femoroacetabular impingement 
19 </p>

<p>Pincer type 
3 </p>

<p>Cam type 
14 </p>

<p>Combined type 
2 </p>

<p>Labral tear 
6 </p>

<p>Arthroscopic treatment </p>

<p>Chondroplasty 
3 </p>

<p>Femoroplasty with labral repair 
16 </p>

<p>Labral repair 
3 </p>

<p>Labral debridement 
3 </p>



<p>Hwang et al. Arthroscopic Treatment of Symptomatic Internal Snapping Hip </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • Vol. 7, No. 2, 2015 • www.ecios.org </p>

<p>scheduled visits were contacted by telephone. 
Clinical evaluations were performed using the Har-
ris hip score (HHS), 
14) visual analog pain score (VAS), hip 
outcome score (HOS)-activities of daily living subscale 
and HOS-sports subscale. Radiographic analysis included 
anteroposterior view of the pelvis, frog-leg lateral view, 
and cross-table lateral view of the hip. All radiographs 
were assessed using the Tonnis classification 
15) to grade 
radiographic degenerative changes and the Outerbridge 
classification system 
16) that grades according to the degree 
of chondromalacia. 
The difference between preoperative and postop-
erative outcome measures were analyzed using Wilcoxon 
signed rank test for continuous outcome measures and 
Fisher exact test for categorical outcome measures. The 
null hypotheses of no difference was rejected if p-values </p>

<p>were &lt; 0.05. Statistical analyses used <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">15.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS, Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). 
The design and protocol of this retrospective study 
were approved by the Institutional Review Board of 
Chung-Ang University Hospital, Seoul, Korea. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Clinical Outcome 
Snapping sounds and pain had disappeared at the 2-year 
follow-up in 24 of the 25 patients. During follow-up, sig-
nificant loss of flexion strength in all patients was present 
after surgery but improved by 6 to 10 weeks. The overall 
rating for the 25 patients (25 hips) using the HHS was 
65 points (range, 46 to 86 points) preoperatively and 84 
points (range, 67 to 98 points) postoperatively (p &lt; 0.001). 
Seven hips (28%) had an excellent score, 15 hips (60%) a 
good score, 2 hips (8%) a fair score, and one hip (4%) a 
poor score. The HOS-activities of daily living subscale and 
HOS-sports subscale preoperatively were 66% and 60%, 
respectively. The score changed to 87% and 82%, respec-
tively, at the final follow-up evaluation. University of Cali-
fornia, Los Angeles (UCLA) activity at the latest follow-up 
was improved in 17 patients and remained the same in 8 
patients. The mean VAS score decreased from 6 to 2 at the 
latest follow-up. </p>

<p>Radiologic Outcome 
Five patients had an Outerbridge grade III articular car-
tilage lesion of the acetabulum at the time of the surgical 
exploration. The Tonnis grade of osteoarthritis did not 
change in any of the patients at the last follow-up. </p>

<p>Complications 
Although significant complications such as infection, 
heterotopic ossification, thromboembolic episode or per-</p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Intraoperative photographs of a 
31-year-old woman who was diagnosed 
with labral tear and internal snapping 
hip show intact iliopsoas tendon (A) and 
released iliopsoas tendon (B). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Fluoroscopic image of the arthroscope and an electrocautery in 
position inside the iliopsoas bursa around head and neck junction. </p>



<p>Hwang et al. Arthroscopic Treatment of Symptomatic Internal Snapping Hip </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • Vol. 7, No. 2, 2015 • www.ecios.org </p>

<p>manent nerve injury did not occur, one patient had a re-
operation because of recurred painful snapping hip 3 days 
postoperatively. The patient did not experience further 
recurrence throughout the 2-year follow-up. One patient 
experienced a recurrent audible sound at the 1-year post-
operative follow-up. However, the clinical symptoms were 
much improved at the last follow-up. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Good-to-excellent clinical outcomes after arthroscopic 
release of internal snapping hip have been reported since 
the year 2000. However, most of the reported studies have 
focused on the surgical techniques used and the clinical 
outcomes of isolated internal snapping. 
9-11,17) This study 
was done to evaluate clinical outcomes after combined ar-
throscopic iliopsoas tendon release and other arthroscopic 
procedures in patients with internal snapping and other in-
tracapsular pathologies. Twenty-four of 25 patients experi-
enced disappearance of the snapping sound and 22 patients 
(88%) had scores indicating excellent and good responses 
over the minimal 2-year follow-up period (Table 2). 
In 2006, Ilizaliturri et al. 
10) performed arthroscopic 
release of the iliopsoas tendon in 7 hips. They reported 
that the snapping symptoms disappeared in all patients 
over the average 21-month follow-up period and signifi-
cant loss of flexion strength was present after surgery but 
had improved by 8 weeks. In 2009, Ilizaliturri et al. 
11) per-
formed a prospective randomized study of two different 
techniques for endoscopic iliopsoas tendon release in 19 
patients. The Western Ontario and McMaster Universi-
ties (WOMAC) scores in both groups improved without 
complications. Flanum et al. 
18) reported all 6 patients in 
the case series reported no recurrence of their snapping or 
pain at the last follow-up. Our findings are consistent with 
those of the previous three studies. 
The aforementioned three studies focused only on 
the snapping symptoms and pain. However, in this study, </p>

<p>all patients had combined internal hip pathologies such 
as labral tear (6 patients) and femoroacetabular impinge-
ments (19 patients). Domb et al. 
12) performed arthroscopic 
iliopsoas tendon release in 25 patients. They observed 
anterior labral tears at the 3 o' clock area and suggested that 
iliopsoas impingement is one of the causes of labral tear in 
the hip. Fabricant el al. 
17) evaluated the clinical outcomes 
of 67 patients with internal snapping hip who underwent 
arthroscopic psoas tendon lengthening. Thirty-seven of 
these patients had combined structural pathologies. Also, 
increased femoral anteversion was reported as a risk factor 
for inferior clinical outcomes after arthroscopic lengthen-
ing for symptomatic internal snapping hip. Patients with 
internal snapping hip might have combined hip patholo-
gies. However, during open surgical treatment of internal 
snapping hip, it may be difficult to evaluate and treat 
combined internal hip pathologies such as structural bony 
abnormalities, labral tear, and femoral anteversion. 
12,17) Re-
cently, Khan et al. 
19) performed a systemic review using 11 
eligible studies. They reported that arthroscopic surgery 
for internal snapping hip syndrome showed a decreased 
failure rate, fewer complications, and decreased postop-
erative pain in comparison with open management. 
19) A 
possible reason for the better outcomes after arthroscopic 
iliopsoas tendon release is that combined intraartcular hip 
pathologies can easily be treated during this procedure. 
We think that clinical outcomes after iliopsoas tendon 
release might be related to the treatment of combined hip 
pathologies. 
The medial femoral circumflex artery is close to the 
psoas tendon. 
20) Theoretically, there is a risk of osteone-
crosis of the femoral head after injury to the medial femo-
ral circumflex artery during arthroscopic psoas tendon 
release. However, to our knowledge, there has been no 
report of medial femoral circumflex artery injury during 
arthroscopic psoas tendon release, and it did not occur in 
this study. 
Presently, rehabilitation after arthroscopic iliopsoas </p>

<p>Table 2. Summary of Outcomes for Arthroscopic Iliopsoas Tendon Release </p>

<p>Study 
No. of 
hips </p>

<p>Mean 
age (yr) </p>

<p>Mean duration of 
follow-up (mo) 
Procedure 
Outcomes 
Data failure </p>

<p>Contreras et al. (2010) </p>

<p>9) </p>

<p>7 
33.6 
24 
Arthroscopy, iliopsoas release Five patients good to excellent results Two patients not improved </p>

<p>Ilizaliturri et al. (2009) </p>

<p>11) </p>

<p>19 
32 
24 
Arthroscopy, iliopsoas release Improving HHS score 
-</p>

<p>Fabricant et al. (2012) </p>

<p>17) </p>

<p>67 
-
36 
Arthroscopy, iliopsoas release Improving HHS score 
Poor result in high anteversion </p>

<p>Current study 
25 
32 
24 
Arthroscopy, iliopsoas release 88% Good to excellent results 
One patient not satisfied </p>

<p>HHS: Harris hip score. </p>



<p>Hwang et al. Arthroscopic Treatment of Symptomatic Internal Snapping Hip </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • Vol. 7, No. 2, 2015 • www.ecios.org </p>

<p>tendon release was delayed and a crutch was needed for 
a longer time than after typical arthroscopic hip surgery 
because of loss of flexion strength. Others reported that 
significant loss of flexion strength was present after sur-
gery but improved by 8 weeks. 
10) In the present study, all 
patients who had presented with loss of flexion strength 
postoperatively showed recovery by week 6 to 10. There-
fore, patients should be told about the inevitable loss of 
flexion strength and the longer rehabilitation period plus 
the longer period of crutch use that occur after this proce-
dure. 
There are several limitations of this study. First, it is 
a retrospective review of prospectively collected data and 
no control group was used, it might be hard to know what 
effect the psoas tendon release had on the overall results. 
However, we are sure of the reliability of our study because 
all patients had painful snapping hip and completed the 
follow-up for the minimum 2-year period. Second, all 
patients had combined hip pathology. It might be difficult 
to evaluate the effect of arthroscopic iliopsoas release on 
internal snapping hip only when there is combined hip 
pathology. In addition, patients with internal snapping hip 
should be thoroughly evaluated and a plan made for the 
treatment of combined pathology such as structural bony </p>

<p>abnormalities, labral tear, and femoral anteversion. Dy-
namic ultrasound is a well-suited, complementary tool for 
diagnosing snapping hip because of its real-time visualiza-
tion of the snapping structures. This diagnostic method 
might be helpful to evaluate painful internal snapping hip. 
However, dynamic ultrasound technique was not available 
in this study period. 
Patients with painful internal snapping hip have 
combined hip pathologies. Therefore, the surgeon should 
keep in mind the possibility that painful internal snap-
ping hips can frequently accompany concomitant intra-
articular pathologies. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was 
reported. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS </p>

<p>Video clip for arthroscopic iliopsoas tendon release. A vid-
eo clip is available in the electronic version of this paper at 
the CiOS web site, www.ecios.org. </p>





<p>Hwang et al. Arthroscopic Treatment of Symptomatic Internal Snapping Hip </p>



</text></tei>