<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4261519" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>RNA polymerase II carboxyl-terminal domain (RNAPII CTD) 
phosphatases are responsible for the dephosphorylation of the 
C-terminal domain of the small subunit of RNAPII in 
eukaryotes. Recently, we demonstrated the identification of 
several interacting partners with human small CTD phos-
phatase1 (hSCP1) and the substrate specificity to delineate an 
appearance of the dephosphorylation catalyzed by SCP1. In 
this study, using the established cells for inducibly expressing 
hSCP1 proteins, we monitored the modification of β-O-linked 
N-acetylglucosamine (O-GlcNAc). O-GlcNAcylation is one of 
the most common post-translational modifications (PTMs). To 
gain insight into the PTM of hSCP1, we used the Western blot, 
immunoprecipitation, succinylayed wheat germ agglutinin-
precipitation, liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry analy-
ses, and site-directed mutagenesis and identified the Ser </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>residue of hSCP1 as the O-GlcNAc modification site. These 
results suggest that hSCP1 may be an O-GlcNAcylated protein 
in vivo, and its N-terminus may function a possible role in the 
PTM, providing a scaffold for binding the protein(s). [BMB 
Reports 2014; 47(10): 593-598] </p>

<p>RNA polymerase II (RNAPII) is a key complex multisubunit en-
zymatic component in the transcription apparatus for the syn-
thesis of mRNAs and many noncoding RNAs and for its regu-
lation (1, 2). Eukaryotic RNAPII has several (up to 52 in mam-
mals) conserved tandem heptad repeats (Y </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>, name-
ly C-terminal domain (CTD)) at its C-terminus that is not present 
in other RNAPs (3). The phosphorylation of S 
2 and S 
5 of this re-
peat along with proline cis/trans isomerization and glyco-
sylation creates a code that seemingly can be read to mediate a </p>

<p>number of processes (4, 5) and is thought to act as a scaffold to 
coordinate the binding of proteins involved in the different 
phases of transcription and couples the transcription with other 
nuclear process. Indeed, the phosphorylation status of this re-
peat is a hallmark for different transcriptional sdtages of the 
RNAPII complexes (6). Thus, the enzymes responsible for the 
phosphorylation status of these serine (Sr) residues play pivotal 
roles in the regulation of transcription and related processes (7). 
These events are largely mediated by the participation of the 
proline-directed kinases such as cyclin-dependent kinases. 
Moreover, several phosphatases have been implicated for the 
removal of phosphates from the CTD, thereby mediating tran-
sitions in the transcription cycle (8, 9). A systematic approach 
investigating the genome-wide distribution of the CTD mod-
ifications indicated a considerable crosstalk between the CTD 
kinases and phosphatases, suggesting that the transcription op-
erates in a uniform mode at virtually all the genes (10). 
In higher eukaryotes, small CTD phosphatases (SCPs) with 
activities preferential for phosphoryl-Ser 
5 ( </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>) were identified, 
containing a catalytic domain (FCPH domain) with Mg </p>

<p>+2 </p>

<p>-bind-
ing DXDX(T/V) signature motif but lack a breast cancer protein 
related C-terminal domain (11, 12). The SCPs are related to the 
catalytic subunit of FCP1, the first discovered CTD phospha-
tase, which is highly conserved, essential enzyme for dephos-
phorylating the CTD of RNAPII and preferential for phosphor-
ylating </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. These are also transcriptional regulators for gene si-
lencing activities in neuronal genes and phase regulation in the 
cell cycle (13, 14). The catalytic mechanisms of the SCPs and 
the structural basis for their CTD specificity are well under-
stood (15, 16); however, the identity of physiological regu-
latory mechanisms explaining the biological activities of the 
SCPs has remained mainly elusive. 
The β-O-linked N-acetylglucosamine (O-GlcNAc) mod-
ification (O-GlcNAcylation) has been proposed to act as a nu-
trient sensor and changes in response to many signals, including 
the morphogens, cell cycle, development, extracellular glucose 
levels, and numerous forms of cellular stress (17, 18). This mod-
ification of Ser and threonine (Thr) residues of various nuclear, 
mitochondrial, and cytoplasmic proteins is one of a number of 
post-translational modifications (PTMs) thought to mediate cel-
lular function, and a variety of proteins can be O-GlcNAcylated 
(19). The O-GlcNAcylation is highly dynamic and interestingly </p>

<p>O-GlcNAcylation of CTD phosphatase SCP1 
JaeHyung Koo and Young Yil Bahk </p>

<p> 
http://bmbreports.org </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Microscopic assays for the EGFP expression in hSCP1 inducible cells. Images of hSCP1(Wt and D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N)-induced NIH/3T3 cells in the 
absence (A) or presence (B) (Phase contrast image) and (C) of 2 μg/ml doxycycline for 72 h were taken using a Leika M205FA stereo-
microscope (Leika Microsystems, Wetzler, Germany) equipped with the <rs type="software">LAS</rs> software for fluorescence imaging. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Establishment of hSCP1-expressing inducible NIH/3T3 cells ((A) NIH/3T3/hSCP1-V5 and (B) NIH/3T3/M2-hSCP1). The expression lev-
els of hSCP1 (Wt and D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N) treated with or without the inducer for the indicated periods of time were monitored by Western blot analy-
ses with the appropriate antibodies. For reverted cells, the cells were treated with the inducer for the indicated periods, and after the re-
placement with fresh medium, the cells were allowed to grow for the indicated periods of time without the inducer. (C) For the compar-
ison of molecular sizes of hSCP1 (Wt and D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N) from NIH/3T3/hSCP1-V5 and NIH/3T3/M2-hSCP1 cells, equal amounts (30 μg) of total 
cell lysates from the abovementioned cell lines were analyzed by immunoblotting with a mixture of α-DYKDDDDK and α-V5 antibodies 
and detected with HRP-conjugated secondary antibodies. </p>

<p>regulates protein function in a manner analogous to the phos-
phorylation of protein by changing the localization of proteins, 
regulating protein-protein or protein-DNA interactions, altering 
the half-life of proteins, and regulating the activity of proteins 
(20). Taken together, it is well established that the O-GlcNAcy-
lation is a key PTM employed by the cells and animals to rapidly 
respond for the survival against stress. 
Previously, we demonstrated the identification of several in-
teracting partners with hSCP1 and the substrate specificity to 
delineate an appearance of the dephosphorylation reaction cat-
alyzed by SCP1 phosphatase using a specific inducible express-
ing system of the human SCP1 (hSCP1) (21). SCP1 protein sub-
jected to diverse PTMs in spite of the known O-GlcNAcylation 
of RNAPII (5), particularly CTD, has not been reported. In this 
study, we interrogated the PTMs into this SCP1 as a CTD phos-
phatase and report hSCP1 as a target for the O-GlcNAcylation. 
The O-GlcNAcylated hSCP1 peptides were analyzed by mass </p>

<p>spectrometry using the established NIH/3T3 cells expressing 
hSCP1 proteins under the tight control by doxycycline. 
Moreover, the intrinsically disordered N-terminal portion of 
SCP1 may provide a scaffold for binding the protein(s) involved 
in the PTM such as the O-GlcNAcylation. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Establishment of NIH/3T3 cell lines for hSCP1 </p>

<p>The active site of the CTD-phosphatases was characterized by 
the signature motif ψψψDXDX(T/V)ψψ, where ψ is a hydro-
phobic residue. The D 
96 in the hSCP1 has been shown to be 
catalytically pivotal. The hSCP1 was tagged either with the Flag 
sequence at its N-terminus (5'-region) or V5 epitope sequence 
at its C-terminus (3'-region) and then subcloned into 
pTRE-IRES-EGFP mammalian inducible plasmid (21-23). After 
the transfections of wild type (Wt) and D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N mutant hSCP1 in </p>

<p>O-GlcNAcylation of CTD phosphatase SCP1 
JaeHyung Koo and Young Yil Bahk </p>

<p> 
http://bmbreports.org 
BMB Reports </p>

<p>pTRE-IRES-EGFP vector placing together pEF1α-Tet, several 
candidates were primarily chosen based on their antibiotic se-
lection (puromycin, 10 μg/ml) and microscopic appearance for 
the EGFP monitored into the IRES-driven EGFP expression in 
order for the expression to be tracked by fluorescence (Fig. 1) 
and finally selected using the Western blot analysis with α-Flag 
and α-DYKDDDDK antibodies or α-V5 epitope antibodies in 
all the NIH/3T3 cells (Fig. 2). The selected and used expression 
clones in this study were shown to be ＞99% expression of the 
EGFP whenever they were induced by 2 μg/ml doxycycline as 
an inducer (Fig. 1C). An increase in the hSCP1 expression was 
only shown in response to doxycycline depending on the in-
duction time (Fig. 2). However, after the treatment of doxycy-
cline for the indicated periods of time, when the cells were re-
plated on new culture dishes with fresh medium without the in-
ducer, the hSCP1 finally reverted to no expression. Moreover, 
the immunoprecipitation analyses with 2 mg of the total cell ly-
sates with appropriate antibodies did not show any positive sig-
nal from the noninduced cell lines. Thus, its expression was un-
der the tight control of doxycycline and is a suitable, unique, 
and useful system for characterizing hSCP1. The established 
hSCP1 (Wt and D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N) inducible NIH/3T3 cells were des-
ignated as NIH/3T3/M2-hSCP1 and NIH/3T3/hSCP1-V5 for the 
N-terminal Flag-tagged hSCP1 and C-terminal V5-epiotpe tag-
ged hSCP1, respectively. To confirm the enzymatic activities of 
the prepared recombinant hSCP1, the Mg </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-dependent phos-
phatase activities of the immunocomplexes from the induced 
expressed hSCP1 (Wt) from the NIH/3T3 cells were measured 
by the enzymatic activity against the artificial substrate, para-ni-
trophenyl phosphate (pNPP) (21), whereas those from the mu-
tant hSCP1 (D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N) inducible cell lines did not show any 
activity. This is in a very good agreement with the previous 
reports. The preparation of the enzyme source for the SCP1 in 
the mammalian system is not reported. The production of a 
full-length version of recombinant SCP1 in the functional form 
under native conditions was not possible, primarily because of 
solubility issues (24). Furthermore, even purifying the 
full-length form of the hSCP1 from E. coli expression system 
has also not been possible previously for another reason, be-
cause the protein consistently underwent proteolysis along the 
N-terminus during the expression (16). The N-terminus was 
predicted to be structurally disordered, overcoming the biggest 
challenge of its solubility, because of the presence of the dis-
ordered N-terminus. The full-length SCP1 could only be puri-
fied under denaturing conditions followed by refolding. 
However, it had very little enzymatic activity remaining, and 
the N-terminus-truncated SCP1 purified under native con-
ditions was functional (25). In this study, as shown in Fig. 2C, 
only mutant hSCP1(D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N) from NIH/3T3/ hSCP1(D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N)-V5 
cells had a slightly faster electrophoretic mobility than hSCP1 
from NIH/3T3/hSCP1(Wt)-V5 and NIH/3T3/M2-hSCP1(Wt), 
and even hSCP1 from NIH/3T3/M2-hSCP1(D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N) cells. 
Hence, this truncation is likely because of specific proteolytic 
cleavage of the full-length hSCP1 and lability of the </p>

<p>hSCP1(D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N) protein toward the proteolytic cleavage. 
However, the formation of the truncated version of hSCP1 was 
abolished, when the hSCP1 from NIH/3T3/ M2-hSCP1 cells 
was masked with the Flag-tag sequence in its N-terminal (Fig. 
2C, lane 4). All together, these data indicate that our C-terminal 
tagged hSCP1(D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N) in the inducibly expressing cells 
(NIH/3T3/hSCP1-V5) was expressed as a truncated version of 
the hSCP1 protein at its N-terminal region. In fact, several re-
ports have demonstrated that the N-terminus of the SCP1 is pre-
dicted to be structurally disordered and play a role of the in-
trinsically disordered N-terminus in the protein-protein inter-
actions (26-28). Our data demonstrate that the mammalian 
hSCP1 inducible cell lines are suitable, useful, and effective 
tools for dissecting the cellular and physiological functions of 
each hSCP1 in vivo. </p>

<p>hSCP1 modification by O-GlcNAcylation </p>

<p>The usefulness of our inducible protein expressing cell systems 
to validate the proteome profile changes, dissect the signaling 
network, and monitor the PTM, particularly phosphorylation has 
been previously (22, 23, 29, 30) considered. In this study, we 
first addressed the question whether the hSCP1 is a target sub-
strate of O-GlcNAc transferase (OGT). For this, immunologically 
confirmed epitope tagged hSCP1s (Wt and D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N) at different in-
duction time points (0, 24, 48, 72 h) were used in the presence 
of Thiamet-G as an inhibitor of O-GlcNAcase, immunoprecipi-
tated with either the α-Flag or α-V5 epitope antibody-conjugated 
Agarose beads and analyzed for the O-GlcNAcylation by 
Western blot analysis using α-O-GlcNAc antibody (CTD110.6) 
at each induction time point. As shown in Figs. 3A and 3B, 
hSCP1 except the truncated hSCP1(D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N) from NIH/3T3/ 
hSCP1-V5, lacking the N-terminal region, was modified by the 
O-GlcNAc. Most proteins undergo PTMs, which might be im-
portant for their function. Moreover, in many proteins, some re-
gions are partially unstructured or even native folded under the 
physiological conditions. Furthermore, the cell lysates from 
each hSCP1-expressed cells were incubated with sWGA 
Agarose, a lectin that specifically interacts with terminal GlcNAc 
moieties. The sWGA precipitates were resolved by SDS-PAGE 
and Western blotting using either α-Flag or α-V5 epitope 
antibody. Fig. 3C shows that also hSCP1 except the truncated 
hSCP1 (D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N) from NIH/3T3/hSCP1-V5 was detected in the 
sWGA precipitates, indicating that they carry O-GlcNAc moiety 
in their N-terminus and is in a very good agreement with the pre-
vious immunoprecipitation result. 
Conformational disorder is proposed to be important for 
binding diversity in the protein-protein interactions (26-28). In 
many in vitro studies of the recombinant SCP1, the inability to 
produce an active full-length version of the SCP1 under native 
conditions necessitated the use of a truncated form, but the re-
sults regarding its protein-protein interaction were inconclusive 
(15, 16). In this study, an active full-length hSCP1 in mamma-
lian system was successfully produced and shown to possess in 
vivo O-GlcNAcylation, thus demonstrating a pivotal role of its </p>

<p>O-GlcNAcylation of CTD phosphatase SCP1 
JaeHyung Koo and Young Yil Bahk </p>

<p> 
http://bmbreports.org </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Human SCP1 as a substrate target for O-GlcNAcylation. The 
immunologically defined epitope-tagged hSCP1s (Wt and D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N) 
were induced in NIH/3T3/hSCP1-V5 (A) and NIH/3T3/M2-hSCP1 (B) 
cells for the indicated periods and hSCP1 from equal amount of 
total cell lysate (2 mg) were immunoprecipitated with either α-Flag 
antibody or α-V5 epitope antibody. O-GlcNAcylated hSCP1 was 
detected using the α-O-GlcNAc antibody. For reprobing the blots, 
the blots were washed, incubated with BlotFresh Western Blot 
Stripping Reagent, and remonitored the input hSCP1 proteins. (B) 
At 72 h of the postinduction, total cell lysates (2 mg) from the 
noninduced and induced cells for the indicated periods were in-
cubated with sWGA Agarose beads. The affinity-purified hSCP1 in 
the precipitate was resolved onto SDS-PAGE and probed with ei-
ther α-DYKDDDDK or α-V5 epitope antibody. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Determination of O-GlcNAcylation site on hSCP1. (A) The Flag-tagged hSCP1 (Wt) from NIH/3T3/M2-hSCP1 cells (20 mg of total cell ly-
sate) was subjected to the immunoprecipitation with α-Flag-Agarose. The immunoprecipitates were subjected to 6-15% SDS-PAGE and stained with 
CBB. Arrow indicates hSCP1. (B) A small portion of immunoprecipitate was subjected to Western blot analysis with α-DYKDDDDK antibody. (C) 
The Q-TOF spectrum and the sequencing results of a GlcNAc-modified peptide corresponding to residues 36-50 are shown. S 
41 residue in hSCP1 
is an O-GlcNAcylation site. The expected increase in mass by the O-GlcNAc modification is 203.2 Da. (D) Whole cell lysates of NIH/3T3 trans-
fected with V5-tagged hSCP1 (empty vector (pcDNA3), Wt and S </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>A) were immunoprecipitated with V5-epitope Agarose beads and characterized 
by Western blot analysis with α O-GlcNAc antibody. The protein input was monitored with α-V5 antibody after stripping the blot. Arrow head 
indicates IgG light chain. </p>

<p>N-terminus in events such as PTMs and proteolysis, which 
might provide a specific location for the protein-protein inter-
action platform. </p>

<p>Ser 
41 residue in hSCP1 as an O-GlcNAcylation site </p>

<p>To determine the O-GlcNAcylation site of hSCP1, 20 mg of total 
cell lysate from NIH/3T3/M2-hSCP1 for Flag-tagged hSCP1(Wt) 
with the lysis buffer A, described in "Materials and Methods" 
section, was immunoprecipitated with the α-Flag anti-
body-conjugated Agarose beads. The immunoprecipitates were 
resolved onto 6-15% gradient sodium dodecyl sulphate--polya-
crylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) and visualized by 
Coomassie Brilliant Blue G250 (Fig. 4A). After confirming the re-
combinant hSCP1 of the immunoprecipitate (1/30 volume) with 
α-DYKDDDDK antibody (Fig. 4B), the excised hSCP1 band was 
digested with Glu-C. The extracted peptides were analyzed us-
ing Q-TOF MS, and the O-GlcNAc-modified peptide was identi-
fied by calculating the difference of 203.2. Only one 
O-GlcNAc-modified peptide of hSCP1 corresponding to residue 
R </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>GILHS </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>LFCCVCRDD 
50 was identified, and the Q-TOF spec-
trum and sequencing results of the GlcNAc-modified peptide 
corresponding to residues 36-50 are shown in Fig. 4C. The ex-
pected increase in mass by the O-GlcNAc modification was 
203.2 Da. To assess the O-GlcNAcylation site at S </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>, a full length 
hSCP1 (S </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>A) tagged with V5-epitope at its C-terminal region was 
created. Either hSCP1 (S </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>A) or hSCP1 (Wt) in pcDNA3 vector 
was then transfected into NIH/3T3 cells in the presence of 10 
μM Thiamet-G. Alterations in the level of O-GlcNAcylation 
were monitored by immunoprecipitation with V5-Agarose </p>

<p>O-GlcNAcylation of CTD phosphatase SCP1 
JaeHyung Koo and Young Yil Bahk </p>

<p> 
http://bmbreports.org 
BMB Reports </p>

<p>beads and Western blot analysis. The O-GlcNAcylation level of 
hSCP1 (S </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>A) proteins was significantly reduced relative to the 
hSCP1 (Wt) transfected cells (Fig. 4D). Because of the presence 
of an internal Ser residue in this peptide, we concluded that S </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>was modified by the O-GlcNAc. 
Despite its importance in coordinately regulating phosphor-
ylation and dephosphorylation of the CTD in the transcription 
and mRNA processing, the mechanism of the regulation of SCP1 
phosphatase remains largely undefined. It is not clear whether 
the PTMs of the SCP1 phosphatases by enzymatic reactions are 
essential for their pathway. The PTMs create a highly dynamic 
relay system, responding to signaling events without requiring 
de novo protein synthesis and offer a platform for signaling path-
way components involved in the regulation of the signaling sys-
tem, hence providing alternative opportunities for targeting the 
specific signaling pathway. 
In this study, we established clonal cell lines in which the ex-
pressions of hSCP1(Wt) and dominant negative hSCP1 (D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N) are 
under the tight control of an antibiotic, doxycycline as an inducer. 
Moreover, we demonstrate that hSCP1 was modified with 
O-GlcNAcylation in NIH/3T3 cells and identified an O-GlcNAcy-
lated peptide from the hSCP1, and S 
41 located near the N-terminal 
region the O-GlcNAcylation site. These experiments may shed 
some light on not only the successful production of the functional 
full-length hSCP1 in the mammalian system, but also the future 
evaluation of the functional role of its N-terminus in the pro-
tein-protein interaction. Although the functional role of the 
O-GlcNAcylation on the N-terminal region of SCP1 such as the 
role of O-GlcNAcylated RNAPII CTD remains speculative, accu-
mulating evidences indicate that the reversible PTMs such as 
O-GlcNAcylation are mostly used to modulate the protein stabil-
ity, allowing catalytic functions of the ordered proteins and is fre-
quently used for the signaling activities of intrinsically disordered 
proteins. We believe that a novel O-GlcNAcylated protein, 
hSCP1, identified in this study could function as a valuable re-
source for a further study of the role of RNAPII CTD phosphatases, 
a newly emerging family of phosphatases. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Cell culture and establishment of inducible 
hSCP1-expressing cell lines </p>

<p>NIH/3T3 cells were purchased from ATCC (Bethesda, MD, USA) 
and maintained in high glucose (25 mM) DMEM (Life 
Technologies, Burlington, ON, USA) supplemented with 10% 
bovine serum and antibiotics (Life Technologies) in a humidified 
incubator at 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C with 5% CO2 as recommended by the manu-
facturer's instruction. Tetracycline-inducible cell lines for the 
specific hSCP1 protein expression were established as pre-
viously described (23, 29, 30). The expressed hSCP1s (Wt and 
D </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>N mutant) were tagged with V5 epitope and Flag sequence at 
the C-and N-terminal regions of the hSCP1 cDNA, respectively. 
For O-GlcNAcase inhibition, the established expressing cells 
were cultured in the presence of 10 μM Thiamet-G (Cayman </p>

<p>Chemical, Ann Arbor, MI, USA) during the induction time. </p>

<p>Immunoblot analysis, immunoprecipitation assays, and 
sWGA lectin precipitation </p>

<p>The cells were washed with ice-cold PBS and lysed using lysis 
buffer A (50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 
and 1% Triton X-100 containing protease inhibitor cocktails 
(Roche, Manheim, Germany) for particularly Flag tagged hSCP1 
as per manufacturer's recommendation or conventional RIPA 
buffer containing protease inhibitors. The procedures for 
Western blot analysis and immunoprecipitation assays were per-
formed as described previously (21, 29). The anti-V5 epitope an-
tibody-conjugated Agarose beads and α-Flag antibody-conju-
gates were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich. Primary antibodies 
used are as follows: mouse α-Flag (M2 clone, Sigma-Aldrich), rat 
α-DYKDDDDK (BioLegend, San Diego, CA, USA), mouse α-V5 
epitope (Santa Cruz Biotech., Santa Cruz, CA, USA), mouse 
α-O-GlcNAc (CTD110.6 clone, Covance, Prinston, NJ, USA), 
and rabbit a α-tubulin (AbClon, Seoul, Korea). Succinylated 
wheat germ agglutinin (sWGA) lectin provides a convenient 
method for enriching and detecting O-GlcNAc-modified 
proteins. Precipitation with sWGA Agarose (Vector, Burlingame, 
CA, USA) was performed as previously described (19). The de-
tection of α-tubulin as a primary antibody was used as an internal 
control. For reprobing the blots, the blots were washed in 1X TBS 
to remove the chemiluminescent substrate and incubated with 
BlotFresh Western Blot Stripping Reagent (SignaGen Laborato-
ries, Gaithersburg, MD, USA) according to the manufacturer's 
instruction. </p>

<p>Phosphatase assays </p>

<p>The hSCP1-catalyzed dephosphorylation of the phosphorylated 
substrate was performed as previously described (21). </p>

<p>Site-directed mutagenesis and transient expression of SCP1 </p>

<p>Ser 
41 of the hSCP1 cDNA was mutagenized to Ala using a 
QuikChange 
TM site-directed mutagenesis kit (Stratagene, La 
Jolla, CA). The sequence change was verified using an ABI Prism 
sequencing kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). 
Transfections for the transient expression were performed using 
FuGENE 6 Reagent (Roche) according to the manufacturer's 
instruction. 3 μg of cDNA construct in pcDNA3 was used for all 
the transfections. </p>

<p>Mass spectrometric analysis </p>

<p>The specific protein bands from the CBB-stained gel of the im-
munoprecipitated complexes (20 mg of total cell lysate) were di-
gested with endoproteinase Glu-C (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) 
at 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C according to the manufacturer's instruction. The resulting 
peptides were extracted using 50% acetonitrile and dried in a 
vacuum evaporator for further analysis. Mass spectrometric anal-
ysis was performed using a QSTAR Pulsar Q-TOF MS (Applied 
Biosystems) equipped with a nanoelectrospray ion source 
(Protana, Odense, Denmark) as described previously (21, 29). </p>

<p>O-GlcNAcylation of CTD phosphatase SCP1 
JaeHyung Koo and Young Yil Bahk </p>

<p>598 BMB Reports 
http://bmbreports.org </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by grants from the National Research 
Foundation of Korea: 2010-0024199 for YYB and 2013R1A1 
A2009145 for JHK. </p>



</text></tei>