<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4401356" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T16:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: To evaluate the safety and efficacy of switching from dorzolamide 1.0%/timolol 
maleate 0.5% fixed-combination (DTFC) eye drops to brinzolamide 1.0%/timolol maleate 
0.5% fixed-combination (BTFC) eye drops in patients with primary open-angle glaucoma or 
ocular hypertension. 
Methods: A total of 35 eyes of 35 patients with primary open-angle glaucoma or ocular 
hypertension using DTFC eye drops were included. Participants discontinued DTFC drops and 
immediately began using BTFC drops. All other eye drops currently being used were continued. 
Intraocular pressure (IOP) 1 and 3 months after switching medications was compared with 
baseline IOP. One month after switching medications, participant preference and adherence 
were evaluated. Adverse reactions were monitored at each study visit. 
Results: The IOP was 17.9±2.6 mmHg at baseline and 18.3±4.1 mmHg and 17.8±3.4 mmHg 
1 month and 3 months after switching medications, respectively (P=0.633). The frequency of 
missing a dose was not different before (6.1%) and after (6.1%) switching to BTFC. Signifi-
cantly fewer participants reported stinging after switching to BTFC (15.2%) than while using 
DTFC (51.5%, P,0.01). Blurred vision was reported with the same frequency before (39.4%) 
and after (42.4%) switching to BTFC. A total of 33.3% and 27.3% of patients preferred DTFC 
and BTFC, respectively. Several patients withdrew from the study because of discomfort (n=2, 
5.7%), discharge (n=1, 2.9%), dizziness (n=1, 2.9%), or increased IOP (n=2, 5.7%). 
Conclusion: Switching from DTFC to BTFC was well tolerated and did not result in IOP 
changes or a decreased patient adherence. When glaucoma patients complain of stinging with 
DTFC administration, switching to BTFC is an acceptable treatment option. 
The ultimate goal of treating glaucoma is to reduce intraocular pressure (IOP) and to 
preserve the visual field. Initial glaucoma therapies generally consist of prostaglandin 
analog monotherapy. 
1,2 However, when inadequate IOP control with a single analog 
occurs, a different monotherapy agent or an additional medication must be used. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Multiple medications increase the number of eye drops instilled, which can lead to 
poor patient adherence. Therefore, a fixed-combination eye drop that contains two 
different medications is recommended. Several fixed-combination eye drops have 
been approved for use in Japan and have been available since 2011. These include 
fixed combinations of a prostaglandin analog and timolol (latanoprost/timolol 
[Xalacom 
® , Pfizer, Inc., New York, NY, USA], travoprost/timolol [DuoTrav 
® , 
Alcon Laboratories Inc., Fort Worth, TX, USA]) and a fixed combination of a </p>

<p>Correspondence: Kenji Inoue 
Inouye Eye Hospital, 4-3 Kanda-
Surugadai, Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 101-0062, 
Japan 
Tel +81 03 3295 0911 
Fax +81 03 3295 0917 
Email inoue-k@inouye-eye.or.jp </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Clinical Ophthalmology 
9 April 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>620 </p>

<p>Inoue et al </p>

<p>carbonic anhydrase inhibitor and timolol ( dorzolamide/ 
timolol [Cosopt 
® , Merck &amp; Co., Inc., Whitehouse Station, 
NJ, USA]). In November 2013, a fixed-combination eye 
drop containing brinzolamide and timolol (Azarga, Alcon 
Laboratories, Inc.) was approved for use in Japan. This 
brinzolamide/timolol fixed-combination (BTFC) eye drop 
was shown to be extremely effective in reducing IOP in 
Japanese glaucoma patients. 
4-6 However, dorzolamide/ 
timolol fixed-combination (DTFC) eye drops have been 
shown to be better for reducing IOP reduction than both 
latanoprost 
7 and brimonidine/timolol fixed-combination 
drops. 
8 It has been shown that switching patients from a 
DTFC eye drop to a BTFC eye drop is both safe and effec-
tive in reducing IOP, 
9-11 but this has not been specifically 
examined in a Japanese population. 
Here, we prospectively evaluate IOP reduction, patient 
comfort, and treatment safety when switching from a DTFC 
eye drop to a BTFC eyed drop in patients with primary open-
angle glaucoma and ocular hypertension. Patients were fol-
lowed for 3 months following the medication switch. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>A total of 35 eyes of 35 patients (12 men, 23 women) with 
primary open-angle glaucoma or ocular hypertension who 
were using DTFC eye drops at Inouye Eye Hospital were 
enrolled in this study between November 2013 and August 
2014. The protocol was approved by the hospital's ethical 
committee, and all participants provided written informed </p>

<p>consent before any study procedure or examination was 
performed. 
Participants discontinued their twice-daily use of DTFC 
eye drops (Cosopt </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, Merck &amp; Co., Inc.) and immediately 
switched to a twice-daily use (morning and evening instilla-
tion) of BTFC eye drops (Azarga, Alcon Laboratories, Inc.) 
(twice a day, morning and evening instillation). All other 
topical medication used remained the same. When participant 
were using DTFC eye drops in both eyes, the eye with the 
higher IOP was selected as the study eye. If both eyes had the 
same IOP, the right eye was selected as the study eye. 
The IOP was measured at approximately the same time 
each visit using a Goldmann tonometer. The magnitude of 
IOP reduction was defined as the IOP 3 months after switch-
ing medication minus the IOP at baseline. One month after 
switching medications, participant preference and adherence 
to BTFC therapy use were evaluated (Table 1). Participants 
were also asked about experiencing specific adverse reac-
tions at each study visit. Reasons for participant dropout 
were also recorded. </p>

<p>Data analyses </p>

<p>All data are presented as mean ± standard deviation, where 
applicable. Differences in mean IOP at baseline and at 1 and 
3 months were analyzed using paired t-tests. Commercially 
available statistical software (<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 22</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA</rs>) was used to perform all statistical analy-
ses. Statistical significance was defined as P,0.05. </p>

<p>Table 1 Questionnaire regarding brinzolamide/timolol fixed-combination eyed drop use </p>

<p>Q1. What time did you use eye drops each day? 
AM: PM: 
Q2. 1. Did you use eye drops every day? 
Yes 
No 
2. If you answered "No" to the previous question, please answer the questions below: 
How often did you forget to use eye drops-in a week? 
1 time 
2 times 
3 times 
more than 4 times 
Have you ever forget to use your previous eye drops? 
Yes No 
If you answered "Yes" to the previous question, please answer the question below: 
How often did you forget to use eye drops this week? 
1 time 
2 times 
3 times 
more than 4 times 
Q3. Compared to your previous eye drops 
1. How much stinging does brinzolamide/timolol fixed combination cause? 
Not stinging 
Same 
Stinging 
No answer 
2. How about your blurred vision? 
Moderate 
Same 
Discomfort 
No answer 
Q4. 1. Compared to your previous eye drops, how well does brinzolamide/timolol fixed combination work? 
Better 
Same 
Worse 
2. What effect does taking brinzolamide/timolol fixed combination-have on your daily life? (multiple answers allowed) 
Stinging 
Blurred vision 
Discomfort 
Good for IOP 
Other effect () </p>

<p>Abbreviation: IOP, intraocular pressure. </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>621 </p>

<p>Switching from DTFC to BTFC treatment </p>

<p>Results 
Subject characteristics </p>

<p>Mean subject age at baseline was 67.5±9.0 years (range: 
46-84 years). A total of 33 eyes had primary open-angle 
glaucoma and 2 eyes had ocular hypertension. The number of 
drops used before switching medications was 3.5±0.6 drops 
per day, including 19 (54.3%) patients who used 3 drops 
per day, 14 (40.0%) patients who used 4 drops per day, and 
2 (5.7%) patients who used 5 drops per day. The DTFC eye 
drop counted as 2 drops. Baseline IOP was 17.9±2.6 mmHg 
(range: 14.0-23.5 mmHg) and Humphrey visual field 
(30-2 SITA Standard) mean deviation was −8.5±6.5 dB 
(range: −19.1-1.6 dB). </p>

<p>IOP after switching medications </p>

<p>The IOP 1 and 3 months after switching medications was 
18.3±4.1 mmHg (n=33 eyes) and 17.8±3.4 mmHg (n=29 
eyes), respectively. These slight differences from baseline 
(17.9±2.6 mmHg, n=35 eyes) were not statistically significant 
(P=0.633, Figure 1). Three months after switching medication, 
10 (34.5%) eyes had a decrease in IOP $2 mmHg, 13 (44.8%) 
eyes had no change in IOP (within 2 mmHg of baseline), and 
6 (20.7%) eyes had an increase in IOP $2 mmHg. </p>

<p>Subject compliance and comfort </p>

<p>Subject comfort and compliance were evaluated 1 month 
after switching medications. Two (6.1%) subjects reported </p>

<p>missing BTFC drop doses, which was not significantly 
different than the 2 (6.1%) subjects who missed DTFC drop 
doses (P=0.999, Table 2). 
Five (15.2%) subjects reported stinging with BTFC drop 
use, which was significantly less than the 17 (51.5%) sub-
jects who reported stinging with DTFC drop use (P,0.01). 
Thirteen (39.4%) subjects reported blurred vision with 
DTFC drop use, which was not significantly different than 
the 14 (42.4%) subjects who reported blurred vision with 
BTFC drop use (P=0.999). Figure 2 summarizes the stinging 
and blurred vision that subjects experienced during BTFC 
drop use. 
A total of 9 (27.3%) participants preferred to use BTFC 
drops, 11 (33.3%) participants preferred to use DTFC 
drops, and 13 (39.4%) participants expressed no preference 
( Figure 3). Subjects preferred BTFC drops because they had 
less stinging (n=5 subjects) and better IOP reduction (n=5 
subjects). Subjects preferred DTFC drops because they had 
less blurred vision (n=7 subjects), less stinging (n=2 sub-
jects), and less discomfort (n=2 subjects). 
Six (17.1%) participants dropped out of the study before 
the end of the 3-month study period. Participants withdrew 
from the study because of increased IOP (n=2 [5.7%] 
subjects, 1 and 2 months after switching), ocular discomfort 
(n=2 [5.7%] subjects, #1 month after switching), ocular 
discharge (n=1 [2.9%] subject, 1 month after switching), and 
dizziness (n=1 [2.9%] subject, 3 days after switching). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Several reports on the efficacy of BTFC eye drops in Japanese 
patients have been published. 
4-6 Yoshikawa et al 
4 treated 
301 patients with primary open-angle glaucoma or ocular hyper-
tension with timolol for 4 weeks. Patients were then divided 
into two groups, with one group switched to BTFC drops 
(150 cases) and the other group continuing on timolol drops 
(151 cases). Treatment was continued for an additional 8 weeks 
in both groups. Eight weeks after group differentiation, IOP 
in the BTFC group was 3.2 mmHg lower (measured 2 hours 
after drop instillation) than before the switch. Adverse reac-
tions experienced were stinging (5%), blurred vision (1%), and 
hyperemia (1%). Nagayama et al 
5 administered timolol therapy </p>

<p>Table 2 Summary of adverse reactions </p>

<p>Brinzolamide/timolol 
Dorzolamide/timolol 
P-value </p>

<p>Omission of ocular instillation 
2/36 (5.6%) 
2/36 (5.6%) 
P.0.999 
Stinging 
5/36 (13.9%) 
18/36 (50.0%) 
P,0.01** 
Blurred vision 
15/36 (41.7%) 
13/36 (36.1%) 
P=0.8092 </p>

<p>Notes: Statistical significance examined with a χ 
2 test. **P,0.01. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Intraocular pressure values before and after switching medications. 
Note: Statistical significance examined with a paired t-test. 
Abbreviation: NS, not significant. </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Inoue et al </p>

<p>to 319 patients with primary open-angle glaucoma or ocular 
hypertension for 4 weeks. Patients were then divided into two 
groups, with one group switching to BTFC therapy (158 cases) 
and the other group switching to brinzolamide and timolol 
therapy (161 cases). Treatment was continued for an additional 
8 weeks in both groups. After 8 weeks, the decrease in IOP was 
not significantly different between the BTFC group (range: 
2.5-3.4 mmHg) and the brinzolamide-added group (range: 
2.7-3.3 mmHg). Adverse reactions observed in the BTFC 
group were punctate keratitis (1%), blurred vision (1%), ocular 
pruritus (1%), and dysgeusia (1%). Nakajima et al 
6 administered 
BTFC eye drops to 126 patients with primary open-angle glau-
coma or ocular hypertension for 52 weeks. After the 52-week 
treatment period, IOP had been reduced between 4.1 mmHg </p>

<p>and 5.7 mmHg in each patient. Adverse reactions included, but 
were not limited to, punctate keratitis (10%), ocular irritation 
(6%), keratitis (3%), and dysgeusia (3%). 
Several studies reporting what happens after switching from 
DTFC to BTFC therapy have been published. 
9-11 Lanzl and 
Raber 
9 reported what happened after switching from various 
therapies to BTFC drops. In the 2,937 patients who switched from 
DTFC drops to BTFC drops, IOP significantly decreased from 
18.5±4.1 mmHg to 16.5±3.2 mmHg. Moreover, IOP was signif-
icantly lower in 823 patients who switched from a prostaglandin 
analog plus DTFC drops (18.3±5.0 mmHg) to a prostaglandin 
analog plus BTFC drops (16.4±3.9 mmHg). Auger et al 
10 evalu-
ated stinging, blurred vision, eye redness, and abnormal taste in 
31 patients who switched from DTFC to BTFC. Patients 
using DTFC drops experienced more stinging and patients 
using BTFC drops experienced more blurred vision. There 
were no differences in eye redness and abnormal taste. Rossi 
et al 
11 investigated tear film breakup time, corneal stinging, 
and glaucoma symptom scale score 
12 in 72 patients switching 
from DTFC. A significant improvement was reported for all 
evaluations. Adverse reactions included blurred vision (4.2%) 
and dysgeusia (2.7%). IOP was not affected by switching 
medications. 
In our study, no patients used DTFC drops concomitantly 
with an analog. We observed no changes in IOP that resulted 
from switching to a prostaglandin analog plus BTFC drops 
(n=18 cases). These results differed from those reported by 
Lanzl and Raber. 
9 However, IOP decreased or increased 
by $2 mmHg in 55.2% of subjects. Therefore, we conclude 
that changes in IOP vary between patients. 
Our observed efficacy in reducing IOP was not sig-
nificantly different from a previous report comparing 
dorzolamide 2.0%/timolol fixed-combination drops with </p>

<p>Stinging </p>

<p>No answer, 
3, 8.3% 
No answer, 
4, 11.1% </p>

<p>Stinging, 
5, 13.9% </p>

<p>Discomfort, 
15, 41.7% </p>

<p>Not stinging, 
18, 50.0% </p>

<p>Same, 
10, 27.8% 
Same, 
4, 11.1% </p>

<p>Moderate, 
13, 36.1% </p>

<p>Blurred vision </p>

<p>Figure 2 Stinging and blurred vision in subjects using brinzolamide/timolol fixed-combination eye drops. </p>

<p>Patient preferences </p>

<p>No 
answer, 
2, 5% </p>

<p>Dorzolamide/ 
timolol, 
11, 31% </p>

<p>Brinzolamide/ 
timolol, 
10, 28% </p>

<p>Neither dorzolamide/timolol 
nor brinzolamide/timolol, 
13, 36% </p>

<p>Figure 3 Patient preferences for each medication examined. </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/clinical-ophthalmology-journal </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology is an international, peer-reviewed journal 
covering all subspecialties within ophthalmology. Key topics include: 
Optometry; Visual science; Pharmacology and drug therapy in eye 
diseases; Basic Sciences; Primary and Secondary eye care; Patient 
Safety and Quality of Care Improvements. This journal is indexed on </p>

<p>PubMed Central and CAS, and is the official journal of The Society of 
Clinical Ophthalmology (SCO). The manuscript management system 
is completely online and includes a very quick and fair peer-review 
system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/ 
testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Clinical Ophthalmology 2015:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>623 </p>

<p>Switching from DTFC to BTFC treatment </p>

<p>BTFC drops. 
13 However, this previous study reported that 
participants withdrew from the study because of adverse 
reactions, including discomfort, discharge, and dizziness. In 
our study, 14.3% and 40% of participants reported stinging 
and blurred vision, respectively. This was not significantly 
different than that reported in a previous study (stinging in 
42%, blurred vision in 55%). 
10 Moreover, we observed no 
severe adverse reactions, which is in agreement with past 
reports. 
4-6,9-11,13,14 Also in agreement with past reports, </p>

<p>10,13,14 </p>

<p>less stinging was reported in the BTFC group than in the 
DTFC group. We believe that less stinging occurred because 
of pH differences between medications (dorzolamide/timolol 
pH =5.6, brinzolamide/timolol pH =7.2). The frequency 
of blurred vision in the DTFC group was not significantly 
different from that observed in the BTFC group. This is in 
agreement with one previous study, 
13 but two other studies </p>

<p>10,14 </p>

<p>found that BTFC drops caused blurred vision more often than 
DTFC drops. BTFC drops are a liquid suspension, which is 
known to cause blurred vision. In a previous study, 79.2% of 
patients preferred BTFC drops over DTFC drops. 
14 Likewise, 
Lanzl and Raber 
9 reported that patients preferred BTFC drop 
(82.0%) significantly more often than they preferred DTFC 
drops (8.8%). We found that 33.3% of our participants pre-
ferred using DTFC drops and that 27.3% of our participants 
preferred using BTFC drops. The reason cited for preferring 
DTFC was less vision blurring. Participants preferred BTFC 
drops because they caused less stinging. Consequently, we 
considered the importance of sensation in determining patient 
preference. 
In conclusion, we found no significant difference in 
IOP, subject compliance, or blurred vision in participants 
who switched from DTFC drops to BTFC drops. However, 
stinging was reported more frequently during treatment with 
DTFC drops. Therefore, in patients who experience stinging 
with the administration of DTFC drops, switching to BTFC 
drops is an acceptable glaucoma treatment option. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>No author has any conflicts of interest to declare that is 
relevant to the subject of this article. </p>



</text></tei>