<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4027710" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background and Purpose: Orthostatic hypotension (OH) is known to be present even in 
patients with early Parkinson's disease (PD). To affirm the presence of OH and find correlation 
between OH and other dysautonomic symptoms in PD, this study has done in newly-diagnosed 
PD patients. Methods: Forty-five non-demented patients with no prior history of treatment for 
PD were recruited (17 men, 63.8 ± 10.1 years of age). All the patients were evaluated for OH be-
fore starting medications. Autonomic symptoms were evaluated with structured questionnaires. 
Clinical characteristics of PD were evaluated (median Hoehn and Yahr stage 2.0 (1-3), 1.3 ± 1.1 
years of disease duration), and comorbid medical conditions that could affect blood pressure 
were also recorded. Results: OH was prevalent, and eighteen patients (40%) showed ortho-
static hypotension, and twenty-seven (60%) did not (normotensive group). There was no sig-
nificant difference in demographic and clinical characteristics between groups. The presence 
or severity of symptoms of autonomic dysfunction in the OH group also not differed from 
those of the normotensive group. Conclusions: OH was prevalent even in the early stage of 
PD, and was not related to presence or severity of any other symptoms of autonomic dys-
function. Our findings suggest that clinicians should pay attention to OH from the early stage of 
disease. </p>

<p>Journal of Movement Disorders 2011;4:33-37 </p>

<p>Key Words: Parkinson's disease, Orthostatic hypotension, Autonomic dysfunction. </p>

<p>Clinically, Parkinson's disease (PD) is mainly characterized by motor symptoms such as 
bradykinesia, rigidity, tremor, and postural instability. However, patients with PD may also 
experience many complaints beyond motor symptoms, which are referred to as non-motor 
symptoms. 1 The non-motor symptoms of PD are very diverse, including neuropsychiatric 
symptoms, sleep disturbances, sensory symptoms, and dysautonomic symptoms. 2 It has be-
come increasingly apparent that non-motor symptoms have a quite considerable impact on the 
quality of life of PD patients. 1 
Impaired cardiovascular response to postural changes, particularly orthostatic hypotension 
(OH) is considered an important clinical and even diagnostic feature for the multiple system 
atrophy or pure autonomic failure. 3,4 In PD, OH was thought to develop later in the disease cou-
rse or only in more severe cases often in elderly patients. 5-7 Moreover, OH has been thought to 
be a side effect of anti-parkinsonian medications, like levodopa and dopamine agonists. 8-12 How-
ever, it is accepted that OH is also a common finding even in the early stages of PD. 13,14 
The authors evaluated OH among newly-diagnosed PD patients and the relationship be-
tween OH and other symptoms of autonomic dysfunctions in patients. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Subjects </p>

<p>We studied 45 selected PD patients without dementia. The subjects had been diagnosed as 
PD for the first time or diagnosed as PD by other clinicians but had never been treated before. 
The diagnosis of PD was established according to the criteria of the United Kingdom Parkin-
son's Disease Society Brain Bank. 15 We excluded atypical or secondary parkinsonisms, and </p>

<p>online © ML Comm </p>



<p>Journal of Movement Disorders ▐ 2011;4:33-37 </p>

<p>the diagnosis was confirmed during the follow up visits for 
more than 6 months. Comorbid medical conditions that could 
affect blood pressure were also evaluated, which included hy-
pertension, diabetes mellitus, and benign prostatic hypertrophy. </p>

<p>Evaluation of parkinsonian symptoms </p>

<p>Severity and stage of parkisonism were rated using the unified 
Parkinson's disease rating scale, the Hoehn and Yahr stage and 
the Modified Schwab and England activities of daily living. </p>

<p>Evaluation of orthostatic hypotension and 
autonomic dysfunction </p>

<p>All patients were evaluated for the presence of OH, regard-
less of symptoms of orthostatic dizziness or syncope. To avoid 
the blood pressure lowering effect of dopaminergic drugs, all 
patients evaluated for OH before medication. OH was measured 
by monitoring systolic and diastolic blood pressure and heart 
rate. After a 10 minute period of lying down, systolic and dia-
stolic blood pressures were checked in the first, third, and fifth 
minutes after standing up. If the patient could not stand up by 
his or herself, a tilt table was used. OH was defined as a drop 
in systolic BP ≥ 20 mmHg or diastolic BP ≥ 10 mmHg at any-
time following standing up. 
Comprehensive assessment of autonomic dysfunction was </p>

<p>also assessed using a systematized autonomic dysfunction ques-
tionnaire (ADQ). 3 The ADQ covered gastrointestinal symp-
toms, urinary symptoms, sexual dysfunction, cardiovascular sy-
mptoms and thermoregulatory symptoms. The severity or freque-
ncy of each of the symptoms was expressed as scores (Table 1). </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">14</rs> for Windows was used for statistical calcu-
lations. Mann-Whitney and Chi tests were employed to ana-
lyze intergroup difference. Statistical significance was de-
clared at the p &lt; 0.05 range. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>General and clinical characteristics of patients </p>

<p>The subjects (17 men and 28 women, age of 63.8 ± 10.1 years) 
showed mild disease [median Hoehn and Yahr stage 2.0 (1-3)] 
with 1.3 ± 1.1 years of disease duration. Twenty-two patients 
had comorbid disease, which could affect blood pressure. Hy-
pertension (20/45 patients) was the most common, followed 
by diabetes (7/45) and benign prostatic hyperplasia (1/45). 
Eighteen patients showed OH (OH group, 8 men, age 61.3 ± 
10.8 years) and twenty-seven patients (normotensive group, 9 </p>

<p>Table 1. Autonomic dysfunction questionnaire </p>

<p>Gastrointestinal </p>

<p>symptoms 
Urinary symptoms 
Sexual dysfunction 
Cardiovascular </p>

<p>symptoms </p>

<p>Thermoregulatory </p>

<p>symptoms </p>

<p>Salivation 
Hesitancy 
Erectile dysfunction 
Orthostasis 
Sweating (Face) </p>

<p>Dysphagia 
Urgency 
Ejaculation difficulty 
Syncope 
Sweating (Trunk) </p>

<p>Nausea 
Incomplete voiding 
Libido change 
Sweating (Limb) </p>

<p>Constipation 
Weak stream 
Heat intolerance </p>

<p>Defecatory dysfunction </p>

<p>(anismus) </p>

<p>Frequency 
Cold intolerance </p>

<p>Nocturia 
Oiliness &amp; seborrhea </p>

<p>Urinary incontinence </p>

<p>Table 2. Demographic &amp; parkinsonian features in each group </p>

<p>Group 
Patients with orthostatic </p>

<p>hypotension (n = 18) </p>

<p>Patients without orthostatic </p>

<p>hypotension (n = 27) 
p </p>

<p>Sex (M : F) 
8 : 10 
9 : 18 
NS </p>

<p>Age (Y) 
61.3 ± 10.8 
65.5 ± 9.4 
NS </p>

<p>Duration of symptoms (M) 
13.8 ± 10.1 
16.1 ± 15.9 
NS </p>

<p>Duration of education (y) 
08.0 ± 3.9 
05.9 ± 4.6 
NS </p>

<p>Comorbid disorders 
9 (50.0%) 
13 (48.1%) 
NS </p>

<p>UPDRS Part I 
02.7 ± 1.5 
02.4 ± 1.5 
NS </p>

<p>UPDRS Part II 
09.0 ± 4.5 
09.1 ± 3.7 
NS </p>

<p>UPDRS Part III 
24.3 ± 7.7 
26.5 ± 8.9 
NS </p>

<p>UPDRS total 
36.7 ± 10.5 
38.2 ± 11.8 
NS </p>

<p>Hoehn &amp; yahr stage 
02.0 ± 0.6 
02.0 ± 0.5 
NS </p>

<p>SEADL 
73.3 ± 11.5 
75.4 ± 11.2 
NS </p>

<p>K-MMSE: Korean version of mini-mental status exam, ADL: activity of daily living, SEADL: schwab and england activity of daily living </p>

<p>www.e-jmd.org 35 </p>

<p>Orthostatic Hypotension in PD ▐ Bae HJ, et al. </p>

<p>men, age 65.5 ± 9.4 years) did not. Patients without OH were 
older and showed shorter duration of education, but those de-
mographic characteristics were not significantly different be-
tween groups (Table 2). Parkinsonian symptoms and daily ac-
tivities of the patients also showed no significant difference 
between groups (Table 2). </p>

<p>Symptoms of autonomic dysfunctions 
in patients </p>

<p>Many dysautonomic symptoms were accompanied with OH 
in patients, and all the patients had more than two of those sym-
ptoms (Table 3). Urinary symptoms were most common and fol-
lowed by sexual symptoms. Although urinary incontinence 
was more prevalence in OH group, it did not reach statistical 
significance. The presence of OH was not related with the pres-
ence of other symptoms. 
Total score in the ADQ was slightly increased in patients 
with OH compared to that of patients without OH (Table 4). 
However, the differences did not reach statistical significance. 
In spite of the insignificant difference, the scores of all do-
mains in the OH group were higher than those of the normo-</p>

<p>tensive group. However, even in the questions of cardiovascu-
lar symptoms, orthostatic dizziness and history of syncope, 
there was no difference between groups. Only eight patients 
complained of orthostatic dizziness and four of those patients 
showed OH. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Abnormal cardiovascular regulation, including orthostatic 
hypotension was frequently expressed in various stages of PD 
patients. 16,17 The cardiovascular autonomic disturbances are 
following the gastrointestinal symptoms in frequency, but they 
have a higher impact on the quality of life in PD patients. 
Lewy bodies, a pathological hallmark of Parkinson's dis-
ease, have been found in autonomic regulatory regions of the 
brain or peripheral autonomic ganglia in PD patients. 18 And, 
many studies have shown the evidence of cardiac sympathetic 
denervation in early PD patients by using cardiac sympathetic 
imaging. 19,20 
Symptoms of autonomic dysfunction in PD patients were 
known to be related with older age, long disease duration, se-</p>

<p>Table 3. Presence of dysautonomic symptoms in each group </p>

<p>Patients with orthostatic </p>

<p>hypotension (n = 18) </p>

<p>Patients without orthostatic </p>

<p>hypotension (n = 27) 
p </p>

<p>Gastrointestinal symptom </p>

<p>Salivation 
27.8% (5) 
25.9% (7) 
NS </p>

<p>Dysphagia 
11.1% (2) 
14.8% (4) 
NS </p>

<p>Nausea 
22.2% (4) 
25.9% (7) 
NS </p>

<p>Constipation 
44.4% (8) 
25.9% (7) 
NS </p>

<p>Anismus 
27.8% (5) 
11.1% (3) 
NS </p>

<p>Urinary symptom </p>

<p>Hesitancy 
33.3% (6) 
29.6% (8) 
NS </p>

<p>Urgency 
27.8% (5) 
33.3% (9) 
NS </p>

<p>Incomplete voiding 
38.9% (7) 
44.4% (12) 
NS </p>

<p>Weak stream 
38.9% (7) 
33.3% (9) 
NS </p>

<p>Frequency 
77.8% (14) 
66.7% (18) 
NS </p>

<p>Nocturia 
72.2% (13) 
74.1% (20) 
NS </p>

<p>Incontinence 
27.8% (5) 
07.4% (2) 
NS </p>

<p>Sexual dysfunction </p>

<p>Erectile dysfunction* 
37.5% (3/8) 
22.2% (2/9) 
NS </p>

<p>Ejaculation difficulty* 
37.5% (3/8) 
33.3% (3/9) 
NS </p>

<p>Change of libido 
50.0% (9) 
40.7% (11) 
NS </p>

<p>Cardiovascular symptom </p>

<p>Orthostasis 
22.2% (4) 
07.4% (2) 
NS </p>

<p>Syncope 
11.1% (2) 
00.0% (0) 
NS </p>

<p>Thermoregulatory symptom </p>

<p>Sweat 
11.1% (2) 
11.1% (3) 
NS </p>

<p>Heat intolerance 
11.1% (2) 
11.1% (3) 
NS </p>

<p>Cold intolerance 
05.6% (1) 
00.0% (0) 
NS </p>

<p>Oiliness of skin 
11.1% (2) 
00.0% (0) 
NS </p>

<p>*evaluated male patients only </p>



<p>Journal of Movement Disorders ▐ 2011;4:33-37 </p>

<p>vere disease stage and anti-parkinsonian medication. 7 Howev-
er, Allcock et al. showed that frequency of OH was indepen-
dent of duration and severity of movement symptoms in the 
study of the frequency of OH in a community-based cohort of 
PD patients. 13 The prevalence of OH in PD was variable accor-
ding to criteria and methods. In 5 relatively large studies in-
volving more than 80 patients each, the frequency of OH 
ranged from 30% to 58%. 6 Bonuccelli et al. 21 showed the high 
prevalence of OH in de novo PD patients. In our study, preva-
lence of OH in the drug-naïve PD patients was moderate 
(18/45 patients, 40%), and similarly shown in the patients 
without comorbid disease (9/23 patient, 39.1%). Patients with 
OH were young and showed a short duration of disease, but 
those differences did not reach statistical significance, and the 
severity of parkinsonian symptoms was similar to those of pa-</p>

<p>tients without OH. The presence or severity of dysautonomic 
symptoms was not different between patients with or without 
OH, even in the cardiovascular domain. Therefore, OH did not 
respect the severity or distribution of other autonomic symp-
toms. Actually, the complaint of orthostasis was made by only 
six patients (13.3%), four of those patients showed OH. Most 
patients with OH did not complain of orthostasis, and Steven 
et al. showed that the majority of patients with profound ortho-
static hypotension either did not show the typical symptoms 
(33%), or showed only atypical symptoms (24%). 22 The un-
awareness of orthostatic hypotension stresses the importance of 
blood pressure monitoring irrelevant to complaints of patients. 
Although we could not find statistical significance, patients 
with urinary incontinence were much higher in OH group 
(27.8% vs. 7.4%). This finding suggests that those patients can </p>

<p>Table 4. Severity of dysautonomic symptoms in each group </p>

<p>Patients with orthostatic </p>

<p>hypotension (n = 18) </p>

<p>Patients without orthostatic </p>

<p>hypotension (n = 27) 
p </p>

<p>Gastrointestinal symptom </p>

<p>Salivation 
00.2 ± 0.4 
00.4 ± 0.4 
NS </p>

<p>Dysphagia 
00.2 ± 0.5 
00.2 ± 0.7 
NS </p>

<p>Nausea 
00.2 ± 0.4 
00.3 ± 0.5 
NS </p>

<p>Constipation 
00.8 ± 1.1 
00.2 ± 0.4 
NS </p>

<p>Anismus 
00.5 ± 0.9 
00.2 ± 0.5 
NS </p>

<p>Sum 
02.1 ± 2.7 
01.4 ± 1.8 
NS </p>

<p>Urinary symptom </p>

<p>Hesitancy 
00.6 ± 1.2 
01.0 ± 1.6 
NS </p>

<p>Urgency 
00.6 ± 1.2 
00.8 ± 1.4 
NS </p>

<p>Incomplete voiding 
01.1 ± 1.9 
01.2 ± 1.6 
NS </p>

<p>Weak stream 
01.2 ± 1.9 
01.2 ± 1.2 
NS </p>

<p>Frequency 
01.7 ± 1.8 
01.5 ± 1.4 
NS </p>

<p>Nocturia 
01.8 ± 1.5 
01.5 ± 0.9 
NS </p>

<p>Incontinence 
00.5 ± 0.8 
00.1 ± 0.4 
NS </p>

<p>Sum 
07.7 ± 7.9 
07.2 ± 6.5 
NS </p>

<p>Sexual dysfunction </p>

<p>Erectile dysfunction 
00.6 ± 1.4 
00.3 ± 0.9 
NS </p>

<p>Ejaculation difficulty 
00.6 ± 1.5 
00.4 ± 1.0 
NS </p>

<p>Change of libido 
01.8 ± 1.9 
01.4 ± 1.8 
NS </p>

<p>Sum 
03.2 ± 4.2 
02.3 ± 3.4 
NS </p>

<p>Cardiovascular symptom </p>

<p>Orthostasis 
00.5 ± 0.9 
00.1 ± 0.3 
NS </p>

<p>Syncope 
00.0 ± 0.0 
00.0 ± 0.0 
NS </p>

<p>Sum 
00.8 ± 1.5 
00.2 ± 0.5 
NS </p>

<p>Thermoregulatory symptom </p>

<p>Sweat 
00.4 ± 1.0 
00.0 ± 0.0 
NS </p>

<p>Heat intolerance 
00.1 ± 0.3 
00.2 ± 0.6 
NS </p>

<p>Cold intolerance 
00.4 ± 1.0 
00.0 ± 0.0 
NS </p>

<p>Oiliness of skin 
00.1 ± 0.3 
00.0 ± 0.0 
NS </p>

<p>Sum 
01.1 ± 2.6 
00.8 ± 2.2 
NS </p>

<p>Total score 
15.0 ± 15.4 
11.7 ± 9.5 
NS </p>

<p>www.e-jmd.org 37 </p>

<p>Orthostatic Hypotension in PD ▐ Bae HJ, et al. </p>

<p>be diagnosed as multiple system atrophy (MSA). We followed 
all the patients more than six months and confirmed the good 
response to dopaminergic treatment. Because some patients 
with MSA show good response to treatment in early period, we 
could not exclude the possibility of MSA. Further studies with 
longer period of observation and about the change of dysauto-
nomic symptoms along the disease course are warranted. 
Although pathological implications of autonomic dysfunc-
tions in PD patients have not been established yet, clinical im-
plications can be significant enough to impact the daily activi-
ties of PD patients. Furthermore, most patients do not complain 
of noticeable symptoms, and the unawareness of patients war-
rants careful evaluation. Appropriate management of OH can 
prevent further insult and can improve daily activities of PD 
patients. </p>



</text></tei>