<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4977128" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Acellular dermal matrices (ADM) are now routine in postmastectomy 
prosthetic-based breast reconstruction. The goal of the current study was to com-
pare the complications of 2 ADM products-AlloDerm and Cortiva. 
Methods: A retrospective analysis of prosthetic-based breast reconstruction 
in Atlanta, Ga., over 5 years. Inclusion criteria were the use of the ADM types 
( AlloDerm or Cortiva) and use of a tissue expander or implant. Statistical analysis 
compared group demographics, risk factors, and early complications. 
Results: Of the 298 breast reconstructions, 174 (58.4%) used AlloDerm and 
124 (41.6%) used Cortiva. There was no difference in overall complication fre-
quency (16 AlloDerm and 18 Cortiva; P = 0.195). Within specific categories, there 
was a difference in mastectomy skin flap necrosis, but, based on further regression 
analysis, this was attributable to differences in body mass index (P = 0.036). Further-
more, there were no differences in the rates of infection (6 AlloDerm and 5 Cortiva; 
P = 1.0), seroma/hematoma (9 AlloDerm and 7 Cortiva; P = 1.0), or drain duration 
(13.2 day AlloDerm and 14.2 day Cortiva, P = 0.2). By using a general estimating 
equation for binomial logistical regression, it was found that only current tobacco 
use (P = 0.033) was a significant predictor for a complication. Trending predictors 
were body mass index (P = 0.074) and age (P = 0.093). The type of matrix was not a 
significant predictor for any of the recorded complication (P = 0.160). 
Conclusions: Although AlloDerm is well established, we have shown that Cortiva 
has an equivalent complication frequency. Future work will focus on long-term 
outcome measures and histological evaluation of vascularization and integration. 
A Complication Analysis of 2 Acellular Dermal 
Matrices in Prosthetic-based Breast Reconstruction </p>

<p>Disclosure: Dr. Losken is a speaker for RTI, LifeCell, and No-
vadaq. Neither of the other authors has any financial disclosures. 
The Article Processing Charge was paid for by RTI Surgical, Inc. </p>

<p>Breast </p>

<p>Orion P. Keifer, Jr, MD, PhD,* 
Eugenia K. Page, MD,* 
Alexandra Hart, MD, † 
Randall Rudderman, MD, 
FACS, † 
Grant W. Carlson, MD,* 
Albert Losken, MD, FACS* </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>PRS Global Open • 2016 </p>



<p>The ADM was introduced in the mid-1990s for burn 
reconstruction, but its use has expanded to include many 
applications. 
12 In particular, in the mid-2000s, several re-
ports were published showing the benefits of using ADM 
in implant-based and tissue expander-based reconstruc-
tion. 
13-18 Since that time, the use of ADM in these pro-
cedures has grown tremendously. Several advantages of 
using an ADM have been reported. These include claims 
of superior benefits in terms of cosmetic outcomes sec-
ondary to greater control of the inframammary fold posi-
tion (ie, more support, less visible implant rippling, and 
more fullness of lower pole), lower incidence of capsular 
contracture, higher initial volumes of implants and tissue 
expanders with shorter time to full expansion, and less 
tension on mastectomy skin flaps. 
19-22 However, only some 
of these benefits have been formally evaluated. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Given the increased use of ADMs, several companies 
have introduced their own versions of ADM that vary in a 
number of properties including harvesting source, cross-
linking management, and the process for removing an-
tigens. With the advent of these newer ADMs, there is a 
need to compare these different matrices in terms of com-
plication frequency and type. Here, we add to this growing 
and necessary literature by comparing 2 human ADMs: the 
AlloDerm regenerative tissue matrix (RTM, LifeCell Cor-
poration, Bridgewater, N.J.) and Cortiva allograft dermis 
(RTI Surgical, Alachua, Fla.). Although the characteristics 
of the AlloDerm RTM are documented elsewhere, 
24 Cor-
tiva is an 8-x 16-cm Tutoplast-sterilized, noncrosslinked 
allograft dermis (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>PATIENTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>All patients undergoing either implant-based or tissue 
expander-based breast reconstruction at Emory Univer-
sity and a private practice between April 2010 and August 
2015 were included in this retrospective analysis. Approval 
from the Emory University Institutional Review Board was 
obtained to conduct the study. Inclusion criteria included 
the following: the use of 1 of the 2 types of ADM (Allo-
Derm RTM or Cortiva), at least 60 days of documented </p>

<p>follow-up postoperatively, and sufficient data available 
from chart review. Review of the electronic medical record 
was conducted to collect patient data on demographics, 
amedical and surgical history, breast reconstruction surgi-
cal details, oncological diagnosis and management, and 
follow-up course. All mastectomy types were included. A 
total of 3 surgeons performed the breast reconstructions: 
2 surgeons based at Emory University (A.L. and G.W.C.) 
and 1 surgeon in private practice (R. R.). The primary 
outcome of interest was the incidence of postoperative 
complications. Complications were further categorized as 
seroma (requiring clinic or operating room aspiration/ 
drainage), hematoma (requiring drainage in the operat-
ing room), infection (requiring PO or intravenous anti-
biotics), and mastectomy skin flap necrosis (requiring 
debridement or serial dressing changes) to look at the 
distribution of these complications. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>The vast majority of the cases included were bilateral re-
constructions (81.9%); thus, there was concern that these 
breasts were not independent. Therefore, when possible, 
the analyses were adjusted for clustering to correct for any 
potential dependence between breast pairs. All continu-
ous data were reviewed for potential outliers, which were 
defined as values &gt;3 SDs from the mean (11 breasts from 
9 patients were excluded). Any cases with outliers were 
removed from analysis. The resulting patient characteris-
tics, demographics, and complication frequencies between 
the 2 matrix types were compared using Fisher exact test 
(categorical variables), t tests, and Mann-Whitney U test 
(continuous variables, normally or not-normally distrib-
uted, respectively). Additionally, a binomial logistic regres-
sion model using a general estimating equation (GEE) 
approach was used to determine significant predictors of 
whether a complication would occur or not. In addition 
to the matrix type, other a priori predictors were based 
on published data and included age, 
25,26 body mass index 
(BMI), 
27,28 duration of drain in place, 
29 preoperative radia-
tion treatment, 
20,27 hypertensive status, 
25 and active smoking 
status. 
20,27 In all cases, significance was defined as P &lt; 0.05. 
Furthermore, the results from the regression models are 
presented in terms of odds ratio, 95% confidence interval 
(CI), and the respective P value. All analyses were conduct-
ed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS statistics 22</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM, Armonk, N.Y.</rs>.). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Summary of Demographic, Medical, and Surgical Data </p>

<p>Of the 166 patients in the current study, 136 (81.9%) 
patients had bilateral mastectomies and 30 (18.1%) had 
unilateral mastectomies, with a total of 298 breast recon-
structions. Of these reconstructions, 100 (33.6%) were 
direct-to-implant reconstructions and 198 (66.4%) were 
tissue expander-based reconstructions. With respect to 
the ADM type, 174 (58.4%) used AlloDerm during the re-
construction and 124 (41.6%) used Cortiva. 
When comparing the patient populations in the 2 dif-
ferent ADM groups (Table 1), it is notable that there were </p>

<p>Fig. 1. cortiva aDM integration. image of the cortiva aDM integra-
tion in a patient undergoing tissue expander to implant exchange. </p>

<p>Keifer et al • Complications with ADM in Breast Reconstruction </p>



<p>a few significant differences between the groups. In par-
ticular, the Cortiva group was, on average, 1.6 years older, 
weighed nearly 1.7 kg more (thus had a higher BMI), was 
more likely to have hypertension and was more likely to 
have a cancer pathology diagnosis (mastectomy tissue). 
Importantly, all data presented are uncorrected, with a sig-
nificance value of P &lt; 0.05, as the comparisons were both 
planned and directed toward a single question of whether 
these groups are different. Alternatively, and more con-
servatively, a Bonferroni correction approach for multiple 
comparisons resulted in a significance threshold of 0.0024; 
thus, only age and the weight (and hence BMI) would be 
significantly different between the groups. However, all 
significant factors were controlled for in the binary logistic 
regression using the GEE approach (Table 3). </p>

<p>Complication Frequency with AlloDerm and Cortiva </p>

<p>Overall, there were a total of 34 (11.4%) complications 
in the series (Table 2). Of the 34 complications, 16 (9%) 
were in the AlloDerm group and 18 (14%) were in the 
Cortiva group, with no significant differences between the 
groups (P = 0.195). Further categorization of the types 
of complication showed that the Cortiva group was asso-
ciated with significantly higher incidence of mastectomy </p>

<p>flap necrosis (6 vs 1; P = 0.022). There were no significant 
differences in the frequency of infection or hematoma/ 
seroma. Furthermore, there was no difference in the 
number of patients having to return to the operating 
room to resolve the complication (9 vs 13; P = 0.115). 
Given the potential meaningful differences between 
groups (Table 1), a binary logistic regression model was 
built using a GEE approach. The primary outcome of the 
model was the occurrence of a complication, and the pre-
dictors used in the model are presented in Table 3. Of all 
the predictors, only the current smoking status of the pa-
tient was significant in predicting a complication. In par-
ticular, current smoking status was associated with an odds 
ratio of 5.262, with a 95% CI of 1.145-24.184 (P = 0.033). 
None of the factors that were different between the groups 
significantly predicted the occurrence of a complication 
nor did the type of ADM used in the surgery. 
As there seemed to be a significant difference in the oc-
currence of mastectomy flap necrosis between the groups, 
this was further examined with another GEE logistic regres-
sion model looking at predictors of mastectomy flap ne-
crosis from factors that were significantly different between 
the groups (age, BMI, cancer diagnosis, and hypertension) 
and the significant predictor from the overarching regres-</p>

<p>Table 1. Patient Demographics, Medical History, and Surgical Details for Each Matrix </p>

<p>Variable 
Total (%) 
AlloDerm (%) 
Cortiva (%) 
P </p>

<p>Patient count 
166 
98 (59) 
68 (41) 
Breast count 
298 
174 (58.4) 
124 (41.6) 
Mean age ± SD (y) 
50.1 ± 10.9 
48.5 ± 11.0 
52.4 ± 10.3 
0.002* 
Mean weight ± SD (kg) 
64.8 ± 11.7 
63.1 ± 11.0 
69 ± 14.7 
0.008 † 
Mean height ± SD (cm) 
164.3 ± 6.6 
164.2 ± 7.3 
164.5 ± 5.5 
0.921 † 
BMI ± SD 
24.0 ± 4.3 
23.4 ± 4.1 
24.8 ± 5.5 
0.010 † 
Hypertension 
62 (20.8) 
28 (45.2) 
34(54.8) 
0.021 ‡ 
Diabetes 
20 (6.7) 
11 (55) 
9(45) 
0.816 ‡ 
Smoking 
12 (4) 
6 (50) 
6 (50) 
0.564 ‡ 
Cancer diagnosis (mastectomy tissue) 
136 (45.6) 
88 (64.7) 
48 (35.3) 
0.044 ‡ 
Implant-based reconstruction 
100 (33.6) 
57 (57) 
43 (43) 
0.804 ‡ 
Expander-based reconstruction 
198 (66.4) 
117 (59.1) 
81 (49.9) 
Mean initial implant/TE volume ± SD (mL) 
323.5 ± 124.8 
323.4 ± 137.9 
323.7 ± 104.4 
0.332 † 
Bilateral reconstruction 
268 (89.9) 
153(57.1) 
115 (42.9) 
0.241 ‡ 
Axillary lymph node dissection 
64 (21.5) 
40 (62.5) 
24 (37.5) 
0.478 ‡ 
Sentinel lymph node biopsy 
135(45.3) 
81 (60) 
54 (40) 
0.638 ‡ 
Preoperative radiation 
7 (2.4) 
5 (71.4) 
2 (28.6) 
0.703 ‡ 
Mean postoperative drain duration ± SD (d) 
13.6 ± 6.7 
13.2 ± 6.9 
14.2 ± 6.4 
0.200* 
Surgeon 1 
72 (24.2) 
36 (50) 
36 (50) 
0.194 ‡ 
Surgeon 2 
92 (30.8) 
59 (64.1) 
33 (35.9) 
Surgeon 3 
134 (45) 
79 (59) 
55 (41) 
Nipple sparing 
56 (18.2) 
23 (40.7) 
33 (59.3) 
0.098 ‡ 
Skin sparing 
242 (80.2) 
150 (62.3) 
92 (37.7) </p>

<p>*Independent samples t test. 
 †Mann-Whitney U test. 
 ‡Fisher exact test. 
Bold value indicates a significant result. </p>

<p>Table 2. Patient Early Complications (&lt;60 d) for Each Matrix </p>

<p>Variable 
Total (%) 
AlloDerm (%) 
Cortiva (%) 
P </p>

<p>Complication 
34 (11.4) 
16 (47) 
18 (53) 
0.195* 
Seroma/hematoma 
16 (5.4) 
9 (56.3) 
7 (43.7) 
1.000* 
Infection 
11 (3.7) 
6 (54.6) 
5 (45.4) 
1.000* 
Mastectomy flap necrosis 
7 (2.3) 
1 (14.3) 
6 (85.7) 
0.022* 
Complication leading to 
reoperation </p>

<p>22 (7.3) 
9 (40.9) 
13 (59.1) 
0.115* </p>

<p>*Fisher exact test 
Bold value indicates significant result. </p>

<p>PRS Global Open • 2016 </p>



<p>sion (eg, smoking status). The results of the regression 
analysis (Table 4) suggest that the only significant predic-
tor of mastectomy flap necrosis is BMI with an odds ratio 
of 1.587 and a 95% CI of 1.029-2.447 (P = 0.036). Notably, 
matrix type was not a significant predictor. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Given both the increase in the number of ADM options 
and the utilization of ADMs in breast reconstruction, it is 
necessary to study their complication frequency and types. 
There are a number of studies that have compared the va-
riety of ADMs available. In that same vein, this study com-
pared the commonly used AlloDerm matrix with the more 
recent Cortiva matrix. Importantly, this is the first study to 
evaluate the complications associated with Cortiva. 
Our study consisted of 298 breast reconstructions, 
one of the largest data sets in the published literature. 
Of these breast reconstructions, approximately 58% used 
AlloDerm and 42% used Cortiva, which ensured an ad-
equate number of cases for a balanced statistical analysis. 
The overall complication frequency across both ADMs was 
11.4%, which is in line with the reported "true" complica-
tion rate of 12% based on a meta-analysis of previous ADM 
studies. 
19 The overall demographic profiles were also in 
line with previous studies, suggesting generalizability to 
the population undergoing breast reconstruction. 
With respect to the primary outcome measure, the re-
sults of the study show that there is no significant differ-
ence in the overall complication rates between AlloDerm 
and Cortiva. Furthermore, using regression analysis, it was 
found that the only significant predictor for a complica-
tion was current smoking status. The finding that smoking 
is associated with higher complications is well documented 
across the surgical literature, including numerous studies </p>

<p>in breast reconstruction. 
25,30,31 While not reaching signifi-
cance, it is worth noting that age and BMI were trending 
toward significance (P &lt; 0.10). These findings are also 
consistent with previous literature that has suggested, after 
smoking, BMI and age tend to be the next strongest pre-
dictors of complications. 
25,27,28 Although there are multiple 
factors that resulted in a lack of significance, 1 major fac-
tor is that outpatients' mean BMIs were lower than those 
reported in other studies and had a smaller SD. Such dif-
ferences are important as most studies report increased 
complications with BMI scores &gt;30, which was about 10% 
of our sample. 
32 Likewise, the relationship between age 
and complications is often associated with patients whose 
age is &gt;65 years, which was about 8% of our sample. 
Interestingly, although there were no differences in the 
overall complication rate, the frequency of mastectomy skin 
flap necrosis was significantly higher in the Cortiva group. 
However, given the number of factors that were different be-
tween the groups at baseline (eg, age, BMI, cancer diagnosis, 
and hypertension diagnosis), these factors along with ADM 
type and active smoking status were selected for regression 
analysis of only mastectomy skin flap necrosis. Based on the 
results of this analysis, BMI was the only significant predictor 
of mastectomy skin flap necrosis. Thus, after controlling for 
differences between groups, the type of matrix was not sig-
nificant in predicting mastectomy skin flap necrosis. These 
findings are consistent with the fact that the Cortiva group 
had a significantly higher BMI when compared with the Al-
loDerm group (Table 1), and that BMI is a known predictor 
of mastectomy skin flap necrosis. </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>In terms of limitations and generalization, there are 
number of items that should be mentioned. Overall, al-
though the sample size is quite large compared with other 
published studies, the number of complications for analy-
sis limits the robustness of the conclusions. These limita-
tions were partially ameliorating statistical methods that 
could analyze the data at the breast level (versus the patient 
level) while accommodating for potential dependence be-
tween the pair of breasts. Additionally, although there are 
2 centers from which patients' data were collected, these 
centers were located in the same town and may reflect re-
gional demographic differences. Furthermore, the data 
are retrospective, hence neither blinded nor randomized, 
introducing potential confounders. Also, the follow-up 
complications were limited to the first 60 days, as longer 
term data are still not available for many patients. Thus, 
data were unable to address longer term complications in-
cluding capsular contracture. Future work should involve 
a larger sample size, data from geographically separated 
multicenters, and longer follow-up duration for more 
long-term complications (eg, capsular contractures). Ad-
ditionally, given the potential differences in complication 
type between matrices, additional histological analysis of 
integration and vascularization would be beneficial. </p>

<p>Orion Paul Keifer, Jr, MD, PhD 
Emory University School of Medicine 
c/o Emory MD/PhD Program 
1648 Pierce Dr NE 
Atlanta, GA 30307 
E-mail: okeifer@emory.edu </p>

<p>Table 3. Results from GEE Binomial Logistical Regression 
for Overall Complications </p>

<p>Predictors 
Odds Ratio 
95% CI 
P </p>

<p>Age 
0.969 
0.934-1.005 
0.093 
BMI 
1.116 
0.989-1.259 
0.074 
Drain duration 
0.970 
0.919-1.025 
0.277 
Tobacco 
5.262 
1.145-24.184 0.033 
Preoperative radiation 
1.970 
0.157-24.684 0.599 
Matrix type 
1.822 
0.789-4.206 
0.160 
Cancer (mastectomy tissue) 
1.696 
0.846-3.397 
0.136 
Initial TE or implant volume 
0.998 
0.994-1.003 
0.488 
Tissue expander or implant 
reconstruction </p>

<p>0.582 
0.171-1.976 
0.385 </p>

<p>Hypertension 
1.184 
0.375-3.732 
0.773 
Diabetes mellitus 
1.049 
0.159-6.936 
0.960 </p>

<p>Table 4. Results from GEE Binomial Logistical Regression of 
Skin Necrosis </p>

<p>Predictors 
Odds Ratio 
95% CI 
P </p>

<p>Age 
0.988 
0.936-1.042 
0.650 
BMI 
1.587 
1.029-2.447 
0.036 
Tobacco 
4.376 
0.313-61.231 
0.273 
Matrix type 
11.247 
0.916-138.130 0.059 
Cancer (mastectomy tissue) 
0.625 
0.141-2.774 
0.536 
Hypertension 
1.130 
0.202-8.646 
0.772 </p>

<p>Keifer et al • Complications with ADM in Breast Reconstruction </p>



<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Drs. Shannon Gourley and Robert Lyles for sharing 
their time and expertise with advanced statistical analysis. </p>



</text></tei>