<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4989302" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Protists are perhaps the most lineage-rich of microbial lifeforms, but remain largely unknown. 
High-throughput sequencing technologies provide opportunities to screen whole habitats in depth 
and enable detailed comparisons of different habitats to measure, compare and map protistan 
diversity. Such comparisons are often limited by low sample numbers within single studies and a lack 
of standardisation between studies. Here, we analysed 232 samples from 10 sampling campaigns 
using a standardised PCR protocol and bioinformatics pipeline. We show that protistan community 
patterns are highly consistent within habitat types and geographic regions, provided that sample 
processing is standardised. Community profiles are only weakly affected by fluctuations of the 
abundances of the most abundant taxa and, therefore, provide a sound basis for habitat comparison 
beyond random short-term fluctuations in the community composition. Further, we provide evidence 
that distribution patterns are not solely resulting from random processes. Distinct habitat types and 
distinct taxonomic groups are dominated by taxa with distinct distribution patterns that reflect their 
ecology with respect to dispersal and habitat colonisation. However, there is no systematic shift of 
the distribution pattern with taxon abundance. 
Protists are abundant and diverse in aquatic and 
terrestrial ecosystems and fulfil critical ecosystem 
functions (del Campo and Massana, 2011; Triadó-
Margarit and Casamayor, 2012; Bates et al., 2013; 
Geisen et al., 2015). They not only strongly contribute 
to primary production (Field et al., 1998) and bacterial 
grazing (Boenigk and Arndt, 2002; Glücksman et al., 
2010), but are also major players in diverse nutrient 
cycles (Finlay and Esteban, 1998; Coleman and 
Whitman, 2004) and as such, they form the basis of 
aquatic and terrestrial food webs along with bacteria. 
The ecological key role of protists is sharply 
contrasted by an only vague understanding of their 
diversity. During the past decade, the assumption of 
unlimited dispersal of protists was progressively </p>

<p>replaced by the 'moderate endemicity model' 
(Foissner, 2006; Bass and Boenigk, 2011; but see 
Livermore and Jones, 2015). With the increasing 
acceptance of dispersal limitations in protists, the 
research focus turned to the underlying patterns of 
protist distribution and the generalisability of such 
patterns across protistan taxa and across different 
habitat types (Katz et al., 2005; Bik et al., 2012). 
Owing to methodical limitations, analyses of proti-
stan distribution patterns up to recently were centred 
around a handful of more or less abundant taxa (for 
example, Lopéz-García et al., 2001; Moreira and 
López-García, 2002). High-throughput sequencing 
has already revolutionised environmental surveys 
of microbial organisms and opened the door for 
large-scale analyses of molecular microbial commu-
nity analyses. Generating many millions of reads, 
these methods allow for deep-sequencing of micro-
bial communities (Caporaso et al., 2012) and make 
possible a much more realistic understanding of 
protistan diversity and distribution than former, 
lower capacity technologies (Medinger et al., 2010; 
Lecroq et al., 2011; Degnan and Ochman, 2012). </p>

<p>Correspondence: L Grossmann, Biodiversity Department, Centre 
for Water and Environmental Research, University of Duisburg-
Essen, Universitaetsstrasse 5, Essen 45141, Germany. 
E-mail: lars.grossmann@uni-due.de 
Received 15 July 2015; revised 14 December 2015; accepted 
4 January 2016; published online 9 February 2016 </p>

<p>The ISME Journal (2016) 10, 2269-2279 
© 2016 International Society for Microbial Ecology All rights reserved 1751-7362/16 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/ismej </p>

<p>The current high-throughput sequencing technolo-
gies now allow for sufficiently deep community 
analysis. Nevertheless, most studies have been 
restricted to few sampling sites (Caron and 
Countway, 2009; Stoeck et al., 2009; Nolte et al., 
2010; Caporaso et al., 2012). Only recently, large-
scale multisample sets, specifically from the marine 
biome (de Vargas et al., 2015), allow for deeper 
insights into protist distribution patterns. 
Here, we address the generalisability of protist 
distribution patterns with respect to habitat type, 
taxonomic group and taxon abundance based on a 
large data set comprising 232 samples from soil as 
well as fresh, brackish and marine waters. Besides 
judging the relative importance of habitat type, 
seasonality and geographic region in shaping protist 
distribution patterns, we evaluate the question on 
whether or not rare taxa show similar distribution 
patterns to the abundant taxa. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Sampling and sample preparation 
Sampling sites and sampling procedures of the 
assembled data set are summarised in Supple-
mentary Table S1. The 10 different sampling 
campaigns representing eight different habitat types 
are referred to as Alpine spatial, Alpine seasonal, 
Lake District, Winterpico, Estuarine, Soil, Whale 
Fall, Borehole, heterotrophic nanoflagellates (HNF) 
and Biofilm within this paper. Briefly, they comprise 
an alpine transect of freshwater samples (Austria, 32 
lakes at 450-2050 m elevation) and a seasonal 
sampling of three Austrian lakes (Lake Mondsee 
region, 9-28 samples per lake, range: April to 
December), a seasonal sampling in the English Lake 
District, partially size-fractionated (UK, 7 sites, 2-3 
samples per site) and size-fractionated samples of the 
same sites in winter (Winterpico), an estuarine 
gradient (UK, River Colne, 11 sites, partially seaso-
nal), a comparative soil sampling from fallow and re-
cultivated fallow fields (UK, 15 sites across England), 
a sampling on the seabed of and from below a 
sunken whale (Whale fall) (North Sea, Sweden), a 
collection of aquifer samples from boreholes (UK, 
Berkshire), an experimental set-up of a size-filtered 
(5 μm) freshwater sample fed with different food 
bacteria and focusing on heterotrophic nanoflagel-
lates (Czech Republic, Římov reservoir) and an 
experimental set-up of freshwater biofilms treated 
with the viricide TamiFlu (Southern UK). Owing 
to the different natures of the collected samples, 
slightly modified sampling protocols and DNA-
isolation methods (compared in Supplementary 
Table S1) had to be used. </p>

<p>PCR and pyrosequencing 
PCR amplifications targeting the SSU V9 region were 
conducted using primers 1391F (Lane, 1991; Stoeck </p>

<p>et al., 2010) and Euk B (Medlin et al., 1998; Stoeck 
et al., 2010) both carrying a 5′-tail for the 454 
sequencing (adapter A: GCCTCCCTCGCGCCATCAG, 
adapter B: GCCTTGCCAGCCCGCTCAG) to amplify a 
broad spectrum of eukaryotes. The final concentra-
tions in all of the PCR reactions were as follows: 1 μl of 
DNA template in 20 μl PCR reaction with 0.4 units of 
Phusion polymerase; primers at 0.25 μM final concen-
tration; dNTPs at 0.2 mM final concentration; 4 μl 
Phusion buffer; and 12.2 μl water. The PCR conditions 
consisted of an initial denaturation at 94°C for 4 min 
and 35 cycles of: 30 s at 95°C, annealing for 60 s at 
60°C, elongation for 2 min at 72°C, followed by a final 
extension step of 10 min at 72°C. We received 
sequences of about 200bp from PCR. Pyrosequencing 
was carried out on a 454 Genome Sequencer FLX 
System using the Titanium chemistry (454 Life 
Science, Branford, CT, USA) with 50-100 amplified 
samples placed onto one 454 sequencing platform, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Bioinformatics 
For the bioinformatics analyses, we used a standar-
dised pipeline including (i) quality filtering, 
(ii) clustering and (iii) taxonomy annotation. 
Low-quality tails were removed from the reads and 
trimmed reads with an average Phred quality score 
less than 25 were discarded. Additionally, we 
removed all reads with at least one base with a 
quality of less than 15 and also all reads that 
contained errors in the primer regions. Multiplex 
Identifiers were used to separate the different 
samples. Chimeras were removed using UCHIME 
(<rs id="software-0" type="software">USEARCH</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v.6</rs>) (Edgar et al., 2011). Subsequently, 
the sequences that passed the quality filtering were 
clustered into Operational Taxonomic Units (OTUs) 
with <rs id="software-1" type="software">UCLUST</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 6</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Edgar</rs>, 2010) at 97% 
sequence identity for further analyses. Sequences 
were sorted by abundance beforehand clustering 
and clustering was performed for all sequences of all 
sampling campaigns at a time (that is, not individu-
ally by campaigns). For all OTUs, we used <rs id="software-2" type="software">BLASTn</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 2.2.25+</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Altschul</rs> et al., 1990) with the 
nucleotide collection database nr/nt and the NCBI 
Taxonomy Database (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/ 
taxonomy; RefSeq Release 57 (14 January 2013)) 
to annotate the OTUs with taxonomic information. 
For reasons of comparison, we also processed our 
data with the <rs id="software-3" type="software">CANGS</rs> pipeline (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Pandey</rs> et al., 2010) 
and received similar results. </p>

<p>Taxonomic analysis of the sequence data set 
OTUs and their reads from bioinformatic filtering 
and assembling were used to analyse the community 
structure and distribution patterns of OTUs 
(abundant vs rare, habitat-wise, and taxon-wise). 
For analyses on higher taxonomic group level, the 
following taxa were selected: Ciliophora, Dinophy-
ceae, Apicomplexa, Alveolata rest, Bicosoecida, </p>

<p>Protistan community analysis 
L Grossmann et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>Oomycetes, Chrysophyceae, Synurophyceae, Bacil-
lariophyta, Stramenopiles rest, Cercozoa, Rhizaria 
rest, Heterolobosea, Euglenida, Kinetoplastida, 
Euglenozoa rest, Excavata rest, Choanoflagellida, 
Chytridiomycota, Microsporidia, Ascomycota, Basi-
diomycota, Glomeromycota, Amoebozoa, Apusozoa, 
Glaucocystophyceae, Rhodophyta, Viridiplantae 
without Embryophytes, Cryptophyta, Katablephari-
dophyta and Haptophyta. OTUs affiliated with 
metazoa and embryophytes (as multicellular organ-
isms), as well as with Bacteria and Archaea, have 
been excluded before further analyses. Thus, only 
protists were analysed since they were the focus of 
our investigation. The 'rest' categories within the 
analysis are meant to collect minor groups and OTUs 
without further affiliation within Alveolata, Strame-
nopiles, Rhizaria and Excavata in order to fully show 
the protistan diversity present in the samples. 
Eukaryotic OTUs that are not met by one of the 
given taxonomic groups or have not been deleted 
from the data set for the given reasons are shown as 
'others'. Furthermore, OTUs that could not be 
affiliated to entries in the NCBI database are labelled 
as 'unknown'. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis of the sequence data set 
The specific nature of the data matrix that results 
from deep-sequencing diversity counting is charac-
terised by a multitude of zero and single counts of 
OTUs (zero: 98.35%, single counts: 0.83%, two 
counts: 0.27%, ten counts: 0.014%, etc.) not fitting 
traditional statistical methods of diversity compar-
ison. Therefore, we used a two-step standardisation 
of site data; first, rarefaction of the sites was done 
using the 'drarefy' function provided by the VEGAN 
R package (Oksanen et al., 2013), followed by 
Hellinger transformation (Legendre and Gallagher, 
2001). After application of these procedures, the 
resulting pretransformed data matrix of OTUs can be 
submitted to Ward cluster analysis and further 
multivariate analyses (see Figures 1a and b; 
Legendre and Gallagher, 2001; Borcard et al., 
2011). Cluster analysis could be calculated on both 
the OTU and the meta-group level (for chosen meta-
groups see above). The principle component analysis 
based on Hellinger distances shows those taxonomic 
groups with most explanatory value for clustering 
and separation of samples (see Figure 1b). 
As reads per sample differ decisively between 
samples, rarefaction values at a read level of 100 
reads (including extrapolation for a few samples, see 
Colwell et al., 2012) were used to compare species 
richness and composition of OTUs among samples. 
For the shown composition within each sample, the 
'drarefy' function (R package VEGAN; Oksanen et al., 
2013) was used to minimise the bias in the rarefac-
tion analysis. The more classical 'rrarefy' is not 
suitable here, as recently pointed out by McMurdie 
and Holmes (2014). Thus, more exact relationships 
of meta-groups from higher read levels are kept </p>

<p>intact (see Figure 1a); however, this could possibly 
result in OTU percentages per meta-group of less 
than 1 at a read level of 100. The community struc-
tures of the different samples were analysed using 
the mean relative abundance of meta-group reads per 
sampling, which showed significant differences 
between meta-groups among sampling campaigns 
(see Figure 2, also compare Supplementary Table 
S2). </p>

<p>Weibull distribution in protistan OTUs 
Following preliminary tests, the distribution 
patterns of individual OTUs did not follow a Poisson 
distribution (Po0.05) or a normal distribution (Ricci, 
2005). Although not common, a two-parameter 
Weibull density distribution, which is used in 
survival and engineering analyses, fitted our data. 
Recently, a three-parameter Weibull empirical 
cumulative distribution function was used for fitting 
diversity curves (Livermore and Jones, 2015), show-
ing the applicability of the Weibull distribution in 
ecology. For our data, the fitting of the Weibull 
distribution among sites (y-axis = no. of sites, x-
axis = abundance of OTU in these sites) passed the 
KS-test (that is, the null hypothesis could not be 
rejected, P-value: 40.05) for almost all OTUs and 
was consequently used as the distribution for further 
analysis. All KS-tests were performed with R, 
referring to Birnbaum and Tingey (1951). All OTUs 
passed the KS-test (that is, the Weibull distribution 
could not be rejected with all P-values 40.9) when 
P-values were corrected for multiple testing by using 
p.adjust (method = 'fdr', R package 'stats'). When 
corrections for multiple testing were disregarded, the 
KS-test rejected the Weibull distribution for 10 out of 
1249 OTUs. Even though these 10 OTUs passed 
the test when correctly applied (that is, corrected for 
multiple testing), we decided to mark these OTUs in 
the figures (Figures 3a and b, top). The shape 
parameter k of the Weibull distribution is suitable 
for comparing the distribution of abundant and less 
abundant taxa as the total abundance primarily 
affects the scale, but not the shape parameter. 
Therefore, we focus on the comparative analysis of 
the parameter k. For k = 1, the two-parameter 
Weibull distribution switches to that of the expo-
nential distribution, for k~3.6 it switches to a 
Gaussian distribution. The k-values in this study all 
lie between 1 and 3.6 forming curves of positive 
skewness. The skewness of the curves as a function 
of k indicates the value of evenness of OTU reads 
over sites and is, therefore, suitable of showing 
distribution patterns of taxa. Shape values k of 
Weibull distributions were compared using Mann-
Whitney U-tests. All U-tests were performed with 
Sigmaplot 12.5 (Systat Software Inc., Erkrath, 
Germany) referring to Mann and Whitney (1947). 
The control data set, tested against Bacillariophyta as 
the closest subgroup data set within the analysed 
data, was generated by the function 'rnorm' with </p>

<p>Protistan community analysis 
L Grossmann et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>Figure 1 Results of cluster analysis of sites. (a) Bars (left to right) are ordered by clusters from cluster analysis which almost entirely fit 
the actual sampling campaigns (see cluster names); black arrows at bottom indicate those sites within clusters not identified with the 
respective sampling campaign; within clusters, order (left to right) is by species richness of identified taxonomic groups, respectively; 
species richness is shown as height of bars out of 100; community composition is shown as colour of bars by identified taxonomic groups 
(bottom) and merged or unidentified reads (top) (procedure: drarefy, see Materials and methods). (b) PCA showing clusters from cluster 
analysis (encircled) and significant taxonomic groups for sorting of sites (arrows) (pretreatment of data: drarefy+Hellinger transformation, 
see Materials and methods); PCA was calculated on the basis of percentage of taxonomic groups within sites. Abbreviation: PCA, principle 
component analysis. </p>

<p>Protistan community analysis 
L Grossmann et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>n = 55 (normally distributed), average value and 
median = 1 (Ricci, 2005), and with the same standard 
deviation value as calculated for the Bacillariophyta 
data set. We also provide a graph with exemplary 
Weibull curves of typical OTUs in the 
Supplementary Information on methods. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The large-scale analysis undertaken herein-carried 
out as a multiple sample habitat comparison-
showed that protistan communities differ decisively. 
They did so in terms of OTU presences in a distinct 
sample and habitat as well as in the ratio of higher 
taxonomic groups (meta-groups) (Figure 1a). Taking 
all samples into account, Ciliophora were dominat-
ing in terms of d-rarefied sequence abundance at 
13% followed by Bacillariophyta at 9.7% and 
Chrysophyceae at 9%. </p>

<p>Community composition patterns 
Despite many OTUs being distributed across 
different campaigns and sample types, many OTUs 
were either specific for distinct habitats/campaigns 
or their relative abundance deviated considerably 
from that in other habitats/campaigns. Cluster </p>

<p>analysis based on protistan sequence analysis 
separated different habitat types. Specifically soil, 
biofilm and brackish sediments (estuarine), and 
freshwaters were distinguished and each showed 
a specific community composition (Figure 1b). Size-
fractionated samples, such as the heterotrophic 
nanoflagellates data set, were also separated by 
cluster analysis. 
This differentiation based on OTUs was also 
reflected by shifts in the community composition 
on the level of higher taxonomic groups (Figures 1b 
and 2). Substrate-bound taxa were, as expected, 
specifically abundant in sediments. However, while 
Amoebozoa and Cercozoa were specifically more 
abundant in the soil samples (see column A in 
Figure 2), Heterolobosea, Kinetoplastida, Apusozoa 
and to some extent Chrysophyceae were specifically 
abundant in the aquifers of the borehole samples (see 
column B in Figure 2). The Peridiosporomycota 
(Oomycetes) were found to be relatively abundant in 
both habitats. In the size-fractionated samples, small 
heterotrophic nanoflagellates taxa showed relatively 
high sequence abundances, specifically Chrysophy-
ceae, Katablepharidiophyceae, Choanomonada and 
Bicosoecida (see column F in Figure 2). In our 
biofilm samples, we found an increased sequence 
abundance of Chlorophyta and streptophytic algae </p>

<p>Figure 2 Bars in individual graphs showing percentage of indicated taxonomic group in sampling campaigns (bars on the 
x-axis = campaigns, respectively, from left to right: 1-Soil, 2-Borehole, 3-Biofilm, 4-Whale fall, 5-Estuarine, 6-Lake District 
1, 7-Lake District 2, 8-Alpine Lakes, 9-Winterpico, 10-HNF). Columns (a-f) sorting out taxonomic groups with highest percentage in 
(a) Soil, (b) Borehole, (c) Biofilm, (d) Whale fall and Estuarine (salt and brackish waters), (e) Lake District 1 and 2 and Alpine Lakes 
(freshwater) and (f) Winterpico and HNF (size-fractionated samplings). Abbreviation: HNF, heterotrophic nanoflagellates. </p>

<p>Protistan community analysis 
L Grossmann et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>Protistan community analysis 
L Grossmann et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>(labelled as 'Viridiplantae' without Embryophytes), 
Cryptophyta, Bacillariophyta and Chytridiomycota. 
Substrate-bound taxa did not have particularly high 
sequence abundances in the biofilm samples (see 
column C in Figure 2). The marine samples showed 
comparatively low read counts of Chlorophyta, 
streptophytic algae, Chytridiomycota and Crypto-
phyta, but comparatively high reads of Bacillario-
phyta in the salinity gradient along the Colne 
estuary, and of Dinophyceae and Euglenida at the 
whale fall site (see column D in Figure 2). 
These habitat-specific community profiles were 
similar for almost all samples of the respective 
habitat types. Cluster analysis revealed only very 
few samples that would be sorted into the wrong 
campaign based on sequence data (see arrows in 
Figure 1a). </p>

<p>Differential distribution patterns of protistan taxa 
For the analysis of OTU distribution patterns among 
sites, we analysed the shape parameter k of the 
Weibull distribution (see the Materials and methods 
section). This analysis only revealed a minor 
modulation in the shape factor of the Weibull 
distribution between abundant and less abundant 
taxa. The mean Weibull shape value k is rather 
similar irrespective of the relative overall abundance 
of the OTUs (Figure 3a, top). Shape values of 
individual OTUs scatter around a median of 1.67, 
but there was no distinct change in the median k for 
less abundant OTUs. The median shape value of 1.67 
indicates that taxon distribution is not due to 
unlimited random dispersal (which would favour a 
value of 1 or lower, that is, a colonisation from one 
site with high frequency), but on the contrary that 
some factors work against invasion and/or colonisa-
tion of habitats (significant U-test of shape value 1.67 
vs 1, P-value: o0.001). One might argue that this 
effect is caused by the different habitat types 
included in the analysis. However, even when the 
analysis is restricted to one habitat type within a 
distinct geographic region, taxon distribution cannot 
exclusively be explained by unlimited random 
dispersal (for example, soil sites UK: shape </p>

<p>parameter = 2.099, significant U-test vs 1, P-value: 
o0.001; for example, Austrian lakes+Lake District 1: 
shape parameter = 1.711, significant U-test vs 1, P-
value o0.001; compare methods in this paper and 
Figure 3a-mid and bottom). In contrast, the shape 
parameter is even higher when the analysis is 
restricted to soils, indicating that random dispersal 
is even less important in soils compared with aquatic 
habitats. However, the scatter around the median k 
increases for rare taxa (Figure 3b, top right). 
Similarly, the scatter of sites of occurrence as a 
function of total read number increases (Figure 3b, 
top left). In contrast, the most abundant taxa do have 
very similar distribution patterns, indicated by both 
a very similar shape parameter in the Weibull 
distribution (Figure 3b, top right) and a narrow range 
of the ratio of number of sites vs total read 
abundance (Figure 3b, top left). Both observations 
indicate a stronger differentiation of distribution 
patterns in rare taxa, whereas abundant taxa show 
relatively uniform distribution patterns. Owing to 
this, within the rare taxa, a differentiation into more 
generalist taxa (occurring at a relatively high number 
of sites) and more specialised taxa (restricted to a few 
sites) is pronounced. 
Similarly, distribution differs between taxonomic 
groups. Diatom OTUs, as one extreme, are charac-
terised by a comparatively low k and occur at a 
relatively low number of sites for a given total read 
count. Amoebozoa, on the other hand, are charac-
terised by comparatively high shape values and 
occur at a relatively high number of sites for a given 
total read count. The distribution pattern of Amoe-
bozoa indicates a broader (more generalist) distribu-
tion, whereas the Diatom distribution pattern reflects 
a narrower (more specialised) distribution (signifi-
cant U-test of shape values for Amoebozoa vs 
Bacillariophyceae, P-value: o0.001). The Chryso-
phyceae are somewhat in between the two strategies. 
Nevertheless, k is significantly larger as would 
be expected for random distribution for all taxa 
(Amoebozoa: shape parameter = 2.139, significant 
U-test vs 1, P-value: o0.001; Bacillariophyceae: 
shape parameter = 1.449, significant U-test vs 1, 
P-value: o0.001; Chrysophyceae: shape = 1.595, </p>

<p>Figure 3 Distribution patterns as functions of the log abundance of OTUs in the samplings, OTUs are also sorted (left to right) by read 
abundance (logarithmic scale). The grey line shows the relation between read abundance and the number of sites where the distinct OTU 
occurs. (a) Weibull shape of individual OTUs ( = distribution of reads over sites) as red and black dots for all Eukaryota (top), OTUs 
occurring in freshwater (middle) and OTUs occurring in soil (bottom); x indicate the 10 OTUs for which Weibull distribution was rejected 
when corrections for multiple testing were disregarded (Po0.05, see Materials and methods); for OTUs occurring in less than 15 sites, a 
calculation of Weibull shape is not possible (unreliable), these dots were set to 0 instead of filling the lower right part of the plots; OTUs are 
sorted (left to right) by read abundance (logarithmic scale); the grey line (for values see the right y-axis) showing the connection of 
read abundance and presence in sites; the red dotted line showing the median shape value of all Eukaryota; black dotted lines showing the 
median shape value of freshwater and soil, respectively. (b) Graphs showing OTUs as a function of log of occurrence in sites and log of 
abundance of reads (left half of the figure) and as their Weibull shape value ( = distribution of reads over sites) (right half of the figure) for 
all Eukaryota (top-red dots), Amoebozoa (upper middle-black dots), Chrysophyceae (lower middle-black dots) and Bacillariphyta 
(bottom-black dots); the 10 OTUs for which Weibull distribution was rejected (Po0.05, see Materials and methods) are indicated by an x; 
the dotted black vertical line in the left-hand graphs indicates the read abundance threshold up to which Weibull shape value calculation 
(right-hand graphs) was carried out (also see the x-axis); additionally, for OTUs occurring in less than 15 sites, a calculation of Weibull 
shape was not possible (unreliable), these dots were set to 0 instead of filling the lower right part of the plots. </p>

<p>Protistan community analysis 
L Grossmann et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>significant U-test vs 1, P-value: 0.009) (Figure 3b, 
right and left). 
Non-random distribution patterns are also sup-
ported by principle component analysis (Figure 1b). 
Based on the molecular diversity, the samples 
clustered according to habitat types. Nevertheless, 
within habitat types, regional effects were pro-
nounced. Samples from the same sampling site 
clustered together irrespective of seasonal effects. 
Furthermore, samples from the same region (for 
example, from Austria) mostly clustered together. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Here, we address the generalisability of protist 
distribution patterns. We demonstrate that protist 
taxon distribution varies depending on habitat types, 
taxonomic groups and taxon abundance. 
With our analysis, we offer a large-scale and cross-
biome investigation of protist diversity and distribu-
tion. The standardised comparison across diverse 
habitats is, to our knowledge, unique to this study 
and includes standardised nucleic acid processing, 
sequencing, bioinformatics, and statistical analyses 
of sediment, biofilm and water samples of diverse 
locations. Owing to the approach of comparing 
different habitat types, sampling methods had to be 
altered. Standardisation is otherwise complete 
and, therein, goes beyond comparative platform 
approaches (Caporaso et al., 2012; Mahé et al., 
2014). Further, even though an unbiased view on 
protist diversity is difficult to achieve (compare 
Supplementary Information on methods), the stan-
dardisation over all 232 samples of the analysis 
allows for addressing overarching patterns of protist 
diversity in a comparative approach. </p>

<p>General patterns of dispersal limitation 
Protist distribution and potential dispersal limita-
tions have been in the focus of protist ecology and 
diversity research since the early observations. The 
scientific dispute can be traced back at least to de 
Candolle (1820) and Ehrenberg (1849, 1850). With 
the catchy phrase 'Everything is everywhere, but the 
habitat selects' Baas-Becking formulated the central 
idea behind the ongoing dispute (Bass and Boenigk, 
2011; Boenigk, 2014). In this form, the idea of global 
dispersal was revived in the 1980s, resulting in the 
recent debate on protist dispersal and endemism as 
summarised by O'Malley (2007), de Wit and Bouvier 
(2006) and Bass and Boenigk (2011). It is now 
generally believed that protist distributions cannot 
be explained exclusively by unlimited dispersal 
(Foissner, 2006; Bass and Boenigk, 2011), expressed, 
for instance, by the moderate endemicity model 
(Foissner, 1999, 2004, 2006). However, microbial 
organisms may, in general, show wider distribution 
patterns as compared with higher organisms 
(Livermore and Jones, 2015). We demonstrate that </p>

<p>the distribution patterns of individual protistan 
OTUs, specifically as expressed by the shape para-
meter of the Weibull distribution, violate the 
assumption of unlimited dispersal. This is consistent 
with findings of Livermore and Jones (2015) who 
demonstrated for bacteria that microbial diversity 
patterns non-randomly vary between ecosystem 
types. Our analysis further shows that patterns of 
non-random dispersal are stronger in soil habitats 
than aquatic habitats. </p>

<p>Consistency of distribution patterns within habitat types 
Molecular data produce strong protistan community 
signatures, that is, habitats being characterised by 
distinct protistan communities (Bates et al., 2011; 
Tedersoo et al., 2014; de Vargas et al., 2015). 
Consistent with earlier findings from microscopy 
and Sanger sequencing studies (Fenchel, 1994; 
Anderson, 2012; Tikhonenkov et al., 2012), soil 
and aquifer protist communities are dominated by 
substrate-bound taxa (Foissner, 1991; Novarino et al., 
1997; Adl, 2003; Adl and Coleman, 2005; Risse-Buhl 
et al., 2013). Likewise, the marine samples showed a 
high proportion of sequences affiliated with diatoms, 
dinoflagellates and euglenids (Ingmanson and 
Wallace, 1995; Graham et al., 2009), whereas 
Synurales, Cryptophytes, Chlorophyta and Chytri-
diomycota were particularly prominent in fresh-
water samples (Dokulil et al., 2001; Graham et al., 
2009). 
The consistency of distribution patterns with 
respect to habitat type was also reflected at the level 
of individual OTUs. Principle component analysis, 
as well as cluster analysis, revealed similar commu-
nity profiles for samples originating from similar 
habitats. These community profiles were highly 
specific for distinct habitat types. Even seasonal 
variation did not blur the distinctiveness of commu-
nity structure. Therefore, community profiles based 
on high-throughput sequencing data (in this case the 
18S rDNA V9 region) appear highly promising 
for overarching habitat comparisons as well as for 
long-term monitoring studies. </p>

<p>The relatively uniform distribution pattern of abundant 
taxa is contrasted by a high variation in rare taxa 
Molecular studies typically report a high fraction of 
rare taxa. The high number of rare taxa led to the 
assumption that rarity might be an evolutionarily 
advantageous trait in these organisms (Logares et al., 
2014) and favoured speculations on potentially 
deviating distribution patterns between rare and 
abundant taxa (for example, Nolte et al., 2010). 
In contrast to these earlier studies, we show that rare 
and abundant taxa have generally similar distribu-
tion patterns. However, whereas the distribution 
patterns of individual taxa are relatively uniform for 
abundant OTUs, the deviation among individual rare 
OTUs is high. Further, the proportion of rare and </p>

<p>Protistan community analysis 
L Grossmann et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>abundant taxa differs distinctively by habitat type: 
the soil samples are characterised by a high even-
ness, that is, a multitude of OTUs appear at higher 
abundances in many of the samples. On the contrary, 
aquatic sites have a comparatively lower evenness 
with usually only a small number of dominant 
species reaching higher abundances, accompanied 
by many rare taxa, at a distinct point in time. Thus, 
in addition to taxonomic profile/community struc-
ture differences between habitats, abundance and 
diversity patterns appear to be characteristic for 
different habitat types. 
Differences in distribution patterns indicate differ-
ential niche widths between taxa (Boenigk et al., 
2006; Bass et al., 2009). In general, broad niche 
widths and high ecophysiological tolerances should 
be reflected by broad distributions of taxa across 
different samples. In contrast, taxa with more 
restricted niche widths and/or ecophysiological 
tolerances should be restricted to fewer samples. 
The largely uniform distribution patterns for abun-
dant OTUs indicate that dispersal and success of 
colonisation is largely comparable between taxa, 
resulting in similar distribution patterns. Within the 
rare biosphere, however, distribution patterns vary 
strongly between individual taxa, presumably indi-
cating a more selective niche adaptation. Thus, we 
suspect that the rare biosphere offers an even 
stronger potential use for comparative habitat ana-
lyses, including biological monitoring, as compared 
to the more abundant taxa, which are usually the 
focus of such studies. </p>

<p>Differential patterns between taxonomic groups 
With respect to taxonomic groups, amoebozoan 
taxa (that is, amoebozoan OTUs in our analysis) are 
often characterised by broader distribution patterns, 
indicating a more generalist strategy, whereas the 
diatom taxa (that is, OTUs) are often characterised by 
narrower distribution patterns, indicating a more 
specialised strategy. The Chrysophytes, for instance, 
show intermediate distribution patterns. These dif-
ferences in distribution presumably indicate a 
differential dispersal and proliferation among taxa 
even on higher taxonomic levels, including not all, 
but most OTUs of a higher taxonomic group. With 
regard to taxonomy, it seems plausible that distribu-
tions are markedly different between soil-inhabiting 
and endobenthic taxa, such as Amoebozoa, which 
are presumably less prone to random dispersal, and 
planktonic or epibenthic taxa. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>With our analyses, we show that limited dispersal 
and distribution in protists differ by habitat type as 
well as by taxonomic group. Further, rare and 
abundant taxa do not show generally different 
patterns of distribution. The variation of distribution </p>

<p>patterns in rare taxa is, however, much more 
pronounced making the rare biosphere as revealed 
by molecular investigations a promising candidate 
for comparative habitat analyses. For analyses as 
undertaken herein, standardisation of a large number 
of samples is essential and can be provided by large-
scale, methodologically unified data sets and parallel 
investigations made possible by high-throughput 
methods. Such investigations are more directly 
comparable than data sets generated by different 
'wet' laboratory conditions (PCR protocols, cycling 
conditions, reagents, etc.) and different bioinformatic 
methods. This unified/standardised approach is 
recommended for revealing robust and fine-scale 
differences between community structures and 
distributions of taxa that might be missed or skewed 
by non-standardised comparisons. This is important 
for further illuminating the biodiversity and biology 
of protists on Earth and thus broaden our knowledge 
on these and other under-researched micro-
organisms. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank all cooperation partners, especially Thomas Bell, 
Gary Bending, Adrian Glover, Paul Gosling, Rene Groben, 
Martin Hahn, Sally Hilton, Katja Lehmann, Stephen 
Maberly, Cecilia Martinez-Perez, Louise Maurice, Mark 
Osborn, Kevin Purdy, Karel Šimek, Andrew Singer, Cindy 
Smith, Peter Stadler and CEH Lancaster and Wallingford 
(UK) for access to samples and assistance with sampling. 
We thank the German Research Foundation (BO-3245/2) 
for financial support. </p>



<p>Protistan community analysis 
L Grossmann et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>



<p>Protistan community analysis 
L Grossmann et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>



<p>This work is licensed under a Creative 
Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-
NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or 
other third party material in this article are included 
in the article's Creative Commons license, unless 
indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material 
is not included under the Creative Commons license, 
users will need to obtain permission from the license 
holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy 
of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on The ISME Journal website (http://www.nature.com/ismej) </p>

<p>Protistan community analysis 
L Grossmann et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

</text></tei>