<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4623719" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>578 </p>

<p>Objective: to describe self-care behavior and its associated factors in a sample of heart failure </p>

<p>Brazilian patients. Method: descriptive cross-sectional study with non-probabilistic sample of </p>

<p>116 ambulatory patients undergoing heart failure treatment. Self-care was evaluated using the </p>

<p>Self-Care of Heart Failure Index, (scores ≥70 points=appropriate self-care). Association tests </p>

<p>were applied, considering a descriptive level of 0.05. Results: the mean age of participants was </p>

<p>57.7 (SD =11.3) years; 54.3% were male; the mean schooling was 5.5 (SD = 4.0) years; and </p>

<p>74.1% had functional class II-III. The mean scores on the subscales of the Self-Care of Heart </p>

<p>Failure Index indicated inappropriate self-care (self-care maintenance: 53.2 (SD =14.3), self-</p>

<p>care management: 50.0 (SD = 20.3) and self-care confidence: 52.6 (SD=22.7)) and it was </p>

<p>found low frequencies of participants with appropriate self-care (self-care maintenance, 6.9%), </p>

<p>self-care management (14.7%) and self-care confidence (19%). Higher scores of the Self-Care </p>

<p>of Heart Failure Index were associated with: reduced left ventricular ejection fraction (p=0.001), </p>

<p>longer time of experience with the disease (p=0.05) and joint monitoring by physician and </p>

<p>nurse (p=0.007). Conclusion: investments are needed to improve the self-care behavior and the </p>

<p>nursing can play a relevant role in this improvement. </p>

<p>Self-care in chronic diseases is related to the </p>

<p>maintenance of the appropriate level of physical </p>

<p>and psychological well-being, decrease in morbidity </p>

<p>and mortality and in the use and cost of healthcare, </p>

<p>increase in patient's satisfaction, improvement of </p>

<p>control sense and life quality, reasons by which self-</p>

<p>care is a central concern in the care for people with </p>

<p>chronic diseases (1) . </p>

<p>The self-care concept has evolved over the years. </p>

<p>It is associated with autonomy, independence and </p>

<p>individual responsibility for healthy behaviors, as well </p>

<p>as for the development of activities required to manage </p>

<p>and monitor health conditions (2-3) . </p>

<p>The illness experience requires that people integrate </p>

<p>practices and recommendations to self-care, in order to </p>

<p>maintain the greatest well-being possible. The self-care </p>

<p>promotion is essential in chronic disease by involving </p>

<p>activities and skills that should be learned and used by </p>

<p>the individuals to improve their quality of life (3) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Chronic diseases are the main causes of mortality </p>

<p>worldwide, with heart failure standing out as one of </p>

<p>the leading causes of hospitalization and high rates </p>

<p>of morbidity and mortality in many countries (4) . Heart </p>

<p>failure (HF) is currently one of the major public health </p>

<p>problems in Brazil, and its complex and progressive </p>

<p>nature often results in adverse events, such as high </p>

<p>rate of rehospitalization and mortality, which could be </p>

<p>reduced if there were appropriate self-care (5) . </p>

<p>In HF, self-care refers to the behaviors </p>

<p>developed by people to maintain their health (self-</p>

<p>care maintenance) and decisions they make about </p>

<p>worsening of symptoms when they occur (self-care </p>

<p>management) (2) . The self-care maintenance involves </p>

<p>adherence to pharmacological recommendations, </p>

<p>consumption of a low-salt diet, cessation of tobacco </p>

<p>use, limited alcohol consumption, daily monitoring </p>

<p>of body weight, signs or symptoms, and HF </p>

<p>decompensation. From this perspective, self-care is a </p>

<p>decision-making process that patients use in choosing </p>

<p>behaviors that maintain physiological stability, and </p>

<p>response to the symptoms when they occur (2) . </p>

<p>Self-care has been the focus of research in the </p>

<p>healthcare area and instruments for its evaluation </p>

<p>have been developed. In a systematic review (6) , which </p>

<p>aimed to identify the instruments to measure self-</p>

<p>care in HF patients, 14 instruments were identified of </p>

<p>which two had been subjected to rigorous psychometric </p>

<p>tests: European Heart Failure Self-Care Behaviour </p>

<p>Scale (EHFScBS) and Self-Care of Heart Failure Index </p>

<p>(SCHFI). Both instruments assess different aspects of </p>

<p>self-care behavior and have been validated for use in </p>

<p>Brazil (7) . The EHFScBS aims to assess the recognition of </p>

<p>signs and symptoms of decompensation and decision-</p>

<p>making in the occurrence of these symptoms; SCHFI, </p>

<p>in turn, in addition to evaluating the recognition and </p>

<p>actions to improve the signs and symptoms of clinical </p>

<p>decompensation, includes aspects related to how </p>

<p>confident the individual feels to perform activities </p>

<p>related to self-care (2) . </p>

<p>Recent studies with samples of HF patients indicate </p>

<p>that self-care is inappropriate (7-10) and that individuals </p>

<p>who participated in educational self-management </p>

<p>programmes showed a better self-care behavior (11) . </p>

<p>Socio-demographic and clinical characteristics typical </p>

<p>of HF are described in the literature as variables that </p>

<p>influence self-care of HF patients. Cultural aspects </p>

<p>and education level are also mentioned as factors </p>

<p>that can influence self-care behavior in different </p>

<p>nationalities (12-13) . </p>

<p>In Brazil, self-care behavior is little studied and </p>

<p>the variables that influence self-care are still little </p>

<p>explored in this population, which motivated this </p>

<p>study. Knowing the self-care behavior in samples of </p>

<p>Brazilians with HF contributes to the understanding </p>

<p>of this phenomenon and so that nurses recognize </p>

<p>behaviors that need to be modified or added for a </p>

<p>better disease control and consequently, a better </p>

<p>quality of life for HF people. </p>

<p>Based on the above, the objectives of this study </p>

<p>were to describe the self-care behavior of HF adult </p>

<p>patients, by means of the SCHFI, Brazilian version; and </p>

<p>analyze self-care based on certain socio-demographic </p>

<p>and clinical variables and monitoring type. </p>

<p>Method </p>

<p>The cross-sectional observational study was </p>

<p>performed with data obtained by personal interview </p>

<p>of a non-probabilistic sample of 116 adult patients in </p>

<p>an ambulatory care setting for HF in the period from </p>

<p>April to September 2013. Researchers previously </p>

<p>checked the medical records of potentially eligible </p>

<p>patients for their recruitment. Those who met the </p>

<p>inclusion criteria were invited to participate in the </p>

<p>study, with a study explanation and presentation </p>

<p>of the Informed Consent (IC). It was included </p>

<p>all who agreed to participate in the study in the </p>

<p>predetermined period. </p>

<p>580 </p>

<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Rev. Latino-Am. Enfermagem 2015 July-Aug.;23(4):578-86. </p>

<p>The study was carried out at an ambulatory of </p>

<p>a public teaching hospital, specialized in cardiology, </p>

<p>in the city of São Paulo, Brazil. Such ambulatory has </p>

<p>a multidisciplinary approach for monitoring clinically </p>

<p>stable patients. The nursing consultation is routinely </p>

<p>performed to those patients who need therapeutic </p>

<p>optimization, as well as general guidance on the disease, </p>

<p>symptoms control and treatment adherence, following </p>

<p>the guidelines of the III Brazilian Guidelines on Chronic </p>

<p>Heart Failure (14) . However, due to insufficient number of </p>

<p>nurses, this service is not offered to all patients who </p>

<p>attend the service. The medical team refers to the </p>

<p>nursing care only patients with clinical decompensation, </p>

<p>difficulty of adherence to the treatment regimen and </p>

<p>those in need of optimization and a better control of the </p>

<p>therapeutic regimen. </p>

<p>The inclusion criteria were: regularly enrolled in the </p>

<p>HF ambulatory of the institution where the data were </p>

<p>collected; 18 years or older, confirmed medical diagnosis </p>

<p>for HF, functional class I, II or III, according to the </p>

<p>classification of the NYHA (14) , and clinical conditions that </p>

<p>would allow them to participate in the interviews. It was </p>

<p>excluded those with psychiatric disorders, oncological </p>

<p>diseases, infectious diseases with repercussions on the </p>

<p>general state or endocrine-metabolic diseases without </p>

<p>treatment (for example, diabetes mellitus or thyroid </p>

<p>diseases); patients in early postoperative period (up </p>

<p>to 60 days postoperatively) of any surgical procedure, </p>

<p>conditions that could interfere with usual self-care </p>

<p>behavior. </p>

<p>The self-care behavior was evaluated using the </p>

<p>Brazilian version of the Self-Care of Heart Failure Index </p>

<p>-v 6.2 (SCHFI) (7) . The SCHFI is a self-care measure </p>

<p>composed of 22 items divided into three scales: self-</p>

<p>care maintenance (10 items), self-care management (6 </p>

<p>items) and self-care confidence (6 items). The scores </p>

<p>for each domain range from 0 to 100 points, calculated </p>

<p>from the transformation of the pure scores (each </p>

<p>item of the scale ranges from 1 to 4). Higher scores </p>

<p>reflect greater self-care and scores ≥70 points for each </p>

<p>subscale indicate appropriate self-care (2) . The Brazilian </p>

<p>version of the SCHFI revealed reasonable reliability and </p>

<p>validity estimates (7) . In the present study, Cronbach's </p>

<p>alpha coefficient for the total of the SCHFI was 0.70, </p>

<p>and in the subscales, it ranged from 0.40 to 0.74. </p>

<p>According to the guidelines for use of the SCHFI (2) , the </p>

<p>"self-care management" subscale should be applied only </p>

<p>to patients who reported difficulty to breath or swelling </p>

<p>in the ankles in the month prior to the application of the </p>

<p>instrument. </p>

<p>Regarding to socio-demographic variables, it </p>

<p>was considered age, gender, education, ethnicity (as </p>

<p>patient's medical record, according to the categories </p>

<p>described by the Brazilian Institute of Geography and </p>

<p>Statistics -IBGE); marital cohabitation, employment </p>

<p>status (self-report for the current work situation). The </p>

<p>clinical variables were: HF functional status (as assessed </p>

<p>by the investigators at the data collection time, following </p>

<p>the guidelines established by the New York Heart </p>

<p>Association -NYHA (14) ), Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction </p>

<p>(LVEF) (as recorded in the echocardiogram reports), </p>

<p>HF etiology (as recorded in the patient's chart), time of </p>

<p>experience with the disease (self-report of years since HF </p>

<p>was diagnosed and/or the date of the first register of HF </p>

<p>diagnosis at the medical record), cognitive aspect (Mini </p>

<p>Mental State Examination -MMSE (15) ) and comorbidity </p>

<p>(Charlson Comorbidity Index -CCI) (16) , classified as low </p>

<p>(scores 1-2), moderate (3-4) and high (≥5) comorbidity </p>

<p>index (16) . It was also assessed the type of monitoring </p>

<p>received by the patient (if supervised exclusively by the </p>

<p>physician or by physician and nurse). </p>

<p>Data were analyzed using descriptive statistics; the </p>

<p>association of the SCHFI with the variables of interest </p>

<p>was carried out using an ANCOVA model, controlling by </p>

<p>the cognitive decline. All analyzes were performed using </p>

<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> ® , <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 17</rs>, and the significance level adopted </p>

<p>was of 5%. </p>

<p>The Ethics Committee of the institution where it </p>

<p>was conducted approved the study (Protocol number </p>

<p>145.630 -2012) and all participants signed the Informed </p>

<p>Consent Form. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Table 1 shows the socio-demographic and clinical </p>

<p>characteristics of the participants. </p>

<p>Table 2 shows the descriptive statistics for the </p>

<p>scales of self-care maintenance (maintenance), self-care </p>

<p>management (management) and self-care confidence </p>

<p>(confidence). The proportions of patients with appropriate </p>

<p>self-care (score ≥70 points) were: maintenance=6.9% </p>

<p>management=14.7% and confidence=19% </p>

<p>Tables 3, 4 and 5 show the results of the association </p>

<p>tests between selected variables and the SCHFI. On the </p>

<p>self-care maintenance scale, the care provided by the </p>

<p>physician and nurse (p=0.007) was associated with a </p>

<p>better self-care (Table 3). In the self-care management </p>

<p>subscale, ejection fraction (p=0.001) and longer time of </p>

<p>experience with the disease (p=0.05) were associated </p>

<p>with better self-care (Table 4). There was no association </p>

<p>581 </p>

<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Conceição AP, Santos MA, Santos B, Cruz DALM. </p>

<p>Table 1 -Socio-demographic characterization, clinical and type of monitoring of the participants (N=116). São Paulo, </p>

<p>SP, Brazil, 2014 </p>

<p>Variables 
Mean 
Standard 
deviation 
Minimum 
Maximum 
N 
% </p>

<p>Age (years) 
57.7 
11.3 
20 
81 </p>

<p>Education (years of study) 
5.5 
4.0 
0 
20 </p>

<p>Time of experience with the disease (in months) 
46.7 
42.4 
2 
149 </p>

<p>Ejection fraction (%)* 
40.4 
12.9 
20 
73 </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Male 
63 
54.3 </p>

<p>Female 
53 
45.7 </p>

<p>Ethnicity </p>

<p>White 
69 
59.5 </p>

<p>Black 
31 
26.7 </p>

<p>Brown 
16 
13.8 </p>

<p>Marital cohabitation 
70 
60.3 </p>

<p>Work situation </p>

<p>Works 
26 
22.4 </p>

<p>Unemployed 
16 
13.8 </p>

<p>Retired or pensioner 
61 
52.6 </p>

<p>Sick leave 
13 
11.2 </p>

<p>HF functional class (New York Heart Association) </p>

<p>I 
30 
25.9 </p>

<p>II 
54 
46.5 </p>

<p>III 
32 
27.6 </p>

<p>Cognitive impairment 
52 
44.8 </p>

<p>HF Etiology </p>

<p>Dilated cardiomyopathy 
47 
40.5 </p>

<p>Chagas cardiomyopathy 
44 
37.9 </p>

<p>Ischemic cardiomyopathy 
13 
11.2 </p>

<p>Cardiomyopathy to clarify 
12 
10.3 </p>

<p>High level of comorbidity CCI  † 
30 
25.9 </p>

<p>Type of monitoring </p>

<p>Consultation with a physician 
61 
52.6 </p>

<p>Consultation with physician and nurse 
55 
47.4 </p>

<p>*Missing data for a patient </p>

<p> †Charlson Comorbidity Index </p>

<p>Table 2 -Descriptive statistics of the Self-Care Heart Failure Index, Brazilian version (N=116). São Paulo, SP, Brazil, </p>

<p>2014 </p>

<p>N 
Mean 
Standard 
deviation 
95% CI 
Median </p>

<p>Self-care maintenance </p>

<p>1. Do you weigh yourself? 
116 
1.9 
0.9 
[1.7;2.1] 
2.0 </p>

<p>2. Do you check if your ankles are swollen? 
116 
2.9 
1.1 
[2.7;3.1] 
3.5 </p>

<p>3. Do you try to avoid getting sick (for example: be vaccinated 
against flu, avoid contact with sick people)? 
116 
3.0 
1.2 
[2.8;3.3] 
4.0 </p>

<p>4. Do you practice any physical activity? 
116 
1.5 
0.9 
[1.3;1.7] 
1.0 </p>

<p>5. Are you assiduous in the consultations with the doctor or nurse? 
116 
2.9 
1.4 
[2.7;3.2] 
4.0 </p>

<p>6. Do you ingest a low-salt diet? 
116 
3.4 
1.0 
[3.2;3.6] 
4.0 </p>

<p>7. Do you exercise for 30 minutes? 
116 
1.5 
1.0 
[1.3;1.7] 
1.0 </p>

<p>8. Do you forget or fail to take any of your medicines? 
116 
3.3 
0.8 
[3.2;3.5] 
3.0 </p>

<p>9. Do you request foods with little salt when eating out or visiting 
someone? 
116 
1.4 
0.9 
[1.2;1.6] 
1.0 </p>

<p>10. Do you use a system (pillbox, reminders) to remind you about 
your medicines? 
116 
2.9 
1.3 
[2.6;3.2] 
4.0 </p>

<p>Total score -self-care maintenance 
116 
50.5 
15.7 
[47.6;53.4] 
54.9 </p>

<p>Self-care management* </p>

<p>(continue...) </p>

<p>582 </p>

<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Rev. Latino-Am. Enfermagem 2015 July-Aug.;23(4):578-86. </p>

<p>N 
Mean 
Standard 
deviation 
95% CI 
Median </p>

<p>11. How quickly did you recognize them as symptoms of heart 
failure? 
68 
2.7 
1.4 
[2.3;3.1] 
3.0 </p>

<p>12. Reduce the salt at your diet 
68 
2.5 
1.1 
[2.2;2.8] 
3.0 </p>

<p>13. Reduce fluid intake 
68 
2.5 
1.2 
[2.2;2.8] 
3.0 </p>

<p>14. Take a further diuretic 
68 
1.6 
1.0 
[1.3;1.9] 
1.0 </p>

<p>15. Contact your doctor or nurse for guidance 
68 
3.1 
1.0 
[2.8;3.3] 
3.0 </p>

<p>16. Think of one of the above features you tried the last time when 
you had trouble to breath or swollen ankles. Are you sure this 
feature helped you? </p>

<p>68 
1.4 
1.6 
[1.0;1.8] 
0.0 </p>

<p>Total score -self-care management 
68 
50.0 
20.3 
[45.0; 54.9] 
50.0 </p>

<p>Self-care confidence </p>

<p>17. Be free of the heart failure symptoms? 
116 
2.4 
0.9 
[2.2;2.6] 
2.0 </p>

<p>18. Follow the recommended treatment? 
116 
3.1 
0.6 
[3.0;3.3] 
3.0 </p>

<p>19. Evaluate the importance of your symptoms? 
116 
2.6 
0.8 
[2.4;2.7] 
2.5 </p>

<p>20. Recognize changes in health, if they occur? 
116 
2.7 
0.8 
[2.6;2.9] 
3.0 </p>

<p>21. Do something that can relieve your symptoms? 
116 
2.5 
0.8 
[2.3;2.7] 
2.0 </p>

<p>22. Assess whether a drug works? 
116 
2.8 
0.7 
[2.7;3.0] 
3.0 </p>

<p>Total score -self-care confidence 
116 
58.1 
18.2 
[54.8;61.3] 
55.6 </p>

<p>*The data of the self-care management subscale are lower because this scale is administered only to patients with heart failure symptoms in the last month. </p>

<p>Table 2 -(continuation) </p>

<p>between the variables and the self-care confidence </p>

<p>subscale (Table 5). </p>

<p>The ejection fraction had no significant negative </p>

<p>correlation with the scores in self-care maintenance </p>

<p>(r= -0,143; p=0.102) and the time of experience with </p>

<p>the disease had no significant correlation with self-care </p>

<p>maintenance (r=0.068; p=0.435). </p>

<p>The correlation tests between self-care </p>

<p>management scores and ejection fraction resulted </p>

<p>in significant negative correlation (r= -0,361; </p>

<p>p=0.001). The correlation between self-care </p>

<p>management and time of experience with the </p>

<p>disease was positive but was not significant </p>

<p>(r=0.239; p=0.052). </p>

<p>There was no significant correlation between </p>

<p>the self-care confidence scores and ejection fraction </p>

<p>(r=0.029; p=0.816), or time of experience with the </p>

<p>disease (r=-0.142; p=0.136). </p>

<p>Table 3 -Association analysis between the selected variables and the Self-Care Heart Failure Index, self-care </p>

<p>maintenance subscale, Brazilian version (N=116). São Paulo, SP, Brazil, 20-p </p>

<p>Variables 
Self-care maintenance </p>

<p>Mean 
Standard deviation 
Median 
p* Value </p>

<p>Gender 
0.542 </p>

<p>Male 
49.5 
16.5 
49.9 </p>

<p>Female 
51.8 
14.8 
53.3 </p>

<p>Ethnicity 
0.835 </p>

<p>White 
50.5 
16.2 
50.0 </p>

<p>Black 
51.6 
14.4 
53.3 </p>

<p>Brown 
48.9 
17.0 
50.0 </p>

<p>CCI  † 
0.268 </p>

<p>Low 
46.0 
13.6 
50.0 </p>

<p>Moderate 
51.1 
15.6 
50.0 </p>

<p>High 
53.4 
17.2 
51.7 </p>

<p>NYHA 
0.515 </p>

<p>I 
50.9 
16.7 
53.3 </p>

<p>II 
48.8 
14.3 
50.0 </p>

<p>III 
53.2 
17.1 
53.3 </p>

<p>Type of healthcare 
0.007 </p>

<p>Medical and nursing consultation 
54.8 
14.6 
56.6 </p>

<p>Medical consultation 
46.7 
15.8 
49.9 </p>

<p>*ANCOVA test </p>

<p> †Charlson Comorbidity Index </p>

<p>583 </p>

<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Conceição AP, Santos MA, Santos B, Cruz DALM. </p>

<p>Table 5 -Analysis of association between selected variables and the Self-Care Heart Failure Index, self-care confidence </p>

<p>subscale, Brazilian version (N=116). São Paulo, SP, Brazil, 2014 </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>Self-care maintenance </p>

<p>Mean 
Standard 
deviation 
Median 
p* Value </p>

<p>Gender 
0.832 </p>

<p>Male 
57.7 
17.8 
61.1 </p>

<p>Female 
58.7 
18.8 
66.7 </p>

<p>Ethnicity 
0.924 </p>

<p>White 
58.6 
19.2 
66.7 </p>

<p>Black 
57.7 
18.5 
66.7 </p>

<p>Brown 
56.9 
13.0 
61.2 </p>

<p>CCI  † 
0.546 </p>

<p>Low 
55.3 
17.8 
66.7 </p>

<p>Moderate 
59.9 
17.9 
66.7 </p>

<p>High 
57.0 
19.2 
58.4 </p>

<p>NYHA 
0.478 </p>

<p>I 
58.3 
19.2 
66.7 </p>

<p>II 
59.7 
17.0 
66.7 </p>

<p>III 
55.4 
19.2 
55.6 </p>

<p>Type of healthcare 
0.969 </p>

<p>Medical and nursing consultation 
58.3 
16.8 
61.1 </p>

<p>Medical consultation 
58.0 
19.4 
66.7 </p>

<p>*ANCOVA test </p>

<p> †Charlson Comorbidity Index </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, the mean scores obtained for the scales </p>

<p>of self-care maintenance, management and confidence </p>

<p>of the SCHFI, version 6.2, were all below 70 points </p>

<p>(Table 2) which is the minimum limit score indicative </p>

<p>of appropriate self-care. These results are similar to </p>

<p>the studies conducted in other countries (8-10,17-19) . In </p>

<p>another study with a sample of Brazilian residents of </p>

<p>the State of Rio Grande do Sul, self-care maintenance </p>

<p>Table 4 -Association analysis between the selected variables and the Self-Care Heart Failure Index, self-care </p>

<p>management subscale, Brazilian version (N=116). São Paulo, SP, Brazil, 2014 </p>

<p>Variables 
Self-care maintenance </p>

<p>Mean 
Standard deviation 
Median 
p* Value </p>

<p>Gender 
0.663 </p>

<p>Male 
48.0 
22.1 
35.0 </p>

<p>Female 
52.1 
18.2 
40.0 </p>

<p>Ethnicity 
0.271 </p>

<p>White 
52 
20.3 
50.0 </p>

<p>Black 
44.7 
18.8 
40.0 </p>

<p>Brown 
50.5 
22.9 
45.0 </p>

<p>CCI  † 
0.942 </p>

<p>Low 
46.1 
21.5 
50.0 </p>

<p>Moderate 
50.1 
20.2 
45.0 </p>

<p>High 
53.7 
19.7 
57.5 </p>

<p>NYHA 
0.069 </p>

<p>I 
41.2 
16.2 
30.0 </p>

<p>II 
45.4 
21.5 
37.5 </p>

<p>III 
57.2 
18.1 
57.5 </p>

<p>Type of healthcare 
0.098 </p>

<p>Medical and nursing consultation 
55.4 
20.1 
45.0 </p>

<p>Medical consultation 
45.4 
19.5 
35.0 </p>

<p>*ANCOVA test </p>

<p> †Charlson Comorbidity Index </p>

<p>584 </p>

<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Rev. Latino-Am. Enfermagem 2015 July-Aug.;23(4):578-86. </p>

<p>(47.0; SD=28.3) (7) and self-care confidence (58.0; </p>

<p>SD=25.5) (7) were similar to this study (50.0, SD=20.3 </p>

<p>and 58.1; SD=18.2, respectively, as shown in Table 2). </p>

<p>However, the same was not observed for the self-care </p>

<p>management, which in the mentioned study had a mean </p>

<p>score of 57.0 (SD=14.3) (7) and 50.5 was obtained in </p>

<p>this study (SD=15.7; Table 2). It is noteworthy that, in </p>

<p>the association study (7) , it was excluded patients with </p>

<p>cognitive impairment and all patients had participated in </p>

<p>at least one nursing consultation. In this study, 44.8% of </p>

<p>patients had cognitive decline and 52.6% have not gone </p>

<p>through a nursing consultation (Table 1). These factors </p>

<p>may have contributed to the differences observed </p>

<p>between the two studies. </p>

<p>The appropriate self-care proportion (6.9%) in </p>

<p>the self-care maintainance scale of this study was </p>

<p>lower than that observed in other studies, in which </p>

<p>the proportion ranged from 14.5 to 52.0% (9-10,17-21) . </p>

<p>The content of the self-care maintenance scale refers </p>

<p>to behaviors to maintain the physiological stability (2) . </p>

<p>Participation in multidisciplinary programmes focused </p>

<p>on the symptoms control is a strategy commonly </p>

<p>performed in other realities (22) , different from the reality </p>

<p>of the study population (52.6% are assisted only by the </p>

<p>doctor), which could explain the results regarding self-</p>

<p>care maintenance. This observation can be reinforced </p>

<p>by the results of this study which showed that patients </p>

<p>followed up also by the nurse had significantly higher </p>

<p>scores for self-care maintenance (p=0.007) (Table 3). </p>

<p>Among the items of the self-care maintenance </p>

<p>subscale, the lowest average scores were observed </p>

<p>for the behaviors: "Do you practice any physical </p>

<p>activity?", "Do you exercise for 30 minutes?" and "Do </p>

<p>you request foods with little salt when eating out or </p>

<p>visiting someone?" (Table 2). These findings are similar </p>

<p>to those of other studies, showing that low levels </p>

<p>of physical activity and excessive sodium intake are </p>

<p>common among HF patients, despite possible cultural </p>

<p>differences (9-10,18,23) . The low level of physical activity </p>

<p>may be related to activity intolerance and exacerbation </p>

<p>of symptoms to efforts, common in HF patients, and </p>

<p>lack of programmes promoting physical activity by HF </p>

<p>patients, in our environment. </p>

<p>On the self-care management scale, which deals </p>

<p>with patient's responses to the symptoms when they </p>

<p>occur, the proportion of patients with appropriate self-</p>

<p>care (14.7%) was higher than that found in a sample </p>

<p>of Australians (12.0%) (6) and Thai (5.0%) (17) , but lower </p>

<p>than it was found for samples of Italians (24.4%) (9) , </p>

<p>Canadians (21.0%) (21) and Chineses (34.9%) (10) . </p>

<p>The item "Take a further diuretic" had one of the </p>

<p>lowest scores in the self-care management scale (Table </p>

<p>2), which may have contributed so that the mean </p>

<p>score on this scale has fallen far below appropriate, as </p>

<p>observed in other studies (7,9-10) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>At the ambulatory where </p>

<p>this research was conducted, to recommend the use of </p>

<p>an extra diuretic, is not a routine practice, as well as in </p>

<p>other countries (9-10) . </p>

<p>Higher self-care management scores were </p>

<p>associated with lower ejection fraction (p=0.001) </p>

<p>and it was expected that a longer time of experience </p>

<p>with the disease was associated with better self-</p>

<p>care management performance, which did not occur </p>

<p>(r=0.239; p=0.052). Studies with larger samples may </p>

<p>reveal significant correlation among these variables, </p>

<p>which would be consistent with the theoretical model </p>

<p>of the SCHFI. This model is based on the naturalistic </p>

<p>decision-making, where decision-making depends </p>

<p>on the experience and knowledge that has been </p>

<p>developed through experience (2) . For HF patients, the </p>

<p>key to a naturalistic decision-making is the symptoms </p>

<p>recognition, which would explain the expectation of high </p>

<p>scores in self-care management for patients with long </p>

<p>time of experience with the disease (2) . Self-care requires </p>

<p>learning, understanding, interpreting and responding </p>

<p>skills, and decision-making is an important process </p>

<p>for the health management (24) . In this study, cognitive </p>

<p>impairment was present in most of the population </p>

<p>evaluated (52%), which possibly may have contributed </p>

<p>to low scores in the self-care scale. A systematic </p>

<p>review showed that HF patients have significantly </p>

<p>worse cognitive performance than healthy controls and </p>

<p>ischemic heart disease patients (25) . Considering the </p>

<p>importance of the decision-making regarding the theory </p>

<p>of self-care in HF, cognition is an important variable to </p>

<p>be considered. The cognitive impairment has relevant </p>

<p>prevalence in this population. Therefore, knowing the </p>

<p>self-care behavior in patients with HF and cognitive </p>

<p>impairment can direct the nurse to choosing the best </p>

<p>educational strategies to assist this patient to acquire </p>

<p>and maintain the appropriate self-care. </p>

<p>Although the situation of self-care in this study </p>

<p>sample is worrying, patients who were also followed up </p>

<p>by nurses, by not only doctors, showed higher scores </p>

<p>on self-care maintenance and self-care management </p>

<p>scales in the association tests (Tables 3 and 4). To </p>

<p>better interpret the results obtained, it would be </p>

<p>necessary to have data on the reasons why certain </p>

<p>patients are referred for nurses monitoring. Due to the </p>

<p>low availability of nurses to the patient demand, it is </p>

<p>585 </p>

<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Conceição AP, Santos MA, Santos B, Cruz DALM. </p>

<p>assumed that patients who have more trouble controlling </p>

<p>the disease are referred, which can difficult achieving </p>

<p>the appropriate self-care. In addition, it was observed </p>

<p>that the nursing instructions practiced in the study </p>

<p>place, focused on specific patients' complaints without </p>

<p>a theoretical orientation, such as HF self-care, which </p>

<p>provides support for the establishment of programmes </p>

<p>to develop self-care, integrating maintenance and </p>

<p>management dimensions (22) . Interventions that focus </p>

<p>on specific self-care behaviors are more effective </p>

<p>than general educational programmes (23) . The key </p>

<p>role of the nurse is the patient's education for early </p>

<p>recognition of symptoms, for better decisions to be </p>

<p>taken in the presence of symptoms and evaluation of </p>

<p>the effectiveness of the actions taken. </p>

<p>The proportion of patients with appropriate self-</p>

<p>care confidence (19.0%) was similar to those found </p>

<p>in studies conducted in developed countries: Italy </p>

<p>(21.2%) (9) and Canada (22.0%) (21) . Self-care confidence </p>

<p>requires cognitive skills that directly impact the process </p>

<p>of therapeutic decision-making and performance of </p>

<p>the patient's self-care (24) . It is believed that the self-</p>

<p>care confidence has moderating effect on self-care at </p>

<p>different outcomes such as, for example, in adherence. </p>

<p>The implementation of multidisciplinary programmes </p>

<p>with home visits and telephone follow-up, so that the </p>

<p>patients recognize and properly handle their symptoms </p>

<p>is a combination whose efficacy for self-care may include </p>

<p>the reinforcement of the patients' confidence in the field </p>

<p>of their health condition (8,11) . </p>

<p>Another important consideration is that the </p>

<p>confidence level in the self-care can be influenced </p>

<p>by social desirability (23-24) , which requires caution in </p>

<p>interpreting the results of this scale. </p>

<p>The Cronbach's alpha values obtained in this </p>

<p>study, for the total score of the SCHFI (0.70), self-care </p>

<p>maintenance (0.47) and confidence subscales (0.74) </p>

<p>were similar to that found in the study of adaptation of </p>

<p>the SCHFI for the Brazilian version (7) (0.77, 0.43 and </p>

<p>0.94, respectively) and lower (0.40) to that found in </p>

<p>the self-care management subscale (0.76). This result </p>

<p>suggests that, in this study sample, the questions that </p>

<p>compose this subscale deserve more attention. </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>The main limitations of this study were the small </p>

<p>sample size, study carried out with patients with mild to </p>

<p>moderate symptoms (NYHA Class I, II and III), from a </p>

<p>single specialized and teaching hospital, low Cronbach's </p>

<p>alpha values of the SCHFI, as well as cross-sectional </p>

<p>design which does not establish temporal relationships </p>

<p>between the variables. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>In this study with a sample of Brazilians, self-care </p>

<p>has been shown as inappropriate, but similar to those </p>

<p>with patients of other countries. Other studies with </p>

<p>Brazilian samples should be conducted in order to test </p>

<p>the self-care model in HF and identify potential variables </p>

<p>involved in self-care response. </p>

<p>The results of this research will be useful for </p>

<p>the development of nursing interventions that </p>

<p>can promote/improve self-care in this population, </p>

<p>especially by means of the use of self-care model in </p>

<p>HF to develop interventions. Educational actions, by </p>

<p>means of nursing consultations, can and should be </p>

<p>used to empower patients to symptoms recognition </p>

<p>and management. </p>

<p>Studies that produce and synthesize evidence on </p>

<p>interventions for self-care management/maintenance </p>

<p>in HF patients are needed to guide therapeutic team </p>

<p>decisions aiming a better quality of life for these </p>

<p>patients. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>To all patients who participated in this research, </p>

<p>to the Nursing Director and the nurses of the HF and </p>

<p>Ventricular Dysfunction Ambulatory of the Dante </p>

<p>Pazzanese Institute of Cardiology for their support </p>

<p>during this research, and the nurses who assisted in the </p>

<p>data collection. </p>



</text></tei>