<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4951474" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: Bariatric surgery is relatively new in Korea, and studies comparing different bariatric procedures in Koreans are lacking. 
This study aimed to compare the clinical outcomes of laparoscopic adjustable gastric banding (LAGB), Roux-en-Y gastric bypass 
(RYGB), and sleeve gastrectomy (SG) for treating morbidly obese Korean adults. 
Materials and Methods: In this multicenter retrospective cohort study, we reviewed the medical records of 261 obese patients 
who underwent different bariatric procedures. Clinical outcomes were measured in terms of weight loss and resolution of co-
morbidities, such as diabetes, hypertension, and dyslipidemia. Safety profiles for the procedures were also evaluated. 
Results: In terms of weight loss, the three procedures showed similar results at 18 months (weight loss in 52.1% for SG, 61.0% for 
LAGB, and 69.2% for RYGB). Remission of diabetes, hypertension, and dyslipidemia was more frequent in patients who under-
went RYGB (65.9%, 63.6%, and 100% of patients, respectively). Safety profiles were similar among groups. Early complications oc-
curred in 26 patients (9.9%) and late complications in 32 (12.3%). In the LAGB group, five bands (6.9%) were removed. Among all 
patients, one death (1/261=0.38%) occurred in the RYGB group due to aspiration pneumonia. 
Conclusion: The three bariatric procedures were comparable in regards to weight-loss outcomes; nevertheless, RYGB showed a 
higher rate of comorbidity resolution. Bariatric surgery is effective and relatively safe; however, due to complications, some bands 
had to be removed in the LAGB group and a relatively high rate of reoperations was observed in the RYGB group. </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J 2016 Jul;57(4):956-962 
http://dx.Obesity is a serious health problem for Western countries and a 
growing health concern for most countries in the Asia-Pacific 
region. In Korea, the prevalence of obesity in adults, defined as 
a body mass index (BMI) ≥25 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, has gradually increased 
from 29.2% in 2001 to 31.4% in 2011. </p>

<p>1   Bariatric surgery is considered the most efficacious treatment 
for severe obesity in the long term. Bariatric surgery results in 
long-term weight-loss control, along with lifestyle improve-
ments and amelioration of risk factors, within a decade after 
surgery. 
2 Furthermore, bariatric surgery is widely known to of-
fer metabolic effects in patients with type II diabetes. One study 
demonstrated that diabetes remission, defined by blood glu-
cose &lt;110 mg/dL without diabetes medications, was 72.3% at 2 
years and 30.4% at 15 years after bariatric surgery. 
3 Worldwide, 
metabolic/bariatric surgeries have more than doubled from 
2003 to 2011: the most frequently performed bariatric in 2011 
was the Roux-en-Y gastric bypass (RYGB), followed by sleeve 
gastrectomy (SG) and laparoscopic adjustable gastric banding 
(LAGB). </p>

<p>4   Many bariatric surgeons prefer RYGB over SG or LAGB, be-
cause the former procedure is associated with better outcomes 
of weight loss and resolution of comorbidities. However, RYGB is 
also associated with higher rates of readmission and reopera-
tion/intervention; 
5 hence, other surgeons prefer SG or LAGB 
over RYGB, because these procedures have a better safety profile. 
Bariatric surgery is relatively new in Korea: the first laparo-
scopic bariatric procedure was performed in 2003. 
6 According-
ly, large comparative studies are still lacking. We conducted this 
study to compare the clinical outcomes of RYGB vs. SG vs. LAGB 
in an effort to outline which procedure should be considered 
optimal for treating obesity and its comorbidities in obese Ko-
rean adults. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Data source and patient identification </p>

<p>This study applied a retrospective cohort design based on med-
ical chart review. We collected data on 261 consecutive obese 
adults (BMI ≥30 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) who underwent LAGB, RYGB, or SG 
between 2008 and 2011 in the surgical departments of seven 
different Korean tertiary medical centers. Patients aged 17 years 
old or less were excluded. Patients were categorized into three 
groups depending on the surgical procedure: LAGB (n=72), 
RYGB (n=73), and SG (n=116). The ethics review boards of the 
National Evidence-based Healthcare Collaborating Agency and 
each participating hospital approved the study protocols. </p>

<p>Data collection </p>

<p>Baseline height, weight, blood pressures, and biochemical data 
were collected during the physical examination and laboratory </p>

<p>assessments performed within a few days of bariatric surgery. 
Subsequent data were collected when the subjects made fol-
low-up visits to the hospitals. Weight measurements at routine 
visits were averaged over three months to determine changes 
in weight at specific time points. For example, if patients mea-
sured their weight twice over three months from baseline, the 
weight at three months was recorded as the average value of the 
two measurements. Information on the patients' medical histo-
ry before bariatric surgery was obtained through chart review. 
To investigate complications related with bariatric surgery, de-
tails of each event, onset date, and hospitalization were recorded. </p>

<p>Operative method </p>

<p>Details on each of the surgical bariatric procedures are provid-
ed hereafter. Briefly, for LAGB, a four-or five-port laparoscopic 
approach was used, depending on the surgeon's preference. 
The pars flaccida technique was applied for creation of the ret-
rogastric tunnel, and either the LAP-BAND 
® (Allergan, Irvine, 
CA, USA) or the Realize Band 
® (Johnson &amp; Johnson, Neenah, 
WI, USA) was used. Several gastrogastric fixation sutures with 
nonabsorbable suture material were applied in all cases. The 
access port was exteriorized through a subcutaneous tunnel, 
and was placed by fixation to the rectus abdominis fascia. In all 
cases, intraoperative band filling was not performed, allowing 
at least four to eight weeks for capsule maturation around the 
band. 
For RYGB, a six-or seven-port laparoscopic technique was 
used, and after creation of a small gastric pouch of less than 30 
cc, a side-to-side gastrojejunostomy was constructed using a 
linear stapler. The measured Roux limb length was about 100 
cm, and side-to-side jejunojejunostomy was performed using 
linear staplers. Potential areas for internal hernias were all su-
ture-closed with nonabsorbable suture materials. 
Finally, for SG, a five-or six-port laparoscopic technique was 
used. Omental dissection extended from about 5 cm proximal 
to the pylorus up to the angle of His; using a bougie with a di-
ameter ranging from 36-40 French or a gastrofiberscope, sever-
al linear staples were applied, and a narrow sleeve was achieved. 
Suture reinforcement was performed or not, depending on the 
surgeon's preference. </p>

<p>Clinical effectiveness </p>

<p>Clinical effectiveness was investigated using four parameters: 
percentage of weight loss (%WL), percentage of excess weight 
loss (%EWL), percentage of excess BMI loss (%EBMIL), and ab-
solute weight loss (AWL) from baseline. Percentage of WL was 
calculated by dividing changes in weight from baseline by base-
line weight; %EWL was calculated by dividing weight changes 
from baseline by excess weight, which was obtained by sub-
tracting ideal body weight from actual baseline weight. Ideal 
body weight was calculated as the height-adjusted weight de-
pending on sex for a medium frame, according to the Metro-
politan Life Insurance Company tables (1983). 
7 Percentage of </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2016.57.4.956 </p>



<p>Comparison of Bariatric Procedures in Korea </p>

<p>EBMIL was calculated by dividing BMI change from baseline 
by excess BMI, which was obtained by subtracting the ideal 
BMI (25 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) from the actual BMI. AWL from baseline was 
calculated by subtracting weight at a specific time point from 
weight at baseline. 
Remission from comorbidities, including diabetes, hyperten-
sion, and dyslipidemia, was investigated over time. In most cas-
es, the management and follow-up of these comorbidities was 
usually performed by internists or primary care physicians, not 
by bariatric surgeons. Using the following definitions of con-
comitant diseases, prevalence before and improvement after 
bariatric surgery were investigated objectively. Diabetes was 
defined as the use of antidiabetic medications, fasting blood 
glucose (FBG) ≥126 mg/dL, or a hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) level 
≥6.5%. Hypertension was defined as the use of antihypertensive 
medications, systolic blood pressure ≥140 mm Hg, or diastolic 
blood pressure ≥90 mm Hg. Dyslipidemia was defined as the 
use of cholesterol-lowering medications, total cholesterol ≥240 
mg/dL, triglycerides ≥200 mg/dL, or low-density lipoprotein 
cholesterol ≥160 mg/dL. Remission was defined as the patient 
being off medication and having laboratory/measurement val-
ues below the diagnostic criteria. </p>

<p>Safety assessment </p>

<p>Safety assessment was performed by collecting clinical infor-
mation at two time points: within 30 days and after 30 days 
from bariatric surgery. Within 30 days, any occurrence of spe-
cific complications was noted, including deep vein thrombosis, 
venous thromboembolism, tracheal reintubation, performance 
of interventional endoscopic procedure for control of luminal 
bleeding, dilatation of strictures, air reduction in a kinked gas-
tric tube, tracheostomy placement, percutaneous drain place-</p>

<p>ment, anastomotic complication (e.g., leak, obstruction), bowel 
obstruction, incisional hernia, band slippage, gastric perfora-
tion, port/tubing system complication, pouch dilatation, or 
pneumonia. After 30 days, any occurrence of gastroesophageal 
reflux disease, nausea/vomiting, internal hernia, gastric pro-
lapse, band erosion, band removal, anastomotic stenosis, gall-
bladder stone, or marginal ulcer was also recorded. If patients 
reported other complications, they were specified in detail. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>We summarized the patient characteristics and used analysis of 
variance (ANOVA) for continuous variables and the chi-square 
test for categorical variables to investigate differences in base-
line characteristics among the three groups. Changes in %WL, 
%EWL, %EBMIL, and AWL were summarized at 0 (baseline), 3, 
6, 9, 12, 15, and 18 months, and 95% confidence intervals were 
also calculated. ANOVA was used for the statistical testing of 
outcomes among the three groups at each time point. To re-
duce data entry error, two people independently input data into 
the data collection forms, which were developed using Micro-
soft Access software (2007). Subsequently, the accuracy of the 
inputted data was checked with <rs type="software">SAS</rs> and corrected. Statistical 
data analysis was conducted with <rs id="software-2" type="software">SAS</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">9.2</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SAS Insti- tute</rs>, Cary, NC, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The characteristics of the 261 patients included in this study are 
presented in Table 1. The median follow-up period ranged from 
6.3 to 11.6 months. BMI was similar among the three groups. 
Female sex was predominant in all three groups. The mean age </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographics </p>

<p>LAGB (n=72) 
RYGB (n=73) 
SG (n=116) 
p value 
n 
% 
n 
% 
n 
% 
Follow up (days) 
Median 
347 
209 
189.5 
0.0005 
BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
Mean±SD 
38.9±5.4 
39.0±6.9 
39.1±6.2 
0.9259 
30≤BMI&lt;35 
19 
26.4 
23 
31.5 
32 
27.6 
0.9206 
35≤BMI&lt;40 
25 
34.7 
26 
35.6 
44 
37.9 
BMI≥40 
28 
38.9 
24 
32.9 
40 
34.5 
Sex 
0.9026 
Male 
17 
23.6 
17 
23.3 
30 
25.9 
Female 
55 
76.4 
56 
76.7 
86 
74.1 
Age (yrs) 
Mean±SD 
33.6±10.3 
39.1±11.1 
35.0±10.4 
0.0046 
Concomitant disease 
Hypertension 
37 
51.4 
47 
64.4 
62 
53.4 
&lt;0.0001 
Dyslipidemia 
29 
40.3 
40 
54.8 
56 
48.3 
0.1802 
Diabetes 
15 
20.8 
44 
60.3 
43 
37.1 
&lt;0.0001 
LAGB, laparoscopic adjustable gastric banding; RYGB, Roux-en-Y gastric bypass; SG, sleeve gastrectomy; BMI, body mass index. </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2016.57.4.956 </p>

<p>Sang Kuon Lee, et al. </p>

<p>was slightly higher in the RYGB group. The prevalences of hy-
pertension and diabetes were higher in the RYGB group. </p>

<p>Weight-loss outcomes </p>

<p>Changes in %WL, %EWL, %EBMIL, and AWL are listed in Table 
2, and presented graphically in Fig. 1. Patients who underwent 
RYGB showed a tendency towards greater weight loss than 
those who underwent SG or LAGB; the difference was statisti-
cally significant only at a few time points. The %WL was signifi-
cant at 9 months (RYGB vs. LAGB), and AWL was significant at 
6, 9, and 15 months (RYGB vs. LAGB). The mean %EWL at the 
last follow-up (18 months) was 52.1% for SG, 61.0% for LAGB, 
and 69.2% for RYGB. </p>

<p>Resolution of comorbidities </p>

<p>The prevalence of dyslipidemia was similar among the three 
groups before surgery. Meanwhile, diabetes and hypertension 
were more prevalent in the RYGB group, followed by SG. Re-
mission from all concomitant diseases (diabetes, hypertension, 
and dyslipidemia) was more frequent in those who underwent 
RYGB (Table 3). While 65.9%, 63.6%, and 100% of patients 
showed remission from diabetes, hypertension, and dyslipid-
emia, respectively, in the RYGB group, remission rates were </p>

<p>lower in the SG group (30.2%, 14.3%, and 73.7%) and the LAGB 
group (40%, 34.8%, and 66.7%). Laboratory measurements, in-
cluding FBG and HbA1c, improved significantly from baseline 
values in the RYGB and SG groups. </p>

<p>Complications </p>

<p>Early complications (within 30 days from surgery) occurred in 
26 patients (9.9%), accounting for 12.5% of the LAGB, 12.3% of 
the RYGB, and 6.9% of the SG, while complications later than 
30 days from surgery occurred in 32 patients (12.3%), repre-
senting 22.2% of the LAGB, 12.3% of the RYGB, and 6% of the 
SG (Table 4). The most frequent complication within 30 days 
from bariatric surgery was surgical site infection, followed by 
pneumonia/atelectasis. One patient who had undergone RYGB 
underwent reoperation because of small bowel obstruction. 
Other complications included leakage, bleeding, kinking of the 
gastric sleeve, stoma obstruction, rhabdomyolysis, band slip-
page, access port complications, diarrhea, and reflux symp-
toms. Complications at more than 30 days after surgery were 
more common in the LAGB group, although this difference was 
not statistically significant. Late band complications were 
mainly due to occurrence of port leak/revision and band ero-
sion/removal. Five bands (6.9%) needed to be removed because </p>

<p>Table 2. Weight Change from Baseline </p>

<p>Time (month) 
LAGB 
RYGB 
SG 
p value 
n 
Mean 
n 
Mean 
n 
Mean </p>

<p>%WL </p>

<p>3 
61 
9.3 
65 
9.1 
79 
10.6 
0.090 
6 
49 
16.8 
52 
19.1 
60 
19.1 
0.090 
9 
39 
20.3 
36 
25.2 
36 
22.2 
0.042 
12 
33 
24.0 
27 
26.1 
24 
24.0 
0.572 
15 
20 
21.9 
24 
28.0 
25 
25.4 
0.099 
18 
17 
20.8 
15 
26.6 
12 
22.3 
0.256 </p>

<p>AWL </p>

<p>3 
61 
9.9 
65 
9.8 
79 
11.5 
0.115 
6 
48 
17.5 
52 
20.9 
60 
21.3 
0.041 
9 
40 
21.1 
36 
28.6 
36 
24.2 
0.009 
12 
33 
25.2 
27 
29.0 
24 
26.0 
0.413 
15 
20 
22.9 
24 
33.7 
25 
27.3 
0.049 
18 
17 
20.8 
15 
29.3 
12 
26.8 
0.215 </p>

<p>%EWL </p>

<p>3 
61 
24.1 
65 
23.2 
79 
27.2 
0.208 
6 
48 
41.8 
52 
48.1 
60 
45.9 
0.209 
9 
40 
55.0 
36 
62.0 
36 
57.8 
0.493 
12 
33 
63.9 
27 
64.3 
24 
59.6 
0.742 
15 
20 
61.3 
24 
67.0 
25 
63.9 
0.778 
18 
17 
61.0 
15 
69.3 
12 
52.1 
0.325 </p>

<p>%EBMIL </p>

<p>3 
61 
29.9 
65 
28.3 
79 
33.2 
0.302 
6 
48 
51.1 
52 
58.6 
60 
54.9 
0.321 
9 
40 
68.2 
36 
75.6 
36 
71.6 
0.664 
12 
33 
79.1 
27 
78.6 
24 
70.9 
0.608 
15 
20 
78.6 
24 
81.4 
25 
77.7 
0.942 
18 
17 
77.2 
15 
87.0 
12 
61.4 
0.300 
LAGB, laparoscopic adjustable gastric banding; RYGB, Roux-en-Y gastric bypass; SG, sleeve gastrectomy; %WL, percentage of weight loss; %EWL, percentage 
of excess weight loss; %EBMIL, percentage of excess body mass index loss; AWL, absolute weight loss. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2016.57.4.956 </p>



<p>Comparison of Bariatric Procedures in Korea </p>

<p>of band erosion, access port infection, or band leakage. Other 
late complications included cholecystitis, internal hernia, intes-
tinal perforation, wound dehiscence, and access port problems. 
Details on complications by type of surgery are described in Ta-
ble 5. Some patients had more than one complication. There was 
one death (1/261=0.38%) due to aspiration pneumonia within 
30 days from surgery in a patient who underwent RYGB. The 
other groups recorded no mortality. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This is the first Korean national study in which several academ-
ic institutions participated and pooled their data on bariatric 
surgery to compare clinical outcomes among different bariatric 
procedures (LAGB, RYGB, and SG). In our previous study, we 
showed that bariatric surgery was more effective than conven-
tional medical treatment for obese patients in terms of weight-
loss and improvement/resolution of comorbidities. 
8 In this 
multicenter study, our intention was to analyze the compara-
tive bariatric outcomes among different weight loss procedures. 
Bariatric surgery was first performed in Korea in January </p>

<p>2003, when the first laparoscopic SG was performed, 
9 followed 
later in the same year by laparoscopic RYGB, mini-gastric by-
pass, and vertical banded gastroplasty. In 2004, the first LAGB 
procedure was performed. By 2009, LAGB was the most popu-
lar bariatric procedure in Korea (68%), followed by RYGB (16%), 
SG (5.5%), and mini-gastric bypass (3%). 
6 This is an interesting 
phenomenon, since LAGB is decreasing in popularity world-
wide in favor of other procedures. 
4 One possible reason is the 
less invasive nature of the LAGB procedure and the reluctance 
of Korean patients to undergo "major" surgery. 
Many papers have compared surgical outcomes between dif-
ferent bariatric procedures; however, the conclusions were not 
categorical and sometimes conflicted. Chapman, et al. 
10 com-
pared LAGB with vertical banded gastroplasty and RYGB, con-
cluding that LAGB was superior to the other procedures in 
terms of safety and weight-loss outcome, at least after 4 years of 
follow-up. However, a cohort study that compared RYGB with 
LAGB in matched patients and followed them for 3 years showed 
superior weight loss and comorbidity reduction in the RYGB 
group. 
11 In a multicenter study that compared RYGB with SG, 
RYGB was associated with greater morbidity; however, weight 
loss was comparable at 6, 12, and 18 months, and remission of </p>

<p>Fig. 1. (A) Comparison of percentage of weight loss (%WL) over an 18-month follow-up. (B) Comparison of percentage of excess weight loss (%EWL) 
over an 18-month follow-up. %WL, percentage of weight loss; %EWL, percentage of excess weight loss; LAGB, laparoscopic adjustable gastric banding; 
RYGB, Roux-en-Y gastric bypass; SG, sleeve gastrectomy. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>%WL </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 
0 
3 
6 
9 
12 
15 
18 
0 
3 
6 
9 
12 
15 
18 </p>

<p>Month 
Month </p>

<p>p=0.09 </p>

<p>LAGB </p>

<p>RYGB </p>

<p>SG </p>

<p>p=0.09 </p>

<p>p=0.04 </p>

<p>p=0.57 
p=0.10 
p=0.26 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>%EWL </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>p=0.20 </p>

<p>LAGB </p>

<p>RYGB </p>

<p>SG </p>

<p>p=0.20 </p>

<p>p=0.49 </p>

<p>p=0.74 p=0.77 </p>

<p>p=0.32 </p>

<p>Table 3. Remission from Concomitant Diseases </p>

<p>LAGB (n=72) 
RYGB (n=73) 
SG (n=116) 
p value 
n 
% 
n 
% 
n 
% 
Diabetes 
Prevalence 
15/72 
20.8 
44/73 
60.3 
43/116 
37.1 
&lt;0.0001 
Remission 
6/15 
40 
29/44 
65.9 
13/43 
30.2 
0.035 
Hypertension 
Prevalence 
38/72 
52.8 
49/73 
67.1 
62/116 
53.4 
0.124 
Remission 
8/23 
34.8 
28/44 
63.6 
4/28 
14.3 
0.005 
Dyslipidemia 
Prevalence 
26/72 
36.1 
29/73 
39.7 
44/116 
37.9 
0.904 
Remission 
10/15 
66.7 
28/28 
100 
14/19 
73.7 
0.006 
LAGB, laparoscopic adjustable gastric banding; RYGB, Roux-en-Y gastric bypass; SG, sleeve gastrectomy. </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2016.57.4.956 </p>

<p>Sang Kuon Lee, et al. </p>

<p>type 2 diabetes was more frequent. 
12 Given the increasing pop-
ularity of SG over LAGB as a restrictive procedure, one interest-
ing study by Chakravarty, et al. 
13 compared LAGB with RYGB, 
vertical banded gastroplasty, and SG. In this systematic review 
of randomized controlled trials, the authors concluded that 
LAGB was not the most effective bariatric procedure to reduce 
weight, compared with the other procedures; nevertheless, it 
was associated with fewer early complications, as well as a 
shorter operative time and shorter length of hospital stay. 
In the current study, although patients who underwent RYGB 
showed a tendency to have greater %WL, compared with those 
who underwent SG and LAGB, at 6 months postoperation; 
thereafter, the difference became statistically significant only at 
9 months. The percentage of EWL was similar for the three pro-
cedures. In terms of AWL, RYGB demonstrated better outcomes 
only at 6, 9, and 15 postoperative months. As this study was not 
prospective, this marginal difference in weight loss may have 
been due to the heterogeneous population group and inter-in-
stitutional differences in patient management protocols. More-
over, the follow-up period of only 18 months was quite short. 
We may speculate that the weight-loss outcome might have 
been more pronounced in favor of RYGB and SG over a longer 
follow-up period. Indeed, a systematic review of randomized 
trials comparing SG, RYGB, and LAGB has shown a trend to-
ward a better weight-loss outcome with RYGB (62.1-94.4%), 
compared to SG (49-81%) and LAGB (28.7-48%), over a follow-
up period of up to 3 years. </p>

<p>14   We demonstrated an effective resolution of comorbidities af-
ter bariatric procedures. RYGB, in particular, showed signifi-
cantly better outcomes than LAGB and SG in regards resolution 
of diabetes and dyslipidemia. These results are consistent with 
those from other studies that analyzed the resolution of comor-
bidities after different operations. 
15 However, since the preva-
lence of comorbidities was different among groups, it would be 
difficult to make a direct comparison and determine which 
procedure was superior in this respect. 
Whereas complications from LAGB occurring more than 30 
days from surgery were almost double those occurring within 
30 days, the complication rates in the RYGB and SG groups 
were similar for both time periods. This finding is in accordance 
with the findings from another study, in which LAGB was asso-
ciated with more long-term complications, including band ero-
sion, pouch dilatation, intractable reflux symptoms, and band 
removals. 
16 However, we must take into consideration that the </p>

<p>LAGB group had a longer mean follow-up time, which may 
have influenced the increased complication rate. 
In our study, one death was observed in the RYGB group. A 
multi-institutional study carried out by the American College of 
Surgeons, which compared LAGB, SG, and RYGB based on 
prospective longitudinal data, showed 30-day mortality rates of </p>

<p>Table 4. Postoperative Complication Rate </p>

<p>LAGB (n=72) 
RYGB (n=73) 
SG (n=116) 
No. of patients No. of patients No. of patients 
Total 
21 (29.2%) 
16 (21.9%) 
14 (12.1%) 
Within 30 PODs 
9 (12.5%) 
9 (12.3%)* 
8 (6.9%) 
After POD 30 
16 (22.2%) 
9 (12.3%) 
7 (6.0%) 
LAGB, laparoscopic adjustable gastric banding; RYGB, Roux-en-Y gastric by-
pass; SG, sleeve gastrectomy; POD, postoperative day. 
*Including one death. </p>

<p>Table 5. Details of Surgical Complications by Type of Surgery </p>

<p>LAGB 
RYGB 
SG 
No. 
of events </p>

<p>No. 
of events </p>

<p>No. 
of events 
Within 30 PODs 
Fever/leakage 
1 
Pneumonia 
1 
Port/tubing complication 
1 
Rhabdomyolysis 
1 
Slippage 
1 
Stoma obstruction 
1 
Wound complication 
3 
2 
4 
Atelectasis 
2 
Bleeding 
1 
Bowel obstruction* 
2 
Diarrhea 
1 
Aspiration pneumonia </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>1 
GERD 
1 
Kinking 
2 
Leakage 
1 
After POD 30 
Pneumonia 
1 
Port flip 
2 
Port flip/port revision 
1 
Port infection/band removal </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>1 
Port infection/port revision 
2 
Port leak/port revision 
1 
Band erosion/band removal </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>3 
Band leakage/band removal </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>1 
Slippage 
4 
GERD 
1 
3 
Nausea/vomiting 
1 
1 
Dizziness 
1 
Hypoglycemia 
1 
Iron deficiency anemia 
1 
1 
Gallbladder stone 
1 
1 
Depression 
1 
Hair loss 
1 
Internal hernia </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>1 
Intestinal perforation </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>1 
Mallory-Weiss syndrome 
1 
Incisional hernia* 
2 
LAGB, laparoscopic adjustable gastric banding; RYGB, Roux-en-Y gastric by-
pass; SG, sleeve gastrectomy; POD, postoperative day; GERD, gastroesopha-
geal reflux disease. 
*One patient was reoperated, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Died, </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Band removed, </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>Reoperated. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2016.57.4.956 </p>



<p>Comparison of Bariatric Procedures in Korea </p>

<p>0.05%, 0.11%, and 0.14%, respectively, suggesting that the surgi-
cal risk of bariatric procedures is highest for RYGB, followed by 
SG and LAGB. </p>

<p>5   This study had several limitations that should be taken into 
consideration. First, the patient population was not homoge-
nous, as those who underwent RYGB had more comorbidities. 
Second, the surgeons participating in this study had varying 
levels of bariatric surgical experience. Third, this was not a pro-
spective study, but a retrospective cohort study with a limited 
follow-up period. Particularly, the total numbers of patients fol-
lowed up was 84 (32.1%) at postoperative 12 months and 44 
(16.8%) at postoperative 18 months; therefore, the statistical 
power of the study results is limited. Finally, there were notice-
able inter-institutional differences in the management of bar-
iatric patients. Nonetheless, the significance of this paper is that 
it is the first multi-institutional national study in which most 
major centers in Korea participated. 
To conclude, this study demonstrates that all three bariatric 
procedures were comparably effective in terms of weight loss, 
with quite effective resolution of comorbidities. Complications 
were more severe in the RYGB group; however, LAGB was asso-
ciated with a higher rate of late complications. Our results sug-
gest that all three procedures are viable alternatives for patients 
whose obesity problem is not amenable to medical treatment. 
A prospective randomized study would be desirable to deter-
mine the relative superiorities of each of the bariatric proce-
dures. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study was completed as part of the health technology as-
sessment report (Project no. NA2011-003) funded by the Na-
tional Evidence-based Healthcare Collaborating Agency (NECA) 
in South Korea. </p>



</text></tei>