<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4724760" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Despite the benefits associated with receiving a kidney, 
10-year kidney transplant function continues to be low 
(50%), with a 60% increased risk of kidney failure attributed 
to patients not taking their immunosuppressive medications 
as prescribed. 1,2 The rate of non-adherence to immunosup-
pressive medications is reported to range from 30% to 35% 
for kidney transplant recipients. 3,4 For example, in the United 
States, more than 181,000 kidney transplant patients are liv-
ing with a functioning kidney. If the rates of non-adherence 
are true, then roughly 55,000 to 65,000 patients are either 
non-adherent or at risk of becoming so. 1,5 This likely under-
estimates the true prevalence of non-adherence due to varia-
tions in the definition and measures of non-adherence as well </p>

<p>as the fact that end-stage renal disease (ESRD) is a global 
issue with the number of centers providing kidney trans-
plants on the rise. 3,6 </p>

<p>Improving medication adherence among 
kidney transplant recipients: Findings from 
other industries, patient engagement, and 
behavioral economics-A scoping review </p>

<p>Shelley R Oberlin 1 , Stephen T Parente 1,2 and Timothy L Pruett 3 </p>

<p>Abstract 
The immune system is a powerful barrier to successful organ transplantation, but one that has been routinely thwarted 
through modern pharmacotherapeutics. Despite the benefits of immunosuppressive therapy, medication non-adherence 
leads to an increased risk of graft rejection, higher hospital utilization and costs, and poor outcomes. We conduct a scoping 
review following Arksey and O'Malley's five-stage framework methodology to identify established or novel interventions that 
could be applied to kidney transplant recipients to improve medication adherence. As the desired outcome is a behavior 
(taking a pill), we assess three areas: behavioral-focused interventions in other industries, patient engagement theories, 
and behavioral economic principles. Search strategies included mining business, social sciences, and medical literature with 
additional guidance from six consultative interviews. Our review suggests that no intervention stands out as superior or likely 
to be more effective than any other intervention; yet promising strategies and interventions were identified across all three 
areas examined. Based on our findings, we believe there are five strategies that transplant centers and other organizations 
can implement to improve medication adherence: (1) Build a foundation of trust; (2) Employ multiple interventions; (3) 
Stratify the population; (4) Develop collaborative partnerships; and (5) Embed medication adherence into the organization's 
culture. The effectiveness of these interventions will need to be investigated further, but we believe they are a step in the 
right direction for organizations to consider in their efforts to improve medication adherence. </p>

<p>Keywords 
Kidney transplant, medication adherence, immunosuppressive therapy, patient engagement, behavioral economics, patient 
behavior </p>

<p>Date received: 3 August 2015; accepted: 29 November 2015 </p>

<p>1 Health Systems Innovation Network, LLC, Wayzata, MN, USA 
2 Carlson School of Management, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, 
MN, USA 
3 Division of Transplantation, Department of Surgery, University of 
Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, USA </p>

<p>Corresponding author: 
Shelley R Oberlin, Health Systems Innovation Network, LLC, 2601 Arcola 
Lane, Wayzata, MN 55391, USA. 
Email: shelley.oberlin@hsinetwork.com </p>

<p>625026S MO0010.1177/2050312115625026SAGE Open MedicineOberlin et al. </p>

<p>research-article2016 </p>

<p>Review Article </p>



<p>SAGE Open Medicine </p>

<p>Previous studies have shown that medication non-adher-
ence leads to suboptimal outcomes and has been observed in 
almost half of graft losses. 7-9 This outcome impacts patients 
and other stakeholders. For patients, failure to take immuno-
suppressive drugs is associated with decreased graft func-
tion, increased risk of kidney loss, and premature death. 10,11 
About 25% of kidney transplant recipients who experience 
graft failure will die within 2 years, and overall life expec-
tancy is 4 years less for recipients who are non-adherent to 
immunosuppressive therapy (IST). 10 For health care systems 
and payers, medication non-adherence leads to increased use 
of resources, higher hospital readmission rates, and potential 
need for re-transplantation and/or return to dialysis. 3,7,12,13 
Graft failures resulting from medication non-adherence dur-
ing the first year post-transplant are estimated to cost the 
United States US$100 million annually. 13 Additionally, 
return to dialysis carries an increased cost burden approxi-
mately twice that of caring for a transplant recipient. 1 As a 
global comparison, in Nigeria, a session of hemodialysis 
costs US$100 which is twice the minimum monthly wage for 
federal government workers. 6 
In their 2015 systematic review, Low et al. 2 define adher-
ence as the extent to which people follow their instructions to a 
prescribed treatment regimen. They further explain non-adher-
ence can be either intentional or unintentional and occur for a 
number of reasons. In 2008, participants at a Non-adherence 
Consensus Conference agreed that the following five catego-
ries (which are aligned with the categories outlined in 2003 by 
the World Health Organization (WHO)) are associated with 
non-adherence: (1) socioeconomic, (2) patient-related, (3) dis-
ease-related, (4) treatment-related, and (5) health care setting/ 
provider-related. 2,3 Within these five categories, they identified 
26 subcategories. 3 Constantiner and Cukor 10 simplified the 
number of factors to those repeatedly emerging as predictive of 
non-adherence such as minority status, gender, age, marital sta-
tus, post-transplant symptoms, and time since transplantation. 
Chisholm-Burns et al. 12 included costs, forgetfulness, confu-
sion over complicated regimens, psychosocial factors, and 
adverse drug effects. As predictive risk factors for non-adher-
ence vary by individual and over time, health care organiza-
tions are challenged with developing successful and sustainable 
interventions that are tailored to the individual yet apply to a 
larger subset of the population to help manage resources. 
Published studies of interventions to improve IST adher-
ence are rare. 14,15 De Bleser et al. 16 found only four rand-
omized controlled trials (RCTs), of which three showed a 
statistically significant improvement from the intervention. 
The interventions (varying by study) included educational 
sessions, counseling, monthly review of medications, and 
behavioral and support interventions. Chisholm-Burns et al. 15 
reported inconsistent findings from interventions focused on 
improving adherence for adult renal transplant recipients 
(RTRs). Most recently Low et al. identified 12 interventions, 
6 of which showed statistical significance. One study focused 
on reducing the dosing regimen to once daily, and the other </p>

<p>five studies were multidimensional addressing informational, 
behavioral, and emotional elements. While the multidimen-
sional interventions were more effective in improving medi-
cation adherence, some of the studies were limited by small 
samples sizes, study design, and duration of the intervention(s) 
(i.e. most were short-term ranging from 3 to 12 months). 2 We 
aim to identify strategies, techniques, and interventions that 
could be utilized by providers to help kidney transplant recip-
ients improve and/or maintain adherence to their prescribed 
medications long term. </p>

<p>Conceptual framework </p>

<p>Identifying ways to improve medication adherence and com-
pliance has been a topic of investigation for decades. To date 
there are more than 18,000 articles in PubMed focusing on 
"medication adherence" and more than 25,000 on "medica-
tion compliance." With the passage of the Affordable Care 
Act in 2010 and the need to demonstrate better outcomes at 
a lower cost, medication adherence and compliance has 
become a growing concern among providers, payers, and 
other stakeholders. 
Medications are effective and studies have shown that 
patients who adhere to their treatment protocols have better 
health outcomes and lower resource consumption compared 
to patients that are non-adherent. 2 The challenge is identify-
ing ways to ensure initial adherence and maintaining this 
behavior over the course of treatment. Previous studies have 
shown that the kidney transplant population is not homoge-
neous with respect to a predisposition for medication adher-
ence, and individual behaviors can be modified through 
self-management techniques and interventions targeted at 
the health care system. 2,17 While some existing interventions 
show promise, they range in terms of their effectiveness and 
durability of improving adherence long term. As such, min-
ing the business and social sciences literature as well as the 
medical literature for applicable interventions and/or metrics 
or tools that can be directly employed or modified for adher-
ence improvements is warranted. 
We conduct a scoping review following the methodologi-
cal framework as described by Arksey and O'Malley 18 (see 
methodology for additional details). Unlike a systematic 
review, the scoping review allows us to rapidly assess a 
breadth of available literature and summarize a range of 
findings regardless of field of study or study design. We 
assess industries outside health care for relevant models and, 
as the desired outcome is a changed behavior, we also assess 
patient engagement and behavioral economic literature to 
determine if there are adherence engaging interventions 
applicable to the kidney transplant population. </p>

<p>Methodology </p>

<p>We conducted a scoping review to find established or novel 
interventions to improve medication adherence among kidney </p>

<p>Oberlin et al. </p>



<p>transplant recipients. We followed Arksey and O'Malley's 
five-stage framework with a few modifications including the 
addition of the optional consultation exercise. Figure 1 shows 
the five stages of the scoping review framework. </p>

<p>Framework stage 1: identify the research 
question(s) </p>

<p>The following three questions are addressed in this scoping 
review: (1) Can established approaches from outside health 
care be used to improve medication adherence; (2) Can we 
use insights from patient engagement theories to improve 
medication adherence; and (3) Can we apply behavioral eco-
nomic principles and techniques to the kidney transplant 
population to improve medication adherence? See section 
"Conceptual framework" for rationale. </p>

<p>Framework stage 2: identify relevant studies </p>

<p>To identify articles relevant to our research areas, we used a 
combination of sources including electronic databases, refer-
ence lists from applicable articles, a brainstorming session, 
and consultative interviews. The latter is considered an 
optional stage that we labeled as stage 2a. 
For the electronic database search our primary source was 
the University of Minnesota Library's MNCAT Discovery. 19 
MNCAT is a search tool that combines the traditional library 
catalog of databases with a large interdisciplinary search for 
journal, magazine, and newspaper articles. It provides more 
of a cross section of results and includes more than 500 active 
sources such as PubMed, Medline, EBSCO, and Business 
Source Premiere. The initial search focused on peer-reviewed 
journal articles with variations on the following search terms: 
behavioral economics, patient engagement, medication 
adherence and outcomes for patients with chronic illnesses, 
interventions to improve medication non-adherence, RTRs, 
and durability, and longitudinal adherence studies. For other 
industries, we choose key words that would likely influence a </p>

<p>behavior including behavioral change strategies, forming 
habits, customer engagement, and customer loyalty. We rec-
ognized some of these industries may have limited peer-
reviewed publications, so we also conducted general Google 
searches using the search terms listed above. 
When search terms reached saturation (e.g. similar refer-
ences or primary research already discussed in a systematic 
review), we presumed that the review was nearly exhaustive 
and moved to the next search term. As this was a scoping 
review, we did not document all study queries nor review all 
abstracts or articles from each search term. Instead we moved 
forward with reviewing the articles, scanning the reference 
lists for applicable articles, and determining if the article was 
applicable for study selection. To minimize overlooking use-
ful methods or tools, we did not set strict parameters around 
years searched but we did find that articles pre-2005 were 
often cited in more recent articles and were therefore consid-
ered redundant for the purposes of this review. 
As Arksey and O'Malley point out, the use of existing 
knowledge and networks can provide additional informa-
tion to include or help frame the scoping review. At the start 
of our review, we conducted a brainstorming session to 
identify industries likely to have engagement (e.g. cus-
tomer-service dynamic) and behavioral (e.g. loyalty) aspects 
over time. Our network consisted of the three researchers on 
our team, including a transplant surgeon, a health care econ-
omist, and a consultant with experience in the health care 
provider sector, along with two others, including a trans-
plant nurse and a pediatric nephrologist, who attended the 
2008 Non-adherence Consensus Conference. At this ses-
sion, we identified the following industries/fields to include 
as "other industries": retail, finance, the military, social 
media, organizations using 360-degree reviews, and support 
group organizations such as Alcoholics Anonymous (AA) 
and Weight Watchers (WW). We also discussed the out-
comes of the Non-Adherence Consensus Conference to 
identify gaps and prevent us from replicating research 
efforts already underway. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Arksey and O'Malley's framework stages for conducting a scoping review. </p>



<p>SAGE Open Medicine </p>

<p>Framework stage 2a: consultation exercise </p>

<p>To refine our literature review and gain further insight on 
existing approaches and interventions in practice, we con-
ducted six interviews. Interviews were consultative in nature. 
Below is a brief overview of the interviewees' industry and 
rationale for why they were chosen. Interviewees are refer-
enced in the results section where applicable. </p>

<p>1. Executive health coach who works with executive 
teams across many industries-The purpose of this 
interview was to identify other applicable industries 
that were not identified in our brainstorming session. 
2. Vice president of a large financial institution-This 
interview focused on understanding strategies to 
engage customers and/or promote behavior change. 
3. Principal at a large consulting firm who advises hos-
pital and health system executives on strategic and 
operational issues-The goal of this interview was to 
determine what patient engagement (or other inter-
ventions) are being tested that may be too "novel" for 
publication. 
4. Manager of a top performing transplant center in 
northern California-The purpose of this interview 
was to identify strategies being used at a large, repu-
table transplant center. 
5. Registered nurse at a large health system in 
Minnesota-The purpose of this interview was to 
gain additional information on the Patient Activation 
Measure (PAM) currently used in a primary care 
setting. 
6. Researcher and co-developer of the PAM-The 
focus of this interview was to learn more about PAM 
and its potential utility in the ESRD and kidney trans-
plant population. PAM is materialized in our litera-
ture search for patient engagement and in reference 
lists. While PAM is excluded from our results section 
as it is not an intervention, it is one way to help better 
target interventions to a population of patients and is 
therefore included in the discussion section. </p>

<p>Framework stage 3: study selection </p>

<p>To ensure that the studies selected addressed our research 
questions, we developed criteria for inclusion. Given that the 
framework stages 2-4 are iterative, our criteria were revised 
throughout the process as we became more familiar with the 
literature. The inclusion criteria included: </p>

<p>1. An intervention: For all three research areas (other 
industries, patient engagement, and behavioral eco-
nomics), the study had to include a strategy, method, 
or intervention to (a) improve medication adherence 
or adherence to a treatment regimen, (b) change a 
behavior, (c) form a habit, or (d) influence a desired 
outcome (e.g. customer loyalty); </p>

<p>2. Systematic review of interventions: As we were not 
conducting a systematic review, we prioritized our 
research efforts on systematic review with a number 
of interventions rather than reanalyzing all primary 
research studies. This allowed us to identify and 
assess multiple interventions quickly. 
3. Interventions from primary research: We did include 
primary research studies that were unique and not 
included in systematic reviews. In some cases, we 
included primary studies from reviews if the review 
was lacking details that contributed to stage 4 of our 
framework (chart the data). 
4. Interventions specific to kidney transplant recipients: 
As we reviewed patient engagement and behavioral 
economic interventions we further researched 
whether these interventions were already being used 
in the transplant community. This was necessary as 
our focus was on new or different approaches that we 
refer to as "novel" for our purposes. For example, 
motivational interviewing (MI) and behavioral con-
tracting were identified as behavioral change strate-
gies used to improve adherence for patient with 
chronic conditions. After adding renal transplant to 
our search term, we found both of these are known 
techniques at some transplant centers, but the degree 
to which they are used and effective remained to be 
determined. As such, some of these studies were 
included for additional analysis. </p>

<p>Framework stage 4: chart the data </p>

<p>In systematic reviews and meta-analyses, this stage would 
involve more rigorous quantitative methods and statistical 
analysis. For this review, stage 4 was used to synthesize our 
findings quantitatively (if data was available) and qualita-
tively through common themes. For example, findings from 
other industries were more qualitative in nature with results 
presented as themes. However, patient engagement and 
behavioral economic interventions had more quantitative 
elements allowing us to group interventions by other criteria 
such as type of intervention, industry/disease state, study 
timeframe (duration), frequency of engagement (by whom), 
outcomes, and applicability to the kidney transplant popula-
tion. As we populated the tables for analysis, we recognized 
that many of the patient engagement interventions were not 
novel and became redundant with other systematic reviews. 
Rather than replicating these studies, we stratified papers for 
frequency of interactions and durability of behavior change 
over time; both of which were our criteria for addressing 
applicability to the kidney transplant population (e.g. Is it 
feasible for transplant centers to implement this intervention 
from a resource and cost perspective and will the interven-
tion be sustainable to improve 5-and 10-year graft func-
tion?). Behavioral economics literature did not appear in any 
combined transplant literature reviewed, so we included 
more details for this area in the narrative and through the use </p>

<p>Oberlin et al. </p>



<p>of a summary table, outlining the type of intervention, exam-
ples of how it has been used, and the advantages and disad-
vantages of the intervention as it relates to improving or 
changing a desired behavior. </p>

<p>Framework stage 5: collate, summarize, and 
report results </p>

<p>The benefit of conducting a scoping review is the opportu-
nity to discuss a broad range of material. The difficulty is 
determining the best way to report the results in a meaning-
ful and concise way. Given the heterogeneity in the three 
areas assessed (other industries, patient engagement, and 
behavioral economics), we did not aggregate all findings, but 
chose to present results by each area. We summarize our 
findings through common themes, figures, and tables with 
emphasis on commonalities or differences that are most 
informative of the interventions reviewed. We present a 
qualitative summary of our findings below. </p>

<p>Limitations to the study </p>

<p>Similar to systematic reviews, scoping reviews are also at 
risk for limitations such as selection bias. While we made 
every attempt to minimize selection bias, we recognize the 
benefits of an iterative process (stages 2-4) allowed us to 
modify and refine our methodology as we progressed, but 
may have also resulted in subjectivity around key decision 
items. In setting parameters around key words searched 
and other industries, stages 2 and 2a, we may have excluded 
industries that could have proved beneficial to include. We 
believe our review of references and the inclusion of addi-
tional key words after our initial search helped prevent this 
from being an issue. At the onset of the study, we also set 
a timeframe and budget of 6 months to complete all five 
stages. As such, we had a cut-off time period for our litera-
ture search (stage 3), which may have resulted in relevant 
papers being missed. To correct for this, we included addi-
tional references from 2015 while editing the manuscript. 
In stage 4, to determine if a strategy or intervention was 
applicable to the kidney transplant population, we relied 
on existing literature and stratified studies based on 
resource need/consumption (frequency and type of engage-
ment) and duration of the intervention over time. By apply-
ing this consistently across interventions reviewed, we 
believe we removed potential bias of arbitrarily selecting 
specific interventions. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>After completing stages 2 through 4 of our scoping review 
methodology, 129 full-text articles were reviewed. Forty-six 
articles (other industries n = 10, patient engagement n = 20, 
and behavioral economics n = 16) met our inclusion criteria 
for further review and analysis. </p>

<p>Overall our review suggests that no new intervention 
stands out as superior or likely to be more effective than 
other interventions at improving medication adherence. Yet 
promising strategies and interventions were identified that 
can enhance existing methods or be incorporated as new 
methods to improve adherence among kidney transplant 
recipients. We summarize these strategies and interventions 
according to our three question areas: (1) findings from other 
industries; (2) insights from patient engagement theories and 
practices; and (3) behavioral economic principles and 
interventions. </p>

<p>Findings from other industries </p>

<p>In our review of the literature for other industries, we found 
that RCTs are rarely performed. As we grouped articles by 
commonalities, however, three behavioral themes emerged: 
(1) relationships built on trust contribute to loyalty and con-
tinued engagement; (2) peer pressure is a powerful behavior 
modifier; and (3) individual rewards, attention, and recogni-
tion help maintain motivation. These themes were viewed as 
potentially applicable to transplant centers to improve medi-
cation adherence through enhancing engagement (e.g. devel-
oping brand loyalty) and by directly improving adherence 
(e.g. showing conformity of behavior to a desired pattern). 
Each of these themes and their applicability to transplant 
centers are discussed further below. </p>

<p>1. Relationships built on trust contribute to loyalty and 
continued engagement. In a report by Gallup, suc-
cessful companies win customers for life by emo-
tionally connecting to their customers and continuing 
to measure customer engagement. 20 Turbo Tax ® rec-
ognizes the emotional needs and psychological barri-
ers of tax payers that must be addressed to effectively 
engage them in the tax preparation process. Their 
online filing process uses statements like "we double 
check your tax returns" and provides positive rein-
forcement by showing refund amounts throughout 
the process to empathize with and nurture their cus-
tomers. They also personalize the process and make 
it easy for customers to navigate by offering live chat 
or phone support and including features such as the 
ability to save and come back when needed. 21 An 
online survey by Fulcrum found that retail compa-
nies such as Baskin Robins, Ruby's and Starbucks, 
who recognized their customers' birthdays, not only 
strengthened the customer relationship but increased 
customer loyalty by 87%. 22 In grocery retailing, 
Guenzi et al. 23 found that customer trust in the sales 
associate and brand products increased perceived 
value and store loyalty. They recommend retailer's 
focus on building trust as an alternative to price cuts 
and promotions to foster store patronage. Even the 
military, which is based on command and control, </p>



<p>SAGE Open Medicine </p>

<p>emphasizes that a continuous flow of information 
between a senior officer and subordinates makes the 
system work. 24 </p>

<p>In health care, there is a growing amount of evidence that 
patients who are engaged, active participants in their own 
care, have better health outcomes and measureable cost sav-
ings. 25 The challenge is that patient engagement changes 
over time indicating a need for transplant centers to continue 
to cultivate and preserve relationships over the long term 
(Hibbard J, 1 October 2014, consultative interview). </p>

<p>2. Peer pressure is a powerful behavior modifier. 
Attendance at programs such as AA and WW is asso-
ciated with abstinence from drinking and weight 
loss. 26,27 Much of the success has been attributed to 
sharing stories which fosters human contact, self-
examination, and self-expression. 26 Social support 
has been used to address forgetfulness as a reason for 
non-adherence, yet the small nature of the associa-
tion suggests that social support alone may not be as 
effective as combining social support with other 
interventions. 28 
3. Individual rewards, attention, and recognition help 
maintain motivation. Rewards and recognition-mon-
etary or non-monetary-help to motivate and maintain 
positive behaviors (Wolf E, 24 August 2014, consulta-
tive interview). American AgCredit, which provides 
loans to agricultural customers, lowers interest rates to 
reward customers who pay on time and maintain a 
strong balance sheet (Oberlin M, 21 September 2014, 
consultative interview). To motivate consultants to turn 
in their case work, Anderson Consulting rewards teams 
with the best record and recognizes them publicly as 
the best among their peers (Wolf E, 24 August 2014, 
consultative interview). Both AA and WW provide 
chips or tokens at specific milestones to recognize and 
reward a behavior. Many have described these as moti-
vational, which help maintain the desired behavior. 26 
360-degree reviews, when implemented correctly, pro-
vide a framework to recognize an employee's contribu-
tions and identify an action plan to foster continuous 
improvements and career development. 29 </p>

<p>Similar to the barriers to medication adherence, motiva-
tional strategies to influence a behavioral change varies by 
individual.2,30 For example, WW offers in-person meetings 
and an online program. Determining which option will work 
best depends on an individual's will power and determina-
tion. The online program takes more discipline while the in-
person meetings allow people to witness others with similar 
experiences, a technique that often provides the drive needed 
to keep people dedicated.31 This suggests that multiple inter-
ventions are likely to be needed to elicit an effective behavio-
ral response for an individual or subset of the population. </p>

<p>Insights from patient engagement </p>

<p>The connection between better health outcomes at a lower 
cost and the passage of the Affordable Care Act in 2010, 
"Patient engagement" has been gaining attention from pro-
viders, researchers, policymakers, employers, and insurers. 25 
The challenge with identifying patient engagement strategies 
in practice is a lack of consensus around the term's defini-
tion. Some view patient engagement as a risk factor, yet oth-
ers describe it as a strategy. 32 We also found interventions to 
improve engagement varied in what constituted engagement 
(e.g. engagement, self-efficacy, communication) and whether 
or not the intervention was effective. 
Through our review of patient engagement interventions 
with a follow-up review of the transplant literature, many 
patient engagement interventions are known in the transplant 
community and are therefore not deemed novel. For example, 
education sessions, case-management, self-management, 
health coaching, and decision aids are all used to improve 
medication adherence for patients with chronic conditions 
and several of them are used by some kidney transplant cent-
ers. The issue is that they vary widely in their effectiveness 
and, where studied, only some lead to improved outcomes. In 
a systematic review of 20 interventions to improve adherence 
for chronic illnesses, Viswanathan et al. 33 found only one 
intervention-education with behavioral support through 
continued patient contact-showed consistent evidence of 
improved adherence. In another systematic review of 10 
interventions, only integrative health coaching for diabetics 
was shown to improve adherence. The other nine interven-
tions, which were primarily self-management programs, did 
show improvements in other factors such as self-efficacy, 
healthy behaviors, and outcomes (e.g. lower HbA1C), yet 
results varied by study. 32 
Other methods such as behavioral contracts, MI, and 
appointment-based models (ABMs) (or medication syn-
chronization programs) are also being investigated. 
Behavioral contracts have improved medication adherence 
in adult RTRs. 15 MI, an empathic, non-judgmental style of 
interviewing that encourages patients to determine and 
verbalize their own goals for a behavior or behavior 
change, improved medication and visit adherence over tra-
ditional methods. 30,34 In a RCT, Paradis et al. 35 found com-
bining the transtheoretical model stages of change with 
MI-improved medication adherence for heart failure 
patients. Multidimensional interventions are increasing. In 
a 2008 meta-analysis, only 5 of 13 studies using mixed 
interventions improved adherence. 36 The ABM, an inter-
vention which combines monthly pharmacy counseling 
sessions with prescription refill synchronization, showed 
patients using it were 3-6 times more likely to be adherent 
compared with a control group. 37 
In 2011, Berben et al. 14 conducted a survey of current clini-
cal practice to identify interventions used by health care pro-
fessionals to enhance medication adherence in transplant </p>

<p>Oberlin et al. </p>



<p>patients. They classified interventions into educational/cogni-
tive, counseling/behavioral, and psychological/affective. They 
found that interventions showing evidence of promoting 
healthy behaviors or improving adherence appear to be rarely 
used by transplant centers. Figure 2 illustrates the interven-
tions in a modified, conceptual graphic. 
From Figure 2, interventions identified as being more 
effective at improving adherence (e.g. behavioral contracts, 
support groups, peer mentoring, intense counseling by phar-
macists) are used less frequently by transplant centers. Some 
interventions, used more frequently by transplant centers, 
such as establishing a partnership, providing written materi-
als, and using cues, have shown evidence of improving 
adherence. 38,39 Interventions combing multiple strategies and 
targeting providers have also shown significant improve-
ments in adherence; although they vary in their degree of 
effectiveness with minimal evidence supporting any one 
strategy. 2,17 As described in almost all studies mentioning the 
interventions above, many are personnel-intensive, costly, 
and have only been tested over a short duration. For example, 
studies that tested interventions such as counseling, health 
coaching, self-management programs, and behavioral con-
tracting, involved frequent interactions (weekly, monthly, and 
quarterly) over a short-time period (ranging from 6 weeks to 
24 months, with most interventions lasting 12 months or 
less). 15,32,38 
Patient engagement interventions have expanded beyond 
the physician-patient relationship to other care team 
members-such as pharmacists, nurses, social workers, and 
case managers-and peer mentors. Joost et al. 40 found that 
30-min counseling sessions with a pharmacist focused on 
educational, behavioral, and technical aspects improved 
medication adherence in kidney transplant patients. Peer-led </p>

<p>workshops increased healthy behaviors among patients with 
HIV and other chronic conditions. 30,41 
Technology-based interventions also are increasing. 
These include internet-based self-management programs, 
medication reminders via text message, telemonitoring, 
mobile applications, and social media. While there has been 
some success with internet-based programs, tablets and 
mobile apps, and text messaging, many of these are still in 
development and continue to have challenges. 32,42,43 For 
example, telemonitoring and iPhone chats with providers are 
not yet reimbursed and the use of electronic health records 
(EHRs) and social media are slow on the uptake; the latter is 
for fear of breaching professional confidentiality. 25,44,45 </p>

<p>Behavioral economics </p>

<p>Behavioral Economics relies heavily on psychology and 
other social sciences, and differs from patient engagement 
theories and traditional economics in that it is based on the 
belief that individuals make "predictably irrational" 
decisions. 46 While some decisions are based on reasoning, 
behavioral economists believe most people act intuitively; 
and this intuitiveness can be predictable. 47 Behavioral econ-
omists also believe patient engagement may or may not be 
needed to invoke a behavioral change. Blumenthal-Barby 
and Burroughs 48 further explain that people are motivated by 
incentives-with more sensitivity to losses than gains. As a 
result, behavioral economic interventions are typically in the 
form of financial incentives and nudges, which preserve peo-
ple's freedom by guiding them to a choice rather than speci-
fying a designated treatment regimen. 46 Table 1 provides an 
overview of the types of nudges and financial incentives 
reviewed, select examples of where these have been utilized, </p>

<p>Figure 2. "Patient engagement" interventions used by health care professionals. </p>



<p>SAGE Open Medicine </p>

<p>and the advantages and disadvantages of each as they relate 
to improving medication adherence for kidney transplant 
recipients. 
Behavioral economic principles have been used by other 
industries for decades. The most notable example is the 
401(k) retirement plans from companies. Historically, com-
panies offered employees the choice of enrolling in a 401(k) 
plan. By incorporating active choice, a strategy that requires 
individuals to select between options, companies experi-
enced a 28% increase in 401(k) participation over the stand-
ard opt in procedure. Applying loss aversion through </p>

<p>enhanced active choice (e.g. "I don't want to enroll in a 
401(k) plan and don't want to take advantage of the employer 
match") has been shown to induce more compliance. 57,58 The 
federal Administration of Children and Families (ACF) used 
a series of interventions to encourage Texas prison inmates 
to lower the amount of child support they owe while they are 
in prison. The primary driver is that state welfare agencies 
are at risk of losing federal funding for late and unpaid child 
support payments. The interventions included sending a 
teaser postcard before the official letter arrived, printing 
materials on blue paper to distinguish it from other mail, </p>

<p>Table 1. Behavioral economic interventions. </p>

<p>Intervention 
Type 
Examples 
Advantages 
Disadvantages </p>

<p>Automated 
hovering </p>

<p>Nudges 
Processing nudges: 
Intuitive and heuristic 
• 
• Salient interventions 
• 
• narratives, images, film 
• 
• Norms and messenger 
• 
• comparative information 
• 
• Subconscious priming 
• 
• environmental cues 
• 
• Commitments and 
egos 
• 
• Public promises </p>

<p>Smoking cessation 
Exercise/nutrition 
Seat belt use 
Screening for colon 
cancer 
Breast cancer risk 48 </p>

<p>• 
• Effective at improving a 
desired behavior 
• 
• Quick, low cost 
method </p>

<p>• 
• Center/system will have 
to define, design and 
develop the intervention 
• 
• If perceived negatively 
there is a risk of mistrust 
• 
• May be useful to spark 
initial engagement, but 
likely not a long-term 
solution </p>

<p>Reasoning nudges: 
Deliberate and conscious 
• 
• Active choice 
• 
• Enhanced active choice </p>

<p>Enrollment in automatic 
Rx refill program 
Organ donation 49 
Flu shots 
401(k) plans </p>

<p>• 
• Improved compliance 
and some indication of 
commitment over time 
• 
• Quick, low cost 
method </p>

<p>• 
• Most useful for one-time 
events/decision points </p>

<p>Financial 
Incentives </p>

<p>Dollars or vouchers 
• 
• Individual payment or 
lottery-based 
• 
• Patient or provider </p>

<p>HIV treatment 
adherence 50 
warfarin adherence 51 
Diabetes/glucose control 
(combined with peer 
mentoring) 52 
Smoking cessation 53,54 
Wellness programs 55 </p>

<p>• 
• Success at improving 
desired behavior 
during intervention 
• 
• Financial incentives 
combined with peer 
mentors 
• 
• Improved glucose 
control for diabetic 
veterans </p>

<p>• 
• Behaviors reverts 
to baseline after 
intervention stops 
• 
• Expensive to maintain 
long term even with a 
lottery-based system 
• 
• Wellness programs 
currently have 
low participation; 
encouraging action plans 
may improve motivation 
Co-payment Reduction 
• 
• Value-based insurance 
design </p>

<p>Diabetes and vascular 
disease (statins) 
Clopidogrel (blot clot 
inhibitor) 56 </p>

<p>• 
• Better aligns payment 
system with health 
outcomes </p>

<p>• 
• Only modest 
improvements in 
adherence rates 
• 
• Requires partnerships 
(e.g. payer, employers). 
• 
• Likely more applicable 
for chronic conditions 
with a larger population 
base 
Premium linked to 
behavior 
• 
• Rewards or penalties </p>

<p>• 
• Smoking cessation 
• 
• Exercise/nutrition 
• 
• If premiums 
adjustments are of 
the right magnitude 
and "unlinked" to 
paychecks, they may 
increase their salience 
to employees; Further 
testing is needed </p>

<p>• 
• Little evidence of 
improved behavior 
• 
• May require partnerships 
with employers 
• 
• Risk of premium 
increases for engaging in 
unhealthy behaviors </p>

<p>Oberlin et al. </p>



<p>explaining other parents had successfully reduced their child 
support, and sending a reminder postcard for those that did 
not respond. While fewer than 50% of eligible inmates par-
ticipated, a social science researcher at ACF explains this 
was a big impact at a low cost. 59 
More recently, researchers have partnered with employ-
ers, insurers, and pharmacy benefit managers to develop (or 
investigate) the use of behavioral economics in the health 
care industry. Interventions have ranged from simple nudges 
such as promoting seat belt use or encouraging more healthy 
eating choices by putting the salad bar at the front of a buffet 
to increasing organ donation and providing financial incen-
tives and peer mentoring to improve medication adherence 
for patients with chronic conditions. While many interven-
tions target the patient, some target physicians. For exam-
ple, a radiologist spent more time with a patient's report and 
felt more connected to the patient when the patient's picture 
was attached to an X-ray. Patients were 24 times more likely 
to have a sigmoidoscopy and 9 times more likely to have a 
fecal occult blood test relative to a control group when phy-
sicians suggested screening for colon cancer. 48 These types 
of nudges are geared toward individuals making one-time 
decisions (e.g. organ donation). If the goal is to improve 
medication adherence (a behavior that occurs frequently), 
then the intervention should occur just as frequently. 
Behavioral economists believe automated hovering is one 
way to do this. 55 
Automated hovering has been described as a cost-effec-
tive way to monitor and provide feedback to patients. 
Examples include <rs type="software">NudgerSize</rs> TM (an iPhone application 
that sends daily exercise reminders to users), electronic pill 
bottles, glucometers and other devices that transmit infor-
mation from the patient to the provider. 55 Automatic entry 
into a daily lottery for taking pills is another example. 
While there are advantages to using automated hovering 
(e.g. less resource intensive option for daily engagement), 
it is not for everyone. Asch et al. 60 explain that cell phones 
and automatic pill bottle reminders are not ideal for some-
one frequently hospitalized who likely requires a more 
personnel-intensive approach. In a RCT using electronic 
pill bottles to improve warfarin adherence, only patients 
with baseline international normalized ratio (INR) below 
the therapeutic range showed significant improvements in 
anticoagulation, indicating that the intervention worked for 
only a subset of the population. 51 
Studies using financial incentives to influence a behavio-
ral response varied in their effectiveness. Of those with evi-
dence of effectiveness, many included some form of 
interaction with health care professionals or peers, and most 
behaviors reverted back to baseline once the intervention 
stops. Similarly, offering co-payment reductions through 
value-based insurance design or linking premiums to healthy 
behaviors has only had modest impacts. 55 In a 2009 system-
atic review, adult RTRs, when offered free IST, were 95% 
adherent 6 months post-transplant yet only 48% adherent at </p>

<p>12 months with many becoming non-adherent by the 
10th month. The conclusion was that cost does not appear to 
influence adherence. 16 Volpp et al. 61 explain the effective-
ness of the incentive depends on how they are framed, timed, 
and distributed, and should ideally be small and combined 
with frequent positive feedback and rewards. 
Behavioral economics starts with the simplest and most 
cost-effective interventions first, then moves to more in-
depth, personnel-intensive approaches if the initial interven-
tion fails. 7,60 For example, in a Centers for Medicare and 
Medicaid Services (CMS) trial to improve medication adher-
ence and health outcomes for acute MI patients, participants 
follow a cascade of interventions starting with a pill bottle 
that tracks and wirelessly transmits data about their medica-
tion use. Patients who take their medication are entered into 
a daily sweepstakes and eligible for cash prizes. Patients are 
then contacted the next day (via email, text, or voice record-
ing) to (1) inform them of their prize or (2) inform them 
about what they could have won had if they had taken their 
medication. If patients miss more than two medications, a 
family member or other support person is contacted in an 
effort to provide social pressure to encourage adherence. If 
the patient misses four consecutive doses, then a clinical 
social worker is employed. Combining a behavioral nudge 
with technology, followed by involvement with a social 
worker if needed, is thought to improve traditional care man-
agement interventions. 46 Further studies of behavioral eco-
nomic interventions within the transplant community will be 
needed to quantify effectiveness and cost feasibility. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Adherence to immunosuppressive medications is necessary to 
prevent graft rejection or loss, minimize unnecessary hospitali-
zations, reduce resource use and costs, and promote positive 
long-term outcomes and quality of life for kidney transplant 
recipient. Despite methods currently in use, the rates of non-
adherence-and subsequent suboptimal outcomes-remains a 
significant health care problem. We conducted a scoping 
review to identify methods or tools to improve medication 
adherence for kidney transplant recipients. To look for novel 
approaches, we focused our research on industries outside of 
health care. Since taking a pill requires a desired behavior, we 
also included the fields of patient engagement and behavioral 
economics. 
Through this review, we did not find any one intervention 
or any one area surfacing as superior to any other. Our assess-
ment of other industries was less scientific compared to 
patient engagement and behavioral economics. In our review 
of the patient engagement literature, we found that many of 
the interventions are known in the transplant community, yet 
those that seem most effective are rarely used. This is likely 
due to interventions being time-consuming and costly to 
implement. Similar to patient engagement, behavioral eco-
nomic interventions appear to work best when they are </p>



<p>SAGE Open Medicine </p>

<p>multidimensional, combined with frequent engagement, 
peer mentors, and for a subset of the population that is at 
higher risk for poor adherence. Given the potential high cost 
and the effectiveness tapering off when the intervention 
stopped, behavioral economic interventions may not be the 
best option or feasible for individual transplant centers. 
Despite these shortcomings, we believe the themes and 
findings from this review can translate into practical applica-
tions for transplant centers. In consolidating our findings, we 
propose five strategies that transplant centers and other sys-
tems can implement to engage patients in a desired behavior. 
We recognize some of these are not novel, but we believe 
should be included as foundational strategies to improving 
medication adherence: </p>

<p>1. Build a foundation of trust-while this is viewed as a 
central principle in self-management models, not all 
transplant centers follow this model. Patients must 
feel comfortable discussing potential reasons for 
non-adherence and understand why adhering to their 
treatment regimen is important. The literature sup-
ports the idea that adherence to medications depends 
on believing in the importance of the regimen, fol-
lowed by the ability and capacity to take the pills. 
Most of the existing techniques assume patients are 
rational beings and that reminding them to take their 
pills will get the desired result. This may be neces-
sary, but to date it has not proved to be sufficient. The 
patient must actually believe and trust that consistent 
adherence is more important than not taking the med-
ication. Trust-building is personnel-intensive and 
requires frequent levels of engagement that will 
depend on the individual patient. 
2. Employ multiple interventions-there is no consen-
sus that a one-size-fits-all approach exists to improve 
medication adherence. What motivates one person 
may not motivate another. This holds not only across 
a patient population, but also for the individual. 
Behaviors are emotionally driven and dynamic. They 
can change daily and/or with major life events. 
Rather than have a laundry list of interventions to 
pull from, interventions should be prioritized and 
timed. For example: </p>

<p>(a) Immediately: Train center professionals in MI 
techniques 
(b) Pre-transplant: Identify the patient's preferred 
method of communication and reinforce expec-
tations and goals around medication adherence. 
Examples of interventions may include active 
choice models and behavioral contracts. 
(c) Post-transplant: Stress the importance of tak-
ing immunosuppressive medications for long-
term function. Start with nudges and automated 
reminders (e.g. text messaging or alarms) reserv-
ing personnel-intensive interventions for those </p>

<p>most in need. The use of peer-led workshops and 
support groups to keep people engaged has been 
useful, but the duration of the intervention for 
maintaining consistency is unproven. Further 
research is needed around how the frequency 
and duration of the interventions may impact 
long-term kidney transplant function. </p>

<p>3. Group patients by similar needs-grouping the 
patient population may be useful to more effectively 
tailor interventions and manage resources. While this 
was exclusion from our review as it is not an inter-
vention, one promising technique is the PAM survey. 
Many organization use either the four levels of acti-
vation as originally intended or further categorize 
patients into low (levels 1 and 2) or high (levels 3 and 
4). As patients tend to shift levels over time, the sur-
vey should be redistributed on an annual basis to con-
firm or modify each patient's activation level. With 
EHRs, organizations may also choose to look at other 
predictive risk factors such as age, education, and 
diversity/culture to create their own customized 
patient population strata. 
4. Develop collaborative partnerships-a transplant 
center is only one part of the care team needed to sup-
port kidney transplant recipients. Creating smooth 
transitions will help maintain trust and maximize the 
likelihood that adherence remains a priority. 
Transplant centers need collaborative relationships 
with community nephrologists, primary care provid-
ers, and pharmacists among others to effectively help 
patients manage their conditions and minimize their 
confusion from a multitude of potentially conflicting, 
independent messages. Partnerships with payers may 
also prove beneficial especially as the industry con-
tinues to move toward value-based insurance design. 
Some transplant recipients become non-adherent 
36 months post-transplant when Medicare stops pay-
ing for immunosuppressive medication. 
5. Embed medication adherence into the organization's 
culture-an initial education session around non-
adherence is not enough. In order to optimize long-
term function of kidney grafts, transplant centers 
need to establish methods to measure and track 
adherence over time. Tools to assess risk for or 
development of non-adherence to immunosuppres-
sive drug regimens should be coupled with adher-
ence-enhancing interventions and effectiveness 
assessments. Since many interventions can be per-
sonnel-intensive, demonstrating a positive return on 
investment (ROI) is necessary to compete in an era 
of efficiency and cost-effectiveness. Having dedi-
cated social workers and case managers to screen 
reasons for and provide solutions for non-adherence, 
along with dedicated pharmacists to help manage 
and monitor drug regimens, is a start. </p>

<p>Oberlin et al. </p>



<p>With an unacceptably high rate of kidney failure among 
long-term (10-year) kidney transplant recipients attributed to 
medication non-adherence, finding and implementing strate-
gies to engage patients in their care is necessary for reducing 
the number of lost kidneys and the associated morbidity, 
mortality, and health care costs. The transplant center's goal 
is to return kidney recipients to a functional life. As this 
occurs, the interactions between the transplant center person-
nel and kidney recipient decreases over time. While there is 
inter-and intra-patient variability in what factors keep a 
patient adherent, failure is more likely when interactions 
with health care providers diminishes. New approaches to 
either extend certain relationships or provide techniques that 
act as a surrogate to keeping the patient engaged and adher-
ent are warranted. While the effectiveness of the interven-
tions in the five steps outlined above remains to be 
determined, we believe these are a step in the right direction 
for transplant centers and other organizations to consider in 
their efforts to improve medication adherence. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors thank Roger Feldman and Thomas Rundall for their 
comments on earlier versions of this article. </p>

<p>Declaration of Conflicting Interests </p>

<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect 
to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support 
for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This 
scoping review was funded by Novartis Pharmaceuticals 
Corporation, Task Order Number HEORUSU200331. </p>





<p>SAGE Open Medicine </p>



</text></tei>