<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4503903" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>‫عالجها‬ ‫مت‬ ‫التي‬ ‫املبيض‬ ‫تكيس‬ ‫حاالت‬ ‫جميع‬ ‫مراجعة‬ ‫األهداف:‬ 
‫حتديد‬ ‫أجل‬ ‫من‬ ‫وذلك‬ ‫العزيز‬ ‫عبد‬ ‫امللك‬ ‫جامعة‬ ‫مستشفى‬ ‫في‬ 
‫التنظير.‬ ‫من‬ ً 
‫بدال‬ ‫البطن‬ ‫فتح‬ ‫عملية‬ ‫تستلزم‬ ‫التي‬ ‫العوامل‬ </p>

<p>‫مراجعة‬ ‫على‬ ‫االسترجاعية‬ ‫الدراسة‬ ‫هذه‬ ‫اعتمدت‬ ‫الطريقة:‬ 
‫في‬ ‫وعالجها‬ ‫تشخيصها‬ ‫مت‬ ‫التي‬ ‫للحاالت‬ ‫الطبية‬ ‫السجالت‬ 
‫جدة،‬ ‫عبدالعزيز،‬ ‫امللك‬ ‫جامعة‬ ‫مستشفى‬ ‫والوالدة،‬ ‫النساء‬ ‫قسم‬ 
‫0102م‬ ‫يناير‬ ‫من‬ ‫الفترة‬ ‫خالل‬ ‫وذلك‬ ‫السعودية‬ ‫العربية‬ ‫اململكة‬ 
‫السجالت‬ ‫من‬ ‫البيانات‬ ‫بجمع‬ ‫قمنا‬ ‫ولقد‬ ‫4102م.‬ ‫أغسطس‬ ‫إلى‬ 
‫يخص‬ ‫فيما‬ ‫باملرضى‬ ‫اخلاصة‬ ‫التفاصيل‬ ‫إلى‬ ‫باإلضافة‬ ‫الطبية،‬ 
‫عالجها‬ ‫وطرق‬ ‫ونوعيتها،‬ ‫األكياس،‬ ‫ووصف‬ ‫السريرية،‬ ‫األعراض‬ 
‫على‬ ‫حصلنا‬ ‫وقد‬ ‫البطن.‬ ‫فتح‬ ‫أو‬ ‫التنظير‬ ‫طريق‬ ‫عن‬ ‫كان‬ ‫سواء‬ 
‫البحث.‬ ‫هذا‬ ‫على‬ ‫لألبحاث‬ ‫األخالقية‬ ‫اللجنة‬ ‫موافقة‬ </p>

<p>‫املبايض‬ ‫بتكيس‬ ‫مصابة‬ ‫حالة‬ 244 ‫الدراسة‬ ‫شملت‬ ‫النتائج:‬ 
‫أشهر‬ 3 ‫من‬ ‫املرضى‬ ‫عمر‬ ‫تراوح‬ ‫ولقد‬ ‫الدراسة،‬ ‫فترة‬ ‫خالل‬ ‫وذلك‬ 
‫تراوح‬ ‫ولقد‬ ‫مرة.‬ 0-6 ‫السابق‬ ‫احلمل‬ ‫عدد‬ ‫وبلغ‬ .ً ‫عاما‬ 77 ‫إلى‬ 
‫بني‬ ‫ما‬ ‫الوزن‬ ‫تراوح‬ ‫فيما‬ ،ً ‫عاما‬ 37-180 ‫بني‬ ‫ما‬ ‫املرضى‬ ‫طول‬ 
‫عدد‬ ‫وكان‬ .12-47 ‫اجلسم‬ ‫كتلة‬ ‫مؤشر‬ ‫بلغ‬ ‫حيث‬ ‫كلغ‬ 3-161 
‫حالة‬ 244 ‫أصل‬ ‫من‬ ‫وذلك‬ )67.4%( 165 ‫املتزوجة‬ ‫احلاالت‬ 
‫كانت‬ ‫ولقد‬ .)6.6%( ‫حالة‬ 16 ‫بينهم‬ ‫احلمل‬ ‫عدد‬ ‫كان‬ ‫حيث‬ 
142 ‫منه‬ ‫عانت‬ ‫الذي‬ ‫البطن‬ ‫ألم‬ ً 
‫شيوعا‬ ‫السريرية‬ ‫األعراض‬ ‫أكثر‬ 
،79.9% ‫املبايض‬ ‫بتكيس‬ ‫اإلصابة‬ ‫نسبة‬ ‫وبلغت‬ .)58.2%( ‫حالة‬ 
.17.5% ‫اجلهتني‬ ‫في‬ ‫أو‬ ‫األمين‬ ‫املبيض‬ ‫في‬ ‫التكيس‬ ‫نسبة‬ ‫وكانت‬ 
‫كانت‬ ‫فيما‬ ‫احلاالت،‬ ‫من‬ 63.1 ‫لدى‬ ‫اليمني‬ ‫املبايض‬ ‫تأثرت‬ ‫وقد‬ 
‫وظيفية‬ ‫األكياس‬ ‫هذه‬ ‫نوع‬ ‫وكان‬ ‫احلاالت.‬ ‫من‬ 18.9% ‫لدى‬ ‫ثنائية‬ 
‫فيما‬ ،19.3% ‫لدى‬ ‫حميدة‬ ‫وأكياس‬ ‫احلاالت،‬ ‫من‬ 33.2% ‫لدى‬ 
.12.3% ‫لدى‬ ‫جنينية‬ ‫كانت‬ </p>

<p>‫تكيس‬ ‫عالج‬ ‫إلى‬ ‫أدت‬ ‫التي‬ ‫العوامل‬ ‫بأن‬ ‫الدراسة‬ ‫أظهرت‬ ‫اخلامتة:‬ 
‫الفئات‬ ‫كانت‬ ‫قد‬ ‫التنظير‬ ‫من‬ ً 
‫بدال‬ ‫البطن‬ ‫فتح‬ ‫طريق‬ ‫عن‬ ‫املبايض‬ 
‫والنساء‬ ‫متزوجات،‬ ‫الغير‬ ‫والنساء‬ ،ً ‫عاما‬ 35 ‫من‬ ‫األكثر‬ ‫العمرية‬ 
‫بأكثر‬ ‫املصابات‬ ‫وكذلك‬ ‫البطن،‬ ‫في‬ ‫ألم‬ ‫من‬ ‫يعانني‬ ‫والالتي‬ ‫احلمل،‬ 
‫املبايض.‬ ‫في‬ ‫واحد‬ ‫كيس‬ ‫من‬ </p>

<p>Objectives: To review cases of ovarian cysts managed 
at a University Hospital, and to identify the factors 
necessitating the use of laparotomy over laparoscopy. </p>

<p>Methods: We carried out a retrospective chart review 
of all cases of ovarian cysts diagnosed and managed at 
the . All data 
collected from medical record charts, patents details, 
clinical presentations, ovarian cysts description, and 
pathology type were recorded, and management 
by laparoscopy or laparotomy was identified. 
Ethical approval was obtained from ethical hospital 
committee. </p>

<p>Results: There were 244 cases of ovarian cysts during 
the study period. The age ranged from 3 months to 
77 years of age. The parity from 0-6. The height range 
from 37-180 cm. The weight range from 3-161 kg, 
and calculated body mass index ranged from 12-47. 
Out of 244 patients diagnosed, 165 were married 
(67.4%). Of those, only 16 patients were pregnant 
(6.6%). The most common presentation was 
abdominal pain in 142 patients (58.2%). Only 
79.9% were ovarian cysts, and 17.5% were either 
para-ovarian or retroperitoneal. The right ovaries were 
affected in 63.1%, and only 18.9% were bilateral. 
The types of ovarian cysts included functional cysts 
33.2%, benign cyst-adenoma 19.3%, and dermoid 
cysts 12.3%. </p>

<p>Conclusion: Factors associated with laparotomy 
management rather than laparoscopy included older 
age &gt;35, single, pregnant, or patients presenting with 
abdominal pain, and more than one cyst. </p>

<p>835 </p>

<p>www.smj.org.sa Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (7) </p>

<p>Review cases of ovarian cysts … Abduljabbar et al </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>n ovarian cyst is a common gynecological problem 
and is divided into 2 main categories; physiological 
and pathological. 
1 Physiological cysts are follicular cysts 
and luteal cysts. Pathological cysts are considered as 
ovarian tumors, which might be benign, malignant, and 
borderline. Benign tumors are more common in young 
females, but malignant are more frequent in elderly 
females. 
2 Most ovarian cysts are asymptomatic and 
disappear spontaneously. When ovarian cysts are large, 
they may cause abdominal discomfort. If pressing on 
the bladder it may also cause frequency of urination. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>The signs and symptoms of ovarian cysts may include; 
pelvic pain, dysmenorrheal, and dyspareunia. Other 
symptoms are nausea, vomiting, or breast tenderness, 
fullness and heaviness in the abdomen and frequency 
and difficulty emptying of the bladder. 
4 Patients with 
clear, simple ovarian cysts diagnosed by ultrasound 
might not require any treatment. However, monitoring 
using serial ultrasonography was carried out in women 
with simple ovarian cysts smaller than 5 cm in diameter 
and a normal CA 125. There is a good evidence to 
suggest safety of observing even a 10 cm ovarian cyst. </p>

<p>5,6 </p>

<p>The aim of this study is to review cases of ovarian 
cysts treated at a university hospital, and to analyze 
the method of management and factors affecting 
the decision regarding the method of management 
(laparoscopy versus laparotomy). </p>

<p>Methods. We carried out a retrospective medical 
charts review of all cases of ovarian cysts diagnosed 
and managed at the Department of Obstetrics and 
Gynecology, King Abdulaziz University Hospital 
(KAUH), Jeddah, Saudi Arabia, between January 2010 
and August 2014. Ethical approval was obtained from 
the hospital ethical committee. The study included 244 
cases diagnosed as ovarian cysts. The data collected from 
medical record charts included; age in years, nationality 
(Saudi or non-Saudi), parity, weight in kilograms, height 
in centimeters, body mass index (BMI), the patient's 
marital status (single, married, or having been married), 
whether patient was pregnant or not. Also, their clinical 
presentation, such as vaginal bleeding, abdominal pain 
or swelling, and infertility was reviewed and collected. </p>

<p>In addition, asymptomatic women found to have an 
ovarian cyst as an "incidental" finding on ultrasound 
examination for other reasons, such as pregnancy, were 
included in this study. The number of cysts, unilateral 
or bilateral, clear cysts or complicated, plus the location 
or side of the cysts and type (functional, simple clear, 
dermoid, endometriosis, cystadenoma, malignant, 
and complicated) were all recorded. Finally, how they 
were managed either by laparoscopy or laparotomy was 
documented. 
Inclusion and exclusion criteria. Patients admitted 
with a diagnosis of ovarian cysts and managed at 
KAUH were included. Exclusion criteria cases were 
those transferred to another facility, or if we found their 
chart was incomplete. 
The <rs id="software-0" type="software">IBM SPSS Statistics</rs> for Windows <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 22.0</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corp.</rs>, Armonk, NY, USA) was used to analyze 
data. Variables included age in years, nationality 
Saudi and non-Saudi, married or not, parity, height 
in cm, weight, BMI, and pregnant or not. Clinical 
presentation abdominal pain or otherwise, number of 
cysts, location and type of cysts was also included. The 
mean and standard deviation was calculated for the 
continuous variables. Frequency and percentage of other 
nominal variables were also computed. Using bivariate 
correlation, the different data variables were analyzed 
according to the surgical management; with the code 
0 for laparoscopy, and 1 for laparatomy. In addition, 
Pearson correlation and logistic regression were carried 
out determining factors affecting the choice of surgical 
modality used. </p>

<p>Results. A total of 244 cases of ovarian cysts were 
included. The mean ± standard deviation [SD] age of 
these patients was 35.35±12.849 years. The mean±SD 
parity was 2.20±2.676. The height ranged was from 
37-180 cm with a mean±SD of 153.88±16.227. The 
weight ranged from 3-161 kg with a mean±SD of 
69.58±22.506. The calculated BMI ranged from 12-47 
with a mean±SD of 27.76±6.314 (Table 1). Out of 
244 patients diagnosed with ovarian cysts, 165 were 
married (67.4%), and of those only 16 were pregnant 
(6.6%). The most common clinical presentation was 
abdominal pain in 142 patients (58.2%). Only 79.9% 
were ovarian cysts, and 17.5% were either para-ovarian 
or retroperitoneal. The most common affected was the 
right ovaries (63.1%) and only 18.9% were bilateral 
(Table 2). The type of ovarian cysts were recorded 
accordingly; 33.2% were functional cysts, 19.3% benign 
cyst adenoma, and 12.3% dermoid cysts (Table 3). </p>

<p>Disclosure. Authors have no conflict of interests, and 
the work was not supported or funded by any drug 
company. </p>



<p>Review cases of ovarian cysts … Abduljabbar et al </p>

<p>Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (7) www.smj.org.sa </p>

<p>Factors that are associated with the use of laparotomy 
for management rather than laparoscopy; older age &gt;35 
(odds ratio [OR] = 1.059; 95% confidence interval [CI]: 
1.019-1.101), single (OR = 2.176; 95% CI: 0.859-
1.509), pregnant (OR = 2.274; 95% CI: 1.027-3.796), 
patients presenting with abdominal pain (OR = 2.723; 
95% CI: 1.257-5.899), and if more than one cysts (OR 
= 2.753; 95% CI: 1.130-6.711) (Table 4). </p>

<p>Discussion. Functional ovarian cysts are common 
in women of reproductive age, but rare after menopause. </p>

<p>It can occur at any age including the fetus (in uterus). </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>In the present study, the patients were of all ages, the 
youngest 3-months-old, and the eldest 77 years old. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Treatment of ovarian cysts with laparoscopy was found 
to be a safe and effective method in young females 
provided that features of the cyst was benign and 
malignancy was not suspected clinically. 
8 It was found 
clinical features of the cysts correlated well with the 
final pathology. 
Symptomatic patients commonly present with 
abdominal pain, although most of the patients are 
asymptomatic and the cysts were found accidently 
by bimanual examination or ultrasound. Pain can 
present as dull ache or pain in the lower back or 
abdomen. Acute severe pain can occur in complicated 
ovarian cysts, torsion, infarction, or hemorrhage. 
9 The 
incidence of ovarian cysts in pregnant women is one 
out of 600. Most are benign cysts, and 50% are mature 
cystic teratoma, followed by benign cyst adenomas 
(20%). Ovarian cancer contributes to only 0.6% of 
cases and 13% of functional ovarian cysts. 
10 When 
managing giant benign ovarian cysts, laparoscopy </p>

<p>Table 3 -Type of ovarian cysts including the 
frequency in number and percentage. </p>

<p>Type 
n 
(%) 
Functional cysts 
81 (33.2) 
Dermoid 
30 (12.3) 
Endometriosis 
26 (10.7) 
Benign cyst adenoma 
47 (19.3) 
Malignant 
10 
(4.1) 
Complicated cysts 
22 
(9.0) 
N/A 
28 (11.5) 
Total 
244 
(100) 
N/A -not available </p>

<p>Table 4 -Factors affecting decisions of ovarian cysts. </p>

<p>Variables 
Significant 
Odds ratio 95% Confidence 
intervals 
Age in years 
0.003* 
1.059 
(1.019-1.101) 
Nationality 
0.723 
0.863 
(0.381-1.952) 
Single 
0.040* 
2.176 
(0.859-1.509) 
Parity 
0.750 
0.972 
(0.814-1.159) 
Height in cm 
0.297 
0.947 
(0.854-1.049) 
Weight in gram 
0.981 
0.998 
(0.856-1.164) 
Body mass index 
0.976 
1.006 
(0.695-1.455) 
Pregnant 
0.027* 
2.274 
(1.027-3.796) 
Clinical presentation 
0.011* 
2.723 
(1.257-5.899) 
Number of cysts 
0.0026* 
2.753 
(1.130-6.711) 
Location 
0.115 
0.424 
(0.146-1.230) 
Type 
0.307 
1.635 
(0.637-4.197) 
N/A -Not available </p>

<p>Table 2 -Analysis of 244 cases diagnosed with ovarian cysts. </p>

<p>Demographic characteristics 
n 
(%) 
Marital status 
Married 
165 
(67.6) 
Single 
79 
(32.4) 
Pregnant 
No 
224 
(91.8) 
Yes 
16 
(6.6) 
Not applicable 
4 
(1.6) 
Clinical presentation 
Vaginal bleeding 
47 
(19.3) 
Abdominal pain 
142 
(58.2) 
Abdominal swelling 
17 
(7.0) 
Incidental 
24 
(9.8) 
Infertility 
9 
(3.7) 
Not applicable 
5 
(2.0) 
Location 
Ovarian 
195 
(79.9) 
Para-ovarian 
25 
(10.2) 
Retroperitoneal 
17 
(7.0) 
Not applicable 
7 
(2.9) 
Side 
Right 
154 
(63.1) 
Left 
79 
(32.4) 
Not applicable 
11 
(4.5) 
Unilateral versus bilateral 
Unilateral 
194 
(79.5) 
Bilateral 
46 
(18.9) 
Not applicable 
4 
(1.6) </p>

<p>Table 1 -Demographic characteristics of 244 cases diagnosed with 
ovarian cysts. </p>

<p>Variables 
Minimum 
Maximum 
Mean 
Standard 
deviation 
Age 
1 
77 
35.35 
12.849 
Parity 
0 
11 
2.20 
2.676 
Height 
37 
180 
153.88 
16.227 
Weight 
3 
161 
69.58 
22.506 
BMI 
12 
47 
27.76 
6.314 </p>



<p>www.smj.org.sa Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (7) </p>

<p>Review cases of ovarian cysts … Abduljabbar et al </p>

<p>is considered a safe and minimally invasive surgical 
procedure. 
11 Ultrasound-guided drainage with excision 
of giant ovarian cysts is a safe and appropriate modality 
of treatment. Even in suspected torsions; laparoscopy 
can be used to diagnose and treat these cases. 
12 In an 
Iranian study, 
13 functional cysts (57%) were the most 
common benign ovarian mass followed by serous cyst 
adenoma (13%), and dermoid cyst (10%). In a study 
from Ireland, 
14 the most common was endometrioma 
(29%) followed by dermoid cyst (24%), and functional 
cyst (19%). 
14 In an Italian study, 
15 the most common 
was also endometrioma (19%) followed by functional 
cyst (18%). 
15 In our study, the most common was 
functional cysts (33%) followed by cyst adenoma 
(19.3%), and endometriosis (10.7%). 
In conservative management of ovarian cysts, the 
cysts can disappear or be under control. In a situation, 
where it has to be removed, this can be carried out 
laparoscopically or through a laparotomy. 
16 The 
traditional option for ovarian cyst removal is laparotomy, 
and this approach is the oldest method, and is an 
entirely invasive procedure. Over the last 2 decades, 
gynecologists have aimed for less invasive procedures 
in the pelvis; namely, laparoscopy. The choice of which 
procedure to use in most cases, will be laparoscopy 
if possible, and laparotomy is only used if there are 
contraindications with the use of laparoscopy, such as 
cardiopulmonary disease, history of previous operations 
in the pelvis, known adhesion in the abdominal cavity, 
and late trimester of pregnancy. 
17 One advantage of 
laparoscopic surgery of the ovary is that it is safe and 
effective and used for many indications for benign 
simple to more complicated hemorrhagic cysts, and 
many more gynecological problems. 
18 Other advantages 
of laparoscopy over laparotomy include; small scar, 
less operative time, fast recovery, fewer adhesions, and 
lower cost. In addition, laparoscopy is associated with 
less postoperative pain, less febrile complications, a 
reduction in the number of days in the hospital, and 
total cost. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Certain factors such as umbilical hernia or the 
presence of mesh or adhesion, in cases of pregnancy, 
and obese patients makes laparoscopy difficult or 
dangerous, and the surgeon may choose laparotomy 
for the procedure, or non-umbilical access. 
20,21 In 
cases where adhesions are suspected in patients with 
a history of abdominal surgery or infection or others, 
micro laparoscopy is indicated instead of a blind trocar 
insertion or an alternate location for entry. 
22,23 Large 
pelvic mass, pregnancy, obesity, extreme thinness, and 
abdominal wall laxity all can dictate the surgeon to shift 
to laparotomy or use a different approach. </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Limitations of this study included its retrospective 
design, and management of patient by different 
consultants. Future study should be prospective, and 
management should be by either one consultant or by 
a protocol followed by group of consultants to identify 
the relevant factors. 
In conclusion, the types of ovarian cysts were 
functional cysts in 33.2%, followed by benign cyst 
adenoma, and dermoid cysts. Factors that are associated 
with laparotomy for management rather than 
laparoscopy are older age &gt;35, single, pregnant, patients 
presenting with abdominal pain, and more than one 
cyst. </p>







</text></tei>