<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4304534" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Introduction: Cognitive training (CT) has been reported to improve cognition in older adults. 
Its combination with protective factors such as physical activity (CPT) has rarely been studied, 
but it has been suggested that CPT might show stronger effects than pure CT. 
Materials and methods: Healthy older adults (aged 50-85 years) were trained with CPT 
(n=15) or CT (n=15). Interventions were conducted in 90-minute sessions twice weekly for 
6.5 weeks. Cognitive functions were assessed before and immediately after the interventions, 
and at 1-year follow-up. 
Results: The main finding was an interaction effect on attention, with comparable gains from 
CPT and CT from pre-to post-test, but stronger effects of CPT to follow-up (P=0.02). Signifi-
cant effects were found in subjects in terms of cognitive state (P=0.02), letter verbal fluency 
(P=0.00), and immediate (P=0.00) and delayed (P=0.01) verbal memory. Post hoc analyses 
indicated that these latter domains were affected differentially by CPT and CT. No significant 
between-subject effects were found. 
Conclusion: Our results suggest that CPT might lead to stronger long-term effects on attention. 
However, as the difference between CT and CPT was only evident at follow-up, these effects 
cannot be interpreted as a direct consequence of CPT; they may have been related to sustained 
physical activity after the training. Other domains were improved by both interventions, but no 
typical pattern could be identified. Possible underlying mechanisms are discussed, and directions 
for future research are suggested. 
Increasing evidence suggests that even the aging brain is still amenable to neuronal and 
cognitive plasticity. For example, there is strong evidence that cognitive training (CT) 
can lead to improvement of cognitive functions in healthy older adults; eg, in immedi-
ate and delayed memory, speed of processing, executive functions, fluid intelligence, 
visual reasoning, visuospatial construction, attention, subjective cognitive performance, 
and neuropsychological status. 
1-5 However, probably due to different types of training 
and study designs (eg, comparison to an active or passive control group), different 
effects have been reported. As a result, establishing any specification of the effects 
of CT programs remains difficult. 
1,2 Transfer effects into nontrained domains cannot 
yet be clearly supported; therefore, recent studies suggest that multidomain CT seems 
more promising than interventions focused on only one domain for inducing lasting 
improvement of different cognitive functions in healthy older adults. </p>

<p>3,5,6   In addition, many studies suggest a positive effect of physical activity and struc-
tured exercise on cognitive functions, with the most consistent findings being reported </p>

<p>Correspondence: elke Kalbe 
Institute of gerontology, Psychological 
gerontology and CenDI, University 
of Vechta, Driverstrasse 22, 49377 
Vechta, germany 
Tel +49 4441 15204 
Fax +49 4441 15621 
email elke.kalbe@uni-vechta.de </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Clinical Interventions in Aging 
19 January 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>298 </p>

<p>rahe et al </p>

<p>for executive functions. 
7-10 In particular, the combination 
of diverse exercise forms in multicomponent interventions 
that train endurance, strength, balance/coordination, and 
flexibility might constitute a promising approach to improve 
various cognitive domains of healthy older adults, 
11,12 as 
both aerobic 
7,8 and anaerobic 
10,13 activities seem to benefit 
brain health and cognitive functions. Recently, it has been 
argued that the combination of different protective factors 
of healthy cognitive aging might be most promising when 
attempting to delay cognitive decline and preserve cognitive 
abilities. 
14,15 Particularly, the combination of cognitive and 
physical activity has attracted increasing interest. 
Early evidence indicates that CT supplemented by 
physical activity or exercise (CPT) might result in supe-
rior effects on cognitive abilities in healthy older adults 
compared to CT. 
16-18 However, such evidence remains con-
troversial, probably due to methodological limitations as 
well as differences in interventions and study designs. </p>

<p>19-22   For example, studies of combined cognitive and physical 
interventions in healthy older adults differ substantially 
in the application of CPT. Most studies do not include 
multidomain cognitive 
16-19,22 and multicomponent physical 
activity 
16-22 as has been recommended when attempting to 
improve cognition. 
3,5,12 Furthermore, duration, frequency, 
and intensity of the CT applied have varied extremely, 
from 8 total hours 
21 to 45 total hours. 
16 The same holds 
for the physical activity parts, which vary from 13 total 
hours 
18 to 42 hours. 
22 Moreover, the combined interven-
tions have been conducted both consecutively 
16,17,19-22 and 
simultaneously. 
18 As a result, there are enormous dis-
crepancies within the CPT, and duration, frequency, and 
intensity of the contrasted interventions are almost never 
comparable between the different studies. In three studies, 
the training sessions were doubled by implementing both 
CT and physical training into the CPT group. 
20-22 Others 
tried to compensate for additional training either through 
additional social contact in the noncombined groups or 
by equalizing the duration of the training sessions in the 
different intervention groups. 
16-19 Finally, the long-term 
effects of CPT have been reported in only two studies; </p>

<p>16,21   most investigations restrict themselves to pretest/post-test 
comparisons. 
17-20,22 Especially in healthy older adults, long-
term effects assessed in follow-ups are highly relevant 
because the possible effects of interventions on subsequent 
age-associated decline cannot be assessed directly after 
training. Evidence of stronger cognitive effects of CPT 
compared to single CT is inconclusive, and further inves-
tigation is necessary. </p>

<p>Based on the current literature, the aim of this study was 
to examine whether the cognitive effects of CPT are superior 
to that of CT in healthy older adults, and to address the impor-
tant criticisms raised above. For this purpose, healthy older 
adults were trained in a standardized group setting with CPT 
targeting multiple cognitive domains (memory, attention, 
executive functions) and multiple physical fitness compo-
nents (strength, balance/coordination, flexibility, endurance) 
or pure multidomain CT. Training duration, frequency, and 
intensity were made comparable between the two interven-
tions. Effects on various cognitive domains, assessed with 
an elaborate neuropsychological test battery, were compared 
between the groups directly after training and after 1 year. 
Neither a nonactive waiting-list control group nor a control 
group with intervention for which no cognitive effects could 
be expected was included, intentionally, as (i) the benefits 
of pure CT have been demonstrated extensively before, and 
(ii) the focus of this study is on the additional benefits of CPT. 
Derived from the current state of research, we hypothesized 
that, due to the consistent effects of physical activity mainly 
on executive functions, CPT might lead to stronger effects 
on executive functions when compared to pure CT. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>This study was conducted as a controlled trial. The design 
involved two groups, each assessed three times, to evaluate 
the efficacy of CPT compared to pure CT for the improve-
ment and maintenance of cognitive functions in healthy older 
adults immediately after training and at 1-year follow-up. </p>

<p>Participants and procedure </p>

<p>Healthy older adults were recruited and trained with CPT 
in Osnabrück, Germany. We recruited via advertisements 
in the local press, health centers, and local Senior Service 
Offices. To compare CPT with pure CT, we used existing 
data from a database of 31 participants, who had already 
been trained with CT in Cologne, Germany, and tested before 
and after training and at 1-year follow-up. CT participants 
who matched those in the CPT group in age, education, and 
sex were selected from this database for statistical analysis 
controlling for differences between the two intervention 
groups. Matching for comparable age had first priority, 
because age is the most likely factor to influence cognitive 
functions. Comparable group sizes were ensured for the 
statistical analyses with this design, although the trial was 
controlled and the trainings were conducted in comparable, 
standardized settings, randomization was not possible, and 
only the dropout rate of the CPT can be reported. However, </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>299 </p>

<p>Cognitive training with physical activity </p>

<p>the matched participants selected for the CT were compared 
with the unselected participants to ensure that no other differ-
ences between groups were introduced by the matching. 
In both intervention groups, participants underwent 
a telephone interview to establish personal data and his-
tory of diseases. Inclusion criteria were the following: age 
50-85 years; normal or corrected-to-normal vision and hear-
ing; at least 80% attendance at training; and completion of 
the three assessments. The wide age range was chosen to 
correspond with the training used in this study. 
Participants were excluded if they reported any psychiat-
ric or neurological disease (past or present), were suffering 
a condition that prohibited moderate physical activity, took 
psychotropic drugs, did not perform in the normal range of 
cognitive function in the DemTect test (#12 points), 
23-25 or 
had clinically relevant symptoms of depression, assessed 
according to the German Beck Depression Inventory 
2 ($20 points) 
26 at pretest. Written informed consent was 
obtained before the first neuropsychological assessment. 
The study was conducted after being approved by the ethics 
committee of the University Hospital Cologne. </p>

<p>neuropsychological test battery </p>

<p>A comprehensive neuropsychological test battery was con-
ducted with all participants at pretest, after the interventions 
at post-test, and 1 year after completion of the interventions. 
The addressed domains were overall cognitive state, memory, 
attention, executive functions, visuospatial construction, 
and number processing. We used established tests that are 
sensitive to age-related cognitive decline and have good 
reliability and validity. When available, parallel forms were 
used to minimize retest effects; at pretest version A was used, 
at post-test version B was used, and at follow-up version A 
was used again. 
The overall cognitive state was screened with the Dem-
Tect test, which included the subtests wordlist immediate and 
delayed recall, digit span backwards, verbal fluency (naming 
supermarket items or animals), and number transcoding. </p>

<p>23,24   Two parallel versions of the DemTect test are available. </p>

<p>25   For the assessment of verbal memory, the subtests 
immediate and delayed recall of the DemTect test were 
analyzed. 
23-25 The Complex Figure Test (CFT) in the delayed 
recall condition was used to assess figural memory and the 
Rey Complex Figure (version A) and the Modified Taylor 
Figure (version B) were used as parallel forms. 
27 Auditory 
divided attention was assessed with the Brief Test of Atten-
tion (BTA). 
27 Several (sub) tests were used to broadly cover 
the executive domain, including tests of working memory, </p>

<p>executive control, and verbal fluency. Working memory was 
assessed with the DemTect subtest digit span backwards. </p>

<p>23-25   Executive control was examined with the ratio of part B 
divided by part A of the Trail Making Test (TMT B/A). </p>

<p>27   Semantic and letter fluency were measured with the parallel 
subtests supermarket (version A)/animal test (version B) of 
the DemTect and with the Controlled Oral Word Associa-
tion Test (COWA), respectively. 
23-25,27 To measure changes 
in visuospatial construction, the copy trial of the CFT was 
used. 
27 In order to evaluate number processing, the DemTect 
subtest number transcoding was applied. </p>

<p>23-25   Neuropsychological assessments were conducted in a 
standardized face-to-face situation and lasted 90 minutes. 
Tests were performed by experienced neuropsychologists 
trained intensively in test application and scoring; due to 
the nature of the above-reported design, the neuropsycholo-
gists could not be blinded. All tests were applied as paper/ 
pencil tests. </p>

<p>self-reported physical activity </p>

<p>For the assessment of the self-reported physical activity, 
the German version of the International Physical Activity 
Questionnaire (IPAQ) was used in the CPT group. 
28 Par-
ticipants answered questions about their physical activity 
during the last 7 days, and the mean time per day spent with 
an activity was assessed. Depending on this information, a 
domain-specific score for walking, moderate, and vigorous 
activities, as well as a total score of the metabolic equivalent 
(MET) was estimated. Referring to Ainsworth et al 1 MET 
corresponds to the resting metabolic rate obtained during 
quiet sitting. 
29 Different physical activities can be rated 
by multiplying the amount of time spent on the respective 
activity by an activity-typical factor in the range between 
0.9 for sleeping and 18 for running. 
29 The total score and 
the information from moderate and vigorous activities were 
used to build categories indicating whether participants were 
highly active, moderately active, or mildly active (for exact 
criteria see Scoring Protocol under http://www.ipaq.ki.se/ 
scoring.pdf). The MET subscores and the total MET score 
as well as the categories were used for data analysis. </p>

<p>Interventions </p>

<p>Participants were trained with CPT in groups of five to eight, 
led by a certified trainer, for 6.5 weeks. Age-, education-, and 
sex-matched participants who had been trained with pure CT 
in groups of five to eight participants by a certified trainer 
for 6 weeks were used for group comparison. Standardized 
manuals were used in both groups. We chose group settings </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>rahe et al </p>

<p>because social activity has been found to positively impact 
cognition and the risk of dementia; also, group training is 
more cost effective and is therefore well suited for clinical 
practice. </p>

<p>30   Pure cognitive training </p>

<p>The neuropsychological group training course NEUROvitalis 
was used for CT. 
31 The training consists of 12 sessions in 
which the aging-sensitive domains memory, attention, and 
executive functions are trained. One session lasts 90 minutes 
and there are two sessions per week. The main aim of the CT 
was to improve different cognitive functions. Furthermore, it 
aimed to activate and to motivate participants to improve their 
cognitive health behavior by remaining cognitively active and 
compensating deficits with learned mnemonic strategies after 
training. Each session had a special topic that was explained in 
a psycho-educational short lecture by the trainer. In addition, 
participants performed group games, single and group tasks in 
the form of paper/pencil tasks, verbal exercises, or board games 
to train the targeted domains. Participants were also asked to 
perform cognitive homework for 10 minutes each day. 
The CT was not individually tailored because it was 
performed in groups. Levels of difficulty corresponding </p>

<p>to the group's cognitive level were used where available 
in the training material. Table 1 gives an overview of the 
structure and contents of the CT. For a detailed description 
of NEUROvitalis, see Petrelli et al. </p>

<p>32   CT with additional physical activity </p>

<p>In the CPT group, the modified version NEUROvitalis 
Plus of the CT NEUROvitalis 
31,32 was used. It consisted 
of the same cognitive parts as the pure CT supplemented 
by a session named Physical activity and nutrition and 
a physical activity program. The additional session and 
the physical activity program were developed on the basis of 
the physical activity recommendations made by Nelson et al. </p>

<p>33   Information about healthy nutrition mainly focused on the 
Mediterranean diet, which has been thoroughly studied by 
Scarmeas et al. 
34-36 The structure and content of the CPT is 
shown in Table 1. 
The physical activity part was conducted for the first 
20 minutes of every training session, so that the physical and 
cognitive elements were trained in a consecutive manner. 
To ensure that session duration was comparable to that of 
CT, the single tasks were given as additional homework in 
CPT. The physical activity part targeted multiple physical </p>

<p>Table 1 Overview of the two intervention groups </p>

<p>CPT 
CT </p>

<p>Main cognitive domains trained 
Memory, attention, and executive functions in both intervention groups 
Typical session 
1. Physical activity (20 min) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2. group games (15 min) 
3. Psychoeducation (10 min) 
4. Cognitive training in group 
setting (45 min) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1. group games (15 min) 
2. Psychoeducation (10 min) 
3. Cognitive training in group 
setting (45 min) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>4. single cognitive exercises (20 min) 
Homework 
Cognitive homework 
single cognitive exercises as 
additional homework </p>

<p>Cognitive homework </p>

<p>Topic of the psychoeducation 
Session # 
Session # </p>

<p>Mental capacity: detriments and training 
1 
1 
Physical activity and nutrition </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>2 
The meaning of attention 
3 
2 
how does memory work? 
4 
3 
Working memory 
5 
4 
Memory and language 
6 
5 
Memory strategies I 
7 
6 
Memory strategies II 
8 
7 
Memory for names and faces 
9 
8 
Appointments and transactions 
10 
9 
Understanding and remembering texts 
11 
10 
Planning and problem solving 
12 
11 
risk and protective factors 
13 
12 </p>

<p>Notes: neUrOvitalis 
21,22 was used as CT, the new version of the CT named neUrOvitalis Plus was used as CPT. In CPT an additional physical activity program was 
performed over the course of the training. Both CT and CPT were performed in groups of five to eight participants led by a certified trainer. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>exercises of a multicomponent 
program (strength, coordination/balance, flexibility, endurance) were used in the CPT. 
b Paper/pencil tasks, verbal group exercises, and board games were used in the CT, and 
the difficulty level was adapted to the group's performance where available in the training's material. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>A session named Physical activity and nutrition was added in CPT. 
Abbreviations: CPT, cognitive training with additional physical activity; CT, cognitive training; min, minutes. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>301 </p>

<p>Cognitive training with physical activity </p>

<p>fitness components with exercises of strength, flexibility, and 
coordination/balance. Endurance was trained with a moder-
ate walking or seated aerobic warm-up in each session for 
10 minutes. To improve physical-health behavior after the 
training, participants were encouraged to use strategies such 
as taking the stairs where possible, or cycling. As support, 
the participants received a booklet with the exercises from 
the training sessions for practice at home. 
In total, the two intervention groups only differed in 
(i) the additional session about Physical activity and nutri-
tion in CPT, and (ii) the single tasks performed during the 
sessions in the pure CT, where in the CPT the participants 
performed physical exercises instead, with the single tasks 
being performed as homework. </p>

<p>statistical analyses </p>

<p>Statistics were calculated using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS Statistics 21</rs> for Win-
dows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>, Armonk, NY, USA). Normal dis-
tributions were tested using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. 
The Levene's test was applied assessing the homogeneity of 
variances for between-group comparisons. Baseline overall 
cognitive state and differences in demographics between 
groups, selected and unselected participants of the CT, and 
drop-outs and completers of the CPT were compared between 
groups. We used t-tests for independent samples to compare 
the age, Mann-Whitney tests to compare performance in 
DemTect and education, and chi-square tests for the compari-
son of the sex distribution, each with a significance level of 
α=0.05. <rs id="software-1" type="software">G*Power</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://www.gpower.hhu.de</rs>) was used to 
estimate the achieved power with a post hoc analysis. </p>

<p>37   Cognitive variables </p>

<p>Gains from CT from pre-to post-test and to 1 year follow-up 
were estimated with analysis of variance (ANOVA) for 
repeated measures (rANOVAs) with a significance level 
of α=0.05. Due to the intercorrelations between the differ-
ent cognitive variables (eg, DemTect subscores with the 
total score), a multivariate analysis was not appropriate. 
The within-subject variable Time had three levels (pretest 
vs post-test vs follow-up). The between-subject variable 
Training had two levels (CPT vs pure CT). The interaction 
Time × Training was used to specify which training group 
showed stronger effects. We report Greenhouse-Geisser 
values to handle possible violations of sphericity. The effect 
size partial η² (η p ²) is reported, indicating a small (η p ².0.01), 
moderate (η p ².0.06), or strong effect (η p ².0.14). 
38 In a sec-
ond step, post hoc pairwise comparisons were calculated for 
the significant Time effects of the rANOVAs. The Bonferroni </p>

<p>correction of <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> was used to prevent an inflated type I 
error, with an overall value of α=0.05. Here, the effect size d 
is reported, indicating a small (d.0.10), moderate (d.0.30), 
or strong effect (d.0.50). </p>

<p>38   If variables violated the assumptions of normal distribu-
tion and homogeneity of variances, the Friedman's ANOVA 
was used as a nonparametric equivalent. The effect size ω is 
reported, indicating a small (ω.0.10), moderate (ω.0.30), 
or strong effect (ω.0.50). 
38 The Wilcoxon signed-rank test 
was used in this case to compare the gains achieved within the 
training groups as a post hoc test for the significant variables 
of the Friedman's ANOVAs. The Bonferroni procedure was 
applied manually to prevent an inflated type I error (α=0.05/ 
comparisons per group). The effect size ϕ is reported, indicat-
ing a small (ϕ.0.10), moderate (ϕ.0.30), or strong effect 
(ϕ.0.50). 
38 The nonparametric Kruskal-Wallis test was used 
to estimate between-group differences at the three test points 
with the value α=0.05. </p>

<p>self-reported physical activity </p>

<p>As the IPAQ was administered only in the CPT group, 
changes in self-reported physical activity from pre-to post-
test and to 1 year follow-up were estimated with rANOVAs 
only within the combined group (n=15) with a significance 
level of α=0.05. The effect size η p ² is reported. Dependent 
t-tests for the comparisons of the physical activity at the 
three assessments were calculated for the significant Time 
effects of the rANOVAs. The Bonferroni correction was 
used to address possible problems of multiple comparisons 
with a significance level of α=0.05/number of comparisons. 
The effect size d is reported. Furthermore, the distribu-
tion of the IPAQ categories at the three assessments was 
compared with a Friedman's ANOVA. The effect size ω 
is reported. </p>

<p>Results 
Baseline characteristics and dropout rate </p>

<p>At baseline, participants of the two interventions did not 
differ significantly in age, (t=-0.46 [28], P=0.65), educa-
tion (U=76.50, z=-1.77, P=0.08), overall cognitive state 
(DemTect) (U=70.00, z=-1.56, P=0.12), or sex, (χ 
2 [1]=0.16, 
P=0.69). Table 2 shows the baseline characteristics of both 
intervention groups. 
In sum, 26 participants were recruited for CPT. At pre-
test, two had to be excluded due to neurological diseases. 
Altogether, 24 participants were trained with CPT. Two 
participants quit the training because of time constraints. 
Of the 22 trained participants who completed pre-and </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>302 </p>

<p>rahe et al </p>

<p>post-tests, 15 returned for the 1-year follow-up. One par-
ticipant was unavailable at follow-up. The other 6 refused 
to take part in an assessment. The reasons for refusal were 
illness or engagements with other activities. The dropouts 
and completers of the CPT did not differ significantly in 
age (t=0.92 [22], P=0.37), education (U=49.00, z=-1.11, 
P=0.29), or overall cognitive state (DemTect) (U=58.50, 
z=-0.55, P=0.60). 
As indicated in the Methods section, no dropout rate can 
be reported for the pure CT due to the study design. However, 
the comparison of the selected and matched participants 
trained with CT with those of the data pool who were not 
selected for this study revealed no significant differences 
concerning age (t=1.28 [29], P=0.21), education (U=104.50, 
z=-0.62, P=0.55), or overall cognitive state (DemTect) 
(U=111.50, z=-0.37, P=0.74). </p>

<p>Analysis of the group differences 
in the cognitive variables </p>

<p>We achieved 20% power to detect a small interaction effect 
(η p ².0.01), 85% power to detect a moderate interaction 
effect (η p ².0.06), and 99% power to detect a strong interac-
tion effect (η p ².0.14) with the rANOVAs (N=30; two-tailed 
α=0.05). Test performance of both groups at the three assess-
ments is shown in Table 3. 
The rANOVAs revealed one significant Time × Training 
interaction effect. This effect occurred in favor of CPT for 
the domain of divided attention (BTA): F(1.68, 46.96)=4.47, 
MSE=3.97, P=0.02, η p ²=0.14. 
From pre-to post-test, both groups showed comparable 
gains in attention (CPT: mean difference [ mean diff; post-
pre]=1.46 vs pure CT: mean diff [post-pre]=1.67), but to the 
1-year follow-up the CPT showed a further improvement 
( mean diff [follow-up-pre]=2.73) while the pure CT could not 
stabilize the short-term gain ( mean diff [follow-up-pre]=0.40; 
see Figure 1). Furthermore, we analyzed the within-subject 
effect of Time to find whether there were changes in the 
cognitive domains over the three assessments. A significant </p>

<p>within-subject Time effect was found for letter verbal fluency 
(COWA): F(1.84, 51.37)=14.56, MSE=48.94, P=0.00, 
η p ²=0.34. The nonparametric analyses found significant 
within-subjects effects of Time for overall cognitive state 
(DemTect) (χ²=7.74 [2], P=0.02, ω=0.51), as well as imme-
diate and delayed verbal memory (DemTect, immediate and 
delayed recall; χ²=26.06 [2], P=0.00, ω=0.93 and χ²=8.66 
[2], P=0.01, ω=0.54). No significant overall changes were 
found in the other cognitive domains, and none of the 
between-subjects effects of Training reached significance 
(all P.0.05). 
Post hoc tests under Bonferroni correction were applied 
for the significant variables of the within-subjects effects 
of Time (parametric pairwise comparisons with an overall 
significance level of α=0.05; nonparametric Wilcoxon 
signed-rank tests with a manually calculated significance 
level of α=0.01 [0.05/6 comparisons per group]). Table 4 
gives an overview of the results of the post hoc tests of the 
within-group differences. </p>

<p>Analysis of the self-reported 
physical activity </p>

<p>The rANOVAs showed significant changes in the self-
reported physical activity for the IPAQ variables moderate 
activity (F[1.61, 22.53]=5.87, MSE=3,438,820.60, P=0.01, 
η p ²=0.30) and total MET-Score (F[1.43, 20.10]=5.00, 
MSE=7,353,402,97, P=0.03, η p ²=0.26) in the combined 
training group. The variables walking and vigorous activity 
did not change significantly. Post hoc tests with Bonferroni 
correction (α=0.05/4=0.01) were executed for the significant 
variables of the within-subjects effects of Time. The CPT 
group reported significantly more physical activity from pre-to 
post-test in moderate activity (t[14]=3.93, P=0.00, d=1.01) and 
reached higher total MET scores (t[14]=2.38, P=0.03, d=0.61), 
although the latter only approached significance because of 
the Bonferroni correction. However, although comparison of 
physical activity between pretest and follow-up did not show 
significance either for moderate activity or total MET scores, on </p>

<p>Table 2 Baseline characteristics of the study sample </p>

<p>Demographics 
CPT n=15 
CT n=15 
P </p>

<p>Mean (SD) 
Range 
Mean (SD) 
Range </p>

<p>Age 
67.13 (4.09) 
62-75 
66.33 (5.33) 
55-77 
0.65 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>education 
16.87 (4.22) 
12-25 
14.27 (4.08) 
8-21 
0.08 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Cognitive state: DemTect 
15.60 (1.99) 
13-18 
16.80 (1.52) 
14-18 
0.12 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>sex 
♀=10 
♂=5 
♀=11 
♂=4 
0.69 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Notes: DemTect is from Kalbe et al. 
23,24 range of DemTect norms for normal cognitive state: 13-18. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Comparison of groups at baseline with t-test for independent samples. 
b Comparisons of groups at baseline with Mann-Whitney tests. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Comparison of groups at baseline with chi-square test. 
Abbreviations: ♀, female; ♂, male; CPT, cognitive training with additional physical activity; CT, cognitive training; n, subsample. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>303 </p>

<p>Cognitive training with physical activity </p>

<p>Table 3 Test performance of the intervention groups at pretest, post-test, and at 1-year follow-up </p>

<p>Domain </p>

<p>Max score </p>

<p>CPT n=15 </p>

<p>CT n=15 </p>

<p>Pretest </p>

<p>Post-test </p>

<p>Follow-up </p>

<p>Pretest </p>

<p>Post-test </p>

<p>Follow-up </p>

<p>Mean (SD) or median (range) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mean (SD) or median (range) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Cognitive state 
DemTect </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>15.00 (13-18)   18.00 (14-18)   18.00 (14-18)   17.00 (14-18)   18.00 (15-18)   18.00 (14-18) </p>

<p>Memory 
Verbal memory 
DemTect, Ir </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>13.00 (10-18) </p>

<p>16.00 (11-20)   14.00 (11-18)   14.00 (10-20)   17.00 (13-19)   17.00 (11-18)   DemTect, Dr </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4.00 (0-10) </p>

<p>7.00 (1-10) </p>

<p>6.00 (2-10) </p>

<p>5.00 (1-10) </p>

<p>6.00 (4-10) </p>

<p>6.00 (2-10) </p>

<p>Figural memory 
CFT, Dr </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>20.63 (6.07) </p>

<p>23.40 (4.39) </p>

<p>23.33 (4.37) </p>

<p>21.40 (6.73) </p>

<p>21.93 (6.84) </p>

<p>21.37 (6.19) </p>

<p>Attention </p>

<p>BTA </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15.87 (3.02) </p>

<p>17.33 (2.80) </p>

<p>18.60 (1.68) </p>

<p>17.73 (2.60) </p>

<p>19.40 (1.55) </p>

<p>18.13 (1.84) </p>

<p>Executive functions 
Working memory 
DemTect, DsB </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5.00 (4-6) </p>

<p>6.00 (4-6) </p>

<p>6.00 (4-6) </p>

<p>5.00 (3-6) </p>

<p>6.00 (4-6) </p>

<p>5.00 (3-6) </p>

<p>executive control 
TMT B/A </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>2.21 (0.73) </p>

<p>2.44 (0.89) </p>

<p>2.00 (0.68) </p>

<p>2.05 (0.65) </p>

<p>1.99 (0.52) </p>

<p>2.15 (0.66) </p>

<p>Verbal fluency 
semantic: DemTect, s/A </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>4.00 (2-4) </p>

<p>4.00 (4) </p>

<p>4.00 (4) </p>

<p>4.00 (4) </p>

<p>4.00 (4) </p>

<p>4.00 (3-4)   letter: COWA </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>37.80 (10.14) </p>

<p>49.33 (10.06) </p>

<p>46.87 (13.04) </p>

<p>44.13 (12.74) </p>

<p>49.00 (13.16) </p>

<p>51.00 (15.83) </p>

<p>Visuoconstruction </p>

<p>CFT, copy </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>36.00 (30-36) </p>

<p>36.00 (32-36) </p>

<p>36.00 (34-36) </p>

<p>36.00 (34-36) </p>

<p>36.00 (34-36) </p>

<p>36.00 (31-36) </p>

<p>Number processing 
DemTect, nT </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>4.00 (3-4) </p>

<p>4.00 (3-4) </p>

<p>4.00 (3-4) </p>

<p>4.00 (3-4) </p>

<p>4.00 (0.00) 4.00 (4-4) </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>4.00 (3-4) </p>

<p>Notes: The DemTect is from Kalbe et al. </p>

<p>23,24   CFT, BTA, TMT A and B, and COWA as described in strauss et al were used. </p>

<p>27   Significant results are highlighted in bold. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Median and range are only displayed for variables that had to be </p>

<p>analyzed with nonparametric methods. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Variable violates assumptions of normal distribution and homogeneity of variances; therefore, nonparametric statistical analysis was used. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Parallel versions were used to minimize retest effects. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>All </p>

<p>participants reached a score of 4.00 so that no variation can be reported for the range. 
Abbreviations: BTA, Brief Test of Attention; B/A, ratio of part B divided by part A; CFT, Complex Figure Test; COWA, Controlled Oral Word Association Test; CPT, cognitive training with additional physical activity; CT, cognitive </p>

<p>training; Dr, subtest delayed recall; DsB, subtest digit span backwards; Ir, subtest immediate recall; Max, maximum; n, subsample; nT, subtest number transcoding; s/A, subtest supermarket/animal; sD, standard deviation; TMT, Trail 
Making Test. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>304 </p>

<p>rahe et al </p>

<p>Figure 1 Significant interaction effect Time × Training for divided attention 
measured with BTA. 
Note: The BTA as described in strauss et al was used. </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: BTA, Brief Test of Attention; CPT, cognitive training with additional 
physical activity; CT, cognitive training. </p>

<p>Table 4 results of the post hoc tests of the within-group differences </p>

<p>Domain 
CPT n=15 
CT n=15 </p>

<p>Test value 
P 
Effect size 
Test value 
P 
Effect size </p>

<p>Cognitive state 
DemTect </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Post-pre 
z=1.99 
0.03* 
ϕ=0.51 
z=1.55 
0.07 
ϕ=0.40 
FU-pre 
z=2.69 
0.00*** 
ϕ=0.69 
z=0.31 
0.41 
ϕ=0.08 
Memory 
Verbal memory 
DemTect, Ir </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Post-pre 
z=3.43 
0.00*** 
ϕ=0.89 
z=3.25 
0.00*** 
ϕ=0.84 
FU-pre 
z=1.61 
0.07 
ϕ=0.41 
z=2.46 
0.01** 
ϕ=0.64 
DemTect, Dr </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Post-pre 
z=2.25 
0.01** 
ϕ=0.58 
z=1.35 
0.10 
ϕ=0.35 
FU-pre 
z=2.54 
0.01** 
ϕ=0.66 
z=0.98 
0.19 
ϕ=0.25 
Executive functions 
Verbal fluency 
letter: COWA </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Post-pre </p>

<p>mean </p>

<p>diff=11.53 
0.00*** 
d=2.04 </p>

<p>mean </p>

<p>diff=4.87 
0.10 
d=0.46 
FU-pre </p>

<p>mean </p>

<p>diff=9.07 
0.00*** 
d=1.21 </p>

<p>mean </p>

<p>diff=6.87 
0.02* 
d=0.66 </p>

<p>Notes: The DemTect is from Kalbe et al. 
23,24 The COWA as described in strauss et al was used. 
27 Significant results are highlighted in bold. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Wilcoxon signed-rank test 
was used to compare the training gains within the groups. The Bonferroni procedure was applied manually to prevent an inflated type I error (0.05/6 comparisons per 
group; α=0.01) for the nonparametric variables. The effect size ϕ is reported, indicating a small (ϕ.0.10), moderate (ϕ.0.30), or strong effect (ϕ.0.50). </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Post hoc pairwise 
comparisons were calculated with an overall α=0.05 after the Bonferroni correction of <rs type="software">sPss</rs>. The effect size d is reported indicating a small (d.0.10), moderate (d.0.30), or 
strong effect (d.0.50). *P#0.05; **P#0.01; ***P#0.001. 
Abbreviations: COWA, Controlled Oral Word Association Test; CPT, cognitive training with additional physical activity; CT, cognitive training; Dr, subtest delayed recall; 
FU, 1-year follow-up; Ir, subtest immediate recall; n, subsample; post, post-test; pre, pretest. </p>

<p>a descriptive level the activity level concerning moderate activ-
ity at follow-up remained increased compared to pretest. 
The Friedman's ANOVA showed that the distribution of 
the IPAQ categories changed over time (χ²=10.23[2], P=0.01, 
ω=0.83). At pretest two participants were categorized as 
mildly active, four as moderately active, and nine as highly 
active. At post-test all participants were at least moderately 
active (n=1), and most participants even highly active 
(n=14). At 1-year follow-up six participants remained highly 
active, whereas nine participants were at least moderately 
active; none of the participants could be rated as mildly active. 
Table 5 gives an overview of the results in the IPAQ. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The aim of this study was to examine whether the effects of a 
CPT are superior to those of pure CT in healthy older adults 
in the domain of executive functions. The main finding is a 
significant interaction effect in divided attention; from pre-to 
post-test both CT and CPT showed comparable gains, but 
in the follow-up period CPT led to further improvements in 
attention while the CT participants returned to the baseline 
level (see Figure 1). In other words, at first glimpse CPT 
seems to be more successful than pure CT; detailed analysis, 
however, shows that the difference in the attention effects 
occurred mainly within the time after the training until 
follow-up. In addition, we found significant within-subject 
effects of Time for overall cognitive state, executive func-
tions operationalized by a letter verbal fluency task, and 
immediate and delayed verbal memory. Post hoc analyses 
indicated that these latter domains were affected differentially 
by the two interventions (see Table 4). However, we did not 
find significant between-subject effects of Group, indicat-
ing that the training effects in several cognitive domains 
were generally comparable between groups. Therefore, our 
hypothesis that CPT is superior to pure CT in improving 
executive functions is not clearly supported. 
As the main finding was an interaction effect for atten-
tion, this domain deserves a closer look. It is important to 
note that attention is a crucial precondition for most cogni-
tive functions such as memory, information processing, 
planning, problem solving, speech, or orientation, which </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>305 </p>

<p>Cognitive training with physical activity </p>

<p>Table 5 self-reported physical activity pretest, post-test, and at 1-year follow-up of the CPT group </p>

<p>Self-reported physical activity </p>

<p>Pretest 
Post-test 
Follow-up </p>

<p>Mean (SD) 
Range 
Mean (SD) 
Range 
Mean (SD) 
Range </p>

<p>IPAQ scores in MET 
Walking 
1,821.60 (1,869.16) 
0-6,237 
1,331.00 (766.16) 
0-2,772 
1,152.80 (1,194.27) 
0-4,851 
Moderate activities 
1,804.00 (1,721.32) 
0-5,580 
3,758.40 (2,381.43) 
0-8,340 
2,160.87 (2,853.26) 
0-5,040 
Vigorous activities 
1,120.00 (1,271.40) 
0-4,080 
1,522.67 (2,059.48) 
0-6,720 
736.00 (1,297.10) 
160-10,920 
Total MeT score 
4,745.60 (3,026.15) 
319-9,642 
6,612.07 (3,404.46) 
1,782-14,073 
4,048.13 (4,289.28) 
1,089-15,021 
IPAQ categories 
n=2 mildly active 
n=4 moderately active 
n=9 highly active </p>

<p>n=1 moderately active 
n=14 highly active </p>

<p>n=9 moderately active 
n=6 highly active </p>

<p>Notes: The IPAQ is from Craig et al. 
28 One MeT corresponds to the resting metabolic rate obtained during quiet sitting. </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CPT, cognitive training with additional physical activity; IPAQ, International Physical Activity Questionnaire; MeT, metabolic equivalent; sD, standard 
deviation. </p>

<p>in turn are necessary for an independent and autonomous 
life. 
39 It is well known that attention is one cognitive func-
tion which is very aging sensitive, meaning that its decline 
is part of the normal process of cognitive aging. 
40 Therefore, 
the superiority of CPT in this domain compared to pure CT 
within the follow-up period is highly relevant for prevention 
of cognitive aging. 
When considering studies investigating the cognitive 
effects of physical activity, it is striking that effects have 
most consistently been reported not in attention, but in the 
domain of executive functions. 
7,8 At first sight, this seems 
controversial. However, when looking at details of relevant 
studies, improvements found have commonly been measured 
with tests that have vast similarity to the test that we used to 
assess attention. In more detail, these studies used inhibition 
tasks such as the Flanker task or the Stroop test. 
10,13,41 Consis-
tently, the reported effects of physical activity on executive 
functions seem to be selective for inhibition in older adults, 
but have been referred to as affecting executive functions. </p>

<p>42   The inhibition tasks used in those studies and the divided 
attention task used in our study both apply distractors which 
have to be ignored. Due to the similarity of the tasks, we can 
assume that the main result of this study is in line with those 
previous findings and that the difference lies primarily in the 
denomination of the cognitive domain (executive functions 
and attention, in this case both referring to similar cognitive 
processes). 
However, as a possible reason for the stronger effects of 
CPT, it has been assumed that physical activity might lead 
to acute improvement of brain metabolism and plasticity; 
the mentally demanding tasks of the CT might then result in 
stronger improvement by making use of the enhanced brain 
metabolism and guiding the plasticity processes. 
15,16 Look-
ing closer at the improvements in attention shown in both </p>

<p>groups of this study, our results do not entirely support this 
assumption: As can be seen in Figure 1, both groups seemed 
to show nearly comparable gains from pre-to post-test (CPT: </p>

<p>mean </p>

<p>diff=1.46 vs pure CT: mean diff=1.67), and the significant 
interaction effect seems to be mainly driven by the stronger 
improvement in the year after the training (CPT: mean diff=2.73 
vs pure CT: mean diff=0.40). The short-term gains from pre-to 
post-test in attention after both interventions can be inter-
preted as a relevant achievement of both kinds of training. 
However, with regard to the self-reported physical activity 
and the changes in the different MET scores, as well as the 
categories concerning physical activity over the three assess-
ments, we found that the pretest/post-test increase of physical 
activity induced by the CPT could be stabilized at follow-up 
on a group level. First, at baseline 2 participants were cat-
egorized as mildly active, whereas at post-test and at 1-year 
follow-up all participants were at least moderately active or 
even highly active. Second, even if the improvements in the 
MET scores from pre-to post-test in vigorous activity and 
the total MET score could not be stabilized to follow-up, at 
least for moderate activity, the raw scores indicate that even 
at follow-up moderate activities were more often performed 
by the participants than at baseline. As the main focus of the 
physical part of the CPT intervention lay on moderate activi-
ties, this result supports the efficacy of the CPT intervention to 
motivate participants to remain physically active on a moder-
ate level even after the training. Thus, we assume that due to 
the stabilization of moderate physical activity, the effect on 
attention primarily achieved through both types of interven-
tion (probably by different mechanisms) could be maintained 
and even be strengthened in the combined group. In the pure 
CT group, attention was trained and improved to post-test as 
well, but, probably because of the lack of training and physi-
cal activity afterwards, these gains could not be maintained </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>306 </p>

<p>rahe et al </p>

<p>to follow-up. However, these results imply that it was not the 
CPT training itself but the activity after the training that was 
important for the interaction effect. Therefore, we conclude 
that our data do not support the notion that CPT in itself is 
superior in improving executive functions or attention from 
pre-to post-test; however, the data do show that it could 
be useful to improve motivational variables which support 
participants in maintaining healthy lifestyle activities such 
as physical activity beyond the training period. The lack of 
significant between-subject effects of Group for attention 
strengthens the conclusion that we cannot support our supe-
riority hypothesis for CPT. However, these assumptions are 
highly speculative and should be proven in future studies. 
Therefore, individual differences in motivation should be 
assessed; eg, with personality-factor questionnaires such as 
the Neuroticism-Extraversion-Openness Five-Factor Inven-
tory. 
43 Furthermore, as our results show that the differences in 
the effects on attention were not apparent until the follow-up, 
this reinforces the need for follow-up assessments when 
investigating effects of cognitive interventions in healthy 
older adults. Recently, a randomized controlled CPT trial 
in healthy older adults with a 3-month follow-up was also 
unable to verify any superiority of CPT versus CT. 
21 Other 
recent randomized controlled trials on CPT have similarly 
failed to support the superiority hypothesis. 
19,20,22 In good 
accordance with the study by Linde and Alfermann, both 
groups in our study showed improvements in attention from 
pre-to post-test. 
21 However, contrary to the follow-up results 
of the other study, which was unable to find any significant 
long-term effects on attention of either CT or CPT, the dif-
ference between the groups became most apparent in the 
follow-up period. It may be that the lack of a multicomponent 
physical activity training led to the lack of significant long-
term effects in that study; the follow-up period of 3 months 
may also have been too short compared to 1 year to detect 
superior effects of CPT. However, Oswald et al found com-
parable long-term improvement of attention after both CT 
and CPT. 
16 Unfortunately, the intervention groups in that 
study were contrasted to a nonactive control group, while 
the direct contrast (CPT vs CT) was not analyzed. Therefore, 
our results are only partially comparable. Other studies that 
found no improvement of attention in either intervention 
group, 
18 or after pure CT but not CPT, 
19,20 did not assess 
long-term effects. Again, the lack of follow-ups might explain 
the differential effects of the interventions on attention in 
these studies. Another explanation for controversial findings 
concerning the domain of attention might be the lack of a 
multicomponent physical training in the CPT. </p>

<p>It should be noted that, next to the domain of attention, 
we found no further interaction effect of Time × Group. 
One likely reason for this is that we did not contrast the 
two intervention groups with a passive control group. Our 
study design was chosen because it has already been dem-
onstrated that both CT and CPT are effective in improving 
cognitive functions in healthy older adults. 
3,5,16-18 It is likely 
that differences between these effects would have been too 
small to result in further significant interaction effects in the 
overall analysis. Furthermore, the small sample size of this 
study might have led to an underestimation of interaction 
effects. Some variables (overall cognitive state, immediate 
and delayed verbal memory) also had to be estimated with 
nonparametric analysis, such that no interaction effects could 
be calculated. However, as interaction effects include both the 
effects of Time and of Training, the nonparametric analyses 
should have shown differences in both these categories. We 
found only Time effects, which indicates that there were 
changes over the three assessments; the lack of group dif-
ferences also supports the assumption, however, that these 
changes were comparable between the groups. 
Still, the analyses within the intervention groups are 
interesting as well, because they reveal significant within-
subject effects of Time for several domains, including overall 
cognitive state, immediate and delayed verbal memory, and 
executive functions operationalized by a letter verbal fluency 
task. The post hoc comparisons indicated differential patterns 
of CT gains within the two intervention groups for these lat-
ter domains: We found significant short-term improvement 
of letter verbal fluency, significant long-term improvement 
of overall cognitive state, and significant short-and long-
term improvement of delayed verbal memory exclusively 
in the CPT group, compared to a long-term improvement of 
immediate verbal memory only in the pure CT group. This 
unique long-term improvement of immediate verbal memory 
of the pure CT points to the fact that at least the effects of 
the interventions on memory might need to be regarded in a 
more differentiated way. 
The significant long-term gain in overall cognitive state 
after CPT but not CT is in part in line with two other stud-
ies, in which stronger improvement after CPT in composite 
scores of cognitive functions were reported. 
16,17 In contrast, 
other studies have reported no differences between the inter-
vention groups in their composite score. 
19 Unfortunately, the 
composite scores are not identical, as different subtests were 
integrated in the different trials. Beyond that, the results of 
the present study indicate that different training forms may 
enhance cognitive processes in multiple domains. When, for </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>307 </p>

<p>Cognitive training with physical activity </p>

<p>example, tests for executive functions, attention, and 
memory are integrated in a composite score, the differential 
effects may be masked. Therefore, in future investigations 
the effects on individual tests rather than composite scores 
should be reported. 
Both training groups improved significantly in immediate 
verbal memory performance directly after training, but only 
after CT was this improvement maintained. The short-term 
result supports the findings of another study that found no 
differences between the groups in verbal memory gains. </p>

<p>19   However, at follow-up, we found a trend for difference 
in immediate verbal memory between groups (DemTect, 
immediate recall: H[1]=3.64, P=0.06, ϕ=0.67). This might 
have been because of the fact that in pure CT, the participants 
had 20 minutes more to train memory tasks, to learn about 
memory functions, and to practice the mnemonic strategies 
more intensively (see Table 1). Therefore, one might specu-
late that in our investigation the newly learned mnemonic 
strategies stood an increased chance of being retained in the 
cognitive health behavior repertoire of the CT participants 
after the training. Unfortunately, the use of strategies until 
follow-up was not recorded, which leaves this assumption 
speculative. A question also remains as to why no significant 
short-or long-term improvement after CT was observed in 
the delayed verbal memory recall condition compared to after 
CPT. It has to be emphasized that the CT group showed a 
nonsignificant improvement directly after training (DemTect, 
delayed recall: z=-1.35, P=0.10, ϕ=0.35) that was main-
tained until follow-up (z=-0.98, P=0.19, ϕ=0.25). A lack 
of power due to the small sample size may explain the non-
significant improvement after CT. Contrary to our findings, 
Shatil reported an improvement in long-term memory only 
after CT. 
20 However, others have found significant improve-
ment after CPT in other memory tasks; eg, word-association 
tasks or logical memory immediate recall tasks. 
16-18 Future 
studies will have to further investigate the differential effects 
of CT and CPT on memory. 
It should be noted that our results on memory functions 
could, at least in principle, result from retest effects. How-
ever, the differential mnestic pattern of CPT vs CT speaks 
against this notion. In addition, the used DemTect test has a 
high retest reliability (after 6 months retest effects comprised 
only 0.40 points of the total score of 18); we also used par-
allel forms to minimize retest effects. 
23,25 Compared to the 
retest effect of 0.40 points in a comparable but nontrained 
sample of healthy older adults, in our study CPT improved 
DemTect total scores by about 1.07 from pre-to post-test 
and about 1.67 from pretest to follow-up; CT improved </p>

<p>DemTect total scores by about 0.80 from pre-to post-test 
and about 0.20 from pretest to follow-up. These changes are 
substantially higher than the retest effects in the comparable 
sample without training. Therefore, retest effects are unlikely 
to explain our results. 
Contrary to other studies, which were unable to report 
an effect on executive functions in terms of improvement in 
verbal fluency tasks, 
16 or did not find a difference between 
intervention groups, 
19 in this study CPT led to significant 
short-and long-term improvement in verbal letter fluency 
compared to CT, which only improved significantly by 
follow-up. Possibly, the lack of multicomponent physical 
activity and multidomain CT in these other studies might 
explain the controversial results. Due to the lack of a pas-
sive control group in this trial, again one might argue that 
the follow-up improvement could result from a retest effect. 
However, the significant improvement of CPT directly after 
the training, but not of CT, does not support this notion. 
Furthermore, at follow-up the gain of the combined group 
slightly declined, but still remained significant compared 
to the baseline. Therefore, we interpret this result, albeit 
with caution, to be in line with the often-reported short-
term effects of physical activity interventions on executive 
functions. 
Some limitations have to be taken into account when 
interpreting the results of our study. First of all, by necessity 
of the design of this study, we conducted a controlled but not 
randomized trial, and research assistants were not blinded 
to the training groups. Nevertheless, the effect of this lack 
of randomization should be minimal, if it is present at all, 
as (i) no significant baseline differences between the groups 
were found, as participants were matched for age, education, 
and sex, (ii) recruitment strategies were comparable, and 
(iii) all participants were assessed by members of the same 
working group of experienced neuropsychologists trained 
intensively in test application and scoring. Furthermore, the 
main result is in line with existing evidence. However, the 
baseline comparison of education came close to significance, 
with P=0.08. We matched participants for age and educa-
tion, but with the focus on age as this seems to be the most 
important variable influencing cognitive functions. Due to 
different education ranges in CT and CPT (see Table 2), we 
recalculated the ANOVAs with education as a covariate. 
The results did not differ from the reported findings (the 
interaction effect for the BTA was still significant), and we 
therefore abandoned this option to report the parametric 
analyses with education as a covariate and the nonparamet-
ric without education as a covariate. We thus assume that </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>308 </p>

<p>rahe et al </p>

<p>the reported effects are robust and can be assigned to real 
training effects. 
A second limitation is that groups were only matched 
regarding age, education, and sex -some other variables 
which might induce training effects were not considered 
in the matching (eg, general health status). However, as all 
participants were healthy older adults and any neurological 
or psychiatric disease would have led to exclusion from the 
study, we are convinced that the influence of health status or 
medication on cognition is minimal if not nonexistent in our 
sample. In addition, the IPAQ was performed solely in the 
CPT group, so that the level of physical activity was known 
for the CPT participants only. The level of physical activity 
might have had an influence on the CT effects; therefore, 
future studies on CPT should control for baseline differences 
in physical fitness. 
A third limitation could be that the sample may have been 
biased: Participants were highly educated and constituted 
an active group of older adults who were eager enough to 
maintain participation until post-test and follow-up exami-
nation. Participants who had not completed all three assess-
ments were excluded because the missing values would have 
caused problems in the statistical analyses; estimated values 
would not have been appropriate due to our sample size. 
However, we compared completers and drop-outs and did 
not find significant differences concerning age, education, or 
cognitive status, indicating that such sample characteristics 
were unlikely to bias our results. Unfortunately, selectivity 
concerning education and active style of living appears to 
be a more general problem that affects most interventional 
studies in healthy adults, as participation is always voluntary 
and it can be expected that volunteers differ, for example 
in motivation. 
16 Thus, although it must be emphasized that 
conclusions can only be drawn for this probably biased group 
of participants, we are convinced that these conclusions pro-
vide important information, as our study sample represents a 
typical target group for these types of intervention. 
Due to the small sample size, only limited power could 
be achieved in some comparisons. This may have led to an 
underestimation of interaction effects, as power analyses 
indicated a power of only 20% to detect small interaction 
effects. However, the detection rate of moderate to strong 
interaction effects was 85% to 99%. Also, due to the study 
design the achieved power could only be estimated with 
a post hoc analysis, rather than an a priori power calcula-
tion. In future studies, a priori power calculations should 
be used to plan appropriate sample sizes. Additionally, as 
the assumptions of normal distribution and homogeneity of </p>

<p>variances were violated for some variables, it was neces-
sary to use nonparametric analysis in these cases, so that 
no interaction effects could be tested for the domains of 
overall cognitive state and verbal memory. The post hoc 
analyses of the significant within-subjects effects of Time 
enabled a comparison of the improved domains within the 
two intervention groups, but no direct comparison could 
be made, and therefore no conclusion can be drawn about 
the relative strengths of the effects of the interventions for 
these domains. Therefore, future studies with larger sample 
sizes and complete randomization should aim to confirm the 
found differential improvement patterns of CPT vs pure CT 
with appropriate statistical analyses. 
Although no significant difference was observed between 
the groups at baseline, the CPT group started with slightly 
worse baseline scores in nearly all cognitive tests compared 
to pure CT. Even if none of the differences at baseline was 
significant, one could argue that participants with lower 
initial scores had a greater chance to improve in a cognitive 
domain. Post hoc analyses showed that the improvement was 
negatively correlated with baseline performance in the cor-
responding domain (all P#0.05). In other words, participants 
with a lower baseline score showed a stronger improvement 
in these domains. It has already been discussed that the lower 
range of a high-functioning sample can be improved more. </p>

<p>44   But on the contrary, other studies have reported that higher 
baseline scores were found to be predictive for maintaining 
benefits of memory training. 
45 This merits further investiga-
tion, and predictor analysis will be useful here. Also, the CPT 
and the pure CT were considered as comparable concerning 
training duration, frequency, and intensity, though the com-
bined group received one additional session of 90 minutes 
on the topic Physical activity and nutrition. However, in our 
view, the difference between CPT and CT in this study is 
minimal compared to other investigations in which (i) training 
sessions were doubled by implementing both cognitive and 
physical training in the combined group 
20-22 or (ii) additional 
training was compensated through additional social contact 
in the noncombined groups. 
16,17 In future studies, the total 
amount of interventions should be equal across groups. 
The level of physical activity was assessed only with 
the IPAQ, a self-reported physical-activity questionnaire 
which refers to physical activity only during the last week. 
In future studies, the activity level should be assessed with 
objective measures, such as maximum oxygen consumption, 
an ergometer test (eg, Physical Work Capacity) or a Rockport 
Walking Test. 
46 Furthermore, participants were encouraged 
to engage in additional physical activity (next to the training) </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>309 </p>

<p>Cognitive training with physical activity </p>

<p>strategies appear promising, as it might target more aspects 
of the complex assembly of protective and risk factors asso-
ciated with cognitive aging. 
14,15 Future studies on combined 
intervention approaches will have to prove these assumptions 
and investigate the underlying biological mechanisms. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This research was conducted at the University of Vechta und 
the University Hospital of Cologne, and supported by budget 
resources of these institutions. We thank all participants for 
their interest in the study, as well as Jennifer Liesk, Johanna 
Henschel, Ann-Kristin Folkerts, Annabell Zink, and Katrin 
Müller for their help with data collection. Furthermore, we 
gratefully acknowledge the support of Anette Herlitzius and 
Ulrich Freisel of the Senior Service Office in Osnabrück, 
Germany. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>J Rahe, A Petrelli, S Kaesberg, E Kalbe, and J Kessler are 
authors of the forthcoming NEUROvitalis Plus program. 
S Kaesberg, E Kalbe, and J Kessler are authors of the NEU-
ROvitalis program. The authors report no other conflicts of 
interest in this work. </p>



<p>in their leisure time, but this was not controlled for time and 
intensity. Future studies should address this point as well. 
Finally, as the CPT provided an additional session about 
the topic Physical activity and nutrition, where the partici-
pants received information about physical activity as well 
as healthy nutrition, the found superior effect of CPT on 
attention might not solely be attributed to additional physical 
activity but could also be influenced by nutritional aspects. 
Further research is needed to investigate which components 
of comparable combined interventions drive improvement. 
To our knowledge, this is the first study to use CPT 
that targets both multiple cognitive domains and multiple 
physical fitness components, as has been recommended. 
Further strengths are that the CPT and the contrasted pure 
CT were widely comparable in duration, frequency, and 
intensity. Additionally, this is one of the first investigations 
to assess not only short-term but also long-term effects of 
the interventions, and participants in the pure CT and the 
CPT groups were matched for age, education, and sex to 
minimize confounding effects. Importantly, with regard 
to the length of training, it has recently been argued that at 
least 2 months of a combined intervention are necessary to 
improve cognitive functions. 
14 To our knowledge, this is the 
first study to report cognitive benefits of CPT of even shorter 
duration (6.5 weeks). The issue of duration is important when 
considering the cost-effectiveness of interventions, but also 
relates to the participants' adherence to the program. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In conclusion, our hypothesis that CPT would lead to stronger 
improvements of executive functions compared to pure CT 
cannot be verified. The significant interaction effect for atten-
tion does not clearly support the superiority of CPT, either, 
as the main difference between groups became apparent only 
in the follow-up period. Other factors, such as motivation to 
engage in a healthy and physically active lifestyle after the 
training, might explain this result, and will have to be inves-
tigated in future studies. Significant within-subject effects 
of Time for overall cognitive state, immediate and delayed 
verbal memory, and executive functions operationalized by 
a verbal letter fluency task were found, and post hoc analyses 
indicated that these latter domains were affected differentially 
by CPT and pure CT. 
Thus, both CPT and pure CT seem to improve cognitive 
function and can both be regarded as useful, inexpensive, and 
easily accessible preventive tools against aging-associated 
cognitive decline in healthy older adults. At least the effect 
on attention makes the combination of different prevention </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/clinical-interventions-in-aging-journal </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging is an international, peer-reviewed journal 
focusing on evidence-based reports on the value or lack thereof of treatments 
intended to prevent or delay the onset of maladaptive correlates of aging 
in human beings. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, MedLine, </p>

<p>CAS, Scopus and the Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The manuscript 
management system is completely online and includes a very quick and fair 
peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress. 
com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>310 </p>

<p>rahe et al </p>



</text></tei>