<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4184560" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Objective: Congenital cytomegalovirus (CMV) infection is the leading viral 
cause of neurodevelopmental disorders in humans, with the most severe and 
permanent sequelae being those affecting the cerebrum. As the fetal immune 
reactions to congenital CMV infection in the brain and their effects on cerebral 
development remain elusive, our aim was to investigate primitive innate immu-
nity to CMV infection and its effects on cerebral corticogenesis in a mouse 
model for congenital CMV infection using a precise intraplacental inoculation 
method. Methods: At 13.5 embryonic days (E13.5), pregnant C57BL/6 mice 
were intraplacentally infected with murine CMV (MCMV). Placentas and fetal 
organs were collected at 1, 3, and 5 days postinfection and analyzed. Results: 
MCMV antigens were found frequently in perivascular macrophages, and subse-
quently in neural stem/progenitor cells (NSPCs). With increased expression 
of inducible nitric oxide synthase and proinflammatory cytokines, activated 
macrophages infiltrated into the infectious foci. In addition to the infected area, 
the numbers of both meningeal macrophages and parenchymal microglia 
increased even in the uninfected areas of MCMV-infected brain due to recruit-
ment of their precursors from other sites. A bromodeoxyuridine (BrdU) incor-
poration experiment demonstrated that MCMV infection globally disrupted the 
self-renewal of NSPCs. Furthermore, BrdU-labeled neurons, particularly Brn2 + 
neurons of upper layers II/III in the cortical plate, decreased in number signifi-
cantly in the MCMV-infected E18.5 cerebrum. Interpretation: Brain macro-
phages are crucial for innate immunity during MCMV infection in the fetal 
brain, while their aberrant recruitment and activation may adversely impact on 
the stemness of NSPCs, resulting in neurodevelopmental disorders. </p>

<p>Intrauterine infection with cytomegalovirus (CMV) is the 
leading viral cause of developmental disorders of the 
central nervous system (CNS) in humans, 1,2 and more 
frequently causes disabilities than do other well-known 
childhood disorders, such as Down syndrome. 3 Although 
human CMV (HCMV) can infect multiple organs, the 
most severe and permanent sequelae after congenital 
infection are those affecting the cerebrum, such as 
microcephaly, epilepsy, and mental retardation. 4-7 These </p>

<p>sequelae are found more frequently in infants infected 
during the first trimester, a critical period for cerebral 
corticogenesis, 8 than in those infected during the later 
trimesters. 9 In cerebral corticogenesis, neural stem/pro-
genitor cells (NSPCs) of the ventricular and subventricu-
lar zone (VZ and SVZ) generate the cerebral cortex 
through their "stemness"; that is, through their prolifera-
tion, migration, and differentiation. 10 Therefore, congeni-
tal HCMV infection can be a teratogenic factor for 
cortical malformations that result in the abovementioned 
sequelae. </p>

<p>570 </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and 
distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>In terms of the direct teratogenic action of CMV, previ-
ous in vitro studies have clearly demonstrated that murine 
and human NSPCs infected with murine CMV (MCMV) 
and HCMV, respectively, lose their stemness. 11-13 
Although growing evidence indicates that inflammatory 
reactions triggered by infectious agents have serious 
impacts on immature developing brains and are possibly 
related to brain malformations and neurodevelopmental 
disorders, 14-17 most of the evidence is based on studies 
using bacterial and viral mimics, such as lipopolysaccha-
ride and polyinocinic-polycytidylic acid. 14,17 In other 
words, fetal immune reactions to neuroinvasion with a live 
virus and the influence of the immune reactions on cere-
bral corticogenesis have not yet been well investigated. 18 
Although studies on human subjects have obvious limi-
tations, and while CMV has strict species specificity, in 
vivo model systems using mouse embryos and neonates 
infected with MCMV have nevertheless shed light on the 
neuropathogenesis of congenital CMV infection. 19,20 Pre-
viously, we developed a mouse model of intraplacental 
MCMV infection to simulate transplacental HCMV infec-
tion and to investigate CMV neuropathogenesis. 21 In this 
model, neonatal mice infected with MCMV in utero 
exhibited growth retardation and microcephaly in a fash-
ion similar to that observed in association with congenital 
CMV infection in humans. However, there have been 
no precise pathological or immunological analyses of 
the effects of congenital CMV infection on fetal brain 
development. 
In this study, by using a fine glass micropipette, we 
improved the accuracy of the intraplacental inoculation 
with MCMV and made the inoculation process less inva-
sive. The model allowed us to show the transmission of 
MCMV from placenta to fetal brain as well as the fetal 
innate immune responses, including macrophage/microg-
lial reactions, and their impact on cerebral corticogenesis. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Ethical statement </p>

<p>This study was approved by the Animal Care and Use 
Committee of Hamamatsu University School of Medicine. 
All animal experiments were performed in accordance 
with the "Guidelines for Animal Experiments of Ham-
amatsu University School of Medicine." All surgery was 
performed under anesthesia, and all efforts were made to 
minimize suffering. </p>

<p>Virus, cells, and plaque assay </p>

<p>The wild-type Smith strain of MCMV, MCMV-Smith, 
which had been passaged in mouse embryonic fibroblasts, </p>

<p>was provided by Dr. Y Minamishima (Miyazaki, Japan). 
Construction of MCMV-EGFP, MCMV expressing 
enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP) under the 
control of the MCMV e1 promoter, was described previ-
ously. 22 MCMV-EGFP and MCMV-Smith showed similar 
viral growth, latency, and pathogenesis. 23 Mouse embry-
onic fibroblasts were prepared from 12.5-day-old embryos 
(E12.5) of BALB/c mice (SLC Japan, Hamamatsu, Japan), 
and were grown in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's essential 
medium (DMEM) containing penicillin (100 U/mL), 
streptomycin (50 lg/mL), and 10% fetal bovine serum. 
Viral titers were determined by a plaque assay using 
mouse embryonic fibroblasts monolayers as described 
previously. 24 Ultraviolet light (UV)-inactivated MCMV 
that neither replicates nor produces any detectable level 
of the IE1 protein was used as a mock control. </p>

<p>Intraplacental MCMV infection </p>

<p>Inbred specific pathogen-free pregnant C57BL/6 female 
mice were purchased from SLC Japan. All mice were 
housed under specific pathogen-free conditions. Pregnant 
mice were randomly divided into two groups: the 
MCMV-and mock-infected groups. MCMV inoculation 
to the placenta was performed via a fine glass micropi-
pette with a diameter of 40 lm (Fig. 1A), which was 
made from a borosilicate glass capillary (No. 30-0019, 
1.0 mm O.D. 9 0.58 mm I.D., Harvard Apparatus, Holl-
iston, MA) using a micropipette puller (Model P-97; Sut-
ter Instrument Company, Novato, CA), as described for 
transient delivery of serotonin into the placenta. 25 In the 
MCMV-infected group, 1 9 10 5 plaque-forming unit 
(PFU) of MCMV-Smith or MCMV-EGFP in 1 lL of 
DMEM was injected through the uterine wall into the 
labyrinth region in the placenta. In the mock-infected 
group, UV-inactivated MCMV virus in 1 lL of DMEM 
was injected into the placenta in the same way. All 
surgical procedures were performed under anesthesia 
induced by an intraperitoneal injection of 0.2-0.3 mL of 
6.5 mg/mL sodium pentobarbital. Fetuses were surgically 
collected at the indicated number of days postinfection 
(dpi), and the number of live fetuses and dead fetuses 
were counted, followed by the weighing of the fetuses, 
placentas, and brains. The placenta, brain, heart, and liver 
were stored at À80°C and used for plaque assays, real-
time polymerase chain reaction (PCR), and real-time 
reverse transcriptase PCR (RT-PCR). For immunohisto-
chemical analysis and in situ hybridization, the brains 
were fixed by perfusion with 4% paraformaldehyde 
(PFA), removed, immersed in 20% sucrose, and quickly 
frozen in liquid nitrogen. Coronal sections were cut with 
a cryostat at 12 lm, air dried, and then stored at À80°C. 
Some of the infected brains were frozen in liquid nitrogen </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. 
Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV </p>

<p>without fixation with PFA, serially cut, then fixed in iso-
propyl alcohol, and stored at À80°C. For the labeling of 
proliferating cells, a number of pregnant mice were intra-
peritoneally injected with bromodeoxyuridine (BrdU, 
50 mg/kg; Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO). </p>

<p>Real-time PCR for quantification of the 
MCMV copy number </p>

<p>DNA was extracted from tissue homogenates with Trizol 
(Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) according to the manufac-
turer's protocol. All real-time PCRs were performed using 
TaqMan Gene Expression Master Mix in an ABI7500 Fast 
System using the standard curve (absolute quantitation) 
assay (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). One hundred </p>

<p>ng of DNA was added as template DNA to a reaction 
mixture that contained 29 TaqMan Reaction Mixture, 
900 nmol/L primers, and 250 nmol/L TaqMan MGB 
probe. The MCMV genome was quantified by amplifica-
tion of the major immediate-early promoter (MIEP) gene 
using the primers 5 0 -GGTGGTCAGACCGAAGACT and 
5 0 -GCTGAGCTGCGTTCTACGT, and the probe 5 0 -FAM-
CTGGTCGCGCCTCTTA. 26 As a cellular gene, the b-actin 
gene was quantified using primers 5 0 -CGTTCCGAAAG 
TTGCCTTTTA, 5-0 GCCGCCGGGTTTTATAGG, and the 
probe 5 0 -FAM-CTCGAGTGGCCGCTG. The thermal 
cycling conditions were one cycle at 50°C for 2 min and 
at 95°C for 10 min followed by 50 cycles of 95°C for 
15 sec and 60°C for 1 min. Serial dilutions of pSM3fr 
bacterial artificial chromosome (BAC) containing the </p>

<p>Figure 1. Intraplacental MCMV infection and development of MCMV-infected fetuses. (A) Inoculation procedure during surgery. The arrowhead 
and arrow indicate the glass micropipette for injection and the labyrinth region in the placenta, respectively. (B) Survival rates of fetuses infected 
with MCMV at E13.5 and infection rates of their brains. (C) Fluorescence stereomicroscopic views of MCMV-EGFP infectious foci at 3 dpi in a 
fetus, its brain, and placenta. A magnified view of an infectious focus in the fetus is also shown in the inner panel. The fluorescence images of 
brain and placenta were superimposed on their bright field images. The arrowhead in the image of the placenta indicates the injection site. Fetal 
body, scale bar = 2 mm. Brain and placenta, scale bar = 1 mm. (D) Weights of the fetal body, brain, and placenta at E18.5 (5 dpi). 
Mean AE standard error of mean (SEM) are shown. *P &lt; 0.05 compared with mock-infected mice. MCMV, murine cytomegalovirus; EGFP, 
enhanced green fluorescent protein. </p>



<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV 
M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. </p>

<p>MCMV whole genome, which was kindly provided by 
Dr. UH Koszinowski (Munich, Germany), 27 were used as 
the quantification standard for MCMV. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Mouse monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) specific for the 
MCMV-IE1 nuclear antigen (Ag) (1:2000, kindly provided 
by Dr. S Jonjic, Rijeka, Croatia) 28 and the MCMV-E1 
nuclear Ag (1:5) 29 were used for detection of MCMV-
infected cells. 
For immunoperoxidase staining, after microwave treat-
ment, fetal brain sections were reacted with anti-IE1 mAb 
and then with horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated 
goat anti-mouse IgG polyclonal antibody (pAb) (N-Histo-
fine simple stain mouse MAX PO; Nichirei Bioscience, 
Tokyo, Japan), and colored with 3,3-diaminobenzidine 
tetrahydrochloride (DAB). 
For immunofluorescence staining, in addition to mAb 
for MCMV-Ag, the following primary antibodies were 
used: inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS, rabbit pAb, 
1:100; Abcam, Cambridge, UK), BrdU (rat mAb, 1:200; 
Abcam), Brn2 (goat pAb, 1:100; Santa Cruz, Dallas, TX), 
Tbr1 (rabbit pAb, 1:100; Chemicon, Billerica, MA), Iba-1 
(rabbit pAb, 1:500, Wako, Osaka, Japan), SOX2 (rabbit 
pAb, 1:200; MBL, Nagoya, Japan), F4/80 (rat mAb, 1:20; 
AbD Serotec, Oxford, UK), CD45 (rabbit pAb, 1:100; 
Abcam), major histocopatibility complex (MHC) class II 
(rat mAb, 1:100; BioLegend, San Diego, CA), CD31 (rab-
bit pAb, 1:50; Abcam), and NG2 (rabbit pAb, 1:200; Mil-
lipore, Billerica, MA). The following secondary antibodies 
were also used: Alexa Fluor 488 anti-mouse IgG1 or 
IgG2a, Alexa Fluor 546 anti-rabbit, -rat, or -goat IgG, or 
Alexa Fluor 647 anti-rabbit IgG (Invitrogen). Nuclei were 
stained with 4 0 ,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole, dihydrochlo-
ride (DAPI) (Sigma-Aldrich). For BrdU staining, sections 
were incubated in 2 N HCl followed by 0.1 mol/L sodium 
borate after microwave treatment. 
Confocal images were captured using an <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Olympus</rs> 
FV1000 microscope with the latest <rs id="software-0" type="software">Fluoview</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Ver.3.1</rs> (Olympus, Tokyo, Japan). A stack of five images from 
0.5-lm step slices was combined for the analysis. At least 
three different animals in each group were used for the 
analysis, and sections from three fields in each brain were 
evaluated. </p>

<p>In situ hybridization for MCMV DNA 
detection </p>

<p>Using the PFA-fixed sections adjacent to the sections used 
for immunostaining, chromogenic in situ hybridization 
was performed for the detection of MCMV DNA as 
described previously. 30 The DNA probe was made from </p>

<p>pSM3fr BAC labeled with digoxigenin (DIG)-11-dUTP 
using a nick translation kit (Roche, Mannheim, Ger-
many). After hybridization, the sections were subsequently 
incubated with HRP-conjugated anti-DIG Fab fragments 
(1:100; Roche) and colored with DAB, followed by hema-
toxylin counterstaining. </p>

<p>Flow cytometry </p>

<p>At 3 and 5 dpi, mock-and MCMV-EGFP-infected fetuses 
were perfused through the left cardiac ventricle with 
5 mL of ice-cold phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), con-
taining 2 U/mL heparin. Each cerebrum with meninges 
and the choroid plexus was minced into small fragments 
and then incubated in the presence of 25 U/mL DNase I 
and 0.01% collagenase II at 37°C for 30 min. The cells 
were filtered through a nylon screen (70 lm; BD Biosci-
ence, San Diego, CA) to remove cell aggregates, centri-
fuged, and then twice washed with RPMI 1640 medium. 
The cells were incubated with antibodies against CD45-
APC (1:100), CD11b-PE/Cy7 (1:100), NK1.1-APC/Cy7 
(1:20), Ly-6G/Ly-6C (Gr1)-PacificBlue (1:50), Cd45R/ 
B220-PerCP/Cy5.5 (1:100), and CD3-Alexa Flour 700 
(1:100) (BioLegend) for 30 min. After collection, rinsing 
with RPMI 1640 and filtration through a nylon screen 
(40 lm), the cells were sorted and analyzed on a FACSA-
ria system (BD Bioscience). Isotype antibodies were used 
as controls. 
To sort the mononuclear cells from each cerebrum 
with meninges, cells were stained with a combination of 
CD45-APC and CD11b-PE/Cy7, and then separated into 
CD45 high /CD11b + (isolated cell numbers: 10,835 AE 5593 
cells in the mock-infected brain at 5 dpi, n = 6; 
15,000 AE 0 cells in the MCMV-infected brain at 5 dpi, 
n = 4), CD45 low /CD11b + (14,314 AE 6408 cells in the </p>

<p>mock-infected brain at 5 dpi, n = 6; 15,520 AE 1804 cells 
in the MCMV-infected brain at 5 dpi, n = 4), CD45 high / 
CD11b + (1235 AE 286.0 cells in the mock-infected brain 
at 5 dpi, n = 6; 1541 AE 234 cells in the MCMV-infected 
brain at 5 dpi, n = 4), and CD45 low /CD11b + populations 
(cell sorting was stopped at 100,000 cells in both the 
mock-and MCMV-infected brains). The sorted cellular 
populations were stored at À80°C in Trizol and used later 
for RNA isolation. </p>

<p>Real-time RT-PCR for quantification of 
mRNA expression of inflammatory 
mediators </p>

<p>Total RNA was isolated from the frozen samples, purified 
with an RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) and 
treated with RNase-free DNase I (Qiagen), according to 
the manufacturer's instructions. One hundred nanograms </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. 
Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV </p>

<p>of cDNA synthesized using a SuperScript III First Strand 
Synthesis kit with random primers (Invitrogen) was used 
for each PCR reaction. TaqMan assay mixtures for IL-1b 
(Mm00434228), INF-a4 (Mm00833969), INF-b1 (Mm00 
439552), IL-10 (Mm00439614), and monocyte chemotac-
tic protein-1 (MCP-1)/chemokine (C-C motif) ligand 2 
(CCL2) (Mm00441242) were obtained from Applied 
Biosystems. The following primer pairs and probes were 
synthesized commercially (Sigma-Aldrich): iNOS, 5 0 -CA 
GCTGGGCTGTACAAACCTT, 5 0 -CATTGGAAGTGAAGC 
GTTTCG, and 5 0 -FAM-CGGGCAGCCTGTGAGACCTTT 
GA; IL-1b, 5 0 -CAACCAACAAGTGATATTCTCCATG, 5 0 -
GATCCACACTCTCCAGCTGCA, and 5 0 -FAM-CTGTGT 
AATGAAAGACGGCACACCCACC; TNF-a, 5 0 -CATCTTC 
TCAAAATTCGAGTGCAA, 5 0 -TGGGAGTAGACAAGGTA 
CAACCC, 5 0 -FAM-CACGTCGTAGCAAACCACCAAGTG 
GA; IL-6, 5 0 -GAGGATACCACTCCCAACAGACC, 5 0 -AAG 
TGCATCATCGTTGTTCATACA, and 5 0 -FAM-CAGAATT 
GCCATTGCACAACTCTTTTCTCA; INF-c, 5 0 -TCAAGTG 
GCATAGATGTGGAAGAA, 5 0 -TGGCTCTGCAGGATTTT 
CATG, and 5 0 -FAM-TCACCATCCTTTTGCCAGTTCCTC 
CAG; glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAP-
DH), 5 0 -TCACCACCATGGAGAAGGC, 5 0 -GCTAAGCAG 
TTGGTGGTGCA, and 5 0 -FAM-ATGCCCCCATGTTTGT 
GATGGGTGT. 
Real-time PCR was performed using the StepOne Plus 
System (Applied Biosystems). The GAPDH housekeeping 
gene was used as a control for all experiments. The GAP-
DH expression level from the mock-infected animals was 
taken as 1 and the gene expression levels of the target 
genes were expressed as relative values. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Numerical results were expressed as the mean AE standard 
error of mean (SEM) obtained from at least three inde-
pendent experiments. Statistical analysis was performed 
using an unpaired two-tailed Student's t-test. Probability 
values (P) &lt;0.05 were considered to be significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Establishment of a congenital infection 
model using intraplacental MCMV 
inoculation </p>

<p>As described in the Materials and Methods section, all 
pregnant C57BL/6 mice were treated surgically and intra-
placentally infected with 1 9 10 5 PFU of MCMV, mock 
infected, or inoculated with DMEM using a fine glass 
micropipette (Fig. 1A). In the first set of mice, inocula-
tion with MCMV-Smith was performed at E11.5, E12.5, 
and E13.5, and the fetuses were collected at 3 dpi. The </p>

<p>survival rates of the fetuses in dams infected with 
MCMV-Smith were 25% (2/8), 35% (13/37), and 67% 
(10/15) at E11.5, E12.5, and E13.5, respectively. Those in 
dams infected with UV-inactivated virus (mock infected) 
were 50% (10/20), 63% (10/16), and 89% (8/9) at E11.5, 
E12.5, and E13.5, respectively. Similar results were 
obtained using dams that had undergone a similar surgi-
cal procedure but were inoculated with DMEM. There-
fore, it is likely that fetuses at E11.5 and E12.5 do not 
readily develop in utero after surgery, and fetuses at E13.5 
were used for the subsequent studies. 
Next, pregnant mice were infected intraplacentally at 
E13.5 as described above, and the fetuses were collected 
at 1, 3, and 5 dpi. Although the survival rates of the 
fetuses gradually decreased, the infection rates (the detec-
tion limit was 1 viral DNA copy/million cells) in the 
brains were 30-40% (Fig. 1B). Amplification by PCR did 
not reveal any MCMV genomic DNA in the placentas or 
brains of the mock-infected fetuses. 
Pregnant mice were also infected intraplacentally with 
MCMV-EGFP, MCMV expressing EGFP during the viral 
replicative cycle, as we previously demonstrated that 
MCMV-EGFP grows in the same way as MCMV-Smith. 23 
Fluorescence stereomicroscopic views of the placentas and 
fetuses at 3 dpi demonstrated multiple infectious foci, 
consisting of infected cells in a "green mirror ball" 
arrangement, in the fetal body surface, fetal brain, and 
placenta (Fig. 1C). Although the body weight of the 
MCMV-EGFP-infected fetuses at 5 dpi was 15% less than 
that of mock-infected fetuses (Fig. 1D), both mock-and 
MCMV-infected mice had no macroscopic morphological 
abnormalities and no significant differences in the 
weight of the placenta and brain were observed at any 
time points. </p>

<p>Dynamics of MCMV infection and 
distribution of MCMV-infected cells in the 
fetal cerebrum </p>

<p>The viral titers of MCMV-Smith in the placenta peaked 
at 3 dpi, while the titers in the other organs increased 
until 5 dpi (Fig. 2A). The viral DNA copy numbers in all 
organs increased in parallel (Fig. 2B). Viral loads in the 
placenta, liver, and heart exceeded those in the brain, sug-
gesting that MCMV replication in the placenta and 
peripheral organs preceded viral spread to the brain. As 
there were no substantial differences in the viral titer 
kinetics and DNA copy numbers between the wild-type 
MCMV-Smith and MCMV-EGFP even in this study (data 
not shown), all further experiments were performed using 
MCMV-EGFP. 
MCMV-antigen (Ag) + cells in the serial sections pre-
pared from more than 30 MCMV-infected fetal cerebra at </p>



<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV 
M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. </p>

<p>each time point were detected using monoclonal antibod-
ies (mAbs) against the MCMV IE1 nuclear protein, the 
antigen expressed immediately after viral infection, and 
against the E1 protein, the antigen expressed only during 
the viral productive phase. As immunohistological stain-
ing with both antibodies yielded the same images of 
MCMV-infected cells in the fetal cerebra, we describe 
these as "MCMV-Ag + cells" hereafter. MCMV-Ag + cells 
were found most frequently in the meninges, and then 
focally in the periventricular area surrounding the lateral 
ventricles, the third ventricle, and the cerebral aqueduct 
of the cerebral parenchyma (Fig. 2C and D). There were 
no significant differences in the numbers or distribution 
of the MCMV-Ag + cells in the brains at 3 and at 5 dpi 
(Fig. 2C). Signals obtained in the in situ hybridization </p>

<p>assay for detection of replicated viral DNA corresponded 
to MCMV-Ag + cells identified in the adjacent section 
(Fig. 2D, right panel). Thus, congenital infection in our 
MCMV model resulted in replicative infection in the fetal 
cerebrum. </p>

<p>MCMV invades the fetal brain via the 
bloodstream and targets macrophages and 
NSPCs in the cerebrum </p>

<p>The type of MCMV-infected cells in the fetal cerebrum 
was determined by immunohistochemical analysis for 
MCMV-Ag and various cell markers. In the meninges 
(Fig. 3A-D), MCMV-Ag + cells were distributed along the 
CD31 + blood vessels and involved CD31 + endothelial </p>

<p>Figure 2. Infectious dynamics and intracerebral distribution of MCMV in the fetus. Viral loads in the brain, placenta, heart, and liver determined 
by infectious viral titers (A) and DNA copy numbers (B). The dotted line in (A) indicates the detection limit. Mean AE SEM of five mice in each 
group are shown. (C) Distribution of MCMV-IE1 Ag + cells in the fetal cerebrum at 3 and 5 dpi. The number of MCMV-IE1 Ag + cells in each 
anatomical region was counted for 10 coronal sections sequentially cut at intervals of 240 lm. Mean AE SEM in each anatomical region of six 
MCMV-infected fetal cerebra are shown. (D) A representative coronal section of MCMV-infected cerebrum at 3 dpi (left panel, scale 
bar = 0.5 mm) and its high-power views (middle panel, scale bar = 50 lm). Arrowheads indicate MCMV-IE1 Ag + infectious foci. Detection of 
MCMV DNA in serial sections by in situ hybridization (ISH) is shown in the right panels. MCMV, murine cytomegalovirus. </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. 
Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV </p>

<p>cells in some cases (Fig. 3A, arrow head), while over half 
of the MCMV-Ag + cells were F4/80 + macrophages 
(Fig. 3B, arrow head). F4/80+ macrophages existed in the 
infectious foci twinning around CD31+ endothelial 
cells (Fig. 3C). In the brain parenchyma (Fig. 3E-P), 
MCMV-Ag + cells were detected along the CD31 + blood </p>

<p>vessels penetrating into the brain parenchyma from the 
lateral ventricle (LV) (Fig. 3E). F4/80 + macrophages infil-
trated into the infectious foci (Fig. 3F), and existed along-
side the CD31 + blood vessels (Fig. 3G). In addition to 
F4/80 + macrophages, CD31 + endothelial cells (Fig. 3I, 
arrow head) and NG2 + perivascular cells (pericytes) </p>

<p>Figure 3. Identification of MCMV-Ag + cell types in MCMV-infected fetal cerebrum. Detection of MCMV-E1 Ag (green) and various cell markers 
in the infectious foci in the sections of MCMV-infected fetal cerebrum at 3 dpi by immunofluorescence staining using primary antibodies against 
macrophage/microglia (F4/80, in cyan), endothelial cells (CD31, in red), perivascular cells (NG2, in red), and NSPCs (SOX2, in red), respectively. 
Nuclei were stained with DAPI (in blue). Meninges (A-D), parenchyma (E-P), and the VZ/SVZ of the periventricular area (Q-T) stained with the 
indicated antibodies are shown. Arrowheads in (A) and (I), those in (B), (J), and (N), and those in (M) indicate endothelial cells, macrophages, and 
perivascular cells, respectively. Dotted lines in (E-H) indicate the interface between the lateral ventricle (LV) and parenchyma. Scale bars = 50 lm 
(A-D, Q-T), 100 lm (E-H), and 20 lm (I-P). MCMV, murine cytomegalovirus; NSPC, neural stem/progenitor cells; VZ, ventricular zone; SVZ, 
subventricular zone. </p>



<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV 
M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. </p>

<p>(Fig. 3M, arrow head) were occasionally infected with 
MCMV. Regardless of the number of MCMV-infected 
cells in the meninges, MCMV-Ag was detected only occa-
sionally in the parenchyma just below the infected menin-
ges. These results indicate that MCMV invasion into the 
parenchyma occurs via a transvascular process, not as the 
result of direct invasion from the meninges. 
In the infectious foci of the cerebral periventricular 
area (Fig. 3Q-T) and periaqueductal gray matter, most of 
MCMV-Ag + cells were SOX-2 + NSPCs (Fig. 3Q). Unin-
fected F4/80 + macrophages crowded around the infectious 
foci of the NSPCs (Fig. 3R), and infiltrated into the foci 
(Fig. 3S). The infiltration of uninfected F4/80 + macro-
phages was found at all infectious foci, and they outnum-
bered the MCMV-infected macrophages. 
Thus, in the fetal cerebrum, the major target cells 
allowing MCMV replication are macrophages and NSPCs. </p>

<p>MCMV infection induces macrophage 
infiltration and aberrant distribution of 
microglia in the fetal cerebrum </p>

<p>As we observed infiltration of uninfected macrophages 
into the infectious foci, cell numbers and distributions of 
Iba1 + brain macrophages were compared between the 
fetal cerebra obtained from mock-and MCMV-infected 
dams. Iba1 + brain macrophages, including microglia, 
increased in the cerebra at both E16.5 (3 dpi) (Fig. 4A) 
and at E18.5 (5 dpi) (Fig. 4B) in the infected fetuses. 
These increases in Iba1 + macrophages were observed pre-
dominantly not only around the infectious foci in the 
meninges and parenchyma (Fig. 4A -arrow head -and 
C), but also in the uninfected area of the MCMV-infected 
cerebrum. At 5 dpi (E18.5), the number of Iba1 + cells in 
the uninfected area were significantly increased in the 
meninges, cerebral cortex, and hippocampus in MCMV-
infected cerebra compared with the mock-infected cerebra 
(Fig. 4D). Interestingly, in the MCMV-infected cerebra, 
microglia without viral infection aberrantly appeared in 
the cortical plate (CP) (Fig. 4B, upper panel), where 
microglia are usually absent during the fetal period in the 
mice brain. 31 </p>

<p>Aberrant increase in macrophages/microglia 
is not due to their in situ proliferation </p>

<p>To determine whether the aberrant increase in uninfected 
Iba-1 + brain macrophages, including microglia, in the 
uninfected areas was due to in situ proliferation or 
recruitment from other sites, a BrdU incorporation assay 
for proliferating cells was performed at 5 dpi (Fig. 4B). 
Although MCMV infection induced a significant increase 
in the number of fetal brain macrophages in the </p>

<p>uninfected areas of the brain except for the marginal zone 
(MZ) and intermediate zone (IZ) (Fig. 4D), the numbers 
of BrdU-labeled proliferating macrophages in the unin-
fected areas of the MCMV-infected fetuses were signifi-
cantly reduced in comparison with those in the mock-
infected fetuses (Fig. 4E). Therefore, the aberrant increase 
in macrophages in the MCMV-infected animals is 
thought not to be due to cell proliferation, but is likely 
the result of the recruitment of macrophages from other 
sites. </p>

<p>MCMV infection increased the number of 
macrophages and microglia in the fetal 
cerebrum </p>

<p>To characterize the types of cells showing increased num-
bers, a flow cytometric analysis based on the expression 
levels of CD45 and CD11b were performed. 32 CD11b + 
populations were divided into three fractions, namely, 
CD45 high /CD11b + , CD45 int /CD11b + , and CD45 low / 
CD11b + populations, which correspond to the monocyte/ 
macrophage, intermediate microglia and microglia popu-
lations, respectively (Fig. 5A and B). CD11b + cells in the 
MCMV-infected cerebra both at 3 dpi and 5 dpi were 
significantly increased by ~1.6 times those in the mock-
infected cerebra, and accounted for ~3% of the total 
number of cerebral cells. The monocyte/macrophage pop-
ulation in the MCMV-infected cerebra was increased by 
nearly twice of that in the mock-infected ones. The 
microglia population in the infected cerebra was also 
increased by ~1.5 times. In both mock-and MCMV-
infected cerebra, the percentages of microglia were larger 
at 3 dpi, but smaller at 5 dpi, than those of monocyte/ 
macrophages. Intermediate microglia accounted for only 
~6% of the CD11b + population, and no significant differ-</p>

<p>ence was observed between the populations in mock-and 
MCMV-infected cerebra. The proportions of the other 
CD45 high leukocytes, including natural killer (NK) cells, T 
cells, B cells, and granulocytes, in the all cerebral cells 
were very small in comparison with the monocyte/ 
macrophage and microglia populations and again no 
significant differences were observed in their populations 
between the mock-and MCMV-infected cerebra at 3 dpi 
(Fig. 5C). In addition, ~90% of the monocyte/macro-
phage population in both mock-and MCMV-infected 
cerebra clearly expressed both F4/80 and Iba-1 antigens 
(data not shown). This suggests that the monocyte pro-
portion of the monocyte/macrophage population was very 
low as they usually express CD11b but not Iba-1. 33 Thus, 
the flow cytometric data are consistent with the histologi-
cal findings showing the MCMV-induced dramatic and 
aberrant increases in brain macrophages, including 
microglia. </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. 
Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV </p>

<p>Figure 4. Increase in the number of brain macrophages in MCMV-infected fetal cerebrum. (A) Representative corresponding coronal sections in 
mock-(left) and MCMV-infected (right) E16.5 (3 dpi) fetal cerebra. The sections were stained doubly with mAbs against MCMV-E1 Ag (green) 
and Iba-1 (red). Arrowheads indicate MCMV infectious foci. Scale bar = 0.5 mm. (B) Representative corresponding coronal sections of uninfected 
cerebral cortex in mock-(left) and MCMV-infected (right) E18.5 (5 dpi) fetal cerebra. Mock-or MCMV-infected pregnant mice were pulsed 
intraperitoneally with BrdU at E18.5 and the brains of their fetus were removed 3 h later. The sections were stained doubly with mAbs against 
Iba-1 (red) and BrdU (cyan). Arrowheads indicate Iba-1 and BrdU double-positive cells. Arrows indicate autofluorescence of red blood cells. Scale 
bar = 50 lm. (C) The numbers of Iba1 + brain macrophages in 0.4 mm 2 areas of the cerebrum which contained one infectious focus and those in 
the corresponding cerebral areas of mock-infected fetuses at E16.5 (3 dpi). Mean AE SEM of three mice under each set of conditions is shown. 
*P &lt; 0.05 compared with mock-infected mice. (D) The number of Iba1 + meningeal macrophages and microglia cells in uninfected cerebral areas </p>

<p>in MCMV-infected E18.5 (5 dpi) fetuses. The numbers of Iba1 + cells were also counted in the corresponding anatomical areas of mock-infected 
cerebra. Mean AE SEM of three mice are shown. *P &lt; 0.05 compared with mock-infected mice. (E) The numbers of Iba-1 and BrdU double-
positive cells in the uninfected areas of MCMV-infected E18.5 (5 dpi) fetal cerebra. The numbers of Iba1 and BrdU double-positive cells were 
counted in the corresponding anatomical areas in mock-infected cerebra. Mean AE SEM of three mice are shown. *P &lt; 0.05 compared with 
mock-infected mice. MCMV, murine cytomegalovirus. </p>



<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV 
M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. </p>

<p>Localization of macrophages and microglia 
in MCMV-infected fetal cerebrum </p>

<p>The flow cytometric data led us to analyze the localization 
of brain macrophages by immunofluorescence staining of 
cerebral sections with mAbs against CD45 and F4/80. In 
the MCMV-infected cerebra, CD45-and F4/80-positive 
cells were found throughout the meninges (Fig. 6A-D: </p>

<p>uninfected area and Fig. 6E-H: MCMV-infected area), 
while these cells were exclusively found in the infectious 
foci in the parenchyma (Fig. 6M-P). In both the menin-
ges and parenchyma, the fluorescence intensity of CD45 
was prominent in the infectious foci. Furthermore, CD45-
and F4/80-positive cells in the infectious foci expressed 
the macrophage activation markers MHC class II 
(Fig. 6I-L and Q-T) and iNOS (Fig. 6U-X). The </p>

<p>Figure 5. Flow cytometric analysis of cells in the fetal cerebra with meninges of mock-and MCMV-infected fetuses at E16.5 (3 dpi) and E18.5 
(5 dpi). Total leukocytes were gated for CD45 expression and further characterized for CD11b, NK1.1 (NK cells), CD3 (T cells), B220 (B cells), and 
Gr1 (neutrophils). The analysis was performed in triplicate using a total of nine mock-and four MCMV-infected fetuses at each time point. (A) 
Representative flow cytometric plots separating monocyte/macrophage (CD45 high /CD11b + , Mo/Mφ), intermediate microglia (CD45 int /CD11b + , Int 
Mi), and microglia (CD45 low /CD11b + , Mi) populations of mock-(left panel) or MCMV-infected (right panel) cerebra at E16.5 (3 dpi). (B) The 
percentages of total CD11b + cells, Mo/Mφ, Int Mi, and Mi among the total cerebral cells of mock-infected or MCMV-infected fetuses at E16.5 
(3 dpi) and E18.5 (5 dpi). Mean AE SEM of nine mock-and four MCMV-infected fetuses at E16.5 (3 dpi) and E18.5 (5 dpi) are shown. *P &lt; 0.05 
compared with mock-infected mice. (C) The percentages of Mo/Mφ, Mi, NK cells (CD45 high /NK1.1 high , NK1.1+), T cells (CD45 high /CD3 high , CD3+), 
B cells (CD45 high /B220 high , B220+), and neutrophils (CD45 high /Gr1 high , Gr1+) among the total cerebral cells of mock-or MCMV-infected fetuses at 
E16.5 (3 dpi). Mean AE SEM of nine mock-or four MCMV-infected fetuses. *P &lt; 0.05 compared with mock-infected mice. MCMV, murine 
cytomegalovirus. </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. 
Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV </p>

<p>CD45 high /CD11b + population shown in the flow cytome-
try was supposed to be comprised of activated macro-
phages in the infectious foci and meningeal macrophages. </p>

<p>F4/80 + microglia, localizing outside the infectious foci, 
increased in number but did not express the markers for 
macrophage activation, CD45 (Fig. 6M-P) or MHC class </p>

<p>Figure 6. The localization of activated brain macrophages and microglia in MCMV-infected fetal cerebrum. Detection of MCMV-E1 Ag (green), 
F4/80 (cyan) and an indicator for macrophage activation (red), CD45, MHC class II, or iNOS, by immunofluorescence staining of sections of 
MCMV-infected fetal cerebrum at 5 dpi. Nuclei were stained with DAPI (blue). (A-D) The uninfected area of the meninges in the MCMV-infected 
brain stained with CD45 and F4/80. CD45 + /F4/80 + cells exist throughout the meninges. (E-H) The area including MCMV infectious focus of the 
meninges stained with MCMV-E1 Ag, CD45, and F4/80. The arrowhead in (E) indicates MCMV-infected cells. CD45 + /F4/80 + cells exist throughout 
the meninges, locating around the infectious foci. (I-L) An MCMV infectious focus of the meninges stained with MCMV-E1 Ag, MHC class II, and 
F4/80. MCMV-infected cells are surrounded by MHC class II + /F4/80 + activated macrophages. (M-P) An MCMV infectious focus in brain 
parenchyma stained with MCMV-E1 Ag, CD45, and F4/80. CD45 + /F4/80 + activated macrophages infiltrate into the infectious foci. (Q-T) The serial 
section, adjacent to the section used for M-P, stained with MCMV-E1 Ag, MHC class II, and F4/80. MHC class II + /F4/80 + activated macrophages 
infiltrate into the infectious foci. F4/80 + microglia surrounding an infectious focus express neither CD45 nor MHC class II. (U-X) An MCMV 
infectious focus in the parenchyma stained with MCMV-E1 Ag, iNOS, and F4/80. MCMV-infected cells are surrounded by iNOS + /F4/80 + activated 
macrophages. Scale bar = 100 lm (A-H), 50 lm (M-T) and 20 lm (I-L and U-X). MCMV, murine cytomegalovirus; iNOS, inducible nitric oxide 
synthase. </p>



<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV 
M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. </p>

<p>II (Fig. 6Q-T). These results are consistent in support of 
the fact that MCMV infection induces the infiltration of 
activated macrophages into the infectious foci and the 
aberrant recruitment of microglia in the uninfected 
parenchyma of the fetal cerebra. </p>

<p>Effects of MCMV infection on the stemness 
of NSPCs and cerebral corticogenesis </p>

<p>To investigate the impact of MCMV infection on NSPC 
proliferation, which reflects their ability to self-renew as a 
primary aspect of stemness, nuclear BrdU incorporation 
into SOX2 + NSPCs in the VZ/SVZ was analyzed. Infected 
pregnant mice were pulsed with BrdU at 3 or 5 dpi and 
the fetal brains were removed 3 h later. MCMV-infected 
NSPCs in the VZ/SVZ did not incorporate BrdU at all 
(Fig. 7A). Furthermore, BrdU incorporation into NSPCs 
aside from the infectious foci was also decreased (Fig. 7B 
and C). These data indicate that MCMV infection impairs 
NSPCs proliferation via not only direct viral cytopathicity 
but also indirect pathways. 
We next examined how the impairment of the stem-
ness of NSPCs in the VZ/SVZ influences cortical develop-
ment. According to the widely accepted model of 
neocortical development, the upper cortical layers, unique 
to the mammalian brain, are derived from cortical pre-
cursor cells generated in the VZ during the period 
between E14 and E18. 34 We injected BrdU into MCMV-
infected pregnant mice at 1 dpi (E14.5) and then col-
lected fetal brains at 5 dpi (E18.5). MCMV infection 
reduced the number of BrdU-labeled cells arriving at the 
upper layers of the CP in the E18.5 fetal brains, suggest-
ing MCMV infection disturbs the development of the 
cortical upper layers (Fig. 7D and E). 
To exclude the possibility that the reduction in BrdU-
labeled cells was due to circulatory disturbance, we ana-
lyzed expression of the T-box brain 1 (Tbr1) transcription 
factor protein in the cerebral cortex, which is involved in 
the migration and differentiation of neurons, specifically 
within layer VI of developing six-layered cortex. 35 There 
were no significant differences in the number of Tbr1 + 
neurons destined for layer VI between the mock-and 
MCMV-infected cerebra at 5 dpi (Fig. 8A and B), sug-
gesting that MCMV infection after E13.5 produces little 
effect of the development of the lower layers. In contrast, 
the number of Brn2 + neuronal cells in the cerebral cortex, 
especially in the upper CP, was reduced in the MCMV-
infected brain (Fig. 8A and B). Brn2, POU-homeodomain 
transcription factor (Pou3f2), is required for the produc-
tion of the neural cells in layers II/III, as they migrate to 
the proper position from their departure point in 
the VZ. 36,37 These data indicate that MCMV infection 
impairs the onset of Brn2 expression in NSPCs, resulting </p>

<p>in a reduction in the number of neurons destined 
for the upper cortical layers. Collectively, MCMV infec-
tion impairs the stemness of NSPCs via broad and 
indirect mechanisms, resulting in disordered cerebral 
corticogenesis. </p>

<p>Immune activation in MCMV-infected fetal 
cerebrum </p>

<p>To elucidate the mechanism involved in the reactions of 
brain macrophages and aberrant localization of microglia, 
we evaluated the immune activation status of MCMV-
infected fetal cerebra. For this purpose, expression levels 
of iNOS, MCP-1/CCL2, and representative inflammatory 
cytokines in the whole cerebra including the meninges 
were analyzed (Fig. 9). Expressions of iNOS, TNF-a, and 
IL-1b, reflecting macrophage activation, increased mark-
edly in the MCMV-infected cerebra with time after infec-
tion, but not in the mock-infected cerebra. IL-10 also 
showed similar mRNA expression kinetics. Interestingly, 
INF-a and -b, as type I interferons, contributed little to 
innate immunity in the MCMV-infected fetal cerebra, 
although they usually play an important role in the earli-
est innate host defense against viral infections. INF-c and 
IL-6 showed a delayed increase, and MCP-1 expression 
peaked at 3 dpi in the MCMV-infected cerebra. </p>

<p>Differential expression of iNOS, 
inflammatory cytokines, and interferons 
between activated macrophages and 
microglia </p>

<p>To determine the cellular populations responsible for the 
increased expression of iNOS and cytokines in the 
MCMV-infected fetal cerebra, four cell populations, 
monocyte/macrophages, microglia, CD11b À leukocytes, 
and other cerebral cells, were prepared by cell sorting 
during flow cytometry, and the expression of iNOS and 
cytokines in each population was analyzed (Fig. 10). The 
monocyte/macrophage population in the MCMV-infected 
cerebra was exclusively responsible for the expression of 
the proinflammatory cytokines, TNF-a, IL-1b, and IL-6. 
Expression of iNOS and INF-b were also prominent in 
the monocyte/macrophage population, and substantially 
observed in the other populations. In addition, the mono-
cyte/macrophage population contributed to the expression 
of IL-10. These data appear to well explain the activated 
immune status of the monocyte/macrophage population 
in the infectious foci. In contrast, the microglia contrib-
uted little to the mRNA expression of pro-and anti-
inflammatory cytokines, except for iNOS, INF-a, and -b. 
The expression of iNOS in the microglia of the MCMV-
infected cerebra was reduced compared with that of the </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. 
Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV </p>

<p>mock-infected cerebra. Except for the aberrant but minor 
expression of INF-a and -b, these results indicated a silent 
or suppressive immune status of microglia in the 
MCMV-infected fetal cerebrum. The CD11b À leukocyte 
population was primarily responsible for the expression 
of INF-c. Although this population had been supposed to 
consist of CD3 + /CD11b À T cells and B220 + /CD11b À B 
cells, we found B cells were almost absent (Fig. 5C). 
Therefore, INF-c, probably derived from T cells, contrib-</p>

<p>uted to the expression of iNOS during the late phase of 
MCMV infection. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study, using the mouse model of intraplacen-
tal MCMV infection, focused on the effects of MCMV 
infection on late corticogenesis from E14.5 to E18.5. This 
time frame corresponds to the period from 11 to </p>

<p>Figure 7. MCMV infection inhibits the proliferation of NSPCs via both direct and indirect mechanisms. (A-C) Mock-and MCMV-infected 
pregnant mice were injected with BrdU at 3 and 5 dpi, and the brains of their fetuses were removed at 3 h after the injection. (A) Detection of 
MCMV-IE1 Ag (green), BrdU (red), and SOX2 (magenta) by immunofluorescence staining of section of the MCMV-infected fetal cerebrum at 
3 dpi. Nuclei were stained with DAPI (blue). At 3 dpi, BrdU incorporation is completely inhibited in MCMV-infected NSPCs of the VZ/SVZ between 
dotted lines. Scale bar = 20 lm. (B) The number of BrdU + NSPCs adjacent to MCMV infectious focus in the MCMV-infected cerebrum (right) 
decreased in comparison with that in the mock-infected cerebrum (left) at 5 dpi (E18.5). Scale bar = 50 lm. (C) The number of BrdU + cells in the 
uninfected areas of the VZ/SVZ in the mock-or MCMV-infected cerebrum at 3 or 5 dpi. Data are expressed as mean AE SEM of three fetuses. 
*P &lt; 0.05 compared with mock-infected fetuses. (D-E) Mock-and MCMV-infected pregnant mice were injected with BrdU at 24 h after infection </p>

<p>and then the fetuses were removed at 96 h after BrdU injection (E18.5, 5 dpi). (D) The number of BrdU + cells in the cortical plate of the MCMV-
infected cerebrum (right) decreased in comparison with the mock-infected cerebrum (left). Scale bar = 50 lm. (E) The number of BrdU + cells in 
the upper layer or the lower layer of the cortical plate in the mock-infected or MCMV-infected cerebrum at 5 dpi. Data are expressed 
as mean AE SEM of three fetuses. *P &lt; 0.05 compared with mock-infected fetuses. MCMV, murine cytomegalovirus; NSPC, neural stem/ 
progenitor cells; VZ, ventricular zone; SVZ, subventricular zone. </p>



<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV 
M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. </p>

<p>15 weeks during the first to second trimesters of human 
pregnancy. 8 During this period, the upper cortical layers 
II and III are generated both in mice and humans, and 
disturbances in these layers in humans have been impli-
cated in the etiologies of neurodevelopmental disorders, 
such as schizophrenia. 38 The neonatal mice models with 
intracranial, 30,39 or intraperitoneal MCMV inoculation 40 
instead of MCMV intraplacental infection, have offered 
important of the neuropathogenesis of congenital CMV 
infection. However, in these models, it was difficult to 
investigate the effects of MCMV infection on cerebral cor-
ticogenesis in terms of the route of infection and the 
stage of CNS development. In this study, we have estab-
lished an improved model system of congenital MCMV 
infection using a highly accurate and less invasive method 
for intraplacental MCMV inoculation based on the use of 
a fine glass micropipette. This less invasive method 
improved the survival rate of fetuses infected with </p>

<p>MCMV intraplacentally. Furthermore, it minimized the 
influence of immune response incidentally induced by 
surgical procedures. 
The main findings of the present study are as follows: 
(1) intraplacentally inoculated MCMV invades the cere-
brum via the bloodstream from the placenta in the same 
way as congenital HCMV infection; (2) brain macrophag-
es are not only the major cells infected in the MCMV-
infected fetal brain, but also crucial cells for primitive 
innate immune response; (3) MCMV directly infects 
NSPCs and impairs their stemness. Furthermore, we 
found that MCMV infection impairs their stemness by 
global and indirect mechanisms during the late cerebral 
corticogenesis. As the global and indirect mechanisms for 
the impairment of the stemness of NSPCs in MCMV-infected 
fetal brain, we would like to propose the disturbances 
caused by soluble mediators from activated macrophages 
and the alteration of the brain microenvironment due to </p>

<p>Figure 8. MCMV infection impairs cerebral corticogenesis in the upper layer rather than the lower layer. Detection of Tbr1 (green) and Brn2 
(red), as lower and upper layer markers, respectively, by immunofluorescence staining of sections of MCMV-infected fetal cerebra at 5 dpi. Nuclei 
were stained with DAPI (blue). (A) The localization of Tbr1 + or Brn2 + cells in a representative cerebral section of E18.5 fetus infected with mock 
virus (upper panel) or MCMV (lower panel). Despite no differences in the number of Tbr1 + neurons in the lower layer between the mock-and 
MCMV-infected cerebra, the number of Brn2 + neurons in the upper layer in the MCMV-infected cerebrum decreased. Scale bar = 100 lm. (B) 
The numbers of Tbr1 + and Brn2 + neurons in the upper and lower layers in a 1.6 mm 2 area of MCMV-infected cerebrum and in the 
corresponding area of mock-infected cerebrum. Data are expressed as mean AE SEM of three fetuses. *P &lt; 0.05 compared with mock-infected 
fetuses. MCMV, murine cytomegalovirus. </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. 
Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV </p>

<p>the improper distribution of microglia together with an 
aberrant increase in number. 
In our mouse model, multifocal and disseminated 
MCMV infectious foci were formed through the whole 
fetal body, including the brain, as shown in congenital 
HCMV infection. 41 In the cerebrum of our mouse model, 
MCMV infectious foci were distributed along blood ves-
sels throughout the brain parenchyma and meninges, with 
the periventricular area as a preferred site of MCMV 
infection. The infectious foci mostly consisted of infil-
trated macrophages, and only a part of them were 
infected with MCMV. Since immature myelomonocytic 
leukocytes have been shown to participate in MCMV dis-
semination via the bloodstream, 42 it is supposed that 
these immature monocyte/macrophage lineage cells may 
contribute to transvascular invasion of blood-borne 
MCMV into the fetal cerebrum. 
In the present study, it is worthy of note that focal 
MCMV infection of the fetal cerebrum globally induced a 
dramatic and aberrant increase in brain macrophages, 
including microglia, and this increase was dependent on 
the recruitment of precursor cells from other sites rather </p>

<p>than in situ proliferation. Activated macrophages were 
few in number compared with the other brain macro-
phage populations, but exclusively expressed MHC class 
II and iNOS, indicating macrophage activation. These 
activated macrophages in the infectious foci were the pri-
mary source of iNOS and proinflammatory cytokines, 
TNF-a and IL-1b, which have been reported to suppress 
MCMV replication. 43,44 Considering the delayed expres-
sion of INF-c, we speculate that the expression of these 
mediators may be first induced by the direct interaction 
between MCMV and macrophages, perhaps via mecha-
nisms involving the activation of pattern recognition 
receptors. 45 This macrophage activation was restricted to 
the infectious foci with active MCMV replication, as 
reported previously for the MCMV infection of the post-
natal brain, 30 and possibly prevented the spread of 
MCMV infection. It is likely that both the activated mac-
rophages in the infectious foci and the recruited menin-
geal macrophages derive from the fetal liver where the 
major fetal hematopoiesis occurs after E12, instead of 
from the yolk sac in mice. 46 In contrast to the activated 
macrophages, microglia showed no potent activation but </p>

<p>Figure 9. The relative mRNA expression of iNOS, cytokines, and chemokine in mock-and MCMV-infected fetal cerebrum. The mRNA expression 
levels of iNOS, TNF-a, IL-1b, IL-6, IL-10, INF-a, IFN-b, INF-c, and MCP-1/CCL2 in mock-infected or MCMV-infected fetal cerebra with meninges at 
1, 3, and 5 dpi were assessed by quantitative real-time PCR. The measurements were normalized against the expression of the GAPDH gene. 
Expression levels of samples were expressed as fold changes against the expression level in the mock-infected cerebra at 1 dpi. Since the 
expression levels of IL-10 at 1 dpi and INF-a at 1 and 3 dpi were undetectable, fold changes against their expression in the mock-infected 
cerebrum at 3 or 5 dpi are shown. Mean AE SEM of three mock-or four MCMV-infected fetuses are shown. *P &lt; 0.05 compared with mock-
infected fetuses. MCMV, murine cytomegalovirus; iNOS, inducible nitric oxide synthase. </p>



<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV 
M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. </p>

<p>improperly appeared in the CP associated with an aber-
rant increase in their number, suggesting this improper 
and excessive distribution of microglia could adversely 
affect cerebral development. However, the source of the 
increase in microglia, whether primitive macrophages 
in the yolk sac or fetal liver monocytes, remains to be 
clarified. 47 
With regard to the neuropathogenesis of congenital 
CMV infection, great attention has been paid to 
NSPCs, 19,20 as HCMV preferentially infects the VZ/SVZ in 
the brains of congenitally infected patients. 48 A loss of 
stemness in NSPCs caused by direct CMV cytopathicity 
has been demonstrated in previous in vitro studies. 11-13 
Our intraplacental MCMV infection model simulated 
transplacental HCHV infection, and demonstrated that in-
traplacentally inoculated MCMV preferentially infects 
NSPCs in the developing fetal cerebrum and directly 
impairs their stemness. At the same time, global and indi-
rect impairment of NSPCs was observed in the MCMV-
infected fetal cerebra. Postnatal mouse models infected by 
intraventricular MCMV injection showed delayed cerebel-
lar development with decreases in granular neuron prolif-
eration and migration 40 and improved development of 
MCMV-infected cerebellum in response to suppression of 
inflammation by glucocorticoid treatment. 49 These reports 
are highly suggestive of an impact by focal MCMV infec-
tion on CNS development via broad inflammatory 
responses. The dysregulation of immune mediators has 
been suggested to adversely affect neurodevelopment. 50 In 
this study, the induction of iNOS, TNF-a, IL-1b, and IL-
10 from activated macrophages infiltrating infections foci 
was the earliest primitive innate immune response against 
MCMV infection in the fetal cerebrum. These immune 
mediators, TNF-a, IL-1b, and IL-10, are known to 
adversely influence the stemness of NSPCs and are associ-
ated with neurodevelopmental disorders, such as schizo-
phrenia and epilepsy. 51-55 In addition to the activated 
macrophage response, MCMV infection in the developing 
fetal cerebrum induced improper and excess distribution 
of microglia, which physiologically regulate NSPCs and 
supports cerebral cortical development. 56,57 iNOS expres-
sion was suppressed in these aberrantly recruited microglia 
during MCMV infection. NO produced by iNOS is an 
important player in neuronal development. 58 These aber-
rantly recruited microglia may disturb normal brain devel-
opment via alterations in the microenvironment not only 
due to their improper and excessive distribution in the 
fetal brain, but also due to their adverse immune response. 
Recent studies have proposed an association between 
aberrant microglial status and impairment of corticogene-
sis in neurodevelopmental diseases, such as schizophre-
nia. 59 However, the origin of aberrant microglia and the 
specific causal relationships between microglial status and </p>

<p>Figure 10. mRNA expression of iNOS and inflammatory cytokines in 
microglia and activated macrophages in the fetal cerebrum. Four 
cellular populations, monocyte/macrophage (CD45 high /CD11b + , Mo/ 
Mφ), microglia (CD45 low /CD11b + , Mi), CD11b À leukocyte (CD45 high / 
CD11b À , CD11b À Leu), and other cerebral cells (CD45 low /CD11b À , 
Cr) were obtained from MCMV-infected fetal cerebra at 5 dpi using a 
flow cytometric cell sorting device as described in Materials and 
Methods. mRNA expression levels in each cell population were 
assessed by quantitative real-time PCR and normalized against the 
expression of GAPDH gene. Expression levels of iNOS and 
inflammatory cytokines in each cell population were expressed as fold 
changes against those of mock-infected cerebra. Mean AE SEM of 
three fetuses are shown. *P &lt; 0.05 compared with mock-infected 
fetuses. MCMV, murine cytomegalovirus; iNOS, inducible nitric oxide 
synthase; PCR, polymerase chain reaction. </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. 
Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV </p>

<p>diseases remain unclear. Our present study implies that 
inflammatory responses during embryogenesis can trigger 
microglial dysregulation and that such dysregulation may 
result in certain kinds of neuropsychiatric diseases. It 
would be interesting to see the relationship between neu-
rophysiological and neuroethological outcomes and aber-
rant microglia status in the brains of adult mice that 
survive congenital MCMV infection in our model. 
In conclusion, we have established an improved mouse 
model that can closely reflect congenital CMV infection 
in humans. The model indicated that immune responses 
to viral infection, including aberrant recruitment and 
activation of brain macrophages, compromise the stem-
ness of NSPCs, thus resulting in neurodevelopmental 
disorders. </p>

<p>Authors' Contributions </p>

<p>M. S. and I. K. conceived and designed the study. M. S., 
H. K., T. A., S. M., and I. K. contributed to the data 
acquisition. M. S., N. I., and I. K. analyzed and inter-
preted the data. M. S., H. M., T. I., Y. T., N. I., and I. K. 
wrote and reviewed the manuscript. All authors read and 
approved the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank Ms. Kawashima, Ms. Suzuki, Mr. Kaneta 
(Department of Regenerative and Infectious Pathology, 
Hamamatsu University School of Medicine), Mr. Furukawa 
(Department of Neurophysiology, Hamamatsu University 
School of Medicine), and Mr. Shibata (Research Equipment 
Center, Hamamatsu University School of Medicine) for 
their excellent technical assistance. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>None declared. </p>





<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV 
M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. </p>



<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. 
Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV </p>





<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Fetal Macrophage/Microglial Reactions to CMV 
M. Sakao-Suzuki et al. </p>

</text></tei>