<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4386318" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: It is well known that contact with some physical, chemical or biological compounds can increase the incidence of mutation. 
Among these compounds, are pharmaceuticals that meet long duration of use and potentially could be misused and taken more than the 
ordered dosage. </p>

<p>Objectives: The aim of this study was to evaluate mutagenic effect of methadone in addicted patients referred to Imam Khomeini Hospital 
in Ahvaz by single cell gel electrophoresis technic or comet assay. </p>

<p>Patients and Methods: In this study, 90 subjects were divided into dichromate treated group, no treated healthy volunteers group and 
test group. Each group included 30 subjects. Screening was performed according to questionnaire and qualified subjects were entered the 
study. Blood samples were collected and lymphocytes were isolated, mixed with low melting point agarose for slide preparation according 
to standard method. Slides were analyzed using fluorescence microscope and comet patterns were assessed. </p>

<p>Results: The mutagenicity index in addicted group was robustly higher than healthy volunteers. Fortunately, this significant difference 
was lower than positive control. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Genome instability in addicted patients was demonstrated in this study. Controversially, considering incoherent results of 
previous studies and our data, more studies in longer duration of methadone use are needed to elucidate the consequence. </p>

<p>Keywords:Methadone; Comet Assay; Mutagens </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015, School of Pharmacy, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the mate-
rial just in noncommercial usages, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>Control of pain in a successful treatment is an impor-
tant point and requires careful consideration of appro-
priate dosage, type of medication and cognitive disease 
(1). Using opioids to control pain in acute conditions is 
different with chronic conditions. In these cases, other 
factors must be considered, particularly the rate of toler-
ance and physical dependence (2). 
Methadone hydrochloride (synthetic derivative of diphe-
nyl heptane) is an opioid analgesic used for moderate to 
light pain and detoxification and maintenance treatment 
of addiction to opioid (3). Methadone is similar to mor-
phine, but its effect is somewhat longer than morphine. At 
least its potency and efficiency is equal to morphine. Meth-
adone is effective via orally consumption and drug toler-
ance and physical dependence is slower than morphine. 
Symptoms of drug withdrawal after abrupt discontinua-
tion of methadone are milder but longer than morphine. 
These characteristics made methadone as a medication for 
detoxification and maintenance treatment of chronic ad-
diction to heroin (4). Methadone is a part of admitted pro-
gram of FDA to detoxification, which acts through binding 
to opioid receptors in CNS and inhibition of pain pathway 
and general CNS depression (3). Methadone clearance is 
increased in pregnant women and its half-life is decreased </p>

<p>in the third trimester of pregnancy. Therefore, to achieve 
an effective result, its dosage should be increased and fre-
quency of dosages should be reduced. Detoxification by 
methadone is performed long-term and short-term and al-
cohol, benzodiazepines and medications for HIV or hepati-
tis can be used concomitantly (5). 
With chronic exposure to some physical, chemical or 
biological conditions, mutation probability can be in-
creased by several times. These include medicines that 
can damage the DNA of cells (6). Using some compounds 
in a long-term (7) or simultaneous usage of some medi-
cations may produce metabolites able to cause mutation. 
Results regarding methadone genotoxicity are controver-
sial and need a comprehensive evaluation to obtain un-
equivocal conclusions. Brambilla and colleagues in 2009 
studied the effects of genetic toxicity and carcinogenicity 
of 120 analgesics, anti-inflammatory and anti-pyretic. Due 
to long-term use of methadone and higher risk of side ef-
fects, it was selected for evaluation and finally positive 
results were demonstrated in three assays as below: 
1) Gene mutation, mouse lymphoma L5178Y cell, Tk locus 
2) Chromosomal aberrations, mammalian spermatogo-
nia in vivo 
3) Dominant lethal test, mice (7). </p>

<p>Rezaei M et al. </p>

<p>Jundishapur J Nat Pharm Prod. 2015;10(1):e17008 
2 </p>

<p>Gorazd et al. studied genetic toxicity of methadone in 
23 patients recovering methadone maintenance ther-
apy. Lymphocytes of two control groups were exposed 
to known mutagenic agents. Higher proportion of cells 
with elevated numbers of chromatid exchanges demon-
strated methadone genotoxicity (8). In another study, 
Skowronska et al. evaluated genotoxic effect of metha-
done on peripheral blood lymphocytes of 12 addict pa-
tients; sampling was performed during and at beginning 
of maintenance therapy (9). Surprisingly, DNA breaks 
and damages were reported to be reduced in methadone 
treated groups. Same results were reported by Zimmer-
ing et al. and Badr et al., using drosophila melanogaster 
and dominant lethal mutation consecutively (10, 11). 
Apoptotic effects of methadone may directly or indirectly 
contribute to its proposed DNA toxic effects. In this regard, 
Friesen and colleagues found that methadone is a potent 
inducer of programmed cell death in leukemic cells and 
Non-leukemic lymphocytes. Methadone treatment resides 
and resistance to chemotherapy decreased (12). </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>Given controversial results regarding methadone geno-
toxicity, we investigated the effect of methadone genotox-
icity. Altogether, research on mutagenesis of methadone 
may uncover its potential adverse effects contributing to 
overall health of patients. </p>

<p>3. Patients and Methods </p>

<p>HEPES, Na 2 HPO 4 and Disodium EDTA were obtained 
from Sigma (USA), C 15 H 28 NO 3 Na, Tris Hydrochloride and 
Triton x-100 from Merck (Germany), LMPA and Agarose 
normal from Fermentas (EU) and Methadone from Exir 
(Tehran, Iran). </p>

<p>3.1. Patients and Healthy Subjects </p>

<p>This study was performed to evaluate mutagenic effect 
of methadone in addicted patients referred to Imam 
Khomeini Hospital in Ahvaz. Total samples of 90 subjects 
were divided into dichromate treated group, no treated 
healthy volunteers group and test group. Each group in-
cluded 30 subjects as follows: 
No treated healthy volunteers group: normal subjects 
without any history of opioid consumption in the last 
six months. All individuals filled a detailed questionnaire 
according to the published protocol by the International 
Commission for Protection against Environmental Muta-
gens and Carcinogens. 
Dichromate treated group: 500 μM of dichromate was 
added to samples as a positive agent for induction of DNA 
breakage (13). 
Test group: all 30 subjects in this group met the inclu-
sion criteria. 
Inclusion criteria were methadone use 60 to 120 mg dai-
ly, age of 18 to 65 years, minimum period of three years </p>

<p>for methadone consumption and IQ above 75 (10, 11). Con-
sents were obtained from all subjects participated in this 
study according to university Ethics Committee. 
Exclusion criteria were use of any medicines such as 
benzodiazepines, amphetamine derivatives, antipsy-
chotics, mood stabilizers, use of substances such as mari-
juana, crack, opiates, tramadol, mental disorders (per-
sonality disorders, mood disorders, anxiety disorders, 
psychoses), organic disease and positive results for HIV 
Ab , HCV Ab or HBS Ag (7, 10, 11). </p>

<p>3.2. Isolation of Peripheral Blood Lymphocytes </p>

<p>Two milliliters of peripheral blood were collected from 
each patient in heparinized tubes. Whole blood with 
Hank's solution was diluted to a ratio of 1 to 2.5 mL of ster-
ile Ficoll solution (in the dark and temperature of 2-8°C), 
added to a centrifuge tube and diluted blood poured 
slowly to form a layer on top of the tube. The tubes were 
centrifuged for 20 minutes 1000 rpm (at this stage cen-
trifugal brake or stopping using hand was avoided). After 
centrifugation, mononuclear cells (including lympho-
cytes) settle as a white layer between Ficoll and plasma. 
Lymphocytes were collected using pipette and transferred 
to another tube. The tube was filled with Hank's solution 
and centrifuged at 440 rpm for 10 minutes. The superna-
tant discarded, deposited again on Hank's solution added 
and mixed gently and centrifuged again for 15 minutes at 
230 rpm. Besides, washing repeated with 110 rpm again. At 
this point, fully isolated lymphocytes achieved (14). </p>

<p>3.3. Comet Assay </p>

<p>Afterwards, 100 µL of cell suspension premixed with 
low melting point agarose (LMA 1%) poured on a slide 
coated with normal melting point agarose (NMA 1%) and 
covered with cover slips. Slides were kept for 15 to 20 
minutes horizontally in the ice tray to solidify. Next, the 
cover slips were removed from the slides and placed in a 
lysis solution (14.61 g NaCl, 3.72 g EDTA, 0.125 g Tris ,0.9 g 
NaOH , 1 g sodium lauryl sarcosinate %1, DMSO 10% , Triton 
x-100 1% and pH = 10) for one hour and then washed by 
deionized water, kept for 20 minutes in electrophoresis 
buffer (NaOH 12 g, EDTA 372.0 g, dH 2 O to 1000 mL and pH 
= 13) and electrophoresed at 25 V and 300 mA for 20 min-
utes and then washed with neutralized buffer (Tris 1.12 g, 
dH 2 O to 250 mL and pH = 7.5) for five minutes three times. 
Slides were immersed in ethidium bromide solution for 
five minutes and according to the method described by 
Speit and Hartmann (15), which is based on the original 
work of Singh et al. (16), slides were analyzed by fluores-
cence microscope. The extent and distribution of DNA 
damage indicated by comet assay was evaluated by ex-
amining cells. The cells were visually scored into comet 
classes according to tail size class (17-19): 0 = no tail, 1 = 
tail shorter than the diameter of the head (nucleus), 2 = 
tail length 1 to 2x the diameter of the head and score 3 = 
tail longer than 2x the diameter of the head. Comet with-</p>

<p>Rezaei M et al. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Jundishapur J Nat Pharm Prod. 2015;10(1):e17008 </p>

<p>out head and those with nearly all the DNA in the tail or 
with a very wide tail were excluded from the evaluation, 
because they probably represented dead cells (20, 21). Tail 
length and the mutagenic index were calculated accord-
ing the following formula MI = (0 NMC+ 1 SMC+ 2 MMC+ 3 
LMC)/200, or we could express it as NMC = No migration 
cells (score 0), SMC = Short migration cells (score 1) MMC 
= Medium migration cells (score 2), LMC = Long migra-
tion cells (score 3) (22). </p>

<p>3.4. Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Using <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> software, Chi-square was performed to com-
pare the groups. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>Peripheral blood was collected from 30 addicted pa-
tients screened to be exclusively on methadone and lym-
phocytes were separated to assess the genotoxicity by 
the comet assay. Percent of mutagenicity index (MI) was 
significantly lower in the test group compared to positive 
control and conversely, it was higher compared to the 
negative control group. Addicted patients showed more 
than two fold MI% compared to negative control or nor-
mal samples. Damaged cells in the test group were signif-
icantly higher compared to negative control. Altogether, 
instability of genome was demonstrated for addicted 
patients according to scores obtained for damaged cells. </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>Brambilla et al. studied the carcinogenic effects of 120 dif-
ferent drugs including analgesics, anti-inflammatory and 
antipyretics. Methadone, because of its predominant and 
long-term use for treating severe pain, and its possible side 
effects was investigated. Results were deemed positive in 
the following three areas: gene mutation, chromosomal 
aberrations and dominant lethal test in mice (7). 
Gorazd and Kamenczak studied genetic toxicity of meth-
adone in lymphocytes cultures of 34 patients treated with 
methadone. Micronuclei occurrences along with number 
of chromatids' changes taking place in the metaphase 
indicate genetic mutation. Two control groups with ele-
ments of genetic mutation were used. Increased ratio of 
number of cells to immense chromatid changes are indi-
cators of genetic toxicity of methadone, although these 
changes are not so apparent in other groups facing mu-
tagen (8). As indicated by these studies, genetic mutation 
in patients treated with methadone is controversial and 
therefore in this study we investigated its possible geno-
toxic effect. Lowest concentration of sodium dichromate, 
which causes a break in DNA strand is 50 µM, correlating 
to the dosage can increase to its maximum amount of 500 
µM. higher concentrations of dichromate would cause 
the curve of DNA strand breaks vs. dichromate concentra-
tions to turn into plateau. The reason for this phenome-
non could be cross binding of DNA-DNA and protein-DNA, 
which would prevent DNA migration or could be satura-</p>

<p>tion of activation paths to dichromate (like decrease in 
GSH) or even modifications in improved mechanism of 
DNA. Therefore, sodium dichromate in 500 µM concentra-
tion can be used as a positive control for comparison or 
revealing other unknown mutating agents (13). 
Hodges et al. studied sodium dichromate's abilities in 
breaking DNA chains in three different kinds of cells: hu-
man blood cells, separated lymphocyte and cultures of 
A549 cells of lung's epithelial tissue. In the experiment 
using comet assay, increasing concentrations (10 µM, 50 
and 500) had a correlating effect in breaking the number 
of DNA strands (23). Percentages of healthy and mutated 
cells (in pattern of comet) for the experimental group 
were determined and compared to percentage of health 
and mutated cells in the control groups (Figure 1). Figure 
2 demonstrated the rate of mutation of experimental 
group and control groups, rate of mutation of experi-
mental group compared to control group is deemed neg-
ative. There is a significant difference between the two 
groups. This can be an indication of instability of genome 
in patients participating in the experiment, compared to 
control group regarding scores in the experiment. 
Figure 2 compares percentage of comet mass patterns 
between the experimental and control groups. In the 
control groups, zero scores were most prevalent and 
score ones were next in the numbers. In the experimental 
groups, scores of 1 and 3 reduced respectively. There are no 
2 and 3 scores in the negative control groups. Although, 
there were 2 and 3 scores in the experimental group, and 
there was a significant statistical difference with these 
scores in the negative control group, this difference could 
indicate instability in the genome of experimental group 
compared to the negative control group. 
In Figure 3, percentage of comet mass patterns between 
the experimental and control groups were compared. 
Zero scores in the experimental group were less com-
pared to negative control group, which showed a mean-
ingful difference. On the other hand, scores of 1, 2 and 3 in 
the experimental group increased compared to negative 
control group and the two had a meaningful difference 
regarding 1, 2 and 3 scores with each other. Increased 2 
and 3 scores indicates instability in genome of experi-
mental group compared to negative control group. 
In Figure 1, percentage of mutated cells in the experimen-
tal group and control groups were compared. Mutated 
cells are sum of cells with 2 and 3 for a score. Percentage 
of experimental groups' mutated cells increased com-
pared to control group, and showed a significant differ-
ence. This difference could be an indication of less stability 
of genome of experimental group patients compared to 
negative control group. Perez-Alvarez and Cuenca-Lopez 
observed that high concentrations of methadone are 
needed to induce death in SH-SY5Y cells. Methadone leads 
to a kind of cellular death and has greater similarity to ne-
crosis than apoptosis. Cell cultures show a change in outer 
mitochondria membrane potential and it has been com-
promised and penetrable. No engagement was observed </p>

<p>Rezaei M et al. </p>

<p>Jundishapur J Nat Pharm Prod. 2015;10(1):e17008 
4 </p>

<p>by controlling proteins of apoptosis such as BCL-XL and 
p53 in this process. This study showed that a reduction in 
cell energy level would result in cell necrosis (24). </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>60 66 </p>

<p>Positive Control 
Negative Control 
Test Group </p>

<p>Groups </p>

<p>0 
1.46 
Damaged Cells, % </p>

<p>Figure 1. Percentages of Healthy and Mutated Cells (in Pattern of Comet) 
for the Experimental Group Were Determined and Compared to Percent-
age of Health and Mutated Cells in the Control Groups </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>MI, % </p>

<p>Positive Control 
Negative Control 
Test Group 
Group </p>

<p>45 29 </p>

<p>1.54 </p>

<p>6.14 </p>

<p>Figure 2. The Rate of Mutation in Experimental and Control Groups </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Frequency 
Score 0 
Score 1 
Score 2 </p>

<p>Score 3 </p>

<p>Positive Control Negative Control Test Group </p>

<p>Group </p>

<p>Figure 3. Comparing the Percentage of Comet Mass Patterns Between the 
Experimental and Control Groups </p>

<p>Garcia-Fuster et al. studied external and internal apop-
tosis pathways in prefrontal cortex of persons using 
methadone and heroin. Their findings showed that in 
such individuals these pathways were not activated in an 
abnormal manner. Instead, slowing or continuous ma-
nipulation of some parts of these pathways (downregula-
tion cytochrome C and upregulation BCL-21) induces anti 
apoptosis activity (25). 
Friesen et al. indicated methadone as a strong inducer 
of death in leukemia cells. Methadone controls the pro-
liferation of leukemia cells and induces apoptosis in 
them. Contrary to leukemia cells, non-leukemic lympho-
mas after treatment with methadone remain healthy 
and alive. The study showed that methadone kills leu-
kemia cells and eliminates resistance to chemotherapy 
and apoptosis (12). 
There was a significant difference between mutation in-
dicators of the experimental and negative control groups 
(P &lt; 0.0001). Individuals who used methadone during 
this study had a less stable lymphoma genome compared 
to healthy individuals. Although on this subject and the 
reasons for instability of genome, study showed conflict-
ing results, but continuous manipulation of immune sys-
tem via methadone can induce or modify cellular death. 
Proving genotoxic effects of methadone requires further 
studies for a longer time of usage. To get more conclusive 
findings from this and previous studies, it is necessary to: 
-Perform an extensive review of methadone usage peri-
ods and its effects on genome and cellular deaths. 
-Conduct studies reviewing methadone usage and its 
relation to autoimmune diseases and allergies. 
-More detailed review of reasons for instability of ge-
nome by methadone as means of new clinical targets. </p>

<p>Authors' Contributions </p>

<p>Study concept and design: Mohsen Rezaei. Analysis and 
interpretation of data: Mohsen Rezaei. Sample collec-
tion: Mehdi Sayah Bargard. Practical work: Mahsa Abas-
inia. Drafting of the manuscript: Forouzan Khodaei and 
Mohsen Rezaei. Critical revision of the manuscript for 
important intellectual content: Mohsen Rezaei. Statisti-
cal analysis: Mohsen Rezaei. </p>

<p>Funding/Support </p>

<p>This work was supported by a grant (NO. 768) from the 
Deputy of Research, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of 
Medical Sciences, Ahvaz, Iran. </p>



</text></tei>