<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4800296" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Methods: QGP-1 and BON-1, two human PNET cell lines, were cultured with increasing concentrations of everolimus up to 22 
weeks to reach a dose of 1 mM everolimus, respectively, 1000-fold and 250-fold initial IC 50 . Using total DNA content as a measure of 
cell number, growth inhibitory dose-response curves of everolimus were determined at the end of resistance induction and over 
time after everolimus withdrawal. Response to ATP-competitive mTOR inhibitors OSI-027 and AZD2014, and PI3K-mTOR inhibitor 
NVP-BEZ235 was studied. Gene expression of 10 PI3K-Akt-mTOR pathway-related genes was evaluated using quantitative real-
time PCR (RT-qPCR). </p>

<p>Results: Long-term everolimus-treated BON-1/R and QGP-1/R showed a significant reduction in everolimus sensitivity. During 
a drug holiday, gradual return of everolimus sensitivity in BON-1/R and QGP-1/R led to complete reversal of resistance after 10-12 
weeks. Treatment with AZD2014, OSI-027 and NVP-BEZ235 had an inhibitory effect on cell proliferation in both sensitive and 
resistant cell lines. Gene expression in BON-1/R revealed downregulation of MTOR, RICTOR, RAPTOR, AKT and HIF1A, whereas 
4EBP1 was upregulated. In QGP-1/R, a downregulation of HIF1A and an upregulation of ERK2 were observed. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Long-term everolimus resistance was induced in two human PNET cell lines. Novel PI3K-AKT-mTOR pathway-
targeting drugs can overcome everolimus resistance. Differential gene expression profiles suggest different mechanisms 
of everolimus resistance in BON-1 and QGP-1. </p>

<p>Neuroendocrine tumours (NETs) are a diverse group of neoplasms, 
mainly found in the gastrointestinal tract, lung and pancreas. </p>

<p>Pancreas NETs (PNETs) are relatively rare, with an incidence of 0.43 
per 100 000 according to the Surveillance, Epidemiology and End </p>

<p>*Correspondence: Dr LJ Hofland; E-mail: l.hofland@erasmusmc.nl 
6 These authors contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>Received 16 October 2015; revised 9 January 2016; accepted 13 January 2016 </p>

<p>&amp; 2016 Cancer Research UK. All rights reserved 0007 -0920/16 </p>

<p>FULL PAPER </p>

<p>Keywords: Everolimus resistance; PNET; NVP-BEZ235; AZD2014; OSI-027 </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2016) 114, 650-658 | doi: 10.1038/bjc.2016.25 </p>

<p>650 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2016.25 </p>

<p>Results (SEER) registry (Yao et al, 2008). However, this rate has 
doubled during the last 20 years (Lawrence et al, 2011; Fraenkel et al, 
2012). Primary therapy for localised PNET remains surgical excision. 
However, up to 60% of all patients present with unresectable disease 
(Halfdanarson et al, 2008). In these patients, systemic treatment has 
an essential role in controlling the disease (Falconi et al, 2012). 
The role of traditional cytotoxic therapies in PNET remains a matter 
of debate, with only small series showing response to streptozocin-
based chemotherapy (Calender, 1997; Hansel et al, 2004; Schonhoff 
et al, 2004). Newer chemotherapy regimens with temozolomide 
alone (Ekeblad et al, 2007), or in combination with capecitabine 
(Strosberg et al, 2011), show promise. The low response rate for 
streptozocin-based chemotherapy and the associated side effects 
underscore the need for targeted drugs. 
The phosphoinositide-3-kinase/Akt/mammalian target of rapa-
mycin (PI3K-Akt-mTOR) signalling pathway has a major role in 
NET by regulating cell growth, proliferation, survival and protein 
synthesis (Figure 1A). Furthermore, elevated mTOR expression 
and activity is associated with a higher proliferative capacity 
and worse prognosis (Missiaglia et al, 2010). Recently, exome 
sequencing of primary PNET tumour samples revealed mTOR 
pathway genes to be mutated in 16% of all PNETs, in addition 
to highlighting mutations in other genes, including MEN1 (44% of 
all patients), DAXX (25%) and ATRX (18%) (Jiao et al, 2011). 
mTOR acts as the catalytic subunit of two functionally distinct 
complexes, named mTOR complex 1 (mTORC1) and mTOR 
complex 2 (mTORC2) (Capdevila et al, 2011). mTOR proves to be 
an interesting target for therapy of PNET with mTOR-inhibiting 
rapamycin and analogues (rapalogues) such as everolimus 
(RAD001). Rapamycin, everolimus and other rapalogues form a 
complex with the 12 kD FK506-binding protein FKBP12 (Lach 
et al, 1999; Helpap and Kollermann, 2001). This rapalogue-
FKBP12 complex allosterically inhibits mTOR when it is part of 
mTORC1. However, rapalogues only have limited effect on mTOR 
when mTOR is part of mTORC2 because of steric hindrance by 
the Rictor mTORC2-subunit (Goto et al, 2001). A phase III trial 
with everolimus was conducted in 410 patients with well-and 
moderately differentiated PNETs and showed an improvement in 
median progression-free survival (PFS) in the everolimus-treated 
group compared with the placebo group (Yao et al, 2011). Similar 
results were seen in the phase III trial with sunitinib, a pan-tyrosine 
kinase inhibitor (Raymond et al, 2011). On the basis of these 
results everolimus and sunitinib became the first FDA and EMA 
approved drugs in 30 years for the treatment of locally advanced, 
unresectable or metastatic PNETs. However, an objective partial 
response was only seen in 5% of the patients receiving everolimus 
or sunitinib. The significant effect on PFS was thus mainly due 
to disease stabilisation and minor reductions in tumour growth. 
As PFS in phase III study with everolimus is still limited to 11 
months, adaptive resistance to mTOR inhibition with rapalogues 
was described (Yao et al, 2013). To overcome this resistance, novel 
PI3K-AKT-mTOR targeting drugs have been developed, such as 
NVP-BEZ235, OSI-027 and AZD2014. Exploiting the homology 
between the kinase domain of mTOR and PI3K, NVP-BEZ235 
docks in the active pocket of both molecules and reduces kinase 
activity of PI3K and mTOR by competing with ATP-binding. 
The selective mTOR inhibitors AZD2014 and OSI-027 target the 
kinase domain of mTOR, blocking both mTORC1 and mTORC2 
in an ATP-competitive manner, without blocking PI3K kinase 
activity (Maira et al, 2008; Yu et al, 2009). Although the efficacy 
of novel drugs in PNET cell line model of short-term adaptive 
resistance to everolimus has been studied (Passacantilli et al, 2014), 
no data are currently available about long-term adaptive resistance 
in everolimus-treated PNET. A better understanding of the 
mechanisms underlying resistance to rapalogues is thus necessary 
for a predictive biomarker for everolimus resistance to be 
identified. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Cell lines and culture conditions. BON-1 and QGP-1, two human 
PNET cell line models, were used in this study. The BON-1 cell line 
was a kind gift from Dr Townsend (University of Texas Medical 
Brachn, Galveston, TX, USA; Townsend et al, 1993). The QGP-1 cell 
line was purchased from the Japanese Collection of Research 
Bioresources Cell Bank (JRCB, Osaka, Japan; Kaku et al, 1980). 
BON-1 and QGP-1 cell line identity was confirmed using short 
tandem repeat profiling (Vandamme et al, 2015). The BON-1 cell 
line was cultured in 1 : 1 mixture of Dulbecco's modified Eagle 
medium (DMEM) and F12 medium, supplemented with 10% fetal 
calf serum (FCS), penicillin (1 Â 10 
5 units per l), fungizone 
(0.5 mg l </p>

<p>À 1 </p>

<p>), and L-glutamine (2 mmol l </p>

<p>À 1 </p>

<p>). The QGP-1 cell line 
was cultured in Roswell Park Memorial Institute (RPMI) 1640 
medium, supplemented with 10% FCS and penicillin-streptomycin 
(1 Â 10 
5 units per l penicillin and 1 Â 10 
5 units per l streptomycin). 
All cell lines were incubated in an atmosphere of 95% humidity and 
5% CO 2 at 37 1C. Media and supplements were obtained from Life 
Technologies Bio-cult Europe (Invitrogen, Breda, The Netherlands). </p>

<p>Drugs and reagents. Everolimus (RAD001), AZD2014, OSI-027 
and NVP-BEZ235 were purchased from Selleckchem (Selleck 
Chemicals, Houston, TX, USA). Rapamycin was purchased from 
LG Laboratories (Woburn, MA, USA). All inhibitors were dissolved 
in 100% dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO) to a 1 mM concentration and 
stored in À 20 1C. All drugs were diluted to working concentrations 
in 40% DMSO before use. In all the experiments, controls were 
treated with a vehicle DMSO concentration equivalent to the 0.4% 
final DMSO concentration in the treatment dilutions. </p>

<p>Cell proliferation assay using total DNA content. Cells were 
plated in 1 ml medium in 24-well plates at the density necessary to 
obtain a 70-80% cell confluence in the control groups at the end of 
the experiment. Medium was refreshed and the tested compounds 
were added to wells in quadruplicate after 24 h for QGP-1 and 72 h 
for BON-1. Time points were chosen to reduce inter-and intra-
experiment variability. The concentrations of compounds tested 
ranged between 0,1 nM and 1 mM for everolimus, rapamycin and 
NVP-BEZ235. Given the narrow therapeutic margin of AZD2014 
and OSI-027, the used concentrations ranged from 10 nM to 1 mM 
with an added 250 nM and 500 nM concentration. Every 3 days, the 
cells were supplied with fresh medium and compounds. After 7 
days of treatment, the cells were harvested for DNA measurement. 
Measurement of total DNA content, as a measure of cell number, 
was performed with the bisbenzimide DNA-intercalating fluor-
escent dye (Hoechst 33258; Boehring Diagnostics, La Jolla, CA, 
USA) as previously described (Barrett et al, 1995). </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time PCR of PI3K-AKT-mTOR pathway 
genes. The tested cell line conditions were plated in 3 ml medium 
in six-well plates at the density required to obtain 70-80% cell 
confluence at the end of the experiment. Twenty-four hours later for 
QGP-1 cell line conditions and 72 h later for BON-1 cell line 
conditions, medium was replaced and cells were incubated for 72 h with 
vehicle. One-step reverse transcription quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR) 
was performed on total RNA from six biological replicates in 
a single reaction using the Power SYBR Green RNA-To-CT 1-Step 
kit (Life Technologies, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, 
USA) on a LightCycler 480 instrument (Roche Applied Science, 
Penzberg, Germany). Primers were designed using QuantPrime 
software (Arvidsson et al, 2008) and RTPrimerDB (http:// 
www.rtprimerdb.org) and have been obtained from Integrated 
DNA Technologies (Leuven, Belgium) (Supplementary Table 1). 
All reactions have been performed in triplicates in 384-well plates 
with 2 ml total RNA (prediluted to 15 ng ml 
À 1 ) as input in a total 
reaction volume of 10 ml, further comprising 5 ml Power SYBR </p>

<p>Long-term everolimus resistance in PNET 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2016.25 </p>

<p>
Green RT-PCR Mix (2 Â ; Life Technologies, Thermo Fisher 
Scientific), 0.08 ml RT Enzyme Mix (125 Â ; Life Technologies, 
Thermo Fisher Scientific) and 200 nM of each primer (final 
concentration). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. All cell proliferation assays were performed 
at least twice at different times. The repeated experiments gave 
comparable results. The comparative statistical evaluations 
between the different cell line conditions were performed by 
two-way ANOVA with treatment concentration and cell line 
condition as variables. For post hoc testing, a multiple comparative 
test with Dunn-Šidák correction was used. For RT-qPCR 
experiments, normalised relative gene expression values were 
calculated using <rs id="software-1" type="software">qBasePLUS</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 1.5</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Biogazelle</rs>, </p>

<p>Zwijnaarde, Belgium). Messenger RNA expression was normalised 
to household gene expression (GAPDH and RPL13A for BON-1; 
HPRT and YWAZ for QGP-1) according to the geNorm algorithm 
(Mestdagh et al, 2009). Comparison between gene expression levels 
was done by Student's t-test and adjusted for multiple testing using 
Holm-Bonferroni correction. All statistical analyses were done 
using <rs id="software-2" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">5.0 for Windows</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>, 
La Jolla, CA, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Inducing everolimus resistance. In untreated human PNET 
cell lines BON-1 and QGP-1, the everolimus concentration that </p>

<p>PI3 K </p>

<p>AKT </p>

<p>S6K1 </p>

<p>IRS1 </p>

<p>Cap-dependent translation and protein translation </p>

<p>Rictor </p>

<p>mTOR </p>

<p>PIP 2 
PIP 3 </p>

<p>Raptor </p>

<p>mTOR </p>

<p>mTOR complex 1 </p>

<p>mTOR complex 2 </p>

<p>MEK </p>

<p>PTEN </p>

<p>4EBP1 </p>

<p>GRB10 </p>

<p>RAF </p>

<p>RAS </p>

<p>ERK1/2 </p>

<p>Dual 
inhibitor </p>

<p>PI3 K </p>

<p>AKT </p>

<p>S6K1 </p>

<p>IRS1 </p>

<p>Cap-dependent translation and protein translation </p>

<p>Rictor </p>

<p>mTOR </p>

<p>PIP 2 
PIP 3 </p>

<p>Raptor </p>

<p>mTOR </p>

<p>mTOR complex 1 </p>

<p>mTOR complex 2 </p>

<p>MEK </p>

<p>PTEN </p>

<p>4EBP1 </p>

<p>GRB10 </p>

<p>RAF </p>

<p>RAS </p>

<p>ERK1/2 </p>

<p>ATP 
inhibitor </p>

<p>PI3 K </p>

<p>AKT </p>

<p>S6K1 </p>

<p>IRS1 </p>

<p>Cap-dependent translation and protein translation </p>

<p>Rictor </p>

<p>mTOR </p>

<p>PIP 2 
PIP 3 </p>

<p>Raptor </p>

<p>mTOR </p>

<p>mTOR complex 1 </p>

<p>mTOR complex 2 </p>

<p>MEK </p>

<p>PTEN </p>

<p>4EBP1 </p>

<p>GRB10 </p>

<p>RAF </p>

<p>RAS </p>

<p>ERK1/2 </p>

<p>Rapalog </p>

<p>PI3 K </p>

<p>AKT </p>

<p>S6K1 </p>

<p>IRS1 </p>

<p>Cap-dependent translation and protein translation </p>

<p>Rictor </p>

<p>mTOR </p>

<p>PIP 2 
PIP 3 </p>

<p>Raptor </p>

<p>mTOR </p>

<p>mTOR complex 1 </p>

<p>Growth factor </p>

<p>TK receptor </p>

<p>mTOR complex 2 </p>

<p>MEK </p>

<p>PTEN </p>

<p>4EBP1 </p>

<p>GRB10 </p>

<p>RAF </p>

<p>RAS </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>ERK1/2 </p>

<p>TSC1/2 </p>

<p>RHEB </p>

<p>TSC1/2 </p>

<p>RHEB </p>

<p>RHEB </p>

<p>TSC1/2 
TSC1/2 </p>

<p>RHEB </p>

<p>GTP 
GTP </p>

<p>GTP 
GTP </p>

<p>Figure 1. Simplified representation of the PI3K-AKT-mTOR pathway in pancreatic neuroendocrine tumours. Constitutional activation of the 
pathway (A) and its response to rapalogues (B), ATP-competitive inhibitors (C) and dual PI3K-mTOR inhibitors (D) is shown. Red full lines describe 
an increase and red dashed lines show a decrease of feedback under different conditions. A detailed description can be found in the text. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Long-term everolimus resistance in PNET </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2016.25 </p>

<p>reduces growth by 50% (IC 50 ) after 7 days of treatment was 1 and 
4 nM, respectively (data not shown). Starting from this IC 50 
concentration, QGP-1 and BON-1 were continuously cultured in 
increasing concentrations of everolimus. The everolimus concen-
tration was progressively doubled every 14 days during 8-10 dose 
doublings until a final concentration of 1 mM was reached. In 
parallel, clonal BON-1 and QGP-1 cells were long-term vehicle 
treated. The established long-term everolimus-treated cell lines 
(BON-1/R and QGP-1/R) were maintained in the maximally 
achieved everolimus concentration. No morphological changes 
were seen between the long-term vehicle-treated cell lines and the 
long-term everolimus-treated cell lines (Supplementary Figure 2). 
After the establishment of the long-term everolimus-treated BON-
1/R and QGP-1/R, both showed a statistically significant reduced 
growth inhibitory response to everolimus in comparison with long-
term vehicle-treated BON-1 and QGP-1 at everolimus concentra-
tions between 10 nM and 1 mM for BON-1/R and at 1 nM and 1 mM 
for QGP-1/R, respectively (Figure 2A and B). In addition, BON-1/ 
R and QGP-1/R had a significantly reduced sensitivity to 
rapamycin in concentrations ranging from 1 nM to 1 mM when 
compared with their long-term vehicle-treated BON-1 and QGP-1 
counterparts (Figure 2C and D). </p>

<p>Evolution of everolimus-resistance over time. In order to study 
reversibility of everolimus-resistance, the BON-1/R and QGP-1/R 
cell lines were cultured without everolimus maintenance treatment 
during 10 and 12 weeks, respectively, showing a gradual return 
of everolimus sensitivity (data not shown). After 10-12 weeks, 
this resulted in the BON-1/R STOP and QGP-1/R STOP cell line 
conditions. When comparing these cell line conditions with 
BON-1/R and QGP-1/R, maintained during 10-12 weeks at 
maximum 1 mM everolimus concentration, and vehicle-treated 
BON-1 and QGP-1, a return of BON-1/R STOP and QGP-1/R </p>

<p>STOP to the sensitivity levels of BON-1 and QGP-1 was observed 
(Figure 3A and B). </p>

<p>Overcoming everolimus-resistance. A dose-response study in 
both everolimus-resistant and -sensitive BON-1 and QGP-1 cells 
to the growth inhibitory effect of AZD2014, OSI-027 and 
NVP-BEZ235 was executed in parallel. After a 7-day-treatment 
with AZD2014, cell proliferation was significantly less reduced 
at the 250 nM and 500 nM concentration of AZD2014 in BON-1/R 
when compared with long-term vehicle-treated BON-1. When 
exposing QGP-1/R and QGP-1 to AZD2014 during 7 days, growth 
reduction was significantly more pronounced in long-term vehicle-
treated QGP-1 when compared with QGP-1/R in all tested 
AZD2014 concentrations above 100 nM. A maximal inhibition 
of 480% of cell proliferation was obtained at 1 mM of AZD2014 in 
all cell lines tested (Figure 4A and B). BON-1/R and long-term 
vehicle-treated BON-1 did not respond significantly different to 
OSI-027, while QGP-1/R was more resistant to OSI-027 than 
QGP-1 in all concentrations tested above 100 nM. The maximum 
inhibition with OSI-027 reached in BON-1/R, BON-1 and QGP-1 
cells was a 50% reduction of cell proliferation (Figure 4C and D). 
No statistically significant difference in the inhibition of cell 
proliferation was observed after 7 days of treatment with NVP-
BEZ235 in BON-1/R when compared with long-term vehicle-
treated BON-1 in the 1 nM to 1 mM NVP-BEZ235 concentration 
range. In both everolimus-sensitive and -resistant BON-1 cells, 
a maximum inhibition of 492% of control cell proliferation was 
reached at 100 nM of NVP-BEZ235. When comparing the QGP-1/ 
R and QGP-1, NVP-BEZ235 was less potent at 10 nM, compared 
with QGP-1/R cells. Maximal cell growth inhibition was achieved 
a 100 nM in both QGP-1/R and long-term vehicle-treated QGP-1 
(Figure 4E and F). </p>

<p>QGP-1 
BON-1 </p>

<p>B 
A </p>

<p>D 
C </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
DNA (% control) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
DNA (% control) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
DNA (% control) </p>

<p>DNA (% control) </p>

<p>*** 
*** 
*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** 
*** 
*** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>*** 
* 
*** 
*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 
n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>Everolimus </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 
n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>Rapamycin </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 
n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>Rapamycin </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 
n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>Everolimus </p>

<p>BON-1 </p>

<p>BON-1/R </p>

<p>QGP-1 </p>

<p>QGP-1/R </p>

<p>** P &lt; 0.01 
*** P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>* P &lt; 0.05 
*** P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Everolimus dose response curves of QGP-1/R and long-term vehicle-treated QGP-1 and BON-1/R and long-term vehicle-treated 
BON-1. All cells were treated for 7 days with increasing concentrations of everolimus (A, B) or rapamycin (C, D), respectively. Growth inhibitory 
response is expressed as the percentage of vehicle-treated control ( ± s.e.m.). Control is normalised at 100%. </p>

<p>Long-term everolimus resistance in PNET 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2016.25 </p>

<p>
Gene expression changes in everolimus resistance. Differential 
gene expression of MTOR, RAPTOR, RICTOR, AKT, S6K1, 4EBP1, 
ERK1, ERK2, BCL2 and HIF1A between BON-1/R and long-term 
vehicle-treated BON-1 showed a significant downregulation of 
MTOR, RICTOR, RAPTOR, AKT and HIF1A, whereas 4EBP1 was 
significantly upregulated (Po0.05) (Figure 5). When comparing 
QGP-1/R and QGP-1, a significant downregulation of HIF1A and 
a significant upregulation of ERK2 were observed (Po0.05). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, to the best of our knowledge, the first two PNET 
models for long-term acquired everolimus resistance were 
established. Both QGP-1 and BON-1 were cultured during more 
than 20 weeks in increasing concentrations of everolimus and 
continued to grow under a 250 and 1000-fold IC 50 growth 
inhibitory concentration of everolimus, respectively. Correspond-
ing in vivo concentrations are not reachable in patients (O'Donnell 
et al, 2008). Continued cell growth under these high everolimus 
concentrations, unreachable in patients, hence indicates an ever-
olimus resistance with possible clinical implications. Both the 
resulting BON-1/R and QGP-1/R show a significantly decreased 
response to everolimus in comparison with long-term vehicle-
treated BON-1 and QGP-1, even in the highest concentrations 
tested (1 mM). Similar results were seen when comparing BON-1/R 
and QGP-1/R and its vehicle-treated counterparts for response to 
rapamycin. This indicates that BON-1/R and QGP-1/R are not 
only everolimus-resistant, but are also resistant to other rapalogues. 
A previous study looked at everolimus-resistance in BON-1 
(Passacantilli et al, 2014). However, this study treated BON-1 
cells during 8 weeks with a dose of 10 nM, which is a much shorter 
period and a lower dose than used in this study. In addition, 
the authors did not perform a resistance induction experiment 
with QGP-1. Given the long duration of treatment, the resulting 
BON-1/R and QGP-1/R cell lines in our study could be considered 
as a representative model for rapalogue resistance seen in PNET 
patients, where median time to treatment failure and, thus, 
acquired everolimus resistance is 11 months (Yao et al, 2011). 
Various mechanisms have been proposed for the limited 
response to everolimus in PNET (Figure 1B). Not all </p>

<p>phosphorylation sites of mTORC1 downstream proteins such as 
p70 ribosomal S6 kinase 1 (S6K1), growth factor receptor bound 
protein 10 (GRB10) and eukaryotic translation initiation factor 4E 
binding protein 1 (4E-BP1) respond to the same extent to allosteric 
inhibition of mTORC1 by rapalogues(Kang et al, 2013), thereby 
diminishing rapalogue efficacy. Adaptive resistance may also 
be caused by induction of activated phosphorylation of AKT. 
This occurs through the lifting of negative feedback of the 
mTORC1 downstream p70 ribosomal S6 kinase 1 (S6K1) on the 
PI3K-AKT-mTOR pathway(Ohike et al, 2003; O'Reilly et al, 2006; 
Julien et al, 2010). S6K1 effects this negative-feedback on insulin 
receptor substrate-1 (IRS-1), which regulates insulin-like growth 
factor I (IGF-1; O'Reilly et al, 2006). Furthermore, mTORC1 
activates GRB10, which negatively regulates IGF-1 signalling. 
When mTORC1 is inhibited by rapalogues, this negative feedback-
loop of IGF-1 is suppressed, synergistically adding to the effect 
of mTOR inhibition of the S6K1-feedback loop (Emerling and 
Akcakanat, 2011). As rapalogues effectively block mTORC1 but 
only have a limited, dose-dependent action on the mTORC2, the 
effect of rapalogues on mTOR signalling may be circumvented 
through increased activity of mTORC2 (O'Reilly et al, 2006; Julien 
et al, 2010). Furthermore, a direct role of S6K1 on mTORC2-
mediated AKT phosphorylation has been described since S6K1 
might be instrumental in the inhibitory phosphorylation of Rictor, 
the rapalogue-insensitive component of mTORC2 (Julien et al, 
2010). Novel mTOR inhibitors, blocking both mTORC1 and 
mTORC2 by competitively binding the ATP-binding mTOR 
kinase pocket, have been developed to overcome these escape 
mechanisms. AZD2014 is an ATP-competitive mTOR inhibitor, 
currently undergoing phase II evaluation in different tumour types 
(Pike et al, 2013; Basu et al, 2015a) (Figure 1C). In our study, 
AZD2014 effectively reduces cell proliferation both in the 
everolimus-sensitive QGP-1 and BON-1, as well as in the 
everolimus-resistant BON-1/R and QGP-1/R. This is the first time 
that AZD2014 shows efficacy in PNET models. In addition, these 
results indicate that AZD2014 overcomes everolimus resistance in 
PNET in concentrations reachable in patients (Basu et al, 2015a). 
Further development of this drug in PNET could hence benefit 
PNET patients. In addition, OSI-027, a drug from the same ATP-
competitive mTOR inhibiting class was tested. In contrast with the 
other tested compounds, the growth inhibitory effect of OSI-027 in </p>

<p>BON-1 
QGP-1 </p>

<p>B 
A </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
DNA (% control) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
DNA (% control) </p>

<p>*** 
*** 
*** 
** 
** 
** </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 
n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>Everolimus </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 
n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>Everolimus </p>

<p>BON-1 
BON-1/R 
BON-1/R STOP 
QGP-1/R STOP </p>

<p>QGP-1/R </p>

<p>** P &lt; 0.01 
*** P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>QGP-1 </p>

<p>Figure 3. Everolimus dose response curves after 10 to 12 weeks of wash-out. Response was evaluated after 7 days of treatment with increasing 
everolimus concentrations in BON-1/R, long-term vehicle-treated BON-1, and BON-1/R after an everolimus wash-out period of 12 weeks 
(BON-1/R STOP) (A) and QGP-1/R, and in long-term vehicle-treated QGP-1/ and QGP-1/R after an everolimus wash-out period of 10 weeks 
(QGP-1/R STOP) (B). Growth inhibitory response is expressed as the percentage of vehicle-treated control ( ± s.e.m.). Control is normalised at 
100%. P-values shown are for Dunn Sídá k post hoc comparison after two-way ANOVA between BON-1/R and QGP-1/R and BON-1/R STOP and 
QGP-1/R STOP, respectively. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Long-term everolimus resistance in PNET </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2016.25 </p>

<p>the concentration ranges tested reaches growth inhibition by only 
50% at 1 mM in vehicle-treated BON-1 and QGP-1 cell lines. 
In a xenograft mouse model, concentrations of up to 2 mM could 
be reached, but further studies on pharmacokinetics in humans are 
needed (Bhagwat et al, 2011). Although resistant and sensitive 
BON-1 responded equally to OSI-027 treatment, only limited 
efficacy in overcoming everolimus resistance with OSI-027 was 
observed in the QGP-1 cell line. This difference in response to OSI-
027 between BON-1/R and QGP-1/R suggests two distinct 
molecular mechanisms of resistance. NVP-BEZ235 is a dual 
blocker of mTOR, blocking both mTORC1 and mTORC2, and the 
upstream PI3K (Doglioni et al, 1998) (Figure 1D). NVP-BEZ235 
has proven efficacy in in vitro and in vivo PNET models (Doglioni 
et al, 1998; Paireder et al, 2013). Dual inhibition of the PI3K-
mTOR pathway could prevent cross-talk activation of the mitogen-
activated kinase and extracellular signal-regulated kinase (MAPK-
ERK pathway) through PI3K-mediated feedback loop (Helpap and 
Kollermann, 1999; Carracedo et al, 2008; Zitzmann et al, 2010; 
Svejda et al, 2011; Paireder et al, 2013). This cross-talk could lead 
to an escape of mTORC1 inhibition and, hence, to rapalogue 
resistance. Although NVP-BEZ235 has completed phase II studies, </p>

<p>clinical development of this drug might not progress to phase III 
because of the drug's safety profile (Fazio et al, 2016). However, 
our current study demonstrates that dual blocking of PI3K and 
mTOR could be an attractive strategy to overcome long-term 
acquired everolimus resistance. In addition, maximum inhibition 
in both resistant and sensitive cell lines was reached with 
NVP-BEZ235 concentrations more than 10-fold lower than dose-
limiting plasma concentrations obtained in phase I studies (Bendell 
et al, 2015). As this is in line with previously reported in vitro 
results and an in vivo study with lower dose NVP-BEZ235 in a 
glioblastoma model demonstrated efficacy, it could hence be 
interesting to evaluate low-dose NVP-BEZ235 in PNET (Maira 
et al, 2008; Passacantilli et al, 2014). 
Another possible mechanism for everolimus resistance is 
tumour heterogeneity. Within-patient and within-tumour hetero-
geneity in proliferation, genomic alterations and functional 
imaging characteristics have been demonstrated in neuroendocrine 
tumour patients (Gebauer et al, 2014; Shi et al, 2015; Basu et al, 
2015b). This heterogeneity could be caused by tumoural subclones 
with different phenotypes and responses to treatement (Marusyk 
et al, 2014). By treating a patient with everolimus, selection of </p>

<p>BON-1 </p>

<p>BON-1/R </p>

<p>QGP-1 </p>

<p>QGP-1/R </p>

<p>BON-1 
QGP-1 </p>

<p>B 
A </p>

<p>D 
C </p>

<p>F 
E </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
DNA (% control) </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>2 5 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>5 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>AZD2014 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
DNA (% control) </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>2 5 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>5 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>OSI-027 
OSI-027 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
DNA (% control) </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>2 5 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>5 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
DNA (% control) </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 
n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>NVP-BEZ235 
NVP-BEZ235 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
DNA (% control) </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 
n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
DNA (% control) </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>2 5 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>5 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>AZD2014 </p>

<p>*** P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>** P &lt; 0.01 
*** P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>** P &lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>Figure 4. Dose-response curves with novel PI3K-Akt-mTOR inhibitors in BON-1/R and long-term vehicle-treated BON-1 and QGP-1/R and long-
term vehicle-treated QGP-1. Cells were treated during 7 days with, respectively, AZD2014 (A, B), OSI-027 (C, D) and NVP-BEZ235 (E, F). Response 
is expressed as the percentage of vehicle-treated control ( ± s.e.m.). Control is normalised at 100%. </p>

<p>Long-term everolimus resistance in PNET 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2016.25 </p>

<p>
everolimus-resistant subclones could occur, leading to resistance. 
Although short-term everolimus resistance is mainly driven by 
phosphorylation changes in PI3K-AKT-mTOR pathway proteins 
(O'Reilly et al, 2006), a shift in clonal population could be a driving 
force in long-term everolimus resistance. This is illustrated by the 
gradual reversal of everolimus resistance in BON-1/R and QGP-1/R, 
with a complete return of everolimus sensitivity only after 42 
months of culturing without everolimus. If this resistance would only 
be caused by phosphorylation and dephosphorylation of proteins, a 
faster reversal of everolimus resistance could be expected. Long-term 
treatment with everolimus might hence select or induce subclones 
with a different genetic, epigenetic or transcriptional make-up that 
makes them more resistant to everolimus. Future studies using next </p>

<p>generation sequencing would be a good strategy to identify these 
resistant subclones and yield biomarkers for everolimus resistance. 
Given the long timeframe of sustained resistance, alterations in gene 
expression were studied to elucidate possible resistance mechanisms. 
In BON-1/R, the main components of both mTORC1 and mTORC2 
and the important upstream protein AKT were downregulated, 
whereas effector protein 4EBP1 expression was upregulated, hinting 
at a compensatory mechanism in which 4EBP1 is less dependent on 
mTORC1 and mTORC2. On the other hand, the main upregulated 
gene in QGP-1/R was ERK2, part of the MAPK-ERK pathway, 
illustrating a possible escape through this pathway. Interestingly, 
both cell lines seem to have a differential gene expression profile after 
developing resistance to everolimus. This is corroborated by their 
different response to novel PI3K-AKT-mTOR pathway targeting 
drugs. QGP-1/R is more resistant to treatment with the two tested 
ATP-competitive mTOR inhibitors, AZD2014 and OSI-027, than 
BON-1/R. Similarly, although full inhibition of proliferation with 
NVP-BEZ235 could be reached in both BON-1/R and QGP-1/R, 
a higher concentration of NVP-BEZ235 is needed to overcome 
resistance in QGP-1/R. Hence, we could conclude that the underlying 
mechanisms of everolimus resistance in BON-1/R and QGP-1/R 
might be different. If our data can be extrapolated to PNET patients, 
our study could provide an insight in the mechanisms determining 
resistance to mTOR inhibition in the clinic. Ultimately, this might 
lead to a better selection of patients and true personalised medicine. 
In conclusion, the first PNET models for long-term everolimus 
treatment, resulting in acquired rapalogue-resistance, are presented 
here. Both the ATP-competitive mTOR blocker, AZD2014, as the 
dual PI3K-mTOR blocker NVP-BEZ235 are able to overcome this 
rapalogue resistance. Further evaluation of both drugs in in vivo 
and patient studies, targeted at overcoming everolimus resistance, 
could hence be challenging. In addition, both models allow the 
study of the detailed mechanisms of acquired resistance in PNET. 
Expanding these studies with advanced genetic and genomic 
techniques, such as next generation sequencing, could lead to the 
identification of biomarkers for everolimus resistance. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The BON-1 cell line was a kind gift from J.C. Thompson, Department 
of Surgery, University of Texas Medical Branch, Galveston, TX, USA 
to Leo J. Hofland, Section of Endocrinology, Department of Internal 
Medicine, Erasmus Medical Center, Rotterdam, the Netherlands for 
research purposes. This work was supported by the Flemish Agency of 
Scientifc Research (FWO grant G.0327.13N) and the ENETS-Ipsen 
2013 Translational Research Fellowship. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>TV, WdH and MP: advisory role and speakers' fees for Ipsen and 
Novartis. The remaining authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>m 
T O </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R 
I C 
T O </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R 
A P T O </p>

<p>R 
A K T 
4 E B P 1 
S 6 K 1 
B C </p>

<p>L 2 
H 
I F 1 A E R </p>

<p>K 1 
E R </p>

<p>K 2 </p>

<p>-100 </p>

<p>-50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>Genes 
% Change gene expression </p>

<p>BON-1/R vs BON-1 </p>

<p>m 
T O </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R 
I C 
T O </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R 
A P T O </p>

<p>R 
A K T 
4 E B P 1 
S 6 K 1 
B C </p>

<p>L 2 
H 
I F 1 A 
E R </p>

<p>K 1 
E R </p>

<p>K 2 </p>

<p>-100 </p>

<p>-50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>Genes 
% Change gene expression </p>

<p>QGP-1/R vs QGP-1 </p>

<p>Significant gene expression changes </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 5. Changes in mRNA expression between resistant and 
sensitive cell lines. Changes are expressed in mean percentage±s.e.m 
between BON-1/R and BON-1 and QGP-1/R (A) and QGP-1 (B). 
In addition to MTOR, mTORC1 component RAPTOR and mTORC2 
component RICTOR expression was studied. Moreover, gene 
expression of AKT, encoding the mTOR upstream AKT, S6K1 and 
4EBP1, encoding the mTOR downstream p70 ribosomal kinase 1 
(S6K1) and eukaryotic translation initiation factor 4E-binding protein 1 
(4E-BP1), respectively, was determined. In addition, BCL2, a gene 
encoding for anti-apoptotic protein B-cell leukaemia 2 (Bcl-2), and 
HIF1A, encoding the hypoxia-inducible factor 1-alpha protein (HIF-1 
alpha) was used to study the overall effect on apoptosis and 
proliferation in the cell. Finally, expression of ERK1 and ERK2, two 
components of the MAPK-ERK pathway was determined. Differences 
were tested using Student's t-test. Po0.05, after Bonferroni correction 
for multiple testing, was considered significant (hatched bars). </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Long-term everolimus resistance in PNET </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2016.25 </p>



<p>Long-term everolimus resistance in PNET 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2016.25 </p>



<p>
This work is published under the standard license to publish agree-
ment. After 12 months the work will become freely available and 
the license terms will switch to a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-Share Alike 4.0 Unported License. </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on British Journal of Cancer website (http://www.nature.com/bjc) </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Long-term everolimus resistance in PNET </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2016.25 </p>

</text></tei>