<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4304516" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Backgrounds/Aims: Combined hepatocellular carcinoma and cholangiocarcinoma (cHCC-CC) is an uncommon subtype 
of primary liver cancer that has rarely been reported in detail. This study was performed in order to evaluate the clin-
icopathological characteristics and prognostic factors of cHCC-CC in single center. Methods: The clinicopathological 
fea¬tures of patients diagnosed and operated with cHCC-CC at Chonbuk National Hospital between July 1998 and 
July 2007 were retrospectively studied by comparing them with patients with only hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) who 
had undergone a hepatic resection during the same period. Results: Ten out of 152 patients who had undergone 
a hepatic resection were diagnosed with cHCC-CC and thus included in this study (M : F=8 : 2, median age: 52±11.1 
years). According to the parameters of the 7th American Joint Committee on Cancer T staging, there were 76 (50.0%), 
44 (28.9%), 9 (5.9%), 18 (11.8%) and 5 (3.3%) patients with T stages 1, 2, 3a, 3b and 4, respectively. The overall 
survival period was longer in the HCC only group (68±40.4 months) than in the combined cHCC-CC group (23±40.1 
months) (p＜0.0001). The 5-year survival rate was 10% in the cHCC-CC group and 60% in the HCC group (p＜0.0001). 
The disease free survival for patients with cHCC-HCC and HCC were 16±37.4 and 51±44.3 months, respectively (p 
＜0.0001). Univariate analysis revealed that age, gender, transarterial chemoembolization (TACE), and T stage were 
statistically significant in terms of patient's overall survival. However, there were no significant clinicopathological factors 
identified by the multivariate analysis. Conclusions: Even after the hepatic resection in the HCC, the prognosis is poorer 
if the patient has cholangiocellular components compared to the usual HCC. (Korean J Hepatobiliary Pancreat Surg 
2013;17:152-156) </p>

<p>Combined hepatocellular carcinoma and cholangio-</p>

<p>carcinoma (cHCC-CC) is a rare subtype of liver cancer </p>

<p>displaying components of both hepatocellular and chol-</p>

<p>angiocellular carcinoma. The World Health Organization </p>

<p>(WHO) classification defines combined HCC-CC, classi-</p>

<p>cal type as a tumor containing unequivocal elements of </p>

<p>both hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) and cholangio-</p>

<p>carcinoma (CC), which are intimately admixed; this tumor </p>

<p>should be distinguished from separate HCC and CC aris-</p>

<p>ing in the same liver. 1 </p>

<p>Primary liver cancer is a major worldwide health </p>

<p>problem. Most primary cancers of the liver are classified </p>

<p>into two major types: hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC), </p>

<p>which originates in the hepatocytes, and cholangiocar-</p>

<p>cinoma (CC), which originates from the epithelial cells in </p>

<p>the bile duct. Many reports have examined the clinical </p>

<p>features, survival outcomes or prognostic factors of </p>

<p>cHCC-CC. 2-4 To define the clinicopathologic features and </p>

<p>clinical out-comes more fully, we compared patients with </p>

<p>combined tumors to those with pure HCC. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Patients 
A total of 152 patients with primary liver cancer, ex-</p>

<p>cept CC, underwent hepatic resection between July 1, </p>

<p>1998 and July 31, 2007 at Chonbuk National University </p>

<p>Hospital. </p>

<p>Sang Eun Park, et al. Combined hepatocellular carcinoma and cholangiocarcinoma 153 </p>

<p>Table 1. Clinicopathological characteristics of patients with HCC and cHCC-CC </p>

<p>HCC (n=142) 
cHCC-CC (n=10) 
p-value </p>

<p>Age (yrs) 
Gender 
Male 
Female 
Etiology 
HBV 
HCV 
Alcoholic 
HBV &amp; alcoholic 
Non-specific 
Laboratory lab 
AST (IU/L) 
ALT (IU/L) 
AFP (ng/ml) 
Operation method 
Segmentectomy 
Wedge resection 
Hemihepatectomy 
Enucleation 
Liver transplantation 
TACE 
No 
Pre-operative TACE 
Post-operative TACE 
Both 
Tumor stage 
T1 
T2 
T3a 
T3b 
T4 </p>

<p>55 (25-75) </p>

<p>120 (84.5%) 
22 (15.5%) </p>

<p>58 (40.8%) 
5 (3.5%) 
10 (7.0%) 
1 (0.7%) 
68 (47.9%) </p>

<p>52 (15-438) 
45 (10-348) 
2,997 (1.6-87,500) </p>

<p>70 (49.3%) 
44 (31.0%) 
16 (11.3%) 
10 (7.0%) 
2 (1.4%) </p>

<p>46 (32.4%) 
1 (0.7%) 
89 (62.7%) 
6 (4.2%) </p>

<p>74 (52.1%) 
41 (28.9%) 
8 (5.6%) 
15 (10.6%) 
4 (2.8%) </p>

<p>52 (39-70) </p>

<p>8 (80.0%) 
2 (20.0%) </p>

<p>8 (80.0%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
2 (20.0%) </p>

<p>53 (30-87) 
40 (12-70) 
9,362 (5.4-75,680) </p>

<p>3 (30.0%) 
4 (40.0%) 
3 (30.0%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) </p>

<p>7 (70.0%) 
0 (0%) 
3 (30.0%) 
0 (0%) </p>

<p>2 (20.0%) 
3 (30.0%) 
1 (10.0%) 
3 (30.0%) 
1 (10.0%) </p>

<p>0.648 
0.706 </p>

<p>0.459 </p>

<p>0.925 
0.634 
0.467 
0.351 </p>

<p>0.115 </p>

<p>0.154 </p>

<p>HBV, hepatitis B virus; HCV, hepatitis C virus; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AFP, alpha-feto-
protein; TACE, transarterial chemoembolization </p>

<p>They were comprised of 10 patients with a histopatho-</p>

<p>logic diagnosis of combined tumor (cHCC-CC group) and </p>

<p>142 patients with HCC (HCC group). </p>

<p>Methods 
A retrospective review of a database provided in-</p>

<p>formation on the total number of patients. The variables </p>

<p>that were used to evaluate our series included the follow-</p>

<p>ing: clinical variables of age, sex, laboratory data, alpha-</p>

<p>fetoprotein (AFP), Hepatitis B (HBV) and hepatitis C </p>

<p>(HCV) viral markers, which included the HBV surface an-</p>

<p>tigen, operative type and pre or postoperative transarterial </p>

<p>chemoembolization (TACE). </p>

<p>Pathologically, all tumors were staged based on T stag-</p>

<p>ing of the AJCC (American Joint Committee on Cancer) </p>

<p>7th edition staging system. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Student's t-tests and χ2-tests were used for statistical </p>

<p>analysis. To identify predictors of survival, a univariate </p>

<p>analysis was performed using the Kaplan-Meier method </p>

<p>and compared with the log-lank test. A multivariate analy-</p>

<p>sis was performed using the Cox regression hazards model </p>

<p>in order to identify the independent prognostic factors. All </p>

<p>statistical analyses were made using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18.0</rs> for </p>

<p>Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>. Chicago, III). A p-value less than </p>

<p>0.05 was considered as statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Clinicopathological characteristics 
In the HCC (n=142) group, the median age was 55 </p>

<p>years (22-75); there were 120 men (84.5%) and 22 women </p>



<p>Fig. 1. Overall survival of patients with HCC and cHCC-CC. 
The overall survival of the cHCC-CC group was lower than 
the HCC group (p＜0.0001). 1-year, 3-year and 5-year surviv-
al rates in the HCC group were 82%, 73% and 60%, 
respectively. On the other hand, the cHCC-CC group showed 
downward results with 1-year, 3-year and 5-year survival 
rates at 20%, 20% and 10%, respectively. (p＜0.000) Mean 
survival period in the HCC and cHCC-CC groups were 
68±40.4 and 23±40.1 months, respectively. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Disease free survival of patients with HCC and 
cHCC-CC. The disease free survival of the cHCC-CC group 
was lower than the HCC group (p＜0.0001). 1-year, 3-year 
and 5-year disease free survival rates in the HCC group were 
67%, 59% and 50%, respectively. On the other hand, the 
cHCC-CC group showed 1-year, 3-year and 5-year survival 
rates of 10%, 10% and 10%, respectively (p＜0.0001). </p>

<p>(15.5%) (p=0.003). The prevalence of the hepatitis B sur-</p>

<p>face antigen was found in 58 (40.8%) patients; positive </p>

<p>serology for hepatitis C infection was found in 5 (3.5%) </p>

<p>patients. Alcoholic liver cirrhosis was found in 10 (7%) </p>

<p>patients. The hepatitis B surface antigen with alcoholic </p>

<p>liver cirrhosis was found in 1 (0.7%) patient (Table 1). </p>

<p>The median level of AFP was 2,997 ng/ml (1.6-</p>

<p>875,000). In terms of the operative method, segmentec-</p>

<p>tomy was performed in 70 (49.3%) patients. Wedge re-</p>

<p>section, hemihepatectomy, mass enucleation and liver </p>

<p>transplantation were performed in 44 (31%), 16 (11.3%), </p>

<p>10 (7%), and 2 (1.4%) patients, respectively. Pre-and </p>

<p>post-operative TACE were performed in 1 (0.7%) and 89 </p>

<p>(62.7%) patients, respectively. There were 74 (52.1%), 41 </p>

<p>(28.9%), 8 (5.6%), 15 (10.6%) and 4 (2.8%) patients with </p>

<p>T stages 1, 2, 3a, 3b and 4, respectively. </p>

<p>In the cHCC-CC (n=10) group, the median age was 52 </p>

<p>years (39-70); there were 8 men (80%) and 2 women </p>

<p>(20%). The prevalence of the hepatitis B surface antigen </p>

<p>was 8 (80%). </p>

<p>The median level of AFP was 9,361 ng/ml (5.4-75680). </p>

<p>Postoperative TACE was conducted in 3 (30%) patients. </p>

<p>There were 2 (20.0%), 3 (30.0%), 1 (10%), 3(30%) and </p>

<p>1 (10%) patients with T stages 1, 2, 3a, 3b and 4, </p>

<p>respectively. </p>

<p>There was no significant difference between the HCC </p>

<p>and cHCC-CC group based on the clinicopathological </p>

<p>factors. </p>

<p>Overall and disease-free survival rate of patients 
with HCC and cHCC-CC 
The 1-year overall survival rate was 82%, the 3-year </p>

<p>overall survival rate was 73%, and the 5-year overall sur-</p>

<p>vival rate was 60% in the HCC group. On the other hand, </p>

<p>the cHCC-CC group showed that the 1-year overall sur-</p>

<p>vival rate was 20%, the 3-year overall survival rate was </p>

<p>20%, and the 5-year overall survival rate was 10% </p>

<p>(p=0.000). Median survival periods in the HCC and </p>

<p>cHCC-CC groups were 68±40.4 and 23±40.1 months, re-</p>

<p>spectively (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>In the HCC group, the 1-year disease free survival rate </p>

<p>was 67%, the 3-year disease free survival rate was 59%, </p>

<p>and the 5-year disease free survival rate was 50%. On the </p>

<p>other hand, the cHCC-CC group indicated that the 1-year </p>

<p>disease free survival rate was 10%, the 3-year disease free </p>

<p>survival rate was 10%, and the 5-year disease free surviv-</p>

<p>al rate was 10% (p＜0.0001). </p>

<p>Except for 1 case in which the patient survived for 122 </p>

<p>months at the T1 stage, most patients in the cHCC-CC </p>

<p>group died or experienced recurrence within 1 year (Fig. </p>

<p>2). According to the overall survival rate, significant prog-</p>

<p>nostic factors in the cHCC-CC group were age (p=0.005), </p>

<p>Sang Eun Park, et al. Combined hepatocellular carcinoma and cholangiocarcinoma 155 </p>

<p>Table 2. Prognostic factors of overall survival in HCC and cHCC-CC </p>

<p>HCC (n=142) 
cHCC-CC (n=10) </p>

<p>Univariate analysis, 
p-value </p>

<p>Multivariate analysis, 
p-value </p>

<p>Univariate analysis, 
p-value </p>

<p>Multivariate analysis, 
p-value </p>

<p>Age (≥60 vs.60＜) 
Gender (Male vs. Female) 
Etiology (HBV/HCV vs. Non-viral) 
AST (＞40 IU/L) 
ALT (＞40 IU/L) 
AFP (＞400 ng/ml) 
TACE (Yes vs. No) 
T stage (I/II vs. III/IV) </p>

<p>0.335 
0.003 
0.007 
0.000 
0.003 
0.538 
0.007 
0.006 </p>

<p>0.097 
0.021 
0.014 
0.513 </p>

<p>0.075 
0.005 </p>

<p>0.005 
0.046 
0.393 
0.767 
0.092 
0.055 
0.009 
0.029 </p>

<p>0.594 
0.278 </p>

<p>0.951 
0.059 </p>

<p>AST, aspartate aminotransferase; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AFP, alpha-fetoprotein,; TACE, transarterial chemoembolization; 
HBV, hepatitis B virus; HCV, hepatitis C virus </p>

<p>Table 3. Prognostic factors of disease free survival in HCC and cHCC-CC </p>

<p>HCC (n=142) 
cHCC-CC (n=10) </p>

<p>Univariate analysis, 
p-value </p>

<p>Multivariate analysis, 
p-value </p>

<p>Univariate analysis, 
p-value </p>

<p>Multivariate analysis, 
p-value </p>

<p>Age (≥60 vs. 60＜) 
Gender (Male vs. Female) 
Etiology (HBV/HCV vs. Non virus) 
AST (＞40 IU/L) 
ALT (＞40 IU/L) 
AFP (＞400 ng/ml) 
TACE (Yes vs. No) 
T stage (I/II vs. III/IV) </p>

<p>0.201 
0.002 
0.053 
0.000 
0.002 
0.440 
0.000 
0.002 </p>

<p>0.118 </p>

<p>0.061 
0.332 </p>

<p>0.002 
0.009 </p>

<p>0.006 
0.046 
0.826 
0.736 
0.030 
0.092 
0.069 
0.005 </p>

<p>0.695 
0.468 </p>

<p>0.955 </p>

<p>0.169 </p>

<p>AST, aspartate aminotransferase; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AFP, alpha-fetoprotein; TACE, transarterial chemoembolization; 
HBV, hepatitis B virus; HCV, hepatitis C virus </p>

<p>sex (p=0.046), TACE (p=0.009) and T stage (p=0.029) in </p>

<p>the univariate analysis, but not in the multivariate analysis </p>

<p>(Table 2). </p>

<p>According to the disease free survival rate, significant </p>

<p>prognostic factors in the cHCC-CC group were age (p= </p>

<p>0.006), sex (p=0.046), preoperative alanine transaminase </p>

<p>(ALT) (p=0.03) and T stage (p=0.005) in the univariate </p>

<p>analysis, but not in the multivariate analysis (Table 3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>cHCC-CC is an uncommon liver malignancy with dis-</p>

<p>tinctive features compared with HCC and CC in respect </p>

<p>to its clinicopathologic changes and prognosis. The in-</p>

<p>cidence of cHCC-CC varies widely, from a rate of 2.4% </p>

<p>to 14.2%. 2 In our study, the incidence of cHCC-CC was </p>

<p>6.6%. Generally, the clinicopathological features of </p>

<p>cHCC-CC were similar to those of HCC. </p>

<p>5,8 </p>

<p>Most cHCC-CC patients in our series were men with </p>

<p>a high prevalence of HBV, suggesting that HBV infection </p>

<p>is a main cause for both HCC and cHCC-CC in Asia. </p>

<p>According to AFP, the elevation of AFP was found in both </p>

<p>groups. Some authors reported that high elevation of the </p>

<p>AFP level (≥400 IU/L) was an independent prognostic </p>

<p>factor in cHCC-CC. 5,7 On the other hand, Jarnagin et al. </p>

<p>reported that the level of AFP in cHCC-CC was lower </p>

<p>than that in HCC, but had no significant difference. 
10 In </p>

<p>our study, there was no significant difference in the AFP </p>

<p>levels as well as in the statistical relationship with a sur-</p>

<p>vival rate between the HCC-CC group and the HCC group. </p>

<p>The number of tumor and UICC stage in cHCC-CC </p>

<p>were predictive factors of the overall survival rate. 2 Our </p>

<p>study demonstrated that the T stage was related to a sig-</p>

<p>nificant difference in the survival rate in the univariate </p>



<p>analysis, but not in multivariate analysis. </p>

<p>cHCC-CC patients had poorer prognosis compared to </p>

<p>HCC patients, and CC had a relatively unfavorable prog-</p>

<p>nosis compared with cHCC-CC and HCC. 
5,9 In our study, </p>

<p>the cHCC-CC group had significantly poorer prognosis </p>

<p>than the HCC patients. Okuda 
12 reported that patient prog-</p>

<p>nosis with cHCC-CC was poorer than that of HCC be-</p>

<p>cause lymph node metastasis occurred more frequently. In </p>

<p>our study, the disease free survival rate was 16 months </p>

<p>and T stage was a significant prognostic factor. </p>

<p>TACE is indicated for patients with non-resectable or </p>

<p>recurrent HCC for palliative purposes because it has been </p>

<p>proved to increase the survival of these patients. However, </p>

<p>the therapeutic effect of TACE for cHCC-CCs remains </p>

<p>unclear. Compared with HCC, many cHCC-CCs are less </p>

<p>vascular than HCC and thus, may poorly respond to </p>

<p>TACE. Other reports showed that patients in advanced-</p>

<p>stage disease cases who had received TACE treatment had </p>

<p>a significantly longer 6-month survival than patients who </p>

<p>received supportive treatment. 8,13,14 </p>

<p>Our 3 patients who underwent TACE showed a sig-</p>

<p>nificant improvement in the survival rate. Some studies re-</p>

<p>ported radiation treatment attempts to patients with non-re-</p>

<p>sectable or local recurrent tumor for a better survival rate. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>There are some limitations in our study. First, this study </p>

<p>was retrospective and could have been affected by any and </p>

<p>all of the limitations of this investigational design. </p>

<p>Second, both HCC and cHCC-CC were compared with-</p>

<p>out CC. </p>

<p>In conclusion, most reports have indicated that surgical </p>

<p>intervention was an effective treatment for cHCC-CC. </p>

<p>However, patients with cHCC-CC have a significantly </p>

<p>poorer survival outcome after hepatic resection than do </p>

<p>patients with HCC. Further studies on effective treatment </p>

<p>modalities and clinical predictors for cHCC-CC are re-</p>

<p>quired in order to prolong the survival of these patients. </p>



</text></tei>