<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4590259" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Background: UNICEF and WHO recommend colostrum as newborns' perfect food that should 
be initiated within the first hour after birth. 
Objective: To assess colostrum avoidance practices and associated factors among mothers of 
children aged &lt;24 months in Raya Kobo district, North-eastern Ethiopia. 
Methods: A quantitative community-based cross-sectional study supplemented by qualitative 
method was used. Descriptive statistics, binary and multivariable logistic regression analyses were 
used in the statistical analysis. 
Results: Colostrum avoidance was practiced by 13.5% (95% confidence interval: 10.99-16.33) of 
mothers having children aged &lt;24 months. In multivariable logistic regression analysis, giving birth 
at home, mother-heading households, lack of awareness on the advantages of colostrum and late ini-
tiation of breastfeeding remained statistically significant factors associated with colostrum avoidance 
practices. 
Conclusion: Promoting institutional delivery, timely initiation of breastfeeding and creating 
awareness on the advantages of colostrum feeding are recommended interventions to reduce colos-
trum avoidance. </p>

<p>K E Y W O R D S : colostrum, Raya Kobo, Ethiopia. </p>

<p>B A C K G R O U N D 
Optimal breastfeeding practices rank among the 
most effective interventions to improve child health 
[1]. Studies showed that globally 60% of infant and 
young child deaths attributed to suboptimal </p>

<p>breastfeeding practices [1-3]. Suboptimal breast-
feeding is responsible for 45% of neonatal infectious 
deaths, 30% of diarrheal deaths and 18% of acute re-
spiratory deaths in children &lt;5 years of age [4]. The </p>

<p>V C The Author [2015]. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, 
please contact journals.permissions@oup.com </p>



<p>357 </p>

<p>Journal of Tropical Pediatrics, 2015, 61, 357-363 
doi: 10.1093/tropej/fmv039 
Advance Access Publication Date: 2 July 2015 
Original Paper </p>

<p>risk of mortality due to diarrheal and other infectious 
diseases is higher in infants who are either partially 
breastfed or not breastfed at all [1]. In Ethiopia, 
about 18% of the infant deaths have been attributed 
to poor feeding practices [5]. 
The practice of optimal breastfeeding starts from 
the first minute of birth. UNICEF and WHO recom-
mend colostrum as newborns' perfect food that 
should be initiated within the first hour after birth. 
Colostrum is the first liquid that is produced in the 
first few hours after delivery [6]. It is called 'inger' in 
Amharic language by the rural Amhara communities 
[7]. Colostrum is thick, sticky and clear to yellowish 
in color. It contains proteins, vitamin A and maternal 
antibodies important to the newborn's nutrition until 
lactation is fully established [6]. 
Colostrum establishes important bacteria in the 
baby's gut. It also acts as 'paint', coating the infant's 
gastrointestinal tract. Therefore, colostrum provides 
natural immunity (baby's first immunization) against 
many bacteria and viruses [6, 8]. In contrary to these 
advantages, colostrum is considered heavy, thick, 
dirty, toxic and harmful to children's health and 
therefore in some societies, a portion of colostrum is 
discarded [7, 9, 10]. This is also a common practice 
in Ethiopia [11]. 
Colostrum feeding was recommended in the 
Ethiopian Infant and Young Child Feeding Guideline 
that was developed in 2004 [12]. However, colos-
trum avoidance is still practiced in many parts of 
Ethiopia including Amhara regional state. Moreover, 
there is a paucity of evidence regarding factors asso-
ciated with colostrum avoidance in Ethiopia, particu-
larly in Raya Kobo District. Hence, this study aimed 
to investigate factors associated with colostrum avoid-
ance among mothers of children aged &lt;24 
months in Raya Kobo District, North-eastern 
Ethiopia. </p>

<p>M E T H O D S </p>

<p>Study design and sampling procedure 
This study was conducted in Raya Kobo district of 
Amhara region, North-eastern Ethiopia from 
December to 18 January 2014. A quantitative 
community-based cross-sectional study, supplemented 
by a qualitative study, was used on mothers of </p>

<p>children aged &lt;24 months. In this study, 630 
mother-child pairs were included. There are 42 
kebeles (the smallest administrative unit in Ethiopia) 
in Raya Kobo district. One urban kebele and seven 
rural kebeles were selected by simple random sam-
pling technique for this study. The sample size was 
proportionally allocated for urban and rural kebeles 
by assuming there could be a difference regarding col-
ostrum avoidance between urban and rural residents. 
The households that had eligible study subjects were 
identified by the assistance of the health extension 
workers logbook, and systematic random sampling 
technique was used to choose the household for the 
interview. </p>

<p>Measurements 
In this study, the outcome variable was colostrum 
avoidance practice among mothers of children aged 
&lt;24 months. Colostrum avoidance is the failure to 
feed infants the first, thick and yellowish milk that is 
produced in the first 3 days after birth [6]. Avoiding 
colostrum was coded as '1', while colostrum feeding 
was coded as '0' for regression analysis. The independ-
ent variables were maternal characteristics (age, educa-
tional status, religion, ethnicity and marital status), 
household characteristics (area of residence, i.e. urban-
rural, household head and family size), husband's edu-
cational status, child's sex, antenatal care utilization, 
place of delivery, breastfeeding initiation and the moth-
er's awareness on the advantages of colostrum feeding. 
Antenatal care utilization was defined as having at least 
one visit to a health institution for checkup purpose 
during the pregnancy of the index child [13]. </p>

<p>Data collection instrument and process 
Quantitative data were collected using a pretested, 
structured and interviewer-administered question-
naire adopted from the Ethiopian Demographic and 
Health Survey [11] and the national nutrition survey 
questionnaire [14]. The quantitative data were 
collected by trained data collectors using the 
Amharic version of the questionnaire. Focus group 
discussions (FGDs) and in-depth interviews were 
used to collect the qualitative data by a trained 
BSc nurse with the assistance of two note takers. The 
participants for FGD and in-depth interviews were </p>



<p>selected purposively based on their role in the com-
munity to explore cultural beliefs about colostrum 
avoidance practices. Two FGDs were undertaken in 
a group of grandmothers (women who had at least 
one grandchild), each composed of eight discussants. 
The in-depth interviews were undertaken with four 
traditional birth attendants (two trained and two un-
trained traditional birth attendants). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
After the completeness and consistency of the 
quantitative data were checked on the printed form 
of the questionnaire, it was cleaned, coded and 
entered into <rs id="software-0" type="software">EpiData</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.02</rs>. The data analysis 
was performed by using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">16.0</rs> statis-
tical package for analysis. Descriptive statistics were 
used to show the prevalence of colostrum avoidance 
practices, reason for discarding colostrum and the 
mother's awareness on the advantages of colostrum. 
Binary and multivariable logistic regression analyses 
were carried out to identify the factors associated 
with colostrum avoidance. Variables found statistic-
ally significant at p-value &lt;0.25 [15] during binary 
logistic regression analysis were included in the 
multivariable logistic regression model. Both crude 
and adjusted odds ratios (AORs) were reported 
with 95% confidence interval (CI). Variables at p-
value &lt;0.05 in the final multivariable model were 
concluded as factors associated with colostrum 
avoidance. 
Qualitative data were transcribed into English text 
by the principal investigator. Thematic framework 
analysis approach was used to analyze the qualitative 
data. Finally, the result was presented in triangula-
tion with the quantitative findings. </p>

<p>Ethical consideration 
A letter of ethical approval was obtained from the 
Institutional Health Research Ethics Review 
Committee of Haramaya University. Permission 
was obtained from Raya Kobo district and a support 
letter was written to each selected kebele. Informed 
written consent was taken from the participants 
before the interview. Illiterate mothers were con-
sented by their thumb print after verbal consent. 
The participants were also assured about the confi-
dentiality of the information they provided. </p>

<p>R E S U L T S </p>

<p>Colostrum avoidance practices 
Colostrum was discarded by 13.5% (95% CI: 10.99-
16.33) of mothers of children aged &lt;24 months. 
Among those who discarded colostrum, 25.9% of 
mothers reasoned out that they believe colostrum is 
not good. Above 23.5% of the mothers discarded col-
ostrums because it is tradition. About 58% of moth-
ers were not aware about advantages of colostrum 
(Table 1). </p>

<p>In relation to colostrum avoidance, a 39 year old dis-
cussant said, 'colostrum cannot prevent disease rather 
it causes abdominal cramp; it is yellowish dirty food 
that should be discarded' (FGD-Grandmother). </p>

<p>Mothers reported that the most influential individ-
uals for colostrum avoidance were grandmothers 
(44%), untrained traditional birth attendants (44%) 
and husbands (12%). </p>

<p>In support of the idea of colostrum discarding, a 
42 year old mother said, 'in our community colos-
trum is believed to cause abdominal cramp, there-
fore to prevent such problem as grandmother of 
children I recommend my daughter to discard col-
ostrum for the first three days before breastfeeding 
initiation' (FGD-Grandmother). 
A 45 year old woman said, 'Since colostrum 
causes abdominal cramp and raw butter cleans 
infants' stomach, I recommend mothers to discard 
colostrum and to feed their infants with raw but-
ter before breastfeeding initiation. In rich families 
mothers discard colostrum and feed newborns 
with raw butter within the first 3-7 days' 
(In-depth interview-untrained traditional birth 
attendant). 
A 37 year old woman said, 'Since colostrum is 
sticky and yellowish it seems dirty, but I recom-
mend mothers to feed their infants with colos-
trums' (In-depth interview-trained traditional 
birth attendant). </p>

<p>Binary logistic regression analysis showed that living 
in rural places, mother-heading households, giving 
birth at home, late initiation of breastfeeding and </p>

<p>Community-based Cross-sectional Study 359 </p>

<p>mothers that did not know advantages of colostrum 
were statistically associated with colostrum avoidance 
at p-value &lt;0.25 (Table 2). However, maternal age, 
educational status, ethnicity, marital status, husband's 
educational status and antenatal care attendance 
were not found significantly associated with colos-
trum avoidance at p-value &lt;0.25 in the binary logis-
tic regression model. Thus, these variables were not 
included in multivariable regression analysis model. 
In multivariable logistic regression analysis, giving 
birth at home, mother-heading households, lack of 
awareness on advantage of colostrum and late initi-
ation of breastfeeding remained statistically signifi-
cant factors associated with colostrum avoidance 
practices. Household-head mothers were 2.6 times 
(AOR ¼ 2.6; 95% CI: 1.08-6.44) more likely to dis-
card colostrum compared with mothers who were 
not household heads. Those mothers who delivered 
the index child at home were 2.6 times (AOR ¼ 2.6; 
95% CI: 1.13-5.79) more likely to discard colos-</p>

<p>trums as compared with mothers who gave birth at 
health institutions. Mothers who had late initiation 
of breastfeeding (initiation after 1 h of delivery) 
(AOR ¼ 2.4; 95% CI: 1.44-4.00) had more odds of 
discarding colostrum than mothers who initiated 
breastfeeding within 1 h after delivery. Mothers who 
did not know advantages of colostrum (AOR ¼ 5.5; 
95% CI: 2.63-11.32) were more likely to discard col-
ostrum than their counterparts (Table 2). </p>

<p>D I S C U S S I O N 
Breastfeeding practices are suboptimal in Raya Kobo 
district of North-eastern Ethiopia. In this study the 
prevalence of colostrum avoidance was 13.5% (95% 
CI: 10.99-16.33), which is higher than the preva-
lence of colostrum avoidance reported from Kersa 
district, South-eastern Ethiopia (8.5%) [16]. The 
national prevalence of colostrum avoidance was 
reported as 39.8% [14]. A relatively consistent preva-
lence of colostrum avoidance was found in the city 
of Bahir Dar (16.7%), north-western Ethiopia [17]. 
This could be due to the fact that the culture of 
Bahir Dar community is relatively similar to Raya 
Kobo district; both areas are dominated by the 
Amhara ethnic group. Colostrum avoidance is lower 
in Ethiopia as compared with the prevalence found 
in India (76.0%) [18] and Kuwait (81.8%) [19]. 
In this study, mothers of children aged &lt;24 
months reported that grandmothers and untrained 
traditional birth attendants were the most influential 
individuals to discard colostrum. Moreover, FGDs 
and in-depth interviews revealed that grandmothers 
and untrained traditional birth attendants thought 
colostrum causes abdominal cramp in infants. 
Therefore, they influence other mothers to discard 
colostrum. Likewise, grandmothers of the child tend 
to have strong influence on their daughters not to 
feed colostrum to their infants in Somalia [9] and 
Bangladesh [8]. 
Mothers who were not aware of the advantages of 
colostrum were 5.5 times more likely to discard col-
ostrum compared with mothers who were aware of 
the advantages of colostrum for infants. Similarly, 
colostrum is discarded primarily because of lack of 
basic information about the importance of colostrum 
for infants in Somali [9]. In addition, qualitative find-
ings in Raya Kobo showed that, mothers thought </p>

<p>Table 1. Distribution of respondents based on 
colostrum avoidance practices in Raya Kobo 
district, 2014 </p>

<p>Variable 
Frequency (n) (%) </p>

<p>Mother knows what colostrum is? 
(n ¼ 630) 
Yes 
348 (55.2) 
No 
282 (44.8) 
Colostrum discarded (n ¼ 630) 
Yes 
85 (13.5) 
No 
545 (86.5) 
Reasons to discard 
colostrum(n ¼ 85) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Colostrum is not good 
22 (25.9) 
Tradition 
20 (23.5) 
Colostrum is dirty 
19 (22.4) 
Influenced by other person 
16 (18.8) 
Infant unable to feed 
13 (15.3) 
Delayed lactation 
11 (12.9) 
Colostrum is yellow/thick 
9 (10.6) 
Awareness on advantages of 
colostrums (n ¼ 630) 
Yes 
366 (58.1) 
No 
264 (41.9) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Variables with multiple responses. </p>



<p>colostrum as yellowish-dirty milk that is not good for 
infants. A study in Tigray region of Ethiopia also re-
vealed that colostrum is perceived as not good for in-
fants, and more than half of the mothers had no 
knowledge on colostrum feeding [20]. Other studies 
from Goba, South-eastern Ethiopia and Jimma Arjo, 
South-western Ethiopia districts also found that col-
ostrum is believed to cause disease [10, 21]. There 
were also similar findings from Foni Kansala district 
of Gambia [22]. 
Late initiation of breastfeeding was associated 
with colostrum avoidance practices. Compared with 
mothers who initiated breastfeeding within 1 h of de-
livery, mothers who initiated breastfeeding beyond 
1 h of delivery were 2.4 times more likely to discard 
colostrum. This could be because of the fact that </p>

<p>those mothers who discarded the colostrum might 
take more time to discard it and initiate breastfeeding 
later. The reverse might be also correct. When moth-
ers tend to initiate breastfeeding later, they would 
have more time for infant feeding malpractices like 
colostrum avoidance. 
Mothers who delivered the index child at home 
were 2.6 times more likely to practice colostrum 
avoidance compared with mothers who gave birth at 
health institutions. Similarly, in India, mothers who 
gave birth at home were more likely to discard colos-
trum compared with mothers who gave birth at 
health institutions [23]. Grandmothers and trad-
itional birth attendants usually attend the birth in 
homes. The FGDs and in-depth interviews findings 
showed that grandmothers and traditional birth </p>

<p>Table 2. Binary and multivariable logistic regression analysis showing factors associated with colos-
trum avoidance among mothers of children aged less than 24 months in Raya Kobo district, 2014 </p>

<p>Variable 
Colostrum 
avoidance n (%) </p>

<p>Crude odds 
ratio (COR) 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Adjusted odds 
ratio (AOR) 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Residence 
Urban 
5(5.7) 
1 
1 
Rural 
80 (14.8) 
2.9 (1.13-7.31) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.7 (0.59-4.66) 
Religion of mother 
Orthodox 
52 (12.3) 
1 
1 
Muslim 
33 (15.9) 
1.4 (0.84-2.17) 
0.9 (0.56-1.65) 
Household headship 
Mothers of index child 
16 (28.1) 
2.8(1.52-5.35) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>2.6(1.08-6.44) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Other person </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>69 (12.0) 
1 
1 
Family size 
2 
6 (26) 
2.4 (0.91-6.46) 
1.0 (0.24-4.15) 
3-4 
31 (13.5) 
1.1 (0.66-1.75) 
0.9 (0.55-1.69) 
&gt;5 
48 (10) 
1 
1 
Delivery place 
Home 
76 (15.9) 
3 (1.47-6.15) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>2.6 (1.13-5.79) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Health institution 
9 (5.9) 
1 
1 
Breastfeeding initiation time 
&lt;1 h 
40 (8.9) 
1 
1 
&gt;1 h 
38 (21.6) 
2.8 (1.73-4.55) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>2.4 (1.44-4.00) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Maternal awareness on advantage of colostrums 
Yes 
12 (4.5) 
1 
1 
No 
73 (19.9) 
5.2 (2.78-9.86) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>5.5 (2.63-11.32) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Respondent's husband, father and mother. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Statistically significant variables at p &lt; 0.05. Hosmer-Lemeshowgoodness-of-fit ¼ 0.719. </p>

<p>Community-based Cross-sectional Study 361 </p>

<p>attendants thought colostrum caused abdominal 
cramps in infants. Therefore, giving birth at home 
may create a favorable environment for different 
socio-cultural malpractices such as the practice of col-
ostrum avoidance. Alternatively, mothers who gave 
birth in health institutions might be advised by health 
professionals about the advantages of colostrum. 
Household-head mothers were 2.6 times more 
likely to discard colostrum compared with mothers 
who were not household heads. This could be ex-
plained in such a way that mothers who were house-
hold heads might be self-directed and may lack the 
supportive advice offered on the importance of col-
ostrum feeding for newborns compared with moth-
ers who were not household heads. 
One of the strengths of this study was that it 
included both quantitative and qualitative methods. 
This study has also limitations. The first limitation 
was that information obtained from mothers having 
children aged &lt;24 months is subject to recall 
bias. The study also shares the limitation of the 
cross-sectional study design. </p>

<p>C O N C L U S I O N 
Colostrum avoidance was more common among 
mothers who lacked awareness on the advantages of 
colostrum feeding, who gave birth at home, who 
practiced improper commencement of breastfeeding 
and mothers who were household heads. Promoting 
institutional delivery, timely initiation of breastfeed-
ing and creating awareness on the advantages of col-
ostrum feeding are recommended interventions to 
reduce colostrum avoidance. </p>

<p>F U N D I N G 
This work was supported by Haramaya University. 
The funders had no role in study design, data collec-
tion and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation 
of the manuscript. </p>

<p>A C K N O W L E D G E M E N T S </p>

<p>We authors thank Haramaya University, data collectors, 
supervisors and respondents. </p>

<p>R E F E R E N C E S </p>







<p>Community-based Cross-sectional Study 363 </p>

</text></tei>