<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4174215" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: One of the primary benefits of breast conserving therapy 
(BCT) is the potential ability to preserve the aesthetic appearance of the 
breast. However, current literature and clinical experience suggest that the 
aesthetic benefits of BCT may not be equally shared among ethnic groups. 
This is a pilot study that uses novel techniques to evaluate the cosmetic out-
comes of African American and white women following BCT. 
Methods: A total of 21 participants (10 African American and 11 white) 
completed the study. Cosmetic outcomes following BCT were evaluated by a 
multidisciplinary team using both quantitative and qualitative measures, in-
cluding 3-dimensional photographic analysis and a pilot questionnaire. Pre-
liminary measures were taken to evaluate the validity of the questionnaire. 
Results: There were no statistically significant differences in objective mea-
sures of breast symmetry between African American patients and white 
patients (P &gt; 0.05 in all cases). However, all raters reported the African 
American patients to have worse breast symmetry and appearance when 
compared with white patients. Interrater reliability was found to be fair 
with regard to the nipple complex questions [intraclass correlation (ICC), 
0.56], good with regard to the breast mound questions (ICC, 0.66), and 
poor with regard to the scar appearance questions (ICC = 0.32). 
Conclusions: Although generalizing the results of this study is limited by the 
small sample size, it seems that there is a difference in the perception of cos-
metic outcomes between white and African American patients. The novel 
techniques of cosmetic evaluation used in this study show promise toward 
identifying variables that can affect cosmetic outcome following BCT. (Plast 
Reconstr Surg Glob Open 2013;1:e94; Elliot M. Hirsch, MD* 
Christiana S. U. Chukwu, BA* 
Zeeshan Butt, PhD † ‡ 
Seema A. Khan, MD ‡ 
Robert D. Galiano, MD* </p>

<p>A Pilot Assessment of Ethnic Differences 
in Cosmetic Outcomes following Breast 
Conservation Therapy </p>

<p>Copyright © 2014 The Authors. Published by Lippincott 
Williams &amp; Wilkins on behalf of The American Society of 
Plastic Surgeons. PRS Global Open is a publication of the 
American Society of Plastic Surgeons. This is an open-access 
article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 3.0 License, where 
it is permissible to download and share the work provided it 
is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or 
used commercially. 
DOI: 10.1097/GOX.0000000000000013 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>PRS GO • 2014 </p>



<p>may experience worse postoperative cosmesis than 
white women. 
1-3 For example, previous studies have 
identified 19-28% of African American patients as 
having fair/poor outcomes (72-81% with excellent/ 
good outcomes) compared with 5-18% of white pa-
tients who have fair/poor outcomes (82-95% with 
excellent/good outcomes). </p>

<p>1-3 </p>

<p>However, these studies are hampered by 2 main 
issues: first, there is no consensus as to what con-
stitutes an optimal aesthetic result following BCT, 
and second, no validated assessment instrument 
of aesthetic outcomes exists to help form such a 
consensus. 
4,5 Although it is likely that there are 
many factors that affect aesthetic outcomes fol-
lowing BCT such as scarring and reaction to radia-
tion, these variables are not captured in existing 
assessments. 
1-3,6 This lack of specificity is signifi-
cant given that preserving breast aesthetics is one 
of the primary goals of BCT. If the factors that in-
fluence aesthetic outcomes following BCT can be 
established, it may be possible to tailor treatment 
regimens to optimize aesthetics while preserving 
oncologic efficacy. 
Therefore, both to evaluate cosmetic differences 
between African American and white patients fol-
lowing BCT and to take an initial step toward the 
development of a consensus-driven evaluation to de-
fine optimal cosmetic outcome in BCT, we propose 
a multimodal approach to assessment that includes 
patient-and clinician-reported outcome measures 
and objective measurements. To this end, this study 
reports on the outcome data from a pilot study of 
African American and white women who underwent 
BCT at the Lynn Sage Comprehensive Breast Center 
at Northwestern Memorial Hospital. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>This study received institutional review board ap-
proval from Northwestern University before the con-
duct of any study-related activities. </p>

<p>Participants 
Potential participants were prospectively iden-
tified as they presented to the Lynn Sage Compre-
hensive Breast Center at Northwestern Memorial 
Hospital. Patients were eligible if they were English-
speaking, over 21 years old, and had completed uni-
lateral BCT at least 1 year before study enrollment. </p>

<p>Patients were not eligible if they had undergone 
any reconstructive or cosmetic procedures on ei-
ther breast at any point in the past or if the patient 
had previously undergone any surgical procedures 
on the nontreated breast. A total of 21 patients (10 
African American and 11 white) provided informed 
consent and completed the study. </p>

<p>Biometric Measurements 
To obtain objective measurements of the symme-
try between the treated and untreated breasts, the fol-
lowing measurements were made bilaterally for each 
patient: nipple to inframammary fold distance, mid-
clavicle to nipple distance, and nipple to the center of 
the sternum distance. In addition, the 3-dimensional 
Vectra camera (Canfield Imaging Systems, N.J.) was 
used to calculate the breast volume of the treated and 
untreated sides as demonstrated in Figures 1-4. </p>

<p>Qualitative Ratings 
The patient and a plastic surgeon, a breast on-
cologic surgeon, and a trained clinical research as-</p>

<p>Fig. 1. example of 3D image of surgical site in an african 
american patient. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. example of 3D image of surgical site in a white patient. </p>

<p>Disclosure: The authors have no financial interest 
to declare in relation to the content of this article. The 
Article Processing Charge was paid for by the authors. </p>

<p>Hirsch et al. • Ethnic Differences in Cosmetic Outcome following BCT </p>



<p>sistant filled out a questionnaire that evaluated both 
the appearance of the breast that had undergone 
BCT and the untreated breast. The questionnaire 
was developed by these investigators and an expert 
in patient-reported outcomes and was specifically 
designed to evaluate 13 aspects of breast cosme-
sis. The areas of breast cosmesis were divided into 
4 categories: nipple complex, breast mound, scar, 
and skin (Table 1). Each of these variables was rated 
on a 5-point scale, with 1 = poor and 5 = excellent. 
The plastic surgeon and the breast oncologic sur-
geon rated the patient based on photographs taken 
with a 3-dimensional Vectra camera (Canfield Im-
aging Systems), whereas the research assistant rated 
the patient based on the clinical examination. The 
research assistant and patient evaluated all 4 cate-
gories, whereas the plastic surgeon and the breast 
oncologic surgeon evaluated 3 categories: nipple 
complex, breast mound, and scar. </p>

<p>Data Analysis 
Patient health history and demographic informa-
tion was obtained through interview and through 
the review of electronic medical records. Table 2 
summarizes the patient demographic characteris-
tics. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 20</rs> predictive analytics soft-
ware was used in the analysis of all the statistical 
tests. Because multiple raters (plastic surgeon, breast 
oncologic surgeon, and research assistant) indepen-
dently assessed all patients, agreement in the obser-
vational ratings was tested via interrater reliability 
(IRR). Specifically, IRR was interpreted by calculat-
ing intraclass correlation (ICC) for interval variables 
in a 2-way, mixed-effect model. Student's t test with </p>

<p>Fig. 3. example of 3D image of quantitative measurements of 
breast symmetry in an african american patient. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. example of 3D image of quantitative measurements of 
breast symmetry in a white patient. </p>

<p>Table 1. Classification of Cosmetic Variables 
Assessed in This Study </p>

<p>Variables of Cosmesis </p>

<p>Nipple complex 
Nipple projection 
Areola shape 
Areola texture 
Breast mound 
Breast size 
Breast height 
Breast projection 
Skin 
Skin texture 
Firmness 
Tenderness 
Scar 
Surgical site 
Scar elevation 
Scar width 
Scar color </p>

<p>Table 2. Patient Demographic Characteristics </p>

<p>Characteristic </p>

<p>African 
American 
White </p>

<p>P 
n 
% 
n 
% </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
&gt;0.05 
&lt;50 
2 
20.0 
1 
9.1 
50-59 
5 
50.0 
6 
54.5 
60-69 
2 
20.0 
3 
27.3 
70-79 
1 
10.0 
1 
9.1 
BMI 
&gt;0.05 
18.5 to &lt;25 
1 
10.0 
4 
36.4 
25 to &lt;30 
5 
50.0 
1 
9.1 
30 to &lt;40 
3 
30.0 
6 
54.5 
≥40 
1 
10.0 
-
-
Time since last 
radiation 
treatment 
(mo) </p>

<p>&gt;0.05 </p>

<p>0-25 
7 
70.0 
4 
36.4 
26-50 
2 
20.0 
1 
9.1 
51-75 
-
-
1 
9.1 
76-100 
-
-
1 
9.1 
100-125 
-
-
1 
9.1 
Unknown 
1 
10.0 
3 
27.3 </p>

<p>BMI, body mass index. </p>

<p>PRS GO • 2014 </p>



<p>a 95% confidence interval was used to evaluate the 
biometric measures. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Results from the objective measurements of 
breast symmetry are displayed in Table 3. The aver-
age volume of the treated breast vs the untreated 
breast in African American patients was 530.3 cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>vs 617.5 cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, with an average difference of 90.4 cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>. 
The average volume of the treated breast vs the 
untreated breast in white patients was 512.7 cm 
3 vs 
541.5 cm 
3 , with an average difference of 101.3 cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>. 
There were no statistically significant differences ei-
ther in breast volume or in any of the symmetry mea-
surements between African American patients and 
white patients (P &gt; 0.05 in all cases). 
Results of the qualitative scores of breast cosmesis 
are displayed in Table 4. Regarding the qualitative 
measures, both the research assistant and patient 
reported a better nipple complex score for white </p>

<p>patients than for African American patients, whereas 
the plastic surgeon and breast oncologic surgeon 
rated the appearance of the nipple complex as be-
ing better in African American patients (Table 4). 
There was fair IRR in this section as indicated by 
the ICC of 0.56. 
7 For the breast mound category, all 
observers were in good agreement that the results 
of white patients were better than that of African 
American patients (ICC = 0.663). When evaluating 
the appearance of the scar, both the plastic surgeon 
and the breast oncologic surgeon reported better 
scaring results in African American patients than 
white patients, whereas the research assistant rated 
scar result as worse in African American patients. 
The ICC for this category was 0.316, showing poor 
IRR. Finally, both the research assistant and patients 
rated the appearance and feel of the skin as being 
better in white patients. Although the difference in 
research assistant's scores between African American 
and white was not significant (P &gt; 0.05), there was 
a statistically significant difference between the self-
reported scores provided by the patients (P &lt; 0.05); 
that is, African American patients consistently re-
ported their skin as having a worse appearance than 
the white patients. Overall, the differences in the 
ratings between patient groups provided by the plas-
tic surgeon, breast oncologic surgeon, and indepen-
dent observer were not statistically significant with 
the exceptions as noted above (P &gt; 0.05 in all cases). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The existing literature does not provide a clear 
picture regarding ethnic differences in cosmetic out-
come following BCT. This is in large part due to the 
fact that currently there is no consensus regarding 
optimal methods of measurement of cosmetic out-
come following BCT. 
4,5 Numerous researchers from </p>

<p>Table 3. Biometric Measures </p>

<p>African 
American White 
P </p>

<p>Average volume difference 
between the treated and 
untreated breast (cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) 
90.4 
101.3 &gt;0.05 
Average difference in distance 
of inframammary fold to 
treated breast vs untreated 
breast (cm) </p>

<p>0.9 
0.9 &gt;0.05 </p>

<p>Average in distance of mid-
clavicle to nipple of treated 
breast vs nipple of untreated 
breast (cm) </p>

<p>1.9 
1.1 &gt;0.05 </p>

<p>Average difference between 
medial areolar border of 
treated vs untreated breast to 
midsternum (cm) </p>

<p>1.5 
1.5 &gt;0.05 </p>

<p>Table 4. Interrater Reliability for Measures of Cosmesis </p>

<p>Cosmetic 
Parameter 
Rater </p>

<p>Average Score (Scale 1-5, with 
1 = Poor and 5 = Excellent) </p>

<p>Reliability/Significance 
African American 
White </p>

<p>Nipple complex 
Patient 
4.10 
4.48 
ICC = 0.56 
Plastic surgeon 
3.77 
3.66 
Breast oncologic surgeon 
4.67 
4.66 
Research assistant 
4.10 
4.16 
Breast mound 
Patient 
3.52 
3.92 
ICC = 0.66 
Plastic surgeon 
3.57 
4.09 
Breast oncologic surgeon 
3.89 
4.58 
Research assistant 
3.70 
4.13 
Scar 
Patient 
3.76 
4.56 
ICC = 0.32 
Plastic surgeon 
3.20 
3.14 
Breast oncologic surgeon 
4.53 
4.48 
Research assistant 
3.38 
4.07 
Skin 
Research assistant 
3.33 
3.74 
P = 0.33 
Patient 
3.76 
4.66 
P = 0.003 </p>

<p>Hirsch et al. • Ethnic Differences in Cosmetic Outcome following BCT </p>



<p>different disciplines, including plastic surgery, 
8,9 sur-
gical oncology, 
10 radiation oncology, 
1,3,11-15 and even 
multidisciplinary teams, 
16-20 have assessed cosmetic 
outcomes, using a variety of techniques. The vast 
majority of studies have evaluated results using some 
variation of a 4-point rating scale, frequently in con-
junction with a questionnaire that evaluates a global 
form of cosmesis. Although investigators have used 
validated instruments to evaluate BCT outcomes, </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>these measures only provided a general measure of 
patient satisfaction with their results and did not allow 
for specific identifiers in cosmesis, which could reveal 
dissatisfaction with the surgical scar, breast symmetry, 
or other variables. It remains that there is no consen-
sus regarding optimal methods of measurement of 
cosmetic outcome, 
4,5 and the question of ethnic dif-
ferences in cosmetic outcome remains unanswered. 
Other techniques that have been used by re-
searchers include directly measuring anatomic dif-
ferences between the patient's treated and untreated 
breasts, then using these measurements to extrapo-
late the relative symmetry between the breasts. In the 
past, these measurements were made on postopera-
tive pictures 
11-13,15 and patients were given symmetry 
scores. In addition, researchers evaluated the breasts 
for the presence of visible changes after BCT, such 
as telangiectasias or nipple retraction, which were 
also assigned scores. In more recent studies, 3-di-
mensional photographic analysis 
20 and sophisticated 
computer programs 
21 have been developed to evalu-
ate breast symmetry and cosmesis. Although these 
objective forms of measurement are clearly effective 
in identifying breast asymmetry after BCT, they can-
not assess breast texture, sensitivity, or fibrosis. Per-
haps most importantly, they only provide an objective 
measure of results and do not take into account the 
patient's opinion of their cosmesis, which arguably 
may provide the most important perspective. 
This study represents an attempt to not only iden-
tify the factors that contribute to specific differences 
in cosmetic outcome between African American and 
white patients but also to quantify these differences 
and include the patient's opinion in the rating of the 
appearance of the breasts. Given our small cohort, 
we cannot provide a definitive statement regarding 
causation for perceived differences in cosmetic out-
comes. With a larger sample size, it may be possible 
to identify subtle differences in rating that could 
identify areas of poor cosmesis that may be amenable 
to surgical correction. However, it is interesting to 
note that the objective measurements of breast volu-
metric differences and breast symmetric differences 
are similar between the white and African American 
groups (less than 20 cm 
3 volume and less than 1 cm 
difference between the 2 groups), yet all 4 observers </p>

<p>(plastic surgeon, breast oncologic surgeon, research 
assistant, and patient) consistently rated the Afri-
can American patients as having worse results with 
regard to breast mound symmetry and appearance. 
Moreover, there was also a statistically significant dif-
ference in the way that African American patients 
rated the appearance of their skin when compared 
with white patients. It is possible that despite hav-
ing similar objective measures of cosmesis, African 
American patients themselves perceive and are per-
ceived by others as having worse cosmetic outcomes 
than white patients. This is an interesting finding as 
it implies that surgical technique may not be enough 
to achieve better outcomes-a psychological compo-
nent may play a role as well. As this study progresses 
and the measures used to evaluate cosmesis become 
more clearly defined, these findings can be further 
investigated. The ICC rating of the nipple-areola 
complex and breast mound demonstrated fair to 
good IRR, which indicates the effectiveness of the 
questionnaire that was developed for this study. With 
continued validation techniques and the acquisition 
of more data, this questionnaire could become a 
valuable tool in helping quantify cosmetic outcomes 
following BCT. In the areas of the questionnaire relat-
ing to scarring and response to radiation, the differ-
ence between white and African American patients 
was larger than in the other measures of cosmesis 
that were evaluated in this study. This finding agrees 
with the clinical experience of the investigators and 
reports in the literature, which suggests that African 
American patients experience more severe physical 
reactions to radiation than white patients, including 
hyperpigmentation and adverse scarring. 
1-3 It has 
been suggested that these differences in response to 
radiation may have a genetic basis as single nucleo-
tide polymorphisms may potentially play a role in ra-
diation toxicity. 
22 Again, without a clear measure of 
cosmesis, it is difficult to quantify adverse outcomes 
and therefore identify candidate patients for genetic 
analysis. Moreover, the ICC rating was poor for the 
scar ratings, so further steps could include the ap-
plication of existing scar rating instruments to help 
further evaluate the variables examined in this study. 
Limitations of this study include its small sample 
size and the fact that the questionnaire has not been 
subject to rigorous analysis concerning its validity. 
Additionally, the small sample size precludes evalu-
ations on additional variables such as body mass 
index. However, this study is a pilot study and the re-
sults are not intended to be generalized to the larger 
patient population. With continued patient enroll-
ment and data analysis, this study could represent 
an important first step in optimizing cosmetic out-
comes following BCT. </p>

<p>PRS GO • 2014 </p>



<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>This study evaluates differences in cosmetic out-
come between African American and white women 
who have undergone BCT for breast cancer and be-
gins the process of developing qualitative measures 
to evaluate cosmetic outcome in this patient popula-
tion. It is important to identify which factors contrib-
ute to poor cosmesis as there is evidence that suggests 
body image, psychosocial morbidity, and self-esteem 
influence cosmetic results following BCT. 
16,23,24 Thus, 
by evaluating specific causes of poor cosmesis, it may 
be possible to modify treatment regimens to maxi-
mize quality of life outcomes while still maintaining 
oncologic efficacy. </p>

<p>Robert D. Galiano, MD 
Division of Plastic Surgery 
Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine 
Galter 19-250, 675 North St. Clair Street 
Chicago, IL 60611 
E-mail: rgaliano@nmh.org </p>



</text></tei>