<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4913573" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Echocardiographic assessment of diastolic function is challenging in cats, partially because of transmitral 
flow pattern fusion associated with high heart rates. With heart rate (HR) reduction, transmitral flow waveforms separate, 
allowing identification of diastolic dysfunction. Timolol, an ophthalmic, nonselective beta-blocker used in glaucoma is safe 
and transiently decreases HR in clinical trials. 
Hypothesis: Administration of timolol ophthalmic solution decreases HR and facilitates echocardiographic assessment of 
diastolic function in cats without inducing clinically relevant adverse effects. 
Animals: Twenty-five apparently healthy cats. 
Methods: Electrocardiograms and echocardiograms including transmitral flow patterns were evaluated before and 20 min-
utes after ocular administration of 1 drop of timolol 0.5% solution. Twenty cats underwent treatment with timolol, and 5 
different cats served as untreated controls to evaluate the effects of acclimation to the hospital environment on HR. 
Results: Acclimation to the hospital had no effect on HR in control cats. After timolol administration, a significant med-
ian HR reduction of 25 bpm was observed (P &lt; .0001). Timolol had no effect on E/A ratio in cats without E/A fusion (7/20, 
P = .44). Of the 13 cats with E and A waves that were fused before timolol application, separation of these waves was 
identified in 8 cats (62%) after timolol treatment. No bradyarrhythmias were noted after timolol administration, but 2 cats 
had first-degree atrioventricular block. Timolol resulted in resolution of dynamic outflow tract obstruction in 6 of 6 cats. 
Conclusions and clinical importance: Ocular administration of timolol safely decreases HR in cats and could facilitate 
assessment of diastolic function. 
H </p>

<p>ypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM) is the most 
commonly diagnosed cardiac disease in cats. </p>

<p>1-4 </p>

<p>The diagnosis of HCM is made when the left ventricu-
lar septum or free wall measurement is &gt;6 mm at the 
end diastole and no metabolic or cardiovascular causes 
of hypertrophy are identified. 
2 However, HCM is 
heterogeneous in its presentation and progression, and 
there is no consensus regarding the classification of cats 
with equivocal echocardiographic findings (ie, left ven-
tricular [LV] wall thickness 5.0-5.9 mm or segmental 
hypertrophy). 
a These factors makes early diagnosis of 
HCM a clinical challenge. The pathophysiology of 
HCM is due in part to diastolic dysfunction secondary 
to a hypertrophied LV. 
4 Diastolic dysfunction also is </p>

<p>implicated in other cardiomyopathies of cats such as 
restrictive cardiomyopathy. 
5 Doppler echocardiographic 
identification of impaired relaxation has been suggested 
as a possible means for detection of occult cardiomy-
opathy in cats. 
6-13 One of the techniques used to assess 
diastolic function is echocardiographic evaluation of 
transmitral flow patterns. Because transmitral flow can 
be affected by ventricular loading conditions, age, and 
heart rate, among other factors, its assessment should 
be interpreted in conjunction with other echocardio-
graphic and clinical variables such as case history or 
genetic testing to increase suspicion for occult car-
diomyopathy. Normal transmitral flow patterns consist 
of a peak in early diastole that corresponds with early </p>

<p>From the Department of Medicine &amp; Epidemiology, School of 
Veterinary Medicine, University of California Davis, Davis, CA 
(Gunther-Harrington, Ontiveros, Visser, Stern); Veterinary Medical 
Center, University of California, San Diego, CA (Hodge). 
All work was performed at the William R. Pritchard Veterinary 
Medical Teaching Hospital of the University of California, Davis. 
One Garrod Drive Davis, CA 95616, USA. Prior Publication/ 
Presentation: Presented as an oral abstract at 2015 ACVIM Forum, 
Indianapolis, IN. 
Corresponding author: J.A. Stern, DVM, PhD, DACVIM (Car-
diology), Department of Medicine and Epidemiology, School of 
Veterinary Medicine, University of California, Davis, One Shields 
Avenue, Davis, CA 95616; e-mail: jstern@ucdavis.edu. </p>

<p>Submitted September 12, 2015; Revised January 25, 2016; 
Accepted February 25, 2016. </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016 The Authors. Journal of Veterinary Internal 
Medicine published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of the Ameri-
can College of Veterinary Internal Medicine. 
This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License, which permits use, 
distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original 
work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes. 
DOI: 10.1111/jvim.13931 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: </p>

<p>ADRB1 
beta-1 adrenergic receptor gene 
A vel 
velocity of late diastolic transmitral flow 
DRVOTO 
dynamic right ventricular outflow tract obstruction 
E vel 
velocity of early diastolic transmitral flow 
E/A 
ratio of E vel and A vel 
FS 
fractional shortening 
HCM 
hypertrophic cardiomyopathy 
HOCM 
hypertrophic obstructive cardiomyopathy 
HR 
heart rate 
IVSd 
interventricular septum in diastole 
LVIDd 
left ventricular internal dimension during diastole 
LVIDs 
left ventricular internal dimension during systole 
LVPWd 
left ventricular free wall in diastole 
LVOT 
left ventricular outflow tract 
OD 
right eye 
P277Q 
missense mutation changing a proline to glutamine at 
the 277th amino acid 
UCD-VMTH University of California, Davis William R. Pritchard 
Veterinary Medical Teaching Hospital </p>

<p>J Vet Intern Med 2016;30:733-740 </p>

<p>left ventricular filling (E wave), and a second peak (A 
wave) that corresponds with atrial systole. 
14 In humans, 
dogs, and cats with impaired relaxation, an alteration in 
this pattern is noted. This change is characterized by a 
decrease in E velocity, prolonged E deceleration time, 
and an increase in atrial contribution to left ventricular 
filling, manifested as an increase in A velocity. </p>

<p>6,14,15 </p>

<p>Therefore, an E/A ratio &lt;1.0 suggests impaired relax-
ation. 
14,16 The high heart rates encountered in cats 
exposed to the clinical situation can lead to E and A 
wave fusion. 
9,10 When fusion is present, evaluation of 
the E and A velocities is not possible and therefore 
diastolic dysfunction could go undetected. 
Timolol is a nonselective beta-blocker, commonly 
used in dogs and cats for the treatment of glau-
coma. 
17,18 In 1 study, instillation of 1 drop of 0.5% 
timolol ophthalmic solution twice daily decreased heart 
rate (HR) in healthy cats by a mean of 17 bpm. 
19 Oph-
thalmic administration of timolol has been reported to 
decrease HR in healthy beagle dogs by 10%. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>The aims of this study were to (i) evaluate the clinical 
effectiveness of topical timolol ophthalmic solution in 
HR reduction and (ii) identify its effects on selected 
echocardiographic parameters in clinically healthy cats. 
We hypothesized that the administration of timolol 
ophthalmic solution would decrease HR and facilitate 
echocardiographic assessment of selected diastolic func-
tion parameters without clinically relevant adverse 
effects in cats. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>The study protocol was reviewed and approved by the 
University of California, Davis Animal Care and Use Committee 
protocol #18093. Signed consent was obtained from each owner 
before enrollment in the study. </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>Apparently healthy cats with and without heart murmurs were 
recruited from referring veterinarians, veterinary students and 
staff, and clinical cases presenting to the University of California 
Davis William R. Pritchard Veterinary Medical Teaching Hospital 
(UCD-VMTH). Cats with ocular disease, history of respiratory 
disease or cough, documented arrhythmia, or clinical signs of con-
gestive heart failure were excluded. Cats receiving medications 
considered to have cardiovascular effects were excluded. Cats with 
a disposition that prevented safe handling for an echocardiogram 
without sedation also were excluded. </p>

<p>Study Design </p>

<p>A physical examination, 6-lead electrocardiogram (ECG), 
venous blood sampling, and full echocardiographic study including 
transmitral flow velocities were performed in that order. 
21 One 
drop of 0.5% timolol maleate ophthalmic solution 
b was instilled 
into the right eye and the cats were returned to their hospital cage 
or carrier. Twenty minutes later, a 6-lead ECG and repeated 
echocardiogram were performed. The right eye then was irrigated 
with saline solution to remove any residual timolol and cats were 
discharged to their owners. The owners were contacted the next 
day to document any adverse signs after discharge from the 
hospital. </p>

<p>Five cats were selected from the clinical case load to serve as a 
control group in order to evaluate the effect of acclimation to the 
hospital environment on HR. This group received a full physical 
examination, a lead II ECG, and a complete echocardiogram. 
They then were placed into a cage within the UCD-VMTH cardi-
ology treatment room for 20 minutes. No timolol intervention was 
provided. A reevaluation lead II ECG was performed. </p>

<p>Electrocardiography </p>

<p>Six-lead and lead II ECGs were obtained in right lateral recum-
bency. 
c Recordings were made at 50 mm/s with an amplitude of 
20 mm/mV. A 10-second ECG was recorded and saved for manual 
measurement by 1 of the authors (CGH). Heart rate, PR interval, 
QRS interval, and QT interval were measured for all 6-lead ECGs, 
and HR was measured for each lead II ECG. All intervals were 
measured and recorded as an average of 3 consecutive complexes. </p>

<p>Echocardiography </p>

<p>All echocardiograms were performed by 1 of 2 investigators 
(JAS or CGH) using an 12-4 mHz sector array transducer. 
d Each 
cat was manually restrained in right, then left lateral recumbency; 
no sedatives were employed. Two-dimensional, M-mode, color 
Doppler, and spectral Doppler echocardiographic measurements 
were obtained. Transmitral flow velocities were obtained from the 
left parasternal apical view as previously described. 
6,22 Sample vol-
ume was set at 1.5 mm with a sweep speed of 150 mm/s. Left 
auricular flow velocity was obtained from an oblique left apical 
parasternal long-axis view as previously described. 
23 All measure-
ments were performed by 1 observer (CGH) using an offline work 
station. 
e The average value for 3 consecutive cardiac cycles was 
obtained for each measurement whenever possible. Left ventricular 
wall measurements (interventricular septum ([VS] and left ventricu-
lar free wall [LVPW]) were obtained in diastole at the level of the 
chordae tendineae and measured leading edge-to-leading edge from 
an M-mode recording. Two-dimensional maximal diastolic dimen-
sion of LVPW and IVS also were obtained in right parasternal 
short-and long-axis imaging planes during the initial echocardio-
gram for each cat. Left atrial size was measured in 2 dimensions 
(2D) on the right parasternal short-axis view and indexed to aortic 
root diameter. The aortic diameter was measured parallel to the 
commissure of the noncoronary and right coronary aortic valve 
cusps. The left atrial dimension was measured parallel to the com-
missure of the left coronary and noncoronary aortic valve cusps as 
previously described. 
24 The E and A wave fusion on the transmi-
tral flow pattern was defined as either complete summation of the 
E and A waves (no overlap) or partial summation where the initia-
tion of the A wave overlap was &gt;0.20 m/s relative to the E wave 
peak velocity. E and A wave separation was defined as a transmi-
tral E and A wave pattern where the initiation of the A wave 
began at a point &lt;0.20 m/s of the peak E wave velocity. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Pharmacogenetic Analysis </p>

<p>A polymorphism in the feline beta-1 adrenergic receptor gene 
(ADBR1) has been described as a missense mutation changing 
proline to glutamine at the 277th amino acid position (P277Q), 
although a functional effect of this polymorphism has not yet been 
characterized in cats. 
26 To examine a potential pharmacogenetic 
association between the documented ADRB1 polymorphism and 
response to ophthalmic timolol in cats of this study, a venous 
blood sample was obtained from all participating cats. The geno-
typing methodology was carried out as previously described. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Briefly, DNA was extracted from whole blood. Routine poly-
merase chain reaction (PCR) and Sanger sequencing were </p>

<p> 
Gunther-Harrington et al </p>

<p>performed to determine the genotype of the P277Q polymorphism. 
Sequences were aligned to the reference sequence and cats were 
classified as wild type, heterozygous, or homozygous for this 
previously described polymorphism. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Data were assessed for normality both visually and with a 
D'Agostino &amp; Pearson omnibus normality test when the sample 
size was adequate for testing (N &gt; 6). For sample sizes &lt;6 (control 
cats), data were treated as nonnormally distributed. All normally 
distributed data are reported as mean AE SD and nonnormally dis-
tributed data are reported as median (interquartile range [IQR]). 
Differences between pre-and post-timolol ECG and echocardio-
graphic measurements were assessed using a paired t-test for nor-
mally distributed data and a Wilcoxon matched pairs signed rank 
test for nonnormally distributed data. Heart rates before and after 
20 minutes of hospitalization in untreated cats were compared 
using Wilcoxon matched pairs signed rank test. Statistical software 
was used for calculations and analysis. 
f Statistical significance was 
determined at a P value &lt;.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>A total of 27 cats were recruited and 25 cats were 
enrolled. No cats were receiving any medications at the 
time of study enrollment. One cat was excluded because 
evidence of first-degree atrioventricular block was noted 
on its initial ECG; the second cat was excluded because 
its disposition did not allow a complete echocardiogram 
to be performed without sedation. Five control cats 
were selected from clinical cases undergoing echocardio-
graphy for evaluation of incidentally detected heart 
murmurs. The remaining 20 cats were enrolled in the 
timolol portion of the study. For subjects enrolled in 
the timolol portion of the study, age ranged from 
7 months to 17 years with mean age of 6.1 (AE4.55) 
years. Six cats had a heart murmur auscultated on 
physical examination. Heart rate on initial ECG ranged 
from 137 to 272 bpm with a median HR of 188 bpm. 
After timolol application, a significant decrease in HR 
(P &lt; .0001) to a median of 159 bpm (range 137-
200 bpm) occurred (Fig 1A). On visual inspection of 
the data, cats with HR &lt;175 bpm (n = 3) did not have 
a substantial change in HR after timolol application. 
For 5 control cats, age ranged from 5 to 12 years 
with a median age of 7 years. Baseline HR of control 
cats was not significantly different from baseline HR of 
cats that received timolol (P = .42). Median HR on ini-
tial presentation was 200 bpm (range, 160-233 bpm), 
and after 20 minutes of acclimation to the hospital 
environment, no significant difference was detected in 
HR (median, 214 bpm; range, 151-225; P = .81; 
Fig 1B). 
For cats that received timolol, baseline echocardio-
gram transmitral flow velocity measurement showed E 
and A wave fusion in 13 of 20 cats, whereas clear E 
and A wave separation was visualized in the remaining 
7 cats. All 13 of the cats with E and A wave fusion had 
complete fusion with no discernable E and A waves. 
After timolol administration, 5 of these 13 cats (38%) 
had E and A waves that remained fused, whereas 8/13 </p>

<p>cats (62%) had E and A separation (Fig 2). When all 
data points were pooled, median HR was significantly 
higher in cats with E and A wave fusion at 197 bpm 
(IQR: 190, 203) when compared to those with E and A 
wave separation (median, 158 bpm; range, 151-163; 
P &lt; .0001). In the 7 cats in which E and A waves were 
separated at baseline, these waves remained separated, 
with no significant change in E/A ratio, after timolol 
administration (P = .4). Of those 7 cats, all E/A ratios 
that were &lt;1.0 remained &lt;1.0 after timolol, and those 
that were &gt;1.0 remained &gt;1.0 (Fig 3). 
Two-dimensional and M-mode-derived echocardio-
graphic measurements are summarized in Table 1. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. (A) Heart rate (HR; y-axis) at baseline and after timolol 
time points (x-axis) for 20 cats. After timolol administration, there 
was a significant decrease in HR (P &lt; .0001), with no substantial 
change appreciated in cats with an initial HR &lt;176 bpm. (B) Heart 
rate (HR; y-axis) at baseline and 20 minutes after acclimation (x-
axis) for 5 control cats that did not receive timolol. There was no 
significant difference between HR at baseline or after acclimation 
in these cats (P = .8) </p>

<p>Timolol for Diastolic Function Testing </p>

<p>
There was no significant difference in septal or left ven-
tricular free wall measurements in diastole after timolol 
application (P = .91 and P = .18, respectively). An 
example of the effects of timolol on transmitral flow 
pattern is shown in Fig 4. Comparison of baseline and 
posttimolol measurements identified a significant 
decrease in left ventricular systolic function, assessed by 
fractional shortening (FS)% (P &lt; .0001) and left </p>

<p>ventricular internal dimension in systole (LVIDs; 
P &lt; .0001). After timolol application there was no sig-
nificant change in LA/Ao (P = .36) or left auricular 
flow velocity (P = .117). 
On baseline echocardiogram, 1 cat was diagnosed 
with hypertrophic obstructive cardiomyopathy with sys-
tolic cranial motion of the mitral valve and a peak left 
ventricular outflow tract (LVOT) velocity of 3.4 m/s; 
the interventricular septum measured 7.1 mm in diastole 
with a free wall measurement of 5.6 mm. After timolol 
application, no evidence of obstruction was noted on 
color flow Doppler and peak left ventricular outflow 
tract (LVOT) velocity was decreased to 1.3 m/s. The 
remaining cats in the study did not have structural car-
diac disease. Five cats had dynamic right ventricular 
outflow tract obstruction (DRVOTO) noted on initial 
echocardiogram based on color Doppler and spectral 
Doppler assessment. After timolol application, 
DRVOTO was no longer noted in any of these cats. 
Ptyalism was noted immediately after timolol was 
applied in 2/20 cats (10%) and lasted &lt;5 minutes. 
Anisocoria with miosis OD (the treated eye) was 
reported in 11 cats (55%) after timolol application but 
was temporary. Most owners noted return to normal 
pupil size within 24 hours. In 1 cat, miosis lasted 
48 hours. 
No hemodynamically relevant arrhythmias were iden-
tified after application of timolol but 2 cats (10%) 
developed mild first-degree atrioventricular block with 
PR intervals of 95 and 100 ms. No significant difference 
in QRS duration or QT interval was observed before 
and after timolol application (P = .80 and P = .08, 
respectively). 
No genotypic differences were identified in this popu-
lation and all cats (25/25) were found to be wild type 
(matching the reference sequence) for the P277Q 
ADRB1 polymorphism. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, ophthalmic application of timolol 
decreased HR and facilitated visualization of separated 
E and A waves on transmitral flow in the majority of 
cats in which the waves initially were fused. Assessment 
of diastolic function is a routine portion of the echocar-
diographic examination when evaluating cats for car-
diomyopathies. Spectral Doppler assessment of 
transmitral flow patterns is a common tool used to 
diagnose diastolic dysfunction, and it has been pro-
posed that this technique may help identify occult car-
diomyopathy when interpreted as part of the complete 
clinical evaluation. 
25 Although these data are useful in 
cats, the high HR of cats in the clinic and subsequent E 
and A wave fusion on spectral Doppler assessment 
make transmitral flow patterns impossible to assess in 
some subjects. Previous investigators have reported suc-
cess in separating E and A waves with vagal maneuvers, 
but in our experience, the response is exceedingly tran-
sient and not as robust as previously reported. 
25 Addi-
tionally, cat demeanor often precludes application of 
ocular or nasal planum pressure, which is reported to </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Graphical depiction of cats with transmitral flow E and A 
wave fusion or separation at baseline (left) and after timolol 
administration (right). At baseline time point 13 of 20 cats (65%) 
had E and A fusion, whereas 7 of 20 cats (35%) had separation. 
After ophthalmic administration of timolol 62% of previously 
fused waves became separated, whereas the waves in 5 of 13 cats 
(38%) remained fused. All 7 of 7 initially separated profiles, 
remained separated. E-peak early diastolic flow velocity; A-peak 
late diastolic flow velocity. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. E/A ratio at baseline and after timolol time points in the 
7 cats that had E and A wave separation at baseline. The blue line 
denotes an E/A ratio of 1.0. Below the line, or an E/A ratio &lt;1.0 
is consistent with impaired relaxation, whereas above the line is 
considered normal. All cats that had evidence of impaired relax-
ation (n = 3) at the baseline time point, remained impaired after 
timolol administration. The 4 cats with a normal E/A ratio before 
timolol remained normal after timolol. E/A-ratio of peak E to 
peak A velocity. </p>

<p> 
Gunther-Harrington et al </p>

<p>be most successful at increasing vagal tone in cats 
undergoing echocardiography. 
25 A potential alternate 
solution is the identification of a safe, effective, and 
temporary pharmacologic intervention that decreases 
HR and facilitates diastolic function testing without 
altering the ultimate assessment. 
Timolol, a nonselective topically-applied ophthalmic 
beta-blocker, significantly decreased HR in cats under-
going echocardiographic examination. The greatest </p>

<p>effect on HR was noted in tachycardic cats. This obser-
vation is consistent with the expectation that increased 
HR in these cats was secondary to increased sympa-
thetic tone, 
27 and that sympathetic drive was amelio-
rated by a single ophthalmic dose of timolol in some 
cats. A similar effect previously has been reported in 
human patients in whom a single topical dose of timolol 
created statistically significant cardiovascular effects at 
rest and after exercise, as well as a decrease in cardiac 
sympathetic tone. 
28 Data from the control group of cats 
supports the conclusion that acclimation to the hospital 
environment was not solely responsible for the 
decreased HR observed in our study, and leads to the 
conclusion that the effects noted in our study are a 
result of beta-blockade from systemic absorption of 
timolol. 
Ophthalmic dosing of timolol effectively separated 
transmitral flow patterns (E and A wave separation) in 
62% of the cats in which the waves initially were fused, 
thereby allowing diastolic function assessment in these 
individuals. Importantly, the effect of beta-blockade by 
timolol did not have an adverse effect on our ability to 
interpret E and A profiles because the profiles that were 
separated at baseline did not significantly change after 
timolol administration. This finding supports the notion 
that opthalmically administered timolol can aid in 
assessment of myocardial relaxation, a common compo-
nent of screening for occult cardiomyopathy. 
Transmitral flow profiles can be affected by HR, 
Doppler angle, loading conditions, left atrial function, 
and age. 
6,10,29 In our study, each cat acted as its own 
baseline control, ruling out an effect of age on the 
results obtained. In the absence of E and A wave 
fusion, HR has minimal effect on the interpretation of 
E/A ratio. 
29 In our study, changes in left ventricular 
loading conditions were seen between baseline and post-
timolol time points, as demonstrated by increased left 
ventricular systolic dimensions and decreased FS. How-
ever, the effect of these alterations on transmitral flow 
pattern was not statistically significant or clinically rele-
vant based on our data. Ours was a pilot study and a 
larger patient population and more extensive diastolic 
function assessment were not included. </p>

<p>Table 1. Echocardiographic measurements for baseline time point and after timolol administration in 20 cats </p>

<p>Variable 
Baseline 
Posttimolol 
% change 
P value </p>

<p>HR (bpm) 
188 (177, 199) 
159 (155, 167) 
À13.6 (À9.4, 20.5) 
&lt;.0001 
IVSd (cm) 
0.46 (0.41, 0.50) 
0.45 (0.41, 0.51) 
0.98 (À10.6, 9.3) 
.91 
LVPWd (cm) 
0.48 (0.44, 0.53) 
0.50 (0.42, 0.53) 
À3.8 (À7.1, 2.8) 
.18 
LVIDd (cm) 
1.50 (1.37, 1.69) 
1.60 (1.42, 1.69) 
3.1 (À6.9, 9.4) 
.53 
LVIDs (cm) 
0.67 (0.13) 
0.87 (0.15) 
30.9 (20.7) 
&lt;.0001 
FS% 
55.86 (7.69) 
44.14 (7.60) 
À20.4 (12.1) 
&lt;.0001 
LA (cm) 
1.18 (0.14) 
1.25 (0.14) 
7.0 (14.3) 
.10 
LA/Ao 
1.22 (0.11) 
1.26 (0.18) 
4.3 (15.6) 
.36 
LAA Flow Vel (cm/s) 
49.68 (17.25) 
45.37 (13.07) 
À4.6 (24.2) 
.117 </p>

<p>Normally distributed data are presented with mean (SD). For nonnormally distributed data median (IQR) is listed. HR, heart rate; IVS, 
interventricular septum; LVPW, left ventricular free wall; LVID, left ventricular internal dimension; d, measured in end-diastole; s, mea-
sured at end-systole; FS%, left ventricular shortening fraction; LA, 2-dimensional left atrial diameter; LA/Ao, left atrial diameter indexed 
to aortic diameter; LAA Flow Vel, left auricular appendage flow velocity. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Transmitral flow from a 3-year-old cat enrolled in the 
timolol portion of this study. Heart rate at baseline (A) was 
210 bpm, and 182 bpm after timolol administration (B). E and A 
fusion noted at baseline, with clear separation appreciated after 
timolol administration. Sweep speed is 150 mm/s, lead II timing 
lead is also depicted. MC-male castrated; DSH-domestic 
shorthair. </p>

<p>Timolol for Diastolic Function Testing </p>

<p>
The variable response in E and A wave separation 
noted could be related to individual variability in sym-
pathetic tone and excitement. Other considerations 
for variable response to timolol include variable ocular 
absorption, variable drug metabolism, or perhaps 
other pharmacogenetic factors such as beta receptor 
polymorphisms beyond those already identified in 
cats. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>Left atrial size did not change significantly between 
baseline and posttimolol application, but our study may 
have been underpowered to detect a difference given the 
small variation in left atrial size recorded among cats. 
One measure of left atrial function, left auricular flow 
velocity, was not significantly different from baseline, 
therefore the effect of timolol on atrial contribution to 
left ventricular filling is thought to be negligible. Addi-
tional assessments of left atrial function (eg, LA ejec-
tion fraction, shortening fraction) may represent an 
area of future investigation. Given the effect of timolol 
on left ventricular function and the theoretical effect on 
left atrial size, caution should be observed with respect 
to the ocular application of timolol in cats with clinical 
signs of congestive heart failure, left atrial enlargement, 
or impaired systolic function. The effects of timolol on 
systolic function highlight the importance of obtaining 
systolic function assessments before application of timo-
lol, as performed in this study. For instance, a clinical 
strategy could be to perform a complete echocardio-
gram, then if E and A fusion was noted on transmitral 
flow, administer ophthalmic timolol, wait 20 minutes 
and then reassess transmitral flow profiles. In our study, 
timolol was evaluated as a tool to facilitate assessment 
of 1 measure of diastolic function in an effort to iden-
tify cats with occult cardiomyopathy. Therefore, the 
utility of this medication in cats with clear evidence of 
hemodynamically relevant heart disease is beyond the 
scope of our study. 
In our study, timolol resulted in significant decrease in 
both measures of systolic function measured. This obser-
vation is consistent with the negative inotropic effects 
expected with beta-blockade. Therefore, ophthalmic 
application of timolol may help elucidate a patient's 
response to beta-blockade and could be particularly use-
ful in cats with obstructive cardiomyopathy, although 
further study is needed to investigate this hypothesis. In 
our study, all cats (6 total) with evidence of dynamic 
obstruction (DRVOTO or hypertrophic obstructive car-
diomyopathy (HOCM)) on baseline echocardiogram 
had relief of that obstruction after timolol administra-
tion. Although it has yet to be proven effective, treat-
ment for cats with occult hypertrophic cardiomyopathy 
might include beta-blockade. 
30-33 The ability to under-
stand an individual's response to beta-blockade at the 
time of initial evaluation could represent a benefit of 
ophthalmic timolol application. 
Pharmacogenetics and individualized medicine are 
growing fields. In humans, genetic polymorphisms that 
result in variable response to beta-blocker treatment 
could alter therapeutic choices. 
34 This pharmacogenetic 
effect on medication administration also has been 
demonstrated in dogs. 
35 Although the functional effects </p>

<p>of feline beta receptor polymorphism are not well docu-
mented, this remains an area of interest for future 
investigation. In our study, an influence of the docu-
mented P277Q ADRB1 polymorphism was not respon-
sible for the variable response to timolol. Because all of 
the cats in our study had the wild type genotype we 
cannot accurately assess the functional relevance of this 
polymorphism. Obviously, the role of polymorphisms 
that have yet to be reported cannot be predicted. Practi-
cally, topical application of timolol in the clinic might 
help determine if a cat will respond as expected to 
systemic beta-blocker treatment, although further 
investigation is necessary. 
No clinically relevant adverse effects were noted after 
timolol administration. As previously reported, miosis 
was observed in the treated eye. 
17,36 Miosis occurred 
secondary to inhibition of beta-adrenergic fibers of the 
iris sphincter muscle, 
18,37 which is reported to be tran-
sient in nature. 
17 Although miosis induced by timolol 
may be disturbing to an owner, it is not considered clin-
ical relevant to the animal. 
37 First-degree AV block was 
noted in a small proportion of the cats treated with 
timolol (10%). This occurrence was not considered 
pathologic or dangerous, but caution should be 
employed when administering timolol to cats with a 
previously documented conduction disturbance or 
arrhythmia. A history respiratory disease or current 
cough were exclusion criteria for our study and as such 
the safety data generated cannot be applied to cats in 
which respiratory disease is a concern. 
Based on our findings, systemic absorption of timolol 
after ophthalmic administration occurs in cats as has 
been documented in human patients. 
38 In humans, 
approximately 80% of the topically administered medi-
cation drains through the nasolacrimal duct and thereby 
is systemically absorbed. 
39 Fewer cardiovascular effects 
are noted in people when the 0.1% hydrogel formula-
tion is used as compared to the 0.5% aqueous solution 
used in our study. </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>Our study had several limitations. Because of the 
marked and obvious effects of beta-blockade on HR 
and left ventricular systolic function, no attempt at 
blinding was made. Ours was a pilot study that 
aimed to include both healthy cats and those with 
occult cardiomyopathy, but only 1 subject with a 
diagnosis of hypertrophic obstructive cardiomyopathy 
was enrolled. Furthermore, the sample size of patients 
with E and A wave separation at baseline was small, 
and small alterations in E and A velocity after timo-
lol may not be have been appreciated. Although a 
significant decrease in HR was noted in treated cats 
and not in control cats, the control group does not 
necessarily rule out the possibility of individual varia-
tion in hospital acclimation. A future direction to 
address this limitation could include a single-blinded, 
placebo-controlled study using a cross-over design to 
confirm that alteration in HR was not caused by 
individual variation in acclimation. A final limitation 
is that the study design included evaluation only at a 
20-minute time period and effects beyond this time 
frame are unknown. </p>

<p> 
Gunther-Harrington et al </p>

<p>Several assessments were outside the scope of this 
investigation and worth consideration in future investi-
gations. Although the majority of cats included in this 
study had a HR that returned to normal before hospital 
discharge (generally within 1-2 hours), this information 
was not recorded for all cats and long term HR data 
were not collected for this study. Therefore, the 
duration of action of timolol and its effects on HR after 
a single dose are not fully understood at this time. 
Additionally, our study did not aim to determine the 
optimal effective dose. A single dose of 1 drop of 0.5% 
solution was applied based on a previous study, 
36 but a 
similar HR response might be noted with a lower dose 
or could be marked with higher doses. 
In conclusion, ophthalmic timolol application in 
cats safely decreased HR, generated changes in 
echocardiographic parameters and facilitated diastolic 
function assessment in cats in our study. Thus, the 
ophthalmically administered timolol may facilitate 
echocardiographic assessment of cats and warrants 
further investigation. </p>

<p>Footnotes </p>

<p>a Wilkie L, Fuentes VL, Rishniw M. Online survey to assess inter-
and intraobserver agreement on echocardiographic classification 
of cardiomyopathy in cats (abstract). J Vet Intern Med 2015; 
29: 1263. 
b Timolol Maleate Ophthalmic Solution, USP 0.5%. Akorn, Inc. 
Lake Forest, IL. 
c Mac 5500 Electrocardiogram, GE Healthcare, Waukesha, WI. 
d Philips iE33 Ultrasound, Philips Heathcare, Andover, MA. 
e syngo Dynamics, Siemens Medical Solutions, Malvern, PA. 
f <rs id="software-1" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">6.0</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Graph Pad Software</rs>, La Jolla, CA. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank Dr. Christine Kinkade of the 
University of California Davis Veterinary Center for 
Clinical Trials for help with study recruitment and 
Denise Berger for her expert technical assistance. 
Funding Sources: None. 
Conflict of Interest Declaration: Authors declare no 
conflict of interest. 
Off-label Antimicrobial Declaration: Authors declare 
no off-label use of antimicrobials. </p>



<p>Timolol for Diastolic Function Testing </p>



<p>
 
Gunther-Harrington et al </p>

</text></tei>