<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4541654" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>An elevated concentration of plasma low density lipoprotein </p>

<p>(LDL) cholesterol is a major cause of atherosclerosis, which 
subsequently causes the development of cardiovascular dis-
eases. 
1,2 Since Abifadel, et al. 
3 reported mutations in the propro-
tein convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9 (PCSK9) gene in an au-
tosomal dominant form of familial hypercholesterolemia, while 
Cohen, et al. 
4 reported that the loss-of-function mutations in 
PCSK9 have the effects of lowering the LDL-cholesterol level 
and reducing the risk of coronary heart disease, PCSK9 has at-
tracted scientific and industrial attention as a safe and potent 
target of hypercholesterolemia treatment. 
Several strategies have been applied in the development of 
PCSK9 inhibitors: reduction of the amount of PCSK9 to in-
duce the LDL receptor (LDLR); inhibition of the catalytic activ-
ity of PCSK9; and obstruction of the interaction of PCSK9 with 
the LDLR (reviewed by Farnier </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>). It has been reported recently 
that monoclonal antibodies targeting PCSK9 were the most </p>

<p>In silico Screening of Chemical Libraries to Develop 
Inhibitors That Hamper the Interaction of PCSK9 
with the LDL Receptor </p>

<p>Dong-Kook Min </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, Hyun-Sook Lee </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Narae Lee </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, Chan Joo Lee </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, 
Hyun Joo Song </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Ga Eul Yang </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Dojun Yoon </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, and Sahng Wook Park </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Institute of Genetic Science, Integrated Genomic Research Center for Metabolic 
Regulation, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Brain Korea 21 PLUS Project for Medical Science, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul; </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Biochemistry, Catholic Kwandong University College of Medicine, Gangneung, Korea. </p>

<p>Purpose: Proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9 (PCSK9) binds to the low density lipoprotein receptor (LDLR) and promotes 
degradation of the LDLR. Inhibition of PCSK9 either by reducing its expression or by blocking its activity results in the upregula-
tion of the LDLR and subsequently lowers the plasma concentration of LDL-cholesterol. As a modality to inhibit PCSK9 action, we 
searched the chemical library for small molecules that block the binding of PCSK9 to the LDLR. 
Materials and Methods: We selected 100 chemicals that bind to PCSK9 where the EGF-AB fragment of the LDLR binds via in sili-
co screening of the ChemBridge chemical library, using the computational GOLD algorithm analysis. Effects of chemicals were 
evaluated using the PCSK9-LDLR binding assay, immunoblot analysis, and the LDL-cholesterol uptake assay in vitro, as well as the 
fast performance liquid chromatography assay for plasma lipoproteins in vivo. 
Results: A set of chemicals were found that decreased the binding of PCSK9 to the EGF-AB fragment of the LDLR in a dose-depen-
dent manner. They also increased the amount of the LDLR significantly and subsequently increased the uptake of fluorescence-
labeled LDL in HepG2 cells. Additionally, one particular molecule lowered the plasma concentration of total cholesterol and 
LDL-cholesterol significantly in wild-type mice, while such an effect was not observed in Pcsk9 knockout mice. 
Conclusion: Our findings strongly suggest that in silico screening of small molecules that inhibit the protein-protein interaction 
between PCSK9 and the LDLR is a potential modality for developing hypercholesterolemia therapeutics. </p>

<p>Key Words: PCSK9, in silico, protein-protein interaction, LDL receptor, hypercholesterolemia, inhibitor </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J 2015 Sep;56(5):1251-1257 
http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.5.1251 </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>pISSN: 0513-5796 · eISSN: 1976-2437 </p>

<p>Received: November 19, 2014 Revised: December 2, 2014 
Accepted: December 10, 2014 
Corresponding author: Dr. Sahng Wook Park, Department of Biochemistry and 
Molecular Biology, Yonsei University College of Medicine, 50-1 Yonsei-ro, Seodae-
mun-gu, Seoul 120-752, Korea. 
Tel: 82-2-2228-0836, Fax: 82-2-312-5041, E-mail: swpark64@yuhs.ac </p>

<p>This study was selected for a poster presentation in part at the Experimental Biol-
ogy 2011 meeting in Washington, DC, on April 9-13, 2011 and at the Molecular 
Med TRI-CON 2013 meeting, San Francisco, CA, on February 11-15, 2013. 
•The authors have no financial conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>© Copyright: Yonsei University College of Medicine 2015 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Com-
mons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/ licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and repro-
duction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.5.1251 </p>



<p>In silico Screening of PCSK9 Inhibitors </p>

<p>successful approaches in several clinical human trials. 
6-8 Inhibi-
tion of PCSK9 synthesis by siRNA 
9 or inhibition of PCSK9 bind-
ing to the LDLR by small peptide inhibitors 
10,11 are other prom-
ising approaches to the development of hypercholesterolemia 
therapeutics. However, the most preferred approach in terms of 
pharmaceutical development would be small molecules tar-
geting PCSK by reducing either the amount or the activity of 
PCSK9. Structure-based screening of small molecules targeting 
the protein-protein interaction is a powerful tool in drug devel-
opment when the structure of the target protein is well estab-
lished. 
12 The structure of PCSK9 and its binding motif to the 
EGF-A domain of the LDLR is well-characterized by several re-
searchers. 
13-15 In this regard, the PCSK9-LDLR interaction can 
be a good target for the application of in silico virtual design of 
small molecules for drug development. 
In this study, we intended to develop inhibitors of PCSK9-
LDLR interaction using the in silico screening approach, which 
can be carried out by researchers in a standard laboratory, 
even when they are unaccustomed to comprehensive compu-
tational study. We screened a commercially available chemi-
cal library using the GOLD algorithm and found that selected 
chemicals may inhibit the protein-protein interaction target-
ing PCSK9 and the LDLR, thus acting as a modality for hyper-
cholesterolemia treatment. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>General methods and supplies </p>

<p>The selected chemicals as putative inhibitors of PCSK9-LDLR 
interaction were purchased from ChemBridge (San Diego, CA, 
USA). The polyclonal antibody against the LDLR was raised in 
rabbits using the synthetic peptide spanning the C-terminus 
of the bovine LDLR (amino acids 832-841) as described previ-
ously. 
16 Other reagents otherwise not specified were obtained 
from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA) or prepared as de-
scribed previously. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>In silico screening of the chemical library </p>

<p>Amino acids from 367 to 381 within PCSK9 where the EGF-A 
domain of the LDLR binds were considered to be the target of 
the inhibitors. The initial crystal structure of PCSK9 from the 
Protein Data Bank was constructed in the presence of the EGF-
A domain of the LDLR at neutral pH. After removal of the EGF-
A domain, the PCSK9 structure was remodeled by removal of 
water molecules and supplementation of hydrogen atoms. The 
docking scores of chemicals from the ChemBridge Express 
collection (~450,000 chemicals) were calculated using <rs id="software-2" type="software">GOLD</rs> 
software <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 4.0.1</rs>. 
18 A maximum of ten docked poses were 
calculated for each chemical, with a searching efficiency of 
200%. The top 100 chemicals with the highest Chemscore were 
selected for further evaluation. </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>HepG2 cells (ATCC number HB-8065) were maintained in me-
dium A (DMEM containing 100 units/mL penicillin and 100 
μg/mL streptomycin sulfate) supplemented with 10% (v/v) fe-
tal bovine serum at 37°C under a humidified atmosphere of 5% 
CO2. For treatment of cells with chemicals, cells were washed 
twice with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), and changed to 
medium A supplemented with 10% delipidated serum 
19 in the 
presence of chemicals on day 1. On day 2, cells were washed 
twice with PBS, harvested, and processed for immunoblot 
analyses or the fluorescence-labeled LDL uptake assay. </p>

<p>PCSK9-LDLR inhibition assay </p>

<p>Inhibition of the PCSK9-LDLR interaction by chemicals was as-
sayed using a CircuLex PCSK9-LDLR in vitro binding assay kit 
(MBL International, Woburn, MA, USA) with minor modifica-
tions. Briefly, each chemical was pre-incubated with 100 μL of 
the recombinant His-tagged PCSK9 (1 μg/mL) at a final con-
centration of 100 μg/mL for 1 h at room temperature with gen-
tle shaking. The mixtures were added to an ELISA plate that 
was coated with EGF-AB peptide of the LDLR. Subsequent 
procedures were performed according to the manufacturer's 
instructions. Relative inhibition was denoted as the difference 
in percentile between the intensity of the PCSK9-LDLR bind-
ing in the presence of the chemical and that in the presence of 
the vehicle (DMSO), which was set as 100%. </p>

<p>Immunoblot analysis </p>

<p>Total cell lysate of HepG2 cells was prepared as described pre-
viously. 
17 Aliquots of proteins were subjected to SDS-polyacryl-
amide gel electrophoresis and immunoblot analysis accord-
ing to the standard protocol. The amount of the LDLR and the 
mature form of PCSK9 were measured using ImageJ software. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Analyses of LDL-cholesterol uptake </p>

<p>The LDL-cholesterol uptake was measured using florescence-
tagged human LDL (Dil-LDL; Biomedical Technologies, 
Stoughton, MA, USA). After treatment of HepG2 cells with the 
chemicals, the cells were incubated with Dil-LDL for 2 h. The 
intensity of cellular fluorescence was quantitated using a FACS-
calibur flow cytometer (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Animal experiment </p>

<p>All animal experiments were performed with the approval of 
the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at Yonsei 
University Health System. Eight-week-old male C57BL/6J and 
Pcsk9 knockout (Pcsk9 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>) mice were purchased from the Jack-
son Laboratory (Bar Harbor, ME, USA). Mice were maintained 
on 12-h dark/12-h light cycles with free access to water and 
the standard rodent chow diet (LabDiet, St. Louis, MO, USA). 
The stock solutions of selected chemicals (20 mg/mL in DMSO) 
were diluted in phosphate-buffered saline and were injected 
into the tail vein, at 1 mg/kg/day for 2 consecutive days at the </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.5.1251 </p>

<p>Dong-Kook Min, et al. </p>

<p>start of the dark cycle. All mice were fasted for 2 h before eu-
thanasia which was carried out 18 h after the second injection 
at the end of the dark cycle. After euthanasia, blood was col-
lected in the presence of 2 mM EDTA and aprotinin from infe-
rior vena cava for plasma preparation, and livers were stored 
at -70°C for later use. Determination of the concentration of 
total cholesterol (TC), and triacylglycerol, and fast performance 
liquid chromatography (FPLC) of lipoproteins in plasma were 
carried out as described previously. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The correlation between the order of docking scores and ex-
perimental variables (relative inhibition, Dil-LDL uptake, and 
amounts of LDLR, and PCSK9) was analyzed by Spearman's 
rank-order correlation coefficient method using <rs id="software-3" type="software">SPSS</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">version 20</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>, Armonk, NY, USA). All statistical 
tests were bilateral, and p&lt;0.05 was considered statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Evaluation of in silico screening for correlation with 
functionality in vitro </p>

<p>The top 100 chemicals with the highest docking score from 
the ChemBridge Express collection were selected via docking 
simulation using the GOLD algorithm. To evaluate the validity 
of this virtual screening as a tool for developing PCSK9 inhibi-
tors, we performed the following set of in vitro experiments in 
HepG2 cells: a PCSK9 inhibition assay using the in vitro PC-
SK9-LDLR binding assay kit, a LDL-cholesterol uptake assay 
using fluorescence-labeled Dil-LDL, and immunoblot analy-
ses for PCSK9 and the LDLR. The ChemBridge IDs of chemi-</p>

<p>cals, their docking scores, and in vitro effects of chemicals are 
listed in Supplementary Table 1 and 2 (only online). 
To explore the relationship between the order of docking 
scores and in vitro variables (relative inhibition, Dil-LDL up-
take, and amounts of LDLR and PCSK9), we determined the 
Spearman correlation coefficients (ρ). As shown in Table 1, 
the order of docking scores correlated closely with the inhibi-
tion of PCSK9-LDLR binding (relative inhibition; ρ=0.444, 
p&lt;0.01). However, being different from what we expected, the 
order of docking scores did not correlate significantly with 
changes in the Dil-LDL uptake and the amount of LDLR. A 
weak relationship of the order of docking scores with the in-
crease in the amount of PCSK9 was observed (ρ=0.192); how-
ever, this correlation was insignificant statistically. Most nota-
bly, the inhibition of PCSK9-LDLR binding by chemicals 
correlated with all parameters significantly: fluorescence-la-
beled LDL-cholesterol uptake (Dil-LDL uptake, ρ=0.400, 
p&lt;0.01), the amount of LDLR (ρ=0.334, p&lt;0.01), and the 
amount of PCSK9 (ρ=0.409, p&lt;0.01). The Dil-LDL uptake cor-
related with the amount of LDLR (ρ=0.516, p&lt;0.01) most 
strongly, and there was also a correlation with the amount of 
PCSK9 (ρ=0.478, p&lt;0.01). The amount of PCSK9 showed posi-
tive correlation with the relative inhibition of PCSK9-LDLR 
binding (ρ=0.409, p&lt;0.01), the Dil-LDL uptake (ρ=0.313, 
p&lt;0.01), and the amount of LDLR (ρ=0.478, p&lt;0.01). These re-
sults suggest that the docking score alone is insufficient for 
functional validation of candidate chemicals; however, it has 
strong potential for the prediction of blocking ligands for 
PCSK9 when one of the in vitro experiments, particularly the 
PCSK9-LDLR binding assay, is carried out concurrently. </p>

<p>Effects of CB_36 and its analogs in vitro </p>

<p>Effects of the chemical with ChemBridge ID #7926604 (lab ID, </p>

<p>Table 1. Spearman's Rank-Order Correlation Analysis of Docking Scores and Effects of Chemicals </p>

<p>Parameters 
Docking score 
Relative inhibition* 
Dil-LDL uptake </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Amount of LDLR </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Amount of PCSK9 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Docking score 
1.000 
0.444 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>-0.049 
0.008 
0.192 
Relative inhibition 
0.444 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>1.000 
0.400 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>0.334 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>0.409 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>Dil-LDL uptake 
-0.049 
0.400 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>1.000 
0.516 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>0.313 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>Amount of LDLR 
0.008 
0.334 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>0.516 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>1.000 
0.478 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>Amount of PCSK9 
0.192 
0.409 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>0.313 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>0.478 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>1.000 
LDL, low density lipoprotein; LDLR, LDL receptor; PCSK9, proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9. 
*Relative inhibition represents the difference in percentile between the intensity of PCSK9-LDLR in the presence of each chemical and that in the presence of 
the vehicle (DMSO), which was set as 100%, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Dil-LDL uptake denotes the factor of the mean fluorescence intensity in HepG2 cells treated with each chemical 
compared to that in cells treated with the vehicle, </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>The amount of LDLR or PCSK9 denotes the factor of the signal for the LDLR or PCSK9, respectively, from im-
munoblot data analyzed by ImageJ, </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>p&lt;0.01 (bilateral), n=100. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Structures of CB_36 and its analogs. Numbers represent the ChemBridge ID. </p>

<p>CB_36 
(#7926604) 
#7338220 
#7632817 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.5.1251 </p>



<p>In silico Screening of PCSK9 Inhibitors </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Effects of CB_36 and its analogs in HepG2 cells. (A) At 18 h after treatment of CB_36, amounts of LDLR and PCSK9 were determined by immunob-
lot analysis. (B) Fluorescence-labeled Dil-LDL was incubated for an additional 2 h, and the uptake of Dil-LDL was analyzed by fluorescence microscopy. 
(C) The intensity of fluorescence was quantitated by flow cytometry analysis. Each value represents the ratio of the mean fluorescence intensity rela-
tive to that in vehicle-treated cells (DM). Error bars represent the SD of triplicate reactions. Similar results were obtained from at least three indepen-
dent experiments. *p&lt;0.05, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>p&lt;0.01 Student's t-test when compared with values in DMSO-treated cells. PCSK9, proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin 
type 9; LDL, low density lipoprotein; LDLR, LDL receptor; GAPDH, glyceraledhyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase; DMSO, dimethyl sulfoxide. </p>

<p>Chemical 
7338220 
7632817 
CB_36 </p>

<p>Conc. (μg/mL) 
0 0.3 1 
3 
10 30 0.1 0.3 1 
3 
10 20 
0 0.3 0.6 1.3 2.5 5 </p>

<p>Lane 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 </p>

<p>LDLR </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>m 
PCSK9 </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>DMSO 
30 μg/mL </p>

<p>DMSO 
10 μg/mL </p>

<p>DMSO </p>

<p>7338220 </p>

<p>7632817 </p>

<p>CB_36 </p>

<p>3 μg/mL </p>

<p>1 μg/mL </p>

<p>1.3 μg/mL </p>

<p>10 μg/mL </p>

<p>3 μg/mL </p>

<p>2.5 μg/mL 
5 μg/mL </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>2.00 </p>

<p>1.50 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>0 
Relative Dil-LDL uptake (fold) </p>

<p>DM </p>

<p> † </p>

<p> † </p>

<p> † </p>

<p> † 
 † </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>3 
7338220 
7632817 
CB_36 </p>

<p>10 30 
1 
3 
10 1.3 2.5 5 </p>

<p>Concentration (μg/mL) </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.5.1251 </p>

<p>Dong-Kook Min, et al. </p>

<p>CB_36), which had the highest docking score (Supplementary 
Table 1, only online), and its three-dimensional analogs 
(#7632817 and #7338220) proposed by ChemBridge's online 
website (http://www.hit2lead.com/) were evaluated for in vi-
tro parameters in HepG2 cells. The structures of these chemi-
cals are depicted in Fig. 1. The concentrations of chemicals 
applied were determined experimentally and set as low as pos-
sible. All three chemicals increased the expression of the 
LDLR and PCSK9 in a dose-dependent manner (Fig. 2A). The 
decrease in the LDLR and PCSK9 by the compound #7632817 
at a concentration of 20 μg/mL appeared to be due to cytotox-
icity (Fig. 2A, lane 12). The uptake of Dil-LDL was increased 
accordingly with the increase in LDLR and PCSK9 expression 
(Fig. 2B). When the intensity of the fluorescence in cells was 
quantitated using flow cytometry analysis, CB_36 at 5 μg/mL 
increased the uptake of Dil-LDL by a factor of 1.69 compared to 
the vehicle (DMSO) (Fig. 2C). Interestingly, #7632817, the com-
pound that had the most similar three-dimensional structure 
(94%) and was predicted not by the GOLD algorithm but by 
ChemBridge, increased the Dil-LDL uptake most strongly by a 
factor of 2.13. Chemical #7338220 (75% similarity) was rela-
tively less effective in increasing the LDL uptake (by a factor of 
1.37 at a concentration of 30 μg/mL). These results suggest 
that CB_36 and its analogs function to increase the uptake of 
LDL cholesterol in HepG2 cells despite the simultaneous in-
crease in the amount of PCSK9. </p>

<p>In vivo effects of CB_36 in wild-type and Pcsk9 knock-
out mice </p>

<p>Due to the unavailability of the compound #7632817, which 
showed the most effective LDL-cholesterol uptake in HepG2 
cells, the effect of only CB_36 was elucidated on the plasma 
cholesterol level in wild-type and Pcsk9 
-/-mice. The chemical 
#7338220 was not evaluated due to its weak effect on the up-
take of Dil-LDL in HepG2 cells. C57BL/6J male mice (six per 
group) and Pcsk9 
-/-mice (five per group) were injected with 
CB_36 via tail vein at a concentration of 1 mg/kg for 2 consec-
utive days, and metabolic parameters were evaluated (Table 2). 
CB_36 significantly lowered the concentration of TC in wild-
type mice by 18% compared to that in vehicle-treated mice (p </p>

<p>&lt;0.05), while the other phenotypic parameters in wild-type 
mice remained unchanged. More importantly, CB_36 had no 
effect on any parameters in Pcsk9 
-/-mice, suggesting that the 
action of CB_36 may involve a PCSK9-dependent pathway. 
The decrease in the plasma concentration of TC by CB_36 in 
wild-type mice was re-defined as a consequence of the de-
crease in LDL fractions in the lipoprotein profile determined 
by FPLC in wild-type mice (Fig. 3A; fraction numbers 15-22), 
while no change was observed in Pcsk9 
-/-mice. In wild-type 
mice, CB_36 also lowered the cholesterol level in fractions 
containing high-density lipoprotein (Fig. 3A; fraction num-
bers 23-30), of which the ApoE was also the ligand to the 
LDLR. 
22 However, in contrast to the results from HepG2 cells, 
CB_36 showed no differences in the amounts of LDLR and 
PCSK9 in the livers of wild-type or Pcsk9 
-/-mice (Fig. 3B). 
These results strongly suggest that CB_36 has the effect of low-
ering the TC level in plasma, particularly by lowering the LDL 
fraction of lipoproteins in a PCSK9-dependent manner, al-
though amounts of LDLR and PCSK9 in the liver remained 
unchanged. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Inhibition of PCSK9 is an attractive objective in the develop-
ment of new therapeutics for hypercholesterolemia. As almost 
all patents of statin drugs expired recently, numerous phar-
maceutical industries are devoting effort to developing new 
drugs that can be used in patients with hypercholesterolemia 
in combination with statins. The other advantage of PCSK9 
inhibition is possible augmentation of the cholesterol-lower-
ing effect by statins, which induce simultaneously the expres-
sion of PCSK9 and LDLR. Among several strategies applied 
for the development of PCSK9 inhibitors, it is evident that the 
most up-to-date approach is the use of monoclonal antibod-
ies against PCSK9. However, the cost-effectiveness and the in-
jection route of antibody therapeutics into patients with hy-
percholesterolemia alone would be the major obstacles to 
overcome. In this respect, recent advances in public compu-
tational algorithms and open chemical databases have en-</p>

<p>Table 2. The Effect of CB_36 in Wild-Type and Pcsk9 Knock-Out Mice </p>

<p>Parameter 
Wild-type 
Pcsk9 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>Vehicle 
CB_36 
Vehicle 
CB_36 
Number of mice 
6 
6 
5 
5 
Body weight (g) 
26.5±1.2 
26.5±0.3 
26.1±0.9 
27.4±1.4 
Liver weight (g) 
1.27±0.12 
1.24±0.03 
1.23±0.11 
1.31±0.15 
Liver weight/body weight (%) 
4.76±0.31 
4.68±0.04 
4.72±0.40 
4.78±0.34 
Plasma triglycerides (mg/dL) 
77±4 
63±5* 
38±11 
34±3 
Plasma cholesterol (mg/dL) 
71±9 
58±10 
58±3 
68±11 
SEM, standard error of the mean. 
Male mice, 10-12 weeks of age, were injected with CB_36 as described under "Materials and Methods." Each value represents the mean±SEM of the indicat-
ed number of mice. 
*p&lt;0.05 (Student's t-test) when compared with values in vehicle-injected mice. Similar results were obtained in one additional independent experiment. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.5.1251 </p>



<p>In silico Screening of PCSK9 Inhibitors </p>

<p>abled standard laboratories to carry out a large-scale screen-
ing of small molecular inhibitors of protein-protein interaction 
for drug development at ease. In silico virtual screening has 
been used to discover many small-molecule inhibitory li-
gands for enzymes such as BCR-ABL tyrosine kinase, 
23 P. falci-
parum dihydrofolate reductase, 
24 and inhibitors of protein-
protein interaction such as interaction between insulin-like 
growth factor-1 and the N-terminus of the IGF-binding pro-
tein-5 
25 or the C-terminal tail of myosin A and the myosin-tail 
interacting protein in P. falciparum. 
26 However, without any 
evident reason, there have been no known reports involving 
searches for small chemical molecules that inhibit PCSK9-
LDLR interaction. 
In this study, we report the first approach for the develop-
ment of small molecular inhibitors targeting the protein-pro-
tein interaction between PCSK9 and the LDLR by performing 
in silico virtual screening using commercially available chemi-
cal libraries and the GOLD algorithm. In general, in order to 
acceptably predict desirable compounds, multiple selection 
processes using various docking programs such as <rs type="software">AutoDock 
Vina</rs> 
27 or Glide 
28 must be applied; however, we did not attempt 
to complete these comprehensive processes, as the primary 
purpose of this study was to evaluate the usefulness of rela-
tively simple in silico chemical development methods that of-
fered ease of use. 
CB_36, the chemical with the highest docking score among 
100 predicted chemicals, was validated for its ability to inhibit 
the binding of PCSK9 to the EGF-AB domain of the LDLR in a 
dose-dependent manner (Supplementary Fig. 1, only online). 
Detailed kinetic studies on the mechanism of inhibition by 
CB_36 were not carried out, as the required research resourc-
es were unavailable and the purpose of this study was limited 
to the overall evaluation of the application of in silico screen-
ing. Direct evidence by mapping the ligand-binding site by 
site-directed mutagenesis of PCSK9 or by performing NMR </p>

<p>studies, for example, needs to be obtained in future studies. 
CB_36 and its two analogs, which were proposed by Chem-
Bridge's web-based information, inhibited the PCSK9-LDLR 
interaction and increased the amount of LDLR, PCSK9, and 
the uptake of LDL-cholesterol in vitro. Most importantly, 
CB_36 lowered the total plasma cholesterol level in wild-type 
mice, particularly LDL cholesterol. Several additional chemi-
cals other than CB_36 showed similar results both in vitro and 
in vivo (data not shown). However, the mechanism for this 
cholesterol-lowering effect by CB_36 could not be elucidated 
in mice, as the amounts of LDLR and PCSK9 remained un-
changed by CB_36. It is possible to assume that additional 
mechanisms exert a feedback reconstitution of the LDLR after 
an increase in the metabolism of LDL cholesterol in the liver 
as in lovastatin-treated wild-type mice, which showed a de-
crease in plasma LDL cholesterol despite a slight decrease in 
LDLR expression. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Additional concrete evidence for the usefulness of these 
chemicals remains to be provided, for example, whether these 
chemicals bind to PCSK9 directly, whether their effects are 
mediated by PCSK9 in a specific-manner, whether they are 
safe enough for practical application in patients, and why the 
decrease in blood cholesterol level by chemicals is minimal 
compared to that caused by statin drugs. However, this study 
provides strong support for in silico screening of chemical li-
braries for the development of new cholesterol-lowering agents 
that inhibit the interaction between PCSK9 and the LDLR. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>Hyun Joo Song at Phillips Exeter Academy, NH 03833, partici-
pated in the animal studies as an attendee of an Internship 
Program in 2013 held by the IGRCMD. This work was sup-
ported by a National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) 
grant funded by the Korean government [MSIP; (NRF-2008-</p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Fraction No. </p>

<p>Wild-type DMSO </p>

<p>Wild-type CB_36 </p>

<p>Pcsk9 
-/-DMSO </p>

<p>Pcsk9 
-/-CB_36 </p>

<p>5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 
35 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. In vivo effects of CB_36 in wild-type and Pcsk9 knockout mice. (A) FPLC profiles of plasma cholesterol from wild-type (WT) and Pcsk9 
-/-mice 
after injection with CB_36. The pooled plasma from mice described in Table 2 was fractionated by FPLC, and the concentration of cholesterol in each 
fraction was measured as described under "Materials and Methods." (B) Aliquots of liver lysates were subjected to SDS-polyacrylamide gel electro-
phoresis (livers from two mice were pooled for lanes 1-6 in WT and for lanes 7, 8, 10, and 11 in Pcsk9 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>), and amounts of Ldlr and Pcsk9 were deter-
mined by immunoblot analysis. Gapdh was used as an invariant control. FPLC, fast performance liquid chromatography. </p>

<p>Ldlr </p>

<p>Pcsk9 </p>

<p>Gapdh 
The amount of cholesterol (μg/fraction) </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Genotype 
Wild-type 
Pcsk9 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>Chemical 
DMSO 
CB_36 
DMSO 
CB_36 </p>

<p>Lane 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2015.56.5.1251 </p>

<p>Dong-Kook Min, et al. </p>

<p>313-E00086, NRF-2010-0011550, NRF-2011-0030086)] and by 
a faculty research grant from Yonsei University College of 
Medicine in 2007 (6-2007-0141). </p>



</text></tei>