<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4771038" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
There has been continued interest in clinical objective measures of binaural processing. One commonly proposed measure is 
the binaural interaction component (BIC), which is obtained typically by recording auditory brainstem responses 
(ABRs)-the BIC reflects the difference between the binaural ABR and the sum of the monaural ABRs (i.e., 
binaural À (left þ right)). We have recently developed an alternative, direct measure of sensitivity to interaural time differ-
ences, namely, a following response to modulations in interaural phase difference (the interaural phase modulation following 
response; IPM-FR). To obtain this measure, an ongoing diotically amplitude-modulated signal is presented, and the interaural 
phase difference of the carrier is switched periodically at minima in the modulation cycle. Such periodic modulations to 
interaural phase difference can evoke a steady state following response. BIC and IPM-FR measurements were compared from 
10 normal-hearing subjects using a 16-channel electroencephalographic system. Both ABRs and IPM-FRs were observed most 
clearly from similar electrode locations-differential recordings taken from electrodes near the ear (e.g., mastoid) in refer-
ence to a vertex electrode (Cz). Although all subjects displayed clear ABRs, the BIC was not reliably observed. In contrast, 
the IPM-FR typically elicited a robust and significant response. In addition, the IPM-FR measure required a considerably 
shorter recording session. As the IPM-FR magnitude varied with interaural phase difference modulation depth, it 
could potentially serve as a correlate of perceptual salience. Overall, the IPM-FR appears a more suitable clinical measure 
than the BIC. </p>

<p>Binaural hearing confers considerable advantages in 
everyday listening environments. Specifically, differences 
in the timing and intensity of a sound at the two ear-
s-interaural time and interaural level differences (ITDs 
and ILDs, respectively)-provide reliable cues as to the 
location of sound sources. Sensitivity to ITDs offers add-
itional advantages in cocktail party conditions, enabling 
listeners to follow a conversation against a background 
of interfering noise from other talkers or from room 
reflections (Bronkhorst, 2000). Sensitivity to ITDs con-
veyed in the temporal fine structure (TFS) of sounds 
is limited to frequencies below about 1.4 kHz; above 
this frequency, phase locking in the auditory nerve </p>

<p>apparently declines sharply, but sound wavelength 
decreases sufficiently to interact with the head to create 
useful localization cues based on ILD (Hartmann &amp; 
Macaulay, 2014; Mills, 1958; see Stecker &amp; Gallun, 
2012 for a review). However, since many real-world 
sounds are modulated in amplitude, additional ITD 
cues conveyed in the modulated envelopes of high-</p>

<p>1 UCL Ear Institute, UCL School of Life and Medical Sciences, University 
College London, UK </p>

<p>Corresponding author: 
Nicholas R. Haywood, Department of Linguistics, The Australian Hearing 
Hub, Macquarie University, 16 University Avenue, Sydney, NSW 2109, 
Australia. 
Email: nick.haywood@mq.edu.au </p>

<p>Creative Commons CC-BY-NC: This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 License 
(http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further 
permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access page (https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage). </p>

<p>Trends in Hearing 
2015, Vol. 19: 1-17 </p>

<p>! The Author(s) 2015 
Reprints and permissions: 
sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav 
DOI: 10.1177/2331216515619039 
tia.sagepub.com </p>

<p>frequency sounds also provide a potentially useful local-
ization cue (Bernstein &amp; Trahiotis, 1985; Henning, 1974). 
Given the benefits conferred by binaural hearing, par-
ticularly sensitivity to low-frequency ITDs, impairment 
to ITD processing is likely to be detrimental to auditory 
perception. ITD sensitivity declines with ageing (Abel, 
Giguere, Consoli, &amp; Papsin, 2000; Babkoff et al., 2002; 
Herman, Warren, &amp; Wagener, 1977; King, Hopkins, &amp; 
Plack, 2014)-consistent with the notion that temporal 
processing might be impaired in older listeners (Gallun 
et al., 2014; Moore, Glasberg, Stoev, Fu¨llgrabe, &amp; 
Hopkins, 2012)-and in listeners with hearing loss, 
albeit with variability (Moore, Hutchings, &amp; Meyer, 
1991; Noble, Byrne, &amp; Lepage, 1994; Smoski &amp; 
Trahiotis, 1986). Such impairments in ITD processing, 
which are not necessarily predicted by the perceived sen-
sation level of the stimulus, are interpreted as arising 
from some as-yet-undefined impairment in the process-
ing of TFS information following cochlear damage 
(Lacher-Fouge`re &amp; Demany, 2005). 
A desire to understand how hearing impairment 
results in (or from) a loss of sensitivity to information 
conveyed in the TFS of sounds has led to an interest in 
developing clinically viable, objective measures of bin-
aural processing. One commonly proposed electroence-
phalographic measure is the binaural interaction 
component (BIC). The analysis of the BIC is most com-
monly based on Wave V of the auditory brainstem 
response (ABR), since earlier response components do 
not show binaural interaction (e.g., Debruyne, 1984). 
The response of binaurally innervated neurons to bin-
aural stimulation is not necessarily twice that of mon-
aural stimulation. Hence, the summed magnitude of 
ABRs to sequential monaural stimulation of either ear 
alone can be larger than the magnitude of the ABR to 
simultaneous binaural presentation of the same stimulus 
(i.e., left-ear monaural ABR þ right-ear monaural 
ABR &gt; binaural ABR; Dobie &amp; Berlin, 1979; Dobie &amp; 
Norton, 1980). As such, the BIC can be attributed to 
simple binaural convergence at the level of the auditory 
brainstem but is not necessarily evidence of neural sen-
sitivity to ITD (Ungan &amp; Yagcioglu, 2002). Another, 
more practical, limitation of this measure is that the 
BIC derived from ABRs reflects only a small and 
subtle difference between ABR waveforms and can be 
difficult to detect against background noise in record-
ings, especially in neonates and children (Cone-Wesson, 
Ma, &amp; Fowler, 1997; Stollman, Snik, Hombergen, 
Nieuwenhuys, &amp; Koppel, 1996). The BIC calculated 
from middle-or late-latency responses, however, is usu-
ally somewhat larger (McPherson &amp; Starr, 1993). Direct 
comparisons between studies are confounded partially 
by differing stimuli and recording techniques, but many 
authors have reported successfully observing the ABR 
BIC despite the relatively small magnitude of the </p>

<p>component. For example, Ito, Hoke, Pantev, and 
Lu¨tkenho¨ner (1988) and Levine (1981) reported clear 
BIC responses in over 90% of subjects, and Fowler 
and Leonards (1985) and Fowler and Broadard (1988) 
reported successfully recording a BIC in all subjects 
tested (see also Van Yper, Vermeire, De Vel, Battmer, 
&amp; Dhooge, 2015). Several authors have reported high 
mean BIC amplitudes but without reporting individual 
variability; for example, Fowler and Horn (2012) 
reported a 0.30 mV BIC, Dobie and Norton (1980) 
reported a BIC amplitude of approximately 0.40 mV, 
and McPherson and Starr (1995) reported an exception-
ally large 0.85 to 0.92 mV BIC. Nevertheless, despite pre-
vious studies reporting apparently robust BIC 
recordings, many studies did not provide an estimate 
of signal-to-noise ratio (SNR), and so a complete inter-
pretation of findings is difficult. 
A number of studies have failed to demonstrate a 
consistent or reliable influence of ITDs on the BIC, 
although it is generally accepted that BIC amplitude 
decreases, and latency increases, as the ITD is increased. 
Furst, Levine, and McGaffigan (1985) proposed that the 
BIC of the ABR is a physiological correlate of binaural 
fusion, with the BIC being relatively constant in ampli-
tude for ITDs of up to 1 ms, but no BIC was observed 
for ITDs greater than 1.2 ms. Jones and Van der Poel 
(1990) calculated the BIC of middle-latency responses 
and demonstrated that the latency of the BIC was 
delayed by approximately half the magnitude of the 
ITD compared with the latency of the BIC latency 
observed for diotic presentation. Again, BIC amplitude 
varied little across the range of ITDs tested (0-800 ms; see 
also Brantberg, Hansson, Fransson, &amp; Rosenhall, 1999). 
In contrast, McPherson and Starr (1995) reported that 
the magnitude of the ABR-derived BIC decreased pro-
gressively with increasing ITD or ILD, and that the BIC 
remained detectable for ITDs up to 1600 ms ITD. Riedel 
and Kollmeier (2002) reported that the ABR BIC 
decreased significantly for an ITD of 400 ms in compari-
son to a diotic (zero ITD) stimulus. However, such find-
ings might be accounted for simply by the reduced 
overlap of the excitation from both ears arriving at 
binaurally sensitive neurons as the tone clicks are sepa-
rated in time by the ITD. 
More direct objective measures of ITD processing 
than the BIC can be evoked with salient changes to an 
ongoing stimulus and have been demonstrated with audi-
tory-evoked P1-N1-P2 responses, which are attributed to 
multiple generator sites in the thalamus and auditory 
cortex (Hari, Aittoniemi, Ja¨rvinen, Katila, &amp; Varpula, 
1980; Liegeois-Chauvel, Musolino, Badier, Marquis, &amp; 
Chauvel, 1994; Na¨a¨ta¨nen &amp; Picton, 1987; Picton, 
Hillyard, Krausz, &amp; Galambos, 1974). In particular, 
abrupt changes in either ITD (Halliday &amp; Callaway, 
1978; McEvoy, Picton, &amp; Champagne, 1991) or </p>

<p> 
Trends in Hearing </p>

<p>interaural correlation (Chait, Poeppel, de Cheveigne´, &amp; 
Simon, 2005; Dajani &amp; Picton, 2006) of a broadband 
noise can evoke P1-N1-P2 responses. Recording magne-
toencephalographic responses from normal-hearing 
listeners, Ross, Tremblay, and Picton (2007b) demon-
strated that an abrupt change in the interaural phase 
difference (IPD) at a minimum of an on-going ampli-
tude-modulated low-frequency tone elicited P1-N1-P2 
responses (see also Ross, Fujioka, Tremblay, &amp; Picton, 
2007a; Ross, 2008). In this study, an equal, diotic, rate of 
sinusoidal amplitude modulation (AM) was applied to 
both ears. The carrier was abruptly changed in IPD at 
an energy minimum in the modulation cycle, so as to 
minimize otherwise salient monaural phase-shift cues. 
Significant responses to the IPD transition were observed 
for carrier frequencies of 500 Hz and 1000 Hz but not for 
1500 Hz. This was broadly consistent with subjects' 
behavioral thresholds for detecting IPD changes 
($1200 Hz) and the upper frequency limit of IPD sensi-
tivity (Garner &amp; Wertheimer, 1951; Schiano, Trahiotis, 
&amp; Bernstein, 1986; Zwislocki &amp; Feldman, 1956). Steady-
state responses, such as those elicited by AM, are 
thought to reflect the superposition of transient middle-
latency responses (e.g., Galambos, Makeig, and 
Talmachoff, 1981). McAlpine, Haywood, Undurraga, 
and Marquardt (in press) demonstrated a steady-state 
response to periodic interaural phase modulations 
(IPMs) in an ongoing AM tone, in which IPM was 
applied periodically at minima in a 41-Hz diotic AM 
cycle. The abrupt IPD transitions occurred at a rate of 
6.8 Hz or every six AM cycles (see also Dajani &amp; Picton 
2006 for a related study employing periodic changes in 
the interaural correlation of noise). In contrast to Ross 
et al. (2007b), the IPD switched between left-and right-
ear leading, causing anti-phasic modulation in the acti-
vations of the left and right brain hemispheres, and a 
periodically changing stimulus lateralization percept. 
The periodic IPM evoked a steady-state response, 
termed the IPM following response, or IPM-FR. The 
magnitude of the IPM-FR varied with the depth of the 
IPM and was maximal in the AE90 
IPM condition; cor-
responding to an IPM depth of 180 
, the largest IPD 
transition is possible. Indeed, smaller or larger IPMs 
(e.g., AE67.5 
, AE112.5 
) elicited smaller magnitude 
responses. Furthermore, McAlpine et al. (in press) also 
provided psychophysical evidence that an IPM of AE90 </p>



<p>(i.e., a 180 
transition) was more perceptually salient 
than changes between smaller or larger IPDs, as expected 
(e.g., Garner &amp; Wertheimer, 1951). This correlation 
between evoked responses and behavioral performance 
supports the notion that the IPM-FR can provide a 
meaningful index of IPD sensitivity. 
The robust responses to IPD changes observed by 
McAlpine et al. (in press) suggest that the IPM-FR 
could be a suitable clinical measure of ITD sensitivity. </p>

<p>Here, we compare the clinical utility of the IPM-FR and 
the BIC, in terms of the reliability of detecting binaural-
evoked neural responses. The BIC was calculated in 
response to diotic stimuli only, using stimulus and rec-
ording parameters similar to those used by Riedel and 
Kollmeier (2002). As BIC amplitude is thought to either 
be unaffected or even marginally reduced by imposition 
of ITDs within the physiological range, the effect of ITD 
on the BIC was not investigated. A second aim of this 
study was to assess the best positioning of a single-
channel electrode montage for IPM-FR recordings. 
To this end, responses were recorded from 16 electrode 
channels, and their magnitudes were compared. 
We observed that subjects typically showed a robust 
IPM-FR, whereas the BIC was not reliably observed. 
Additionally, a single IPM-FR was observed within a 
considerably shorter recording time than the BIC 
(5 min vs. 30 min). The IPM-FR provided a measure of 
ITD sensitivity that could be related directly to percep-
tual saliency-as larger IPMs evoked larger magnitude 
IPM-FRs. From these findings, it is concluded that the 
IPM-FR is a measure of binaural processing with greater 
overall clinical utility than the BIC for acoustically hear-
ing subjects. </p>

<p>Method 
Subjects </p>

<p>Ten normal-hearing subjects took part in the experiment 
(five female, mean age ¼ 23 years; range 19-30 years). 
None reported any known hearing difficulties, and all 
demonstrated hearing thresholds of 20 dB HL or better 
for pure tones presented between 250 and 8000 Hz. The 
experiment lasted for approximately one and a half 
hours and was completed in a single session. The experi-
ment was approved by the University College London 
ethics committee. All subjects provided their informed 
consent before beginning the experiment and were paid 
an honorarium for their time. </p>

<p>Stimuli: BIC </p>

<p>Rarefaction click stimuli were 100 ms rectangular voltage 
pulses presented at 95 dB peSPL. The interval between 
successive stimuli was in the range 55 to 65 ms, as the 
duration of the interstimuli interval was jittered randomly 
between AE5 ms from a base of 60 ms. Subjects were pre-
sented with an equal number of left-ear monaural, right-
ear monaural, and binaural stimuli in a continuous 
sequence, and the presentation order of stimuli was ran-
domized within the sequence (10,440 of each arrangement, 
31,320 stimuli in total). The recording session lasted for 
approximately 30 min. Stimulus parameters were adapted 
from Riedel and Kollmeier (2002). </p>

<p>Haywood et al. </p>

<p>
Stimuli: IPM-FR </p>

<p>All stimuli comprised a 520-Hz carrier tone with full 
sinusoidal AM at a rate of 41 Hz. The stimulus was pre-
sented continuously for 4 min and 48 s, at 80 dB SPL. 
Only the carrier was presented with an IPD, as the 
modulation envelope remained diotic at all times. 
Although the magnitude of the carrier IPD was held 
constant throughout the stimulus, its sign was periodic-
ally modulated between leading in the right and the left 
ear to create IPM. The sign inversion generating the IPM 
was applied instantaneously at a minimum in the modu-
lation cycle. IPM occurred at a rate of 6.8 Hz (corres-
ponded to an IPD transition every six AM cycles)-a 
value that indicates the total number of IPD transitions 
per second, irrespective of the direction of the transition 
(see Figure 1). IPM rate was described in this manner </p>

<p>because the direction of the IPD transition was not pre-
dicted to affect the characteristics of the neural respon-
se-any directional effects would also be difficult to 
interpret due to the anticipated superpositioning of 
responses to successive IPD transitions. 
Five different depths of IPM were assessed. These dif-
ferent conditions are referred to by the magnitude of the 
ongoing IPD and not by overall change in IPD at each 
IPD transition. To this end, for example, the descriptor 
of AE45 
represents a condition in which carrier IPD was 
modulated between leading in the right ear by þ45 
and 
then leading in the left ear by À45 
. Accordingly, the 
IPD traversed 90 
at every IPD transition. Each IPD 
transition was created by concurrently alternating carrier 
phase at each ear. This means that, in the AE45 
condi-
tion, the phase of the signal in the right ear would </p>

<p>−24.4 ms 
0 ms 
+24.4 ms </p>

<p>Amplitude </p>

<p>[B] AM Signal (48.8 ms) </p>

<p>−4.4 ms 
0 ms 
+4.4 ms </p>

<p>Amplitude </p>

<p>[A] Unmodulated Signal (8.8 ms) </p>

<p>−294 ms 
−147 ms 
0 ms 
+147 ms 
+294 ms </p>

<p>Amplitude </p>

<p>[C] AM Signal (588 ms) </p>

<p>−294 ms 
−147 ms 
0 ms 
+147 ms 
+294 ms 
Time (ms) </p>

<p>[D] Intercranial Image (588 ms) </p>

<p>Figure 1. Schematic illustration of the IPM-FR stimuli. Note that differing time scales are used in plots a, b, c, andd. (a) Red and blue 
traces correspond to the stimuli presented to the right and left ear, respectively. Here, an on-going þ90 
IPD is imposed on an 
unmodulated carrier. At 0 s, an IPD transition to À90 
is imposed: The stimulus changes from right-ear leading to left-ear leading. 
(b) A 41-Hz AM is imposed on the carrier. The IPD transition occurs at a minima in the modulation cycle, reducing the perceptual salience 
of the monaural phase shifts. (c) Additional modulation cycles of the same stimulus are displayed. Here, the carrier is not illustrated; 
instead, red and blue shaded modulation cycles correspond to cycles in which the carrier IPD is leading in the right ear or left ear, 
respectively. Note that IPMs occurs every six modulation cycles, at a rate corresponding to 6.8 Hz. (d) Illustrative intercranial image 
locations associated with the stimulus shown in (c; if the IPM frequency would be &lt;2 Hz). </p>

<p> 
Trends in Hearing </p>

<p>alternate between þ22.5 
and À22.5 
, while that in the 
left ear would simultaneously alternate between À22.5 </p>



<p>and þ22.5 
. In total, five different IPM conditions were 
tested; AE22.5 
, AE45 
, AE90 
, AE112.5 
, and AE135 
(corres-
ponding, respectively, to ITDs of 120, 240, 481, 601, and 
721 ms for the 520-Hz carrier). 
To verify that the evoked responses were not elicited 
by monaural phase cues, two diotic control conditions 
were assessed. In these conditions, both ears shared the 
same carrier phase at all times, but diotic phase transi-
tions were imposed at a rate of 6.8 Hz. Phase changes of 
AE22.5 
and AE56.25 
were tested, corresponding to the 
size of the phase changes in the monaural signals of 
the AE45 
and AE112.5 
IPM conditions, respectively. 
Similar diotic control conditions were employed in the 
study by McAlpine et al. (in press), and the diotic phase 
changes did not evoke responses (see also Ross et al., 
2007a, 2007b). However, the presentation level in the 
current experiment was higher than the 65 dB SPL used 
by McAlpine et al. (in press), and so these two diotic 
control conditions were included to ensure no monaural 
effects existed at 80 dB SPL. </p>

<p>Procedure </p>

<p>Subjects first completed the BIC recording session and 
then completed the IPM-FR session. Subjects were </p>

<p>offered a short break between these two sessions. The 
BIC recording session comprised a single recording run 
of approximately 30 min, whereas the IPM-FR recording 
session comprised seven 5-min records (five IPM condi-
tions and two diotic controls). Here, subjects were pre-
sented with a single repetition of each condition, in a 
random order, during a single testing session. During 
all recordings, subjects sat in a comfortable chair in an 
acoustically isolated sound booth, were encouraged to sit 
as still as possible, and watched a subtitled film. 
Responses were differentially recorded primarily from 
silver or silver chloride disc surface electrodes; the refer-
ence electrode was placed on the vertex (Cz) and the 
ground electrode was placed on the right clavicle. 
Fourteen recording electrodes were placed around the 
scalp (F3, Fz, F4, C3, C4, T9, T10, P7, P3, Pz, P4, P8, 
O1, and O2-see Figure 2). Two additional electrodes 
were placed in the left and right ear canal (gold-coated 
foam insert ear tips-Etymotic ER3-26A; Etymotic 
Research Inc., IL, USA). Electrode impedances were 
kept below 5 kV and monitored throughout the record-
ing session. Stimuli were created in <rs id="software-0" type="software">MATLAB</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">2013b</rs> and 
presented via an RME Fireface UC sound card (24 bits, 
48 kHz sampling rate; RME, Haimhausen, Germany) 
connected to Etymotic Research ER-2 insert earphones 
(Etymotic Research Inc., IL, USA). Sound level was ver-
ified with a 2-cc ear simulator (Bru¨el &amp; Kjaer 4157, </p>

<p>C Z 
LE 
T 9 
T 7 
C 5 
C 3 
C 1 
C 2 
C 4 
C 6 
T 8 
T 10 
RE </p>

<p>TP 7 </p>

<p>P 7 </p>

<p>PO 7 </p>

<p>O 1 
O Z 
O 2 </p>

<p>PO 8 </p>

<p>P 8 </p>

<p>TP 8 </p>

<p>FT 8 </p>

<p>F 8 </p>

<p>AF 8 </p>

<p>FP 2 
FP Z 
FP 1 </p>

<p>AF 7 </p>

<p>F 7 </p>

<p>FT 7 </p>

<p>I Z </p>

<p>CP Z </p>

<p>P Z </p>

<p>PO Z </p>

<p>FC Z </p>

<p>F Z </p>

<p>AF Z </p>

<p>F 1 </p>

<p>FC 1 </p>

<p>CP 1 </p>

<p>P 1 </p>

<p>F 2 </p>

<p>FC 2 </p>

<p>CP 2 </p>

<p>P 2 </p>

<p>AF 3 </p>

<p>F 3 </p>

<p>FC 3 </p>

<p>CP 3 </p>

<p>P 3 </p>

<p>PO 3 </p>

<p>AF 4 </p>

<p>F 4 </p>

<p>FC 4 </p>

<p>CP 4 </p>

<p>P 4 </p>

<p>PO 4 </p>

<p>F 5 </p>

<p>FC 5 </p>

<p>CP 5 </p>

<p>P 5 </p>

<p>F 6 </p>

<p>FC 6 </p>

<p>CP 6 </p>

<p>P 6 </p>

<p>P 9 
P 10 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Schematic of the electrode positions used in the experiment. Electrode Cz served as a reference. Recording electrodes are 
shaded gray. RE and LE correspond to electrodes placed in the right and left ear canal (gold-coated foam inserts). </p>

<p>Haywood et al. </p>

<p>
Sound and Vibration Measurement A/S, Naerum, 
Denmark). Responses were amplified with a 20 Â gain 
(RA-16LI; Tucker-Davis Technologies, FL, USA) and 
digitized with 16 bits per sample at a rate 
of 24.414 kHz (Medusa RA16PA; Tucker-Davis 
Technologies). The cutoff frequencies of the internal 
bandpass filters were 2.2 Hz to 7.5 kHz (6 dB per 
octave). Recordings were stored on a TDT RX5 
Pentusa before being passed to the hard disk of the 
host computer via custom software. Subsequent off-line 
analysis was conducted in <rs id="software-2" type="software">MATLAB</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">2013b</rs>. </p>

<p>Data Analysis: BIC </p>

<p>ABR responses were first assessed for individual subjects 
and for each electrode channel separately. The entire 
ABR recording was divided into time windows 
(epochs) starting at stimulus onset and ending 10 ms 
after stimulus offset. Responses were then grouped 
according to whether they were evoked by left ear, 
right ear, or binaural stimulation. Responses to each of 
the three presentation types were averaged using a 
weighted averaging procedure (Don &amp; Elberling, 1994; 
Elberling &amp; Don, 1984; Elberling &amp; Wahlgreen, 1985). 
For all conditions, the average Wave V ampli-
tude-defined as the difference between the positive 
peak and the following trough-was identified by 
the experimenter. Earlier response components 
were not considered during analysis. The SNR was cal-
culated using the method proposed by Don and 
Elberling (1994). 
The BIC was computed from the established subtrac-
tion method-namely, by subtracting the binaural 
response waveform from the sum of the left-ear and 
right-ear monaural response waveforms (i.e., bin-
aural À [left þ right]). This was performed on the aver-
aged response waveforms from each subject, and each 
recording channel individually. The BIC amplitudes 
were identified by the experimenter at time windows cor-
responding broadly to Wave V of the ABR response, 
defined as the difference between the positive peak and 
the following negative trough. For the purpose of SNR 
estimation, it was assumed that the residual noise in the 
three ABR recordings was uncorrelated, and so the esti-
mate of residual noise in the BIC was calculated by sum-
ming the power of the variance from the three individual 
ABR recordings. </p>

<p>Data Analysis: IPM-FR </p>

<p>The IPM-FR analysis was conducted exclusively in the 
frequency domain. Each measurement was split into 75 
epochs of 4.096 s. Epochs were transformed to the fre-
quency domain (fast Fourier transform, 100,000 points, 
0.24 Hz resolution). For individual responses, the </p>

<p>frequency bins corresponding to the 6.8 Hz IPM rate 
and the 41 Hz AM rate were analyzed for significance 
using a two-dimensional, repeated measures Hotelling's 
T 
2 test (Picton, John, Dimitrijevic, &amp; Purcell, 2003). </p>

<p>Results 
ABR Results </p>

<p>Mean Wave V amplitudes and SNRs for all 10 subjects 
are shown in Table 1 for each of the 16 electrode chan-
nels. It is apparent that frontal and central electrodes did 
not reliably record ABR responses. Accordingly, a one-
way ANOVA-conducted on a subset of the binaural 
dataset for which electrodes in frontal (F3, Fz, and F4) 
and central (C3 and C4) positions were excluded from 
the analysis, and for which the dependent variable was 
the peak-to-peak amplitude-confirmed a significant 
effect of electrode position, F(10,90) ¼ 32.13, p &lt; .001. 
Bonferroni-corrected pairwise comparisons revealed 
that there were no significant differences between 
temporal, occipital, and in-ear electrodes. However, 
response amplitudes from centrally located parietal 
electrodes P3 and Pz were significantly lower than from 
temporal, occipital, and in-ear positions (p &lt; .05 in all 
cases). Further analyses of electrode position were not 
pursued, as it is well established that a vertex-mastoid 
montage provides optimal signal representation for 
single-channel scalp-based positions (e.g., Picton et al., 
1974). Finally, an analysis of the residual noise con-
ducted on the entire dataset confirmed a significant 
effect of electrode position, F(15,135) ¼ 9.20, p &lt; .001, 
but not of stimulus type, monaural: left, right, or bin-
aural: F(2,18) ¼ 0.04, p ¼ .96, and the interaction was 
also nonsignificant, F(30,270) ¼ 1.27, p ¼ .16. This indi-
cates that the residual noise did not vary with stimulus 
condition. 
A second ANOVA compared responses to binaural 
presentation from temporal-parietal (T9 and T10) and 
in-ear electrodes only. The two-way ANOVA with two 
factors (position vs. hemisphere) indicated no significant 
main effect of hemisphere, left ¼ 0.44 mV, right ¼ 0.49 mV: 
F(1,9) ¼ 4.45, p ¼ .064), or of position, in-ear ¼ 0.46 mV, 
scalp ¼ 0.47 mV: F(1,9) ¼ 2.45, p ¼ .15. A similar analysis 
of the SNR revealed it to be significantly higher for the 
in-ear position (15.63 dB) than for the scalp positions 
(14.56 dB), F(1,9) ¼ 10.75, p ¼ .009, and for the right 
hemisphere (15.98 dB) compared with the left hemi-
sphere (14.21 dB), F(1,9) ¼ 8.03, p ¼ .019. The interaction 
between factors was nonsignificant, F(1,9) ¼ 1.29, 
p &gt; .284. Overall, this suggests that in-ear electrodes 
may provide a modest improvement in the SNR of 
ABR recordings in comparison to proximate scalp-
placed electrodes. This is consistent with previous find-
ings (Atcherson, Lim, Moore, &amp; Minaya, 2012). </p>

<p> 
Trends in Hearing </p>

<p>Table 1. Mean ABR Wave V Data From All 16 Electrode Positions. </p>

<p>Right-monaural ABRs </p>

<p>Left-monaural ABRs </p>

<p>Binaural ABRs </p>

<p>BIC </p>

<p>Hemisphere Electrode Position </p>

<p>Mean 
amplitude </p>

<p>(nV) </p>

<p>Mean 
SNR 
(dB) </p>

<p>Number of 
responses 
53.01 </p>

<p>dB </p>

<p>SNR </p>

<p>Mean 
amplitude </p>

<p>(nV) </p>

<p>Mean 
SNR (dB) </p>

<p>Number of 
responses 
53.01 </p>

<p>dB </p>

<p>SNR </p>

<p>Mean 
amplitude </p>

<p>(nV) </p>

<p>Mean 
SNR 
(dB) </p>

<p>Number of 
responses 
53.01 </p>

<p>dB </p>

<p>SNR </p>

<p>Mean 
amplitude </p>

<p>(nV) </p>

<p>Mean 
SNR 
(dB) </p>

<p>Number of 
responses 
53.01 </p>

<p>dB </p>

<p>SNR </p>

<p>Left </p>

<p>F3 </p>

<p>Frontal </p>

<p>72.4 </p>

<p>À2.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>78.9 </p>

<p>À1.7 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>113.0 </p>

<p>1.7 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>À7.06 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>C3 </p>

<p>Central </p>

<p>63.7 </p>

<p>À1.7 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>70.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>75.1 </p>

<p>2.6 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>À5.09 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>P3 </p>

<p>Parietal 
(Medial) </p>

<p>69.1 </p>

<p>2.7 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>135.4 </p>

<p>5.2 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>173.5 </p>

<p>9.0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0.09 </p>

<p>À3.67 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>P7 </p>

<p>Parietal 
(Lateral) </p>

<p>108.3 </p>

<p>6.4 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>206.6 </p>

<p>8.3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>296.3 </p>

<p>11.9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0.11 </p>

<p>À7.20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>O1 </p>

<p>Occipital </p>

<p>196.4 </p>

<p>8.1 10 </p>

<p>259.9 </p>

<p>8.1 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>441.7 </p>

<p>14.0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>À4.32 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>T9 </p>

<p>Mastoid </p>

<p>194.8 </p>

<p>7.7 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>278.0 </p>

<p>9.5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>433.4 </p>

<p>13.5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>À4.08 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Left ear </p>

<p>Ear canal </p>

<p>182.8 </p>

<p>8.3 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>270.9 </p>

<p>11.1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>443.6 </p>

<p>15.0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>À6.37 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Right </p>

<p>F4 </p>

<p>Frontal </p>

<p>86.8 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>76.5 </p>

<p>À2.8 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>119.3 </p>

<p>2.3 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>À8.12 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>C4 </p>

<p>Central </p>

<p>97.1 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>52.3 </p>

<p>À5.4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>97.3 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>À16.22 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>P4 </p>

<p>Parietal 
(Medial) </p>

<p>152.2 </p>

<p>6.5 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>113.9 </p>

<p>3.3 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>239.3 </p>

<p>11.1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>À7.68 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>P8 </p>

<p>Parietal 
(Lateral) </p>

<p>233.2 </p>

<p>9.6 10 </p>

<p>157.1 </p>

<p>5.9 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>350.7 </p>

<p>13.5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>À6.77 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>O2 </p>

<p>Occipital </p>

<p>229.6 </p>

<p>8.9 10 </p>

<p>222.0 </p>

<p>7.1 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>433.0 </p>

<p>14.5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>À4.52 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>T10 </p>

<p>Mastoid </p>

<p>316.1 </p>

<p>11.6 10 </p>

<p>254.4 </p>

<p>8.8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>516.9 </p>

<p>15.7 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0.12 </p>

<p>À6.54 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Right ear Ear canal </p>

<p>287.3 </p>

<p>12.5 10 </p>

<p>212.1 </p>

<p>8.8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>471.5 </p>

<p>16.3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>À10.83 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Central </p>

<p>Fz </p>

<p>Frontal </p>

<p>53.9 </p>

<p>À3.7 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>49.2 </p>

<p>À4.7 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>79.7 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>À9.57 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Pz </p>

<p>Parietal </p>

<p>72.5 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>83.9 </p>

<p>À0.3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>129.6 </p>

<p>7.0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>À9.77 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Note. Data are averaged across all 10 subjects, and separately displayed for right-ear monaural, left-ear monaural, and binaural presentations. Data corresponding to the BIC are also presented. Mean peak-
to-peak amplitude, SNR (dB), and the number of significant responses (out of the 10 subjects) with an SNR of 53.01 </p>

<p>dB (Don et al., 1984). Both significant and nonsignificant responses contribute to the </p>

<p>mean values presented. ABR ¼ 
auditory brainstem responses; BIC ¼ 
binaural interaction component; SNR ¼ </p>

<p>signal-to-noise ratio. </p>

<p>Haywood et al. </p>

<p>
BIC Results </p>

<p>The BIC analysis focused exclusively on electrode chan-
nels T9, T10, right ear, and left ear, as these channels 
typically recorded the best ABR signals. A two-way 
ANOVA (position and hemisphere) assessed the BIC 
amplitude. The analysis revealed a significant main 
effect of hemisphere, left ¼ 0.14 mV, right ¼ 0.11 mV: 
F(1,9) ¼ 6.55, p ¼ .031, but not of position, 
in-ear ¼ 0.11 mV, scalp ¼ 0.14 mV: F(1,9) ¼ 4.41, p ¼ .065. 
A second ANOVA assessed how the SNR was affected 
by these factors. The interaction between factors was not 
significant, F(1,9) ¼ 0.232, p ¼ .641. This analysis again 
revealed 
a 
significant 
effect 
of 
hemisphere, 
right ¼À8.60 dB, left ¼À5.23 dB: F(1,9) ¼ 7.73, p ¼ .021, 
but not of position, in-ear ¼ À8.60 dB, scalp ¼ À5.13 dB: 
F(1,9) ¼ 1.81, p ¼ .082. The interaction between factors 
was not significant, F(1,9) ¼ 1.37, p ¼ 271. When con-
sidering the SNR of the BIC, the residual noise estimate 
was calculated from the sum of the power of the variance 
from the three individual ABR recordings. This estab-
lished procedure arguably yields a relatively conservative 
estimate of SNR. 
Given the lack of consistent differences between 
responses recorded at in-ear and scalp positions, we 
next assessed activity recorded at electrode T9 only-the 
electrode providing the highest mean amplitude 
(0.16 mV) and the best SNR (À4.08 dB). Individual 
values of SNR for this electrode are shown in Table 2, 
and individual BIC responses are shown in Figure 3(b); 
corresponding binaural ABR responses are shown in 
Figure 3(a). From Table 2 and Figure 3, it is apparent 
that the BIC was not reliably recorded from all sub-
jects-indeed, in the majority of cases, it was ambiguous 
as to whether the waveform interpreted as being the BIC 
was, in actual fact, simply variability in the noise. </p>

<p>IPM-FR Results </p>

<p>Responses were averaged across subjects to provide a 
mean response for each IPM condition. Illustrative 
group-averaged responses for the AE90 
IPM condition, 
as recorded from electrode T9, are shown in Figure 4. 
Note that here, and in other sections of the IPM-FR 
analysis, electrode T9 was chosen despite other right-
sided electrodes typically generating larger magnitude 
responses (see subsequent analyses). The choice of elec-
trode T9 was so IPM-FR characteristics could be com-
pared with the best-observed BIC-as this electrode 
recorded the largest mean amplitude and SNR for BIC 
responses. From Figure 4, a clear IPM-FR is evident, 
corresponding to the IPM rate (6.8 Hz), as well as a 
modulation-evoked auditory steady-state response 
(ASSR) at 41 Hz. In the first stage of analysis, data 
from the 16 electrode locations were averaged across 
all 10 subjects and the 5 IPM conditions. Mean spectral 
magnitude at 41 Hz and 6.8 Hz, SNR, and the number of 
significant responses from these recordings are summar-
ized in Table 3. Note that because the data in Table 3 are 
averaged across all IPM conditions (AE22.5 
to AE135 
), 
the systematic variation in IPM-FR magnitude with IPM 
depth is considered later in this section. Nevertheless, 
from Table 3, it is apparent that the IPM-FRs recorded 
from frontal and central electrodes (F3, Fz, F4, C3, and 
C4) had relatively low magnitudes and SNRs. As such, 
these electrodes were excluded from all further analysis. 
Group-averaged response amplitudes were compared by 
means of a three-way repeated measures ANOVA. 
Diotic control conditions were excluded from this ana-
lysis. We assessed the dependence of the IPM-FR on the 
electrode hemisphere (left vs. right), electrode position, 
and IPM condition. Electrode pZ was excluded from this 
analysis, owing to its mid-line position. We observed a </p>

<p>Table 2. BIC amplitude and SNR Values for Each of the 10 Subjects (S1, S2, . . .) for Mastoid and In-Ear Electrodes Locations. </p>

<p>S1 
S2 
S3 
S4 
S5 
S6 
S7 
S8 
S9 
S10 
Mean </p>

<p>BIC amplitude 
T10 
0.12 
0.15 
0.09 
0.13 
0.12 
0.06 
0.13 
0.15 
0.08 
0.17 
0.12 
T9 
0.21 
0.11 
0.16 
0.21 
0.13 
0.12 
0.14 
0.28 
0.05 
0.17 
0.16 
Right ear 
0.10 
0.16 
0.09 
0.09 
0.11 
0.07 
0.10 
0.14 
0.09 
0.07 
0.10 
Left ear 
0.18 
0.14 
0.10 
0.10 
0.14 
0.10 
0.16 
0.18 
0.06 
0.14 
0.13 </p>

<p>BIC SNR 
T10 
À5.93 
1.64 
À11.13 
À3.91 
À11.55 
À12.29 
À7.79 
À0.40 
À8.02 
À6.03 
À6.54 
T9 
À0.56 
À0.94 
0.67 
0.27 
À13.71 
À3.50 
À13.11 
À0.54 
À6.93 
À2.46 
À4.08 
Right ear 
À6.88 
À5.04 
À8.66 
À31.93 
À12.50 
À14.21 
À5.46 
À6.24 
À11.30 
À6.03 
À10.83 
Left ear 
À0.97 
À2.27 
ÀÀ8.43 
À20.27 
À2.40 
À5.74 
À4.81 
À3.40 
À8.38 
À7.06 
À6.37 </p>

<p>Note. Each subject's highest amplitude or SNR value is indicated in italics. BIC ¼ binaural interaction component; SNR ¼ signal-to-noise ratio. </p>

<p> 
Trends in Hearing </p>

<p>main effect of electrode position, F(4,36) ¼ 31.23, 
p &lt; .001, and of IPM, F(4,36) ¼ 4.11, p ¼ .007. There 
was also a significant effect of hemisphere, with right-
sided 
electrodes 
recording 
larger 
responses, 
F(1,9) ¼ 26.93, p &lt; .001. No interactions were significant 
(p &gt; .05 in all cases). Concerning electrode position, 
Bonferroni-corrected post-hoc analysis indicated both 
mastoid (T9 and T10) and in-ear electrodes to generate 
significantly stronger responses than all parietal elec-
trodes (P3, P4, P7, and P8; p &lt; .05 in all comparisons). 
No other comparisons were significantly different from 
each other (p &gt; .05 in all comparisons). Mean response 
magnitudes for different electrode positions are displayed 
in Figure 5. 
We next assessed the influence of the depth of IPM on 
the magnitude of the IPM-FR (Figure 6). In general, a 
broad tuning function was observed, with theAE90 
IPM 
condition evoking the largest IPM-FR. Bonferroni-</p>

<p>corrected post-hoc analysis revealed that responses in 
the AE90 
condition were significantly larger than either 
the AE22.5 
or AE135 
conditions (p &lt; .05 in both cases), 
but not from either the AE45 
or AE112.5 
conditions 
(p &gt; .05 in both cases). Both the AE45 
and AE112.5 
con-
ditions evoked significantly larger responses than the 
AE22.5 
condition (p &lt; .05). No other differences were sig-
nificant (p &gt; .05 in all cases). To demonstrate that IPM-
FR observed under optimal recording parameters is 
robust, Table 4 illustrates responses from the AE90 </p>



<p>IPM condition as recorded from electrode T9. Nine of 
the 10 subjects displayed clear and significant IPM-FR 
responses. Only subject S2 showed a nonsignificant IPM-
FR response and a poor SNR. Nonetheless, this subject 
did display a clear 41-Hz ASSR (Table 4, bottom 
panels), and so it is possible that a single earphone 
may have been partially blocked. This would have 
reduced interaural cues, but would have had less effect </p>

<p>Figure 3. (a) Individual binaural ABR responses recorded from electrode T10. Each trace corresponds to the average response from a 
single subject (as indicated by the labels S1-S10). Narrow vertical lines indicate the values in the waveform that were used by the 
experimenter to estimate Wave V amplitude. (b) Individual BIC responses recorded from electrode T9. Each trace corresponds to the BIC 
from a single subject; presented in the same subject order as used in (a). Narrow vertical lines indicate the values in the waveform to 
estimate BIC amplitude. (c and d) As for 3(a) and 3(b), respectively, except the plots represent responses observed from electrode T10. </p>

<p>Haywood et al. </p>

<p>
on the AM-evoked ASSR, which can also be evoked 
monaurally. 
Diotic controls were tested for the AE45 
and AE112.5 </p>



<p>conditions. In contrast to the IPM conditions, diotic 
responses at all recording electrodes had a negative 
SNR (Table 3). A two-way ANOVA concerning elec-
trode T9 only investigated how response magnitude 
was affected by both phase transition sizes in the stimuli 
(45 
and 112.5 
, corresponding to AE45 
and AE112.5 </p>



<p>IPM conditions) and control (diotic) versus IPM 
(dichotic) presentation. This analysis did not find a sig-
nificant main effect of IPM, F(1,9) ¼ 2.96, p ¼ .0631, but, 
most importantly, did reveal a significant effect inter-
aural phase configuration (i.e., diotic vs. IPM), 
F(1,9) ¼ 20.19, p ¼ .001. The interaction was not signifi-
cant. Overall, the data indicate that the IPM-FR evoked </p>

<p>a substantially larger response than comparative diotic 
phase shifts (see also Table 3). This is evidence that the 
IPM-FR reflects primarily binaural processing. 
Of less importance for the research question, but 
nevertheless interesting, is the analysis of the ASSR to 
the 41-Hz AM. Subjects typically displayed a strong 
ASSR alongside the IPM-FR (e.g., see Table 4). 
A three-way ANOVA was conducted on the hemi-
sphere-separated dataset (i.e., F3, Fz, F4, C3, C4, and 
Pz excluded) and confirmed a significant effect of elec-
trode position, F(4,36) ¼ 16.62, p &lt; .001, but not of IPM, 
F(4,36) ¼ 1.99, p ¼ .117. There was a significant main 
effect of hemisphere, F(1,9) ¼ 20.14, p ¼ .003, due to 
responses being larger for right-sided electrodes. The 
interaction between hemisphere and position was also 
significant, F(4,36) ¼ 4.77, p ¼ .03. The lack of an effect </p>

<p>0 
0.15 
0.29 
0.44 
0.58 
−1500.0 </p>

<p>−1000.0 </p>

<p>−500.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>500.0 </p>

<p>1000.0 </p>

<p>1500.0 </p>

<p>Time (s) </p>

<p>Voltage (nV) </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>±90°IPM: Time domain response </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
0.0 </p>

<p>250.0 </p>

<p>500.0 </p>

<p>750.0 </p>

<p>1000.0 </p>

<p>1250.0 </p>

<p>1500.0 </p>

<p>Frequency (Hz) 
Spectral Magnitude (nV) </p>

<p>±90°IPM: Frequency domain response </p>

<p>Figure 4. (a) Averaged responses from the AE90 
IPM condition, as recorded from electrode T9. Time domain responses were filtered 
between 2 Hz and 20 Hz. The grand averaged response is highlighted with a thick black line, whereas individual responses are shown in gray. 
Dashed vertical lines indicate the time at which IPD transitions occurred. Note that for illustrative clarity, data in this panel are presented 
after being averaged into a 0.585 s epoch-for the main analysis and the spectrum below (b), a longer epoch was used (4.096 s). (b) 
Averaged responses in the frequency domain. The grand averaged response is highlighted with a thick black line, whereas individual 
responses are shown in gray. Data in this panel were not low-pass filtered. Note the clear peaks in the response at 6.8 Hz and 41 Hz, 
corresponding to the IPM rate and the amplitude modulation rate, respectively. As such, both forms of modulation are interpreted to have 
evoked a neural following response. </p>

<p> 
Trends in Hearing </p>

<p>of IPM on ASSR magnitude was not due to the inclusion 
of poor-performing electrodes, as a one-way ANOVA, 
conducted for responses from electrode T9 only, indi-
cated no significant effect of IPM condition on ASSR 
magnitude, F(4,36) ¼ 0.33, p ¼ .867. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We recorded BIC and IPM-FR responses in the same 
group of normal-hearing subjects, with the primary 
aim of comparing the reliability of both measures. In 
general, the BIC proved difficult to detect, being of low 
amplitude and, in most cases, showed a negative 
SNR-even when recorded from electrode montages 
considered optimal for ABRs (King &amp; Sininger, 1992; 
Sininger &amp; Don, 1989). As such, it was difficult to inter-
pret whether peaks in the residual waveform truly 
reflected a BIC. This was despite the fact that subjects' 
ABR responses were reliably observed. In line with our 
experience reported here, several reports have concluded 
that the low amplitudes and high intersubject variability </p>

<p>of the BIC limit its potential usefulness as a clinical 
measure of binaural function (Stollman et al., 1996; 
Van Yper et al., 2015; Wilson, Kelly-Ballweber, &amp; 
Dobie, 1985). A primary interest of the current research 
was to develop an objective measure of ITD processing, 
not just of binaural convergence. Given that BIC ampli-
tude is either not influenced or is reduced when an ITD is 
imposed (e.g., Brantberg et al., 1999; Riedel &amp; 
Kollmeier, 2002), it would likely have been challenging 
to record BIC responses to stimuli with ITD in the cur-
rent experiment. Nevertheless, any successful replication 
of previous findings concerning the effect of ITD on the 
BIC could potentially allow for further comparison 
between the two measures tested here by correlating, 
for example, how individual response properties change 
with increasing ITD or IPD. However, on the basis of 
the current data, clear challenges exist when measuring 
the BIC. Moreover, these challenges limit the clinical 
utility of the BIC for measuring binaural processing in 
normal-hearing listeners and, likely, in hearing-impaired 
listeners also. The measure may, however, have greater </p>

<p>Table 3. Mean IPM-FR Data for the 16 Electrode Positions. </p>

<p>ASSR (41 Hz) 
IPM-FR (6.8 Hz) 
Diotic (6.8 Hz) </p>

<p>Hemisphere Electrode Position </p>

<p>Mean 
spectral 
magnitude 
(nV) </p>

<p>Mean 
SNR 
(dB) </p>

<p>Percent 
significant 
(Hotelling's T 
2 ) </p>

<p>Mean 
spectral 
magnitude 
(nV) </p>

<p>Mean 
SNR 
(dB) </p>

<p>Percent 
significant 
(Hotelling's T </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Mean 
spectral 
magnitude 
(nV) </p>

<p>Mean 
SNR 
(dB) </p>

<p>Percent 
significant 
(Hotelling's T 
2 ) </p>

<p>Left 
F3 
Frontal 
169.8 
9.4 
84.4 
168.1 
À1.8 18 
127.5 
À4.3 
0 </p>

<p>C3 
Central 
75.7 
10.0 
91.1 
88.0 
À2.7 
6 
62.5 
À2.3 
0 </p>

<p>P3 
Parietal 
(Medial) </p>

<p>378.8 
21.5 
100 
207.6 
1.7 42 
114.3 
À1.5 
0 </p>

<p>P7 
Parietal 
(Lateral) </p>

<p>515.9 
20.0 
100 
313.5 
2.8 50 
133.4 
À2.6 10 </p>

<p>O1 
Occipital 
693.0 
22.0 
100 
343.1 
3.9 58 
163.1 
À1.9 15 
T9 
Mastoid 
667.6 
21.2 
100 
398.2 
6.1 80 
144.2 
À2.1 10 
Left ear 
Ear canal 
652.1 
22.0 
100 
421.0 
6.1 78 
154.1 
À1.8 
0 </p>

<p>Right 
F4 
Frontal 
145.1 
8.6 
82.2 
150.5 
À1.2 24 
123.8 
À2.0 15 
C4 
Central 
106.7 
13.7 
100 
107.1 
1.3 38 
54.2 
À4.7 
5 </p>

<p>P4 
Parietal 
(Medial) </p>

<p>532.8 
23.8 
100 
290.6 
3.7 66 
105.4 
À1.3 15 </p>

<p>P8 
Parietal 
(Lateral) </p>

<p>663.9 
23.8 
100 
403.2 
7.0 86 
128.2 
À3.3 
5 </p>

<p>O2 
Occipital 
693.9 
22.3 
100 
397.4 
À1.0 22 
255.8 
À2.7 10 
T10 
Mastoid 
792.3 
24.9 
100 
463.2 
7.9 84 
145.4 
À0.9 10 
Right ear Ear canal 
728.6 
24.3 
100 
446.3 
7.1 80 
141.9 
À1.8 10 
Central 
Fz 
Frontal 
122.7 
11.6 
84.4 
110.8 
À2.5 
8 
92.2 
À2.0 
5 </p>

<p>Pz 
Parietal 
365.6 
23.9 
100 
184.3 
1.6 52 
78.2 
À1.3 10 </p>

<p>Note. Data are averaged across all 10 subjects. Mean spectral magnitude, SNR, and the percentage of significant responses (Hotelling's T 
2 test) are displayed. 
Column (A) reflects the 41 Hz ASSR evoked from the amplitude modulation envelope; data from the five IPM conditions plus the two control conditions are 
averaged. Column (B) reflects the 6.8 Hz IPM-FR evoked from the periodic IPMs; data from the five (Dichotic) IPM conditions are averaged. Column (C) 
reflects the average 6.8 Hz evoked response observed from the two diotic control conditions. Concerning the group-averaged data, the mean SNR values 
indicate that the spectral magnitude at this frequency bin (6.8 Hz) was undistinguishable from the noise floor. ASSR ¼ auditory steady-state response; 
IPM-FR ¼ interaural phase modulation following response; SNR ¼ signal-to-noise ratio. </p>

<p>Haywood et al. </p>

<p>
merit for assessing bilateral cochlear implant users, a 
consideration discussed later in this section. 
The second measure tested in the current experiment, 
the IPM-FR, showed considerable advantages over the 
BIC. In the optimum AE90 
IPM condition, as recorded 
at electrode T9, the mean response spectral magnitude 
was 0.47 mV, and 9 out of the 10 subjects displayed SNRs 
in excess of 9 dB (Table 4). A single subject failed to 
display an IPM-FR response. Direct comparisons 
between BIC and IPM-FR measures are made difficult 
due to the different nature of the two responses. Instead, 
one can consider the number of reliably observed 
responses for each measure. Electrode T9, on average, 
recorded the best BIC SNR. Even so, none of the 10 
subjects displayed a significant BIC at this recording 
site (compare values in Table 2 with the criterion SNR 
of 53.01 dB, as suggested by Don &amp; Waring, 1984). In 
contrast, for the AE90 
IPM condition, 9 of the 10 sub-
jects displayed a significant IPM-FR (as evaluated with a 
Hotelling's T 
2 test suggested by Picton et al., 2003; see </p>

<p>Table 4). A McNemar's test conducted on these results 
confirmed that significantly more significant responses 
were observed with the IPM-FR measure than with the 
BIC (McNemar's chi-squared ¼ 7.11, df ¼ 1, p &lt; .01). On 
the basis of signal detection, the current results provide 
strong evidence that the IPM-FR is a more efficient 
measure than the BIC. The IPM-FR confers additional 
practical benefits over the BIC, particularly in terms of 
time efficiency-a single IPM-FR recording lasts around 
5 min. Further investigations could assess whether even 
this short recording duration could be reduced further 
while preserving the reliably detectable response. In con-
trast, a single BIC measurement required 30 min in the 
current experiment, and a reduction in recording time 
seems impossible given the already poor SNR of the 
BIC response. A second benefit is that the IPM stimulus 
also captures an ASSR response to the modulation enve-
lope that can serve as a monitor of the recording quality. 
In populations with impaired ITD processing, the rela-
tive strengths of the ASSR, which reflects neural </p>

<p>P3 P7 O1 Ear T9 
P4 P8 O2 Ear T10 
0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>450 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>550 </p>

<p>Mean Spectral Magnitude (nV) </p>

<p>Electrode Position </p>

<p>Left Hemisphere 
Right Hemisphere </p>

<p>Figure 5. The spectral magnitude of the IPM-FR as observed from different electrode locations. Data are averaged across subjects and all 
IPM-FR conditions. Note that response magnitudes were comparatively larger in the right hemisphere in the left hemisphere. Largest 
magnitude responses were observed from the In-Ear and Mastoid positioned electrodes. Error bars represent þ1 standard error. Frontally 
and centrally located electrodes failed to detect a reliable IPM-FR (Table 3) and so are not represented in this figure. </p>

<p> 
Trends in Hearing </p>

<p>sensitivity to the temporal envelope, and the IPM-FR, 
which reflects sensitivity to the TFS, may be insightful, 
and further study could compare the ratio of ASSR and 
IPM-FR magnitudes in subjects with normal and psy-
choacoustically assessed impairment in binaural 
processing. 
The robust nature of the IPM-FR is consistent with 
the results of McAlpine et al. (in press). As for both 
McAlpine et al. (in press) and Ross et al. (2007a, 
2007b), diotic phase-shifted stimuli did not evoke follow-
ing responses, and so the IPM-FR is interpreted as an 
indication of dedicated ITD processing. Thus, unlike the 
BIC, the IPM-FR provides a direct measure of ITD pro-
cessing, as the magnitude of the IPM-FR varied mean-
ingfully with the magnitude of the IPM depth. In the 
current experiment, we observed a broad tuning in the 
magnitude of the IPM-FR to the AE90 
condition. This 
condition corresponded to an IPM of 180 
, which is the </p>

<p>largest IPD difference possible, giving the cyclic nature 
of phase. Testing similar conditions, the study by 
McAlpine et al. (in press) also demonstrated tuning to 
IPM depth, and in addition showed a correlation 
between IPM-FR magnitude and IPM detection in a psy-
chophysical task (an adaptive masking-based proced-
ure). Such findings extend upon previous studies by 
Ross et al. (2007a, 2007b), as these authors tested only 
an IPD transition from diotic to anti-phasic, an arrange-
ment which would unlikely cause variation in the hemi-
spheric balance of brain activation. The current stimuli 
were modulated between symmetrical left-and right-
leading IPDs, and so would likely modulate the activa-
tion of left and right brain hemispheres, as well as the 
stimulus lateralization percept. 
There is considerable interest in developing an object-
ive measurement of binaural processing in bilateral 
cochlear-implant users. An electrically evoked BIC has </p>

<p>±22.5°±45°±67.5°±90°±112.5°±135°2 
00 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>450 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>550 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>650 </p>

<p>Mean Spectral Magnitude (nV) </p>

<p>IPM Condition </p>

<p>T9 </p>

<p>T10 </p>

<p>Left Hemisphere Mean </p>

<p>Right Hemisphere Mean </p>

<p>Figure 6. The effect of IPM depth on the mean spectral magnitude of the IPM-FR. The gray traces indicate mean response magnitudes as 
observed from electrodes T9 (circles) and T10 (downward triangles). The black traces indicate mean data as averaged from all good 
electrodes sites. The left hemisphere dataset (circles) indicate the mean from electrodes P3, P7, O1, T9, and the left in-ear electrode. The 
right hemisphere dataset (downward triangles) indicate the mean from electrodes P4, P8, O2, T10, and the right in-ear electrode. Error 
bars indicate AE1 standard error. </p>

<p>Haywood et al. </p>

<p>
been observed from bilateral cochlear implant users, 
which is characterized by a shorter latency and larger 
amplitude than the acoustically derived BIC associated 
with normal hearing (Gordon, Valero, &amp; Papsin, 2007; 
He, Brown, &amp; Abbas, 2010; Pelizzone, Kasper, &amp; 
Montandon, 1990). This likely reflects in part differing 
morphologies associated with acoustically and electric-
ally evoked ABRs. Reduced evoked ABR latency is 
attributed to a reduced synaptic delay, resulting from 
the absence of a cochlear travelling wave and the synap-
tic excitation of afferent neurons (Van den Honert &amp; 
Stypulkowski, 1986). Increased response amplitudes 
likely reflect increased synchronicity in peripheral 
responses to electrical stimulation (e.g., Shepherd &amp; 
Javel, 1997). Evidence exists to suggests that the 
BIC might be a useful tool for matching implant elec-
trodes across the ears (interaurally)-with stimulation to 
tonotopically matched electrode pairs evoking a 
larger amplitude BIC (He et al., 2010; Hu &amp; Dietz, 
2015). The electrically evoked BIC has also been 
observed in children, and those with a longer duration 
of unilateral CI use prior to bilateral implantation 
showed increased BIC latency (Gordon et al., 2007). 
Concerning the IPM-FR, it may be possible to translate 
the stimulus paradigm to electrical stimulation and 
so assess sound-source localization abilities objectively 
in subjects with bilateral cochlear implants. Such a 
measure could also be used for matching interaural elec-
trode pairs. However, it remains to be established 
whether rapid changes in ongoing ITD would be salient 
to bilateral CI users. 
One aim of the current study was to confirm the opti-
mum electrode positions for single-channel IPM-FR 
recordings. For both ABR and modulation-evoked 
ASSR recordings, the data are consistent with the clin-
ical convention that vertex-mastoid differential recording 
are optimal (e.g., see also Picton et al., 1974 for ABR; 
Tlumak, Rubinstein, &amp; Durrant, 2007 for an ASSR </p>

<p>review). Although IPM-FR responses have not previ-
ously been investigated, we also found that the electrode 
montages that best recorded the modulation ASSR (i.e., 
temporal and parietal positions) were also those that best 
recorded the IPM-FR component. Further research 
would be required to identify the exact generator site 
for the IPM-FR. It is plausible that the IPM-FR reflects 
a superpositioning of successive P1-N1-P2 responses. 
This is because Dajani and Picton (2006) demonstrated 
that periodic modulations to the correlation of interaural 
noise evoked P1-N1-P2 responses at slow modulation 
rates (&lt;3 Hz), but at faster modulation rates (e.g., 
&gt;6 Hz), the evoked response to this modulation 
became steady state in nature. If this finding extends to 
the IPM-FR paradigm used currently, P1-N1-P2 gener-
ators are thought to be located in lateral aspects of 
Heschl's gyrus and the temporal plane (Eggermont &amp; 
Ponton, 2002; Pantev et al., 1995). In contrast, the 
steady-state responses are thought to originate more 
medially in primary auditory cortex (Ma¨kela¨&amp; Hari, 
1987; Pantev, Roberts, Elbert, Ross, &amp; Wienbruch, 
1996). As such, if the IPM-FR does indeed reflect a 
superpositioning of P1-N1-P2 responses occurring at a 
relatively slow rate (i.e., 6.8 Hz), it is conceivable that 
generators at either or both of these sites exist. Further 
study would be required to establish the exact nature of 
the IPM-FR and the associated generator sites. 
In practical terms, however, responses from primary 
auditory cortex will likely share the same optimum pos-
itioning of scalp-based electrodes, and so it is unsurpris-
ing that both the ASSR and the IPM-FR share similar 
optimum positions. Both IPM-FR and ASSR responses 
were asymmetrical, as larger responses were observed in 
electrodes placed on the right hemisphere. This is con-
sistent with the notion that the right hemisphere may be 
more selective to spatial information (Paloma¨ki, 
Tiitinen, Ma¨kinen, May, &amp; Alku, 2005; Salminen, 
Tiitinen, Yrttiaho, &amp; May, 2010; Tiitinen et al., 2006). </p>

<p>Table 4. IPM-FR and ASSR Response Characteristics for Each of the 10 Subjects (S1, S2, . . .) From Electrode Position T9 Only. </p>

<p>Subject </p>

<p>S1 
S2 
S3 
S4 
S5 
S6 
S7 
S8 
S9 
S10 </p>

<p>IPM-FR (6.8 Hz) 
Spectral magnitude (nV) 517.2 
297.2 
542.7 
463.9 
832.6 
296.4 
524.3 
481.4 
470.4 
300.1 
SNR (dB) 
8.1 
À0.1 
13.1 
8.4 
15.3 
6.8 
11.6 
12.7 
7.8 
5.4 
p value (Hotelling's T </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) &lt;0.005 
&gt;0.05 
&lt;0.0001 &lt;0.001 
&lt;0.0001 &lt;0.005 
&lt;0.0001 &lt;0.0001 &lt;0.005 
&lt;0.05 </p>

<p>ASSR (41 Hz) 
Spectral magnitude (nV) 511.7 
231.8 
544.8 
608.7 
462.2 
284.7 
1169.7 
974.8 
953.2 
419.5 
SNR (dB) 
18.4 
20.5 
20.0 
23.4 
16.6 
16.3 
23.7 
26.8 
25.4 
21.1 
p value (Hotelling's T </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) &lt;0.0001 &lt;0.0001 &lt;0.0001 &lt;0.0001 &lt;0.0001 &lt;0.0001 &lt;0.0001 &lt;0.0001 &lt;0.0001 &lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>Note. Data reflect the AE90 
IPM condition only. ASSR ¼ auditory steady-state response; IPM-FR ¼ interaural phase modulation following response; SNR ¼ 
signal-to-noise ratio. </p>

<p> 
Trends in Hearing </p>

<p>Previous studies have also demonstrated ASSRs to be 
most strongly represented in the right hemisphere 
(Poelmans, Luts, Vandermosten, Ghesquie`re, &amp; 
Wouters, 2012; Ross, Herdman, &amp; Pantev, 2005). 
Despite this, the IPM-FR was also well observed from 
left-sided electrodes, and indeed, detailed single-channel 
IPM-FR analysis was conducted primarily from elec-
trode T9. This electrode was chosen as it observed the 
best BIC response-albeit, even for this electrode the 
BIC was not reliably observed (see Table 2). Despite 
this criterion, the IPM-FR was observed clearly from 
this recording site. Finally, we demonstrated that in-ear 
electrodes offer little advantage to mastoid-placed sur-
face electrodes. 
In summary, our comparison of the magnitude and 
reliability of the IPM-FR compared with the BIC sug-
gests that the IPM-FR could be a more clinically viable 
measure of ITD sensitivity in terms of signal detection. 
Further study could investigate the IPM-FR in clinical 
populations such as the elderly or the hearing impaired. 
For example, Ross et al. (2007a) demonstrated that both 
the N1-P2 response magnitude and psychophysical 
detection thresholds for a change in IPD both deterio-
rated as carrier frequency was increased. Using both 
measures, these authors demonstrated the upper fre-
quency limit of ITD sensitivity decreased with aging. 
Moreover, the ITD-change-evoked response latency 
increased with ageing-but the evoked response to 
sound onset was consistent across groups. One might 
expect the IPM-FR to similarly be able to characterize 
reduced ITD sensitivity in elderly and potentially hearing 
impaired populations. </p>

<p>Declaration of Conflicting Interests </p>

<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with 
respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this 
article. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>The authors disclosed receipt of the following financial sup-
port for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this 
article: The research leading to these results has received fund-
ing from the European Union's Seventh Framework 
Programme (FP7/2007-2013) under ABCIT grant agreement 
number 304912. </p>



<p>Haywood et al. </p>



<p>
 
Trends in Hearing </p>



<p>Haywood et al. </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>