<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4038421" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>correspondence: sam-Wook choi 
gangnam eulji hospital, eulji University, 
202 Dosan-daero, gangnam-gu, seoul, 
135-816, south Korea 
Tel +82 2 3438 1121 
Fax +82 2 3438 1001 
email peaceinu@hanmail.net </p>

<p>Purpose: This study aimed to classify distinct subgroups of people who use both smartphone 
and the internet based on addiction severity levels. Additionally, how the classified groups dif-
fered in terms of sex and psychosocial traits was examined. 
Methods: A total of 448 university students (178 males and 270 females) in Korea participated. 
The participants were given a set of questionnaires examining the severity of their internet and 
smartphone addictions, their mood, their anxiety, and their personality. Latent class analysis 
and ANOVA (analysis of variance) were the statistical methods used. 
Results: Significant differences between males and females were found for most of the variables 
(all P,0.05). Specifically, in terms of internet usage, males were more addicted than females 
(P,0.05); however, regarding smartphone, this pattern was reversed (P,0.001). Due to these 
observed differences, classifications of the subjects into subgroups based on internet and smart-
phone addiction were performed separately for each sex. Each sex showed clear patterns with the 
three-class model based on likelihood level of internet and smartphone addiction (P,0.001). 
A common trend for psychosocial trait factors was found for both sexes: anxiety levels and 
neurotic personality traits increased with addiction severity levels (all P,0.001). However, Lie 
dimension was inversely related to the addiction severity levels (all P,0.01). 
Conclusion: Through the latent classification process, this study identified three distinct 
internet and smartphone user groups in each sex. Moreover, psychosocial traits that differed in 
terms of addiction severity levels were also examined. It is expected that these results should 
aid the understanding of traits of internet and smartphone addiction and facilitate further study 
in this field. 
Internet addiction is defined as the inability to control one's internet use and is a con-
dition that results in the serious impairment of various life functions. 
1-4 Over the last 
2 decades, the global internet-using population has grown to almost 2.5 billion. 
5 It is 
an undeniable fact that internet brings many benefits to our lives. However, emerg-
ing evidence associated with various negative consequences indicates that excessive 
internet use can be problematic for some individuals. 
6,7 The psychological consequences 
involve the following: obsession for the internet or internet gaming; imbalance of 
real-life relationships, sleep, work, and education; 
8-15 increased aggression, hostility, 
and stress; 
8,16,17 problems with verbal memory and attention; 
8,17,18 maladaptive coping 
strategies; 
8,19,20 and low wellbeing and high loneliness. 
21 In addition, psychosomatic </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 
20 May 2014 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>818 </p>

<p>Mok et al </p>

<p>and neuro-anatomic studies on internet addiction have been 
accumulated to widen the understanding of the possible rela-
tionship between brain alteration and internet addiction. </p>

<p>8,22 </p>

<p>Although discrepancies in measurements, as well as the 
different cutoff points, reliability problems of self-reporting 
formats, and culturally limited studies, make some research-
ers still cast doubt on diagnosis of internet addiction, the dis-
order is now considered as one of the behavior addictions. </p>

<p>23,24 </p>

<p>Indeed, in May 2013, internet addiction was included in an 
appendix of the newly updated version of the Diagnostic 
and Statistical Manual for Mental Disorders (DSM-5) as 
a new term, "internet Gaming Disorder." This would indi-
cate the fact that the American Psychiatric Association has 
officially approved internet gaming disorder as a condition 
that requires consideration of clinicians and researchers, 
like other behavioral addictions. 
25 Furthermore, as develop-
ment of internet-based smart-mobile devices increases, the 
significance of this research is likely to increase. </p>

<p>smartphone addiction </p>

<p>With abundant applications, smartphones provide users with 
internet-based communication, business trading, education, 
entertainment media, and even clinical applications. Given 
their variety of functions and ease of use, the number of esti-
mated global users was more than 1.08 billion in early 2012, 
and it is increasing with great speed. However, smartphones 
can be problematic when used excessively. For example, 
excessive smartphone use can cause maladaptive behavioral 
difficulties seen in impulse control disorders in general or 
pathological gambling; it can interfere with school or work, </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>decrease real-life social interaction, decrease academic 
ability, cause relationship problems, 
27 and cause physical 
health-related problems including blurred vision and pain 
in the wrists or the back of the neck. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>Most behaviors performed under conscious control are 
selected to fulfil one's social, functional, and psychological 
needs. Therefore, when a behavior brings a satisfaction to 
an individual, it is actively continued and habituated. In 
this sense, it is difficult to simply class habitual smartphone 
usage as an addiction-like behavior. However, according to 
previous studies, 
29,30 problematic smartphone use could be 
included in the behavior addiction category when the follow-
ing components of addiction are taken into consideration: 
1) the individual is preoccupied with a specific behavior (smart-
phone use); 2) the behavior is used in order to escape reality or 
create a feeling of euphoria; 3) as the behavior is continued, 
tolerance develops; 4) when the behavior is abstained or 
interfered with, withdrawal symptoms occur (feeling anxious, </p>

<p>depressed, or irritable); 5) as a consequence of the continuous 
behavior, interpersonal problems occur; and 6) individual 
experiences relapse against one's will. Previous studies have 
indeed found that smartphones are addictive for users and are 
closely attached to their lives. A Taiwanese study of 10,191 
adolescents reported that 30% of participants exhibited tol-
erance, 36% exhibited withdrawal, 27% exhibited use that 
was heavier than intended, 18% made unsuccessful attempts 
to reduce, and 10% experienced functional impairment of 
close relationships. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>It is true that many authorities carefully acknowledge that 
there certainly is a risk of addiction due to the excessive use 
or misuse of a smartphone. However, because of the limited 
findings, which lack a validated standard, nothing about smart-
phone addiction or the characteristics of problematic users has 
yet been clearly concluded. Meanwhile, a main feature of the 
smartphone is the operation of internet-based applications; 
thus, smartphone use must share many functional or psycho-
logical properties with internet use. Therefore, based on the 
possible relationship, investigating smartphone addiction in 
relation to internet addiction by integrative study would be 
reasonable. </p>

<p>Objectives </p>

<p>Although some clinicians have intuitively demonstrated the 
association between internet and smartphone addiction, little 
research has been performed. Considering the current lack of 
reliable diagnostic indicators and validated cutoff standards 
for internet and smartphone addiction, this present study 
will contribute to the literature by specifically exploring the 
relationship between internet and smartphone addiction and 
the unique characteristics of addictive users. 
In this study, we firstly categorized internet and smartphone 
users into groups based on their addiction severities. Cross-
sectional comparisons of the profiles were then performed on 
psychological traits of each group. Moreover, before the main 
analysis, we empirically confirmed the existence of a difference 
between male and female internet and smartphone addiction 
levels. Female participants were more prone to smartphone 
addiction, and male participants exhibited highly addictive 
patterns toward both the internetand internet gaming. There-
fore, we decided to analyze the data separately for each sex to 
eliminate systematic effects from the results. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Participants </p>

<p>A total of 463 Korean college students from Seoul (n=78, 
16.9%), Sungnam (n=154, 33.3%), Nonsan (n=76, 16.4%), </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>819 </p>

<p>internet and smartphone addiction </p>

<p>and Daejeon (n=155, 33.5%) participated in the study. Data 
from 15 participants were excluded because more than 
50% of the values were missing. All participants who met 
the inclusion criteria for internet and smartphone use were 
retained for the analyses. </p>

<p>Procedures </p>

<p>Ethical approval was obtained from the Institutional Review 
Board of Eulji University Hospital prior to data collection 
(reference 12-068). Detailed research and instruction pack-
ages were sent to four universities in Korea. This package 
requested the allocation of 60-70 minutes of in-class testing 
time to complete the questionnaires. Written informed con-
sent was attained from all participants prior to participation. 
Participants were informed that they were not obliged to 
participate, that all responses were anonymous, and that they 
were free to refuse to answer any questions. </p>

<p>Measurements </p>

<p>Respondents completed a number of validated screening 
tools for demographic information (age, academic year, 
and sex), internet addiction, smartphone addiction, mood, 
anxiety, and personality. All questionnaires were in the self-
report format. </p>

<p>internet addiction </p>

<p>Young's Internet Addiction Test (IAT) 
1 has been widely used 
to screen for internet addiction. The IAT contains 20 items and 
assesses productivity (work, school, or home), social behaviors, 
emotional connection, and general patterns of internet use. The 
items are rated on a 5-point scale (1= very rarely and 5= very 
frequently) and produce an overall score of between 20 and 100. 
The Cronbach's alpha coefficient for the IAT is 0.94. </p>

<p>smartphone addiction </p>

<p>The Smartphone Addiction Scale (SAS) 
28 contains six 
subscales of problematic smartphone usage (daily-life-
disturbance, positive-anticipation, withdrawal, overuse, 
tolerance, and cyberspace-oriented relationship). The SAS 
also yields a total score that is indicative of the severity of 
smartphone addiction; higher scores indicate more severe 
addictions. The SAS has 33 items that rate on 6-point 
scales from 1 (strongly disagree) to 6 (strongly agree). The 
Cronbach's alpha coefficient for the SAS is 0.967. </p>

<p>Depression </p>

<p>Beck's Depression Inventory (BDI)-I 
32 is composed of 
21 items that evaluate the degree of depression. Each question </p>

<p>inquires about the respondent's particular symptoms and 
changes in mood over the past week, with a 4-point scale. 
The severity of depression is indicated by the total score. The 
Cronbach's alpha coefficient of the BDI-I is 0.91, and that 
of the Korean version of the BDI-I is 0.85. </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>anxiety </p>

<p>The State-Trait Anxiety Inventory, Trait Version (STAI-T) </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>is a validated self-report measure with 20 items that are rated 
from 1 (not at all) to 4 (very much). The STAI-T is one of the 
most widely used tools for examining individual differences 
in anxiety personality traits. Various studies of the STAI-T 
have confirmed that it is an appropriate and adequate mea-
sure for studying anxiety in research and clinical settings. </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>The internal consistency coefficient of the Korean version 
of STAI-T is 0.88. </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>Personality </p>

<p>The Eysenck Personality Questionnaire (EPQ) 
37 measures 
individuals' personalities across four dimensions: psychoti-
cism, extroversion-introversion, neuroticism/anxiety, and 
social desirability (a Lie scale). The original English ver-
sion contains 90 items; however, the Korean version has 
79 items because some irrelevant items were removed. 
38 Of 
these 79 items, the psychoticism scale contains 15 items, 
the extroversion scale contains 20 items (two with reversed 
answers), the neuroticism scale contains 24 items, and the Lie 
scale is measured with 20 items (15 with reversed answers). 
The EPQ questions elicit dichotomous responses (yes or no). 
The Cronbach's alpha coefficients that have been reported 
for the four scales are as follows: psychoticism, 0.82-0.95; 
extraversion, 0.98-1.00; neuroticism, 0.82-0.95; and Lie 
scale, 0.97-0.99. </p>

<p>Data analyses </p>

<p>Data analyses were performed in the following phases: 
1) descriptive analysis (means, standard deviations, and 
proportions) was performed to examine the distributions of 
the variables; 2) latent class analysis (LCA), ie, subgrouping 
based on internet and smartphone addiction; and 3) analysis 
of variance (ANOVA) and post hoc tests of latent classes. </p>

<p>lca </p>

<p>Because the goal of this research was to identify subgroups 
of individuals who use both a smartphone and the internet, 
we employed LCA by using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">Latent Gold</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">4.5</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Statistical Innovations Inc., Bermont, MA, USA</rs>) software. 
39 Unlike 
correlation studies that include parameters only describing </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>820 </p>

<p>Mok et al </p>

<p>relationships among observed variables, latent analysis models 
can be used to find latent and homogeneous populations and 
meaningful groups of profiles. 
40,41 Because LCA assesses 
individual probabilities and makes decisions regarding the 
best-fitting latent classes, class memberships are mutually 
exclusive, and individuals within a class are homogeneous. 
Identifying the model with the optimal number of latent 
classes is a critical step for the whole analysis. In this study, 
models with one to six class solutions were considered, and 
the overall fits produced by these models were compared. 
Model fits were examined using the Bayesian information 
criterion (BIC), Bozdogan's criterion (consistent Akaike's 
information criterion [CAIC]), and Akaike's information 
criterion (AIC). Because the BIC provides a relatively quali-
fied measure of overall model fit, it was our primary measure 
for comparing classes. 
42 Lower BIC and CAIC values indi-
cate better model fits. However, it is also important that the 
extracted LCA solution produces logically meaningful and 
distinctive patterns. </p>

<p>cross-class comparison </p>

<p>After the best model was selected, psychosocial factors were 
compared across the classified subgroups. The comparisons 
were performed with nonparametric statistics, χ²-tests (for cat-
egorical variables), and ANOVAs (for continuous variables). 
When the tests produced significant differences, post hoc 
analyses with Bonferroni tests were used to examine these 
differences. The level of significance was set to α=0.05, and 
the <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">IBM Corporation, Armonk, NY, USA</rs>) <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 18.0</rs> statistical software package was used. </p>

<p>Results 
Descriptive statistics (Phase 1) </p>

<p>After an initial examination of the data, 448 college students 
were included (male =178, 39.7%; female =270, 60.3%). 
The age distributions of each sex were similar (male, 
mean [M] =21.80, standard deviation [SD] =3.39; female, 
M =20.38, SD =2.45). The participants were equally sampled 
from in terms of academic grade level (first year =27%, 
second year =18%, third year =32%, fourth year =21.4%). 
As observed in Table 1, most of the variables were sig-
nificantly different between each sex, with the exception 
of a couple of personality factors (psychoticism and 
extroversion). The female participants were more depressed 
and insecure than the males. Regarding internet usage, 
the male participants were more addicted than the female 
participants, and this pattern was reversed for smartphone 
usage. </p>

<p>Determination of the number 
of latent classes (Phase 2) </p>

<p>The first step in determining the best-fitting model was to 
compare model fits based on log likelihood-based estimates 
(the BIC, CAIC, and other likelihood ratio values) and logi-
cal interpretabilities. Tables 2 and 3 show the selected model 
parameters for the three-class model and the competing mod-
els for the female and male samples. The three-class model 
had the lowest BIC and CAIC. However, the low AIC differ-
ence value shown in Table 3 indicates that the three-and four-
class models were similar in terms of approximating abilities. 
Although the three-and four-class models both seemed to fit 
the data, we selected the model with fewer classes for reasons 
of effectiveness. Thus, we extracted three-class models for 
both the female and male samples for comparisons. </p>

<p>latent class characteristics </p>

<p>For the three-class LCA models, Figure 1 shows the dis-
tinguishable patterns of internet and smartphone addic-
tion between the male and female samples in terms of 
conditional solution probabilities. A solution probability </p>

<p>Table 1 Means and standard deviations of the variables between 
sexes </p>

<p>Variable 
Mean (SD) 
P-value 
F </p>

<p>Male 
(n=178) </p>

<p>Female 
(n=270) </p>

<p>Depression 
15.58 (10.75) 19.58 (13.40) 0.001 
11.127 
anxiety 
41.60 (9.68) 
45.69 (9.42) 
,0.0001 19.780 
internet addiction 35.65 (11.72) 32.91 (10.58) 0.011 
6.588 
smartphone 
addiction </p>

<p>59.65 (21.08) 74.67 (25.50) ,0.0001 42.408 </p>

<p>Personality 
Psychoticism 
2.94 (2.57) 
2.97 (1.49) 
0.875 
0.025 
extroversion 
10.90 (4.20) 
10.49 (3.81) 
0.290 
1.124 
Neuroticism 
12.19 (5.33) 
15.53 (4.64) 
,0.0001 49.527 
social 
desirability (lie) </p>

<p>2.44 (1.31) 
2.08 (1.24) 
0.003 
8.771 </p>

<p>Abbreviation: sD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Table 2 Indicators of fit for models (log likelihood based) in male 
sample </p>

<p>Class 
BIC 
AIC 
CAIC </p>

<p>1 
2970.5638 
2954.6549 
2975.5638 
2 
2925.6651 
2893.8473 
2935.6651 
3 
2916.363 
2868.6362 
2931.363 
4 
2932.5235 
2868.8878 
2952.5235 
5 
2951.5571 
2872.0125 
2976.5571 
6 
2968.2831 
2872.8296 
2998.2831 </p>

<p>Note: Boldface indicates values of selected model. 
Abbreviations: aic, akaike information criterion; Bic, Bayesian information 
criterion; caic, consistent akaike information criterion. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>821 </p>

<p>internet and smartphone addiction </p>

<p>close to 1 indicates a high likelihood of scoring high on 
the respective scale. 
In the male group, latent class 1 (LC1; 24% of the entire 
male sample, n=47, low internet addiction, low smartphone 
addiction) exhibited low risks of internet and smart-
phone addiction, as demonstrated by the low probabilities 
(0.08 and 0.07, respectively). Thus, this class was the group 
with the lowest addiction-related risks. 
Latent class 2 (LC2; 50% of the entire male sample, 
n=95, moderate internet addiction, moderate smartphone 
addiction) contained individuals who seemed to take 
advantage of both the internet and smartphone in many 
ways in their everyday lives. However, their patterns of 
internet and smartphone use exhibited mild-to-moderate </p>

<p>levels of addiction risk (the internet addiction risk of this 
class was slightly higher than that of the female LC1, and 
the smartphone addiction risk of this class was roughly half 
that of the female LC1). The probabilities of internet and 
smartphone addiction for this class were 0.25 and 0.22, 
respectively. 
Latent class 3 (LC3; 26% of the entire male sample, 
n=36, high internet addiction, high smartphone addiction) 
represented the subgroup of male students with the highest 
risk level for internet addiction (including the female classes). 
The likelihood rates of internet and smartphone addiction 
were 0.48 and 0.38, respectively. Therefore, this subgroup 
represented the class with the greatest potential for addiction 
in the male sample. 
In contrast, the members of female LC1 (27.9% of the 
entire female sample, n=83, low internet addiction/low 
smartphone addiction) were the least likely to be addicted 
to the internet (0.07) or smartphone (0.22) among the entire 
sample. Based on this pattern, this class represented the 
female group with minimal risks of addiction to the internet 
and smartphone. 
LC2 (54.8% of the entire female sample, n=154, low 
internet addiction/high smartphone addiction) was a sub-
group of female students who exhibited a low likelihood 
(0.18) of internet addiction and a relatively high likelihood </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>internet </p>

<p>Solution probability </p>

<p>Solution probability </p>

<p>Class 1 
Class 2 
Class 3 </p>

<p>Smartphone </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>internet </p>

<p>Class 1 
Class 2 
Class 3 </p>

<p>Smartphone </p>

<p>3-class profile of 
female sample 
(n=270) </p>

<p>3-class profile of 
male sample 
(n=178) </p>

<p>Figure 1 latent class model in male and female samples. </p>

<p>Table 3 Indicators of fit for models (log likelihood based) in 
female sample </p>

<p>Class 
BIC 
AIC 
CAIC </p>

<p>1 
4569.1972 
4551.2051 
4574.1972 
2 
4492.1404 
4456.1562 
4502.1404 
3 
4486.3599 
4432.3836 
4501.3599 
4 
4493.1058 
4421.1374 
4513.1058 
5 
4495.0191 
4405.0586 
4520.0191 
6 
4511.9313 
4403.9786 
4541.9313 </p>

<p>Notes: Boldface indicates values of selected model. 
Abbreviations: aic, akaike information criterion; Bic, Bayesian information 
criterion; caic, consistent akaike information criterion. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>822 </p>

<p>Mok et al </p>

<p>(0.46) of smartphone addiction. Although all classes exhib-
ited a tendency to have a higher probability of smartphone 
addiction than internet addiction, this tendency was radically 
increased in class 2 (ie, smartphone addiction was more than 
twice as prevalent as internet addiction). In summary, this 
class appeared to represent a unique subgroup of females 
with a high risk of smartphone addiction and a low risk of 
internet addiction. 
LC3 (17.3% of the entire female sample, n=33, high inter-
net addiction/high smartphone addiction) members tended 
to seriously indulge in both internet and smartphone use. 
Hence, the probabilities of internet (0.40) and smartphone 
addiction (0.50) in this class were greater than those in the 
other classes. Furthermore, the probability of smartphone 
addiction in this class was the greatest of all classes (including 
those of the male sample). This class represented a typical 
group of people with low behavioral control. </p>

<p>cross-class comparisons (Phase 3) </p>

<p>smartphone addiction </p>

<p>As mentioned earlier, the females exhibited a higher aver-
age level of smartphone addiction than did the males (male, 
M =59.68, SD =21.08; female, M =74.67, SD =25.50) 
(Table 1). To examine differences in characteristics across 
classes, ANOVAs were conducted on the total scores of 
the SAS and its six sub-factors; the results are illustrated 
in Table 4. Significant overall differences in the SAS total 
scores and the scores on the six sub-factors were confirmed 
across classes in both sexes. These findings indicate that 
the classes within each sex exhibited distinct patterns 
of smartphone addiction levels and that the classes were 
correctly clustered according to the specific features of 
smartphone addiction. 
In post hoc analyses, LC1 scored significantly lower 
than any other subgroup within the female group on total 
smartphone addiction and smartphone-related problems 
across the six dimensions (all P,0.001). Members of LC3 
exhibited the most seriously problematic smartphone use; 
however, LC3 and LC2 were not significantly different 
in smartphone addiction levels. Therefore, in contrast to 
LC1, LC2 and LC3 exhibited similar levels of smartphone 
addiction (LC2. LC1). 
In contrast, in the male sample, three discrete classes 
were identified from post hoc analyses. LC1 exhibited the 
lowest level of smartphone-related problems and the lowest 
total SAS scores (all P,0.001). Additionally, LC2 exhibited 
SAS scores that were significantly higher than those of LC1 
and significantly lower than those of LC3 (all P,0.01). Thus, </p>

<p>the smartphone problem severity levels were as follows: LC3 
had the most serious problems, LC2 exhibited a medium level 
of problems, and LC1 exhibited the lowest level of problems 
(ie, LC3. LC2. LC1). </p>

<p>internet addiction </p>

<p>In contrast to the smartphone addiction pattern, the aver-
age internet addiction test score of the male participants 
was significantly higher than that of the females (male, 
M =35.65, SD =11.72; female, M =32.91, SD =10.58) 
(Table 1). 
An overall F-test revealed that internet addiction 
levels were significantly different across the three latent 
classes of both the female and male groups (all P,0.001) 
(Table 4). Additionally, Bonferroni multiple comparison 
tests indicated that the female LC3 exhibited the greatest 
level of internet addiction within the sample. LC2 followed 
LC3, and LC1 exhibited the lowest level of internet addic-
tion (ie, LC3. LC2. LC1). A similar pattern of internet 
addiction severity was observed in the male sample; LC3 
exhibited the greatest addiction severity, followed by LC2, 
and LC1 exhibited the lowest level of addiction severity 
(ie, LC3. LC2. LC1). With the exception that the grand 
mean trends of the sexes were different, the general pat-
tern of internet addiction was similar to that of smartphone 
addiction. </p>

<p>Depression </p>

<p>ANOVA and post hoc analyses were performed on the total 
BDI-I scores. A difference was found between the sexes: 
the female sample was significantly more depressed than 
the male sample (F=11.127, P=0.001) (Table 1). More-
over, as observed in Table 4, all participants reported that 
they had been slightly depressed during the last week. All 
male classes reported mild levels of depression, and the 
females reported more moderate levels of depression, 
especially the LC3 group (M =23.5, SD =15.3). How-
ever, significant differences between the latent classes 
were not found (all P.0.1) (Table 4). The severities of 
internet and smartphone addiction were not factors that 
had significant influence on differentiating levels of 
depressive feelings. </p>

<p>anxiety </p>

<p>Overall F-test and post hoc analyses revealed that both 
sexes showed significant differences across latent classes 
(all P,0.001). These findings illustrate that each class had a 
firmly independent anxiety level relationship (Table 1). </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>823 </p>

<p>internet and smartphone addiction </p>

<p>Table 4 analysis of cross-class comparison between sexes </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>Male (n=178) </p>

<p>Female (n=270) </p>

<p>Mean (SD) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>Post hoc </p>

<p>Mean (SD) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>Post hoc </p>

<p>LC1 </p>

<p>LC2 </p>

<p>LC3 </p>

<p>LC1 </p>

<p>LC2 </p>

<p>LC3 </p>

<p>smartphone addiction </p>

<p>41.34 (5.84) </p>

<p>59.39 (13.61) </p>

<p>84.39 (25.0) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>80.95 </p>

<p>1,2,3 
54.41 (10.79) </p>

<p>83.49 (24.76) </p>

<p>84.48 (26.42) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>52.29 </p>

<p>1,2≒3 </p>

<p>sas sub-factor 
Daily-life disturbance </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.5 (0.6) </p>

<p>2.3 (1.0) </p>

<p>3.0 (0.9) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>32.31 </p>

<p>1,2,3 </p>

<p>2.3 (0.8) </p>

<p>3.2 (1.1) </p>

<p>3.3 (1.2) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>26.88 </p>

<p>1,2≒3 </p>

<p>Positive anticipation </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.1 (0.2) </p>

<p>1.4 (0.4) </p>

<p>2.3 (1.0) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>46.18 </p>

<p>1,2,3 </p>

<p>1.3 (0.4) </p>

<p>2.1 (1.0) </p>

<p>2.1 (0.9) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>24.00 </p>

<p>1,3≒2 </p>

<p>Withdrawal </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>1.2 (0.3) </p>

<p>1.7 (0.6) </p>

<p>2.7 (1.0) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>48.35 </p>

<p>1,2,3 </p>

<p>1.5 (0.6) </p>

<p>2.6 (1.1) </p>

<p>2.6 (1.0) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>40.05 </p>

<p>1,3≒2 </p>

<p>cyber relationship </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>1.2 (0.4) </p>

<p>1.5 (0.5) </p>

<p>2.2 (0.7) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>37.49 </p>

<p>1,2,3 </p>

<p>1.5 (0.5) </p>

<p>2.0 (0.7) </p>

<p>2.2 (1.0) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>17.59 </p>

<p>1,2≒3 </p>

<p>Overuse </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>1.5 (0.6) </p>

<p>2.7 (0.9) </p>

<p>3.5 (1.2) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>52.30 </p>

<p>1,2,3 </p>

<p>2.3 (0.8) </p>

<p>3.7 (1.2) </p>

<p>3.6 (1.2) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>45.02 </p>

<p>1,3≒2 </p>

<p>Tolerance </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>1.1 (0.2) </p>

<p>1.5 (0.7) </p>

<p>2.0 (0.8) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>20.30 </p>

<p>1,2,3 </p>

<p>1.3 (0.5) </p>

<p>2.1 (1.0) </p>

<p>2.0 (1.0) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>21.95 </p>

<p>1,3≒2 </p>

<p>internet addiction </p>

<p>24.49 (2.73) </p>

<p>35.11 (6.83) </p>

<p>51.67 (11.31) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>143.77 </p>

<p>1,2,3 </p>

<p>24.5 (2.4) </p>

<p>32.9 (6.2) </p>

<p>54.3 (9.4) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>307.71 </p>

<p>1,2,3 </p>

<p>level of depression </p>

<p>14.8 (9.7) </p>

<p>16.1 (113) </p>

<p>15.2 (10.7) </p>

<p>0.760 </p>

<p>0.275 </p>

<p>18.4 (12.7) </p>

<p>19.4 (13.3) </p>

<p>23.5 (15.3) </p>

<p>0.178 </p>

<p>1.74 </p>

<p>level of anxiety </p>

<p>35.1 (7.0) </p>

<p>42.5 (9.4) </p>

<p>47.7 (8.7) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>22.55 </p>

<p>1,2,3 </p>

<p>42.9 (9.0) </p>

<p>46.3 (9.3) </p>

<p>49.8 (9.4) </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>7.51 </p>

<p>1,2≒3 </p>

<p>Personality 
Psychoticism </p>

<p>2.3 (1.9) </p>

<p>3.2 (3.1) </p>

<p>3.1 (1.6) </p>

<p>0.126 </p>

<p>2.09 </p>

<p>2.6 (1.2) </p>

<p>3.0 (1.4) </p>

<p>3.9 (2.1) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>10.22 </p>

<p>1,2,3 </p>

<p>extroversion </p>

<p>11.3 (3.9) </p>

<p>10.8 (4.2) </p>

<p>10.7 (4.7) </p>

<p>0.703 </p>

<p>0.353 </p>

<p>11.3 (3.4) </p>

<p>10.2 (3.9) </p>

<p>10.1 (4.3) </p>

<p>0.091 </p>

<p>2.42 </p>

<p>Neuroticism </p>

<p>8.3 (4.2) </p>

<p>13.0 (5.0) </p>

<p>15.1 (4.7) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>24.13 </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>14.0 (4.8) </p>

<p>16.0 (4.4) </p>

<p>17.3 (4.4) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>8.38 </p>

<p>1,2≒3 </p>

<p>social desirability (lie) </p>

<p>3.0 (1.3) </p>

<p>2.3 (1.2) </p>

<p>2.0 (1.3) </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>7.82 </p>

<p>2,1 </p>

<p>2.4 (1.2) </p>

<p>2.0 (1.3) </p>

<p>1.7 (0.9) </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>5.70 </p>

<p>3≒2,1 </p>

<p>Notes: sas sub-factors indicate six dimensions of smartphone-related problems. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>"Daily-life disturbance" includes interference with daily life (eg, missing work, physical pain, or problems); </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>"positive anticipation" is positive feelings related </p>

<p>to using a smartphone or negative feelings when not using a smartphone; </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>"withdrawal" involves not coping with being without a smartphone, constantly using a smartphone, and becoming easily irritated when smartphone use is interfered </p>

<p>with; </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>"cyberspace-oriented relationship" is having more intimate relationships through smartphone than in real life; </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>"overuse" refers to uncontrollable use of a smartphone and constantly feeling the urge to use a smartphone; </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>"tolerance" </p>

<p>is continuous failure to control smartphone use (ie, lack of willpower). Significant differences of Bonferroni multiple comparisons between latent classes (P,0.05) are denoted by the same class number in each row. 
Abbreviations: lc, latent class; sas, smartphone addiction scale; sD, standard deviation </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>824 </p>

<p>Mok et al </p>

<p>Although the total mean STAI-T score was meaningfully 
higher in the female group (M =45.7, SD =9.4) than in 
the male group (M =41.6, SD =9.7) (F=19.78, P,0.001), 
the trends of the two groups were similar; ie, more severe 
internet and smartphone problems were accompanied by 
higher levels of anxiety (all P,0.01; LC3. LC2. LC1). 
A similar pattern was confirmed in the female group. 
Therefore, LC1 exhibited the lowest anxiety levels (all 
P,0.01), and the anxiety levels of LC2 were greater 
than those of LC1 (P,0.01) and lower than those of LC3 
(P,0.05) (LC3. LC2. LC1). No group's anxiety level 
exceeded the normal range (Table 4). </p>

<p>Personality </p>

<p>Significant differences between the sexes were found in 
the personality factors of the EPQ. Females (M =15.53, 
SD =4.64) were more neurotic than males (M =12.19, 
SD =5.33) (F=49.53, P,0.001), and males wanted to display 
socially desirable aspects of themselves to a greater degree 
than did females (male, M =2.44, SD =1.31; female, M =2.08, 
SD =1.24) (F=8.77, P,0.01) (Table 1). 
Moreover, a comparison of the latent classes revealed 
some differences. Specifically, the female group exhibited sig-
nificant differences on the psychoticism (F=10.22, P,0.001), 
neuroticism (F=8.38, P,0.001), and social desirability (Lie) 
scales (F=5.698, P,0.01), and the difference in the extrover-
sion scale was marginal (F=2.42, P=0.091). The male groups 
exhibited differences in the neuroticism (F=24.13, P,0.001) 
and social desirability scales (F=7.82, P=0.001). 
Post hoc analyses indicated that the females in LC3 
exhibited psychoticism and neuroticism scores that were 
greater than those of LC1 (all P,0.001). Conversely, on 
the Lie scale, which indicates social desirability, LC1 was 
more socially desirable than were any of the other classes 
(all P,0.05). Regarding the male group, LC3 scored higher 
in neuroticism than LC2 or LC1 (P,0.05), and LC1 was 
the least neurotic (P,0.001). In contrast, the social desir-
ability pattern of the males was similar to that of the females 
(P,0.01) (Table 4). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The concept of "internet addiction" or "smartphone addic-
tion" could be unfamiliar to some researchers. In South-East 
Asian countries, however, the adverse impact of internet or 
smartphone addiction has been taken seriously and has led 
to a series of studies and social work by the government and 
health care givers to curb and alleviate the problem. A recent 
study by the Korean Ministry of Gender Equality and Family </p>

<p>in 2013 reported that of the 1.63 million Korean adolescents, 
17.9% comprised those with smartphone addiction. 
43 More-
over, over 24% of children diagnosed with internet addiction 
are hospitalized. 
44 A very similar trend is found in Japan. 
A study by the Japanese Ministry of Education has led to 
the recognition of the necessity for a government-managed 
system. 
45 Likewise, some specialized treatment centers and 
care-giving programs have been established in Europe (the 
outpatient clinic for behavior addictions in Mainz, Germany, 
and the Capio Nightingale Hospital in London, UK) and 
the USA (the inpatient centers RESTART internet addic-
tion recovery program in Seattle, and digital detoxification 
and recovery center in Pennsylvania, USA). 
46 It implies that 
internet and smartphone addiction presents a significant 
global challenge. 
The present study examined the relationship between 
internet and smartphone addiction with LCA, by subgroup-
ing users based on their levels of usage and the severities 
of addiction-related problems. It has been noted that most 
researchers in this field tend to rely on correlation studies when 
reporting internet use and other psychological factors; how-
ever, the corresponding effect sizes are considerably small. </p>

<p>47,48 </p>

<p>Hence, it was necessary to treat measurements in a manner that 
allowed the more complex relationship between internet and 
smartphone addictions to be captured. Additionally, because 
concepts of these behavioral addictions were not clearly 
defined, the adoption of a latent profile model was necessary 
to comprehensively observe the relationship. 
Moreover, to examine differences between the sexes in 
various personality traits, we separated the sample by sex 
prior to LCA. As expected, the initial analysis revealed that 
females were more vulnerable to smartphone addiction than 
internet addiction and that males exhibited the opposite 
pattern. Although some controversy remains, recent studies 
of smartphone addiction and low self-controllability 
49 and 
problematic mobile phone use 
50,51 have produced outcomes 
that are convergent with this study. However, conflicting 
results regarding differences between the sexes in internet 
use have also been reported. 
52-54 According to previous stud-
ies, male-female differences in internet addiction are due 
to differences in usage patterns, motivations, or purposes. 
For example, social use is significantly more important for 
females than it is for males, and leisure or interest-oriented 
use is more salient for males than it is for females. </p>

<p>47,54-56 </p>

<p>Although the literature has not reached a clear agreement, 
the findings of this study suggest that sex may influence 
examinations of the relationship between internet and 
smartphone addictions. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>825 </p>

<p>internet and smartphone addiction </p>

<p>In summary, based on examination of multiple models, we 
concluded that the three-class model was the most effective 
and informative in terms of elucidating the unique charac-
teristics of each sex group. The pattern of addiction severity 
and related problems for the latent classes of both sexes was 
characterized by increasing severity from LC1 to LC3. This 
result is very comparable to a project study performed by 
the Korean National Information Society Agency in 2011. 
The study found that both adult and adolescent smartphone 
users could be divided into three different groups based on 
addiction proneness levels. Among adolescents, 2.2% identi-
fied as belonging to the high-risk group, and 9.3% were in 
the low-medium-risk group. In adults, 1% of the users were 
in the high-risk group, and 6.7% were in the low-medium 
risk group. </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>Furthermore, multiple cross-comparison results revealed 
a trend that was common to both sexes: anxiety levels and 
neurotic personality traits increased with addiction severity 
levels. However, the scores on the Lie dimension of the 
EPQ, which is an indication of social desirability level, were 
inversely related to the severity levels of the latent classes. 
For the females only, more severely addicted people exhib-
ited more psychotic personality traits in the EPQ. 
The present findings on personality are highly consistent 
with previous studies. A study on internet addiction among 
Chinese adolescents reported that the internet-addicted 
group scored higher in the neuroticism and psychoticism 
dimensions and lower in the Lie dimension than the control 
group. 
58 Similarly, internet addiction has been found to 
strongly positively correlate with neuroticism and negatively 
correlate with social desirability (Lie). 
59 Additionally, a study 
demonstrated that typical internet addicts exhibit anxiousness 
and problems with social contact. </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>These findings are corroborated by the results of our 
study. It is well known that the neuroticism dimension encom-
passes moodiness and vulnerability to emotional stimuli, </p>

<p>61 </p>

<p>and these traits are similar to those of anxiety. Therefore, 
the observed positive relationships of neuroticism and 
anxiety with addiction severity are relevant. Furthermore, 
psychoticism is strongly associated with aggressiveness, 
socially unacceptable behavior, 
62-64 sensation-seeking, </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>and low impulse control. 
66 As mentioned previously, the 
core features of behavioral addiction include the follow-
ing: 1) continued engagement in a behavior despite adverse 
consequences; 2) diminished control over participation in 
the behavior; 3) compulsive participation; and 4) craving 
or appetitive urges that immediately precede engagement 
in the behavior. 
67,68 Therefore, the pattern of psychoticism </p>

<p>observed in the female participants can be interpreted with 
the sensation-seeking behavior and impaired abilities to 
control smartphone usage. Eysenck and Eysenck 
37 reported 
that people who score high on the Lie scale tend to score 
low on psychoticism and extraversion. A negative relation-
ship between the Lie dimension and sensation-seeking has 
also been reported. 
65 Furthermore, Montag et al 
59 found a 
significant negative correlation between internet addiction 
and the Lie dimension. 
Similarly to a previous study, 
69 we observed a significant 
correlation between internet and smartphone use in both sexes 
(male, r=0.36, P,0.001; female, r=0.206, P=0.001); the 
implications of the abovementioned studies can be employed 
to interpret this study. Because Cao and Su 
58 interpreted the 
Lie dimension as being beneficial for behavioral develop-
ment, the Lie personality category can be identified as a cat-
egory of social desirability or social conformity. Hence, it can 
be assumed that the LC1 participants of both sexes had the 
greatest desires to be socially desirable and exhibited the least 
unstable and impulsive traits. Consequently, we suggest that, 
for the people in LC1, the beneficial influence of the social 
desirability trait might have suppressed the other problematic 
traits related to internet and smartphone addiction. Because 
internet and smartphone problems were inversely related to 
social desirability traits, this supposition may be relevant for 
explaining the differences among classes. 
Several limitations of this study should be considered. 
First, the participants were all college students who did not 
exhibit significant functional impairments. Hence, generaliz-
ing the results to a clinical setting could be difficult. However, 
because internet and smartphone addiction are a recently 
reported phenomenon and most users are young, this study 
reflects reality rather well. Additionally, given the paucity of 
valid research into smartphone-related problems, this study 
will provide information that will aid clinicians' understand-
ings of the characteristics of smartphone users and related 
problems. Comparisons of the results from clinical popula-
tions with those of the present study are also recommended. 
Second, it should be admitted that reported studies on 
internet or smartphone addiction are partially regionally 
limited, mainly in Asian countries. Accordingly, perceived 
importance of the issue has been overlooked in North 
American and European societies. However, as mentioned 
above, 
46 recently growing concerns from some European 
countries and the US disprove the argument of a "culturally 
limited phenomenon" of internet and smartphone addiction. 
This would reflect increasing need for specialized help on 
the problem. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Mok et al </p>

<p>Third, because the present study only measured severity 
and the problems caused by internet and smartphone addic-
tion, no additional information was provided to support the 
findings. Some studies have identified personality and internet 
usage motives, 
70 the influence of internet usage purpose on 
internet addiction, 
59 and the effect of stress on smartphone 
addiction 
49 to provide more valid explanations. Therefore, we 
suggest that further studies investigating and comparing latent 
classes should include information related to the number of 
hours of use, motives for use, and types of use (applications, 
games, or websites) to enhance clinical validity. 
Lastly, the use of supporting neurocognitive tests 
or neurobiological markers would increase the validity 
of the results. Nonetheless, all of the measures that we 
employed are widely used and are considered effective 
and appropriate for determining the relevant psychologi-
cal traits of individuals. Therefore, we suggest the use of 
neurological or biological evidence to enrich the results 
of future studies. 
Overall, this study considered novel and noteworthy phe-
nomena: internet and smartphone addictions. Little research 
has cast light on these issues, despite the increasing negative 
influence of these addictions on our lives. Therefore, the pres-
ent study, which sought to explore the relationship between 
internet and smartphone addiction and related psychosocial 
problems, would be worthy of notice. We identified three 
latent classes based on addiction severity and confirmed 
the distinctive traits of these classes. The present results are 
expected to contribute to expanding the behavioral addic-
tion field and to facilitate further research into its clinical 
implications. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Funding for this study was provided by a grant from the Korea 
Health Technology R&amp;D Project, Ministry of Health and 
Welfare, Republic of Korea (A120157). The funders had no 
role in the study design, collection, analysis or interpretation 
of data, writing of the manuscript, and the decision to submit 
the paper for publication. We thank the study participants 
who were willing to participate and complete the long 
questionnaire. We also thank Ji-Young Hwang for data 
collection and data analysis assistance. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>All the authors contributed to the design of the study. All 
authors contributed to development of the manuscript, 
revised it critically, and gave their approval of this version 
to be published. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/neuropsychiatric-disease-and-treatment-journal </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment is an international, peer-
reviewed journal of clinical therapeutics and pharmacology focusing 
on concise rapid reporting of clinical or pre-clinical studies on a 
range of neuropsychiatric and neurological disorders. This journal 
is indexed on PubMed Central, the 'PsycINFO' database and CAS. </p>

<p>The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Mok et al </p>

</text></tei>