<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4760300" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>In a phase IV trial, 84 patients (age 18-79) with acute myeloid leukemia (AML) in first complete remission (CR) 
received cycles of immunotherapy with histamine dihydrochloride (HDC) and low-dose human recombinant interleukin 
2 (IL-2) for 18 months to prevent leukemic relapse. During cycles, the treatment resulted in expansion of CD56 </p>

<p>bright </p>

<p>(CD3 
¡ /16 
¡ /56 
bright ) and CD16 
C (CD3 
¡ /16 
C /56 
C ) natural killer (NK) cells in the blood along with increased NK cell 
expression of the natural cytotoxicity receptors (NCRs) NKp30 and NKp46. Multivariate analyses correcting for age and 
risk group demonstrated that high CD56 
bright NK cell counts and high expression of NKp30 or NKp46 on CD16 
C NK cells 
independently predicted leukemia-free survival (LFS) and overall survival (OS). Our results suggest that the dynamics of 
NK cell subsets and their NCR expression may determine the efficiency of relapse-preventive immunotherapy in AML. </p>

<p>AML is characterized by the rapid accumulation of abnormal 
myeloid cells in the bone marrow and other organs. In the 
United States, AML is the most common form of acute leukemia 
in adults with 20,000 estimated new cases in 2015. 
1 The current 
therapy comprises induction chemotherapy aiming at reducing 
the burden of the leukemia to microscopically undetectable levels 
(CR) and consolidation chemotherapy aiming at eradicating 
residual malignant cells. Younger AML patients with high-risk 
disease may also be subjected to allogeneic stem cell transplanta-
tion, which is usually performed in the post-consolidation phase. 
Despite advances in AML therapy in recent decades, the 5-year 
survival rate is in the range of 25-40%, which is significantly 
explained by a high incidence of leukemic relapse. 
2-5 Novel ther-
apies, including strategies to prevent relapse in the post-chemo-
therapy phase, are highly warranted. 
Myeloid leukemic cells are frequently susceptible to the 
cytotoxicity of NK cells. The results of clinical studies imply 
that a deficient NK cell-mediated cytotoxicity and reduced 
NK cell counts in the blood are common in AML and that 
NK cell functions may determine the risk of relapse and sur-
vival. 
6-14 The claim that NK cell function is relevant to the </p>

<p>course of AML is further bolstered by reports of a low inci-
dence of relapse in allo-transplanted patients with donor/ 
recipient mismatches of killer immunoglobulin-like receptors 
(KIR) and HLA, whose leukemic cells are incapable of inhib-
iting alloreactive NK cells via KIR/HLA interactions </p>

<p>15,16   (reviewed in ref. 17). 
Human NK cells comprise two main cellular phenotypes that 
differ in function and in their expression of the cell surface markers 
CD16 and CD56. 
18 In healthy subjects, 90-95% of blood NK cells 
are CD16  C /56 
C (here referred to as CD16 
C NK cells) and 5-10% 
are CD16 
¡ /56 
bright cells (CD56 
bright NK cells). CD16 
C NK cells 
are cytotoxic to several histiotypes of malignant cells, including 
myeloid leukemic cells, whereas CD56 
bright NK cells are only 
weakly cytotoxic and are widely accepted to be precursors to the 
cytotoxic CD16 
C NK cells. 
19-22 NK cell cytotoxicity is regulated 
by activating and inhibitory NK cell receptors and their cognate 
ligands on leukemic cells. 
23-26 The main inhibitory receptors 
encompass the family of KIRs and the NKG2A -CD94 hetero-
dimer, whereas the main activating receptors comprise the NCRs 
(NKp46, NKp30, and NKp44) and NKG2D. </p>

<p>23-26 </p>

<p>The insufficiency of NK cells in AML and the purported 
prognostic role of NK cells have inspired the design of NK cell-
based immunotherapies, including the use of NK cell-activating </p>

<p>© Anna Martner, Anna Rydstr€ om, Rebecca E Riise, Johan Aurelius, Harald Anderson, Mats Brune, Robin Fo a, Kristoffer Hellstrand, and Fredrik B Thor en 
*Correspondence to: Kristoffer Hellstrand; Email: kristoffer.hellstrand@gu.se 
Submitted: 02/05/2015; Revised: 04/07/2015; Accepted: 04/10/2015 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/2162402X.2015.1041701 </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0/), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The 
moral rights of the named author(s) have been asserted. </p>

<p>www.tandfonline.com 
e1041701-1 
OncoImmunology </p>

<p>OncoImmunology 5:1, e1041701; January 2016; Published with license by Taylor &amp; Francis Group, LLC </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>cytokines and the adoptive transfer of NK cells, for relapse pre-
vention. 
13,27 In a phase III trial, immunotherapy with histamine 
dihydrochloride and low-dose interleukin-2 (HDC/IL-2) was 
shown to prevent relapse in patients with AML who had achieved 
CR and completed the phase of consolidation chemotherapy. </p>

<p>28   The IL-2 component of this regimen aims at promoting antitu-
mor functions of NK cells, whereas the HDC component aims at 
reducing the production of immunosuppressive reactive oxygen 
species (ROS) from malignant and non-malignant myeloid cells, 
and thus at rescuing NK cells from ROS-induced inactivation 
and apoptosis. 
29-32 In vitro and in vivo studies imply that NK 
cells are essential for the anti-neoplastic efficacy of HDC, used as 
a single agent or in conjunction with IL-2 
31,33,34 ; however, a sys-
tematic analysis of the immunomodulatory properties of treat-
ment with HDC/IL-2 within the framework of a clinical trial has 
not been carried out. 
Here we report the results of a phase IV trial (Re:Mission trial; 
NCT01347996) in patients with AML who received immuno-
therapy with HDC/IL-2 for relapse control. Our results suggest 
that subsets of NK cells and their NCR expression are induced 
during immunotherapy and that these aspects of NK cell biology 
herald favorable outcome in terms of relapse risk and survival. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Immunotherapy with HDC/IL-2 triggers accumulation 
of NK cell subsets in the blood 
AML patients in first CR received 10 consecutive 3-week 
cycles of HDC/IL-2 in the post-consolidation phase. Peripheral 
blood was collected before and after treatment cycles 1 and 3, </p>

<p>and analyzed for NK cell content and phenotype. The treatment 
schema is outlined in Fig. 1. Treatment with HDC/IL-2 induced 
a 3-fold increase in the absolute number of blood NK cells dur-
ing cycle 1. An increment of NK cell counts was observed in 46/ 
47 evaluable patients. The expanded NK cells comprised 
CD56 
bright and CD16 
C NK cells (Fig. 2, with gating strategies 
shown in Fig. S1). NK cell numbers in the blood declined 
between the end of treatment cycle 1 and the start of cycle 3. 
CD56 
bright cell counts typically returned to pre-treatment levels, 
whereas CD16 
C NK cell counts remained modestly elevated at 
the onset of cycle 3 as compared with levels at the onset of cycle 
1 (p &lt; 0.01, paired t-test; n D 46). A renewed accumulation of 
CD56 
bright and CD16 
C NK cells in the blood was observed dur-
ing treatment cycle 3 (Fig. 2). </p>

<p>Induction of NCR expression on NK cells 
During cycle 1 the median fluorescence intensity (MFI) of 
NKp30 and NKp46 expressed by CD16 
C NK cells increased by 
30% and 50%, respectively (Figs. 3B, D). The MFI of NCRs on 
CD16 
C NK cells increased during cycle 1 in 50/56 evaluable 
patients for NKp30 and in 43/56 patients for NKp46. For 
CD56 
bright cells, the results were discordant with a pronounced 
induction of NKp30 and no induction of NKp46 during cycle 1 
(Figs. 3A, C). As was observed for NK cell counts, the expression 
intensity of these NCRs declined during the resting period 
between cycles. However, for CD56 
bright cells the NKp30 expres-
sion remained significantly elevated at the onset of cycle 3 com-
pared with levels at the onset of cycle 1 and was significantly 
higher at the end of cycle 3 than at the end of cycle 1 (P &lt; 0.05, 
paired t-test; n D 42). The NKp30 expression on CD56 </p>

<p>bright </p>

<p>cells, as well as the NCR expression on CD16 
C NK cells, 
increased during cycle 3 to an extent 
similar to that recorded during cycle 1 
(Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Impact of NK cell counts and NCR 
expression on LFS and OS 
In analyses of the impact of NK cell 
markers on clinical outcome (reflected 
by leukemia-free survival, LFS, and 
overall survival, OS), patients were 
dichotomized at the median with 
respect to NK cell counts in the blood 
or NCR expression (MFI) on NK cells 
and analyzed for LFS and OS using the 
logrank test. Hazard ratios were deter-
mined by univariate Cox regression 
analyses and multivariate Cox analyses 
adjusted for age and risk groups. There 
was a strong correlation between relapse 
and death -one patient (59 years old) 
died without a preceding relapse (from 
myocardial infarction at 19 months 
after the onset of treatment) -emphasiz-
ing that relapse is a major risk factor for 
death for AML patients in CR. </p>

<p>35,36   Figure 1. Overview of the Re:Mission phase IV trial. AML patients in first complete remission (CR) were 
evaluated for eligibility after induction and consolidation chemotherapy. Eligible patients received 3-
week cycles of HDC/IL-2 over 18 months. Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) were collected 
before and after cycles 1 and 3. The protocol specified additional follow-up for 6 months after com-
pleting the last treatment cycle. </p>

<p>e1041701-2 
Volume 5 Issue 1 
OncoImmunology </p>

<p>At the onset of the first cycle of 
therapy, high counts of CD56 </p>

<p>bright </p>

<p>NK cells predicted LFS, which trans-
lated into an improved OS (Figs. 4A, 
B with multivariate analysis shown in 
Table 1). In contrast, CD16 
C NK cell 
blood counts at onset of cycle 1 did 
not influence outcome (Fig. 4C). 
Also, LFS and OS were not signifi-
cantly impacted by the magnitude of 
the increment of CD56 </p>

<p>bright </p>

<p>or 
CD16 
C NK cell counts during the 
first cycle of therapy (data not shown) 
or by the absolute counts of these NK 
cell populations on day 21 of cycle 1 
(Figs. 4D-F). 
A high (above median) expression 
of NKp46 on CD16 
C NK cells at the 
onset of cycle 1 was associated with a 
favorable outcome (Figs. 5A-C and 
Table 1). The magnitude of NCR 
induction during cycle 1 did not pre-
dict LFS or OS. However, patients 
with high NKp46 MFI on CD16 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>NK cells on day 21 of cycle 1 showed 
a favorable outcome (Fig. 5E, F and 
Table 1). A similar trend was observed 
for patients with high NKp30 expres-
sion before and after cycle 1 (Fig. 5D). 
There were also trends toward a favor-
able outcome in patients with high 
NKp30 and NKp46 expression on 
CD56 
bright NK cells (Fig. S2). </p>

<p>Treatment-induced accumulation 
of CD16 
C NK cells predicts outcome 
At the onset of therapy, there was a 
skewed ratio of CD56 
bright cells to CD16 
C cells in favor of 
CD56 
bright cells (median ratio D 0.58 on cycle 1, day 1 vs. &lt;0.1 
in healthy subjects), which is in agreement with previous </p>

<p>studies. 
37,38 The increase of CD16 
C NK cell counts between the 
onset of treatment in cycle 1 and the start of cycle 3 resulted in a 
shift of the distribution of NK cell subtypes in blood toward a </p>

<p>Figure 2. Induction of NK cell subsets in 
the blood during immunotherapy with 
HDC/IL-2. (A) shows representative dot 
plots of the expression intensity of CD16 
and CD56 on CD3 
¡ cells in samples </p>

<p>obtained at the onset of cycle 1 (C1D1), 
at the end of cycle 1 (C1D21), at the onset 
of cycle 3 (C3D1) and at the end of cycle 3 
(C3D21). Figures indicate the percentage 
of CD56 
bright and CD16 
C NK cells of CD3-</p>

<p>lymphocytes. (B and C) show blood 
counts of CD56 
bright and CD16 
C NK cells </p>

<p>before and after cycles 1 and 3. Treat-
ment with HDC/IL-2 increased blood 
counts of CD56 
bright cells and CD16 
C NK </p>

<p>cells during cycle 1 (n D 47) and cycle 3 
(n D 46; Student's paired t-test). </p>

<p>www.tandfonline.com 
e1041701-3 
OncoImmunology </p>

<p>normalized ratio of CD56 
bright to CD16 
C NK cells between cycle 
1, day 1 and cycle 3, day 1 (0.58 vs. 0.28, median ratios, p D 
0.001, signed rank test, n D 46). When assessing the induction 
of CD16 
C NK cells in relapsing and non-relapsing patients fol-
lowed for at least 18 months, a significant induction was 
observed only in patients who remained in remission (Fig. 6A). 
In line with this finding, there was a trend toward a favorable </p>

<p>LFS and OS in patients with a high 
maintained level of CD16  C NK cells 
at the onset of cycle 3 (Figs. 6B, C 
and Table 1). </p>

<p>Post-hoc analyses of lymphocyte 
increment vs. LFS in a phase III trial 
In an attempt to confirm that 
CD16 
C NK cells accumulated in the 
blood between the onset of cycles 1 
and 3, we performed post-hoc analyses 
of the results of a phase III trial 
(M0201 trial) that compared out-
comes in AML patients in CR who 
were randomly assigned to receive 
HDC/IL-2 (n D 160) or standard-of-
care (n D 160). 
28 Lymphocyte counts 
in the blood, but not lymphocyte phe-
notypes, were captured before and 
during treatment cycles. In the phase 
III trial, the absolute lymphocyte 
counts increased between onset of 
treatment (C1D1) and the start of 
cycle 3 in HDC/IL-2-treated patients 
(p D 0.004), but not in untreated 
control patients (Fig. 6D). 
39 The 
increment of lymphocyte counts 
between treatment cycles in this phase 
III trial likely reflected an accumula-
tion of CD16 
C NK cells, since 
CD16 
C NK cells accounted for the 
majority (median 53%) of the lym-
phocyte increment between the onset 
of cycles 1 and 3 in the current phase 
IV Re:Mission trial using the identical 
treatment regimen. In agreement with 
the results in the Re:Mission trial, the 
lymphocyte induction between the 
onset of treatment and the start of 
cycle 3 in HDC/IL-2 treated patients 
in the phase III trial was predictive of 
LFS and OS (Figs. 6E, F). No such 
correlations were observed in the cor-
responding control patients (p &gt; 0.5, 
data not shown). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The purported role of NK cells for 
the outcome of AML has inspired attempts at pharmacologically 
enhancing NK cell functions to improve clearance of leukemic 
cells and thus preventing relapse. Such immunotherapy seems 
intuitively attractive for patients in CR who have completed con-
solidation chemotherapy and thus carry a minimal burden of leu-
kemia. However, most previous attempts to boost the functions </p>

<p>Figure 3. Induction of NCRs during immunotherapy with HDC/IL-2. The box plots show the median fluo-
rescence intensity (MFI) of NKp30 and NKp46 expression on CD56 
bright (A and C) and CD16 
C NK cells (B </p>

<p>and D) at indicated time points (D1 D day 1). NKp30 was induced in both NK cell subsets during cycle 1 
(n D 56) and during cycle 3 (n D 48). NKp46 was significantly up-regulated on CD16 
C NK cells during </p>

<p>both cycles, while no significant induction of NKp46 was observed on CD56 
bright cells (Student's paired 
t-test). </p>

<p>e1041701-4 
Volume 5 Issue 1 
OncoImmunology </p>

<p>of endogenous NK cells for relapse prevention in AML have been 
unsuccessful. For example, monotherapy with IL-2, a prototypic 
NK cell-activating cytokine, in the post-consolidation phase of 
AML did not significantly prevent relapse or prolong the dura-
tion of CR in any of six randomized trials. 
40-45 The inefficiency </p>

<p>of IL-2 monotherapy to prevent relapse is supported by the 
results of meta-analyses comprising a total of &gt;1,400 IL 2-
treated patients. </p>

<p>36,46   HDC is assumed to improve the anti-leukemic efficiency of 
NK cell activators by targeting immunosuppressive ROS. </p>

<p>29-32   Figure 4. Impact of NK cell subsets on LFS and OS in AML patients receiving HDC/IL-2. Patients were dichotomized based on above (red) or below (black) 
median blood cell counts of CD56 
bright (A, B and D, E) or CD16 
C (C and F) NK cells before or after one cycle of treatment and analyzed with regard to LFS </p>

<p>(A, C, D and F) and OS (B and E). LFS and OS were analyzed using the logrank test. </p>

<p>Table 1. Multivariate analysis of LFS and OS. LFS or OS in patients with above or below median values of each variable as determined by univariate and mul-
tivariate Cox regression analyses. In the multivariate analyses, hazard ratios were corrected for age and risk group classification. </p>

<p>Univariate analysis 
Multivariate analysis </p>

<p>Variable 
Hazard ratio 
Confidence interval 
p-value 
Hazard ratio 
Confidence interval 
p-value </p>

<p>No. of CD56 
bright NK, C1D1, LFS 
0.44 
0.20-0.94 
0.033 
0.40 
0.15-1.02 
0.053 
No. of CD56 
bright NK, C1D1, OS 
0.31 
0.10-0.87 
0.025 
0.22 
0.06-0.74 
0.014 
NKp30 expression CD16 
C NK, C1D1, LFS 
0.58 
0.27-1.21 
0.15 
0.32 
0.13-0.78 
0.011 
NKp46 expression CD16 
C NK C1D1, LFS 
0.46 
0.22-0.97 
0.040 
0.41 
0.18-0.89 
0.024 
NKp46 expression CD16 
C NK C1D1, OS 
0.26 
0.09-0.75 
0.012 
0.26 
0.08-0.75 
0.013 
NKp46 expression CD16 
C NK, C1D21, LFS 
0.33 
0.15-0.69 
0.003 
0.34 
0.15-0.75 
0.007 
NKp46 expression CD16 
C NK, C1D21, OS 
0.22 
0.07-0.62 
0.004 
0.29 
0.09-0.88 
0.028 
Induction of CD16 
C NK, C1D1-C3D1, LFS 
0.34 
0.12-0.92 
0.032 
0.38 
0.12-1.20 
0.098 </p>

<p>LFS or OS in patients with above or below median values of each variable as determined by univariate and multivariate Cox regression analyses. In the 
multivariate analyses, hazard ratios were corrected for age and risk group classification. </p>

<p>www.tandfonline.com 
e1041701-5 
OncoImmunology </p>

<p>These toxic oxygen derivatives, which are formed by the 
NADPH oxidase (NOX2) of several subsets of myeloid cells, are 
pivotal effector molecules in anti-microbial defense but have also 
been ascribed a role as negative regulators of cellular immunity 
by inducing dysfunction and apoptosis in adjacent NK cells and 
T cells. 
30,31,47 HDC blocks the activity of NOX2 by targeting 
H 2 -type histamine receptors. The resulting reduction of extracel-
lular release of ROS from myeloid cells rescues NK cells from 
inhibition and apoptosis and thus promotes activation of anti-
leukemic properties of IL-2 and other NK cell-activating com-
pounds. 
29-31 The synergy between IL-2 and HDC in activating 
NK cells in vitro 
31,48 and in reducing the growth of NK cell-sen-
sitive tumors in murine models in vivo 
33 formed the basis for 
the evaluation of the clinical efficacy of HDC/IL-2 in several 
forms of cancer. 
49,50 A phase III trial with 320 non-transplanted 
AML patients in CR in the post-consolidation phase showed a 
significantly improved LFS and a reduced incidence of relapse 
among patients randomly assigned to receive HDC/IL-2 vs. stan-
dard-of-care, in particular among patients in their first CR. </p>

<p>28   This regimen has not yet been evaluated in patients who have not 
achieved CR. </p>

<p>A main finding in the present study was that the adminis-
tration of HDC/IL-2 to patients with AML pronouncedly 
augmented NK cell counts in the blood. The induction of NK 
cell counts was noted during each evaluated 21-d cycle and 
comprised NK cells of the CD16 
C and CD56 
bright pheno-
types. Attempts to define the impact of NK cell phenotypes in 
the blood on LFS and OS revealed that above-median counts 
of CD56 
bright NK cells at onset, but not at later time points, 
predicted a favorable outcome as did treatment-induced accu-
mulation of CD16 
C NK cells between the start of cycle 1 and 
start of cycle 3. The validity of the latter finding was sup-
ported by post-hoc analyses of the results of a previous phase 
III trial, where induction of lymphocytes between cycles 1 and 
3 was significantly associated with LFS and OS in patients ran-
domized to receive HDC/IL-2 but not in untreated control 
patients. 
39 Since CD56 
bright NK cells are assumed to be the 
immediate precursors of CD16 
C NK cells, 
19-22 we hypothesize 
from these findings that the anti-leukemic efficacy of HDC/ 
IL-2 immunotherapy results, at least in part, from initial acti-
vation and expansion of CD56 
bright NK cells that subsequently 
differentiate into cytotoxic CD16 
C cells. The finding of a </p>

<p>Figure 5. Impact of NCR expression on LFS and OS in AML patients receiving HDC/IL-2. Patients were dichotomized based on above (red) or below 
(black) median expression (MFI) of NKp30 (A and D) or NKp46 (B, C, E and F) on CD16 
C NK cells before or after first treatment cycle. LFS and OS were ana-</p>

<p>lyzed using the logrank test. </p>

<p>e1041701-6 
Volume 5 Issue 1 
OncoImmunology </p>

<p>significantly increased ratio of CD16 
C to CD56 
bright NK cell 
counts between the first days of cycles 1 and 3 supports that 
CD56 
bright cells may have differentiated into cytotoxic 
CD16 
C cells during immunotherapy. 
The expression of NKp30 on subsets of NK cells during treat-
ment cycles largely paralleled the induction of NK cell counts in 
blood. Thus, the MFI of NKp30 was markedly increased during 
cycles 1 and 3 on CD16 
C NK cells as well as on CD56 
bright cells, 
and the NKp30 expression remained modestly elevated on </p>

<p>CD56 
bright NK cells at the onset of cycle 3 when compared with 
the level of expression at the start of therapy. NKp46 expression 
was strongly induced on CD16 
C cells but not on CD56 
bright cells 
and no between-cycles induction of NKp46 was observed in any 
of the NK cell subtypes. Despite these differences in the dynam-
ics of NCR expression during immunotherapy, a high expression 
of NKp30 or NK46 on CD16 
C NK cells at onset and/or after 
the first cycle of therapy was positively and significantly associ-
ated with LFS and OS. The validity of these findings is bolstered </p>

<p>Figure 6. Impact of sustained expansion of CD16 
C NK cells on LFS and OS. (A) shows the absolute blood counts of CD16 
C NK cells on day 1 of cycles 1 </p>

<p>and 3 (C1D1 and C3D1) in relapsing (n D 16) and non-relapsing (n D 16) patients followed for more than 18 months. In (B) and (C), patients were dichot-
omized based on above (red) or below (black) the median induction of CD16 
C NK cells between C1D1 and C3D1. LFS (B) and OS (C) were analyzed using </p>

<p>the logrank test. Panels (D)-(F) show post-hoc results from a phase III AML trial (0201), where patients in CR were randomized to receive HDC/IL-2 or no 
treatment (control). (D) shows lymphocyte counts at the onset of treatment and at the onset of cycle 3 (C1D1 and C3D1) in HDC/IL-2-treated patients 
and controls, analyzed using the Student's paired t-test. In (E) and (F), HDC/IL-2-treated patients were dichotomized based on above (red) or below 
(black) median induction of lymphocytes between C1D1 and C3D1. LFS (E) and OS (F) were analyzed using the logrank test. </p>

<p>www.tandfonline.com 
e1041701-7 
OncoImmunology </p>

<p>by previous studies showing that newly diagnosed AML patients 
frequently show deficient expression of NCRs with negative 
impact on OS. </p>

<p>7   In our study, we did not observe significant correlations 
between outcome and in-cycle induction of NCR expression 
when analyzing the entire study population, and it thus remains 
uncertain whether the favorable outcome in patients with high 
NCR expression was related to the immunotherapy or a reflec-
tion of variable baseline NCR expression among patients. How-
ever, post-hoc analyses of patients with low NCR expression at 
onset of therapy supported that treatment-induced NCR expres-
sion was associated with a favorable outcome. In this subgroup, 
induction of NKp46 expression on CD56 
bright cells during the 
first treatment cycle was significantly associated with a favorable 
outcome (Fig. S3). 
We propose that the dynamics of NK cell subsets and their 
NCR expression may contribute to the anti-leukemic efficiency 
of immunotherapy with HDC/IL-2 in AML. While the explor-
atory nature of these findings should be emphasized, it is conceiv-
able that AML patients with an intact NCR expression may 
benefit from relapse-preventive immunotherapy with HDC/IL-
2, or other strategies aimed at boosting NK cell function and, 
also, that NCR expression may be a valid biomarker in future tri-
als evaluating immunotherapy in AML. </p>

<p>Patients and Methods </p>

<p>Patients 
Eighty-four patients aged 18 years or older (age 18-79, 
median 61) with de novo or secondary AML in first CR were eli-
gible for enrollment. In this multicenter study, induction and 
consolidation courses were given as per each participating center. 
For all patients, the induction courses included cytarabine, either 
as continuous infusion 7 d or in intermediate doses (2000-
3000 mg bid) for 3-5 d. Anthracyclines used in the induction 
courses were daunorubicin (n D 77), whereas in 7 cases idarubi-
cin and fludarabine were used. Ten patients received cytarabine 
with other additional chemotherapy including etoposide (n D 7), 
amsacrine (n D 1) and ozogamizin (n D 1). Twenty patients 
achieved CR after two induction courses. 
The number of post-remission courses were 1 (n D 15), 2 
(n D 20), 3 (n D 37), 4 (n D 5), or 5 (n D 1).Typically, consoli-
dation courses included cytarabine and an anthracycline; dauno-
rubicin (n D 45), idarubicin (n D 10) or mitoxantrone (n D 2). 
Four patients received cytarabine and other drugs (etoposide,ozo-
gamizin, methotrexate). In 15 patients the consolidation courses 
comprised high or intermediate doses of cytarabine as the single 
drug. Six patients did not receive any post-remission therapy, of 
these 5 had received 2 induction courses to achieve CR. Precise 
data on consolidation were missing in 2 patients. 
The baseline characteristics of participating patients and their 
impact on LFS are shown in Table S1. Inclusion criteria 
included adequate renal, cardiac, and pulmonary functions along 
with a performance status (according to Eastern Cooperative 
Oncology Group [ECOG] criteria) of 0 to 1. Any previous </p>

<p>induction or consolidation therapy, including autologous bone 
marrow transplantation, was allowed with the exception of allo-
geneic transplantation (performed or planned). Other exclusion 
criteria included FAB-M3 AML, class III or class IV cardiac dis-
ease, other active malignancies and severe hypersensitivity reac-
tions. Elapsed time from dates of CR and the completion of 
consolidation chemotherapy were not to exceed 6 and 3 months 
respectively. The mean time from CR to study entry was 121 d. </p>

<p>Study design and objective 
This single-armed multicenter phase IV study (Re:Mission, 
NCT01347996) enrolled 84 patients at 20 European centers 
between September 2009 and August 2012. The primary end-
point included assessment of the quantitative and qualitative 
pharmacodynamic effects of HDC/IL-2 on the immune 
responses of T and NK cells, including NCR expression. An 
interim analysis report based on data available on May 21st 2013 
was submitted by the study sponsor to the European Medicines 
Agency (EMA). The analyses of NK cell markers vs. outcome are 
based on data for LFS available at this date. The trial was 
approved by the Ethics Committees of each participating institu-
tion, and was conducted in accordance with the Helsinki Decla-
ration. All patients gave written informed consent before 
enrollment. </p>

<p>Treatment and dosing 
Patients received 10 consecutive 3-week cycles of HDC/IL-2 
with 3 weeks off treatment in cycles 1 to 3, and 6 weeks off treat-
ment in cycles 4 to 10. The treatment continued for a total of 
18 months or until the patients relapsed, died, discontinued ther-
apy because of adverse events, withdrew consent, or became lost 
to follow-up. In each cycle, patients received HDC (0.5 mg; Epi-
Cept Corporation) subcutaneously bid and human recombinant 
IL-2 (aldesleukin; 16,400 U/kg; Chiron Corporation) subcuta-
neously bid (Fig. 1). The scheduled total follow-up time was 
2 years, and all patients included for the present analyses were 
followed until the closing date for this analysis. </p>

<p>Definitions and response criteria 
Relapse was defined as at least 5% blast cells in the bone mar-
row or extramedullary leukemia. LFS was defined as the time in 
days from the first day of treatment with HDC/IL-2 to relapse or 
death from any cause. OS was defined as corresponding time to 
death regardless of cause. Risk groups were classified according to 
recommendations by the European LeukemiaNet. </p>

<p>51   Sampling of peripheral blood and flow cytometry 
Peripheral blood was collected before and after treatment 
cycles 1 and 3, i.e. on day 1 and day 21 of cycle 1 (C1D1 and 
C1D21), and on day 1 and day 21 of cycle 3 (C3D1 and 
C3D21). The patient blood was collected into BD Vacutainer 
CPT tubes with sodium citrate (BectonDickinson, Stockholm, 
Sweden), and within two hours PBMCs were isolated by density 
centrifugation. The prepared PBMCs were cryopreserved at local 
sites in CryoMaxx S cryopreservation media (PAA), and shipped 
on dry ice to the central laboratory for immunological assessment </p>

<p>e1041701-8 
Volume 5 Issue 1 
OncoImmunology </p>

<p>(at the Sahlgrenska Cancer Center, University of Gothenburg, 
Sweden). The central laboratory operates under Good Clinical 
Practice (GCP) conditions and passed a GCP-inspection by the 
EMA in August 2013 (2013/014). In addition it forms part of 
the Good Laboratory Practice (GLP) accredited laboratories at 
the Department of Clinical Virology, which is reviewed by the 
Swedish Board for Accreditation and Conformity Assessment. 
Samples were available from 79 out of 84 participating patients. 
Samples were analyzed flow cytometrically within 30 months 
of collection, with a median time until analysis of 15 months. 
The frozen PBMC samples were thawed quickly and washed in 
warm medium. Samples were first stained with LIVE/DEAD 
Fixable Yellow Stain (Invitrogen) in PBS. After washing, cells 
were stained with a cocktail of antibodies in PBS containing 
0.5% BSA and 0.1% EDTA. The following anti-human mono-
clonal antibodies were purchased from BD Biosciences (Stock-
holm, Sweden): anti-CD3-FITC (clone: HIT3a), CD4-APCH7 
(RPA-T4), CD8-PerCpCy5.5 (SK1), CD16-V450 (3G8) 
CD56-APC (B159). The antibodies to NCRs NKp30-PE 
(AF29-4D12), NKp46-APC (9E2) were purchased from Milte-
nyi Biotec. Samples were collected via a 4-laser BD LSRFortessa 
SORP (405, 488, 532, and 640 nm; BD Biosciences). Data were 
analyzed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">FACSDiva</rs> Version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">6</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">BD Biosciences</rs>) or 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">FlowJo</rs> Version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">8.4</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">TreeStar</rs>). All available samples 
were analyzed. If an analysis failed according to pre-defined crite-
ria (experimental failure, few cells, below 25% cellular viability), 
a second sample was thawed for re-analysis. In 18 cases for 
C1D1 samples and in 12 cases for C1D21 samples, also the sec-
ond attempt failed to generate data, and these samples were 
excluded from analysis. Differential counts of whole blood were 
performed at local sites and were utilized to calculate absolute 
counts of blood NK cells. </p>

<p>Analyses of lymphocyte counts vs. outcome in a phase III 
trial 
In an open-label, randomized phase III study 
(NCT00003991), 320 AML patients were enrolled after induc-
tion/consolidation therapies and randomly assigned to an HDC/ 
IL-2 arm (with treatment schedule and dosing identical to 
patients in the Re:Mission Trial) or a control arm (no treat-
ment). 
28 Lymphocyte counts were captured before treatment as 
well as before and after treatment cycles. For the present study, 
the prognostic impact of an increment in lymphocyte counts dur-
ing therapy was determined by dichotomizing patients by high or 
low (by the median) lymphocyte counts followed by analysis of 
LFS and OS in these groups by the logrank test. </p>

<p>Statistics 
As specified in the statistical plan, paired t-test was used for 
single comparisons of NK cell phenotypes. In exploratory analy-
ses the impact of NK cell-related markers on outcome were deter-
mined by dichotomizing patients by high or low (by the median) 
NK cell counts or NCR expression intensity (median fluores-
cence intensity, MFI) followed by analysis of LFS and OS in 
these groups by the logrank test. Parameters that significantly 
predicted LFS and/or OS using the logrank test were further ana-
lyzed by univariate and multivariate Cox regression analysis. In 
the multivariate analyses, hazard ratios were corrected for age and 
risk group classification (Table 1). For practical reasons, the first 
day of treatment was set to day 0 in all survival analyses, also in 
those that evaluated immunological status on day 1 in cycle 3. 
Since the time between first day of treatment and C3D1 is con-
stant for all patients (84 d), this has no consequence for the con-
ducted analyses. All indicated p values are 2-sided. </p>

<p>Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>Authors KH and MB are past or present consultants to the 
study sponsor (Meda Pharma). Author KH holds patents protect-
ing the use of histamine dihydrochloride in cancer immunother-
apy. Authors AM, RF, and FBT have received honoraria and/or 
travel grants from the study sponsor. The other authors declare 
no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors are indebted to all participants in the Re:Mission 
Study Group. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by Meda Pharma, Bad Homburg, 
Germany (Study Sponsor), the Swedish Research Council 
(2012-2047, 2012-3205, 2011-3003), the Swedish Society for 
Medical Research (SSMF), the Swedish Society of Medicine 
(SLS-406151), the Swedish Cancer Society (CAN 212/595, 
CAN 213/550), the Swedish state via the ALF agreement 
(ALFGBG-151441, ALFGBG-292701), the Erna and Victor 
Hasselblad foundation, the Torsten and Ragnar S€ oderberg Foun-
dation, The IngaBritt and Arne Lundberg Foundation, Bio-
CARE -a National Strategic Research Program at University of 
Gothenburg, and the Sahlgrenska Academy at University of 
Gothenburg. </p>



<p>www.tandfonline.com 
e1041701-9 
OncoImmunology </p>



<p>e1041701-10 
Volume 5 Issue 1 
OncoImmunology </p>



<p>www.tandfonline.com 
e1041701-11 
OncoImmunology </p>

</text></tei>