<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4375646" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objectives: Simultaneous scalp EEG-fMRI can identify hemodynamic changes associated with the generation of 
interictal epileptiform discharges (IEDs), and it has the potential of becoming a standard, non-invasive technique 
for pre-surgical assessment of patients with medically intractable epilepsy. This study was designed to assess the 
BOLD response to focal IEDs recorded via simultaneous intracranial EEG-functional MRI (iEEG-fMRI). 
Methods: Twelve consecutive patients undergoing intracranial video EEG monitoring were recruited for iEEG-
fMRI studies at 3 T. Depth, subdural strip, or grid electrodes were implanted according to our standard clinical 
protocol. Subjects underwent 10-60 min of continuous iEEG-fMRI scanning. IEDs were marked, and the most sta-
tistically significant clusters of BOLD signal were identified (Z-score 2.3, p value b 0.05). We assessed the concor-
dance between the locations of the BOLD response and the IED. Concordance was defined as a distance b1.0 cm 
between the IED and BOLD response location. Negative BOLD responses were not studied in this project. 
Results: Nine patients (7 females) with a mean age of 31 years (range 22-56) had 11 different types of IEDs during 
fMR scanning. The IEDs were divided based on the location of the active electrode contact into mesial temporal, 
lateral temporal, and extra-temporal. Seven (5 left) mesial temporal IED types were recorded in 5 patients 
(110-2092 IEDs per spike location). Six of these IEDs had concordant BOLD response in the ipsilateral mesial tem-
poral structures, b1 cm from the most active contact. One of the two subjects with left lateral temporal IEDs had 
BOLD responses concordant with the location of the most active contact, as well other ipsilateral and contralat-
eral sites. Notably, the remaining two subjects with extratemporal discharges showed no BOLD signal near the 
active electrode contact. 
Conclusions: iEEG-fMRI is a feasible and low-risk method for assessment of hemodynamic changes of very focal 
IEDs that may not be recorded by scalp EEG. A high concordance rate between the location of the BOLD response 
and IEDs was seen for mesial temporal (6/7) IEDs. Significant BOLD activation was also seen in areas distant from 
the active electrode and these sites exhibited maximal BOLD activation in the majority of cases. This implies that 
iEEG-fMRI may further describe the areas involved in the generation of IEDs beyond the vicinity of the 
electrode(s). 
Scalp electroencephalography (EEG) is widely regarded as an 
effective method for recording epileptic discharges, and is a mainstay </p>

<p>in a typical epilepsy unit. Despite its widespread use, however, 
there are inherent limitations. Scalp EEG primarily records activity 
of pyramidal neurons near the surface of the brain. Thus, epileptiform 
activity originating from deep sources is not recorded. In addition, 
a minimum of 10-20 cm 
2 of synchronous, or nearly synchronous </p>

<p>activity is required for the detection of interictal epileptiform 
discharges (IEDs) with scalp EEG (Tao et al., 2005). Hence, IEDs 
originating from small regions of epileptogenic cortex are not recorded. 
Finally, the spatial resolution of scalp EEG is only 22-37 cm 
3 when </p>

<p>NeuroImage: Clinical 7 (2015) 755-763 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: IED, interictal epileptiform discharge; VEM, video-EEG monitoring. 
⁎ Corresponding author at: Hotchkiss Brain Institute, University of Calgary, Foothills 
Medical Centre, Room C1214a, 1403 29th Street NW, Calgary, AB T2N 2T9, Canada. 
Tel.: +1 403 944 4091; fax: +1 403 283 2270. 
E-mail address: pfederic@ucalgary.ca (P. Federico). </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.nicl.2015.03.002 
2213-1582/© 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/). </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>NeuroImage: Clinical </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / y n i c l </p>

<p>using a routine set of 19 electrodes, and improves to only 6-8 cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>when using up to 128 electrodes (Ferree et al., 2001). 
The poor spatial resolution of scalp EEG can be mitigated by combin-
ing EEG with functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI). Simulta-
neous EEG-fMRI can also noninvasively evaluate the hemodynamic 
changes associated with IEDs and has been used successfully for pre-
surgical assessment of patients with medically intractable epilepsy 
(An et al., 2013; Gotman and Pittau, 2011; Laufs and Duncan, 2007; 
Moeller et al., 2009; Thornton et al., 2010; Zijlmans et al., 2007). For ex-
ample, an EEG-fMRI study of 29 patients initially rejected for epilepsy 
surgery due to inaccurate localization of the seizure focus through stan-
dard clinical investigations, identified focal and significant blood oxygen 
level dependent (BOLD) responses in 15 subjects (Zijlmans et al., 2007). 
Eight of these 15 subjects had a BOLD response concordant with IED lo-
calization. Furthermore, two patients subsequently underwent intracra-
nial EEG (iEEG) monitoring; the BOLD response showed concordance 
with the ictal onset zone determined by iEEG. One of these patients 
underwent surgical resection and had a good post-surgical outcome 
(Engel class II). In another EEG-fMRI study, the BOLD signal from nine 
non-lesional frontal lobe epilepsy patients was compared to the topog-
raphy of spikes, and to positron emission tomography and single photon 
emission computerized tomography results, when available (Moeller 
et al., 2009). Concordance between IED localization and the location of 
BOLD response was demonstrated in 8 of the 9 patients. In two cases, 
reviewing the structural MRI guided by EEG-fMRI data resulted in the 
consideration of a suspicious, deep sulcus as potential pathology. 
These two patients subsequently underwent surgical resection and his-
tology confirmed cortical dysplasia in one and microdysgenesis in the 
other. The EEG-fMRI data had shown activation just adjacent to the 
resected pathologic area. These studies suggest that scalp EEG-fMRI pro-
vides added value as a pre-surgical tool; however, the limitations of 
scalp EEG3s insensitivity to deep structures and to small regions of epi-
leptogenic cortex remain. 
Compared to scalp EEG, iEEG has greater sensitivity and spatial spec-
ificity for recording focal IEDs from deep structures such as the mesial 
temporal regions (Morris and Luders, 1985), and the area of cortex re-
quired for detection using iEEG is reduced to within a 1 cm vicinity of 
the recording electrode (Lachaux et al., 2003). In combination with 
fMRI, iEEG thus possesses great clinical potential. With this in mind, 
our research group recently assessed the risk and feasibility of simulta-
neous iEEG-fMRI at 3 T in phantoms and epilepsy patients (Boucousis 
et al., 2012; Cunningham et al., 2012). We found that standard 
gradient-echo based structural and functional MR protocols did not in-
duce any clinically significant electrode heating, electrode movement, 
or electrical currents. As such, simultaneous iEEG-fMRI was deemed 
low-risk by our local ethics and safety committee. Since then, we have 
been actively using simultaneous iEEG-fMRI for the study of epilepsy 
patients. In the present study, we assessed the concordance between 
the location of focal IEDs and the associated BOLD responses recorded 
with simultaneous iEEG-fMRI. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>2.1. Intracranial EEG subjects </p>

<p>The Conjoint Health Research Ethics Board of our institution ap-
proved this project. Written informed consent was obtained from all 
participants prior to their participation. Twelve consecutive patients un-
dergoing intracranial video-EEG monitoring (VEM) at our center were 
recruited. The inclusion criteria included: age ≥ 18 years, no MR contra-
indications (e.g., ferromagnetic implants, claustrophobia), no post-
implantation complications (e.g., subdural hematoma, infection, severe 
headache), and the ability to provide informed consent. 
Intracranial VEM data were reviewed by an experienced epileptologist 
(PF) to select electrodes for recording during the iEEG-fMRI session. </p>

<p>The first seven subjects had the two most active strip or depth elec-
trodes selected for data collection. Electrodes were attached via 
commercially available connector blocks (product number L-SRL-
10DIN; Ad-Tech, Racine, WI) to a custom-built, two-tailed electrode 
connector capable of recording 19 contacts (Compumedics NeuroScan, 
Charlotte, NC) and coupled with a commercial scalp EEG-fMRI system 
(MagLink RT; Compumedics NeuroScan). The next five subjects had 
up to eight strip or depth electrodes selected for data collection. These 
electrodes were attached to a custom built, eight-tailed electrode con-
nector capable of recording 64 contacts (Compumedics NeuroScan). 
We have previously shown that these connectors are of low-risk 
in our 3 Tesla environment (Boucousis et al., 2012; Cunningham et al., 
2012). </p>

<p>2.2. iEEG-fMRI acquisition </p>

<p>The subjects underwent 10-60 min of fMRI scanning as per the grad-
ual implementation protocol established prior to the start of the project 
(see Cunningham et al., 2012). EEG data were continuously collected at 
10 kHz using a SynAmps 
2 amplification/digitization system and Scan 4.4 </p>

<p>Software (Compumedics NeuroScan). The first seven subjects were 
scanned using a 3 Tesla GE, Signa LX whole body scanner and a 
receive-only eight-channel phased-array head coil, while the last five 
subjects were scanned using a 3 Tesla GE Discovery MR750 whole 
body scanner and a receive-only eight-channel phased-array coil (GE 
Healthcare, Waukesha, WI). No adverse events were reported during 
the scanning of any patient. 
The MR imaging protocol for the 3.0 T GE, Signa LX scanner 
included multislice anatomical imaging (spoiled gradient-recalled 
echo, TE = min full, TR = 150 ms, flip angle = 18°, 128 × 128 matrix, 
24 5-mm thick slices), anatomical 3D T 1 -weighted imaging (magnetiza-
tion-prepared rapid gradient-echo: TE = min full, TR = 8.9 ms, flip 
angle = 20°, 384 × 256 × 64 matrix, 2-mm thick slices), a non-linear 
shimming sequence to minimize magnetic field inhomogeneities, 
and fMRI (gradient recalled echo planar imaging sequence, with TE = 
30 ms, TR = 1500 ms, flip angle = 60°, 24-cm field of view, 64 × 64 ma-
trix, 24 5-mm thick slices). The MR imaging protocol for the 3.0 T GE 
Discovery MR750 included multislice anatomical imaging (spoiled 
gradient-recalled echo 2D multi-slice sequence, TE = 2.1 ms, TR = 
150 ms, flip angle = 18°, 128 × 128 matrix, 24 5-mm thick slices), ana-
tomical 3D T 1 -weighted imaging (TE = 3.8 ms, TR = 9.3 ms, flip 
angle = 12°, 24-cm field of view, 320 × 256 × 64 matrix, 2-mm thick 
slices), a non-linear shimming sequence to minimize magnetic field in-
homogeneities, and fMRI (spoiled gradient recalled echo planar imag-
ing, TE = 30 ms, TR = 1500 ms, flip angle = 65°, 24-cm field of view, 
64 × 64 matrix, 24 5-mm thick slices). 
The subjects3 heads were immobilized in the head coil using com-
pressible foam cushions, and the electrode tails/connector blocks were 
directed outside of the coil, padded, and secured to the scanning table 
to minimize movement, vibration, and RF energy deposition. Subjects 
were encouraged to sleep. During iEEG-fMRI data collection, EEG re-
cordings were filtered online for viewing purposes and were monitored 
in real-time by an experienced epileptologist (PF). Raw EEG data were 
stored for offline analyses. </p>

<p>2.3. Intracranial EEG data processing </p>

<p>All EEG data processing was performed using <rs id="software-8" type="software">ScanEdit</rs> <rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">v4.4</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-8" type="creator">Compumedics NeuroScan</rs>). Gradient switching artifact was removed 
using average artifact subtraction, which uses the regularity of the gra-
dient switching induced waveform to generate a moving average arti-
fact that can be successfully removed from the baseline EEG (Allen 
et al., 2000). Cardioballistic artifact is commonly seen in routine scalp 
EEG recordings. It is greatly amplified when EEG is recorded in the MR 
environment because movement of electrically conductive material in </p>

<p> 
Y. Aghakhani et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 7 (2015) 755-763 </p>

<p>a static field results in electromagnetic induction. In contrast, 
cardioballistic artifact is not seen in routine clinical intracranial EEG re-
cords, nor was it seen in our intracranial EEG recordings in the MR </p>

<p>environment. Therefore, removal of this artifact was not necessary. 
The reason why this artifact is not seen in clinical intracranial EEG re-
cordings or in our iEEG-fMRI recordings is that intracranial electrodes </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Intracranial EEG recordings from patient 3. (A) Interictal iEEG recordings obtained in our Seizure Monitoring Unit. (B) Intracranial EEG of clinical quality acquired during simulta-
neous fMR image acquisition at 3 T. (C) Ictal iEEG recording of a right mesial temporal lobe seizure recorded in our Seizure Monitoring Unit. Note that the EEG samples in A and B are 1 s 
data segments containing interictal epileptiform discharges. </p>

<p> 
Y. Aghakhani et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 7 (2015) 755-763 </p>

<p>(depth or subdural electrodes) are less prone to movement with cardiac 
pulsations because they are fixed to the skull or dura. Additionally, the 
distance between the active and reference electrodes is smaller for 
iEEG than scalp EEG, which further reduces the amplitude of 
cardioballistic artifact. 
A low-pass filter at 30 Hz was applied to the EEG data, and a bipolar 
montage for each electrode bank was generated. Two experienced elec-
troencephalographers (PF, YA) reviewed the EEG data noting the 
timing, morphology, and location of interictal discharges. Examples of 
iEEG recorded outside the MR scanner in the seizure monitoring unit 
for clinical purposes using a clinical EEG recording system (Natus 
Xltek NeuroWorks, Natus Medical Incorporated, San Carlos, CA) and in-
side the MR scanner are shown in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>2.4. fMRI data processing </p>

<p>fMRI data processing was carried out using <rs id="software-9" type="software">FEAT [FMRI Expert 
Analysis Tool</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-number">Version 6.00</rs>, part of <rs id="software-10" type="software">FSL (FMRIB3s Software Library</rs>, 
<rs corresp="#software-10" type="url">http://www.fmrib.ox.ac.uk/fsl</rs>)]. The following pre-processing was ap-
plied: motion correction using <rs type="software">MCFLIRT</rs> [Motion Correction: FMRIB3s 
Linear Image Registration Tool (Jenkinson et al., 2002)], slice-timing 
correction using Fourier-space time-series phase-shifting; non-brain re-
moval using the <rs type="software">Brain Extraction Tool</rs> (Smith, 2002), spatial smoothing 
using a Gaussian kernel of FWHM 6.0 mm; high-pass temporal filtering 
(Gaussian-weighted least-squares straight line fitting, with sigma = 
50.0 s). Registration of fMRI data to high-resolution structural and 
standard-space images was carried out using <rs type="software">FLIRT</rs> [FMRIB3s Linear 
Image Registration Tool (Jenkinson et al., 2002; Jenkinson and Smith, 
2001)]. Because patient movement was minimal (b3 mm) in most pa-
tients, motion parameters were not included as regressors since motion 
correction via <rs type="software">MCFLIRT</rs> [Motion Correction: FMRIB3s Linear Image Reg-
istration Tool (Jenkinson et al., 2002)] sufficiently minimized any mo-
tion effects. 
The binary timing of interictal discharges was convolved with multi-
ple hemodynamic response functions (HRFs) with time-to-peak rang-
ing from 0-13 s, similar to the methodology employed for scalp EEG-
fMRI analyses by other groups (Bagshaw et al., 2004; Kobayashi et al., 
2006a; Kobayashi et al., 2006b). The generated model was imported 
into FEAT where a time-series statistical analysis was carried out using 
<rs type="software">FILM (FMRIB3s Improved Linear Model</rs>) with local autocorrelation cor-
rection for each run (Woolrich et al., 2001). Higher-level analyses 
were performed using a fixed effects model, by forcing the random ef-
fects variance to zero in FLAME (FMRIB3s Local Analysis of Mixed Ef-
fects) (Beckmann et al., 2003; Woolrich et al., 2004; Woolrich, 2008), 
generating a statistical average of all runs. To account for the increased 
probability of Type 1 error through the use of multiple HRFs, 
data were corrected using <rs type="software">AlphaSim</rs> of the <rs id="software-18" type="software">AFNI</rs> analysis package 
<rs corresp="#software-18" type="url">http://afni.nimh.nih.gov/pub/dist/doc/program_help/AlphaSim.html</rs> 
that performs both probability and cluster-based thresholding at a sig-
nificance level of p b 0.05, as determined by Monte Carlo simulations 
(Ward, 2000). Locations of the strongest activation were identified as 
the cluster (as determined by AlphaSim) with maximum peak response 
(Z-score). The gamma function time-to-peak for each subject3s maximal 
response was used. Parametric maps were overlaid onto high-
resolution structural images that were registered to MNI standard 
space. 
The BOLD response(s) for each IED was visually evaluated. If 
the BOLD response was within 1 cm of the center of recording 
electrode(s) showing maximal involvement of the IEDs (defined as 
the maximal amplitude in referential montage and/or phase reversal 
in bipolar montage), there was considered to be good concordance 
between BOLD response and the recorded discharges. A significant 
BOLD response in the same lobe as the active electrode was assessed 
as relative concordance, and outside of the same lobe as poor 
concordance. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Subjects </p>

<p>All twelve patients underwent simultaneous intracranial EEG-fMRI 
data acquisition without adverse event. Three subjects were excluded 
from analysis due to inadequate grounding of the EEG signal and persis-
tent MR gradient switching EEG artifact that could not be removed dur-
ing post-processing, which rendered the EEG uninterpretable. Patient 
movement during data collection was limited as all patients but one 
had a maximum displacement b3 mm. One patient had a maximum dis-
placement of 20 mm on a few occasions during scanning. The segments 
containing N3 mm displacement for this patient were excluded from 
analysis. Of the nine analyzed datasets, the ictal semiology was sugges-
tive of a temporal focus in 7 patients (one neocortical) and a frontal 
focus in 2 patients (Table 1). Structural MRI revealed no lesion in 4 pa-
tients, but revealed mesial temporal lobe sclerosis in 1, bilateral 
periventricular nodular heterotopia in 1, enlarged amygdala in 1, unilat-
eral perisylvian polymicrogyria in 1, and unilateral post-traumatic 
encephalomalacia in frontotemporal region in 1. </p>

<p>3.2. Clinical EEG data </p>

<p>All patients underwent scalp VEM. Generally, the interictal EEG find-
ings were not well localized except for patient 6 who had epileptiform 
discharges over the left temporal lobe (Table 1). The ictal EEG changes 
were also poorly localized except for patients 6 and 7, who both had sei-
zure onsets over the left temporal area. All patients except patients 6, 7, 
and 9 had bilateral electrode implantation using subdural strips with or 
without depth electrodes. Patient 6 had unilateral grid, strip and depth 
electrodes, patient 7 had unilateral subdural strip and depth electrodes, 
and patient 9 had subdural strip electrodes. Subjects had between 48 
and 156 recording contacts (mean = 82). Interpretation of the intracra-
nial VEM data identified the seizure onset zone in all subjects: unilateral 
mesial temporal lobe in 2 patients, independent bilateral temporal lobe 
in 3, temporal neocortex in 2, and multifocal in 2 (Table 1). </p>

<p>3.3. iEEG-fMRI data </p>

<p>iEEG of clinical quality was recorded during functional MR scanning 
(Fig. 1B). Based on the location of spiking, 11 different types of IEDs 
were recorded during iEEG-fMRI studies ranging from 37-2611 dis-
charges per location (mean 857 ± 286). Subjects were divided into 
the following groups based on the location of the contact where the dis-
charges were most frequently observed: mesial temporal, lateral tem-
poral, and extra-temporal. </p>

<p>3.3.1. Mesial temporal discharges 
Seven (5 left, 2 right) mesial temporal IED types were recorded in 
five patients (patients 1-5; patients 2 and 3 had bilateral independent 
temporal epileptic foci). The number of discharges recorded in these pa-
tients ranged from 110-2092 with an average of 738 ± 353 discharges. 
Six of the 7 mesial temporal IEDs had a BOLD response with good con-
cordance (b1 cm distance) in the ipsilateral mesial temporal structures 
with an average Z-score of 5.8 (range 3.15-9.65) and an average activat-
ed cluster volume of 3.14 cm 
3 (range 0.75-8.61 cm 
3, Fig. 2A, Table 2). </p>

<p>Four of these discharge types had additional extra-temporal BOLD clus-
ters: contralateral parietal in 2 patients, bilateral frontal-parietal in 2, 
ipsilateral temporal-parietal in 1, bilateral occipital in 1, contralateral 
insula in 1, and contralateral temporal pole in 1 (Fig. 2A). The BOLD clus-
ter with the maximum Z-score value was located at the discharge loca-
tion in 2 datasets (subject 2 right and left), and was extra-temporal in 5 
(patients 1, 3, right and left, 4, 5). One subject (subject 5) in this group 
had a significant BOLD cluster only in the ipsilateral occipital cortex 
(poor concordance). Notably, this subject showed a large area of elec-
trode susceptibility artifact over the temporal lobe that was likely wors-
ened by additional movement artifact. This, in turn, resulted in </p>

<p> 
Y. Aghakhani et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 7 (2015) 755-763 </p>

<p>significant loss of BOLD signal in the temporal region (Fig. 2A, Table 2). 
Patient 1, with good concordance, underwent left temporal lobectomy 
with class I outcome, and patient 5, with poor concordance, had a 
large left temporal neocortical resection with class IV outcome. Patients 
2, 3, and 4 did not undergo surgical resection. </p>

<p>3.3.2. Temporal neocortical discharges 
Two subjects had left temporal neocortical discharges. Patient 6 had 
concordant BOLD activation in the ipsilateral posterior hippocampus, 
ipsilateral frontal and posterior temporal lobe, and contralateral insula 
(good concordance, Fig. 2B). Patient 7 had multifocal BOLD clusters in 
the ipsilateral frontal opercular, frontoparietal, parieto-occipital, post-
temporal-occipital cortices, and cerebellum in the other (relative </p>

<p>concordance, Fig. 2B). Both achieved class I outcome with left temporal 
lobectomy and left temporal neocortical resection, respectively. </p>

<p>3.3.3. Extratemporal discharges 
These two subjects (patients 8 and 9) with left posterolateral frontal 
and left parietal discharges showed no BOLD response at the location of 
the interictal discharges (Fig. 2C). Subject 8 showed a BOLD response in 
the ipsilateral orbitofrontal, contralateral frontal and contralateral tem-
poral pole (relative concordance). For subject 9, a BOLD response was 
seen in the bilateral parietal cortices with maximum Z-score in the con-
tralateral parietal region (poor concordance). These patients did not un-
dergo surgical resection due to poor clinical iEEG localization of the 
seizure focus. </p>

<p>Table 1 
Demographic, ictal semiology, MRI and EEG data of the study subjects. </p>

<p>Pt Age/sex Seizure semiology 
MRI findings 
Scalp 
EEG 
interictal </p>

<p>Scalp EEG 
ictal 
onset </p>

<p>iEEG coverage 
iEEG interictal 
iEEG ictal 
onset </p>

<p>Surgery 
Outcome, F/U </p>

<p>1 20/♀ 
Abdominal pain → 
Bil PVNH L N R 
Bil FT 
1. RFT 
R:Am, Hc, PVNH 
Active LT, rare 
L T 
LT lobectomy 
Class I, 5 yrs 
Hyperventilation → 
Staring→ </p>

<p>2. LT 
R mesial T </p>

<p>LOC and oral 
automatism → </p>

<p>L: mesial &amp; lateral 
F, and sub T </p>

<p>2°GTC 
2 29/♀ 
1. Smell→ 
Flashing light→ </p>

<p>L enlarged Am 
Bil T 
Bil T 
R: lateral, mesial 
&amp; sub T </p>

<p>Bil mesial T 
Bil TLE 
Bil HS 
Class IV, 5 yrs </p>

<p>Deja vu → LOC 
2. Nocturnal GTC </p>

<p>L: lateral, mesial &amp; sub T </p>

<p>3 52/♀ 
1. Deja vu→ Smell 
→ LOC </p>

<p>Normal 
Bil T, 
R N L </p>

<p>Bi T 
R: mesial, lateral, &amp; sub 
T </p>

<p>Bil TR N L 
Bil TLE 
Not operated 
Class III, 9 mo </p>

<p>2. Nocturnal GTC 
L: mesial, lateral, &amp; sub 
T 
4 24/♂ 
Gustatory, 
epigastric, flashing </p>

<p>Normal 
Bil F, 
R N L 
(rare) </p>

<p>Bi T 
R: mesial, inferior &amp; 
lateral T-O </p>

<p>Bil mesial T 
Bil TLE 
Not operated 
Seizure free, </p>

<p>Light staring → with 
LOC, oral and arm 
automatisms </p>

<p>2 yrs </p>

<p>→ 2°GTC </p>

<p>L: mesial, inferior &amp; 
lateral T-O </p>

<p>5 56/♀ 
Head turning to L 
→ R arm stiffening 
→ 2°GTC </p>

<p>L MTS 
Bil T, 
L N R </p>

<p>1. LF 
R: mesial -sub T, 
lateral FT, &amp; lateral F </p>

<p>Multifocal: LT, 
L mesial T LT neocortex </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Class IV, 6 mo 
2. Bil F </p>

<p>Lateral F </p>

<p>RT LF, RF 
3. Diffuse </p>

<p>L: mesial -sub T, 
lateral FT, &amp; lateral F 
Lateral F 
6 27/♀ 
Deja vu, chest 
/abdominal </p>

<p>L perisylvian PMG LT 
LT 
L: orbito F and T, lateral 
F &amp; inslua </p>

<p>L anterior T 
L anterior 
T </p>

<p>LT lobectomy 
Class I, 3 yrs </p>

<p>discomfort 
→ Staring with </p>

<p>Insula </p>

<p>LOC and R eye 
blinking and 
nocturnal GTC 
7 24/♀ 
Hears music → Loss 
of speech → At 
times 2°GTC </p>

<p>LF-T 
None 
LT 
L: lateral T, anterior T, 
Hc, first T gyrus, &amp; 
Heschl gyrus </p>

<p>LT neocortex 
LT 
neocortex </p>

<p>LT neocortex </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Class I, 1 yr 
Encephalomalacia </p>

<p>8 29/♀ 
1. Staring with LOC 
and gibberish speech </p>

<p>Normal 
GSW 
max F </p>

<p>GSW max 
L F </p>

<p>R: lateral, mesial 
&amp; orbito F </p>

<p>Multifocal: 
Multifocal: Not operated 
Seizure free, 
LF, RF 
LF, RF 
4 mo </p>

<p>2. Head turning to R 
then GTC </p>

<p>L: lateral, mesial 
&amp; sub F 
9 22/♂ 
Headache, dreamy 
state, loss of speech 
→ LOC </p>

<p>Normal 
LT, LP− 
L: lateral O, T, P, 
and under O </p>

<p>Multifocal: 
Multifocal: Not operated 
Unchanged, </p>

<p>with oral automatism 
→ 2°GTC </p>

<p>post T 
LP-O-post 
T 
&amp; T </p>

<p>P, T, O 
P, T, O 
1 yr </p>

<p>Abbreviations: Am amygdala, Bil bilateral, F frontal, FT frontotemporal, GTC generalized tonic-clonic seizures, GSW generalized spike/polyspike and wave, Hc hippocampus, HS hippocam-
pal stimulator, I insula, L left, LOC loss of consciousness, mo month, max maximal, MTS mesial temporal sclerosis, NA not available, O occipital, P parietal, PMG polymicrogyria, PVNH 
periventricular nodular heterotopia, R right, T temporal, yr year. 
a Sparing mesial T structures. </p>

<p> 
Y. Aghakhani et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 7 (2015) 755-763 </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>This study has produced several notable findings about BOLD signal 
changes associated with focal IEDs recorded by intracranial electrodes. 
First, our data confirm the results of our and other studies of the feasibil-
ity and low-risk of iEEG-fMRI when performed under controlled condi-
tions (Boucousis et al., 2012; Carmichael et al., 2012; Cunningham et al., 
2012; Vulliemoz et al., 2011). 
Second, significant BOLD activation was seen in all 9 (out of a total of 
12) patients in whom interpretable EEG was obtained. Previous scalp 
EEG-fMRI studies detected BOLD responses associated with IEDs in 
50-60% and 60-70% of patients studied with spike-triggered or contin-
uous EEG-fMRI, respectively (Mulert and Lemieux, 2009). Other re-
search groups have shown that the yield of scalp EEG-fMRI can be 
increased to 80-100% by performing convolutions using multiple he-
modynamic response functions peaking at 3, 5, 7, and 9 s (Kobayashi 
et al., 2006a; Kobayashi et al., 2006b; Pittau et al., 2012). Following the 
success of this analytical approach, we employed a multiple HRF 
model for our analyses that may in part, explain the high yield from 
the present study. Another possible explanation may be the high num-
ber of epileptiform discharges that were analyzed in our subjects (range 
37-2611, mean 857 ± 286). The nature of intracranial EEG also offers 
the advantage of recording of epileptiform activity without attenuation 
by the dura, skull, and scalp, which has been theorized to act as a phys-
iological signal filter that allows only the IEDs of the greatest amplitude, 
which recruit large areas of the cortex, to be visible on scalp EEG (Tao 
et al., 2005). Additionally, seemingly spike-free periods seen on scalp 
EEG-fMRI may have IEDs that cannot be detected by scalp EEG. The 
presence of these unrecorded discharges could contaminate the base-
line BOLD signal used for statistical comparison to the periods of spiking 
by the fMRI general linear model (GLM). Intracranial EEG-fMRI circum-
vents this limitation; however, it offers limited sampling of the brain 
that is dependent on the placement of intracranial EEG electrodes. 
Three EEG datasets, performed early in this project, were deemed unin-
terpretable due to persistent artifact, attributed to insufficient ground-
ing of the EEG signal by the 20-electrode connector, and a lack of 
synchronization between the internal clocks of the MRI and EEG sys-
tems. We have experienced no further losses of data (2011 to present) </p>

<p>since subsequently using a new 64-electrode connector and an MRI-
to-EEG clock synchronizer (Compumedics NeuroScan). 
Third, we found high concordance between location of the recorded 
IEDs and BOLD responses. The highest concordance was seen with me-
sial temporal lobe epileptiform discharges, with 6 of the 7 patients 
(86%) showing good concordance. The remaining patient (subject 
5) with mesial temporal discharges had an ipsilateral occipital BOLD re-
sponse without any temporal BOLD signal. Interestingly, this patient 
had a poor postsurgical outcome. It would therefore be tempting to 
speculate that the lack of a significant BOLD response in the intended 
surgical target should prompt a search for an ictal onset zone elsewhere 
in the brain, particularly where the BOLD response was seen, which in 
this case, was not covered by intracranial EEG electrodes. However, 
the poor concordance in this case may also be partly related to signifi-
cant BOLD signal loss in the temporal region due to susceptibility artifact 
resulting from a combination of a high number of temporal electrodes 
and a large amount of patient motion (N20 mm) during the scanning 
session limiting the amount of analyzable data collected. 
The higher likelihood of good concordance in the mesial temporal 
group seen in the present study compared to previous studies looking 
at iEEG and scalp EEG-fMRI data separately (Al-Asmi et al., 2003; 
Benar et al., 2006; Lazeyras et al., 2000), may be related to our capability 
of iEEG to record IEDs for fMRI correlation with higher spatial resolution 
and sensitivity than scalp EEG. Furthermore, the criteria used to mea-
sure concordance in the present study, b1.0 cm between the IED and 
BOLD response location, is stricter than previously published work 
that used b2.0 cm between area of interest (resection margin) and 
BOLD response as selection for good concordance (An et al., 2013). 
Good concordance was seen in one of two patients with neocortical 
discharges and relative concordance in the other. In the two subjects 
with extra-temporal epileptiform discharges, one in the left frontal 
lobe and the other in the left parietal lobe, significant BOLD responses 
were seen in the same lobe, but not adjacent to the recording electrodes. 
The small number of patients with lateral temporal and extra-
temporal spikes is one limitation of our study that precludes definitive 
conclusions about these groups. However a trend towards a possible 
difference in the degree of concordance between the lateral and extra-
temporal groups compared to the mesial temporal group was seen. </p>

<p>Table 2 
iEEG and BOLD response data of the 11 iEEG epileptiform discharge types recorded during fMR scanning. </p>

<p>Pt Number 
of IEDs </p>

<p>Location of IEDs 
BOLD at 
location 
of spike </p>

<p>Max Z score 
at location 
of spike </p>

<p>Volume of BOLD 
at location of 
spike (cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Distance from 
susceptibility 
(mm) </p>

<p>BOLD 
in other 
location(s) </p>

<p>Location 
of max 
BOLD </p>

<p>Max 
Z score </p>

<p>Volume of 
max BOLD 
(cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Time to 
peak BOLD 
(sec) </p>

<p>Max patient 
movement 
(mm) </p>

<p>1 
216 
L parahippocampus Yes 
3.68 
5.84 
12 
R mesial P 
R mesial P 3.68 
0.71 
5 
0.6 
2a 
184 
R mesial T 
Yes 
6.14 
8.61 
8 
No 
R mesial T 6.14 
8.61 
4.5 
2.0 
2b 
277 
L mesial T 
Yes 
5.31 
1.14 
12 
No 
L mesial T 
5.31 
1.14 
5 
2.0 
3a 2035 
R mesial T 
Yes 
4.43 
0.75 
14 
Bil F−P, R 
R mesial P 9.65 
532.50 
7 
2.0 
mesial T-P, 
LT pole 
3b 
253 
L mesial T 
Yes 
3.15 
0.91 
14 
Bil Occipital, R cuneous 4.98 
68.21 
8 
2.0 
RP, 
R insula 
4 
2092 
L mesial T 
Yes 
5.94 
1.57 
14 
Bil post F−P LP-O 
6.78 
256.25 
5.5 
1.5 
5 
110 
L mesial T 
No 
-
-
12 
LO 
LO 
3.2 
0.86 
8 
20 
6 
1541 
L lateral T 
Yes 
5.77 
10.26 
26 
L post Hc 
L lateral T 
5.77 
10.26 
4 
1.2 
7 
75 
L middle T gyrus 
No 
-
-
12 
LF 
LF 
4.4 
2.78 
7 
1.3 
opercular, L 
operculum 
post F−P, 
LP-O, 
L post T-O, 
L cerebellum 
8 
37 
L posterolateral F 
No 
-
-
20 
L orbito-F, 
RF 
3.19 
1.14 
8 
1.3 
RF, 
RT pole 
9 
2611 
L anterior P 
No 
-
-
44 
LP, 
RP 
4.73 
1.04 
4.5 
1.5 
RP </p>

<p>Abbreviations: Bil bilateral, F frontal, Hc hippocampus, IED interictal epileptiform discharge, L left, O occipital, P parietal, R right, T temporal. </p>

<p> 
Y. Aghakhani et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 7 (2015) 755-763 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Significant BOLD clusters associated with interictal discharges recorded via simultaneous iEEG-fMRI. (A) Mesial temporal lobe patients. Significant BOLD clusters (p b 0.05, AlphaSim 
correction) were found in all 5 subjects in this group. Two patients had independent, bilateral temporal discharges that were modeled independently of one another providing 7 datasets 
for analysis. A significant cluster is found adjacent to the active intracranial electrode contact (marked by a green circle) in 6/7 analyses. One patient (subject 5), had a large amount of 
susceptibility artifact in the left temporal lobe associated with a large amount of subject motion during data collection. (B) Lateral temporal lobe patients. Significant BOLD clusters 
(p b 0.05, AlphaSim correction) were found in both patients in this group. A significant cluster was found adjacent to the active intracranial electrode contact (green circle) in 1 of 2 anal-
yses. (C) Extratemporal patients. Two patients with extra-temporal lobe epilepsy showed no significant clusters adjacent to the active electrode(s). </p>

<p> 
Y. Aghakhani et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 7 (2015) 755-763 </p>

<p>This could be due to a difference in the functional character of IEDs from 
mesial temporal sources versus neocortical temporal and extratemporal 
discharges (Laufs and Duncan, 2007). The lack of concordance in the 
extra temporal patients may also highlight an inability to fully localize 
the ictal onset zone using clinical data (iEEG VEM, MR, positron emis-
sion tomography, single photon emission computerized tomography, 
etc.) as can occur in focal cortical dysplasia, for example (Cendes, 
2013). Indeed, it is possible that the intracranial EEG electrodes were 
not placed at the center of the irritative zone, but instead were placed 
at the edge. Thus, the site of maximum BOLD activation seen in these 
subjects may in fact be the center of the irritative zone, where electrodes 
were not placed, and possibly, should have been placed. Consistent with 
our findings, the subjects with extratemporal IEDs were not offered sur-
gery since ictal iEEG recordings failed to identify the seizure onset zone. 
As previous work has shown, scalp EEG-fMRI may sometimes provide 
additional data to direct subsequent clinical investigations that can im-
prove patient post-surgical outcomes (Zijlmans et al., 2007). We feel 
that iEEG-fMRI may have a similar function. 
Overall, significant BOLD responses were seen distant from the ac-
tive electrode in 9 of 11 (82%) datasets (Table 2). In fact, the cluster 
with maximum BOLD response was found to be distant rather than ad-
jacent to the active electrode in 8 out of 11 datasets (contralateral in 3). 
We hypothesize that this may be a result of EPI signal loss due to the 
susceptibility artifact associated with the intracranial electrodes. In-
deed, as discussed in our previous work detailing the susceptibility arti-
fact associated with iEEG-fMRI (Boucousis et al., 2012), T2* signal 
intensity can be decreased up to 40% within 1.5 cm of the intracranial 
electrode; at a distance 2.0 cm from the electrode, signal loss is negligi-
ble. This decrease in signal-to-noise ratio may have negatively impacted 
the statistical analyses performed on these data (Parrish et al., 2000), 
leading to an underestimation of the strength of activation immediately 
adjacent to the site of the active intracranial electrode contact. 
Extra-temporal BOLD clusters generated from temporal spikes have 
been previously reported in a scalp EEG-fMRI study of 35 patients with 
lesional and non-lesional mesial and neocortical temporal lobe epilepsy 
(Kobayashi et al., 2006a). Unilateral temporal discharges (mesial and 
neocortical) were associated with BOLD activation in ipsilateral mesial 
temporal structures, ipsilateral basal ganglia, bilateral neocortical tem-
poral regions and in the contralateral temporal lobe. The observed pat-
terns of BOLD activation did not show a correlation with the location of 
the discharges or with the presence or absence of a lesion. Comparison 
of this study to ours is challenging, especially for our mesial temporal 
subjects, since strictly mesial temporal discharges cannot be recorded 
on scalp EEG; instead, these discharges reflect simultaneous involve-
ment of the mesial and neocortical temporal lobes. Despite this, we ob-
served similar widespread patterns of BOLD activation involving mesial 
and neocortical temporal and extra-temporal sites. The small number of 
patients in our study, combined with patient heterogeneity does not 
allow any conclusions or associations to be made between the underly-
ing lesion type or location of discharge with the pattern of BOLD activa-
tion. One notable exception, however, was subject 2, who had non-
lesional independent bitemporal lobe seizures and independent mesial 
temporal lobe discharges. This subject, unlike all the other patients in 
our study, had very focal BOLD signal increases that were maximal 
and adjacent to the active electrode. The reasons for this unique pattern 
of BOLD activation are unclear as there appear to be no clear clinical, 
EEG, or MR imaging characteristics that differentiate this subject from 
the others in our study. 
The functional connectivity of the temporal lobe to other cortical and 
subcortical structures, and the rapid propagation of spikes may explain 
the extra-temporal BOLD responses from temporal lobe spikes seen in 
previous studies (Kobayashi et al., 2006a; Walker et al., 2010) and our 
study. This may also apply to extra-temporal epileptiform discharges, 
explaining the BOLD responses in distant areas. In our study, 3 patients 
had a maximum BOLD response near the location of the active elec-
trode. In the remaining, the maximum BOLD response was distant to </p>

<p>the active electrode even though a significant BOLD response was 
seen at the active electrode. This might suggest that the spike generator 
is distant from the active electrode. However, we feel that this is not the 
case for several reasons: First, the limited intracranial electrode record-
ing field makes it very unlikely that recorded spikes originated from a 
distant active electrode. Second, clinical recordings of seizures con-
firmed that the ictal onset zone included the active electrodes used in 
our iEEG-fMRI analyses (Fig. 1C). Furthermore, three of our subjects 
had resections that included the active electrode contact and they are 
now seizure-free. Lastly, susceptibility artifact is present in the immedi-
ate vicinity of intracranial EEG electrodes (Table 2) which results in at-
tenuation of the BOLD signal in up to 20 mm of cortex adjacent to the 
active electrode(s) (Boucousis et al., 2012; Cunningham et al., 2012). 
This may explain the lack of a maximum BOLD response immediately 
adjacent to the active electrode contact. 
Despite the limitation of signal loss near the electrodes, intracranial 
EEG-fMRI offers a number of advantages over scalp EEG-fMRI and other 
imaging methods. These include the ability to study very focal or low 
amplitude epileptiform discharges not recordable by scalp EEG 
(e.g., IEDs that do not require N10 cm 
2 of cortical surface activity) or dis-</p>

<p>charges originating from deep structures such as mesial temporal struc-
tures or the cingulate gyrus. More importantly, iEEG-fMRI opens a new 
avenue for a better understanding of the hemodynamic response to ep-
ileptiform discharges by affording the opportunity to study very focal 
discharges with great precision or for further mapping the seizure net-
work by providing information that could be complementary to routine 
clinical investigations such as EEG, structural MRI, PET, and SPECT (An 
et al., 2013; Gotman and Pittau, 2011; Laufs and Duncan, 2007; 
Moeller et al., 2009; Thornton et al., 2010; Zijlmans et al., 2007). Al-
though ictal EEG and high frequency oscillations are better markers of 
the epileptogenic zone than IEDs, IEDs still provide useful clinical infor-
mation about the irritative zone, which often includes the ictal onset 
zone. Therefore, iEEG-fMRI may provide a better understanding of the 
irritative zone and consequently the ictal onset zone because it can de-
lineate the irritative zone with greater spatial resolution than iEEG 
alone, which provides limited sampling of the brain. Lastly, intracranial 
EEG-fMRI may allow the study of the hemodynamic response to high 
frequency oscillations. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>iEEG-fMRI is a feasible and low-risk method for assessment of the 
hemodynamic changes associated with very focal interictal epileptiform 
discharges that cannot typically be recorded using scalp EEG-fMRI. We 
also demonstrated high yield and concordance rates of BOLD responses 
to interictal epileptiform discharges of mesial temporal discharges. No-
tably, however, most datasets (8/11) showed maximal BOLD signal at 
locations distant to the most active electrode contact. Intracranial 
EEG-fMRI may provide useful data to help better understand the func-
tional networks generating interictal discharges in focal epilepsy. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Canadian Institutes for Health Re-
search (MOP-136839). CB was supported by a Clinician Researcher 
Training award from Alberta Innovates -Health Solutions. </p>



<p> 
Y. Aghakhani et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 7 (2015) 755-763 </p>



<p> 
Y. Aghakhani et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 7 (2015) 755-763 </p>

</text></tei>