<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4888764" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: Cardiac bioenergetics are known to be abnormal in experimental uremia as exemplified 
by a reduced phosphocreatine (PCr)/adenosine triphosphate (ATP) ratio. However, the progres-
sion of these bioenergetic changes during the development of uremia still requires further study 
and was therefore investigated at baseline, 4 weeks and 8 weeks after partial nephrectomy 
(PNx). 
Methods: A two-stage PNx uremia model in male Wistar rats was used to explore in vivo 
cardiac and skeletal muscles' bioenergetic changes over time. High-energy phosphate nucle-
otides were determined by phosphorus-31 nuclear magnetic resonance ( </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P-NMR) and capillary 
zone electrophoresis. 
Results: </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P-NMR spectroscopy revealed lower PCr/ATP ratios in PNx hearts compared to 
sham (SH)-operated animals 4 weeks after PNx (median values given ± SD, 0.64±0.16 PNx, 
1.13±0.31 SH, P,0.02). However, 8 weeks after PNx, the same ratio was more comparable 
between the two groups (0.84±0.15 PNx, 1.04±0.44 SH, P= not significant), suggestive of an 
adaptive mechanism. When 8-week hearts were prestressed with dobutamine, the PCr/ATP 
ratio was again lower in the PNx group (1.08±0.36 PNx, 1.55±0.38 SH, P,0.02), indicating 
a reduced energy reserve during the progression of uremic heart disease. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P-NMR data were 
confirmed by capillary zone electrophoresis, and the changes in myocardial bioenergetics were 
replicated in the skeletal muscle. 
Conclusion: This study provides evidence of the changes that occur in myocardial energetics 
in experimental uremia and highlights how skeletal muscle bioenergetics mirror those found in 
the cardiac tissue and so might potentially serve as a practical surrogate tissue during clinical 
cardiac NMR investigations. 
Ischemic heart disease, hypertension, and anemia are common in patients with chronic 
kidney disease (CKD), but there is evidence that a number of other important factors 
contribute to the clinical syndrome that has been termed uremic cardiomyopathy. The 
changes seen in the uremic heart have not been shown to be specific to uremia, and 
it is likely that uremic cardiomyopathy is multifactorial and derived from a combina-
tion of features present in the uremic patient. The critical importance of bioenergetics 
during the development of uremic cardiomyopathies and of the signaling pathways 
involved has been highlighted, including the role of mTOR 
1 and insulin resistance 
via Akt. 
2 However, while changing cardiac bioenergetics have been studied in many 
different pathologies, such as left ventricular hypertrophy (LVH), obesity, diabetes, </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of Nephrology and Renovascular Disease 
24 May 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>International Journal of Nephrology and Renovascular Disease 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>130 </p>

<p>chesser et al </p>

<p>heart failure, and myocardial ischemia, 
3-7 the progressive 
bioenergetic changes found in the uremic heart have been 
largely overlooked. 
It is an established practice when assessing myocar-
dial bioenergetics to calculate the phosphocreatine (PCr)/ 
adenosine triphosphate (ATP) ratio. This is because ATP 
production within the myocardium is produced largely 
from intramitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation. This 
in turn is then transported to the sites of energy utilization, 
particularly the myofibrils. This is enabled by the generation 
of PCr that diffuses to the myofibrils where ATP is regener-
ated. Increases in energy demand tend, therefore, to result 
in a decreased PCr/ATP ratio rather than a fall in ATP. Thus, 
the PCr/ATP ratio represents a measure of instantaneous 
cardiac energetic state. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Clinical studies of LVH using phosphorus-31 nuclear 
magnetic resonance ( 
31 P-NMR) have tended to suffer from 
small patient numbers and have shown conflicting results. </p>

<p>8,9 </p>

<p>Both Conway et al 
10 and Neubauer et al 
11 while studying 
patients with aortic stenosis and investigating patients with 
aortic incompetence, respectively, found that any reduc-
tion in the PCr/ATP ratio was related to the degree of heart 
failure. However, a study of patients with mitral regurgita-
tion found significant reductions in the PCr/ATP ratio that 
correlated with both the degree of heart failure and LVH. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Lamb et al 
13 found a reduced PCr/ATP ratio in eleven hyper-
tensive patients with a strong association between ratios and 
the degree of diastolic dysfunction. More recent work using 
a higher magnetic field (3 T instead of 1.5 T) 
7 and a larger 
patient population revealed that the PCr/ATP ratio is greatly 
reduced in patients with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (n=26) 
compared to control subjects (n=37, P,0.0001). In contrast 
to these results, studies of elite athletes with "physiological" 
LVH have shown no reduction in the PCr/ATP ratio compared 
to that of control subjects. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>There are only a few cardiac bioenergetics studies avail-
able about patients with CKD. Tagami et al 
15 studied 14 CKD 
patients treated with maintenance dialysis (hemodialysis 
or continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis) and found 
a decreased cardiac PCr/ATP ratio, particularly in patients 
with a history of heart failure. Perseghin et al 
16 compared 
the left ventricle PCr/ATP ratio in many different patient 
groups and found a significant reduction when comparing 
uremic patients (n=10) with control subjects (n=13). More 
recent work by Patel et al 
17 demonstrated that patients with 
CKD had lower PCr/ATP ratios than hypertensive patients 
with and without LVH. This observation confirms the much 
earlier findings of Raine et al 
18 who found that the uremic rat 
(partial nephrectomy [PNx]) had significantly lower PCr/ATP </p>

<p>ratios in the uremic group compared to sham (SH)-operated 
control animals. This reduction in the PCr/ATP ratio was 
accompanied by reduced contractile indices in the functional 
assessment of the uremic hearts. However, much of this work 
was generated using an ex vivo Langendorff heart preparation 
that limits its clinical significance. 
Most of the clinical and experimental studies conducted 
so far have been cross-sectional in nature, which has ensured 
that the mechanism by which uremia induces cardiac ener-
getic changes over time remains largely unknown. The 
longitudinal study presented here attempts to address this 
lack of knowledge by following the bioenergetic changes 
that occur in an experimental rat model of uremia. The 
hearts were studied in vivo using NMR spectroscopy to 
investigate the time course of changes in the PCr/ATP ratio 
after PNx. The relationship of the bioenergetic parameters 
to the degree of uremia, hemoglobin status, and blood pres-
sure were all studied. Cardiac and skeletal muscles were 
assessed with the aim of identifying if parallel changes 
occurred in both tissues. In addition, confirmation of our 
NMR findings was sought by using a distinct methodology 
(capillary zone electrophoresis [CZE]) to determine PCr 
and ATP concentrations. </p>

<p>Methods 
PNx model of chronic uremia in the rat </p>

<p>All procedures were performed on male Wistar rats after 
obtaining ethical permission from the home office (UK) 
(project license number PPL/5014). Care of the rats was 
carried out in accordance with the Animals (Scientific Pro-
cedures) Act 1986. The animals (150-200 g) were purchased 
from Charles River Ltd (Margate, Kent, UK). A 5/6th PNx 
model was used that has long been established in our labo-
ratory. 
19 The two stages of the procedure were performed 
7 days apart. </p>

<p>anesthesia for PNx </p>

<p>Initially, animals were given an intramuscular injection of 
0.16 mL Hypnorm (fentanyl citrate 0.315 mg/mL and fluani-
sone 10 mg/mL from Janssen-Cilag Ltd, Saunderton, High 
Wycombe, Bucks, UK) into the hind leg. Subsequently, an 
intraperitoneal (ip) injection of 0.1 mL diazepam ( Phoenix 
Pharmaceuticals Ltd, Gloucester, UK) was given. This com-
bination induced deep anesthesia lasting 40-50 minutes, 
sufficient to cover the surgery period. </p>

<p>Blood pressure measurement </p>

<p>Blood pressure was measured by the direct cannulation of the 
femoral artery. Gaseous anesthesia was administered to the </p>

<p>International Journal of Nephrology and Renovascular Disease 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>Myocardial bioenergetic abnormalities in experimental uremia </p>

<p>animals in the form of nitrous oxide (1 L/min) and oxygen 
(1 L/min) with gaseous halothane (2%) until the animal was 
unconscious. Throughout surgery, the same concentrations 
of nitrous oxide and oxygen were given and the concentra-
tion of halothane was varied between 1% and 2% in order 
to maintain deep anesthesia. The animals were allowed to 
recover from surgery, and blood pressure was measured in 
the conscious unrestrained rat at least 24 hours and no later 
than 4 days following line insertion. The blood pressure was 
measured continuously for 10 minutes for all analyses, but 
only the final 5 minutes of recording was used. The mean 
blood pressures were calculated, as the damping effect of 
the tubing affected the values of peak systolic and diastolic 
pressures without affecting the mean pressure. </p>

<p>cardiac NMR studies </p>

<p>Following blood pressure measurement, the rat was given an 
ip injection of sodium thiopentone 30 mg/kg body weight. 
A 1 cm midline incision was made in the front of the neck. 
The trachea was identified within the strap muscles, and 
a silk tie was passed behind it. Using a handheld cutting 
diathermy, a hole was made in the trachea a few millimeters 
across. The tracheostomy tube was inserted into the trachea 
through this hole, tied in position, and connected to a venti-
lator via a length of Portex tubing. The ventilator was set at 
a ventilator frequency of 58/minute, with a variable stroke 
volume. A sample of arterial blood was taken via the femoral 
arterial line and analyzed in a blood gas analyzer. The stroke 
volume of the ventilator was adjusted so that the pH of the 
blood was between 7.3 and 7.5. Supplementary oxygen was 
given as required according to blood gas measurement so 
that the animal was at no stage hypoxic. </p>

<p>Preparation of the heart for NMR </p>

<p>The method was based on that of Beech et al 
20 and has been 
previously described. </p>

<p>Preparation of skeletal muscle for NMR </p>

<p>A skin flap was retracted from the adductor muscles of one 
thigh. The 8 mm surface coil was placed over this muscle, 
separated from it by a layer of plastic film. The animal was 
placed in the center of the magnet. Spectroscopy methods 
for both cardiac and skeletal muscles were identical (see the 
" </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P-NMR spectroscopy measurements" section). </p>

<p>31 P-NMR spectroscopy measurements </p>

<p>The animal was placed in the bore of an Oxford Instruments 
4.7 T horizontal bore superconducting magnet (Oxford Instru-
ments, Abingdon, UK) interfaced with a SISCO 200 imaging </p>

<p>spectrometer (Spectroscopy Imaging Systems Co., Varian 
Medical Systems UK Ltd, Crawley, UK). The surface coil 
was tuned to 81 MHz, and the magnetic field was optimized 
by shimming on the </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>H (water) signal from tissue. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>P-NMR 
spectra were then recorded at 81 MHz. A 50 µs nonselective 
pulse was applied with a pulse interval of 1.96 seconds. Spec-
tra were acquired by signal-averaging 512 pulse repetitions, 
leading to a total acquisition time of 16 minutes. Acquired 
free induction decays were exponentially multiplied with a line 
broadening of 20 Hz. The data were then Fourier transformed, 
and first-order phase correction was carried out manually. </p>

<p>Preparation of hearts for cZe </p>

<p>The hearts used for this study originated from two different 
sets of animals: those with unstressed and those with stressed 
hearts. Unstressed hearts were obtained from rats at 4 weeks 
and 8 weeks following PNx. The heart was exposed and 
freeze clamped using steel tongs precooled in liquid nitrogen. 
Stressed hearts 8 weeks following PNx were obtained 
from animals given intravenous dobutamine as an infusion 
(15 µg⋅kg 
−1 ⋅min 
−1 ) for 20 minutes prior to freeze clamping. 
A blood gas sample was taken to ensure that pH and pO 2 
remained within the desired range. Blood was reserved for 
hemoglobin and creatinine measurement from both stressed 
and unstressed hearts. </p>

<p>extraction of nucleotides from cardiac 
tissue for cZe </p>

<p>Approximately 100 mg of heart tissue was ground with a 
mortar and pestle in liquid nitrogen and accurately weighed 
and extracted in ice-cold 9% perchloric acid (1 mL perchloric 
acid solution per 100 mg tissue). 
21 The sample was vigorously 
shaken, and the homogenate was centrifuged at 16,000× g for 
3 minutes at 4°C. The supernatant was removed and neutral-
ized using potassium hydroxide (5 mol/L). The neutralized 
supernatant was centrifuged to precipitate all the formed 
potassium perchlorate, and the remaining solution was then 
stored at −80°C. Before analysis by CZE, 
21 the sample was 
recentrifuged and any further precipitate excluded. At all 
stages, the volumes of samples were carefully measured and 
recorded. In addition, for each heart, ∼100 mg of freeze-
clamped myocardium was dried using vacuum centrifugation 
to allow calculation of wet weight to dry weight ratios. </p>

<p>cZe </p>

<p>All determinations were performed on a Thermo Separation 
Products [TSP] 2000 Capillary Electrophoresis instru-
ment (TSP, Stone, UK). Data collecting and handling were 
carried out using dedicated software (<rs id="software-0" type="software">Spectacle</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">TSP</rs>). The </p>

<p>International Journal of Nephrology and Renovascular Disease 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>132 </p>

<p>chesser et al </p>

<p>electrophoretic analyses were performed using a fused silica 
capillary (35 cm from injector to detector, 42 cm total length, 
and 50 µm internal diameter) as previously described. 
22 Sam-
ples were injected in hydrodynamic mode for 3 seconds. The 
voltage applied was 17.5 kV, and ultraviolet (UV) detection 
was performed at 254 nm for adenine nucleotides or 200 nm 
for PCr. The capillary was thermostatically maintained at 
25°C. The separation buffer used in all experiments was 
sodium tetraborate (20 mM) and ethylenediaminetetraacetic 
acid (1 mM), adjusted to pH 9.2. The spatial area of each 
peak was calculated by integrating the area of the migration 
time. For each standard, the area under the curve was plotted 
against the concentration injected and calibration curves were 
constructed. From the spatial area of each peak on the electro-
pherogram of each heart sample extract, the concentration of 
each substance was determined from the calibration curves. </p>

<p>statistics </p>

<p>Differences between groups were compared by using either 
a two-tailed parametric test (unpaired Student's t-test) or a 
nonparametric test (two-tailed Mann-Whitney test) where 
appropriate (<rs id="software-1" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">5.04</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">GraphPad Software, Inc.</rs>., 
La Jolla, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Results 
Unstressed hearts </p>

<p>Four-week heart NMR study </p>

<p>Four weeks after completion of surgery in PNx and SH-
operated animals, seven control and six PNx animals yielded 
spectra suitable for analysis. Baseline data for the animals 
included in the analysis are shown in Table 1. PNx rats were 
significantly anemic and hypertensive, with significantly 
raised serum creatinine concentrations. There was no signifi-
cant difference in the final weights of the animals. Figure 1A 
shows the PCr/ATP ratio calculated for each group and 
demonstrates a significant difference in the PCr/ATP ratio 
between control and uremic animals. </p>

<p>eight-week heart NMR study </p>

<p>Eight weeks from completion of surgery, seven control and 
five PNx animals yielded spectra suitable for analysis. Sum-
maries of the animal weights, blood pressures, and blood 
parameters are shown in Table 2. Figure 1B shows the PCr/ 
ATP ratio of each group. Unlike the 4-week data here, there 
was no significant difference in PCr/ATP ratios between 
control and uremic hearts (P= not significant). In addition, 
there was no significant correlation found between PCr/ATP 
ratio and mean arterial blood pressure or with serum urea or 
creatinine concentrations. </p>

<p>Four-week skeletal muscle NMR study </p>

<p>Eight control and seven PNx animals yielded spectra suit-
able for analysis. Reassuringly, intracellular pH was not 
significantly different as measured by NMR when comparing 
control and PNx groups (Table 3), as it could not be mea-
sured reliably in our in vivo cardiac study. PCr/ATP ratios 
were significantly lower in the skeletal muscle of the uremic 
group compared to that of the control group (Figure 1C), 
independent of intracellular pH. </p>

<p>eight-week skeletal muscle NMR study </p>

<p>Five control and eight uremic animals yielded spectra suitable 
for analysis (Table 4). There was no significant difference </p>

<p>Table 1 Four-week heart NMR study </p>

<p>Control 
Uremic 
P </p>

<p>Number of animals 
7 
6 
Days following PNx/sham operation 
29.3±4.9 
30.0±4.1 
Ns 
Weight (g) 
350.0±54.0 318.7±82.5 Ns 
Mean arterial blood pressure (mmhg) 129.7±11.1 150.1±20.6 0.02 
hemoglobin (g/dl) 
11.5±1.9 
8.7±1.2 
0.04 
Urea (mmol/l) 
6.24±0.88 16.35±0.92 ,0.01 
creatinine (µmol/l) 
50.6±15.7 175±81.3 
,0.01 </p>

<p>Notes: Baseline data for animals studied by heart NMR 4 weeks post-PNx or sham 
operation. Values given are mean ± sD, and statistical analysis was performed by 
unpaired student's t-test. 
Abbreviations: NMR, nuclear magnetic resonance; PNx, partial nephrectomy; 
NS, not significant. </p>

<p>Table 2 eight-week heart NMR study </p>

<p>Control 
Uremic 
P </p>

<p>Number of animals 
7 
5 
Days following PNx/sham operation 
60.4±5.7 
61.8±1.8 
Ns 
Weight (g) 
370.0±40.6 367.2±21.9 Ns 
Mean arterial blood pressure (mmhg) 124.7±5.6 149.2±8.9 ,0.01 
hemoglobin (g/dl) 
12.9±3.0 
9.7±1.8 
,0.01 
Urea (mmol/l) 
7.06±0.97 15.03±2.15 ,0.01 
creatinine (µmol/l) 
46.8±8.1 
91.5±23.5 ,0.01 </p>

<p>Notes: Baseline data for animals studied by heart NMR 8 weeks post-PNx. Values 
given are mean ± sD, and statistical analysis was performed by unpaired student's 
t-test. 
Abbreviations: NMR, nuclear magnetic resonance; PNx, partial nephrectomy; Ns, 
not significant. </p>

<p>Table 3 Four-week skeletal muscle NMR study </p>

<p>Control Uremic 
P </p>

<p>Number of animals 
8 
7 
animal weight (g) 
335±48 
299±45 
Ns 
Mean arterial blood pressure (mmhg) 110.2±8.1 139.8±10.0 ,0.01 
hemoglobin (g/dl) 
12.6±0.4 
8.9±1.1 
,0.01 
creatinine (µmol/l) 
50.6±15.7 175±81.3 
,0.01 
Intracellular ph 
7.12±0.30 7.17±0.10 
Ns </p>

<p>Notes: Four-week baseline data for the NMR study using rat skeletal muscle. Values 
given are mean ± sD, and statistical analysis was performed by unpaired student's 
t-test. 
Abbreviations: NMR, nuclear magnetic resonance; NS, not significant. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nephrology and Renovascular Disease 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>133 </p>

<p>Myocardial bioenergetic abnormalities in experimental uremia </p>

<p>in PCr/ATP ratios (Figure 1D, two-tailed Mann-Whitney 
test) when comparing control to PNx animals, similar to the 
findings shown in the myocardial studies at this time point 
(Figure 1B, two-tailed Mann-Whitney test). </p>

<p>eight-week cZe study </p>

<p>Eight pairs of hearts were suitable for study. CZE measure-
ments showed no significant differences in the concentra-
tions of PCr, ATP, adenosine diphosphate, or adenosine </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.02 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>Heart PCr/ATP ratio </p>

<p>0 
Control 
Uremic </p>

<p>4-week study (NMR, unstressed) </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>P=NS </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>Heart PCr/ATP ratio </p>

<p>0 
Control 
Uremic </p>

<p>8-week study (NMR, unstressed) </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.02 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>4.5 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 
1.5 
1 </p>

<p>Skeletal muscle PCr/ATP ratio </p>

<p>0 
Control 
Uremic 
4-week study (NMR, unstressed) </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>4.5 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Skeletal muscle PCr/ATP ratio </p>

<p>0 
Control 
Uremic </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>P=NS </p>

<p>E 2 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>1.8 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>Heart PCr/ATP ratio </p>

<p>0 
Control </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>P=NS </p>

<p>Uremic 
8-week study (CZE, unstressed) </p>

<p>8-week study (NMR, unstressed) </p>

<p>Figure 1 Pcr/aTP ratios in 4 weeks and 8 weeks post-PNx in unstressed rats. 
Notes: After 4 weeks of uremia, NMR revealed that PCr/ATP ratios were significantly reduced in both cardiac and skeletal muscles (A and C). At 8 weeks, no significant 
difference in the ratio was seen (B and D). CZE confirmed the cardiac NMR findings at 8 weeks (E). Two-tailed Mann-Whitney analysis with median values ± sD is 
presented. 
Abbreviations: Pcr, phosphocreatine; aTP, adenosine triphosphate; PNx, partial nephrectomy; NMR, nuclear magnetic resonance; cZe, capillary zone electrophoresis; 
NS, not significant. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nephrology and Renovascular Disease 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>134 </p>

<p>chesser et al </p>

<p>monophosphate (Table 5) when comparing control to uremic 
hearts. In addition, PCr/ATP ratios were not significantly 
different between control and uremic hearts (Figure 1E, 
two-tailed Mann-Whitney test). </p>

<p>stressed hearts (dobutamine treated) </p>

<p>eight-week stressed heart NMR study </p>

<p>Five pairs of animals yielded spectra suitable for analysis 
(Table 6). In baseline conditions, there was no significant dif-
ference between the two groups' PCr/ATP ratios. When the 
spectra were reacquired during the infusion of intravenous 
dobutamine, PCr/ATP ratios fell significantly in the uremic 
group ( P,0.05, two-tailed Mann-Whitney test), while there 
was no significant change in the PCr/ATP ratios between the 
control groups (see control groups unstressed versus stressed in 
Figure 2A and B). However, there were significant reductions 
in PCr/ATP ratios in the stressed hearts from uremic animals 
compared to those from SH-operated animals (Figure 2B). </p>

<p>eight-week stressed heart cZe study </p>

<p>The hearts were freeze clamped following an intravenous 
infusion of dobutamine (15 µg⋅kg </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>⋅min 
−1 for 20 minutes prior </p>

<p>to freeze clamping). Experiments were conducted 8 weeks 
following PNx (Table 7). While a comparison of ATP and 
PCr concentrations did not reach statistical significance, PCr/ 
ATP ratios were significantly reduced in the uremic group 
compared to those in control animals (P,0.05, two-tailed 
Mann-Whitney test, Figure 2C). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>These experiments have demonstrated a reduction in the PCr/ 
ATP ratio in uremic rat hearts in vivo 4 weeks after PNx. 
However, identical experiments conducted 8 weeks following 
PNx showed no reduction in the PCr/ATP ratio. A possible 
reason for this finding is that the development of adaptive 
and compensatory myocardial changes formed over time is 
masking bioenergetic abnormalities at rest. This hypothesis is 
supported by the evidence that the stressor agent dobutamine 
was able to reveal changes in the PCr/ATP at 8 weeks that 
were not seen when the hearts were unstressed (comparing 
Figure 2A and B). Tellingly, similar bioenergetic changes 
were observed when studying skeletal muscle, and this raises </p>

<p>Table 4 eight-week skeletal muscle NMR study </p>

<p>Control 
Uremic 
P </p>

<p>Number of animals 
5 
8 
animal weight (g) 
369±35 
374±20.5 
Ns 
Mean arterial blood pressure (mmhg) 118.1±10.2 143.3±12.7 0.03 
hemoglobin (g/dl) 
12.4±0.2 
8.8±2.4 
,0.01 
creatinine (µmol/l) 
43.7±2.1 
102.0±27.3 ,0.01 
Intracellular ph 
7.15±0.13 7.19±0.13 Ns </p>

<p>Notes: eight-week baseline data for the NMR study using rat skeletal muscle. 
Values given are mean ± sD, and statistical analysis was performed by unpaired 
student's t-test. 
Abbreviations: NMR, nuclear magnetic resonance; NS, not significant. </p>

<p>Table 5 eight-week cZe study in hearts </p>

<p>Control 
Uremic 
P </p>

<p>Number of animals 
8 
8 
Mean arterial blood pressure (mmhg) 141±15 
174±22 
,0.01 
hemoglobin (g/dl) 
15.0±2.7 
11.3±3.2 
0.03 </p>

<p>creatinine (µmol/l) 
45.5±10.0 
189.8±80.2 ,0.01 
heart wet wt/dry wt ratio 
24.3%±2.2% 26.7%±5.9% Ns 
Pcr (nmol/mg heart tissue) 
13.8±6.1 
14.0±1.78 
Ns 
aTP (nmol/mg heart tissue) 
12.0±2.1 
13.1±3.2 
Ns 
aDP (nmol/mg heart tissue) 
7.94±1.14 
7.80±2.36 
Ns 
aMP (nmol/mg heart tissue) 
3.15±1.55 
2.51±1.30 
Ns </p>

<p>Notes: cZe measurements using unstressed hearts at 8 weeks showing baseline 
animal data and the concentrations of high-energy phosphate-containing molecules. 
Values given are mean ± sD, and statistical analysis was performed by unpaired 
student's t-test. 
Abbreviations: CZE, capillary zone electrophoresis; wt, weight; NS, not significant; 
Pcr, phosphocreatine; aTP, adenosine triphosphate; aDP, adenosine diphosphate; 
aMP, adenosine monophosphate. </p>

<p>Table 6 eight-week stressed heart NMR study </p>

<p>Control 
Uremic 
P </p>

<p>Number of animals 
5 
5 
animal weight (g) 
442±55 
409±41 
Ns 
Mean arterial blood pressure (mmhg) 
108±6 
152±32 
0.02 
hemoglobin (g/dl) 
12.5±0.7 
10.1±2.0 
0.03 
Urea (mmol/l) 
6.4±0.7 
16.7±8.0 
0.04 </p>

<p>creatinine (µmol/l) 
61±2 
154±89 
0.04 </p>

<p>Notes: In vivo heart stress NMR experiments showing post-dobutamine animal 
data. Values given are mean ± sD, and statistical analysis was performed by unpaired 
student's t-test. 
Abbreviations: NMR, nuclear magnetic resonance; NS, not significant. </p>

<p>Table 7 eight-week stressed heart cZe study </p>

<p>Control 
Uremic 
P </p>

<p>Number of animals 
7 
9 
animal weight (g) 
405±63 
383±59 
Ns 
Mean arterial blood pressure (mmhg) 111±6 
151±26 
,0.01 
hemoglobin (g/dl) 
12.6±1.2 
9.2±2.9 
0.01 
Urea (mmol/l) 
6.5±0.7 
15.5±5.5 
,0.01 
creatinine (µmol/l) 
63.1±2.7 
138.2±58.8 ,0.01 
heart wet wt/dry wt ratio 
21.2%±3.2% 23.8%±4.1% Ns 
Pcr (nmol/mg heart tissue) 
13.8±7.5 
12.6±4.5 
Ns 
aTP (nmol/mg heart tissue) 
19.8±6.2 
25.8±7.1 
Ns 
aDP (nmol/mg heart tissue) 
6.6±2.2 
6.4±1.8 
Ns 
aMP (nmol/mg heart tissue) 
2.7±1.8 
1.4±0.6 
Ns </p>

<p>Notes: cZe experiments using stressed hearts at 8 weeks showing baseline animal 
data and concentrations of high-energy phosphate-containing molecules. Values 
given are mean ± sD, and statistical analysis is performed by unpaired student's 
t-test. 
Abbreviations: CZE, capillary zone electrophoresis; wt, weight; NS, not significant; 
Pcr, phosphocreatine; aTP, adenosine triphosphate; aDP, adenosine diphosphate; 
aMP, adenosine monophosphate. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nephrology and Renovascular Disease 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>135 </p>

<p>Myocardial bioenergetic abnormalities in experimental uremia </p>

<p>the possibility of using skeletal muscle bioenergetics as a 
surrogate tissue for the heart, as determination of skeletal 
muscle bioenergetics is a much easier and less invasive pro-
cedure to perform than cardiac measurement. 
To the best of our knowledge, there are no reports in 
the literature of in vivo studies of myocardial bioenergetics 
measured by NMR in animal models of uremia at different 
time points or in the presence and absence of dobutamine-
induced stress. However, Seymour's group in a study of myo-
cardial substrate utilization using an in vivo uremic model 
have determined altered cardiac bioenergetics, but only at a 
single time point. 
23,24 Interesting recent work from the same 
group has revealed how mitochondrial respiration in the 
uremic heart is chronically uncoupled. 
25 Raine et al 
18 studied 
the hearts of rats 3 weeks following PNx using an isolated 
working heart model. Here they demonstrated reduced PCr/ 
ATP ratios, similar in pattern to the results obtained in these 
experiments 4 weeks post-PNx in vivo. 
There are many possible causes for a diminished PCr/ 
ATP ratio in the heart. In normal circumstances, large 
changes in energy expenditure produce only modest changes 
in the PCr/ATP ratio as a result of the tight regulation of 
oxidative phosphorylation. 
26 Oxygen limitation due to cell 
metabolism may occur because of the well-recognized 
capillary rarefaction. Anemia may exacerbate this effect, in 
addition to any increase in catecholamine levels or myocyte 
sensitivity to catecholamines 
5,27,28 with or without changes 
in intracellular changes in calcium concentration and sensi-
tivity. Catecholamine stress has also been shown to reduce 
the PCr/ATP ratio in obese subjects but not in subjects of 
normal weight. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Another possible cause of abnormal myocardial bioener-
getics in uremia may be due to altered substrate utilization. 
Previous studies in animals have shown that in LVH, an 
increase in the utilization of glucose in preference to free 
fatty acids occurs. 
29 Christe and Rodgers studied the isolated 
perfused heart of the spontaneously hypertensive rat with 
LVH and hypertension. 
30 They found enhanced glucose oxi-
dation and suppressed fatty acid oxidation in the spontane-
ously hypertensive rat compared to normotensive controls. 
Similar findings of depressed fatty acid oxidation 
31,32 and 
enhanced glycolytic capacity 
33 have been observed in other 
forms of LVH. It is possible that in the uremic environment, 
the substrate specificity is different from normal hearts 
early on during the course of uremia, and this may explain 
the decreased PCr/ATP ratio seen at 4 weeks post-PNx. The 
change in substrate utilization may take some time to become 
fully effective, and this is a possible explanation for the "nor-
malization" of PCr/ATP ratios seen in the uremic hearts at 
8 weeks: the adaptive mechanism has become functional. 
A loss of total creatine in the heart, as seen in some non-
uremic models of LVH, 
34 might also lead to a reduction in PCr 
concentration and a reduction in PCr/ATP ratio via the creatine 
kinase system. Total creatine was not measured in these experi-
ments, but it is noteworthy that Raine et al 
18 did not find any 
reduction in total creatine in the uremic heart despite finding 
significant reductions in PCr/ATP ratios in the isolated perfused 
heart. Reduced total creatine therefore appears unlikely to be 
the cause of the abnormalities seen in the uremic heart. 
Uremic skeletal muscle showed similar bioenergetic 
changes as cardiac tissue. Uremic animal skeletal muscle 
was studied 4 weeks after PNx and found to have reduced </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>P=NS </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Heart PCr/ATP ratio </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>0 
Control </p>

<p>8-week study (NMR, prestressed) </p>

<p>Uremic </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.02 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Heart PCr/ATP ratio </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>0 
Control </p>

<p>8-week study (NMR, stressed) </p>

<p>Uremic </p>

<p>C 0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 </p>

<p>Heart PCr/ATP ratio </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>8-week study (CZE, stressed) </p>

<p>Uremic </p>

<p>Figure 2 Pcr/aTP ratios 8 weeks post-PNx in rats with dobutamine stress (15 µg⋅kg 
−1 ⋅min 
−1 for 20 minutes prior to freeze clamping). 
Notes: Prior to dobutamine addition, as in the unstressed study, no significant difference in the PCr/ATP ratio was seen (A). however, dobutamine stress showed 
significant reductions in PCr/ATP ratios in the heart from uremic animals compared to sham-operated animals by both NMR (B) and cZe (C) determinations. Two-tailed 
Mann-Whitney analysis with median values ± sD is presented. 
Abbreviations: Pcr, phosphocreatine; aTP, adenosine triphosphate; PNx, partial nephrectomy; NMR, nuclear magnetic resonance; cZe, capillary zone electrophoresis. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nephrology and Renovascular Disease 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>136 </p>

<p>chesser et al </p>

<p>PCr/ATP ratios compared to control skeletal muscle. Rats 
studied 8 weeks post-PNx had no difference in their muscle 
PCr/ATP ratios when compared to SH-operated control 
animals. These findings therefore closely mirror the cardiac 
data. Previous studies of skeletal muscle bioenergetics in 
uremia have produced conflicting results. One study of calf 
muscle in dialysis patients using NMR found no differences 
in PCr, ATP, or inorganic phosphate levels at rest, but when 
the muscle was exercised, a reduction in PCr and ATP con-
centrations was seen in uremic patients. 
35 Recovery of PCr 
concentrations was slower in the dialysis group, suggesting 
a defect in oxidative metabolism in the uremic muscle. </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>Another study provides support for this conclusion, with 
a decreased calculated phosphorylation potential in the 
skeletal muscle of dialysis patients compared to healthy 
control subjects. </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>The results described here suggest that skeletal muscle 
and cardiac muscle may behave in a similar manner in CKD. 
Skeletal muscle is simpler to study in vivo than cardiac 
muscle, and results obtained in skeletal muscle may therefore 
prove to extend to cardiac muscle. Moreover, intracellular pH 
in skeletal muscle can be measured much more easily than in 
cardiac muscle. Skeletal muscle intracellular pH in uremic and 
control groups was found to be similar, consistent with other 
published findings, 
35 which permits us to rule out acid/base 
changes being the cause of the abnormal bioenergetics. 
The work presented here is not without its limitations. 
More definitive evidence would have been provided in terms 
of bioenergetics reserve if we had conducted dobutamine 
stress in the heart tissue at 4 weeks and further confirmation 
of the surrogate nature of skeletal muscle had we performed 
a stress test in that tissue at 8 weeks. However, this was only 
appreciated after the study was complete. Nevertheless, we 
believe that the evidence shown here in this in vivo study 
provides important data of bioenergetics in a realistic setting 
of uremia, with no restriction of substrate or neurohumoral 
mechanisms such as those found in ex vivo studies. In addi-
tion, our in vivo NMR data are supported by our chromato-
graphic study using CZE. This suggests that the changes 
in bioenergetics measured by NMR in this study do reflect 
genuine changes in high-energy phosphates in vivo and 
furthermore give credence to the possibility of using skeletal 
muscle as a useful surrogate marker for cardiac tissue in 
clinical subjects where required. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>This study provides evidence of the impaired myocardial 
bioenergetics in experimental uremia and that skeletal </p>

<p>muscle bioenergetics changes mirror those seen in the 
cardiac tissue. Therefore, skeletal muscle could potentially 
be used as a surrogate tissue during clinical cardiac NMR 
studies. This work has also highlighted the utility of cat-
echolaminergic stress induced by dobutamine being able 
to unmask the changes in energetics that had resulted from 
experimental uremia. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors would like to acknowledge the help given by 
Dr Anne-Marie Seymour in initiating this project. AMSC was 
supported by a British Heart Foundation's Junior Fellowship 
grant during this study. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>International Journal of Nephrology and Renovascular Disease </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-nephrology-and-renovascular-disease-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of Nephrology and Renovascular Disease is 
an international, peer-reviewed open-access journal focusing on the 
pathophysiology of the kidney and vascular supply. Epidemiology, screen-
ing, diagnosis, and treatment interventions are covered as well as basic 
science, biochemical and immunological studies. The journal welcomes </p>

<p>original research, clinical studies, reviews &amp; evaluations, expert opinion and 
commentary, case reports and extended reports. The manuscript manage-
ment system is completely online and includes a very quick and fair peer-
review system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/ 
testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nephrology and Renovascular Disease 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>