<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4535552" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Geriatric patients with femoral neck fracture (FNF) have unacceptably high rates 
of postoperative complications and mortality. The purpose of this study was to compare the 
effects of epidural anesthesia versus peripheral nerve block (PNB) on postoperative outcomes 
in elderly Chinese patients with FNF. 
Methods: This retrospective study explored mortality and postoperative complications in 
geriatric patients with FNF who underwent epidural anesthesia or PNB at the Chinese People's 
Liberation Army General Hospital from January 2008 to December 2012. The electronic database 
at the Chinese People's Liberation Army General Hospital includes discharge records for all 
patients treated in the hospital. Information on patient demographics, preoperative comorbidity, 
postoperative complications, type of anesthesia used, and in-hospital, 30-day, and 1-year 
mortality after surgery was obtained from this database. 
Results: Two hundred and fifty-eight patients were identified for analysis. The mean patient 
age was 79.7 years, and 71.7% of the patients were women. In-hospital, 30-day, and 1-year 
postoperative mortality was 4.3%, 12.4%, and 22.9%, respectively, and no differences in 
mortality or cardiovascular complications were found between patients who received epidural 
anesthesia and those who received PNB. More patients with dementia or delirium were given 
PNB. No statistically significant differences were found between groups for other comorbidities 
or intraoperative parameters. The most common complications were acute cardiovascular events 
(23.6%), electrolyte disturbances (20.9%), and hypoxemia (18.2%). Patients who received PNB 
had more postoperative delirium (P=0.027). Postoperative acute respiratory events were more 
common (P=0.048) and postoperative stroke was less common (P=0.018) in the PNB group. 
There were fewer admissions to intensive care (P=0.024) in the epidural anesthesia group. Key 
factors with a negative influence on mortality were acute cardiovascular events, dementia, male 
sex, age, American Society of Anesthesiologists score, acute respiratory events, intensive care 
admission, and comorbidities. 
Conclusion: PNB was not associated with lower mortality or lower cardiovascular complica-
tion rates when compared with epidural anesthesia in elderly patients with FNF. 
Femoral neck fractures (FNFs) are common injuries in geriatric patients, who are 
usually frail and very elderly, with more than 30% being 85 years of age or older. </p>

<p>1,2   Furthermore, it is well known that these injuries are accompanied by high mortal-
ity rates, ranging from 11% to 36% within the 1st year after surgery, 
3,4 so swift and </p>

<p>Correspondence: Junle liu 
Department of Anesthesiology, Chinese 
People's liberation Army 105 hospital, 
Changjiang West road 424th, hefei 
230031, People's republic of China 
Tel +86 551 6596 6530 
email analgesistliu@sina.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Clinical Interventions in Aging 
7 August 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Jin et al </p>

<p>conclusive recommendations are needed to address this 
public health problem. </p>

<p>5   Currently, three surgical treat ment options are available 
for management of FNF, ie, internal fixation, hemiarthro-
plasty, and total hip arthroplasty. The type of surgery offered 
is determined by the degree of fracture, the patient's age, 
functional demands, and the risk profile, such as physical 
fitness and cognitive function. </p>

<p>6,7   The choice of anesthesia for this type of surgery is still a mat-
ter of ongoing debate. Regional anesthesia including epidural 
anesthesia, peripheral nerve block (PNB), and general anesthe-
sia are all suitable for surgery in frail patients. The first paper 
addressing type of anesthesia in these patients was published 
in 1936 by Nygaard. Since then, there have been many trials, 
observational studies, and systematic reviews on this subject. </p>

<p>8-10   However, few papers have compared the postoperative out-
comes of epidural anesthesia and PNB in older patients. </p>

<p>11,12   A heterogeneous mix of fracture types, surgery, and 
anesthesia styles can affect the prognosis of these aged 
patients. Therefore, we decided to investigate a population 
with a more homogeneous fracture pattern, ie, FNF, and 
a homogeneous surgery type, ie, hemiarthroplasty, at our 
hospital to compare the effects of epidural anesthesia and 
PNB. The primary outcome was in-hospital, 30-day, and 
1-year mortality after surgery. The secondary outcomes were 
postoperative complications. This retrospective study offered 
unique strength focusing on investigation of anesthetic fac-
tors influencing mortality and postoperative complications 
of elderly patients with FNF. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Data source </p>

<p>This single-center retrospective study was conducted to 
explore mortality and postoperative complications in elderly 
patients undergoing urgent hemiarthroplasty for FNF under 
epidural anesthesia or PNB at the Chinese People's Liberation 
Army General Hospital from January 2008 to December 2012. 
Ethical consent was obtained from the Chinese People's Lib-
eration Army General Hospital. The data were anonymized 
before analysis. Informed consent was waived. The electronic 
database at the Chinese People's Liberation Army General 
Hospital includes discharge records for all patients treated in 
the hospital. Information on patient demographics, preopera-
tive comorbidities, postoperative complications, and type of 
anesthesia were retrieved from the database by MG and GW. 
In-hospital, 30-day, and 1-year postoperative mortality rates 
were recorded in a telephone interview by JJ. 
To create a cohort of patients aged 65 years or older, 
we identified all discharges with a principal or secondary </p>

<p>diagnosis of FNF, including pathological fractures and 
trauma. To restrict our sample, we excluded patients 
diagnosed with multiple trauma, those who underwent a 
secondary surgical procedure during their hospital stay, 
those for whom a different type of surgery was performed, 
ie, internal fixation or total hip arthroplasty, and those who 
had no surgery. Of note, patients with failed epidural anes-
thesia or PNB who were subsequently converted to general 
anesthesia were also excluded from the analysis. Records for 
the remaining 258 subjects who received hemiarthroplasty 
were analyzed further (Figure 1). 
First, we evaluated in-hospital mortality because the 
immediate postoperative period is more likely to reflect 
anesthesia-related complications. Thirty-day mortality was 
included in the primary outcome because it is not subject to 
detection bias and because 30 days following surgery is the 
standard time point for assessing perioperative outcome. 
One-year mortality is usually considered as important 
observation time. 
All patients were given low molecular weight heparin 
calcium (Fraxiparine 
® , GlaxoSmithKline) preoperatively 
and for at least 10 days postoperatively, interrupted only 
for the 24 hours before surgery to 12 hours after surgery. 
Ceftriaxone sodium (Rocephin 
® , Roche) 1.0 g was given 
30 minutes preoperatively followed by two additional doses 
during the first 72 hours postoperatively. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>The primary study outcome was in-hospital, 30-day, and 
1-year mortality after surgery. The second outcomes 
were postoperative complications. General complica-
tions included the following: acute cardiovascular events, 
acute respiratory events, stroke, delirium, renal disease, 
electrolyte disturbances, anemia, hypoxemia, deep wound 
infection, and deep vein thrombosis/pulmonary embo-
lism. We also collected data on waiting time to operation, 
duration of surgery, length of postoperative hospital stay, 
admission to intensive care, hospital costs, blood loss, and 
transfusion. 
For continuous parameters, Student's t-tests are used to 
test for differences between groups, and for discontinuous 
parameters, chi-square statistics are used to detect differ-
ences between groups. Univariate and multivariate Cox 
regression analysis of all variables was used for 30-day and 
1-year mortality after surgery. The significance level was set 
at 5% (P,0.05) for all statistical tests. Data were coded and 
stored in <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">Excel</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">2007</rs> and analyzed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">17.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>, Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1225 </p>

<p>Postoperative outcomes in elderly patients </p>

<p>Figure 1 Flow chart showing patient enrolment and analysis. 
Abbreviations: eA, epidural anesthesia; PnB, peripheral nerve block; FnF, femoral neck fracture. </p>

<p>• 
• 
• </p>

<p>Results 
Demographics </p>

<p>Over the 5-year study period, 258 elderly patients of mean 
age 79.7 (range 65-109) years underwent hemiarthroplasty 
and were included for our analysis. The Student's t-test or </p>

<p>chi-square test was used to compare patient characteristics 
between the epidural anesthesia group and the PNB group 
(Table 1). Women (n=185, 71.7%) outnumbered their male 
counterparts. Waiting time to surgery, length of postopera-
tive hospital stay, admission to intensive care, hospital costs, </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1226 </p>

<p>Jin et al </p>

<p>duration of surgery, intraoperative fluids required, blood loss, 
and transfusion in each of the two groups are presented in 
Table 2. No statistically significant differences were found, 
except for admission to intensive care, which was more 
common in the PNB group (χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=5.695; P=0.024). Moreover, 
patients admitted to intensive care incurred more hospital 
costs, and their postoperative hospital stay was longer. Blood 
loss in the epidural anesthesia group was less than in the PNB 
group (382±170 mL versus 422±194 mL, respectively), but 
the difference was not statistically significant (95% CI (-5.47, 
-85.60); P=0.084). There were no significant differences in 
waiting time to operation, length of postoperative hospital 
stay, hospital costs, duration of surgery, intraoperative fluids 
required, and blood transfusion between the two groups. </p>

<p>Mortality </p>

<p>In-hospital, 30-day, and 1-year mortality was 4.3%, 12.4%, 
and 22.9%, respectively. In-hospital mortality was slightly </p>

<p>lower at 5.5% (8/145) in the PNB group when compared with 
2.7% (3/113) in the epidural anesthesia group. However, this 
difference was not statistically significant (P=0.413, Fisher's 
Exact test). One-year mortality was 24.1% (35/145) in the 
PNB group and 21.2% (24/113) in the epidural anesthesia 
group (χ 
2 =0.30; P=0.582). </p>

<p>Preoperative comorbidities </p>

<p>Seventy-two patients (27.9%) in our study had no preopera-
tive comorbidity, while 84 (32.6%) had one, 61 (23.6%) had 
two, and 41 (15.9%) had three or more comorbidities. Table 3 
lists the comorbidities recorded and their incidence in the two 
groups. The most common comorbidities were cardiovascular 
disease (78, 30.2%; One patient had a myocardial infarc-
tion after admission in each group), diabetes (60, 23.3%), 
respiratory disease (60, 23.3%), and stroke (56, 21.7%); 
one patient suffered a stroke after admission in each group. 
Dementia was more common in the PNB group than in the </p>

<p>Table 1 Comparison of demographics for 258 elderly patients receiving epidural anesthesia or PnB </p>

<p>Total 
(n=258) </p>

<p>EA group 
(n=113) </p>

<p>PNB group 
(n=145) </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P-value 
95% CI </p>

<p>Male sex* 
73 (28.3%) 
28 (24.8%) 
45 (31.0%) 
1.225 
0.330 
Age (years) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>79.7±6.8 
78.8±6.5 
80.1±7.0 
0.129 
-2.980, -0.385 
Weight (kg) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>58.8±11.7 
58.9±10.9 
58.8±12.3 
0.921 
-3.032, -2.741 
height (cm) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>161.9±7.5 
161.4±7.3 
162.2±7.7 
0.399 
-1.065, -2.665 
BMI (kg/m 
2 )* 
22.27±3.54 
22.57±3.65 
22.22±3.75 
0.448 
-1.269, -0.563 
surgical site (left)* 
133 (51.6%) 
61 (54.0%) 
72 (49.7%) 
0.476 
0.490 
AsA status* 
1.557 
0.459 
II 
97 (37.6%) 
45 (39.8%) 
52 (35.9%) 
III 
116 (45.0%) 
52 (46.0%) 
64 (44.1%) 
$IV 
45 (17.4%) 
16 (14.2%) 
29 (20.0%) </p>

<p>Notes: Data are presented as the number (percentage), ratio, or mean ± standard deviation. *Chi-square test; 
 † two-tailed student's t-test. 
Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; CI, confidence interval; EA, epidural anesthesia; ASA, American Society of Anesthesiologists; PNB, peripheral nerve block. </p>

<p>Table 2 Intraoperative and postoperative data for 258 elderly patients receiving epidural anesthesia or PnB </p>

<p>Total 
(n=258) </p>

<p>EA group 
(n=113) </p>

<p>PNB group 
(n=145) </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P-value 
95% CI </p>

<p>Waiting time to operation (days) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>7.04±3.98 
6.76±3.81 
7.26±4.11 
0.317 
-0.482, -1.484 
Postoperative lOs (days) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>9.55±9.45 
9.95±10.55 
9.25±8.53 
0.557 
-3.038, -1.641 
ICU admission* 
49 (14.8%) 
11 (9.7%) 
29 (20%) 
5.109 
0.024 
Costs (10 
3 rMB) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>26.9±23.6 
24.4±20.4 
28.8±25.7 
0.137 
-0.141, -1.022 
Duration of surgery (minutes) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>103±30 
100±27 
104±33 
0.275 
-3.332, -11.649 
Intraoperative fluids (mL) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>708±198 
691±190 
723±200 
0.192 
-16.23, -80.48 
Blood loss (ml) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>404±185 
382±170 
422±194 
0.084 
-5.474, -85.60 
Intraoperatively 
240±135 
227±127 
250±140 
0.169 
-9.927, -56.496 
Postoperatively 
164±111 
155±103 
172±118 
0.231 
-10.719, -44.276 
Blood transfusion (sAgM) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Blood plasma 
247±257 
228±298 
260±222 
0.319 
-31.376, -95.86 
red blood cells 
4.05±2.90 
4.19±3.21 
3.94±2.64 
0.501 
-0.963, -0.472 </p>

<p>Notes: Data are presented as number (percentage), or ratio or mean ± standard deviation. *Chi-square; 
 † two-tailed student's t-test. 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; EA, epidural anesthesia; PNB, peripheral nerve block; ICU, intensive care unit; LOS, length of stay; SAGM, modified saline-adenine-
glucose. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1227 </p>

<p>Postoperative outcomes in elderly patients </p>

<p>epidural anesthesia group (χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=5.11; P=0.025). The proportion 
of patients with preoperative delirium was high in this frail 
patient group, being ten (8.8%) in the epidural anesthesia 
group and 23 (15.9%) in the PNB group (χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=4.198; P=0.041). 
There were no statistically significant differences in other 
preoperative parameters between the two groups (Table 3). </p>

<p>Postoperative complications </p>

<p>Seventy-seven patients (29.8%) have one postoperative com-
plication, 62 (24.0%) had two complications, and 22 (8.5%) 
had three or more complications. Table 3 shows the incidence 
of postoperative complications, the most common of which </p>

<p>were acute cardiovascular events (61, 23.6%), electrolyte 
disturbances (54, 20.9%), and hypoxemia (47, 18.2%). The 
incidence of acute respiratory events was higher in the PNB 
group (χ 
2 =3.91; P=0.048), whereas postoperative stroke 
was significantly more common in the epidural anesthesia 
group (χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=5.64; P=0.018). Six patients (5.3%) in the epidural 
anesthesia group and six (4.1%) in the PNB group developed 
deep vein thrombosis or pulmonary embolism despite receiv-
ing prophylactic low molecular weight heparin. Thirty-two 
(22.1%) patients with postoperative delirium in PNB group 
was significant higher than 13 (11.5%) in epidural anesthesia 
group (χ 
2 =4.922; P=0.027). </p>

<p>Table 3 Preoperative comorbidity, postoperative complications and mortality of 258 elderly patients in eA and PnB groups </p>

<p>Total (n=258) 
EA group (n=113) 
PNB group (n=145) 
χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Preoperative comorbidities 
Cardiovascular disease 
78 (30.2%) 
30 (26.5%) 
48 (33.1%) 
1.294 
0.255 
Myocardial infarction 
23 (8.9%) 
9 (8.0%) 
14 (9.7%) 
0.224 
0.636 
respiratory disease 
60 (23.3%) 
23 (20.4%) 
37 (25.5%) 
0.949 
0.330 
Diabetes 
60 (23.3%) 
25 (22.1%) 
35 (24.1%) 
0.144 
0.704 
stroke 
56 (21.7%) 
24 (21.2%) 
32 (22.1%) 
0.026 
0.873 
Dementia 
17 (6.6%) 
3 (2.7%) 
14 (9.7%) 
5.056 
0.025 
Delirium 
33 (12.8%) 
10 (8.8%) 
23 (15.9%) 
4.198 
0.041 
renal disease 
28 (10.8%) 
14 (12.4%) 
14 (9.7%) 
0.491 
0.484 
electrolyte disturbances 
24 (9.3%) 
10 (8.8%) 
14 (9.7%) 
0.049 
0.825 
hypoxemia 
38 (14.7%) 
18 (15.9%) 
20 (13.8%) 
0.231 
0.631 
Malignancy 
30 (11.6%) 
11 (9.7%) 
19 (13.1%) 
0.701 
0.402 
Comorbidities (n) 
72 (27.9%) 
32 (28.3%) 
40 (27.6%) 
6.181 
0.103 
1 
84 (32.6%) 
37 (32.7%) 
47 (32.4%) 
2 
61 (23.6%) 
25 (22.1%) 
36 (24.8%) </p>

<p>$3 
41 (15.9%) 
19 (16.8%) 
22 (15.2%) </p>

<p>Postoperative complications 
Acute cardiovascular events 
61 (23.6%) 
24 (21.2%) 
37 (25.5%) 
0.644 
0.422 
Myocardial infarction 
9 (3.5%) 
3 (2.7%) 
6 (4.1%) 
0.415 
0.520 
Acute respiratory events 
27 (10.5%) 
7 (6.2%) 
20 (13.8%) 
3.913 
0.048 
stroke 
20 (7.8%) 
11 (9.7%) 
4 (2.8%) 
5.644 
0.018 
Delirium 
45 (17.4%) 
13 (11.5%) 
32 (22.1%) 
4.922 
0.027 
DVT/Pe 
12 (4.7%) 
6 (5.3%) 
6 (4.1%) 
0.197 
0.658 
renal disorder 
46 (17.8%) 
20 (17.7%) 
26 (17.9%) 
0.002 
0.962 
electrolyte disturbances 
54 (20.9%) 
23 (20.4%) 
31 (21.4%) 
0.040 
0.841 
Anemia 
38 (14.7%) 
17 (15.0%) 
21 (14.5%) 
0.016 
0.900 
hypoxemia 
47 (18.2%) 
24 (21.2%) 
23 (15.9%) 
1.232 
0.267 
Deep wound infection 
25 (9.7%) 
12 (10.6%) 
13 (9.0%) 
0.199 
0.656 
Complications (n) 
97 (37.6%) 
43 (38.1%) 
54 (37.2%) 
0.239 
0.971 
1 
77 (29.8%) 
32 (28.3%) 
45 (31.0%) 
2 
62 (24.0%) 
28 (24.8%) 
34 (23.5%) </p>

<p>$3 
22 (8.5%) 
10 (8.8%) 
12 (8.3%) </p>

<p>Postoperative mortality 
In-hospital 
11 (4.3%) 
3 (2.7%) 
8 (5.5%) 
0.6699 
0.4131 
30-day 
32 (12.4%) 
12 (10.6%) 
20 (13.8%) 
0.5887 
0.4429 
1-year 
59 (22.9%) 
24 (21.2%) 
35 (24.1%) 
0.3026 
0.5823 </p>

<p>Notes: Data are presented as number (percentage), ratio, or mean ± standard deviation. Cardiovascular disease includes hypertension, coronary artery disease, and 
arrhythmia; respiratory disease includes chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, asthma, pulmonary fibrosis, pneumonia, and chronic bronchitis. Differences in complication 
rates between the two groups were tested using chi-square statistics. 
Abbreviations: eA, epidural anesthesia; PnB, peripheral nerve block; DVT/Pe, deep vein thrombosis/pulmonary embolus. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1228 </p>

<p>Jin et al </p>

<p>Preoperative and postoperative risk 
factors for mortality </p>

<p>Table 4 shows the univariate Cox regression analysis of the 
variables for mortality at 30 days and 1 year after surgery. 
Table 5 shows the results of the multivariate Cox regres-
sion analysis. In patients with acute cardiovascular events 
postoperatively, mortality was 39.3% (n=24) at 30 days 
(hazard ratio 6.2, 95% confidence interval [CI] 5.0-11.2) and 
78.7% (n=48) at 1 year (hazard ratio 4.4, 95% CI 3.1-9.3). In 
patients with acute respiratory events, mortality was 22.2% 
(n=6) at 30 days (hazard ratio 4.0, 95% CI 3.6-9.2) and 66.7% 
(n=18) at 1 year (hazard ratio 3.8, 95% CI 3.0-6.7). 
After adjustment for age and sex, patients with three or 
more comorbidities had a hazard ratio of 2.1 for death (95% 
CI 1.7-3.0), males had a hazard ratio of 1.8 (95% CI 1.5-2.4), 
those with acute respiratory events had a hazard ratio of 
1.9 (95% CI 1.3-2.4), and those with dementia had a hazard 
ratio of 2.0 (95% CI 1.4-4.7) at 30 days. Increasing age, 
admission to intensive care, and three or more postoperative 
complications were also key factors. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we found in-hospital, 30-day, and 1-year mor-
tality rates of 4.3%, 12.4%, and 22.9% in elderly patients 
undergoing hemiarthroplasty for FNF. One hundred and 
sixty-one (62.4%) patients had one or more postoperative 
complications, the most common being acute cardiovascular 
events, electrolyte disturbances, and hypoxemia. There was 
a higher incidence of acute respiratory events and fewer 
strokes in the PNB group. In-hospital mortality decreased 
slightly from 5.5% in the PNB group to 2.7% in the epidural 
anesthesia group, but the difference did not reach statistical 
significance. Within 30 days of surgery, 24 patients (39.3%) 
with acute cardiovascular events died, six (22.2%) with acute 
respiratory events died, and six patients (11.7%) with elec-
trolyte disturbances died. Forty-eight patients (78.7%) with 
acute cardiovascular events died within 1 year. Preoperative 
parameters were not significantly different, except for more 
dementia and delirium in the PNB group. Waiting time to 
operation, length of postoperative hospital stay, hospital 
costs, duration of operation, intraoperative fluids required, and 
number of blood transfusions were not significantly different 
between the two groups. Admission to intensive care was 
more common in the PNB group. Older age, male sex, three 
or more comorbidities, acute cardiovascular events, acute 
respiratory events, three or more complications, and admis-
sion to intensive care were all risk factors for mortality. </p>

<p>Table 4 Univariate Cox regression analysis of the variables for 
30-day and 1-year mortality </p>

<p>30-day 
mortality </p>

<p>1-year 
mortality </p>

<p>Male sex 
1.8 (1.5-2.4)** 
1.5 (1.4-3.0)** 
ICU admission 
1.9 (1.2-4.2) 
1.3 (0.7-2.1) 
Age $85 years 
2.7 (1.4-5.2)* 
3.1 (2.2-5.3)* 
Preoperative comorbidities 
Cardiovascular disease 
1.6 (1.2-1.9) 
1.3 (1.1-1.8)* 
Diabetes 
1.2 (0.9-1.8) 
1.4 (1.2-1.7)* 
respiratory disease 
1.9 (1.3-2.4)** 
1.6 (1.2-1.8)* 
stroke 
1.2 (1.1-1.7) 
1.1 (0.9-1.4) 
Dementia 
2.0 (1.4-4.7)* 
2.5 (2.2-3.8) 
renal disease 
1.8 (1.3-4.0) 
2.2 (1.5-4.4)* 
hypoxia 
3.3 (0.8-13.2) 
1.8 (0.6-5.4) 
Malignancy 
1.3 (1.0-2.1) 
1.6 (1.3-2.6)* 
Comorbidities $3 
2.1 (1.7-3.0) 
2.5 (2.0-3.6) </p>

<p>AsA $3 
2.3 (1.9-3.4)** 
3.6 (2.6-5.0)** 
Postoperative complications 
Acute cardiovascular events 
8.1 (5.2-18.3)** 
6.5 (3.1-11.0)** 
Myocardial infarction 
11.0 (2.3-56.7)** 
10.4 (2.0-56.1)** 
Acute respiratory events 
7.5 (6.2-11.0)** 
5.1 (4.3-6.2)** 
stroke 
8.6 (4.6-17.0)** 
5.5 (3.3-8.4)* 
Delirium 
1.8 (0.9-4.06) 
1.8 (0.9-4.2) 
DVT/Pe 
2.1 (1.1-4.6) 
2.6 (1.7-3.8) 
hypoxia 
2.8 (0.9-8.8)* 
2.0 (0.8-4.6) 
Anemia 
0.9 (0.4-2.5) 
1.8 (0.9-3.8) 
Deep wound infection 
0.4 (0-5.7) 
1.1 (1.3-3.4) 
$3 complications 
13.8 (8.7-18.5)** 
6.8 (5.9-8.5)** </p>

<p>Notes: Figures are hazard ratios (95% confidence intervals). *P,0.05; **P,0.01. 
Abbreviations: AsA, American society of Anesthesiologists; ICU, intensive care 
unit; DVT/Pe, deep vein thrombosis/pulmonary embolus. </p>

<p>Table 5 Multivariate Cox regression analysis of the variables for 
30-day and 1-year mortality </p>

<p>30-day 
mortality </p>

<p>1-year 
mortality </p>

<p>Male sex 
1.5 (1.1-2.0)* 
1.8 (1.6-3.5)** 
ICU admission 
1.8 (1.1-4.1) 
1.3 (0.8-2.3) 
Age $85 years 
1.7 (1.2-3.8) 
2.1 (1.6-4.3) 
Preoperative comorbidities 
Cardiovascular disease 
0.8 (0.7-1.2) 
1.1 (0.9-1.8) 
Diabetes 
1.0 (0.8-1.6) 
1.3 (1.1-1.7)* 
respiratory disease 
2.2 (1.7-3.2)* 
1.7 (1.2-2.8)* 
stroke 
1.0 (0.9-1.8) 
1.1 (0.9-1.5) 
Dementia 
1.8 (1.3-3.7) 
2.2 (2.0-3.8) 
renal disease 
1.6 (1.3-3.0)* 
1.4 (1.1-3.4)* 
hypoxia 
2.8 (1.8-7.4) 
1.3 (0.6-2.4) 
Malignancy 
1.3 (1.1-2.3)* 
1.5 (1.2-2.8)** 
Postoperative complications 
Acute cardiovascular events 
6.2 (5.0-11.2)** 
4.4 (3.1-9.3)** 
Myocardial infarction 
4.0 (2.5-6.6)** 
3.4 (2.0-4.1)** 
Acute respiratory events 
4.0 (3.6-9.2)** 
3.8 (3.0-6.7)** 
stroke 
1.6 (1.2-5.3)** 
2.5 (2.1-5.4)* 
Acute renal impairment 
2.0 (0.8-3.6) 
2.1 (1.1-3.8) 
hypoxia 
2.5 (0.9-4.8) 
1.8 (1.1-2.6) </p>

<p>Notes: Figures are hazard ratios (95% confidence intervals). *P,0.05; **P,0.01. 
Abbreviation: ICU, intensive care unit. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Postoperative outcomes in elderly patients </p>

<p>The mortality at 30 days and at 1 year after surgery is 
similar to that in a previous study, 
2 and no significant differ-
ence was found in mortality rates between the two anesthetic 
techniques. Our results could be similar in terms of absolute 
risk to the findings of Urwin et al and O'Hara et al 
10,13 who 
reported a marginal 30-day survival advantage in favor of 
regional anesthesia in their meta-analysis. Further, male 
patients (n=14, 19.2%) had a significantly higher 30-day 
mortality than female patients (n=18, 9.7%; who live longer 
on average); this finding is consistent with another report. </p>

<p>14   In this retrospective study, patients with acute cardiovascular 
and respiratory events had high mortality, with 24.8% (64) 
of geriatric patients developing cardiovascular or respiratory 
complications, which accounted for 32.8% (21) of deaths at 
30 days after surgery. Closer scrutiny of the mortality data 
raises uncertainty. The likelihood of postoperative death is 
largely dependent on prefracture morbidity, so the potency 
of the anesthesia style was only slightly reflected in the mor-
tality rate unless a subgroup analysis is performed in a large 
population of patients. </p>

<p>15   One hundred and eighty-six patients (72.1%) had one 
or more comorbidities on admission. The most common 
were cardiovascular disease, diabetes, respiratory disease, 
and stroke. It appears that patients with certain preoperative 
comorbidities did not have serious postoperative complica-
tions. Previous research has indicated that myocardial infarc-
tion, dementia, and respiratory disease are associated with a 
greater risk of postoperative complications and can increase 
mortality. 
16 In our study, two patients had myocardial infarc-
tion after surgery, one of whom died during their in-hospital 
stay and the other died within 30 days of surgery. Two patients 
with perioperative stroke died in hospital, although they had 
been managed carefully and operated on successfully. 
Seventeen patients (6.6%) in our study had dementia, 
which is thought to be associated with higher postoperative 
complication and mortality rates. 
17,18 Dementia was much 
common in the PNB group (9.7%) than in the epidural 
anesthesia group (2.7%). 
Delirium is a syndrome characterized by acute onset of 
fluctuating levels of alertness or consciousness and a variety of 
other mental symptoms. In our study, 33 (12.8%) patients had 
delirium preoperatively, the reason for which might have been 
aging and trauma. Delirium (15.9%) was more common in the 
PNB group than in the epidural anesthesia group (8.8%). 
Comparing the proportions of dementia and delirium 
between the two anesthesia groups, we speculated that 
mental status may affect the choice of anesthesia in elderly 
patients. Accordingly, the lower mortality seen in the epidural </p>

<p>anesthesia group could not be fully attributed to the type of 
anesthesia given. 
Although there is little presurgical blood loss in patients 
with FNF, hypovolemia is poorly tolerated by the frail 
elderly. A retrospective study of over 8,000 elderly patients 
with hip fracture found that perioperative transfusion had no 
influence on mortality risk in patients with hemoglobin con-
centrations .80 g/L, 
19 although there is some evidence that 
transfusion at higher hemoglobin concentrations for patients 
with known cardiac disease may be beneficial. 
20 Correction 
of anemia with blood transfusion is fraught with debate. 
Further, persistent hypoxia may be present in all patients 
with hip fracture from the time of admission up until several 
days postoperatively. 
21 In our study, 38 (14.7%) patients were 
hypoxemic when the first arterial blood sample was drawn, 
and 30 (78.9%) of these patients still had arterial oxygen pres-
sure below 60 mmHg after surgery. Anemia, hypoxemia, and 
hypoproteinemia invariably occur concomitantly, and may 
be associated with increased postoperative complications and 
mortality. 
22 As such, an appropriate transfusion threshold in 
the elderly that would limit risk and optimize benefit would 
be advantageous. In our department, all patients breathed 
oxygen (3-5 L/min) continuously before and after surgery. 
The hemoglobin level signaling a need for transfusion should 
be 90 g/L in geriatric patients. 
Electrolyte disturbances were common preoperatively 
(24; 9.3%) and postoperatively (54; 20.9%) in our study. 
Hypokalemia was the most common electrolyte abnormal-
ity, and was intractable even when intravenous and oral 
potassium supplements were given. Seven (13.0%) patients 
with postoperative electrolyte disturbances died within 
30 days of surgery. 
Hip fracture patients have the highest risk of concomitant 
delirium, with a reported incidence of 35%-50%. 
8,18 In our 
study, the incidence was 22.1 (32) postoperatively in the 
PNB group, and was much higher than in the epidural anes-
thesia group (χ 
2 =4.922; P=0.027). Nevertheless, the higher 
incidence of preoperative delirium and dementia in the PNB 
group could have affected the postoperative outcome. 
Admission to intensive care in the PNB group (29; 20%) 
was more common than in the epidural anesthesia group (11; 
9.7%). As would be expected, we found that admission to 
intensive care was positively associated with increased mor-
tality at the observed time points. Patients in intensive care 
incurred higher hospital costs and had a longer postoperative 
hospital stay. 
The duration of surgery was not significantly different 
between the two anesthesia groups (104±33 minutes in the PNB </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Jin et al </p>

<p>group versus 100±27 minutes in the epidural anesthesia group; 
P=0.275). A previous report indicated that epidural anesthesia 
can provide optimal muscle relaxation, which makes dissection 
and placement of the prosthesis easier to perform. </p>

<p>23   In our study, no significant differences were found 
between the groups for blood loss (382±170 mL versus 
422±194 mL; P=0.084) or blood transfusion (4.19±3.21u 
versus 3.94±2.64u). A meta-analysis has shown that many 
studies have demonstrated there was less blood loss in 
patients who had undergone epidural anesthesia. 
19 However, 
these reports compared blood loss between regional anesthe-
sia and general anesthesia, and we are the first to compare 
blood loss between two regional anesthetic techniques. As 
mentioned in previous reports, 
19 blood loss in our epidural 
anesthesia group might be attributable to decreased blood 
pressure. Unfortunately, we did not analyze perioperative 
blood pressure between the groups due to the limited record-
ing data available. 
Waiting time to surgery was longer, with some surger-
ies being delayed for up to 1 week in our study. Empirical 
evidence demonstrates that decreasing the waiting time to 
surgery decreases mortality. 
24,25 However, there are some 
recent data showing no significant difference in mortality 
between patients having early or delayed surgery. 
26 Some 
trauma patients did not have adequate physiologic reserve 
and remained under resuscitated before surgery. These 
fragile patients given earlier surgery could increase postop-
erative complications. Hence, suitable preoperative prepara-
tion and optimized medical conditions could optimize the 
outcomes. 
It has been reported that deep vein thrombosis may be 
less frequent in patients who have had a hip fracture and 
been given regional anesthesia. However, the group had no 
anticoagulation in its study. 
23 In our department, all patients 
undergoing lower limb surgery must have prophylactic anti-
coagulation with low molecular weight heparin, consistent 
with the report by Geerts et al. 
27 We did not find a differ-
ence in occurrence of thrombosis between the two regional 
anesthetic techniques (P=0.658). 
The length of postoperative hospital stay was not signifi-
cantly different between the two groups (P=0.557), despite 
the higher number of admissions to intensive care in the 
PNB group. Further, there was no significant difference in 
hospital costs between the epidural anesthesia group and 
the PNB group. Costs excluding procedural and equipment 
charges are more dependent on preoperative comorbidities 
and care for postoperative complications. However, the cost 
of hospitalization increased with delays in surgery, longer </p>

<p>postoperative hospital stay, and admission to intensive care, 
which is consistent with previous reports. </p>

<p>28   With the development of ultrasonographic imaging and 
neurostimulation technology, more anesthesiologists are 
tending to select PNB for lower limb surgery. 
29 Use of PNB 
increased sharply at our institution from 14.3% to 52.7% 
during our 5-year study period. PNB with propofol sedation 
is a sophisticated technique, and is generally implemented at 
our hospital. The technique is neither solely regional anesthe-
sia nor general anesthesia, but is a combination of both, and 
involves administration of balance anesthesia, with or with-
out an oropharynx parichnos or laryngeal mask. Perioperative 
hemodynamic stability and improved postoperative analgesia 
could have decreased the incidence of cardio-cerebrovascular 
and respiratory complications. </p>

<p>13,30   We recognize that our study has some limitations. First, it 
was retrospective in nature and used an ad ministrative data-
base that may be subject to inaccuracies in coding, which could 
have influenced our results. Some "atypical" complications 
are more common in elderly patients, and some patients who 
were treated conservatively without surgery had extremely 
high mortality. This data was not recorded and therefore was 
not analyzed. Furthermore, the sicker patients were more 
likely to be given PNB anesthesia. However, our findings 
may reflect selection bias, hence, the accurate mortality is 
inconsistent to our existent data. Our exclusion of patients 
who did not undergo surgery along with those who received 
general anesthesia may limit the generalizability of our results. 
Third, postoperative functional recovery is also an important 
outcome in elderly patients, but could not be investigated in 
this retrospective study. Finally, the small sample size and 
single-center nature of our study made it difficult to appreciate 
significant differences between the two study groups. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Our study shows that PNB is not associated with lower 
mortality or cardiovascular complication rates than epidural 
anesthesia in patients receiving hemiarthroplasty for FNF. 
Patients who received PNB were more likely to have demen-
tia and acute respiratory events postoperatively than those 
who received epidural anesthesia, and those who had epidural 
anesthesia were more likely to have a stroke postoperatively. 
It is possible that perioperative management might be 
more important than the type of anesthesia administered. 
Therefore, further studies should aim to identify optimal 
management for these patients to improve their outcome 
using a team-based approach, and then use best practice 
guidelines and standardized outcome measures. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/clinical-interventions-in-aging-journal </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging is an international, peer-reviewed journal 
focusing on evidence-based reports on the value or lack thereof of treatments 
intended to prevent or delay the onset of maladaptive correlates of aging 
in human beings. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, MedLine, </p>

<p>CAS, Scopus and the Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The manuscript 
management system is completely online and includes a very quick and fair 
peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress. 
com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1231 </p>

<p>Postoperative outcomes in elderly patients </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank the many research staff members, nursing 
staff, and their surgical and anesthesiology colleagues at the 
Chinese People's Liberation Army General Hospital who 
helped with the conduct of the study, especially Qun Zhang 
and Yonggang Zhou in the Department of Orthopaedics. 
They are also grateful to Zhi Li (Shanxi Medical University, 
Taiyuan, People's Republic of China) for assistance with the 
statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



</text></tei>