<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4851261" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: The development of rapid and safe antidepressants for the treatment of major depression is in urgent demand. 
Converging evidence suggests that glutamatergic signaling seems to play important roles in the pathophysiology of 
depression. 
Methods: We studied the antidepressant effects of 3 ' -deoxyadenosine (3'-dA, Cordycepin) and the critical role of the α-amino-3-
hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazole propionic acid (AMPA) receptor in male CD-1 mice via behavioral and biochemical experiments. 
After 3'-dA treatment, the phosphorylation and synaptic localization of the AMPA receptors GluR1 and GluR2 were determined 
in the prefrontal cortex (PFC) and hippocampus (HIP). The traditional antidepressant imipramine was applied as a positive 
control. 
Results: We found that an injection of 3'-dA led to a rapid and robust antidepressant effect, which was significantly faster 
and stronger than imipramine, after 45 min in tail suspension and forced swim tests. This antidepressant effect remained 
after 5 days of treatment with 3'-dA. Unlike the psycho-stimulants, 3'-dA did not show a hyperactive effect in the open field 
test. After 45 min or 5 days of treatment, 3'-dA enhanced GluR1 S845 phosphorylation in both the PFC and HIP. In addition, 
after 45 min of treatment, 3'-dA significantly up-regulated GluR1 S845 phosphorylation and GluR1, but not GluR2 levels, at 
the synapses in the PFC. After 5 days of treatment, 3'-dA significantly enhanced GluR1 S845 phosphorylation and GluR1, but 
not GluR2, at the synapses in the PFC and HIP. Moreover, the AMPA-specific antagonist GYKI 52466 was able to block the rapid 
antidepressant effects of 3'-dA. </p>

<p>2 | International Journal of Neuropsychopharmacology, 2016 </p>

<p>Conclusion: This study identified 3'-dA as a novel rapid antidepressant with clinical potential and multiple beneficial 
mechanisms, particularly in regulating the prefrontal AMPA receptor signaling pathway. </p>

<p>Keywords: 3'-deoxyadenosine, synapse, animal behavior, GluR1, rapid antidepressant </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Due to the millions of individuals who suffer from major depression 
today, and the delayed efficacy of the existing therapeutic agents, 
there exists an interest in finding a safer compound with robust and 
rapid antidepressant effects (Krystal et al., 2013; Caddy et al., 2014). 
The most famous rapid antidepressant, Ketamine, a non-competi-
tive N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptor antagonist, was found 
to rely on increasing α-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazole 
propionic acid (AMPA) signaling to exert its antidepressant efficacy 
(Maeng et al., 2008). A previous study has shown that a traditional 
Chinese medicine, Cordyceps Militaris powder, demonstrated an 
antidepressant effect in the tail suspension test (TST; Nishizawa 
et al., 2007). Moreover, 3'-deoxyadenosine (3'-dA, Cordycepin), one 
of the major bioactive metabolites in the Cordyceps Militaris (Tuli 
et al., 2013), exerted a beneficial effect in a 6-week chronic unpre-
dictable mild stress (CUMS) mouse model via the forced swim test 
(FST; Tianzhu et al., 2014). 3'-dA possesses a wide range of benefi-
cial effects of therapeutic potential, including anti-insomnia, anti-
inflammatory, anti-cancer, anti-viral, and anti-fungal activities (Hu 
et al., 2013; Tuli et al., 2013). However, whether or not 3'-dA has a 
fast-acting antidepressant effect remains unknown. 
Glutamate mediates the vast majority of excitatory transmis-
sions and about 80% of neurons form 85% of the synapses, which 
are spiny and excitatory in the central nervous system (CNS; 
Douglas and Martin, 2007; Sanacora et al., 2012). A growing body 
of evidence suggests that the glutamatergic system might be 
very important in the pathophysiology and treatment of depres-
sion (Krystal et al., 2002; Sanacora et al., 2012; Musazzi et al., 
2013; Pilc et al., 2013). The AMPA receptor channel is a tetramer 
assembled from the four subunits, including GluR1, GluR2, GluR3, 
and GluR4. Clinical evidence has shown that the expression of 
AMPA receptors, particularly GluR1, is decreased in the brains of 
patients with depression (Beneyto et al., 2007; Duric et al., 2013). 
Additionally, the trafficking of AMPA receptor subunit GluR1 and 
synaptic plasticity are regulated by the phosphorylation of spe-
cific subunits (Malinow and Malenka, 2002; Esteban et al., 2003). 
Phosphorylation of GluR1 at serine 845 (S845) was increased fol-
lowing antidepressant treatment with flouxetine or tianeptine in 
mice (Svenningsson et al., 2002, 2007), suggesting that phospho-
rylation of GluR1 might be associated with the potentiation of 
AMPA receptor currents (Wang et al., 2005). Previous studies have 
shown that phosphorylation of GluR1 at S845 and GluR1 synaptic 
localization might be common mechanisms for the agents with 
antidepressant efficacy, such as imipramine, lamotrigine, and 
riluzol (Du et al., 2007; Gould et al., 2008). However, whether 3'-dA 
regulates AMPA synaptic plasticity is still unknown. 
Based on these premises, we designed a series of behavioral 
and biochemical experiments to investigate the antidepressant 
effects of 3'-dA in animal models of depression. We studied the 
rapid and chronic effects of various concentrations of 3'-dA via 
behavioral tests, including the TST, FST, and open field test (OFT). 
The phosphorylation of GluR1 S845 and synaptic localization of 
GluR1 and GluR2 were determined in the prefrontal cortex (PFC) 
and hippocampus (HIP) after 45-min and 5-day treatments. In 
addition, the role of the enhanced AMPA function in the rapid 
antidepressant effect was addressed by pretreatment with 
AMPA receptor-specific antagonist GYKI 52466 followed by TST. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Animal Behavioral Studies </p>

<p>All animal treatments, procedures, and care were approved by 
the medical ethics committee of the School of Medicine, Yunnan 
University, and followed the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory 
Animals (ISBN 0-309-05377-3). Male CD-1 mice (6 weeks; starting 
weight, 23-28 g; Vital River) were group housed (n = 4/cage) in an 
animal room with a constant temperature (21 ± 3°C) and main-
tained on a 12-hour light/dark cycle (lights on/off at 09:00 and 
21:00 hours), with constant humidity (55 ± 10%) and free access to 
water and food. After a 1-week acclimatization period, the mice 
were treated with drugs or vehicle in a volume of 10 μl/g by intra-
peritonial (i.p.) injection and tested between 10:00 and 14:00 hours. 
To examine the rapid (45-min treatment) and chronic (5-day 
treatment) antidepressant effects of 3'-dA (Sigma), mice were 
randomly assigned to four treatment groups: saline (0.9% sterile 
sodium chloride solution), low dose of 3'-dA (5 mg/kg, dissolved 
in saline), high dose of 3'-dA (12.5 mg/kg, in saline), and imipra-
mine (15 mg/kg, in saline; Sigma). Animal behavioral tests were 
performed 45 minutes after drug or vehicle administration, TST 
was performed on the first day, OFT on the third day, and FST on 
the fifth day. To confirm the rapid and chronic antidepressant 
effects of 3'-dA, another two batches of mice were subjected to 
the FST and TST, respectively, under similar settings. 
To examine whether the rapid antidepressant effect of 3'-dA 
could be blocked by GYKI 52466 (a selective non-competitive AMPA 
receptor antagonist; TOCRIS Bioscience, R&amp;D), mice were treated 
with GYKI 52466 (30 mg/kg in 26% DMSO/74% saline), followed by 
a high dose of 3'-dA treatment. Since a previous study showed 
that plasma levels of GYKI 52466 peaked at 15 minutes after i.p. 
injection and then fell to 21% of the peak value at 60 minutes (De 
Sarro et al., 1998), we administered GYKI 15 minutes before 3'-dA 
treatment and performed the TST 45 minutes later. For each drug 
treatment, the control mice received the respective vehicle alone. </p>

<p>Tail Suspension Test 
A 7 cm long and 2 cm wide tape was positioned with approximately 
2 mm of tail protruding. In a series of pilot experiments using this 
procedure, we observed that no mice climbed their tails. Each 
mouse was individually suspended by the tail from a bar (30 cm 
high) and videotaped during a 6-min test session. Immobility time 
was quantified by a naive observer for the last 4 minutes. </p>

<p>Open Field Test 
An activity chamber (60 × 60 × 30 cm) with a black floor divided 
into 16 squares of an equal area (15 × 15 cm) by white lines was 
used to study 3'-dA-induced hyperactivity. After 3 days of i.p. 
injection of drugs, mice were placed in the center of the cham-
ber and their behavior was recorded for 60 minutes. Total dis-
tance traveled and the amount of distance traveled in the center 
area (the 4-square area in the middle of the chamber) were ana-
lyzed by <rs id="software-2" type="software">Anymaze system</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Stoelting</rs>). </p>

<p>Forced Swim Test 
Mice were placed in a cylinder (Ф = 20 cm) with water 20 cm in 
depth (temperature between 23 ± 1°C). Mice were videotaped </p>

<p>Li et al. | 3 </p>

<p>during a 6-min test session, which was later analyzed by a naive 
observer for activity during the final 4 minutes. Mobility was 
defined as any movement beyond what was necessary to main-
tain the head above water. 
After the behavioral experiments, all mice were decapitated 
immediately. The PFC and HIP were dissected, frozen rapidly in 
liquid nitrogen, and stored at −80°C until further analysis. </p>

<p>Western Blot Analysis </p>

<p>PFC or HIP tissue was lysed with an ice-cold radioimmuno-
precipitation assay buffer (20 mM Tris [pH 7.5], 150 mM NaCl, 
1% Triton X-100, sodium pyrophosphate, β-glycerophosphate, 
EDTA, Na 3 VO 4, leupeptin plus a Protease Inhibitor Cocktail Tablet 
[Roche], and Phosphatase Inhibitor Cocktail Tablet [Roche]) in 
a tissue grinder (Wheaton). Protein concentrations were deter-
mined using the BCA protein assay kit (Pierce Biotechnology). 
Equal amounts of proteins were subjected to 7-10% SDS-PAGE 
gels electrophoresis, then transferred to polyvinylidene dif-
luoride (PVDF) membranes (Pall) and blocked with 1% BSA in 
TBST (0.1% Tween). Antibodies against Phos-GluR1 S845 (Rabbit 
mAb, 1:1000, Cell Signaling Technology) and GluR1 (Goat pAb, 
1:1000, Santa Cruz) in 5% BSA-TBST were applied to the mem-
branes. The secondary antibodies were horseradish peroxi-
dase conjugated goat anti-rabbit (1:5000, Affinity Bioscience) or 
donkey anti-goat antibodies (1:5000, Santa Cruz). Antibody for 
β-actin (Mouse mAb, 0.2 μg/ml, Affinity Bioscience) was applied 
for loading calibration. Immunoreactive bands were visualized 
using the ECL detection system (Millipore). Images were acquired 
by the FlourChem E image system (FE0511, ProteinSimple) and 
quantified by the Image-Pro Plus Version 6.0 software (Media 
Cybernetics). </p>

<p>Synaptosomes Preparation </p>

<p>Synaptosomal fractions were prepared from PFC or HIP tis-
sue using the differential and discontinuous Ficoll gradient 
centrifugation method (Pozzo-Miller et al., 1999; Du et al., 
2004a, 2008). Tissue was homogenized by tissue grinder and 
then electronic polytron homogenizer (AutoScience) in cold 
Syn buffer (300 mM mannitol and 1 mM EDTA, pH 7.4). The 
crude homogenates were centrifuged at 5000 × g for 10 min-
utes and the supernatants were again centrifuged at 15000 × g 
for 30 minutes. The resuspended pellets were loaded on Ficoll </p>

<p>gradient tubes and centrifuged at 22000 × g for 90 minutes. The 
8/12% and 12/16% interfaces were carefully removed, diluted 
in Syn buffer in a ratio of 1:4, and centrifuged for 20 minutes 
at 15000 × g. Pellets were resuspended and lysed with Lysis 
buffer. All samples were constantly maintained at 4°C dur-
ing all steps. Western blot was applied to analyze the synap-
tic expressions of Phos-GluR1 S845, GluR1, and GluR2 (Rabbit 
mAb, 1:2000, Abcam). </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>All data were analyzed by one-way ANOVA and post hoc 
Bonferroni (unequal sample) or Tukey (equal sample) tests and 
presented as the mean ± standard error via SPSS 17. A p-value 
less than 0.05 was considered a significant difference. Figures 
were generated by <rs id="software-1" type="software">Graphpad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">Version 5</rs> software. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>3'-dA Demonstrated a Rapid and Significant 
Antidepressant Effect </p>

<p>To investigate whether 3'-dA plays a role in regulating depres-
sion-like behavior, we i.p. injected the 7-week-old CD-1 mice with 
a low (5 mg/kg) or high (12.5 mg/kg) dose of 3'-dA for 45 minutes 
or 5 days. 45 minutes after the treatment, mice were subjected 
to either the TST or FST. The data showed that the immobility 
times in the 3'-dA-treated groups were significantly lower than 
in the controls (101.74 ± 6.49 sec) in a dose dependent manner: 
54.60 ± 7.73 sec (for 12.5 mg/kg of 3'-dA) and 76.57 ± 6.49 sec (for 
5 mg/kg of 3'-dA) in the TST (Figure 1A). It is noteworthy that the 
high dose of 3'-dA (12.5 mg/kg) reduced the immobility time of 
TST to a much larger extent than that of the comparable tradi-
tional antidepressant imipramine (15 mg/kg; Figure 1A). To con-
firm the data in the TST, the FST was performed under similar 
settings. After 45 minutes of treatment with 3'-dA, the high dose 
group also demonstrated a stronger antidepressant effect, as low 
as 48.23 ± 10.11 sec, compared with the control (92.69 ± 9.24 sec) 
and the imipramine group (79.92 ± 9.92 sec; Figure 1B). 
To further study this antidepressant effect for long-term 
treatment, we treated the mice with a low (5 mg/kg) or high 
(12.5 mg/kg) dose of 3'-dA for 5 days, then performed the TST 
and FST. The data showed that both low and high doses of 3'-dA 
significantly decreased immobility time, to 50.35 % and 55.36 % </p>

<p>Figure 1. 3 ' -deoxyadenosine (3'-dA) demonstrated rapid and significant antidepressant effects in the tail suspension test (TST) and forced swim test (FST). CD-1 mice were </p>

<p>i.p. injected with a low dose of 3'-dA (5 mg/kg/day, dA-L), a high dose of 3'-dA (12.5 mg/kg/day, dA-H), imipramine (15mg/kg/day, IMI), or saline (Sal). 45 minutes after the drug </p>

<p>injection, mice were subjected to the TST or FST. The number of mice per group is indicated in each individual graph. Data were analyzed by one-way ANOVA and presented </p>

<p>as mean ± standard error (post hoc Bonferroni test, *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001; post hoc Tukey test, ★p &lt; 0.05, ★★p &lt; 0.01). (A, B) 45 minutes after the injection, 3'-dA </p>

<p>significantly reduced the immobility time in the TST and FST. (C, D) After 5 consecutive days of injection, 3'-dA significantly reduced the immobility time in the TST and FST. </p>



<p>of control in the TST and 64.95 % and 36.78 % of control in the 
FST, respectively, in a dose-dependent manner. Imipramine also 
showed a stable and strong antidepressant effect in both the 
TST and FST (Figure 1C and D). </p>

<p>Unlike the Psycho-Stimulants, 3'-dA Did Not Show 
Locomotor Hyperactivity in the OFT </p>

<p>To further determine whether 3'-dA causes locomotor hyperac-
tivity, one of the core features of mania-like symptoms, we per-
formed the OFT after 3 days of treatment with a low or high dose 
of 3'-dA. The total distance traveled showed no significant differ-
ence in 3'-dA-treated groups compared with controls, suggesting 
that 3'-dA does not cause hyperactivity in mice (Figure 2A). This 
is different from the psycho-stimulant amphetamine, which sig-
nificantly increased the total distance travelled in rats during the 
OFT (Labonte et al., 2012). 3'-dA showed a trend to increase the 
distance travelled in the center area, but it was not statistically 
significant (Figure 2B). The weights of mice after 5 days of treat-
ment did not show a significant difference (Figure 2C). </p>

<p>After 45 Min of Treatment, High Concentration of 3'-
dA Enhanced AMPA GluR1 S845 Phosphorylation in 
the PFC and HIP </p>

<p>Previous studies from our group showed that phosphorylation 
of AMPA GluR1 S845 presented a common mechanism for the 
treatment of depression (Du et al., 2007). In this context, we fur-
ther addressed whether Phos-GluR1 S845 levels were changed 
after treatment with 3'-dA. We found that after 45 minutes of i.p. 
injection, the phosphorylation of GluR1 S845 was rapidly and sig-
nificantly increased in both the PFC and HIP from the high-dose 
3'-dA-treated group (Figure 3A). In contrast, the phosphoryla-
tion of GluR1 S845 in the imipramine-treated group remained 
unchanged after 45 minutes of treatment, which is consistent 
with the fact that the antidepressant effects of imipramine were 
not significant after 45 minutes of treatment (Figures 1A and B 
and 3A). The levels of total GluR1 proteins in these brain regions 
remained unchanged (Figure 3B). </p>

<p>After 5 Days of Treatment, 3'-dA and Imipramine 
Enhanced AMPA GluR1 S845 Phosphorylation in 
Both the PFC and HIP </p>

<p>To determine the long-term effects of 3'-dA, we treated the mice 
with 3'-dA for 5 days, and found that the phosphorylation of GluR1 </p>

<p>S845 was significantly increased in both the low (175.44 ± 14.32%; 
169.86 ± 11.83%) and high (174.75 ± 13.00%; 158.06 ± 11.62%) dose 
groups in the PFC and HIP, respectively (Figure 3C). The imipra-
mine-treated group also demonstrated a significant increase in 
Phos-GluR1 S845 levels in both the PFC (163.02 ± 12.08%) and HIP 
(148.52 ± 12.16%) after 5 days of treatment (Figure 3C), which is 
consistent with a previous publication (Du et al., 2007). The total 
GluR1 levels in the PFC and HIP remained unchanged (Figure 3D). </p>

<p>After 45 Min of Treatment, 3'-dA Significantly Up-
Regulated AMPA GluR1 S845 Phosphorylation and 
GluR1 Levels at the Synapses in the PFC </p>

<p>To further determine whether GluR1 localization at the synapses 
in the PFC or HIP was increased, we isolated the synaptosomal 
fractions from the PFC and HIP tissue. Western blot analysis of 
Phos-GluR1 S845, GluR1, and GluR2 were performed with the 
synaptic fractions. Here, we found that levels of GluR1 and GluR2 
were significantly enriched at the synapses, compared with the 
total protein (Figure 4A). After 45 minutes of treatment with the 
high dose of 3'-dA (12.5 mg/kg), Phos-GluR1 S845 and GluR1 levels, 
but not GluR2 levels, were significantly increased in the synapto-
somal fractions in the PFC (Figures 4B and C and 5A). It is note-
worthy that the acute treatment of the traditional antidepressant 
imipramine did not lead to a significant increase in GluR1 levels 
at the synapses (Figure 4C), which is consistent with the results in 
the TST and FST after 45 minutes of treatment (Figure 1A and B). </p>

<p>After 5 Days of Treatment, 3'-dA Significantly 
Enhanced AMPA Receptor GluR1 S845 
Phosphorylation and GluR1, But Not GluR2 Levels at 
the Synapses </p>

<p>After 5 days of treatment with drugs, 3'-dA and imipramine 
enhanced the phosphorylation levels of GluR1 S845 in the PFC 
and HIP (Figure 4D). We found that both the low and high doses 
of 3'-dA induced an increase in GluR1 S845 phosphorylation (low 
dose: 304.01 ± 24.46% in PFC, 244.82 ± 28.91% in HIP; high dose: 
285.14 ± 24.54% in PFC, 245.27 ± 26.39% in HIP). Both the low and 
high doses of 3'-dA induced an increase in GluR1 levels (low 
dose: 144.12 ± 10.21% in PFC, 129.02 ± 5.04% in HIP; high dose: 
152.37 ± 12.47% in PFC, 147.48 ± 10.98% in HIP), but not GluR2 levels, 
in the PFC and HIP, suggesting that the regulation of 3'-dA to AMPA 
was subtype-specific. For the imipramine-treated group, chronic 
treatment resulted in both GluR1 (157.46 ± 7.69% in PFC) and GluR2 
(138.01 ± 9.20% in PFC) increases at the synapses, suggesting the </p>

<p>Figure 2. An open field test (OFT) of animals after 3 days of treatment with 3 ' -deoxyadenosine (3'-dA). After 3 days of treatment, mice were subjected to the OFT. Total </p>

<p>distance traveled and the distance traveled in the center area was determined by automated tracking system. The number of mice per group is indicated in each indi-</p>

<p>vidual graph. Data were analyzed by one-way ANOVA and presented as mean ± standard error. (A) The total distance traveled in the field after 3'-dA treatment. (B) The </p>

<p>distance traveled in the center area of field after 3'-dA treatment. (C) Body weight of the 5 consecutive days after 3'-dA treatment. </p>

<p>Li et al. | 5 </p>

<p>regulation is in a GluR1/2 subtype-specific manner, which is dif-
ferent from the 3'-dA regulation (Figure 4E and 5B). </p>

<p>The Rapid Antidepressant Effect of 3'-dA was 
Blocked by the AMPA Receptor Specific Antagonist 
GYKI 52466 </p>

<p>We hypothesized that the AMPA receptor increase is critical for 
the rapid antidepressant effects of 3'-dA. To determine whether 
the rapid antidepressant effects of 3'-dA could be blocked by the 
AMPA receptor-specific antagonist GYKI 52466, we pretreated 
the mice with 30 mg/kg of GYKI, followed by the i.p. injection of 
3'-dA (12.5 mg/kg). The mice were subjected to TST 45 minutes 
after the 3'-dA injection. The pretreatment of GYKI 52466 almost 
completely blocked the decrease of immobility time caused by 
3'-dA (control: 130.06 ± 11.67 sec; 3'-dA: 65.69 ± 12.02 sec; GYKI 
+ 3'-dA: 122.91 ± 8.65 sec; Figure 6), suggesting that enhanced 
AMPA receptor excitability at the synapses might play an impor-
tant role in the rapid antidepressant effects of 3'-dA. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study sought to determine the rapid and robust antidepres-
sant effects of 3'-dA and its possible underlying mechanisms </p>

<p>in regulating AMPA receptor signaling. We found that: (1) 3'-dA 
had rapid and robust antidepressant effects in the TST and FST 
after 45 min of treatment, and this effect remained after 5 days 
of treatment; (2) unlike the psycho-stimulants, 3'-dA had no 
hyperactive effect in the OFT; (3) after 45 min of treatment, only 
high doses of 3'-dA enhanced Phos-GluR1 S845 in the PFC and 
HIP, and after 5 days of treatment, 3'-dA, similar to imipramine, 
enhanced Phos-GluR1 S845 in both the PFC and HIP; (4) after 
45 min of treatment, only high doses of 3'-dA enhanced Phos-
GluR1 S845 and GluR1, but not GluR2 levels, at the synapses in 
the PFC, and after 5 days of treatment, 3'-dA enhanced Phos-
GluR1 S845 and GluR1, but not GluR2 levels, at the synapse in 
both the PFC and HIP; and (5) AMPA receptor-specific antagonist 
GYKI 52466 was able to block the rapid and robust antidepres-
sant effects of 3'-dA, suggesting enhanced AMPA synaptic trans-
mission is essential for the rapid antidepressant effects. </p>

<p>The Rapid and Robust Antidepressant Effect 
of 3'-dA was Unique to the Psycho-Stimulant 
Antidepressant Effect </p>

<p>The most famous rapid antidepressant is ketamine, a non-
competitive N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptor antagonist 
that elicits a rapid antidepressant response in patients with </p>

<p>Figure 3. Enhanced phosphorylation of GluR1 S845 after 45-minute and 5-day treatments of 3 ' -deoxyadenosine (3'-dA) in the prefrontal cortex (PFC) and hippocampus </p>

<p>(HIP). CD-1 mice were i.p. injected with a low dose of 3'-dA (5 mg/kg/day, dA-L), a high dose of 3'-dA (12.5 mg/kg/day, dA-H), imipramine (15mg/kg/day, IMI), or saline (Sal) </p>

<p>for 45 minutes or 5 days. Western blot analyses of the proteins from the PFC or HIP were performed with anti-Phos-GluR1 S845 or anti-GluR1 antibodies. The number of </p>

<p>mice per group is indicated in each individual graph. Data were analyzed by one-way ANOVA and presented as mean ± standard error (post hoc Tukey test, ★p &lt; 0.05, 
★★p &lt; 0.01). (A, B) The expression levels of Phos-GluR1 S845 or GluR1 in both the PFC and HIP after 45 minutes of treatment with 3'-dA. (C, D) The expression levels of </p>

<p>Phos-GluR1 S845 and GluR1 in both the PFC and HIP after 5 days of treatment with 3'-dA. </p>



<p>Figure 4. Rapid and chronic effects of 3 ' -deoxyadenosine (3'-dA) on synaptic phosphorylation of GluR1 S845 and GluR1 in the prefrontal cortex (PFC) and hip-</p>

<p>pocampus (HIP). CD-1 mice were i.p. injected with a low dose of 3'-dA (5 mg/kg/day, dA-L), a high dose of 3'-dA (12.5 mg/kg/day, dA-H), imipramine (15mg/kg/ </p>

<p>day, IMI), or saline (Sal) for 45 minutes or 5 days. Synaptosomal fractions from the PFC or the HIP were prepared and subjected to Western blot analyses with </p>

<p>anti-Phos-GluR1 S845 or anti-GluR1 antibodies. The number of mice per group is indicated in each individual graph. Data were analyzed by one-way ANOVA and </p>

<p>presented as mean ± standard error (post hoc Tukey test, ★p &lt; 0.05, ★★p &lt; 0.01, ★★★p &lt; 0.001; two-tail t-test, #p &lt; 0.05, ###p &lt; 0.001). (A) Enrichments of GluR1 </p>

<p>and GluR2 at synapses compared with the total protein. (B, C) The expression levels of synaptic Phos-GluR1 S845 and GluR1 were increased in the PFC, but not </p>

<p>in the HIP, after 45 minutes of treatment with 3'-dA. (D, E) After 5 days of treatment, 3'-dA enhanced synaptic Phos-GluR1 S845 and GluR1 expressions in both </p>

<p>the PFC and HIP. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Rapid and chronic effects of 3 ' -deoxyadenosine (3'-dA) on synaptic GluR2 in the prefrontal cortex (PFC) and hippocampus (HIP). CD-1 mice were i.p. injected </p>

<p>with a low dose of 3'-dA (5 mg/kg/day, dA-L), a high dose of 3'-dA (12.5 mg/kg/day, dA-H), imipramine (15mg/kg/day, IMI), or saline (Sal) for 45 minutes or 5 days. Synap-</p>

<p>tosomal fractions from the PFC or HIP were prepared and subjected to Western blot analyses with anti-GluR2 antibodies. The number of mice per group is indicated in </p>

<p>each individual graph. Data were analyzed by one-way ANOVA and presented as mean ± standard error (post hoc Tukey test, ★p &lt; 0.05). (A, B) The expression levels of </p>

<p>synaptic GluR2 were not increased in the PFC and HIP after 45-minute or 5-day treatments with 3'-dA. </p>

<p>Li et al. | 7 </p>

<p>depression (Berman et al., 2000; Zarate et al., 2006; Price et al., 
2009) or bipolar depression (DiazGranados et al., 2010; Zarate 
et al., 2012; Krystal et al., 2013). However, ketamine does not pre-
sent ideal features as an antidepressant because of its potential 
psychotomimetic effects and abuse. The underlying antidepres-
sant mechanism of ketamine has been well studied, and emerg-
ing evidence shows that ketamine's antidepressant properties 
rely on blocking NMDA receptors, increasing AMPA signaling, 
and rapidly inducing synaptogenesis (Maeng et al., 2008; Caddy 
et al., 2014). The antidepressant effect of ketamine appears to be 
fast-acting and lasts for a few days to weeks (Aan Het Rot et al., 
2012). Some clinical evidence indicates that depressed patients 
might have side effects of a fast heart rate, high blood pressure, 
respiratory depression, and hallucinations after treatment with 
ketamine (Bowdle et al., 1998; Roback et al., 2006; Paul et al., 
2009; Aan Het Rot et al., 2010). Other psycho-stimulants, such 
as cocaine and amphetamine, may also have rapid antidepres-
sant effects: however, these psycho-stimulants usually induce 
excitatory neural toxicity and drug addiction (Pierce and Kalivas, 
1997; McCance-Katz et al., 1998). Moreover, most psycho-stimu-
lants also lead to the development of depressive symptoms dur-
ing withdrawal (Che et al., 2013; Krzascik et al., 2015). 
3'-dA is an analogue of adenosine, which is a neurotrans-
mitter in the nervous system (Haas and Selbach, 2000). It has 
been shown that adenosine-derived drugs can be transported 
from blood to the brain via an adenosine transporter across the 
blood-brain barrier (Li et al., 2001; Pardridge, 2012). Very recently, 
it has been shown that 3'-dA has a beneficial effect in CUMS-
induced behavioral deficits after treatment with doses of 20 mg/ 
kg and 40 mg/kg for 3-6 weeks (Tianzhu et al., 2014). Chronic 
3'-dA (20, 40 mg/kg) treatments reversed the behavioral defi-
ciency induced by CUMS exposure in the TST and FST (Tianzhu </p>

<p>et al., 2014). Here, we report a rapid and robust antidepressant 
effect of 3'-dA alone within a lower dose range (5-12.5 mg/kg). In 
our study, the 3'-dA resulted in approximately a 45% reduction 
in immobility time within 45 minutes in both the TST and FST, 
which is significantly stronger and faster than the traditional 
antidepressant imipramine (Figure 1A and B). The imipramine 
dose range commonly used for mouse models of depression is 
10-20 mg/kg/day (Solomon et al., 2014; Ichikawa et al., 2015). We 
chose the middle of this range, 15 mg/kg, to compare with the 
similar dose of 3'-dA (12.5 mg/kg) and found that after 45 min of 
treatment, the imipramine (15 mg/kg) did not reach significant 
antidepressant effects, but 3'-dA demonstrated faster antide-
pressant effects (Figure 1A and B). It is noteworthy that recently 
evidence has shown that i.p. injection with a low dose of imipra-
mine (&lt;20 mg/kg) did not lead to fast antidepressant effects in 30 
minutes, but a dose of 30 or 40 mg/kg decreased the immobility 
time in mice in the TST and FST (Villard et al., 2011; Cai et al., 
2013; Nguyen and Matsumoto, 2015). Therefore, we only con-
cluded that compared to the imipramine dose of 15 mg/kg, 3'-dA 
(12.5 mg/kg) demonstrated faster and stronger antidepressant 
effects (Figure 1A and B). Although 3'-dA demonstrated rapid 
and strong antidepressant effects, it did not elicit hyperactivity 
like some of the psycho-stimulants (Figure 2A and B). </p>

<p>Consistent with Traditional Antidepressants, 3'-dA 
Regulated GluR1 S845 Phorsphorylation </p>

<p>A growing body of data suggests that AMPA receptor signaling 
plays a critical role in regulating synaptic strength, as well as vari-
ous forms of neural and behavioral plasticity (Carlezon and Nestler, 
2002; Malenka, 2003; Kendell et al., 2005; Rumpel et al., 2005; 
Sun et al., 2005). 3'-dA is an agonist for the adenosine A3 recep-
tor (Kitamura et al., 2011; Nakamura et al., 2015), which regulates 
synaptic plasticity and long-term potentiation in vivo and in vitro 
(Costenla et al., 2001; Maggi et al., 2009). Therefore, we hypothesized 
that 3'-dA may mediate through the adenosine A3 receptor to regu-
late the AMPA receptor function, which we will explore in our future 
research. GluR1 phosphorylation at the S845 site, which is a PKA 
site, is often viewed as an indicator for GluR1 membrane insertion 
in neurons and wide channel openings (Roche et al., 1996; Banke 
et al., 2000; Lee et al., 2000; Esteban et al., 2003). A previous study 
has shown that the levels of GluR1 in the PFCs of depressed patients 
were decreased (Beneyto et al., 2007), which was consistent with the 
animal experiments (Toth et al., 2008; Yuen et al., 2012; Kallarackal 
et al., 2013). The AMPA receptor may serve as a common mecha-
nism for the treatment of mood disorders, since the two anticon-
vulsants riluzole (with a predominantly antidepressant profile) and 
lamotrigine enhanced GluR1 phosphorylation at the S845 site. In 
contrast, the anticonvulsant valproate (with a predominantly anti-
manic profile) exerted the opposite effect on GluR1 phosphoryla-
tion at the S845 site (Du et al., 2004a, 2007, 2008, 2010; Gould et al., 
2008). Consistent with previous findings, we found that 3'-dA was 
able to enhance GluR1 S845 phosphorylation and GluR1 synaptic 
localization in the PFC within 45 minutes (Figures 3A and 4B and 
C), which is faster than the traditional antidepressant imipramine. 
After 5 days of treatment, both 3'-dA and imipramine were able to 
enhance the phosphorylation of GluR1 S845 and synaptic GluR1 
significantly in the PFC and HIP (Figures 3C and 4D and E). </p>

<p>3'-dA Modulated GluR1 Synaptic Localization in a 
Subtype-Specific and Brain Region-Specific Manner </p>

<p>Previous studies showed that there are three major types of AMPA 
tetramers in most brain regions: GluR1/2, GluR2/3, and GluR1/3 </p>

<p>Figure 6. The α-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazole propionic acid (AMPA) </p>

<p>receptor-specific antagonist GYKI 52466 significantly blocked the 3 ' -deoxyaden-</p>

<p>osine (3'-dA)-induced rapid antidepressant effect in the tail suspension test </p>

<p>(TST). CD-1 mice were i.p. injected with AMPA-specific antagonist GYKI 52466 </p>

<p>(30 mg/kg) or vehicle. After 15 minutes, the high dose of 3'-dA or vehicle was also </p>

<p>injected. 45 minutes later, the CD-1 mice were subjected to the TST. Immobility </p>

<p>time was determined. The number of mice per group is indicated in each indi-</p>

<p>vidual graph. Data were analyzed by one-way ANOVA and presented as mean ± </p>

<p>standard error (post hoc Tukey test, ★p &lt; 0.05, ★★p &lt; 0.01, ★★★p &lt; 0.001). </p>



<p>(Du et al., 2004a, 2004b, 2007, 2008; Ampuero et al., 2010; Blanco 
et al., 2012, 2014). It has been reported that a traditional antide-
pressant regulated the GluR1/2 tetramers in the PFC (Ampuero 
et al., 2010). We also found that the chronic treatment of imi-
pramine enhanced GluR1/2 levels at the synapses (Figure 4E), 
suggesting that imipramine regulates GluR1/2 tetramers of 
AMPA receptors, which is consistent with previous studies (Du 
et al., 2004a, 2004b, 2007, 2008). However, it has been shown that 
drugs mediating the fast-acting antidepressant mechanisms, 
like cocaine, regulate the GluR1/3, instead of GluR1/2, in the PFC 
(Blanco et al., 2012, 2014). 3'-dA did not increase GluR2 levels at 
the synapses, suggesting that this regulation of increased AMPA 
synaptic transmission may be mediated through a subtype-spe-
cific manner and that other subtypes of AMPA tetramers, such 
as GluR1/3, might be involved. This is consistent with its fast-
acting antidepressant effect. 
Previous studies found that PFC was one of the most impor-
tant brain regions involved in depression. Clinical evidence has 
demonstrated that neuronal activity in the PFC is reduced in 
depressed patients, and could be restored by selective seroto-
nin reuptake inhibitor antidepressants (Kennedy et al., 2001; 
Fales et al., 2009). In rodent models, chronic stress decreased the 
expression levels of AMPA receptors, NMDA receptors, and vari-
ous synaptic proteins, induced the atrophy of distal dendrites 
of pyramidal cells, and damaged the dendritic spines in the PFC 
(Liston et al., 2006; Radley et al., 2008; Li et al., 2011). In addition, 
a recent study showed that the expression levels of GluR1 were 
decreased in rat PFCs, but not in HIPs after 7 days of chronic 
restraint stress, suggesting that the PFC is more susceptible to 
stress (Yuen et al., 2012). In this paper, we found that within 
45 min, 3'-dA enhanced GluR1 synaptic localization in the PFC 
(Figure 4B). </p>

<p>AMPA Receptor Signaling Regulated by 3'-dA 
Might be Essential for its Rapid and Robust 
Antidepressant Effect </p>

<p>A previous study showed that lithium exerts fast (1.5 days) and 
chronic antidepressant effects in mice TST and FST via up-
regulating the AMPA receptor subunits GluR1 and GluR2 in the 
HIP, and an AMPA inhibitor was able to block the antidepres-
sant effect of lithium (Gould et al., 2008). In this paper, we found 
that the effect of 3'-dA on up-regulating AMPA receptor sign-
aling at the synapses might be essential for the rapid antide-
pressant effects (Figures 1A and B, 3A, and 4B and C), and AMPA 
antagonist GYKI 52466 was able to block 3'-dA-induced rapid 
antidepressant effects (Figure 6). This is consistent with a recent 
clinical trial showing that Org 26576 (ionotropic AMPA-type glu-
tamate receptor enhancer) significantly improved symptoms 
in patients diagnosed as depressed by the Montgomery-Asberg 
Depression Rating Scale (Nations et al., 2012). 
3'-dA is the main effective component of Cordyceps Militaris, 
which has been used as a Chinese herb and food for hundreds 
of years. Other beneficial effects of 3'-dA, such as the anti-viral 
and anti-fungal effects, may also provide additional benefits to 
depressed patients, because viral or fungal infections contribute 
to or even cause depressive symptoms (Tuli et al., 2013). 3'-dA 
also improves the quality of sleep by increasing non-rapid eye 
movement sleep (Hu et al., 2013). Therefore, 3'-dA is considered 
relatively safe and beneficial for use as a potential novel anti-
depressant drug. In summary, in this paper we have identified 
a rapid and relatively safe antidepressant for the treatment 
of depression, mediated through enhancing prefrontal AMPA 
receptor synaptic plasticity. This discovery sheds light on the </p>

<p>development of a novel, effective, safe, and rapid drug for the 
devastating disorder of major depression. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Yunnan High-Level Professional 
Funding (2012HA004) from the Department of Science and 
Technology of Yunnan Province; General Program (81372360) 
from the National Natural Science Foundation of China; 
National Science Fund for Young Scholars (31300891) from 
the National Natural Science Foundation of China; Scientific 
Research Fund (2013Y366) from Yunnan Provincial Education 
Department; two Postgraduate Research Funds (2013J073, 
2014J004) from the Yunnan Provincial Education Department; 
Postgraduate Innovative Research Project (ynuy201340) from 
Yunnan University; Innovation Funding for Small and Medium-
sized Enterprise (Z10110100191034) from the Department of 
Science and Technology of Beijing; and Applied Basic Research 
Key Project of Yunnan Province (2011FA004). 
The authors thank Dr Li Zhang for his critical scientific 
reading. </p>

<p>Statement of Interest </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose, financial 
or otherwise. </p>







</text></tei>