<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4443294" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Objective: Lipid peroxides and their reactive aldehyde derivatives (LPPs) have been linked to obesity-related pathologies, but whether they have 
a causal role has remained unclear. Glutathione peroxidase 4 (GPx4) is a selenoenzyme that selectively neutralizes lipid hydroperoxides, and 
human gpx4 gene variants have been associated with obesity and cardiovascular disease in epidemiological studies. This study tested the 
hypothesis that LPPs underlie cardio-metabolic derangements in obesity using a high fat, high sucrose (HFHS) diet in gpx4 haploinsufficient mice 
(GPx4 
þ/À ) and in samples of human myocardium. </p>

<p>Methods: Wild-type (WT) and GPx4 
þ/À mice were fed either a standard chow (CNTL) or HFHS diet for 24 weeks, with metabolic and car-</p>

<p>diovascular parameters measured throughout. Biochemical and immuno-histological analysis was performed in heart and liver at termination of 
study, and mitochondrial function was analyzed in heart. Biochemical analysis was also performed on samples of human atrial myocardium from 
a cohort of 103 patients undergoing elective heart surgery. 
Results: Following HFHS diet, WT mice displayed moderate increases in 4-hydroxynonenal (HNE)-adducts and carbonyl stress, and a 1.5-fold 
increase in GPx4 enzyme in both liver and heart, while gpx4 haploinsufficient (GPx4 
þ/À ) mice had marked carbonyl stress in these organs </p>

<p>accompanied by exacerbated glucose intolerance, dyslipidemia, and liver steatosis. Although normotensive, cardiac hypertrophy was evident with 
obesity, and cardiac fibrosis more pronounced in obese GPx4 
þ/À mice. Mitochondrial dysfunction manifesting as decreased fat oxidation capacity </p>

<p>and increased reactive oxygen species was also present in obese GPx4 
þ/À but not WT hearts, along with up-regulation of pro-inflammatory and </p>

<p>pro-fibrotic genes. Patients with diabetes and hyperglycemia exhibited significantly less GPx4 enzyme and greater HNE-adducts in their hearts, 
compared with age-matched non-diabetic patients. 
Conclusion: These findings suggest LPPs are key factors underlying cardio-metabolic derangements that occur with obesity and that GPx4 
serves a critical role as an adaptive countermeasure. </p>

<p>The prevalence of obesity is rapidly spreading throughout the world 
with over 28% of adults having a body mass index (BMI) of !25 kg/ </p>

<p>m 
2 [1,2]. In addition to the increased risk for type 2 diabetes, a 
growing number of studies have reported a high prevalence of car-
diomyopathy in obese patients (w40% by some estimates) [3], with 
'preclinical' myocardial damage [4] and diastolic dysfunction already </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Pharmacology &amp; Toxicology, East Carolina University, Greenville, NC, United States 
2 Department of Physiology, East Carolina University, Greenville, NC, 
United States 
3 Department of Public Health, East Carolina University, Greenville, NC, United States </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>East Carolina Diabetes and Obesity Institute, East Carolina University, 
Greenville, NC, United States </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>East Carolina Heart Institute, East Carolina University, Greenville, NC, United States </p>

<p>*Corresponding author. Department of Pharmacology &amp; Toxicology, Brody School of Medicine, East Carolina University, BSOM 6S-11, 600 Moye Blvd., Greenville, NC 27834, 
United States. E-mail: andersonet@ecu.edu (E.J. Anderson). </p>

<p>Abbreviations: PUFA, polyunsaturated fatty acids; LPPs, lipid peroxidation end products; GPx4, glutathione peroxidase 4; HFHS, high fat, high sucrose; WT, wild type; CNTL, 
control; BMI, body mass index; 4-HNE, 4-hydroxynonenal; ROS, reactive oxygen species; RNS, reactive nitrogen species; HDL, high-density lipoprotein; TG, triglycerides; EF, 
ejection fraction; FS, fractional shortening; Nrf2, nuclear factor (erythroid-derived 2)-like 2; IL-1b, interleukin-1 beta; IL-6, interleukin-6; TNF-a, tumor necrosis factor-a; </p>

<p>iNOS, inducible nitric oxide synthase; RAGE, receptor for advanced glycation end products; Coll1a1, collagen, type I, alpha; Coll4a1, collagen, type IV, alpha 1; b-MHC, b </p>

<p>myosin heavy chain; TGF-b1, transforming growth factor beta 1; TGF-b2, transforming growth factor beta 2 </p>

<p>Received March 24, 2015 Revision received April 8, 2015 Accepted April 14, 2015 Available online 22 April 2015 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.molmet.2015.04.001 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>MOLECULAR METABOLISM 4 (2015) 493e506 Ó 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>



<p>evident in young adult ( 35 yrs) obese/diabetic patients [5] and even 
children [6]. Importantly, these cardiac derangements appear in the 
absence of detectable coronary disease or hypertension. Together, 
these findings strongly indicate a need for more careful examination 
of potential mechanisms that underlie cardiomyopathy in obese 
individuals. 
Polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs) are continuously oxidized in vivo 
through both enzymatic and non-enzymatic reactions [7,8], forming 
lipid peroxidation end products (LPPs) such as isoprostanes, isofurans, </p>

<p>thromboxanes, and a,b-unsaturated aldehydes [9], all of which have </p>

<p>biological effects [10e13]. These aldehydes cause post-translational 
modifications of proteins through Michael addition with lysines and 
histidines, and through covalent modification of sulfhydryl groups (e.g., 
cysteines) to form carbonyl adducts [14,15]. Due to this high degree of 
reactivity, many of these aldehydes have been proposed to be etiologic </p>

<p>agents in disease [7,14,16e21]. 4-hydroxynonenal (HNE) is a a,b-</p>

<p>unsaturated aldehyde derived from n-6 PUFA peroxidation, and HNE 
levels increase proportionally with ROS/RNS levels [22]. One recent 
report showed that HNE-modified albumin is significantly increased in 
the serum of type 2 diabetic patients [23]. 
Mitochondrial membranes are abundant with unsaturated fatty 
acids, which are prone to peroxidation [24e26]. The mitochondrion 
is also the primary source of cellular ROS, making it a major 
source of LPPs [27]. As a countermeasure, mitochondria contain an 
elaborate system of antioxidant and LPP-detoxifying enzymes. One 
of these is glutathione peroxidase 4 (GPx4), which resides in the 
mitochondrial inner membrane (in addition to nucleus and cytosol) 
to specifically scavenge lipid hydroperoxides [28e30]. GPx4 is one 
of a few antioxidant enzymes known to neutralize both simple and 
complex lipid hydroperoxides (e.g., Cholesterol hydroperoxide) 
[31,32]. It is the only member of the GPx super-family that is 
indispensable during development, with embryonic lethality of GPx4 
null mice occurring at stage E7.5 [33e35]. In recent genetic and 
epidemiological studies, variants of gpx4 that result in diminished 
content and/or catalytic activity have been associated with obesity 
[36], cardiovascular disease [37,38] and inflammation [39,40]. 
However, no experimental studies to date have explored GPx4 in 
the context of obesity or its related pathologies, and this may be a 
significant oversight given the well-known association between 
mitochondrial-derived oxidative stress and metabolic disease 
[41,42]. In this study, we tested the hypothesis that LPPs are a 
causal factor underlying cardio-metabolic derangements in 
obesity by investigating the effect of a long-term high fat, high 
sucrose (HFHS) diet in a mouse model of gpx4 haploinsufficiency 
(GPx4 
þ/À ) and in samples of human atrial myocardium obtained </p>

<p>from non-diabetic and diabetic patients undergoing elective heart 
surgery. </p>

<p>2. RESULTS </p>

<p>2.1. GPx4 deficiency in obesity leads to enhanced lipid 
peroxidation and carbonyl stress in liver, exacerbating insulin 
resistance and steatosis 
To test our hypothesis that LPPs underlie obesity-related pathologies 
we used a GPx4-deficient (GPx4 
þ/À ) mouse model. GPx4 
þ/À mice are </p>

<p>phenotypically indistinguishable from WT in the absence of an exog-
enous stressor but more susceptible to damage from radiation and 
environmental toxicants [43,44]. The rationale for using this mouse 
model was that it mimics the effect of previously identified gpx4 gene 
variants on GPx4 enzyme levels and activity in human cells [36,38,45]. 
Following HFHS diet no significant differences in adiposity or weight 
gain were observed between WT and GPx4 
þ/À mice, although obese </p>

<p>GPx4 
þ/À mice had substantial dyslipidemia and fasting hyperglycemia </p>

<p>with HFHS diet (Table 1). Whole body energy expenditure, determined 
by VO2 and VCO2 using indirect calorimetry, was not different between 
WT and GPx4 
þ/À mice, either with CNTL or HFHS diet (data not </p>

<p>shown). Glucose intolerance was exacerbated in the GPx4 
þ/À mice </p>

<p>compared with WT (Figure 1A), although serum insulin levels were 
increased with HFHS diet to equal extent regardless of genotype 
(Figure 1B). GPx4 enzyme levels in liver of WT mice increased 
significantly as a result of HFHS diet, although GPx4 
þ/À mice contain </p>

<p>significantly less enzyme than WT (Figure 1C and Supplemental 
Figure 1A). In parallel with the increase in GPx4, levels of HNE-
adducts in liver increased in WT with HFHS diet but were signifi-
cantly more pronounced in GPx4 
þ/À mice compared with WT. To </p>

<p>determine whether the increased lipid peroxidation in the GPx4 </p>

<p>þ/À </p>

<p>mice corresponded to a more severe liver pathology following HFHS 
diet, liver triglycerides and collagen were measured by oil red O and 
picrosirius red staining, respectively. GPx4 
þ/À mice displayed greater </p>

<p>liver steatosis (Figure 1D) and fibrosis (Figure 1E) than WT mice 
following HFHS diet. </p>

<p>2.2. Cardiac structural remodeling and fibrosis are exacerbated by 
GPx4 deficiency in obesity 
Previous studies have shown that HFHS diet-induced obesity causes 
significant cardiac hypertrophy and left ventricular (LV) diastolic 
dysfunction in rodent models [46e48]. Here, HFHS diet caused an 
increase in cardiac mass to a similar extent between WT and GPx4 </p>

<p>þ/À </p>

<p>mice (Figure 2A,E). However, compared with WT, GPx4 
þ/À mice </p>

<p>display significantly greater cardiomyocyte diameter (Figure 2E,F) and 
fibrosis (Figure 2B,C) following HFHS diet. Obese mice also have 
increased levels of serum brain natriuretic peptide (BNP, Figure 2G), 
indicative of ventricular wall stress. This evidence of cardiomyopathy 
exists in the absence of any changes in LV systolic function (Figure 2H), 
blood pressure (Figure 2I) or heart rate (Figure 2J) in the mice following </p>

<p>Table 1 e Body composition and metabolic parameters. </p>

<p>Variables 
WT 
CNTL </p>

<p>WT 
HFHS </p>

<p>GPx4 
þ/-CNTL 
GPx4 </p>

<p>þ/À </p>

<p>HFHS </p>

<p>p-value </p>

<p>Terminal body weight (g) 
34.5 AE 1.3 
48.0 AE 2.2 * 
35.8 AE 4.2 
48.5 AE 1.2 *x 
&lt;0.0001 
Fat mass (g) 
8.4 AE 1.0 
17.7 AE 0.9 * 
10.0 AE 2.9 </p>

<p>¤ </p>

<p>19.4 AE 0.8 *x 
0.0001 
Lean mass (g) 
21.6 AE 0.4 
26.0 AE 1.2 * 
22.3 AE 1.4 </p>

<p>¤ </p>

<p>24.9 AE 0.4 * 
0.004 
Body fat (%) 
24.0 AE 2.1 
36.9 AE 0.5 * 
31.3 AE 3.0 * 
40.0 AE 0.8 *x 
&lt;0.0001 
Fasting glucose (mg/dL) 
141.3 AE 4.1 
168.6 AE 14.2 * 
148.0 AE 3.7 
204.8 AE 11.3 *¤x 
0.007 
Cholesterol (mg/dL) 
51.0 AE 8.6 
72.8 AE 6.5 
34.0 AE 8.7 
103.5 AE 17.8 *x 
0.01 
Triglycerides (mg/dL) 
46.8 AE 6.3 
44.0 AE 10.6 
55.5 AE 1.5 
99.5 AE 11.3 *¤x 
0.003 
HDL cholesterol (mg/dL) 
74.9 AE 8.0 
96.7 AE 7.2 
53.1 AE 9.4 
118.4 AE 14.4 *x 
0.009 </p>

<p>All values expressed as mean AE S.E.M., n ¼ 4e6 per group. * P&lt;0.05 vs. WT-CNTL vs. ¤ P&lt;0.05 vs. WT-HFHS. x P&lt;0.05 vs. GPX4 
þ/-CNTL. </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>494 MOLECULAR METABOLISM 4 (2015) 493e506 Ó 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>

<p>HFHS diet, indicating that any cardiomyopathy which might be present 
in these mice is not due to increased afterload. 
Recently, in two independent experimental models of cardiac hyper-
trophy it was observed that GPx4 and Thioredoxin Reductase (TxnRd) 
were the only antioxidant seleno-enzymes to increase in the heart, 
suggesting that they are critical for cardiac compensatory response to 
hypertrophic stimuli [49,50]. A significant increase in GPx4 mRNA 
(Figure 3A) and enzyme content (Figure 3B and Supplemental 
Figure 1B) in myocardium of WT mice with HFHS diet was observed. 
Conversely, GPx4 
þ/À mice had lower levels of mRNA that did not </p>

<p>correspond to any significant change in GPx4 enzyme levels following 
HFHS diet. Levels of HNE-adducts (Figure 3C) and protein carbonyls 
(Figure 3C) do increase moderately in WT hearts with HFHS diet, 
although GPx4 deficiency leads to a striking increase in this protein 
carbonylation with obesity. To determine if GPx4 deficiency and 
augmented carbonyl stress in obesity triggered a compensatory redox 
adaptive response in the heart, expression of a number of antioxidant 
genes were examined. GPx4 
þ/À mice were found to have increased </p>

<p>expression of several antioxidant genes following HFHS diet 
(Figure 3D). </p>

<p>2.3. GPx4 deficiency causes mitochondrial abnormalities and up-
regulation of cardiac inflammation and fibrosis signaling pathways 
with obesity 
Mitochondrial dysfunction, as characterized by decreased ATP and/or 
respiration combined with increased ROS, has been linked to several 
obesity-related pathologies, including insulin resistance and cardio-
myopathy, and recent studies have implicated a role for mitochondrial 
protein carbonylation in mediating this dysfunction [51e53]. Param-
eters of mitochondrial function in permeabilized LV myofibers were 
examined to assess the relationship between GPx4 deficiency, 
carbonyl stress, and mitochondria in the obese myocardium. GPx4 </p>

<p>enzyme content was measured in the mitochondrial fraction isolated 
from whole hearts. GPx4 increased in cardiac mitochondria of WT mice 
with HFHS diet, while total levels of GPx4 were lower and remained 
that way following HFHS diet in the GPx4 
þ/À mice (Figure 4A and </p>

<p>Supplemental Figure 2A). 
It was expected that mitochondrial GPx4 deficiency would potentially 
lead to a greater degree of mitochondrial membrane lipid peroxidation 
and reactive aldehyde formation. Here, the amount of mitochondrial 
HNE-adducts were greater in GPx4 
þ/À hearts than WT, and the HFHS </p>

<p>diet increased the relative amount of these adducts in both WT and 
GPx4 
þ/À mice (Figure 4B and Supplemental Figure 2B). These </p>

<p>increased HNE-adducts may have functional consequences since 
recent studies have documented that mitochondrial HNE-adducts 
correspond to decreased oxidative phosphorylation in diabetic heart 
mitochondria [74,75]. Moreover, another report highlights the impor-</p>

<p>tance of mitochondrial fatty acid b-oxidation as a metabolic 'sink' for </p>

<p>HNE [72]. In WT hearts, both basal and maximal ADP-stimulated 
palmitoyl-L-carnitine supported respiration was markedly increased 
following HFHS diet, while these rates were unchanged with HFHS diet 
in the GPx4 
þ/À mice (Figure 4B). </p>

<p>In a previous study we reported that the selenoenzyme thioredoxin 
reductase-2 (TxnRd2) increased in rat heart with HFHS diet [54], 
corresponding to a decreased rate of mitochondrial H 2 O 2 emission in 
the obese rat heart. Other groups have also reported decreased 
mitochondrial ROS with obesity/diabetes in mouse [55] and rat models 
[56]. Given our previous findings, combined with the fact that TxnRd2 
expression was increased in GPx4 
þ/À hearts with HFHS diet </p>

<p>(Figure 3E), we sought to ascertain whether a similar adaptation in 
redox buffering was occurring in cardiac mitochondria of these mice. 
Here, using paired H 2 O 2 emission experiments in the absence and 
presence of the TxnRd2 inhibitor auranofin, a dramatic (w4-fold) in-
crease in total H 2 O 2 emission was observed in permeabilized </p>

<p>Figure 1: Glycemic control and liver biochemistry/pathology. Shown in A are oral glucose tolerance tests, along with fed-state serum insulin levels B after 24 weeks on the </p>

<p>diet. In C are representative immunoblots of GPx4 and HNE-adducts in liver from 4 individual mice in each group, along with the corresponding b-actin loading control. </p>

<p>Representative images of liver triglycerides stained with oil red O D, and collagen stained with picrosirius red under polarized light E are shown for each group. Images are 
representative of 16 image fields captured per mouse, n ¼ 2e3 mice per treatment group. Data shown as mean AE S.E.M., n ¼ 7e8 mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. CNTL within 
genotype, yP &lt; 0.05 vs. WT-HFHS. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR METABOLISM 4 (2015) 493e506 Ó 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>



<p>myofibers prepared from obese GPx4 
þ/À mice fed HFHS diet, while a </p>

<p>decrease in this ROS emission was observed in the obese WT mice 
following HFHS diet (Figure 4C). Auranofin exposure significantly 
increased the rate of mitochondrial ROS in the obese WT mice but not 
obese GPx4 
þ/À mice. </p>

<p>Chronic, low-grade inflammation in the obese heart is known to cause 
profibrotic and hypertrophic signaling. Although it has been difficult to 
fully ascertain the exact nature of the relationship between inflam-
mation and cardiac remodeling, some investigators have proposed that 
activation of the receptor for advanced glycation end products (RAGE) 
may play a role. RAGE belongs to a family of pattern recognition re-
ceptors for AGE and has been studied extensively in the context of 
diabetes-related pathologies [57,58]. Increased expression of RAGE is 
present in the hearts of obese GPx4 
þ/À mice (Figure 5A), and this is </p>

<p>consistent with the increased carbonyl stress present in these hearts 
since reactive aldehydes such as HNE are known to potentiate AGE 
formation [59]. Activation of RAGE has been shown to induce chronic 
activation of nuclear factor kappa-light-chain-enhancer of activated B 
cells (NFkB), which, in turn, activates further inflammatory pathways. 
Furthermore, there is extensive crosstalk between the RAGE and 
Transforming Growth Factor-Beta (TGF-b) family of proteins [60e62]. 
Notably, the hearts of obese GPx4 
þ/À mice also displayed greater pro-</p>

<p>inflammatory cytokine expression and genes involved in fibrosis and 
hypertrophy compared with WT following HFHS diet, while only a 
modest increase in a few select genes was observed with HFHS diet in 
WT hearts (Figure 5A &amp; B). </p>

<p>2.4. Cardiac GPx4 deficiency is associated with increased HNE-
adducts and relative risk (RR) for diabetes in humans 
Next, we sought to determine whether there is an association between 
GPx4 and lipid-derived carbonyl stress in human heart and, also, to 
examine whether there is a connection between these parameters and 
human metabolic disease. In a small pilot study of w20 patients, we 
previously reported greater levels of HNE-protein adducts in the hearts 
of hyperglycemic type 2 diabetic patients, and these increased HNE-
adducts were accompanied by depletion of cardiac glutathione and 
increased mitochondrial ROS production [63]. Here, using samples of 
atrial myocardium obtained from patients (n ¼ 103) undergoing 
elective cardiac surgery (Table 2), we observed that diabetic patients 
had significantly less cardiac GPx4 than non-diabetic patients 
(Figure 6A), and this corresponded with greater levels of HNE-adducts 
in the diabetic hearts (Figure 6B). A multivariable regression analysis 
was performed on quartiles of cardiac GPx4 and tertiles of HNE-
adducts, and cardiac GPx4 was found to be negatively associated 
while HNE-adducts positively associated with RR for diabetes in these 
patients (Table 3). To determine if hyperglycemia was associated with 
cardiac GPx4 or HNE-adducts in these patients, a multiple linear 
regression model was applied, adjusting for sex. No significant as-
sociation between cardiac GPx4 or HNE-adduct levels and HbA1c was 
observed in these patients (Table 3 and Supplemental Figure 1). 
Similar to what was observed with the WT-HFHS mice, cardiac GPx4 
content was positively correlated with cardiac HNE-adducts in these 
patients (Figure 6C), suggesting that GPx4 is an adaptive response of </p>

<p>Figure 2: Cardiac structural and functional parameters. Panels shown are representative images of whole hearts A, cardiac collagen stained with picosirius red under 
polarized light B,C, and Masson's Trichrome stained cardiac tissue D, from mice within each study group. Shown in E are heart weight/tibia length ratio, cardiomyocyte diameter F, 
and serum BNP levels G. Cardiac contractility H, mean arterial pressure I, and heart rate J are shown for each group Images are representative of 16 image fields captured per 
mouse, n ¼ 2e3 mice per treatment group. Data in E-J are shown as mean AE S.E.M., n ¼ 6e8 mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. WT-CNTL, yP &lt; 0.05 vs. WT-HFHS, xP &lt; 0.05 vs. 
GPx4 </p>

<p>þ/-</p>

<p>-CNTL. </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>496 MOLECULAR METABOLISM 4 (2015) 493e506 Ó 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>

<p>Figure 3: Cardiac GPx4, protein carbonylation and redox signaling. Shown here is GPx4 mRNA expression A and protein content B in whole hearts from mice used in this 
study. Representative immunoblot of HNE-adducts and hydrazide-labeled protein carbonyls C are shown from 3 individual mice in each group, Expression of redox and phase II 
detoxifying genes are shown in D. Data shown in A &amp; D are means AE S.E.M, n ¼ 5e7 per group. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. WT-CNTL, ¤ P &lt; 0.05 vs. WT-HFHS, xP &lt; 0.05 vs. GPx4 
þ/--CNTL. </p>

<p>CAT-Catalase; TrxII-Thioredoxin reductase II; GR-Glutathione Reductase; GPX1-Glutathione Peroxidase1; NQO1-NAD(P)H:quinine oxidoreductase; HO-1-Heme oxygenase-1; 
GSTA1-glutathione s-transferase-1. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR METABOLISM 4 (2015) 493e506 Ó 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>



<p>Figure 4: Cardiac mitochondrial GPx4 and functional parameters. A representative immunoblot of GPx4 protein A and HNE-adducts B along with corresponding COX IV loading 
control are shown of isolated cardiac mitochondria obtained from mice used in this study. In C are maximal ADP-stimulated rates of mitochondrial respiration (JO 2 ) supported by 
palmitoyl-L-carnitine in permeabilized cardiac myofibers from these mice. Shown in D are rates of mitochondrial H 2 O 2 emission (mito-JH 2 O 2 ) in phosphorylating state supported by </p>

<p>palmitoyl-L-carnitine þ 100 mM ADP, in the absence (À) and presence (þ) of the TxnRd2 inhibitor Auranofin. Data shown in C &amp; D are means AE S.E.M, N ¼ 4e6 per group. </p>

<p>*P &lt; 0.05 vs. all other groups for each respiratory state, yP &lt; 0.05 vs. WT-HFHS, xP &lt; 0.05 vs. GPx4 
þ/--CNTL, #P &lt; 0.05 for Auranofin effect within group. </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>498 MOLECULAR METABOLISM 4 (2015) 493e506 Ó 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>

<p>the tissue to persistent oxidative stress. Interestingly, the ratio of HNE-
adducts/GPx4 was much higher in diabetic than non-diabetic hearts 
(Figure 6D), indicating that the GPx4 adaptive response has been over-
whelmed or compromised in these patients. </p>

<p>3. DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Only an increased understanding of the mechanisms underlying 
obesity-related pathologies will enable physicians to better manage 
diseases associated with this emerging epidemic. Lipid peroxides and 
their reactive aldehyde derivatives have been postulated to play a 
causal role in obesity-related cardio-metabolic diseases, and emerging 
epidemiologic data has reported a link between polymorphisms and 
mutations in gpx4 and human diseases, including obesity. Together, 
these previous findings suggest that GPx4 may be an adaptive 
component that serves a protective role against the persistent oxidative 
stress in obesity. The present study tested this hypothesis in a 
translational model of HFHS diet-induced obese GPx4 
þ/À (i.e. GPx4 </p>

<p>deficient) mice, combined with cardiac tissue samples obtained from 
patients undergoing elective cardiac surgery. The findings from this 
study demonstrate that GPx4 deficiency with diet-induced obesity 
leads to significant increases in lipid peroxide-derived aldehydes, 
corresponding to more severe cardio-metabolic derangements 
including glucose intolerance, dyslipidemia, liver steatosis, and cardiac 
hypertrophy and fibrosis. Abnormalities in mitochondrial function in 
hearts from the obese GPx4 
þ/À mice implicate a role for the enzyme in </p>

<p>protecting that critical organelle from oxidative damage in obesity. </p>

<p>Furthermore, the adverse cardiac remodeling observed in the obese 
GPx4 
þ/À mice was accompanied by up-regulation of genes involved in </p>

<p>cardiac inflammation and remodeling, illustrating the importance of 
carbonyl stress as a causal factor in these pathways. Lastly, the 
relationship between decreased cardiac GPx4 and increased HNE-
adducts and human metabolic disease was confirmed by studying 
cardiac tissue samples obtained from non-diabetic and diabetic pa-
tients. Collectively, these observations allow for a proposed model of 
GPx4 as a protective adaptation in obesity (as shown in the Graphical 
Abstract). Clearly, when lipid peroxidation increases as a result of 
persistent oxidative stress in obesity/nutrient overload, GPx4 is upre-
gulated to compensate (Figures 1 and 3). However, over time and 
possibly due to underlying genetic causes, GPx4 becomes over-
whelmed in an obese individual and HNE-adducts increase (along with 
numerous other LPPs that were not measured in this study). The 
consequence of this is increased inflammation, mitochondrial 
dysfunction (and likely potentiation of mitochondrial ROS), and the 
broad cardio-metabolic pathologies that are known to follow (e.g., 
diabetes, cardiomyopathy, liver disease). 
These findings stand in contrast to preceding studies of diet-induced 
obesity in antioxidant-deficient models. One recent study of high fat-
fed GPx1-deficient mice (whole body GPx1 
À/À ) found that systemic </p>

<p>oxidative stress increased with obesity as expected, but these mice 
were actually protected from insulin resistance and liver steatosis [98]. 
In a study using high fat diet in SOD2 
þ/À mice (also exhibiting greater </p>

<p>oxidative stress), insulin sensitivity was again unchanged with obesity, </p>

<p>although a modest effect on pancreatic b-cell release of insulin was </p>

<p>observed [99]. Another intriguing study used high fat diet in a 
glutathione-deficient (GclmÀ/À) mouse model. The authors found that 
despite a huge increase in systemic oxidative stress with the diet, 
these mice were also protected from increased adiposity, insulin 
resistance and steatosis, possibly due to an increase in basal energy 
expenditure [100]. Given these recent findings, the fact that GPx4 
haploinsufficiency alone can induce such a damaging effect on cardio-
metabolic parameters with HFHS diet implies that lipid peroxides and 
their LPP derivatives are a distinctive form of oxidative stress that must 
play a very prominent etiological role in obesity-related cardio-meta-
bolic diseases. 
Deleterious effects of lipid-derived aldehydes in biological systems 
have been well known for many years. For example, nucleophilic 
attack of cysteine residues by aldehydes has negative ramifications on 
metabolic pathways in the cell [14,64]. A recent mass spectrometric 
analysis of cysteine oxidation status in hearts from mice fed a dia-
betogenic diet for 8 months showed that w40% of total oxidized 
cysteines are mitochondrial in origin [65]. Proteomic analysis of 
mitochondria from diabetic rat hearts reveals an increased formation of 
carbonyl adducts (e.g. HNE, MDA) with complexes of the electron 
transport chain and respiratory complexes, and these adducts corre-
spond to a reduction in enzyme activity [18]. Our data suggest that 
GPx4 protects against cardiac mitochondrial dysfunction with obesity 
as the obese GPx4 
þ/À mice had very high levels of carbonyl stress in </p>

<p>their hearts (Figure 3), particularly HNE-adducts in the cardiac mito-
chondria (Figure 4B), accompanied by mitochondrial dysfunction, as 
compared with obese WT mice. Several studies have shown that GPx4 
preserves ATP production and attenuates cytochrome c release in the 
mitochondria under oxidative stress [66e68]. Cardiac-specific over-
expression of mitochondrial GPx4 is protective in models of cardiac 
ischemia/reperfusion injury and in a streptozotocin (STZ)-induced 
diabetes model [69,70]. GPx4 exists as both short (i.e., mitochondrial-
localized) and long (i.e., cytosolic-localized) isoforms, yet only deletion 
of the former is lethal in mice [67]. Thioredoxin Reductase is the only </p>

<p>Figure 5: Cardiac inflammatory and pro-fibrotic/hypertrophic gene expression. 
Expression of pro-inflammatory A, pro-fibrotic and hypertrophy genes B are shown in </p>

<p>hearts from all four groups of mice in this study. B-MHC-b-Myosin Heavy Chain; </p>

<p>Coll1a1-Collagen 1a1; Coll4a1-Collagen 4a1; TGFb1 and 2 -Transforming Growth 
Factorb 1 and 2; IL-b-Interleukin-1 Beta; IL-6 -Interleukin À6; TNF-a-Tumor Necrosis 
Factor-alpha; iNOS-Inducible nitric oxide synthase; RAGE-Receptor for Advanced 
Glycation End Products. All target genes normalized to 18S ribosome RNA. Data shown 
are means AE S.E.M, N ¼ 4e6 per group. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. WT-CNTL, ¤ P &lt; 0.05 vs. WT-
HFHS, xP &lt; 0.05 vs. GPx4 
þ/--CNTL. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR METABOLISM 4 (2015) 493e506 Ó 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>



<p>other essential selenoenzyme identified to date, and this enzyme also 
has both mitochondrial (TxnRd2) and cytosolic (TxnRd1) isoforms [71]. 
In the present study, increased mitochondrial H 2 O 2 emission was 
observed in hearts of lean GPx4 
þ/À mice following the inhibition of </p>

<p>TxnRd2 with auranofin (Figure 4C), although auranofin did not signif-
icantly affect the rate in the obese GPx4 
þ/À mice (which was already </p>

<p>much greater than all other groups). This suggests that mitochondrial 
lipid peroxide-scavenging with GPx4 and the thioredoxin redox couple 
are both important adaptive responses of cardiac mitochondria in 
obesity-related cardiac hypertrophy and that TxnRd2 cannot appro-
priately compensate for GPx4 deficiency within cardiac mitochondria if 
animals are obese. </p>

<p>A recent study showed that fatty acid b-oxidation is a novel HNE </p>

<p>clearance pathway in heart [72]. Considering the diminished rates of 
maximal palmitoyl carnitine-supported respiration observed in the 
obese GPx4 
þ/À hearts, it is plausible that the elevated carbonyl stress </p>

<p>observed in the hearts of these mice is a result of both increased 
mitochondrial ROS production (which initiates more lipid peroxidation) 
as well as a disruption of aldehyde detoxification pathways. The 
decreased GPx4 and correspondingly increased HNE-adducts seen 
here in myocardium of diabetic patients support our previous obser-
vations of decreased palmitoyl-L-carnitine supported respiration and 
increased mitochondrial ROS in diabetic human hearts [42,73]. A link 
between mitochondrial HNE-adduct formation and decreased oxidative 
phosphorylation in diabetic heart mitochondria has recently been made 
[74,75], and our findings suggest that GPx4 deficiency may underlie 
these oxidative modifications. High variability in dietary fat may also be 
a contributor to the greater levels of cardiac HNE-adducts in the dia-
betic patients, as it has been reported that diets consisting of high fat 
mixed with carbohydrate, or high fat alone, can lead to drastically </p>

<p>Table 2 e Patient clinical and demographic characteristics. </p>

<p>Variables 
Diabetes 
n (%) </p>

<p>No diabetes 
n (%) </p>

<p>p-value </p>

<p>Age 
Mean AE SD 
64 AE 9.28 
61 AE 11 
0.49 
Median (IQR) 
65 (16) 
60 (17) 
Sex 
Female 
7 (14) 
1 (2) 
Male 
42 (85) 
53 (97) 
0.026 
Race 
White 
41 (83) 
47 (86) 
0.78 
Black 
8 (16) 
7 (13) 
BMI 
Mean AE SD 
31 AE 6.6 
30 AE 5.3 
0.46 
Median (IQR) 
30 (7.4) 
29 (4.5) 
Preoperative medications </p>

<p>b-blockers </p>

<p>34 (69) 
41 (75) 
0.87 
ACEi/ARBs 
15 (31) 
22 (41) 
0.79 
Diuretics 
21 (43) 
20 (37) 
0.69 
CCBs 
10 (20) 
13 (24) 
0.89 
Diabetic medications 
43 (87) 
2 (4) 
&lt;0.0001 
Insulin 
32 (65) 
2 (4) 
Metformin 
15 (31) 
0 
Sulfonylureas 
4 (8) 
0 
Glitazones 
1 (2) 
0 
GLP-1 agonist 
2 (4) 
0 
DDP-4 inhibitor 
3 (6) 
0 
Statins 
41 (83) 
46 (84) 
0.94 
Nitrates 
19 (39] 
32 (59) 
0.65 
Heart failure 
8 (16) 
5 (9) 
0.31 
LVEF (%) 
51.8 AE 3.9 
53.6 AE 6.4 
0.87 </p>

<p>Sample size N ¼ 103 for GPx4, N ¼ 61 for HNE-adduct. </p>

<p>Figure 6: GPx4 content and HNE-adducts in human myocardium. Total GPx4 enzyme content A and HNE-adducts B are shown in atrial myocardium obtained from non-
diabetic and diabetic patients undergoing elective heart surgery. Shown in C is association between HNE-adducts and GPx4 enzyme in these heart samples, and the ratio of 
HNE-adduct to GPx4 enzyme are depicted in D. Each symbol corresponds to one individual patient (N ¼ 103, see Table 2 for demographics and clinical variables). P-value 
computed using Friedman's nonparametric test for central tendency, adjusting for sex. </p>

<p>Original article </p>



<p>www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>

<p>different outcomes in HNE accumulation in oxidative tissues [101]. 
Other studies directed at examining the role that alternative aldehyde-
producing (e.g., monoamine oxidase) and detoxifying enzymes (e.g., 
aldehyde dehydrogenases) may have in pathologies of obese/diabetic 
hearts may also be useful [64]. In addition, an improved understanding 
of the regulation of selenocysteine status may serve as a major clue to 
uncovering the mechanisms that govern the progression to mal-
adaptive remodeling in hearts of patients with metabolic disease. 
Epidemiological studies of Keshan's disease, a cardiomyopathy 
endemic to regions of China, confirm that the heart is highly sus-
ceptible to injury resulting from disturbances to selenocysteine en-
zymes. Cardiomyopathy in Keshan's disease manifests as acute 
cardiac fibrosis and mitochondrial dysfunction [76], a phenotype that is 
strikingly similar to the GPx4 
þ/À mice in the present study. </p>

<p>Aside from measurements of liver steatosis and serum lipids, our study 
did not explore the potential contribution of altered lipid metabolism 
that might exist in these mice. Lipotoxicity is a consistent feature of 
cardio-metabolic disease in both humans and animal models of obesity 
[77e82] and therefore may contribute to the severe liver and cardiac 
pathology observed in the obese GPx4 
þ/À mice. The obese GPx4 </p>

<p>þ/À </p>

<p>mice do not possess significantly greater adiposity than obese WT, as 
determined by % body fat. However, we cannot exclude that there may 
have been differences in adipose distribution between groups. It is also 
known that GPx4 directly modulates the lipoxygenase and cyclo-
oxygenase II enzyme systems, and, when viewed in this context, the 
increased cardiac inflammation present in obese GPx4 
þ/À mice sup-</p>

<p>ports a potential role for prostaglandins and other oxidized lipids in 
mediating the severe metabolic pathologies in this model. Thus, we 
cannot exclude the contribution of these mediators in the obese 
GPx4 
þ/À mice. Other studies have documented that proteolysis and </p>

<p>autophagy become compromised with carbonyl stress, and the 
diminished activity of these cellular processes may also explain the 
more severe phenotype observed in the obese GPx4 
þ/À hearts [83,84]. </p>

<p>None of these alternative pathways were explored in the present study. 
It is anticipated that these findings will serve to lay a foundation for 
future mechanistic studies directed at understanding how LPPs 
contribute to obesity-related pathologies and the adaptive role of GPx4. 
Considering that the most severe effects observed in the obese GPx4 </p>

<p>þ/ </p>

<p>À mice were evident in oxidative tissues (i.e., liver, heart, muscle), it </p>

<p>will be very important in future studies to identify the cell-and tissue-
specific role of GPx4 in mediating lipid peroxidation and carbonyl stress 
with obesity. Furthermore, our findings have clinical implications as 
they suggest that patients exhibiting decreased GPx4 expression and 
activity might be predisposed to obesity-related cardio-metabolic 
diseases. Indeed, clinical studies and human cell models have shown 
that GPx4 expression and activity vary widely in response to envi-
ronmental and nutritional cues [38,45,85e88]. Finally, although our 
understanding of the role of lipid-derived aldehydes and carbonyl 
stress in the etiology of obesity-related diseases is in its infancy, it is 
important to recognize that compounds that scavenge HNE and other 
lipid-derived aldehydes specifically, such as histidine-containing di-
peptides, may be very useful in this regard [89,90,102] and have 
experienced some success in pre-clinical testing and even clinical 
trials [91e93]. Thus, further research into novel therapeutics targeting 
carbonyl stress will be important for mitigating the numerous cardio-
metabolic diseases that accompany this rising epidemic of obesity. </p>

<p>4. METHODS </p>

<p>4.1. Mouse model and study design 
Animal care and experimental procedures were performed with 
approval from the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of East 
Carolina University and were in compliance with the National Institutes 
of Health's Guide for Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. C57BL6/J 
female mice (Jackson Laboratory) were crossed to male GPx4 
þ/À mice </p>

<p>and pups were genotyped by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using 
primers described in [43]. At 8e12 weeks, WT and GPx4 
þ/À male and </p>

<p>female age-matched littermates (n ¼ 6) were randomly assigned to 
groups and individually housed. Mice were fed either control (CNTL-
TD110367) or high fat high sucrose (HFHS-TD110365) diet from 
Harlan-Teklad Laboratories (Madison, WI) ad libidum for 25 weeks. 
The composition of this diet was a special formulation consisting of 
mixed saturated and n-6 PUFA (44.6% kcal/g fat), with high sucrose 
(34% kcal/g) content [54]. Mice were housed at controlled temperature 
and a 12hr light/dark cycle was maintained. At the end of the diet 
period, all live animal metabolic and echocardiographic measurements 
were made 1e2 weeks prior to tissue collection to allow for a 'wash-
out period' to minimize artifact attributable to additional stress that 
may have been introduced by these procedures. </p>

<p>4.2. Patient enrollment and myocardial tissue collection 
The Institutional Review Board of the Brody School of Medicine at East 
Carolina University approved all aspects of this study. Adult patients 
undergoing primary, non-emergent elective coronary artery bypass graft 
(CABG) or CABG/valve surgery between January 2011 and December 
2014 were enrolled for this study. Demographic and clinical variables 
for these patients, including preoperative cardiovascular and metabolic 
drugs, are listed in Table 2 according to diabetes status. Those having 
prior cardiac surgery, history of arrhythmia, or severely enlarged atria 
(&gt;4.0 cm) were excluded from the study. Atrial appendage biopsies 
were obtained from each patient as previously described [94], directly 
prior to institution of cardiopulmonary bypass. Myocardium was 
dissected from the endocardial side of the biopsy, rinsed briefly and 
frozen in liquid N 2 . All samples were rapidly processed this way to 
minimize protein and mRNA degradation across patients. </p>

<p>4.3. Metabolic parameters 
Body weight of the mice was recorded on a weekly basis throughout 
HFHS diet. Body composition was analyzed by nuclear-MRI (EchoMRI </p>

<p>Table 3 e Multivariable analysis of GPx4 and HNE-adducts in human heart. </p>

<p>GPx4 content (ug/ml) 
Diabetes 
n (%) </p>

<p>No diabetes 
n (%) </p>

<p>RR (95% CI) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mean AE SD 
6.2 AE 4.2 
8.7 AE 5.9 
P ¼ 0.034 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Median (IQR) 
6.0 (5.2) 
6.7 (6.6) 
Q1 ( 3.9) 
17 (35) 
9 (17) 
1.0 Referent 
Q2 (&gt;3.9e6.3) 
10 (20) 
15 (28) 
0.65 (0.37e1.1) 
Q3 (&gt;6.3e9.4) 
13 (27) 
13 (24) 
0.74 (0.47e1.2) 
Q4 (&gt;9.4) 
9 (18) 
17 (31) 
0.58 (0.31e1.1) 
P trend ¼ 0.063 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>HNE content (mM) 
Mean AE SD 
18 AE 8.3 
14 AE 9.8 
P ¼ 0.028 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Median (IQR) 
16 (11) 
11 (12) 
T1 ( 9.0) 
3 (10) 
21 (47) 
1.0 Referent 
T2 (&gt;9.0e17) 
14 (47) 
11 (24) 
4.2 (1.4e13) 
T3 (&gt;17) 
13 (43) 
13 (29) 
3.9 (1.2e12) 
P trend ¼ 0.050 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>a Relative Risk (RR) and 95% Confidence Interval (CI), adjusted for sex. 
b P-value computed using Friedman's Nonparametric test for central tendency, </p>

<p>adjusting for sex. 
c P-value computed using the likelihood ratio trend test, adjusting for sex. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR METABOLISM 4 (2015) 493e506 Ó 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>



<p>700 Echo Medical Systems, Houston, TX). An oral glucose tolerance 
test (dose-0.5 g/kg) was performed following a w4 h fast in week 22 
of the HFHS diet period. Glucose levels were measured using a 
standard glucometer (OneTouch UltraMini, LifeScan, Milpitas, CA) in 
blood collected from a tail nick. Serum cholesterol, high-density li-
poprotein (HDL), and triglycerides (TG) were analyzed using UniCel DxC 
600 (Beckman Coulter, Indianapolis, IN). </p>

<p>4.4. Assessment of cardiovascular function 
At end of the diet intervention, blood pressure was determined by non-
invasive tail-cuff plethysmography (SC1000, Hattaras Instruments, 
Cary, NC). Mice were acclimated to the procedure for 3 days, and the 
average of blood pressure readings made over 3 consecutive days was 
recorded. A single recording was an average of 10 measurements after 
5 acclimatization cycles, with duration no longer than 10 min, at 
approximately the same time every day. Also at this time, high-
resolution echocardiography was performed on fully conscious mice 
using a 30 MHz transducer (Vevo 2100, VisualSonics, Toronto, ON) to 
assess cardiac function and structural parameters in vivo. Parasternal 
long-and short-axis views were captured in M-mode and recordings 
analyzed using system software. </p>

<p>4.5. Liver and cardiac histology 
Mice were anesthetized with isoflurane. Hearts (n ¼ 2/group) were 
stopped with KCl, fixed in Zinc Fixative then embedded in paraffin. 
Next, they were cut cross-sectionally, stained in Hematoxylin and eosin 
or picosirus red (collagen), then viewed under polarized light. Livers 
from these animals were fixed, embedded and stained in a similar 
fashion, with the exception that oil red O was used for liver tri-
glycerides. Images of each heart were captured at 20X. The car-
diomyocyte diameter of 8e10 myocytes from 5 captured images per 
animal was analyzed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Image J</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://imagej.nih.gov/ij</rs>/) by an 
individual blinded to the treatment group. </p>

<p>4.6. Preparation of permeabilized cardiac myofibers and 
mitochondrial function measurements 
All procedures for these measurements have been described in detail 
by our group previously [42,54,73,95]. The mice were anesthetized 
with isoflurane and rapidly euthanized by pneumothorax. Blood was 
collected for serum analysis via cardiac puncture. Whole hearts were 
dissected, weighed, and a small portion of the left ventricle (LV) was 
cut for preparation of permeabilized myofibers (w30 mg) and placed 
in Buffer X containing (in mM): 7.23 K 2 EGTA, 2.77 CaK 2 EGTA, 20 
Imidazole, 20 Taurine, 5.7 ATP, 14.3 Phosphocreatine, 6.56 MgCl 2 -
6H 2 O and 50 MES (pH 7.1, 295 mOsm). Of the remaining LV/septum, 
one portion was used for standard mitochondrial isolation, and another 
was snap frozen in liquid N 2 and stored at À80 C for further </p>

<p>biochemical analysis. Following permeabilization in 50 mg/ml saponin </p>

<p>for 30 min, fibers were transferred to Buffer Z containing (in mM): 
110 K-MES, 35 KCl, 1 EGTA, 5 K 2 HPO 2 , 3 MgCl 2 -6H 2 O, and 5 mg/ml 
BSA (pH 7.4, 295 mOsm) and remained in Buffer Z with 20uM 
Blebbstatin on a rotator at 4 C until analysis (&lt;1.5 h). Fibers were 
then transferred to an Oroboros O2K (Oroboros Instruments, Innsbruck, 
Austria) where respiration was recorded in Buffer Z þ 20uM Bleb-
bistatin, 20 mM Creatine at 30 C. Respiration (JO 2 ) measurements 
were performed following addition of 125uM palmitoyl-
carnitine þ 1 mM malate followed by 4 mM ADP. H 2 O 2 emission was 
measured using a spectrofluorometer (Photon Technology In-</p>

<p>struments, Birmingham, NJ) in Buffer Z þ 20uM Blebbistatin, 10 mM </p>

<p>Amplex Red, 1 U/ml horseradish peroxidase, 25 U/ml superoxide dis-
mutase. For H 2 O 2 measurements, respiratory substrates used were </p>

<p>125 palmitoyl-carnitine, 2 mM Malate þ100 mM ADP, 5 mM glucose </p>

<p>and 1 U/ml hexokinase (i.e., phosphorylating state) followed by 
sequential addition of 5 mM glutamate then 5 mM succinate. Once 
mitochondrial experiments completed, fibers were collected, rinsed in 
ddH 2 O to remove excess salts, and lyophilized (Labconco, Kansas City, 
MO). Fibers were then weighted on a microbalance (Mettler Toledo, 
Denver, CO) and mitochondrial JO 2 (oxygen consumption rate) and 
JH 2 O 2 (peroxide emission rate) were normalized to dry weight. </p>

<p>4.7. Real-time qPCR of gene expression 
Cardiac samples (w10 mg) were homogenized in glass grinders 
(Kimble Chase, Vineland, NJ) then subjected to Proteinase K digestion. 
All materials used in RNA extraction were provided in RNeasy 
Ò Fibrous </p>

<p>Tissue Mini Kit (Qiagen Inc, Valencia, CA cat# 74704). Reverse Tran-
scription was performed using the iScript Ô cDNA Kit (Biorad Labo-
ratories, Hercules, CA cat# 170e8891). The SsoAdvanced Ô SYBER </p>

<p>Ò </p>

<p>Green reaction cocktail was used in the amplification and detection of 
DNA in RT-PCR. All protocols were performed according to product 
specifications unless otherwise stated. Cycle threshold (C(t)) values 
were converted to relative gene expression levels using the 2-DDC(t) 
method and normalized to the level of 18S ribosomal RNA. Data are 
reported as fold-change in gene expression (arbitrary units) AE S.E.M. 
relative to WT-CNTL mice (n ¼ 4e5 per group). The sequences and 
references for the primers used in qRT-PCR are listed in Supplemental 
Table 1. </p>

<p>4.8. Mitochondria isolation 
The technique applied has been modified from methods previously 
described [96,97]. Briefly, w100 mg of cardiac tissue was excised 
and added to a petri dish with ice. The tissue was minced for 4e5 min, 
until it could pass through a pipette, and subjected to a brief (2 min) 
trypsin incubation. The mixture was transferred to a 50 mL conical 
tube and allowed to settle. The supernatant was removed and dis-
carded. The remaining mixture was resuspended in 3 mL of Mito-
chondria Isolation Medium (MIM) (300 mM Sucrose, 10 mM Na-
HEPES, 0.2 mM EDTA) with BSA, then transferred to a pre-chilled 
Dounce homogenizer and slowly homogenized for a total of w10e 
12 counts. The homogenate was then subjected to a series of differ-
ential centrifugation steps. The fractions of isolated mitochondria ob-
tained (mixed subsarcolemmal and intermyofibrillar) were 
resuspended in a small volume of MIM þ BSA and frozen at À80 for 
biochemical analysis. </p>

<p>4.9. Immunoblot and enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) 
Cardiac tissue was homogenized in TEET Buffer (10 mM Tris, 1 mM 
EDTA, 1 mM EGTA þ 0.5% Triton X-100), then loaded on 4e20% pre-
cast polyacrylamide SDS gel (Biorad, Hercules, CA) under reducing 
conditions. Protein was transferred to PVDF membranes (Millipore, </p>

<p>Bellerica, CA) and incubated with primary antibodies for GPx4 and a-
tubulin (Abcam, Cambridge, UK), COX IV and b-actin (Cell Signaling </p>

<p>Technology, Danvers MA), and HNE-adduct (Percipio Biosciences). 
Membranes were incubated using infrared fluorophore-conjugated 
secondary antibodies (LiCor Biosciences, Lincoln, NE), scanned using 
Odyssey Clx Infrared Imaging System (Li-Cor) and analyzed by 
densitometry using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Image J</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">NIH</rs>). The absolute quantities of GPx4 and 
HNE-modified protein adducts in human cardiac tissue was deter-
mined by a quantitative ELISA approach developed in our lab, as 
described previously [54]. Fixed concentrations of HNE-adducts were 
made by incubating 4-hydroxynonenal (Cayman Chemical, Ann Arbor, 
MI) with BSA. A standard curve of both recombinant GPx4 (AbFrontier, 
Seoul, Korea) and HNE-modified BSA were then incubated on </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>502 MOLECULAR METABOLISM 4 (2015) 493e506 Ó 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>

<p>immunolon-coated 96-well assay plate (Fisher Scientific) along with 
diluted cardiac protein. Samples were incubated overnight at 4 C, and 
subsequently washed with PBSþ0.05% Tween-20 and blocked for 2 h 
with BSA or NB4025 (NOF America, White Plains, NY) at 37 C. 
Samples were then incubated with primary antibodies for GPx4 and 
HNE adduct for 2 h at 37 C. Samples were washed with PBSþ0.05% 
Tween-20 and incubated with HRP-conjugated secondary antibody for 
2 h at 27 C. Following this incubation, samples were washed as </p>

<p>before and incubated with Amplex Red (10 mM). Concentrations of </p>

<p>GPx4 and HNE-adducts in the samples were determined by fitting to 
the standard curve within each plate and normalized to total protein 
concentration. </p>

<p>4.10. Hydrazide labeling of carbonyl-modified proteins 
Hydrazide Cy5.5 dye (GE Healthcare Bio-Sciences, Pittsburgh, PA) was 
diluted in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) at a stock concentration 1 mg/ml. 
Tissue was homogenized under an anaerobic chamber (Coy Laboratory 
Products, Grass Lake, MI) in 10 mM sodium phosphate buffer, con-
taining 0.1% Triton X-100, and de-gassed using dry vacuum pump 
(Welch No. 25228e01, Monroe, LA). Dye was added to half of the 
homogenate (1:10). The samples were left under anaerobic conditions 
for 2 h and incubated overnight on orbital shaker at 4 C. The other 
aliquot of tissue homogenate was used to quantify protein content. 
Portions of the labeled cardiac tissue homogenate were subjected to 
SDS-PAGE on 10% SDS polyacrylamide gel. The gels were scanned 
using Odyssey Clx Infrared Imaging System (Li-Cor) and Cy5.5-labeled 
proteins were analyzed by densitometry using <rs id="software-3" type="software">Image J</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">NIH</rs>). </p>

<p>4.11. Statistical analysis 
All animal data are presented as mean AE SEM. Statistical analysis on 
mouse model variables were performed with <rs type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> 
(GraphPad Prism, La Jolla, Ca.). One way ANOVA was performed on 
continuous variables followed by NewmaneKeuls post test, with </p>

<p>a &lt; 0.05 considered statistically significant. In the human data </p>

<p>analysis, categorical variables are presented as frequency and per-
centage and continuous variables were presented as mean AE standard 
deviation, mediation, median and interquartile range. Fisher exact and 
Chi (c 
2 ) procedures were used to compute statistical significance of 
group comparisons for categorical variables. Deuchler-Wilcoxon was 
used for continuous variables. Biochemical variables were divided into 
quartiles (GPx4) or tertiles (HNE) and analyzed using a robust Poisson 
regression model (with relative risk as the measure of association). 
Missing values for all clinical and biochemical variable were imputed 
using the iterative expectation-maximization (EM) algorithm as 
described in a recent study [94]. Variables that were statistically sig-
nificant in the univariable analysis were included into the multivariable 
analysis. P-value was computed using Friedman's Nonparametric test 
for central tendency while adjusting for age. P trend was computed using 
likelihood ratio trend test, adjusting for age and sex. Statistical sig-
nificance was defined as P &lt; 0.05. SAS Version 9.3 was used for all 
analyses of human biochemical and clinical variables. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>This research was supported in part by National Institutes of Health 
grant 1R01HL122863 to E.J.A </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors have no conflict of interest to declare. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This authors would like to thank Amy Bullock for assistance with animal care and 
breeding and Joany Oswald Zary for assistance with histology. </p>

<p>APPENDIX A. SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary data related to this article can be found at doi:10.1016/j.molmet. 
2015.04.001. </p>



<p>MOLECULAR METABOLISM 4 (2015) 493e506 Ó 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>





<p>Original article </p>

<p>504 MOLECULAR METABOLISM 4 (2015) 493e506 Ó 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>



<p>MOLECULAR METABOLISM 4 (2015) 493e506 Ó 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>





<p>Original article </p>

<p>506 MOLECULAR METABOLISM 4 (2015) 493e506 Ó 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>www.molecularmetabolism.com </p>

</text></tei>