<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4388098" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: The hospitalized elderly are at risk of functional decline. We evaluated the </p>

<p>effects and care costs of a specialized geriatric rehabilitation program aimed at preventing 
functional decline among at-risk hospitalized elderly. 
Methods: The prospective nonrandomized controlled trial reported here was performed in 
three hospitals in the Netherlands. One hospital implemented the Prevention and Reactivation 
Care Program (PReCaP), while two other hospitals providing usual care served as control 
settings. Within the PReCaP hospital we compared patients pre-implementation with patients 
post-implementation of the PReCaP ("within-hospital analysis"), while our nonrandomized 
controlled trial compared patients of the PReCaP hospital post-implementation with patients 
from the two control hospitals providing usual care ("between-hospital analysis"). Hospitalized 
patients 65 years or older and at risk of functional decline were interviewed at baseline and at 
3 and 12 months using validated questionnaires to score functioning, depression, and health-
related quality of life (HRQoL). We estimated costs per unit of care from hospital information 
systems and national data sources. We used adjusted general linear mixed models to analyze 
functioning and HRQoL. 
Results: Between-hospital analysis showed no difference in activities of daily living (ADL) 
or instrumental activities of daily living (IADL) between PReCaP patients and control 
groups. PReCaP patients did have slightly better cognitive functioning (Mini Mental State 
Examination; 0.4 [95% confidence interval (CI) 0.2-0.6]), lower depression (Geriatric Depres-
sion Scale 15; -0.9 [95% -1.1 to -0.6]) and higher perceived health (Short-Form 20; 5.6 [95% 
CI 2.8-8.4]) than control patients. Analyses within the PReCaP hospital comparing patients 
pre-and post-implementation of the PReCaP showed no improvement over time in functioning, 
depression, and HRQoL. One-year health care costs were higher for PReCaP patients, both for 
the within-hospital analysis (+€7,000) and the between-hospital analysis (+€2,500). 
Conclusion: We did not find any effect of the PReCaP on ADL and IADL. The PReCaP may 
possibly provide some benefits to hospitalized patients at risk of functional decline with respect 
to cognitive functioning, depression, and perceived health. Further evaluations of integrated 
intervention programs to limit functional decline are therefore required. 
The hospitalized elderly are at risk of "functional decline", defined as a loss in ability 
to perform activities of daily living (ADL) or instrumental activities of daily living </p>

<p>Correspondence: ewout W steyerberg 
Department of Public health, erasmus 
University Medical Center, room 
na2324, Wytemaweg 80, 3015 Cn, 
rotterdam, the netherlands 
email e.steyerberg@erasmusmc.nl </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Clinical Interventions in Aging 
30 March 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>650 </p>

<p>Asmus-szepesi et al </p>

<p>(IADL), 
1 which leads to lower health-related quality of 
life (HRQoL), higher health care utilization and associated 
costs, and early death. 
1,2 The hospitalized elderly at risk 
of functional decline are also at higher risk of cognitive 
impairment, problems in social and psychological function-
ing, multi-morbidity, and other geriatric symptoms such 
as malnutrition and falls. 
3,4 Hospital care should focus on 
this multitude of geriatric problems in addition to treating 
the medical diagnosis for which patients are admitted. </p>

<p>5-8 </p>

<p>Several interventions, such as case management and mul-
tidisciplinary care, have by themselves proved successful 
in lowering the number of hospital and nursing home (re) 
admissions; improving physical functioning; reducing fall 
incidence; reducing length of hospital stay; and improving 
communication between patients, caregivers, and health 
professionals. 
9-12 In the trial reported here, we aimed to 
evaluate the effects of an integrated program to prevent func-
tional decline among older hospitalized patients on patient 
(I)ADL functioning and HRQoL compared with usual 
care. This program, the Prevention and Reactivation Care 
Program (PReCaP), consists of a combination of elements 
proved successful in the past. By combining these successful 
elements, we hoped to further improve their positive effects. 
We also evaluated the effects of the PReCaP on mortality; 
(re)admissions; falling; health care costs; and the HRQoL 
of, and burden of care on, informal caregivers. </p>

<p>Methods 
The Prevention and reactivation Care 
Program </p>

<p>The "PReCaP" is a preventive program supplementary to 
usual care for hospitalized elderly that has been developed 
and implemented in three departments (ie, geriatrics, 
internal medicine, and cardiology) of a regional hospi-
tal in the Netherlands. The supplementary nature of the 
PReCaP means that the patient receives usual care from 
the professionals of the department they are staying in, 
and, in addition, receive PReCaP care from a multidisci-
plinary team that is not connected to a specific department 
but active across hospital departments. Thus, the care this 
team provides is "supplementary" to the usual care patients 
already receive in their specific departments. The PReCaP 
aims to reduce hospital-related functional decline among 
the hospitalized elderly by offering multidisciplinary, inte-
grated, and goal-oriented care focused on physical, social, 
and psychological domains of functioning. 
13 Important ele-
ments of the PReCaP are the early identification of patients 
at risk of functional decline using the Identification Seniors 
At Risk -Hospitalized Patients questionnaire (ISAR-HP 
14 ), </p>

<p>intensive follow-up treatment for elderly patients with 
complex problems at a prevention and reactivation center 
(PRC), multidisciplinary geriatric expertise, support for 
informal caregivers, and geriatric case-management from 
hospital admission to well after discharge. 
13,15 Previous 
studies have evaluated these elements separately and found 
each one successful (see Table S1). </p>

<p>6,8,12,16 </p>

<p>setting </p>

<p>The Vlietland Hospital (hereafter referred to as the "PReCaP 
hospital") is a 450-bed regional hospital, which employs 131 
medical specialists and 1,782 staff members. The hospital has 
a geriatric unit with 22 beds (including four beds for patients 
suffering from delirium), direct access to hospital replacement 
care, and provisions for follow-up in primary care through the 
PReCaP (de Vos AJ et al, unpublished data, 2014). 
The Sint Franciscus Gasthuis (SFG), one of two control 
hospitals in this study, is a 613-bed, top clinical teaching 
hospital (150 medical specialists; 2,300 staff members) 
with onsite hospital replacement care, but without a clinical 
geriatric unit or provisions for follow-up in primary care. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>The Ruwaard van Putten Ziekenhuis, Spijkenisse, the second 
of the two control hospitals in this study, is a 288-bed regional 
hospital (70 medical specialists; 1,000 staff members). The 
Ruwaard van Putten Ziekenhuis does not have a geriatric 
unit, hospital replacement care, or provisions for follow-up 
in primary care. 
This quasi-experimental study consisted of two parts. We 
first conducted a pre-implementation study in the PReCaP 
hospital, which included patients 65 years or older and 
admitted to the PReCaP hospital between May 2010 and 
October 2010, and their informal caregivers. This period 
served as a baseline study before implementation of the 
PReCaP to allow for within-PReCaP-hospital-analysis over 
time, to choose a suitable instrument to identify elderly 
patients at risk of functional decline, and to generate data 
needed for power calculations. 
17 We then conducted a pro-
spective nonrandomized controlled trial including patients 
aged 65 years or older admitted to either the departments of 
geriatrics, internal medicine, or cardiology of the PReCaP 
hospital post-implementation, or to one of the two control 
hospitals providing usual care, between February 2011 and 
September 2013. We excluded patients who were unable to 
answer questions due to severe cognitive problems (Mini 
Mental State Examination [MMSE] score 12) or language 
problems, who had a life expectancy of less than 3 months, 
or who scored 0 on the ISAR-HP. 
The ISAR-HP was administered by trained research 
nurses or research assistants at hospital admission to select </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>651 </p>

<p>evaluation of PreCaP for hospitalized elderly </p>

<p>patients at risk of functional decline. The ISAR-HP consists 
of four yes/no questions regarding inability to travel inde-
pendently, inability to walk, educational level, and house-
keeping dependence. Scores range from 0 to 5, with higher 
scores corresponding to higher risk of functional decline. </p>

<p>14,18 </p>

<p>Patients with a ISAR-HP score 1 were considered at risk 
of functional decline 
3 and were eligible for participation in 
this study. Within the PReCaP hospital, we compared out-
comes of at-risk patients treated pre-implementation with 
those of at-risk patients treated post-implementation (within-
hospital analysis). We further compared at-risk patients of the 
PReCaP hospital post-implementation with at-risk patients 
of the control hospitals (between-hospital analysis). </p>

<p>Data collection </p>

<p>The primary outcomes were ADL and IADL functioning of 
the elderly patient. Cognitive functioning, HRQoL, depres-
sion, falling, readmission to the hospital, (re)admission to a 
nursing home or elderly home, and survival were secondary 
outcomes. Other secondary outcomes were the burden of 
care on, and HRQoL of, primary informal caregivers, as well 
as costs of care. After obtaining informed consent, trained 
research nurses or trained research assistants interviewed 
patients in hospital within 48 hours of admission and in the 
patient's personal environment at 3 and 12 months after 
hospital admission using validated questionnaires. Informal 
caregivers were sent paper questionnaires to fill out and return 
by postal mail at the same time patients were interviewed. 
ADL and IADL were scored using the Katz Index of 
Independence in Activities of Daily Living 
19 and the Lawton 
Instrumental Activities of Daily Living Scale, 
20 respectively. 
Questionnaires used to score secondary outcomes included 
the (short) version of the MMSE 
21 for cognitive functioning, 
the EuroQol (EQ-5D™ 
22 ), the Short-Form 20 (SF-20 </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>) for 
HRQoL, and the Geriatric Depression Scale 15 (GDS-15 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>) 
for depression. The HRQoL of, and subjective burden of care 
on, informal caregivers were determined with the EQ-5D and 
the Caregiver Strain Index (CSI), 
25 respectively (see study 
protocol 
17 for more details). Survival data were collected by 
telephone, either by trying to reach patients and their families 
for follow-up interviews or by calling general practitioners 
at 12-month follow-up. 
Costs per unit of health care consumption were retrieved 
from hospital information systems or from nationally repre-
sentative unit-costs research. 
26 Cost-per-day estimates were 
applied to evaluate length of stay in hospital or nursing/elderly 
home. Formal homecare services were measured in costs per 
hour, general practitioner visits were based on average costs 
per contact, and costs of aids/modifications were estimated </p>

<p>using current retail prices. Informal homecare utilization was 
collected among primary informal caregivers by mailed paper 
questionnaires. Costs per hour for informal homecare were 
estimated using the proxy good method. </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>sample size </p>

<p>Based on the average number of elderly patients admitted to 
the different hospitals during our inclusion period of 1 year, 
we expected to be able to collect a sample size of around 
1,100 patients in the intervention hospital (900 patients 
treated with the new intervention program and 200 patients 
treated with the new intervention program, including a stay at 
a PRC). Samples of a minimum of 500 to 600 patients were 
expected in each of the two control hospitals. According 
to our baseline study results on ADL (Katz Index of Inde-
pendence in Activities of Daily Living) and iADL (Lawton 
Instrumental Activities of Daily Living Scale), a population 
of n=500 in the control hospitals would lead to around n=300 
persons analyzable at 3 months, whereas a baseline popula-
tion of n=1,100 in the PReCaP hospital would lead to around 
733 persons analyzable at 3 months. Using an effect size of 
0.25 this would lead to a power of 95%. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Furthermore, to detect a smaller effect size (Cohen's D 
of 0.2), n=1,100 in the intervention hospital and n=500 for 
the control hospitals would lead to a power of 83%. As 
expected, we collected a sample size of around 900 post-
implementation patients in the PReCaP hospital, and samples 
of at least 500 patients in each of the two control hospitals. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>We controlled for case-mix differences by including patients 
from the departments of geriatrics, internal medicine, and 
cardiology for analyses of changes over time within the 
PReCaP hospital. 
For between-hospital analysis, we included patients from 
internal medicine and cardiology only, since the control 
hospitals had no geriatrics department. The two control 
hospitals were pooled into one group to increase statistical 
power for analyses on the impact of the intervention. </p>

<p>statistical methods </p>

<p>We analyzed differences in patient and informal caregiver 
outcomes within the PReCaP hospital and between the 
PReCaP hospital and control hospitals with general linear 
mixed models (GLMMs) of repeated measurements. We 
used pair-wise comparisons with fixed time and hospital 
effects and a random intercept, which resulted in a mean 
difference with 95% confidence interval (CI). We adjusted 
GLMM analyses for potential confounders, sex, age, 
ISAR-HP score, baseline score of the studied outcome vari-
able, and admission diagnosis. Falling and (re)admissions </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>652 </p>

<p>Asmus-szepesi et al </p>

<p>were analyzed using logistic regression adjusted for sex, 
age, ISAR-HP score, baseline score of the studied outcome 
variable, and admission diagnosis. Survival was analyzed 
using Kaplan-Meier plots and multivariable Cox regres-
sion. All analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v 21.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>, Armonk, NY, USA). Missing 
values for costs were assumed to be missing at random, 
conditional on observed baseline characteristics and out-
come variables. 
28 Thus, we performed a multiple imputation 
procedure with predictive mean matching, generating five 
completed datasets including a rich set of baseline variables 
(eg, age, sex, ISAR-HP score) and accounting for death 
and length of survival. The medical ethics committee of 
the Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, the 
Netherlands approved the study protocol under protocol 
number MEC2011-041. </p>

<p>Results 
Participants </p>

<p>Of the 985 pre-implementation patients who were assessed 
for eligibility in the PReCaP hospital, 34% were excluded 
and 19% refused participation, leaving 460 recruited patients 
(Figure 1A). We controlled for case-mix differences by 
excluding people with an ISAR-HP score of 0 or who were 
admitted to departments other than geriatrics, internal medi-
cine, or cardiology, leaving 143 (31%) patients for analysis. 
Of the 2,811 PReCaP post-implementation patients assessed 
for eligibility, 46% were excluded, 20% refused, and 959 
(34%) patients were recruited and analyzed. 
After controlling for case mix by selecting patients from 
cardiology and internal medicine departments, 699 (73%) 
of the post-implementation PReCaP patients were included 
for between-hospital analysis (Figure 1B). Of the 4,972 
patients assessed for eligibility in the control hospitals, 43% 
were excluded and 24% refused, leaving 1,676 patients. We 
selected 540 (32%) patients from the cardiology and internal 
medicine departments for analysis. We found similar results 
in the groups of patients admitted to either the cardiology 
or internal medicine departments. Patient characteristics 
between lost-to-follow-up patients and complete cases were 
similar for all hospital groups (Table S2). </p>

<p>Descriptive data </p>

<p>Pre-implementation PReCaP patients were significantly 
younger, more often men, more often married, and more often 
living independently with others than post-implementation 
PReCaP patients (Table 1). Furthermore, they had slightly 
higher ADL and IADL scores, were less likely to have </p>

<p>multi-morbidity, and had lower ISAR-HP scores than post-
implementation PReCaP patients. 
Patients from the control hospitals were significantly 
more often women than the post-implementation PReCaP 
patients, but these groups did not differ in other baseline 
characteristics (Table 1). </p>

<p>Components of the Prevention 
and reactivation Care Program received </p>

<p>All PReCaP post-implementation patients were screened with 
the ISAR-HP and about 90% received case management. 
However, only around 50% of the patients were discussed 
in a multidisciplinary meeting. Most PReCaP patients were 
discharged to their home independently, with homecare or 
with outpatient rehabilitation (83%; Table S3). </p>

<p>Functioning, health-related quality 
of life, and survival </p>

<p>No substantial differences in ADL, IADL, cognitive 
functioning, HRQoL, depression, or risk of falling from 
hospital admission to 1 year after were found between pre-
implementation and post-implementation PReCaP patients 
(Tables 2 and 3). Even thought not significant, the differences 
were generally in favor of the post-implementation PReCaP 
group. On the other hand, these patients were at higher risk of 
readmission to the hospital within 3 months of initial admis-
sion (Table 3; odds ratio [OR] 3.7; 95% CI 1.8-7.6) than 
pre-implementation patients. Survival did not differ between 
groups (hazard ratio [HR] 1.18; 95% CI 0.79-1.77). 
Physical functioning, falling, and HRQoL sub-
scales other than perceived health did not differ between 
post-implementation PReCaP patients and control patients 
(Tables 2 and 3). Post-implementation PReCaP patients had 
higher cognitive functioning (MMSE 0.4; 95% CI 0.2-0.6), 
fewer symptoms of depression (GDS-15 -0.9; 95% CI -1.1 
to -0.6), and perceived their health after hospitalization as 
better (5.6 points at SF-20 current health perceptions [95% 
CI 2.8-8.4]), than control patients in the year after hospital 
admission (Table 2, Figure S1). As expected, patients from 
the PReCaP hospital post-implementation were much more 
likely to be admitted to a nursing home within 3 months of their 
initial hospital admission (OR 9.5; 95% CI 2.7-34) than control 
patients, since a stay at a PRC was part of the PReCaP (Table 
3). Mortality did not differ (HR 1.20; 95% CI 0.89-1.62). </p>

<p>Impact on informal caregivers </p>

<p>Approximately 26% of pre-implementation PReCaP patients 
and 36% of post-implementation PReCaP patients received </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>653 </p>

<p>evaluation of PreCaP for hospitalized elderly </p>

<p>-Not available at time of recruitment (n=336) 
-Discharged before invitate to participate (n=185) </p>

<p>Unknown (total n=1,165 (44%)) 
Note: this group entails people who were assessed 
as well as people who were not assessed for 
eligibility. Since reasons were not registered 
properly these people ar all classified as not 
assessed </p>

<p>Excluded (total n=525 (53%)) </p>

<p>Not assessed for eligibility (total n=521 (20%)) </p>

<p>1. Ineligible (n=336 (34%)) 
-Too ill/terminally ill (n=152) 
-Not able to speak/read Dutch (n=20) 
-Readmissions (n=114) 
-Length of stay &lt;48 hours (n=34) 
-Other reasons for exclusion (n=16) </p>

<p>-Not at risk for functional decline 
(ISAR-HP=O) (n=128(28%)) 
-Admitted to another ward than Geriatrics, 
internal medicine or cardiology (n=189 
(41%)) </p>

<p>-Too ill to participate (n=73) 
-Unknown (n=25) </p>

<p>-Did not want to participate (n=93) </p>

<p>Patients recruited 
at T0 and included 
in analysis 
n=959 (34%) </p>

<p>2. Eligible but not recruited (n=189 (19%)) 
-Refused participation (n=189) 
-Unknown (see "not assessed for eligibility 
box") </p>

<p>Total recruited 
patients 
N=460 (47%) </p>

<p>Patients included 
in analysis 
n=143 (31%) </p>

<p>75 (52%) with T1 follow-up 
21 (15%) died beween T0 and T1 
1 without T1 but with T2 </p>

<p>57 (40%) with T2 follow-up 
6 (4%) died between 
T1 and T2 </p>

<p>588 (61%) with T2 follow-up 
41 (4%) died between 
T1 and T2 </p>

<p>Recruited but excluded from analysis 
(total n=317 (69%)) </p>

<p>Lost to follow-up T2 (12 months) 
(total n=13 (19%)) 
-Did not want to participate (n=6) 
-Too ill to participate (n=l) 
-Unknown (n=6) </p>

<p>-Did not want to participate (n=18) 
-Too ill to participate (n=20) 
-Unknown (n=8) </p>

<p>Lost to follow-up T1 (3 months) 
(total n=46 (32%)) 
Lost to follow-up T1 (3 months) 
(total n=191(20%)) </p>

<p>-Too ill to participate (n=19) 
-Unknown (n=4) </p>

<p>-Did not want to participate (n=24) </p>

<p>Lost to follow-up T2 (12 months) 
(total n=191(20%)) </p>

<p>660 (69%) with 
T1 follow-up 108 (11%) 
died beween T0 and T1 
16 without 
T1 but with T2 </p>

<p>Patients assessed 
for elegibility 
n=2,811 </p>

<p>2,960 older patients 
potentially eligble at 
hospital admission </p>

<p>Not assessed for eligibility (total n=149 (5%)) 
-Discharged before invitation to participate 
(n=149) </p>

<p>Excluded (total n=1,852 (66%)) </p>

<p>1. Ineligible (n=806 (29%)) 
-Not at risk for functional decline 
(ISAR-HP = 0) (n=806) </p>

<p>2. Ineligible (n=471 (17%)) 
-Too ill/Terminally ill (n=363) 
-Not able to speak/read Dutch (n=39) 
-Cognitive impaired (MMSE &lt;18) (n=69) </p>

<p>3. Eligible but not recruited (n=575 (20%)) 
-Refused (n=557) 
-Unknown (n=18) </p>

<p>2,671 patients 
potentially eligible </p>

<p>Patients assessed 
for elegibility 
n=985 </p>

<p>Pre-intervention study 
Intervention study </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Figure 1 (Continued) </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>654 </p>

<p>Asmus-szepesi et al </p>

<p>Intervention hospital 
Control hospitals </p>

<p>5497 older patients eligble at 
hospital admission 
2,960 older patients 
potentially eligible at 
hospital admission </p>

<p>Patients assessed 
for elegibility 
n=2,811 
Excluded (total n=1,852 (66%)) </p>

<p>1. lneligible (n=806 (29%)) 
-Not at risk of functional decline 
(ISAR HP =0) </p>

<p>Patients assessed 
for elegibility 
n=4,972 </p>

<p>Patients recruited 
at T0 
n=1,676 (34%) </p>

<p>lost ro follow-up T1 (3 months) 
(total n=127 (18%)) 
-Did not want to participate (n=66) 
-Too ill to participate (n=43) 
-Unknown (n=18) </p>

<p>-Did not want to participate (n=14) 
-Too ill to participate (n=10) 
-Unknown (n=6) </p>

<p>Patients recruited 
at T0 
n=959 (34%) </p>

<p>Patients included 
in analysis 
n=699 (73%) </p>

<p>Patients included 
in analysis 
n=540 (32%) </p>

<p>375 (69%) with T1 follow-up 
54 (10%) died between T0 an T1 
1 without T1 but with T2 </p>

<p>1. lneligible (n=1,573 (32%)) 
-Not at risk of functional decline (ISAR-HP=O) </p>

<p>2. lneligible (n=553 (11%)) 
-Too ill/Terminally ill (n=414) 
-Not able to speak/read Dutch (n=54)) 
-Cognitive impaired (MMSE &lt;1) (n=85) </p>

<p>3. Eligible but not recruited (n=1,170 (24%)) 
-Refused (n=1,094) 
-Unknown (n=76) </p>

<p>Excluded (total n=3,296 (66%)) </p>

<p>Recruited but excluded from analysis 
(total n=1,136 (68%)) 
-Admitted to another ward than 
internal medicine or cardiology </p>

<p>Recruited but excluded from analysis 
(total n=260 (27%)) 
-Admitted to another ward than 
internal medicine or cardiology </p>

<p>-Discharged before invitation to participate </p>

<p>Not assessed for eligibility (total n=149 (5%)) 
Not assessed for eligibility (n=525 (10%)) 
-Discharged before invitation to 
participate </p>

<p>2. lneligible (n=471 (17%)) 
-Too ill/Terminally ill (n=363) 
-Not able to speak/read Dutch (n=39) 
-Cognitive impaired (MMSE &lt;18) (n=69) </p>

<p>3. Eligible but not recruited (n=575 (20%)) 
-Refused (n=557) 
-Unknown (n=18) </p>

<p>492 (70%) with T1 follow-up 
70 (10%) died between T0 
and T1 10 without 
T1 but with T2 </p>

<p>Lost to follow-up T2 (12 months) 
(total n=33%)) 
-Did not want to participate (n=17) 
-Too ill to participate (n=14) 
-Unknown (n=2) </p>

<p>Lost to follow-up T1 (3 months) 
(total n=11 (20%)) 
-Did not want to participate (n=51) 
-Too ill to participate (n=29) 
-Unknown (n=30) </p>

<p>Lost to follow-up T2 (12 months) 
(total n=30 (6%)) </p>

<p>435 (62%) with T2 follow-up 
34 (5%) died between T1 and T2 </p>

<p>312 (58%) with T2 follow-up 34 
(6%) died between T1 and T2 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 1 (A) Flow chart of within-hospital comparison. (B) Flow chart of between-hospital comparison. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>655 </p>

<p>evaluation of PreCaP for hospitalized elderly </p>

<p>Table 1 Baseline characteristics of patients </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Within-hospital comparison </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Between-hospital comparison </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Pre-intervention 
(N=143) </p>

<p>Intervention 
(N=959) </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>Control 
hospitals (N=540) </p>

<p>Intervention 
hospital (N=699) </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>Age, mean (sD) 
78.2 (7.5) 
80.0 (7.4) 
0.008 78.6 (7.4) 
78.7 (7.3) 
0.164 
sex, men, n (%) 
69 (48) 
369 (39) 
0.026 197 (37) 
299 (43) 
0.025 
Married/living together, n (%) 
74 (52) 
393 (41) 
0.005 225 (42) 
323 (46) 
0.055 
living independently alone, n (%) 
60 (42) 
475 (50) 
0.045 267 (49) 
327 (47) 
0.360 
living independently with others, n (%) 
75 (52) 
392 (41) 
232 (43) 
328 (47) 
length of admission (days), median (25th, 75th) 6 (4, 9) 
7 (4, 11) 
5 (3, 9) 
6 (4, 10) 
Two or more illnesses, n (%) 
101 (71) 
438 (87) 
0.000 301 (84) 
359 (87) 
0.165 
IsAr-hP score, 
c n (%) 
0.006 
0.291 
1 
40 (28) 
189 (20) 
132 (24) 
171 (25) 
2 
25 (18) 
145 (15) 
93 (17) 
124 (18) 
3 
23 (16) 
157 (16) 
119 (22) 
118 (17) 
4 
36 (25) 
282 (29) 
131 (24) 
173 (25) 
5 
19 (13) 
186 (19) 
65 (12) 
113 (16) 
Katz Index of Independence in Activities of Daily 
living, 
d mean (sD) 
Pre-admission 
nA 
5.1 (1.3) 
nA 
5.3 (1.1) 
5.3 (1.1) 
0.754 
During admission 
4.8 (1.5) 
4.4 (1.7) 
0.016 4.7 (1.6) 
4.7 (1.5) 
0.416 
lawton, 
e mean (sD) 
Pre-admission 
nA 
5.3 (1.9) 
nA 
5.7 (1.8) 
5.6 (1.8) 
0.162 
During admission 
5.2 (2.0) 
4.7 (1.9) 
0.012 5.0 (1.9) 
4.9 (1.9) 
0.636 
hrQol, mean (sD) 
eQ-5D™ </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>0.63 (0.31) 
0.61 (0.30) 
0.286 0.62 (0.3) 
0.64 (0.3) 
0.268 
sF-20 
g -physical functioning 
42 (30) 
45 (31) 
0.278 46 (29) 
47 (30) 
0.533 
sF-20 -role functioning 
39 (45) 
31 (42) 
0.053 33 (41) 
35 (43) 
0.814 
sF-20 -social functioning 
65 (41) 
63 (34) 
0.174 60 (35) 
64 (35) 
0.084 
sF-20 -mental health 
72 (21) 
71 (20) 
0.298 70 (20) 
73 (19) 
0.018 
sF-20 -current health perceptions 
40 (26) 
36 (23) 
0.132 35 (24) 
34 (23) 
0.998 
sF-20 -physical pain 
48 (45) 
60 (41) 
0.010 64 (39) 
62 (41) 
0.758 
MMse </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>20.1 (2.4) 
19.4 (2.4) 
0.005 19.9 (2.3) 
19.7 (2.4) 
0.150 
gDs-15 </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>nA 
3.8 (2.8) 
nA 
3.6 (2.8) 
3.6 (2.7) 
0.694 
Falling during 6 months before T0 
In home environment, n (%) 
30 (21) 
342 (36) 
0.001 174 (33) 
211 (30) 
0.450 
Outside home environment, n (%) 
27 (19) 
190 (20) 
0.003 107 (20) 
137 (20) 
0.927 
hospital admission, year before T0, n (%) 
61 (43) 
295 (31) 
0.000 186 (35) 
234 (34) 
0.637 
Admission diagnoses (most frequent), n (%) 
Cardiovascular 
63 (44) 
213 (22) 
122 (23) 
196 (28) 
Infection, inflammation 
2 (1) 
48 (5) 
40 (7) 
35 (5) 
Pulmonary 
12 (8) 
48 (5) 
11 (2) 
28 (4) 
gastrointestinal 
8 (6) 
49 (5) 
42 (8) 
30 (4) 
neoplasms/blood/blood-forming organs 
12 (8) 
48 (5) 
40 (7) 
33 (5) 
surgery 
6 (4) 
21 (2) 
35 (6) 
18 (3) 
Other 
9 (6) 
377 (39) 
204 (38) 
244 (35) 
Unknown 
31 (22) 
155 (16) 
46 (9) 
115 (16) </p>

<p>Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Within hospital comparison compares patients from the baseline study (pre-implementation of the PreCaP) with patients treated with the PreCaP (post-
implementation). 
b Between hospital comparison concerns the comparison between PreCaP patients and control patients; data from control hospitals were pooled and 
analysis was performed on patients from cardiology and internal medicine departments to control for initial case-mix differences. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Score 0-5, with a higher score reflecting a 
higher risk of functional decline. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Measured by the Katz six-item index, score 0-6, with higher scores reflecting higher independence. 
e Measured by the lawton Instrumental 
Activities of Daily Living Scale, score 0-8, with higher scores reflecting higher independence. 
f EuroQOL, score 0-1, with a higher score reflecting higher HRQoL. </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>score 
0-100, with higher scores reflecting better HRQoL, except for physical pain, which is reversed. </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>Score 0-23, with a higher score reflecting better cognitive functioning. 
i score 
0-15, with higher scores reflecting more symptoms of depression. 
j P-value differences measured with chi square for categorical variables and nonparametric Kruskall-Wallis 
for continuous variables. 
Abbreviations: euroQol, euro Quality of life questionnaire; gDs-15, geriatric Depression scale-15; hrQol, health-related quality of life; IADl, instrumental activities 
of daily living; ISAR-HP, Identification of Seniors At Risk -Hospitalized Patients; MMSE, Mini Mental State Examination (short version); NA, not applicable; SD, standard 
deviation; sF-20, short-Form 20. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>656 </p>

<p>Asmus-szepesi et al </p>

<p>Table 2 Comparison of patient outcomes within hospital and between hospitals using generalized linear mixed modeling* </p>

<p>Outcome </p>

<p>Unadjusted overall effects </p>

<p>Adjusted overall effects </p>

<p># </p>

<p>Mean (SE) 
pre-intervention/controls </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mean (SE) 
intervention 
Mean difference 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>Mean (SE) 
pre-intervention/controls </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mean (SE) 
intervention 
Mean difference 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>Within hospital 
eQ-5D™ </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>0.74 (0.03) </p>

<p>0.65 (0.01) </p>

<p>-0.08 (-0.14 to </p>

<p>-0.02) 0.008 </p>

<p>0.71 (0.03) </p>

<p>0.65 (0.02) 
-0.06 (-0.12 to 0.001) 0.053 </p>

<p>sF-20 </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>Physical functioning </p>

<p>47 (3.1) </p>

<p>45 (1.1) 
-2.74 (-9.22 to 3.73) </p>

<p>0.405 
47 (2.7) </p>

<p>45 (1.6) 
-1.72 (-6.90 to 3.46) </p>

<p>0.514 </p>

<p>role functioning </p>

<p>38 (3.9) </p>

<p>33 (1.4) 
-4.67 (-12.8 to 3.46) </p>

<p>0.260 
32 (3.7) </p>

<p>33 (2.0) 
1.61 (-5.53 to 8.74) </p>

<p>0.659 </p>

<p>social functioning </p>

<p>67 (3.4) </p>

<p>69 (1.2) 
2.61 (-4.40 to 9.62) </p>

<p>0.465 
65 (3.5) </p>

<p>70 (1.9) 
5.23 (-1.53 to 11.99) </p>

<p>0.129 </p>

<p>Mental health </p>

<p>75 (1.8) </p>

<p>75 (0.6) 
0.25 (-3.48 to 3.98) </p>

<p>0.896 
74 (1.7) </p>

<p>74 (1.0) 
-0.06 (-3.28 to 3.16) </p>

<p>0.971 </p>

<p>Current health perceptions 50 (2.7) </p>

<p>51 (1.0) 
1.65 (-3.99 to 7.30) </p>

<p>0.565 
47 (2.7) </p>

<p>51 (1.5) 
3.39 (-1.85 to 8.64) </p>

<p>0.204 </p>

<p>Physical pain </p>

<p>45 (4.0) </p>

<p>49 (1.4) 
3.34 (-5.03 to 11.70) </p>

<p>0.434 
51 (4.4) </p>

<p>47 (2.4) 
-3.22 (-11.68 to 5.23) 0.454 </p>

<p>Katz Index of Independence 
in Activities of Daily living </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>5.35 (0.13) </p>

<p>5.13 (0.05) 
-0.21 (-0.48 to 0.06) </p>

<p>0.125 
5.29 (0.12) </p>

<p>5.30 (0.07) 
0.02 (-0.22 to 0.25) </p>

<p>0.895 </p>

<p>lawton Instrumental Activities </p>

<p>of Daily living scale </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>5.62 (0.22) </p>

<p>5.06 (0.08) </p>

<p>-0.56 (-1.02 to </p>

<p>-0.10) 0.018 </p>

<p>5.39 (0.21) </p>

<p>5.19 (0.13) 
-0.20 (-0.59 to 0.19) </p>

<p>0.304 </p>

<p>MMse </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>20.8 (0.24) </p>

<p>20.8 (0.08) 
0.01 (-0.48 to 0.50) </p>

<p>0.976 
20.6 (0.26) </p>

<p>20.9 (0.15) 
0.24 (-0.25 to 0.73) </p>

<p>0.338 </p>

<p>gDs-15 </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>3.00 (0.27) </p>

<p>2.47 (0.10) 
-0.52 (-1.08 to 0.04) </p>

<p>0.069 
3.10 (0.31) </p>

<p>2.57 (0.17) 
-0.53 (-1.12 to 0.07) </p>

<p>0.082 </p>

<p>Between hospitals 
eQ-5D </p>

<p>0.67 (0.01) </p>

<p>0.68 (0.01) 
0.01 (-0.03 to 0.04) </p>

<p>0.666 
0.69 (0.02) </p>

<p>0.69 (0.02) 
-0.001 (-0.03 to 0.03) 0.935 </p>

<p>sF-20 
Physical functioning </p>

<p>46 (1.5) </p>

<p>48 (1.3) 
1.20 (-2.67 to 4.98) </p>

<p>0.552 
47 (1.9) </p>

<p>48 (1.9) 
0.99 (-2.05 to 4.03) </p>

<p>0.524 </p>

<p>role functioning </p>

<p>34 (1.8) </p>

<p>37 (1.6) 
2.82 (-1.83 to 7.46) </p>

<p>0.234 
37 (2.5) </p>

<p>40 (2.4) 
3.05 (-0.90 to 6.99) </p>

<p>0.130 </p>

<p>social functioning </p>

<p>68 (1.5) </p>

<p>71 (1.4) 
3.84 (-0.20 to 7.87) </p>

<p>0.063 
70 (2.3) </p>

<p>73 (2.3) 
2.37 (-1.36 to 6.11) </p>

<p>0.213 </p>

<p>Mental health </p>

<p>75 (0.9) </p>

<p>76 (0.8) 
0.91 (-1.40 to 3.22) </p>

<p>0.441 
78 (1.2) </p>

<p>77 (1.2) 
-0.75 (-2.63 to 1.13) </p>

<p>0.435 </p>

<p>Current health perceptions 47 (1.2) </p>

<p>52 (1.1) </p>

<p>5.00 (1.80 to 8.20) </p>

<p>0.002 
45 (1.8) </p>

<p>51 (1.7) </p>

<p>5.58 (2.82 to 8.35) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Physical pain </p>

<p>53 (1.8) </p>

<p>49 (1.6) 
-4.46 (-9.17 to 0.25) </p>

<p>0.064 
53 (2.9) </p>

<p>49 (2.8) 
-3.25 (-7.72 to 1.22) </p>

<p>0.154 </p>

<p>Katz Index of Independence 
in Activities of Daily living </p>

<p>5.22 (0.06) </p>

<p>5.28 (0.05) 
0.06 (-0.08 to 0.21) </p>

<p>0.399 
5.26 (0.06) </p>

<p>5.30 (0.06) 
0.04 (-0.06 to 0.13) </p>

<p>0.479 </p>

<p>lawton Instrumental 
Activities of Daily living scale </p>

<p>5.49 (0.09) </p>

<p>5.39 (0.08) 
-0.10 (-0.34 to 0.15) </p>

<p>0.434 
5.43 (0.12) </p>

<p>5.40 (0.12) 
-0.03 (-0.22 to 0.15) </p>

<p>0.733 </p>

<p>MMse </p>

<p>20.6 (0.10) </p>

<p>20.9 (0.09) 
0.35 (0.08 to 0.62) </p>

<p>0.010 
20.5 (0.15) </p>

<p>21.0 (0.14) 
0.41 (0.18 to 0.64) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>gDs-15 </p>

<p>3.07 (0.13) </p>

<p>2.36 (0.11) </p>

<p>-0.71 (-1.04 to </p>

<p>-0.38) 0.000 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>3.09 (0.17) </p>

<p>2.22 (0.17) </p>

<p>-0.88 (-1.15 to </p>

<p>-0.61) 0.000 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Notes: *effects measured over time from hospital admission to 12 months after admission; </p>

<p># </p>

<p>Analyses controlled for initial differences in case-mix as well as age, sex, admission diagnosis (ICD10), baseline score, and IsAr-hP score; </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>"Pre-intervention" relates to within hospital; "controls" relate to between hospitals. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Analyses controlled for initial differences in case mix as well as age, sex, admission diagnosis (International Classification of Diseases, tenth revision), </p>

<p>baseline score, and Identification of Seniors At Risk -Hospitalized Patients score. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>no baseline data available for gDs-15 in pilot, thus not adjusted for baseline gDs-15 score. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Significant differences at </p>

<p>α=0.001 level. </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>euroQOl, score 0-1, </p>

<p>with a higher score reflecting higher HRQoL. </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>Score 0-100, with higher scores reflecting better HRQoL, except for physical pain, which is reversed. </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>Measured by the Katz Index of Activities of Daily living, score 0-6, with higher scores </p>

<p>reflecting higher independence. </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>Measured by the Lawton Insturmental Activities of Daily Living Scale, score 0-8, with higher scores reflecting higher independence. </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>Score 0-23, with a higher score reflecting better cognitive functioning. </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>iScore 0-15, with higher scores reflecting more symptoms of depression. 
Abbreviations: ADl, activities of daily living; gDs-15, geriatric Depression scale-15; IADl, instrumental activities of daily living; MMse, Mini Mental state examination (short version); se, standard error; sF-20, short-Form 20; </p>

<p>CI, confidence interval; EuroQol, Euro Quality of Life questionnaire; HRQoL, health-related quality of life. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>657 </p>

<p>evaluation of PreCaP for hospitalized elderly </p>

<p>Table 3 Falling and (re)admissions within hospital and between hospitals using logistic regression </p>

<p>Falling/(re)admission 
3-month follow-up (T1) 
12-month follow-up (T2) </p>

<p>Unadjusted OR (95% CI) Adjusted* OR (95% CI) Unadjusted OR (95% CI) Adjusted* OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Within hospital 
Falling 
1.90 (0.9-3.7) 
1.60 (0.8-3.3) 
1.90 (0.9-3.7) 
1.50 (0.7-3.1) 
hospital readmission 
3.60 (1.9-6.7) 
3.70 (1.8-7.6)* 
1.10 (0.6-2.2) 
1.10 (0.5-2.6) 
nursing home admission nA 
nA 
1.70 (0.2-13.1) 
1.20 (0.1-12.5) 
elderly home admission 
1.50 (0.4-6.6) 
1.00 (0.2-4.9) 
0.10 (0.03-0.7) 
0.030 (0.0-0.5) 
Between hospitals 
Falling 
1.00 (0.7-1.4) 
1.00 (0.7-1.4) 
0.90 (0.6-1.3) 
0.90 (0.6-1.3) 
hospital readmission 
0.80 (0.6-1.2) 
0.90 (0.6-1.3) 
1.30 (0.9-1.8) 
1.30 (0.9-1.8) 
nursing home admission 7.40 (2.2-24.7) 
9.50 (2.7-33.5)* 
2.00 (0.4-11.3) 
4.20 (0.4-44.1) 
elderly home admission 
0.80 (0.4-1.7) 
0.60 (0.3-1.3) 
0.20 (0.04-0.91) 
0.20 (0.0-1.0) </p>

<p>Notes: *Significant difference; adjusted for age, sex, International Classification of Diseases, tenth revision admission diagnosis, Identification of Seniors At Risk -Hospitalized 
Patients score, and admissions/falling incidence before initial hospital admission. 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; NA, not applicable; OR, odds ratio. </p>

<p>informal care. In both groups, around 70% of informal caregivers 
were women and the average age was 65 and 63 years for pre-
implementation and post-implementation patients, respectively. 
Around 63% and 46% of informal caregivers were patients' 
partners in the pre-implementation and post-implementation 
groups, respectively. GLMM adjusted for age, sex, baseline 
scores, and ISAR-HP score showed no differences in HRQoL 
(EQ-5D -0.09; 95% CI -0.16 to -0.02), and burden of care 
(CSI -0.02; 95% CI -0.08 to 0.05) between caregivers of pre-
implementation and post-implementation PReCaP patients. 
Between-hospital comparisons showed that around 
25%-32% of patients received informal care before hospital 
admission in the PReCaP hospital post-implementation and 
control hospitals, respectively. More than 65% of informal 
caregivers were women, 50% were partners, and the aver-
age age of the informal caregivers was 63 years among both 
groups. HRQoL and burden of care did not differ between 
informal caregivers in both groups (EQ-5D 0.0; 95% CI -0.0 
to 0.0 and CSI -0.3; 95% CI -0.8 to 0.3). </p>

<p>societal costs </p>

<p>After multiple imputation of missing cost data, the average 
care costs were €14,286 per person per year in the pre-
implementation PReCaP group and €21,251 per person per 
year in the post-implementation PReCaP group (Figure 2). 
All sub-domains of costs were higher for post-implementa-
tion PReCaP patients, except for informal health care costs, 
between discharge and 3-month follow-up (€1,119 for post-
implementation group vs €1,374 for the pre-implementation 
group; Figures 2 and Table S4). Formal health care costs 
between hospital discharge and 3-month follow-up were more 
than twofold, and costs between the 3-and 12-month follow-
ups were around 1.5 times higher for post-implementation </p>

<p>PReCaP patients than for pre-implementation patients 
(Figures 2 and Table S4A-C). 
Between-hospital analysis showed average costs from 
hospital admission to 1 year after admission were €16,476 for 
control patients compared to €18,292 for PReCaP patients. 
Costs of hospital stay as well as formal health care costs 
were higher for PReCaP patients than for control patients, 
especially average formal health care costs between the 
3-and 12-month follow-ups, which were €4,751 for controls 
and €5,676 for PReCaP patients. Informal health care costs 
were somewhat lower for the PReCaP patients than for the 
controls (Figures 2 and Table S4A-C). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The PReCaP had no effect on ADL and IADL, in both the 
within-hospital analysis over time and the between-hospital 
analysis. Elderly patients from internal medicine or cardiology 
departments who were treated with the PReCaP had slightly 
higher cognitive functioning, fewer symptoms of depression, 
and higher perceived health 1 year after admission than elderly 
patients treated with usual care in the control hospitals. Clinical 
relevance was limited, though. 
29 No relevant differences were 
found in the HRQoL of, and burden of care on, informal care-
givers, both in the within-hospital analysis over time as well 
as in the between-hospital analysis. Costs of care from hospital 
admission to 1 year after were higher for elderly patients treated 
with the PReCaP. The higher costs of the PReCaP and its small 
effects on ADL and IADL suggest that the PReCaP, in its cur-
rent supplementary form, is unlikely to be cost-effective. </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>This study has several limitations. In our attempts to control 
for selection bias, 
30 we included only 143 pre-implementation </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>658 </p>

<p>Asmus-szepesi et al </p>

<p>Figure 2 health care costs within and between hospitals from admission to 1 year after admission. 
Abbreviations: wh-pre-interv, within hospital, pre-intervention; wh-intervention, within hospital, during intervention; bh-controls, between hospitals, controls; bh-
intervention, between hospitals, during intervention. </p>

<p>patients and 959 post-implementation patients within the 
PReCaP hospital comparison over time. We included 699 
post-implementation PReCaP patients and 540 control 
patients for between-hospital comparison for the same 
reason. Even though low inclusion rates are expected when 
conducting studies among elderly populations, 
4 our results 
may not be generalizable to a general hospital population. 
Loss to follow-up was substantial, which might be expected 
among a frail hospitalized older population, but baseline 
characteristics were similar for patients with or without 
complete follow-up. 
We used both primary and secondary outcomes in our 
study. A possible pitfall in using secondary outcomes is the 
fact that a statistically significant result might have arisen 
by chance alone. The significant results on secondary out-
comes reported here should therefore be interpreted with 
caution. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>Compliance of patients to treatment and recommenda-
tions suggested by the nurse or physicians may have affected 
our results. A limitation of our study is that we had no compli-
ance numbers available. Nevertheless, since patients received 
the majority of the intervention during their hospital stay, we 
expect compliance rates were relatively high. Furthermore, 
we assumed similar compliance rates across the intervention 
and control hospitals, thus expect compliance to be only a 
small factor affecting our results. </p>

<p>Since a group of elderly patients in the study were 
independent in both ADL and IADL before hospital 
admission, a ceiling effect may have occurred. Nevertheless, 
when we removed from our analysis the patients who were 
independent in both ADL and IADL before hospital admis-
sion, results were still similar. It is therefore unlikely that a 
ceiling effect has affected our results. 
When collecting data on hospital readmissions, we did 
not distinguish between planned and unplanned readmis-
sions. Since planned readmissions may not be preventable by 
hospital interventions, we would recommend distinguishing 
between planned and unplanned readmissions in future evalu-
ations with hospital readmissions as an outcome. 
The real-life context in which the PReCaP was imple-
mented and evaluated was a strength, since it made gener-
alization to other contexts possible. Nevertheless, it was a 
limitation as well, since many elements of the PReCaP proved 
difficult to implement. 
15 Problems in implementation might 
be due to the inherent nature of a supplementary complex 
intervention such as the PReCaP. The PReCaP focuses on 
functioning, continued assessments throughout hospital stay, 
avoiding complications, promoting independent functioning, 
and providing support throughout hospital stay and after 
discharge, which all have may contributed to prevention of 
hospital-related disability. 
8 We aimed to evaluate the PReCaP 
as a whole instead of its separate elements. 
5,32 Nevertheless, </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>659 </p>

<p>evaluation of PreCaP for hospitalized elderly </p>

<p>geriatric patients often have multiple problems in different 
domains (eg, cognitive, physical, social). These problems 
are difficult to isolate and may change back and forth over 
time. 
7,8 Therefore, the implementation and evaluation of 
geriatric care programs such as the PReCaP are complicated. 
In addition, patient characteristics, social support, resources, 
and environment will also influence the patient's ability to 
live independently at home after discharge. 
33 It is therefore 
unclear whether differences in cognitive functioning, depres-
sion, and perceived health between the intervention and 
control hospital groups can be attributed solely to imple-
mentation of the PReCaP. 
Furthermore, practical problems interfered with imple-
mentation of the PReCaP, such as lack of capacity within 
the PReCaP hospital (eg, too few trained personnel avail-
able). In addition, the intervention hospital dealt with many 
changes (eg, financial problems, and hospital board as well as 
management changes) that hampered the implementation of 
the intervention. 
15 Moreover, improvements in geriatric care 
offered in the control hospitals limited the contrast between 
the PReCaP hospital and control hospitals. Our results may 
have been influenced by this lack of contrast between the 
intervention hospital and control hospitals. Transitions within 
the three hospitals that were unrelated to the study may have 
influenced outcomes. For example, the SFG has started scal-
ing up its specialized clinical geriatric care in light of the 
implementation of national guidelines on elderly care. The 
lack of contrast between the hospitals in provided health care 
was supported by a qualitative analysis of hospital processes. 
Results of this analysis showed that the three hospitals, even 
though they used different methods, all screened patients at 
admission in order to develop personalized care. They all 
used similar standardized care plans concerning the nursing 
care process, with the exception of the Vlietland Hospital 
geriatric unit and the SFG cardiology unit, in which patient 
independence in daily activities was emphasized more. 
Even though the Vlietland Hospital employs three geriatri-
cians and three geriatric nurses who provide specialized 
geriatric care for older patients hospital wide, the control 
hospitals employ consultative psychiatric nurses who often 
provide advice to (psycho-) geriatric patients. Furthermore, 
all three hospitals employ transfer nurses who coordinate 
the post-discharge follow-up care of older patients. Finally, 
coordination and management, even though different in the 
three hospitals, were comparable in their ultimate goals and 
thus lacked contrast. 
In addition, the setting in which the PReCaP was imple-
mented might have influenced results. The earlier literature </p>

<p>suggests that providing consultative multidisciplinary care 
supplementary to usual care in different hospital departments 
might be less effective than providing multidisciplinary care 
from day 1 via a dedicated integrated team from within an 
inpatient geriatric unit. 
8 The PReCaP contains multidisci-
plinary geriatric care, including regular multidisciplinary 
meetings, and the use of goal-attainment scaling to plan 
individualized care. Nevertheless, since this care was offered 
supplementary to usual care, implementation of the PReCaP 
elements often started days after the patient was admit-
ted, which may have reduced effects on patient outcomes. 
Another, similar suggestion concerns home rehabilitation as 
an effective setting for improving mobility and functioning, </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>since patients will be better able to benefit from rehabilita-
tion if they are able to live in their own home environment. 
The case manager might facilitate rehabilitation in the home 
setting, and can contact external organizations to offer home 
rehabilitation for a patient who they think might benefit. 
Nevertheless, this would be additional treatment after the 
PReCaP ends and as such is not a part of the PReCaP, which 
for the most part takes place during the hospital stay. 
Finally, even though qualitative and quantitative methods 
were combined in our evaluation, researchers had no effect 
on the development or implementation of the intervention, 
the PReCaP itself, which was the responsibility of the inter-
vention hospital and its personnel. Therefore, it is possible 
that the lack of effects of our evaluation were due to the 
evaluation trial being conducted too early in the develop-
ment stage of the PReCaP, 
35 and that the effectiveness of 
the different PReCaP ingredients as well as the feasibility 
of both the implementation of the program as well as the 
starting of an evaluation trial in the current hospital setting 
were questionable. </p>

<p>Conclusion and future directions </p>

<p>Elderly patients at risk of functional decline and treated 
with the PReCaP did not differ in terms of ADL or IADL 
from control patients. Even though the PReCaP possibly 
provides some psychological benefits to hospitalized patients 
at risk of functional decline, we should aim to further study 
prognostic factors and underlying gradients of frailty or 
risk of functional decline, thereby allowing and improving 
the design of integrated interventions that can mediate this 
risk and improve patient outcomes. Further studies should 
evaluate treatments focused on both medical condition and 
domains of reactivation care but tailored to the needs of risk 
groups -for example, patients with cardiovascular diseases. </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>Consequently, patients may have a better prognosis after </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>660 </p>

<p>Asmus-szepesi et al </p>

<p>discharge. This will prevent dependence on informal and 
formal health care and associated costs and instead will help 
older people remain independent in daily life as long as pos-
sible after hospital discharge. </p>

<p>Trial registration </p>

<p>The trial is registered in the Netherlands National Trial 
Register as NTR2317. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by a grant (number 60-61900-98-
130) from the Netherlands Organization for Health Research 
and Development (ZonMw) as part of the National Care for 
the Elderly Program. The sponsor (ZonMw) was not involved 
in any aspect of our research or in preparing the manuscript. 
Other contributors to this study were Annemarie de Vos and 
Jeroen van Wijngaarden, who provided us with valuable 
information on the process evaluation. Also we would like to 
thank Rianne van Eijsden and all data collectors/interviewers 
for their valuable contributions made to data collection and 
Gerard Borsboom for his statistical support. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>KJA performed statistical analyses, and drafted and edited the 
manuscript. LEF performed statistical analyses and editing 
of the manuscript. MAK was involved in study design and 
analysis of costs as well as editing the manuscript. APN and 
TJB were involved in the overall study design and editing 
of the manuscript. JPM and ES were involved in the overall 
study design, planning of statistical analyses, and editing 
of the manuscript. All authors contributed to writing and 
critically reviewing the manuscript and approved the final 
version for publication. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/clinical-interventions-in-aging-journal </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging is an international, peer-reviewed journal 
focusing on evidence-based reports on the value or lack thereof of treatments 
intended to prevent or delay the onset of maladaptive correlates of aging 
in human beings. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, MedLine, </p>

<p>CAS, Scopus and the Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The manuscript 
management system is completely online and includes a very quick and fair 
peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress. 
com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>