<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4374707" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:46+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>As digital imaging is becoming a fundamental part of medical and biomedical research, 
the demand for computer-based evaluation using advanced image analysis is becoming 
an integral part of many research projects. A common problem when developing new 
image analysis algorithms is the need of large datasets with ground truth on which the 
algorithms can be tested and optimized. Generating such datasets is often tedious and 
introduces subjectivity and interindividual and intraindividual variations. An alterna-
tive to manually created ground-truth data is to generate synthetic images where the 
ground truth is known. The challenge then is to make the images sufficiently similar to 
the real ones to be useful in algorithm development. One of the first and most widely 
studied medical image analysis tasks is to automate screening for cervical cancer 
through Pap-smear analysis. As part of an effort to develop a new generation cervical 
cancer screening system, we have developed a framework for the creation of realistic 
synthetic bright-field microscopy images that can be used for algorithm development 
and benchmarking. The resulting framework has been assessed through a visual evalua-
tion by experts with extensive experience of Pap-smear images. The results show that 
images produced using our described methods are realistic enough to be mistaken for 
real microscopy images. The developed simulation framework is very flexible and can 
be modified to mimic many other types of bright-field microscopy images. V C 2015 </p>

<p>The Authors. Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of ISAC </p>

<p><rs type="software">SIMCEP</rs><rs type="software">DIPimage</rs>Figure 9. The creation process of leukocyte clusters. (Left) Shapes generated using parametric model. (Middle) Shape masks added to the 
final cluster. (Right) The final result with added Perlin noise. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p> 
Simulation of Bright-Field Microscopy Images </p>

<p>exponent, I d (x, y) 
n . The background is initialized as a uniform 
image, H(x, y), with a predefined intensity, H(x, y) 5 b. The 
perturbed background illumination can then be written as </p>

<p>I b ðx; yÞ5Hðx; yÞI d ðx; yÞ 
n ; 
(8) </p>

<p>where the exponent, n, controls the strength of the variation. 
We can now add the second type of aberration which is related 
to light scattering in the slide. To simulate these effects, we 
have chosen to use a Perlin noise image, I pe (x, y): [0,1], 
together with a constant, c pe , that controls the strength of the 
variations. Perlin noise is a computationally efficient way of 
generating correlated noise (32). It is commonly used in com-
puter graphics to generate natural looking textures. It is not 
directly based on any physical model of light transport, but 
the results are visually similar to that caused by the light scat-
tering effects. 
The Perlin noise variations are added to the background 
illumination as </p>

<p>I b ðx; yÞ5 Hðx; yÞ2c pe I pe ðx; yÞ 
Â 
Ã 
I d ðx; yÞ 
n : 
(9) </p>

<p>The final step of the background generation is to calcu-
late the logarithm of the generated image, </p>

<p>I b ðx; yÞ5log 10 Hðx; yÞ2c pe I pe ðx; yÞ 
Â 
Ã 
I d ðx; yÞ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>À 
Á 
: 
(10) </p>

<p>This is done to facilitate the use of absorbance values, as 
will be explained in the following section. </p>

<p>Absorbance. In bright-field microscopy an object's color is 
related to its light absorption properties. This behavior can be 
described using the well known Beer-Lambert law (34), which 
states that </p>

<p>A k 52log 10 
I 1 
I 0 
; 
(11)   where A k is the material's absorbance at a specific wavelength, 
k, of incoming light, I 0 is the intensity of the light before it 
passes through the sample, and I 1 is the intensity of light that 
remains after passing through the sample. Essentially, for the 
Pap-smear application, the Beer-Lambert law relates the 
absorbance of the Pap-stain to its concentration </p>

<p>A k 5k3c3l; 
(12) </p>

<p>where k is a constant commonly referred to as the extinction 
coefficient (a characteristic of the dye), c is the concentration 
of the dye, and l is the length of the light path. 
For the simulation, each object type is given a specific 
absorbance value. These values can be directly based on meas-
urements taken from source materials or selected based on a 
specific desired target appearance. In this project, we meas-
ured representative values from our cellular database. </p>

<p>Impulse response. The shape of the PSF for a specific 
bright-field microscopy setup is dependent on the NA of the 
objective used, the refractive index of the medium between 
the sample and the objective lens and the wavelength, k, of the 
image forming light (6). Trying to mathematically determine 
the precise degenerative effects of the PSF for specific hard-</p>

<p>ware specifications can be exceedingly difficult. For this study, 
we have instead chosen to simplify the process by approximat-
ing the impulse response function with a Gaussian function, 
G r . Furthermore, for simplicity and speed, we have elected to 
separate the blurring process into a depth of focus blurring, 
G Dz , and an image plane blurring, G Dx,y . 
Because of the availability of focus stacks as reference 
data, we have been able to quantifiably determine a suitable 
standard deviation for the Gaussian kernel related to the 
depth of focus. This was achieved by first studying a nucleus 
at the focus level at which it is in focus. This level was deter-
mined by summing the gradient magnitude values within the 
cell nuclei for all focus levels and choosing the level with the 
greatest sum. We can then compare each offset step in the 
focus stack to a Gaussian blurred version of the focused 
image, allowing us to decide which sigma yields a degradation 
that lies closest to the observed one. The quantification is 
achieved by taking the sum of the intensity difference for each 
pixel of the nucleus. In Figure 10, a plot showing the optimal 
ratio r/mm, relative to each focus level offset can be seen for a 
sample cell. The same experiment was carried out for a repre-
sentative population of 10 different cells. For small focus off-
sets, it is, due to discretization issues, hard to get reliable 
measurements. However, for offsets &gt;1 mm it becomes appa-
rent that a reasonable approximation of the impulse response 
in the z-direction is r ' d z , where d z is the z-offset in mm. 
The impulse response in the image plane is more difficult 
to approximate quantifiably. Generally, the PSF is smaller in 
the x-y dimension relative to the z-dimension, r x;y &lt; r z . By 
taking an image depicting a step function, that is, a sharp 
edge, and studying the first derivative of that image, it is pos-
sible to obtain an approximation of the PSF that lies close to 
reality. The measured PSF can then be compared to Gaussian 
kernels with different sigma to find the closest match. Using 
this approach, a suitable value for r x,y for the model system 
used in this project was found to be 0.9 pixels corresponding 
to around 0.22 microns. </p>

<p>Signal Detection and Digitalization 
The most commonly used type of imaging sensor within 
microscopy is the charged coupled device (CCD) sensor. 
These sensors operate using a linear transfer function, that is, 
the output signal for each pixel is proportional to the number 
of photons it receives. Optical imaging sensors have, as has 
been previously stated, certain limitations. The dominant 
source of noise in sensors, known as photon noise, is related 
to the fact that the number of photons emitted from a con-
stant light source over a finite time interval is stochastic. 
Under normal operating conditions, this noise is Poisson dis-
tributed and quite easy to simulate. A second type of sensor 
noise significant enough to be added to the simulation is 
called readout noise that is a product of phenomena related to 
the A/D converter and amplification circuits. This noise 
behaves as additive white Gaussian noise (35). </p>

<p>Final Image Formation 
The formation of the final simulated image, I f , can be 
written as </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Cytometry Part A 87A: 212À226, 2015 </p>

<p>
I f ðx; yÞ5g po 10 </p>

<p>I b ðx;yÞ2Ipðx;yÞ </p>

<p>ð 
Þ Ã G rx;y </p>

<p>
1g g 
(13) </p>

<p>where g po and g g constitute the addition of Poisson and Gaussian 
noise, respectively, (*) denotes a convolution operation, G rx;y 
stands for the approximation of the PSF with a Gaussian kernel 
with sigma r x;y , I b ðx; yÞ is the background image generated by 
Eq. (10) and I p ðx; yÞ is a phantom image. The phantom image 
contains the set of N p phantom objects, P5fp 1 ; p 2 ; . . . ; p Np g. To 
simulate the depth of field, each object, p i , is assigned a z position, 
z i , using a median filtered Perlin noise image, scaled to encompass 
the desired depth in the image. The generation of the phantom 
image can then be written as a sum of phantom objects with 
appropriate amounts of out-of-focus blur, </p>

<p>I p 5 
X Np </p>

<p>i51 </p>

<p>p i Ã G rz i 
(14) </p>

<p>The final step of the synthesis process is to remove some 
of the degenerative effects applied to the parts of the image </p>

<p>displaying nucleus texture. Because the nucleus texture is a 
product of patch-based texture generation from source mate-
rial, the texture has actually already been subjected to the 
degenerative effects of the optics and the sensor system. 
Therefore, the final image, I f (x, y) is updated according to </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>f x; y 
ð Þ5I p x; y 
ð ÞC 
0 x; y 
ð Þ1I f x; y 
ð Þð12C 
0 ðx; yÞÞ 
(15) </p>

<p>where C 
0 is a feathered nucleus mask generated as </p>

<p>C 
0 5C Ã G r </p>

<p>C5 
1; if nucleus </p>

<p>0; otherwise </p>

<p>( </p>

<p>(16) </p>

<p>The feathering, or blurring, of the nucleus mask, C, prevents 
the creation of sharp, unnatural edges around the nucleus texture. </p>

<p>EVALUATION </p>

<p>The quality and realism of the synthetic images which are 
generated through the described procedure needs to be </p>

<p>Figure 10. (Top) Nucleus at its focus level (Left) and its actual degeneration at a 1.2-mm offset (Middle image), compared to a Gaussian 
degeneration with r 5 1.2 (Right image). (Bottom) Plot discerning optimal ratio for r relative to the z-offset (lm) as a function of the z-off-
set for specific offsets. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p> 
Simulation of Bright-Field Microscopy Images </p>

<p>evaluated. As we are generating images that can be visually 
inspected, a natural approach is to do a visual comparison 
between synthetic and real images. This approach also seems 
relevant since the most common way of analyzing Pap-test 
specimens is through visual inspection. In designing such a 
test, it becomes important to have realistic conditions for the 
visual inspection. Given unlimited time and the possibility of 
zooming and scrolling the images, it is in most cases possible 
to find out which image is real and which is synthetic. But, 
this is far from the conditions under which this kind of images 
normally are scrutinized. 
We have, therefore, designed a customized evaluation 
test. The experimental design was inspired by a study devised 
by Meyer et al. (36). In that study, users were asked to com-
pare a real scene to an identical computer generated one. For 
the experiment, the subject was showed a tightly cropped view 
of the real and synthetic scene projected through a lightly 
frosted glass, to account for limitations of existing display 
devices. For our validation study, a simple user interface was 
designed. A patch of size 200 3 200 pixels, randomly selected, 
was cut out from an image that in turn was randomly selected 
from a database of images containing 25 synthetic images cre-
ated with varying settings and 25 real images from different 
specimen. Before showing the image to the user, a pixel-wise 
Gaussian noise (r 5 0.7 graylevels) was added. This was done 
to make the variations in background intensity and smooth-
ness between different real images less visually disturbing, 
making it easier to focus on the details in the images. The 
patch was shown to the test subject for 2 s, after which a non-
timed prompt for an answer was displayed. In total, 120 
patches were displayed to each user. However, the first two 
patches were training images used to get the user comfortable 
with the validation system and are not counted in the final 
result. The outcome of this study is discussed in Results 
section. 
Another approach to evaluating the quality of the syn-
thetic image generation algorithms, is to compare results from 
an automated image cytometry algorithm applied to synthetic 
images and real data with expert annotated ground truth (4). 
Other validation approaches have included comparing results 
for several image cytometry tools when used on synthetic 
images (4) or comparing scores for different image descriptive 
features from synthetic and real images (12). 
Such tests can give valuable evaluations of whether the 
feature distributions obtained from the synthetic images are 
the same as those obtained from real ones. There are, however, 
problems in that many aspects of the synthetic images are gen-
erated from feature distributions extracted from real images. 
So, for many simple features such as nuclear size, we can 
obtain perfect agreement between normal and synthetic distri-
butions. Another issue is the fact that manually obtaining a 
suitable ground truth dataset is, as has previously been dis-
cussed, a far from trivial task paired with many difficulties. 
We have as a complement to the visual evaluation made a 
comparison of the distribution of one nontrivial feature, the 
moments of the nuclear texture distribution. The choice is 
motivated by the fact that from a diagnostic perspective, the </p>

<p>key structures in Pap-smear images are the nuclei and their 
chromatin structure. Following the approach taken by Svo-
boda et al. (5), a number of central moments as well as an 
entropy score was calculated for several real and synthetic 
nuclei. The n th central moment is calculated as </p>

<p>l n 5 
X L21 </p>

<p>i50 </p>

<p>z i 2m 
ð 
Þ 
n p z i 
ð Þ; 
(17) </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>m5 
X L21 </p>

<p>i50 </p>

<p>z i p z i 
ð Þ: 
(18) </p>

<p>Here, z i is a discrete random variable denoting the partic-
ular intensity level present in the image. The sum covers the 
range of all the image intensity levels (L). The entropy defines 
the amount of uncertainty in the measured data and is calcu-
lated as </p>

<p>H5 
X L21 </p>

<p>i50 </p>

<p>p z i 
ð Þlog p z i 
ð Þ: 
(19) </p>

<p>Five central moments, n 52,. . .,6, as well as the entropy 
was calculated for a sample of 30 nuclei from real images and 
an equal number from synthetic images. From this, individual 
quantile-quantile (Q-Q) plots have been generated for each 
feature (Fig. 11). A Q-Q plot is a probability plot that com-
pares two distributions by plotting their quantiles against each 
other (37). If the compared populations are drawn from simi-
lar distributions, the points should have an approximately lin-
ear relation. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>An example of a finished synthetic image compared to a 
real image can be seen in Figure 12. The results of the visual 
evaluation can be seen in Table 1. Six test subjects have been 
used for the evaluation. The first (1) test subject is a cytologist 
with over 30 year experience of cervical smear screening. Test 
subjects 2-5 are cytometry algorithm developers with several 
year experiences from developing methods for automated 
Pap-smear analysis. The last test subject (6) is an algorithm 
developer with experience in life-science applications. This 
person had no experience with cytometry images and was 
included as a reference. Also for reference purposes, a random 
result subject (x) has been added to the result. For all subjects, 
the test was the first time they came into contact with the 
image generation method described in this article. All the sub-
jects had prior experience with observing Pap-smear images 
in grayscale. For each user the number of true positives (TP), 
false positives (FP), true negatives (TN), and false negatives 
(FN) were counted. For this evaluation, a real image was 
counted as a positive and a synthetic image as a negative. 
Based on these values, the sensitivity, TP/(TP1FN), and spec-
ificity, TN/(TN1FP), for each user was also calculated. In this 
setting, the sensitivity value relates to the ability to accurately 
detect real images as being real and the specificity the ability 
to accurately detect synthetic images as synthetic. The </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Cytometry Part A 87A: 212À226, 2015 </p>

<p>
sensitivity for the six human test subjects is not consistent 
with a random result (Mean: 0.7667, 95% confidence interval 
[0.671, 0.863]), but it is still low enough to indicate that expe-
rienced individuals had a difficult time separating real images 
from synthetic ones under these experimental conditions. The 
random assignment, "subject x," achieved almost as good 
results as the actual persons, it deviated somewhat from the 
expected 0.50 in sensitivity and specificity as the population 
size was rather small. A different experimental design may 
have given different results. It is usually possible to tell the dif-
ference if you are given unlimited time and can zoom and 
scroll the image arbitrarily. But in routine cytology screening, 
the time available for this analysis is extremely limited so our 
conclusion is that our synthetic images are visually quite simi-
lar to real ones when studied under realistic conditions. 
The Q-Q plot in Figure 11 show a distinct linear relation-
ship between the synthetic and real nuclei for all features, 
indicating that, as is expected, the two populations are drawn 
from similar distributions. However, the angle of the linear 
dependency shows that the real data have a wider distribution 
than the synthetic data. This, again, is not surprising as each 
synthetic nucleus texture represents a combination of data 
from three real nuclei. The choice of using three nuclei as a 
sampling base stems from an effort to make the texture of the 
synthetic nuclei more general and not a scrambled copy of a 
single. This had the side effect of making the variation in the 
synthesized textures somewhat smaller than in the real ones. </p>

<p>This effect would be reduced if we used a single real nucleus 
as a model for the texture of a synthetic one. 
We have generated a small population of synthetic images 
and also picked an equal number of real images and cropped 
those to the same size as the synthetic ones and supplied these 
two image datasets as Supporting Information allowing the 
reader to evaluate the similarities and differences between the 
images. These images can be found as a Supporting 
Information. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this article, we present a synthetic image generation 
framework for simulating bright-field microscopy images of 
cervical cell populations. The simulation method accurately 
models object primitives as well as the characteristics and 
behavior of the measurement system. In our evaluation study, 
even experienced cytology professionals showed rather poor 
performance in deciding whether an image was synthetic or 
real when shown the images under realistic screening condi-
tions. A simple test on nuclear texture features indicated that 
they came from similar distributions. 
The presented framework offers a flexible approach to 
image synthesis. Each block of the process is interchangeable 
depending on the requirements on the finished results. Fur-
thermore, if needed, additional object types can be added with 
minimal effort using the methods and principles described in </p>

<p>Figure 11. Quantile-quantile plot comparison of descriptors computed from real and synthetic cervical cell nuclei. The quantile-quantile 
plot illustrate whether the acquired measurements belong to the same distribution. A linear relationship indicates that points belong to the 
same probability distribution. When the trend is steeper than 45 degrees, which is the case in the plots above, it is an indication that the 
data plotted on the y-axis, which refers to real data in this figure, has a larger dispersion than the x-axis data. The descriptors shown above 
are: (Top row, left to right) second central moment, third central moment, and fourth central moment. (Bottom row, left to right) Fifth central 
moment, sixth central moment, and entropy. [Color figure can be viewed in the online issue, which is available at wileyonlinelibrary.com.] </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p> 
Simulation of Bright-Field Microscopy Images </p>

<p>this article. As an example, the addition of other common cer-
vical epithelial cell types, for example, parabasal cells or squa-
mous superficial cells, can be achieved by creating small 
databases of primitives that can then be used as the basis for 
shape and texture generation. To illustrate this, a dataset of 
cells, expert classified to exhibit signs conforming to high 
grade intraepithelial lesions, were collected and added to the 
simulation pipeline. A resulting image can be seen in Figure 
13. This flexibility indicates that the synthesis process could 
be adapted to mimic other types of cellular material com-
monly analyzed using bright-field microscopy, for example, 
lung or oral cavity smears. 
For the time being, the method produces one diagnostic 
cell type (squamous intermediate) and four levels of debris. In 
the future, more cell types and other types of debris should be 
added. Also, other common types of distortion such as folding 
should be included to the cytoplasm model to add even more 
variety in the shapes that are produced. The greatest benefit 
with the use of simulated images is the availability of ground 
truth. Using simulated images reduces the dependency on 
manually generated ground-truth data, which has the draw-
back of being expensive and time consuming to produce. </p>

<p>Well-designed synthetic images make it possible to reserve 
that valuable ground truth data for final control validation. 
For instance, first the endless supply of synthetic data can be 
used to form hypotheses about how varying amount of debris 
or inhomogeneous background illumination will affect the 
qualitative performance of a segmentation algorithm. Then 
brute force parameter tuning, over an arbitrary large parame-
ter space, can point out optimal parameters, a plausible range 
of optimal parameters or relations and dependence between 
different optimal parameter settings from which the algorithm 
designer can gain insight and form hypotheses. Then finally, a 
rigorous and more data economical procedure can be used for 
fine tuning and cross-validation on expert annotated real data 
to estimate the performance of an algorithm on real life data. 
It is important to recognize the fact that, while synthetic 
images can function as a great development tool, problems </p>

<p>Figure 12. An example of a finished synthetic image (Left) an a real image for comparison (Right). </p>

<p>Table 1. Results of evaluation of the generated synthetic images </p>

<p>SUBJECT 
TP 
FP 
TN 
FN 
SENS. 
SPEC. </p>

<p>1 
35 
29 
37 
17 
0.67 
0.56 
2 
39 
29 
29 
21 
0.65 
0.50 
3 
50 
16 
38 
14 
0.78 
0.70 
4 
49 
20 
36 
13 
0.79 
0.64 
5 
51 
17 
39 
11 
0.82 
0.70 
6 
58 
32 
21 
7 
0.89 
0.40 
x 
37 
31 
24 
26 
0.54 
0.48 </p>

<p>Results are shown for the six test subjects (1-6) and a ran-
dom result (x). The results show the number of true positives 
(TP), the number of false positives (FP), the number of true nega-
tives (TN), and the number of false negatives (FN). From these 
numbers, the sensitivity TP/(TP1FN) and specificity TN/(TN1FP) 
have also been calculated. </p>

<p>Figure 13. Example of two simulated cells corresponding to high 
grade lesions added to the simulation framework. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Cytometry Part A 87A: 212À226, 2015 </p>

<p>
such as overfitting need to be taken into account. Because syn-
thetic images are the result of their defining parameters, there 
exists a limitation in the variation present in the images. 
Good design can, to a certain extent, alleviate the problem, 
but the fact remains that real data remains a necessity in the 
creation of any image processing algorithm aimed at real 
world applications. However, one can compare the risk of 
overfitting synthetic data with the risks of overfitting when 
tuning algorithms with the help of small amounts of real 
ground truth data. We can benefit from the great flexibility of 
synthetic data, while at the same time guarantee an estimate 
on real data if proper cross-validation is performed for the 
final parameter tuning using real expert annotated data. </p>

<p>AVAILABILITY </p>

<p>The synthesis framework described in this article is avail-
able on the <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> file-exchange, at http://www.mathworks. 
com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/48915-synthetic-bright-field-
microscopy-image-generator, as an open-source code package 
on publication acceptance. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank the participants of the 
user study. The work was carried out within the framework of 
a collaboration with a research project at the Center for 
Advanced Computing in Thiruvananthapuram headed by 
Rajesh Kumar and the Regional Cancer Center, Kerala, India, 
headed by Dr K Sujathan, funded by the Department of Infor-
mation Technology, Government of India. Ethical permit for 
using stained Pap smears was obtained from Indian Council 
of Medical Research, permit number INDO/FRC/402/2005-
IHD. Funding was also provided by the Swedish Research 
Council (2008-2738) and VINNOVA (2008-01712). </p>

<p>LITERATURE CITED </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p> 
Simulation of Bright-Field Microscopy Images </p>

</text></tei>