<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4003544" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>King cobra (Ophiophagus hannah) venom L-amino acid oxidase (OH-LAAO), a heat stable en-
zyme, has been shown to exhibit very potent anti-proliferative activity against human breast and 
lung tumorigenic cells but not in their non-tumorigenic counterparts. We further examine its in 
vitro and in vivo anti-tumor activity in a human prostate adenocarcinoma (PC-3) model. OH-LAAO 
demonstrated potent cytotoxicity against PC-3 cells with IC 50 of 0.05 µg/mL after 72 h incubation 
in vitro. It induced apoptosis as evidenced with an increase in caspase-3/7 cleavages and an increase 
in annexin V-stained cells. To examine its in vivo anti-tumor activity, we treated PC-3 tumor 
xenograft implanted subcutaneously in immunodeficient NU/NU (nude) mice with 1 µg/g 
OH-LAAO given intraperitoneally (i.p.). After 8 weeks of treatment, OH-LAAO treated PC-3 
tumors were markedly inhibited, when compared to the control group (P &lt;0.05). TUNEL staining 
analysis on the tumor sections showed a significantly increase of apoptotic cells in the 
LAAO-treated animals. Histological examinations of the vital organs in these two groups showed 
no significant differences with normal tissues, indicating no obvious tissue damage. The treatment 
also did not cause any significant changes on the body weight of the mice during the duration of the 
study. These observations suggest that OH-LAAO cytotoxic effects may be specific to tumor 
xenografts and less to normal organs. Given its potent anti-tumor activities shown in vitro as well as 
in vivo, the king cobra venom LAAO can potentially be developed to treat prostate cancer and 
other solid tumors. </p>

<p>Prostate cancer is the second leading cause of 
cancer deaths after lung cancer worldwide [1]. Similar 
to other cancers, prostate cancer arise from prostate 
epithelial cells which display uncontrollable growth 
(beyond the normal limits), invasion, and metastasis 
capabilities [2]. Current chemotherapy regimen for 
prostate cancer usually involves the use of substances </p>

<p>toxic to normal cells and hence the treatment is usu-
ally accompanied by a range of side effects such as 
vomiting, nausea and alopecia. Thus, there is contin-
ual need to search for potential natural-based cancer 
therapeutic agents that exhibit highly selective cyto-
toxicity against cancer cells over the normal cells. 
Snake venom L-amino acid oxidase (LAAO, </p>

<p>Ivyspring </p>

<p>International Publisher </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>L-amino acid: O 2 oxidoreductase, EC 1.4.3.2) has been 
reported to exhibit a wide range of pharmacological 
activities including anti-proliferative [3] and an-
ti-bacterial activities [4]. It catalyzes oxidative deam-
ination of L-amino acid to produce the corresponding 
α-keto acid, hydrogen peroxide and ammonia [5,6]. 
The biological activities are primarily caused by the 
hydrogen peroxide produced during the oxidative 
deamination and the cytotoxic action was believed to 
exert via apoptosis [3]. Unlike other venom LAAOs, 
king cobra (Ophiophagus hannah) venom LAAO, with a 
molecular weight of 130 kDa, has an unusual thermal 
stability. At pH 7.4, the enzyme retained 100% activity 
after incubation at 37 °C for 5 days. Unlike other snake 
venom LAAO, king cobra venom LAAO was stable at 
alkaline condition and was not inactivated by freezing 
[7]. Because of these favourable stability properties, 
king cobra venom LAAO has a greater potential, 
when compared to other venom LAAOs, to be de-
veloped as a cancer therapeutic agent. Earlier studies 
also showed that the king cobra venom enzyme ex-
hibited extremely potent anti-proliferative activities in 
comparison with other venom LAAOs, and that its 
cytotoxicity was selective against tumorigenic cells 
[3]. 
Here we examined the enzyme's anti-tumor 
effect in a PC-3 tumor xenograft mouse model 
implanted in immunodeficient NU/NU mice, and 
evaluated its toxicity on vital organs. As yet, there are 
very few studies that demonstrated the in vivo an-
ti-cancer action of snake venom LAAOs on tumors [8]. 
Human prostate adenocarcinoma (PC-3) cell line was 
used in this study because of its irresponsiveness to 
androgens, glucocorticoids, or epidermal or fibroblast 
growth factors [9]. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Ethics statement </p>

<p>All animal handling and procedures were per-
formed according to the CIOMS guidelines [10]. The 
use of animals in this study was approved by the 
Animal Care and Use Committee (ACUC) of the 
University of Malaya (Ethical clearance letter No. 
2013-06-07/MOL/R/FSY). </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>Four-week-old, male NU/NU mice (18-25 g) 
were purchased from BioLASCO, Taiwan (Certificate 
no: VP302S10023105). All mice were housed under 
specific pathogen free (SPF) conditions (3 mice per 
cage) and were fed with sterilized standard pellets 
and water ad libitum. To allow sufficient adaption to 
the new environment, these mice were housed for a 
week prior to the start of experiments. </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>Human prostate adenocarcinoma (PC-3) cell line 
was purchased from American Type Culture Collec-
tion (ATCC) (USA). The cells were grown in 
RPMI-1640 (Biowest, France) media supplemented 
with 10% foetal bovine serum (Sigma, USA). Cells 
were cultured in a humidified 37 °C incubator with 
5% CO2 atmosphere. </p>

<p>Isolation of L-amino acid oxidase from king 
cobra venom and assay of enzyme activity </p>

<p>The venom, which was milked from several 
adult Malaysian king cobras, was obtained from 
Snake Valley (Seremban, Malaysia). The snakes were 
identified by one of the authors (N.H. Tan). King co-
bra snake venom LAAO was purified using a sin-
gle-step Resource Q high performance liquid chro-
matography as described previously [4]. L-amino acid 
oxidase activity was determined according to Berg-
meyer [11], using L-leucine as substrate, as described 
in Lee et al. [4]. Protein concentration was determined 
by the Bradford method [12] and the specific activity 
of the purified OH-LAAO obtained was 437.7 
μmol/min/mg [4]. </p>

<p>Cell viability assay </p>

<p>The cytotoxic effect of king cobra venom LAAO 
and the IC 50 values were determined using MTT 
(3,(4,5-dimethythiazol-2-yl)-2,3-diphenyl tetrazolium 
bromide) method according to Ahn et al. [13] with 
modifications [3]. </p>

<p>Caspase-3/7 and PE-Annexin V/7-AAD assays </p>

<p>Caspase-3/7 activity was measured using 
Caspase-Glo ® 3/7 assay kit (Promega, USA) accord-
ing to the manufacturer's protocol as described pre-
viously [3]. Human prostate adenocarcinoma (PC-3) 
cells were seeded into white-walled 96-well plates 
and treated with LAAO at its IC 50 . The luminescence 
of each sample was measured using Glomax-Multi 
detection system (Promega, USA). PE-Annexin 
V/7-AAD assay was performed using PE annexin V 
apoptosis detection kit I (BD Biosciences, USA) ac-
cording to the manufacturer's instructions and as de-
scribed in Lee at al. [3]. The cells were treated with 
0.05 µg/mL of LAAO (IC50 of PC-3) for 72 h. Data 
analysis were performed using FCS express 4 flow 
software (De Novo software, CA) and results were 
expressed in density plots and plotted as 7-AAD 
versus PE-Annexin V. </p>

<p>PC-3 tumor xenograft mouse model </p>

<p>Prostate adenocarcinoma cells (PC-3) were 
grown to 80% -90% confluency before harvested us-
ing trypsin-EDTA (Sigma, USA). The cells were </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>washed twice with PBS followed by centrifugation. 
The cell pellet was re-suspended in PBS and the 
number of viable cells was determined using trypan 
blue exclusion method and counted with a haemocy-
tometer. The cell suspension was then mixed with an 
equal volume of Matrigel TM (BD Biosciences, USA). 
Each mouse was inoculated subcutaneously (s.c) with 
200 µL of the cells-Matrigel TM mixture which con-
tained approximately 0.6 x 10 7 cells. Mice were exam-
ined daily for tumor growth at the injection site. Tu-
mor volumes (mm 3 ) were measured weekly using a 
digital calliper and were calculated as length x width 
x height x π/6, to approximate the volume of a sphe-
roid. When the tumor volume had reached about 100 -
200 mm 3 (usually 1 -2 weeks after injection of the 
PC-3 cells), mice were randomly assigned into two 
groups (n = 6/group). Mice were treated i.p daily for 8 
weeks with either vehicle (PBS) or LAAO at a dose of 
1 µg/g/day/200 µL. The tumor volume and body 
weight of the individual animals were monitored and 
recorded weekly over the 8-week treatment period. </p>

<p>Toxicity study of LAAO in tumor-bearing mice </p>

<p>Mice from both treated and control group were 
sacrificed by cervical dislocation under anesthesia at 
the end of the 8 weeks study. Vital organs (lung, liver, 
heart, spleen, kidneys) and solid tumor tissues were 
harvested and fixed in 10% buffered formalin for 48 h. 
The tissues were dehydrated by ethanol and cleared 
with xylene followed by paraffin embedding and sec-
tioning processes. Histological sections were stained 
with hematoxylin and eosin and examined using light 
microscopy. </p>

<p>TdT-mediated dUTP nicked-end labelling 
(TUNEL) immunohistochemical staining </p>

<p>Terminal 
deoxynucleotidyl 
transferase 
(TdT)-mediated dUTP nicked-end labelling (TUNEL) 
for the detection of apoptotic cells were performed 
using ApopTag ® plus peroxidase in situ apoptosis 
detection kit (Millipore, USA) according to the man-
ufacturer's protocols. Briefly, 5 µm thin tumor sec-
tions mounted on the silanized slides were dewaxed, 
washed with PBS and pre-treated with proteinase K 
(20 mg/mL) (Millipore, USA) for 15 min. Sections 
were then quenched in 3% hydrogen peroxide for 5 
min and an adequate amount of the equilibration 
buffer was applied onto each section and incubated 
for 10 sec. Subsequently, tumor sections were incu-
bated with TdT enzyme at 37 °C for 1 h in a humidi-
fied chamber. After labelling, sections were washed 
and allowed to bind to anti-digoxigenin conjugate in a 
humidified chamber for 30 min. Slides were then 
stained with 3, 3'-diaminobenzidine (DAB) peroxi-
dase substrate for 5 min, counter stained with 0.5% </p>

<p>methyl green for 10 min and finally mounted under 
the coverslips. Slides were examined under light mi-
croscope and the pictures of 5 random fields of view 
per section at 200X magnification were taken. The 
percentage of apoptotic cells were scored as an aver-
age of the ratio of TUNEL-positive cells to the total 
number of cells presence in each field. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Results for cytotoxicity, caspase-3/7 and 
PE-annexin V/7-AAD were expressed as mean ± S.D. 
The in vivo anti-tumor activity was expressed as mean 
± S.E.M. The significance of the differences of the 
means was determined by one way ANOVA, fol-
lowed by Tukey's post hoc multiple comparison test. 
The statistical analysis was conducted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">17.0</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Cytotoxicity of king cobra venom LAAO 
(OH-LAAO) against PC-3 cells </p>

<p>The cytotoxic activity of OH-LAAO on PC-3 cell 
line was dose-dependent (Figure 1). The cell kill 
curves were similar between 24 h and 72 h, yielding 
IC 50 values 0.08 ± 0.02 and 0.05 ± 0.01 µg/mL, respec-
tively. LAAO-treated cells also demonstrated a 
3.8-fold increase in caspase-3/7 activity, when com-
pared with vehicle-treated cells (Figure 2A). Low lev-
els of caspase-3/7 activity was also detected in the 
control cells, which was presumably due to the small 
amount of apoptotic cells present in the growing cell 
population. PE-annexin V/7-AAD analysis also 
showed greater number of apoptotic cells by 
OH-LAAO treatment (29.5%) compared to vehicle 
group (4.8%) (Figure 2B). These data suggest that 
LAAO-mediated cell death in PC-3 cells is via induc-
tion of apoptosis </p>

<p>Anti-tumor effects of OH-LAAO in PC-3 
tumor xenograft mouse model </p>

<p>PC-3 tumor-bearing nude mice were treated 
with 1 µg/g/day of OH-LAAO for 8 weeks. As shown 
in Figure 3, LAAO-treated tumors grew markedly 
slower than those treated with vehicle. A significant 
difference in mean tumor size was seen between ve-
hicle-treated and LAAO-treated group (P &lt;0.01), as 
early as 7 days post treatment. By the 8 th week, tumors 
in control mice had grown to greater than 700% of the 
original size (size of the tumor at the start of treatment 
= 100%), whereas for the treated mice, the average 
tumor size was 300% of their original size (P &lt;0.01, 
between treated and control). All tumors were har-
vested at the end of the study (week 8). Interestingly, 
one of the tumors achieved complete regression with 
no sign of tissue left for harvest. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Figure 1. The cytotoxic actions of king cobra venom LAAO (OH-LAAO) on PC-3 cells. The PC-3 cells were treated with different concentrations of OH-LAAO 
(0.01 -5.00 µg/mL) for 24 h (A) or 72 h (B), with or without catalase (400 µg/mL). The viability of the cells was measured by MTT assay. Results given are mean ± S.D (n = 3). 
Solid line -■-: without catalase; Broken line ---♦---: with catalase. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Apoptotic effects of king cobra venom LAAO (OH-LAAO) on PC-3 cells. A) Caspase-3/7 activities of OH-LAAO treated cells. The PC-3 cells were treated 
with OH-LAAO at IC50 dosage (0.05 µg/mL) for 72h. Caspase-3/7 activities were determined using Caspase-Glo 3/7 assay kit (n= 3). The fold change of the control is considered 
as 1 and the error bars indicate standard deviations. * P &lt; 0.05 in the LAAO-treated versus control cells. B) PE-Annexin V/7-AAD analysis of the effect of OH-LAAO treatment 
on the PC-3 cells. The cells were treated with 0.05 µg/mL of OH-LAAO for 72 h and were then stained with Annexin V conjugated to Phycoerythrin (PE) and 
7-Amino-Actinomycin D (7-AAD) prior to the FACS analysis. Cells (10,000 events) were analyzed by fluorescent-activated cell scanner. The lower left quadrant contains the 
viable (Annexin V negative; 7-AAD negative) population, the upper left quadrant contains the damage (Annexin V negative; 7-AAD positive) population, the upper right quadrant 
contains the late apoptotic (Annexin V positive; 7-AAD positive) cells and the lower right quadrant contains the early apoptotic (Annexin V positive; 7-AAD negative) cells. Left: 
PC-3 cells control; Right: OH-LAAO treated PC-3 cells. Total apoptotic cells (%) are shown in each figure. Figures are representatives of duplicate analysis from 2-independent 
experiments. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Figure 3. Anti-tumor effect of OH-LAAO on solid PC-3 prostrate tumor in nude mice. PC-3 tumor-bearing mice were treated i.p. daily with either vehicle (control, 
broken line---♦---, n = 6) or OH-LAAO (1 µg/g, solid line -■-, n = 6). Tumors were measured weekly, and the percentage of tumor volume was shown after comparison with 
those at week 0. Data was expressed as mean ± SEM. (P &lt;0.05 for data points marked with *, P &lt;0.01 for data points marked with #). Insert A: Representative tumor image of 
the control group. Insert B: Representative tumor image of the LAAO-treated group. </p>

<p>Toxicity study of OH-LAAO in tumor-bearing 
mice </p>

<p>To further evaluate whether daily treatment of 
OH-LAAO in tumor-bearing nude mice for 8 weeks 
affected the vital organs, we performed detailed his-
tological examinations on the organs harvested at the 
end of study. Heart, kidney, liver, lung and spleen in 
LAAO-treated mice did not show any abnormal 
pathological changes when compared to those in ve-
hicle-treated mice (Figure 4). Also, the body weight of 
the LAAO-treated group did not differ (P &gt;0.05) from 
the vehicle-treated mice throughout the treatment 
period (Figure 5). </p>

<p>OH-LAAO induced apoptosis in PC-3 tumor 
cells </p>

<p>To determine whether LAAO-mediated tumor 
size reduction is due to induction of apoptosis, we 
examined the DNA fragmentation in these tumors 
using TUNEL assay. Representative tumor sections 
stained with TUNEL are shown in Figure 6A. Signif-
icant greater apoptotic cells were observed in 
LAAO-treated tumors (26.7%) than in vehicle-treated 
tumors (2.5%) (Figure 6B). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We previously showed that king cobra venom 
LAAO exerts potent cytotoxicity against breast cancer 
and lung cancer cells [3]. In this study, we further 
showed that OH-LAAO is similarly potent in inhibit-
ing the growth of human prostate cancer cells, PC-3, </p>

<p>in vitro and in vivo. Its cytotoxicity is due to induction 
of apoptosis, as in agreement with previous reports 
[14-20]. In vivo studies using PC-3 tumor xenograft in 
nude mice showed that 8 weeks of OH-LAAO treat-
ment at a dose of 1 μg/g (i.p.) markedly inhibited the 
growth of the solid tumor. 
The dose of 1 μg/g OH-LAAO was chosen for 
experimental treatment as earlier work reported that 
the enzyme has an LD50 of 5.0 µg/g [7]. The 8-week 
OH-LAAO treatment at this dose indeed did not 
cause any significant differences in the body weight 
between the treated and control mice, nor any signif-
icant pathological abnormalities in the major organs 
of the treated animals. These observations, together 
with the high IC50 of OH-LAAO determined in 
non-tumorigenic breast and lung cells as reported 
earlier [3], strongly suggest that this enzyme is rela-
tively non-toxic to normal tissues. The selective cyto-
toxicity of OH-LAAO could be due to the differences 
in the metabolism of the cells (tumor cells versus 
non-tumorigenic cells) or the selective binding of the 
enzyme to tumorigenic cells. Wei et al. [21] reported 
that at dosage up to 50 µg Bungarus faciastus LAAO 
did not induce significant organ damage including 
lung, heart, kidneys, liver and spleen. Bregge-Silva et 
al. [22] reported that 100 µg of Lachesis muta LAAO 
did not cause morphological changes in the heart, 
lung and kidney tissues. However, Wei et al. [23] re-
ported that 50 µg of Agkistrodon blomhoffii ussurensis 
LAAO caused severe lung lesions after 6 and 24 h 
injections, indicating that LAAOs from different 
venoms may differ in their toxicity. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Figure 4. Histological sections of major organs of OH-LAAO treated mice. Hematoxylin and eosin stained sections of heart, kidney, liver, lung and spleen tissues of 
vehicle-treated mice (1A -5A) as well as mice treated with i.p. administration of 1 µg/g of OH-LAAO daily for 8 weeks (1B -5B). The treatment did not reveal significant 
pathological changes. Images were shown at 100X magnification. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Figure 5. OH-LAAO treatment did not affect body weight of mice. Changes in body weight of the mice in OH-LAAO-treated group and control group were de-
termined weekly. There was no significant differences in the average body weight of the two groups over the 8 weeks treatment period (P &gt; 0.05). Solid line -■-: Treated mice; 
Broken line ---♦---: Control mice. Data was expressed as mean ± SEM. </p>

<p>Figure 6. Apoptotic effect of OH-LAAO in PC-3 solid tumor.(A) Representative TUNEL stained of tumor sections harvested from tumor-bearing nude mice treated 
with vehicle (PBS, the controls) and OH-LAAO, at 200X magnifications. Apoptosis were evidenced in cells with dark brown-stained nuclei. (B) Percentage of TUNEL-positive 
cells in tumor sections from the vehicle-(n = 6) and LAAO-treated mice (n = 5). One of the tumors from the LAAO-treated group achieved complete regression, with no tumor 
tissue left after 8-weeks treatment. Data was expressed as mean ± SEM. * P &lt; 0.05 in the LAAO-treated versus control group. </p>

<p>The detailed mechanism of cytotoxic action of 
snake venom LAAO on cancer cells has not been es-
tablished. A possibility is that the injected OH-LAAO 
acts by binding to the tumor cell surface and generates </p>

<p>a highly localized (and hence concentrated) H 2 O 2. The 
H 2 O 2 may have direct cytotoxic action or may act via 
the oxidative modifications of signalling proteins. The 
dose of OH-LAAO chosen in the in vivo anti-tumor </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>studies (1 µg/g body weight) was estimated to give a 
theoretical level of LAAO of about 5 µg/mL in the 
extracellular fluid (ECF) of the mice, assuming that 
ECF was 20% of body weight [24], if all the injected 
LAAO were absorbed and distributed throughout the 
entire ECF compartment instantaneously. This level 
would far exceed the IC50 dose of PC-3 cells in vitro. 
However, it should be noted that absorption of LAAO 
injected is not likely to be instantaneous, and not all 
injected LAAO would be absorbed. Further, a certain 
quantity of LAAO may be degraded or excreted be-
fore it reaches the target cells. Also, the rate and abil-
ity of the LAAO to permeate the capillary wall and 
penetrate to the tumor cells are likely to be limited. 
Thus, the exact level of LAAO that the tumor cells in 
the treated mice are exposed to is likely to be much 
lower than 5 µg/mL. Nevertheless, at this dose of 
treatment (1 µg/g body weight) the LAAO in the 
animals was shown to be able to inhibit growth of the 
tumor effectively, with no visible deleterious effect on 
the major organs or reducing the body weight of the 
animals. 
It is well established that many anticancer drugs 
cannot penetrate solid tumor tissue efficiently to reach 
the target cancer cells due to the tumor microenvi-
ronment [25] and this is particularly likely also for a 
large molecules such as snake venom LAAOs (with 
molecular weight of 130 kDa), which possess low 
diffusion coefficient. In our studies, we demonstrated 
that despite the large molecular size, king cobra 
venom LAAO could effectively inhibit solid tumor 
growth in vivo. Compared to the control, treatment 
with OH-LAAO caused 39% reduction on PC-3 tumor 
size in the mice (P &lt;0.01) after just one week of treat-
ment. While substantial individual variation in an-
ti-tumor effect was observed in the LAAO-treated 
mice during the 8-week treatment. Our data demon-
strate that king cobra venom LAAO could indeed 
effectively inhibit tumor growth in vivo. The ability of 
king cobra venom LAAO to effectively inhibit the 
tumor growth is presumably due to its very high cy-
totoxicity towards PC-3 cells (IC50 = 0.05 µg/mL, 72 h 
incubation). Earlier, Zhang and Wu [8] reported that 
10 days treatment with 1.5 µg/g of Agkistrodon acutus 
venom LAAO inhibited tumor growth of Hepatoma 
22, Sarcoma 180 and Ehrlich ascites carcinoma tumors 
(established in Kun Ming mice) by 21.6%, 12.9% and 
14.2%, respectively. However, it is not known wheth-
er the mice used were immunocompromised and 
hence the validity of results difficult to assess. In this 
study, we used immunocompromised mice, and the 
king cobra venom LAAO yielded greater level of 
growth inhibition, including one complete regression 
after 8 weeks of treatment. 
In conclusion, the effectiveness of king cobra </p>

<p>venom LAAO in suppressing the growth of solid tu-
mors in vivo without causing much significant toxic 
effects supports its potential as an anti-cancer agent. 
However, its high molecular weight may hinder its 
penetration into the tumor; therefore further devel-
opment in delivery system may be required. For ex-
ample, magnetic nanoparticle-enzyme system may 
allow the use of lower amount of LAAO to target 
specifically the tumor area, while maintaining maxi-
mal cytotoxicity. This approach has been used in the 
application D-amino acid oxidase for cancer treatment 
[26]. In addition, the enzyme is probably more effec-
tive against cancer cell suspensions such as leukemias 
and ascites, than in solid tumors. Alternatively, the 
enzyme could be cloned and transfected to tumor 
cells to induce cell death in situ, an approach sug-
gested by Sun et al. [17]. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Ms Kavita S. Subramaniam for her as-
sistance in FACS analysis. This work was supported 
by UMRG 075/12BIO and PV 069/2011B from 
University of Malaya. </p>

<p>Competing Interests </p>

<p>The authors have declared that no competing 
interest exists. </p>



<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>





</text></tei>