<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4913543" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Cluster of differentiation 44 (CD44) is an important surface marker of cancer stem </p>

<p>cells in a variety of tumors. A number of previous studies have been conducted to investigate 
the association between CD44 gene rs13347 CT polymorphism and cancer risk in humans; 
nevertheless, the results remain controversial. We therefore performed this meta-analysis to 
confirm the role of this polymorphism in susceptibility to human cancer. 
Materials and methods: The studies published up to December 2015 were searched in </p>

<p>PubMed, Web of Science, and China National Knowledge Infrastructure databases. Twelve 
eligible case-control studies were identified, involving a total of 6,982 cases and 7,430 controls. 
Pooled odds ratio (OR) and corresponding 95% confidence interval (CI) were calculated using 
a fixed or random-effect model to estimate the strength of the association. 
Results: The results of the overall analyses indicated that CD44 gene rs13347 polymorphism was </p>

<p>significantly associated with cancer risk in Asians (CT vs CC: OR =1.35, 95% CI =1.12-1.62; 
TT vs CC: OR =1.99, 95% CI =1.52-2.60; TT + CT vs CC: OR =1.41, 95% CI =1.16-1.71; and 
TT vs CC + CT: OR =1.74, 95% CI =1.41-2.14), especially in Chinese population (CT vs CC: 
OR =1.42, 95% CI =1.16-1.75; TT vs CC: OR =2.13, 95% CI =1.58-2.86; TT + CT vs CC: 
OR =1.50, 95% CI =1.21-1.87; and TT vs CC + CT: OR =1.80, 95% CI =1.43-2.26). In stratified 
analyses by cancer types, there was evidence for an association between this polymorphism and 
nasopharyngeal cancer and breast cancer, respectively. 
Conclusion: The results of this meta-analysis suggest that the CD44 gene rs13347 CT poly-</p>

<p>morphism is associated with elevated risk of human cancer in Asians, especially in Chinese 
population. Further well-designed studies on a larger population covering other ethnicities 
should be carried out to validate our results. 
Cancer is currently a serious public health burden in the world, which results from 
interactions between accumulations of genetic mutation and environmental risk 
factors. 1,2 In recent years, a small subgroup of cancer cells, called cancer stem 
cells (CSCs), have been proved to be responsible for tumor initiation, progression, 
metastasis, recurrence, and drug resistance and cause cancer heterogeneity. 3 Thus, 
eliminating CSCs is considered to be efficient and critical in cancer therapy. 4 Several 
cell surface markers have been found to identify CSCs, and overexpression of these 
markers, such as cluster of differentiation 44 (CD44), CD24, CD133, CD166, and 
ALDH1A1, indicates severe clinical features and poor prognosis in a number of 
cancers. 5-10 Among these cell surface markers, CD44 is one of the most frequently </p>

<p>correspondence: Xiaoxi Zhou 
Department of respiratory Medicine, 
Zhejiang hospital, 12 lingyin road, 
hangzhou 310009, Zhejiang Province, 
People's republic of china 
Tel +86 571 8798 7373 
Fax +86 571 8798 2776 
email xingeliu@hotmail.com </p>

<p>Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
13 June 2016 </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3494 </p>

<p>shi et al </p>

<p>reported markers, which was utilized to isolate CSCs from 
other cancer cells. 11-13 
CD44, a transmembrane glycoprotein, is ubiquitously 
expressed in many cell types. 14 As a cell surface receptor 
for hyaluronate and osteopontin, CD44 is involved in 
many biological and physiological processes including cell 
migration, hematopoiesis, lymphocyte homing, embryonal 
development, and apoptosis. 14,15 Besides its regulation 
of cellular processes, CD44 plays a critical role in tumor 
cell proliferation, differentiation, invasion, and migration, 
which contributes to the progression and metastasis of 
tumors. 16-19 Therefore, overexpression of CD44 leads to the 
development of tumors and poor prognosis of several human 
malignancies. 20-22 In addition, it has been reported that CD44 + 
cancer cells represent enhanced resistance to chemotherapy 
in the nude mice-engrafted tumor model. 23,24 Recent studies 
have revealed that the genetic variants of CD44 gene could 
influence tumor cell growth and migration, 25,26 which were 
associated with the risk prediction and prognosis of various 
human cancers. 27-29 
The gene encoding CD44 is located on chromosome 
11p13. 30 A growing number of studies have been carried out 
to investigate the effects of several CD44 gene single nucle-
otide polymorphisms (SNPs) on cancer risk. Among them, the 
rs13347 CT polymorphism, located on the 3′-untranslated 
region (3′-UTR) of CD44 gene, is the most frequently 
studied. 20,31,32 This SNP might influence the CD44 gene expres-
sion, since it has been reported that subjects carrying TT and 
CT genotypes had remarkably higher levels of CD44 protein 
than those carrying CC genotype in breast cancer, nasopha-
ryngeal carcinoma, and acute myeloid leukemia. 28,31,33 
To date, a number of case-control studies have been 
conducted to evaluate the role of CD44 gene rs13347 poly-
morphism in predisposition to several human cancers. 28,29,32-35 
Nevertheless, the results from different articles remain contro-
versial. To clarify the association between CD44 gene rs13347 
polymorphism and risk of cancer, we performed this meta-
analysis by integrating data from eligible published studies. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
search strategy </p>

<p>Relevant reports were retrieved by searching the electronic 
databases: PubMed, Web of Science, and China National 
Knowledge Infrastructure (CNKI; from inception to 
December 20, 2015), using the following keywords: 
("CD44") and ("tumor" or "cancer" or "carcinoma" or 
"neoplasm" or "malignancy") and ("polymorphism" or 
"polymorphisms" or "SNP" or "variant" or "variation"). The </p>

<p>search was filtered to English-language journals in PubMed. 
Besides, we also performed a manual search among the 
references of the relevant publications and related articles. 
The studies with overlapping data by the same investigators 
or based on the same population were checked prudently, 
and the most recent articles covering the largest numbers of 
cases and controls would be included. </p>

<p>inclusion and exclusion criteria </p>

<p>The eligible studies in this meta-analysis were required to 
strictly follow the predetermined criteria: 1) use a case-
control study design, 2) evaluate the association between 
CD44 rs13347 CT polymorphism and risk of cancer, and 
3) report an estimation of odds ratio (OR) and 95% confi-
dence interval (CI), or sufficient data to allow calculation of 
these two statistics. The main exclusion criteria were studies 
1) that did not use a case-control design (eg, case reports, 
letters, animal studies, reviews, and editorials), 2) that are 
duplicate of previous publications, 3) that involve inherited 
cancers, 4) with sample size of cases or controls 100, and 
5) in which genotype distribution of controls is not in agree-
ment with the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium. </p>

<p>Data extraction </p>

<p>All the eligible studies were reviewed by two authors inde-
pendently to extract useful data. The following information 
were collected: the name of the first author, the year of 
publication, the ethnicity of study population, the country of 
origin, sample size of cases and controls, source of controls 
(hospital based or population based), genotyping method, 
and genotype distributions of cases and controls. The dis-
agreements in this step were solved by rechecking the original 
data to reach a consensus. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium was estimated by the goodness-
of-fit test based on the chi-square test in the control group 
of each study. 36 Pooled analysis was conducted to estimate 
the strength of the association between CD44 rs13347 CT 
polymorphism and cancer risk, using an OR with a cor-
responding 95% CI. The pooled ORs were calculated by 
comparisons with a codominant model (CT vs CC and TT 
vs CC), a dominant model (TT + CT vs CC), and a reces-
sive model (TT vs CC + CT). The values of the pooled ORs 
were tested by the Z-test. 37 Stratified analyses were further 
performed based on country (People's Republic of China 
or India), specific cancer types (nasopharyngeal cancer, 
gallbladder cancer, or breast cancer), source of controls </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3495 </p>

<p>cD44 rs13347 cT polymorphism and cancer risk </p>

<p>(hospital based or population based), and genotyping method 
(TaqMan or matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization 
time-of-flight). Heterogeneity among the included studies 
was evaluated by the chi-square-based Q-test. 38 Pooled ORs 
were calculated using a fixed (Mantel-Haenszel method 39 ) 
or a random (DerSimonian-Laird method 40 ) effective model, 
according to the absence (P0.10 and I 2 50%) or presence 
(P0.10 or I 2 50%) of heterogeneity. Sensitivity analyses 
were performed by omitting one study each time to evaluate 
the stability of the results. The potential publication bias of 
the included studies was assessed by Begg's funnel plots 
graphically and Egger's test quantitatively. 41 
All the statistical calculations were carried out with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata/ 
SE</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 12.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StataCorp LP</rs>, College Station, 
TX, USA), using two-sided P-values, and P0.05 was con-
sidered to be significant. </p>

<p>Results 
literature search and characteristics of 
eligible studies </p>

<p>A total of 890 potential relevant records were retrieved 
through the search strategy described previously. Eight 
hundred and seventy records were excluded after title or </p>

<p>abstract scanning. After full-text reviewing, eight studies 
were excluded. Finally, 12 studies were eligible for pooled 
analysis. The flow process of detailed literature search and 
study selection is shown in Figure 1. 
There were 12 case-control studies included in this meta-
analysis, 28,29,31-35,42-46 involving a total of 6,982 cases and 
7,430 controls. All the studies were conducted on an Asian 
population. Among them, nine originated from the People's 
Republic of China and the other three from India. There was 
no study conducted on Caucasians or Africans. Cancer types 
included bladder cancer, non-small-cell lung cancer, gallbladder 
cancer, colorectal cancer, nasopharyngeal cancer, hepatocel-
lular carcinoma, oral cancer, breast cancer, and acute myeloid 
leukemia. The distribution of genotypes in all the control groups 
was in agreement with Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium. The 
characteristics of each eligible study are listed in Table 1. </p>

<p>Quantitative synthesis </p>

<p>The pooled results of the present meta-analysis are shown in 
Table 2 and Figure 2. There was an association between CD44 
gene rs13347 polymorphism and risk of cancer in the overall 
analyses. Significantly elevated cancer risk was revealed in 
the codominant genetic model (CT vs CC: OR =1.35, 95% </p>































<p>Figure 1 Flow diagram of the study identification process. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3496 </p>

<p>shi et al </p>

<p>CI =1.12-1.62 and TT vs CC: OR =1.99, 95% CI =1.52-2.60), 
dominant model (TT + CT vs CC: OR =1.41, 95% CI =1.16-1.71), 
and recessive model (TT vs CC + CT: OR =1.74, 95% 
CI =1.41-2.14). In the subgroup analyses stratified by country, 
there was evidence in Chinese population for an association 
between this SNP and cancer risk (CT vs CC: OR =1.42, 95% 
CI =1.16-1.75; TT vs CC: OR =2.13, 95% CI =1.58-2.86; 
TT + CT vs CC: OR =1.50, 95% CI =1.21-1.87; and TT vs 
CC + CT: OR =1.80, 95% CI =1.43-2.26). According to the 
source of control, both population based and hospital based 
subgroups were linked to cancer risk. For specific cancer types, 
increased risk among studies of nasopharyngeal cancer and 
breast cancer was observed in several genetic models. </p>

<p>Test for heterogeneity and sensitivity 
analysis </p>

<p>There was significant heterogeneity in the overall compari-
sons under all the genetic models (CT vs CC: P0.001 and 
I 2 =82.4% for heterogeneity, TT vs CC: P0.001 and I 2 =67.7% 
for heterogeneity, TT + CT vs CC: P0.001 and I 2 =85.8% for 
heterogeneity, and TT vs CC + CT: P=0.031 and I 2 =48.3% 
for heterogeneity; Table 2). The source of heterogeneity was 
investigated by covariates, such as country, cancer type, source 
of control, and genotype method. According to subgroup </p>

<p>analyses, country and cancer type might be the source of 
heterogeneity. To explore the main origin of heterogeneity, 
a meta-regression analysis was performed in the comparison 
TT vs CC, which indicated that cancer type contributed to 
the most proportion in heterogeneity. Moreover, two studies 
on nasopharyngeal cancer 33,42 were under suspicion. After 
omitting these two studies, the pooled OR was not altered 
(TT vs CC: OR =1.74, 95% CI =1.39-2.16), whereas the 
heterogeneity remarkably decreased (TT vs CC: P=0.110 
and I 2 =34.7% for heterogeneity). 
Sensitivity analysis was performed, and the pooled 
ORs were not influenced qualitatively in all the genetic 
models by removing any single study, which indicated that 
the pooled results of this meta-analysis were statistically 
stable (Figure 3). </p>

<p>Publication bias </p>

<p>The potential publication bias of the eligible studies was 
assessed by Begg's funnel plots graphically and Egger's test sta-
tistically. The shapes of funnel plots in all the genetic models did 
not indicate any evidence of an obvious asymmetry (Figure 4). 
Meanwhile, Egger's test revealed that there was no publica-
tion bias either (CT vs CC: P=0.139, TT vs CC: P=0.755, 
TT + CT vs CC: P=0.186, and TT vs CC + CT: P=0.975). </p>

<p>Table 1 characteristics of eligible studies in the meta-analysis </p>

<p>ID Reference Year Country 
Source of 
control </p>

<p>Cancer type 
Genotyping 
method </p>

<p>Sample size 
case/control </p>

<p>Genotype (case/control) 
HWE </p>

<p>CC 
CT 
TT </p>

<p>1 
Weng 
et al 44 </p>

<p>2015 People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>hB 
Bladder 
TaqMan 
275/275 
138/143 
111/117 26/15 
0.153 </p>

<p>2 
liu 
et al 32 </p>

<p>2015 People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>PB 
nsclc 
TaqMan 
234/468 
179/337 
51/121 4/10 
0.823 </p>

<p>3 
Yadav 
et al 46 </p>

<p>2016 india 
PB 
gallbladder 
TaqMan 
610/250 
378/162 
201/80 31/8 
0.620 </p>

<p>4 
Wu 
et al 45 </p>

<p>2015 People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>hB 
colorectal 
MalDi-TOF 946/989 
416/578 
441/348 89/63 
0.279 </p>

<p>5 
lou 
et al 42 </p>

<p>2014 People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>hB 
nasopharyngeal TaqMan 
272/489 
104/288 
126/174 42/27 
0.915 </p>

<p>6 
chou 
et al 34 </p>

<p>2014 People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>hB 
hepatocellular TaqMan 
203/561 
110/295 
72/223 21/43 
0.924 </p>

<p>7 
chou 
et al 35 </p>

<p>2014 People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>hB 
Oral 
TaqMan 
599/561 
287/295 
262/223 50/43 
0.924 </p>

<p>8 
sharma 
et al 43 </p>

<p>2014 india 
na 
gallbladder 
TaqMan 
405/200 
293/154 
104/42 8/4 
0.572 </p>

<p>9 
Wu 
et al 31 </p>

<p>2015 People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>PB 
aMl 
MalDi-TOF 421/461 
163/254 
196/171 62/36 
0.340 </p>

<p>10 Tulsyan 
et al 29 </p>

<p>2013 india 
hB 
Breast 
TaqMan 
258/241 
191/178 
60/57 
7/6 
0.577 </p>

<p>11 Xiao 
et al 33 </p>

<p>2013 People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>PB 
nasopharyngeal MalDi-TOF 906/943 
386/606 
418/297 102/40 0.637 </p>

<p>12 Jiang 
et al 28 </p>

<p>2013 People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>PB 
Breast 
MalDi-TOF 1,853/1,992 
812/1,146 850/727 190/119 0.795 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: PB, population based; hB, hospital based; na, not available; hWe, hardy-Weinberg equilibrium; aMl, acute myeloid leukemia; nsclc, non-small-cell lung 
cancer; MALDI-TOF, matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3497 </p>

<p>cD44 rs13347 cT polymorphism and cancer risk </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Cancer is a group of heterogeneous diseases that result from 
genetic and environmental factors, as well as their interac-
tions. According to CSC theory, CSCs can drive cancer 
initiation, progression, and metastasis. 3 As an important 
CSC surface maker in variant tumors, CD44 is reportedly 
a risk factor and poor prognostic molecular marker in vari-
ous cancers. 47-50 CD44 plays a crucial role in the invasion 
and migration of cancer cells. In addition, overexpression 
of CD44 in primary tumors has been revealed to be associ-
ated with early metastasis in several human cancers. 20,29,51 
CD44 gene rs13347 CT polymorphism is a common 
genetic variation in the 3′-UTR. It has been proved that the 
expression of CD44 was modulated by mRNAs, and rs13347 
CT polymorphism could alter has-mir-509-3p-mediated 
CD44 gene expression activity. Recently, a number of 
studies have been carried out to evaluate the association 
between this SNP and risk of cancer; however, the results 
were conflicting. The possible reason may be that the effects 
of CD44 on the development of different cancer types are 
not the same. 
To our knowledge, the present meta-analysis, includ-
ing 6,982 cases and 7,430 controls from 12 case-control 
studies, is the first comprehensive study to assess the 
association between CD44 gene rs13347 polymorphism 
and risk of cancer. We found an association between CD44 
gene rs13347 polymorphism and human cancer risk by 
pooling all the data from eligible studies. The results were 
robust because the pooled ORs did not alter statistically in 
sensitivity analyses. Stratified analyses suggested that this 
association was mainly in a Chinese population. According 
to specific cancer types, this polymorphism was linked to 
elevated risk of gallbladder cancer, nasopharyngeal cancer, 
and breast cancer, the significance of which was limited 
because there were only two studies for each cancer type. 
Since there was significant heterogeneity by the Q-test 
in all the genetic models, a meta-regression analysis was 
performed to explore the origin of heterogeneity. As a 
result, different cancer types were considered to be the 
main source of interstudy variance, especially two studies 
on nasopharyngeal cancer. By removing these two studies, 
the heterogeneity significantly decreased but pooled ORs 
were not altered. However, this kind of heterogeneity was 
hard to eliminate in the present meta-analysis, because there 
were only one or two studies for one specific cancer type. 
Moreover, pooling data from different cancer types might 
affect the significance of this meta-analysis because differ-
ent cancer types might give rise to different host responses, </p>

<p>Table 2 Pooled analysis of association between cD44 rs13347 cT polymorphism and cancer risk in asians </p>

<p>Study </p>

<p>N 
CT vs CC </p>

<p>TT vs CC </p>

<p>TT + 
CT vs CC </p>

<p>TT vs CC + </p>

<p>CT </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>I 2 </p>

<p>(%) 
OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>I 2 </p>

<p>(%) 
OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>I 2 </p>

<p>(%) 
OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>I 2 </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>Overall </p>

<p>12 
1.35 (1.12-1.62) </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>82.4 
1.99 (1.52-2.60) </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>67.7 
1.41 (1.16-1.71) </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>85.8 
1.74 (1.41-2.14) </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>48.3 </p>

<p>country 
People's republic of china </p>

<p>9 
1.42 (1.16-1.75) </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>84.7 
2.13 (1.58-2.86) </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>73.9 
1.50 (1.21-1.87) </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>87.6 
1.80 (1.43-2.26) </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>59.0 </p>

<p>india </p>

<p>3 
1.11 (0.89-1.37) </p>

<p>0.619 </p>

<p>0.0 
1.36 (0.77-2.39) </p>

<p>0.753 </p>

<p>0.0 
1.13 (0.92-1.39) </p>

<p>0.672 </p>

<p>0.0 
1.32 (0.75-2.33) </p>

<p>0.744 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>cancer type 
nasopharyngeal </p>

<p>2 
2.15 (1.82-2.54) </p>

<p>0.613 </p>

<p>0.0 
4.10 (2.99-5.61) </p>

<p>0.827 </p>

<p>0.0 
2.39 (2.04-2.81) </p>

<p>0.802 </p>

<p>0.0 
2.95 (2.17-3.99) </p>

<p>0.787 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>gallbladder </p>

<p>2 
1.16 (0.90-1.49) </p>

<p>0.473 </p>

<p>0.0 
1.46 (0.75-2.84) </p>

<p>0.637 </p>

<p>0.0 
1.18 (0.93-1.51) </p>

<p>0.625 </p>

<p>0.0 
1.41 (0.73-2.73) </p>

<p>0.502 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>Breast </p>

<p>2 
1.32 (0.80-2.19) </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>81.5 
2.17 (1.71-2.76) </p>

<p>0.210 </p>

<p>36.5 
1.36 (0.79-2.33) </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>85.3 
1.76 (1.39-2.22) </p>

<p>0.387 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>source of control 
PB </p>

<p>5 
1.45 (1.08-1.95) </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>86.9 
2.39 (1.65-3.47) </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>65.2 
1.53 (1.12-2.09) </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>89.6 
1.99 (1.67-2.37) </p>

<p>0.142 </p>

<p>41.9 </p>

<p>hB </p>

<p>6 
1.26 (0.96-1.65) </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>80.8 
1.79 (1.20-2.67) </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>68.5 
1.33 (1.00-1.76) </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>83.5 
1.60 (1.17-2.19) </p>

<p>0.061 </p>

<p>52.7 </p>

<p>genotyping method 
TaqMan </p>

<p>8 
1.12 (0.91-1.37) </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>64.8 
1.56 (1.03-2.35) </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>61.2 
1.16 (0.93-1.46) </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>73.9 
1.50 (1.08-2.09) </p>

<p>0.089 </p>

<p>43.4 </p>

<p>MalDi-TOF </p>

<p>4 
1.80 (1.64-1.97) </p>

<p>0.115 </p>

<p>49.4 
2.58 (1.93-3.45) </p>

<p>0.039 </p>

<p>64.0 
1.94 (1.66-2.27) </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>66.3 
1.96 (1.53-2.51) </p>

<p>0.091 </p>

<p>53.6 </p>

<p>Notes: n, number of studies; P </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>, P-value </p>

<p>of Q-test 
for heterogeneity. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: PB, population based; HB, hospital based; MALDI-TOF, matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight; OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3498 </p>

<p>shi et al </p>

























































































<p>Figure 2 Forest plot of the association between CD44 gene rs13347 cT polymorphism and risk of cancer in the overall analysis (TT vs cc). 
Note: Weights are from random effects analysis. 
Abbreviations: OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval. </p>







<p>@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ </p>





























<p>Figure 3 sensitivity analysis of the association between CD44 gene rs13347 cT polymorphism and risk of cancer in the overall analysis (TT vs cc). 
Abbreviation: CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3499 </p>

<p>cD44 rs13347 cT polymorphism and cancer risk </p>

<p>and the interactions between different environmental factors 
and host might also influence the susceptibility to different 
cancer types. 
Some limitations of the present meta-analysis should 
be pointed out. First, the pooled results were calculated 
based on unadjusted estimates, which limited us to per-
form a more precise assessment on adjusted estimates by 
several important factors such as sex, age, lifestyle, etc. 
Thus, lack of the baseline information restricted further 
evaluation of the potential interactions, because malig-
nancy predisposition might be influenced by gene-gene 
and gene-environment interactions. Second, most of the 
included studies just focused on the relationship between 
CD44 gene rs13347 polymorphism and cancer risk, which 
made it hard to assess the effects of CD44 gene haplotypes 
composed of different CD44 gene SNPs on carcinogenesis. 
There was evidence that CD44 gene rs187115 AG and 
rs115214213 TC polymorphisms were associated with 
cancer risk. 35,42,44 Thus, the status of other CD44 gene 
polymorphisms might cover up the effects of rs13347 TC 
polymorphism, which could lead to controversial results 
among different studies. 
Despite these limitations, advantages in this meta-analysis 
should also be acknowledged. First, the statistical power was 
remarkably increased since we pooled a substantial number 
of cases and controls. Second, the quality of all the eligible 
studies met the inclusion criteria completely and strictly. 
Third, there was no publication bias observed through Begg's 
funnel plots and Egger's test, which indicated that the pooled 
outcomes should be unbiased. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The results of the present meta-analysis were robust and 
credible. The relationship between CD44 gene rs13347 
polymorphism and cancer risk was assessed, and this SNP 
was associated with elevated cancer risk in Asians. To draw 
a more conclusive result, further studies should be conducted 
with more detailed information on individuals and environ-
mental factors, concerning the effects of different haplotypes 
and other SNPs and enrolling properly identified cases and 
well-matched controls, especially in other ethnicities includ-
ing Africans and Caucasians, to validate the role of CD44 
gene rs13347 CT polymorphism in carcinogenesis. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>This work was granted by National Natural Science 
Foundation of China (grant no 91229104). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>

<p>References </p>























<p>Figure 4 Begg's funnel plot of publication bias test in the overall analysis (TT vs cc); 
each point represents a single study for the indicated association. 
Abbreviations: logOr, natural logarithm of the Or; se of logOr, standard error 
of the logOr; Or, odds ratio. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open 
access journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>