<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4956186" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:32+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Micrometer-scale acoustic waves are highly useful for refined optomechanical and acoustofluidic manipulation, 
where these fields are spatially localized along the transducer aperture but not along the acoustic propagation 
direction. In the case of acoustic tweezers, such a conventional acoustic standing wave results in particle and cell 
patterning across the entire width of a microfluidic channel, preventing selective trapping. We demonstrate the use 
of nanosecond-scale pulsed surface acoustic waves (SAWs) with a pulse period that is less than the time of flight 
between opposing transducers to generate localized time-averaged patterning regions while using conventional 
electrode structures. These nodal positions can be readily and arbitrarily positioned in two dimensions and within 
the patterning region itself through the imposition of pulse delays, frequency modulation, and phase shifts. This 
straightforward concept adds new spatial dimensions to which acoustic fields can be localized in SAW applications 
in a manner analogous to optical tweezers, including spatially selective acoustic tweezers and optical waveguides. </p>

<p>Surface acoustic waves (SAWs) are an efficient tool for microscale 
manipulation in diverse applications, including optical scattering, 
waveguides and computing (1-5), telecommunications (6), sensing 
(7), and microscale manipulation (8, 9). A standing SAW field results 
in time-averaged nodal and antinodal positions on the substrate and 
fluids into which it couples and is readily generated on planar piezo-
electric substrates by an AC signal applied to opposing sets of inter-
digital transducers (IDTs). However, this standing wave develops 
across the entire inter-IDT space, preventing localized manipulation 
in a manner analogous to optical tweezers. The term "acoustic tweezers" 
has been applied to microfluidic systems using SAW (10, 11), but the 
imposition of this field results in cell and particle patterning in the 
entirety of a microfluidic channel, although phased array bulk acoustic 
wave (BAW) transducers are capable of generating nonuniform acous-
tic patterns using several piezoelectric elements (12, 13). Here, we dem-
onstrate the straightforward application of nanosecond-scale SAW 
pulses in a sub-time-of-flight (sub-TOF) regime, where the locations 
and dimensions of the localized standing wave regions in the substrate 
are determined by the TOF and pulse length of a SAW, and where only 
two sets of transducers are required. In recent work, Fourier synthesis 
has been used to shape the time-averaged substrate waveforms (14), 
although pulsed SAW has not been previously used to generate spatial-
ly localized standing wave patterning. The time-averaged field resulting 
from intersecting SAW pulses yields discrete standing wave locations 
in a coupled fluid independent of channel dimensions. This method-
ology uses conventionally fabricated IDTs on a piezoelectric/optical 
material-lithium niobate (LN, LiNbO 3 )-that is commonly used in 
optical waveguide and microfluidic applications. In contrast to SAW 
generated by pulsed lasers, typically used for material characterization 
(15), this IDT-based method presents a more conventional, easily used 
route for the generation of nanosecond-scale traveling SAW pulses with-
out the need for optical equipment and permits the generation of high-
amplitude substrate displacements for microfluidic manipulation. </p>

<p>SAW is profoundly useful for microscale manipulation because the 
length scale of the waves themselves is on the order of micrometers. 
Typical SAW wavelengths, 1 to 300 mm, are generated using frequencies 
between 10 and 1000 MHz (16, 17). SAW is driven by conducting IDT 
structures on a piezoelectric substrate, where (at resonance) the mechan-
ical displacements emanating from one set of finger pairs are reinforced 
by those from neighboring ones, with the resulting displacements max-
imized when f = c s /l SAW , where c s is the sound speed in the substrate. 
Compared to BAW transducers (18-20), SAW is especially suitable for 
microfluidic applications because it is generated on a planar surface, is 
readily integrated with channel structures, and generates an acoustic 
field only in desired locations (17). These advantages have been used 
in SAW applications, including cell patterning (21), interfacial manip-
ulation (22, 23), free surface translation (24, 25), atomization (26, 27), 
thin-film formation (27, 28), particle and cell separation (29-32), fluid 
pumping (33), localized heating (34, 35), and selective sorting (31, 36). 
This work represents a substantial evolution of acoustic micro-
fluidics, where standing wave-induced acoustic forces can be confined 
not only across the width of the transducers as in conventional SAW but 
also along the direction of propagation. This method takes advantage of 
the small, microsecond-order TOF over which a SAW will propagate 
from one set of transducers to the opposing set, with TOF = d/c s , where 
d is the characteristic distance over which a wave travels. When these 
IDTs are actuated by a pulse width with time t p less than this character-
istic TOF, the width of the overlapping region (w) where the traveling 
waves emanating from each set of IDTs intersect is a subset of the total 
distance between them, with </p>

<p>tp </p>

<p>TOF ∼ w 
d . This principle is shown in the 
conceptual diagram in Fig. 1A and the sketch in Fig. 1B. Figure 1C shows 
an example of a completed device, where a polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS) 
channel is used to contain a fluid volume with suspended particles. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Our analytical models and numerical simulations of this TOF re-
gime closely mirror one another. Figure 2 shows both the simulated 
and modeled traveling waveform (Fig. 2A) and the resulting time-
averaged displacements (Fig. 2B) from the intersection of two of these </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Pillar of Engineering Product Development, Singapore University of Technology and 
Design, Singapore 487372, Singapore. 2 Department of Mechanical and Aerospace En-
gineering, Monash University, Melbourne, Victoria 3800, Australia. 
*Corresponding author. Email: adrian.neild@monash.edu (A.N.); aiye@sutd.edu.sg (Y.A.) </p>

<p>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Collins et al. Sci. Adv. 2016; 2 : e1600089 
13 July 2016 
1 of 8 </p>

<p>counterpropagating waves. The waveform shape of the propagating wave 
x x (x) can be analytically modeled by calculating the contributions from each 
finger pair in the set of IDTs over the length of the SAW pulse, given by </p>

<p>x x x 
ð Þ ¼ x 0 </p>

<p>x À 
w t 
2 
for x ¼ À 
w t 
2 
À 
w x 
2 
; À 
w t 
2 
þ 
w x 
2 </p>

<p>h 
i </p>

<p>1 
f o r x ¼ À 
w t 
2 
þ 
w x 
2 
; 
w t 
2 
À 
w x 
2 </p>

<p>h 
i </p>

<p>1 À x þ 
w t 
2 
À 
w x 
2 </p>



<p>for x ¼ 
w t 
2 
À 
w x 
2 
; 
w t 
2 
þ 
w x 
2 </p>

<p>h 
i </p>

<p>8 
&gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; </p>

<p>&gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; : </p>

<p> 
&gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; = </p>

<p>&gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; ; </p>

<p>ð1Þ </p>

<p>where x 0 is the initial SAW displacement, w t = c s t p is the applied pulse 
width, w x = Nl SAW (both in units of length), and N is the number of 
finger pairs. The first and third terms account for the ramping regions 
on either end of the pulse, resulting from the incomplete resonance 
from a subset of the total number of finger pairs. The total pulse width 
(w) is equal to w t + w x (for w t &gt; w x ) due to the contributions from all 
IDT finger pairs, where w is at least as large as w x . For w t &lt; w x , the maxi-
mum displacement amplitude is given by x x 
max = w t /w x , shown by the 
green lines in Fig. 2A. The modeled time-averaged waveform shape is 
computed from the autocorrelation (self-intersection) of the transient 
modeled waveform, with x x </p>

<p>avg </p>

<p>(x) = x x (x)*x x (x), and compares favorably 
to the simulated time-averaged displacement (Fig. 2B). Figure 2C dem-
onstrates the sequence of stages in the development of a spatially lo-
calized intersecting SAW in full 3D simulation of a SAW emanating 
from opposing sets of IDTs on a piezoelectric LN substrate, including 
the initial generation, propagation, intersection, and continuous prop-
agation after intersection. The maximum displacement amplitude at 
complete intersection for 5T, 10T, and 20T pulses are shown in Fig. 2D; 
note the graded amplitude decay at either end of this region, a feature 
that arises from the partial reinforcement of displacements for the ini-
tial few periods when more than one finger pair is used in a set of IDTs. 
It follows that the maximum amplitude is only reached for a given 
pulse when the pulse time exceeds the time required for a SAW to tra-
verse the width of the IDTs. Figure 2A shows these effects, where, for a 
six-finger pair device, there are six local maxima before reaching max-
imum amplitude at the leading (and trailing) edges except for the case 
in which a pulse time of 5T is applied, in which case the steady-state 
maximum is never reached. That Eq. 1 is a good match for the sim-
ulation results in Fig. 2A, which emerge directly from applying an AC 
boundary condition to our electrodes on a simulated LN substrate, is a 
good verification of this model. 
Figure 3A demonstrates the existence of discrete patterning loca-
tions in an experimental setup, actuated by opposing sets of six-
finger pair IDTs (7-mm aperture) with a time-averaged applied power 
of 0.35 W (with a duty cycle of 0.1 and a period 10 times the pulse 
width). Figure 3A shows larger localized patterning regions for both 
longer pulse times and larger numbers of finger pairs, as expected 
from Eq. 1. Continuous SAW results in acoustic nodal positions 
throughout the width of the microfluidic channel (37-39), whereas 
pulsed nanosecond-scale actuation only results in particle patterning in 
the locations where the intersecting waves overlap (the localized standing 
wave region), leaving particles outside of this region largely unaffected. 
Graphs associated with each experimental image show predicted 
minimum displacement locations, corresponding to areas where 2-mm 
particles collect (MagSphere), where these analytical models incorporate 
the attenuation of the acoustic beam as it travels along the substrate/ 
fluid interface and display the time-averaged displacement relative to 
that before exposure to the fluid. The dimensions of the predicted region 
compare favorably for smaller pulse lengths, although the observed 
patterning region is somewhat smaller than the full extent of the re-
gion for which a partial standing wave exists at longer pulse lengths. 
This illustrates the effect of acoustic attenuation arising from a water-
loaded SAW: With an attenuation length of ~500 mm, the magnitude 
of each propagating 40-mm-wavelength SAW is reduced to 13% of 
the original one at the channel center and is less than 5% by the end 
of the predicted patterning region (at approximately y = 550 mm in 
the case of a 300-ns pulse). The dotted lines in Fig. 3A represent the con-
dition where the local average displacement minima are less than 0.2x 0 , </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Principle of TOF localized standing waves. (A) The opposing sets 
of IDTs are both actuated with a pulse length shorter than the TOF between 
them, resulting in traveling waves (TW) that constructively/destructively 
interfere where these two waves meet. (B) Over multiple pulses, the time-
averaged effect of this localized standing wave (SW) yields a number of 
fixed nodal positions in the substrate, resulting in particle patterning in 
discrete locations where these pulsed waves intersect. (C) A PDMS channel 
is used to contain particles suspended in a fluid, which is replaced here with 
blue dye to better visualize the channel extents. </p>

<p>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Collins et al. Sci. Adv. 2016; 2 : e1600089 </p>

<p>
which yields a consistent and reasonable match for the dimensions in 
which strong patterning occurs for the given applied power and channel 
dimensions used here. Although local minima exist outside this region, 
these prove insufficient for the purpose of producing strong and repro-
ducible patterning phenomena, owing to the relative weakness of the 
local acoustic field. These patterning regions are demonstrated in a con-
tinuous flow in movie S4. 
An important consideration in acoustic microfluidics is the influ-
ence of the traveling waves themselves on particle behavior. This is not 
a significant factor in this instance due to the size of the particles rela-
tive to that of the fluid wavelength. The reflections in the vicinity of the 
particle become increasingly directional and of larger magnitude with 
increasing particle dimensions, where the force scaling changes from 
an F~R 6 /F~R 3 relationship [depending on the viscosity of the surround-
ing medium (40)], where F is the acoustic force and R is the particle 
radius, to a more complex relationship as the particle size approaches 
the acoustic wavelength (41, 42). Although the size of the viscous </p>

<p>boundary layer varies with fluid density and viscosity (43), which in turn 
influences the particle size at which the traveling wave forces become 
significant for the purposes of particle translation, this transition has 
been experimentally determined to occur in the vicinity of k ≈ 1.3 to 
1.4 for polystyrene particles in water (44-46). Here, k = pd/l f , where d is 
the particle diameter and l f is the wavelength in the fluid, yielding a 
maximum diameter (d max ) of 6 and 12 mm for the 40-and 80-mm wave-
lengths (l SAW ), respectively, used in this work. The traveling wave force 
does not significantly modify particle positions below such dimensions, 
and particles will be translated toward the channel center at dimensions 
above these. For the 2-and 3-mm particles used in this work, these equate 
to k values of 0.4 and 0.6, respectively, which accordingly failed to demon-
strate directional particle motions arising from the traveling wave force. 
The development of the localized field is analyzed in Fig. 3B, which 
shows the mean fluorescence intensity of the particles as they are being 
patterned across the simulated region shown in Fig. 3C (see movie S1). 
The primary aggregation of particles occurs in the localized standing </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Simulated and modeled response to SAW pulses on the order of 100 ns. (A) The simulated shapes of the transient traveling SAW pulses closely 
match the model in Eq. 1 for actuation by six-finger pair IDTs, with pulse time periods (tp) of 5T, 10T, and 20T, where T = l SAW /c s , which is the time it takes 
for a traveling SAW to traverse one SAW wavelength (here simulated with l SAW = 40 mm). (B) The simulated time-averaged substrate displacements 
closely match the modeled displacement curves for these same finger pair and T values, here showing the convolution x x (x)*x x (x) from Eq. 1. (C) The 
time-averaged nodal positions result from the combination of transient pulses, here showing an intersection sequence using a full 3D simulation 
during SAW generation (t = 2T), SAW propagation (t = 6T), intersection (t = 12T), and continuing propagation (t = 18T). See movie S2 for time-dependent 
simulations. (D) The time-averaged minimum displacement locations in (B) correspond to the nodal positions presented here, which show the instan-
taneous maximum displacements at transient wave intersection. Scale bars, 100 mm. </p>

<p>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Collins et al. Sci. Adv. 2016; 2 : e1600089 </p>

<p>
Fig. 3. Experimental particle patterning actuated by continuous and sub-TOF regime pulsed SAW. (A) In contrast to conventionally applied 
acoustic fields, applying pulse lengths with t p &lt; TOF results in the time-averaged standing wave locations only where the two incident waves overlap, 
here with t p = 50, 100, 200, and 300 ns (approximately 5T, 10T, 20T, and 30T), driven by 40-mm six-finger pair transducers at 96 MHz, visualized with 2-mm 
particles in a 2-mm-wide channel after 5 s of pulsed excitation (time-averaged applied power = 0.35 W). These patterns correspond to the predicted 
patterning locations at time-averaged minimum displacement conditions, especially for smaller time-averaged minima (dotted lines correspond to 
conditions where |x| minima are less than 0.2). Continuous patterning is demonstrated in movie S4. (B) During pattern development in a 1-mm-wide 
channel, 3-mm primary particle patterns result from the combination of the intersecting 100-ns pulsed traveling waves (between dotted lines). a.u., ar-
bitrary units. (C) Mean intensity along the x direction is assayed in the region (for t = 10 s) from movie S1. (D) The appearance of secondary near-field 
patterning [dash-dot boxes in (B)] results from diffraction in the vicinity of the acoustic impedance discontinuity at the channel wall boundary shown here. 
Scale bars, 200 mm. </p>

<p>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Collins et al. Sci. Adv. 2016; 2 : e1600089 </p>

<p>
wave region, whereas secondary near-field patterning is observed to de-
velop over longer time scales (dash-dot lines in Fig. 3B). We find that 
the emergence of this effect can be explained by the generation of time-
averaged pressure amplitude patterns in the vicinity of the acoustic 
property discontinuity at the PDMS/fluid boundary (see Fig. 3D). This 
2D numerical simulation, a video of which is shown in movie S2, models 
the solid/fluid acoustic interactions in a pulsed field. The spherical prop-
agation of acoustic displacements in the vicinity of this interface accord-
ing to the Huygens-Fresnel principle results in near-field diffraction and 
time-averaged regions of lower acoustic energy toward which particles 
will preferentially migrate (43), although the magnitude of these varia-
tions is less pronounced than that in the central patterning region, which 
has larger acoustic pressure gradients. This model (pictured at t = 41T) 
simulates the interaction of a SAW emanating from a six-finger pair set 
of IDTs actuated with a pulse lasting 10T (~100 ns) along a piezoelectric 
LN substrate and the effects of the PDMS domain at the channel periph-
ery. The top surface of the fluid domain, the channel roof, is imposed 
with a PDMS impedance boundary condition, which is sufficient because 
the PDMS domain is much larger than the channel height, whereas the 
50-mm PDMS walls are explicitly simulated. The effect of a physical 
PDMS boundary over the fluid domain is minimal, resulting in a small 
amount of reflection due to the fractional acoustic impedance difference 
between water and PDMS and thus a degree of acoustic patterning in 
the z direction, although the magnitude of this effect is secondary to that 
of primary patterning. 
Patterning in the TOF regime is not limited to the generation of 
unitary localized standing wave fields. Figure 4 shows the generation 
of three separate time-averaged patterning regions by using a pulse 
period that is less than the amount of time the entire traveling wave 
pulse takes to traverse the width of the channel (here, a 75-ns pulse 
with a 200-ns period was used, which is less than the 254-ns TOF + 
75-ns pulse length of the 1-mm channel). The instantaneous, analyt-
ically modeled, and interfering waves, as well as their time-averaged 
displacements, are shown in movie S3. The modeled minimum dis-
placements in Fig. 4C correlate with the observed particle aggregation 
locations, measured from the mean fluorescence intensity in Fig. 4 
(A and B). Here, the channel is displaced (90 mm vertically) from the 
midpoint between opposing transducers to demonstrate the indepen-
dence of the patterning region from the channel dimensions; because 
the standing wave locations are substrate-bound, the patterning loca-
tions can be arbitrarily determined with respect to the channel. 
In the cases examined so far, the patterning regions have been 
symmetrical about the midpoint between the opposing sets of IDTs: 
This is where counterpropagating waves intersect when each set of 
transducers is actuated simultaneously. However, the TOF-induced 
patterning regions can also be applied at arbitrary locations along the 
propagation direction by independently controlling the times at which 
each set of transducers is actuated. By applying a triggered delay to the 
100-ns, 48-MHz pulse to one of two sets of 80-mm six-finger pair IDTs 
in a 3-mm-wide channel in Fig. 5A, we demonstrate that the pattern-
ing locations can be generated independently of the channel position 
on the SAW device. Here, the traveling SAW propagating along the x 
direction from the upper set of IDTs generated hundreds of nano-
seconds before and after that from the lower set, resulting in highly ac-
curate patterning region shifts. Patterning localization can similarly be 
extended into the y direction by using a SAW device architecture where 
the acoustic wavelength varies across the IDT aperture. Figure 1C shows 
such a device, where l SAW varies between 40 and 80 mm, corresponding </p>

<p>to resonant frequency conditions between 48 and 96 MHz (larger wave-
lengths correspond to lower frequencies). Applying 100-ns pulses at 
frequencies in this range results in localized patterning only where a 
SAW is produced, as shown in Fig. 5B, where the patterning region is 
shifted laterally along the device aperture for 55-, 65-, 75-, and 85-MHz 
frequencies (corresponding to wavelengths of 71, 60, 52, and 46 mm). 
However, the localization along the y direction (~1 mm) is not as dis-
crete as that along the propagation direction (~100 mm) in this imple-
mentation, given the large device aperture (10 mm) and the small 
number of finger pairs (6) that result in a wide transmission bandwidth 
(47); the localization in this direction could be improved with larger num-
bers of finger pairs and/or larger wavelength gradients (using smaller 
apertures and/or wider frequency ranges), although as a trade-off, the 
width of the x direction patterning region would increase in line with 
Eq. 1 for an increasing number of finger pairs. 
Although the extent of the patterning regions is on the order of 
100 mm at a minimum for wavelengths on the order of tens of micro-
meters and thus by itself limits the application of these patterning re-
gions for manipulation of individual particles or cells in concentrated 
solutions, this can be somewhat circumvented via the fine-grained con-
trol that is achievable within the patterning region itself, where phase 
shifts can result in translated time-averaged nodal positions (48, 49). 
Figure 5C demonstrates the shift in nodal positions with the applica-
tion of a phase-shifted, 48-MHz, 100-ns pulse in a device with a l SAW 
of 80 mm. Applying a phase delay of Dφ = 180° results in an inversion of 
the nodal/antinodal positions compared to Dφ = 0°, for example, and 
the gradual shift between these two cases results in total translation/ 
nodal position differences that are smaller than the acoustic wavelength. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The effect of attenuation at the LN/water interface, which results from 
the transfer of energy from the solid substrate to the coupled fluid, 
with an attenuation length (over which the initial displacement ampli-
tude decays to 1/e of its initial value) of 12.8 l SAW is yet to be discussed 
(31, 50). For the case tested, this means that each incoming 40-mm wave 
will have attenuated to approximately 38% of its initial value at the 
center of a 1-mm channel but approximately 14% at the center of a 
2-mm channel. Not surprisingly, this attenuation has little effect on 
the expected nodal positions where particles aggregate for a smaller 
channel width but has considerable effect for larger channels. Note 
that patterning is demonstrated across the width of the 1-mm channel 
in Fig. 4A, whereas longer pulse lengths result in smaller-than-expected 
patterning regions for the wider channel in Fig. 3A. However, even a 
standing wave at a fractional value of its initial intensity should still 
eventually lead to particle migration, albeit at a lower rate. However, 
amplitude attenuation in the fluid itself presents a potentially more 
potent effect on particle translation, where the propagation of a high-
frequency acoustic wave through a dispersive medium, such as water, 
generates a body force in the direction of propagation (50). This effect 
can be reduced by minimizing the body force gradients that give rise to 
acoustic streaming, at their strongest at the edge of the SAW beam, and 
reducing the channel height where appropriate (28, 51). Acoustic gra-
dients can be ameliorated for patterning applications, as it has been in 
this work, by using channel widths smaller than the IDT aperture (3.2 
and 3.6 mm for the 40-mm device in Fig. 3B). This is not necessarily 
required, where streaming is similarly not a noticeable concern even </p>

<p>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Collins et al. Sci. Adv. 2016; 2 : e1600089 </p>

<p>
Fig. 4. Generation of multiple discrete patterning regions. (A) The application of a 75-ns pulse with a 200-ns period, which is less than the minimum 
time it takes for a complete wave to pass across the 1-mm channel (the channel's 254-ns TOF plus the 75-ns pulse period), generates symmetric standing 
wave regions as visualized with patterned 3-mm particles. (B and C) The measured mean intensity across the width of the channel (B), corresponding to the 
predicted locations of minimum time-averaged displacement (C). Scale bar, 200 mm. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. 2D patterning control. (A) The patterning region in the direction of propagation (the x direction) can be arbitrarily determined through the 
imposition of a time-delayed pulse, where the pulse traveling from the top of the device is delayed by the value shown. (B) The patterning regions in 
the y direction (in dashed boxes) can similarly be modified using a SAW device whose wavelength changes along the y direction (here between 40 and 
80 mm; device shown in Fig. 1C). All other results are for nonslanted IDT designs. (C) The patterning of nodal positions within the patterning region can 
also be shifted by imposing a phase shift Dφ to one of the opposing sets of transducers. All particles are 2 mm. Scale bars, 200 mm. </p>

<p>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Collins et al. Sci. Adv. 2016; 2 : e1600089 </p>

<p>
with the use of slanted-finger IDTs, as is the case in Fig. 5C, where the 
SAW beam width is smaller than that of the channel. This is partly due 
to the graded drop-off in displacement magnitude with this transducer 
type (52). 
Given the wide range of activities that are already accomplished 
with SAW, the use of nanosecond-scale pulses to generate locality 
along the direction of propagation and across the width of the trans-
ducers represents a conceptually simple but significant evolution in 
the dexterity that is possible using microscale acoustic fields. Reducing 
the width of the region over which a standing wave is formed permits 
localized trapping in a manner more analogous to optical tweezers, leav-
ing surrounding regions unaffected. Phase shifts between opposing 
transducers combined with the imposition of an additional orthogonal 
SAW allow for selective and fully 2D particle and cell manipulation. 
Moreover, given the wide use of SAW for optical and mechanical ma-
nipulation, the ability to further localize acoustic fields presents a new 
avenue for the fine-tuned generation of highly local SAW displacements. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Numerical simulation 
The numerical simulation was performed using <rs type="software">COMSOL</rs> v5.0 (see 
Fig. 2, C and D). A time-dependent transient 2D model was used to sim-
ulate waveforms by applying an AC signal to regions representing the 
IDT finger pairs on a piezoelectric substrate. The stiffness, coupling co-
efficient, and electrical permittivity matrices were rotated to correspond 
to the 128° y-cut x-propagating LN crystal used experimentally. The max-
imum mesh size dimension was l SAW /10. </p>

<p>SAW devices 
IDTs are composed of a conductive 200-nm Al or Au layer on a 7-nm 
Cr adhesion layer and patterned on a piezoelectric LN substrate using 
the lift-off process after evaporative metal deposition. The width of 
each metal strip is equal to l SAW /4, 10 mm for l SAW = 40 mm, 20 mm for 
l SAW = 80 mm, and linearly graded between 10 and 20 mm for the 40-to 
80-mm slanted-finger IDT device. A finished device was produced by 
bonding a PDMS microchannel to the substrate after exposure to an 
air plasma (Harrick Plasma PDC-32G; 1000 mtorr, 18 W). This bonded 
microchannel (1 mm wide and 20 mm high, 2 mm wide and 40 mm high, 
or 3 mm wide and 60 mm high) incorporated an air channel over the 
IDTs and a small, 50-mm-thick PDMS wall between the air-and fluid-
filled sections to minimize attenuation before the fluid channel. These 
devices were actuated with a signal generator (AnaPico APGEN3000HC 
and Tektronix AFG3102C) and an amplifier (Ophir 5084 and Empower 
1100) on a custom-printed, 3D-printed mount with spring-loaded probes 
making contact with the electrode pads and visualized with an inverted 
microscope through the transparent substrate. Phase shifts and time 
delays at 48 MHz (for the results in Fig. 5, A and C) were readily achieved 
in the two-channel Tektronix unit, which uses a common reference os-
cillator. A blank piece of LN was used to eliminate birefringence through 
this optically polarizing material. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS </p>

<p>Supplementary material for this article is available at http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/ 
content/full/2/7/e1600089/DC1 
movie S1. Development of localized acoustic patterning region. </p>

<p>movie S2. Numerical simulation of pulsed SAW, including 2D and 3D models of the 
piezoelectric substrate and a model of the acoustofluidic interaction. 
movie S3. Analytical model of sub-TOF regime SAW. 
movie S4. Generation of time-averaged localized patterning regions using 50-, 100-, 200-, and 
300-ns pulses. </p>



<p>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Collins et al. Sci. Adv. 2016; 2 : e1600089 </p>



<p>
Acknowledgments 
Funding: We acknowledge the support received from the Singapore University of Technology 
and Design (SUTD)-Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) International Design Center 
(IDG11300101) and SUTD Start-up Research Grant (SREP13053) awarded to Y.A. Author con-
tributions: D.J.C. developed the concept, performed the experiments, created analytical 
models, and wrote the manuscript. Z.M. performed preliminary experiments. C.D. performed 
numerical modeling. J.W.N. helped with the device fabrication. A.N. and Y.A. helped shape 
experiments and modeling, analyzed the data, interpreted the results, and revised the manuscript. 
All authors read and approved the completed manuscript. Competing interests: The authors 
declare that they have no competing interests. Data and materials availability: All data needed 
to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper and/or the Supplementary 
Materials. Additional data related to this paper may be requested from the authors. </p>

<p>Submitted 19 January 2016 
Accepted 14 June 2016 
Published 13 July 2016 
10.1126/sciadv.1600089 </p>

<p>Citation: D. J. Collins, C. Devendran, Z. Ma, J. W. Ng, A. Neild, Y. Ai, Acoustic tweezers via sub-
time-of-flight regime surface acoustic waves. Sci. Adv. 2, e1600089 (2016). </p>

<p>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Collins et al. Sci. Adv. 2016; 2 : e1600089 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>