<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4602909" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Sorafenib has been recommended as first-or second-line </p>

<p>treatment for metastatic renal cell carcinoma (mRCC) by several 
guidelines. The objective of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of 
sorafenib monotherapy in Chinese patients with mRCC and determine 
the prognostic clinicopathologic factors associated with survival in 
these patients. 
This is a single-arm retrospective study conducted in 2 tertiary 
medical centers; 140 mRCC patients were enrolled between January 
2007 and June 2014. Sorafenib was administered at a dose of 400 mg 
twice daily, and continued until disease progression, at which point the 
dose was increased to 600 or 800 mg twice daily, or the onset of an 
intolerable adverse drug event (ADE) that required dose reduction or 
temporary suspension of treatment. 
The primary endpoint was overall survival (OS), and the secondary 
endpoints included progression-free survival (PFS), objective response 
rate (ORR), disease control rate (DCR), and safety. 
The median follow-up time was 32 months. The median OS and PFS 
were 24 months (range, 3-88 months) and 16 months (range, 0-88 
months), respectively. Patients with clear cell carcinoma had a greater 
OS (P ¼ 0.001) whereas sarcomatoid differentiation (P ¼ 0.045) and 
disease progression (P ¼ 0.010) negatively impacted OS; time from 
kidney surgery or biopsy to initiation of sorafenib treatment was associ-
ated with PFS (P ¼ 0.027). Efficacy analysis revealed that 3 (2.1%) 
patients achieved complete responses, 28 (20.0%) patients experienced 
partial responses, 88 (62.9%) patients had stable disease, and 21 (15.0%) 
patients developed progressive disease. Moreover, the ORR was 22.1%, 
and the DCR was 85.0%. Most ADEs were classified as grades 1 or 2 with 
only 14 (10.0%) patients experiencing a severe ADE (grade 3). 
Sorafenib monotherapy can achieve promising OS and PFS for 
Chinese patients with mRCC, especially in those with clear cell carci-
noma, with manageable adverse events. </p>

<p>(Medicine 94(34):e1361) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ADE = adverse drug event, CI = confidence 
interval, CR = complete response, DCR = disease control rate, HR 
= hazard ratio, IL-2 = interleukin-2, mRCC = metastatic renal cell 
carcinoma, ORR = objective response rate, OS = overall survival, 
PD = progressive disease, PFS = progression-free survival, PR = 
partial response, RCC = renal cell carcinoma, RECIST = Response 
Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors, SD = stable disease. </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>enal cell carcinoma (RCC) accounts for nearly 3% of all 
adult malignancies, and its incidence is increasing in 
China. 
1,2 The poor prognosis of these patients is due in part 
to its late detection; approximately one-third of patients are 
diagnosed with metastatic RCC (mRCC) at first presentation. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>In addition, although surgery is the most effective treatment, 
approximately 20% to 40% of patients experience distant 
metastasis or local recurrence after primary nephrectomy 
4 with 
a 5-year survival rate of &lt;10%. 
5 Furthermore, mRCC is highly 
resistant to chemotherapy and radiotherapy; therefore, immu-
notherapy had been the main treatment option for these patients. 
However, low tumor response and high toxicities limit this 
treatment option to only a select few patients. 
6,7 Surgical 
resection of mRCC at multiple sites also improves long-term 
survival, but it is not always technically feasible. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>The advent of targeted therapy that inhibit specific signal-
ing pathways important for tumor growth and metastasis, 
including the vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) sig-
naling pathway, 
9 has changed the treatment paradigms of 
mRCC. Since the use of the first VEGF tyrosine kinase inhibi-
tor, sunitinib, the treatment algorithm of mRCC has dramatic-
ally changed. Sorafenib (Nexavar, Bayer Pharmaceuticals, 
West Haven, Conn and Onyx Pharmaceuticals, Emeryville, 
Calif) is another tyrosine kinase inhibitor, targeting the VEGF 
receptor, platelet-derived growth factor receptor, Raf kinase 1, 
KIT, and Fms-like tyrosine kinase 3. 
10-12 Previous studies have 
shown that sorafenib improves progression-free survival (PFS) 
in mRCC by 2.7 months 
11 as well as overall survival (OS) 
13 ; 
therefore, it has been recommended by several guidelines, 
including those of the National Comprehensive Cancer Net-
work, as a second-line treatment option for those who failed 
prior immunotherapy. 
14 However, its efficacy in Chinese 
patients is not fully known. Therefore, this retrospective study 
analyzed the characteristics and outcomes of 140 patients with 
mRCC who were treated with sorafenib at 2 large-volume 
centers in China to evaluate the efficacy and safety of sorafenib 
and identify any prognostic factors related to the efficacy 
of sorafenib. </p>

<p>Editor: Ming-hui Wu. 
Received: March 16, 2015; revised: June 28, 2015; accepted: July 20, 2015. 
From the Department of Urology (XY, XL, CZ, LH, DF, YS, LZ), Peking 
University First Hospital, Institute of Urology, National Urological Cancer 
Center, Peking University; and Department of Urology (GG, XZ), State 
Key Laboratory of Kidney Diseases, Chinese People's Liberation Army 
General Hospital, Beijing, China. 
Correspondence: Liqun Zhou, Department of Urology, Peking University 
First Hospital, Institute of Urology, National Urological Cancer Center, 
Peking University, Beijing 100034, China (e-mail: zhouliqunmail@ 
sina.com). 
Supplemental Digital Content is available for this article. 
YX, GG, and LX equally contributed to this study. 
The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose. 
Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. 
This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License 4.0, where it is 
permissible to download, share and reproduce the work in any medium, 
provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or 
used commercially. 
ISSN: 0025-7974 
DOI: 10.1097/MD.0000000000001361 </p>

<p>Medicine </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>OBSERVATIONAL STUDY </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 34, August 2015 </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 1 </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>Between January 2007 and June 2014, 191 mRCC patients 
treated with sorafenib were included in this retrospective study. 
All the patients were enrolled from 2 large-volume Chinese 
centers: the Peking University First Hospital and the Chinese 
People's Liberation Army General Hospital. Among the 191 
patients, 28 were considered being at high risk for recurrence 
(ie, !T3, !G3, N1-2, larger tumor diameter, with tumor 
necrosis, higher grade of the cell nucleus) and were treated 
with sorafenib as adjuvant therapy. The remaining 163 patients 
had mRCC, which was confirmed by histopathological 
methods. Of these 163 mRCC cases, 16 were lost at follow-
up and 7 were excluded because of incomplete data. Thus, 140 
patients were analyzed. This study was approved by the Ethics 
Committees of Peking University First Hospital and Chinese 
People's Liberation Army General Hospital, and informed 
consent was obtained from each participant. </p>

<p>Treatment and Follow-Up </p>

<p>Sorafenib monotherapy was administered as first-line 
therapy for 106 (75.7%) patients, second-line therapy after 
immunotherapy for 23(16.4%) patients, and second-line therapy 
following sunitinib for 11 (79%) patients. Sorafenib was admi-
nistered at a dose of 400 mg twice daily over 1 cycle, which 
consisted of 4 weeks, and continued until disease progression, 
defined as new metastases outbreak or a 20% increase in size 
over baseline, or the onset of an intolerable adverse drug event 
(ADE). The dosage was increased to 600 mg twice daily or 
800 mg twice daily in patients with disease progression and 
manageable toxicity as previously described. 
15 Dose reduction 
or temporary suspension was allowed according to the ADE 
grade and individual tolerability. The median of duration of 
sorafenib treatment was 20 months (range, 3-88 months), 
and the median follow-up time was 32 months (range, 3-88 
months). 
The primary endpoint was OS, and secondary endpoints 
included PFS, objective response rate (ORR), disease control 
rate (DCR), and safety. ORR was calculated as complete 
response (CR) þ partial response (PR), and the DCR was 
determined by CR þ PR þ stable disease (SD). CR, PR, SD, 
and progressive disease (PD) were defined according to the 
Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 
criteria. 
16 We assessed the tumor response by computed tom-
ography or magnetic resonance intensity once every other cycle. 
Efficacy was defined according to the RECIST criteria 
16 ; a 30% 
reduction in tumor size was deemed effective. The PFS was 
calculated from the time of sorafenib initiation to the occurrence 
of PD. ADEs were examined and graded every cycle according 
to the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria 
for Adverse Events version 3.0. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Patients' clinical and pathological characteristics were 
represented as mean with range (minimum to maximum) for 
continuous variables and n (%) for categorical variables. To 
evaluate the association of OS and PFS with patients' clinical 
and pathological characteristics, patients' clinical and patho-
logical characteristic data were summarized as n (%) for given 
OS and PFS values. Univariate and multivariate Cox-regression 
model analyses were applied, and the results were shown as 
hazard ratios (HRs) with corresponding 95% confidence </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Patients' Clinical and Pathological Characteristics </p>

<p>Characteristics 
(N ¼ 140) </p>

<p>Age, y 
57.34 (17-79) 
Sex 
Male 
101 (72.1%) 
Female 
39 (27.9%) 
Time from kidney surgery or 
biopsy to sorafenib, mo </p>

<p>12 (1-144) </p>

<p>Prior nephrectomy 
Yes 
112 (80.0%) 
No 
28 (20.0%) 
Prior immunotherapy 
None 
117 (83.6%) 
IFN 
13 (9.3%) 
IL-2 
3 (2.1%) 
IFN þ IL-2 
6 (4.3%) 
IFN þ IL-2 þ 5-FU 
1 (0.7%) 
Prior systemic therapy 
Treatment naïve 
106 (75.7%) 
Second line after immunotherapy 
23 (16.4%) 
Second line after sunitinib 
11 (7.9%) 
Pathology 
Clear cell 
125 (89.3%) 
Papillary 
12 (8.6%) 
Undifferentiated 
1 (0.7%) 
Chromophobe 
2 (1.4%) 
Sarcomatoid differentiation 
Yes 
9 (6.4%) 
No 
131 (93.6%) 
Dosage change 
None 
95 (67.9%) 
Escalation 
40 (28.6%) 
Reduction or discontinuation 
3 (2.1%) 
Temporary discontinuation 
followed by escalation with 
disease progression </p>

<p>2 (1.4%) </p>

<p>Multiorgans 
&gt;2 organs 
101 (72.1%) 
Single organ 
39 (27.9%) 
Metastasis 
Only lung involved 
58 (41.4%) 
Others 
82 (58.6%) 
Metastatic sites 
Lung 
86 (61.4%) 
Bone 
44 (31.4%) 
Liver 
12 (8.6%) 
Brain 
1 (0.7%) 
Adrenal gland 
14 (10.0%) 
Lymph node 
26 (18.6%) 
Others 
4 (2.9%) 
Progressive disease 
Yes 
79 (56.4%) 
No 
61 (43.6%) 
Survival status 
Alive 
59 (42.1%) 
Dead 
81 (57.9%) </p>

<p>5-FU ¼ 5-fluorouracil, IFN ¼ interferon, IL-2 ¼ interleukin-2. Data 
were represented as mean with range (minimum to maximum) for 
continuous variables and n (%) for categorical ones. </p>

<p>Yu et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 34, August 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>intervals (95% CIs). Variables with significance level of P &lt; 0.1 
in the univariate Cox-regression model were selected for multi-
variate analysis. Kaplan-Meier survival curves with a log-rank 
test were performed to identify the OS and PFS among the 
clinical and pathological characteristics. 
18 All statistical assess-
ments were 2-tailed, and P values &lt;0.05 were considered 
significant. All statistical analyses were carried out with <rs id="software-0" type="software">IBM 
SPSS</rs> statistical software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 22</rs> for Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corp.</rs>., 
New York, NY). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Patients' Clinical and Pathological 
Characteristics </p>

<p>A total of 140 mRCC patients (101 men and 39 women) 
with a mean age of 57.3 years (range, 17-79 years) receiving 
sorafenib monotherapy (median dosage of 400 mg twice daily) 
were enrolled in this study. All the clinical and pathological 
characteristics of patients are shown in Table 1. The median 
time from kidney surgery or biopsy to initiation of sorafenib 
therapy was 12 months (range, 1-144 months); 112 (80%) 
patients underwent nephrectomy and 23 (16.4%) patients 
received prior immunotherapy, including combinations of </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Kaplan-Meier curve of overall survival (OS) for 140 
Chinese metastatic renal cell carcinoma patients receiving sora-
fenib. 95% CI, 95% confidence intervals of median OS times. ''þ'' 
indicates censored cases. The median OS times were derived at 
24 months with 95% CI ¼ 17.9-30.1 months. </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Association of Overall Survival With Patients' Clinical and Pathological Characteristics (N ¼ 140) </p>

<p>Survival Status 
Univariate 
Multivariate </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Dead 
Alive 
HR (95% CI) 
P Value 
HR (95% CI) 
P Value </p>

<p>Total patients 
81 
59 
Sex 
Male 
58 (57.4%) 
43 (42.6%) 
1.213 (0.745, 1.976) 
0.438 
-
Female 
23 (59.0%) 
16 (41.0%) 
Reference 
Time from kidney surgery or biopsy 
to initiation of sorafenib 
12 (1-89) 
10 (1-144) 
0.994 (0.984, 1.003) 
0.205 
-</p>

<p>Prior nephrectomy 
Yes 
63 (56.2%) 
49 (43.8%) 
0.818 (0.484, 1.382) 
0.452 
-
No 
18 (64.3%) 
10 (35.7%) 
Reference 
Prior systemic therapy 
Treatment naïve 
59 (55.7%) 
47 (44.3%) 
Reference 
Second line after immunotherapy 
15 (65.2%) 
8 (34.8%) 
1.064 (0.603, 1.878) 
0.830 
-
Second line after sunitinib 
7 (63.6%) 
4 (36.4%) 
1.133 (0.517, 2.486) 
0.755 
-
Pathology 
Clear cell 
67 (53.6%) 
58 (46.4%) 
0.386 (0.216, 0.692) 
0.001 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>0.329 (0.182, 0.596) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>Others </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>14 (93.3%) 
1 (6.7%) 
Reference 
Reference 
Sarcomatoid differentiation 
Yes 
7 (77.8%) 
2 (22.2%) 
2.123 (0.973, 4.629) 
0.058 
2.232 (1.019, 4.889) 
0.045 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>No 
74 (56.5%) 
57 (43.5%) 
Reference 
Multiorgans 
&gt;2 organs 
52 (51.5%) 
49 (48.5%) 
1.245 (0.790, 1.963) 
0.345 
-
Single organs 
29 (74.4%) 
10 (25.6%) 
Reference 
Metastasis 
Only lung involved 
31 (53.4%) 
27 (46.6%) 
1.052 (0.670, 1.652) 
0.825 
-
Others 
50 (61.0%) 
32 (39.0%) 
Reference 
Progressive disease 
Yes 
56 (70.9%) 
23 (29.1%) 
1.685 (1.051, 2.701) 
0.030 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>1.879 (1.164, 3.033) 
0.010 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>No 
25 (41.0%) 
36 (59.0%) 
Reference 
Having at least once ADEs with grade 3 or 4 
Yes 
11 (78.6%) 
3 (21.4%) 
1.040 (0.547, 1.977) 
0.904 
-
No 
70 (55.6%) 
56 (44.4%) 
Reference </p>

<p>Clinical and pathological characteristic data were presented as n (%) for a given survival status. ADEs ¼ adverse drug-related events. Univariate and 
multivariate Cox-regression model analyses were applied, and results were shown as hazard ratio (HR) with corresponding 95% confidence intervals 
(95% CIs). Variables with significance level &lt;0.1 in univariate Cox-regression model were selected for multivariate Cox-regression model analysis. 
a Others indicated pathological results in papillary, undifferentiated, and chromophobe subtypes. 
Ã P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 34, August 2015 
Sorafenib for Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 3 </p>

<p>interferon, interleukin-2 (IL-2), and 5-fluorouracil (Table 1). 
Histologic analysis revealed that 125 (89.3%) patients had clear 
cell carcinoma and 9 (6.4%) patients had sarcomatoid differ-
entiation. In addition, 101 (72.1%) patients had metastasis to &gt;2 
organs, including the lung, bone, lymph node, adrenal gland, 
liver, and brain, whereas 58 (41.4%) patients had metastatic 
involvement in the lung alone (Table 1). During the treatment 
period, 40 (28.6) patients had their sorafenib dosage increased; 
3 (2.1%) patients had their dosage reduced or their treatment 
discontinued altogether, and 2 (1.4%) patients had a mixture of 
dosage escalation, reduction, and treatment discontinuation 
(Table 1). Moreover, 79 (56.4%) patients experienced PD at 
least once during the follow-up period using the RECIST 
criteria, and 59 (42.1%) patients were alive at the last fol-
low-up (Table 1). </p>

<p>Clinicopathological Factors Associated With OS 
and Disease Progression in mRCC Patients 
Treated With Sorafenib </p>

<p>The median OS was 24 months (range, 3-88 months; 
Figure 1). The association between OS and the patients' clinical 
and pathological characteristics were presented in Table 2. 
Univariate and multivariate analyses suggest that patients with 
clear cell carcinoma have a better OS than those with other types 
of mRCC (ie, papillary, undifferentiated, chromophobe) 
(HR ¼ 0.33, 95% CI ¼ 0.182-0.596, P &lt; 0.001). In addition, 
sarcomatoid differentiation (HR ¼ 2.23, 95% CI ¼ 1.02-4.89, 
P ¼ 0.045) and disease progression (HR ¼ 1.88, 95% 
CI ¼ 1.16-3.03, P ¼ 0.010) were also associated with higher 
risk for death during the follow-up period (Table 2). These 
characteristics continued to be associated with OS by multi-
variate analysis that included all relevant variables (Supple-
mentary Table S1, http://links.lww.com/MD/A382). Kaplan-
Meier survival curves with a log-rank analysis of OS by 
pathological results, sarcomatoid differentiation, and disease 
progression are shown in Figure 2. 
As shown in Table 3, the clinicopathologic variables 
associated with PFS were next analyzed. Progressive status 
(PS) included patients with PD as well as those that had died at 
last follow-up. A total of 104 (74.2%) patients had PS, including 
patients who experienced PD (the aforementioned 79 patients) 
along with patients without PD that had died of mRCC, and 
Kaplan-Meier curves of the PFS among the 140 patients were 
illustrated in Figure 3. Univariate Cox-regression analysis 
revealed that time from kidney surgery or biopsy to initiation 
of sorafenib treatment was associated with PFS (HR ¼ 0.990, 
95% CI ¼ 0.981-0.999, P ¼ 0.028; Table 3). This variable 
continued to be associated with PFS in a multivariate analysis 
that included all relevant variables (P &lt; 0.027; Table S2, http:// 
links.lww.com/MD/A382). </p>

<p>Efficacy Evaluation </p>

<p>All of the 140 patients enrolled received sorafenib for at least 
2 cycles and were included in the evaluation of treatment efficacy. 
The ORR was 22.1%. In addition, 3 (2.1%) patients achieved CRs, 
28 (20.0%) patients reached PRs, 88 (62.9%) patients experienced 
SD for &gt;2 cycles, and 21 (15.0%) patients developed PD. The 
ORR included patients with CR and PR. Moreover, the DCR, 
including patients with CR, PR, or SD, was 85.0%. </p>

<p>Analysis of Sorafenib Safety in mRCC Patients </p>

<p>As shown in Table 4, the 6 most common ADEs after 
sorafenib initiation were diarrhea (48.6% of patients), hand-</p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Kaplan-Meier curves of overall survival (OS) times for 
140 Chinese metastatic renal cell carcinoma patients receiving 
sorafenib by pathological result. The log-rank test was performed 
to identify the significance of OS by specific characteristics, includ-
ing (A) clear cell carcinoma, (B) sarcomatoid differentiation, and 
(C) progressive disease. 95% CI, 95% confidence intervals of 
median OS times. ''þ'' indicates censored cases. </p>

<p>Yu et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 34, August 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>foot syndrome (45.0% of patients), fatigue (30.0% of patients), 
hypertension (25.7% of patients), alopecia (17.9% of patients), 
and rash (17.9% of patients). Other ADEs included anemia, 
leukocytopenia, elevated alanine transaminase, elevated uric 
acid, hoarseness, and arthralgia. Most ADEs were mild to 
moderate (grades 1 or 2; range, 1.4%-45%). However, some 
ADEs were severe (grades 3; range, 0%-6.4%; Table 4). In this 
study, a total of 40 patients received dose escalation (higher 
dose group); however, no correlation between higher sorafenib 
doses and severe ADEs were observed in this study cohort (data 
not shown). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Sorafenib improves PFS 
11 and OS 
13 in mRCC patients and 
is currently recommended as a second-line treatment option for 
those who failed prior immunotherapy. 
14 However, few studies 
have analyzed its efficacy in Chinese patients. 
19,20 In this 
retrospective study, the outcomes were analyzed in 140 Chinese 
mRCC patients treated with sorafenib with a median follow-up 
time of 32 months. The median OS was 24 months, and PFS was 
16 months. Moreover, the ORR was 22.1%, and the DCR was </p>

<p>85.0% with manageable ADEs. The presence of clear cell 
carcinoma and the absence of sarcomatoid differentiation or 
disease progression might be associated with increased OS 
whereas the time from kidney surgery or biopsy to initiation 
of sorafenib treatment may be associated with PFS. 
In the Treatment Approaches in Renal Cancer Global 
Evaluation Trial study, a phase III clinical trial involving 
903 RCC patients treated in centers in Europe and in the United 
States, sorafenib significantly improved the PFS (5.5 vs 2.7 
months) 
11 and OS (17.8 vs 14.3 months) 
13 of patients refractory 
to prior immunotherapy as compared to the placebo group. 
Moreover, the DCR in the sorafenib and placebo groups was 
62% and 37%, respectively. However, studies in Chinese 
patients suggest that the efficacy of sorafenib may be even 
greater. 
2 In a study that included 98 mRCC patients, Zhang 
et al 
19 reported a PFS of 15 months, but the median follow-up 
time was relatively short, and the impact on OS was not 
evaluated. In another small study of 30 Chinese patients with 
advanced RCC, Yang et al 
20 reported that the OS and PFS was 
16 and 14 months, respectively. Consistent with the previous 
studies evaluating the efficacy of sorafenib in Chinese mRCC 
patients, 
2 the median PFS in the present study was 16 months </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Association of Progression-Free Survival With Patients' Clinical and Pathological Characteristics (N ¼ 140) </p>

<p>Progressive Situation 
Univariate </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Non-PS 
PS 
HR (95% CI) 
P Value </p>

<p>Total patients 
36 
104 
Sex 
Male 
28 (27.7%) 
73 (72.3%) 
1.043 (0.680, 1.601) 
0.846 
Female 
8 (20.5%) 
31 (79.5%) 
Reference 
Time from kidney surgery or biopsy to initiation of sorafenib 
17.41 (1-144) 
17.31 (1-89) 
0.990 (0.981, 0.999) 
0.028 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>Prior nephrectomy 
Yes 
30 (26.8%) 
82 (73.2%) 
0.969 (0.604, 1.555) 
0.896 
No 
6 (21.4%) 
22 (78.6%) 
Reference 
Prior systemic therapy 
Treatment naïve 
27 (25.5%) 
79 (74.5%) 
Reference 
Second line after immunotherapy 
7 (30.4%) 
16 (69.6%) 
0.788 (0.459, 1.353) 
0.387 
Second line after sunitinib 
2 (18.2%) 
9 (81.8%) 
1.421 (0.708, 2.851) 
0.323 
Pathology 
Clear cell 
35 (28.0%) 
90 (72.0%) 
0.656 (0.371, 1.158) 
0.146 
Others </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1 (6.7%) 
14 (93.3%) 
Reference 
Sarcomatoid differentiation 
Yes 
2 (22.2%) 
7 (77.8%) 
1.451 (0.671, 3.138) 
0.344 
No 
34 (26.0%) 
97 (74.0%) 
Reference 
Multiorgans 
&gt;2 organs 
7 (17.9%) 
32 (82.1%) 
1.075 (0.707, 1.635) 
0.735 
Single organs 
29 (28.7%) 
72 (71.3%) 
Reference 
Metastasis 
Only lung involved 
17 (29.3%) 
41 (70.7%) 
0.969 (0.653, 1.437) 
0.876 
Others 
19 (23.2%) 
63 (76.8%) 
Reference 
Having at least once ADEs with grade 3 or 4 
Yes 
1 (7.1%) 
13 (92.9%) 
1.031 (0.573, 1.854) 
0.919 
No 
35 (27.8%) 
91 (72.2%) 
Reference </p>

<p>ADEs ¼ adverse drug-related events, PS ¼ progressive status, which included patients either with progressive disease or those that were dead at last 
follow-up. Clinical and pathological characteristic data were presented as n (%) for a given PS situation. Univariate Cox-regression model analysis 
was applied, and results were shown as hazard ratio (HR) with corresponding 95% confidence intervals (95% CIs). Multivarariate analysis was not 
performed because of only one variable with significance level &lt;0.1 in univariate Cox-regression model. 
a Others indicated pathological results in papillary, undifferentiated, and chromophobe subtypes. 
Ã P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 34, August 2015 
Sorafenib for Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 5 </p>

<p>with ORR and DCR of 22.1% and 85.0%, respectively, which is 
relatively higher than previous studies in Western popu-
lations. 
11,13 It is also higher than a study of 82 Chinese patients 
with advanced kidney cancer treated with gemcitabine and IL-2, 
oxaliplatin and capecitabine, or sorafenib alone with PFS rates 
of 9.1 (95% CI ¼ 7.9-10.3), 7.5 (95% CI ¼ 5.5-9.5), and 10.9 
(95% CI ¼ 10.5-11.3) months, respectively. 
21 The improved 
response to sorafenib in Chinese patients may be attributed to 
the inherent genetic differences between the ethnic groups, 
which may result in differences in drug pharmacokinetics 
and pharmacodynamics. This theory is supported by similar 
findings in Japanese 
22,23 and Korean 
24 patients with advanced 
RCC. However, as shown in a recently published systemic 
review, the median OS and PFS for sorafenib-treated mRCC 
patients in Western countries varies. 
25 For example, the TIVO 
trial 
26 reported a median OS of 29.3 months, which is similar to 
the OS in the present study (24 months). Alternatively, the 
greater proportion of patients receiving dose escalation in this </p>

<p>study may have contributed to better OS as dose escalation 
therapy may prove superior over therapy discontinuation in the 
case of disease progression. 
15,27,28 Therefore, further investi-
gations are needed to determine if there are truly significantly 
different prognoses for various ethnic groups as well as to 
investigate the effects of documented tumor marker differences 
and varying molecular characteristics in different ethnic groups 
in order to select the best candidates for different targeted drugs. 
In a small study that included 37 Chinese mRCC patients, 
Zhao et al 
29 found that the absence of symptoms, the absence of 
bone or pancreatic metastasis, and a relative dose intensity of 
targeting agents in the first month were all independently 
associated with OS. In the present study, 3 independent factors 
were identified that impacted the survival of mRCC patients 
treated with sorafenib. First, clear cell carcinoma appeared to 
offer a benefit to OS of 14 months, which was similar to 
previous studies in which nonclear cell histology was an adverse 
prognostic factor for predicting OS. 
30,31 In addition, we found 
that sarcomatoid differentiation and PD negatively impacted 
OS, and the time from kidney surgery or biopsy to initiation of 
sorafenib treatment may be associated with PFS. Although the 
association of tumor sarcomatoid differentiation with poor 
prognosis was consistent with the previous reports, 
32-34 this 
result should not be overinterpreted considering the small 
sample of patients with sarcomatoid differentiation (9 out of 
140 patients). Thus, further studies are required to confirm 
this association. 
In terms of ADEs related to sorafenib, the most commonly 
reported include hand-foot syndrome, rashes, allopecia, diar-
rhea, hypertension, and fatigue, 
35,36 which is consistent with 
those observed in the present study. However, the ADEs were 
manageable in that most were mild or moderate. Only 14 
(10.0%) patients experienced severe, 19 grade 3 ADEs. Several 
previous studies have explored the correlation between ADEs 
and efficacy of tyrosine kinase inhibitors and suggest that the 
incidence of ADEs (even high-grade ADEs) may indicate better 
outcome. 
37-39 DiFiore et al 
40 suggested that severe clinical 
toxicities or grades 3 and 4 ADEs may result in better prognosis, 
with a median OS benefit of 24 months as compared to those 
without grades 3 and 4 ADEs. In contrast, ADEs were not 
associated with a longer OS in the present study, which may be 
because of differences in the pharmacokinetic and pharmaco-
dynamic parameters between ethnic groups. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Kaplan-Meier curve of progressive-free survival (PFS) 
for 140 Chinese metastatic renal cell carcinoma patients treated 
with sorafenib. 95% CI, 95% confidence intervals of median PFS 
times. ''þ'' indicates censored cases. The median PFS times were 
derived at 16 months with 95% CI ¼ 13.7-18.3 months. </p>

<p>TABLE 4. Summary of the Adverse Drug-Related Events in Chinese mRCC Patients (N ¼ 140) </p>

<p>Adverse Drug-Related Events 
None 
Grade 1 
Grade 2 
Grade 3 
Grade 4 </p>

<p>Diarrhea 
72 (51.4%) 
43 (30.7%) 
20 (14.3%) 
5 (3.6%) 
0 (0%) 
Hand-foot syndrome 
77 (55.0%) 
29 (20.7%) 
25 (17.9%) 
9 (6.4%) 
0 (0%) 
Fatigue 
98 (70.0%) 
34 (24.3%) 
8 (5.7%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
Hypertension 
104 (74.3%) 
30 (21.4%) 
4 (2.9%) 
2 (1.4%) 
0 (0%) 
Alopecia 
115 (82.1%) 
23 (16.4%) 
2 (1.4%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
Rash 
115 (82.1%) 
20 (14.3%) 
2 (1.4%) 
3 (2.1%) 
0 (0%) 
Anemia 
136 (97.1%) 
3 (2.1%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
Leukocytopenia 
137 (97.9%) 
3 (2.1%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
Elevation of ALT 
133 (95.0%) 
5 (3.6%) 
2 (1.4%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
Elevation of uric acid 
136 (97.1%) 
4 (2.9%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
Hoarseness 
138 (98.6%) 
2 (1.4%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
Arthralgia 
136 (97.1%) 
3 (2.1%) 
1 (0.7%) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) </p>

<p>ALT ¼ alanine transaminase, mRCC ¼ metastatic renal cell carcinoma. Data were summarized as n (%) for a specific drug-related event. </p>

<p>Yu et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 34, August 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>The present study is limited by its retrospective nature. In 
addition, although the patients lost to last follow-up was &lt;10%, 
some ADEs may have been missed and some data were 
incomplete (eg, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group perform-
ance status, Karnofsky performance scale, hemoglobin, and 
calcium concentration). Moreover, we did not investigate the 
specific biomarkers related to clear cell carcinoma and OS. 
Despite these limitations, our study is the largest multicenter 
retrospective study of Chinese patients treated with sorafenib 
with the longest follow-up to date. Further studies are needed to 
elucidate the underlying mechanism and biomarkers associated 
with efficacy or survival. 
In summary, sorafenib monotherapy can achieve promis-
ing OS and PFS for Chinese patients with mRCC, especially for 
those with clear cell carcinoma, resulting in a satisfactory DCR 
and manageable ADEs. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank the entire staff of the 
Department of Urology, Peking University First Hospital and 
Chinese People's Liberation Army General Hospital, Beijing, 
China, for their assistance. </p>



<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 34, August 2015 
Sorafenib for Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 7 </p>



<p>Yu et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 34, August 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

</text></tei>