<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4050386" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The concurrence of tomato yellow leaf curl virus (TYLCV) with the spread of its vector Bemisia tabaci Q 
rather than B in China suggests a more mutualistic relationship between TYLCV and Q. Here, we 
investigated the hypothesis that viruliferous B and Q have different effects on plant defenses. We found the 
fecundity of nonviruliferous B, nonviruliferous Q, viruliferous Q and viruliferous B was 11.080, 12.060, 
10.760, and 11.220 respectively on plants previously attacked by the other biotype, however, on their 
respective noninfested control leaves fecundity was 12.000, 10.880, 9.760, and 8.020 respectively. Only 
viruliferous B had higher fecundity on viruliferous Q-infested plants than on control plants. The longevity of 
viruliferous B showed the same phenomenon. At 1 d infestion, the jasmonic acid content in leaves 
noninfested and in leaves infested with nonviruliferous B, nonviruliferous Q, viruliferous B and viruliferous 
Q was 407.000, 281.333, 301.333, 266.667 and 134.000 ng/g FW, respectively. The JA content was lowest in 
viruliferous Q-infested leaves. The proteinase inhibitor activity and expression of JA-related upstream gene 
LOX and downstream gene PI II showed the same trend. The substantial suppression of host defenses by Q 
carrying TYLCV probably enhances the spread of Q and TYLCV in China. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>bout 80% of plant viruses depend on insect vectors for their transmission </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>, and recent research showed 
that plant viruses, like other pathogens and parasites, can induce changes in their hosts or vectors that can 
enhance their transmission </p>

<p>3,4 </p>

<p>. The three-way interaction between virus, plant, and insect vector is com-
plex. Plant viruses can directly and indirectly (via the host plant) modify the growth and development of their 
vectors. At the same time, feeding by viruliferous vectors can affect plant defense responses, inverse, plant also 
affects viruliferous vectors 
5,6 . Both the plant virus and the vector may benefit from such changes from plants. 
The whitefly Bemisia tabaci (Gennadius) is a phloem-feeding pest that causes serious damage by its direct 
feeding and by its transmission of plant viruses </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>. B. tabaci is a species complex consisting of morphologically 
indistinguishable biotypes that differ in feeding behavior, endosymbiont communities, insecticide resistance, 
virus transmission, or other properties </p>

<p>8-12 </p>

<p>. B. tabaci B and Q are the two most invasive and harmful whiteflies; 
they have invaded nearly 60 countries and have caused massive agricultural losses during the past two decades </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>. 
Tomato yellow leaf curl virus (TYLCV) is a single-stranded DNA plant virus in the genus Begomovirus, family 
Geminiviridae. It is transmitted by B. tabaci in a persistent and circulative manner. TYLCV has recently become a 
serious threat to tomato production in many countries </p>

<p>14-16 </p>

<p>. In China, TYLCV was not detected until B. tabaci Q 
became established in 2005, even though B. tabaci B is an important vector of TYLCV and has been found in 
China since the mid-1990's </p>

<p>10,17 </p>

<p>. 
The concurrence of the spread of TYLCV with the invasion of B. tabaci Q rather than B suggests that the 
relationship between TYLCV and B. tabaci is more mutualistic for Q than B </p>

<p>6,10,12,18 </p>

<p>. Our recent research showed 
that TYLCV indirectly benefits B. tabaci Q 
6,18 but directly and indirectly harms B. tabaci B </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>. In this context, 
indirect benefit or harm is mediated by the host plant. 
Plant-mediated interactions between plant pathogens and herbivorous arthropods are potentially important 
determinants of the population dynamics of both the pathogens and the arthropods in managed and natural 
ecosystems </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>. Plant defenses including those involving jasmonic acid (JA) and salicylic acid (SA) play key regulatory 
roles in the interaction of insects and their vectored viruses </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>. Proteinase inhibitor (PI) and other defense-related 
proteins are also inducible during insect feeding </p>

<p>21,22 </p>

<p>, and their related gene expression such as PI II in resisting insect 
herbivores have been well demonstrated </p>

<p>23-25 </p>

<p>. Zhang et al. (2004) 
24 showed that the expression of PI II gene is caused </p>

<p>OPEN </p>

<p>SUBJECT AREAS: </p>

<p>ENTOMOLOGY </p>

<p>VIRUS-HOST INTERACTIONS </p>

<p>INVASIVE SPECIES </p>

<p>by JA as a result of injury. Another study demonstrated that LOX gene 
is also involved in wound-induced JA biosynthesis such as aphids-
infeston </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>. The prevailing view is that the SA pathway induces resist-
ance against biotrophic pathogens and some phloem feeders, whereas 
the JA pathway induces resistance against chewing herbivores, some 
phloem-feeding insects, and necrotrophic pathogens </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>. Few studies, 
however, have investigated the role of JA or SA when a plant is 
simultaneously inoculated with an insect vector and virus </p>

<p>5,27 </p>

<p>. Our 
latest study showed that SA content was always higher in leaves 
infested with viruliferous B than with viruliferous Q </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>. Furthermore, 
the relative gene expression associated with SA signaling was 
increased by the feeding of viruliferous B but not by the feeding of 
viruliferous Q </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>. Zhang et al. (2012) 
27 demonstrated that co-infection of 
the begomovirus tomato yellow leaf curl China virus (TYLCCNV) and 
its betasatellite can repress JA-regulated defenses of tobacco against 
invasive whiteflies and accelerate population increases of the insects. 
Our recent study also showed that the interactions between tomato 
plant, TYLCV, and B. tabaci Q can reduce JA-and PI-associated plant 
defense </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>. However, the comprehensive understanding of plant-
mediated interaction between viruliferous B and Q is still limited. 
Several studies investigated how damage by herbivore feeding 
affects subsequent herbivore feeding because feeding may alter plant 
defenses </p>

<p>29-31 </p>

<p>. Sarmento et al. (2011b) </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>, for example, showed that 
Tetranychus evansi had reduced performance on plants that were 
previously attacked by its congener Tetranychus urticae. During </p>

<p>the invasion and spread of TYLCV and B. tabaci Q in China, B. 
tabaci B and Q and TYLCV usually coexist on the same host plants. 
However, no study has evaluated the role of JA in the interactions 
among B. tabaci B and Q, TYLCV, and the host plant. 
In the current study, we compared the performance of B. tabaci B 
and Q on plants previously attacked by B. tabaci Q and B that were or 
were not carrying TYLCV, respectively. The viral load in viruliferous 
B and Q infected leaves was also compared. We also quantified the 
endogenous JA level and PI activity and JA-related gene expression 
in healthy tomato plants or plants infested by nonviruliferous and 
viruliferous B. tabaci B and Q. Our goals were to determine how plant 
defense responses were differently affected by viruliferous B. tabaci B 
vs. Q vectors and how those responses affect vector performance. </p>

<p>Results 
Fecundity and longevity of viruliferous and nonviruliferous Q and 
B on plants previously exposed to viruliferous and nonviruliferous 
B and Q. Nonviruliferous Q laid an average number of 12.060 and 
10.880 eggs per day on plants that were previously infested by nonvi-
ruliferous B and on noninfested control plants (F 1, 18 5 2.413, P 5 
0.138) (Fig. 1A). Nonviruliferous B laid an average number of 11.080 
and 12.000 eggs per day on plants that were previously infested by 
nonviruliferous Q and on noninfested control plants (F 1, 18 5 1.119, 
P5 0.304) (Fig. 1C). Viruliferous Q laid an average number of 10.760 
and 9.760 eggs per day on plants that were previously infested by </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Fecundity of Bemisia tabaci B and Q on tomato plants previously infested with nonviruliferous or viruliferous B and Q and on noninfested </p>

<p>control plants (CK). The virus was TYLCV. (A). Fecundity of nonviruliferous Q (NVQ) on plants previously exposed to nonviruliferous B (NVB-
damaged) and on noninfested plants (CK). (B). Fecundity of nonviruliferous B (NVB) on plants previously exposed to nonviruliferous Q (NVQ-
damaged) and on noninfested plants (CK). (C). Fecundity of viruliferous Q (VQ) on plants previously exposed to viruliferous B (VB-damaged) and on 
noninfested plants (CK). (D). Fecundity of viruliferous B (VB) on plants previously exposed to viruliferous Q (VQ-damaged) and on noninfested plants 
(CK). Values are means 6 SE. Asterisks indicate significant differences (P , 0.05). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5230 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05230 </p>

<p>
viruliferous B and on control plants (F 1, 18 5 2.468, P 5 0.134) 
(Fig. 1B). In contrast, viruliferous B laid an average number of 
11.220 and 8.020 eggs per day on plants that were previously 
infested by viruliferous Q and on noninfested control plants (F 1, 18 
5 80.616, P , 0.001) (Fig. 1D). Only viruliferous B laid significantly 
more eggs on plants that were previously infested by viruliferous Q 
than on noninfested control plants. 
The longevity of nonviruliferous Q was 31.500 and 31.300 days on 
plants previously infested by nonviruliferous B and on noninfested 
control plants (F 1, 18 5 1.220, P 5 0.866) (Fig. 2A). The longevity of 
viruliferous Q was 33.200 and 31.400 days on plants previously 
infested by viruliferous B and on noninfested control plants (F 1, 18 
5 6.787, P 5 0.291) (Fig. 2B). The longevity of nonviruliferous B was 
31.300 and 33.000 days on plants previously infested by nonviruli-
ferous Q and on noninfested control plants (F 1, 18 5 0.061, P 5 
0.029) (Fig. 2C). The longevity of viruliferous B was 32.100 and 
27.400 days on plants previously infested by viruliferous Q and on 
noninfested control plants (F 1, 18 5 2.866, P , 0.001) (Fig. 2D). 
Nonviruliferous B lived shorter on plants previously infested by non-
viruliferous Q than on noninfested control plants. On the contrary, 
viruliferous B lived longer on plants previously infested by virulifer-
ous Q than on noninfested control plants. </p>

<p>Viral load in viruliferous whiteflies-infected and healthy tomato 
plants. After 7-day different biotypes inoculation, there wasn't 
significant TYLCV symptom on leaves. However, the viral load </p>

<p>was highest in viruliferous Q-infected leaves than in leaves infested 
with viruliferous B (F 2, 33 5 82.824, P , 0.001) (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>JA content in leaves infested by viruliferous and nonviruliferous B 
and Q. The JA content was highest in control leaves, lowest in leaves </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Longevity of Bemisia tabaci B and Q on tomato plants previously infested with nonviruliferous or viruliferous B and Q and on noninfested </p>

<p>control plants (CK). The virus was TYLCV. (A). Longevity of nonviruliferous Q (NVQ) on plants previously exposed to nonviruliferous B (NVBD) 
and on noninfested plants (CK). (B). Longevity of nonviruliferous B (NVB) on plants previously exposed to nonviruliferous Q (NVQD) and on 
noninfested plants (CK). (C). Longevity of viruliferous Q (VQ) on plants previously exposed to viruliferous B (VBD) and on noninfested plants (CK). 
(D). Longevity of viruliferous B (VB) on plants previously exposed to viruliferous Q (VQD) and on noninfested plants (CK). Values are means 6 SE. 
Within each panel, different letters indicate significant differences (P , 0.05). </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Viral load in viruliferous whiteflies-infected and healthy </p>

<p>tomato plants. VQ: Leaves were infested with viruliferous Q for 7 days; VB: 
Leaves were infested with viruliferous B for 7 days; CK: Leaves were not 
infested with whiteflies. Values are means 6 SE. Different letters indicate 
significant differences (P , 0.05). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5230 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05230 </p>

<p>
infested with viruliferous Q, and intermediate in leaves infested with 
nonviruliferous B and Q whiteflies (F 4, 40 5 348.001, P , 0.001) 
(Fig. 4). JA titers were much lower in leaves infested with 
viruliferous Q than with nonviruliferous Q. However, JA titers did 
not differ in leaves infested with viruliferous and nonviruliferous B 
(Fig. 4). For example, at 1 d infestion, the JA content in leaves 
infested with nonviruliferous B, nonviruliferous Q, viruliferous B 
and viruliferous Q was 281.333, 301.333, 266.667 and 134.000 ng/g 
FW, respectively. </p>

<p>PI activity in leaves infested by nonviruliferous and viruliferous B 
and Q. The proteinase inhibitor activity in leaves noninfested and in 
leaves infested with nonviruliferous B, nonviruliferous Q, 
viruliferous B and viruliferous Q was 0.536, 0.642, 0.401, 0.195 and 
0.863 nmol mg 
21 protein, respectively. PI activity was highest in the 
control leaves and was lower in leaves infested with viruliferous Q 
than with nonviruliferous Q (F 4, 40 5 62.567, P , 0.001) (Fig. 5). PI 
activity tended to be lower in leaves that were infested with 
viruliferous B than with nonviruliferous B. PI activity was signifi-
cantly lower in leaves infested with viruliferous Q than with 
viruliferous B (Fig. 5). </p>

<p>Gene expression in leaves infested by viruliferous and nonviru-
liferous B and Q. The relative expression of LOX was lower in leaves 
that were infested with viruliferous Q than with nonviruliferous Q 
and was lowest in the control (F 4, 10 5 11.830, P 5 0.001) (Fig. 6). 
LOX expression was significantly lower in leaves infested with 
viruliferous Q than with nonviruliferous B and Q. 
The expression of PI II was highest in the control, lowest in leaves 
infested with viruliferous Q, and intermediate in leaves infested with 
nonviruliferous Q, nonviruliferous B, and viruliferous B (F 4, 10 5 
21.695, P , 0.001) (Fig. 6). </p>

<p>Discussion 
Bemisia tabaci and its associated begomoviruses have caused serious 
economic losses in many parts of the world </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>. The indirect losses 
resulting from virus transmission far surpass the direct losses result-
ing from feeding. In recent years, B. tabaci Q has invaded China 
34 and </p>

<p>has now displaced B as the predominant B. tabaci in most parts of the 
country </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>. Concurrent with the spread of B. tabaci Q, TYLCV out-
breaks have caused great damage to tomato production in many 
provinces in China </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>. In this study, we determined how the inter-
action between B. tabaci B and Q is affected by their virus status. The 
results showed that when plants were first damaged by nonvirulifer-
ous B and Q, the performance of the B. tabaci that subsequently 
infested the plants was not affected. However, the fecundity and 
longevity of viruliferous B were significantly higher on plants that 
had been previously infested by viruliferous Q than on noninfested 
plants. The fecundity and longevity of viruliferous Q were not affec-
ted on plants that were previously attacked by viruliferous B and on 
noninfested plants. In other words, the feeding by nonviruliferous B. 
tabaci did not affect the performance of B. tabaci that followed, but 
the feeding of viruliferous Q enhanced the performance of virulifer-
ous B that followed. In addition, the viral load was significantly 
higher in viruliferous Q-infected leaves than in viruliferous B-
infected leaves at 7 days after the initial inoculation. We concluded 
that the interactions between B. tabaci B and Q were differentially 
altered by TYLCV depending on which biotypes of B. tabaci initially 
infested the host plant. Most importantly, the results indicated that 
infestation by viruliferous B. tabaci Q reduced the plant's defense 
against subsequent infestation by B. tabaci. 
Recent studies showed that the defense provided by the JA signal-
ing pathway against phloem-feeding insects can be reduced by 
insect-vectored viruses </p>

<p>27,35,36 </p>

<p>. For example, Lewsey et al. (2010) </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>indicated that infection of plants with cucumber mosaic virus, which 
is transmitted by the aphid Myzus persicae, strongly inhibited 
JA-regulated gene expression. Our recent study also showed that 
viruliferous Q reduced the JA content to a lower level than nonvir-
uliferous Q </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>. Furthermore, our study determined that the endogen-
ous JA content of leaves was greatly reduced by infestation with 
viruliferous Q but only moderately reduced by infestation with non-
viruliferous Q, nonviruliferous B, or viruliferous B. We concluded 
that the co-infection of TYLCV and B. tabaci Q rather than B could 
reduce JA production and promote the spread of both Q and TYLCV. 
Many reports documented antagonistic interactions between the 
SA and JA pathways </p>

<p>37,38 </p>

<p>. For example, application of exogenous SA 
reduced the JA-dependent defense response </p>

<p>39-41 </p>

<p>. Evidence also indi-
cated that SA accumulation was induced by phloem-feeding 
insects </p>

<p>40,42 </p>

<p>. Our previous study showed that feeding by viruliferous 
B. tabaci B induced higher levels of endogenous SA than feeding by 
nonviruliferous B but that feeding by viruliferous Q did not induce 
higher levels of endogenous SA than feeding by nonviruliferous Q </p>

<p>5,28 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Figure 4 | JA content of tomato leaves without Bemisia tabaci infestation </p>

<p>or after infestation (for 0.5 h to 7 d) with viruliferous or nonviruliferous 
Bemisia tabaci B and Q. The virus was TYLCV. NVQ: Leaves were 
infested with nonviruliferous Q; NVB: Leaves were infested with 
nonviruliferous B; VQ: Leaves were infested with viruliferous Q; VB: 
Leaves were infested with viruliferous B; CK: Leaves were not infested with 
whiteflies or virus. Values are means 6 SE. Different letters indicate 
significant differences (P , 0.05). </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Proteinase inhibitor activity in tomato leaves without Bemisia 
tabaci infestation or after infestation (for 1 day) with viruliferous or 
nonviruliferous Bemisia tabaci B and Q. The virus was TYLCV. NVB: 
non-viruliferous B; VB: viruliferous B; NVQ: nonviruliferous Q; VQ: 
viruliferous Q; CK: noninfested leaves. Values are means 6 SE. Different 
letters indicate significant differences (P , 0.05). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5230 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05230 </p>

<p>
According to this previous study and the current study, feeding by 
viruliferous Q greatly reduced JA content but did not increase SA 
content relative to feeding by nonviruliferous Q. Overall, viruliferous 
Q seems to have the ability to suppress plant defenses. 
An increase in PI activity contributes to the plant defense response 
against insects and pathogens, and JA is known to mediate the induc-
tion of PIs </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>. The previous study showed that PI activity in leaves 
infested by viruliferous Q was lower than the activity in leaves 
infested by nonviruliferous Q 
8 . Most importantly, our study demon-
strated that the PI activity in leaves infested by viruliferous Q was 
lower than in leaves infested by viruliferous B and was much lower 
than in noninfested leaves. There was also a positive correlation 
between JA content and PI activity, i.e., both JA content and PI 
activity were significantly reduced by viruliferous Q. This result pro-
vides additional evidence that viruliferous Q can suppress JA-related 
plant defenses. 
The JA-responsive upstream gene LOX and downstream gene PI II 
are two important genes in JA signaling pathway </p>

<p>24,25,43-46 </p>

<p>. Our results 
showed that LOX was induced and PI II was reduced, which are 
consistent with previous study indicating that the upstream gene 
LOX2 was induced, whereas the downstream gene VSP1 was reduced 
after B. tabaci nymph infestion </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>. For example, LOX2 transcript was 
significantly induced by B. tabaci nymph feeding at 14 d but not at 
7 d after infestation </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>. In our study, the gene expression of LOX was 
induced at 1 d after infestation, so we speculate that there may be a 
different process of gene response in tomato and Arabidopsis. 
Besides, the JA-related defense response induced by adults may be 
different from nymphs because nymphs have a long-term interaction 
with plants whereas adults may induce a transient response. 
Furthermore, our data indicated that JA pathway was differently 
manipulated by nonviruliferous and viruliferous B. tabaci B and Q. 
The gene expression was always reduced to a lower level by infestion 
of viruliferous Q than by infestion of nonviruliferous Q, nonviruli-
ferous B, and viruliferous B, regardless of LOX or PI II. 
The effects of viruliferous B. tabaci Q can be explained in several 
related ways. First, TYLCV infection may reduce levels of carbohy-
drates and amino acids in leaves and in the phloem in ways that 
reduce plant quality for viruliferous B but not for viruliferous Q. 
Second, the feeding behaviors of B. tabaci B and Q may differ. Our 
recent study showed that when nonviruliferous whiteflies fed on 
healthy and TYLCV-infected tomato plants, B. tabaci Q engaged 
in more phloem salivation and phloem sap ingestion than B. tabaci 
B </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>. Third, virus infection could change the primary and secondary 
compounds produced by the host plant, which in turn could differ-</p>

<p>entially affect the performance of B. tabaci B and Q. Further experi-
ments are needed to investigate the biochemical and physiological 
mechanisms underlying the effects of TYLCV on B. tabaci B and Q. 
In conclusion, we found that the interactions between B. tabaci B 
and Q were differentially altered by TYLCV and the JA-related plant 
defense response was reduced more by B. tabaci Q carrying TYLCV 
than by B carrying TYLCV. These different responses to TYLCV-
carrying B and Q are likely to favor the spread of Q and TYLCV in 
China. More research is needed to clarify the molecular mechanisms 
by which viruliferous B. tabaci Q suppresses plant defense. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Host plants. Tomato plants (Lycopersicon esculentum, cv. Zhongza 9) were grown in 
pots containing a mixture of vermiculite and organic fertilizer at 25 6 1uC, 60 6 100% 
RH, and L14: D10 in a greenhouse. TYLCV-infected plants were produced by 
Agrobacterium tumefaciens-mediated inoculation at the 3-4 true-leaf stage with a 
cloned TYLCV genome (GenBank accession ID: AM282874) that was originally 
isolated from Shanghai, China </p>

<p>46 </p>

<p>. Viral infection of test plants was confirmed by 
characteristic leaf curl symptoms and by molecular analysis 
10 . </p>

<p>Establishment of viruliferous and nonviruliferous B and Q colonies. B populations 
were originally collected from infested cabbage (Brassica oleracea. cv. Jingfeng 1) in 
Beijing, China in 2004 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>, and Q populations were originally collected from infested 
poinsettia (Euphorbia pulcherrima Wild. ex Klotz.) in Beijing, China in 2009 
10 . We 
obtained viruliferous B and Q colonies by placing four TYLCV-infected tomato 
plants in each of two cages (60 3 60 3 60 cm). We then transferred 300 
nonviruliferous B and Q adults to each of the two cages, one biotype per cage. We 
simultaneously established nonviruliferous B and Q colonies by transferring 300 
nonviruliferous B and Q adults to cages with virus-free tomato plants, one biotype per 
cage. All colonies were maintained for more than six generations in greenhouses. The 
purity of these populations was monitored by sampling 20 adults per generation using 
the CAPS (cleavage amplified polymorphic sequence) molecular diagnostic 
technique and the molecular marker mitochondrial cytochrome oxidase I gene 
(mtCOI) </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Fecundity and longevity of viruliferous and nonviruliferous B and Q on plants 
previously exposed to viruliferous and nonviruliferous Q and B. Eighty tomato 
plants with eight true leaves were selected. Five leaves on each plant were placed in clip 
cages and each clip cage had 60 newly emerged nonviruliferous or viruliferous B or Q. 
In other words, each tomato plant was inoculated by 300 viruliferous or non-
viruliferous whiteflies for seven days. Control plants with the same size were placed in 
five clip cages per plant without whiteflies. There were each of 10 plants with 
nonviruliferous B, nonviruliferous Q, viruliferous B, viruliferous Q respectively, and 
40 noninfested control plants. After seven days, all whiteflies adults, instars and eggs 
were removed gently with a brush from the clip cages, and the control plants were also 
treated with a brush, and then one adult female (two days since eclosion) was placed 
in one of five clip cages on each plant. The adult females were either B or Q. For 
example, one viruliferous Q was added to one of five leaves on each of 10 plants 
previously exposed to viruliferous B and to one of five leaves on 10 non-infested 
control plants. Similarly, one viruliferous B was added to one of five leaves on each of 
10 plants that had been previously exposed to viruliferous Q and to 10 non-infested </p>

<p>Figure 6 | Relative expression of LOX and PI II genes in tomato leaves without Bemisia tabaci infestation or after infestation (for 1 day) with 
viruliferous or nonviruliferous Bemisia tabaci B and Q. The virus was TYLCV. Values are normalized to ACT and UBI. NVB: non-viruliferous B; VB: 
viruliferous B; NVQ: nonviruliferous Q; VQ: viruliferous Q; CK: noninfested leaves. Values are means 6 SE. Different letters indicate significant 
differences (P , 0.05). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5230 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05230 </p>

<p>
control plants. After one day, the whitefly on one leave was replaced with another 
leave of the five leaves. The same was done with nonviruliferous B and Q. The new 
eggs deposited on the leaves during the first 5 days were counted. The mean longevity 
of B. tabaci was calculated after all whiteflies had died. </p>

<p>Viral load with TAS-ELISA. After seven days inoculation by different whiteflies, the 
infested and non-infested tomato leaves were tested for TYLCV with a triple antibody 
sandwich enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (TAS-ELISA). A kit supplied by 
Adgen Phytodiagnotics (Neogen Europe (Ayr), Ltd) was used. Leaf samples of 0.1 g 
were ground in 1 ml of extraction buffer. Each of the three treatments (viruliferous B-
infested leaves; viruliferous Q-infested leaves, and non-infested leaves) was 
represented by 12 replicates. Absorbance was read with a spectrophotometer at the 
wavelength of 405 nm. The samples were considered positive for TYLCV when the 
mean optical density (OD) values at 405 nm were over three times that of the healthy 
controls. </p>

<p>JA content in leaves infested by viruliferous and nonviruliferous B and Q. 
Endogenous JA was quantified according to Flors et al. (2008) 
48 and Huang et al. 
(2012) 
49 . Tomato plants with eight true leaves were used. Six leaves with 50 adults (or 
no whiteflies) per leave on each plant were placed in clip cages. There were five 
treatments: nonviruliferous B, nonviruliferous Q, viruliferous B, viruliferous Q, or no 
whiteflies. After infestation times of 0.5 h, 1 h, 1 d, 3 d, 5 d, and 7 d, the clip cages 
and whiteflies within were removed, and the corresponding leaves were collected. The 
entire plant received the same treatment, and each treatment was represented by nine 
replicates. The leaves were frozen, and a 0.5-g sample was ground with 3 ml of 80% 
methanol and kept at 220uC for 12 h before an internal standard containing 6 ml of 
[9,10]-dihydro-JA (50 ng ml 
21 ) was added. The mixture was centrifuged at 7500 g for 
10 min. The first supernatant was transferred and saved, and the precipitate was re-
suspended in 2 ml of 100% methanol before the mixture was centrifuged again at 
7500 g for 10 min. The first and second supernatants were combined and adjusted to 
pH 2.5-3.0 with 3 M HCl and then extracted with an equal volume of ethyl acetate. 
After the organic fraction was evaporated, the solid residue was re-suspended in 
0.1 M acetic acid and loaded on a C18 column (Waters, Milford, MA, USA). The C18 
column was then eluted, and the eluents were collected and evaporated. After 
esterification of the residue with excess diazomethane, the sample volume was 
adjusted to 50 ml with acetic acid and analyzed using GC/MS system (6890N/5973N; 
Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA) with a DB-5-MS column (30 m 3 
0.32 mm 3 0.25 mm, J&amp;W Scientific, Agilent Technologies). Endogenous JA and the 
internal standard were analyzed using full-scan mode. </p>

<p>PI activity in leaves infested by viruliferous and nonviruliferous B and Q. Tomato 
plants with 6-7 true leaves were used. Six leaves with 50 adults (or no whiteflies) per 
leave on each plant were placed in clip cages for one day. There were five treatments: 
nonviruliferous B, nonviruliferous Q, viruliferous B, viruliferous Q, or no whiteflies. 
The entire plant received the same treatment, and each treatment was represented by 
nine replicates. Leaf tissue of 600 mg was ground in liquid nitrogen, homogenized in 
1 000 ml of extraction buffer (0.1 M Tris-HCl buffer, pH 8.2, and 20 mM CaCl 2 ; 153 
w/v), and centrifuged at 17 200 g for 30 min at 4uC. A mixture containing 50 ml of the 
supernatant, 50 ml of trypsin (4.7 3 10 
25 M), and 500 ml of extraction buffer was 
incubated at room temperature for 5 min. Controls include 500 ml of extraction 
buffer and 50 ml of trypsin. A 500 ml volume of the mixture was added to 500 ml of 
extraction buffer and 500 ml of Na-Benzoyl-D, L-arginine 4-nitroanilide 
hydrochloride (1.2 mM) 
31 . Trypsin activity was detected at 410 nm with a 
spectrophotometer. The difference between the absorbance at 150 and 60 s was used 
to determine trypsin activity. Measurements were performed in triplicate for each 
sample, were converted to mg of trypsin inhibited per gram of protein 
50 , and were 
corrected for the dilution </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Gene expression levels in leaves infested by viruliferous and nonviruliferous B and 
Q. Tomato leaves in clip cages were treated the same as leaves used for determination 
of PI activity. To determine how B. tabaci infestation affected the JA pathway and its 
related PI genes, the expression levels of the upstream LOX gene 
25,44,45 and the 
downstream PI II gene were measured 
52,53 of the JA signal pathway and used actin 
(ACT) and ubiquitin 3 (UBI) 
54 as reference genes (Table 1). Total RNA was extracted 
from 0.2 g of treated or control leaves, and 1.0 mg of RNA was used to synthesize the </p>

<p>first-strand cDNA using the PrimeScriptH RT reagent Kit (Takara Bio, Tokyo, Japan) 
with gDNA Eraser (Perfect Real Time, TaKara, Shiga, Japan). The 25.0 ml reaction 
system containing 10.5 ml of ddH 2 O, 1.0 ml of cDNA, 12.5 ml of SYBRH Green PCR 
Master Mix (TIANGEN, Beijing, China), and 0.5 ml of each primer. Relative 
quantities of RNA were calculated using the comparative cycle threshold (Ct) (2 
2DDCt ) 
method </p>

<p>55,56 </p>

<p>. Three biological replicates and four technical replicates were analyzed. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses. Repeated-measures ANOVAs were used to compare the daily 
fecundity of nonviruliferous and viruliferous B or Q on plants that had been 
previously exposed to nonviruliferous and viruliferous Q or B and on noninfested 
control plants. T-test was used to compare the longevity of nonviruliferous and 
viruliferous B or Q on plants that had been previously exposed to nonviruliferous and 
viruliferous Q or B and on noninfested control plants, respectively. One-way 
ANOVA was used to compare the viral load in leaves infested by viruliferous B and Q. 
One-way ANOVA was also used to compare the JA content, PI activity, and relative 
gene expression of LOX and PI II in control leaves and leaves infested by 
nonviruliferous and viruliferous B and Q. <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 20.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, 
USA) was used for all statistical analyses. </p>



<p>Table 1 | Primer sequences used for qPCR analysis </p>

<p>Gene </p>

<p>GeneBank 
accession no. 
Primer sequence </p>

<p>LOX NM_001247330 F: 59-ACTCATCAGCACCGACATCG-39 
R: 59-ACTCTCCAGAAAGAACTCCTGC-39 
PI II K03291 
F: 59-CCTATTCAAGATGTCCCCGTTC-39 
R: 59-GGGCAATCCAGAAGATGG-39 
ACT BT013707 
F: 59-AGGCAGGATTTGCTGGTGATGATGCT-39 
R: 59-ATACGCATCCTTCTGTCCCATTCCGA-39 
UBI X58253 
F: 59-TCGTAAGGAGTGCCCTAATGCTGA-39 
R: 59-CAATCGCCTCCAGCCTTGTTGTAA-39 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5230 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05230 </p>



<p>
Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This research was supported by the 973 Program (2013CB127602), the Beijing Natural 
Science Foundation (6131002), the Special Fund for Agro-scientific Research in the Public 
Interest (201303019) and the Beijing Key Laboratory for Pest Control and Sustainable 
Cultivation of Vegetables. The granting agencies had no role in study design, data collection 
and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>Y.J.Z., X.B.S., H.P.P. designed the experiment. X.B.S., H.Y.Z., Y.F., G.C. performed the 
experiment. X.G.J., W.X., Q.J.W., S.L.W., X.G.Z. contributed reagents/materials. X.B.S., 
H.P.P., Y.J.Z. wrote the paper. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Shi, X.B. et al. Bemisia tabaci Q carrying tomato yellow leaf curl 
virus strongly suppresses host plant defenses. Sci. Rep. 4, 5230; DOI:10.1038/srep05230 
(2014). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. The images in this article are included in the 
article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the image credit; 
if the image is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to 
obtain permission from the license holder in order to reproduce the image. To view 
a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5230 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05230 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>