<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4387613" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Isolated congenital atrioventricular block (CAVB) is a rare condition with multiple clinical outcomes. Ventricular 
remodeling can occur in approximately 10% of the patients after pacemaker (PM) implantation. </p>

<p>Objectives: To assess the functional capacity of children and young adults with isolated CAVB and chronic pacing of the right 
ventricle (RV) and evaluate its correlation with predictors of ventricular remodeling. </p>

<p>Methods: This cross-sectional study used a cohort of patients with isolated CAVB and RV pacing for over a year. The subjects 
underwent clinical and echocardiographic evaluation. Functional capacity was assessed using the six-minute walk test. 
Chi-square test, Fisher's exact test, and Pearson correlation coefficient were used, considering a significance level of 5%. </p>

<p>Results: A total of 61 individuals were evaluated between March 2010 and December 2013, of which 67.2% were women, 
aged between 7 and 41 years, who were using PMs for 13.5 ± 6.3 years. The percentage of ventricular pacing was 
97.9 ± 4.1%, and the duration of the paced QRS complex was 153.7 ± 19.1 ms. Majority of the subjects (95.1%) were 
asymptomatic and did not use any medication. The mean distance walked was 546.9 ± 76.2 meters and was strongly 
correlated with the predicted distance (r = 0.907, p = 0.001) but not with risk factors for ventricular remodeling. </p>

<p>Conclusions: The functional capacity of isolated CAVB patients with chronic RV pacing was satisfactory but did not correlate 
with risk factors for ventricular remodeling. (Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(1):67-77) </p>

<p>Keywords: Congenital Heart Diseases; Atrioventricular Block; Child; Artificial Pacemaker; Young Adult; Walk. </p>

<p>Considering the rarity of CAVB, the effects of chronic 
RV pacing on the functional ability remain poorly studied. 
The data available in the literature were obtained from a small 
series of cases involving individuals who had not yet undergone 
PM implantation </p>

<p>17,18   . </p>

<p>To investigate the functional capacity of children and young 
adults with PM suffering from CAVB, we conducted a cross-
sectional analysis in a prospective cohort comprising individuals 
with CAVB and artificial cardiac PMs during follow-up in our 
institution. We hypothesized that chronic RV pacing did not 
impair the functional capacity of individuals not suffering from 
structural heart diseases associated with impulse disturbance. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study design and population </p>

<p>Between 1982 and 2013, 165 individuals with CAVB 
underwent a first implantation of a permanent cardiac 
PM at our institution before completing 21 years of age. 
This prospective cohort group was monitored for the 
evaluation of clinical, functional, and echocardiographic 
effects of chronic cardiac pacing in children and young adults 
with CAVB (ClinicalTrials.gov ID = NCT01477658). </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Atrioventricular (AV) block is a rare congenital condition, 
with an estimated incidence of 1 case in 20,000 births 
1,2 . 
Its isolated form, i.e., without associated intracardiac 
defects, corresponds to approximately 70% of the cases. 
The pathophysiology of AV block is strongly correlated with 
maternal autoimmune diseases 
3-7 . The implantation of a 
permanent cardiac pacemaker (PM) is the only form of 
treatment and results in significant long-term survival rates </p>

<p>8-10   . </p>

<p>Despite the satisfactory clinical outcome in most cases, 
approximately 10% of the patients develop severe ventricular 
dysfunction, even after treatment with a PM. There is evidence 
that the unfavorable outcome is associated with intrauterine 
autoimmune myocarditis and with the deleterious effect of 
chronic pacing of the right ventricle (RV) </p>

<p>1,10-16   . </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(1):67-77 </p>

<p>Oliveira Júnior et al 
Functional capacity in congenital AV block subjects </p>

<p>In the present study, a cross-sectional analysis of this 
population was performed considering the following inclusion 
criteria: (1) age &lt; 21 years at the first PM implantation; (2)  unifocal RV pacing for &gt; 1 year; (3) absence of intracardiac 
defects regardless of surgical correction. Subjects with LV or 
multifocal pacing were not included. The study was approved 
by the research ethics committee of our institution, and all the 
subjects signed an informed consent form. </p>

<p>Study outcome </p>

<p>The functional capacity was assessed using the six-
minute walk test (6MWT), and the expected outcome was 
that individuals would walk a distance close to 90% of the 
predicted value. </p>

<p>Patient recruitment </p>

<p>The subjects were consecutively recruited during outpatient 
care or by referring to the database of the surgical PM unit. </p>

<p>Analysis of medical records </p>

<p>The medical history of each patient was analyzed with 
interviews and reviews of medical records. The following 
data were collected: (1) demographic data; (2) clinical data 
preceding the PM implantation (during the diagnosis of CAVB), 
including clinical events, comorbidities, medications used, 
and electrocardiogram and echocardiogram results; (3) data 
associated with the first PM implantation (age, time between 
diagnosis and implantation, type of PM, route of access used, 
and site of RV pacing). </p>

<p>Population profile at the time of enrollment </p>

<p>At enrollment, all subjects underwent physical examination, 
Also, a revision of their medical records, including the 
assessment of heart failure symptoms and use of cardiovascular 
drugs, was made. </p>

<p>Evaluation of implantable electronic cardiac devices </p>

<p>The evaluation of the cardiac pacing device aimed at 
determining several parameters, including the pacing mode, 
atrial pacing, ventricular pacing, heart rate, duration of the 
QRS complex (spontaneous and with an active PM), mode 
of operation, and percentage of ventricular pacing. Specific 
programmers for each PM model and the Hewlett-Packard 
Page Writer 200 electrocardiograph with capacity for 
automatic analysis of axes and intervals were used. </p>

<p>Evaluation of functional capacity </p>

<p>The 6MWT was performed according to the guidelines 
of the American Thoracic Society (ATS) 
19 . All participants 
were instructed to walk at the maximum possible speed in 
a 45-meter long corridor with demarcations on the ground 
at every meter. Participants were verbally encouraged at two 
and four minutes after the beginning of the test. The examiner 
determined the completion of the test after six minutes. </p>

<p>Before beginning and after completing the test, blood 
pressure, heart rate, and oxygen saturation were measured, </p>

<p>and each individual described their level of dyspnea and 
fatigue using the modified Borg scale </p>

<p>19   . The criteria for test 
interruption included angina, significant dyspnea, lower limb 
fatigue, dizziness, profuse sweating, and pallor. </p>

<p>Functional capacity was assessed by evaluating the distance 
walked during the six minutes (in meters). The predicted 
distance was calculated using the equation proposed for the 
Brazilian population </p>

<p>20   . </p>

<p>Electronic data collection and management </p>

<p>Data were stored in a database developed with the Research 
Electronic Data Capture (<rs type="software">REDCap</rs>) system </p>

<p>21   , which is hosted 
on the server of our institution. This software, developed at 
Vanderbilt University (Tennessee, USA), is fully web-based and 
enables electronic data collection and management and also 
study process management, while meeting the criteria set by 
the international policies on data privacy and security in the 
health sector </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>. The use of this tool also allowed the validation, 
auditing, and electronic data export. Figure 1 illustrates the 
software functionalities. </p>

<p>Variable analysis </p>

<p>Several variables that could influence the functional 
capacity of the individuals and serve as predictors of ventricular 
remodeling were studied, including gender, age at first PM 
implantation, current age, functional class according to the 
New York Heart Association (NYHA), use of cardiovascular 
drugs, type of PM in use (ventricular or atrioventricular), length 
of PM use, duration of artificially stimulated QRS complex, left 
ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) using Simpson's method, 
left ventricular diastolic diameter (LVDD), left intraventricular 
electromechanical delay determined by tissue Doppler, and 
the presence of autoantibodies (anti-Ro/SSA and anti-La/SSB) 
in the mothers of the study participants. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data were exported to <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> <rs id="software-3" type="software">Excel</rs> spreadsheets 
and analyzed using <rs type="software">SAS</rs> (Statistical Analysis System), <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> 
(Statistical Package for Social Sciences), and <rs type="software">R Studio</rs> 
softwares. </p>

<p>The quantitative variables were described using the 
mean and standard deviation, and qualitative variables were 
presented as absolute and relative frequencies. </p>

<p>The correlation of the qualitative variables with the 
predicted distance achieved in the walk test (greater or 
smaller than 90%) was measured using chi-square test 
or Fisher's exact test. The correlation of the quantitative 
variables with the predicted distance achieved was analyzed 
using Pearson's correlation coefficient. P values ≤0.05 were 
considered significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Between 1982 and 2013, 165 individuals diagnosed 
with CAVB had undergone the first PM implantation at our 
institution before completing 21 years of age. Of these, 
45 had associated cardiac defects and were not eligible </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira Júnior et al. 
Functional capacity in congenital AV block subjects </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(1):67-77 </p>

<p>for the study. Of the 120 eligible, 61 met the study criteria 
(Figure 2). Of the remaining subjects, two had died, six had 
been monitored for other medical complications, and 25 
could not be located, and therefore were not considered for 
follow-up. In addition, 26 other subjects were located but 
were not included in the study for the following reasons: RV 
pacing for less than one year or LV pacing at the time of the 
study in 13 subjects; change to a biventricular type of PM in 4 
subjects; cardiac transplantation in one subject; and residing 
in remote locations in 8 subjects. </p>

<p>Demographic and clinical data were collected during the 
first PM implantation and are summarized in Table 1. </p>

<p>The mean age of participants at the first implantation was 
8.5 ± 6.2 years (range 4 days to 20.2 years). The mean period 
between diagnosis and first PM implantation was 4.8 ± 5.4 years 
(range from 4 days to 20 years) with a median of 2.5 years. </p>

<p>The clinical events that motivated the PM implantation 
were symptomatic bradycardia in 44 individuals (72.1%), and 
included signs and symptoms of heart failure, syncope, pre-
syncope, dizziness, and palpitations. Other patients presented 
asymptomatic bradycardia with complex ventricular arrhythmia, 
prolonged QT interval, chronotropic incompetence, or poor 
weight development. </p>

<p>Preoperative echocardiography was performed in 44 
(72.1%) subjects. In all cases, heart in situs solitus, levocardia, 
and absence of defects in the cardiac septum and valves were 
observed. </p>

<p>Data obtained during the first pacemaker implantation </p>

<p>Unicameral ventricular pacing was used in 65.6% of the 
implantations, and only three children (4.9%) aged ≤10 years 
underwent implantation of atrioventricular PMs. </p>

<p>The epicardium was used as the access route in 4 of 6 
infants and in 5 of 8 pre-school children. The transvenous 
route through the femoral vein was used as the access route 
in the remaining groups. The subclavian vein was used as the 
access route in 43% of the patients comprising pre-school 
children, school children, and adolescents. </p>

<p>The apical endocardium of RV was the site of pacing in 
33 (54.1%) patients. Of the 10 epicardial implants (16.4%), 
7 (11.5%) were initially performed in LV. </p>

<p>Population profile at enrollment </p>

<p>The profile of the study population at enrollment is 
summarized in Table 2. </p>

<p>Figure 1 -The <rs type="software">REDCap</rs> electronic form developed to collect data related to the evaluation of the functional capacity of patients with PM presenting congenital 
atrioventricular block. </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira Júnior et al. 
Functional capacity in congenital AV block subjects </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(1):67-77 </p>

<p>Clinical and pacemaker evaluation </p>

<p>There were no reports of hospitalization for treatment 
of heart failure from the period of PM implantation until 
study enrollment. Only three subjects (4.9%) reported 
symptoms of fatigue during major physical effort. The use 
of cardiovascular medication was reported by five subjects 
(8.2%), as shown in Table 2. </p>

<p>The 35 individuals using AV PMs had adequate sinus 
function, evidenced by a low percentage of atrial pacing 
(27.0 ± 23.7%, median = 19%). The established limits 
of minimum frequency of pacing varied between 50 and 
80 ppm (59.9 ± 3.1 ppm) and the maximum frequency 
varied between 110 and 170 ppm (130.7 ± 15.8 ppm). </p>

<p>The 26 individuals with ventricular PMs were using 
sensors to modulate the pacing frequency. Twenty 
individuals were using sensors for body movement 
(accelerometers) and six were using the combination of 
respiratory minute-volume sensors with body movement. 
The established limits of minimum frequency of pacing 
varied between 60 and 80 ppm (70.0 ± 6.3 ppm), and 
the maximum frequency varied between 120 and 170 ppm 
(145.7 ± 18.4 ppm). </p>

<p>Evaluation of functional capacity </p>

<p>The 6MWT was performed in 61 subjects, aged between 
7 and 41 years. No cases of test interruption or need for 
special care were reported. The mean walking distance 
was 546.9 ± 76.2 meters, representing 91.0 ± 12.5% 
of the value predicted by the equation used in this study 
(Graph 1). Most participants walked a distance greater than 
80% of the predicted value, whereas 18 (29.5%) participants 
walked distances greater than the values estimated by the 
equation (Chart 1). Chart 2 shows the strong correlation 
between the total distance walked and the predicted 
distance (r = 0.907, p = 0.001). </p>

<p>The cardiorespiratory parameters measured before and 
after the 6MWT are described in Table 3. All parameters 
had a normal physiological behavior. However, individuals 
with responsive ventricular PMs with sensors tended to 
have a greater variation in heart rate when compared with 
those treated with AV PMs synchronized with spontaneous 
P waves (p = 0.141). </p>

<p>Despite the variation detected in the functional capacity, 
there was no correlation between the distance walked 
and age, both at the initial PM implantation (r = 0.030, </p>

<p>Figure 2 -Profile of the study population. 
AVB: atrioventricular block; PM: pacemaker; 6MWT: six-minute walk test; CRT: cardiac resynchronization therapy. 
* Two individuals were not included in the analysis because they were not old enough to perform the walk test (infants), although they fulfilled the eligibility criteria. </p>

<p>Study period: 1982-2013 
PM implantation in 165 subjects 
with congenital AVB 
(aged &lt;21 years) </p>

<p>CAVB with associated 
cardiac defects 
(n = 45) </p>

<p>Subjects eligible 
for the study 
(n = 120) </p>

<p>59 subjects were not included in the 
study for the following reasons: 
• Were not located (N = 25) 
• Were subjected to follow up for other 
medical complications (N = 6) 
• Death (N = 2) 
• Without inclusion criteria (N = 13) 
• Geographical distance (N = 8) 
• Subjects undergoing CRT (N = 4) 
• Subjects with heart transplant (N = 1) 
• Subjects not subjected to 6MWT (N = 2) </p>

<p>Subjects enrolled 
in the study 
(n = 61) </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira Júnior et al. 
Functional capacity in congenital AV block subjects </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(1):67-77 </p>

<p>Table 1 -Demographic and clinical profile of the study group </p>

<p>Baseline demographic and clinical characteristics </p>

<p>Female, N (%) 
41 (67.2) </p>

<p>Ethnicity, N (%) </p>

<p>Caucasian 
28 (45.9) </p>

<p>Black 
3 (4.9) </p>

<p>Mixed 
30 (49.2) </p>

<p>Time of CAVB diagnosis, N (%) </p>

<p>Intrauterine 
17 (27.9) </p>

<p>Neonatal 
8 (13.1) </p>

<p>Infant 
12 (19.7) </p>

<p>Pre-school age 
6 (9.8) </p>

<p>School age 
9 (14.8) </p>

<p>Adolescence 
9 (14.8) </p>

<p>Time of PM implantation, N (%) </p>

<p>Neonatal 
6 (9.8) </p>

<p>Infant 
8 (13.1) </p>

<p>Pre-school age 
8 (13.1) </p>

<p>School age 
11 (18.0) </p>

<p>Adolescence 
28 (45.9) </p>

<p>Indication for PM implantation, N (%) </p>

<p>Symptomatic bradycardia 
44 (72.1) </p>

<p>Isolated bradycardia 
17 (27.9) </p>

<p>Comorbidities, N (%) </p>

<p>None 
58 (95.1) </p>

<p>Systemic arterial hypertension 
1 (1.6) </p>

<p>Mitral valve prolapse 
1 (1.6) </p>

<p>Myocarditis 
1 (1.6) </p>

<p>Use of cardiovascular drugs, N (%) </p>

<p>Not used 
57 (93.4) </p>

<p>Angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors 
2 (3.3) </p>

<p>Furosemide 
1 (1.6) </p>

<p>Beta blockers 
1 (1.6) </p>

<p>Heart rate before PM implantation, bpm (mean ± SD) 
51.0 ± 11.9 </p>

<p>QRS complex duration before PM implantation (mean ± SD) 
85.5 ± 15.2 </p>

<p>Axis of the QRS complex before PM implantation (range) 
30-175 
degrees− </p>

<p>Ventricular rhythm, N (%) </p>

<p>Complete atrioventricular block 
58 (95.2) </p>

<p>Mobitz II second-degree atrioventricular block 
1 (1.6) </p>

<p>Second-degree atrioventricular block with 2:1 conduction ratio 
2 (3.3) </p>

<p>LV ejection fraction (%) -Teicholz (mean ± SD) 
55.6 ± 20.5 </p>

<p>End-systolic LV diameter, mm (mean ± SD) 
24.4 ± 9.3 </p>

<p>End-diastolic LV diameter, mm (mean ± SD) 
40.0 ± 11.6 </p>

<p>CAVB: complete congenital atrioventricular block; bpm: beats per minute; SD: 
standard deviation; LV: left ventricle; PM: pacemaker. </p>

<p>Table 2 -Profile of the study group at the time of enrollment </p>

<p>Profile of the study group </p>

<p>Age at the time of evaluation, years (mean ± SD) 
21.6 ± 8.4 </p>

<p>Period of RV stimulation, years (mean ± SD) 
9.9 ± 5.2 </p>

<p>Total length of PM use, years (mean ± SD) 
13.5 ± 6.3 </p>

<p>Clinical evaluation </p>

<p>NYHA functional class in the last evaluation, N (%) </p>

<p>I 
58 (95.1) </p>

<p>II 
3 (4.9) </p>

<p>Cardiovascular drug, N (%) </p>

<p>Atenolol 
1 (1.6) </p>

<p>Atenolol and enalapril 
2 (3.3) </p>

<p>Captopril and aspirin 
1 (1.6) </p>

<p>Losartan and hydrochlorothiazide 
1 (1.6) </p>

<p>Evaluation of pacemaker </p>

<p>Type of PM, N (%) </p>

<p>Ventricular 
26 (42.6) </p>

<p>Atrioventricular 
35 (57.4) </p>

<p>Percentage of ventricular pacing, % (mean ± SD) 
97.9 ± 4.1 </p>

<p>Duration of stimulated QRS, ms (mean ± SD) 
153.7 ± 19.1 </p>

<p>Duration of inhibited QRS, ms (mean ± SD) 
88.7 ± 12.6 </p>

<p>Heart rate, N (%) </p>

<p>Sequential atrioventricular pacing 
19 (31.1) </p>

<p>Exclusive ventricular pacing (AV dissociation) 
26 (42.6) </p>

<p>Ventricular pacing synchronized to P waves 
16 (26.6) </p>

<p>Site of RV stimulation, N (%) </p>

<p>Interventricular septum 
20 (32.8) </p>

<p>Other RV regions (including the apical septum) 
41 (67.2) </p>

<p>Echocardiographic study </p>

<p>LV ejection fraction, % (mean ± SD) 
54.7 ± 7.1 </p>

<p>Diastolic LV diameter, mm (mean ± SD) 
48.2 ± 5.8 </p>

<p>Mitral regurgitation, N (%) </p>

<p>Absent 
5 (8.2) </p>

<p>Discreet 
43 (70.5) </p>

<p>Mild/moderate 
12 (19.7) </p>

<p>Moderate/severe 
1 (1.6) </p>

<p>Intraventricular delay, ms (mean ± SD) 
87.8 ± 57.8 </p>

<p>Interventricular delay, ms (mean ± SD) 
144.1 ± 89.3 </p>

<p>AV: atrioventricular; SD: standard deviation; NYHA: New York Heart 
Association; RV: right ventricle; LV: left ventricle. </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira Júnior et al. 
Functional capacity in congenital AV block subjects </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(1):67-77 </p>

<p>p = 0.816) and during the study period (r = 0.053, 
p = 0.684). Similarly, there was no correlation between 
the distance walked with the duration of RV stimulation 
(r = 0.099, p = 0.448), total duration of PM use 
(r = 0.057, p = 0.664), LVEF (r = 0.071, p = 0.877), 
LVDD (r = 0.161, p = 0.216), and the duration of the 
stimulated QRS complex (r = 0.057, p = 0.664) (Chart 3). </p>

<p>Chart 4 indicates the lack of association between 
the distance walked and gender (p = 0.121), mode of 
pacing (p = 0.821), position of the electrode in the RV </p>

<p>(p = 0.928), or presence of maternal autoantibodies 
(p = 0.288). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Congenital AV block can be adequately treated only with 
cardiac pacing. Considering its rarity, pathophysiology, and 
multiple clinical events it, presents peculiarities that make it 
difficult to standardize a routine care. Furthermore, there is 
no consensus as to the best time for PM implantation, pacing </p>

<p>Chart 2 -Correlation between the total distance walked and the distance predicted by the equation. </p>

<p>Total distance walked (meters) </p>

<p>Predicted distance 
(meters) </p>

<p>r = 0.907 
p = 0.001 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500 
520 
540 
560 
580 
600 
620 
640 
660 
680 </p>

<p>Chart 1 -Total distance walked and percentage of the predicted distance achieved during the six-minute walk test. </p>

<p>Total distance walked (meters) </p>

<p>Number of subjects </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 
370 
400 -500 
501 -600 601 -700 
&gt; 700 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Predicted distance achieved (%) </p>

<p>60 -70% 
71 -80% 
81 -90% 
91 -100% acima de 100% </p>

<p>Number of subjects </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>18 </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira Júnior et al. 
Functional capacity in congenital AV block subjects </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(1):67-77 </p>

<p>Table 3 -Cardiorespiratory parameters measured before and after the six-minute walk test according to the type of pacemaker in use </p>

<p>Measured parameters 
VVIR mode 
DDDR mode 
p value </p>

<p>Before the test </p>

<p>Heart rate (bpm) 
73.3 ± 12.2 
75.1 ± 13.3 
0.599 </p>

<p>Systolic pressure (mmHg) 
111.2 ± 11.7 
111.2 ± 7.1 
0.994 </p>

<p>Diastolic pressure (mmHg) 
75.0 ± 12.1 
74.3 ± 7.2 
0.804 </p>

<p>Oxygen saturation (%) 
97.6 ± 1.3 
96.7 ± 1.7 
0.028 </p>

<p>Borg scale 
1.0 ± 0.1 
1.3 ± 1.4 
0.230 </p>

<p>After the test </p>

<p>Heart rate (bpm) 
95.2 ± 24.7 
86.8 ± 16.6 
0.141 </p>

<p>Systolic pressure (mmHg) 
116.7 ± 11.1 
114.9 ± 10.7 
0.553 </p>

<p>Diastolic pressure (mmHg) 
78.1 ± 11.8 
77.1 ± 9.4 
0.717 </p>

<p>Oxygen saturation (%) 
97.5 ± 1.6 
97.1 ± 1.7 
0.344 </p>

<p>Borg scale 
2.2 ± 2.0 
2.0 ± 2.0 
0.727 </p>

<p>Chart 3 -Correlation between the predicted distance walked in the six-minute walk test and age at the time of PM implantation (A), age during the study (B), duration 
of RV pacing (C), total period of PM use (D), LVEF (E), and LVDD (F). </p>

<p>Predicted distance achieved (%) </p>

<p>Age at the first pacemaker implantation (years) </p>

<p>Duration of RV pacing (years) </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
0 
2 
4 
6 
8 
10 
12 
14 
16 
18 
20 </p>

<p>r = 0,030 
p = 0,816 </p>

<p>A 
140 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 
10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 
20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>30 
30 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 
40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 
50 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>60 
60 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>70 
70 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 
45 </p>

<p>r = 0,053 
p = 0,684 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Predicted distance achieved (%) </p>

<p>Age during the study (years) </p>

<p>Total duration of PM use (years) </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>140 
140 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>120 
120 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 
100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>80 
80 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>60 
60 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>40 
40 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>20 
20 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>0 
Predicted distance achieved (%) 
Predicted distance achieved (%) </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>r = 0,099 
p = 0,448 </p>

<p>r = 0,057 
p = 0,664 </p>

<p>Predicted distance achieved (%) </p>

<p>LFEV (%) </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>r = 0,071 
p = 0,877 </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>LVDD (mm) </p>

<p>r = 0,161 
p = 0,216 
Predicted distance achieved (%) </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira Júnior et al. 
Functional capacity in congenital AV block subjects </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(1):67-77 </p>

<p>mode, or access route to be used. Among the difficulties in 
patient monitoring, the inability to identify those who will 
develop late onset cardiomyopathy and severe heart failure 
has been the most important </p>

<p>1,3,6-16   . </p>

<p>The selection criteria used in this study allowed the 
formation of a homogeneous group with isolated CAVB 
maintained with chronic RV pacing. Their preoperative 
characteristics exemplify the diversity of clinical presentations, 
in which 27.9% of the individuals presented with asymptomatic 
bradycardia and had marked differences in age during the first 
PM implantation, varying between a few days of life until 20 
years of age. Although the ECG showed complete AV block in 
95.2% of the patients, there was a large variation in the type 
of PM used, and patients with ventricular pacing represented 
65.6% of the cases. The clinical improvement reported in 
the literature was confirmed in this study, with only 4.9% of 
the patients showing heart failure symptoms and only 8.2% 
requiring the use of cardiovascular medication </p>

<p>6-16   . </p>

<p>There is evidence that chronic RV pacing may have 
deleterious effects on the LV function 
23,24 . The delayed </p>

<p>activation, particularly of the free wall of LV, in relation to the 
interventricular septum, has been reported as an important 
cause of decreased efficiency of contraction, leading to 
increased volume, geometry changes and dysfunction of 
the LV 
23-26 . The population evaluated comprised individuals 
without cardiac defects, except CAVB, and represented 
an excellent model for understanding the effects caused 
by cardiac dyssynchrony induced by cardiac pacing , 
considering that, in addition to the normal cardiac anatomy, 
intraventricular impulse conduction is also normal in most 
cases. In the present study, we evaluated the primary factors 
related to poor clinical and functional outcomes, including 
age at the first PM implantation 
27 , pacing mode used 
10 , 
site of RV pacing 
11,28,29 , duration of cardiac pacing 
7,16,30,31 , 
duration of the PM-stimulated QRS complex 
12,29,30 , presence 
of dyssynchrony on echocardiography 
32,33 , and the presence 
of maternal autoantibodies 
34-36 . </p>

<p>In this scenario, the walk test can greatly contribute to 
the early detection of clinical worsening by allowing an 
objective assessment of functional capacity. The 6MWT 
is considered a submaximal test used to assess functional </p>

<p>Chart 4 -Comparison between the predicted distance walked in the six-minute walk test and gender (A), pacing mode (B), position of the electrode in the RV (C), and 
presence of anti-Ro/SSA autoantibodies in patients' mothers (D). </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>25 
25 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Number of subjects 
Number of subjects </p>

<p>Number of subjects 
Number of subjects </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>20 
20 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>15 
15 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>10 
10 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>5 
5 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>0 
Men </p>

<p>Not septal 
Anti-Ro positive </p>

<p>Women </p>

<p>Septal 
Anti-Ro negative </p>

<p>p = 0.121 
p = 0.821 
A 
B </p>

<p>Predicted distance achieved ≥ 90% 
Predicted distance achieved ≥ 90% 
Predicted distance achieved &lt; 90% 
Predicted distance achieved &lt; 90% </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Ventricular 
Atrioventricular </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>13 
13 </p>

<p>Predicted distance achieved ≥ 90% 
Predicted distance achieved ≥ 90% 
Predicted distance achieved &lt; 90% 
Predicted distance achieved &lt; 90% </p>

<p>p = 0.928 
p = 0.288 </p>

<p>D 
C </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>13 </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira Júnior et al. 
Functional capacity in congenital AV block subjects </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(1):67-77 </p>

<p>capacity, in view of the global and integrated responses 
of the systems involved during exercise (cardiorespiratory 
system, systemic and peripheral circulation, neuromuscular 
units, and muscle metabolism) 
19 . The 6MWT can be 
performed by children, young people, older people with 
fragilities or other limitations, and by those who cannot 
be evaluated through standardized bicycle or treadmill 
maximal tests. Moreover, it is a quick and inexpensive way 
to measure the physical exercise capacity, and is safe, valid, 
and reproducible 
37 . </p>

<p>In the present study, despite the large age variation of 
individuals at the time of test application, most of them 
had a good functional capacity and walked distances 
greater than 80% of the predicted value, and 29.5% of 
the subjects walked a distance greater than that estimated 
by the equation. Moreover, a strong correlation was 
observed between the total distance covered and the 
distance predicted. On the other hand, the walk test did 
not correlate with any of the predictors of poor outcome 
in the study group. </p>

<p>With regard to the mode of pacing, in addition to the 
hemodynamic effects inherent to the loss of AV synchrony 
when ventricular PMs are used, the use of AV PMs enables 
individuals to take advantage of the physiological response 
of the heart rate because ventricular pacing is synchronized 
with spontaneous P waves. However, no difference was 
observed between the functional capacity of patients with 
AV PMs and that of patients with ventricular PMs 
12,13,27 . 
The tendency of increased heart rate variation between 
the initiation and completion of the walk test in patients 
with ventricular PMs modulated by sensors compared with 
that in patients with AV PMs modulated by spontaneous P 
waves may suggest that sensors may overestimate the need 
to adjust the heart rate. </p>

<p>Several equations for predicting the walking distance for 
normal populations have been proposed 
38-40 . One of the 
most commonly used is based on adults aged between 40 
and 80 years 
38 . However, the option to use the Brazilian 
equation as a parameter of normality in the present study 
was justified by the fact that our sample comprised young 
subjects, with a physique different from international 
standards 
20 . The validity of this equation was tested in 
85 subjects aged 41 ± 13 years, who walked 571 ± 74 
meters versus a predicted distance of 575 ± 38 meters, 
which represented 99.6 ± 11.9% of the predicted value. 
In the present study, although the distance walked was 
smaller than expected, there was a significant correlation 
between the predicted and the walked distance, and 
the values obtained were similar to those achieved by 
normal subjects 
38-40 . These findings suggest that chronic RV 
pacing did not significantly limit the functional capacity of 
individuals with CAVB. </p>

<p>To the best of our knowledge, the study sample was 
the largest in which the functional capacity of a cohort of 
children and young adults with ICAVB and artificial PMs 
was evaluated after a long follow-up period in a single 
cardiology center. Recently, the functional capacity of 16 
children with ICAVB was evaluated, 3 of which had not </p>

<p>yet been subjected to PM implantation. Despite the small 
sample size, the authors found no differences between 
exercise capacity in the two groups 
18 . </p>

<p>Study limitations </p>

<p>The present study has limitations related to the cross-
sectional analyses, such as the lack of a preoperative assessment 
of the functional capacity of the study group. Similarly, the 
lack of a control group prevented the formulation of more 
consistent hypotheses on the actual effects of PM implantation 
on the daily lives of patients. The rarity of this condition limits 
the design of clinical studies aimed at comparing outcomes 
before and after PM implantation, even in multicenter 
projects. The longitudinal follow-up, associated with clinical, 
laboratory, and detailed echocardiographic investigations, may 
provide more robust evidence on the possible deleterious 
effects of conventional PMs on the outcomes of individuals 
presented with isolated CAVB. </p>

<p>Some considerations need to be made in the 
interpretation of our results. The 6MWT does not determine 
peak oxygen consumption or allow the identification 
of the causes underlying potential physical exercise 
limitations, and this task is more appropriately performed 
using cardiopulmonary exercise testing. Therefore, the 
information provided by the 6MWT should be considered 
complementary to the cardiopulmonary exercise test 
but not a replacement. On the other hand, the walk test 
has been widely used to measure clinical outcomes in 
randomized studies with very large populations of patients 
with implantable electronic cardiac devices and therefore, 
can serve as a fast and objective measure of functional 
capacity and even as a prognostic marker of mortality and 
hospitalization in patients with heart failure. Additionally, 
it has been shown that the 6MWT correlates with the 
NYHA functional class, peak oxygen consumption, and 
life quality scores 
41 . </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The functional capacity of children and young adults 
with isolated congenital AV block and right ventricular 
pacing was satisfactory and compatible with their clinical 
evaluation. However, the walk test failed to identify 
individuals with worse cardiac function and morphology 
outcomes or factors associated with poor outcome. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We would like to thank Adriana Yun Huang, Marianna 
Sobral Lacerda and Marina Bertelli Rossi for their help in 
performing the walking tests and Associação para Estudo e 
Desenvolvimento da Eletroterapia Cardíaca. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>Conception and design of the research and Analysis and 
interpretation of the data: Oliveira Júnior RM, Silva KR, Costa R; 
Acquisition of data: Oliveira Júnior RM; Statistical analysis: Alves 
LBO; Obtaining financing: Costa R; Writing of the manuscript: </p>



<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Oliveira Júnior et al. 
Functional capacity in congenital AV block subjects </p>

<p>Arq Bras Cardiol. 2015; 104(1):67-77 </p>



<p>Potential Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was 
reported. </p>

<p>Sources of Funding </p>

<p>There were no external funding sources for this study. </p>

<p>Study Association </p>

<p>This article is part of the thesis of Doctoral submitted by 
Roberto Márcio de Oliveira Júnior, from Universidade de 
São Paulo. </p>



<p>Original Article </p>





</text></tei>