<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4537151" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Clinical guidelines, prediction tools, and computerized decision support (CDS) are 
underutilized outside of research contexts, and conventional teaching of evidence-based practice (EBP) skills 
fails to change practitioner behavior. Overcoming these challenges requires traversing practice, policy, and 
implementation domains. In this article, we describe a program's conceptual design, the results of institutional 
participation, and the program's evolution. Next steps include integration of instruction in principles of CDS. </p>

<p>Conceptual Model: Teaching Evidence Assimilation for Collaborative Health Care (TEACH) is a 
multidisciplinary annual conference series involving on-and off-site trainings and facilitation within health 
care provider organizations (HPOs). Separate conference tracks address clinical policy and guideline 
development, implementation science, and foundational EBP skills. The implementation track uses a model 
encompassing problem delineation, identifying knowing-doing gaps, synthesizing evidence to address those 
gaps, adapting guidelines for local use, assessing implementation barriers, measuring outcomes, and sustaining 
evidence use. Training in CDS principles is an anticipated component within this track. Within participating 
organizations, the program engages senior administration, middle management, and frontline care providers. 
On-site care improvement projects serve as vehicles for developing ongoing, sustainable capabilities. TEACH 
facilitators conduct on-site workshops to enhance project development, integration of stakeholder 
engagement and decision support. Both on-and off-site components emphasize narrative skills and shared 
decision-making. </p>

<p>Experience: Since 2009, 430 participants attended TEACH conferences. Delegations from five centers 
attended an initial series of three conferences. Improvement projects centered on stroke care, hospital 
readmissions, and infection control. Successful implementation efforts were characterized by strong support 
of senior administration, involvement of a broad multidisciplinary constituency within the organization, and 
on-site facilitation on the part of TEACH faculty. Involvement of nursing management at the senior faculty 
level led to increased presence of nursing and other disciplines at subsequent conferences. </p>

<p>Conclusions: A multidisciplinary and multifaceted approach to on-and off-site training and facilitation may 
lead to enhanced use of research to improve the quality of care within HPOs. Such training may provide 
valuable contextual grounding for effective use of CDS within such organizations. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Funding for the TEACH conference was made possible in part by Grant # 5R13HS018607 from the Agency 
for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ). The following individuals contributed substantially to the 
TEACH project: Saadia Akhtar, MD, Mt. Sinai Beth Israel Medical Center, Icahn School of Medicine, NY; 
Barnet Eskin, MD, PhD, Morristown Medical Center, NJ; Ian Graham, PhD, University of Ottawa, Canada; 
Judy Honig, EdD, DNP, Columbia University School of Nursing, NY; T.J. Jirasevijinda, MD, Weill Cornell 
Medical College, NY; Barbara Lock, MD, Columbia University Medical Center, NY; Pattie Mongelis, MLS, 
New York City; Patricia Quinlan, RN, DScN, Hospital for Special Surgery, NY; Dorice Vieira, MLS, MPH, NY 
University Langone Medical Center, NY; and Arlene Smaldone, RN, PhD, Columbia University School of 
Nursing, NY. </p>

<p>This model/framework is available at EDM Forum Community: http://repository.academyhealth.org/egems/vol3/iss2/7 </p>

<p>Keywords </p>

<p>Learning health care system; evidence based medicine; decision support </p>

<p>Disciplines </p>

<p>Education | Medicine and Health Sciences </p>

<p>Creative Commons License </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No Derivative Works 3.0 
License. </p>

<p>Authors </p>

<p>Peter C Wyer, Columbia University Medical Center; Craig A Umscheid, Center for Evidence-based Practice and 
Department of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA; Stewart Wright, Department of Emergency 
Medicine University of Cincinnati, OH; Suzana A Silva, Amil Assistência Medica Internacional / Instituto Nacional 
de Cardiologia, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil; Eddy Lang, Department of Emergency Medicine, Cumming School of 
Medicine Alberta Health Services, Calgary Zone, CA. </p>

<p>This model/framework is available at EDM Forum Community: http://repository.academyhealth.org/egems/vol3/iss2/7 </p>

<p>Teaching Evidence Assimilation for Collaborative 
Health Care (TEACH) 2009-2014: Building 
Evidence-Based Capacity within Health Care 
Provider Organizations </p>

<p>Peter C. Wyer, MD; </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>Craig A. Umscheid, MD, MSCE; </p>

<p>ii </p>

<p>Stewart Wright, MD, MEd; </p>

<p>iii </p>

<p>Suzana A. Silva, MD, PhD; </p>

<p>iv </p>

<p>Eddy Lang MD </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>Columbia University Medical Center, 
ii Center for Evidence-based Practice and Department of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, 
iii Department 
of Emergency Medicine, University of Cincinnati, 
iv Amil Assistência Medica Internacional/Instituto Nacional de Cardiologia, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>Department of Emergency Medicine, Cumming School of Medicine Alberta Health Services, Calgary Zone, Canada </p>

<p>Background: Clinical guidelines, prediction tools, and computerized decision support (CDS) are 
underutilized outside of research contexts, and conventional teaching of evidence-based practice (EBP) 
skills fails to change practitioner behavior. Overcoming these challenges requires traversing practice, 
policy, and implementation domains. In this article, we describe a program's conceptual design, the 
results of institutional participation, and the program's evolution. Next steps include integration of 
instruction in principles of CDS. </p>

<p>Conceptual Model: Teaching Evidence Assimilation for Collaborative Health Care (TEACH) is a 
multidisciplinary annual conference series involving on-and off-site trainings and facilitation within 
health care provider organizations (HPOs). Separate conference tracks address clinical policy and 
guideline development, implementation science, and foundational EBP skills. The implementation 
track uses a model encompassing problem delineation, identifying knowing-doing gaps, synthesizing 
evidence to address those gaps, adapting guidelines for local use, assessing implementation barriers, 
measuring outcomes, and sustaining evidence use. Training in CDS principles is an anticipated 
component within this track. Within participating organizations, the program engages senior 
administration, middle management, and frontline care providers. On-site care improvement projects 
serve as vehicles for developing ongoing, sustainable capabilities. TEACH facilitators conduct on-site 
workshops to enhance project development, integration of stakeholder engagement and decision 
support. Both on-and off-site components emphasize narrative skills and shared decision-making. </p>

<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Generating Evidence &amp; Methods 
to improve patient outcomes </p>

<p>eGEMs </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Wyer et al.: Teaching Evidence Assimilation </p>

<p>Published by EDM Forum Community, 2015 </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>The failure of efforts in evidence-based health 
care (EBHC) to verifiably inform clinical practice 
has become more conspicuous, even as the 
methodological rigor and sophistication of 
epidemiological and research tools and instruments 
have advanced. Clinical guidelines continue to be 
ignored, </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>and decision support instruments are 
inconsistently utilized. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Abundant literature attests 
to the failure of conventional, practitioner-based, 
educational efforts to change behavior. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Finally, a 
landmark study </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>showed that, despite richness of 
technology and resources within the United States 
health care system, only half of Americans receive 
evidence-based interventions for common and 
important health conditions. </p>

<p>In 2009, concerned about these failures, educators 
at the New York Academy of Medicine expanded a 
previously existing workshop to address capacity 
building needs within health care organizations. </p>

<p>"Teaching Evidence Assimilation for Collaborative 
Health Care (TEACH)" incorporates training in 
skill areas beyond critical appraisal of published 
research, including those required to develop clinical 
policies and guidelines as well as their successful 
implementation within organized care settings. In 
developing the TEACH design we were influenced 
by literature addressing the fragmentation of 
conventional training in EBHC as an underlying 
cause for lack of uptake of research in practice. 
Specifically, David Eddy had warned that the 
teaching of evidence-based medicine (EBM) was 
being confined to the context of health care delivery 
to individual patients, while evidence-based clinical 
guidelines and implementation skills were being 
ignored. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Recently, a review of the status of medical 
education in the United States commissioned by the 
Carnegie Foundation determined that instruction in 
quality improvement and multidisciplinary, systems-
based health care constitutes a major deficiency 
at both undergraduate and graduate levels. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>We </p>

<p>Experience: 
attended an initial series of three conferences. Improvement projects centered on stroke care, hospital 
readmissions, and infection control. Successful implementation efforts were characterized by strong 
support of senior administration, involvement of a broad multidisciplinary constituency within the 
organization, and on-site facilitation on the part of TEACH faculty. Involvement of nursing management 
at the senior faculty level led to increased presence of nursing and other disciplines at subsequent 
conferences. </p>

<p>Conclusions: A multidisciplinary and multifaceted approach to on-and off-site training and facilitation 
may lead to enhanced use of research to improve the quality of care within HPOs. Such training may 
provide valuable contextual grounding for effective use of CDS within such organizations. </p>

<p>CONT'D </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>eGEMs (Generating Evidence &amp; Methods to improve patient outcomes), Vol. 3 [2015], Iss. 2, Art. 7 </p>

<p>http://repository.academyhealth.org/egems/vol3/iss2/7 
DOI: 10.13063/2327-9214.1165 </p>

<p>Volume 3 (2015) Issue Number 2 </p>

<p>concluded that an adequate approach to education 
and training in EBHC would require attention to 
at least three dimensions: clinical guidelines and 
policies, systems level implementation, and delivery 
of health services to individual patients. </p>

<p>Efforts to integrate training across the dimensions 
of EBHC have been sparse. Wahabi et al. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>linked 
conventional instruction in EBM to a capacity 
building program for public health project 
development in rural Saudi Arabia. Wright et 
al. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>described a multidisciplinary, emergency 
department based program combining evidence-
based training and literature review with a team-
based approach to improvement in specific clinical 
areas. An innovative workshop in Rio de Janeiro 
engages health care managers, policymakers, and 
clinicians in a multidisciplinary setting, </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>and has 
more recently incorporated guideline development 
and implementation into the scope of training. 
However, training programs in evidence-based 
practice continue to focus largely upon clinicians 
and clinical educators and the skill sets applicable to 
individual patient care. </p>

<p>10,11 </p>

<p>In this article, we describe the conceptual design 
of the TEACH program, our program experience to 
date including results of institutional participation, 
and its evolution. In the context of future directions 
for the program, we also address the process of 
integrating instruction in principles of computerized 
decision support (CDS) into the TEACH program 
and preliminary steps in that direction. </p>

<p>Conceptual Design of the TEACH Program </p>

<p>TEACH was initiated in 2009 at the New York 
Academy of Medicine (NYAM) as an annual 
conference series linked to on-site facilitation and 
educational efforts for interested institutional 
subscribers. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>The three-day conferences combine 
plenary sessions with workshop-style small group 
learning. A three-level design corresponds to three </p>

<p>broadly defined dimensions of EBHC, i.e., basic 
skills and delivery of services to individual patients 
(Level 1), development of clinical policies and 
recommendations (Level 2), and implementation of 
evidence-based clinical policies in specific clinical 
settings (Level 3). These conform to three critically 
important domains activity within health care 
provider organizations (HPOs). Within this design we 
consider that a common skill set is carried through 
the successive levels in a fashion that reflects 
greater complexity of application. The sections 
that follow describe the learning objectives, target 
audience, and the content and structure of the 
TEACH conferences and workshops, as well as other 
features of the TEACH program. </p>

<p>Learning Objectives </p>

<p>The global objective of TEACH is to facilitate 
the acquisition of knowledge and skills needed 
to maximize the use of research within HPOs. 
Participants attending Level 1 are expected to 
acquire a basic familiarity with the basic knowledge 
and skills that pertain to assembling, appraising, 
and applying evidence from research to specific 
problems and information needs. They also gain 
insight with respect to use of these skills in the care 
of individual patients. Level 2 participants learn to 
apply the same skills in a more advanced framework, 
that of performing evidence-based reviews as well 
as developing and adapting clinical policies and 
guidelines within an HPO. Level 3 attendees are 
introduced to principles of evidence-based practice 
on a systems level, encompassing implementation 
science and knowledge translation. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Target Audience </p>

<p>We market TEACH conferences to a broad range 
of health care specialties and disciplines including 
professionals in training, together with those who 
are highly experienced. Most attendees are directly 
involved with the delivery of health care within </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Wyer et al.: Teaching Evidence Assimilation </p>

<p>Published by EDM Forum Community, 2015 </p>

<p>HPOs. The TEACH workshop also provides a training 
ground for librarians, who account for 5-10 percent 
of attendees. Attendees may enroll as individuals 
or come as part of HPO delegations. Small groups 
of 8-10 participants are constituted to maximize 
interdisciplinary sharing of perspectives. Small 
group facilitators are similarly assigned so as to 
complement the diversity of participants. </p>

<p>Content and Structure of the TEACH Conferences </p>

<p>The conference design revolves around the 
notion that multiple dimensions of health care 
delivery are necessary to the objectives of EBHC, 
and that, to be successful, capacity building 
efforts must address these. Table 1 summarizes 
the three-level design, skill content, and specific 
learning objectives of the TEACH conferences and 
workshops. The foundations of evidence-based 
care track offers a practice-based approach to 
evidence-based practice that emphasizes relational 
over epidemiological principles. </p>

<p>14,15 </p>

<p>It embraces a 
broader framework of research than conventional 
EBM. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Level 2 initially concentrated on the Grading 
Recommendations Assessment, Development 
and Recommendations (GRADE) system </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>and 
currently embraces broader issues of development 
of clinical policies and recommendations within 
HPOs. Level 3 uses the knowledge-to-action (K2A) 
model </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>as a conceptual framework. The K2A model </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>encompasses the steps summarized in the Level 3 
learning objectives in Table 1. TEACH participants 
attend all plenary sessions, but attend only one 
track and corresponding small group during a 
given conference. Members of HPO delegations are 
encouraged to distribute themselves throughout the 
different workshop tracks. </p>

<p>The SIMPLE Website </p>

<p>The TEACH program developed and uses the 
Scientifically Informed Medical Practice and 
Learning (SIMPLE) website (Figure 1). The password 
protected site is also used at workshops at McMaster 
University and in connection with a workshop series 
in Rio de Janeiro. The SIMPLE format accommodates 
multiple tracks including preparatory readings 
and assignments, interactive exercises, and other 
interactive features specific to small groups and 
parallel learning tracks. Conference participants have 
access to all materials. "Sharing point," an interactive 
feature, provides a living electronic environment 
that enhances the small group process. It allows 
small group members to communicate with each 
other and their facilitator both before and during the 
workshop as well as to upload files. </p>

<p>Beyond the Conferences: On-Site Facilitation </p>

<p>The TEACH program offers facilitation of the 
development of evidence-based improvement 
projects to participating HPOs. Such projects involve 
organized team efforts within those institutions and 
the utilization of knowledge and skills introduced 
in the annual workshop. TEACH facilitation </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>takes 
different forms with different HPOs. A customized 
plan is worked out with HPO leadership prior to their 
initial conference attendance. Facilitation ranges 
from ongoing participation in a project team, to one 
or more site visits over a one-or two-year period. 
In some cases TEACH faculty have designed and 
led customized on-site educational programs that 
complement or supplement the conference content. 
In others, they have served as project consultants. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>eGEMs (Generating Evidence &amp; Methods to improve patient outcomes), Vol. 3 [2015], Iss. 2, Art. 7 </p>

<p>http://repository.academyhealth.org/egems/vol3/iss2/7 
DOI: 10.13063/2327-9214.1165 </p>

<p>Volume 3 (2015) Issue Number 2 </p>

<p>Note: *Grading Recommendations Assessment, Development and Recommendations (GRADE) </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Table 1. TEACH Conference Framework </p>

<p>LEVEL 
TITLE 
CONTENT 
LEARNING OBJECTIVES </p>

<p>1 
Foundations of 
evidence-based 
care </p>

<p>Basic evidence literacy 
skills, </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>narrative 
principles. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Defining problems and 
formulating questions. </p>

<p>Finding relevant research. </p>

<p>Appraising the applicability, 
practical importance and 
quality of research. </p>

<p>2 
Clinical policies, 
guidelines, 
and the GRADE 
system* </p>

<p>Developing rapid 
reviews </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>and 
recommendations to 
serve policy and practice 
needs within organized 
health care settings. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Use of the GRADE* 
system and the 
<rs type="software">GRADEpro</rs> software for 
evidence synthesis. </p>

<p>Performing systematic reviews, 
including rapid reviews, on well-
defined health care questions. </p>

<p>Applying the GRADE* system 
for evidence summaries. </p>

<p>Finding and selecting 
guidelines relevant to a health 
care problem. </p>

<p>Appraising the quality of 
guidelines </p>

<p>Adapting guidelines for local 
use. </p>

<p>3 
Implementing 
evidence-based 
care </p>

<p>Use of the knowledge-
to-action (K2A) 
framework to 
guide sustainable 
implementation of 
evidence-based clinical 
policies. </p>

<p>Identifying clinical problems 
conducive to knowledge 
translation methods. </p>

<p>Applying the principles of 
knowledge translation and the 
K2A cycle to implementation of 
evidence-based policies. </p>

<p>Using EBHC skills to inform 
the process of implementing 
policies. </p>

<p>Defining and measuring 
outcomes of implementation of 
clinical policies. </p>



<p>Wyer et al.: Teaching Evidence Assimilation </p>

<p>Published by EDM Forum Community, 2015 </p>

<p>Experience with the TEACH Framework </p>

<p>From 2009 to 2014, 430 participants took the 
three-day TEACH course at NYAM. The breakdown 
of attendees by discipline evolved across the six-
year period (Table 2). In 2009, 65/81 (80 percent) 
of attendees were physicians and physicians in 
training. During the first three years (2009-2011) </p>

<p>physicians and physician trainees accounted for 
163/230 (72 percent) of all participants. There was 
a modest shift toward increased nursing and allied 
profession participation in the third year (43/81 
= 54 percent physician and physician trainees). 
Nonetheless, after three years, we perceived the 
need to enhance multidisciplinary participation. 
We augmented our faculty to include facilitators 
with nursing backgrounds in all Level 1 and Level 3 
tracks and added plenary speakers from nursing </p>

<p>Figure 1. Home Page of the Website Developed to Facilitate the TEACH Program </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>eGEMs (Generating Evidence &amp; Methods to improve patient outcomes), Vol. 3 [2015], Iss. 2, Art. 7 </p>

<p>http://repository.academyhealth.org/egems/vol3/iss2/7 
DOI: 10.13063/2327-9214.1165 </p>

<p>Volume 3 (2015) Issue Number 2 </p>

<p>management and implementation. Facilitator 
teams currently include a physician, a nurse, and a 
librarian. We also intensified our promotion to and 
recruitment from allied health professions. By 2014, 
30/79 (38 percent) of total attendees came from a 
nursing background. Physicians attending clinically 
related tracks accounted for 15/79 (19 percent) of 
attendance, while 26/79 (33 percent) were made 
up of health professionals engaged in administrative 
and policy roles. </p>

<p>Results of Institutional Participation </p>

<p>Although we originally intended to assess gains 
in knowledge and skills related to EBHC among 
conference attendees, this proved impractical for 
several reasons. Validated instruments relevant to all 
of the TEACH domains did not exist. Furthermore, 
conference attendees are already asked to do 
preliminary readings and other preparatory work. 
Increasing the time burden with cognitive testing 
during the preconference period seemed unwise. 
We therefore concentrated evaluation efforts on 
the use of EBHC knowledge and skill by institutional 
participants to achieve tangible improvements </p>

<p>in care. Between 25 and 40 percent of TEACH 
participants stem from institutional delegations. In 
some cases, these participants were clustered into 
a single workshop group and used a project drawn 
from their specific institutional interests and needs 
as the learning vehicle. In other cases, delegations 
were distributed over the different workshop tracks 
in order to obtain the broadest possible experience 
of the conference. </p>

<p>Table 3 lists institutional participants by institution 
type, change agent and project leadership profiles 
and the nature of projects worked on for a 
representative sample. Table 4 summarizes the six 
participating institutions for which outcome data 
is available. We followed the latter for at least one 
year following their participation to determine the 
extent to which projects were carried through to 
implementation. Although quantitative outcomes 
were rarely available, one HPO sent delegations 
of participants to the TEACH conference over a 
three-year period resulting in a program to decrease 
heart failure readmissions and reported a 17 percent 
drop in readmissions during the first year of 
implementation. </p>

<p>Table 2. Distribution of TEACH Conference Attendees across the Tracks, 2009-2014 </p>

<p>YEAR </p>

<p>TRACK 1 
(NUMBER OF 
PARTICIPANTS) </p>

<p>TRACK 2 
(NUMBER OF PARTICIPANTS) 
TRACK 3 
(NUMBER OF 
PARTICIPANTS) </p>

<p>TOTAL 
(NUMBER OF 
PARTICIPANTS) 
POLICIES/ 
RECOMMENDATIONS 
GRADE </p>

<p>2009 
40 
-
15 
26 
81 </p>

<p>2010 
29 
-
11 
28 
68 </p>

<p>2011 
31 
-
15 
35 
81 </p>

<p>2012 
20 
6 
8 
16 
50 </p>

<p>2013 
20 
10 
25 
16 
71 </p>

<p>2014 
22 
14 
19 
24 
79 </p>

<p>TOTAL 
162 
30 
93 
145 
430 </p>



<p>Wyer et al.: Teaching Evidence Assimilation </p>

<p>Published by EDM Forum Community, 2015 </p>

<p>Table 3. Characteristics of Institutional Subscribers to the TEACH Program and Evidence-Based 
Projects Developed 2009-2014 </p>

<p>INSTITUTION LOCATION 
TYPE 
CHANGE 
AGENTS </p>

<p>PROJECT 
LEADERSHIP 
PROJECTS 
OUTCOME </p>

<p>1 
N e w Y o r k 
City (NYC) </p>

<p>Community 
hospital 
adjunct to 
academic 
center </p>

<p>Senior 
administration, 
clinical 
leadership </p>

<p>Clinical 
leadership </p>

<p>Reducing 
hospital 
readmission 
for patients 
admitted for 
acute heart 
failure </p>

<p>Reduced 
heart failure 
readmissions 
during first 
year of 
implementation </p>

<p>2 
E a s t e r n 
Canada </p>

<p>Community-
based 
academic 
affiliate </p>

<p>Emergency 
physician 
trained in 
evidence-
based practice 
and quality 
improvement 
(QI) </p>

<p>Varied 
• Pediatric 
diabetes care 
• Pediatric 
sepsis 
• Misc. 
emergency 
care 
protocols </p>

<p>Protocols 
developed and 
disseminated </p>

<p>3 
Midwest 
Hospital 
network 
linked to 
academic 
center </p>

<p>Emergency 
physician </p>

<p>Network QI 
director </p>

<p>• Imaging for 
acute stroke 
• Extending 
thrombolytic 
therapy to 
rural stroke 
victims </p>

<p>Protocols 
developed and 
disseminated </p>

<p>4 
Midwest 
Hospital 
network 
linked to 
academic 
center </p>

<p>Emergency 
physician </p>

<p>Network QI 
director </p>

<p>CAUTI* 
Protocols 
developed and 
disseminated </p>

<p>5 
Philadelphia Academic 
medical 
center and 
affiliate </p>

<p>Nursing clinical 
specialists </p>

<p>Nursing 
clinical 
specialists </p>

<p>CAUTI* </p>

<p>• Enhanced 
Magnet*** 
qualifications </p>

<p>Protocols 
developed </p>

<p>6 
NYC 
Community 
teaching 
hospital </p>

<p>Hospital 
administration </p>

<p>Poorly 
wdefined </p>

<p>Sepsis care 
Protocols 
developed </p>

<p>7 
NYC 
Ambulatory 
home care 
network </p>

<p>Senior 
administration </p>

<p>Various 
• Falls 
• Hospital 
readmissions 
• Patient 
satisfaction 
• Magnet 
designation </p>

<p>NA** </p>

<p>Notes: *Catheter associated urinary tract infections (CAUTI) 
**Newly initiated participation, no outcomes available </p>

<p>EBCP is a requirement for this award </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>eGEMs (Generating Evidence &amp; Methods to improve patient outcomes), Vol. 3 [2015], Iss. 2, Art. 7 </p>

<p>http://repository.academyhealth.org/egems/vol3/iss2/7 
DOI: 10.13063/2327-9214.1165 </p>

<p>Volume 3 (2015) Issue Number 2 </p>

<p>Several potential insights emerging from the TEACH 
program experience with HPOs might be of use to 
others attempting to link conference and workshop 
training in EBHC to on-site improvement projects. 
Specifically, results seemed particularly impressive 
when the change agent reflected a partnership 
between senior administration, middle management, 
and clinical providers, and when the change agent 
and leadership had prior training in evidence-
based practice. Results were less impressive when 
the change agent and leadership reflected limited 
roles and interests within the institution. Table 4 
broadly suggests a qualitative relationship between 
the degree of project success and the intensity of 
facilitation efforts. Potential reasons for failure of 
project development included lack of leadership, 
isolated leadership vulnerable to replacement, 
and the inability to define and efficiently monitor 
appropriate metrics over time through the use of 
information technology (IT) and electronic medical 
record data. </p>

<p>Evolution of the TEACH Conference Design-The 
Role of Computerized Decision Support (CDS) </p>

<p>Lessons learned and insights gained since the 
TEACH program began have led to important 
design changes. Bringing three dimensions into 
a workshop framework otherwise modeled on 
traditional EBM approaches </p>

<p>10,11 </p>

<p>did not in itself prove 
adequate to achieving a fully integrated learning 
environment. Several approaches to enhancing 
such integration were also ineffective. For example, 
wrap-up summaries by attendees from different 
tracks of their activities during the workshop proved 
distracting and inconsistently engaging. Similarly, 
a seminar framework in which TEACH faculty 
presented track-specific content to participants 
in different tracks resulted in negative participant 
feedback. Maximizing use of the interactive website 
during the preparation period, using the opening 
plenary session to set the stage for the workshop 
experience as a whole, and selecting plenary 
sessions to bring forward issues pertaining to the </p>

<p>Table 4. Types of Facilitation within Institutions Subscribing to the TEACH Program </p>

<p>INSTITUTION 
TYPES OF FACILITATION </p>

<p>1 
On-site course extending TEACH conference participation. </p>

<p>Ongoing process facilitation by TEACH core faculty member. </p>

<p>2 
Site visits by TEACH faculty with lecture and consultative meetings. </p>

<p>Ongoing process facilitation by TEACH core faculty member. </p>

<p>3 
Site visits by TEACH faculty with lecture and consultative meetings. </p>

<p>Ongoing process and content facilitation by TEACH faculty liaison. </p>

<p>4 
Site visits by TEACH faculty with lecture and consultative meetings. </p>

<p>5 
On-site facilitation by core TEACH faculty. </p>

<p>6 
No facilitation beyond TEACH attendance. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Wyer et al.: Teaching Evidence Assimilation </p>

<p>Published by EDM Forum Community, 2015 </p>

<p>different tracks in a way that is of interest to all 
participants have proved more promising. </p>

<p>The TEACH conference design has undergone 
several broad changes. We expanded Level 2 
through the addition of a track aimed at developing 
clinical policies and guidelines within health care 
organizations. The track is staffed by faculty from 
an established hospital evidence-based practice 
center. </p>

<p>19,20 </p>

<p>Its addition rendered the guidelines and 
recommendations track relevant to institutional 
participants. The recruitment for this track further 
enhanced multidisciplinary participation, which in 
turn serves to align the TEACH environment with the 
principles of team-based health care. </p>

<p>From the outset, the TEACH program has 
emphasized principles of narrative medicine, </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>storytelling, and the relational dimension of health 
care. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Initially, a narrative medicine pioneer took 
active part in the conferences, including delivering 
plenary presentations. Although many participants 
were enthusiastic, others failed to recognize the 
relevance of these presentations. We therefore 
revised the approach by dedicating half of the 
plenary time on day 2 to a special integrated session 
addressing issues to do with patient-centered health 
care in a way that is relevant to all dimensions of the 
conference. </p>

<p>As the TEACH program has matured, the era of 
the electronic health record (EHR) and the role of 
CDS has come into its own. Although the advent 
of the EHR-and health IT in general-has brought 
great promise, </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>important risks and barriers to 
uptake are also visible. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Furthermore, CDS remains 
underutilized </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>even though some recent efforts 
report success. </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Clearly, the interface between 
clinical evidence, evidence-informed clinical 
policies and guidelines, and the delivery of care to 
individual patients is going to be more and more 
an electronic one. Hence, models for profiling and </p>

<p>responding to user attitudes and experiences have 
become essential components of a structured 
approach to implementing clinical policies </p>

<p>25,26 </p>

<p>and 
have also begun to be incorporated into knowledge 
translation texts. </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>Accordingly, we plan to augment 
the Level 3 implementation track of the TEACH 
program by incorporating principles of IT and 
CDS into the learning objectives in the context of 
knowledge translation and implementation skills. 
The TEACH environment should provide a valuable 
learning context around acquisition of principles of 
CDS and IT. </p>

<p>Strengths, Weaknesses, Future 
Perspectives </p>

<p>The TEACH framework offers an environment in 
which learners from HPO's can gain knowledge 
and skills pertaining to multiple dimensions of 
EBHC. It provides all participants with access to 
internationally recognized innovators in three major 
dimensions of EBHC, as well as intensive tutelage in 
a preferred learning area. The structure of TEACH 
reflects the complexity inherent in maximizing 
the contribution of information from research to 
the quality of health services. This opportunity-
combined with the multidisciplinary, team-based 
makeup of the tracks and small groups and the 
inclusion of front line health care professionals 
alongside administrators and policymakers-
generates a compelling learning environment. Over 
time, organizations-including guideline committees 
from medical specialty societies-have assigned 
participants to attend multiple tracks within the 
conference, maximizing their ability to absorb the 
key skill sets that characterize the different domains. </p>

<p>A potential limitation of TEACH is the fact that it 
is pitched to the needs of moderate-size HPO's. 
Hence, it may be perceived to have less appeal 
to practitioners within a small or solo practice 
environment than to those within large integrated </p>



<p>eGEMs (Generating Evidence &amp; Methods to improve patient outcomes), Vol. 3 [2015], Iss. 2, Art. 7 </p>

<p>http://repository.academyhealth.org/egems/vol3/iss2/7 
DOI: 10.13063/2327-9214.1165 </p>

<p>Volume 3 (2015) Issue Number 2 </p>

<p>delivery systems. The former's contexts may prevent 
their directly absorbing the range of knowledge, 
skills, and activities embodied within the TEACH 
program. The latter characteristically have their 
own differentiated frameworks for realizing 
evidence-based care. However, the TEACH program 
has something to offer virtually any health care 
professional likely to enroll in it. Many health care 
professionals enroll as individuals and are able 
to increase knowledge and skills they would be 
exposed to in conventional evidence-based training 
programs, but within a broader framework of 
application. </p>

<p>TEACH is to be distinguished from other training 
efforts that have encompassed multiple EBHC skill 
areas. One such effort offered tracks in different 
areas related to EBHC, including the GRADE system, 
knowledge translation, and the conducting of 
systematic reviews. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>However, the program was not 
generated by a unified concept of organizational 
capacity building and did not address the needs 
of delegations from HPOs. We believe that TEACH 
is unique among training programs in EBHC in 
its systematic identification and incorporation of 
distinct but essential domains of knowledge, skill, 
and proficiency. Traditional EBM workshops, largely 
following the McMaster University model, focus on 
critical appraisal skills framed within the context of 
the care of individual patients. </p>

<p>10,11 </p>

<p>Additionally, the 
Institute for Healthcare Improvement (IHI) conducts 
seminars for delegations from provider organizations 
focused on training in quality improvement skills, 
while the intensive training programs offered 
by Intermountain Healthcare focus more on the 
organizational level, also from a quality improvement 
standpoint. Although quality improvement efforts 
share goals with those of knowledge translation 
and the K2A model, they also have differences. </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>Otherwise, the IHI program only marginally overlaps 
the content of training in EBHC. </p>

<p>From the standpoint of cost, the three-day TEACH 
conference compares favorably with other EBHC 
training programs and is priced in the lower range 
of such workshops. It operates on a breakeven basis 
within the host institution that provides section 
discounts on facilities for internally sponsored 
events. This allows the offering of tuition discounts 
for students and group rates for participating 
institutions. Additional fees are required for on-
site courses and other facilitation efforts. One 
institution estimated the total cost of participation 
over a three-year period to be $100,000, of 
which $10,000 comprised the cost of conference 
attendance for approximately 20 individuals, and 
the remainder reflected costs of personnel time-
including conference attendance and on-site time 
requirements-and the salary of an additional full-
time on-site nurse coordinator who was hired as 
part of an implementation plan to decrease hospital 
readmissions. </p>

<p>Effectiveness of the TEACH framework is limited 
by resource constraints within participating 
institutions. For example, the ability to collect, mine, 
and interpret practice-based evidence drawn from 
EHR data is rapidly becoming a critically important 
dimension of EBHC. </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Many smaller HPOs are still 
in the early stages of developing such capacity. We 
have observed that the lack of those capabilities 
frequently disables the ability to create verifiable and 
sustainable improvements within project frameworks 
arising from institutional participation in TEACH. 
Longer-term outcome information on TEACH related 
projects has proved to be elusive. Furthermore 
we have not been able to relate actual increases 
in knowledge and skill on the part of conference 
participants to demonstrable increases in capacity 
for EBHC within participating institutions. Lack of 
validated assessment tools across the full range 
of required skills </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>renders this an objective that 
will require longer range development. We believe </p>



<p>Wyer et al.: Teaching Evidence Assimilation </p>

<p>Published by EDM Forum Community, 2015 </p>

<p>that we have demonstrated that it is possible for 
an EBHC training program operating within the 
scale of conventional EBM workshops to address a 
minimum range of skill domains required to increase 
the use of research within organized health care 
settings. An integrated learning environment for 
EBHC may provide a context within which principles 
of CDS may be absorbed in a fashion that increases 
utilization and effectiveness. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Funding for the TEACH conference was made 
possible in part by Grant # 5R13HS018607 from 
the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality 
(AHRQ). </p>

<p>The following individuals contributed substantially to 
the TEACH project: Saadia Akhtar, MD, Mt. Sinai Beth 
Israel Medical Center, Icahn School of Medicine, NY; 
Barnet Eskin, MD, PhD, Morristown Medical Center, 
NJ; Ian Graham, PhD, University of Ottawa, Canada; 
Judy Honig, EdD, DNP, Columbia University School 
of Nursing, NY; T.J. Jirasevijinda, MD, Weill Cornell 
Medical College, NY; Barbara Lock, MD, Columbia 
University Medical Center, NY; Pattie Mongelis, MLS, 
New York City; Patricia Quinlan, RN, DScN, Hospital 
for Special Surgery, NY; Dorice Vieira, MLS, MPH, NY 
University Langone Medical Center, NY; and Arlene 
Smaldone, RN, PhD, Columbia University School of 
Nursing, NY. </p>





<p>eGEMs (Generating Evidence &amp; Methods to improve patient outcomes), Vol. 3 [2015], Iss. 2, Art. 7 </p>

<p>http://repository.academyhealth.org/egems/vol3/iss2/7 
DOI: 10.13063/2327-9214.1165 </p>





<p>Wyer et al.: Teaching Evidence Assimilation </p>

<p>Published by EDM Forum Community, 2015 </p>

</text></tei>