<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4583605" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Context: The optimal duration of dual anti-platelet therapy (DAPT) after the implantation of drug-eluting coronary stents (DES) is still the 
subject of ongoing debate. This meta-analysis was performed to investigate the optimal duration between ≤ 6 months and ≥ 12 months for 
DAPT after implantation of DES. 
Evidence Acquisition: This study was conducted at the department of cardiology, the first college of clinical medical sciences, institute 
of cardiovascular diseases of Three Gorges university during December 2014. Pub-med, Cochrane, Scopus and clinicaltrials.gov databases 
were searched for papers published until December 2014. Searches of the above databases included terms "dual anti-platelet therapy" and 
"myocardial infarction (MI)" and "drug-eluting stents (DES)". All the searched literatures were limited to Randomized Controlled Trials 
(RCTs). Quality assessments were evaluated with the Jadad quality scale. Data were extracted by two independent observers (FZ and YC). For 
all analyses, the 95% confidence interval (CI) was calculated and heterogeneity of the studies was analyzed using I2 statistics. 
Results: Five RCTs with 9979 participants satisfying the inclusion criteria were finally analyzed. Overall, there were 4993 patients with 
shorter duration of DAPT and 4986 patients with a longer treatment. Clopidogrel was the used P2Y12 receptor inhibitor in all five RCTs. On 
one hand compared to shorter duration (≤ 12 months) DAPT, longer duration (≥ 12 months) did not reduce risk of mortality, cardiac death, 
cerebrovascular accidents, myocardial infarction and stent thrombosis (pooled OR 1.03, 95% Confidence Interval (CI) 0.80 -1.32, P = 0.85, I 2 
= 0%; pooled OR 0.91, 95% CI 0.64 -1.29, P = 0.60, I 2 = 0%; pooled OR 0.84, 95% CI 0.50 -1.42, P = 0.51, I 2 = 0%; pooled OR 1.17, 95% CI 0.87 -1.58, P = 
0.29, I 2 = 0%; pooled OR 1.36, 95% CI 0.81 -2.29, P = 0.24, I 2 = 0%). On the other hand, longer duration (≥ 12 months) could also increase the risk 
of thrombolysis in myocardial infarction (TIMI) major bleeding (pooled OR 0.50, 95% CI 0.29 -0.85, P = 0.01, I 2 = 0%). 
Conclusions: Regarding the efficacy outcomes of the patients after DES implantation, no differences were found between shorter (≤ 6 
months) and longer (≥ 12 months) duration of DAPT. What is worse is that longer duration (≥ 12 months) was associated with increased 
risk of bleeding complications. </p>

<p>Dual anti-platelet therapy (DAPT), which was defined 
as the use of a P2Y12 receptor inhibitor (clopidogrel (1), 
ticagrelor (2) or prasugrel (3)) and aspirin, is an impor-
tant clinical treatment strategy for patients after im-
plantation of drug eluting stents (DES) (4, 5). Current 
clinical guidelines recommend 12 months of DAPT in 
patients after implantation of DES, who are not at a high 
risk of bleeding, and suggest that early discontinuation 
of DAPT may result in stent thrombosis (4). However, 
considering the potential for TIMI major bleeding, the 
continuation of DAPT after DES implantation remains 
unclear (6-9). During the American Heart Association 
2014 (AHA2014), many clinical trials (dual anti-platelet 
therapy (DAPT)) (10), intracoronary stenting and anti-
thrombotic regimen: safety and efficacy of 6 months 
dual antiplatelet therapy after drug-eluting stenting </p>

<p>(ISAR-SAFE) (11) and is there a life for des after discon-
tinuation of clopidogrel (ITALIC) (12)) about the opti-
mal continuation time of DAPT after DES implantation 
were announced. However, the outcomes of these three 
clinical studies were different. Briefly, the outcomes 
from DAPT indicated that DAPT beyond one year after 
placement of DES could significantly reduce the risks of 
stent thrombosis, cerebrovascular events and major ad-
verse cardiovascular, though with an increased risk of 
TIMI major bleeding. Conversely, patients assigned six 
months of DAPT had similar net clinical outcomes com-
pared with patients assigned 12 months of DAPT after 
percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) with a DES, 
according to new data from the ISAR-SAFE study. At the 
same time, the ITALIC trial showed that rates of bleed-
ing and of thrombotic events were not significantly </p>

<p>Yang J et al. </p>

<p>Iran Red Crescent Med J. 2015;17(7):e26904 </p>

<p>
different for the six-month versus 24-month long DAPT 
after PCI with new generation DES in good aspirin re-
sponders. All in all, the optimal duration of DAPT after 
DES implantation remains uncertain until now. Here, 
a meta-analysis was performed to investigate the opti-
mal duration, between ≤ 6 months and ≥ 12 months, for 
DAPT after implantation of DES. </p>

<p>2. Evidence Acquisition </p>

<p>A meta-analysis of available published researches about 
intervention of DAPT after DES implantation was per-
formed. During December 2014, a literature search was 
conducted at the department of cardiology, the first col-
lege of clinical medical sciences, Institute of cardiovas-
cular diseases, China, Three Gorges university. Articles, 
which had been published before December 2014 were 
preselected. </p>

<p>2.1. Literature Search Strategy </p>

<p>To identify all prospective randomized controlled trials 
(RCTs) of DAPT after DES implantation, we systematically 
searched the literature through the Pub-med, Scopus, Co-
chrane and clinicaltrials.gov databases. Searches of the 
above database included the following phrases, "dual 
anti-platelet therapy" and "Myocardial Infarction (MI)" 
and "drug-eluting stents (DES)." The search was filtered 
to show only English articles and was limited to clinical 
trials. The steps of the literature search process are sum-
marized in Figure 1. </p>

<p>2.2. Criterions of Inclusion and Exclusion </p>

<p>The inclusion criteria were as follows: 1) random-
ized clinical trial, 2) patients with implantation of DES 
older than 18 years 3) DAPT ≤ 6 months OR ≥ 12 months, 
4) DAPT used were aspirin and clopidogrel, 5) English 
language studies. We excluded trails that did not re-
port any of the outcomes mentioned above and articles 
without the data available. </p>

<p>223 potentially relevant references identified and 
screened for relieved from electronic search </p>

<p>214 excluded based on 
title and abstract </p>

<p>4 excluded 
Not RCT (2=01) 
No available data (n=1) 
No ≤6 months DAPT data(n=1) </p>

<p>9 references retrieved for full text review </p>

<p>5 ECTs eligible randomized controlled trials included in the meta analysis </p>

<p>Figure 1. Flow Diagram of the Study Selection Process in the Meta-Analysis </p>

<p>2.3. Data Collection Process </p>

<p>The identification of titles and abstracts and extract-
ing of data were independently screened by two re-
viewers (FZ and YC). The corresponding author (YJ) 
was responsible for the potential of disagreement and 
discordance between the two reviewers. Quality as-
sessments were evaluated with the Jadad quality scale 
(a numerical score between zero and seven, with zero 
being the weakest and seven being the strongest), in-
cluding the following: 1) double blinding, 2) allocation 
concealment, 3) random sequence generation and 4) 
description of withdrawals and drop-outs. </p>

<p>2.4. Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>All statistical analyses were performed using the Rev-
Man <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0</rs> software, provided by the Cochrane Collabora-
tion. The effect measure of odds ratio (OR) with 95% Confi-
dence Interval (CI) and the statistical method of random 
effects were used. Heterogeneity was assessed using I 2 
statistics and the statistical significance was set at 0.05. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Included Clinical Trials </p>

<p>There were 223 relevant reports identified by the 
search; nine full text articles were retrieved for de-
tailed evaluation. In total, five RCTs enrolling 9,979 
participants (4,993 patients were with shorter duration 
of DAPT and 4,986 patients with a longer treatment) 
satisfying the inclusion criteria were finally analyzed. 
Figure 1 shows the flow diagram of the study selection 
process in the meta-analysis. According to the Jadad 
quality scale, all included trials were of general quality 
(the score was five), as indicated by Table 1. All five RCTs 
were published between 2012 and 2014 and all the five 
RCTs were open-label yet not double blind, which may 
bias the results. </p>

<p>3.2. Characteristics of the Included Clinical Trials </p>

<p>The baseline characteristics of patients in both ≤ 6 
months and ≥ 12 months groups were similar (charac-
teristics of the clinical trials are shown in Table 2). Fe-
males were under-represented compared to males in 
all trials (about 30%). Participants in all five RCTs had a 
mean age of 63 years and there were about 49% acute 
coronary syndromes (ACS) patients in this meta-analy-
sis. The mean duration of the shorter duration group 
was 4.8 months while for the longer duration group 
this was 17 months. </p>

<p>3.3. The Results of Data Analysis </p>

<p>All the five RCTs had a good homogeneity, thus this 
meta-analysis used a fixed effects model. All causes 
of death, MI, cardiac death, cerebrovascular accident, 
stent thrombosis and major bleeding were assessed </p>

<p>Yang J et al. </p>



<p>Iran Red Crescent Med J. 2015;17(7):e26904 </p>

<p>Table 1. Summary of Quality Evaluation by the Jadad Scale for Clinical Trials of Dual Anti-Platelet Therapy After Drug Eluting Stents 
Implantation </p>

<p>Trials 
Random Sequence 
Generation </p>

<p>Allocation 
Concealment </p>

<p>Double Blinding 
Description of 
Withdrawals and Drop-Out </p>

<p>Score </p>

<p>Excellent (13) 2012 
2 
1 
1 
1 
5 </p>

<p>Prodigy (14) 2012 
2 
1 
1 
1 
5 </p>

<p>Reset (15) 2012 
2 
1 
1 
1 
5 </p>

<p>Optimize (16) 2013 
2 
1 
1 
1 
5 </p>

<p>Italic (12) 2014 
2 
1 
1 
1 
5 </p>

<p>Table 2. Characteristics of the Included Clinical Trials a,b </p>

<p>Clinical Trials Excellent (13) 2012 
Prodigy (14) 2012 
Reset (15) 2012 
Optimize (16) 2013 
Italic (12) 2014 </p>

<p>Group 
Shorter 
(n = 722) 
Longer (n 
= 721) 
Shorter 
(n = 737) 
Longer 
(n = 741) 
Shorter 
(n = 1059) 
Longer 
(n = 1058) 
Shorter 
(n = 1563) 
Longer 
(n = 1556) 
Shorter 
(n = 910) 
Longer 
(n = 912) </p>

<p>Identifier NO. 
NCT00698607 
NCT00611286 
NCT01145079 
NCT01113372 
NCT 01476020 </p>

<p>Female b 
34.9 
36.1 
24.0 
22.6 
35.6 
37.1 
36.5 
36.9 
19.2 
20.8 </p>

<p>Age, y 
63.0 
62.4 
67.9 
67.8 
62.4 
62.4 
61.3 
61.9 
61.7 
61.5 </p>

<p>ACS b 
51.1 
52.0 
73.5 
73.3 
55.5 
53.7 
31.6 
32.3 
43.4 
43.5 </p>

<p>Sent type 
Sirolimus Everoli-
mus 
Paclitaxel Everoli-
mus Zotarolimus 
Sirolimus Everolimus 
Zotarolimus 
Zotarolimus 
Xience V </p>

<p>Duration of 
DAPT, months 
6 
12 
6 
24 
3 
12 
3 
12 
6 
24 </p>

<p>Intervention 
12 month aspirin or 
clopidogrel versus 3 
month aspirin and 
clopidogrel </p>

<p>24 month aspirin or 
clopidogrel versus 6 
month aspirin and 
clopidogrel </p>

<p>12 month aspirin or 
clopidogrel versus 3 
month aspirin and 
clopidogrel </p>

<p>12 month aspirin or 
clopidogrel versus 3 
month aspirin and 
clopidogrel </p>

<p>24 month aspirin 
or clopidogrel ver-
sus 6 month aspirin 
and clopidogrel </p>

<p>Primary end 
point 
Composite of all 
cause death, MI, 
stroke, or major 
bleeding </p>

<p>Composite of all 
cause death, MI, 
stroke, or major 
bleeding </p>

<p>Composite of all 
cause death, MI, 
stroke, or major 
bleeding </p>

<p>Composite of all 
cause death, MI, 
stroke, or major 
bleeding </p>

<p>Composite of all 
cause death, MI, 
stroke, or major 
bleeding </p>

<p>a Abbreviations: ACS, acute coronary syndromes; DAPT, Dual Anti-Platelet Therapy; MI, myocardial infarction. 
b Values are presented as %. </p>

<p>in this meta-analysis. Longer duration of therapy (≥ 12 
months) did not reduce the risk of mortality, including, 
all causes of death, cardiac death, cerebrovascular ac-
cidents, myocardial infarction and stent thrombosis 
(pooled OR 1.03, 95% CI 0.80 -1.32, P = 0.85, I 2 = 0%, Figure 
2 A; pooled OR 0.91, 95% CI 0.64 -1.29, P = 0.60, I 2 = 0%, 
Figure 2 B; pooled OR 0.84, 95% CI 0.50 -1.42, P = 0.51, I 2 = 
0% , Figure 2 C; pooled OR 1.17, 95% CI 0.87 -1.58, P = 0.29, 
I 2 = 0%, Figure 2 D; pooled OR 1.36, 95% CI 0.81 -2.29, P = 
0.24, I 2 = 0%, Figure 2 E). Longer duration (≥ 12 months) </p>

<p>increased the risk of TIMI major bleeding (pooled OR 
0.50, 95% CI 0.29 -0.85, P = 0.01, I 2 = 0%; Figure 3). The 
total events of primary end points of DAPT after DES im-
plantation are summarized in Table 3. </p>

<p>3.4. Evaluation for Publication Bias </p>

<p>Considering all the five RCTs, the funnel plot of all 
causes of mortality was symmetrical (Figure 4), which in-
dicates that publication bias is low. </p>

<p>Yang J et al. </p>

<p>Iran Red Crescent Med J. 2015;17(7):e26904 </p>

<p>
Figure 2. Effect of Long and Short Duration of Therapy on the Risk of Death Caused by Cardiac Arrest, Cerebrovascular Accidents, Myocardial Infarction, </p>

<p>Stent Thrombosis and Other Causes of Death </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>Pooled OR 1.03, 95% CI 0.80 -1.32, P = 0.85, I 2 = 0%, A; pooled OR 0.91, 95% CI 0.64 -1.29, P = 0.60, I 2 = 0%, B; pooled OR 0.84, 95% CI 0.50 -1.42, P = 0.51, I 2 = 0%, 
C; pooled OR 1.17, 95% CI 0.87 -1.58, P = 0.29, I 2 = 0%, D; pooled OR 1.36, 95% CI 0.81 -2.29, P = 0.24, I 2 = 0%, E. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Longer Duration (≥ 12 Months) Could Increase the Risk of thrombolysis in myocardial infarction (TIMI) Major Bleeding </p>

<p>Pooled OR 0.50, 95% CI 0.29 -0.85, P = 0.01, I 2 = 0%. </p>

<p>Yang J et al. </p>



<p>Iran Red Crescent Med J. 2015;17(7):e26904 </p>

<p>Table 3. Summary of Primary End Points of Clinical Trials of Dual Anti-Platelet Therapy After Drug Eluting Stents Implantation </p>

<p>Primary end Points 
Shorter, ≤ 6 mo, (n = 
4993) </p>

<p>Longer, ≥ 12 mo, (n = 
4986) </p>

<p>OR 
P Value </p>

<p>All causes of mortality 
125 
122 
1.03 (0.80, 1.32) 
0.85 </p>

<p>Cardiac death 
63 
69 
0.91 (0.64, 1.29) 
0.60 </p>

<p>Cerebrovascular 
26 
31 
0.84 (0.50, 1.42) 
0.51 </p>

<p>MI 
96 
82 
1.17 (0.87, 1.58) 
0.29 </p>

<p>Stent thrombosis 
34 
25 
1.36 (0.81, 2.29) 
0.24 </p>

<p>TIMI major bleeding 
20 
40 
0.50 (0.29, 0.85) 
0.01 </p>

<p>SE(log[OR]) 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 
0.01 
0.1 
1 
10 
100 </p>

<p>OR </p>

<p>Figure 4. The Funnel Plot for All Causes of Mortality </p>

<p>4. Conclusions </p>

<p>Current clinical guidelines recommend 12 months of 
DAPT following implantation of DES (4, 9, 17, 18). However, 
the optimal duration of DAPT after implantation of DES re-
mains undetermined. Recently, some RCTs have compared 
the different outcomes between shorter and longer dura-
tion of DAPT after DES implantation (10-12). However, the 
outcomes are still the subject of ongoing debate (19). 
During the AHA2014, many clinical trials (DAPT, ISAR-
SAFE and ITALIC) about the optimal duration of DAPT 
after DES implantation were announced. However, the 
outcomes from these three clinical studies were differ-
ent. Briefly, the outcomes from DAPT indicated that 
DAPT beyond one year after placement of a DES sig-
nificantly reduced the risks of cerebrovascular events, 
stent thrombosis and major adverse cardiovascular, 
though with an increased risk of TIMI major bleeding. 
Conversely, patients assigned to six months of DAPT 
had similar net clinical outcomes compared with pa-
tients assigned to 12 months of DAPT after PCI with a 
DES, according to new data from the ISAR-SAFE study. 
At the same time, the ITALIC trial showed that rates of 
bleeding and of thrombotic events were not signifi-
cantly different for the 6-versus 24-month DAPT pro-
gram after PCI with new generation DES in good aspirin 
responders. 
Here, a meta-analysis was performed to investigate </p>

<p>the different outcomes between ≤ 6 months and ≥ 12 
months DAPT after DES. Our findings were in agreement 
with previous publications (7-9). However, it also had some 
differences with previous reports. The biggest difference 
was that we included the latest clinical study (ITALIC). Sim-
ilarly, the latest published meta-analysis, (6) carried out by 
Elmariah et al. (6) identified 14 eligible trials (but without 
ITALIC) that randomly assigned 69644 participants to dif-
ferent durations of DAPT. The outcomes indicated that 
compared with aspirin alone or short duration of DAPT, 
continued treatment was not associated with a difference 
in all causes of mortality, cardiovascular and non-cardio-
vascular mortality. Thus, compared to the meta-analysis 
of Elmariah et al. (6) our meta-analysis only analyzed the 
shorter (≤ 6 months) and longer (≥ 12 months) dura-
tion of DAPT without comparing aspirin alone. However, 
the outcomes of our meta-analysis were also in agreement 
with this meta-analysis. In other words, the findings of our 
meta-analysis suggested that to stabilize coronary athero-
sclerotic heart disease (CAD) patients, the duration of ≤ 
6 months and ≥ 12 months may be equally effective yet 
the longer duration was associated with increased risk of 
bleeding. 
Of course, this meta-analysis also had some limitations; 
there was no patient level data and the five RCIs were not 
double blinded. Besides, different stent types were used 
in these five different studies (Table 2), which may also 
affect the outcome. Third, the only used P2Y12 receptor 
inhibitor in this meta-analysis was clopidogrel. The other 
inhibitors, ticagrelor and prasugrel, were not included in 
the analysis. Last but not least, the five studies had a low 
event rate, and ITALIC was prematurely terminated due 
to problems with recruitment, which would influence 
the quality of the clinical trials. 
The optimal duration for DAPT after the implantation 
of DES is still undetermined. In clinical practice, the 
treatment plan of DAPT on different patients should be 
based on the individual's specific circumstances. For 
example, patients with a history or other risk factors 
for bleeding may be suitable for shortened period of 
DAPT. While, patients with a higher risk of thrombotic 
events (for example, with a variety of ischemic disease 
or multiple risk factors) should be on extended treat-
ment. This meta-analysis was only an investigation in 
this area and the results may be more appropriately ap-</p>

<p>Yang J et al. </p>

<p>Iran Red Crescent Med J. 2015;17(7):e26904 </p>

<p>
plied to stable CAD patients. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors wish to offer their special thanks to Dr. Jun 
Yang, Dean of the Department of Cardiology, for his guid-
ance and financial supports. </p>

<p>Authors' Contributions </p>

<p>The identification of titles and abstracts and extract-
ing of data were independently screened by Zhi-Xing Fan 
and Chao-Jun Yang. Hui-Bo Wang was responsible for the 
potential of disagreement and discordance between Zhi-
Xing Fan and Chao-Jun Yang. The corresponding author, 
Jian Yang, contributed to the development of the proto-
col and prepared the manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding/Support </p>

<p>This work was supported by the National Natural Sci-
ence Foundation of China (Grant No. 81200088 and 
81470387), the Natural Science Foundation of Yichang city 
(Grant No. A12301-01) and the Hubei Province Outstand-
ing Medical Academic Leader Program of China. </p>



</text></tei>