<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4582561" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Salivary analysis can be used to assess the severity of caries. Of the known salivary proteins, a paucity of information exists concerning the 
role of proteinase 3 (PR3), a serine protease of the chymotrypsin family, in dental caries. Whole, unstimulated saliva was collected from 
children with varying degrees of active caries and tested using a Human Protease Array Kit and an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. 
A significantly decreased concentration of salivary PR3 was noted with increasing severity of dental caries (P,0.01); a positive correlation 
(r50.87; P,0.01; Pearson's correlation analysis) was also observed between salivary pH and PR3 concentration. In an antibacterial test, 
a PR3 concentration of 250 ng?mL 21 or higher significantly inhibited Streptococcus mutans UA159 growth after 12 h of incubation 
(P,0.05). These studies indicate that PR3 is a salivary factor associated with the severity of dental caries, as suggested by the negative 
relationship between salivary PR3 concentration and the severity of caries as well as the susceptibility of S. mutans to PR3. 
Nevertheless, this does not preclude other proteases from associations 
with caries, including another significant oral protease, proteinase 3 
(PR3). A serine protease of the chymotrypsin family, PR3 is stored in 
the primary granules of polymorphonuclear neutrophils (PMNs) and 
is implicated in a variety of infectious inflammatory diseases, such as 
lung disease, as well as non-infectious inflammatory processes such as 
glomerulonephritis, arthritis and bullous pemphigoid. 15-19 However, 
the role of PR3 in cariology is presently unknown. 
The aim of the present study, therefore, was to investigate the 
association of salivary proteases with caries in Chengdu, China, par-
ticularly in 6-year-old children with differing degrees of dental 
caries. More specifically, we analysed the role of PR3 in dental caries 
and its effect on Streptococcus mutans, a component of the normal 
flora of the human mouth that is commonly associated with 
dental caries. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Ethics statement 
All human saliva samples were collected from 6-year-old children 
attending Yong'an kindergarten in Chengdu, China, under the 
approved guidelines of Sichuan University, China. Written informed 
consent for children who participated in the experimental investiga-
tion was obtained from their guardians. The study and consent pro-
cedures were approved by the Ethics Committees of West China 
Hospital of Stomatology and State Key Laboratory of Oral Diseases, 
both of Sichuan University, China. </p>

<p>OPEN </p>

<p>State Key Laboratory of Oral Diseases, West China Hospital of Stomatology, Sichuan University, Chengdu, China 
Correspondence: Professor XD Zhou, State Key Laboratory of Oral Diseases, West China Hospital of Stomatology, Sichuan University, No. 14, Section 3, Renmin South Road, 
Chengdu 610041, China 
E-mail: zhouxd@scu.edu.cn 
Professor P Zhang, State Key Laboratory of Oral Diseases, West China Hospital of Stomatology, Sichuan University, No. 14, Section 3, Renmin South Road, Chengdu 610041, 
China 
E-mail: pingzhang68@hotmail.com 
Accepted 1 April 2015 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science (2015) 7, 174-178 
ß 2015 WCSS. All rights reserved 1674-2818/15 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/ijos </p>

<p>Data and sample collection 
A total of 128 healthy children with and without caries, from Yong'an 
kindergarten, were included in this study. Each child was examined 
under natural light with the aid of a dental mirror and probe. World 
Health Organization (WHO) diagnostic criteria were used in deter-
mining decayed (non-cavitated or cavitated lesions), missing teeth 
(due to caries) and filled teeth (DMFT/deft) indices. 
Children were divided into three groups according to the severity of 
dental caries: 8 no dental caries (NDC) group, consisting of 46 children; 
low dental caries (LDC) group with a DMFT/deft of 1-4, consisting of 
49 children; and high dental caries (HDC) group with a DMFT/deft of 
5-15, consisting of 33 children. 
All subjects were instructed to refrain from eating and drinking for 
12 h prior to saliva collection and to brush their teeth in the morning. 
Up to 5 mL of fasting, unstimulated, whole saliva was collected 
between 8:00 and 10:00. 
After collection, the saliva specimens were kept on ice and imme-
diately taken to the laboratory. Samples were centrifuged at 1000g 
for 2 min, and the supernatants were stored at 280 6 C until use. </p>

<p>Protease array and image analysis 
In this study, 1 mL of donor saliva supernatant from each participant 
in the NDC group and 1 mL of donor saliva supernatant from each 
participant in the HDC group were tested using a Human Protease 
Array Kit (R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA), which measures 
the relative protein expression of 34 human proteases (each protease 
contains a pair of pot in one membrane). For image analysis, X-ray 
film was scanned with a CanoScan LiDE 700F (Canon, Beijing, China) 
and analysed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">ImageJ</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">National Institutes of Health</rs>, Bethesda, 
MD, USA). </p>

<p>PR3 concentration assay 
Salivary PR3 concentrations in all the 128 donors were measured using 
an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) kit (Cloud-Clone C, 
Wuhan, China). The product of the PR3 concentration was analysed 
spectrophotometrically at a wavelength of 450 nm. The results were 
analysed using a Varioskan Flash Multimode Reader (Thermo 
Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). </p>

<p>Measurement of pH 
The pH of each saliva sample was tested using a SevenEasy S20 pH 
meter (Shanghai Joystech Environmental Protection Technology, 
Shanghai, China). </p>

<p>Antibacterial test 
Human PR3 (Cloud-Clone, Wuhan, China) was purchased. A freshly 
prepared microbial (Streptococcus mutans UA159) suspension (diluted 
to an optical density (OD) value of 0.2) and brain-heart infusion (BHI) 
medium were pipetted into a 96-well microtiter plate (20 mL microbial 
suspension and 80 mL BHI medium per well). To a plate with eight rows, 
sterile phosphate buffer solution (PBS) was added to the first row 
(100 mL per well) as the control. Two-fold serial dilutions of PR3 
solution were then made, with concentrations ranging from 2 000 to 
31.5 ng?mL 21 ; then, these dilutions were added to the remaining seven 
rows. Each mixed solution used in the bacterial test contained 20 mL 
bacterial suspension, 80 mL BHI medium and 100 mL PR3 (or PBS 
control) solution per well. A final concentration range of PR3 from 
15.75 to 1 000 ng?mL 21 was used. Each plate was incubated at 37 6 C 
for 24 h, after which the OD value of each mixed solution was measured </p>

<p>at 600 nm every 3 h using a Varioskan Flash Multimode Reader. Three 
replicates were used in the test. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS19.0 software (SPSS, 
Chicago, IL, USA). Numerical data are presented as the mean 6 
standard deviation (SD). The difference between the means was ana-
lysed by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). Differences were 
considered significant when P,0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
The state of caries at Yong'an kindergarten is presented in Table 1. The 
mean prevalence of caries in subjects was 64.06%. The mean DMFT/ 
dmft for the total group was 2.3962.89, with females showing signifi-
cantly lower values than males (P50.19). The mean DMFT/dmft for 
the LDC and HDC groups was 1.9810.83 and 6.3312.76, respectively, 
and the difference between these groups was significant (P,0.01). 
The protease array results suggested that the pixel density of MMP-
8 for the NDC group was significantly lower than that for the HDC 
group (Figure 1; P,0.01). In contrast, the pixel density of PR3 for the 
NDC group was significantly higher than that for the HDC group 
(Figure 1; P,0.01). 
We next measured the PR3 concentration between the three groups 
(NDC, LDC, HDC) and found them to be significantly different 
(P50.009; an overall P value). Compared to the mean concentration 
of PR3 for the NDC group (17.8267.31) ng?mL 21 , those for the LDC 
group (12.7966.19) ng?mL 21 and HDC group (11.0767.10) ng?mL 21 
were significant lower (Figure 2a; P50.02 and P50.003, respectively, vs. 
NDC group). However, we did not find a significant difference between 
the LDC and HDC groups (Figure 2a; P50.434), based on the mean 
PR3 concentration. Between the genders (male (14.6366.69) ng?mL 21 ; 
female (13.5268.52) ng?mL 21 , we found no significant difference 
(P50.574) in the concentration of PR3 (Figure 2b). There was also 
no significant overall difference (P50.13) in the mean pH values of 
saliva from the three groups (Figure 2c; NDC group, pH=7.1360.23, 
n546; LDC group, pH=7.0260.30, n549; HDC group, pH= 
6.9660.25, n533). No significant difference (P50.23) was observed 
between the pH values of saliva from males and females (results not 
shown). However, there was a positive correlation between saliva pH 
and PR3 concentration (Figure 2d; r50.87; P,0.01; Pearson's correla-
tion analysis). 
With regard to the susceptibility of S. mutans to PR3, there was no 
significant difference (P.0.05) in OD values between any groups with 
a PR3 concentration between 15.75 and 125 ng?mL 21 after 24 h of 
incubation (results not shown). However, when the concentration of 
PR3 was increased to 250 ng?mL 21 or above, a significant difference in 
OD values of S. mutans was noted after 12 h of incubation onwards 
(Figure 3; P,0.05). </p>

<p>Table 1 Caries in children from Yong'an kindergarten </p>

<p>Gender/ 
group </p>

<p>Number of 
subjects </p>

<p>DMFT/dmft 
mean value </p>

<p>Caries 
Prevalence/% </p>

<p>Total 
DMFT/dmft </p>

<p>Male 
68 
2.6763.27 
63.24 
184 
Female 
60 
2.0062.35 
65.00 
122 
NDC 
46 
0 
0 
0 
LDC 
49 
1.9860.83 
100 
209 
HDC 
33 
6.3362.76 
100 
97 
Total 
128 
2.3962.89 
64.06 
306 </p>

<p>DMFT, decayed,missing and filled teeth; HDC, high dental caries; LDC, low dental 
caries; NDC, no dental caries. </p>

<p>Role of saliva PR3 in dental caries 
TY Yang et al 
175 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>MMP-8 </p>

<p>60 000 </p>

<p>40 000 </p>

<p>NDC </p>

<p>HDC </p>

<p>20 000 
Mean pixel density </p>

<p>0 
MMP-8 
MMP-8 
PR3 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>PR3 </p>

<p>PR3 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Protease array. (a) Human protease array membrane for one saliva supernatant sample from the NDC group. (b) Human protease array membrane for one 
saliva supernatant sample from the HDC group. (c) Mean pixel density of MMP-8 and PR3. The pixel density of MMP-8 in the NDC group (Figure 1a, n51) was lower 
than that in the HDC group (Figure 1b, n51). The pixel density of PR3 in the NDC group was significantly higher than that in the HDC group. **P,0.01 as determined 
by one-way ANOVA, followed by a post-hoc Tukey's test. ANOVA, analysis of variance; HDC, high dental caries; MMP, metalloproteinase; NDC, no dental caries; PR3, 
proteinase 3. </p>

<p>30 
* </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>8.5 </p>

<p>8.0 </p>

<p>7.5 </p>

<p>7.0 </p>

<p>6.5 </p>

<p>6.0 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 
pH values 
pH values </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Concentration/(ng·mL -1 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c 
d </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>NDC 
HDC 
LDC </p>

<p>NDC 
HDC 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>PR3 concentration/(ng·mL -1 ) </p>

<p>30 
40 
50 
LDC </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Concentration/(ng·mL -1 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Males 
Females </p>

<p>Figure 2 PR3 concentration and pH of saliva from different severities of dental caries. (a) PR3 concentration in different severities of dental caries. The mean PR3 
concentration in the LDC group (12.7966.19) ng?mL 21 and HDC group (11.0767.10) ng . mL 21 was significantly lower than that in the NDC group (17.8267.31) 
ng . mL 21 as measured by ELISA. *P,0.05 and **P,0.01 as determined by one-way ANOVA, followed by a post-hoc Tukey's test. (b) Concentration of PR3 in 
males and females. No significant difference (P50.574) in PR3 concentration was observed between males and females. (c) Saliva pH in different severities of 
dental caries. There was no significant overall difference (P50.13) in the mean pH values of saliva from the three groups (NDC group, pH=7.1360.23, n546; 
LDC group, pH=7.0260.30, n549; HDC group, pH56.9660.25, n533). (d) The correlation between PR3 and pH. There was a positive correlation (r50.87; 
P,0.01; Pearson's correlation analysis) between salivary pH values and PR3 concentration. ELISA, enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay; HDC, high dental 
caries; LDC, low dental caries; NDC, no dental caries; PR3, proteinase 3. </p>

<p>Role of saliva PR3 in dental caries 
TY Yang et al 
176 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Human saliva contains a large array of proteases that have important 
biological functions. 1 Examining the differences in protease levels under 
different physiological conditions or pathologic states, using a new 
approach, may help us to better assess oral and systemic diseases. 1,9 
We found the total mean DMFT/dmft value in our study was 
2.3962.89, indicating a low-level caries severity according to WHO 
standards. 20 The prevalence of caries in our study was 64.06%, similar 
to a report from the Namakkal District in India; 21 however, the pre-
valence of caries in England, Finland and the USA is lower, at 4%, 6% 
and 20.2%, respectively, than in our study. 22 These results highlight 
the overwhelming need for oral health education among pre-school 
children to be taken seriously by both parents and kindergartens, 
especially in outlying, poverty-stricken areas. 23-24 As a result, the 
development and implementation of oral health promotion strategies 
is highly recommended. 21,25 
The protease array results suggested that the level of MMP-8 within 
saliva samples from subjects with caries was higher than that in sub-
jects without caries. This finding is consistent with previous studies, 
which indicated that the presence of caries correlates strongly with 
salivary levels of MMP-8. 26 It has been reported that MMPs play an 
important role in dental caries pathogenesis because collagen degra-
dation is thought to be initiated by MMPs. 14,27 However, the levels of 
salivary PR3 and other proteases in caries were noted to be lower in a 
caries-free environment, and an explanation for this observation has 
been lacking to date. 
The known biological functions of PR3 include the following: 
degradation of extracellular matrix (ECM) components; 28 cleavage 
of inflammatory mediators; 29 platelet activation; 30 induction of endo-
thelial cell apoptosis; 31 negative feedback regulation of granulopoiesis; 32 
and the target of auto-antibodies in Wegener's granulomatosis. 33 
Previous studies have not described any known relationship 
between PR3 and dental caries. As shown with ELISA, we found 
that children who were caries-resistant, whether they were male or 
female, demonstrated higher PR3 concentrations in their saliva; 
conversely, the more serious the caries, the lower the concentration 
of PR3. This suggests that PR3 may act as a protease factor in the 
severity of dental caries, with low levels leading to a greater severity 
of caries. Thus, analysis of PR3 levels may help to assess the severity 
of caries. </p>

<p>The pH of whole saliva was also measured in this study. Caries-free 
children produced saliva with a slightly higher pH level than children 
with severe dental caries. In support of this finding, a report by Kuriakose 
et al. 34 showed that the pH of saliva from children who suffered from 
rampant dental caries was significantly lower than that from children 
who were caries resistant. In our study, however, no significant overall 
difference was observed after comparing the three groups of differing 
severities of dental caries. This result suggests that using salivary pH on 
its own may not be useful for evaluating the severity of dental caries and 
that salivary pH should be considered in conjunction with dental plaque 
or other components in the oral cavity. 35-36 
It has been reported that the optimal pH for PR3 activity is 8.0. 15,37 
In our study, a significantly positive correlation was shown between 
PR3 concentration and pH, with higher pH leading to increased PR3 
concentration. In the oral cavity, an alkaline environment may be 
more conducive to enzyme activity by PR3 or other proteases. 15 
The bactericidal mechanism of PR3 was also studied. 38-39 Previous 
findings indicated that PR3 has an extracellular, microbicidal role in 
neutrophil extracellular traps. 39 PR3 can also process human cathe-
licidin (hCAP-18) to generate the potent, antibacterial 4.5 kDa pep-
tide LL-37. 40 Some reports have even suggested that PR3 can defend 
against fungal infections. 41 However, the role of PR3 in cariology is 
presently unknown. Our data confirm that S. mutans, part of the oral 
flora associated with dental caries, are also susceptible to PR3. This 
susceptibility may be mediated by a bacteriostatic effect or an effect on 
bacterial growth. When the concentration of PR3 was increased to 
250 ng?mL 21 or above, bacterial growth was significantly inhibited 
after 12 h of incubation. However, the PR3 concentration in the oral 
cavity is approximately 3-30 ng?mL 21 ; thus, further study is required 
to determine whether the PR3 concentration can reach 250 ng?mL 21 
or above in the human oral cavity. Thus, additional studies are 
required to explore the physiological significance of the concentra-
tion of PR3 required to inhibit bacterial growth and to determine 
whether PR3 can be used as a preventive measure for dental caries in 
clinical trials. 
In conclusion, our analyses utilizing protease arrays and ELISAs 
indicate that the protease PR3 is associated with the severity of dental 
caries, with low levels being associated with a greater severity of caries. 
Moreover, our antibacterial test results showed that S. mutans is sus-
ceptible to PR3. </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 
OD values </p>

<p>0.0 
0 
3 
6 
9 </p>

<p>Time/h </p>

<p>12 15 18 21 24 27 30 </p>

<p>0 ng·mL -1 
250 ng·mL -1 </p>

<p>500 ng·mL -1 
1 000 ng·mL -1 </p>

<p>Figure 3 Antibacterial properties of PR3 towards S. mutans. The OD of mixed solutions of differing PR3 concentrations and S. mutans (0, 250, 500 and 
1 000 ng?mL 21 ) was measured every 3 h for 24 h. There was a significant difference (P,0.05; one-way ANOVA, followed by a post-hoc Tukey's test) in OD values 
between the groups after 12 h of incubation. Compared with the control group (0 ng?mL 21 ), the higher the concentration of PR3, the lower the OD values of S. mutans. 
OD, optical density; PR3, proteinase 3. </p>

<p>Role of saliva PR3 in dental caries 
TY Yang et al 
177 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </p>

<p>The authors acknowledge the support of the National Natural Science 
Foundation of China (No. 81372892), Sichuan Province Science and 
Technology Innovation Team Program (JCPT 2011-9). </p>



<p>This license allows readers to copy, distribute and transmit the Contribution 
as long as it is attributed back to the author. Readers may not alter, transform 
or build upon the Contribution, or use the article for commercial purposes. Please read the 
full license for further details at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>Role of saliva PR3 in dental caries 
TY Yang et al </p>

<p>
International Journal of Oral Science </p>

</text></tei>