<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4216798" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: EGFR expression and pathway activation are common in triple-negative breast 
cancer (TNBC). However, anti-EGFR therapies have not been effective in these patients. We 
aimed to study the efficacy of targeting MET in overcoming resistance to EGFR therapy in TNBC 
cell lines. 
Methods: TNBC lines (MDA-MB-468, HCC-1395, and MDA-MB-231), and a hormone recep-
tor-positive breast cancer line (T47D) were stimulated with epidermal growth factor (EGF) and 
hepatocyte growth factor (HGF). Lines were then treated with different concentrations of EGFR 
inhibitors (gefitinib or cetuximab), with or without a MET tyrosine kinase inhibitor (EMD 
1214063). Proliferation was measured by MTS assay, in soft agar and with a matrigel assay. Synergy 
was measured with Calcusyn. Protein expression and signaling were examined with immunob-
lotting. 
Results: There was activation of ligand-receptor-downstream signaling pathways in MDA-MB-468 
and HCC-1395 upon stimulation with EGF and HGF. In these cell lines, we observed synergism 
when combining EGFR and MET inhibitors. These results were observed across assays. In western 
blotting, combination therapy resulted in abrogation of pAKT and pMAPK while monotherapy did 
not. 
Conclusion: Our data demonstrate that dual EGFR/MET inhibition is synergistic in TNBC. 
Targeting both EGFR and MET receptors may provide an effective therapeutic strategy in TNBC. </p>

<p>Key words: cMET, EGFR, Therapy resistance, Triple-negative breast cancer </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC) comprises 
15% of breast cancers, and today has the poorest sur-
vival outcome of all breast cancer subtypes. Due to its 
heterogeneity, TNBC lacks validated therapeutic tar-
gets compared with other breast cancer subtypes [1]. 
Several molecular targets including the epidermal 
growth factor receptor (EGFR), the poly ADP ribose </p>

<p>polymerase (PARP), and angiogenesis ligands and 
receptors, are currently under clinical investigation 
for the treatment of this disease [2]. 
In breast cancer, EGFR has been reported to be 
overexpressed in approximately in 50% of TNBC and 
observed to be an independent predictor of poor 
prognosis [3,4]. Genomic amplification of EGFR is </p>

<p>Ivyspring </p>

<p>International Publisher </p>

<p>Journal of Cancer 2014, Vol. 5 </p>

<p>http://www.jcancer.org </p>



<p>also reported in 6% of breast cancers and correlates 
with increased protein expression [5]. However, the 
use of anti-EGFR therapies, either with EGFR catalytic 
domain inhibitors or monoclonal antibodies has not 
proven to be effective in this disease. [6,7]. 
The receptor tyrosine kinase MET acts as an on-
cogene in many human cancers [8]. It is overexpressed 
in 20-30% of breast cancer and seems to be associated 
with a worse prognosis [8-11]. MET amplification and 
overexpression leads to resistance to anti-EGFR ther-
apies in non-small cell lung cancer [12] and contrib-
utes to inefficiency of gefitinib in brain tumors 
through receptor co-activation with EGFR [13]. We 
hypothesized that MET activation contributes to the 
intrinsic resistance to anti-EGFR therapies in TNBC. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Cell lines </p>

<p>TNBC cell lines (MDA-MB-468, HCC-1395, and 
MDA-MB-231) and the hormone receptor positive cell 
line (T47D) were used. Cell lines were obtained from 
MD Anderson Cancer Center (MDACC)'s cell line 
core. Cells were grown in Roswell Park Memorial 
Institute (RPMI)-1640 medium supplemented with 5% 
fetal bovine serum (FBS) and penicillin/streptavidin, 
and maintained at 37°C in a humidified atmosphere at 
5% CO2. </p>

<p>Chemicals </p>

<p>Gefitinib was.purchased from LC laboratories 
(Woburn, MA). EMD 1214063 (MSC2156119J) was 
provided by EMD Serono (Rockland, MA). Both 
drugs were dissolved in DMSO. Cetuximab pur-
chased from ImClone Systems, Inc. (Bridgewater, NJ) 
was provided by the clinical pharmacy at MDACC. 
Compounds were stored as 10mM aliquots at -80°C. 
EGF and HGF were purchased from R&amp;D system 
(Minneapolis, MN). </p>

<p>Cell viability assays </p>

<p>Cells were seeded in 96-well microplates in me-
dium supplemented with 5% FBS and penicil-
lin/streptavidin. The optimal cell number for each cell 
line was determined to ensure that each was in log 
growth phase at the end of the assay (~70% conflu-
ency). Cells were allowed to attach for 24 hours. The 
media was changed to low FBS (2%) and drugs with 
different combinations were added (cetuximab 
200ug/mL, gefitinib 0.25-8 umol/L and EMD 121463 
2-10 umol/L). In terms of determination of drug con-
centration for combination assays, twofold serial di-
lution was conducted for gefitinib and dose was in-
creased by 2 umol/L in EMD 121463 with the upper 
limit of 10 umol/L because of poor solubility. Cells 
were incubated at 37°C for 72 hours. Growth was de-</p>

<p>termined with Cell Titer Blue (Promega, Madison, WI) 
at a 72-hour time point according to the manufactur-
er's instructions. Quantification of fluorescent signal 
intensity was performed using a fluorescent plate 
reader at excitation and emission wavelengths of 
530/604. </p>

<p>Soft agar assay </p>

<p>Cells were suspended in complete RPMI me-
dium containing 0.3% soft agar and seeded in tripli-
cate on 35-mm dishes precoated with 0.6% agar in 
complete growth medium mixed with the corre-
sponding drug and incubated at 37°C, 5% CO 2 . Drug 
concentrations were decided from the results of cell 
viability assay (cetuximab 200ug/mL, gefitinib 0.25-8 
umol/L and EMD 121463 2-10 umol/L). The same 
drug concentration was used both as a single agent 
and in combinations. Medium containing different 
drugs or combinations were added to each well every 
3-4 days. After 10 days, colonies were photographed 
and counted in 10 randomly chosen fields and ex-
pressed as means of triplicates. For staining of the 
colonies, 0.005% crystal violet in 20% methanol solu-
tion was added to the dishes for 30 minutes and 
washed until the background became clear. </p>

<p>Matrigel assay </p>

<p>3D matrices were reconstituted from Matrigel 
(BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA). Thawed 45ul Matrigel 
on ice were placed in each well of a pre-cooled 8-well 
glass chamber slide (BD Falcon, San Jose, CA). After 
30 minutes of solidification, TNBC cell lines and T47D 
mixed in ice-cold medium with 2% Matrigel and 
drugs were loaded in each well of the 8-chamber slide 
and incubated at 37°C. Media with 2% Matrigel and 
drugs were changed every three days. Drug concen-
trations were decided from the results of cell viability 
assay (cetuximab 200ug/mL, gefitinib 0.25-8 umol/L 
and EMD 121463 2-10 umol/L). </p>

<p>Western blot </p>

<p>Cells were starved with RPMI 1640 medium 
overnight and next morning, they were stimulated 
with EGF 20ng/mL and/or recombinant human HGF 
75ng/mL for 10 minutes before cell lysis. Cells were 
lysed in ice-cold X-100 lysis buffer (1% Triton X-100, 
50mM Hepes, pH 7.4, 150mM NaCl, 1.5mM MgCl2, 
1mM EGTA, 10% glycerol, 100mM NaF, 10mM so-
dium pyrophosphate, and 1mM Na3VO4). Before use, 
protease and phosphatase inhibitors (Roche Applied 
Science, Indianapolis, IN) were added. Cell lysates 
were resolved by SDS/PAGE, transferred to Immo-
bilon (polyvinylidene difluoride), and immunoblotted 
with antibodies following the protocols provided by 
the manufacturers. Immunocomplexes were visual-
ized with an enhanced chemiluminescence detection </p>

<p>Journal of Cancer 2014, Vol. 5 </p>

<p>http://www.jcancer.org </p>



<p>kit (Amersham Bioscience, Pittsburgh, PA) using 
horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary anti-
bodies (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). The following anti-
bodies were used for immunoblotting: An-
ti-phospho-Akt (T308, S474), anti-total Akt, an-
ti-EGFR, anti-pEGFR (Y992, Y1068), anti-MET, an-
ti-pMET (Y1235), anti-pMAPK (T202/Y204), anti-pS6 
(S235/236), anti-S6, anti-pSTAT3 (Y1289) were from 
Cell Signaling Technology (Beverly, MA). Anti-total 
Erk was purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnology 
(Santa Cruz, CA) and anti-β actin from Sigma (St. 
Louis, MO). 
Immunocomplexes were visualized with an en-
hanced chemiluminescence detection kit (Amersham 
Biosciences) using horseradish peroxidase-conjugated 
secondary antibodies (Bio-Rad, Herculus, CA). </p>

<p>Antibody arrays </p>

<p>MDA-MB-468 in 100mm dish was harvested as 
described in western blotting and Phospho-Receptor 
Tyrosine Kinase (RTK) antibody arrays (R&amp;D System, 
#ARY-001, Minneapolis, MN) were performed as 
recommended but with 450ug protein lysate per ar-
ray. </p>

<p>DNA transfection </p>

<p>AKT and MEK inserted in pCMV5-expression 
vector with a selection marker of ampicilline 
(100ug/ml) were kindly provided by Dr. Ueno at 
MDACC. DNA was gently diluted (0.01ug/ul) with 
serum free media. Diluted DNA (100ul) was mixed 
with X-tremeGENE DNA transfection reagent (3ul) 
(Roche Applied Science) and incubated for 15 minutes 
at room temperature. These mixtures were added into 
the 60mm dish culturing MDA-MB-468 on day 1 and 
incubated overnight and drugs including gefitinib 
(1uM) and EMD 121463 (5uM) alone or in combina-
tion were treated with serum-free media on day 2. 
Cells were harvested for western blotting after treat-
ment of EGF 20ng/mL and/or recombinant human 
HGF 75ng/mL for 10 minutes before cell lysis. </p>

<p>Statistical Methods </p>

<p>Student's t test was used to compare unpaired 
variables and P&lt;0.05 (2-sided) was considered statis-
tically significant. Synergism for combination thera-
pies was defined using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Calcusyn</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Biosoft</rs>, 
Ferguson, MO) and applied to MTS assays. The frac-
tion of cells affected (Fa) was determined and combi-
nation indices (CI) were produced by the software 
that utilizes the methodology applied by Chou and 
Talalay [14]. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Combination of EGFR and MET inhibition is 
synergistic in triple-negative breast cancer cell 
lines. </p>

<p>To determine the sensitivity of TNBC cell lines 
and T47D to EGFR inhibition, MET inhibition, and 
combined therapy inhibition, breast cancer cell lines 
were treated with gefitinib (0.25-8 umol/L), EMD 
121463 (2-10 umol/L), or both agents given at the 
same concentration in combination for 72 hours. GI 50 
of these cell lines were 1-5 uM to gefitinib and 4uM-
≥10uM to EMD 121463. These cell lines were essen-
tially resistant to both gefitinib and EMD 121463 as 
single agents. The inhibitory effect of combined 
treatment with gefitinib and EMD 121463 was signif-
icantly enhanced compared with single agent therapy 
in MDA-MB-468 cells (P=0.002) but not in the other 
cell lines (MDA-MB-231, HCC1395, and T47D) (Fig.1). 
However, when data were analyzed in Calcusyn 
software, synergism was also documented at different 
concentration combinations in the other cell lines 
(Table 1). These experiments indicate a dose de-
pendent synergistic interaction between gefitinib and 
EMD 121463 in suppressing growth of triple-negative 
breast cancer cells. </p>

<p>Table 1. Combination index (CI) </p>

<p>Cell line 
Gefitinib (uM) 
EMD 121463 (uM) CI </p>

<p>MDA-MB-468 
1 
6 
0.87 </p>

<p>HCC 1395 
0.5 
2 
0.39 </p>

<p>HCC 1395 
1 
4 
0.15 </p>

<p>HCC 1395 
2 
6 
0.29 </p>

<p>MDA-MB-231 
0.5 
2 
0.59 </p>

<p>T47D 
0.5 
2 
0.55 </p>

<p>T47D 
1 
4 
0.73 </p>

<p>Effects of EGFR and MET inhibition in soft agar 
and 3D culture </p>

<p>In order to evaluate effects of drug combinations 
on anchorage independent growth, cells were seeded 
in soft agar and EGFR inhibitors (gefitinib or cetuxi-
mab), EMD 121463, or combinations were added. Af-
ter 10-14 days, the colony size and number were sig-
nificantly reduced in the MDA-MB-468 cell line when 
gefitinib or cetuximab was combined with EMD 
121463 compared to single agents. In MDA-MB-231 
cell line, there was a significant reduction of colony 
number when EMD 121463 was combined with ge-
fitinib but not with cetuximab compared to single 
agents (Fig. 2). </p>

<p>Journal of Cancer 2014, Vol. 5 </p>

<p>http://www.jcancer.org </p>



<p>Fig. 1. Effects of combination of EGFR inhibitors with cMET inhibitor, EMD 1214063 in MTS assay. Cells were seeded in 96-well microplates in medium sup-
plemented with 5% FBS and penicillin/streptavidin. The optimal cell number for each cell line was determined to ensure that each was in growth phase at the end of the assay 
(~70% confluency). Cells were allowed to attach for 24 hours. The media was changed to low FBS (2%) and drugs with different combinations were added (cetuximab 200ug/mL, 
gefitinib 0.25-8 umol/L and EMD 121463 2-10 umol/L). In terms of determination of drug concentration, twofold serial dilution was conducted for gefitinib and dose was increased 
by 2 umol/L in EMD 121463 with the upper limit of 10 umol/L because of poor solubility. Cells were incubated at 37°C for 72 hours. Growth inhibition was determined with Cell 
Titer Blue (Promega, Madison, WI) at a 72-hour time point according to the manufacturer's instructions. Quantification of fluorescent signal intensity was performed using a 
fluorescent plate reader at excitation and emission wavelengths of 530/604. Drug concentrations were as follows; Gefitinib 1uM and EMD 121463 5uM in MDA-MB-468; Gefitinib 
5uM and EMD 121463 5uM in MDA-MB-231. There was no statistical difference in T47D and HCC1395 (data not shown). The data are mean ± standard deviations of triplicates 
(*, P&lt;0.001). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Effects of combination of EGFR inhibitors with cMET inhibitor EMD 1214063 on soft agar assay. Cells were suspended in complete RPMI medium con-
taining 0.3% soft agar and seeded in triplicate on 35-mm dishes precoated with 0.6% agar in complete growth medium mixed with corresponding drug and incubated at 37°C, 5% 
CO2. After 10 days, colonies were photographed and counted in 10 randomly chosen fields and expressed as means of triplicates. For staining of the colonies, 0.005% crystal 
violet in 20% methanol solution were added to the dishes for 30 minutes and washed until the background becomes clear. Drug concentrations were as follows; Gefitinib 1uM, 
EMD 121463 5uM, and Cetuximab 200 ug/ml, in MDA-MB-468; Gefitinib 5uM, EMD 121463 5uM, and Cetuximab 200 ug/ml in MDA-MB-231. Colonies were not formed in HCC 
1395 and there were no difference between single agent and combination in T47D (data not shown). The data are mean ± standard deviations of triplicates (*, P&lt;0.001 vs EMD 
121463; **, P&lt;0.05 vs EMD 121463; ***, P&lt;0.001 vs gefitinib; #, P&gt;0.05 vs cetuximab). </p>

<p>Journal of Cancer 2014, Vol. 5 </p>

<p>http://www.jcancer.org </p>



<p>Fig. 3. Matrigel assay in TNBC cell lines, and T47D. Thawed 45ul Matrigel on ice were placed in each well of a pre-cooled 8-well glass chamber slide. After 30 minutes of 
solidification, TNBC cell lines and T47D mixed in ice-cold medium with 2% Matrigel and drugs were loaded in each well of the 8-chamber slide and incubated at 37°C. Media with 
2% Matrigel and various concentrations of drugs were changed every three days. Drug concentrations were as follows; Gefitinib 1um, EMD 121463 1uM and Cetuximab 200ug/ml 
in MDA-MB-468, Gefitinib 1um, EMD 121463 5uM and Cetuximab 200ug/ml in HCC 1395, Gefitinib 5um, EMD 121463 2uM and Cetuximab 200ug/ml in T47D. </p>

<p>We also observed three-dimensional morpholo-
gy of the cell lines in Matrigel with the drugs as de-
scribed above. Again, MDA-MB-468 showed re-
markable regression when the drug combination was 
applied but not with the other cell lines assessed (Fig. 
3). </p>

<p>Effects of EGFR and MET inhibition on down-
stream signaling </p>

<p>Then, we investigated the changes in down-
stream signaling for each cell line before and after 
treatment of drug alone and in combination. In west-
ern blotting, both gefitinib and cetuximab reduced 
pEGFR and EMD1214063 abrogated pMET, respec-
tively in MDA-MB-468 as well as in HCC-1395. Either 
drug alone was insufficient to alter pAKT, pMAPK 
and pS6 levels. Strikingly, however the combination 
of these two drugs significantly reduced or abrogated 
the expression of downstream signaling molecules. 
These results suggest that each inhibitor has effects on 
their respective direct targets but that these effects are 
not translated into blocking of survival and prolifera-
tive pathways. However, the combination of EGFR 
and MET inhibition could abrogate the activation of 
essential molecules required for cell growth control. 
Interestingly, in MDA-MB-231 and T47D, there were 
no effects on PI3K or MAPK signaling not only after 
the single agent therapy but also even after combina-
tion treatment (Fig. 4). Next, we checked if we could 
reverse the inhibition of these drugs on downstream </p>

<p>molecules when we transfect either AKT or MEK into 
the cells. As shown in Figure 5, transfection of wild 
type AKT and/or wild type MEK into MDA-MB-468 
cells increased pAKT and pMEK respectively (Fig 5). 
Surprisingly, in transfected cells, the combination of 
EGFR or MET inhibition failed to decrease pAKT in 
AKT transfected cells and pMEK in MEK transfected 
cells. This effect was also seen when AKT and MEK 
were cotransfected (Fig. 5). </p>

<p>Determination of active EGFR/MET pathways 
in cell lines </p>

<p>To determine the potential mechanisms involved 
with the pathway inhibition, cells were treated with 
EGF and/or HGF after overnight starvation with 
RPMI-1640 without FBS and lysed to perform western 
blotting. MDA-MB-468 and HCC-1395 were respon-
sive to both EGF and HGF stimulation consistent with 
the presence of functional cell surface receptors able 
to link to downstream signals including pMAPK and 
pAKT. However, MDA-MB-231 and T47D showed 
faint or negligible expression of pEGFR and pMET 
even after stimulation with growth factors and there 
were little changes in levels of downstream targets 
including pMAPK and pAKT (Fig. 6). Accordingly, 
we designated MDA-MB-468 and HCC-1395 as cell 
lines that have active EGFR and MET pathways and 
MDA-MB-231 and T47D as cell lines with inactive 
EGFR and MET pathways. These results are con-
sistent with MDA-MB-468 and HCC-1395 responding </p>

<p>Journal of Cancer 2014, Vol. 5 </p>

<p>http://www.jcancer.org </p>



<p>to gefitinib and EMD 121463 and with MDA-MB-231 
and T47D not responding or poorly responding. </p>

<p>Phospho-Receptor Tyrosine Kinase (Phos-
pho-RTK) arrays </p>

<p>Using phospho-receptor tyrosine kinase array, 
we investigated whether alternative growth factor 
receptors responded to EGF or HGF and whether ge-
fitinib or the combination of gefitinib and EMD 
121463 would alter the activity. In MDA MB-468 cells, 
EGF increased levels of pEGFR and pErbB3 whereas </p>

<p>EGF and HGF together increased phosphorylated 
MET, EGFR and ErbB3. ErbB3 plays a critical role in 
escaping from EGFR TKI inhibition via Akt negative 
feedback [15]. Geifitinb and EMD 121463 abrogated 
pMET as well as pErbb3 (Fig. 7). The effects of the 
combination of gefitinib and EMD 121463 do not seem 
to be compensated by activation of other RTKs in 
MDA MB-468 cells (Fig.7). Similar findings were ob-
tained with HCC-1395 (data not shown). </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Evaluation of receptors and downstream pathways after different treatments in TNBC cell lines and T47D. Treated cells were starved with RPMI 1640 
medium overnight and next morning, they were stimulated with EGF 20ng/mL and/or recombinant human HGF 75ng/mL for 10 minutes before cell lysis. Thereafter, cell lysates 
were collected and loaded for Western blot with antibodies as indicated. Actin was used as a loading control. D; DMSO, G; Gefitinib, E; EMD 121463, C; Cetuximab. EGF 20ng/ml, 
HGF 75ng/ml were treated 10 min before cell lysis. </p>

<p>Journal of Cancer 2014, Vol. 5 </p>

<p>http://www.jcancer.org </p>



<p>Fig. 5. Rescue experiment evaluating AKT and MEK transfection after therapy inhibition. AKT and MEK inserted in pCMV5-expression vector with a selection 
marker of ampicillin (100ug/ml) was gently diluted (0.01ug/ul) with serum-free media. Diluted DNA (100ul) was mixed with X-tremeGENE DNA transfection reagent (3ul) and 
incubated for 15 minutes at room temperature. These mixtures were added into the 60mm dish culturing MDA-MB-468 on day 1 and incubated overnight with drugs including 
gefitinib (1uM) and EMD 121463 (5uM) alone or in combination; they were treated with serum-free media on day 2. Cells were harvested for western blotting after treatment 
of EGF 20ng/mL and/or recombinant human HGF 75ng/mL for 10 minutes before cell lysis. </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Western blot results after stimulation with EGF, HGF, and their combination in TNBC cell lines, and T47D. Cells were starved with RPMI 1640 medium 
overnight and next morning, they were stimulated with EGF 20ng/mL and/or recombinant human HGF 75ng/mL for 10 minutes before cell lysis. Thereafter, cell lysates were 
collected and loaded for Western blot with antibodies as indicated. Actin was used as a loading control. </p>

<p>Journal of Cancer 2014, Vol. 5 </p>

<p>http://www.jcancer.org </p>



<p>Fig. 7. Phospho-receptor tyrosine kinase array results in MDA-MB-468. 
After stimulation of EGF and HGF and after treatment of gefitinib and gefitinib plus 
EMD 121463: MDA-MB-468 in 100mm dish was harvested as described in western 
blotting and Phospho-Receptor Tyrosine Kinase (RTK) antibody arrays (R&amp;D System, 
#ARY-001, Minneapolis, MN) were performed as recommended but with 450ug 
protein lysate per array. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we demonstrate that MET and 
EGFR inhibition are synergistic in TNBC cell lines 
especially when cell lines have active lig-
and-receptor-downstream signaling loops. This com-
bination could be helpful to overcome intrinsic EGFR 
resistance in TNBC. 
Overexpression of EGFR is one of the most 
common aberrations in breast cancer [3,4,15,16]. Con-
stitutively activating mutations like EGFR in 
non-small cell lung cancer or V600K BRAF mutations 
in melanoma are rarely found in breast cancer 
[5,16,17] . In terms of MET, ligand-independent MET 
activation, by mutation or overexpression, has been 
detected in a minority of cancers. More commonly 
solid tumors are ligand-responsive and require either 
autocrine or paracrine HGF for malignant transfor-</p>

<p>mation [18-20]. Therefore, it was assumed that au-
to/paracrine loop with the activating ligands such as 
EGF and HGF would play a greater role in TNBC in 
which both EGFR and MET amplifications occur [21] 
and where elevated tyrosine phosphorylation of both 
receptors was found in reverse phase protein array 
[22]. However, the data demonstrate that EGF and 
HGF 
activated 
downstream 
signaling 
in 
MDA-MB-468 and HCC 1395 but not the other breast 
cancer cell lines assessed. Whether this represents the 
underlying genetic aberrations in the lines with for 
example MD MB 231 cells have both RAS and RAF 
mutations remains to be ascertained. 
With this perspective, we report that the combi-
nation of EGFR and MET inhibitors is effective in cell 
lines 
that 
have 
functionally 
active 
lig-
and-receptor-downstream signaling pathways in 
TNBC. Failure to induced inhibition of Akt has been 
reported as a major cause of resistance to EGFR in-
hibitors [6,23]. Especially, PTEN mutation in 
MDA-MB-468 is like to contribute to the inability of 
inhibition of EGFR to down-regulate downstream Akt 
activity [20,24,25]. In TNBC MDA-MB-468 cell lines 
that respond to EGF and HGF, the combination of 
gefitinib and EMD 1214063 shows not only enhanced 
cytotoxicity but also reduced or abrogated down-
stream activation of signaling molecules such as Akt, 
MAPK, S6 and STAT3. 
Previous studies of the interactions between 
EGFR and MET inhibitors suggested that cSRC and 
MET cooperate to cope with the effects of EGFR in-
hibitors in breast cancers [26]. Synergistic effects be-
tween EGFR and MET inhibitors were also seen in 
HGF transgenic severe combined immunodeficient 
mice [27]. In this study, we focused on determining 
the effectiveness of combined treatment in triple neg-
ative breast cell lines to investigate the potential 
translational relevance of EGFR-MET combination 
therapy in TNBC. 
Combined therapy with EGFR and MET inhibi-
tors are being studied in other disease including col-
orectal cancer, head and neck cancer and lung cancer 
[12,20,28]. Triple negative breast cancer is now con-
sidered to represent a heterogenous group of diseases 
based on gene expression profiles of TNBC cell lines 
[29]. MDA-MB-468 is categorized as Basal-Like sub-
type and MDA-MB-231 is grouped as Mesenchy-
mal-Like subtype while HCC 1395 is regarded as Un-
classified. Therefore, in order to develop biomarkers 
of the treatment of EGFR and MET inhibition, TNBC 
should not be studied as a whole entity, rather it 
should be studied based on biomarkers such as a 
presence of active EGFR and MET pathways. In con-
trast to oncogenic addictions like activating mutation 
or gene rearrangement followed by constitutive sig-</p>

<p>Journal of Cancer 2014, Vol. 5 </p>

<p>http://www.jcancer.org </p>



<p>naling, receptor overexpression can contribute to ac-
tivation of additional receptors or so called receptor 
co-activation [13,30]. In this case, it would be desirable 
to block both pathways after identification of the ac-
tive receptor co-activation processes in future clinical 
trials. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was supported in part by National 
Cancer Institute 1K23CA121994 (AMG) ASCO Career 
Development Award (AMG), Komen for the Cure 
Catalystic Award KG090341 (AMG), Komen for the 
Cure SAC 1000004, American Cancer Society Research 
Scholar Grant 121329-RSG-11-187-01-TBG (AMG), 
The Commonwealth Foundation for Cancer research 
(AMG), and EMD Serono (Billerica, MA). </p>

<p>Competing Interests </p>

<p>AMG has received compound donation from 
EMD Serono and NTU has research funding from 
EMD Serono. EMD Serono has reviewed the publica-
tion. The views and opinions described in the publi-
cation do not necessarily reflect those of EMD Serono. </p>



</text></tei>