<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4212086" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Quantification of cells in BAL fluids 
BAL fluid was prepared by washing the lungs with 0.8 ml 
of PBS. The cell pellets were prepared by centrifugation at 
300 ×g for 3 min. After discarding the supernatants, cell pel-
lets were resuspended in RPMI 1640. Cells were stained with 
trypan blue, and the total number of viable cells was de-
termined using a hemocytometer. </p>

<p>Histological evaluation of tissue inflammation 
To evaluate tissue inflammation, the left lung from each 
mouse was fixed in 10% neutral-buffered formalin (pH 7.0) 
for 48 hours and embedded in paraffin. Sections (2-μm 
thick) were prepared and stained with hematoxylin and 
eosin. Tissue inflammation in each sample was examined by 
light microscopy and was expressed as a numerical score. 
Tissue inflammation based on the abundance of lesions was 
scored as follows: 0=non-specific lesion, 1=slight, 2=mild, 
3=moderate, 4=marked, and 5=severe. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Differences among the mean values of the different groups 
were analyzed, and the values were expressed as mean±SD. 
Statistical analyses were performed by Student's t-test by 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>, San Diego, 
CA, USA). Values of p＜0.05 were considered significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>TRIF deficiency does not contribute to histopa-
thological changes in an OVA-induced model of 
airway inflammation 
Inflammation in tissues was assessed by histological examina-
tion, and the total number of cells in BAL fluid was counted 
(Fig. 2). OVA-sensitized/challenged WT and TRIF 
−/− mice </p>

<p>showed inflammatory cell infiltration around the airways and 
interstitium of the alveoli (Fig. 2A). These lesions did not ap-
pear in PBS-sensitized/challenged control WT and TRIF </p>

<p>−/− </p>

<p>mice. Scores indicating severity of inflammation were sig-
nificantly increased in OVA-sensitized/challenged WT and 
TRIF 
−/− mice compared to PBS-sensitized/challenged WT and </p>

<p>TRIF 
−/− mice; however, a significant difference in the scores </p>

<p>was not observed between OVA-sensitized/challenged WT 
mice and OVA-sensitized/challenged TRIF 
−/− mice (Fig. 2B). </p>

<p>The total number of cells in BAL fluid was also increased in 
OVA-sensitized/challenged WT and TRIF 
−/− mice, and no </p>

<p>significant difference in the total number of cells was detected 
between the two groups (Fig. 2C). </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant from the Korean Health 
Technology R&amp;D project from the Ministry of Health &amp; 
Welfare, Republic of Korea (Grant No. A111025). </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors have no financial conflict of interest. </p>



<p>Role of TRIF in Allergic Airway Inflammation 
Tae-Hyoun Kim, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 14, No. 5: 249-254, October, 2014 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>