<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4848362" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A b s t r a c t </p>

<p>Introduction: Both end-organ damage and high red cell distribution width 
(RDW) values are associated with adverse cardiovascular events, inflamma-
tory status, and neurohumoral activation in hypertensive disease and in the 
general population. In this study, we investigated the relationship between 
RDW and end-organ damage in hypertensive patients. 
Material and methods: The 446 systo-diastolic hypertensive patients in-
cluded in the study received 24-hour ambulatory blood pressure monitoring. 
Left ventricular mass index, glomerular filtration rate, and microalbuminuria 
were measured to identify end-organ damage. High-sensitivity C-reactive 
protein (hs-CRP) and N-terminal pro-B-type natriuretic peptide (NT-proBNP) 
levels of all patients were also examined. 
Results: The mean age of the participants was 49.96 ±11.04 years. The mean 
RDW was 13.06 ±1.05%. Red cell distribution width was positively correlated 
with left ventricular myocardial index (LVMI), urinary albumin, hs-CRP, and 
NT-proBNP (r = 0.298, p &lt; 0.001; r = 0.228, p &lt; 0.001; r = 0.337, p &lt; 0.001; 
r = 0.277, p &lt; 0.001, respectively), while RDW was negatively correlated with 
eGFR (r = -0.153, p &lt; 0.001). Additionally, while there was a positive cor-
relation between RDW and 24-h systolic blood pressure, no correlation was 
found between RDW and 24-h diastolic blood pressure (r = 0.132, p = 0.006 
and r = 0.017, p = 0.725, respectively). Multiple linear regression analysis 
revealed that RDW levels were independently associated with eGFR, LVMI, 
and severity of albuminuria (β = 0.126, p = 0.010; β = -0.149, p = 0.002; 
β = 0.114, p = 0.035). 
Conclusions: High RDW levels in systo-diastolic hypertensive patients were 
found to be an independent predictor of end-organ damage. </p>

<p>Hypertension is a well-known risk factor for cardiovascular event de-
velopment. In particular, hypertensive patients with end-organ damage 
are associated with increased cardiovascular events [1, 2], while end-or-
gan damage development in hypertensive patients is reported to be 
associated with increased inflammation and neurohumoral activation 
[3-5]. Increases in inflammation and neurohumoral activation cause in-
creased red cell distribution width (RDW), and increased RDW levels that 
reflect size heterogeneity of the erythrocytes in the circulation are also </p>

<p>Hamdi Pusuroglu, Ozgur Akgul, Mehmet Erturk, Ozgur Surgit, Omer Tasbulak, Emre Akkaya, Serkan Yazan, Mehmet Gül, Selahattin Türen </p>

<p> 
Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2016 </p>

<p>reported to be associated with heart failure, coro-
nary artery disease, and increased mortality in the 
general population [6-9]. 
Left ventricular myocardial index (LVMI), mi-
croalbuminuria, and estimated glomerular fil-
tration rate (eGFR) are the most frequently used 
indicators of end-organ damage in hypertensive 
patients. While there are studies on the associ-
ation of high-sensitivity C-reactive protein (hs-
CRP) and N-terminal pro-B-type natriuretic pep-
tide (NT-proBNP) levels with end-organ damage 
in hypertensive patients, not many studies have 
investigated the association between RDW and 
development of end-organ damage [3-5]. In this 
study, therefore, the association between RDW 
and end-organ damage, hs-CRP, and NT-proBNP 
was investigated in systo-diastolic hypertensive 
patients. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>A total of 446 patients aged between 20-87 
years, who had presented at the cardiology out-
patient clinic and had office blood pressure over 
140/90 at least twice at different times, were 
included in the study. All patients were put on 
24-hour ambulatory blood pressure monitoring 
(ABPM). Medical history, physical examination 
findings and anthropometric measurements of 
the patients were recorded by an experienced car-
diologist. 
Hypertension was defined as an office blood 
pressure (OBP) of ≥ 140/90 mm Hg or the active 
use of antihypertensive drugs [10]. Sustained 
systo-diastolic hypertension was defined as hav-
ing an OBP of ≥ 140/90 mm Hg and the daytime 
ABPM mean of ≥ 135/85 mm Hg, or the nighttime 
ABPM mean of ≥ 120/70 mm Hg [10]. "White-coat-
hypertension" was defined as blood pressure if el-
evated in the office at repeated visits and normal 
on ABPM [10]. 
Diabetes was defined based on the American 
Diabetes Association criteria (fasting serum glu-
cose ≥ 126 mg/dl (7 mmol/l), or non-fasting glu-
cose ≥ 200 mg/dl (11.1 mmol/l), or active use of 
anti-diabetic treatment) [11]. Body mass index 
was calculated as weight in kilograms/(height 
in meters)², and eGFR was calculated using the 
Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology Collabora-
tion (CKD-EPI) formula [12]. 
Urinary albumin was expressed in milligrams 
per gram (mg/g). Albuminuria was defined as an 
albumin/creatinine (A/C) ratio of 30 mg/g or high-
er, stratified into two groups of microalbuminuria 
and macroalbuminuria with an A/C ratio of 30-
299 mg/g and 300 mg/g or higher, respectively. 
Echocardiographic examinations were per-
formed by a cardiologist using the Vivid 7 system 
(General Electric Vivid 7 GE Vingmend Ultrasound </p>

<p>AS, Horten, Norway). The left ventricular (LV) mass 
in grams was calculated from M-mode echocar-
diograms according to the formula described by 
Devereux et al. [13]. Left ventricular mass was 
indexed to body surface area as LV mass index 
(LVMI) in g/m² of body surface area. 
The exclusion criteria of this study were sec-
ondary hypertension, heart failure, coronary ar-
tery disease, stroke, moderate-to-severe valvular 
disease, chronic renal failure, chronic liver dis-
ease, thromboembolic disorders, hematological 
abnormalities, and chronic obstructive pulmonary 
disease. The local ethics committee approved the 
study protocol and informed consent was ob-
tained from all patients. </p>

<p>Ambulatory blood pressure monitoring </p>

<p>Ambulatory blood pressure monitoring (ABPM) 
was performed for 24 h using an ambulatory 
blood pressure monitor (Tonoport V, GE Health-
care). The monitor was programmed to measure 
the blood pressure every 20 min. Daytime and 
nighttime blood pressure was defined as mea-
sured from 07:00 AM to 11:00 PM and from 11:00 
PM to 07:00 AM, respectively. Twenty-four hour 
mean systolic blood pressure was defined as the 
mean systolic blood pressure measured during 
24 h by the monitor and was automatically pro-
vided in the report. </p>

<p>Blood sampling </p>

<p>Red cell distribution width was measured in 
blood samples collected in EDTA tubes, which 
were analyzed with an automated hematology 
analysis system (Mindray BC5800). Normal RDW 
values ranged from 11% to 16% in our laborato-
ry. Standard laboratory parameters, including to-
tal leukocyte and neutrophil counts, hematocrit, 
glucose and creatinine levels and lipid profiles, 
were determined with standard methods. Plasma 
NT-proBNP levels were measured using a Cobas 
e411 device (Roche, Germany) via the immuno-
assay method. The NT-proBNP reference values 
were determined as 0-125 pg/ml. Hs-CRP was 
measured using a BN2 model nephelometer. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed using the 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 20</rs>. The variables were 
investigated using visual (histograms, proba-
bility plots) and analytical methods (Kolmogor-
ov-Smirnov) to determine whether they were 
normally distributed. Descriptive analyses were 
presented using means and standard deviations 
(SD) for normally distributed variables, medians 
and maximum-minimum values for non-normal-
ly distributed variables, and percentages for cat-</p>

<p>Red cell distribution width and end-organ damage in patients with systo-diastolic hypertension </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2016 </p>

<p>
egorical variables. Chi-square (χ 
2 ), Student's t, 
and Mann-Whitney U tests were used where ap-
propriate. A Spearman correlation analysis was 
performed to determine the association of RDW 
with the examined variables. Multiple linear re-
gression analyses were performed to identify the 
significance of the relationship of RDW levels with 
microalbuminuria, LVMI, and eGFR. An overall 5% 
type-I error level was used to infer statistical sig-
nificance. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Of the 446 participants included in the study, 
72.7% had sustained systo-diastolic hyperten-
sion and 27.3% had white-coat hypertension. 
Male patients constituted 51.1% of the sample. 
The mean age was 49 ±11.04 years; 23.3% of the 
participants were smokers and 14.4% had type 2 
diabetes mellitus. The mean value of RDW was 
13.06 ±1.05%, LVMI was 96.04 ±25.6 g/m 
2 , uri-
nary albumin was 63.72 ±127.09 mg/g, eGFR was 
97.14 ±17.99 ml/min/1.73 m², hs-CRP was 3.96 
±4.62 mg/l and NT-proBNP was 55.21 ±69.99 pg/ 
ml. The other demographic and clinical character-
istics of the participants are presented in Table I. 
As shown in Figure 1 and Table II, RDW was 
positively correlated with LVMI, albuminuria, 
hs-CRP, and NT-proBNP (r = 0.298, p &lt; 0.001; 
r = 0.228, p &lt; 0.001; r = 0.337, p &lt; 0.001; r = 0.277, 
p &lt; 0.001, respectively), while RDW was negatively 
correlated with eGFR (r = -0.153, p &lt; 0.001). Ad-
ditionally, while there was a positive correlation 
between RDW and 24-h systolic blood pressure, 
no correlation was found between RDW and 24-h 
diastolic blood pressure (r = 0.132, p = 0.006 and 
r = 0.017, p = 0.725, respectively) (Figure 2, Table II). 
Multiple linear regression analysis revealed 
that RDW levels were independently associated 
with eGFR, LVMI, and severity of albuminuria (β = 
0.126, p = 0.010; β = -0.149, p = 0.002; β = 0.114, 
p = 0.035) (Table III). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Based on the results of this study, increased 
RDW levels were identified as independent predic-
tors of increased LVMI, decreased eGFR values and 
severity of microalbuminuria in systo-diastolic hy-
pertensive patients. Also, it was determined that 
RDW levels were correlated with hs-CRP, NT-proBNP 
levels and 24-h systolic blood pressure. 
End-organ damage development in hypertensive 
patients is a significant indicator of cardiovascular 
risk. Diagnosis of kidney damage associated with 
hypertension is made by the detection of symp-
toms of declining kidney function or increased 
urinary albuminuria [14]. We demonstrated that 
increased RDW levels were independent predictors </p>

<p>of decreased eGFR values, although the creatinine 
values were within the normal range. Our results 
are in agreement with those of Lippi et al., who 
also reported that a low eGFR was a predictor of 
high RDW values [15]. In another study, a strong 
association between decreased renal function 
and high RDW levels was attributed to impaired 
erythrocyte maturation in chronic kidney disease 
patients due to increased inflammation [16]. 
Another finding that demonstrates impaired 
renal function in hypertensive patients is the de-
gree of microalbuminuria. Microalbuminuria is 
associated with increased cardiovascular risk in 
both diabetic and nondiabetic patients who are 
undergoing treatment [1, 17]. Microalbuminuria is 
not only a predictor of subclinical renal damage 
but is also a predictor of generalized endothelial 
dysfunction and increased inflammation [3, 18]. </p>

<p>Table I. Characteristics of the study population </p>

<p>Variable 
Result </p>

<p>Gender (male), n (%) 
228 (51.1) </p>

<p>Age [years] 
49.96 ±11.04 </p>

<p>BMI [kg/m²] 
29.46 ±4.46 </p>

<p>Smoking, n (%) 
104 (23.3) </p>

<p>Diabetes, n (%) 
64 (14.4) </p>

<p>24-h SBP [mg/dl] 
145 ±64 </p>

<p>24-h DBP [mg/dl] 
88.35 ±13 </p>

<p>Glucose [mg/dl] 
104.5 ±28.6 </p>

<p>Creatinine [mg/dl] 
0.8 ±0.2 </p>

<p>Total cholesterol [mg/dl] 
204.4 ±43.57 </p>

<p>LDL cholesterol [mg/dl] 
132.14 ±39.27 </p>

<p>HDL cholesterol [mg/dl] 
46.64 ±13.37 </p>

<p>Triglyceride [mg/dl] 
163.71 ±91.94 </p>

<p>Uric acid [mg/dl] 
5.37 ±1.57 </p>

<p>Hematocrit (%) 
41.9 ±4.4 </p>

<p>Platelet count [× 10 
3 /µl] 
265.97 ±73 </p>

<p>RDW (%) 
13.06 ±1.05 </p>

<p>LVMI [g/m²] 
96.04 ±25.6 </p>

<p>eGFR [ml/min/1.73 m²] 
97.14 ±17.99 </p>

<p>Urinary albumin [mg/g] 
63.72 ±127.09 </p>

<p>Hs-CRP [mg/l] 
3.96 ±4.62 </p>

<p>NT-proBNP [pg/ml] 
55.21 ±69.99 </p>

<p>HDL -high-density lipoprotein, LVMI -left ventricular mass index, 
NT-proBNP -N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide, SBP -sys-
tolic blood pressure, RDW -red cell distribution width, hsCRP -
high-sensitivity C-reactive protein, eGFR -estimated glomerular fil-
tration rate. </p>

<p>Hamdi Pusuroglu, Ozgur Akgul, Mehmet Erturk, Ozgur Surgit, Omer Tasbulak, Emre Akkaya, Serkan Yazan, Mehmet Gül, Selahattin Türen </p>

<p> 
Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2016 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Correlation between red cell distribution width (RDW) and high-sensitivity C-reactive protein (hs-CRP), 
microalbuminuria, left ventricular mass index (LVMI), and estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) </p>

<p>Table II. Correlation coefficients of the relationship 
between red cell distribution width (RDW) and se-
lected variables </p>

<p>Variable 
β 
P-value </p>

<p>NT-proBNP 
0.277 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Urinary albumin [mg/g] 
0.0228 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>LVMI 
0.298 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>hs-CRP 
0.337 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>eGFR 
-0.153 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>24-h SBP 
0.132 
0.006 </p>

<p>24-h DBP 
0.017 
0.725 </p>

<p>NT-proBNP -N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide, LVMI -left 
ventricular mass index, hs-CRP -high-sensitivity C-reactive protein, 
SBP -systolic blood pressure, DBP -diastolic blood pressure, 
eGFR -estimated glomerular filtration rate. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Correlation between red cell distribution 
width (RDW) and 24-h systolic blood pressure </p>

<p>RDW [%] </p>

<p>RDW (%) 
RDW (%) </p>

<p>RDW (%) 
RDW (%) </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>R 
2 linear = 0.004 
R 
2 linear = 0.097 </p>

<p>R 
2 linear = 0.069 
R 
2 linear = 0.040 </p>

<p>y = 11.93 + 0.01x 
y = 14.61 + 0.01x </p>

<p>y = 12.73 + 0.09x 
y = 12.81 + 4.87E3x </p>

<p>90 
120 
150 
180 
210 
24-h SBP [mm Hg] </p>

<p>0 
50 
100 
150 
200 
250 
LVMI [g/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>] </p>

<p>50 
75 
100 
125 
150 
175 
eGFR [ml/min] </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
hs-CRP [mg/l] </p>

<p>0 
50 
100 
150 
200 
250 
300 
NT-proBNP [pg/ml] </p>

<p>RDW 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>95% Confidence interval for B </p>

<p>Lower bound 
Upper bound </p>

<p>LVMI [g/m 
2 ] 
0.084 
0.08 
0.015 </p>

<p>eGFR [ml/min] 
0.097 
-0.016 
-0.009 </p>

<p>NT-proBNP [pg/ml] 
0.040 
0.003 
0.007 </p>

<p>Hs-CRP [mg/l] 
0.069 
0.060 
0.123 </p>

<p>Red cell distribution width and end-organ damage in patients with systo-diastolic hypertension </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2016 </p>

<p>
A study conducted on grade 1 hypertensive pa-
tients reported an association between increased 
RDW and endothelial dysfunction [19], and 
a population-based study by Afonso et al. found 
an association between an increase in RDW and 
proteinuria development; this was attributed to 
inflammation, neurohumoral activation, and en-
dothelial dysfunction [20]. In our study, we also 
found that increased RDW levels were indepen-
dent predictors of microalbuminuria. 
Left ventricular hypertrophy, like microalbumin-
uria, has also been demonstrated to be a predic-
tor of poor cardiovascular prognosis [2, 21]. In our 
study we demonstrated that high RDW levels were 
an independent predictor of LVMI. Since increased 
neurohumoral activation and inflammation are 
associated with increased LVMI in hypertensive 
patients [5, 22], these factors may be responsible 
for the association between LVMI and RDW. Kili-
caslan et al. recently demonstrated that RDW val-
ues were associated with ventricular geometrical 
patterns [23] in untreated hypertensive patients. 
Studies have indicated that systolic blood pres-
sure (SBP) has a greater association with RDW lev-
els and mortality than does diastolic blood pres-
sure (DBP) [7, 9, 24]. While we detected a positive 
correlation between 24-hour SBP and RDW, we 
could not detect an association between DBP and 
RDW. Systolic hypertension has also been shown 
to be more closely associated with increased in-
flammation and NT-proBNP than is diastolic hy-
pertension [25, 26]. This may explain the different 
associations of RDW with SBP and DBP. 
At least a part of the association of RDW with 
increased cardiovascular incidence and mortality 
was attributed to the association between RDW 
and inflammation [8, 9]. However, Perlstein et al. 
found that increased RDW levels were associ-
ated with increased mortality among a patient 
population with low CRP [8]. In patients with 
coronary artery disease, Fukuta et al. reported 
high RDW values associated with increased BNP 
values, but no association was detected with hs-
CRP levels [27]. Fukuta et al. proposed that the 
association between RDW and adverse clinical 
incidents in the studied patient population was 
related to neurohumoral activation rather than 
inflammation. The renin-angiotensin system, in-
flammation, and oxidative stress are hyperactive 
in hypertension [28, 29], and increases in these 
factors have been associated with increased 
end-organ damage and increased RDW levels [5, 
30, 31]. 
To our best knowledge there is no study assess-
ing the association of RDW level with NT-proBNP, 
hs-CRP levels and end-organ damage in hyperten-
sive patients. In our study, we determined that 
a high RDW level was a predictor of end-organ </p>

<p>damage in hypertensive patients. Moreover, we 
found that RDW was associated with hs-CRP and 
NT-proBNP levels. Increased neurohumoral acti-
vation and inflammation may, therefore, be the 
cause of the association between increased RDW 
and adverse cardiovascular events observed in hy-
pertensive patients. 
There are several limitations in this study. First, 
this was a non-randomized study and therefore 
was subject to selection bias. Second, hyperten-
sive patients with heart failure, coronary artery </p>

<p>Table III. Multiple linear regression analyses: re-
lationship between left ventricular mass index 
(LVMI), estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR), 
urinary albumin and selected variables </p>

<p>Variable 
Coefficient 
P-value </p>

<p>Dependent variable -eGFR: 
(r² = 0.219) </p>

<p>RDW 
-0.126 
0.010 </p>

<p>Hs-CRP 
-0.079 
0.113 </p>

<p>NT-proBNP 
-0.144 
0.040 </p>

<p>24-h SBP 
-0.013 
0.741 </p>

<p>24-h DBP 
-0.073 
0.142 </p>

<p>Uric acid 
-0.388 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>BMI 
0.055 
0.254 </p>

<p>Dependent variable -urinary albumin: 
(r² = 0.048) </p>

<p>RDW 
0.114 
0.035 </p>

<p>Hs-CRP 
0.109 
0.047 </p>

<p>NT-proBNP 
0.010 
0.851 </p>

<p>24-h SBP 
0.021 
0.662 </p>

<p>24-h DBP 
0.106 
0.053 </p>

<p>Uric acid 
0.029 
0.583 </p>

<p>BMI 
0.010 
0.852 </p>

<p>Dependent variable -LVMI: 
(r² = 0.238) </p>

<p>RDW 
0.149 
0.002 </p>

<p>Hs-CRP 
0.335 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>NT-proBNP 
0.156 
0.001 </p>

<p>24-h SBP 
0.080 
0.091 </p>

<p>24-h DBP 
0.090 
0.065 </p>

<p>Uric acid 
0.054 
0.256 </p>

<p>BMI 
-0.045 
0.348 </p>

<p>NT-proBNP -N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide, LVMI -left 
ventricular mass index, hs-CRP -high-sensitivity C-reactive protein, 
SBP -systolic blood pressure, DBP -diastolic blood pressure, eGFR 
-estimated glomerular filtration rate, BMI -body mass index, 
RDW -red cell distribution width. </p>

<p>Hamdi Pusuroglu, Ozgur Akgul, Mehmet Erturk, Ozgur Surgit, Omer Tasbulak, Emre Akkaya, Serkan Yazan, Mehmet Gül, Selahattin Türen </p>

<p> 
Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2016 </p>

<p>disease, stroke, and moderate-to-severe vascular 
disease were excluded. Thus, our findings cannot 
be generalized to the entire hypertensive popula-
tion. Also, normotensive patients were not includ-
ed in this study. Finally, we did not measure vita-
min B 12 , folate levels, and iron status, which may 
also affect RDW levels. 
In conclusion, increased RDW levels are as-
sociated with end-organ damage, increased in-
flammation and NT-proBNP levels in systolo-di-
astolic hypertensive patients. This association 
may be used for risk classification in this patient 
group. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>R e f e r e n c e s </p>



<p>Red cell distribution width and end-organ damage in patients with systo-diastolic hypertension </p>

<p>Arch Med Sci 2, April / 2016 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>