<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4863732" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background A variety of experimental animal models are used extensively to study mechanisms underlying cancer cachexia, 
and to identify potential treatments. The important potential confounding effect of dietary composition and intake used in 
many preclinical studies of cancer cachexia is frequently overlooked. Dietary designs applied in experimental studies should 
maximize the applicability to human cancer cachexia, meeting the essential requirements of the species used in the study, 
matched between treatment and control groups as well as also being generally similar to human consumption. </p>

<p>Methods A literature review of scientific studies using animal models of cancer and cancer cachexia with dietary interven-
tions was performed. Studies that investigated interventions using lipid sources were selected as the focus of discussion. </p>

<p>Results The search revealed a number of nutrient intervention studies (n = 44), with the majority including n-3 fatty acids 
(n = 16), mainly eicosapentaenoic acid and/or docosahexaenoic acid. A review of the literature revealed that the majority of 
studies do not provide information about dietary design; food intake or pair-feeding is rarely reported. Further, there is a lack 
of standardization in dietary design, content, source, and overall composition in animal models of cancer cachexia. A model is 
proposed with the intent of guiding dietary design in preclinical studies to enable comparisons of dietary treatments within the 
same study, translation across different study designs, as well as application to human nutrient intakes. </p>

<p>Conclusion The potential for experimental endpoints to be affected by variations in food intake, macronutrient content, and 
diet composition is likely. Diet content and composition should be reported, and food intake assessed. Minimum standards for 
diet definition in cachexia studies would improve reproducibility of pre-clinical studies and aid the interpretation and 
translation of results to humans with cancer. </p>

<p>Keywords Cancer; Cachexia; Animal model; Dietary design </p>

<p>Received: 26 January 2015; Revised: 24 May 2015; Accepted: 16 June 2015 
*Correspondence to: Vera C. Mazurak, 4-002 Li Ka Shing Centre for Health Research Innovation, 8602-112 St NW, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada: (780) 492-8048; 
E-mail: vera.mazurak@ualberta.ca </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Cancer cachexia is a wasting syndrome characterized by 
ongoing loss of skeletal muscle mass (with or without loss of 
fat mass) that leads to progressive functional impairment. 1 
A global feature of cachexia is negative protein and energy 
balance driven by a variable combination of reduced food 
intake and abnormal metabolism. Experimental models are 
used extensively to study mechanisms underlying cachexia 
and to identify potential treatments. Preclinical studies enable 
control of many factors such as genetics, age, tumour type, 
and load that would be expected to influence the results of </p>

<p>an intervention in a human population. Paradoxically, the 
important potential confounding effect of dietary intake and 
composition used in many pre-clinical studies of cancer 
cachexia is frequently overlooked. Where details of dietary 
intake in animal experiments of cancer cachexia have been 
included, the majority of animal diets are imbalanced or 
lack certain essential nutrients, and frequently bear no 
resemblance to those normally consumed by humans with 
respect to macronutrient and micronutrient levels. 2 
Where nutrient interventions have been used for cancer 
cachexia studies, there is wide variation in timing and 
duration of supplementation, as well as route and frequency </p>

<p>R E V I E W </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Society of Sarcopenia, Cachexia and Wasting Disorders </p>

<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
Published online 15 October 2015 in Wiley Online Library (wileyonlinelibrary.com) DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and distribution in any medium, 
provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>of administration of any given nutrient, making it difficult to 
compare results across different animal models, study 
designs, and laboratory groups. Key metabolic differences 
between rodents and humans are not widely appreciated. 
Moreover the importance of background diet is often 
ignored. Thus, animals fed nutrient-deficient diets may be 
particularly sensitive to nutritional stress induced by the 
cancer-bearing state, and demonstrate corresponding 
exaggerated beneficial responses to supplements containing 
the missing nutrients. Finally it can be argued that, to 
maximize the applicability to human cachexia, attention 
should be paid to making the composition of diets used for 
experimental animals both sufficient for essential baseline 
requirements for the species under study but also generally 
similar to human diets. 
To illustrate these points we have reviewed studies 
performed in rodents that used a dietary intervention for 
cancer or cancer cachexia. Evidence to support the consider-
ation of diet as an important experimental factor is 
presented. Moreover, we suggest that minimum standards for 
diet definition in cachexia studies should be adopted to 
improve reproducibility of preclinical studies and aid interpreta-
tion and translation of results to humans with cancer. </p>

<p>Challenges in using animal models of human 
cancer cachexia </p>

<p>In humans, the mechanisms underlying cancer cachexia are 
complex, heterogeneous, and largely poorly defined. This 
complexity cannot be fully reproduced in animal models of 
cachexia, despite attempts to try and bridge the gap between 
human disease and animal models of cancer. A limited 
number of tumour cell types are used in rodent experiments 
[Lewis lung carcinoma (LLC); Colon 26 adenocarcinoma (C26)] 
but these are often chosen to be representative of tumour-
types (i.e. lung and colorectal cancers) which are more 
frequently associated with cachexia in humans. Tumour cell 
lines are typically implanted subcutaneously into experimen-
tal animal models, and are left to grow until the tumour-
burden induces cachexia symptoms. 3 Although tumour cell 
implantation induces cachexia, these tumours rarely metasta-
size, a key difference from cachexia-causing neoplasms in 
humans. 3 A variety of cachexia models are available, and 
methodological variations within models also make study 
comparisons difficult. 4 The majority of animal models for 
cancer and cancer cachexia use mice and each strain may 
have important differences relevant to their metabolic 
responses to cancer. Thus, some strains of in-bred animals 
are more susceptible to developing obesity and diabetes such 
as the C57BL/6J strain, 5 which can significantly affect study 
outcomes in cachexia. Furthermore, sex differences in growth 
responses are recognized in rodents, which may also limit 
generalizability of results to humans. Female rodents are </p>

<p>preferred over male rodents in studies with endpoints 
involving body weight changes since females have a slower 
growth curve and are less susceptible to rapid changes in body 
weight. In contrast, studies attempting to limit hormonal 
fluctuations within an animal prefer male rodents. 6 </p>

<p>In addition to metabolic and growth differences between 
sexes and strains of rodents, it is important to remember that 
there are also several important differences between human 
and rodent metabolism. Young and healthy rodents are 
commonly utilized in experimental studies; however young, 
healthy animals may not accurately reflect the manifestation 
of disease in adult or aging humans. For example, cancer 
patients may present with a number of comorbidities such 
as obesity, diabetes, heart disease, and are typically over 
the age of 50 years old. 7 Furthermore, the progression and 
timeline of aging in humans are not equivalent to that in 
rodents. Quinn (2005) determined that the ratio of rat to 
human life span is 1 to 30, making the age of the host species 
an important factor to consider in the study design. 8 
Moreover, rats reach mature skeletal size much earlier than 
humans. 9 Rodents also differ from humans in several aspects 
of metabolism. For example, rats have a higher activity of 
liver enzymes involved in altering the chemical structure of 
fats 10 and liver CYP enzymes involved in drug metabolism. 11 
Compared to human hepatocytes, rat hepatocytes are 
much less susceptible to carcinogenic factors and mutagenic-
ity. 12 Absence of a gall bladder in rats enables certain fats to 
be secreted directly into the intestine; 13 thus, rats have an 
increased ability to eliminate cholesterol from the body. 
Unlike humans, rats are capable of liver vitamin C synthesis 
de novo, 14 resulting in 2.5-fold higher levels of vitamin C in 
their bodies compared to humans. 15 Rats also have a higher 
metabolic rate than other mammals and indeterminant 
growth, thus have a higher demand for energy relative to 
their small body size compared to human requirements. 16 
In spite of all this, the similarities between rodents and humans 
are still sufficient to justify use of rodents as models of human 
disease, 8 but attention in design and interpretation of each 
experiment is required. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Scientific articles were obtained through <rs type="software">PubMed</rs> MEDLINE 
searches containing the following search strings: (((cancer 
OR neoplasm OR carcinoma OR malignant OR metastases) 
AND (mouse OR mice OR murine OR rats)) AND cachexia) 
AND (diet OR nutrition OR nutrient). Papers that did not 
include a nutrient intervention were excluded as well as 
interventions that involved pharmaceutical agents (Figure 1). 
In the 1970s the American Institute of Nutrition (AIN) began 
to develop semi-purified diets, with these diets becoming 
more readily used and commercially available after 1985. </p>

<p>Diet composition in experimental animal models of cancer cachexia </p>



<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

<p>For this reason, papers before 1985 were not included in the 
present review. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The search captured 353 papers in the initial search (Figure 1). 
After removal of studies not meeting the inclusion criteria, 
44 papers investigating a number of nutrient interventions 
remained (see Figure 1). The majority of studies applying a 
nutrient intervention involved n-3 fatty acids, mainly 
eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA; 20:5n-3) and/or docosahexaenoic 
acid (DHA; 22:6n-3) (n = 16 studies). This review will focus in </p>

<p>detail on the influences of dietary content on the results and 
interpretation of studies, with an emphasis on study designs 
applying interventions with various lipid sources. </p>

<p>Important variations in the delivery of 
experimental diets </p>

<p>The majority of pre-clinical models reviewed in the literature 
provide diets ad libitum (free access), while fewer studies 
control daily food intakes with fixed amounts. 17,18 Certain 
animal strains may require food to be delivered in controlled 
daily amounts to prevent over-feeding. 17 In contrast, 
providing diets ad libitum when food intake is also recorded </p>

<p>Figure 1 Search results and paper exclusion. </p>

<p>112 </p>

<p>K. Giles et al. </p>

<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

<p>may enable researchers to associate the amount of nutrient 
intake with outcome measures. Form of diet delivery may 
explain differences in study outcomes if animals ate different 
amounts of food during the study. Typical outcomes in 
cachexia studies include muscle mass and weight loss, both 
of which are intimately related to food intake. Regardless of 
the diet control, food intake is an essential measure particu-
larly when nutrient intakes are associated with study 
outcomes. The use of rodent models also enables pair 
feeding which would not be ethically conceivable in human 
subjects and allows precise manipulation of dietary intakes 
while accounting for the effects of food intake per se on 
experimental outcomes. </p>

<p>Composition of experimental animal diets </p>

<p>Animal diets used in the laboratory are categorized into three 
main groups: cereal-based (non-purified) chow, purified or 
semi-purified, and chemically defined diets. 19 Diets either 
have an open formula, indicating that the dietary composi-
tion has been published and is available to the scientific 
community, or diets can have a closed formula, indicating 
the dietary composition and ingredients are known only to 
the manufacturer. 20 Chemically defined, or elemental diets, 
are made of purified triglycerides, free fatty acids, free amino 
acids, sugars, vitamins, and minerals. 21 Semi-purified diets 
are composed of purified proteins, starch, sugars, and 
defined lipid components from specified fats and oils. </p>

<p>Standard laboratory chow diets 
From the body of literature reviewed, it is clear that the 
majority of diets used are standard laboratory chow from 
commercial sources provided ab libitum (free access). Two 
of the most common laboratory rodent chows are the 
Standard Rat and Mouse Breeding Diet from Pilsbury 
(Birmingham, UK) and Panlab Laboratory Chow (Barcelona, 
Spain). Laboratory chow does not have a standard macronu-
trient composition, and is formulated from plant materials, 
meat meal, fishmeal, and fats that are rarely defined. 21 
Standard laboratory chow diets vary from batch to batch, 
and individual ingredients may also vary over time. 22,23 
Chows with closed formulas are incompletely characterized, 
making it nearly impossible to determine exactly what is in 
a particular batch. 21 These factors make it difficult to report 
the composition of lab chow, aside from the manufacturers 
name, since a batch fed five years ago will be different from 
a batch fed one year ago making results from individual 
studies difficult to replicate in future studies. Laboratory 
chow aims to meet the essential requirements for a rodent, 
but is delivered pre-mixed, making it difficult to modify. 21 
Most laboratory chows provide the minimum requirement 
for essential fatty acids for rodents, usually 1.5% total </p>

<p>diet, 24,25 and the primary source of fat in standard laboratory 
chow diet is most often corn oil. 26 
Laboratory chow diets also contain micronutrients or 
compounds that are unknown to researchers and may impact 
study endpoints and results. For example, many commonly 
used natural-ingredient laboratory chows use soy as a protein 
source, inadvertently adding phytoestrogens to the diet in 
the form of isoflavones. 27 A number of studies have 
investigated the effects of using laboratory chow in animal 
models of breast cancer and endocrine/hormonal organ 
systems 28,29 have determined that the variability in commer-
cial rodent chow diets interferes with the value of these 
animal models and experimental results. 27 The variation in 
isoflavone content between formulations of rodent chow 
and between batches of the same formulation has been 
shown to be several fold different. 27 A number of studies 
have also found chemicals present in rodent chow such as 
arsenic, 30 mercury, 31 and polychlorinated dioxins, 32 with 
these chemicals having the potential to exert effects on gene 
expression and phenotypic outcomes. Chow diets may 
significantly alter effects of experimental treatments, and in 
particular, affect gene and protein expression. </p>

<p>Purified, semi-purified, and nutritionally made diets 
The most common commercial source for semi-purified diets 
is the American Institute of Nutrition (AIN) formulation. The 
AIN first developed these diets to reduce the variance when 
researchers developed their own formulations. Results from 
studies prior to AIN-developed diets were difficult to 
compare across studies and nutrition disciplines. The original 
AIN diet was the AIN-76A formulation, which was later 
revised and replaced by AIN-93. 33 AIN-93 diets are offered 
in Growth (G) or Maintenance (M) forms, depending on the 
age of the animals being fed. AIN semi-purified diets are 
available without macronutrients and micronutrients, which 
enables researchers to formulate and alter the diet according 
to the particular study objectives. As opposed to corn oil, 
which was used in AIN diets prior to 1993, soybean oil has 
been used since 1993 which, compared to corn oil, has a 
more balanced fatty acid composition [15% saturated fat, 
54% linoleic acid (n-6 fatty acid), 8% alpha linoleic acid (n-3 
fatty acid), 23% oleic acid (n-9 fatty acid)]. Unlike protein 
meal used in chow diets, the protein source is purified and 
contains high quality defined protein sources. 
In comparison to laboratory chow, the ingredients included 
in purified or semi-purified diets are considered open formu-
las and are well characterized. There are several benefits to 
using semi-/purified diets over laboratory chow in murine 
study designs. When diet modifications occur in nutrient 
interventions, semi-purified diets provide a benefit over 
laboratory chow; if the nutrient intervention involves a 
modification of the fat source, semi-purified diets enable fats 
to be added and modified by the researcher. For example, 
corn oil can be substituted for olive oil, safflower oil, fish </p>

<p>Diet composition in experimental animal models of cancer cachexia </p>



<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

<p>oil, or individual fatty acids of interest to determine effects of 
fatty acids or to enable matching of fatty acid composition 
between experimental groups. Furthermore, semi-purified 
diets allow researchers to modify fat quantity, and the propor-
tion each type of fat contributes to the diet as a whole. </p>

<p>The influence of background diet on results of 
nutritional interventions </p>

<p>In nutrient intervention studies, little attention is paid to 
background diets for their particular nutrient of interest. 
The phrase, 'a standard rodent chow was used' is written fre-
quently, indicating that the content and composition of the 
animal diet are either unknown to researchers, or considered </p>

<p>unimportant. 27 Knowing the composition and quantity of the 
diet fed is required to interpret findings relative to human 
disease states. After meeting nutritional requirements of 
the rat, the first criteria in dietary design are formulating 
the comparison diets to be isocaloric and isonitrogenous 
between treatment and control diets within the same study 
(Figure 2). Although studies may define dietary compositions 
in detail, fundamental matching of calories and nitrogen 
content between diets is often overlooked 34-36 (Table 1). 
Second, proportions of macro-and micronutrients could be 
made similar to human intakes (Figure 2). 
A review of the literature reveals that many dietary designs 
do not subscribe to the criteria outlined in Figure 2. In 
three similar studies, male NMRI mice were implanted with 
MAC16 tumour cells, and supplemented with medium-chain </p>

<p>Figure 2 Proposed dietary design flow chart. </p>



<p>K. Giles et al. </p>

<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

<p>Table 1 Preclinical studies with a nutrient intervention </p>

<p>Reference [#] </p>

<p>Animal + tumour 
model </p>

<p>Nutrient 
intervention </p>

<p>Isonitrogenous/ 
isocaloric </p>

<p>Diet control </p>

<p>Diet composition </p>

<p>Fish Oil, EPA 
± DHA interventions </p>

<p>Costelli et al., </p>

<p>1995 37 </p>

<p>Lack of effect of EPA in 
preventing cancer cachexia </p>

<p>and inhibiting tumour growth </p>

<p>Male Wistar rats bearing 
Yoshida AH-130 ascites 
hepatoma </p>

<p>EPA as fatty acid 
methyl esters </p>

<p>Not isocaloric or 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Ad libitum 
Background diet: standard laboratory chow 
Source/brand: Panlab (Barcelona, Spain) </p>

<p>(1) Control diet: standard laboratory chow 
(2) Treatment diet: daily intragastric dose of EPA 
(1.5 g/kgBW); </p>

<p>-Complete diet compositions not defined </p>

<p>Dagnelie et al., </p>

<p>1994 24 </p>

<p>Effects of 
fish oil on cancer </p>

<p>cachexia and host liver 
metabolism in rats with </p>

<p>prostate tumours </p>

<p>Copenhagen-Fisher F1 hybrid </p>

<p>rats inoculated with MATLy-
Lu prostate tumour cells </p>

<p>EPA </p>

<p>Isocaloric and 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Ad libitum 
Background diet: standard laboratory chow (control diet); 
semi-purified 
fish oil (FO) diet </p>

<p>Source/brand: Rat and mouse breeding diet, Pilsbury, 
Birmingham, United Kingdom (control diet); source 
undefined (FO diet) </p>

<p>(1) Control diet: standard laboratory chow containing 
50% total kcal carbohydrates, 20% total kcal protein, 
11.5% total kcal fat </p>

<p>(2) FO diet: semi-purified diet, undefined, containing 50% total 
kcal coming from 
fish oil, which substituted for carbohydrates </p>

<p>-Complete diet compositions not defined </p>

<p>Dumas et al., </p>

<p>2010 38 </p>

<p>N-3 PUFA-enriched diet 
delays the occurrence of 
cancer cachexia in rat with 
peritoneal carcinosis </p>

<p>Male Berlin Druckery IX 
(BDIX) rats bearing DHD/K12 
cells from a dimethyl-
hydrazine induced colon 
tumour </p>

<p>Fish oil (FO) 
EPA/DHA </p>

<p>Isocaloric and 
isonitrogenous 
Representative of human </p>

<p>intakes </p>

<p>Ad libitum 
Background diet: semi-purified diet 
Source/brand: undefined </p>

<p>(1) Control diet (g/kg): casein (220), sucrose (187), cellulose 
(20), DL-methionine (1.6), mineral mixture (40), vitamin 
mixture (no vitamin E; 10), cornstarch (371.4), lipids (150): 
12% peanut oil, 3% rapeseed oil </p>

<p>(2) FO diet (g/kg): casein (220), sucrose (187), cellulose (20), 
DL-methionine (1.6), mineral mixture (40), vitamin mixture </p>

<p>(no vitamin E; 10), cornstarch (371.4), lipids (150): 8% peanut 
oil, 2% rapeseed oil, 5% </p>

<p>fish oil </p>

<p>(3) Pair-fed group: control diet 
-Complete diet composition defined 
-Both diets (1) and (2) contain 4460 kcal/kg diet 
-Nature of lipids changed in both diets 
-Fat accounts for ~28% total kcal diets (1) and (2) </p>

<p>Fini et al., </p>

<p>2010 17 </p>

<p>Highly purified EPA as free 
fatty acids strongly 
suppresses Polyps in </p>

<p>Apc </p>

<p>Min/+ </p>

<p>mice </p>

<p>Male Apc </p>

<p>Min/+ </p>

<p>mice on a </p>

<p>C57BL/6J background and 
corresponding wild-type </p>

<p>(wt) mice </p>

<p>99% pure 
preparation of </p>

<p>EPA as n-3 free 
fatty acids </p>

<p>Isocaloric and 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Controlled 
Background diet: semi-purified 
Source/brand: AIN-93G diet: 18.8% total kcal protein, 16.4% </p>

<p>total kcal fat, 65.1% total kcal carbohydrates (Research Diets) 
(1) Control diet: modified AIN-93G diet, corn oil substituted 
for soybean oil </p>

<p>(2) EPA diet: modified AIN-93G diet, soybean oil substituted 
for EPA free fatty acids at 2.5% weight/weight (w/w) </p>

<p>(3) EPA diet: modified AIN-93G diet, soybean oil substituted 
for EPA free fatty acids at 5% w/w </p>

<p>-Complete diet compositions defined 
-99% EPA-FFA in </p>

<p>fish oil diets </p>

<p>-Soybean oil substituted for EPA in varying amounts (w/w) in 
diets (2) and (3) </p>

<p>Griffini et al., </p>

<p>1998 65 </p>

<p>Dietary omega-3 PUFAs 
promote colon carcinoma 
metastasis in rat liver </p>

<p>Male and female Wag-rij 
rats bearing CC531 colon 
carcinoma cells </p>

<p>Fish oil (FO) 
EPA/DHA </p>

<p>Not isocaloric or 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Ab libitum </p>

<p>Background diet: </p>

<p>semi-purified </p>

<p>Source/brand: Hope Farms (Woerden, The Netherlands); </p>

<p>standard diets contain 41% total kcal carbohydrates, 38% total kcal </p>

<p>fat, 20% total kcal protein </p>

<p>(Continues) </p>

<p>Diet composition in experimental animal models of cancer cachexia </p>



<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

<p>(Continues) </p>

<p>Table 1 (Continued) 
Reference [#] </p>

<p>Animal + tumour 
model </p>

<p>Nutrient 
intervention </p>

<p>Isonitrogenous/ 
isocaloric </p>

<p>Diet control </p>

<p>Diet composition </p>

<p>(1) Low fat diet: 69% total kcal carbohydrates, 20% total kcal 
protein; 11% total kcal fat </p>

<p>(2) n-6 PUFA diet (safflower oil): 41% total kcal carbohydrates, 
38% total kcal fat, 20% total kcal protein </p>

<p>(3) n-3 PUFA diet (fish oil): 41% total kcal carbohydrates, 38% total 
kcal fat, 20% total kcal protein </p>

<p>-Complete dietary composition defined 
-Fat source in n-6 PUFA diet is safflower oil; fat source in n-3 
PUFA diet is </p>

<p>fish oil </p>

<p>Jho et al., </p>

<p>2002 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Eicosapentaenoic acid 
supplementation reduces </p>

<p>tumour volume and 
attenuates cachexia in a rat </p>

<p>model of progressive non-
metastasizing malignancy </p>

<p>Fischer 344 rats bearing the 
methylchol-anthrene-induced </p>

<p>fibrosarcoma (MCA) tumour </p>

<p>EPA </p>

<p>Not isocaloric or 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Controlled 
Background diet: undefined 
Source/brand: undefined </p>

<p>(1) Control diet: undefined, oral gavage isovolemic 5.0 g/kg per 
day of corn oil (isocaloric) combined with 10 IU vitamin E/g 
fat, or isovolemic but nonisocaloric normal saline (NS) 
combined with 10 IU vitamin E/g NS </p>

<p>(2) EPA diet: undefined, oral gavage twice daily, providing 5.0 g/kg 
per day of EPA with 10 IU vitamin E/g fat </p>

<p>-Complete dietary compositions undefined </p>

<p>Mannini et al., </p>

<p>2009 </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>Dietary n-3 polyunsaturated 
fatty acids enhance 
metastatic dissemination of 
murine T lymphoma cells </p>

<p>C57B1/6 mice bearing (i) 
highly metastatic S11 cell 
line or (ii) low-metastatic 
164T2 lymphoma cell line </p>

<p>Fish oil (FO) 
EPA/DHA </p>

<p>Isonitrogenous and </p>

<p>isocaloric </p>

<p>Ab libitum 
Background diet: semi-purified 
Source/brand: undefined </p>

<p>(1) Maize oil (MO) diet: 70% sucrose, 16% casein, 3% 
alpha-cellulose, 1% choline chloride, 1% vitamins, 4% salt </p>

<p>mixture, 5% maize oil </p>

<p>(2) FO diet: 70% sucrose, 16% casein, 3% alpha-cellulose, 
1% choline chloride, 1% vitamins, 4% salt mixture, 5% </p>

<p>fish oil </p>

<p>-Complete dietary composition defined 
-Both diets contain: 72% total kcal carbohydrates, 16% total kcal 
protein, 12% total kcal fat </p>

<p>Pizato et al., </p>

<p>2005 39 </p>

<p>Ratio of n-6 to n-3 fatty 
acids in the diet affects 
tumour growth and 
cachexia in Walker 256 
tumour-bearing rats </p>

<p>Male Wistar rats bearing 
the Walker 256 tumour </p>

<p>Fish oil (FO) </p>

<p>Isonitrogenous, not </p>

<p>isocaloric </p>

<p>Ab libitum 
Background diet: standard laboratory chow (control group), 
semi-purified diet (treatment diets) 
Source/brand: Nuvital CR-1, Curitiba, Brazil (control diet); </p>

<p>undefined semi-purified source </p>

<p>(1) Control group: standard chow diet, 62% total kcal 
carbohydrates, 29% total kcal protein, 9% total kcal fat </p>

<p>Pizato et al., </p>

<p>2005 39 </p>

<p>Ratio of n-6 to n-3 fatty 
acids in the diet affects 
tumour growth and 
cachexia in Walker 256 
tumour-bearing rats </p>

<p>Male Wistar rats bearing 
the Walker 256 tumour </p>

<p>Fish oil (FO) </p>

<p>Isonitrogenous, not </p>

<p>isocaloric </p>

<p>Ab libitum 
Background diet: standard laboratory chow (control group), 
semi-purified diet (treatment diets) </p>

<p>Source/brand: Nuvital </p>

<p>CR-1, Curitiba, Brazil (control diet); undefined semi-purified source 
(1) Control group: standard chow diet, 62% total kcal 
carbohydrates, 29% total kcal protein, 9% total kcal fat </p>

<p>(2) High-fat diet: modified standard laboratory chow, 49% total 
kcal fat, 29% total kcal carbohydrates, 22% total kcal 
protein; 33% of fat substituted as coconut oil </p>

<p>(3) N-3 diet high-fat FO diet: same background as (2) High-fat diet, 
but 66% of fat as substituted as FO </p>

<p>(4) N-6 diet high fat sunflower oil diet: same background as (2) 
High-fat diet, but 66% fat substituted as sunflower oil </p>



<p>K. Giles et al. </p>

<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

<p>Table 1 (Continued) </p>

<p>Reference [#] </p>

<p>Animal + tumour 
model </p>

<p>Nutrient 
intervention </p>

<p>Isonitrogenous/ 
isocaloric </p>

<p>Diet control </p>

<p>Diet composition </p>

<p>(5) 6:1 diet: 49% total kcal fat, 29% total kcal 
carbohydrates, 22% total kcal protein; 33% of fat </p>

<p>substituted as coconut oil and 66% as blend of FO </p>

<p>and sunflower oil to yield n-6 to n-3 PUFA ratios of 
approximately 6:1 </p>

<p>(6) 30:1 diet: same background as [6:1 diet]; 66% of fat 
substituted as a blend of FO and sunflower oil to </p>

<p>yield n-6 to n-3 PUFA ratios of approximately 30:1 </p>

<p>(7) 60:1 diet: same background as [6:1 diet]; 66% of fat 
substituted as a blend of FO and sunflower oil to </p>

<p>yield n-6 to n-3 PUFA ratios of approximately 60:1 </p>

<p>-Complete dietary composition defined 
-Oils blended to maintain linoleic acid content consistency; n-6 
to n-3 PUFA ratio was changed by altering n-3 PUFA content 
-All diets contained the same amounts of protein (230 g/kg), 
fibre (60 g/kg), and vitamins and minerals (10 g/kg) </p>

<p>Pizato et al., </p>

<p>2006 40 
Fish oil </p>

<p>alter T-lymphocyte proliferation 
and macrophage responses in 
Walker 256 tumour-bearing rats </p>

<p>Male Wistar rats bearing 
the Walker 256 tumour </p>

<p>Fish oil (FO) </p>

<p>Isonitrogenous, not </p>

<p>isocaloric </p>

<p>Ab libitum 
Same diet as Pizato et al., </p>

<p>2005; See reference #9. </p>

<p>Fish oil, EPA/DHA in combination with other nutrients </p>

<p>Hudson et al., </p>

<p>1994 41 </p>

<p>Comparison of the 
effectiveness of 
eicosapentaenoic acid </p>

<p>administered as either the </p>

<p>free acid or ethyl ester as an 
anticachectic and 
antitumour agent </p>

<p>NMRI mice bearing the 
MAC16 colon 
adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>EPA as free fatty 
acids or ethyl ester 
Medium chain 
triglycerides (MCT) </p>

<p>Not isocaloric or 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Ab libitum 
Background diet: standard laboratory chow 
Source/brand: rat and mouse breeding diet, Pilsbury, 
Birmingham, United Kingdom </p>

<p>(1) Control diet: standard laboratory chow, 11.5% total kcal as fat 
(2) EPA diet: modified standard laboratory chow with 80% as 
EPA ethyl esters </p>

<p>(3) MCT diet: modified standard laboratory chow with 80% as MCT 
-Complete dietary compositions undefined 
-Unidentified route of oral administration of EPA as free fatty 
acid form or ethyl ester form 
-Complete dietary compositions undefined 
-Unidentified route of oral administration of EPA as 
free fatty acid form or ethyl ester form </p>

<p>Tisdale et al., </p>

<p>1990 25 </p>

<p>Inhibition of weight loss by </p>

<p>n-3 fatty acids in an 
experimental cachexia </p>

<p>model </p>

<p>NMRI mice bearing the 
MAC16 tumour </p>

<p>Fish oil (FO) 
Medium chain 
triglycerides </p>

<p>(MCT) </p>

<p>Isocaloric and 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Ab libitum 
Background diet: standard laboratory chow (control diet); 
semi-purified 
fish oil (FO) diet </p>

<p>Source/brand: rat and mouse breeding diet, Pilsbury, 
Birmingham, United Kingdom (control diet); source 
undefined (FO and MCT diets) </p>

<p>(1) Standard breeding diet for all groups; 50% total kcal 
carbohydrates, 20% total kcal protein, 11.5% total kcal fat </p>

<p>Total kcal from fat: 
(2) 5% FO 
(3) 10% FO 
(4) 25% FO 
(5) 25% FO + 55% MCT 
(6) 50% FO </p>

<p>(Continues) </p>

<p>Diet composition in experimental animal models of cancer cachexia </p>



<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

<p>Table 1 (Continued) </p>

<p>Reference [#] </p>

<p>Animal + tumour 
model </p>

<p>Nutrient 
intervention </p>

<p>Isonitrogenous/ 
isocaloric </p>

<p>Diet control </p>

<p>Diet composition </p>

<p>(7) 50% FO + 30% MCT 
-Complete dietary composition defined 
-Isocaloric and isonitrogenous diets were prepared by 
decreasing the carbohydrate content and supplying </p>

<p>the remaining energy from either FO or MCT </p>

<p>Bonatto et al., </p>

<p>2006 42 </p>

<p>Lifelong exposure to dietary </p>

<p>fish oil alters macrophage 
responses in Walker 256 
tumor-bearing rats 
Male wister rats, bearing 
Walker-256 tumour </p>

<p>Fish oil (FO) 
Coconut oil (CO) </p>

<p>Not isocaloric or 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Ab libitum 
Background diet: standard laboratory chow 
Source/brand: undefined </p>

<p>(1) Control diet: Standard laboratory chow 
(2) CO Diet: Standard laboratory chow + oral micropipette bolus 
dose of coconut oil (1 g/kgBW) </p>

<p>(3) FO Diet: Standard laboratory chow + oral micropipette 
bolus dose of 
fish oil (1 g/kgBW) </p>

<p>-Complete dietary composition not defined 
-Fish oil is mixed marine triacylglycerol preparation 
containing 180 g EPA, 120 g DHA per kg </p>

<p>Busquets et al., </p>

<p>2007 43 </p>

<p>Resveratrol does not 
ameliorate muscle wasting </p>

<p>in different types of cancer 
cachexia models </p>

<p>Male Wistar rats bearing 
Yoshida AH-130 ascites 
hepatoma or Lewis Lung 
C57Bl/6 mice bearing 
Yoshida AH-130 ascites 
hepatoma or Lewis Lung </p>

<p>Resveratrol Fish </p>

<p>oil (FO) </p>

<p>Not isocaloric or 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Ad libitum 
Background diet: undefined 
Source/brand: undefined </p>

<p>Yoshida AH-130 ascites hepatoma diets: </p>

<p>(1) Resveratrol-treated: Daily i.p. dose of resveratrol (1 mg/kgBW) 
(2) Untreated: saline i.p. dose (1 mg/kgBW) 
(3) Combination treatment, FO + resveratrol: intragastric 
injection of 1 mL FO + 3 mg/kgBW resveratrol dissolved in FO </p>

<p>(4) Control treatment: intragastric injection of 1 mL olive oil 
Lewis lung carcinoma diets: 
(1) Resveratrol-treated: i.p. dose of resveratrol (5 or 25 mg/kg BW) 
(2) Untreated: i.p. dose of saline (5 or 25 mg/kg BW) </p>

<p>Cremades et al., </p>

<p>2007 44 </p>

<p>Nutritional treatment of </p>

<p>cancer cachexia in rats </p>

<p>Male Wistar rats bearing 
Yoshida AH-130 ascites 
hepatoma </p>

<p>Crayfish enzymatic 
extract (CFEE) 
containing n-3 </p>

<p>fatty acid </p>

<p>Isocaloric and 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Ad libitum 
Background diet: semi-purified 
Source/brand: AIN-76A diet (Research Diets) </p>

<p>(1) Standard diet: consisting of 63.5% carbohydrate (corn 
starch, sucrose), 12% protein (casein) and 5% fat (olive oil); 
the difference to 100% comprised of minerals, vitamins and 
non-digestible material </p>

<p>(2) CFEE diet: consisting of 63.5% carbohydrate (corn starch, 
sucrose), 12% protein (crayfish enzymatic extract) and </p>

<p>5% fat (olive oil); the difference to 100% comprised of 
minerals, vitamins and non-digestible material </p>

<p>-Complete dietary composition defined 
-Both diets contain: 79% total kcal carbohydrates, 15% total 
kcal protein, 6% total kcal fat 
-CFEE contains high-quality proteins, essential amino 
acids, n-3 fatty acids, and carotenoids </p>

<p>Faber et al., </p>

<p>2008 34 </p>

<p>Beneficial immune 
modulatory effects of a </p>

<p>specific nutritional 
combination in a murine </p>

<p>model for cancer cachexia </p>

<p>Male CD2F1 (BALB/c × DBA/2) 
mice bearing C26 
adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>Fish oil (FO) Specific 
oligo-saccharide 
mixture (SOM) 
High protein leucine 
formulation (HPLeu) </p>

<p>Experiment A: </p>

<p>Not </p>

<p>isonitrogenous or isocaloric </p>

<p>Experiment B: </p>

<p>not 
isonitrogenous or isocaloric 
Representative of human </p>

<p>intakes </p>

<p>Ad libitum </p>

<p>Experiments A: 
Background diet: semi-purified diet 
Source/brand: AIN93-M diet (Research Diets) </p>

<p>(1) Control diet (g/kg): 126 g protein (100% casein), 727 g 
carbohydrates and 40 g fat (100% soy oil) </p>

<p>(2) FO diet: control diet + 22.1 g </p>

<p>fish oil (6.9 g EPA and 3.1 g </p>

<p>DHA) per kg food </p>

<p>(Continues) </p>



<p>K. Giles et al. </p>

<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

<p>Table 1 (Continued) </p>

<p>Reference [#] </p>

<p>Animal + tumour 
model </p>

<p>Nutrient 
intervention </p>

<p>Isonitrogenous/ 
isocaloric </p>

<p>Diet control </p>

<p>Diet composition </p>

<p>(3) SOM diet: control diet + 18 g short-chain galacto-
oligosaccharides and 2 g short-chain fructo-
oligosaccharides per kg food </p>

<p>(4) HPLeu: control diet + 151 g casein and 16 g leucine 
per kg food 
Experiments B: 
Background diet: semi-purified diet </p>

<p>(1) Control diet (g/kg): 126 g protein (100% casein), 699 g 
carbohydrates and 52.6 g fat (100% corn oil) </p>

<p>(2) Nutritional mixture diet: 210 g protein (189 g intact protein 
of which 68% casein, 32% whey, 21 g free leucine), 561 g 
carbohydrates, 52.5 g fat (20.2 g corn oil, 10.2 g canola oil </p>

<p>and 22.1 g 
fish oil (providing 6.9 g EPA and 3.1 g DHA)), </p>

<p>18 g short-chain galacto-oligosaccharides and 2 g 
short-chain fructo-oligosaccharides </p>

<p>-Complete dietary compositions defined 
-Category B experiment control diet was a more humanized diet 
-Both control diets in Experiments A and B were 
isonitrogenous and isocaloric (Exp. A: 3773 kcal/kg </p>

<p>diet; Exp. B: 3772 kcal/kg diet) with varying proportions of 
macronutrients: 
•Experiment A: 74% total kcal carbohydrates, 13% </p>

<p>total kcal protein, 13% total kcal fat 
•Experiment B: 77% total kcal carbohydrates, 13% </p>

<p>total kcal protein, 10% total kcal fat </p>

<p>Van Norren et al., </p>

<p>2009 36 </p>

<p>Dietary supplementation with a 
specific combination of high 
protein, leucine, and </p>

<p>fish oil </p>

<p>improves muscle function and </p>

<p>daily activity in tumour-bearing 
cachectic mice </p>

<p>Male CD2F1 (BALB/c × 
DBA/2) mice bearing C26 
adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>Fish oil (FO) 
Specific oligo-
saccharide mixture </p>

<p>(SOM) High 
protein leucine 
formulation </p>

<p>(HPLeu) </p>

<p>Experiment A: </p>

<p>Not </p>

<p>isonitrogenous or isocaloric </p>

<p>Experiment B: </p>

<p>not 
isonitrogenous or isocaloric 
Representative of human </p>

<p>intakes </p>

<p>Ad libitum 
Same diet as Faber et al., </p>

<p>2008; See reference #15. </p>

<p>Togni et al., </p>

<p>2003 45 </p>

<p>Cancer </p>

<p>cachexia and tumour growth 
reduction in Walker 256 
tumour-bearing rats 
supplemented with n-3 
polyunsaturated fatty acids </p>

<p>for one generation </p>

<p>Female Wistar rats bearing </p>

<p>the Walker 256 tumour </p>

<p>Fish oil (FO) 
Coconut oil (CO) </p>

<p>Not isocaloric or 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Ad libitum 
Background diet: standard laboratory chow Source/brand: 
undefined (1) Control diet: standard laboratory chow (2) FO 
treatment: standard laboratory chow, supplemented orally </p>

<p>with 
fish oil (3) CO treatment: standard laboratory chow, 
supplemented orally with coconut oil -Complete dietary 
compositions not defined -Oils were supplemented at a level </p>

<p>of 1 g/kg body weight per day and were provided as a single 
bolus using a pipette </p>

<p>Other nutrient interventions </p>

<p>Beck et al., </p>

<p>1989 46 </p>

<p>Nitrogen </p>

<p>excretion in cancer cachexia and </p>

<p>its modification by a high fat 
diet in mice </p>

<p>NMRI mice bearing 
MAC16 tumour </p>

<p>Medium-chain 
triglycerides (MCT) 
Not isocaloric or 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Ad libitum 
Background diet: standard laboratory chow Source/brand: rat </p>

<p>and mouse breeding diet, Pilsbury, Birmingham, United 
Kingdom (1) Control diet: standard laboratory chow; 11.5% </p>

<p>total kcal as fat (2) MCT diet: modified standard laboratory 
chow with 80% total kcal from MCT (3) Standard diet, water 
supplemented with sodium D-(À)-3-hydroxybutyrate at </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>μmol/mL </p>

<p>-Complete dietary compositions not defined </p>

<p>(Continues) </p>

<p>Diet composition in experimental animal models of cancer cachexia </p>



<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

<p>Table 1 (Continued) </p>

<p>Reference [#] </p>

<p>Animal + tumour 
model </p>

<p>Nutrient 
intervention </p>

<p>Isonitrogenous/ 
isocaloric </p>

<p>Diet control </p>

<p>Diet composition </p>

<p>Tisdale et al., </p>

<p>1987 47 </p>

<p>Reduction of weight loss </p>

<p>and tumour size in a 
cachexia model by a high fat </p>

<p>diet </p>

<p>Male NMRI mice bearing 
MAC16 tumour </p>

<p>Medium-chain 
triglycerides </p>

<p>(MCT) </p>

<p>Not isocaloric or 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Ad libitum 
Background diet: standard laboratory chow (control diet); 
semi-purified 
fish oil (FO) diet </p>

<p>Source/brand: rat and mouse breeding diet, Pilsbury, 
Birmingham, United Kingdom (control diet); source 
undefined (MCT diet) </p>

<p>(1) Control diet: standard laboratory chow; 50% total kcal 
carbohydrates, 20% total kcal protein, 11.5% total kcal fat </p>

<p>(2) High-fat diet: authors indicated there was a reduced 
carbohydrate proportion, and 80% total kcal from 
medium-chain triglyceride </p>

<p>-Complete dietary compositions not defined </p>

<p>Graves et al., </p>

<p>2005 6 </p>

<p>Conjugated </p>

<p>linoleic acid preserves 
gastrocnemius muscle mass in </p>

<p>mice bearing the colon-26 
adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>Female CD2F1 mice bearing 
C26 adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>Conjugated linoleic </p>

<p>acid (CLA) </p>

<p>Not isocaloric or 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Ad libitum 
Background diet: standard laboratory chow Source/brand: 
undefined (1) Control diet: pulverized rodent chow (2) CLA </p>

<p>diet: pulverized rodent chow supplemented with 0.5% CLA </p>

<p>-Complete dietary compositions not defined </p>

<p>Gomes-Marcondes et al., </p>

<p>2002 35 </p>

<p>A leucine-supplemented diet 
improved protein content of 
skeletal muscle in young tumour-
bearing rats </p>

<p>Male Wistar rats bearing 
Walker 256 carcinoma </p>

<p>Leucine </p>

<p>Isocaloric </p>

<p>Ad libitum 
Background diet: semi-purified Source/brand: AIN-93G 
(Research Diets) (1) Control diet: modified AIN-93G diet, 
containing 15% protein (2) Leucine diet: modified AIN-93G </p>

<p>diet, containing 15% protein supplemented with 3% leucine </p>

<p>-Complete dietary compositions not defined since AIN-93G 
standard diet was modified for protein </p>

<p>Iizuka et al., </p>

<p>2002 48 </p>

<p>Anticachectic </p>

<p>effects of the natural herb 
Coptidis rhizoma 
and berberine </p>

<p>on mice bearing colon 
26/clone-20 adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>Male BALB/c mice bearing 
C26 adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>Coptidis rhizoma </p>

<p>(CR) herb + 
berberine </p>

<p>Isonitrogenous and </p>

<p>isocaloric </p>

<p>Ad libitum 
Background diet: standard laboratory chow Source/brand: F1 
breeding diet (Funabashi Farm, Funabashi, Japan) (1) Control </p>

<p>diet: standard laboratory chow, Funabashi Farms containing 
21.3% protein, 57.1% carbohydrates, 5.6% fat, 3.3% </p>

<p>fibre, </p>

<p>5.7% ash, and 7.0% moisture (2) Treatment: standard 
laboratory chow (same as control diet); C. rhizoma </p>

<p>was </p>

<p>incorporated into breeding diet at a </p>

<p>final concentration of </p>

<p>1% (10 mg/g) or 2% (20 mg/g); berberine was added at a </p>

<p>final </p>

<p>concentration of 0.1% (1 mg/g) to 0.4% (4 mg/g) at </p>

<p>Funabashi Farms (3) Pair-fed group: standard laboratory </p>

<p>chow -Complete dietary composition defined -Both diets (1) 
and (2) contained 63% total kcal carbohydrates, 23% total 
kcal protein, 14% total kcal fat </p>

<p>Carbo et al., </p>

<p>1999 49 </p>

<p>Resveratrol, a natural product </p>

<p>present in wine, increases 
tumour growth in a rat tumour 
model </p>

<p>Male Wistar bearing Yoshida 
AH-130 ascites hepatoma </p>

<p>Resveratrol </p>

<p>Not isocaloric or 
isonitrogenous </p>

<p>Ad libitum 
Background diet: standard laboratory show Source/brand: </p>

<p>Panlab (Barcelona, Spain) (1) Control diet: standard 
laboratory chow, 71% total kcal carbohydrates, 22% total </p>

<p>kcal protein, 7% total kcal fat (2) Resveratrol treatment: 
standard laboratory chow + i.p. injection of 1 mg/kgBW 
resveratrol per day -Complete dietary composition not 
defined </p>



<p>K. Giles et al. </p>

<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

<p>triglycerides 46,47 and eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA; Table 1). 41 
Mice were fed a rat/mouse breeding diet ad libitum for 2 weeks 
before a dietary intervention began. Mice were randomized 
into diet groups containing 11.5% total energy from fat (source 
and composition unspecified by Beck and Tisdale, 1989 46 and 
Hudson and Tisdale, 1994; 41 palm oil used in control diet in 
by Tisdale, Brennan and Fearon, 1987 47 ). All three studies 
modified the control diet to consist of 80% of total energy from 
medium-chain triglycerides, and Hudson et al. 41 included a sec-
ond treatment diet group, which consisted of 80% total energy 
from EPA ethyl esters. The proportions of fat in the diets within 
the same study are not similar to each other, nor are they 
congruent with human intakes. In another study, male Wistar 
rats bearing the Yoshida AH-130 ascites hepatoma, animals 
were randomized to receive resveratrol injections, or saline 
injections while consuming standard laboratory chow. 49 The 
diet consisted of 71% total kcal carbohydrates, 22% total kcal 
protein, and 7% total kcal fat. In contrast to the very high 
contribution of fat to the diets in Beck et al., 46 Hudson 
et al., 41 and Tisdale et al., 47 the macronutrient proportion of 
this diet compared to a typical human diet would be considered 
low in fat. Thus, results are difficult to extrapolate to humans, 
since the macronutrient imbalance results in either a high 
fat/low carbohydrate diets or low fat/high carbohydrate diets. 
These examples represent the majority of typical animal dietary 
designs in the preclinical cachexia literature, where the first 
criteria of matching kilocalories between diets are not met. </p>

<p>Important considerations related to fat quantity 
and composition in dietary models </p>

<p>The following discussion will aim to provide a framework 
focused on fat content and composition of experimental 
diets. The principles and underlying considerations applied 
to fat as a macronutrient can also be applied to protein and 
carbohydrate quantity and composition. 
Fat content and composition are important to consider, 
especially in studies focused on 'tumour × host × nutrient' 
interactions. As a recommendation, it is important for fats 
included in the diet to first meet the nutrient requirements 
for the species being used, and second, for the composition 
and types of fat in the diet to be matched between diet treat-
ments, and finally to represent what is commonly consumed 
by humans (Figure 2). Most laboratory chow diets use corn oil 
as the only source of fat, 50 while fat blends that include more 
than one type of oil or fat source are used only in semi-
purified or nutritionally made diets. 21 A corn oil-based diet 
will result in a higher proportion of n-6 fatty acids and n-6/ 
n-3 fatty acid ratio than other oil types. In Wistar rats bearing 
the Walker 256 tumour, rats were fed high-fat diets (49% 
total kcals), low-fat diets (9% total kcals), or diets with fish 
oil and sunflower oil with varied ratios of n-6/n-3, 6:1; 
30:1; and 60:1 (Table 1). 39,40 Pizato et al. 39,40 aimed to </p>

<p>demonstrate that a lower n-6/n-3 ratio (6:1) was more effective 
in preventing cachexia compared to higher n-6/n-3 ratio diets; 
however the diets were not matched for calories. Higher ratios 
of n-6/n-3 fatty acids have been associated with greater 
inflammation and enhanced tumour growth, 51,52 emphasizing 
the importance of considering the n-6/n-3 ratio in dietary 
design. In addition to metabolic differences between n-6 and 
n-3 fatty acids, the length of fatty acid chains also has an 
impact on metabolism and energy expenditure. Compared 
to long chain fatty acids, medium chain fatty acids are 
absorbed more efficiently and have been associated with 
weight loss or reduced weight gain in long-term studies. Thus, 
fatty acid chain length is an additional factor to consider in 
dietary design given the differences in metabolism between 
long and medium chain fatty acids. 53 A number of studies to 
date have reported that promotion of mammary tumours in 
rodents fed a high-fat diet, compared with those fed a low-
fat diet, may be due to specific metabolic activities of the type 
of fatty acids in the diet, independent of calories. 54 These find-
ings reiterate the importance of designing macronutrient in-
takes to be representative of the research question at hand, 
and to further take into account the composition of the mac-
ronutrient class in addition to matching diets for kilocalories. 
When adding or replacing fat in diets it is also important to 
note that this frequently alters other aspects of diet composi-
tion. The majority of studies that provide high-fat diets used 
sources of fat, with or without another nutrient, added to a 
background diet of standard laboratory chow. 37,43 These 
results should be interpreted cautiously since the capacity 
for chow diets to be modified is limited, and adding nutrients 
into the diet may reduce concentrations of the other nutri-
ents. 23 This can result in a diet that is deficient for example, 
in protein per gram of chow. When animals are fed ad libitum, 
they will consume to a specific number of calories per day, 
therefore a high-fat diet, which is more calorie dense per 
gram of diet, also affects protein intake. The addition of nutri-
ents to standard chow also makes it difficult to compare to 
the original lab chow. The control group may be receiving 
adequate proportions of macro-and micronutrients, whereas 
the experimental group may be deficient in certain nutrients. </p>

<p>EPA and DHA nutrient interventions </p>

<p>Although there is an abundance of evidence that suggests the 
fatty acid profile is of importance for the efficacy of EPA and 
DHA in vivo, most preclinical models have not considered the 
fatty acid profile of the background diet when designing 
nutrient intervention diets. The effectiveness of long-chain 
fatty acids EPA and DHA on enhancing drug antitumour 
activity has been demonstrated in several rodent models of 
cancer. 55 Interestingly, a comparison of studies has shown 
that the effectiveness of EPA and DHA for antineoplastic 
activities depends on the background diet, with effects </p>

<p>Diet composition in experimental animal models of cancer cachexia </p>



<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

<p>greatest in studies where control diets contain fat sources of 
palm or corn oil, and subsequently low levels of total polyun-
saturated fatty acids. 56,57 Control diets with fat sources 
from safflower or sunflower oil, and therefore higher levels 
of total PUFA, do not give the same results. 21,55,58 N-3 fatty 
acids may exert different biological effects depending on 
the background diet fat composition, n-6/n-3 ratio, and 
polyunsaturated/saturated fat ratio. 39,59,60 Collectively, 
studies suggest that amount of total PUFA in the diet may 
be an important factor in determining efficacy of EPA and 
DHA on cancer-related outcomes. These findings emphasize 
the importance of a well-developed background diet in 
studies of nutrient interventions, particularly those with 
EPA and DHA. It is difficult to compare studies and interpret 
findings when the majority of studies fail to provide appropri-</p>

<p>ate background diets. </p>

<p>Dietary designs to represent macronutrient content of human 
diets 
Many dietary designs do not reflect macronutrient propor-
tions typical of human consumption. While it is appreciated 
the high degree of variability in dietary consumption patterns 
of cancer patients over the disease trajectory, 61 it is still 
possible and probably advisable to use diets which are at 
least approximately in line with typical human diet macro-
nutrient composition to facilitate interpretation between 
studies as well as translation to human populations. 
Cremades et al. 44 aimed to investigate whether a diet formu-
lated with a crayfish enzymatic extract enriched in essential 
amino acids and n-3 fatty acids would be effective for the 
treatment of cancer-associated cachexia by decreasing 
mortality, morbidity and lengthened survival. A semi-purified 
diet using the AIN-76A Vitamin and Mineral mixture was 
developed with a macronutrient distribution of: 79% total 
kcal carbohydrates, 15% total kcal protein, and 6% total kcal 
fat. The source of fat in this diet was solely from olive oil, 
being high in n-9 fatty acids, and relatively low in n-6 and 
saturated fat, with minimal n-3 fatty acids. Although the fatty 
acid profile was not given much consideration, Cremades 
et al. 44 carefully considered the nitrogen balance of the diet. 
Since crayfish enzymatic extract is mainly protein and con-
tains all essential amino acids, the casein from the standard 
diet was removed and replaced by the enzyme for the 
crayfish diet to achieve isonitrogenous diets. While the 
dietary design from this study includes a source of high quality 
protein, it would be considered low in fat compared to typical 
human intakes that fall in the range of 20-35% total kcal from 
fat. 62 Moreover, a low fat diet is not ideal in an experiment with 
weight gain or maintenance as a study endpoint. </p>

<p>Nutrients provided via gavage 
The majority of nutrient intervention studies administer the 
intervention via the diet, either by incorporation into semi-
purified diets, or the addition of a nutrient to a standard </p>

<p>chow diet. However, some studies administer a nutrient 
gavage, where oral pipettes are used to deliver an exact 
amount of the nutrient to the animal ensuring that the nutrient 
is ingested regardless of food intake. The dietary design upon 
which the gavage is administered is still a key consideration. 
Wistar rats inoculated with Walker 256 tumour cells were 
randomized to receive a standard laboratory chow diet, or 
treatment with coconut oil or fish oil (Table 1). 45 An 
undefined source and amount of standard laboratory chow 
was fed to all groups; rats were given bolus doses of either 
coconut oil or fish oil at 1 g/kgBW/day. Since the route of 
administration was gavage, the addition of fat kilocalories 
on top of the background diet of standard laboratory would 
result in diets being dissimilar between control and treat-
ment groups. Feeding coconut oil (&gt;90% saturated fat) on 
top of laboratory chow (rich in n-6 fatty acids) does not 
achieve a dietary intake resembling a human diet, which 
consists of approximately 10% saturated fat. Moreover, the 
authors do not provide any information about the back-
ground diet, proportion of macronutrients, kcals consumed, 
or food intake, so it is not possible to determine the amount 
of fat consumed in total or the intake of other macronutrients 
in respect to the fat, such as the n-6/n-3 ratio. The fatty acid 
composition of the background diet is particularly important 
when the nutrient of interest is fat. 
Costelli et al. 37 fed male Wistar rats bearing the Yoshida 
ascites hepatoma (YAH-130) standard laboratory chow (Panlab, 
Barcelona, Spain) and similar to Togni et al. 45 treatment ani-
mals received intragastric injections of EPA (1.5 g/kgBW/day). 
The composition of the background diet of standard laboratory 
chow was not defined, and food intake was not reported. While 
EPA was administered in a consistent dose, food intake may 
have been reduced during the study period, which would 
change other source of nutrients during the study period that 
are known to interfere with EPA effectiveness such as the ratio 
of n-3/n-6 fatty acids. Several other studies have administered 
EPA/DHA interventions intragastrically 43 (Table 1), or by bolus 
micropipette dose, 45,42 with only one of these studies adminis-
tering the background diet in a controlled daily amount and 
reporting food intake 18 (Table 1). In addition to the amount 
of n-6 fatty acids, research also suggests that the absorption 
of long chain n-3 fatty acids may be improved through the 
meat, fish, and poultry factor or when consumed with monoun-
saturated fatty acids. 63-65 Chow diets are high in n-6 fatty 
acids, and unbalanced for n-6/n-3 ratio which may alter the 
absorption of EPA and/or DHA. It is difficult to know, however, 
to what extent food intake is a factor when it is not reported. </p>

<p>Overall fat content and n-6/n-3 ratio in dietary design 
Evidence suggests that the consumption of n-3 fatty acids 
may exert antineoplastic effects through the incorporation 
of n-3 fatty acids into membranes, replacing the n-6 fatty 
acid, arachidonic acid. A higher intake of n-3 fatty acids, 
therefore, may reduce pro-inflammatory mediators. 66 On </p>



<p>K. Giles et al. </p>

<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

<p>the basis of this hypothesis, Griffini et al. 67 fed Wag-rij rats 
bearing CC531 colon carcinoma cells (i) low fat diet (11% total 
kcal fat), (ii) n-6 PUFA diet (38% total kcal from fat as 
safflower oil), or (iii) n-3 PUFA diet (38% total kcal from fat 
as fish oil). The sole source of fat in the n-6 and n-3 fatty 
acid treatment diets was safflower oil and fish oil respec-
tively. When evaluating this diet, one must first consider that 
n-6 and n-3 fatty acids are dietary essential nutrients. When 
providing fat sources with minimal amounts of either n-6 or 
n-3 fatty acids, there is a risk of essential fatty acid 
deficiency. Results could be attributed to the deficiency, 
since the effects of n-3 fatty acids are being interpreted 
against a diet containing only n-6 fatty acids as the PUFA 
source, and additionally, results may be exaggerated when 
comparing treatment and control groups. 50,56 Further, diets 
are not matched for calories, and food intake was not reported. 
In three similar studies, Tisdale et al. 25,47 investigated the 
effects of feeding a fish oil or high fat diet on cachexia and 
tumour growth in female NMRI mice bearing the MAC16 
tumour, and Dagnelie et al. 24 investigated the effects of 
feeding fish oil on cancer cachexia and host liver metabolism 
in Fisher F1 hybrid rats injected with MAT-Ly-Lu prostate 
tumour cells. All three studies used the same dietary design. 
Animals were fed a standard diet of laboratory chow, 
containing 50% total kcal from carbohydrates, 20% total kcal 
from protein, and 11.5% total kcal from fat (Pilsbury's, 
Birmingham, United Kingdom), or semi-purified treatment 
diets with varying amounts of medium-chain triglycerides or 
fish oil supplemented up to 80% total kcal supplied as </p>

<p>medium-chain triglycerides or 50% total kcal supplied as fish 
oil (Table 1). The authors indicate that the treatment diets 
were developed to be isonitrogenous and isocaloric by 
reducing the carbohydrate content and supplementing the 
remaining energy from the fish oil or medium-chain triglycer-
ides. However, this is not possible given the macronutrient 
composition as fat provides 9 kcal/g, whereas carbohydrates 
provide 4 kcal/g. Similar to Cremades et al., 44 the standard 
diet in both studies conducted by Tisdale et al. 25,47 and 
Dagnelie et al. 24 was low in fat, which is not ideal when 
the study endpoints involve weight loss or gain. Moreover, 
the proportion of fat in the high fat and fish-oil diets 
aforementioned, 68-80% medium chain triglycerides and 
50% fish oil respectively, are not proportions that are applica-
ble to human dietary intakes where very few medium-chain 
triglycerides or fish oil lipids are consumed in the daily diet. 
Similar to Griffini et al. 67 feeding fish oil as the sole source of 
fat eliminates n-6 fatty acids from the diet and places animals 
at a risk for essential fatty acid deficiency. Both studies fed a 
high dose of fish oil, accounting for 50% of total energy in the 
absence of n-6 fatty acids. Rats had free access to food through-
out the study period. Dagnelie et al. 24 did report that the fish 
oil group had significantly lower food intake compared to 
control animals, however, this could be related to caloric 
density of the diets. </p>

<p>One additional consideration for dietary intervention 
studies where fish oils or other lipids are used is the suscep-
tibility of the prepared diets with the oils to peroxidation. 
Peroxidation can change the flavour of the food, making it 
less palatable, and can also result in a loss of the bioactive 
lipid being studied. Therefore, it is recommended that diets 
be prepared fresh, especially when using nutrients that are 
susceptible to oxidation and a quality control measure is 
implemented at various points throughout the study (i.e. diet 
composition analysis at the beginning, middle and end of 
the study) to ensure the diet components do not change 
over the course of the study, and/or contribute to changes 
in food intake. </p>

<p>Dietary design: case study </p>

<p>To illustrate a dietary design that meets the criteria outlined in 
Figure 2, the study conducted by Dumas et al. 38 will be outlined. 
Dumas et al. 38 developed isocaloric and isonitrogenous semi-
purified diets and included a pair-fed group to discriminate 
the effects of food intake reduction per se from those of the 
tumour or cachexia. The review of the literature revealed that 
there was only one other fat supplementation study that 
included a pair-fed group. 48 Dumas et al. 38 aimed to prevent 
severe cachexia by limiting a decline in food intake, weight 
loss, and by reducing the inflammatory marker, TNF-alpha in 
Berlin-Druckrey IX rats inoculated with DHD/K12 colon 
tumour cells. Animals were randomized to the semi-purified 
control diet or fish oil supplemented diet with free access 
(Table 1). Diets were matched for calories and nitrogen 
content, differing only in fatty acid composition. Dietary 
composition was defined in g/kg diet: casein (220 g), sucrose 
(187 g), cellulose (20 g), DL-methionine (1.6 g), mineral 
mixture (40 g), vitamin mixture (without vitamin E; 10 g), 
corn starch (371.4 g), and lipids (150 g). A variety of lipid 
sources were used to match diets for fat amount and 
composition. The lipid mixture in the control diet was 
composed of 12% peanut oil and 3% canola oil; lipid mix-
ture in the fish oil diet was 8% peanut oil, 2% canola oil, 
and 5% fish oil. Peanut oil and canola oil are high in oleic 
acid (n-9 fatty acids) and linoleic acid (n-6 fatty acids), 
while peanut oil is also a major source of saturated fat. 
The main difference in composition of these diets is the 
EPA and DHA in the treatment diet, allowing researchers 
to attribute differences in the outcomes to the treatments. 
The lipid profile and major macronutrient proportions of 
the control diet are within the range of human dietary 
intakes, within a range of fish oil intake that would be 
achievable in humans, rendering these results applicable to 
human populations. Macronutrient proportions that are 
representative of typical human intakes, though rare in 
preclinical studies, remain advantageous in enabling translation 
of findings to human populations. </p>

<p>Diet composition in experimental animal models of cancer cachexia </p>



<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>There is a lack of standardization in dietary design, content, 
source, and overall composition in animal studies of cancer 
cachexia. In many cases, information about the diet is not 
included. Standard lab chow may be easy and convenient to 
use, but the uncertainty about diet content when using a 
closed label diet is poorly appreciated. Knowledge that 
different groups of animals within the same experimental 
study are consuming diets divergent in nutrient content 
may be critical to fully interpret the effectiveness of a given 
intervention. Many studies using preclinical models fre-
quently fail to report food intake, or total energy and protein 
content of the diet. The role of a variety of dietary and other 
interventions cannot be effectively evaluated without more 
detailed dietary disclosure and information about potential 
confounding effect of dietary factors. Correct interpretation 
of outcomes with a particular intervention is enabled 
when full dietary disclosure accompanies rigorous dietary 
designs. At minimum, diet content and composition should 
be reported and food intake assessed during the study. </p>

<p>Implementation of a standard dietary design as set out in 
Figure 2 that meets minimum basic criteria of dietary design 
would facilitate comparison of preclinical studies and 
replication of studies between research groups. Standardiz-
ing dietary designs in studies that are using preclinical 
models to explore important questions regarding mecha-
nisms and interventions for cancer cachexia would be an 
important step to moving preclinical findings to human 
application. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest, and that this work 
has not been previously published elsewhere. The authors 
certify that they comply with the ethical guidelines for author-
ship and publishing of the Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and 
Muscle (von Haehling S, Morley JE, Coats AJS, Anker SD. Ethical 
guidelines for authorship and publishing in the Journal of 
Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle. 2010;1:7-8). </p>





<p>K. Giles et al. </p>

<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>



<p>Diet composition in experimental animal models of cancer cachexia </p>



<p>Journal of Cachexia, Sarcopenia and Muscle 2016; 7: 110-125 
DOI: 10.1002/jcsm.12058 </p>

</text></tei>