<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4541475" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>People who inject drugs (PWID) are a key population at 
risk for HIV infection in the Middle East and North </p>

<p>Africa (MENA) [1]. A recent systematic review 
documented emerging HIV epidemics among PWID 
in at least one-third of MENA countries [2]. Most 
epidemics are recent and suggest potential for further </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Infectious Disease Epidemiology Group, Weill Cornell Medical College -Qatar, Cornell University, Qatar Foundation -
Education City, Doha, Qatar, b MRC Tropical Epidemiology Group, Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, Faculty of 
Epidemiology and Population Health, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, c School of Social and 
Community Medicine, University of Bristol, Bristol, UK, d Department of Healthcare Policy and Research, Weill Cornell Medical 
College, Cornell University, Ithaca, New York, and e Vaccine and Infectious Disease Institute, Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research 
Center, Seattle, Washington, USA. 
Correspondence to Ghina R. Mumtaz, Weill Cornell Medical College -Qatar, Qatar Foundation -Education City, P.O. Box 24144, 
Doha, Qatar. 
Tel: +974 4492 8406; fax: +974 4492 8422; e-mail: gim2006@qatar-med.cornell.edu 
Received: 17 December 2014; revised: 26 May 2015; accepted: 28 May 2015. </p>

<p>DOI:10.1097/QAD.0000000000000761 </p>

<p>ISSN 0269-9370 Copyright Q 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms 
of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 License, where it is permissible to download and share the work 
provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially. </p>



<p>growth [2]. Our research question is to estimate the HIV 
epidemic potential among PWID, that is to estimate the 
predicted growth in HIV prevalence to the time it reaches 
endemic equilibrium, in order to inform policy and 
intervention programmes. </p>

<p>Although HIV and, in rare instances [3], hepatitis C virus 
(HCV) can be transmitted sexually, sharing of needles/ 
syringes is their main transmission mode among PWID 
[4]. HCV is about 10 times more infectious than HIV 
through percutaneous exposure [5-7], partially explain-
ing why HCV is hyperendemic among PWID globally, 
but HIV is not [8,9]. As HCV is transmitted more rapidly 
than HIV along the same transmission route, it could be 
used as a marker of HIV potential spread among PWID. 
Ecological studies and mathematical modelling have 
found a positive association between HCV and HIV 
among PWID globally, with a threshold HCV prevalence 
of about 30% to sustain HIV transmission [6,7,10]. The 
relationship between the two infections is however 
complex, dependent on the setting and risk environment, 
and overall remains poorly understood [7]. </p>

<p>The use of HCVas a population-level marker of injecting 
risk behaviour and, consequently, HIV risk and epidemic 
potential is appealing with the constrained resources for 
HIV research and programming. In MENA, wherein 
surveillance is rather limited and difficult to implement, 
using existing data to make inferences about future size of 
HIV epidemics is a potentially efficient strategy. </p>

<p>The aims of this study are to understand analytically 
the epidemiological links and association between 
HCV and HIV infections among PWID, and to 
estimate HIV epidemic potential in this population 
across MENA countries, using data compiled through 
the systematic review of HIV and HCV among PWID 
in MENA [2]. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Conceptual framework and hypotheses 
We hypothesize that endemic HCV prevalence predicts 
HIV prevalence among PWID, as both infections result 
from injecting risk behaviour. We further hypothesize 
that the relationship between HCV and HIV prevalence 
is dependent on the HIV epidemic state among PWID, 
whether low-level (HIV has not reached significant 
levels), emerging (HIV prevalence has started its initial 
growth and is increasing) or established/saturated (the 
epidemic has reached its peak and HIV prevalence is 
approaching, or already is at, its endemic level) [2]. We 
hypothesize that the association between HCV and HIV 
in established HIV epidemics can be used to predict 
HIV epidemic potential among PWID in other settings, 
even where the HIV epidemic is still at low level or 
emerging. </p>

<p>Our hypothesis is motivated by theoretical mathematical 
modelling work on the joint epidemiology of HCV and 
HIV. A stochastic compartmental model was built to 
simulate HCV and HIV epidemic trajectories among a 
prototype PWID population (V. Akbarzadeh, G.R. 
Mumtaz, L.J. Abu-Raddad, in preparation). Figure 1a 
depicts a case scenario wherein HIV is introduced into a 
PWID population originally naive to HIV and where 
HCV is endemic at high prevalence indicating substantial 
injecting risk behaviour. When the HIV epidemic is still 
at low level, HCV prevalence is not predictive of the level 
of HIV prevalence (Fig. 1a). When the HIV epidemic 
emerges, HCV prevalence becomes associated with HIV 
prevalence; however, the magnitude of this association 
varies with time, as HIV prevalence is still increasing 
(Fig. 1a). It is only when the HIV epidemic becomes 
established, that the association between HCV and HIV 
prevalence becomes stable and simply quantified, as both 
infections have reached endemicity (Fig. 1a). This pattern 
is reflected in the risk ratio of HCV to HIV prevalence 
(RR HCV/HIV ) (Fig. 1b). As the HIV epidemic emerges, 
the RR HCV/HIV decreases until it reaches a plateau, with a 
stable RR HCV/HIV , when the HIV epidemic reaches 
equilibrium (established HIV epidemic, Fig. 1b). Ende-
mic HCV prevalence can accordingly be used to predict 
the future size (at endemic equilibrium) of the HIV 
epidemic among PWID. Varying levels of endemic 
HCV prevalence entail varying levels of endemic HIV 
prevalence. </p>

<p>On the basis of the above analytical framework, we will 
stratify our analyses by HIV epidemic state to explore the 
differential association between HCV and HIV in the 
three epidemic states. Results of the analyses in settings of 
established HIV epidemics will be used to predict HIV 
epidemic potential among PWID. </p>

<p>Sources of data 
This study used data extracted from a recent systematic 
review whose main objective was to assess the status of the 
HIVepidemic among PWID in 23 MENA countries that 
are part of the MENA definition of the Joint United 
Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS), WHO 
and World Bank [2]. In brief, the review followed 
PRISMA guidelines and included all studies on PWID, 
published in PubMed, Embase and regional databases, 
and unpublished in the form of country reports, until 16 
December 2013 [2]. </p>

<p>In the present study, we started with 197 HIV and 93 
HCV prevalence measures among PWID (Fig. 2) [2]. 
After excluding four HIV and five HCV self-reported 
prevalence measures, there were 71 paired biological 
HCV-HIV data points, that is HCV and HIV prevalence 
on the same PWID population. As we are studying the 
relationship between the two infections, the analysis was 
restricted to settings wherein HIV has already been 
introduced, and thus, 16 HCV-HIV data points with zero </p>



<p>HIV prevalence were excluded. One outlier (89% HIV 
prevalence in Libya [11]) was further excluded, leaving 54 
paired HCV-HIV prevalence measures in the statistical 
analysis (Fig. 2). </p>

<p>Classification by HIV epidemic state 
Country-specific criteria were devised to classify the data 
into one of three HIV epidemic states: low-level, 
emerging or established [2]. This classification was a 
main aim of the MENA PWID systematic review, 
wherein a comprehensive analysis of available HIV 
biological data was performed using rigorous method-
ology to characterize HIV epidemic state at country-level 
[2]. HCV biological data were not part of the criteria to 
characterize HIV epidemic states. Details of the methods, 
classification criteria and findings that led to these </p>

<p>epidemic states can be found in the corresponding 
publication [2]. The epidemic states for countries in the 
present study are summarized in Table S1. This baseline 
classification was adjusted in specific cases to accommo-
date for geographic heterogeneity in HIV epidemic 
dynamics within a single country [2]. For example, in 
Iran, all data points after 2006 were classified as 
'established', except for one province, Isfahan, where 
HIV prevalence among PWID has been consistently 
negligible [2]. </p>

<p>Data analysis 
Analyses were performed in <rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA/SE</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.0</rs> (Stata 
Corp., College Station, Texas, USA). Two types of 
analyses were conducted to understand the association 
between the two infections: a meta-analysis of the </p>

<p>HIV epidemic potential among people who inject drugs Mumtaz et al. 1703 </p>

<p>Low-level </p>

<p>Low-level </p>

<p>Emerging </p>

<p>Emerging </p>

<p>Time (years) </p>

<p>Prevalence (%) </p>

<p>Ratio (Log scale) </p>

<p>HIV introduction </p>

<p>Established </p>

<p>Established </p>

<p>Risk ratio (HCV/HIV) </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1900 
1995 
2000 
2005 
2010 
2015 
2020 
2025 
2030 
2035 
2040 </p>

<p>Time (years) </p>

<p>1900 
1995 
2000 
2005 
2010 
2015 
2020 
2025 
2030 
2035 
2040 </p>

<p>HIV introduction </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>HIV prevalence (%) </p>

<p>HCV prevalence (%) </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Mathematical modelling simulation of an HIV epidemic expansion among a prototype PWID population. (a) A case 
scenario for an HIV epidemic expansion in a PWID population wherein HCV is endemic at a prevalence level of about 75% 
indicating high injecting risk behaviour. HIV is introduced in 1990, starts emerging with increasing prevalence about two decades 
later in the late 1990s, and saturates near the year 2020 at a prevalence of about 20%. The corresponding three HIV epidemic 
states -low level, emerging and established -are shown on the graph. (b) The risk ratio of HCV to HIV prevalence (RR HCV/HIV ) 
among this PWID population. </p>

<p>RR HCV/HIV and linear regression to quantify the extent 
to which any change in HIV prevalence is related to 
change in HCV prevalence. Results of these analyses were 
used to predict future HIV prevalence at endemic 
equilibrium among PWID at country-level. </p>

<p>Meta-analysis 
Three meta-analyses of the RR HCV/HIV in each of the 
three HIVepidemic states were applied. The RR HCV/HIV 
is an 'ecological' risk ratio defined as the ratio of the 
prevalence ('risk') of HCV to that of HIV in the same 
population. The objective of using this measure was to 
quantify the association between the two infections at the 
population level. </p>

<p>The 54 RR HCV/HIV were pooled using DerSimonian-
Laird random-effects models with inverse variance 
weighting using the metan command [12]. The I 2 statistic 
was calculated as a measure of heterogeneity in effect size, 
which is the proportion of overall between-study 
variation in RR HCV/HIV that is due to differences 
between studies in effect size and not chance [12]. </p>

<p>Linear regression 
Three multivariable linear regression models, one in each 
HIV epidemic state, were fitted to the data. Log HIV 
prevalence was the dependent variable. Explanatory 
variables included HCV -our main predictor of interest 
-country and study characteristics including sampling 
technique (probability versus nonprobability-based), 
sample size (&lt;100 or !100) and study site (community, 
facility-based or prison). The regression analyses used 
robust standard errors to adjust for heteroscedasticity. 
Each data point was weighed by its sample size. As a first 
step, all explanatory variables were included in the model 
and only variables significant at P value less than 0.1 (in 
addition to HCV) were kept in the final model. </p>

<p>HIV epidemic potential prediction 
The final regression model predicting HIV prevalence in 
settings of established HIVepidemics was used to estimate 
the prevalence and 95% confidence intervals of HIV at 
endemic equilibrium among PWID, using the margins 
command. On the basis of predictions of the fitted model, 
margins calculate HIV prevalence for specific values of 
covariates in the model. The predictions were made using 
the mean HCV prevalence among PWID per country 
using all available biological HCV prevalence measures 
(including where HIV is zero) [11,13-78]. The 
prevalence of HIV at endemic equilibrium was also 
estimated using results of the meta-analysis by dividing 
the mean HCV prevalence by the pooled RR HCV/HIV . 
Results of the two methods of prediction were compared. </p>

<p>We devised criteria to classify HIV epidemic potential. 
They depend on comparing the predicted HIV prevalence 
with the most recent representative HIV prevalence as 
extracted from surveillance studies [2]. HIV epidemic 
potential was classified as high, moderate or low. High 
epidemic potential was considered if the estimated HIV 
prevalence at endemic equilibrium was at least 10 absolute 
percentage points higher than current HIV prevalence and 
at least twice as high as current HIV prevalence (estimated/ 
current HIV prevalence &gt;2). Low epidemic potential was 
considered if the estimated HIV prevalence at endemic 
equilibrium was less than five absolute percentage points 
higher than current HIV prevalence and less than 20% 
higher than current HIV prevalence (estimated/current 
HIV prevalence &lt;1.2). Moderate epidemic potential was 
considered in remaining scenarios. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The 54 paired HCV-HIV prevalence measures among 
PWID were from five countries: Iran (n ¼ 31), Afghani-
stan (n ¼ 11), Pakistan (n ¼ 8), Morocco (n ¼ 2) and </p>

<p>1704 AIDS 2015, Vol 29 No 13 </p>

<p>197 HIV prevalence 
measures </p>

<p>93 HCV prevalence 
measures </p>

<p>4 self-reported HIV prevalence 
measures excluded </p>

<p>5 self-reported HCV prevalence 
measures excluded </p>

<p>193 biological HIV 
prevalence measures </p>

<p>88 biological HCV 
prevalence measures </p>

<p>71 paired biological HCV-HIV 
prevalence measures </p>

<p>16 paired data points with zero 
HIV prevalence excluded </p>

<p>1 outlier excluded 
(HIV prevalence = 89%) </p>

<p>54 paired biological HCV-HIV 
prevalence measures included 
in the statistical analyses </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Sample selection process. </p>

<p>Tunisia (n ¼ 2). There were 20 paired HCV-HIV 
measures in low-level, 22 in emerging, and 12 in 
established HIV epidemic settings. Iran was the only 
country in the established epidemic strata. The data are 
summarized in Table S2. </p>

<p>The meta-analyses showed that the RR HCV/HIV is 
highest in low-level HIV epidemics at 16.3 [95% 
confidence interval (95% CI) 11.5-23.1], followed by 
that in emerging HIVepidemics at 3.8 (95% CI 3.1-4.7), 
while the lowest RR HCV/HIV was observed in established 
HIV epidemics at 2.8 (95% CI 2.1-3.6) (Table 1). The 
corresponding forest plots are in Figures S1-S3. These 
results suggest that HIV prevalence at endemic equi-
librium is about one-third of the endemic HCV 
prevalence, assuming no major confounding effect by 
other predictors. There was evidence of heterogeneity 
between studies in the three epidemic states with an I 2 of 
80-87% (P &lt; 0.001), indicating that the variation in 
RR HCV/HIV between studies is due to differences in 
effect size, and not chance. </p>

<p>Table 2 summarizes the final multivariable regression 
models predicting log HIV prevalence. HCV prevalence 
was not associated with HIV in low-level HIV epidemics 
(ß ¼ À1.3, 95% CI À3.4 to 0.9). In these settings, country 
and study site were the significant predictors of HIV. 
HCV was a significant predictor of HIV prevalence in 
sites wherein the HIV epidemic is emerging or 
established. In emerging epidemics, HCV was signifi-
cantly associated with the highest increase in log HIV 
prevalence compared with the other epidemic states 
(ß ¼ 5.4, 95% CI 2.7-8.2). Country and study site were 
also significant predictors of HIV in emerging epidemic 
states. In established epidemics, HCV prevalence was the 
only predictor of HIV (ß ¼ 1.7, 95% CI 0.8-2.7) (Table 2). </p>

<p>Table 3 displays the predicted HIV prevalence at endemic 
equilibrium among PWID in MENA using results of 
both regression analysis and meta-analysis. The two 
methods predicted similar endemic HIV prevalence, with 
a median difference of 10% between the two methods. 
The median estimated HIV prevalence across countries 
was 17% [interquartile range (IQR): 13-20%] and 19% 
(IQR: 13-22%) as predicted by the regression and meta-
analysis models, respectively. The highest estimated 
endemic HIV prevalence was 20-22% in Egypt, </p>

<p>Morocco, Pakistan, Saudi Arabia and Syria. The lowest 
was 8% in Tunisia (Table 3). </p>

<p>HIV epidemic potential was found to be high among 
PWID in Egypt, Lebanon, Palestine, Saudi Arabia and 
Syria, and moderate in Afghanistan, Morocco and 
Tunisia. Apart from Iran that was used to derive the 
predictive relationship, Pakistan was the only country 
with low epidemic potential and where the HIVepidemic 
among PWID is predicted to have reached or is close to 
saturation (Table 3). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study illustrates our hypothesis that HCV prevalence 
can be used to predict HIV epidemic potential among 
PWID. With HCV being hyperendemic among PWID 
globally, its prevalence is indicative of the level of injecting 
risk behaviour and therefore could possibly predict future 
HIV prevalence. Our analyses in MENA suggest that 
HIV prevalence will reach, at endemic equilibrium, 
about one-third of HCV prevalence in a given PWID 
population wherein HIV is introduced. </p>

<p>The association between HCV and HIV among PWID is 
complex and varied depending on HIV epidemic state, as 
postulated in our hypothesis and motivated by the 
modelling simulations. When the HIV epidemic was at 
low level, HCV was not predictive of HIV prevalence. 
HIV may have been recently introduced, or may have 
been spreading for some time but slowly and inefficiently 
due to stochastic effects. In these settings, HIV prevalence 
is not a reflection of the level of injecting risk behaviour. 
In an emerging HIV epidemic, the intensity of HIV 
prevalence growth depends on the level of injecting risk 
behaviour, and this is confirmed by the observed 
association between HCVand HIV prevalence. However, 
there are also other predictors of epidemic expansion 
intensity including time since epidemic emergence, and 
other factors such as setting of injection and country, both 
of which were significant predictive proxies for the risk 
environment (Table 2). In established HIVepidemics, and 
confirming our hypothesis (Fig. 2), HCV was the only 
significant predictor of HIV prevalence. This highlights 
how HCV is a proxy of injecting risk behaviour in PWID </p>

<p>HIV epidemic potential among people who inject drugs Mumtaz et al. 1705 </p>

<p>Table 1. Pooled risk ratio of hepatitis C virus to HIV prevalence (RR HCV/HIV ) among people who inject drug in Middle East and North Africa. </p>

<p>Epidemic state 
No datasets </p>

<p>Total un-weighted 
Total un-weighted 
Studies RRHCV/HIV </p>

<p>Pooled RR HCV/HIV </p>

<p>HCV prevalence 
HIV prevalence 
Median (IQR) 
% (95% CI) 
I 2 
P </p>

<p>Low level 
20 
3264/7699 (42.4%) 
217/7730 (2.8%) 
13.8 (9.6-56.9) 
16.3 (11.5-23.1) 
80.2% 
0.000 
Emerging 
22 
2200/3749 (58.7%) 
554/3698 (15.0%) 
4.4 (3.1-5.6) 
3.8 (3.1-4.7) 
79.5% 
0.000 
Established 
12 
1635/3498 (51.1%) 
605/3508 (23.2%) 
3.3 (2.1-4.2) 
2.8 (2.1-3.6) 
87.2% 
0.000 </p>

<p>CI, confidence interval; HCV, hepatitis C virus; IQR, interquartile range. </p>

<p>and can be used to generate inferences on the size of HIV 
epidemics, regardless of current HIV epidemic state. 
HCV prevalence 'summarizes' collectively the risk 
environment and acts as a 'temperature scale' of the 
level of risk behaviour and HIV epidemic potential in a 
PWID population. </p>

<p>We estimated HIV epidemic potential in nine countries 
where HCV prevalence data were available. Both the 
regression analysis and meta-analysis produced similar 
results, not a surprising outcome, as HCV was the only 
significant predictor of HIV in the regression analysis of 
established HIV epidemics. In most countries, we found 
room for further HIV growth, with five of these having 
high and three moderate HIV epidemic potential, 
highlighting the emerging and growing nature of the 
HIV epidemic among PWID in MENA, as suggested 
recently [1,2]. Although HIV prevalence in Pakistan 
showed an increasing trend from 10.8% in 2005 to 25.2% 
in 2011 [79-82], our predictions suggest that the HIV 
epidemic could be reaching saturation with limited 
potential for further growth. Still, HIV incidence remains 
considerable in such settings of high HIV prevalence, and 
the limited epidemic potential should not be interpreted 
as low priority for prevention interventions. </p>

<p>Our findings have important policy implications, as they 
provide a simple tool to identify PWID populations at a 
high risk of future HIV epidemic expansion. In half of 
MENA countries with considerable epidemic potential, </p>

<p>the HIV epidemic is still at low level, and therefore, there 
is significant benefit in preventing the infection from 
taking root in this population. In countries where 
epidemic status is unknown, using HCV prevalence data 
could help identify hidden HIV epidemics before they 
grow substantially. One example is Saudi Arabia where 
the high HCV prevalence suggests the potential for 
substantial, though undetected, HIV transmission. 
Recent case notification data also hint at this conclusion 
[1]. Although the top priority for public health 
programmes should be settings already at known high 
HIV incidence, such country-specific predictions high-
light the need to also implement intervention packages 
and conduct surveillance studies in settings with high 
HIV epidemic potential and where there could be 
complacency in view of the current low HIV prevalence. </p>

<p>There were several limitations in our study. The analysis 
used a relatively simple approach to a probably complex 
association. We assumed a linear association between 
HCV and HIV, which fitted well our data. However, the 
effect size can be affected by heterogeneity in risk and 
nonlinearity in this association, as suggested by the 
observed high I 2 values, earlier modelling work [7,10] 
and an ecological analysis [6]. The latter also suggests a 
threshold effect where HIV prevalence would remain 
negligible in countries with low HCV prevalence [6], 
such as Tunisia. The HCV-HIV association can also be 
affected by interventions, if they affect each infection 
differentially, such as antiretroviral therapy (ART) that </p>



<p>Table 2. Multivariable linear regression models a predicting log of HIV among people who inject drug in Middle East and North Africa, stratified 
by HIV epidemic state among people who inject drug. </p>

<p>HIV epidemic state 
Variables 
b 
95% CI 
P 
R 2 </p>

<p>Low level (n ¼ 16) 
HCV prevalence b 
À1.3 
À3.4 to 0.9 
0.216 
0.754 
Country 
0.000 
Afghanistan 
ref 
Iran 
À0.3 
À1.6 to 1.0 
Morocco 
À1.8 
À3 to À0.6 
Pakistan 
À0.6 
À2.4 to 1.1 
Tunisia 
0.3 
À1.0 to 1.6 
Study site 
0.025 
Community 
ref 
Prison 
1.3 
À0.3 to 3.0 
Facility-based 
À0.1 
À1.7 to 1.5 
Mixed 
0.4 
À1.3 to 2.1 
Emerging (n ¼ 21) 
HCV prevalence b 
5.4 
2.7-8.2 
0.001 
0.724 
Country 
0.001 
Afghanistan 
ref 
Iran 
À2.2 
À3.1 to À1.4 
Morocco 
À0.6 
À1.1 to À0.2 
Pakistan 
À1.3 
À2.2 to À0.3 
Study site 
0.000 
Community 
ref 
Prison 
1.0 
0.1-2.0 
Facility-based 
2.8 
1.3-4.2 
Mixed 
2.8 
2.0-3.7 
Established (n ¼ 12) 
HCV prevalence b 
1.7 
0.8-2.7 
0.002 
0.340 </p>

<p>CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Weighting for sample size and using robust methods to adjust for heteroscedasticity. The displayed final models include only statistically 
significant covariates. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Proportion. </p>

<p>affects survival with HIV and infection transmission. In 
MENA, ART coverage is low across countries, with a 
median of 16% (IQR: 6-17%) [83]. If ART coverage 
increases substantially in the coming years, our current 
predictions may underestimate endemic HIV prevalence 
with the longer survival effect. ART can affect the 
quantitative HCV-HIV association, but not its existence 
nor the principle behind it. When applied to settings with 
substantial ART coverage, a more generic association 
could be derived by including ART coverage as one 
additional covariate in the regression models. </p>

<p>We assumed that HCV and HIV among PWID are 
transmitted through sharing of needles/syringes and that 
there is limited sexual transmission of these infections in 
this population. We also assumed a negligible effect of 
background HCV prevalence due to iatrogenic trans-
mission, as HCV prevalence in the population at large is 
generally much smaller than HCV prevalence among 
PWID [2,84,85]. We further assumed that HCV is at 
endemic equilibrium. All of these assumptions are only 
approximately valid. </p>

<p>The small sample size of paired HCV-HIV measures 
limited the range of mathematical complexity that could 
be explored and number of potential confounders to 
control for and prevented us from conducting meta-
regressions to account for heterogeneity in effect size. Iran 
was also the only country providing data in the established 
HIV epidemic state, but this could introduce bias if the 
data from other countries are not representative of the 
same generic HCV-HIV epidemiological association. 
The predictions of HIV epidemic potential also depend 
on the quality of HCV prevalence data. For some 
countries, there were few measures and these may not be 
representative of the PWID population at large. Our 
predictions were also made at the national level, but there 
could be geographic heterogeneity in risk environment, 
leading to geographically clustered HCV prevalence and 
predicted HIV epidemic size. For example in Pakistan, 
HCV prevalence of over 90% was observed in Karachi 
and Lahore [2], while the mean prevalence at the 
country-level was only 61%. Finally, our methodology 
provides only the scale and not the timeframe of predicted 
epidemic growth. It is expected, however, based on 
generic mathematical modelling results [11,86], that the 
pace of an epidemic should correlate with its HIV 
epidemic potential, as estimated here. </p>

<p>Despite these limitations, our study provides important 
insights into a poorly understood and barely investigated 
association [6,7]. Using a mechanistic and analytical 
methodology, our study confirms that the HCV-HIV 
association is robust and characterized differentially by 
HIVepidemic state. The association can also be described, 
at least grossly, using a simple methodology that can be 
easily and widely applied to assess HIVepidemic potential. 
Even if some of the input data used to generate the </p>

<p>HIV epidemic potential among people who inject drugs Mumtaz et al. 1707 </p>

<p>Table 3. Estimated HIV prevalence at endemic equilibrium among people who inject drug in Middle East and North Africa. </p>

<p>No 
datasets </p>

<p>Mean HCV 
prevalence </p>

<p>HIV epidemic 
state among 
PWID a </p>

<p>[2] </p>

<p>Most recent 
representative HIV 
prevalence [2] </p>

<p>Estimated endemic HIV 
prevalence using 
regression </p>

<p>Estimated endemic HIV 
prevalence using 
meta-analysis </p>

<p>HIV 
epidemic 
potential </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>95% CI </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>95% CI </p>

<p>Afghanistan </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>34.2% </p>

<p>Emerging </p>

<p>4.4% </p>

<p>12.5 </p>

<p>8.7-18.0 </p>

<p>12.3 </p>

<p>9.6-15.9 </p>

<p>Medium </p>

<p>Egypt </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>63.0% </p>

<p>Emerging </p>

<p>7.2% </p>

<p>20.7 </p>

<p>16.1-26.6 </p>

<p>22.7 </p>

<p>17.6-29.3 </p>

<p>High </p>

<p>Iran </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>47.1% </p>

<p>Established </p>

<p>15.1% </p>

<p>15.7 </p>

<p>11.8-20.9 </p>

<p>17.0 </p>

<p>13.2-21.9 </p>

<p>Low </p>

<p>Lebanon </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>29.0% </p>

<p>Low-level </p>

<p>0.0% </p>

<p>11.4 </p>

<p>7.7-17.1 </p>

<p>10.5 </p>

<p>8.1-13.5 </p>

<p>High </p>

<p>Morocco </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>57.6% </p>

<p>Emerging </p>

<p>13.0% </p>

<p>18.9 </p>

<p>14.6-24.3 </p>

<p>20.8 </p>

<p>16.1-26.8 </p>

<p>Medium </p>

<p>Palestine </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>43.8% </p>

<p>Low-level </p>

<p>0.0% </p>

<p>14.8 </p>

<p>10.9-20.0 </p>

<p>15.8 </p>

<p>12.2-20.4 </p>

<p>High </p>

<p>Pakistan </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>60.7% </p>

<p>Emerging </p>

<p>25.2% </p>

<p>19.9 </p>

<p>15.5-25.6 </p>

<p>21.9 </p>

<p>17.0-28.3 </p>

<p>Low </p>

<p>Saudi Arabia </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>60.5% </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>0.6% </p>

<p>19.8 </p>

<p>15.4-25.5 </p>

<p>21.8 </p>

<p>16.9-28.2 </p>

<p>High </p>

<p>Syria </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>60.5% </p>

<p>Low-level </p>

<p>0.5% </p>

<p>19.8 </p>

<p>15.4-25.5 </p>

<p>21.8 </p>

<p>16.9-28.2 </p>

<p>High </p>

<p>Tunisia </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>22.6% </p>

<p>Low-level </p>

<p>3.0% </p>

<p>10.2 </p>

<p>6.5-16.0 </p>

<p>8.2 </p>

<p>6.3-10.5 </p>

<p>Medium </p>

<p>CI, confidence interval; HCV, hepatitis C virus. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Overall current HIV epidemic state among PWID at country-level. </p>

<p>predictions may prove unrepresentative with further 
empirical data, the value of this work remains in 
delineating a powerful concept of using data on one 
infection, HCV, to estimate the scale of epidemics of 
another infection, HIV. This concept exploits the 
epidemiological links that underpin the dynamics of 
two infections sharing the same mode of transmission and 
propagating on the same network structure. With further 
data over the coming years, and use of global data on 
PWID beyond MENA, the value of this approach can be 
enhanced for a wider applicability across countries and 
contexts, including fine-grained predictions at small 
geographic scales. Moreover, if combined with appro-
priate dynamic mathematical modelling, our results could 
be used to generate predictions for the time evolution 
of epidemics. </p>

<p>In conclusion, we described a concept that has a 
pragmatic and useful application, to predict future HIV 
epidemics and their scales using HCV prevalence. The 
proof of concept was manifested by modelling the HCV-
HIV association in few countries, and then generating 
predictions for more countries with limited HIV data. In 
addition to informing our theoretical understanding of 
the overlapping epidemiology of these two infections, this 
approach optimizes the use of available data and informs 
resources allocation and planning of interventions and 
research studies. Findings from this proposed method-
ology can complement those of other methods of 
measurement and estimation such as prospective inci-
dence studies, and indirect estimations of HIV incidence 
using the innovative HIV incidence assays and math-
ematical models [87,88]. Triangulation of complimentary 
approaches will allow the corroboration of findings across 
different methods, the adjustment of potential limitations 
in each one of them and is essential for the formulation of 
an optimal HIV response. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>G.R.M. designed the study, conducted the analyses and 
wrote the first draft of the manuscript. H.A.W. coled the 
study design, study conduct and analyses. P.V. and N.L. 
contributed to the development of the study method-
ology. L.J.A. conceived the study and co-led the study 
design, study conduct and analyses. All authors con-
tributed to the interpretation of findings and drafting of 
the manuscript. All authors approved the final version of 
the manuscript. </p>

<p>This publication was made possible by NPRP grant 
number (NPRP 04-924-3-251) from the Qatar National 
Research Fund (a member of Qatar Foundation). 
Additional support was provided by the Biostatistics, 
Epidemiology and Biomathematics Research Core at the 
Weill Cornell Medical College in Qatar. The statements 
made herein are solely the responsibility of the authors </p>

<p>and the funders had no role in study design, data 
collection and analysis, decision to publish or preparation 
of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest 
There are no conflicts of interest. </p>







<p>HIV epidemic potential among people who inject drugs Mumtaz et al. 1709 </p>





</text></tei>