<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4644632" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Hepatologists have studied serologic markers of liver injury for decades. Annexins are a prominent group of such markers 
and annexin A2 (AnxA2) is one of the best characterized annexins. AnxA2 inhibits HBV polymerase among other functions. Its expression 
is up-regulated in regenerative hepatocytes. 
Objectives: To determine if serum AnxA2 level has a role in estimating liver damage in chronic HBV infection and investigate whether 
AnxA2 levels correlate with hepatic fibrosis. 
Patients and Methods: This study included 173 patients with chronic hepatitis B (CHB) and 51 healthy controls. Liver fibrosis was graded 
histologically on liver biopsy samples. Blood samples were taken from patients during biopsy and serum AnxA2 levels were measured 
with ELISA. 
Keywords: Annexin A2, Hepatitis B, Chronic, Liver Fibrosis, Biological Marker </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015, Kowsar Corp. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial usages, provided the original 
work is properly cited. </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>There are more than 350 million hepatitis B virus (HBV) 
infected people worldwide. HBV is the most important 
cause of chronic hepatitis, cirrhosis and hepatocellular 
carcinoma (HCC). HBV causes significant morbidity and 
medical expenditure (1, 2). 
ANXs are a family of calcium and lipid-binding pro-
teins that contain unique calcium-binding properties. 
Twelve ANX subfamilies have been identified in verte-
brates (3). AnxA2, also called annexin II, is one of the 
best-characterized ANXs. AnxA2 has a role in exocytosis 
and endocytosis, cell-cell adhesion, cell proliferation, 
cell surface fibrinolysis, osteoclast formation and bone 
resorption. Furthermore, AnxA2 has been implicated in 
cell growth regulation and apoptosis. It has also been 
reported that HBV polymerase activity is inhibited by </p>

<p>S100A10, a protein binding to AnxA2 (3, 4). 
AnxA2 expression is up-regulated in several types of 
spontaneous neoplasms, such as pancreatic cancer, gas-
tric cancer, colorectal cancer and high-grade glioma (5, 
6). AnxA2 levels are increased in proliferative or regenera-
tive hepatocytes, suggesting that this protein plays a role 
in normal hepatocyte growth (7). AnxA2 levels are also 
elevated in patients with HCC. 
To overcome the complications risked by invasive tis-
sue sampling in liver biopsy, noninvasive serological 
biomarkers of hepatic fibrosis have been developed to 
estimate liver damage. Among serologic biomarkers, so-
called "direct serological markers" include procollagen 
types I and III. Indirect serological markers include gam-
ma-glutamyl transferase (GGT), total bilirubin, alpha-</p>

<p>Kolgelier S et al. </p>

<p>Hepat Mon. 2015;15(10):e30655 </p>

<p>
2-macroglobulin and alpha-2-globulin (haptoglobin). 
Furthermore, some diagnostic panels for liver fibrosis 
include aspartate aminotransferase (AST) to platelet ra-
tio (APRI), Hepascore, FibroTest/FibroSure and FibroSpect 
(8). These clinical diagnostic panels of liver fibrosis have 
been studied mainly in chronic hepatitis C (HCV). Cur-
rently, no single serum biomarker is the diagnostic "gold 
standard" for liver fibrosis (9). 
As AnxA2 is overexpressed in regenerative hepatocytes, 
we hypothesized that AnxA2 could be implemented as a 
surrogate marker of liver injury in CHB patients. </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>To determine if serum AnxA2 level has a role in estimat-
ing liver damage in chronic HBV infection and investi-
gate whether AnxA2 levels correlate with hepatic fibrosis. </p>

<p>3. Patients and Methods </p>

<p>3.1. Patients </p>

<p>A total of 173 CHB patients and 51 healthy controls were 
included in this study. The study was performed in the 
infectious disease clinics of Adiyaman State Hospital, 
Adiyaman 82 nd Year State Hospital, and Adana State 
Hospital between January 1st and December 31st, 2010. 
Patients' characteristics and demographic data were 
recorded in special forms. The control group consisted 
of healthy volunteers without any sign of viral hepatitis 
(HBsAg negative, anti-HBc negative, anti-HCV negative) 
with normal ALT/AST ratios. Patients with coagulation 
abnormalities (PT ≥ 1.5 INR [international normalized 
ratio] and/or platelet count ≤ 50,000/mm 3 ) and those 
who did not consent to liver biopsy were excluded from 
the study. Furthermore, patients were screened for un-
derlying HCC with AFP and liver ultrasound. Patients 
who had an elevated AFP level or mass lesion in the liver 
were excluded from the study. </p>

<p>3.2. Ethics </p>

<p>This study was performed in accordance with the 2000 
Declaration of Helsinki of the World Medical Association. 
The ethical committee of Adiyaman University reviewed 
and approved the study protocol. All patients were in-
formed about possible adverse outcomes by the authors 
before the liver biopsy. All participants read and signed 
an informed consent agreement. </p>

<p>3.3. Preparation for Liver Biopsy </p>

<p>All patients underwent pre-biopsy screening tests in-
cluding a hepatitis panel as well as tests for ALT, AST, 
HBV DNA, platelet (PLT) count and prothrombin time 
(PT). Ultrasound imaging of the liver was mandatory 
before the liver biopsy. Patients were excluded per the 
criteria above. </p>

<p>3.4. Liver Biopsy </p>

<p>Liver biopsy indication was established as suggested by 
the American Association for the study of liver diseases 
(AASLD) (10). The degree of fibrosis was assessed using a 
six-stage scoring system, the Ishak score (11). This scor-
ing system has separate staging systems for fibrosis and 
necro-inflammation (11). </p>

<p>3.5. Determination of AnxA2 </p>

<p>This study was performed using a USCN AnxA2 micro 
ELISA kit (Uscn E91944HU, Wuhan, Hubei, China). </p>

<p>3.6. Virological and Biochemical Parameters </p>

<p>HBsAg, anti-HBs, HBeAg and anti-HBe were detected 
with Macro-ELISA (Abbott AXSYM System, Germany). 
HBV DNA was measured with real-time PCR (ICycler 
IQ Real-Time PCR; BioRad, USA). ALT, AST and albumin 
levels were measured using an Abbott Architect Plus 
c16000 device. Complete blood count was measured 
with Sysmex XT 2000i (Roche). A Modular E170 (Roche) 
device was used to determine serum alpha-fetoprotein 
(AFP) levels. </p>

<p>3.7. Statistical Analyses </p>

<p>Data was analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">16.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs>, Amer-
ica). The descriptive statistics are shown as Mean ± Stan-
dard Deviation, median (minimum-maximum value) 
and percentage distribution. Statistical analysis was 
performed using a chi-square test and t-test for indepen-
dent groups. Kruskal-Wallis test and post-hoc Bonferro-
ni modified Mann-Whitney U test were used for AnxA2 
analysis based on stages. As a result of the analyses, P &lt; 
0.05 considered as statistically significant. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>Of 173 patients, 112 (64.7%) were male and 61 (35.3%) fe-
male. The control group consisted of 25 (49.0%) male 
and 26 (51.0%) female volunteers. The mean age of pa-
tients was 34.0 ± 10.8 years and that of the control group 
33.8 ± 9.3 years. 
ALT, HBV DNA, AFP, PLT and albumin values (median; 
range) of patients based on fibrosis stages in the liver bi-
opsies are shown in Table 1. 
The AnxA2 value of patients was higher than that of the 
control group (P = 0.001; Figure 1 A). When we assessed 
AnxA2 levels based on fibrosis stages, the serum AnxA2 
levels of patients with early fibrosis (stages 1, 2, and 3) 
were significantly higher than the AnxA2 levels of pa-
tients with advanced fibrosis (stages 4 and 5, P = 0.001; 
Figure 1 B).There was no difference between serum AnxA2 
levels of patients with stage 5 fibrosis and those of the 
control group; AnxA2 levels did not differ according to 
age and gender groups. </p>

<p>Kolgelier S et al. </p>



<p>Hepat Mon. 2015;15(10):e30655 </p>

<p>Table 1. ALT, HBV DNA, AFP, PLT and Albumin Values of Patients Based on Fibrosis Stages in Liver Biopsy a,b </p>

<p>Variable 
Stage 1 (N = 33) 
Stage 2 (N = 68) 
Stage 3 (N = 37) 
Stage 4 (N = 23) 
Stage 5 (N = 12) </p>

<p>ALT, U/L 
54 (32 -144) 
56 (32 -124) 
82 (32 -164) 
69 (43 -145) 
87 (54 -144) </p>

<p>HBV DNA, IU/mL 
6.7 × 10 4 (1.2 × 10 4 -
11 × 10 7 ) 
1.3 × 10 5 (1.2 × 10 4 -11 
× 10 7 ) 
11 × 10 8 (1.2 × 10 4 -
9.8 × 10 10 ) 
6 × 10 7 (4.5 × 10 5 -1.2 
× 10 10 ) 
1.1 × 10 9 (2.3 × 10 6 -
3.2 × 10 9 ) </p>

<p>AFP, ng/mL 
5 (3 -8) 
5 (3 -8) 
6 (3 -8) 
6 (3 -13) 
6 (3 -34) </p>

<p>PLT, mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2.3 × 10 5 (1.1 × 10 5 -
4.3 × 10 5 ) 
2.8 × 10 5 (1.8 × 10 5 -
4.3 × 10 5 ) 
2.8 × 10 5 (1.8 × 10 5 -
3.5 × 10 5 ) 
2.7 × 10 5 (1.1 × 10 5 -
4.3 × 10 5 ) 
1.8 × 10 5 (1.1 × 10 5 -
2.8 × 10 5 ) </p>

<p>Albumin, g/dL 
4.0 (3.9 -4.5) 
4.0 (3.9 -4.6) 
4.0 (3.8 -4.6) 
3.9 (3.2 -4.0) 
3.5 (3.0 -4.1) </p>

<p>a Abbreviations: AFP: alpha fetoprotein, ALT: alanine aminotransferase, HBVDNA; hepatitis B virus DNA, PLT: platelet. 
b Values are presented as median (range). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Change in Annexin A2 Levels </p>

<p>Annexin A2 ng/ml </p>

<p>40,00 </p>

<p>30,00 </p>

<p>20,00 </p>

<p>10,00 </p>

<p>0,00 </p>

<p>Controls 
Group 
Patients </p>

<p>B 
A </p>

<p>30,00 </p>

<p>25,00 </p>

<p>20,00 </p>

<p>15,00 </p>

<p>10,00 </p>

<p>5,00 </p>

<p>0,00 </p>

<p>Annexin A2 ng/ml </p>

<p>Early Stage 
A dvanced Stage 
Stage </p>

<p>A, Annexin A2 values of patients and control groups. B, Annexin A2 levels according to Fibrosis stages. </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>AnxA2 is a biomarker associated with liver fibrosis, but 
its mechanism and clinicaluse are unknown. Only a few 
studies have investigated the association of AnxA2 and 
liver fibrosis (3, 4). 
During the development of liver fibrosis, many molecu-
lar changes occur. AnxA2 was first defined as a biomarker 
of liver fibrosis by Zhang et al. (12). It was postulated that 
AnxA2 could be used as a noninvasive marker for diagnosis 
of HBV-related liver fibrosis. Moreover, we and others have 
shown that age and gender did not affect serum AnxA2 lev-
els (13). To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study 
evaluating serum AnxA2 levels in CHB patients. In our 
study, AnxA2 levels of CHB patients were significantly high-
er than those of control group, reflecting ongoing hepa-
tocyte injury through the course of CHB disease. Further-
more, we examined whether serum AnxA2 levels could be 
implemented as a tool for noninvasive liver fibrosis mea-
surement. Serum AnxA2 levels of patients with early stage </p>

<p>fibrosis (stages 1, 2, and 3) were significantly higher than 
serum AnxA2 levels of patients with advanced stage fibro-
sis (stages 4 and 5; Figure 1 B). Zhang et al. (12) previously 
showed in an animal model that AnxA2 expression was el-
evated in advanced cirrhosis compared to early liver dam-
age. They could not demonstrate that plasma AnxA2 levels 
differed between early and advanced stages of fibrosis. We 
speculate that AnxA2 may be overexpressed in the liver 
without elevating serum AnxA2. Since hepatocytes are the 
main source of AnxA2, decreased serum AnxA2 levels may 
reflect a diminished hepatocyte reservoir at advanced fi-
brosis stages. Elevated AnxA2 levels could also result from 
denovo liver carcinogenesis. In this study, we tried to rule 
out possible underlying HCC by excluding patients with el-
evated AFP levels or ultrasound abnormalities. That is why 
we think our results were not biased by underlying HCC. 
Furthermore, to our knowledge, none of our patients de-
veloped cancer until the year 2015. </p>

<p>Kolgelier S et al. </p>

<p>Hepat Mon. 2015;15(10):e30655 </p>

<p>
Our study had some limitations, including its retrospec-
tive design and a limited number of advanced-stage pa-
tients. Future studies designed to analyze larger cohorts 
prospectively could improve the evidence for AnxA2 
as a clinical biomarker for hepatic fibrosis. Because we 
could not identify the source of AnxA2 in this study, it is 
not easy to speculate regarding abnormal AnxA2 levels. 
AnxA2 is not liver-specific and its level may increase in 
the presence of concomitant inflammatory conditions. 
In addition, its serum level depends on its clearance rate, 
which may be influenced by some cofounders such as 
dysfunction of endothelial cells, impaired biliary excre-
tion or renal function, ethnicity and body mass index (12), 
which were not focused in the study. 
In conclusion, we showed that serum AnxA2 levels are 
most elevated early in the course of CHB infection. AnxA2 
may have clinical use as a biomarker or may be integrat-
ed with one or more liver fibrosis-predicting biomarker 
panels for the detection of early-stage fibrosis in patients 
with CHB infection. </p>

<p>Footnote </p>

<p>Authors' Contributions:Servet Kolgelier, Nazlim Ak-
tug Demir, Serap Ozcimen: examination of patients, 
data collection, writing the manuscript; Ahmet Cagkan 
Inkaya, Sua Sumer: writing the manuscript; Lutfi Saltuk 
Demir: statistical analysis; Fatma Seher Pehlivan: patho-
logical analysis; Mahmure Arslan, Abdullah Arpaci: bio-
chemical analysis. </p>



</text></tei>