<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4345638" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Ubiquitination is a post translational modification which 
mostly links with proteasome dependent protein degradation. 
This process has been known to play pivotal roles in the 
number of biological events including apoptosis, cell 
signaling, transcription and translation. Although the process 
of ubiquitination has been studied extensively, the mechanism 
of polyubiquitination by multi protein E3 ubiquitin ligase, SCF 
complex remains elusive. In the present study, we identified 
UbcH5a as a novel stimulating factor for poly-ubiquitination 
catalyzed by SCF 
hFBH1 using biochemical fractionations and 
MALDI-TOF. Moreover, we showed that recombinant UbcH5a 
and Cdc34 synergistically stimulate SCF 
hFBH1 catalyzed poly-
ubiquitination in vitro. These data may provide an important 
cue to understand the mechanism how the SCF complex 
efficiently polyubiquitinates target substrates. [BMB Reports 
2015; 48(1): 25-29] </p>

<p>Ubiquitin is a conserved 76 amino acid polypeptide con-
jugated to a lysine residue of target substrates through isopep-
tide bond, which is called ubiquitination (1-3). Ubiquitination 
is a post-translational modification process that consists of con-
secutive enzymatic steps. First, ubiquitin is activated by E1 </p>

<p>ubiquitin activating enzyme (E1), resulting in a thioester link-
age between the C-terminal carboxyl group of ubiquitin and 
the E1 cysteine residue (1). This process requires ATP as an en-
ergy source. Then, activated ubiquitin is transferred from E1 to 
the active site cysteine residue of ubiquitin conjugating en-
zyme (E2) (2). At the final step, ubiquitin ligase enzyme (E3) 
recognizes the substrate for ubiquitination and mediates the 
specific interaction with E2 and substrate. By doing so, the 
C-terminal glycine of ubiquitin is attached on a lysine residue 
of the target protein which is mediated by E3 (1-3). In general, 
polyubiquitinated target proteins are captured and degraded 
by the proteasome (4). In most organisms, E1, E2 and E3 en-
zymes exist in a hierarchical way. A single E1 enzyme acti-
vates ubiquitin for the entire array of downstream conjugating 
enzyme (1, 2). All E2s share a conserved core domain consist-
ing of about 150 amino acids. Despite their similarity to one 
other, different E2s execute distinct biological functions and 
the reflection of the specificity of E2 may be derived from the 
specific interaction with E3 (2, 3). Ubiquitination has been 
demonstrated to be involved in almost all biological processes 
such as cell cycle progression, signal transduction and tran-
scriptional regulation (5). 
Human F-box helicase 1 (hFBH1) is an F-box containing 
DNA helicase. It has been shown to act as DNA helicase and 
E3 ubiquitin ligase along with Skp1, Cul1 and Roc1, making 
an SCF complex (6). In the SCF complex, the interchangeable 
F-box protein governs the substrate specificity through physical 
interaction with target substrates. The best characterized F-box 
proteins are β-TRCP and SKP2. Both of them play roles in the 
recognition and degradation of IκBα and p27 respectively (7, 
8). Recently, it has been reported that hFBH1 is required for 
the apoptosis induced by DNA damage in response to DNA 
replication stress and that the level of hFBH1 is regulated by its 
own F-box domain, indicating hFBH1 ubiquitinates itself (9, 
10). However, the target substrates for SCF 
hFBH1 and its mecha-
nism of actions remain elusive. 
In the present study, we identified UbcH5a as a stimulating 
factor for SCF 
hFBH1 mediated polyubiquitination using bio-</p>

<p>UbcH5a stimulates SCF 
hFBH1 catalyzed polyubiquitination 
Jeong-Hoon Kim, et al. </p>

<p>26 BMB Reports 
http://bmbreports.org </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Purification of a stimulating factor for SCF 
hFBH1 catalyzed 
polyubiquitination from HeLa nuclear extracts. (A) Ubiquitin ligase 
assay was performed with or without HeLa nuclear extracts as de-
scribed in Materials and Methods (B) Flowchart of purification 
procedure. D: DEAE fractions, H: Heparin fractions, P: Hydroxya-
patite fractions. (C) Stimulation of polyubiquitin chain formation by 
Sephadex 75 fractions. Ubiquitin ligase assay was carried out us-
ing each Sephadex 75 fractions. The fraction number is shown as 
the top of each lane. Lo, Load on fraction. (D) The Sephadex 75 
fractions were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and silver staining. The 
fraction number is shown as the top of each lane. Molecular size 
markers are indicated at the left of the panel. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Sequence alignment of UbcH5s and purification of re-
combinant UbcH5s. (A) Amino acids sequences of human 
UbcH5s were aligned using <rs type="software">CLUSTRALW</rs>. (B) Purified recombi-
nant UbcH5s were analyzed by SDS-PAGE. Molecular size mark-
ers are indicated at the left of the panel. </p>

<p>chemical fractionation followed by MALDI-TOF. Moreover, 
we demonstrated that UbcH5a and Cdc34 can synergistically 
catalyze polyubiquitination in vitro. These data may render an 
important cue to understand the mechanism of ubiquitination 
by SCF ubiquitin ligase complex. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>HeLa nuclear extract stimulates SCF 
hFBH1 catalyzed 
polyubiquitination </p>

<p>In pursue of polyubiquitination substrates for SCF 
hFBH1 com-
plex, we developed the in vitro ubiquitination assay using puri-
fied SCF </p>

<p>hFBH1 </p>

<p>, ubiquitin activating enzyme E1 and ubiquitin 
conjugating enzyme Cdc34 which has been well-known as E2 
enzyme for SCF complex. It has been previously demonstrated 
that polyubiquitin is formed in the presence of E1, E2, ubiquitin 
ligase enzyme (E3) and ATP even in the absence of specific 
substrates for ubiquitination (11). Since hFBH1 is mainly lo-
calized in the nucleus, we assumed that the potential substrate </p>

<p>would be also localized in the nucleus. Thus, using HeLa nu-
clear extract, the in vitro ubiquitination assay was performed. 
Surprisingly, HeLa nuclear extract stimulated the formation of 
polyubiquitination (Fig. 1A), compared with the reaction with-
out nuclear extract (Fig. 1A, lane 7 and lane 8). When either E2 
or E3 was omitted, the polyubiquitin chain was not formed 
(lanes 1, 2, 3, 4 and 6), indicating that the polyubiquitin chain 
formation is dependent on both E2 and E3. Noting that the re-
action without E1 produced the polyubiquitin chains as much 
as the reaction with E1, we suggest that HeLa nuclear extracts 
contained sufficient E1 enzyme to produce polyubiquitin 
chains. Next, we decided to purify protein responsible for this 
stimulation by biochemical fractionations. Starting with HeLa 
nuclear extracts, we performed consecutive purifications by fol-
lowing the stimulating activity (Fig. 1B). Using biochemical as-
say with fractions from Sephadex 75, the stimulating activity 
peaked in fraction number 40 (Fig. 1C). Thus, in order to pin-
point this protein, fractions from Sephadex 75 were analyzed 
by SDS-PAGE and silver staining (Fig. 1D). Comparing the stim-
ulating activity and protein bands in SDS-PAGE, the stimulating 
activity was coincident with about 18KDa protein (Fig. 1D). </p>

<p>UbcH5a is identified as the stimulating factor </p>

<p>The respective gel band was excised and analyzed by 
MALDI-TOF to identify 18kDa protein. Two peptides (IYH 
PNINSNGSICLDILR and VLLSICSLLCDPNPDDPLVPDIAQIYK) 
corresponding to UbcH5a were determined. UbcH5 belongs 
to an evolutionally conserved subfamily of E2s involved in the 
ubiquitination of tumor suppressor p53 and hypoxia inducible 
transcription factor, HIF1α (12, 13). In mammals, there are 3 </p>

<p>UbcH5a stimulates SCF 
hFBH1 catalyzed polyubiquitination 
Jeong-Hoon Kim, et al. </p>

<p>27 
http://bmbreports.org 
BMB Reports </p>

<p>Fig. 3. The formation of ubiquitin polymers by SCF 
hFBH1 was cata-
lyzed by either UbcH5a or UbcH5c but not by UbcH5b. (A) The 
ubiquitin ligase assay was performed with various E2 enzymes 
(Cdc34, UbcH5a, UbcH5b or UbcH5c). (B) The ubiquitin ligase 
assay was performed under addition of indicated E2 enzyme. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. UbcH5a stimulates SCF 
hFBH1 mediated polyubiquitination. 
(A) Ubiquitin ligase assay was performed in different incubation 
time periods. The top and bottom panels were analyzed by 
13.5% and 7.5% SDS-PAGE, respectively. (B) The quantitation of 
the results is obtained in (A). The intensity of high molecular lad-
ders was measured using a Phosphorimager. (C) The ubiquitin li-
gase assay was performed using K48R ubiquitin. </p>

<p>UbcH5 isotypes; UbcH5a, UbcH5b and UbcH5c, sharing a 
highly homology of amino acid sequences (the identity of 
UbcH5a and UbcH5b; 89%, the identity of UbcH5a and 
UbcH5c; 88% and the identity of UbcH5b and UbcH5c; 97%) 
(Fig. 2A). We then wondered whether UbcH5a as well as 
UbcH5b and UbcH5c can stimulate SCF 
hFBH1 mediating the 
formation of polyubiquitin chains. To this end, recombinant 
UbcH5a, UbcH5b and UbcH5c were purified using E. coli ex-
pression system. The recombinant UbcH5a, UbcH5b and 
UbcH5c used in this study are shown in Fig. 2B. </p>

<p>UbcH5a and UbcH5c but not UbcH5b facilitate SCF </p>

<p>hFBH1 </p>

<p>catalyzed polyubiquitination </p>

<p>Since UbcH5 is an E2 ubiquitin conjugating enzyme per se, it 
is possible that sole UbcH5 can promote the formation of pol-
yubiquitin in the absence of Cdc34, a well-known E2 for the 
SCF complex. To test this, an increasing amount of either 
Cdc34, UbcH5a, UbcH5b or UbcH5c was incubated with 
ubiquitin, E1, and SCF 
hFBH1 in the presence of ATP. As shown 
in Fig. 3A, UbcH5a and UbcH5c promoted SCF 
hFBH1 catalyzed </p>

<p>polyubiquitination less efficiently when compared to Cdc34, 
suggesting that UbcH5a and UbcH5c can act as E2 for 
SCF </p>

<p>hFBH1 </p>

<p>. Although there are only 4 amino acids difference be-</p>

<p>UbcH5a stimulates SCF 
 
Jeong-Hoon Kim, et al. </p>

<p>28 BMB Reports 
http://bmbreports.org </p>

<p>tween UbcH5b and UbcH5c, UbcH5b did not promote the 
polyubiquitination (Fig. 3A, lanes 12-15). Note that different 
E2 showed different patterns of mono-and di-ubiquitination. 
As UbcH5a initially was identified as a stimulating factor for 
SCF 
hFBH1 catalyzed polyubiquitination, we tested whether 
UbcH5s could stimulate the polyubiquitination or not. For this 
purpose, purified UbcH5a, UbcH5b or UbcH5c was addition-
ally added to the reaction containing Ubiquitin, E1, Cdc34 and 
SCF </p>

<p>hFBH1 </p>

<p>. When increasing amounts of UbcH5a or UbcH5c 
were added, more polyubiquitin chains were formed com-
pared with the reaction with either the same amounts of 
UbcH5 or Cdc34 (Fig. 3B, lanes 2-8 and lanes 14-18). 
However, similar to the previous result, UbcH5b did not show 
a stimulating activity even in the presence of Cdc34 (Fig. 3B, 
lanes 9-13). It should be noted that the formation of poly-ubiq-
uitin chains was totally dependent on SCF </p>

<p>hFBH1 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>UbcH5a and cdc34 synergistically stimulates SCF </p>

<p>hFBH1 </p>

<p>catalyzed polyubiquitination </p>

<p>We carried out the time course experiments to observe the ef-
fect of UbcH5a in a time dependent manner. Since we did not 
observe any differences between UbcH5a and UbcH5c, 
UbcH5a was tested. The rate of poly-ubiquitin chain formation 
by UbcH5a was slow with a lag period, whereas that by Cdc34 
was rapid and saturated at 20 minutes (Fig. 4A and 4B). When 
UbcH5a and Cdc34 were both added, the poly-ubiquitin for-
mation proceeded with a short lag period (less than 2 minutes), 
and was still actively catalyzed at 60 minutes. The levels of 
ubiquitin polymers produced by both UbcH5a and cdc34 were 
significantly increased, implying that UbcH5a and cdc34 syn-
ergistically act on the formation of poly-ubiquitin chains (Fig. 
4A and 4B). There is a literature describing that UbcH5a cata-
lyzes non K48-linked poly-ubiquitination together with HECT 
E3 (14). Therefore, the question was raised if synergistically cat-
alyzed ubiquitin polymers could be non K48-linked 
polyubiquitination. To test this possibility, the time course ex-
periment was performed using mutant Ubiquitin where lysine 
48 was mutated to arginine (K48R mutant). As a result, the for-
mation of poly-ubiquitin chains was greatly reduced with the 
use of K48R Ubiquitin (Fig. 4C), even though UbcH5 and cdc34 
were charged by K48R Ubiquitin. This result suggests that ubiq-
uitin polymers synergistically produced by UbcH5a and cdc34 
are lysine 48 linked poly-ubiquitination. Interestingly, our re-
sults somewhat support a previous report that a single ubiquitin 
is initially rapidly transferred by UbcH5 to IκBα and then 
Cdc34 catalyzes SCF 
βTrCp2 catalyzed poly-ubiquitination of IKBα 
(15). Ryu and his colleagues showed E2 dependent target specif-
icity and processivity of p27 ubiquitination (16). The difference 
between previous reports and our results may be caused by the 
window we observed here that the formation of polyubiquitin 
chains was neither mono-nor di-ubiquitination. In addition, we 
utilized an in vitro reconstituted system to examine the SCF cat-
alyzed polyubiquitination. Considering the amino acid se-
quences and the structural similarity of UbcH5s, the other inter-</p>

<p>esting finding was that UbcH5a and UbcH5c can stimulate pol-
yubiquitination but UbcH5b did not. It would be intriguing to 
know if UbcH5b/c chimeric mutant were generated and exam-
ined to stimulate polyubiquitin formation or not. This iterative 
mutation experiments could render which amino acid is critical 
to differentiate the specificity among UbcH5a, b and c. In sum-
mary, we present the synergistic effect of two E2 enzymes in the 
formation of polyubiquitin chains. These results may provide a 
mechanistic cue to understand the process of SCF catalyzed 
polyubiquitination. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Purification of stimulating factor of SCF 
hFBH1 catalyzed 
polyubiquitination </p>

<p>HeLa nuclear extract was prepared as described previously 
(17). Nuclear extracts were dialyzed with T50. Dialyzed ex-
tract (75 ml, 365 mg) was loaded onto DEAE dextrose (50 ml). 
Flow-through fractions (85 ml, 97 mg) were fractionated over 
heparin sepharose (15 ml) which was preequilibrated with 
Buffer T50 (25 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 50 mM NaCl, 10% glyc-
erol, 1 mM DTT and 1 mM EDTA). The flow-through fraction 
of heparin sepharose (90 ml, 54 mg) was dialyzed with Buffer 
H (50 mM HEPES-KOH pH6.0, 50 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, 1 
mM DTT) and resulting fractions were subjected onto a 
Hydroxyapatite column (2 ml). Bound proteins were eluted 
with buffer p200 (200 mM Potassium phosphate pH6.0, 50 
mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, 1 mM DTT) (0.5 ml, 4 mg). Eluted 
proteins were loaded onto Sephadex 75 HR 10/30 (GE). The 
peak activity was exhibited by approximately 12 ml of eluted 
fraction. Each fraction was precipitated by TCA. Precipitants 
were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and silver staining. </p>

<p>Purification of recombinant UbcH5s </p>

<p>The full length cDNAs of UbcH5s were cloned by PCR using 
HeLa cDNA library. Amplified cDNA was subcloned to pET28 
(Life Technologies, NY, USA). All DNA sequences of UbcH5s 
were confirmed by sequencing. E. coli BL21 (DE3) harboring 
pET28-UbcH5s (0.5 L) were grown at 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C and induced with 
IPTG for 2 hours. The cell pellets were resuspended in buffer 
containing 25 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 200 mM NaCl, 10% glyc-
erol 5 mM imidazole and disrupted by sonication (3 cycles of 
30 second pulses and a 2 minutes cooling interval). The ex-
tracts were cleared by centrifugation at 40,000 rpm for 20 mi-
nutes in a Beckman 70 Ti rotor and the supernatant was load-
ed onto 1 ml of Ni-chelating Hitrap (GE, PA, USA). After ex-
tensive washing with buffer containing 50 mM imidazole, the 
column was eluted with buffer containing 200 mM imidazole. 
The peak fractions were pooled and dialyzed with buffer con-
taining 25 mM Tris-HCl pH7.5, 100 mM NaCl, 20% glycerol, 
1 mM DTT, 1 mM EDTA and protease inhibitors. </p>

<p>Ubiquitin ligation assay </p>

<p>Recombinant E1, Cdc34, SCF </p>

<p>hFBH1 </p>

<p>, and pk-Ub proteins were </p>

<p>UbcH5a stimulates SCF 
hFBH1 catalyzed polyubiquitination 
Jeong-Hoon Kim, et al. </p>

<p>29 
http://bmbreports.org 
BMB Reports </p>

<p>isolated as previously described (6). Briefly, pk-Ub (7 ug) was 
phosphorylated in a reaction mixture containing 20 mM 
Tris-HCl pH 7.4, 12 mM MgCl2, 2 mM NaF, 50 mM NaCl, 25 
uM ATP, 5 uCi of [r-32P] ATP, 0.1 mg/ml BSA, and 1 U of 
cAMP kinase (Sigma). To inactivate the reaction, the mixture 
was boiled at 70 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C for 5 minutes. The reaction mixture (30 μl) 
contained 50 mM Tris-HCl pH7.4, 5 mM MgCl2, 2 mM NaF, 
10 nM okadaic acid, 2 mM ATP, 0.6 mM DTT, 5 μg of </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P-Ub, 
E1 (2 pmol), Cdc34 (10 pmol) were incubated at 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C for 60 
minutes, added with 10 μl of 5XSDS loading buffer and boiled 
for 3 minutes prior to loading to SDS-PAGE for analysis. The 
amounts of polyubiquitin chains larger than E2 were measured 
using a Phosphorimager (BAS, FUJIFILM, Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>MALDI-TOF/MS </p>

<p>Corresponding silver stained bands were excised and analyzed 
by MALDI-TOF/MS. Mass spectrometry (MS) was performed 
on Yonsei proteome research center (YPRC, Korea) with a 
MALDI-TOF/TOF mass spectrometer (4800 ABSciex, MA, 
USA). Amino acid sequences of two peptides corresponding 
UbcH5a were determined (IYHPNINSNGSICLDILR and 
VLLSICSLLCDPNPDDPLVPDIAQIYK). </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank S. Y. Cho and K. H. Bae for the critical reading of 
the manuscript. This work was supported by KRIBB and re-
search grants from the National Research Foundation of Korea 
(2011-0008842 and NRF-2011-0028172). </p>



</text></tei>