<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4431426" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Educational clinical environment has an important role in nursing students' learning. 
Any difference between actual and expected clinical environment will decrease nursing students' 
interest in clinical environments and has a negative correlation with their clinical performance. 
Methods: This descriptive cross-sectional study is an attempt to compare nursing students' percep-
tion of the actual and expected status of clinical environments in medical-surgical wards. 
Participants of the study were 127 bachelor nursing students of Iran University of Medical Sciences 
in the internship period. Data gathering instruments were a demographic questionnaire (including 
sex, age, and grade point average), and the Clinical Learning Environment Inventory (CLEI) origi-
nally developed by Professor Chan (2001), in which its modified Farsi version (Actual and Preferred 
forms) consisting 42 items, 6 scales and 7 items per scale was used. Descriptive and inferential statis-
tics (t-test, paired t-test, ANOVA) were used for data analysis through SPSS version 16. 
Results: The results indicated that there were significant differences between the preferred and ac-
tual form in all six scales. In other word, comparing with the actual form, the mean scores of all 
items in the preferred form were higher. The maximum mean difference was in innovation and the 
highest mean difference was in involvement scale. 
Conclusion: It is concluded that nursing students do not have a positive perception of their actual 
clinical teaching environment and this perception is significantly different from their perception of 
their expected environment. </p>

<p>Keywords: Clinical learning environment, Nursing education, Nursing student. </p>

<p>Cite this article as: Bigdeli Sh, Pakpour V, Aalaa M, Shekarabi R, Sanjari M, Haghani H, Mehrdad N. Clinical learning environments </p>

<p>(actual and expected): percep-tions of Iran University of Medical Sciences nursing students. Med J Islam Repub Iran 2015 (4 February). 
Vol. 29:173. </p>

<p>Introduction 
Nursing education is strongly related to 
theoretical and clinical teaching. In this re-
gard, Nursing students' clinical experiences 
is an important element of the nursing pro-</p>

<p>fession (1) as well as clinical teaching 
which is cornerstone of the nursing educa-
tion. In this learning environment, students 
learn how to apply nursing knowledge, 
nursing skills, patient communication and </p>

<p>Clinical Learning environments </p>



<p>MJIRI, Vol. 29.173. 4 February 2015 </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>professionalization (2) and prepare them-
selves for practice in future workplaces. 
In this regard, several studies have shown 
that the learning environment is a signifi-
cant component with respect to clinical 
learning and learning outcomes (3). 
Throughout nursing history, clinical place-
ments play an essential role in the learning 
process of nursing students (4). Additional-
ly, nursing students may think that clinical 
environment is the most influential educa-
tional component to acquire nursing 
knowledge and skills (5). The clinical envi-
ronment consists of inpatient, hospital out-
patient and community settings, which has 
its specific challenges. Pringle and Green 
believed that nursing clinical experience is 
a factor that affects nursing student attribu-
tion (6). According to Farnia et al (2005), 
nursing students look for a favorable learn-
ing environment and their perception of the 
clinical learning environment is different 
from their perception of the actual learning 
environment (7). Zuzelo (2001) claimed 
that the most important step to develop 
continuing nursing education is to study 
nursing students' perception and to find the 
impacts of educational program on bache-
lor degrees (8). In this regard, Pugnair, et 
al. (2004) also supposed that assessing stu-
dents' perception and satisfaction of clini-
cal nursing experience would be essential 
for nursing faculty, because it gives feed-
back to students, faculty and school and 
leads to enhanced educational performance 
(9). To increase the quality of nursing edu-
cation programs along with evaluating 
nursing schools, students' comments 
should be considered important. Nursing 
students' perceptions about clinical educa-
tion has been assessed in different countries 
(10-14), however, Iranian studies in this 
field are rare (15). 
As a part of their clinical education nurs-
ing students participate in new clinical en-
vironments to gain clinical experience. 
Learning in these settings depends on en-
couraging environment based on psycho-
logical and pedagogical aspects (16-17). 
This is achieved by the teacher-student </p>

<p>connection and considerable learning situa-
tions that form a pedagogic atmosphere 
(16). 
One of the most important purposes in 
clinical education is decreasing the gap be-
tween the actual and expected clinical envi-
ronments that leads to an increased clinical 
learning performance. Therefore, it is of 
interest to examine how nursing students 
perceive clinical learning environments that 
they are assigned to as parts of nursing ed-
ucation. Hence, this study is an attempt to 
compare Iran University of Medical Sci-
ences (IUMS) medical-surgical nursing 
students' perceptions of actual and ex-
pected clinical environments. </p>

<p>Methods 
In this cross-sectional study, all sopho-
mores, junior and senior nursing bachelor 
students studying in the first semester of 
2009-10 at IUMS were selected. The inclu-
sion criteria were: to be a student and to 
spend clinical practice in a medical or sur-
gical ward. Freshman Nursing students 
were excluded due to lack of enough clini-
cal contact at the time of the study to pro-
vide adequate feedback on their clinical 
experiences. In addition, those students 
who suffered from chronic or disabling dis-
eases and psychosomatic disorders were 
excluded from the study. Moreover, partic-
ipants of the study were informed about the 
purpose of the study. Then, consent form 
was secured from each of them. After-
wards, the demographic questionnaire and 
Farsi version of Clinical Learning Envi-
ronment Inventory (CLEI) were distributed 
among all participants at the end of their 
internship period in medical or surgical 
wards. </p>

<p>Instruments 
Data gathering instruments were a demo-
graphic questionnaire (including sex, aca-
demic year, and grade point average), and 
modified Farsi version of CLEI for Iranian 
context. The original CLEI (actual and ex-
pected) was developed by Chan (18-19) as 
a 42-item instrument, consisting of 6 scales </p>

<p>Sh. Bigdeli, et al. </p>



<p>MJIRI, Vol. 29.173. 4 February 2015 </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>with 7 items per each scale. Each positive 
statement is scored on the basis of a 5-point 
Likert scale ranging from strongly disagree 
(1) to strongly agree (5), and each invalid 
response scored 3, whilst negative state-
ments were scored in the reverse manner. 
By assessing the actual and expected situa-
tions, and considering students' perceptions 
of psychosocial characteristics of the clini-
cal learning environment, this inventory 
assesses students' perceptions of their ex-
pected ideal clinical environment. 
The CLEI six domains are personaliza-
tion, student satisfaction, involvement, in-
dividualization, task orientation and inno-
vation (18-19). Individualization reflects 
the extent to which students are encouraged 
to make decisions and are treated different-
ly according to their ability or interest. In-
novation measures the extent to which clin-
ical teacher or clinician plans for interesting 
productive learning experiences. Involve-
ment assesses the extent to which students 
participate actively and attentively in hospi-
tal activities. Personalization emphasizes 
on opportunities for each individual student 
to interact with the clinical teacher. Task 
Orientation, however, assesses whether the 
instructions for hospital activities are clear 
and well organized. Student Satisfaction in 
actual form was used to assess the students' 
level of satisfaction due to their clinical 
placements (10, 13). An Australian study 
has identified the validity of the CLEI via 
Cronbach alpha in which coefficients 
ranged from 0.73 to 0.84 and 0.66-0.80 
respectively for the actual and the expected 
forms (20). 
For the purposes of this study, required 
permission to use the CLEI was obtained 
from its original developer through consec-
utive emails. Then, the CLEI was translated 
into Farsi and its content validity was 
checked by 8 experts, the results of which 
were decided upon on the basis of consen-
sus between two final experts as referees. 
For this modified Farsi version, the 
Cronbach's alpha coefficient reliability 
score was 0.76 and 0.80 for actual and ex-
pected forms, respectively. </p>

<p>Thereafter, the study was performed ac-
cording to the approval of the Center for 
Nursing Care Research (CNCR), and Ethics 
Committee of School of Nursing and Mid-
wifery of Iran University of Medical Sci-
ences. 
Students were informed that their anony-
mous responses would be used for further 
development and planning of hospital 
placements. It was emphasized that the stu-
dents' participation in the study was entire-
ly voluntary and that they have the right to 
refuse to participate or withdraw from the 
study at any time. Students were invited to 
complete the questionnaires in privacy, im-
plied consent was assumed when students 
returned the completed questionnaires in 
the sealed box provided. It was estimated 
that students spent approximately 20 
minutes answering the two questionnaires. </p>

<p>Statistical Methods 
The data were analyzed using descriptive 
and inferential statistics (t-test, paired t-test, 
ANOVA) through <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">16</rs>. Kol-
mogorov-Smirnov test was used to check 
the normality of data. 
T-test was used to compare differences of 
mean scores in actual and preferred clinical 
learning environments between males and 
females. ANOVA was used to compare dif-
ferences of mean scores in actual and pre-
ferred clinical learning environments be-
tween age, and grade point average. Paired 
t-test was used to compare differences of 
mean scores between nursing students ac-
tual and preferred clinical learning envi-
ronments. </p>

<p>Results 
One hundred thirty three questionnaires 
were distributed among the participants 
with a response rate of 95% (127). Of all 
the respondents, 62.2% were female (79), 
64.6% sophomore (82), and 41.7% (53) had 
grade point average of 14-16 (Table 1). 
We examined the mean scores and stand-
ard deviations of the CLEI scales. In this 
regard, in the actual form of the instrument, 
personalization and innovation scored the </p>

<p>Clinical Learning environments </p>



<p>MJIRI, Vol. 29.173. 4 February 2015 </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>highest (23.65±5.393) and the lowest 
means (17.20±5.09) (Table 2). 
In the expected form of the instrument, 
student satisfaction scored the highest 
(30.51±3.542) and involvement the lowest 
means (24.67±3.050) (Table 2). 
Students had different perceptions about 
actual and expected clinical learning envi-
ronments assessed by investigating the dif-
ferences on related scales of the CLEI actu-
al and expected forms. A paired t-test was 
used to analyze the paired samples (n 
=127). The results suggested significant 
differences (p&lt;0.001) between all the 
paired scales in the actual and expected 
forms. In this regard, comparing the mean 
scores of all scales between expected and 
actual forms indicated that the mean scores 
of expected forms were higher than the ac-
tual one. The highest mean differences be-
longed to the innovation (12.45± 6.781) 
and the lowest mean difference was in in-
volvement scale (3.39± 4.478) (Table 2). 
Results of t-test showed that there was no 
significant difference among students' per-
ception of the actual environment accord-
ing to their sex (p=0. 096), while a signifi-
cant difference was seen in two scales of 
satisfaction and task orientation (p=0.002). 
One-way ANOVA results showed signif-
icant differences between actual and ex-</p>

<p>pected environments, in all scales for all 
participants according to their year of study 
(junior and senior) (p&lt;0.001). While, in an 
expected environment individualization 
was the only scale that showed significant 
difference according to the year of this 
study (p&lt;0.001). Also, it indicated that in 
the actual environment, there is no signifi-
cant difference among students' percep-
tions of all scales according to grade point 
average, but in an expected environment 
the involvement scale showed a significant 
difference according to the grade point av-
erage (p=0.006). </p>

<p>Discussion 
According to the results, the mean scores 
of actual and expected situations of the 
clinical learning environment in six do-
mains were different. There was a signifi-
cant difference between actual and ex-
pected environments. In other words, stu-
dents' expectations of clinical environment 
were not satisfied and comparing to the ex-
perienced clinical education environment 
they preferred an enhanced educational en-
vironment. Chan also confirms this finding 
(20); however, this result is different from 
Perli &amp; Brugnolli's findings in which all 
domains had high score in Italy and their 
actual and expected situations scored the </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic Characteristics of Participants 
Variable 
n(%) 
Sex 
Male 
48 (37.8) 
Female 
79 (62.2) 
Student years 
2 nd year 
82 (64.4) 
3 rd year 
45 (35.4) 
Grade average 
Below 14 
12 (9.4) 
14-16 
53 (41.7) 
Above 16 
39 (30.7) </p>

<p>Table 2. The CLEI assessment scores for IUMS nursing students 
p&lt; 
Mean difference 
SD (N=127) 
Mean (n=127) 
Scale 
Preferred 
Actual 
Preferred 
Actual </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
5.99 
2.770 
5.393 
29.64 
23.65 
Personalization 
&lt;0.001 
9.31 
3.542 
6.715 
30.51 
21.38 
Student Satisfaction 
&lt;0.001 
3.39 
3.050 
3.428 
24.67 
21.28 
Involvement 
&lt;0.001 
6.26 
2.957 
4.801 
29.41 
23.15 
Task Orientation 
&lt;0.001 
12.45 
4.003 
5.091 
29.65 
17.20 
Innovation 
&lt;0.001 
7.48 
6.124 
5.259 
27.83 
20.35 
Individualization </p>

<p>Sh. Bigdeli, et al. </p>



<p>MJIRI, Vol. 29.173. 4 February 2015 </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>same (21). 
In this study, the highest and lowest mean 
scores between actual and expected envi-
ronments belonged to innovation and in-
volvement domains, respectively. The 
mean score of the other domains such as 
student satisfaction, and personalization 
were situated between the extremes. This 
shows that the deepest gap was between 
actual and expected environments in "inno-
vation" domain. 
In this regard, innovation could be con-
sidered as one of the main drivers of quality 
teaching improvement and can be spurred 
by a number of factors (22). On the other 
hand critical thinking in all health care set-
tings is a skill that develops over time and 
requires the conscious application of this 
process (23). Thus, it is concluded that 
combination of these two essential compo-
nents in teaching and learning environment 
will increase the effectiveness of regular 
methods and leads to increased learning. 
Other studies in Iranian context by Delaram 
(24), Pardijani (25), and Rahimi and Ah-
madi (26), emphasized that innovation has 
a critical importance in clinical education 
of nursing students, however lack of inno-
vation and new technologies are the critical 
difficulties of clinical education in Iran. 
"Student satisfaction of clinical educa-
tion" was the second domain with signifi-
cant difference between actual and ex-
pected environments. This means that it 
was not considered in clinical education 
environments. In another Iranian study, 
Moattari and Ramezani (27) supported this 
finding and considered student satisfaction 
as one of the major components of the clin-
ical education atmosphere. Chan has con-
sidered student satisfaction as education 
outcome and has attracted the attention of 
nursing authorities and policy makers to 
this issue (20). 
The third difference seen between actual 
and expected environments was in "indi-
vidualization domain" which showed that 
nursing instructors has paid less attention to 
this issue. Pardijani (25) has considered 
individual differences and qualifications of </p>

<p>students as the main elements of education-
al quality improvement. 
In individualization domain, students' in-
dependence in clinical decision making was 
taken into account. Lack of attention into 
individual differences is one of the weak-
nesses of clinical education environments 
that is unable to provide the conditions in 
which students become fully competent to 
make independent clinical decisions; this is 
supported by Hadizadeh et al, in another 
Iranian study (28). 
Zeighami indicated that 76% of students' 
dissatisfaction were due to inability to 
make decisions for proper planning of clin-
ical care of patients(29). Delaram men-
tioned that 57.1% of nursing students were 
unable to make independent decisions 
about patients' care plan (24). 
"Task orientation" was the fourth differ-
ence between actual and expected envi-
ronments that is due to ambiguity of stu-
dents' tasks in clinical settings. They per-
ceived task orientation as an important fac-
tor that influences the outcomes of their 
clinical placement. The students perceived 
the opportunities for themselves to be di-
rectly involved with hands-on skills often 
controlled by clinicians and clinical teach-
ers. It is apparent that the participants have 
enjoyed applying their learned skills into 
practice in the clinical environment. 
Most importantly, the compliment from 
clients and clinicians for a well done job 
were both encouraging and rewarding. This 
supports the findings of Hart and Rotem 
which suggested that students enjoy being 
active and having a proper level of auton-
omy (30). 
Task orientation in the CLEI evaluations, 
for understanding the extent students know 
the clinical activities in the ward are clear 
and well-ordered. Many students perceive 
clinical experience as anxiety-provoking 
(31-32). They often, while becoming less 
worried in clinical environment after few 
encounters in ward activities (10). To facil-
itate the beginners to enthusiastically coop-
erate in ward activities that probably affect 
the clients health directly, the working </p>

<p>Clinical Learning environments </p>



<p>MJIRI, Vol. 29.173. 4 February 2015 </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>ward staff are supposed to present clear de-
tailed directions for students' safe practice. 
Newell, as cited in Harandi et al, men-
tioned that course objectives provide the 
opportunity to select teaching-learning ac-
tivities (33). Yazdankhah also indicated 
unclear course objectives and tasks as the 
most important stress inducing factors (34). 
This study showed that students need to be 
task-oriented in clinical educational envi-
ronments. 
The fifth difference between actual and 
expected settings was "personalization", in 
which instructors have not paid enough at-
tention to students' personality and did not 
involve them in professional and clinical 
practice. The actual form reflected that the 
maximum mean score in personalization is 
related to the previous support student re-
ceived. However, the students in clinical 
environment who felt being supported, re-
spected, and recognized, supported the 
personalization scale of preferred form by 
means of allocating high scores (13). 
The maximum score in CLEI belonged to 
the personalization. This scale emphasizes 
the chance of student to cooperate with 
clinical educator and clinical staff in addi-
tion to concerning student's personal wel-
fare. In each semester, nursing students 
should be trained for sevral weeks in hospi-
tals as a clinical environment during the 
period of clinical placement, nursing stu-
dents commonly feel vulnerable. It seems 
that during training period in clinical 
placement, nurse students are expected to 
earn respect, support and recognition, 
which could be a reason for high mean 
score of personalization in the actual form. 
It should be mentioned that the higher score 
for personalization in the preferred form 
showed that nursing students, in general, 
require more support, respect and recogni-
tion from clinical educator and clinician in 
the clinical learning environment (10). 
Since in Iran nurse students spend a lim-
ited time in each ward and because ward 
rotation interact with different instructors, it 
seems that they expect a better interaction 
with their instructors. According to Chan's </p>

<p>description of personalization, from the 
stand point of 74.1% of students, instructor-
student interaction is the strength of clinical 
education (20). In one Iranian study, this 
issue and attention to the student's person-
ality were reported as the strengths of clini-
cal education that should be emphasized in 
educational environments (26). Salmani's 
study indicated that 78.9% of nursing stu-
dents considered instructor-student interac-
tion and students' personality at an average 
point (35). Midwifery students believe that, 
in most cases, barriers in clinical education 
are related to instructor's personality (36). 
According to the results of this research, 
students have not assigned a high score to 
the actual state of "personalization in the 
clinical setting". Additionally, students 
stated no satisfaction in students -clinical 
teacher relationship. This occurred as op-
posed to varied opportunities available for 
students to cooperate with their teachers. In 
this regard, the level of difference between 
the actual and expected states is "involve-
ment in clinical activities". Consistent with 
Chan's findings, the lowest difference may 
be associated with the minimum tendency 
of students to do clinical activities (10). 
Students name the following situations as 
stress inducing: care of a terminally ill pa-
tient, time pressure of certain activities, 
clinical trial evaluations, performance and 
frequent changes of services/health insti-
tutes (37-39), which may be due to stu-
dents' low expectations to become involved 
in clinical activities. On the other hand, ac-
cording to Chan, students believe that after 
being involved in clinical activities they 
experience less anxiety and stress in clini-
cal environments (10). This shows that if 
instructors facilitate involvement of stu-
dents in clinical activities, there may be a 
room for students' expectations. Clinical 
staff must provide clear instructions to ren-
der safe care by students that shows the re-
lationship between the two domains, in-
cluding "students' involvement in clinical 
activities" and "task orientation in clinical 
period" in order to facilitate student in-
volvement in ward activities. In general, the </p>

<p>Sh. Bigdeli, et al. </p>



<p>MJIRI, Vol. 29.173. 4 February 2015 </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>results showed that students' expectation of 
their involvement in clinical practice is near 
to the actual status, but to fulfill their ex-
pectations in this regard there is a need to 
take specific steps. 
Nursing students have different percep-
tions of the expected and actual environ-
ment in clinical teaching. In other words, 
students' expectations of the clinical teach-
ing environment have not been fulfilled in 
any domain. In contrast, students prefer a 
theoretical teaching environment than a 
clinical teaching environment that benefits 
from the highest level scores in all do-
mains. Finally, the results of this study 
show that nursing students do not have a 
positive perception of clinical teaching en-
vironment and their perceptions of the ac-
tual environment is significantly different 
to their perceptions of an expected envi-
ronment. </p>

<p>Conclusion 
According to the results of this research, 
considering students' expectations of clini-
cal teaching environment and decreasing 
the gap between the actual and expected 
clinical environments is necessary. In addi-
tion, continuous studies on clinical teaching 
environment evaluation and their results, 
and to assess clinical instructors' and clini-
cal staff opinions about the clinical teach-
ing environment are recommended. 
One of the limitations of the current study 
was that the participants were selected from 
one nursing school in Iran. Therefore, the 
sample may not be representative of Iranian 
nursing students in general. Accordingly, to 
generalize the findings should be done cau-
tiously. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements 
We appreciate Professor Dominic SK 
Chan, who kindly permitted us to adapt 
CLES inventory for Iranian contexts. We 
are grateful to professors, instructors, and 
students of Iran University of Medical Sci-
ences Nursing and Midwifery School with-
out whose support and cooperation this re-
search was impossible. Furthermore, this </p>

<p>paper is the result of a Master's thesis enti-
tled "Perception of nursing students about 
the actual and expected clinical education 
environment in Iran University of Medical 
Sciences" which was granted by Center for 
Nursing Care Research of Iran University 
of Medical Sciences. </p>



<p>Clinical Learning environments </p>





</text></tei>