<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4504747" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Aim To evaluate the association with diabetic kidney disease of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) that may 
contribute to mitochondrial dysfunction. </p>

<p>Methods The mitochondrial genome and 1039 nuclear genes that are integral to mitochondrial function were 
investigated using a case (n = 823 individuals with diabetic kidney disease) vs. control (n = 903 individuals with 
diabetes and no renal disease) approach. All people included in the analysis were of white European origin and were 
diagnosed with Type 1 diabetes before the age of 31 years. Replication was conducted in 5093 people with similar 
phenotypes to those of the discovery collection. Association analyses were performed using the PLINK genetic analysis 
toolset, with adjustment for relevant covariates. </p>

<p>Results A total of 25 SNPs were evaluated in the mitochondrial genome, but none were significantly associated with 
diabetic kidney disease or end-stage renal disease. A total of 38 SNPs in nuclear genes influencing mitochondrial function 
were nominally associated with diabetic kidney disease and 16 SNPS were associated with end-stage renal disease, 
secondary to diabetic kidney disease, with meta-analyses confirming the same direction of effect. Three independent 
signals (seven SNPs) were common to the replication data for both phenotypes with Type 1 diabetes and persistent 
proteinuria or end-stage renal disease. </p>

<p>Conclusions Our results suggest that SNPs in nuclear genes that influence mitochondrial function are significantly 
associated with diabetic kidney disease in a white European population. </p>

<p>Diabetic kidney disease is a complex renal disorder repre-
senting a major global economic burden [1,2]. There is 
an inherited genetic predisposition for diabetic kidney 
disease, but the majority of studies to date have focused on 
genetic variation in the nuclear genome [3]. Mitochondria 
are specialized organelles that generate energy by oxidative 
phosphorylation, but they are susceptible to oxidative </p>

<p>damage from cellular stress, including hyperglycaemia and 
exposure to a uraemic environment. Chronic inflammation is 
a common contributor to progressive renal failure and leads 
to premature mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) damage. Path-
ogenic mutations in mtDNA represent an increasingly 
recognized cause of chronic morbidity, and mitochondrial 
mutations have been implicated in a range of complex 
disorders, including kidney disease [4-6]. There is a 
synergistic relationship between the mitochondrial and 
nuclear genomes, with the expression of nuclear genes being 
essential for critical mitochondrial functions. 
The aim of the present study was to investigate genetic 
variation that may contribute to mitochondrial dysfunction, 
both across the mitochondrial genome and in nuclear genes </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Amy Jayne McKnight. E-mail: a.j.mcknight@qub.ac.uk 
This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and 
distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the 
use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>1104 </p>

<p>ª 2015 The Authors. 
Diabetic Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Diabetes UK. </p>

<p>DIABETICMedicine </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1111/dme.12763 </p>

<p>that affect mitochondrial function, using a case-control 
approach, followed by independent replication. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Participants </p>

<p>Written informed consent was obtained from all individuals 
in the discovery cohort who were recruited to the All-Ireland-
Warren 3-Genetics of Kidneys in Diabetes (GoKinD) UK 
collections. Cases (n = 823) were white European individu-
als with Type 1 diabetes of at least 10 years duration, who 
had persistent proteinuria ( &gt; 500 mg/24 h), hypertension 
( ≥ 135/85 mmHg) and retinopathy. End-stage renal disease 
(n = 246), secondary to diabetic kidney disease, was defined 
as requiring renal replacement therapy (chronic dialysis or 
kidney transplantation). Control subjects (n = 903) were 
people with at least 15 years' duration of Type 1 diabetes, 
with no evidence of renal disease on repeated testing. Control 
subjects were not prescribed anti-hypertensive medication to 
avoid misclassification of phenotype, as blood pressure-
lowering treatment may reduce proteinuria. The discovery 
and replication groups have been previously described and 
include the FinnDiane (Finland), GoKinD (USA), and Steno 
Diabetes Centre (Denmark) cohorts (Table S1) [7]. In all, 
3245 people with diabetic kidney disease, 1422 people with 
end-stage renal disease and 3574 control subjects were 
analysed in the present study. </p>

<p>Gene, single-nucleotide polymorphism selection and </p>

<p>genotyping </p>

<p>Twenty-five single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in the 
mitochondrial genome were investigated using existing </p>

<p>genotype data from individuals genotyped using the 
Omni1-quad array using a case vs control group approach 
(Table S2) [7]. Relevant nuclear genes (n = 1096) were 
extracted from MITOCARTA [8] (n = 1012 genes) and MITOMAP 
[9] (n = 84 genes). Downloaded gene lists were revised to 
approved unique HUGO Gene Nomenclature Committee 
[10] symbols, resulting in the removal of 57 duplicate gene 
names; a total of 1039 unique nuclear genes were analysed. 
The SNPs were downloaded from the Ensembl genome 
browser [11] using Ensembl genes 74 database on the Homo 
sapiens (GRCh37.p13) dataset. The SNPs (n = 9 243 501) 
associated with 1039 genes in the nuclear genome that 
influence mitochondrial function were investigated for their 
association with diabetic kidney disease. Genotype data for 
nuclear genes were extracted for relevant genes from 
imputed, publicly accessible directly typed genome-wide 
data for the discovery cohort (dbGaP Study Accession: 
phs000389.v1.p1; [7]). In silico replication was conducted 
for all top-ranked SNPs, where P ≤ 0.05 in the discovery 
study when considering either diabetic kidney disease or end-
stage renal disease as the phenotype; data were retrieved 
from the GENIE genome-wide association study meta-
analysis [7]. De novo genotyping was conducted for 
replication of the top seven independent signals using 
commercially available TaqMan 5' nuclease assays (Life 
Technologies, Warrington, UK) according to the manufac-
turer's instructions. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Allelic association was adjusted for age, duration of diabetes, 
gender and multiple testing using <rs id="software-1" type="software">PLINK</rs> software (version 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">1.07</rs> [12]) for de novo genotyping. <rs id="software-2" type="software">PLINK</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">http:// pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/~purcell/plink</rs>) is a free, open-
source whole-genome association analysis toolset, which 
efficiently performs association studies for single SNPs or 
computationally intensive genome-wide association studies. 
Replication was conducted in silico for the FinnDiane 
(n = 2910) and USA (n = 1595) populations, followed by 
de novo genotyping in a Danish (n = 588) cohort. Genotype 
data were evaluated for their association with diabetic 
kidney disease and end-stage renal disease. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Concordance between genotype duplicates (n = 12) was 
100%, with genotype completion rates of &gt; 89% for SNPs 
in the mitochondrial genome and &gt; 97.5% for SNPs in the 
nuclear genome. 
One mtDNA SNP was monomorphic in the UK collection; 
MitoT9951C. A further 19 mtDNA SNPs were present with 
a minor allele frequency ≤ 5%. Five SNPs were observed 
with a minor allele frequency of &gt; 5%, but no SNPs in the 
mitochondrial genome were associated with diabetic kidney 
disease (Table S2). </p>

<p>What's new? </p>

<p>• Mitochondrial dysfunction has been identified in dia-
betic kidney disease, but relatively large-scale genetic 
and epigenetic studies focused on mitochondria have 
not yet been described. </p>

<p>• We report a novel case-control analysis, with indepen-
dent replication, of genetic variation focused on the 
mitochondrial genome and 1039 nuclear genes that are 
important for mitochondrial function. </p>

<p>• Single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in nuclear 
genes affecting mitochondrial function were found to be 
associated with diabetic kidney disease. The highlighted 
SNPs were within the genes implicated in regulation of 
epigenetic processes. Further research to explore the 
interactions between hyperglycaemia, uraemia and 
epigenetic modifications of the genome could shed 
new light on how these nuclear genome SNPs are 
associated with kidney disease. </p>

<p>ª 2015 The Authors. 
Diabetic Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Diabetes UK. </p>



<p>Research article 
DIABETICMedicine </p>

<p>A total of 9 243 501 SNPs in mitochondrial-related 
nuclear genes were downloaded from Ensembl [11]. A 
comparison of 823 cases with Type 1 diabetes and nephrop-
athy with 903 control subjects with Type 1 diabetes and no 
evidence of nephropathy identified 421 SNPs in 86 unique 
genes with a nominal association (P ≤ 0.05) with diabetic 
kidney disease, without correction for multiple testing. In 
silico replication in the FinnDiane (n = 2910), and USA 
(n = 1595) cohorts supported the association of 38 SNPs in 
17 unique genes with consistent direction of effect across all 
collections (Table S3). Consideration of the more extreme 
phenotype of end-stage renal disease (246 cases vs. 903 
controls) identified 139 SNPs in 50 unique genes where 
P ≤ 0.05. In silico replication in the FinnDiane and GoKinD 
USA cohorts supported the association of 16 SNPs in eight 
genes (seven independent signals, P &lt; 0.05), with a consis-
tent direction of effect observed across all three case-control 
collections for end-stage renal disease (Table 1). SNPs were 
investigated for regulatory features using HAPLOREG and 
Blood eQTL browsers (Tables S4 and S5, respectively). 
Seven SNPs (representing three independent signals) were 
common to both diabetic kidney disease and end-stage renal 
disease for the in silico replication analyses; SNPs represent-
ing each of these three independent signals were taken 
forward for additional de novo genotyping using indepen-
dent samples. As the recent GENIE genome-wide association 
study [7] identified more significant hits with end-stage renal 
disease, all independent signals observed for end-stage renal 
disease (n = 7; Table 1) were also de novo genotyped in a 
Danish cohort of 588 individuals. Four SNPs (rs2147653, 
rs7387720, rs1167726, rs7213412) in the Danish cohort 
showed non-significant trends in the same direction as the 
earlier results, with rs17745445 (TXNRD2 gene on 
22q11.21) showing the most evidence for association. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The mitochondrial genome is circular, is 16 569 DNA bases 
in length, encodes 37 genes, and can be transcribed and 
translated independently of nuclear DNA. There are several 
differences between mitochondrial and nuclear genomes; 
mtDNA is primarily coding (lacking introns), and has 
overlapping genes, different codons, a higher mutation rate 
and a greater number of copies of mtDNA present in cells 
that have high energy consumption. 
Previous publications have reported that SNPs in the 
mitochondrial and nuclear genomes affect mitochondrial 
function and have been associated with renal dysfunction 
[5,6,13-16]. In the present study, none of the genotyped 
SNPs in the mitochondrial genome were significantly 
associated with diabetic kidney disease, but the majority 
were present at very low frequency meaning that the 
discovery collection was only adequately powered to 
identify a statistically significant association for five of the 
25 SNPs investigated. It should be noted that only 25 SNPs, </p>

<p>from the mitochondrial genome, were present on the 
Omni1-quad array so only a limited number of mitochon-
drial SNPs were considered for their association with 
diabetic kidney disease using this array-based method. It 
is conceivable that more comprehensive examination of the 
entire mitochondrial genome by next-generation sequencing 
methods would identify hundreds of inherited and somatic 
mutations and some of these mitochondrial variants may be 
associated with diabetic kidney disease. Seven SNPs, repre-
senting three independent signals across five nuclear genes 
(COQ5, COX6A1, GATC, TOP1MT and PARCRG) were 
associated with both diabetic kidney disease and end-stage 
renal disease in the discovery and in silico replication 
analyses. 
Six SNPs identified as associated with end-stage renal 
disease and diabetic kidney disease after in silico replication 
were co-located, representing one independent signal at 
12q24.31. There are multiple genes within this linkage 
disequilibrium block, making it challenging to identify 
potential biological roles for these intronic or intergenic 
mutations (Fig. S1). Coenzyme Q is an antioxidant essential 
for electron-transport in the respiratory chain of the mito-
chondria; coenzyme Q5 homologue (COQ5) encodes methyl-
transferase. Cytochrome c oxidase (COX) is an enzyme, 
catalysing the last step in the respiratory cycle, transferring 
electrons from reduced cytochrome c to molecular oxygen. 
This process is then coupled to the translocation of protons 
in the inner mitochondrial membrane. A total of 13 subunits 
comprise COX, of which three larger subunits are encoded 
by mtDNA and the remaining 10 are encoded by nuclear 
DNA [17]. COX deficiencies have been previously associated 
with clinical phenotypes including neurological disorders, 
Leigh syndrome, cardiomyopathy and hepatopathy [17]. The 
effect of the intronic SNP located in the COX6A1 may lead 
to an increase in oxidative stress within the kidney. Glutam-
yl-tRNA(Gln) amidotransferase, subunit C (GATC) is a 
protein-coding gene, and clusters with long non-coding 
RNA. 
Two SNPS comprised a second independent signal around 
the TOP1MT gene (mitochondrial topoisomerase I), which 
encodes an enzyme, topoisomerase, that exclusively targets 
mitochondria and plays a crucial role in the modification of 
DNA [18]. TOP1MT relieves the tension of mtDNA 
supercoiling generated from mtDNA transcription and rep-
lication, within the mitochondrial genome. TOP1MT is a 
type 1B topoisomerase. It catalyses the temporary breaking 
of the DNA and allows the DNA to turn in a controlled 
rotation, before covalently linking the DNA to relax the 
super coiling [18]. 
The third independent signal showed a consistent direction 
of effect across all four collections (UK-ROI, Finnish, 
American and Danish) for two intronic SNPs in the 
TXNRD2 gene. This gene plays a key role in regulating 
cellular redox environment, particularly scavenging of reac-
tive oxygen species in mitochondria. TNXRD2 is a stress </p>



<p>ª 2015 The Authors. 
Diabetic Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Diabetes UK. </p>

<p>DIABETICMedicine 
mtDNA SNPs and diabetic kidney disease E. J. Swan et al. </p>

<p>Table 1 
Discovery and replication results for SNPs with 
P ≤ 0.05 for end-stage renal disease in the UK collection </p>

<p>SNP </p>

<p>Gene </p>

<p>Location </p>

<p>of SNP </p>

<p>Chromosome </p>

<p>Independent </p>

<p>signal </p>

<p>Allele </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Allele </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Allele 
frequency, </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>End-stage </p>

<p>renal disease </p>

<p>P value for 
UK collection </p>

<p>End-stage </p>

<p>renal disease </p>

<p>P value (UK, 
FD, GoKinD 
USA) </p>

<p>Direction </p>

<p>of effect 
(UK, FD, 
GoKinD 
USA) </p>

<p>Diabetic 
kidney 
disease </p>

<p>P value 
for UK 
collection </p>

<p>Diabetic 
kidney 
disease </p>

<p>P value 
(UK, FD, 
GoKinD 
USA) </p>

<p>End-stage </p>

<p>renal 
disease </p>

<p>P value 
Steno </p>

<p>Diabetic 
kidney 
disease </p>

<p>P value 
Steno </p>

<p>rs1167726* </p>

<p>COQ5 </p>

<p>intronic </p>

<p>12q24.31 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>84.29 </p>

<p>0.0019 </p>

<p>1.00E-06 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.006 
2.00E-05 0.32 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.39 </p>

<p>rs614226* </p>

<p>COQ5 </p>

<p>intronic </p>

<p>12q24.31 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>84.29 </p>

<p>0.0018 </p>

<p>1.00E-06 </p>

<p>ÀÀÀ </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>2.00E-05 </p>

<p>rs1167725 </p>

<p>COQ5 
intergenic 12q24.31 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>17.76 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>2.00E-06 </p>

<p>ÀÀÀ </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>4.00E-05 </p>

<p>rs12310837* 
COX6A1 intergenic 12q24 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>84.22 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>2.00E-06 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>3.00E-05 </p>

<p>rs2235222* </p>

<p>GATC </p>

<p>intronic </p>

<p>12q24.31 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>15.66 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>3.00E-06 </p>

<p>ÀÀÀ </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>4.00E-05 </p>

<p>rs7137953* </p>

<p>GATC </p>

<p>intronic </p>

<p>12q24.31 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>84.34 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>3.00E-06 </p>

<p>ÀÀÀ </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>4.00E-05 </p>

<p>rs7387720 
TOP1MT intergenic 8q24.3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>53.97 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>7.00E-06 </p>

<p>ÀÀÀ </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>9.00E-05 0.70 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.94 </p>

<p>rs724037* 
TOP1MT intronic </p>

<p>8q24.3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>54.03 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>2.00E-05 </p>

<p>ÀÀÀ </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>2.00E-04 </p>

<p>rs17745445 
TXNRD2 intronic </p>

<p>22q11.21 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>13.69 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>7.00E-05 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>3.00E-04 0.06 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>rs17745433 
TXNRD2 intronic </p>

<p>22q11.21 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>14.28 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>7.00E-05 </p>

<p>ÀÀÀ </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>4.00E-04 </p>

<p>rs5992495 
TXNRD2 missense </p>

<p>22q11.21 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>15.85 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>5.00E-04 </p>

<p>ÀÀÀ </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.14 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.14 </p>

<p>rs5992493 
TXNRD2 intronic </p>

<p>22q11.21 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>84.16 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>5.00E-04 </p>

<p>ÀÀÀ </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>rs176903 </p>

<p>SPTLC2 </p>

<p>intronic </p>

<p>14q24.3 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>34.62 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>ÀÀÀ </p>

<p>0.0003 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.14 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.09 </p>

<p>rs7213412 </p>

<p>COX10 </p>

<p>intronic </p>

<p>17p12 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>65.99 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>0.048 </p>

<p>0.33 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.29 </p>

<p>rs2147653* </p>

<p>PACRG </p>

<p>intronic </p>

<p>6q26 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>92.64 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>ÀÀÀ </p>

<p>0.0001 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.63 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.81 </p>

<p>rs1408705 </p>

<p>PACRG </p>

<p>intronic </p>

<p>6q26 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>92.70 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>ÀÀÀ </p>

<p>0.0001 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>SNP, single-nucleotide polymorphism; FD, FinnDiane; GoKiND, All-Ireland-Warren 3-Genetics of Kidneys in Diabetes cohort; </p>

<p>COQ5,coenzyme Q5 homologue, methyltransferase (S. </p>

<p>cerevisiae); </p>

<p>COX6A1, cytochrome 
c oxidase subunit VIa polypeptide 1; 
GATC, glutamyl-tRNA(Gln) amidotransferase, subunit C; </p>

<p>TOP1MT, topoisomerase (DNA) I, mitochondrial; </p>

<p>TXNRD2, thioredoxin </p>

<p>reductase 2; 
SPTLC2, serine palmitoyltransferase, long-chain base subunit 2; 
COX10, COX10 heme A:farnesyltransferase cytochrome c oxidase assembly factor; </p>

<p>PACRG, PARK2 co-regulated. </p>

<p>*SNPs that were common to diabetic kidney disease and end-stage renal disease </p>

<p>in silico replication. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Combined meta-analysis for rs1167726 </p>

<p>= 0.0000004; rs7387720 </p>

<p>= 0.000004; rs17745445 </p>

<p>= 0.000002; rs5992495 </p>

<p>= 0.0003; rs176903 
= 0.0008; rs7213412 </p>

<p>= 0.001; rs2147653 </p>

<p>= 0.001. </p>

<p>ª 2015 The Authors. 
Diabetic Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Diabetes UK. </p>



<p>Research article 
DIABETICMedicine </p>

<p>response gene involved in many signalling pathways, includ-
ing WNT which is associated with renal fibrosis in diabetic 
kidney disease. Gene expression of TNXRD2 is differentially 
regulated by epigenetic mechanisms in response to high 
glucose and is a probable target of microRNAs miR335 and 
miR34a [19,20]. 
Complementary to the single-SNP analysis described 
above, interaction analyses have produced novel findings 
for common phenotypes such as cancer [21], heart disease 
[22] and BMI [23], particularly when considered in asso-
ciation with environmental variables whose effects are 
under genetic and epigenetic control such as smoking. It 
is possible that a cumulative effect of common and/or rare 
genetic variants influence diabetic kidney disease, particu-
larly where combined SNPs are located in the same 
biological pathway. More comprehensive analysis of the 
mitochondrial genome and genotyping in a larger popula-
tion, such as the recently funded Juvenile Diabetes Research 
Foundation Genetics of Diabetic Nephropathy Collabora-
tive Research Initiative, are required to robustly consider 
this approach for diabetic kidney disease. SNP-SNP inter-
action analyses for SNPs in the mitochondrial genome, did 
not reveal further associations in the present study. Clusters 
of correlated SNPs were identified at top-ranked genetic 
loci, as shown in the supplementary regional association 
plots (Figures S1-7). 
Our data support the hypothesis that variants in genes 
affecting mitochondrial function are associated with renal 
disease including diabetic kidney disease. The identified SNPs 
are found within nuclear genes implicated in the regulation 
of epigenetic processes. Further research to explore the 
interactions between hyperglycaemia, uraemia and epige-
netic modifications of the genome could shed new light on 
how these nuclear genome SNPs are associated with the 
phenotypes of diabetic kidney disease and end-stage renal 
disease. </p>

<p>Funding sources </p>

<p>E.J.S. is supported by a Diabetes UK PhD studentship (BDA 
10/0004154). The Warren 3/UK GoKinD Study Group was 
jointly funded by Diabetes UK and the Juvenile Diabetes 
Research Foundation and includes: Belfast: A. P. Maxwell, 
A. J. McKnight, D. A. Savage; Edinburgh: J. Walker; 
London: S. Thomas, G. C. Viberti; Manchester: A. J. M. 
Boulton; Newcastle: S. Marshall; Plymouth: A. G. Demaine, 
B. A. Millward; Swansea: S. C. Bain. The FinnDiane genome-
wide association study was supported by grants from the 
Folkh€ alsan Research Foundation, the Wilhelm and Else 
Stockmann Foundation, Liv och H€ alsa Foundation, Helsinki 
University Central Hospital Research Funds (EVO), the 
Sigrid Juselius Foundation, the Signe and Arne Gyllenberg 
Foundation, Finska L€ akares€ allskapet, TEKES, Academy of 
Finland (134379), and the European Union's Seventh 
Framework Program (FP7/2007-2013) for the Innovative </p>

<p>Medicine Initiative under grant agreement IMI/115006 (the 
SUMMIT consortium). The GENIE consortium conducted 
the primary genome-wide association study, which was 
supported by a US Ireland R&amp;D partnership award funded 
by the Science Foundation Ireland under Grant No. SFI/08/ 
US/B1517, the Northern Ireland Research Development 
Office, and NIH NIDDK R01 DK081923. </p>

<p>Competing interests </p>

<p>P.-H.G. has received research grants from Eli Lilly and 
Roche, is an advisory board member for Boehringer-Ingel-
heim, Novartis, Cebix and Abbott. He has also received 
lecture fees from Boehringer-Ingelheim, Eli Lilly, Genzyme, 
Novartis, Novo Nordisk, Sanofi and MSD. </p>





<p>ª 2015 The Authors. 
Diabetic Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Diabetes UK. </p>

<p>DIABETICMedicine 
mtDNA SNPs and diabetic kidney disease E. J. Swan et al. </p>



<p>Supporting Information </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the 
online version of this article: </p>

<p>Table S1. Characteristics of populations participating in the 
discovery and replication analyses. 
Table S2. Association results for diabetic kidney disease and 
SNPs in the mitochondrial genome sorted by minor allele 
frequency. 
Table S3. Discovery and meta-analysis results combined, 
where P ≤ 0.05 for diabetic kidney disease. 
Table S4. HAPLOREG annotations for variants described in 
Table 1. 
Table S5. eQTL data retrieved from Westra et al., Nature 
Genetics 2013, 45: 1238-1243. 
Fig. S1. LocusZoom plot showing the genetic region 
surrounding rs1167726 (signal 1). 
Fig. S2. LocusZoom plot showing the genetic region 
surrounding signal 2. 
Fig. S3. LocusZoom plot showing the genetic region 
surrounding signal 3. 
Fig. S4. LocusZoom plot showing the genetic region 
surrounding signal 4 
Fig. S5. LocusZoom plot showing the genetic region 
surrounding signal 5. 
Fig. S6. LocusZoom plot showing the genetic region 
surrounding signal 6. 
Fig. S7. LocusZoom plot showing the genetic region 
surrounding signal 7. </p>

<p>ª 2015 The Authors. 
Diabetic Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Diabetes UK. </p>



<p>Research article 
DIABETICMedicine </p>

</text></tei>