<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4779866" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Although non-alcoholic fatty liver disease has been reported as a cardiometabolic risk 
factor, the effect of non-alcoholic fatty liver is yet to be clarified on abdominal obesity. 
Therefore, this study was conducted to investigate the longitudinal relationship of non-
alcoholic fatty liver on the development of abdominal obesity. The study participants were 
composed of 11,212 Korean men without abdominal obesity. They were followed up from 
2005 to 2010 to be monitored for the development of abdominal obesity according to 
their degree of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (normal, mild, and moderate to severe). 
Cox-proportional hazard model was used to calculate the hazard ratios for abdominal 
obesity according to the degree of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease. While the average 
incidence was 15.5%, the incidence of abdominal obesity increased according to the 
degree of non-alcoholic fatty liver (normal: 11.6%, mild: 25.2%, moderate to severe: 
41.0%, P &lt; 0.001). Multivariable-adjusted hazard ratios for abdominal obesity 
independently increased proportionally to the degree of NAFLD (mild [1.07; 0.94-1.23], 
moderate to severe [1.58; 1.11-2.26], P for trend &lt; 0.001). The risk of abdominal obesity 
increased proportionally to the degree of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease. This finding 
guarantees further studies to reveal the incidental relationship of abdominal obesity with 
non-alcoholic fatty liver disease. </p>

<p>Obesity is a significant medical issue threatening public health 
not only in Western countries but also in Asian countries. As of 
2008, more than 10% of the world population, about 500 mil-
lion adults, was obese (1), which was expected to explosively 
increase in the future (2). Especially, abdominal obesity has 
more serious clinical implication. It has been reported that ab-
dominal obesity was more significant risk factors for various 
diseases such as diabetes, cardiovascular disease and metabol-
ic syndrome than general obesity (3-5). In addition, medical 
problems related to abdominal obesity are rapidly raising med-
ical cost, which is burdening social financial stability (6). Ac-
cordingly, these situations are increasing the necessity for aca-
demic activity or business to prevent abdominal obesity. 
Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) is the most preva-
lent chronic liver disease characterized as the fatty liver infiltra-
tion and damaged hepatocyte (7,8). Since a lot of researches 
have been actually performed to investigate the association be-
tween NAFLD and abdominal obesity, deep clinical and me-
chanical relationships were revealed between 2 factors. How-
ever, most of studies have mainly focused on the effect of abdo-
minal obesity for NAFLD, and studies for the reverse relation-
ship were very rare. Nonetheless, considering the significant </p>

<p>function of liver in processing biochemical reaction of major 
metabolic factors such as fat, glucose, and insulin, it is worthy 
to research into the effect of NAFLD on the development of ab-
dominal obesity. Thus, we conducted this study to investigate 
the risk of abdominal obesity according to the degree of NAFLD. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study design 
A prospective cohort study was conducted in order to investi-
gate the association between NAFLD and the development of 
abdominal obesity. Study population consisted of Korean men 
undergoing a medical health check-up program annually or bi-
ennially at Total Healthcare Center of Kangbuk Samsung Hos-
pital, Sungkyunkwan University, Seoul, Korea. The background 
and the purpose of medical health check up program was de-
scribed in our previous journal in detail (9). </p>

<p>Study population 
The study participants were the total of 28,425 men who had 
examined the waist circumference (WC) for medical check-up 
in 2005 participated in this study. Among the 28,425 participants, 
12,498 were excluded for various reasons: 1,340 had a positive 
serologic marker for hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg); 53 had </p>

<p>ORIGINAL ARTICLE </p>

<p>Gastroenterology &amp; Hepatology </p>

<p>Park SK, et al. • Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and Obesity </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2016.31.3.410 </p>

<p>a positive serologic marker for hepatitis C virus antibody (HCV-
Ab); 308 had abnormal ultrasonographical findings of chronic 
liver disease, liver cirrhosis, and/or current or past history of 
clonorchiasis; 149 had a past history of a malignancy; 226 had a 
past history of cardiovascular disease; 2,107 were receiving med-
ication for lipid-lowering agents; 4,479 had an alcohol intake of 
≥ 20 g/day; 2,002 had elevated γ-glutamyltransferase (GGT) 
levels ( &gt; 100 U/L); 375 had elevated alanine aminotransferase 
(ALT) levels ( &gt; 100 U/L) and 6,245 were diagnosed as baseline 
abdominal obesity (WC &gt; 90 cm) at initial examinations. The 
total number of eligible participants was 15,927. We further ex-
cluded 4,715 participants who did not attend any follow-up visit 
between 2006 and 2010. Without the follow-up visit, we could 
not identify the development of abdominal obesity and also cal-
culate the individual person year. Eventually, 11,212 participants 
were enrolled in the final analysis and observed for the develop-
ment of obesity (Fig. 1). The total follow-up period was 39,399.1 
person year and average follow-up period was 3.51 (standard 
deviation [SD], 1.53) person year. </p>

<p>Clinical and laboratory measurements 
Study data included a medical history, a physical examination, 
information provided by a questionnaire, anthropometric mea-
surements and laboratory measurements. The medical and drug 
prescription history were assessed by the examining physicians. 
All the participants were asked to respond to a health-related 
behavior questionnaire, which included the topics of alcohol 
consumption, smoking and exercise. The questions about alco-
hol intake included the frequency of alcohol consumption on a 
weekly basis and the typical amount that was consumed on a </p>

<p>daily basis (≥ 20 g/day). In addition, the participants were asked 
about their weekly frequency, amount and duration of exercise 
to evaluate status of their physical activity. Participants taking 
exercise such as jogging, bicycling, and swimming that lasted 
long enough to produce perspiration ( ≥ 1 time/week) were re-
garded as people with regular exercise. 
Anthropometric measurements and procedures for blood 
tests including biochemical analysis, lipid profiles, and immu-
noradiometric assay were described in detail elsewhere (9). 
The diagnosis of chronic liver disease, fatty liver and its de-
gree were based on the results of abdominal US with a 3.5-MHz 
transducer (Logic Q700 MR, GE, Milwaukee, USA). Abdominal 
US were carried out by eleven experienced radiologists who were 
unaware of the aims of the study and blind to the laboratory 
values. 
The criteria of chronic liver disease are as follows (10,11): 
Findings meet one of following criteria. 
1) Coarse or highly non-homogenous liver parenchymal echo-
texture 
2) Irregular or nodular liver surface (inferior margin of right 
lobe) 
3) Blunted or rounded liver edge 
4) Enlarged liver size (&gt; 15 cm in mid-clavicular line) or Shrin-
ken liver size ( &lt; 10 cm in mid-clavicular line) 
5) Enlarged spleen size ( &gt; 13 cm) 
The degree of hepatic fatty infiltration was evaluated by quan-
titative grading system conventionally used in radiologic field 
(12-14) as follows: 
Normal (grade 0): Hepatic parenchymal echogenicity is usu-
ally equal to that of the renal cortex. 
Mild fatty liver (grade 1): diffuse slight increase in fine echoes 
in the hepatic parenchyma with normal visualization of the dia-
phragm and intrahepatic vessel borders. 
Moderate fatty liver (grade 2): moderate diffuse increase in 
fine echoes with slightly impaired visualization of the intrahe-
patic vessels and diaphragm. 
Severe fatty liver (grade 3): marked increase in fine echoes 
with poor or no visualization of the intrahepatic vessel borders, 
diaphragm and posterior portion of the right lobe of the liver. 
The WC was measured in the standing position, at the level 
of umbilicus by a single examiner, and WC &gt; 90 cm was defined 
as abdominal obesity according to the recommendation sug-
gested by joint interim statement of the International Diabetes 
Federation Task Force on Epidemiology and Prevention (15). </p>

<p>Statistical analyses 
Data were expressed as means ± (standard deviation) or medi-
ans (interquartile range) for continuous variables and percent-
ages of the number for categorical variables. 
The one-way ANOVA and χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-test were used to analyze the sta-
tistical differences among the characteristics of the study par-</p>

<p>Fig. 1. Flow chart of enrolled study participants. </p>

<p>Initial participants screened in 2005 (n = 28,425) </p>

<p>Initial cohort in 2005 (n = 15,927) </p>

<p>Final sample size (n = 11,212) </p>

<p>Follow-up loss between 2006 and 2010 (n = 4,715) </p>

<p>Exclusion Criteria in 2005 
(n = 12,498) 
Baseline abdominal obesity 
(n = 6,245) 
Medication for lipid lowering agent 
(n = 2,107) 
Past history of malignancy 
(n = 149) 
Alcohol intake ≥ 20 g/week 
(n = 4,479) 
γ-glutamyltransferase &gt; 100 
(n = 2,022) 
Alanine aminotransferase &gt; 100 
(n = 375) 
HBV + HCVserologic marker positive 
(n = 1,393) 
Chronic liver disease 
(n = 308) 
Past history of cardiovascular disease 
(n = 226) 
Ischemic heart disease 
(n = 112) 
Cerebrovascular disease 
(n = 58) 
Valvular heart disease 
(n = 41) 
Peripheral vascular disease 
(n = 15) </p>

<p>Park SK, et al. • Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and Obesity </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2016.31.3.410 </p>

<p>ticipants at the time of enrollment in relation to the NAFLD cat-
egories. Categories of the NAFLD comprised the following: nor-
mal, mild, moderate and severe. Moderate (N = 133, 1.19%) and 
severe NAFLD (N = 1, 0.01%) was combined into moderate to 
severe NAFLD category for analyses, owing to the small num-
ber of severe NAFLD. The distributions of continuous variables 
were evaluated, and log transformations were used in the anal-
ysis as required. 
For incident abdominal obesity cases, the time of abdominal 
obesity occurrence was assumed to be the midpoint between 
the visit at which abdominal obesity was first diagnosed and 
the baseline visit (2005). The person years were calculated as 
the sum of follow-up times from the baseline until an assumed 
time of abdominal obesity development or until the final ex-
amination of each individual. We used Cox proportional haz-
ards models to estimate adjusted hazard ratios (HRs) and 95% 
confidence intervals (CI) for incident abdominal obesity com-
paring the mild and moderate to severe NAFLD categories vs. 
the normal group. The data were adjusted, first for age alone, 
then for the multiple covariates. In the multivariate models, we 
included variables that might confound the relationship between 
the NAFLD and abdominal obesity, which include: age, base-
line WC, total cholesterol, log(hsCRP), HOMA-IR, eGFR, cur-</p>

<p>rent smoking status, regular exercise, hypertension and diabe-
tes mellitus. The change level of WC was calculated by follow-
ing formula: WC on censoring time -baseline WC. The average 
change of WC was compared among 3 groups (normal, mild 
and moderate to severe NAFLD groups) by one-way ANOVA 
and χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-test. P values &lt; 0.05 were considered to be statistically 
significant. Statistical analyses were performed <rs id="software-0" type="software">PASW Statistics</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>Ethics statement 
Ethics approvals for the study protocol and analysis of the data 
were obtained from the institutional review board of Kangbuk 
Samsung Hospital (KBC12060). The informed consent require-
ment was exempted from the institutional review board because 
the researchers only retrospectively accessed a de-identified da-
tabase for analytical purposes. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>During 39,399.1 person-years of follow-up, 1,740 (15.5%) inci-
dent cases of abdominal obesity developed between 2006 and 
2010. While 11,212 enrolled study participants were comprised 
of 8,160 normal group (72.7%), 2,918 mild fatty liver group (26.0%) </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline characteristics of participants according to the categories of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (n = 11,212) </p>

<p>Characteristics </p>

<p>NAFLD </p>

<p>Overall 
Normal 
(n = 8,160) </p>

<p>Mild 
(n = 2,918) </p>

<p>Moderate to severe 
(n = 134) 
P for trend </p>

<p>Person-yr (total) 
39,399.1 
29,347.4 
9,641.1 
410.6 
Person-yr (average) 
3.51 ± (1.53) 
3.60 ± (1.49) 
3.30 ± (1.62) 
3.06 ± (1.65) 
&lt; 0.001 
Age, yr 
44.3 ± (7.7) 
44.3 ± (7.8) 
44.4 ± (7.4) 
43.3 ± (6.8) 
0.119 
BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>23.5 ± (2.2) 
23.0 ± (2.1) 
24.8 ± (1.8) 
25.8 ± (2.0) 
&lt; 0.001 
WC, cm 
81.1 ± (5.7) 
79.9 ± (5.8) 
84.2 ± (4.1) 
86.3 ± (3.4) 
&lt; 0.001 
Systolic BP, mmHg 
112.3 ± (13.9) 
111.2 ± (13.6) 
115.1 ± (14.2) 
115.4 ± (13.5) 
&lt; 0.001 
Diastolic BP, mmHg 
77.3 ± (9.4) 
76.6 ± (9.2) 
79.6 ± (9.3) 
80.0 ± (9.6) 
&lt; 0.001 
Total cholesterol, mg/dL 
192.1 ± (30.7) 
188.7 ± (30.0) 
201.1 ± (30.7) 
204.6 ± (29.9) 
&lt; 0.001 
Triglyceride, mg/dL 
115 (84-160) 
104 (78-142) 
150 (111-204) 
172 (137-246) 
&lt; 0.001 
HDL-cholesterol, mg/dL 
50.3 ± (10.8) 
52.2 ± (10.6) 
47.2 ± (8.3) 
45.2 ± (7.3) 
&lt; 0.001 
LDL-cholesterol, mg/dL 
113.0 ± (26.1) 
110.2 ± (25.5) 
120.2 ± (26.2) 
122.2 ± (27.6) 
&lt; 0.001 
Fasting serum glucose, mg/dL 
96.9 ± (14.8) 
95.7 ± (13.3) 
100.3 ± (17.8) 
101.4 ± (17.0) 
&lt; 0.001 
HOMA-IR 
1.84 (1.44-2.38) 
1.69 (1.36-2.14) 
2.27 (1.80-2.87) 
2.78 (2.21-3.52) 
&lt; 0.001 
Insulin, uU/dL 
8.3 ± (3.0) 
7.7 ± (2.7) 
9.8 ± (3.2) 
11.8 ± (3.8) 
&lt; 0.001 
SCr, mg/dL 
1.13 ± (0.16) 
1.13 ± (0.18) 
1.14 ± (0.10) 
1.16 ± (0.14) 
0.019 
eGFR, mL/min per 1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>79.4 ± (9.9) 
79.7 ± (9.9) 
78.4 ± (9.8) 
77.6 ± (9.5) 
0.016 
hsCRP, mg/L 
0.05 (0.03-0.10) 
0.04 (0.02-0.08) 
0.07 (0.04-0.13) 
0.11 (0.05-0.20) 
0.013 
AST, U/L 
23 (19-26) 
22 (19-25) 
24 (21-29) 
30 (25-37) 
&lt; 0.001 
ALT, U/L 
23 (18-30) 
21 (16-26) 
30 (23-39) 
46 (35-64) 
&lt; 0.001 
GGT, U/L 
25 (18-38) 
23 (16-34) 
34 (24-47) 
46 (30-62) 
&lt; 0.001 
Current smoker, % 
35.9 
35.2 
37.7 
36.6 
0.024 
Regular exercise, % 
19.6 
20.8 
16.5 
13.7 
&lt; 0.001 
Diabetes mellitus, % 
3.3 
2.1 
6.3 
8.2 
&lt; 0.001 
Hypertension, % 
16.0 
14.0 
21.3 
20.2 
&lt; 0.001 
Development of obesity, % 
15.5 
11.6 
25.2 
41.0 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Data are means (standard deviation), medians (interquartile range), or percentages. BMI, body mass index; WC, waist circumference; BP, blood pressure; HDL, high-density li-
poprotein; LDL, low-density lipoprotein; HOMA-IR, homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance; SCr, serum creatinine; eGFR, estimated glomerular filtration rate; hsCRP, 
high-sensitivity C-reactive protein; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; GGT, γ-glutamyltransferase. </p>

<p>Park SK, et al. • Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and Obesity </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2016.31.3.410 </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of baseline characteristics between participants with and with-
out incident abdominal obesity </p>

<p>Characteristics </p>

<p>Without incident 
abdominal obesity 
(n = 9,472) </p>

<p>With incident 
abdominal obesity 
(n = 1,740) </p>

<p>P value* </p>

<p>Age, yr 
44.1 ± (7.6) 
45.3 ± (7.8) 
&lt; 0.001 
BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>23.1 ± (2.1) 
25.8 ± (1.6) 
&lt; 0.001 
WC, cm 
80.2 ± (5.6) 
86.1 ± (3.2) 
&lt; 0.001 
Systolic BP, mmHg 
111.6 ± (13.9) 116.0 ± (13.2) &lt; 0.001 
Diastolic BP, mmHg 
76.9 ± (9.3) 
80.2 ± (8.9) 
&lt; 0.001 
Total cholesterol, mg/dL 
191.2 ± (30.6) 196.6 ± (30.5) &lt; 0.001 
Triglyceride, mg/dL 
128.4 ± (69.5) 153.0 ± (79.3) &lt; 0.001 
HDL-cholesterol, mg/dL 
51.3 ± (10.4) 
48.1 ± (9.3) 
&lt; 0.001 
LDL-cholesterol, mg/dL 
112.2 ± (25.9) 117.0 ± (26.2) &lt; 0.001 
Fasting serum glucose, mg/dL 
96.6 ± (14.4) 
98.8 ± (16.8) &lt; 0.001 
HOMA-IR 
1.94 ± (0.79) 
2.31 ± (0.91) &lt; 0.001 
Insulin, uU/dL 
8.1 ± (2.9) 
9.5 ± (2.3) 
&lt; 0.001 
SCr, mg/dL 
1.13 ± (0.17) 
1.14 ± (0.11) &lt; 0.001 
eGFR, mL/min per 1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>79.9 ± (9.9) 
77.7 ± (9.6) 
&lt; 0.001 
hsCRP, mg/L 
0.12 ± (0.33) 
0.14 ± (0.38) 
0.105 
AST, U/L 
23.4 ± (6.8) 
24.2 ± (7.7) 
&lt; 0.001 
ALT, U/L 
25.0 ± (12.0) 
29.3 ± (14.6) &lt; 0.001 
GGT, U/L 
29.5 ± (17.5) 
35.9 ± (18.9) &lt; 0.001 
Current smoker, % 
35.4 
38.5 
0.013 
Proper exercise, % 
18.8 
23.9 
&lt; 0.001 
Diabetes mellitus, % 
3.2 
3.7 
0.220 
Hypertension, % 
14.7 
23.1 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Data are expressed as means (standard deviation) or percentages. *P value by t-test 
for continuous variables and χ 
2 test for categorical variables. BMI, body mass index; 
WC, waist circumference; BP, blood pressure; HDL, high-density lipoprotein; LDL, 
low-density lipoprotein; HOMA-IR, homeostasis model assessment of insulin resis-
tance; SCr, serum creatinine; eGFR, estimated glomerular filtration rate; hsCRP, high-
sensitivity C-reactive protein; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; ALT, alanine amino-
transferase; GGT, γ-glutamyltransferase. </p>

<p>Table 3. Hazard ratios and 95% confidence intervals for the incidence of abdominal obesity according to categories of non-alcoholic fatty liver diseases </p>

<p>Obesity variables 
Hazard ratios (95% confidence interval) </p>

<p>Unadjusted 
Age-adjusted 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>NAFLD 
Normal 
Mild 
Moderate to severe 
P for trend </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
2.34 (2.12-2.57) 
4.19 (3.19-5.50) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
2.35 (2.14-2.59) 
4.39 (3.35-5.77) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
1.05 (0.92-1.19) 
1.47 (1.03-2.10) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
1.07 (0.94-1.23) 
1.58 (1.11-2.26) 
&lt; 0.001 
Age 
-
1.02 (1.02-1.03) 
1.02 (1.01-1.02) 
1.02 (1.01-1.02) 
Baseline WC 
-
-
1.29 (1.26-1.31) 
1.29 (1.26-1.31) 
Total cholesterol 
-
-
1.00 (0.99-1.01) 
1.00 (0.99-1.01) 
Log(hsCRP) 
-
-
1.01 (0.95-1.08) 
1.01 (0.94-1.07) 
HOMA-IR 
-
-
1.07 (1.01-1.15) 
1.08 (1.00-1.16) 
eGFR 
-
-
0.99 (0.99-1.00) 
0.99 (0.99-1.00) 
Smoking status 
-
-
-
1.12 (0.98-1.28) 
Regular exercise 
-
-
-
0.69 (0.59-0.80) 
Hypertension 
-
-
-
1.25 (1.08-1.46) 
Diabetes mellitus 
-
-
-
1.22 (0.89-1.67) </p>

<p>Model 1 was adjusted for age, baseline WC, total cholesterol, log(hsCRP), HOMA-IR and eGFR. Model 2 was adjusted for model 1 plus recent smoking status, regular exercise, 
hypertension and diabetes mellitus. NAFLD, non-alcoholic fatty liver disease; WC, waist circumference; hsCRP, high-sensitivity C-reactive protein; HOMA-IR, homeostasis mod-
el assessment of insulin resistance; eGFR, estimated glomerular filtration rate. </p>

<p>and 134 moderate to severe fatty liver group (1.1%), 4,715 exclud-
ed people for follow-up loss were comprised of 3,473 normal 
group (73.7%), 1,194 mild fatty liver group (25.3%) and 48 mod-</p>

<p>erate to severe group (1.01%). 
The baseline characteristics of the study participants in rela-
tion to the NAFLD categories are presented in Table 1. At base-
line, the mean (SD) age and WC of study participants were 44.3 
(7.7) years and 81.1 (5.7) cm, respectively. There were clear dose 
response relationships between all of the listed variables and 
NAFLD categories except for age. 
In contrast to participants without incident abdominal obe-
sity, those with incident abdominal obesity were slightly older 
(45.3 vs. 44.1) and generally had less favorable metabolic pro-
files at baseline (Table 2). 
Table 3 shows the hazard ratios and 95% confidence interval 
for incident abdominal obesity according to the NAFLD catego-
ries. In the unadjusted model, the hazard ratios and 95% confi-
dence interval for incident abdominal obesity comparing mild 
to moderate and severe NAFLD to normal NAFLD were 2.34 
(2.12-2.57) and 4.19 (3.19-5.50), respectively (P for trend &lt; 0.001). 
After adjustments for covariates in model 1 and 2, this associa-
tion was attenuated in mild NAFLD group, but still maintained 
statistically significant (P for trend &lt; 0.001). In Cox proportion-
al hazards models adjusting for age, baseline WC, total choles-
terol, log(hsCRP), HOMA-IR, eGFR, current smoking status, reg-
ular exercise, hypertension and diabetes mellitus (model 2), the 
adjusted hazard ratios and 95% confidence interval for incident 
obesity were 1.07 (0.94-1.23) and 1.58 (1.11-2.26), respectively 
(P for trend &lt; 0.001). Subgroup analysis by age ( &lt; 45 and ≥ 45 
years) also showed the similar trend of association between the 
degree of NAFLD and the incidence of obesity (Supplementary 
Tables 1 and 2). The average and overall change level of WC dur-
ing follow-up was evaluated for all study participants and peo-
ple with incident obesity (Table 4). The average change level of 
WC increased in proportion to the degree of NAFLD in all study </p>

<p>Park SK, et al. • Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and Obesity </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2016.31.3.410 </p>

<p>participants and people with incident obesity. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Up to the present, there have been a lot of studies regarding caus-
ative factors for NAFLD. Out of them, abdominal obesity was 
known to be one of the most significant factors. Nonetheless, 
there was scarce information about the effect of NAFLD on the 
development of abdominal obesity. In this study, incidence and 
risk of abdominal obesity increased proportionally to the degree 
of NAFLD, even after adjusting for multiple covariates. There-
fore, these findings could be the significant clinical background 
for the previous studies demonstrating the higher prevalence of 
adult disease under NAFLD. In short, as NAFLD patients are 
vulnerable to abdominal obesity, risk for diseases related to ab-
dominal obesity may also increase in NAFLD patients. 
Comparing our study findings with those of previous studies, 
we could see an interesting fact. Mean baseline WC of every 
group, even if less than 90 cm, cut-off value of central obesity, 
was in proportion to the degree of NAFLD. Baseline mean value 
of HOMA-IR, indicator of insulin resistance, also increased with 
the same tendency of WC. These findings agree well with the 
previous reports showing metabolic factors associated with the 
development and progression of NAFLD (16-18). In addition, 
mean baseline metabolic factors associated with NAFLD were 
more unfavorable in more progressed NAFLD group. Therefore, 
it was undoubted that various deleterious metabolic conditions 
interactively contributed to the development of NAFLD. None-
theless, to the best of our knowledge, there was no study show-
ing that NAFLD induced by these factors increased the risk for 
abdominal obesity in proportion to the degree of NAFLD. Ac-
cordingly, our study findings imply that NAFLD developed by 
some deleterious conditions can induce abdominal obesity thr-
ough its independent action. 
The mechanism of our study finding is not necessarily matched </p>

<p>up with that of previous studies, because there is no report cor-
responding to ours. However, several theories could be suggest-
ed. One of the most probable theories is elevated insulin level 
associated with insulin resistance. As well known, insulin resis-
tance plays a core role in the development and progression of 
NAFLD, and hyperinsulinemia is a definite clinical manifesta-
tion of insulin resistance. Previous studies showed that elevated 
insulin level could cause obesity. Johnson et al reported that 
hyperinsulinemia drove a diet-induced obesity independently 
of brain insulin production (19), and clinical studies showed 
that long term insulin therapy could induce weight gain (20,21). 
Our study also showed that baseline insulin levels were elevat-
ed in proportion to the severity of NAFLD. Accordingly, hyper-
insulinemia associated with insulin resistance might play a sig-
nificant role in the development of obesity. 
When interpreting our results, some limitations should be 
considered. First, bias from follow-up loss may have affected 
our results. Participants not included in analysis (n = 4,715) were 
older and had less favorable metabolic profiles at baseline than 
those in analytic cohort. Thus, this follow-up loss of high-risk 
people would probably lead to a conservative bias and subse-
quent underestimation of risk. 
Second is the methodological limitation for the diagnosing 
NAFLD. In this study, the presence of NAFLD was assessed by 
US instead of pathologic method. Although US is regarded rea-
sonable and accurate in detecting NAFLD, it cannot identify fat-
ty infiltration of the liver below the threshold of 30% (22). There-
fore, there might have been possibility of discrepancy between 
ultrasonographic finding and real NAFLD. Nonetheless, it was 
inappropriate to perform invasive test in a population based 
epidemiological study (23). Additionally, US is a widely used 
and acceptable modality for diagnosis of NAFLD with high sen-
sitivity (82%-94%) and specificity (66%-95%) (24-26). Particu-
larly, all examinations were carried out by experienced radiolo-
gists using widely established methods and criteria. Thus, de-</p>

<p>Table 4-1. Average change level of waist circumference (WC) in all study participants and people with incident obesity </p>

<p>Characteristic (all study participants) </p>

<p>NAFLD (11,212 all study participants) </p>

<p>Overall 
(n = 11,212) </p>

<p>Normal 
(n = 8,160) </p>

<p>Mild 
(n = 2,918) </p>

<p>Moderate to severe 
(N = 134) 
P for trend </p>

<p>Average change of WC, cm 
3.08 ( ± 2.13) 
3.04 ( ± 1.97) 
3.18 ( ± 2.07) 
3.46 ( ± 2.16) 
&lt; 0.001 
Range of WC change, cm 
-8.6 -+11.4 
-8.6 -+9.6 
-6.9 -+9.3 
-7.4 -+11.4 </p>

<p>WC (waist circumference) change was calculated by as follows: WC on censoring time -baseline WC. NAFLD, non-alcoholic fatty liver disease. </p>

<p>Table 4-2. Average change level of waist circumference (WC) in people with incident obesity </p>

<p>Characteristic (people with incident obesity) </p>

<p>NAFLD (1,740 people with incident obesity) </p>

<p>Overall 
(N = 1,740) </p>

<p>Normal 
(N = 947) </p>

<p>Mild 
(N = 737) </p>

<p>Moderate to severe 
(N = 56) 
P for trend </p>

<p>Average change of WC, cm 
6.13 ( ± 3.04) 
6.03 ( ± 2.99) 
6.22 ( ± 3.15) 
6.71 ( ± 3.11) 
&lt; 0.001 
Range of WC change, cm 
+3.8 -+ 12.8 
+4.2 -+ 11.5 
+4.1 -+ 12.8 
+3.8 -+ 12.3 </p>

<p>WC (waist circumference) change was calculated by as follows: WC on censoring time -baseline WC. NAFLD, non-alcoholic fatty liver disease. </p>

<p>Park SK, et al. • Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and Obesity </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2016.31.3.410 </p>

<p>spite this limitation, US might be clinically reasonable and prop-
er modality to diagnose NAFLD in this study. 
In conclusion, our study indicated that the risk of abdominal 
obesity independently increased according to the degree of NA-
FLD. These findings suggest the clinical significance of NAFLD 
as an early predictor for abdominal obesity. Therefore, further 
studies should be conducted to clarify the more correct relation-
ship between NAFLD and abdominal obesity. </p>

<p>DISCLOSURE </p>

<p>The authors have no potential conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTION </p>

<p>Conception and coordination of the study: Choi JM. Design of 
ethical issues: Choi JM. Acquisition of data: Park SK. Data re-
view: Park SK, Choi JM. Statistical analysis: Park SK, Ryoo JH. 
Manuscript preparation: Park SK, Choi JM, Seo MW, Park CM. 
Manuscript approval: all authors. </p>

<p>ORCID </p>

<p>Sung Keun Park http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4703-9917 
Jae-Hong Ryoo http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5232-1426 
Joong-Myung Choi http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3610-6662 
Min Woo Seo http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6574-8453 
Chung Min Park http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0604-4672 </p>



<p>Park SK, et al. • Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and Obesity </p>





<p>Park SK, et al. • Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and Obesity </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2016.31.3.410 </p>

<p>Supplementary Table 1. Hazard ratios and 95% confidence intervals for the incidence of abdominal obesity according to categories of non-alcoholic fatty liver diseases in 
people with age &lt; 45 yr (n = 6,158) </p>

<p>Hazard ratios (95% confidence interval) </p>

<p>Unadjusted 
Age-adjusted 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>NAFLD 
Normal 
Mild 
Moderate to severe 
P for trend </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
2.23 (1.94-2.56) 
3.63 (2.46-5.35) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
2.22 (1.94-2.55) 
3.63 (2.46-5.35) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
0.99 (0.82-1.19) 
1.16 (0.70-1.91) 
0.087 </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
1.05 (0.86-1.27) 
1.28 (0.77-2.11) 
0.035 
Age 
-
1.01 (0.99-1.03) 
0.98 (0.96-1.01) 
0.98 (0.96-1.01) 
Baseline WC 
-
-
1.30 (1.27-1.34) 
1.31 (1.27-1.34) 
Total cholesterol 
-
-
1.00 (1.00-1.01) 
1.00 (1.00-1.01) 
Log(hsCRP) 
-
-
1.04 (0.95-1.13) 
1.03 (0.94-1.12) 
HOMA-IR 
-
-
1.02 (0.93-1.13) 
1.05 (0.94-1.16) 
eGFR 
-
-
0.99 (0.98-1.00) 
0.99 (0.98-1.00) 
Smoking status 
-
-
-
1.05 (0.88-1.26) 
Regular exercise 
-
-
-
0.57 (0.45-0.72) 
Hypertension 
-
-
-
1.09 (0.85-1.40) 
Diabetes mellitus 
-
-
-
1.83 (0.88-3.78) </p>

<p>Model 1 was adjusted for age, baseline WC, total cholesterol, log(hsCRP), HOMA-IR and eGFR. Model 2 was adjusted for model 1 plus recent smoking status, regular exercise, 
hypertension and diabetes mellitus. NAFLD, non alcoholic fatty liver disease; WC, waist circumference; hsCRP, high-sensitivity C-reactive protein; HOMA-IR, homeostasis model 
assessment of insulin resistance; eGFR, estimated glomerular filtration rate. </p>

<p>Park SK, et al. • Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease and Obesity </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>Supplementary Table 2. Hazard ratios and 95% confidence intervals for the incidence of abdominal obesity according to categories of non-alcoholic fatty liver diseases in 
people with age ≥ 45 yr (n = 5,054) </p>

<p>Hazard ratios (95% confidence interval) </p>

<p>Unadjusted 
Age-adjusted 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>NAFLD 
Normal 
Mild 
Moderate to severe 
P for trend </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
2.44 (2.13-2.79) 
5.14 (3.51-7.53) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
2.46 (2.15-2.81) 
5.32 (3.63-7.79) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
1.08 (0.89-1.31) 
1.80 (1.08-3.00) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>1.00 (reference) 
1.09 (0.90-1.33) 
1.95 (1.16-3.26) 
&lt; 0.001 
Age 
-
1.02 (1.01-1.03) 
1.01 (1.00-1.03) 
1.01 (1.00-1.02) 
Baseline WC 
-
-
1.27 (1.24-1.31) 
1.27 (1.23-1.30) 
Total cholesterol 
-
-
1.00 (0.99-1.00) 
1.00 (0.99-1.00) 
Log(hsCRP) 
-
-
1.00 (0.91-1.09) 
0.98 (0.89-1.08) 
HOMA-IR 
-
-
1.13 (1.02-1.25) 
1.12 (1.01-1.25) 
eGFR 
-
-
1.00 (0.98-1.01) 
1.00 (0.99-1.01) 
Smoking status 
-
-
-
1.22 (1.00-1.47) 
Regular exercise 
-
-
-
0.78 (0.63-0.95) 
Hypertension 
-
-
-
1.36 (1.12-1.66) 
Diabetes mellitus 
-
-
-
1.11 (0.78-1.59) </p>

<p>Model 1 was adjusted for age, baseline WC, total cholesterol, log(hsCRP), HOMA-IR and eGFR. Model 2 was adjusted for model 1 plus recent smoking status, regular exercise, 
hypertension and diabetes mellitus. NAFLD, non alcoholic fatty liver disease; WC, waist circumference; hsCRP, high-sensitivity C-reactive protein; HOMA-IR, homeostasis model 
assessment of insulin resistance; eGFR, estimated glomerular filtration rate. </p>

</text></tei>