<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4584013" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Aristolochic acids (AAs) are the active components of herbal drugs derived from Aristolochia species that have 
been used for medicinal purposes since antiquity. However, AAs have recently been discovered to be highly 
nephrotoxic and induced urothelial cancer in humans and malignant tumors in the kidney and urinary tract of 
rodents. In this study, we exposed rat renal proximal tubule cells in vitro to a sub-cytotoxic level of AAs at 
three different time points (6 h, 24 h and 72 h). We then analyzed the gene expression profile after the compound 
exposure. Functional analysis with Ingenuity Pathways Analysis and DAVID tools revealed that at the late time 
point (72 h) there are many significantly altered genes involved in cancer-related pathways such as p53 
signaling. 
MIAMI-compliant microarray data are deposited in the NCBI GEO database under accession number GSE68687 
and can be found at: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE68687. 
Genomics Data </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : h t t p : / / w w w . j o u r n a l s . e l s e v i e r . c o m / g e n o m i c s -d a t a / </p>

<p>AA-DNA adducts. Rats treated with AAs develop mutations in p53 gene 
and the presence of AA-DNA adducts in renal cortex and p53 mutations 
in tumor tissue were reported in patients with endemic nephropathy 
[12]. </p>

<p>3. Materials and methods </p>

<p>3.1. Materials </p>

<p>A mixture of AAI and AAII was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich, UK. 
TRIzol reagent and GlutaMAX were obtained from (Invitrogen, UK) 
and RNeasy Total RNA Mini Kit and RNA later from (Qiagen, UK). </p>

<p>3.2. Cell culture </p>

<p>NRK-52E cells (ATCC, CRL-1571) were cultured in Dulbecco's 
Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM) with 10% fetal calf serum, penicillin 
100 IU ml </p>

<p>−1   , and streptomycin solution 100 μg ml 
−1 in a humidified </p>

<p>5% CO 2 incubator at 37°C. </p>

<p>3.3. Cytotoxicity-determination of IC 10 </p>

<p>A dose-response curve for AAs was determined using the MTT assay 
[13]. Cells were exposed for 72 h in 96-well plates to a wide range of 
concentrations of AAs dissolved in DMSO and diluted to give a final con-
centration of 0.1% v/v DMSO. Control cells were exposed to DMSO alone 
(0.1% v/v). At least three separate experiments were conducted. The 
dose that caused approximately 10% cytotoxicity (IC 10 ) at 72 h was se-
lected for the transcriptomics studies. </p>

<p>3.4. Cell treatment </p>

<p>NRK-52E cells were cultured to confluence on 6-well plates. For 
transcriptomics studies, cells were exposed to AAs dissolved in DMSO 
(0.1% v/v) at the IC 10 concentration at 72 h (1.65 μM) or DMSO 
(0.1% v/v) alone. After 6 h, 24 h and 72 h the medium was removed 
and RNA was extracted from cells. For replication, three studies were 
conducted at each time point. </p>

<p>3.5. RNA isolation and microarray </p>

<p>From in vitro studies total RNA was isolated from DMSO (control) 
and AA-treated cells. TRIzol reagent was used for RNA isolation. Total 
RNA was purified using the RNeasy Total RNA Mini Kit (Qiagen) accord-
ing to the manufacturer's instructions. RNA was checked for purity and 
integrity using Agilent 2001 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies GmbH, 
Germany) before processing. Transcriptomics data was generated 
using GeneChip Rat Genome 230 2.0 The rat array provides comprehen-
sive coverage of the transcribed rat genome and comprised of more 
than 31,000 probe sets, analyzing over 30,000 transcripts and variants 
from over 28,000 well-substantiated rat genes. </p>

<p>3.6. Microarray hybridization </p>

<p>3.6.1. Target preparation 
cDNA was prepared using the Affymetrix IVT express kit (Affymetrix, 
Santa Clara). cDNA synthesis and labeling were performed according to 
the manufacturer's procedures. Subsequent labeling of the samples was 
conducted by synthesis of Biotin-labeled complementary RNA (cRNA) 
using the GeneChip IVT labeling kit (Affymetrix). Purified cRNA was 
quantified using a spectrophotometer, and unfragmented samples 
were checked on the Bioanalyzer. Subsequently, cRNA samples were 
fragmented for target preparation according to the Affymetrix manual 
and checked on the Bioanalyzer. Samples were stored at −20°C until 
ready to perform hybridization. </p>

<p>3.6.2. Hybridization 
cRNA targets were hybridized on high-density oligonucleotide gene 
chips (Affymetrix Human Genome U133 Plus 2.0 and GeneChip Rat 
Genome 230 2.0 Arrays) according to the Affymetrix Eukaryotic Target 
Hybridization manual. The gene chips were washed and stained using 
the Affymetrix Fluidics Station 450 and <rs type="software">Genechip Operating Software</rs> 
and scanned by means of an Affymetrix GeneArray scanner. </p>

<p>3.6.3. Microarray analysis 
The intensity values of different genes (probe sets) generated by 
Affymetrix GeneChip Operating Software were imported into GeneSpring </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Chemical structure of aristolochic acid I and II. </p>

<p>Table 1 
KEGG pathways enriched after 72 h exposure to AAs. </p>

<p>KEGG pathway 
No. of genes 
involved in 
pathway </p>

<p>Total no. of genes 
involved in the 
pathway (%) </p>

<p>P-value 
(Benjamini) </p>

<p>p53 signaling pathway 
16 
1.9 
8.5E−8 (1.3E−5) 
Pathways in cancer 
30 
3.6 
8.6E−5 (6.4E−3) </p>

<p>Table 2 
Ingenuity pathways enriched after 72 h exposure to AAs. </p>

<p>Ingenuity canonical pathway 
No. of genes involved 
in the pathway </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>p53 signaling 
17/98 
9.65E−08 
Glutathione biosynthesis 
3/3 
4.96E−05 
ATM signaling 
10/59 
5.20E−05 
Cell cycle: G2/M DNA damage 
checkpoint regulation </p>

<p>9/49 
6.44E−05 </p>

<p>Molecular mechanisms of cancer 
8/99 
6.74E−05 </p>

<p> 
K.M. Bloch et al. / Genomics Data 5 (2015) 254-256 </p>

<p>version 11 software (Agilent) for data analysis. The raw data files (CEL 
files) containing signal values for individual probes were pre-processed 
to generate one value per probeset. Pre-processing of arrays was done 
using GC-RMA (Robust Multiarray Analysis algorithm). To identify the 
differentially expressed (DE) probe sets, two sampled t-test (unpaired 
t-test) with a P-value b 0.05 and Benjamini-Hochberg correction for 
multiple testing correction and a fold cut off of 2 was used. Comparisons 
were made between control DMSO-exposed and AA-exposed cells. 
Three studies were conducted at each time point. </p>

<p>3.6.4. Functional annotation 
To understand the biological meaning behind the list of DE genes, 
Kyoto Encyclopaedia of Genes and Genomes database (KEGG) pathways 
analysis and Gene Ontology (GO) from DAVID website (The Database 
for Annotation, Visualization and Integrated Discovery) v 6.7 (http:// 
david.abcc.ncifcrf.gov/) were used. Only GO and pathways with P-
value b 0.05 (Benjamin-Hochberg corrected) and with 5 or more 
genes were analyzed and discussed. In addition, <rs type="software">Ingenuity Pathway Analysis</rs> (IPA) was used. Only pathways and functions with P b 0.05 
(Fisher's exact test right-tailed) were analyzed and discussed. </p>

<p>3.6.5. Data deposition 
MIAMI-compliant microarray data were deposited in the NCBI GEO 
database under accession number GSE68687; http://www.ncbi.nlm. 
nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE68687. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>4.1. Gene expression profile induced after aristolochic acids exposure </p>

<p>No genes were differentially expressed after 6 h and 24 h exposure 
to AAs, however at 72 h, 1204 genes were found to be differentially 
expressed. Both IPA and KEGG pathways identify p53 signaling as a 
top statistically significantly enriched pathway (Tables 1 and 2). Addi-
tionally after 72 h exposure genes involved in apoptosis, stress </p>

<p>response, DNA damage and glutathione biosynthesis were identify 
(Tables 2 and 3). </p>

<p>5. Conclusion </p>

<p>Our results suggest that microarray analysis is a useful tool for de-
tecting AA exposure in vitro and the gene expression analysis can iden-
tify the responses to toxicity and carcinogenicity of AAs in rat renal 
proximal tubule cells. In addition, the significantly altered genes were 
identify to be associated with cancer pathways and specifically p53 sig-
naling, DNA damage responses and apoptosis. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This study was funded primarily by the 6th EU Framework project 
(LSHB-CT-2006-037712) carcinoGENOMICS. </p>



<p>Table 3 
GO enriched after 72 h exposure to AAs. </p>

<p>GO 
No. of genes involved 
in pathway </p>

<p>Total no. of genes involved 
in the pathway (%) </p>

<p>P-value (Benjamini) </p>

<p>Regulation of apoptosis 
61 
7.4 
1.80E−08 (5.10E−05) 
Release of cytochrome c from mitochondria 
8 
1 
1.40E−05 (3.70E−03) 
Regulation of cell proliferation 
51 
6.2 
3.30E−05 (7.60E−03) 
Apoptotic mitochondrial changes 
8 
1 
1.50E−04 (2.40E−02) 
Blood vessel morphogenesis 
20 
2.4 
2.70E−04 (4.20E−02) 
Tissue remodeling 
11 
1.3 
2.80E−04 (4.10E−02) 
Response to abiotic stimulus 
33 
4 
2.90E−04 (4.00E−02) 
Cellular response to stress 
35 
4.2 
3.20E−04 (4.00E−02) 
DNA damage response, signal transduction resulting in induction of apoptosis 
7 
0.8 
3.60E−04 (4.30E−02) 
Regulation of cell adhesion 
15 
1.8 
4.50E−04 (4.60E−02) 
Response to DNA damage stimulus 
24 
2.9 
4.80E−04 (4.70E−02) </p>

<p> 
K.M. Bloch et al. / Genomics Data 5 (2015) 254-256 </p>

</text></tei>