<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4913653" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>M </p>

<p>yxomatous mitral valve disease (MMVD) often 
causes cardiac-related death in dogs &lt;10 years of 
age. 
1 The disease results in valvular extracellular matrix 
changes including deposition of mucopolysaccarides 
and collagen degeneration. 
2 The valvular changes may 
cause mitral valve prolapse (MVP) and insufficient clo-
sure of the mitral valve leading to mitral regurgitation. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Mitral regurgitation murmur intensity and echocardio-
graphic MVP are predictors of MMVD progression in 
dogs. 
3-5 The disease is most common in small and med-
ium-sized dog breeds, but often is a relatively benign 
condition because of its slow disease progression. 
5,6 A 
higher prevalence and earlier onset of the disease have 
been reported in Cavalier King Charles Spaniels 
(CKCS) compared to other dog breeds. 
1,3,7 A study 
from Sweden based on animal insurance data from 
1995 to 2006 shows that the disease accounts for 37% 
of the total mortality among CKCS &lt;10 years of age. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Hereditary background of MMVD has long been 
suggested on the basis of a higher prevalence of the dis-
ease in certain dog breeds, 
2 and more recent studies 
indicate strong genetic background with polygenic 
inheritance. 
8,9 In CKCS, a positive association between 
parental heart status and mitral regurgitation murmur </p>

<p>From the Department of Veterinary Disease Biology (Olsen, 
Birkeg ard, Reimann) and the Department of Biostatistics 
(Martinussen), Faculty of Health and Medical Sciences, University 
of Copenhagen, Frederiksberg, Denmark; the Department of 
Clinical Sciences, Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences, 
Uppsala, Sweden (H€ aggstr€ om); and the Novo Nordisk A/S, 
Maaloev,Denmark (Pedersen). 
The work was performed at Departments of Veterinary Disease 
Biology and Veterinary Clinical and Animal Sciences, Faculty of 
Health and Medical Sciences, University of Copenhagen; Aalborg 
Animal Hospital, Aalborg; Aarslev Animal Hospital, Aarslev; 
Bygholm Animal Hospital, Horsens; Rødding and Trekantens 
Animal Hospital, Rødding; and Varde Animal Hospital, Varde, 
Denmark. 
Preliminary results from this study were presented at the American 
College of Veterinary Internal Medicine (ACVIM) Forum in 
Seattle, Washington, USA, June 2013. The study was supported by 
The Cavalier King Charles Spaniel Club in Denmark and the Danish 
Kennel Club Association and by a grant from the Danish National 
Research Council (Project no. 271-08-0998). 
Shared senior authorship: Discussed and agreed on all major 
issues throughout the study; with HDP being the main driving force 
before -and LHO after -November 2004. 
Corresponding author: L.H. Olsen, Department of Veterinary 
Disease Biology, Faculty of Health and Medical Sciences, University 
of Copenhagen, 9 Ridebanevej, 1870 Frederiksberg C, Denmark; 
e-mail: lisbeth.hoier@sund.ku.dk. </p>

<p>Submitted April 27, 2015; Revised August 18, 2015; Accepted 
October 8, 2015. </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 The Authors. Journal of Veterinary Internal 
Medicine published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of the Ameri-
can College of Veterinary Internal Medicine. 
This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License, which permits use, 
distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original 
work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes. 
DOI: 10.1111/jvim.13663 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: </p>

<p>CKCS 
Cavalier King Charles Spaniels 
DKCA 
Danish Kennel Club Association 
MMVD 
myxomatous mitral valve disease 
MVP 
mitral valve prolapse 
non-PB 
non-products of the breeding scheme 
PB 
products of the breeding scheme </p>

<p>J Vet Intern Med 2016;30:63-68 </p>

<p>intensity in 5 year-old offspring has been reported. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Furthermore, in Dachshunds, a positive association has 
been found between the degree of MVP in parents and 
offspring. 
9 Based on data from the United Kingdom, a 
high heritability for MMVD in CKCS has been esti-
mated. 
10 The heritability for having a mitral regurgita-
tion murmur and for the grade of murmur intensity was 
estimated to 0.33 and 0.67, respectively. 
10 Furthermore, 
a recent genome-wide association study found 2 gene 
loci on chromosomes 13 and 14 that differ between 
CKCS with early and late onset of MMVD. 
11 However, 
another similar genome-wide association study includ-
ing a lower number of CKCS did not find any associa-
tion between gene loci and MMVD disease severity. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Additional studies are needed to further elucidate asso-
ciations between gene changes and MMVD disease 
severity. 
Breeding restrictions or recommendations aimed at 
decreasing the prevalence of MMVD in CKCS have 
been developed in breeding clubs in different countries. 
The high heritability of the disease indicates that selec-
tion against the disease could be successful. 
10 From 
2001, a breeding scheme has been ongoing in Denmark 
as a collaboration between the Danish Kennel Club 
Association (DKCA), The Cavalier Club in Denmark 
and the University of Copenhagen. The aim of this-
study was to evaluate if a mandatory breeding scheme 
based on echocardiography and cardiac auscultation 
results in decreased MMVD severity in CKCS after an 
8-to 10-year time period. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Study Design </p>

<p>A retrospective study of the mandatory cardiac examinations 
in the DKCA breeding scheme was performed. Inclusion criteria 
for the statistical analyses were that the cardiac examinations 
were performed in the period 2002-2011 (both years included), 
all data from the individual examination were available, and that 
the dogs were registered in DKCA. Dogs had to be at least 
1.5 years at the first examination and registered in the DKCA 
with a verified CKCS pedigree. Pregnant and lactating dogs were 
excluded. </p>

<p>Cardiac Examination and Observers </p>

<p>Cardiac auscultation was performed and the degree of mitral 
regurgitation murmur was graded from 1 to 6. 
13 The echocardio-
graphic degree of MVP was evaluated with the dog placed in right 
lateral recumbency using a right parastenal long axis 4-chamber 
echocardiographic view with focus on the mitral valve. </p>

<p>14,15 </p>

<p>Echocardiographic recordings were stored on video tape or digi-
tally on DVD. Auscultation and echocardiography were performed 
by 1 of 8 veterinarians (clinical observers; Table 1). Five clinical 
observers were general practitioners with cardiovascular interest 
selected by University of Copenhagen, trained at least 2 days in 
cardiac auscultation and MVP echocardiography and approved by 
the founder of the breeding scheme (HDP) in 2001 at University 
of Copenhagen. Two cardiovascular researchers (LHO and JK) 
with at least 8 years small animal cardiovascular clinical research 
experience were included as clinical observers in 2004 and 2009, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Echocardiographic Assessment of MVP </p>

<p>The degree of MVP was evaluated by LHO or HDP (MVP 
observers). The degree of MVP was assessed as 0 (≤1.5 mm as the 
sum of the maximum protrusion of the cranial, caudal and coap-
tion point of the mitral valve according to annulus plane), 1 (&gt;1.5 
and ≤4.5 mm), 2 (&gt;4.5 and ≤7.5 mm), and 3 (&gt;7.5 mm). 
14-16 One 
of the MVP observers (HDP) evaluated the MVP echocardiograms 
from the debut of the breeding scheme until November 2004, here-
after the recordings were evaluated by the other MVP observer 
(LHO). The MVP observers made the final approval for the 
DKCA report (see below). </p>

<p>Breeding Guidelines and Cardiac Health Criteria </p>

<p>Dogs examined ≥1½ years of age were approved for breeding 
until 4 years of age if cardiac health criteria were fulfilled. To con-
tinue breeding in DKCS after 4 years of age dogs had to be reex-
amined. From January 2007, an additional restriction was decided 
introducing an additional reexamination after 6 years of age for 
male dogs. At all examination time points, dogs were excluded 
from breeding if they had MVP grade 3 (first a criterion from 
2007) or a mitral regurgitation murmur grade ≥3. Dogs with grade 
2 murmurs were excluded if they had MVP grades 2 or 3. Thus, 
cardiac health criteria for breeding in the MMVD breeding scheme 
of the DKCA were as follows: Mitral regurgitation murmur of 1 
at a maximum combined with a MVP grade 2 at a maximum; or a 
grade 2 murmur combined with a degree of MVP not &gt;1. Before 
2007, dogs with a grade 3 MVP were approved if they had a mur-
mur grade not &gt;1. Ejection murmurs (physiological flow murmurs) 
were accepted. They were diagnosed as systolic murmurs with 
crescendo-decresendo sound configuration, point of maximal 
intensity at the left heart base and with minimal or no concurrent 
mitral regurgitation estimated using color flow Doppler echocar-
diography. 
17 These dogs often have aortic flow maximum velocity 
on the higher side of the normal reference range (&gt;1.5 m/s). 
18 This 
observation was used to confirm the diagnosis. Dogs with heart 
murmurs caused by non-MMVD cardiac disease were excluded. 
Mitral regurgitation murmur intensity and MVP status of all 
examined dogs became freely available from DKCA homepage 
after examination. Each parent needed to fulfill the cardiac health 
criteria for registration of their puppies in DKCA. </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>All statistical calculations were conducted with a statistical soft-
ware program (<rs type="software">SAS</rs>) 
a and a statistical significance level of 5% was 
used. 
Logistic regression analysis taking clustering caused by multiple 
measurements per clinical observer into account was performed 
using proc genmod in the <rs type="software">SAS</rs> system. Dogs examined in the years 
of 2002, 2003, 2010, and 2011 were divided into 3 groups. Group 
1 was defined as all dogs examined in 2002 and 2003. Dogs in 
group 2 were examined in 2010 and 2011, and in addition, were a 
product of the breeding scheme (PB). Group 3 consisted of dogs 
also examined in 2010 and 2011 but not a product of the breeding 
scheme (non-PB). Products of the breeding scheme were defined as 
dogs with both parents approved by the DKCA breeding scheme. 
Only the most recent examination was included in the statistical 
analyses if a dog had repeated examinations within the time per-
iod. The presence of mitral regurgitation murmur (yes/no) or 
degree of MVP &gt; 1 (yes/no) were included as response variables 
and age at examination, group (1, 2 or 3) and sex (male or female) 
were included as explanatory variables. Backward stepwise elimi-
nation was performed until only explanatory variables showing 
significance were left in the model. If an overall significance of </p>

<p> 
Birkeg ard et al </p>

<p>group was found, the risk of having a mitral regurgitation murmur 
or MVP &gt; 1 was compared between group 1 (all dogs examined in 
2002 and 2003) and group 2 (PB examined in 2010 and 2011), 
group 1 and group 3 (non-PB examined in 2010 and 2011), and 
finally group 2 and 3, to evaluate a potential effect of the MMVD 
breeding scheme. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>A total of 1,471 cardiac examinations were performed 
from the debut of the DKCA breeding scheme in 
December 2001 until the end of 2011. Ninety-one car-
diac examinations were excluded from the statistical 
analyses according to predefined criteria (Fig 1). A total 
of 1,380 cardiac examinations were included from 2002 
to 2011 (Tables 1 and 2). In the period, 997 dogs were 
evaluated (689 females and 308 males). Dogs of both 
sexes were evaluated 1-4 times with an average of 1.4 </p>

<p>Table 1. Number of dogs examined by 8 different clinical observers from 2002 to 2011 in the Danish Kennel Club 
Association (DKCA) myxomatous mitral valve disease (MMVD) breeding scheme. </p>

<p>Clinical 
observer 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 </p>

<p>Total 
Exams </p>

<p>Number of 
Excluded Dogs </p>

<p>% Excluded 
Dogs </p>

<p>2002 
64 
0 
0 
8 
19 
29 
12 
1 
133 
11 
8.3 
2003 
57 
1 
0 
6 
6 
1 7 
1 0 
2 
9 9 
5 
5 . 1 
2004 
34 
18 
0 
7 
2 
2 4 
9 
1 
9 5 
3 
3 . 2 
2005 
0 
79 
0 
10 
4 
16 
7 
2 
118 
4 
3.4 
2006 
1 
79 
0 
10 
1 
24 
5 
2 
122 
6 
4.9 
2007 
0 
91 
0 
6 
6 
3 1 
1 5 
5 
1 5 4 
1 7 
11.0 
2008 
0 
124 
0 
8 
7 
2 1 
7 
3 
1 7 0 
1 0 
5 . 9 
2009 
0 
117 
2 
7 
4 
1 5 
6 
8 
1 5 9 
5 
3 . 1 
2010 
0 
131 
1 
2 
3 
8 
11 
7 
163 
8 
4.9 
2011 
0 
123 
3 
9 
5 
1 6 
8 
3 
1 6 7 
9 
5 . 4 
Total 
156 
763 
6 
73 
57 
201 
90 
34 
1,380 
78 
5.7 </p>

<p>Table 2. Characteristics of the dogs examined from 
2002 to 2011 in the Danish Kennel Club Association 
(DKCA) myxomatous mitral valve disease (MMVD) 
breeding scheme included in the statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Group 1 
2002-2003 </p>

<p>Group 2 (PB) 
2010-2011 </p>

<p>Group 3 
(Non-PB) 
2010-2011 </p>

<p>n 
215 
172 
153 
Age (years) 
2.5 (1.8-4.4) 
2.0 (1.7-4.1) 
2.3 (1.6-4.4) 
Sex (m/f) 
63/152 
54/118 
63/90 </p>

<p>Only the most recent examination was included in the statistical 
analyses if dogs had repeated examinations. Group 1 is dogs 
examined in 2002 and 2003. Group 2 and 3 are dogs examined in 
2010 and 2011 that are products of the breeding scheme (PB) and 
nonproducts of the breeding scheme (non-PB), respectively. f, 
female; m, male. Except for sex, data are shown as median and 25 
and 75% interquartile intervals. </p>

<p>Fig 1. Flowchart for the study. </p>

<p>Mitral Valve Disease Breeding Scheme </p>

<p>
evaluations per dog. Presence of heart murmur could 
not be evaluated satisfactorily in 5 dogs and therefore 
their results regarding murmur were removed from the 
statistical analyses. Among the 1,380 cardiac examina-
tions, 137 mitral regurgitation murmurs (10%), 83 inno-
cent flow murmurs (6%) and 84 MVP grade 3 (6%) 
were found. In total, 78 dogs (5.7%; 39 males and 39 
females) were excluded from breeding (31 males and 18 
females from 2007 to 2011). Among dogs with repeated 
examinations (n = 343 [306 dogs twice, 34 dogs 3 times 
and 3 dogs 4 times]), 6 dogs (2%) had decreased degree 
of mitral regurgitation murmur of 1 grade and 11 dogs 
(3%) had decreased MVP of 1 grade over time. </p>

<p>Reduction in Risk of Having a Mitral Regurgitation 
Murmur </p>

<p>Group and age statistically significantly influenced 
the presence of mitral regurgitation murmur (Table 3). 
The odds of having mitral regurgitation murmur in 
2010-2011 compared to 2002-2003 were 0.27 if the dogs 
in 2010-2011 were PB, reflecting a 73% decreased risk 
(P &lt; .0001; Table 3 and Fig 2). Similarly, within 2010-
2011, the odds of having mitral regurgitation murmur 
for dogs that was PB was 0.31 compared to non-PB, 
reflecting 69% decreased risk (P &lt; .0001). If non-PB 
examined in 2010-2011 were compared with dogs exam-
ined in 2002-2003, no statistical difference in odds of 
having mitral regurgitation murmur was found 
(P = .4873). There was no significant influence of sex 
on odds of murmur. Odds of having a murmur were 
higher with advancing age (P &lt; .0001; Table 3). </p>

<p>Reduction in Risk of Having MVP &gt; 1 </p>

<p>Group, sex, and age at examination significantly 
influenced the presence of MVP above grade 1 
(Table 3). In 2010-2011, the odds of PB having 
MVP &gt; 1 compared to non-PB was 0.64 reflecting a 
36% reduced risk (P &lt; .0006; Table 3 and Fig 3). There 
was no significant difference in odds of having 
MVP &gt; 1 in 2010-2011 compared with 2002-2003. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Our study shows that a breeding scheme based on 
cardiac auscultation and echocardiography markedly 
decreased the risk of having a mitral regurgitation mur-
mur caused by MMVD after an 8-to 10-year period. 
The reduction in risk was only significant for offspring 
where both parents had been approved by the breeding 
scheme (PB), not for offspring where 1 or both parents 
not were approved by the breeding scheme (non-PB). 
The risk of having moderate to severe MVP (MVP &gt; 1) 
was not decreased after the 8-to 10-year period, but PB 
had lower risk of MVP &gt; 1 than did non-PB within the 
years 2010 and 2011. 
To the authors' knowledge ours is the first study 
reporting a clear effect of a breeding scheme aimed at 
decreasing the prevalence of MMVD in CKCS (or in 
any breed). Preliminary findings from the British volun-
tary breeding scheme (annual cardiac auscultation and 
parents' murmur status) reported an effect in the group 
of dogs auscultated by a general practitioner but only a 
trend was reported when the dogs were auscultated by 
a veterinary cardiologist. 
19 A mandatory breeding 
scheme in Sweden including annual cardiac auscultation 
and parent information did not result in significant 
effect of the scheme, albeit after a short follow-up per-
iod (2007-2009). </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Different breeding schemes aimed at decreasing the 
prevalence of MMVD in CKCS are ongoing in several 
countries worldwide to guide dog breeders. 
19 The breed-
ing schemes are mandatory or voluntary, include car-
diac auscultation or both cardiac auscultation and 
echocardiography and some programs include parent 
cardiac information. Some schemes include annual car-
diac examinations where as others have a more limited 
number of cardiac examinations during the dog's life-
time. In some schemes, the cardiac examination results 
are open to the public, in others the results are only 
known by the dog owner. How much such factors influ-
ence the effect of a breeding scheme still needs much 
clarification. 
Voluntary participation may decrease the number of 
dog owners who follow the breeding advice and thereby </p>

<p>Table 3. Odds for occurrence of mitral regurgitation murmur and moderate to severe mitral valve prolapse (MVP) 
in dogs examined in 2010 and 2011 compared with dogs examined in 2002 and 2003. </p>

<p>Response 
Variable </p>

<p>Variables 
Adjusted For </p>

<p>PB 2010-2011 
Versus 2002-2003 
(Group 2 Versus Group 1) </p>

<p>Non-PB 2010-2011 
Versus 2002-2003 
(Group 3 Versus Group 1) </p>

<p>PB Versus Non-PB 2010-2011 
(Group 2 Versus Group 3) </p>

<p>MR murmur &gt; 0 Age 
a at examination 
(P &lt; .0001) </p>

<p>P 
&lt;.0001 
.49 
&lt;.0001 
OR 
0.27 
-
0.31 
95% 
0.16-0.43 
-
0.24-0.41 
MVP &gt; 1 
Age 
a at examination 
and sex </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>(both P &lt; .0001) </p>

<p>P 
.23 
.78 
.0006 
OR 
-
-
0.64 
95% 
-
-
0.49-0.82 </p>

<p>Group 1 is dogs examined in 2002 and 2003. Group 2 and 3 are dogs examined in 2010 and 2011 that are products of the breeding 
scheme (PB) and nonproducts of the breeding scheme (non-PB), respectively. MR, mitral regurgitation. OR, odds ratio; 95%, 95% confi-
dence interval for the odds ratio. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Odds increase with advancing age. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Male higher odds than female. </p>

<p> 
Birkeg ard et al </p>

<p>decrease the effect of a breeding scheme. In a subanaly-
sis of the voluntary British breeding scheme, it became 
evident that only 4% of the dog owners had followed 
the breeding advice. 
21 Number of included observers 
and observer experience also may influence the effect of 
breeding schemes because observer variations are well-
known with regard to cardiac auscultation and echocar-
diography. 
14,17 Therefore interobserver variation was 
taken into account in the statistical analyses in this 
study. Unexpected reduction over time in individual 
mitral regurgitation murmur intensity or degree of 
MVP was observed in only a few dogs with repeated </p>

<p>examinations. The reductions may be the result of chan-
ged physiological conditions in the dog such as changed 
body condition, heart rate, or both. </p>

<p>9,17 </p>

<p>Color flow Doppler echocardiography can confirm the 
diagnosis of mitral regurgitation, but experienced obser-
vers can detect mitral regurgitation using auscultation in 
89% of dogs with mild or more severe mitral regurgita-
tion (regurgitant jet area &gt;30% of the left atrial area). </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Moderately, experienced observers (general practitioners 
level) can detect mitral regurgitation in 72% of the dogs 
by auscultation. Echocardiography is useful to support 
the diagnosis of ejection murmurs (physiological flow 
murmurs) and other heart murmurs not associated with 
mitral regurgitation. 
17 In this study, approximately 6% 
of the dogs examined from 2002 to 2011 were diagnosed 
with ejection murmurs based on clinical findings and 
echocardiography. In a previous study, 6 of 57 (10%) 
CKCS were diagnosed with ejection murmurs based on 
auscultation and phonography. 
17 Ejection murmurs do 
not seem to be associated with heart disease, 
17,18 and 
exclusion of dogs with ejection murmurs in breeding 
schemes may unnecessarily decrease the number of 
CKCS available for breeding. Estimation of mitral regur-
gitant jet size in relation to left atrial area using color 
flow Doppler echocardiography is a semi-quantitative 
estimate influenced by several factors including echocar-
diographic equipment and technical settings. 
22 This limi-
tation may affect the use of this method in breeding 
schemes including multicenter clinical examinations. 
Studies have shown that MVP is an early predictor 
of MMVD disease progression and is correlated with 
other disease variables such as degree of mitral regurgi-
tation and mitral valve thickness. 
4,5 In this study, the 
risk of having moderate to severe MVP was not found 
to be decrease in the breeding scheme during the 8-to 
10-year follow-up period. However in 2010 and 2011, 
PB were found to have a decreased risk of having mod-
erate to severe MVP compared to non-PB suggesting an 
effect of the breeding scheme on this parameter as well. 
The study has limitations. One of the observers in the 
breeding scheme was replaced in 2004 and the overall 
observer performance may have changed during the 8-
to 10-year time period. Clinical observer was included as 
random variable in the statistical models to take obser-
ver variation into account. However, it was not possible 
to include MVP observer variation in the modeling. Yet, 
the finding of a decreased risk of MMVD was confirmed 
by comparison of the risk of having a mitral regurgita-
tion murmur and moderate to severe MVP (MVP &gt; 1) 
within a limited time period (2010-2011) between PB 
and non-PB during a period with no observer replace-
ments. Finally, it is a study limitation that observers 
were not blinded to the identity of the dogs. 
Further evaluations of breeding schemes are recom-
mended to identify factors with major influence on the 
effect of such schemes. Echocardiography and manda-
tory registrations are time-consuming. Therefore, fur-
ther evaluation of ongoing breeding schemes is 
necessary to find the scheme with the highest cost bene-
fit. Until now, the present DKCA breeding scheme is 
the only scheme with a documented effect. This pro-</p>

<p>Fig 2. Mitral regurgitation murmur intensity (grade 1-6) in dogs 
examined in the Danish Kennel Club Association (DKCA) myxo-
matous mitral valve disease (MMVD) breeding scheme in 2002-
2003 and 2010-2011. The Y axis indicates the percentage of dogs 
with different degrees of mitral regurgitation murmur among dogs 
examined within the time period. Only the most recent examina-
tion is included in the figure if dogs had repeated examinations. 
PB, products of the breeding scheme. Non-PB, nonproducts of the 
breeding scheme. </p>

<p>Fig 3. Degree of mitral valve prolapse (MVP) (grade 0-3) in dogs 
examined in the Danish Kennel Club Association (DKCA) myxo-
matous mitral valve disease (MMVD) breeding scheme in 
2002-2003 and 2010-2011. The Y axis indicates the percentage of 
dogs with different degrees of MVP among dogs examined within 
the time period. Only the most recent examination is included in the 
figure if dogs had repeated examinations. PB, products of the breed-
ing scheme. Non-PB, nonproducts of the breeding scheme. </p>

<p>Mitral Valve Disease Breeding Scheme </p>

<p>
gram is recommended until other breeding schemes 
aimed at decreasing the prevalence of MMVD with 
higher performance are described. Genetic tests poten-
tially could be included in future breeding schemes. 
In conclusion, a mandatory breeding scheme based 
on auscultation and echocardiography significantly 
decreased the prevalence of MMVD over the 8-to 10-
year time period. Therefore, such a breeding scheme is 
recommended for CKCS. </p>

<p>Footnote </p>

<p>a SAS statistical software, version 9.3, SAS Institute A/S, Cary, 
NC </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank the general veterinary practitioners 
Christian Mogensen, Varde Animal Hospital, Varde, 
Denmark; Gustaf Valentiner-Branth, Bygholm Animal 
Hospital, Horsens; Mette Rønn-Landbo, Aalborg Ani-
mal Hospital, Aalborg, Denmark; Jesper Lund Søren-
sen, Rødding and Trekantens Animal Hospital, 
Rødding, Denmark, Peter Knold, Aarslev Animal 
Hospital, Aarslev, Denmark; and associate professor 
Jørgen Koch, Department of Veterinary Clinical and 
Animal Sciences, University of Copenhagen, Frederiks-
berg, Denmark, for performing cardiac auscultation 
and echocardiography of dogs in the breeding scheme. 
Christina Tirsdal Kjempff, Dennis Jensen and Hanne 
Carlsson at the Department of Veterinary Clinical and 
Animal Sciences, University of Copenhagen, Frederiks-
berg, Denmark are acknowledged for excellent technical 
assistance. 
Conflict of Interest Declaration: Authors disclose no 
conflict of interest. 
Off-Label Antimicrobial Declaration: Authors declare 
no off-label use of antimicrobials. </p>



<p> 
Birkeg ard et al </p>

</text></tei>