<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4368859" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: The rate of entry of cocaine into the brain is a critical factor that influences neuronal plasticity and the 
development of cocaine addiction. Until now, passive diffusion has been considered the unique mechanism known by 
which cocaine crosses the blood-brain barrier. 
Methods: We reassessed mechanisms of transport of cocaine at the blood-brain barrier using a human cerebral capillary 
endothelial cell line (hCMEC/D3) and in situ mouse carotid perfusion. 
Results: Both in vivo and in vitro cocaine transport studies demonstrated the coexistence of a carrier-mediated process with 
passive diffusion. At pharmacological exposure level, passive diffusion of cocaine accounted for only 22.5% of the total cocaine 
influx in mice and 5.9% in hCMEC/D3 cells, whereas the carrier-mediated influx rate was 3.4 times greater than its passive 
diffusion rate in vivo. The functional identification of this carrier-mediated transport demonstrated the involvement of a 
proton antiporter that shared the properties of the previously characterized clonidine and nicotine transporter. The functionnal 
characterization suggests that the solute carrier (SLC) transporters Oct (Slc22a1-3), Mate (Slc47a1) and Octn (Slc22a4-5) are 
not involved in the cocaine transport in vivo and in vitro. Diphenhydramine, heroin, tramadol, cocaethylene, and norcocaine 
all strongly inhibited cocaine transport, unlike benzoylecgonine. Trans-stimulation studies indicated that diphenhydramine, 
nicotine, 3,4-methylenedioxyamphetamine (ecstasy) and the cathinone compound 3,4-methylenedioxypyrovalerone (MDPV) 
were also substrates of the cocaine transporter. 
Conclusions: Cocaine transport at the BBB involves a proton-antiporter flux that is quantitatively much more important 
than its passive diffusion. The molecular identification and characterization of this transporter will provide new tools to 
understand its role in addictive mechanisms. </p>

<p>Keywords: blood-brain barrier, biological transport, cocaine, drug of abuse, pharmacokinetics. </p>



<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Cocaine is a psychoactive drug that acts predominantly as an 
inhibitor of solute carrier family (SLC)6A3, also known as the 
dopamine transporter (DAT), and is involved in dopamine 
uptake at the synaptic cleft. This inhibition is considered to be 
the main contributor to the reinforcement and behavioral prop-
erties of cocaine (Volkow et al., 1997b). Cocaine has been shown 
to be more addictive when smoked (crack use) or intravenously 
injected compared with nasal inhalation (or snorting) (Gossop 
et al., 1992; Cone, 1995). Neurobehavioral and molecular studies 
have demonstrated the critical role of the rate of cocaine deliv-
ery to the brain in the neuronal plasticity and reward effects 
induced by cocaine (Samaha et al., 2004; Samaha and Robinson, 
2005; Volkow et al., 2012; Minogianis et al., 2013). Increasing the 
rapidity of cocaine administration leads to an increase of its 
abuse liability (Volkow et al., 2000; Abreu et al., 2001; Samaha 
et al., 2004). Variability in the rate of brain cocaine uptake may 
thus have significant consequences on its acute and chronic 
effects in the central nervous system (CNS). 
The rate at which drugs reach the brain parenchyma depends 
not only on their route of administration but also on their ability 
to cross the cerebral endothelium, also called the blood-brain 
barrier (BBB), which constitutes the main brain interface modu-
lating exchanges of compounds between the brain and blood 
(Abbott et al., 2010). Passive diffusion is the primary route by 
which solutes cross membranes. According to the pH partition 
theory, nonionized drugs cross cell membranes, and neurophar-
macodynamic events depend solely on their neutral unbound 
fraction in the plasma. The relative "sufficient" lipophilicity 
(estimated by log P) of the neutral form has been historically 
correlated with the rate of drug diffusion at the BBB. As 6% of 
cocaine is uncharged (clog P 3.1) at pH 7.4 (clog D 7.4 1.5; pK a 8.6), 
it has been assumed that this 6% crosses the BBB by passive 
diffusion and fast enough to produce its CNS effects, whereas 
the 94% of positively charged cocaine cannot cross the BBB. 
Although the pH partition theory is physicochemically relevant, 
it leads to the misinterpretation of the CNS effects of many 
psychotropic drugs, such as ecstasy (3,4-methylenedioxyam-
phetamine [MDMA]; clog P 1.8; clog D 7.4 −0.9; pK a 10.1), which are 
99.8% cationic at neutral pH. An alternative hypothesis is that a 
carrier-mediated transport process, capable of carrying at least 
the cationic form of these psychostimulant substances across 
the BBB, may also be involved. 
The question of how CNS drugs are transferred to the brain 
parenchyma has been poorly addressed, mainly because of 
these redundant mechanistic assumptions concerning passive 
diffusion. Although some pharmacokinetic studies suggest that 
passive diffusion is not the only mechanism by which cocaine 
crosses the BBB (Benuck et al., 1987; Gatley et al., 1990; Telang 
et al., 1999; Raje et al., 2003), this mechanism of transport has 
not yet been elucidated at the BBB. Although our knowledge of 
carrier-mediated systems is still incomplete, it is known that 
ABC transporters, such as P-glycoprotein (P-gp; ABCB1) or BCRP 
(ABCG2) could be involved in the unidirectional transport of 
their substrates by limiting their brain uptake and/or increas-
ing their efflux from the brain into the blood. Some bidirectional 
SLC transporters are also known to be involved in the transport 
of compounds at the BBB (Abbott et al., 2010; Giacomini et al., 
2010; Tournier et al., 2011). Functional studies have previously 
established that a drug/proton-coupled antiporter present at the 
mouse BBB speeds up the transport of nicotine or clonidine and 
that it can unlikely be saturated by their in vivo pharmacologi-
cal plasma concentrations (Andre et al., 2009; Cisternino et al., </p>

<p>2013). Cocaine has also been shown previously to modulate the 
clonidine transporter at the mouse BBB (Andre et al., 2009). 
Based on these preliminary results, we have characterized 
cocaine transport at the mouse luminal BBB by in situ brain per-
fusion (Dagenais et al., 2000) and in hCMEC/D3 cells used as an 
in vitro model of the human BBB (Dauchy et al., 2009; Weksler 
et al., 2013). Both models permit the qualitative and quantita-
tive properties of drug transport to be determined (Takasato 
et al., 1984; Dagenais et al., 2000) and can be used to evaluate 
the contribution of carrier-mediated systems by assessing the 
concentration dependency of the transport through exposure 
of these models to cocaine concentrations high enough to sur-
pass the concentration at the half-maximal carrier velocity (K m ) 
of the transporter (Kell et al., 2013). Our results show that the 
transport of cocaine across the BBB mainly involves a carrier-
mediated system functionally identified as a proton/cocaine-
antiporter, in addition to a relative minor passive component in 
the pharmacological vascular/extracellular concentration range. 
The features of this molecularly unknown transporter highlight 
its importance in governing the delivery of cocaine to the mouse 
and possibly to the human brain. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Drugs and Chemicals </p>

<p>[ 3 H]-(−)Cocaine (35.3 Ci/mmol) and [ 14 C]-sucrose (435 mCi/ 
mmol) were purchased from Perkin Elmer (Courtaboeuf, France). 
Opioids and levogyre cocaine-related compounds were obtained 
from Euromedex (Souffelweyersheim, France). (−)-Cocaine and 
morphine were obtained from Francopia (Paris, France). MDMA 
and 3,4-methylenedioxypyrovalerone (MDPV) (purity &gt;99%) were 
synthetized by the chemistry departments of Paris Descartes 
University (Dr. H. Galons and Dr. H. Chen). PSC833 was donated 
by Novartis (Basel, Switzerland). All other chemicals were from 
Sigma (Saint Quentin-Fallavier, France). </p>

<p>Cell Culture </p>

<p>hCMEC/D3 cells were seeded at 25 000 cells/cm 2 on collagen-
coated culture flask in EBM-2 medium (Lonza, Basel, Switzerland) 
supplemented as described in Dauchy et al. (2009). For experi-
ments, cells seeded in multiwell dishes (25 000 cells/cm 2 ) were 
used 3 to 4 days after seeding and between passages 28 and 35. </p>

<p>In Vitro Transport Experiment </p>

<p>hCMEC/D3 cells prepared as described above were first preincu-
bated 30 minutes with the Krebs N-2-hydroxyethylpiperazine-
N'-2-ethanesulfonic acid (HEPES) (KH) buffer (in mM: 128, NaCl; 
24, NaHCO 3 ; 4.2, KCl; 2.4, NaH 2 PO 4 ; 1.5, CaCl 2 ; 0.9, MgSO 4 ; 10, 
HEPES; and 9, d-glucose) adjusted to pH 7.40. In some experi-
ments, iso-osmotic substitution of sodium in KH buffer was 
performed with N-methyl-d-glucamine chloride (NMDG). 
The experiment was initiated by adding KH buffer contain-
ing [ 3 H]-cocaine (0.1 µCi/mL, ~3 nM) in presence or absence of 
another drug. After 5 minutes of incubation at 37°C, cells were 
placed on ice, and ice-cold Dulbecco's phosphate buffered saline 
was added to stop the transport. Cells were then rapidly washed 
twice with ice-cold Dulbecco's phosphate buffered saline and 
lysed with sodium dodecyl sulfate 10% (30 minutes at 37°C 
under agitation). In trans-stimulation studies, cells were loaded </p>

<p>Chapy et al. | 3 </p>

<p>5 minutes with [ 3 H]-cocaine (0.1 µCi/mL; KH buffer) before incu-
bation with KH buffer with or without (control) an unlabeled 
compound (10 µM) before stopping the transport and washing 
the cells as describe. Cell lysates were placed in vials and mixed 
with Ultima gold (Perkin Elmer) before being counted in a Tri-
Carb counter (Perkin Elmer) to measure disintegrations per min-
ute (dpm). Cell lysate was kept to quantify proteins (micro BCA 
protein assay kit, Pierce, Sigma). </p>

<p>Manipulation of pH 
To bring KH buffer to pH 5.40 or 6.40, hydrochloric acid was 
added. NH 4 Cl prepulse condition leads to cytosol acidification 
and was achieved first by preincubating cells with KH buffer con-
taining NH 4 Cl (30 mM) for 15 minutes, which was subsequently 
replaced by NH 4 Cl-free KH buffer for 5 minutes before initiating 
the transport of [ 3 H]-cocaine as described above. Alkalinization 
of the cytosol was obtained by NH 4 Cl pulse condition, which 
consists of studying the transport of [ 3 H]-cocaine in a KH buffer 
(pH e 7.40) also containing NH 4 Cl (30 mM) for 5 minutes. </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>In vivo experiments were performed with Swiss mice (25-
40 g; Janvier, Genest, France) unless otherwise specified. In 
some experiments, DBA, C57bl/6, Fvb (Janvier), and Fvb dou-
ble knockout organic cation transporter 1 and 2 [Oct1,2(−/−)] 
(The Netherlands Cancer Institute, Amsterdam) male mice 
were used. All mice (7-11 weeks old) were housed in a con-
trolled environment (22 ± 3°C; 55 ± 10% relative humidity) and a 
12-hour-dark/-light cycle with access to food and tap water ad 
libitum. All experiments complied with the ethical rules of the 
Agriculture French Ministry for experimentation with labora-
tory animals and were approved by the ethics review committee 
(Paris Descartes University no. 12-183). </p>

<p>In Situ Carotid Perfusion </p>

<p>Surgical procedure and perfusion 
The transport of [ 3 H]-cocaine at the luminal BBB was measured 
by in situ carotid perfusion allowing to totally substitute brain 
vascular composition with an artificial perfusion fluid (Dagenais 
et al., 2000). Briefly, mice were anesthetized with ketamine-
xylazine (140-8 mg/kg, intraperitoneally), and a catheter was 
inserted into the right carotid artery. Before perfusion, the tho-
rax was opened and the heart was cut. Perfusion was started 
immediately at a constant flow rate of 2.5 mL/min, reaching a 
carotid pressure of ~120 mmHg. Each mouse was perfused with 
[ 3 H]-cocaine (0.3 µCi/mL, ~9 nM) and [ 14 C]-sucrose (0.1 µCi/mL) as 
a vascular marker. Perfusion was terminated after 60 seconds 
by decapitating the mouse. The right cerebral hemisphere and 2 
aliquots of perfusion fluid were placed in tared vials, weighted, 
digested with Solvable (Perkin Elmer), and mixed with Ultima 
gold before dual-labeled dpm counting. </p>

<p>Perfusion fluid 
The perfusion fluid was Krebs-carbonate similar to KH buffer 
without HEPES gassed with 95% O 2 /5% CO 2 to bring pH to 
7.40 unless otherwise specified. Hydrochloric acid was added 
in some experiments to bring the pH to 5.40 or 6.40. Krebs-
carbonate perfusate was changed to remove Na + and/or Cl − by 
iso-osmotic replacement. Sodium was replaced by lithium chlo-
ride, and sodium and chloride were replaced by mannitol. Mice 
were also perfused with carbonate-free HEPES-buffered saline 
(in mM: 152, NaCl; 4.2, KCl; 1.5, CaCl 2 ; 0.9, MgSO 4 ; 10, HEPES; and </p>

<p>9, d-glucose), gassed with O 2 , and brought to pH 7.40. The perfu-
sion fluid was warmed to 37°C and checked with a digital pH 
meter (±0.05 pH units) before perfusion. </p>

<p>[ 3 H]-Cocaine transport study 
The brain accumulation of [ 3 H]-cocaine was measured under 
trans-influx zero to determine the kinetic conditions required 
to measure transport solely across the membrane separating 
the sucrose (vascular) space from the non-sucrose (brain paren-
chyma) space. The perfusion time adopted (60 seconds) ensured 
that the tissue distribution of the drug was that of the initial lin-
ear part of the distribution kinetics. The brain apparent distribu-
tion did not reach (pseudo-) equilibrium during this initial linear 
phase (data not shown). The first membrane (luminal) delimit-
ing the sucrose space is the only kinetic interface that affected 
the distribution of [ 3 H]-cocaine. Cis-inhibition was performed 
by co-perfusion of [ 3 H]-cocaine (60 seconds) with an unlabeled 
drug. </p>

<p>Apparent tissue distribution volume and initial 
transport parameters 
Calculations were done as previously described (Dagenais et al., 
2000). The brain "vascular" volume was estimated using the 
[ 14 C]-sucrose distribution volume (V v ; µL/g): </p>

<p>V 
X 
C </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>perf </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(Equation 1) </p>

<p>where X * (dpm/g) is the amount of [ 14 C]-sucrose in the right brain 
hemisphere, and C * </p>

<p>perf </p>

<p>(dpm/µL) is the [ 14 C]-sucrose concentra-
tion in the perfusion fluid. The data for any mouse whose V v was 
above the normal value (Cattelotte et al., 2008) was excluded 
from the study. 
The apparent tissue distribution volume (V tissue , µL/g) was 
calculated as: </p>

<p>V 
X 
C </p>

<p>tissue 
tissue </p>

<p>perf </p>

<p>= 
(Equation 2) </p>

<p>where X tissue (dpm/g) is the calculated amount of [ 3 H]-cocaine 
from the right brain hemisphere and C perf (dpm/µL) is the 
[ 3 H]-cocaine concentration in the perfusion fluid: </p>

<p>X 
X 
V C </p>

<p>tissue 
tot 
v perf </p>

<p>= 
− 
(Equation 3) </p>

<p>where X tot (dpm/g) is the total quantity of [ 3 H]-cocaine measured 
in the sample tissue. The amount of [ 3 H]-cocaine in the vascu-
lar "[ 14 C]-sucrose" space ( V C 
v perf ) was calculated and subtracted 
from the total (X tot ) (Equation 3). 
The initial transport rate, also called brain clearance, 
expressed as a K in (µL/sec/g), was calculated from: </p>

<p>K 
V 
T </p>

<p>in 
tissue </p>

<p>= 
(Equation 4) </p>

<p>where T is the perfusion time (seconds). 
The permeability-surface area product (PS, µL/sec/g) was cal-
culated as </p>

<p>PS 
F 
K F </p>

<p>in </p>

<p>= − 
− 
ln( 
) 
1 
(Equation 5) </p>

<p>where F (vascular flow rate; µL/sec/g) has been previously meas-
ured to be 42.3 µL/sec/g (Cattelotte et al., 2008). 
The flux (J in ; nmol/sec/g of brain) is given by: </p>

<p>J 
PS C </p>

<p>in 
tot </p>

<p>= × 
(Equation 6) </p>



<p>The cocaine brain flux (J in ) or cellular uptake velocity (nmol/min/ 
mg) is described as a saturable (Michaelis-Menten term) and a 
passive unsaturable component: </p>

<p>J 
V C 
K 
C 
K 
C </p>

<p>in 
tot </p>

<p>m 
t ot </p>

<p>passive tot </p>

<p>= 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>(Equation 7) </p>

<p>where C tot (mM) is the total cocaine concentration in the perfu-
sate or incubation buffer, V max (nmol/sec/g or nmol/min/mg) is 
the maximal velocity of transport, and K m (mM) represents the 
concentration at the half-maximal carrier velocity. K passive (µL/ 
sec/g or µL/min/mg) is an unsaturable component that repre-
sents the rate of transport by passive diffusion. The data were 
fitted using nonlinear regression analysis. </p>

<p>Data Analysis </p>

<p>Data are means ± standard deviation (SD). One way analysis of 
variance and post hoc test (Dunnett) were used to identify sig-
nificant differences, unless specified otherwise, and statistical 
significance was set at P &lt; 0.05. The transport parameters (K m , 
V max , K passive ) were estimated by plotting cocaine brain or cell flux 
data against total concentration using Equation 7 and nonlinear 
regression with <rs type="software">WinNonlin</rs> software. The errors associated with 
these parameters are asymptotic standard errors returned by 
the nonlinear regression routine. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Brain Transport of Cocaine Measured by in Situ 
Brain Perfusion in Selected Transport-Deficient or 
Wild-Type Mouse Strains </p>

<p>The transport rate of [ 3 H]-cocaine was measured by in situ brain 
perfusion to check for differences in cocaine transport between 
mouse strains and to test the hypothesis of the involvement of 
specific transporters. Brain transport (K in ; n = 4-5 mice) meas-
ured in selected mouse strains perfused with [ 3 H]-cocaine 
(9 nM) for 60 seconds in Krebs-carbonate buffer (pH 7.40) was 
as follows: DBA (21 ± 2 µL/sec/g), C57Bl/6 (19 ± 2 µL/sec/g), Fvb 
(20 ± 2 µL/sec/g), and Swiss (20 ± 2 µL/sec/g). These rates were 
not significantly different. The transport of [ 3 H]-cocaine in wild-
type Fvb did not differ significantly from that in [Oct1,Oct2(−/−)] </p>

<p>mice (19 ± 2 µL/sec/g; n = 4). P-gp was not involved in [ 3 H]-cocaine 
transport, since its transport rate was not significantly modi-
fied by co-perfusion of the highly potent P-gp inhibitor PSC833 
(10 µM) (23 ± 3 µL/sec/g; n = 4) in Swiss mice. </p>

<p>Passive and Carrier-Mediated Cocaine Transport 
Components </p>

<p>Concentration dependence of cocaine transport in vitro 
The concentration dependence of cocaine uptake was assessed 
in hCMEC/D3 cells over a range of concentrations high enough to 
surpass the K m for xenobiotic transporters. Cells were incubated 
for 5 minutes in KH buffer (pH 7.40, 37°C) containing cocaine 
(0.05-10 mM) and [ 3 H]-cocaine (0.1 µCi/mL). The total cocaine 
uptake velocity (nmol/min/mg of protein) was plotted against the 
total cocaine concentration in the incubation buffer. This global 
cocaine uptake velocity (dashed line) resulted in both a satura-
ble uptake component fitted by a Michaelis-Menten equation in 
addition to an unsaturable component (Equation 7) (Figure 1a-
b). Kinetic analysis provided a K m of 0.123 ± 0.023 mM, a V max of 
4.27 ± 0.26 nmol/min/mg, and a K passive of 1.09 ± 0.09 µL/min/mg 
for the transport of cocaine in hCMEC/D3 cells. At concentra-
tions (&lt;10 µM) far less than the K m , this passive flux represents 
5.9% of the total flux of cocaine (Figure 1b). </p>

<p>Concentration dependence of cocaine transport in vivo 
The experimentally determined net cocaine flux (J in ) was plotted 
against its concentration (Figure 2a-b). J in was fitted to Equation 7 
(dashed line), which yielded both a saturable (Michaelis-Menten) 
and an unsaturable component, as shown by the shape of the 
curve (Figure 2a). Regression analysis of the unsaturated compo-
nent of cocaine flux into the brain yielded a K passive of 4.5 ± 1.0 µL/ 
sec/g (pH e 7.40). The unsaturated flux (dotted line) was sub-
tracted from the total cocaine flux measured (J in ) to obtain the 
carrier-mediated cocaine component (solid line), which was 
plotted against the total (unbound) cocaine concentration. 
Modeling this carrier-mediated brain cocaine flux yielded an 
apparent K m of 4.5 ± 1.8 mM and a V max of 127.2 ± 34.5 nmol/sec/g 
of brain (solid line; Figure 2a). Using Equation 7, we found that 
the minimal experimental concentration at which passive dif-
fusion and carrier-mediated flux are equal is around 24 mM of 
cocaine. Above this theoretical vascular cocaine concentration, </p>

<p>Figure 1. Passive and carrier-mediated flux of cocaine in hCMEC/D3 cells. A, Total uptake (nmol/min/mg; dashed line) was measured in hCMEC/D3 cells and plotted </p>

<p>against total cocaine concentration in the KH incubation buffer at pH e 7.40. The straight dotted line represents the passive transport of cocaine (K passive of 1.09 ± 0.09 µL/ </p>

<p>min/mg at pH 7.40). The solid line represents the curve obtained by subtracting the passive flux from the total flux and fitting to the carrier-mediated Michaelis-</p>

<p>Menten term (see Equation 7) by nonlinear least-square regression. Estimated parameters for cocaine transport in hCMEC/D3 cells are: K m , 0.123 ± 0.023 mM; V max , </p>

<p>4.26 ± 0.26 nmol/min/mg. Data represent means ± SD of experiments performed in triplicate. B, Total (dashed line) and individual passive (dotted line) and carrier-</p>

<p>mediated (solid line) cocaine transport into hCMEC/D3 cells fitted according to Equation 7 for concentrations &lt;0.5 mM. Data represent means ± SD of experiments </p>

<p>performed in triplicate. </p>

<p>Chapy et al. | 5 </p>

<p>the passive diffusion flux will surpass the carrier-mediated 
one. The net brain cocaine transport rate (K in ) under unsatu-
rated conditions (which also reflect the pharmacological con-
centration range) is about 20 µL/sec/g. This represents a total 
brain extraction of about 47% as compared with the vascular 
flow marker diazepam (see Methods); passive diffusion (K passive 
4.5 ± 1.0 µL/sec/g) represents 22.5% of the total cocaine flux at 
the mouse BBB. </p>

<p>Effect of cis-Inhibition of Selected Compounds on 
[ 3 H]-Cocaine Transport in vitro and in vivo </p>

<p>We performed drug-cocaine interaction studies on hCMEC/D3 
cells and mice using cis-inhibition of [ 3 H]-cocaine transport to 
discriminate between the effects of known transporters pos-
sibly involved in drug influx and to gain more insight into the 
molecular features of drugs that could interact with the cocaine 
transporter. Many compounds inhibit/modulate transporters, 
although they are not necessarily transported themselves, as is 
known for cocaine and SLC6A3. The concentrations used do not 
reflect or predict in vivo drug-drug interactions, as the unbound 
concentrations used can never be reached by their systemic 
administration in mice or humans. 
We used broad-range inhibitors like tetraethylammonium 
(TEA), choline, and carnitine, which inhibit a wide range of known 
organic transporters, including Octs (Slc22a1-3), Mate (Slc47a1), 
and Octn (Slc22a4-5), both in vitro and in vivo. These compounds 
used at concentrations surpassing the cocaine transporter K m 
did not significantly modulate the transport of [ 3 H]-cocaine in 
vitro or in vivo, suggesting that these SLC transporters are not 
involved in cocaine transport at the BBB (Tables 1A and 2). It has 
previously been demonstrated that Oct1-3, Pmat, and Mate1 are 
not expressed or functional at the mouse BBB (Agarwal et al., 
2012; Andre et al., 2012). However, the hCMEC/D3 cell line has 
been shown to express some OCTs that could affect its func-
tional properties (Weksler et al., 2013). In parallel experiments in 
the hCMEC/D3 cell line, we found that MPP + , a known substrate 
of the OCTs, was significantly inhibited by TEA (2 mM), a sub-
strate/inhibitor for OCTs (data not shown). However, the same 
TEA concentration did not affect [ 3 H]-cocaine transport in these 
cells (Table 1A). Previous reports have also identified a range 
of substrates of a drug/proton-antiporter, such as clonidine, 
nicotine, diphenhydramine, oxycodone, and naloxone; these 
significantly affected [ 3 H]-cocaine transport with varying poten-
cies (Tables 1 and 2). Some cocaine metabolites were also tested: </p>

<p>benzoylecgonine and ecgonine altered [ 3 H]-cocaine transport in 
vivo and/or in vitro but with low potencies, whereas a few other 
cocaine-related compounds such as norcocaine, cocaethylene, 
and ecgonine methylester significantly decreased the BBB trans-
port of [ 3 H]-cocaine at lower concentrations (Tables 1B and 2). </p>

<p>Effect of trans-Stimulation by Organic Compounds 
on Intracellular [ 3 H]-Cocaine Content in hCMEC/ 
D3 Cells </p>

<p>The trans-stimulation technique provides a qualitative indica-
tion of whether a given compound is a substrate, but it does 
not provide kinetic information to quantify active vs passive 
transport rate. We assessed the ability of some compounds 
present in the extracellular compartment to further stimulate 
the exit of accumulated [ 3 H]-cocaine from hCMEC/D3 cells that 
could occur with a bidirectional transporter. The trans-efflux 
zero or exit of [ 3 H]-cocaine was strongly stimulated (P &lt; 0.001) 
by MDMA, MDPV, nicotine, and diphenhydramine (Figure 3), 
suggesting that they may also be substrates of the cocaine 
transporter. The trans-stimulation study also suggests that the 
transporter is bidirectional and could transport cocaine in or 
out of the cell according to its concentration gradient. Cells not 
exposed to the 5-minute washout with KH buffer had about 4.6-
fold more intracellular [ 3 H]-cocaine than control cells that were 
washed out (P &lt; 0.001, n = 4). </p>

<p>Effects of Inorganic Ions on [ 3 H]-Cocaine Transport </p>

<p>To study the force driving the cocaine carrier and gain further 
biochemical information to better assess its functional iden-
tity, the intracellular pH and extracellular proton or sodium 
concentrations were manipulated in both in vitro and in vivo 
models. </p>

<p>Modulations of the extracellular/vascular pHe 
The proportion of neutral and cationic species of cocaine 
depends on the pH e , which can be estimated using a basic pKa 
value of 8.6 for cocaine in water (Lu et al., 2007). Cocaine is 0.06% 
neutral at pH e 5.40, 0.6% at pH e 6.40, and 5.9% at pH e 7.40. The 
incubation of hCMEC/D3 cells with KH buffer set to yield a pH e 
of 5.40, 6.40, or 7.40 shows a 2.5-and 4.6-fold increase (P &lt; 0.001) 
in [ 3 H]-cocaine uptake at pH e 6.40 and 7.40, respectively, as com-
pared with pH e 5.40 (Figure 4a). Similarly, the brain transport 
of [ 3 H]-cocaine measured for 60 seconds at pH e 6.40 and 7.40 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Passive and carrier-mediated flux of cocaine at the mouse luminal BBB. A, Total flux (J in ; nmol/sec/g; dashed line) measured in the right brain hemisphere of </p>

<p>male Swiss mice and plotted against total cocaine concentration in the perfusion buffer (Krebs-carbonate) at pH e 7.40 (Equation 6). The straight dotted line represents </p>

<p>the passive diffusion flux of cocaine (K passive of 4.5 ± 1.0 µL/sec/g at pH 7.4). The solid line represents the curve obtained by subtracting the passive flux from the total </p>

<p>flux and fitted to the carrier-mediated Michaelis-Menten term (see Equation 7) by nonlinear least-square regression. Estimated parameters for the brain transport of </p>

<p>cocaine are: K m , 4.5 ± 1.8 mM; V max , 127.2 ± 34.5 nmol/sec/g. Data represent means ± SD of 4 to 5 mice. B, Total (dashed line), carrier-mediated (solid line), and passive (dot-</p>

<p>ted line) cocaine fluxes at pharmacological concentrations at the mouse BBB, fitted according to Equation 7 for concentrations &lt;0.1 mM. </p>



<p>in mice was significantly increased (P &lt; 0.001) by 4.7-and 16.9-
fold, respectively, as compared with its transport measured at 
pH e 5.40 (Figure 5a). This increase could be related to the higher 
neutral cocaine fraction in the perfusate and/or to a change in 
the transport rate according to the proton extracellular con-
centration. Adding unlabeled cocaine (10 mM) led to a signifi-
cant 1.8-, 2.0-, and 1.9-fold decrease in [ 3 H]-cocaine transport 
at the mouse BBB at pH e 5.40, 6.40, and 7.40, respectively, con-
firming that a carrier-mediated process is involved (Figure 5a). 
This inhibition effect by unlabeled cocaine shown at pH e 5.40 or 
6.40 could suggest that the cationic form (&gt;99.4%) of cocaine is 
a substrate of the transporter. However, with these functional </p>

<p>Table 1. Effects of Selected Organic Compounds, Psychoactive 
Drugs, and Their Metabolites (A) and Cocaine Metabolites (B) on 
[ 3 H]-Cocaine Uptake in hCMEC/D3 Cells a </p>

<p>Compound </p>

<p>Concentration, 
mM </p>

<p>Relative 
uptake, % </p>

<p>A 
Carnitine 
5 
96.1 ± 15.0 
Choline 
5 
102.0 ± 14.2 
TEA 
5 
120.6 ± 9.8 
Nicotine 
0.05 
73.8 ± 2.6* 
MDMA 
0.05 
29.7 ± 0.7*** 
MDPV 
0.05 
18.1 ± 0.4 *** 
Clonidine 
0.05 
17.3 ± 1.3*** 
Diphenhydramine 
0.05 
8.3 ± 0.4*** 
Verapamil 
0.05 
3.7 ± 0.2*** 
Imipramine 
0.05 
1.6 ± 0.4*** 
Oxycodone 
0.05 
68.7 ± 4.4*** 
Codeine 
0.05 
63.4 ± 5.0** 
Morphine 
0.05 
62.9 ± 14.7 ** 
Hydrocodone 
0.05 
49.2 ± 5.8*** 
Oxymorphone 
0.05 
36.3 ± 1.1*** 
Norbuprenorphine 
0.05 
31.7 ± 6.3** 
6-Acetylcodeine 
0.05 
31.3 ± 1.7*** 
Naloxone 
0.05 
28.3 ± 0.9*** 
Heroin 
0.05 
20.6 ± 0.6*** 
Tramadol 
0.05 
19.3 ± 2.0*** 
Methadone 
0.05 
6.1 ± 0.3*** 
B 
Benzoylecgonine 
0.05 
104.1 ± 3.0 
0.1 
94.2 ± 14.9 
1 
72.0 ± 11.4* 
Ecgonine 
0.05 
103.9 ± 8.7 
0.1 
93.2 ± 2.5 
1 
75.3 ± 5.0* 
Ecgonine methylester 
0.01 
62.9 ± 4.0*** 
0.05 
27.7 ± 2.2*** 
0.1 
18.3 ± 3.4*** 
Cocaethylene 
0.01 
35.4 ± 4.4*** 
0.05 
15.3 ± 0.3*** 
0.1 
12.0 ± 0.6*** 
Norcocaine 
0.01 
29.5 ± 1.1*** 
0.05 
18.2 ± 0.1*** 
0.1 
13.5 ± 0.3*** </p>

<p>Abbreviations: MDMA, 3,4-methylenedioxyamphetamine; MDPV, 3,4-methylen-
edioxypyrovalerone; TEA, tetraethylammonium. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>The inhibition of the transport of [ 3 H]-cocaine (3 nM) by the above 
compounds was evaluated in hCMEC/D3 cells with Krebs-HEPES 
buffer (pH e 7.40) and an incubation time of 5 min. The uptake rate 
for controls set at 100 ± 10% was 0.105 ± 0.01 µL/min/µg. Data are ex-
pressed as means ± SD (performed in triplicate). * P &lt; 0.05, ** P &lt; 0.01, 
*** P &lt; 0.001 compared with the control group. </p>

<p>Table 2. Effects of Selected Organic Compounds, Psychoactive Drugs, 
and Their Metabolites on [ 3 H]-Cocaine Transport in the Mouse Brain a </p>

<p>Compound </p>

<p>Concentration, 
mM </p>

<p>Relative 
transport 
rate, % </p>

<p>Carnitine 
15 
107.4 ± 9.2 
Choline 
10 
109.8 ± 14.5 
TEA 
15 
115.1 ± 13.9 
Benzoylecgonine 
5 
110.3 ± 12.6 
Norcocaine 
5 
59.7 ± 3.7*** 
Cocaethylene 
5 
55.1 ± 3.0*** 
Morphine 
5 
96.8 ± 11.9 
MDMA 
5 
82.1 ± 7.1* 
Nicotine 
10 
76.7 ± 6.9** 
Methadone 
5 
76.3 ± 7.6** 
MDPV 
5 
59.8 ± 7.7*** 
Diphenhydramine 
5 
46.6 ± 2.4*** </p>

<p>Abbreviations: MDMA, 3,4-methylenedioxyamphetamine; MDPV, 3,4-methylen-</p>

<p>edioxypyrovalerone; TEA, tetraethylammonium. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>The effect of the above compounds on the luminal BBB transport of 
[ 3 H]-cocaine (9 nM) was measured by in situ brain co-perfusion (cis-in-
hibition) in Krebs-carbonate perfusion fluid (pH e 7.40) for 60 sec in Swiss 
mice. Brain transport (K in ) for controls, set at 100%, was 20.1 ± 3.0 µL/ 
sec/g. Data are expressed as means ± SD (n = 4-6 mice per condition). * 
P &lt; 0.05, ** P &lt; 0.01, *** P &lt; 0.001 compared with the control group. </p>

<p>Chapy et al. | 7 </p>

<p>approaches, we cannot reject that the neutral form of cocaine 
is not a substrate. </p>

<p>Alteration of the intracellular pHi 
To limit the confounding effect of the proportion of neutral 
cocaine in the extracellular/vascular compartment and thus to 
better illustrate the effect of proton on the transporter activity, 
[ 3 H]-cocaine transport (pH e 7.40) was also evaluated with proto-
cols that only increased or decreased the pH i (Taylor et al., 2006; 
Andre et al., 2009). </p>

<p>Alkalinization protocols 
In hCMEC/D3 cells, a NH 4 Cl pulse (30 mM) significantly decreased 
[ 3 H]-cocaine uptake into the cells (Figure 4b). In vivo, mouse 
brains were perfused for 60 seconds with Krebs-carbonate buffer </p>

<p>containing [ 3 H]-cocaine (9 nM) with or without NH 4 Cl (30 mM), 
adjusted to pH e 7.40. This increase in pH i by NH 4 Cl led to a sig-
nificant 1.8-fold reduction (P &lt; 0.001) in the brain transport of 
[ 3 H]-cocaine (Figure 5b) in accordance with a proton-antiporter 
mechanism. 
Physiologically, the blood acts as a carbonate buffer, and 
replacing it abruptly by a vascular solution without carbonate 
(eg, HEPES-medium) rapidly and transiently increases the pH i 
of endothelial cells. The brain transport of [ 3 H]-cocaine was 
decreased 1.8-fold with HEPES-buffer compared with Krebs-
carbonate buffer (Figure 5b). </p>

<p>Acidification protocols 
NH 4 Cl prepulse treatment resulted in a significant 1.85-
fold (P &lt; 0.001) increase in cocaine uptake in hCMEC/D3 cells 
(Figure 4b). This protocol could not be easily transposed to in 
situ brain perfusion. Instead, we used a pH i acidification protocol 
in which sodium was removed from the vascular solution that 
rapidly and transiently decreased the pH i . The [ 3 H]-cocaine K in of 
mice perfused with the mannitol perfusion buffer was increased 
1.35-fold (P &lt; 0.05) compared with control Krebs-carbonate-per-
fused mice (Figure 5b) in accordance with a proton-antiporter 
mechanism. </p>

<p>Effect of sodium on [ 3 H]-cocaine transport 
When hCMEC/D3 cells were incubated with NMDG-buffer (pH e 
7.40), no significant change (97.0 ± 9.7%, n = 5) in [ 3 H]-cocaine 
transport was observed after 5 minutes of incubation compared 
with control in KH buffer (100.0 ± 9.0%). It can be difficult to study 
the influence of ions such as sodium on a putative H + -coupled 
transport system in situ, because acute exposure to an Na + -free 
extracellular medium can alter the Na + -dependent transport-
ers involved in controlling the pH i and thus indirectly alter the 
activity of proton-dependent transporters. We then perfused the 
brains of mice with [ 3 H]-cocaine in lithium buffer, which does 
not significantly affect the pH i at the BBB (Figure 5b) (Andre 
et al., 2009), and compared this with [ 3 H]-cocaine in regular 
Krebs-carbonate buffer. There was no significant change in the 
brain transport of [ 3 H]-cocaine, suggesting that sodium is not 
involved in [ 3 H]-cocaine transport at the BBB (Figure 5b). </p>

<p>Figure 3. Trans-stimulation studies of cocaine transport in hCMEC/D3 cells. </p>

<p>hCMEC/D3 cells were loaded with [ 3 H]-cocaine for 5 minutes and then incu-</p>

<p>bated with KH buffer alone (control) or with 10 µM of unlabeled compound (TEA, </p>

<p>benzoylecgonine, cocaine, MDPV, MDMA, diphenhydramine, or nicotine) in KH </p>

<p>buffer. Data represent means ± SD performed in quadruplicate. *** P &lt; 0.001 com-</p>

<p>pared with controls. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Effect of the modulation of extracellular (pH e ) and intracellular (pH i ) pH on cocaine transport in hCMEC/D3 cells. a, Effects of changes in the incubation buffer </p>

<p>pH e . [ 3 H]-Cocaine uptake was measured for 5 minutes in KH buffer adjusted to pH 5.40, 6.40, or 7.40. *** P &lt; 0.001 compared with the pH 5.4 group, and ### P &lt; 0.001 for a </p>

<p>comparison between pH 6.40 and 7.40 (n = 3-4). b, Modulation of pH i with NH 4 Cl. In pulse condition (cellular alkalinization): after 30 minutes of the usual preincubation, </p>

<p>a solution (pH e 7.40) with NH 4 Cl (30 mM) and containing [ 3 H]-cocaine was added for 5 minutes. The NH 4 Cl prepulse condition (cellular acidification) was obtained by </p>

<p>preincubating cells with the incubation buffer (pH e 7.40) plus NH 4 Cl (30 mM) for 15 minutes. Then, the incubation medium was replaced by the usual KH buffer without </p>

<p>NH 4 Cl for 5 minutes. [ 3 H]-Cocaine uptake was measured in the usual KH incubation buffer for 5 minutes (n = 3-4). </p>



<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Cocaine saturability studies of brain endothelial cells in 
vivo and in vitro demonstrate the coexistence of an additive 
carrier-mediated process along with the passive diffusion flux 
of cocaine at the BBB. The highest plasma cocaine concentra-
tions reported in human or rodent studies are &lt;10 µM (Benuck 
et al., 1987; Booze et al., 1997; Volkow et al., 2000). Therefore, 
according to the apparent K m , an unbound extracellular/vas-
cular cocaine concentration &lt;4.5 mM in mice or 0.12 mM in 
human cells would allow a cocaine flux across the BBB that 
is always proportional to its vascular/extracellular concen-
tration. At the pharmacotoxicological range of cocaine con-
centrations (which are far less than the transporter K m ), the 
passive diffusion flux of cocaine accounts for about 22.5% of 
the total cocaine influx in mice and 5.9% of the flux in hCMEC/ 
D3 cells. A comparison of the in vivo passive (~4.5 µL/sec/g) 
and carrier-mediated (~15.5 µL/sec/g) transport rates suggests 
that the carrier-mediated influx of cocaine is 3.4 times greater 
than its passive diffusion when concentrations are less than 
the apparent carrier-mediated K m . This carrier-mediated com-
ponent could be responsible for the fast rise in cocaine concen-
tration in the brain parenchyma. Although both in vitro and in 
vivo experiments show that the proportion of passive cocaine 
flux is minor compared with its active flux, quantitative differ-
ences do exist between the 2 types of models. Some in vitro-
in vivo studies have identified a few factors that could affect 
these proportions. The presence of an unstirred water layer in 
static in vitro models, but not in in situ perfusion model, could 
contribute to a boundary layer of water that decreases passive 
diffusion in vitro (Avdeef et al., 2004). The greatest biophysical 
difference between models comes from the lack of a pressure 
gradient in in vitro systems, which could allow passive diffu-
sion to be described simply by Fick's law. The existence of a 
hydrostatic pressure gradient in vivo/in situ permits a greater 
convective solvent effect that also affects and increases the 
convective/passive transport of the solute in accordance with 
the Navier-Stokes equations. This also contributes to a greater 
passive diffusion rate in vivo compared with in vitro experi-
ments. Although speculative, differences between the K m and 
V max measured in vitro/human and in vivo/mouse models </p>

<p>could possibly be linked to interspecies differences and expres-
sion levels, respectively. Better molecular tools are needed to 
understand the differences between models in this polyspe-
cific, high-capacity, carrier-mediated system. 
Our studies suggest that P-gp is not involved but reveal a 
carrier-mediated system that favors the influx of cocaine at the 
BBB, which could result from its ability to interact with an SLC 
transporter. The lack of in vitro or in vivo inhibition by known 
transporter inhibitors and the lack of differences in Oct1,2-
knockout mice suggest that at least Octs, Mate, and Octn are 
not likely to be involved in the active handling of cocaine in 
these models. The diverse chemical or biochemical approaches 
used in in vitro and in vivo protocols altered the transport of 
cocaine at the BBB in a way that suggests the presence of a 
sodium-independent cocaine/proton-antiporter with features 
similar to those found for nicotine, diphenhydramine, tramadol, 
and clonidine transport at the mouse BBB (Andre et al., 2009; 
Cisternino et al., 2013). A transporter with similar biochemi-
cal features has also been found in some rodent BBB cell lines, 
where it transports oxycodone, diphenhydramine, and codeine 
(Okura et al., 2008; Fischer et al., 2010; Sadiq et al., 2011). The 
trans-stimulation of cocaine transport in hCMEC/D3 cells by 
nicotine, diphenhydramine, MDMA, or MDPV suggests that they 
share the same transporter. Interestingly, an analogous MDMA/ 
proton-antiporter, which interacts with some other ampheta-
mines, has also been functionally characterized in Caco-2 cells 
(Kuwayama et al., 2008). The lack of a trans-stimulation effect of 
benzoylecgonine could also indicate that it is not a substrate, in 
accordance with certain studies showing that benzoylecgonine 
has no significant brain uptake (Gatley et al., 1994; Chow et al., 
2001). To obtain more information on the chemical structures 
able to interact with this transporter, we performed cis-inhibi-
tion experiments with substrate-related compounds that shared 
a similar DAT and with other pharmacological substances tar-
geting the CNS, such as opioids, diphenhydramine, and nicotine. 
Compounds like heroin, diphenhydramine, or imipramine were 
shown in vitro to exhibit a high potency of inhibition. In the 
smaller set of compounds tested in vivo, diphenhydramine was 
shown to be the strongest. However, the concentration needed 
to significantly inhibit cocaine transport precluded any poten-
tial for drug-drug interactions in vivo. The inhibitory ability of </p>

<p>Figure 5. Effects of changes in the vascular perfusion medium pH e , alteration of the BBB pH i , and sodium dependency of [ 3 H]-cocaine transport at the BBB in Swiss mice. </p>

<p>a, Effects of the Krebs-carbonate perfusion buffer at a pH e of 5.40, 6.40, or 7.40 on [ 3 H]-cocaine brain transport (Kin; µL/sec/g), with (black column) or without (white </p>

<p>column) co-perfusion with unlabeled cocaine (10 mM), measured by in situ mouse brain perfusion for 60 seconds. Data represent means ± SD (n = 4 mice). * P &lt; 0.05, ** </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.01, *** P &lt; 0.001 compared with the pH 5.4 group; + P &lt; 0.05, +++ P &lt; 0.001 for comparison (Student t test) between with and without unlabeled cocaine at the same </p>

<p>pH; and ### P &lt; 0.001 for a comparison of pH 6.40 and 7.40 without unlabeled cocaine. b, Effects of altering pH i (white columns) and removing sodium (grey column). </p>

<p>The vascular perfusion media were Krebs-carbonate buffer plus NH 4 Cl (30 mM; "NH 4 Cl pulse"), carbonate-free HEPES-buffered solution, and "mannitol" (sodium-free </p>

<p>and chloride-free) Krebs-carbonate buffer to alter pH i (white columns). The effect of Na + -free perfusion buffer (pH e 7.40) was studied by replacing sodium with lithium 
(Li + ; grey column). Data represent means ± SD of 4 to 7 animals. * P &lt; 0.05, ** P &lt; 0.01, *** P &lt; 0.001 compared with the control group. </p>

<p>Chapy et al. | 9 </p>

<p>several of these compounds suggests, however, that this trans-
porter interacts with specific chemical features but with differ-
ent potencies within the same chemical family, as illustrated by 
the slight inhibitory potency of benzoylecgonine in vitro and in 
vivo. The methoxy moiety missing only in benzoylecgonine and 
ecgonine compared with the other cocaine-related structures 
could represent a critical chemical moiety in this recognition 
and inhibition. The quite wide chemical diversity of interacting 
compounds suggests that computational chemical approaches 
with a wider range of structures could better assess the critical 
chemical moieties involved in such interactions. 
Neurobiological studies have recently confirmed that the 
BBB transport rate of drugs of abuse like nicotine, morphine, 
or cocaine is a critical factor that affects the neurobehavioral 
plasticity involved in addiction (Samaha and Robinson, 2005; 
Minogianis et al., 2013; Seleman et al., 2014). A higher rate of 
cocaine brain delivery is associated with a greater risk of addic-
tion in rodents (Minogianis et al., 2013). Positron emission 
tomography (PET) studies have also shown that the pharma-
cokinetic profiles of drugs of abuse like nicotine and cocaine, 
and in particular the speed/rate at which drugs enter the human 
brain, are crucial for their reward effects (Volkow et al., 2012). 
Indeed, these PET studies have shown that the rate of cocaine 
entry into the brain is the key factor associated with the sub-
jective "high" effect rather than the overall presence or extent 
of drug distribution into the brain (Volkow et al., 1997a, 1997b, 
2000). Interestingly, some differences in pharmacokinetics and 
cocaine conditioning have been shown depending on the strain 
of mice used and suggest that the DAB strain is more resist-
ant to cocaine conditioning in the place preference paradigm 
(Niculescu et al., 2005; Eisener-Dorman et al., 2011). However, 
our experiments did not reveal a difference in cocaine transport 
at the BBB of DAB mice, suggesting that such cocaine condition-
ing differences are more likely linked to a neural mechanism 
(Eisener-Dorman et al., 2011). Remarkably, a clinical PET study 
performed in cocaine abusers abstinent for 3 months (detoxifi-
cation unit) and who were defined by a history of cocaine use of 
&gt;4 g/wk of snorting and/or crack for at least 6 months has shown 
a decreased brain uptake of [ 11 C]-cocaine without any change for 
DAT availability (Volkow et al., 1996). In light of our results, this 
decrease in BBB cocaine uptake in recent cocaine abusers could 
be related to decreased activity of this cocaine transporter, pos-
sibly representing an endothelial cell-related brain mechanism 
involved in tolerance. 
In conclusion, cocaine transport at the mouse BBB involves 
a proton-antiporter flux that is quantitatively much more 
important than its passive diffusion. This carrier-mediated sys-
tem could be responsible for the faster uptake of cocaine by 
the brain, which in turn may be involved in high risk of addic-
tion. Although the CNS effects of cocaine have been shown to 
be dependent on its rate of access to its CNS biological targets, 
which depends on its route of administration, our study adds 
a new rate-regulatory component within the BBB. The cocaine/ 
proton-antiporter could be a new pharmacological target whose 
inhibition could be used to limit drug effects and the risk of 
relapse. The knowledge of its molecular identity is thus critical 
to exploit this potential. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Dr. A. H. Schinkel for supplying the knockout mice, Dr. 
H. Galons and Dr. H. Chen for generously supplying MDMA and 
MDPV, and Novartis for generously supplying PSC833. We thank 
Dr. S. Rasika at Gap-Junction.com for editing the English text. </p>

<p>We also thank the Paris Descartes University foundation and 
Servier Laboratories for the financial support granted to Hélène 
Chapy. </p>

<p>Statement of Interest </p>

<p>None. </p>







</text></tei>