<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4632933" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: This study evaluated the efficacy and safety of irinotecan/cisplatin 
(IP) and etoposide/cisplatin (EP) in extensive-stage small cell lung cancer (ES-
SCLC) and the distribution of uridine diphosphate glucuronosyltransferase 
(UGT1A1). The relationship between UGT1A1 genotypes and patient outcomes 
was also assessed. 
Method: Patients with untreated ES-SCLC were randomly assigned to receive either 
IP or EP, and blood specimens were collected to test the genotypes of UGT1A1*28 
and UGT1A1*6. The association of efficacy and toxicity of an IP regimen with 
UGT1A1 genotype was analyzed. 
Results: Of the 62 patients enrolled from three institutions, 30 patients were in the 
IP and 32 patients were in the EP arms, respectively. Disease control rates with IP and 
EP were 83.3% and 71.9%, respectively (P = 0.043). Median progression-free sur-
vival for IP and EP were both six months. Median overall survival for IP and EP were 
18.1 and 15.8 months respectively, without significant difference. Grade 3-4 throm-
bocytopenia was more common with EP (18.8% vs. 6.7%; P = 0.035), while the inci-
dence of diarrhea was higher with IP (70% vs. 15.6%; P = 0.008). The incidence of 
grade 1-4 late-onset diarrhea of wild-type, heterozygous, and homozygous 
UGT1A1*28 were 65.0%, 85.7%, and 66.7%, respectively (P = 0.037). UGT1A1*28 
polymorphisms, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status, and 
chemotherapy cycles were essential factors affecting grade 1-4 late-onset diarrhea in 
logistic regression analysis. 
Conclusions: The efficacy of the IP regimen was similar to the EP regimen for 
untreated ES-SCLC. UGT1A1 polymorphisms were associated with late-onset diar-
rhea; however, there was no influence on efficacy. </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Lung cancer is the most commonly diagnosed cancer in 
China with an estimated 610 000 new cases in 2010. 
1 Small-
cell lung cancer (SCLC) now accounts for 10-15% of all 
newly diagnosed lung cancer cases, and 60-70% of patients 
present with extensive stage (ES). 
2 Over the past 20 years, 
standard therapy for most patients with ES-SCLC has 
been either carboplatin or cisplatin in combination with 
etoposide. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>In 2002, Japanese investigators reported superior results 
with the topoisomerase I inhibitor irinotecan combined with 
cisplatin (IP) compared with standard therapy with 
etoposide plus cisplatin (EP) in a randomized phase III trial 
comprising 154 patients with ES-SCLC. 
4 Prolonged median 
overall survival (OS) (12.8 vs. 9.4 months; P = 0.002) and a 
non-significantly higher two-year survival rate of 19.5% 
versus 5.2% were observed in the IP treatment arm compared 
with the EP arm. Patients in the EP arm experienced 
significantly higher rates of grade 3/4 neutropenia and </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer ISSN 1759-7706 </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 6 (2015) 785-791 
© 2015 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>

<p>785 </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, 
provided the original work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes. </p>

<p>thrombocytopenia, but lower rates of grade 3/4 diarrhea than 
those in the IP arm. However, two subsequent large phase III 
trials performed in the United States (US) comparing IP with 
EP failed to show a significant difference in response rate or 
OS between the regimens. 
5,6 Moreover, grade 3/4 hematologi-
cal toxic effects were more frequent in both EP and IP arms in 
Japanese compared to Western patients. 
7 It is possible that the 
differences in efficacy and toxicity in these randomized trials 
may partly be because the polymorphisms of genes involved 
in the metabolism or transport of chemotherapy vary among 
ethnic populations. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>The present study was designed to compare the efficacy of 
EP and IP in untreated patients with ES-SCLC in a multi-
center setting. Additionally, we sought to explore the dis-
tribution of uridine diphosphate glucuronosyltransferase 
(UGT1A1) polymorphisms and to find out the relationship 
between UGT1A1 genotypes and patient outcomes, as well as 
incidence of diarrhea after chemotherapy. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Patient selection </p>

<p>From April 2010 to December 2012, a consecutive case series 
of 62 patients with ES-SCLC were enrolled in this study 
(Table 1). Patients had cytologically or histologically con-
firmed SCLC. ES disease was defined as extrathoracic meta-
static disease, malignant pleural effusion, bilateral or 
contralateral supraclavicular lymph node metastasis, or con-
tralateral hilar lymph node metastasis. Eligibility criteria 
included: Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) 
performance status (PS) of 0-2; a life expectancy of at least 
three months; measurable lesions; age 18-70 years; adequate </p>

<p>hematologic function (neutrophil count ≥ 2.0 × 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L, plate-
let count ≥ 100 × 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L, hemoglobin ≥ 90 g/L); and no severe 
hepatic or renal dysfunction (a bilirubine ≤ 1.5 × upper limit 
of normal [UNL] and creatinine, urea nitrogen ≤UNL, 
ALT,AST,ALP ≤ 2.5 × UNL or ALT,AST ≤ 5 × UNL if liver 
metastases were present or ALP ≤ 10 × UNL if bone metasta-
ses). Patients with central nervous system metastases were eli-
gible if they were asymptomatic and it had been a minimum 
of four weeks since treatment. Newly diagnosed and relapsed 
or metastases after radiotherapy or surgery were permitted if 
it had been at least six months since adjuvant chemotherapy 
had been administered. 
The exclusion criteria were: infection; myocardial infarc-
tion within the preceding three months; symptomatic brain 
metastases; administration of radiotherapy less than four 
weeks previous; and pregnancy or breast-feeding. 
The ethics committees of CAMS &amp; PUMC, Chinese Peo-
ple's Liberation Army General Hospital, and China-Japan 
Friendship Hospital, approved the study. All patients were 
required to provide written informed consent. </p>

<p>Treatment assignment and 
genotyping procedures </p>

<p>The IP regimen consisted of a maximum of six cycles of 
irinotecan 65 mg/m 
2 of body-surface area on days one and 
eight, and cisplatin 75 mg/m 
2 of body-surface area on day 
one. The EP regimen consisted of a maximum of six cycles of 
etoposide 100 mg/m 
2 of body-surface area from days one to 
three and cisplatin 75 mg/m 
2 of body-surface area on day 
one. Cycle length for the two arms was three weeks. If 
necessary, the acceptable dose adjustment was within 
±5% per investigator discretion. Both regimens required 
hydration and the administration of antiemetic drugs 
(5-hydroxytryptamin3 [5-HT3] receptor antagonist). 
Peripheral blood (2 mL) was obtained from each patient 
three times: before the first cycle, after the second cycle, and 
after the last cycle of chemotherapy. Blood was refrigerated at 
−20°C. Genomic DNA was directly extracted from blood 
specimens, and the UGT1A1*6 and UGT1A1*28 genotypes 
were amplified by polymerase chain reaction. Polymorphic 
regions were analyzed by a bi-direct sequencing method. </p>

<p>Evaluation </p>

<p>Pretreatment baseline evaluation included complete medical 
history and physical examination, complete blood cell count 
with classification, biochemical tests, and PS evaluation. 
Chest X-rays, chest or abdominal computed tomography 
(CT) scans, brain CT scans or magnetic resonance imaging, 
radionuclide bone scans, and any other diagnostic clinically 
indicated procedures were performed. Tumor response was 
evaluated according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid </p>

<p>Table 1 Patient characteristics </p>

<p>Parameter 
IP (n = 30) 
EP (n = 32) 
P value </p>

<p>Gender 
0.124 
Male 
21 (70%) 
26 (81.3%) 
Female 
9 (30%) 
6 (18.8%) 
Median age 
59 
57 
0.172 
ECOG 
0.079 
0 
3 (10%) 
2 (6.3%) 
1 
24 (80%) 
27 (84.4%) 
2 
3 (10%) 
3 (9.4%) 
Metastatic site 
0.386 
Lung 
8 (26.6%) 
10 (31.3%) 
Liver 
6 (20%) 
5 (15.6%) 
CNS 
2 (6.7%) 
3 (9.4%) 
Adrenal 
3 (10%) 
2 (6.2%) 
Bone 
9 (30%) 
7 (21.9%) 
Distant lymph node 
2 (6.7%) 
5 (15.6%) </p>

<p>CNS, central nervous system; ECOG, Eastern Cooperative Oncology 
Group; EP, etoposide plus cisplatin; IP, irinotecan plus cisplatin. </p>

<p>Irinotecan for small cell lung cancer 
Y. Shi et al. </p>



<p>Thoracic Cancer 6 (2015) 785-791 
© 2015 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>

<p>Tumors. 
8 Objective response rate (ORR) was calculated as the 
ratio of the number of patients who achieved complete 
response (CR) or partial response (PR) and the total number 
of patients enrolled. Disease control rate (DCR) was calcu-
lated as the percentage of patients who achieved CR, PR, and 
stable disease (SD). Assessment was conducted at least every 
two cycles. Safety was evaluated using treatment-emergent 
adverse events (AEs) graded according to National Cancer 
Institute-Common Toxicity Criteria (version 3.0). All 
patients were counseled about the importance of early recog-
nition and treatment of diarrhea. OS was measured as the 
date of treatment to the date of death or the date of the most 
recent follow-up. Progression-free survival (PFS) was mea-
sured as the date of treatment to the date of the first observa-
tion of disease progression or the date of death from any 
cause if there had been no progression. After all cycles of 
treatment, routine follow-up by imaging analysis was per-
formed every two months until the date of death. The last 
follow-up date was 30 December 2012. Three patients were 
lost to follow-up; the follow-up rate was 95.2%. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>This was a multicenter, open-label, randomized, prospective 
phase II study. The primary objective of the study was to 
compare PFS associated with the use of IP and EP for the 
treatment of patients with previously untreated ES-SCLC. 
Secondary objectives were to compare the antitumor efficacy 
as assessed by ORR and OS, and to evaluate the safety and tol-
erability of each regimen. All calculations and statistical 
analyses were conducted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">17.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, 
IL, USA). Comparisons of analyzed parameters between 
groups were performed with the chi-square test or Fisher's 
exact test for proportional variables. Survival data were ana-
lyzed using the Kaplan-Meier method, and survival curves 
were compared using the log-rank test. Multivariable analysis 
of the associations between diarrhea and UGT1A1 genotype 
in the IP arm were assessed with logistic regression. Two sided 
values of P &lt; 0.05 were considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Response and survival </p>

<p>In the IP arm, a total of 128 cycles were administered with an 
average of 4.3 cycles: one cycle in one patient, two cycles in 
four, three in two, four in 10, five in five, and six in eight. In the 
EP arm, a total of 147 cycles were administered with an 
average of 4.6 cycles: two cycles in four patients, three cycles in 
zero, four in 14, five in three, and six in 12. There was no sig-
nificant difference between the two groups (P = 0.064). ORR 
was 70% in the IP arm and 65.6% in the EP arm without sig-
nificant difference (P = 0.056). However, DCR in the IP arm </p>

<p>was 83.3%, significantly higher than in the EP arm (71.9%; 
P = 0.043, Table 2). With a median follow-up of 13.8 months, 
the median OS for all patients was 16.6 months. There was no 
statistical difference in PFS (Fig 1) or OS (Fig 2) between the 
two arms. The median OS and PFS rates in the IP arm were 
18.1 and six months, respectively, while in the EP arm the 
medians were 15.8 and six months, respectively. </p>

<p>Toxicity </p>

<p>The most common adverse effects were hematologic and 
gastrointestinal toxicities. The incidence of grade 1-4 </p>

<p>Table 2 Treatment administration and efficacy in both EP and IP arms </p>

<p>Parameter 
IP (n = 30) 
EP (n = 32) 
P value </p>

<p>Cycles 
0.064 
1 
1 (3.3%) 
0 
2 
4 (13.3%) 
4 (12.5%) 
3 
2 (6.7%) 
0 
4 
10 (33.3%) 
13 (40.6%) 
5 
5 (16.7%) 
3 (9.4%) 
6 
8 (26.7%) 
12 (37.5%) 
Average cycles 
4.3 
4.6 
Response 
CR 
2 (6.7%) 
0 
PR 
19 (63.3%) 
21 (65.6%) 
SD 
4 (13.3%) 
2 (6.3%) 
PD 
5 (16.7%) 
9 (28.1%) 
ORR (CR+PR) 
21 (70%) 
21 (65.6%) 
0.056 
DCR (CR+PR+SD) 
25 (83.3%) 
23 (71.9%) 
0.043 </p>

<p>CR, complete response; DCR: disease control rate; EP, etoposide plus 
cisplatin; IP, irinotecan plus cisplatin; ORR: overall response rate; PD, pro-
gressive disease; PR, partial response; SD, stable disease. </p>

<p>Survival Functions </p>

<p>Progression-free survival (months) </p>

<p>Cumulative survival </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0 
5 
1 0 </p>

<p>EP arm </p>

<p>IP arm </p>

<p>15 
20 
30 
25 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Progression-free survival of patients with extensive-stage small 
cell lung cancer treated with irinotecan plus cisplatin (IP) and etoposide 
plus cisplatin (EP). 
, 1 IP; 
, 2 EP; , 1-censored; , 2-censored. </p>

<p>Y. Shi et al. 
Irinotecan for small cell lung cancer </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 6 (2015) 785-791 
© 2015 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>



<p>neutropenia, leukocytopenia, and anemia did not differ sig-
nificantly between the two groups. In the IP arm, the occur-
rence of grade 3-4 thrombocytopenia was 6.7% and 18.8% 
(P = 0.035) in the IP and EP arms, respectively. However, 
grade 3-4 diarrhea was more frequent in the IP than in the EP 
arm (P = 0.008). The details are shown in Table 3. </p>

<p>Uridine diphosphate 
glucuronosyltransferase (UGT1A1) 
polymorphisms </p>

<p>Uridine diphosphate glucuronosyltransferase is a key enzyme 
involved in the complex metabolism of irinotecan. </p>

<p>UGT1A1*28 is a common allele with seven TA repeats in the 
promoter of UGT1A1, compared with the wild-type allele 
which has six repeats. UGT1A1*28 could be classified into 
three groups: wild-type (TA6/6), heterozygous (TA6/7), and 
homozygous (TA7/7). Another polymorphism, UGT1A1*6, 
characterized by replacing a single nucleotide in exon1 of 
UGT1A1, could be classified into wild-type (GG), heterozy-
gous (GA), and homozygous (AA). According to the fre-
quency of mutation alleles, including both UGT1A1*6 and 
UGT1A1*28, genotypes could be classified into wild-type, 
single, and double mutations. Allele frequency was tested to 
conform to the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (Table 4). </p>

<p>UGT1A1 polymorphisms and 
late-onset diarrhea </p>

<p>The incidence of grade 1-4 late-onset diarrhea of wild-type, 
heterozygous, and homozygous UGT1A1*28 were 65.0%, 
85.7%, and 66.7%, respectively, with statistical difference 
(P = 0.037). However, the incidence of grade 3-4 late-onset 
diarrhea was 10.0%, 14.3%, and 66.7% (P = 0.087), respec-
tively. There was no significant difference in UGT1A1*6 allele 
and the incidence of grade 1-4 or 3-4 late-onset diarrhea. </p>

<p>Table 3 Toxicity and side effects </p>

<p>Toxicity type </p>

<p>IP (n = 30) 
EP (n = 32) </p>

<p>P value 
Grade1-2 
Grade3-4 (%) 
Grade1-2 
Grade3-4 (%) </p>

<p>Neutropenia 
10 
16 (53.3) 
8 
23 (71.9) 
0.057 
Leukopenia 
13 
13 (43.3) 
12 
17 (53.1) 
0.271 
Anemia 
18 
9 (30.0) 
18 
10 (31.3) 
0.114 
Thrombocytopenia 
5 
2 (6.7) 
16 
6 (18.8) 
0.035 
Nausea/vomiting 
23 
4 (13.3) 
23 
3 (9.4) 
0.237 
Diarrhea 
16 
5 (16.7) 
5 
0 (0.0) 
0.008 
Constipation 
8 
3 (10.0) 
7 
3 (9.4) 
0.167 
Infection 
5 
1 (3.3) 
2 
1 (3.1) 
0.076 
Alopecia 
3 
0 (0.0) 
4 
0 (0) 
0.107 
Fatigue 
24 
3 (10.0) 
23 
4 (12.5) 
0.236 
Hepatic dysfunction 
12 
1 (3.3) 
6 
1 (3.1) 
0.191 </p>

<p>EP, etoposide plus cisplatin; IP, irinotecan plus cisplatin. </p>

<p>Survival Functions </p>

<p>Overall survival (months) </p>

<p>Cumulative survival </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.0 
10.0 </p>

<p>EP arm </p>

<p>IP arm </p>

<p>20.0 
30.0 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Overall survival of patients with extensive-stage small cell lung 
cancer treated with irinotecan plus cisplatin (IP) and etoposide plus 
cisplatin (EP). 
, 1 IP; 
, 2 EP; , 1-censored; , 2-censored. </p>

<p>Table 4 Distribution of UGT1A1 of patients treated with IP (n = 30) </p>

<p>Genotype </p>

<p>Genotype 
n (%) 
UGT1A1*28 (n) 
UGT1A1*6 (n) </p>

<p>TA6/6 (20) 
G/G (21) 
Wild-type 
12 (40.0) 
TA6/6 (20) 
A/G (8) 
Single mutation 
7 (23.4) 
TA6/7 (7) 
G/G (21) 
Singe mutation 
6 (20.0) 
TA6/7 (7) 
A/G (8) 
Double mutation 
1 (3.3) 
TA7/7 (3) 
G/G (21) 
Double mutation 
3 (10.0) 
TA6/6 (20) 
A/A (1) 
Double mutation 
1 (3.3) </p>

<p>IP, irinotecan plus cisplatin; UGT1A1, uridine diphosphate 
glucuronosyltransferase. </p>

<p>Irinotecan for small cell lung cancer 
Y. Shi et al. </p>



<p>Thoracic Cancer 6 (2015) 785-791 
© 2015 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>

<p>According to the frequency of mutation alleles for both 
UGT1A1*28 and UGT1A1*6, the incidence of grade 1-4 late-
onset diarrhea of wild-type, single, and double mutation were 
66.7%, 76.9%, and 75.0% (P = 0.267), respectively, whereas 
grade 3-4 were 8.3%, 15.4%, and 50.0% (P = 0.075), respec-
tively. Details are summarized in Table 5. </p>

<p>Factors affecting the late-onset diarrhea </p>

<p>Uridine diphosphate glucuronosyltransferase*28 genotype, 
ECOG PS, and chemotherapy cycles were the essential factors 
affecting grade 1-4 late-onset diarrhea in logistic regression 
analysis. With respect to the UGT1A1 genotype, a significant 
association was observed between the UGT1A1*28 allele and 
late-onset diarrhea (hazard ratio 5.48, 95% confidence inter-
val 1.256-9.311; P = 0.028). Patients with an ECOG PS of 2 
had a higher risk of late-onset diarrhea than those with a PS of 
0-1 (P = 0.003). Meanwhile, a significant association was 
observed between patients treated with less than four cycles 
and four or more cycles (P = 0.031). Details are summarized 
in Table 6. </p>

<p>UGT1A1 polymorphisms and efficacy </p>

<p>None of the genotypes were associated with better efficacy. 
There was no significant difference among wild-type, hetero-</p>

<p>zygous, and homozygous UGT1A1*28 (P = 0.628) or 
UGT1A1*6. No difference was observed in the mutation 
allele frequency of UGT1A1*28 and UGT1A1*6 (P = 0.336), 
as shown in Table 7. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The current standard chemotherapy for ES-SCLC is an EP or 
IP regimen. Noda et al. first reported a phase III study 
(JCOG9511) of an IP compared with an EP regimen in 154 
patients with ES-SCLC. During interim analysis, they found 
significant differences in OS and a toxicity profile in favor of 
the IP arm and, thus, prematurely closed the study. However, 
large randomized trials conducted in North America, includ-
ing the Southwest Oncology Group trial (SWOG S0124) 
using almost the same eligibility criteria and identical </p>

<p>Table 5 Relationship between UGT1A1 polymorphisms and late-onset diarrhea of patients treated with IP (n = 30) </p>

<p>Genotype 
n </p>

<p>Late-onset diarrhea </p>

<p>Grade 1-4 (%) 
P 
Grade 3-4 (%) 
P </p>

<p>UGT1A1*28 
0.037 
0.087 
TA6/6 
20 
13 (65.0) 
2 (10.0) 
TA6/7 
7 
6 (85.7) 
1 (14.3) 
TA7/7 
3 
2 (66.7) 
2 (66.7) 
UGT1A1*6 
0.348 
0.083 
G/G 
21 
15 (71.4) 
1 (4.8) 
A/G 
8 
5 (62.5) 
3 (37.5) 
A/A 
1 
1 (100.0) 
1 (100.0) 
UGT1A1*6 and GT1A1*28 
0.267 
0.075 
Wild-type 
12 
8 (66.7) 
1 (8.3) 
Single mutation 
13 
10 (76.9) 
2 (15.4) 
Double mutation 
4 
3 (75.0) 
2 (50.0) </p>

<p>IP, irinotecan plus cisplatin; UGT1A1, uridine diphosphate glucuronosyltransferase. </p>

<p>Table 6 Multivariable analysis of factors affecting grade 3-4 late-onset 
diarrhea </p>

<p>Factors 
HR (95%CI) 
P </p>

<p>UGT1A1*28 
5.848 (1.256-9.311) 
0.028 
ECOG: 0-1 versus 2 
8.726 (3.269-30.378) 
0.003 
Cycles: &lt; 4 versus ≥ 4 
3.264 (1.543-8.326) 
0.031 </p>

<p>CI, confidence interval; ECOG, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group; HR, 
hazard ratio; UGT1A1, uridine diphosphate glucuronosyltransferase. </p>

<p>Table 7 Relationship between UGT1A1 polymorphisms and efficacy of 
patients treated with IP (n = 30) </p>

<p>Genotype 
n 
RR (%) 
P </p>

<p>UGT1A1*28 
0.628 
TA6/6 
20 
14 (70.0) 
TA6/7 
7 
5 (71.4) 
TA7/7 
3 
2 (66.7) 
UGT1A1*6 
0.352 
G/G 
21 
14 (66.7) 
A/G 
8 
6 (75.0) 
A/A 
1 
1 (100.0) 
UGT1A1*6 and UGT1A1*28 
0.336 
Wild-type 
12 
8 (66.7) 
Single mutation 
13 
10 (76.9) 
Double mutation 
4 
3 (75.0) </p>

<p>UGT1A1*28: TA6/6, wild-type; TA6/7, heterozygous; TA7/7, homozy-
gous; UGT1A1*6: GG, wild-type; GA, heterozygous; AA, homozygous. 
IP, irinotecan plus cisplatin; RR, response rate; UGT1A1, uridine diphos-
phate glucuronosyltransferase. </p>

<p>Y. Shi et al. 
Irinotecan for small cell lung cancer </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 6 (2015) 785-791 
© 2015 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>



<p>treatment regimens as JCOG9511, did not confirm the 
JCOG9511 results. Despite several negative trials, two meta-
analyses using non-individual patient data showed a signifi-
cant survival improvement with IP compared with EP in 
patients with ES-SCLC. </p>

<p>9,10 </p>

<p>This multicenter, phase II, randomized study did not reveal 
a statistically significant difference in OS and PFS between the 
IP and EP regimens; however, the DCR in the IP arm was 
83.3%, higher than the EP arm (71.9%; P = 0.043) and similar 
to JCOG9511 results. Non-hematological adverse events were 
much the same between the two groups, except the incidence 
of diarrhea was 70.0% in the IP arm and 15.6% in the EP arm 
(P = 0.008). However, the IP arm was associated with signifi-
cantly lower rates of grade 3-4 thrombocytopenia (P = 
0.035). Our results are consistent with previous trials, which 
reported that the IP regimen produced more non-
hematological toxicities and less hematological toxicities 
compared with the EP regimen. </p>

<p>4-7 </p>

<p>A comparative analysis of response rates and toxicities 
between the IP arms of JCOG9511 and SWOG S0124 suggests 
that pharmacogenomic factors may account for differences in 
the efficacy and toxicities seen in the two trials. 
7 In the IP 
arms, the incidence of grade 3-4 neutropenia was 65% in 
the JCOG 9511 trial and 34% in the SWOG S0124 trial 
(P &lt; 0.001). Many studies have indicated that SN38 
glucuronidation activity and irinotecan-induced toxicity are 
associated with UGT1A1*28, which generates a repeat poly-
morphism in the TATA box promoter of UGT1A1, demon-
strating a lower allele frequency in Asians compared with 
Caucasians. 
11 There is fairly strong evidence that individuals 
with the homozygote UGT1A1*28 genotype tend to have a 
higher prevalence of irinotecan-induced neutropenia. </p>

<p>12-14 </p>

<p>Ferraldeschi et al. observed an association between the 
UGT1A1*28 genotype and diarrhea; however, other studies 
have reported no statistically significant association. 
15-17 A 
meta-analysis reported that patients carrying UGT1A1*28 
alleles are at an increased risk of severe diarrhea, and this 
increased risk is only apparent in those who are administered 
medium or high doses of irinotecan. 
18 Moreover, there was a 
significant linear correlation between irinotecan doses and 
related odds ratios (ORs) of severe diarrhea; however, this 
association was only observed when comparing the risk of 
diarrhea between patients with a homozygous UGT1A1*28 
genotype and those carrying wild-type alleles. 
18 In the present 
study, the incidence of grade 1-4 diarrhea was related to 
UGT1A1*28 polymorphisms (P = 0.037); however the rela-
tionship of the severe diarrhea (grade 3-4) and UGT1A1*28 
polymorphisms was not observed. 
Another genotype, UGT1A1*6, characterized by replacing 
a single nucleotide in exon1 of UGT1A1, has been considered 
to be related to reduced SN38 glucuronidation activity and 
bears a higher allele frequency in Asians compared with Cau-
casians. 
17,19 Moreover, grade 3-4 neutropenia is significantly </p>

<p>more frequent in patients who have the UGT1A1*6 genotype, 
and the homozygosity for the UGT1A1*6 is associated with 
an increased risk of severe neutropenia in Asians. 
20 In a meta-
analysis of Asian patients, UGT1A1*6 polymorphisms 
increased the incidence of severe neutropenia in high/ 
medium and low doses of irinotecan. 
21 For severe diarrhea, 
the heterozygous variant of UGT1A1*6 showed no signifi-
cant risk, while the homozygous variant indicated a notable 
risk. 
21 However, our data did not support this theory, most 
likely because the sample of UGT1A1*6 cases in this study 
was too small. 
In 2005, UGT1A1*28 polymorphisms were taken into 
consideration by the US Food and Drug Administration 
(FDA) as predictors for evaluating the risk of irinotecan-
induced toxicity. However, a reduction in dosage might 
also be associated with reduced tumor response and/or 
increased morbidity. 
22 In 2009, the Evaluation of Genomic 
Applications in Practice and Prevention Working Group 
reported that routine UGT1A1 genotyping for guiding 
irinotecan dosing is not recommended. 
23 Definitive evidence 
of whether the UGT1A1*28 genotype is associated with 
clinical outcomes of irinotecan-based chemotherapy is not 
yet available to assist in a clinical setting. As for the correla-
tion between efficacy and the UGT1A1 genotype, we did not 
observe a significant difference in our study. Our result was 
consistent with Liu et al.'s meta-analysis, in which no asso-
ciation between UGT1A1*28 genotypes and IP response was 
found. 
24 However, the UGT1A1*28 allele showed significant 
or marginal association with poorer OS, especially in the low 
dose irinotecan subgroup of the homozygous model. 
Furthermore, the irinotecan dose also did not impact 
upon therapeutic response or PFS according to UGT1A1 
genotype. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>In conclusion, the present study failed to show a significant 
superiority in efficacy for the IP regimen compared with the 
standard of care EP for ES-SCLC. The UGT1A1 genotype has 
an influence on late-onset diarrhea, but there was no evidence 
of UGT1A1 having an impact on the efficacy of the IP 
regimen for SCLC. Phase III clinical trials are urgently 
required. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>This work was supported in part by grants from the National 
Key Technology Research and Development Program of 
the Ministry of Science and Technology of China 
(2014BAI09B01). Zhou Tao performed statistical analysis 
(Medical Department of Pfizer). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>No authors report any conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Irinotecan for small cell lung cancer 
Y. Shi et al. </p>



<p>Thoracic Cancer 6 (2015) 785-791 
© 2015 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>



<p>Y. Shi et al. 
Irinotecan for small cell lung cancer </p>

<p>Thoracic Cancer 6 (2015) 785-791 
© 2015 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>



</text></tei>