<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4852604" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Chronic subdural hematoma (CSDH) is one of the most 
common disorders in the field of neurosurgery. 2) The current 
understanding of the mechanism of development of CSDH 
is that damage to the bridging veins by minor head trauma 
results in a collection of hematomas in the subdural space. 15) 
Then, the hematomas form a vessel-rich outer membrane. 18,21) 
Fragility of this neovasculature leads to repeated micro-
bleeding and increases the permeability of the membrane, 
resulting in the development of CSDH. 2,3,13,14) The known 
risk factors of CSDH are trauma, old age, brain atrophy, al-
cohol abuse, seizure, coagulopathy, the use of anti-platelets, </p>

<p>and the use of anticoagulants. 7,10) In this study, we focused 
on the fact that some patients do not develop CSDH after 
head trauma and proceed through therapy without any com-
plications, while others need additional surgeries to treat 
CSDH. Assuming there are differences between the pa-
tients who develop CSDH and those who do not, we inves-
tigated the various known risk factors, along with the com-
puted tomographic findings at the time of the head injury. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>We conducted a survey of 277 patients who scored over 
13 on the Glasgow coma scale who received treatment at 
our institution after minor head trauma in the period from 
January 2012 to December 2013. Patients were enrolled pro-
spectively and their medical records were reviewed retro-
spectively. All the patients did not require surgery at the time 
of their arrival. During the follow-up period, the 20 patients 
who required surgery to treat CSDH were designated as the </p>

<p>Prediction of Chronic Subdural Hematoma in Minor 
Head Trauma Patients </p>

<p>Sang-Beom Han, MD, Seung-Won Choi, MD, Shi-Hun Song, MD, Jin-Young Youm, MD, 
Hyeon-Song Koh, MD, Seon-Hwan Kim, MD, and Hyon-Jo Kwon, MD </p>

<p>Department of Neurosurgery, School of Medicine, Chungnam National University, Daejeon, Korea </p>

<p>Objective: Chronic subdural hematoma (CSDH) is relatively common in neurosurgical field. However not all patients de-
velop CSDH after minor head trauma. In this study, we evaluate the risk factors of post-traumatic CSDH. 
Methods: Two-hundred and seventy-seven patients were enrolled and analyzed in this study from January 2012 to Decem-
ber 2013. Of those, 20 participants had minor head trauma developed CSDH afterward. We also included 257 patients with 
minor head trauma who did not develop CSDH during the same follow-up period as the control group. We investigated the 
risk factors related to the development of CSDH after minor head trauma. 
Results: Old age (p=0.014), preexisting diabetes mellitus (p=0.010), hypertension (p=0.026), history of cerebral infarction 
(p=0.035), antiplatelet agents (p=0.000), acute subdural hematoma in the convexity (p=0.000), encephalomalacia (p= 
0.029), and long distance between skull and brain parenchyma (p=0.000) were significantly correlated with the develop-
ment of CSDH after trauma. Multivariate analysis revealed that only the maximum distance between the skull and the cere-
bral parenchyma was the independent risk factor for the occurrence of CSDH (hazard ratio 2.55, p=0.000). 
Conclusion: We should consider the possibility of developing CSDH in the post-traumatic patients with the identified risk 
factors. </p>

<p>(Korean J Neurotrauma 2014;10(2):106-111) </p>

<p>KEY WORDS: Hematoma subdural chronic ㆍRisk factors ㆍCraniocerebral trauma. </p>

<p>Received: September 16, 2014 / Revised: October 13, 2014 
Accepted: October 15, 2014 
Address for correspondence: Seung-Won Choi, MD </p>

<p>Department of Neurosurgery, School of Medicine, Chungnam Na-
tional University, 282 Munhwa-ro, Jung-gu, Daejeon 301-721, Korea 
Tel: +82-42-280-7361, Fax: +82-42-280-7363 
E-mail: swchoi@cnu.ac.kr </p>

<p>CLINICAL ARTICLE </p>

<p>Korean J Neurotrauma 2014;10(2):106-111 </p>

<p>pISSN 2234-8999 / eISSN 2288-2243 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.13004/kjnt.2014.10.2.106 </p>

<p>online © ML Comm </p>

<p>Sang-Beom Han, et al. </p>

<p>http://www.kjnt.org 107 </p>

<p>patient group, while the remaining 257 patients who did not 
develop CSDH after minor head trauma and completed treat-
ment were selected as the control group. Head trauma, out 
of many other factors, was set as the controlled variable. Age, 
gender, and the history of diabetes mellitus (DM), hyper-
tension, cerebral infarction, cardiac disease, hematologic dis-
ease, and epilepsy were investigated as the factors contrib-
uting to progression of CSDH after minor trauma. The me-
dication history of antiplatelet and anticoagulant agents was 
also surveyed, as well as the smoking and drinking habits 
of subjects. The presence of acute subdural hematoma (AS-
DH) in the convexity, accompanying hemorrhage and en-
cephalomalacia, and the maximum distance from skull to </p>

<p>cerebral parenchyma (Figure 1) were investigated by exam-
ining the patients' initial computerized tomography (CT) 
scans. In our study, cardiac disease included valve disease, 
arrhythmia, and ischemic heart disease. The diseases that 
could cause coagulopathy, such as hematological malignan-
cies, were defined as hematologic disease. In cases where 
the patients' initial brain CT scans showed cerebral contu-
sion, subarachnoid hemorrhage, epidural hemorrhage, or 
intracerebral hemorrhage, we defined the finding as an ac-
companying hemorrhage. The statistical analysis was per-
formed using Window <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 20.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chi-
cago, IL, USA). Statistical analyses included chi-square test, 
Fisher's exact test and multivariate logistic regression anal-
ysis to assess the relationship between CSDH and various 
factors. Differences were considered statistically significant 
if the p value was less than 0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Demographic data, medical history, social history, and 
CT findings are summarized in Table 1. 
The number of patients enrolled in the study was 277, with 
an age range of 0 to 94 years, and a mean age of 53.9 years. 
The average age of the patient group was 67.5 years, while 
that of the control group was 52.9 years, showing that the 
patient group was statistically significantly older than the 
control group (p=0.014)(Figure 2). Thirteen male patients 
(65%) and 7 female patients (35%) were in the patient group, 
while 173 male patients (67.3%) and 84 female patients (37.7%) 
made up the control group with males contributing a little 
higher number in both groups, without a noticeable signifi-
cance in the gender difference (p=0.832). </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Analysis of factors related to the occurrence of chronic subdural hematoma </p>

<p>Factors 
Patient group (n=20) 
Control group (n=257) 
p value </p>

<p>Male/female (% male) 
13/7 (65.0%) 
173/84 (67.3%) 
0.832 </p>

<p>DM 
7 (35.0%) 
35 (13.6%) 
0.010 </p>

<p>Hypertension 
12 (60.0%) 
90 (35.0%) 
0.026 </p>

<p>Hx of CI 
3 (15.0%) 
11 (4.3%) 
0.035 </p>

<p>Cardiac disease 
4 (20.0%) 
29 (11.3%) 
0.246 </p>

<p>Hematologic disease 
0 (0%) 
3 (1.2%) 
0.627 </p>

<p>Epilepsy 
0 (0%) 
4 (1.6%) 
0.547 </p>

<p>Antiplatelet agent 
10 (50.0%) 
45 (17.5%) 
0.000 </p>

<p>Anticoagulant agent 
1 (5.0%) 
11 (4.3%) 
0.879 </p>

<p>Smoking 
3 (15.0%) 
71 (27.6%) 
0.219 </p>

<p>Alcohol 
5 (25.0%) 
114 (44.4%) 
0.092 </p>

<p>Convexity ASDH 
15 (75.0%) 
73 (28.4%) 
0.000 </p>

<p>Combined hemorrhages 
20 (100.0%) 
236 (91.8%) 
0.184 </p>

<p>Encephalomalacia 
4 (20.0%) 
17 (6.6%) 
0.029 </p>

<p>ASDH: acute subdural hematoma, DM: diabetic mellitus, Hx of CI: history of cerebral infarction </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Brain computed tomography scans showing how to 
measure the maximal distance between the skull and brain pa-
renchyma (arrow). </p>



<p>Prediction of Chronic Subdural Hematoma in Minor Head Trauma </p>

<p>In the patient group, there were 7 (35%) patients with DM 
and 12 (65%) patients with hypertension, while there were 
35 (13.6%) patients with DM and 90 (35.0%) patients with 
hypertension in the control group. The presence of DM or 
hypertension showed a statistical significance between 
groups (p=0.010, p=0.026). 
The numbers of the patients with a history of cerebral in-
farction were 3 (15%) in the patient group and 11 (4.3%) in 
the control group, which was also statistically significant 
(p=0.035). 
With regards to medication history, the administration of 
antiplatelet agents presented a statistically significant dif-
ference between the two groups (p=0.000); 10 in the patient 
group (50%), 45 in the control group (17.5%). 
The brain CT scans taken on the time of admission were 
examined. A higher percentage of subjects in the patient 
group (15 patients, 75%) had ASDH in the convexity from 
the trauma than that of patients in the control group (78 pa-
tients, 28.4%) at a level of statistical significance (p=0.000). 
Four subjects in the patient group (20%) had encephalo-
malacia, while 17 patients (6.6%) in the control group had 
the affliction with statistically significant (p=0.029). 
The brain CT scans taken right after the trauma were used 
to measure the maximum distance between the skull and 
the cerebral parenchyma. The average maximum distance 
of the patient group (7.15 mm) was much longer than that of </p>

<p>the control group (1.35 mm) and the difference was statisti-
cally significant (p=0.000)(Figure 3). The receiver operat-
ing characteristic curve was drawn by plotting the occur-
rence of CSDH according to the maximum distance between 
the skull and the brain parenchyma. It was determined to 
be reliable test model due to its large area under the curve. 
We found that the distance between the skull and parenchy-
ma as 3.52 mm can be a cutoff value, yielding 90.0% sensi-
tivity and 90.7% specificity (Figure 4). 
The multivariate logistic regression analysis was used to 
verify the correlation between the statistically significant 
factors and CSDH occurrence. As a result, only the maxi-
mum distance between the skull and the cerebral parenchy-
ma showed a reliable correlation with CSDH occurrence (p= 
0.000), while the other factors failed to show any remarkable 
statistical significance (Table 2). 
Each group was classified according to the type of trau-
ma. Slipping down stood out as the most common cause of 
trauma but with no statistical significance between the two 
groups (p=0.236)(Table 3). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Unlike other studies, 7,10) this study demonstrates that the 
presence of DM or hypertension significantly influences 
the occurrence of CSDH after minor head trauma. On the </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Age </p>

<p>p=0.014 </p>

<p>Patient group </p>

<p>Control group </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Bar graph showing the average age between two 
groups. Average age of the patient group is significantly older 
than that of the control group (p=0.014). </p>

<p>Patient group </p>

<p>Control group </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>mm </p>

<p>p=0.000 </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Bar graph shows the average maximal distance be-
tween skull and brain parenchyma of the two groups. The patient 
group had a statistically significant longer distance than control 
group (p=0.000). </p>

<p>Sang-Beom Han, et al. </p>

<p>http://www.kjnt.org 109 </p>

<p>contrary, a study conducted by Yamamoto et al. 22) reported 
that the hyperglycemia in DM patients leads to the hyper-
viscosity of blood and increases the intravascular osmotic 
pressure, resulting in a reduced probability of CSDH recur. 
However, considering the fact that one of the major compli-
cations of DM is capillary vasculopathy such as retinal hem-
orrhage, and the fact that micro-bleedings and the exuda-
tion of immature capillaries surrounding the CSDH outer 
membrane are the major mechanisms in developing CSDH, 
the capillary vasculopathy in DM patients affects the im-
mature capillaries around the outer membrane of the sub-
dural hematoma after head trauma, and consequently re-
sults in the development CSDH. 20) 
Also, in the case of patients with hypertension, higher 
blood pressures put more pressure on the immature capil-
laries around the outer membrane have to endure, increas-
ing the probability of repeated capillary injuries and micro-
bleedings. Even though there are few preexisting studies on 
the impact of hypertension on the CSDH, 8) additional stud-
ies need to be performed to confirm a correlation between 
hypertension and CSDH. 
It is known that the old age is associated with CSDH, as 
there is a higher CSDH prevalence rate among the elder-
ly. 1,5,6) The fragility of the bridging veins and accompany-</p>

<p>ing cerebral atrophy from the aging process are considered 
as the major factors causing the increased prevalence. 5,19) As 
aging progresses, the volume of the cerebral parenchyma 
shrinks, resulting in an increase of the subdural space be-
tween the skull and the cerebral parenchyma. The enlarged 
subdural space enables the brain to move around the skull 
while patient ambulates, and the vulnerable bridging veins 
can be injured easily with a minor head trauma. 9,12,23) The 
correlation between the occurrence of CSDH and old age 
was also confirmed in this study, and there was a tendency 
to develop post-traumatic CSDH among the patients with 
larger subdural spaces due to cerebral atrophy. The reason 
why the history of cerebral infarction and the presence of 
encephalomalacia are correlated with CSDH occurrence in 
this study can be explained by considering the same mech-
anism described above. The presence of encephalomalacia 
after the brain injury, such as cerebral infarction, results in 
the reduction of brain parenchyma volume, which enlarges 
the subdural space between the skull and brain parenchy-
ma, and consequently results in higher tendency of post-trau-
matic CSDH. 16) 
A study from Lindvall and Koskinen, 10) which analyzed 
71 patients with CSDH concluded that the administration 
of antiplatelet or anticoagulation agents contributed a sig-
nificant difference in CSDH occurrence in the patients with-
out trauma compared to the patients with trauma. Another </p>

<p>1.000 </p>

<p>0.800 </p>

<p>0.600 </p>

<p>0.400 </p>

<p>0.200 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>Sensitivity </p>

<p>0.000 
0.200 
0.400 
0.600 
0.800 
1.000 </p>

<p>1-specificity </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve of the 
maximal distance between the skull and brain parenchyme. In a 
ROC curve, the true positive rate (sensitivity) is plotted against the 
false positive rate (1-specificity) for different cut-off points of a pa-
rameter. In this graph, 3.52 mm is the cutoff value of 90.0% sen-
sitivity and 90.7% specificity. The area under the ROC curve is a 
measurement of how well a parameter can distinguish between 
two groups. Here, the maximal depth between the skull and brain 
parenchyma is a good parameter for distinguishing between the 
two groups. </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Multivariate logistic regression analysis of factors af-
fecting the occurrence of chronic subdural hematoma </p>

<p>Factors 
Odds ratio 
p value </p>

<p>Age 
0.815 
0.807 </p>

<p>DM 
0.348 
0.244 </p>

<p>Hx of CI 
0.265 
0.625 </p>

<p>Antiplatelet agent 
1.719 
0.559 </p>

<p>Convexity ASDH 
0.630 
0.544 </p>

<p>Encephalomalacia 
1.608 
0.855 </p>

<p>Maximum distance 
2.550 
0.000 </p>

<p>ASDH: acute subdural hematoma, DM: diabetic mellitus, Hx 
of CI: history of cerebral infarction, Maximum distance: maxi-
mum distance between the skull and brain parenchyma </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Classification of trauma </p>

<p>Trauma 
Patient 
group (n=20) 
Control 
group (n=257) </p>

<p>Slip down 
11 (55%) 
106 (41.2%) </p>

<p>Fall down 
3 (15%) 
45 (17.5%) </p>

<p>Driver accident 
4 (20%) 
19 (7.4%) </p>

<p>Pedestrian accident 
1 (5%) 
43 (16.7%) </p>

<p>Hit by material 
0 (0%) 
18 (7%) </p>

<p>Violence 
0 (0%) 
3 (1.2%) </p>

<p>Unknown 
1 (5%) 
23 (8.9%) </p>

<p>No statistical significance between group (p value=0.236) </p>



<p>Prediction of Chronic Subdural Hematoma in Minor Head Trauma </p>

<p>study conducted by Reymond et al. 17) analyzing 198 patients 
with severe head trauma also reported that there was a sta-
tistical significance between the administration of anti-
platelet or anticoagulation agents in CSDH occurrence. 
Considering the analogous result in the preceding two stud-
ies, the same outcome was expected when analyzing our 
data. However, there was no statistically significant differ-
ence between using anticoagulation agents and the occur-
rence of CSDH, while there was a significant correlation be-
tween the use of antiplatelet agents and the occurrence of 
CSDH. While the preceding studies analyzed patients who 
already developed CSDH or had severe head trauma, we in-
cluded all the patients with minor head trauma, which may 
explain the difference in the outcome. Also, the fact that the 
patient group only had a limited number of the patients may 
be related to the difference as well. 
It was expected that there would be a correlation between 
CSDH occurrence and the patients with cerebral infarction 
or with cardiac disease, as they are commonly administered 
antiplatelet or anticoagulant agents. 10) The actual study 
showed a higher ratio of patients with cerebral infarction 
or cardiac disease in the patient group than in the control 
group. However, only the history of cerebral infarction dem-
onstrated a statistically significant difference, while the 
presence of cardiac disease failed to show a statistical sig-
nificance. With regard to cerebral infarction, aside from us-
ing antiplatelet agents or anticoagulants, other co-factors, 
such as a decrease in brain volume due to encephalomala-
cia after infarction, could influence the outcome. Also, the 
insufficient number of the patients analyzed in the patient 
group is likely the reason why we could not find a signifi-
cance relationship between CSDH occurrence and the pres-
ence of cardiac disease. 
Generally, the hematologic diseases that cause coagulop-
athy are known to be risk factors for post-traumatic CSDH 
occurrence. 1,4) The history of epilepsy is also expected to be 
a risk factor of CSDH since it can cause repeated seizures. 1,11) 
We began our analysis considering these known concepts, 
but the history of hematologic diseases and epilepsy showed 
no significant differences in our study. Yet, there was no pa-
tient with a history of hematologic diseases or epilepsy in 
the patient group, and a very small number of the patients 
with a history of hematologic diseases (1.1%) or epilepsy 
(1.4%) were present among the entire test population. It is 
assumed that the limited number of patients analyzed in the 
study impacted the result as well. 
Limitations of the current study include the small num-
ber of patient group and the retrospective nature of the study 
design. However this study creatively demonstrated the pre-</p>

<p>dictive factors of CSDH in patients with minor head trauma. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Based on the results of this study, the predictive factors 
of post-traumatic CSDH occurrence are old age, preexisting 
DM, hypertension, and history of cerebral infarction, the 
presence of ASDH in the convexity found in brain CT scans 
taken right after the trauma, encephalomalacia, and an en-
larged subdural space between skull and brain parenchyma. 
When treating patients with minor head trauma accompa-
nied by those risk factors, physicians must pay careful at-
tention to the possibility of post-traumatic CSDH and need 
to continuously observe the patients. </p>

<p>■ The authors have no financial conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>REFERENCES </p>

<p>1) Adhiyaman V, Asghar M, Ganeshram KN, Bhowmick BK. Chron-</p>

<p>ic subdural haematoma in the elderly. Postgrad Med J 78:71-75, 
2002 </p>

<p>2) Asghar M, Adhiyaman V, Greenway MW, Bhowmick BK, Bates </p>

<p>A. Chronic subdural haematoma in the elderly--a North Wales ex-
perience. J R Soc Med 95:290-292, 2002 </p>

<p>3) Berghauser Pont LM, Dammers R, Schouten JW, Lingsma HF, </p>

<p>Dirven CM. Clinical factors associated with outcome in chronic 
subdural hematoma: a retrospective cohort study of patients on 
preoperative corticosteroid therapy. Neurosurgery 70:873-880; 
discussion 880, 2012 </p>

<p>4) Chon KH, Lee JM, Koh EJ, Choi HY. Independent predictors for </p>

<p>recurrence of chronic subdural hematoma. Acta Neurochir (Wien) 
154:1541-1548, 2012 </p>

<p>5) Jolobe OM. Chronic subdural haematoma in the elderly. J R Soc </p>

<p>Med 95:427-428, 2002 </p>

<p>6) Jones S, Kafetz K. A prospective study of chronic subdural hae-</p>

<p>matomas in elderly patients. Age Ageing 28:519-521, 1999 </p>

<p>7) Ko BS, Lee JK, Seo BR, Moon SJ, Kim JH, Kim SH. Clinical anal-</p>

<p>ysis of risk factors related to recurrent chronic subdural hemato-
ma. J Korean Neurosurg Soc 43:11-15, 2008 </p>

<p>8) Laviv Y, Rappaport ZH. Risk factors for development of signifi-</p>

<p>cant chronic subdural hematoma following conservative treatment 
of acute subdural hemorrhage. Br J Neurosurg:1-6, 2014 </p>

<p>9) Lee KS, Bae WK, Doh JW, Bae HG, Yun IG. Origin of chronic sub-</p>

<p>dural haematoma and relation to traumatic subdural lesions. Brain 
Inj 12:901-910, 1998 </p>

<p>10) Lindvall P, Koskinen LO. Anticoagulants and antiplatelet agents </p>

<p>and the risk of development and recurrence of chronic subdural 
haematomas. J Clin Neurosci 16:1287-1290, 2009 </p>

<p>11) Luxon LM, Harrison MJ. Chronic subdural haematoma. Q J Med </p>

<p>48:43-53, 1979 </p>

<p>12) Markwalder TM. Chronic subdural hematomas: a review. J Neu-</p>

<p>rosurg 54:637-645, 1981 </p>

<p>13) Mori K, Adachi K, Cho K, Ishimaru S, Maeda M. Quantitative ki-</p>

<p>netic analysis of blood vessels in the outer membranes of chronic 
subdural hematomas. Neurol Med Chir (Tokyo) 38:697-702; dis-
cussion 702-703, 1998 </p>

<p>14) Mori K, Mitsuoka H, Cho K, Tajima A, Maeda M. Rate constant of </p>

<p>gadolinium (Gd)-DTPA transfer into chronic subdural hematomas. 
Neurol Res 18:126-134, 1996 </p>

<p>Sang-Beom Han, et al. </p>

<p>http://www.kjnt.org 111 </p>

<p>15) Ohno K, Suzuki R, Masaoka H, Matsushima Y, Inaba Y, Monma </p>

<p>S. Chronic subdural haematoma preceded by persistent traumatic 
subdural fluid collection. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry 50:1694-
1697, 1987 </p>

<p>16) Okano A, Oya S, Fujisawa N, Tsuchiya T, Indo M, Nakamura T, et </p>

<p>al. Analysis of risk factors for chronic subdural haematoma recur-
rence after burr hole surgery: optimal management of patients on 
antiplatelet therapy. Br J Neurosurg 28:204-208, 2014 </p>

<p>17) Reymond MA, Marbet G, Radü EW, Gratzl O. Aspirin as a risk </p>

<p>factor for hemorrhage in patients with head injuries. Neurosurg 
Rev 15:21-25, 1992 </p>

<p>18) Sato S, Suzuki J. Ultrastructural observations of the capsule of </p>

<p>chronic subdural hematoma in various clinical stages. J Neuro-
surg 43:569-578, 1975 </p>

<p>19) Teale EA, Iliffe S, Young JB. Subdural haematoma in the elderly. </p>

<p>BMJ 348:g1682, 2014 </p>

<p>20) Torihashi K, Sadamasa N, Yoshida K, Narumi O, Chin M, Yamaga-</p>

<p>ta S. Independent predictors for recurrence of chronic subdural 
hematoma: a review of 343 consecutive surgical cases. Neurosur-
gery 63:1125-1129; discussion 1129, 2008 </p>

<p>21) Yamada H, Nihei H, Watanabe T, Shibui S, Murata S. [Chronic </p>

<p>subdural hematoma occurring consequently to the posttraumatic 
subdural hygroma--on the pathogenesis of the chronic subdural he-
matoma (author's transl)]. No To Shinkei 31:115-121, 1979 </p>

<p>22) Yamamoto H, Hirashima Y, Hamada H, Hayashi N, Origasa H, Endo </p>

<p>S. Independent predictors of recurrence of chronic subdural hema-
toma: results of multivariate analysis performed using a logistic 
regression model. J Neurosurg 98:1217-1221, 2003 </p>

<p>23) Yoon JW, Park IS, Park H, Kang DH, Park KB, Lee CH, et al. A </p>

<p>study of the progression from acute subdural hematoma to chron-
ic stage requiring surgical treatment. Korean J Neurotrauma 9: 
74-80, 2013 </p>

</text></tei>