<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4987885" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p><rs type="software">SuperLooper2</rs> (SL2) (http://proteinformatics.charite. 
de/sl2) is the updated version of our previous web-
server SuperLooper, a fragment based tool for the 
prediction and interactive placement of loop struc-
tures into globular and helical membrane proteins. 
In comparison to our previous version, <rs type="software">SL2</rs> benefits 
from both a considerably enlarged database of frag-
ments derived from high-resolution 3D protein struc-
tures of globular and helical membrane proteins, and 
the integration of a new protein viewer. The database, 
now with double the content, significantly improved 
the coverage of fragment conformations and predic-
tion quality. The employment of the NGL viewer for 
visualization of the protein under investigation and 
interactive selection of appropriate loops makes <rs type="software">SL2</rs> 
independent of third-party plug-ins and additional in-
stallations. </p>

<p>Structural biology is an established but still emerging re-
search field of life sciences, as reflected by the exponential 
rise of atomic models deposited in the Research Collab-
oratory for Structural Bioinformatics Protein Data Bank 
(RCSB PDB) (1). However, in more than one half of all 
entries deposited in the RSCB PDB segments are missing 
(2). These missing segments are often located in flexible and 
functionally important regions of proteins such as loops or 
turns, not resolved by X-ray crystallography or single parti-
cle cryo-electron microscopy. These regions have to be mod-
eled to obtain a more complete structural model for further 
analysis of the structure, e.g. for molecular dynamics simu-
lations (3). 
Loop regions are one of the most demanding regions in 
homology modeling workflows. A prominent example are 
G protein coupled receptors (GPCRs), which constitute the 
largest protein family in the human genome. The number of </p>

<p>available templates for modeling of GPCRs has increased 
dramatically in the last decade facilitating the generation 
of homology models for structure-based drug design. The 
common topology of the transmembrane-spanning regions, 
even of distantly related GPCRs, allows homology model-
ing of these regions and docking of small rigid orthosteric 
ligands with close to experimental accuracy. However, pre-
dictions of long or flexible loops remain unsolved problems, 
as evaluated recently by the community-wide GPCR Dock 
assessment (4). As the sequence similarity within loop re-
gions is generally much lower than within other parts of 
proteins, specialized methods are required for modeling. 
Loop modeling approaches can be divided into ab initio 
(5-8), fragment-based, (9-12) or a mixture of both meth-
ods (13,14). Ab initio based methods utilize molecular me-
chanics force fields to determine possible loop conforma-
tions. These methods are generally CPU-intensive but ca-
pable of predicting currently unknown loop conformations. 
Fragment-based methods on the other hand are less CPU-
intensive and thus faster, but depend on known structures 
and precalculated fragment databases to find loop confor-
mations. It remains unclear which method provides the bet-
ter predictions. Some studies find that both methods per-
form on a similar level (9,12), while others describe advan-
tages to either ab initio (15) or fragment-based (16) methods. 
As fragment-based methods generally provide results much 
faster, they are well suited for web-based tools such as Su-
perLooper (17), allowing instant visualization and control 
of the results. 
The quality of fragment-based loop predictions using de-
pends on the completeness of the fragment database. Inde-
pendent studies have shown that the conformational space 
for short loops up to 12-14 residues is covered by structural 
fragments derived from the RCSB PDB (18,19). Enlarge-
ment of fragment databases may thus particularly enhance 
prediction of longer loops. Depending on the method used, 
also the prediction of shorter loops might benefit from a 
larger pool of available templates, e.g. when the exact fit of 
the stem atoms of the template loop to the gap is an evalua-</p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +49 30450524190; Fax: +49 30450524952; Email: peter.hildebrand@charite.de </p>

<p>Present address: Alexander S. Rose, San Diego Supercomputer Center, University of California, San Diego, CA 92093-0743, USA. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>The Author(s) 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which 
permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, Web Server issue W391 </p>

<p>tion criterion. The database of globular and membrane pro-
teins has more than doubled since our previous publication 
(17). In order to benefit from this enlargement of available 
structures we updated our fragment database. 
Fragment-based tools such as <rs type="software">SuperLooper</rs> depend on 
databases too large to distribute as stand-alone programs 
(∼80 GB in the case of <rs type="software">SL2</rs>). The rapid delivery of a large 
number of possible loop conformation makes web-based 
tools a perfect candidate. The database remains on a server 
and the user is able to choose a suitable loop from listed re-
sults using a web-based molecule viewer. Here, we use <rs type="software">NGL</rs> 
(20) for protein and fragment visualization, which adopts 
capabilities of modern web browsers, such as <rs type="software">WebGL</rs> for 
molecular graphics. <rs type="software">NGL</rs> allows interactive display of even 
large molecular complexes and is unaffected by the retire-
ment of third-party plug-ins such as Flash or Java-Applets. 
This viewer offers comprehensive molecular visualization 
through a graphical user interface so that life scientists can 
easily access and utilize available structural data without 
any further installations (20). 
Thus, <rs type="software">SL2</rs> benefits from the significantly enlarged 
database of fragments and new fast molecule viewer. Due 
to the improved coverage of the conformational loop space, 
the quality of prediction, measured by the backbone root 
mean square deviation (RMSD), has improved by 20% on 
average compared to our previous version (17). The new 
version of our fragment-based web-application for loop 
modeling <rs type="software">SL2</rs> thus has an improved performance in loop 
prediction as well as an up-to-date visualization. </p>

<p>UPDATE OF THE LIP AND LIMP DATABASE </p>

<p>The loop database (LIP) is composed of all possible frag-
ments of 3-35 amino acids length extracted from the RSCB 
PDB entries in December 2015. Here, not only loops 
are considered but also fragments derived from secondary 
structure elements like helices and -sheets. For each frag-
ment, the amino acid sequence, PDB identifier, chain iden-
tifier, residue number of stem atoms and a geometrical fin-
gerprint is stored. 
Geometrical fingerprint matching is used as a criterion to 
estimate the sterical fit of stem atoms of N-and C-termini 
of each database fragment to the C-and N-terminal stem 
atoms of a gap in a protein structure. The geometrical fin-
gerprints of both the stem atoms of each database fragment 
and the stem atoms of the gap are composed of the dis-
tance between the N-and C-terminal stem atoms and three 
angles defining their relative orientation (Figure 1). Com-
pared to our previous version, we slightly altered the geo-
metric fingerprint. Previously, we used a combination of two 
distances and two angles for scoring, resulting in a higher 
weighting of the fit of the residue where the angle was mea-
sured. In <rs type="software">SL2</rs>, we solved this problem employing distance 
and three angles. 
Since the first release of <rs type="software">SuperLooper</rs> in 2008, the num-
ber of entries deposited in the RSCB PDB has more than 
doubled from 54 543 structures to 114 693 in 2015. A total 
of 901 609 231 fragments with a length of 3 to 35 residues 
was extracted from this enlarged pool of template structures 
(Figure 2A). Because more short than long overlapping 
fragments are extracted from a given template structure, </p>

<p>Figure 1. Schematic representation of the geometrical fingerprint: The ge-
ometrical fingerprint is characterized by the distance d between the N-
terminal C-and the C-terminal N atom and the following three angles: 
defined by the line between C (N) , C (N) and d, is spanned by the line 
between N (C) , C (C) and d, is the angle between the two planes A (de-
fined by C (N) , C (N) and N (C) ) and B (C (C) , C (N) and N (C) ). </p>

<p>Figure 2. Length dependency of the number of fragments stored in our 
previous (black) and present fragment (gray) database; (A) loops in pro-
teins (LIP), and (B) loops in membrane proteins (LIMP). </p>

<p>the number of fragments decreases linearly with length. For 
loops with three amino acids, more than 30 million frag-
ments are stored in the database, for 35 amino acids 24 mil-
lion fragments are available. To benefit from the continuous 
growth of the RCSB PDB an update protocol was imple-</p>

<p>W392 Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, Web Server issue </p>

<p>mented that automatically adds novel fragments to the LIP 
or LIMP database every three months. 
Due to (partial) embedding into the lipid bilayer, loops 
of membrane proteins have a more hydrophobic amino 
acid composition compared to loops of globular proteins 
(21). Tools developed for the prediction of loops connect-
ing transmembrane helices were indeed found to enhance 
prediction of GPCR loops (22). In <rs type="software">SL2</rs>, such loops can be 
selected from LIMP, which is a collection of fragments ex-
tracted from loops of all helical transmembrane proteins. 
Loops were defined as parts without regular fold, thus also 
containing kinks, bulges or re-entrant loops (23). To allow 
selection of membrane protein loops taking the lipid bilayer 
into account, the extension of the lipid bilayer is indicated 
by two parallel planes (as described below). 
The number of membrane protein structures deposited in 
the RCSB PDB rose from 805 (in 2008) to 2298 (in 2015) ac-
cording to the Protein Data Bank of Transmembrane Pro-
teins (24). As a result, the loops stored in LIMP doubled 
from 179 580 to 378 839. For LIMP is composed mainly 
of loop structures, the length distribution differs from LIP 
where the fragments also include helical fragments and frag-
ments derived from -sheets. In LIMP (Figure 2B), few loop 
templates are available for short loops of 3-5 amino acids 
in length. The number of loops stored in LIMP increases 
markedly to a maximum of 20 000 up to a length of 20 
residues before it decreases again. </p>

<p>SEARCH PROCEDURE </p>

<p>To start the search the stem residues flanking the N-and C-
terminus of a missing (or existing) loop in a protein model 
and the amino acid sequence have to be provided. As in 
our previous version, the search procedure is based on a 
stepwise approach which minimizes the calculation time. 
Fragments with appropriate sequence length, and with ge-
ometrical fingerprints of the fragment and the gap match-
ing with an accuracy of at least 0.75Å RMSD distance are 
selected. This RMSD value is subsequently used to deter-
mine the top 1000 loop candidates. These loop candidates 
are then rescored by the parameters 'sequence similarity be-
tween missing segment and template loop' and 'fingerprint 
matching of the template loop to the gap in the model.' 
Only one representative of fragments with identical primary 
structure and high tertiary structure similarity (with back-
bone RMSD &lt; 0.5 ˚ 
A) is kept in the results list to maximize 
the conformational space of fragments used for further cal-
culations. The top 100 loop candidates are finally displayed 
in the results list. Suitable candidates can be selected from 
that list by visual inspection. </p>

<p>VISUALIZATION AND USER INTERFACE </p>

<p>For visual inspection of results, we employed the NGL 
viewer which works without installation of additional plug-
ins (20). As a common graphical user interface for the 
NGL viewer (Figure 3) the search mask and the results list 
were implemented within JavaScript. A protein structure 
uploaded via the file selection dialog is instantly loaded to 
the NGL viewer. The stem residues of the gap in the protein 
model must either be typed into the according search field or </p>

<p>can be selected by clicking them in the NGL viewer. The se-
quence of the missing segment must be typed or copied into 
the search mask. If the membrane protein-specific LIMP 
data base (Membrane DB) is not checked, the LIP data base 
will be searched. After the submission button is pressed, the 
search is started. Depending on the loop length, results are 
expected to appear after few seconds or up to half a minute 
in the results list. 
The top hit will automatically be loaded into the gap of 
the protein model depicted in the viewer window. Alterna-
tive loop conformations can be selected from the results ta-
ble containing the 100 best loop candidates. For each can-
didate, the score ranging from 0 to 0.455, the RCSB PDB 
entry-code and sequence of the template protein, the num-
ber of clashes, and the sequence identity between target and 
template are listed. If no appropriate loop is found, the 
user can select 'Decrease N-terminal stem' or 'Increase C-
terminal stem' to add a residue to the loop and shift the 
stem atoms of the gap, accordingly. As an additional vi-
sual control, for helical membrane proteins, the position 
of the lipid bilayer can be calculated ('Calculate membrane 
planes'), employing the web-service TMDET (25). 
There is an option to display the complete list of loop 
candidates at the same time as visualizing the conforma-
tion space of the loop. Loop candidates can be colored ac-
cording to score, sequence identity or clashes by selecting 
the corresponding color scheme from the dropdown menu. 
The completed structure (initial model plus selected loop) 
can be downloaded by clicking the download button. Al-
ternatively, the complete list of loops can be downloaded 
for further analysis. </p>

<p>TECHNICAL ASPECTS </p>

<p>Visualization is carried out by the NGL viewer (20). To use 
the full feature set of the NGL viewer an up-to-date web 
browser (tested on the recent versions of Firefox, Google 
Chrome, Safari, IE and Edge) is recommended. The spe-
cialized graphical user interface is written in JavaScript. For 
job handling a simple python job server based on the Flask 
framework (http://flask.pocoo.org/) is used. </p>

<p>PERFORMANCE, LIMITATIONS AND OUTLOOK </p>

<p>The updated version of our fragment based web-application 
tool for loop modeling, <rs type="software">SL2</rs>, benefits from an enlarged frag-
ment database and a new user interface including an up-
dated protein viewer. As a result of the enlarged fragment 
database the prediction quality has been further improved. 
Using the same dataset (15) and validation procedure as in 
our previous publication (17), an average gain in prediction 
quality by 20% is observed for loops of 3-16 residues length 
(Figure 4). A drop of the backbone RMSD between ex-
perimentally determined and modeled loops (only the top 
hit was considered) starts to become evident for loops with 
eight residues length. This implies that the coverage of pos-
sible loop conformations has been further optimized start-
ing with this length. 
Despite the gain of prediction quality, the top hit results 
obtained by <rs type="software">SL2</rs> sometimes deviate from the experimentally 
determined structure even for short loops. There are several </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, Web Server issue W393 </p>

<p>Figure 3. Screenshot of the <rs type="software">SL2</rs> results page (NGL viewer). Structure of the human cytomegalovirus GPCR US28 (PDB-ID: 4xt1) in a gray cartoon rep-
resentation with top ranked loop (green) and calculated membrane planes. The list of loop candidates filling the gap 94 to 103 in the GPCR structure is 
displayed as table on the right hand just below the search mask. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Comparison of benchmarks of our previous (17) (black rhom-
bus) and updated version <rs type="software">SL2</rs> (gray star) using a standard loop dataset 
(15). </p>

<p>possible reasons for this. First, many loops are highly flexi-
ble or are even located in structurally disordered regions of 
proteins (26,27). The conformations suggested by <rs type="software">SL2</rs> may 
thus indicate alternative loop conformations not observed 
by protein X-ray structure crystallography (e.g. Figure S6 
in (28)). Second, as scoring of the loops mainly depends on 
the stem residues, experimentally caused distortions of these 
stem atoms may prevent selection of a specific conformation 
(29). Prediction quality drops with loop length, mainly due 
to the increased conformational space. A promising strategy 
to enhance prediction quality of longer loops would be in-</p>

<p>clusion of additional experimental constraints such as mass 
spectrometry (30,31) or electron density maps from single 
particle cryo-electron microscopy (32). </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft [Sfb740/B6, DFG HI 
1502/1-2, BI 893/8]; 'Norddeutscher Verbund f ¨ 
ur Hoch-
und H ¨ 
ochstleistungsrechner' (HLRN) (in part). Funding 
for open access charge: Sfb740 / B6. 
Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



</text></tei>