<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4265209" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background This study assessed the effects of two doses of glucose and a caffeine-glucose combination on mood and performance of an 
ecologically valid, computerised multi-tasking platform. 
Materials and methods Following a double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomised, parallel-groups design, 150 healthy adults (mean age 
34.78 years) consumed drinks containing placebo, 25 g glucose, 60 g glucose or 60 g glucose with 40 mg caffeine. They completed a multi-
tasking framework at baseline and then 30 min following drink consumption with mood assessments immediately before and after the multi-
tasking framework. Blood glucose and salivary caffeine were co-monitored. 
Results The caffeine-glucose group had significantly better total multi-tasking scores than the placebo or 60 g glucose groups and were 
significantly faster at mental arithmetic tasks than either glucose drink group. There were no significant treatment effects on mood. Caffeine 
and glucose levels confirmed compliance with overnight abstinence/fasting, respectively, and followed the predicted post-drink patterns. 
Conclusion These data suggest that co-administration of glucose and caffeine allows greater allocation of attentional resources than 
placebo or glucose alone. At present, we cannot rule out the possibility that the effects are due to caffeine alone Future studies should aim 
at disentangling caffeine and glucose effects. Caffeine and glucose are two of the most widely 
consumed centrally active substances in the world. 
Caffeine (and to a lesser extent glucose) are used partly 
because of their potential cognition-enhancing proper-
ties. Although they are often co-consumed, including 
increasingly in the form of energy drinks, there is 
surprisingly little research examining the effects of 
the two substances in combination in the context of 
neurocognitive function. 
The mood and cognitive effects of caffeine have 
been comprehensively reviewed elsewhere (Glade, 
2010; Rogers et al., 2011; Smith, 2002). Typically, ad-
ministration of caffeine in the range of 50 to 150 mg 
improves reaction times, psychomotor function, 
attention, vigilance and alertness-with the effects 
being particularly evident in fatigued individuals. 
Lower doses of caffeine have been less thoroughly </p>

<p>researched, but doses as low as 12.5 mg, a level 
roughly equivalent to half a serving of cola, have been 
shown to be psychopharmacologically active (Smit 
and Rogers, 2000). 
Glucose is the primary source of energy for the brain 
and, as such, is essential for central nervous system 
functioning. It has been extensively reported that cog-
nitive performance can be enhanced following admin-
istration of drinks containing 25-50 g glucose. The 
effect is most apparent on tasks with a declarative 
memory component and/or those with heavier cogni-
tive demands (Benton et al., 1994; Donohoe and 
Benton, 1999; Riby, 2004; Scholey et al., 2009b; 
Scholey and Fowles, 2002; Scholey et al., 2001; 
Sünram-Lea et al., 2008), including dual tasking 
(Foster et al., 1998; Scholey et al., 2009b; Smith et al., 
2011; Sünram-Lea et al., 2002; Scholey et al., 2013). 
Despite the abundance of studies investigating the 
behavioural effects of the two substances individually, 
there is surprisingly little research evaluating the mood 
and cognitive effects of caffeine and glucose both 
separately and together. This has been given further </p>

<p>*Correspondence to: A. Scholey, Centre for Human Psychopharmacology, 
Swinburne University, Melbourne, VIC 3122, Australia. Tel: +61(0)3 9214 
8932 E-mail: andrew@scholeylab.com </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Human Psychopharmacology: Clinical and Experimental published by John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. Received 18 December 2013 </p>

<p>Accepted 12 May 2014 </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and 
distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>human psychopharmacology </p>

<p>Hum. Psychopharmacol Clin Exp 2014; 29: 434-445. </p>

<p>Published online 28 July 2014 in Wiley Online Library 
(wileyonlinelibrary.com) DOI: 10.1002/hup.2417 </p>

<p>impetus from the fact that they are increasingly con-
sumed concomitantly in so-called energy drinks. 
One recent study investigating the combined and 
separate effects of 75 g glucose and 75 mg caffeine 
revealed beneficial effects to both sustained attention 
and learning from the combination (Adan and Serra 
Grabulosa, 2010). These effects were not observed in 
either the caffeine-only or glucose-only condition. In 
a follow-up study that used the same doses and 
included a functional magnetic resonance imaging 
component, the same group found no differences in 
performance of an attentional task between glucose, 
caffeine and their combination (Serra Grabulosa 
et al., 2010). Functional imaging during task perfor-
mance, however, revealed lower activation of parietal 
and prefrontal cortices in the caffeine-glucose condi-
tion. These findings can be interpreted as suggesting 
that the caffeine-glucose drink increased 'neural effi-
ciency', such that less brain activation was required 
to maintain a level of cognitive performance. 
The doses used in both the aforementioned studies 
were 75 g glucose and 75 mg caffeine. This caffeine 
level is consistent with, for example, coffee, which typically 
contains between 50 and 100 mg caffeine. Energy drinks 
can also contain caffeine in the range of 75 to 200 mg 
caffeine or more per serving. Some, however, have lower 
levels more typical of colas (35-45 mg). 
Regarding the amount of glucose used in the Adan 
and Serra Grabulosa studies, 75 g is far higher than 
the levels found in sweetened coffee or tea. It is also 
higher than the 25-50 g used in studies into glucose 
effects on cognition (Riby, 2004) and is relatively high 
compared with many caffeinated beverages such as 
energy drinks, which typically contain around half this 
amount. 
Earlier studies have examined the cognitive effects 
of glucose and caffeine at levels more typical of every-
day consumption. Compared with a glucose-and-
caffeine-free control, drinks containing glucose/ 
caffeine at both 68 g/38 mg and 68 g/46 mg improved 
performance during sustained, cognitively demanding 
tasks (Kennedy and Scholey, 2004). Other studies in-
dicate an additive or even synergistic effect between 
caffeine and glucose on various domains of cognition. 
In separate studies, 37.5 g glucose, 75 mg caffeine 
drinks improved sustained attention, working memory 
(Smit et al., 2004), declarative memory and speed of 
attention (Scholey and Kennedy, 2004) above levels 
of either substance alone. 
The distribution of attentional resources over multiple 
tasks engages a number of mental processes that 
increase cognitive demand relative to a single task 
performance. Moreover, the ability to effectively and </p>

<p>accurately multi-task has great utility in planning and 
decision making in everyday life. Interventions that 
have the capacity to improve these cognitive abilities 
are therefore of interest both scientifically and practi-
cally. The current study was therefore designed to assess 
the potential effects of glucose (two doses, 25 and 60 g) 
and a caffeine-glucose combination (60 g glucose, 
40 mg caffeine) on cognitive performance and mood 
associated with cognitive multi-tasking. Specifically, it 
aimed to investigate effects on 'everyday' cognition 
using a multi-tasking framework (MTF)-comprising 
four tasks completed simultaneously-and on mood 
ratings taken before and after completion of the MTF. 
Two main hypotheses were tested. The primary 
hypothesis was that, compared with placebo, caffeine-
glucose in combination would result in improved cogni-
tive multi-tasking performance as measured by overall 
MTF scores. We have previously argued that glucose 
preferentially targets more mentally effortful cognitive 
processes. Glucose is particularly effective at increasing 
performance during effortful processing, including 
during dual attention tasks (Scholey et al., 2009b; 
Sünram-Lea et al., 2002). As dividing cognitive 
resources over several tasks involves relatively high 
mental effort, we hypothesised that the two doses of 
glucose alone would also improve performance. The 
secondary hypotheses were that, compared with 
placebo and/or glucose alone, the caffeine-glucose 
combination would improve task performance on indi-
vidual tasks from the MTF and improve subjective 
feelings of mood, stress and fatigue during extended 
cognitive multi-tasking. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Design </p>

<p>The investigation was a single-centre, randomised, 
double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel-groups 
study conducted at the Centre for Human Psychophar-
macology, Swinburne University, Australia. The study 
was approved by the Swinburne University Human 
Research Ethics Committee (ref SUHREC #2010/ 
299) and conducted in accordance with the Declaration 
of Helsinki. All participants provided written informed 
consent. The trial was registered on the Australian 
New Zealand Clinical Trials Registry (ANZCTR) as 
ACTRN12613000247774. 
The study assessed the effects of two doses of glu-
cose alone (25 and 60 g) and one dose of a (40 mg, 
60 g) caffeine-glucose combination on cognitive 
performance, fatigue, stress and mood associated with 
extended multi-tasking. </p>

<p>435 
glucose, caffeine and multi-tasking </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Human Psychopharmacology: Clinical and Experimental 
published by John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. </p>

<p>Hum. Psychopharmacol Clin Exp 2014; 29: 434-445. 
DOI: 10.1002/hup </p>

<p>Participants </p>

<p>One hundred and sixty healthy adults (male and fe-
male) aged between 18 and 55 years were recruited 
for the study. Participants were recruited from the in-
vestigators' existing database and via local media ad-
vertising. All participants were healthy, non-smoking, 
regular caffeine consumers with no significant concur-
rent illnesses or a history of psychiatric disease. </p>

<p>Blood glucose measurement </p>

<p>Blood glucose levels were monitored using a MediSense 
Optium Xceed Blood Glucose Sensor and disposable 
MediSense Blood Glucose Electrodes (MediSense 
Britain Ltd, Birmingham, UK). The accuracy and 
consistency of MediSense blood glucose sensors have 
previously been established (Matthews et al., 1987). 
The reliability of the test has previously been confirmed. 
Blood samples were taken using Owen Mumford 
'Unistik 2' single-use capillary blood sampling devices 
(Owen Mumford Ltd, Oxford, UK). Alcohol-soaked 
skin cleansing swabs (Briemarkap, Koo Wee Rup, Victoria, 
Australia) were used for pre-sampling sterilisation. </p>

<p>Salivary caffeine measurement </p>

<p>Saliva samples were collected using salivettes. These 
consist of a small test tube fitted with an inner recepta-
cle containing a sterile cotton wool bud. Participants 
were required to remove the cotton wool bud and place 
it in the mouth, chewing gently for approximately 
2 min and then replacing it in the test tube. The test 
tube with the saliva-cotton wool was then centrifuged, 
and the sample frozen for analysis. Salivary caffeine 
was measured using a caffeine immunoassay as previ-
ously described (Haskell et al., 2005). </p>

<p>Multi-tasking framework </p>

<p>A computerised MTF was used. This platform offers 
relatively high ecological validity in terms of the 
cognitive demands required to complete several dispa-
rate tasks simultaneously in the work environment 
(Wetherell and Carter, 2013). The computerised MTF 
comprises four cognitive and psychomotor tasks that 
are undertaken simultaneously using a four-way split 
screen. 
Responses to all of the tasks are made using the 
mouse and cursor. Completion of the battery for an ex-
tended period has been shown to induce stress-related 
physiological processes (Wetherell and Sidgreaves, 
2005) and to modulate subjective feelings of mood, 
including decreased alertness and increased mental 
fatigue and anxiety (Kennedy et al., 2004; Scholey 
et al., 2009a). In terms of cognitive performance, the </p>

<p>MTF has also been shown to be sensitive to a number 
of natural interventions, including food supplements 
and herbal extracts (Kennedy et al., 2006; Kennedy 
et al., 2004). 
In this study, a 20-min version of the MTF was 
employed with the framework set at medium 
intensity (see Scholey et al., 2009a, for details). The 
individual MTF tasks used here were as follows 
(arranged clockwise from top left). </p>

<p>Mathematical processing task. A series of addition 
calculations are presented. Each calculation requires 
the participant to add two numbers together, entering 
the three-figure answer via an onscreen number pad. 
On completion of each calculation, the participant 
clicks the 'done' button, which cues the next calcula-
tion. The outcomes are the speed of performance 
(number of calculations completed in 20 min) and ac-
curacy (% correct). The module also generates an over-
all score incorporating correct answers (+10 points) 
and incorrect answers (À10 points). </p>

<p>Stroop colour-word task. Words describing one of 
four colours ('RED', 'YELLOW', 'GREEN' and 
'BLUE') are presented in different coloured fonts. The 
participant clicks on colour panels in order to identify 
the font colour (e.g. if the word 'GREEN' is presented 
in a blue font, the correct response would be to click 
on the blue panel). If the participant fails to respond 
within 20 s, the task times out and the stimulus is re-
placed. The outcomes are the speed of performance 
(number of responses within 20 min) and accuracy 
(% correct). The module also generates an overall score 
incorporating correct answers (+10 points), incorrect 
answers (À10 points) and timeouts (À10 points). </p>

<p>Memory search task. Four letters appear for the partic-
ipants to remember. After 4 s, the letters disappear but 
can be viewed again by clicking on 'retrieve list' but-
ton. Every 10 s, a single target letter appears. Partici-
pants are instructed to indicate whether the target 
letter had appeared in the original list of four letters 
by clicking on the 'yes' or 'no' buttons. If the partici-
pant fails to respond within 15 s, the task times out 
and the stimulus is replaced. The outcomes are the 
speed of performance (number of responses within 
20 min) and accuracy (% correct). The module also 
generates an overall score incorporating the number 
of responses (+10 points each), incorrect responses 
(À10 points) and timeouts (À10 points). </p>

<p>Target tracker. A red dot moves slowly outwards 
from the centre of target-shaped concentric circles hold </p>

<p>436 
a. scholey ET AL. </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Human Psychopharmacology: Clinical and Experimental 
published by John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. </p>

<p>Hum. Psychopharmacol Clin Exp 2014; 29: 434-445. 
DOI: 10.1002/hup </p>

<p>(at a speed of approximately 3 s/cm). Participants must 
click on one of two 'reset' buttons before the dot 
reaches the outer circle in order to re-centre the dot. 
Each larger circle increases the score by two points, 
from two to a maximum of 10 points. The red dot will 
begin to flash when touching the outer circle if reset 
buttons are not pressed, losing 10 points per 0.5 s until 
a response is made. The outcomes are the speed of 
performance (number of responses within 20 min) 
and accuracy (% correct). The module also generates 
an overall score incorporating number of responses 
and timeouts. </p>

<p>Pencil-and-paper measures </p>

<p>Bond-Lader visual analogue mood scales. The Bond 
and Lader (1974) mood scales have been utilised in nu-
merous pharmacological, psychopharmacological and 
medical trials. The measure comprises 16 × 100 mm vi-
sual analogue mood scales with the endpoints anchored 
by the following antonyms: alert-drowsy, calm-excited, 
strong-feeble, muzzy-clearheaded, well coordinated-
clumsy, lethargic-energetic, contented-discontented, 
troubled-tranquil, mentally slow-quick witted, tense-
relaxed, attentive-dreamy, incompetent-proficient, 
happy-sad, antagonistic-friendly, interested-bored and 
withdrawn-sociable. Participants were presented with 
a sheet of paper containing the scales and instructed to 
mark their current mood state on each line. These are 
combined as recommended by the authors to form three 
mood factors, 'alert', 'calm' and 'contented', with scores 
on each ranging from 0 to 100. </p>

<p>Stress and fatigue visual analogue mood scales. These 
single visual analogue scales aim to gauge subjective 
mood at the present moment. The items consist of sin-
gle 100-mm lines labelled 'stress' and 'fatigue' with 
the endpoints labelled 'not at all' and 'extremely'. </p>

<p>State-Trait Anxiety Inventory-State portion. The 
State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI; Spielberger 
et al., 1970) comprises two scales. The 'State' 
(STAI-S) subscale is a widely used instrument for 
measuring fluctuating levels of anxiety. Participants 
rate how much statements match their current state 
by marking a 4-point scale ranging from not at all to 
very much so. The subscale contains 20 statements 
(e.g. 'I am calm'). Scores range from 20 to 80, with 
higher scores indicating more anxiety. </p>

<p>The National Aeronautics and Space Administration 
Task Load Index perceived workload questionnaire. 
The National Aeronautics and Space Administration 
Task Load Index (NASA-TLX; Hart and Staveland, </p>

<p>1988) assesses work load. Participants rate the per-
ceived effort (from very low to very high) involved 
in performing the MTF along six dimensions. Three 
gauge the demand placed upon the respondent by the 
task (mental demand, physical demand and temporal 
demand), and three gauge elements of the interaction 
between participant and task (effort, frustration and 
perceived performance). </p>

<p>Treatments </p>

<p>On their study day, each participant received one of 
four treatments supplied in the form of a 330 ml 
orange-flavoured drink in unlabelled bottles in opaque 
sleeves. The drinks comprised (i) placebo, a commercial 
sugar-free fizzy orange drink; (ii) 25 g glucose, in the form 
of a fruit-flavoured, carbonated drink (iii) 60 g glucose, in 
a carbonated, fruit-flavoured drink and (iv) caffeine-
glucose, in the form of a commercially available, fruit-
flavoured, carbonated drink containing 40 mg caffeine 
and 60 g glucose. Note that the glucose was in the form 
of glucose syrup formulated to release 60 g of glucose 
when broken down. 
Randomisation to treatment was achieved by allocating 
each individual to a condition as determined by a disin-
terested third party who played no other part in the study. 
All products contained inactive commercially avail-
able food ingredients including sweeteners (sucralose/ 
acesulfame K), acidulant (malic acid), preservative 
(potassium sorbate) and flavourings. Each participant 
was allowed 5 min to consume one of the treatments 
during their testing visit. Treatment bottles were placed 
in identical sleeves before consumption to maintain the 
double blind by preventing sighting of colour/texture 
differences between the treatments by researcher or 
participant. 
Products were manufactured and supplied by GSK 
Nutritional Healthcare R&amp;D (Brentford, UK) who 
monitored and approved chemical, sensorial and 
microbiological stability of the products used on 
study initiation and for the duration of the study. The 
levels of caffeine were determined by analysis, and 
confirmed before the start of the study. </p>

<p>Procedure </p>

<p>Participants visited the laboratory on two occasions. 
The first was an initial practice session, where they 
signed a participant informed consent form indicating 
comprehension and compliance with study processes 
and were allocated a study identification number. Mor-
phometric and demographic data were recorded as well 
as details of any relevant medical history and concom-
itant medications. The practice session also included 
measures of personality and emotional intelligence </p>

<p>437 
glucose, caffeine and multi-tasking </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Human Psychopharmacology: Clinical and Experimental 
published by John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. </p>

<p>Hum. Psychopharmacol Clin Exp 2014; 29: 434-445. 
DOI: 10.1002/hup </p>

<p>(paper questionnaires) for purposes unrelated to the 
current study. These included the Trait portion of the 
Spielberger State-Trait Anxiety scale, the Profile of 
Mood States, the Swinburne University Emotional 
Intelligence Test and the Neuroticism-Extroversion-
Openness Inventory Five Factor Inventory. Partici-
pants were familiarised with the mood questionnaires 
including the Bond-Lader, STAI-S, visual analogue 
scales and NASA-TLX and practiced completing the 
computer-based cognitive MTF. This served to famil-
iarise subjects with task requirements and to attenuate 
any practice effects. 
The subsequent visit comprised the study days that 
took place at least 24 h after the practice visit [mean 
6.51 days, standard deviation (SD) 4.52]. Participants 
were instructed to fast for 12 h prior to study days 
and to abstain from drinking alcohol and caffeinated 
drinks for 24 and 12 h, respectively. The study day 
testing session lasted for 1.5 h. Upon arrival, partici-
pants provided blood and saliva for baseline fasted 
glucose and caffeine measurement, respectively. 
Following this, baseline mood, stress and fatigue 
measures were completed immediately before and after 
the computer-based MTF. The treatment drink was 
then administered to the participant who was allowed 
5 min to consume the product. Exactly 30 min later 
(to allow for product absorption), a second blood 
glucose measure was taken. Participants again 
completed mood, fatigue and stress questionnaires 
immediately before and after completion of the MTF. 
After this session (60 min post-dose), final blood 
glucose measurement and salivary samples were 
provided. Participants were thanked and fully debriefed, 
and they were asked to indicate which condition they 
believed they had been in and then given the opportunity 
to ask questions of the experimenter before leaving the 
laboratory. </p>

<p>STATISTICS </p>

<p>Sample size calculation. Sample size was determined 
on the basis of the data from Kennedy and Scholey 
(2004). Mean change-from-baseline rapid visual infor-
mation processing accuracy scores were averaged 
across the 30-, 40-and 50-min post-treatment mea-
sures for the 40 g caffeine plus 68 g glucose and the 
placebo conditions, respectively. The resulting effect 
size (Cohen's d) of 0.372 was used to calculate the 
sample size for a four-condition analysis of variance 
(ANOVA) using <rs id="software-1" type="software">G*POWER</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">v3.12</rs> (Faul et al., 2007). 
This generated an N of 132 to detect a significant difference 
at an α level of 0.05 with 95% power. Given the </p>

<p>exploratory nature of this study, and the possibility of 
attrition, the N was increased to 40/cell in order to optimise 
the chances of capturing treatment-related effects. </p>

<p>Data treatment and analysis. Data were analysed 
using the statistical software <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">v20</rs> for Windows 
unless otherwise stated. 
Demographic and morphometric data were analysed 
using one-way ANOVA comparing treatments with 
pairwise comparisons where appropriate to ensure that 
the groups were matched. Blood glucose levels were 
analysed using a 2-way ANOVA examining effects of 
Treatment × Time (baseline, pre-testing, post-testing) 
with the latter as a within-subjects factor. Salivary 
caffeine was analysed using a 2-way ANOVA examining 
effects of Treatment × Time (pre-testing, post-testing) 
with the latter as a within-subjects factor. 
The primary outcome was the overall multi-tasking 
score. Secondary outcomes included scores on the 
individual tasks. Multi-tasking performance (overall 
score and individual task scores) were analysed as 
follows. Each score was computed as change from 
baseline, group outliers were removed from resulting 
scores and data were then analysed by one-way 
ANOVA comparing treatments. Group differences 
were explored by all pairwise comparisons (least 
significant difference statistic). 
Mood and stress reactivity (i.e. the changes in alert-
ness, calmness, contentedness, state anxiety, stress and 
fatigue) were computed (post-stressor minus pre-
stressor or Δ). The resulting scores were examined as 
change from baseline Δ and were analysed by one-
way ANOVA in the same way as the performance 
scores. Changes in aspects of perceived effort as mea-
sured using the NASA-TLX were analysed by one-way 
ANOVA examining effects of treatment (drink). Planned 
pairwise comparisons (least significant difference) were 
conducted to establish differences between active treat-
ments and placebo and between different active drinks. 
Treatment guessing data were analysed by chi-square 
comparing the distribution of treatment guesses to 
chance within each condition using <rs type="software">GRAPHPAD</rs> software 
(GraphPad Software, La Jolla, CA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Participant characteristics </p>

<p>Of 160 participants enrolled into the study, there were 
150 suitable datasets for analysis. The flow of partici-
pants through the study is presented in Figure 1. 
Participants were non-smokers and regular caffeine 
consumers (at least one caffeinated beverage per 
day). Further demographic variables are presented in </p>

<p>438 
a. scholey ET AL. </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Human Psychopharmacology: Clinical and Experimental 
published by John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. </p>

<p>Hum. Psychopharmacol Clin Exp 2014; 29: 434-445. 
DOI: 10.1002/hup </p>

<p>Table 1, and there were no group differences in any 
demographic or morphometric measure. </p>

<p>Blood glucose </p>

<p>There was a significant time × condition interaction for 
blood glucose levels [F(6, 292) = 20.68, p &lt; 0.001]. 
Blood glucose levels did not differ at baseline 
[F(3, 146) = 0.91, p = 0.438]. There were significant 
group differences at both at the 30-min (pre-task) 
[F(3, 146) = 25.48, p &lt; 0.001] and 60-min (post-task) 
[F(3, 146) = 27.21, p &lt; 0.001] time points. Pairwise 
comparisons revealed that all measures were signifi-
cantly higher than placebo at both post-baseline time 
points (p &lt; 0.005) and that the 25 g drink was associated 
with lower blood glucose levels than the caffeine-
glucose drink at the pre-task measure (p = 0.038) and 
both the 60 g drink and the caffeine-glucose drink at 
the post-test measure (p &lt; 0.005 in both cases). These 
data are plotted in Figure 2 (upper panel). </p>

<p>Salivary caffeine </p>

<p>A threshold of 2000 ng/ml salivary caffeine was used 
as a cut-off for compliance to overnight caffeine with-
drawal (Rogers et al., 2005). Compliance was high 
with no exclusions owing to supra-threshold salivary 
caffeine. There was, however, a high variability in 
baseline caffeine levels ranging from sub-detection 
levels to 1942 ng/ml. 
There was a significant Treatment × Time interaction 
for salivary caffeine levels [F(3, 136) = 23.38, 
p &lt; 0.001]. Salivary caffeine levels did not differ at 
baseline [F(3, 136) = 0.34, p = 0.798]. There were 
significant differences in the post-task samples 
[F(3, 136) = 7.76, p &lt; 0.001] compared with those in 
the caffeine-glucose drink condition having signifi-
cantly higher salivary caffeine levels than those in 
the placebo, 25 g glucose and 60 g glucose condi-
tions (p &lt; 0.005). These data are plotted in Figure 2 
(lower panel). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Flow of participants through the study, including numbers screened, entered into the study, lost to data capture errors and analysed </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic and morphometric characteristics of participants included in analysis </p>

<p>All 
Placebo 
25 g glucose 
60 g glucose 
Caffeine-glucose </p>

<p>N 
150 
37 
38 
39 
36 
M/F 
58/92 
12/25 
17/21 
14/25 
15/21 
Age 
34.78 (10.63) 
30.51 (10.00) 
31.85 (11.02) 
31.44 (10.32) 
34.78 (11.09) 
BMI 
24.36 (4.45) 
24.70 (4.05) 
24.10 (5.22) 
23.97 (3.65) 
24.72 (4.86) 
Years education 
17.24 (3.02) 
17.00 (2.56) 
17.44 (3.44) 
16.95 (2.71) 
17.58 (3.33) </p>

<p>Overall Ns and numbers of male/female (M/F) adults are shown along with mean (with standard deviation) age, body mass index (BMI), and years 
of education. </p>

<p> 
glucose, caffeine and multi-tasking </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Human Psychopharmacology: Clinical and Experimental 
published by John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. </p>

<p>Hum. Psychopharmacol Clin Exp 2014; 29: 434-445. 
DOI: 10.1002/hup </p>

<p>Multi-tasking and mood </p>

<p>To ensure that the MTF had the established effects on 
self-rated mood, mood scores collected pre-and post-
MTF were subjected to a three-way Treatment × Time 
(baseline, post-treatment) × MTF (pre-, post-) ANOVA. 
Independent of any treatment effects, the MTF had the 
expected effect on mood as reflected by significant 
main effects of MTF associated with significantly 
decreased calmness [F(1, 146) = 7.56, p = 0.007] and 
contentment [F(1, 146) = 47.83, p &lt; 0.001], coupled 
with increased stress [F(1, 146) = 34.90, p &lt; 0.001], 
fatigue [F(1, 146) = 79.50, p &lt; 0.001] and state anxiety 
[F(1, 146) = 13.13, p &lt; 0.001]. 
Prior to analysing treatment effects, each outcome 
measure was subject to a one-way ANOVA comparing 
pre-treatment baseline scores in each treatment group 
(presented in Table 2). There were no significant 
differences. 
Regarding post-treatment effects, there was a signif-
icant main effect of treatment on the primary outcome 
variable, namely the overall multi-tasking score </p>

<p>[F(3, 146) = 3.56, p = 0.015]. Pairwise comparisons 
revealed a significant difference between placebo and 
the caffeine-glucose drink (p = 0.005), and between 
the 60 g glucose and the glucose + caffeine drinks 
(p = 0.006)-see Figure 3. There was a significant 
main effect of treatment on speed of performing the 
mathematical reasoning task [F(3, 145) = 4.14, 
p = 0.008]. The glucose + caffeine group performed 
significantly faster than the 25 g glucose group 
(p = 0.034) and the 60 g glucose group (p = 0.001). 
There was a trend for a treatment effect for speed of 
responding on the Stroop task [F(3, 143) = 2.62, 
p = 0.054]. The caffeine-glucose drink was associated 
with faster responses than the placebo and the 60 g 
glucose drink [p = 0.027 and p = 0.011, respectively]. 
There were no significant treatment effects on mood 
measures or perceived effort as gauged using the 
NASA-TLX. Mean scores for the mood measures and the 
NASA-TLX are presented in Tables 3 and 4, respectively. </p>

<p>Treatment guessing </p>

<p>Overall, there was a significant bias towards guessing 
the glucose conditions [χ 
2 (3) = 17.093, p = 0.0007] 
with 38.67% and 25.33% guessing that they had re-
ceived 25 and 60 g glucose, respectively, compared 
with 18% each guessing they had received the placebo 
and caffeine-glucose drinks. Within each condition, 
however, the distribution of guesses did not differ signif-
icantly for the placebo [χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(3) = 0.407, ns], 25 g glucose 
[χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(3) = 0.897, ns], 60 g glucose [χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(3) = 3.684, ns] or 
caffeine-glucose [χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(3) = 5.444, ns] (Table 5). 
There were no adverse events. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Supporting our hypothesis, there was a significant 
treatment effect on multi-tasking performance with 
those in the caffeine-glucose drink outperforming the 
placebo condition. Multi-tasking performance was also 
significantly better in the caffeine-glucose condition 
than in the 60 g glucose drink condition. These data 
are consistent with the hypothesis that a caffeine-
glucose drink can increase the amount of attentional re-
sources, which can be allocated to task performance. 
This is in broad agreement with the results of a func-
tional magnetic resonance imaging study showing lower 
levels of neural activation following a caffeine-glucose 
combination (albeit at different levels) than placebo or 
caffeine or glucose alone (Serra Grabulosa et al., 2010). 
Regarding the mechanisms underlying superior 
multi-tasking, we can be confident that the double 
blind was effective and that expectations as to condi-
tions did not influence results. Treatment guessing </p>

<p>CAFFEINE ng/ml </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>BASELINE 
POST-TEST </p>

<p>BASELINE PRE-TEST POST-TEST </p>

<p>BLOOD GLUCOSE (mmol/l) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>PLACEBO 
GLUCOSE 25 g 
GLUCOSE 60 g 
CAFFEINE-GLUCOSE </p>

<p>a 
a </p>

<p>b 
c </p>

<p>a. GLUCOSE </p>

<p>b. CAFFEINE </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>Figure 2. Mean ± standard error of mean blood glucose levels (top) 
and salivary caffeine levels (bottom). For blood glucose a, significantly 
different to all other drink conditions; b, significantly different from 
caffeine-glucose; c, significantly different from 60 g glucose and caffeine-
glucose at same time point. For salivary caffeine levels </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>p &lt; 0.005 at same 
time point </p>

<p>440 
a. scholey ET AL. </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Human Psychopharmacology: Clinical and Experimental 
published by John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. </p>

<p>Hum. Psychopharmacol Clin Exp 2014; 29: 434-445. 
DOI: 10.1002/hup </p>

<p>Table 2. Summary statistics showing treatment effects (mean and SD) on multi-tasking measures </p>

<p>Baseline 
Post-treatment 
Change from baseline </p>

<p>Mean 
SD 
Mean 
SD 
Mean 
SD </p>

<p>Multi-tasking score </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Placebo 
8596 
2756 
9228 
3006 
632 
1003 
25 g glucose 
8859 
2436 
9848 
2538 
989 
1195 
60 g glucose 
8754 
2654 
9422 
2528 
668 
1179 
Caffeine-glucose 
9530 
2277 
10 999 
2470 
1469 
1538 
Mathematical reasoning score 
Placebo 
484 
289 
530 
315 
63 
117 
25 g glucose 
369 
150 
377 
168 
8 
101 
60 g glucose 
434 
334 
485 
346 
52 
162 
Caffeine-glucose 
374 
215 
403 
250 
29 
102 
Maths correct (number) 
Placebo 
53 
28 
57 
31 
6 
11 
25 g glucose 
41 
15 
41 
17 
0 
9 
60 g glucose 
51 
27 
55 
28 
5 
16 
Caffeine-glucose 
42 
20 
45 
23 
3 
10 
Maths errors (number) 
Placebo 
4 
4 
4 
4 
0 
3 
25 g glucose 
4 
4 
4 
2 
0 
4 
60 g glucose 
7 
13 
7 
14 
À1 
4 
Caffeine-glucose 
5 
7 
5 
9 
0 
2 
Maths speed 
a (ms) 
Placebo 
6047 
3489 
5208 
2627 
À505 
902 
25 g glucose 
5537 
1471 
5266 
1871 
À387 
1256 
60 g glucose 
4762 
1851 
4558 
1711 
À39 
751 
Caffeine-glucose 
5512 
2206 
4712 
1781 
À927 
1270 
Stroop score 
Placebo 
3431 
1248 
3588 
1439 
157 
627 
25 g glucose 
3730 
1328 
4182 
1362 
353 
798 
60 g glucose 
3235 
1154 
3542 
1187 
307 
813 
Caffeine-glucose 
3561 
1144 
3975 
1207 
414 
875 
Stroop error (number) 
Placebo 
1 
2 
2 
3 
1 
3 
25 g glucose 
2 
2 
3 
3 
1 
3 
60 g glucose 
3 
5 
4 
5 
1 
3 
Caffeine-glucose 
2 
2 
3 
5 
0 
2 
Stroop speed 
b (ms) 
Placebo 
1961 
1462 
1869 
1624 
À135 
238 
25 g glucose 
1700 
539 
1587 
566 
À86 
228 
60 g glucose 
1715 
1054 
1647 
1050 
À68 
253 
Caffeine-glucose 
1761 
770 
1515 
599 
À218 
278 
Stroop misses (number) 
Placebo 
27 
13 
27 
14 
0 
4 
25 g glucose 
26 
11 
25 
12 
À1 
7 
60 g glucose 
30 
12 
29 
13 
À1 
6 
Caffeine-glucose 
26 
12 
27 
12 
1 
5 
Tracking score 
Placebo 
429 
59 
415 
80 
À14 
86 
25 g glucose 
378 
130 
288 
533 
À5 
7 4 
60 g glucose 
358 
183 
378 
99 
À11 
108 
Caffeine-glucose 
384 
129 
362 
166 
À21 
102 
Tracking timeouts (number) 
Placebo 
36 
41 
46 
66 
2 
48 
25 g glucose 
71 
94 
151 
493 
1 
55 
60 g glucose 
87 
152 
65 
67 
6 
77 
Caffeine-glucose 
64 
79 
76 
103 
11 
75 
Working memory score 
Placebo 
4383 
1863 
5002 
1989 
619 
1157 
25 g glucose 
4728 
1863 
5017 
1843 
289 
1092 
60 g glucose 
5212 
2037 
6260 
2451 
845 
1344 
Caffeine-glucose 
4639 
2006 
5232 
2280 
515 
1142 
Working memory responses (number) 
Placebo 
504 
232 
559 
264 
43 
93 
25 g glucose 
518 
217 
590 
228 
71 
121 
60 g glucose 
556 
198 
590 
215 
34 
129 
Caffeine-glucose 
595 
221 
713 
273 
96 
134 
Working memory errors (number) 
Placebo 
20 
28 
26 
39 
4 
10 
25 g glucose 
21 
24 
27 
30 
6 
13 
60 g glucose 
23 
22 
26 
29 
1 
12 
Caffeine-glucose 
18 
16 
27 
22 
9 
15 
Working memory timeouts (number) 
Placebo 
38 
15 
36 
15 
À1 
7 
25 g glucose 
38 
12 
35 
16 
À3 
8 
60 g glucose 
37 
12 
36 
14 
À1 
6 
Caffeine-glucose 
36 
12 
33 
14 
À3 
8 
Working memory speed (ms) 
Placebo 
1695 
1747 
1600 
1706 
À49 
207 
25 g glucose 
1366 
661 
1229 
517 
À100 
306 </p>

<p>(Continues) </p>

<p> 
glucose, caffeine and multi-tasking </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Human Psychopharmacology: Clinical and Experimental 
published by John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. </p>

<p>Hum. Psychopharmacol Clin Exp 2014; 29: 434-445. 
DOI: 10.1002/hup </p>

<p>did not differ significantly by condition. We cannot, 
however, rule out the possibility that those in the 
caffeine-glucose condition were able to change their 
strategy to optimise their score. However, this seems 
unlikely as the most effective strategy to increase 
overall score is to focus on the working memory task, 
and there was no evidence that this was the case. There 
were significant improvements to the speed of 
performing mental arithmetic associated with the 
caffeine-glucose drink. Those in the combination 
drink were faster than either glucose drink alone, again 
suggesting that caffeine conferred a benefit to perfor-
mance. Mathematical processing requires manipula-
tion of information held in consciousness and, like 
multi-tasking, draws heavily on working memory and </p>

<p>PLA 
25 g GLU 60 g GLU CAFF-GLU </p>

<p>CHANGE FROM BASELINE (score) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>Figure 3. Effects of treatment on multi-tasking performance. Bars show 
mean change from baseline scores ± standard error of mean. 
** p &lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>Table 3. Summary statistics showing treatment effects (mean and SD) on mood measures </p>

<p>Baseline 
pre-MTF </p>

<p>Baseline 
post-MTF </p>

<p>Baseline 
change </p>

<p>Treatment 
pre-MTF </p>

<p>Treatment 
post-MTF </p>

<p>Treatment 
change </p>

<p>Change 
pre-MTF 
change Δ </p>

<p>Mean SD Mean SD 
Mean 
SD Mean SD Mean SD 
Mean 
SD Mean SD Mean SD </p>

<p>Alert 
Placebo 
57 20 
59 17 
2 
15 
66 15 
65 18 
À1 
16 
8 
19 
À2 
20 
25 g glucose 
60 17 
61 18 
1 
11 
67 14 
66 17 
À1 
10 
7 
13 
À2 
1 
60 g glucose 
56 20 
53 19 
À3 
18 
60 17 
59 20 
À1 
16 
4 
17 
2 
20 
Caffeine-glucose 63 18 
60 19 
À3 
16 
71 14 
66 16 
À5 
15 
9 
14 
À2 
18 
Calm 
Placebo 
67 16 
58 20 
À9 
18 
58 65 
54 19 
À4 
16 
À9 
20 
6 
22 
25 g glucose 
69 13 
58 18 
À10 
17 
65 17 
55 22 
À10 
15 
À4 
13 
1 
13 
60 g glucose 
64 17 
57 16 
À8 
16 
60 16 
55 16 
À5 
13 
À4 
18 
3 
17 
Caffeine-glucose 70 15 
59 18 
À12 
13 
61 20 
59 21 
À2 
20 
À9 
16 
10 
17 
Content 
Placebo 
70 16 
68 16 
À2 
12 
72 14 
73 14 
1 
11 
2 
13 
4 
15 
25 g glucose 
70 15 
69 15 
À1 
10 
73 13 
72 15 
À2 
8 
3 
9 
À1 
10 
60 g glucose 
67 12 
62 12 
À5 
13 
69 11 
66 13 
À3 
10 
2 
12 
2 
11 
Caffeine-glucose 71 20 
67 16 
À4 
15 
72 13 
71 12 
À2 
9 
À1 
10 
3 
19 
Fatigue 
Placebo 
46 
2.65 54 
2.06 
0.72 2.22 37 
2.10 49 
2.38 
1.21 2.34 À0.92 2.34 
0.59 2.92 
25 g glucose 
41 
2.29 52 
2.09 
1.14 1.98 36 
1.85 50 
2.28 
1.42 1.99 À0.47 1.48 
0.33 2.18 
60 g glucose 
40 
2.75 51 
2.56 
1.09 2.16 35 
2.33 49 
2.42 
1.45 2.39 À0.57 2.88 
0.42 3.13 
Caffeine-glucose 39 
2.69 53 
2.47 
1.39 2.23 29 
1.83 44 
2.48 
1.55 2.51 À0.96 2.46 À0.18 1.97 
Stress 
Placebo 
28 
2.17 39 
2.38 
1.23 2.28 28 
1.77 40 
2.57 
1.24 2.21 
0.16 1.58 
0.07 2.06 
25 g glucose 
26 
1.98 39 
1.99 
1.31 2.02 29 
1.94 41 
2.24 
1.22 2.02 
0.24 1.94 À0.04 1.79 
60 g glucose 
23 
1.98 38 
2.12 
1.50 1.71 25 
1.89 35 
2.27 
0.97 1.99 
0.23 1.91 À0.45 2.39 
Caffeine-glucose 26 
2.35 42 
2.41 
1.64 2.48 26 
2.21 37 
2.58 
1.18 2.26 
0.19 1.22 À0.84 2.39 
State anxiety Placebo 
45 
5.05 44 
5.17 À0.92 3.57 44 
4.84 43 
6.02 À0.05 4.8 À0.89 3.67 
0.42 5.33 
25 g glucose 
45 
5.60 43 
5.06 À1.49 4.01 43 
5.25 44 
5.3 
0.4 
3.09 À1.65 3.67 
1.89 5.13 
60 g glucose 
44 
4.88 44 
4.20 À0.27 4.07 43 
5.24 43 
5.89 
0 
4.82 À0.78 4.41 
0.27 6.18 
Caffeine-glucose 44 
4.62 42 
4.69 À2.84 3.85 44 
5.46 42 
6.41 À1.67 3.81 À1 
2.85 
1.16 4.15 </p>

<p>Table 2. (Continued) </p>

<p>Baseline 
Post-treatment 
Change from baseline </p>

<p>Mean 
SD 
Mean 
SD 
Mean 
SD </p>

<p>60 g glucose 
1388 
1199 
1256 
797 
À37 
197 
Caffeine-glucose 
1251 
669 
1109 
618 
À143 
212 
Working memory list retrieves (number) 
Placebo 
3 
8 
3 
8 
0 
1 
25 g glucose 
2 
2 
1 
1 
0 
1 
60 g glucose 
1 
1 
1 
1 
0 
1 
Caffeine-glucose 
2 
3 
1 
2 
À1 
1 </p>

<p>Means with SDs are shown. 
a Significant main effect. 
b Trend towards a main effect of treatment on change-from-baseline scores. </p>

<p>442 
a. scholey ET AL. </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Human Psychopharmacology: Clinical and Experimental 
published by John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. </p>

<p>Hum. Psychopharmacol Clin Exp 2014; 29: 434-445. 
DOI: 10.1002/hup </p>

<p>executive processes. Taken together, these findings 
suggest that the caffeine-glucose combination can im-
prove executive functioning through the allocation of 
more attentional resources to multi-task performance. 
There was also some evidence of improvements to 
the speed of responding on the Stroop module. The 
Stroop task is a classic measure of selective attention 
and response inhibition. Again, effective performance 
relies on executive responses-in this case, inhibiting 
the response to the word meaning in favour of its per-
ceptual properties. 
Counter to our hypotheses, there were no behav-
ioural effects of either dose of glucose alone. Those 
in the 25 g glucose condition had numerically better 
performance (although this did not approach statistical </p>

<p>significance), whereas performance in the 60 g condi-
tion was similar to that in placebo and significantly 
worse than that in the caffeine-glucose drink. These 
performance differences between the two glucose-only 
conditions support the notion of an inverted U dose-
response curve for glucose on some aspects of cogni-
tion (Riby, 2004). With regard to specific outcomes, 
in previous studies examining the effects of glucose 
on sequentially performed tasks, 25 g glucose has im-
proved working memory (serial subtraction) perfor-
mance (Scholey et al., 2001). On the other hand, 
performance of a task very similar to the working 
memory module in the current study was unaffected 
by 37.5 g glucose, either alone or in combination with 
glucose (Scholey and Kennedy, 2004). Owen et al. 
(2012) specifically compared the mood and cognitive 
effects of 25 and 60 g glucose drinks. Her data reveal 
a complex pattern of effects, with the two doses 
interacting differentially with task type and fast dura-
tion. The 25 g drink was associated with better serial 
sevens performance following a 2-h fast only, and 
faster choice reaction times following an overnight fast 
only. The 60 g dose speeded word recognition and 
improved serial threes performance following an over-
night (but not 2 h) fast. None of the affected tasks were 
a direct analogue of those in the current study. Never-
theless, we have previously argued that tasks that 
require higher levels of mental effort for effective </p>

<p>Table 4. Summary statistics showing treatment effects (mean and SD) on measures derived from the NASA-TLX </p>

<p>Baseline 
Post-treatment 
Change from baseline </p>

<p>Mean 
SD 
Mean 
SD 
Mean 
SD </p>

<p>Mental demand 
Placebo 
61 
21 
60 
24 
À1 
1 6 
25 g glucose 
63 
18 
58 
24 
À4 
1 9 
60 g glucose 
53 
23 
53 
25 
À1 
2 1 
Caffeine-glucose 
59 
17 
58 
18 
0 
15 
Physical demand 
Placebo 
28 
21 
32 
26 
4 
16 
25 g glucose 
29 
22 
27 
20 
À2 
1 3 
60 g glucose 
29 
25 
33 
26 
5 
12 
Caffeine-glucose 
24 
18 
31 
22 
8 
18 
Temporal demand 
Placebo 
65 
20 
62 
25 
À3 
2 2 
25 g glucose 
63 
19 
61 
24 
À2 
1 8 
60 g glucose 
60 
17 
55 
22 
À5 
1 9 
Caffeine-glucose 
60 
18 
55 
21 
À5 
1 5 
Performance 
Placebo 
34 
17 
32 
16 
À3 
1 9 
25 g glucose 
41 
17 
37 
21 
À4 
2 0 
60 g glucose 
44 
22 
40 
22 
À4 
2 0 
Caffeine-glucose 
35 
20 
33 
22 
À2 
2 3 
Effort 
Placebo 
68 
18 
65 
19 
À2 
1 1 
25 g glucose 
66 
17 
63 
24 
À3 
1 4 
60 g glucose 
64 
21 
62 
20 
À2 
1 8 
Caffeine-glucose 
62 
18 
56 
21 
À7 
1 7 
Frustration 
Placebo 
42 
24 
42 
22 
0 
22 
25 g glucose 
36 
23 
36 
24 
0 
16 
60 g glucose 
42 
22 
40 
23 
À2 
2 2 
Caffeine-glucose 
36 
26 
37 
23 
1 
20 </p>

<p>Table 5. Number of participants guessing which treatment they had 
received by condition </p>

<p>Treatment guessed (N) </p>

<p>Placebo 25 g glucose 60 g glucose Caffeine-glucose </p>

<p>Placebo 
6 
15 
8 
8 
25 g glucose 
6 
17 
10 
5 
60 g glucose 
8 
14 
14 
3 
Caffeine-glucose 7 
12 
6 
11 
p 
0.938 
0.826 
0.298 
0.142 </p>

<p>p indicates probability of difference from chance values within each treat-
ment guessed. </p>

<p> 
glucose, caffeine and multi-tasking </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Human Psychopharmacology: Clinical and Experimental 
published by John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. </p>

<p>Hum. Psychopharmacol Clin Exp 2014; 29: 434-445. 
DOI: 10.1002/hup </p>

<p>execution are more susceptible to the glucose enhance-
ment effect. It might be assumed that multi-tasking 
would fall into this category, and indeed the mood 
changes associated performing the MTF support this 
contention. On the other hand, previous studies that 
have found effects of glucose (usually 25 g) during 
dual tasking have included more individual task such 
as effortful psychomotor tracking (Scholey et al., 
2009b) or repeated, alternating hand movements 
(Sünram-Lea et al., 2002). The effect may be because 
such tasks are more effortful than the MTF used in 
the current study, for example, co-performing hand 
movements can reduce memory performance to near 
chance levels (Scholey et al., 2013; Scholey et al., 
2006). Alternatively, previous dual tasking studies 
have typically included a declarative memory compo-
nent, which may be more susceptible to the glucose-
related enhancement. 
These positive effects seen here may be due to the 
additive/synergistic effects of glucose and caffeine in 
combination, supporting previous behavioural studies 
showing that the effects of caffeine and glucose 
together were significantly better than those of either 
substance alone (Scholey and Kennedy, 2004). Alter-
natively, at present, we cannot rule out the possibility 
that they may be attributable to caffeine contained 
within this treatment only. Future studies should com-
pare the effects of caffeine alone with the other treat-
ments used in the current study. 
There were no mood changes associated with any 
drink. This is consistent with much of the previous lit-
erature regarding glucose. However, caffeine is often 
associated with alerting effects, although these are 
most easily detected in individuals who are in a depri-
vation state owing to (e.g.) fatigue and are most readily 
found with higher caffeine doses. In any case, these 
findings suggest that the significant improvement in 
multi-tasking performance following the caffeine-
glucose drink reflects direct effects on performance 
rather than a secondary effect of improved arousal/ 
alertness. 
It is worth noting that the mean body mass index of 
the participants is towards the high end of the normal 
range (mean body mass index = 24.36, SD 4.47). We 
have previously reported that body composition differ-
entially influences glucose absorption and possibly 
cognitive responses to glucose (Owen et al., 2013). 
Further work might usefully be directed to discerning 
the effect of body composition on cognitive responses 
to various nutritional interventions. 
In summary, a drink containing 40 mg caffeine/60 g 
glucose improved performance of an ecologically valid 
task of multi-tasking. As the same drink improved </p>

<p>aspects of executive functioning and attention, it is possible 
that increased allocation of attentional resources underlie 
this effect. Further work should be aimed at delineating 
the underlying mechanisms of these effects, including the 
use of functional brain imaging. It would be of great interest 
to examine different levels of glucose in combination with 
caffeine in order to determine the threshold levels of the 
two substances for positive effects on multi-tasking. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>B. V. O. N. and C. P. are employees of GlaxoSmithKline. 
A. S., L. O. and C. S. have received research funding, 
consultancy and/or speakers fees from industry sources. 
The other authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </p>

<p>This study was funded by GlaxoSmithKline and grant num-
ber DP1093834 from the Australian Research Council. </p>



<p> 
a. scholey ET AL. </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Human Psychopharmacology: Clinical and Experimental 
published by John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. </p>

<p>Hum. Psychopharmacol Clin Exp 2014; 29: 434-445. 
DOI: 10.1002/hup </p>



<p> 
glucose, caffeine and multi-tasking </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Human Psychopharmacology: Clinical and Experimental 
published by John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. </p>

<p>Hum. Psychopharmacol Clin Exp 2014; 29: 434-445. 
DOI: 10.1002/hup </p>

</text></tei>