<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4234239" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Aims/Introduction: To compare carotid and lower limb atherosclerotic lesions, and 
examine if carotid atherosclerotic lesions are in line with lower limb atherosclerotic lesions, 
and can reflect generalized atherosclerosis in inpatients with type 2 diabetes. 
Materials and Methods: This was an observational study carried out in 867 Chinese 
inpatients with type 2 diabetes, including 573 previously known and 294 newly diagnosed 
patients. Ultrasonographic assessments of intima-media thickness (IMT), plaques, and 
stenosis in the carotid and lower limb arteries were evaluated. Atherosclerotic lesions 
between the carotid and lower limb arteries were compared in both previously known 
and newly diagnosed diabetes, respectively. 
Results: In both the known (77.3% vs 49.4%, P &lt; 0.001) and the newly diagnosed dia-
betes (55.4% vs 29.9%, P &lt; 0.001), the prevalence of atherosclerotic plaques was signifi-
cantly higher in the lower limb arteries than in the carotid arteries. Likewise, the 
prevalence of stenosis was also significantly higher (P &lt; 0.001) in the lower limb arteries 
(16.9%) than in the carotid arteries (4.2%) in the established diabetes patients. However, 
there was no significant difference in the mean IMT between common carotid and com-
mon femoral arteries in both the previously known (0.90 -0.24 mm vs 0.89 -0.20 mm, 
P = 0.675) and the newly diagnosed diabetes patients (0.86 -0.22 mm vs 
0.85 -0.16 mm, P = 0.436). 
Conclusions: Carotid plaques might underestimate generalized plaques in inpatients 
with type 2 diabetes, as shown by its significantly lower prevalence compared with that of 
the lower extremity arteries. A combined carotid and lower limb ultrasound examination 
can improve the detection of atherosclerotic lesions in inpatients with type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p>lesions commonly occur 2 . Diabetes accelerates the progression 
of atherosclerosis, and increases the incidence of myocardial 
infarction, stroke and peripheral arterial disease 2-5 . Therefore, 
early detection of atherosclerosis in individuals with diabetes is 
crucial in reducing the risk of cardiovascular, cerebrovascular 
and amputation events. 
Currently, ultrasound examination of carotid arteries is used 
to investigate the signs of early atherosclerotic vascular disease. </p>

<p> †These authors equally contributed to this work. 
Received 16 November 2012; revised 11 December 2013; accepted 7 January 2014 </p>

<p>734 </p>

<p>J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 6 November 2014 
ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by Asian Association of the Study of Diabetes (AASD) and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License, which permits use, distribution and 
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes. </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E </p>

<p>Carotid atherosclerotic lesions are regarded as an indicator of 
generalized atherosclerosis. For example, previous studies 
showed that carotid atherosclerosis detected by ultrasonography 
could be an appropriate marker of atherosclerotic disease, and 
had been shown to independently reflect both cardiovascular 
and cerebrovascular events 6-8 . However, there is controversy 
whether carotid atherosclerosis detected by ultrasonography can 
be used as a surrogate marker of generalized atherosclerosis. 
For example, there are studies that showed that plaque forma-
tion in the carotid arteries was weakly associated with plaques 
in other peripheral arteries 9,10 . In particular, based on ultraso-
nography, studies comparing the difference of carotid and lower 
limb atherosclerotic lesions in type 2 diabetes are almost com-
pletely lacking. 
In a previous study, we found that combining carotid and 
lower limb ultrasound examination could improve the detection 
of atherosclerotic plaques in patients with type 2 diabetes 11 . In 
the present study, we further compared the intima-media thick-
ness (IMT) value and the prevalence of atherosclerotic plaques 
and stenosis between the carotid and lower limb arteries, and 
examined if carotid atherosclerotic lesions were in parallel with 
lower extremity atherosclerotic lesions in patients with type 2 
diabetes using vascular Doppler ultrasonography. Given the fact 
that the duration of diabetes is an important risk factor for ath-
erosclerosis of carotid and lower limb arteries in type 2 diabe-
tes 11 , we divided the type 2 diabetics into previously known 
and newly diagnosed patients, and investigated if the character-
istics of atherosclerotic lesions were different between the previ-
ously known and the newly diagnosed patients with type 2 
diabetes. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Participants and Study Design 
The current study was a cross-sectional study and partly based 
on data used in our previous study 11 . Between May 2007 and 
July 2008, 917 consecutive type 2 diabetes patients who were 
admitted to the Department of Endocrinology and Metabolism, 
Shanghai Jiao Tong University Affiliated Sixth People's Hospi-
tal, Shanghai, China, were observed, and valid information was 
available for 867 patients including 573 previously known and 
294 newly diagnosed patients with type 2 diabetes in the pres-
ent study. According to the World Health Organization crite-
ria 12 , newly diagnosed diabetes was defined as having either 
fasting plasma glucose (FPG) ≥7.0 mmol/L and/or 2-h post-
prandial plasma glucose (2-h PPG) ≥11.1 mmol/L or a 2-h 
plasma glucose ≥11.1 mmol/L during a 75-g oral glucose toler-
ance test in patients without a history of diabetes. Previously 
known diabetes was defined based on self-reported physician 
diagnosis or use of antidiabetic agents. The definition of dia-
betic retinopathy, diabetic nephropathy and cardiocerebrovascu-
lar events was according to our previous study 11 . All 
participants were interviewed to obtain their history of hyper-
tension, cardiocerebrovascular events, alcohol consumption and 
smoking habits, and underwent an ultrasonographic evaluation </p>

<p>of IMT, plaque, and stenosis in both the carotid and lower 
extremity arteries. The study was approved by the Ethics Com-
mittee of the hospital, and all participants gave written 
informed consent. </p>

<p>Physical Examination and Laboratory Assays 
A physical examination including weight, height and blood 
pressure was carried out. Body mass index (BMI) was calcu-
lated as weight divided by height squared. Hypertension was 
defined according to our previously described criteria 11 . Blood 
samples for plasma glucose; C-peptide; glycated hemoglobin 
A1c (HbA1c); renal function tests including blood urea 
nitrogen (BUN), serum creatinine (Scr) and blood uric 
acid (BUA); liver function tests including aspartate 
aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and 
c-glutamyltransferase (c-GT); and lipid levels including total 
cholesterol (TC), total triglycerides (TG), high-density lipopro-
tein cholesterol (HDL-C) and low density lipoprotein choles-
terol (LDL-C) were obtained after an overnight fast, and 2 h 
after breakfast. </p>

<p>Ultrasonography Measurements 
Color Doppler sonography was carried out with an Acuson 
Sequoia 512 (Siemens Medical Solutions, Mountain View, CA, 
USA) scanner equipped with a 5-13-MHz linear array trans-
ducer. The ultrasonographic examination was carried out by 
three experienced ultrasonographers according to a standard-
ized technique. After the participants had remained in the 
supine position for 5 min, the transducer was placed on the 
neck and lower limbs to show both vessel imaging and blood 
flow characteristics. At each location, IMT, atherosclerotic pla-
ques and stenosis were recorded. Carotid arteries were exam-
ined bilaterally at the levels of the common carotid arteries, 
the bifurcation, the external carotid arteries, and the internal 
carotid arteries from transverse and longitudinal orientations. 
Seven locations of each lower limb artery were evaluated: 
common femoral artery, profunda femoris artery, superficial 
femoral artery, popliteal artery, anterior tibial artery, posterior 
tibial artery and peroneal artery. The IMT was defined as the 
distance between the leading edge of the lumen-intima echo 
and the leading edge of the media-adventitia echo. The mean 
IMT was defined as the mean of IMT in both right and left 
sides of the common carotid artery or common femoral 
artery. Atherosclerotic plaque was defined as a focal structure 
encroaching into the arterial lumen of 0.5 mm or 50% of the 
surrounding IMT value or IMT of &gt;1.5 mm 13 . Carotid athero-
sclerotic plaque was defined as the presence of atherosclerotic 
plaques in any of the aforementioned carotid arteries seg-
ments 11,14 . Lower limb atherosclerotic plaque was defined as 
the presence of atherosclerotic plaques in any of the above-
mentioned lower limb artery segments 11 . Based on previous 
literature 15-17 , artery stenosis in the present study was classi-
fied into three categories: normal, 1-49% diameter reduction 
and ≥50% diameter reduction. A significant artery stenosis </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd 
J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 6 November 2014 </p>



<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi 
Comparison of atherosclerotic lesions </p>

<p>was defined as ≥50% stenosis. Both the intraobserver and inte-
robserver reproducibility were determined using Spearman's 
correlation coefficient. The intraobserver correlation coefficients 
were 0.91-0.92 for carotid IMT and 0.92-0.94 for femoral 
IMT, 0.88-0.89 for carotid plaque and 0.89-0.94 for lower 
limb arterial plaque, and 0.87-0.94 for carotid stenosis and 
0.94-1.00 for lower limb arterial stenosis, respectively. The in-
terobserver correlation coefficients were 0.87-0.97 for carotid 
IMT and 0.95-0.97 for femoral IMT, 0.83-0.94 for carotid 
plaque and 0.89-0.94 for lower limb arterial plaque, and 0.82-
0.89 for carotid stenosis and 0.83-0.89 for lower limb arterial 
stenosis, respectively. </p>

<p>Comparison of Carotid and Lower Limb Atherosclerotic 
Lesions 
The comparisons of carotid and lower limb atherosclerotic 
lesions in the present study population were based on the 
comparison of atherosclerotic plaques, stenosis and IMT. The 
comparisons of atherosclerotic plaques and stenosis were carried 
out at both the patient-level and vessel-level. In the vessel-level 
analysis, the left carotid artery, the right carotid artery, the left 
lower limb artery and the right lower limb artery were consid-
ered separately. In the patient-level analysis, the prevalence of 
plaque and stenosis between the carotid and lower limb arteries 
was compared. In addition to comparing the prevalence of ath-
erosclerotic plaques, the prevalence of artery stenosis and signifi-
cant artery stenosis was also compared. The comparison of IMT 
was carried out between the mean common carotid IMT and 
the mean common femoral IMT. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
The data were analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">11.0</rs> for Windows (SPSS 
Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). For continuous variables, the Kol-
mogorov-Smirnov test was applied to examine normal distribu-
tion. Continuous variables were expressed as mean -standard 
deviation, and compared by two-sided t-tests or, if the data 
were not distributed normally, variables were expressed as med-
ian with interquartile range and the Mann-Whitney U-test was 
used. Categorical variables were expressed as percentages and 
using a v 2 -test or Fisher's exact test. Linear regression was used 
to evaluate differences of continuous variables while adjusting 
for age and/or sex. Binary logistic regression was used to evalu-
ate differences of categorical variables while adjusting for age 
and/or sex. A two-sided alpha level of 0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Clinical Characteristics of the Study Patients 
The clinical characteristics of the 867 inpatients with type 2 
diabetes are shown in Table 1. The mean age of the previously 
known diabetics (62 -11 years) was significantly older than 
that of the newly diagnosed diabetics (52 -15 years). Interest-
ingly, after adjustment for age and sex, only the lower limb 
atherosclerotic lesions in the previously known type 2 diabetics </p>

<p>were more severe than in the newly diagnosed type 2 diabetes. 
The prevalence of diabetic retinopathy, diabetic nephropathy 
and cardiocerebrovascular events was markedly higher in 
the previously known diabetics than in the newly diagnosed 
diabetics, even after adjustment for age and sex. </p>

<p>Comparison of Carotid and Lower Limb Atherosclerotic 
Plaques 
The comparison of carotid and lower limb atherosclerotic 
plaques is shown in Figure 1. Patient-level analysis showed that 
in both the previously known diabetes group and in the newly 
diagnosed diabetes group, the prevalence of atherosclerotic pla-
ques was significantly higher in the lower limb arteries than in 
the carotid arteries (all P &lt; 0.001; Figure 1a). 
Vessel-level analysis showed that both in the previously 
known group and in the newly diagnosed diabetes group, more 
than 50% of the left and right lower limb arteries had athero-
sclerotic plaques, giving them the highest prevalence of plaque 
in our patient population (Figure 1b). Between 25 and 50% of 
the left and right carotid arteries had plaques in the previously 
known diabetes (Figure 1b). Less than 25% of the left and right 
carotid arteries were diseased in the newly diagnosed patients 
with diabetes, giving them the lowest prevalence of plaque in 
our patient population (Figure 1b). 
In contrast, the prevalence of isolated carotid plaque was 
6.8%, isolated lower extremity plaque 32.3%, and plaques in 
both the carotid and lower extremity arteries 23.1% in the 
newly diagnosed diabetes patients (Figure 1c). However, more 
patients tended to have atherosclerotic plaques in both the car-
otid and lower limbs (43.4%) than in either the isolated carotid 
(5.9%) or in the isolated lower limb arteries (33.9%) in the pre-
viously known diabetes patients (Figure 1c). </p>

<p>Comparison of Carotid and Lower Limb Atherosclerotic 
Stenosis 
Figure 2 shows the comparison of carotid and lower limb 
atherosclerotic stenosis. In the patient-level analysis, the 
prevalence of atherosclerotic stenosis was significantly higher 
in the lower limb arteries than in the carotid arteries in the 
established diabetes (Figure 2a). In contrast, the prevalence of 
stenosis was not significantly different between the carotid 
and lower limb arteries in the newly diagnosed diabetes 
patients (Figure 2a). In the newly diagnosed diabetes patients, 
the prevalence of isolated carotid arterial stenosis and isolated 
lower extremity arterial stenosis was 3.0 and 4.8%, and there 
was no stenosis in both the carotid and lower extremity 
arteries (Figure 2b). In the previously known diabetes, artery 
stenosis tended to be more often seen just in the lower limb 
arteries, which was much higher than in either isolated caro-
tid arteries or in both the carotid and lower limb arteries 
(Figure 2b). 
In the vessel-level analysis, the left lower limb artery (16.6%) 
had the greatest prevalence in the previously known diabetes 
patients, followed by the right lower limb artery (16.2%), and </p>



<p>J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 6 November 2014 
ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
Li et al. 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi </p>

<p>the left and right carotid artery (all 3.3%; Figure 2c). Similarly, 
in the newly diagnosed type 2 diabetes, the left and right lower 
limb artery (all 4.1%) had the greatest prevalence, followed by 
the left carotid artery (2.4%) and the right carotid artery (1.7%; 
Figure 2c). 
When considering the prevalence of significant artery steno-
sis (≥50% stenosis) in the previously known diabetes, the left 
carotid artery had a prevalence of 73.7%, the left lower limb 
artery 71.6%, the right lower limb artery 67.8% and the right 
carotid artery 52.6%, respectively (Figure 2d). In contrast, in 
the newly diagnosed diabetes, the left and right lower limb 
arteries had the greatest prevalence of significant artery stenosis 
(all 66.7%), and there was a prevalence of significant artery ste-</p>

<p>nosis of 12.5% in the left carotid artery (Figure 2d). The right 
carotid artery had no significant artery stenosis in the newly 
diagnosed diabetes (Figure 2d). </p>

<p>Comparison of Mean IMT Between Common Carotid and 
Common Femoral Arteries 
The comparison of mean IMT between common carotid and 
common femoral arteries is presented in Figure 3. In both the 
previously known diabetes group (0.90 -0.24 mm vs 
0.89 -0.20 mm) and the newly diagnosed diabetes group 
(0.86 -0.22 mm vs 0.85 -0.16 mm), there was no significant 
difference between the mean common carotid IMT and the 
mean common femoral IMT (Figure 3). </p>

<p>Table 1 | Characteristics and comparison between previously known and newly diagnosed type 2 diabetes patients </p>

<p>Variables 
Previously known type 
2 diabetes (n = 573) </p>

<p>Newly diagnosed 
type 2 diabetes (n = 294) </p>

<p>P-value 
P-value* </p>

<p>Male, n (%) 
284 (49.6%) 
191 (65.0%) 
&lt;0.001 
0.02 
Age (years) 
62 -11 
52 -15 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
Duration of diabetes (months) 
118 -79 
-
-
Smoking, n (%) 
133 (23.2%) 
61 (20.8%) 
0.503 
0.615 
Alcohol, n (%) 
162 (28.3) 
87 (29.6%) 
0.712 
0.789 
Hypertension, n (%) 
308 (53.8%) 
115 (39.1%) 
&lt;0.001 
0.242 
Hyperlipidemia, n (%) 
450 (78.5%) 
203 (69.0%) 
0.227 
0.428 
Body mass index (kg/m 2 ) 
24.79 -3.59 
25.26 -3.71 
0.079 
0.454 
Waist circumference (cm) † 
89 (83-96) 
90 (84-96) 
0.508 
0.537 
Systolic blood pressure (mmHg) 
133 -18 
127 -15 
&lt;0.001 
0.049 
Diastolic blood pressure (mmHg) 
90 -9 
8 1 -10 
0.202 
0.309 
Aspartate aminotransferase (U/L) † 
19 (14-29) 
26 (16.5-42.5) 
&lt;0.001 
0.003 
Alanine aminotransferase (U/L) † 
19 (16-24) 
23 (17-32) 
&lt;0.001 
0.027 
c-glutamyltransferase (U/L) † 
23 (16-40) 
31 (21.5-53.5) 
&lt;0.001 
0.479 
Blood urea nitrogen (lmol/L) † 
5.50 (4.53-6.70) 
4.9 (4.0-6.3) 
&lt;0.001 
0.079 
Serum creatinine (lmol/L) † 
67 (56-80) 
68 (56-80) 
0.996 
0.734 
Blood uric acid (lmol/L) † 
313 (255-371) 
303 (241-373) 
0.319 
0.310 
Total triglycerides (mmol/L) † 
1.40 (0.98-2.12) 
1.51 (1.07-2.13) 
0.081 
0.746 
Total cholesterol (mmol/L) † 
4.50 (4.00-5.30) 
4.90 (4.10-5.61) 
0.001 
0.003 
High-density lipoprotein (mmol/L) † 
1.11 (0.95-1.31) 
1.05 (0.89-1.23) 
0.001 
0.416 
Low-density lipoprotein (mmol/L) † 
2.91 (2.42-3.40) 
3.30 (2.57-3.99) 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
Fasting plasma glucose (mmol/L) † 
7.46 (5.84-9.30) 
8.57 (6.79-11.33) 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
2 h plasma glucose (mmol/L) 
12.77 -4.44 
15.58 -5.63 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
Fasting C-peptide (ng/mL) † 
1.71 (1.07-2.59) 
1.65 (0.88-2.43) 
0.616 
0.102 
2-h Postprandial C-peptide(ng/mL) † 
3.84 (2.15-5.68) 
3.34 (1.9-5.48) 
0.105 
0.732 
Glycated hemoglobin A1C (%) 
8.82 -2.42 
10.86 -2.50 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
Mean femoral IMT (mm) 
0.89 -0.20 
0.85 -0.16 
0.005 
0.045 
Mean carotid IMT (mm) 
0.87 -0.24 
0.79 -0.23 
&lt;0.001 
0.849 
Carotid plaques, n (%) 
283 (49.4%) 
88 (29.9%) 
&lt;0.001 
0.135 
Lower limb plaques, n (%) 
443 (77.3%) 
163 (55.4%) 
&lt;0.001 
0.052 
Carotid stenosis, n (%) 
24 (4.2%) 
9 (3.1%) 
0.412 
0.425 
Lower limb stenosis, n (%) 
97 (16.9%) 
14 (4.8%) 
&lt;0.001 
0.010 
Diabetic retinopathy, n (%) 
171 (29.8%) 
47 (16.0%) 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
Diabetic nephropathy, n (%) 
163 (28.4%) 
26 (8.8%) 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
Cardio-cerebrovascular events, n (%) 
132 (23%) 
23 (7.8%) 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Values are expressed as the mean -standard deviation, or median with interquartile range, or percentages.  †Non-normal distribution of continuous 
variables. The P-values were not adjusted for age and sex for trend. *The P values were adjusted for age and sex for trend. </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd 
J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 6 November 2014 </p>



<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi 
Comparison of atherosclerotic lesions </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Carotid ultrasonography is presently widely used as a means 
of assessing atherosclerotic changes in type 2 diabetes 18-20 . 
Meanwhile, carotid atherosclerosis has been commonly 
recognized as an indicator of general atherosclerosis because of 
its relationship to coronary atherosclerosis, lower limb athero-
sclerosis and atherosclerosis elsewhere in the circulation 21-23 . 
For example, Hulthe et al. 24 showed that the presence of 
atherosclerosis in the carotid arteries is known to be reflective 
for the extent of coronary atherosclerosis. Another previous </p>

<p>study found that there was a significant correlation between 
carotid artery disease and lower extremity arterial disease in a 
healthy population of elderly adults with isolated systolic hyper-
tension 25 . Therefore, carotid atherosclerosis appears to mark the 
presence of generalized atherosclerosis. 
However, conflicting results have been reported for the corre-
lation between carotid atherosclerosis and atherosclerosis else-
where in the arterial system. Furthermore, little has been 
published regarding the comparison of carotid and lower limb 
artery atherosclerotic lesions in patients with diabetes. For </p>

<p>100% 
(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>(c) </p>

<p>75% 
P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>32.3% </p>

<p>23.1% </p>

<p>43.4% 
Isolated carotid AS 
Isolated lower limb AS 
AS in both carotid and 
lower limb arteries </p>

<p>33.9% </p>

<p>P = 0.034 
P = 0.009 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>29.9% </p>

<p>Newly diagnosed diabetes </p>

<p>LCA RCA LLLA RLLA 
LCA RCA LLLA RLLA </p>

<p>Previously known diabetes </p>

<p>55.4% 
49.4% </p>

<p>77.3% </p>

<p>Carotid arteries 
Lower limb arteries </p>

<p>Without AS </p>

<p>With AS 
Prevalence of atherosclerosis </p>

<p>Prevalence of atherosclerosis </p>

<p>Percentage </p>

<p>25% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>75% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>Newly diagnosed diabetes 
Previously known diabetes </p>

<p>Newly diagnosed diabetes 
Previously known diabetes </p>

<p>25% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>15% </p>

<p>30% </p>

<p>45% </p>

<p>60% </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Comparison of carotid and lower limb atherosclerotic plaques in both the previously known and the newly diagnosed diabetes 
patients. (a) The comparison of the prevalence of atherosclerotic plaques in the carotid and lower limb arteries. (b) The comparison of the 
prevalence of atherosclerotic plaques in the left carotid, right carotid, left lower limb and right lower limb artery. An artery was considered normal 
if there was no evidence of atherosclerotic plaque present. An artery was considered "diseased" if there was evidence of any level of 
atherosclerotic plaque. (c) The percentage of patients with atherosclerotic plaques. The patients with plaques were divided into three groups 
including the patients with isolated carotid plaque, patients with isolated lower extremity plaque, and patients with plaques in both the carotid 
and lower extremity arteries. The P-values for three group comparisons were all &lt;0.001 in both the newly diagnosed diabetes patients and the 
previously known diabetes patients. LCA, left carotid artery; LLLA, left lower limb artery; RCA, right carotid artery; RLLA, right lower limb artery. </p>



<p>J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 6 November 2014 
ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
Li et al. 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi </p>

<p>example, there are studies showing that the presence of athero-
sclerotic plaques in the carotid arteries does not reflect athero-
sclerosis elsewhere in the arterial system 9,10,26 . This view might 
be further strengthened by findings from a study in which 
there is no correlation between the degree of lower extremity 
atherosclerosis and asymptomatic carotid artery stenosis &gt;50% 
in male veterans with symptomatic lower limb atherosclerosis 27 . 
Furthermore, Sosnowski et al. 28 believe that the presence of 
femoral atherosclerotic plaque more precisely than that of the 
carotid plaque reflects the probability and severity of coronary 
artery atherosclerosis. </p>

<p>The present findings in a hospital-based sample of type 2 
diabetes also showed that the plaque and stenosis in the carotid 
arteries did not indicate those in the lower extremity arteries in 
both the known and newly diagnosed type 2 diabetes patients, 
although the condition was more severe in the established 
patients with diabetes than in the newly diagnosed patients 
with diabetes. We compared the prevalence of atherosclerotic 
plaques and stenosis between the carotid and lower extremity 
arteries, based on both patient-level and vessel-level analyses. 
Patient-level analyses showed that in both the known and the 
newly diagnosed patients with diabetes, the prevalence of ath-</p>

<p>Newly diagnosed diabetes </p>

<p>1.40 </p>

<p>1.05 </p>

<p>0.70 </p>

<p>0.35 
Mean IMT (mm) </p>

<p>0.00 
Previously known diabetes </p>

<p>Common carotid arteries 
Common femoral arteries </p>

<p>P = 0.675 
P = 0.436 </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Comparison of mean intima-media thickness (IMT) between common carotid and common femoral arteries in both the previously 
known and the newly diagnosed diabetes patients. </p>

<p>24% </p>

<p>(a) 
(b) </p>

<p>(c) 
(d) </p>

<p>18% </p>

<p>12% 
Prevalence of stenosis </p>

<p>6% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>24% </p>

<p>18% </p>

<p>12% 
Prevalence of stenosis </p>

<p>6% </p>

<p>0% 
Newly diagnosed diabetes 
Previously known diabetes </p>

<p>Newly diagnosed diabetes 
Previously known diabetes </p>

<p>Newly diagnosed diabetes 
Previously known diabetes </p>

<p>Carotid arteries 
Lower limb arteries </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P = 0.007 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 
P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P = 0.297 </p>

<p>P = 1.000 </p>

<p>P = 0.297 </p>

<p>4.2% </p>

<p>16.9% </p>

<p>3.1% </p>

<p>4.8% </p>

<p>0.0% </p>

<p>2.1% </p>

<p>14.8% </p>

<p>2.1% </p>

<p>4.8% 
3.1% </p>

<p>Isolated carotid stenosis </p>

<p>Isolated lower limb stenosis </p>

<p>Stenosis in both carotid and 
lower limb arteries </p>

<p>Percentage </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>75% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>25% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>LCA RCA LLLA RLLA 
LCA RCA LLLA RLLA 
Without stenosis </p>

<p>With stenosis </p>

<p>Newly diagnosed diabetes 
Previously known diabetes </p>

<p>Percentage </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>75% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>25% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>LCA RCA LLLA RLLA 
LCA RCA LLLA RLLA 
Stenosis &lt; 50% </p>

<p>Stenosis ≥ 50% </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Comparison of carotid and lower limb atherosclerotic stenosis in both the previously known and the newly diagnosed diabetes 
patients. (a) The comparison of the prevalence of atherosclerotic stenosis in the carotid and lower limb arteries. (b) The percentage of patients with 
stenosis. The patients with stenosis were divided into three groups including patients with isolated carotid stenosis, patients with isolated lower 
extremity stenosis, and patients with stenoses in both the carotid and lower extremity arteries. The P-values for three group comparisons were 
0.001 in the newly diagnosed diabetes patients and &lt;0.001 in the previously known diabetes patients, respectively. (c) The comparison of the 
prevalence of atherosclerotic stenosis in the left carotid, right carotid, left lower limb and right lower limb artery. Artery stenosis including both 1-
49% diameter reduction and ≥50% diameter reduction. (d) The comparison of the prevalence of significant atherosclerotic stenosis in the left 
carotid artery (LCA), right carotid artery (RCA), left lower limb artery (LLLA) and right lower limb artery (RCLA). Stenosis was considered significant if 
it caused ≥50% stenosis of a vessel. </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd 
J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 6 November 2014 </p>



<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi 
Comparison of atherosclerotic lesions </p>

<p>erosclerotic plaques was markedly higher in the lower extremity 
arteries than in the carotid arteries. 
There was a similar trend for the prevalence of stenosis in 
the previously known diabetes patients. In contrast, there was 
no significant difference in the prevalence of stenosis between 
the carotid and the lower extremity arteries in the newly diag-
nosed diabetes patients. When considering the prevalence of 
significant artery stenosis in the previously known diabetes 
patients, there was no significant difference between the lower 
extremity and carotid arteries. However, for the newly diag-
nosed type 2 diabetes, the prevalence of the significant artery 
stenosis was significantly higher in the lower limb artery than 
in the carotid artery, which showed that significant artery ste-
nosis occurred earlier in the limb arteries in type 2 diabetes. 
A previous study showed that the prevalence of carotid pla-
ques was 28% in type 2 diabetic patients at baseline 29 . After a 
2-year follow up, the prevalence of carotid plaques increased to 
62% 29 . A study by Lacroix et al. 30 showed that the prevalence 
of carotid stenosis &lt;60% and ≥60% was 63.6% and 4.7% in 
type 2 diabetic patients, respectively. The prevalence of lower 
extremity diseases was approximately 27% in both undiagnosed 
diabetes and diagnosed diabetes 31 . The higher prevalence of 
diabetic atherosclerotic lesions in the present study might be 
explained by the more serious condition in our studied popula-
tion. Because of their more serious condition, such patients are 
more likely to be hospitalized, and to have a higher prevalence 
of atherosclerotic disease compared with the general population. 
In addition, it might also be explained by the different defini-
tion of atherosclerotic lesions and different measures of athero-
sclerosis in other studies. 
Interestingly, in contrast to atherosclerotic plaques, whether 
in the previously known diabetes patients or in the newly diag-
nosed diabetes patients, there was no marked difference in the 
mean IMT between the common carotid and the common 
femoral arteries. IMT increase is an early event, and appears 
before plaque occurrence in the development of atherosclerosis, 
whereas formation of plaques represents advanced atheroscle-
rotic lesions 32 . Additionally, carotid IMT is under genetic con-
trol, whereas carotid plaque is strongly influenced by 
environmental factors and less influenced by genetic factors 32,33 . 
Ebrahim et al. 34 have provided evidence that carotid plaque 
predicts cardiovascular events better than carotid IMT. Further-
more, the study by Held et al. 35 confirmed that carotid IMT 
was a weak predictor of events, and carotid plaques tended to 
predict the risk of cardiovascular death or myocardial infarc-
tion, whereas femoral artery IMT and plaques predicted the 
risk of revascularization. Therefore, based on the present results 
that carotid artery IMT value was similar to femoral artery 
IMT value, increased carotid IMT might represent a marker of 
general atherosclerosis and can be used as a way to detect early 
atherosclerosis risk populations, such as diabetic patients, in 
which prevention could be more efficient, but evaluations of 
plaques provided better prediction of cardiovascular events than 
assessments of IMT in patients with type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p>Thus, the present findings suggested that carotid plaque and 
stenosis might not represent atherosclerotic burden in type 2 
diabetes, although it appears to do in general populations. 
However, carotid IMT might represent a marker of general ath-
erosclerosis in type 2 diabetic patients. Different rheological 
conditions in the carotid and lower limb arteries could contrib-
ute to the differences presently observed. 
The discrepancy between the present results and findings of 
other studies could be explained by the different definition of 
atherosclerosis and different populations studied by the 
researchers. The differences in study population and the meth-
ods used to assess atherosclerosis likely result in inconsistent 
results between studies. It is possible that carotid atherosclerosis 
is associated with lower limb atherosclerosis only in patients 
with a low risk of cardiovascular disease, but not in those with 
a high risk of cardiovascular disease, such as patients with dia-
betes. For example, in the Rotterdam Study, lower extremity 
atherosclerosis was defined as an ankle-arm index &lt;0.90 in 
subjects aged ≥55 years 21 . However, based on ultrasound 
screening, the ankle-to-brachial index might underestimate the 
prevalence of peripheral occlusive disease in patients with dia-
betes 36 . More studies are required to determine whether carotid 
atherosclerosis reflects lower limb atherosclerosis in a popula-
tion other than diabetes mellitus patients using ultrasound 
examination. 
The present study has potential clinical significance and prac-
tical application. Our findings call into question the widespread 
use of carotid atherosclerotic plaques as an indicator of general 
atherosclerosis in patients with diabetes. The carotid plaque 
severely underestimates the burden of lower extremity athero-
sclerosis in both the previously known and newly diagnosed 
type 2 diabetes patients. The combination of carotid and lower 
extremity ultrasonography will be of considerable use in future 
clinical applications. Although screening the general population 
for lower limb atherosclerosis is currently of unproven value in 
effecting outcomes, it would be cost-effective in a population at 
high risk for atherosclerosis, such as diabetes, coronary artery 
disease and cerebrovascular disease patients. 
Several potential limitations of the current study should be 
mentioned. First, the present sample was limited to inpatients 
with type 2 diabetes. Therefore, caution should be exercised in 
drawing conclusions regarding other populations, such as the 
general population and type 1 diabetic patients. Second, because 
our study design was cross-sectional, we cannot assess the evo-
lution of the process of atherosclerosis. Finally, the present 
study was limited by the small sample size, and a further large-
scale study to confirm our findings would be useful. 
In conclusion, the present study provides evidence that caro-
tid atherosclerotic plaques cannot reflect generalized atheroscle-
rosis in type 2 dietetic patients, as shown by its significantly 
lower prevalence compared with that of the lower extremity 
arteries, which not only exists in previously known diabetics, 
but also in newly diagnosed diabetics. Carotid ultrasonography 
can provide important information of carotid arterial lesions, </p>



<p>J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 6 November 2014 
ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
Li et al. 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi </p>

<p>but cannot accurately assess the presence and severity of ath-
erosclerosis elsewhere in type 2 diabetes. It emphasizes the 
value of the combination of ultrasonography of carotid and 
lower extremity arteries in detection of early atherosclerotic 
lesions in patients with type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS 
This work was supported by grants from the National Natural 
Science Foundation of China (81170759 and 81370965), the 
National 973 Program (2011CB504001), Natural Science Foun-
dation of Jiangsu Province, China (BK2009208) and the Science 
Foundation of Shanghai Jiao Tong University Affiliated Sixth 
People's Hospital (1112 and 1435). There is no financial sup-
port or relationship that might pose a conflict of interest. </p>





<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi 
Comparison of atherosclerotic lesions </p>





<p>J Diabetes Invest Vol. 5 No. 6 November 2014 
ª 2014 The Authors. Journal of Diabetes Investigation published by AASD and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>

<p>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E 
Li et al. 
http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/jdi </p>

</text></tei>