<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4812167" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Glioblastoma is the most common and devastating primary 
malignant intracranial tumor in adults (1). The current standard 
of care (SOC) for newly diagnosed glioblastomas is surgical 
resection followed by radiotherapy (RT) plus concomitant 
and adjuvant temozolomide (TMZ) (2). The prognosis 
remains relatively poor with a median overall survival of only 
14.6 months, median progression free survival of 6.9 months 
and 5 year survival rate of only 9.8% following diagnosis (2,3). 
The fast recurrence and multi-drug resistance are some of 
the key challenges in combating brain tumors. Glioma stem 
cells (GSCs) are considered to be a major source of relapse 
and chemoresistance (4), and are therefore an important thera-
peutic target for glioblastoma. 
Accumulating evidence has also demonstrated that 
glioblastoma frequently display hyperactivation of the 
phosphatidylinositol-3-kinase (PI3K)-Akt pathway (5-7) and 
endogenous Akt kinase activity may be activated in response to 
clinically relevant concentrations of TMZ (8,9). Akt activation 
is correlated with the increased tumorigenicity, invasiveness 
and stemness (6) and overexpression of an active form of Akt 
increases glioma cell resistance to TMZ (5,8). It has demon-
strated that cancer stem cells are preferentially sensitive to an 
inhibitor of Akt (7,10) and down-regulation of the PI3K/Akt 
pathway enhances the cytotoxicity of TMZ (11). At present, 
the most effective drug for the treatment of glioblastoma is 
TMZ, the primary path leading to glioma cell death is forma-
tion of O-6-methylguanine and apoptotic signalling triggered 
by O-6-methyl G:T mispairs, but apoptotic signalling goes 
through a step mediated by AMPK (12). However, there are 
obvious disadvantages as described above. 
Metformin (MET), a first-line treatment for type-2 
diabetes, can reduce cancer incidence (13) and mortality (14), 
and increases the number of breast carcinoma patients 
obtaining complete response to neo-adjuvant therapy (15). 
Previous studies have demonstrated that MET can selectively 
kill cancer stem cells (16-19) with minor adverse effects (20). 
Its mechanism of antiproliferative action is considered to be 
activation of AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) (17,18) 
and/or inhibition of Akt activity (19,21). On the basis of this 
evidence, a number of clinical trials are underway (22,23). 
Soritau et al (24) proved that the tumor cells isolated from </p>

<p>Temozolomide in combination with metformin act synergistically 
to inhibit proliferation and expansion of glioma stem-like cells </p>

<p>ZHIYUN YU 
1 , GANG ZHAO 
1 , PENGLIANG LI 
1 , YUNQIAN LI 
1 , </p>

<p>GUANGTONG ZHOU 
1 , YONG CHEN 
1 and GUIFANG XIE </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Departments of </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Neurosurgery, and </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Obstetrics and Gynecology, First Hospital of Jilin University, 
Changchun, Jilin 130021, P.R. China </p>

<p>Received December 23, 2014; Accepted January 27, 2016 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/ol.2016.4315 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Miss. Guifang Xie, Department of Obstetrics </p>

<p>and Gynecology, First Hospital of Jilin University, 71 Xinmin Street, 
Changchun, Jilin 130021, P.R. China 
E-mail: 664857729@qq.com </p>

<p>Mr. Yong Chen, Department of Neurosurgery, First Hospital of Jilin 
University, 71 Xinmin Street, Changchun, Jilin 130021, P.R. China 
E-mail: 85349202@qq.com </p>

<p>Key words: temozolomide, metformin, glioma, cancer stem cell, Akt </p>

<p>YU et al: MET ENHANCES THE CYTOTOXICITY OF TMZ IN GSCs </p>



<p>patients with high-grade gliomas who were treated with TMZ 
and MET exhibited a significant decrease in proliferation rate 
when compared to those treated with TMZ alone. But whether 
MET may potentiate the cytotoxicity of TMZ for GSCs is 
unknown. 
In the present study, GSCs isolated from human glioma 
cell line U87 and Rat glioma cell line C6, were treated with 
TMZ either alone or with MET. The combination index 
(CI) value was analyzed and calculated by the Chou-Talalay 
method (25). The present study demonstrated that MET acts 
synergistically with TMZ in inhibiting GSCs proliferation and 
expansion, showed a significant apoptosis compared to either 
agent alone and reinforced the effect on cell cycle arrest. The 
present study provides a rationale for why the combination 
of MET and TMZ may improve treatment of patients with 
glioblastoma. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Cell and gliosphere culture. The human glioma cell line U87 
and Rat glioma cell line C6 were purchased from Nanjing 
KGI Biotechnology Company (Nanjing, China). The cells 
were cultured in Gibco DMEM media (Thermo Fisher Scien-
tific, Inc., Waltham, USA), supplemented with Hyclone 10% 
fetal bovine serum (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.), Hyclone 
Penicillin-Streptomycin (100 U/ml), Hyclone glutamine (2 M) 
in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO 2 at 37˚C. The cells were 
dissociated using 0.25% trypsin (Gibco; Thermo Fisher Scien-
tific, Inc.) and 0.02% EDTA solution and subcultured once in 
3-5 days. To generate gliospheres, U87 and C6 glioblastoma cells 
were dissociated from DMEM cultures using trypsin-EDTA 
solution and cultured in Gibco Neurobasal medium (NBM) 
supplemented with Gibco N2 (1x), B27 (1x), glutaMAX (1x), 
heparin (2 ug/ml), recombinant human FGF-basic (b-FGF, 
20 ng/ml; PeproTech China, Suzhou, China), recombinant 
human epidermal growth factor (EGF, 20 ng/ml; PeproTech), 
Hyclone Penicillin-Streptomycin (100 U/ml). The gliospheres 
were cultured in 6-well plates in 5% CO 2 incubator at 37˚C with 
a medium change every 2-3 days. After gliospheres formed 
and reached 100-200 cells/sphere, within 10 days, gliospheres 
were dissociated by accutase (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, 
USA) and reseeded at a ratio of 1:2-3. </p>

<p>GSCs identification (immunofluorescence staining). Glio-
spheres were plated onto poly-L-lysine (Sigma-Aldrich) 
coated glass cover slips in DMEM with 10% FBS for 8 h. The 
Gliospheres were washed with cold PBS (0.01 M), fixed with 
4% paraformaldehyde (Gibco; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.) 
for 30 min, permeabilized with 0.1% Triton X-100 for 15 min 
and blocked in 5% BSA (Sigma-Aldrich) for 1 h at room 
temperature. Then the gliospheres were immunostained with 
rabbit anti-human polyclonal CD133 (cat. no. ZA-0426; 1:100; 
ZSGB-BIO; OriGene Technologies, Inc., Beijing, China), 
mouse anti-human monoclonal nestin (cat. no. ZM-0323; 
1:40; ZSGB-BIO; OriGene Technologies, Inc.), mouse anti-
human monoclonal β-tubulin III (cat. no. TA500047; 1:100; 
ZSGB-BIO; OriGene Technologies, Inc.) and rabbit anit-
human monoclonal glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP; 
cat. no. ZA-0529; 1:100, ZSGB-BIO; OriGene Technologies, 
Inc.) antibodies at 4˚C overnight. Subsequent visualization </p>

<p>was performed with fluorescein-conjugated AffiniPure goat 
anti-rabbit IgG (cat. no. ZF-0311; 1:100) and tetramethyl-
rhodamine-conjugated AffiniPure goat anti-mouse IgG 
(cat. no. ZF-0313; 1:100) secondary antibodies (ZSGB-BIO; 
OriGene Technologies, Inc.) for 30 min at room temperature 
in darkness, and the nuclei were counterstained with DAPI 
(0.5 µg/ml; Institute of Biotechnology, Haimen, China). 
For immunostaining of differentiated tumor cells, glio-
spheres were transferred to DMEM with 10% FBS for another 
7 days and immunocytochemistry was performed as described 
above. The fluorescent signals were detected and images were 
captured with a fluorescence microscope (Olympus IX51, 
Olympus Corporation, Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>Gliosphere formation and expansion assay. To test the effect 
of two agents (TMZ and/or MET) on gliosphere formation, 
after primary sphere formation was observed, gliospheres 
were dissociated and plated in 96-well plates (5x10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>/ml/well) in 
NBM with B27, N2, glutaMAX, 2 µg/ml heparin and 20 ng/ml 
EGF+bFGF in the absence or presence of TMZ, MET or 
TMZ plus MET. Cultures were fed 0.02 ml of NBM every 
2 days and images were captured (x200 magnification) after 
7 days using IX51 Olympus microscope. To determine the 
gliosphere counts, U87 and C6 gliospheres were dissociated 
and plated in 96-well plates (5x10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>/ml/well) in NBM with B27, 
N2, glutaMAX, 2 µg/ml heparin and 20 ng/ml EGF+bFGF 
in the presence of TMZ, MET or TMZ plus MET for 7 days 
and the number of gliospheres counted under IX51 Olympus 
microscope. </p>

<p>Combination proliferation assay. The cytotoxic effect of 
TMZ or/and MET on GSCs was measured by cell counting 
kit-8 (CCK-8) assay. Briefly, U87 and C6 gliospheres were 
cultured in 96-well tissue culture plates (5x10 
3 per 100 µl per 
well) in NBM with B27, N2, glutaMAX, 2 µg/ml heparin 
and 20 ng/ml EGF+bFGF at 37˚C for 24 h, then different 
concentrations of TMZ (0-3.2 mmol, Sigma-Aldrich) or MET 
(0-160 mmol, Sigma-Aldrich) were added and compared with 
the DMSO-treated control. The CCK-8 reagent (10 µl/well) 
was added at 93 h, and the OD was measured at 450 nm after 
96 h using a Synergy HTX Multi-Mode Microplate Reader 
(BioTek, Winooski, VT, USA). In order to determine the 
combination cytotoxic effect on GSCs, parallel studies were 
performed in cells treated with TMZ (0-3.2 mmol) plus MET 
(0-160 mmol) (1:50, TMZ:MET). The combination index 
(CI) value was analyzed by <rs id="software-0" type="software">CalcuSyn</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version2</rs>; 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Biosoft</rs>, Cambridge, UK) and calculated by the Chou-Talalay 
method (25). CI values &lt;1.0, =1, and &gt;1.0 indicates synergistic 
interaction (more than additive), summation (additive), and 
antagonistic interaction (less than additive), respectively. </p>

<p>Cell cycle analysis. To determine the effect of TMZ in 
combination with MET on cell cycle progression, U87 and C6 
gliospheres were cultured in NBM with B27, N2, glutaMAX, 
2 µg/ml heparin and 20 ng/ml EGF+bFGF in the absence or 
presence of 0.4 mmol TMZ, 20 mmol MET or 0.4 mmol TMZ 
plus 20 mmol MET in 5% CO 2 incubator at 37˚C. After 48 h, 
the GSCs were dissociated by accutase (Sigma-Aldrich), fixed 
and permeabilized with 500 µl of 70% cold ethanol at -20˚C 
overnight. After washing in PBS, the cells were treated with </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY LETTERS 11: 2792-2800, 2016 </p>



<p>100 µg/ml of RNase (Sigma-Aldrich) and incubated at 37˚C 
for 30 min. Then the cells stained with 100 µg/ml of prop-
idium iodide (PI, Sigma-Aldrich) at 4˚C for another 30 min in 
darkness. The percentage of cells at different cell cycle stages 
(G0/G1, G2/M and S phase) was determined on the basis of 
DNA content by flow cytometer using <rs id="software-1" type="software">ModFit LT</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">3.3</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Verity Software House, Inc.</rs>., Topsham, ME, USA). </p>

<p>Apoptosis assay. To determine the effect of TMZ or/and MET 
on GSCs apoptosis, U87 and C6 gliospheres were cultured in 
NBM with B27, N2, glutaMAX, 2 µg/ml heparin and 20 ng/ml 
EGF+bFGF in the absence or presence of 0.4 mmol TMZ, 
20 mmol MET or 0.4 mmol TMZ plus 20 mmol MET in 5% 
CO 2 incubator at 37˚C. After 48 h, the GSCs were collected. 
Apoptotic and necrotic cell death was analyzed by double 
staining with fluorescein-isothiocyanate (FITC)-conjugated 
annexin V and PI, in which annexin V bound to the early and 
late apoptotic cells with membrane-exposed phosphatidyl-
serine, while PI labeled only the late apoptotic/necrotic cells 
with membrane damage. Staining was performed using the 
FITC Annexin V Apoptosis Detection Kit (BD Pharmingen, 
San Diego, CA, USA), according to the manufacturer's instruc-
tions. The stained cells were analyzed with a BD FACSAria III 
flow cytometer (BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA). 
The numbers of viable (annexin V-/PI-), apoptotic (annexin 
V+/PI-), and necrotic (annexin V+/PI+) cells were calculated 
with the <rs id="software-2" type="software">FACSDiva</rs> software, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 6.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">BD Biosciences</rs>). </p>

<p>Western blot analysis. To investigate possible molecular 
determinants of MET effects, U87 and C6 gliospheres 
were treated with TMZ (400 µmol), MET (20 mmol) or 
TMZ+MET (400 µmol+20 mmol) for 72 h were collected 
and lysed in RIPA buffer. Equal amounts of proteins (30 µg) 
were separated by SDS-PAGE gels and were transferred to 
a PVDF membrane (Pierce; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.) 
and blocked for 2 h in 5% nonfat dry milk in PBS-T. The 
blots were incubated with primary antibodies, including 
rabbit anti-human monoclonal phospho-Akt (cat. no. 13038P; 
1:1,000; Cell Signaling Technology, Inc., Danvers, MA, USA), 
rabbit anti-human monoclonal Akt (cat. no. 4691P; 1:1,000; 
Cell Signaling Technology, Inc.) and mouse anti-human 
monoclonal β-actin (cat. no. A1978; 1:1,000; Sigma-Aldrich), 
at 4˚C for 12 h. The membranes were then washed with 
PBS-T and incubated with HRP-conjugated goat anti-rabbit 
IgG (cat. no. ZB-2301; 1:5,000) or HRP-conjugated goat 
anti-mouse IgG (cat. no. ZB-2305; 1:5,000) secondary anti-
bodies (ZSGB-BIO; OriGene Technologies, Inc.) for 2 h. 
After subsequent washes, specific signals were showed using 
the Pierce ECL Western Blotting Substrate (Thermo Fisher 
Scientific, Inc.) and detected by the western blot automated 
chemiluminescence image analysis system (Tanon5200; 
Shanghai-Day Technology Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. The experiments were performed 
≥3 times and data were expressed as the mean ± standard 
deviation. Statistical comparisons were assessed using the 
Student's t test. Statistical analysis was performed with <rs id="software-3" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
software, <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">version 19.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">IBM SPSS</rs>&lt; Armonk, NY, USA). 
P&lt;0.05 was considered to indicate a statistically significant 
difference. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Isolation, characterization and differentiation of GSCs 
isolated from U87 and C6 glioma cells. U87 and C6 gliospheres 
cultures were characterized for recognized GSC signatures: 
Self-renewal, neural stem cell marker expression and differ-
entiation. The cells within the sphere were positive for neural 
stem cell markers CD133 (Fig. 1A) and nestin (Fig. 1B), and 
lack of immunoreactivity for markers of differentiated neural 
cell types such as GFAP for astrocytes and β-tubulin III for 
neurons. The assay of multi-lineage differentiation capacity of 
cells within the sphere was demonstrated by culturing the cells 
in differentiation-inducing culture medium (DMEN+10% 
FBS) for 7 days. These cells lost expression of CD133 and 
nestin when subjected to differentiating conditions, showed 
typical morphological differentiation towards neuronal and 
astrocytic lineages, identified as β-tubulin-III positive for 
neurons and GFAP positive for astrocytes (Fig. 1C). The 
self-renewing capacity of the tumor spheres was assayed by 
dissociation of primary tumor spheres. When the self-renewal 
capacity was compared among tumor subtypes at a plating 
density of 5x10 
3 cells/well, U87 were observed to generate 
a greater mean number of secondary tumor spheres (151±5) 
compared with C6 (123±4) (Fig. 2). </p>

<p>TMZ plus MET contribute more effectively to inhibit glio-
spheres formation and expansion. To determine whether 
TMZ plus MET is more effective in the inhibition of U87 and 
C6 gliosphere formation and expansion compared with either 
drug alone, culture conditions were established to generate 
gliospheres in vitro. U87 and C6 glioma cells were cultured in 
NBM with B27, N2, glutaMAX, 2 ug/ml heparin and 20 ng/ml 
EGF+bFGF, promotes gliosphere formation in 5-7 days and 
increases in size in 7-10 days. In vitro treatment with TMZ 
or MET resulted in a marked reduction in the number and 
size of gliospheres generated from U87 and C6 cells (P&lt;0.05). 
Notably, when the cells were treated with MTZ plus MET, a 
significant decrease was observed in the number and size of 
gliospheres compare to either agent alone (P&lt;0.01). Further 
analyses demonstrated that in vitro treatment with TMZ, MET 
or TMZ plus MET resulted in a dose-dependent decrease 
in the number and size of gliospheres (Fig. 2). These results 
indicate that TMZ plus MET combination treatment is more 
effective at inhibiting U87 and C6 gliosphere formation and 
expansion compared with single agent treatment. </p>

<p>TMZ plus MET acts synergistically in inhibiting GSCs prolif-
eration. In order to determine whether the MET, which is 
currently in clinical trials for cancer treatment, augments the 
cell proliferation inhibitory effects of TMZ in GSCs, U87 and 
C6 GSCs were plated with 0-3.2 mmol TMZ either alone or 
with 0-160 mmol MET for 72 h and the cells were assessed 
using the CCK-8 assay. Both U87-GSCs and C6-GSCs 
exhibited reduced proliferation levels as a dose-dependent 
response to TMZ and MET. The combination of TMZ and 
MET (1:50, TMZ:MET) resulted in a significant shift in the 
proliferation inhibition curve compared with treatment with 
either drug alone(Fig. 3). The statistical combination index 
(CI) was determined for the dual therapy to determine whether 
combination therapy was synergistic, additive, or antagonistic. </p>

<p>YU et al: MET ENHANCES THE CYTOTOXICITY OF TMZ IN GSCs </p>



<p>As shown in Fig. 3 and Table I, MET acted synergistically 
(CI&lt;1.0) with TMZ to inhibit U87-GSCs and C6-GSCs growth 
at all combination doses tested. As the concentration of TMZ </p>

<p>in combination with MET was increased, the trend in CI value 
was reduced, suggesting that increasing the dosage of TMZ 
and MET increases the synergistic effect. </p>

<p>TMZ and/or MET induced cell cycle arrest in GSCs. Whether 
the inhibition of proliferation by TMZ or MET was due to cell 
cycle arrest or apoptosis in GSCs was investigated using flow 
cytometry. U87-GSCs and C6-GSCs were treated with TMZ 
(0.4 mmol), MET (20 mmol) or TMZ (0.4 mmol) plus MET 
(20 mmol) for 48 h and the cell cycle phase was determined. 
As shown in Fig. 4 and Table II, U87-GSCs cultured in NBM 
with B27, N2, glutaMAX, heparin and EGF+bFGF showed 
62.79% G0/G1 cells, 18.3% G2/M cells and 18.91% S-phase 
cells, addition of TMZ or MET resulted in a reduction in G0/G1 
cells (45.19 and 59.2%, respectively), a marked increase in 
G2/M cells (34.49 and 22.19%, respectively) and an increase 
in S-phase cells (20.32 and 18.61%, respectively). However, 
when U87-GSCs were treated with TMZ plus MET, a greater 
reduction in G0/G1 cells (22.67%; P&lt;0.05), and a greater 
increase in G2/M and S-phase cells was observed (48.89 and 
28.43%, respectively; P&lt;0.05). This result indicates that the 
U87-GSC cells were arrested at the G2/M phase by TMZ or 
MET treatment, but TMZ plus MET induced cell cycle arrest 
at both the G2/M phase and S-phase; the effect was mark-
edly better than treatment with a single agent, particularly 
for the G2/M phase arrest. C6-GSCs, cultured in NBM with 
B27, N2, glutaMAX, heparin and EGF+bFGF, were analyzed 
by flow cytometry and the result demonstrated that 66.43% 
cells were in G0/G1, 8.53% were in G2/M and 25.04% were 
in S-phase. The addition of TMZ or MET resulted in a slight 
decrease in the percentage of G0/G1 cells (60.06 and 56.34%, 
respectively), an increase in the percentage of G2/M cells 
(22.64 and 25.02%, respectively) and a slight decrease in the 
percentage of S-phase cells (17.30 and 18.65%, respectively). </p>

<p>Figure 2. Inhibition of gliosphere formation and expansion by TMZ and 
MET. (A) U87-GSCs and (B) C6-GSCs were cultured in the absence or 
presence of TMZ, MET or TMZ and MET for 7 days and the number of 
gliospheres counted under a microscope. The results are representative of 
3 independent experiments </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05, compared with control group; 
∆ P&lt;0.01, 
compared with single agents. GSCs, glioma stem cells; TMZ, temozolomid; 
MET, metformin. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Identification, characterization and differentiation U87-GSCs and C6-GSCs. U87 and C6 gliospheres were cultured for 7 days, immunocytochemical 
staining of (A) the cancer stem cell marker, CD133, and (B) the neural progenitor marker, nestin, in U87-GSC and C6-GSC cells. (C) Following differentiation, 
the U87 and C6 glioma cells were immunostained with β-tubulin-III and GFAP. The fluorescent signals were detected and images were captured at x200 
magnification. GSCs, glioma stem cells; GFAP, glial fibrillary acidic protein. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY LETTERS 11: 2792-2800, 2016 </p>



<p>When C6-GSCs were treated with TMZ plus MET resulted in 
a greater reduction in the percentage of G0/G1 cells (43.09%; 
P&lt;0.05) and a marked increase in the percentage of cells in 
S-phase (31.92%; P&lt;0.05). These results indicated that the 
C6-GSCs cycles were arrested at S phase following treatment 
with TMZ plus MET; however, little difference was observed 
in the percentage of C6-GSCs in G2/M arrest when treated </p>

<p>with TMZ plus MET compared with either single agent. 
These results suggest that TMZ plus MET treatment regulates 
cell cycle progression of GSCs in culture and using the agents 
together enhances the effects. </p>

<p>TMZ plus MET significantly induced apoptosis in GSCs. The 
present study also aimed to determine whether the TMZ or </p>

<p>Figure 3. MET augments the effects of TMZ in GSCs. (A) U87-GSCs and (C) C6-GSCs were treated with TMZ alone (0-160 mmol), MET (0-3.2 mmol) or 
the combination of TMZ and MET (1:50, TMZ:MET). <rs type="software">Calcusyn</rs> software was used to ascertain the combination index (CI) value for each combination ratio 
to determine whether combination treatments have an additive or synergistic effect on (B) U87-GSCs or (D) C6-GSCs. CI values &lt;1.0, =1, and &gt;1.0 indicates 
synergistic interaction (more than additive), summation (additive), and antagonistic interaction (less than additive), respectively. Results are representative of 
3 independent experiments. GSCs, glioma stem cells; TMZ, temozolomid; MET, metformin; CI, combination index. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Effects of TMZ, MET or TMZ and MET on cell cycle distribution. (A) U87-GSCs and (B) C6-GSCs (2x10 
5 cells) were cultured in the presence of 
0.4 mmol TMZ, 20 mmol MET or TMZ and MET. The cells were harvested after 48 h and stained with propidium iodide (PI), and analyzed by flow cytometry. 
GSCs, glioma stem cells; TMZ, temozolomid; MET, metformin. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>YU et al: MET ENHANCES THE CYTOTOXICITY OF TMZ IN GSCs </p>



<p>MET-induced reduction in cell viability is accompanied by 
cell apoptosis. Annexin V and PI staining and flow cytom-
etry was used to detect apoptosis in U87-GSCs and C6-GSCs 
treated with TMZ (0.4 mmol), MET (20 mmol) or TMZ 
(0.4 mmol) plus MET (20 mmol) for 48 h. As shown in Fig. 5, 
U87-GSCs and C6-GSCs cultured without TMZ or MET 
exhibited low apoptotic cell death. Treatment with TMZ or 
MET induced cell apoptosis (P&lt;0.05); however, treatment 
with TMZ plus MET resulted in a significant increase in 
apoptotic cells compared with single agents (P&lt;0.05). In 
U87-GSCs, the percentage of apoptotic cells in the control 
group was 15.86%, while those of TMZ and MET groups 
were 31.84 and 28.23%, respectively, and was significantly 
increased to 61.73% in TMZ plus MET group (P&lt;0.05). In 
C6-GSCs, the percentage of apoptotic cells in the control </p>

<p>group was 11.21%, and those of the TMZ and MET groups 
were 36.96% and 41.59%, respectively; and was significantly 
increased to 62.73% in TMZ plus MET group (P&lt;0.05). The 
above results demonstrated that TMZ or MET significantly 
induced apoptosis in GSCs compared with the control groups 
and MET treatment enhances TMZ-induced apoptosis. </p>

<p>MET potentiates the cytotoxicity of TMZ for GSCs by inhibi-
tion of Akt activation. Fig. 6 demonstrates that when GSCs 
were treated with TMZ alone for 72 h, Akt phosphoryla-
tion is slightly enhanced. However, Akt phosphorylation 
was inhibited by MET, suggesting that Akt inhibition is 
required for MET antiproliferative activity in GSCs. 
Notably, the phosphorylated Akt (P-Akt) levels were mark-
edly down-regulated compared with the control group and </p>

<p>Table I. Combination treatments with TMZ and MET synergistically inhibit cell growth in U87-GSCs and C6-GSCs. </p>

<p>TMZ 
MET 
Combination 
------------------------------------------------------
-----------------------------------------------------
-------------------------------------------------
Dose 
Growth 
Dose 
Growth 
Growth 
Cell line 
(mmol) 
inhibition (%) 
(mmol) 
inhibition (%) 
Ratio 
inhibition (%) 
CI value </p>

<p>U87-GSCs 
0.05 
15.9±0.83 
2.5 
14.0±0.75 
1:50 
24.8±0.87 
0.602 
0.1 
16.9±1.22 
5 
18.9±1.24 
1:50 
32.6±2.65 
0.691 
0.2 
26.4±1.15 
10 
22.7±1.32 
1:50 
43.8±1.39 
0.693 
0.4 
32.8±1.85 
20 
29.4±1.58 
1:50 
57.6±2.12 
0.619 
0.8 
45.2±3.21 
40 
41.6±2.01 
1:50 
68.1±1.85 
0.643 </p>

<p>C6-GSCs 
0.05 
26.1±0.95 
2.5 
32.5±0.98 
1:50 
46.3±2.34 
0.582 
0.1 
38.2±1.30 
5 
44.2±2.09 
1:50 
58.2±1.08 
0.493 
0.2 
42.6±1.59 
10 
55.1±2.32 
1:50 
70.0±3.05 
0.388 
0.4 
51.6±2.03 
20 
62.3±1.68 
1:50 
79.7±2.71 
0.308 
0.8 
64.7±2.08 
40 
69.0±2.41 
1:50 
84.2±3.02 
0.358 </p>

<p>Cells were treated with a 1:50 combination (ratio) of TMZ:MET at the indicated concentrations. Percentage growth inhibition of the com-
bination treatments was calculated compared to untreated cells (DMSO). <rs type="software">Calcusyn</rs> software was used to ascertain the combination index to 
determine whether combination treatments have an additive or synergistic effect. CI values &lt;1.0, =1, and &gt;1.0 indicates synergistic interac-
tion (more than additive), summation (additive), and antagonistic interaction (less than additive), respectively. TMZ, temozolomid; MET, 
metformin; CI, Combination index. </p>

<p>Table II. Modulation of cell cycle and apoptosis by TMZ, MET or TMZ plus MET. </p>

<p>Mean (%) 
Mean (%) 
Mean (%) 
Mean (%) 
Cell line 
Sub-group 
Sub G0 phase 
G0/G1 phase 
S phase 
G2/M phase </p>

<p>U87-GSGS 
Control 
0.08±0.02 
62.79±3.10 
18.91±2.30 
18.30±1.65 
TMZ 
6.22±0.20 
45.19±1.28 
20.32±1.41 
34.49±1.69 
MET 
5.38±0.03 
59.20±2.36 
18.61±1.36 
22.19±2.52 
TMZ+MET 
14.77±1.09 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>22.67±3.21 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>28.43±2.84 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>48.89±3.21 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>C6-GSCs 
Control 
0.05±0.01 
66.43±2.89 
25.04±1.05 
8.53±0.39 
TMZ 
5.37±0.05 
60.06±2.03 
17.30±0.56 
22.64±0.58 
MET 
6.28±0.24 
56.34±1.38 
18.65±0.47 
25.02±0.12 
TMZ+MET 
19.61±0.31 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>43.09±0.45 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>31.92±0.90 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>24.99±0.14 </p>

<p>The analysis of cell cycle distribution and apoptosis rate in U87-GSCs and C6-GSCs. Data is presented as the mean and are representative of 
three independent experiments ( </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05, compared with single agent). TMZ, temozolomid; MET, metformin; GSCs, glioma stem cells. </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY LETTERS 11: 2792-2800, 2016 </p>



<p>TMZ alone groups compared with treatment with TMZ and 
MET in combination. These results indicate that the poten-
tial mechanism of MET enhancing TMZ cytotoxicity may 
involve down-regulation of P-Akt. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Previous studies have indicated that glioblastomas originate 
from a pool of stem-like cells that share properties in common 
with neuronal stem cells. GSCs are a small population of cells 
that have self-renewal, transplantation, recurrence properties 
and multidrug resistance (26). The identification of stem-like 
cells in tumors and the proposed role for this subpopulation 
in drug resistance opened the search for targeted molecular 
therapies and novel drugs able to deplete this tumor cell 
subpopulation, either by activating differentiation or through 
selective toxicity that causes loss of self-renewal (19). However, 
in medicine, it is usually difficult to get agents with high target 
specificity; only a few of compounds have showed selective 
toxicity for cancer stem cells (27,28). However, certain drugs 
already used in the clinic that may have encouraging results, 
such as MET, may selectively kill cancer stem cells (16-19) 
with minor adverse events (20). 
To the best of our knowledge, the present report demon-
strates for the first time the ability of MET to function 
synergistically with TMZ to reduce U87-GSCs and C6-GSCs </p>

<p>Figure 5. TMZ plus MET significantly induced apoptosis in GSCs. (A) U87-GSCs and (B) C6-GSCs (2x10 
5 cells) were cultured in the presence of 0.4 mmol 
TMZ, 20 mmol MET or TMZ plus MET. The cells were harvested after 48 h and stained with Annexin V-FITC, propidium iodide, and analyzed by flow 
cytometry. (C) Quantitative analysis of the early and late apoptosis rate. Results are representative of three independent experiments ( </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05, compared with 
single agents). GSCs, glioma stem cells; TMZ, temozolomid; MET, metformin. </p>

<p>Figure 6. Western blot analysis of phosphorylated Akt protein expression. 
MET acts synergistically with TMZ in inhibiting GSCs proliferation and 
expansion by inhibition of Akt activation. GSCs, glioma stem cells; TMZ, 
temozolomid; MET, metformin. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>YU et al: MET ENHANCES THE CYTOTOXICITY OF TMZ IN GSCs </p>



<p>proliferation, although it has been proved previously that 
MET improves the survival of cisplatin-treated tumour 
cells (29). 
TMZ is currently the most effective drug for the treat-
ment of glioblastoma and one mechanism of TMZ-induced 
apoptosis involves an obligatory AMP-activated protein 
kinase (AMPK) activation step (12); however, this increases 
the activity of Akt which increases glioma cell resistance to 
TMZ (5,8) and may increase the tumorigenicity, invasiveness 
and stemness of tumor cells (6). The anticancer mechanism of 
MET is considered to be activation of AMPK (17,18) or inhi-
bition of the PI3K-Akt pathway (19,21). Although the present 
study demonstrated that MET potentiates the cytotoxicity of 
TMZ for GSCs and has a synergistic effect, whether this is 
achieved through increased AMPK activity and/or inhibition 
of AKT activity in GSCs remains unknown. 
The potential for MET to target GBM proliferation was 
proposed due to the hypothesized synergy with TMZ on 
AMPK activation (17); the present authors are sceptical of this 
hypothesis and it has not been confirmed. However, certain 
studies support this hypothesis. Liu et al (30), suggested that 
MET's growth inhibition in vitro does not require AMPK. 
Instead, AMPK activation may be a response mechanism to 
counter stress induced by anticancer agents (30). It is possible 
that the growth-inhibiting effects are a combination of the 
AMPK-independent mTOR-dependent cellular and systemic 
effects of MET (30). Gritti et al (16) determined that MET 
exhibits its selective antiproliferative effects in human GSCs 
via inhibition of the CLIC1-mediated ion current, although 
this requires further studies to confirm this observation. 
It has been proposed that the Akt pathway represents 
a novel target for the sensitization of Akt overexpression 
gliomas to chemotherapeutic methylating agents such as 
TMZ (5), due to the ability of Akt overexpression to suppress 
TMZ-induced mitotic catastrophe as well as TMZ-induced 
senescence (5). It has been proved that TMZ combined with 
the PI3K inhibitor LY294002 inhibits melanoma cell growth, 
survival and invasion (31); and similar results were observed 
in glioma cells (11). Akt activation has been reported to 
suppress activation of the G2 checkpoint in human colon 
carcinoma cells exposed to radiation (32), Akt activation has 
also been proven to suppresses TMZ-induced G2 arrest (5). 
However, in our trial, MET, through the inhibition of Akt 
activation, selectively killed cancer stem cells and acted 
synergetic with TMZ, enhancing TMZ-induced G2 arrest for 
U87-GSCs; however, in C6-GSCs, they just reinforced each 
other and induced cell cycle arrest at S phase. Based on the 
experimental results of the present study, MET may enhance 
the cytotoxicity of TMZ by down-regulation of the PI3K/Akt 
pathway, these results warrant further in vivo exploration. 
Although the present study presents evidence that MET 
acts synergistically with TMZ in inhibiting GSCs prolif-
eration and generating the highest apoptotic rates when 
compared with either drug alone, but the exact mechanism 
of action remains unclear. Soritau et al (24) reported that 
tumor cells isolated from patients with high-grade gliomas 
who were treated with TMZ and MET exhibited a significant 
decrease in proliferation rate when compared to those treated 
with TMZ alone. In conclusion, future trials are required to 
explore the detailed mechanisms. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The present study was supported by the Young Scientists Fund 
of the National Natural Sciene Foundation of China (grant 
no. 21401072). </p>



<p>ONCOLOGY LETTERS 11: 2792-2800, 2016 </p>





</text></tei>