<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4959023" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:32+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>During copulation, male Drosophila transfers Sex Peptide 
(SP) to females where it acts on internal sensory neurons 
expressing pickpocket (ppk). These neurons induce a 
post-mating response (PMR) that includes elevated egg-
laying and refractoriness to re-mating. Exactly how ppk 
neurons regulate the different aspects of the PMR, howev-
er, remains unclear. Here, we identify a small subset of the 
ppk neurons which requires expression of a pre-mRNA 
splicing factor CG3542 for egg-laying, but not refractori-
ness to mating. We identify two CG3542-ppk expressing 
neurons that innervate the upper oviduct and appear to be 
responsible for normal egg-laying. Our results suggest 
specific subsets of the ppk neurons are responsible for 
each PMR component. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Egg-laying is a key reproductive behavior in many invertebrates 
that depends on the coordinated action of multiple physiological 
and behavioral steps associated with egg formation, ovulation, 
and oviposition. Like reproduction in mammals, each step of 
egg-laying is influenced by endocrine factors; juvenile hormone 
(JH) is required for egg formation (Bownes, 1989; Gruntenko et  al., 2010; Sliter et al., 1987), and octopamine is required for 
ovulation (Monastirioti, 1996; 2003; Rodri et al., 2006). Even 
neurons producing Insulin-like peptide 7 (Ilp7) have been linked 
to oviposition in Drosophila melanogaster (Yang et al., 2008). 
As with many other animals, egg-laying in Drosophila is tight-
ly associated with mating. After a female mates and receives 
sperm from a male, she becomes refractory to further mating 
and begins to lay eggs. This behavioral switch, which is known 
as the post-mating response (PMR), is induced by Sex Peptide 
(SP) in the seminal fluid transferred to females during insemina-
tion (Aigaki and Fleischmann, 1991; Chen et al., 1988; Liu and  Kubli, 2003). Females that mate with males lacking SP lay few </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>School of Life Sciences, Gwangju Institute of Science and Technol-
ogy, Gwangju 61005, Korea, </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>These authors contributed equally to 
this work. 
*Correspondence: kimyj@gist.ac.kr (YJK); zeeyong@gist.ac.kr (ZYP) </p>

<p>Received 10 May, 2016; revised 25 May, 2016; accepted 25 May, 2016; 
published online 24 June, 2016 </p>

<p>Keywords: CG3542, egg-laying, phosphoprotein, pickpocket, post 
mating response, sex peptide </p>

<p>eggs and mate multiple times (Peng et al., 2005a). SP is also 
associated with other behavioral and physiological changes, 
such as feeding, sleep and immune responses (Carvalho et al.,  2006; Domanitskaya et al., 2007; Isaac et al., 2010; Peng et al.,  2005b; Ribeiro and Dickson, 2010; Walker et al., 2015). 
SP acts via a G-protein coupled receptor called SP receptor 
(SPR) (Yapici et al., 2008). SPR expression in pickpocket (ppk) 
neurons is required for a normal PMR, and the activation of 
SPR in ppk neurons is sufficient to induce the PMR even in 
virgin flies. The female genital tract houses 30-38 ppk neurons. 
Silencing of these neurons induces a PMR similar to that 
caused by mating or SPR activation. This indicates activation of 
SPR suppresses the activity of the ppk neurons (Häsemeyer et  al., 2009; Yang et al., 2009). ppk is co-expressed in female 
reproductive organs with fruitless (fru) and/or doublesex (dsx), 
two genes encoding transcription factors important for sex de-
termination (Häsemeyer et al., 2009; Rezával et al., 2012; Yang  et al., 2009). The ppk gene encodes an amiloride-sensitive 
sodium channel important for mechanosensation (Adams et al.,  1998; Zhong et al., 2010). Because of this, peripheral neurons 
in the legs, wings, and genital tract that express ppk are gener-
ally considered sensory neurons that signal to the central brain. 
Still, even though SP and SPR in ppk neurons clearly direct the 
various components of the PMR, it is unclear which ppk neu-
rons regulate the distinct behaviors of mating receptivity and 
egg-laying. 
As a GPCR, SPR appears to be coupled with Gαi or Gαo, both 
of which reduce levels of the intracellular second messenger 
cAMP (Yapici et al., 2008). This drop in cAMP, in turn, modulates 
the activity of cAMP-dependent protein kinase A (PKA). Thus, we 
reasoned SPR activation should result in global changes in the 
phosphorylation state of many proteins, including important 
mediators downstream of SPR. In this study, we took a mass 
spectrometry-based proteomic approach to identify phospho-
proteins downstream of SPR signaling. After identifying proteins 
whose phosphorylation status changes in response to SP 
treatment, we examined the functions of these proteins using 
RNAi. We found that CG3542 (Mount and Salz, 2000; Zhu et  al., 2005), which encodes a protein closely related to the pre-
mRNA processing factor PRP40, is important in ppk neurons 
for the increase in egg-laying of mated females but not for their 
reduced mating receptivity. Using an intersectional genetic 
approach, we identified a group of 2-3 ppk and CG3542 dou-
ble-positive neurons that innervate the upper oviduct. Silencing 
of these neurons affects egg-laying but not mating receptivity in 
mated females. Our results suggest egg-laying and mating 
receptivity are regulated by distinct subsets of ppk neurons. </p>

<p>Molecules 
and 
Cells </p>

<p>http://molcells.org </p>

<p>Established in 1990 </p>

<p>eISSN: 0219-1032 
The Korean Society for Molecular and Cellular Biology. All rights reserved. 
This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. To 
view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/. </p>

<p>Oviduct Pickpocket Neurons Important for Egg-Laying 
Hyunjin Lee et al. </p>

<p>574 Mol. Cells 
http://molcells.org </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Phosphoprotein analysis 
BG2 cells were obtained from Drosophila Genome Resource 
Center (Cell line stock number, 51), and cultured according to 
the protocol form the provider (https://dgrc.bio.indiana.edu/ 
include/file/general_maintenance.pdf). BG2 cells with or without 
SP treatment were lysed in protein extraction buffer containing 
50mM Tris-HCl pH 8.2, 8 M Urea, 75 mM NaCl, 1 mM NaF, 1 
mM β-glycerophosphate, 1mM sodium orthovanadate, 1 mM 
sodium pyrophosphate and 1 mM PMSF. After sonication, pro-
tein concentrations were determined using a BCA Protein As-
say Kit (Thermo Scientific, UK). Protein samples (100 μg each) 
were chemically reduced (5 mM, DTT) and alkylated (25 mM, 
IAA) prior to trypsin digestion. After 4-fold dilution with 25 mM 
Tris-HCl buffer (pH 8.2), the protein samples were enzymatical-
ly digested using a sequencing grade trypsin at an enzyme to 
substrate ratio of 1:50 at 37°C for 16 h. Digestion reaction was 
stopped by the addition of 90% formic acid to a final concentra-
tion of 1%. Resulting tryptic digest peptide samples were de-
salted for subsequent phosphopeptide enrichment procedure. 
Phosphopeptides enriched with IMAC POROS 20 MC were 
subsequently subjected to the micro RPLC-MS/MS analysis 
described previously (Choi et al., 2011). Briefly, analyses of 
phosphopeptide-enriched samples were performed using Ag-
ilent 1100 Series high-performance liquid chromatography 
(HPLC) (Agilent Technologies) coupled to a linear quadrupole 
ion trap mass spectrometer (LTQ, Thermo Finnigan, USA). The 
resulting MS/MS spectra searched against a composite protein 
database containing the <rs id="software-4" type="software">IPI mouse protein database</rs> (v.<rs corresp="#software-4" type="version">3.28</rs>), 
and its reversed complement using SEQUEST algorithm (<rs type="software">Sor- cerer system</rs>). Differential modification search options for phos-
phorylation modification (+80 on Ser, Thr, Tyr), and oxidation 
(+16 on Met), were considered in the search. 'Peptide prophet' 
and 'Protein prophet' scores of 90% was used to filter the 
search results. We applied the log2(protein ratio) from relative 
spectral counts (Rsc) for label free quantification (Old et al.,  2005). RSC = log2[(n2 + f)/(n1 + f)] + log2[(t1 -n1 + f)/(t2 -n2 + 
f)] where, for each protein, RSC is the log2 ratio of abundance 
between Samples 1 and 2; n1 and n2 are spectral counts for 
the protein in Samples 1 and 2, respectively; t1 and t2 are total 
numbers of spectra over all proteins in control and SP-treated 
samples; and ƒ is a correction factor, set to 0.5 (Beissbarth et  al., 2004). Ammonium bicarbonate, calcium chloride, dithio-
threitol (DTT), iodoacetamide (IAA), sodium chloride, sodium 
orthovanadate (Na 3 VO 4 ), sodium fluoride (NaF), phenylmethyl-
sulfonyl fluoride (PMSF), sodium β-glycerophosphate, urea and 
ammonium dihydrogen phosphate (NH 4 H 2 PO 4 ) were pur-
chased from Sigma (USA). Formic acid (FA) and trifluoroacetic 
acid (TFA) were obtained from Merck (Germany). HPLC grade 
acetonitrile (ACN), methanol and deionized water were all pur-
chased from Fisher Science. Sequencing grade modified tryp-
sin was obtained from Promega (USA). Aqua C18 (particle size 
5 μm) reversed-phase column material was purchased from 
Phenomenx (USA). The IMAC POROS 20 MC was purchased 
from Applied Biosystems (USA). </p>

<p>Fly strains 
We obtained the following RNAi transgenic lines from the Vien-
na Drosophila RNAi Center (VDRC) (Austria): CG14939-IR1 
(VDRC stock number 107010), CG6983-IR1 (35159), CG5643-
IR1 (27470), CG3333-IR1 (34597), CG8594-IR1 (4642), 
CG8201-IR1 (52553), CG11621-IR1 (16240), CG3542-IR1 
(26227), CG3542-IR2 (26229), CG10480-IR1 (38389), </p>

<p>CG2173-IR1 (36516), CG8108-IR1 (35343), CG11417-IR1 
(18087), CG4236-IR1 (26455), CG6831-IR1 (40399), CG33979-
IR1 (21995), CG31678-IR1 (103705), CG6338-IR1 (12633), 
CG10033-IR1 (38320), CG42250-IR1 (33799), CG3696-IR1 
(10762), CG6418-IR1 (40379), CG9191-IR1 (52549), CG30122-
IR1 (106984), CG16973-IR1 (101517), CG2691-IR1 (110718), 
CG6501-IR1 (105605), CG14616-IR1 (106973), CG8092-
IR1 (28196), and CG42783-IR1 (105624). Y. Jan (UCSF) 
provided ppk-Gal4. We combined ppk-GAL4 with UAS-
Dicer2 and used it as a ppk-specific driver for all the RNAi 
experiments. B.J. Dickson kindly provided UAS&gt;stop&gt;nSyb-
GFP, UAS&gt;stop&gt;DSCAM17.1-GFP and UAS&gt;stop&gt;Kir2.1. 
We also used the published lines UAS&gt;stop&gt;mCD8-GFP (Yu  et al., 2010); LexAop-FLP (Bussell et al., 2014) and UAS-mSP 
(Nakayama et al., 1997) in this study. To generate CG3542-
LexA and CG3542-GAL4, we performed a PCR amplification of 
the genomic region 5′ of the CG3542 transcriptional start site 
(+228 to -22) (forward primer, 5′ NNGCGGCCGCCGATAA 
CAGAAAATCTACCGGGT-3′; reverse primer, 5′-NNTCTAGA 
CCCACGCTAGGAGGAACATT-3′) and cloned the product into 
the pENTR vector (Invitrogen). We then recombined this into 
the pBPnlsLexAp65Uw vector for the LexA line or the 
pPTGAL4(+) vector for the GAL4 line (Pfeiffer et al., 2010). We 
injected each final plasmid into embryos using standard tech-
iniqes for insertion into a specific site on the second chromo-
some (VIE-72A) using phiC31-mediated recombination. </p>

<p>Behavioral assays 
We raised all flies on normal fly food at 25°C under a 12 h: 12 h 
light: dark cycle (Park et al., 2014). For all behavioral assays, 
we collected flies immediately after eclosion and aged females 
3-5 days in groups of ~10 and males 4 days individually. For 
the initial mating assays, we paired virgin females individually 
with naïve Canton S (CS) males in 1 cm diameter chambers 
and counted the number of mating pairs for 1 h. In case of egg-
laying, we transferred individual females who copulated within 1 
h to vials containing normal fly food. Then, we counted the eggs 
laid by each female over the course of 48 h. For virgin egg-
laying, we transferred 5 aged virgin females to vials containing 
normal fly food and counted the total eggs laid over the course 
of 48 h. For re-mating, we paired individual females who had 
mated within the past 48 h with naïve CS males and observed 
their mating for 1 h. All behavioral assays were performed at RT 
(25°C) and 60% humidity. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry 
We dissected ovaries in phosphate buffered saline (PBS) (pH 
7.4) and fixed them in 4% paraformaldehyde in PBS for 30 min 
at room temperature. After washing them with PBST, we incu-
bated them with a rabbit anti-GFP antibody (1:1000; Invitrogen, 
A11122) for 48 h at 4°C. After washing, we then incubated the 
samples for 24 h at 4°C with an Alexa 488-conjugated goat 
anti-rabbit (1:1000; Invitrogen, A11008) secondary antibody and 
an Alexa 555-conjugated phalloidin (1:1000; Invitrogen, 
A34055) to visualize actin in the muscle-rich reproductive tract. 
Finally, we mounted the tissues in Vectashield and imaged 
them with an LSM 700/Axiovert 200M confocal microscope 
(Zeiss). All confocal images are maximal intensity Z-projections. 
We performed all image processing with <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs>. </p>

<p>Statistics 
We used <rs id="software-2" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version">5</rs> to compare experimental groups 
with multiple control groups using the ANOVA followed by Tuk-
ey's test for multiple comparisons. </p>

<p>Oviduct Pickpocket Neurons Important for Egg-Laying 
Hyunjin Lee et al. </p>

<p>http://molcells.org 
Mol. Cells 575 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Identification of signal-
ing molecules downstream of 
SPR via a mass spectrome-
try-based label-free phospho-
proteomic approach. (A) Ex-
perimental scheme for phos-
phopeptide enrichment. (B) 
Experimental scheme for micro 
RPLC-MS/MS analysis and 
label-free quantification. (C) 
Proteins showing reduced 
levels of phosphorylation in 
SP-treated BG2 cells as 
filtered by R SC significance (p 
&lt; 0.1). (D) Proteins showing 
elevated levels of phos-
phorylation in SP-treated 
BG2 cells as filtered by R SC 
significance (p &lt; 0.1). </p>

<p>A 
C </p>

<p>B 
D </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>In this study, we hoped to discover proteins downstream of SP 
and SPR actions as well as the neurons that express them. To 
apply our mass spectrometry-based phospho-proteomic ap-
proach, we needed a cell line that expresses SPR. After exam-
ining several cell lines derived from Drosophila melanogaster 
nervous tissue, we found that the BG2 cell line derived from 
third instar larval brains meets this criterion (data not shown). 
After treating BG2 cells with 100 nM SP for 2 h, we analyzed 
them with label-free quantitative mass spectrometry. This tech-
nique permits the unbiased monitoring of protein phosphoryla-
tion levels at specific individual phosphorylation sites. We iden-</p>

<p>tified 35 proteins that show significantly different levels of phos-
phorylation between SP-and vehicle-treated cells (p &lt; 0.1). 
Consistent with our prediction that SPR activation would reduce 
PKA activity, we found more proteins with reduced phosphory-
lation (21) than increased phosphorylation (14) (Fig. 1). 
To determine whether any of these proteins showing altered 
phosphorylation upon SPR activation affect the egg-laying or 
mating refractoriness components of the PMR in vivo, we per-
formed a small-scale RNAi screen knocking-down each candi-
date in ppk neurons (Fig. 2A). In this screen, we found females 
expressing CG3542-IR1 show significantly elevated egg-laying 
for 48 h post-mating (Fig. 2B). Although knock-down of 
CG3542 affects egg-laying, it does not seem to affect receptiv-</p>

<p>Oviduct Pickpocket Neurons Important for Egg-Laying 
Hyunjin Lee et al. </p>

<p>576 Mol. Cells 
http://molcells.org </p>

<p>Fig. 2. CG3542 knock-down in ppk neurons af-
fects egg-laying in mated females. (A) Behavioral 
protocol used for (B, C). (B) Eggs laid per female 
of the indicated UAS line crossed with ppk-Gal4 
for 48 h post-mating, n = 20-58 (n of CG8101-
RNAi =12). ***p &lt; 0.001 for comparisons against 
ppk-GAL4 alone (white bar); one-way ANOVA 
followed by Tukey's test for multiple comparisons. 
(C) Re-mating rate, n = 20-58 (CG47283-RNAi 
haven't be tested). ***p &lt; 0.001 for comparisons 
against ppk-GAL4 alone; Fisher's exact test. (D) 
Eggs laid per female of the indicated genotype for 
48 h post-mating, n = 20-35. ***p &lt; 0.001, one-
way ANOVA followed by Tukey's test for multiple 
comparisons. </p>

<p>A 
D </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>ity to re-mating 48 h after initial mating (Fig. 2C). We confirmed 
the specificity of the RNAi-mediated knock-down of CG3542 by 
testing an additional RNAi line (CG3542-IR2) and observed a 
similar effect on egg-laying (Fig. 2D). This suggests CG3542 is 
important for the function of ppk neurons, especially the subset 
of the ppk neurons that direct post-mating changes in egg-
laying. CG3542 encodes a protein predicted to regulate mRNA 
splicing, but this has not yet been confirmed. 
Since knock-down of CG3542 in ppk neurons affects egg-
laying but not re-mating, we reasoned that we should be able to 
affect egg-laying by manipulating the activity of ppk neurons 
positive for CG3542. To test this idea, we adopted an intersec-
tional genetic approach. We generated a CG3542-LexA 
transgene (Fig. 3A) and combined it with LexAOP-FLP, ppk-
GAL4, and UAS-FRT-stop-FRT-Kir2.1. In females carrying all of 
these transgenes, CG3542-LexA drives the expression of a 
flippase that removes the transcriptional stop cassette flanked 
by FRT sites (FRT-stop-FRT) in the UAS transgene. This 
means only cells expressing both CG3542-LexA and ppk-
GAL4 will produce Kir2.1, an inwardly-rectifying potassium 
channel (Johns and Marx, 1999) that suppresses neural depo-
larization (Fig. 3B). Indeed, although mated females with si-
lenced CG3542-LexA and ppk-GAL4 double-positive (hence-
forth, CG3542-ppk) neurons lay more eggs than controls (Fig. 
3C), their virgin counterparts do not. The egg-laying phenotype 
in these females is comparable to that observed in 
ppk&gt;CG3542-IR females. When we activated CG3542-ppk 
neurons using dTrpA1, a temperature-sensitive cation channel 
that depolarizes neurons at warmer temperatures (30°C), we 
observed no change in egg-laying (Fig. 3D). It is important to 
note that the silencing of all ppk neurons was previously report-
ed to induce significant egg-laying even in virgin females (See 
also Fig. 3E). Since, in contrast, the silencing of CG3542-ppk 
neurons has no effect on virgin egg-laying, we have confirmed 
a role for CG3542-ppk neurons in specifically regulating post-
mating egg-laying. 
We next examined EGFP-expressing neurons in the genital </p>

<p>tract of females carrying CG3542-LexA, LexAOP-FLP, ppk-
GAL4, and UAS-FRT-stop-FRT-mCD8-EGFP. Remarkably, we 
were only able to detect 2-3 EGFP-positive neurons per female 
genital tract (Fig. 3F): two in the lateral oviduct (Fig. 3F′) and 
one in the middle oviduct near the spermatheca (Fig. 3F′′). The 
neurons in the lateral oviduct were paired in most preparations 
(n = 4/5), but the neurons in the common oviduct always ap-
peared alone (n = 5/5). In most preparations, we were unable to 
detect any EGFP in the uterus (n = 4/5). To better understand 
the function of these CG3542-ppk neurons, we examined their 
polarity using the pre-synaptic marker nsyb-EGFP (Zhang et al.,  2002) and the post-synaptic marker Dscam-GFP. We detected 
significant accumulation of nsyb-EGFP, but not Dscam-GFP in 
processes innervating the lateral oviduct. This indicates the 
CG3542-ppk neurons are likely efferent modulators of lateral 
oviduct contractility for controlling ovulation (Figs. 3G-3H). 
Expression of a membrane-tethered SP (mSP) in either all 
neurons or specifically in ppk neurons suppresses mating and 
increases egg-laying in virgin females, recapitulating the post-
mating response of mated females (Nakayama et al., 1997;  Rezával et al., 2012; Yang et al., 2009). Since we found the 
CG3542-ppk neurons regulate egg-laying, we next asked 
whether driving expression of mSP in CG3542 neurons also 
induces egg-laying in virgin females. To do so, we generated 
CG3542-GAL4 flies using the same genomic fragment we used 
to generate CG3542-LexA (Fig. 3A). We confirmed CG3542-
GAL4 driving the expression of Kir2.1 affects the egg-laying of 
both mated and virgin females without affecting mating recep-
tivity (Figs. 4A-4C). This indicates CG3542-GAL4, like CG3542-
LexA, is expressed in neurons relevant to egg-laying. Finally, 
we combined CG3542-GAL4 and UAS-mSP to express mSP in 
the CG3542 neurons and compared their virgin egg-laying 
behavior with that of ppk&gt;mSP flies. We confirmed that 
ppk&gt;mSP virgins show elevated egg-laying compared to con-
trols, but CG3542&gt;mSP do not (Figs. 4D-4F). This suggests 
the presence of an unknown subset of ppk neurons in addition 
to the CG3542-ppk neurons that also regulates egg-laying. </p>

<p>Oviduct Pickpocket Neurons Important for Egg-Laying 
Hyunjin Lee et al. </p>

<p>http://molcells.org 
Mol. Cells 577 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D 
E </p>

<p>F 
F′ 
G 
G′ </p>

<p>F′′ 
H 
H′ </p>

<p>Fig. 3. ppk-Gal4 and CG3542-LexA double positive neurons modulate egg-laying in mated females. (A) The CG3542 gene structure (top) and 
the genomic fragment used to generate CG3542-LexA (bottom). The gray and red boxes indicate untranslated and translated exons of the 
CG3542 transcript, respectively. (B) Schematic detailing our intersectional genetic approach. (C) Mating receptivity in virgin females (left), egg-
laying by mated females (middle) and egg-laying by virgin females (right) of the indicated genotypes. For egg-laying, we counted eggs laid per 
mated female or per five virgin females for 48 h. The numbers inside each bar indicate n. Data are presented as mean percentages (for mating 
receptivity) or means ± SEM (for egg-laying). **p &lt; 0.01, not significant (ns) p &gt; 0.05 for comparisons against both controls (yellow bars); Fish-
er's exact test (mating receptivity); one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's test for multiple comparisons (egg-laying). (D) Eggs laid per mated 
female of the indicated genotypes for 48 h. The numbers inside each bar indicate n. Data are presented as means ± SEM. Not significant (ns), 
p &gt; 0.05 for comparisons against both controls (pink bars); one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's test for multiple comparisons. (E) Eggs laid 
per five virgin females of the indicated genotypes for 48 h. The numbers inside each bar indicate n. Data are presented as means ± SEM. ***p 
&lt; 0.001 for comparisons against both controls (yellow bars); one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's test for multiple comparisons. (F) Confocal 
images of reproductive organs from ppk-Gal4 CG3542-LexA LexAop-FLP UAS&gt;stop&gt;mCD8-EGFP females, stained with an anti-GFP (green) 
antibody and a fluorophore-conjugated phalloidin (red). Ov, ovary; Lo, lateral oviduct; Co, common oviduct; Ut, uterus. Scale bar, 100 μm. (F′ 
and F′′) High magnification view of the areas outlined in (E). (G and G′) Visualization of the pre-synaptic marker nSyb-EGFP in CG3542-ppk 
neurons from females carrying ppk-Gal4, CG3542-LexA, LexAop-FLP, and UAS&gt;stop&gt;nSyb-EGFP, stained with an anti-GFP (green) antibody 
and a fluorophore-conjugated phalloidin (red). (F), the lateral oviduct. (F′), the common oviduct. Scale bar, 100 μm. (H and H′) Visualization of 
the post-synaptic marker Dscam-GFP in CG3542-ppk neurons from females carrying ppk-Gal4, CG3542-LexA, LexAop-FLP, and 
UAS&gt;stop&gt;Dscam-GFP, stained with an anti-GFP (red) antibody and the color was presented in red. (G), the lateral oviduct. (G′), the common 
oviduct. Scale bar, 100 μm. </p>

<p>Oviduct Pickpocket Neurons Important for Egg-Laying 
Hyunjin Lee et al. </p>

<p>578 Mol. Cells 
http://molcells.org </p>

<p>Fig. 4. SPR activation in CG3542 neurons is insufficient 
for inducing egg-laying in virgin females. (A) Mating 
receptivity of virgin females of the indicated genotypes. 
The numbers inside each bar indicate n. Data are pre-
sented as mean percentages. Not significant (ns), p &gt; 
0.05 for comparisons against both controls (light gray 
bars); Fisher's exact test. (B, D) Eggs laid per female of 
the indicated genotypes for 48 h post-mating. The num-
bers inside each bar indicate n. Data are presented as 
means ± SEM. **p &lt; 0.01 and not significant (ns), p &gt; 
0.05 for comparisons against both controls (light gray 
bars); one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's test for mul-
tiple comparisons. (C, E, and F) Eggs laid per five virgin 
females of the indicated genotypes for 48 h. The num-
bers inside each bar indicate n. Data are presented as 
means ± SEM. ***p &lt; 0.001 and not significant (ns), p &gt; 
0.05 for comparisons against both controls (light gray 
bars); one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's test for mul-
tiple comparisons. </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>D 
E 
F </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Here, we have identified a small subset of ppk neurons that 
modulate egg-laying activity in female Drosophila. Using prote-
omic techniques we identified CG3542 as a gene whose phos-
phorylation is enhanced by SP treatment. We found that ex-
pression of CG3542 in ppk neurons is required to maintain 
normal levels of egg-laying. CG3542 encodes a protein homol-
ogous to the yeast pre-mRNA splicing factor 40 (PRP40), which 
associates with the U1 small nuclear ribonucleoprotein 
(snRNP) and bridges the 5′ and 3′ ends of spliced introns (Tang  and Rosbash, 1996). Normal male courtship behavior was 
recently found to depend on the interaction between the P-
element Somatic Inhibitor (PSI) and the U1 snRNP complex. 
This complex affects the alternative splicing of a list of roughly 
1,200 genes, including the sexually dimorphic transcription 
factor fruitless (fru) that regulates gender-specific behaviors 
(Wang et al., 2016). Although it remains unclear whether the 
oviduct CG3542-ppk neurons are fru-positive, one pair of lateral 
oviduct ppk neurons expresses fru </p>

<p>GAL4   , a GAL4 knock-in at the 
fru-P1 locus (Yang et al., 2009). Thus, we speculate that the 
knock-down of CG3542 in the CG3542-ppk neurons alters the 
splicing of genes important for their development and/or func-
tion. 
SPR is a Gαi/Gαo-coupled GPCR. Its activation inhibits ade-
nylate cyclase, reduces intracellular cAMP, and inhibits PKA. 
Thus, SPR activation should produce global changes in the 
phosphorylation states of many proteins, particularly substrates 
of PKA. Indeed, our analysis identified many proteins that be-
come hypo-phosphorylated upon SP treatment. Unexpectedly, 
we also identified several proteins, including CG3542, that be-
come hyper-phosphorylated. This means SPR can promote </p>

<p>protein phosphorylation as well as de-phosphorylation. Alt-
hough the mechanism underlying this phenomenon remains 
unclear, it is likely SPR can affect downstream signaling path-
ways other than PKA. Consistent with this, over-expression in 
ppk neurons of an activated PKA affects mating receptivity 
much more strongly than it affects egg-laying (Yang et al.,  2009). This suggests the distinct components of the PMR de-
pend on distinct signaling pathways downstream of SPR. It is 
also of course possible that the hyper-phosphorylation of 
CG3542 induced by SPR activation is indirect. 
Here, we report that the silencing of a small subset of ppk neu-
rons increases post-mating egg-laying. Previously, Haesemeyer  et al. (2009) found silencing all the ppk neurons has very little 
impact on post-mating egg-laying behavior. This discrepancy 
with our results may stem from a difference in the genetic rea-
gents used to silence the ppk neurons. Haesemeyer et al. used 
the temperature-sensitive, dominant-negative dynamin mutant 
shi 
ts to conditionally block the recycling of neurotransmitter 
vesicles at the restrictive temperatures (Kitamoto, 2001). We, 
instead chose the inward-rectifying potassium channel Kir2.1 to 
achieve much stronger silencing. 
Previous studies have suggested mating receptivity and egg-
laying are genetically separable in Drosophila (Yang et al.,  2009). This is consistent with our observation that silencing only 
2-3 CG3542-ppk neurons of the ~38 ppk neurons in the female 
genital tract affects egg-laying but not mating receptivity. Never-
theless, we found mSP expression in the CG3542-ppk neurons 
is insufficient to induce egg-laying in virgin females, unlike mSP 
expression in all ppk neurons. Egg-laying is the culmination of a 
multi-step process comprising egg-formation, ovulation, fertili-
zation, and oviposition. The anatomy of the CG3542-ppk neu-
rons suggests they may play a role only in ovulation, because </p>

<p>Oviduct Pickpocket Neurons Important for Egg-Laying 
Hyunjin Lee et al. </p>

<p>http://molcells.org 
Mol. Cells 579 </p>

<p>their pre-synaptic processes extensively innervate the basal 
domain of the lateral oviduct. This may explain why SPR activa-
tion in the 2-3 CG3542-ppk neurons cannot activate all steps of 
the process enough to increase egg-laying as a whole. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We would like to thank Hae-Sook Yoon, Jungha Mun, and 
Ju-won Song for excellent technical assistance. We also 
acknowledge the Vienna Drosophila Resource Center for 
providing fly stocks. This work was supported by Basic Science 
Research Program grants to Y-J.K. (NRF-2013R1A1A2010475 
and 2015R1A2A1A10054304) from the National Research 
Foundation of Korea (NRF), which is funded by the Republic of 
Korea Ministry of Science, ICT, and Future Planning (MSIP). </p>



</text></tei>