<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4236336" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Artificial neural networks imitate learning processes and 
interactions between human neurons. 
8 During the training phase, 
it gradually reduces the deviation of prediction by learning the 
relationships among inputs (variables) and outputs (prediction results) 
as well as relationships between the input variables. Finally, the ANN 
has the ability to predict the probability of BCR. 
Opinions vary regarding the comparison between ANN and 
LR. 
9-14 Most criticism arises from the limited prediction accuracy due 
to limitations of the algorithm. 
15,16 LR is a special form of ANN. If the 
relationships among input parameters are nonlinear, ANN models will 
perform better than LR. Otherwise, the LR is preferable because the 
influence of each parameter can be observed much easier than in ANNs. 
In this study, we describe the suitability of ANNs as a prediction 
tools for BCR. Evaluation of the ability of a computer model to predict 
of BCR after radical prostatectomy is mainly based on the following 
parameters: the accuracy of the predicting models, the universality 
of the internal/external validation, correction capability, complexity, 
and clinical value. 
17 Here, we analyzed ANN and LR performance in 
predicting BCR based on these criteria. In addition to the ANN and LR 
models immediately after surgery, we analyzed ANN and LR models 
that evaluate BCR risk at 6-month intervals, which allows for a more </p>

<p>5   For higher accuracy and specificity; multivariate logistic regression 
(LR) models such as nomograms 
6 have been used to improve 
prediction. Most applications of LR in BCR prediction are available 
with standard nomograms, but there are only few artificial neural 
networks (ANNs) available for BCR prediction 
7 and none is freely 
available online. Further, there are no available models that calculate the 
individual BCR free probability at multiple time-points after operation 
especially after different time periods without BCR. </p>

<p>ORIGINAL ARTICLE </p>

<p>Risk prediction models for biochemical recurrence 
after radical prostatectomy using prostate-specific 
antigen and Gleason score </p>

<p>Xin-Hai Hu 
1 , Henning Cammann 
2 , Hellmuth-A Meyer </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Klaus Jung </p>

<p>1,3 </p>

<p>, Hong-Biao Lu </p>

<p>1,4 </p>

<p>, Natalia Leva 
5 , 
Ahmed Magheli 
1 , Carsten Stephan </p>

<p>1,3 </p>

<p>, Jonas Busch </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Many computer models for predicting the risk of prostate cancer have been developed including for prediction of biochemical recurrence 
(BCR). However, models for individual BCR free probability at individual time-points after a BCR free period are rare. Follow-up data 
from 1656 patients who underwent laparoscopic radical prostatectomy (LRP) were used to develop an artificial neural network (ANN) 
to predict BCR and to compare it with a logistic regression (LR) model using clinical and pathologic parameters, prostate-specific 
antigen (PSA), margin status (R0/1), pathological stage (pT), and Gleason Score (GS). For individual BCR prediction at any given 
time after operation, additional ANN, and LR models were calculated every 6 months for up to 7.5 years of follow-up. The areas 
under the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve (AUC) for the ANN (0.754) and LR models (0.755) calculated immediately 
following LRP, were larger than that for GS (AUC: 0.715; P = 0.0015 and 0.001), pT or PSA (AUC: 0.619; P always &lt;0.0001) alone. 
The GS predicted the BCR better than PSA (P = 0.0001), but there was no difference between the ANN and LR models (P = 0.39). 
Our ANN and LR models predicted individual BCR risk from radical prostatectomy for up to 10 years postoperative. ANN and LR 
models equally and significantly improved the prediction of BCR compared with PSA and GS alone. When the GS and ANN output 
values are combined, a more accurate BCR prediction is possible, especially in high-risk patients with GS ≥7. 
Asian Journal of Andrology (2014) 16, 897-901; doi: 10.4103/1008-682X.129940; published online: 04 July 2014 </p>

<p>Keywords: artificial neural network; prostate cancer; recurrence </p>

<p>1 Department of Urology, Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany; 
2 Institute of Medical Informatics, Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany; 
3 Berlin Institute for Urologic Research, Berlin, Germany; </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Department of Urology, Changzhou No. 2 People's Hospital, Changzhou, China; </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Stanford University School of 
Medicine, Stanford, CA, USA. 
Correspondence: Dr. J Busch (jonas.busch@charite.de) 
Received: 29 October 2013; Revised: 08 December 2013; Accepted: 22 January 2014 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Prostate Disease </p>

<p>Asian Journal of Andrology </p>

<p>Recurrence models for PCa 
XH Hu et al </p>



<p>accurate prediction of BCR at any given time after surgery. ANN has 
already been described as a good alternative to Cox and other regression 
models. 
18 From a practical point of view, there is an urgent need for 
tools that provide information on recurrence-free survival (FS) at 
distinct time points after radical prostatectomy taking into account 
the already elapsed recurrence-free interval. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Study population 
Between 1999 and 2007, 1897 PCa patients underwent LRP at our 
institution. Among them, 322 patients were lost to follow-up or had 
to be eliminated due to neo-adjuvant hormonal therapy or largely 
incomplete datasets. The remaining 1575 patients were divided into two 
groups: 1300 patients (82.5%) with no evidence of BCR (nonBCR) and 
275 patients (17.5%) with BCR (BCR group). The median follow-up 
period was 82.1 months (range from 0.2 to 129.5). </p>

<p>Data collection 
Biochemical recurrence was defined as serum PSA levels greater than 
0.1 ng ml 
−1 at two consecutive time points. All preoperative blood 
samples were measured by Immulite® 2000 assays (Siemens Healthcare, 
Erlangen, Germany). Data collection included: age, PSA, free/total 
PSA (%fPSA), prostate weight, digital rectal examination (DRE) 
status, pT, 
19 margin status (positive surgical margin [PSM] or negative 
surgical margin [NSM]) and GS. 
20 For the parameter distribution 
analysis, pTs of the prostatectomy specimens were classified into 
pT2, pT3/4; GS &lt;7, GS =7, GS &gt;7; PSM or NSM; positive DRE or 
negative DRE. PSA, margin status, pT and GS were used for ANN 
and LR analysis. 
This study was conducted under a local Ethics Committee approved 
protocol and obeys Reporting of Diagnostic Accuracy guidelines. </p>

<p>21   Statistical analysis 
Artificial neural network and LR models were computed using the 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">MATLAB</rs>-software and the Neural Network Toolbox (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Mathworks</rs>, 
Natick, MA, USA). Each ANN (feed forward network with error back 
propagation) had three layers: input layer with four neurons, hidden 
layer with two neurons and output layer with one neuron representing 
the nonBCR probability. Follow-up data after LRP were collected every 
6 months and respectively added into the separate models. Every 
6 months separate models (ANN and LR) were calculated with those 
patients still not having a BCR at this time-point (those with a BCR 
earlier were excluded) and those who were not censored. For all models, 
internal validation was performed with the leave one out method. 
Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version">19.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">IBM</rs>, Chicago, 
IL, USA) and <rs id="software-3" type="software">MedCalc</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version">12.4.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">MedCalc Software</rs>, Mariakerke, Belgium) 
to compare all variables using receiver operating characteristic (ROC) 
analyses regarding sensitivity, specificity and areas under ROC curve 
(AUC). The comparison of ROC curves were performed with the 
method of Delong and the comparison of prediction results were 
conducted using Mann-Whitney U test for continuous variables and 
Fisher's exact test for ordinal variables. Differences were considered 
statistically significant if P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Baseline characteristics 
Table 1 displays the patient characteristics as well as the distribution 
of clinico-patholological parameters of the BCR and nonBCR group. 
There were no relevant differences between the two groups for 
age (P = 0.37), PSA (P = 0.12), %fPSA (P = 0.26), prostate volume 
(P = 0.33), and PSA density (P = 0.11). In contrast, the pathological GS, </p>

<p>margin status, and pT were different between the BCR and nonBCR 
group except for GS =7 (P = 0.12), as shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>Receiver operating characteristic analysis of selected parameters 
Specificities of the BCR prediction results computed by ANN and LR 
models with the PSA, margin status, pT, and GS directly after LRP 
were the highest at both sensitivity cutoffs of 90% and 95%, as shown 
in Table 2. GS and PSA showed lower specificities and lower AUCs 
than ANN and LR. Figure 1 clearly shows the larger AUCs of the 
two models compared with GS and PSA alone. Table 3 displays the 
pairwise comparison of all parameters. While ANN and LR were not 
different (P = 0.39), ANN and LR predicted BCR better than PSA or </p>

<p>Table 1: Clinical characteristics of the study population </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Total 
Non-BCR 
BCR 
P </p>

<p>Number 
1575 
1300 
275 </p>

<p>Age (year) </p>

<p>Median 
(IQR 25%-75%) </p>

<p>63 
(59-66) </p>

<p>63 
(59-66) </p>

<p>63 
(59-67) </p>

<p>0.374 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Range 
43-75 
43-75 
43-75 </p>

<p>PSA (ng ml </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Median 
(IQR 25%-75%) </p>

<p>7.5 
(5.3-11.0) </p>

<p>7.5 
(5.2-10.4) </p>

<p>7.5 
(6.3-14.1) </p>

<p>0.115 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Range 
1.3-50.7 
1.3-50.7 
1.7-50.6 </p>

<p>%fPSA </p>

<p>Median 
(IQR 25%-75%) </p>

<p>9.35 
(6.51-13.1) </p>

<p>9.60 
(6.67-13.4) </p>

<p>8.0 
(6.07-11.6) </p>

<p>0.257 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Range 
1.18-41.2 
1.18-41.2 
1.57-27.0 </p>

<p>PV (ml) </p>

<p>Median 
(IQR 25%-75%) </p>

<p>35 
(26-47) </p>

<p>35 
(26-48) </p>

<p>30 
(25-42) </p>

<p>0.334 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Range 
7-190 
7-190 
12-105 </p>

<p>PSA density </p>

<p>Median 
(IQR 25%-75%) </p>

<p>0.21 
(0.14-0.33) </p>

<p>0.20 
(0.13-0.31) </p>

<p>0.29 
(0.18-0.44) </p>

<p>0.108 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Range 
0.02-1.66 
0.02-1.66 
0.04-1.64 </p>

<p>DRE positive 
548 
410 
138 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>R1=1 
488 
341 
147 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Gleason, n (%) </p>

<p>Gleason&lt;7 
549 (35) 
509 (39) 
40 (15) 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Gleason=7 
766 (49) 
644 (50) 
122 (44) </p>

<p>Gleason&gt;7 
260 (16) 
147 (11) 
113 (41) </p>

<p>pT, n (%) </p>

<p>pT=2 
1119 (71) 
1004 (77) 
115 (42) 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>pT=3 
446 (28) 
292 (22) 
154 (56) </p>

<p>pT=4 
10 (1) 
4 (1) 
6 (2) </p>

<p>IQR: interquartile range; BCR: biochemical recurrence; DRE: digital rectal examination; 
%fPSA: percent free PSA; PSA: prostate-specific antigen; PV: prostate volume; 
R1: margin status. a Values in parentheses are IQRs or percentages of patients' number; 
b Mann-Whitney U test; c Fisher's exact test </p>

<p>Table 2: ROC analysis with prediction results at 90% sensitivity and 
95% sensitivity </p>

<p>90% sensitivity 
95% sensitivity 
AUC 
95% CI </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Specificity 
CI 
Specificity 
CI </p>

<p>ANN 
35.1 
32.6-37.8 
20 
17.9-22.3 0.754 0.721-0.786 </p>

<p>LR 
36.5 
33.9-39.2 
18.8 
16.8-21.1 0.755 0.723-0.787 </p>

<p>GS 
NA 
8.92 
7.4-10.6 0.715 0.680-0.750 </p>

<p>PSA 
18.6 
16.5-20.8 
8.46 
7.0-10.1 0.619 0.582-0.657 </p>

<p>GS: Gleason score; ROC: receiver operating characteristic; ANN: artificial neural network; 
AUC: area under ROC curve; CI: confidence interval; LR: logistic regression; PSA, 
prostate-specific antigen. a 95% CI of the respective AUC </p>

<p>Asian Journal of Andrology </p>

<p>Recurrence models for PCa 
XH Hu et al </p>



<p>GS (P = 0.0015 for ANN vs GS and P &lt; 0.0001 for ANN vs PSA, LR vs 
GS and vs PSA, respectively). </p>

<p>Biochemical recurrence-free survival curves 
Figure 2 displays probabilities for BCR-FS up to 2.5, 5, and 7.5 years 
after LRP for different categories of GS and ANN outputs. PCa patients 
with GS &lt;7 always have the highest probability for BCR-FS compared 
with patients with GS =7 or GS &gt;7 (Figure 2a-2c). 
In predicting BCR-FS, ANN, and LR perform similarly (LR data not 
shown). To allow better differentiation of patients who more urgently 
may need adjuvant radiation (and hormonal treatment) we subdivided 
all patients using the continuous ANN output values and separated 
them into two groups below and above the median. This median 
output was calculated from the 1575 ANN output values according to 
the prevalence of nonBCR. Figure 2d-2f shows the difference between 
patients above and below the median ANN output values with up to 
2.5, 5, and 7.5 years of follow-up. 
Analysis of individual ANN output values had no benefit in 
patients with a GS &lt;7 PCa but it improved the prediction for all 
patients with GS ≥7. Of all 1026 PCa patients with GS ≥7, 235 (23%) 
had a BCR (Table 4). Of the 768 patients with an ANN value below 
the median cutoff, only 16.5% (n = 127) developed BCR. On the 
other hand, of the 258 patients with an ANN value above the median 
cutoff, 41.9% (n = 108) developed BCR. Further analysis of the 
260 patients with a GS &gt;7 showed an overall BCR rate of 43.5% (113 
of 260) that dropped tremendously when the ANN value was below 
the cutoff. Only 28 of 96 patients (29.2%) had a BCR. Interestingly, </p>

<p>among patients with aggressive PCa and high ANN values, 51.8% 
had a BCR (85 of 164). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Different types of ANNs have been used for a variety of purposes in 
management of PCa. For example, PSA, prostate volume, DRE, and 
other variables are used as input parameters for diagnosing PCa. </p>

<p>22   ANN is also used to predict the outcome of repeat prostate biopsies, </p>

<p>23   and furthermore, to predict the risk of lymph node metastasis in PCa 
patients. 
24 However, ANN applications to predict BCR are rare. </p>

<p>7,10   Our data on BCR prediction show that ANN and LR models 
including the parameters PSA, margin status, pT and GS, can 
correctly simulate and reflect interactions between variables in 
the training set. The models improve the prediction better than 
any single variable and thus estimate BCR more accurately for 
each individual patient with PCa. 
25 Some studies have verified 
that ANN models have the ability to improve prognosis prediction 
for PCa patients after prostatectomy. 
7,10,26-29 These data have been 
summarized in Table 5. One of the first studies in 1994 demonstrated 
87% accuracy. </p>

<p>26   Among all available studies to date, the results by Tewari et al. </p>

<p>7   showed the best AUC with 0.83; however, their accuracy was somewhat 
lower than in the present study and in other studies. Potter et al. 
26 gained 
similar AUCs of 0.71, 0.74, 0.74 using different input parameters, but 
the specificity was relatively lower than in our present study. However, 
despite large differences in sensitivity and specificity levels there are 
relatively small accuracy ranges (70%-87%) and AUCs between 
0.71 and 0.83 for all studies. This demonstrates that the parameters 
that were used do not allow a better prediction of BCR. Interestingly, 
PSA has been thought to improve prediction of BCR following PCa 
diagnosis; 
30 however in our study, %fPSA did not improve prognosis. 
The median values were not different between the non-BCR and BCR 
group (10.7 vs 9.2%; P = 0.26) (Table 1). 
An important finding was the additional benefit of our ANN for 
patients with aggressive PCa (GS ≥7). Among 1026 patients, 235 had a 
BCR (23%). Patients with a low ANN value (below the chosen cutoff) 
had only 16.5% of the 768 BCR (Table 4). But if patients had an ANN 
value above the cutoff, 41.9% showed BCR. This rate is almost doubled 
in comparison to the 23% without considering the ANN output value 
and almost tripled in comparison to the group below the cutoff. 
However, analysis of individual ANN output values had no benefit in 
patients with GS &lt;7 PCa, where only 40 patients had a BCR. 
When further analyzing the 260 patients with highly aggressive 
PCa and a GS &gt; 7, the overall BCR rate of 43.5% (113 of 260). This 
rate dropped when the ANN value was below the cutoff. Only 28 
of 96 patients (29.2%) had a BCR. In contrast, those patients with 
aggressive PCa and high ANN values had a &gt;50% likelihood to have a 
BCR (51.8%; 85 of 164). This individual risk estimation could support 
further treatment, especially in patients with high GS and high ANN 
values compared with lower risk patients. 
Uniquely, our calculated models at every 6 months following 
surgery can provide the individual BCR free probability at individual </p>

<p>Table 3: Pairwise comparison of prediction methods </p>

<p>Pairwise comparisons methods 
ANN versus LR 
ANN versus Gleason 
ANN versus PSA 
LR versus Gleason 
LR versus PSA 
Gleason versus PSA </p>

<p>AUC difference between areas 
0.001 
0.039 
0.134 
0.040 
0.136 
0.096 </p>

<p>95% CIs 
0.002-0.005 
0.014-0.063 
0.093-0.175 
0.016-0.064 
0.095-0.177 
0.048-0.143 </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.39 
0.0015 
&lt;0.0001 
0.0001 
&lt;0.0001 
0.0001 </p>

<p>ROC: receiver operating characteristic; CI: confidence interval; ANN: artificial neural network; AUC: area under ROC curve; LR: logistic regression; PSA: prostate-specific antigen; </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Delong test </p>

<p>Figure 1: Receiver operating characteristic curves for the models: artificial 
neural network (area under ROC curve [AUC] 0.754) and logistic regression 
(AUC 0.755) and the variables Gleason Score (AUC 0.715) and prostate-
specific antigen (AUC 0.619). </p>

<p>Asian Journal of Andrology </p>

<p>Recurrence models for PCa 
XH Hu et al </p>



<p>time-points after a BCR free period. For example, as shown in 
Figure 2b, a patient with a GS of 7 and a recurrence free survival of 
3 years after LRP only has an 8% likelihood of a BCR up to 5 years, and 
14% up to 7.5 years (Figure 2c). Without considering the three BCR 
free years, the estimated BCR risk would be ~22%. This allows for a 
more optimistic prognosis in comparison to those values calculating 
risk only immediately after prostatectomy. 
A limitation of this study is the availability of only internal 
validation results for all models. However, our aim was to demonstrate 
the possibility of improving individual BCR estimation at any point 
after LRP. Another limitation was the decreased available patient data 
with increased follow-up time. 
Nevertheless, patient's age, PSA, and GS were found to play 
a distinct role in PCa prognosis. 
3,31,32 Currently, those prediction 
parameters and the ANN output value best predict a PCa recurrence. 
Further, with our ANN models, this prediction can be made for an 
individual time point after LRP and with patients who have BCR free 
time-points. Other parameters such as %fPSA or the margin status 
did not contribute as speculated before. The %fPSA performs well in </p>

<p>PCa diagnosis, but is less competitive in the prognosis of PCa or BCR, 
therefore it is not used in our models. </p>

<p>Table 5: Comparison of ANNs with different parameters </p>

<p>Study 
No. of 
patients </p>

<p>Variables 
Sensitivity 
(%) </p>

<p>Specificity 
(%) </p>

<p>Accuracy 
(%) </p>

<p>AUC </p>

<p>Tewari 
et al. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>1280 Age, PSA, systematic 
biopsy-based, 
stage, perineural 
infiltration, GS, 
duration of follow-up 
in months </p>

<p>76 
85 
76 
0.831 </p>

<p>Ziada 
et al. </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>309 TNM stage, prostate 
size, PSA, GS, 
percentage of 
positive biopsy, age </p>

<p>79 
81 
80 </p>

<p>Potter 
et al. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>214 GS, extraprostatic 
extension, surgical 
margin status, age </p>

<p>88.2 
61.1 
74.3 0.713 </p>

<p>Potter 
et al. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>214 DNA ploidy, the 
variance of 41 
different nuclear 
morphometric 
descriptors </p>

<p>74.5 
85.2 
80.0 
0.74 </p>

<p>Potter 
et al. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>214 GS, extraprostatic 
extension, surgical 
margin status, 
age, DNA ploidy, 
QNG (the variance of 
41 different nuclear 
morphometric 
descriptors) </p>

<p>84.3 
72.2 
78.1 0.735 </p>

<p>Porter 
et al. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>196 Biopsy primary, 
secondary Gleason 
grade, biopsy GS, 
age, PSA </p>

<p>74 
78 
81 
0.80 </p>

<p>Present 
study </p>

<p>1575 Age, PSA, GS 
40.7 
87.5 
79.3 0.754 </p>

<p>ROC: receiver operating characteristic; ANN: artificial neural network; AUC: area under 
ROC curve; GS: Gleason score; LR: logistic regression; PSA: prostate-specific antigen; 
QNG: quantitative nuclear grade, TNM: tumor, node, metastases, DNA: deoxyribonucleic acid </p>

<p>Table 4: Proportion of patients with biochemical recurrence depending 
of Gleason score and artificial neural network output </p>

<p>No. patients (n) Patients with BCR (n, %) 
P </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>GS 7-10 
1026 
235 (22.9) </p>

<p>ANN 
output&lt;cutoff </p>

<p>768 
127 (16.5) 
&lt;0.00001 </p>

<p>ANN 
output≥cutoff </p>

<p>258 
108 (41.9) </p>

<p>GS 8-10 
260 
113 (43.5) </p>

<p>ANN 
output&lt;cutoff </p>

<p>96 
28 (29.2) 
0.0006 </p>

<p>ANN 
output≥cutoff </p>

<p>164 
85 (51.8) </p>

<p>ANN: artificial neural network; BCR: biochemical recurrence; GS: Gleason score. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Calculated by Fisher's exact test </p>

<p>Figure 2: Probability of recurrence-free survival at 2.5, 5, and 7.5 years after laparoscopic radical prostatectomy (LRP) according to Gleason score (above 
three figures) and artificial neural network output (below three figures). The curves are based on Kaplan-Meier curves computed every 6 months after LRP 
for patients which are under investigation, that is, patients without biochemical recurrence or not censored patients. </p>

<p>Asian Journal of Andrology </p>

<p>Recurrence models for PCa 
XH Hu et al </p>



<p>CONCLUSION 
The predictive ability of our ANN and LR models is better than single 
standard parameters GS and PSA. Our models for individual BCR free 
probability at individual time-points after a BCR free period offer an 
individual BCR prediction. By combining the GS and ANN output 
value, a BCR prediction is more accurate and may lead to a more 
accurate application of adjuvant therapy after prostatectomy especially 
in high-risk patients with GS ≥7. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS 
CS, JB, HC, HAM, and KJ took part in conception and design, in 
acquisition, analysis, and interpretation of data. XHH and HBL took 
part in acquisition, analysis, and interpretation of data. NL and AM 
took part in the acquisition of data. All authors took part in drafting 
and revising the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final 
version of the manuscript. </p>

<p>COMPETING INTERESTS 
The authors declare no competing interests. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant of the Berliner Sparkassenstiftung Medizin 
(Grant No. 89838600). </p>



</text></tei>