<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4146730" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>PURPOSE. Numerous methods were used to etch the fiber posts to improve its bonding to root canal dentin. Our 
aim was to evaluate the efficacy of 37% phosphoric acid in etching fiber posts in comparison with 24% 
hydrogen peroxide. MATERIALS AND METHODS. Ninety human maxillary central incisors were taken and post 
space preparation was done. Ninety fiber posts were taken and divided into three groups (n=30) based on the 
surface treatment they received (H 3 PO 4 , H 2 O 2 , distilled water) and each group was further divided (n=10) based 
on the time period of application (15 seconds, 30 seconds, 60 seconds). All the posts were luted into canals 
using Rely X UniCem-2. Each tooth was then sectioned into six slices and subjected to push out test. Data 
obtained was subjected to statistical analysis at P&lt;.05. The surface topography was evaluated using scanning 
electron microscopy. RESULTS. Highest bond strength values were noted in 15 seconds etched phosphoric acid 
group and 60 seconds etched hydrogen peroxide group with no significant difference between two groups. 
Surface topography revealed complete epoxy layer removal with no damage to its structural integrity in those 
groups. CONCLUSION. H 3 PO 4 etching for a period of 15 seconds is an effective alternative in improving the 
adhesion of fiber post to root dentin. [ J Adv Prosthodont 2014;6:295-301] </p>

<p>Fiber posts and resin based materials can behave as a 
mechanically homogeneous complex with dentin; their clin-
ical use introduced a new restorative concept, ensuring high 
resistance to occlusal loading. 
1 This assumption has been 
recently supported by several in vivo and in vitro investiga-
tions. </p>

<p>2-7 </p>

<p>Formation of monoblock is essential for the success of </p>

<p>a post luted to root canal dentin. 
8 Improper bonding at 
dentin/cement, cement/post interface leads to increased 
stress to occlusal loading leading to failure of post retained 
restorations. Bonding between resin cement and fiber post 
is aided by micromechanical and chemical means. 
9-12 Fiber 
post is covered by epoxy resin which is highly cross-linked 
and has a high degree of conversion. 
13 Therefore roughen-
ing the post to improve micromechanical bonding has been 
recommended. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Many techniques like sandblasting, etching with hydro-
fluoric acid were used to improve bonding, 
11,14,15 but these 
methods caused damage to the structure of glass fibers and 
affected the integrity of posts. 
11 Agents that dissolve only 
the epoxy matrix portion without interfering with fiber 
integrity were studied. 
12,16-18 Potassium permanganate, sodi-
um ethoxide, and hydrogen peroxide were used to etch and 
expose the glass fibers. </p>

<p>10,12,16-18 </p>

<p>Twenty-four percent hydrogen peroxide etching for 1 
min proved to be effective in improving bond strength. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Thirty-seven percent phosphoric acid is the commonly 
used agent to etch enamel and dentin that is readily avail-</p>

<p>Corresponding author: 
Chandrakanth Majeti 
Department of Conservative Dentistry and Endodontics, Mamata Dental 
College, Giri Prasad nagar, Khammam, Andhra Pradesh, India 
Tel. 09985456734: e-mail, drchandrakanthmajeti@gmail.com 
Received January 7, 2014 / Last Revision May 6, 2014 / Accepted May 
12, 2014 </p>

<p>© 2014 The Korean Academy of Prosthodontics 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons. 
org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, 
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original 
work is properly cited. </p>

<p>pISSN 2005-7806, eISSN 2005-7814 </p>



<p>able. The objective of the present in vitro study was to eval-
uate the efficacy of 37% H 3 PO 4 in comparison with 24% 
H 2 O 2 to etch fiber posts in terms of push out bond 
strength at various time periods. In addition surface topog-
raphy was evaluated by SEM and bond strengths at various 
root regions were compared. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Approval for the study was taken from Human Rights and 
Research Committee, Mamata Dental College. Ninety 
freshly extracted human maxillary central incisors were tak-
en and stored in sterile saline (0.9% NaCl). Each tooth was 
decoronated 1 to 2 mm below CEJ using safe-sided dia-
mond disk under water coolant so that length was standard-
ized to 16 mm. Patency was confirmed with a 10 K-file and 
root canals were enlarged using ProTaper rotary instru-
ments (Maillefer Dentsply, Ballaigues, Switzerland) until file 
F3 reached the working length (1 mm from apical fora-
men). Irrigation was done with 5% NaOCl (Vishal Dento 
care Pvt. Ltd., Ahmedabad, India) and 17% EDTA 
(Canalarge, Ammdent, Chandigarh, India) between each 
instrument. Finally canals were dried with paper points and 
obturation was done using Gutta percha cones (Maillefer 
Dentsply, Ballaigues, Switzerland) and AH plus sealer 
(Dentsply, Delhi, India) by lateral condensation method. 
The specimens were stored 37ºC, at 100% relative humidity 
for a period of 72 hours so as the resin sealer sets completely. 
Following this the coronal gutta percha removal was 
done with peeso-reamers #1 to 3 (Mani Inc., Tochigi, 
Japan) leaving 4 mm apical GP. Final post space prepara-
tion was done with #3 drill provided by the manufacturer 
of the Glassix post system (Swiss dental products of disin-
fection, Nordin, Switzerland). Finally post spaces were irri-
gated with distilled water and canals were dried. 
Ninety glass fiber reinforced parallel and smooth posts 
(Glassix posts, Nr3-Ø 1.35, Swiss dental products of disin-
fection, Nordin, Switzerland) were taken and divided into </p>

<p>three groups (n=30) according to the surface treatment 
they received (37% H 3 PO 4 , 24% H 2 O 2 , distilled water). 
Each group was further divided into 3 sub-groups (n=10) 
based on the time period of etchant application (15 sec-
onds, 30 seconds, 60 seconds). In H 3 PO 4 group, gel (Etch 
gel, DentoInc., St. Paul, MN, USA) was applied over entire 
surface of the post; in other two groups posts were 
immersed in respective solutions; all posts were then treat-
ed with distilled water and air dried. Etched posts are then 
luted into the root canals using Rely X Unicem-2 Clicker 
(3M ESPE AG, Seefeld, Germany) and light activated 
through cervical portion for 40 second (Blue phase C8, 
Ivoclar vivident, Schaan, Liechtenstein). The specimens 
were then stored for 24 hours at 37ºC in distilled water. 
Following storage, each specimen was sectioned into six 
slices of 2 mm each using diamond saw under water cool-
ant. The first two represent the coronal; second two middle 
and last two represent the apical regions of the root. The 
apical side of each specimen was marked with an indelible 
marker and each section was subjected to push out test 
from apical to coronal side in Universal testing machine 
(Autograph AG 15, Shimadzu, Kyoto, Japan) where the 
loading was performed at a cross head speed of 0.5 mm/ 
min until post dislodged from the root slice. Schematic rep-
resentation of entire push-out test is shown in Fig. 1. 
Comparison of bond strength values were done using 
Repeated measures of ANOVA (<rs id="software-0" type="software">IBM SPSS statistics</rs> for 
Windows, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 21.0</rs>, Armonk, NY, USA) and pair wise 
comparison was done by Tukey multiple post hoc test at a 
significance level at P&lt;.05. 
Twenty seven fiber posts were taken and divided into 3 
groups (n=9) based on the surface treatment (H 3 PO 4 , 
H 2 O 2 , distilled water). Each group was subdivided into 
three (n=3) based on the time period of etchant application 
(15, 30, 60 seconds). After etching all specimens were 
cleaned ultrasonically for 5 min. in deionoized water, fol-
lowed by immersion in 96% ethanol and gently air dried. 
The posts were then gold sputtered (model JFC-1600, </p>

<p>fig. 1. (A) Sectioning of tooth into six 2 mm sections, (B) Thin slice (2 mm) showing the post at center adhered to 
dentin, (C) Specimen placement in Universal Testing Machine, (D) Pictorial representation of cross-section of push out 
test. </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>2 mm </p>

<p>2 mm </p>

<p>2 mm </p>

<p>2 mm </p>

<p>2 mm </p>

<p>2 mm </p>

<p>Apical </p>

<p>Apical </p>

<p>Middle </p>

<p>Middle </p>

<p>Cervical </p>

<p>Cervical </p>

<p>4 mm GP </p>

<p>A 
C </p>

<p>Push out force </p>

<p>Push out jig </p>

<p>Post </p>

<p>Dentin 
Dentin </p>

<p>Platform 
Platform </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>J Adv Prosthodont 2014;6:295-301 </p>

<p>The Journal of Advanced Prosthodontics 297 </p>

<p>JEOL, Tokyo, Japan) and evaluated under SEM (model 
JSM-5600, JEOL, Tokyo, Japan). 
Dislodged specimens after push out test were examine 
under stereomicroscope (Olympus Opto Systems, India Pvt 
Ltd., Noida, India) at ×4.5 magnification and mode of fail-
ure was classified as adhesive between cement and dentin, 
adhesive between cement and post, cohesive within the 
cement. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The mean values of all the groups are shown in Fig. 2. 
Results showed highest bond strength values for H 3 PO 4 
group at 15 seconds and H 2 O 2 group at 60 seconds at all 
the three root regions with no significant difference 
between those two groups (P&gt;.05)(Table 1). Bond strength 
was greater in the coronal region followed by middle then 
apical irrespective of etchant and time period (P&lt;.05). </p>

<p>Table 1. Mean bond strength values of all groups in Mega Pascals </p>

<p>Root region </p>

<p>Etchant 
Time period (Seconds) 
Cervical 
Middle 
Apical 
Tukey* </p>

<p>H 3 PO 4 
15 
14.57 (0.62) 
12.20 (0.24) 
6.41 (0.32) 
a </p>

<p>30 
12.14 (0.54) 
10.57 (0.38) 
5.60 (0.34) 
b </p>

<p>60 
11.62 (0.24) 
10.10 (0.65) 
5.14 (0.30) 
b </p>

<p>H 2 O 2 
15 
10.57 (0.43) 
9.86 (0.50) 
4.17 (0.24) 
c </p>

<p>30 
10.66 (0.34) 
9.92 (0.58) 
5.19 (0.22) 
c </p>

<p>60 
14.38 (0.64) 
12.40 (0.42) 
6.07 (0.37) 
a </p>

<p>Water 
15 
10.89 (0.80) 
9.63 (0.46) 
4.16 (0.24) 
c </p>

<p>30 
11.09 (0.72) 
9.38 (0.44) 
4.15 (0.25) 
c </p>

<p>60 
10.97 (0.51) 
9.46 (0.38) 
4.10 (0.26) 
c </p>

<p>Tukey* 
A 
B 
C </p>

<p>*(Different letters -Capital letters -Comparison among columns, lower case letters -Comparison among rows) indicates statistical difference (P&lt;.05). </p>

<p>fig. 2. Comparison of bond strength of different etchants at various time periods and at various root regions (Mean Values). </p>

<p>MPa 
18.00 </p>

<p>16.00 </p>

<p>14.00 </p>

<p>12.00 </p>

<p>10.00 </p>

<p>8.00 </p>

<p>6.00 </p>

<p>4.00 </p>

<p>2.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>15 sec 
30 sec 
60 sec </p>

<p>H 3 PO 4 
Cervical </p>

<p>H 2 O 2 
Cervical </p>

<p>Water 
Cervical </p>

<p>H 3 PO 4 
Apical </p>

<p>H 2 O 2 
Apical </p>

<p>Water 
Apical </p>

<p>H 3 PO 4 
Middle </p>

<p>H 2 O 2 
Middle </p>

<p>Water 
Middle </p>

<p>A simplified etching technique to improve the adhesion of fiber post </p>



<p>SEM pictures of all the groups are shown in Fig. 3. 
Epoxy resin matrix was not removed in groups etched with 
distilled water at all time periods and in 15 seconds, 30 sec-
onds H 2 O 2 etched groups; complete removal of epoxy layer 
without damaging the fiber integrity was seen in 15 seconds 
H 3 PO 4 etched group and 60 seconds H 2 O 2 etched group. 
Some amount of damage to fiber integrity and complete 
damage to fiber integrity was noted in groups etched with 
H 3 PO 4 for 30 and 60 seconds respectively. 
The percentages of failures are shown in Table 2. </p>

<p>Adhesive failure between the cement and root canal dentin 
is the most common type of failure irrelevant to the type 
of surface treatment. Cohesive failure within the luting 
agent is the second most common type of failure in all the 
groups. Adhesive failure between cement and post are less 
compared to others. Fig. 4 shows various modes of failures. 
Among all groups, 60 seconds etched H 2 O 2 group and 15 
seconds etched H 3 PO 4 group showed the least adhesive 
failures between cement and post, also highest number of 
cohesive failures within the cement. </p>

<p>fig. 3. SEM topographic images. (A) distilled water for 15 sec, (B) distilled water for 30 sec, (C) distilled water for 60 
sec, (D) H 3 PO 4 for 15 sec, (E) H 3 PO 4 for 30 sec, (F) H 3 PO 4 for 60 sec, (G) H 2 O 2 for 15 sec, (H) H 2 O 2 for 30 sec, (I) H 2 O 2 for 
60 sec. Arrows in image A, B, C, G, H shows the epoxy layer covering the fibers; arrows in image D, I show clearly 
exposed glass fibers with complete epoxy layer removal; arrows in image E, F shows the areas where damage to fiber 
integrity has occurred. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>H </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>J Adv Prosthodont 2014;6:295-301 </p>

<p>The Journal of Advanced Prosthodontics 299 </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Posts rely on strength of bond between different interfaces 
for their retention. Among them, the interface between 
root dentin and resin cement, post and resin cement, post 
and core has been the object of several studies involving 
bond strengths. Use of fiber posts has gained wide accep-
tance in the recent era. The main problem often encoun-</p>

<p>tered is incomplete adhesion of post to resin cement and 
also to the core. Many procedures have been put forward to 
enhance its adhesive effectiveness from simple etching pro-
cedures to sand blasting etc. 
Results obtained in the present study clearly show the 
effectiveness of H 3 PO 4 in etching fiber post and improving 
its adhesion to root canal dentin. In the present study H 2 O 2 
is used since it had been proven to be effective in etching </p>

<p>Table 2. Percentages of various modes of failures </p>

<p>Etchant 
Time period (seconds) 
Adhesive failure between 
cement and dentin (%) </p>

<p>Adhesive failure between 
cement and post (%) </p>

<p>Cohesive within 
the cement (%) </p>

<p>Distilled water 
15 
41.6 
26.6 
31.6 </p>

<p>30 
43.3 
28.3 
28.3 </p>

<p>60 
41.6 
26.6 
31.6 </p>

<p>H 2 O 2 
15 
43.3 
28.3 
28.3 </p>

<p>30 
41.6 
26.6 
31.6 </p>

<p>60 
48.3 
16.6 
35.0 </p>

<p>H 3 PO 4 
15 
46.6 
18.3 
35.0 </p>

<p>30 
45.0 
21.6 
33.3 </p>

<p>60 
41.6 
26.6 
31.6 </p>

<p>fig. 4. Stereomicroscopic images (A) specimen before push out test, (B) adhesive failure between cement and post, (C) 
adhesive failure between cement and dentin, (D) cohesive failure within the cement. Arrows in image A shows the 
junction between luting agent and post, in image B shows the cement adhering to dentin, in image C represents dentin 
free of cement, in image D shows cement adhered both to the post and inner dentinal surface. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>A simplified etching technique to improve the adhesion of fiber post </p>



<p>fiber post 
19 and improving the bond strength; H 3 PO 4 is 
attempted to use in the present study since it is the com-
monly used chair side etchant. 
Fiber posts are covered by epoxy resin, which has a high 
degree of conversion and few reactive sites to chemically 
bond to the resin cement. 
13 So to improve the bond 
between post and adhesive resin, removal of epoxy layer is 
essential without disturbing the fiber integrity. Unlike the 
use of corrosive forms of industrial epoxy resin etching 
techniques such as sodium ethoxide or potassium perman-
ganate: H 2 O 2 and H 3 PO 4 etching provides clinically reliable 
methods to enhance micromechanical retention. Care 
should be taken not to etch for a longer time period since it 
affects the fiber integrity similarly to that of HF etching 
which had been proven to be an aggressive etching proce-
dure. 
17 Dissolution of epoxy resin probably relies on an 
electrophilic attack of the H 2 O 2 to the cured secondary 
amine. Thus the spaces created between the fibers provide 
conditions for the micro-mechanical interlocking of the 
resin with the post. Etching with H 2 O 2 is a proved subject 
but studies are still under progress evaluating the efficacy 
of various concentrations and time periods in altering its 
etching capability. </p>

<p>20-22 </p>

<p>SEM images clearly depict the removal of epoxy layer 
with intact glass fibers in H 2 O 2 and H 3 PO 4 groups at 1 min 
and 15 seconds time intervals respectively. So the exposed 
glass fibers aid in improving the bond strength both by 
micro-mechanical interlocking and by chemical means due 
interaction between methacrylate group of luting agent and 
glass fibers. 
Push out test was done since it produces shear stress at 
the interface between post and cement which mimics the 
stresses under clinical situation. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>The use of adhesive resins have gained popularity from 
the past few years with their advantage of minimizing the 
number of steps required and ease of use, so we have 
selected a self adhesive resin cement. The adhesive proper-
ties are claimed to be based upon acidic monomers that 
demineralize and infiltrate the tooth substrate, and create 
micromechanical retention and chemical adhesion to 
hydroxyapatite by forming resin tags. 
Our results are similar and support the study by 
Menezes et al. 
19 who proved H 2 O 2 etching for one minute 
improves the bond strength of fiber post. Our results also 
showed highest bond strength values in the coronal fol-
lowed by middle then apical root regions which is in accor-
dance with previous studies. 
23-27 The reason thought for this 
might be the decrease in the tubule density from coronal to 
apical region as explained previously by Ferrari et al. 
28 Most 
likely explanation for this higher resistance to dislodgement 
of post in coronal region and decreased resistance in apical 
region could be due to decreased effectiveness of curing 
light to penetrate from coronal region to the apex. Also the 
reduction in the bond strength may be related to the diffi-
culties of moisture control in apical third of post space 
which may resist complete infiltration of the resin cement. 
The type of failure modes reveal the least adhesive fail-</p>

<p>ures between the cement and post in 15 seconds H 3 PO 4 
group and 60 second H 2 O 2 group indicating the possible 
improvement in bonding between post and cement after 
etching. Also due to increased adhesion of cement to the 
post there might be internal stress created within the 
cement at the time of loading causing increased number of 
cohesive failures within the cement in those groups. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Within the limitations of the present in vitro study it can be 
concluded that etching of fiber post is essential to improve 
adhesion. 37% H 3 PO 4 etching for 15 second is a better and 
comfortable alternative to other methods in improving the 
adhesion of fiber post to root canal dentin. </p>



<p>J Adv Prosthodont 2014;6:295-301 </p>

<p>The Journal of Advanced Prosthodontics 301 </p>



<p>A simplified etching technique to improve the adhesion of fiber post </p>

</text></tei>