<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4965703" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>In the movement to improve the health of patients with multiple chronic conditions and vulnerabilities, while 
reducing the need for hospitalizations, care management programs have garnered wide attention and support. 
The qualitative data presented in this paper sheds new light on key components of successful chronic care 
management programs. By going beyond a task-and temporal-based framework, this analysis identifies and 
defines the importance of ''authentic healing relationships'' in driving individual and systemic change. Drawing 
on the voices of 30 former clients of the Camden Coalition of Healthcare Providers, the investigators use 
qualitative methods to identify and elaborate the core elements of the authentic healing relationship-security, 
genuineness, and continuity-a relationship that is linked to patient motivation and active health management. 
Although not readily found in the traditional health care delivery system, these authentic healing relationships 
present significant implications for addressing the persistent health-related needs of patients with frequent 
F </p>

<p>aced with accelerating health care costs in the 
United States, policy makers have grappled over the last 
several decades with the challenge of reducing spending 
while improving quality of care. 
1 As frequent hospital utili-
zation is considered to be a major contributor to health care 
spending, increased attention has been focused on the rela-
tively small proportion of the population described as ''high 
risk'' and ''high cost'' (also known as ''super-utilizers,'' 
''frequent flyers,'' and ''heavy users''). 
2 Despite a vast body 
of literature on a critical question in health care policy and 
delivery, there remains a great deal of uncertainty about the 
specific care needs of individuals with frequent hospitaliza-
tions and successful mechanisms to address these needs. </p>

<p>3,4   This paper is one in a series that utilizes data from interviews 
with former clients of the Camden Coalition of Healthcare 
Providers (The Coalition) to gain a more comprehensive 
understanding of these frequent health care users and targeted </p>

<p>care management programs. Using qualitative methods, this 
study draws on 30 patient interviews to identify and de-
fine the characteristics and roles of authentic relationships in 
care management, an emergent concept currently missing in 
the literature. 
Population-level studies have shown that patients with 
multiple chronic illnesses and social vulnerabilities report 
and are documented to have much more frequent hospital 
use when compared with the general population. 
5,6 Because 
the US health care system is designed primarily to treat 
acute medical illnesses, such patients must regularly navi-
gate a complicated and fragmented system of different pro-
viders and conflicting opinions. 
7 Common results include 
inappropriate, ineffective, or absent follow-up care, unnec-
essary duplication of tests, and inconsistent medication 
prescriptions with harmful drug interactions. </p>

<p>8,9   Care management programs have garnered wide attention 
and support as a potential solution to these problems. 
10 In 
theory, care management is ''a set of activities designed to </p>

<p>1 Sidney Kimmel Medical College, Thomas Jefferson University, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. 
2 Camden Coalition of Healthcare Providers, Camden, New Jersey. 
3 Department of Family and Community Medicine, Thomas Jefferson University, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. 
4 Urban Health Institute, Cooper Medical School of Rowan University, Camden, New Jersey. </p>

<p>ª The Author(s) 2015; Published by Mary Ann Liebert, Inc. This Open Access article is distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution Noncommercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits any noncommercial use, 
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited. </p>

<p>POPULATION HEALTH MANAGEMENT 
Volume 19, Number 4, 2016 
Mary Ann Liebert, Inc. 
DOI: 10.1089/pop.2015.0097 </p>



<p>assist patients and their support systems in managing med-
ical conditions and related psychosocial problems more ef-
fectively.''  11 In reality, there is great variability in the 
settings, durations, payers, philosophies, and protocols of 
care management programs. 
12 The level and type of support 
provided to patients by these programs ranges from tele-
phonic care management by a single provider, to in-person, 
home-based care management provided by integrated mul-
tidisciplinary teams. 
The Synthesis Project of the Robert Wood Johnson 
Foundation published a landmark report that summarized 
the current literature of the efficacy of care management 
programs. According to the data, care management pro-
grams targeting the hospital-to-home transition (a model 
used by The Coalition) have had the most success in quality 
improvement and cost reduction. 
11 The Foundation report 
identified in-person encounters, home visits, specially 
trained care managers with low caseloads, multidisciplinary 
teams, use of coaching, and presence of informal caregivers 
as key elements of successful care management programs. 
This paper, by going beyond a task-based framework, 
identifies an additional element of success that is missing 
from the current literature on care management: the nuanced 
emotional relationships between patients and providers that 
drive individual behavior. 
13 Studies in a variety of disci-
plines have examined and highlighted the importance of 
relationships in caregiving, particularly in the mental health 
field. 
14-17 However, this is the first study, to the investiga-
tors' knowledge, to identify and detail the attributes and role 
of what is termed ''authentic healing relationships'' in the 
management of care for patients with frequent hospitaliza-
tions. Although a handful of studies have demonstrated that 
''continuous healing relationships,'' or physician-patient 
continuity, 
18 is associated with improved quality of care and 
decreased likelihood of future hospitalizations, 
19-21 these 
studies focus on the element of continuity. The present 
analysis of ''authentic healing relationships'' encompasses 
not only continuity, but also the nontemporal components of 
security and genuineness. </p>

<p>22   The first section of this paper describes the qualitative 
study methods. The second section illustrates the com-
plexity of the sample population, to contextualize the re-
sults. The third section identifies the characteristics and 
role of authentic healing relationships by drawing on 
interviewee descriptions of their care management. The 
fourth section explores the advantages and limitations of 
family and friend networks in fostering authentic healing 
relationships. Finally, the paper concludes with a discus-
sion of the findings and policy recommendations to bolster 
authentic healing relationships in the formal health care 
system and beyond. </p>

<p>Setting </p>

<p>The Coalition care management initiative is designed to 
reduce readmissions for patients with multiple chronic 
conditions and vulnerabilities. The Coalition has developed 
a citywide Health Information Exchange (HIE) to share data 
among 4 health systems including all 3 hospitals in Camden, 
New Jersey. Real-time data feeds in the HIE allow outreach 
staff to identify hospitalized patients who are candidates for 
the intervention. Patients with 2 or more hospital admissions </p>

<p>in the last 6 months are considered eligible for the care 
management initiative if they meet at least 3 of the fol-
lowing criteria: 2 or more chronic conditions, 5 or more 
outpatient medications, difficulty accessing services, lack of 
social support, mental health comorbidity, active drug use, 
or homelessness. Once eligibility is established, patients are 
enrolled in the The Coalition care intervention if they meet 
the following additional inclusion criteria: currently insured, 
between the ages of 18-81, still admitted to the hospital at 
time of triage, and willing and able to consent. 
The care management initiative uses a multidisciplin-
ary team who work together to support and coordinate 
care for enrolled individuals for an estimated 90-120-
day period following hospital discharge. The multidis-
ciplinary team consists of bachelor's-level registered nurses, 
licensed practical nurses, community health workers, so-
cial workers, and AmeriCorps volunteer health coaches. 
An array of interventions customized to the patient's 
needs are employed including: routine visits in the home, 
medication reconciliation, primary care and specialty ap-
pointment accompaniment, facilitation of transportation to 
medical appointments, and assistance in applying for enti-
tlements and benefits. </p>

<p>23   The multidisciplinary team members utilize an approach 
that is community based and patient centered. The care 
management teams, who provide care in the homes of 
patients, utilize an acceptance framework to customize the 
intervention and decision-making process. Team members 
are trained in harm reduction, motivational interviewing, 
and trauma-informed care. 
24 The Coalition care delivery is 
informed by the understanding that past experiences, par-
ticularly those related to trauma, have lasting effects on 
patient well-being, including their day-to-day functioning 
and physical, social, and emotional health. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Design </p>

<p>This study builds on prior qualitative work with former 
clients of the Coalition. In that first study, the research team 
interviewed 19 former clients of the Coalition and illustrated 
the psychosocial complexity of patients with frequent hos-
pitalizations, including early-life trauma, unstable or violent 
relationships, and familial estrangement. The study high-
lighted how these psychological factors influenced self-care, 
access to care, and interactions between patients and their 
care providers. </p>

<p>25   This paper presents an analysis of more recent inter-
views with 30 former clients of the Coalition. The research 
team created a semi-structured interview guide based on 
the results of the first study 
25 and input from staff mem-
bers at the Coalition. Topics included employment and 
living situation, behavioral health risks, usual sources 
of care, adult protective factors, adverse childhood expe-
riences, ability to recover from stress, perceived self-
efficacy, and experiences with the Coalition. For questions 
requiring an affirmative, negative, or numerical response, 
prompts and probes extended the narratives. A small 
number of these prompts were revised after several initial 
interviews to address confusion. The data presented in 
this paper represent a subset of themes from the interview 
data set. </p>

<p>ROLE OF AUTHENTIC RELATIONSHIPS IN CARING FOR PATIENTS </p>

<p>
Study cohort </p>

<p>Thirty face-to-face in-depth interviews were completed. 
Non-English speaking clients were excluded from the study. 
Interviewees had been enrolled in the Coalition based on the 
aforementioned utilization and eligibility criteria. From June 
2013 to September 2014, numerous calls were placed to 
contact eligible individuals who had worked with a Coali-
tion care team between October 2012 and September 2014. 
Of the original potential participants who were called 
(n = 133), 30 were interviewed in their homes (Fig. 1). The 
demographics and medicosocial characteristics (Table 1) of 
the study sample population are statistically consistent with 
the attempted contact group and overall English-speaking 
Coalition client population (with the exception of the Coa-
lition outcome status). 
With consent, the interviews were conducted and audio 
recorded in English by investigators trained in qualitative 
interviewing techniques. The interviews lasted between 30 
and 60 minutes. The Institutional Review Boards of Thomas 
Jefferson University and the Cooper Health System of 
Cooper University Hospital approved the study protocol. </p>

<p>Analysis </p>

<p>Recordings were transcribed, de-identified, checked for 
accuracy, and analyzed using a general inductive approach 
to identify themes. The purpose of using an inductive ap-
proach is to derive themes organically from raw data, rather 
than using a priori hypotheses to predict outcomes. 
26 As 
transcripts became available, 2 investigators (CG and MH) 
conducted detailed readings of the transcripts to identify 
emergent themes. The analysis team discussed and refined 
these themes as a group. Thematic saturation occurred after 
reviewing and discussing 20 interviews. The themes iden-
tified were used to generate and define inductive codes. The 
transcripts were then imported into the qualitative analysis 
software <rs id="software-0" type="software">NVivo</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">10</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">QSR International Pty Ltd</rs>, Doncaster, 
Victoria, Australia), after which the 2 investigators inde-
pendently coded the transcripts, with meetings to resolve 
discrepancies and reach consensus on preliminary and final 
codes. The researchers then identified the overarching 
theme of characteristics and role of relationships in care 
management. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Medicosocial complexity of individuals 
with multiple chronic conditions and vulnerabilities </p>

<p>This study population is medically complex and their 
health care needs are significant; the participants presented 
with multiple chronic conditions, took several medications 
to manage these conditions, experienced repeated hospital 
stays and emergency department visits, and in general de-
scribed poor health. 
All interviewees reported more than 5 medications, more 
than 75% reported 5 or more chronic conditions, and more 
than 80% reported their health as poor/fair. More than two 
thirds of the interviewees reported mild or severe pain that 
limits daily activities and mobility (Table 1). A preponder-
ance of participants described pain frequency as constant 
(from the time I wake up to the time I go to sleep) and pain 
intensity as sharp, excruciating, and unbearable. The same 
participants went on to describe how their pain limits es-
sential activities of daily living. As illustrated by one in-
terviewee: It has made my life, where I have no life. I don't 
visit people because the pain is too bad . I . even when I 
try to do the crossing guard, that's extremely painful, but I 
don't have a choice because the rent is so high. </p>

<p>Characteristics and role of the authentic 
healing relationship </p>

<p>While describing their experiences with the Coalition 
care management intervention, the theme of a unique au-
thentic healing relationship emerged, which was not found 
elsewhere in interviewee descriptions of the formal health 
system. Although participants mentioned a number of task-
based services provided by the Coalition care teams, par-
ticipants spent the majority of time and emphasis recalling 
and describing the relationships formed with their care team 
members. This relationship often was linked with motiva-
tion to engage in and sustain active health management. 
From these reflections, security, genuineness, and continuity 
emerged as crucial ingredients in what the investigators 
have identified as an authentic healing relationship. 
Interviewees characterized relationships with their Coa-
lition care teams as ones in which the staff member was both 
secure (accepting, present, reliable, attentive) and genuine 
(nurturing, honest, respectful, and interested in the indi-
vidual). Participants often drew a connection between this 
relationship and active motivation. One interviewee said: 
Havin' people [the Coalition] around, it was nice, um . 
goin' to the doctors, I really didn't care too much but I went 
anyway. Just to have them [the Coalition] come around and 
sit and talk . is what I enjoyed. The fact that team members 
reliably visited clients in their homes created a sense of 
security and, as one participant stated succinctly, motivation 
to do better. 
Patients also described genuineness as a key ingredient of 
their relationship with the members of their Coalition care 
teams: I loved working with her. I'll work with her any day 
of the week, she was normal to me; she talked to me as a 
person, not as a patient. This genuineness in patient inter-
actions was often cited as a catalyst for personal change: 
[knowing that the care team was] interested in me . it's like 
wow, me? I felt good, I felt better, I felt somebody really </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Interview enrollment. </p>

<p>250 
GRINBERG ET AL. </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographics, Chronic Conditions, Vulnerabilities Reported at the Coalition Enrollment </p>

<p>Interview 
Group </p>

<p>Attempted Contact, 
Excluding Interviewed* 
P </p>

<p>Enrolled in the Coalition, 
Excluding Interviewed* 
P 
N = 30 
N = 103 
N = 186 </p>

<p>Age (yrs), mean 
57.2 -13.6 
55.2 -13.9 
.487 
54.4 -13.1 
.281 
Sex, n (%) 
.413 
.332 
Female 
13 (43) 
54 (52) 
99 (53) 
Male 
17 (57) 
49 (48) 
87 (47) 
Race, n (%) 
.740 
.927 
Black/African American 
21 (70) 
73 (71) 
124 (67) 
Hispanic/Latino 
2 (7) 
9 (9) 
19 (10) 
Multiracial 
3 (10) 
5 (5) 
14 (7) 
White 
4 (13) 
16 (15) 
29 (16) 
Missing 
0 
0 
0 
Education, n (%) 
.159 
.078 
Grades 1 through 11 
11 (37) 
55 (56) 
103 (59) 
High school graduate or GED 
11 (37) 
23 (23) 
42 (24) 
College 1 year to 3 years 
5 (17) 
16 (16) 
24 (14) 
College graduate 
3 (10) 
4 (4) 
7 (4) 
Missing 
0 
5 
10 
Marital Status, n (%) 
.187 
.061 
Divorced/Separated 
10 (34) 
27 (27) 
44 (24) 
Married/Domestic Partnership 
6 (21) 
11 (11) 
23 (13) 
Single/Never Married 
9 (31) 
52 (51) 
103 (56) 
Widowed 
4 (14) 
11 (11) 
14 (8) 
Missing 
1 
2 
2 
Camden Coalition Outcome, n (%) 
.005 
.000 
Graduated 
29 (97) 
76 (74) 
118 (63) 
Incomplete 
1 (3) 
27 (26) 
68 (37) </p>

<p>Number of Chronic Conditions, n (%) 
.199 
.163 
0-1 
0 (0) 
1 (1) 
1 (1) 
2-4 
6 (21) 
38 (37) 
70 (38) 
5-9 
22 (76) 
62 (61) 
109 (60) 
10-15 
1 (3) 
1 (1) 
2 (1) 
 ‡16 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Missing 
1 
1 
4 
Baseline ED visits in prior 
6 months, n (%) </p>

<p>.076 
.094 </p>

<p>0-2 
27 (90) 
68 (66) 
126 (68) 
3-5 
3 (10) 
24 (23) 
35 (19) 
6-8 
0 (0) 
3 (3) 
8 (4) 
 ‡9 
0 (0) 
8 (8) 
17 (9) 
Baseline hospital stays in prior 
6 months, n (%) </p>

<p>.546 
.721 </p>

<p>0-1 
1 (3) 
1 (1) 
4 (2) 
2-3 
26 (87) 
83 (81) 
151 (81) 
4-7 
3 (10) 
17 (17) 
28 (15) 
 ‡8 
0 (0) 
2 (2) 
3 (2) 
Reported 5+ Medications, n (%) 
.347 
.136 
Yes 
29 (100) 
95 (93) 
166 (91) 
No 
0 (0) 
7 (7) 
16 (9) 
Missing 
1 
1 
4 
Reported Pain, n (%) 
.254 
.451 
No Pain 
10 (36) 
30 (36) 
46 (32) 
Mild or Moderate 
12 (43) 
24 (29) 
49 (34) 
Severe 
6 (21) 
30 (36) 
48 (34) 
Missing 
2 
19 
43 
General Health Rating, n (%) 
.274 
.378 
Poor/Fair 
26 (87) 
94 (91) 
168 (90) 
Good 
3 (10) 
9 (9) 
16 (9) 
Very Good/Excellent 
1 (3) 
0 (0) 
2 (1) 
Missing 
0 
0 
1 </p>

<p>(continued) </p>

<p>ROLE OF AUTHENTIC RELATIONSHIPS IN CARING FOR PATIENTS </p>

<p>
cares about me . I'm livin', and I'm not here by myself. 
And I think that what's made me, you know, actually do 
it . I started takin' my medication, I started, you know, 
getting out. 
The secure and genuine relationships mentioned were 
exclusive to the Coalition care team members; they were not 
found elsewhere in participant descriptions of the formal 
health system. When interviewees spoke about their rela-
tionships with primary care offices or hospitals, the concepts 
of presence, reliability, motivation, and interest in the in-
dividual were absent. The remaining elements-attentive, 
accepting, honest, caring, respectful-occasionally emerged, 
but not as frequently as in discussions of the Coalition in-
terventions. The contrast is summarized in Table 2. 
Lack of continuity of care may help explain the dearth of 
authentic healing relationships in primary care offices and 
hospitals. Each patient narrative showed at least some dis-
continuity. In the patient view, services are only temporarily 
offered before being discontinued, and follow-up care is not 
offered. Many interviewees could not provide the names and 
roles of their outpatient and inpatient providers, demon-
strating a lack of understanding of their care provider net-
works. Some interviewees described being rotated among </p>

<p>practitioners or locations too often to establish a meaningful 
relationship; others noted their providers were seen too in-
frequently or temporarily to develop rapport, and still other 
interviewees mentioned the great number of providers they 
were required to visit each month. Discontinuity has sig-
nificant consequences. Interviewees often mentioned un-
fulfilled promises made by providers in the formal health 
care system. In describing how the Coalition care team stuck 
to their word, one participant highlighted that in contrast 
with other providers: A lot of people say they going to do 
this and going to do that and they sell you a dream that is 
not true . someone come to me and social work says, ''I am 
going to get you a wheelchair, a bathtub chair,'' and you be 
like, where is it? And it never come. 
Insurance plans appear to contribute to discontinuity by 
covering home-based services for only a limited time. After 
recounting several terrible experiences with her office-based 
primary care provider, one interviewee described her recent 
switch to a very caring home-based practitioner. The par-
ticipant first noted how the new practitioner doesn't stay 
long . he only stays like 15 minutes. He [is] only allowed 
that. Then the participant noted a great deal of uncertainty 
around continuity: I had to go through them [new insurance </p>

<p>Table 1. (Continued) </p>

<p>Interview 
Group </p>

<p>Attempted Contact, 
Excluding Interviewed* 
P </p>

<p>Enrolled in the Coalition, 
Excluding Interviewed* 
P 
N = 30 
N = 103 
N = 186 </p>

<p>Social Support Available, n (%) 
.428 
.299 
Always/Often 
19 (63) 
53 (51) 
96 (52) 
Sometimes 
6 (20) 
21 (20) 
34 (18) 
Rarely/Never 
5 (17) 
29 (28) 
56 (30) 
Missing 
0 
0 
0 
Living Situation, n (%) 
.587 
.138 
Homeless 
0 
5 (5) 
17 (9) 
Not Homeless 
30 (100) 
98 (95) 
169 (91) 
Missing 
0 
0 
1 </p>

<p>*English-speaking Coalition clients with an outcome date on or before August 26, 2014. 
The Coalition, Camden Coalition of Healthcare Providers; ED, emergency department; GED, general equivalency diploma. </p>

<p>Table 2. Relationship Descriptions of Care Providers in the Formal Health Care System </p>

<p>The Coalition 
Primary Care Office 
Hospital </p>

<p>Just to have them come around and 
sit and talk . is what I enjoyed. 
She kept calling me, it got a little 
annoying sometimes. 
They stuck to their word. 
They took the time to listen, they 
took the time to explain. 
They showed me how to bring 
myself back. 
They showed me that they care. 
They was always honest with me, 
they never sugar coated anything. 
Very polite . told who they were, 
explained what they do. 
She talked to me as a person, not 
a patient. </p>

<p>He knows my health condition, 
that's about it, but personally, no. 
He is a pretty nice guy. He makes 
you feel comfortable and he asks 
you questions. 
I ask the questions and he gives me 
an answer . That's what I do. 
Being that I don't see him that much 
I don't have a relationship. 
We ain't bonded. 
The nurse at the clinic . She knows 
me pretty well. 
They give you medicine when they 
want to. When you need medicine 
they don't give it to you. </p>

<p>Nobody was explaining anything. 
[The care at the hospital is] perfect, 
beautiful, they treat me nice. 
They wanted to cut my leg off. 
Never talk to my husband. They 
don't talk to me; they don't talk 
to my doc. 
I got mistreated by the whole 
facility and hospital. 
I went in the hospital for one thing, 
come out another thing. </p>

<p>The Coalition, Camden Coalition of Healthcare Providers. </p>

<p>252 
GRINBERG ET AL. </p>

<p>provider] to get approved that I can get the house doctor 
and I am very well prepared just to keep this doctor. I don't 
know how long they allow me . So it is not a thing that I 
can get for permanent. 
Interviewees placed a great value on continuity of care. 
Many described reliable follow-up care as the best aspect of 
working with the Coalition care team: When they'd promise 
me they'd be there . they were and that meant a lot to me. 
Other interviewees expressed sadness when graduating from 
their Coalition care team. Numerous participants requested 
that the Coalition care team come back, or to have follow-up 
after a year, or a step-down aspect to the program. A couple 
of interviewees even spoke of checking into a hospital in 
order to be assigned back to the Coalition, although the 
program is only available to patients once. Consistent with 
other studies, 
18-21 continuity appeared to be an essential 
element of the authentic healing relationship. 
It is important to note that the Coalition care teams were 
not always successful in reducing discontinuity of care, and 
in a number of cases, further contributed to the fragmenta-
tion of health care delivery. One interviewee described a 
negative care experience when an unfamiliar staff member 
performed the same tasks as a familiar staff member: [A 
Coalition staff member] showing up at my doctor's office, 
not even informing me that you're gonna be there and ev-
erything else . you're invading my privacy. I don't like 
that . I didn't even know who [they] were.'' In re-
commending changes to the Coalition care program, one 
interviewee stated: Maybe longer participation with the 
client because once they left, the problem wasn't solved. 
They started but they didn't have enough time to solve it. 
Finally, clients' efforts to sustain the impact of the Coali-
tion's care management intervention and maintain active 
health management may depend on continuity. As one in-
terviewee described: I used to look for them to give me my 
energy I need to keep things going properly. When they fell 
off I kinda fell off. When they were there I was more ener-
getic maybe or persistent on doing what I was doing. 
In summary, the Coalition care teams were often suc-
cessful in establishing authentic healing relationships with 
their patients. The interviewees were clear that such rela-
tionships were rarely found in hospitals and primary care 
offices. This relationship is linked to positive participant 
motivation to sustain active management of health condi-
tions. The 3 core elements of this relationship were identi-
fied as security, genuineness, and continuity. When 1 or 
more of these core elements was missing, authentic healing 
relationships and their associated positive impacts were 
jeopardized. </p>

<p>Authentic healing relationships and family 
and friend networks </p>

<p>It emerged from the interviews that friend and family 
networks contain some key elements of the authentic heal-
ing relationship; namely, the concepts of presence, reli-
ability, and attention. Although the interviewees suffer from 
multiple chronic conditions and have complex health needs, 
when asked, ''Who cares for you?'' more than half answered 
family. The majority of unpaid help provided by family 
members (ie, with eating, bathing, dressing, getting around 
the house [activities of daily living], and shopping, house-
hold chores, and driving [instrumental activities of daily 
living]) are services not generally offered by the formal 
health care system (excluding home health aides). Other 
assistance described included making appointments and 
providing transportation to appointments. In the words of 
one participant who described the breadth of care received 
from family members: My son helps me around the house 
and sometimes he helps me financially. My daughter is al-
ways making sure that I am okay health-wise. If I've got to 
get a doctor or something and I can't get there, she helps me 
get there. 
Although the element of security may exist in friend and 
family networks, at times other elements of genuineness and 
continuity may not always be found. Access to friend and 
family networks and personalities of both patients and their 
personal networks were identified as potential barriers to 
achieving genuineness and continuity (Table 3). 
With respect to access, a number of interviewees de-
scribed having no available support network or networks 
with competing priorities. As described by an interviewee: 
Oh myself. Everybody left me. The sister-caregiver of an-
other spoke of balancing raising her teenage daughter alone 
after losing my mother and a marriage in the same year, 
while providing care for her brother. A number of inter-
viewees described not being able to take care of themselves, 
because of their responsibility to take care of other family 
members. 
Finally, a number of interviewees explained their refusal 
to use informal care networks because of a desire or ne-
cessity for independence. Some participants noted how their 
desire to be independent, or their perception of indepen-
dence, allowed for self-reliance. A handful of interviewees 
also noted how they had to be self-sufficient because they do 
not want to burden or bother family members and friends 
(including former Coalition care team members). 
Friends and family members can play an important role in 
meeting the daily health care needs of patients with multiple </p>

<p>Table 3. Relationship Barriers of Friend and Family Care Networks 
Access 
My momma is in the nursing home right now. And she don't even love me and I take care of her . who pays 
for her insurance policies? I do. You know. They [two sisters] don't come to visit me. They know that I am 
sick. 
I don't have nobody to talk to. You know even when I try to talk to my daughter or my son, she don't even 
come around like that. And my son, he says, 'Oh mom, I don't want to hear that.' 
Personality My kids try, but they have children of their own, and they have to pay their bills, and they have to take care of 
their children. So I don't, you know, try to bother them. 
I can't even walk a whole half a block . I usually go to the stores that have the wheel carts. Because I am 
independent. I'd rather do it myself than to have people do it for me. Even though it's hard. It's nobody's 
fault, you can't blame nobody, I'm grown, they're all my problems, nobody else's. </p>

<p>ROLE OF AUTHENTIC RELATIONSHIPS IN CARING FOR PATIENTS </p>

<p>
chronic conditions and vulnerabilities. Family and Friend 
networks by their nature can be secure at times, (one key 
aspect of the authentic healing relationship), but many lack 
the key elements of genuineness and continuity, thus leaving 
significant gaps in access to medical and social services. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The authentic healing relationships established between 
the Coalition care teams and their patients present signifi-
cant implications for addressing the persistent health-related 
needs of patients with frequent inpatient hospitalizations. 
Authentic healing relationships were positively linked to 
patient motivation to take an active role in their personal 
health management. The present analysis illustrates that 
security, genuineness, and continuity are essential ingredi-
ents for building desired authentic healing relationships 
between providers and their patients. Parry et al. have 
written similarly about the importance of patient rapport 
with health care providers, concluding ''competence 
alone may be insufficient to engage patients in the self-
management aspects'' of care management and primary care 
interventions. 
27 In fact, although this research focused on a 
specific population, research in more general populations 
has demonstrated that positive patient experiences are both 
important to patients and positively related to outcomes 
including psychological and functional status, medication 
compliance, and readmission rates. 
13,28 In patient satisfac-
tion research with broader populations, there are parallels 
between individual variables that predict positive patient 
experiences and elements of the authentic healing relation-
ship, including providers that are empathetic, listen, re-
spectful, and take the time to explain. 
13,29 However, this 
paper highlights the importance of a holistic incorporation 
of all elements of the authentic healing relationship for 
sustained impact. 
Participants consistently reported that security, genuine-
ness, and continuity were not always guaranteed by their 
care management team, and were not readily found in pri-
mary care offices and hospitals. The present analysis also 
showed that when 1 or more ingredients were missing, au-
thentic healing relationships, and their associated positive 
health impacts, were in jeopardy: interviewees lost their 
motivation to manage their own health actively. 
Three broad policy implications can be derived from the 
experiences of the study participants. First, there is a need to 
shift beyond the traditional biomedical paradigm to create 
authentic healing relationships in health care delivery. To 
scale this relationship throughout health care delivery, tools 
and techniques to identify, foster, assess, and sustain this 
relationship need to be thoughtfully developed so that it can 
be taught and replicated without jeopardizing the essence of 
the relationship. Training on creating authentic healing re-
lationships should be integrated into health care professional 
training curricula and accreditation. 
Second, care management programs, primary care of-
fices, and hospitals working to address the health-related 
needs of patients with frequent hospitalizations should draw 
on practices from the disciplines of behavioral health, psy-
chology, and public health, among others, to incorporate 
principles and techniques from attachment theory, motiva-
tional interviewing, trauma-informed care, and harm re-</p>

<p>duction. Interprofessional care teams drawing on these best 
practices may have the best chance to cause desired shifts in 
self-management of disease, health care utilization, and 
outcomes. 
Finally, care management programs should expand be-
yond a central focus on individual behavior change. 
11 Ex-
isting authentic healing relationships with family and friends 
and long-term care networks must be supported and built 
into care management. Because care management programs 
tend to be transient, training family and friends in care 
management (as well as expanding care management ser-
vices for people without social support systems) would al-
low for the continued benefits of authentic healing 
relationships. One mechanism to facilitate this is to design 
and expand services and support for family and friend 
caregivers, as well as direct-care workers (nurse aides, home 
health aides, and personal care aides). At this time, many 
''informal caregivers'' lack educational, emotional, and fi-
nancial support, which often translates into psychological 
and physical burnout. 
30 Although policy makers have called 
for and implemented caregiver support programs for elderly 
persons and disabled children (The National Family Care-
giver Support Act), 
31,32 the present analysis demonstrates 
that many other individuals who fall between these 2 age 
groups also require substantial care and assistance in their 
homes. Longitudinal support for home-based services is 
needed for patients at risk of frequent hospitalizations, re-
gardless of age. 
Limitations of this study include a sample with narrowly 
defined inclusion/exclusion criteria, as previous clients of 
the Coalition. Only English-speaking participants were eli-
gible. No homeless individuals were interviewed, though 
they were recruited. The sample is small, although thematic 
saturation occurred after 20 interviews. Finally, 25% of 
potential participants called were interviewed. The subset 
interviewed significantly underrepresents individuals who 
did not graduate from the intervention, likely because the 
difficulty recruiting those individuals for the study mirrored 
difficulty recruiting them for the intervention itself. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The investigators sought to better understand the complex 
needs and health-related experiences of individuals with 
multiple chronic illnesses and vulnerabilities by interview-
ing former clients of the Coalition in Camden, New Jersey. 
The data presented in this paper sheds new light on previous 
studies regarding the importance of a continuous healing 
relationship in decreasing hospitalizations and improving 
care and outcomes. Three core elements of authentic healing 
relationships were identified: security, genuineness, and 
continuity. Despite their power to improve health care de-
livery and motivate patient involvement in their own treat-
ment, authentic healing relationships are not readily found 
in the traditional health care system. Future research should 
seek to better understand how authentic healing relation-
ships can be taught, sustained, and supported. </p>

<p>Author Disclosure Statement </p>

<p>Drs. Mautner, Brenner, and LaNoue, and Ms. Grinberg 
and Ms. Hawthorne declared no conflicts of interest with </p>

<p>254 
GRINBERG ET AL. </p>

<p>respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this 
article. 
The authors received the following financial support for 
the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: 
Grant Number 1C1CMS330967 from Centers for Medicare 
and Medicaid Innovation (CMMI). The project described 
also was supported in part by Grant Number D55HP10334 
and Grant Number D56HP20783 from the Health Resources 
and Services Administration (HRSA) of the US Department 
of Health and Human Services (HHS). Its contents are solely 
the responsibility of the authors and do not necessarily 
represent the official views of CMMI or HRSA/HHS. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors wish to acknowledge the Camden Coalition 
of Healthcare Providers staff and the patients who shared 
their stories and insights to help improve the health of their 
communities. Finally, we wish to thank Howard Rabino-
witz, MD, and Randa Sifri, MD at the Thomas Jefferson 
Department of Family and Community Medicine and HRSA 
for the postdoctoral fellowship support of Dr. Mautner, 
during which a portion of this work was completed. </p>

<p>Prior Presentation </p>

<p>Parts of this work were presented at the North American 
Primary Care Research Group annual meeting in New York, 
New York, in November 2014. </p>



<p>ROLE OF AUTHENTIC RELATIONSHIPS IN CARING FOR PATIENTS 
255 </p>



<p>Address correspondence to: 
Ms. Charlotte Grinberg 
C/O Dawn Mautner 
Thomas Jefferson University, Family Medicine 
1015 Walnut Street Suite 401 
Philadelphia, PA, USA 19107 </p>

<p>E-mail: cngrinberg@gmail.com </p>

<p>256 
GRINBERG ET AL. </p>

</text></tei>