<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4013958" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:42+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Cell lines originating from horses are necessary for isolation and propagation of equine 
herpesviruses (EHV). Although we established an equine-derived cell line, FHK-Tcl3, 
propagation ceased after fewer than 40 passages. In this study, FHK-Tcl3 cell propagation 
continued beyond 40 passages, achieving over 100 passages. FHK-Tcl3 cells were then 
cloned by limiting dilution at the 100th passage. Cloned cells were termed FHK-Tcl3.1. 
FHK-Tcl3.1 cells grew well and were propagated every 3 to 4 days by splitting 1:5. In 
addition, EHV-1, -2 and -4 showed a clear cytopathic effect (CPE) in FHK-Tcl3.1 cells, and 
this CPE was very similar to those seen in parental FHK-Tcl3 and primary fetal horse kidney 
cells. FHK-Tcl3.1 cells continue to propagate and the current passage record is over 100 
times after cloning. Therefore, this cell appears to have been immortalized. FHK-Tcl3.1 
cells have potential for growth and diagnosis of various equine viruses, including equine 
herpesviruses. 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Motic Images plus</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Ver. 2.1</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Shimazu-rika</rs>We would like to thank Dr. Shigeru Yasumoto 
(Kanagawa Cancer Institute, Yokohama, Japan) for 
kindly providing plasmid pLNCLT. 
This study was supported by Grants-in-Aid from the 
Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and 
Technology of Japan and from the Innovation Center 
of Yamaguchi University. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Growth of cloned cells. Vertical error bars indicate 
standard deviation of means. </p>

<p> 
FURTHER DEVELOPMENT OF EQUINE CELL LINE </p>



<p>K. ANDOH, K, KAI, T. MATSUMURA ET AL. </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>