<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4240489" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Interest in finding alternatives and major innovation in surgical </p>

<p>technology has led to improvements in anesthesia and perioper-
ative care with documented benefits on early and late postoper-
ative outcomes. Since endoscopic surgical techniques have been 
developed, proper anesthetic management should be tailored 
for optimal visualization of the surgical field, controlling intra-
operative hemodynamic, homeostasis and hemostasis [1]. 
Premedication with clonidine reduce bleeding during endo-
scopic sinus surgery (ESS) and therefore lowers the risk of surgi-
cal complications mostly due to its known benefit related to re-
duction in nasal mucosa blood flow [2,3]. Also, in patients un-
dergoing non-cardiac surgery, clonidine used as a premedication </p>

<p>• Received August 26, 2013 
Revision November 12, 2013 
Accepted November 19, 2013 </p>

<p>• Corresponding author: Katarzyna Wawrzyniak 
Department of Anesthesiology and Intensive Therapy, Collegium Medium 
in Bydgoszcz, Nicolaus Copernicus University of Torun, Sklodowska-Curie 
9 Street, 85-094 Bydgoszcz, Poland 
Tel: +48-52-5854750, Fax: +48-52-5854022 
E-mail: kwawrzyniak@wp.pl </p>

<p>pISSN 1976-8710 eISSN 2005-0720 </p>

<p>Comparison of Clonidine and Midazolam 
Premedication Before Endoscopic Sinus Surgery: 
Results of Clinical Trial </p>

<p>Katarzyna Wawrzyniak 
1 • Krzysztof Kusza 
1,2 • Jacek B. Cywinski </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Anesthesiology and Intensive Therapy, Collegium Medicum in Bydgoszcz, Nicolaus Copernicus University of Torun, Torun; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Anesthesiology and Intensive Therapy, Poznan University of Medical Sciences, Poznan, Poland; </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of General Anesthesiology, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, OH, USA </p>

<p>Objectives. Premedication with clonidine has been found to reduce the bleeding during endoscopic sinus surgery (ESS), 
therefore lowering the risk of surgical complications. Premedication is an essential part of pre-surgical care and can 
potentially affect magnitude of systemic stress response to a surgical procedure. The aim of this study was to compare 
the efficacy of premedication with clonidine and midazolam in patients undergoing sinus surgery. </p>

<p>Methods. Forty-four patients undergoing ESS for chronic sinusitis and polyp removal were enrolled and randomly assigned 
to receive either oral clonidine or midazolam as a premedication before receiving propofol/remifentanil total intrave-
nous anesthesia. The effect of this premedication choice on anesthetic requirements, intraoperative hemodynamic 
profile, preoperative anxiety and sedation as well as postoperative pain and shivering were examined in each pre-
medication group. </p>

<p>Results. Total intraoperative remifentanil requirement was lower in the clonidine group as compared to the midazolam 
group 503.2±147.0 µg vs. 784.5±283.8 µg, respectively (P&lt;0.001). There was no difference between groups in re-
quired induction dose of propofol, level of preoperative anxiety, level of sedation and postoperative shivering. Intra-
operative systemic blood pressure and heart rate response had a more favorable profile in patients premedicated with 
clonidine. Postoperative pain assessed by visual analogue scale for pain was lower in the clonidine group compared 
with to the midazolam premedication group. </p>

<p>Conclusion. Premedication with clonidine provides better attenuation of hemodynamic response and reduction of intraop-
erative remifentanil requirements in patients undergoing ESS. Postoperative pain seems to be better controlled after 
clonidine premedication as well. </p>

<p>Keywords. Anesthesia, Surgical procedures, Minimally invasive, Clonidine, Premedication </p>



<p>agent was reported to reduce the risk of cardiac mortality [4]  and to have an anesthetic sparing effect [5-7]. 
The present study was design to test the hypothesis that pre-
medication with clonidine can provide clinically relevant bene-
fits. We therefore compared the effect of clonidine and conven-
tional premedication with midazolam on intraoperative anes-
thetic requirements, hemodynamic profile, level of preoperative 
anxiety and sedation as well as postoperative pain and shivering 
in patients undergoing ESS. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>After obtaining approval from the local Institutional Review 
Board (Bioethics Committee of the Nicolaus Copernicus Univer-
sity) and informed consent from each participant, 44 patients 
with an American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical 
status I or II were included in this trial. All patients had the same 
indications for ESS and comparable advancement of polyps in 
the nasal cavities as assessed by preoperative computed tomogra-
phy (CT) of the paranasal sinuses (graded on Lund-Mackay scale) 
[8]. 
Exclusion criteria included significant heart disease, epilepsy, 
perceptive hearing loss, body weight less than 50 kg and over 
100 kg, pregnancy, and preoperative anxiety score (visual ana-
logue scale for anxiety, VAS-A) above 5. Also, patients receiving 
clonidine or benzodiazepines, neuroleptics or antidepressants 
two weeks prior to the study were excluded. 
Patients were randomized (simple random sampling) to receive 
oral premedication consisting of clonidine (Iporel, WZF Polfa, 
Warsaw, Poland) at a dose of approximately 3 µg/kg body weight 
or midazolam at a dose of approximately 0.1 mg/kg body weight 
(Dormicum, Roche, Bache, Switzerland) 60 minutes before in-
duction of general anesthesia. 
Prior to administration of premedication anxiety level was 
evaluated using VAS-A 1. After transfer to the operating room 
but before induction of general anesthesia anxiety and sedation 
were assessed using VAS-A 2 and Ramsay sedation score (RSS), 
respectively. 
Standard ASA noninvasive monitoring [9] was supplemented 
with A-line autoregressive index (AAI) in all patients (AEP/2 
monitor; Danmeter, Odense C, Denmark); with numerical value 
between 0 and 60 (0 indicating very deep hypnosis and 60 indi-
cating awake state). All patients received the same induction con-
sisting of propofol (Plofed 1%; Polfa Warszawa S.A., Warsaw, Po-
land) delivered in divided doses of 20 mg every 20 seconds, sup-
plemented with fentanyl 2 µg/kg (Fentanyl, WZF Polfa) titrated 
to achieve AAI index of 15-25 and clinical signs of unconscious-
ness as assessed by observer's assessment of alertness/sedation 
scale (OASS). After loss of consciousness, muscle relaxant, ve-
curonium (Norcuron, Organon, Holland) at a dose of 0.1 mg/kg 
was administered to facilitate endotracheal intubation. General </p>

<p>anesthesia was maintained with infusion of propofol/remifentanil 
total intravenous anesthesia (TIVA). Mechanical ventilation was 
provided with a mixture of oxygen and air to maintain FiO2 0.4-
0.5 and end-tidal carbon dioxide concentration at 35-38 mmHg. 
TIVA was maintained with continuous infusion of remifentanil 
to obtain predicted serum concentration in the range of 1.5-6.0 
ng/mL (Minto model), titrated to the hemodynamic parameters 
(heart rate [HR] between 60-90 bpm and mean blood pressure 
between 60-95 mmHg), if the incremental increase of remifent-
anil infusion rate was not sufficient to decrease mean arterial 
pressure (MAP) below 95 mmHg, bolus dose (10 mg) of urapi-
dil (Ebrantil, Byk Gulden Lomberg, Konstanz, Germany) was 
administered intravenously. 
Propofol infusion was targeted to obtain a predicted serum 
concentration of 3.0 μg/mL (Schneider model). The infusion of 
propofol and remifentanil were stopped at the conclusion of the 
surgical procedure followed by intravenous administration of ac-
etaminophen (Perfalgan, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Uxbridge, UK) 
at a dose of 1 g. Both groups received the same amount of intra-
venous fluids: 0.9% NaCl solution at a rate of 5 mL/kg/hour. 
The propofol dose used during induction of anesthesia, the ap-
plication rates and cumulative dose of remifentanil used during 
the entire case were recorded. Hemodynamic parameters includ-
ing systolic blood pressure (SAP), diastolic blood pressure (DAP), 
mean arterial pressure (MAP), and HR were recorded upon ad-
mission to the operating room (SAP1, DAP1, MAP1, HR1), after 
induction of anesthesia (SAP2, DAP2, MAP2, HR2) during en-
dotracheal intubation (SAP3, DAP3, MAP3, HR3) and extuba-
tion (SAP4, DAP4, MAP4, HR4). In the recovery room, pain and 
shivering were assessed using the visual analogue scale for pain 
(VAS-P) and the 5-point scale of Wrench respectively [10]. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Mann-Whitney U-test, Student t-test, χ 2 -test, the Fisher exact 
test were used as appropriate to compare premedication groups 
with respect to baseline characteristic and outcomes of interest; 
significance level was set at 0.05, <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistica</rs> ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">8.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StatSoft</rs>, 
Tulsa, OK, USA) was used to perform the analysis. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics of patients in clonidine and midazolam 
premedication groups were similar (Table 1). </p>

<p>Medication requirements </p>

<p>The total induction dose of propofol, was similar in both groups 
(124.3±20.8 mg vs. 131.3±25.7 mg; P=0.32) (Table 2). Howev-
er, the total remifentanil requirement during the entire procedure 
was lower in the clonidine group (503.2±147.0 µg vs. 784.5± 
283.8 µg; P&lt;0.001) as well as application rates (0.08±0.02 µg/ 
kg/minute vs. 0.11±0.02 µg/kg/minute; P&lt;0.001) (Table 2). </p>

<p>Wawrzyniak K et al. Clonidine and Midazolam Premedication Before ESS 309 </p>

<p>Hemodynamic profile </p>

<p>SAP was lower in the clonidine group after induction of anes-
thesia, during endotracheal intubation and extubation (P=0.02, 
P&lt;0.001, P=0.01), as compared to the midazolam group (Fig. </p>

<p>1A). Mean blood pressure was lower in clonidine group during 
endotracheal intubation and extubation (P&lt;0.001, P=0.009, re-
spectively) (Fig. 1B). DAP was lower in clonidine premedication 
group during endotracheal intubation and extubation as com-
pared with patients in the midazolam premedication group 
(P=0.001, P=0.021, respectively) (Fig. 1C). HR in the clonidine 
group was lower after induction of anesthesia, during endotra-
cheal intubation and extubation as compared with patients after 
midazolam premedication (P =0.002, P&lt;0.001, P&lt;0.001, re-
spectively) (Fig. 1D). </p>

<p>Sedation, anxiety and pain </p>

<p>There was no difference between the groups in the level of seda-</p>

<p>Table 1. Comparison of perioperative characteristic between cloni-
dine and midazolam premedication groups </p>

<p>Variable 
Clonidine (n=22) Midazolam (n=22) P-value </p>

<p>Age (year) 
48.72±5.85 
48.5±9.37 
0.92* 
Height (cm) 
170.36±7.63 
169.81±9.42 
0.83* 
Body mass (kg) 
73.09±13.28 
68.63±12.77 
0.26* 
BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
25.00±0.34 
23.60±0.25 
0.11* 
Sex (female:male) 
11:11 
13:9 
0.55 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>ASA I:II 
7:15 
5:17 
0.50 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±SD. 
BMI, body mass index; ASA, American Society of Anesthesiologists. 
*Student t-test. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-test. </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of premedication choice (clonidine vs. mid-
azolam) on anesthetic requirement and postoperative shivering </p>

<p>Variable 
Clonidine (n=22) Midazolam (n=22) P-value </p>

<p>Remifentanil (µg) 
503.2±147.0 
784.5±283.8 
&lt;0.001* 
Remifentanil (µg/kg/min) 
0.08±0.02 
0.11±0.02 
&lt;0.001* 
Propofol (mg) 
124.31±20.83 
131.36±25.68 
0.32 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Shivering 
0 
3 (13.64) 
0.23 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±SD or number (%). 
*Mann-Whitney U-test. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Student t-test. </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Fisher exact test. </p>

<p>SAP1 
SAP2 
SAP3 
SAP4 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>mmHg </p>

<p>Clonidine 
Midazolam </p>

<p>A 
MAP1 
MAP2 
MAP3 
MAP4 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>mmHg </p>

<p>Clonidine 
Midazolam </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>DAP1 
DAP2 
DAP3 
DAP4 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>mmHg </p>

<p>Clonidine 
Midazolam </p>

<p>C 
HR1 
HR2 
HR3 
HR4 </p>

<p>90 
80 
70 
60 
50 
40 
30 
20 
10 
0 
Heart rate (beats min-I) </p>

<p>Clonidine 
Midazolam </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Comparison of premedication choice (clonidine vs. midazolam) on hemodynamic parameters during procedure. Heart rate (HR), systol-
ic blood pressure (SAP), diastolic blood pressure (DAP), mean arterial pressure (MAP) in admission to the operating room (SAP1, DAP1, 
MAP1, HR1), after induction of anesthesia (SAP2, DAP2, MAP2, HR2) during endotracheal intubation (SAP3, DAP3, MAP3, HR3) and extuba-
tion (SAP4, DAP4, MAP4, HR4). </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparison of premedication choice (clonidine vs. mid-
azolam) </p>

<p>Variable 
Clonidine n=22 
Midazolam n=22 
P-value </p>

<p>RSS 
2 (2-2) 
2 (1-3) 
0.16* 
VAS-A 1 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>3 (2-4) 
3 (2-3) 
0.64* 
VAS-A 2 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>3 (2-4) 
3 (2-4) 
0.31* 
VAS-P 
2 (2-3) 
3 (1-4) 
0.05* </p>

<p>Values are presented as median (min-max). 
RSS, Ramsay sedation score; VAS-A, visual analogue scale for anxiety; 
VAS-P, visual analogue scale for pain. 
*Mann-Whitney U-test. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Anxiety level prior to administration of premedica-
tion. </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Anxiety level after transfer to the operating room but before induction 
of general anesthesia. </p>



<p>tion and anxiety scores (Table 3) as well as incidence of postop-
erative shivering (P=0.16, P=0.64, P=0.31, P=0.23, respective-
ly) (Table 2). Postoperative pain scores measured using the VAS-
P scale were lower in clonidine group (P=0.05) (Table 3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our investigation demonstrated that premedication with cloni-
dine, as compared to standard midazolam premedication, can 
provide clinically relevant benefits: reduction of intraoperative 
requirement for remifentanil, better postoperative pain control 
and smoother intraoperative hemodynamic profile. 
Alpha-2 agonists have been shown to have beneficial analge-
sic, sedative [6,11,12] and opioid sparing effects [13]. In animal 
studies clonidine and dexmedetomidine were reported to reduce 
the minimal alveolar concentration for halothane by nearly 50% 
and 90%, respectively [14,15]. The anesthetic and analgesic spar-
ing effects is most likely related to the direct action on alpha-2 
adrenergic receptors in the central nervous system [16,17] and is 
evident for volatile and intravenous anesthetics. Ghignone et al. 
[5] showed a 45% reduction in requirements for analgesics dur-
ing the intraoperative period after clonidine premedication com-
pared to standard premedication in patients undergoing bypass 
surgery. Flacke et al. [18] demonstrated reduced sufentanil re-
quirement by 40% while improving hemodynamic profile during 
coronary artery bypass graft as well. Interestingly Frank et al. 
[19], similarly to our investigation, demonstrated a reduction in 
cumulative remifentanil dose by 24% after clonidine premedica-
tion in patients undergoing maxillofacial surgery under TIVA. 
In contrast to other studies, we were unable to demonstrate 
reduction in propofol dose required for induction of general an-
esthesia [20,21]. That could be related to the differences in moni-
toring of unconsciousness amongst the studies: we used auditory 
evoked potential-guided propofol dosing while others used he-
modynamic parameters or processed electroencephalography to 
determine state of unconsciousness during induction [20-22]. 
Clonidine administration in perioperative settings is safe and 
serious complications are very rare. In clinically relevant doses, 
preoperative use of clonidine is not associated with a risk of re-
spiratory depression, which may be of particular importance in 
patients undergoing procedures on upper airways [6]. Also be-
cause clonidine stimulates not only the alpha 2 receptor but al-
pha 1 receptors as well, it does not inhibit the baroreceptor re-
flex, but only reduces its sensitivity, which prevents the signifi-
cant decrease in blood pressure [6]. This is of particular impor-
tance in same day surgery patients as postoperative hypotension 
may delay discharge. 
Our results confirmed the beneficial effect of clonidine on at-
tenuation of hemodynamic response associated with laryngos-
copy and endotracheal intubation [23]. As previously described, 
hypertension, tachycardia and in some cases cardiac arrhyth-</p>

<p>mias are driven by sudden increase of plasma adrenaline and 
noradrenaline concentration in response to the manipulation of 
the airways [24-26]. Interestingly 5 patients in the midazolam 
group (vs. none in clonidine group) required administration of 
an additional agent (urapidil) to treat intraoperative hyperten-
sion, this suggests that premedication with clonidine provides 
much better control of the hemodynamic response to the stress 
of surgery intraoperatively. 
Consistently with other studies we did not demonstrate any 
difference in degree of anxiolysis [19] or the level of sedation 
based on RSS [27] provided by premedication doses of clonidine 
and midazolam. 
Postoperative pain was lower in patients who received cloni-
dine premedication. This finding is in agreement with previous 
studies showing that patients undergoing abdominal hysterecto-
my treated with clonidine reported less pain in the postoperative 
period [28]. 
Postoperative shivering may complicate postoperative recovery 
after general anesthesia in as many as 5%-65% of patients [1]. 
Clonidine has been demonstrated to reduce the incidence of shiv-
ering significantly, however in our study we were not able to con-
firm that. This could be related to the fact that five patients in the 
midazolam premedication group received intraoperatively urapi-
dil (to control hypertension), which by itself reduces shivering. 
One of the limitations of this study is that we evaluated the 
effect of clonidine premedication in ASA I and II patients only, 
excluding patients with significant comorbidities. However pre-
sented results may be considered a pilot for the future investiga-
tion evaluating outcomes in patients with advanced coexisting 
diseases undergoing sinus surgery for whom, better hemody-
namic profile provided by clonidine premedication may be more 
important. Based on the results of this investigation premedica-
tion with clonidine may be an attractive alternative for standard 
midazolam premedication before ESS. 
In conclusion, premedication with clonidine provides better 
attenuation of hemodynamic responses and reduction of intra-
operative remifentanil requirements in patients undergoing ESS. 
Postoperative pain seems to be better controlled after clonidine 
premedication as well. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was re-
ported. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank the patients for taking part in 
this study. </p>

<p>Wawrzyniak K et al. Clonidine and Midazolam Premedication Before ESS 311 </p>



</text></tei>