<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4751907" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Province Key laboratory of 
radiation Oncology, shandong cancer 
hospital and institute, shandong 
University, Jinan, People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>*These authors contributed equally 
to this work </p>

<p>Purpose: Brain metastasis (BM) is associated with impaired quality of life and increased 
mortality. The study aimed to compare BM risk after erlotinib administration and chemotherapy 
in stage IIIB/IV pulmonary adenocarcinoma patients harboring epidermal growth factor recep-
tor (EGFR) mutation. 
Patients and methods: Eligible patients underwent match pair process with matching fac-
tors, including age, sex, performance status score, first-line or second-line treatment, first-line 
chemotherapy regimen (for the second-line treatment subgroup), stage IIIB or IV, and genotypes 
of EGFR mutation. BM and mortality risk of both groups were recorded and compared. 
Results: In total 129 matched pairs were included for analysis. During a median follow-up of 
21.5 months, time to BM risk was longer and incidences of BM within 2 years were lower in 
patients who received erlotinib than chemotherapy in total population, as well as subgroups of 
first-line treatment, second-line treatment, stage IIIB, stage IV, exon 19 deletion mutation, and 
exon 21 L858R mutation. Similar overall survival time and 2-year survival rates were seen in 
two groups totally or in any subgroup. Multivariate analysis showed that BM was retarded in 
patients who received erlotinib administration (hazard ratio, 1.695; P=0.001) and in patients 
who were in stage IIIB (hazard ratio, 1.751; P=0.001). 
Conclusion: Erlotinib administration decreases BM risk in advanced pulmonary adenocarci-
noma patients harboring sensitive EGFR mutations. 
Approximately half of the patients with non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC) suffer 
from brain metastasis (BM) during their clinical disease progression, which is associ-
ated with a significantly impaired quality of life and a fourfold increase in mortality. </p>

<p>1-3 </p>

<p>Advances in modern neuroimaging techniques and prolonged life span under improved 
systemic treatments also contribute to high incidences of BM, which makes preven-
tion and control of BM emerge as a vital therapeutic strategy for tumor control and 
life quality improvement. 
In the era of molecular targeted therapy, epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR)-
mutant lung cancer has been labeled as a specific subset of disease, demonstrating 
distinct clinical and biological features. Recent studies 
4,5 showed that patients with 
EGFR-mutant NSCLC were prone to develop BM than patients with wild EGFR. 
EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs), such as erlotinib, are associated with a high 
response rate of up to 80% to EGFR-mutant lung cancer. 
6 In addition, it may penetrate 
through the blood-brain barrier (BBB) more efficiently 
7-10 than large chemotherapeutic </p>

<p>correspondence: Jinming Yu; li Kong 
Department of radiation Oncology, 
shandong Province Key laboratory of 
radiation Oncology, shandong cancer 
hospital and institute, 440 Jiyan road, 
Jinan 250117, People's republic of china 
Tel +86 531 6762 6729; 
+86 531 6762 6111 
Fax +86 531 6762 6079; 
+86 531 6762 6111 
email sdyujinming@126.com; 
klsdcancer@163.com </p>

<p>Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
5 February 2016 </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>672 </p>

<p>liu et al </p>

<p>molecules. 
11,12 However, few studies have been conducted to 
examine the impact of upfront EGFR-targeted therapy versus 
conventional chemotherapy on BM risk in NSCLC patients 
with sensitive EGFR mutation. In prospective, randomized, 
and controlled trails, 
13,14 comparing erlotinib or gefitinib with 
chemotherapy for advanced EGFR-mutant NSCLC, the dif-
ferences in BM risk between two groups were not reported. A 
retrospective study 
15 exploring the effect of first-line EGFR-
TKI versus conventional chemotherapy on risk of metastasis 
to the central nervous system (CNS) in stage IV EGFR-mutant 
NSCLC patients showed a lower cumulative risk of CNS 
metastasis after first-line EGFR-TKI treatment (77 patients) 
compared with the chemotherapy treatment (42 patients) 
(P=0.032). Nevertheless, the aforementioned data should be 
interpreted rigorously due to the small sample size, lack of 
survival information, and retrospective analysis in nature. 
Therefore, we retrieved clinical materials and survival data 
of stage IIIB/IV EGFR-mutant pulmonary adenocarcinoma, 
comparing BM risk and survival in matched pair patients 
who had been administered with erlotinib or chemotherapy. </p>

<p>Patients and methods 
Patient selection </p>

<p>The study was approved by the Shandong Cancer Hospi-
tal and Institute ethics committee. All patients signed an 
informed consent form for voluntary participation prior to 
their inclusion in the study. From January 2008 to August 
2014, pathologically confirmed pulmonary adenocarcinoma 
patients with treat-naive advanced (stage IIIB/IV) disease 
were reviewed for eligibility. Inclusion criteria were the 
patients 1) who were completely evaluated for medical his-
tory and physical examination and underwent an enhanced 
computed tomography (CT) scan of chest and abdomen, a 
magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of brain, and a single-
photon emission computerized tomography scan of bone at 
diagnosis; 2) who had histological diagnoses from biopsies 
with bronchoscope, mediastinoscope, or CT-guided needle 
biopsy; 3) with EGFR genotype determined as sensitive 
mutation by direct sequencing or amplification refractory 
mutation system technique; 4) who were BM-free at diagnosis 
for stage IV patients; 5) in whom efficacy evaluation after 
treatment was routinely performed; and 6) in whom follow-up 
examinations using enhanced CT and/or MRI scans of the 
brain were performed every 3 months for the initial 2 years 
and then every 6 months afterward at least. 
Patients who received erlotinib were defined as erlotinib 
group, while those who received chemotherapy were defined 
as chemotherapy group. Additional inclusion criteria for the </p>

<p>erlotinib group were the patients 1) in whom erlotinib was 
administrated in first-line or second-line treatment (with 
cisplatin/pemetrexed or carboplatin/paclitaxel applied in 
first-line chemotherapy for at least two cycles); 2) in whom 
erlotinib was orally administrated at a prescribed daily dose 
of 100-150 mg until any disease progression or intolerable 
toxicity was evaluated by qualified oncologists; 3) without 
any anti-EGFR therapy, other than erlotinib, before the 
occurrence of BM; 4) in whom erlotinib administration lasted 
for .2 months, followed by efficacy evaluation based on the 
Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 
guidelines 
16 obtaining complete response (CR)/partial 
response (PR) or stable disease (SD). Additional inclusion 
criteria for the chemotherapy group were the patients 1) in 
whom chemotherapy was administrated in first-line and/ 
or second-line treatment; 2) in whom at least two cycles of 
cisplatin/pemetrexed or carboplatin/paclitaxel combined reg-
imens in first-line treatment; 3) in whom at least two cycles 
of single or combined regimens including docetaxel, pem-
etrexed, gemcitabine, and platinum in second-line treatment; 
and 4) without any anti-EGFR therapy before the occurrence 
of BM. Additionally, doses and duration of chemotherapy 
regimens were applied according to the clinical guidelines. 
Patients who received concurrent radiotherapy during first-
line and/or second-line treatments were excluded. </p>

<p>study design </p>

<p>The information of all the eligible patients were retrieved 
from the patient database, including age, sex, smoking his-
tory, performance status (PS) score (Eastern Cooperative 
Oncology Group), and treatment schemes (regimens and 
cycles of chemotherapy; targets and doses/fractionation of 
radiotherapy; classifications, doses, and duration of targeted 
molecular treatments; response evaluation of the treatment; 
etc). The matching factors included age (within ±5 years), 
sex, PS, first-/second-line treatment, first-line chemotherapy 
regimen (for second-line treatment subgroup), stage IIIB/ 
IV, and EGFR genotype. If more than one patient in a group 
was eligible, the best match was chosen by random selection 
(Figure 1). The matching procedure was conducted blindly 
without any information about patient outcomes. 
The first day of erlotinib administration or chemotherapy 
was set as the starting point for analysis. The end point event 
was the occurrence of BM, which was diagnosed by enhanced 
brain MRI or CT. The definition of time to BM was the time 
interval from first day of first-/second-line treatment to BM 
or the last follow-up. Overall survival (OS) was defined as the 
time interval from the starting point of the research study to </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>673 </p>

<p>erlotinib reduced BM risk in egFr-mutant nsclc </p>

<p>death by any reason or the last follow-up. The PS score and 
adverse reactions of each patient during erlotinib administration 
or chemotherapy were also recorded and analyzed. 
The patterns of disease progression during follow-up were 
assessed based on pathology and/or serial images, including 
CT, MRI, and positron emission tomography. Local-regional 
progression, BM development, and other distant metastases 
were recorded separately, regardless of the timing of disease 
progression. For patients suffering from BM, subsequent 
treatments were recorded and compared. For those who 
received radiotherapy for BM, including whole brain radiation 
therapy (WBRT) or stereotactic radiosurgery (SRS), response 
rates of disease were evaluated according to the RECIST. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>egFr mutation test </p>

<p>Direct sequencing or amplification refractory mutation 
system using ADx EGFR mutations detection kit (Amoy 
Diagnostics, Xiamen, People's Republic of China) was </p>

<p>applied to determine EGFR genotype. All procedures were 
performed following the user manual. Sensitive genotypes, 
including exon 19 deletion, exon 21 L858R and L861, exon 
18 G719X and G719, and exon 20 S768I mutations, can be 
detected. Patients who underwent EGFR determination by 
paraffin-embedded tissue after initial diagnosis or even after 
the occurrence of BM were also eligible. </p>

<p>statistical methods </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 19.0</rs>). 
The Fisher's exact test was applied for every matching crite-
rion and nonmatching parameters. The survival curves (time 
to BM and OS) were compared by Kaplan-Meier method and 
log rank test. The incidences of BM within 2 years and the 
2-year survival rates were calculated from the survival curves. 
Factors that are associated with the survival outcomes were 
explored by univariate analysis. The subsequent multivariate 
survival analysis was also conducted by Cox regression model </p>

<p>Figure 1 Flowchart of match pair process. 
Abbreviations: excl, excluded; egFr, epidermal growth factor receptor; BM, brain metastasis; pts, patients. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>674 </p>

<p>liu et al </p>

<p>with the backward stepwise manner. Two-sided P-values 
,0.05 were considered as statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results 
Patient characteristics </p>

<p>A total of 2,270 advanced pulmonary adenocarcinoma 
patients were screened in our institution. Based on the 
matching criteria, 129 matched pairs were included for 
final analysis (Figure 1). Table 1 summarized the matched 
clinical and tumor factors and the comparisons between the 
erlotinib and the chemotherapy groups. The median age 
was 58 years old (range: 22-89) totally. A balance existed 
between the erlotinib group and the chemotherapy group in 
all clinical characteristics. Sixty-six pairs and 63 pairs of 
patients had sensitive EGFR mutations of exon 19 deletion 
and exon 21 L858R mutations, respectively. Mutations in 
exon 21 L861 (one patient) and exon 18 G719 (one patient) 
were also found in the erlotinib group but failed in match pair 
process. No other EGFR mutation was detected. </p>

<p>Brain metastases rate, time, and 
correlation factors </p>

<p>At last follow-up, 73 patients in the erlotinib group and 88 
patients in the chemotherapy group experienced BM. Twenty </p>

<p>versus 33 patients in the erlotinib and the chemotherapy 
groups experienced BM as the first site of disease progres-
sion. In addition to BM, 49 versus 58 patients in the erlotinib 
and the chemotherapy groups also suffered local-regional 
progression and/or other distant metastases. Among patients 
not suffering from BM by last follow-up, 31 patients in the 
erlotinib group and 26 patients in the chemotherapy group 
experienced extracranial disease progression. 
Table 2 and Figures 2 and 3 presented the incidences 
of BM and the time to BM in total patients and subgroups. 
By the end of a median follow-up interval of 21.50 months 
(range: 2.63-55.53 months), the incidences of BM within 
2 years were 66.40% and 84.50% for the erlotinib and the 
chemotherapy groups (P=0.001), respectively. The median 
time to BM was 17.60 months for the erlotinib group, whereas 
15.37 months for the chemotherapy group (P=0.002). 
Furthermore, subgroup analysis also showed significantly 
that incidences of BM within 2 years are lower and time to 
BM is longer in patients who received erlotinib treatment than 
chemotherapy in all subgroups, including first-line treatment, 
second-line treatment, stage IIIB, stage IV, exon 19 deletion 
mutation, and L858R mutation in exon 21. 
Univariate analysis demonstrated that stage IIIB (P=0.001) 
and erlotinib treatment (P=0.002) were significantly related 
to reduced BM risk. As for multivariate analysis, the time 
to BM was longer for patients with erlotinib administration 
(hazard ratio [HR], 1.695; 95% confidence interval [CI], 
1.238-2.320; P=0.001) and stage IIIB (HR, 1.751; 95% CI, 
1.266-2.423; P=0.001). </p>

<p>Treatments and response </p>

<p>Erlotinib/gefitinib was applied after the occurrence of BM 
in chemotherapy group in 79 patients. Of all patients who 
experienced BM, 62 versus 73 patients in the erlotinib and 
the chemotherapy groups received brain irradiation combined 
with erlotinib/gefitinib (30 vs 14 patients) or chemotherapy 
(15 vs 32 patients) or without any systemic treatment. For 
patients who had single BM, SRS (ten in the eroltinib group 
and 14 in the chemotherapy group), or WBRT plus SRS boost 
(three in the eroltinib group and two in the chemotherapy 
group) were delivered. Objective response rates (CR + PR) 
of brain irradiation were 54.8% (six CRs and 28 PRs) and 
56.2% (seven CRs and 34 PRs) in patients administrating 
erlotinib and chemotherapy (P=0.986), respectively. </p>

<p>survival analysis and adverse reactions </p>

<p>A median OS of 22.60 months (95% CI, 20.95-24.25 months) 
and a 2-year survival rate of 43.10% (95% CI, 35.06%-51.14%) </p>

<p>Table 1 Basic clinical characteristics of 129 pairs of pulmonary 
adenocarcinoma patients </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Erlotinib group 
Chemotherapy 
group </p>

<p>age (years) 
Median (range) 
59 (22-89) 
58 (28-82) 
,60 
70 (54.3%) 
71 (55.0%) </p>

<p>$60 
59 (45.7%) 
58 (45.0%) 
sex 
Male 
56 (43.4%) 
56 (43.4%) 
Female 
73 (56.6%) 
73 (56.6%) 
stage 
iiiB 
54 (41.9%) 
54 (41.9%) 
iV 
75 (58.1%) 
75 (58.1%) 
egFr genotype 
exon 19 deletion 
66 (51.2%) 
66 (51.2%) 
exon 21 l858r mutation 
63 (48.8%) 
63 (48.8%) 
Performance status 
0-1 
108 (83.7%) 
108 (83.7%) 
2-3 
21 (16.3%) 
21 (16.3%) 
Treatment 
First-line 
66 (51.2%) 
66 (51.2%) 
second-line 
63 (48.8%) 
63 (48.8%) 
First-line regimens in second-line subgroup 
cisplatin/pemetrexed 
43 (68.3%) 
43 (68.3%) 
carboplatin/paclitaxel 
20 (31.7%) 
20 (31.7%) </p>

<p>Note: all P-values .0.05. 
Abbreviation: egFr, epidermal growth factor receptor. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>675 </p>

<p>erlotinib reduced BM risk in egFr-mutant nsclc </p>

<p>were calculated for total population. The median OS was 
22.93 months and 22.27 months for the erlotinib and the 
chemotherapy applied patients, with 2-year survival rates 
of 43.70% and 42.60%, respectively (P=0.924, P=1.000; 
Figure 2, Table 3). Subgroup analysis showed no statisti-
cal differences in OS and 2-year survival rates between 
the different treatments in subgroups of first-line treatment 
(P=0.796, P=0.596), second-line treatment (P=0.894, 
P=0.591), stage IIIB (P=0.507, P=1.000), stage IV (P=0.391, 
P=0.866), exon 19 deletion mutation (P=0.993, P=1.000), or 
exon 21 L858R mutation (P=0.828, P=1.000). 
Univariate analysis shows that longer OS is sig-
nificantly associated with stage IIIB (P=0.003) but not 
with age (P=0.592), sex (P=0.416), PS score (P=0.603), </p>

<p>erlotinib/chemotherapy administration (P=0.924), EGFR 
mutation genotypes (P=0.937), or first-/second-line treat-
ment (P=0.604). In multivariate analysis, OS remained 
longer for patients with stage IIIB disease (HR, 1.719; 95% 
CI, 1.192-2.479; P=0.004). 
Approximately half of patients maintained stable PS score 
before, during, and after erlotinib administration. Forty-one 
patients experienced improved PS score during erlotinib 
treatment because of symptoms relieve. Nineteen patients 
suffered severe but tolerable adverse reactions with decreased 
PS score. As for the chemotherapy group, six patients 
obtained elevated PS score and 44 patients suffered deterio-
rated PS. The difference between the erlotinib group and the 
chemotherapy group was statistically significant (P,0.001). </p>

<p>Table 2 Time to BM and incidences of BM within 2 years in total population and subgroups </p>

<p>Subgroup 
Time to BM (median, month) 
P-value Incidences of BM within 2 years (%) 
P-value </p>

<p>Erlotinib group 
Chemotherapy group 
Erlotinib group 
Chemotherapy group </p>

<p>Total patients (129 pairs) 
17.60 (15.55-19.65) 15.37 (13.99-16.75) 
0.002 
66.40 (55.23-77.57) 84.50 (76.27-92.73) 
0.001 
First-line treatment (66 pairs) 
17.60 (15.59-19.61) 15.20 (11.71-18.69) 
0.009 
55.80 (38.94-72.66) 86.50 (75.33-97.67) 
,0.001 
second-line treatment (63 pairs) 
18.13 (15.61-20.65) 16.00 (14.44-17.56) 
0.048 
61.20 (47.28-75.12) 82.30 (70.15-94.45) 
0.016 
stage iiiB (54 pairs) 
19.97 (6.54-33.40) 18.63 (14.61-22.65) 
0.028 
54.60 (36.37-72.83) 77.20 (63.09-91.31) 
0.014 
stage iV (75 pairs) 
16.50 (14.62-18.38) 14.20 (11.45-16.95) 
0.009 
75.50 (61.98-89.02) 90.30 (80.70-99.90) 
0.027 
exon 19 deletion (66 pairs) 
17.90 (15.08-20.72) 16.23 (14.12-18.34) 
0.047 
61.60 (46.12-77.08) 80.90 (68.94-92.86) 
0.034 
exon 21 l858r mutation (63 pairs) 17.30 (14.70-19.90) 14.60 (12.00-17.20) 
0.008 
70.60 (55.12-86.08) 89.10 (80.08-98.12) 
0.014 </p>

<p>Note: Values within parentheses show 95% ci. 
Abbreviations: BM, brain metastasis; CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Time to BM (A) and overall survival (B) of the erlotinib group versus chemotherapy group. 
Abbreviation: BM, brain metastasis. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>676 </p>

<p>liu et al </p>

<p>Figure 3 Time to BM in the erlotinib group versus the chemotherapy group in subgroups of first-line treatment (A), second-line treatment (B), stage iiiB (C), stage iV (D), 
exon 19 deletion (E), and exon 21 l858r mutation (F). 
Abbreviation: BM, brain metastasis. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>677 </p>

<p>erlotinib reduced BM risk in egFr-mutant nsclc </p>

<p>Table 3 Os and 2-year survival rates of total population and subgroups </p>

<p>Subgroup 
OS (median, month) 
P-value 2-year survival rates (%) 
P-value </p>

<p>Erlotinib group 
Chemotherapy group 
Erlotinib group 
Chemotherapy group </p>

<p>Total patients (129 pairs) 
22.93 (21.16-24.70) 22.27 (20.04-24.50) 
0.924 
43.70 (33.12-54.28) 42.60 (30.45-54.75) 
1.000 
First-line treatment (66 pairs) 
22.57 (17.35-27.79) 21.17 (15.10-27.24) 
0.796 
38.20 (21.93-54.47) 44.60 (27.35-61.85) 
0.596 
second-line treatment (63 pairs) 
23.97 (18.93-29.01) 22.27 (20.13-24.41) 
0.894 
48.20 (34.09-62.31) 41.30 (24.44-58.16) 
0.591 
stage iiiB (54 pairs) 
26.63 (21.83-31.43) 25.70 (11.17-40.23) 
0.507 
50.30 (33.84-66.76) 50.80 (32.57-69.03) 
1.000 
stage iV (75 pairs) 
22.57 (18.32-26.82) 20.6 (15.52-25.68) 
0.391 
39.00 (25.28-52.72) 36.20 (20.32-52.08) 
0.866 
exon 19 deletion (66 pairs) 
23.07 (16.73-29.41) 22.27 (19.80-24.74) 
0.993 
44.10 (29.01-59.19) 42.10 (26.22-57.98) 
1.000 
exon 21 l858r mutation (63 pairs) 22.93 (20.94-24.92) 21.73 (16.44-27.02) 
0.828 
43.50 (28.41-58.59) 43.90 (25.28-62.52) 
1.000 </p>

<p>Note: Values within parentheses show 95% ci. 
Abbreviations: OS, overall survival; CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>The most common adverse event with erlotinib was rash 
(81.4%) and diarrhea (40.3%), with most cases classified 
as grade 1 or 2 in severity. Chemotherapy was associated 
with a high incidence of gastrointestinal adverse reactions 
(86.8%) and hematologic toxicities (75.2%). Grades 3-4 
leukopenia and thrombocytopenia were significantly more 
frequent with chemotherapy compared with erlotinib (1.6% 
vs 31.8%, P,0.001; 0.8% vs 24.8%, P,0.001). </p>

<p>subgroup analysis </p>

<p>For the erlotinib group, according to different clinical 
responses to erlotinib after 2-month administration, subgroup 
analysis showed that the median times to BM, median OS, 
incidences of BM within 2 years, and 2-year survival rates 
were 19.03 months, 23.07 months, 59.00%, and 44.40% 
for the CR/PR patients, while 15.37 months, 22.57 months, 
85.40%, and 40.80% for the SD patients, respectively 
(P=0.001, P=0.465, P=0.007, P=0.835). Further analysis 
showed that time to BM is longer and the incidences of BM 
within 2 years are lower in the CR/PR group than in the SD 
group, with substantial statistical significance in subgroups 
of exon 19 deletion mutation (P=0.009, P=0.043) and L858R 
mutation in exon 21 (P=0.028, 0.047). For OS and 2-year 
survival rates, no statistical significance existed in the sub-
groups of exon 19 deletion mutation (P=0.247, P=0.579) or 
exon 21 L858R mutation (P=0.972, P=1.000). 
When analysis narrowed to the second-line treatment 
group, similar median times to BM, median OS, incidences 
of BM within 2 years, and 2-year survival rates were seen 
in patients receiving cisplatin/pemetrexed than those receiv-
ing carboplatin/paclitaxel (18.63 vs 15.13 months, P=0.192; 
23.97 vs 20.60 months, P=0.159; 75.70% vs 76.70%, 
P=1.000; and 49.00% vs 38.40%, P=0.593, respectively). 
Subgroup analysis showed that time to BM was longer and 
incidences of BM within 2 years were lower in erlotinib 
administration than chemotherapy in patients receiving 
cisplatin/pemetrexed (P=0.080, P=0.293) or carboplatin/ </p>

<p>paclitaxel (P=0.275, P=1.000) without statistical signifi-
cance. For OS and 2-year survival rates, no statistical sig-
nificance existed in the subgroups of cisplatin/pemetrexed 
(P=0.897, P=1.000) and carboplatin/paclitaxel (P=0.761, 
P=0.353). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The treatment for patients with EGFR-mutant pulmonary 
adenocarcinoma has been significantly improved. However, 
BM still occurs in many patients months or even years after 
their initial treatment. Mutant EGFR genotype and BM 
were correlated significantly in patients with pulmonary 
adenocarcinomas as exhibited in a recent study. 
4 More EGFR 
mutations were reported in patients with existed BM than 
extracranial metastases. In this retrospective matched pair 
study, we found that erlotinib treatment reduced BM risk 
in pulmonary adenocarcinoma patients with stage IIIB/IV 
EGFR-mutant NSCLC. It suggested that erlotinib administra-
tion might prevent or delay the occurrence of BM. 
It is reasonable to suppose that EGFR-targeted therapy 
may be more effective for EGFR-mutant lung cancer patients 
in reducing BM risk because of the confirmed systemic 
response and molecular permeability through intact BBB. 
Present study showed prolonged time to BM and a lowered 
2-year cumulative risk of BM development in patients 
receiving erlotinib than chemotherapy. The cause-specific 
HR for erlotinib versus chemotherapy was 1.695, suggesting 
an increased risk of 69.5% for chemotherapy than erlotinib. 
Thus, the observed lower BM incidence seems to be due, at 
least in part, to the effect of the EGFR TKI. The promising 
effect of erlotinib was also seen in subgroups of patients 
with first-line treatment, second-line treatment, stage IIIB 
disease, stage IV disease, exon 19 deletion mutation, and 
L858R mutation in exon 21. For patients administrated with 
erlotinib, CR/PR of extracranial disease predicted lower BM 
risk than effect evaluation of SD. Cisplatin/pemetrexed and 
carboplatin/paclitaxel applied in first-line treatment resulted </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>678 </p>

<p>liu et al </p>

<p>similar BM risks in patients of the second-line treatment 
group. When considered for OS, no statistical significances 
were seen between the erlotinib and the chemotherapy 
groups or in any subgroup. Existed studies 
17,18 showed 
potential better prognostic values in patients harboring exon 
19 deletion mutation compared with patients with L858R 
mutation. In our analysis, similar survival outcomes were 
found between both EGFR mutations. During follow-up, 
approximately two-thirds of patients who suffered from 
BM received subsequent WBRT or SRS, either alone or 
combined with EGFR TKI or systemic chemotherapy. 
Objective response rates were .50%, which was similar to 
previous studies. 
19 In addition, erlotinib provided significant 
improvement in quality of life compared with chemotherapy 
in terms of simple PS score. In consistent with existed reports, 
toxicities of erlotinib were exhibited as rash, diarrhea, etc, 
which were milder in severity and easier to be controlled 
when compared with chemotherapy. 
Erlotinib accumulation in BM has been clearly exhib-
ited through 
11 C-erlotinib imaging using clinical positron 
emission tomography. 
8 Furthermore, after erlotinib admin-
istration, high erlotinib concentrations in the cerebrospinal 
fluid and the subsequent BM regression were certified. </p>

<p>7,8 </p>

<p>For patients with asymptomatic BM, single erlotinib 
administration was also active and well tolerated. 
20 It is 
worth noting that EGFR TKIs may also pass through an 
intact BBB in patients not suffering from BM. 
9,10 Concen-
trations of erlotinib had been determined to be substantial 
enough to inhibit tumor cell proliferation in cerebrospinal 
fluid after an intravenous dose in healthy adult rhesus 
monkeys. 
10,21 However, the contributing effects of EGFR-
targeted therapy on the risk of BM remain undefined in 
clinical practice. 
The 2.23-month longer median time to BM in the patients 
administrating erlotinib failed to transfer into survival benefit 
in our study. Although BM occurrence largely shortened the 
survival of patients, subsequent treatments, including radio-
therapy, systemic chemotherapy, and anti-EGFR treatment, 
succeeded in controlling BM to a certain extent. Disease 
progression in local disease and distant metastases other 
than brain also account for the balanced survival between 
two groups. Additionally, several randomized studies </p>

<p>13,22-24 </p>

<p>demonstrated that the first-line EGFR TKI resulted signifi-
cant improvement in both disease response to treatment and 
progression-free survival than conventional platinum-based 
combined chemotherapy, but not in OS. The rather high 
proportion of patients in the chemotherapy arm crossing over 
to the EGFR TKI arm during disease progression provided </p>

<p>the interpretation. Similarly in our study, 79 patients from 
the chemotherapy group took EGFR TKI orally after BM 
occurrence. The crossing over to erlotinib treatments makes 
the survival benefit not significant enough to be analyzed in 
statistics. Furthermore, for some patients in our study who 
died without BM occurrence, the 6.0-month time interval 
between median time to BM and median OS was shorter 
than the survival time after BM occurrence. 
Although the data from this study are well compared 
and promising, it is important to take into consideration 
the limitations of the study. First, although our study used 
a match pairing procedure to reduce the effect of several 
variables on the outcomes, the retrospective single-center 
nonrandomized design weakened the persuasion when inter-
preting the results. Therefore, comparisons were carried out 
in subgroups of stage IIIB, stage IV, first-line and second-line 
treatments, and different EGFR mutations, which broadened 
the potential benefit population, thus helped to explore the 
best benefit population and best time point for erlotinib 
administration. Second, due to the 6-year long time span of 
our study, majority patients in the chemotherapy group did 
not undergo EGFR mutation screening at initial diagnosis 
because of underestimating its importance. Currently, EGFR 
mutation genotype is routinely determined in pulmonary 
adenocarcinoma. Furthermore, for lung cancer patients with 
BM, highly sensitive polymerase chain reaction techniques 
provide the feasibility of determination of EGFR mutation 
genotype in BM, 
25 which provides detail biological informa-
tion of BM and thus guide treatment decisions in clinical 
practice. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In summary, present matched pair study demonstrated the 
role of erlotinib administration in delaying and/or preventing 
BM in stage IIIB/IV EGFR-mutant pulmonary adenocar-
cinoma patients. It is necessary to conduct well-designed 
prospective clinical trials with specific BM end points, 
scheduled CNS imaging, and confirmed EGFR mutation 
status to validate our findings. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This research was funded by the National Natural Science 
Foundation of China (81301868 and 81502667) and Natural 
Science Foundation of Shandong, People's Republic of China 
(ZR2014HP041). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open 
access journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>679 </p>

<p>erlotinib reduced BM risk in egFr-mutant nsclc </p>



</text></tei>