<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4886572" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Introduction: People in tropical and semi-tropical areas are in danger of scorpion sting, and this can be a serious 
problem for them. Mortality due to scorpion sting in the tropical and semi-tropical areas of Iran is about 75%, and 
this makes scorpion sting in these areas a serious medical problem. Because of this problem, our aim was to assess 
the epidemiological aspects of scorpion sting in Bandar Abbas, Iran, during 2009-2011. 
Methods: In this cross-sectional retrospective study, epidemiologic data of 698 scorpion sting cases, who were 
referred to the Shahid Mohamadi Hospital of Bandar Abbas in Hormozgan Province collected from 2009 until 
2011. The data included demographic and individual information, such as age, gender, geographic location, bite 
site, when the incident occurred, and anti-venom consumption. The required data were extracted from the patients' 
recorded information in the Hospital, and we recorded data in a special checklist and imported the data into the 
computer for statistical analysis using of <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 21.0</rs>. Descriptive statistics, including mean, 
standard deviation, frequency, and percentage, were used for data analysis. 
Results: Two hundred and sixty-one (37.4%) of the cases were urban and 437(62.6%) were rural. Males comprised 
50.1% of the cases, and women comprised 49.9% (p &gt;0.05). Twenty-five point two percent of scorpion sting cases 
occurred among people in the 21 to 30 age group, and there were very few cases among people in the 51 to 60 age 
range (p&lt;0.05). Most of cases were recorded in April and October, and the fewest cases were recorded in July and 
January (p&lt;0.05); also 32.2% of scorpion sting cases occurred after midnight and in the early morning hours. 
Conclusion: Our survey showed that there was a high incidence of scorpion stings in rural areas, among 21-30 age 
group, among housekeepers, and among students. These results indicate the need for public education programs 
and better sanitation services in the rural areas around Bandar Abbas city. Prospective studies can help to health 
and medicine organization for prevention and treatment of scorpion sting. 
1.2. Statement of problem 
In west and southwest of Iran, scorpion sting is one of the medical problems. Razi Serum Institution's studies have 
shown that the most mortality due to poisoning are from scorpion stings (8). The mortality rate associated with 
scorpion sting in the tropical and semi-tropical areas of Iran is about 75%, and this makes scorpion sting in these areas 
a serious medical problem. Khuzestan, Sistan Baloochestan, Charmahal Bakhtiari, Bushehr and Hormozgan Provinces 
have more reported scorpion sting cases than anywhere else in Iran (9-11). More than 2,300 cases of scorpion sting 
per year occur in Hormozgan Province, and most of the cases are in Bandar Abbas County. Between 2011 and 2014, 
four deaths of children less than five years old occurred due to scorpion sting in Bandar Abbas. This study tries to 
clarify the epidemiologic status of scorpion stings in Hormozgan Province in the absence of any past epidemiologic 
studies. </p>

<p>1.3 Objectives 
The general objective of the current study was to report the epidemiological aspect of scorpion sting in Bandar Abbas, 
Iran, from 2009 through 2011.Specific objectives included the following: 
1) 
To determine the epidemiological aspect of scorpion sting according to the age 
2) 
To determine the epidemiological aspect of scorpion sting according to the job 
3) 
To determine the epidemiological aspect of scorpion sting according to the month 
4) 
To determine the epidemiological aspect of scorpion sting according to the period of 24 hours 
5) 
To determine the epidemiological aspect of scorpion sting according to the sting site </p>

<p>2. Material and Methods 
2.1. Study area 
Hormozgan Province is located in the south of the country, and it has a 900-km border with the Persian Gulf and 
Oman Sea. This Province has a subtropical climate, and it has two different areas, i.e., coastal plain in south and a 
mountainous area in the north. Bandar Abbas is the main port of the country. The study area was located in the 
mountainous and coastal part of Bandar Abbas county with a surface area of 10,359 km </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>located in southern Iran 
(between 26° 53'-27° 31' N latitude and 54° 53'-56° 30' E longitude). The county has four districts, i.e., the Central 
district, Fin, Thakht and QalehQazi. The county includes 336 officially registered localities, such as villages and rural 
areas. In the 2009 census, the Bandar Abbas County's population was 588,228, from this population 139,427 (23.7%) 
were rural vicinities. The major portion of the Province has mountainous terrain, with the southern sector of the Zagros 
Mountain Range stretching out from the northwest to southeast. The total annual rainfall is in the range of 100-150 
mm, and the mean annual relative humidity is 59.5%.The maximum and minimum mean annual temperatures are 49 
and 6 °C, respectively. </p>

<p>2.2. Sampling and data collection 
All the scorpion sting cases who were referred to the Adult and Pediatric Central Hospital of Bandar Abbas from 2009 
through 2011 were included in the study. In this cross-sectional retrospective study, the epidemiologic data of 698 
scorpion sting cases were statistically analyzed. The data included demographic and individual information, such as 
age, gender, geographic location, sting site, the time the sting occurred, and the consumption of anti-venom. </p>

<p>2.3. Measurement tools 
The required data were extracted from the patients' recorded information in the hospital. Data for each patient were 
recorded in a special checklist and imported into the computer for statistical analysis. </p>

<p>2.4. Research ethics 
The information about the patients was kept confidential. Also, the information was extracted without name by using 
codes. This study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of Hormozgan University of Medical Sciences 
(ethic code: HUMS.REC.1394.83). </p>

<p>http://www.ephysician.ir </p>



<p>2.5. Statistical analysis 
Data was analyzed using SPSS software, version 21. Descriptive statistics, including mean, standard deviation, 
frequency, and percentage were used for data analysis. </p>

<p>3. Results 
In this study, 698 scorpion sting cases were studied. Two hundred and sixty-one (37.4%) of the cases were urban, and 
437(62.6%) were rural. The urban-to-rural ratio of scorpion stings was 1/67. Among these people, 50.1% were male, 
and 49.9% were female. Twenty-five point two percent of scorpion sting cases occurred among people whose ages 
were from 21 to 30, and 20.2% occurred among people whose ages ranged from 11 to 20. The fewest cases occurred 
for people in the age range of 51 to 60 (p&lt;0.05) (Table 1). Housekeepers and students were more at risk of scorpion 
sting (46.4 and 16%, respectively) and employees were at lower risk (6.9%) (p&lt;0.05). Most of cases occurred in April 
and October, and the fewest cases occurred in July and January (p&lt;0.05) (Figure 1). Fifty-eight point nine percent 
(411) of cases reported from residential places, and 41.9% (287) of the cases were in non-residential areas. Thirty-two 
point two percent of scorpion sting cases occurred after midnight and in the early morning hours. The lowest incidence 
of scorpion sting occurred between 12 to 18 o'clock at the day long (p&lt;0.05).Foot, hand, trunk, head, and neck were 
more at risk of sting by scorpions, with feet being the most likely site of stings (41.5%), while the head and neck were 
the least likely locations (4.6%). </p>

<p>Table 1. Age distribution of scorpion sting cases in Bandar Abbas during 2009-2011 
Age (Year) n 
% 
0-10 
95 
13.6 
11-20 
141 20.2 
21-30 
176 25.2 
31-40 
113 16.2 
41-50 
66 
9.5 
51-60 
54 
7.7 
&gt; 60 
53 
7.6 
Total 
698 100 </p>

<p>Figure1. Mean scorpion sting cases by months of the year in Bandar Abbas over 3 years, 2009-2011 </p>

<p>4. Discussion 
This study is the first cross-sectional study on epidemiologic features of scorpion stings in Hormozgan Province, and 
it showed that most scorpion sting cases occur in rural areas. Dehghani et al., Jahana et al., and Kassiri et al. also 
reported similar findings in our results (1, 2, 12). Studies in Khuzestan have shown the rate of scorpion stings in urban 
areas to be about 60% (13). That indicates that the rural environmental status is an important and adverse factor in 
increasing scorpion sting cases in Bandar Abbas city. Other studies also have shown more reported cases of scorpion 
stings in rural areas in comparison to urban areas. Our results didn't show any differences in occurrence of scorpion </p>

<p>Electronic physician </p>



<p>sting between males and females. Karami et al. reported more scorpion stings in female patients who were referred to 
Ramhormoz Health Center than male patients, and their finding was similar to that of Vazirianzadeh et al.'s finding 
in Khuzestan (13, 14).Studies in Saudi Arabia have shown more incidence of scorpion sting among males. This finding 
could be due to their culture, job, geographic location, and social activity of men in comparison to women. Kassiri et 
al. in Khuzestan reported 52.6% of scorpion sting cases in men and 47.4% of cases in women (15-19). In our study 
the greatest rate of scorpion stings occurred among people in the age range of 21-30, but Talebian &amp; Doroodgar 
reported the highest rate among children less than 10 (18). Also, Kassiri et al. reported the greatest rate among people 
in the 15-24 age range (19). The increased incidence of scorpion stings among young people is due to their social 
activity, which exposes them to greater danger of being stung. In our study, the highest incidences of scorpion stings 
were recorded in the spring and in the last month of summer. Our results showed two peak periods of scorpion sting, 
one in May and one in October. The findings of studies in several areas of Iran and in neighboring countries, such as 
Turkey and Saudi Arabia, indicated high incidences of scorpion stings in the summer (14, 15, 19-21). Maybe the poor 
correlation between our results and the results of these other studies was due to the climate in Bandar Abbas and its 
geographic location. Bandar Abbas is located in a subtropical area, and there is significant scorpion activity in May 
and October. Also, people spend more times outside their homes for rest and amusement and also increase of scorpion 
sting rate was because of starting the cultivation season in these months, which can lead to more exposure to scorpion 
sting. Most scorpion stings occurred after midnight and in the early morning hours. This result also was reported by 
Hoseininasab et al. and Rahmani et al. in southern Kerman and Ahwaz. Scorpion's night activity is a reasonable 
explanation for this result (22, 23). </p>

<p>5. Conclusions 
This study is the first epidemiologic study about scorpion stings in Hormozgan Province. The high incidence of 
scorpion stings in rural areas among people in the age range of 21-30, housekeepers, and students suggests that public 
education programs and better sanitation services are needed in the rural areas of Bandar Abbas County. Prospective 
studies about ecology and distribution of various species of scorpions can help to health and medicine organization 
for prevention and management of scorpion sting. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments: 
The authors are thankful to Bandar Abbas health center for their contribution for completing the data for this study. 
Also the authors are thankful to Hormozgan University of Medical Sciences for their support and help. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: 
There is no conflict of interest to be declared. </p>

<p>Authors' contributions: 
All authors contributed to this project and article equally. All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </p>



<p>http://www.ephysician.ir </p>





</text></tei>