<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4568868" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The bacterial spot of tomato, caused by Xanthomonas spp., is a very important disease, especially in 
the hot and humid periods of the year. The chemical control of the disease has not been very effective 
for a number of reasons. This study aimed to evaluate, under greenhouse conditions, the efficacy of 
leaf-spraying chemicals (acibenzolar-S-methyl (ASM) (0.025 g.L -1 ), fluazinam (0.25 g.L -1 ), pyra-
clostrobin (0.08 g.L -1 ), pyraclostrobin + methiran (0.02 g.L -1 + 2.2 g.L -1 ), copper oxychloride 
(1.50 g.L -1 ), mancozeb + copper oxychloride (0.88 g.L -1 + 0.60 g.L -1 ), and oxytetracycline 
(0.40 g.L -1 )) on control of bacterial spot. Tomatoes Santa Clara and Gisele cultivars were pulverized 
3 days before inoculation with Xanthomonas perforans. The production of enzymes associated with 
resistance induction (peroxidase, polyphenol oxidase, phenylalanine ammonia-lyase, b-1,3-glu-
canase, and protease) was quantified from leaf samples collected 24 hours before and 24 hours after 
chemical spraying and at 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 days after bacterial inoculation. All products tested con-
trolled bacterial spot, but only ASM, pyraclostrobin, and pyraclostrobin + metiram increased the pro-
duction of peroxidase in the leaves of the two tomato cultivars, and increased the production of 
polyphenol oxidase and b-1,3-glucanase in the Santa Clara cultivar. </p>

<p>The tomato can be considered one of the main fruits 
produced and consumed in Brazil, and tomatoes are grown 
in several regions of the country, especially the south, 
southeast and mid-west (Camargo and Camargo Filho, 
2008). There are several factors that decrease tomato pro-
duction, including diseases caused by fungi, bacteria, and 
viruses (Lopes and Avila, 2005). 
A disease known as bacterial spot, caused by 
Xanthomonas euvesicatoria, X. vesicatoria, X. perforans, 
and X. gardneri (Jones et al., 2004), attacks tomatoes in 
Brazil (Quezado-Duval et al., 2005; Pereira et al., 2011). 
Field management of the disease is difficult due to high 
temperatures and intense rainfall, and preventive measures 
are adopted for the management of bacterial spot, espe-
cially crop rotation, the use of healthy seeds and seedlings, </p>

<p>balanced fertilization, and spraying of chemical products 
(Lopes and Avila, 2005). 
In tomato fields, the use of copper fungicides, antibi-
otics, and copper carbamate mixtures do not always pro-
vide satisfactory control of the disease (Maringoni et al., 
1986) and can cause the selection of resistant bacterial iso-
lates (Marco and Stall, 1983; Maringoni and Kimati 1987; 
Quezado-Duval et al., 2003). Previous research has demon-
strated the effectiveness of applying acibenzolar-S-methyl 
(ASM) to control bacterial spot (Louws et al., 2001; Caval-
canti et al., 2005a, b). ASM induces resistance to the dis-
ease in tomato plants (Cavalcanti et al., 2005a, b) without 
directly affecting the bacteria (Itako et al., 2012a). 
In Brazil, several fungicides are used to control fun-
gal diseases in tomato including pyraclostrobin (Agrofit, 
2012). Besides controlling early blight and late blight in to-
matoes, it also activates the synthesis of proteins associated </p>

<p>Brazilian Journal of Microbiology 46, 3, 701-706 (2015) 
Copyright © 2015, Sociedade Brasileira de Microbiologia 
ISSN 1678-4405 
www.sbmicrobiologia.org.br 
DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/S1517-838246320140177 </p>

<p>Send correspondence to A.C. Maringoni. Departamento de Proteção Vegetal, Faculdade de Ciências Agronômicas, Universidade Estadual Paulista "Júlio 
de Mesquita Filho", 18603-970 Botucatu, SP, Brazil. E-mail: maringoni@fca.unesp.br. </p>

<p>Research Paper </p>

<p>with the induction of resistance in plants (Herms et al., 
2002; Vigo et al., 2012). Studies conducted by Itako et al. 
(2012b) showed that ASM and pyraclostrobin help control 
the bacterial spot on the tomato hybrid AP 529, and that 
these products affect the activity of peroxidase, polyphenol 
oxidase, and b-1,3-glucanase. 
This study aimed to evaluate, under greenhouse con-
ditions, the efficacy of leaf spraying with various chemicals 
(ASM, fluzinam, pyraclostrobin, pyraclostrobin + metiram, 
copper oxychloride, copper oxychloride + mancozeb, and 
oxytetracycline) on the control of bacterial spot on Santa 
Clara and Gisele tomato cultivars. We also evaluated 
whether these chemicals induce the production of peroxi-
dase, polyphenol oxidase, b-1,3-glucanase, phenylalanine 
ammonia-lyase, and protease, which are associated with re-
sistance to bacterial spot of tomato (Cavalcanti et al., 
2005a, b; Itako et al., 2012b; Luiz et al., 2012). </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Effects of fungicides and antibiotic on bacterial spot </p>

<p>In order to evaluate the effect of different products on 
the control of bacterial spot of the tomato cultivars Santa 
Clara and Gisele, two sets of these plants were transplanted 
into pots 25 days after emergence. Pots contained 3 L of 
substrates consisting of soil, manure, and thick sand (3:2:1 
(v/v)), plus 50 g of dolomite lime and 100 g of 4-14-8 fertil-
izer per 100 L of mixture. The plants were kept in a green-
house. Fifteen days after transplanting, they were sprayed 
with acibenzolar-S-methyl (0.025 g.L -1 ), fluazinam 
(0.25 g.L -1 ), pyraclostrobin (0.08 g.L -1 ), pyraclostrobin + 
methiran (0.02 g + 2.2 g.L -1 ), copper oxychloride 
(1.50 g.L -1 ), mancozeb + copper oxychloride (0.88 g.L -1 + 
0.60 g.L -1 ), and oxytetracycline (0.40 g.L -1 ). Three days af-
ter spraying, leaves were inoculated with a suspension of X. 
perforans strain (10 6 cfu.mL -1 ) by spraying. The control 
treatment was represented by tomato plants inoculated or 
not inoculated and sprayed with water. Twenty-four hours 
before and 24 hours after inoculation, the plants were 
placed in a moist chamber. 
Bacterial spot severity was assessed using a diagram-
matic scale that considers the leaf area, according to Mello 
et al. (1997). Disease evaluations were done 8, 11, 14, 17, 
and 20 days after inoculation (DAI). The severity values 
obtained were used to determine the area under the disease 
progression curve (AUDPC), according to Campbell and 
Madden (1990). 
The experimental design was randomized, with nine 
treatments (seven chemicals, control inoculated, and con-
trol non-inoculated) and seven replicates. Each experimen-
tal plot consisted of one pot containing two plants. The 
AUDPC values were subjected to analysis of variance us-
ing SISVAR software (Ferreira, 2011) and means were 
compared by the Scott-Knott test at 5% probability. </p>

<p>Activation of the enzymes associated with resistance 
induction in tomato plants pulverized with fungicides and 
antibiotic, and inoculated with X. perforans 
Two trials, each with one cultivar (Santa Clara or 
Giselle), were conducted in the greenhouse. The plants 
were sprayed with chemicals and inoculated with X. 
perforans, using the same methodology and the same ex-
perimental design as described in effect of fungicides and 
antibiotic on bacterial spot, with five replicates. 
Samples for foliar enzymatic determinations were 
collected 24 h before and 24 h after spraying with fungi-
cides and antibiotic, and 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 days after inocula-
tion. The samples were packed in plastic bags and placed 
immediately in an expanded polystyrene box containing ice 
and transported without delay to the laboratory for weigh-
ing and processing, and subsequent freezer storage. 
Leaf samples were homogenized mechanically in 
4 mL of 100 mM sodium acetate buffer (pH 5.0). The ho-
mogenate was centrifuged at 20,000 g for 25 min, at 4 °C, 
and the supernatant was stored at -20 °C for determination 
of the activity of peroxidase, polyphenol oxidase, b-1,3-
glucanase, phenylalanine ammonia-lyase, and protease, 
and for protein content determination. 
Peroxidase activity was determined using a direct 
spectrophotometric method by measuring the conversion of 
guaiacol into tetraguaiacol at 470 nm (Lusso and Pascho-
lati, 1999). Peroxidase activity results are expressed as spe-
cific activity (D abs 470 nm.min -1 .mg -1 protein). 
Polyphenol oxidase activity was obtained by the 
method of Duangmal and Apentem (1999). The reaction 
was prepared by mixing 900 mL of substrate and 100 mL of 
enzymatic extract. The substrate was composed of catechol 
at a concentration of 20 mM in 100 mM sodium phosphate 
buffer (pH 6.0). Readings were performed directly for a pe-
riod of 3 min. The results are expressed as D abs 
420 nm.min -1 .mg -1 protein. 
b-1,3-glucanase activity was determined by colori-
metric quantification of the glucose released from lami-
narin, through the use of hydrazide r-hydroxybenzoic acid 
(PAHBAH) (Lever, 1972). The reaction mixture contain-
ing 150 mL of enzymatic extract and laminarin 
(2.0 mg.mL -1 ) was incubated at 37 °C for 1 h (Abeles and 
Foence, 1970). After this period, 1.5 mL of PAHBAH solu-
tion was added (0.5 g dissolved in 20 mL of 0.5 M HCl plus 
80 mL of 0.5 M NaOH), and then the mixture was heated to 
100 °C for 10 min. After cooling to 25 °C, the sample 
absorbances were determined at 410 nm against the extrac-
tion buffer. 
Phenylalanine ammonia-lyase activity was deter-
mined by colorimetric quantification of trans-cinnamic 
acid released from the phenylalanine substrate (Umesha, 
2006). The absorbance of the samples was determined at 
290 nm against the extraction buffer, and the value of the 
control was subtracted from each sample (this control cor-</p>

<p>702 
Itako et al. </p>

<p>responded to a mixture of 100 mL protein extract and 
900 mL of 25 mM Tris HCl buffer, pH 8.8). The absorbance 
readings were plotted on the standard curve for the trans-
cinnamic acid and the enzymatic activity was expressed in 
mg of trans-cinnamic per min per mg protein </p>

<p>(mg.min -1 .mg -1 ). </p>

<p>Protease activity was obtained according to Fialho 
(2004). A total of 0.5 g of casein was dissolved in 40 mL 
distilled water and allowed to stir for 20 min. Then, 1 mL of 
NaOH (1 M) and 2.5 mL of Tris (1 M) were added. After a 
period of agitation, with the casein completely dissolved, 
the pH was adjusted to 7.8 with 85% phosphoric acid. For 
the reaction, 500 mL of substrate was incubated with 
200 mL of sample at 30 °C for 30 min. The reaction was 
stopped by adding 650 mL of 10% (m/v) trichloroacetic 
acid (TCA), followed by centrifugation at 10,000 g for 
15 min. The absorbance reading was conducted at 280 nm 
and the results are expressed as absorbance units per mg 
protein (AU.mg -1 ). </p>

<p>Total protein in the extracts was determined accord-
ing to Bradford (1976). To each 0.8 mL sample, 0.2 mL of 
Bradford concentrate reagent was added while stirring. The 
protein concentration, expressed in terms of mg equivalent 
of bovine serum albumin (BSA) in 1 mL of sample (mg pro-
tein.mL -1 ) was determined using a standard curve of BSA 
concentrations, ranging from 0 to 20 mg.mL -1 . </p>

<p>The area under the enzyme progression curve was 
calculated as a function of time (samples), as in Soares et al. 
(2004), and the data was subjected to analysis of variance, 
using the statistical program <rs id="software-1" type="software">SISVAR</rs> software (Ferreira, 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2011</rs>). Means were compared by the Scott-Knott test at 5% 
probability </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Effects of fungicides and antibiotic on bacterial spot </p>

<p>Values of the AUDPC for the tomato cultivars Santa 
Clara and Gisele sprayed with different chemicals and in-
oculated with X. perforans are shown in Table 1. In both ex-
periments, each with a different tomato cultivar, the 
AUDPC of the inoculated control differed from that of the 
chemical treatments (p £ 0.05). The lowest values of 
AUDPC was obtained with acibenzolar-S-methyl in both 
cultivars. The tomato varieties differed in their responses to 
the chemicals evaluated. After the acibenzola-S-methyl, 
the best treatments for the Gisele cultivar were copper + 
mancozeb, fluazinam, and oxytetracycline, and the best 
treatments for the Santa Clara cultivar were pyraclostrobin 
+ metiram, fluazinam, and oxytetracycline. The AUDPC 
value for control inoculated treatment of the two tomato 
cultivars also differed, being lower for Santa Clara cultivar 
than for Gisele cultivar. </p>

<p>Evaluation of the production of enzymes associated 
with plant resistance induction </p>

<p>Increased production of peroxidase, polyphenol oxi-
dase (Table 2), and b-1,3-glucanase (Table 3) were ob-
served in leaves of the Santa Clara cultivar (p £ 0.05), 
whereas only the peroxidase increased significantly 
(p £ 0.05) in the leaves of the Gisele cultivar when ASM, 
pyraclostrobin + metiram, and pyraclostrobin were sprayed 
(Table 2). There were no significant differences (p &gt; 0.05) 
in the production of phenylalanine ammonia-lyase or prote-
ase in the leaves of either tomato cultivar (Table 3) sprayed 
with the different chemicals. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The effectiveness of chemicals on the control of bac-
terial spot of tomato is variable, since it depends, in part, on 
how vulnerable the bacteria is to the chemicals used. In our 
study, a reduction in AUDPC when ASM was sprayed was 
associated with the induction of biochemical mechanisms 
of resistance (Kessmann et al., 1994), as previously re-
ported in several studies (Calvacanti et al., 2006a, b; Ishida 
et al., 2008; Itako et al., 2012b). The results observed here 
for the effectiveness of ASM on control of the disease are 
consistent with those observed by Silva et al. (2003), 
Cavalcanti (2006a, b) and Itako et al. (2012b). 
The copper-based products, fluazinam and oxytetra-
cycline, satisfactorily reduced the AUDPC. With the ex-
ception of fluazinam, these products are traditionally used 
in the control of bacterial leaf spot and other bacterial dis-
eases of tomato (Louws et al., 2001). The efficacy of these 
products, however, appears to depend on the intrinsic sensi-
tivity of the bacterial strains prevalent in the field, since low 
sensitivity and/or resistance in vitro has been reported, not 
only to copper-based products, but also to some antibiotics 
(Marco and Stall, 1983; Maringoni and Kimati, 1987; Bou-</p>

<p>Chemical products 
703 </p>

<p>Table 1 -Area under the disease progress curve (AUDPC) of the bacterial 
spot for two tomatoes cultivars spayed with fungicides and antibiotic. </p>

<p>Treatment 
Santa Clara 
Gisele </p>

<p>Acibenzolar-S-methyl 
12.83 a* 
55.50 a </p>

<p>Piraclostrobin + metiram 
38.04 b 
210.26 c </p>

<p>Piraclostrobin 
58.42 c 
194.41 c </p>

<p>Copper oxychloride 
66.00 d 
178.40 c </p>

<p>Copper oxychloride + mancozeb 
51.75 c 
120.72 b </p>

<p>Fluazinam 
31.96 b 
128.52 b </p>

<p>Oxitetracicline 
42.00 b 
131.03 b </p>

<p>Control inoculated 
104.85 e 
436.03 d </p>

<p>Control non-inoculated 
0.0 
0.0 </p>

<p>C.V. (%) 
17.0 
13.2 </p>

<p>*Means followed by the same letter do not differ by Scott-Knott test at 5% 
probability. </p>

<p>zar et al., 1999; Aguiar et al., 2000; Quezado-Duval et al., 
2003). </p>

<p>According to Marco and Stall (1983), the use of 
ethylenebis (dithiocarbamate) fungicides mixed with cop-
per compounds has been effective on control of copper-
resistant or semi-resistant strains of Xanthomonas spp. 
Maringoni and Kimati (1987) observed some strains of 
Xanthomonas spp. were more sensitive in vitro to a mix-
ture of copper with mancozeb or zineb than to copper 
alone. </p>

<p>Pyraclostrobin, pyraclostrobin + metiram, and fluazi-
nam are recommended for the control of fungal diseases on 
the leaves of tomatoes, but are not indexed as controlling 
bacterial spot (Agrofit, 2012). However, under the condi-
tions tested in this study, these products have shown prom-
ise for control of bacterial spot of tomato. </p>

<p>The increased activity of peroxidase, polyphenol oxi-
dase, and b-1,3-glucanase in leaves on the Santa Clara 
cultivar and peroxidase in leaves of the Gisele cultivar may 
be associated with less disease severity, especially when 
leaves are sprayed with ASM, pyraclostrobin, and pyraclo-
strobin + metiram (Table 4), since ASM and pyraclostrobin 
are not known to have a direct action on the bacterium in vi-
tro, whereas the other products evaluated have bactericidal 
and/or bacteriostatic action (Itako et al., 2012a). </p>

<p>Peroxidases, besides strengthening the cell wall via 
increased production of lignin and suberin, polysaccha-
rides, and glycoproteins rich in hydroxyproline, stimulate 
the production of free oxygen, which has an antimicrobial 
effect and induces the production of phytoalexin (Bolwell 
et al., 1995; Wojtaszek, 1997; Kristensen et al., 1999). The 
polyphenol oxidase catalyzes the oxidation of phenols to </p>

<p>704 
Itako et al. </p>

<p>Table 3 -Area under the enzyme progression curve of ß-1,3 glucanase, phenylalanine ammonia-lyase and protease in leaves of two tomatoes cultivars 
sprayed with fungicides and antibiotic, after inoculation with Xanthomonas perforans. </p>

<p>Treatment 
Santa Clara 
Gisele </p>

<p>b-1,3-glucanase 
Phenylalanine 
ammonia-lyase </p>

<p>Protease 
b-1,3-glucanase 
Phenylalanine 
ammonia-lyase </p>

<p>Protease </p>

<p>Acibenzolar-S-mehtyl 
312.86 a 
6.47 a 
9.96 a 
332.33 a 
6.24 a 
7.45 a </p>

<p>Piraclostrobin + metiram 
310.47 a 
6.50 a 
10.45 a 
226.57 a 
7.40 a 
6.98 a </p>

<p>Piraclostrobin 
229.86 b 
6.75 a 
10.75 a 
277.94 a 
7.31 a 
6.91 a </p>

<p>Copper oxychloride 
154.22 c 
6.92 a 
11.64 a 
155.01 b 
8.97 a 
8.06 a </p>

<p>Cop. oxych. + mancozeb 
154.22 c 
7.16 a 
12.26 a 
271.98 a 
9.51 a 
8.60 a </p>

<p>Fluazinam 
190.24 c 
8.35 a 
12.46 a 
160.37 b 
6.28 a 
7.59 a </p>

<p>Oxitetracicline 
112.06 c 
8.83 a 
13.21 a 
142.04 b 
6.10 a 
7.89 a </p>

<p>Control inoculated 
144.95 c 
9.13 a 
14.28 a 
145.06 b 
6.67 a 
6.41 a </p>

<p>Control non-inoculated 
148.78 c 
11.27 a 
17.69 a 
256.23 a 
6.59 a 
10.20 a </p>

<p>C.V. (%) 
17.43 
17.43 
27.35 
39.37 
36.48 
22.03 </p>

<p>*Means followed by the same letter do not differ by Scott-Knott test at 5% probability. </p>

<p>Table 2 -Area under the enzyme progression curve of peroxidase and polyphenol oxidase in leaves of two tomatoes cultivars sprayed with fungicides and 
antibiotic, after inoculation with Xanthomonas perforans. </p>

<p>Treatment 
Santa Clara 
Gisele </p>

<p>Peroxidase 
Polyphenol oxidase 
Peroxidase 
Polyphenol oxidase </p>

<p>Acibenzolar-S-methyl 
28.18 a* 
8.67 a 
44.88 a 
15.95 a </p>

<p>Piraclostrobin + metiram 
24.12 a 
7.32 a 
39.47 a 
11.62 b </p>

<p>Piraclostrobin 
20.61 b 
8.40 a 
42.66 a 
11.91 b </p>

<p>Copper oxychloride 
8.06 d 
5.34b 
21.38 c 
9.76 c </p>

<p>Cop. oxych. + mancozeb 
8.66 d 
4.25 b 
22.14 c 
9.14 c </p>

<p>Fluazinam 
14.13 c 
5.25 b 
31.56 b 
18.06 a </p>

<p>Oxitetracicline 
9.59 d 
5.38 b 
23.39 c 
4.98 c </p>

<p>Control inoculated 
11.77 c 
5.61 b 
16.39 c 
6.10 c </p>

<p>Control non-inoculated 
12.47 c 
6.30 b 
31.09 b 
14.52 a </p>

<p>C.V. (%) 
25.7 
16.6 
18.2 
29.6 </p>

<p>*Means followed by the same letter do not differ by Scott-Knott test at 5% probability. </p>

<p>quinones in the presence of oxygen. The expression of 
polyphenol oxidase may add an additional line of defense 
by protecting plants from pathogens and insects (Thipya-
pong and Steffens, 1997). According to Cutt and Klessig 
(1992), b-1,3-glucanases cause the release of glycosidic 
fragments not only from the pathogen itself but also from 
the walls of the plant cells, and these glycosidic fragments 
can elicit the host defense. 
Research involving ASM and Ecolife® showed the 
effectiveness of these products on the control of bacterial 
spot, caused by X. vesicatoria, on the Santa Cruz Kada to-
mato cultivar, and also in the activation of peroxidase, 
polyphenol oxidase, and b-1,3-glucanase. The Increased 
activity of these enzymes was correlated with induced re-
sistance of leaves of this tomato cultivar (Cavalcanti et al., 
2006a, b). Similar results were obtained by Itako et al. 
(2012b), who reported a reduction in disease symptoms and 
increased production of peroxidase, polyphenol oxidase, 
and b-1,3-glucanase on leaves of tomato AP 529 hybrid 
sprayed with ASM and pyraclostrobin. According to Luiz 
et al. (2012), there was a reduction in the severity of bacte-
rial spot caused by X. gardneri, and increased production of 
peroxidase, polyphenol oxidase, and glucanase in tomato 
leaves of Santa Cruz Kada sprayed with polysaccharides 
extracted from leaves of Aloe barbadensis. 
Research using pyraclostrobin in plant defense 
against some pathogens has been reported by Herms et al. 
(2002), who found an increased resistance of the tobacco 
plant to infection by the tobacco mosaic virus and Pseudo-
monas syringae pv. tabaci. In their data, salicylic acid and 
PR-1 proteins accumulated in the tissues of the treated 
plants, indicating that the pyraclostrobin activated defense 
mechanisms in the plants, in addition to its fungicidal ac-
tion. Vigo et al. (2012), on the other hand, found that ASM 
and pyraclostrobin caused increased levels of polyphenol 
oxidase, peroxidase, and total soluble proteins on the leaves 
of snap beans Bragança cultivar, suggesting their participa-
tion in the mechanisms of induction of resistance to com-
mon bacterial blight. These results were similar to those 
observed here for the tomato, and thus is an indication that 
these products, particularly the pyraclostrobin, induced 
mechanisms of resistance, since these mechanisms are well 
known for ASM. Thus, the action of ASM and pyraclos-
trobin on control of bacterial spot caused by X. perforans on 
leaves of the tomato Santa Clara and Gisele cultivars is as-
sociated with the production of enzymes related with resis-
tance induction. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This research was supported by FAPESP (The State 
of Sao Paulo Research Foundation), grant 2010/52702-0, 
and National Council for the Improvement of Higher Edu-
cation (CAPES). </p>



<p>Associate Editor: Raquel Silva Peixoto </p>

<p>All the content of the journal, except where otherwise noted, is licensed under a 
Creative Commons License CC BY-NC. </p>

<p>706 
Itako et al. </p>

</text></tei>