<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4785310" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives: To investigate if language spoken at home </p>

<p>mediates the relationship between ethnicity and 
doctor-patient communication for South Asian and 
White British patients. </p>

<p>Methods: We conducted secondary analysis of patient </p>

<p>experience survey data collected from 5870 patients 
across 25 English general practices. Mixed effect linear 
regression estimated the difference in composite 
general practitioner-patient communication scores 
between White British and South Asian patients, 
controlling for practice, patient demographics and 
patient language. </p>

<p>Results: There was strong evidence of an association </p>

<p>between doctor-patient communication scores and 
ethnicity. South Asian patients reported scores 
averaging 3.0 percentage points lower (scale of 0-100) 
than White British patients (95% CI −4.9 to −1.1, 
p=0.002). This difference reduced to 1.4 points (95% 
CI −3.1 to 0.4) after accounting for speaking a non-
English language at home; respondents who spoke a 
non-English language at home reported lower scores 
than English-speakers (adjusted difference 3.3 points, 
95% CI −6.4 to −0.2). </p>

<p>Conclusions: South Asian patients rate </p>

<p>communication lower than White British patients within 
the same practices and with similar demographics. Our 
analysis further shows that this disparity is largely 
mediated by language. </p>

<p>experience has been increasingly valued as 
an important outcome for medical care, in 
part due to its association with other aspects 
of the quality of care. </p>

<p>1 2 </p>

<p>Communication is an important compo-
nent of patient experience, and has been 
shown to influence healthcare access, health 
outcomes and patient satisfaction. 
3 Doctor-
patient communication is key in either 
enabling or preventing the development of 
trusting, empathetic interpersonal relation-
ships, the exchange of information and col-
laborative decision-making. 
4 However, there 
are differences in doctor-patient communi-
cation across populations. A recent study in 
the UK found strong evidence to conclude 
that South Asian and Chinese patients report 
lower ratings of physician communication 
than White British patients in primary care </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ This study builds upon previous research to 
determine whether or not English-proficiency 
influences the association between ethnicity and 
doctor-patient communication ratings. 
▪ This study is made possible by collecting infor-
mation on the language patients normally speak 
at home, which is not routinely collected in 
patient experience surveys. 
▪ Questionnaires were in English, limiting respon-
dents to those who were able to complete a 
written questionnaire in this language. 
▪ Data protection issues prohibited sociodemo-
graphic data on non-responders from being col-
lected, so we were unable to assess the 
representativeness of our sample. 
▪ Small sample numbers and colinearity between 
language, ethnicity and birthplace limited the 
power to disentangle the relative effects of these 
factors and reduced the precision of the effect 
estimates. </p>

<p>Brodie K, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010042. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010042 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>settings. 
5 Around half of the difference in scores was 
explained by the concentration of South Asian and 
Chinese patients in low-scoring primary care practices. 
The remaining difference may arise either because 
South Asian and Chinese patients rate the same care 
lower, or because they receive lower quality care: 
however, the effect of language on experiences of care 
was not explored. 
It is necessary to evaluate language with communica-
tion because communication includes and is highly 
influenced by language. In the healthcare field, the 
term 'language-concordance' describes patients and 
physicians sharing proficiency in the same language, 
and 'language-discordance' describes a lack of profi-
ciency in a shared language. 
6 Compared to White 
British patients, South Asian patients frequently report 
poorer doctor communication (regarding offering time, 
showing care and concern, questioning the patient, 
listening, explaining, and involving patient in decision-
making); however, when language-concordant consulta-
tions are available to Bangladeshi or Pakistani patients, 
there is no longer a difference in these doctor-patient 
communication scores. 
7 This suggests that language-
concordance influences patient perception of the 
quality of doctors' communication, possibly due to 
improved verbal and cultural understanding and trust. 
In the UK, immigration rates have risen to historically 
high levels, according to the Parliament's Migration 
Statistics report in 2015, thereby increasing the size of 
the population with limited English proficiency. 
8 The 
2011 Census noted that 11% of the non-UK born popu-
lation in the UK report being unable to speak English 
well. 
9 This population is of particular concern for 
language-discordant consultations, potentially inhibiting 
access to high-quality healthcare. 
10 However, it is import-
ant to note that sizeable proportions of many minority 
ethnic groups-long established in their country of resi-
dence or not-report a lack of language proficiency in 
the official languages. 
9 For example, among UK-born 
individuals identifying as Bangladeshi, Pakistani, or 
Indian, a respective 30%, 23% and 14% report not 
speaking English well or at all, despite the fact that 67%, 
61%, and 54% of the respective populations have lived 
in the UK for at least 10 years. 
11 Without substantial 
developments for incorporating culturally sensitive, 
multilingual healthcare training and delivery, this 
growing population faces major challenges accessing, 
navigating and utilising healthcare services. 
This study builds on previous evidence on the differ-
ences in patient experience across ethnic groups by 
investigating how language influences the association 
between ethnicity and patients' rating of doctor-patient 
communication. We focus on South Asians and White 
British as previous research in the UK found that South 
Asians, one of the largest ethnic minority populations in 
England, 
12 report notably lower patient satisfaction and 
experience than White British patients. 
5 Choosing to 
study the largest ethnic minority group provides the </p>

<p>largest sample of patients, increases the power of the 
study, and reduces the likelihood of chance influencing 
the results. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Study design 
We conducted a secondary complete-case analysis of 
data from a cross-sectional patient survey from a strati-
fied, random sample of general practices in Cornwall, 
Devon, Bristol, Bedfordshire, Cambridgeshire and North 
London. Full details are reported elsewhere. 
13 Based on 
results from the 2009/2010 English National GP Patient 
Survey, 15 practices in the lowest quarter for doctors' 
interpersonal communication scores, five practices in 
the 37.5th-62.5th centile (the middle quarter) and five 
in the highest quarter were recruited. In order to be eli-
gible for the study, the general practices needed to have 
at least two registered general practitioners (GPs) 
working a minimum of four sessions per week (40% of a 
full-time equivalent), excluding trainees and short-term 
locums. The random sampling of practices was stratified 
based on communication score banding, general prac-
tice size, deprivation index from postcode and geograph-
ical location. 
Approval for the survey and subsequent studies was 
granted on the 28 January 2011 by the South West 2 
Research Ethics Committee (ref: 09/H0202/65). Patient 
consent to participate in the study was indicated by the 
return of the completed questionnaire. </p>

<p>Data collection 
Data were collected between November 2011 and June 
2013. Electronic medical records for each participating 
practice were searched to identify adult face-to-face con-
sultations with GPs within the previous 3 weeks. Patients 
suffering from a terminal illness were excluded. 
Additionally, patients whose GP identified them as 
having reduced mental capacity were excluded. The 
remaining patients were mailed the study questionnaire 
-a version of the national GP Patient Survey (https:// 
gp-patient.co.uk)-amended to reflect on a specific 
face-to-face consultation that physician identified in an 
accompanying letter. The survey is included in online 
supplementary figure S1. Questionnaires were sent in 
cycles (involving iterative identification, screening and 
mail-outs) until at least 50 completed questionnaires 
were received for each participating GP or until three 
cycles had been completed. One reminder was sent to 
patients who did not respond within 3 weeks. Responses 
were accepted up to 100 days after the initial mail out. </p>

<p>Measure of doctor-patient communication 
The study questionnaire covered continuity and inter-
personal aspects of care, as well as questions about socio-
demographic information including age, sex, ethnicity, 
self-rated health and language spoken most often at 
home. The primary outcome evaluated was patient-</p>



<p>Brodie K, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010042. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010042 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>reported doctor communication indicated by a compos-
ite score for seven aspects of physician communication 
(based on Q22 in online supplementary figure S1), 
including providing sufficient time to the patient, asking 
about patient symptoms, listening, explaining tests and 
treatments, involving patient in decision-making, demon-
strating care and concern, taking patient problems ser-
iously. These aspects of physician communication have 
been validated as robust and reliable quality indicators 
used by in the UK national GP Patient Survey, as well as 
several previous studies. 
5 7 13 The doctor-patient com-
munication score was defined as the mean rating of all 
informative responses. Each aspect of doctor-patient 
communication was measured on the same response 
scale ranging from 'very good' to 'very poor' with inter-
mediate response options of 'good,' 'neither good nor 
poor' and 'poor.' If at least four of the seven questions 
had informative responses, these ordinal data points 
were linearly rescaled from 0 to 100 (very poor=0, 
poor=25, etc) then averaged to provide this score. 
Responses of 'Doesn't apply' were considered 
uninformative. </p>

<p>Language spoken at home 
Information on language spoken at home was gathered 
by a question asking, 'What language do you speak most 
often at home?' with possible responses including 
English or a free-response section to specify another lan-
guage. If the patient checked the box for speaking 
English or wrote English anywhere in the free-response 
box, they were identified as English-speaking. All others 
responses were categorised as non-English speaking. 
Given that the patients included in this analysis either 
identified as White British or South Asian, the vast 
majority of the non-English languages were South Asian 
languages. However, all patients in these two ethnic 
groups were included regardless of the language they 
spoke in order to reduce potential selection bias and to 
maximise the generalisability of the findings. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Only patients who self-identified as White British or 
South Asian, provided information on age, gender, self-
rated health, birthplace, and language and gave inform-
ative response to the relevant outcomes (Q12, 22-24 in 
online supplementary figure S1) were included in the 
analysis. This inclusion criterion represented the largest 
ethnic groups-South Asian and White British-to 
provide the largest power to the study. Using univariable 
linear regression, we examined crude associations 
between each of the covariates and doctor-patient com-
munication. We then modelled the composite communi-
cation score using three multivariable linear regression 
models. All models included a random effect for prac-
tice to account for the fact that South Asian patients 
may cluster in lower performing practices. The first 
model's variables included age, gender, self-rated health, 
and ethnicity, all previously shown to be associated with </p>

<p>patient experience. Because the patient survey did not 
collect information on occupation, this could not be 
included in the model. The second model augmented 
this to include language spoken most often at home 
(hereafter referred to as 'language') to determine if the 
effect of ethnicity on the patient experience was partially 
attributed to language. Lastly, the third model included 
the model 1 variables, language and birthplace, dichoto-
mised as UK or non-UK. Language (English vs 
non-English speaking) and birthplace (UK vs non-UK) 
were binary variables in order to maximise the power. 
CIs and p values were based on bootstrapping clustered 
by practice with 500 repetitions to account for the 
skewed distribution of doctor-patient communication 
scores. 
All analyses were executed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata/IC</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.0</rs>. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Response rates, patient demographics 
Of the 15 172 questionnaires sent to patients, 7721 
patients-seen by 105 GPs across 25 practices-
responded. The overall response rate was 51% and 
ranged from 24% to 81% across GPs. Of these 
responses, 6716 (87%) questionnaires had complete, 
informative responses for at least four of the seven 
doctor-patient communication indicators as well as for 
all of the other questions analysed. The number of 
informative responses ranged from 107 to 589 per prac-
tice. White British individuals made up 83% (n=5558) of 
the respondents, and the largest non-White population 
was South Asian, making 5% of the sample population. 
Figure 1 illustrates how the 5870 patients who identified 
as either White British or South Asian were included in 
the analysis. 
The demographics of these 5870 patients with com-
plete, informative responses are described in table 1. In 
this sample, the largest proportions of responses were 
from females (61.9%), individuals aged between 55 and 
84 years (59%), and patients in good to excellent health 
(67%). Of all 5870 patients, 312 (5%) identified as 
South Asian or Asian British (hereafter referred to as 
South Asian), and 209 (4%) patients spoke non-English 
languages at home, which are summarised in table 2. Of 
the 312 South Asians, 173 (55%) did not speak English 
as their primary language at home, of which 132 (76%) 
specified primarily speaking one of four languages: 
Punjabi, Bengali, Urdu or Gujarati. The languages pri-
marily spoken at home by White British respondents are 
shown in online supplementary table S1. </p>

<p>Main findings 
The univariable linear regression models provided 
strong evidence ( p&lt;0.0001) that physician communica-
tion scores crudely varied across ethnicity, birthplace, 
language, self-reported health and age groups. The 
median doctor-patient communication score rated by 
White British was 100 and IQR of 78-100, and the South </p>

<p>Brodie K, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010042. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010042 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Asian group had a median score of 86 and IQR of 75-
100. There was no evidence of an association between 
physician communication and gender ( p=0.21) or pres-
ence of a long-standing emotional or psychological dis-
order ( p=0.46) (table 3). 
The results of the three multivariable linear regression 
models used to evaluate associations between independ-
ent and dependent variables are summarised in table 4. 
The first multivariable linear regression model investi-
gated the association between doctor-patient communi-
cation and the exposure variables including practice, 
age, gender, self-reported health and ethnicity. There 
was strong evidence ( p=0.002) of an association between 
patient ethnicity and patient-reported doctor communi-
cation score. On average, South Asians rated doctor-
patient communication 3.0 percentage points below 
(95% CI −4.9 to −1.1) White British patients (model 1). 
The second model additionally controlled for languages 
spoken at home. In model 2, there was some evidence 
( p=0.04) of an association between language and 
doctor-patient 
communication 
ratings 
with 
non-English-speakers reporting doctor-patient commu-
nications scores 3.3 percentage points lower (95% CI </p>

<p>−6.4 to −0.2) than English-speaking patients. By 
accounting for language, we also found the average dif-
ference between South Asian and White British scores of 
doctor-patient communication decreased from 3.0 per-
centage points (found in model 1) to 1.4 points (95% 
CI −3.1 to 0.4, p=0.13) found in model 2. Following this 
decrease, the difference was no longer statistically signifi-
cant. This change would imply that language appears to 
account for around half of the observed difference 
between South Asian and White British patients' ratings 
of doctor communication. When ethnicity, language and 
birthplace were all included (model 3), there was only 
weak evidence of an association between language and 
doctor-patient communication rating ( p=0.07) with no 
evidence of an association with ethnicity or birthplace. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSION 
Discussion 
We have presented a secondary analysis of survey data 
showing an association between patient ethnicity and 
patient-reported doctor communication score, with 
South Asian's ratings of doctor-patient communication </p>

<p>Figure 1 Questionnaire responses included in analysis. </p>

<p>Table 1 Demographic profile of 5870 patients in analysis 
sample </p>

<p>N 
Per cent </p>

<p>Gender 
Female 
3633 
61.9 
Male 
2237 
38.1 
Age 
18-24 
167 
2.8 
25-34 
511 
8.7 
35-44 
665 
11.3 
45-54 
837 
14.3 
55-64 
1226 
20.9 
65-74 
1292 
22.0 
75-84 
947 
16.1 
85 or older 
225 
3.8 
Self-reported health 
Excellent 
402 
6.9 
Very good 
1555 
26.5 
Good 
1955 
33.3 
Fair 
1417 
24.1 
Poor 
541 
9.2 
Long-standing psychological or emotional condition 
Not present 
5325 
90.7 
Present 
545 
9.3 
Ethnicity 
White British 
5558 
94.7 
South Asian or Asian British 
312 
5.3 
Language spoken most often at home 
English 
5661 
96.4 
Other language 
209 
3.6 
Birthplace 
Born in the UK 
5404 
92.1 
Not born in the UK 
466 
7.9 </p>



<p>Brodie K, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010042. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010042 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>falling below those of White British patients. When add-
itionally accounting for language spoken at home, the 
average difference between South Asian and White </p>

<p>British scores of doctor-patient communication 
decreased, suggesting that language appears to account 
for around half of the difference between South Asian </p>

<p>Table 2 Languages spoken most often at home by South Asian Respondents (N=312) </p>

<p>Language n </p>

<p>Percentage of 
non-EPL 
Respondents </p>

<p>% of all South 
Asian 
Responses 
Language 
n </p>

<p>Percentage of 
non-EPL 
Respondents </p>

<p>Percentage of all 
South Asian 
Responses </p>

<p>Total English Speaking South Asians 
139 
-
44.6 
Total Non-English Speaking South Asians 
173 100 
55.4 
Total South Asian Respondents 
312 
-
100 
Arabic 
1 
0.6 
0.3 
Kyrgyz 
1 
0.6 
0.3 
Bengali 
44 25.4 
14.1 
Malayalam 
3 
1.7 
1.0 
Farsi 
8 
4.6 
2.6 
Pashto 
3 
1.7 
1.0 
Filipino 
2 
1.2 
0.6 
Portuguese 
1 
0.6 
0.3 
French 
1 
0.6 
0.3 
Punjabi 
47 
27.2 
15.1 
German 
1 
0.6 
0.3 
Sinhalese 
3 
1.7 
1.0 
Gujarati 
16 
9.2 
5.1 
Sylheti 
1 
0.6 
0.3 
Hindi 
4 
2.3 
1.3 
Tagalog 
1 
0.6 
0.3 
Indian 
2 
1.2 
0.6 
Tamil 
2 
1.2 
0.6 
Kannada 
1 
0.6 
0.3 
Urdu 
25 
14.4 
8.0 
Kurdish 
5 
2.9 
1.6 
Vietnamese 
1 
0.6 
0.3 </p>

<p>EPL, English as Primary Language Spoken at Home. </p>

<p>Table 3 Differences in physician communication scores (scaled from 0 to 100) across demographic groups from univariable 
linear regression </p>

<p>95% CI 
Variable 
Mean difference 
Lower bound 
Upper bound 
p Value* </p>

<p>Gender 
Male (reference) 
-
-
-
0.21 
Female 
−0.57 
−1.46 
0.32 
Age 
18-24 
−6.15 
−8.86 
−3.45 
&lt;0.0001 
25-34 
−5.12 
−6.85 
−3.40 
35-44 
−4.09 
−5.67 
−2.51 
45-54 
−1.68 
−3.14 
−0.21 
55-64 (reference) 
-
-
-
65-74 
1.64 
0.33 
2.94 
75-84 
2.50 
1.09 
3.92 
85 or older 
1.99 
−0.39 
4.37 
Ethnicity 
British (reference) 
-
-
-
&lt;0.0001 
South Asian 
−6.27 
−8.19 
−4.35 
Primary language spoken at home 
English (reference) 
-
-
-
&lt;0.0001 
Other language 
−7.15 
−9.49 
−4.83 
Birthplace 
UK 
-
-
-
&lt;0.0001 
Not the UK 
−4.34 
−5.93 
−2.74 
Self-reported health 
Excellent (reference) 
-
-
-
&lt;0.0001 
Very good 
−0.41 
−2.26 
1.44 
Good 
−2.95 
−4.76 
−1.13 
Fair 
−2.96 
−4.83 
−1.09 
Poor 
−1.98 
−4.16 
0.19 
Longstanding emotional or psychological condition 
Yes 
−0.57 
−2.06 
0.92 
0.46 
No 
-
-
-</p>

<p>*p Values shown for joint tests of variables. </p>

<p>Brodie K, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010042. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010042 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>and White British patients' ratings of doctor 
communication. 
Our study's findings were consistent with previous 
studies showing that, in England, minority ethnic 
groups, particularly Asian populations, have poorer 
patient experiences. 
5 14 Language may be a key driver of 
ethnic differences in patient-reported doctor communi-
cation, for minority ethnic groups with poor English pro-
ficiency often have less information provided to them 
and poorer information recall thereby influencing their 
experience, 
15 and minority ethnic populations have 
higher ratings of physician communication when pro-
vided language-concordant consultations. 
7 Additionally, 
physicians have been found to be less likely to respond 
to non-English speakers' comments and used less 
emotive communication when speaking to those with 
poor language proficiency, 
15 16 which may help explain 
why we found that primarily non-English speakers report 
poorer doctor-patient communication. Studies found 
language, more than ethnicity, determined patient 
experience with doctor communication; however, this 
may have been partly attributed to reduced available 
time due to the time necessary for translation. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations 
Lyratzopoulos' study analysed data from the national GP 
Patient Survey and found that South Asian and Chinese 
patients reported lower ratings of physician communica-
tion than White British patients in primary care settings. 
However, the survey did not gather any data on patients' 
language use or proficiency. Therefore, this study was 
able to build on Lyratzopoulos' study, for one remaining 
question posed by the authors was whether or not 
English-proficiency influences the association found in 
their study. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Questionnaires were in English, limiting respondents 
to those who were able to complete a written question-
naire in this language. The result of this exclusion is most 
likely a bias such that we underestimate the true differ-
ence in scores across ethnic and language groups. It is 
worth noting that while the national GP Patient Survey-</p>

<p>on which this questionnaire was based-is available in 13 
languages other than English, in 2014/2015 only 0.001% 
of respondents chose to complete the survey in an alter-
native language (Ipsos MORI January 2015 Report). 
Therefore, providing questionnaires in additional lan-
guages is unlikely to address these selection bias issues 
especially given this proportion electing to complete 
surveys in other languages is far less than the 1.3% of the 
entire population in England and Wales that reports not 
speaking English well and 0.3% that does not speak any 
English, according to the 2011 Census. Additionally, the 
language in which the consultation was conducted was 
not known. Therefore, we are unable to identify 
language-discordant consultations, which other studies 
have found to be associated with poorer patient ratings of 
doctor-patient communication. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Data protection issues meant sociodemographic data 
on non-responders were not available, so we were unable 
to assess the representativeness of our sample. However, 
by adjusting for age, gender and health status, we should 
account for major differences. Lastly, there was limited 
power to disentangle the relative effects of ethnicity, 
birthplace and language especially due to small sample 
numbers and collinearity between the three variables. 
Small samples also reduced the precision of the effect 
estimates. </p>

<p>Practice implications 
Given that effective doctor communication has been 
associated with improved health outcomes, symptoms 
control, and patient adherence, this difference in ratings 
of doctor communication across ethnic and language 
groups likely parallels differences in health outcomes 
across these groups. 
17 18 Our study shows that language, 
being a key driver of ethnic differences in patient experi-
ence with doctor communication, should be a focus of 
institutional change to best improve patient experience 
and outcomes. In order to develop effective measures to 
improve patient experience of physician communica-
tion, one must consider what our definition and meas-
urement of 'language' within surveys, such as these, </p>

<p>Table 4 Mean differences in doctor-patient communication from Multivariable Linear Regression (variable scaled from 0 to 
100) </p>

<p>Mean difference (95% CI) 
Model 1 
p Value 
Model 2 
p Value 
Model 3 
p Value </p>

<p>Ethnicity 
White British 
0.002 
0.133 
0.458 
South Asian 
−2.99 
(−4.89 to −1.10) </p>

<p>−1.35 
(−3.11 to 0.41) </p>

<p>−0.77 
(−2.80 to 1.26) 
Language 
English 
0.040 
0.072 
Other 
−3.26 
(−6.38 to −0.15) </p>

<p>−2.90 
(−6.06 to 0.25) 
Birthplace 
UK 
0.343 
Non-UK 
−0.98 
(−2.99 to 1.04) </p>

<p>In addition to variables shown, all models also adjusted for age, gender and self-reported health and included a random effect for practice. </p>



<p>Brodie K, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010042. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010042 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>actually represents. Figure 2 summarises how language 
might represent a variety of different factors. By identify-
ing these different manifestations of language, we may 
start to focus better on how to reduce differences in 
doctor-patient communication ratings across language 
groups. 
First, language spoken at home may represent a 
simple 
measure 
of 
the 
patient's 
level 
of 
English-proficiency or ability to communicate with the 
physician. Thus, poor patient satisfaction and experience 
are likely to be consequences of an inability to effectively 
articulate one's emotions and symptoms, as well as ques-
tions necessary to better understand medical conditions. 
In response, a possible solution is to increase the multi-
lingual workforce, improve access and availability of 
interpreting services and refine interpreting techniques. 
Second, beyond basic language proficiency, language 
may be a marker of cultural differences in behaviour, 
including communication, information sharing and 
evaluation by the patient and the physician. Researchers 
hypothesise that cultural practices and behaviours can 
lead to differences in patient satisfaction and experience 
ratings, 
15 19 20 and that physicians have implicit biases 
and differential attitudes that influence the evaluation 
and care for patients. 
21 Furthermore, studies have found 
patients report greater satisfaction with language-
concordant consultations due to better ease of commu-
nication, greater empathy and higher probability of the 
physician having a basic understanding of their cultural 
health beliefs. 
7 22 23 These cultural beliefs influence 
one's interaction with the healthcare system and there-
fore contribute to differences in experience. For 
example, some cultural groups show respect by refrain-
ing from asking questions, which can result in patients 
feeling that some of their concerns have not been 
addressed. 
24 Additionally, cultural reporting tendencies 
affect a patient's evaluation of the healthcare experi-
ence. 
24-26 For example, Chinese patients were found to 
mark moderate responses more frequently than extreme 
responses, 
26 meaning differences in responses may not 
reflect actual differences in care. If language is a marker </p>

<p>of cultural norms and expectations, patient experience 
could be improved by hiring minority ethnic physicians 
who could better understand these behavioural differ-
ences. Additionally, redesigning medical education and 
mid-career training would help to further develop inter-
cultural communication skills and cultural competency 
to interact appropriately and communicate effectively 
with other ethnic groups. The term 'cultural compe-
tence' was developed recognising differences in patient 
experience across ethnic groups to define and refine 
medical practices tailored towards minority ethnic 
groups. Cultural competence requires career-long self-
appraisal to reduce the imbalance of power between the 
patient and physician and develop and maintain mutu-
ally respectful partnerships. The process involves collab-
oration with patients, communities and colleagues. 
Third, if language spoken at home is a marker of 
acculturation, then our findings may reflect systematic 
differences in cultural expectations of doctor-patient 
consultations rather than direct problems with commu-
nication within a consultation. If patient experience is 
poor due to misunderstandings about how the system 
works and what it can and cannot provide, then health 
education programmes could reduce these unmet 
expectations by informing the population about avail-
able healthcare services and options. By more effectively 
dispersing health system information to targeted popula-
tions, the health systems could improve access and 
clarify the responsibilities of the physicians and health-
care system. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
Having presented several possible interventions, the 
most effective approach to reduce the gap in patient 
experience across ethnic and language groups will likely 
require some combination of all of these solutions: pro-
viding more language-concordant physicians, acknow-
ledging and responding to cultural differences in 
communication, and educating patients about the 
healthcare system resources and responsibilities. 
Inevitably, aspects of these would require major system-
wide investment and overhaul, and would require suffi-
cient evidence of effectiveness and acceptability. 
Additionally, all of these potential methods of improving 
patient experience are based on the assumption that 
there is thorough understanding of the number, 
characteristics, language proficiency, preferences, health 
needs, and expectations of minority ethnic groups and 
the interplay between these factors. Currently, not all of 
this information is well known. Further research is 
needed to study the complex interaction of ethnicity, 
language, religion and acculturation. As immigration 
rates continue to rise, it will be increasingly important 
for countries to actively collect more information on 
patient characteristics to better understand the range of 
their patients' cultural backgrounds to be able to deliver 
more patient-centred care. Only after doing so can we </p>

<p>Figure 2 Language as a mediator between ethnicity and 
patient experience. </p>

<p>Brodie K, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010042. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010042 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>begin to develop effective policies and programmes to 
reduce these differences in patient experience. </p>

<p>Twitter Follow Jenni Burt at @jenniaburt </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors thank the patients, practice managers, 
general practitioners, and other staff of the general practices who kindly 
agreed to participate in the survey from which this analysis was derived, and 
without whom the survey would not have been possible. The authors thank 
also go to Natasha Elmore, Antoinette Davey, Emily Taylor, Jenny Newbould, 
Emma Whitton, Amy Gratton, Charlotte Paddison, and Dawn Swancutt for 
invaluable help with study set-up, practice recruitment, data collection, and 
data entry during the conduct of the survey. The authors particular 
acknowledge Professor Martin Roland at the University of Cambridge Centre 
for Health Services Research and Professor John Campbell at the University 
of Exeter Medical School, Principal Investigators of the programme of work 
on patient experience for which the survey was conducted, and who gave 
permission for us to conduct a secondary analysis of the data for this study. </p>

<p>Contributors KB conducted the statistical analyses and literature review and 
drafted the manuscript. GA designed and interpreted the statistical analysis. 
JB and GA designed the research question and critically revised the 
manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding The work was conducted as part of an MPhil course, and involved 
secondary analysis of survey data designed and collected by a collaboration 
between the Cambridge Centre for Health Services Research at the University of 
Cambridge and the University of Exeter Medical School. KB was not employed 
by the University of Cambridge, nor did she receive any funding at any time 
during the project. GA and JB were funded for the original NIHR grant which 
funded the original survey but received no funding for this specific work. All 
authors read and approved the final manuscript. The survey on which this 
secondary analysis was based was funded by a National Institute for Health 
Research Programme Grant for Applied Research (NIHR PGfAR) programme 
(RP-PG-0608-10050). The views expressed are those of the author(s) and not 
necessarily those of the NHS, the NIHR, or the Department of Health. </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Ethics approval South West 2 Research Ethics Committee (ref: 09/H0202/65). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Brodie K, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010042. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010042 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>