<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4588797" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:43+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>How to cite the article: 
Walimbe H, Kontham U, Bijle MN, Wani V, Nankar M, Muchandi S. 
Knowledge, attitude and practice of devitalizing agents: A survey of 
general dental practitioners. J Int Oral Health 2015;7(8):86-88. 
Abstract: 
Background: This study aimed to analyze knowledge, attitude 
and practice of general dental practitioners regarding the use of 
devitalizing agents in their respective practice. 
Materials and Methods: A total of 100 practicing general dentists 
were randomly chosen as per the list of practitioners available to 
local state association. The questionnaire was designed to cover 
general information of the participating dentist and concerning 
different aspects of devitalizing agents. The collected data was 
subjected to statistical analysis using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS (Statistical Package for Social Sciences</rs>) version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">17.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Statistics</rs>, Chicago, Illinois, 
USA). Descriptive statistics was drawn with respective percentages 
to have a comparative overview. 
Results: The response rate was 97%, of which the effective and 
complete replies received were 77% (75). 56% respondents 
used paraformaldehyde containing pastes. Majority of general 
practitioners (61%) did not observe any post-operative 
complication following the use of devitalising agent. 33% (25) of 
the respondents were not aware of the complications of devitalizing 
agents. 
Conclusion: Thus, it can be concluded that general dental 
practitioners in Pune and Nashik district of Maharashtra, India do </p>

<p>use pulp devitalizing agents in spite of possessing knowledge related 
to the complications. </p>

<p>2   Pulpal inflammation as the sequel of dental caries figures a 
significant component of endodontic diseases. Many general 
dental practitioners find management of the inflamed pulp 
challenging in their routine dental practice. To handle such 
challenges, clinicians use devitalizing agents where dental 
anesthesia fails to be effective. The devitalizing agents compose 
of formaldehyde, cresol, paraformaldehyde, and arsenic 
compounds. These agents are delineated as harmful to the 
patients posing facts being highly toxic, allergic, carcinogenic 
and mutagenic/genotoxic. 
3,4 In addition, there are reported 
cases that support the verity and proves the detrimental effects 
of agents. The reports range from gingival to the alveolar 
necrosis. 
5-7 In spite of the disadvantages noted, general dental 
clinicians are seen to use these products in their routine practice 
as per published literature from few countries. </p>

<p>8,9   With the advent of information being available at fingertips in 
today's era due to the accessibility of data on internet and online 
databases, it is very easy for a clinicians to keep themselves 
updated with the current concepts. Thus, it can be hypothesized 
that general dental practitioners are benefitting to update their 
knowledge with current technology in hand. The same also 
applies with updating of knowledge in respect to devitalizing 
agents since it forms a major part of dental practice. However, 
there is no latest reported literature available, which speaks 
about the behavior of general dental practitioners in relation to 
devitalizing agents considering the hypothesis aforementioned. </p>



<p>Journal of International Oral Health 2015; 7(8):86-88 
Devitalizing agents in general dental practice … Walimbe H et al </p>

<p>Thus, this study aims to analyze knowledge, attitude and 
practice of general dental practitioners regarding the use of 
devitalizing agents in their respective practice. Keeping into 
account the reach limitation of contributors, the survey was 
limited to Pune and Nashik district of Maharashtra, India. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
100 practicing general dentists were randomly selected as 
per the list of practitioners available to local state association. 
The questionnaire was designed to cover general information 
of the participating dentist and concerning different aspects 
of devitalising agents. General information was in place to 
record the qualification of the practitioner, location/address 
for correspondence, experience -years of practice and whether 
the practitioner is a part of teaching faculty in a dental school. </p>

<p>Following collection of general information, questions 
formulated regarding devitalising agents were handed over to 
the professionals comprising 13 questions. These questions 
were subjected to internal and external validity by respective 
subject experts and persons known in the state of the art. 
The questions inquired as use of devitalising agents, type 
of agent used, purpose of use, frequency of use, usage in 
deciduous or permanent dentition, post-operative problems 
experienced (if any), frequency of the complications 
experienced, duration of use of devitalising agent within the 
tooth, clinically observed changes in the tooth, reasons for 
usage and awareness regarding side effects/complications 
after use of devitalising agents. </p>

<p>The participants of the survey were given prior instructions 
necessary to fill the questionnaire. The questions were major 
in multiple choice questions, and the respondents were given 
the freedom to choose one or more suitable choices that meet 
their nature. </p>

<p>The collected data was subjected to statistical analysis using 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS (Statistical Package for Social Sciences</rs>) version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">17.0</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM Statistics</rs>, Chicago, Illinois, USA). Descriptive statistics 
was drawn with respective percentages to have a comparative 
overview. </p>

<p>Results 
The response rate was 97%, of which the effective and complete 
replies received 77% (75); since 22 practitioners did not 
use devitalizing agents in their clinical practice. However, 
preliminary data was in receipt from all 97 respondents and 
thereby the demographic and professional results of the 
respondents was drawn. </p>

<p>37% (36) of the respondents had 1-5 years of professional 
experience whereas 16% (16) of the respondents had more 
than 16 years of work experience. Majority of the participants 
(82%) were not attached to a teaching institution. </p>

<p>36% of the respondents were using formocresol as a 
devitalising agent. 56% respondents used paraformaldehyde 
containing pastes. Very few respondents were using arsenic 
devitalising fiber, 3% and 5% sodium hypochlorite, phenol 
and camphorated mono-chloro phenol (Table 1). However, 
the frequency of use amongst the majority was very less with 
its maximum use in permanent teeth as compared to primary 
teeth. 47% (35) of the respondents kept the devitalising agent 
inside the tooth for 3-5 days, whereas the practitioners reported 
the stay for 7-15 days as well. 52% (39) of the respondents 
obtained only partial devitalisation with use of the devitalising 
agents. </p>

<p>Majority of general practitioners (61%) did not observe any 
post-operative complication following the use of devitalising 
agent. However, the remaining respondents reported severe 
post-operative pain 24% (18) as the most frequently observed 
complication. Few others noted complications like swelling 5% 
(4) and gingival necrosis 7% (5). 33% (25) of the respondents 
were not aware of the complications of devitalizing agents. The 
remaining respondents were aware of possible complications 
like necrosis of gingiva (43%), necrosis of bone (25%) and 
severe pain (19%)(Table 2). </p>

<p>Discussion 
Until date, there are few studies 
8,10 reported on the aspect of 
endodontic therapy, in general dental practice. The response 
rate for the literature published was approximately 45% 
average, until date. However, this study has a better response 
rate since the survey was done in person rather using any other 
technological means. </p>

<p>When compared to other research, 
8,10 the respondents 
using devitalizing agents in practice were much higher, in 
spite of maximum having knowledge related to the existing 
complications. The use of aldehyde containing agents was </p>

<p>Table 1: Types of devitalizing agents used by general dental 
practitioners. </p>

<p>Devitalising agent 
Number of 
doctors (n=75) </p>

<p>Percentage </p>

<p>Formocresol 
27 
36 
Paraformaldehyde containing pastes 
42 
56 
Others 
6 
8 
Total 
75 
100 </p>

<p>Table 2: Awareness of side effects/complications of use of devitalising 
agent in study group. </p>

<p>Side effects/ 
complications </p>

<p>Number of 
doctors (n=75) </p>

<p>Percentage </p>

<p>Severe pain 
14 
18.67 
Necrosis of gingiva 
32 
42.67 
Necrosis of bone 
19 
25.33 
Others 
4 
5.33 
No 
25 
33.33 </p>



<p>Journal of International Oral Health 2015; 7(8):86-88 
Devitalizing agents in general dental practice … Walimbe H et al </p>

<p>more in the present study than other studies where they have 
used the recently available devitalizing agents like arsenic based 
compounds. This could be rationalized on the basis of dental 
education sought by the practitioners. Although, majority of 
practitioners belong to practice group of 1-5 years, the same 
could have confounding factors with respect to their education 
pursued till establishment of practice. The elimination of same 
was not possible within the aegis of the study. The reasons 
reported by the practitioners for use of agents as fore-stated 
is probably due to the fact that these agents are perceived 
to be quick and painless in action, eliminating the necessity 
of administration of local anesthesia thus saving time and 
maximising patient cooperation. For pediatric patients, reasons 
for use of such agents were the difficulty they face in managing 
behavior of a child in administering local anesthesia. This 
projects the use of devitalizing agents overruled the importance 
of local anesthesia in endodontic treatment. </p>

<p>The fact that more than half of the respondents obtained only 
partial devitalisation of the pulp suggests that the action of the 
devitalising agent is unpredictable, hence cannot be completely 
relied upon. Majority of dental practitioners did not observe 
post-operative complications, but few did. However, the 
existence of literature 
5-7 and the intensity of harm the patients 
experienced to date cannot be ignored. In addition, few 
respondents in the present study also observed post-operative 
complications in variety. </p>

<p>Conclusion 
Thus, it can be concluded that general dental practitioners in 
Pune and Nashik district of Maharashtra, India do use pulp 
devitalizing agents in spite of possessing knowledge related to 
the complications. This arises the need today to establish better 
understanding of the subject by practitioners in the region 
through their involvement in continuing dental education </p>

<p>programs of the title. However, it is also recommended that a 
similar study to be carried out considering a larger sample and 
covering major area which could represent national knowledge, 
attitude and practice of general dental practitioners regarding 
the use of devitalizing agents. </p>



</text></tei>