<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4345972" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: This study aimed to explore the influence of two genetic polymorphisms of the 
5-hydroxytryptamine 1A receptor (5-HT1A) and solute carrier family 6, member 4 (SLC6A4) 
genes on the clinical symptoms and treatment resistance in Slovenian patients with schizophre-
nia. A total of 138 patients with schizophrenia were evaluated using the Positive and Negative 
Syndrome Scale, Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale, Clinical Global Impression, and Global Assess-
ment of Functioning. Based on the selected criteria, 94 patients were included in the treatment-
responsive and 44 in the treatment-resistant group. All subjects and 94 controls were genotyped 
for the 5-HT1A rs6295 and 5-HTTLPR polymorphisms. There were no statistically significant 
differences in the frequencies of these polymorphisms between the patients with schizophrenia 
and the control group and between the treatment-resistant and treatment-responsive group of 
schizophrenia patients. Polymorphisms rs6295 and 5-HTTLPR had an influence on the Global 
Assessment of Functioning scale score, while 5-HTTLPR also had an influence on the total score 
of the negative subscale within the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale. Although we found no 
effect on progression toward the treatment-resistant schizophrenia, our data suggest that the rs6295 
and 5-HTTLPR polymorphisms can influence some clinical symptoms in schizophrenia. 
Treatment-resistant schizophrenia represents a significant public health problem. 
Studies have shown that one-fifth to one-third of patients with schizophrenia do not 
respond to treatment. 
1 These patients have persistent positive psychotic symptoms 
(delusions and hallucinations), more pronounced negative symptoms (apathy, blunted 
affect, lack of spontaneity, and emotional withdrawal) and more pronounced cognitive 
symptoms (memory and attention impairment) than treatment-responsive patients. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Furthermore, they stay in the hospital longer and have a very low level of functioning 
in the community. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>A recent American study showed that schizophrenia is a group of heritable 
disorders caused by a moderate number of separate genotypic networks associated 
with several distinct clinical syndromes. 
3 The serotonin system plays an important 
role in schizophrenia. The role of genetic variants of serotonin (5-HT) receptors in 
treatment-resistant schizophrenia has already been investigated. 
4 The serotonergic 
system is involved in the pharmacological mechanisms of atypical antipsychotics, 
which are widely used for the treatment of schizophrenia. 5-HT1A is a subtype 
of the serotonergic receptor that has an important influence on dopamine release. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Correspondence: Blanka Kores Plesničar 
ljubljana University Psychiatric hospital, 
studenec 48, 1260 ljubljana, slovenia 
Tel +386 1 587 24 67 
Fax +386 1 529 41 11 
email blanka.kores@psih-klinika.si </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 
20 February 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>454 </p>

<p>Terzić et al </p>

<p>When serotonin acts on 5-HT1A receptors, it accelerates 
dopamine release in the prefrontal cortex and consequently 
improves the negative, cognitive and affective symptoms of 
schizophrenia. 
5 5-HT1A receptors have an important role 
in the modulation of mood, cognition and motor behavior </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>and in the control of nonpsychotic symptoms, 
7 which is an 
important clinical issue in treatment-resistant schizophre-
nia. The main indication of clozapine is treatment-resistant 
schizophrenia, 
8 in which it acts as a weak partial agonist at 
the level of 5-HT1A receptors. 
9 In 1999, Wu and Comings 
reported a common polymorphism in the promoter region 
of the 5-HT1A gene, 
10 which was later shown to have a 
significant association with schizophrenia. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>The serotonin transporter (5-HTT), encoded by the 
SLC6A4 gene, is a major regulator of serotonin function. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>5-HTT is specific for serotonin and helps to terminate its 
actions by pumping it out of the synapse. 
5 5-HTTLPR is 
a 44-bp insertion/deletion polymorphism in the promoter 
region of SLC6A4 that has been frequently studied in a 
number of psychiatric disorders. 
13,14 It has also been shown 
to have an important association with schizophrenia. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Indeed, some previous studies examined the influence of 
5-HTTLPR variants on the symptoms and treatment response 
in schizophrenia. </p>

<p>16,17 </p>

<p>An early response to antipsychotic treatment is important 
for schizophrenia patients, as it predicts further treatment 
effectiveness. 
18 Classification of the genes responsible for 
heritable components of various psychiatric disorders is 
crucial to the advancement of our understanding of the 
underlying neurobiology and pathology of complex psychi-
atric diseases. 
19 As responses to psychotropic medication 
are complex, the identification of the key phenotypic mea-
sures for their definition is still a major issue in psychiatry 
and pharmacogenomics and has as yet been only partially 
implemented in the clinical setting. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>The present study investigated the association between 
the genetic variants of the 5-HT1A and SLC6A4 genes and 
the clinical symptoms and development of treatment-resistant 
schizophrenia. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
sample collection and DNa preparation </p>

<p>Patients diagnosed with schizophrenia according to the Diag-
nostic and Statistical Manual IV were randomly recruited 
from the outpatient unit of the Ljubljana University Psychi-
atric Clinic (Slovenia). Their psychopathological symptoms 
were assessed using the Positive and Negative Syndrome 
Scale (PANSS), 
21 Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale (BPRS), </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Clinical Global Impression (CGI) Scale, 
23 and Global Assess-
ment of Functioning (GAF). </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>The inclusion criteria for the treatment-resistant group 
were based on the definition of Conley and Kelly 
1 and 
included patients who did not respond to treatment with at 
least two different antipsychotics (at least one being atypical) 
at doses equivalent to more than 400-600 mg chlorprom-
azine, for a period of 6 weeks. Furthermore, they showed a 
moderate item score (4) on at least two of four symptom 
items according to PANSS (P2, P3, P6, and G9) and at 
least moderately severe illness as rated by the total BPRS 
score (45), with no stable period of good social and/or 
occupational functioning within the last 5 years. 
1 The inclu-
sion criteria for the treatment-responsive group were based 
on those of Andreasen et al 
25 and van Os et al. 
26 Treatment 
responders had achieved remission and had an item score 
of 3 on the selected symptom items according to PANSS 
(P1, P2, P3, P6, N1, N4, N6, G5, and G9). The exclusion 
criteria were the presence of another mental or somatic 
disorder, poor compliance to treatment, and the occurrence 
of important side effects during previous antipsychotic treat-
ments. Healthy blood donors constituted the control group. 
The chlorpromazine-equivalent daily dose of antipsychotics 
administered to each patient was calculated according to the 
guidelines for atypical antipsychotics, 
27 for fluphenasine 
decanoate, 
28 and for classic antipsychotics. </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>The study was approved by The Slovenian Ethics Com-
mittee for Research in Medicine. Written informed consent 
was obtained from each subject prior to his/her inclusion in 
the study. </p>

<p>genotyping method </p>

<p>Genomic DNA was isolated from peripheral blood leukocytes 
using Qiagen FlexiGene kits (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). 
Blood samples (5 mL) were taken from patients, and cells from 
the blood donation were retrieved for the control group. Geno-
typing was performed blind to the patient clinical status and 
was carried out using fluorescence-based competitive allele-
specific polymerase chain reaction (KASPar) assays according 
to the manufacturer's instructions (KBiosciences, Herts, UK). 
Two functional polymorphisms were studied, 5-HT1A rs6295 
and 5-HTTLPR. The dominant allele model was followed and 
the CG and GG genotypes for 5-HT1A rs6295 were grouped. 
For the 5-HTTLPR genotypes, a two-stage genotyping 
approach was used, with the biallelic 5-HTTLPR genotypes (L 
and S alleles) determined first. The SS and SL genotypes were 
grouped as in previous studies. 
12,16 In the second step, the A 
→ G substitution within the L allele was identified, so that the </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>455 </p>

<p>serotonergic genetic variants and schizophrenia </p>

<p>L A represented the common allele and the L G the polymorphic 
allele. The L G allele can be considered similar to the S allele 
in terms of transcriptional efficiency. </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>The frequencies of the SL and L A L G S alleles for 
5-HTTLPR were in the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium 
(P=0.94, P=0.24, respectively). The frequencies of HTR1A 
rs6295 were not in the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium 
(P=0.012), but matched those found in the single-nucleotide 
polymorphism database. The frequencies of HTR1A rs6295 in 
the control group were in the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium 
(P=0.103). </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was carried out using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 21.0</rs>) for Windows. The values of the variables 
are presented as arithmetic means with standard deviations 
or as frequencies or other descriptive statistical forms. The 
dominant genetic model was used, and the associations of 
having at least one minor allele versus having two wild-type 
alleles were tested. Association tests between the genotypes 
and the demographic traits were carried out with χ 
2 tests 
and Mann-Whitney U-tests. Association tests between the 
genotypes and the clinical responses were performed using 
analysis of covariance, with the current antipsychotic dose 
acting as a confounder. The differences in allele frequencies 
between responsive and resistant schizophrenic patients were 
assessed using χ 
2 tests. The limit of statistical significance 
was set at 0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Among the 138 patients with schizophrenia included in 
the study (70 female, 68 male), 94 met the criteria for the 
treatment-responsive group and 44 for the treatment-resistant 
group. The control group consisted of 94 healthy blood 
donors. All subjects were of Slovenian origin. 
Some significant differences in the demographical data 
were found between the treatment-responsive and treatment-
resistant groups. The treatment-resistant group included 28 
(63.6%) male and 16 (36.4%) female patients, while the 
treatment-responsive group included 40 (42.6%) male and 
54 (57.4%) female patients. The treatment-resistant group 
had significantly more male than female patients (P=0.021). 
The first psychotic episode occurred at an average age of 
24.26 years in the treatment-resistant group and 28.12 years 
in the treatment-responsive group, which also represents 
a significant difference (P=0.005). Treatment-resistant 
patients had a significantly higher number of psychiatric 
hospitalizations (P0.001) and had received significantly </p>

<p>higher doses of antipsychotic agents (P0.05) compared to 
treatment responders. Most of the patients were prescribed 
more than one antipsychotic at the time of the inclusion 
in the study. Clozapine was prescribed to 58 patients with 
schizophrenia, 44 of them were treatment resistant and 14 
were treatment responsive. Furthermore, 28 patients were 
prescribed risperidone, 25 aripiprazole, 21 fluphenazine, 
19 zuclopenthixol, 18 quetiapine, 13 amisulpride, and 
12 olanzapine, while other prescribed antipsychotics were 
less frequent (paliperidone, ziprasidone, flupentixol, halo-
peridol, and promazine). 
The frequencies of 5-HT1A rs6295 in the group of all 
patients included in the study were 81.9% for GG/CG and 
18.1% for CC, while the frequencies in the control group 
were 85.1% for GG/CC and 14.9% for CC. There were no 
significant differences in the frequencies of the polymor-
phisms either between the group of all patients and the control 
group (P=0.519) or between the treatment-responsive and 
treatment-resistant patients (P=0.06) (Table 1). 
The frequencies of 5-HTTLPR in the group of all patients 
were 37.7% for LL, 51.4% for LS, and 10.9% for SS. The 
frequencies of the three-allelic 5-HTTLPR genotypes were 
28.3% for L A L A , 54.3% for L A S or L A L G , and 17.4% for 
L G L G , L G S, or SS. In the control group, the frequencies were 
50.0% for LL, 36.2% for LS, 13.8% for SS, 40.4% for L A 
L A , 43.6% for L A S or L A L G , and 16.0% for L G L G , L G S or 
SS (Table 1). There were no significant differences in the 
frequencies of the allelic variants between the group of all 
patients and the control group (P=0.071 and P=0.146) or 
between the treatment-responsive and treatment-resistant 
groups of patients (P=0.262 and P=0.131) (Table 1). 
The possible associations between the genotypes and 
severity of symptoms in all patients were also investigated. 
An association between the 5-HT1A rs6295 and GAF 
(P=0.007) was found. Patients carrying the CC genotype had 
higher GAF scores compared to those with the CG or GG 
genotypes, which indicates better global patient functioning. 
No significant associations were found between the 5-HT1A 
rs6295 variants and the other clinical scores (Table 2). 
No significant association was found between the LS 
carriers of 5-HTTLPR and the severity of symptoms either. 
However, there was an association between the three-allelic 
5-HTTLPR polymorphism and GAF (P=0.025) and the nega-
tive subscale of PANSS (P=0.044). Patients with the L G or 
S alleles had higher GAF scores and lower total scores on 
the negative subscale of PANSS compared to those with at 
least one L A allele, which means better patient functioning 
and fewer negative symptoms (Table 2). </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>456 </p>

<p>Terzić et al </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Our study investigated the influence of 5-HT1A rs6295 
and 5-HTTLPR on the occurrence of schizophrenia and 
treatment-resistant schizophrenia and clinical symptoms in 
Slovenian patients. 
Demographical characteristics in the treatment-resistant 
group were as expected. Male predominance and an earlier 
onset of the first psychotic episode in treatment-resistant 
schizophrenia patients have already been described in other 
studies. 
31 These patients had a higher number of psychiatric 
hospitalizations and had received significantly higher doses 
of antipsychotic agents compared to treatment responders, 
which has also been reported in other studies. 
32 Among the 
prescribed antipsychotics clozapine, aripiprazole, haloperidol, 
olanzapine, quetiapine, and ziprasidone act as partial agonists 
on 5-HT1A and risperidone as an antagonist on 5-HT1A. </p>

<p>5-HTTLPR genetic variants seem to affect the 5-HT1A recep-
tor binding. A PET (positron emission tomography) study 
reported that 5-HT1A receptor binding potential values were 
lower in all brain regions in subjects with 5-HTTLPR SS or 
SL genotypes than in those with LL genotypes. 
33 The lower 
transcriptional efficiency associated with the S allele of the 
5-HTTLPR may lead to decreased 5-HTT function, which in 
turn may lead to a lifelong increase in 5-HT tone, which may 
in turn desensitize and downregulate 5-HT1A receptors. </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>Our data showed no significant influence of the 5-HT1A 
rs6295 allelic variants on the occurrence of schizophrenia, 
although some studies have indicated this association. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Similarly, there was no increased risk for treatment-resistant 
schizophrenia in the 5-HT1A variants, although activation of 
these receptors can influence adult neurogenesis 
34 and might 
therefore influence the clinical outcome of the disease. </p>

<p>Table 1 Comparison of genotype frequencies in the treatment-responsive versus treatment-resistant schizophrenia patients and in the 
group of all patients versus the control group </p>

<p>SNP 
Patient group 
Genotype [n (%)] 
P-value </p>

<p>5-HT1A 
GG/CG 
CC 
responsive 
73 (77.7) 
21 (22.3) 
0.06 </p>

<p>resistant 
40 (90.9) 
4 (9.1) </p>

<p>all patients 
113 (81.9) 
25 (18.1) 
0.519 </p>

<p>controls 
80 (85.1) 
14 (14.9) </p>

<p>5-HTTLPR 
LL 
LS 
SS 
responsive 
34 (36.2) 
47 (50.0) 
13 (13.8) 
0.262 
resistant 
18 (40.9) 
24 (54.5) 
2 (4.5) 
all patients 
52 (37.7) 
71 (51.4) 
15 (10.9) 
0.071 
controls 
47 (50.0) 
34 (36.2) 
13 (13.8) 
5-HTTLPR 
L A L A 
L A S, L A L G 
L G S, L G L G , SS 
responsive 
23 (24.5) 
51 (54.3) 
20 (21.3) 
0.131 
resistant 
16 (36.4) 
24 (54.5) 
4 (9.1) 
all patients 
39 (28.3) 
75 (54.3) 
24 (17.4) 
0.146 
controls 
38 (40.4) 
41 (43.6) 
15 (16.0) </p>

<p>Abbreviation: SNP, single-nucleotide polymorphism. </p>

<p>Table 2 associations between genotype variants and schizophrenia clinical scores in all patients </p>

<p>SNP 
Gene variant 
PANSS subscales and total (mean ± SD) 
GAF (mean ± SD) 
CGI (mean ± SD) </p>

<p>Positive 
Negative 
General 
Total score </p>

<p>5-HTR1A rs6295 
gg/cg 
11.94 (4.98) 
17.19 (6.46) 
31.33 (9.80) 
60.45 (19.84) 
57.06 (10.70) 
3.81 (0.81) 
cc 
10.32 (4.29) 
14.28 (6.27) 
27.72 (7.86) 
52.32 (17.49) 
63.52 (9.12) 
3.6 (0.76) 
P-value 
0.187 
0.06 
0.11 
0.08 
0.007 
0.29 
5-HTTLPR 
ll 
12.04 (4.97) 
17.75 (6.74) 
32.46 (9.83) 
62.25 (20.19) 
56.13 (10.89) 
3.81 (0.74) 
ls/ss 
11.41 (4.85) 
16.00 (6.30) 
29.59 (9.28) 
57.00 (19.13) 
59.50 (10.38) 
3.76 (0.84) 
P-value 
0.709 
0.139 
0.094 
0.136 
0.084 
0.900 
5-HTTLPR 
l a l a 
12.44 (5.23) 
18.64 (6.53) 
33.72 (10.36) 
64.79 (20.81) 
54.56 (10.16) 
3.90 (0.72) 
l a s, l a l g 
11.83 (5.05) 
16.57 (6.49) 
30.31 (9.16) 
58.71 (19.43) 
58.57 (10.84) 
3.83 (0.83) 
l g l g , l g s, ss 
9.79 (3.20) 
13.71 (5.46) 
26.87 (8.09) 
50.37 (15.13) 
63.13 (8.97) 
3.42 (0.78) 
P-value 
0.330 
0.044 
0.064 
0.064 
0.025 
0.16 </p>

<p>Note: The figures shown in bold are statistically significant, considering P value 0.05. 
Abbreviations: CGI, Clinical Global Impression; GAF, Global Assessment of Functioning; PANSS, Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale for schizophrenia; SD, standard 
deviation; SNP, single-nucleotide polymorphism. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>457 </p>

<p>serotonergic genetic variants and schizophrenia </p>

<p>The 5-HTTLPR allelic variants also had no influence 
on increased risk for schizophrenia, which is consistent 
with prior studies. 
35 Furthermore, no association was found 
between 5-HTTLPR and treatment-resistant schizophre-
nia. However, a Croatian study reported that 5-HTTLPR 
SS carriers were less likely to develop treatment-resistant 
schizophrenia compared to those with all other 5-HTTLPR 
genotypes and that L A S carriers were almost three times 
more likely to develop treatment-resistant schizophrenia 
compared to SS carriers. 
36 Reduced function of the serotonin 
transporter means higher serotonin concentrations for down-
stream regulation of 5-HT receptors and could probably play 
a factor in creating more favorable conditions for antipsy-
chotic treatment, with a reduced probability of developing 
treatment-resistant schizophrenia. 
36 The difference from 
our study could be explained in the different sample size 
and different inclusion criteria for the treatment-resistant 
schizophrenia. In the Croatian study, there were 53.2% of 
treatment-resistant patients, 
36 which is a considerably higher 
percentage than in our study. 
Allelic variants of 5-HT1A rs6295 showed a correlation 
with the GAF score. The GAF score was also shown to 
correlate with positive and negative symptoms, as well as 
with agitation levels. 
37 Although no significant associations 
were found between the 5-HT1A rs6295 variants and the 
other clinical scores, it can be assumed that the CC genotype 
is associated with better patient functioning. These data 
are in agreement with the suggestion that the occurrence 
of a G allele at this locus prevents the binding of putative 
repressor proteins, which leads to enhanced gene expres-
sion and reduced serotonergic neurotransmission. 
38 Other 
studies have reported similar data, with the G allele being 
involved in reduced serotonergic neurotransmission. Two 
studies described an association between the CC genotype 
of 5-HT1A rs6295 and greater improvement in negative 
symptoms following treatment, compared with the CG or 
GG genotypes. </p>

<p>39,40 </p>

<p>An association was also found between the L G or 
S alleles and higher GAF scores or lower scores on the 
negative subscale of PANSS, while other studies have 
reported conflicting data regarding this association. An 
American study reported that the LL carriers had worse 
clinical schizophrenia outcomes when compared with the 
LS/SS carriers. 
16 On the other hand, in a Korean popula-
tion, the SS genotype of 5-HTTLPR was found to be con-
nected to a higher negative symptom score and general 
psychopathology score, compared to the LS/LL carriers. </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>The S allele has even been associated with violent suicide </p>

<p>attempts in patients with schizophrenia. 
42 A Slovenian study 
showed that the L G or S alleles of 5-HTTLPR are associ-
ated with lower improvement in schizophrenia symptoms 
during treatment. 
43 In patients with depressive disorder, 
the L variants of 5-HTTLPR were associated with a higher 
probability of remission and response to selective serotonin 
reuptake inhibitors. 
44 Theoretically, the L and S alleles can 
differentially modulate the transcription of the SLC6A4 
gene. The S allele reduces the transcriptional efficiency of 
the gene, which results in reduced 5-HTT expression and 
serotonin uptake. 
12 Evidence suggests that the L G allele 
might have a transcriptional activity similar to that of the 
S allele, while only the L A allele increases transcriptional 
activity. 
45 However, it is possible that other mechanisms, 
such as regulatory posttranslational processing of 5-HTT, 
can influence receptor activity. </p>

<p>46 </p>

<p>Our study had several limitations. Treatment resistance 
was defined retrospectively and a part of the initial group 
of patients could not be classified because of insufficient 
information. The criteria for treatment-resistant schizo-
phrenia remain to be fully defined. A number of studies 
have proposed criteria for treatment resistance in patients 
with schizophrenia, 
8,47 as well as the guidelines for their 
treatment. 
48 Furthermore, the P-values were not corrected 
for multiple comparisons. The data should be interpreted 
with caution because of the small sample size and borderline 
statistical significance, so there is a chance of false-positive 
findings. 
The present study examined the influence of two genetic 
polymorphisms in the 5-HT1A gene and SLC6A4 gene on 
clinical symptoms and treatment resistance in patients with 
schizophrenia. The 5-HT1A rs6295 and the 5-HTTLPR 
polymorphisms have an influence on global patient func-
tioning, and the 5-HTTLPR has an influence on the nega-
tive symptoms of schizophrenia. However, neither of the 
polymorphisms have any impact on the development of 
treatment-resistant schizophrenia. Because a limited sample 
size was used, these findings should be replicated in larger 
data sets. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Anja Plemenitaš, who contributed the blood 
samples of the healthy blood donors for the study. This study 
was financially supported by the Slovenian Research Agency 
(ARRS grant numbers P1-0170 and P3-0366). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>458 </p>

<p>Terzić et al </p>



<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/neuropsychiatric-disease-and-treatment-journal </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment is an international, peer-
reviewed journal of clinical therapeutics and pharmacology focusing 
on concise rapid reporting of clinical or pre-clinical studies on a 
range of neuropsychiatric and neurological disorders. This journal 
is indexed on PubMed Central, the 'PsycINFO' database and CAS, </p>

<p>and is the official journal of The International Neuropsychiatric 
Association (INA). The manuscript management system is completely 
online and includes a very quick and fair peer-review system, which 
is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to 
read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>