<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4112233" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract A β-glucan synthase gene was isolated from the genomic DNA of polypore mushroom Sparassis crispa, which 
reportedly produces unusually high amount of soluble β-1,3-glucan (β-glucan). Sequencing and subsequent open reading frame 
analysis of the isolated gene revealed that the gene (5,502 bp) consisted of 10 exons separated by nine introns. The predicted 
mRNA encoded a β-glucan synthase protein, consisting of 1,576 amino acid residues. Comparison of the predicted protein 
sequence with multiple fungal β-glucan synthases estimated that the isolated gene contained a complete N-terminus but was 
lacking approximately 70 amino acid residues in the C-terminus. Fungal β-glucan synthases are integral membrane proteins, 
containing the two catalytic and two transmembrane domains. The lacking C-terminal part of S. crispa β-glucan synthase was 
estimated to include catalytically insignificant transmembrane α-helices and loops. Sequence analysis of 101 fungal β-glucan 
synthases, obtained from public databases, revealed that the β-glucan synthases with various fungal origins were categorized into 
corresponding fungal groups in the classification system. Interestingly, mushrooms belonging to the class Agaricomycetes were 
found to contain two distinct types (Type I and II) of β-glucan synthases with the type-specific sequence signatures in the loop 
regions. S. crispa β-glucan synthase in this study belonged to Type II family, meaning Type I β-glucan synthase is expected to be 
discovered in S. crispa. The high productivity of soluble β-glucan was not explained but detailed biochemical studies on the 
catalytic loop domain in the S. crispa β-glucan synthase will provide better explanations. </p>

<p>168 Yang et al. </p>

<p>expression of tumor suppression cytokines [11, 12]. 
The content of soluble β-glucan, which is of particular 
importance in immune stimulation, is essentially dependent 
on mushroom species. Cultivated mushrooms, Pleurotus 
ostreatus, P. eryngii, P. pulmonarius, and L. edodes, consist 
of 0.6~1.5% soluble β-glucan on a dry weight basis [13]. 
The content can vary according to the cultivation conditions, 
such as the carbon to nitrogen ratio of the substrate, pH, and 
culture temperature [14]. Interestingly, polypore mushroom 
Sparassis crispa has been reported to contain an unusually high 
amount of soluble β-glucan (40% dry weight) in its fruiting 
body [15]. Hot water or alkali extract of S. crispa displays 
anti-tumor activity and stimulates hematopoietic responses 
[16]. S. crispa is a parasitic and saprotrophic mushroom, 
growing on the roots or basis of oak or conifer trees. It is 
also considered to be a brown-rot fungus since it does not 
produce lignin-degrading enzyme [17]. This mushroom has 
drawn much attention as a soluble β-glucan producer, but 
further study has been impeded due to its extremely slow 
growth rate. As an alternative, the production of β-glucan 
through mycelial culture has been recently examined by 
introducing a high β-glucan producing mutant strain [18]. 
In this study, the β-glucan synthase gene from a S. crispa 
strain was isolated and its primary structure was examined 
by comparative study with known fungal β-glucan synthase 
genes in order to provide an explanation for the unusual 
high β-glucan productivity of S. crispa. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Strains and culture conditions. S. crispa IUM4010 was 
obtained from the Culture Collection of Wild Mushrooms 
(CCWM), University of Incheon, Korea. The strain was 
maintained on potato-dextrose agar medium (Ventech Bio 
Co., Eumseong, Korea). For the liquid culture, the mushroom 
mycelia were cultured in potato dextrose broth (PDB; Ventech 
Bio Co.) with gentle shaking at 25 o 
C for 2~3 wk. </p>

<p>Extraction of genomic DNA. Genomic DNA was 
extracted from the mushroom mycelia grown in PDB 
using the previously described method [19]. In brief, the 
mushroom mycelia were harvested and then ground with a 
mortar and pestle. The ground powder was then suspended 
in 0.5 mL of lysing buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl [pH 8.0], 0.2 M 
EDTA, and 10 μg/mL of proteinase K; Sigma-Aldrich Co. 
St. Louis, MO, USA) to a final concentration of 1 g/mL, after 
which the suspension was incubated for 10 min at 65 o 
C. 
The clarified supernatant was obtained by centrifugation. 
The nucleic acids in the solution were precipitated with 
40% isopropanol. The precipitates were dried and then 
resuspended in 0.2 mL of TE buffer containing 0.05 mL/ 
mL of RNase. The solution was incubated at 50 o 
C for 
10 min. Proteins in the solution were removed by treatment 
with 0.2 mL of chloroform : isoamylalcohol (24 : 1) solution. 
The isopropanol precipitates were suspended in 0.1 mL of 
TE buffer for further analysis. </p>

<p>Isolation of β-glucan synthase gene. To isolate the β-
glucan synthase gene from genomic DNA, degenerated 
primer sets were designed from a conserved C2 domain 
region of 19 fungal β-glucan synthase gene sequences (1F, 
1R in Table 1, Fig. 1). PCR using the primer set yielded a 
1.5 kbp product. The sequence of the C2 domain product 
was determined, and then new specific primers (SC1R, SC1F) 
targeting the outside of C2 domain were generated. The 
second PCR reactions were performed using combinations 
of the specific primers and degenerated primers (2F, 9R). 
The primer sets 2F/SC1R and SC1F/9R targeted 5' and 3' 
regions of the C2 domain, respectively. The PCR reactions 
yielded a 2 kbp DNA band for the 5' region and a 1.5 kbp 
band for the 3' region. The DNA sequences for both products 
were determined and assembled with the C2 domain 
sequence, yielding an incomplete β-glucan synthase gene 
sequence with a size of 4,905 bp. The remaining 5' end 
region was further determined by inverse PCR technology 
[20]. As a result, the sequence of the S. crispa β-glucan 
synthase gene with a size of 5,502 bp was determined and 
deposited into Genebank (accession No. KJ187309). </p>

<p>Analysis of β-glucan synthase gene structure. The 
exon arrangement of the S. crispa β-glucan synthase gene was 
analyzed by <rs id="software-7" type="software">FGENESH</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-7" type="url">http://linux1.softberry.com/</rs>/) 
[21] using Coprinopsis cinerea genome as a reference. 
Transmembrane domain of the β-glucan synthase protein 
was analyzed by <rs id="software-3" type="software">Phobius</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="url">http://phobius.sbc.su.se/</rs>/) 
[22]. Phylogenetic analysis with the fungal β-glucan 
synthases was conducted using <rs id="software-2" type="software">MEGA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">ver. 2.0</rs> software. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Primary structure of the S. crispa β-glucan synthase 
gene. The DNA sequence with a size of 5,502 bp for the 
S. crispa β-glucan synthase gene was determined. Sequence </p>

<p>Table 1. Primers for the cloning of β-glucan synthase gene 
in Sparassis crispa </p>

<p>Primer 
Sequence </p>

<p>1F 
5'-TGG AAY GCY RTN RTY ATY TCN ATG TA-3' 
1R 
5'-CAT YTG YTC WCC CAT RCC NG-3' 
2F 
5'-GAG GAY ATY TTY YTB GAY CTC AC-3' 
SC1R 
5'-GTA GAT AAA AGA TGT TCG CGG TAC-3' 
SC1F 
5'-TCC TGA ACT TCC AGA CGA AAC TGG-3' 
9R 
5'-GAA YTC DCG MGC NGG YTG HGA C-3' </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Locations of primers targeting the β-glucan synthase 
gene in Sparassis crispa. Two catalytic domains are marked as 
C1 and C2. The transmembrane domains are marked as 
TM1 and TM2. </p>

<p>β-Glucan Synthase from Sparassis crispa 169 </p>

<p>comparison analysis of multiple fungal β-glucan synthase 
genes revealed that the determined sequence was incomplete, 
lacking approximately 400 bp at the 3' end region. The β-
glucan synthase gene was analyzed by the <rs type="software">FGENESH</rs> 
program to predict the open reading frame using the C. 
cinerea genome as the reference. As a result, the β-glucan 
synthase gene was found to consist of 10 exon sequences 
separated by nine introns. The predicted size of the mRNA 
was 4,728 bp. The mRNA encoded a polypeptide consisting 
of 1,576 amino acid residues. Since mushroom β-glucan 
synthases of this type are generally composed of 1,640~ 
1,650 amino acid residues, the S. crispa β-glucan synthase 
in this study is estimated to be devoid of approximately 70 
amino acids at its C-terminus. However, the protein 
regions critical for enzyme function, including the active 
site, are mostly contained within the 1,500 amino acid 
residues for fungal β-glucan synthase [5]. The amino acid 
sequence for S. crispa β-glucan synthase is estimated to 
carry most of the information required for the analysis of 
enzyme function. </p>

<p>Domain analysis for S. crispa β-glucan synthase. 
Fungal β-glucan synthase is an integral membrane protein, 
consisting of two cytosolic and two transmembrane domains 
[1, 23]. Topology of S. crispa β-glucan synthase was analyzed 
by the <rs type="software">Phobius</rs> program to predict the functional domain 
regions. As shown in Fig. 2A, S. crispa β-glucan synthase </p>

<p>was predicted to consist of 15 loops (L1~L15) and 14 
transmembrane α-helices (H1~H14). Catalytic domains C1 
and C2, homologous to Fks1, were found in L1 and L9, 
respectively. The two domains were separated by the 
transmembrane domain TM1, which was shown to comprise 
eight transmembrane α-helices (H1~H8). TM2, composed 
of six transmembrane α-helices (H7~H14), was located at 
the C-terminus of the protein (Fig. 2B). The large loop 
structures L1, L9, and L11 with lengths of 367, 573, and 
143 aa, respectively, were located at the cytosolic side of 
the membrane, implying their function in the synthesis of 
β-glucan. In the yeast homologue Fks1, the L9 loop was 
reported to play a critical role in enzyme catalysis [24]. 
Mutations in the core catalytic regionof the Fks1 L9 loop, 
ranging 830~1,050 aa, caused more than 80% reduction in 
catalytic activity, as shown by the mutant strains fks1-1144 
(L872F, E907K, N982S) and fks1-1154 (K877N, A899S, 
Q977P) [25]. The L9 loop of S. crispa β-glucan synthase 
was highly homologous to that of Fks1 (Fig. 3). The amino 
acid residues reported to affect the catalytic activity of Fks1 
were well conserved in S. crispa β-glucan synthase (Fig. 3, 
shaded amino acids). </p>

<p>Analysis of fungal β-glucan synthase family. 
Phylogenetic analysis was conducted using the amino acid 
sequences of 101 fungal β-glucan synthases registered in 
Genebank in order to elucidate the diversity of β-glucan </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Topology of the β-glucan synthase from Sparassis crispa. A, Predicted topology by <rs type="software">Phobius</rs> software; B, Schematic 
description based on the predicted topology. Random loops were designated as L1~L15. Transmembrane α-helices were marked 
as H in panel (B). </p>



<p>synthase as well as the exact position of S. crispa β-glucan 
synthase. All fungal β-glucan synthases were categorized 
into two phyla (Ascomycota and Basidiomycota) of the 
classification system (Fig. 4). In Ascomycota, most of the 
β-glucan synthases belonged to the subphylum Pezizomycotina. 
In Basidiomycota, the enzyme was distributed to four different 
subphyla, but most belonged to the class Agaricomycetes </p>

<p>in the subphylum Agraricomycotina (Fig. 4). 
Those mushrooms only in the class Agaricomycetes, 
including Agaricus bisporus, Trametes versicolor, Schizophyllum 
commune, and C. cinerea, were found to contain two distinct 
types of β-glucan synthases (Fig. 5). For example, A. 
bisporus carries two different β-glucan synthases, EKM78523 
and EKM82691. Therefore, having two different types of </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Phylogenetic analysis of fungal β-glucan synthases. The number in the parenthesis is the number of sequences 
belonging to the corresponding group. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Comparison of core catalytic regions in the L9 loops of Sparassis crispa (KJ187309) and Saccharomyces cerevisiae 
(FKS1). The shaded amino acids were reported to be important for catalytic function of FKS1 [24]. </p>

<p>β-Glucan Synthase from Sparassis crispa 171 </p>

<p>β-glucan synthases in the same cell appears to be a common 
characteristic of Agaricomycetes mushrooms. The reason 
why only these mushrooms display this feature is not clear, 
but it may imply gene duplication in the common ancestor </p>

<p>of Agaricomycetes and subsequent divergent evolution of 
each β-glucan synthase gene in the same organism. S. 
crispa β-glucan synthase in this study belonged to Type II 
family (Fig. 5), meaning Type I β-glucan synthase is expected </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Sequence analysis of β-glucan synthases belonging to the class Agaricomycetes. The β-glucan synthase from Sparassis 
crispa belonged to Type II. </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Comparison of the loop regions in Type I and Type II β-glucan synthases. The boxed regions contain type-specific signatures. </p>

<p>172 Yang et al. </p>

<p>to be discovered in S. crispa. </p>

<p>Characteristics of Type I and Type II β-glucan 
synthases. Multiple sequence alignment analysis was 
conducted on the two different types of β-glucan synthases 
from A. bisporus, C. cinerea, Laccaria bicolor, S. commune, 
and S. crispa. TM domains were mostly conserved regardless 
of type. However, we detected highly variable, but specific 
for Type I or Type II family, regions in the loops, L1, L2, 
L4, L9, L12, and L13 (Fig. 6). In the L9 loop, a conserved 
sequence motif (AMFNGXNPFAXE/D) was discovered in 
Type I, whereas it was deleted or randomized in Type II 
(Fig. 6, boxed region in L9). A distinct sequence motif for 
Type II was also discovered. The consensus sequence 
WXK/R in L13 was a specific sequence signature for Type 
II β-glucan synthase. S. crispa β-glucan synthase carries 
this signature as WTR. 
S. cerevisiae, a member of Ascomycota, produces two β-
glucan synthases from two independent genes, FKS1 and 
FKS2. However, these enzymes are highly homologous 
proteins and do not belong to any type of Agaricomycetes 
β-glucan synthase. The L9 catalytic loop regions for both 
enzymes are virtually identical, implying that both enzymes 
may have similar catalytic activity. FKS1 is primarily expressed 
in the vegetative growth, whereas FKS2 is expressed under 
stress conditions, including starvation, sporulation, and 
mating [26]. Therefore, S. cerevisiae β-glucan synthases are 
catalytically identical but functionally independent enzymes. 
Mushrooms belonging to Agaricomycetes express two 
types of β-glucan synthases, that are potentially different in 
terms of catalytic activity as suggested by different amino 
acid arrangements in the catalytic loop region, may function 
in different developmental stages. Transcriptome analyses 
of A. bisporus H97 in different developmental stages have 
shown that Type II β-glucan synthase (XP_006458137, 
a homologue of EKM78523) was constantly expressed 
throughout the developmental stages whereas Type I β-glucan 
synthase (XP_006455356, a homologue of EKM82691) was 
highly expressed in the fruiting body stage [27]. Further 
studies will clarify the detailed role of these enzymes. The 
exceptionally high production of soluble β-glucan by S. 
crispa was not fully explained. Comparative biochemical 
study with various Agaricomycetes β-glucan synthases will 
provide better explanations. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by GyeongNam Technopark 
program (#70011463), the Ministry of Knowledge Economy, 
Korea. </p>



</text></tei>