<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4306576" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background-A substantial number of young women experience pregnancy scares -thinking 
they might be pregnant, and later discovering that they are not. Although pregnancy scares are 
distressing events, little is known about who experiences them and whether they are important to 
our understanding of unintended pregnancy. </p>

<p>Objective-We describe the young women who experience pregnancy scares, and examine the 
link between pregnancy scares and subsequent unintended pregnancy. </p>

<p>Methods-We used data from the Relationship Dynamics and Social Life Study. T-tests and 
regression analyses were conducted using baseline and weekly data to estimate relationships 
between respondent characteristics and subsequent pregnancy scares. Event history methods were 
used to assess pregnancy scares as a predictor of unintended pregnancy. </p>

<p>Results-Nine percent of the young women experienced a pregnancy scare during the study. 
African-American race, lack of two-parent family structure, lower GPA, cohabitation, and sex 
without birth control prior to the study are associated with experiencing a pregnancy scare and 
with experiencing a greater number of pregnancy scares. Further, experiencing a pregnancy scare 
is strongly associated with subsequent unintended pregnancy, independent of background factors. 
Forty percent of the women who experienced a pregnancy scare subsequently had an unintended 
pregnancy during the study period, relative to only 11% of those who did not experience a 
pregnancy scare. </p>

<p>Conclusions-Young women from less advantaged backgrounds are more likely to experience 
a pregnancy scare, and pregnancy scares are often followed by an unintended pregnancy. </p>

<p>In the United States, the term 'pregnancy scare' describes when a woman who wants to 
avoid pregnancy believes she is pregnant, but later learns that she is not. For example, as one 
respondent (who did not desire a pregnancy) told us shortly after her pregnancy scare, "I 
thought there could have been a chance that I was pregnant but it turned out that I wasn't, so 
I am very thankful for that." Many respondents reported, "I missed this month's period," or 
"My period started seven days late" to explain why they temporarily thought they were 
pregnant. </p>

<p>Pregnancy scares are common -over half of the young women (54%) who participated in a 
recent survey conducted by the National Campaign to Prevent Teen and Unplanned 
Pregnancy (2011) reported that they had had a pregnancy scare. In the Henry J. Kaiser 
Family Foundation's National Survey of Adolescents and Young Adults, 3 in 5 respondents 
reported that they or their female partner had ever experienced a pregnancy scare (Hoff, 
Greene, and Davis 2003). Relatively little is known about pregnancy scares and their 
consequences. </p>

<p>Our first objective is to describe the young women who experience pregnancy scares. We 
hypothesize that disadvantaged sociodemographic background characteristics and early 
experiences with sex, lack of contraception, and pregnancy will be associated with 
pregnancy scares, much as they are associated with unintended pregnancy. </p>

<p>Our second objective is to examine the link between pregnancy scares and subsequent 
unintended pregnancy. A pregnancy scare may be an indicator that a young woman is at 
high risk of an unintended pregnancy, for several reasons. First, adjustment to the idea of a 
possible pregnancy might introduce some ambivalence into a young woman's desire to avoid 
pregnancy. This can occur after a miscarriage of an unintended pregnancy. As one 
respondent told us, "I found out I was pregnant and I miscarried. I didn't know that I wanted 
a baby until I lost it. That is why part of me wants to get pregnant now. I'm not trying to but 
I would be happy if I did." If pregnancy scares affect pregnancy desire, or ambivalence 
about pregnancy, in a similar way, then pregnancy scares will have a direct effect on the 
likelihood of experiencing a later pregnancy. Second, for imperfect contraceptors, a 
pregnancy scare is likely to precede an actual unintended pregnancy, because the average 
pregnancy rate for any given month is only about 50% for young women even when sex is 
perfectly timed to ovulation (Dunson, Colombo, and Baird 2002). Third, personality traits or 
skills that lead to pregnancy scares may predict unintended pregnancy as well -for example, 
the ability to consistently adhere to a contraception regimen. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>We use data from the Relationship Dynamics and Social Life (RDSL) study, which 
interviewed a random, population-based sample of 1,003 young women ages 18-19, residing 
in a Michigan county. Women were selected from the state driver's license and personal 
identification card databases. Investigators conducted a 60-minute face-to-face baseline 
survey between March 2008 and July 2009. Women then participated in a 2.5-year follow-
up study that required completion of weekly online or telephone surveys about contraceptive </p>

<p>Gatny et al. </p>

<p>
Demogr Res. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 20. </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>use, relationships, and prospective pregnancy intentions. In this paper we refer to the follow-
up study as "the journal," and the weekly surveys as "journals". The follow-up study 
concluded in February 2012. The response rate for the baseline interview was 84%, 99% 
agreed to participate in the journal, and 75% participated in the journal for at least 18 
months. </p>

<p>In this study we use only the first 18 months of the journal data to minimize bias from 
attrition. We analyze the weeks in which the respondent was not pregnant and did not 
strongly desire a pregnancy. We use two questions from the weekly surveys that measured 
pregnancy desires to identify those weeks. The first question asked respondents how much 
they wanted to get pregnant during the next month. The second question asked respondents 
how much they wanted to avoid getting pregnant during the next month. Both questions 
used a response scale from 0 to 5. Figure 1 summarizes the combined responses to these two 
questions, which we describe as strong antinatal, moderate antinatal, ambivalent/indifferent/ 
moderate pronatal, and strong pronatal. The design of these measures and how they relate to 
subsequent pregnancy have been described elsewhere (Miller, Barber, and Gatny 2013). In 
this study we omit weeks classified as strong pronatal in Figure 1. The result is an analytic 
sample of 901 young women and 34,943 observations. </p>

<p>2.1 Measures </p>

<p>Outcomes-Each week, respondents were asked about their pregnancy status, and are 
coded as "not pregnant," "probably pregnant," or "pregnant." "Pregnant" is defined as a 
self-report of a positive pregnancy test. Of the 901 young women in our analytic sample, 
114 (13%) reported 126 unintended pregnancies during the 18-month study period. Table 1 
summarizes these statistics. Of those women who experienced an unintended pregnancy 
during the study, 89% reported only one and 11% reported two. </p>

<p>Because we are analyzing only weeks in which respondents do not desire pregnancy, any 
"probably pregnant" report that is not subsequently verified by a pregnancy test (or, 
eventually, a birth, miscarriage, or abortion) is considered a "pregnancy scare". Descriptive 
statistics of these measures are also presented in Table 1. Of the 901 women in our analytic 
sample, 85 women (9%) reported 114 pregnancy scares during the 18-month study period. 
The majority reported only one pregnancy scare (78%), but a substantial proportion reported 
two (13%), and even three or four scares (9%). Of the 126 unintended pregnancies, 26 
(21%) were preceded by a pregnancy scare within the study period, and among the 85 
women who reported a pregnancy scare, 34 (40%) subsequently had an unintended 
pregnancy during the study (not shown in tables). Among the 816 women in our analytic 
sample who did not report a pregnancy scare, only 88 (11%) subsequently had an 
unintended pregnancy during the study (not shown in tables). </p>

<p>Sociodemographic characteristics and adolescent pregnancy-related 
experiences-We include characteristics measured in the baseline interview, summarized 
in Table 2. All of these variables are dichotomous, except high school GPA, which is 
continuous. Currently receiving public assistance includes WIC (Women, Infants and 
Children Program), FIP (Family Independence Program), cash welfare, or food stamps. </p>

<p>Gatny et al. </p>

<p>
Demogr Res. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 20. </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Other indicators-In regression models we use the total number of journals completed to 
control for repeated observation and exposure time. And, in hazard models, we include 
respondents' time in study, time in study squared, and total number of journals completed, to 
control for the increasing hazard of pregnancy and repeated observations. Time in study is 
coded in months and ranges from 0.49 to 18 months, with a mean of 8.60 months. </p>

<p>2.2 Data analysis </p>

<p>First we calculate the descriptive statistics for all independent variables for the total sample, 
as well as two subsamples: those who never experienced a pregnancy scare, and those who 
experienced a pregnancy scare (Table 2). Independent samples' t-tests indicate whether the 
independent variables are statistically different in the two subsamples. Next we investigate 
these characteristics in a multivariate context, using logistic regression for models of 
experiencing any pregnancy scare, and Poisson regression for models of the number of 
pregnancy scares (Table 3). Lastly, we estimate hazard models, implemented using logistic 
regression, to illustrate the relationship between a pregnancy scare and subsequent 
unintended pregnancy (Table 4). All analyses were conducted in <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">12.1</rs> using the logit, 
poisson, and xtlogit commands. The hazard models were estimated with xtlogit to account 
for the clustering effect of multiple journals per respondent. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1 Characteristics of respondents who had a pregnancy scare </p>

<p>Table 2 shows that, overall, sociodemographic characteristics associated with disadvantage 
are overrepresented in the subsample of young women who experienced a pregnancy scare. 
For example, while only 32% of those who did not experience a pregnancy scare are African 
American, 54% of those who experienced a pregnancy scare are African American. Also, 
young women with early pregnancy-related experiences are overrepresented in the 
pregnancy scares subsample. </p>

<p>3.2 Multivariate models of experiencing a pregnancy scare </p>

<p>The results in Table 3 are similar to the bivariate results presented in Table 2, although some 
of the associations are not statistically significant in the multivariate models. Further, the 
results are quite similar across specifications -characteristics associated with the probability 
of experiencing a pregnancy scare are also associated with the number of pregnancy scares 
actually reported, with only minor differences. </p>

<p>Column 1 shows that young women who are African-American, did not have a two-parent 
family structure, had a lower GPA in high school, and/or were living with a partner had 
higher probability of a pregnancy scare. In addition, young women who had had sex without 
birth control in the past had marginally higher probability of a pregnancy scare. </p>

<p>Column 2 shows that these same individual characteristics are also associated with a larger 
number of pregnancy scares. In addition, young women with two or more sexual partners 
experienced a marginally higher number of pregnancy scares than their peers. This suggests 
that women who had multiple sexual partners are disproportionately represented in the </p>

<p>Gatny et al. </p>

<p>
Demogr Res. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 20. </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>group that experienced multiple pregnancy scares. In these multivariate regression models, 
having had sex without birth control is the only adolescent pregnancy-related experience 
strongly related to pregnancy scares. Recall that in the bivariate models, on the other hand, 
early sex, multiple partners, prior sex without birth control, and one or more prior 
pregnancies are strongly related to pregnancy scares. This suggests that early sex, multiple 
sexual partners, and prior pregnancy are associated with pregnancy scares largely because of 
the sociodemographic characteristics of those young women who have early sex, multiple 
partners, and teen pregnancies, or because of their association with having sex without birth 
control. This is consistent with existing research; for example, finding that early sexual 
debut is associated with less contraceptive use (Kusunoki and Upchurch 2011; Manning, 
Longmore, and Giordano 2000; Manlove, Ryan, and Franzetta 2007). Note also that 
respondents who completed more journals were more likely to report a pregnancy scare, 
likely in part because it is associated with more time in the study period. </p>

<p>3.3 Multivariate models of the hazard of experiencing an unintended pregnancy </p>

<p>Finally, in Table 4 we estimate hazard models to illustrate the relationship between a 
pregnancy scare and subsequent unintended pregnancy rates. Model 1 includes only the 
control variables and shows higher unintended pregnancy rates among young African 
American women, those whose mothers had their first birth as a teen, those with a lower 
high school GPA, those receiving public assistance, and those living with a romantic 
partner. In terms of respondents' prior experiences, unintended pregnancy rates are higher 
among those who had sexual intercourse at or before age 16, had two or more sexual 
partners during adolescence, and/or had an adolescent pregnancy. In addition, the time 
variables are significant -the risk of unintended pregnancy increases throughout most of the 
study period, but then declines slightly near the end (indicated by the small negative 
coefficient for the variable indicating squared months in the study). Respondents who 
completed more journals during the study also had a lower hazard of unintended pregnancy. 
Note that because total number of journals completed is net of time in the study in these 
models, the negative coefficient likely represents the type of respondent who completed 
many journals within a specific period. Thus, the negative association is due to 
characteristics that lead respondents to complete more journals and also reduce the risk of 
unintended pregnancy, for example, conscientiousness. </p>

<p>Model 2 shows that young women who experienced a pregnancy scare had higher 
subsequent unintended pregnancy rates than those respondents who did not. More precisely, 
the weekly log-odds of experiencing an unintended pregnancy were 99% higher, which 
translates into nearly double the unintended pregnancy rate for women who had a prior 
pregnancy scare compared to those who did not. </p>

<p>Model 3 indicates higher unintended pregnancy rates after a pregnancy scare even when 
measures of sociodemographic characteristics are included as controls. In other words, 
although women from disadvantaged backgrounds experience more pregnancy scares and 
higher unintended pregnancy rates, young women who experience a pregnancy scare have 
higher unintended pregnancy rates than their peers without a pregnancy scare, net of their 
disadvantaged background. However, the fact that the magnitude of the pregnancy scare </p>

<p>Gatny et al. </p>

<p>
Demogr Res. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 20. </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>effect declines by 20% between models 2 and 3 indicates that pregnancy scares are 
associated with unintended pregnancy in part because of the sociodemographic 
characteristics linked to both experiences. </p>

<p>The adolescent pregnancy-related experiences added to Model 4 explain an additional 6% of 
the relationship between pregnancy scares and unintended pregnancy, but the coefficient 
remains large and statistically significant. Although adolescent experiences with early sex 
and multiple partners are strongly related to the rate of unintended pregnancy, for the most 
part they do not explain the difference in unintended pregnancy rates between young women 
who experienced pregnancy scares and those who did not. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>We found that a substantial proportion (9%) of young women experienced a pregnancy scare 
during the 18-month study period. A wide range of sociodemographic characteristics and 
adolescent experiences were associated with pregnancy scares in our bivariate analyses. 
However, in our multivariate analyses, only being African-American, growing up with 
something other than a two-parent family structure, having a lower high school GPA, living 
with a romantic partner, and having sex without birth control during adolescence were 
independently associated with a higher probability of a pregnancy scare. We found similar 
results when we predicted number of pregnancy scares. This suggests that although 
pregnancy scares occur to all types of young women, those from less advantaged 
backgrounds are more likely to experience a pregnancy scare than those from more 
advantaged backgrounds. </p>

<p>We found that 21% of the unintended pregnancies were preceded by a pregnancy scare 
within the study period, and -even more dramatic -more than 40% of women who reported 
a pregnancy scare went on to experience an unintended pregnancy, even during the 
relatively limited period of observation in our study (18 months). In our hazard models, 
pregnancy scares are a strong predictor of unintended pregnancy, independent of key 
sociodemographic characteristics and adolescent experiences. In other words, young women 
who experience a pregnancy scare have higher unintended pregnancy rates than those who 
do not, regardless of their background. This suggests that pregnancy scares may be a 
harbinger of a future unintended pregnancy. </p>

<p>It is beyond the scope of the current study to discern the mechanisms that explain why 
pregnancy scares are followed by unintended pregnancies, but future research should 
examine whether young women's attitudes or behaviors change after this experience. Of 
course, we cannot rule out that other unknown or unmeasured factors associated with 
unintended pregnancy are captured by pregnancy scares. But even if this is the case, a 
pregnancy scare could mark an important point for intervention. </p>

<p>The study has several limitations. The single county sample design may decrease the 
generalizability of the results. The sample does, however, hold constant the geographic 
differences in pregnancy scares and/or unintended pregnancy rates, as well as the geographic 
factors (e.g., media, policy, etc.) that are not a focus in this study. The very few Latinas in 
the county, and in our sample, precludes assessing them as a separate category. Research has </p>

<p>Gatny et al. </p>

<p>
Demogr Res. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 20. </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>estimated that other surveys capture only about one-half of abortions (Jones and Kost 2007). 
Thus, unintended pregnancies that end in abortion are likely underrepresented in our 
analyses. </p>

<p>Finally, although we measure pregnancy desires prospectively with two unipolar scales, this 
measurement does not fully capture the range of emotions surrounding pregnancy. We also 
use a broad definition of "unintended" in this analysis -we consider all pregnancies that 
were not fully intended (i.e., strong desire to get pregnant and no desire to avoid pregnancy) 
to be unintended. Our goal in this analysis was not to develop a complex measure of the 
intention status of pregnancies or pregnancy scares, but rather to limit our analyses to time 
periods when young women were not specifically trying to become pregnant. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>Our research describes the young women who have pregnancy scares -information we must 
have for reducing the incidence of these distressing events. In addition, we find that 
pregnancy scares often precede unintended pregnancies. Asking young women whether they 
have ever had a pregnancy scare is a simple and straightforward way to assess pregnancy 
risk, and may help clinicians gauge how effectively young women are using their chosen 
contraceptive method. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This research was supported by two grants from the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development 
(R01 HD050329, R01 HD050329-S1, PI Barber), a grant from the National Institute on Drug Abuse (R21 
DA024186, PI Axinn), and a population center grant from the National Institute of Child Health and Human 
Development to the University of Michigan's Population Studies Center (R24 HD041028). We thank N.E. Barr for 
valuable editing assistance, and John Casterline and Ann Biddlecom for helpful comments on an earlier draft of the 
paper. We gratefully acknowledge the Survey Research Operations (SRO) unit at the Survey Research Center of the 
Institute for Social Research for their help with the data collection, particularly Vivienne Outlaw, Sharon Parker, 
and Meg Stephenson. We also gratefully acknowledge the intellectual contributions of the other members of the 
original RDSL project team, including William Axinn, Mick Couper, and Steven Heeringa, as well as the Advisory 
Committee for the project: Larry Bumpass, Elizabeth Cooksey, Kathie Harris, and Linda Waite. </p>



<p>Gatny et al. </p>

<p>
Demogr Res. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 20. </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Miller WB, Barber JS, Gatny HH. The effects of ambivalent fertility desires on pregnancy risk in 
young women in the USA. Population studies. 2013; 67(1):25-38.10.1080/00324728.2012.738823 
[PubMed: 23234316] 
National Campaign to Prevent Teen and Unplanned Pregnancy. Fast facts: How is the 3 in 10 statistic 
calculated?. 2011. [electronic resource]. https://grist.files.wordpress.com/2011/10/ 
fastfacts_3in10.pdf </p>

<p>Gatny et al. </p>

<p>
Demogr Res. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 20. </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 1. Categories of the combined responses to the questions measuring pregnancy desires </p>

<p>Gatny et al. </p>

<p>
Demogr Res. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 20. </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Gatny et al. </p>

<p>
Table 1 </p>

<p>Percent of sample experiencing unintended pregnancy and pregnancy scares (n=901) </p>

<p>Percent </p>

<p>Any unintended pregnancy 
13 </p>

<p>Number of unintended pregnancies (among those who experienced any unintended pregnancy, N= 114) </p>

<p>1 unintended pregnancy 
89 </p>

<p>2 unintended pregnancies 
11 </p>

<p>Any pregnancy scare 
9 </p>

<p>Number of pregnancy scares (among those who experienced any pregnancy scare, N= 85) </p>

<p>1 pregnancy scare 
78 </p>

<p>2 pregnancy scares 
13 </p>

<p>3-4 pregnancy scares 
9 </p>

<p>Demogr Res. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 20. </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Gatny et al. </p>

<p>
Table 2 </p>

<p>Sociodemographic characteristics and adolescent pregnancy-related experiences </p>

<p>Total Sample (n=901) </p>

<p>Subsample who did not 
experience a pregnancy 
scare (n=816) </p>

<p>Subsample who experienced 
a pregnancy scare (n=85) 
p-value </p>

<p>% 
% 
% </p>

<p>Sociodemographic Characteristics </p>

<p>African American 
.34 
.32 
.54 *** </p>

<p>Bio mom &lt;20 years old at 1st birth 
.36 
.34 
.52 *** </p>

<p>Two-parent childhood family structure 
.53 
.56 
.28 *** </p>

<p>High school GPA a 
3.17 b 
3.20 
2.93 *** </p>

<p>Currently receiving public assistance 
.26 
.24 
.40 *** </p>

<p>Living with partner 
.17 
.15 
.27 *** </p>

<p>Adolescent Pregnancy-Related Experiences </p>

<p>Age at first sex ≤ 16 years 
.52 
.50 
.72 *** </p>

<p>Two or more sexual partners 
.59 
.57 
.79 *** </p>

<p>Ever had sex without birth control 
.47 
.45 
.71 *** </p>

<p>1 or more prior pregnancies 
.25 
.23 
.44 *** </p>

<p>Note: + p &lt; 0.10; </p>

<p>* p &lt; 0.05; </p>

<p>** 
p &lt; 0.01; </p>

<p>*** p &lt; 0.001 (one-tailed independent samples t-tests for significant differences between the two subsamples) </p>

<p>a mean GPA presented for sample and subsamples; </p>

<p>b std. dev.=.59 </p>

<p>Demogr Res. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 20. </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Gatny et al. </p>

<p>
Table 3 </p>

<p>Regression coefficients for models of any pregnancy scare (logistic) and number of 
pregnancy scares (poisson) (N=901) </p>

<p>(1) Any Pregnancy Scare (2) Number of Pregnancy Scares </p>

<p>Sociodemographic Characteristics </p>

<p>African American 
.67 *** (.27) 
.81 *** (.21) </p>

<p>Bio mom &lt;20 years old at 1st birth 
.30 (.25) 
.18 (.20) </p>

<p>Two-parent childhood family structure 
-.75 *** (.28) 
-.84 *** (.24) </p>

<p>High school GPA 
-.50 *** (.18) 
-.36 *** (.14) </p>

<p>Currently receiving public assistance 
-.07 (.30) 
-.17 (.24) </p>

<p>Living with partner 
.58 *** (.30) 
.49 *** (.24) </p>

<p>Adolescent Pregnancy-Related Experiences </p>

<p>Age at first sex ≤ 16 years 
.14 (.33) 
.16 (.27) </p>

<p>Two or more sexual partners 
.41 (.35) 
.39  † (.29) </p>

<p>Ever had sex without birth control 
.48  † (.31) 
.67 *** (.26) </p>

<p>1 or more prior pregnancies 
.36 (.30) 
.15 (.24) </p>

<p>Other </p>

<p>Total number of journals completed 
.01 *** (.00) 
.01 *** (.00) </p>

<p>χ 2 
66.36 
100.06 </p>

<p>Pseudo-R 2 
.12 
.14 </p>

<p>Note: Standard errors in parentheses. </p>

<p> † p &lt; 0.10; </p>

<p>* p &lt; 0.05; </p>

<p>** p &lt; 0.01; </p>

<p>*** p &lt; 0.001 (one-tailed tests) </p>

<p>Demogr Res. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 20. </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>NIH-PA Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Gatny et al. </p>

<p>
Table 4 </p>

<p>Logistic regression coefficients (additive effects on log-odds) for models of the hazard of 
unintended pregnancy (N=901 individuals, 34,943 observations) </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>Any pregnancy scare 
.99 *** (.26) 
.79 *** (.28) 
.73 *** (.28) </p>

<p>Sociodemographic Characteristics </p>

<p>African American 
.41 ** (.24) 
.36 + (.23) 
.36 + (.24) </p>

<p>Bio mom &lt;20 years old at 1st birth 
.30 + (.22) 
.35 + (.22) 
.29 + (.22) </p>

<p>Two-parent childhood family structure 
-0.12 (.23) 
-.16 (.23) 
-.07 (.23) </p>

<p>High school GPA 
-0.28 ** (.17) 
-.28 * (.16) 
-.23 + (.17) </p>

<p>Currently receiving public assistance 
.35 + (.26) 
.36 + (.26) 
.34 + (.26) </p>

<p>Living with partner 
.58 ** (.26) 
.67 ** (.26) 
.53 ** (.26) </p>

<p>Adolescent Pregnancy-Related Experiences </p>

<p>Age at first sex 16 years or less 
.58 ** (.30) 
.55 ** (.30) </p>

<p>Two or more sexual partners 
.55 ** (.31) 
.56 ** (.30) </p>

<p>Ever had sex without birth control 
.30 (.27) 
.24 (.27) </p>

<p>1 or more prior pregnancies 
.52 ** (.27) 
1.31 *** (.21) .85 *** (.25) 
.52 ** (.27) </p>

<p>Other </p>

<p>Time in study 
.25 *** (.08) 
.21 *** (.08) 
.23 *** (.08) 
.24 *** (.08) </p>

<p>Time in study 2 
-0.01 ** (.00) 
-.01 ** (.00) 
-.01 ** (.00) 
-.01 ** (.00) </p>

<p>Total number of journals completed 
-0.02 *** (.00) -.02 *** (.00) -.02 *** (.00) -.02 *** (.00) </p>

<p>χ 2 
127.53 
141.97 
133.22 
128.96 </p>

<p>Log-likelihood 
-731.27 
-746.23 
-736.33 
-728.00 </p>

<p>Note: Standard errors in parentheses. </p>

<p>+ p &lt; 0.10; </p>

<p>* p &lt; 0.05; </p>

<p>** p &lt; 0.01; </p>

<p>*** p &lt; 0.001 (one-tailed tests) </p>

<p>Demogr Res. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 20. </p>

</text></tei>