<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4201231" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Patients suffering from diabetes mellitus usually develop 
severe complications such as microvascular and macrovas-
cular diseases, retinopathy, liver and brain dysfunctions, and 
neuropathy (Gerbitz et al., 1995; Toth et al., 2006). Periph-
eral neuropathy is one of the most common complications of 
diabetes mellitus, with nerve damage developing in over 50% 
of all diabetic patients. It is associated with chronic aberrant 
sensations, numbness, and pain, which affect quality of life, 
disrupt sleep, and can lead to depression (Vinik et al., 1995;  Vinik et al., 2000; Calcutt, 2004; Canta et al., 2009). Currently, 
drugs for diabetic neuropathy have been limited to those that 
reduce pain and relieve other symptoms. The antiepileptics 
gabapentin (GABA) and the antioxidant α-lipoic acid (LA) are 
common drugs used to ameliorate the symptoms of diabet-
ic neuropathy. However, GABA has been reported to cause 
side effects such as dizziness, fatigue, and peripheral edema 
(FDA, 2009). LA can cause nausea or stomach upset, fatigue, </p>

<p>and insomnia (Singh and Jialal, 2008). Therefore, research is 
underway to find safer candidates for the treatment of diabetic 
peripheral neuropathy. 
The pathological processes of diabetic peripheral neuropa-
thy are not yet fully understood. However, possible etiologic 
factors have been suggested. They include long-standing hy-
perglycemia, increased flux of the polyol pathway, enhanced 
non-enzymatic advanced glycation end-product formation, 
free radical and oxidative stress, and impaired nerve growth 
factor (NGF) support (Zorrilla Hernandez et al., 1994; Sima  and Sugimoto, 1999; van Dam, 2002; Obrosova, 2003; Vin- cent et al., 2004). Several studies suggest that NGF deficien-
cy may be one of the major risk factors for the development of 
diabetic neuropathy (Hellweg and Hartung, 1990; Apfel et al.,  1994; Hellweg et al., 1994; Ordonez et al., 1994; Anand et al.,  1996). NGF levels in the sciatic nerve of experimental diabetic 
animals with neuropathy decreased significantly in compari-
son with those in normal animals. When diabetic animals were 
treated with NGF or enhancers of endogenous NGF synthe-</p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Biomol Ther 22(5), 445-452 (2014) </p>

<p>* Corresponding Author </p>

<p>E-mail: sunnykim@gachon.ac.kr 
Tel: +82-32-899-6411, Fax: +82-32-899-6591 
 † The first two authors contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>Received May 7, 2014 Revised Jun 30, 2014 Accepted Jul 4, 2014 
Published online Sep 30, 2014 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2014.051 </p>

<p>Copyright © 2014 The Korean Society of Applied Pharmacology </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Com-
mons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licens-
es/by-nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, 
and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>The purpose of this study was to investigate the therapeutic effects of DA-9801, an optimized extract of Dioscorea species, on 
diabetic peripheral neuropathy in a type 2 diabetic animal model. In this study, db/db mice were treated with DA-9801 (30 and 100 
mg/kg, daily, p.o.) for 12 weeks. DA-9801 reduced the blood glucose levels and increased the withdrawal latencies in hot plate 
tests. Moreover, it prevented nerve damage based on increased nerve conduction velocity and ultrastructural changes. Decrease 
of nerve growth factor (NGF) may have a detrimental effect on diabetic neuropathy. We previously reported NGF regulatory prop-
erties of the Dioscorea genus. In this study, DA-9801 induced NGF production in rat primary astrocytes. In addition, it increased 
NGF levels in the sciatic nerve and the plasma of type 2 diabetic animals. DA-9801 also increased neurite outgrowth and mRNA 
expression of Tieg1/Klf10, an NGF target gene, in PC12 cells. These results demonstrated the attenuation of diabetic peripheral 
neuropathy by oral treatment with DA-9801 via NGF regulation. DA-9801 is currently being evaluated in a phase II clinical study. </p>

<p>Key Words: DA-9801, Dioscorea japonica Thunb, Dioscorea nipponica Makino, Diabetic peripheral neuropathy, Nerve growth factor, 
Type 2 diabetes mellitus </p>

<p>Dioscorea Extract (DA-9801) Modulates Markers of Peripheral 
Neuropathy in Type 2 Diabetic db/db Mice </p>

<p>Eunjung Moon 
1, † , Sung Ok Lee 
2, † , Tong Ho Kang 
3 , Hye Ju Kim 
4 , Sang Zin Choi 
4 , Mi-Won Son </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>and Sun Yeou Kim </p>

<p>1,5, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1 College of Pharmacy, Gachon University, Incheon 406-799, 
2 Graduate School of East-West Medical Science, 
3 College of Life Sciences, Kyung Hee University Global Campus, Yongin 446-701, 
4 Dong-A Pharm Institute, Yongin 446-905, 
5 Gachon Medical Research Institute, Gil Medical Center, Incheon 406-799, Republic of Korea </p>

<p>Abstract </p>



<p>Biomol Ther 22(5), 445-452 (2014) </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2014.051 </p>

<p>sis, neuropathy-related abnormalities such as reduced nerve 
conduction velocity, atrophy of myelinated nerve fi bers and 
axons, and dysesthesia were statistically signifi cantly allevi-
ated compared with that in untreated animals (Pearlstone et  al., 1992; Apfel et al., 1994; Kakinoki et al., 2006). 
In oriental medicine, the dried rhizome of Dioscorea ja-
ponica Thunb (D. japonica, known as "SanYak" in Korea) is 
a representative nourishing and tonifying herb. Its taste is 
sweet, and its nature is neutral. It supplements Ki, fortifi es the 
spleen, supplements the lungs and the kidney, and secures 
the essence. It has been traditionally used for diarrhea and 
dysentery due to spleen defi ciency, fatigue, coughing and 
wheezing, wasting and thirsting, seminal emission, vaginal 
discharge, and frequent urination. The dried rhizome of Di-
oscorea nipponica Makino (D. nipponica) is called "Buchema" 
in Korea, and is an herb for clearing and transforming phlegm-
heat. Its taste is bitter and its nature is cold. It dissipates lumps 
and disperses goiter, clears heat, relieves toxicity, cools the 
blood, stops bleeding and coughing, and calms wheezing. It 
has been applied for goiter and scrofula, swelling and toxins 
of sores, poisonous snake bites, bleeding due to blood-heat, 
and whooping cough (Xu and Wang, 2002). Many species of 
Dioscorea have traditionally been used clinically in Asia for 
the treatment of various syndromes related to metabolic dis-
eases. Moreover, the extracts of the Dioscorea species have 
been reported to have antidiabetic and antiobesity effects 
(Hikino et al., 1986; Gao et al., 2007; Maithili et al., 2011). In 
particular, D. japonica has inhibitory activities on polyuria and 
diabetes (Kim, 1998) and D. nipponica has antiobesity proper-
ties (Jung et al., 2003). Previously, we reported that furostanol 
saponins isolated from D. japonica upregulated NGF contents 
in rat glioma C6 cells (Kim et al., 2011a) and diosgenin from 
D. nipponica ameliorated diabetic neuropathy by increasing 
the endogenous NGF levels in streptozotocin (STZ)-induced 
diabetic mice (Kang et al., 2011). Therefore, we proposed that 
these two Dioscorea species might improve various symp-
toms of diabetic neuropathy via NGF regulation. Through 
activity-guided in vivo screening, we selected an optimized 
combination drug DA-9801, a mixture of D. japonica and D. 
nipponica (KR Patent No. 10-1341692-0000). NGF agonistic 
activities of DA-9801 in PC12 cells and dorsal root ganglion 
neurons were recently reported (Kim et al., 2011b). Jin et al.  also reported that oral treatment with DA-9801 had therapeu-
tic potential for peripheral neuropathy in a representative type 
1 diabetic animal model, STZ-induced diabetic rats (Jin et al.,  2013). According to this report, DA-9801 improved tactile and 
thermal hyperalgesia, and blunted the morphological changes 
and the reduction of intraepidermal nerve fi ber density. More-
over, it increased NGF and decreased tumor necrosis factor α 
and interleukin-6 protein levels in the sciatic nerve and spinal 
cord. These results indicated that DA-9801 might prevent pe-
ripheral neuropathy in STZ-induced diabetic rats via enhance-
ment of neurotrophic activity and anti-infl ammatory response. 
Previously, our group described that DA-9801 improved nerve 
conduction velocity (NCV) signifi cantly in type 2 diabetic db/ 
db mice (Choi and Son, 2011). However, further investiga-
tions of DA-9801 in peripheral neuropathy in type 2 diabetic 
animal models have not been reported. Because of the higher 
prevalence of type 2 diabetes than type 1, it is very importance 
to check the impact of DA-9801 on type 2 diabetes. There-
fore, the purpose of this study was to investigate the effect of 
DA-9801 on improvement of peripheral neuropathy in type 2 </p>

<p>diabetic db/db mice. In particular, to determine its therapeutic 
mechanism, we focused on the NGF regulatory activity of DA-
9801. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>Dried D. japonica and D. nipponica were purchased at a 
specialty market for traditional herbal medicine (Kyungdong 
herb market, Seoul, Korea), and their identity was confi rmed 
by Dr. Changsoo Yuk (a specialist in plant classifi cation, 
Kyung Hee University, Seoul, Korea). Roswell Park Memo-
rial Institute (RPMI) 1640 medium and Minimum Essential 
medium-α (MEM-α), fetal bovine serum (FBS), horse serum 
(HS), and penicillin-streptomycin (PS) were purchased from 
Gibco-BRL (Gaithersburg, MD, USA). Specifi c primers (NGF, 
Tieg1/Klf10, and GAPDH), M-MLV reverse transcriptase and 
Taq DNA polymerase were purchased from TaKaRa (TaKaRa, 
Shiga, Japan). The rat β-NGF enzyme-linked immunosorbent 
assay development kit was obtained from R&amp;D Systems (Min-
neapolis, MN, USA). The other chemicals used in this study 
were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). </p>

<p>Preparation of DA-9801 </p>

<p>A preparation of the rhizome mixture of dried Dioscorea 
species, D. japonica and D. nipponica, was extracted with 
50% aqueous ethanol at room temperature for 48 h. The ex-
tracts were fi ltered and concentrated using a rotary vacuum 
evaporator. The DA-9801 voucher specimen was deposited 
at Dong-A Pharmaceutical (Youngin, Korea). The yield of to-
tal extracts (DA-9801) was 10.0%. A high-performance liquid 
chromatography analysis was performed for quantitative de-
termination of dioscin and allantoin, the marker components of 
D. japonica and D. nipponica, in DA-9801. DA-9801 contained 
0.829% dioscin and 2.711% allantoin (Fig. S1). </p>

<p>Animals and drug administration </p>

<p>Nine-week old male db/db mice (C57BLKS/J Iar-+Lepr </p>

<p>db </p>

<p>/+Lepr 
db ) were purchased from Japan SLC, Inc. (Hamamat-
su, Japan). We performed all procedures in the animal ex-
periments in accordance with the Laboratory Animal Care and 
Use Guideline of Kyung Hee University, Korea. Animals show-
ing blood glucose levels of ≥300 mg/dl were used as diabetic 
models in this study. 
DB/DB mice were divided into 5 groups (n=10/group): a con-
trol group that received vehicle and four drug groups that re-
ceived DA-9801 extract (30 and 100 mg/kg), α-lipoic acid (LA, 
50 mg/kg) and gabapentin (GABA, 100 mg/kg), respectively. 
In this study, the modulators of diabetic neuropathy, α-lipoic 
acid and gabapentin, were used as positive controls. The oral 
administration of vehicle or drugs was performed once per day 
for 12 weeks. We measured body weight and blood glucose 
levels of animals during the experimental period. </p>

<p>Behavioral tests </p>

<p>Hot plate tests were performed using a modifi cation of the 
methods reported by Hayes (Hayes et al., 1987). The hot plate 
apparatus, and analgesy-meter were purchased from Ugo 
Basile (Comerio, Italy). </p>



<p>Moon et al. DA-9801 Improves Neuropathy in db/db Mice </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>Measurements of nerve conduction velocity in motor and 
sensory nerves </p>

<p>The NCV tests were performed using the methods reported 
by Kang (Kang et al., 2011). Animals were anesthetized using 
a combination of 1.5% isofluorane (Choongwae Pharma Co., 
Seoul, Korea) with 70% N 2 O and 30% O 2 gas using a gas 
anesthesia machine (Tabletop research anesthesia machine 
sets, SurgiVet, USA). Then, their motor and sensory nerves 
were isolated. Each isolated nerve was connected to a stimu-
lator and sensor probes with aeration. The distance between 
the sensor and stimulator probes was 15.0 mm. A digital stor-
age oscilloscope (Tektronix 2211, Madell Technology Co., 
Ontario, CA, USA) was used to record the conduction times 
(3-5V stimulation and 5 milliseconds duration). The NCV was 
calculated based on the time and the distance between the 
electrodes. </p>

<p>Morphometric analysis in the sciatic nerves </p>

<p>Morphometric analysis in the sciatic nerves was also per-
formed using the methods reported by Kang (Kang et al.,  2011). For examination of the sciatic nerve morphology, iso-
lated sciatic nerves from db/db mice were immersed in fixative 
(2.5% glutaraldehyde) and incubated at 4 
o C for 12 h. There-
after, each specimen was immersed in 2% osmium tetroxide 
in 0.1 M phosphate buffer for 2 h at 4 
o C, dehydrated, and em-
bedded. Following polymerization, ultrathin sections (50-60 
nm thick) were cut and stained with uranyl acetate and lead 
citrate. The sciatic nerve morphology was examined using 
transmission electron microscopy (H7100, Hitachi, Ibaraki, Ja-
pan), and the diameter and the thickness of the myelin sheath 
in the sciatic nerve were also measured. </p>

<p>NGF assay in animal models </p>

<p>To investigate the effect of DA-9801 on NGF production in 
animals, the sciatic nerves and the plasma of diabetic mice 
were isolated. Then, NGF concentrations were measured us-
ing an NGF ELISA kit. Briefly, tissue samples were homog-
enized in NGF lysis buffer (Tris-HCl 100 mM, bovine serum al-
bumin 2%, NaCl 1 M, EDTA-2Na2H 2 O 4 mM, Triton X-100 2%, 
sodium azide 0.1%, pH 7.0, and phenylmethylsulfonylfluoride 
17 mg/ml) and centrifuged; the supernatant was subjected to 
ELISA in 96-well plates according to the manufacturer's in-
structions. </p>

<p>Cell culture and in vitro assay </p>

<p>The primary astrocytes were cultured from the cerebral cor-
tices of neonatal Sprague-Dawley (Crl:SD) rats (1-day-old) in 
MEM-α containing 10% fetal bovine serum and 1% penicillin/ 
streptomicyn. PC12 cells were cultured in RPMI 1640 with 5% 
FBS, 10% HS and 1% PS. All cells were maintained in 5% 
CO 2 incubator at 37 
o C. 
To evaluate the effects of DA-9801 on NGF induction, pri-
mary astrocytes were seeded onto 24-well plates at a density 
of 1×10 
5 cells/well. After 24 h, cells were treated with various 
concentrations of DA-9801 in MEM-α containing 2% FBS and 
1% PS. The media were collected after 24 h incubation, and 
the supernatant of the harvested media was used for NGF de-
termination. The level of secreted NGF in conditioned media 
was determined using a β-NGF ELISA development kit and 
calculated from the standard curve. To detect NGF mRNA 
expression, we treated primary astrocyte cells with DA-9801 
for 2 h. Total RNA was extracted and first-strand cDNA was </p>

<p>synthesized using TRIzol reagent and M-MLV reverse tran-
scriptase. Then, cDNA was amplified using NGF-specific 
primer, dNTP mixture and Taq DNA polymerase. The primer 
sets were as follows: NGF, forward, 5'-TGGCCAGTGGTCGT-
GCAGTC-3'; reverse, 5'-AAGTCAGCCTCTTGCAGC-3'. The 
twenty six cycles of PCR were performed (for NGF: denatur-
ation at 95 
o C for 30 s; annealing at 60 
o C; extension at 72 
o C for 
160 s; for GAPDH: denaturation at 95 
o C for 30 s; annealing at 
56 
o C; extension at 72 
o C for 160 s). The twenty six-cycle reac-
tion was followed by a final extension step at 72 
o C for 300 s. 
PCR amplicons were separated by agarose gel electrophore-
sis and visualized using ethidium bromide staining. 
To investigate the effect of DA-9801 on neurite outgrowth, 
PC12 cells (1×10 
5 cells/well) were seeded onto 6-well poly-
D-lysine-coated plates. After 24 hours, the cells were treated 
with DA-9801 plus 2 ng/ml NGF in RPMI1640 medium con-
taining 1% FBS, 2% HS and 1% PS. The neurite outgrowth 
per cell was observed every other day, and at 4 days, micro-
photographs were obtained from 10 random fields for each 
cell group. To detect Tieg1/Klf10 mRNA expression, PC12 
cells were treated with DA-9801 (10, 100, and 200 μg/ml) 
and NGF (50 ng/ml) for 6 h. The primer sets were as follows: 
Tieg1/Klf10, forward, 5'-CACAGGGGAAAAAACCTTTCA-3', 
reverse, 5'-ACTTCCATTTGCCAGTTTGG-3'. Twenty six cy-
cles of PCR were performed for Tieg1/Klf10: denaturation at 
95 
o C for 45 s; annealing at 60 
o C; extension at 72 
o C for 180 s. 
The twenty six-cycle reaction was followed by a final exten-
sion step at 72 
o C for 300 s. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>In vivo data were expressed as mean ± S.E.M. Statistical 
comparisons between different groups were performed using 
a one-way ANOVA test followed by Newman-Keuls multiple 
range test. Values with a superscript are significantly differ-
ent from the control group ( </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05, </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>p&lt;0.01 and 
C p&lt;0.001) 
or LA-treated group ( 
a p&lt;0.05 and 
b p&lt;0.01) or GABA-treated 
group ( </p>

<p>α </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05, </p>

<p>β </p>

<p>p&lt;0.01 and 
γ p&lt;0.001). In vitro data were ex-
pressed as mean ± S.D. A Student's t-test was used for sta-
tistical analyses for in vitro and sciatic nerves morphometric 
assays. *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01 and ***p&lt;0.001 indicate statistically 
significant differences from the control group. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Effects of DA-9801 on blood glucose level in type 2 dia-
betic db/db mice </p>

<p>To evaluate the effects of DA-9801 on peripheral neuropa-
thy in type 2 diabetes, we first measured the body weight and 
blood glucose levels in db/db mice at last administration. All 
samples had no effect on body weight of animals (data not 
shown). However, DA-9801 treatment significantly reduced 
blood glucose levels. Blood glucose concentration of control 
mice was 423.9 ± 35.0 mg/dl. However, the blood glucose 
concentrations of DA-9801-treated mice were 317.0 ± 25.4 
and 311.2 ± 25.3 mg/dl at doses of 30 and 100 mg/kg. LA and 
GABA had no influence on blood glucose levels (Fig. 1A). </p>

<p>Effects of DA-9801 on neuropathic pain in type 2 diabetic 
db/db mice </p>

<p>We also performed thermal hyperalgesia test to evaluate 
the effect of DA-9801 treatment on peripheral neuropathic </p>



<p>Biomol Ther 22(5), 445-452 (2014) </p>



<p>pain in type 2 diabetes. As shown in Fig. 1B, oral administra-
tion of DA-9801 significantly increased the thermal response 
latencies in the hot plate assay compared with control group. 
Latency time of control mice was 12.7 ± 1.6 sec, while those 
of DA-9801 30 and 100 mg/kg-treated groups were 23.7 ± 4.1 
and 28.0 ± 5.4 sec. Latency times of LA and GABA-treated 
mice were 15.4 ± 1.8 and 16.1 ± 2.7 sec, respectively. </p>

<p>Effects of DA-9801 on nerve conduction velocity in type 2 
diabetic db/db mice </p>

<p>To investigate the effects of DA-9801 on NCV, we admin-
istered DA-9801 (30 and 100 mg/kg) to db/db mice and mea-
sured NCV in motor and sensory nerves. As shown in Fig. 1C, 
treatment with DA-9801 strongly induced nerve conductivity. </p>

<p>The motor and sensory NCVs were 20.3 ± 0.3 and 22.4 ± 0.3 
m/sec in control mice. However, mice treated with DA-9801 30 
mg/kg had motor NCV of 29.3 ± 0.4 m/sec and sensory NCV 
of 31.2 ± 0.5 m/sec. The effects of DA-9801 on NCV might be 
independent of dose. Although the motor and sensory NCVs 
were 24.0 ± 0.3 and 24.9 ± 0.6 m/sec at dose of 100 mg/kg of 
DA-9801, there was no statistically significant difference be-
tween these and the control group. The LA-and GABA-treated 
groups had NCVs of 24.7 ± 0.3 and 22.4 ± 0.4 m/sec in motor 
nerves and 24.8 ± 0.3 and 25.4 ± 0.4 m/sec in sensory nerves, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Effects of DA-9801 on diabetic peripheral neuropathy in type 2 diabetic db/db mice. To investigate the effects of DA-9801 on the </p>

<p>improvement of diabetic peripheral neuropathy, we administered DA-9801 (30 and 100 mg/kg) once per day orally for 12 weeks in type 2 
diabetic db/db mice. Then we evaluated (A) the blood glucose levels and (B) the thermal hyperalgesia latencies using hot plate test, and 
measured (C) nerve conduction velocity (NCV) in motor and sensory nerves. Statistical comparisons between different groups were per-
formed using a one-way ANOVA test followed by Newman-Keuls multiple range test. Values with a superscript are significantly different from 
the control group ( </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05 and </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>p&lt;0.01) or LA-treated group ( 
a p&lt;0.05) or GABA-treated group ( </p>

<p>α </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05). We also confirmed (D) the sciatic 
nerve histology using electron microscopy, and then (E) the axon diameter and (F) the thickness of the myelin sheath in the sciatic nerves. 
*p&lt;0.05 and **p&lt;0.01 indicate statistically significant differences from the control group (Student's t-test). α-Lipoic acid (LA, 50 mg/kg) and 
gabapentin (GABA, 100 mg/kg) were used as positive controls. All data are expressed as mean ± S.E.M. </p>



<p>Moon et al. DA-9801 Improves Neuropathy in db/db Mice </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>Effects of DA-9801 on histological changes in the sciatic 
nerves of type 2 diabetic db/db mice </p>

<p>In this study, the ultrastructural changes of sciatic nerves 
after treatment with DA-9801 were evaluated by electron mi-
croscopy in db/db mice. As shown in Fig. 1D, DA-9801 treat-
ment improved the loss of the myelin sheath and axon, and 
the increase of endoneural space. Moreover, the diameter and 
thickness of the myelin sheath were increased in DA-9801-</p>

<p>treated mice compared with diabetic control mice (Fig. 1E, F). 
These responses were also independent of the dose of DA-
9801. </p>

<p>Effects of DA-9801 on NGF regulation in vitro and in dia-
betic animal models </p>

<p>To investigate the effect of DA-9801 on NGF regulation, 
we first tested the effect of samples on the induction of NGF </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Effects of DA-9801 on NGF regulation. To determine the effect of DA-9801 on NGF production, rat primary astrocytes were treated </p>

<p>with various concentrations of DA-9801. After 24 h, (A) NGF content in the medium was measured using a rat βNGF assay kit. (B) NGF 
mRNA expression was confirmed via reverse transcription PCR after 2 h of DA-9801 treatment. Also, we measured (C) NGF levels in the 
sciatic nerves and (D) the plasma of DA-9801-treated db/db mice. To investigate the NGF-mimetic activity of DA-9801, we treated PC12 
cells with 125 μg/ml of DA-9801. The neurite outgrowth per cell was observed every other day, and (E) images were taken of randomly se-
lected fields using a camera attached to a microscope at 4 days. (F) The neurite length was determined using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Optimas</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">6.5</rs> program (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Media Cybernetics</rs>, MD, USA). The differentiation of PC12 cells was scored as follows: cells without neurite outgrowth (0); cells bearing neurites 
as long as one cell diameter (1); cells bearing neurites two times longer in length than their diameter (2); and cells that had synapse-like 
neurites (4). (G) We also detected Tieg1/Klf10 mRNA by reverse transcription PCR after 6 h of DA-9801 treatment. In this study, 50 ng/ml 
NGF was used as a positive control. (A) and (F) were expressed as mean ± S.D. and ***p&lt;0.001 indicate statistically significant differences 
from the control group (Student's t-test). (C) and (D) were expressed as mean ± S.E.M. Statistical comparisons between different groups 
were performed using a one-way ANOVA test followed by Newman-Keuls multiple range test. ( </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05, </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>p&lt;0.01 and 
C p&lt;0.001 compared 
with control mice. 
a p&lt;0.05 and 
b p&lt;0.01 compared with LA-treated mice. </p>

<p>α </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05, </p>

<p>β </p>

<p>p&lt;0.01 and 
γ p&lt;0.001 compared with GABA-treated mice). </p>



<p>Biomol Ther 22(5), 445-452 (2014) </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2014.051 </p>

<p>in primary astrocytes isolated from cerebral cortices of neo-
natal rats. As shown in Fig. 2A, treatment with DA-9801 sig-
nificantly increased NGF secretion. The contents of NGF in 
the medium were 31.7 ± 5.8 pg/ml in control cells and 319.6 
± 2.3 and 609.4 ± 57.1 pg/ml in DA-9801-treated cells (100 
and 200 mg/ml), respectively. Moreover, DA-9801 increased 
NGF mRNA expression in a dose-dependent manner in rat 
primary astrocytes (Fig. 2B). We also measured NGF levels in 
the sciatic nerves and the plasma of db/db mice treated with 
DA-9801. Our results showed that NGF levels in the sciatic 
nerves were increased by oral administration of DA-9801. The 
NGF content was 6.2 ± 0.5 pg/ml in control mice. However, 
the DA-9801-treated mice secreted 9.9 ± 0.3 pg/ml (DA-9801 
30 mg/kg) and 11.6 ± 1.0 pg/ml of NGF (DA-9801 100 mg/kg), 
respectively (Fig. 2C). In the plasma of db/db mice, NGF con-
centration was also increased by treatment with DA-9801 100 
mg/kg (Fig. 2D). In both the sciatic nerves and the plasma of 
db/db mice, LA and GABA had no influence on NGF induction. 
We also evaluated NGF-mimetic activities of DA-9801 us-
ing PC12 cells, which respond to NGF by flattening their cell 
bodies and extending neurite-like processes (Traverse et al.,  1992). As shown in Fig. 2E and F, we confirmed increases in 
the neurite length after treatment with DA-9801. The response 
of PC12 cells treated with DA-9801 (125 mg/ml) was similar 
to that of the cells treated with NGF (50 ng/ml). We also as-
sessed Tieg1/Klf10 mRNA levels in PC12 cells after treatment 
with DA-9801 for 6 h. Tieg1/Klf10 is an NGF target gene via 
the TrkA signaling pathway in PC12 cells (Spittau et al., 2010). 
As shown in Fig. 2G, DA-9801 increased Tieg1/Klf10 mRNA 
expression in a dose-dependent manner. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>One of the important pathological factors of diabetic neu-
ropathy is nerve damage. Nerve damage such as the loss and 
centripetal degeneration of small myelinated axons in diabetic 
neuropathy is likely associated with a marked deprivation of 
NGF. Jin et al. reported the therapeutic potential of DA-9801 
on the peripheral neuropathy via enhancement of neurotroph-
ic activity in STZ-induced diabetic rats, a representative type 
1 diabetic model (Jin et al., 2013). To extend the research on 
DA-9801, we investigated whether DA-9801 had therapeutic 
activity for peripheral neuropathy via NGF regulation in db/ 
db mice, a type 2 diabetic animal model. In the present study, 
oral administration of DA-9801 significantly reduced hyperal-
gesia by increasing the response latency to noxious thermal 
stimuli in db/db mice. DA-9801-administrated group showed 
higher NCVs of sensory and motor nerves than each diabetic 
control group. Accordingly, DA-9801 may have a therapeutic 
effect on nerve injury due to diabetic neuropathy by increasing 
the transmission speed of the nerves of db/db mice. Moreover, 
the therapeutic effect of the DA-9801 on the neuropathy was 
identified by measuring the histological change of the sciatic 
nerves. Namely, in the DA-9801-treated groups, the axon and 
the myelin sheath in the central part of the sciatic nerve clearly 
expanded. These data show that DA-9801 can protect and 
treat the shrunken sciatic nerves in the neuropathy in type 2 
diabetic condition. Moreover, DA-9801 increased NGF pro-
duction in rat primary astrocytes. In addition, the amounts of 
endogenous NGF in the sciatic nerves and the plasma of DA-
9801-treated db/db mice were significantly higher than that of </p>

<p>control mice. Therefore, our results indicate that oral treatment 
with DA-9801 might improve peripheral neuropathy by sup-
pressing the degeneration and death of neurons in type 2 dia-
betes via NGF induction. 
Type 2 diabetes is the most common form of diabetes, ac-
counting for about 90% of all diabetes cases. Its main patho-
logical cause is insulin resistance which associated with aging, 
obesity, and lack of physical activity (Boden, 2001). Therefore, 
the importance of investigating type 2 diabetes and its compli-
cations has increased markedly with the trends of an increas-
ingly aging and obese society. Previously, Jin et al. reported 
that oral treatment with DA-9801 at a single dose of 100 mg/ 
kg/day for 16 weeks had therapeutic properties for peripheral 
neuropathy in STZ-induced diabetic rats via enhancement of 
neurotrophic activity (Jin et al., 2013). They used Sprague-
Dawley rats injected intraperitoneally with STZ 60 mg/kg in 
their research. Their animal model was a late-state type 2 
diabetic or typical type 1 diabetic model. However, chemical-
induced diabetic animals have some disadvantages in a gen-
eral type 2 diabetes study. Hyperglycemia develops primarily 
by direct cytotoxic actions on the β cells and insulin deficiency, 
rather than as a consequence of insulin resistance. Moreover, 
these animals cannot show the phenotype of obesity. How-
ever, db/db mice, in which diabetes develops spontaneously 
with genetic background, can develop characteristic features 
resembling human type 2 diabetes (Srinivasan and Ramarao,  2007). Therefore, db/db mice are a more suitable animal mod-
el than STZ-induced diabetic rats in the study of human type 
2 diabetes and its complications. Thus, our research showed 
the therapeutic effect of DA-9801 on peripheral neuropathy 
via NGF regulation in general type 2 diabetes. In comparison, 
Jin's research ascertained the attenuation of neuropathy by 
DA-9801 treatment in type 1 and late type 2 diabetes. And to 
conclude, DA-9801 might improve peripheral neuropathy via 
NGF regulation in both type 1 and type 2 diabetes. 
NGF agonistic activities of DA-9801 were recently pub-
lished. In that study, Kim et al. reported that DA-9801 had a 
significant effect on neurite outgrowth and phosphorylation 
of TrkA, a high-affinity catalytic receptor for NGF (Kim et al.,  2011b). In this study, we also found that DA-9801 increased 
neurite outgrowth and NGF target gene Tieg1/Klf10 mRNA 
expression in PC12 cells. These results indicate that DA-
9801 may act not only as an NGF inducer but also as an NGF 
mimetic. Therefore, we suggest that DA-9801 may improve 
diabetic peripheral neuropathy via NGF regulation and that it 
may be used to treat various diabetic complications associ-
ated with NGF deficiency. 
Our study showed that DA-9801 was more active than LA 
and GABA. Until now, drugs to target NGF regulation (such as 
NGF inducer or NGF mimetics) in diabetic neuropathy have 
not yet been developed. Therefore, we were confronted with 
difficulty in our study because there was no suitable positive 
control. GABA, as a first line drug for the regulation neuropath-
ic pain, is used to relieve diabetic neuropathic pain. Also, there 
is evidence that LA may help with control of diabetic neuropa-
thy. Therefore, we decided to use GABA and LA as alternative 
positive controls because they are drugs used to ameliorate 
the symptoms of diabetic neuropathy. Sure, GABA or LA is not 
perfect positive control of diabetic neuropathy because of its 
side effects and low efficacy. Considering these aspects, we 
used LA or GABA as a proper positive control. Moreover, the 
therapeutic effects of GABA and/or LA on neuropathic pain in </p>



<p>Moon et al. DA-9801 Improves Neuropathy in db/db Mice </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>db/db mice have not been reported yet. Our study is the first 
to examine the efficacy of these drugs in type 2 diabetic db/ 
db mice. 
In this study, we confirmed the effects of two doses of DA-
9801 on diabetic neuropathy and NGF induction. However, the 
effects of DA-9801 on blood glucose levels, NCVs and nerve 
histology might be independent of the dose. The thermal re-
sponse latencies and NGF levels in sciatic nerves showed in-
creasing tendencies but there was no statistical significance 
between the two doses. These dose-independent effects may 
be caused by various ingredients in DA-9801. Therefore, more 
research on various doses of DA-9801 and its most active 
compounds in diabetic neuropathy are needed in in vivo ani-
mal systems. According to previous studies, we suggest that 
furostanol sapogenins (Kim et al., 2011a) and diosgenin (Kang  et al., 2011) may be the main active components of DA-9801. 
Nerve damage and diabetic neuropathic pain can be in-
duced by various pathological causes such as increased al-
dose reductase activity, angiotensin-converting enzyme acti-
vation, and the proinflammatory response (Obrosova, 2009). 
Previous studies reported that many Dioscorea species exert 
potential activities against these pathological factors in vari-
ous experimental models. Dioscorea opposite prevents the 
increase of serum aldose reductase activity in STZ-induced 
diabetic mice (Hayes et al., 1987). The tuber storage protein 
of Dioscorea alata, dioscorin (Hsu et al., 2002), and red mold 
Dioscorea (Wu et al., 2009) exhibit angiotensin-converting en-
zyme inhibitory activities. Moreover, some Dioscorea species 
and their constituents are known to have anti-inflammatory 
properties (Oh and Lim, 2008; Hiransai et al., 2010; Nguele- fack et al., 2010; Mbiantcha et al., 2011). Considering the previ-
ous references, the inhibitory activities of DA-9801 on diabetic 
neuropathy may be exerted by multi-targeted pharmacological 
activities of the Dioscorea species. Jin et al. also reported that 
DA-9801 had therapeutic properties for peripheral neuropathy 
in STZ-induced diabetic rats via NGF regulation and an anti-
inflammatory response. DA-9801 decreased tumor necrosis 
factor α and interleukin-6 protein levels in the sciatic nerve and 
spinal cord (Jin et al., 2013). Therefore, further studies of the 
potential mechanism of DA-9801, especially its anti-inflamma-
tory properties, in peripheral neuropathy in a type 2 diabetic 
model are needed. Due to the different pathogenesis between 
type 1 diabetes and type 2diabetes, their induced inflamma-
tion may also be followed by different features. Especially, the 
main pathogenesis of type 2 diabetes, insulin resistance, re-
sults in complex alterations of lipid and glucose homeostasis, 
which lead to systemic inflammation (Pedicino et al., 2013). 
In previous comparative study of type 1 diabetes and type 2 
diabetes, the level of an inflammation marker was higher in 
serum of type 2 diabetic patients than in that of type 1 diabetic 
patients (Pedicino et al., 2013). Therefore, if DA-9801 can pro-
mote peripheral neuropathy via its anti-inflammatory activity in 
type 2 diabetes, it is possible that this activity would be more 
sensitive in type 2 diabetes than type 1diabetes. 
This study shows that DA-9801, a novel botanical drug from 
the Dioscorea species, reduced blood glucose levels and in-
creased the response latency to noxious thermal stimuli. It 
also improved peripheral nerve damage by increasing NCVs 
and ameliorating abnormal nerve histology in db/db type 2 dia-
betic mice. These results may have occurred partially due to 
the effect of DA-9801 on NGF regulation. Currently, DA-9801 
is being evaluated in a phase II clinical study. We expect that </p>

<p>DA-9801 can be used as a botanical drug for the treatment of 
diabetic neuropathy. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant from the Korea Health 
21 R&amp;D Project, Ministry of Health and Welfare, Republic of 
Korea (A111082). </p>





<p>Biomol Ther 22(5), 445-452 (2014) </p>



</text></tei>