<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4675816" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract This paper reports investigations into the preparation and characterization of surface 
molecularly imprinted nanoparticles (SMINs) designed to adhere to Helicobacter pylori (H. pylori). 
Imprinted nanoparticles were prepared by the inverse microemulsion polymerization method. A fraction 
of Lpp20, an outer membrane protein of H. pylori known as NQA, was chosen as template and modified 
with myristic acid to facilitate its localization on the surface of the nanoparticles. The interaction between 
these SMINs with the template NQA were evaluated using surface plasmon resonance (SPR), change in 
zeta potential and fluorescence polarization (FP). The results were highly consistent in demonstrating a 
preferential recognition of the template NQA for SMINs compared with the control nanoparticles. In vitro 
experiments also indicate that such SMINs are able to adhere to H. pylori and may be useful for H. pylori 
eradication. </p>

<p>During recent decades, mucoadhesive drug delivery systems 
(MDDS) for Helicobacter pylori (H. pylori) eradication have been 
frequently reported. The ability of MDDS to adhere to the mucus 
layer prolongs their retention time in the gastrointestinal tract and 
thereby enables the loaded drug to interact with H. pylori for a 
longer time. However, this non-specific adhesion is affected not 
only by varying turnover time and composition of mucus but also 
by how the mucoadhesive polymer used to make MDDS responds 
to changes in pH and physiological or disease conditions. Such 
variability seriously limits the application of this technique 
1 . This 
paper reports the results of an investigation into the preparation 
and characterization of surface molecularly imprinted nanoparti-
cles (SMINs) designed to bind to H. pylori. 
Molecular imprinting involves the synthesis of polymers in the 
presence of a template molecule. The process produces polymers 
with surface binding sites that complement those of the template in 
terms of its size, shape and functional group orientation 
2 . 
Molecularly imprinted polymers (MIPs) have been widely recog-
nized as promising alternatives to enzymes, antibodies and natural 
receptors due to their specificity, robustness and reusability 
3 . 
However, most of the successful examples are imprinted with 
low molecular weight compounds while imprinting with larger 
molecules such as peptides and proteins, or with complex systems 
such as viruses and cells is still in its infancy. According to 
Kryscio et al. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>, it is now evident that the general design principles 
of low molecular weight MIPs do not apply to the macromolecular 
regime. The monomers commonly employed in MIPs significantly 
alter the template conformation prior to polymerization and 
compromise the specific recognition of the template. 
Three main approaches have been developed for protein 
imprinting 
2 : (1) Bulk imprinting where the protein template is 
wholly imprinted in the bulk of the polymer matrix and is bound 
as a whole molecule by functional monomers; (2) surface imprint-
ing where the protein template is partially imprinted in the bulk of 
the polymer matrix and binding sites are at or close to the surface; 
and (3) epitope imprinting where only a small part of the protein is 
imprinted but the resulting MIPs are able to recognize the whole 
protein. In bulk imprinting, the binding sites of the template 
proteins tend to be restricted within the polymer matrix and are 
only exposed by grinding the matrix. As a result, surface and 
epitope imprinting have attracted increasing interest. 
To mimic the genuine "antigen-antibody" interaction, it is 
important that well-designed imprints are evenly distributed on 
the surface of SMINs. To achieve this goal, Zeng et al. 
5 initiated a 
so-called "general strategy for surface imprinting" in which a 
hydrophilic peptide could be located at the surface of nanoparticles 
after modification. We have used this approach in preparing 
SMINs. 
Lpp20 is a conserved 20 kDa outer membrane lipoprotein 
antigen specifically expressed by all strains of H. pylori that has 
been shown to act as a potential target for vaccine and pharma-
cotherapy 
6,7 . In our laboratory, an exposed antigenic domain of 
Lpp20 (amino acids 83-115 from the N-terminus, abbreviated as 
NQA) was imprinted on the surface of nanoparticles. According to 
research by our group 
8 and Zeng et al. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>, "surface imprinting" is 
more likely to be achieved during an inverse mini-emulsion 
polymerization process when the template molecules are amphi-
philic. Based on this consideration, the hydrophilic NQA was 
modified with a long hydrocarbon tail (from myristic acid (Myr)) 
and used as the template to imprint surface capture sites for the </p>

<p>entire Lpp20 lipoprotein. Such an epitope imprinting strategy has 
been previously used to capture Staphylococus aureus </p>

<p>9-11 </p>

<p>. 
Some reports have argued that one of the technical challenges in 
molecular imprinting of proteins relates to the quantitation of the 
resulting binding. In many cases, determination of the extent of 
binding is unreliable and leads to unconvincing results 
12 . There-
fore, newly designed approaches to quantitation are required. In 
the current study, several approaches to assess protein-protein 
interactions or the bioadhesive properties of polymers including 
surface plasmon resonance (SPR), fluorescence polarization (FP) 
and changes in zeta potential were applied to evaluate the binding 
of the template to the MIPs. Preliminary in vitro studies were also 
performed to evaluate the efficacy of the MIPs to specifically 
adhere to H. pylori. Further studies on therapeutic drug delivery by 
means of this type of SMINs are underway. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Materials </p>

<p>Acrylamide, N,N′-methylenebisacrylamide (BisAM), ammonium 
persulfate (APS) and N,N,N′,N′-tetramethylethylenediamine 
(TEMED) were purchased from Aladdin Reagents Co., Ltd. 
(Shanghai). 5-Carboxyfluoresccein (FAM) and dioctyl sulfosucci-
nate sodium salt (AOT) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich. Brij 
30 was supplied by J&amp;K Chemicals. NQA (MW 3582 Da, pI 9.5), 
myristic acid modified NQA (Myr-NQA), and FAM modified 
NQA (FAM-NQA) were obtained from GL Biochem. The Biacore 
sensor chip CM5 and HBS-EP buffer were purchased from GE 
Healthcare. All other chemicals and solvents were analytical grade 
and used as received. Deionized water was produced by a Milli-Q 
integral water purification system (Millipore). </p>

<p>2.2. Cell lines and H. pylori strain </p>

<p>Human gastric epithelial (AGS) cells were obtained from the 
Institute of Biochemistry and Cell Biology, Shanghai Institute for 
Biological Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences. Cells were 
maintained in Ham's F-12 medium (GIBCO BRL, Grand Island, 
NY, USA) containing 10% fetal calf serum and cultured in 
incubators maintaining 5% CO 2 under microaerophilic conditions 
at 37 1C. H. pylori strain SS1 was obtained from the Institute of 
Gastrointestinal Disease, Yan Chai Hospital. </p>

<p>2.3. Preparation of nanoparticles </p>

<p>Myr-NQA imprinted nanoparticles (Myr-NQA-MINs) were pre-
pared as previously reported with some modifications 
5 . Briefly, a 
monomer solution was formed by dissolving acrylamide (0.45 g) 
and BisAM (0.13 g) in 1.0 mL water. Myr-NQA (8.0 mg) was 
added to the solution and magnetically stirred to facilitate effective 
monomer-template interaction. Subsequently, 1.0 mL of this 
monomer-template solution was added dropwise to a deoxyge-
nated mixture of hexane (21.5 mL), AOT (0.70 g) and Brij 30 
(1.50 g), and stirred continuously for 30 min. Finally, APS 
solution (10% w/v, 50 μL) followed by TEMED (25 μL) were 
added to the mixture to initiate polymerization. The reaction was 
allowed to proceed at room temperature for 2 h after which 
nanoparticles were precipitated and washed 4 times with excess 
ethanol to remove unreacted monomer, template and surfactant. </p>

<p>Jiaying Han et al. </p>

<p>
Nanoparticles were collected, resuspended in water and purified by 
gel chromatography (G50). Purified nanoparticles were lyophilized 
and kept at room temperature until further characterization. NQA 
imprinted nanoparticles (NQA-MINs) and non-imprinted nanopar-
ticles (NINs) were prepared in the same way using NQA as 
template in the former and no template in the latter. </p>

<p>2.4. Particle size and morphology </p>

<p>Size and zeta potential of nanoparticles were measured using a 
Malvern Zetasizer 
s Nano ZS90 (Malvern Instruments, UK). </p>

<p>Nanoparticles were suspended in deionized water at a concentra-
tion of 2 mg/mL and sonicated prior to measurement. Nanoparticle 
morphology was examined by transmission electron microscopy 
(TEM) (JEM-2100 F, JEOL, Japan) and dynamic light scattering 
(DLS). </p>

<p>2.5. Template nanoparticle interaction </p>

<p>2.5.1. SPR analysis 
Template-nanoparticle interaction was investigated using a Biacore 
X100 instrument (GE Healthcare, USA). NQA was immobilized 
on a CM5 sensor chip according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
Suspensions of nanoparticles were filtered through 0.22 μm 
syringe filters and diluted in HBS-EP buffer (GE Healthcare, 
USA) to give a three-fold concentration series (0.25, 0.74, 2.22, 
6.67 and 20 mg/mL). The freshly prepared suspensions were then 
allowed to flow over the NQA sensor chip according to a so-called 
"kinetic titration" procedure using HBS-EP as running buffer 
13,14 . 
For each injection, nanoparticle suspensions flowed over the 
sensor chip at 20 μL/min at 25 1C for 3 min. An unmodified 
sensor chip served as a reference to correct for instrumental noise 
and drift. </p>

<p>2.5.2. Change in zeta potential 
Analysis of zeta potential was based on the "mucin particle method" 
previously used to study the mucoadhesion of polymers to commer-
cially available mucin particles </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>. Briefly, to nanoparticle suspensions 
in water (4 mg/mL), NQA was added to give a final concentration of 
75 μg/mL and incubated overnight. Since NQA is positively charged 
at pH 7.0 (pI 9.5), it was assumed that the zeta potential of 
nanoparticles would increase due to adsorption of template. Zeta 
potential of nanoparticles was monitored using a Malvern Zetasizer </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>Nano Series DTS 1060 (Malvern Instruments, UK). </p>

<p>2.5.3. Fluorescence polarization (FP) studies 
The application of FP is based on the assumption that binding of 
the fluorescence-labeled molecule to nanoparticles decreases its 
molecular rotation in solution which can be detected by FP. NQA 
was N-terminally labeled with FAM and purified. Then a constant 
amount of FAM-labeled peptide (about 20 nmol/L) was incubated 
with suspensions of nanoparticles in water at a range of concen-
trations. FP was measured using a Tecan M1000 microplate reader 
(Tecan, Swiss), and values corrected by subtracting the value 
corresponding to the labeled peptide in water. </p>

<p>2.6. In vitro interaction between nanoparticles and H. pylori </p>

<p>2.6.1. Flow cytometry studies 
A BD FACSCalibur fluorescence-activated flow cytometer (BD, 
USA) was used to investigate the interaction between </p>

<p>nanoparticles and H. pylori. FAM-loaded nanoparticles (FAM-
Myr-NQA-MINs, FAM-NQA-MINs and FAM-NINs) were pre-
pared by adding FAM during their preparation. FAM-loaded 
nanoparticles were separated from free FAM by gel chromato-
graphy and lyophilized. Examination by fluorescence spectrometry 
showed that all nanoparticles displayed similar fluorescence 
intensity. The standard microbial strain of H. pylori (Sydney 
Strain SS1) was cultivated for two days microaerophilically at 
37 1C on solid medium. The bacteria were then suspended in 
physiological saline and nutrient medium, respectively, incubated 
with 2 mg/mL FAM-loaded nanoparticles for 2 h and fixed with 
2.5% glutaraldehyde. Finally samples were centrifuged, rinsed and 
subjected to flow cytometric analysis. For each measurement, 
1 Â 10 
4 and 2 Â 10 
4 bacteria were counted to determine the 
number giving a positive signal in the FL-1 channel. </p>

<p>2.6.2. Studies using the SS1-AGS model 
A fluorescence microscope was used to observe the in vitro 
interaction between nanoparticles and SS1 H. pylori adsorbed on 
AGS cells. This was based on the premise that the SS1-AGS 
model mimics the adhesion of H. pylori to gastric epithelial cells 
in vivo. SS1 bacteria were microaerophilically cultivated for 48 h 
at 37 1C on solid medium and then suspended in F12 medium at 
about 1.0 Â 10 
8 cells/mL. AGS cells were cultivated in a 24-well 
plate for 48 h after which 0.3 mL bacteria suspension was added 
into each well and incubated for 1 h before washing 3 times with 
saline. Then aliquots (0.3 mL) of suspensions (2 mg/mL) of FAM-
loaded nanoparticles were added into each well and incubated with 
either AGS cells or the SS1-AGS model for 2 h. Finally samples 
were examined by fluorescence microscopy. </p>

<p>2.7. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical comparison between samples was evaluated by Student's 
t-tests performed using <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">Excel</rs>. </p>

<p>3. Results and discussion </p>

<p>3.1. Synthesis of SMINs </p>

<p>Subsequent to the conventional bulk polymerization method in 
which template molecules are embedded within the bulk of the 
polymer matrix, some novel approaches such as mini-emulsion 
polymerization and precipitation polymerization have recently 
been introduced to prepare micro-and nano-structured protein 
imprinted polymers 
16-18 . Compared to the conventional approach, 
the products of these newer techniques possess higher adsorption 
capacity due to their increased surface area. However, they are still 
deficient, because protein molecules are mostly hydrophilic and 
randomly distributed in the aqueous monomer solution, the 
majority of protein is restricted in the polymeric matrix and 
inaccessible to the template. To solve this problem, we employed 
inverse microemulsion polymerization as proposed by Zeng et al. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>and modified the hydrophilic NQA with the long-chain fatty acid, 
myristic acid, to form an amphiphilic molecule. During the 
emulsion process, the amphiphilic template functions as a surfac-
tant and arranges itself at the oil-water interface with its hydro-
philic head protruding into the aqueous phase and its hydrophobic 
tail oriented outwards. This was anticipated to promote interaction 
between the hydrophilic peptide and the monomer and also create 
imprints directly at or near the surface of the nanoparticles. The </p>

<p>Preliminary investigations into surface molecularly imprinted nanoparticles </p>

<p>
template should then have easy access to surface specific sites as 
found in the natural immune response where only the surface 
epitope part of a macromolecule is recognized by the antibody 
2 . 
The preparation procedure is summarized in Scheme 1. </p>

<p>3.2. Particle size and morphology </p>

<p>A TEM micrograph showing the morphology of Myr-NQA-MINs 
is shown in Fig. 1. The nanoparticles are seen to be regularly 
shaped and highly monodispersed. DLS studies (Table 1) show 
that nanoparticles were about 30 nm in diameter and display 
similar values of particle distribution index (PDI) despite the 
addition of template peptide during preparation. </p>

<p>3.3. SPR studies </p>

<p>Interaction between immobilized NQA and nanoparticles as studied by 
SPR is shown in Fig. 2. It was found that injection of Myr-NQA-MINs 
resulted in a marked concentration-dependent increase in response 
values (RU). Thus injection of suspensions with the three higher 
concentrations (2.22, 6.67 and 20 mg/mL) led to particularly high 
levels of RU whereas signals for nanoparticle suspensions with lower 
concentrations were less significant. This indicates that, at higher 
concentrations, the presence of a large number of high-affinity binding 
sites on the surface of Myr-NQA-MINs offers more opportunity for 
rapid adsorption of template molecules. NQA-MINs did not seem to </p>

<p>interact strongly with immobilized template at any concentration and 
its sensorgram was quite similar to that of NINs. This was probably 
because the absence of surface imprints prevented them from 
effectively interacting with the template molecules. These results 
indicate the successful fabrication of specifically imprinted cavities 
on the surface of Myr-NQA-MINs. 
Interestingly, no dissociation of bound nanoparticles was observed 
at any concentration after the association process. This is consistent 
with the findings of Verheyen et al. 
12 who concluded that the absence 
of dissociation was due to a very strong interaction between SMINs 
and template. However, we maintain that, besides the interaction, the 
phenomenon could also be partly due to sedimentation of nanoparticles 
onto the sensor chip leading to a "strong binding" artifact. Because of 
this, we employed a "kinetic titration" approach characterized by sequ-
entially injecting an increasing concentration of nanoparticles with no 
regeneration step </p>

<p>13,14 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>3.4. Change in zeta potential </p>

<p>According to the "mucin particle method", the surface of mucin 
particles is changed by adhesion of mucoadhesive polymer giving rise 
to a change in zeta potential of the particles </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>. Changes resulting from 
the interaction between templates and nanoparticles are shown in 
Fig. 3. For NINs, NQA-MINs and Myr-NQA-MINs, zeta potential 
increased by 2.86, 2.88 and 5.22 mV respectively. This was as 
expected given that surface imprinted Myr-NQA-MINs probably 
display a higher affinity toward NQA than its counterparts. For NINs 
and NQA-MINs, the increase in zeta potential is probably due to 
nonspecific adsorption of template peptide. </p>

<p>Scheme 1 Schematic representation of the preparation of surface 
molecularly imprinted nanoparticles. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Micrograph of Myr-NQA-MINs obtained by transmission 
electron microscopy. The scale bars represents 100 nm. </p>

<p>Table 1 Summary information of the sizes of NINs, NQA-
MINs and Myr-NQA-MINs. </p>

<p>Sample 
Mean diameter (nm) 
PDI </p>

<p>NINs 
30.4 
0.126 
NQA-MINs 
28.5 
0.155 
Myr-NQA-MINs 
27.9 
0.200 </p>

<p>NINs, non-imprinted nanoparticles; NQA-MINs, NQA imprinted 
nanoparticles; Myr-NQA-MINs, myristic acid modified NQA 
imprinted nanoparticles; PDI, particle distribution index. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Sensorgrams of time-dependent binding of Myr-NQA-
MINs, NQA-MINs and NINs to template peptide immobilized on an 
SPR chip. The corresponding concentrations of nanoparticles are 0, 
0.25, 0.74, 2.22, 6.67 and 20 mg/mL. </p>

<p>Jiaying Han et al. </p>

<p>
3.5. FP studies </p>

<p>FP is a versatile solution-based technique that has long been 
employed to study protein-protein interactions. The principle of 
FP derives from the fact that the degree of polarization of a 
fluorophore (in this case FAM) is inversely related to its 
molecular rotation as indicated in Scheme 2 
19 . As shown in 
Fig. 4, at low concentrations of nanoparticles (0.78 and 
1.56 μg/mL), FP of Myr-NQA-MINs after incubation with 
FAM labeled template was significantly higher than FP of 
NQA-MINs and NINs. This can be attributed to the higher 
affinity of Myr-NQA-MINs for template molecules. However, at 
higher concentrations of nanoparticles (100 and 200 μg/mL), 
there were no significant differences in FP of the three types of 
nanoparticles. This is presumably because in all cases the 
majority of template molecules are adsorbed onto the nanopar-
ticles due to both specific and nonspecific interactions and the 
greater affinity of Myr-NQA-MINs for template is masked. </p>

<p>3.6. H. pylori adhesion studies </p>

<p>3.6.1. Cytometric analysis 
The ability of the three types of nanoparticles to adhere to H. pylori is 
compared in Fig. 5. Binding of NINs to H. pylori still occurred 
presumably due to non-specific adsorption. Adsorption of Myr-NQA-
MINs was the highest but adsorption of NQA-MINs was somewhat 
inconsistent being higher than that of NINs for some groups but less 
for others. We hypothesize this reflects inconsistent imprinting of the 
surface of NQA-MINs due to the hydrophilic quality of NQA 
or that the sites created do not matchthe NQA on the SS1 H. pylori 
bacteria. </p>

<p>3.6.2. Fluorescence microscopy studies 
Both FAM-Myr-NQA-MINs and FAM-NINs were adsorbed onto 
AGS cells but the surface fluorescence intensity on AGS cells was 
much lower than that on the SS1-AGS model (Fig. 6). FAM-Myr-
NQA-MINs were adsorbed more on H. pylori as indicated by the 
higher fluorescence intensity on the bacteria. On the other hand, 
FAM-NINs were scattered more randomly on the surface of the 
AGS cells. We infer this is because Myr-NQA-MINs are </p>

<p>Figure 3 (a) Zeta potential of NINs, NQA-MINs and Myr-NQA-MINs before (white) and after (black) incubation with NQA for 12 h and (b) the 
zeta potential differences ( </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Po0.01, Student's t-test). </p>

<p>Scheme 2 Illustration of the principle of fluorescence polarization as 
applied to study the interaction between template and nanoparticles. </p>

<p>Figure 4 Fluorescence polarization of FAM-labeled NQA (20 nmol/ 
L) after incubation with nanoparticles suspensions with different 
concentrations ( </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Po0.01, </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Po0.005, Student's t-test). NPs, 
nanoparticles. </p>

<p>Figure 5 Specific binding of various nanoparticles to the Sydney 
Strain of H. pylori (SS1) detected by flow cytometry ( </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Po0.01, 
Student's t-test). </p>

<p>Preliminary investigations into surface molecularly imprinted nanoparticles </p>

<p>
recognized by the surface lipoprotein of H. pylori and are more 
specifically absorbed while NINs are probably adsorbed non-
specifically onto AGS cells. </p>

<p>4. Conclusions </p>

<p>In the present study, we prepared a novel peptide imprinted 
nanoparticle for specific H. pylori adhesion. We used the general 
strategy of surface imprinting with an epitope imprinting approach. 
Studies of the interaction between template peptide and nanopar-
ticles based on SPR, change in zeta potential and FP indicated that 
Myr-NQA-MINs possess specific recognition sites for the template 
compared to NQA-MINs and NINs. A preliminary in vitro study 
of the ability of these surface molecularly imprinted nanoparticles 
to adhere to H. pylori was sufficiently positive to encourage us to 
further explore the therapeutic potential of this kind of nanopar-
ticle for H. pylori eradication. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors acknowledge the financial support from the National 
Natural Science Foundation of China (Nos. 30973653, H3008/ 
81102385) and National S&amp;T Major Special Project on Major 
New Drug Innovation (No. 2009ZX09310-006). </p>



<p>Figure 6 Representative fluorescent photomicrographs of binding of various nanoparticles to SS1-AGS model. The concentration of 
nanoparticles is 2 mg/mL. The scale bars represents 200 μm. </p>

<p>Jiaying Han et al. </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>