<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4553351" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Complications from chronic ear infections are decreasing be-
cause of earlier diagnosis and initiation of appropriate treat-
ments. However, chronic ear infections can still cause many in-
tracranial and extracranial complications [1-5]. Among these 
complications, facial nerve paralysis is a potentially serious com-
plication because it can result in facial asymmetry. In the litera-</p>

<p>ture, the incidences of facial paralysis were reported to range 
from 1%-3% in patients with chronic otitis media [6-8]. Facial 
nerve paralysis was frequently observed in cholesteatoma pa-
tients and in patients with chronic suppurative otitis media with-
out cholesteatoma [6,8-11]. In this study, we aimed to investi-
gate the clinical features, radiologic findings, and treatment out-
comes in patients of facial nerve paralysis with chronic ear infec-
tions. And we also aimed to evaluate for radiologic sensitivities 
on facial canal, labyrinth and cranial fossa dehiscences in middle 
ear cholesteatomas. Our study includes a retrospective review of 
13 patients with facial paralysis secondary to chronic ear infec-
tions. In addition, temporal bone computed tomographys (CTs) 
and operative reports of 254 cholesteatoma patients were re-
viewed to investigate for radiologic evidence of any fallopian 
canal, bony labyrinth and/or cranial base dehiscences. </p>

<p>• Received May 2, 2014 
Revised July 25, 2014 
Accepted August 14, 2014 </p>

<p>• Corresponding author: Yong-Ho Park 
Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Chungnam 
National University Hospital, Chungnam National University School of 
Medicine, 282 Munhwa-ro, Jung-gu, Daejeon 301-721, Korea 
Tel: +82-42-280-7697, Fax: +82-42-253-4059 
E-mail: parkyh@cnu.ac.kr </p>

<p>pISSN 1976-8710 eISSN 2005-0720 </p>

<p>Facial Nerve Paralysis in Patients With Chronic Ear 
Infections: Surgical Outcomes and Radiologic Analysis </p>

<p>Jin Woong Choi </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>·Yong-Ho Park </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Brain Research Institute, Chungnam National University School of Medicine, Daejeon, Korea </p>

<p>Objectives. The purpose of this study was to investigate the clinical features, radiologic findings, and treatment outcomes in 
patients of facial nerve paralysis with chronic ear infections. And we also aimed to evaluate for radiologic sensitivities 
on facial canal, labyrinth and cranial fossa dehiscences in middle ear cholesteatomas. </p>

<p>Methods. A total of 13 patients were enrolled in this study. Medical records were retrospectively reviewed for clinical fea-
tures, radiologic findings, surgical findings, and recovery course. In addition, retrospective review of temporal bone 
computed tomography (CT) and operative records in 254 middle ear cholesteatoma patients were also performed. </p>

<p>Results. Of the 13 patients, eight had cholesteatomas in the middle ear, while two patients exhibited external auditory ca-
nal cholesteatomas. Chronic suppurative otitis media, petrous apex cholesteatoma and tuberculous otitis media were 
also observed in some patients. The prevalence of facial paralysis in middle ear cholesteatoma patients was 3.5%. The 
most common involved site of the facial nerve was the tympanic segment. Labyrinthine fistulas and destruction of 
cranial bases were more frequently observed in facial paralysis patients than nonfacial paralysis patients. The radio-
logic sensitivity for facial canal dehiscence was 91%. The surgical outcomes for facial paralysis were relatively satis-
factory in all patients except in two patients who had petrous apex cholesteatoma and requiring conservative man-
agement. </p>

<p>Conclusion. Facial paralyses associated with chronic ear infections were observed in more advanced lesions and the surgi-
cal outcomes for facial paralysis were relatively satisfactory. Facial canal dehiscences can be anticipated preoperative-
ly with high resolution CTs. </p>

<p>Keywords. Facial Paralysis; Ear; Infection; Cholesteatoma </p>

<p>Choi JW et al. Facial Nerve Paralysis in Chronic Ear Infections 219 </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Between May 2004 and June 2009, there were 1,123 patients 
with chronic ear infections, of which 13 cases involving facial pa-
ralysis were investigated. The details described in our database 
included age at presentation, gender, affected side, associated 
symptoms, air-conduction and bone-conduction pure tone audi-
ometry, and assessment of facial nerve function using the House-
Brackmann grading system (Table 1). 
Temporal bone CTs of these patients were also reviewed. Bony 
defects in the facial canal, and combined bony defects in the cra-
nial base and bony labyrinth were analyzed. The preoperative 
and postoperative medications included antibiotics and cortico-
steroids in all but one patient who had complete facial paralysis 
managed conservatively. The type of surgery, operative findings, 
pathology, and the postoperative facial nerve functions were re-
viewed. A final assessment of facial nerve function was performed 
one year postoperatively. 
All temporal bone CTs and operation records for 254 middle 
ear cholesteatoma patients were reviewed to evaluate for radio-
logic sensitivities on facial canal, labyrinth and cranial fossa de-
hiscences in middle ear cholesteatomas. Using the temporal bone 
CT, we evaluated for facial canal dehiscence, the presences of 
combined labyrinthine fistula and cranial base defects. The size of 
facial canal dehiscence was based on operative reports. 
The differences in prevalence of bony labyrinth and cranial 
base defects between facial paralysis patients and nonfacial pa-
ralysis patients were examined using the Fisher exact test. Differ-
ences in facial canal dehiscence size between facial paralysis pa-
tients and nonfacial paralysis patients were compared using the 
Mann-Whitney U-test. P-values less than 0.05 were considered 
to be statistically significant. <rs id="software-0" type="software">GraphPad InStat</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3</rs> (GraphPad Soft-</p>

<p>ware Inc., La Jolla, CA, USA) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">ver.13</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chi-
cago, IL, USA) were used for the statistical analysis. This study 
was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Chungnam 
National University Hospital. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Of the 13 patients, eight had cholesteatomas in the middle ear, 
while two patients exhibited external auditory canal cholesteato-
mas. Chronic suppurative otitis media, petrous apex cholesteato-
ma and tuberculous otitis media were also observed in one pa-
tient respectively. There were four males and nine females with a 
mean age of 54.4±17 years (range, 15 to 81 years). Affected ears 
included the right in seven cases and left in six cases. The dura-
tion of facial paralysis until surgery varied from 1 to 6 days ex-
cept in two cases with complete paralysis. Many of the patients 
had a long history of ear disease. The onsets of facial nerve paral-
ysis were sudden in 11 patients and gradual in one patient. Onset 
of paralysis was unknown in one patient who presented with 
complete paralysis. All patients presented with otorrhea and 
hearing loss, with five presenting with total deafness. Other fre-
quently associated symptoms included otalgia in 10 patients and 
dizziness in four patients. The patient with petrous apex choles-
teatoma also displayed signs of meningitis, but there were no 
other combined intracranial complications in other patients. The 
initial grades of facial paralysis according to the House-Brack-
mann grading system were II in one patient, III in nine patients, 
IV in one patient, and VI in two patients (Table 1). 
On high resolution temporal bone CT, 11 of them showed 
bony wall defects in the tympanic segment of the facial nerve, 
while two patients with external auditory canal cholesteatomas </p>

<p>Table 1. Clinical findings in 13 cases of chronic ear infections complicated by facial paralysis </p>

<p>No. 
Age/sex/ 
side </p>

<p>Duration of 
disease </p>

<p>Associated 
symptoms </p>

<p>Onset of 
paralysis </p>

<p>Duration of paralysis 
until surgery (day) </p>

<p>Hearing (dB), 
BC/AC 
Etiology </p>

<p>1 
43/M/L 25 Years 
Otalgia, otorrjea, hearing loss 
Sudden 
5 
30/40 
Middle ear cholesteatoma 
2 
81/F/L 
Since childhood Otorrhea, hearing loss 
Unknown 
Not done 
60/100 Middle ear cholesteatoma 
3 
57/M/R Since childhood Otalgia, otorrhea, hearing loss, 
dizziness </p>

<p>Sudden 
3 
60/100 Middle ear cholesteatoma </p>

<p>4 
56/F/R 
8 Years 
Otorrhea, hearing loss 
Gradual 
4 
45/60 
EAC cholesteatoma 
5 
41/F/R 
Since childhood Otalgia, otorrhea, hearing loss 
Sudden 
4 
60/100 Middle ear cholesteatoma 
6 
44/F/R 
22 Years 
Otalgia, otorrhea, hearing loss, 
dizziness </p>

<p>Sudden 
2 
20/55 
Middle ear cholesteatoma </p>

<p>7 
64/F/R 
31 Years 
Otalgia, otorrhea, hearing loss, 
dizziness </p>

<p>Sudden 
2 
60/100 Middle ear cholesteatoma </p>

<p>8 
70/F/L 
7 Years 
Otorrhea, hearing loss, dizziness Sudden 
6 
30/50 
EAC cholesteatoma 
9 
47/F/L 
Since childhood Otalgia, otorrhea, hearing loss 
Sudden 
5 
30/70 
Middle ear cholesteatoma 
10 
15/F/R 
3 Months 
Otalgia, otorrhea, hearing loss 
Sudden 
1 
10/40 
Middle ear tuberculosis 
11 
72/M/R 40 Years 
Otalgia, otorrhea, hearing loss 
Sudden 
1 
60/80 
Chronic suppurative otitis media 
12 
54/M/L 32 Years 
Otalgia, otorrhea, hearing loss, 
headache </p>

<p>Sudden 
30 Years 
60/100 Petrous apex cholesteatoma </p>

<p>13 
64/F/L 
Since childhood Otalgia, otorrhea, hearing loss 
Sudden 
3 
50/70 
Middle ear cholesteatoma </p>

<p>R, right; L, left; BC, bone conduction; AC, air conduction; EAC, external auditory canal. </p>



<p>revealed bony dehiscences in the mastoid segment of the facial 
nerve (Fig. 1). There were two patients that showed canal defects 
in both tympanic and mastoid segments. Two patients with com-
plete facial paralysis showed that wide segments of the facial 
nerve were involved. Combined bony defects in the tegmen tym-
pani were observed in eight patients, and three of them also re-
vealed the defects in the posterior cranial fossa. Destruction of 
bony labyrinths was observed in six patients in the lateral semi-
circular canal, and there was one patient who had destruction of 
all semicircular canals and vestibules (Fig. 2). Four patients with 
bony labyrinth destruction showed total deafness during audio-
gram testing. 
Surgical interventions were performed as early as possible us-
ing the transmastoid approach in 12 patients except in one pa-
tient who had complete facial paralysis requiring conservative 
management. Among 12 patients, nine patients underwent canal 
wall down mastoidectomy, two patients underwent intact canal 
wall mastoidectomy, and one patient with a petrous apex cho-
lesteatoma underwent a subtotal petrosectomy. Total removal of 
the cholesteatoma lesions or granulation tissues around the fa-
cial nerve was performed. The one patient with a petrous apex 
cholesteatoma underwent a subtotal petrosectomy without fa-
cial nerve repair. Only limited bony wall decompression was 
performed around the dehiscent area and incision of the epi-
neural sheath was not performed in all surgical cases. Exposed 
facial nerves were covered by temporal muscle fascia. Facial 
nerve paralysis was improved to House-Brackmann grade I in 
10 patients within 3 months, while there was one patient who </p>

<p>failed to show improvement beyond grade II one year after sur-
gery (Table 2). 
Among 254 patients with middle ear cholesteatomas, 54% of 
patients (138/254) revealed facial canal dehiscences based on 
high resolution temporal bone CTs. However, the true incidence 
of facial canal dehiscence was 52% in middle ear cholesteatoma 
patients (133/254). Only 3.5% of middle ear cholesteatoma pa-
tients (9/254) showed facial paralysis and it was 6.8% in pa-
tients with facial canal dehiscence (9/133). The radiological sen-
sitivities were 91% in facial canal dehiscence (121/133), 87% in 
labyrinth (13/15), and 87% in cranial base defects (26/30) (Table 
3). The median sizes of facial canal dehiscences were 5.3±1.87 
mm in facial paralysis patients and 4.4±1.8 mm in nonfacial pa-
ralysis patients. There was no difference in the size of facial canal 
dehiscence between facial paralysis and nonfacial paralysis pa-
tients. The prevalence of labyrinthine fistula was significantly in-
creased in facial paralysis patients (6/9) than in nonfacial paraly-
sis patients as (9/245) (P&lt;0.001). Cranial base defects were also 
significantly frequent in facial paralysis patients (7/9) than in 
nonfacial paralysis patients (23/245) (P&lt;0.001) (Table 4). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In the temporal bone, the facial nerve is an important structure 
that controls facial expression, lacrimation and taste sensation. It 
is generally surrounded by bony structures but can be exposed 
during the ossification process developmentally, during trauma, </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Preoperative temporal bone computed tomography of patient 
No. 8 showing a fallopian canal defect in the mastoid segment of 
the facial nerve (arrow). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Computed tomography of patient No. 2 showing all semicir-
cular canals and vestibular destructions. Note the absence of the 
facial nerve in the tympanic and mastoid segment with a combined 
posterior cranial base defect (arrows). </p>

<p>Choi JW et al. Facial Nerve Paralysis in Chronic Ear Infections 221 </p>

<p>during otologic surgery and in inflammatory diseases such as 
otitis media and cholesteatoma. In the medical literature, the in-
cidence of facial canal dehiscence was reported to be between 
20%-74% in temporal bone studies [12-14]. The most common 
location of dehiscence is known to be the tympanic segment of 
the fallopian canal because it is located in the floor of middle 
ear and has very thin bony coverage. The tympanic part of the 
fallopian canal developed anteroposteriorly from the geniculate 
fossa to enclose the facial nerve embryologically. Incomplete 
closure of facial sulcus could lead to congenital bony defects of 
the tympanic segment [15]. 
However, the prevalence of facial paralysis in chronic ear dis-
ease was not very high. Most involved middle ear cholesteato-
mas and chronic otitis media patients. According to Quaranta 
and colleagues, only 1.2% of more than 1,400 cholesteatomas </p>

<p>showed facial paralysis and others reported less than approxi-
mately 3% of chronic otitis media with or without cholesteato-
ma [6-8,16-18]. In our series, 3.5% of cholesteatoma patients 
revealed facial paralysis and it was observed in around 1% of 
chronic infectious ear disease that underwent ear surgery. Inter-</p>

<p>Table 2. Surgical findings and outcomes in 13 cases of chronic ear infections complicated by facial paralysis </p>

<p>No. 
Bony dehiscence 
of facial canal </p>

<p>Labyrinthine 
fistula </p>

<p>Destruction of 
cranial base </p>

<p>Size of facial canal 
dehiscence (mm) </p>

<p>Type of 
surgery </p>

<p>Initial grade 
of paralysis </p>

<p>Final grade 
of paralysis </p>

<p>Recovery time 
(month) </p>

<p>1 
Tympanic 
-
MCF 
6 
CWD 
II 
I 
1 
2 
Labyrinthine 
LSCC 
MCF 
Unknown 
Not done 
VI 
VI 
No recovery 
GG 
PSCC 
PCF 
Tympanic 
SSCC 
Mastoid 
Vestibule 
3 
Tympanic 
LSCC 
-
6 
CWD 
III 
I 
3 
Mastoid 
2 
4 
Mastoid 
-
-
5 
CWD 
III 
I 
2 
5 
Tympanic 
LSCC 
MCF 
7 
CWD 
III 
I 
3 
Mastoid 
3 
6 
Tympanic 
LSCC 
-
5 
CWD 
III 
I 
3 
7 
Tympanic 
LSCC 
MCF 
5 
CWD 
III 
I 
3 
8 
Mastoid 
-
-
4 
CWD 
II 
I 
1 
9 
Tympanic 
LSCC 
MCF 
6 
CWD 
III 
I 
3 
PCF 
10 
Tympanic 
-
-
6 
ICW 
IV 
I 
2 
11 
Tympanic 
-
MCF 
5 
ICW 
III 
II 
2 
12 
IAC 
-
MCF 
Unknown 
Petrosectomy 
VI 
VI 
No recovery 
Labyrinthine 
PCF 
GG 
Tympanic 
13 
Tympanic 
-
MCF 
8 
CWD 
III 
I 
2 </p>

<p>MCF, middle cranial fossa; CWD, canal wall down; GG, geniculate ganglion; LSCC, lateral semiciucular canal; PSCC, posterior semicircular canal; SSCC, 
superior semicircular canal; PCF, posterior cranial fossa; ICW, intact canal wall; IAC, internal auditory canal. </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparisons of dehiscences in facial canal, bony labyrinth 
and cranial fossa between radiology and operation record in 254 
middle ear cholesteatomas </p>

<p>True dehiscence </p>

<p>Radiologic dehiscence </p>

<p>Facial canal 
Bony labyrinth 
Cranial fossa </p>

<p>+ 
-
+ 
-
+ 
-</p>

<p>+ (n=133) 
121 
12 
13 
2 
26 
4 
-(n=121) 
17 
104 
1 
238 
2 
222 
Total (n=254) 
138 
116 
14 
240 
28 
226 </p>

<p>Table 4. Comparisons of dehiscences in facial canal, labyrinth, and cranial base between facial paralysis group and non-facial paralysis group 
in 254 middle ear cholesteatomas </p>

<p>Facial paralysis </p>

<p>Dehiscence 
Size of facial canal dehiscence (mm), 
mean±SD 
Facial canal 
Labyrinth 
Cranial fossa </p>

<p>+ 
-
+ 
-
+ 
-</p>

<p>+ (n=9) 
9*** 
0 
6*** 
3 
7*** 
2 
5.3±1.87 
-(n=245) 
124 
121 
9 
236 
23 
222 
4.4±1.80 
Total (n=254) 
133 
121 
15 
239 
30 
224 </p>

<p>***P &lt;0.001. </p>



<p>estingly there were two patients with external auditory choles-
teatoma causing facial paralysis. Chronic suppurative otitis me-
dia and tuberculous otitis media were also observed. Although 
52% of middle ear cholesteatoma patients exhibited facial canal 
dehiscences, only 6.8% of patients revealed facial paralysis. This 
result indicates that the facial nerve has a relatively high resis-
tance to infection. 
Although there were no significant size differences in facial 
canal dehiscence between facial paralysis patients and nonparal-
ysis patients, combined bony labyrinth destructions and cranial 
base defects were more frequently observed in facial paralysis 
patients. According to Ikeda et al. [16], 56% of facial paralysis 
patients with cholesteatoma had bony labyrinth destruction and 
63% of those patients had cranial base destruction [16]. Those 
result coincided well with our results. In our series, 67% of fa-
cial paralysis patients with middle ear cholesteatoma showed 
bony labyrinth destruction and 78% of those patients also had 
cranial base destruction. As a result, it appears that facial nerve 
paralysis occurs in more advanced diseases. 
The precise etiology of facial paralysis in chronic ear infection 
is not well known, but the direct inflammatory involvement of 
the facial nerve through fallopian canal dehiscence and compres-
sion resulting from edema is believed to be the involved patho-
physiology. Some believe that the cholesteatoma itself could 
cause facial paralysis through neurotoxic substances that it might 
secrete and or cause bony destruction via various enzymatic ac-
tivities [9,19]. There was also a histopathological study showing 
degenerative and inflammatory changes of the facial nerve in 
patients with facial paralysis due to chronic suppurative otitis 
media [20] 
Sometimes it may be difficult to visualize the facial canal de-
hiscence by temporal bone CT because the bone surrounding 
the tympanic segment can be very thin and soft tissue lesions 
such as a cholesteatoma or granulation tissues may be adjacent 
to the facial canal. However, diagnoses preoperatively can be 
more easily attained with high resolution CT, with its radiologi-
cal sensitivity for facial canal dehiscence reported to be approxi-
mately 66% [21]. In our series, the radiologic sensitivity of fa-
cial canal dehiscence was approximately 91% with a specificity 
of 86%. These results reveal that preoperative high resolution 
CT is a useful diagnostic tool for facial canal dehiscence. 
Early surgical intervention can lead to more favorable improve-
ments in facial function. There was a report that patients who had 
underwent surgery more than 2 months after the onset of paraly-
sis displayed poorer outcome [16]. In our series, we performed 
surgery as soon as possible, with preoperative duration of paraly-
sis not exceeding 6 days except in the patient with the petrous 
apex lesion. Although we could not compare the treatment result 
between an early and late intervention group, we believe that our 
good results were in part due to early intervention. 
There have been many disagreements regarding the extent of 
facial nerve decompression required for treatment. Some authors </p>

<p>postulated that a neural sheath incision should be performed for 
cases of complete paralysis, while there was reporting bony de-
compression from the geniculate ganglion to the stylomastoid 
foramen [8,22]. We did not perform any wide decompressions, 
with only limited bony decompressions around the dehiscences 
completed. None of the procedures had a neural sheath incision 
performed. All cholesteatomas and granulation tissues could be 
dissected relatively easily from the facial nerve under magnified 
view of the microscope. We thought that those infectious condi-
tions should be regarded as different with other facial paralysis 
condition such as temporal bone fracture and idiopathic facial 
paralysis. We felt that the neural sheath might not only be a pow-
erful barrier itself from infection, but that incision of the neural 
sheath could induce further nerve injury and possibly make the 
site more vulnerable for infection. 
Prognosis for facial paralysis was relatively good in our series. 
There were two patients exhibiting normal facial function within 
one month and all the others except the patient with the petrous 
apex lesion had improvement within 2 or 3 months postopera-
tively. However, there was one patient that had no improvement 
beyond House-Brackmann grade II 1-year following surgery. This 
patient was more elderly with other major comorbidities such as 
diabetes possibly affecting his recovery course. 
In conclusion, we analyzed 13 patients with chronic ear infec-
tions and facial paralysis. The most common pathology involved 
a cholesteatoma affecting the middle ear, external auditory ca-
nal, and petrous apex. Tuberculous otitis media and noncholes-
teatomatous suppurative otitis media could also be the cause for 
facial paralysis. The prevalence of facial paralysis was about 1% 
in chronic ear infections and 3.5% in middle ear cholesteato-
mas. The tympanic segment was the most frequently affected lo-
cation and patients with facial paralysis had more frequent de-
structions involving the bony labyrinth and cranial base. Facial 
canal dehiscences were observed in 52% of middle ear choles-
teatoma patients. The radiologic sensitivity of facial canal dehis-
cence was 91% and careful preoperative examination will be 
helpful to anticipate the facial nerve exposure during surgery 
and the surgical outcomes for facial paralysis were relatively sat-
isfactory. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was re-
ported. </p>



<p>Choi JW et al. Facial Nerve Paralysis in Chronic Ear Infections 223 </p>



</text></tei>