<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4718351" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>were con-
sidered. Cases have been matched for gender, department and 
period of hospitalization with two or three controls when it is pos-
sible. A table including intrinsic and extrinsic 'fall risk' factors, 
not foreseen by Conley Scale, and setted up after a literature 
overview was built. Univariate analysis and conditional logistic 
regression model have been performed. 
Results. 50 cases and 102 controls were included. Adverse event 
'fall' were associated with filled Conley scale at the admis-</p>

<p>sion to care unit (OR = 4.92, 95%CI = 2.34-10.37). Univariate 
analysis identified intrinsic factors increasing risk of falls: diz-
ziness (OR = 3.22; 95%CI = 1.34-7.75), psychomotor agitation 
(OR = 2.61; 95%CI = 1.06-6.43); and use of means of restraint 
(OR = 5.05 95%CI = 1.77-14.43). Conditional logistic regression 
model revealed a significant association with the following vari-
ables: use of instruments of restraint (HR = 5.54, 95%CI = 1.2-
23.80), dizziness (OR = 3.97, 95%CI = 1.22-12.89). 
Patient falls are one of the most common adverse events 
and one of the most important issue in the context of risk 
management, both for the frequency with which they 
occur, and for the consequences that may ensue. Some 
studies show that falls represent up to 70% of hospital 
accidents, entailing a direct physical and psychological 
impact [1, 2]. Hospital falls, that involve death or serious 
harm for the patient, are treated, in Italy, as a sentinel 
event by Ministerial Protocol [3]. 
Falls have a multifactorial etiology and more than 400 
risk factors have been described. 
The incidence of this phenomenon is prevalent in the elderly 
population, but the event can also occur in younger subjects; 
the causes may be attributable to diseases or physiologi-
cal situations, fall is an event that, for frequency and con-
sequences entailed, requires a multidisciplinary approach, 
articulated at different levels, aimed at the prevention and 
containment of risk, especially among older people [4]. 
Some studies [5, 6] classify falls as: 
• predictable: they occur in individuals exposed to identi-
fiable risk factors (disorientation, difficulty in walking, 
gait changes caused by neurological diseases, etc.); 
• unpredictable: determined by physiological condi-
tions unpredictable until the fall, falls that cannot be 
predicted 'a priori' (presence of seizures, dizziness, 
drug reactions, syncope); </p>

<p>• accidental: falls attributable to environmental factors 
or fatality: when the person falls unintentionally (eg 
slipping on the wet floor). 
14% of falls in hospital are classified as accidental, 8% 
as unpredictable, while the remaining 78% are included 
between predictable falls. 
Risk of falling cannot be completely eliminated by care 
settings, but the early identification of patients at higher 
risk, allows us to identify and focus prevention, on a 
population that really needs [7]. In order to reduce the 
incidence of this adverse event, some risk assessment 
instruments are used to identify patients at risk. 
According to WHO, risk factors can be divided in two 
categories: 
a. intrinsic factors, which concern to patient health 
condition, they include data on reason of health care 
admission, co-morbidities and drug therapies; 
b. extrinsic factors, related to the organizational aspects 
of the hospital structure, environmental features and 
ergonomic resources, or health facilities employed [8]. 
Outcomes related to the adverse event 'fall' are a cause 
of costs increasing, due to prolonged hospitalization 
and further diagnostic and therapeutic procedures need-
ed [9]. Moreover, in terms of quality of care, this kind of 
event can take on a negative ethical and legal features, 
for operators involved. 
The rating scales for risk of falls can be used both at the 
entrance of the patient in the hospital and for subsequent </p>

<p>A.S. Guzzo et Al. </p>

<p>E78 </p>

<p>monitoring during hospitalization. Different scales have 
been constructed and applied during the last 20 years, 
eg. Conley, Morse, Tinetti, Stratify [10-17]. 
However, a critical review of the literature published 
in 2003 emphasizes that none of these scales seems to 
have been sufficiently studied in terms of validity and 
reliability [18]. A problem of particular importance is 
the poor reproducibility on populations different from 
the experimental ones, that can result in an excessive 
expenditure of resources in front of a little benefit in 
terms of prevention [18]. Examining the different risk 
factors included in the risk assessment scales, it is easy 
to argue that some items are detected in two or more of 
them, even if with different formulations. Moreover, the 
most recent critical review of literature made possible to 
select and confirm a set of risk factors most important 
in terms of predictability, in particular: history of falls, 
balance and gait problems, impaired mobility, vision, 
orthostatic hypotension, use of different drugs, psycho-
motor status [19]. Latest trends consider risk assessment 
not based on the use of items and scores 'preformed', 
but rather on a detected core of individual variables. 
Conley Scale [10] was developed by D. Conley in the 
United States during a study conducted within medical 
and surgical Units, in 1999. An article regarding Conley 
scale, has established values of sensitivity around 69%, 
and specificity between 41% and 61%, therefore, the use 
of this clinical tool is justified by the good margin of 
accuracy and predictability in identifying true positives 
patients truly exposed to the risk of fall [20]. 
The main objective of this study was to identify factors that 
can significantly influence the phenomenon 'patient falls' in 
the hospital, and to describe conditions in which the event 
'fall' occurs through monitoring application of Conley Scale, 
in different hospital departments. A case -control study was 
performed in the Teaching Hospital "Umberto I" in Rome. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Sample detection 
In the present study cases have been defined as "patients 
who have had an accidental fall during their hospitaliza-
tion", from March 1 
st 2012 to September 30 
th 2013. Setting 
of research was Umberto I General Hospital in Rome. Data 
were collected through the analysis of medical records 
which contains, among other information, the "SHEET OF 
FALL DESCRIPTION"; sent to the Risk Manager of the 
Hospital at the moment of adverse event occurred. 
Cases have been excluded from analysis for the follow-
ing reasons: 
• "SHEET OF FALL DESCRIPTION" not properly filled 
in, so that was not possible to trace the number SDO 
(Hospital Discharge Data) of the medical record (N = 2); 
• regime of hospitalizations different from the ordi-
nary one. 
Moreover the cases included were paired with two 
(N = 48 cases) or three controls (N = 2 cases). 
The selection criteria for controls were: 
• ordinary regime of hospitalization; </p>

<p>• hospitalization during the day of the event fall of case; 
• no falls during hospitalization; 
• hospitalization in the same care unit of the respective case; 
• pairing by gender. 
Exclusion criteria for controls was: 
• discharge before case fall. 
The computerized system <rs type="software">GIPSE</rs> (Management Informa-
tion First Aid and Emergency) has been used for detection 
of controls, it is a technical tool for the computerization of 
Emergency Services, and disclosures discharge required 
by SIES (Emergency Medical Information System). 
The search criteria considered to determine the controls 
have been the department, the event date fall (admis-
sions have been considered starting from the four days 
before case fall) and gender. Medical folders have been 
identified by SDO codes that stemmed entering this in-
formation into <rs type="software">GIPSE</rs> program. </p>

<p>Description of measuring tool 
A table built ad hoc has been used to extract data (Appen-
dix 1). The framework has been divided into three sections: 
the first two had to being filled in for cases and controls, 
and the third part was dedicated to cases data collection. 
The first section refers to socio-demographic data, related 
to hospitalization and conditions of the patient at admis-
sion: date of birth, age, gender, residence, nationality, 
SDO code of medical records, admission date, discharge 
date, department of hospitalization, type (ordinary, day 
hospital), type of admission (emergency, programmed, 
transferred), principal diagnosis and secondary diagnoses 
coded ICD9-CM possible critical condition / instability 
of the patient at the time of admission and the four risk 
factors of WHO (Patient ≥ 65 years; taking &gt; 4 drugs; 
weakness in the hips; unstable equilibrium). 
The second section examines some of the information 
contained in the medical record relatively: data of ad-
mission day, presence or not of fall, filled or not filled 
Conley scale (at admission and any subsequent updates: 
the scale should be completed within 24 hours of admis-
sion or, after clinical stabilization if the admission oc-
curred in emergency departments). Subsequent assess-
ment should be repeated: whenever a change is detected 
in patient's clinical condition, eg. after surgery, changes 
in therapeutic, addition or replacement of sleep-inducing 
drugs, anti-anxiety drugs, psychotropic drugs, benzodi-
azepines, diuretics etc.; after 72 hours from the first as-
sessment; every 5 days after the second evaluation until 
discharge; after a fall, at the time of discharge / trans-
fer [20]); bodily functions on the date of case fall; intrin-
sic and extrinsic risk factors present at time of case fall. 
The third section reports the same data present in the fall 
report form. </p>

<p>Data collection 
Hospital records have been formally requested through a 
letter submitted to the Health Management Department 
of Teaching Hospital Umberto I. 
Folders have been divided between cases and controls 
and controls hospitalization period has been assessed to 
include the day of the respective fall case. </p>

<p>Assessment of Conley sCAle in fAll risk prevention </p>

<p>E79 </p>

<p>Each folder has been analyzed independently by two re-
viewers using the data extracting form preformed. Medi-
cal records evaluations were compared and any disagree-
ment has been resolved with the help of a third reviewer. 
Finally, data collected by extraction form have been in-
serted in an <rs type="software">Excel</rs> file. 
In the statistical analysis, possible associations between 
patient falls and variables have been evaluated using 
Chi-square test, Fisher's exact test, Student's t, Mann-
Whitney and odds ratio (OR), with confidence intervals 
(CI) at 95%. The level of significance for all analyzes 
has been setted at p &lt; 0.05. 
A conditional logistic regression was used to investigate 
the relationship between the outcome of being a case 
or a control and the set of prognostic factors (intrinsic 
and estrinsic). Parameters were estimated using condi-
tional method for matched data [21]. The model fitted 
only included covariates resulted significant at univari-
ate analysis. The likelihood-ratio test has been applied 
to evaluate the goodness of model. Data were analyzed 
using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">19.0</rs>. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Descriptive analysis of the sample 
50 cases and 102 controls have been identified (Tab. 
I). The 71.7% of the sample were male, 62.3% was 64 
years old and 91.3% had Italian nationality. 
66% (33/50) of fall cases occurred in Neurology and 
Psychiatry Department, 8% (4/50) in Infectious Diseas-</p>

<p>es Department and 4% (2/50) in Orthopedics Units, 4% 
(2/50) in Emergency Department. 
With regard to Conley scale criteria, established by WHO, 
the present data confirmed that: the average age of cases 
was 69 years, while 64 years among controls. The differ-
ence was statistically significant (p = 0.001). 54% of the 
sample took more than 4 drugs, 31% had critical clinical 
conditions at the admission, 37.8% showed hips weakness 
and 45.6% had unstable balance. 46% of hospitalizations 
featured a filled Conley scale at the admission to care unit. 
In addition to the main diagnosis, comorbidities infor-
mations have been selected among anamnesis data, and 
thereafter collected and compared between cases and con-
trols. The most part of cases presented one comorbidity </p>

<p>Tab. I. description of sample. </p>

<p>Variables 
N (%) 
Missing </p>

<p>gender 
m 
109 (71.7) 
0 
F 
43 (28.3) </p>

<p>Nationality 
Foreign 
13 (8.7) 
0 
Italian 
137 (91.3) </p>

<p>Age &gt; 64 years 
yes 
94 (62.3) 
1 
No 
57 (37.7) 
The number of drugs taken 
&gt; 4 </p>

<p>yes 
79 (54) 
1 
No 
67 (45.9) </p>

<p>Critical conditions 
yes 
47 (31) 
1 
No 
104 (68.9) </p>

<p>hips weakness 
yes 
56 (37.8) 
4 
No 
92 (62.2) </p>

<p>Unstable balance 
yes 
67 (45.6) 
5 
No 
80 (54.4) 
Conley filled in at the 
admission into Care Unit </p>

<p>yes 
69 (46) 
2 
No 
81 (54) </p>

<p>Tab. II a. Univariate analysis between cases and controls. </p>

<p>Variables 
Controls 
(not fallen) N (%) </p>

<p>Cases 
(fallen) N (%) 
P 
OR (95%CI) </p>

<p>gender 
m 
75 (73.5) 
34 (68.0) 
0.48 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.3 (0.62 -2.73) 
F 
27 (26.5) 
16 (32.0) </p>

<p>Nation 
Italian 
91 (91.0) 
46 (92.0) 
0.99 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.13 (0.33 -3.9) 
Foreign 
9 (9.0) 
4 (8.0) </p>

<p>pt &gt; 64 years 
yes 
58 (57.4) 
36 (72.0) 
0.08 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.91 (0.92 -3.96) 
No 
43 (42.6) 
14 (28.0 ) </p>

<p>pt &gt; 4 drugs 
yes 
53 (54.6) 
26 (53.1) 
0.86 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.94 (0.47 -1.87) 
No 
44 (45.4) 
23 (46.9) 
Critical clinical 
conditions </p>

<p>yes 
27 (26.7) 
40 (40.0) 
0.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.83 (0.89 -3.74) 
No 
74 (73.3) 
30 (60.0) </p>

<p>hips weakness 
yes 
37 (37.4) 
19 (38.8) 
0.86 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.06 (0.52 -2.15) 
No 
62 (62.6) 
30 (61.2) </p>

<p>Unstable balance 
yes 
42 (42.9) 
25 (51.0) 
0.35 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.39 (0.70 -2.76) 
No 
56 (57.1) 
24 (49.0) 
Conley filled 
at admission </p>

<p>yes 
42 (42.9) 
25 (51.0) 
&lt; 0.001 
4.92 (2.34 -10.37) 
No 
56 (57.1) 
24 (49.0) </p>

<p>Average (SD) 
Average (SD) 
p 
95%CI 
Age 
63 (21) 
69 (12) 
0.53 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>(-10.89-0.065) 
Average (SD)/ 
median 
(min;max) </p>

<p>Average (SD)/ 
median 
(min;max) </p>

<p>p 
95%CI </p>

<p>Conley 
Score </p>

<p>2,9 (± 1.97) / 
3 (0;5) </p>

<p>3,27 (± 2.66) / 
2 (0;9) 
0.96 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>(-1.89-1.17) </p>

<p>pt : patient 
a p-value chi-square² test </p>

<p>b p-value Fisher exact test </p>

<p>c p-value t-student test for independent samples with unequal variances </p>

<p>d p-value mann-Whitney Test </p>

<p>A.S. Guzzo et Al. </p>

<p>E80 </p>

<p>(11, 22%), and the most part of controls showed 3 (28, 
27.5%). In 4 cases (8%) and 5 controls (4.9%) were found 
6 comorbidities in addition to principal diagnosis. The 
differences were not statistically significant (p= 0.334). 
The two groups, cases and controls, were homogeneous 
for gender, age, citizenship, while, with respect to the pa-
rameters WHO, the adverse event fall, seemed to be as-
sociated with compiling Conley scale at the admission to 
care unit (OR = 4.92, 95%CI: 2.34 -10.37) (Tab. II a, b). </p>

<p>Univariate analysis showed (Tab. IIa-IIb) that intrinsic 
factors that increase the risk of falling out are: pres-
ence of dizziness (OR = 3.22; 95%CI = 1.34 to 7.75), 
and psychomotor agitation (OR = 2.61; 95%CI = 1.06 
to 6.43); among extrinsic risk factors the use of means 
of containment is associated with risk of adverse event 
(OR = 5.05 95%CI = 1.77 to 14.43). 
Conditional logistic regression included 'risk of being a 
case' as dependent variable, and the following covari-</p>

<p>Tab. II b. Univariate analysis between cases and controls. </p>

<p>Variables 
Controls 
(not fallen) N (%) </p>

<p>Cases 
(fallen) N (%) 
P 
OR (95%CI) </p>

<p>hypotension: 
Systolic Bp ≤ 90 </p>

<p>yes 
2 
2 
0.61 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.95 (0.26 -14.34) 
No 
90 
46 
hypertension: 
Systolic Bp ≥ 180 </p>

<p>yes 
2 
2 
0.61 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.93 (0.26 -14.18) 
No 
89 
46 </p>

<p>Fever≥ 38° 
yes 
4 
2 
0.99 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.08 (0.19 -6.15) 
No 
91 
42 </p>

<p>Not integrity of consciousness state 
yes 
7 
3 
0.99 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.80 (0.19 -3.29) 
No 
77 
41 </p>

<p>disoriented 
yes 
13 
8 
0.58 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.30 (0.50 -3.39) 
No 
89 
42 </p>

<p>dizziness 
yes 
11 
14 
0.007 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>3.22 (1.34 -7.75) 
No 
91 
36 
Impaired driving, creeping step, broad base of support, 
unstable march </p>

<p>yes 
45 
25 
0.494 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.27 (0.64-2.50) 
No 
57 
25 </p>

<p>Agitated 
yes 
11 
12 
0.033 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2.61 (1.06 -6.43) 
No 
91 
38 </p>

<p>Impairment of judgment / lack of the sense of danger 
yes 
12 
12 
0.05 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2.37 (0.98 -5.74) 
No 
90 
38 </p>

<p>reduced muscle strength 
yes 
45 
20 
0.59 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.83 (0.42 -1.65) 
No 
56 
30 </p>

<p>patient with impaired vision 
yes 
13 
5 
0.62 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.76 (0.25 -2.27) 
No 
89 
45 </p>

<p>Incontinence (fecal / urine) 
yes 
9 
6 
0.57 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.41 (0.47-4.21) 
No 
93 
44 </p>

<p>Sleeplessness 
yes 
17 
6 
0.45 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.68 (0.25-1.85) 
No 
85 
44 </p>

<p>depression 
yes 
9 
3 
0.75 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.66 (0.17 -2.55) 
No 
93 
47 </p>

<p>Language comprehension deficits (aphasia, foreigner) 
yes 
23 
8 
0.35 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.65 (0.27-1.59) 
No 
79 
42 </p>

<p>memory impairment 
yes 
6 
1 
0.43 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.33 (0.04 -2.79) 
No 
96 
49 </p>

<p>dressings (sutures, decubitus wounds, etc.) 
yes 
8 
6 
0.39 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.60 (0.52 -4.90) 
No 
94 
44 </p>

<p>drainage 
yes 
1 
1 
0.55 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>2.06 (0.12-33.65) 
No 
101 
49 </p>

<p>Urinary catheter 
yes 
23 
12 
0.84 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.08 (0.49-2.41) 
No 
79 
38 </p>

<p>Therapy i.v. (peripheral or central venous access) 
yes 
70 
34 
0.94 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.97 (0.47-2.01) 
No 
32 
16 </p>

<p>Therapy with sedatives 
yes 
35 
17 
0.97 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.99 (0.48 -2.01) 
No 
67 
33 </p>

<p>Treatment with laxatives 
yes 
11 
8 
0.36 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.58 (0.59 -4.20) 
No 
91 
42 </p>

<p>diuretic therapy 
yes 
30 
13 
0.63 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.83 (0.39 -1.78) 
No 
71 
37 </p>

<p>Antihypertensive therapy 
yes 
60 
32 
0.58 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.21 (0.60 -2.45) 
No 
41 
18 </p>

<p>Substances Abuse (alcohol and drugs) 
yes 
8 
4 
0.99 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.02 (0.29-3.57) 
No 
94 
46 </p>

<p>patient in postoperative / anesthesia 
yes 
2 
1 
0.99 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.02(0.09 -11.53) 
No 
100 
49 </p>

<p>Use of restraint means 
yes 
6 
12 
0.001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>5.05 (1.77 -14.43) 
No 
96 
38 </p>

<p>Bold: p &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>Bp: blood pressure </p>

<p>i.v therapy: intravenous therapy </p>

<p>Assessment of Conley sCAle in fAll risk prevention </p>

<p>E81 </p>

<p>ates as independent: gender, age, dizziness, psychomo-
tor agitation and use of means of restraint. 
The fitted model (Tab. III) to analyze association between 
intrinsic and extrinsic factors and risk of falls, revealed a 
statistically significant association with the following out-
come variables, in order: use of means of restraint (HR = 
5.54, 95%CI = 1.29 to 23.80) and dizziness (HR = 3.97, 
95%CI = 1.22 to 12.89). The variable psychomotor agita-
tion is not significantly associated with the outcome fall 
(HR = 1.08, 95%CI = 0.28 to 4.17). The comparison of 
null model to the full model which includes the predictors 
shows a significant difference: the Likelihood Ratio Test 
is: χ² = 16.220 with p = 0.001. </p>

<p>Descriptive analysis of falls dynamic 
Fall events occur mostly during evening and night hours, 
tending to double in specific time range (2:00-2.30; 
4:00-4:30; 6:00-7:00; 21:30-22:00) up to three times 
between 1:30-2:00 a.m. Other patients were present in 
76% of cases (32/42), when event fall occurred, in 7.1% 
(3/42) of cases health personnel and in 2.3% (1/42) fam-
ily members. 
Modality of falling were, in order: from standing posi-
tion in 42% of cases (18/43), from bed in 37% (16/43) 
of cases, by sitting in 14% (6/43) and from wheelchair 
in 2% (2/43). 
With regard to reason of fall, 37% of falls (11/30) occurred 
as a result of loss of balance and sliding on dry pavement; 
while 13% (4/30) was due to loss of strength and 7% (2/30) 
was related to slipping on wet floor and stumbling. 
Analysis of the fall place revealed that 82% (37/45) of 
falls occurred in the hospital room, 15% (7/45) in the 
bathroom and 2% (1/45) in the hallway. 
The type of shoe worn at the moment of fall was, in 45% 
(16/36) of the cases 'an open type', in 14% (5/36) closed 
or socks, and in 28% (10/36) patient was barefoot. 
Means of protection were not in use in 36% of cases 
(16/44), instead they were present in 64% of cases (28/44). 
57% (24/42) of patients fallen had been allowed to get 
up out of bed, while 43% (18/42) had been forbidden. 
Drugs that lower blood pressure, as antihypertensive 
(22/43, 51%) and diuretics (11/43, 25%), have been con-
firmed as the most frequently used among cases, followed 
by benzodiazepines or CNS sedative (10/43, 23%), laxa-
tives (3/43, 7%) and other drugs (20/43, 46.6%). </p>

<p>Falls had serious damage as outcome in 80% of cases 
(35/43), while 20% (9/43) hesitated in minor damage. 
Considering the total cases, the most part of them did not 
require further investigation than the clinical visit, after 
the event, though in 22% of cases (11/50) and in 11% 
(9/50) more detailed radiological diagnostic exams, CT/ 
MRI and RX respectively, have been necessary. Other 
tests have been conducted in 14% of cases (7/50). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Falls are common among hospital inpatients. Rates from 
2.9-13 falls per 1,000 bed days have been reported [5]. 
Up to 30% of reported falls [23] may result in injury, 
including fracture, head and soft tissue trauma, all of 
which may in turn lead to impaired rehabilitation and 
co-morbidity [15, 24]. 
In the present study, despite the heterogeneity of set-
tings, populations and risk factors, a small number of 
items, provided by Conley Scale, emerged as significant 
in relation to risk falling: psychomotor agitation and diz-
ziness, among intrinsic risk factors, already provided by 
Conley Scale, and use of restraints. The first two items 
increase the risk of falling , once and three times, respec-
tively, the use of instruments of restraint, considered as 
extrinsic risk factor, increases the risk of falls over 4 
times. The absence of filling in Conley Scale, at the en-
trance to care unit, predisposes to the event. 
The intake of more than four drugs, the critical clini-
cal conditions, the weakness in the hips and the unstable 
equilibrium, have been confirmed as characteristics that 
increase the risk of falling. On the other hand, the pres-
ence of co-morbidities in addition to the main diagnosis, 
does not appear to increase the risk significantly. 
With regard to the category of drugs, antihypertensive and 
benzodiazepines are the most widely used among cases. 
There is small but a consistent association between the 
use of most classes of psychotropic drugs and falls; spe-
cifically, odds ratio for sedative/hypnotic use was 1.54 
(95%CI, 1.40-1.70) Further adjustment for confounders, 
dosage, or duration of therapy are necessary [25]. In ad-
dition, a metanalysis that studied the relationships of falls 
and medications which included studies that examined 
both multiple and single risk factors found a significantly 
increased risk from psychotropic medications (OR = 1.7), 
Class 1a antiarrhythmic medications (OR = 1.6), digoxin 
(OR = 1.2) and diuretics (OR = 1.1) [26]. As regards the 
description of the fall, most of them occurs during night 
hours, inside the inpatient room, and they are due to loss 
of balance or force. In the 80% of cases no outcomes of 
damage were reported, such as to require further diagnos-
tic tests, such as x-rays or tc. 
Interaction and probable synergism between multiple risk 
factors, is probably important such as identifying risk fac-
tors. Several studies have shown that the risk of falling in-
creases dramatically as the number of risk factors increases. 
Tinetti et al. reported that percentages of persons falling in-
creased from 27% for those with no or one risk factors, to 
78% for those with four or more risk factors [27]. </p>

<p>Tab. III. Conditional logistic regression model of the association be-
tween event fall and covariates: psychomotor agitation, dizziness 
and means of restraint. </p>

<p>Covariates 
hr 
95%CI 
Lower 
Upper 
psychomotor agitation 
1.085 
0.282 
4.169 
dizziness 
3.966 
1.221 
12.886 
means of restraint 
5.537 
1.288 
23.798 
model -2 Log likelihood: 79.33 
Initial Log Likelihood function: -2 Log likelihood: 95.55 
Likelihood ratio test: chi-square=16.220, df=3, p=0.001 </p>

<p>Bold: p &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>A.S. Guzzo et Al. </p>

<p>E82 </p>

<p>Newitt et al. reported that the percentage of community 
living persons with recurrent falls increased from 10% 
to 69% as the number of risk factors increased from one 
to four or more [28]. 
As emerged from other study, profile of patient at risk 
of falling, is a person with mental status and mobility 
impairments [29]. Intrinsic risk factors were identified 
by Rawsky's review [30]: cognitive impairment/psy-
chological status, acute/chronic illness and mobility, 
sensory deficits, fall history, and elimination, recent 
syncope episode and cognitive status [31, 32]. Ruben-
stein et al. [7] analyzed 16 studies and reported the fol-
lowing risk factors, in order: muscle weakness, history 
of falls, gait deficits, balance deficits, use of assistive 
devices, visual deficits, arthritis, impaired activities of 
daily living, depression, cognitive impairments, and age 
80 years. In general, factors related to cognitive impair-
ment, functional decline, and chronic disorders result in 
a higher risk of falls [33]. 
Extrinsic factors (e.g., environmental hazards or hazard-
ous activities) are described as primary causes for ap-
proximately half of all falls [34]. In a review of 20 arti-
cles, Connell [35] found that environmental hazards (e.g., 
walking on slippery/rough surfaces, obstacles, inadequate 
light, or loose carpets) create conditions for trips or slips 
in elderly people who may already have multiple intrinsic 
risk factors for falls. Additionally, the risk from hazard-
ous activities can be increased by behaviors (e.g., faller 
was hurried or inattentive, difficulty or discomfort dur-
ing a task, or moving beyond limits of stability). Within 
inpatient facilities, commonly reported extrinsic factors 
are related use of bedrails, height and stability of seating 
(low toilets, wheelchair braking problems, "gerichairs," 
or portable commodes), and obstacles created by mobil-
ity aids (e.g., wheelchairs and walkers;). Finally, com-
mon locations for inpatient falls are resident rooms or 
bathrooms, with the falls often involving problems with 
ambulation and transfers [35-37]. 
Falls occurred most often in the patient's room when 
they were alone and unassisted while trying to get to the 
bathroom [37]. 
An effective and efficient fall prevention program should 
require quick, reliable, and valid fall risk screens to iden-
tify high-risk patients. In general, recommend criteria 
for choosing the most appropriate assessment tool for a 
specific setting should be: high sensitivity, specificity, 
and reliability [36]. Despite this, the specific instrument 
chosen might vary, depending on the setting and profes-
sionals engaged for filling. Nursing assessment scales 
seem the most appropriate approach for Acute Care Set-
tings and extended care setting, where the majority of 
patients may be at high risk. A substantial number of 
fall risk assessment tools are readily available, most with 
evidence supporting their reliability and validity [36]. 
Frequent monitoring of drugs effects on patients is crucial, 
according to the most part of guidelines. Drugs with an in-
creased need for monitoring, due to their important impact 
on the risk of fall are: antihypertensive and diuretics as it 
can cause hypotension and incontinence of urgency; hyp-
notics; hypoglycemic; neuroleptics because they can in-</p>

<p>duce extrapyramidal disorders. The infusion therapy would 
take a break during the night rest, when possible. 
For prevention, containment and risk of falls multifacto-
rial interventions are required in hospital , which ensure 
evaluative information essential for all types of patients, 
and educational interventions should be tailored to the 
risk emerged. A particular attention should be paid to 
periodic environmental assessment targeted on possible 
risk factors assessed. 
Needs of mobilization and ambulation requires special 
attention by the medical staff, it's important to educate 
patient and caregivers about the correct methods for 
handling and having a safe ambulation (eg. How to per-
form postural changes or movements from bed to chair, 
pass from sitting to standing without loss of balance). 
Patients and caregivers should be trained about aids and 
facilities, in order to avoid their misuse: encouraging the 
use of shoes with not slippery soles; instructing patients to 
get up slowly; assisting patients during high risk transfers 
(eg. from ambulatory to corridor once or vice versa). 
There is no scientific evidence in literature, that use of 
physical or pharmacological restraint protect patients 
from falls. Means of mechanical restraint can result 
psychological and physical adverse effects, direct and 
indirect. Restraint should be applied only when strictly 
necessary, supported by prescription or documented 
evaluations by the nursing care staff, after understand-
ing causes and after taking all possible alternative care 
strategies, including relational interventions. 
Pharmacological restraints (sedation) is acceptable when 
it represents an integral intervention to the therapy. Al-
ternatively to restraint, following initiatives can be un-
dertaken: increasing surveillance, modifying treatments, 
preferring oral feeding to parenteral or nasogastric tube, 
removing catheters and drains. 
Further environmental changes could be: to increase the 
light in the room; to place a disoriented patient near a gate-
house; do not place bed rails; to create a peaceful environ-
ment; to keep the alarm-bell close to patient and answer im-
mediately to calls; to use reality-orienting therapy (ROT) or 
other psychosocial interventions for involving patient in the 
conversation; to provide reference points (calendar, televi-
sion, radio, clock); to use listening activities; to promote 
cognitive recreational and physical activities. 
Finally, as Tinetti et al. argued in a previous study [37], 
all prevention interventions are aimed at increasing 
nursing awareness of patient risk and involving patient 
and caregivers: teaching them; promoting patient inde-
pendence and decreasing use of restraints; and, finally, 
paying attention to patients with impairments or altered 
elimination patterns (incontinence, frequency, nicturia). 
Our results bear out the evidence of scientific literature 
about Conley employment in assessing fall risk. Lovallo 
et al. comparing Conley Scale and Hendrich Risk Mod-
el [37], stated that Conley Scale gave sensitivity and 
specificity values of 69-49% and 61% respectively. The 
Hendrich Model [37] gave a sensitivity value of 45-76% 
and a specificity value of 71%. Conley Scale is more 
indicated for use in medical and surgical sectors on the 
strength of its high sensitivity and specificity, since its </p>

<p>Assessment of Conley sCAle in fAll risk prevention </p>

<p>E83 </p>

<p>specificity is very low it is deemed useful to submit in-
dividual patients giving positive results to more in-depth 
clinical evaluation [22]. Conley Scale doesn't investi-
gate some important clinical characteristics of patient 
that can represent a risk, like: visual impairment [14] 
and sensor-motor functions, incontinence, asthenia, cog-
nitive impairments or sedation [14, 27], and depression; 
likewise it is important to assess environmental condi-
tions and the use of assistive devices, as well [22]. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>It has been shown that in acute care settings, falls during 
hospitalization are more common in confused patients 
and those with greater comorbidity [24]; but the present 
study doesn't support this evidence, maybe comorbidi-
ties should be stratified for disease severity. 
Risk factors should be stratified for specific unit care de-
partments, this population was heterogeneous for diag-
nosis and sample size was small. The most part of cases 
have been recorded in Neurology Department, and it is 
already acknowledged that several diseases have been 
shown to increase the risk of fall such as Alzheimer's 
disease [39], Parkinson's disease [28], and stroke [40]. 
According to the literature further studies need to be car-
ried out in order to: 
• test Conley Scale on a larger sample and stratify risk 
for unit department or comorbidities [41, 42]; 
• empower the role of nurses in fall prevention: en-
couraging the account of risk factors not provided 
by Conley, intrinsic and extrinsic; carrying out a 
comprehensive patient evaluation of motor cognitive 
functionality and psychological status [43]; 
• involve and inform patient and caregivers about fall 
risk. </p>



<p>A.S. Guzzo et Al. </p>





<p>Assessment of Conley sCAle in fAll risk prevention </p>

<p>E85 </p>

<p>Appendix 1 </p>

<p>DATA COLLECTION FORM HOSPITAL ACCIDENTAL FALLS 
N……………………. 
0.MEDICAL RECORD CODE ………………………………………. </p>

<p>1. Is this patient fallen?  yes (CASE)  no (CONTROL) </p>

<p>2. Patient data: 
2.a Birth date (dd/mm/yyyy)…………… (age……… with respect to year of hospitalization) 
2.b Gender: M  F  
2.c City of residence…………………………2.d County/district……………. 
2.e Nationality:  Italian  foreigner </p>

<p>3. Hospitalization data 
3.a Date of admission: dd/mm/ yyyy:……../……./………..…. 
3.b Date of discharge: dd/mm/ yyyy:….…../….…./…………. 
3.c Department of Hospitalization:…………………………………………..…………..(see DB) 
3.d Inpatient: &lt; &gt; ordinary &lt; &gt; day hospital 
3.e Inpatient type: &lt; &gt; urgent &lt; &gt; planned admission (RRR into TRIAGE form) 
&lt; &gt; transferred (see Fax from other hospital) 
3.f Primary diagnosis code (ICD9-CM) : …………… 
3.g Secondary diagnosis codes : I …………….II………..…III……..…IV…………V…….…… </p>

<p>4. Patient at admission 
4.a Unstable/critical patient: yes  no  
If not, answer to following 4 questions (OMS factors): 
4.b .&gt; = 65 years yes  no  
4.c More than four drugs in assumption:yes  no  ß (see ED form or anamnesis) 
4.d Hips weakness: yes  no  
4.e. Unstable balance: yes  no  
4.f Conley filled in at admission: yes  no  
4.g. If CASE: Conley Scale filled in available before fal: yes  no  
4.h Data. Date of the last available CONLEY Scale (FOR CASES: Conley before the fall): 
………………/………………./………………….(dd/mm/aaaa) </p>

<p>Insert Data of CONLEY mentioned above: </p>

<p>C0. Questions to : </p>

<p>patient  Caregiver  Familiy  </p>

<p>Previous Falls 
yes 
no 
missing 
C1. have you fallen in the last three months? 
C2. have you never had vertigo and dizziness? (In the last 3 months) 
C3. have you ever lose urine or feces while going to the bathroom? (In the last 3 months) 
Cognitive impairment (Nurses' Observation) 
C4. Impaired walking, creeping step, broad base of support, unstable march 
C5. Agitated (definition: excessive motor activity, usually no purposeful and associated with 
internal tension. ex. Inability to sit still, moving restlessly, pulling clothes, etc.) 
C6. Impairment of judgment / lack of a sense of safety awareness </p>

<p>CONLEY INDEX ≥ 2 Nursing diagnosis: patient at risk of falling </p>

<p>A.S. Guzzo et Al. </p>

<p>E86 </p>

<p>5. Factors present in the day of case fall: 
Fill in with 'x' for cases and for controls, referring to the day of fall event: 
YES, if the features are explicitly mentioned in the medical record. 
NO, if the features are explicitly mentioned in the medical record. 
NOT PRESENT, if they are not reported in the medical record. </p>

<p>Body Functions 
yes 
no 
NOT PRESENT 
F1) hypotension: pA systolic &lt;= 90 
F2) hypertension: pA systolic&gt; = 180 
F3) Fever &gt;=38° (see clinical diary) 
F4) unhealthy state of consciousness </p>

<p>Fill in for cases and controls referring to the day of the fall of the case. 
Mark with a "x" in case of presence inside medical record or in case of element otherwise deductible for clini-
cal condition. </p>

<p>INTRINSIC FACTORS 
 
FI1) disoriented 
FI2) presence of dizziness 
FI3) (alias C4) Impaired walking, creeping step, broad base of support, unstable march 
FI4) (alias C5) Agitated (definition: excessive motor activity, usually not finalized and associated with inner turmoil. ex. Inability 
to sit still, moving restlessly, pulling clothes, etc.) 
FI5) (alias C6) Impairment of judgment / lack of a sense of danger 
FI6) reduced muscle strength 
FI7) patient with impaired vision 
FI8) Incontinence (fecal / urine) 
FI9) Insomnia (see drugs Benzodiazepines / diary) 
FI10) depreSSION 
FI11) deFICIT UNderSTANdINg LINgUSITCA only if explicitly stated (aphasia, stranger) 
FI12) memory impairment only if explicitly stated 
extrinsic factors 
FA1) dressings (sutures, decubitus wounds, etc.) (see diary / register operative) 
FA2) drainage (see diary and kind intervention) 
FA3) Catetere urinario (vedi diario) 
FA4) Therapy i.v. (peripheral or central venous access) (see chart therapy) 
FA5) Therapy with sedatives (see data falls for cases) 
FA6) Laxative therapy (see data falls for cases) 
FA7) diuretic therapy (see data falls for cases) 
FA8) Antihypertensive therapy (see data falls for cases) 
FA9) Substance Abuse (alcohol and drugs) (see diary) 
FA10) postoperative patient / anesthesia 
FA11) Use of instruments of restraint </p>

<p>Assessment of Conley sCAle in fAll risk prevention </p>

<p>E87 </p>



</text></tei>