<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4662707" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Objective: To quantify the effects of cognitive training (CT) on cognitive and behavioral outcome </p>

<p>measures in patients with Parkinson disease (PD). </p>

<p>Methods: We systematically searched 5 databases for randomized controlled trials (RCTs) of CT </p>

<p>in patients with PD reporting cognitive or behavioral outcomes. Efficacy was measured as stan-
dardized mean difference (Hedges g) of post-training change. </p>

<p>Results: Seven studies encompassing 272 patients with Hoehn &amp; Yahr Stages 1-3 were included. The </p>

<p>overall effect of CT over and above control conditions was small but statistically significant (7 studies: 
g 5 0.23, 95% confidence interval [CI] 0.014-0.44, p 5 0.037). True heterogeneity across studies 
was low (I 
2 5 0%) and there was no evidence of publication bias. Larger effect sizes were noted on 
working memory (4 studies: g 5 0.74, CI 0.32-1.17, p 5 0.001), processing speed (4 studies: 
g 5 0.31, CI 0.01-0.61, p 5 0.04), and executive function (5 studies: g 5 0.30, CI 0.01-0.58, 
p 5 0.042), while effects on measures of global cognition (4 studies), memory (5 studies), visuospatial 
skills (4 studies), and depression (5 studies), as well as attention, quality of life, and instrumental activ-
ities of daily living (3 studies each), were not statistically significant. No adverse events were reported. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Though still small, the current body of RCT evidence indicates that CT is safe and </p>

<p>modestly effective on cognition in patients with mild to moderate PD. Larger RCTs are necessary 
to examine the utility of CT for secondary prevention of cognitive decline in this population. </p>

<p>Neurology ® 2015;85:1843-1851 </p>

<p>GLOSSARY </p>

<p>CI 5 confidence interval; CT 5 cognitive training; MCI 5 mild cognitive impairment; MMSE 5 Mini-Mental State Examination; 
PD 5 Parkinson disease; PEDro 5 Physiotherapy Evidence Database; RCT 5 randomized controlled trial; SMD 5 standard-
ized mean difference. </p>

<p>Cognitive impairment is increasingly recognized as an important nonmotor symptom of Parkin-
son disease (PD). 
1 Neuropsychological impairments in PD are common, with the majority of 
patients showing at least some evidence of cognitive decline, while many progress to mild 
cognitive impairment (MCI) 
2 or dementia. 
3 These changes have a significant impact on quality 
of life in patients, as well as increasing caregiver burden and health care costs. Therefore, 
investigating potential methods of cognitive restoration is vital. </p>

<p>4   Medications have been shown to have only limited benefit in the treatment of cognitive 
impairment in PD 
5 and nonpharmacologic interventions are of interest because the majority 
of patients with advanced PD are already burdened by complex polypharmacy. Cognitive 
training (CT) is one such option, which involves structured and theoretically driven teaching 
of strategies or guided practice on tasks that target particular cognitive domains. 
6 A recent meta-
analysis has shown that computerized CT is efficacious on cognition in healthy older adults 
when supervised, 
7 and a systematic review found evidence for efficacy in MCI. </p>

<p>Reviews of CT in PD have been reported 
previously. 
9-11 However, the literature has 
grown considerably since their publication, 
and meta-analytic techniques had not been pre-
viously employed. Furthermore, these reviews 
were not restricted to randomized controlled 
trials (RCTs) and combined results from CT 
studies with other cognitive interventions. 
Therefore, this study aims to quantitatively 
and systematically examine whether RCTs of 
strictly defined CT can improve cognitive and 
psychosocial outcomes in patients with PD. </p>

<p>METHODS This review adheres to the Preferred Reporting 
Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) 
guidelines, 
12 was prospectively registered with PROSPERO, 
CRD42014012936, and follows methods established in our 
previous review of computerized CT in healthy elderly. </p>

<p>7   Eligibility criteria. We included published reports of RCTs </p>

<p>examining behavioral effects (cognition, instrumental activities of 
daily living, quality of life, and depression) of CT in patients with 
PD. CT was defined as repeated practice on cognitively challenging 
tasks, including strategy training or drill-and-practice exercises using 
computers or pencil-and-paper approaches, for at least 4 hours. For 
studies that used CT in combination with other interventions (e.g., 
occupational therapy), we included only those that had CT as the 
differentiating condition between the study groups and where CT 
comprised at least 50% of the intervention. </p>

<p>Information sources and study selection. We systematically </p>

<p>searched Medline (Ovid), Embase, PsycInfo, CINAHL, and CEN-
TRAL for the term Parkinson's in combination with widely used 
terms describing cognition-based intervention (see full search 
strategy in appendix e-1 on the Neurology ® Web site at 
Neurology.org) from inception to November 6, 2014. There was 
no limit on publication language. Reference and citation lists of 
relevant studies were manually scanned for potential eligible 
articles. One reviewer (I.H.K.L.) performed initial eligibility 
screening by assessing titles and abstracts of all results. Following 
initial screening, 2 independent reviewers (I.H.K.L. and A.L.) 
assessed full-text versions of potentially eligible articles. </p>

<p>Data collection and coding. Two reviewers (I.H.K.L. and </p>

<p>C.C.W.) coded each outcome measure into one cognitive or 
behavioral domain based on the categorization provided in 
Strauss et al., 
13 A Compendium of Neuropsychological Tests, when-
ever possible. Other outcomes were coded by consensus and 
approved by A.L. (see table e-1 for categorization of outcomes 
by domains). Outcomes were recorded as mean and SD for each 
group at baseline and follow-up or as means and SDs of pre-post 
change. All data were entered into <rs id="software-5" type="software">Comprehensive Meta-Analysis</rs> 
(CMA) version <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Biostat</rs>, Englewood, NJ), and utilized an a 
priori pre-post correlation of 0.6. </p>

<p>Risk of bias in individual studies and study appraisal. </p>

<p>Risk of bias in individual studies was conducted in accordance 
with the Cochrane Collaboration's risk of bias tool. 
14 This tool 
assesses high, low, or unclear risk of bias in 6 categories: sequence 
generation; allocation concealment; blinding of participants, 
therapists, and assessors; incomplete outcome data; selective out-
come reporting; and other sources of bias. 
14 We did not assess 
blinding of participants and therapists as such blinding is </p>

<p>impractical in CT trials. We considered studies that lacked asses-
sor blinding or did not adhere to intention-to-treat analysis (i.e., 
those with high risk for incomplete outcome data 
14 ) as having 
high risk of bias. In addition, we used an adapted version of the 
Physiotherapy Evidence Database (PEDro-P) Rating Scale 
15 to 
assess the methodologic quality of the individual studies. The 
original PEDro scale consists of 11 items; however, 2 of the 
scale's items that assessed blinding of therapists and patients 
were not considered due to impracticality in CT trials, and so 
the maximum possible PEDro score was set at 9. The assessment 
of each article was conducted by multiple independent reviewers 
(I.H.K.L., C.C.W., and H.H.). Disagreements were solved by a 
senior reviewer (A.L.). Table e-2 provides the results of risk of bias 
and PEDro assessments for each trial. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. The unit of analysis was standardized mean </p>

<p>difference (SMD) between CT and control groups of change from 
baseline to immediately post-training. We calculated SMD as 
Hedges g with a 95% confidence interval (CI) for each outcome 
measure. We analyzed overall effects by calculating the mean SMD 
of all outcomes in each study and correcting for intercorrelation 
among outcomes by adjusting the mean variance by a factor of 
0.7. 
16,17 SMD and variance from each study were then pooled 
using random-effects model. We analyzed domain-specific effects 
using a similar method, but intercorrelations among tests were 
assumed at 0.8. We used CMA for all analyses. 
Positive values imply training-induced improvement in the 
CT group over and above control. An effect size of g # 0.30 
was considered small, g . 0.30 was considered moderate, and 
$0.60 was considered large. We used the I 
2 statistic with 95% CI 
to quantify the proportion of true variance (i.e., variance from the 
true effect size rather than due to sampling error) from total 
observed variance. 
18 I 
2 values of 25%, 50%, and 75% imply 
low, moderate, and large proportions of variance from the true 
effect size (true heterogeneity), respectively. </p>

<p>18   Finally, we generated funnel plots for each analysis by charting 
SMDs against their standard errors in order to inspect for asymmetry 
that might suggest small study effect (publication bias). 
19 Planned 
analysis of funnel plot asymmetry using Egger test of the intercepts 
was not conducted as there were fewer than 10 studies in the review, 
which does not provide sufficient power for such an analysis. 
19 As a 
pragmatic alternative, we performed sensitivity analyses for domains 
with potential asymmetry by repeating the random-effects analysis 
after removal of outliers. Similarly, a planned series of subgroup 
analyses based on our previously published methods 
7 was not con-
ducted due to an insufficient number of studies. </p>

<p>RESULTS Study selection. After removing duplicate 
entries, we screened 1,109 articles for initial eligibility, 
and excluded 1,014 articles based on their abstract and 
title. We then assessed the full-text versions of 95 full-
text articles and found 8 studies eligible for 
inclusion. </p>

<p>20-27   We requested summary data or 
clarifications from authors of 3 studies; 1 responded 
to and provided information, 1 responded but did not 
provide the requested information, and 1 did not 
respond. Finally, 1 study 
26 was excluded from the 
review as the original article did not report group 
summary data and these could not be obtained from 
the authors (figure 1). A study by Petrelli et al. </p>

<p>24   presented data from 2 intervention groups, namely 
structured and unstructured training, and a passive </p>

<p> 
Neurology 85 November 24, 2015 </p>

<p>ª 2015 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>control group. Analysis of this study compared the 
structured to the passive control group due to lack of 
appropriate control for the second intervention. </p>

<p>Characteristics of included studies. The 7 studies 
included in this review included an overall number 
of 272 participants (CT, n 5 133, mean group size 5 
19; controls, n 5 139, mean group size 5 20; table 1). 
Eighty-one outcomes were used to generate effect sizes. 
Mean age across samples ranged from 59.8 to 69.1 
years. Approximately 57% of patients were male. 
Participants' disease severity ranged between Hoehn 
&amp; Yahr Stages 1 and 3. Five studies were conducted 
in Europe, 
20,22-24,27 1 in the United States, 
21 and 1 in 
Brazil. 
25 Five of the studies compared CT to an active 
control intervention (for description of individual 
studies, see table 1). The average PEDro score was 
6.57/9 (SD 1.18). Six of the 7 studies were found to 
have a high risk of bias due to lack of adherence to 
intention-to-treat analysis, and lack of assessor blinding 
was noted in 2 studies 
21,27 (table e-2). 
Intervention design varied across studies (table 1). 
Four studies used computerized CT, 2 used paper-
based CT, and 1 used a combination of paper-based 
and computerized exercises. Five studies trained </p>

<p>participants in a center (group) settings, 1 provided 
training at home, and 1 included both. Session length 
ranged from 30 to 90 minutes, and total training time 
ranged from 7 to 36 hours. All studies provided 2-3 
training sessions per week. </p>

<p>Overall efficacy on cognitive outcomes. The overall effect 
of CT on cognitive outcomes was small and statistically 
significant (g 5 0.23, 95% CI 0.014-0.44, p 5 0.037; 
figure 2). True heterogeneity across studies was low 
(I 
2 5 0%, 95% 0%-68.58%). The funnel plot did 
not show substantial asymmetry (figure e-1). </p>

<p>Domain-specific efficacy. Executive functions. Five studies 
reported outcomes with measures of executive func-
tions. The combined effect size was moderate and sta-
tistically significant (g 5 0.30, 95% CI 0.01-0.58, p 5 
0.042; figure 3). True heterogeneity across studies was 
low (I 
2 5 0%, 95% CI 0%-59.9%). The funnel plot 
did not show substantial asymmetry (figure e-1). 
Processing speed. Four studies reported processing 
speed outcomes. The combined effect size was moder-
ate and statistically significant (g 5 0.31, 95% CI 
0.01-0.61, p 5 0.04; figure 3). True heterogeneity 
across studies was low (I 
2 5 0%, 95% CI 0%-
74.59%). The funnel plot showed that the 2 least pre-
cise studies yielded the biggest effect sizes (figure e-1). 
Working memory. Four studies reported working 
memory outcomes. The combined effect size was large 
and statistically significant (g 5 0.74, 95% CI 0.32-
1.17, p 5 0.001; figure 3). True heterogeneity across 
studies was low (I 
2 5 27.91%, 95% CI 0%-73.18%). 
The funnel plot did not show significant asymmetry 
(figure e-1), but one outlier with large effect size and 
low precision was detected. 
20 A sensitivity analysis 
excluding the outlier revealed large and statistically sig-
nificant effect (g 5 0.62, 95% CI 0.25-0.99, p 5 
0.001; I 
2 5 0%, 95% CI 0%-95.16%). 
Global cognition. Four studies reported global cogni-
tion outcomes. The combined effect size was moder-
ate and statistically nonsignificant (g 5 0.32, 95% CI 
20.03 to 0.67, p 5 0.065; figure 3). True heteroge-
neity across studies was low (I 
2 5 0%, 95% CI 0%-
61.58%), and the funnel plot did not show evidence 
of asymmetry (figure e-1). 
Memory. Five studies reported memory outcomes. 
The combined effect size was small and statistically 
nonsignificant (g 5 0.13, 95% CI 20.29 to 0.55, 
p 5 0.55; figure 4). True heterogeneity across studies 
was moderate (I 
2 5 55.13%, 95% CI 0%-83.43%), 
and the funnel plot did not show evidence of asym-
metry (figure e-1). 
Visuospatial skills. Four studies reported visuospatial 
outcomes. The combined effect size was negligible 
and statistically nonsignificant (g 5 0.01, 95% CI 
20.58 to 0.61, p 5 0.96; figure 4). True heteroge-
neity across studies was moderate (I 
2 5 65.19%, 95% </p>

<p>Figure 1 
Summary of trial identification and selection </p>

<p>Note that a single study could be excluded on more than one criterion, but appears only once 
in the chart. RCT 5 randomized controlled trial. </p>

<p>Neurology 85 November 24, 2015 </p>

<p>
ª 2015 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>CI 0%-88.18%), and the funnel plot did not show 
evidence of asymmetry (figure e-1). </p>

<p>Depression. Five studies reported depression out-
comes. The combined effect size was moderate and sta-
tistically nonsignificant (g 5 0.50, 95% CI 20.28 to 
1.28, p 5 0.21; figure 4). True heterogeneity across </p>

<p>studies was large (I 
2 5 85.49%, 95% CI 67.98%-
93.43%). The funnel plot revealed one conspicuous 
outlier 
22 (figure e-1). Removal of this study yielded a 
negligible and statistically nonsignificant combined 
effect size (g 5 0.11, 95% CI 20.28 to 0.50, p 5 
0.58; I 
2 5 31.42, 95% CI 0% to 75.37). </p>

<p>Table 1 
Characteristics of included studies </p>

<p>Study </p>

<p>Sample characteristics </p>

<p>Study design: program description </p>

<p>No. 
(% male) </p>

<p>Mean (SD) 
age, y </p>

<p>Mean (SD) 
MMSE </p>

<p>H&amp;Y 
range </p>

<p>Mean (SD) years 
since diagnosis </p>

<p>Ref. 20 15 (60) 
59.70 (10.9) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>29.05 (1.1) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1-3 
3.35 (0.9) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>CT: computerized CT program (<rs type="software">RehaCom</rs>), 
2 3 60 minutes per week for 6 weeks 
(group-based); control: a simple 
computerized visuomotor tapping task </p>

<p>Ref. 21 73 (69) 
68.78 (8.1) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>28.07 (1.5) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1-3 
6.94 (5.5) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>CT: computerized CT (<rs type="software">InSight</rs>), 1-3 3 
60 minutes per week for 13 weeks (home-
based); control: no contact </p>

<p>Ref. 22 42 (68) 
67.84 (6.4) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>27.05 (2.7) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1-3 
6.50 (5.2) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>CT: structured paper-pencil tasks that 
target multiple domains (REHACOP), 3 3 
60 minutes session per week for 12 weeks 
(group-based); control: basic occupational 
activities </p>

<p>Ref. 23 28 (50) 
65.04 (9.2) 
27.89 (1.4) 
1-3 
7.5 (6.8) 
CT: multidomain training combining paper-
pencil with computerized exercises 
(<rs type="software">SmartBrain Tool</rs>), 3 3 45-minute per week 
for 4 weeks (group-based, in addition to 
home exercises); control: speech therapy </p>

<p>Ref. 24 43 (69) 
69.15 (8.7) 
27.9 (2.0) 
1-3 
5.47 (3.2) 
CT: group-based multidomain training 
(NEUROvitalis), 2 3 90 minutes session per 
week for 6 weeks; control: no contact </p>

<p>Ref. 25 32 (67) 
67.40 (8.1) 
26.80 (2.4) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1-2 
5 (4.5) 
CT: multidomain training with an integrative 
computerized CT program combining motor 
training with attention and working memory, 
2 3 30 minutes per week for 7 weeks 
(group-based); control: balance exercises </p>

<p>Ref. 27 39 (68) 
68.05 (8.3) 
29 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>5.15 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>CT: multidomain computerized training 
(<rs type="software">CogniPlus</rs>), 3 3 40 minutes session per 
week for 4 weeks (group-based); control: 
Exergames (Nintendo Wii) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CT 5 cognitive training; H&amp;Y 5 Hoehn &amp; Yahr; MMSE 5 Mini-Mental State Examination. 
a Means for the complete sample (comprising subjects who were not included in the final analysis). 
b Measured with the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (1-30 range). 
c Average of median scores. 
d Based on subtracting mean age at diagnosis from mean age at baseline. </p>

<p>Figure 2 
Overall efficacy of cognitive training on all cognitive outcomes </p>

<p>Effect estimates are based on a random-effects model. CI 5 confidence interval; CT 5 cognitive training. </p>

<p> 
Neurology 85 November 24, 2015 </p>

<p>ª 2015 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>Other outcomes. Analyses of domains that were 
reported in only 3 studies each did not reveal statis-
tically significant results (attention: g 5 20.13, 
p 5 0.72; instrumental activities of daily living: 
g 5 0.01, p 5 0.93; quality of life: g 5 20.10, 
p 5 0.64). </p>

<p>Adverse events. No adverse events related to CT 
were reported. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION Following previous findings from 
systematic reviews establishing the efficacy of CT 
on cognition in healthy older adults 
7 and MCI, </p>

<p>8   we report that this intervention could potentially 
help to attenuate cognitive deficits in patients with 
PD. The current body of RCT evidence is small 
but of reasonable quality, and synthesis of out-
comes found clinically meaningful improvements </p>

<p>Figure 3 
Efficacy of cognitive training on measures of executive function, processing speed, working memory, and global cognition </p>

<p>Effect estimates are based on a random-effects model. CI 5 confidence interval; CT 5 cognitive training. </p>

<p>Neurology 85 November 24, 2015 
1847 </p>

<p>ª 2015 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>in overall cognition, as well as moderate to large 
effect sizes on measures of working memory, pro-
cessing speed, and executive functions. Overall, 
our review provides the first high-level evidence 
that CT is efficacious on cognition in patients 
with PD. </p>

<p>The effect on Mini-Mental State Examination 
(MMSE) and Montreal Cognitive Assessment as 
measures of global cognition did not reach the thresh-
old of statistical significance, though this may reflect 
relatively high baseline scores (average MMSE score 
range 26.8-29) as well as the insensitivity of these </p>

<p>Figure 4 
Efficacy of cognitive training on measures of attention, memory, visuospatial skills, and depression </p>

<p>Effect estimates are based on a random-effects model. CI 5 confidence interval; CT 5 cognitive training. </p>

<p> 
Neurology 85 November 24, 2015 </p>

<p>ª 2015 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>global tools as outcome measures. The MMSE in 
particular is known to be an unreliable tool in patients 
with PD, 
28 and this may have impacted the finding as 
3 of the 4 studies assessing global cognitive outcomes 
reported MMSE scores. 
In patients with PD without dementia, cognitive 
deficits are typically frontostriatal by nature. </p>

<p>29   Thus, executive skills such as planning, cognitive 
flexibility, verbal fluency, and inhibitory control 
in addition to working memory type tasks have all 
been shown to be impaired in this patient 
group. 
30,31 That these functions are improved in 
response to CT is encouraging, providing strong 
support for continuation of CT trials in this popu-
lation. Interestingly, improvements in executive 
functions were not shown in a recent meta-
analysis in healthy older adults, 
7 possibly because 
deterioration in these domains is less pronounced 
in normal cognitive aging than in PD. Processing 
speed is another cognitive domain that is vitally 
important for everyday functioning, and typically 
shows declines in PD. 
32 Effects in this domain are 
consistent with those found in healthy elderly. </p>

<p>7   Memory did not demonstrate any statistically 
significant effect. Similarly, lack of effect on visuospa-
tial skills, a key domain of PD-related cognitive defi-
cits 
33 that responds well to CT in healthy older 
adults, 
7 warrants development of new CT exercises 
that target these domains. An analysis of depression 
yielded a negligible effect size after one outlier study 
was removed. However, depression scores in the sam-
ples were low; for example, the average Geriatric 
Depression Scale-15 score of the CT in the 2 studies 
that reported this outcome 
22,23 was 2.33 (SD 1.51), 
while the average Beck Depression Inventory-II score 
was 8.90 (SD 3.1) in 2 other studies </p>

<p>20,24   ; neither 
indicates depressive symptoms in the cohorts and 
thus a ceiling effect is likely. 
The findings of the current meta-analysis are of 
particular interest given the lack of efficacy illustrated 
in pharmacologic treatments for cognitive decline in 
PD. An extensive evidence-based medical review of 
the area in 2011 
5 showed that with the possible 
exception of rivastigmine there is insufficient evi-
dence for pharmacologic therapy for dementia in 
PD. Thus, given its efficacy, safety, and relatively 
low cost, implementation of CT should be pushed 
forward as a pragmatic approach for maintaining cog-
nition in PD. </p>

<p>4   The current body of evidence is thus compelling 
and warrants further studies aiming at establishing 
standards for CT in PD populations and clinical im-
plementation. To achieve this goal, future studies 
will need to ensure adherence to the highest RCT 
standards, as several recent studies were excluded 
for non-RCT criteria (e.g., references 34-36), and </p>

<p>while RCTs in this review reported relatively low 
attrition rates (all # 15%), intention-to-treat anal-
yses were not performed in 6 studies, thereby poten-
tially inflating the results to some extent. Not least 
important is to ensure assessor blinding, mask in-
terventions as much as possible by using active con-
trol groups or head-to-head comparisons of 
different CT interventions, and include large 
enough sample sizes to sufficiently power studies 
to detect effects on key clinical outcomes. Indeed, 
the typical trial in this review was modest in size 
(median n 5 39), while the sample size needed to 
provide 80% power at the 0.05 level for an antici-
pated effect size of g 5 0.23 is approximately 129, 
allowing for 15% attrition rate. Given objective dif-
ficulties recruiting and working with a PD popula-
tion on a consistent basis as required for CT, the 
field might benefit from the inception of large, mul-
ticenter trials. 
Clearly, the relatively small number of RCTs and 
their typically small sample sizes limited the precision 
of our findings and our ability to perform planned 
analyses in several domains. Similarly, we could not 
perform subgroup analyses that could indicate the rel-
ative efficacy of intervention design elements, due to 
the small number of studies as well as the lack of 
true heterogeneity (i.e., I 
2 5 0%) in overall cognitive 
results. Further, neuropsychological classification into 
independent domains cannot accurately reflect the 
complex nature of these tasks, which often tap into 
multiple areas of cognition. Replication of this meta-
analysis in the future will be crucial once further stud-
ies have been completed. 
This meta-analysis suggests that CT leads to mea-
surable improvements in cognitive performance in in-
dividuals with PD, particularly in working memory, 
executive functioning, and processing speed, which 
are typically impaired in the disease. Future RCTs 
employing large samples are required. The efficacy 
of CT in more cognitively impaired PD cohorts re-
mains to be investigated. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </p>

<p>Design and/or conceptualization of the study: I.H.K.L., M.V., A.L. Anal-
ysis and/or interpretation of the data: I.H.K.L., C.C.W., H.H., M.V., 
A.L. Drafting and/or revising the manuscript: I.H.K.L., C.C.W., 
H.H., S.J.G.L., M.V., A.L. </p>

<p>STUDY FUNDING </p>

<p>C.C.W. is supported by an Australian Postgraduate Award at the Univer-
sity of Sydney. S.J.G.L. is supported by a National Health and Medical 
Research Council of Australia (NHMRC) Practitioner Fellowship (ID 
1003007). M.V. is an NHMRC Clinical Career Development Research 
Fellow (ID 1004156). A.L. is supported by an NHMRC Project Grant 
(ID 1084880). </p>

<p>DISCLOSURE </p>

<p>I. Leung, C. Walton, H. Hallock, and S. Lewis report no disclosures 
relevant to the manuscript. M. Valenzuela receives in-kind research </p>

<p>Neurology 85 November 24, 2015 </p>

<p>
ª 2015 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>support in the form of no-cost software from BrainTrain Inc. (USA) 
and HAPPYneuron Inc. (USA/France) for projects unrelated to this 
work. A. Lampit receives in-kind research support in the form of no-
cost software from BrainTrain Inc. (USA) and HAPPYneuron Inc. 
(USA/France) for projects unrelated to this work. Go to Neurology. 
org for full disclosures. </p>

<p>Received February 6, 2015. Accepted in final form June 25, 2015. </p>



<p> 
Neurology 85 November 24, 2015 </p>

<p>ª 2015 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>



<p>Neurology 85 November 24, 2015 </p>

<p>
ª 2015 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

</text></tei>