<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4303630" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Eukaryotic microbes are key ecosystem drivers; however, we have little theory and few data 
elucidating the processes influencing their observed population patterns. Here we provide an 
in-depth quantitative analysis of population separation and similarity in the yeast Saccharomyces 
cerevisiae with the aim of providing a more detailed account of the population processes occurring 
in microbes. Over 10 000 individual isolates were collected from native plants, vineyards and 
spontaneous ferments of fruit from six major regions spanning 1000 km across New Zealand. From 
these, hundreds of S. cerevisiae genotypes were obtained, and using a suite of analytical methods 
we provide comprehensive quantitative estimates for both population structure and rates of gene 
flow or migration. No genetic differentiation was detected within geographic regions, even between 
populations inhabiting native forests and vineyards. We do, however, reveal a picture of national 
population structure at scales above B100 km with distinctive populations in the more remote 
Nelson and Central Otago regions primarily contributing to this. In addition, differential degrees of 
connectivity between regional populations are observed and correlate with the movement of fruit by 
the New Zealand wine industry. This suggests some anthropogenic influence on these observed 
population patterns. 
Research to date attempting to elucidate the patterns 
and processes involved in shaping natural popula-
tions has largely focused on readily observed macro-
organisms but comparatively little work has been 
conducted on microbial species (Anderson and Kohn, 
1998; Martiny et al., 2006; Prosser et al., 2007). 
Because of their large population sizes, and ease of 
transfer, one might expect microbial populations to 
be well mixed (Finlay, 2002); however, there is 
increasing evidence showing that many are not 
homogeneous but structured (Taylor et al., 2006; 
Whitaker and Banfield, 2006; Hanson et al., 2012). 
Most microbial ecology studies have focused on 
bacteria, but eukaryotic microbes, which undergo 
sex (with recombination), also have key ecosystem 
roles (Green et al., 2008; Van Der Heijden et al., 2008). 
It is not clear whether the population patterns 
estimated for eukaryotic 'macrobes' generally hold for 
eukaryotic microbes (Hartl and Clark, 1997; Anderson 
and Kohn, 1998; Halkett et al., 2005; Taylor et al., 
2006; Prosser et al., 2007; Tsai et al., 2008). </p>

<p>A metapopulation comprises a number of spa-
tially separated populations of the same species 
that interact to some extent. To date all studies 
examining microbial populations have simply 
examined whether population structure is evident 
or not (Aa et al., 2006; Achtman, 2008; Liti et al., 
2009; Goddard et al., 2010; Anderson and Shearer, 
2011; Härnströ m et al., 2011; Gayevskiy and 
Goddard, 2012; Wang et al., 2012). Merely defining 
microbial populations as either structured or 
homogeneous is highly unlikely to reflect the true 
biological situation. A more accurate approach is 
not only to assess the degree to which populations 
are structured, but also connected by gene flow, and 
crucially go onto quantify these processes; however, 
to the best of our knowledge, there are no previous 
studies that have used a unified framework to do 
this. Here we analyse the natural population of 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae in New Zealand (NZ), 
and in doing so take the first steps towards 
quantifying microbial population structure and 
similarity. 
S. cerevisiae, a budding yeast, has been closely 
associated with humans since the dawn of civilisa-
tion because of its fermentative capabilities, and has 
come to be of significant commercial importance in 
the production of bread, wine, beer and other 
alcoholic beverages (McGovern et al., 1996; 
Pretorius, 2000; Cavalieri et al., 2003; Chambers 
and Pretorius, 2010). S. cerevisiae is also a classic </p>

<p>Correspondence: S Knight, School of Biological Sciences, 
University of Auckland, 3A Symonds St Private Bag 92019, 
Auckland Mail Centre, Auckland 1142, New Zealand. 
E-mail: s.knight@auckland.ac.nz 
Received 6 April 2014; revised 3 June 2014; accepted 11 June 
2014; published online 25 July 2014 </p>

<p>The ISME Journal (2015) 9, 361-370 
&amp; 2015 International Society for Microbial Ecology All rights reserved 1751-7362/15 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/ismej </p>

<p>model organism for research into cell biology, 
genetics and increasingly ecology and evolution 
(Chambers and Pretorius, 2010; Dujon, 2010; Gray 
and Goddard, 2012; Hittinger, 2013; Hyma and Fay, 
2013). Recent studies have revealed a large genetic 
diversity within S. cerevisiae, and there is good 
evidence for population structure at intercontinental 
scales (Fay and Benavides, 2005; Schuller et al., 
2005; Aa et al., 2006; Lopandic et al., 2008; Liti 
et al., 2009; Goddard et al., 2010; Mercado et al., 
2011; Di Maio et al., 2012; Wang et al., 2012). 
Similar inferences have been made at finer scales 
with reports that some genotypes were unique to 
different geographic locations in Austria, although 
many were also ubiquitous across regions (Lopandic 
et al., 2008). In addition, Bayesian inference 
shows genetic differentiation between populations 
spanning hundreds of kilometres in NZ (Gayevskiy 
and Goddard, 2012). While the scales of these 
studies differ, they all commonly report the 
presence of hybrid or mosaic strains indicative of 
some levels of connectivity between populations via 
gene flow. 
Global-scale analyses have suggested that ecolo-
gical function may define population structure to a 
greater extent than geographic origin (Fay and 
Benavides, 2005; Legras et al., 2007). Strains 
associated with wine appear somewhat distinct 
from those isolated from distilling, bread making, 
fermented milk, rice wine, ale and lager, with 
geographic origin only explaining 28% of variability 
(Legras et al., 2007). Furthermore, whole-genome 
analyses of a limited number of strains suggest 
specific S. cerevisiae populations associated with 
vineyards, sake and related ferments, although some 
of these clusters are confounded with geographic 
origin (Liti et al., 2009; Schacherer et al., 2009). In 
contrast, a recent rigorous genome-wide population 
study has provided evidence of gene flow across 
small distances (o17 km) between distinct popula-
tions inhabiting vineyards and oak trees, showing 
connectivity between ecological niches at small 
scales (Hyma and Fay, 2013). 
Despite these excellent efforts to date, most 
studies have been drawn from widely dispersed 
isolates often from different ecological niches, with 
relatively small sample sizes from any one discrete 
population (Fay and Benavides, 2005; Aa et al., 
2006; Legras et al., 2007; Liti et al., 2009; Schacherer 
et al., 2009; Wang et al., 2012) and have thus not 
afforded adequate power to quantify 'ecological 
scale' population processes such as gene flow. 
Previous work using both microsatellite and RAD-
seq analyses shows that a distinct S. cerevisiae 
population resides in NZ, suggesting that this 
population is not subject to rampant inward inter-
national gene flow (Goddard et al., 2010; Cromie 
et al., 2013). Therefore, in addition to its geographic 
isolation, the NZ S. cerevisiae population appears 
relatively self-contained and thus provides a good 
population to study the processes we are interested in. </p>

<p>Here we analyse close to a thousand S. cerevisiae 
isolates from four niches across six regions spanning 
over 1000 km. We quantify both the degree to which 
this population is structured and go on to quantify 
the extent to which the various regional populations 
are connected by gene flow in one of the most 
comprehensive studies of a microbial metapopula-
tion to date. Lastly, this study sheds light on the 
connection between farmed (managed) and native 
ecosystems by examining the relationship between 
microbial populations residing in vineyards and 
native NZ forest. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Sample collection and processing 
Six to seven Vitis vinifera var. Sauvignon Blanc 
vineyards were selected from each of Hawke's Bay, 
Martinborough, Nelson, Awatere Valley, Wairau 
Valley and Central Otago in NZ (Figure 1). Approxi-
mately 5 g of soil were aseptically taken from each of 
these 37 vineyards between 1 and 4 weeks before 
harvest in mid-March 2011. Ten litres of juice 
derived from the same vineyards were collected 
from commercial settling tanks (one vineyard pro-
vided juice samples from two pressing tiers, result-
ing in a total of 38 juice samples). Soil and fruit 
samples were taken from six native NZ plants 
located in non-managed native bush reserves within 
each region (Supplementary Table S2), ranging from 
0.1 to 50 km from the vineyard sites, totalling 72 
native samples (36 soil and 36 fruit). S. cerevisiae is 
rare in niches other than in actively fermenting fruit, 
so equivalent selective culturing methods were 
employed for all samples to control for the effects 
of high sugar and ethanol (Mortimer and Polsinelli, 
1999; Pretorius, 2000; Xufre et al., 2006; Goddard, 
2008; Taylor et al., 2014). An enrichment method 
emulating fermenting selection pressures was 
employed for all 147 environmental samples 
(Mortimer and Polsinelli, 1999; Serjeant et al., 
2008). Samples were submerged in 10 ml SelMed 
media (1% yeast extract, 2% peptone, 10% glucose 
and 5% ethanol) for six days; 500 ml was then 
transferred to 10 ml fresh SelMed for four additional 
days, and then dilutions plated onto YPD (1% yeast 
extract, 2% peptone, 2% glucose) with 50 mg ml </p>

<p>À 1 </p>

<p>chloramphenicol to retard bacterial growth. All 
incubation was at 28 
1 C. Up to 94 colonies were 
taken from each sample and stored in 15% glycerol 
at À 80 
1 C. A total of 7144 individuals were isolated 
from environmental samples. A natural enrichment 
of the juice samples was performed by allowing 
them to ferment spontaneously at 15 1C. In all, 
100 ml was concentrated by centrifugation after 21 
days, and plated on YPD with 50 mg ml 
À 1 chloram-
phenicol. Again 94 colonies were isolated from each 
ferment sample totalling 3572 individuals. All 
niches were thus evenly sampled and in total 
10 716 individuals were collected. </p>

<p>Structure and gene flow in a microbial eukaryote 
S Knight and MR Goddard </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>Molecular methods 
Genomic DNA was extracted from colonies with 
15 ml of 1.25 mg ml 
À 1 Zymolyase solution dissolved 
in 1.2 M sorbitol and 0.1 M KH 2 PO 4 at pH 7.2 and 
treated with EMA to bind unwanted DNA fragments 
(Rueckert and Morgan, 2007). We employed a 
multiplex PCR reaction to distinguish S. cerevisiae, 
and this also identifies S. uvarum (de Melo Pereira 
et al., 2010). DNA from eight S. cerevisiae colonies 
from each sample were initially amplified and 
scored at 10 unlinked loci as described by 
Richards et al. (2009) using capillary electrophoresis 
on an ABI3130XL (Applied Biosystems, Life 
Technologies, Mulgrave, VIC, Australia). If all eight 
initial isolates were genotypically identical then no 
further genotyping was performed for that sample; 
however, if more than one genotype was recovered, 
another eight were genotyped until either no new 
genotypes were seen, or all isolates from the sample 
had been genotyped. A number of control samples </p>

<p>were submitted for the calculation of error rates per 
allele and per locus as described by Pompanon et al. 
(2005). To further ascertain the reliability of micro-
satellite loci amplification and scoring, we analysed 
an additional 96-well control plate replicating the 
same strain for DNA extraction, PCR amplification 
and genotyping. </p>

<p>Data analyses 
A ± 1-bp error in size calling from run to run 
variation and plus-A effects was observed and 
loci were binned accordingly using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Genemapper</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 4</rs>). F-statistics, migration estimates (Nm values) 
and Mantel tests were performed with <rs id="software-1" type="software">GenAlEx 
(Genetic Analyses in Excel</rs>) <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 6.5</rs> (Peakall and 
Smouse, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-date">2006</rs>; Peakall and Smouse, 2012). 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">Estimates</rs> of population diversity were calculated 
by rarefaction (which controls for unequal 
sample sizes) using EstimateS (Colwell, 2006). </p>

<p>Figure 1 The location of NZ regions and analyses of population structure and connectivity. Plots of the ancestry profiles are shown 
beside each region: each vertical line represents an individual with the different colours showing the proportion of ancestry of each 
individual to each of the 16 inferred populations. Arrows connecting different regions show directional migration rates as calculated in 
MIGRATE with the width of the arrows representing the number of migrants per generation as indicated in the scale. Absolute numbers 
can be found in Supplementary Table S4. The table reports pairwise F ST values below the diagonal and the number of migrants per 
generation (Nm) as calculated from F ST above the diagonal. All F ST values are significant (Po0.01). </p>

<p>Structure and gene flow in a microbial eukaryote 
S Knight and MR Goddard </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>The maximum likelihood outcrossing rates were 
estimated in <rs id="software-3" type="software">Mathematica</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">7</rs> following the method used 
by <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Johnson</rs> et al. (2004) that estimates the proportion of 
matings between spores from the same meiotic event 
(that is, that are asci mates), and those from indepen-
dent meiotic events (code available at http:// 
goddardlab.auckland.ac.nz/data-and-code/). Allelic 
richness was estimated using rarefaction with HP 
rare, again controlling for unequal sample sizes, 
based on the lowest number of 94 observed alleles 
among sampled populations (Kalinowski, 2005). 
Population structure was evaluated using the 
Bayesian clustering method implemented in 
<rs type="software">InStruct</rs>, which does not assume Hardy-Weinberg 
Equilibrium, accounts for inbreeding, and makes no 
a priori assumptions about the sampling location of 
the genotypes (Gao et al., 2007). This method 
estimates the most likely number of populations 
and assigns genotypes to these probabilistically. 
Admixture was allowed and the proportion of each 
genotype's ancestry in each inferred population was 
estimated. Three chains of one million MCMC 
iterations with a burn-in of 10 000 were run for 
K ¼ 1-25. Convergence of the MCMC chain was 
confirmed using the Gelman-Rubin statistic 
(Gelman and Rubin, 1992). Analyses of the resulting 
ancestry profiles evaluating and quantifying the 
contribution of niche and geographic region to 
population structure was conducted with <rs id="software-5" type="software">ObStruct</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Gayevskiy et al.</rs>., <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-date">2014</rs>). 
Directional migration rates were quantified using 
the Bayesian coalescent approach implemented in 
MIGRATE that assumes constant population sizes, 
random mating, a constant mutation rate and that 
populations are connected only through migration, 
not population divergence (Beerli and Felsenstein, 
2001; Beerli, 2006, 2009; Beerli and Palczewski, 
2010). Mutation-scaled population sizes (y) were 
calculated using the number of sampled alleles 
(Haasl and Payseur, 2010). We employed a Brownian 
motion allele mutation model with starting esti-
mates of the mutation-scaled migration rate derived 
from F ST calculations to estimate all possible migra-
tion routes. Chains of one million steps with a burn-
in of 50 000 were run with 10 replicates, sampling 
every 100 steps (Beerli, 2009). The analysis was run 
in parallel on the NeSI pan cluster at the University 
of Auckland. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>S. cerevisiae presence, abundance and genetic diversity 
PCR analyses revealed that 3900 (36%) of the 10 716 
isolates were S. cerevisiae. Of the 3780 isolates from 
spontaneous ferments, 2210 (56%) were S. cerevisiae 
and 1570 (40%) S. uvarum, revealing the co-existence 
of a sister Saccharomyces species in this niche. 
Here we do not pursue the population genetics 
of S. uvarum. S. cerevisiae was detected in 13 of the 
37 vineyard soils, and four and one of the 36 native </p>

<p>soil and fruit samples, respectively. The breakdown 
of samples that yielded S. cerevisiae is shown in 
Supplementary Tables S1 and S2. 
From control samples, two loci (YOR267C and 
YBR240C) amplified unreliably and were removed 
from all analyses. Overall the mean error rates per 
allele and locus were ± 4.08% and 4.35%, respec-
tively. In total 850 individuals were genotyped, with 
681 isolates from spontaneous ferments, 130 from 
vineyard soil, 31 from native soil and 8 from native 
fruits. Identical genotypes within the same sample 
were collapsed to conservatively account for clonal 
expansion during enrichment and fermentation 
meaning the data set was compressed to 380 
genotype profiles. Just 11 genotypes matched com-
mercially available wine strains commonly used in 
NZ (Richards et al., 2009) and were removed 
from further analyses. This resulted in a final 
data set comprising 369 microsatellite profiles 
(Supplementary Data set S1). Interestingly, no geno-
types matched a genetically and ecologically diverse 
set of international strains (Liti et al., 2009) geno-
typed using the same method (Richards et al., 2009; 
Goddard et al., 2010). 
For the entire data set, a large allelic diversity was 
detected at all loci. YFR028C and YML091C had the 
greatest diversity with 25 and 30 alleles, respec-
tively, and all other loci had between 11 and 16 
alleles. Overall, 295 different genotypes were recov-
ered and only 38 of these were identified in more 
than one sample. On average samples that yielded 
S. cerevisiae contained 4.7 unique genotypes, 
although most alleles were shared between popula-
tions (Supplementary Data set S1). Rarefaction 
analyses (Chao, 1987; Colwell, 2006) estimate that 
these genotypes were sampled from an underlying 
NZ population containing B1700 different geno-
types (with 95% confidence limits of 1159-2486). </p>

<p>Testing for ecological drivers of population structure 
Only four different genotypes were derived from 
native fruits and soil, and 21 from vineyard soil 
(Supplementary S1 and S2). This translates to low 
statistical power to test how the niche of isolation 
affects population structure. Despite this, observa-
tions of identical genotypes between niches within, 
but not between, regions are striking. For example, 
genotypes recovered from native soil and fruit in the 
Martinborough region (Waiohine Gorge) were iden-
tical to spontaneous ferment isolates recovered 
20 km away in Martinborough vineyards but were 
not found in other NZ regions; three of the 
genotypes isolated from vineyard soil in the Wairau 
Valley were identical to isolates from spontaneous 
ferments sourced in the same region, with one of 
these vineyard soil genotypes being identical to an 
isolate from the spontaneous ferment from the same 
vineyard. F ST values between environmental sam-
ples (from native soil and fruit and vineyard soil) 
and spontaneous ferment samples within regions </p>

<p>Structure and gene flow in a microbial eukaryote 
S Knight and MR Goddard </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>are extremely low (o0.005) and insignificant 
(P40.33) with the exception of Martinborough 
(F ST ¼ 0.046, P ¼ 0.003); however, this F ST value is 
classed as only representing 'low' differentiation 
(Wright, 1978). There is complete overlap of isolates 
deriving from all niches in a principal component 
analysis of genetic distances between genotypes 
(Supplementary Figure S1) and no significant 
population differentiation between niches within 
regions using <rs type="software">InStruct</rs> and subsequent <rs type="software">ObStruct</rs> 
analyses (P40.119, Supplementary Figure S2). 
Together, this provides no substantial evidence of 
an effect of niche on population structure within 
regions. Some of the S. cerevisiae genotypes con-
tributing to spontaneous ferments may have derived 
from wineries, as opposed to the 'environment' 
(Bokulich et al., 2013). As all of these wineries 
reside within the same geographic regions the fruit 
was collected from, these potentially winery derived 
genotypes form part of the local population we wish 
to study. Thus, individuals from various niches 
within regions comprise homogenous populations, 
and so we combined all genotypes from different 
niches within regions to form regional populations 
for further analyses. </p>

<p>Testing for geographic drivers of population structure 
There was significant genetic differentiation, as 
estimated by pairwise F ST values, between popula-
tions deriving from all six regions (Po0.01), with the 
exception of those between the Wairau and Awatere 
Valley's (F ST ¼ 0.001, P ¼ 0.310). These two valleys 
comprise the wider Marlborough region and were 
thus combined to represent one population residing 
in Marlborough. The subsequent pairwise F ST values 
between regions are shown in Figure 1. A low albeit 
significant correlation was observed between genetic 
and geographic distance (Mantel Test: R 
2 ¼ 0.181, 
Po0.001). Population diversity, as estimated by 
rarefaction analyses to control for uneven numbers 
of genotypes, differs by as much as threefold between 
regions (Table 1). Hawke's Bay and Marlborough </p>

<p>harbour the greatest diversity, whereas Nelson and 
Central Otago the least. Allelic richness across regions 
is comparable to estimates within one s.d. of each 
other (Table 1). All eight loci in all regions are 
significantly out of Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium 
(Po0.001), and show strong signals for inbreeding; 
however, outcrossing rates are significantly above 
zero within each region (Table 1). </p>

<p>Quantifying geographic population structure 
<rs id="software-9" type="software">InStruct</rs> analyses (<rs corresp="#software-9" type="creator">Gao et al.)</rs>., <rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-date">2007</rs>) indicate the 
optimal number of populations, given the data are 
16. Examination of the ancestry profile plots 
(Rosenberg, 2004) resulting from this analysis are 
indicative of population structure by region to some 
degree (for example, the blocks of green, red and 
yellow in Nelson, Central Otago and Martinborough, 
respectively) and are in agreement with the magni-
tude of the pairwise F ST estimates (Figure 1). Sub-
sequent <rs type="software">ObStruct</rs> analyses revealed that the inferred 
population structure is significantly correlated with 
geographic location (R 
2 ¼ 0.16, Po0.0001), and this 
explains about one-sixth of the genetic variability 
observed. Individuals from the Nelson and Central 
Otago regions contributed the greatest signal to 
overall population structure with significant 
decreases in the R 
2 values observed when these are 
removed (R 
2 ¼ D À 0.05 and D À 0.02, respectively). 
The R 
2 value remained constant when data from 
Martinborough were removed but increased when 
Hawke's Bay and Marlborough data were indepen-
dently removed (R 
2 ¼ D þ 0.03 for both). Increases in 
R 
2 suggest individuals from these regions add noise 
to any signal for structure (that is, have homogenised 
not localised populations). Further, canonical 
discriminant analysis shows that B80% of the 
variation in ancestry profiles can be represented 
with the first and second axes, suggesting that 
most of the variation can be visualised in these 
graphical representations of the data (Supplementary 
Figure S3). Ancestry profiles from Central Otago and 
Nelson cluster the most discretely in these plots, </p>

<p>Table 1 Summary of the populations isolated from each region </p>

<p>Region 
Number of 
individuals </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Number of different 
genotypes </p>

<p>Estimated total 
number of 
genotypes </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Mean allelic 
richness </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Inbreeding 
Coefficient F IS </p>

<p>Outcrossing 
rate </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Region-specific 
genotypes </p>

<p>Hawke's Bay 
94 
87 
482: 272-932 
10.72±4.86 
0.6483 
0.12: 0.09-0.16 
79/87: 91% 
Martinborough 
68 
56 
291: 150-647 
11.02±4.29 
0.6067 
0.11: 0.08-0.16 
52/56: 93% 
Nelson 
66 
48 
131: 82-252 
7.29±1.83 
0.2620 
0.42: 0.32-0.54 
44/48: 92% 
Marlborough 
91 
76 
415: 138-1610 10.47 ± 3.64 
0.5331 
0.18: 0.14-0.24 
70/76: 92% 
Central Otago 
50 
44 
144: 84-293 
8.29 ± 2.84 
0.5869 
0.14: 0.09-0.20 
39/44: 89% </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>The number of individuals included in the final analysis after the collapsing of identical individuals because of clonal expansion. 
b The estimated number of genotypes in the population by rarefaction with 95% upper and lower rarefaction limit calculated using <rs id="software-11" type="software">EstimateS</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-11" type="creator">Colwell</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-11" type="version-date">2006</rs>). </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Calculated for each locus independently using HP Rare and based on 94 genes. The mean±1 s.d. are reported. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>The average proportion of spores mating from independent tetrads per meiotic generation surrounded by 2 log likelihood support limits 
(equivalent to a 95% confidence interval), calculated following Johnson et al. (2004). </p>

<p>Structure and gene flow in a microbial eukaryote 
S Knight and MR Goddard </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>recapitulating that populations from these regions 
provide the strongest signals for differentiation. 
Pairwise comparisons between regions all signifi-
cantly differ (Po0.001 or P ¼ 0.06 between Hawke's 
Bay and Marlborough), but the R 
2 values vary from 
0.02 to 0.23 (Supplementary Table S3). </p>

<p>Quantifying population connectivity and migration 
Pairwise estimates of migration between the regions 
(Nm values) using classic methods derived from F ST 
values (Hartl and Clark, 1997) suggest that 
Hawke's Bay and Marlborough are the most 
connected, closely followed by Marlborough and 
Martinborough, and Hawke's Bay and Martinbor-
ough (Figure 1). Nelson and Central Otago share the 
lowest number of migrants with an estimate of just 
one per generation (Figure 1). <rs type="software">MIGRATE</rs> analyses 
showed an acceptance ratio for each parameter 
ranging from 0.38 to 0.65, and an effective sample 
size of approximately two million, suggesting that 
the chain length was sufficient. The autocorrelation 
between parameters and the prior was high and 
estimated to be around 0.96 overall, indicating a 
lack of information in data. This is reflected in the 
high confidence intervals surrounding the estimates 
(Supplementary Table S4). However, consistent 
patterns between multiple runs were evident, 
allowing meaningful estimates of gene flow between 
regions to be made. Inferred mean rates of move-
ment between regions span an order of magnitude 
ranging from 6 to 63 migrants per generation 
(Figure 1 and Supplementary Table S4), and show 
differential inward and outward movements for 
some regions. Correlating with the classic Nm 
estimates, and the analyses of population structure, 
Nelson and Central Otago show greatest isolation 
with twofold greater rates of outward than inward 
migration, and show an average of just 51 inward 
migrants per generation, 3.2-fold less than the 
overall average inward migration rate of 164 
migrants per generation for all other regions 
(Figure 1 and Supplementary Table S4). Conversely, 
Marlborough and the Hawke's Bay, which harbours 
some of the least distinctive and most diverse 
populations, experience some of the greatest inward 
migration rates at an average of 171 migrants per 
generation, 1.4-fold more than the average inward 
migration rate (Supplementary Table S4). In line 
with the low F ST estimates, a high degree of 
individuals with shared ancestry from <rs type="software">InStruct</rs>, 
and a large proportion of admixed individuals 
(Figure 1), Marlborough and the Hawke's Bay are 
the most connected regions, and experience an 
average of twofold more migration between these 
regions than the average overall migration rate. The 
extent of migration between regions does not 
correlate with geographic location (P40.21) show-
ing the difference in the extent of gene flow is not 
simply a function of distance. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We have very few models attempting to generally 
describe the population biology of microbes. 
Accurate quantification of short-term population 
level processes is necessary to understand the 
likely longer-term evolutionary trajectories of 
populations (Smadja and Butlin, 2011; Gray and 
Goddard, 2012), as well as how microbes may 
interact with other members of the community 
(Ruxton et al., 2014). We have attempted to make a 
significant step forward: rather than simply 
describing this S. cerevisiae population as either 
structured or not, here we paint a more biologically 
realistic picture by quantifying the role that 
geography has in defining structure, and go on to 
provide quantitative estimates of gene flow 
between populations residing in different regions. 
S. cerevisiae has clearly been isolated many times 
from managed vineyard ecosystems and ferments of 
fruit (Lopandic et al., 2008; Liti et al., 2009; 
Schacherer et al., 2009; Goddard et al., 2010; 
Gayevskiy and Goddard, 2012; Bokulich et al., 
2014). This species is also well reported from native 
niches in the northern hemisphere (Sniegowski 
et al., 2002; Wang et al., 2012; Hyma and Fay, 
2013), and in the Southern hemisphere has been 
isolated from exotic Quercus species in NZ, and 
from Nothofagus in Patagonia (Zhang et al., 2010; 
Libkind et al., 2011). Here we provide the first report 
of S. cerevisiae from multiple native tree species 
in the South Pacific region. Overall, this NZ 
S. cerevisiae metapopulation displays large genetic 
variance, compounding evidence that NZ harbours a 
large and diverse population of this species 
(Goddard et al., 2010; Gayevskiy and Goddard, 
2012; Cromie et al., 2013). Within regions, which 
typically encompass a radius of under 100 km, there 
is no compelling evidence for genetic differentiation 
between niches within managed ecosystems nor 
more strikingly between managed and native eco-
systems. The lack of genetic differentiation between 
managed and native ecosystems seen here does not 
permit us to determine whether vineyards or native 
forests are the sources or sinks of these populations, 
just that they are connected. Thus, there appears to 
be a free flow of individuals between these various 
niches at subregional scales, supporting previous 
reports from NZ and the United States of America 
(Goddard et al., 2010; Hyma and Fay, 2013). The 
inference of little differentiation between niches at 
regional scales is in contrast to previous reports 
showing differentiation between isolates from var-
ious ecological niches at global scales (Fay and 
Benavides, 2005; Legras et al., 2007). One explana-
tion for this is the extent of sample effort within any 
one population. The studies, including this one, 
reporting a minor effect of niche examined a large 
number of individuals from specific more localised 
populations, and in some sense evaluate 'ecological 
scale' processes: it may be that some strains are less </p>

<p>Structure and gene flow in a microbial eukaryote 
S Knight and MR Goddard </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>well adapted to various niches and that selection 
will eventually result in their removal. Studies 
evaluating strains from different geographic and 
ecological sources only include a handful of strains 
from any one specific population and unfortunately 
tend to confound geographic location with niche, 
but conclude that niche has a stronger role; in some 
sense these studies might examine populations 
where selection has possibly had more time to 
operate. Perhaps, the drivers of population struc-
ture differ at different scales? Lastly, it might be 
that NZ has relatively recently been colonised by 
only one of the inferred lineages of S. cerevisiae, 
and this has radiated to all niches. This would also 
provide a signal for the lack of differentiation 
between niches. Estimates of the rates of global 
flux for S. cerevisiae would help disentangle these 
possibilities. 
Whereas populations appear homogeneous within 
regions, analyses provide compelling evidence for 
various degrees of genetic differentiation between 
populations inhabiting major NZ regions. This 
differentiation is not absolute and there is also a 
degree of connectivity between regions. This is in 
line with a previous smaller-scale study with this 
species that reported both differentiation and con-
nection between regions in the North Island of NZ 
(Gayevskiy and Goddard, 2012), and this is also 
echoed at global scales (Liti et al., 2009; Wang et al., 
2012). Here all analyses, both classic and more 
sophisticated Bayesian approaches, converge on the 
same conclusion. F ST , Bayesian, ancestry profile and 
migration analyses show that the populations resid-
ing in Nelson and Central Otago are the most 
distinct and experience the least inward migration. 
Conversely, Marlborough and Hawke's Bay have 
smaller pairwise F ST values and Bayesian, ancestry 
profile and migration analyses show that these 
regions are the most mixed and connected. 
Marlborough and Hawke's Bay experience the most 
inward migration at approximately three times that 
into Nelson and Central Otago. This is consistent 
with the higher genetic diversity observed in these 
regions and implies that they accumulate genetic 
diversity from around the country. 
S. cerevisiae cells and spores are sessile; however, 
there are a variety of possible vectors that may move 
this unicellular eukaryote around. S. cerevisiae has 
been shown to be associated with both wasps and 
bees and has long been known to be associated with 
fruit flies (Reuter et al., 2007; Goddard et al., 2010; 
Stefanini et al., 2012). Recent work provides 
evidence that certain volatiles released by 
S. cerevisiae attract Drosophila, and this enhances 
the likelihood of movement, and potentially facil-
itates a mutualism between these species (Buser et al., 
2014). These insect species easily move over 
regional scales, and so presumably have some part 
in the homogenisation of S. cerevisiae within 
regions. Insects less likely move S. cerevisiae over 
hundreds of kilometres between regions, although </p>

<p>S. cerevisiae may also be associated with birds that 
can easily cover these distances (Francesca et al., 
2012). Humans are also obvious vectors. Indeed, 
the patterns of separation, and rates of migration in 
and out the various regions shown here are nicely in 
line with the flow of fruit and equipment because of 
the actions of the NZ wine industry. Marlborough 
and the Hawke's Bay are the two largest viticultural 
and winemaking regions in the country, and fruit 
from other regions is often transferred to them, 
mirroring the inferred migration of S. cerevisiae into 
these regions. This national 'ecological' scale picture 
complements and mirrors the global 'evolutionary' 
scale picture revealed for this species: that this is a 
genetically diverse species that shows some degree 
of structure and connectivity, and these patterns 
are consistent with human-influenced dispersal 
(Fay and Benavides, 2005; Legras et al., 2007). 
Although the above interpretation fits nicely 
with the population patterns observed here, it is 
important to consider alternate explanations. The 
connections between populations could instead be 
indicative of recent divergence events. The NZ wine 
industry is very young in evolutionary terms and it 
is possible that S. cerevisiae was introduced to these 
regions via the introduction of vines and winery 
equipment such as barrels (Goddard et al., 2010). 
The patterns observed in this analysis could be 
explained by the large wine-producing regions of 
Hawke's Bay and Marlborough being the source of 
variation and the outlying regions resulting from 
founder events with subsequent population expan-
sion and divergence (Hartl and Clark, 1997). The 
method of migration analysis employed here 
assumes that population divergence has not 
occurred, and only invokes migration to explain 
any similarity in genetic diversity between popula-
tions (Beerli, 2009). One issue with a divergence (as 
opposed to migration) explanation is that source 
populations must exist before the populations they 
are proposed to have founded. Whereas Hawke's 
Bay is one of the oldest wine-producing regions in 
NZ, Marlborough is one of the youngest having only 
been established around 1970. Thus, the divergence 
hypothesis fits less well, given the vast diversity and 
admixture observed in the recently established 
Marlborough region. In addition, whilst it appears 
that the NZ S. cerevisiae population is reasonably 
internationally distinct, these patterns of differen-
tiation may also be explained by the inward 
migration of genotypes from offshore. These expla-
nations are not mutually exclusive and it is likely 
that population divergence from founding popula-
tions is occurring alongside inevitable national and 
international migration of strains because of the vast 
movement of fruit, equipment and people by the 
wine industry. 
The demonstration that certain regions have 
'signature' microbial populations is of relevance to 
the wine industry. It is often suggested that certain 
wines reflect their geographic origin, and this is </p>

<p>Structure and gene flow in a microbial eukaryote 
S Knight and MR Goddard </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>encapsulated in the concept of terroir (Bokulich 
et al., 2014). Classically, this was thought to largely 
result from the interaction between specific Vitis 
vinifera varieties and the local soils, geography and 
climate; however, there is limited but increasing 
evidence showing that the microbes that influence 
vine growth, fermentation and wine style (as 
S. cerevisiae does) also exhibit regional differentia-
tion (Gayevskiy and Goddard, 2012; Bokulich et al., 
2014; Taylor et al., 2014), as we again demonstrate 
here. Thus, these data further support the concept 
that there could be a microbial aspect to terroir. 
Metabolic profiling of regionally defined genotypes 
is necessary to determine whether the genetic 
differentiation demonstrated here translates to pheno-
types that are relevant to wine, and thus whether 
microbes contribute to terroir in a predictable and 
consistent way. 
Here we provide a more advanced insight into 
the population biology of a well-established model 
microbial eukaryote that has also been biotechno-
logically harnessed by humans since the dawn of 
civilisation. We take a significant step towards 
quantifying these processes by providing the first 
estimates for metapopulation separation and 
similarity. We reveal S. cerevisiae population 
differentiation in NZ at scales over 100 km, with 
the most signal provided by the more remote 
regions, but no differentiation within regions, 
even between populations inhabiting native 
forests and vineyards. We also show differential 
migration of this species between regions, and 
postulate that this may be due, at least in part, to 
human influence. By quantifying the magnitude of 
these forces in microbes we begin to provide 
one crucial aspect of an inclusive framework 
attempting to more fully integrate ecological and 
evolutionary processes. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Amisfeild, Ata Rangi, Churton, Coal Pit, 
Constellation, Delegats, Domain Road, Frey Vineyard, 
Huia, Misha's Vineyard, Mt Difficulty, Mt Riley, Neudorf, 
Palliser, Pernod Ricard, Rippon, Seifried, Seresin, Te 
Kairanga, Te Whare Ra, Tohu, Trinity Hill, Villa Maria 
and Vita Brevis for access to their land and providing 
samples. Soon Lee, Peter Morrison-Whittle and Velimir 
Gayevskiy assisted with sample collection and processing. 
We also acknowledge the contribution of the NeSI high-
performance computing facilities at the University of 
Auckland and the staff, particularly Jordi Blasco, at NeSI 
and Centre for eResearch. New Zealand's national facilities 
are provided by the New Zealand eScience Infrastructure 
(NeSI) and funded jointly by NeSI's collaborator institutions 
and through the Ministry of Business, Innovation and 
Employment's Infrastructure programme. This work was 
funded by a University of Auckland doctoral scholarship </p>

<p>to SK and grants to MG from the New Zealand Ministry of 
Business, Innovation and Employment, New Zealand 
Winegrowers and Plant and Food Research. </p>



<p>Structure and gene flow in a microbial eukaryote 
S Knight and MR Goddard </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>





<p>The ISME Journal </p>



<p>This work is licensed under a Creative 
Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. The images or 
other third party material in this article are included 
in the article's Creative Commons license, unless 
indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is 
not included under the Creative Commons license, 
users will need to obtain permission from the license 
holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy 
of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on The ISME Journal website (http://www.nature.com/ismej) </p>

<p>Structure and gene flow in a microbial eukaryote 
S Knight and MR Goddard </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

</text></tei>