<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4951770" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Upper extremity lymph edema is the most common side effect of breast cancer treatment that may produce signif-
icant physical and psychological morbidity. Pain is the frequent symptom of lymph edema that causes impairment of activities in 
daily life. 
Objectives: The aim of this study was assessment of the effect of complex decongestive therapy (CDT) on upper extremity lymph 
edema and pain in women with post breast surgery lymph edema. 
Patients and Methods: In this quasi-experimental research with before-after design, 36 women with moderate lymph edema 
after breast surgery participated in the program. Edema volume was measured by water displacement method; pain values were 
evaluated by visual analog scale (VAS). Data were recorded before intervention and 2 and 4 weeks after it. CDT included the first 
phase (intensive phase) and the second phase (maintenance phase). Each phase lasted 2 weeks. After use of Shapiro Wilk test for 
normality, analysis of variances with GEE and repeated measurements were used to analyze the data. 
Results: After one month doing CDT program, significant decrease of edema was noticed (P &lt; 0.0001), also pain decreased during 
2 and 4 weeks after intervention (P &lt; 0.0001). 
Conclusions: This study indicated that CDT program is effective in reducing lymph edema volume and pain in women with mod-
erate post breast surgery lymph edema. It seems that raising patients' awareness and training healthcare professionals regarding 
lymph edema preventive strategies have an important role in earlier and better combating this complication. </p>

<p>Keywords: Breast Cancer, Lymph Edema, Complex Decongestive Therapy, Pain </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>Breast cancer, with the incidence of 2% annually (1), 
is one of the most common malignancies among Iranian 
women (2) and the lowest mean age in the middle east 
(3). Although its treatments such as surgery, radiother-
apy, chemotherapy and hormonal therapy reduce mortal-
ity rates of breast cancer, each may lead to different side 
effects (4). 
The secondary upper limb lymph edema related to 
breast cancer (5) is one of the most common morbidities 
and important consequences of treatment (6) that is usu-
ally unilateral (5), with mild to severe intensity at any time 
during the life (7). It is known as a chronic, incurable (6)  visible and progressive disease (8). So it is causing physi-
cal and psychological disorders (9). Without intervention, 
lymph edema can lead to progressive swollen and larger in 
size of limb or localized fluid accumulation in other body 
areas, tightness, heaviness, limitation of mobility in up-</p>

<p>per limb and hand, numbness and tingling, pain, fatigue 
(5), skin changes (10), deformities (11), body image impair-
ment, stress, depression, loss of confidence, lack of partic-
ipation in social activities (9), and even death in advanced 
stages of lymph edema in these patients (12). </p>

<p>Despite the large studies for the treatment of lym-
phedema, there is not any certain cure (8). The gold stan-
dard treatment so far has been complex decongestive ther-
apy (CDT). The international association of north Amer-
ica (LANA) has known CDT as common, standard, and an 
effective treatment. It is a two-phase program. The first 
phase (intensive phase) usually, depending on the degree 
of edema, lasts 2 to 4 weeks. The patient receives treatment 
5 days per week and the second phase (maintenance phase) 
immediately begins after the first phase that is life-long 
self-care to maintain the size of the limb (5-8). </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016, Iranian Journal of Cancer Prevention. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 
International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial usages, provided the 
original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Angooti Oshnari L et al. </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>Due to the increase of life expectancy in patients with 
breast cancer and lymph edema related to it as a chronic 
disease and also the lack of lymph therapist in our society, 
so in this research, CDT program with emphasis on rais-
ing awareness and education of the patients on early diag-
nosis, prevention, encouragement to continue long-time 
treatment by themselves and compatibility with the pres-
ence of lymph edema is used, in order to the patient is 
helped to reduce complications of this condition such as 
pain. </p>

<p>3. Patients and Methods </p>

<p>This quasi-experimental clinical trial with before-af-
ter design, after being confirmed by ethical committee of 
lymph edema clinic of Shohadaye Tajrish hospital, Tehran 
was performed in 2011. 36 women with breast carcinoma 
treatment and moderate lymph edema (&gt; 200 -&lt; 400 cc), 
were considered eligible to participate in this study. The 
criteria for excluding the patients from study were: breast 
cancer recurrence, malignancy, infection, bilateral lymph 
edema, history of trauma, previous treatment for lymph 
edema, heart and kidney insufficiency, hypertension, dia-
betic, thrombosis, unheard wound and skin diseases, frac-
ture, neuromuscular diseases and any absolute contraindi-
cations for CDT (5,9,13). 
Non-invasive CDT treatment was implemented in two 
phases for 4 weeks (6 days a week except for Fridays). 
The first phase (intensive phase) for 2 weeks consisted 
of 45 minutes Manual Lymph Drainage (MLD) massage 
slightly by therapist, the multi-layered low stretch ban-
dages (Lohmann Rauscher bandage set) up to start the next 
session, five lymph exercises with the bandages and skin-
nail care. The second phase (maintenance phase) with 2-
week follow-up, included daily Self-Lymph Drainage (SLD) 
massage by the patient, the use of A-H sleeve (Sigvaris 
brand) with support straps in category 500 and class 2 
pressure (23-32 mm hg in German standard pressure), the 
multi-layered low stretch bandages in nights, going on to 
do exercise and skin-nail care. 
In addition to demographic questionnaire, the volume 
of edema was measured with water displacement volumet-
ric by a blinded investigator not engaged in the treatment. 
This method is the gold standard, as mentioned earlier, 2 
and 4 weeks after the intervention. The edema volume in 
texts explained as the volume difference between affected 
and unaffected arms. Then to calculate the percent of vol-
ume reduction (PVR) at the end of phase 1, the volume dif-
ference between before and 2 weeks after intervention is di-
vided by before volume then multiplied by 100. Also, PVR at </p>

<p>the end of phase 2 was calculated by the volume difference 
between 2 weeks after intervention and 2 weeks follow up 
divided by 2 weeks intervention volume multiplied by 100 
(5, 9, 13, 14). 
Also, pain value was evaluated by visual analog scale 
(VAS) that is standard, valid, reliable and simple in use (15), 
in this study in order to express the amount of pain, pa-
tients were marked with a pencil on the line by themselves 
before, 2 and 4 weeks after the intervention. 
After data gathering and coding, due to the fact that 
the pain variable did not follow the normal distribution in 
Shapiro Wilk test, generalized estimating equation (GEE) 
to determine the existence of differences and repeated 
measurement to identify disagreements in measurement 
modes were used by using statistical package <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18</rs>. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>Tables 1 and 2 demonstrate some demographic data 
of participants. The average of age in participants was 
53 years (± 10.28), the average of body mass index (BMI) 
was 28.84 kg/m 
2 (± 4.55), the average of distance between </p>

<p>surgery until the initial assessment was 35 months (± 
45.65), the average of number of lymph nodes removed 
was 14 (± 9.51), and the average of number of lymph nodes 
involved was 3 (± 3.29). 
As shown in Table 3, the mean of percent of volume re-
duction increased during both phases. Also, according to 
a paired t-test, the mean percent of volume reduction, dur-
ing first two weeks 46.45 (± 18.67) and second two weeks 
17.12 (± 22.35) were significant P &lt; 0.0001) and it was ob-
served that PVR in first two weeks was less than second two 
weeks. In addition, the average of pain score before treat-
ment was 4.86 (± 2.82) and 2 and 4 weeks after treatment 
reduced to 1.97 (± 1.81) and 1.63 (± 1.95) respectively. Ac-
cording to GEE method, the average of pain in repeated 
measurements were significantly different (P &lt; 0.0001). 
In Table 4, results of paired comparison test to de-
termine the differences in measurements, the average of 
pain showed a significant difference between before and 
2 weeks after the intervention (P &lt; 0.0001), between be-
fore and 4 weeks after the intervention (P &lt; 0.0001), and 
between 2 and 4 weeks after the intervention (P = 0.023). </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>This study, to evaluate effect of CDT on upper extrem-
ity lymph edema and pain in women after breast cancer 
surgery, showed that CDT led to a significant increase in 
mean percentage of volume reduction in both phases, but 
in the first phase provided better results. Hamner et al. </p>

<p> 
Iran J Cancer Prev. 2016; 9(2):e4209. </p>

<p>Angooti Oshnari L et al. </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic Characteristics of Patients (N = 36) </p>

<p>Variable 
No. (%) </p>

<p>Marital status </p>

<p>Single 
2 (5.6) </p>

<p>Married 
31 (86.1) </p>

<p>Widowed/Divorced 
3 (8.3) </p>

<p>Education </p>

<p>Illiterate 
5 (13.9) </p>

<p>Less than high school 
16 (44.4) </p>

<p>High school 
10 (27.8) </p>

<p>Higher education 
5 (13.9) </p>

<p>Job </p>

<p>Housewife 
33 (91.7) </p>

<p>Employed 
3 (8.3) </p>

<p>Dominant limb </p>

<p>Right 
34 (94.4) </p>

<p>Left 
2 (5.6) </p>

<p>Table 2. Clinical Characteristics of Patients (N = 36) </p>

<p>Variable 
No. (%) </p>

<p>Involved limb </p>

<p>Right 
14 (38.9) </p>

<p>Left 
22 (61.1) </p>

<p>Breast surgery </p>

<p>MRM 
32 (88.9) </p>

<p>BP 
4 (11.1) </p>

<p>Axillaries surgery </p>

<p>Lymph nodes removal 
35 (97.2) </p>

<p>Sentinel node removal 
1 (2.8) </p>

<p>Radiation therapy </p>

<p>Yes 
28 (77.8) </p>

<p>No 
8 (22.2) </p>

<p>Chemotherapy </p>

<p>Yes 
36 (100) </p>

<p>No 
0 (0) </p>

<p>(2006) (16) and Haghighat et al. (2008) found that CDT had 
impressive results in lower volume too (17). Also, Morgan et 
al. found out Patients in the first phase more than 50% and 
in the second phase about 50% of lymph edema decreased 
(18). It seems that the multi-layered low stretch bandages 
to reduce lymph edema and sleeves to avoid presence of </p>

<p>lymph edema are used (9). And the second phase imme-
diately after the first phase is done to maintain the maxi-
mum results of the first phase (13). No studies were found 
to increase the volume of lymph edema due to breast can-
cer with CDT, but a study by Szuba et al. showed that CDT 
and pneumatic compression pump reduced the volume of </p>

<p>Iran J Cancer Prev. 2016; 9(2):e4209. </p>

<p>
Angooti Oshnari L et al. </p>

<p>Table 3. Average and Significant Variables in the Analysis of Repeated Measures (N = 36) </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Mean ± SD </p>

<p>P Value </p>

<p>Percent of volume reduction 
0.0001 </p>

<p>First two weeks </p>

<p>46.45 ± 18.67 </p>

<p>Second two weeks </p>

<p>17.12 ± 22.35 </p>

<p>Pain 
0.0001 </p>

<p>Before </p>

<p>4.86 ± 2.82 </p>

<p>Two weeks </p>

<p>1.97 ± 1.81 </p>

<p>Four weeks </p>

<p>1.63 ± 1.95 </p>

<p>Table 4. Paired Comparison of the Average Pain in Patients (N = 36) </p>

<p>Pain 
Difference of Mean (SE) 
P Value 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Upper Limit 
Lower Limit </p>

<p>Before and 2 weeks 
2.89 (0.37) 
&lt; 0.0001 
2.17 
3.61 </p>

<p>2 weeks and 4 weeks 
0.33 (0.15) 
0.023 
0.05 
0.62 </p>

<p>Before and 4 weeks 
3.22 (0.41) 
&lt; 0.0001 
2.18 
4.02 </p>

<p>edema more than CDT alone in patients (19). </p>

<p>Also in this study the average of pain scale in both 
phases reduced, but in the first phase was more than the 
second one. As mentioned in the sources, causes of pain in 
limb lymph edema can be due to muscles strain (9), elonga-
tion of nerve fibers in the skin, and pressure on the nerve 
trunk by excessive accumulation of fluid (20). Therefore, 
more evacuation of lymph edema causes less strain on ves-
sels and peripheral nerves of the skin and muscles of the 
upper extremity and trunk. However, lymph edema causes 
pain (9), but massage can reduce pain (21), so there was re-
duction of pain in both phases. </p>

<p>Hammner et al. found CDT has effects on pain reduc-
tion (16). Mandery received pain reduction in VAS Score 
from 7 to 1 with CDT too (22). Khoshnazar also showed that 
the rehabilitation program led to a significant reduction 
in pain (15). As well, Cassileth found that manual lymph 
drainage massage reduced pain and discomfort in upper 
limb lymph edema caused by the removal of lymph nodes 
(23). It should be noted that no study was found to in-
crease the pain of breast cancer treatment with CDT, but 
Haghighat et al. reported that the use of CDT alone and 
CDT with pneumatic compression pump pressure had the 
same significant reduction of pain (24). </p>

<p>Overall, this study showed that complex decongestive 
therapy rehabilitation program services is effective on re-
duction of lymph edema and pain in women with lymph 
edema after breast surgery. </p>

<p>Since breast cancer is an important problem in public </p>

<p>health, is considered one of the most common malignan-
cies in women (25), and unfortunately with regard to the 
lack of awareness of women in society not only on the role 
of the prophylactic factors of breast cancer and the exam-
ination (26), but also in treatment-related complications, 
including lymph edema, cause to the treatment centers 
will be late (15). As well , due to the fact that most of the ex-
perts thought that lymph edema is an inevitable and incur-
able complication, late referral of patients, lack of lymph 
edema treatment clinics and providing services in the field 
of educational planning cause treatment as CDT should be 
provided limited or very time-consuming and costly. 
Due to the need to enhance or restore the ability and 
minimize disability to improve independence without 
pain in activities of daily living in these patients, this study 
can serve as an introduction to broader and more complete 
prevention of lymph edema research by researchers and 
therapists. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>None declared. </p>

<p>Footnotes </p>

<p>Authors' Contributions: None declared. </p>

<p>Financial Disclosure: We have no financial interests re-
lated to the material in the manuscript. </p>

<p> 
Iran J Cancer Prev. 2016; 9(2):e4209. </p>

<p>Angooti Oshnari L et al. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interests: None declared. </p>

<p>Funding/Support: This study was not supported. </p>



<p>Iran J Cancer Prev. 2016; 9(2):e4209. </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>