<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4797302" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T14:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The spatial organization of the genome influences 
cellular function, notably gene regulation. Recent 
studies have assessed the three-dimensional (3D) 
co-localization of functional annotations (e.g. cen-
tromeres, long terminal repeats) using 3D genome 
reconstructions from Hi-C (genome-wide chromo-
some conformation capture) data; however, corre-
sponding assessments for continuous functional 
genomic data (e.g. chromatin immunoprecipitation-
sequencing (ChIP-seq) peak height) are lacking. 
Here, we demonstrate that applying bump hunting 
via the patient rule induction method (PRIM) to ChIP-
seq data superposed on a Saccharomyces cerevisiae 
3D genome reconstruction can discover 'functional 
3D hotspots', regions in 3-space for which the mean 
ChIP-seq peak height is significantly elevated. For 
the transcription factor Swi6, the top hotspot by P-
value contains MSB2 and ERG11 -known Swi6 target 
genes on different chromosomes. We verify this find-
ing in a number of ways. First, this top hotspot is rel-
atively stable under PRIM across parameter settings. 
Second, this hotspot is among the top hotspots by 
mean outcome identified by an alternative algorithm, 
k-Nearest Neighbor (k-NN) regression. Third, the dis-
tance between MSB2 and ERG11 is smaller than ex-
pected (by resampling) in two other 3D reconstruc-
tions generated via different normalization and re-
construction algorithms. This analytic approach can 
discover functional 3D hotspots and potentially re-
veal novel regulatory interactions. </p>

<p>The three-dimensional (3D) configuration of chromosomes 
within the eukaryotic nucleus is important for several cellu-
lar functions including gene regulation and epigenetic pat-</p>

<p>terning (1) and is also strongly associated with transloca-
tion events and cancer-driving gene fusions (2,3). While 
visualization of such architecture remains limited to low-
resolution, low-throughput, targeted techniques such as flu-
orescent in situ hybridization (FISH) (4), the ability to infer 
genome architecture at high resolution has been enabled by 
recently-devised assays derived from chromosome confor-
mation capture (3C) techniques (5). In particular, when cou-
pled with next generation sequencing, such methods (here-
after termed Hi-C (6,7)) yield an inventory of genome-wide 
chromatin interactions which, in turn, provide a basis for re-
constructing 3D chromatin configuration, as described be-
low. Here, we use such 3D reconstructions to discover 'func-
tional 3D hotspots' in the nucleus (e.g. transcription facto-
ries) (8-10). 
The contact data from Hi-C analysis lists two genomic 
positions--each corresponding to a restriction enzyme site 
(or bin if the data are binned)--and an 'interaction fre-
quency': the number of times the two positions were lig-
ated and paired-end sequenced together. This interaction 
frequency is inversely related to the physical 3D distance be-
tween the two genomic positions in the nucleus (7,11). 
By quantifying the relationship between interaction fre-
quency and physical distance, Duan et al. (7) proceeded to 
generate a 3D reconstruction of the Saccharomyces cere-
visiae genome (16 chromosomes, 12.2 Megabases (Mb) and 
∼6275 genes) by solving a multi-dimensional scaling cri-
terion (7,11-14) via constrained optimization -with con-
straints based on prior biophysical and biological knowl-
edge (e.g. imposition of within-chromosome contiguity, and 
avoidance of steric clash). A 3D genome reconstruction 
has also been generated (11) for Plasmodium falciparum 
3D7 (14 chromosomes, 23.3 Mb and ∼5300 genes), the 
causative agent of malaria, using a similar approach. Addi-
tional methods for generating 3D genome reconstructions 
using alternate approaches to inferring distances from inter-
action frequencies and differing optimization methods or 
reconstruction algorithms have been advanced (12-14), as 
have methods for gauging the concordance of 3D genome 
reconstructions (15). </p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 415 514 8034; Fax: +1 415 514 8150; Email: Mark.Segal@ucsf.edu </p>

<p>C The Author(s) 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which 
permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 5 2029 </p>

<p>Several recent studies have used the contact data (16), 
the 3D genome reconstructions (11) or both (17) to test 
the hypothesis that functionally related genomic annota-
tions (hereafter 'marks') co-localize in 3-space in the nu-
cleus. Centromeres, telomeres and long terminal repeats 
were detected as significantly co-localized in S. cerevisiae 
(17). Interestingly, in P. falciparum, sets of genes with de-
velopmentally regulated expression were detected as signifi-
cantly co-localized in 3D-reconstruction-based assessments 
but not in contact-based assessments (17). This finding il-
lustrates a potential advantage of 3D reconstructions: they 
enable the detection of multi-level co-localizations (i.e. of 
multiple (inter)chromosomal regions), whereas the contact 
data are inherently limited to detecting strictly pairwise co-
localization. In other words, 3D reconstruction-based anal-
yses may detect if a set of marks occupies a smaller subset 
of the nucleus than expected by chance even if the set is not 
enriched for individual pairs of marks that are exceptionally 
close together. Another advantage of the 3D reconstruc-
tion is that for genomic regions that have missing contact 
data their position in the 3D reconstruction can be inferred 
from neighboring genomic regions via chromatin contigu-
ity. Furthermore, superposition of genomic locus-indexed 
attributes onto 3D reconstructions can be readily and nat-
urally performed, as we subsequently illustrate. For contact 
level data, such overlay is less immediate again due to the 
contact data's pairwise structure. 
Here, we extend such downstream analyses of 3D genome 
reconstructions to continuous functional genomic data. 
We illustrate our methodology corresponding to overlay-
ing an S. cerevisiae 3D genome reconstruction with the 
peak height of chromatin immunoprecipitation-sequencing 
(ChIP-seq) data for the transcription factor Swi6 (18). 
A previous study superposed continuous functional ge-
nomic data (microarray gene expression data) on a model-
based 3D structure (19); however, this was solely for visual-
ization purposes. Another study assessed the global coher-
ence of gene expression profiles with a 3D reconstruction 
(11). Our study makes the novel contribution of analyzing 
3D genome reconstructions overlaid with continuous func-
tional genomic data (ChIP-seq peak height) with the ob-
jective of discovering focal regions in 3-space for which the 
overlaid outcome is extreme; we refer to these foci as func-
tional 3D hotspots. The algorithm that we employ for dis-
covering such functional 3D hotspots is the patient rule in-
duction method (PRIM) (20,21) (detailed in the 'Results' 
section). 
An important motivation for focal assessments is that 
downstream analysis of, for example, the gene membership 
of functional 3D hotspots can reveal biological insights, 
concordant with the scale of activity, in contrast to global 
assessments. Further, focal assessments of continuous out-
come provide a potential advantage over focal assessments 
of marks. For the previous analyses of marks (e.g. target 
genes), the target genes to be tested for co-localization had 
to be specified from the outset. In contrast, the analytic ap-
proaches that we advance for continuous outcomes can dis-
cover functional co-localizations without target genes be-
ing pre-specified. Rather, these techniques analyze genome-
indexed signals superposed on 3D reconstructions and dis-
cover putative hotspots, which are then subjected to down-</p>

<p>stream biological analyses (e.g. gene membership). As such, 
the approaches detailed here may detect novel interactions 
for which the interacting target genes are not known a pri-
ori. The functional outcomes that we analyze here derive 
from ChIP-seq as mentioned; however, the methods can be 
applied irrespective of outcome type. 
Examples of functional 3D hotspots are transcription 
factories: transcription does not occur uniformly through-
out the nucleus, but rather at discrete foci where the poly-
merase machinery has been assembled -and where active 
genes then become localized (8,22,23). Another example of 
a functional 3D hotspot is that some inducible genes be-
come localized near the nuclear pore complex during acti-
vation (9,24). In addition, some repressed heterochromatic 
regions cluster near the nuclear periphery based on interac-
tions with nuclear envelope proteins (10). </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Hi-C contact data normalization and 3D reconstruction gen-
eration </p>

<p>The S. cerevisiae Hi-C contact data (HindIII, pre-FDR, 
no masking) from (7) (Supplementary Data) were down-
loaded from https://noble.gs.washington.edu/proj/yeast-
architecture/sup.html. We performed explicit-factor 
normalization of this contact data to control for GC 
content, mappability and fragment length using <rs type="software">HiC- Norm</rs> (25) genome-wide (chromosome by chromosome) 
as per (17) and then generated a new 3D reconstruc-
tion using the constrained optimization approach (7). 
The HiCNorm source code was downloaded from 
http://www.people.fas.harvard.edu/∼junliu/HiCNorm/. </p>

<p>ChIP-seq data normalization </p>

<p>The raw ChIP-seq data set (18), which contains three in-
put samples (Swi6, Tup1 and RNA polymerase II phos-
phorylated at serine 5 (Pol2ser5p)) and a mock immuno-
precipitation (IP) control sample (DMSO, Illumina), was 
obtained from GEO (data set GSE51251; http://www.ncbi. 
nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc = GSE51251). We con-
verted the raw sequencing SRA data to FASTQ format us-
ing '<rs id="software-12" type="software">fastq-dump</rs>' version <rs corresp="#software-12" type="version">2.3.4</rs> in the sequence read archive 
(<rs type="software">SRA) Toolkit</rs> (26). We aligned the reads to the S. cere-
visiae reference genome (sacCer2) using <rs id="software-14" type="software">Bowtie 2</rs> (27) ver-
sion <rs corresp="#software-14" type="version">2.2.1</rs> with default parameters and then converted the 
sequence alignment / map (SAM) output to binary align-
ment / map (BAM) format using <rs id="software-15" type="software">SAMtools</rs> (28) version 
<rs corresp="#software-15" type="version">0.1.19-44428cd</rs>. We filtered the sequencing reads (using the 
R package '<rs id="software-16" type="software">ShortRead</rs>' (29) version <rs corresp="#software-16" type="version">1.20.0</rs> with a custom fil-
ter) to retain only those with two or less expected errors per 
read: given a Phred quality score q for each base call, the 
probability that a base call is erroneous is P = 10 
(− q / 10) , 
which is then summed over the bases in the read to give 
the expected errors per read. Using '<rs type="software">ShortRead</rs>' (29), we 
deduplicated the reads to control for PCR amplification 
bias (30,31) and masked the highly repetitive chromosome 
XII rDNA region (via a custom filter) because of the diffi-
culty of aligning short reads there. We log 2 -normalized each 
ChIP-seq sample to the mock IP control using the function 
get.smoothed.enrichment.mle() in the R package 'spp' (32) </p>



<p>version 1.11 with a 200 basepair (bp) bandwidth and 100 bp 
stepsize. 'spp' was downloaded from http://compbio.med. 
harvard.edu/Supplements/ChIP-seq/. 
We performed a smoothing step to control for the lo-
cal dependency of the signal in linear genomic space, since 
we are interested in identifying 3D hotspots of physically 
proximal yet genomically distal ChIP-seq peaks in sub-
sequent analyses. Specifically, we smoothed each normal-
ized ChIP-seq signal along each chromosome arm using 
<rs type="software">SuperSmoother</rs> (33), which is implemented as supsmu() 
in R (version 3.0.2) package '<rs type="software">stats</rs>', with the span deter-
mined by cross-validation. We then took the residuals of 
each smoothed normalized signal -this constitutes the fi-
nal 'ChIP-seq peak height' that we proceeded to superpose 
onto the 3D genome reconstruction. </p>

<p>Data superposition </p>

<p>The 3D genome reconstruction consists of a series of beads 
spaced along each chromosome; each bead has a genomic 
position and (X,Y,Z) coordinates. For each ChIP-seq in-
put, we binned its peak height data (i.e. the residuals of 
the smoothed log 2 -normalized signal) such that each bin 
was centered on a bead. We then assigned to each bead the 
most extreme ChIP-seq peak height (positive or negative) 
from the bin centered on that bead. The result is a 3D chro-
matin configuration reconstruction overlaid with functional 
genomic data: each bead now has a genomic position, phys-
ical coordinates (X,Y,Z) and a ChIP-seq peak height value. 
We visualized this superposed 3D reconstruction in <rs id="software-23" type="software">MacPy- MOL</rs> <rs corresp="#software-23" type="version">1.3</rs> (34) by first converting the data to the Protein 
Data Bank (PDB) file format (35) with the ChIP-seq peak 
height value rescaled as the temperature factor (B-factor) in 
the PDB file. </p>

<p>PRIM </p>

<p>We applied <rs type="software">PRIM</rs> using the R package 'prim' (36) to dis-
cover 3D hotspots in ChIP-seq peak height superposed on 
the 3D reconstruction. We used the default parameter set-
tings peel alpha = 0.5 and paste alpha = 0.01 (we explored 
alternative settings subsequently) and used min beads = 25, 
the smallest parameter setting out of those tested (10, 25, 
50 and 100) for which inter-chromosomal hotspots could 
be detected. After applying PRIM, each bead in the super-
posed 3D reconstruction now has a genomic position, phys-
ical (X,Y,Z) coordinates, a ChIP-seq peak height value and 
a numerical PRIM box label (the largest numerical label is 
a placeholder for the beads that were not boxed). We es-
timated the significance of all of the PRIM boxes (except 
for the placeholder) by permutations as follows. We pre-
served the mapping of beads to PRIM boxes, and then per-
muted the ChIP-seq peak height along each chromosome. 
Then, we computed the mean ChIP-seq peak height for 
each PRIM box from the permuted data. We repeated this 
for a total of 10 
5 permutations. The P-value of each box 
was estimated by comparing its mean ChIP-seq peak height 
from the observed data to its mean ChIP-seq peak height 
values from the permuted data. We ranked these potential 
3D hotspots by P-value and Holm-adjusted the P-values to 
account for multiple testing. To gauge the effect size of the </p>

<p>mean ChIP-seq peak height of each hotspot, we also com-
puted Z-scores: the difference between the observed mean 
outcome and the mean of the mean outcomes across all per-
mutations, divided by the standard deviation of the mean 
outcomes across all permutations. </p>

<p>k-Nearest Neighbor (k-NN) regression </p>

<p>We applied k-NN regression to the ChIP-seq peak height 
superposed on the 3D reconstruction using the R package 
'<rs type="software">FNN</rs>' (37), where k is the specified number of physically 
proximal beads to be analyzed together as a grouping. First, 
we selected 'seed' beads evenly spaced along each chromo-
some by a bead interval of 0.5*k. Next, for each seed bead, 
we found its k nearest beads in Euclidean distance via the 
function knn.index() to create a bead grouping. Finally, we 
found the mean ChIP-seq peak height of each bead group-
ing via the function knn.reg() and ranked the list of bead 
groupings by mean ChIP-seq peak height. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Superposing ChIP-seq data on the 3D reconstruction </p>

<p>We normalized the S. cerevisiae contact data from (7) us-
ing <rs type="software">HiCNorm</rs> (25) (see 'Methods') and then generated a 
new 3D genome reconstruction from the normalized con-
tact data via the constrained optimization approach from 
(7) as per (17) (the original study (7) preceded the formaliza-
tion of pipelines for normalizing Hi-C contact data (25,38- 40)). 
We focus on ChIP-seq data for the transcription fac-
tor Swi6 as the continuous functional genomic outcome. 
Swi6 is a component of two transcriptional regulatory 
complexes: SBF (composed of Swi6 and the sequence-
specific transcription factor Swi4) and MBF (composed of 
Swi6 and the sequence-specific transcription factor Mbp1) 
(41,42). SBF and MBF regulate genes that function in G1/S 
(e.g. cell growth genes, DNA synthesis genes) (41,42). 
We aligned the sequencing reads for Swi6 ChIP-seq and 
the sequencing reads for a mock IP control (18) to the 
reference genome and then log 2 -normalized the signal to 
the control (see 'Methods'). We applied quality control fil-
ters, performed read deduplication and obtained residuals 
from smoothing the signal along each chromosome arm 
(see 'Methods') -this constitutes the final 'ChIP-seq peak 
height' that we proceeded to analyze. 
We superposed the ChIP-seq peak height on the 3D 
genome reconstruction (Figure 1). The 3D reconstruction 
consists of a series of 'beads' spaced along each chromo-
some, with each bead having a genomic position and an 
(X,Y,Z) coordinate. We binned the Swi6 ChIP-seq peak 
height data at the same genomic spacing as the beads (see 
'Methods'). The result is that each bead now has a ge-
nomic position, an (X,Y,Z) coordinate, and a ChIP-seq 
peak height value. We applied PRIM to this data, with 
ChIP-seq peak height as outcome and (X,Y,Z) coordinates 
as covariates, to identify functional 3D hotspots. </p>

<p>PRIM </p>

<p>PRIM seeks to identify hotspots by sequentially and strate-
gically paring away data regions so that the average out-</p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 5 2031 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Swi6 ChIP-seq peak height superposed on the 3D chromatin 
configuration reconstruction. The 3D reconstruction is colored by (A) 
chromosome or (B) Swi6 ChIP-seq peak height. For (B), regions are col-
ored red if their log 2 -normalized ChIP-seq peak height is greater than 1; 
otherwise, they are colored yellow (except for the masked chrXII rDNA 
repeat region, which is colored blue). </p>

<p>come over the remaining data are elevated. At each itera-
tion, a fraction of the beads (peel alpha) are peeled off the 
3D reconstruction by evaluating the extremal slices orthog-
onal to each of the coordinate axes and removing data from 
whichever slice results in the highest mean ChIP-seq peak 
height for the remaining beads. This process is continued 
until a prescribed minimum number of beads (min beads) 
remains (we used the smallest setting out of those tested for 
which inter-chromosomal hotspots could be detected, de-
tailed in 'Methods'). The resultant region can be enlarged 
to correct potential overshoot by pasting additional beads 
on to the region (via paste alpha, which is smaller than 
peel alpha) if that increases the mean ChIP-seq peak height 
(see 'Methods'). At this point, a PRIM region or 'box' has 
been identified, which represents a potential 3D hotspot. 
The beads comprising this box are then excluded and the 
entire procedure is repeated to identify additional boxes. We 
performed inference as follows: for each PRIM box, we pre-
served the beads comprising that box, then permuted ChIP-
seq peak height values along each chromosome, and com-
puted the mean ChIP-seq peak height of the box with the 
permuted data to generate a null referent distribution for 
estimating a P-value (see 'Methods'). </p>

<p>The top Swi6 3D hotspot contains known Swi6 target genes 
on different chromosomes </p>

<p>We focus on the top-ranked Swi6 3D hotspot by P-value un-
der PRIM to illustrate the potential of such hotspot discov-
ery by subsequently performing extensive downstream ver-
ification of the stability and robustness of this 3D hotspot. 
This top 3D hotspot contains a region from chromosome 
VII (chrVII), a region from chrVIII and a region from 
chrXVI (Figure 2). Notably, two of these genomic regions 
contain a known Swi6 target gene, as previously identified 
in a Swi6 ChIP-on-chip analysis (41). In other words, two 
out of the seven genes in this 3D hotspot are known Swi6 
target genes, compared to 207 known Swi6 target genes out 
of 6275 genes in the yeast genome (hypergeometric P &lt; 
0.033; additional summary statistics are presented in Ta-
ble 1). Specifically, the chrVII region contains the cell ad-
hesion mucin gene MSB2 (43) and the chrVIII region con-
tains the ergosterol (cell membrane sterol) biosynthesis gene 
ERG11 (44). This 3D hotspot may also contain other as yet </p>

<p>Swi6 ChIP−seq </p>

<p>Genes </p>

<p>−3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>516 
520 </p>

<p>chrVII </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>&gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; </p>

<p>SNU71 </p>

<p>&gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; </p>

<p>MSB2 </p>

<p>122 
125 </p>

<p>chrVIII </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>&lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; 
ERG11 </p>

<p>&lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; </p>

<p>YHR007C </p>

<p>&lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; </p>

<p>SOD2 </p>

<p>&lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; </p>

<p>TDA3   515 
517 </p>

<p>chrXVI </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>&lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; &lt; </p>

<p>VTC3 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Genomic regions in the top Swi6 3D hotspot under PRIM. This 
3D hotspot contains one region from chrVII, one region from chrVIII and 
one region from chrXVI. The top panels show the log 2 -normalized ChIP-
seq peak height in each region (gray background); if the boundary of a 
region is intergenic, the region is extended (white background) to the near-
est gene. The x-axis is the chromosomal position in kilobases. The bottom 
panels show the genes in each region by their names, genomic positions and 
orientations. The genes MSB2 and ERG11 (highlighted in red) were previ-
ously identified as significant Swi6 target genes in a ChIP-on-chip analysis 
(41). </p>

<p>uncharacterized Swi6 target genes. For example, the Sac-
charomyces genome database (45) indicates that VTC3, the 
membrane trafficking gene (46) in the chrXVI region of this 
hotspot, has Swi4 (Swi6's binding partner in the SBF com-
plex) as one of its regulators (47). If VTC3 turns out to 
be a bona fide Swi6 target gene, then the P-value of Swi6 
target gene enrichment in this hotspot will be markedly 
smaller than is currently reported. Thus, the top functional 
3D hotspot discovered by applying PRIM to Swi6 ChIP-seq 
peak height superposed on the 3D reconstruction contains 
known Swi6 target genes on different chromosomes. We an-
alyzed two additional ChIP-seq inputs (the repressor Tup1 
and the active form of RNA polymerase II (18)) separately 
superposed on the 3D reconstruction (Supplementary Fig-
ures S1-S3) but did not detect significant enrichment of tar-
get genes (or gene ontology terms) in the top 3D hotspot of 
either. Next, we pursued rigorous downstream analyses to 
verify the robustness of the top Swi6 3D hotspot discovered. </p>

<p>The top Swi6 3D hotspot under PRIM is relatively stable 
across parameter settings </p>

<p>The initial hotspot discovery was performed using the de-
fault PRIM tuning parameters (peel alpha = 0.05 and 
paste alpha = 0.01). As an initial sensitivity assessment of 
the top Swi6 3D hotspot containing MSB2 and ERG11 to 
these specifications, we applied PRIM with alternative pa-
rameter settings. We tested the six crossed combinations 
of three values for peel alpha (0.075, 0.05 or 0.025) and 
two values for paste alpha (0.025 or 0.01). Encouragingly, </p>



<p>Table 1. Summary of top Swi6 3D hotspot under PRIM </p>

<p>Rank by P-value 
1 (of 643) 
Holm P-value 
6.4 × 10 −3 
Mean ChIP-seq peak height (log 2 -normalized) 
0.82 
Z-score of mean ChIP-seq peak height 
4.83 
Number of genes in hotspot 
7 
Swi6 target genes in hotspot 
MSB2 (chrVII), ERG11 (chrVIII) 
P-value of target gene enrichment 
3.3 × 10 −2 </p>

<p>for five of the six combinations, the 3D hotspot contain-
ing MSB2 and ERG11 was ranked first by P-value (of 548 
to 717 potential hotspots) (Supplementary Table S1). For 
the other combination, it was ranked 22nd (of 503 poten-
tial hotspots). Thus, this top Swi6 3D hotspot is relatively 
stable across PRIM parameter settings. 
We also evaluated whether the discovery of this top 3D 
hotspot was specific to the bead interval of the 3D re-
construction to which PRIM was applied. For this pur-
pose, we generated two down-sampled 3D reconstructions 
by dropping every 3rd bead or every 2nd bead from the 
original 3D reconstruction. We superposed the Swi6 ChIP-
seq peak height on to each of these 3D reconstructions 
(in doing so the ChIP-seq peak height becomes binned at 
the same interval as the beads) and then applied PRIM. 
When the min beads parameter was reduced (from 25 to 
15)--consistent with the larger bead intervals (and smaller 
number of beads in the 3D reconstructions)--the 3D 
hotspot containing MSB2 and ERG11 was ranked 1st (of 
754 potential hotspots) for the 3D reconstruction resulting 
from dropping every 3rd bead, and was ranked 3rd (of 544 
potential hotspots) for the 3D reconstruction resulting from 
dropping every 2nd bead (Supplementary Table S2). This 
finding indicates that the top 3D hotspot is stable across 3D 
reconstructions that have different resolutions. 
In addition, we assessed whether elicitation of this top 
3D hotspot was sensitive to the orientation of the 3D re-
construction to which PRIM was applied. While PRIM's 
adaptivity makes it an effective tool for hotspot discov-
ery, a caveat is that it's paste and peel operations are 
performed with respect to (untransformed) input covari-
ates. In the present setting this may be problematic as the 
'covariates'--X, Y and Z axes--have no intrinsic meaning 
since the 3D reconstruction is coordinate free with no pre-
ferred orientation. To address this concern, we applied rota-
tion matrices to the original 3D reconstruction to generate 
six rotated 3D reconstructions (three combinations of two-
angle 45 
• rotations, and three combinations of two-angle 
315 
• rotations) and then applied PRIM to each of these. 
The 3D hotspot containing MSB2 and ERG11 ranked 
1st (of 652 to 712 potential hotspots) for three of these ro-
tated 3D reconstructions, and ranked 12th(of 663 poten-
tial hotspots) for another of the rotated 3D reconstruc-
tions (Supplementary Table S3). This 3D hotspot ranked 
poorly for the other two rotated 3D reconstructions, sug-
gesting that there are 3D reconstruction orientations for 
which PRIM cannot precisely home in on the 3D region of 
extreme ChIP-seq peak height orthogonally. Nevertheless, 
it is encouraging that this 3D hotspot ranks prominently for 
four of the six rotated 3D reconstructions, as this demon-
strates that this 3D hotspot is not specific to one orientation. </p>

<p>Applying PRIM after rotation of coordinate data to prin-
cipal axes represents a natural invariance-inducing strategy, 
although it is possible that this specific rotation may be non-
optimal with respect to hotspot identification. </p>

<p>An alternative algorithm identifies the same Swi6 3D hotspot </p>

<p>We next applied k-NN regression (21,48), which operates 
very differently from PRIM and is inherently invariant to 
3D reconstruction orientation. Briefly, the k beads nearest 
(here we use Euclidean distance) a starting seed bead are 
grouped together and the mean outcome of this group com-
puted, this representing a potential hotspot. This process is 
repeated at seed beads evenly spaced along each chromo-
some by a fixed interval, and groups are then ranked by 
mean outcome (see 'Methods'). Since the 'bottom-up' k-
NN regression groups together more genomically adjacent 
beads than the 'top-down' PRIM, we used the setting k = 
2*min beads = 50 to be able to elicit 3D hotspots comprised 
of more than one genomic region. 
It is notable that the third-ranked 3D hotspot under k-
NN regression (out of 957 potential 3D hotspots) contains 
two genomic regions: the chrVII region containing MSB2 
and the chrVIII region containing ERG11 (Supplementary 
Figure S4). This finding, utilizing a distinct, rotationally in-
variant analytical approach, is affirming of the robustness 
of the 3D hotspot containing MSB2 and ERG11. How-
ever, while k-NN regression can be effectively deployed for 
3D hotspot discovery, a potential limitation is that, due to 
its prescriptive, rather than adaptive, nature (all resulting 
hotspots will contain exactly k beads) and the attendant 
multiple testing burden, it may not prove sufficiently pow-
erful to detect statistically significant hotspots, as was the 
case here. </p>

<p>MSB2 and ERG11 are co-localized in other 3D reconstruc-
tions </p>

<p>A major advantage of utilizing 3D reconstructions for 
hotspot discovery is that functional genomic data can be 
readily superposed on 3D reconstructions. This contrasts 
with contact level data where such superposition is prob-
lematic in view of its inherent pairwise structure. In addi-
tion, the use of a 3D reconstruction serves to dramatically 
reduce the hotspot discovery search space in comparison 
with the combinatorial explosion of hotspot candidates if 
analyses were to be performed using pairwise contact data. 
However, an obvious concern in basing hotspot discovery 
on a 3D reconstruction is that the hotspots depend on the 
3D reconstruction used and, as previously noted, gauging 
the accuracy of a given 3D reconstruction is challenging 
(15). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 5 2033   To address this concern, we tested whether the two 
Swi6 target genes in the top 3D hotspot from PRIM were 
closer together than expected in various 3D reconstruc-
tions. Specifically, we assessed the significance of the Eu-
clidean distance between MSB2 and ERG11 via resam-
pling with preservation of the chromosome structure of 
the data as per (17). We performed this assessment on 
the 3D reconstruction that was used for hotspot discovery, 
which was generated via explicit-factor normalization fol-
lowed by constrained optimization of a multi-dimensional 
scaling (MDS) criterion, the constraints reflecting numer-
ous biologically-based restrictions (7). In addition, we per-
formed this assessment on two 3D reconstructions from 
(13), which were generated via a different normalization 
algorithm (iterative correction and eigenvector decomposi-
tion (ICE) (39)) followed by differing reconstruction algo-
rithms: an unconstrained MDS optimization and a Poisson 
regression model (13). 
Encouragingly, MSB2 and ERG11 were found to be 
closer together than expected not only in the 3D recon-
struction that was used for hotspot discovery (P = 9.9 × 
10 
−4 ), but also in the two 3D reconstructions generated via 
a different normalization algorithm followed by an uncon-
strained MDS optimization (P = 4.6 × 10 
−2 ) or by a Pois-
son regression model (P = 4.0 × 10 
−2 ) (Figure 3). This 
result provides evidence that the biological finding is not 
reconstruction-specific. We were not able to discover this 
hotspot de novo by applying PRIM to the 3D reconstruc-
tions generated via different normalization and reconstruc-
tion algorithms; however, this is not surprising given the dis-
similarity of the 3D reconstructions (Figure 3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Identifying functional interactions in the nucleus is an im-
portant and challenging problem. Examples of transcrip-
tion factories (or 'regulatory depots') have been described 
in experimental literature (8,22,23). Previous attempts to 
utilize Hi-C data to identify such co-localizations (whether 
from contact level data or from 3D reconstructions) have 
so far only assessed marks such as centromeres, telomeres 
and long terminal repeats (11,16,17). Relatedly, Ben-Elazar 
et al. (49) used a sophisticated approach that adjusts for 
genomic proximity in assessing 3D spatial co-localization 
of transcription factor target genes. Here, we made the 
novel contribution of extending such analyses to continuous 
functional genomic data. We applied PRIM to Swi6 ChIP-
seq data superposed on a 3D genome reconstruction and 
demonstrated that the top-ranked 3D hotspot by P-value 
contains known Swi6 target genes on different chromo-
somes. Extensive downstream analyses demonstrated the 
robustness of this 3D hotspot -it being detected under a 
range of PRIM parameter settings, 3D reconstruction reso-
lutions, 3D reconstruction rotations and also emergent us-
ing an alternative algorithm, k-NN regression. Moreover, 
the known Swi6 target genes contained in this hotspot, 
MSB2 and ERG11, are also co-localized under alternate 3D 
reconstructions. 
Other techniques could potentially be used to discover 
3D hotspots. Recursive partitioning or tree-structured re-
gression methods (21) can isolate regions by successive split-</p>

<p>Figure 3. Swi6 target genes MSB2 (chrVII) and ERG11 (chrVIII) in differ-
ent 3D chromatin configuration reconstructions. (A) The 3D reconstruc-
tion used for hotspot discovery, which was generated via explicit-factor 
normalization followed by constrained optimization of a multidimensional 
scaling criterion. (B) A 3D reconstruction (13), which was generated via 
matrix balancing followed by a Poisson regression model. The 3D recon-
structions are colored by chromosome, or are colored yellow with MSB2 
and ERG11 highlighted in red. The first two rows display the full 3D re-
constructions. The last two rows display only chromosomes VII and VIII. 
The P-value of the Euclidean distance between MSB2 and ERG11 was es-
timated by resampling within chromosome. </p>

<p>ting. However, it was partly to overcome the top-down 
greediness of these approaches that PRIM was advanced. 
Like PRIM, these methods are not invariant under rota-
tion, but such invariance can be attained using splits that 
are linear combinations of the coordinate axes. Neverthe-
less, due to computational expense and instability, trees with 
such oblique splits are disfavored (21). Approaches based 
on algebraic topology and in particular persistent homol-
ogy and Betti number barcodes (50) have possible utility in 
eliciting 3D hotspots but are undeveloped from an inferen-
tial perspective. 
Identification of novel chromatin structures has been en-
abled by the recent emergence of Hi-C assays. In partic-</p>



<p>ular, both topologically associated domains (51) and con-
tact domains (52) delineate 'regions' with substantial self-
chromatin interactions. However, as these constructs are de-
fined in terms of contiguous chromatin intervals they are in-
herently intra-chromosomal and, unlike our functional 3D 
hotspots, cannot be comprised of inter-chromosomal re-
gions characterized by extreme values of associated func-
tional outcomes. We note that while the Swi6 3D hotspot 
presented here contains regions from different chromo-
somes our approach can identify 3D hotspots containing 
distal intra-chromosomal regions, as may be more likely to 
arise for higher-order eukaryotes due to the existence of 
chromosome territories (53). 
The physical extent of an identified 3D hotspot is a func-
tion not just of the magnitude and localization of the out-
come being analyzed but also the resolution of the under-
lying Hi-C data. Even in instances wherein this resolution 
appreciably exceeds the extent of, say, physical DNA : pro-
tein complex interactions there is still biological utility in 
hotspot elicitation, as we have illustrated and analogous to 
linkage and/or GWAS studies as precursors to fine map-
ping. 
There are putative advantages in utilizing 3D reconstruc-
tions for discovering functional 3D hotspots in comparison 
with pursuing such discovery using contact level data. At-
tempts to elicit hotspots by search of raw (pairwise) contacts 
(interaction frequencies) would potentially face combinato-
rial explosion. In addition, superposing functional genomic 
data onto the contact level data in the first place is prob-
lematic because of the pairwise nature of the contacts. As 
an example of what can be gleaned from the contact level 
data, a recent study applied hierarchical clustering to the 
pairwise contacts based on the epigenetic status of the first 
locus in each pair (54); however, this merely groups together 
pairs that have the same epigenetic status (of the first locus), 
regardless of whether the different pairs are physically prox-
imal. 
Conversely, functional hotspots discovered from 3D re-
constructions are conditional on the quality of the 3D re-
construction. Previous studies have advanced methods for 
gauging the reproducibility of 3D reconstructions (15) or 
have used FISH measurements to calibrate Hi-C derived 
distances (55). However, the ability to arbitrate between 
competing solutions remains limited. Herein, we performed 
analyses to demonstrate that the Swi6 target genes in the top 
3D hotspot discovered in one 3D reconstruction are also 
closer together than expected in 3D reconstructions gener-
ated via different normalization and reconstruction algo-
rithms. The recent emergence of single cell (56,57) and in 
situ (52) Hi-C assays will potentially enable, by means of a 
series of carefully designed experiments, improved assess-
ments of 3D reconstruction reproducibility. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>Some computations were performed using the UCSF Bio-
statistics High Performance Computing System. We thank </p>

<p>William Noble and two reviewers for very helpful comments 
on this manuscript and thank Nelle Varoquaux for provid-
ing data. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fel-
lowship [1144247]; National Institutes of Health (NIH) 
[R01 GM109457]; National Institutes of Health Train-
ing [T32 GM007175 to D.C. in part]. Funding for open 
access charge: National Institutes of Health (NIH) [R01 
GM109457]. 
Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 5 2035 </p>



</text></tei>