<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4251217" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Introduction: This study examines the emergency department (ED) waiting room (WR) population's 
knowledge about the ED process and hospital function and explores the types of educational 
materials that might appeal to patients and their companions in an ED waiting room. Our goal was to 
identify potential high-impact opportunities for patient education. </p>

<p>Methods: A 32-question survey about demographics, usage of primary care physicians (PCP), 
understanding of the ED and triage process, desire to know about delays, health education and 
understanding of teaching hospitals was offered to all qualified individuals. </p>

<p>Results: Five hundred and forty-four surveys were returned. Fifty-five percent reported having a 
PCP, of which 53% (29% of all WR patients) called a PCP prior to coming to the ED. It was found 
that 51.2% can define triage; 51% as an acuity assessment and 17% as a vital signs check. Sixty-
nine percent knew why patients were seen according to triage priority. Seventy-two percent wanted 
to know about delays, yet only 25% wanted to know others' wait times. People wanted updates 
every 41 minutes and only three percent wanted a physician to do this. Forty-one percent wanted 
information on how the ED functions, 60% via handouts and 43% via video. Information on updates 
and common medical emergencies is significantly more important than material on common 
illnesses, finding a PCP, or ED function (p&lt;0.05). Median estimated time for medical workup ranged 
from 35 minutes for radiographs, to one hour for lab results, computed tomography, specialist 
consult, and admission. Sixty-nine percent knew the definition of a teaching hospital and of those, 
87% knew they were at a teaching hospital. Subgroup analysis between racial groups showed 
significantly reduced knowledge of the definitions of triage and teaching hospitals and significantly 
increased desire for information on ED function in minority groups (p&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Conclusion: The major findings in this study were that many visitors would like handouts about 
ED function and medical emergencies over other topics. Additionally, the knowledge of functions 
such as triage and teaching hospitals were 70% and 69%, respectively. This was reduced in non-
Caucasian ethnicities, while there was an increased desire for information on ED function relative 
to Caucasians. This research suggests increasing updates and educational materials in the 
waiting room could impact the waiting room and overall hospital experience. [West J Emerg Med. 
2014;15(7):764-769.] </p>

<p>ED visits have been increasing every year, with the mean 
occupancy rate increasing at an even more rapid rate. 
2 As a 
result, a substantial amount of time is spent in ED waiting </p>

<p>Volume XV, NO. 7 : November 2014 </p>

<p> 
Western Journal of Emergency Medicine </p>

<p>Seibert et al. 
What Do Patients Want? </p>

<p>rooms. A 2006 study estimated that the average ED wait 
time was 45 minutes with a range of 27 to 83 minutes. 
3 Time 
spent in the waiting room may bring frustration to patients 
and their family members as wait times extend, other patients 
receive care, and no updates are given. Educating patients 
while they wait to be seen could be a valuable tool that has 
been minimally studied. Studies on health education in the 
ED waiting room have shown that patients are interested in 
wellness topics and desire education in the form of brochures 
and books. 
4 A study evaluating the effectiveness of showing 
patients a video explaining what to expect during an ED visit 
demonstrated increased patient satisfaction with the visit. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>However, no study to date has specifically assessed patients' 
knowledge of the ED visit process including the length of or 
cause for delays, what information they would like to know 
while they wait, and their understanding of the triage process. 
The lack of information and understanding of patient's desires 
and knowledge of the ED process makes it very difficult 
for hospital administrators, physicians, and staff to address 
patients' needs. It also creates challenges when trying to 
deliver the desired information to the waiting room (WR) 
population in order to create a better ED experience with 
increased patient satisfaction. 
The objective of this study was to determine baseline 
knowledge of ED and hospital processes, and to establish 
types of information WR patients want, including expected 
wait times, causes of delays, and the triage process. 
Furthermore, we sought to determine how they would like 
this information delivered. In addition, we asked patients and 
family members what were expected estimated times for labs, 
imaging studies, and admission. Secondarily we sought to 
determine if different desires correlate with racial groups, and 
to assess if patients wanted educational health materials. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Study Design, Setting, Population, and Protocol 
Study design and methods were approved by the local 
institutional review board. The study was conducted at an 
urban university teaching hospital in the WR of the ED. 
The 32-bed ED had 72,000 annual visits at the time of the 
study and is an American College of Surgeons Level II 
trauma center. A written survey was distributed to eligible 
participants during convenience-selected blocks of time 
between December 2011 and February 2013. These survey 
blocks ranged in length from two to eight hours and were 
chosen to include various times of day and days of the week. 
Inclusion criteria included patients registering for medical 
care and their accompanying family members, friends, or 
coworkers, age greater than 18, the ability to understand 
written English or Spanish, arrival by personal transportation 
to the ED, and not needing immediate medical attention. 
Any person meeting inclusion criteria was offered a survey 
by the research assistant (RA) after the registration process 
was completed. Only one member of each group of a patient </p>

<p>plus his or her companions was offered a survey. Participants 
were asked to fill out the survey and place it in a collection 
box when finished, thereby maintaining confidentiality; they 
were informed that the survey was optional both verbally 
and by reading the first paragraph of the survey. The RA was 
available to answer questions and monitored the WR while 
participants filled out the survey. 
The survey was developed through a consensus panel 
of emergency physicians (EP) that was subsequently 
evaluated through mock participants. The English survey 
was translated into Spanish by a native speaking, certified 
translator. Surveys were deployed in paper format. Final 
survey design resulted in 32 mixed response questions with 
a Flesch-Kincaid reading grade level of 6.5 (see appendix 
A). Answers to "free-text" questions were deemed correct 
or incorrect as compared a standard set by a consensus of 
EPs and researchers. For questions 7-9, asking why some 
patients are seen before others despite order of arrival, 
responses were judged to be correct if some mention was 
made of patients being seen in order of acuity. For question 
11, asking the definition of triage, responses were sorted into 
three categories: Those making a mention of triage as an 
acuity check, those defining triage as a vital signs check, and 
all others (which were judged to be incorrect). </p>

<p>Measurements and Data Analysis 
We did data analysis with <rs id="software-0" type="software">R</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 3.1.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Vienna, Austria</rs>) and <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> <rs id="software-1" type="software">Excel</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2010</rs> (Redmond, Washington), 
with the assistance from the university's Research Consulting 
Laboratory. Responses for each question on the survey were 
first compared between the English and Spanish surveys. We 
analyzed differences between language groups as categorical 
variables using a Chi-squared test. When the assumptions of 
the Chi-squared test were not met, a Fisher's exact test was 
used. For this analysis, questions 1 and 20-24 were analyzed 
as continuous variables and compared between language 
groups using a two-sample t-test. Because 47 comparisons 
were made, we used a significance threshold of p&lt;0.0001 for 
all comparisons. 
No significant differences were noted between English 
and Spanish language survey responses except for race/ 
ethnicity (See Results). As a result, in subsequent analysis, 
responses from English and Spanish surveys were combined 
and analyzed as a single group. We compared the responses to 
questions 20-24 using analysis of variance with the question 
as a categorical predictor and the response as a continuous 
outcome. Questions 14 and 28 were compared on the log-scale 
using two-sample t-tests and then the results were converted 
back to a normal scale due to highly skewed results. The 
results for these items are presented as the geometric mean 
and a 95% confidence interval. We omitted responses with a 
value of 0 from this portion of the analysis. 
Finally, we made comparisons between racial/ethnic 
groups for questions 5, 10, 16, and 25. Native American and </p>

<p>Western Journal of Emergency Medicine </p>

<p> 
Volume XV, NO. 7 : November 2014 </p>

<p>What Do Patients Want? 
Seibert et al. </p>

<p>Asian respondents were combined with "Other" respondents 
in statistical analysis, while Caucasians, African-Americans, 
and Hispanics were analyzed as their own groups. We made 
comparisons between groups using logistic regression. 
Differences between individual ethnic groups were compared 
when the overall test ratio reached significance. We used 
the Tukey honest significant difference method to adjust 
p-values for multiple pairwise corrections for multiple 
hypotheses testing. Adjusted p-values less than 0.05 were 
considered significant. 
On two separate surveys, participants responded "No" to 
question 10 ("Do you know what triage means?") and then also 
attempted to define triage, which they were not instructed to do 
unless answering "Yes" to question 10. These two results were 
included in the subsequent analysis despite this discrepancy. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
A total of 544 surveys were returned to the collection 
box (93.7% of those that were distributed to consenting 
participants), supporting acceptable research protocol. Of 
these surveys, 7.1% were in Spanish. Only ethnicity/race was 
significantly different between English and Spanish surveys 
(p&lt;0.0001). For all subsequent analyses, results from English 
and Spanish surveys were therefore combined and analyzed 
as a group. On average, 25 out of the 32 of the questions 
were completed. Demographic data regarding respondents is 
displayed in Table 1. 
Of respondents, 54.9% reported having an established 
relationship with a primary care physician (PCP). Of those 
respondents with a PCP, 53.0% called their PCP. The PCP </p>

<p>informed 45.1% of those who called they were ill enough 
to require a visit to the ED, 33.4% were told there were 
no appointments available, 14.4% were told they needed 
further testing, and 6.9% were told they were no longer the 
PCP's patient. 
Of all respondents, 68.8% claimed to know why some 
patients were seen sooner than others despite arriving later. Of 
that group, 87.0% were able to give a valid reason, determined 
by a consensus of professional opinion of EPs and the research 
group (see Methods), for this practice while 13.0% were not. 
Of all respondents 31.2% reported they did not know why 
some patients were seen sooner than others despite arriving 
later. We observed a statistically significant difference in the 
percentage of respondents reporting it is fair to see some 
patients before others between the group who did not claim to 
know why this happens and the group who both claimed they 
did know why this happens and provided a valid explanation 
as to why (Table 2). 
Of respondents, 48.7% claimed to know what triage 
meant. Of respondents who attempted to define triage, 51.9% 
defined it as an evaluation of the patient's acuity, 17.5% 
defined in as a vital signs check, and 30.6% of respondents 
gave an incorrect answer as judged by the authors using a 
consensus definition of triage (See Methods). 
When asked what information they would like to be 
provided with, 72.2% of respondents indicated they would 
like to know about foreseeable delays, while only 24.6% 
of respondents wanted to know about other patients' wait 
times. Respondents wanted to receive updates every 41 
minutes on average (SD ± 32 minutes). Seventy-four </p>

<p>Age 
n (%) 
Race 
n (%) 
Role 
n (%) </p>

<p>18-19 
22 (5) 
Caucasian 
221 (41) 
Patient 
377 (69) </p>

<p>20-29 
154 (28) 
African American 
123 (23) 
Family member 
132 (25) </p>

<p>30-39 
111 (20) 
Hispanic 
125 (23) 
Friend 
30 (6) </p>

<p>40-49 
99 (18) 
Asian 
19 (4) 
Coworker 
2 (0.4) </p>

<p>50-59 
89 (16) 
Native American 
7 (1) 
Has a PCP 
297 (55) </p>

<p>60-69 
41 (8) 
Other 
43 (8) </p>

<p>70-79 
19 (3) </p>

<p>&gt;80 
3 (1) </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographics of respondents surveyed. </p>

<p>PCP, primary care physician </p>

<p>Claim to know why some patients are seen 
before others </p>

<p>Able to provide a valid reason for this 
practice </p>

<p>Percentage of group who thought this 
practice was fair </p>

<p>Yes 
Yes 
96.2%* </p>

<p>Yes 
No 
86.0% </p>

<p>No 
-
55.0%* </p>

<p>Table 2. Proportion of respondents reporting it is fair to see some patients before others despite later arrival, stratified by self-reported 
knowledge of why this occurs and ability to provide a valid reason why it does. </p>

<p>* Indicates statistically significant difference between groups (p&lt;0.0001). </p>

<p>Volume XV, NO. 7 : November 2014 </p>

<p> 
Western Journal of Emergency Medicine </p>

<p>Seibert et al. 
What Do Patients Want? </p>

<p>percent of respondents had no preference who gave these 
updates, while 13.7% of respondents felt a clerk should 
provide the updates, 9.0% of respondents preferred a nurse, 
and 3.3% of respondents preferred the updates coming 
directly from physicians. 
Forty-one percent of respondents would like to be 
provided with more information on how the ED functions. 
When asked in which medium they would like this 
information, 59.9% of respondents indicated they would like 
handouts, 42.9% indicated they would like videos, and 9.5% 
indicated they would like updates through a computer in the 
waiting room (note: percentages do not add to 100% because 
respondents were able to choose multiple answers). When 
asked what information they found important on a scale of 1 
(not important) to 4 (very important), information on updates 
(mean 2.93; 95% CI 2.85-3.02) and serious medical conditions 
such as cerebral vascular accidents and myocardial infarctions 
(mean 2.90; 95% CI 2.81-2.99) were significantly more 
important to respondents (p&lt;0.05) than information regarding 
common illnesses (mean 2.68; 95% CI 2.59-2.77), finding a 
PCP (mean 2.71; 95% CI 2.62-2.80), and ED function (mean 
2.66; 95% CI 2.57-2.75) (Figure 1). 
In regards to knowledge about teaching hospitals, 69.2% 
of respondents claimed to know what a teaching hospital 
was, and 87.4% of this group knew they were currently 
in a teaching hospital. When asked to identify aspects 
that differentiate a teaching hospital from other hospitals, 
respondents selected attributes shown in Figure 2. 
Respondents were asked to estimate the time it would 
take to complete lab work, x-rays, computed tomography 
(CT), specialist consultations, and hospital admission. The 
ranges of responses were large with the mean considerably 
skewed from outliers so interquartile ranges (IQR) were 
reported along with medians instead of means and standard 
deviations. Lab work had an IQR of 0.5 to 1 h with a median </p>

<p>of 1 h. X-rays also had an IQR of 0.5 to 1 h and a median 
of 0.58 h. CTs had an IQR of 0.5 to 1.34 h with a median of 
1 h. Consultations with specialists had an IQR of 0.5 to 1.5 
h and a median of 1 h, and admissions had an IQR of 0.62 
to 2 h with a median of 1 h. None of these were found to be 
significantly different from another. 
Compared to Caucasians, there was reduced likelihood 
of answering "yes" when asked what triage meant among 
African-Americans (OR 0.46, 95% CI 0.29-0.72, p=0.003), 
Hispanics (OR 0.23, 95% CI 0.14-0.37, p&lt;0.001), and 
"Others" (OR 0.36, 95% CI 0.20-0.63, p=0.002). Conversely, 
compared to Caucasians there was an increased likelihood of 
answering "yes" when asked about a desire for information 
on ED function by African-Americans (OR 3.01, 95% CI 
1.89-4.84, p&lt;0.001), Hispanics (OR 1.99, 95% CI 1.24-
3.20, p=0.016), and "Others" (OR 3.12, 95% CI 1.76-5.58, 
p&lt;0.001). Furthermore, compared to Caucasians, there was a 
decreased likelihood of answering "yes" when asked whether 
the university hospital was a teaching hospital among African-
Americans (OR 0.40, 95% CI 0.24-0.68, p=0.002), Hispanics 
(OR 0.17, 95% CI 0.10-0.28, p&lt;0.001), and "Others" (OR 
0.40, 95% CI 0.21-0.75, p=0.015). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Multiple factors, such as increased length of stay, lack of 
hospital beds leading to ED boarding and an aging population, 
have led to increased ED WR times. 
6 While many strategies 
have been attempted to expedite and improve the WR 
experience, hospitals continue to struggle with how to manage 
their ED waiting rooms to improve patient satisfaction of the 
visit. Extended length of stay in the WR is a serious concern, 
and it is the number one reason patients with possible critical 
medical issues leave without being seen by a provider. 
7 Many 
strategies have been used to reduce the time or improve the 
experience of the WR, including physician/physician assistant </p>

<p>Figure 1. Rated level of importance of information available in the emergency department waiting room on a scale from 1 (not impor-
tant) to 4 (very important); mean value with 95% CI displayed. 
PCP, primary care physician; ED, emergency department </p>

<p>Western Journal of Emergency Medicine </p>

<p> 
Volume XV, NO. 7 : November 2014 </p>

<p>What Do Patients Want? 
Seibert et al. </p>

<p>triage, wait-time timers, and remodeling waiting rooms. </p>

<p>4,8 </p>

<p>Patients who left without being seen also cited lack of 
communication as a major reason for leaving. 
9 To reduce the 
communication barrier between patients and medical providers 
and to interact effectively with the WR population, the medical 
community must understand what patients wish to know as they 
wait and how to best describe ED workflow to patients. 
This study allows us to approach ED communication 
improvement projects with a better understanding of what 
needs to be conveyed to improve the experience in the WR. 
Defining how the ED functions appears to be an area of 
improvement as only 70% of respondents were able to give 
a valid definition of triage -a mainstay of ED function. 
Explaining how the ED functions via handouts or video, 
combined with information on serious medical conditions, 
may be helpful in a number of ways. Past studies have 
shown that patients are interested in wellness topics and 
desire education in the form of brochures and books in the 
ED, and providing health and wellness information in that 
context could have public health impact. Videos explaining 
what to expect during an ED visit have been shown to 
increase patient satisfaction with the visit, 
4 and keeping 
patients in the waiting room occupied with educational 
material could theoretically reduce perceived wait time and 
alleviate some of the stress of the wait. 
10 Though participants 
in another survey thought a time tracker would improve 
their experience, our study shows that only around one-
quarter of people actually want to know the wait times of 
others. 
11 Our study showed what seemed more important to 
the WR population as a whole was frequent updates about 
foreseeable delays coming from any person on the ED team; 
it did not need to be a physician giving updates. 
Only 69% of our survey respondents knew the functions 
of a teaching hospital. This means that facts about the </p>

<p>hospital being visited and about the meaning of a teaching 
hospital could be communicated to those in the ED waiting 
room to great effect. Providing this information could help 
remove some of the stress-inducing confusion patients may 
experience when they do not understand certain aspects of 
their visit, such as why they are seen by trainees at various 
levels of education. Information about average times 
for procedures, radiology, laboratory tests, consults, and 
admission seem to be greatly needed; respondents' estimates 
of these times had massive standard deviations, indicating 
limited knowledge of ED time courses. This would increase 
transparency as patients gain understanding of what is 
happening during their visit and how much time they can 
reasonably expect it to take. In theory, this could also reduce 
the stress and frustration of waiting. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Non-Caucasian ethnicities seem especially primed for 
increased education and communication as compared to 
Caucasians; their understanding of ED function and teaching 
hospitals was significantly lower while their requests for 
information on ED function was significantly higher. These 
differences do not appear to be related to language, since the 
proportions of respondents who correctly answered these 
questions were not significantly different between the Spanish 
and English surveys. Among other things, these findings could 
represent variations in cultural beliefs regarding the value 
and objective of a healthcare visit or disparities in healthcare 
literacy between different ethnic groups. </p>

<p>LIMITATIONS 
There are limitations to this study. First, the survey was 
only distributed in one ED with its given demographics. This 
limits the ability to generalize our findings to other EDs. In 
particular, suburban or rural ED demographics might differ 
substantially from ours and thus might limit generalizability </p>

<p>Figure 2. Aspects of teaching hospitals compared to other hospitals by waiting room respondents. </p>

<p>Volume XV, NO. 7 : November 2014 </p>

<p> 
Western Journal of Emergency Medicine </p>

<p>Seibert et al. 
What Do Patients Want? </p>

<p>of our findings to those settings. 
Second, there were respondents who did not, or were not 
able to, return our survey after agreeing to participate. Among 
other reasons, this occurred because patients were called into 
the ED to be seen, patients left without being seen, and patients 
reconsidered their decision to participate in the survey before 
completing it. Our decision to concentrate primarily on the WR 
as a focus for patient education guided our methodology of 
administering a survey in the WR before a patient visit in the 
ED proper. This limited our ability to assess patient satisfaction 
with the visit itself or patient understanding of discharge 
instructions. We are thus not able to draw any conclusions about 
patients' comprehension of those aspects of their visit. 
We did not explore whether a higher proportion of 
respondents would have reported a preference for receiving 
updates from higher-level providers (e.g., physicians or nurses) 
if they knew those updates would not influence their wait 
time. While our survey text did not suggest any link between 
receiving updates from physicians or nurses and increased wait 
times, we cannot rule out the possibility that many respondents 
held this belief. This presents an additional opportunity to 
educate patients about the workflow within the ED. 
Finally, our survey was only in two languages. This 
restricted responses from a minority of people approached 
because of fluency in only an additional language. 
Financial, time, and availability constraints limited the 
availability of interpreters for use in this study. Future 
avenues of research could include repeating this study in 
additional locations; adding more languages; expanding 
the survey to examine patient understanding of actual visits 
with a physician and subsequent discharge instructions; and 
implementing and evaluating the findings of this research, 
such as by providing more information on ED function and 
major medical emergencies. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
The ED waiting room is the first stop for the majority of 
patients to be seen at the hospital. Here, we have identified 
multiple areas where limited knowledge, 70% knowledge of 
triage and 69% knowledge of teaching hospitals, and a desire for 
more information overlap in the ED waiting room population. 
The significant differences in knowledge and desire for education 
material in non-Caucasian ethnicities are an important finding 
and should direct future projects to take each ED's ethnicities 
into account. These findings suggest possible high-impact targets 
for intervention in patient education and ED throughput with 
the goal of improving patient satisfaction. These could include 
providing educational materials about hospital and ED function 
and severe health conditions (both reported as highly desired), 
as well as giving regular updates regarding foreseeable delays. 
Further study, potentially including targeted trials of the above 
interventions, would be needed to address whether these changes 
would have any measurable impact on patient satisfaction or 
would improve the patient experience in the ED. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS 
The authors would like to acknowledge Pamela Simon and 
Rachel Blumhagen for their assistance with statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Address for Correspondence: Thomas Seibert, MD MS, 1542 
Tulane Avenue Room 452 Box T4M2, New Orleans, LA 70112. 
Email: Thomas.Seibert@ucdenver.edu. </p>

<p>Conflicts of Interest: By the WestJEM article submission 
agreement, all authors are required to disclose all affiliations, 
funding sources and financial or management relationships that 
could be perceived as potential sources of bias. The authors 
disclosed none. </p>



</text></tei>