<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4582469" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Backgrounds/Aims: Surveillance programs and imaging modality developments have increased the detection rate of 
small hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). In particular, liver transplantation produces good results and is now regarded 
an alternative to liver resection. However, optimal treatment for small HCC is still debated, and thus, the authors de-
signed this study to document clinicopathological characteristics, to identify the prognostic factors of small HCC, and 
to determine the effectiveness of surgery. Methods: A total of 507 patients underwent curative liver resection for HCC 
between January 1996 and August 2006 in our institution. One hundred and thirty four of these patients with a single 
HCC of less than 3 cm and no gross vascular invasion were enrolled. Results: Major resection was performed in 
32 (23.9%) patients; there was no postoperative mortality. Fifty-eight (43.3%) patients experienced recurrence, 53 de-
veloped intrahepatic recurrence alone, and 50 (94.3%) of 53 had tumors within the Milan criteria. Five-year disease-free 
and overall survival rates were 51.0% and 77.3%, respectively. Microscopic vascular invasion, positivity for hepatitis 
B surface antigen or antibody to hepatitis C, and an indocyanine green retention test at 15 minutes of more than 
10% were found to be significantly correlated with disease-free overall survival. A platelet count of less than 
100,000/mm 
3 was the only independent prognostic factors of overall survival identified. Conclusions: This study showed </p>

<p>favorable outcome comparable to the survival after liver transplantation, thus that liver resection appears to be the 
primary treatment option for small HCC, even in cases with poor prognostic factors. (Korean J Hepatobiliary Pancreat 
Surg 2011;15:199-205) </p>

<p>The majority of hepatocellular carcinomas (HCC) arise </p>

<p>in the background of chronic hepatitis and cirrhosis, and </p>

<p>thus, liver transplantation is the most ideal treatment mo-</p>

<p>dality as it corrects the underling liver disease. However, </p>

<p>because of the donor shortage situation, liver resection is </p>

<p>the preferred treatment. Furthermore, the use of liver re-</p>

<p>section in patients with HCC is largely limited by ad-</p>

<p>vanced disease and poor liver function. 
Recently, a randomized controlled study was performed </p>

<p>to determine the merits of HCC screening in China. 
1 It </p>

<p>was found screening confers survival benefits and that de-</p>

<p>velopment of imaging modalities and surveillance pro-</p>

<p>grams have increased the detection rate of small resect-</p>

<p>able HCC. 
2,3 Several studies have reported the outcomes </p>

<p>of treatment modalities for small HCC, 
4-8 and despite the </p>

<p>different definitions used for small HCC, liver trans-</p>

<p>plantation has been proposed as an alternative strategy for </p>

<p>small HCC instead of liver resection. 
8,9 Nevertheless, the </p>

<p>optimal treatment for small HCC remains controver-</p>

<p>sial. 
10,11 Small HCC has a favorable prognosis, but its out-</p>

<p>come was different according to the prognostic strat-</p>

<p>ification and prognostic scoring system for patients treated </p>

<p>by liver resection. </p>

<p>6,12 </p>

<p>In the present study, we investigated the clinicopatho-</p>

<p>logical characteristics and prognostic factors of small </p>

<p>HCC and attempted to determine the effectiveness of sur-</p>

<p>gery with the intention of finding the best approach for </p>

<p>its treatment. </p>



<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Definitions 
Curative resection was defined as complete tumor re-</p>

<p>section with a clear microscopic margin and no residual </p>

<p>tumor by imaging at 1 month after surgery. Major liver </p>

<p>resection was defined as the resection of ≥3 Couinaud </p>

<p>segments. Postoperative mortality was defined as death </p>

<p>within 1 month after surgery, and recurrence as typical </p>

<p>arterial enhancement with delayed washout on computed </p>

<p>tomography (CT) images. Causes of patient death were </p>

<p>classified as recurred HCC-related death, complications of </p>

<p>liver cirrhosis without recurrence, and unrelated causes. </p>

<p>Patients 
Five hundred and seven patients underwent curative liv-</p>

<p>er resection for HCC between January 1996 and August </p>

<p>2006 at the Department of Surgery, Yonsei University </p>

<p>Health System, Seoul, Korea. Of these 507 patients, 146 </p>

<p>had single HCC of ≤3 cm in diameter. Twelve of the </p>

<p>146 patients were also excluded because of gross portal </p>

<p>or hepatic vein involvement. Finally, 134 patients were </p>

<p>enrolled in this study. </p>

<p>Preoperative evaluation and follow-up 
methods 
A preoperative CT scan, biochemistry testing, and an </p>

<p>indocyanine green retention test at 15 minutes (ICG R15) </p>

<p>were performed on all patients. The decision whether to </p>

<p>perform major or minor resection was made pre-</p>

<p>operatively based on tumor location by CT, liver function, </p>

<p>Child-Pugh status, ICG R15, and on the likelihood of ach-</p>

<p>ieving an adequate resection margin. Alpha-fetoprotein </p>

<p>(AFP) levels were determined and underwent ultra-</p>

<p>sonography (US) or CT performed on all patients every </p>

<p>3-6 months after surgery. </p>

<p>Outcomes 
Prognostic factors for disease-free survival and overall </p>

<p>survival were sought from among the following 18 clin-</p>

<p>icopathologic variables. Nine were patient factors, namely, </p>

<p>age, gender, etiology of liver disease, serum albumin lev-</p>

<p>el, serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine </p>

<p>aminotransferase (ALT) levels, ICG R15, platelet count, </p>

<p>and liver cirrhosis grade. Five were surgical factors, that </p>

<p>is, intraoperative bleeding amount, perioperative trans-</p>

<p>fusion, surgical tumor-free resection margin, extent of re-</p>

<p>section, and type of resection, and four were tumor fac-</p>

<p>tors, that is, tumor size, microscopic vascular invasion, </p>

<p>Edmondson-Steiner grade, and serum AFP level. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v 12.0</rs> </p>

<p>software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). Continuous re-</p>

<p>sults are presented as medians (ranges) and categorical re-</p>

<p>sults are presented as numbers (percentages). 
Disease-free and overall survival rates were calculated </p>

<p>using the Kaplan-Meier method. Prognostic factors of dis-</p>

<p>ease-free and overall survival rates were indentified using </p>

<p>the log-rank test and univariate analysis. Multivariate </p>

<p>analysis was performed using the Cox proportional hazard </p>

<p>model; factors significant by univariate analysis were </p>

<p>included. Statistical significance was accepted for p-values </p>

<p>of ＜0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Clinical characteristics 
The clinical characteristics are presented in Table 1. </p>

<p>The 134 study subjects had a median age of 53.1 years </p>

<p>(range, 24-73 years), and 99 were male. The most com-</p>

<p>mon etiology of liver disease was hepatitis B virus </p>

<p>(n=104, 77.6%). Liver cirrhosis was proved by pathologic </p>

<p>examination in 86 patients (64.2%). All patients except </p>

<p>one were of Child-Pugh class A. Major resections were </p>

<p>performed in 32 patients (23.8%). Forty-five patients </p>

<p>(48.9%) received a perioperative transfusion, and there </p>

<p>was no postoperative mortality. </p>

<p>Long-term surgical outcomes after resection 
During a median follow-up of 43.5 months (4-110 </p>

<p>months), 58 (43.3%) patients recurred. Fifty-three patients </p>

<p>developed intrahepatic recurrence alone, 4 extrahepatic re-</p>

<p>currences alone, and 1 concurrent intrahepatic and extra-</p>

<p>hepatic recurrence. Fifty (86.2%) of the intrahepatic re-</p>

<p>currence patients had tumors within the Milan criteria, and </p>

<p>17 patients (12.7%) expired due to recurrence (Table 2). </p>

<p>The 1-year, 3-year, and 5-year disease-free and overall </p>

<p>survival rates were 82.0%, 62.4%, and 51.0%, and 97.0%, </p>

<p>89.5%, and 77.3%, respectively (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>Young Ju Hong, et al. Small hepatocellular carcinoma 201 </p>

<p>Table 1. Clinical characteristics </p>

<p>Variables 
n (%) </p>

<p>Age (year, range) 
Gender (male/female) 
Etiology of liver disease 
Hepatitis B virus 
Hepatitis C virus 
Others 
Child Pugh classification 
A/B 
Cirrhosis 
Operative procedure 
Major resection 
Right hepatectomy 
Left hepatectomy 
Right or left extended 
hepatectomy 
Minor resection 
Lateral sectionectomy 
Posterior sectionectomy 
Bisegmentectomy 
Segmentectomy 
Partial hepatectomy 
Perioperative transfusion 
Postoperative mortality </p>

<p>53.1 (24-73) 
99 (73.9%)/35 (26.1%) </p>

<p>104 (77.6%) 
11 (8.2%) 
19 (14.2%) </p>

<p>133 (99.3%)/1 (0.7%) 
86 (64.2%) </p>

<p>32 (23.9%) 
21 (15.7%) 
9 (6.7%) 
2 (1.5%) </p>

<p>102 (76.1%) 
21 (15.7%) 
6 (4.5%) 
2 (1.5%) 
53 (39.6%) 
20 (14.9%) 
45 (48.9%) 
0 (0.0%) </p>

<p>Table 2. Long-term surgical outcomes after resection </p>

<p>Variables 
n (%) </p>

<p>Type of recurrence 
IH nodular (≤3 nodules) recurrence 
IH multiple (＞3 nodules) recurrence 
EH recurrence 
IH+EH recurrence 
Cause of death 
HCC recurrence 
Complication of liver cirrhosis without 
recurrence 
Unrelated </p>

<p>58 (43.3%) 
50 (86.2%) 
3 (5.2%) 
4 (6.9%) 
1 (1.7%) 
27 (20.1%) 
17 (63.0%) 
7 (25.9%) </p>

<p>3 (11.1%) </p>

<p>IH, intrahepatic; EH, extrahepatic; HCC, hepatocellular car-
cinoma. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Survival curves after liver resection for small hepatocellular carcinoma. (A) 1-, 3-, and 5-year disease-free survival rates 
were 82.0%, 62.4%, and 51.0%, respectively. (B) 1-, 3-, and 5-year overall survival rates were 97.0%, 89.5%, and 77.3%, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Prognostic factors of disease-free and overall 
survival 
Microscopic vascular invasion (Hazard ratio [HR]= </p>

<p>1.738; 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.015-2.977; p= </p>

<p>0.044), positivity for hepatitis B surface antigen or anti-</p>

<p>body to hepatitis C (HR=3.490; 95% CI, 1.258-9.682; 
p=0.016), and an ICG R15 of ＞10% (HR=1.737; 95% </p>

<p>CI, 1.019-2.960; p=0.042) were found to be significantly </p>

<p>and negatively correlated with disease-free survival by </p>

<p>both univariate and multivariate analyses (Table 3-5). 
A serum albumin of ＜3.5 g/dl, a serum platelet count </p>

<p>of ＜100,000/mm 
3 and non-anatomic resection were found </p>

<p>to be significantly associated with overall survival by uni-</p>

<p>variate analysis (Table 3, 4). However, only a platelet </p>

<p>count of ＜100,000/mm 
3 (HR=2.907; 95% CI, 1.341-</p>

<p>6.299; p=0.007) was found to be independently associated </p>

<p>with prognosis by multivariate analysis (Table 5). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Mazzaferro et al. 
13 first reported good results for liver </p>

<p>transplantation in selected patients, and several studies </p>

<p>conducted since have concluded that liver transplantation </p>

<p>is the better treatment option. 
9,14-17 Accordingly, liver </p>

<p>transplantation is now viewed as the treatment of choice </p>



<p>Table 3. Host and treatment related prognostic factors by univariate analysis </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>Disease-free survival 
Overall survival </p>

<p>No. of 
patients </p>

<p>5-year 
survival (%) 
p-value 
No. of 
patients </p>

<p>5-year 
survival (%) 
p-value </p>

<p>Age (years) 
≤60 
＞60 
Gender 
Male 
Female 
Etiology of liver disease 
HBV 
HCV 
Others 
Serum albumin (g/dl) 
≤3.5 
＞3.5 
AST (IU/L) 
≤50 
＞50 
ALT (IU/L) 
≤50 
＞50 
Liver cirrhosis 
No 
Yes 
Intraoperative bleeding (ml) 
≤1,000 
＞1,000 
Platelet count (mm 
3 ) 
≤100,000 
＞100,000 
ICG R15 (%) 
≤10 
＞10 
Perioperative transfusion 
No 
Yes 
Surgical margin (cm) 
≤1.0 
＞1.0 
Extent of resection 
Minor 
Major 
Type of resection 
Anatomic 
Non-anatomic </p>

<p>
101 
33 </p>

<p>99 
35 </p>

<p>104 
11 
19 </p>

<p>14 
120 </p>

<p>111 
23 </p>

<p>94 
40 </p>

<p>48 
86 </p>

<p>96 
38 </p>

<p>36 
98 </p>

<p>85 
49 </p>

<p>89 
45 </p>

<p>46 
88 </p>

<p>96 
38 </p>

<p>114 
20 </p>

<p>
51.5 
47 </p>

<p>49.6 
53.9 </p>

<p>45.8 
63.6 
74.6 </p>

<p>41.7 
52.2 </p>

<p>54.1 
37.9 </p>

<p>54.9 
41.9 </p>

<p>56.9 
48 </p>

<p>50.3 
52.2 </p>

<p>46.5 
52.3 </p>

<p>55 
44 </p>

<p>55.2 
42.9 </p>

<p>56.9 
47.9 </p>

<p>52.5 
43.4 </p>

<p>50.6 
52.6 </p>

<p>0.469 </p>

<p>
0.813 </p>

<p>
0.024 </p>



<p>0.108 </p>

<p>
0.323 </p>

<p>
0.359 </p>

<p>
0.054 </p>

<p>
0.698 </p>

<p>
0.111 </p>

<p>
0.049 </p>

<p>
0.36 </p>

<p>
0.936 </p>

<p>
0.875 </p>

<p>
0.28 </p>



<p>
101 
33 </p>

<p>99 
35 </p>

<p>104 
11 
19 </p>

<p>14 
120 </p>

<p>111 
23 </p>

<p>94 
40 </p>

<p>48 
86 </p>

<p>96 
38 </p>

<p>36 
98 </p>

<p>85 
49 </p>

<p>89 
45 </p>

<p>46 
88 </p>

<p>96 
38 </p>

<p>114 
20 </p>

<p>
75.3 
84 </p>

<p>76.8 
78.9 </p>

<p>73.3 
85.7 
94.1 </p>

<p>42.4 
82 </p>

<p>79.6 
68 </p>

<p>80.2 
70.2 </p>

<p>81.9 
74.8 </p>

<p>74.3 
85.5 </p>

<p>68.9 
81.5 </p>

<p>78.8 
68.9 </p>

<p>70.2 
57.1 </p>

<p>62.4 
65 </p>

<p>76.4 
80.9 </p>

<p>79.9 
64.5 </p>

<p>0.686 </p>

<p>
0.598 </p>

<p>
0.82 </p>



<p>0.032 </p>

<p>
0.154 </p>

<p>
0.598 </p>

<p>
0.222 </p>

<p>
0.668 </p>

<p>
0.005 </p>

<p>
0.075 </p>

<p>
0.875 </p>

<p>
0.183 </p>

<p>
0.899 </p>

<p>
0.013 </p>



<p>ICG R15=indocyanine green retention test at 15 minutes. HBV, hepatitis B virus; HCV, hepatitis C virus; AST, aspartate amino-
transferase; ALT, alanine aminotransferase. </p>

<p>for early HCC in Child-Pugh class B or C cirrhosis. </p>

<p>However, liver resection has also produced good results </p>

<p>in patients with small HCC; in fact, the 5-year overall sur-</p>

<p>vival rate in the present study was 77.3%. These results </p>

<p>show, although the disease-free survival rate for liver re-</p>

<p>section is poorer than of liver transplantation, that the </p>

<p>overall survival rates of liver resection and liver trans-</p>

<p>plantation are similar for patients with small HCC, and </p>

<p>suggest that liver resection is a good treatment option in </p>

<p>patients with small HCC. </p>

<p>18,19 </p>

<p>The merits and demerits of major versus minor resection </p>

<p>and anatomical resection versus non-anatomical resection </p>

<p>Young Ju Hong, et al. Small hepatocellular carcinoma 203 </p>

<p>Table 4. Tumor related prognostic factors by univariate analysis </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>Disease-free survival 
Overall survival </p>

<p>No. of 
patients </p>

<p>5-year 
survival (%) 
p-value 
No. of 
patients </p>

<p>5-year 
survival (%) 
p-value </p>

<p>Tumor size 
≤2 cm 
＞2 cm 
Microscopic vascular invasion 
Absent 
Present 
Edmondson-Steiner grade 
I-II 
III-IV 
Serum AFP (IU/ml) 
≤400 
＞400 </p>

<p>
52 
82 </p>

<p>92 
42 </p>

<p>92 
23 </p>

<p>107 
27 </p>

<p>
49.1 
52.2 </p>

<p>57.7 
39 </p>

<p>49 
60.3 </p>

<p>48.9 
60.8 </p>

<p>0.521 </p>

<p>
0.036 </p>

<p>
0.801 </p>

<p>
0.299 </p>



<p>
52 
82 </p>

<p>92 
42 </p>

<p>92 
23 </p>

<p>107 
27 </p>

<p>
75.9 
78.4 </p>

<p>80.9 
75.2 </p>

<p>75 
70.9 </p>

<p>78.4 
72.5 </p>

<p>0.786 </p>

<p>
0.256 </p>

<p>
0.621 </p>

<p>
0.201 </p>



<p>AFP, alpha-fetoprotein. </p>

<p>Table 5. Independent prognostic factors for disease-free and overall survival by multivariate analysis </p>

<p>Variable 
Coefficient 
Standard error 
p-value 
Hazard ratio (95% CI) </p>

<p>Disease-free survival 
Microscopic vascular invasion 
Etiology of liver disease (HBV vs. others) 
Overall survival 
Platelet count (≤100,000 vs. ＞100,000) </p>

<p>
0.553 
1.031 </p>

<p>1.067 </p>

<p>
0.275 
0.524 </p>

<p>0.395 </p>

<p>
0.044 
0.049 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>
1.738 (1.015-2.977) 
2.803 (1.003-7.832) </p>

<p>2.907 (1.341-6.299) </p>

<p>HBV, hepatitis B virus. </p>

<p>are still debated for small HCC. In the present study, 102 </p>

<p>(76.1%) patients underwent minor resection, including </p>

<p>non-anatomical resection (n=20, 14.9%), and operation </p>

<p>type was not found to be associated with disease-free or </p>

<p>overall survival. In a previous report, we reported that </p>

<p>non-anatomical resection for small HCC had no adverse </p>

<p>effect on disease-free survival, 
20 and other authors have </p>

<p>reported similarly. 
21,22 In fact, these authors also con-</p>

<p>cluded that minor and non-anatomical resection of small </p>

<p>HCC (except for deep-seated HCCs or HCCs located </p>

<p>alongside a major vessel) is an effective treatment option. 
Prognosis after HCC resection has been shown to be </p>

<p>affected by tumor invasiveness and underlying liver </p>

<p>function. 
23-25 According to our results, the long-term prog-</p>

<p>nosis of patients with a single small HCC is more asso-</p>

<p>ciated with underlying liver function than invasiveness. </p>

<p>Microscopic vascular invasion and positivity for hepatitis </p>

<p>B surface antigen may develop intrahepatic metastasis and </p>

<p>de novo carcinogenesis, respectively, after resection, but </p>

<p>in the present study, the majority of recurrences (n=53, </p>

<p>91.4%) were confined to the remaining liver. In addition, </p>

<p>50 patients developed nodular recurrence, which was well </p>

<p>controlled by multimodality treatments and had a better </p>

<p>prognosis than other recurrence patterns. These ob-</p>

<p>servations suggest that long-term prognosis is associated </p>

<p>with liver function and the extent to which the liver can </p>

<p>resist recurrence given aggressive treatment. 
However, according to our data, overall survival rate at </p>

<p>5 years after resection decreased, indicating that liver </p>

<p>transplantation was eventually required because of the </p>

<p>progression of underlying liver disease or HCC recur-</p>

<p>rence. Salvage liver transplantation provides an alternative </p>

<p>in patients with recurrence after liver resection. However, </p>

<p>the initial experiences with salvage liver transplantation </p>

<p>were relatively poor, in which operative mortality was </p>

<p>high (23.5%) and survival was unfavorable, but many of </p>

<p>the of patients had a tumor beyond the Milan criteria. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>It has been reported that salvage liver transplantation is </p>

<p>feasible in 75-80% of patients after liver resection, 
27 and </p>

<p>in the present study, salvage liver transplantation was </p>

<p>found to be feasible in 50 of 53 patients (94.3%). It was </p>

<p>recently reported that salvage liver transplantation can be </p>



<p>performed with acceptable morbidity and mortality rates </p>

<p>and produce results comparable to those of primary liver </p>

<p>transplantation. 
28,29 Furthermore, in one these previous </p>

<p>studies, patients that underwent liver resection or liver </p>

<p>transplantation showed similar survival rates by in-</p>

<p>tention-to-treat analysis. 
29 However, salvage rates of only </p>

<p>up to 20% have been reported by others. 
29-31 Thus, further </p>

<p>studies are needed before salvage liver transplantation can </p>

<p>be generally adopted. 
Liver resection has been adopted as the primary treat-</p>

<p>ment modality for small HCC because its overall survival </p>

<p>rate is comparable to that of liver transplantation. </p>

<p>Moreover, because salvage liver transplantation produces </p>

<p>attractive results, liver resection, including minor and </p>

<p>non-anatomical resection, can be chosen as a primary </p>

<p>treatment option for patients with small HCC, even for </p>

<p>those with risk factors of a poor prognosis. </p>



<p>Young Ju Hong, et al. Small hepatocellular carcinoma 205 </p>



</text></tei>