<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4122291" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Quantum-confined nanostructures are considered 'artificial atoms' because the wave-
functions of their charge carriers resemble those of atomic orbitals. For multiple-domain 
heterostructures, however, carrier wavefunctions are more complex and still not well 
understood. We have prepared a unique series of cation-exchanged Hg x Cd 1 À x Te quantum 
dots (QDs) and seven epitaxial core-shell QDs and measured their first and second exciton 
peak oscillator strengths as a function of size and chemical composition. A major finding is 
that carrier locations can be quantitatively mapped and visualized during shell growth or 
cation exchange simply using absorption transition strengths. These results reveal that 
a broad range of quantum heterostructures with different internal structures and band 
alignments exhibit distinct carrier localization patterns that can be used to further improve 
the performance of optoelectronic devices and enhance the brightness of QD probes for 
bioimaging. </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>emiconductor quantum dots (QDs) have recently 
attracted broad attention for applications in bioimaging, 
light-emitting devices, photovoltaics and quantum 
computing 1-10 . Compared with bulk semiconductor crystals, 
these nanocrystals exhibit unique optical and electronic 
properties, including size-tunable bandgaps and fluorescence 
emission, ultrafast charge-transfer rates and decreased lasing 
thresholds 9-17 . These properties largely arise from the quantum 
confinement effect, in which electronic charge carriers (electrons 
and holes) are spatially confined because of the small crystal size, 
similar to a spherical 'particle in a box.' This confinement results 
in quantized electronic energy levels that are analogous to discrete 
electronic transitions of atoms in the gas phase. However, this 
analogy becomes much more complex for quantum-confined 
heterostructures containing multiple chemical or structural 
domains. In these composite nanomaterials, separate regions 
have distinct potential energies that shape the spatial distribution 
and transport behaviour of different charge carriers. For example, 
in core-shell heterostructures with a 'type-I' band alignment, the 
potential energy of the electron and hole is lowest in the same 
domain (for example, the core) and thus the electron and 
hole are colocalized, resulting in a high probability of radiative 
recombination and a fluorescence quantum efficiency that can 
approach unity 18-20 . In contrast, in core-shell heterostructures 
with 'type-II' band alignments, the potential energy minima for 
the electron and hole are in different domains, resulting in charge 
carrier separation, longer excited state lifetimes and broad 
wavelength tunability 21 . It is thus critically important to 
determine and control the spatial distribution patterns of 
charge carriers; however, at present there are few experimental 
approaches available for such fundamental studies. Scanning 
tunnelling microscopy with spectroscopy has been used to image 
specific wavefunctions but the technique is very challenging and 
has low throughput 22 . Computational modelling studies also 
provide insight; however, alone they are of only limited utility as 
continuum models do not account for microscopic structural 
attributes and immense computational power is needed to 
account for atomistic effects when large numbers of atoms are 
involved 23 . 
Here we report a simple semiempirical method based on 
quantum mechanical models of the effective mass approximation 
(EMA) and steady-state optical absorption measurements for 
mapping the wavefunctions of charge carriers in quantum-
confined heterostructures. Specifically, we have prepared a unique 
series of cation-exchanged Hg x Cd 1 À x Te heterostructures, for 
which quantum mechanical calculations are simplified and the </p>

<p>electronic transition probabilities are solely dependent on the 
electron-hole overlap integral. For this series of heterostructures, 
we have experimentally measured the 1st and 2nd exciton 
transition intensities (oscillator strengths) as a function of both 
particle size and chemical composition. The results show that the 
oscillator strength of the 1st exciton peak is dependent on the 
relative electron-hole overlap, while the intensity of second 
exciton peak measures the absolute spatial localizations of the 
electron and hole. We have further carried out extensive work, 
both experimental and theoretical, on seven common core/shell 
heterostructures, demonstrating that the relationship between 
electronic transition strengths and charge-carrier distributions is 
generalizable to a broad range of core-shell and alloyed 
nanostructures. These fundamental insights are critical for 
patterning the shapes and spatial locations of charge carrier 
wavefunctions and for funneling oscillator strength into specific 
optical transitions, which will help to exploit the novel properties 
of quantum nanostructures for future use in optoelectronic 
devices, quantum computing, solar energy conversion as well as 
bioimaging. </p>

<p>Results 
Wavefunction modelling. In a single-electron hydrogenic atom 
(for example, H, He þ , Li 2 þ ) in the gas phase, the electron energy 
levels are quantized, leading to a discrete set of electronic orbitals 
(s, p, d, and so on) with distinct absorption transitions. In 
semiconductor QDs, the crystalline lattice of atoms provides a 
potential energy well for excited-state charge carriers (electrons 
and holes), which have analogous wavefunction shapes. Figure 1a 
depicts the lowest-energy electronic energy states for the electron 
(1S) and hole (1S) in addition to the next highest energy state of 
the hole (2S) in a pure cadmium telluride (CdTe) QD; the shapes 
resemble the corresponding 1s and 2s atomic orbitals. Figure 1b 
depicts plots of the wavefunctions (c) and radial distribution 
functions (RDF, c 
2 r 
2 ) of these carriers based on the EMA 24 . The 
1S electron exhibits greater spatial confinement than the 1S hole 
because the effective mass of an electron (m e ¼ 0.090) is much 
smaller than that of a hole (m HH , heavy-hole effective mass is 
equal to 0.83; see Supplementary Table 1). As a result, the 1S 
electron density is distributed further away from the QD centre 
than the 1S hole state (see RDF plots). 
Figure 1c shows a typical electronic absorption spectrum for a 
QD composed of II-VI materials (here CdTe), showing multiple 
distinct electronic transitions. Through comparisons with 
quantum mechanical models, the absorption peaks have been </p>

<p>1S(h) 1S(e) </p>

<p>2S(h) 1S(e) </p>

<p>Energy (eV) </p>

<p>Absorption </p>

<p>Radius (nm) 
Radius (nm) 
Radius (nm) </p>

<p>2S hole 
1S hole 
1S electron 
Quantum dot 
1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>2 r 2 
2 r 2 
2 r 2 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>1.8 2.0 2.2 2.4 2.6 2.8 3.0 3.2 </p>

<p>CB </p>

<p>VB </p>

<p>2.05 eV 
2.2 eV </p>

<p>1S(e) </p>

<p>1S(h) 
2S(h) </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Quantum mechanical modelling of charge carriers in quantum dot artificial atoms. (a) Cross-sectional views of a 3.8-nm CdTe quantum dot 
and its 1S(e), 1S(h) and 2S(h) wavefunctions; (b) corresponding wavefunction (c) and radial distribution function (c 
2 r 
2 ) plots; and (c) steady-state 
absorption spectrum showing the 1st exciton 1S(h)-1S(e) and the 2nd exciton 2S(h)-1S(e) transitions. The energy band diagram in the inset depicts 
these absorption transitions between quantum-confined electron (e) and hole (h) energy states. Black lines indicate potential energy wells in 
the CB and VB. For clarity, energy levels are not drawn to scale and higher energy levels are omitted. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 5:4506 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>assigned to transitions between specific electronic energy levels 
(Supplementary Fig. 1 and Supplementary Table 2). The 1st 
transition, 1S(h)-1S(e), arises from light absorption by an 
electron in the highest energy valence band (VB) state to 
transition to the lowest energy conduction band (CB) state 25,26 . 
This transition is also known as the 1st exciton peak, as it results 
in a bound electron-hole pair, a ground-state exciton. In the 
resulting 1S(e)1S(h) exciton, both carriers occupy 1S 
wavefunctions that substantially overlap in space. The 2nd 
exciton peak, 2S(h)-1S(e), arises from the excitation of an 
electron in the next highest VB level, again to the lowest energy 
CB level 27,28 . This results in a 1S(e)2S(h) exciton in which the 
hole occupies a 2S wavefunction. Both the 1S(h) and 2S(h) 
wavefunctions are spherically symmetric; however, the 2S(h) has 
a spherical nodal surface with zero electronic density separating 
regions of opposite polarity, as indicated by red and blue colours 
in Fig. 1a,b. Therefore, whereas the 1S(e)1S(h) exciton has strong 
electron-hole overlap, the 1S(e)2S(h) exciton overlap is small 
because of contributions from both constructive and destructive 
interference between the 1S electron and the two domains of 
opposite polarity of the 2S hole. As discussed below, the first and 
second exciton wavefunctions are greatly influenced by the 
nanocrystal structure and composition, and together can be used 
to map the spatial distributions of charge carriers in quantum 
nanostructures. </p>

<p>Electronic transitions and oscillator strengths. We are inter-
ested in measuring the oscillator strengths of the first and second 
excitonic transitions. Figure 2 depicts the two-step process to 
extract these values from QD electronic absorption spectra. The 
first step is to determine the electronic transition energies from 
often broad or apparently featureless absorption spectra, and then 
reconstruct the spectrum from a sum of Gaussian peaks, with 
integrated areas corresponding to transition oscillator strengths. 
Transition energy extraction is limited by spectral overlap 
between adjacent peaks. Peak width is a function of sample 
homogeneity (size, shape and composition), transition energy and 
homogeneous broadening effects. As a result, significant peak 
overlap is observed even for QD samples that are considered 
structurally homogeneous by current standards. Moreover, even if 
the spectral peaks are distinct, their maxima do not necessarily 
correspond with the true peak energy because contributing 
shoulders from neighbouring peaks can shift the observed peak 
centroid. To overcome this problem, we have used differential 
absorption spectroscopy (DAS) for mathematical narrowing of 
convolved peaks: even order derivatives (for example, 2nd, 4th 
derivatives) have substantially narrower peak profiles than those 
of the zeroth-order spectra (see Supplementary Methods for more 
details). 
On the basis of analyses of synthetic spectra of QDs with 
known Gaussian transition energies, we have determined the 
spectral parameters for which transition energy and oscillator 
strength can be accurately measured. Figure 3a,b shows synthetic 
spectra of two sizes of CdTe nanocrystals with a range of size 
dispersions, with vertical lines indicating input transition 
energies, numbered 1-6. We extracted the transition energies 
using the 4th derivative: Fig. 3c,d shows that the first exciton 
energy (blue curves) is at least 99% accurate (within 20-30 meV 
depending on size) even when the size dispersion is as large as 
20% relative s.d. in diameter (Dd Á d À 1 ) . The determined energy 
of the second exciton transitions using DAS is at least 99% 
accurate for Dd Á d À 1 o11% (red curves, open circle markers). 
Spectral reconstruction through least squares fitting further 
improves the transition energy accuracy. Thus, we find that it is 
not necessary to determine the peak energy with very high </p>

<p>accuracy but rather it is more important to determine the 
accurate number of peaks within a specific spectral window (see 
Supplementary Discussion). The extracted energy provides an 
'initial guess' for the energy; by allowing the energies to shift, the 
curve-fitting algorithm finds the original peaks. We show that </p>

<p>Energy (eV) </p>

<p>Absorption </p>

<p>Reconstructed spectrum </p>

<p>Energy (eV) </p>

<p>DAS spectra </p>

<p>Energy (eV) </p>

<p>Experimental spectrum </p>

<p>Absorption </p>

<p>1.8 
2.3 
2.8 
3.3 </p>

<p>1.8 
2.3 
2.8 
3.3 </p>

<p>1.8 
2.3 
2.8 
3.3 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>A/dE </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Mathematical extraction of electronic transition energies 
and oscillator strengths for quantum-confined nanostructures. (a) An 
experimental spectrum is first subject to mathematical line narrowing 
through differentiation with respect to energy, resulting in differential 
absorption spectra. (b) Fourth derivatives are shown: the top is the original 
differential spectrum and the lower spectrum has been flattened to reveal 
lower intensity features. Vertical dotted lines indicate observed transition 
energies. (c) Using these energies, least squares fitting is used to 
reconstruct the original spectrum from a sum of Gaussian peaks with initial 
guesses for transition energies derived from differential absorption 
spectroscopy analysis. Integrated peak areas correspond to oscillator 
strengths. </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 5:4506 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>even when the extracted 4th derivative is inaccurate by 90 meV, 
the fitting algorithm finds the original peak, within several meV 
(compare the open and closed circle markers in Fig. 3c,d), and the 
resulting energies are at least 99% accurate for Dd Á d À 1 r15%. 
We have also investigated whether experimental band narrowing 
through photoluminescence excitation (PLE) spectroscopy, rather 
than through DAS, could improve the resolution of contributing 
absorption peaks. As shown in Supplementary Fig. 2, the low 
energy peaks were similar to those of the DAS spectra; this is 
consistent with previous PLE spectral analysis of CdTe nano-
crystals by Zhong et al. 29 , as well as with theoretical predictions 
by Efros et al. 27 (see Supplementary Fig. 1). 
Figure 3e,f depicts the error in calculated oscillator strength of 
the first three transitions of these nanocrystals, determined 
through least squares fitting. At low size dispersions, all spectra 
are accurately fit, but deviations arise with increasing size 
dispersion. Higher accuracy is obtained for larger nanocrystals 
compared with smaller nanocrystals with the same size dispersion, 
as peaks are less 'hidden' by the first exciton for larger sizes. The 
1st and 2nd exciton oscillator strengths are found to be accurate 
(within 5% of the input value) for 3.0-nm nanocrystals with </p>

<p>Dd Á d À 1 r12% and for 6.7-nm nanocrystals with Dd Á d À 1 o14%. 
The corresponding spectra are marked in red in Fig. 3a,b. It is 
surprising that even for these somewhat featureless spectra, the 
subtle changes in curvature provide sufficient information about 
the underlying peaks, which allow us to determine the number 
and strength of peaks. All QDs analysed in this paper have spectral 
bandwidths narrower than these threshold values, such that their 
transition energies and oscillator strengths are determined with 
Z99% and Z95% accuracy, respectively. </p>

<p>Core-shell and alloyed heterostructures. To understand how the 
shapes of potential energy wells in complex heterostructures 
dictate carrier wavefunction shapes and oscillator strengths, we 
have carried out systematic experimental and theoretical studies 
of core-shell and cation-exchanged QDs. We first discuss cation-
exchanged Hg x Cd 1 À x Te heterostructures as a model system 
because they are nearly free from lattice strain and quantum 
mechanical calculations are simplified. For colloidal synthesis we 
start with monodisperse CdTe nanocrystals with tunable size and 
exchange Cd 2 þ ions in the lattice with Hg 2 þ ions as previously </p>

<p>Oscillator strength 
relative error 
Oscillator strength 
relative error </p>

<p>Energy (eV) 
Energy (eV) </p>

<p>Absorption transitions: </p>

<p>6.7 nm CdTe </p>

<p>Energy (eV) </p>

<p>1.8 
2.1 
2.4 
1.5 </p>

<p>Absorption </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>0.14 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>Trans: 1 2 3 4 5 
6 
Δd·d </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>Energy (eV) </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>0.12 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>Δd·d </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>Absorption </p>

<p>3.0 nm CdTe </p>

<p>Trans: </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.9 </p>

<p>1.8 </p>

<p>1.7 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Trans: </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2.8 </p>

<p>2.7 </p>

<p>2.6 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2.4 </p>

<p>2.3 </p>

<p>2.2 </p>

<p>Trans: 
Trans: </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3 
2 
1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>-1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>-1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.06 
0.10 
0.14 
0.18 
0.06 </p>

<p>1.8 
2.3 
2.8 
3.3 </p>

<p>Trans: 1 2 3 4 5 6 </p>

<p>0.10 
0.14 
0.18 </p>

<p>0.06 
0.10 
0.14 
0.18 
0.06 
0.10 
0.14 
0.18 
Δd·d </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>Δd·d </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>Δd·d </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>Δd·d </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>Detected, 
Input, 
L.S. fit </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Effect of quantum dot size dispersion on the extraction accuracy of electronic transition energies and oscillator strengths Spectra were 
generated from sums of Gaussian curves with contributing noise and widened according to specific dispersions of diameter (Dd Á d À 1 ). a,b show the spectra 
that were generated from Gaussian peaks with energies noted by vertical dotted lines (transitions 1-6). c,d show peaks that were extracted from 
the 4th derivatives of these spectra (coloured lines with open circles), and then fit to the original spectrum (coloured lines with closed circles), in addition 
to the input energy for each peak (dotted black lines). e,f depict the relative oscillator strengths of the 1st (blue), 2nd (red) and 3rd (green) 
absorption transitions with size dispersion. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 5:4506 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>reported 30 . Energy-dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (EDX) and 
inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (ICP-MS) 
demonstrate the substitution of cadmium for mercury 
(Supplementary Figs 3 and 4). Cubic CdTe and HgTe are fully 
miscible as a ternary alloy and have nearly identical lattice 
constants (a CdTe ¼ 6.48 Å, a HgTe ¼ 6.46 Å); therefore, the bond 
lengths and crystallinity do not substantially change with mercury 
exchange, as verified by powder X-ray diffraction (Supplementary 
Fig. 5) and transmission electron microscopy (Supplementary 
Figs 6 and 7). Large CdTe nanocrystals form core-shell 
structures, as determined by Raman scattering (Supplementary 
Fig. 8): the CdTe phonon modes remain after substantial cation 
exchange but are broadened because of reduced domain size, and 
new broad scattering modes arise corresponding to those of 
HgTe. Furthermore, a kinetic analysis of exchange reactions 
reveals that for larger nanocrystals (45 nm), exchange occurs 
rapidly (minutes) until a monolayer has been formed, after which 
the exchange rate is substantially reduced (Supplementary Fig. 9). 
This is not the case for smaller nanocrystals, for which exchange 
beyond a monolayer is rapid; these particles have a dynamic 
structure with significantly higher ion mobility that leads to 
homogeneous alloying, as described below. 
Cation exchange leads to significant alterations to the optical 
spectra because of the very different bandgap energies and 
electron-hole masses of CdTe and HgTe. These changes depend 
on whether the final structure is a core-shell or alloy (Fig. 4a). 
The bulk bandgap energy of CdTe is 1.5 eV, whereas that of HgTe 
is À 0.15 eV (a near-zero bandgap in which the bottom of the CB 
is almost aligned with the top of the VB). Thus, as shown in 
Fig. 4b (energy band structures based on EMA calculations), </p>

<p>cation substitution of Cd 2 þ by Hg 2 þ in CdTe nanocrystals leads 
to a decrease in bandgap energy and altered degree of carrier 
confinement. For homogeneous alloys, the CB shifts to lower 
energy and the VB shifts to higher energy. This is not the case for 
the core-shell products, for which two separate domains emerge: 
the electron now has a lower energy level in the shell region that 
results in a substantial reduction in bandgap energy. Although the 
hole well is also deepened, the 1S and 2S hole levels do not 
significantly change in energy relative to the CdTe nanocrystals or 
redistribute to the shell because the small effective mass of the 
hole in HgTe (m HH ¼ 0.03) offsets changes in potential well 
depth. Thus, the electron is redistributed to the shell region, 
whereas hole states remain distributed throughout the nanocrys-
tal, resulting in a pseudo-type II band alignment with a spatially 
indirect bandgap. 
The EMA predicts that the potential energy shapes for the two 
possible products will yield substantial differences in carrier 
wavefunction shapes for the 1st and 2nd excitons (Fig. 4c,d) that 
will lead to alterations in exciton overlaps that can be directly 
measured by changes in absorption oscillator strength. For core 
CdTe nanocrystals, the 1S(e) and 1S(h) states of the 1st exciton 
initially strongly overlap (overlap integral F 1 ¼ 0.94, Fig. 4c), 
whereas for the 2nd exciton, 1S(e) overlaps both with regions of 
negative and positive polarity of 2S(h), yielding a small net 
overlap (F 2 ¼ 0.25, Fig. 4d). If the resulting Hg x Cd 1 À x Te 
nanocrystal is a homogeneous alloy, the overlaps do not 
substantially change compared with the CdTe nanocrystal 
(F 1 ¼ 0.94, F 2 ¼ 0.27). However, for the core-shell CdTe/HgTe 
nanocrystals, the electron migrates to the shell region and the 
hole remains distributed throughout the nanocrystal so the 1st </p>

<p>h 
e 
h 
e </p>

<p>1.5 eV </p>

<p>-0.15 eV </p>

<p>CdTe/HgTe </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>h 
e </p>

<p>0.80 eV </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>=0.25 </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>1.5 eV </p>

<p>CdTe </p>

<p>or </p>

<p>Hg </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>Cd </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>Radius (nm) </p>

<p>Energy </p>

<p>Nanocrystal 
structure 
1 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 
1 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 
1 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>2 
2 </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=0.94 </p>

<p>=0.66 
=0.56 </p>

<p>=0.27 </p>

<p>=0.94 </p>

<p>1st exciton 
2nd exciton 
Band structure </p>

<p>Hg x Cd 1-x Te </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Structure and charge carrier properties of CdTe QDs and cation-exchanged Hg x Cd 1 À x Te QDs. (a) Schematic illustrations of CdTe QDs, 
homogeneous alloy Hg x Cd 1 À x Te QDs, or core-shell CdTe/HgTe QDs generated through Cd 2 þ replacement by Hg 2 þ . (b) Energy band diagrams showing the 
valence and conduction bands (grey), potential energy wells (black lines) and quantum-confined kinetic energy levels (red lines) of electrons and 
holes in each QD, as calculated using the effective mass approximation. (c,d) RDF (c 
2 r 
2 , nm À 1 ) plots of the electron (e) and hole (h) for the 1st and 2nd 
excitons. Wavefunction overlap integrals (f) are also provided. Constructive overlap is schematically depicted as green and destructive overlap is black. </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 5:4506 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>exciton overlap decreases (to F 1 ¼ 0.66) and the 2nd exciton 
overlap increases (to F 2 ¼ 0.56) because the electron moves away 
from the 2S hole node to increase overlap with a region of like 
polarity and reduce overlap with regions of opposite polarity. 
Thus, for cation-exchanged core-shell nanostructures, the 1st 
exciton transition strength is predicted to decrease and the 2nd 
exciton strength will increase (more than twofold); these will not 
substantially change for an alloyed structure. This decrease in 
oscillator strength of the 1st exciton peak has been widely 
reported for type-II heterostructures 21,31,32 . However, the 2nd 
exciton peak has not been explored in this context but should be a 
more specific and sensitive 'reporter' for localization because of 
the capacity to either decrease or increase depending on small 
shifts in wavefunction distribution. Whereas the 1st exciton peak 
oscillator strength can reveal a relative change in electron-hole 
overlap, changes in the 2nd exciton peak provide a sensitive probe 
for the absolute spatial localization of the electron or hole in the 
core or shell. 
We compared predictions from the EMA model with 
experimental data from CdTe-Hg x Cd 1 À x Te cation-exchanged 
nanocrystals. Figure 5a shows that mercury exchange of 3.2-nm 
CdTe QDs leads to a monotonic shift of the absorption spectra to 
lower energies, and the major excitonic transitions remain 
discrete and with similar intensities and bandwidths (the molar 
QD concentration is identical for all spectra plotted on the same 
chart herein), indicating uniform cation exchange across the 
nanocrystal ensemble. Different trends were observed when the 
same experiment was performed on larger nanocrystals (6.2 nm, 
Fig. 5b): the 1st exciton transition initially exhibited little change 
in energy while absorption at higher energies increased. In 
addition, the 2nd exciton peak increased in intensity and merged 
with the 1st exciton peak. This trend was similar for 8.4-nm 
nanocrystals (Supplementary Fig. 10). 
We extracted absorption transition energies and transition 
oscillator strengths for these Hg x Cd 1 À x Te QDs, monitoring each 
specific transition that was originally assigned in CdTe as we 
incrementally increased mercury content, traced by elemental 
analysis (see Supplementary Fig. 4). For small nanocrystals 
(o5 nm), all of the CdTe core transitions shifted to lower 
energies nearly linearly with increasing Hg content 
(Supplementary Fig. 11a). This is expected for homogeneous 
alloys with similar VB structures, that is, common-anion alloys 
(the VB predominantly arises from the anion p orbitals). In 
contrast, larger nanocrystals exhibited nonlinear transition trends 
with increasing Hg content, with several peaks becoming too 
closely spaced in energy to be distinguished (Supplementary 
Fig. 11b). To reconstruct the band edges for oscillator strength 
calculation, at least four peaks were used for small nanocrystals 
and at least seven peaks were used for large nanocrystals (see 
Supplementary Methods) and the oscillator strengths of the 1st 
and 2nd exciton transitions (f 1 and f 2 , respectively) were 
calculated from the integrated peak areas 33 . Figure 5c shows 
oscillator strengths per QD for pure CdTe nanocrystals (x ¼ 0, no 
mercury) with diameters between 2 and 12 nm. The oscillator 
strength of the 1st exciton transition is nearly constant with size 
(f 1 ¼ 1.33 ± 0.10), as predicted by the EMA (Fig. 4b). These values 
are in close agreement with those found previously for CdTe 
nanocrystals 34 , and follow trends previously observed for CdS 35  and InAs 36 . 
Unlike f 1 , f 2 is almost linearly proportional to diameter 
(f 2 ¼ 0.239d nm À 1 ) for sizes smaller than 9 nm. The increasing 
value of f 2 relative to f 1 with diameter is apparent when 
comparing the spectra of 3.2 and 6.2 nm CdTe nanocrystals in 
Fig. 5a,b. A trend of increasing f 2 with size was previously 
reported for CdSe nanocrystals by Klimov 33 ; however, we are not 
aware of other experimental investigations of f 2 for colloidal QDs. </p>

<p>A two-band interacting EMA model for these transition oscillator 
strengths shows a similar trend in Fig. 5d. The disproportionate 
concentration of oscillator strength in the 1S(h)-1S(e) transition 
for small nanocrystals compared with the 2S(h)-1S(e) and 
higher energy transitions is a result of the near-independence of 
the 1st exciton overlap with QD size. This is in contrast to the 2nd 
exciton, for which small changes in electron or hole confinement 
lead to substantial changes in net overlap because of the presence 
of the 2S hole node. It is notable that the experimental trend in 
the 2nd exciton oscillator strength could not be reproduced in 
EMA models unless band interactions were taken into account. 
The resulting wavefunctions showed that interactions become 
important for larger sizes, as the relatively unconfined 2S hole 
attracts the 1S electron closer to the centre of the nanocrystal as 
the node spreads farther from the centre, increasing net overlap 
with increasing size. 
We note that the CdTe nanocrystals used in this work are 
slightly prolate (with an aspect ratio of B1.3). This would result 
in anisotropic wavefunctions for which one dimension is 
elongated relatively to the other two dimensions. However, 
Norris et al. 37 have shown that for nonspherical CdSe 
nanocrystals (also with an aspect ratio near 1.3), the transition 
energy and peak splitting are largely unaffected by this degree of 
anisotropy. For nonsperical CdTe, EMA calculations show a 
roughly fivefold smaller splitting energy compared with that of 
prolate CdSe 38 . This result is consistent with our data, in that we 
observed no spectral peak splitting or transition energy shifts in 
comparison with predictions from theory and previous PLE 
spectroscopic results (Supplementary Fig. 1) 27,29 . 
For the Hg x Cd 1 À x Te cation-exchanged QDs, trends in f 1 and f 2 
with mercury content were strongly dependent on nanocrystal 
size and the cation exchange rate. We investigated three cation 
exchange methods: (1) in water using mercury-thioglycerol 
complexes, (2) in nonpolar solvents using mercury octanethiolate 
and (3) in nonpolar solvents using highly reactive mercury 
acetate. Methods 1 and 2 allowed slow, controlled exchange 
yielding spectral shifts over hours to days, whereas method 3 
resulted in a rapid spectral red-shift in just seconds; we designate 
these two exchange regimes 'slow' or 'fast.' For large nanocrystals, 
the result of fast and slow exchange was similar: f 1 decreased and 
f 2 increased with increasing mercury content (Fig. 5e). This trend 
was anticipated for core-shell nanocrystals: in Fig. 5f, solid lines 
depict EMA predictions for core-shell nanocrystals and dotted 
lines show homogeneous alloys, which change very little with 
increasing mercury content. For small nanocrystals, slow and fast 
exchange modes were markedly different. For slow exchange, f 1 
and f 2 only changed slightly with increasing mercury content 
(Supplementary Fig. 12), in accord with the formation of a 
homogeneous alloy, whereas for fast exchange, f 1 decreased and f 2 
increased, reflecting a core-shell structure. For fast exchange, f 1 
and f 2 slowly approached their original values, suggesting 
redistribution of mercury to the core and suggesting that the 
cation exchange process is kinetically controlled by a balance 
between surface exchange and diffusion/alloying within the 
nanocrystal, which is consistent with our kinetic exchange 
experiments (Supplementary Fig. 9). </p>

<p>Diagrams of charge carrier localization. We next determined 
how oscillator strength analyses could be used as a generalizable 
tool for a wide variety of core-shell QDs. Validation with cation-
exchanged Hg x Cd 1 À x Te was a critical step because the photo-
physics of this system are simple: the total number of oscillators 
(that is, atoms or bonding electrons) and the size does not change, 
and thus f is solely dependent on the electron-hole overlap 
integral. In addition, this system is nearly free from lattice strain </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 5:4506 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>because CdTe and HgTe have similar cubic lattice constants. 
This is important because strain is expected to strongly 
impact the optical and electronic properties of lattice-mismatched 
core-shell systems because of alterations to bond lengths that 
shift electronic energy bands, warp bands at interfaces and split 
degenerate hole states 11,32 . Typically, core-shell materials are 
grown through epitaxial deposition of a shell on a preformed 
core, such that the total number of oscillators and the nanocrystal 
size change, and strain effects are often dramatic when using 
lattice-mismatched materials 11,31 . To examine these effects with 
respect to f 1 and f 2 , we prepared seven core-shell nanocrystals </p>

<p>starting from highly homogeneous cores: CdTe/CdSe, CdSe/CdS, 
CdSe/ZnTe, CdSe/ZnS, CdS/CdSe, CdS/ZnSe and CdS/ZnS. 
Similar to CdTe, the 1st and 2nd exciton transitions of CdS 
and CdSe were previously assigned as the 1S(h)-1S(e) and 
2S(h)-1S(e) transitions, respectively. So that we did not have to 
calculate absolute oscillator strengths, we simply calculated 
relative oscillator strengths (ROSs) per QD, defined as: </p>

<p>f 
rel ¼ 
f core=shell 
f core 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>EMA calculations 
Experimental data </p>

<p>Oscillator strength (rel.) </p>

<p>EMA calculations </p>

<p>Oscillator strength (abs.) </p>

<p>Experimental data </p>

<p>Size dependence: CdTe </p>

<p>Energy (eV) </p>

<p>Absorption </p>

<p>Increasing Hg </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.3 
1.5 
1.7 
1.9 </p>

<p>Absorption </p>

<p>Energy (eV) </p>

<p>Increasing Hg </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>2S(h) 
2S(h) 
1S(e) 
1S(e) 
1S(h) 
1S(h) </p>

<p>Diameter (nm) </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
6 
8 
10 12 
Diameter (nm) </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
6 
8 
10 12 
0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>f 2 </p>

<p>f 2 </p>

<p>f 1 
f 1 </p>

<p>f 2 </p>

<p>f 2 </p>

<p>f 1 
0.5 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0 
0 
0.05 0.10 0.15 0.20 
Oscillator strength (rel.) 
Oscillator strength (rel.) </p>

<p>x (Hg x Cd 1-x Te) 
x (Hg x Cd 1-x Te) </p>

<p>0 
0.1 
0.2 
0.3 
0.4 </p>

<p>1.3 
1.8 
2.8 
2.3 </p>

<p>1S(e) 
1S(e) </p>

<p>6.2 nm Hg x Cd 1-x Te 
3.2 nm Hg x Cd 1-x Te </p>

<p>Composition dependence: Hg x Cd 1-x Te </p>

<p>f 1 </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Optical absorption spectra during Hg x Cd 1 À x Te cation exchange. Mercury cation exchange was performed on CdTe cores with a diameter of 
(a) 3.2 nm or (b) 6.2 nm. For 3.2-nm nanocrystals, absorption increases substantially at high energy with little change in band-edge oscillator strength. For 
the 6.2-nm nanocrystals, the 2nd exciton peak becomes dominant with increasing mercury content. (c) Experimental oscillator strengths of the 1st exciton 
transition (f 1 , blue) and 2nd exciton transition (f 2 , red) for CdTe QDs with sizes from B2 to 12 nm diameter, in absolute units. (d) Theoretical EMA 
calculations (plotted in relative units). (e) Experimental oscillator strengths of the 1st and 2nd exciton transitions for large CdTe nanocrystals (6.2 nm) after 
cation exchange. (f) Theoretical EMA calculations (plotted in relative units). For plots in c-f, solid curves show values for core-shell nanocrystals and 
dotted lines indicate values for homogeneous alloys. Error bars are s.d. </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 5:4506 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>f rel was calculated from concentration-normalized absorption 
spectra obtained during shell growth. Spectra were reconstructed 
through least-squares fitting of a sum of Gaussian curves to 
determine f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>1 and f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>2 . As shown in Fig. 6, trends were clear for 
specific electron-hole localization regimes with just 0-1.2 ML of 
shell growth, and match expected oscillator strength relationships 
based on the EMA model. Homoepitaxy (simply growing CdTe 
on CdTe cores, Fig. 6a,e) did not alter f </p>

<p>rel 
1 </p>

<p>but resulted in a 
monotonic increase in f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>2 , in accord with Fig. 5c,d. Type I QDs 
with strong localization of the electron and hole in the core 
showed little change in f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>1 and f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>2 with increasing shell thickness 
(CdSe/ZnS, panels b,f). Type II h/e QDs with core-localized hole 
and shell-localized electron showed a strong decrease in f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>1 and a 
strong increase in f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>2 with increasing shell thickness (CdTe/CdSe, 
panels c,g), much like CdTe/HgTe nanocrystals with large cores. 
Type II e/h QDs with core-localized electron and shell-localized 
hole showed little change in f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>1 and a strong decrease in f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>2 with 
increasing shell thickness (CdSe/ZnTe, panels d,h) as the 2S hole 
migrates towards the shell, increasing overlap between the 
electron wavefunction maximum and the hole node. We also 
investigated type I core/shell QDs for which both the electron and 
hole localize to the shell, often called quantum wells (CdS/CdSe, 
Supplementary Fig. 13d,h). 
These trends are best summarized on a ROS chart of f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>2 versus 
f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>1 (Fig. 7), which graphically depicts localization regimes based 
on capping-induced redistribution of oscillator strength. A 
capping experiment starts with 'origin' coordinates of (1,1) for 
the core nanocrystal, and shell growth results in a trajectory 
moving away from this initial point along a specific path of 
carrier localization regimes. These plots clearly distinguish 
between the two type II regimes (e/h versus h/e), which is not 
possible solely through an examination of the 1st exciton peak, 
and distinguishes the two type I regimes for which the carriers 
are localized in the core (eh/o) or in the shell (o/eh). The 
magnitude of localization is also depicted; that is, significant 
delocalization of carriers from the core results in trajectories 
leading far from the origin compared with pseudo-type II regimes 
that remain close to the origin. Indeed, CdSe/CdS QDs </p>

<p>(Supplementary Fig. 13c,g), previously shown to allow partial 
leakage of just the electron into the shell 39 , occupy ROS chart 
regions between type-II h/e and type-I eh/o regions, whereas 
CdS/ZnS QDs (Supplementary Fig. 13b,f) allow partial leakage of 
just the hole into the shell and are intermediate between the 
type-II e/h and type-I o/eh chart regions. Thus, there is 
theoretically a continuum of possible core-shell combinations 
of charge carrier localization that can be explored using various 
material combinations, and this methodology provides rapid 
analysis of localization of the resulting wavefunctions. 
The diagonal dashed line through (1,1) in the ROS chart 
segregates regions indicative of increasing combined oscillator 
strength of the first two transitions (towards the top right, </p>

<p>f 2 </p>

<p>f 1 </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 
f 2 </p>

<p>f 1 </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>f 2 </p>

<p>f 1 </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 
f 2 </p>

<p>f 1 </p>

<p>Homo-epitaxy 
Type I 
Type II: h/e 
Type II: e/h 
1.2 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 
2.0 
2.2 
2.4 
2.6 
2.0 
1.8 
2.2 2.4 2.6 
2.0 
1.8 
2.2 
2.4 </p>

<p>Energy (eV) 
Energy (eV) 
Energy (eV) 
Energy (eV) </p>

<p>ML shell 
ML shell 
ML shell 
ML shell </p>

<p>1.9 2.1 2.3 2.5 2.7 </p>

<p>Absorption 
Absorption 
Absorption 
Absorption </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 
1.0 
0 
0.5 
1.0 
0 
0.5 
1.0 
0 
0.5 
1.0 
0 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0 
0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>Figure 6 | Epitaxial shell growth in four different carrier localization regimes. Absorption spectra are shown in a-d and relative oscillator strengths are 
plotted for the 1st exciton transition (f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>1 ) and 2nd exciton transition (f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>2 ) in e-g. Regimes are designated as: (a,e) homoepitaxial growth (CdTe/CdTe), 
(b,f) Type I with electron and hole in the core (CdSe/ZnS), (c,g) Type II h/e with the hole in the core and electron in shell (CdTe/CdSe) and (d,h) Type II e/ 
h with the electron in the core and hole in the shell (CdSe/ZnTe). Absorption spectra show cores with nominal shell thicknesses of 0 (black), 0.6 (red) and 
1.2 (blue) monolayers (ML). Error bars are s.d. </p>

<p>CdTe/CdTe </p>

<p>Type II 
h/e </p>

<p>Type I 
eh/o </p>

<p>Type I 
o/eh 
Type II 
e/h </p>

<p>Core 
growth </p>

<p>Core 
degrad. </p>

<p>CdSe/CdSe </p>

<p>CdS/CdSe </p>

<p>CdSe/ZnTe </p>

<p>CdSe/ZnS </p>

<p>CdSe degrad. </p>

<p>CdTe/CdSe </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 
0.8 
1 
1.4 
1.2 
0.6 
1 
1.4 
1.2 
0.8 
0.6 </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>2 
rel </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>2 
rel </p>

<p>f 1 </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>f 1 </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>Figure 7 | Relative oscillator strength phase diagrams showing different 
localization regimes for charge carriers in core/shell QDs. Left: example 
experimental data from epitaxial shell growth. Right: summary chart of 
charge carrier localization regimes from 24 experiments of homoepitaxial 
shell growth ('core growth') and core etching ('core degradation') of CdSe 
and CdTe, as well as shell growth experiments for type-I eh/o materials 
(CdSe/ZnS, CdSe/CdS, CdS/ZnS), type-I o/eh materials (CdS/CdSe), 
type-II h/e materials (CdTe/CdSe) and type-II e/h materials (CdSe/ZnTe, 
CdS/ZnSe). The diagonal dashed line indicates a region for zero net change 
in combined band edge oscillator strength. Error bars are s.d. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 5:4506 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>1 þ f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>2 42) from those with decreasing combined oscillator 
strength (towards the bottom left, f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>1 þ f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>2 o2). The former 
generally indicates a decrease in quantum confinement as the 
exciton spreads over a larger number of atoms, involving more 
oscillators in the transition (for example, homoepitaxial growth of 
CdSe/CdSe or CdTe/CdTe). The latter regime indicates a decrease 
in the number of atoms sharing the wavefunction or a net 
increase in confinement. Regions along the line simply indicate a 
redistribution of oscillator strength without a net change in 
confinement. 
Importantly, trends in f </p>

<p>rel 
1 </p>

<p>and f </p>

<p>rel 
2 </p>

<p>indicative of different 
localization regimes become apparent after deposition of just 0.3 
monolayers of shell (a fractional monolayer; see Fig. 6e-h), which 
is only a small change in nanocrystal structure. Other spectral 
signatures also become apparent but only after thicker shells are 
grown. For example, for type II e/h QDs (Fig. 6d) the 1st exciton 
does not substantially shift in energy, and the fluorescence 
quantum yield is very low (o1%). For type-II h/e QDs 
(Fig. 6c), the 1st exciton peak shifts substantially and the quantum 
yield can remain high (20% or more). These regimes also exhibit 
distinct signatures in intraband absorption in the infrared, 
although such experiments require specialized instruments 40 . It 
is noteworthy that core-shell materials in which the shell bandgap 
is smaller than that of the core are problematic to analyse when the 
shell thickness is greater than approximately one monolayer 
because of new transitions that arise near the band edge and 
overlap with the 1st and 2nd exciton peaks. It should be possible to 
overcome this problem by acquiring spectra at lower temperatures 
and validating transition energies with PLE spectroscopy. 
In summary, we have demonstrated that the 1st and 2nd 
exciton transitions in steady-state absorption spectra of QD 
heterostructures are sensitive probes for electron and hole 
localization. Minute changes to electron and hole localization 
are reflected in alterations in the oscillator strengths of these 
transitions and can be conveniently visualized on an f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>1 À f </p>

<p>rel 
2 </p>

<p>plot to map the locations of charge carriers during shell growth. 
When coupled with a simple quantum mechanical model, these 
spectral signatures can reveal detailed structural changes to the 
nanocrystal that may not be clearly distinguishable using 
advanced material characterization techniques, as exemplified 
for the analysis of Hg x Cd 1 À x Te QDs. These methods should 
improve our understanding of confinement in complex hetero-
structures that are of considerable current interest derived from 
cation exchange 30,41-43 and seeded growth 44-46 just by 
monitoring the absorption spectrum. We expect these methods 
to be widely applicable to four-coordinate direct-bandgap II-VI 
and III-V materials, and extrapolation to other materials, such as 
the six-coordinate IV-VI family, should require just an analysis 
of the 1S-1S transition and any higher order transition with 
spherical symmetry. Examples here used the most simplistic 
spherical nanocrystals and wavefunction symmetries; novel 
properties are expected to arise in structures containing 
multiple domains with different shapes, such as tetrapod 
structures in which low energy state are geometrically similar to 
sp 3 atomic orbitals 47 . This new localization information will be 
particularly valuable for distinguishing the degree to which the 
electron and hole are spatially localized in electronic device 
components to maximize or minimize transfer of particular 
charge carriers, to maximize or minimize recombination and for 
determining the degree to which multicomponent structures alloy 
at their interface. This methodology does not require specialized 
equipment, and analysis can be easily automated for the 
observation of incremental structural changes, simply requiring 
a homogeneous core nanocrystal. These analyses will also be 
valuable for wavefunction engineering applications to precisely 
pattern the shapes and spatial locations of charge carrier </p>

<p>wavefunctions, and to funnel oscillator strength into specific 
optical transitions. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Core nanocrystal synthesis. CdTe QDs were prepared using a high-temperature 
fast-injection reaction between cadmium tetradecylphosphonate and elemental 
tellurium in a solvent mixture consisting of oleylamine, trioctylphosphine, diphe-
nylphosphine and octadecene 30,48 . By controlling the reaction time, and through 
the addition of extra precursors, the nanocrystal diameter could be adjusted 
between 2 and 12 nm with B10% s.d. in diameter and 25-32 nm full-width-at-half-
maximum of the fluorescence emission band. These CdTe nanocrystals were 
previously found to have zinc blende lattice structures with wurtzite (hexagonal) 
stacking faults (in 30-40% of the {111} planes) 32 . These nanocrystals showed well-
resolved 1st and 2nd exciton peaks (see Fig. 1 and Supplementary Fig. 14), and 
their size-bandgap dependence matched previous correlations as determined 
through electron microscopy 49,50 . Quasi-spherical zinc blende CdS and CdSe 
nanocrystals were synthesized using methods previously reported in the 
literature 51,52 . Nanocrystals were purified by precipitation from acetone followed 
by extraction in hexane/methanol. </p>

<p>Mercury cation exchange of CdTe-Hg x Cd 1 À x Te. CdTe nanocrystals were 
exchanged with mercury using three different methods: organic/fast, organic/slow 
and aqueous/slow 30,48 . Organic/fast: with rapid stirring, a mercury acetate solution 
in octylamine (0.1 M) was quickly added to a hexane suspension of purified CdTe 
nanocrystals (20 mM) mixed 1:1 with a solution of oleic acid, oleylamine and 
hexane (1:1:2 by volume). The solution was monitored via UV-vis absorption 
spectroscopy until the desired absorption was observed. The nanocrystals were 
purified by extraction (1:2:3 decane:hexane:methanol). Organic/slow: with rapid 
stirring, a mercury octanethiolate solution in chloroform (0.1 M) was quickly added 
to a hexane suspension of purified CdTe nanocrystals (20 mM) containing 
octylamine (1% by volume). Purification was performed by precipitation from 
acetone. Aqueous/slow: CdTe nanocrystals were phase-transferred to aqueous 
solution. A suspension of nanocrystals in chloroform (B20 mM) was mixed with 
an excess of thioglycerol (B0.2 M) and repeatedly sonicated and vortexed for 
B15 min. The nanocrystals were isolated via centrifugation, washed with acetone 
and then dried under vacuum. After resuspension in a solution of 1 mM 
thioglycerol in deionized water (pH 11), the nanocrystals were sonicated, 
centrifuged at 7,000 g for 15 min to remove aggregates and finally passed through a 
0.2-mm filter. For mercury exchange, a freshly prepared solution of mercury 
perchlorate (1 mM) in deionized water was quickly added with rapid stirring to the 
suspension of nanocrystals (20 mM). Nanocrystals were purified using a centrifugal 
filtration device (5 kDa molecular weight cutoff). </p>

<p>Epitaxial shell growth. A purified hexane suspension of nanocrystals (200 nmol) 
was diluted in a mixture of trioctylphosphine oxide (500 mg, 99%) and octadecene 
(5 ml). Hexane was removed under vacuum and the mixture was refluxed at 100°C 
for 30 min under vacuum and purged with argon. After heating to 160°C for 
cadmium-based shells, or 185°C for zinc-based shells, appropriate precursor 
solutions (0.1 M) were added dropwise. Precursors were solutions of S (elemental 
sulfur in octadecene), Se (elemental selenium in octadecene), Te (elemental tell-
urium with 0.25 M trioctylphosphine in octadecene), Zn (zinc acetate in oleyla-
mine) or Cd (cadmium acetate in oleylamine). Samples were removed with a 
needle, diluted in chloroform and purified by acetone precipitations before 
characterization. </p>

<p>Instrumentation. Absorption spectra were measured using a Shimadzu UV-
2401PC scanning spectrophotometer (300-900 nm) or an Ocean Optics NIR-512 
spectrometer with tungsten halogen lamp (850-1,700 nm). Room-temperature 
steady-state fluorescence spectra were obtained at using a Photon Technology 
International spectrofluorometer with photomultiplier tube for the 400-800 nm 
spectral range and InGaAs detector for 800-1,700 nm. Photoluminescence exci-
tation spectroscopy was performed using a Horiba Nanolog UV-vis-NIR spec-
trofluorometer (240-1,550 nm) with internal excitation intensity correction and 
photomultiplier tube for the 400-to 800-nm spectral range and InGaAs detector 
for 800-1,550 nm. PLE spectra were obtained at 0°C using a cell immersed in an 
ice water bath. Room-temperature Raman spectra were obtained using a Spex 
Triplemate microscope with Princeton Instruments CCD detector and 532-nm 
laser excitation. Samples were cast from hexane solutions on aluminum slides. For 
X-ray diffraction, dried solid nanocrystals from hexane solutions were analysed 
using a PANalytical X-Pert PRO with Cu X-ray source. For electron microscopy 
and EDX spectroscopy, samples were prepared from a hexane suspension of 
purified nanocrystals (5 ml) dropped on formvar/carbon 200 mesh TEM grids. 
Normal resolution TEM imaging was performed with a Hitachi H-7500 TEM. 
High-resolution images were obtained using a Tecnai F30 with Oxford EDX 6763 
attachment (in the lab of ZL Wang, supported by NSF funding DMR 0922776). For 
elemental analysis, purified aqueous nanocrystals were dissolved with the addition 
of a small amount of nitric acid; hydrophobic nanocrystals in nonpolar solvents 
were purified with acetone precipitations, dried under vacuum, dissolved in aqua </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 5:4506 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>regia at 80°C for B4 h and diluted in deionized water. Solutions were analysed for 
cadmium, mercury and tellurium using ICP-MS (VG PlasmaQuad 3). </p>

<p>Elemental analysis. To simplify studies of Hg x Cd 1 À x Te nanocrystals without the 
need to characterize all samples for composition, we performed ICP-MS analysis 
on six different CdTe sizes (2.3, 3.0, 4.0, 4.9, 6.1 and 8.4 nm) before and after 
mercury cation exchange to establish spectral relationships. The aqueous exchange 
procedure allowed for efficient purification from excess mercury for ICP-MS. The 
fraction of mercury (x) incorporated into the nanocrystals scaled nearly linearly 
with the absorption cross-section at high energy for all six nanocrystal sizes sub-
jected to cation exchange in water. The value of x could be calculated using the 
following equation: </p>

<p>x ¼ 0:331 
A alloy 
A CdTe 
À 1 </p>



<p>ð2Þ </p>

<p>where A CdTe is the absorption of the CdTe QDs at 4.0 eV and A alloy is the 
absorption after mercury exchange, assuming that the QD concentration does not 
change and that the same number of atoms are in the CdTe nanocrystals as are in 
the resulting Hg x Cd 1 À x Te nanocrystals. </p>

<p>Empirical oscillator strength determination. For the analysis of CdTe QDs, we 
calculated absolute oscillator strengths by first acquiring absolute absorption 
coefficient spectra. Absorption spectra were obtained for suspensions of nano-
crystals with experimentally measured concentration and diameter. Spectra were 
then plotted as absorption coefficient (a, cm À 1 ) versus frequency (n, s À 1 ), vali-
dated through convergence with the spectrum of bulk CdTe (corrected for local 
field effects) at high energy where energy bands are nearly continuous (3.3-4.0 eV) 
because quantum confinement effects are small (Supplementary Fig. 14) 33,50,53 . 
Each spectrum was then fit to a sum of Gaussian functions using the method of 
Klimov 33 : </p>

<p>a n 
ð Þ ¼ 
X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>a i 
2 
ffiffiffiffiffi 
2p 
p 
dRðn i À n g Þ 
exp À 
ðn À n g Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>8 dR 2 ðn i À n g Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>" 
# </p>

<p>ð3Þ </p>

<p>where there are a total of n Gaussian functions (that is, transitions), i, each with an 
area of a i (cm À 1 s À 1 ) and centroid frequency n i (s À 1 ). dR is the relative s.d. of the 
nanocrystal radius and n g (s À 1 ) is the bandgap frequency of the bulk material. Best 
fits of a i , n i and dR were calculated using the least squares method. Initial guesses 
for n i values were determined from the minima of the 2nd derivative of the 
spectrum or maxima of the 4th derivative of the spectrum (see detailed description 
in Supplementary Methods and Supplementary Figs 15-21). Values of a i and dR 
were unbounded, but n i was typically bound to ±50 meV of the initial guess. All 
calculations were performed using an automated <rs type="software">Matlab</rs> script. The values of a i 
were converted to absolute oscillator strengths (f 1 ) with the following formula 54 : </p>

<p>f i ¼ 
4m e e o c 
e 2 h 
Á 
4 
3 
pr 
3 Á a i 
ð4Þ </p>

<p>where m e is the electron mass, e o is the permittivity of free space, c is the speed of 
light, e is the elementary charge, h is the Planck constant and r is the nanocrystal 
radius. To determine f rel values, absorption spectra were simply obtained from 
equal-concentration QD solutions. In this case, absorption spectra were not 
normalized to absorption coefficient, yielding an effective value of each transition 
peak a i . Thus, </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>i ¼ </p>

<p>a i;core=shell 
a i;core 
ð5Þ </p>

<p>and f </p>

<p>rel </p>

<p>i ¼ 1 for the core. </p>

<p>EMA. Nanocrystals were modelled using the EMA and assumed to be spherically 
symmetric and with finite energy wells. Nanocrystals were modelled with N total 
concentric layers (L), with increasing L value from the core (L ¼ 1) to the sur-
roundings (L ¼ N), with discrete boundaries between layers. Radial distances for 
each layer were designated as r L , with material parameters for each layer specified 
in Supplementary Table 1. For non-interacting models of s-type wavefunctions 
(l ¼ 0) of the electron and hole, we use the method of Haus et al. 24 , with Coulombic 
terms included as perturbations included for bandgap calculations, ignoring 
interfacial polarization terms that were found to be small. Calculations begin with 
the time-independent Schrödinger equation in three dimensions: </p>

<p>r 
2 c þ 
2m 
' 
2 E K À E P 
½ 
c¼ 0 
ð6Þ </p>

<p>where E K is the kinetic energy of the electron or hole, E P is its potential energy, m is 
its mass and : is the reduced Planck constant. The radial and angular components 
of the wavefunction are separated: </p>

<p>c r; y; j 
ð 
Þ ¼ R r 
ð ÞY y; j 
ð 
Þ 
ð7Þ </p>

<p>where Yðy; jÞ ¼ ð4pÞ 
À 1=2 for c ¼ m c ¼ 0 and R(r) has solutions of the form 24 </p>

<p>R r 
ð Þ¼A L j ' k L r 
ð ÞþB L n ' k L r 
ð Þ 
ð8Þ </p>

<p>Here j c (k L r) is a spherical Bessel function, n c (k L r) is a spherical Neumann 
function and k L is the wavevector of the electron or hole in layer L, defined by the 
equation </p>

<p>E K À E P;L ¼ 
' 
2 k </p>

<p>2 
L </p>

<p>2m L 
ð9Þ </p>

<p>where E P, L is its potential energy and m L is its mass in layer L. We use the 
boundary conditions that c is continuous at all layer interfaces, and rc is 
continuous at all layer interfaces, modulated by changes in effective mass. Thus, 
B 1 ¼ 0 and R(r N ) ¼ 0. This results in a system of 2N À 1 linear equations with 
coefficients A L and B L for each layer L (2N À 1 unknowns), allowing solution for E K 
of each carrier, E K,e and E K,h , as well as the wavefunctions c e and c h , which must 
be normalized according to: 
Z 
c 
j j 
2 dt¼1 
ð10Þ </p>

<p>where dt ¼ dxdydz. To determine the bandgap we account for Coulombic 
interactions between the electron and hole as a perturbation 55 : </p>

<p>E c ¼ À 
e </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4p </p>

<p>Z Z 1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>e ðr e Þc </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>h ðr h Þc e ðr e Þc h ðr h Þ 
r e À r h 
j 
j eðr e ; r h Þ 
dr e dr h 
ð11Þ </p>

<p>where e is the elementary charge, e is the dielectric constant, r e is the vector 
position of the electron and r h is the vector position of the hole. 
Thus, the bandgap is E g,nanocrystal ¼ E g,bulk þ E K,e þ E K,h þ E c . 
Noninteracting wavefunction overlap, f, was calculated as: </p>

<p>f¼ </p>

<p>Z 1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4pr 
2 c e ðrÞc </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>h ðrÞdr 
ð12Þ </p>

<p>Oscillator strength calculations with interactions. The wavefunctions of the 
1S(e)1S(h) and the 1S(e)2S(h) transitions of the alloyed and core-shell particles 
were calculated through the variational principle using the Rayleigh ratio. First, the 
wavefunctions of the non-interacting electron, c r e 
ð Þ, and hole, c r h 
ð Þ, were sepa-
rately solved numerically via a Verner's 8-9th order Runge Kutta scheme according 
to the potential profile cases described above. By superposition, these solutions 
were combined with a Coulombic interaction expression using a form similar to 
previous microcrystal calculations performed by Kayanuma 56 , </p>

<p>exp 
À jr h À r e j 
a </p>



<p>ð13Þ </p>

<p>where a is the variational parameter. This leads to the complete transition 
wavefunction of the form </p>

<p>c r e ; r h 
ð 
Þ¼c r e 
ð Þcðr h Þexp 
À jr h À r e j 
a </p>



<p>ð14Þ </p>

<p>The variational parameter for each transition wavefunction is solved by 
numerical integration to find the interaction energy as a function of a, then finding 
the value of a where the interaction energy is at a minimum. Once the transition 
wavefunction is known, by considering the approximation of the oscillator strength 
of the exciton derived by Henry and Nassau 57 one obtains the proportionality </p>

<p>f / </p>

<p>Z 
c r e ; r h 
ð 
Þd 
3 r </p>









<p>
2 </p>

<p>ð15Þ </p>

<p>Thus, ratios of the oscillator strength of a Hg x Cd 1 À x Te particle after cation 
exchange (f) to a pure CdTe particle (f 0 ) were calculated where, for a core/shell 
example, the 1S(e)2S(h) transition is represented by </p>

<p>f 
f 0 
¼ </p>

<p>R 
c 1s r e 
ð Þc 2s ðr h Þexp À </p>

<p>rh À re 
j 
j 
a </p>

<p>h 
i 
d 
3 rj </p>

<p>2 
core=shell </p>

<p>R 
c 1s r e 
ð Þc 2s ðr h Þexp À </p>

<p>rh À re 
j 
j 
a </p>

<p>h 
i 
d 
3 rj </p>

<p>2 
core </p>











<p>ð16Þ </p>

<p>For both models we have focused on the heavy holes; light holes are also 
expected to contribute, although to a much smaller extent 58 ; a model incorporating 
multiple hole states will likely further improve accuracy. It is also important to note 
the poor accuracy of the EMA for small particles under strong confinement because 
of non-parabolic shapes of the energy band dispersion curves at high energy. 
In order to model homogeneously alloyed Hg x Cd 1 À x Te nanocrystals the well 
depth and material properties were simply determined using Vegard's Law. For 
core-shell CdTe/HgTe nanocrystals, we must account for fractional monolayers for 
small quantities of mercury incorporated. It is thus assumed that a single 
monolayer will develop first following Vegard's law for this outer well. Then, once 
mercury has completely replaced the cadmium in the first monolayer, a second 
monolayer adjacent to the first monolayer nearer to the core will begin to develop 
in the same manner. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 5:4506 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>



<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was supported by grants from the National Institutes of Health 
(R01CA163256, RC2CA148265 and HHSN268201000043C to S.N.). A.M.S. acknowl-
edges the NCI Nano-Alliance Program for a Pathway to Independence Award </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 5:4506 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>



<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>All authors conceived and designed experiments, characterizations and modelling, and 
contributed to theory. A.M.S. performed all of the chemical syntheses and optical 
characterizations. L.A.L. performed quantum mechanical modelling. A.M.S. and S.N. 
wrote the paper. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
naturecommunications </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Reprints and permission information is available online at http://npg.nature.com/ 
reprintsandpermissions/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Smith, A. M. et al. Mapping the spatial distribution 
of charge carriers in quantum-confined heterostructures. Nat. Commun. 5:4506 
doi: 10.1038/ncomms5506 (2014). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or 
other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons 
license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under 
the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license 
holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 5:4506 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms5506 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>&amp; 2014 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

</text></tei>