<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4120417" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Introduction: While it is predicted that telecare and </p>

<p>other information and communication technology 
(ICT)-assisted services will have an increasingly 
important role in future healthcare services, their 
implementation in practice is complex. For 
implementation of telecare to be successful and ensure 
quality of care, sufficient training for staff (healthcare 
professionals) and service users ( patients) is 
fundamental. Telecare training has been found to have 
positive effects on attitudes to, sustained use of, and 
outcomes associated with telecare. However, the 
potential contribution of training in the adoption, 
quality and safety of telecare services is an under-
investigated research field. The overall aim of this 
study is to develop and evaluate simulation-based 
telecare training programmes to aid the use of 
videophone technology in elderly home care. 
Research-based training programmes will be 
designed for healthcare professionals, service users 
and next of kin, and the study will explore the impact 
of training on adoption, quality and safety of new 
telecare services. </p>

<p>1   while the predicted 
number of healthcare professionals available 
to deliver healthcare services will be far 
fewer than those needed to cope with 
demand. 
2 3 The rapidly growing population 
of elderly people in Norway and across the 
world increases healthcare needs, with more 
services expected to be delivered at home. </p>

<p>4 5   In order to handle the aging population, sig-
nificant changes are needed in the way 
healthcare is delivered. 
4 5 Telecare, meaning 
the use of technology that enables health-
care professionals to remotely care and 
support home dwelling individuals, promises 
to be an important solution to the many 
challenges facing future healthcare services. </p>

<p>6   While it is predicted that telecare and other 
information and communication technology 
(ICT)-assisted services will have an increas-
ingly important role in future healthcare ser-
vices, their implementation in practice is 
complex. 
7 8 There are ergonomics-related 
barriers and risks associated with the imple-
mentation and adoption of telecare, such as 
healthcare professionals lacking the attitudes, 
knowledge and skills needed to use the tech-
nology as part of healthcare delivery. 
9-11 This 
may result in poor quality and safety of health-
care services. 
12-14 For implementation to be 
successful and ensure quality of care, staff </p>

<p>15   and organisations 
16 17 must be ready to 
change and adopt innovation. Accordingly, it 
is widely acknowledged that training of staff 
(healthcare professionals) and service users 
( patients) is fundamental to successful tele-
care implementation. </p>

<p>9 11 18   Telecare training has been found to have 
positive effects on attitudes to, sustained use 
of and outcomes associated with tele-
care. 
10 19-21 Training is recommended as a 
fundamental part of telecare implementation </p>

<p>Wiig S, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004995. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-004995 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Protocol </p>

<p>processes, but there is a lack of targeted staff and service 
user training programmes for this purpose, and training 
is not always offered 
10 or it is inadequate. 
22 A review of 
telecare education initiatives by Basu et al 
23 identified 
only 10 training courses, none of which were for profes-
sionals working in elderly home care services. This lack 
of pedagogical and professional development models 
related to telecare applications led Basu et al 
23 conclude 
that education for telecare is an emergent field. Their 
findings further highlight that telecare training is not 
simply about learning a new technology; it is about 
adapting practice to engage with new technology. 
23 In 
addition to technical skills training, it is important, 
therefore, to focus on the development of the knowl-
edge, skills, attitudes and experiences required for the 
new ways of working associated with telecare use. </p>

<p>11 22   Awareness raising and training can help motivate health 
professionals to adopt telecare in their clinical prac-
tices. 
11 24 Previous research has also demonstrated a lack 
of training activities focusing on how simulation can be 
developed and used to improve adoption of technology 
in the home context. 
25 Simulation is considered a 
powerful tool for the teaching of a range of knowledge 
and skills necessary for sound clinical practice. 
Simulation has long been in use within education and 
training for healthcare professionals to foster both tech-
nical and non-technical skills, including communication 
and interpersonal skills and decision-making abilities. </p>

<p>26   Simulation is largely underpinned by active learning 
principles that requires participation in and reflection 
on meaningful activities. 
27 The value of simulation as an 
educational tool that promotes an overall culture of 
safety and underscores safe and reflexive clinical pro-
cesses to improve healthcare is acknowledged by 
many. 
28-31 In an effort to encourage high-quality prac-
tices related to new telecare services in the home care 
arena, it therefore makes sense to utilise simulation in 
telecare training, as this is lacking in current practice. 
The potential contribution of training in the adoption, 
quality and safety of telecare services is an under-
investigated research field. 
23 25 More research is therefore 
needed on development, implementation and evaluation 
of practice focused telecare training to explore the 
impact of such training on healthcare professionals' 
adoption of safe and effective telecare services. Research 
is also needed to address implementation and training 
challenges from the service users' perspective, in order 
to develop targeted training programmes for service 
users and next of kin. Currently, service users or next of 
kin are often not included or consulted in development 
of telecare technology and the redesign of healthcare 
processes, implying that their attitudes, needs and skills 
are not given proper attention. </p>

<p>Aim 
The Safer@Home-Simulation and training study (August 
2011-December 2016) forms part of an interdisciplinary 
research project called 'Smart systems to support safer </p>

<p>independent living and social interaction for elderly at 
home' (Safer@Home). Our study protocol is limited to 
the work package concerned with simulation and train-
ing. The aim of the Safer@Home-Simulation and training 
study is to develop and evaluate simulation-based tele-
care training programmes for use with videophone tech-
nology in elderly home care services, based on 
stakeholder experiences and needs. Specifically, we will 
develop simulation-based training programmes for 
health professionals ( providers), service users ( patients) 
and next of kin, and explore the impact of such training 
on adoption, quality and safety of new telecare tools that 
allow for virtual visits in the elderly home care services. 
A key feature of the study is its methodological 
approach, relying on cyclic action research 
32 and simula-
tion as a pedagogical training tool. 
26 Despite previous 
recommendations and the promising fit of the action 
research approach to research on implementation and 
adoption of healthcare innovations, application in 
research on telecare has been limited. 
33 Our study will 
therefore contribute new knowledge on the use of 
action research and simulation-based training in imple-
mentation and adoption of telecare services. </p>

<p>METHODS AND ANALYSIS 
Design and context 
Action research is a participative, process-oriented meth-
odology grounded in experience, which aims to facilitate 
social change and innovation. It is the ideal method-
ology for identifying and improving problems in prac-
tice 
34 and is increasingly employed in healthcare 
settings. 
35 This study is designed as a cyclic action 
research project 
32 with the aim of developing and evalu-
ating a pilot telecare training programme for elderly 
service users living at home, their next of kin, and 
healthcare professionals working in home-based elderly 
care services. The training programme development 
depends on problem identification and problem solving, 
with involvement and input from multiple stakeholders 
involved in service provision and service use. Action 
research is participatory research where researchers 
work with people rather than doing research on 
them. 
35 36 This is crucial in our study as it depends on 
collaboration and stakeholder involvement, and focuses 
on generating solutions to practical problems in relation 
to how to best establish and use a videophone service in 
home care settings. The videophone will allow for 
virtual visits in home care services. Not only technical 
aspects of training related to how to use the equipment 
are necessary, but health professionals also need to learn 
about and train for managing ergonomic barriers and 
risks that may occur as a result of new ways of providing 
care at home. 
The research context of our project is the municipal 
home care environment. Norwegian municipalities are 
responsible for delivering primary healthcare for elderly 
people living at home. By implementing telecare in its </p>



<p>Wiig S, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004995. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-004995 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>home care services, the involved municipalities aim at 
providing healthcare services of high quality and safety 
and to enable elderly people to live longer at home. By 
applying an action research design, the municipalities 
alongside the technology vendor and university research-
ers are approaching the phenomena in a collaborative 
way to identify and solve upcoming educational chal-
lenges in implementation and training of videophone 
services in home care settings. 
The design of the action research approach 
32 features 
five cyclical study phases which allow for a variety of 
research and evaluation methods to be used within the 
approach. The five phases are: 
▸ Diagnosis: identify and define the problem and 
collect data for further investigation; 
▸ Action planning: consider courses of action based on 
initial diagnosis; 
▸ Implementation: take action according to the speci-
fied plan; 
▸ Evaluation: assess the actions and their consequences; 
and 
▸ Learning and refinement: document and interpret 
cycle outcomes to aid improvement. 
Although the research process might appear linear and 
instrumental and conducted step by step in separated 
phases, it will be in practice a cyclic and iterative process. 
As described by Susman and Evered 
32 the action research 
approach is characterised by cyclical iterations, with 
overlap and feedback between the five phases. This cyc-
lical approach implies an openness to for example, 
change the course of the actions taken to solve the 
problem based on the evaluation findings, and to con-
sider how unsolved problems from an initial cycle can be 
taken into account in later iterations of the problem 
solving process. Research findings will be continuously 
integrated in the research process in close collaboration 
between the researchers, representatives from the muni-
cipalities and the technology vendor. The municipalities 
and technology vendor involved in implementing the 
technology and training programme, will collaborate with 
researchers in all phases. Consequently, there will be a 
sound basis for revealing barriers and success factors in 
the technology design and development, implementation 
and refinement of the training programme. </p>

<p>32   The following overarching research questions will 
guide the study: 
▸ What does the literature identify as risks and chal-
lenges associated with the implementation and use of 
telecare services in home-based elderly care? 
▸ How can identified training needs of telecare users 
guide design and development of a simulation-based 
training programme for service users, next of kin and 
healthcare professionals working in home care ser-
vices for the elderly? 
▸ How can a simulation-based training programme for 
healthcare professionals, service users and next of kin 
best be implemented to enable adoption of high-
quality telecare services in home-based elderly care? </p>

<p>▸ What is the impact of simulation-based training for 
healthcare professionals, service users and next of kin 
on adoption, quality and safety of new telecare ser-
vices in home-based elderly care? </p>

<p>Study sample 
The study is executed in five phases, with the first four 
phases (diagnosis, action planning, implantation, evalu-
ation) involving collection of data. Data collection 
started in July 2013 and is ongoing. Two municipalities 
are involved in all phases and videophone technology 
will be implemented and tested in their home care ser-
vices. The sample from these two municipalities will 
include service users, next of kin, healthcare profes-
sionals, managers and other key personnel. 
In phase 1 the sample will also include informants 
from two to four additional municipalities which have 
applied videophone or similar technology in their home 
care services. Here we will collect data on experience, 
knowledge and training needs, from healthcare profes-
sionals, service users and next of kin with telecare or 
videophone technology experience in elderly home care 
services. It is also relevant to explore experiences from 
certain specialised healthcare services where telemedi-
cine solutions involving screen-based communication 
between the hospital and patient have been used, as the 
use of videophone tools in home care settings in Norway 
is currently limited. 
The recruitment will be strategic and purposive in all 
phases, in order to include informants with specific 
knowledge, experience and needs related to telecare use 
and training. The recruitment of healthcare profes-
sionals will be led by University of Stavanger (UiS) 
researchers in collaboration with municipality represen-
tatives. Healthcare professionals involved in this study 
are mainly nurses, and enrolled nurses working in home 
healthcare. We may also include physiotherapists and 
ergonomists in the sample, as these are healthcare pro-
fessionals in the municipal primary healthcare services 
who are considered potential users of technology to 
allow virtual visits in the project. When recruiting service 
users a representative from the respective municipality 
will be responsible for approaching potential partici-
pants as other project members will not have access to 
personal information about users of municipal primary 
healthcare services. Formal agreement with involved 
municipalities will be obtained before approaching any 
informants or services. </p>

<p>Data collection 
Phase 1: Diagnosis 
Training cannot be effective unless it meets the identi-
fied needs of trainees. 
37 The diagnosis phase focuses on 
identifying and defining the problem under investiga-
tion and entails an analysis of the educational needs of 
healthcare professionals, service users and next of kin. 
First, two systematic literature reviews will be conducted 
to (1) identify and map key patient safety risks associated </p>

<p>Wiig S, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004995. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-004995 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>with telecare use in home care settings, and map if and 
how patient safety risks have been addressed in training 
activities; and (2) to identify and map technology use, to 
explore experiences with and types of training related to 
virtual visits in home healthcare for elderly people. This 
will clarify conditions that may help or hinder safe and 
successful adoption of videophones in elderly home 
care services and identify previously used training 
activities. 
Moreover, a purposive sample of around 10-15 service 
users and next of kin will be recruited for individual 
interviews to gain insights into their real-life experiences 
and identified needs associated with telecare use. 
Themes to be covered are: technology experiences and atti-
tudes; quality and safety issues; training and user support; self-
care ability. Furthermore, a sample of around 15-20 
healthcare professionals and service development man-
agers from the municipal healthcare services will be 
recruited for individual and focus group interviews. 
Themes to be covered are: technology experience in home 
care services; implementation of a videophone service; quality 
and safety; and training needs. A sample of around 5-10 
informants identified as key actors in developing or 
implementing telecare tools will be recruited from the 
municipalities and the technology vendor. Specific 
topics for this data collection are: the implementation 
process and involved actors; quality and safety; training and 
user support issues; leadership, culture and funding. Aspects 
related to organisational processes will also be covered 
via observation in meetings between the municipalities 
and the technology vendor, and in internal municipal 
meetings. The observation guide covers: involved organi-
sations/professions/professional communities; order of speaking, 
meeting topics and atmosphere; decision-making, collaboration 
and collaboration barriers; power issues; training. </p>

<p>Phase 2: Action planning 
Action planning is concerned with the design and devel-
opment of a pilot simulation-based training programme. 
The training programme will be informed by analysis of 
the results from the diagnostic phase. Action planning 
will feature the development of simulation scenarios in 
collaboration with the project partners and healthcare 
professionals working in clinical practice. Once the 
format and content of the training programmes have 
been established, a plan for the implementation and 
evaluation will be finalised. 
In this phase a reference group of about 8-10 partici-
pants will be established to give advice and input on the 
form and content of the different training programmes. 
Members of the reference group will be key individuals 
from the involved municipalities, healthcare profes-
sionals and user representatives (eg, members from the 
municipal elderly council). </p>

<p>Phase 3: Implementation 
Phase 3 involves implementation of the simulation-based 
pilot training programme in practice. Simulation </p>

<p>scenarios will provide opportunities for practicing the 
videophone technology in real-life settings. The simula-
tion will involve the actual technology, and will be held 
in a high-fidelity simulation centre with possibilities for 
videotaping and debriefing. It will possibly involve both 
individual and group training. The sample in the imple-
mentation and evaluation phase will involve service 
users, next of kin and healthcare professionals who will 
be trained in using the videophone technology. The new 
videophone equipment will be implemented and will 
allow for virtual home visits in the two municipalities 
involved. A purposive sampling approach will be used to 
recruit an anticipated sample of 20 nurse and enrolled 
nurse participants from municipal elderly home care 
services, and 20 service users and next of kin who will 
test the simulation-based training programme and the 
virtual visits as part of their home care services. Focus 
group interviews will be carried out in aid of training 
programme evaluation. </p>

<p>Phase 4: Evaluation 
Phase 4 entails an in-depth exploratory evaluation 
process to explore the impact of the pilot simulation-
based training programmes on adoption, quality and 
safety of new telecare technologies in home care services 
for the elderly. The theoretical framework adopted for 
the evaluation is the Integrated Model of Training 
Evaluation and Effectiveness (IMTEE). 
37 According to 
the IMTEE, the purpose of training evaluation is to 
examine learning outcomes and the extent to which 
training programmes meet intended goals. 
37 Chosen 
evaluation approaches will thus depend on stated train-
ing goals and can include measures of training content 
and design, changes in learners' knowledge, attitudes or 
skills 
or 
organisational 
benefits 
of 
training. 
Understandings of evaluation outcomes can be 
enhanced by attention to the effectiveness of training, 
that is, measures of individual, training and organisa-
tional variables likely to influence outcomes at various 
stages of the training process. 
37 Our evaluation is inter-
ested in assessing training content and design, as well as 
exploring possible changes in knowledge, attitudes or 
skills. Effects ascribable to individual and training vari-
ables before, during and after training will also be 
assessed, focusing on participant demographics, experi-
ence and abilities, attitudes and expectations, as well as 
instructional style, practice and feedback. 
37 Evaluation 
will thus focus on participants' opinions on course form 
and content, whether the training programmes meet 
needs and expectations, and whether it impacts on per-
ceptions of telecare services, intention to adopt such ser-
vices in practice and service quality and safety. The 
evaluation process will run in three stages before, during 
and after training implementation and will feature quali-
tative research methods including focus group interviews 
with healthcare professionals and service users/next of 
kin, and observation of healthcare professionals and 
service users during the training sessions. </p>



<p>Wiig S, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004995. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-004995 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>The focus group interview guides will be developed 
based on results from the diagnostic phase and action 
planning phase. Possible topics to be covered are: knowl-
edge and reflections about patient safety risk; attitudes 
towards new means of service provision; trust in services; 
technical skills; communication skills; patient empower-
ment; and cost-effectiveness. Observations of the train-
ing sessions with all healthcare professionals and service 
users will be conducted and inform the evaluation and 
improvement of the training programmes. An observa-
tion guide will be developed in the action planning 
phase. There will not be observation of real-time service 
provision via virtual visits, as this would involve patient 
sensitive information not included in our ethical 
approval. 
Expected outcomes of the training programme for 
healthcare professionals will be related to knowledge, 
skills and attitudes regarding the use of new technolo-
gies. Outcomes are expected to include positive attitudes 
towards using new telecare tools in home care services; 
improved communication skills with elderly in a new 
healthcare provider situation via videophone; and 
increased awareness of patient safety risks in applying 
virtual visits as part of providing home care. These ele-
ments will be incorporated in the training programme 
and simulation scenarios. Similarly, expected outcome 
for the elderly service users are related to knowledge, 
skills and attitudes regarding the use of new technolo-
gies, alongside improved care quality and safety; 
increased patient empowerment and ability to live 
longer at home; and maintained trust in healthcare </p>

<p>services. However, we can also expect that some service 
users and healthcare professionals will hold negative atti-
tudes towards these new ways of providing services. All 
results will be included in the training programme devel-
opment process according to the cyclical action research 
approach, to improve the design and content of the 
training programmes for all involved groups. 
Data collection methods and samples related to all 
research phases are described in table 1. Data collection 
started in August 2013 and will continue until second 
quarter of 2015. </p>

<p>Phase 5: Learning and refinement 
The final phase will assess the evaluation outcomes in 
aid of the refinement and improvement of the training 
programmes and their implementation. The outcomes 
of the entire initial cycle will be documented, focusing 
on both theory and practice, for further possible study 
and improvement. </p>

<p>Data analysis and quality of research 
To ensure quality of research and trustworthiness in 
terms of credibility, in the analysis we will apply analyst 
triangulation and member checks. Also, the reference 
group will be involved so that credibility of the findings 
will be enhanced in the different research phases. 
38 The 
research team will be involved in discussions and refine-
ment of the undertaken analysis. The analytical process 
will follow the aforementioned research steps and the 
material will be categorised and analysed to inform the 
next phase of the research process. There will also be </p>

<p>Table 1 Description of research process and methods </p>

<p>Research 
process phase 
Methods 
Sample </p>

<p>Diagnosis 
▸ Literature reviews 
▸ Individual interviews 
▸ Focus group interviews 
▸ Participant observations </p>

<p>▸ 10-15 service users/next of kin 
▸ 15-20 healthcare professionals and service 
managers 
▸ 5-10 key actors 
Action planning 
▸ Reference group involved in providing input to 
training programme development </p>

<p>▸ 10 representatives from the involved 
municipalities, health professionals, service 
users, next of kin, technology developers 
Implementation 
▸ Recruitment of health professionals and service 
users/next of kin 
▸ 2 prepilot focus group interviews with 
healthcare professionals and service users 
before testing the training programmes </p>

<p>▸ 20 nurses/enrolled nurses 
▸ 20 service users/next of kin </p>

<p>Evaluation 
▸ 2 focus group interviews with healthcare 
professionals (before and after participating in 
the pilot) 
▸ 2 focus group interviews with service users and 
next of kin (before and after training session) 
▸ Observation of the training sessions for 
healthcare professionals and for service users </p>

<p>▸ 20 nurses/enrolled nurses 
▸ 20 service users/next of kin 
▸ Observation of all during training sessions </p>

<p>Learning and 
refinement </p>

<p>▸ Assessment and analysis of total data material 
to refine training programmes ready for large 
scale implementation </p>

<p>Wiig S, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004995. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-004995 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>feedback between the five phases in our cyclic approach 
to ensure continuous corrections and improvement. All 
transcribed data material from interviews and observa-
tions will be uploaded and systemised by using the soft-
ware program <rs id="software-1" type="software">QSR International NVivo</rs> V.<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version">10</rs>. </p>

<p>39   The data analysis is a combination of induction and 
deduction. In the diagnosis phase we will apply induc-
tion to establish the overall impression of the data mater-
ial according to Malterud's </p>

<p>40   systematic text 
condensation approach. This will involve the Norwegian 
speaking members of the research team. All team 
members will individually read the data material and 
come together in an analysis seminar to discuss the 
main themes 
40 emerging from the data and which are 
most important to incorporate in the training pro-
gramme content and methods. This total impression 
along with the systematic literature reviews will form the 
basis for the action planning phase where the training 
programmes will be designed. The analysis of the data 
material from the implementation and evaluation 
phases will also be analysed according to the systematic 
text condensation approach. This analysis is deductive 
and theory 
40 driven as it will apply predefined categories 
based on Alvarez et al's 
37 theoretical framework IMTEE. 
Research quality in terms of transferability to other 
contexts is key in qualitative research. 
38 Generalisability 
in the sense of exact replication of results across studies 
is not the goal of action research inquiries. According to 
Susman and Evered, 
32 the basis of generalisation in 
action research is narrow, situational and bound by 
context. 
32 This is also true for our study; however action 
research encourages transferability of project outcomes 
to similar settings when appropriate. Depending on con-
textual similarity, it is possible to judge the relevance of 
findings from our study and whether they can be 
applied to another study setting. There is a potential 
conflict between our purposive sampling and transfer-
ability of results to other settings. This will be addressed 
by providing details of the context in which our research 
occurs in our publications. Also, we will collect data 
about our sample regarding for example, their experi-
ence with technology, age, gender and education, which 
we consider of relevance for other studies and popula-
tions. This information will also be provided in our pub-
lications and enable a better ability to evaluate if our 
results are transferable to other contextual settings. </p>

<p>38   ETHICAL CONCERNS AND DISSEMINATION 
The study is based on informed written consent, and 
informants and service users can withdraw at any point 
during the project. Interview and observation data will 
be managed confidentially. Tape recordings will be 
deleted after transcription. Each interview and observa-
tion will be marked with a code, and the list matching 
the person identification and code will be securely 
stored (locked cabinet or password-protected PC at the 
university) by the research group ( project manager: SW, </p>

<p>and principal researcher: VG). Anonymised transcribed 
data material will be stored at the research institution 
for 3 years after the project ends. 
Results will be disseminated at several research confer-
ences, one PhD thesis (VG), and in articles published in 
peer reviewed journals. Moreover, we will present the 
study to audiences outside the academic community 
through public presentations and popular scientific 
publications. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
The rationale for choosing an action research approach 
in our study is found in action research's characteristics 
of being participatory, 
41 collaborative, 
42 empowering </p>

<p>43   and suitable for contextualisation 
44 of problems facing 
processes of development and implementation of tele-
care solutions in healthcare. Involving a multistake-
holder partnership in the research team and 
participation from health professionals and user repre-
sentatives in the reference group is expected to increase 
the likelihood of an effective practice innovation in 
terms of training programmes well-suited for health pro-
fessionals, service users and next of kin intended to use 
videophone technology to conduct virtual visits in 
elderly home care. 
While the action research approach is seen to have 
strong potential within telecare projects 
45-47 there is 
little documented use. The reasons for its limited use in 
telecare studies are unclear but could be related to per-
ceived methodological problems associated with the 
approach. Issues of context, roles, politics, dynamics and 
ethics are deeply embedded in the action research 
method and influence its emergent process, quality and 
outcomes. 
48 The primary strength of the action research 
methodology as applied to telecare studies is however its 
ability to actively engage people in research and 
empower them 
35 and it has long been advocated for in 
telecare studies. 
49 It is not uncommon that new telecare 
technologies fail to see sustained adoption in prac-
tice 
24 50 51 because intended users seldom get to contrib-
ute to development and implementation. 
45 The main 
contribution of our study is therefore new knowledge 
and experience regarding application of action research 
in telecare projects. By taking advantage of a combin-
ation of user experience, user involvement, collaboration 
and research evidence, we will develop research-based 
training programmes more suited for developing both 
technical and non-technical skills related to use of video-
phone technology. 
Telecare can be considered to be one important solu-
tion for future healthcare challenges. 
6 However, differ-
ent parties may have different views and perception of 
how healthcare services can benefit from implementing 
new technological tools and changed ways in how 
healthcare is provided. In this study we need to carefully 
consider these different views and the fact that partici-
pants in both the service user and healthcare </p>



<p>Wiig S, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004995. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-004995 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>professional sample may regard the video telephone as a 
too complicated tool with an inadequate design, or that 
communication and service provision via virtual visits is 
not increasing care quality. Since we have close collabor-
ation with the technology vendor, we will be able to give 
input to improve technology design, functionality and 
sound and picture quality based on actual user experi-
ence (health professionals and patients). We need to be 
aware of the contested nature of implementing ICTs in 
healthcare and we believe our research design opens the 
way for a continuous dialogue between researchers, tech-
nology users and the technology vendor, minimising the 
risk for low uptake and sustainability in practice. </p>

<p>24 50 51   There is a need to consider both the benefits, chal-
lenges and limitations of action research applied to tele-
care projects and reflect on the role of the action 
researcher. The action researcher is a researcher acting 
to increase knowledge and understanding while simul-
taneously being a facilitator for organisational change. 
Action research thus implies an inherently dual role for 
the researcher 
52 who needs to be able to move between 
different roles when needed. 
53 This is a possible 
research challenge and limitation in our project and will 
require good knowledge of the action research process, 
alongside comprehensive research skills and an overall 
flexible and pragmatic approach. It also necessitates the 
personal skills necessary to foster and handle diverse 
interpersonal relationships; ability to communicate and 
negotiate; social and cultural demands; and realistic 
time keeping. 
54 As collaborative problems, such as differ-
ent assumptions, values and world views between stake-
holders, 
55 have been demonstrated by others as very 
disruptive and time consuming to the action research 
process, they need to be anticipated and openly dis-
cussed and managed by participants in the project. </p>

<p>41   This will be solved by organising regular meetings involv-
ing all project partners, including the technology 
vendor, the municipalities and the researchers. In struc-
tured meetings we will provide opportunities to discuss 
and overcome disagreement and collaborative problems 
in the multistakeholder team. An additional challenge 
and possible limitation relates to municipal decision-
making processes not involving research team members 
but with possible relevance for the project. Decisions 
related to technology development, technology costs 
and organisational change processes could emerge as 
critical for the project. Possible future decisions in the 
involved municipalities could affect our research project, 
such as those related to new telecare solutions, new tele-
care strategies and choice of vendors or IT-related deci-
sions that might interfere with the chosen videophone 
solution in this project. Moreover, a possible challenge is 
related to the development of the videophone technol-
ogy. This is not in the hands of the project team and 
challenges such as a delay in the production might inter-
fere with our design of training programmes in the 
action planning phase and the pilot testing in the imple-
mentation phase. However, in an attempt to pre-empt </p>

<p>such a problem, there are collaborative meetings with 
members from all work packages in the overall project. 
In addition, a project team member ( principal 
researcher: VG) is part of the videophone development 
group working to guide the development of the final 
videophone tool, together with representatives from the 
municipalities and the technology vendor. The research 
team member was invited by the development team to 
coordinate the videophone development group, a coord-
inator role that extends to managing communications 
between our research project team and the videophone 
development project, in order to keep both project 
goals and deadlines coordinated, as both projects 
depend on each other for success. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors would like to thank the funders and 
Department of Health Studies, University of Stavanger, for the possibility for 
carrying out this research. The authors would like to thank both reviewers for 
constructive and helpful comments that improved the study protocol. The 
authors would also like to thank partners in the overall Safer@home project: 
Lyse; Department of Electronical Engineering and Computer Sciences at 
University of Stavanger; Stavanger municipality; Cisco; DevoTeam; VS-Safety; 
SINTEF; SAFER/Laerdal Medical; Stavanger University hospital/SESAM. </p>

<p>Contributors SW planned the study design and study protocol, contributed to 
the development of data collection tools, drafted and revised this manuscript. 
VG contributed to the study design, was responsible for the development of 
data collection tools and ethical approval and contributed to drafting and 
revision of the manuscript. JA, IT, AMLH, MS, ES, KLM contributed to study 
design and commented on the manuscript draft and revision. All authors have 
read and approved the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding The Safer@home-simulation and training study is part of the 
project 'Smart systems to support safer independent living and social 
interaction for elderly at home' (Safer@Home). This project is supported by 
the Norwegian Research Council grant number 210799. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Patient consent Obtained. </p>

<p>Ethics approval The study has been approved by the Norwegian Social 
Science Data Services (NSD) (Ref 32934, 16 April 2013). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>



<p>Wiig S, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004995. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-004995 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>





<p>Wiig S, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e004995. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-004995 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>