<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4230620" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT Fluorescence tagging of proteins is a widely used tool to study protein function 
and dynamics in live cells. However, the extent to which different mammalian transgene 
methods faithfully report on the properties of endogenous proteins has not been studied 
comparatively. Here we use quantitative live-cell imaging and single-molecule spectroscopy 
to analyze how different transgene systems affect imaging of the functional properties of the 
mitotic kinase Aurora B. We show that the transgene method fundamentally influences level 
and variability of expression and can severely compromise the ability to report on endoge-
nous binding and localization parameters, providing a guide for quantitative imaging studies 
in mammalian cells. </p>

<p>Gene tagging with green fluorescent protein (GFP) has revolution-
ized our understanding of the dynamic properties of the cellular 
proteome. Powerful fluorescence imaging technologies have made 
quantitative measurements of protein biophysics and biochemistry 
feasible in situ (Wu and Pollard, 2005; Maeder et al., 2007). High-
throughput imaging and computational data integration make such 
studies scalable to whole pathways and proteomes (Wu and Pollard, 
2005; Maeder et al., 2007). Whereas fusing fluorescent tags to en-
dogenous proteins is routine in yeast, in human cells, the insight 
gained from quantitative imaging approaches has been limited by 
the available transgene methodologies. The majority of past studies 
relied on systems that do not faithfully maintain physiological gene 
expression, such as cDNA plasmids with heterologous promoters 
that are randomly integrated into the human cell's genome for </p>

<p>stable expression. The resulting overexpression or underexpression 
is known to affect protein function through numerous mechanisms, 
such as nonspecific aggregation, alterations in folding, and imbal-
ance with endogenous binding partners (Burgess et al., 2012; 
Gibson et al., 2013). These considerations have motivated the de-
velopment of second-generation plasmid-based systems such as 
bacterial artificial chromosomes (BACs), which retain endogenous 
cis-acting regulatory sequences and can also be randomly inte-
grated into the genome of the host cell (Poser et al., 2008). How-
ever, position-effect variegation in BACs has not been investigated, 
and all superexpression systems suffer from the continued presence 
of untagged protein produced from endogenous loci, which cannot 
be imaged but may carry out all or part of the function of the fusion 
protein under study (Yue et al., 2008). Although RNA interference 
(RNAi) knockdown of endogenous protein can be used in combina-
tion with RNAi-resistant transgenes, incomplete knockdown and 
off-target effects make such experiments difficult to control and in-
terpret (Ma et al., 2006). Recently multiple genome-editing tech-
nologies, including zinc finger nucleases (ZFNs) and Tale-activated 
endonucleases (TALENs), have been developed to modify endoge-
nous mammalian loci (Bibikova et al., 2003; Miller et al., 2011). How-
ever, whether such knock-in transgenes truly are quantitatively supe-
rior to superexpression approaches has not been systematically 
studied to date. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>To address this issue, we created HeLa cell lines stably expressing 
C-terminal monomeric enhanced GFP (mEGFP) fusions of the key </p>

<p>Monitoring Editor 
Jennifer Lippincott-Schwartz 
National Institutes of Health </p>

<p>Received: Jun 13, 2014 
Revised: Sep 5, 2014 
Accepted: Sep 11, 2014 </p>

<p>This article was published online ahead of print in MBoC in Press (http://www 
.molbiolcell.org/cgi/doi/10.1091/mbc.E14-06-1091) on September 17, 2014. 
B.K., R.M., A.P.G., and J.M. constructed cell lines. R.M., M.W., and A.Z.P. per-
formed and analyzed FCS measurements. All authors analyzed data. R.M con-
ceived the project. R.M and J.E. wrote the manuscript. 
The authors declare no competing financial interests. 
Address correspondence to: J. Ellenberg (ellenberg@embl.de). </p>

<p>© 2014 Mahen et al. This article is distributed by The American Society for Cell 
Biology under license from the author(s). Two months after publication it is avail-
able to the public under an Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported 
Creative Commons License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0). 
"ASCB ® ," "The American Society for Cell Biology ® ," and "Molecular Biology of 
the Cell ® " are registered trademarks of The American Society for Cell Biology. </p>

<p>Abbreviation used: AURKB, Aurora kinase B; BAC, bacterial artificial chromo-
some; FCS, fluorescence correlation spectroscopy; GFP, green fluorescent pro-
tein; TALEN, Tale-activated endonuclease; ZFN, zinc finger nuclease. </p>

<p>Volume 25 November 5, 2014 </p>

<p>Systematic comparison transgene methods | 3611 </p>

<p>homology to endogenous loci (Figure 1Ai). In addition, we per-
formed random integration of BACs or cDNA plasmids (Figure 1Aii; 
Poser et al., 2008). For each transgene method (Figure 1A), we cre-
ated several monoclonal or pooled HeLa lines stably expressing </p>

<p>mitotic kinase Aurora kinase B (AURKB-GFP) using four different 
transgene methods (Figure 1A). We used genome editing by ZFNs 
(Bibikova et al., 2003) or TALENs (Miller et al., 2011) to target recom-
bination of EGFP from a donor plasmid containing regions of </p>

<p>FIGURE 1: Construction and validation of genome-edited cell lines expressing AURKB-GFP. (A) Schematic of fluorescent 
gene-tagging systems used to create AURKB-GFP. (i) ZFNs or TALENs cause DNA double-strand breaks at the 
C-terminus of the AURKB locus, before repair with a donor construct containing EGFP (arrow). (ii) Plasmids containing 
AURKB-GFP as either the full mouse gene (BAC) or as cDNA are randomly integrated into the genome. (B) Flowchart of 
assays used to construct genome-edited cell lines. Junction PCR was not used to screen plasmid-based systems since 
the genomic locations are unknown. (C) Fluorescence-activated cell sorting of GFP-positive cells. Gates were drawn 
based on comparison to nonfluorescent wild-type parental cells. (D) Fluorescence confocal microscopy maximum-
intensity z-projections of genome-edited AURKB-GFP cells (clone HZ2). (E) Junction PCR screening of ZFN genome-
edited AURKB-GFP clonal cells. Stars denote clones with all alleles successfully targeted. (F) Western blot screening of 
nocodazole-arrested ZFN AURKB-GFP cells with anti-AURKB antibody. (G) Southern blot screening of ZFN AURKB-GFP 
cells using a probe in AURKB intron 2 after Kpnl and Nsil digestion. (H) Mitotic timing from live-cell imaging; cells were 
automatically classified into cell cycle stages using mCherry-H2B as previously described (Held et al., 2010). n &gt;355 cells 
from two experiments. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>levels. As expected for a constitutive heterologous promoter (cyto-
megalovirus; Boshart et al., 1985), different cDNA clones showed 
the strongest overexpression and the most variable expression be-
tween cell lines (∼0.4-to 5.7-fold). Flow cytometry of the intensity 
distribution of AURKB-GFP from 20,000 cells for each tagging 
method showed greatest cell-to-cell homogeneity for the two ge-
nome-editing methods (CV = 23 [ZFN], 23 [TALEN]), followed 
by BACs and cDNAs, which exhibited more variability (Figure 2B; 
CV = 30 and 112, respectively). Similarly, whereas in genome-edited 
and BAC systems, nearly all cells expressed the fusion protein (ZFN, 
99%; BAC, 92-99%), cDNA clones had a variable number of ex-
pressing cells (Figure 2B; 28-89%). 
Having assessed total expression level and cell-to-cell variation, 
we next addressed subcellular abundance of the fusion proteins in 
mitotic metaphase, when AURKB resides mostly on mitotic chro-
mosomes (Carmena et al., 2012). Genome-edited cells exhibited the 
expected specific localization to metaphase chromosomes, with 
barely detectable levels of unbound cytoplasmic protein. By con-
trast, overexpression from the plasmid-based systems led to ele-
vated cytoplasmic signal (Figure 2C and Supplemental Figure S2B, 
arrowheads). We quantified the absolute cytoplasmic concentration 
of AURKB-GFP using fluorescence correlation spectroscopy (FCS) in 
living cells. FCS records fluorescence intensity fluctuations in a small 
confocal volume as a function of time, allowing determination of 
physical properties, including the concentration of the fluorescent 
species from the amplitude of the FCS autocorrelation function 
(Figure 2D; see Materials and Methods). As such, it is well suited to 
the detection of mobile cytosolic proteins expressed at nanomolar 
to micromolar levels. AURKB-GFP genome-edited cells showed a 
clear autocorrelation signal distinguishable from that of wild-type 
cells (Supplemental Figure S2C), indicating the presence of a cyto-
plasmic pool. Consistent with our Western blotting, flow cytometry, 
and fluorescence microscopy data, FCS analysis showed that AURKB-
GFP genome-edited cells had a low cytoplasmic concentration of 
8.6 nM ± 5.3 SD (ZFN) or 6.9 nM ± 3.5 (TALEN), whereas overexpres-
sion from the plasmid-based systems resulted in significantly higher 
cytoplasmic concentrations of 23.8 nM ± 17.1 (BAC) or 86.7 nM ± 
156.7 (cDNA; Figure 2, E and F, and Supplemental Figure S2D). 
AURKB plays several critical roles in genome segregation via the 
phosphorylation of substrates on chromatin such as core histones 
and kinetochore proteins and by forming phosphorylation gradients 
(Tanaka et al., 2002; Wang et al., 2011; Carmena et al., 2012). The 
balance between soluble cytoplasmic and chromosome-bound ki-
nase is therefore key to interpreting its function. To determine 
whether the transgene method would perturb this balance, we 
quantified the amount of AURKB-GFP localized to chromosomes on 
the metaphase plate using FCS-calibrated confocal imaging in live, 
dividing cells. Here first we recorded an FCS trace in the cytoplasm 
to determine the absolute local concentration of GFP and calibrate 
the corresponding confocal pixel intensity, which thus allows us to 
transform the entire confocal image into a concentration map 
(Figure 3A). Despite the different total cell expression levels, BACs 
showed a similar chromatin-bound AURKB-GFP concentration to 
genome-edited cells, whereas cDNAs were very variable (Figure 3, 
B and C). By combining our concentration measurements with three-
dimensional reconstructed volumes of mitotic chromosomes and 
cytoplasm, we obtained the total number of chromatin-bound and 
free AURKB-GFP proteins. We found that the fraction of AURKB-
GFP bound to chromatin is significantly higher in genome-edited 
cells than in plasmid-based systems (Figure 3D). Whereas in ge-
nome-edited cells, ∼75% of total cellular AURKB-GFP resides on 
chromatin, only 40-50% does so in plasmid-based systems, with the </p>

<p>AURKB-GFP, which we validated with a series of assays (Figure 1B; 
see Materials and Methods for detailed protocols). Briefly, after in-
troduction of the tag, expressing cells were isolated by fluorescence-
activated cell sorting (FACS; Figure 1C) and then screened by fluo-
rescence microscopy for specific localization to mitotic organelles as 
expected for AURKB (Figure 1D; Terada et al., 1998). We distin-
guished homozygous from heterozygous clones (AURKB has three 
alleles in HeLa cells; Landry et al., 2013) for the genome-editing 
methods (Figure 1B; In vitro) by genomic PCR (Figure 1E and Sup-
plemental Figure S1A), Western blot (Figure 1F and Supplemental 
Figure S1B), and Southern blot (Figure 1G and Supplemental Figure 
S1, C and D). 
This validation workflow allowed us to select clones with homozy-
gous insertion of EGFP into all three AURKB alleles as well as 
heterozygous clones for further analysis. Independent of the target-
ing method used for genome editing, we found some evidence of 
extra integration sites by Southern blot (Figure 1G and Supplemental 
Figure S1, C and D). This did not result in unexpected size bands by 
genomic PCR or Western blot, however (Figure 1, E and F, and Sup-
plemental Figure S1, A and B), and therefore they likely lie in non-
coding regions. Homozygous and heterozygous AURKB-GFP cells 
exhibited indistinguishable cell cycle timing compared with wild-
type HeLa cells as measured by automated classification of live-cell 
imaging data (Held et al., 2010; Figure 1H and Supplemental Figure 
S1E) or flow cytometry (Supplemental Figure S1F), indicating that the 
fluorescent fusion protein was fully functional to support cell division. 
The complete set of cell lines used in this study is listed in Table 1. 
Having validated this set of AURKB-GFP cells generated from 
the same parental HeLa line, we systematically analyzed the behav-
ior of the expressed fusion proteins. First, we examined total ex-
pression level of AURKB-GFP by Western blotting of whole-cell ex-
tracts with anti-AURKB or anti-GFP antibodies (Figure 2A and 
Supplemental Figure S2A). All genome-edited clones exhibited 
AURKB-GFP levels similar to the endogenous protein with relatively 
little variation and independent of the genome-targeting method 
used to generate them or their zygosity (∼0.6-to 1.7-fold wild type). 
By contrast, expression of AURKB-GFP from randomly integrated 
BACs resulted in clearly visible overexpression in the tested clones 
(∼2.1-to 3.6-fold wild type), suggesting that the presence of the 
native promoter is not sufficient to ensure physiological expression </p>

<p>Expression system 
Name 
Transgene species </p>

<p>ZFN 
Z HZ1 
Human </p>

<p>ZFN 
Z HZ2 
Human </p>

<p>ZFN 
Z HET1 
Human </p>

<p>TALEN 
T HET1 
Human </p>

<p>TALEN 
T HET2 
Human </p>

<p>mBAC 
B P1 
Mouse </p>

<p>mBAC 
BC1 
Mouse </p>

<p>mBAC 
B P2 
Mouse </p>

<p>mBAC 
B C2 
Mouse </p>

<p>cDNA 
cD P1 
Human </p>

<p>cDNA 
cD C1 
Human </p>

<p>cDNA 
cD C2 
Human </p>

<p>cDNA 
cD C3 
Human </p>

<p>TABLE 1: Cell lines used in this study. </p>

<p>Volume 25 November 5, 2014 </p>

<p>Systematic comparison transgene methods | 3613 </p>

<p>that chromatin-binding sites become saturated in overexpression 
systems, forcing aberrant accumulation of the fusion protein in the 
cytosol. 
A key prerequisite for systems microscopy is to detect complexes 
incorporating the tagged protein inside the cell. It is known that </p>

<p>fraction decreasing as the total amount of AURKB increases. This 
relationship is in agreement with a mathematical model (solid line in 
Figure 3E; see Materials and Methods) that has a limited number of 
high-affinity binding sites on chromatin (∼130,000-150,000 mole-
cules), with a binding K d of 3.4-5.8 nM. Thus, our results suggest </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Expression system determines AURKB-GFP levels. (A) Western blot comparison of AURKB levels in 
nocodazole-arrested cells. BAC-expressed AURKB-GFP runs at a higher molecular weight due to the presence of an 
S-peptide in addition to the EGFP tag. The graph shows the mean ± SD of three independent experiments. (B) Flow 
cytometry analysis of AURKB-GFP intensity in nocodazole-arrested cells. Coefficient of variation is from the whole 
population. GFP+ was defined as 3 SD above autofluorescence from wild-type cells. (C) Sum intensity confocal images 
of AURKB-GFP using the same imaging conditions throughout. One metaphase cell is shown per panel. Left to right: 
ZHZ2, ZHZ1, ZHET1, THET1, THET2, BP1, BC1, BP2, BC2, cDP1, cDC1, cDC2, and cDC3. Scale bar, 7 μm. (D) The 
amplitude of the FCS autocorrelation function (see Materials and Methods), G(0), is inversely proportional to particle 
number. Absolute protein concentration, c, is calculated using the measured confocal volume, V. (E) AURKB-GFP FCS 
autocorrelation curves from single representative cells. Top to bottom: ZHZ2, THET1, ZHET1, cDC3, BP2, BC2, cDC2, 
and cDC1. (F) AURKB-GFP cytoplasmic concentration calculated by fitting FCS autocorrelation curves with a one-
component anomalous model of diffusion as described in Materials and Methods. The box and whiskers plot is from 
&gt;23 cells/sample from two experiments. The mean is depicted as a diamond and the median as a horizontal line, and 
the whiskers show the minimum and maximum. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: Overexpression alters AURKB-GFP biophysical properties on chromatin and in the cytosol. (A) Schematic of 
FCS-calibrated imaging. Concentration is determined in one location using FCS, and then an image is taken of the same 
cell. The image is converted to absolute concentrations using the FCS calibration. (B) Absolute concentration maps of 
AURKB-GFP in metaphase cells. The line profiles were taken in the areas depicted by the white arrows in the image 
directly above. Scale bar, 7 μm. (C) AURKB-GFP concentration on the metaphase plate. DNA was automatically 
identified based on a threshold of Hoechst staining of DNA (white line). Scale bar, 10 μm. (D) Fraction of AURKB-GFP 
proteins bound on chromatin. Horizontal bar shows the mean. (E) Fraction of chromatin bound AURKB-GFP (dots) as a 
function of the total number of AURKB proteins. The line is the equilibrium solution of a mass action model of reversible 
AURKB chromatin binding (see Materials and Methods; total number of chromatin-binding sites CT = 147,000, 
K d = 5.21 nM). (F) AURKB-GFP diffusion coefficient from FCS data of &gt;56 cells/sample from four experiments. 
(G) Single-cell-tracking automated FCS and time-lapse microscopy of AURKB-GFP diffusional mobility through the cell 
cycle as described in Materials and Methods. Plotted are the median and interquartile range from 9-45 cells. Scale bar, 
10 μm. Significance testing by Mann-Whitney test. </p>

<p>Volume 25 November 5, 2014 </p>

<p>Systematic comparison transgene methods | 3615 </p>

<p>Thus, phenotypically normal cells may still be unsuitable for quanti-
tative fluorescence microscopy. If quantitative imaging of in vivo 
proteomic parameters is the objective, genome editing appears to 
be the method of choice to fluorescently tag genes in human cells. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Constructs, cell line construction, and growth </p>

<p>Zinc finger nucleases were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, 
MO) with DNA-binding sequences in the 5′-3′ direction of CGC-
CTGATGGTCCCT and CACTCGGGTGCGTGTGTT. TALENs were 
from Cellectis Bioresearch (Romainville, France) with DNA-binding 
domains in the 5′-3′ direction of TTCACTCGGGTGCGTGT and 
TATGTATAGGGGAAAGA. The donor plasmid consisted of mEGFP 
cDNA sequence flanked by a left homology arm (ENSEMBL release 
75, ENST00000316199, chromosome 17:8108992-8108191) and a 
right homology arm (ENSEMBL release 75, ENST00000316199, 
chromosome 17:8107923-8108440), consisting of AURKB genomic 
sequence. ZFN/TALEN and donor plasmid transfection was with 
jetPRIME reagent (Polyplus, Illkirch-Graffenstaden, France). We in-
cubated 0.5 μg of each ZFN/TALEN and 1 μg of donor plasmid for 
15 min with 200 μl of jetPRIME buffer and 4 μl of jetPRIME before 
addition to cells grown to 80% confluency in a six-well dish with 2 ml 
of growth medium. After 4 h, the transfection mix was changed to 
normal medium. 
HeLa Kyoto cells were grown in DMEM supplemented with 10% 
fetal bovine serum at 37°C. Cells expressing AURKB-GFP mouse 
BAC as pool were previously described (Neumann et al., 2010), and 
further pools were also obtained as a kind gift from T. Hyman and I. 
Poser (Max Planck Institute of Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics, 
Dresden, Germany). cDNA AURKB-GFP was cloned by inserting 
GFP into the Sal1 and BamH1 sites of the vector AURKB-mCherry 
pEGFP-N1 (a kind gift of M. Isokane, European Molecular Biology 
Laboratory, Heidelberg, Germany). Cells expressing cDNA AURKB-
GFP were selected in 500 μg/ml neomycin and cells expressing 
cDNA H2B-mCherry with 0.3 μg/ml puromycin. </p>

<p>Fluorescence-activated cell sorting and flow cytometry </p>

<p>At 7-10 d posttransfection of genome-editing constructs, cells 
were synchronized with 2 mM thymidine for 18 h and subsequently 
released into fresh medium for 7-8 h. Mitotic cells were collected 
via mitotic shakeoff before sorting. GFP+ HeLa Kyoto cells were 
sorted with a MoFlo Legacy cell sorter (Beckman Coulter) equipped 
with a 100-μm nozzle. BD FACSFlow sheath (BD Biosciences, San 
Jose, CA) was used as sheath fluid, filtered in-line through a PALL 
Fluorodyne II filter 0.2 μm (Pall). A 488 nm-tuned Coherent Sabre 
laser (TEM 00 mode, 200 mW) was used for the excitation of GFP. 
Fluorescence was collected and detected after filtering through 
488-nm StopLine single-notch and 512/15 BP filters. Laser illumi-
nation, Moflo's L-configuration optical layout, and sorting were 
optimized using Flow-Check Fluorospheres (Beckman Coulter, 
Pasadena, CA). Sort decision was based on a combination of 
regions drawn around FSC-area versus SSC-area and FSC-area 
versus pulse width together with 488 nm-derived fluorescence 
512/15 BP (GFP) versus 670/40 BP (autofluorescence) plots. 
Parental HeLa Kyoto cells transfected only with donor plasmid 
were used as negative control. No correlation was seen between 
the level of AURKB-GFP expression and the number of alleles 
integrated by PCR and Western analysis. 
Cell cycle analysis was performed on an LSR-Fortessa SORP 
cytometer (BD Biosciences) after staining with propidium iodide 
(Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA); cells were washed in phosphate-buffered 
saline (PBS), fixed in cold 70% ethanol for &gt;2 h, washed in PBS, and </p>

<p>AURKB engages in numerous complexes in mitotic cells, including 
binding to members of the so-called chromosomal passenger com-
plex (Wang et al., 2011; Carmena et al., 2012), which should cause 
a decrease in its mobility in the cytoplasm. To assess whether the 
cytoplasmic accumulation in overexpressing clones would interfere 
with our ability to detect AURKB-containing complexes of low 
mobility, we determined the diffusion coefficient of AURKB-GFP by 
FCS. During interphase, AURKB-GFP cytoplasmic diffusion coeffi-
cients were indistinguishable between different transgene methods 
(ZFN, 13.2 μm 2 /s ± 6.4 SD; BAC, 14.0 μm 2 /s ± 4.6; Figure 3F, unfilled 
bars). However, metaphase cells exhibited significant differences in 
diffusion coefficient between expression systems (Figure 3F, filled 
bars). Genome-edited cells had reduced AURKB-GFP mobility com-
pared with interphase (ZFN, 6.5 μm 2 /s ± 3.9 SD), indicative of being 
bound to complexes of a larger Stokes radius, whereas in BAC cells, 
no significant change was detected (BAC, 14.7 μm 2 /s ± 3.9). Of 
interest, cDNA cells showed variable behavior, with a decrease in 
diffusional mobility detectable only in cells with low AURKB-GFP 
expression level (cD C3; ∼10 nM cytoplasmic) but not in higher-ex-
pressing clones (cD C2). Using automated time-lapse FCS to track 
single living nuclei through cell division, we acquired images and 
spectroscopy data every 15 min in dividing cells. Again, the cell cy-
cle-dependent reversible change in diffusion coefficient from G2 to 
mitosis to G1 indicative of complex formation could readily be de-
tected in single genome-edited cells but was not detectable in 
BAC-derived cells (Figure 3G). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Overall our findings show that the choice of transgene system 
strongly affects expression level and variability of fluorescently 
tagged genes in human cells. These expression changes have im-
portant consequences for the accurate quantitation of endogenous 
binding parameters using microscopy. Our data indicate a clear an-
ticorrelation between overexpression-with free ligand dominating 
the overall pool-and the ability to detect both specifically localized 
protein and protein engaged in large complexes. In terms of achiev-
ing a close to physiological expression level, the genome editing 
methods clearly outperformed plasmid-based approaches that suf-
fer from heterologous promoters (cDNA) and position-effect varie-
gation (cDNA and BAC). Furthermore, genome-edited cell lines 
showed far greater homogeneity, with almost any clone obtained by 
thorough screening (Figure 1) closely matching endogenous levels. 
Consistent with previous work (Doyon et al., 2011), this has implica-
tions for understanding the biology of cellular systems tagged with 
fluorescent proteins in human cells. However, it is also an important 
practical consideration when making cell lines stably expressing 
fluorescent fusion proteins, since it is often impossible to screen for 
true endogenous levels of expression in all subcellular pools. In ad-
dition, for essential genes, homozygous genome-edited cells en-
sure biological functionality of the fusion protein and exclude the 
possibility that complex formation and specific binding are obscured 
by the presence of unlabeled endogenous protein. 
A frequent argument for randomly integrated plasmid-based 
transgenes has been that for functionally important tagged genes, 
surviving clones would automatically select for physiological expres-
sion level (Rabut et al., 2004). Our case study with Aurora B provides 
reason for caution. We could generate stable plasmid-based cell 
clones with up to 100-fold overexpression that did not reveal gross 
phenotypic differences in cell division timing or histone H3 phos-
phorylation (Supplemental Figure S3, A-C). Nevertheless, the rele-
vant biophysical properties of Aurora B were completely obscured 
in these cells due to a massive unbound pool in the cytoplasm. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>phase length measurements, classification results were corrected 
with hidden Markov models afterward. </p>

<p>Western blotting </p>

<p>Cells were lysed for 20 min on ice in RIPA buffer (50 mM Tris HCl, 
pH 8, 150 mM NaCl, 1% NP40, 0.5 M sodium deoxycholate, 0.1% 
SDS, complete protease inhibitor cocktail, PhosSTOP [Roche]). 
Protein concentration was quantitated using the bicinchoninic acid 
method (Sigma-Aldrich). Antibodies used in overnight incubations 
were anti-AIM-1 1:400 (611082; BD Bioscience), anti-LEM4 (1:2000), 
and anti-GFP (Yavuz et al., 2010). Bands were quantified in Fiji using 
the Gel Analyzer tool and normalized relative to a standard on each 
gel consisting of either wild-type HeLa cells or ZFN clone HZ2. </p>

<p>Fluorescence correlation spectroscopy </p>

<p>Fluorescence correlation spectroscopy was performed with a Zeiss 
LSM 780 ConfoCor3 system as previously described (Maeder et al., 
2007; Schmidt et al., 2009). Samples were incubated at 37°C and 
excited with a 488-nm laser at minimal power (&lt;1 kW/cm 2 ) to re-
duce bleaching, photophysical effects, and cellular toxicity. Light 
was focused with a water immersion 40×/ 1.2 NA objective lens and 
collected by two avalanche photodiodes in the spectrally distinct 
regions 505-540 nm (F g ) and 600-650 nm (F r ) after passing through 
a pinhole set to 1 Airy unit. The instrument was calibrated before 
each experiment using Alexa 488 and Alexa 568 to align the pin-
holes and perform coverglass corrections. Each measurement was 
taken for 30 s in total. 
From the fluorescence time traces F g and F r , temporal autocor-
relation functions were calculated according to </p>

<p>G t 
F t F t </p>

<p>F t 
F t F t 
F t </p>

<p>dt G 
G t </p>

<p>( , ) 
( ) 
( 
) </p>

<p>( ) 
, 
( ) 
( ) 
( ) </p>

<p>1 
, 
( ) 
( , ) </p>

<p>g r </p>

<p>g r 
g r 
t </p>

<p>g r 
t </p>

<p>g r 
g r 
g r 
t </p>

<p>t 
t </p>

<p>t 
g r 
g r </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>/ 
/ 
, </p>

<p>/ 
, </p>

<p>2 
/ 
/ 
/ 
, </p>

<p>, 
/ 
/ </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>τ 
δ 
δ 
τ 
δ </p>

<p>θ 
τ 
τ θ </p>

<p>′ = 
+ 
= 
− </p>

<p>= 
= 
′ </p>

<p>θ </p>

<p>θ </p>

<p>θ </p>

<p>θ </p>

<p>θ </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>′ 
′ </p>

<p>′+ </p>

<p> 
 </p>

<p>( 1) </p>

<p>Here local averaging with a typical window size of θ ∼ 1 s allows 
for the correction of slow processes such as cellular movement and 
photobleaching. Resulting autocorrelation functions were then fit-
ted with a model function for anomalous diffusion including mole-
cular blinking as sources of fluctuations (Schmidt et al., 2009): </p>

<p>G 
N 
s 
( ) 
1 1 
e xp 
1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>g r 
D 
D 
/ 
blink </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1/2 </p>

<p>τ 
ρ ρ 
τ 
τ 
τ 
τ 
τ 
τ </p>

<p>( ) ( ) 
( ) </p>

<p>= 
− + 
− 
 
  </p>

<p> 
  ⋅ + </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
 
 </p>

<p> 
 ⋅ + 
 </p>

<p> 
 
 </p>

<p> 
 </p>

<p>α 
α 
− 
− </p>

<p>( 2) </p>

<p>where N = cV eff is the number of fluorescent molecules in the focal 
volume V eff and c their concentration, ρ is the fraction of molecules 
in a nonfluorescent state with a lifetime τ blink , and α is the anomaly 
parameter of diffusion resulting in a mean dwell time τ diff of the 
molecules in the focus. The diffusion coefficient D = w 0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>/4τ diff and 
the concentration c were extracted after calibrating the focal vol-
ume V eff = π 3/2 w 0 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s and the lateral and axial focal radii w 0 and sw 0 
using FCS measurements of Alexa 488 with a known diffusion coef-
ficient. For FCS data processing we used the <rs id="software-4" type="software">Fluctuation Analyzer</rs> 
software (written by <rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Malte Wachsmuth</rs>, European Molecular Biology 
Laboratory, Heidelberg, Germany; available upon request). 
Automated FCS with single-cell tracking was performed using 
an in-house-adapted Zeiss 780 ConfoCor3 system. Image and 
FCS acquisition were coordinated using a custom-written VBA 
macro (<rs type="software">AutofocusScreen</rs>, available on request), which coordinated </p>

<p>then stained with 40 μg/ml propidium iodide containing 0.1% 
Triton-100 and RNase A overnight at room temperature to ensure 
saturation of DNA staining. Cell cycle-stage analysis was performed 
by fitting with the cell cycle Watson (pragmatic) algorithm in <rs id="software-2" type="software">FlowJo</rs> 
v7.6.4 software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Tree Star</rs>, Ashland, OR). </p>

<p>Genomic PCR </p>

<p>Junction genomic PCR was performed at endogenous AURKB loci 
to detect the insertion of EGFP at the C-terminus using two separate 
sets of primers, one of which annealed inside GFP and one outside, 
as follows: AURKB forward (AGCTGGAGGTCCATCCTTGT), AURKB 
reverse (ATCACTGCTGCTTCTATTGGCT), and mEGFP reverse 
(gatgttgccgtcctccttga). PCR was performed using HotStar HiFidelity 
(Qiagen, Venlo, Netherlands) according to the supplier's manual and 
with a primer annealing temperature of 53ºC. </p>

<p>Southern blotting </p>

<p>Genomic DNA was prepared with the MasterPure DNA Purification 
Kit (Epicentre Biotechnologies, Madison, WI) according to the sup-
plier's manual. Twenty micrograms of genomic DNA was digested 
with either XbaI or KpnI/NsiI (NEB) at 37°C overnight. We performed 
0.8% agarose gel electrophoresis, and the gel was denatured with 
2× 20-min washes in 0.5 M NaOH/1.5 M NaCl. After neutralization 
by 2× 20-min incubation in 1.5 M NaCl/0.5 M Tris-HCl, pH 7.0, the 
DNA fragments were transferred via capillary forces from the gel to 
a Genescreen Plus R Nylon membrane (PerkinElmer, Boston, MA) in 
10× SSC (1.5 M NaCl/0.15 M Na 3 citrate⋅H 2 O). After cross-linking of 
the DNA via ultraviolet light (UVStratalinker 1800; Stratagene, La 
Jolla, CA), hybridization was performed using DIG Easy Hyb (Roche, 
Basel, Switzerland) accordingly to the manufacturer's guidelines. 
Digoxigenin-dUTP (DIG-dUTP)-labeled AURKB or mEGFP probes 
for detection were generated using the PCR DIG Probe Synthesis 
Kit (Roche). 
The sequence of the AURKB 3′ probe was TAAACAG TTCTGTAC 
CCTAGAAGCTGTCTTTGATTATTTCACTGCTCTGGTCAG-
GATCTAGTACAGGAGCCAATAGAAGCAGCAGTGATTCTGTCTT-
GTTCCTGACATGAGGTTACACTGTTATGCATGATGCTTGCTG-
TAGGTTTTTGATAGATACCCTTTATCAGGTTAAACAGGGCCTAT-
TCTACTCATAGTTTACTCAGAGTCTT. 
The sequence of AURKB intron 2 probe was ATGAA GAAGTTG 
AAAGTGAGAAGTGGTCCAGGGCCATCAGGGTAGCTCTTAGT-
GTCCTTAAAGCCTGTTCTTGCAAAAGTGTAAATCCTGGTTATT-
GCTATAACATTCAAGGCCTCAAGCATCTTATCTAAGCCT-
TAATAAACTAAGCTTTTTAGGAGACTTTGAGAATACCTCTGT-
GCTAAACCCCTTGAATTGTGGGTGTTCATTGACGCAGCTCTC-
TACTGTGGTGTAAGT. </p>

<p>Live-cell time-lapse imaging </p>

<p>Live-cell microscopy was at 37°C in CO 2 -independent medium with-
out phenol red (Invitrogen). A Zeiss 780 laser scanning confocal mi-
croscope with a 63× PlanApochromat, numerical aperture (NA) 1.4 
oil objective was used to acquire 512 × 512 pixel images with a pixel 
size of 0.439 μm at 5-min intervals. The z-stacks of eight slices 
spaced equally through 22.4 μm were acquired and formed into 
maximum-intensity z-projections. Automatic detection of nuclei in 
the H2B-mCherry channel and subsequent analysis of movies for 
mitotic timing were with <rs type="software">CellCognition</rs> software as described previ-
ously (Held et al., 2010). Briefly, six morphological classes were de-
fined: interphase, prophase, prometaphase, metaphase, anaphase, 
and telophase. The training set contained &gt;1000 manually labeled 
nuclei, which were annotated with an overall accuracy of &gt;95% in 
the cross-validation. To reduce the effect of classification errors on </p>

<p>Volume 25 November 5, 2014 </p>

<p>Systematic comparison transgene methods | 3617 </p>

<p>autofocusing, image acquisition, image analysis, and FCS. mCherry-
H2B images of nuclei were thresholded on the fly in Fiji (Schindelin 
et al., 2012) such that two FCS measurement positions per cell in the 
cytoplasm could be specified. FCS measurements were acquired for 
10 s per position, with imaging and FCS repeated at 15 min inter-
vals. Cells were aligned to metaphase after data acquisition. </p>

<p>FCS-calibrated imaging </p>

<p>One or a few FCS measurements were performed in the cytoplasm 
as described in Fluorescence correlation spectroscopy to extract the 
concentration at the respective locations. A confocal slice was then 
taken in the same cell with the same microscope configuration, us-
ing, however, the photomultiplier detectors such that intensities 
were not clipped off, nor was the detector saturated. The image in-
tensities were averaged locally at the FCS measurement spots and 
subsequently related to the measured concentration. This was per-
formed for all cells, yielding a linear relationship between intensity 
and concentration. This linear relationship between concentration 
and intensity was also confirmed in a serial dilution of Alexa 488 dye 
in water. Images were transformed to absolute concentrations after 
background intensity subtraction, where background was defined 
as an area of the image containing no cells. 
The number of moles, n, in a cellular compartment was estimated 
using </p>

<p>n cV 
= 
(3) </p>

<p>where c is the molar concentration, obtained either directly from an 
FCS measurement in the cytoplasm or from FCS-calibrated imaging 
of the chromatin. V is the volume, using estimates of 750 μm 3 for 
DNA and 5750 μm 3 for the cytoplasm (provided by Julius Hossain, 
European Molecular Biology Laboratory, Heidelberg, Germany) in 
metaphase cells. The number of proteins N is related to n by 
Avogadro's number, N A , </p>

<p>N nNA 
= 
(4) </p>

<p>Mathematical modeling </p>

<p>For AURKB binding to chromatin, C, we assume mass-action kinetics 
and reversible binding according to </p>

<p>AURKB + C ↔ AURKB-C </p>

<p>This leads to an equation for the concentration of AURKB bound 
to chromatin, A C , </p>

<p>dA 
dt 
k AC k A 
_ </p>

<p>C 
C </p>

<p>= 
− </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>where C and A are the concentration of chromatin-binding sites and 
AURKB in the cytoplasm, respectively. In equilibrium and assuming 
conservation of chromatin, C T = A C + C, and AURKB, A T = A + A C , 
one obtains for the fraction of molecules bound to chromatin </p>

<p>A 
A </p>

<p>A C 
K 
A C 
K 
A C 
A </p>

<p>( 
) 4 
2 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>T 
T 
d 
T 
T 
d 
T T </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>= 
+ 
+ 
− 
+ 
+ 
− 
(6) </p>

<p>with the dissociation constant K d = k − /k + . The measured fraction 
(A C /A T ) m also includes cytoplasmic proteins diffusing in the DNA 
region but not bound to DNA: </p>

<p>A 
A 
f 
A 
A 
f 
(1 ) </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>T m </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>( ) = + − </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>f 
V 
V 
V 
0.88 </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>cyt </p>

<p>cy 
DNA </p>

<p>= 
+ 
= 
(8) </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Tony Hyman and Ina Poser for donating the mouse BAC 
AURKB-GFP and thank all members of the Ellenberg laboratory for 
support. We thank Kota Miura for help in setting up the automated 
Fiji analysis and Bianca Nijmeijer for help with Southern blotting. 
This study was supported by funding from the European Commis-
sion within the MitoSys and SystemsMicroscopy consortia (FP7/2007-
2013-241548 and FP7/2007-2013-258068). R.M. was supported by 
an EMBO fellowship (ALTF 416-2012, GA-2010-267146) and a Well-
come Trust Henry Wellcome Fellowship (100090/Z/12/Z). </p>

<p>The unknown parameters K d and C T have been fitted to the data 
shown in Figure 3E. The number of untagged nonfluorescent AURKB 
proteins is assumed to be constant in all systems and equal to one-
third of the amount from homozygous knock-in cells. Therefore for 
cDNA and BAC cells, we assume that the total AURKB number 
(tagged plus untagged) is the sum of the measured protein number 
from the homozygous ZFN clone Z HZ2 plus the measured fluores-
cent protein number. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence </p>

<p>Cells grown on coverslips were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde/PBS 
for 5 min and permeabilized in 0.1% Triton X-100/0.1% Tween-20 
for 5 min. Cells were blocked in 3% bovine serum albumin for 1 h 
before primary antibody incubation for 2 h at room temperature. 
Antibodies used were anti-Aurora B pT232 (1:2000; Rockland 
Immunochemicals, Pottstown, PA), anti-histone H3 pS28 (1:500; 
10543; Abcam), and anti-histone H3 (1:500; 46765; Abcam). </p>





<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>



</text></tei>