<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4174131" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective We aimed to derive and validate a clinical 
decision rule (CDR) for suspected cardiac chest pain in 
the emergency department (ED). Incorporating 
information available at the time of first presentation, 
this CDR would effectively risk-stratify patients and 
immediately identify: (A) patients for whom 
hospitalisation may be safely avoided; and (B) high-risk 
patients, facilitating judicious use of resources. 
Methods In two sequential prospective observational 
cohort studies at heterogeneous centres, we included ED 
patients with suspected cardiac chest pain. We recorded 
clinical features and drew blood on arrival. The primary 
outcome was major adverse cardiac events (MACE) 
(death, prevalent or incident acute myocardial infarction, 
coronary revascularisation or new coronary stenosis 
&gt;50%) within 30 days. The CDR was derived by logistic 
regression, considering reliable (κ&gt;0.6) univariate 
predictors ( p&lt;0.05) for inclusion. 
Results In the derivation study (n=698) we derived a 
CDR including eight variables (high sensitivity troponin 
T; heart-type fatty acid binding protein; ECG ischaemia; 
diaphoresis observed; vomiting; pain radiation to right 
arm/shoulder; worsening angina; hypotension), which 
had a C-statistic of 0.95 (95% CI 0.93 to 0.97) implying 
near perfect diagnostic performance. On external 
validation (n=463) the CDR identified 27.0% of patients 
as 'very low risk' and potentially suitable for discharge 
from the ED. 0.0% of these patients had prevalent 
acute myocardial infarction and 1.6% developed MACE 
(n=2; both coronary stenoses without revascularisation). 
9.9% of patients were classified as 'high-risk', 
95.7% of whom developed MACE. 
Conclusions The Manchester Acute Coronary 
Syndromes (MACS) rule has the potential to safely 
reduce unnecessary hospital admissions and facilitate 
judicious use of high dependency resources. </p>

<p>BACKGROUND </p>

<p>Chest pain is the most common reason for emer-
gency hospital admission and the number of admis-
sions is increasing. 1 Only a minority of patients 
who are admitted to hospital on suspicion that they 
have an acute coronary syndrome ultimately have 
that diagnosis. 2 Improving diagnostic technology to 
'rule out' ACSs at the time patients first arrive in 
the emergency department (ED) could (A) reduce 
unnecessary hospital admissions, with potentially </p>

<p>substantial economic benefits for health services 
and (B) enable patients without serious disease to 
be given earlier reassurance. 
While the imperfect sensitivity and negative pre-
dictive value (NPV) of current diagnostic technol-
ogy at the time of arrival in hospital leads to 
unnecessary hospital admissions, suboptimal speci-
ficity and positive predictive value (PPV) also 
present challenges. Using a high sensitivity troponin 
assay, for example, over half of elderly patients 
who do not have acute myocardial infarction (AMI) 
will have elevated troponin levels on arrival. 3 As 
further information such as the δ troponin is not 
available at the time of arrival, there remains a 
need for novel decision aids that emergency physi-
cians may use to selectively target specialist referral 
and use of high dependency resources to patients 
who are at the highest acute risk, enabling judicious 
use of healthcare resources and avoiding exposure 
of patients to unnecessary treatment with its conse-
quent risks. 
We therefore sought to derive and subsequently 
externally validate a customised clinical decision 
rule (CDR) to guide the management of undiffer-
entiated patients presenting to the ED with possible 
cardiac chest pain. This CDR would combine clin-
ical information and biomarker levels. It would be 
designed to reduce unnecessary hospital admissions 
for very low-risk patients and to risk stratify the 
remaining patients, facilitating judicious resource 
use. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>This report details the primary analyses from two 
sequential prospective observational diagnostic 
cohort studies, first at Manchester Royal Infirmary, 
an inner city university affiliated teaching hospital 
(the derivation study) and subsequently at Stepping 
Hill Hospital, Stockport, a suburban district 
general hospital (the validation study). A number of 
secondary analyses have already been published 
from the derivation study. 4-9 
In both studies we included consenting adults 
aged &gt;25 years who presented to the ED within 
24 h of experiencing chest pain suspected to be 
cardiac in origin by the initial treating physician. 
We excluded patients with another medical condi-
tion requiring hospital admission, renal failure 
needing dialysis, significant chest trauma with </p>

<p>Open Access 
Scan to access more 
free content </p>

<p> 
Body R, et al. Heart 2014;100:1462-1468. doi:10.1136/heartjnl-2014-305564 </p>

<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>suspicion of myocardial contusion, pregnancy, those who did 
not speak English, prisoners and those for whom all means of 
follow-up would be impossible. All participants provided 
written informed consent and ethical approval for each study 
was obtained from the Research Ethics Committees (references 
05/Q1410/27 and 09/H1014/74). 
The treating clinician recorded clinical features and their 
ECG interpretation using a custom-designed case report form, 
which included check boxes for all the variables considered for 
inclusion in the decision rule. Clinical data were recorded at the 
time of presentation meaning that clinicians were blinded to 
patient outcome and the results of reference standard investiga-
tions. In these observational studies, all patients were managed 
according to the standard practice at each institution. 
Interobserver reliability was evaluated in a subgroup of 43 
(5.4%) patients and is fully reported elsewhere. 9 Blood was 
drawn at the time of presentation for biomarker evaluation. 
Serum and plasma samples were stored at −70°C pending later 
analysis. All patients underwent cardiac troponin T testing 
(cTnT, Roche Diagnostics fourth generation Elecsys, 99th 
centile 10 ng/L, coefficient of variation &lt;10% at 35 ng/L) on 
arrival and at least 12 h after symptom onset as part of the ref-
erence standard for AMI diagnosis. Patients were followed up 
after 30 days by telephone, email, letter, home visit or in clinic. 
If we were unable to complete follow-up by any of these means 
we contacted the patient's general practitioner. </p>

<p>Laboratory analyses </p>

<p>Aliquots of serum and plasma drawn at the time of arrival in 
the ED (regardless of the time from symptom onset) were tested 
for promising cardiac biomarkers that had been identified on lit-
erature review. Full details of each assay are described in the 
online supplementary appendix. In the validation study, admis-
sion and 12-h samples were tested for high-sensitivity cTnT 
(hs-cTnT) although these levels were not available to clinicians 
or used for clinical decision making during the study period. 
After the initial analysis, we became aware that the batch of 
reagents supplied by the manufacturer for measurement of 
hs-cTnT levels in the validation study had been affected by a 
calibration shift. 10 Thus, we retested aliquots of serum from all 
patients using an unaffected batch of reagents and repeated all 
statistical analyses, which are presented here. </p>

<p>Outcomes </p>

<p>The primary outcome was major adverse cardiac events (MACE) 
within 30 days. This was a composite of prevalent or incident 
AMI, death (all cause) or the need for coronary revascularisation 
(primary percutaneous coronary intervention or coronary artery 
bypass grafting). In the event that a patient was found to have a 
significant (&gt;50%) angiographic coronary stenosis (as reported by 
the treating interventional cardiologist) that was not known to be 
old, they were also deemed (a priori) to have met the primary 
outcome. This condition was intended to account for situations 
where a patient may have significant coronary disease that, 
because of technical difficulties or excessive risk, was not amenable 
to revascularisation. The diagnosis of AMI alone (ie, separated 
from the composite primary outcome) was a secondary outcome. 
The diagnosis of AMI was adjudicated by two independent 
investigators who had all clinical, laboratory and imaging evi-
dence available for review, but who were blinded to investiga-
tional biomarker levels. In accordance with the universal 
definition of AMI, 11 patients were required to have a troponin 
rise and/or fall (≥20 ng/L, based on the analytical characteristics 
of the assay) with at least one troponin measurement above the </p>

<p>99th centile (10 ng/L) in the appropriate clinical context. 
Disagreements (n=2) were resolved by discussion and were 
both explained by human error. </p>

<p>Sensitivity analyses </p>

<p>Since embarking on these studies, high sensitivity troponin 
assays have been implemented in practice and are now used to 
make the diagnosis of AMI at many institutions, which may 
increase the apparent prevalence of AMI. 12 In the validation 
study, therefore, we accounted for this possibility by analysing 
admission and 12-h samples for hs-cTnT. Two independent 
investigators then readjudicated outcomes based on hs-cTnT 
levels, blinded to the results of the previous adjudication and 
standard troponin T levels. A rise and/or fall of &gt;9.2 ng/L was 
considered to be statistically significant. 13 Disagreements (n=1) 
were resolved by discussion. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Derivation of the CDR </p>

<p>Variables that were predictors of AMI or MACE on univariate 
analysis by logistic regression ( p&lt;0.05) and variables with satis-
factory interobserver reliability (κ&gt;0.6) were considered for 
inclusion in the final model. A summary of the univariate ana-
lyses is reported in the online supplementary appendix and add-
itional data are published elsewhere. 5 9 To limit the potential 
for overfitting, only biomarkers with an area under the receiver 
operating characteristic curve of &gt;0.75 were considered for 
inclusion in the final model. 
Potential predictor variables were then entered into a multi-
variate analysis by forward stepwise logistic regression (p&lt;0.05 
for entry, p&gt;0.10 for removal, using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.20.0</rs>; SPSS, 
Chicago, Illinois, USA). Biomarker levels were entered as con-
tinuous variables to avoid the loss of potentially valuable diag-
nostic information at levels below and above dichotomous 
cut-offs. Hs-cTnT levels below the limit of blank for the assay 
(&lt;3 ng/L) were entered as 2 ng/L. We then used the predicted 
probability of developing the primary outcome (according to 
the final model) to categorise patients into four risk groups, 
which were defined a priori according to the disposition deci-
sions available to emergency physicians for this patient group: 
(1) Very low risk (suitable for discharge); (2) Low risk (suitable 
for a low dependency environment such as an ED observation 
unit); (3) Moderate risk (general or acute medical ward); and 
(4) High-risk ( patients who may be considered for immediate 
referral to a high dependency environment, eg, a coronary care 
unit). Diagnostic accuracy of the CDR was evaluated in deriv-
ation and validation studies by calculation of the areas under 
the receiver operating characteristic curves (AUCs), sensitivity, 
specificity, PPV and NPV together with 95% CIs (using 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">MedCalc</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">V.12.4.0.0</rs>, Mariakerke, Belgium). Baseline character-
istics of each cohort were compared by χ 2 testing (for independ-
ent proportions) or the Mann-Whitney U test (ordinal data) 
using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">V.20.0</rs>. 
After completion of the validation study, we noted that 
tobacco smoking had been excluded from the initial multivariate 
analysis in error. We therefore repeated the multivariate analysis 
with tobacco smoking included. The resultant alternative deci-
sion rule and its performance are presented in the online sup-
plementary appendix. </p>

<p>Sample size 
Derivation study </p>

<p>Methodological guidance for the derivation of CDRs states that 
approximately 10 subjects with the primary outcome are </p>

<p>Body R, et al. Heart 2014;100:1462-1468. doi:10.1136/heartjnl-2014-305564 </p>

<p>
Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>required for every predictor included in the decision rule. 14 
Based on the numbers of predictive variables identified by previ-
ous studies of patients with chest pain 15 16 and practical consid-
erations, we felt it was unlikely that the final decision rule 
would incorporate more than 15 predictors, thus requiring 150 
patients with the primary outcome to provide appropriate statis-
tical power. We estimated a 20% incidence of the primary 
outcome 17 18 and predicted 5% loss to follow-up, which would 
require a total of 790 participants. </p>

<p>Validation study </p>

<p>To determine the sample size for the validation study, we deter-
mined the number of patients that would be required to ensure 
that, if the CDR was shown to have a sensitivity of 100%, the 
95% CI would extend no lower than 95%. Assuming a 20% 
incidence of the primary outcome, a sample size of 450 partici-
pants would ensure this degree of precision. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>In total 698 patients were included in the derivation study 
between January 2006 and February 2007, all of whom com-
pleted follow-up (figure 1). Of these patients 130 (18.6%) had 
AMI and 157 (22.5%) developed the primary outcome (MACE 
within 30 days). The validation study included a total of 463 
patients between April and July 2010, all of whom completed 
follow-up (figure 1). Of those patients, 79 (17.1%) had AMI 
and 98 (21.2%) developed MACE within 30 days. Baseline 
characteristics for each study are shown in table 1. </p>

<p>Derivation of the Manchester Acute Coronary 
Syndromes rule </p>

<p>A summary of the univariate analyses is shown in the online 
supplementary appendix. The final decision rule derived by 
multivariate analysis included eight variables (table 2). In the 
derivation study the rule had an AUC of 0.95 (95% CI 0.93 to 
0.97) for predicting MACE. Based on the estimated probability 
assigned by the model, The MACS rule stratified patients into </p>

<p>four risk groups (figure 2). The MACS rule successfully stratified 
patients according to their risk of MACE and AMI. Its use could 
have enabled the 35.5% of patients in the MACS rule 'very low 
risk' group to be immediately discharged with zero (0.0%) 
missed AMIs and one (0.4%) missed MACE (a patient with 
normal ECG and normal troponin who underwent inpatient 
coronary angiography and percutaneous coronary intervention 
to lesions in the left anterior descending and circumflex arter-
ies). Thus, as a dichotomous tool for guiding the decision about 
whether to admit or discharge patients, the MACS rule had an 
overall sensitivity of 99.4% (95% CI 96.5% to 100.0%) and 
NPV 99.6% (97.8% to 100.0%) for MACE. For AMI, </p>

<p>Figure 1 Patient flow diagram. </p>

<p>Table 1 Baseline characteristics of included patients </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Derivation 
study 
(N=698) </p>

<p>Validation 
study 
(N=463) 
p Value </p>

<p>Age in years, mean (SD) 
58.6 (14.3) 
64 (15) 
Men (%) 
429 (61.5) 
270 (58.3) 
0.303 
Previous angina (%) 
220 (31.5) 
186 (40.2) 
0.002 
Previous myocardial infarction (%) 
166 (23.8) 
139 (30.0) 
0.023 
Hypertension (%) 
341 (48.9) 
197 (42.5) 
0.037 
Hyperlipidaemia (%) 
337 (48.3) 
186 (40.2) 
0.008 
Diabetes mellitus (%) 
125 (17.9) 
80 (17.3) 
0.854 
Smoking (%) 
216 (30.9) 
96 (20.7) 
&lt;0.001 
Family history of coronary heart 
disease (%) </p>

<p>337 (48.3) 
171 (36.9) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Previous coronary intervention (%) 
140 (20.1) 
102 (22.0) 
0.480 
Peripheral vascular disease (%) 
13 (1.9) 
15 (3.2) 
0.224 
Cerebrovascular disease (%) 
71 (10.2) 
30 (6.5) 
0.037 
Time from symptom onset 
0-3 h 
324 (46.4) 
212 (45.8) 
0.079 
3-6 h 
166 (23.8) 
94 (20.3) 
6-12 h 
148 (21.2) 
64 (13.8) 
&gt;12 h 
60 (8.6) 
93 (20.1) </p>

<p> 
Body R, et al. Heart 2014;100:1462-1468. doi:10.1136/heartjnl-2014-305564 </p>

<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>sensitivity was 100.0% (97.2% to 100.0%) and NPV 100.0% 
(98.5% to 100.0%). Of the patients in the 'high-risk' group 
(10.6% of the entire cohort) 100.0% developed MACE and 
98.6% had AMI. </p>

<p>External validation </p>

<p>The performance of the MACS rule on external validation is 
shown in figure 3. Again, the MACS rule effectively stratified 
patients according to their risk of MACE and AMI. The rule 
had an AUC of 0.92 (95% CI 0.89 to 0.95) for MACE. The 
125 (27.0%) patients in the 'very low risk' group could have 
been immediately discharged with zero (0.0%) missed AMIs 
and two (1.6%) MACEs within 30 days. Both of these events 
were coronary stenoses detected at angiography but that were 
not deemed to warrant coronary intervention. Thus the MACS 
rule would have enabled decisions to admit or discharge patients 
to have been made with a sensitivity of 98.0% (95% CI 93.0% 
to 99.8%) and NPV 98.7% (95.3% to 99.8%) for MACE. For 
AMI, the MACS rule had a sensitivity of 100.0% (95% CI 
95.4% to 100.0%) and NPV 100.0% (97.1% to 100.0%). Of 
the 'high-risk' patients (n=46, 9.9% of the entire cohort) 
95.7% developed MACE and 91.3% had AMI. </p>

<p>Sensitivity analyses </p>

<p>With a readjudicated diagnosis of AMI using hs-cTnT as the ref-
erence standard, the rates of MACE and AMI stratified by 
MACS rule risk group are shown in figure 4. Again, two (1.6%) 
patients in the very low risk group developed MACE, which 
were both coronary stenoses not deemed to warrant revasculari-
sation. The AUC was 0.92 (95% CI 0.88 to 0.95). As a dichot-
omous tool for facilitating immediate hospital discharge, the 
MACS rule had an overall sensitivity of 98.4% (94.3% to 
99.8%) and NPV 97.9% (92.8% to 99.8%) for MACE. For 
AMI, the sensitivity was 100.0% (95.3% to 100.0%) and NPV 
100.0% (97.0% to 100.0%). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We have presented the derivation and subsequent external valid-
ation of the MACS CDR for use in patients presenting to hos-
pital with suspected cardiac chest pain, which could potentially 
obviate the need for emergency hospital admission for over a 
quarter of patients following a single blood test. This has great 
potential benefit for patients, who could be immediately reas-
sured that they do not have AMI and that any appropriate 
follow-up can safely be arranged on an outpatient basis. Given 
the large number of patients affected (over a quarter of acute 
medical admissions), use of the MACS rule may help to relieve 
the increasing pressure on EDs, where overcrowding is asso-
ciated with more patient safety incidents and rising mortality. 19 
The potential cost saving for health services is also substantial. 
In addition to identifying very low risk patients for whom 
unnecessary hospital admission may be avoided, the MACS rule 
risk stratifies the remaining patients. While the low and moder-
ate risk patients still require further inpatient investigation 
before an acute coronary syndrome can be confirmed or 
excluded, patients in the high-risk group had a very high preva-
lence of AMI and incidence of MACE, potentially facilitating 
selective specialist referral and targeting of high dependency 
resources with high specificity and PPV. 
A number of alternative 'early rule out' strategies have been 
reported. Several CDRs have been derived for use in the ED 
population, although their usefulness is limited by low specifi-
city and none were derived in the era of high sensitivity tropo-
nins. 20 21 Serial biomarker testing over 60-120 min could 
facilitate safe early discharge of low-risk patients with chest 
pain, 22-25 although such strategies may not always be 
cost-effective. 26 Using high sensitivity troponin alone it may be 
possible to exclude AMI within 60-180 min of presentation. 27 28 </p>

<p>Table 2 Multivariate model detailing the components of the 
MACS rule (rounded values are presented) </p>

<p>Variable 
Constant 
OR (95% CI) 
p Value </p>

<p>a. High sensitivity troponin T* 
0.068 
1.1 (1.0 to 1.1) 
&lt;0.0001 
b. Heart-type fatty acid binding 
protein* </p>

<p>0.17 
1.2 (1.0 to 1.4) 
0.018 </p>

<p>c. ECG ischaemia 
1.75 
5.8 (3.1 to 10.8) 
&lt;0.0001 
d. Sweating observed 
1.85 
6.3 (3.0 to 13.3) 
&lt;0.0001 
e. Vomiting 
1.72 
5.6 (1.9 to 16.6) 
0.002 
f. Systolic blood pressure 
&lt;100 mm Hg </p>

<p>1.46 
4.3 (1.2 to 15.1) 
0.022 </p>

<p>g. Worsening angina 
0.92 
2.5 (1.2 to 5.2) 
0.014 
h. Pain radiating to right arm or 
shoulder </p>

<p>0.87 
2.4 (1.0 to 5.6) 
0.044 </p>

<p>Constant 
−4.83 
-
-</p>

<p>The model estimates the probability (p) of MACE as follows (rounded values are 
presented): p=1/(1+e −(0.068a + 0.17b + 1.75c + 1.85d + 1.72e + 1.46f + 0.92g + 0.87h − 4.83) ). 
For each categorical variable, a value of 1 is assigned if the characteristic is present 
and 0 if absent. 
*ORs are presented for a 1 unit increase (ng/L for hs-cTnT; ng/mL for H-FABP). 
MACE, major adverse cardiac events; MACS, Manchester Acute Coronary Syndromes. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Performance of the 
Manchester Acute Coronary Syndromes 
decision rule in the derivation study. 
The suggested disposition for each 
group is as follows: 'Very low risk'-
discharge immediately (estimated 
probability, p, of MACE &lt;0.02); 'low 
risk'-admit to low dependency 
environment, for example, emergency 
department observation unit, 
0.02≤p&lt;0.05); 'moderate risk'-admit 
to acute ward, for example, medical 
admissions unit (0.05≤p&lt;0.95); 'high 
risk'-admit to coronary care unit or 
high dependency environment 
(p≥0.95). AMI, acute myocardial 
infarction; MACE, major adverse 
cardiac events. </p>

<p>Body R, et al. Heart 2014;100:1462-1468. doi:10.1136/heartjnl-2014-305564 </p>

<p>
Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>A secondary analysis from our cohort suggested that a single 
hs-cTnT level below the limit of blank may be sufficient to 
exclude AMI, although this would not facilitate the immediate 
discharge of as many patients as the MACS rule and does not 
make use of clinical, ECG and biochemical data to optimise risk 
stratification. 4 Finally, the HEART score is an emerging alterna-
tive that may enable the safe early discharge of a proportion of 
patients presenting to the ED. 29 Prospective comparison of the 
MACS rule with the most promising of these emerging tech-
nologies is an important area for future research. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations </p>

<p>This MACS rule was derived in accordance with established 
methodological guidance 14 and provides a bespoke tool to aid 
clinical decision making specifically in the undifferentiated ED 
population. It has the potential to reduce unnecessary hospital 
admissions by facilitating the immediate discharge of over a 
quarter of patients using a single blood test at the time of 
arrival. The MACS rule also effectively risk stratifies the remain-
ing patients, identifying high-risk patients with high PPV and 
suggesting courses of action to the clinician. We hope that this 
will prevent a rebound overuse of resources, as has happened 
with previous rapid rule-out strategies that have high sensitivity 
but relatively low specificity. 26 
The MACS rule has several novel features. It combines clinical 
and biochemical data and incorporates contemporary biomarker 
levels, which are considered as continuous variables. This maxi-
mises the richness of diagnostic information that may be lost by </p>

<p>dichotomisation and enables levels even below the 99th centile 
to influence the initial risk stratification, building and improving 
upon a previous analysis from our derivation cohort. 4 
We also consider that inclusion of a second prospective exter-
nal validation study is a strength of this report. This work 
enabled the performance of the MACS rule to be verified in a 
heterogeneous (as demonstrated in table 1) and independent 
population, reducing the potential for statistical overfitting and 
overestimation of diagnostic performance. 
There are some limitations to our work. We aimed to derive 
and validate a CDR that could be used to guide decisions made 
in the ED at the time of initial presentation or following a 
single blood test. However, with the addition of serial sampling 
at 60-90 min it may have been possible to safely identify an 
even greater proportion of patients as eligible for safe early dis-
charge. This strategy has shown promise when used with bio-
marker panels and serial troponin testing, particularly in 
low-risk patients. 22 23 27 Future work should explore whether 
refinements to include early serial sampling will enhance diag-
nostic performance of the MACS rule. Comparison with emer-
ging alternatives such as the HEART score will also be 
important. 
It is important to acknowledge that the MACS rule applies to 
the specific biomarkers and clinical observations used. Future 
assessment with even larger cohorts and other combinations of 
newer biomarkers or observations might, in due course, enable 
further refinement and stratification of the clinical decision-
making process in this group of patients. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Performance of the 
Manchester Acute Coronary Syndromes 
decision rule in the validation study. 
Both MACEs in the very low risk group 
were coronary stenoses identified on 
an outpatient basis that did not require 
intervention. AMI, acute myocardial 
infarction; MACE, major adverse 
cardiac events. </p>

<p>Figure 4 Performance of the 
Manchester Acute Coronary Syndromes 
decision rule with high-sensitivity 
cardiac troponin T (hs-cTnT) as the 
reference standard for the adjudicated 
diagnosis of AMI (validation study). 
A total of 77 patients (16.6%) were 
given a readjudicated diagnosis of AMI 
and 97 (21.0%) developed MACE. 
AMI, acute myocardial infarction; 
MACE, major adverse cardiac events. </p>

<p> 
Body R, et al. Heart 2014;100:1462-1468. doi:10.1136/heartjnl-2014-305564 </p>

<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>Finally, the MACS rule requires a complex calculation necessi-
tating the use of a computer. Rather than categorising or dichot-
omising variables, we have opted to retain the richness of our 
data to optimise diagnostic performance. Other computerised 
clinical prediction models are in widespread use in current clin-
ical practice. The Global Registry of Acute Coronary Events 
score is a good example. 30 As it is almost certain that clinicians 
practising in a contemporary ED with access to contemporary 
biomarker assays will have access to computers in order to 
undertake the required calculation, we do not consider that this 
will limit the usefulness of the MACS decision rule in a clinical 
setting. </p>

<p>Future directions </p>

<p>Having derived and successfully externally validated the MACS 
rule in two sequential observational studies, it is now imperative 
to further evaluate its impact when used in practice. Use of the 
MACS rule may lead to changes in the subsequent investigations 
and treatment that patients receive, which may affect outcome 
rates. Compliance with the decision rule by physicians and 
patients is also unlikely to be perfect. Furthermore, use of the 
rule may still have unanticipated effects such as increasing actual 
resource utilisation. 26 A randomised controlled trial is therefore 
warranted prior to widespread implementation, with analyses 
focusing on clinical, economic and process outcomes. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>We have derived and externally validated the MACS CDR for 
use in patients presenting to the ED with suspected cardiac 
chest pain. Over 25% of patients could be immediately dis-
charged, reducing unnecessary admissions, while selectively 
identifying high-risk patients to make judicious use of specialist 
resources. It is now important to evaluate the clinical and cost-
effectiveness of the MACS rule when it is used in clinical 
practice. </p>

<p>Key messages </p>

<p>What is already known on this subject? 
Current diagnostic technology, including high sensitivity 
troponin assays, has imperfect sensitivity and specificity for 
acute coronary syndromes at the time of initial presentation to 
the emergency department. There is a need for diagnostic tools 
that may help to reduce unnecessary hospital admissions while 
making judicious use of specialist resources. </p>

<p>What this study adds? 
Using information available at the time of first presentation and 
results from a single blood test, the Manchester Acute Coronary 
Syndromes rule could enable more than a quarter of patients to 
be immediately discharged. The rule also selectively identifies 
high-risk patients, which may help emergency physicians to 
target specialist referral and use of high dependency resources 
to those patients at highest risk. </p>

<p>How might this impact on clinical practice? 
Chest pain is the most common reason for emergency hospital 
admission in England and Wales. A decision rule that reduces 
the need for unnecessary hospital admission would have 
tremendous economic benefits for the Health Service while 
reducing inconvenience and exposure to the risks of 
unnecessary treatment for patients. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors acknowledge the support of the Manchester 
Academic Health Science Centre, the Manchester Biomedical Research Centre, the 
National Institute for Health Research (UK) and all of the staff in the emergency 
departments and biochemistry departments at Manchester Royal Infirmary and 
Stepping Hill Hospital who assisted with this work. </p>

<p>Contributors Each author has contributed to the analysis and interpretation of the 
data, drafting and approval of the final manuscript. All authors have also 
contributed to the conception/design of either or both of the studies reported in this 
manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding The derivation study was supported by: (A) research fellowship funding 
from the Centre for Effective Emergency Care, which is a collaboration between 
Manchester Metropolitan University and Central Manchester University Hospitals 
NHS Foundation Trust; (B) a research grant from Central Manchester University 
Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust; (C) reagents donated for the purposes of this 
research by Roche Diagnostics and Randox Laboratories. The validation study was 
funded by a grant from the UK College of Emergency Medicine, was supported by: 
(A) fellowship funding (an Academic Clinical Lectureship for the first author) from 
the UK National Institute for Health Research (NIHR); (B) by the NIHR Clinical 
Research Network (UK CRN 8376); and (C) reagents donated for the purposes of 
the research by Roche Diagnostics. </p>

<p>Competing interests Roche and Randox have paid for the travel (Roche and 
Randox) and accommodation (Roche, 2009) of the corresponding author to present 
research findings. </p>

<p>Patient consent Obtained. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Research Ethics Committee (references 05/Q1410/27 and 09/ 
H1014/74). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement All requests for further data from this study should be 
addressed to the corresponding author. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the 
Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, which 
permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, 
and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is 
properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>

<p> </p>

<p>
Coronary artery disease </p>



<p> 
Body R, et al. Heart 2014;100:1462-1468. doi:10.1136/heartjnl-2014-305564 </p>

<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

</text></tei>