<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4799566" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: It is often challenging to distinguish tuberculous pleural effusion (TPE) from malignant pleural effusion (MPE); thoracoscopy 
is among the techniques with the highest diagnostic ability in this regard. However, such invasive examinations cannot be performed on 
the elderly, or on those in poor physical condition. The aim of this study was to explore the differential diagnostic value of carbohydrate 
antigen 125 (CA125), carbohydrate antigen 199 (CA199), carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA), neuron-specific enolase (NSE), and squamous 
cell carcinoma (SCC) associated antigen in patients with TPE and MPE. 
Methods: Using electrochemiluminescence, we measured the concentration of tumor markers (TMs) in the pleural effusion and serum 
of patients with TPE (n = 35) and MPE (n = 95). We used receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve analysis to evaluate the TMs 
and differentiate between TPE and MPE. 
Results: The cut-off values for each TM in serum were: CA125, 151.55 U/ml; CA199, 9.88 U/ml; CEA, 3.50 ng/ml; NSE, 13.27 ng/ml; 
and SCC, 0.85 ng/ml. Those in pleural fluid were: CA125, 644.30 U/ml; CA199, 12.08 U/ml; CEA, 3.35 ng/ml; NSE, 9.71 ng/ml; and SCC, 
1.35 ng/ml. The cut-off values for the ratio of pleural fluid concentration to serum concentration (P/S ratio) of each TM were: CA125, 5.93; 
CA199, 0.80; CEA, 1.47; NSE, 0.76; and SCC, 0.90. The P/S ratio showed the highest specificity in the case of CEA (97.14%). ROC curve 
analysis revealed that, for all TMs, the area under the curve in pleural fluid (0.95) was significantly different from that in serum (0.85; P &lt; 0.001). 
Conclusions: TMs in TPE differ significantly from those in MPE, especially when detected in pleural fluid. The combined detection of 
TMs can improve diagnostic sensitivity. </p>

<p>Key words: Malignant Pleural Effusion; Tuberculous Pleural Effusion; Tumor Marker </p>

<p>Access this article online </p>

<p>Quick Response Code: 
Website: 
www.cmj.org </p>

<p>DOI: 
10.4103/0366-6999.174501 </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Address for correspondence: Dr. Huan-Zhong Shi, 
Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, Beijing Chao-Yang 
Hospital, Beijing Institute of Respiratory Medicine, Capital Medical 
University, Beijing 100020, China 
Center of Medical Research, Beijing Institute of Respiratory Diseases, 
Beijing 100020, China 
E-Mail: shihuanzhong@sina.com </p>

<p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, 
tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited 
and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms. </p>

<p>For reprints contact: reprints@medknow.com </p>

<p>© 2016 Chinese Medical Journal ¦ Produced by Wolters Kluwer -Medknow </p>

<p>Received: 10-10-2015 Edited by: Li-Min Chen 
How to cite this article: Gu Y, Zhai K, Shi HZ. Clinical Value of 
Tumor Markers for Determining Cause of Pleural Effusion. Chin Med 
J 2016;129:253-8. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ February 5, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 3 </p>

<p>
associated antigen. However, their cut-off values and 
sensitivities in identifying MPE are not well understood. </p>

<p>This retrospective study aimed to assess the diagnostic 
capability of each of the following TMs: CA125, CA199, 
CEA, NSE, and SCC. Their levels were measured in both 
serum and the pleural fluid to differentiate between TPE and 
MPE. Furthermore, the ratio of pleural fluid concentration 
to serum concentration (P/S ratio) for each TM was also 
assessed. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Patients and classification of pleural effusion </p>

<p>We enrolled 130 consecutive patients who had been treated 
at the Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine 
of the Beijing Chao-Yang Hospital between January 2013 
and December 2013. </p>

<p>A diagnosis of MPE (n = 95) or TPE (n = 35) was made based 
on thoracoscopy. The origin and histological types of MPE 
were lung adenocarcinoma (n = 62), lung SCC (n = 5), small 
cell lung carcinoma (n = 9), pleural mesothelioma (n = 12), 
breast cancer (n = 3), ovarian cancer (n = 1), hepatic 
cancer (n = 1), lymphoma (n = 1), and leukemia (n = 1). </p>

<p>Clinical radiological characteristics </p>

<p>The following clinical and radiological characteristics were 
considered [Tables 1 and 2]: (1) PE size (three categories: 
&lt;1/3 of the hemithorax; ≥1/3, but ≤2/3 of the hemithorax; 
&gt;2/3 of the hemithorax), 
[6] and (2) simple X-ray or computed 
tomography images suggestive of malignancy (lung masses, 
pulmonary atelectasis, lung nodules, infiltrated shadow, 
cavity, pleural nodules, and pleural thickening). </p>

<p>Tumor markers assay </p>

<p>Pleural fluid and blood were collected before any 
treatment. Both serum and pleural fluid were centrifuged 
at 3000 r/min for 15 min. TM assays were performed 
using electrochemiluminescence kits (Abbott Laboratories 
i2000™; Abbott Park, USA for CA125, CA199, CEA, and 
SCC; Cobas 6000™; Roche, Mannheim, Germany for NSE). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> statistical software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">17.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs>, USA) was used for data 
processing. The data were mostly expressed as the median 
and interquartile range (IQR). Concentration differences 
between the TPE and MPE groups were evaluated for 
statistical significance using the nonparametric Mann-
Whitney U-test. The optimal sensitivity and specificity points 
were selected as the critical values using the area under the 
receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve; in this way, 
we calculated, for each of the TMs, the sensitivity, specificity, 
positive predictive value, and negative predictive value 
for diagnosing TPE and MPE. In addition, we evaluated 
the ability of a combination of all five TMs to distinguish 
between TPE and MPE. Three prognostic models were 
constructed: Model 1 involved the serum level of TMs, 
Model 2 the pleural fluid level, and Model 3 the P/S ratio. 
P &lt; 0.05 were considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>General clinical data </p>

<p>The study included 23 men and 12 women with TPE 
(median age = 66 years, range = 19-93 years), and 
54 men and 41 women with MPE (median age = 67 years, 
range = 20-99 years). The two groups did not differ 
significantly in terms of age or sex. </p>

<p>Table 2 shows the main clinical and radiological 
characteristics of the patients. A greater percentage of 
patients in the TPE group than in the MPE group experienced 
fever (45.71%; P &lt; 0.001). The two groups also showed 
significant differences in terms of imaging parameters; 
namely, single nodules, pleural nodules, localized pleural 
thickening, and mediastinal hilum lymph node enlargement, 
which is defined as a node diameter &gt;1 cm (P &lt; 0.05 in all 
cases). </p>

<p>Detection of the five tumor markers in pleural fluid and 
serum </p>

<p>Table 1 shows the median concentrations and IQRs of the 
five TMs examined -in both serum and pleural fluid. All 
five TMs were detected in the pleural fluid and serum of 
all patients; however, the concentrations were significantly 
different between the two groups (P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Receiver operating characteristic analysis of the tumor 
markers to differentiate between tuberculous pleural 
effusion and malignant pleural effusion </p>

<p>Table 3 shows the diagnostic value of the five TMs in serum 
and pleural fluid, as well as the P/S ratio for discriminating 
between TPE and MPE. The cut-off values for each TM in 
serum were: CA125, 151.55 U/ml; CA199, 9.88 U/ml; CEA, 
3.50 ng/ml; NSE, 13.27 ng/ml; and SCC, 0.85 ng/ml. CA125 
showed the highest specificity (88.57%) for distinguishing 
between TPE and MPE, but it had low sensitivity (33.68%). 
The cut-off values for the TMs in pleural fluid were: CA125, 
644.30 U/ml; CA199, 12.08 U/ml; CEA, 3.35 ng/ml; NSE, 
9.71 ng/ml; and SCC, 1.35 ng/ml. Those of the P/S ratio for 
each TM were: CA125, 5.93; CA199, 0.80; CEA, 1.47; NSE, 
0.76; and SCC, 0.90. Moreover, the P/S ratio of CEA had 
the highest specificity (97.14%) and sensitivity (61.05%). </p>

<p>We evaluated the diagnostic value of a combination of all 
five TMs in serum and pleural fluid; we analyzed the P/S 
ratio in the same regard. To this end, we established the 
following diagnostic models: Model 1 involved the serum 
level of all TMs; Model 2 the pleural fluid level; Model 3 
the P/S ratio: 
• Model 1 = −2.597 + 0.001 (CA125) + 0.058 (CA199) 
+ 0.353 (CEA) + 0.073 (NSE) + 0.388 (SCC); cut-off 
value = 0.934 
• Model 2 = −4.243 + 0.002 (CA125) + 0.103 (CA199) 
+ 0.360 (CEA) + 0.122 (NSE) + 0.512 (SCC); cut-off 
value = 1.592 
• Model 3 = −4.048 + 0.135 (CA125) + 0.309 (CA199) 
+ 1.108 (CEA) + 2.592 (NSE) + 0.367 (SCC); cut-off 
value = 0.984. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ February 5, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 3 </p>



<p>Table 1: Carbohydrate antigen 125, carbohydrate antigen 199, carcinoembryonic antigen, neuron-specific enolase 
and squamous cell carcinoma in patients with tuberculous pleural effusion and malignant pleural effusion </p>

<p>Histological types 
Tuberculosis 
Adenocarcinoma 
SCC 
Small cell carcinoma 
Mesothelioma </p>

<p>Serum 
CA125 (U/ml) 
74.42 
(28.91-120.95) </p>

<p>92.47 
(35.27-197.03) </p>

<p>171.40 
(114.40-277.40) </p>

<p>106.10 
(55.64-152.90) </p>

<p>47.30 
(19.72-81.27) 
CA199 (U/ml) 
6.03 
(3.04-10.79) </p>

<p>15.99 
(10.16-51.59) </p>

<p>38.19 
(28.87-39.34) </p>

<p>17.49 
(14.28-29.17) </p>

<p>6.27 
(5.68-15.60) 
CEA (ng/ml) 
1.60 
(1.10-2.15) </p>

<p>6.35 
(3.40-23.43) </p>

<p>5.10 
(4.30-26.90) </p>

<p>2.60 
(1.40-8.10) </p>

<p>1.85 
(1.50-2.50) 
NSE (ng/ml) 
13.23 
(11.99-17.27) </p>

<p>14.34 
(11.79-17.91) </p>

<p>19.62 
(16.53-21.12) </p>

<p>52.25 
(23.77-112.40) </p>

<p>14.48 
(13.18-15.89) 
SCC (ng/ml) 
0.60 
(0.40-0.80) </p>

<p>0.60 
(0.50-0.90) </p>

<p>3.70 
(3.10-5.10) </p>

<p>1.00 
(0.70-1.70) </p>

<p>0.90 
(0.60-1.10) 
Pleural fluid 
CA125 (U/ml) 
277.00 
(104.73-561.15) </p>

<p>1172.00 
(508.43-2244.75) </p>

<p>616.90 
(177.30-1108.00) </p>

<p>932.00 
(500.60-1590.00) </p>

<p>383.30 
(316.62-651.05) 
CA199 (U/ml) 
2.93 
(1.62-4.85) </p>

<p>36.99 
(6.97-198.17) </p>

<p>8.55 
(4.04-17.39) </p>

<p>22.70 
(6.01-129.40) </p>

<p>3.39 
(2.66-6.11) 
CEA (ng/ml) 
1.20 
(0.70-1.50) </p>

<p>82.05 
(15.17-487.30) </p>

<p>3.90 
(3.50-7.50) </p>

<p>6.10 
(2.00-48.00) </p>

<p>1.10 
(1.00-1.75) 
NSE (ng/ml) 
8.57 
(6.80-9.61) </p>

<p>9.62 
(7.57-10.93) </p>

<p>10.72 
(8.12-10.72) </p>

<p>58.67 
(21.64-132.17) </p>

<p>8.62 
(8.09-9.82) 
SCC (ng/ml) 
0.70 
(0.35-1.00) </p>

<p>0.80 
(0.70-1.37) </p>

<p>15.10 
(11.40-67.10) </p>

<p>1.60 
(1.00-2.50) </p>

<p>1.00 
(0.40-2.10) 
P/S ratio 
CA125 
3.07 
(1.17-6.22) </p>

<p>10.70 
(4.78-22.50) </p>

<p>2.76 
(0.83-5.39) </p>

<p>8.74 
(3.65-16.66) </p>

<p>11.90 
(6.97-18.65) 
CA199 
0.53 
(0.38-0.74) </p>

<p>1.00 
(0.41-3.89) </p>

<p>0.46 
(0.30-0.48) </p>

<p>1.29 
(0.44-3.20) </p>

<p>0.50 
(0.27-0.62) 
CEA 
0.70 
(0.55-0.91) </p>

<p>7.52 
(2.16-22.54) </p>

<p>0.76 
(0.75-0.81) </p>

<p>3.36 
(0.95-4.36) </p>

<p>0.60 
(0.44-0.74) 
NSE 
0.56 
(0.44-0.70) </p>

<p>0.63 
(0.49-0.80) </p>

<p>0.51 
(0.49-0.68) </p>

<p>0.95 
(0.87-1.12) </p>

<p>0.60 
(0.52-0.74) 
SCC 
0.85 
(0.68-1.34) </p>

<p>1.36 
(1.00-2.41) </p>

<p>3.69 
(3.08-4.70) </p>

<p>1.47 
(0.90-3.33) </p>

<p>0.78 
(0.50-2.17) 
Values are expressed as median and 25 </p>

<p>th </p>

<p>-75 
th percentiles in parenthesis. CEA: Carcinoembryonic antigen; NSE: Neuron-specific enolase; 
SCC: Squamous cell carcinoma; CA125: Carbohydrate antigen 125; CA199: Carbohydrate antigen 199; P/S: Pleural fluid concentration to serum 
concentration. </p>

<p>Table 4 shows the predicted outcome: The accuracy 
of Model 2 (88.15%) was higher than that of the other 
models (P &lt; 0.001). The ROC curves are shown in 
Figure 1. </p>

<p>dIscussIon </p>

<p>PE can be caused by more than 50 diseases, including 
primary lung disease, systemic disease, organ dysfunction, 
drug-induced PE, and tumor metastasis. It is important 
in clinical practice to analyze both the cause and clinical 
features in patients with PE; for this purpose, cytological 
examination is routinely performed. However, the 
positive diagnostic rate of this technique is about 50% 
in patients with MPE. 
[8] Even though adenocarcinoma is 
the most common cause of MPE, a significant number of 
hematological and nonhematological causes also exist. 
To ensure an accurate diagnosis, cytopathologists, and 
clinicians must keep these uncommon phenomena in mind 
during routine practice. </p>

<p>[9]   The currently available data indicate that, in cases where 
aspiration cytology reveals negativity for exudative 
PE, thoracoscopy under local anesthetic is among the 
techniques with the highest diagnostic ability; the method 
has about 88-96% diagnostic sensitivity for malignant 
pleural disease. 
[10-12] However, such invasive examinations 
cannot be performed in the elderly, or in those in poor 
physical condition. Uncontrollable coughing from 
pleural irritation also contraindicates thoracoscopy, as it 
is hazardous to access and visualize the whole pleura in 
such cases. </p>

<p>[13]   Currently, the cause of PE is unclear in nearly 20% of 
patients, 
[14] and many researchers have shown that TMs 
may help differentiate TPE from MPE. Furthermore, a 
combination of several TMs may improve the diagnostic 
power for MPE. 
[5,8,15-18] The choice of TMs in this study was 
based on those used in clinical practice to detect ovarian 
cancer (CA125), gastrointestinal and lung cancer (CA199), 
digestive and lung cancer (CEA), nonsmall cell lung </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ February 5, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 3 </p>

<p>
cancer (SCC), and small cell lung cancer (NSE). The serum 
and pleural fluid concentrations of CA125, CA199, CEA, and 
NSE were significantly higher in MPE than in TPE (P &lt; 0.05); 
similar results have been reported in other studies. </p>

<p>[2,19,20]   We reviewed studies addressing the level of TMs in serum 
and pleural fluid, but only a few described P/S ratio. 
[21,22] In 
this study, we found that the P/S ratios of CEA and CA125 
were lower in TPE than in MPE. Korczynski et al. </p>

<p>[23]   reported a similar result regarding CEA, although the P/S 
ratio of CA125 was not significantly different. Li et al. </p>

<p>[24]   found that higher CA125 levels are associated with an 
increased risk of coronary heart disease in elderly Chinese 
individuals, and that CEA exhibited 70% sensitivity and 
100% specificity for adenocarcinoma cells in PE. </p>

<p>[3]   We believe that these differences may be due to the 
number of pooled patients, as well as to the etiology of 
the analyzed PE in the two studies. Using ROC analysis, 
we determined the cut-off values of CA125, CA199, CEA, </p>

<p>NSE, and SCC in serum and pleural fluid. However, their 
specificities in diagnosing MPE varied. Model 2 had 
better accuracy (86.92%) in terms of MPE diagnosis. 
Pleural fluid cut-off values for differential diagnosis were 
generally higher than those of serum; however, this finding 
does not justify routinely measuring classic TMs in the 
workup of PEs. </p>

<p>There were several limitations to our research. For instance, 
only a small number of patients were enrolled, especially in 
the case of TPE. Furthermore, the majority of primary tumors 
were in the lung; much fewer occurred in other organs. In 
future, we will enroll a larger number of patients with PE 
and design a randomized controlled trial to research the 
differential diagnosis between TPE and MPE. </p>

<p>An ideal diagnostic combination of TMs would have high 
specificity and sensitivity. In cases where MPE is suspected, 
but cytological findings are negative, the level of TMs in 
serum and pleural fluid, as well as the P/S ratio, should 
be evaluated before performing invasive procedures; this 
would help optimize the cost-benefit ratio. First, pleural 
CEA measurement is likely to be useful in diagnosing 
MPE, just as it is in the differentiation of malignant pleural 
mesothelioma from metastatic lung cancer -a high level 
of pleural CEA seems to rule out malignant mesothelioma. 
Second, CA125, CA199, NSE, and SCC are highly specific, 
but insufficiently sensitive to diagnose MPE, although the 
combination of more TMs appears to increase the diagnostic 
sensitivity. </p>

<p>The present study describes a diagnostic model that involves 
five TMs in serum and pleural fluid. In particular, since the 
detection of TMs in pleural fluid has high specificity (100%) 
and accuracy (86.92%), it may be useful in distinguishing 
MPE from TPE. The results of TM assays should be 
interpreted in parallel with clinical findings, and with the 
results of conventional tests. </p>

<p>Figure 1: In Model 1, we evaluated all five tumor markers in serum. In 
Model 2, we evaluated the five tumor markers in pleural fluid. In Model 
3, the ratio of the tumor marker concentration in pleural fluid to that in 
serum was analyzed. </p>

<p>Table 2: Clinical and radiological characteristics of 
patients with pleural effusion </p>

<p>Characteristics 
TPE (n = 35) MPE (n = 95) 
P </p>

<p>n Percentage n Percentage </p>

<p>Smoking 
15 
42.86 
41 
43.16 
0.975 
Dyspnea 
25 
71.43 
80 
84.21 
0.101 
Chest pain 
14 
40.00 
27 
28.42 
0.208 
Cough 
25 
71.43 
67 
70.53 
0.920 
Phlegm 
14 
40.00 
36 
37.89 
0.827 
Hemoptysis 
0 
0.00 
8 
8.42 
0.076 
Fever 
16 
45.71 
10 
10.53 
&lt;0.001 
Weight loss 
7 
20.00 
25 
26.32 
0.458 
Pulmonary atelectasis 
0.413 
Obstructive atelectasis 5 
14.29 
16 
16.84 
Compression atelectasis 17 
48.57 
34 
35.79 
Mass 
1 
2.86 
1 
1.05 
0.458 
Single nodule 
0 
0.00 
38 
40.00 
&lt;0.001 
Multiple nodule 
2 
5.71 
16 
16.84 
0.103 
Infiltrated shadow 
6 
17.14 
28 
29.47 
0.156 
Cavity 
23 
65.71 
66 
69.47 
0.682 
Pleural nodules 
0 
0.00 
25 
26.32 
&lt;0.001 
Pleural thickening 
0.006 
Local 
11 
31.43 
59 
62.11 
Diffusion 
11 
31.43 
13 
13.68 
Lymphadenectasis 
0.027 
≤1 cm 
17 
48.57 
38 
40.00 
&gt;1 cm 
4 
11.43 
33 
34.74 
Laterality 
0.866 
Left 
15 
42.86 
37 
38.95 
Right 
14 
40.00 
43 
45.26 
Bilateral 
6 
17.14 
15 
15.79 
Quantity 
0.683 
&lt;1/3 
1 
2.86 
1 
1.05 
1/3-2/3 
7 
20.00 
16 
16.84 
&gt;2/3 
27 
77.14 
78 
82.11 
TPE: Tuberculous pleural effusion; MPE: Malignant pleural effusion. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ February 5, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 3 </p>



<p>Financial support and sponsorship </p>

<p>This work was supported by grants from National Natural 
Science Foundation of China (No. 91442109, No. 31470883, 
and No. 81270149). </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest </p>

<p>There are no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>references </p>



<p>Table 3: Diagnostic value of five tumour markers in serum, pleural effusion and the ratio of pleural effusion and 
serum for the discrimination between tuberculous pleural effusion and malignant pleural effusion </p>

<p>TM 
Cut-off 
value </p>

<p>AUC 
Specificity 
(%) </p>

<p>Sensitivity 
(%) </p>

<p>Accuracy 
(%) </p>

<p>PLR 
NLR 
LR 
PPV 
(%) </p>

<p>NPV 
(%) </p>

<p>Serum 
CA125 (U/ml) 
151.55 
0.58 
88.57 
33.68 
48.46 
2.95 
0.75 
3.94 
88.89 
32.98 
CA199 (U/ml) 
9.88 
0.76 
74.29 
67.37 
69.23 
2.62 
0.44 
5.96 
87.67 
45.61 
CEA (ng/ml) 
3.50 
0.79 
80.00 
58.95 
64.62 
2.95 
0.51 
5.74 
88.89 
41.79 
NSE (ng/ml) 
13.27 
0.58 
54.29 
70.53 
66.15 
1.54 
0.54 
2.84 
80.72 
40.43 
SCC (ng/ml) 
0.85 
0.57 
77.14 
36.84 
47.69 
1.61 
0.82 
1.97 
81.40 
31.03 
Pleural fluid 
CA125 (U/ml) 
644.3 
0.78 
82.86 
61.05 
66.92 
3.56 
0.47 
7.58 
90.62 
43.94 
CA199 (U/ml) 
12.08 
0.81 
97.14 
53.68 
65.38 
18.79 
0.48 
39.41 
98.08 
43.59 
CEA (ng/ml) 
3.35 
0.86 
94.29 
74.74 
80.00 
13.08 
0.27 
48.81 
97.26 
57.89 
NSE (ng/ml) 
9.71 
0.66 
77.14 
52.63 
59.23 
2.30 
0.61 
3.75 
86.21 
37.50 
SCC (ng/ml) 
1.35 
0.69 
91.43 
36.84 
51.54 
4.30 
0.69 
6.22 
92.11 
34.78 
P/S ratio 
CA125 
5.93 
0.75 
74.29 
67.37 
69.23 
2.62 
0.44 
5.96 
87.67 
45.61 
CA199 
0.80 
0.64 
82.86 
51.58 
60.00 
3.01 
0.58 
5.15 
89.09 
38.67 
CEA 
1.47 
0.79 
97.14 
61.05 
70.77 
21.37 
0.40 
53.30 
98.31 
47.89 
NSE 
0.76 
0.64 
85.71 
38.95 
51.54 
2.73 
0.71 
3.83 
88.10 
34.09 
SCC 
0.90 
0.69 
60.00 
75.79 
71.54 
1.89 
0.40 
4.70 
83.72 
47.73 
TM: Tumor marker; AUC: Area under the receiver operating characteristic curve; PLR: Positive likelihood ratio; NLR: Negative likelihood ratio; PPV: 
Positive predictive value; NPV: Negative predictive value; LR: Likelihood ratio; CA125: Carbohydrate antigen 125; CA199: Carbohydrate antigen 199; 
CEA: Carcinoembryonic antigen; NSE: Neuron-specific enolase; SCC: Squamous cell carcinoma; P/S: Pleural fluid concentration to serum concentration. </p>

<p>Table 4: Diagnostic value of combination of five tumor 
markers in serum, pleural effusion and the ratio of pleural 
effusion and serum for achieving the best diagnostic 
accuracy </p>

<p>TM 
Cut-off 
value </p>

<p>AUC Specificity 
(%) </p>

<p>Sensitivity 
(%) </p>

<p>Accuracy 
(%) </p>

<p>Model 1 
0.93 
0.85 
91.43 
73.68 
78.46 
Model 2 
1.59 
0.95 
100.00 
82.11 
86.92 
Model 3 
0.98 
0.91 
91.43 
78.95 
82.31 
In Model 1: We evaluated all of five TMs in serum; in Model 2: We 
evaluated five TMs in pleural fluid; in Model 3: We evaluated all of the 
TMs in the P/S ratio. TM: Tumor marker; AUC: Area under the receiver 
operating characteristic curve; P/S: Pleural fluid concentration to serum 
concentration. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ February 5, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 3 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>