<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4443457" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background and purpose -Unloading alters the thickness of 
joint cartilage. It is unknown, however, to what extent unload-
ing leads to a loss of glycosaminoglycans (GAGs) in the cartilage 
tissue. We hypothesized that muscle forces, in addition to axial 
loading, are necessary to maintain the joint cartilage GAG con-
tent of the knee and the upper and lower ankle. 
Patients and methods -The HEPHAISTOS orthosis was 
worn unilaterally by 11 men (mean age 31 (23-50) years old) for 
56 days. The orthosis reduces activation and force production of 
the calf muscles while it permits full gravitational loading of the 
lower leg. MRI measurements of the knee and ankle were taken 
before the intervention, during the intervention (on day 49), and 
14 days after the end of the intervention. Cartilage segmentation 
was conducted semiautomatically for the knee joint (4 segments) 
and for the upper (tibio-talar) and lower (subtalar) ankle joints 
(2 segments each). Linear mixed-effects (LME) models were used 
for statistical analysis. 
Results -8 volunteers completed the MRI experiment. In 
the lower ankle joint, differences in ΔT 1 were found between the 
end of the intervention and 14 days after (p = 0.004), indicating a 
decrease in GAG content after reloading. There were no statisti-
cally significant differences in ΔT 1 values in the knee and upper 
ankle joints. 
Interpretation -Our findings suggest that in addition to 
gravitational load, muscular forces affect cartilage composition 
depending on the local distribution of forces in the joints affected 
by muscle contraction. </p>

<p> </p>

<p>Unloading has been shown to cause a decrease in cartilage 
thickness (Vanwanseele et al. 2002a, b, Hinterwimmer et al.  2004, Eckstein et al. 2006, Liphardt et al. 2009, Wang et al.  2010) and is thought to lead to a loss of glycosaminoglycans 
(GAGs) in cartilage tissue (Bashir et al. 1996, 1999). Reduced 
GAG content may be interpreted as an early sign of cartilage 
degeneration (Bashir et al. 1996). Cartilage is known to be 
sensitive to mechanical strain, but it is unclear how far axial 
loading, shear forces, and the pull of the muscles on bone 
contribute to the adaptation of joint cartilage GAG content to 
unloading. 
To investigate the effects of selective muscular unloading 
during normal gravitational load on the lower limb, the HEP-
HAISTOS orthosis was developed and tested in an ambulatory 
clinical interventional study (the HEP study). During walking 
and standing, the orthosis substantially reduces the activation 
of the calf muscles and the production of force on the forefoot 
in the plantar direction, while it permits full gravitational load-
ing of the ankle joint and the lower leg (Weber et al. 2013a). 
It has been shown that muscle contractions have a key role in 
generation of strain in bone during locomotion, and are there-
fore crucial for mechano-adaptation of bone (Rittweger 2008). 
Increased joint cartilage thickness, as found in athletes 
(Eckstein 2014), improves cushioning and protects against 
wear-off. Cartilage thickness is known to depend on both 
mechanical and biochemical factors (Niehoff et al. 2011). 
We investigated the effects of chronically reduced forces 
produced by the plantar flexors, in combination with normal 
axial weight loading, on joint cartilage. The unique feature of </p>

<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2015; 86 (3): 388-392 </p>



<p>the study was that the orthosis enabled us to reduce muscular 
forces while keeping gait and load normal. Delayed gadolin-
ium-enhanced MRI of cartilage (dGEMRIC) was chosen to 
assess changes in the cartilage tissue (Bashir et al. 1996, 1997,  1999, Burstein et al. 2001). We used a standard MRI hard-
ware protocol for dGEMRIC imaging. This protocol has been 
applied to knee joint cartilage in a large number of studies 
(Bashir et al. 1996, 1997, 1999, Burstein et al. 2001, Mayer- hoefer et al. 2010) and to the upper ankle joint in only a few 
studies so far (Domayer et al. 2010, Wiewiorski et al. 2013). 
dGEMRIC measurements of the lower ankle joint have not 
been published before, probably because they are technically 
more demanding. 
We hypothesized that a chronic reduction of plantar flexion 
forces would result in a reduction in GAG content in the carti-
lage of the ankle joints and the knee. We also hypothesized that 
joints that are normally loaded to a higher degree by calf muscle 
contraction would react on calf muscle unloading to a greater 
extent than those joints that are less influenced by calf muscle 
contractions. Thus, effects would be expected to be greatest in 
the lower ankle joint followed by the upper ankle joint. Only 
small effects, if any, would be expected in the knee joint. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Study setting 
The HEPHAISTOS study (HEP study) was conducted at the 
German Aerospace Center in Cologne, Germany, and is regis-
tered at www.clinicaltrials.gov (identifier: NCT01576081). It 
was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Northern Rhine 
Medical Association (Ärztekammer Nordrhein, Düsseldorf, 
Germany, no. 2010169). Out of 11 men (mean age 31 (23-50) 
years) who wore the orthosis unilaterally for 56 days, 8 com-
pleted the MRI experiment presented here. 2 volunteers had 
to be excluded from further MRI measurements after show-
ing symptoms of contrast-agent intolerance and 1 refused to 
participate in the MRI measurements. The study protocol and 
details of the organization, schedule, and methods of the HEP 
study have already been published by Weber et al. (2013a). </p>

<p>The HEPHAISTOS orthosis 
The orthosis causes unloading of the calf muscles while per-
mitting a near to normal gait, thus maintaining full impact of 
the body mass on the ankle and the lower leg (Figure 1). It 
substantially reduces plantar flexor torque and muscle acti-
vation (measured by electromyography), and it affects arte-
rial diameter (measured by ultrasound) (Weber et al. 2013a,  b,2014). When the orthosis is worn, normal movement in the 
knee joint is possible. Flexion and extension are limited in the 
upper ankle joint, while supination and pronation of the lower 
ankle joint are not possible. Tibio-talar forces are reduced by 
three-quarters, while femoro-tibial forces are unaltered when 
wearing HEPHAISTOS. Force development of the gastrocne-</p>

<p>mius muscle and its pull on the calcaneus through the Achilles 
tendon are reduced by the absence of counter-forces on the 
forefoot (unpublished observations). The mechanical role of 
the ankle during walking is taken over by a metallic joint below 
the foot with an integrated spring that replaces the role of the 
calf muscle. To investigate the influence of the orthosis on 
joint cartilage, we analyzed the knee joint and the upper (tibio-
talar) and lower (subtalar) ankle joints. The orthosis was man-
ufactured individually for each subject by ORTEMA GmbH 
(Markgröningen, Germany). The volunteers had to wear the 
HEPHAISTOS orthosis for 56 days, during all locomotive 
activities that required loading of the leg. The following link 
leads to the webpage of the DLR with a video clip presenting 
the HEPHAISTOS unloading orthosis: http://www.dlr.de/me/ 
en/desktopdefault.aspx/tabid-7389/12432_read-35410/. </p>

<p>The dGEMRIC protocol 
MRI scans were done according to the dGEMRIC protocol 
(Mayerhoefer et al. 2010). Each volunteer underwent MRI 
scans of the ankle and knee of the intervention leg before the 
intervention (BDC), on day 49 of the intervention (HEP49), 
and 14 days after the end of the intervention phase (R+14). 
Each time, MRI scans were performed before and after inter-
venous administration of the gadolinium-based contrast agent 
Gd-DOTA (Dotarem; gadoteric acid, 0.4 mg per kg body 
mass). </p>

<p>MRI 
MRI scans of the ankle and the knee were obtained with a 
knee coil in a 3T MRI scanner (Achieva; Philips Medical 
Systems). Measurements were taken with 2 flip angles of 5° 
and 25°, and calculations were performed according to May- erhoefer et al. (2010). Signal intensities were calculated for 
each pixel and intensities were corrected from a B1-map (map 
of relative pulse angles). Scaling of maps was adjusted and 
T1 was calculated pixel-wise. Each ankle measurement was 
planned with a series of cross-sectional images based on sagit-
tal pilot images. From the ankle, 2 individual slices were ana-
lyzed with a 160 × 160 mm field of view, an acquisition matrix 
of 704 × 704 pixels, and 3 mm slice thickness. From the knee, 
2 individual slices were analyzed with a 160 × 160 mm field 
of view, an acquisition matrix of 560 × 560 pixels, and 3 mm 
slice thickness. </p>

<p>Calculation of ΔT 1 values and segmentation 
Segmentation was performed semiautomatically for the areas 
shown in Figure 2. This means that a ROI was first set manu-
ally, and a threshold algorithm was applied to the selected 
region before the cartilage region was defined by region-grow-
ing. The knee joint cartilage was subdivided into 4 segments 
of equal height for analysis. For the ankle joints, a proximal 
segment and a distal segment of equal height were selected. 
The ankle joint cartilage was not thick enough for the analysis 
of more subsegments in the resolution available. </p>



<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2015; 86 (3): 388-392 </p>

<p>Statistics 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS Statistics</rs> release <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">20.0.0</rs> was used to calculate linear 
mixed-effects (LME) models with segment, measurement, 
and their interaction as fixed effects and subjects as a random 
effect (variance components). Significance was assumed at 
p &lt; 0.05. The assumptions made were a normal distribution 
of the raw data and the residuals. The Kolmogorov-Smirnov 
test showed a normal distribution of ΔT 1 values in the carti-
lage of the upper ankle joint (p = 0.6, residuals p = 0.9), the 
lower ankle joint (p = 0.8, residuals p = 0.6), and the knee (p 
= 0.9, residuals p = 0.4). Data are presented as counts with 
their SD. Exclusion conditions were ΔT 1 times of &lt; 400 ms 
and &gt; 1,500 ms. SigmaPlot software version 12.0 was used to 
plot data. ΔT 1 was the primary outcome measure of this study. 
An increase in ΔT 1 corresponded to a decrease in the GAG 
content. </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>An overview of average ΔT 1 values for each site and each 
measurement is provided in Figure 3. Further details are 
shown in Figure 4. </p>

<p>The knee joint 
The LME model revealed a significant difference in ΔT 1 
values between segments (p &lt; 0.001) but no statistically 
significant difference between measurements, either for the 
entire knee cartilage (p = 0.5) or for the interaction with the 
individual segments (p = 0.9). Throughout the study, cartilage 
closer to the bone had lower ΔT 1 values than cartilage further 
away from the bone. </p>

<p>The upper ankle joint 
There was no statistically significant difference between the 
ΔT 1 values of the 2 segments (proximal and distal, p = 0.4) </p>

<p>Figure 1. The HEPHAISTOS 
orthosis. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Segmentation of the upper (green) and lower (red) 
ankle joint (articulatio subtalaris) with a distal and a proximal 
segment each (panel A), and the knee joint (segments 0-3) 
(panel B). </p>

<p>Figure 3. ΔT 1 values in the course of the study, in 
each joint for each volunteer. The baseline mea-
surement was taken before the intervention (base-
line data collection, BDC), the second measure-
ment was on day 49 of the intervention (HEPHAIS-
TOS, HEP49), and the third measurement was 14 
days after the end of the intervention (recovery, 
R+14). ΔT 1 indicates the GAG content (lower ΔT 1 
values reflect higher GAG content). </p>

<p>Figure 4. ΔT 1 values of the separate segments of the knee joint (A), the upper ankle joint (B) and the lower ankle joint (C) in the individual volun-
teers throughout the course of the study. In the knee joint, values differ significantly among segments (p &lt; 0.001). ΔT 1 indicates the GAG content 
(lower ΔT 1 values reflect higher GAG content). </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2015; 86 (3): 388-392 </p>



<p>or between measurements (p = 0.2). The interaction between 
segment and measurement was not significant either (p = 0.7). </p>

<p>The lower ankle joint 
We found a difference in ΔT 1 values between measurements, 
with higher ΔT 1 after the intervention than before (p = 0.004). 
The effect occurred after reloading. ΔT 1 values were similar 
when comparing the proximal and distal segment (p = 0.7), 
and no statistically significant differences could be found 
when we analyzed the interaction between segment and mea-
surement (p = 0.2). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The HEPHAISTOS orthosis makes it possible to investigate 
the effects of widely inactive lower leg muscles during normal 
gravitational load patterns as experienced in everyday life, 
without any substantial change in gravitational and mass-iner-
tial skeletal forces (Weber et al. 2013a). Our main findings 
were as follows. (1) A decrease in GAG content of the lower 
ankle (subtalar) joint cartilage was found to occur not during 
the intervention, but after reloading. (2) Axial load alone was 
sufficient to maintain the cartilage GAG content of the upper 
ankle joint. The GAG content of the knee joint cartilage was 
not affected either. (3) The dGEMRIC method can be applied 
to the lower ankle joint. </p>

<p>Observations in the literature 
The dGEMRIC protocol was initially developed to assess the 
glycosaminoglycan content of knee joint cartilage (Bashir  et al. 1996, 1997, 1999, Burstein et al. 2001). The dGEM-
RIC method was recently applied to the upper ankle joint 
(Domayer et al. 2010, Wiewiorski et al. 2013). To our knowl-
edge, the dGEMRIC method has not been applied to the lower 
ankle joint before, probably because the cartilage is thin 
and segmentation is technically difficult. We found that the 
dGEMRIC protocol can be used to assess relative changes in 
the GAG content of the lower ankle joint, which may be of 
interest for research in foot and ankle surgery as well as for 
rheumatology. 
Unloading has been shown to reduce cartilage thickness 
(Eckstein et al. 2014). By analyzing MRI images taken before 
and after 14 days of 6° head down tilt bed rest in human sub-
jects, Liphardt et al. (2009) showed that the articular knee car-
tilage thickness is sensitive to unloading. They found a sub-
stantial decrease in thickness of the tibial knee joint cartilage 
but not in the thickness of femoral knee joint cartilage. Wang  et al. (2010) performed a 4-week tail suspension study on rats 
and found decreases in cartilage thickness of the patella and 
the medial femoral condyle. Vanwanseele et al. (2002a, b)  found progressive thinning of the knee cartilage in patients 
with spinal cord injuries. Hinterwimmer et al. (2004) showed 
thinning of articular cartilage already after 7 weeks of par-</p>

<p>tial load bearing. Regarding cartilage thickness, changes were 
usually found to occur throughout unloading and not after 
reloading. 
Mayerhoefer et al. (2010) analyzed the effect of 15 min of 
unloading of the knee joint on T1-Gd with the dGEMRIC 
method and found that there was no statistically significant 
effect on T1-Gd relaxation times. Long-term unloading of 
human joint cartilage has not, however, been investigated pre-
viously with this method. The effects of selective muscular 
unloading on joint cartilage during normal weight bearing had 
also not been investigated before our study. One might think 
that the GAG content decreases during unloading, just as car-
tilage thickness has been shown to decrease. Our results, how-
ever, indicate that a decrease in glycosaminoglycan content 
may occur after reloading following muscular inactivation, 
depending on the joint location and the type of immobiliza-
tion. It remains unclear, however, whether reloading causes 
remodeling or whether remodeling is just delayed and takes 
a while to occur. Other studies have shown changes in GAG 
content in cartilage tissue to occur within a few weeks (Roos  et al. 2005, Van Ginckel et al. 2010). However, the timing 
of changes in joint cartilage GAG content remains unclear. 
Increased ΔT 1 is thought to be correlated with reduced gly-
cosaminoglycan content, and it is usually interpreted as a sign 
of early degeneration (Bashir et al. 1996, 1999). Our findings 
indicate that degeneration of joint cartilage might in some 
cases follow reloading after a longer period of unloading. 
Future studies in this field should therefore include a follow-
up period after reambulation. </p>

<p>Possible reasons for asymmetrical findings 
HEPHAISTOS unloads the ankle, but not the knee. When the 
orthosis is worn, normal movement is possible in the knee 
joint while flexion and extension are limited in the upper ankle 
joint and supination and pronation are not possible in the 
lower ankle joint. The subtalar joint has an angle of 30-40° to 
the horizontal line. Supination and pronation are the possible 
movements of the subtalar joint, and both are made impossible 
while wearing HEPHAISTOS. The subtalar joint is therefore 
almost completely immobilized by the orthosis, while the 
upper ankle joint is only partially restricted (extension and 
flexion of the ankle) and the knee joint is not restricted at all. 
Furthermore, tibial forces are known to load eccentrically 
on the calcaneus, leading to torque and shear stresses in the 
joint. Forces are not distributed homogenously throughout the 
articular surface of the subtalar joint (Mueller et al. 2014). In 
cases in which the stabilizing muscles were atrophied after the 
intervention, shear stresses may have exceeded their normal 
extent and led to cartilage impairment. </p>

<p>Clinical relevance of our findings 
Considering our results, a reduction in the GAG content of 
cartilage following reloading after cast immobilization and 
after nonoperative treatment of conditions such as Achilles </p>



<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2015; 86 (3): 388-392 </p>

<p>tendon ruptures appears to be possible and should be investi-
gated further. The same effects may also follow immobiliza-
tion in an external fixator. The findings may fuel the ongoing 
discussions for or against nonoperative and operative treat-
ment options in a number of conditions (Cohen and Balcom  2003, Jiang et al. 2012). For these considerations, it would be 
of interest to know how long the reduction in GAGs lasts, how 
its timely development takes place, and the degree to which it 
is reversible. Furthermore, it is important to identify joints that 
are particularly vulnerable and unloading patterns that prevent 
changes in cartilage. </p>



</text></tei>