<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4530448" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives: To identify patterns in euthanasia </p>

<p>requests and practices relating to psychiatric patients; 
to generate recommendations for future research. </p>

<p>1   In Europe, psychological suffering stemming 
from either a somatic or mental disorder is 
acknowledged as a valid legal basis for 
euthanasia only in Belgium, the Netherlands 
and Luxembourg. 
2 In the Netherlands and 
Luxembourg, the term 'assisted suicide' is 
used when the life-ending drugs are taken 
orally, but in Belgium, the term 'euthanasia' 
is used whether the drugs are received orally 
or intravenously. 
In all three countries, the law stipulates 
substantive and procedural criteria that must 
be met for euthanasia to be legally </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ This is the first report on a relatively large 
(n=100) series of requests for euthanasia exclu-
sively from patients whose requests are based 
on unbearable and untreatable psychological suf-
fering due to a psychiatric illness. 
▪ This retrospective case note review draws atten-
tion to and deepens our understanding of the 
circumstances of a small but severely afflicted 
subgroup of psychiatric patients. 
▪ Selection bias was minimised by the inclusion of 
all consecutive cases that met the selection cri-
teria within a specified time frame. 
▪ Owing to the retrospective study design, some 
potentially important determinants, such as per-
sonal and social background and the details of 
the psychiatric evaluation, were not systematic-
ally collected. 
▪ The sample size limited the generalisability of the 
findings and the scope for detecting statistically 
meaningful differences based on determinants 
that may be associated with a euthanasia request 
being granted, refused or withdrawn. </p>

<p>Thienpont L, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e007454. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007454 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>performed. The substantive criteria are almost identical 
(with the exception of different age limits), but there 
are slight differences in the procedural criteria (eg, the 
number of physicians who must be consulted and the 
necessity of a written request). </p>

<p>2-4   In Belgium, specific criteria and procedures are 
clearly spelt out, including that the physician must 
report to the Federal Control and Evaluation 
Commission (FCEC) within four working days after the 
act of euthanasia, for review of all legal requirements 
relating to the case. 
1 3 5 It is also stated that if there are 
any doubts or irregularities, the FCEC can ask the phys-
ician who performed the euthanasia procedure for add-
itional information, or the case can be referred to 
Belgium's public prosecutor. </p>

<p>1 3 5   The Belgian Euthanasia Law indicates explicitly that 
requests for euthanasia from non-terminally ill adults or 
'emancipated minors' (ie, minors who are legally inde-
pendent from their parents) suffering from 'unbearable 
and untreatable' somatic and psychiatric disorders can 
be granted, as well as those from terminally ill patients. </p>

<p>1   'Unbearable' suffering can be understood as a subject-
ive term. By its nature, the extent to which the suffering 
is unbearable must be determined from the perspective 
of the patient himself or herself, and may depend on his 
or her physical and mental strength and personality. </p>

<p>6   According to the Law, a physician has to come to a level 
of mutual understanding with the patient about the 
extent of his or her unendurable suffering. </p>

<p>1   'Untreatable' is a more objective term. According to 
the guidelines of the Dutch Psychiatric Association 
(NVvP), any therapeutic option for a particular condi-
tion must meet the following three requirements: (1) it 
must offer a real prospect of improvement, (2) it must 
be possible to administer adequate treatment within a 
reasonable period of time and (3) there must be a rea-
sonable balance between the expected treatment results 
and the burden of treatment consequences for the 
patient. </p>

<p>7   Euthanasia for patients with unbearable somatic suffer-
ing is the subject of fierce ethical debate, and the 
debate is even fiercer in cases of unbearable psychiatric 
suffering. 
In 2002, the Belgian legislature had foreseen the possi-
bility of life-ending assistance for psychiatric patients, 
following long political debates on the issue of self-
determination. Delbeke has briefly summarised the 
arguments as follows. 
6 The main argument in favour of 
providing life-ending assistance to psychiatric patients is 
that their suffering can be equally unbearable as the 
somatic suffering of other patients. The main argument 
against providing such assistance is that suicide preven-
tion is a primary purpose of psychiatric care and a key 
focus of training for psychiatrists. From the psychiatrist's 
perspective, if the psychiatric patient has no further 
prospect of improvement, continues to suffer unbearably 
and persists with his or her wish to die, the psychiatrist 
finds himself or herself in the position of having to </p>

<p>accept the validity of this wish, if all legal requirements 
can be fulfilled and all possibilities of mistakes and 
abuses can be carefully avoided. Some opponents reject 
this particular point of view because termination of life 
for non-terminally ill patients is unacceptable and 
incompatible with their views that life has to be pro-
tected at all costs. Furthermore, it should be borne in 
mind that the suffering associated with somatic disorders 
can also induce psychological suffering, such that there 
often exists a combination of physical and psychological 
suffering, which is called multicausality of suffering, and 
which may imply presence of mental illness. Not only 
the nature and origin of the suffering, but also the 
longer life expectancy make euthanasia for psychiatric 
patients more problematic and less acceptable for 
opponents. </p>

<p>6   The specific complexity of this category of patients 
therefore requires the application of stricter conditions 
and criteria. "The Belgian legislature has registered a 
stricter approach for non-terminally-ill patients. Because 
unbearably suffering patients with a psychiatric condi-
tion are not suffering from a life-threatening (somatic) 
disease, they will generally fall under these stricter pro-
cedural conditions." </p>

<p>8   Proponents and opponents of euthanasia generally 
agree on the importance of making every possible effort 
to offer patients the best attainable quality of life, includ-
ing the best possible quality for the end of their lives 
when they consider their lives to be unbearable. For that 
reason, stringent procedures have to be adhered to, and 
monitoring and evaluation remain crucial. </p>

<p>9   In Belgium, a valid request for euthanasia must be 
made in writing, without coercion, by an adult or an 
emancipated minor who is legally competent and con-
scious at the time of making the request. 
1 3 5 10 To be 
considered for euthanasia, an adult or emancipated 
minor must be "in a medically futile condition of 
unbearable and untreatable physical or psychological 
suffering, resulting from a serious and incurable dis-
order caused by accident or illness." 
1 Based on 
Belgium's expanded Euthanasia Law (2013), a request 
for euthanasia from a "minor with the capacity of dis-
cernment" is also eligible for consideration, but only if 
the patient is "in a medically futile condition of unbear-
able physical suffering" due to an untreatable terminal 
illness. 
11 If a physician determines that a patient request-
ing euthanasia meets these criteria, this must be con-
firmed by the assessment of a second, independent 
consulting physician. 
1 3 5 When the patient is not 
expected to die in the near future, additional advice is 
required from a third physician, who should be a psych-
iatrist or medical specialist in the patient's pathology. </p>

<p>1 3 5   This second and third physician's advice is requested 
but is not binding. </p>

<p>6   A patient is considered to be in a medically futile situ-
ation, or treatment-resistant, if the suffering is unbear-
able and untreatable, and there is no prospect of any 
improvement. According to the Law, physician and </p>



<p>Thienpont L, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e007454. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007454 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>patient must both come to the conclusion that there is 
no reasonable alternative left to relieve the patient's suf-
fering. 
1 If the psychiatrist has reason to believe that the 
patient could experience further benefit from treatment 
options, then life-ending options cannot be granted. </p>

<p>6   Since legalisation of euthanasia in Belgium in 2002, 
the number of euthanasia deaths reported by the FCEC 
has increased each year, rising from 742 in 2004/2005 
(including 9 (1.2%) with neuropsychiatric disorders) </p>

<p>12   to 2086 in 2010/2011 (including 58 (2.8%) with neuro-
psychiatric disorders). 
13 14 (The year 2004/2005 was the 
first year that neuropsychiatric disorders were specified 
in the FCEC data). This rise over a 6-year period may 
reflect a true increase or better reporting of cases of 
euthanasia. 
5 Proportionally, no differences with regard 
to gender, age, diagnoses or the nature of the patients' 
suffering were observed over these years. Between 2008 
and 2011, for a total of 3612 euthanasia deaths, the 
FCEC reported a male-to-female ratio of 51:49, and 2% 
of these deaths involved patients aged 20-39 years, 
21.5% were aged 40-59 years, 51.5% were aged 60-
79 years and 25% were 80 years or older. 
13 14 Overall, 
45% of the patients died in a hospital, 45% at home and 
10% elsewhere. 
13 14 The barbiturate, sodium thiopental, 
was the life-ending drug used in the vast majority of 
cases. 
13 14 Over 91% of these patients were terminally ill, 
while 8.5% suffered from a non-terminal condition. 
▸ Of all the terminally ill patients, cancer accounted for 
almost 77%, while 15% had other somatic disorders, 
approximately 3% were linked to neuropsychiatric 
disorders and 5% had multiple or other 
disorders. </p>

<p>13 14   ▸ Among the non-terminally ill patients, cancer 
accounted for about 10%, while 40% had other 
somatic disorders, 24% were linked to neuropsychi-
atric disorders, and 26% had multiple or other 
disorders. </p>

<p>13 14   The overall objectives of this study are: first, to report 
on characteristics of psychiatric patients requesting 
euthanasia because of psychological suffering; and 
second, to describe the formal assessment procedures 
and outcomes of the euthanasia requests. To the best of 
our knowledge, this is the first study to explore the 
determinants, procedures and outcomes of euthanasia 
requests in a relatively large group of psychiatric patients 
with psychological suffering. </p>

<p>METHODS 
This paper describes a retrospective case note review of 
the first 100 consecutive patients who requested euthan-
asia for psychological suffering associated with psychi-
atric disorders between October 2007 and December 
2011. All consecutive cases were selected from among 
patients at an outpatient psychiatric clinical setting in 
the Dutch-speaking region of Belgium, where the first 
author and psychiatrist (LT) works, with intake begin-
ning after LT completed LEIF (Life End Information </p>

<p>Forum) training in March 2007 (the first case was in 
October of that year) and ending in December 2011 (ie, 
when LT joined ULTEAM-a newly founded central 
institute in Belgium to manage end-of-life cases-and 
thus stopped managing new requests for euthanasia at 
her private practice). Since 2012, no new follow-up 
studies were performed as this would have required a 
new study protocol and IRB request. The data analysis 
was closed at the end of 2012, and the data analysis and 
writing were conducted in 2013/2014. 
All patient information had been recorded in full in 
the patient files, providing a clear database of informa-
tion for analysis and follow-up. Sociodemographic data 
(age, gender, employment and living circumstances) 
and diagnoses were analysed. Decisions on euthanasia 
requests (including referrals for further testing/treat-
ment), number of consultations, circumstances of 
euthanasia procedures and patient outcomes, were also 
analysed. By including all consecutive cases that met the 
selection criteria within a specified time frame, selection 
bias was minimised. 
The psychiatric diagnoses were made according to the 
Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 
4th Edition (DSM-IV) classification. LT was involved in 
the counselling, referring and evaluation of all patients, 
as a consultant physician. At the end of 2012, all 100 
patients or their practitioners were contacted to establish 
whether the patients were still alive and, if not, how they 
had died. 
This study was a retrospective, non-interventional 
medical record analysis study of 100 patients requesting 
euthanasia in the context of psychological suffering. 
Given the nature of the study, the Ethics Committee con-
firmed that obtaining informed consent from the 
patients included in the study was not required on con-
dition that the medical records were coded and made 
anonymous. </p>

<p>Implementation of the Euthanasia Law in clinical practice 
To translate the Euthanasia Law into clinical practice in 
Belgium, the psychiatrists and/or LEIF practitioners 
among the authors (LT, WD, KA and PPDD) developed 
a four-track approach based on the guidelines of the 
Dutch Psychiatric Association (NVvP), 
7 which were 
issued in 2004 and revised in 2009, and also adapted to 
the requirements of the Belgian Euthanasia Law. LEIF, 
established in 2003 in Belgium, is a service that refers 
people to qualified healthcare professionals for assist-
ance with end-of-life matters, and also offers training 
programmes for physicians. 
4 15 The NVvP guidelines are 
the first on this subject and are written in the same lan-
guage used in the Dutch-speaking region of Belgium; 
therefore, they serve as a practical and valid basis for the 
application of the Belgian Euthanasia Law in 
the context of this study. For all patients in the sample, 
the four-track approach has been used. Further details 
about this approach are being prepared for publication 
separately. </p>

<p>Thienpont L, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e007454. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007454 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>The four tracks can be described as follows: 
1. There must be a thorough evaluation through mul-
tiple consultations regarding the specific determi-
nants and conditions of 'unbearable and untreatable 
psychological suffering' in each case. LT ascertained 
the psychiatric diagnoses, mental state and history of 
each patient after consultation with the treating prac-
titioner(s), and made a thorough review of the case 
file and full psychiatric evaluation of the patient. 
2. All therapeutic options that could alleviate suffering, 
including palliative care, must be discussed with the 
patients and their practitioners. For these discussions, 
LT used the following NVvP guidelines about these 
therapeutic options: (a) the therapy must offer a real 
prospect of improvement, (b) it must be possible to 
administer adequate treatment within a reasonable 
period of time and (c) there must be a reasonable 
balance between the expected results and the treat-
ment burden for the patient. </p>

<p>7   3. All procedural aspects should be explained to, and 
discussed with, the patient. Only when the patient 
repeatedly expresses the wish to die, and the patient's 
physician or psychiatrist indicates that the patient's 
reasons for this wish are sufficiently tangible and rea-
sonable, will the formal request for euthanasia be 
filed and the planning begin. 
7 According to the Law, 
at least 1 month must elapse between the written 
request (which will be kept on file by the patient's 
practitioner) and the implementation of euthanasia. 
4. The patient's family and/or significant others should 
be involved. Legally, the physician is required to 
discuss the wishes of the patient with the relatives 
named by the patient. Consent from the relatives is </p>

<p>not required, and the attending physician needs the 
patient's permission to inform family members of the 
euthanasia request. 
1 3 Fostering acceptance in 
the patient's social environment can give the patient 
the opportunity to pass away in a serene atmosphere, 
surrounded by family and/or friends, whose mourn-
ing process can thus also be softened. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Subjects 
One hundred consecutive psychiatric patients requesting 
euthanasia based on psychological suffering associated 
with psychiatric disorders during the study period were 
included. </p>

<p>Sociodemographic status 
The patients included 23 men and 77 women, age 
ranging 21-80 years, with an average age at intake of 47 
±13 years (mean±SD); the average was 46±16 years for 
men (range 22-79 years) and 47±12 years for women 
(range 21-80 years). The age-gender distribution is 
shown in figure 1. The majority (n=81) had been profes-
sionally inactive for an extended period of time, includ-
ing 8 who were retired and 73 who were medically unfit 
for work (they were either receiving disability living allow-
ances or had taken early retirement). Fourteen patients 
were still working or temporarily on sick leave. One 
patient was a student, one was imprisoned and one was 
receiving a subsistence income from the Public Social 
Welfare Agency (data on income/employment were not 
available for two patients). Fifty-nine patients were living 
alone while 41 were living with one or more companions. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Frequency of age in 
100 psychiatric patients who 
requested euthanasia, by gender. </p>



<p>Thienpont L, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e007454. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007454 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Referral, diagnoses and mental state 
The 100 patients included in the study were referred for 
psychiatric counselling by LEIF (n=36), their general 
practitioners (n=21), their consulting psychiatrists 
(n=24), their consulting psychotherapists (n=10) or 
otherwise (n=9). 
At the time of the intake consultation with LT, each 
patient had at least one diagnosis that had been given by 
his or her practitioner, which was subsequently con-
firmed by LT (see track 1 in Methods section). Ninety of 
the 100 patients had more than one diagnosis. Most 
patients presented with numerous diagnoses, but for the 
sake of clarity, we report only a maximum of three disor-
ders per patient, taking only the most recent diagnoses 
for each. Most of the patients suffered from a 
treatment-resistant mood disorder (n=58, including 48 
with major depressive disorder and 10 with bipolar dis-
order) and/or a personality disorder (n=50), while 29 
patients had both. Other psychiatric diagnoses included 
post-traumatic stress disorder (n=13), schizophrenia and 
other psychotic disorders (n=14), anxiety disorders 
(n=11), eating disorders (n=10), substance use disorders 
(n=10), somatoform disorders (n=9), pervasive develop-
mental disorders (n=8; including 7 with Asperger syn-
drome-an autism spectrum disorder (ASD)-and 1 
with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder), obsessive-
compulsive disorders (n=7), dissociative disorders (n=7) 
and complicated grief (n=6), among others. In addition 
to their psychiatric disorder(s), 23 patients also had 
somatic illnesses, including chronic fatigue syndrome 
and/or fibromyalgia (n=8), or other chronic somatic suf-
fering (n=15). 
The 50 patients with personality disorders included 
borderline personality disorder (27), dependent person-
ality disorder (3), histrionic personality disorder (2), 
avoidant personality disorder (1), narcissistic personality 
disorder (1), paranoid personality disorder (1), cluster 
B personality disorder (1) and personality disorders not 
otherwise specified (14). 
In all patients, the suffering was chronic, constant and 
unbearable, without prospect of improvement, due to 
treatment resistance. 
All patients were legally competent under the Law. 
Each patient's capacity for discernment was evaluated 
during the process, by LT in consultation with the 
patient's practitioner(s), according to explicit criteria 
described in the Belgian Legal Doctrine. </p>

<p>6   Responses to euthanasia requests 
After initial evaluation, and discussions with each patient 
and his or her practitioner(s) about all therapeutic 
options that could alleviate suffering, as required by the 
Euthanasia Law (see tracks 1 and 2 in Methods section), 
38 patients were referred for further diagnostic tests 
and/or treatment to specialised inpatient (n=17) or out-
patient (n=21) care facilities. Thirteen of those 38 
patients were specifically tested for ASD, and among 
them 12 received an ASD diagnosis (all were Asperger </p>

<p>syndrome). After the further testing/treatment, 17 of 
these 38 requests for euthanasia were accepted (44.7%) 
and 10 were carried out. 
The other 62 patients were not referred for further 
testing or treatment because of the clear absence of rea-
sonable therapeutic alternatives for them, as described 
in the NVvP guidelines. Thirty-one of these 62 patients 
had their requests for euthanasia accepted (50%) and 
25 were carried out. 
In total, 48 of the 100 patients' euthanasia requests 
were accepted (48%), because LT ( psychiatrist), in dis-
cussion with the patients' other practitioners and fam-
ilies, considered the requests to be based on reasons that 
were sufficiently tangible and reasonable, and because 
all legal requirements had been fulfilled. 
Among all 48 patients whose euthanasia requests were 
accepted, euthanasia was performed in 35 patients 
(72.9%), while two committed suicide before the pro-
cedure could be implemented and 11 patients decided 
to either postpone or cancel the euthanasia procedure. 
Of the latter 11 patients, 8 explained (by phone or 
mail) that knowing they had the option to proceed with 
euthanasia gave them sufficient peace of mind to con-
tinue their lives, while 2 withdrew their euthanasia 
requests due to strong family resistance and 1 could not 
be implemented on the grounds that the patient was 
imprisoned. 
Among the 52 patients whose requests were not 
accepted, 38 withdrew their requests before a decision 
was reached, while another 8 continued to pursue their 
requests, 4 committed suicide and 2 died spontaneously. </p>

<p>Outcomes for patients 
By the end of 2012, when follow-up was conducted, 43 
of the 100 patients had died. Euthanasia had been per-
formed on 35 patients (9 men and 26 women). Six 
patients had committed suicide (2 men and 4 women). 
Two other female patients had died, one after palliative 
sedation in a psychiatric hospital, and the other due to 
the terminal stage of anorexia nervosa. 
In the six suicide cases, one (woman, aged 51) found 
the procedure for obtaining the approval for euthanasia 
to be unbearably long, one (woman, 74) found the 
waiting time after the approval unbearably long, and 
one (woman, 42) committed suicide because her family 
resisted the option of euthanasia, even though the 
request had been approved. Two patients (both men, 33 
and 44) committed suicide after breaking off communi-
cation (after requesting euthanasia), and one (woman, 
55) committed suicide after staying in a psychiatric ward 
to which she had been referred. 
In the remaining 57 cases (12 men and 45 women), 
the patients or their practitioners were contacted and it 
was confirmed that these patients were still alive. In nine 
cases their requests were still in process and no decision 
had been reached. In 48 cases, their requests were on 
hold because they were managing with regular, occa-
sional or no therapy. </p>

<p>Thienpont L, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e007454. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007454 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Euthanasia procedure 
Not including an extended history of previous therapy 
sessions with their respective practitioners, among the 
35 patients who underwent euthanasia, the average 
number of psychiatric counselling sessions with LT fol-
lowing the request for euthanasia was 3.49±4.42 (mean 
±SD) per patient. The average time between making the 
request for euthanasia (ie, the first session with LT) and 
performing the euthanasia procedure was 8.66 
±9.55 months (mean±SD). 
Among the 35 patients who received euthanasia, in 20 
cases, the procedure was performed by the patient's 
general practitioner, in 1 case it was performed by her 
neurologist and in the other 14 cases the procedure was 
performed by an LEIF physician consulted for the case. 
The barbiturate, sodium thiopental, was used as the 
main life-ending drug in all 35 euthanasia procedures (31 
intravenously, 4 orally). In 28 cases, the procedure took 
place in domestic surroundings, while 5 took place in the 
neurology ward of a university hospital, 1 took place in the 
office of the consulting physician and 1 at the palliative 
care ward of a general hospital. Thirty of the 35 patients 
had family and/or friends present at the time of death. In 
33 of the 35 procedures, the relatives and the doctors per-
forming euthanasia explicitly reported a calm and smooth 
passing. In one case, tensions rose due to emotional diffi-
culties for some relatives in fully accepting the patient's 
wish to die by means of the euthanasia procedure. In 
another case, the practitioner performing the procedure 
was inexperienced and became overwhelmed and stressed 
by the situation, which caused discomfort for the patient. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Principle findings 
Among 100 patients requesting euthanasia based on psy-
chological suffering associated with psychiatric disorders, 
most had been referred for psychiatric counselling by 
their own practitioner (n=55) or by LEIF (n=36). Ninety 
patients had more than one psychiatric disorder at intake; 
the most frequent diagnoses were depression (n=58) and 
personality disorder (n=50); 29 patients had both. 
Thirty-eight patients were referred for further testing and/ 
or treatment. In total, 48 of the euthanasia requests were 
accepted and 35 were carried out. Among the other 13 
patients whose requests were approved, 2 committed 
suicide before the procedure could be carried out and 11 
patients decided to postpone or cancel the procedure 
(including 8 who said that knowing they had the option to 
proceed with euthanasia gave them sufficient peace of 
mind to continue their lives). Overall, 43 patients had died 
by the time follow-up was conducted by LT at the end of 
December 2012: 35 had died by euthanasia, 6 by suicide, 1 
after palliative sedation and 1 from anorexia nervosa. </p>

<p>Strengths and weaknesses 
To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report on a 
relatively large series of requests for euthanasia based on </p>

<p>psychological suffering due to psychiatric disorders. A 
few studies have explored the determinants of psycho-
logical suffering in patients in the context of requests 
for euthanasia, 
16 17 but these studies did not exclusively 
report on patients requesting euthanasia based on 
unbearable and untreatable psychological suffering due 
to a psychiatric illness. This retrospective study draws 
attention to and deepens our understanding of the cir-
cumstances of a rather small but severely afflicted sub-
group of psychiatric patients. As an indication of the 
current situation of euthanasia practices in Belgium, 
2086 patients died in the 2-year period 2010-2011, after 
having their euthanasia requests granted; those deaths 
constituted 1% of all deaths in Belgium during that 
period, and the non-terminally ill patients (including 
psychiatric patients) accounted for only a small minority 
(less than 10%) of that small group. </p>

<p>14   Nevertheless, this study has inherent limitations. Some 
potentially important determinants, such as personal 
and social background and the details of the psychiatric 
evaluation, were collected as part of the clinical file but 
not in a systematic way, as would have been applied in a 
prospective study. The sample size may have limited the 
ability to detect statistically meaningful differences based 
on determinants that may be associated with a euthan-
asia request being granted, refused or withdrawn. By 
including all consecutive cases that met the selection cri-
teria within a specified time frame, selection bias was 
minimised. It is not possible to estimate how representa-
tive this sample is of the entire population of similar 
patients. Comparing characteristics and outcomes of our 
sample with the national data is not helpful since the 
FCEC only reports data from patients who died by 
euthanasia, not from patients who requested euthanasia. 
Moreover, FCEC does not differentiate between specific 
determinants of patients suffering predominantly from 
neurological and psychiatric disorders. Similarly, it is 
impossible to assess to what extent the findings are gen-
eralisable to other groups of similar patients; a larger 
sample would have strengthened the study in this 
regard. </p>

<p>Interpretation and implications 
In comparison to other studies, our patient group con-
tains more women than men (23 men and 77 women), 
which is different from the male-to-female ratio in the 
euthanasia cases carried out for somatic and/or mental 
reasons as recorded by the FCEC (51:49). This is in line 
with other reports in the literature, which indicate that 
women fulfil the diagnostic criteria for mental disorders 
more often than men, except in the case of substance 
use disorders. 
18 Furthermore, demand for mental 
healthcare 
19 and utilisation of mental healthcare ser-
vices 
20 are higher in women than in men. When com-
pared with the FCEC data, our group of psychiatric 
patients requested to end their lives at a younger age 
(median=47 years) than the overall group of patients 
who have undergone euthanasia for any reason (ie, </p>



<p>Thienpont L, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e007454. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007454 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>somatic and/or mental reasons combined), the majority 
of whom have been older than 60 years. This may be 
partly explained by the earlier onset and longer course 
of psychiatric disorders (eg, treatment-resistant mood 
disorder) compared to the somatic disorders that are 
usually the basis of euthanasia requests (eg, cancer). It 
may also be a reflection of the complex nature of psychi-
atric disorders, which have a sense of hopelessness as a 
core symptom. Furthermore, the complexity of psychi-
atric disorders might have led to the initial underdiagno-
sis of Asperger syndrome in our patient group, the 
analysis of which is beyond the scope of this report. At 
intake, patients already had an ASD diagnosis, and 12 
more patients (who had further testing/treatment after 
requesting euthanasia) were diagnosed by dedicated 
diagnostic work up. All 19 of these patients had 
Asperger syndrome, with normal to high IQ. 
Among the 35 patients in this study who died by 
euthanasia, 28 died in domestic surroundings and 7 in a 
clinical setting. Thirty of these patients died with family 
and/or friends present, in a serene and positive atmos-
phere, which would have been impossible to attain in 
the case of unassisted, traumatic suicide. Patients and 
relatives report their experience of euthanasia as a more 
humane death than suicide, and they expect a less diffi-
cult period of mourning. Bereavement after the suicide 
of a relative or significant other entails an emotional 
turmoil that may last a long time, and, in some cases, 
may end with the mourner's own suicide. 
21 Accordingly, 
we note that the fact that their euthanasia request was 
being considered could not prevent suicide in 6 patients, 
including 2 of the 48 patients (4.2%) whose euthanasia 
requests had been approved and 4 of the 52 patients 
(7.7%) whose requests had not yet been approved. 
Moreover, the modes of suicide were dramatic, but we 
cannot provide further details due to respect for patient 
confidentiality. It is a difficult tightrope to tread: on the 
one hand, there must be sufficient time to accomplish 
all legal and medical requirements, on the other, there 
is a need to take action before the suffering reaches an 
unbearable level and leads to traumatic suicide. 
Likewise, a clear distinction should be made between 
suicidality (in thoughts and behaviour), which is symp-
tomatic of (and/or triggered by) a number of psychi-
atric disorders, and a well-considered euthanasia 
request, which includes a patient's statement that his or 
her suffering is entirely unbearable, and that available 
treatment and medical assistance has been found to be 
inadequate. Therefore, we wish to underline that each 
euthanasia request must be scrutinised as a request for 
effective and far-reaching treatment, and that any such 
request demands exploration of all implications and 
clarification of alternatives. The four-track approach 
implies that patients are compos mentis-that is, they 
can make a rational choice; under the Euthanasia Law it 
is required that patients are legally competent and so 
their capacity for discernment is thoroughly assessed 
before any request for euthanasia is considered. </p>

<p>Unanswered questions and recommendations 
for future research 
A literature review made clear that the concept of 
'unbearable suffering' has not yet been defined 
adequately, and that views on this concept are in a state 
of flux. 
22 It is generally accepted that this concept is con-
sidered to be subjective, dependent on personal values, 
and that it must be determined in the first place by the 
patient. 
6 Nevertheless, a psychiatrist should carefully 
evaluate this in the context of each patient's psychopath-
ology. 
6 Unfortunately, there are no guidelines for the 
management of euthanasia requests on grounds of 
mental suffering in Belgium. Taking into account the 
ongoing fierce ethical debates, it is essential to develop 
such guidelines, and translate them into clear and 
detailed protocols that can be applied in practice. 
Therefore, further studies are recommended, especially 
prospective quantitative and qualitative studies, to obtain 
a better understanding of patients with psychiatric disor-
ders who request euthanasia due to unbearable psycho-
logical suffering. Furthermore, these studies could 
undertake systematic comparisons between groups of 
psychiatric and non-psychiatric patients, thereby explor-
ing the risk factors for, and origins and degree of, 
unbearable suffering in both patient groups. </p>

<p>Author affiliations 
1 University Hospital Brussels, Brussels, Belgium 
2 MSc student at the Open University of the Netherlands, Heerlen, 
The Netherlands 
3 Free University of Brussels, Brussels, Belgium 
4 Department of Psychiatry, Ghent University Hospital, Ghent, Belgium 
5 University of Antwerp, Institute Born-Bunge, Wilrijk, Belgium 
6 University of Groningen, University Medical Center Groningen, Groningen, 
The Netherlands 
7 Middelheim General Hospital, ZNA, Antwerp, Belgium </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors wish to thank Dr Marleen Temmerman for 
her critical input and comments, and her encouragement for us to publish 
this work. They also wish to acknowledge the valuable language and technical 
editing by Jane Patten, of Green Ink, UK. </p>

<p>Contributors LT collected and anonymised all patients' data while PPDD 
managed all related ethical approvals; LT and PPDD constructed the final 
study design after substantive discussions with WD and TVL; MV, KA and WD 
were responsible for all literature searches and references; data analysis and 
interpretation were contributed by LT and KA; MV used <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> V.<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">20.0</rs> to create 
the figure and <rs type="software">Mendeley</rs> for reference management; LT, MV and KA 
contributed more or less equally to the writing. All authors performed a 
critical review and revision of the final manuscript and gave final approval for 
submission. LT is the guarantor. </p>

<p>Funding This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in 
the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Ethical approval for the data analysis was obtained from the 
Ethics Committee of the Antwerp Hospital Network (10/04/2013, EC Approval 
Number 4183). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-</p>

<p>Thienpont L, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e007454. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007454 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Thienpont L, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e007454. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-007454 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>