<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4600182" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T16:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective: To evaluate the current use of Australian </p>

<p>Type 2 Diabetes Risk Assessment Tool (AUSDRISK) as 
a screening tool to identify individuals at high risk of 
developing type 2 diabetes for entry into lifestyle 
modification programs. </p>

<p>Research Design and Methods: AUSDRISK scores </p>

<p>were calculated from participants aged 40-74 years in 
the Greater Green Triangle Risk Factor Study, a cross-
sectional population survey in 3 regions of Southwest 
Victoria, Australia, 2004-2006. Biomedical profiles of 
AUSDRISK risk categories were determined along with 
estimates of the Victorian population included at 
various cut-off scores. Sensitivity, specificity, positive 
predictive value (PPV), negative predictive value, and 
receiver operating characteristics were calculated for 
AUSDRISK in determining fasting plasma glucose 
(FPG) ≥6.1 mmol/L. </p>

<p>Results: Increasing AUSDRISK scores were associated </p>

<p>with an increase in weight, body mass index, FPG, and 
metabolic syndrome. Increasing the minimum cut-off 
score also increased the proportion of individuals who 
were obese and centrally obese, had impaired fasting 
glucose (IFG) and metabolic syndrome. An AUSDRISK 
score of ≥12 was estimated to include 39.5% of the 
Victorian population aged 40-74 (916 000), while a 
score of ≥20 would include only 5.2% of the same 
population (120 000). At AUSDRISK≥20, the PPV for 
detecting FPG≥6.1 mmol/L was 28.4%. </p>

<p>Australia is estimated to reach over 2.3 
million by 2035. 
1 Annual expenditure on dia-
betes in Australia already amounts to over A 
$14 billion in direct costs and government 
subsidies, 
2 therefore population and high-
risk strategies are required to mitigate future 
disease burden. 
A number of studies aimed at prevention 
of type 2 diabetes have included only those 
with disorders of abnormal glucose metabol-
ism. 
3-5 Individuals with impaired glucose tol-
erance (IGT) and impaired fasting glucose 
(IFG), are among the highest risk for devel-
oping type 2 diabetes, with an annual inci-
dence of 5-10% across various categories of 
IGT or IFG. 
6 Such disorders are reversible, 
and trials have demonstrated that intensive 
lifestyle modification programs can success-
fully halt or delay progression to type 2 dia-
betes in high-risk groups. </p>

<p>3-5 </p>

<p>On the basis of the results of these rando-
mized trials, and the national demonstrator 
Greater Green Triangle Diabetes Prevention 
Program (DPP), 
7 along with economic mod-
eling, the Council of Australian Governments 
in 2006 decided to invest in lifestyle modifi-
cation programs for diabetes prevention. </p>

<p>Key messages </p>

<p>▪ Type 2 diabetes risk assessment tools should be 
used in conjunction with fasting glucose, oral 
glucose tolerance testing, or glycated hemoglo-
bin to determine entry into lifestyle modification 
programs. 
▪ Cut-off scores of type 2 diabetes risk assess-
ment tools for screening into lifestyle modifica-
tion programs and further testing should be 
chosen with knowledge of the proportion of the 
population at different risk scores. 
▪ Lowering entry criteria for lifestyle modification 
programs to reduce risk of type 2 diabetes is 
likely to decrease the impact of the program as 
well as the cost-effectiveness. </p>

<p>BMJ Open Diabetes Research and Care 2015;3:e000125. doi:10.1136/bmjdrc-2015-000125 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>The Federal Government's program was targeted at 
adults aged 40-49 years, and the state and territory pro-
grams targeted those aged 50 years and over. National 
standards for lifestyle modification programs were 
agreed on, and work started on an Australian tool for 
risk assessment (Australian Type 2 Diabetes Risk 
Assessment Tool, AUSDRISK) 
8 9 to reflect the ethnic 
diversity of the contemporary Australian population. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>AUSDRISK is a 10-item questionnaire that estimates risk 
of progression to type 2 diabetes over 5 years. Its scoring 
includes questions based on age, sex, ethnicity, family 
history of diabetes, history of abnormal glucose metabol-
ism, smoking status, current hypertensive treatment, 
physical activity, fruit and vegetable consumption, and 
waist circumference. 
The Federal DPP was discontinued in 2011 due to 
poor recruitment and other implementation pro-
blems. 
11 The Victorian Life! program is a statewide DPP 
established by Diabetes Australia-Victoria in 2007. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>AUSDRISK was chosen as the screening tool for Life!, 
with an entry score of ≥15 initially selected, but low 
recruitment rates led to a decision to lower the entry 
score to ≥12. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>The Australian experience with 
AUSDRISK will be relevant to other countries wanting 
to develop a national instrument for screening. 
Many other risk tools have been developed and vali-
dated to predict risk of type 2 diabetes, both in terms of 
current and future risk. These tools have been demon-
strated to be effective and cost-effective in identification 
of individuals at high risk of developing type 2 diabetes, 
though their effectiveness may vary across different 
populations. 
14 Using a questionnaire such as AUSDRISK 
is a practical method to screen for high-risk individuals 
who might benefit from lifestyle modification, but it has 
been recommended that those found to be at high risk 
should also undergo an oral glucose tolerance test 
(OGTT) or glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c) to determine 
impairment of glucose metabolism and screen for 
undiagnosed diabetes. 
15 16 Those found to have abnor-
mal glucose metabolism should be invited to participate 
in lifestyle modification programs, while those with 
normal glucose metabolism should be provided with life-
style advice and reassessed in 2-3 years. </p>

<p>15-17 </p>

<p>Best practice for recruitment and screening of indivi-
duals into real-world DPP remains uncertain. Given this 
knowledge gap and the implications for the effectiveness 
and cost-effectiveness, this paper evaluates the perform-
ance of AUSDRISK in identifying suitable candidates for 
entry into lifestyle modification programs. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS 
Sampling and collection 
The Greater Green Triangle Risk Factor Study (GGT 
RFS) consisted of three cross-sectional surveys of chronic 
disease risk factors carried out in Southwest Victoria 
from 2003 to 2006. This data set was chosen as the 
survey instrument had good agreement with biomedical </p>

<p>and lifestyle questions relevant to AUSDRISK. Collection 
of data has been reported previously. </p>

<p>18 19 </p>

<p>Inclusion and exclusion criteria 
Data from survey respondents aged 40-74 years were 
included for calculating AUSDRISK scores. Individuals 
who self-reported a previous diagnosis of diabetes, 
history of treatment with insulin, oral hypoglycemics or 
both were excluded from the analysis. Those with fasting 
plasma glucose (FPG) &gt;6.9 mmol/L were included in 
the study in order to evaluate the ability of AUSDRISK 
to detect those with undiagnosed diabetes in addition to 
IFG. 
All participants had age and sex data available as they 
were selected from the electoral roll. Participants who 
did not have a waist circumference measurement were 
excluded from analysis, as a score could not be reliably 
imputed from the survey data. </p>

<p>Treatment of missing values 
For AUSDRISK questions not related to waist circumfer-
ence, missing values were assumed to score zero. A sensi-
tivity analysis comparing total risk scores was undertaken 
with missing values imputed as zero versus cases 
excluded if there was at least one missing value. </p>

<p>Conversion of data into risk scores 
Survey responses were coded into scores for AUSDRISK 
from the GGT RFS. Where survey questions did not dir-
ectly match those of the screening tool, either the most 
similar question or a combination of questions was used 
to infer the most likely response. For example, in 
AUSDRISK question eight related to fruit and vegetable 
consumption, respondents were considered to score 0 
(eat fruit everyday) if they reported eating vegetables or 
fruit 5-6 times per week or more. </p>

<p>Definition of IFG and MetS 
The WHO definition of IFG (6.1-6.9 mmol/L) was 
used. 
20 The metabolic syndrome (MetS) was defined as 
per International Diabetes Federation (IDF) criteria, </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>with individuals required to have central obesity 
(defined by waist circumference with ethnicity specific 
values) plus any two of the following risk factors for 
diagnosis: raised triglycerides (≥1.7 mmol/L), reduced 
high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (males, &lt;1.03; 
females, &lt;1.29 mmol/L), raised blood pressure (systolic 
BP≥130 or diastolic BP≥85 mm Hg) or raised FPG 
(≥5.6 mmol/L). </p>

<p>Statistical analyses 
All analyses were performed in <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.13</rs>. Crude base-
line demographic and biomedical measures were 
reported as mean values and SDs. Risk score stratifica-
tions were selected according to their reported risks of 
developing type 2 diabetes. 
9 Annual incidence of type 2 
diabetes for AUSDRISK categories was estimated using </p>



<p>BMJ Open Diabetes Research and Care 2015;3:e000125. doi:10.1136/bmjdrc-2015-000125 </p>

<p>Epidemiology/health services research </p>

<p>the reported risk of progression over 5 years assuming a 
constant yearly risk. 
Proportions of the sample population were stratified 
by risk score, sex and age group. Estimates of the popu-
lation in Victoria, Australia, were made at different 
cut-off scores using the estimated resident population in 
Victoria at 30 June 2014. 
22 Sensitivity, specificity, positive 
predictive value (PPV), and negative predictive value 
were calculated for FPG≥6.1 mmol/L and stratified by 
risk score. Receiver operating characteristics (ROC) are 
also presented. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Of 1690 respondents in the GGT RFS, 1393 fulfilled age 
criteria. Of those, 129 were excluded due to lack of waist 
circumference measurements and a further 75 were 
omitted due to established diagnosis of diabetes, its 
treatment, or both. There was no significant difference 
between mean AUSDRISK scores when missing values 
were imputed as zero versus cases with missing values 
excluded from analysis. The results reported here are 
for those where missing values were assumed to score 
zero. Overall, AUSDRISK scores were calculated for 
1189 individuals. Males were older than females and </p>

<p>comprised a smaller proportion of the overall sample 
(table 1). 
Overall, IFG prevalence was 4.7% (males 6.7%; 
females 2.9%). Mean body mass index (BMI) was similar 
in the overweight range for both genders (table 1). The 
MetS was present in 40.5% of males and 32.6% of 
females. Diabetic and cardiovascular risk factors, except 
total and low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, and also 
the presence of MetS demonstrated a significant linear 
trend when stratified by AUSDRISK group according to 
approximate risk of progression to diabetes (table 2). 
Use of higher cut-off scores demonstrated increases in 
mean values of key diabetic risk factors (weight, BMI, 
waist circumference, FPG) (table 3). 
The proportion of individuals included at different 
AUSDRISK cut-offs increased with age (table 4). Nearly 
40% of the Victorian population aged 40-74 years was 
estimated to have an AUSDRISK score of 12 or more, 
falling to approximately 5.2% at a cut-off score of 20 or 
higher (table 4). 
After an AUSDRISK cut-off of ≥14, the sum of sensitiv-
ity and specificity for detecting FPG≥6.1 mmol/L began 
to decline (table 5). ROC for detecting FPG≥6.1 mmol/L 
was 0.76 (95% CI 0.70 to 0.81). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Apart from the original Australian Diabetes, Obesity and 
Lifestyle study from which AUSDRISK was created, 
8 to 
the best of our knowledge, our study is the first that 
applies a detailed analysis of the risk tool to an 
Australian population to define different risk categories. 
We have evaluated AUSDRISK as a screening tool for 
lifestyle modification programs in Australia and found 
some important limitations that have international impli-
cations for policy and cost-effectiveness of such pro-
grams. Increases in AUSDRISK score categories were 
accompanied by increases in key biological risk factors 
for type 2 diabetes (table 2). Accordingly, using higher 
cut-off scores resulted in a higher proportion of indivi-
duals with obesity, central obesity, IFG and the MetS. 
These findings highlight the need to select a strategy for 
screening individuals into lifestyle modification pro-
grams to ensure that those who will benefit most are 
recruited. 
For countries wishing to develop a national DPP, to 
determine the cut-off points for screening tools requires 
knowledge of the proportion of the population that will 
screen positive, and a minimum entry score should be 
selected to identify a feasible proportion of the popula-
tion it is intended to reach (table 4). Based on our esti-
mates, the current requirement of AUSDRISK≥12 would 
translate into 39.5% (916 000) of Victorians aged 40-
74 years being eligible to participate in the Life! 
program. Increasing the minimum score to ≥20 reduces 
this proportion to 5.2% (120 000). Using previously 
reported prevalence of IGT (13.0%) and IFG (7.4%) 
in Australia among adults aged 40-74 years, </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of GGT RFS sample aged 
40-74 years with a calculated AUSDRISK score </p>

<p>Variable 
N 
Mean 
(SD) </p>

<p>Males 
Age (years) 
561 
58.2 
(9.5) 
Weight (kg) 
560 
87.6 
(16.1) 
BMI (kg/m²) 
560 
28.5 
(4.9) 
Waist circumference (cm) 
561 
100.4 
(12.7) 
FPG (mmol/L) 
519 
5.4 
(0.6) 
Total cholesterol (mmol/L) 
547 
5.4 
(1.0) 
HDL (mmol/L) 
547 
1.3 
(0.4) 
LDL (mmol/L) 
534 
3.3 
(0.9) 
Triglycerides (mmol/L) 
547 
1.7 
(1.1) 
Systolic BP (mm Hg) 
561 
135.2 
(19.0) 
Diastolic BP (mm Hg) 
561 
80.5 
(10.8) 
AUSDRISK value 
561 
12.9 
(4.5) 
Females 
Age (years) 
628 
56.9 
(9.5) 
Weight (kg) 
628 
74.9 
(16.1) 
BMI (kg/m²) 
625 
28.5 
(6.1) 
Waist circumference (cm) 
628 
89.8 
(14.3) 
FPG (mmol/L) 
586 
5.2 
(0.5) 
Total cholesterol (mmol/L) 
600 
5.6 
(1.0) 
HDL (mmol/L) 
600 
1.6 
(0.4) 
LDL (mmol/L) 
597 
3.3 
(1.0) 
Triglycerides (mmol/L) 
600 
1.5 
(0.7) 
Systolic BP (mm Hg) 
628 
131.1 
(19.7) 
Diastolic BP (mm Hg) 
626 
75.4 
(10.6) 
AUSDRISK value 
628 
10.3 
(4.7) </p>

<p>AUSDRISK, Australian Type 2 Diabetes Risk Assessment Tool; 
BMI, body mass index; BP, blood pressure; FPG, fasting plasma 
glucose; GGT RFS, Greater Green Triangle Risk Factor Study; 
HDL, high-density lipoprotein; LDL, low-density lipoprotein. </p>

<p>BMJ Open Diabetes Research and Care 2015;3:e000125. doi:10.1136/bmjdrc-2015-000125 </p>



<p>Epidemiology/health services research </p>

<p>approximately 154 000 and 87 000 Victorians in this age 
group would be expected to have IGT and IFG, respect-
ively. From 2007 to 2011, Life! received 29 000 referrals 
with 8412 initiating the program, and 3114 completed 
session 1 and session 6. 
12 Life! was recently reported to 
have received an updated total of 59 000 referrals. </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Given these numbers, the impact of the Life! program 
has likely been diluted by targeting those at compara-
tively lower risk of developing type 2 diabetes 
(ie, AUSDRISK≥12), and would have a greater impact if 
delivered exclusively to those with abnormal glucose 
metabolism. 
As the prevalence of IFG in our sample (4.7%) and 
the Australian population 
23 is relatively low, even at a 
cut-off of AUSDRISK≥20, the PPV for detecting 
FPG≥6.1 mmol/L was 28.4%. Although 2 h postglucose 
load data was not collected in this study, with the preva-
lence of IGT or IFG previously estimated at 16.4%, 
23 the 
expected PPV for detecting IGT or IFG would be slightly 
greater than that for IFG alone. These results demon-
strate that a diabetes risk assessment tool alone cannot 
be used to determine glucose metabolism status, and 
additional testing with OGTT, fasting glucose, or HbA1c </p>

<p>is required for those who are identified to be at elevated 
risk of progressing to type 2 diabetes, as suggested by 
international guidelines. 
15 16 Previous research has also 
demonstrated that this two-stage screening strategy is a 
more cost-effective method to identify individuals with 
undiagnosed diabetes, IFG and IGT than laboratory 
testing alone. 
25 Even though clinicians may opt to 
proceed directly to laboratory testing, setting an appro-
priate and cost-effective cut-off score for entry to lifestyle 
modification programs is important, given that Life! has 
seen a significant proportion of individuals recruited 
through a variety of methods not involving physicians or 
other health professionals. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Early involvement of family physicians represents an 
important opportunity to identify additional comorbid-
ities and chronic disease risk factors. Our results demon-
strate that a significant proportion of individuals at high 
risk of progressing to type 2 diabetes also have key car-
diovascular risk factors including hypertension, hyper-
cholesterolemia, and MetS (table 3). Previous research 
has demonstrated the existence of treatment gaps in 
treatment of hypertension and dyslipidemia among 
those participating in lifestyle modification programs. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>Table 2 Diabetic and cardiovascular risk factors in GGT RFS by sex and AUSDRISK category </p>

<p>AUSDRISK category 
0-5 
6 -8 
9 -11 
12-15 
16-19 
20-36 
Annual incidence of type 2 diabetes (%) 
0.2 
0.4 
0.7 
1.5 
3.0 
7.8 </p>

<p>Males 
Number of observations (%) 
10 (1.8) 
77 (13.7) 
180 (32.1) 
134 (23.9) 
107 (19.1) 
53 (9.5) 
Age (years) 
41.8 
47.8 
57.2 
61.0 
61.5 
65.5 
Weight (kg) 
87.7 
81.5 
81.6 
84.5 
97.2 
105.1 
BMI (kg/m 
2 ) 
27.9 
26.1 
26.6 
27.6 
31.5 
34.6 
Waist circumference (cm) 
92.2 
91.6 
94.4 
98.8 
110.6 
118.8 
FPG (mmol/L) 
5.2 
5.2 
5.2 
5.3 
5.6 
5.8 
Total cholesterol (mmol/L) 
5.2 
5.7 
5.6 
5.4 
5.1 
5.0 
HDL (mmol/L) 
1.4 
1.4 
1.4 
1.3 
1.2 
1.2 
LDL (mmol/L) 
3.2 
3.6 
3.5 
3.3 
3.1 
2.9 
Triglycerides (mmol/L) 
1.3 
1.5 
1.6 
1.7 
1.9 
2.0 
Systolic BP (mm Hg) 
120.4 
124.5 
130.2 
137.2 
143.2 
149.3 
Diastolic BP (mm Hg) 
79.3 
80.3 
79.3 
79.4 
82.4 
84.0 
MetS (%) 
11.1 
14.7 
26.8 
41.6 
64.9 
83.3 
Females 
Number of observations (%) 
98 (15.6) 
161 (25.6) 
117 (18.6) 
154 (24.5) 
75 (11.9) 
23 (3.7) 
Age (years) 
46.3 
56.1 
56.7 
61.3 
61.6 
65.0 
Weight (kg) 
65.2 
67.5 
74.1 
80.0 
88.8 
92.4 
BMI (kg/m 
2 ) 
24.2 
25.6 
28.1 
30.7 
34.0 
36.5 
Waist circumference (cm) 
77.8 
81.6 
88.0 
96.9 
104.6 
113.2 
FPG (mmol/L) 
4.9 
5.0 
5.1 
5.2 
5.5 
5.7 
Total cholesterol (mmol/L) 
5.1 
5.8 
5.5 
5.9 
5.5 
5.3 
HDL (mmol/L) 
1.8 
1.8 
1.6 
1.6 
1.4 
1.4 
LDL (mmol/L) 
2.8 
3.4 
3.2 
3.5 
3.2 
3.1 
Triglycerides (mmol/L) 
1.0 
1.2 
1.5 
1.8 
1.9 
1.9 
Systolic BP (mm Hg) 
117.0 
126.3 
132.0 
137.8 
141.1 
141.2 
Diastolic BP (mm Hg) 
71.7 
74.3 
77.3 
76.7 
77.8 
73.4 
MetS (%) 
4.4 
11.8 
28.3 
53.1 
64.7 
89.5 </p>

<p>AUSDRISK, Australian Type 2 Diabetes Risk Assessment Tool; BMI, body mass index; BP, blood pressure; FPG, fasting plasma glucose; 
GGT RFS, Greater Green Triangle Risk Factor Study; HDL, high-density lipoprotein; LDL, low-density lipoprotein; MetS, metabolic syndrome. </p>



<p>BMJ Open Diabetes Research and Care 2015;3:e000125. doi:10.1136/bmjdrc-2015-000125 </p>

<p>Epidemiology/health services research </p>

<p>Therefore, in addition to lifestyle modification, addres-
sing these risk factors is essential to reducing future 
disease burden, as cardiovascular disease contributes dis-
proportionately to the morbidity as a result of 
diabetes. </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>The baseline risk of diabetes among participants in 
lifestyle modification programs has important implica-
tions for the cost-effectiveness. Those at highest risk of 
progressing to type 2 diabetes represent the greatest 
potential for absolute reduction of incident cases of type 
2 diabetes. A meta-analysis of 30 studies found that 
annual rate of progression to diabetes was 10-15% in 
those with IGT and IFG, 4.4-6.4% in those with isolated 
IGT, and 6.1-9.2% in those with isolated IFG. 
6 These 
values are similar to the estimated annual rate of pro-
gression to type 2 diabetes for those scoring 
AUSDRISK≥20 (7.8%). Eligibility requirements for Life! 
should therefore include those with IGT, IFG, or both. 
On the basis of the results of the Finnish Diabetes 
Prevention Study (DPS) 
28 29 and the US DPP, 
5 30 the 
Life! program was estimated to potentially reduce risk of 
progression to type 2 diabetes by 21-39% at 8 months. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>However, these results are not necessarily generalizable 
to Life!, as participants in both the Finnish and US 
studies had diagnosed IGT. Even if the relative risk 
reduction is similar among risk groups, a lower baseline </p>

<p>risk translates to decreased absolute risk reduction and 
therefore decreased cost-effectiveness. 
A cost-effectiveness analysis is required to assess the 
economic implications of various entry requirements 
into lifestyle intervention programs. Multiple studies 
have reported lifestyle modification programs to be cost-
effective in participants with IGT or IFG. 
31-33 However, 
cost-effectiveness of lifestyle modification programs has 
not been reported in individuals without abnormal 
glucose metabolism but nonetheless are at elevated risk 
of developing type 2 diabetes. 
A limitation of our study is lack of OGTT or HbA1c 
data. As stated above, based on the prevalence of IFG 
and IGT, the PPV for detecting IGT would be expected 
to greater than that for IFG. While there is overlap 
between those with IGT and IFG, there remains a signifi-
cant proportion of individuals with IGT who have 
normal FPG values. 
23 Our study therefore does not 
wholly evaluate the ability of AUSDRISK to identify indi-
viduals who would benefit from lifestyle modification 
programs. Further study is warranted on the perform-
ance of AUSDRISK in the detection of IGT, elevated 
HbA1c, and undiagnosed diabetes where OGTT and 
HbA1c data are available from an Australian population. 
This research would complement our current study to 
identify a suitable AUSDRISK cut-off score for entry into </p>

<p>Table 3 Characteristics of GGT RFS participants included at different AUSDRISK cut-off values by sex </p>

<p>AUSDRISK cut-off 
Males 
Females 
≥12 
≥16 
≥20 
≥12 
≥16 
≥20 </p>

<p>Age (years) 
62.0 
62.8 
65.5 
61.7 
62.4 
65.0 
Weight (kg) 
92.8 
99.8 
105.1 
83.8 
89.7 
92.4 
BMI (kg/m 
2 ) 
30.3 
32.5 
34.6 
32.2 
34.6 
36.5 
25 to &lt;30 (%) 
42.5 
29.4 
17.0 
30.6 
21.4 
21.7 
≥30 (%) 
46.6 
68.1 
83.0 
61.1 
75.5 
78.3 
Waist circumference (cm) 
106.7 
113.3 
118.8 
100.6 
106.6 
113.2 
Male 94 to &lt;102; female 80 to &lt;88 (%) 
18.7 
5.6 
1.9 
4.8 
3.1 
0.0 
Male ≥102; female ≥88 (%) 
71.4 
92.5 
98.1 
90.1 
94.9 
100.0 
FPG (mmol/L) 
5.5 
5.7 
5.8 
5.4 
5.6 
5.7 
6.1-6.9 (%) 
11.2 
13.4 
20.8 
4.4 
3.5 
10.5 
≥7.0 (%) 
3.4 
5.6 
8.3 
2.2 
5.8 
5.3 
Total cholesterol (mmol/L) 
5.2 
5.1 
5.0 
5.7 
5.5 
5.3 
≥5.5 (%) 
42.2 
36.9 
30.2 
56.4 
48.0 
34.8 
HDL (mmol/L) 
1.3 
1.2 
1.2 
1.5 
1.4 
1.4 
Male &lt;1.0; female &lt;1.3 (%) 
15.7 
20.0 
20.8 
22.6 
27.6 
34.8 
LDL (mmol/L) 
3.2 
3.0 
2.9 
3.4 
3.2 
3.1 
≥3.5 (%) 
35.4 
31.9 
26.4 
40.9 
33.7 
13.0 
Triglycerides (mmol/L) 
1.8 
1.9 
2.0 
1.8 
1.9 
1.9 
≥2.0 (%) 
30.3 
35.6 
41.5 
33.7 
42.9 
43.5 
Systolic BP (mm Hg) 
141.6 
145.2 
149.3 
139.1 
141.1 
141.2 
≥140 (%) 
52.0 
59.4 
69.8 
44.4 
50.0 
52.2 
Diastolic BP (mm Hg) 
81.4 
83.0 
84.0 
76.7 
76.8 
73.4 
≥90 (%) 
23.1 
26.9 
28.3 
11.9 
12.2 
4.4 
MetS (%) 
57.3 
71.1 
83.3 
59.6 
70.1 
89.5 </p>

<p>AUSDRISK, Australian Type 2 Diabetes Risk Assessment Tool; BMI, body mass index; BP, blood pressure; FPG, fasting plasma glucose; 
GGT RFS, Greater Green Triangle Risk Factor Study; HDL, high-density lipoprotein; LDL, low-density lipoprotein; MetS, metabolic syndrome. </p>

<p>BMJ Open Diabetes Research and Care 2015;3:e000125. doi:10.1136/bmjdrc-2015-000125 </p>



<p>Epidemiology/health services research </p>

<p>Life! or any subsequent national DPP. Analysis of 
AUSDRISK performance in relation to detecting ele-
vated HbA1c levels is particularly significant given the 
future transition away from performing OGTT and 
towards HbA1c and FPG testing. 
Data in the GGT RFS was collected in Southwest 
Victoria from 2004 to 2006. There were no systematic dif-
ferences in the prevalence of IFG, MetS, and obesity 
among age and gender groups to those reported in the 
Victorian Health Monitor, a cross-sectional population 
health measurement survey collected between May 2009 </p>

<p>and April 2010. 
34 This suggests our sample for the 
purpose of these analyses remains a satisfactory indicator 
of population health characteristics in Victoria. 
This paper has focused exclusively on the perform-
ance of AUSDRISK as a screening tool to identify those 
who would benefit from a lifestyle modification pro-
grams to prevent type 2 diabetes. It is important to con-
sider that an effective screening method is only one 
aspect of implementing lifestyle modification programs 
to stop or delay the progression to type 2 diabetes. 
Lifestyle modification programs need to demonstrate </p>

<p>Table 4 Proportion of GGT RFS included at different AUSDRISK cut-off values by age and sex </p>

<p>AUSDRISK cut-off 
Age (years) 
N 
≥12 
≥14 
≥16 
≥18 
≥20 </p>

<p>Males 
40-49 
128 23.4 
14.1 
7.0 
1.6 
0.0 
50-59 
184 46.7 
32.1 
25.0 
14.1 
4.3 
60-69 
170 68.2 
55.9 
42.9 
26.5 
18.8 
70-74 
79 78.5 
55.7 
40.5 
26.6 
16.5 
Total 
561 52.4 
38.5 
28.5 
16.8 
9.4 
Females 
40-49 
182 14.8 
9.3 
5.5 
0.5 
0.5 
50-59 
189 36.5 
21.7 
13.8 
5.3 
2.6 
60-69 
187 60.4 
38.5 
22.5 
8.0 
4.8 
70-74 
70 61.4 
52.9 
28.6 
12.9 
11.4 
Total 
628 40.1 
26.6 
15.6 
5.6 
3.7 
Overall 
40-49 
310 18.4 
11.3 
6.1 
1.0 
0.3 
50-59 
373 41.6 
26.8 
19.3 
9.7 
3.5 
60-69 
357 64.1 
46.8 
32.2 
16.8 
11.5 
70-74 
149 70.5 
54.4 
34.9 
20.1 
14.1 
Total 
1189 45.9 
32.2 
21.7 
10.8 
6.4 
Population estimates in Victoria, Australia, aged 40-74 years 
Number of persons 
(000s) (95% CI) </p>

<p>916 (859 to 974) 
637 (583 to 690) 
425 (379 to 472) 
208 (174 to 243) 120 (93 to 146) </p>

<p>Proportion of 
population (95% CI) </p>

<p>39.5 (37.0 to 42.0) 27.5 (25.2 to 29.8) 18.3 (16.3 to 20.4) 9.0 (7.5 to 10.5) 5.2 (4.0 to 6.3) </p>

<p>Data are percentages unless otherwise stated. 
AUSDRISK, Australian Type 2 Diabetes Risk Assessment Tool; GGT RFS, Greater Green Triangle Risk Factor Study. </p>

<p>Table 5 Characteristics of AUSDRISK using various cut-off values for detecting abnormal fasting glucose </p>

<p>FPG≥6.1 mmol/L 
AUSDRISK cut-off 
Sensitivity 
Specificity 
PPV 
NPV </p>

<p>≥12 
81.3 (70.7 to 89.4) 
57.7 (54.6 to 60.7) 
12.3 (9.5 to 15.5) 
97.7 (96.2 to 98.7) 
≥13 
74.7 (63.3 to 84.0) 
63.8 (60.8 to 66.7) 
13.1 (10.0 to 16.6) 
97.2 (95.6 to 98.3) 
≥14 
68.0 (56.2 to 78.3) 
71.6 (68.7 to 74.3) 
14.8 (11.2 to 19.0) 
96.8 (95.3 to 98.0) 
≥15 
61.3 (49.4 to 72.4) 
76.4 (73.7 to 79.0) 
15.9 (11.9 to 20.7) 
96.4 (94.9 to 97.6) 
≥16 
53.3 (41.4 to 64.9) 
81.7 (79.1 to 84.0) 
17.5 (12.8 to 23.0) 
96.0 (94.5 to 97.2) 
≥17 
45.3 (33.8 to 57.3) 
86.3 (84.1 to 88.4) 
19.4 (13.8 to 26.1) 
95.6 (94.1 to 96.8) 
≥18 
34.7 (24.0 to 46.5) 
91.7 (89.9 to 93.4) 
23.4 (15.9 to 32.4) 
95.1 (93.5 to 96.3) 
≥19 
28.0 (18.2 to 39.6) 
94.6 (93.0 to 95.9) 
27.3 (17.7 to 38.6) 
94.7 (93.2 to 96.0) 
≥20 
25.3 (16.0 to 36.7) 
95.3 (93.9 to 96.5) 
28.4 (18.0 to 40.7) 
94.6 (93.1 to 95.9) </p>

<p>Data are % (95% CI). 
AUSDRISK, Australian Type 2 Diabetes Risk Assessment Tool; FPG, fasting plasma glucose; NPV, negative predictive value; PPV, positive 
predictive value. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>BMJ Open Diabetes Research and Care 2015;3:e000125. doi:10.1136/bmjdrc-2015-000125 </p>

<p>Epidemiology/health services research </p>

<p>effectiveness in reducing the progression to type 2 dia-
betes, and promote sustainable lifestyle changes so that 
effects are persistent in the long term. Moreover, lifestyle 
modification programs represent one part of a targeted 
approach to reducing the burden of type 2 diabetes, 
that ideally should be accompanied by a range of 
population-level approaches to diabetogenic environ-
ments. 
35 36 Where lifestyle medication programs are not 
available, screening individuals for risk of developing 
type 2 diabetes remains warranted, provided that simple 
lifestyle advice is provided and appropriate follow-up 
testing for those at high risk is offered, where 
appropriate. 
Our findings indicate that revisiting entry criteria into 
Life! is timely. Relying on AUSDRISK at a relatively low 
cut-off, while recruiting large numbers of people, 
hinders the long-term effectiveness of the program. 
A multifaceted approach is required. Initial screening 
with AUSDRISK, followed by OGTT, fasting glucose, or 
HbA1c for those at high risk to detect IFG, IGT, and 
undiagnosed diabetes is needed. Those with IFG and 
IGT should be invited into Life!, while those at high risk 
but with normal glucose metabolism should be offered 
lifestyle information and rescreened in the following 
3 years. To reliably establish and justify these thresholds, 
economic modeling is required to determine the most 
effective strategy. </p>

<p>Author affiliations </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Greater Green Triangle University Department of Rural Health, Flinders and 
Deakin Universities, Warrnambool, Victoria, Australia </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Western Centre for Health Research and Education, Western Health, 
University of Melbourne, St. Albans, Victoria, Australia </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>National Institute for Health and Welfare, Helsinki, Finland </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Faculty of Health Sciences, Institute of Public Health and Clinical Nutrition, 
University of Eastern Finland, Kuopio, Finland </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Faculty of Health, Deakin Population Health Strategic Research Centre, Deakin 
University, Burwood, Australia </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors thank Ms Anna Chapman, Dr Andrew Baird, 
the nurses who carried out the survey and the regional hospitals that provided 
facilities for the original GGT RFS study. </p>

<p>Contributors JAM helped conceived the idea, conducted the literature search, 
performed the data analysis, and wrote the manuscript. VLV helped conceive 
the idea, provided statistical support and wrote the manuscript. EDJ 
contributed to the discussion. TL, MP and MJC contributed to the results and 
discussion. EV contributed to the results. JAD conceived the idea and wrote 
the manuscript. All authors reviewed and edited the manuscript. JAM is the 
guarantor. </p>

<p>Funding The original GGT RFS study was supported by the Australian 
Government Department of Health and Ageing, the Australian Health 
Ministers' Advisory Council (Priority Driven Research in Population Health 
grant number 01/14), the Royal Australian College of General Practitioners, 
Sanofi-Aventis, Pfizer, Roche Diagnostics and Servier Laboratories Australia. 
JAM completed this research as part of a placement at GGT UDRH through 
the Specialist Training Program funded by the Royal Australasian College of 
Physicians. </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Flinders University Clinical Research Ethics Committee, 
Adelaide, approval number 207/034. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Epidemiology/health services research </p>





<p>BMJ Open Diabetes Research and Care 2015;3:e000125. doi:10.1136/bmjdrc-2015-000125 </p>

<p>Epidemiology/health services research </p>

</text></tei>