<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4830185" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Objective: To identify shared genes and pathways between common absence epilepsy (AE) sub-</p>

<p>types (childhood absence epilepsy [CAE], juvenile absence epilepsy [JAE], and unclassified 
absence epilepsy [UAE]) that may indicate common mechanisms for absence seizure generation 
and potentially a diagnostic continuum. </p>

<p>Methods: We used high-density single-nucleotide polymorphism arrays to analyze genome-wide </p>

<p>rare copy number variation (CNV) in a cohort of 144 children with AEs (95 CAE, 26 UAE, and 
23 JAE). </p>

<p>Results: We identified CNVs that are known risk factors for AE in 4 patients, including 3x </p>

<p>15q11.2 deletion. We also expanded the phenotype at 4 regions more commonly identified in 
other neurodevelopmental disorders: 1p36.33 duplication, 1q21.1 deletion, 22q11.2 duplica-
tion, and Xp22.31 deletion and duplication. Fifteen patients (10.5%) were found to carry rare 
CNVs that disrupt genes associated with neuronal development and function (8 CAE, 2 JAE, 
and 5 UAE). Four categories of protein are each disrupted by several CNVs: (1) synaptic vesicle 
membrane or vesicle endocytosis, (2) synaptic cell adhesion, (3) synapse organization and motility 
via actin, and (4) gap junctions. CNVs within these categories are shared across the AE subtypes. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Our results have reinforced the complex and heterogeneous nature of the AEs and </p>

<p>their potential for shared genetic mechanisms and have highlighted several pathways that may be 
important in epileptogenesis of absence seizures. GLOSSARY </p>

<p>AE 5 absence epilepsy; BDNF 5 brain-derived neurotrophic factor; CAE 5 childhood absence epilepsy; CNV 5 copy number 
variation; GGE 5 genetic generalized epilepsy; GO 5 Gene Ontology; GOI 5 gene of interest; ID 5 intellectual disability; 
JAE 5 juvenile absence epilepsy; LTP 5 long-term potentiation; MR 5 mental retardation; SNP 5 single-nucleotide poly-
morphism; UAE 5 unclassified absence epilepsy. </p>

<p>Absence seizures, abrupt and brief epileptic disruptions of consciousness associated with spike-
and-wave discharges on EEG, are predominant in 2 pediatric genetic generalized epilepsies 
(GGEs): childhood absence epilepsy (CAE) and juvenile absence epilepsy (JAE). Debate con-
cerning the most appropriate diagnostic criteria means many patients receive unclassified 
absence epilepsy (UAE) diagnosis. 
1 UAE could reflect a syndromic continuum between CAE 
and JAE or could be a distinct group (or groups) with different prognoses and potentially 
distinct pathophysiologic mechanisms. 
The complex genetic basis of CAE and JAE remains largely undiscovered; rare mutations and 
susceptibility alleles in predominantly GABA A receptors and voltage-activated calcium channels </p>

<p>have been identified to date. 
2,3 Multiple GGE 
subsyndromes can occur in one family, which 
indicates a close genetic relationship between 
the AEs, consistent with an oligogenic model 
of inheritance. 
4 AEs are often studied apart, 
but some investigations show common genetic 
causality, 
5 whereas others identify factors that 
are not shared. 
6 Recurrent microdeletions at 
15q11.2, 15q13.3, and 16p13.11 are strongly 
associated risk factors for GGEs, occurring in 
0.5% to 1% of patients. 
7 Around 8% of pa-
tients with GGE also carry rare gene-disrupting 
copy number variations (CNVs), with enrich-
ment for genes previously implicated in neuro-
developmental disorders, including deletions of 
RBFOX1 and NRXN1. </p>

<p>8-11 </p>

<p>We identify novel rare CNVs in a cohort of 
classical CAE and JAE cases, as well as UAEs 
with atypical seizure patterns or age at onset. 
The identification of shared genes and path-
ways could indicate common mechanisms for 
absence seizure generation. </p>

<p>METHODS Study participants and phenotyping. Unre-</p>

<p>lated patients of European ancestry, previously recruited for 2 
studies of GGEs from 1997 to 2007, were ascertained from 
hospitals across Europe: United Kingdom, Greece, France, 
Germany, Austria, the Netherlands, Denmark, Sweden, Finland, 
and Italy, as reported previously. 
1,12 In patients with absences but 
without notable myoclonus, we used an adapted version of the 
International League Against Epilepsy 1989 Criteria to classify as 
CAE, JAE, and UAE (table e-1 at Neurology.org/ng) based on 
age at onset, seizure frequency, and EEG findings. 
1,13 The criteria 
require "normal background" EEG, which was interpreted as age-
appropriate normal posterior dominant rhythm during 
wakefulness (sleep EEG was not specifically evaluated for this 
study). Interictal fragments of generalized or bilateral symmetric 
spike-and-wave discharges and some isolated focal discharges are 
commonly seen in AEs and were not considered an exclusion 
criterion for our study. 
To maximize inclusion of relevant patients, criteria were adap-
ted as follows: (1) very frequent absences (several times a day, pyk-
nolepsy) were considered an inclusion criterion for CAE and an 
exclusion criterion for JAE, which aided classification of children 
in the intermediate age range; (2) patients ,4 years who would 
otherwise meet the definition for CAE were included as CAE in our 
analysis, as their clinical course often resembles that of classical 
CAE </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>; and (3) patients with focal neurologic deficits were excluded 
from analysis. Although grossly normal cognitive development is 
presumed in CAE and JAE, patients with comorbid developmental 
delay were included as UAE. 
This study was a retrospective analysis of previously recruited 
cohorts; full reports of MRIs and EEGs of some patients were not 
available for reanalysis in this study (table 1). Patients underwent 
EEG in their clinical workup and had syndromic diagnoses of a 
GGE with predominant absences based on these 
1,12 ; further anal-
ysis of phenotypic information presented in this study was used to 
consistently classify patients into subtypes, rather than question </p>

<p>the GGE diagnosis. Any genetic testing performed as part of 
clinical care was not accessed. </p>

<p>Standard protocol approvals, registrations, and patient 
consents. Individuals from the United Kingdom were recruited </p>

<p>into a previous study as detailed in references 1 and 15 (ethics 
approval numbers 835/5/97 and 98-334, respectively). Written 
informed consent was obtained from all participants and/or their 
parents. Other UK individuals and those with European ancestry 
from Greece, France, Germany, Austria, the Netherlands, 
Denmark, Sweden, Finland, and Italy, collected as part of the sec-
ond study detailed here, 
12 had age-appropriate written informed 
consent obtained. Full protocol approval was obtained from local 
research ethics committees and/or participating institutions as 
appropriate. </p>

<p>Genotyping and copy number variant detection. High-</p>

<p>density single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) genotyping 
arrays (HumanCoreExome-12 v1-0; Illumina, San Diego, CA) 
were used to detect the presence of CNVs from genomic DNA. 
Arrays were processed according to the manufacturer's 
instructions. To minimize false-positives, CNVs were called 
using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Nexus Copy Number</rs> package (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">BioDiscovery Inc</rs>, 
Hawthorne, CA) from signal intensity data after preprocessing 
in <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Illumina</rs> <rs id="software-1" type="software">GenomeStudio</rs> Software. In Nexus, systematic array 
correction files were used with the linear correction model to 
correct for GC bias, and a significance threshold of 1 3 10 </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>was applied. The SNP-FAST2 Segmentation algorithm was used 
for analysis, with homozygous frequency threshold at 0.95, 
hemizygous loss threshold at 20.23, and single copy gain at 
0.13 for the log R ratio. A total of 184 samples were processed 
on the arrays. Samples were removed from the project if they 
had 1 or more of the following: a ,95% call rate (0 samples), 
a probe-to-probe variability (quality) of .0.1 (15 samples), a sex 
mismatch (0 samples), and .100 CNVs (34 samples), leaving n 5 
144. To avoid false-positives, only variants that contained .12 
consecutive altered SNP probes and that were .20 kb in size were 
analyzed. CNVs showing .90% coverage of variants of a frequency 
of $0.1% of the same type, reported in the Database of Genomic 
Variants (http://dgv.tcag.ca/dgv/app/home), using array comparative 
genomic hybridization or SNP arrays, were considered copy number 
polymorphisms and were excluded from further analysis (i.e., CNVs 
reported in this study are designated as "rare"). CNVs that did not 
overlap exons of a gene were also excluded. The potential for 
pathogenicity was based on gene content/disruption, CNV size, 
frequency, and previous association of genes or regions with 
epilepsy and related neurologic conditions. Gene products were 
annotated for Gene Ontology (GO) categories within biological 
processes and molecular functions using the Gene Ontology 
Consortium Web tool at http://geneontology.org/. </p>

<p>Validation of copy number variants. CNV validation was </p>

<p>performed with real-time quantitative PCR using the Qiagen 
(Hilden, Germany) Type-it CNV Sybr Green Kit according to 
the manufacturer's instructions. Reactions were performed in 
10.4-mL volumes in the ABI PRISM 7900 system (Applied 
Biosystems, Foster City, CA). PCR conditions were 5 minutes 
at 95°C followed by 35 cycles of 30 seconds of denaturation at 
95°C and 30 seconds of annealing/extension at 60°C. All samples 
were run in triplicate. The PCR efficiency of each primer pair was 
checked over a dilution series of DNA for comparability with the 
proprietary reference assay of a multicopy gene. The DDC T 
method of relative quantification was used, and the ratio (R) of 
the copy number change of the gene of interest (GOI) in the case 
sample was compared with the control sample calculated using 
R 5 2 </p>

<p>2DDCT </p>

<p>. If R . 1, the copy number of the GOI was higher in </p>

<p> 
Neurology: Genetics </p>

<p>ª 2016 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>the case than in the control; if R , 1, the copy number was lower 
in the case. </p>

<p>RESULTS We studied genome-wide CNV in a 
cohort of 144 European patients with AEs. Of 
these, 95 (66%) had CAE, 26 (18%) had UAE, 
and 23 (16%) had JAE. All CNVs called are listed </p>

<p>in table e-2. We identified recurrent CNV hotspots 
that are known risk factors for GGEs in 4 
individuals (tables 1 and 2). At the GGE hotspot 
15q11.2, there were 3 deletions: 1 in a patient with 
CAE, 1 in a patient with JAE, and 1 in a patient with 
UAE. We also noted a 15q11.2 duplication in a 
patient with CAE. We recorded a smaller duplication </p>

<p>Table 1 
Clinical characteristics of patients with absence epilepsy with recurrent risk factor or rare potential risk factor CNVs </p>

<p>Patient ID (sex) </p>

<p>Diagnosis (age 
at onset, y) 
Seizures </p>

<p>Family history 
(degree) </p>

<p>Interictal epileptiform 
abnormalities </p>

<p>Ictal EEG and activation 
procedures </p>

<p>C382 (F) 
JAE (9-GCTS) 
GTCS, absences, very rare 
myoclonic jerks </p>

<p>None 
PSW 
Response to hyperventilation not 
listed </p>

<p>361202 (M) 
CAE (8) 
Typical absences 
NA 
None seen 
3-Hz GSW on hyperventilation </p>

<p>C626 (F) 
JAE (14) 
Absences; initially GTCS, 
nonepileptic seizures </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>None 
Atypical GSW: irregular 
spikes and sharp waves </p>

<p>No ictal EEG, no response to 
hyperventilation; PPR unknown </p>

<p>371201 (F) 
CAE (7) 
Typical absences 
NA 
Brief generalized PSW 
3-Hz GSW on hyperventilation </p>

<p>367202 (F) 
UAE (7) 
Atypical absences (.1-min duration) NA 
None seen 
No ictal EEG </p>

<p>C215 (M) 
CAE (7) 
Typical absences 
Yes (2nd) 
None seen 
3-Hz GSW on hyperventilation </p>

<p>C457 (F) 
CAE (7) 
Typical absences 
None 
None seen 
3-Hz GSW on hyperventilation, 
several spontaneous absences </p>

<p>C485 (F) 
CAE (8) 
Typical absences, pyknoleptic 
presentation; GTCS onset 14 y </p>

<p>None 
GSW with right emphasis 
GSW with right emphasis; GSW on 
hyperventilation; absence during 
EEG </p>

<p>424004 (F) 
UAE (7) 
Atypical absences (degree of 
postural tone loss) </p>

<p>NA 
NA for review 
NA for review </p>

<p>C516 (M) 
JAE (9-GTCS) 
GTCS; absence onset in teens 
None 
Atypical GSW 
PPR present; no absence during EEG </p>

<p>667201 (M) 
CAE (9) 
Typical absences 
NA 
None seen 
3-Hz GSW and PSW on 
hyperventilation </p>

<p>369201 (F) 
CAE (6) 
Typical absences 
NA 
None seen 
3-Hz GSW </p>

<p>341203 (F) 
UAE (4) 
Typical absences </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>NA 
None seen 
3-Hz GSW on hyperventilation </p>

<p>357201 (M) 
UAE (1) 
Typical absences </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Yes (1st) 
GSW 
3-Hz GSW on hyperventilation </p>

<p>397201 (M) 
CAE (3) 
Typical absences, GTCS 
NA 
GSW 
NA for review </p>

<p>C329 (M) 
CAE (7) 
Typical absences (until 21 y), 
GTCS in teens </p>

<p>None 
NA for review 
"Typical centrencephalic petit mal 
epilepsy" on EEG report </p>

<p>C8 (F) 
UAE (7) 
Atypical absences, initially 2-3/ 
day; aura later reported </p>

<p>Yes (2nd) 
Generalized PSW, 
bilateral temporal 
sharp waves </p>

<p>PSW with aura later reported; no 
absence during EEG </p>

<p>717201 (F) 
CAE (10) 
Typical absences 
NA 
None seen 
3-Hz GSW </p>

<p>C72 (M) 
UAE (6) 
Atypical absences (atypical spike-
wave on hyperventilation pause) </p>

<p>NA 
Atypical spike-wave 
Bursts of slow waves with few 
associated spikes with pause in 
hyperventilation </p>

<p>349201 (M) 
CAE (6) 
Typical absences 
NA 
None seen 
2.5-Hz SW on hyperventilation and 
photosensitive </p>

<p>C451 (M) 
CAE (4) 
Atypical absences 
Yes (1st) 
GSW 
No ictal EEG, no response to 
hyperventilation </p>

<p>830201 (F) 
CAE (9) 
Typical absences 
NA 
Reported focal 
abnormality, NA for 
review </p>

<p>3-Hz GSW on hyperventilation </p>

<p>C454 (M) 
JAE (11) 
Typical absences daily and in 
runs; 1 GTCS age 11y </p>

<p>None 
PSW; focal right-sided 
discharge </p>

<p>PSW; right-sided discharge </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CAE 5 childhood absence epilepsy; CNV 5 copy number variation; GCTS 5 generalized tonic-clonic seizures; GSW 5 generalized spike-
wave discharges; JAE 5 juvenile absence epilepsy; NA 5 not available; PSW 5 polyspike-wave discharges; UAE 5 unclassified absence epilepsy. 
Typical absences: brief interruptions of consciousness (4-20 seconds) with EEG ictal GSW at 3 Hz. Family history refers to family history of any epileptic 
seizure disorder but does not include febrile seizures. Under the "Seizures" and "Ictal EEG" columns, no GTCS, no myoclonus, no febrile seizures (FS), and no 
photoparoxysmal response (PPR) is implied unless stated otherwise. Although patients underwent EEG as part of their initial clinical workup and diagnosis, 
not all full EEGs or EEG reports were available for review; this is indicated in the table above. 
a MRI: no epileptogenic lesion but scattered white matter change and cerebellar atrophy. 
b Also has developmental delay and FS. 
c MRI reported abnormal but no epileptogenic lesion; measles at 10 months; FS provoked by measles, mumps, and rubella vaccine; developmental delay. </p>

<p>Neurology: Genetics </p>

<p>
ª 2016 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>in the patient with JAE (C626) within a second GGE 
hotspot, 15q13.3, including the candidate gene 
CHRNA7. CNVs at 4 further recurrent CNV 
hotspots, more commonly recorded in other 
neurodevelopmental disorders, were also identified in 
this study: a distal 1p36.3 duplication including the 
infantile spasms candidate gene KLHL17 
16 (JAE), a </p>

<p>1q21.1 deletion (CAE), a 2.8-Mb duplication at 
22q11.2 (CAE), and 1 deletion and 1 duplication at 
Xp22.31 (CAE/JAE). Of note, 1 patient with JAE, 
C626, carries 3 of these recurrent CNVs (tables 
1 and 2). 
Fifteen patients (11%) were found to carry rare 
CNVs that disrupt genes associated with neuronal </p>

<p>Table 2 
Genetic characteristics of patients with absence epilepsy with recurrent risk factor or rare potential risk factor CNVs </p>

<p>Patient ID (sex) </p>

<p>Absence 
epilepsy 
CNV coordinates (hg19/B37); cytoband 
Size (kb) and type UCSC gene content </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Cases with recurrent risk 
factor CNVs </p>

<p>C382 (F) 
JAE 
chr1:0-914,659; 1p36.33 
914, Dup 
OR4F5, OR4F29 SAMD11, NOC2L, KLHL17, 
PLEKHN1, PERM1 </p>

<p>361202 (M) 
CAE 
chr1:146,295,308-147,826,789; 1q21.1 
1531, Del 
LOC100288142, PRKAB2, PDIA3P, GJA5, 
GJA8 (17 others) </p>

<p>C626 (F) 
JAE 
chr15:21,903,815-23,103,405; 15q11.2 
1199, Del 
CXADRP2, POTEB, OR4M2, OR4N4 (17 others 
including NIPA2) </p>

<p>chr15:31,991,226-32,567,234; 15q13.3 
576, Dup 
CHRNA7 </p>

<p>chrX:6,457,553-8,123,447; Xp22.31 
1666, Dup 
HDHD1, STS, VCX, PNPLA, VCX2 </p>

<p>371201 (F) 
CAE 
chr15:21,903,815-23,103,405; 15q11.2 
1199, Dup 
As above </p>

<p>367202 (F) 
UAE 
chr15:21,903,815-23,103,405; 15q11.2 
1199, Del 
As above </p>

<p>C485 (F) 
CAE 
chr22:21,803,945-24,654,974; 22q11.21-
q11.23 </p>

<p>2851, Dup 
HIC2, TMEM191C, PI4KAP2, UBE2L3, YDJC 
(1 42 others) </p>

<p>C215 (M) 
CAE 
chr15:22,522,310-23,249,493; 15q11.2 
727, Del 
GOLGA8DP, GOLGA6L1, TUBGCP5, CYFIP1, 
NIPA2, NIPA1 </p>

<p>C457 (F) 
CAE 
chrX:6,449,682-8,138,035; Xp22.31 
1688, Del 
VCX3A, HDHD1, STS, VCX, PNPLA, VCX2 </p>

<p>Cases with potential risk 
factor CNVs </p>

<p>424004 (F) 
UAE 
chr1:240,509,364-240,536,152; 1q43 
26, Dup 
FMN2 </p>

<p>C516 (M) 
JAE 
chr4:20,979,028-21,177,688; 4p15.32 
199. Del 
KCNIP4 </p>

<p>667201 (M) 
CAE 
chr4:183,599,915-184,966,267; 4q35.1 
1366, Dup 
TENM3, DCTD, FAM92A1P2, WWC2-AS2, 
WWC2 (17 others) </p>

<p>369201 (F) 
CAE 
chr5:75,611,865-75,640,024; 5q13.3 
28, Dup 
SV2C </p>

<p>341203 (F) 
UAE 
chr6:38,360,355-38,455,141; 6p21.2 
95, Del 
BTBD9 </p>

<p>357201 (M) 
UAE 
chr7:37,703,928-39,432,281; 7p14.1 
1728, Del 
GPR141, NME8, SFRP4, EPDR1, STARD3NL 
(15 others including AMPH) </p>

<p>chr3:96,735,452-97,332,506; 3q11.2 
597, Del 
EPHA6 </p>

<p>397201 (M) 
CAE 
chr9:12,418,777-13,258,831; 9p23 
840, Dup 
TYRP1, LURAP1L, MPDZ </p>

<p>C329 (M) 
CAE 
chr9:87,412,328-88,425,972; 9q21.33 
1013, Dup 
NTRK2, AGTPBP1 </p>

<p>C8 (F) 
UAE 
chr10:56,195,290-56,465,459; 10q21.1 
270, Del 
PCDH15 </p>

<p>717201 (F) 
CAE 
chr11:93,772,465-93,903,781; 11q21 
131, Dup 
HEPHL1, PANX1 </p>

<p>C72 (M) 
UAE 
chr14:103,402,254-103,462,143; 14q32.3 
60, Del 
CDC42BPB </p>

<p>349201 (M) 
CAE 
chr16:77,768,588-78,186,513; 16q23.1 
417, Del 
NUDT7, VAT1L, CLEC3A, WWOX </p>

<p>C454 (M) 
JAE 
chr16:78,404,208-78,431,974; 16q23.1 
27, Del 
WWOX </p>

<p>C451 (M) 
CAE 
chr20:12,662,517-14,147,317; 20p12.1 
1484, Dup 
SPTLC3, ISM1, TASP1, ESF1, NDUFAF5, 
SEL1L2, MACROD2 </p>

<p>830201 (F) 
CAE 
chrX:70,026,229-71,094,940; Xq13.1 
1069, Del 
TEX11, SLC7A3, SNX12, FOXO4 (113 others 
including NLGN3, GJB1) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CAE 5 childhood absence epilepsy; CNV 5 copy number variation; Del 5 deletion; Dup 5 duplication; JAE 5 juvenile absence epilepsy; 
UAE 5 unclassified absence epilepsy. 
Eight patients with absence epilepsy carry 10 recurrent CNVs classified as risk factors for their epilepsy, and 15 patients carry CNVs classified as 
potential risk factors. 
a Boldface indicates candidate gene. </p>

<p> 
Neurology: Genetics </p>

<p>ª 2016 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>development and function (tables 1 and 2). One 
patient with UAE carries 2 of these CNVs. Although 
the numbers are too small to make population-level 
inference, it seems that the patients with UAE are 
more likely to have a CNV in this category than are 
the patients with JAE and CAE (5/23 UAE, 2/22 
JAE, and 8/91 CAE). The assumption of potential 
pathogenicity is detailed in the Methods section. Of 
these 15 patients, 4 patients with CAE and 1 patient 
with UAE carry large novel CNVs of .1 Mb in size. 
The other 11 CNVs range from 26 to 840 kb. For 
patients with multigene CNVs, several genes may con-
tribute to the phenotype, depending on the function. 
Four categories of protein are each disrupted by sev-
eral CNVs: synaptic vesicle membrane or vesicle endocy-
tosis (GO:0030672/GO:1900242), synaptic cell 
adhesion (GO:0007155), synapse organization and neu-
ronal migration via actin (actin binding GO:0003779 
and actin cytoskeletal reorganization GO:0031532), 
and gap junctions (GO:0005921); these are shared 
across the AE subtypes. We also report 2 individuals 
with CAE (C454 and 349201) and deletions disrupting 
the WW domain-containing oxidoreductase (WWOX), 
known to cause epilepsy, cerebellar ataxia, and mental 
retardation (MR) as well as infantile epileptic 
encephalopathies. </p>

<p>17   In 2 individuals with UAE, genes involved with 
synaptic vesicles are disrupted: the vesicle surface pro-
tein amphiphysin 1 (AMPH) (357201) and BTBD9, 
which controls vesicle recycling (341203). SV2C, 
encoding synaptic vesicle glycoprotein 2C, is also dis-
rupted in individual 369201 with CAE. 
Synaptic cell adhesion genes are disrupted by CNVs 
in 4 individuals: 2 with CAE and 2 with UAE. Individ-
ual 830201 with CAE carries a large novel deletion of 
17 genes, including NLGN3 (neuroligin3), a postsyn-
aptic cell adhesion molecule; individual 357201 with 
UAE (also with the AMPH deletion described above) 
has a breakpoint within the Eph receptor tyrosine 
kinase EPHA6, signaling through which neuronal 
adhesion and development are regulated. TENM3, 
encoding a teneurin transmembrane protein that pro-
motes cell adhesion, is disrupted by a duplication 
breakpoint in patient 667201 with CAE. Lastly, 3 
exons of the protocadherin PCDH15 are deleted in 
C8 with UAE. 
Several AE CNVs reported in this study also dis-
rupt proteins that act to organize the synapse or pro-
mote neuronal migration via interactions with the 
actin cytoskeleton: the serine/threonine protein 
kinase CDC42BPB (C72, UAE), FMN2 encoding 
formin 2 (424004, UAE), and MPDZ (previously 
MUPP1), which contains multiple protein interac-
tion PDZ domains for controlling large synaptic com-
plexes (397201, CAE). EPHA6, mentioned above, 
also regulates cell-matrix interactions and migration, </p>

<p>which indicates the complex interplay between these 
pathways. 
Two patients with CAE carry disrupted gap junction 
genes: GJB1, encoding CX32 (830201), a brain and 
peripheral myelin connexin family member, and 
PANX1, encoding Pannexin1. Of note, the hotspot 
deletion at 1q21.1 in individual 361202 also contains 
2 further connexin gap junction genes, GJA5 and GJA8, 
although they seem not to be expressed in neurons. 
CNVs in the final 3 patients, although disrupting 
genes that have known functions in neuronal devel-
opment and activity, do not share common features 
with the others. Individual C451 with CAE has a 
1.5-kb duplication of 7 genes at 20p12.7, including 
a breakpoint in MACROD2, an enzyme that removes 
ADP-ribose from proteins and a well-known risk fac-
tor for autistic traits. 
18 The potassium channel inter-
acting protein gene KCNIP4 is disrupted by a 
deletion breakpoint in JAE patient C516. Lastly, 
C329, diagnosed with CAE, carries a duplication 
with a breakpoint in NTRK2 (previously TRKB), a 
neurotrophic tyrosine kinase receptor and brain-
derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) receptor. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION The genetic basis of the AEs is com-
plex, with individuals carrying different patterns of 
genetic variants that determine their risk for seizures, 
some of which may be shared between the different 
types of epilepsy. 
3 Even in large families, it is difficult 
to establish genotype-phenotype relationships because 
different members may carry the same genetic variants 
but have different phenotypic manifestations of AE. 
The search for susceptibility variants has now moved 
to whole-genome studies of CNV, epigenetic analysis, 
and genome sequencing. 
Recurrent deletions at 15q11.2, 15q13.3, and 
16p13.11 are consistently identified rare risk factors 
for GGEs including AEs, 
7 and indeed, we found 3 
deletions at 15q11.2 in our cohort. We also noted a 
microduplication within the 15q13.3 hotspot of the 
candidate gene CHRNA7 in a patient also carrying a 
15q11.2 deletion. Although deletions at 15q11.2 are 
robustly associated with GGEs and developmental dis-
orders, duplications at this locus, seen in 1 patient in 
our cohort, were initially reported as variants of 
unknown significance. However, more recent studies 
of the region indicate that mild intellectual disability 
(ID), autism, and seizures are common features in in-
dividuals carrying these duplications, 
19 providing some 
evidence that this CNV may be a risk factor for the 
epilepsy in the individual described here. We also 
uncovered CNVs that are more commonly recorded 
in other neurodevelopmental disorders at 4 further 
recurrent regions. Only 1 patient with JAE and none 
with CAE have been previously reported with the 
1q21.1 deletion. 
20 The deletion leads to a variable </p>

<p>Neurology: Genetics </p>

<p>
ª 2016 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>phenotype, and seizures are seen infrequently, indicat-
ing the novelty of this region in a patient with CAE. 
We also identified 1 deletion and 1 duplication at 
Xp22.31, previously associated with MR and ichthyo-
sis. Although seizures are now becoming a more widely 
reported phenotype, 
21 absence seizures are not. 
22q11.2 duplication syndrome has a variable pheno-
type, with MR and motor delay being the most com-
mon features. Seizures are reported rarely but are not 
well described apart from a recent case with continuous 
spikes and waves during sleep. 
22 Lastly, we observed a 
914-kb duplication of the distal end of Chr1 
(1p36.33), which included the infantile spasm candi-
date KLHL17. 
16 Duplications of 1p36.3 are less fre-
quently recorded, are of variable size, and include 
developmental delay, seizures, and hypotonia with 
wide phenotypic heterogeneity and an overall "milder" 
phenotype than the reciprocal deletions. 
23 It may be 
that the smaller number of duplicated genes in the 
patient described here, including KLHL17, could pre-
dispose to her JAE, but it is difficult to ascribe patho-
genicity in such an isolated case. It seems from previous 
large-scale studies of the GGEs that variation at these 
recurrent regions is indeed rare within the AEs, but 
targeted studies in more patients could help to 
resolve this. 
The identification of 2 patients with CAE with de-
letions that disrupt coding regions of WWOX, known 
to cause infantile epileptic encephalopathies as well as 
epilepsy, cerebellar ataxia, and MR, is intriguing. </p>

<p>17   These severe phenotypes are caused by biallelic muta-
tions or CNV within the gene. The rare heterozygous 
CNVs seen here may cause the less severe syndrome 
of CAE, although very rare exonic deletions (0.04%) 
have been reported in the Database of Genomic Var-
iants. Screening for mutations and CNV as well as 
protein function work in other patients with AE may 
help to answer this question. 
In this investigation we also show that patients 
from all 3 subsyndromes carry rare CNVs that disrupt 
genes shared largely within 4 categories of function, 
involved in developing neural circuitry and at the 
mature synapse. All of these CNVs are unique to 
a given individual and confirm the strong genetic het-
erogeneity in the AEs. 
Synaptic vesicles store and move neurotransmit-
ters for release at the presynaptic membrane, and sev-
eral proteins involved in vesicle release and recycling 
have been related directly to epileptogenesis 
24 and 
are also enriched in CNVs from patients with infan-
tile spasms. 
16 In our investigation we identified 3 
individuals with disrupted synaptic vesicle genes: 
AMPH, SV2C, and BTBD9. AMPH is involved in 
neuronal transmission and development through 
clathrin-mediated endocytosis of synaptic vesicles. 
Amphiphysin 1 is also a substrate for CDKL5, a </p>

<p>kinase associated with neurodevelopmental disorders 
such as X-linked West (infantile spasms) syndrome 
and Rett syndrome. 
25 SV2C acts via presynaptic cal-
cium to regulate neurotransmitter release from 
vesicles in glutamatergic synapses. SV2C shows 
altered brain expression patterns in patients with tem-
poral lobe epilepsy, 
26 and all 3 SV2 family members 
(A, B, and C) are candidates for epilepsy. 
27 Lastly, 
BTBD9, a gene associated with restless legs syndrome 
and Tourette syndrome, may regulate synaptic plas-
ticity via altered synaptic vesicle recycling. </p>

<p>28   Several mechanisms believed to contribute to epi-
leptogenesis are likely to be regulated by cell adhesion, 
such as the dysregulation of GABAergic transmission, 
the guidance of axonal growth, and the stabilization 
of synaptic contacts and long-term potentiation 
(LTP). 
29 Synaptic cell adhesion genes PCDH15, 
NLNG3, TENM3, and EPHA6 are disrupted by 
CNV in our study. The protocadherin PCDH15 me-
diates the formation, maturation, and specification of 
synapses and is a determinant of brain serotonin trans-
porter expression. 
30 Mutations of PCDH15 are known 
to cause Usher syndrome 1F, in which ID and psychi-
atric disturbances are common, and deletions are 
found in patients with epileptic encephalopathies. </p>

<p>31   The family member PCDH19 also causes X-linked 
infantile epileptic encephalopathy. 
32 The postsynaptic 
cell adhesion molecule NLGN3 functions in synapto-
genesis and neuron-glia communications and is a can-
didate for autism with comorbid epilepsy, in which it 
may influence seizure susceptibility. 
33 The teneurin 
member TENM3 promotes cell adhesion and synaptic 
organization, similar to the role of neuroligins, and 
may also regulate excitatory synaptic strength via latro-
philin binding. 
34 Lastly, the Eph receptor tyrosine 
kinase EPHA6 also regulates neuronal cell adhesion, 
cell-matrix interactions (below), and migration, with 
clear roles in modulating synapse formation and plas-
ticity and axon guidance. </p>

<p>35   A third category of genes that are disrupted in 3 pa-
tients with AE are those that organize the synapse and 
neuronal migration via the actin cytoskeleton. MPDZ 
controls large complexes at the synapse and is involved 
in learning-and memory-related synaptic plasticity. Its 
dysfunction has pleiotropic effects on vulnerability to 
seizures through interactions with many types of syn-
aptic receptors. 
36 The kinase CDC42BPB regulates 
cytoskeletal remodeling and cell migration 
37 and is 
involved in hippocampal LTP. Lastly, FMN2 mediates 
synaptic spine density and is highly expressed in the 
developing brain. FMN2 mutations can cause nonsyn-
dromic ID. </p>

<p>38   Gap junctions, both between dendrites and 
between axons and glia, are highly implicated in syn-
chronous seizure activity, and blocking communica-
tion at gap junctions is anticonvulsant. 
39 Two gap </p>

<p> 
Neurology: Genetics </p>

<p>ª 2016 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>junction proteins disrupted here, connexin Cxs32 
(encoded by GJB1) and Pannexin1 (encoded by 
PANX1), are good AE candidates. Mutations in 
GJB1 cause X-linked Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease, 
with some patients also showing CNS symptoms. </p>

<p>40   Cxs32 expression is also altered in the hippocampi of 
patients with mesial temporal lobe epilepsy. 
41 Pan-
nexin1 is upregulated in epileptic brain tissue and 
may contribute to seizures by increasing the levels 
of extracellular ATP. Targeting Pannexin1 improves 
seizure outcome in animal models. </p>

<p>42   Other GOIs that were disrupted by rare CNVs in 
patients with AE include NTRK2, a BDNF receptor 
that modulates excitatory transmission, synaptic plas-
ticity, and hippocampal LTP and is required for epi-
leptogenesis in animal models. 
43 Patients with mesial 
temporal lobe epilepsy show altered NTRK2 expres-
sion, 
44 and dysregulated NTRK2-BDNF signaling is 
implicated in several neurodevelopmental disorders, 
indicating its excellent candidacy for AE. The potassi-
um channel interacting protein gene KCNIP4, deleted 
in a patient with JAE, forms part of a negative feedback 
loop in the Wnt/b-catenin pathway that regulates neu-
ronal development and is a candidate for attention-
deficit/hyperactivity disorder. 
45 Lastly, the autism risk 
factor gene MACROD2 was also disrupted in a patient 
with CAE. </p>

<p>18   A major limitation of our study is that it is a retro-
spective analysis of cohorts collected for previous 
genetic studies of AEs. This meant that we did not 
have useable DNA from family members to assess 
the inheritance of the CNVs and we were not able 
to recontact the families for collection of new DNA. 
Analysis of CNV inheritance would have aided in 
our putative assignment of pathogenicity to the CNVs, 
as those that were inherited with the disorder, or de no-
vo in the probands, would be more likely to predispose 
to the epilepsy. We were also unable to access the orig-
inal EEGs and the MRI reports of some patients, 
which would have allowed us to provide more detailed 
phenotypes in table 1. However, patients' diagnoses 
were ascertained both through the clinical services 
from which they were recruited and by experts in 
childhood epilepsies collating the cohorts for the initial 
studies; we therefore believe that other diagnoses have 
been sufficiently excluded, and further classification 
based on available data for our cohort is robust. 
Our study of CNV across the spectrum of AEs has 
reinforced both the complex and heterogeneous nature 
of these disorders and their potential for shared genetic 
mechanisms. We have strengthened the evidence for 
the role of recurrent CNVs and added AEs as disorders 
potentially associated with CNV at 1q21.1 and 
Xp22.31. Through the study of rare CNV, we indicate 
pathways that may be disrupted across AE subtypes 
and open the door for investigations of neural network </p>

<p>behavior in future large-scale studies of broad category 
patients with AE and their families. This, as well as 
functional work of the disrupted genes, will help in 
understanding the role of these potential new pathways 
in seizure generation. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </p>

<p>L.A. and D.K.P. conceptualized the study. L.A. designed the study. L.A. 
and R.E.R. carried out the laboratory work and analysis of CNV data. 
A.V., R.R., K.V.E., A.M., and L.N. carried out the collection, phenotyp-
ing, and databasing of the patient samples. All authors contributed to 
drafting and revising the manuscript. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENT </p>

<p>The authors thank the participants in this study and their families, without 
whom this research would not be possible. </p>

<p>STUDY FUNDING </p>

<p>This work was supported by a Lilly Innovation Fellowship award (L.A.); 
The Waterloo Foundation (L.A., D.K.P.); European Union Marie Curie 
International Reintegration Award of the Seventh Framework Pro-
gramme (D.K.P.); Charles Sykes Epilepsy Research Trust (D.K.P.); 
NIHR Specialist Biomedical Research Centre for Mental Health of South 
London and Maudsley NHS Foundation Trust (D.K.P.); Isaak Schapera 
Trust for Medical Research (R.R.). The original patient collections were 
funded by the Fund for Epilepsy, the Epilepsy Research Foundation, 
Action Research, the Wellcome Trust, the MRC, and the European 
Commission. </p>

<p>DISCLOSURE </p>

<p>Laura Addis is a contractor for Eli Lilly and has received research support 
from Eli Lilly and the Waterloo Foundation. Richard E. Rosch reports no 
disclosures. Antonio Valentin has received speaker honoraria from Eisai 
Co.; has received publishing royalties for Introduction to Epilepsy, Cam-
bridge University Press, 2012; and has been a tutor for the nonprofit 
VIREPA Distance Education Program (International League Against Epi-
lepsy, ILAE). Andrew Makoff, Robert Robinson, and Kate V. Everett 
report no disclosures. Lina Nashef has served on the scientific advisory 
boards of SUDEP Action (formerly Epilepsy Bereaved UK), Epilepsy 
Research UK, and FQMS; has received speaker honoraria/travel funding 
from Eisai and Bial; has served on the editorial board of Epilepsia; has 
received publishing royalties from Oxford Specialist Handbooks in Neurol-
ogy: Epilepsy, Oxford University Press, 2009 and Neurology and Pregnancy, 
Informa 2013; has been an employee of the National Health Service 
(UK) and King's College Hospital; and has received the eTNS system 
free for use by some patients under her care from NeuroSigma. Deb K. 
Pal has served on the scientific advisory board of Amplexa Genetics, holds 
a patent for Biomarker for centrotemporal spikes, and has received 
research support from the Canadian Institutes for Health Research, the 
European Research Commission, and the Medical Research Council. Go 
to Neurology.org/ng for full disclosure forms. </p>

<p>Received August 31, 2015. Accepted in final form January 4, 2016. </p>



<p>Neurology: Genetics </p>

<p>
ª 2016 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>



<p> 
Neurology: Genetics </p>

<p>ª 2016 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>



<p>Neurology: Genetics </p>

<p>
ª 2016 American Academy of Neurology. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

</text></tei>