<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4164725" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background/Aims: Smoking is widely acknowledged as the single most import-</p>

<p>ant risk factor for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). However, the 
risk of COPD in nonsmokers exposed to secondhand smoke remains controver-
sial. In this study, we investigated the association of secondhand smoke exposure 
with COPD prevalence in nonsmokers who reported never smoking. 
Methods: This study was based on data obtained from the Korean National </p>

<p>Health and Nutrition Examination Surveys (KNHANES) conducted from 2008 to 
2010. Using nationwide stratified random sampling, 8,596 participants aged ≥ 40 
years of age with available spirometry results were recruited. After selecting par-
ticipants who never smoked, the duration of exposure to secondhand smoke was 
assessed based on the KNHANES questionnaire. 
Results: The prevalence of COPD was 6.67% in participants who never smoked. </p>

<p>We divided the participants who had never smoked into those with or without 
exposure to secondhand smoke. The group exposed to secondhand smoke was 
younger with less history of asthma and tuberculosis, higher income, and higher 
educational status. Multivariate logistic regression analysis determined that sec-
ondhand smoke did not increase the prevalence of COPD. 
Conclusions: There was no significant difference in the prevalence of COPD be-</p>

<p>tween participants who had never smoked with or without exposure to second-
hand smoke in our study. Thus, secondhand smoke may not be an important risk 
factor for the development of COPD in patients who have never smoked. </p>

<p>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is a 
lung disease characterized by irreversible airflow lim-
itation due to airway inflammation and lung paren-
chymal damage. COPD is associated with high rates of 
morbidity and mortality worldwide, resulting in serious </p>

<p>social and economic burden [1,2]. COPD is caused by 
multiple external factors including smoking, air pollu-
tion, socioeconomic status, and respiratory infections; 
and host factors including genetic factors, age, gender, 
airway hypersensitivity, and lung growth [3]. 
Smoking is the single most important risk factor for 
development of COPD; therefore, the subjects in most </p>

<p>The effects of secondhand smoke on chronic 
obstructive pulmonary disease in nonsmoking 
Korean adults </p>

<p>Woong Jun Kim 1  , June Seok Song 2 
, Dong Won Park 2 
, Hyun Jung Kwak 2 
, Ji-Yong Moon 2 
, 
Sang-Heon Kim 2  , Jang Won Sohn 2 
, Ho Joo Yoon 2 
, Dong Ho Shin 2 
, Sung Soo Park 2 
, and Tae-Hyung Kim 2 </p>



<p>The Korean Journal of Internal Medicine Vol. 29, No. 5, September 2014 </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2014.29.5.613 </p>

<p>COPD studies are current or ex-smokers. Approximate-
ly one-fourth to one-third of COPD patients have never 
smoked [4-7]. As a result, studies on nonsmoking COPD 
patients have gained attention recently [3]. 
We conducted this study to investigate the degree of 
secondhand smoke exposure in participants who have 
never smoked and the characteristics of COPD in non-
smokers to assess the possible association of second-
hand smoke with the prevalence of COPD. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Study design </p>

<p>We analyzed data obtained from the second year of the 
Korean National Health and Nutrition Examination 
Survey (KNHANES) IV (2008) to the first year of KN-
HANES V (2010). For details refer to previous studies 
regarding COPD that made use of KNHANES data [8,9]. </p>

<p>Setting </p>

<p>The KNHANES is a national cross-sectional survey and 
a population-based epidemiological survey of health 
and nutrition with a stratified multistage clustered 
probability design, conducted by the Ministry of Health 
and Welfare of Korea. KNHANES includes four compo-
nents: the Health Interview Survey, the Health Behavior 
Survey, the Health Examination Survey, and the Nutri-
tion Survey. </p>

<p>Questionnaire and procedures </p>

<p>Standardized questions elicited self-reported informa-
tion on demography, smoking status, family income, 
education status, history of asthma and tuberculosis, 
and respiratory symptoms. Family income was classi-
fied as low, moderate-low, moderate-high and high. Ed-
ucation status was classified as below elementary, mid-
dle school, high school, and college or above. A previous 
history of asthma or tuberculosis was confirmed if the 
patient responded 'yes' regarding whether a physician 
had ever diagnosed asthma or tuberculosis or if they 
currently suffered from asthma or tuberculosis. Sec-
ondhand smoke exposure was assessed by self-reported 
hours of exposure per day at the workplace and home. 
A forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1)/forced 
vital capacity (FVC) &lt; 70% without a bronchodilator re-</p>

<p>sponse test was defined as COPD in subjects ≥ 40 years 
of age. The urine cotinine level was measured by gas 
chromatography-mass spectrometry using the Perkin 
Elmer Clarus600T instrument (PerkinElmer, Turku, 
Finland). </p>

<p>Participants </p>

<p>Subjects were eligible for inclusion in the study if they 
were ≥ 40 years of age, had valid spirometry results, and 
had never smoked, defined as someone who had not 
smoked a cigarette during their lifetime. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>To adjust for unequal probabilities of selection and to 
account for nonparticipation, all estimates were calcu-
lated on the basis of the sampling weight. Comparisons 
between groups were performed using the chi-square 
test or linear regression analysis. Multivariate regres-
sion was performed for the analysis of the association 
of secondhand smoke exposure and COPD prevalence 
after adjustment for age, gender, previous diagnosis of 
asthma or tuberculosis, family income, and education 
status. All values are presented as mean ± SD. Statistical 
analyses were performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">8.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc</rs>., Cary, NC, USA). Statistical significance 
was considered at values of p &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Smoking status stratified by gender and prevalence 
of COPD in participants who had never smoked </p>

<p>The total number of eligible participants was 8,596. The 
proportion that had never smoked was 53.80% among 
Korean adults ≥ 40 years of age (n = 4,989; male 10.69%, 
female 90.50%) (Table 1). The prevalence of COPD 
among those that had never smoked was 6.67% (n = 323), 
and was higher in males (12.96%) than in females (5.77%). 
Among the subjects exposed to secondhand smoke, the 
prevalence of COPD was lower than that among those 
not exposed to secondhand smoke (4.34% vs. 7.80%), and 
this trend was similar regardless of gender (male, 6.73% 
vs. 16.71%; female, 3.94% vs. 6.63%, respectively) (Table 2). </p>



<p>Kim WJ, et al. Secondhand smoke in never smoker COPD </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2014.29.5.613 </p>

<p>Comparison of baseline characteristics among par-
ticipants who had never smoked based on second-
hand smoke exposure </p>

<p>Of the participants that had never smoked, 32.54% had 
been exposed to secondhand smoke. When compared 
to those without secondhand smoke exposure, the 
subjects with secondhand smoke exposure had a lower 
mean age (52.47 vs. 57.74, p &lt;0.01), higher proportion of 
male gender (14.46% vs. 11.62%, p = 0.03), lower previous 
history of asthma (3.55% vs. 5.11%, p = 0.03) and tuber-
culosis (4.39% vs. 6.85%, p = 0.01), greater family income 
(lowest quartile, 17.90% vs. 26.55%, p &lt; 0.01), higher 
education status (elementary school or less, 33.21% vs. 
42.25%, p &lt; 0.01), and higher urine cotinine level (38.24 
ng/mL vs. 21.60 ng/mL, p = 0.02) (Table 3). </p>

<p>Urine cotinine levels and pulmonary function ac-
cording to secondhand smoke exposure </p>

<p>In participants who had never smoked, the urine co-
tinine level increased significantly with duration of 
exposure to secondhand smoke (≤ 2 hours vs. &gt; 8 hours; 
23.71 ng/mL vs. 161.49 ng/mL; p = 0.01). However, there 
was no difference in FEV1/FVC and FEV1 according to 
secondhand smoke exposure time (Table 4). </p>

<p>Risk of COPD according to secondhand smoke ex-
posure </p>

<p>In the group exposed to secondhand smoke for &gt; 6 
hours per day, the odds ratio for COPD prevalence was 
1.75 (0.47 to 6.59, p = 0.41) after adjusting for variables 
such as age, gender, previous diagnosis of asthma and 
tuberculosis, family income and education status. 
Therefore, there was no significant association between 
secondhand smoke and COPD prevalence (Table 5). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Secondhand smoke is known to increase the incidence 
of heart disease, lung cancer, and asthma. It also causes 
respiratory symptoms such as cough and phlegm [10,11]. 
In our study, we investigated the relationship between 
secondhand smoke exposure and COPD in Koreans 
who had never smoked and the epidemiological differ-
ences between groups that were or were not exposed 
to secondhand smoke. Most participants ≥ 40 years of 
age who had never smoked were female, which reflects 
the lifestyle of the Korean population; the male lifetime 
smoking rate is ~90%. Considering that smoking is 
the single most important COPD risk factor, the low </p>

<p>Table 1. Percentage of smokers ≥ 40 years of age stratified by gender </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Variable 
Total popu lation 
Male 
Female </p>

<p>Current smoker 
2,978 (38.51) 
2,609 (74.17) 
369 (8.20) </p>

<p>Former smoker 
629 (7.68) 
578 (15.17) 
51 (1.30) </p>

<p>Never smoker 
4,989 (53.80) 
571 (10.69) 
4,418 (90.50) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%). </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Weighted frequencies (%). </p>

<p>Table 2. Prevalence of COPD among participants ≥ 40 years of age stratified by gender </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Variable 
Total population 
Male 
Female </p>

<p>Total 
323 (6.67) 
82 (12.96) 
241 (5.77) </p>

<p>SHS (+) 
75 (4.34) 
19 (6.73) 
56 (3.94) </p>

<p>SHS (-) 
248 (7.80) 
63 (16.71) 
185 (6.63) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%). 
COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; SHS, secondhand smoke. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Weighted frequencies (%). </p>



<p>The Korean Journal of Internal Medicine Vol. 29, No. 5, September 2014 </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2014.29.5.613 </p>

<p>prevalence of COPD in subjects exposed to secondhand 
smoke was unexpected. These results may be attribut-
able to the characteristics of patients not exposed to 
secondhand smoke, who were generally older had had 
a higher rate of a history of asthma and tuberculosis, 
lower income, and lower education status. Moreover, 
previous studies have reported that females are more 
susceptible to COPD; a greater number of female par-
ticipants in our study population were not exposed to 
secondhand smoke. 
Urine cotinine is a metabolite of nicotine used as an </p>

<p>indicator of secondhand smoke exposure that increases 
over time following exposure [12]. In our study, urine 
cotinine levels were correlated with secondhand smoke 
exposure, confirming the reliability of our results. 
However, there was no significant association between 
secondhand smoke exposure and spirometry results. 
Furthermore, we found no significant association be-
tween secondhand smoke and COPD prevalence by 
multivariate analysis. 
Cigarette smoke contains approximately 4,000 toxic 
substances, such as oxidative gas, heavy metals, cya-</p>

<p>Table 3. Baseline characteristics of participants who had never smoked according to secondhand smoke exposure </p>

<p>Characteristic 
SHS (+) 
SHS (-) 
p value </p>

<p>Age, yr 
52.47 ± 0.30 
57.74 ± 0.32 
&lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>40-49 
45.42 
31.70 
&lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>50-59 
33.40 
26.53 </p>

<p>60-69 
14.46 
20.39 </p>

<p>≥ 70 
6.72 
21.39 </p>

<p>Gender, male 
14.46 
11.62 
0.03 </p>

<p>Asthma 
3.55 
5.11 
0.03 </p>

<p>Tuberculosis 
4.39 
6.85 
0.01 </p>

<p>BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>24.36 ± 0.11 
24.18 ± 0.07 
0.17 </p>

<p>Income </p>

<p>Low 
17.90 
26.55 
&lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>Low-middle 
25.43 
23.37 
&lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>Middle-high 
27.36 
23.73 </p>

<p>High 
29.31 
26.35 </p>

<p>Education </p>

<p>Elementary or less 
33.21 
42.25 
&lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>Middle school 
18.11 
14.51 </p>

<p>High school 
34.06 
26.08 </p>

<p>College or more 
14.63 
17.16 </p>

<p>Symptom </p>

<p>Cough 
0.91 
1.48 
0.42 </p>

<p>Sputum 
2.10 
3.71 
0.12 </p>

<p>Cough or sputum 
2.18 
4.58 
0.04 </p>

<p>Spirometry </p>

<p>FEV1/FVC 
80.31 ± 0.19 
79.19 ± 0.15 
&lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>FEV1 
93.51 ± 0.41 
94.45 ± 0.32 
0.06 </p>

<p>Urine cotinine, ng/mL 
38.24 ± 6.28 
21.60 ± 3.55 
0.02 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± SE or percentage. 
SHS, secondhand smoke; SE, standard error; BMI, body mass index; FEV1, forced expiratory volume in 1 second; FVC, forced 
vital capacity. </p>



<p>Kim WJ, et al. Secondhand smoke in never smoker COPD </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2014.29.5.613 </p>

<p>nide, and at least 50 carcinogens [12]. These hazardous 
substances are emitted into the air in exhaled smoke 
[13]. Several previous studies have reported an associa-
tion between COPD with exposure to passive smoking 
during childhood and respiratory symptoms in adult-
hood [14]. Moreover, passive smoking was associated 
with poorer health status and a greater risk of COPD 
exacerbation [15]. A few studies have contradicted the 
correlation between secondhand smoke exposure and 
COPD prevalence. For example, analysis of approxi-
mately 6,000 Chinese subjects who had never smoked 
showed that passive smoking increased the risk of 
COPD and respiratory symptoms [16]. In contrast, a 
health survey performed in England indicated that in-
creased passive smoking exposure was independently 
associated with an increased risk of COPD in the gen-
eral population, but did not increase the risk of COPD 
in those that had never smoked [17]. 
Our study had several limitations. First, it was of a 
cross-sectional design so we are unable to demonstrate 
a causal relationship between secondhand smoke and 
COPD. However, the strength of this study was the sys-
tematic analysis of the domestic status of those partici-</p>

<p>pants who had never smoked that were exposed to sec-
ondhand smoke using a nationwide Korean database. 
Second, we investigated the presence of secondhand 
smoke exposure using questionnaires only. We account-
ed for the possibility of recall bias due to the charac-
teristics of this cross-sectional survey by assessing the 
urine cotinine level, thereby increasing the reliability 
of the results. However, it is important to note that the 
urine cotinine level reflects nicotine absorption for 2 to 
3 days only and cannot be used to assess long-term ex-
posure. Third, we were unable to obtain information on 
the duration of exposure to secondhand smoke due to 
the simplicity of the survey questions. Chronic diseases 
such as COPD have been associated with continuous 
and long-term exposure to risk factors; therefore, the 
duration and total amount of exposure are important 
variables. If subjects had been asked more specific 
questions regarding their recent exposure, the answers 
would likely focus on more recent exposures that 
would be reflected in the survey and urine cotinine lev-
el. Fourth, we identified significant differences in age, 
gender, previous diagnosis of asthma or tuberculosis, 
income, and education status based on the presence or </p>

<p>Table 5. Risk of COPD according to secondhand smoke exposure </p>

<p>SHS exposure, 
total hr/day 
COPD, % 
Univariate analysis 
Multivariate analysis </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) 
p value 
OR (95% CI) 
p value </p>

<p>0 
7.80 
1.00 
1.00 </p>

<p>0 &lt; exposure time ≤ 6 
4.19 
0.52 (0.37-0.73) 
&lt; 0.01 
0.83 (0.58-1.19) 
0.31 </p>

<p>&gt; 6 
6.18 
0.78 (0.24-2.53) 
0.68 
1.75 (0.47-6.59) 
0.41 </p>

<p>Total 
6.67 </p>

<p>COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; SHS, secondhand smoke; OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>Table 4. Urine cotinine level and lung function according to secondhand smoke exposure </p>

<p>SHS exposure, hr 
Urine cotinine, ng/mL 
FEV1/FVC, % 
FEV1, % </p>

<p>0 
23.26 
80.26 
98.54 </p>

<p>0 &lt; exposure time ≤ 2 
23.71 
80.05 
91.50 </p>

<p>2 &lt; exposure time ≤ 4 
46.68 
80.31 
93.41 </p>

<p>4 &lt; exposure time ≤ 6 
33.09 
80.57 
94.61 </p>

<p>6 &lt; exposure time ≤ 8 
189.82 
80.31 
94.66 </p>

<p>&gt; 8 
161.49 
81.06 
98.53 </p>

<p>p value 
0.01 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>SHS, secondhand smoke; FEV1, forced expiratory volume in 1 second; FVC, forced vital capacity; NS, not significant. </p>



<p>The Korean Journal of Internal Medicine Vol. 29, No. 5, September 2014 </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2014.29.5.613 </p>

<p>absence of secondhand smoke exposure in those par-
ticipants who had never smoked. We did not investigate 
the effect of each variable on the risk of COPD in those 
participants who never smoked, although these vari-
ables are known COPD risk factors in never smokers [3]. 
Further investigation of the correlation between those 
variables and the risk of COPD would yield more accu-
rate information regarding the characteristics of COPD 
in nonsmokers. 
In summary, COPD prevalence was higher in a Ko-
rean population ≥ 40 years of age without secondhand 
smoke exposure; however, this might reflect epidemio-
logical differences between the two groups rather than 
effects of secondhand smoke. A prospective large cohort 
study should be performed to confirm the impact of 
secondhand smoke on the prevalence of COPD among 
those that have never smoked. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article 
was reported. </p>





<p>Kim WJ, et al. Secondhand smoke in never smoker COPD </p>



</text></tei>