<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4717942" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Obesity has become a major health problem among children and adolescents worldwide. This study aimed to examine the 
trends of overweight and obesity among childhood in China and assess their associations with family income, dietary intake, and physical 
activity (PA) between 1997 and 2009. 
Methods: Two waves of cross-sectional data of Chinese children and adolescents aged 7-17 years from the China Health and Nutrition 
Survey were used. Weight and height were measured following standardized procedures. Dietary intake was assessed by 3 consecutive 
24-h recalls. Childhood overweight and obesity were defined using the International Obesity Task Force-recommended body mass index 
cut-offs. Multivariate linear regression analysis was used to examine the associations of family income with diet intakes and PA. Multivariate 
logistic regression analysis was conducted to assess the associations of overweight and obesity with family income, dietary intake, and PA. 
Results: The prevalence of childhood overweight and obesity increased from 12.6% in 1997 to 22.1% in 2009, particularly in the 
medium-and high-family income groups, which increased by 102.7% and 90.3%, respectively. Higher fat intake (% energy), and moderate 
and vigorous PA were significantly associated with overweight and obesity in final model (odds ratio [OR] = 1.01, 95% confidence 
interval [CI]: 1.00-1.02, P = 0.004; and OR = 0.99, 95% CI: 0.98-1.00, P = 0.036, respectively). 
Conclusions: The prevalence of overweight and obesity among Chinese children and adolescents has increased between 1997 and 2009. 
Reducing fat intake and increasing PA may help obesity prevention. </p>

<p>Key words: Adolescent; Child; Dietary Intake; Income; Obesity; Overweight; Physical Activity </p>

<p>Address for correspondence: Prof. Hui-Jun Wang, 
National Institute for Nutrition and Health, Chinese Center for Disease 
Control and Prevention, Beijing 100050, China 
E-Mail: wanghj128@gmail.com </p>

<p>Access this article online </p>

<p>Quick Response Code: 
Website: 
www.cmj.org </p>

<p>DOI: 
10.4103/0366-6999.160648 </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ July 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 14 </p>

<p>
have they been specifically focused in developing nations. 
China, where economic reforms were initiated in the late 
1970s, has become the largest developing nation and the 
second largest economy globally and is undergoing nutrition 
and lifestyle transitions characterized by ample food supply 
and higher living standards, as described elsewhere. 
[14] To our 
knowledge, there are few epidemiological studies exploring 
the status of overweight and obesity in Chinese children and 
adolescents along with their dietary intakes and PA, setting 
these data against the background of widespread nutritional 
and lifestyle transitions. To mitigate the potentially harmful 
effects and to optimize the potential benefits of this transition, 
it is important to address this issue, taking care to delineate 
any differences from western developed countries. </p>

<p>The purpose of this present study was to examine the 
prevalence of overweight and obesity among Chinese 
children and adolescents between 1997 and 2009, and the 
associations of household income with dietary intakes 
and PA behaviors. We also investigate the effects of both 
dietary intakes and PA combined with household income 
on overweight and obesity. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study design and subjects </p>

<p>The China Health and Nutrition Survey (CHNS) is a 
representative cross-sectional survey (with a nested 
longitudinal cohort) that covers nine diverse provinces and 
autonomous regions from south to north (Guangxi, Guizhou, 
Heilongjiang, Henan, Hubei, Hunan, Jiangsu, Liaoning and 
Shandong) and was performed eight rounds between 1989 
and 2009. Details of the study design have been described 
elsewhere. 
[15,16] The present study was based on two 
cross-sectional samples collected in 1997 and 2009 of the 
CHNS. Because the sedentary time of children and adolescents 
was not collected in 1989, 1991, and 1993, we chose 1997 as 
the reference. Of the total 3391 children and adolescents aged 
7-17 years who attended school, 3221 (95%) subjects (2275 
in 1997 and 946 in 2009) had complete and reasonable 
measurements of weight and height. The 155 subjects were 
excluded because of missing data, including household 
income (n = 53), anthropometric measurements (n = 25), 
or PA (n = 77). Another 15 subjects were excluded because 
of extreme body mass index (BMI) (z-scores &gt;5 or &lt;−5) or 
impossible time spent in PA (e.g., 25 h/day). It is worthy to 
address that there was much smaller sample size in 2009 
compared to that in 1997, which resulted from migration of 
new established households with newborns and/or children 
during 1997-2009 into other communities, out of targeted 
communities; lower birth rate from 1997 (16.57%) to 
2009 (11.95%); 
[17] and lost to follow-up some teenagers during 
survey period as attending boarding school. </p>

<p>Written informed consent was provided by parents or 
guardians of each participant. The institutional review boards 
of University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and National 
Institute for Nutrition and Health, Chinese Center for Disease 
Control and Prevention approved the survey. </p>

<p>Key measurements </p>

<p>Body mass index measurement 
Anthropometric measurements were performed by trained 
health workers following standardized procedures. Weight 
was measured to the nearest 0.1 kg with SECA 880 scales 
while the participants were wearing light clothing. Height 
was measured to the nearest 0.1 cm using SECA 206 
wall-mounted metal tapes for bare-footed participants. 
BMI was calculated as weight (kg) divided by the squared 
height (m 
2 ). Overweight and obesity was defined using 
age-and sex-specific BMI cut-offs recommended by the 
International Obesity Task Force (IOTF). </p>

<p>[18] </p>

<p>Family income 
Income measures were based on per capita annual income 
of household by dividing gross annual income of the 
family by household size. The per capita annual income 
of the family was inflated to that of 2009 by adjusting for 
the consumer price index and was categorized into tertiles 
(high-, middle-and low-income levels). </p>

<p>Dietary intakes 
Detailed information on dietary consumption at the 
household and individual levels were collected using a 
weighing method in combination with 3 consecutive 24-h 
recalls, including 1 weekend day and 2 weekdays. Details 
have been introduced elsewhere. 
[15,16] The energy and 
nutrient intake levels for dietary data were calculated using 
the China Food Composition Table. Nutrient variables 
including total energy per day, percentages of calories from 
total fat, total carbohydrate and total protein were calculated. 
Considering the differences in energy requirements of 
children and adolescents based on body size, we added the 
ratio of energy/subjects' height (cm) as a nutrient variable. 
Energy/height (cm) was chosen as both total energy and 
energy/height (cm) gave similar results. </p>

<p>Physical activity assessment 
Physical activity was measured using metabolic 
equivalents of task (MET)-hours per week that account 
for both the average intensity of each activity and the time 
spent. MET is defined as the ratio of a person's working 
metabolic rate to his/her resting (basal) metabolic rate, </p>

<p>[19] </p>

<p>and any given activity is classified as moderate and 
vigorous (≥3 METs) by referring to the Compendium of 
Physical Activities. </p>

<p>[20] </p>

<p>Information on PA being collected included the participation 
in in-school and outside school sports, commuting type and 
required time to school, domestic activities (e.g., buying 
food, preparing food, doing laundry, and childcare), and 
time spent in sedentary activities (e.g., reading, watching 
TV, DVDs, videos, and using computers). Details on survey 
questions, coding, and the method of MET-hours per week 
calculation have been published elsewhere. </p>

<p>[21,22] </p>

<p>Covariates 
Other factors such as surveyed year, gender, and age were 
used in the analysis. Subjects' age was divided into two 
categories (7-12 and 13-17 years). </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ July 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 14 </p>



<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data were expressed as mean ± standard deviation (SD) 
for continuous variables and as percentages for categorical 
variables. The differences between 1997 and 2009 or among 
groups in the same year were assessed using analysis of 
variance or Kruskal-Wallis rank-sum tests depending on 
assumption of parametric test for continuous variables, and 
using Chi-squared test for categorical variables. We reported 
statistically significance at P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Multivariate linear regression models were fit to examine the 
associations of income with diet intakes and PA. Interactions 
among different income levels and surveyed year were 
used to test the difference in income effects between 1997 
and 2009. Potential confounders such as gender, age, and 
surveyed year were also taken into account in the models. In 
order to interpret the coefficients of the models, we simulated 
the predicted level of each diet and PA outcome by income 
group by year. </p>

<p>Finally, we used multivariate logistic regression to examine the 
combined effects of household income, diet intakes, and PA 
on overweight and obesity. Four models were performed by 
consecutively including predictors of overweight and obesity. 
Firstly, we included household income and year (Model 1). 
Subsequently, dietary energy intake was added (Model 2). 
Next moderate and vigorous PA was also included (Model 3). 
Sedentary activity was finally included (Model 4). To interpret 
odds ratios (ORs), we simulated the predicted prevalence of 
overweight and obesity if all subjects had the diet and PA 
profiles of the low-, medium-, or high-income levels in 1997 
and 2009. Although the CHNS is longitudinal in nature, the 
present study focused on cross-sectional analysis of data 
in 1997 and 2009. All analyses were conducted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 9</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA</rs>). </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>Sample characteristics </p>

<p>There were 2275 and 946 children and adolescents in 1997 
and 2009, respectively [Table 1]. No significant difference 
was found using Chi-square analysis in the proportions 
of sex (P = 0.265) and age (P = 0.195) groups. Mean 
height (P &lt; 0.001), weight (P &lt; 0.001), BMI (P = 0.006), 
and income level (P &lt; 0.001) increased from 1997 to 2009. 
A similar increasing trend was found in the percentage of energy 
derived from fat (P &lt; 0.001) and MET-hours/week expended in 
sedentary activity (P &lt; 0.001), but there was a decline in the total 
energy intake (P &lt; 0.001), the ratio of energy/height (P &lt; 0.001), 
the percentage of energy from carbohydrate (P &lt; 0.001), 
and MET-hours/week spent in moderate and vigorous 
activity (P &lt; 0.001) from 1997 to 2009. An increase of over 
three-fourths in overweight and obesity prevalence (P &lt; 0.001) 
from 1997 (12.6%, 287) to 2009 (22.1%, 209) was observed. 
In addition, overweight and obesity prevalence in younger 
subjects (7-12 years, 197, 14.0% and 144, 23.7%) was higher 
than that in older subjects (13-17 years, 89, 10.3% and 65, 
19.2%) in 1997 (P = 0.022) and 2009 (P = 0.006), respectively 
(data not shown in Table 1). </p>

<p>Changes in the prevalence of overweight and obesity, 
diet intake, and physical activity of subjects by income 
level </p>

<p>Table 2 presents an increase in the prevalence of 
overweight and obesity (P &lt; 0.001) by income levels 
between 1997 and 2009. Particularly, the prevalence of 
overweight/obesity increased by 102.7% and 90.3% in the 
medium-and high-family income groups. As compared 
to 1997, three income groups displayed less total energy 
intake (all P &lt; 0.001) in 2009, a smaller ratio of energy/ 
height (P &lt; 0.001), less percentage of energy from 
carbohydrate (P &lt; 0.001) and fewer MET-hours/week spent 
in moderate and vigorous activity (P &lt; 0.001), along with 
a greater percentage of energy from fat (P &lt; 0.001) and 
MET-hours/week spent in sedentary activity (P &lt; 0.001). 
Medium-and high-income groups presented a greater 
percentage of energy from protein in 2009 compared to 1997. </p>

<p>Association of household income with dietary intake 
and physical activity </p>

<p>We tested the main effects of income and year, interaction 
effects between income and year, and the combined 
main effect and interaction effect of income with year 
using the multivariate linear model to assess how income 
affects dietary intake and PA. High-income group had 
a higher percentage of energy from fat (P &lt; 0.001) and 
more MET-hours/week in sedentary activity (P &lt; 0.001), 
but fewer MET-hours/week spent in moderate and 
vigorous activity (P &lt; 0.001), compared with low-income 
group [Table 3]. The high-income group consumed about 
2% (P = 0.249) and 6% (P = 0.029) more energy/height 
and about 46% (P &lt; 0.001) and 16% (P = 0.005) more 
energy from fat than the low-income group in 1997 
and 2009, respectively [Figure 1a and b]. Consistently, 
predicted value for MET-hours/week of sedentary activity in 
high-income group was also higher than low-income group 
in both time periods (P = 0.046 and 0.039, respectively), 
but the predicted value for moderate-vigorous activity in 
high-income group was lower than low-income group in 
both time periods [P &lt; 0.001 and P = 0.004, respectively, 
Figure 1c and d]. </p>

<p>Association of household income, dietary intake and 
physical activity with overweight and obesity </p>

<p>Association of household income, dietary intake and PA with 
overweight and obesity were tested by multivariate logistic 
regression models. The percentage of energy from fat was 
positively related to overweight and obesity (OR = 1.01, 95% 
confidence interval [CI]: 1.00, 1.02) in Model 2 (P = 0.006), 
Model 3 (P = 0.005), and Model 4 (P = 0.004); and 
MET-hours/week spent in moderate and vigorous PA had an 
inverse relationship with overweight and obesity (OR = 0.99, 
95% CI: 0.98, 1.00) in Model 3 (P = 0.044) and Model 4 
[P = 0.036, Table 4]. The risk for being overweight and obese 
was not significantly associated with income, energy intake, 
and MET-hours/week spent in sedentary activity. Figure 2 
shows a U-shaped distribution of predicted prevalence of 
overweight and obesity by different income levels among </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ July 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 14 </p>

<p>
children and adolescents shifted to a stair-shaped distribution 
from 1997 to 2009. In addition, the predicted prevalence 
in 2009 increased from that in 1997 for all income groups 
(all P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>dIscussIon </p>

<p>Our study presented an increment of 9.5% in prevalence of 
overweight and obesity in Chinese 7-17 year-old children 
from 1997 to 2009, rising 0.79% annually in average, 
which was similar to the increment of 9.6% in overweight 
and obesity among Chinese 7-18 year-old children during 
1995-2010, annual growth rate of 0.64%. 
[23] Although the 
previous study was more representative, 
[23] our study still 
could reflect the trends of overweight and obesity in Chinese 
children. Present study used the latest IOTF criteria </p>

<p>[18] </p>

<p>to define childhood overweight and obesity, which is an 
important aspect, and covered many Eastern developed </p>

<p>provinces, which may have higher overweight and obesity 
prevalence, as indicated by previous study. 
[23] Additionally, 
the effects of household income on dietary intakes, PA, and 
overweight and obesity prevalence were enhanced in 2009 
compared to 1997. </p>

<p>Further, there was a significant association between 
MET-hours/week spent in moderate and vigorous activity 
and a decrease in overweight and obesity prevalence, but 
the effect was small. The increase in the prevalence of 
overweight and obesity among children and adolescents 
was consistent with that in other countries, 
[24,25] and was 
accompanied by a concurrent increasing prevalence of 
overweight and obesity among Chinese adults. 
[26] An overall 
increasing trend toward obesity had been found in the study 
of childhood obesity from the US and Brazil, which was 
dramatically similar to our results. 
[24,25] In addition, our 
results showed that overweight and obesity of children and </p>

<p>Table 1: Sample characteristics of children and adolescents aged 7-17 years old in China </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Year 1997 (n = 2275) 
Year 2009 (n = 946) 
P </p>

<p>Sex (male/female, n (%)) 
1203 (52.9)/1072 (47.1) 
521 (55.1)/425 (44.9) 
0.265 
Age group (7-12 years/13-17 years, n (%)) 
1407 (61.8)/868 (38.2) 
608 (64.3)/338 (35.7) 
0.195 
Height (cm) 
141.9 ± 16.0 
145.5 ± 16.1 
&lt;0.001 
Weight (kg) 
36.0 ± 12.0 
38.5 ± 13.1 
&lt;0.001 
BMI (kg/m 
2 ) 
17.3 ± 2.8 
17.7 ± 3.3 
0.006 
Income (RMB)* 
Low 
1150.3 ± 555.6 
2261.8 ± 1421.8 
&lt;0.001 
Medium 
2820.7 ± 545.6 
6336.4 ± 1324.5 
&lt;0.001 
High 
6469.0 ± 29.01.4 
18255.5 ± 13973.6 
&lt;0.001 
Energy (kcal/day) 
2078.9 ± 693.3 
1815.1 ± 632.4 
&lt;0.001 
Fat (% energy) 
24.9 ± 12.4 
32.2 ± 12.9 
&lt;0.001 
Carbohydrate (% energy) 
63.1 ± 12.3 
53.0 ± 11.9 
&lt;0.001 
Energy/height (kcal/cm) 
14.7 ± 4.6 
12.5 ± 4.1 
&lt;0.001 
MVA (MET-hours/week) 
43.5 ± 52.2 
24.0 ± 32.6 
&lt;0.001 
SA (MET-hours/week) 
13.7 ± 12.0 
22.3 ± 13.4 
&lt;0.001 
Overweight + obesity (n (%)) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>287 (12.6) 
209 (22.1) 
&lt;0.001 
*RMB denotes Chinese currency; the per capita annual income of family was inflated to that in 2009 by adjusting for consumer price index; 
 † Overweight 
and obesity was identified based upon age-and sex-specific BMI cut-off points of the IOTF. Values were expressed as percentages (n) or mean ± SD. 
BMI: Body mass index; MET: Metabolic equivalents of task; MVA: Moderate and vigorous activity; SA: Sedentary activity; IOTF: International 
Obesity Task Force; SD: Standard deviation. </p>

<p>Table 2: Shifts over time in the prevalence (%) of overweight and obesity, diet intake, and physical activity of 
children and adolescents by income level in China: 1997 and 2009 </p>

<p>Items 
Low income level 
Medium income level 
High income level </p>

<p>1997 
2009 
P 
1997 
2009 
P 
1997 
2009 
P </p>

<p>Overweight + obesity 
(n (%)) </p>

<p>92 (12.1) 
51 (16.2) 
&lt;0.001 
84 (11.1) 
71 (22.5) 
&lt;0.001 
110 (14.5) 
87 (27.5) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>MVA (MET-hours/week) 47.7 ± 57.1 
25.0 ± 34.9 &lt;0.001 44.3 ± 54.5 
24.5 ± 30.2 &lt;0.001 38.5 ± 43.6 
22.4 ± 32.5 &lt;0.001 
SA (MET-hours/week) 
11.8 ± 11.5 
21.7 ± 12.8 &lt;0.001 14.2 ± 12.1 
21.0 ± 11.6 &lt;0.001 15.0 ± 12.1 
24.4 ± 15.5 &lt;0.001 
Energy (kcal/day) 
2018.8 ± 700.1 1734.1 ± 619.3 &lt;0.001 2073.5 ± 652.0 1787.3 ± 572.0 &lt;0.001 2145.0 ± 720.3 1922.3 ± 686.8 &lt;0.001 
Energy/height (kcal/cm) 
14.4 ± 4.7 
12.2 ± 4.2 
&lt;0.001 
14.7 ± 4.3 
12.3 ± 3.8 
&lt;0.001 
14.8 ± 4.7 
13.0 ± 4.4 
&lt;0.001 
Fat (% energy) 
20.8 ± 10.2 
31.5 ± 17.5 &lt;0.001 23.9 ± 11.8 
31.0 ± 9.9 
&lt;0.001 30.0 ± 13.1 
34.1 ± 9.5 
&lt;0.001 
Protein (% energy) 
11.7 ± 2.4 
12.0 ± 2.6 
0.069 
11.8 ± 2.2 
12.6 ± 2.9 
&lt;0.001 
12.3 ± 2.6 
12.8 ± 2.9 
0.006 
Carbohydrate (% energy) 67.5 ± 10.1 
56.5 ± 11.7 &lt;0.001 64.3 ± 12.0 
56.4 ± 12.0 &lt;0.001 57.7 ± 12.8 
53.1 ± 11.4 &lt;0.001 
Values were expressed as percentages (n) or mean ± SD. MET: Metabolic equivalents of task; MVA: Moderate and vigorous activity; SA: Sedentary 
activity; SD: Standard deviation. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ July 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 14 </p>



<p>adolescents in China increased as income has increased; 
in contrast, only children and adolescents from low-or 
high-income groups had a higher prevalence of obesity in 
other countries. </p>

<p>[24,25] </p>

<p>A striking association of household income with dietary 
intakes and PA in our study was consistent with the findings 
from other studies, which have found differences in nutrient 
intakes by income. 
[7,27] We found more energy intake, higher 
fat intake, and more MET-hours/week spent in sedentary 
activity in the higher-income group, and that high-income 
group also had a higher prevalence of overweight and 
obesity, which was similar to findings from Brazil. </p>

<p>[25] </p>

<p>Traditionally, research into weight status and its influencing 
factors has only focused on a single behavior. However, 
obesity development in childhood and adolescence is 
associated with a complex behavioral pattern of energy 
intake and energy expenditure. Evidence about the 
association of overweight and obesity with multiple variables 
such as income, diet, and PA is still scarce. This is one of 
the first studies from Asia to specifically test the effects of 
the combination of income, diet, and activity on overweight 
and obesity among Chinese children and adolescents. Our 
results were consistent with a recent study conducted in 
American children and adolescents that examined diet and </p>

<p>PA as risk factors for overweight and obesity. 
[28] However, 
some issues need to be clarified by additional studies. We 
found that only MET-hours/week spent in moderate and 
vigorous PA and energy derived from fat appeared to have 
independent associations with overweight and obesity for 
Chinese children and adolescents, which is novel and gives 
interesting implications for research and intervention. </p>

<p>Similar to the results in most previous researches, </p>

<p>[11,26,28] </p>

<p>the present study also did not find an observed effects of 
household income or total energy intakes on overweight and 
obesity. In addition, our results, including the inverse effect 
of moderate and vigorous PA, were consistent with other 
studies summarized in a recent literature review showing 
a negative relationship between moderate and vigorous 
activity and risk of obesity. </p>

<p>[8] </p>

<p>Although conclusions supporting an association between 
sedentary behavior and obesity have not been found, 
our results have indicated that MET-hours/week spent in 
sedentary activity had a marked increase. Strong national 
economic drivers increased the opportunities of Chinese 
children and adolescents for access to screen-based devices 
such as computers and video games, and in the unique 
Chinese cultural setting, most children and adolescents had 
more extracurricular academic activities such as homework </p>

<p>Table 3: Coefficients and intercepts from multivariate linear regression models used to predict dietary intakes and 
physical activity by household income levels </p>

<p>Items 
Energy/height (kcal/cm) 
Fat (% energy) 
MVA (MET-hours) 
SA (MET-hours) </p>

<p>Coefficients 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P 
Coefficients 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P 
Coefficients 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P 
Coefficients 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>Intercept 
13.48 (12.83, 14.13) &lt;0.001 22.10 (20.19, 24.01) &lt;0.001 38.36 (31.25, 45.47) &lt;0.001 17.36 (15.54, 19.18) &lt;0.001 
Income level 
Low-income (ref) 
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
Medium-income 
0.27 (−0.13, 0.68) 0.343 
2.87 (1.69, 4.05) &lt;0.001 −3.35 (−9.46, 2.75) 
0.360 
2.37 (1.25, 3.49) &lt;0.001 
High-income 
0.29 (−0.11, 0.69) 0.142 9.18 (8.01, 10.36) &lt;0.001 −8.51 (−14.61, −2.41) &lt;0.001 3.56 (2.44, 4.69) &lt;0.001 
Year 
1997 (ref) 
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
2009 
−2.20 (−2.72, −1.68) &lt;0.001 9.15 (7.63, 10.67) &lt;0.001 −22.74 (−27.87, −17.60) &lt;0.001 9.22 (7.76, 10.69) &lt;0.001 
Interaction terms 
Low-income × 
year (ref) </p>

<p>NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-</p>

<p>Medium-income × year −0.11 (−0.84, 0.62) 0.561 −1.27 (−3.42, 0.88) 0.003 
3.01 (−4.25, 10.27) 
0.370 −2.74 (−4.81, −0.67) 0.011 
High-income × year 
0.40 (−0.33, 1.13) 0.411 −4.40 (−6.54, −2.26) &lt;0.001 
6.33 (−0.93, 13.58) 
0.277 −1.84 (−3.91, 0.23) 0.699 
Main effect and 
interaction effect 
Low-income + 
low-income × year (ref) </p>

<p>NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-</p>

<p>Medium-income + 
medium-income × year </p>

<p>0.16 (−0.45, 0.77) 0.940 1.60 (−0.20, 3.40) 0.686 
−0.35 (−4.28, 3.59) 
0.098 −0.37 (−2.11, 1.37) 0.532 </p>

<p>High-income + 
high-income × year </p>

<p>0.68 (0.07, 1.29) 
0.042 
4.78 (2.99, 6.58) 
0.005 −2.18 (−6.12, −1.75) 0.006 
1.72 (0.01, 3.47) 
0.004 </p>

<p>Age 
0.09 (0.04, 0.14) 
0.005 −0.17 (−0.31, −0.03) 0.003 −1.04 (−1.51, −0.58) &lt;0.001 0.56 (0.42, 0.69) &lt;0.001 
Gender 
Boy (ref) 
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
Girl 
−1.30 (−1.57, −1.02) &lt;0.001 0.37 (−0.43, 1.18) 0.437 −7.15 (−9.86, −4.44) &lt;0.001 0.23 (−0.54, 1.00) 0.676 
Ref indicates the group as reference. MET: Metabolic equivalents of task; CI: Confidence interval; NA: Not applicable; MVA: Moderate and vigorous 
activity; SA: Sedentary activity. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ July 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 14 </p>

<p>
Table 4: The results of multivariate logistic regression models of predictors of overweight and obesity in children 
and adolescents* </p>

<p>Items 
Model 1 
Model 2 
Model 3 
Model 4 </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) 
P 
OR (95% CI) 
P 
OR (95% CI) 
P 
OR (95% CI) 
P </p>

<p>Income level 
Low-income (ref) 
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
Medium-income 
0.88 (0.65, 1.21) 0.446 0.85 (0.61, 1.18) 0.331 0.85 (0.61, 1.19) 0.341 0.84 (0.61, 1.17) 0.313 
High-income 
1.22 (0.91, 1.65) 0.179 1.12 (0.82, 1.54) 0.538 1.12 (0.82, 1.54) 0.484 1.11 (0.81, 1.53) 0.479 
Year 
1997 (ref) 
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
2009 
1.36 (0.94, 1.98) 0.100 1.25 (0.83, 1.87) 0.379 1.21 (0.81, 1.81) 0.351 1.18 (0.78, 1.77) 0.280 
Interaction terms 
Low-income × year (ref) 
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
Medium-income × year 
1.69 (1.02, 2.82) 0.043 1.85 (1.09, 3.14) 0.022 1.87 (1.10, 3.17) 0.021 1.87 (1.10, 3.18) 0.018 
High-income × year 
1.62 (0.99, 2.64) 0.055 1.74 (1.04, 2.89) 0.034 1.74 (1.04, 2.89) 0.029 1.77 (1.06, 2.95) 0.028 
Diet 
Energy/height (kcal/cm) 
NA 
-
1.01 (0.99, 1.03) 0.494 1.01 (0.99, 1.03) 0.473 1.01 (0.99, 1.03) 0.470 
Fat (% energy) 
NA 
-
1.01 (1.00, 1.02) 0.006 1.01 (1.00, 1.02) 0.005 1.01 (1.00, 1.02) 0.004 
Physical activity (MET-hours/week) 
MVA 
NA 
-
NA 
-
0.99 (0.98, 1.00) 0.044 0.99 (0.98, 1.00) 0.036 
SA 
NA 
-
NA 
-
NA 
-
1.00 (0.99, 1.01) 0.248 
*All models were adjusted for age and sex. Ref indicates the group as reference. MET: Metabolic equivalents of task; CI: Confidence interval; NA: 
Not applicable; OR: Odds ratio; MVA: Moderate and vigorous activity; SA: Sedentary activity. </p>

<p>and night classes, all of which may contribute to rising 
sedentary activity time. Adopting measures to increase PA 
for Chinese children and adolescents at school as well as 
control sedentary activity time are critical and noticeable. </p>

<p>In addition, with the development of Chinese urbanization, 
consumption of "junk food" and foods rich in energy and 
fat has rapidly increased, and snacking and away from home 
eating behaviors have changed dramatically. Therefore, </p>

<p>Figure 1: Prediction of dietary intake and physical activity by family income in 1997 and 2009. (a) Energy intake presented as energy/ 
height; (b) percentage of energy from fat; (c) metabolic equivalents of task (MET)-hours/week spent in moderate and vigorous activity; 
(d) MET-hours/week spent in sedentary activity. </p>

<p>d 
c </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ July 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 14 </p>



<p>making appropriate health-related policies and providing 
better nutritional knowledge from parents or schools would 
also play pivotal roles in interventions for overweight and 
obesity in Chinese children and adolescents. </p>

<p>This study has some limitations. First, we were unable to 
assess causality because of the cross-sectional analysis. 
Second, recall and social desirability biases existed in 
self-reported PA and dietary data, although whether 
over-estimated PA or dietary intakes due to social desirability 
bias in some developed countries 
[29] occurs in developing 
countries is not clear. Third, the collection methods of 
PA and dietary data in children and adolescents varied 
slightly by age groups, with assistance from caregivers for 
children &lt;10 years. While different data collection methods 
were used for improving accuracy of PA or dietary data, </p>

<p>[30] </p>

<p>comparison of CHNS PA and dietary data in children based 
on parent-assisted self-report and self-report has not yet 
been conducted. </p>

<p>In conclusion, to the best of our knowledge, this is the first 
study to assess the shifts over time in household income, 
dietary intake and PA, and their associations with overweight 
and obesity among Chinese children and adolescents 
using nationwide survey data. These findings suggest that 
household income, dietary intake, and PA have changed 
dramatically over time, and prevalence of overweight 
and obesity has increased. Sedentary behaviors are more 
common while moderate and vigorous PA is inadequate. 
Lower fat intake and frequent participation in moderate 
and vigorous PA may be protective against overweight and 
obesity. </p>

<p>AcknowledgMents </p>

<p>We would like to thank all collaborators from the nine provinces 
for their support in the fieldwork. </p>



<p>Figure 2: Predicted prevalence of overweight and obesity by family 
income using multivariate logistic regression models in 1997 and 
2009. Overweight and obesity was defined using age-and sex-specific 
cut-off points for body mass index recommended by the International 
Obesity Task Force. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ July 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 14 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>