<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4361860" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Research on sex differences in renal cancer-specific mortality (RCSM), which considered the sex effect to be 
constant throughout life, has yielded conflicting results. This study hypothesized the sex effect may be 
modified by age, which is a proxy for hormonal status. Data from the Surveillance, Epidemiology and End 
Results database (1988-2010) were used to identify 114,539 patients with renal cell carcinoma (RCC). The 
study cohort was divided into three age groups using cutoffs of 42 and 58 years, which represent the 
premenopausal and postmenopausal periods. The cumulative incidence function and competing risks 
analyses were used to examine the effect of covariates on RCSM and other-cause mortality (OCM). In 
premenopausal period, male sex was a significant predictor of poor RCSM for both localized (adjusted 
subdistribution hazard ratio [aSHR] 5 1.63, P 5 0.002) and advanced (aSHR 5 1.20, P 5 0.041) disease. In 
postmenopausal period, the sex disparity diminished (aSHR 5 1.05, P 5 0.16) and reversed (aSHR 5 0.95, P 
5 0.017) in localized and advanced disease, respectively. On the contrary, similar trend was not found for 
OCM across all age groups. Our results demonstrated the sex effect on RCSM was strongly modified by age. 
These findings may aid in clinical practice and need further evaluation of underlying biological mechanisms. </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>enal cancer is the 13th most common malignancy globally, and it has increased by about 2% annually 
during the last two decades 1 . In 2013, an estimated 65,150 new cases of renal cancer were diagnosed in the 
United States and 13,680 died of the disease 2 . Renal cell carcinoma (RCC), which accounts for approxi-
mately 90% of all renal malignancies, represented 5% of all cancers in men and 3% of all cancers in women in the 
United States in 2013 2,3 . Overall, the incidence of RCC is about 1.6 to 2.0 times higher in men than women, and 
men account for almost two thirds of all deaths from RCC 2-4 . 
Current evidence suggests that the protective role of sex in the incidence of RCC may extend to mortality. 
Results from a multi-institutional sample of 6234 patients with RCC found significant sex differences in out-
comes, with women having better disease-specific survival (hazard ratio [HR] 5 0.75) and overall survival (HR 5 
0.80) compared with men 5 . Rampersaud et al. 6 , who studied 5654 RCC patients treated at 10 international 
academic centers, reported that women had a 19% reduced risk of death compared with men (HR 5 0.81). 
The observed female survival advantage is also supported by biological research. Among all plausible contributing 
factors, estrogen is most commonly discussed 7-10 . A study by Yu et al. 7 found that estrogen, through estrogen 
receptor (ER) b, inhibited the proliferation, migration, and invasion of RCC cells and increased RCC apoptosis by 
affecting the expression of growth factor-related downstream genes and apoptotic genes. Nevertheless, other 
epidemiological studies have failed to support a sex effect on RCC-specific survival 4,11 . It should be noted that the 
peak incidence of RCC occurs in the sixth and seventh decades, during which sex difference in hormones 
decrease. Therefore, the age-associated changes in sex hormones may be one reason for the conflicting results 
of sex and survival outcomes. 
In the current study, we hypothesized that the effect of sex on oncologic outcomes is modified by age, which was 
used as a surrogate for hormone status. To test our hypothesis, we examined the sex effect across age categories on 
renal cancer-specific mortality (RCSM) in patients with RCC from the population-based Surveillance 
Epidemiology and End Results (SEER) database. Moreover, since other-cause mortality (OCM) accounts for </p>

<p>OPEN </p>

<p>SUBJECT AREAS: </p>

<p>UROLOGICAL CANCER </p>

<p>RENAL CANCER </p>

<p>substantial mortality outcomes in RCC, we used competing risks 
analyses to estimate RCSM, which can provide unbiased survival 
estimates. </p>

<p>Results 
Demographic and disease characteristics. Of 114,539 enrolled 
patients, 72,050 (62.90%) were men and 42,489 (37.10%) were 
women (sex ratio 5 1.70). Table 1 summarizes the demographic 
and disease characteristics stratified by the age and sex. Younger 
and older patients were similar in terms of registry area, SES, 
tumor size, and the percentage of clear cell RCC. However, young 
patients were likely to be black, have localized disease and low-grade 
disease, and to have undergone surgical interventions, compared 
with older patients. Sex comparisons revealed that more older men 
were married (74.16%) whereas more older women were unmarried 
(48.91%). Moreover, pathological subtypes of RCC showed a 
predominance of chromophobe (9.25%) and a lower probability of 
papillary (4.78%) in young women. Sex differences in tumor size and 
SEER stage, which may be influenced by the prevalence of early 
detection, were small across the different age groups (Table 1). 
At last follow-up, 20,597 (17.98%) patients died from RCC and 
21,487 (18.76%) succumbed to other causes. The median duration of 
follow-up was 68 months (95% CI, 67.45-68.55 months). Young 
patients had lower RCSM and OCM compared with their old coun-
terparts. It is worth noting that RCSM was higher than OCM in 
young patients; nevertheless, OCM was more common in old 
patients. The lowest RCSM was observed in young females (Table 1). </p>

<p>Sex difference in mortality stratified by age. Cumulative incidence 
curves were constructed for localized disease and regional/distant 
disease, according to age and sex (Figure 1). Young women had the 
lowest RCSM among the six age and sex subgroups for localized 
disease, and sex differences in RCSM narrowed remarkably in older 
patients. However, OCM, which increased with age, was lower in 
females than males across all age groups. We observed a similar 
age-dependent sex effect on mortality for regional/distant disease. 
Since most of the RCSM occurred in 2 years in advanced disease, 
the difference in survival was moderate. 
We also examined the difference in conditional mortality for 
patients who had already survived 1 year after being registered in 
the database. The mortality curves were quite similar to the uncon-
ditioned curves, which indicated that treatment-related short-term 
mortality was unlikely to explain sex-related difference in survival 
(Supplemental Figure). 
The crude SHRs of sex on cause-specific mortalities in each age 
group are shown in Supplemental Table 1. Figure 2, which depicts the 
adjusted effect of sex on cause-specific mortalities in each age group, 
indicates a decreasing SHR on RCSM with increasing age. This 
phenomenon is especially notable for localized disease. In young 
patients, being female was a significant predictor of lower RCSM 
(SHR 5 1.63 for men); however, sex disparity of RCSM diminished 
with advancing age (SHR 5 1.05 for men). Significant interactions 
between sex and age groups were found in multivariate models (P , 
0.01), on the contrary, OCM remain in favor of female across all age 
groups. For advanced disease, we observed similar changing trend of 
RCSM. However, sex disparity of OCM was only found in elderly 
patients. 
Since the observed sex difference in young patients may be related 
to the presence of unmeasured factors, sensitivity analysis was con-
ducted to estimate their potential effect. We included a dichotomized 
factor in the multivariate analysis and calculated the minimum mag-
nitude of the unmeasured factor that could alter the conclusions. We 
found that a factor with at least an SHR of 1.90 (with a female to male 
prevalence ratio of 951) was needed to diminish the prognostic dif-
ference by sex (Supplemental Table 2). The magnitude was higher 
than tumor grade in the same cohort (SHR 5 1.79). </p>

<p>Joint effect of age and sex on mortality. Table 2 shows the 5-year 
mortality rate across all age and sex groups. The 5-year RCSM for 
localized disease was lowest in young women (2.38%), and increased 
to 6.58% in older females. The RCSM was quite similar across 
different age and sex groups for regional/distant disease. 
The joint effects of age and sex on cause-specific mortalities, 
adjusted by the available confounds, are listed in Table 3. Compared 
with young women, the risk of dying from RCC was higher by at least 
63% in the other subgroups for localized disease. In advanced disease, 
young women did not demonstrate a significantly better RCSM com-
pared with older women and men. </p>

<p>Discussion 
The current study confirmed the age-dependent effect of sex on 
RCSM in localized RCC. Using prespecified age cutoffs, the female 
advantage in survival was notable in the premenopausal period and 
was diminished in the postmenopausal period. Joint analyses of age 
and sex showed that young female patients have the most favorable 
RCSM among all subgroups. Taken together, our results provide new 
insight into the contribution of sex to RCC survival. Moreover, the 
significant survival advantage of young females, even after adjusting 
for possible confounds, strongly suggests the need to further study 
the underlying biological mechanisms. 
Epidemiological studies of RCC have reported conflicting results 
about the association between sex and RCSM 4-6,11-13 . Some found 
a significant female advantage, with HRs ranging from 0.75 to 
0.81 5,6,12,13 ; however, these observations were not repeated in other 
large studies 4,11 . Research on other pathophysiological conditions 
indicates that the estrogen axis is one of the most plausible mechan-
isms of the female advantage 7,14-16 . Unfortunately, the above-
mentioned studies examined the sex effect without considering 
age-related changes in estrogen levels. A recent study by Ram-
persaud et al. 6 , which investigated the effect of age on RCC-specific 
survival between sexes, reported: (a) that age was an independent 
predictor of RCC-specific survival in women, but not in men; and (b) 
that the survival advantage for women was only present in patients 
younger than 58 years old. These results, for the first time, indi-
cated a different trajectory of age-related mortality between sexes. 
However, that study did not make in-depth comparisons between 
sexes across age. The current study, to some extent, overcomes the 
limitation regarding the sex effect on RCSM. Prespecified age cutoffs 
divided the patient population into three groups, so that most of the 
upper and lower tertiary groups were homogeneous in menopausal 
status. The sex effect was demonstrated using stringent methodology 
that included multivariate analyses and competing models. 
The mechanism of the observed age-sex interaction in localized 
RCC is still unknown. Based on our findings, we speculate that the 
survival advantage in young, premenopausal women may be con-
ferred by the estrogen axis. The protective effect of the estrogen axis 
on survival has been observed in other cancers, such as colorectal 
cancer 17,18 . Previous biological research has demonstrated that the 
estrogen-ERb axis may play an important role in inhibiting pro-
liferation and inducing apoptosis of RCC cells 7 . Therefore, a rich 
circulation of estrogen may enhance the tumor suppressor func-
tion of ERb. Moreover, the expression of ERb may be different in 
premenopausal and postmenopausal kidneys. Esqueda et al. 19 
found that the expression of ERb was significantly decreased after 
ovariectomy. Therefore, a synchronized increasing expression of 
ERb and estrogen may play a vital role in RCC among premeno-
pausal women. 
This study was unable to account for all types of confounds using a 
population-based database. Some authors have postulated a sex pre-
disposition to hereditary RCC in young patients. However, a reported 
5 to 8% incidence would hardly have resulted in the observed sex 
disparity 20 . Besides germline alterations, somatic changes were more 
frequently observed in young subjects. Although RCC associated with </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 9160 | DOI: 10.1038/srep09160 </p>

<p>
Table 1 | Demographic and disease characteristics for 114,539 RCC patients from SEER database according to age and sex </p>

<p>Variable (%)* </p>

<p>Total </p>

<p>Age 18-41 yr </p>

<p>Age 42-57 yr </p>

<p>Age 58-90 yr </p>

<p>Male </p>

<p>Female </p>

<p>Male </p>

<p>Female </p>

<p>Male </p>

<p>Female </p>

<p>No. </p>

<p>114539 (100.00) </p>

<p>3977 (3.47) </p>

<p>2843 (2.48) </p>

<p>21862 (19.09) </p>

<p>11541 (10.08) </p>

<p>46211 (40.35) </p>

<p>28105 (24.54) </p>

<p>Year of diagnosis 
1988-2004 </p>

<p>57946 (50.59) </p>

<p>2007 (50.47) </p>

<p>1458 (51.28) </p>

<p>11014 (50.38) </p>

<p>5807 (50.32) </p>

<p>23246 (50.30) </p>

<p>14414 (51.29) </p>

<p>2005-2010 </p>

<p>56593 (49.41) </p>

<p>1970 (49.53) </p>

<p>1385 (48.72) </p>

<p>10848 (49.62) </p>

<p>5734 (49.68) </p>

<p>22965 (49.70) </p>

<p>13691 (48.71) </p>

<p>Registry area 
Metropolitan </p>

<p>99696 (87.04) </p>

<p>3546 (89.16) </p>

<p>2523 (88.74) </p>

<p>19171 (87.69) </p>

<p>10061 (87.18) </p>

<p>40130 (86.84) </p>

<p>24265 (86.34) </p>

<p>Urban </p>

<p>12927 (11.29) </p>

<p>382 (9.61) </p>

<p>265 (9.32) </p>

<p>2352 (10.76) </p>

<p>1309 (11.34) </p>

<p>5330 (11.53) </p>

<p>3289 (11.70) </p>

<p>Rural </p>

<p>1722 (1.50) </p>

<p>42 (1.06) </p>

<p>48 (1.69) </p>

<p>311 (1.42) </p>

<p>145 (1.26) </p>

<p>679 (1.47) </p>

<p>497 (1.77) </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>194 (0.17) </p>

<p>7 (0.17) </p>

<p>7 (0.25) </p>

<p>28 (0.13) </p>

<p>26 (0.23) </p>

<p>72 (0.16) </p>

<p>54 (0.19) </p>

<p>Marital status 
Married </p>

<p>73256 (63.96) </p>

<p>2293 (57.66) </p>

<p>1609 (56.60) </p>

<p>14712 (67.29) </p>

<p>7056 (61.14) </p>

<p>34269 (74.16) </p>

<p>13317 (47.38) </p>

<p>Unmarried </p>

<p>37245 (32.52) </p>

<p>1534 (38.57) </p>

<p>1109 (39.01) </p>

<p>6382 (29.19) </p>

<p>4018 (34.82) </p>

<p>10455 (22.62) </p>

<p>13747 (48.91) </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>4038 (3.53) </p>

<p>150 (3.77) </p>

<p>125 (4.40) </p>

<p>768 (3.51) </p>

<p>467 (4.05) </p>

<p>1487 (3.22) </p>

<p>1041 (3.70) </p>

<p>SES 
High </p>

<p>65583 (57.26) </p>

<p>2353 (59.17) </p>

<p>1643 (57.79) </p>

<p>12619 (57.72) </p>

<p>6469 (56.05) </p>

<p>26669 (57.71) </p>

<p>15830 (56.32) </p>

<p>Low </p>

<p>48954 (42.74) </p>

<p>1624 (40.83) </p>

<p>1200 (42.21) </p>

<p>9243 (42.28) </p>

<p>5072 (43.95) </p>

<p>19540 (42.28) </p>

<p>12275 (43.68) </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>2 (,0.01) </p>

<p>0 (,0.01) </p>

<p>0 (,0.01) </p>

<p>0 (,0.01) </p>

<p>0 (,0.01) </p>

<p>2 (,0.01) </p>

<p>0 (,0.01) </p>

<p>Race 
White </p>

<p>95917 (83.74) </p>

<p>3194 (80.31) </p>

<p>2225 (78.26) </p>

<p>17893 (81.85) </p>

<p>9277 (80.38) </p>

<p>39493 (85.46) </p>

<p>23835 (84.81) </p>

<p>Blake </p>

<p>11943 (10.43) </p>

<p>498 (12.52) </p>

<p>403 (14.18) </p>

<p>2615 (11.96) </p>

<p>1477 (12.80) </p>

<p>4144 (8.97) </p>

<p>2806 (9.98) </p>

<p>Other </p>

<p>6077 (5.31) </p>

<p>244 (6.14) </p>

<p>177 (6.23) </p>

<p>1195 (5.47) </p>

<p>703 (6.09) </p>

<p>2394 (5.18) </p>

<p>1364 (4.85) </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>602 (0.53) </p>

<p>41 (1.03) </p>

<p>38 (1.34) </p>

<p>159 (0.73) </p>

<p>84 (0.73) </p>

<p>180 (0.39) </p>

<p>100 (0.36) </p>

<p>Tumor size, cm 
#7 </p>

<p>83159 (72.60) </p>

<p>2972 (74.73) </p>

<p>2152 (75.69) </p>

<p>14897 (68.14) </p>

<p>8465 (73.35) </p>

<p>33573 (72.65) </p>

<p>21100 (75.08) </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>31380 (27.40) </p>

<p>1005 (25.27) </p>

<p>691 (24.31) </p>

<p>6965 (31.86) </p>

<p>3076 (26.65) </p>

<p>12638 (27.35) </p>

<p>7005 (24.92) </p>

<p>SEER stage 
Localized </p>

<p>80107 (69.94) </p>

<p>3213 (80.79) </p>

<p>2389 (84.03) </p>

<p>15219 (69.61) </p>

<p>8964 (77.67) </p>

<p>30356 (65.69) </p>

<p>19966 (71.04) </p>

<p>Regional </p>

<p>19766 (17.26) </p>

<p>460 (11.57) </p>

<p>274 (9.64) </p>

<p>3666 (16.77) </p>

<p>1440 (12.48) </p>

<p>9306 (20.14) </p>

<p>4620 (16.44) </p>

<p>Distant </p>

<p>14666 (12.80) </p>

<p>304 (7.64) </p>

<p>180 (6.33) </p>

<p>2977 (13.62) </p>

<p>1137 (9.85) </p>

<p>6549 (14.17) </p>

<p>3519 (12.52) </p>

<p>Tumor grade 
Grade I-II </p>

<p>53684 (46.87) </p>

<p>2144 (53.91) </p>

<p>1653 (58.14) </p>

<p>10469 (47.89) </p>

<p>6121 (53.04) </p>

<p>19854 (42.96) </p>

<p>13443 (47.83) </p>

<p>Grade III-IV </p>

<p>25746 (22.48) </p>

<p>825 (20.74) </p>

<p>521 (18.33) </p>

<p>5597 (25.60) </p>

<p>2335 (20.23) </p>

<p>11116 (24.05) </p>

<p>5352 (19.04) </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>35109 (30.65) </p>

<p>1008 (25.35) </p>

<p>669 (23.53) </p>

<p>5796 (26.51) </p>

<p>3085 (26.73) </p>

<p>15241 (32.98) </p>

<p>9310 (33.13) </p>

<p>Histology 
Clear cell </p>

<p>99429 (86.81) </p>

<p>3368 (84.69) </p>

<p>2396 (84.28) </p>

<p>18772 (85.87) </p>

<p>10280 (89.07) </p>

<p>39389 (85.24) </p>

<p>25224 (89.75) </p>

<p>Papillary </p>

<p>8991 (7.85) </p>

<p>338 (8.50) </p>

<p>136 (4.78) </p>

<p>1980 (9.06) </p>

<p>561 (4.86) </p>

<p>4561 (9.87) </p>

<p>1415 (5.03) </p>

<p>Chromophobe </p>

<p>4063 (3.55) </p>

<p>197 (4.95) </p>

<p>263 (9.25) </p>

<p>762 (3.49) </p>

<p>538 (4.66) </p>

<p>1342 (2.90) </p>

<p>961 (3.42) </p>

<p>Other </p>

<p>2056 (1.80) </p>

<p>74 (1.86) </p>

<p>48 (1.69) </p>

<p>348 (1.59) </p>

<p>162 (1.40) </p>

<p>919 (1.99) </p>

<p>505 (1.80) </p>

<p>Nephrectomy </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>101421 (88.55) </p>

<p>3800 (95.55) </p>

<p>2741 (96.41) </p>

<p>20181 (92.31) </p>

<p>10853 (94.04) </p>

<p>39763 (86.05) </p>

<p>24083 (85.69) </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>13118 (11.45) </p>

<p>177 (4.45) </p>

<p>102 (3.59) </p>

<p>1681 (7.69) </p>

<p>688 (5.96) </p>

<p>6448 (13.95) </p>

<p>4022 (14.31) </p>

<p>Cause of death 
Renal cancer </p>

<p>20597 (17.98) </p>

<p>493 (12.40) </p>

<p>255 (8.97) </p>

<p>4181 (19.12) </p>

<p>1591 (13.79) </p>

<p>8934 (19.33) </p>

<p>5143 (18.30) </p>

<p>Other causes </p>

<p>21487 (18.76) </p>

<p>203 (5.10) </p>

<p>104 (3.66) </p>

<p>1981 (9.06) </p>

<p>915 (7.93) </p>

<p>11715 (25.35) </p>

<p>6569 (23.37) </p>

<p>Alive </p>

<p>72455 (63.26) </p>

<p>3281 (82.50) </p>

<p>2484 (87.37) </p>

<p>15700 (71.81) </p>

<p>9035 (78.29) </p>

<p>25562 (55.32) </p>

<p>16393 (58.33) </p>

<p>Median follow-up time, 
months (95%CI) </p>

<p>68 (67.45-68.55) </p>

<p>68 (65.24-70.76) </p>

<p>69 (65.65-72.36) </p>

<p>68 (66.83-69.17) </p>

<p>67 (65.37-68.63) </p>

<p>68 (67.08-68.92) </p>

<p>69 (67.84-70.16) </p>

<p>* 
for the first variable, % was calculated according to the row, for other variables, % was calculated according to the column. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 9160 | DOI: 10.1038/srep09160 </p>

<p>
Xp11.2 translocation/TFE3 gene fusion has been suggested to account 
for a substantial amount of RCC at ages , 35, the disease has been 
more frequently diagnosed in females, and has been shown to be 
associated with poorer outcomes 21 . Other factors that have been over-
looked include screening-related factors and treatment-related mor-
tality. The male:female ratio of prevalence of smaller tumors (#7 cm) 
in young patients was 0.99 in the present study, which was compar-
able with the male:female ratio in older patients (0.97), suggesting 
that sex differences in cancer screening were minimal. For treatment-
related related mortality, we tested the conditional mortality curves 
for patients who survived more than 1 year after inclusion in the 
registry. The consistency in the survival advantage excluded the in-
fluence of treatment-related short-term mortality on the survival 
outcome. </p>

<p>There are several limitations to this study. First, the lack of specific 
indicators of hormonal status, such as information on menopausal 
status, use of oral contraceptives, or hormone replacement therapy, 
prohibit a more direct evaluation of their effect and limit our con-
clusions. Second, comorbidities was not included in multivariate 
analyses due to comorbidities data on patients younger than 65 years 
were not available in SEER and linked database. However, our results 
showed that OCM, a probability intimately related to comorbidities, 
remain in favor of female in all age groups, which is in contrast to the 
diminished female advantage in RCSM from premenopausal to post-
menopausal period. Another supporting evidence was found in 
advanced disease: we observed similar trend of RCSM from preme-
nopausal to postmenopausal period, while OCM between sexes was 
similar in young patients and in favor of female in elderly patients </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Distribution of adjusted SHR of male over female in (A) localized and (B) regional/distant disease. Each point represents the value of </p>

<p>SHR measured with the Fine and Gray competing risks regression models. Bars indicate the 95% CI. Adjusted covariates included year of diagnosis, 
registry area, marital status, socioeconomic status, race, tumor size, tumor grade, histological type, and surgery of primary site. SHR, subdistribution 
hazard ratio; 95% CI, 95% confidence interval. </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Cumulative incidence curves according to age and sex for (A) RCSM and (B) OCM in localized disease, and (C) RCSM and (D) OCM in </p>

<p>regional/distant disease. RCSM, renal cancer-specific mortality; OCM, other-cause mortality. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 9160 | DOI: 10.1038/srep09160 </p>

<p>
(Figure 2). Therefore, it is highly likely that other age related imbal-
anced factors account for the changing trend of sex disparity in 
RCSM. Third, the current study only included patients with de novo 
advanced RCC. Whether the phenomenon will be attenuated in 
patients with recurrent systematic disease is an interesting question 
that warrants further investigation. Finally, there are some uncer-
tainties in the accuracy of 'SEER cause-specific death classification' 
although results from published studies have confirmed the concord-
ance between cause-specific death recorded in SEER database and 
the underlying cause of death 22,23 . 
Notwithstanding these limitations, our findings have important 
implications for better understanding the complex effect of sex on 
RCSM. These findings may aid in clinical practice by amending 
prognostic estimation, designing adjuvant trials, and planning fol-
low-up. On one hand, considering the joint effect of age and gender 
on RCSM, physicians could perform more thorough risk assessments 
and optimize the subsequent treatment. On the other hand, owing to 
female advantage in survival was notable in the premenopausal per-
iod and was diminished in the postmenopausal period, different fol-
low-up strategies should be conducted for different age groups under 
the circumstance of valid menopausal status is available. In other 
words, strict follow-up is required for males in younger patients while 
for both males and females in older patients. 
In conclusion, this population-based study confirmed that the sex 
effect on RCSM was strongly modified by age. Female advantage in </p>

<p>RCSM was restrict to premenopausal period for both localized and 
advanced disease. These findings may aid in clinical practice and 
need further evaluation of underlying biological mechanisms. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study population. The study population was obtained from the November 2012 
records of the SEER program of the National Cancer Institute. The SEER database is a 
large population-based dataset from North America. It covers approximately 28% of 
the US population and the characteristics of the SEER population are comparable 
with the general US population, which overcomes the selection bias that commonly 
exists in published studies. Furthermore, the large size of the database guarantees the 
statistical power to detect the sex effect. 
To retrieve subjects from the SEER database, the following criteria were entered in 
the selection statement of <rs type="software">SEER*stat software</rs>: histologically confirmed RCC, 
excluding cancers diagnosed at autopsy or by death certificate only, RCC recorded as 
a first primary malignancy, follow-up months more than 0, diagnosed time-frame 
from 1998 to 2010, and ages 18-90. Of the 125,793 listed cases, we further excluded 
patients with a tumor size equal to 0 or larger than 30 cm (n 5 9558) and SEER 
historic stage unknown (n 5 1696). The study cohort consisted of 114,539 patients 
with RCC. </p>

<p>Variables assessed. To test the study hypothesis, patients were grouped according to 
age cutoffs of 42 and 58, which have been shown to be surrogate measures of sex 
hormone status in multiple epidemiologic studies on menopause in North America. 
Research has found that more than 95% of women were hormone-intact at age 42, 
whereas 97% of women had undergone primary ovarian failure by the age of 58 6,24 . 
Family socioeconomic status (SES) was determined by four variables: median family 
income, the percentage of individuals living below the poverty line, the percentage of 
individuals unemployed, and the percentage of individuals without a bachelor's 
degree. Subsequently, we created a combined SES score by summing the standardized </p>

<p>Table 3 | Adjusted joint effect of age and sex on cause-specific mortalities </p>

<p>Adjusted SHR, 95% CI and P value for cause-specific mortality* </p>

<p>Age 18-41 yr 
Age 42-57 yr 
Age 58-90 yr </p>

<p>SHR 
95% CI 
P value SHR 
95% CI 
P value SHR 
95% CI 
P value </p>

<p>Localized disease 
(1) RCC cause 
Female 
1 # 
1.64 1.25-2.15 ,0.001 2.99 2.32-3.87 ,0.001 
Male 
1.63 1.21-2.21 0.002 2.38 1.84-3.09 ,0.001 3.14 2.44-4.06 ,0.001 
(2) Other causes 
Female 
1 
2.39 1.90-3.02 ,0.001 7.58 6.07-9.47 ,0.001 
Male 
1.52 1.16-1.98 0.002 3.11 2.48-3.90 ,0.001 9.78 7.84-12.20 ,0.001 
Regional/Distant disease 
(3) RCC cause 
Female 
1 
1.13 0.97-1.31 0.120 0.97 0.84-1.12 
0.700 
Male 
1.20 1.01-1.42 0.041 1.20 1.04-1.38 0.015 0.92 0.80-1.06 
0.260 
(4) Other causes 
Female 
1 
1.88 1.23-2.87 0.003 4.63 3.09-6.94 ,0.001 
Male 
1.05 0.63-1.74 0.850 1.77 1.18-2.67 0.006 5.49 3.67-8.22 ,0.001 </p>

<p>* adjusted variables were year of diagnosis, registry area, marital status, social economic status, race, histological type, tumor size, grade and nephrectomy. 
# 1 used as reference. </p>

<p>Table 2 | Five-year cause-specific mortalities and 95% CI estimated using cumulative incidence function according to age and sex </p>

<p>Mortality (95% CI) at 5 years* 
Age 18-41 yr 
Age 42-57 yr 
Age 58-90 yr </p>

<p>Localized disease 
(1) RCC cause 
Female 
2.38 (1.73-3.18) 
3.23 (2.82-3.67) 
6.58 (6.19-6.98) 
Male 
3.23 (2.56-4.02) 
4.74 (4.36-5.15) 
6.45(6.14-6.78) 
(2) Other causes 
Female 
2.77 (2.08-3.62) 
5.38 (4.86-5.94) 
18.20 (17.58-18.82) 
Male 
3.56 (2.87-4.36) 
7.09 (6.62-7.57) 
20.99 (20.45-21.53) 
Regional/Distant disease 
(3) RCC cause 
Female 
44.83 (39.87-49.65) 
48.82 (46.71-50.89) 
46.02 (44.86-47.17) 
Male 
48.54 (44.67-52.29) 
50.81 (49.48-52.11) 
42.56(41.73-43.39) 
(4) Other causes 
Female 
4.99 (3.14-7.45) 
8.12 (7.03-9.30) 
19.22 (18.30-20.15) 
Male 
5.03 (3.55-6.87) 
7.03 (6.38-7.72) 
21.56 (20.87-22.27) </p>

<p>* for each subset, the lowest rate was in bold and the highest rate was underlined. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 9160 | DOI: 10.1038/srep09160 </p>

<p>
scores from these four variables and classified the total scores into high and low SES 
groups, according to the median 25,26 . Tumor size was dichotomized by the cutoff of 
7 cm. Tumor extent was defined according to SEER historic stages as follows: 
localized (confined to the kidney), regional (extension into adjacent tissue or lymph 
node), or distant (metastatic). Variables with missing values were included in the 
analysis and coded as unknown. The percentage of missing values was highest for 
tumor grade (30.65%), followed by marital status (3.53%), race (0.53%), registry area 
(0.17%), and SES (,0.01%). Adjusted covariates included year of diagnosis (1988-
2004 vs. 2005-2010), registry area (metropolitan vs. other), marital status (married vs. 
other), SES (high vs. other), race (white vs. other), tumor size (#7 cm vs. .7 cm), 
stage (localized vs. regional/distant), grade (grade III-IV vs. other), histological type 
(clear cell vs. other), and nephrectomy (yes vs. no). </p>

<p>Outcome measurements. The primary outcome of the current study was cause-
specific mortality, which included RCSM and OCM. The cause-specific survival is a 
net survival measure representing survival of a specified cause of death in the absence 
of other causes of death. The 'SEER cause-specific death classification' variable is used 
to obtain cause-specific survival probability for a given cohort of cancer patients. 
Deaths attributed to the cancer of interest are treated as events and deaths from other 
causes are treated as censored observation (http://seer.cancer.gov/causespecific/). 
Survival time was defined as the time interval between the date of RCC diagnosis and 
the recorded date of death or last follow-up, whichever occurred first. Data on vital 
status, cause of death, and survival time were available until November 2012 for all 
study subjects. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses. To assess the prognostic value of age and sex, we conducted the 
analyses in the following three steps. First, we used the cumulative incidence function 
(CIF) to estimate the crude effect of age and sex on RCSM and OCM. Second, the Fine 
and Gray competing risks regression models were used to examine the effect of sex on 
cause-specific mortalities stratified by age groups after adjusting for possible 
confounds. The subdistribution hazard ratios (SHRs) and 95% confidence intervals 
(CIs) were computed, with SHR less than 1.00 indicating reduced mortality. Finally, 
we analyzed the joint effect of age and sex on RCSM. We also assessed the effect 
required of a hypothetical unmeasured binary factor to explain the observed SHR of 
sex using sensitivity analysis. All the analyses were stratified by localized disease and 
regional/distant disease, because OCM makes a substantial contribution to deaths in 
localized disease, whereas RCSM accounts for the majority of deaths in regional/ 
distant disease. 
All statistical analyses were performed with R software using the packages cmprsk, 
survival and riskRegression 27-29 . The P value was two tailed and was considered to be 
statistically significant when P , 0.05. </p>



<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was partially supported by grants from the Shanghai leaders' foundation and the 
Project of the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No. 81001131, 
81370073 and 81202004). </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>Y.Q. and Y.Z. acquired the data and drafted the manuscript, Y.Q. and H.Z. analyzed and 
interpreted the data, H.C. and J.X. prepared all figures, W.G. and C.G. edited all tables, D.Y. 
and Y.Z. designed the study. All authors reviewed and approved the manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Qu, Y. et al. Age-Dependent Association between Sex and Renal 
Cell Carcinoma Mortality: a Population-Based Analysis. Sci. Rep. 5, 9160; DOI:10.1038/ 
srep09160 (2015). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in 
this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated 
otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative 
Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder 
in order to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 9160 | DOI: 10.1038/srep09160 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>