<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4602874" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: To determine plasma concentrations of angiopoietin (Ang)-</p>

<p>1, Ang-2, Tie-2, and vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) in 
patients with sepsis-induced multiple organ dysfunction syndrome 
(MODS) and determine their association with mortality. 
The study prospectively recruited 96 consecutive patients with 
severe sepsis in a l intensive care unit of a tertiary hospital. Plasma 
Ang-1, Ang-2, Tie-2, and VEGF levels and MODS were determined in 
patients on days 1, 3, and 7 of sepsis. Univariate and Cox proportional 
hazards analysis were performed to develop a prognostic model. 
Days 1, 3, and 7 plasma Ang-1 concentrations were persistently 
decreased in MODS patients than in non-MODS patients (day1: 
4.0 AE 0.5 vs 8.0 AE 0.5 ng/mL, P &lt; 0.0001; day 3, 3.2 AE 0.6 vs 
7.3 AE 0.5 ng/mL, P &lt; 0.0001, day 7, 2.8 AE 0.6 vs 10.4 AE 0.7 ng/mL, 
P &lt; 0.0001). In patients with resolved MODS on day 7 of sepsis, 
Ang-1 levels were increased from day 1 (4.7 AE 0.6 ng/mL vs 
9.1 AE 1.4 ng/mL, n ¼ 43, P ¼ 0.004). Plasma Ang-1 levels were lower 
in nonsurvivors than in survivors on days 1 (4.0 AE 0.5 vs 7.1 AE 0.5 ng/ 
mL, P &lt; 0.0001), 3 (3.8 AE 0.6 vs 7.1 AE 0.5 ng/mL, P &lt; 0.0001), and 7 
(4.7 AE 0.7 vs 11.0 AE 0.8 ng/mL, P &lt; 0.0001) of severe sepsis. In contrast, 
plasma Ang-2 levels were higher in nonsurvivors than in survivors only 
on day 1 (15.8 AE 2.0 vs 9.5 AE 1.2 ng/mL, P ¼ 0.035). VEGF and Tie-2 
levels were not associated with MODS and mortality. Ang-1 level less 
than the median value was the only independent predictor of mortality 
(hazard ratio, 2.57; 95% CI 1.12-5.90, P ¼ 0.025). 
Persistently decreased Ang-1 levels are associated with MODS and 
subsequently, mortality in patients with sepsis. </p>

<p>(Medicine 94(20):e878) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: Ang = angiopoietin, APACHE II = acute 
physiology and chronic health evaluation II, ARDS = acute 
respiratory distress syndrome, CI = confidence interval, CRP = C-
reactive protein, DIC = disseminated intravascular coagulation, HR </p>

<p>= hazard ratios, MODS = multiple organ dysfunction syndrome, 
ROC = receiver operating characteristic, SOFA = sequential organ 
failure assessment, VEGF = vascular endothelial growth factor, 
MICU = medical intensive care unit. </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>merging evidences disclose that endothelial activation and 
injury are involved in the development of multiple organ 
dysfunction syndrome (MODS) during sepsis. In addition to its 
function as vascular barrier, endothelial cells are implicated in 
inflammatory responses and coagulation imbalance in sepsis. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>A study showed that endothelial injury is an independent 
predictor for MODS and mortality in patients with severe sepsis. 
The degree of endothelial injury correlates with the numbers of 
organ failure in those patients. 
2 Taken together, sepsis-induced 
endothelial injury plays a critical role in mediating illness 
progression and outcome. 
The angiopoietin (Ang) family contains 3 members in 
humans, including Ang-1, Ang-2, and Ang-4. 
3,4 Both Ang-1 
and Ang-2 bind to the same site of Tie2 receptor with similar 
affinity. 
5 After binding to Tie-2 receptor, Ang-1 causes activation 
of Tie-2. In contrast, Ang-2 exerts antagonistic response to Tie-
2. 
6 Ang-1 inhibits the endothelial response to inflammatory 
cytokines and exerts protective effects. In addition, Ang-1 inhi-
bits vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF)-induced blood-
vessel formation and adhesion molecule expression, and attenu-
ates increased VEGF and thrombin-induced permeability. </p>

<p>7,8 </p>

<p>However, Ang-2 triggers inflammatory responses by activating 
the endothelial cell and increasing permeability. </p>

<p>9,10 </p>

<p>Because of the important role of Angs in endothelial 
activation and vascular barrier breakdown, many studies have 
explored their role as biomarkers of sepsis. 
11-13 Evidence has 
consistently shown increased Ang-2 levels in patients with 
sepsis compared with those without. But discrepancy exists 
in the levels of Ang-1 in patients with sepsis. Previous reports 
demonstrate that circulating Ang-1 levels remain unchanged, or 
even decrease, in septic patients. 
11-13 Although decreased Ang-
1 levels have recently been reported as an independent predictor 
for mortality in pediatric patients with severe bacterial infec-
tion, 
13 few comprehensive clinical investigations have 
examined the role of circulating Ang-1 during the clinical 
course from MODS to subsequent mortality in sepsis. Whether 
longitudinally measured Ang-1 levels correlate with the resol-
ution or aggravation of MODS during sepsis remains unclear. 
The study aimed to measure plasma concentrations of 
Ang-1, Ang-2, Tie-2, and VEGF in patients with sepsis-induced 
organ failure and examine the independent association between 
these markers and mortality. These markers were also serially </p>

<p>Editor: Evert Eriksson. 
Received: February 4, 2015; revised: April 14, 2015; accepted: April 17, 
2015. 
From the Department of Thoracic Medicine, Chang Gung Memorial 
Hospital, Chang Gung University, School of Medicine, Taipei, Taiwan. 
Correspondence: Han-Pin Kuo, Department of Thoracic Medicine, Chang 
Gung Memorial Hospital, 199 Tun-Hwa N. Rd., Taipei, Taiwan 
(e-mail: q8828@ms11.hinet.net). 
This project was supported by the National Science Council of Taiwan, 
R.O.C. (NSC 97-2314-B-182A-088-MY3) and research grants from 
Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taiwan (CMRPG 3B0822). 
The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. 
Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. 
This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial License, where it is permissible to download, 
share and reproduce the work in any medium, provided it is properly cited. 
The work cannot be used commercially. 
ISSN: 0025-7974 
DOI: 10.1097/MD.0000000000000878 </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 20, May 2015 </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 1 </p>

<p>measured to determine their correlation with evolutional change 
of MODS status during the course of severe sepsis. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>This study was conducted from October 2008 to April 
2010 in a 37-bed medical intensive care unit (MICU) of Chang 
Gung Memorial Hospital, a tertiary medical center. Ninety-six 
patients (46 males and 50 females) were recruited within 
24 hours of diagnosis of severe sepsis. Sepsis was defined as 
the presence of infection and at least 2 of the following 
criteria. 
14 of the American College of Chest Physicians/Society 
of Critical Medicine Consensus Committee: temperature 
&gt;388C or &lt;368C, heart rate &gt;90 beats/minute, respiratory rate 
&gt;20 breaths/minute, PaCO 2 &lt; 32 mmHg, white blood cell 
&gt;12,000/mm 
3 or &lt;4000/mm 
3 or &gt;10% immature (band) forms. 
Patients' baseline data included age, vital signs, blood gas 
analysis, organ failure count, and hematologic and biochemical 
tests. Acute Physiology and Chronic Health Evaluation II 
(APACHE II) scores and Sequential Organ Failure Assessment 
(SOFA) score 
15 were used to assess illness severity. Underlying 
medical history was also collected, including diabetes mellitus, 
hypertension, neurologic disease, congestive heart failure, 
malignancy, and chronic airway obstruction disease. 
The hospital's Institutional Review Board approved the 
study and all patients or their legal representatives provided 
written informed consent. The patients were treated according 
to the Surviving Sepsis Guidelines. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Definitions </p>

<p>Organ failure was diagnosed according to the ACCP-SCCM 
Consensus Committee criteria. 
14 Respiratory failure was defined 
as needing mechanical ventilation. Cardiovascular failure was 
defined as systolic BP 90 mmHg or mean arterial pressur-
e 60 mmHg for 1 hour, despite fluid bolus. Renal failure was 
defined as low urine output (eg, &lt;0.5 mL/kg/hour), increased 
creatinine (!50% increase from baseline), or the need for acute 
dialysis. Hematologic failure was defined as low platelet count 
(&lt;100,000/mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) or PT/PTT &gt; upper limits of normal. Metabolic 
failure was low pH with high lactate (eg, pH &lt; 7.30 and plasma 
lactate &gt; upper limits of normal), while hepatic failure was liver 
enzyme levels &gt;2Â the upper limits of normal. CNS failure was 
defined as altered consciousness or reduced Glasgow Coma 
Score. Those with more than 2 organ dysfunctions were defined 
as MODS. 
2,14 Day 1 was the day the patients were recruited. 
The number of organ failure was determined on days 1, 3, 
and 7 of sepsis in each patient. Patients with persistently MODS 
on days 1 and 7 were defined as having persistent MODS. The no 
MODS group was defined as having organ failure counts less than 
3 on days 1 and 7. Patients with MODS on day 1 but with organ 
failure number less than 3 on day 7 were defined as resolved 
MODS. </p>

<p>Blood Sampling and Measurement </p>

<p>Blood samples were taken on days 1, 3, and 7 of sepsis for 
plasma collection. The maximum levels of laboratory data were 
used for determination of organ function and comparison between 
survivors and nonsurvivors. Soluble Ang-1, Ang-2, VEGF, and 
Tie-2 plasma concentrations (Sekisui Diagnostics, MA) on days 
1, 3, and 7 were determined by ELISA based on the manufac-
turer's instructions. Plasma levels of these mediators were com-
pared between patients with and without MODS, and between </p>

<p>survivors and nonsurvivors. For sequential MODS changes, 
patients were classified into 3 groups (ie, no MODS, resolved 
MODS, and persistent MODS) and compared. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>All data were expressed as mean AE SEM or percentage. 
Since most continuous variables were skewed, nonparametric 
approaches were used. Quantitative variables between 2 groups 
were compared using the Mann-Whitney test for continuous 
and ordinal variables, and the chi-square test for nominal 
variables. Nonparametric tests (Wilcoxon signed rank) were 
used for comparison of time points within a group. Differences 
among comparison for more than 2 groups were determined 
using the Kruskal-Wallis test. The primary outcome studied 
was in-hospital mortality. 
Univariate analyses were primarily used for the selection 
of variables, based on P value less than 0.1. Selected variables, 
including APACHE II score, SOFA score, Ang-1 levels, Ang-2 
levels, C-reactive protein (CRP), and lactate were entered into a 
Cox proportional hazards model to identify the net effects of 
each individual factor. Hazard ratios (HR) with 95% confidence 
interval (CI) were used to assess independent contributions of 
significant factors. Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) 
curves for day 1 APACHE II scores, plasma levels of Ang-1, 
Ang-2, CRP, and lactate for predicting the development of 
MODS and mortality during ICU stay were plotted, and the 
respective areas under the curves were calculated. A P &lt; 0.05 
was considered statistically significant. All analysis was done 
using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 10.0</rs> (Chicago, IL). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Baseline Characteristics </p>

<p>The 96 patients enrolled were classified as survivors and 
nonsurvivors during their hospital stay. Their baseline charac-
teristics were listed in (Table 1). Thirty-six (37.5%) died during 
their hospitalization. There were no differences between survi-
vors and nonsurvivors in age, sex, shock, bacteremia, and origin 
of sepsis. However, the nonsurvivors had higher illness severity 
than survivors, as indicated by APACHE II score (21.7 AE 1.2 vs 
17.4 AE 0.8, P ¼ 0.002). The SOFA scores of nonsurvivors dif-
fered from those of survivors on day 1 (8.2 AE 0.6 vs 5.9 AE 0.3, 
P &lt; 0.0001). They also had higher levels of lactate (24.4 AE 2.5 
vs 17.4 AE 1.7 mg/dL, P ¼ 0.025) and Ang-2 (15.8 AE 3.3 vs 
9.5 AE 1.2 ng/mL, P ¼ 0.035) but lower Ang-1 levels 
(4.0 AE 0.5 vs 7.1 AE 0.5 ng/mL, P &lt; 0.0001) than survivors. </p>

<p>Cox Proportional Hazard Analysis for Predicting 
Mortality </p>

<p>The APACHE II and SOFA scores and CRP, lactate, and 
Ang-1 levels less than the median value (&lt;5.5 ng/mL) and Ang-
2 level higher than the media value (&gt;7.0 ng/mL) were sub-
jected to Cox proportional hazard analysis (Table 2). Except for 
Ang-1 level (HR, 2.57; 95% CI 1.12-5.90, P ¼ 0.025), all other 
variables did not remain significant in the Cox proportional 
hazard analysis. Therefore, Ang-1 levels less than the median 
value were the only independent predictor for mortality in 
patients with severe sepsis. </p>

<p>Plasma Levels of Angiopoietins and Clinical 
Outcomes </p>

<p>The plasma levels of Ang-1 were lower in nonsurvivors 
than in survivors on days 1 (4.0 AE 0.5 vs 7.1 AE 0.5 ng/mL, </p>

<p>Lin et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 20, May 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.0001), 3 (3.8 AE 0.6 vs 7.1 AE 0.5 ng/mL, P &lt; 0.0001), and 7 
(4.7 AE 0.7 vs 11.0 AE 0.8 ng/mL, P &lt; 0.0001) (Figure 1A). In 
contrast, plasma Ang-2 levels were higher in nonsurvivors than 
in survivors only on day 1 (15.8 AE 2.0 vs 9.5 AE 1.2 ng/mL, 
P ¼ 0.035) but not on day 3 (12.7 AE 1.9 vs 10.8 AE 1.7 ng/mL, 
P ¼ 0.474) and day 7 (10.7 AE 1.7 vs 7.2 AE 1.0 ng/mL, P ¼ 0.060) 
(Figure 1B). 
Similarly, plasma Ang-1 levels were lower in MODS 
patients than in those without MODS on days 1 (4.0 AE 0.5 
[n ¼ 50] vs 8.0 AE 0.5 [n ¼ 46] ng/mL, P &lt; 0.0001), 3 
(3.2 AE 0.6 [n ¼ 34] vs 7.3 AE 0.5 [n ¼ 62] ng/mL, P &lt; 0.0001), 
and 7 (2.8 AE 0.6 [n ¼ 19] vs 10.4 AE 0.7 [n ¼ 72] ng/mL, 
P &lt; 0.0001) (Figure 2A). However, plasma levels of Ang-2 
were higher in MODS patients than in non-MODS patients on 
day 7 (15.4 AE 2.5 vs 7.0 AE 0.8 ng/mL, P &lt; 0.0001) but not on 
day 1 (14.5 AE 2.3 vs 8.9 AE 1.6 ng/mL, P ¼ 0.053) and day 3 
(13.0 AE 1.7 vs 10.6 AE 1.7 ng/mL, P ¼ 0.399) (Figure 2B). 
Plasma Ang-1 concentrations in septic patients stratified 
by MODS status were compared (Figure 3). Plasma Ang-1 
concentrations were lower in patients with persistent MODS 
(n ¼ 17) (3.0 AE 0.6 ng/mL on day 1 and 2.4 AE 0.5 ng/mL on day 
7) than in patients with no MODS (n ¼ 29) (day 1, 8.1 AE 0.5 ng/ 
mL, P &lt; 0.0001 and day 7, 11.0 AE 0.7 ng/mL, P &lt; 0.0001). 
However, in patients with resolved MODS (n ¼ 43), the Ang-
1 levels increased from day 1 to day 7 (4.7 AE 0.6 ng/mL vs 
9.1 AE 1.4 ng/mL, P ¼ 0.004). Plasma Ang-1 levels in patients 
with resolving MODS were similar to those of patients with no 
MODS on day 7 (P ¼ 0.188). Patients with persistent MODS </p>

<p>also had persistently low levels of Ang-1 on days 1 and 7 
(P ¼ 0.482). In patients with no MODS, plasma Ang-1 level 
mildly increased from day 1 to day 7 (P ¼ 0.016). Plasma Ang-1 
levels in patients with resolving MODS were similar to those of 
patients with persistent MODS on day 1 (P ¼ 0.07). </p>

<p>Area Under the ROC Curve for Day 1 Soluble 
Factor Levels, SOFA Score and APACHE II Scores 
in Predicting Outcomes </p>

<p>Areas under the ROC curve for plasma Ang-1, Ang-2, 
CRP, and lactate levels, and SOFA and APACHE II scores on </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Factors Associated With Mortality in Patients With Severe Sepsis </p>

<p>Survivors 
Nonsurvivors 
P Value </p>

<p>n ¼ 60 
n ¼ 36 </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics 
Age, years 
68.6 AE 1.8 
70.6 AE 2.4 
0.3528 
Male sex 
27 (45%) 
19 (55.6%) 
0.529 
APACHE II score 
17.4 AE 0.8 
21.7 AE 1.2 
0.002 
SOFA score 
5.9 AE 0.3 
8.2 AE 0.6 
&lt;0.0001 
Presence of shock on day 1 
13 (21.7%) 
10(27.8%) 
0.622 
Bacteremia 
10 (16.7%) 
6 (16.7%) 
1.000 
Primary origin of sepsis, n, % 
Pneumonia 
40 (66.7%) 
23 (63.9%) 
0.827 
Primary bloodstream infection 
8 (13.3%) 
5 (13.9%) 
1.000 
Skin and subcutaneous infection 
3 (5%) 
3 (8.3%) 
0.669 
Urosepsis 
7 (11.7%) 
4 (11.1%) 
1.000 
Other 
2 (3.3%) 
1 (2.8%) 
1.000 
Laboratory data 
PaO 2 /FiO 2 ratio 
315.9 AE 23.5 
266.5 AE 27.7 
0.186 
pH value 
7.438 AE 0.01 
7.426 AE 0.013 
0.488 
WBC, 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L 
13793 AE 1203 
11513 AE 1459 
0.238 
CRP, g/L 
140.7 AE 13.7 
185.6 AE 21 
0.065 
Lactate, mg/mL 
17.4 AE 1.7 
24.4 AE 2.5 
0.025 
Ang-1, ng/mL 
7.1 AE 0.5 
4.0 AE 0.5 
&lt;0.0001 
Ang-1 &lt; median level, ng/mL 
22 (36.7%) 
26 (72.2%) 
0.001 
Ang-2, ng/mL 
9.5 AE 1.2 
15.8 AE 3.3 
0.035 
Ang-2 &gt; median level, ng/mL 
37 (61.7%) 
11 (30.6%) 
0.006 
VEGF, pg/mL 
709.2 AE 62.5 
812.8 AE 367 
0.725 
Tie-2, ng/mL 
21.2 AE 1.4 
22 AE 2.1 
0.747 </p>

<p>Ang ¼ angiopoietin, APACHE ¼ acute physiology and chronic health evaluation, CRP ¼ C-reactive protein, FiO 2 ¼ fraction of inspired oxygen, 
MODS ¼ multiple organ dysfunction syndrome, PaO 2 ¼ partial pressure of oxygen in arterial blood, SOFA ¼ sequential organ failure assessment, 
VEGF ¼ vascular endothelial growth factor, WBC ¼ white blood cell. Values are expressed as mean AE SEM or numbers (%). </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Major Factors Associated With Mortality in Patients 
With Severe Sepsis, by Cox Proportional Hazard Analysis </p>

<p>Variables 
Odds Ratio 
95% CI 
P value </p>

<p>Ang-1 &lt; median 
2.57 
1.12-5.90 
0.025 
Ang-2 &gt; median 
1.72 
0.76-3.92 
0.189 
APACHE II score 
1.05 
0.98-1.12 
0.128 
SOFA score 
0.99 
0.85-1.15 
0.857 
Lactate 
1.01 
0.99-1.03 
0.243 
CRP 
1.00 
0.99-1.01 
0.401 </p>

<p>Ang ¼ angiopoietin, APACHE ¼ acute physiology and chronic health 
evaluation, CI ¼ confidence interval, CRP ¼ C-reactive protein, 
SOFA ¼ sequential organ failure assessment. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 20, May 2015 
Ang-1 Correlates With MODS and Mortality in Sepsis </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 3 </p>

<p>day 1 were compared for predicting clinical outcomes (Table 3). 
Values for areas under the ROC curves showed that day 1 
plasma Ang-1 levels had good discriminative power in predict-
ing MODS (0.743) and mortality (0.898). In addition, APACHE 
II score also had good discriminative power for MODS (0.674) 
and mortality (0.740). The areas under the ROC curve for day 1 
plasma Ang-2 (0.717), CRP (0.617), and lactate (0.716) levels 
and SOFA scores (0.883) were adequate only in predicting 
mortality but not MODS. </p>

<p>Plasma Ang-1 and Organ Dysfunction and Illness 
Severity </p>

<p>To further understand the relationship between Ang-1 and 
organ dysfunction, Ang-1 levels were compared to several 
variables of illness severity and laboratory findings associated 
with organ dysfunction (Table 4). Ang-1 negatively correlated 
with APACHE II (r ¼ À0.255, P ¼ 0.012) and SOFA scores 
(r ¼ À0.565, P &lt; 0.0001), number of organs affected by failure 
(r ¼ À0.580, P &lt; 0.0001), and serum CRP (r ¼ À0.241, 
P ¼ 0.018) and lactate (r ¼ À0.206, P ¼ 0.044) levels. In con-
trast, the plasma Ang-1 levels positively correlated with platelet 
count (r ¼ 0.780, P &lt; 0.0001) such that the platelet count of 
patients with plasma Ang-1 higher than the median level 
(n ¼ 48) (259.6 AE 16.5 1000/mm 
3 ) was higher than those with 
Ang-1 level lower than the median value (n ¼ 48) (106.4 AE 11.4 
1000/mm 
3 , P &lt; 0.0001) (Figure 4). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study reveals that plasma Ang-1 levels changes and 
are decreased with the evolution of MODS in patients with 
severe sepsis. Concentrations of Ang-1 increase in patients with 
resolved MODS but remain low in patients with persistent 
MODS. Moreover, Ang-1 levels on day 1 of sepsis </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Relationship between serial angiopoietin (Ang) plasma 
levels and mortality. (A) Serial mean Ang-1 plasma levels were 
significantly lower in nonsurvivors (filled circle) than in survivors 
(open circle) of severe sepsis on days 1, 3, and 7 (P &lt; 0.0001). (B) 
Plasma levels of Ang-2 were higher in nonsurvivors than in 
survivors only on day 1 (P ¼ 0.035) but not on days 3 and 7 of 
severe sepsis. Data were expressed as mean AE SEM. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Relationship between serial angiopoietin (Ang) plasma 
levels and multiple organ dysfunction syndrome (MODS). (A) 
Serial mean Ang-1 plasma levels were significantly lower in 
patients with MODS (filled circle) than those without (open circle) 
on days 1, 3, and 7 (P &lt; 0.0001) of severe sepsis. (B) Plasma levels 
of Ang-2 were higher in patients with MODS than those without 
only on day 7 (P ¼ 0.035) but not on days 1 and 3 of severe sepsis. 
Data were expressed as mean AE SEM. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Concentrations of angiopoietin-1 (Ang-1) in patients 
with no, resolved, or persistent multiple organ dysfunction syn-
drome (MODS) from day 1 to day 7. Open bars, concentrations of 
Ang-1 on day 1; solid bars, concentrations of Ang-1 on day 7; </p>

<p>ÃP &lt; 0.05 compared to day 1 no MODS group; </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 com-
pared to day 7 no MODS group; </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 compared to day 1 
levels in the same group. Data were expressed as mean AE SEM. </p>

<p>Lin et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 20, May 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>independently predict mortality during hospital stay. Analysis 
of area under the ROC curve confirms that day 1 plasma Ang-1 
levels have good discriminative power for predicting MODS 
and mortality, and decreased Ang-1 levels are associated with 
decreased platelet count in patients with severe sepsis. 
In the current study, the APACHE II and SOFA scores, and 
CRP, lactate, Ang-1, and Ang-2 levels are different between 
survivors and nonsurvivors, even though Ang-1 level is the only 
independent predictor for mortality after Cox proportional 
analysis. The functions of Ang-1 are to maintain vessel integ-
rity, inhibit vascular leakage, suppress inflammatory gene 
expression, and prevent recruitment and transmigration of 
leukocytes. 
17 The inadequate amount of Ang-1 in septic patients 
contributes to uncontrolled inflammation, injury of endothelial 
cells, and increased vascular permeability. 
17 In fact, endothelial 
injury 
2 and increased vascular permeability 
18,19 have been 
documented as possible mechanisms underlying sepsis-induced 
organ failure and mortality. The failure to maintain quiescence 
status of endothelial cells due to inadequate Ang-1 during sepsis 
may play an important role in the development of organ failure 
and followed by mortality. Consistent with previous studies, 
this study demonstrates that day 1 plasma Ang-1 and Ang-2 
levels are significantly different between nonsurvivors and </p>

<p>survivors among patients with severe sepsis. Only Ang-1 level 
remains significant after multivariate analysis. 
11,13 Nonethe-
less, other studies have not consistently shown a correlation 
between Ang-1 levels and mortality. A previous study showed 
that plasma Ang-1 levels were similar between surgical patients 
with acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) and those 
without. 
20 Similarly, another study also failed to demonstrate a 
difference in plasma Ang-1 levels between survivors and non-
survivors among mechanically ventilated patients with septic 
shock. 
11 Discrepancies in the observed association between low 
Ang-1 levels and MODS and mortality in severe sepsis in the 
present study and in previous ones may relate to the difference 
in study populations and illness severity. In contrast to previous 
studies recruiting surgical patients complicated with ARDS or 
mechanically ventilated patients with septic shock, the present 
study recruited patients with sepsis complicated by organ 
dysfunction in an MICU. Less than 30% of the patients had 
septic shock in this study. 
This study also demonstrates that persistently depressed 
plasma Ang-1 level is associated with MODS and subsequent 
death in patients with severe sepsis. The present study reveals 
that Ang-1 levels are repressed in patients with MODS and 
increase with MODS resolution. The values for areas under the </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Comparison of Areas Under the Receiver Operating Characteristic (ROC) Curves for Variables on Day 1 of Severe Sepsis 
(n ¼ 96) </p>

<p>MODS 
Mortality </p>

<p>Area (95% CI) 
P value 
Area (95% CI) 
P value </p>

<p>Ang-1 
0.812 (0.726-0.898) 
&lt;0.001 
0.743 (0.726-0.847) 
0.031 
Ang-2 
0.717 (0.610-0.824) 
&lt;0.001 
0.632 (0.515-0.750) 
0.060 
APACHE II 
score </p>

<p>0.740 (0.642-0.838) 
&lt;0.001 
0.674 (0.563-0.784) 
0.005 </p>

<p>SOFA score 
0.883 (0.816-0.951) 
&lt;0.001 
0.716 (0.609-0.823) 
&lt;0.001 
Lactate 
0.716 (0.612-0.820) 
&lt;0.001 
0.691 (0.581-0.800) 
0.056 
CRP 
0.617 (0.504-0.730) 
0.049 
0.605 (0.485-0.725) 
0.061 </p>

<p>Ang ¼ angiopoietin, APACHE ¼ acute physiology and chronic health evaluation, CI ¼ confidence interval, CRP ¼ C-reactive protein, MOD-
S ¼ multiple organ dysfunction syndrome, SOFA ¼ sequential organ failure assessment. </p>

<p>TABLE 4. Bivariate Correlation Between Angiopooietin-1 and 
Clinical and Biologic Variables in Patients With Sepsis </p>

<p>Variables 
Correlation (r) </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>APACHE II 
À0.255 
0.012 
SOFA score 
À0.565 
&lt;0.0001 
Number of organ failure 
À0.580 
&lt;0.0001 
Platelet number 
0.780 
&lt;0.0001 
pH value 
À0.165 
0.107 
PaO 2 /FiO 2 
0.046 
0.347 
Leukocyte count 
0.166 
0.107 
Lactate 
À0.206 
0.044 
CRP 
À0.241 
0.018 </p>

<p>APACHE ¼ acute physiology and chronic health evaluation, 
CRP ¼ C-reactive protein, FiO 2 ¼ fraction of inspired oxygen, 
PaO 2 ¼ partial pressure of oxygen in arterial blood, SOFA ¼ sequential 
sequential organ failure assessment. 
Ã r, Spearman correlation. </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. The platelet number in patients with plasma angio-
poietin-1 (Ang-1) concentrations lower and higher than the 
median value. Open bars, patients with plasma Ang-1 concen-
trations lower than the median value; solid bars, patients with 
plasma Ang-1 concentrations higher than the median value; </p>

<p>ÃP &lt; 0.05 compared to patients with plasma Ang-1 concen-</p>

<p>trations lower than the median value. Data were expressed as 
mean AE SEM. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 20, May 2015 
Ang-1 Correlates With MODS and Mortality in Sepsis </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 5 </p>

<p>ROC curve also show that plasma Ang-1 level on day 1 of sepsis 
has good discriminative power for predicting both MODS and 
mortality outcomes. These findings suggest that plasma Ang-1 
level may serve as an early predictor of survival in septic 
patients. By serial measurement of Ang-1 levels, the persistent 
depressed Ang-1 levels may be used to identify the patients with 
persistent MODS and are vulnerable to mortality. In contrast, 
increased plasma Ang-1 on day 7 may indicate patients with 
resolved MODS. Our study results, if further confirmed by 
large-scale prospective studies, provided a useful marker to 
stratify the patients by measuring plasma Ang-1 levels. There-
fore, serial measuring plasma Ang-1 in patients with severe 
sepsis should prompt efforts to identify and treat the modifiable 
factors associated with mortality. In patients with persistently 
decreased Ang-1 levels, some interventions may be instituted to 
improve survival. According to the Surviving Sepsis Guide-
lines, 
16 those interventions include: further studies performed 
promptly for confirming potential source of infection, reassess-
ment of antibiotic therapy with microbiology and clinical data, a 
low tidal volume and limitation of inspiratory plateau pressure 
strategy for acute lung injury (ALI)/ARDS, and maintain tissue 
perfusion by targeting a hemoglobin of 7 to 9 g/dL. However, 
further studies are warranted to confirm the application of 
plasma Ang-1 monitoring on the management of patients with 
severe sepsis. 
Plasma Ang-1 levels negatively correlated well with organ 
failure status indicated by SOFA score and organ failure counts 
(Table 4). These findings further support the theory that 
inadequate amount of Ang-1 has a pathogenic role in sepsis 
and contributes to organ dysfunction, likely through endothelial 
activation and subsequent vascular leak, which could result in 
circulatory, hepatic, and renal compromise. These results are in 
agreement with previous clinical study reporting that plasma 
levels of Ang-1 are associated with organ failure in sepsis. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Indeed, an animal study had disclosed that administration of 
Ang-1 significantly protects against sepsis-associated organ 
dysfunctions and improves survival time, most likely by pre-
serving endothelial barrier function. 
22 Recently, platelets have 
been identified as carriers of angiogenic factors since a high 
amount of Ang-1 is found in platelets. 
23,24 Results here demon-
strate a positive correlation between Ang-1 level and platelet 
count. Moreover, the platelet counts of patients with plasma 
Ang-1 &gt;median level is higher than those with Ang-1 level 
&lt;median value. These findings suggest that sepsis-induced 
thrombocytopenia may contribute to the depressed levels of 
Ang-1 in patients with severe sepsis. Thrombocytopenia is 
typically a result of sepsis and mainly caused by sepsis-induced 
disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC). 
2 The presence of 
DIC is closely linked to sepsis-induced MODS and higher 
mortality rates. 
25,26 The thrombocytopenia-associated depres-
sed Ang-1 levels may play a certain role in the progression from 
sepsis-induced DIC to MODS and subsequent death. 
Our study has limitations. First, we stratified the survivors 
versus nonsurvivors according to the in-hospital mortality. It is 
possible that patients who initially recovered from the septic 
insult may have died from another complication of critical 
illness. This would have an effect to decrease the power of 
Ang-1 to predict mortality in those patients with cause of death 
other than sepsis. However, our results that persistently 
decreased Ang-1 correlated with MODS course and mortality 
in patients with severe sepsis reinforces the use of Ang-1 as a 
predictive biomarker. Second, our study was performed in a 
single center. A larger study at multiple sites should be per-
formed to confirm these findings. </p>

<p>In conclusion, plasma Ang-1 levels are repressed in sepsis-
induced MODS and mortality. Plasma concentrations of this 
marker increase concomitantly with the resolution of MODS 
and independently predict mortality in patients with severe 
sepsis. These may suggest that the inadequate amount of 
Ang-1 plays a critical role in progression from MODS to 
mortality. Thus, plasma Ang-1 levels may be used for monitor-
ing MODS status in patients with severe sepsis, particularly day 
1 plasma Ang-1 levels, which may be used as an early predictor 
of mortality. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT 
The authors thank National Science Council of Taiwan and 
research grants from Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Taiwan 
for funding. </p>



<p>Lin et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 20, May 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>



<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 20, May 2015 
Ang-1 Correlates With MODS and Mortality in Sepsis </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 7 </p>

</text></tei>