<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4750770" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background and purpose -Patient satisfaction is important 
in fast-track total hip and knee replacement (THR, TKR). We 
assessed: (1) how satisfied patients were with the treatment; (2) 
factors related to overall satisfaction; and (3) whether there was a 
difference between THR and TKR regarding length of stay (LOS) 
and patient satisfaction. 
Patients and methods -In this follow-up study, a consecu-
tive series of 445 patients undergoing THR and TKR completed 
a questionnaire 2 weeks after discharge. LOS and short-term 
patient satisfaction with the fast-track management were mea-
sured. Patient satisfaction was measured using a numerical rating 
scale (NRS; 0-10). 
Results -For THR, the median satisfaction score was 9-10 
and for TKR it was 8.5-10 in all parameters. Older THR patients 
had higher overall satisfaction. No association was found between 
overall satisfaction following THR or TKR and sex comorbidity, 
or LOS. THR patients had shorter mean LOS than TKR patients, 
even though the median LOS was 2 days for both groups. THR 
patients were more satisfied than TKR patients in the first weeks 
after discharge. 
Interpretation -Patient satisfaction is high following fast-
track THR and TKR, with scores ranging from 8.5 to 10 on the 
NRS. A qualitative investigation of the first weeks after discharge 
is required to learn more about how to improve the experience of 
recovery. </p>

<p> </p>

<p>Patient satisfaction and subjective outcome are some of the 
most important measures of success for today's patient-cen-
tered models of care. Objective outcomes such as radiographs 
may be important, but these might not really matter if the 
patient's perception of the outcome is negative. In fast-track 
surgery (Kehlet and Wilmore 2008, Husted et al. 2010b, 2012,   Kehlet 2013), with the increased focus on reduced length of 
stay (LOS) it is even more important to look at the results of 
treatment and care from the patient's point of view. Approxi-
mately 18,000 patients in Denmark underwent THR and TKR 
in 2012 (Danish Hip Arthroplasty Register 2013, Danish Knee 
Arthroplasty Register 2013), making these amongst the more 
common surgical procedures. Since the year 2000, fast-track 
surgery has been implemented in all Danish departments per-
forming THR and TKR and it has reduced LOS from 10-11 
days in 2000 to 4 days in 2009 (Husted et al. 2012). 
Little is known about short-term patient satisfaction in fast-
track primary unilateral THR and TKR surgery. Only 8 studies 
met the inclusion criteria for a review on patient-reported out-
comes and experiences in enhanced recovery after orthopedic 
surgery (Jones et al. 2014). Only 2 of these 8 studies referred to 
short-term patient satisfaction in fast-track primary unilateral 
THR and TKR, but neither had patients staying 3 days or less 
postoperatively (Husted et al. 2008, 2010a). To our knowledge, 
no publications to date have reported satisfaction in fast-track 
patients staying in hospital for 3 days or less. Our aim was to: 
(1) investigate how satisfied patients are with the process of 
treatment and care; (2) identify factors related to overall satis-
faction in fast-track primary unilateral THR and TKR; and (3) 
investigate whether there might be a difference between THR 
and TKR regarding LOS and patient satisfaction. </p>

<p>Patients and methods </p>

<p>This single-center questionnaire follow-up study was carried 
out in a Danish regional hospital between August 2012 and 
June 2013. A consecutive series of 250 THR patients and 250 
TKR patients was included in the study. The inclusion criteria 
dictated that patients should have undergone elective primary </p>

<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2015; 86 (6): 702-707 </p>



<p>THR or TKR and should be 18 years of age or older. Patients 
were not included if they could not read or write in Danish, if 
they were cognitively impaired, or if they had received simul-
taneous bilateral surgery. Patients undergoing THR or TKR in 
the department were all allocated to the same ward and treated 
according to the same fast-track program (Specht et al. 2015). </p>

<p>Questionnaire procedure 
10 days after discharge, a paper questionnaire along with an 
envelope with prepaid postage was sent to potential partici-
pants. Before discharge, the first author or a project assistant 
informed patients verbally about the study and the question-
naire. The patients were asked to return the questionnaire to 
the hospital within 3 days. Those who did not return the ques-
tionnaire received a reminder after 3-4 weeks. </p>

<p>Study questionnaire 
The questionnaire (Table 1) was developed and pilot-tested by 
the Danish Health and Medicine Authority (Danish Health and 
Medicine Authority 2006, Husted et al. 2010a). Satisfaction 
outcomes were measured on a numerical rating scale (NRS) 
from 0 (not satisfied at all) to10 (best possible satisfaction). 
Responses to 3 questions (questions 9, 12, and 14 in Table 
1) concerning satisfaction with information given prior to 
admission, during the hospital stay, and immediately before </p>

<p>discharge (each on a scale of 0-10) were summed up, result-
ing in a satisfaction NRS total score from 0 to 30. The 3 items 
were merged into one item, and are reported in this paper as 
"information given". 
Possible associations of overall satisfaction with age group 
(&lt; 50, 50-59, 60-69, 70-79, and &gt; 79 years), gender, sur-
geons, LOS, measured satisfaction parameters, and comorbid-
ity were assessed. </p>

<p>Statistics and analyses 
Patient characteristics are reported as frequencies and percent-
ages. 
Bivariate analyses: Kruskal-Wallis equality-of-populations 
rank test was used to test for differences in overall satisfaction 
between surgeons and satisfaction with LOS. Non-parametric 
tests for trend, as described by Cuzick (1985), were used to 
explore the trend of overall satisfaction measured on the NRS 
for age group, LOS, and satisfaction with: information given, 
pain treatment, rehabilitation during hospitalization, discharge 
procedure, and the first weeks at home. 2-sample Wilcoxon 
rank-sum (Mann-Whitney) tests were used to explore dif-
ferences between genders and types of operation (THR and 
TKR). 
Multiple regression: Due to the possible clustering on 
operating surgeon, we used mixed linear regression models 
to estimate the intraclass correlation of the clustering on oper-
ating surgeon. We found that there was no statistically sig-
nificant intraclass correlation. Thus, linear regression with 
robust standard errors using the <rs type="software">STATA</rs> command "cluster 
(cluster variable)"was used-which relaxes the independence 
assumption and requires only that the observations should be 
independent across the clusters (STATA 2013). Overall sat-
isfaction was treated as the outcome and comorbidities were 
treated as the independent variables. LOS, age group, and 
gender were coded as dummy variables (Table 2), and were 
tested for interactions between LOS and comorbidities. Statis-
tically significant interactions were included in the final analy-
sis. Of the 9 surgeons who performed the operations, each per-</p>

<p>Table 1. Questions used in the questionnaire </p>

<p>1. Sex: Female / Male 
2. Age: Years 
3. What type of surgery did you have? (last surgery): Total knee 
replacement / Total hip replacement 
4. How many days did you stay in hospital after your surgery?: 
Days 
5. Do you have any of the following conditions? (please mark the 
conditions you have): Diabetes, Cardiovascular disease, Lung 
disease, Rheumatoid arthritis 
6. Did you receive a pre-admission leaflet?: Yes / No 
7. Did you receive any home care before surgery?: Yes / No 
8. If yes, how often did you receive home care before admission?: 
Several times a day / Once a day / Several times a week / Once 
a week 
9. How satisfied were you with the information you received before 
surgery a ?: 
10. How satisfied were you with the rehabilitation you received from 
the physiotherapists and the nursing staff during admission a ?: 
11. How satisfied were you with the pain treatment you received 
during admission a ?: 
12. How satisfied were you with the information you received during 
your admission a ?: 
13. Were you satisfied with the length of your stay in hospital?: Yes 
/ No, I would have preferred a longer stay / No, I would have 
preferred a shorter stay / Don't know 
14. How well-informed did you feel about the time after discharge a ?: 
15. How satisfied were you with your discharge procedure a ?: 
16. How satisfied were you throughout the first few weeks after 
discharge a ?: 0-10 
17. How was your overall satisfaction with the entire process a ?: </p>

<p>a (on a scale from 0 to 10, where 0 is not satisfied at all and 10 is 
best possible satisfaction) </p>

<p>Table 2. Characteristics of primary THR and TKR patients in fast-
track surgery. Values are number (%) unless otherwise stated </p>

<p>THR 
TKR 
n = 215 
n = 230 </p>

<p>Age, years; mean (range) 
69 (34-91) 
68 (42-88) 
Women 
116 (54) 
144 (63) 
Comorbidity 
diabetes 
17 (8) 
32 (14) 
lung disease 
15 (7) 
9 (4) 
heart and vascular disease 
18 (8) 
19 (8) 
rheumatoid arthritis 
17 (8) 
21 (9) 
one or more comorbidities 
58 (27) 
73 (32) 
Pre-admission leaflet received 
204 (95) 
227 (99) 
Home care received before surgery 
(from 1 visit per week to daily visit) 
10 (5) 
13 (6) </p>



<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2015; 86 (6): 702-707 </p>

<p>formed a mean of 48 (8-79) operations. It has been shown that 
a random variation exists between surgeons (Randsborg et al.  2010). We therefore checked to determine whether the operat-
ing surgeon should be included as a random variable, taking 
into account the random variation across surgeons using linear 
mixed-effect model analysis. 
The statistical assumptions for a linear mixed-effect model 
analysis apply to both the between-subjects and within-sub-
jects effects. The between-subjects assumptions are the same 
as those in a standard regression analysis: the independence 
of scores, normality of the residuals, and equal variances 
(known as homogeneity of variance). As this was not the case, 
we applied cluster robust standard errors using the Hubert-
White sandwich estimator. This relaxes the assumption of 
independence, thus producing "correct" standard errors (in 
the measurement sense) even if the observations are corre-
lated. Even so, caution is needed in interpreting the results. In 
addition, the mixed model also assumes a linear relationship 
between the dependent and independent variables, equality 
of variances of the difference scores for all pairs of scores at 
all levels of the within-subjects factor, and equal covariances 
for the between-subjects factor. This assumption is known as 
the sphericity assumption. Sphericity is especially important 
for mixed model analysis. Bartlett's test for sphericity was 
performed to test for this, and it showed no statistically sig-
nificant departure from the sphericity assumption. Thus, we 
decided to assess the intraclass correlation of the model using 
a linear mixed model with robust standard errors-as the 
assumptions for this model appeared to be fulfilled. If a statis-
tically significant intraclass correlation was evident, a mixed 
linear regression model was used; if not, then "normal" OLS 
linear regression with robust standard errors was used. As no 
significant intraclass correlation was found, a "normal" OLS 
linear regression with robust standard errors was performed 
and q-q normal plots were used to check for normality of the 
residuals of the model. <rs id="software-2" type="software">STATA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">13</rs> and <rs id="software-3" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">17.1</rs> were used 
for the analyses. </p>

<p>Ethics 
The Danish Data Protection Agency approved the study (entry 
no. 2012-41-0326). According to Danish law, the Regional 
Ethical Committee found that formal approval was not 
required. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Response rate 
During the study period, 256 THR patients and 262 TKR 
patients underwent surgery and were eligible for the study. Of 
the 6 THR patients and 12 TKR patients excluded, 3 and 6, 
respectively, could not read or write in Danish, 2 and 6 had 
undergone simultaneous bilateral surgery, and 1 THR patient 
had cognitive impairment. Responses were received from 445 </p>

<p>patients, 86% of the THR patients (177 early responses and 38 
late) and 92% of the TKR patients (195 early responses and 
35 late). </p>

<p>Patients 
Those patients who underwent THR and TKR had a similar 
age distribution, but the TKR patients had a higher proportion 
of women and multiple comorbidities (Table 2). </p>

<p>Responders vs. non-responders 
In both THR and TKR patients, the responders and non-
responders had similar age distribution and median LOS. 
There was a preponderance of women in the TKR non-
responders only. </p>

<p>Length of stay 
The median LOS for both THR patients and TKR patients was 
2 days with an IQR of 2 and 3, respectively (range 1-12 and 
1-15, respectively). THR patients had a statistically signifi-
cantly shorter LOS (p = 0.02). </p>

<p>Overall satisfaction and satisfaction with length of stay 
The median overall satisfaction NRS was 10 (95% CI: 9-10) 
for THR and 9 (95% CI: 9-10) for TKR (IQR 9-10, range 
1-10 for THR; and IQR 8-10, range 2-10 for TKR; p = 0.2). 
89% of THR patients and 91% of TKR patients answered 
"Yes" to the question: "Were you satisfied with the length of 
stay in hospital?", and 10% and 8% (respectively) answered 
"No, I wanted to stay longer in hospital". 1% of the THR 
patients had wanted a shorter stay whereas none of the TKR 
patients had wanted a shorter stay and 1% were undecided. </p>

<p>Satisfaction with information given 
The median satisfaction NRS score (on a scale from 0 to 30) 
for information given for THR and TKR was 28 for both (IQR 
26-30; range 13-30 and 11-30, respectively; p = 0.8). </p>

<p>Satisfaction with pain treatment 
The median NRS score for satisfaction with pain treatment 
was 9 for both THR and TKR (IQR 8-10; range 0-10 and 
2-10, respectively; p = 0.3). </p>

<p>Satisfaction with rehabilitation during hospitalization 
The median NRS score for satisfaction with rehabilitation 
during hospitalization was 9 for both THR and TKR (IQR 
8-10; range 0-10 and 3-10, respectively; p = 0.5). </p>

<p>Satisfaction with discharge procedure 
The median NRS score for satisfaction with the discharge pro-
cedure was 9.5 for THR and 10 for TKR (IQR 8-10; range 
4-10 and 0-10 respectively; p = 0.9). </p>

<p>Satisfaction with the first weeks at home 
The median satisfaction NRS score for the first weeks at home </p>

<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2015; 86 (6): 702-707 </p>



<p>after discharge was 9 for THR and 8.5 for TKR (IQR 8-10, 
range 1-10 for THR; and IQR 7-10, range 0-10 for TKR; p 
= 0.002). </p>

<p>Multiple regression: An association between age groups 
and overall satisfaction was found in THR patients but not in 
TKR patients (p = 0.01 and p = 0.9). No statistically signifi-
cant association was found between gender or LOS and over-
all satisfaction in both THR patients and TKR patients (Table 
4). The association between NRS overall satisfaction for THR 
and TKR and other measures of satisfaction is shown in Table 
4. Associations for THR and TKR were found between over-
all satisfaction and satisfaction with information given (p = 
0.01 and p = 0.04), but not with other measures of satisfac-
tion (Table 4). There was no effect of comorbidity on overall 
satisfaction, except in TKR patients with diabetes (p = 0.01). 
No other interactions were found (Table 4). No statistically 
significant random variation was found between surgeons (p 
= 1.0). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The main finding of the study was that THR and TKR patients 
in a fast-track setting were very satisfied. The median NRS 
score ranged from 8.5 to 10 in all parameters. Husted et al.  (2008) also found high overall short-term patient satisfaction 
in both THR and TKR patients, with mean NRS scores of 9.4 
and 9.3. However, in Husted's study, the patients returned the 
questionnaire at discharge, which may have introduced bias. 
Our results support the existing evidence that fast-track path-
ways for orthopedic patients do not compromise patient satis-
faction (Jones et al. 2014). </p>

<p>Table 3. Overall satisfaction of THR and TKA patients in relation to 
patient-related outcome measures (p-values for bivariate analyses) </p>

<p>Variable 
THR (n = 215) TKR (n = 230) 
p-value 
p-value </p>

<p>Age group a 
0.8 
0.5 
Men 
0.20 
0.03 
LOS b 
&lt; 0.001 
0.3 
Comorbidities: 
rheumatoid arthritis 
0.2 
0.04 
cardiovascular disease 
0.9 
0.1 
lung disease 
0.3 
0.1 
diabetes 
0.02 
0.5 
&gt; 1 comorbidity 
0.6 
0.3 
Satisfaction with: 
information given 
&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 
pain treatment 
&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 
rehabilitation during hospitalization &lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 
discharge procedure 
&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 
first weeks at home 
&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 
LOS b yes (reference) 
no, wanted to stay longer 
0.01 
1.0 
no, wanted a shorter stay 
1.0 
-
do not know 
1.0 
0.3 </p>

<p>a Age group: &lt; 50, 50-59, 60-69, 70-79, and &gt; 79 years. 
b LOS: length of stay in hospital. </p>

<p>Table 4. Overall satisfaction of THR and TKR patients in relation to patient-related outcome 
measures (coefficients with 95% CI and p-values for multiple regression) </p>

<p>Variable 
THR (n = 215) 
TKR (n = 230) 
Coefficient (95% CI) p-value 
Coefficient (95% CI) p-value </p>

<p>Age group a 
0.13 (0.07 to 0.18) 
0.01 
0.01 (-0.15 to 0.14) 
0.9 
Men 
0.02 (-0.39 to 0.42) 0.9 
-0.03 (-0.25 to 0.19) 
0.7 
LOS b 
-0.04 (-0.21 to 0.14) 0.6 
0.01 (-0.01 to 0.03) 
0.1 
Comorbidities: 
rheumatoid arthritis 
0.47 (-0.60 to 1.54) 0.3 
0.29 (-0.14 to 0.72) 
0.1 
cardiovascular disease 
0.73 (-0.85 to 2.31) 0.2 
0.12 (-0.06 to 0.29) 
0.2 
lung disease 
-0.09 (-1.07 to 0.90) 0.8 
-0.34 (-1.87 to 1.19) 
0.6 
diabetes 
-0.30 (-0.97 to 0.38) 0.3 
0.21 (0.09 to 0.34) 
0.01 
&gt; 1 comorbidity 
0.12 (-0.71 to 0.96) 0.7 
-0.07 (-1.00 to 0.86) 
0.9 
Satisfaction with: 
information given 
0.20 (0.09 to 0.31) 
0.01 
0.18 (0.01 to 0.35) 
0.04 
pain treatment 
0.27 (-0.07 to 0.61) 0.09 
0.16 (-0.03 to 0.35) 
0.08 
rehabilitation during 
hospitalization 
-0.01 (-0.22 to 0.24) 0.9 
0.07 (-0.20 to 0.33) 
0.5 
discharge procedure 
-0.01 (-0.25 to 0.23) 0.9 
0.04 (-0.25 to 0.32) 
0.7 
first weeks at home 
0.10 (-0.15 to 0.34) 0.3 
0.08 (-0.01 to 0.18) 
0.08 
LOS b yes (reference) 
no, wanted to stay longer 
0.01 (-0.71 to 0.72) 0.9 
0.47 (-0.35 to 1.29) 
0.2 
no, wanted a shorter stay -0.38 (-1.66 to 0.90) 0.4 
-
-
do not know 
1.30 (0.87 to 1.73) 
0.002 
-0.04 (-0.54 to 0.45) 
0.8 </p>

<p>a Age group: &lt; 50, 50-59, 60-69, 70-79, and &gt; 79 years. 
b LOS: length of stay in hospital. </p>

<p>Factors related to overall satis-
faction 
Bivariate analyses: No association 
was found between overall satisfac-
tion and age group (THR and TKR), 
sex (THR), or LOS (TKR). In TKR 
patients men had higher overall sat-
isfaction than women, with a median 
NRS score of 10 for men and 9 for 
women (p = 0.03) (Table 3). No 
association was found between over-
all satisfaction and satisfaction with 
LOS, except in THR patients who 
wanted to stay longer (p = 0.01). All 
other satisfaction variables listed in 
Table 3 showed an association with 
overall satisfaction. The association 
of comorbidities with overall sat-
isfaction was significant in TKR 
patients with rheumatoid arthritis (p 
= 0.04) and THR patients with dia-
betes (p = 0.02) (Table 3). No asso-
ciation was found between operat-
ing surgeon and overall satisfaction 
in THR or TKR patients (p = 0.2 and 
p = 0.5). </p>



<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2015; 86 (6): 702-707 </p>

<p>Our THR and TKR patients had a median score for overall 
satisfaction of 10 and 9. This demonstrates that the concept 
of fast-track surgery with a median LOS of 2 days is not a 
disadvantage to patients. This is supported by another Danish 
study, which found that THR and TKR patients with a LOS of 
5 days or less had a mean overall satisfaction score of 9.0 for 
THR and 8.3 for TKR (Husted et al. 2006). The TKR patients 
in Husted's study seem to have been less satisfied, as they fell 
outside the 95% CI of the overall satisfaction score in our 
study (median 9, 95% CI: 9-10). Husted et al. (2006, 2010a  used the same Danish questionnaire as in our study, but it was 
sent out at different time points between 2 and 10 months after 
surgery, resulting in a risk of recall bias (Husted et al. 2006,  2010a). 
The THR patients in our study were in hospital for a shorter 
time than the TKR patients, even though both groups had a 
median LOS of 2 days. The majority of patients found the 
short LOS convenient, and only 10% (THR) and 8% (TKR) 
had wanted to stay longer. These results agree with those of 
Jones et al. (2014), who found that orthopedic patients in a 
fast-track pathway prefer a shorter LOS. An explanation could 
be that in a fast-track setting all sub-components of care are 
prioritized, especially oral and written information, in order 
to ensure that patients are safe when they leave the hospital. 
We found no association between age and overall satisfac-
tion in TKR patients, but in THR patients, the older ones were 
more satisfied. Overall, it is unclear whether age has an effect 
on satisfaction (Lau et al. 2012). 
We found no association between gender and overall satis-
faction in THR and TKR patients, as previously found by Lau  et al. (2012). 
We found no relationship between comorbidities and overall 
satisfaction, except in TKR patients with diabetes. This is cor-
roborated by Bourne et al. (2010), who found no relationship 
between satisfaction and comorbidity in TKR patients using 
the American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical 
status score. In contrast to our study, Clement et al. (2013)  found that diabetes had no influence on patient satisfaction in 
TKR patients and Anakwe et al. (2011) did not find any rela-
tionship between diabetes and dissatisfaction in THR patients. 
However, Husted et al. (2008) found that patients with no 
comorbidities were more satisfied than patients with 1 or more 
comorbidities following THR and TKR. These conflicting 
findings about the effect of comorbidities on overall satisfac-
tion were also discussed in a review by Lau et al. (2012). 
The strength of our study is that the questionnaire was com-
pleted at home without any influence from the healthcare pro-
viders at the hospital, and the questionnaire was filled out at an 
early time point to eliminate recall bias. The high percentage 
of patients who participated strengthens the study, and inclu-
sion of the patients consecutively helped to minimize selection 
bias. Finally, the very high response rate also strengthened the 
study. A limitation of the study was that the questionnaire was 
only pilot-tested by the Danish Health and Medicine Author-</p>

<p>ity (Danish Health and Medicine Authority 2006, Husted et  al. 2010a) and was not validated using an accepted valida-
tion method. The questionnaire could be limited in terms of a 
ceiling effect (Taylor 2010), because a high proportion of the 
patients gave the highest possible score on some of the ques-
tions. We must therefore consider that the satisfaction mea-
sured reflects the parameters of the instrument rather than the 
patients' real satisfaction. 
In conclusion, we found that THR and TKR patients were 
very satisfied with the treatment and care they received in a 
fast-track setting. Both groups of patients had similarly high 
scores in all parameters, except in the first weeks at home 
where TKR patients gave a lower score than THR patients. 
A qualitative investigation of the lowest-scoring parameter, 
in the first weeks after discharge, is required to learn more 
about the kinds of challenges that patients deal with at home. 
No relationship was found between overall satisfaction and 
comorbidity, except in TKR patients with diabetes. Older 
THR patients were more satisfied. </p>

<p>KS: study design, performance of the investigation, and writing of the man-
uscript. HK, PK, and BDP: study design. NW: statistical analysis. All the 
authors participated in the interpretation of data, discussions, and critical revi-
sion of the manuscript. </p>

<p>We thank Susanne Leed Henriksen, RN, MSc of the Department of Orthope-
dics, Vejle Hospital, for assistance with this investigation. </p>

<p>The study was funded in part by the Health Research Fund of the Region of 
Southern Denmark. This funding did not lead to any conflicts of interests. The 
study was also funded by the Lundbeck Foundation Center for Fast-track Hip 
and Knee Replacement. Three of the authors were affiliated to the center, but 
these affiliations were of no importance to the findings. </p>

<p>Anakwe R E, Jenkins P J, Moran M. Predicting dissatisfaction after total hip 
arthroplasty: a study of 850 patients. J Arthroplasty 2011; 26 (2): 209-13. 
Bourne R B, Chesworth B M, Davis A M, Mahomed N N, Charron K D. 
Patient satisfaction after total knee arthroplasty: who is satisfied and who is 
not? Clin Orthop Relat Res 2010; 468 (1): 57-63. 
Clement N D, MacDonald D, Burnett R, Breusch S J. Diabetes does not 
influence the early outcome of total knee replacement: a prospective study 
assessing the Oxford knee score, short form 12, and patient satisfaction. 
Knee 2013; 20 (6): 437-41. 
Cuzick J. A Wilcoxon-type test for trend. Stat Med 1985; 4 (1): 87-90. 
Danish Health and Medicine Authority. CEMTV -Evaluering af patientfor-
loeb for patienter som gennemgaar primaere total hofte-eller knaealloplas-
tik operationer i Danmark. [An evaluation of clinical pathway for patients 
in primary total hip and knee arthroplasty in Denmark]. 2006. Danish. 
http://sundhedsstyrelsen.dk/publ/Publ2006/CEMTV/Alloplastik/Baggr-
undsrapport.pdf 
Danish Hip Arthroplasty Register. Annual Report 2013. Danish. http://www. 
dhr.dk/Ny%20mappe/rapporter/DHR%20årsrapport%202013_full%20 
versionfinal_.pdf 
Danish Knee Arthroplasty Register. Annual Report 2013. Danish. https:// 
www.knee.dk/groups/dkr/pdf/DKR_2013.pdf </p>

<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2015; 86 (6): 702-707 </p>





</text></tei>