<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4630182" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Department of gastroenterology, 
huai'an hospital affiliated to Xuzhou 
Medical college and huai'an second 
People's hospital, huai'an, Jiangsu, 
People's republic of china </p>

<p>Objective: Interaction between microRNA (miR-328) and PTPRJ (protein tyrosine phosphatase, 
receptor type, J) has been reported to be responsible for miR-328-dependent increase in epithelial 
cancer cell proliferation. However, the role of miR-328 and PTPRJ in hepatocellular carcinoma 
(HCC) remains unclear. The aim of this study was to investigate the clinical significance of 
miR-328 and/or PTPRJ expression in human HCC and determine their precise biological func-
tions in this malignancy. 
Methods: Expression levels of miR-328 and PTPRJ messenger RNA (mRNA) in 100 pairs 
of HCC and adjacent noncancerous tissues were detected using quantitative real-time reverse 
transcription polymerase chain reaction. The associations between miR-328 and/or PTPRJ 
expression and various clinicopathological features of HCC patients were further statistically 
assessed. Then, the functions of miR-328 and PTPRJ in migration and invasion of two human 
HCC cell lines were determined by transwell assays. 
Results: miR-328 and PTPRJ mRNA expression levels were markedly upregulated and down-
regulated in HCC tissues, respectively, compared to adjacent noncancerous tissues. Notably, 
the upregulation of miR-328 in HCC tissues was significantly correlated with the downregu-
lation of PTPRJ mRNA in HCC tissues (r=−0.362, P=0.01). In addition, miR-328-high and/ 
or PTPRJ-low expression were found to be closely correlated with high Edmondson-Steiner 
grading (all P,0.05) and advanced tumor-node-metastasis stage (all P,0.05). Moreover, the 
restoration of miR-328 dramatically promoted HCC cell migration and invasion by repressing 
PTPRJ expression. Interestingly, the loss of PTPRJ expression could significantly attenuate the 
inhibitory effects of knockdown miR-328 on the migration and invasion of HCC cells. 
Conclusion: These findings demonstrated that the dysregulation of miR-328 and PTPRJ may 
be associated with tumor progression of HCC patients. Functionally, miR-328 may serve as 
a crucial oncogene and be implicated in the motility of HCC cells at least in part by the sup-
pression of PTPRJ. 
Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC), the most prevalent type of malignant liver cancer, 
has been recognized as the third leading cause of cancer-associated death worldwide. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Despite recent advances in disease management and treatment, the unfavorable prognosis 
in HCC patients remains unchanged, with a median survival of most patients of 
6-9 months following diagnosis. 
2 Especially, the overall 5-year survival rate of advanced-
stage HCC patients is less than 5% because of intra-hepatic metastases, extrahepatic 
metastases, early invasion into blood vessels, and recurrence. 
3 Growing evidence based </p>

<p>correspondence: shijie Ma 
Department of gastroenterology, 
huai'an First People's hospital, nanjing 
Medical University, 6 Beijing road 
West, huai'an, Jiangsu 223300, People's 
republic of china 
Tel +86 517 8087 2126 
Fax +86 517 8492 2412 
email shijiema123@126.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
28 October 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3160 </p>

<p>luo et al </p>

<p>on molecular profiling of HCC shows that there are a variety 
of molecular signaling transduction cascades that are involved 
into the aggressive progression of this malignancy. Therefore, 
it is of great significance to improve the understanding of the 
molecular mechanisms responsible for HCC carcinogenesis, 
invasion, and metastasis in order to identify the deregulated 
genes and to develop the novel therapeutic strategies. 
MicroRNAs (miRNAs), a type of small conserved 
noncoding RNAs with approximately 17-23 nucleotides in 
length, function as critical gene regulators via negatively 
regulating the expression of target genes by translational 
inhibition or destabilization of messenger RNAs (mRNAs) 
at a posttranscriptional level. 
4 In recent years, accumulat-
ing attention has been paid to the important biological and 
pathological roles of miRNAs because of their involvement 
in the regulation of various cellular processes, including 
cell development, proliferation, differentiation, apoptosis, 
motility, and cell cycle, which are all closely correlated with 
carcinogenesis and cancer progression. 
5,6 Hence, it is no sur-
prise to find that the deregulation of miRNAs is implicated 
in many human cancers and can function as tumor suppres-
sor genes or oncogenes in a tumor-type manner. Especially, 
recent studies have identified several deregulated miRNAs 
in HCC tissues or cells, and revealed their roles in HCC 
carcinogenesis and progression, providing evidence that 
restoration of the deregulated miRNAs might be considerable 
therapeutic strategies in HCC treatment. </p>

<p>7,8 </p>

<p>miR-328 has been regarded as a cancer-related miRNA. 
Accumulating studies suggest that it may play different roles 
and function as either an oncogene or a tumor suppressor 
depending on cancer types. 
9-14 In particular, Paduano et al </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>experimentally validated the direct regulatory effect of 
miR-328 on the mRNA levels of PTPRJ (protein tyrosine 
phosphatase, receptor type, J) via binding on its 3′-UTR in 
various cancer cells. It has been indicated that the expression 
of PTPRJ, a ubiquitous receptor-type protein tyrosine phos-
phatase, is significantly decreased in a vast majority of human 
epithelial cancers and cancer cell lines. 
15-19 However, the role 
of miR-328 and PTPRJ in HCC remains unclear. Therefore, 
we aimed to investigate the clinical significance of miR-328 
and/or PTPRJ expression in human HCC and determine their 
precise biological functions in this malignancy. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Patients and tissue samples </p>

<p>This study was authorized by the Research Ethics Committee 
of Huai'an First People's Hospital, Huai'an Hospital Affiliated 
to Xuzhou Medical College, and Huai'an Second People's </p>

<p>Hospital, People's Republic of China. Before collecting tumor 
specimens for this study, we acquired written informed consent 
from each enrolled patient. All specimens were handled and 
made anonymous according to the ethical and legal standards. 
A total of 100 HCC patients who underwent hepatec-
tomy at Huai'an First People's Hospital, Huai'an Hospital 
Affiliated to Xuzhou Medical College, and Huai'an Second 
People's Hospital from 2012 to 2014 were enrolled in this 
study. The diagnoses of all patients as having primary HCC 
were confirmed by at least two pathologists according to their 
clinicopathological features. None of the patients received 
any chemotherapy or radiation treatment prior to the surgery. 
Patients with a combination of another cancer and a history 
of liver transplantation were excluded from our cohort. The 
histological differentiation grades were classified according 
to the Edmondson-Steiner classification system. 
20 Tumor 
node metastasis (TNM) stages were graded based on the 
criteria revised by the American Association for the Study 
of Liver. 
21 All samples were snap-frozen and stored in liquid 
nitrogen after collection. </p>

<p>cell culturation and transfection </p>

<p>Two human HCC cell lines (SMMC-7721 and BEL-7402) 
were purchased from the cell bank of the Chinese Academy 
of Sciences. No ethics statement was required from the 
institutional review board for the use of these cell lines. The 
cells were cultured in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium 
(DMEM) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (Thermo 
Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA), 100 U/mL of penicillin 
(Thermo Fisher Scientific) and 100 mg/mL of streptomycin 
(Thermo Fisher Scientific) in a humidified atmosphere of 5% 
CO 2 at 37°C. 
miRNA-328/normal control (NC) mimics, miR-328/NC 
inhibitors, small interfering RNA (siRNA) against PTPRJ 
(si-PTPRJ), and a matched control siRNA (si-con) were 
chemically synthesized by Shanghai GenePharma Company 
(Shanghai, People's Republic of China). SMMC-7721 and 
BEL-7402 cells were transfected with miRNAs (100 nM) 
or siRNAs (50 nM) using Lipofectamine 2000 Transfection 
Reagent (Thermo Fisher Scientific) according to the manu-
facturer's protocol. </p>

<p>rna extraction and quantitative real-
time reverse transcription polymerase 
chain reaction </p>

<p>Total RNA was isolated using TRIzol™ Reagent (Thermo 
Fisher Scientific) according to the manufacturers' instructions. 
Reverse transcription (RT) reactions were performed using </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3161 </p>

<p>mir-328 and PTPrJ in hcc </p>

<p>the Prime-Script RT reagent kit (TaKaRa, Dalian, People's 
Republic of China). The quantitative polymerase chain reaction 
(PCR) was performed using a SYBR Premix Ex Taq TM II kit 
(TaKaRa). For the detection of miR-328 and PTPRJ mRNA 
expression levels, stem-loop miR-328 was reverse-transcribed 
and normalized by U6 and GAPDH, respectively. The sequences 
of the RT and PCR primers were listed as follows: for miR-328, 
miR-328-RT 5′-GTC GTA TCC AGT GCA GGG TCC GAG 
GTA TTC G-3′, miR-328 forward primer 5′-CTG GCC CTC 
TCT GCC C-3′, miR-328 reverse primer 5′-GTG CAG GGT 
CCG AGG T-3′; for U6: U6-RT 5′-GTT GGC TCT GGT GCA 
GGG TCC GAG GTA TTC GCA CCA GAG CCA ACA AAA 
ATA T-3′, U6-forward primer 5′-TTC CTC CGC AAG GAT 
GAC ACG C-3′, U6-reverse primer 5′-GTG CAG GGT CCG 
AGG T-3′; for PTPRJ: PTPRJ-RT 5′-CAG TAC AGT GAA 
TGG GAG CAC TGA C-3′, PTPRJ forward primer 5′-GGA 
TCC TCA GAA CCC ATG AA-3′, PTPRJ reverse primer 
5′-ACC GAC TGT CCA GTG AGA CC-3′; for GAPDH: 
GAPDH-RT 5′-CCT GAA GCC AGG GGT TCA ATA CCA 
ACA AAA ATA C-3′, GAPDH-forward primer 5′-CAC CAT 
CTC TCC AGA AGT GGA C-3′, GAPDH-reverse primer 
5′-GGC GTC ATC AAA GTT CTG CCA AC-3′. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>Total proteins were extracted from human HCC cells by using 
a modified radioimmunoprecipitation assay buffer (150 mM 
NaCl, 1% NP240, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate, 0.1% sodium 
dodecyl sulfate, 50 mM Tris, pH 7.4) in the presence of cOm-
plete, Mini protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche Diagnostics 
GmbH, Mannheim, Germany). Western blot analysis was 
performed after the separation of 50 µg of proteins on a 
sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS)/4%-20% polyacrylamide 
gel (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA) with conventional 
methods and an enhanced chemiluminescence detection kit 
(Amersham, Piscataway, NJ, USA). After that, filters were 
probed with mouse anti-hPTPRJ 1:100, hamster anti-mouse 
PTPRJ 1:1,000, and rabbit anti-GAPDH (Sigma-Aldrich 
Co., St Louis, MO, USA) 1:1,000 plus HRP-conjugated cor-
responding secondary antibodies at 1:1,000 (Cell Signalling 
Technologies, Danvers, MA, USA). Signals were visualized 
with SuperSignal West Pico Chemiluminescent substrate 
(Thermo Fisher Scientific) by exposure to films. </p>

<p>cell migration and invasion assay </p>

<p>The migration and invasion abilities of human HCC cells 
transfected with miR-328/NC mimic or miR-328/NC inhibi-
tor with or without si-PTPRJ/si-con were tested by migration 
and invasion assays, respectively, using the 24-well cell </p>

<p>migration kit with 8 µm-pore polycarbonate membrane 
(Corning Inc, Corning, NY, USA) and the invasion assay kit 
(BD Bioscience, San Jose, CA, USA), according to the manu-
facturer's instructions. The number of migrated or invaded 
cells on the lower side of the membrane was counted at 200× 
magnification from ten different fields of each filter. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 11.0</rs> for Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., 
Chicago, IL, USA) was used to perform all statistical 
analyses. In this study, all experiments were performed in 
triplicate. Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation 
of one representative experiment. Student's t-test was used to 
evaluate the continuous variables. The chi-square or Fisher's 
exact tests were used to evaluate the differences in propor-
tion. In all cases, differences were considered statistically 
significant at P,0.05. </p>

<p>Results 
Upregulation of mir-328 and 
downregulation of PTPrJ mrna in 
human hcc tissues </p>

<p>miR-328 (HCC vs noncancerous: 3.03±0.89 vs 1.95±0.82, 
P,0.01; Figure 1A) and PTPRJ mRNA (HCC vs noncancer-
ous: 2.57±0.91 vs 3.93±0.82, P,0.01; Figure 1B) expression 
levels were markedly upregulated and downregulated in 
HCC tissues, respectively, compared to adjacent noncancerous 
tissues. Notably, the upregulation of miR-328 in HCC tissues 
was significantly correlated with the downregulation of PTPRJ 
mRNA in HCC tissues (r=−0.362, P=0.01; Figure 1C). </p>

<p>Upregulation of mir-328 and/or 
downregulation of PTPrJ mrna 
associate with aggressive progression of 
patients with hcc </p>

<p>To determine the associations of miR-328 and/or PTPRJ 
mRNA expression with various clinicopathological factors, 
100 HCC patients were divided into high or low miR-328/ 
PTPRJ mRNA groups according to the 50th percentile 
(median) of relative miR-328/PTPRJ mRNA expression, 
as analyzed with the chi-square test (Table 1). Of 100 
HCC patients, 23 (23.0%) cases were both high expression 
of miR-328 and PTPRJ, 20 (20.0%) cases were both low 
expression of miR-328 and PTPRJ, 32 (32.0%) cases were 
miR-328-high and PTPRJ-low expression, and 25 (25.0%) 
cases were miR-328-low and PTPRJ-high expression. 
In addition, miR-328-high and/or PTPRJ-low expression </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3162 </p>

<p>luo et al </p>

<p>Figure 1 Upregulation of microrna (mir)-328 and downregulation of PTPrJ messenger rna (mrna) in hepatocellular carcinoma (hcc) tissues. 
Notes: (A) mir-328 (hcc vs noncancerous: 3.03±0.89 vs 1.95±0.82, P,0.01) expression level was markedly upregulated in hcc tissues compared to adjacent noncancerous tissues. 
(B) PTPrJ mrna (hcc vs noncancerous: 2.57±0.91 vs 3.93±0.82, P,0.01) expression level was markedly downregulated in hcc tissues compared to adjacent noncancerous 
tissues. (C) Upregulation of miR-328 in HCC tissues was significantly negatively correlated with the downregulation of PTPRJ mRNA in HCC tissues (r=−0.362, P=0.01). 
Abbreviation: PTPrJ, protein tyrosine phosphatase, receptor type, J. </p>

<p>Table 1 association of microrna (mir)-328 and/or PTPrJ mrna expression with different clinicopathological features of 
hepatocellular carcinoma patients </p>

<p>Clinicopathological 
features </p>

<p>Number of 
cases (%) </p>

<p>miR-328-high 
(n, %) </p>

<p>P-value 
PTPRJ-low 
(n, %) </p>

<p>P-value 
miR-328-high/ 
PTPRJ-low (n, %) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>age (years) 
,50 
42 (42.0) 
23 (54.8) 
ns 
22 (52.3) 
ns 
15 (35.7) 
ns 
$50 
58 (58.0) 
32 (55.2) 
30 (51.7) 
17 (29.3) 
sex 
Male 
88 (88.0) 
48 (54.5) 
ns 
46 (52.3) 
ns 
29 (33.0) 
ns 
Female 
12 (12.0) 
7 (58.3) 
6 (50.0) 
3 (25.0) 
hBV infection 
negative 
18 (18.0) 
10 (55.6) 
ns 
9 (50.0) 
ns 
6 (33.3) 
ns 
Positive 
82 (82.0) 
45 (54.9) 
43 (52.4) 
26 (31.7) 
serum aFP level (ng/ml) 
,400 
25 (25.0) 
10 (40.0) 
ns 
12 (48.0) 
ns 
6 (24.0) 
ns 
$400 
75 (75.0) 
40 (53.3) 
40 (53.3) 
26 (34.7) 
Venous infiltration 
negative 
30 (30.0) 
15 (50.0) 
ns 
15 (50.0) 
ns 
10 (33.3) 
ns 
Positive 
70 (70.0) 
40 (57.1) 
37 (52.9) 
22 (31.4) 
cirrhosis 
negative 
65 (65.0) 
35 (53.8) 
ns 
35 (53.8) 
ns 
22 (33.8) 
ns 
Positive 
35 (35.0) 
20 (57.1) 
17 (48.6) 
10 (28.6) 
edmondson-steiner grading 
i-ii 
72 (72.0) 
35 (48.6) 
0.02 
32 (44.4) 
0.02 
17 (23.6) 
0.01 
iii-iV 
28 (28.0) 
20 (71.4) 
20 (71.4) 
15 (53.6) 
TnM stage 
i-ii 
70 (70.0) 
32 (45.7) 
0.02 
30 (42.9) 
0.02 
12 (17.1) 
0.01 
iii-iV 
30 (30.0) 
23 (76.7) 
23 (76.7) 
20 (66.7) </p>

<p>Note: "NS" refers to the difference without statistical significance. 
Abbreviations: aFP, alpha fetal protein; hBV, hepatitis B virus; TnM, tumor node metastasis; mir, microrna; mrna, messenger rna. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3163 </p>

<p>mir-328 and PTPrJ in hcc </p>

<p>were found to be closely correlated with high Edmondson-
Steiner grading (all P,0.05, Table 1) and advanced TNM 
stage (all P,0.05, Table 1). </p>

<p>Upregulation of mir-328 promotes the 
migration and invasion of hcc cells 
in vitro </p>

<p>To determine the functions of miR-328 in the malignant phe-
notypes of HCC cells, SMMC-7721 and BEL-7402 cells were 
transfected with miR-328/NC mimics or miR-328/NC inhibi-
tors. As shown in Figure 2, the expression levels of miR-328 
in both SMMC-7721 and BEL-7402 cells transfected with 
miR-328 mimic were substantially increased, compared to 
those transfected with NC mimic (both P,0.05). 
Then, we found that the enforced expression of miR-328 
significantly promoted, but the knockdown of miR-328 dra-
matically retarded cell migration and invasion of both SMMC-
7721 and BEL-7402 cells (both P,0.05, Figure 3). </p>

<p>loss of PTPrJ attenuates the inhibitory 
effects of knockdown mir-328 on the 
migration and invasion of hcc cells </p>

<p>To further evaluate the contribution of PTPRJ to functions 
of miR-328 in the malignant phenotypes of HCC cells, we 
silenced the expression of PTPRJ protein by RNA interfer-
ence and confirmed by Western blot normalized to GAPDH. 
At 48 hours posttransfection, Western blot analysis shown in 
Figure 4A revealed that the expression level of PTPRJ protein 
in cells cotransfected with miR-328 inhibitor and si-PTPRJ 
was significantly lower than that in cells cotransfected with 
miR-328 inhibitor and si-con. Moreover, the loss of PTPRJ 
could significantly attenuate the effects of miR-328 inhibitor </p>

<p>on cell migration and invasion of both SMMC-7721 and 
BEL-7402 cells (Figure 4B). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In recent years, the deregulated expression of several 
miRNAs has been observed in HCC tissues. However, 
the molecular mechanisms of these miRNAs acting on 
carcinogenesis and cancer progression have not been fully 
elucidated. In this study, miR-328 was investigated as a 
deregulated miRNA in human HCC tissues. Our data con-
firmed the negative correlation between miR-328 upregula-
tion and PTPRJ downregulation, which has been validated as 
a target mRNA of miR-328, in HCC tissues. Interestingly, we 
revealed that miR-328-high and/or PTPRJ-low expression 
were significantly associated with aggressive progression 
of human HCC, especially with high Edmondson-Steiner 
grading and advanced TNM stage. Functionally, this miRNA 
may act as an onco-miRNA, as it was found to be involved 
in the development and progression of HCC through sup-
pressing the expression of PTPRJ mRNA. These results 
not only confirm the promoting effect of miR-328, but also 
suggest that miR-328 combined with PTPRJ might function 
as a potential therapeutic target for HCC. 
miR-328, together with let-7d* and miR18a*, has been 
reported as one of the multicentric HCC recurrence-related 
miRNAs. 
22 Its oncogenic or suppressive role has been 
confirmed in other types of cancer. MiR-328 may repre-
sent a potential diagnostic biomarker of non-small-cell 
lung cancer, especially for the identification of early-stage 
tumors. 
23 It may play an important role in maintaining can-
cer stem-like side population phenotype and may be a poten-
tial target for effective colorectal cancer therapy. 
24 miR-328 </p>

<p>Figure 2 relative expression of microrna (mir)-328 in both human hepatocellular carcinoma (hcc) cell lines sMMc-7721 and Bel-7402 transfected with mir-328/normal 
control (nc) mimics and mir-328/nc inhibitors. 
Notes: (A) expression levels of mir-328 in both sMMc-7721 and Bel-7402 cells transfected with mir-328 mimic were substantially increased, compared to those 
transfected with nc mimic (*P,0.05). (B) expression levels of mir-328 in both sMMc-7721 and Bel-7402 cells transfected with mir-328 inhibitor were substantially 
decreased, compared to those transfected with nc inhibitor (*P,0.05). </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3164 </p>

<p>luo et al </p>

<p>Figure 3 Microrna (mir)-328 promotes the migration and invasion of hepatocellular carcinoma (hcc) cell lines in vitro. 
Notes: (A) representative images showing the migration and invasion abilities of sMMc-7721 cells transfected with mir-328/normal control (nc) mimics or mir-328/nc 
inhibitors. (B) Enforced expression of miR-328 significantly promoted cell migration and invasion of both SMMC-7721 and BEL-7402 cells (*P,0.05). Knockdown of mir-328 
dramatically retarded cell migration and invasion of both sMMc-7721 and Bel-7402 cells (*P,0.05). </p>

<p>could promote glioma cell invasion via SFRP1-dependent 
Wnt-signaling activation. 
10 Furthermore, macrophages 
in the tumor microenvironment may cause the increased 
expression of CD44 via the suppression of miR-328, leading 
to tumor progression by enhancing reactive oxygen species 
(ROS) defense; thus, miR-328-CD44 signaling mediated by 
macrophages might be a potential target for the treatment 
of gastrointestinal cancer. 
25 In the current study, miR-328 
expression was upregulated in 55.0% of the HCC tissue 
samples and was positively correlated with tumor progres-
sion of HCC patients. Moreover, both the gain-of-function 
and loss-of-function assays confirmed that miR-328 might 
function as an oncogene that promoted HCC cell migration 
and invasion in vitro. 
To elucidate the oncogene mechanism of miR-328 in 
HCC, its target genes were investigated. One such target </p>

<p>gene was PTPRJ (also known as DEP-1, CD148, and HPTP), 
which maps at chromosome 11p11.2, a region involved in 
human tumors through loss of heterozygosity, and encodes 
a receptor-like protein tyrosine phosphatase, the expression 
of which is strongly reduced in the majority of investigated 
cancer cell lines and tumor specimens. 
26,27 PTPRJ negatively 
interferes with intracellular signals mediated by several 
oncogenic receptor tyrosine kinases. 
28 As a ubiquitous gene, 
PTPRJ is extensively expressed in all the investigated tissues, 
including brain, thyroid, liver, spleen, and endothelial cells. 
Pathologically, the aberrant expression of PTPRJ has been 
indicated to be able to interfere with cancer cells malignant 
phenotype both in vitro and in vivo. The binding of PTPRJ 
interacting peptides to cell cultures could dramatically reduce 
the extent of both MAPK phosphorylation and total phospho-
tyrosine levels. Conversely, they could induce a significant </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3165 </p>

<p>mir-328 and PTPrJ in hcc </p>

<p>Figure 4 loss of PTPrJ attenuates the inhibitory effects of knockdown mir-328 on migration and invasion of hepatocellular carcinoma (hcc) cells. 
Notes: (A) at 48 hours posttransfection, Western blot analysis revealed that the expression level of PTPrJ protein in cells cotransfected with mir-328 inhibitor and si-PTPrJ 
was significantly lower than that in cells cotransfected with miR-328 inhibitor and si-con (*P,0.05). (B) Loss of PTPRJ could significantly attenuate the effects of miR-328 
inhibitor on cell migration and invasion of both sMMc-7721 and Bel-7402 cells (*P,0.05). 
Abbreviations: PTPrJ, protein tyrosine phosphatase, receptor type, J; si-con, matched control sirna; mirna, microrna; si, small intefering. </p>

<p>increase in the cell cycle inhibitor p27Kip1. 
14 Moreover, 
PTPRJ agonist peptides both reduce proliferation and trigger 
apoptosis of treated cells, suggesting that peptide agonists of 
PTPRJ positively modulate the PTPRJ activity and may lead 
to novel targeted anticancer therapies. 
14 PTPRJ may promote </p>

<p>breast cancer cell invasion and metastasis via Src activation. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>In particular, the overexpression of miR-328 may decrease 
PTPRJ expression in various cancer cells and miR-328 acts 
directly on the 3′-UTR of PTPRJ, leading to the decreased 
mRNA levels, in line with the results of luciferase assay and </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3166 </p>

<p>luo et al </p>

<p>site-specific mutagenesis, which has identified miR-328 as 
an important player in the regulation of PTPRJ expression. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Because there are no previous reports on the association of 
HCC and PTPRJ, quantitative PCR was performed in the 
current study to detect the expression pattern of PTPRJ in 
HCC tissues. As a result, we found that PTPRJ expression 
was decreased in more than half of HCC patients and was 
negatively correlated with tumor progression. More interest-
ingly, correlation analysis also showed an inverse correlation 
between miR-328 expression and PTPRJ mRNA expression, 
and the combined miR-328/PTPRJ expression has more 
significant associations with clinicopathological features of 
HCC patients than miR-328 or PTPRJ alone. Furthermore, 
the functional assay suggests that PTPRJ siRNA could 
attenuate the inhibitory effects of knockdown miR-328 on 
the migration and invasion of HCC cells. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Our findings demonstrated that the dysregulation of miR-328 
and PTPRJ may be associated with tumor progression of 
HCC patients. Functionally, miR-328 may serve as a crucial 
oncogene and be implicated in the motility of HCC cells at 
least in part by the suppression of PTPRJ. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>All authors made substantial contributions to conception and 
design, acquisition of data, or analysis and interpretation of 
data; took part in either drafting the article or revising it criti-
cally for important intellectual content; gave final approval 
of the version to be published; and agree to be accountable 
for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related 
to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appro-
priately investigated and resolved. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>

<p>References </p>



<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open 
access journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3167 </p>

<p>mir-328 and PTPrJ in hcc </p>

</text></tei>