<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4752095" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
ARTICLE INFO </p>

<p>______________________________________________________________ 
______________________ </p>

<p>Purpose: To report our intermediate experience in treating patients with severe incon-
tinence using an adjustable perineal male sling with a tissue expander. 
Materials and Methods: An adjustable male sling procedure was performed on 21 
patients with severe incontinence. The underlying etiology of urinary incontinence 
was radical prostatectomy in 13 patients, open prostatectomy in 5 patients and tran-
surethral prostate resection in 3 patients. The difference between the classical and 
the adjustable sling is that in the latter there is a 25 mL tissue expander between the 
two layers of polypropylene mesh with an injection port. Adjustment of the sling was 
performed with saline via an inflation port, in case of recurrence or persistence of 
incontinence. 
Results: The mean age of the patients was 66.2±7.3 (50-79) years and mean pad usa-
ge was 6.4±0.6 per day. The mean follow-up time was 40.1±23.2 (6-74) months. The 
balloon was postoperatively inflated on average with 11.6±5.7 (5-25) mL. After the 
mean 40.1 months of follow-up, 16 of the 21 patients (76.2%) were dry (11 patients, 0 
pads; 5 patients using safety pads), 3 patients (14%) had mild and 2 (9.8%) had mo-
derate degree post-prostatectomy urinary incontinence (PPI). The average maximum 
urine flow rate of the patients was 15.6±4.7 (10-31) mL/s. No residual urine was found. 
In 2 patients, all parts of the device were removed due to infection and discomfort, and 
in 3 patients only the inflation component was removed due to local scrotal infection. 
Conclusions: Our results show that using an adjustable perineal male sling with a tissue 
expander seems to be an efficient, and safe surgical treatment option in patients with PPI. </p>

<p>Male urinary incontinence is very distres-
sing problem after prostatic surgery. It has a sig-
nificant impact on the patient's quality of life (1). 
Post-prostatectomy urinary incontinence (PPI) is 
a potential complication of prostate surgery and 
although it is more frequently seen after radical 
prostatectomy it can also occur after endoscopic </p>

<p>or open surgery for benign prostate hyperplasia 
(BPH) (2). Initial management is usually conserva-
tive and includes the use of diapers or pads, penile 
clamps, or various collecting systems (such as a 
condom catheter). Mild degrees of PPI in the early 
postoperative period may be improved by pelvic 
muscle exercises, physiotherapy, and pharmaco-
therapy (3). However, for most patients who have 
moderate to severe PPI, conservative methods are </p>

<p>Vol. 41 (2): 312-318, March -April, 2015 </p>

<p>doi: 10.1590/S1677-5538.IBJU.2015.02.18 </p>

<p>ibju | AdjustAble mAle sling in men </p>



<p>not sufficient to return to their normal lives. Surgery 
is usually necessary to treat the more severe cases. 
Various male slings and devices are avai-
lable for the treatment of PPI. Sub-urethral slings 
can be categorized into adjustable and non-adjus-
table systems. The present study reports our inter-
mediate experience in men who underwent im-
plantation of adjustable perineal male sling using 
a tissue expander for PPI. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>This prospective study was approved by 
the local ethics committee and a comprehensive 
informed consent was obtained from all the pa-
tients before the surgery. Between September 2007 
and May 2013, a total of 21 men with PPI un-
derwent implantation of adjustable perineal male 
sling using a tissue expander. The underlying etio-
logies of PPI in patients were: radical prostatec-
tomy for prostate cancer in 13 patients (open radi-
cal retropubic prostatectomy=12, transperitoneal 
laparoscopic radical prostatectomy=1), open pros-
tatectomy in 5 patients and transurethral prostate 
resection for BPH in 3 patients. 
Patient evaluation consisted of medical 
history, physical examination, blood and urine la-
boratory tests. All the patients underwent a stan-
dard urodynamic study including both cystometry 
and pressure-flow study to evaluate bladder sto-
rage and voiding capabilities, and to exclude ove-
ractive bladder. Also, an urethrocystoscopy was 
conducted in all the patients to exclude urethral 
stricture and/or bladder neck contracture. The pa-
tients who had a history of previous surgery for 
PPI were not included in the study. 
Incontinence in the patients was defined 
according to the use of incontinence pads over a 
24 hours period: mild (using 1 to 2 pads), moderate 
(3 to 5 pads) and severe (more than 5 pads) (4). All 
the patients reported severe urinary incontinence in 
the pre-operative period. All operations were per-
formed within 6 to 12 months after the prostatec-
tomy. The post-operative follow-up was carried out 
in the second week and every 6 months thereafter 
consisting of daily pad use, physical examination, 
maximum urine flow rate (Qmax) and post-voiding 
residual urine volume (PVR) measurement. </p>

<p>SURGICAL PROCEDURE </p>

<p>The surgical procedure was performed 
using the technique described by Inci et al. (5) in 
2008. All patients received prophylactic antibio-
tics (3rd generation cephalosporin) before the in-
duction of anesthesia. Under general or regional 
anesthesia, patients were placed in the lithotomy 
position. After the insertion of a urethral catheter, 
a midline perineal incision of 40 to 50 mm was 
made. The critical point is not to remove periure-
thral fat tissues from urethra. Both sides of urethra 
were dissected down to the lower border of the 
pubic bone (Figure-1a). A Eurosilicone™ (Labora-
toires Eurosilicone, France) tissue expander device 
was used with an adjustable male sling in our pa-
tients. The device contains a silicone balloon ex-
pander, a connecting tube and an inflation com-
ponent (injection port) that allows the expander 
to gradually fill up to a volume of 25 mL saline 
solution (Figure-1b). 
A standard polypropylene mesh of 100 x 
100 mm was used as the sling material. First, the 
mesh was folded and a balloon expander was pla-
ced between the two layers of the modification. 
Secondly, the balloon was completely filled with 
the saline solution, and the two layers of the mesh 
were sutured using 2/0 polypropylene suture to 
create a pocket between the two layers of the mesh 
(Figure-1c). During this procedure, attention must 
be paid not to damage the filled balloon. After 
the pocket was created, the balloon was evacua-
ted. Third, the mesh was stapled on both sides of 
the lower border of the pubic bone using an Auto-
suture Stat TackTM (Tyco Healthcare, UK) stapler 
(Figure-1d). The original surgical method defined 
by Inci, et al. (5) used a polypropylene mesh that 
was fixed on the pubic bone with non-absorbable 
sutures. In our case, this method was modified and 
staples were used to prevent the sutures and the 
mesh from loosening and moving. 
After the sling tension was properly adjus-
ted, the sling was placed as tightly as possible in 
all patients since urinary leakage had been obser-
ved in our patients postoperatively. Then, the ex-
pander was left deflated during surgery. Fourth, a 
scrotal pouch was created as a sleeve for the infla-
tion component. The inflation component has two </p>

<p>ibju | AdjustAble mAle sling in men </p>



<p>sides (Figure-1e). Finally, the wound was closed 
with careful hemostasis. In all the procedures, no 
drain was used. After the surgery, all the patients 
were asked to take an oral antibiotic (2th genera-
tion cephalosporin) for 7 days. 
Post-operative success was assessed by the 
number of pads used per 24 hours as follows; zero </p>

<p>to 1 safety pad-dry, 1 to 2 pads-mild, and 3 to 
5 pads-moderate. At a minimum of 1 week after 
surgery, patients were questioned regarding their 
daily pad use. If incontinence persisted 7 to 10 
days after surgery, tension over the urethra was 
increased by saline injection to expand the tissue 
expander via the injection port using an insulin </p>

<p>Figure 1 -a) Both sides of urethra are dissected; b) A balloon expander; c) A balloon expander between two layers of the 
mesh; d) The mesh is stapled to the pubic bone using Autosuture Stat Tack </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>; e) Prepared scrotal pouch for placing the 
inflation component. </p>

<p>ibju | AdjustAble mAle sling in men </p>



<p>needle. Injection was started with 3 cc and increa-
sed by 2 cc at each injection. In this way the ballo-
on was gradually filled with saline up to 25 mL. 
The patients were asked to return 2 days after each 
adjustment to confirm the status of continence. 
Additional injections were performed in cases of 
recurrent incontinence. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The mean values of the parameters were 
calculated using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for Social 
Sciences</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 13.0</rs> for Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., 
Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The mean age of the patients was 66.2±7.3 
(50-79) years and the mean pad usage was 6.4±0.6 
(6-8) per day. Two patients had a history of pel-
vic radiotherapy. The mean operation time was 
56.2±14.7 (45-85) minutes. No blood transfusion 
was necessary. The mean duration of hospitaliza-
tion was 2.5 (2-4) days. 
The mean follow-up time was 40.1±23.2 
(6-74) months. The mean volume of the postope-
ratively inflated balloon was 11.6±5.7 (5-25) mL. 
After the follow-up period, 16 of the 21 patients 
(76.2%) were dry (11 patients, 0 pads; 5 patients 
using safety pads), 3 patients (14%) had mild de-
gree PPI and 2 patients (9.8%) had moderate degree 
PPI. In the last assessment of the patients, Qmax 
and estimated PVR were found to be 15.6±4.7 (10-
31) mL/s and 10 mL, respectively. 
One patient had scrotal infection and pain, 
and another patient had perineal discomfort. In 
these two patients, the polypropylene mesh with 
balloon, connecting tube and inflation compo-
nent were removed and they did not undergo 
any additional intervention. Local scrotal infec-
tion developed around the inflation component in 
three patients. In these patients, only the inflation 
component was removed, the connecting tube was 
clipped and the polypropylene mesh with inflated 
balloon was kept in place. In these patients, poly-
propylene mesh with inflated balloon provided 
suitable pressure on the urethra. In the follow-up 
period, they were completely dry. No complica-</p>

<p>tions were encountered in patients with a previous 
history of pelvic radiotherapy. 
No complications occurred in relation to 
mesh erosion, voiding dysfunction, voiding di-
fficulty or mechanical failure. Six patients repor-
ted mild perineal pain in the early postoperative 
period but this was resolved using non-steroidal 
anti-inflammatory drugs. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>PPI represents a significant health pro-
blem. The rising elderly population and the incre-
asing number of surgical interventions for pros-
tate cancer mean that the incidence of PPI will 
rise. Since its introduction in 1973, the artificial 
urinary sphincter (AUS) has been considered the 
gold standard treatment for stress urinary incon-
tinence after prostatectomy, offering the patient 
the greatest chance of a cure (6). The success rates 
of AUS range from 59 to 90% (7-9). Although, 
AUS is an effective and durable treatment, many 
patients are hesitant about implantation or refuse 
the procedure. Most patients could not manipu-
late the scrotal pump (10). Furthermore, AUS is 
expensive and requires a complex surgical pro-
cedure that is associated with significant rates of 
complications. A recent systematic review about 
AUS reported that infection or erosion occurred 
in 8.5% of cases (3.3-27.8%), mechanical failure 
in 6.2% (2-13.8%), and urethral atrophy in 7.9% 
(1.9-28.6%). Re-operation rate was reported to 
range from 14.8% to 44.8% (11). 
Thus, many minimally invasive alternati-
ves have been investigated as possible alternati-
ves to AUS. The ProACT™ (Uromedica, US) system 
was first described in 2005 by Hubner et al. (12). 
In theietlr study, there were 117 patients with PPI 
followed for a mean period of 13 months, after 
which 67% of the patients were found to be dry. 
Lebret et al. (13) reported the results of the Pro-
ACT™ intervention in 62 men with PPI and found 
that 71% of the patients wore no pads or used 1 
pad per day after 6 months (following the adjust-
ment). However, in 19 men the device was remo-
ved due to infection and erosion (n=5), migration 
(n=1), and iatrogenic traumatism (n=2). Moreover, 
9 patients experienced device failure. In another </p>

<p>ibju | AdjustAble mAle sling in men </p>



<p>prospective study (14), the authors evaluated the 
results of ProAct™ in 114 men with PPI at a mean 
follow-up time of 58 months and reported an ove-
rall dry rate of 50%. In that study, complications 
included balloon leakage (11%), migration (5%) 
and wound erosion (4%). The authors reported 
that there was a total re-operation rate of 27%, 
and 12% of the patients underwent AUS or a ure-
thral sling procedures due to ProACT™ not being 
effective. 
The Argus™ (Promedon SA, Argentina) 
sub-urethral sling with an adjustable system is 
another treatment option in men with PPI that 
was first described by Romano et al. (15). The 
authors reported a cure rate of 73% and the im-
provement rate was 10% in 48 men with PPI after 
a mean follow-up of 7.5 months. Dalpiaz et al. 
(16) reported mid-term complications after the 
placement of the Argus™ sling in 29 men with 
PPI at a mean follow-up of 35 months. Overall, 
24 patients (83%) experienced complications, 
consisting of acute urinary retention (35%) and 
removal of the sling (35%) owing to urethral ero-
sion, infection, system dislocation, urinary reten-
tion, and persistent pain. Furthermore, 27% of 
the patients complained of significant perineal 
pain. The authors concluded that the ArgusTM 
sub-urethral sling was associated with serious 
mechanical and infectious complications, and 
sparse functional results with negative impact on 
the patient's quality of life. 
Another device used for treating PPI is the 
bulbo-urethral sling. Several variations of male 
sling are currently available. A bone anchored 
sling (BAS) compresses the bulbar urethra with a 
silicone-coated polypropylene mesh by attaching 
the sling to the inferior pubic ramus with bone 
screws. Following initial reports of degradation 
of organic materials, synthetic mesh (InVance™, 
American Medical Systems, US) has become the 
most commonly utilized material with the BAS 
(17). Rajpurkar et al. (4) reported their results in 46 
patients with PPI who undergo BAS implantation. 
In their study, the total cure rate was 37%. Fur-
thermore, 37% of the patients significantly impro-
ved, and the treatment of 26% patients failed after 
an average of 24 months follow-up. They conclu-
ded that the male sling procedure is an effective </p>

<p>and safe procedure for the management of stress 
urinary incontinence. However, it should not be 
considered as an alternative to AUS. Guimaraes 
et al. (18) reported their intermediate results of up 
to 4 years with the InVance™ sling. Their cure rate 
was 65% and the improvement rate was 23% in 54 
men with PPI after a mean follow-up of 28 mon-
ths. The authors claimed that the InVance™ sling 
offers a good intermediate cure and improvement 
rates with acceptably low rate of complications in 
patients suffering from PPI. Another study inves-
tigated the use of the InVance™ sling in 40 pa-
tients with PPI (19). The cure rate was 55% at a 
mean follow-up of 35.2 months. The authors ob-
served perineal pain in 73% of the patients, detru-
sor overactivity in 5% and sling infection in 15%. 
The traditional BAS procedure does not 
provide for the adjustment of the tension of the 
sling material in the post-operative period and 
this can result in progressive failure over time. In 
a study by Castle et al. (1), 42 patients underwent 
the BAS procedure. Only 15.8% of the patients 
were completely dry and 39.5% were socially con-
tinent. Social continence was achieved in 67% 
50% and 0% of mild, moderate and severe cases, 
respectively. Comiter (20) speculated that the sur-
geons left the fatty tissue over the bulbospongious 
intact, and additionally used a piece of porcine 
dermis between the urethra and the sling A combi-
nation of fat necrosis and absorption of the dermis 
over time likely contributes to diminution of the 
compression provided by the sling over the bulbar 
urethra. Onur et al. (21) reported a median time to 
recurrent incontinence as 3 months after BAS pro-
cedure. Similarly, Cespedes and Jacoby reported 
an early failure (within 6 months) in 5% of their 
patients (22). In another study (23), the authors 
retrospectively reported objective and subjective 
outcomes in 40 male patients who underwent BAS 
positioning for stress urinary incontinence due to 
intrinsic sphincter deficiency. Patients with stress 
urinary incontinence due to radical retropubic 
prostatectomy (n=32), robot assisted laparoscopic 
prostatectomy (n=3) and transurethral prostate re-
section (n=5) underwent the BAS procedure over a 
5 years period. Previous anti-incontinence proce-
dures, radiotherapy and transurethral procedures 
due to urethral stricture were performed in 5, 11 </p>

<p>ibju | AdjustAble mAle sling in men </p>



<p>and 5 patients, respectively. At a mean follow-up 
of 35.2 months, 22 patients (55%) were cured, the 
condition of 5 patients (12.5%) improved and the 
treatment of 13 patients (32.5%) failed. The au-
thors concluded that BAS is a simple and effec-
tive procedure that can produce immediate good 
results with low morbidity, especially when stric-
tly selected patients are treated. Radiotherapy re-
mains a strong predictor of failure. 
In the current study, an adjustable perineal 
male sling technique was used for the treatment 
of PPI as described previously (5). In that study 
an adjustable perineal male sling with a 10 mL 
tissue expander was implanted in 19 consecutive 
men with severe PPI. According to the results of 
that study, at a mean follow-up of 17.3 months 
15 patients (78.9%) were completely dry and 2 
(10.5%) improved significantly using only 1 to 2 
pads per day. A total of 11 patients required volu-
me adjustment injections. The average number of 
adjustments was 2 (range 1 to 3) and the average 
injected volume was 6.3 cc (range 5 to 10). Regar-
ding the complications, 1 patient had a superficial 
wound infection, 1 patient required surgical revi-
sion due to infection and 8 patients reported mild 
to moderate perineal pain. The authors concluded 
that the short term results indicate that this mi-
nimally invasive technique seems to be safe and 
effective, and patient satisfaction appears to be 
high. The same group presented their long term 
results in the International Continence Society 
Annual Meeting 2013. In a study by Ergen and 
Ozdemir (24), 58 men underwent the same proce-
dure as described above. The mean follow-up time 
was 52 months. The completely dry rate decrea-
sed from 78.9% to 58% in the long term period. 
The authors concluded that adjustable male sling 
using a 10 mL tissue expander is an effective me-
thod for severe PPI, in the early period, but the 
effectiveness gradually decreases in the long term. 
The review of our intermediate results at 
40.1 months showed that 16 of the 21 patients 
(76.2%) were completely dry, 3 patients (14%) had 
mild incontinence and 2 patients (9.8%) had mo-
derate incontinence. The success rate of the cur-
rent study is better than that of the other studies 
mentioned above (5, 24). A possible explanation 
for our high success rate may be associated with </p>

<p>the high capacity of the silicone balloon. In our 
patients, we used a larger size of silicone balloon 
(25 mL) than the other two studies. Additionally, 
we used a stapler which allows the easier atta-
chment of the polypropylene mesh on the lower 
border of the pubic bone in both sides. Although 
previous pelvic radiotherapy history has also been 
claimed to be a negative predictor of success rate 
in PPI surgery (19, 23), 2 patients in current study 
whom had a previous history of pelvic radiothera-
py were dry in the intermediate follow-up. 
A new device is a perineal sling with a tis-
sue expander, composed of 2 silicone components, 
a balloon expander and an injection port, connec-
ted by a tube. In Turkey, this device is relatively 
cheap compared with AUS, ProACT™, ArgusTM 
($500 vs. $5.000 vs. $2330 vs. $2400) and easy to 
implant, even in difficult cases. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>Although complications occurred in this 
study, including the removal of the device and 
the removal of inflation component due to local 
scrotal infection, our intermediate follow-up stu-
dy suggests that an adjustable perineal male sling 
using a tissue expander appears to be an efficient 
and safe alternative surgical treatment option for 
patients suffering from PPI. The major limitations 
of our study were the small number of patients 
and the duration of the follow-up period. Addi-
tional follow-up and larger series of patients are 
necessary to confirm our results. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>None declared. </p>



<p>ibju | AdjustAble mAle sling in men </p>





<p>_______________________ 
Correspondence address: </p>

<p>Altug Tuncel, MD 
Ministry of Health, Ankara Numune Research and Training 
Hospital, Third Department of Urology, 06120 
Sihhiye, Ankara, Turkey 
Fax: +90 312 310 3460 
E-mail: tuncelaltug@yahoo.com </p>

</text></tei>