<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4583819" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: Paraneoplastic neurologic disorders (PND) are autoimmune diseases associated with cancer and ectopic 
expression of a neuronal antigen in a peripheral tumor. Patients with PND harbor high-titer antibodies and T cells in their 
serum and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) that are specific to the tumor antigen, and treatment with the immunosuppressant 
FK506 (tacrolimus) decreases CSF white blood cell counts. The objective of this study was to determine the effect of 
FK506 on CSF chemokine levels in PND patients. 
Methods: CSF samples before and after FK506 treatment were tested by multiplex assay for the presence of 27 
cytokines. Follow-up in vitro experiments aimed to determine whether T cells secrete CXCL10 in response to cognate 
antigen. 
Results: Here we report that PND patients harbor high levels of the chemokine CXCL10 in their CSF. CXCL10 is a 
cytokine that recruits CXCR3 
1 cells such as activated T cells, and we found that FK506 treatment specifically 
decreased CSF CXCL10 from among 27 cytokines tested. In vitro, CXCL10 was only produced during antigen-
specific cognate interactions between T cells and antigen-presenting cells (APCs) when interferon-c (IFNc) receptors 
were present on the T cell. 
Interpretation: These results support a model in which antigen-specific T cell stimulation by PND APCs triggers 
IFNc, followed by CXCL10 production and further lymphocyte recruitment, suggesting that treatments targeting 
T cells or CXCL10 in the central nervous system (CNS) may interrupt a destructive positive feedback loop present in 
CNS inflammation. </p>

<p>ANN NEUROL 2015;78:619-629 </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>araneoplastic neurologic disorders (PND) are charac-
terized by an immune response against a neuronal 
antigen that is ectopically expressed by tumors outside the 
brain. This autoimmune response not only targets the 
tumor, but also the neurons that normally express the 
antigen. High-titer antibodies to the neuronal protein are 
found in both the serum and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) of 
patients with PND. 
1 However, antibodies are unlikely to </p>

<p>be the sole cause of the neuronal destruction for those 
PNDs in which the target antigens are intracellular. </p>

<p>2,3 </p>

<p>Moreover, PND antigen-specific CD8 
1 T cells are pres-</p>

<p>ent in the peripheral blood and CSF of patients with 
both paraneoplastic cerebellar degeneration (PCD) and 
the paraneoplastic Hu syndrome subtypes of PND. </p>

<p>4-6 </p>

<p>Our laboratory has used FK506 (tacrolimus) in the 
experimental treatment of patients with PND with the 
goal of decreasing the number of PND antigen-specific T 
cells in the brain and attempting to arrest disease progres-
sion. FK506 reduces the number of activated T cells in the 
CSF of patients with PCD. 
4 Not all PND patients </p>

<p>View this article online at wileyonlinelibrary.com. demonstrate dramatic clinical improvements with this 
treatment, 
7 perhaps in part because most patients are diag-</p>

<p>nosed and referred after the onset of the neuronal destruc-
tion that is characteristic of PND. 
1 FK506, a lipid-soluble </p>

<p>immunosuppressant used to prevent transplant rejection, </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>partitions well into the central nervous system (CNS). 
FK506 interferes with calcineurin phosphatase activity via 
FK-binding protein 12, leading to decreased activation of 
inflammatory genes regulated by the transcription factor 
NFAT, 
8-10 and thereby inhibits T cell function. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Here we examined cytokine levels in the CSF of 
PND patients before and after treatment with FK506 
after noting recurrent episodes of CSF pleocytosis follow-
ing FK506 treatments in one PCD patient, suggesting 
that recruitment of peripheral PCD antigen-specific T 
cells to the CSF resumed after treatment. Such CXCL10-
dependent recruitment of T cells into the CNS has been 
documented previously in mice infected with West Nile 
virus. In this model, neurons of infected mice generate 
CXCL10, which recruits CD8 
1 T cells into the CNS. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Cytokines and their receptors have also been proposed to 
help mediate CSF entry of peripheral T cells in multiple 
sclerosis (MS). 
12 In particular, the chemokine CXCL10 </p>

<p>is elevated in CSF during exacerbations of MS, and both 
CXCL10 and its receptor, CXCR3, are elevated in and 
colocalize with active MS lesions. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>When we examined the peripheral blood and CSF of 
8 patients for the presence of 27 cytokines, CXCL10 was 
consistently elevated in the CSF of all patients with PND. 
Remarkably, CXCL10 was the only cytokine that decreased 
after FK506 treatment in patients, and correlated with 
decreases in CSF white blood cell (WBC) counts. We inves-
tigated the potential contribution of T cells in the elevation 
of CXCL10 levels in the CSF, because both were affected by 
drug treatment. We observed that T cells and antigen-
presenting cells (APCs) produce CXCL10 in an antigen-
specific fashion and that production of this chemokine by T 
cells required expression of the interferon-c receptor 
(IFNcR) on the T cell. These observations support a model 
in which a positive feedback develops when antigen-specific 
T cells encounter APCs presenting target antigen in the 
brain, stimulating CXCL10 production, further T cell 
recruitment, and PND disease progression. Hence, targeting 
autoimmune T cells and CXCL10 together may help break 
this cycle, blocking further T cell homing to the CNS, sug-
gesting a new treatment strategy for PND and allied T cell-
mediated CNS disorders. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Patient Samples </p>

<p>Patients positive for the presence of Hu or Yo antibodies were 
enrolled in this Rockefeller University Institutional Review </p>

<p>Board-approved study at the Rockefeller University Hospital 
(RDA-572). Where noted, patients were given FK506 0.15 to 
0.3mg/kg/day in 2 divided doses to maintain plasma levels at 5 
to 20ng/ml and prednisone (60mg/day, tapered to 2.5mg/day) 
for 10 to 28 days. Whole blood and CSF samples were 
obtained before and after treatment. Peripheral blood mononu-
clear cells and plasma were isolated from peripheral blood by 
Ficoll separation. CSF WBC counts were determined at the 
Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center Hematology labora-
tory. CSF was placed on ice immediately after lumbar puncture 
and centrifuged immediately at 48C to remove cells from the 
supernatant. Cells were resuspended in culture medium or 
fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) buffer. Samples used 
for cytokine analysis were taken from the third or fourth collec-
tion tube. CSF supernatant and plasma were stored in aliquots 
at 2808C until analysis. </p>

<p>Mouse Experiments </p>

<p>Female C57BL/6 and IFNcR 
2/2 mice were obtained from Jack-</p>

<p>son Laboratory (Bar Harbor, ME) and were housed in the Rockef-
eller University specific pathogen-free animal facility. CXCL10 </p>

<p>2/2 </p>

<p>mice were obtained from the laboratory of Dr A. Luster at 
Massachusetts General Hospital. All animal procedures were per-
formed according to institutional animal care and use committee 
(IACUC)-approved animal protocols. Mice were immunized intra-
peritoneally with influenza A/PR/8 (Charles River Laboratory, 
Wilmington, MA) 2 weeks before spleens were harvested for isola-
tion of CD4 
1 and CD8 
1 T cells by MACS separation (Miltenyi </p>

<p>Biotec, Auburn, CA). Dendritic cells (DCs) were generated 
from bone marrow cells grown in RPMI/10% fetal bovine serum 
(FBS) with granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor 
(GM-CSF) from J558L cell culture supernatant. 
14 Enzyme-linked </p>

<p>immunospot (Elispot) plates (Millipore, Billerica, MA) were 
coated with and detection was performed with anti-IFNc antibody 
matched pairs (MabTech, Mariemont, OH). Spots were counted 
in a blinded fashion by Zellnet Consulting (Fort Lee, NJ). </p>

<p>Flow Cytometry </p>

<p>All antibodies were purchased from BD Biosciences/Pharmin-
gen (Franklin Lakes, NJ). Cells were resuspended in FACS 
buffer (1% FBS/1% pooled human serum in phosphate-
buffered saline) and stained with fluorochrome-conjugated anti-
bodies for 20 minutes at 48C, washed 3 times, and analyzed on 
a Becton Dickinson (Franklin Lakes, NJ) FACSCaliber. Data 
were analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">FlowJo</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">TreeStar</rs>, Ashland, OR). </p>

<p>Bead-Based Immunoassay of Cytokines </p>

<p>Samples were analyzed using the Bioplex system (BioRad, Her-
cules, CA) 27-plex human cytokine kit according to the manu-
facturer's instructions. Plasma was diluted 1:5 in the provided 
buffers, and CSF was assayed without dilution. All patient sam-
ples were analyzed in duplicate. Tissue culture supernatants 
were assayed undiluted and at 1:10. Human cytokines tested 
were: IL-2, IL-4, IL-6, IL-8, IL-10, GM-CSF, IFNc, TNFa, 
IL-1b, IL-5, IL-7, IL-12(p70), IL-13, IL-17, G-CSF, MCP-1, 
MIP-1b, IL-1ra, IL-9, IL-15, eotaxin, FGF-basic, IP-10 </p>

<p>ANNALS of Neurology </p>

<p>620 
Volume 78, No. 4 </p>

<p>(CXCL10), MIP-1a, PDGF-bb, RANTES, and VEGF. CSF 
CXCL10 levels were initially quantified by bead array, and con-
firmed by human CXCL10 enzyme-linked immunosorbent 
assay (ELISA). </p>

<p>ELISA </p>

<p>CSF samples and tissue culture supernatants were tested for the 
presence of mouse IFNc and IL-17 and human and mouse 
CXCL10 using ELISA kits according to the manufacturer's 
instructions (R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN). </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>Cytokine levels before and after FK506 treatment and the per-
centage of CXCR3 
1 cells before and after FK506 were compared </p>

<p>using the Wilcoxon matched pairs signed rank test, with p &lt; 0.05 
considered significant. Percentages of CXCR3 
1 cells in blood </p>

<p>and CSF were compared using an unpaired, 2-tailed t test assum-
ing unequal variances, with p &lt; 0.05 considered significant. </p>

<p>Declaration of Patient and Animal Study 
Approvals </p>

<p>The patient studies were approved by the Rockefeller University 
Institutional Review Board and were conducted at the Rockefel-
ler University Hospital. Written, informed consent was obtained 
from all patients before they enrolled in the study (RDA-572). 
All experiments involving animals were conducted according to 
a Rockefeller University IACUC-approved animal protocol and 
in accordance with the United States Public Health Service's 
Policy on the Humane Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>CXCL10 Is Elevated in the CSF of Patients with 
PND 
We screened CSF samples from 8 patients with PND for 
the presence of 27 cytokines both before and after FK506 
treatment using a multiplex bead-based assay. Patient char-
acteristics are outlined in Table 1. This initial bead-based 
screen showed high pretreatment levels of CSF CXCL10 in 
these patients, so we confirmed this finding by quantifying 
CSF CXCL10 by ELISA. As shown in Figure 1A (dark 
bars), all patients with PND had elevated levels of CXCL10 
(average 5 2,054 pg/ml, range 5 347-6,846 pg/ml). The 
CSF CXCL10 levels in our patients were similar to or in 
some cases higher than those reported previously in the liter-
ature for MS patients and were also higher than values seen 
in normal CSF. 
15 Although CSF CXCL10 elevation has </p>

<p>been reported in other disease states, 
16-18 this is the first </p>

<p>report to our knowledge that PND patients have elevated 
CSF CXCL10. CCL2 was also detected in PND patient 
CSF pretreatment, but levels were comparable to those 
reported for normal individuals (data not shown). Four of 8 
PND patients had a &lt;2-fold increase in pretreatment CSF 
CXCL8 compared to controls (data not shown). Other cyto-</p>

<p>kines tested were either not present or were below the limit 
of detection of the assay (listed in Materials and Methods). 
We also measured cytokine and chemokine levels in 
these patients after FK506 treatment. Remarkably, CXCL10 
was the only CSF cytokine measured that was consistently 
and significantly changed after treatment with FK506 (Fig 
1A, dark bars vs light bars, average fold decrease 5 4.56; 
p 5 0.011). CCL2 and CXCL8 were not significantly 
altered by the treatment (average fold decrease 5 1.3, 
p 5 0.401 for CCL2; average fold decrease 5 0.88, 
p 5 0.207 for CXCL8 before vs after, data not shown). Of 
note, IL-17, which is an important autoimmune cytokine in 
experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (EAE) mouse 
models of MS, was not detected in the CSF of our patients 
(data not shown). However, we cannot rule out the possibil-
ity that IL-17 might be bound to cell receptors or is other-
wise inaccessible to our assay. 
We studied the inflammatory response of one 
patient with Yo antibody-positive PCD (previously 
described in detail 
7 ; see Fig 1B) over time. This patient </p>

<p>was initially seen with relatively mild symptoms of cere-
bellar dysfunction that had been acutely worsening, and 
was treated with FK506 for 14 days, with subsequent 
clinical stabilization. After experiencing periods of symp-
tom stability lasting from weeks to several months, she 
repeatedly developed episodes of acute symptom exacer-
bation. During the first two of these episodes, CSF was 
obtained prior to and following treatment. Analysis of 
her CSF revealed that during each clinical exacerbation 
the patient demonstrated a CSF pleocytosis that was 
reduced to normal or near-normal levels following 
FK506 treatment, which paralleled the reduction in 
CXCL10 levels in her CSF (see Fig 1C). This repeated 
elevation in CSF WBC suggested that after their elimina-
tion from the CSF, peripheral T cells were regaining 
access to the CNS. </p>

<p>CXCR3 
1 T Cells Are Enriched in the CSF of 
PND Patients Compared to Peripheral Blood 
CXCL10 is an IFNc inducible cytokine that stimulates the 
production and infiltration of inflammatory T cells and 
other cells expressing the CXCR3 receptor into inflamed 
sites. 
19 PND patients typically have abnormally high num-</p>

<p>bers of WBCs in their CSF. 
1 Hence, we examined CSF of </p>

<p>PND patients for the presence of CXCR3 
1 T cells. As has </p>

<p>been reported in MS patients, 
13 we observed enrichment </p>

<p>of CXCR3 
1 T cells in PND CSF when compared to the </p>

<p>peripheral blood CXCR3 
1 T cell population (Fig 2). This </p>

<p>population was enriched nearly 3-fold for CD8 
1 T cells </p>

<p>and 4-fold for CD4 
1 T cells for CXCR3, relative to </p>

<p>peripheral blood T cells. Furthermore, the number of 
CXCR3 
1 T cells decreased after FK506 treatment in all 3 </p>

<p>Roberts et al: CXCL10 Feedback Loop </p>

<p>October 2015 </p>

<p>
TABLE 1. Paraneoplastic Neurologic Disorder Patient Characteristics </p>

<p>Patient ID Age, </p>

<p>yr 
Antibody Tumor </p>

<p>Type </p>

<p>Neurological 
Symptoms </p>

<p>Time from 
Diagnosis, months 
CSF WBC/ll CSF Total Cells </p>

<p>Seen (maximum 
of 100) </p>

<p>CSF Lymphocytes 
(subset of total 
cells seen) </p>

<p>CSF 
RBC/ll </p>

<p>0312 </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>Yo </p>

<p>Ovarian </p>

<p>Cerebellar/brainstem </p>

<p>syndrome </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>0611 </p>

<p>73 </p>

<p>Hu </p>

<p>SCLC 
Sensory neuropathy </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>88 </p>

<p>None seen </p>

<p>0304 </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>Yo </p>

<p>Ovarian </p>

<p>PCD </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>None seen </p>

<p>None seen </p>

<p>None seen </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0308 </p>

<p>61 </p>

<p>Hu </p>

<p>SCLC 
Peripheral neuropathy/ 
pancerebellar syndrome </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>82 </p>

<p>72 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0508 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>Yo </p>

<p>Unknown 
primary </p>

<p>PCD </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>94 </p>

<p>None seen </p>

<p>0603 </p>

<p>74 </p>

<p>Yo </p>

<p>Ovarian and 
breast 
PCD, sensory and 
motor neuropathy </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>0318 </p>

<p>59 </p>

<p>Yo </p>

<p>Ovarian </p>

<p>PCD </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0615 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>Yo </p>

<p>Ovarian </p>

<p>PCD </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>87 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>CSF 5 
cerebrospinal fluid; PCD 5 
paraneoplastic cerebellar degeneration; RBC 5 </p>

<p>red blood cells; SCLC 5 
small cell lung cancer; WBC 5 </p>

<p>white blood cells. </p>

<p>ANNALS of Neurology </p>

<p>622 
Volume 78, No. 4 </p>

<p>patients for whom these data were available, ranging from 
a nearly 2-fold decrease in one patient to a &gt;7-fold reduc-
tion in another (Table 2). These results suggest that there 
may be a role for a specific inflammatory pathway in 
patients with PND involving the cytokine CXCL10 and 
its receptor CXCR3 on T cells. </p>

<p>T Cells from Normal Donors Produce CXCL10 in 
an Antigen-Specific Manner 
Based on the parallel decreases in patient CSF T cells 
and CXCL10 after FK506 treatment, we sought to deter-
mine whether T cells could produce CXCL10 and thus 
implicate them in production of the CXCL10 detected </p>

<p>FIGURE 1: CXCL10 is elevated in paraneoplastic neurologic disorder (PND) patient cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) and is decreased 
after FK506 treatment. (A) Levels of CXCL10 in the CSF of 8 PND patients with the Hu syndrome or paraneoplastic cerebellar 
degeneration (PCD) before and after FK506 treatment, as determined by CXCL10 ELISA. Bars represent the average of 
duplicate wells. p 5 0.011 for patients with PND pre-versus post-treatment by Wilcoxon signed rank test with p &lt; 0.05 consid-
ered significant, indicating a decrease in CXCL10 with treatment. (B) Western blot of serum from PCD patient PCD0615 recog-
nizing cdr2 (50kD). (C) CSF white blood cell (WBC) counts and CXCL10 levels over time in PND patient PCD0615, who was 
treated with repeated courses of FK506. Arrows indicate treatment periods. </p>

<p>Roberts et al: CXCL10 Feedback Loop </p>

<p>October 2015 </p>

<p>
in the PND patient CSF. Previous work by our labora-
tory has shown that peripheral CD8 
1 T cells specific for </p>

<p>the HuD PND antigen express CXCL10. 
6 Due to insuf-</p>

<p>ficient patient CSF T cells available for direct study, we 
modeled this question by assessing CXCL10 production 
from normal donor T cells upon encounter with specific 
antigen presented by DCs as APCs. CD4 
1 or CD8 
1 T </p>

<p>cells were cocultured with DCs loaded with apoptotic 
influenza-infected 3T3 cells (for CD4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>) or DCs directly 
infected with influenza virus (for CD8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>). Analysis of </p>

<p>supernatants from the cultures revealed that CXCL10 
was only produced after a cognate CD4 
1 or CD8 
1 T </p>

<p>cell-DC interaction (Fig 3A). CXCL10 secretion was 
coincident with IFNc production, which was measured 
as a positive control (Fig 3B). These data indicate that 
CXCL10 is produced after an interaction between 
antigen-specific T cells and an APC but not after non-
cognate interactions. </p>

<p>Production of CXCL10 in Mouse T Cell and DC 
Cocultures Is Antigen Specific and Requires the 
IFNcR on the T Cell 
To assess whether these antigen-specific interactions led to 
CXCL10 production by T cells only, APCs only, or both 
cell types, we employed an assay similar to the human cell 
assay just described, but instead using cells from wild-type 
or CXCL10 null mice (Fig 4 A-D). T cells from influenza-
immunized mice were cocultured with DCs pulsed with rel-
evant influenza nucleoprotein peptide or an irrelevant con-
trol peptide. Production of CXCL10 in wild-type 
conditions was found to be antigen-specific and paralleled 
production of IFNc, as was seen with human T cells. Simi-
lar results were obtained using T cells from ovalbumin-
immunized mice (not shown). When influenza-specific 
CXCL10 
2/2 CD4 
1 or CD8 
1 T cells were cocultured with </p>

<p>wild-type DCs presenting antigen, the number of IFNc-
producing cells present was similar to the number of IFNc-
producing cells in the wild-type T cell condition. However, 
when CXCL10 
2/2 T cells were cocultured with wild-type </p>

<p>DCs, 3-fold less CXCL10 was detected. In comparison, no 
CXCL10 was detected when CXCL10 
2/2 T cells were </p>

<p>cocultured with CXCL10 
2/2 DC. Similar data were </p>

<p>obtained using T cells from ovalbumin protein-immunized 
rather than virus-immunized CXCL10 
2/2 mice (data not </p>

<p>shown). Taken together, these results indicate that T cells 
produce the majority of CXCL10 in this assay and that they 
do so in an antigen-specific manner. DCs themselves also 
contribute to the production of CXCL10 after encounter 
with a cognate T cell in this assay, because a low level of 
CXCL10 is still present in the CXCL10 
2/2 T cells plus </p>

<p>wild-type DC condition. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Enrichment of CXCR3 
1 T cells in paraneoplastic 
neurologic disorder (PND) patient cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). 
(A) Flow cytometry analysis of PND patient cells showing 
CXCR3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD4 
1 T cells (top panels) and CXCR3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>CD8 
1 T cells 
(bottom panels) in CSF and peripheral blood. (B) Percentage 
of CD3 
1 /CXCR3 
1 T cells in CSF and peripheral blood from 
individual PND patients. Percentage of CSF CD3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>/CXCR3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>cells mean 5 73; percentage of peripheral blood CD3 
1 / 
CXCR3 
1 cells mean 5 20.4. A t test assuming unequal 
variance was applied to the data with p &lt; 0.05 considered 
significant. p 5 2e10 
28 for CSF versus peripheral blood 
CXCR3 
1 cells. </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Number of CSF CXCR3 
1 T Cells per 
Microliter </p>

<p>Patient 
Pre-FK506 
Post-FK506 </p>

<p>Hu0308 
1.57 
0.83 </p>

<p>PCD0318 
2.25 
0.75 </p>

<p>PCD0615 
35.19 
4.68 </p>

<p>ANNALS of Neurology </p>

<p>624 
Volume 78, No. 4 </p>

<p>DC production of CXCL10 in an antigen-specific 
manner suggests the presence of a signal from T cells 
that have encountered their cognate antigen to the DC 
upon which the antigen is presented. One possible medi-
ator of such a signal from the T cells is IFNc, because 
CXCL10 is known to be IFNc inducible 
20 and both </p>

<p>cytokines were produced in an antigen-specific manner 
in our cocultures. To address this possibility, we assessed 
CXCL10 production following antigen-specific T cell-
DC interactions using cells from mice lacking 
the receptor for IFNc (IFNcR 
2/2 ). Both IFNc and </p>

<p>CXCL10 were produced when wild-type T cells encoun-
tered DCs presenting influenza antigen. However, when 
IFNcR 
2/2 T cells encountered wild-type DCs presenting </p>

<p>influenza antigen, CXCL10 was not detected despite 
detection of expected levels of IFNc (Fig 4E, F). These 
data support the idea that the IFNcR is required on the 
T cell for antigen-specific CXCL10 production. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Our study began with a remarkable observation of a high 
CXCL10 concentration in the CSF of an acutely ill PCD 
patient that was decreased dramatically after treatment </p>

<p>with the immunosuppressive drug FK506. A second 
course of FK506 treatment in the same patient resulted 
in a similar decrease in CSF CXCL10 (Fig 1C). We sub-
sequently found that CXCL10 was decreased after 
FK506 treatment in 7 other PND patients (Fig 1A, 
p 5 0.011). Importantly, 2 other chemokines also present 
in the CSF, CCL2 and CXCL8, were unaffected by the 
drug treatment in the same patients (p 5 0.401 and 
p 5 0.207, respectively). Moreover, the levels of 24 other 
cytokines (listed in Materials and Methods) were either 
undetectable or very similar to normal CSF, and were 
unaffected by FK506 treatment. The specificity of the 
effect of immunosuppressive therapy suggested a strong 
and potentially clinically relevant link to CNS inflamma-
tion in these patients that was pursued to discover a spe-
cific positive feedback loop. In this model (Fig 5), 
antigen-specific T cell stimulation by APCs within the 
CNS triggers T cell IFNc production, followed by 
CXCL10 secretion by both T cells and APCs, leading to 
further lymphocyte recruitment to the area of 
inflammation. 
Many cell types in the brain are able to produce 
CXCL10, such as MS patient astrocytes, 
13 neurons, </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>and microglia. 
22 In addition, a correlation between CSF </p>

<p>CXCL10 levels and CSF leukocyte count has previously 
been observed in MS. 
15 Here, we hypothesized that a </p>

<p>key source of CXCL10 in PND patient CSF might be 
T cells, given that both T cells and CXCL10 were 
elevated in CSF from PND patients (see Table 1 and 
Fig 1), and that we have previously seen CSF PND 
antigen-specific T cell responses in these patients. 
5,6,23 In </p>

<p>support of this idea, we found that CXCL10 can be 
produced by both human and mouse T cells, and that 
this production occurs specifically upon encounter with 
cognate antigen (Figs 3 and 4). 
Interestingly, when we used CXCL10 
2/2 T cells in </p>

<p>this assay we found that a low level of CXCL10 produc-
tion persisted in response to antigen, and we attribute 
this production to the APCs (Fig 4A, B). This result sup-
ports the possibility that the APCs are receiving antigen-
specific signals from the T cells during their interaction, 
inducing them to elaborate the same chemokine, a 
potential component of the positive feedback loop (Fig 
5) that would be location specific. The additional release 
of CXCL10 would further increase recruitment of T cells 
to the local area. A recently published study demon-
strated that CXCL10 production by DC is important in 
DC-T cell interactions during priming of T cells in the 
lymph node. 
24 It is possible that CXCL10 production by </p>

<p>APCs is similarly important for reactivation and further 
recruitment of memory T cells in the brain in PND, and </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: CXCL10 is produced in an antigen (Ag)-specific 
fashion in cultures of human T cells and dendritic cells (DCs) 
from normal donors. (A) CXCL10 was measured by ELISA in 
supernatants from cocultures of CD8 
1 or CD4 
1 T cells and 
DCs presenting influenza antigen (Flu) or uninfected DCs 
(neg). (B) Interferon-c (IFNc) Elispot assay of normal donor 
CD8 
1 and CD4 
1 T cells cultured with DCs presenting 
influenza antigen, performed in parallel with the experiment 
in A. Error bars represent standard deviation from the mean 
of triplicate wells for each condition. </p>

<p>Roberts et al: CXCL10 Feedback Loop </p>

<p>October 2015 </p>

<p>
that CXCL10 production by responding T cells augments 
the response. 
It has been shown previously that microglia are able 
to produce CXCL10 and express its receptor CXCR3. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Our observation of CXCL10 production by antigen-
specific T cells uncovers a new, potentially clinically rele-
vant dimension to T cell inflammation in the brain. It 
has been shown previously that CXCL10-deficient mice </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: T cell interferon-c (IFNc) receptor is required for antigen (Ag)-specific production of CXCL10 in cocultures of T cells and 
dendritic cells (DCs). (A-D) CXCL10 (A, B) and IFNc (C, D) were measured in cocultures of T cells from influenza-immunized 
CXCL10 
2/2 or wild-type (wt) C57BL/6 mice with DC from CXCL10 
2/2 or wild type mice. For CD8 
1 cocultures (A, C), DCs were pulsed 
with influenza nucleoprotein peptide (Flu) or ovalbumin peptide control (neg). For CD4 
1 cocultures (B, D), DCs were fed apoptotic 
influenza-infected 3T3 cells (Flu) or uninfected 3T3 cells (neg). (E) CXCL10 measured in cocultures set up as in A, using T cells from 
influenza-immunized IFNcR 
2/2 mice. (F) IFNc production was determined in parallel. Each experiment was repeated at least 3 times 
with similar results. CXCL10 in coculture supernatants was measured by ELISA and IFNg secretion was measured by Elispot. </p>

<p>ANNALS of Neurology </p>

<p>626 
Volume 78, No. 4 </p>

<p>infected with mouse hepatitis virus show decreased 
migration of effector T cells to the brain. 
19 In light of </p>

<p>our observation that CXCL10 production is antigen spe-
cific, and given cells capable of presenting antigen within 
the brain, 
13,26 we suggest that PND T cells encountering </p>

<p>antigen in the CNS may be the source of the high 
CXCL10 levels in CSF from patients with PND. 
A leading candidate for mediating the signal for 
CXCL10 production between the APC and the T cell 
was the IFNcR, because IFNc is known to induce 
CXCL10 secretion. 
20 When T cells lacking the IFNcR </p>

<p>were cocultured with DC, antigen-specific production of 
CXCL10 was completely obliterated, whereas IFNc pro-
duction remained unchanged (Fig 4E, F). This suggests 
that there is a T cell-intrinsic feedback loop for 
CXCL10 production, and that the low level of CXCL10 
produced by the DCs may require the IFNcR-mediated 
T cell feedback loop as well (Fig 5). CXCL10 and the 
CXCR3 receptor have been proposed to work in an 
inflammation-promoting loop in allergy 
27 and to modu-</p>

<p>late IFNc production in EAE. 
28 CXCR3 has been sug-</p>

<p>gested not only to play a role in T cell priming in the 
lymph node 
24 but also in the recruitment of T cells into </p>

<p>peripheral target tissues. 
29 Taken together, these data sug-</p>

<p>gest that the high concentration of CXCL10 present in 
PND patient CSF may be due to production of this che-
mokine by infiltrating autoimmune T cells interacting 
with APCs in the CNS. 
30 However, EAE can be induced </p>

<p>in CXCL10 
2/2 mice, indicating that this chemokine is </p>

<p>not essential for the development of this MS-like disease 
in mice. </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>It is important to note that previous in vivo studies 
of the inflammatory response to CNS virus infection and 
chronic EAE have demonstrated that astrocytes are a 
major source of CXCL10. 
13,31,32 Our observations of </p>

<p>CXCL10 production by DCs and T cells in an antigen-
specific in vitro system do not rule out the possible addi-
tional production of CXCL10 by astrocytes or other cells 
in patients with PND. It may even be that one cell type 
is responsible for CXCL10 production early during 
disease initiation, and other cell types such as T cells and 
APCs participate in CXCL10 production to propagate 
the disease state. This could lead to recruitment of addi-
tional T cells into the CNS in general or into the 
parenchyma. 
In a clinical study, 10 of 16 of our PND patients 
treated with FK506 showed improvement of their symp-
toms, 
7 which when combined with observed decreases in </p>

<p>CSF WBC count and CXCL10 levels reported here, sug-
gests that this treatment strategy warrants further study, 
particularly if used early in the disease. In addition, the 
specific mechanism by which FK506 decreases CXCL10 
in PND patient CSF is of interest. Although the inhibi-
tion of calcineurin activity in T cells is a known effect of 
FK506, additional intracellular targets such as p38 and 
c-Jun N-terminal kinase have been suggested. 
33 Interest-</p>

<p>ingly, our laboratory has recently shown that FK506 
preferentially accumulates in DCs, thereby targeting T 
cells engaged in antigen-specific T cell-APC interac-
tions. 
34 It is possible that FK506 may similarly act upon </p>

<p>APCs in the brain. Inhibition of the EAE animal model 
of MS has been observed with FK506 treatment. 
35,36 It </p>

<p>would be interesting to determine whether treatment of 
EAE or MS patients with FK506 decreases CXCL10 lev-
els in a fashion similar to that shown in our PND 
patients. A limitation of our study is that patients were 
treated with both FK506 and a tapered prednisone dose. 
Thus, it is possible that some of the effect of treatment 
on CSF CXCL10 may be due to prednisone. However, 
based on studies by others, 
37,38 it is reasonable to expect </p>

<p>FK506 to be responsible for most or all of the effect. 
In conclusion, we have shown a significant effect of 
FK506 immunosuppressive therapy on the important 
inflammatory chemokine CXCL10 in patients with 
PND. As elevated levels of CXCL10 are also found in 
other autoimmune neurological disorders, the presence of 
this chemokine in inflammatory CSF is significant and 
may be directly involved in the autoimmune response. It 
is not known whether the arrival of T cells or peripheral 
APCs in the CNS or another process altogether is the 
initiating event for diseases such as PND. Interestingly, </p>

<p>FIGURE 5: Proposed model of the interactions leading to 
CXCL10 production by T cells and antigen-presenting cells 
(APCs). The T cell is activated by its cognate antigen pre-
sented on an APC. The T cell secretes interferon-c (IFNc) in 
response to the antigen and senses autocrine or paracrine 
IFNc via the IFNc receptor (IFNcR). The T cell and APC 
secrete CXCL10 in this antigen-specific interaction, which 
recruits additional CXCR3 
1 cells into the area. The signal 
that tells the APC to produce CXCL10 was not investigated 
in the current experiments, but may be related to expres-
sion of the IFNcR by APCs or other signals. </p>

<p>Roberts et al: CXCL10 Feedback Loop </p>

<p>October 2015 </p>

<p>
Bailey and colleagues have shown that CNS myeloid 
DCs present endogenous peptide to T cells in the brain 
to drive EAE relapses in mouse models. 
39 The mecha-</p>

<p>nism of immunosuppression and CXCL10 reduction in 
PND patients treated with FK506 may include decreased 
recruitment of T cells and/or APC from the periphery to 
the CNS, or interruption of the interaction of these two 
cell types or their intracellular signaling. Inhibition of T 
cell access to the brain might consequently slow the pro-
gression of disease, and may argue for combination ther-
apy with agents that prevent T cell access to the CNS. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>This study was supported by grants UL1RR024143 8 
and KL2TR000151 from the NIH National Center for 
Research Resources and National Center for Advancing 
Sciences to the Rockefeller University Hospital. R.B.D. is 
an Investigator of the Howard Hughes Medical Institute. 
We thank the patients with paraneoplastic neurologic 
disorders who participated in this study and their fami-
lies; the Rockefeller University Hospital staff for facilitat-
ing patient studies; Dr J. Posner for referring many of 
the patients; Dr A. Luster for kindly providing 
CXCL10 
2/2 mice; Dr C. Tu for statistics advice; and </p>

<p>members of our laboratory for many helpful discussions 
of this work. </p>

<p>Authorship </p>

<p>W.K.R. designed and performed the experiments, ana-
lyzed the data, and wrote the manuscript. N.E.B. helped 
with designing and performing mouse experiments, data 
analysis, and writing the manuscript. M.O.F. recruited, 
enrolled, and followed patients in the study, obtained 
patient samples, and helped with patient data analysis 
and writing the manuscript. A.D. recruited, enrolled, and 
followed patients in the study, obtained patient samples, 
and edited the manuscript. R.M.R. provided advice 
about chemokine analysis and experiments and edited 
the manuscript. R.B.D. supervised the project, helped 
with the design of experiments and data analysis, fol-
lowed patients in the study, and wrote the manuscript. </p>

<p>Potential Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>R.M.R.: employment, Biogen. </p>



<p>ANNALS of Neurology </p>

<p>628 
Volume 78, No. 4 </p>



<p>Roberts et al: CXCL10 Feedback Loop </p>

<p>October 2015 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>