<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4822213" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>a b s t r a c t </p>

<p>We developed a novel PCR-based pre-amplification (PreAmp) technology that can increase the abun-
dance of over 350 target genes one million-fold. To assess potential bias introduced by PreAmp we utilized 
ERCC RNA reference standards, a model system that quantifies measurement error in RNA analysis. We 
assessed three types of bias: amplification bias, dynamic range bias and fold-change bias. We show that 
our PreAmp workflow introduces only minimal amplification and fold-change bias under stringent condi-
tions. We do detect dynamic range bias if a target gene is highly abundant and PreAmp occurred for 16 or 
more PCR cycles; however, this type of bias is easily correctable. To assess PreAmp bias in a gene expres-
sion profiling experiment, we analyzed a panel of genes that are regulated during differentiation using 
the NTera2 stem cell model system. We find that results generated using PreAmp are similar to results 
obtained using standard qPCR (without the pre-amplification step). Importantly, PreAmp maintains pat-
terns of gene expression changes across samples; the same biological insights would be derived from 
a PreAmp experiment as with a standard gene expression profiling experiment. We conclude that our 
PreAmp technology can facilitate analysis of extremely limited samples in gene expression quantification 
experiments. 
Pre-amplification (PreAmp) of nucleic acid is a powerful tech-
nique that allows for the analysis of large numbers of target genes 
from limiting samples. PreAmp can be achieved through whole 
transcriptome amplification [1] or at the level of targeted gene 
panels using PCR-based methodology [2,3]. However, there is a 
legitimate concern that PreAmp might change a sample to an extent 
that results generated from it are misleading or inaccurate. Better 
understanding of the limitations of a PreAmp-based workflow is 
necessary to ensure the reliability of research results. 
To address such concerns, the National Institute of Standards 
and Technology (NIST), in conjunction with the External RNA con-
trols consortium (ERCC) developed a set of reference standards to 
evaluate the performance of RNA quantification systems and work-</p>

<p>Abbreviations: PreAmp, pre-amplification; ERCC, external RNA controls con-
sortium; NIST, National Institute of Standards and Technology; NT2, NTera2; RA, 
retinoic acid. 
 *  Corresponding author. </p>

<p>E-mail addresses: steven okino@bio-rad.com (S.T. Okino), 
michelle kong@bio-rad.com (M. Kong), haya sarras@bio-rad.com (H. Sarras), 
yan wang@bio-rad.com (Y. Wang). </p>

<p>flows [4,5]. The ERCC standards are mixtures of up to 96 synthetic 
RNAs that are spiked into an RNA sample and processed and quanti-
fied along with the natural RNAs. The amount of each ERCC RNA in a 
mixture is precisely defined; the performance of an RNA quantifica-
tion workflow/platform is determined by comparing the measured 
amount with the actual, defined amount of each ERCC control RNA. 
In addition, by spiking two sets of ERCC standards (with defined 
ratios of each ERCC target) into two different biological samples, 
the accuracy in quantifying gene expression differences between 
samples can be determined. ERCC standards have been used to 
assess qPCR, digital PCR, microfluidic qPCR, microarray and RNA-
seq platforms for their precision, accuracy and detection limits in 
RNA quantification [6-10]. 
There are two fundamental challenges in PreAmp reactions 
because multiple targets are amplified simultaneously. The first 
challenge is increasing the capacity of the amplification reaction 
to allow targets of vastly different starting quantity to be effi-
ciently amplified through every PCR cycle. The second challenge 
is maintaining target amplification specificity in the presence of 
large numbers of primers. Unless both challenges are addressed in a 
PreAmp reagent, the probability of having biased pre-amplification 
will be high. We developed a PreAmp reagent that utilizes an engi-
neered DNA polymerase with improved binding affinity to DNA </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bdq.2015.12.001 
2214-7535/© 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/ 
4.0/). </p>



<p>S.T. Okino et al. / Biomolecular Detection and Quantification 6 (2016) 13-21 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Fold-change bias of ERCC standards. ExFold spike in-mixtures were added to 10 ng NT2 RNA, reverse transcribed and pre-amplified for 14 PCR cycles. ERCC targets 
were quantified by qPCR using three technical replicates, the experiment was performed one time. Fold-change measurements for each ERCC target are plotted against target 
abundance. Results show the measured difference, between samples, of the amount of each ERCC target (colored circles) and the actual difference that should be detected 
(Fig. 1A-C; colored lines at 1.0, 0.585, 0 and −2.0 Cq units representing RNA abundance ratios of 2-1, 1.5-1, 1-1 and 1-4 respectively). (A) Analysis of samples that were not 
pre-amplified. (B) Analysis of samples in which 88 ERCC targets were pre-amplified. (C) Analysis of samples in which 355 targets were pre-amplified. (D) Overall fold-change 
bias for 88 ERCC targets. No PreAmp samples (red circles), 88-plex PreAmp samples (yellow circles), 355-plex PreAmp samples (blue circles). </p>

<p>S.T. Okino et al. / Biomolecular Detection and Quantification 6 (2016) 13-21 </p>



<p>Fig. 2. Fold-change bias of native target genes with limited sample. cDNA derived from NT2 cells treated with RA for 0-7 days were pre-amplified for 10 PCR cycles and used 
to quantify native target genes by qPCR; 100 pg, 1 ng and 10 ng cDNA was used in the PreAmp reactions. 1 g cDNA that was not pre-amplified was also used to quantify target 
gene expression by standard qPCR (10 ng per target). The level of expression of each target gene was determined and expressed as "RNA copies per cell" after normalizing 
with TBP and assuming that there are 10 TBP copies per cell. The experiment was performed three times, each with two technical replicates, the average values are reported. 
Error bars represent standard deviation. Data for selected target genes that show RA-induced changes are shown. </p>

<p>and, consequently, dramatically increased processivity. This results 
in improved PreAmp reaction capacity which ensures that all tar-
gets are efficiently amplified [11]. We also focused our PreAmp 
reagent formulation efforts to mediate extremely stringent speci-
ficity of primer annealing. 
To provide a stringent assessment of our new PreAmp reagent, 
we used the ERCC controls to quantify bias in a gene expression pro-
filing experiment involving stem cell differentiation. We then used 
the ERCC information to discriminate regulated genes from back-
ground noise. Our findings, from analysis of ERCC standards and 
natural target genes, demonstrate that our novel PreAmp reagent 
will provide accurate results in gene expression profiling experi-
ments. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Cell culture and sample processing </p>

<p>NTera2 cells (NT2) were obtained from the American Type Cul-
ture Collection (Manassas, VA) and cultured as directed. To induce 
differentiation, cells were treated with 10 M all-trans-Retinoic 
acid (Cat# R2625, Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis MO) for 0, 1, 2, 3, 4 
or 7 days. RNA was isolated using the Aurum Total RNA Mini Kit 
which incorporates an on-column genomic DNA clearance step 
(Cat# 7326820, Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA), quantified 
with a NanoDrop ND-1000 spectrophotometer (Thermo Fischer 
Scientific, Waltham, MA) and stored at −80 • C. ERCC ExFold RNA 
Spike-in Mixes (Cat# 4456739, Thermo Fischer Scientific, Waltham, 
MA) were diluted and spiked into RNA samples which were then 
reverse transcribed using iScript Reverse Transcription Supermix 
as directed by the manufacturer (Cat# 1708849, Bio-Rad Laborato-
ries, Hercules, CA) to make stock cDNA samples which were stored </p>

<p>at −20 • C. Stock cDNA samples were pre-amplified for 10-20 cycles 
using SsoAdvanced PreAmp Supermix as directed by the manufac-
turer (Cat# 1725160, Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA) diluted 
at least 5-fold and stored at −20 • C. PreAmp was performed with 
panels of assays which include PrimePCR PreAmp assays (Bio-Rad 
Laboratories, Hercules, CA), assays culled from public databases, 
assays designed using online software tools and assays from pub-
lished manuscripts (Supplemental Fig. 1); primers were at a final 
concentration of 50 nM each. Target genes were quantified by qPCR 
using SsoAdvanced Universal SYBR Green Supermix (Cat# 1725270, 
Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA) and CFX96 or CFX384 Real-
Time PCR Detection Systems (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA) 
using 20 l or 10 l reaction volumes respectively. Genomic DNA 
contamination was assessed using the PrimePCR DNA Contamina-
tion Control (Cat# 10025352, Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA). 
As a no-PreAmp control, stock cDNA was used to quantify gene tar-
gets directly by standard qPCR using SsoAdvanced Universal SYBR 
Green Supermix. qPCR conditions were: 98 • C for 2 min; 40 cycles 
of (98 • C, 5 s; 60 • C, 30 s); melt curve analysis, 65-98 • C, 0.5 • C incre-
ments, 5 s hold. <rs id="software-1" type="software">CFX Manager</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">3.1</rs> was used for qPCR analysis 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Bio-Rad Laboratories</rs>, Hercules, CA). A synthetic DNA interplate 
calibrator was used to set the Cq baseline. </p>

<p>2.2. Measurement of fold-change bias </p>

<p>The two ERCC ExFold RNA Spike-in mixes contain in-vitro tran-
scribed RNA transcripts in 4 sub-pools that have set ratios between 
the mixes (1:1, 1:1.5, 1:2 and 4:1). To quantify fold-change bias, 
ExFold mixes were spiked into RNA samples and processed as 
described above; the amount of each ERCC target in each sample 
was then determined by qPCR. The 1:1 sub-pool was used as a cal-
ibrator to normalize the Mix 1 and Mix 2 results. To visualize bias </p>



<p>S.T. Okino et al. / Biomolecular Detection and Quantification 6 (2016) 13-21 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Effect of sample input. Titrating amounts of NT2 cDNA, from 10 pg to 1 g, were pre-amplified for 12 PCR cycles; natural target genes encompassing a wide expression 
range were quantified by qPCR using three technical replicates, the experiment was performed one time. Results show the relationship between sample input and target 
gene abundance (Cq). </p>

<p>the Cq value between the Mix 1 and Mix 2 samples was deter-
mined for each target and plotted against the average no PreAmp Cq 
value. Fold-change bias was calculated as the difference between 
the observed Cq and the theoretical Cq for each ERCC target. The 
theoretical Cq is 0, 0.585, 1.0 and 2.0 for the 1:1, 1:1.5, 1:2 and 
4:1 sub-pools, respectively. Variation in fold-change measurement 
error was calculated using the equivalence test from <rs id="software-2" type="software">JMP</rs> statisti-
cal software version <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">12.1.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SAS</rs>, Cary, NC), the practical difference 
threshold was specified as the standard deviation of the no PreAmp 
fold change measurement error. </p>

<p>2.3. Limits-of-detection of fold-change measurement </p>

<p>Fold-change bias 95% confidence intervals were determined 
using Microsoft Excel 2010 for the 
Cq values illustrated in 
Fig. 1B and rounded-up to the closest 0.5Cq. We analyzed three 
different ranges of target abundance, average no PreAmp Cq value 
less than 30, between 30 and 32.5, and greater than 32.5. The limit 
of detection was estimated as 2-fold the 95% confidence interval. 
For example, if the fold-change 95% confidence interval for targets 
between 30 and 32.5 was calculated as 1.0Cq, then 2-fold this value 
is 2.0Cq, which represents a 4-fold change. Therefore, targets with 
a no PreAmp Cq value between 30 and 32.5 have a 4-fold change 
limit of detection. </p>

<p>2.4. Measurement of amplification bias </p>

<p>Analysis of the stock cDNA samples by PreAmp and by stan-
dard qPCR was performed three times independently. PreAmp 
amplification bias was calculated as "Amplification bias = (Cq Tar-
get (no-PreAmp) − Cq Target (PreAmp) ) − 7.03" where 7.03 is a constant 
derived from 14 PreAmp cycles and 5-fold sample dilution, which 
reflects the theoretical Cq between the no-PreAmp and PreAmp 
target gene Cq values if PreAmp is 100% efficient; a PreAmp bias 
score of 0 indicates that target gene PreAmp is 100% efficient. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Analysis of fold-change bias using ERCC controls </p>

<p>To assess bias introduced by PreAmp we used the ERCC ExFold 
RNA spike-in control product; this product consists of two tubes 
that contain the same ERCC RNAs at precisely defined amounts 
and ratios. Analysis of the ERCC standards spiked into two differ-
ent biological samples reveals the ability of a workflow to quantify 
differences between samples [10]. We added the ExFold mixtures 
to two RNA samples and converted them to cDNA. We then pre-
amplified the cDNA samples for 14 cycles using PreAmp primer 
panels targeting either 88 ERCC RNAs only (88-plex PreAmp) or the </p>

<p>S.T. Okino et al. / Biomolecular Detection and Quantification 6 (2016) 13-21 </p>



<p>Fig. 4. Dynamic range bias. ExFold spike in-mixtures were added to 10 ng NT2 RNA, reverse transcribed and pre-amplified for 10-20 PCR cycles; ERCC targets were quantified 
by qPCR using two technical replicates, the experiment was performed one time. (A) The measured amount of ERCC target gene is plotted as a function of actual RNA abundance. 
All ERCC targets can be detected in the no PreAmp sample and in the samples processed for 14 PreAmp cycles. For samples processed for 20 PreAmp cycles, quantification 
of targets in the 1 million copy range, have a Cq value less than 5 and are of unreliable value. (B) qPCR results for ERCC-00144, which contained 5,513 copies in the PreAmp 
reaction, show good results over the entire amplification range. (C) qPCR results for ERCC-00074, which contained 2,822,879 copies in the PreAmp reaction, show poor results 
when amplified for 18 or 20 PCR cycles. </p>



<p>S.T. Okino et al. / Biomolecular Detection and Quantification 6 (2016) 13-21 </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Amplification bias. ExFold spike-in mixture 1 was added to 10 ng NT2 RNA, reverse transcribed and pre-amplified for 14 PCR cycles in a 355-plex PreAmp reaction. All 
355 targets were quantified by qPCR using two technical replicates, the experiment was performed one time. Amplification bias was determined and plotted against target 
gene expression. </p>

<p>ERCC RNAs plus an additional 267 target genes (355-plex PreAmp, 
see Supplemental Table 1 for gene targets and assay information). 
We then quantified each ERCC transcript in the PreAmp'd samples 
as well as in the original, non-amplified cDNA samples. 
Our results show the measured difference versus the actual pre-
defined difference of each ERCC RNA spiked into the two samples 
(Fig. 1A-C). We find that fold-change measurement bias appears 
similar when comparing the no PreAmp, 88-plex PreAmp and 
355-plex PreAmp results. In Fig. 1D we show the measurement 
error in fold-change results; no measurement error would have 
a 
Cq value of 0, a 
Cq value of 1 indicates a measurement 
error of 100%. We observe that measurement error increases as 
the amount of ERCC target RNA decreases. This finding is expected 
and is consistent with stochastic partitioning of a small number 
of RNA molecules in the qPCR reactions. We then quantified the 
fold-change measurement error associated with RNA abundance 
ranges (Table 1). We find that for RNAs with moderate to high 
abundance (Cq &lt; 30) fold-change measurement error is, on average, 
only about 0.1Cq representing 7% error. For low abundance RNAs 
(Cq between 30 and 32.5) measurement error averages 20%, for 
trace RNAs (Cq &gt; 32.5) 75% average measurement error is observed. 
Importantly, a test of statistical equivalence indicates that PreAmp 
(88-plex or 355-plex) has only a slight effect on fold-change mea-
surement error relative to the no PreAmp samples (only the trace 
RNAs in the 88-plex PreAmp sample has a p-Value above the 0.05 
threshold that indicates a PreAmp bias, the p-value is 0.0515). These 
findings are consistent with a previous report [6] and demonstrates 
that our PreAmp workflow only has low fold-change bias when 
analyzing trace expression target genes. 
Our results also imply that the ability to detect a meaningful 
difference in RNA expression between two samples by RT-qPCR is 
a function of RNA abundance. Using the ERCC RNAs as an internal 
control we estimated that the limits-of-detection of fold-change 
measurement is 2-fold for moderately or highly expressed RNA tar-
gets, 4-fold for RNAs with low expression, and, at best, 8-fold for 
RNAs with trace expression (Table 1). </p>

<p>3.2. Analysis of fold-change bias using regulated genes </p>

<p>Our ERCC-based work demonstrates that even high multi-
plex PreAmp does not introduce appreciable bias to fold-change 
measurements. However, the ERCC model system is based on 
spike-in of in-vitro transcribed RNAs, not natural RNA transcripts. 
To determine if the PreAmp workflow can accurately quantify 
gene expression changes of natural targets, we analyzed RNA 
samples purified from NT2 cells, an established model system of </p>

<p>human stem cell behavior. When treated with retinoic acid (RA), 
NT2 cells differentiate into neurons [12,13]; during differentia-
tion the expression of stem cell-specific biomarkers decrease while 
the expression of neuron-specific biomarkers increase [14-17]. 
To identify genes regulated during differentiation we applied the 
fold-change limits-of-detection criteria established in the previ-
ous section (Table 1) to 267 genes involved in cell maintenance, 
cell fate and adaptation. We identified 34 regulated genes, which 
include well known stem cell biomarkers such as NANOG and neu-
ral cell biomarkers such as NEUROD1 (Table 2). Most of these genes 
were previously characterized to be involved in NT2 differentiation 
[14-17], which is confirmatory of our approach. 
We analyzed a panel of 100 genes that are involved in lineage 
determination (Supplemental Table 1). We pre-amplified and ana-
lyzed varied amounts of cDNA (100 pg, 1 ng and 10 ng) derived 
from NT2 cells treated with RA for 0, 1, 2, 3, 4 and 7 days; as a 
no-PreAmp control, 1 g cDNA was used to quantify gene targets 
directly by standard qPCR (10 ng/target, 1 g per 100 target panel). 
We show data for several representative regulated target genes, 
gene transcript levels are expressed as "RNA copies per cell" after 
normalizing with TBP and assuming that there are 10 TBP copies 
per cell [18]; this method of normalization provides information on 
the relative level of target gene expression as well as fold-change 
of RNA abundance (Fig. 2). Data presented in Supplemental Fig. 1 
shows that TBP expression is relatively stable over the time course 
of RA exposure changing less than 0.5Cq (25%), this justifies its 
use as a normalization gene. The assumption that there are 10 TBP 
copies per cell does not affect fold-change results; it is used because 
it provides a relative estimate of target gene levels in a biologically 
relevant context. 
We find that the gene expression profiling results obtained from 
the PreAmp'd samples show similar trends as those derived from 
the original cDNA samples, even though up to 10,000-fold less cDNA 
is analyzed. This implies that PreAmp can analyze limited samples 
effectively and that the same biological insights and conclusions 
would be derived from an experiment using PreAmp and a standard 
gene expression profiling experiment. Importantly, the changes in 
gene expression observed over the NT2 differentiation time course 
are consistent with previously published results [14-17] suggest-
ing that our results are accurate. 
To further explore the dynamic range of sample input, we 
pre-amplified varied amounts of cDNA, from 10 pg to 1 g, and 
then used the samples to analyze gene targets that span a wide 
expression range. Our results show a linear relationship between 
sample input and target amount (Fig. 3). This demonstrates that 
our PreAmp reagent has the capacity to analyze samples with a 6-</p>

<p>S.T. Okino et al. / Biomolecular Detection and Quantification 6 (2016) 13-21 </p>



<p>Table 1 
Fold-change measurement error. </p>

<p>Target gene expression level (Cq) </p>

<p>&lt;30 
30-32.5 
&gt;32.5 </p>

<p>No PreAmp 
Average fold change measurement error (Cq) 
0.093 
0.265 
0.804 
Average fold change measurement error (percent) 
7% 
20% 
75% 
88-plex PreAmp 
Average fold change measurement error (Cq) 
0.094 
0.162 
0.578 
Average fold change measurement error (percent) 
7% 
12% 
49% 
Statistical equivalence with no PreAmp. p-value (upper threshold) 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.0121 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.0515 
Statistical equivalence with no PreAmp. p-value (lower threshold) 
0.0021 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.0003 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>355-plex PreAmp 
Average fold change measurement error (Cq) 
0.108 
0.119 
0.380 
Average fold change measurement error (percent) 
8% 
9% 
30% 
Statistical equivalence with no PreAmp. p-value (upper threshold) 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.0010 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.0074 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Statistical equivalence with no PreAmp. p-value (lower threshold) 
0.0205 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.0050 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.0002 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Estimated fold-change limits-of-detection 
2-fold 
4-fold 
8-fold </p>

<p>a Statistically equivalent with no PreAmp. </p>

<p>log input range (10 pg to 1 g) and faithfully maintain the relative 
quantity of gene targets over a wide expression level range (e.g. a 
span of 18Cq from POU5F1 to NEUROD1). </p>

<p>3.3. Analysis of dynamic range bias </p>

<p>An important consideration in a PreAmp experiment is the num-
ber of amplification cycles. Typically, qPCR platforms require 10-14 
PreAmp cycles for single copy detection. However, microfluidic-
based qPCR instruments have a nanoliter scale interrogation 
volume and often require up to 20 PreAmp cycles to achieve sin-
gle copy detection [19]. To assess bias associated with PreAmp 
cycle number we used the ERCC controls which have wide range 
of RNA abundance [10]. We diluted the ExFold mixtures such that 
all targets should be present in a PreAmp reaction (2.5 copies 
to 5.6 million copies). We then pre-amplified the samples using 
standard (88-plex) and high multiplex (355-plex) conditions for </p>

<p>Table 2 
Genes regulated by retinoic acid. </p>

<p>Target gene No PreAmp Avg Cq 
% Expression in RA treated cells 
relative to control cells </p>

<p>T (Brachyury) 34.1 
1% 
OTX2 
27.4 
6% 
DKK1 
32.2 
10% 
NANOG 
23.7 
18% 
DPPA3 
29.7 
22% 
MIXL1 
30.0 
23% 
TDGF1 
24.6 
23% 
RARG 
29.4 
23% 
PRDM14 
26.3 
24% 
CD44 
28.6 
25% 
PMAIP1 
25.6 
25% 
POU5F1 
21.0 
26% 
SOX9 
27.6 
27% 
CA12 
29.8 
28% 
THY1 
24.5 
47% 
DLL3 
28.8 
307% 
SNCG 
26.8 
404% 
GABRB2 
29.1 
493% 
CRABP2 
20.0 
831% 
POU3F2 
29.7 
1280% 
CDX1 
30.1 
1801% 
MEIS1 
28.6 
1879% 
RARB 
28.6 
1884% 
HOXD4 
29.3 
3074% 
ASCL1 
28.6 
3141% 
HNF4A 
31.5 
3507% 
LEFTY2 
25.1 
6656% 
NEUROG2 
33.2 
8626% 
FOXA1 
33.3 
9277% 
HOXA4 
33.5 
10550% 
PAX6 
27.7 
13467% 
NEUROD1 
35.2 
13703% </p>

<p>10-20 PreAmp cycles; this reflects a target amplification range of 
10 3 -10 6 -fold. The amount of ERCC target detected, as a function 
of RNA abundance, is shown in Fig. 4A. We find that all ERCC tar-
gets can be detected in the no PreAmp sample and in the samples 
processed for 14 PreAmp cycles. This implies that a moderate num-
ber of PreAmp cycles will not bias the 6-log dynamic range of target 
detection. However, for samples that underwent 20 PreAmp cycles, 
quantification of targets in the 1 million copy range, corresponding 
to a Cq value less than 5, are of unreliable value (see Fig. 4C). 
To illustrate the dynamic range bias associated with a highly 
expressed target we show selected qPCR results. Fig. 4B shows 
the qPCR traces for the moderate abundance target, ERCC-00144, 
which is present at ∼5,500 copies in the PreAmp reaction. We find 
that amplification efficiency, with respect to cycle number, is linear 
and close to 100%. However, for the high abundance target ERCC-
00074, which is present at over 2.8 million copies in the PreAmp 
reaction, high numbers of PreAmp cycles results in poor target 
quantification, thus exhibiting dynamic range bias (Fig. 4C). We 
conclude that high numbers of PreAmp cycles could bias results 
for very highly expressed genes and, therefore, recommend using 
the fewest number of PreAmp cycles required to achieve robust 
single copy target gene detection. Supplementary Table 2 lists the 
amplification efficiency and dynamic range bias of all ERCC targets; 
the results demonstrate that our PreAmp workflow supports quan-
titative target gene amplification up to 1 million-fold under both 
standard and high multiplex conditions. 
The data presented in Fig. 4A was also analyzed quantitatively 
to delineate salient properties of the PreAmp reaction (Table 3). We 
find that PreAmp amplifies targets at all levels of abundance with 
similar efficiency; this is reflected by a slope close to 1. We find 
that PreAmp decreases the Cq value associated with single copy 
detection (X-intercept) by the expected 2 cycles for every 2 cycle 
increase in PreAmp cycle number; this reflects linear amplifica-
tion over 10-20 PreAmp cycles. We also observe a slight decrease 
in the R 2 values when using 18-20 PreAmp cycles, likely reflect-
ing unreliable qPCR quantification of targets with extremely highly 
abundance (see Fig. 4C). </p>

<p>3.4. Analysis of amplification bias </p>

<p>Amplification bias is the difference between the measured 
amount of a target gene after pre-amplification, relative to the the-
oretical amount. In practice, the theoretical target gene amount 
can be estimated from the amount of target detected in the non-
amplified cDNA sample and the number of PreAmp cycles (see 
Section 2). To assess amplification bias, we compared target gene 
levels in cDNA samples before and after 14 PreAmp cycles. For 
each target gene we calculated the amplification bias introduced 
by PreAmp and plotted it against the level of target gene expres-</p>



<p>S.T. Okino et al. / Biomolecular Detection and Quantification 6 (2016) 13-21 </p>

<p>Table 3 
Effect of PreAmp cycles on RNA detection. </p>

<p>PreAmp cycles 
ERCC mix 
PreAmp plex 
Slope 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>X-int (Cq) </p>

<p>0 
Mix 1 
NA 
1.005 
0.983 
37.3 
0 
Mix 2 
NA 
0.988 
0.984 
36.9 
10 
Mix 1 
88 
0.995 
0.979 
34.4 
10 
Mix 1 
355 
0.994 
0.978 
34.5 
10 
Mix 2 
88 
0.987 
0.979 
34.1 
10 
Mix 2 
355 
0.985 
0.980 
34.1 
12 
Mix 1 
88 
0.996 
0.979 
32.3 
12 
Mix 1 
355 
0.993 
0.980 
32.4 
12 
Mix 2 
88 
0.989 
0.978 
32.0 
12 
Mix 2 
355 
0.983 
0.979 
32.4 
14 
Mix 1 
88 
0.996 
0.977 
30.3 
14 
Mix 1 
355 
0.991 
0.975 
30.3 
14 
Mix 2 
88 
1.000 
0.977 
30.3 
14 
Mix 2 
355 
0.987 
0.978 
30.1 
16 
Mix 1 
88 
1.009 
0.976 
28.5 
16 
Mix 1 
355 
0.994 
0.972 
28.4 
16 
Mix 2 
88 
0.992 
0.978 
28.2 
16 
Mix 2 
355 
0.994 
0.979 
28.2 
18 
Mix 1 
88 
0.998 
0.969 
26.3 
18 
Mix 1 
355 
0.999 
0.966 
26.4 
18 
Mix 2 
88 
0.997 
0.969 
26.2 
18 
Mix 2 
355 
1.000 
0.971 
26.2 
20 
Mix 1 
88 
1.013 
0.964 
24.3 
20 
Mix 1 
355 
1.010 
0.958 
24.5 
20 
Mix 2 
8 8 
1.010 
0.960 
24.4 
20 
Mix 2 
355 
1.021 
0.960 
24.1 </p>

<p>sion in the original sample (Fig. 5). We considered gene targets 
that have a Cq ≥ 40 in the original sample to be not expressed and 
excluded them from analysis. We observe that for 319 (91%) of the 
346 expressed gene targets, PreAmp did not change the expression 
level by more than 1.0Cq. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>We developed a novel PreAmp reagent that features an 
engineered DNA polymerase designed to improve amplification 
capacity and efficiency. Here we report an in-depth analysis of the 
bias our PreAmp reagent introduces into a gene expression pro-
filing experiment. We analyzed three types of bias: amplification 
bias, dynamic range bias and fold-change bias. 
Amplification bias reflects PreAmp PCR efficiency and is a com-
monly used parameter to measure PreAmp performance [1-3]. 
Specifically, amplification bias measures whether each target is 
amplified at 100% efficiency throughout the PCR cycling. We find 
that our PreAmp reagent performs well on this metric, even under 
high multiplex conditions (Fig. 5). 
In a previous report the amplification bias of 194 genes was 
analyzed using standard qPCR; 80% of targets were not altered by 
more than 1.0  Cq and about 91% of targets were not altered 
by more than 1.5 
Cq [2]. Our results show less amplification 
bias when analyzing 346 genes; 91% of targets were not altered by 
more than 1.0 
Cq. This difference may reflect differences in the 
samples and/or target genes analyzed, it may also reflect differences 
in the reagents and overall workflow used in the analysis. 
Interestingly however, even if a target gene exhibits ampli-
fication bias, as long as it is biased to the same extent in all 
samples, relative gene expression results will still be accurate. Thus, 
amplification bias reproducibility is a key requirement for accu-
rate gene expression profiling results. Not surprisingly, given our 
gene expression profiling data (Fig. 2), we find that amplification 
bias standard deviation is extremely low, averaging 0.06Cq when 
analyzing technical replicates and averaging 0.17Cq when analyz-
ing multiple samples (Supplemental Fig. 2). These results reflect 
the precision associated with our PreAmp-based gene expression 
profiling analysis. </p>

<p>Dynamic range bias measures the ability to accurately quan-
tify target genes over a wide range of abundance. Our standard, no 
PreAmp gene expression profiling workflow can quantify the entire 
6-log dynamic range of the ERCC controls. Pre-amplification for up 
to 14 PCR cycles can also accurately quantify the entire ERCC assay 
set and, thus, does not introduce dynamic range bias. However, in 
instances of high target gene expression coupled with a high num-
ber of PreAmp cycles (e.g. 20 cycles) target gene quantification may 
be compromised. Dynamic range bias was previously reported in 
a microfluidic-based qPCR study and is quite consistent with our 
findings [3]; a high number of PreAmp cycles biased the quantifi-
cation of high abundance target genes. We believe that dynamic 
range bias will not be an issue in standard qPCR experiments. Such 
bias is apparent in the qPCR traces (Fig. 4C), and can be alleviated 
through sample dilution or use of fewer PreAmp cycles. For applica-
tions that require high levels of PreAmp, such as microfluidic-based 
qPCR, our conclusions may not apply. More work is necessary to 
better quantify the various types of bias associated with high PCR 
cycle PreAmp. 
Fold-change measurement is fundamental to gene expression 
profiling experiments; it allows for the comparison of target gene 
expression levels across samples. To our knowledge, this is the 
first report that analyses fold-change bias using RNA reference 
standards and natural target genes. Using the ERCC standards 
we quantified fold-change measurement bias and found that our 
PreAmp reagent does not introduce bias for target genes expressed 
above trace levels (Cq &lt; 32.5); for target genes that have trace 
expression (Cq &gt; 32.5) we do observe low bias and suggest that 
only 8-fold and higher gene expression differences are detectable 
(Table 1). 
There are limitations to our PreAmp workflow; it has limited use 
in detecting gene expression changes of less than 2-fold (Table 1). 
To detect small changes a different platform, such as digital PCR, is 
likely more appropriate [20]. 
We also analyzed the expression of a panel of regulated target 
genes across six samples; here we found that the PreAmp results 
are similar to the results using standard methodology (Fig. 2). 
This finding is significant and implies that PreAmp can be used 
in gene expression profiling experiments without compromising 
results. Indeed, we show that PreAmp faithfully maintains patterns 
of relative gene expression changes (Fig. 2); the same insights and 
conclusions would be drawn from a PreAmp-based experiment and 
a standard gene expression profiling experiment. 
Our novel PreAmp technology amplifies over 350 gene targets 
up to 1 million-fold. The high level of multiplex allows for the 
incorporation of ERCC standards into a PreAmp-based workflow 
as an internal control. We find that this control is valuable because 
it both validates PreAmp performance and establishes screening 
specifications to identify regulated genes with significant expres-
sion changes (Tables 1 and 2). We envision that such a workflow can 
facilitate experimentation with very limited samples and lead to 
advances in fields requiring sensitive and accurate gene expression 
analysis, such as single cell biology. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors are employees and shareholders of Bio-Rad Labo-
ratories Inc. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>No funding outside of Bio-Rad Laboratories was used in this 
research. </p>

<p>S.T. Okino et al. / Biomolecular Detection and Quantification 6 (2016) 13-21 </p>



<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>S.O. and Y.W conceived the project. S.O., M.K., and Y.W. designed 
the experiments. S.O. and M.K. executed the experiments and S.O., 
M.K., H.S. and Y.W analyzed the data. S.O. wrote the first draft of 
the manuscript. H.S. and Y.W edited the manuscript. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors are employees and shareholders of Bio-Rad Labo-
ratories Inc. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Xiao-Song Gong, Evan Bursey, Elizabeth Jordan, Sonia 
Streng and Paul Streng for their advice and assistance on this 
project. No external funding was used in this work. </p>

<p>Appendix A. Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data associated with this article can be found, in 
the online version, at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bdq.2015.12.001. </p>



</text></tei>