<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4280397" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background -Contrast-enhanced spectral mammography (CESM) is a promising new breast 
imaging modality that is superior to conventional mammography for breast cancer detection. We 
aimed to evaluate correlation and agreement of tumor size measurements using CESM. As addi-
tional analysis, we evaluated whether measurements using an additional breast MRI exam would 
yield more accurate results. 
Methods -Between January 1 
st 2013 and April 1 
st 2014, 87 consecutive breast cancer cases that 
underwent CESM were collected and data on maximum tumor size measurements were gathered. 
In 57 cases, tumor size measurements were also available for breast MRI. Histopathological results 
of the surgical specimen served as gold standard in all cases. 
Results -The Pearson's correlation coefficients (PCC) of CESM versus histopathology and breast 
MRI versus histopathology were all &gt;0.9, p&lt;0.0001. For the agreement between measurements, 
the mean difference between CESM and histopathology was 0.03 mm. The mean difference be-
tween breast MRI and histopathology was 2.12 mm. Using a 2x2 contingency table to assess the 
frequency distribution of a relevant size discrepancy of &gt;1 cm between the two imaging modalities 
and histopathological results, we did not observe any advantage of performing an additional breast 
MRI after CESM in any of the cases. 
Conclusion -Quality of tumor size measurement using CESM is good and matches the quality of 
these measurement assessed by breast MRI. Additional measurements using breast MRI did not 
improve the quality of tumor size measurements. </p>

<p>Key words: breast cancer, mammography, CESM, CEDM, MRI. </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Contrast-enhanced spectral mammography 
(CESM, or contrast-enhanced dual-energy mammog-
raphy: CEDM) is a promising new breast imaging 
modality. In CESM, an iodine-based contrast agent is </p>

<p>intravenously administered two minutes prior to the 
acquisition of the mammographic images. These con-
sist of a dual-energy technique which results in the 
acquisition of both a low-and high-energy image [1]. </p>

<p>Ivyspring </p>

<p>International Publisher </p>

<p>Journal of Cancer 2015, Vol. 6 </p>

<p>http://www.jcancer.org </p>



<p>The low-energy image is similar to full-field digital 
mammography (FFDM) [2], whereas the high-energy 
image is used to generate a so-called 'recombined 
image', in which information on enhancing structures 
can be appreciated. A summary review of the most 
recent publications showed that the diagnostic accu-
racy of CESM in breast cancer detection was consist-
ently superior to FFDM [3]. 
Breast MRI is currently regarded as the most 
accurate breast imaging modality available. Breast 
MRI is superior to all other imaging modalities for 
preoperative evaluation of breast cancer extent, since 
it assesses tumor diameter most accurately [4-6]. 
However, since breast MRI and CESM are based on 
similar principles, CESM might show a similar per-
formance. Previously, only one study reported on the 
quality of tumor diameter measurements using both 
CESM and breast MRI [7]. In this paper the correlation 
of both measurements (with histopathological analy-
sis as the gold standard) was presented. Studying the 
reproducibility of these results and more importantly 
the agreement between these two measurements pro-
vides additional information on the quality of these 
measurements [8]. 
In this study, our aims were two-fold: (1) to 
evaluate correlation and agreement of tumor size 
measurements using CESM, and (2) to evaluate 
whether measurements using an additional breast 
MRI exam would yield more accurate results. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>In the Netherlands, research covered by the 
Medical Research Involving Human Subjects Act 
must be submitted to an accredited medical ethics 
committee for approval. Our medical ethics commit-
tee concluded that the research proposal of the cur-
rent retrospective study does not, under Dutch law, 
require medical ethics approval because no extra 
burden is placed on research subjects. Therefore, the 
need for obtaining written informed consent was 
waived by Maastricht University Medical Center eth-
ics committee (decision number: METC 14-4-071). 
In our hospital, all women recalled from the 
breast cancer screening program who have no con-
tra-indications for the intravenous administration of 
an iodine-based contrast agent are eligible for CESM 
(SenoBright*, GE Healthcare, United Kingdom). The 
CESM imaging protocol has been described elsewhere 
in detail [9]. In short, a non-ionic monomeric 
low-osmolar contrast agent (iopromide; Ultravist ® 
300, Bayer Healthcare, Germany) is administered in-
travenously, after which CESM acquires a set of low 
and high energy images in quick succession. As a re-
sult, an image similar to a conventional mammogram 
(i.e. the low-energy CESM image) [2] and an image </p>

<p>containing information on enhancement of structures 
can be reviewed (i.e. the recombined CESM image) 
(Figure 1). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Typical example of the different contrast-enhanced spectral 
mammography images. First, a low-energy image is acquired (A), immedi-
ately followed by the high-energy image (B), which is used in 
post-processing to create the recombined image (C), in which the invasive 
breast cancer is clearly visible (arrow). </p>

<p>All CESM exams performed between January 1 st 
2013 and April 1 st 2014 were included in this retro-
spective study. Out of this database, all consecutive 
breast cancer cases were collected, including ductal 
carcinoma in situ (DCIS). Since both low energy and 
recombined images are an integral part of the exam, 
maximum tumor diameter measurement is performed 
on the entire CESM exam (i.e. viewing both the low 
and recombined images together in both projection 
views) using calipers and a dedicated mammography 
workstation 
(IDI 
MammoWorkstation, 
GE 
Healthcare, United Kingdom). Core biopsies were 
performed immediately after the CESM exam. 
In some cases, breast MRI was performed for 
preoperative staging, according to our national 
guidelines [10]. These indications for preoperative 
breast MRI were: women considering breast con-
serving therapy with either invasive lobular carcino-
ma, high grade ductal carcinoma in situ or size dis-
crepancies between mammography and ultrasound 
&gt;1 cm, and young women with dense breast tissue. 
All breast MRI exams were performed on a single 1.5 
Tesla scanner (Intera, Philips Healthcare, the Nether-
lands) using a dedicated 16-channel breast coil. The 
protocol consisted of a transverse T2w sequence and 
diffusion weighted imaging (DWI), combined with a 
dynamic, contrast-enhanced T1w sequence in the 
transverse plane (consisting of 1.0 mm isotropic 
voxels and a temporal resolution of 93 seconds). 
Blinded for CESM measurements, tumor diameter 
measurements were performed on the first dynamic 
scan after contrast administration, i.e. at peak en-</p>

<p>Journal of Cancer 2015, Vol. 6 </p>

<p>http://www.jcancer.org </p>



<p>hancement of the tumor, using calipers and a dedi-
cated workstation (Dynacad, Invivo International, the 
Netherlands). We recorded the presence of hemato-
mas or other post-biopsy effects seen on breast MRI 
which might influence the accuracy of tumor size 
measurements. 
After surgery, specimens were received fresh, 
routinely handled at the pathology department, and 
tumor size was macroscopically measured in three 
dimensions. Histopathological examination was per-
formed after formalin fixation and paraffin embed-
ding. Hematoxillin and eosin stained sections were 
examined to assess tumor size. Microscopic carcinoma 
size was correlated with tumor size on gross exami-
nation. Tumor diameter (in mm) was defined as larg-
est tumor size based on macroscopic and histopatho-
logic examination. For the comparison of maximum 
lesion diameter found using CESM and pathology, 
surrounding DCIS was included in the final maxi-
mum diameter measurement. In case of multifocal 
breast cancer, the maximum diameter of the largest 
invasive tumor (i.e. the primary index tumor) was 
assessed. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The correlation between maximum tumor diam-
eter based on CESM and histopathology, and breast 
MRI and histopathology was expressed using scat-
terplots and Pearson's correlation coefficient (PCC). In 
addition, the agreement between these measurements 
was expressed using Bland-Altman plots and calcu-
lating the mean difference in diameter between these 
measurements, including their 95% limits of agree-
ment (LOA) [11]. 
A relevant size discrepancy was defined as a size </p>

<p>difference of &gt;1 cm between CESM measurements 
and histopathological results, in line with previous 
publications [12, 13] and concordant with margins 
used by our surgeons. A 2x2 contingency table was 
created for both imaging modalities and their corre-
sponding size estimations. All statistical analyses 
were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS Statistics</rs> (version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">20.0</rs>, 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs>, Armonk, NY, USA). All p-values &lt;0.05 were 
considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>In the study period, a total of 325 patients were 
referred to our hospital because of a suspicious ab-
normality detected in the breast cancer screening 
program. Of these, 87 (26.8%) women were diagnosed 
with either an invasive breast cancer or DCIS, which is 
concordant with disease prevalence known from pre-
vious publications for this population [14]. Mean age 
(of all patients) was 62.4 years, range 49-74 years. One 
patient had bilateral breast cancer, resulting in a total 
of 88 breast cancer lesions for the final analysis. For 
the additional analyses using breast MRI related data, 
57 cases (58 lesions) were available (i.e. having both 
CESM and breast MRI exams performed within two 
weeks' time frame). Invasive ductal carcinoma was 
the most frequently observed cancer type (70.5%), 
followed by DCIS (14.8%) and invasive lobular carci-
noma (10.2%). Mean tumor diameter was 23.6 mm, 
range 3 to 110 mm. We did not observe any 
post-biopsy effects on breast MR images that inter-
fered with the accuracy of tumor size measurements. 
Table 1 presents detailed patient characteristics. 
The correlations of maximum tumor diameter 
measurements between CESM and histopathology, 
and breast MRI and histopathology are presented in 
Figure 2. The PCC of CESM and histo-
pathology was 0.905, p&lt;0.0001. The PCC 
for the comparison between breast MRI 
and histopathology was slightly higher 
than the one for CESM: 0.915, p&lt;0.0001. 
The agreement of maximum tumor 
diameter measurement between CESM 
and histopathology, and breast MRI and 
histopathology is presented in Figure 3. 
The mean difference between CESM and 
histopathology was only 0.03 mm, with 
95% LOA of -18.44 and 18.40 mm, respec-
tively. The mean difference between 
breast MRI and histopathology was 2.12 
mm, with 95% LOA of -11.46 and 15.71 
mm. In short, MRI shows a slight system-
atic overestimation of the tumor diameter 
measured, whereas CESM does not. The 
95% LOA of breast MRI tumor measure-
ments are smaller than those of CESM. </p>

<p>Table 1. Patient characteristics. </p>

<p>Patient characteristics for the total population and the cases that underwent both CESM and breast 
MRI (*). </p>

<p>Journal of Cancer 2015, Vol. 6 </p>

<p>http://www.jcancer.org </p>



<p>Figure 2. Scatterplots and Pearson's correlation coefficients (PCC) of 
maximum tumor diameter measurements between CESM and histo-
pathology (A) and (B) breast MRI and histopathology. 
Figure 3. Bland-Altman plots for the comparison between (A) CESM and 
histopathology and (B) breast MRI and histopathology. Continuous lines 
represent the mean of the differences between measurements, the dotted 
lines represent upper and lower limits of 1.96 times the standard devia-
tions of differences. </p>

<p>Table 2 shows a 2x2 contingency table displaying 
the frequency distribution of the studied variables for 
all 58 lesions that were measured with CESM and 
breast MRI. In most cases (84.5%), no size discrepan-
cies were observed for both modalities. As is ex-
plained on a case-by-case basis below, the addition of 
breast MRI did not result in more accurate size esti-
mations when compared to CESM. 
A relevant size discrepancy was observed for 
both techniques simultaneously in 5 cases (all inva-
sive ductal carcinomas: four grade II and one grade III 
carcinoma). In two cases, tumor size was overesti-
mated by both modalities. A 25 mm carcinoma was 
estimated to be 44 mm on CESM and 40 mm on breast 
MRI. A 35 mm carcinoma was estimated to be 60 mm </p>

<p>on CESM and 54 mm on breast MRI. In three cases, 
tumor size was underestimated by both modalities. In 
these cases, the subsequent diameters were 25, 20 and 
13 mm for CESM and 29, 18 and 15 mm for breast 
MRI. Final histopathological analysis showed these 
tumors to be 40, 40 and 26 mm. Although underesti-
mation of tumor size carries the risk of positive sur-
gical margins, these were not observed in these three 
cases. 
In 3 cases, no relevant size discrepancy was ob-
served for CESM, whereas the addition of breast MRI 
resulted in an inaccurate size estimation. All cases 
were invasive ductal carcinomas (two grade I, one 
grade III carcinomas). All tumor sizes were overesti-
mated by MRI &gt;1 cm. For CESM, tumor diameters </p>

<p>Journal of Cancer 2015, Vol. 6 </p>

<p>http://www.jcancer.org </p>



<p>were 27, 17 and 10 mm, respectively (versus 21, 12 and 
5 mm at histopathological examination). For breast 
MRI, these measurements were 33, 25 and 22 mm, 
respectively. In these cases, CESM would already 
have estimated tumor size accurately and the addition 
of a breast MRI exam would increase the risk of un-
necessary wider tumor excision. 
Only one case showed a potential benefit of the 
addition of breast MRI. This invasive lobular carci-</p>

<p>noma's maximum diameter was 13 mm. The diame-
ters measured by CESM and breast MRI were 24 and 
23 mm, respectively. Per definition, this resulted in a 
relevant size discrepancy for CESM and not for breast 
MRI, but it is obvious that the addition of breast MRI 
did not have any clinical impact. 
In Figure 4 and 5, examples of good and poor 
agreement between tumor diameter measurement 
between CESM and breast MRI can be appreciated. </p>

<p>Table 2. 2×2 contingency table of tumor diameter measurement assessed by CESM or breast MRI. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Image example of good agreement between tumor diameter measurements using CESM and breast MRI. The cancer is ill-defined on the 
low-energy CESM image (A) and can be measured more confidently on the recombined image (B, 60 mm). Subtracted contrast-enhanced T1w images (C) 
showed a similar irregular mass (63 mm). Final pathological results showed a 60 mm invasive ductal carcinoma. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Example of poor agreement between CESM and breast MRI. The low-energy CESM image (A) shows an ill-defined mass behind the nipple, 
enhancing on the recombined images (B, 16 mm). Breast MRI showed a spiculated mass (C, 29 mm). Histopathological results showed a 21 mm invasive 
lobular carcinoma. </p>

<p>Journal of Cancer 2015, Vol. 6 </p>

<p>http://www.jcancer.org </p>



<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we evaluated the quality of maxi-
mum tumor diameter measurements of CESM with 
histopathologic results as gold standard. Where 
available, the quality of tumor diameter measure-
ments as assessed by breast MRI was also studied. We 
demonstrated a good correlation and agreement be-
tween these measurements. A 2x2 contingency table 
showed that the addition of a breast MRI exam after 
CESM did not yield more accurate tumor diameter 
measurements in any of the cases. 
CESM is a new breast imaging tool that recently 
became commercially available. The CESM exam 
provides the radiologist with a so-called low-energy 
image (which is comparable to a regular mammo-
gram) and a 'recombined' image, in which enhancing 
structures are visualized [15]. In a recent summary 
review it was shown that CESM was consistently su-
perior to conventional full-field digital mammogra-
phy [2]. However, these studies mainly focused on the 
ability of CESM to detect breast cancer, not on the 
quality of maximum tumor diameter measurements 
(which are essential for surgical planning). 
There is only one prior publication that calcu-
lated PCC for CESM, breast MRI and histopathology 
[7]. In this study by Fallenberg et al., the PCC for 
CESM and histopathology was 0.733 (p&lt;0.0001), and 
0.654 (p&lt;0.0001) for breast MRI and histopathology. In 
our study, PCC's were 0.905 (p&lt;0.0001) and 0.915 
(p&lt;0.0001) respectively. However, merely calculating 
the PCC can be misleading, since good correlation 
does not automatically imply good agreement be-
tween measurements of two different modalities [8,  11]. If there is a systematic over-or underestimation in 
the two measurements, PCC can be high, while 
agreement can be poor. For these comparisons, a 
Bland-Altman plot might be a more suitable method 
of presenting the results, since it allows us to evaluate 
the range and magnitude of measurement errors and 
shows whether these errors are acceptable in terms of 
clinical consequences [11]. As our Bland-Altman plots 
show, breast MRI shows a small tendency to overes-
timate tumor size (mean difference +2 mm), whereas 
CESM does not. However, the 95% LOA of breast MRI 
are smaller than CESM. These plots also show that the 
observed mean differences are in our opinion clini-
cally neglible. 
In a 2x2 contingency table, we studied the fre-
quency distribution of relevant size discrepancies 
between measurements performed using CESM or 
breast MRI. A relevant size discrepancy was defined 
as &gt;1 cm between CESM tumor size measurements 
and the final histopathological tumor size measure-
ment. This approach allowed us to study in the 58 </p>

<p>lesions that were measured by both CESM and breast 
MRI if an additional breast MRI after a CESM exam 
would results in more accurate tumor size estima-
tions. In the majority of cases, no relevant size dis-
crepancies were observed in both modalities. In three 
cases, CESM already assessed tumor size accurately, 
whereas an additional breast MRI exam would result 
in a larger overestimation of tumor size, resulting in 
unnecessary excision of healthy breast tissue. In three 
cases, both CESM and breast MRI underestimated 
breast cancer size, but this did not result in tu-
mor-positive surgical margins. Only one case of a 13 
mm tumor showed a potential benefit of the addition 
of breast MRI, but this was mainly caused by our 
predefined cut off value for size discrepancy of 1 cm. 
In short, this 2x2 contingency table did not show any 
benefit of additionally performing a breast MRI exam 
after CESM in any of the cases. 
This study had several limitations. First, the 
sample size of the population is small, which re-
frained us from studying the ability of CESM to detect 
multifocal breast cancer in comparison to breast MRI. 
In a paper by Jochelson et al., CESM was compared to 
breast MRI with respect to cancer detection rates and 
false-positive findings, but also for the evaluation of 
multifocal breast cancer. In this study of 52 cancer 
cases, 88% of the additional ipsilateral breast cancers 
were detected by breast MRI, versus 56% detected by 
CESM [16]. Consequently, breast MRI might be more 
accurate than CESM in detecting multifocal breast 
cancers. We could not perform any additional analy-
sis on the ability of CESM to detect multifocal breast 
cancer ourselves due to the limited number of cases 
(n=4). As a result, there is currently insufficient evi-
dence that CESM can also be reliably used in multi-
focal breast cancers, and as such additional breast 
MRI should be considered if multifocal breast cancer 
is suspected. 
Second, studying the agreement between max-
imum tumor diameter using imaging methods and 
comparing them to histopathological results has some 
inherent limitations. For example, tumor diameter 
may be distorted during the process of removal and 
fixation of the surgical specimen [17-20]. Due to the 
pliable nature of the breast, tumor diameter may vary 
depending on patient positioning during imaging 
exams [19]. In addition, orientation of intact speci-
mens so that tumor diameters are measured in the 
similar planes in histologic analysis as in imaging 
might be challenging [17]. These potential errors in 
measurements are particularly important in retro-
spective analyses like our current study, since histo-
pathological tumor size measurements were not per-
formed for the purpose of this study. </p>

<p>Journal of Cancer 2015, Vol. 6 </p>

<p>http://www.jcancer.org </p>



<p>Nonetheless, these promising results warrant 
larger studies which should be performed in multiple 
centers in order to include sufficient cases of espe-
cially multifocal breast cancers. In addition, these 
studies should also focus on the planned surgical 
treatment based on the different modalities and study 
how often the surgical management would be altered 
for the good or the worse. The results of this study 
show the potential of CESM as an alternative for tu-
mor size measurements in hospitals with less access 
the MRI facilities. 
In conclusion, the quality of tumor size meas-
urement using CESM is good and the addition of a 
breast MRI exam for this purpose does not seem ben-
eficial, unless multifocal breast cancer is suspected. 
CESM might be a suitable alternative for preoperative 
evaluation of tumor extent. Potential advantages of 
CESM over breast MRI are the short examination 
times, easy accessibility and fewer costs. Disad-
vantages are the use of an iodine based contrast agent 
instead of a gadolinium based agent and an increase 
in radiation dose as compared to FFDM [21]. Howev-
er, if multifocal breast cancer is suspected, breast MRI 
should remain the preferred imaging modality, as 
there is still insufficient evidence that CESM is equally 
accurate as breast MRI to assess the extent of multi-
focal breast cancers. </p>

<p>Abbreviations </p>

<p>CEDM: contrast-enhanced dual-energy mam-
mography; CESM: contrast-enhanced spectral mam-
mography; DCIS: ductal carcinoma in situ; DWI: dif-
fusion-weighted imaging; FFDM: full-field digital 
mammography; LOA: limits of agreement; MRI: 
magnetic resonance imaging; PCC: Pearson's correla-
tion coefficient. </p>

<p>Competing Interests </p>

<p>The authors have declared that no competing 
interest exists. </p>



</text></tei>