<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4042634" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">


<p>2,5-DHBA augments bacterial growth | Liu et al. </p>

<p>Figure 1. 2,5-DHBA-mediated growth augmentation of E. coli in vitro. (A-D) E. coli W3110 (A), E. coli W3110 mut aroB (B), E. coli W3110FepA 
(C) or E. coli W3110FepA/aroB (D; 10 4 CFU/ml each) was cultured in the presence of the indicated amounts of 2,5-DHBA, 2,3-DHBA, or benzoic acid 
overnight and CFU were determined at 12 h after culture. Data are the means of three independent experiments ± SD. Statistical analysis by one-way 
analysis of variance followed by the Tukey HSD test for multiple comparisons: *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01, ***, P &lt; 0.001. (E and F) E. coli W3110 mut aroB 
(10 4 CFU/ml) was cultured in the presence of 0.1 µM FeCl 3 and increasing concentrations of 2,5-DHBA (E) or 2,3-DHBA (F) overnight and CFU were determined 
at 12 h after culture. Data are the means of three independent experiments ± SD. Statistical analysis by one-way analysis of variance followed by the 
Tukey HSD test for multiple comparisons: *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01; ***, P &lt; 0.001. (G, right) Schematic showing chromium substitution in 2,5-DHBA. 
(left) E. coli W3110 mut aroB (10 4 CFU/ml) was cultured in the presence of 0.1 µM CrCl 3 and increasing concentrations of 2,5-DHBA overnight and CFU 
were determined at 12 h after culture. Data are the means of three independent experiments ± SD. Statistical analysis by one-way analysis of variance 
followed by the Tukey HSD test for multiple comparisons: *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01. (H) E. coli H9049 (10 4 CFU/ml) was cultured as stated in A. Statistical 
analysis by one-way analysis of variance followed by the Tukey HSD test for multiple comparisons: *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01; ***, P &lt; 0.001. (I and J) E. coli 
H9049 (10 4 CFU/ml) was cultured in the presence of 0.1 µM FeCl 3 and increasing concentrations of 2,5-DHBA (H) or 2,3-DHBA (I) and CFU were deter-
mined 12 h after culture. Data are the means of three independent experiments ± SD. Statistical analysis by one-way analysis of variance followed by the 
Tukey HSD test for multiple comparisons: *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01; ***, P &lt; 0.001. (K) DHBA supplementation has no effect on S. aureus growth. S. aureus 
strain 25923 at 10 5 CFU/ml was cultured in the presence of indicated amounts of 2,5-DHBA, 2,3-DHBA, or benzoic acid overnight and CFU were deter-
mined at 12 h after culture by plating onto tryptic soy agar plates. Data are the means of three independent experiments ± SD. Statistical analysis by </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 211, No. 6 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>

<p>1199 </p>

<p>RESULTS 
2,5-DHBA, the mammalian siderophore 
augments bacterial growth in vitro 
Previously, both 2,3-DHBA and enterobactin were shown to 
confer a growth advantage to E. coli by promoting iron uptake 
(Hancock et al., 1977). The mammalian siderophore, 2,5-
DHBA, resembles 2,3-DHBA, so we reasoned that 2,5-DHBA 
may also promote bacterial growth. We tested this hypothesis 
using an E. coli strain harboring a mutation in the aroB gene 
(W3110 mut aroB) whose gene product catalyzes one of the 
early steps in the shikimate pathway preventing enterobactin 
synthesis (Braun et al., 1983; Chaudhuri et al., 1986; Bentley, 
1990). In iron-restrictive medium (RPMI), the aroB mutant 
grows poorly compared with the parental E. coli W3110 strain 
(Braun et al., 1983). As expected, addition of 2,3-DHBA aug-
mented growth of the aroB mutant (Fig. 1 B). The growth 
promoting activity of 2,3-DHBA on the aroB mutant is less 
effective than that observed in parental E. coli W3110 (Fig. 1 A). 
However, 2,5-DHBA also augmented the growth of the aroB 
mutant in a dose-dependent manner (Fig. 1 B). Supplementa-
tion with 2,5-DHBA augmented the growth of parental W3110 
strain, although less efficiently than 2,3-DHBA (Fig. 1 A). In 
contrast, addition of benzoic acid, a chemical paralogue of 
2,5-DHBA, had a minimal effect on the growth of both paren-
tal or aroB mutant E. coli strains (Fig. 1 B). Thus, supplementa-
tion with 2,5-DHBA rescues the growth deficit caused by the 
absence of enterobactin. 
The enterobactin receptor, FepA, facilitates iron import 
mediated by both 2,3-DHBA and enterobactin (Barnard et al., 
2001). To determine whether FepA mediates 2,5-DHBA growth 
promotion we used an E. coli strain lacking fepA (Vakharia and 
Postle, 2002). The fepA deletion strain grew poorly in iron-
limiting medium compared with the parental W3110 strain 
(not depicted). Addition of either 2,3-DHBA or 2,5-DHBA 
failed to augment the growth of the fepA deletion strain (Fig. 1 C; 
Bleuel et al., 2005). However, addition of 2,3-DHBA or 2,5-
DHBA readily promoted the growth of parental W3110 strain 
(Fig. 1 A). These results suggest that both molecules use a com-
mon transport pathway (Fig. 1 C). 
Finally, we tested the effect of 2,5-DHBA on an E. coli 
strain bearing deletions in both fepA and aroB genes (Vakharia 
and Postle, 2002). The double deletion strain grew very poorly 
in iron-limiting medium when compared with parental W3110 
strain (not depicted). Addition of 2,5-DHBA or 2,3-DHBA 
failed to confer a growth advantage to the double deletion 
strain (Fig. 1 D). Therefore, the 2,5-DHBA-mediated growth 
advantage requires FepA. 
Both 2,3-DHBA and 2,5-DHBA chelate ferric iron 
(Albrecht-Gary and Crumbliss, 1998; Devireddy et al., 2010). 
Therefore, the observed growth promoting effect of these </p>

<p>bacteria, secreted 24p3 may not be able to sequester the mul-
tiple siderophores excreted by these bacteria because its bind-
ing pocket is selective for catecholes (Holmes et al., 2005;  Reigstad et al., 2007). Interestingly, 24p3 is also highly induced 
by E. coli infection of C3H/HeJ mice that harbor a mutation 
in TLR4 (Reigstad et al., 2007). Despite high levels of 24p3, 
these mice succumb to E. coli infection; the effect of 24p3 on 
E. coli growth in C3H/HeJ mice is insignificant (Hagberg et al.,  1985). As stated above, 24p3 is a secondary granule protein 
in neutrophils, which is critical for motility and chemotaxis 
(Rathore et al., 2011; Schroll et al., 2012; Liu et al., 2013). 
24p3 deficiency confers enhanced sensitivity upon mice to a 
variety of pathogens independent of their ability to secrete 
siderophores (Liu et al., 2013). These studies suggest that addi-
tional mechanisms may be in place that synergize with 24p3 to 
counter bacterial hijacking of iron. 
Mammalian-derived 24p3 also captures iron indicating the 
existence of siderophore-like molecules (Yang et al., 2003). In 
addition, older studies have suggested the existence of low-
molecular weight iron binding compounds or siderophore-like 
molecules that are capable of binding iron and that stimulate 
proliferation of bacteria (Fernandez-Pol, 1978; Jones et al.,  1980). However, these molecules were not implicated in iron 
carrier function of 24p3. Using 24p3 as bait we recently iden-
tified a siderophore in mammalian cells that facilitates iron 
loading onto 24p3 (Devireddy et al., 2010). The mammalian 
siderophore, 2,5-dihydroxy benzoic acid (2,5-DHBA) is chemi-
cally similar to 2,3-DHBA, the iron-binding moiety of E. coli 
enterobactin (Raymond et al., 2003). One of the short chain 
dehydrogenases (SDR) family of reductases, 3-OH butyrate 
dehydrogenase-2 (Bdh2), a homologue of bacterial EntA, cata-
lyzes a rate-limiting step in the 2,5-dihydroxy benzoic acid 
(DHBA) biosynthetic pathway (Devireddy et al., 2010). 
However, the role of the mammalian siderophore in in-
nate immunity is not clear. Due to its similarity to bacterial 
siderophore, we hypothesized that the mammalian sidero-
phore promotes bacterial growth. We now show that the 
mammalian siderophore augments bacterial growth and can 
rescue a growth deficit conferred by the absence of the E. coli 
siderophore, enterobactin. To counter bacterial coopting of 
the mammalian siderophore, the host responds by suppress-
ing mammalian siderophore biosynthesis. Thus, negative reg-
ulation of the mammalian siderophore provides an ingenious 
strategy to withhold iron from invading pathogens. Of note, 
mammalian siderophore-deficient mice resist pathogenic 
E. coli. In addition to decreasing mammalian siderophore the 
host responds by secreting 24p3 to sequester iron-laden bac-
terial siderophores. Thus, reciprocal regulation of 24p3 and 
the mammalian siderophore restricts the growth of invad-
ing pathogens. </p>

<p>one-way analysis of variance followed by the Tukey HSD test for multiple comparisons. P &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. (L) C. albicans is impervious 
to DHBA supplementation. C. albicans strain 562 at 10 6 CFU/ml was cultured in the presence of indicated amounts of 2,5-DHBA, 2,3-DHBA, or benzoic 
acid overnight and their number was enumerated in a hemocytometer 24 h after culture. Data are the means of three independent experiments ± SD. 
Statistical analysis by one-way analysis of variance, followed by the Tukey HSD test for multiple comparisons. P &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. </p>



<p>2,5-DHBA augments bacterial growth | Liu et al. </p>

<p>we obtained nearly 25% bdh2-null mice suggesting that the 
bdh2 deletion did not affect the viability of the embryos. 
The mutant mice are slightly runted but otherwise grossly 
indistinguishable from their normal counterparts when housed 
in specific pathogen-free conditions and fed standard labora-
tory diet (Prolab RMH3000) containing 0.02% wt/wt iron. 
However, when placed on a low-iron diet (TD.80396; contain-
ing 0.0006% wt/wt iron and 0.001% wt/wt ethoxyquin) the 
mutant mice exhibited severe anemia, alopecia, and hypother-
mia. Challenge with a high-iron diet (TD.08496; containing 
2% wt/wt carbonyl iron and 0.001% wt/wt ethoxyquin) led to 
premature mortality, growth retardation, and extreme iron 
overload (unpublished data). </p>

<p>Bdh2-null mice have no detectable 2,5-DHBA 
We previously demonstrated that suppression of Bdh2 results 
in depletion of 2,5-DHBA in cultured cells (Devireddy  et al., 2010). We next asked whether bdh2 deletion in mice ab-
rogates 2,5-DHBA synthesis. We assessed levels of 2,5-DHBA 
in urine samples collected from WT and bdh2-null mice by 
gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) analysis. 
A prominent GC peak was detected at 7.2 s retention time 
representing 2,5-DHBA in WT urine sample (Fig. 2 B). The 
presence of 2,5-DHBA in urine sample from WT mice was 
further confirmed using a set of DHBA standards (Fig. 2 B). 
In addition to 2,5-DHBA, we also found several DHBA-
like molecules in the WT urine sample (Fig. 2 B). In con-
trast, urine from bdh2-null mice lack 2,5-DHBA reinforcing 
the notion that Bdh2 catalyzes the synthesis of 2,5-DHBA 
(Fig. 2 B). </p>

<p>Disruption of bdh2 does not alter ketone body metabolism 
An earlier study suggested a role for BDH2 in ketone body 
metabolism. Based on a computational model, Bdh2 was as-
sumed to bind and oxidize cytosolic ketone bodies (Guo et al.,  2006). Therefore, we evaluated levels of ketone bodies in plasma 
samples obtained from WT and bdh2-null mice, specifically 
3 hydroxybutyric acid, the most abundant ketone in the body. 
WT mice displayed basal levels of 3 hydroxybutyric acid (Fig. 2 C). 
Surprisingly, 3 hydroxybutyric acid levels in bdh2-null mice 
were comparable to WT mice (Fig. 2 C). Further evaluation 
of acetoacetate also suggested no ketoacidosis in bdh2-null 
mice (Fig. 2 D). 
In mammals, ketone bodies are derived from the oxidation 
of fatty acids that are then exported to other tissues to be used 
as fuel (Cotter et al., 2013). Therefore, we assessed cholesterol, 
free fatty acids (FFA), and triglyceride levels in plasma samples 
from WT and bdh2-null mice. Plasma fatty acid levels were 
unremarkable in bdh2-null mice compared with the levels in 
WT mice (Fig. 2, E-G). In addition, because glucose metabolism 
and ketone body oxidation are linked, we assessed glucose han-
dling in bdh2-null mice after overnight fasting. No significant 
difference was observed between WT and bdh2-null mice (un-
published data). Thus, Bdh2 deficiency does not appear to im-
pair ketone body metabolism. </p>

<p>two molecules may result from enhanced uptake of iron me-
diated by 2,3-DHBA or 2,5-DHBA. We assessed growth rates 
of the aroB mutant under iron-replete condition with or 
without 2,5-DHBA and, as a control, 2,3-DHBA to test this 
idea (Fig. 1, E and F). Exogenous supplementation with ferric 
iron alone conferred a marginal growth advantage when 
compared with medium alone (Fig. 1, E and F). However, ad-
dition of iron complexed with 2,5-DHBA or 2,3-DHBA sub-
stantially enhanced the growth of the aroB mutant strain (Fig. 1, 
E and F). Radiolabeled iron uptake experiments with or with-
out 2,5-DHBA or 2,3-DHBA or benzoic acid as a control 
confirmed this result (unpublished data). Substitution of iron 
with chromium (another d-block transition metal) in the 2,5-
DHBA-ferric iron complex did not further enhance the growth 
of the aroB mutant (Fig. 1 G). These results suggest that 2,5-
DHBA confers a growth advantage on the aroB mutant by fa-
cilitating iron uptake. 
To generalize of these results, we evaluated the growth-
promoting activity of 2,5-DHBA on pathogenic bacteria (viru-
lent E. coli strain H9049 [Flo et al., 2004] and S. aureus strain 
25923) and pathogenic yeast (Candida albicans strain 562). Addi-
tion of 2,5-DHBA augmented the growth of E. coli strain H9049 
(Fig. 1 H), whereas addition of benzoic acid had no effect 
(Fig. 1 H). As expected, addition of 2,3-DHBA also augmented 
growth (Fig. 1 H). We next assessed E. coli H9049 strain growth 
under iron-replete conditions with or without 2,5-DHBA or 
2,3-DHBA as a positive control. Exogenous supplementation 
with ferric iron conferred a marginal growth advantage (Fig. 1, 
I and J). However, addition of 2,5-DHBA or 2,3-DHBA in the 
presence of ferric iron significantly enhanced E. coli H9049 
growth compared with iron or 2,5-DHBA alone (Fig. 1, I and J). 
Collectively, these results suggest that 2,5-DHBA promotes 
E. coli growth by facilitating iron acquisition. 
In contrast to E. coli, we found that addition of 2,5-DHBA 
had no effect on the growth of S. aureus (Fig. 1 K). Similarly, 
addition of 2,3-DHBA or enterobactin had no effect on the 
growth of S. aureus (Fig. 1 K). Supplementation with 2,3-DHBA 
or 2,5-DHBA also failed to significantly affect the growth of 
pathogenic C. albicans (Fig. 1 L). C. albicans lack FepA, which is 
required for 2,3-DHBA-or 2,5-DHBA-mediated growth 
augmentation (Fig. 1; Almeida et al., 2009). In contrast, S. aureus 
expresses FepA but is unable to import ferric enterobactin 
(Fig. 1; Turlin et al., 2013), thus limiting growth promotion by 
either compound. 
In summary, 2,5-DHBA specifically promotes E. coli 
growth by facilitating iron acquisition, and the growth-
promoting effect of 2,5-DHBA is similar to that observed with 
2,3-DHBA. </p>

<p>Derivation of 2,5-DHBA deficient mice 
To test the role of the mammalian siderophore on bacterial 
growth in vivo, we generated mice lacking Bdh2 activity. The 
catalytic activity of Bdh2 is dependent on NPG and SYK 
motifs, which are encoded by exon 7 (Guo et al., 2006). We re-
placed exon 7 of the bdh2 gene with a neomycin resistance 
cassette (Fig. 2 A). By interbreeding bdh2 heterozygous mice, </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 211, No. 6 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>H9049 applies to other pathogenic E. coli we used the E. coli 
25922 strain, which secretes both enterobactin and aerobactin 
(Berger et al., 2006). 2,5-DHBA deficiency also conferred re-
sistance to E. coli 25922 challenge, supporting the generality 
of resistance to bacterial infections conferred by absence of 
BDH2 (Fig. 3 B). 20% of E. coli 25922-infected bdh2-null 
mice recovered from infection, whereas none of the infected 
WT mice survived (Fig. 3 B). The number of bdh2-null mice 
that recovered from E. coli 25922 challenge is lower than the 
number that recovered from E. coli H9049 challenge (Fig. 3, 
A and B). The difference in recovery may result from the 
secretion of additional siderophores by E. coli 25922 making 
them less dependent on 2,5-DHBA for iron uptake. Bacterial 
loads in E. coli 25922-infected mice are also lower than in WT 
mice (unpublished data). The E. coli challenge experiments 
demonstrate that 2,5-DHBA deficiency hampers growth of 
E. coli in vivo and confers resistance to mice. </p>

<p>Siderophore-deficient mice are 
resistant to bacterial infection 
To test whether 2,5-DHBA-deficient mice resist E. coli infec-
tion, we challenged bdh2-null mice with an acute lethal dose 
of a clinical strain of E. coli, H9049. As in earlier studies (Flo  et al., 2004), low doses (&lt;1.5 × 10 8 CFU) did not impair the 
survival of WT mice (unpublished data). However, a higher 
dose (2.5 × 10 8 CFU), resulted in 100% death of the WT 
mice by 24 h compared with 60% of bdh2-null mice (Fig. 3 A). 
40% of the bdh2-null mice went on to recover from infection; 
none of the WT mice survived (Fig. 3 A). Additionally, the 
bacterial burden was lower when compared with WT mice 
(Fig. 3, C-E). 
The E. coli H9049 strain secretes only enterobactin for 
iron acquisition (Flo et al., 2004), whereas most pathogenic 
E. coli secrete more than one siderophore (Henderson et al.,  2009). To determine whether the observed resistance to E. coli </p>

<p>Figure 2. Derivation of bdh2 knockout mice. (A) Schematic representation of the targeting strategy and the expected patterns of Cre-mediated 
homologous recombination. The structure of the bdh2 locus is shown at the top, the targeting construct in the middle and the resulting targeted allele at 
the bottom. Numbered boxes indicate exons. Black triangles indicate LoxP sites. Arrowheads indicate PCR primer locations for genotyping (P1-P4). 5 and 3 
external probes indicated by solid lines. TK, herpes simplex virus thymidine kinase gene. Restriction sites, HindIII (H), EcoRI (E), used for Southern blot 
genotyping are indicated. (B) Assessment of 2,5-DHBA levels in urine samples of control and bdh2-null mice. A total of 10 age-and sex-matched WT and 
bdh2-null mice on C57BL/6 genetic background were analyzed. Representative GC-MS spectra of the TMS-derivatized, small molecule fractions from 
urine specimen from WT and bdh2-null mice were shown. A set of DHBA standards is shown on the top. (C and D) Bdh2 deficiency does not alter ketone 
body metabolism. Measurement of 3-hydroxybutyrate and acetoacetate levels in plasma of 8-wk-old female WT and bdh2-null mice on C57BL/6 genetic 
background. Data are representative of two independent experiments, each with at least 4-9 mice per group. Statistical analysis by one-way analysis of vari-
ance followed by the Tukey HSD test for multiple comparisons. P &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. (E-G) Evaluation of fatty acid profiles in plasma of 8-wk-
old female WT and bdh2-null mice on C57BL/6 genetic background. Data are representative of two independent experiments, each with at least 4-9 mice per 
group. Statistical analysis by one-way analysis of variance followed by the Tukey HSD test for multiple comparisons. P &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. </p>



<p>2,5-DHBA augments bacterial growth | Liu et al. </p>

<p>mice with S. aureus (Fig. 3 F). Although we found that the 
onset of mortality in S. aureus-challenged bdh2-null mice is 
later than in WT mice, the mortality rate was not statistically 
different (Fig. 3 F). Furthermore, liver bacterial loads in </p>

<p>We found that 2,5-DHBA-mediated E. coli growth en-
hancement requires the presence of FepA. Although S. aureus 
expresses FepA, it is unable to import ferric enterobactin (Turlin  et al., 2013). To expand on this finding, we challenged bdh2-null </p>

<p>Figure 3. 2,5-DHBA deficient mice are resistant to E. coli infection. (A and B) WT and bdh2-null mice were infected with 2.5 × 10 8 CFU of E. coli 
H9049 strain (A) or 10 8 CFU of E. coli 25922 strain (B) i.p. and their survival was monitored for 7 d. Data are representative of 2 independent experiments 
with 8-13 mice per group. Statistical analysis by log-rank test: ***, P &lt; 0.001. (C-E) Bacterial loads in blood and parenchymal tissues of WT and bdh2-null 
mice 36 h after infection with 0.6 × 10 8 CFU of E. coli H9049. Blood (C) or homogenates of liver (D) and spleen (E) were plated on LB agar plates and the 
CFU were determined. Symbols represent individual mice. Bars represent the mean CFU. Data are representative of two independent experiments, each 
with at least four mice per group. Statistical analysis by two-tailed unpaired Student's t test with Welch's correction: ***, P &lt; 0.001. (F) Survival curve 
comparing WT and bdh2-null mice after i.p. challenge with S. aureus 25923 strain (3 × 10 8 CFU). Mice were monitored for 4 d after challenge. Data are 
representative of two independent experiments with seven mice per group. Statistical analysis by log-rank test: ns, not significant. (G) Survival curve 
comparing WT and bdh2-null mice after i.p. challenge with 7 × 10 7 C. albicans. Mice were monitored for 3 wk after challenge. Data are representative of 
two independent experiments with 10 mice per group. Statistical analysis by log-rank test: ns, not significant. (H) Survival analysis of WT and bdh2-null 
mice infected with M. tuberculosis (M. tb) H37Rv. Mice were monitored for 300 d after challenge. Each group contained 12 mice. Statistical analysis by 
log-rank test: ns, not significant. (I) Histological analysis of representative lung sections (H&amp;E) from WT and bdh2-null mice infected with M. tuberculosis 
H37Rv. Bars, 100 µM. (J) CFU determination in lung homogenates of WT and bdh2-null mice infected with M. tuberculosis. Symbols represent individual 
mouse. Bars represent the mean CFU. Data are representative of two independent experiments, each with at least three mice per group. Statistical analy-
sis by two-tailed unpaired Student's t test with Welch's correction: ns, not significant; ***, P &lt; 0.001. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 211, No. 6 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>bdh2-null mice were low when compared with untreated WT 
mice (Fig. 3, C-E; and Fig. 4 I). However, supplementation 
with 2,5-DHBA augmented growth of E. coli in both WT 
and bdh2-null mice (Fig. 4 I). Significantly, pretreatment with 
2,5-DHBA + iron complex enhanced growth of E. coli in 
both WT and bdh2-null mice (Fig. 4 I). Under similar experi-
mental conditions, pretreatment with 2,5-DHBA + chromium 
had no effect on the growth of E. coli in control or bdh2-null 
mice (not depicted). 
We assessed the survival rates of mice supplemented with 
either 2,5-DHBA, iron, or 2,5-DHBA + iron (Fig. 4, F-H). We 
found that 2,5-DHBA or iron supplementation alone to WT 
or bdh2-null mice conferred earlier lethality after E. coli infec-
tion (Fig. 4, F and H). Moreover, mice supplemented with 
2,5-DHBA + iron succumbed to E. coli infection even earlier, 
coincident with the heavy E. coli burden in these mice (Fig. 4, 
G and I). Further, bdh2-null mice receiving 2,5-DHBA + iron 
displayed restored sensitivity to E. coli, as judged by 100% mor-
tality 24 h after infection (Fig. 4 G). 
In summary, supplementation with 2,5-DHBA reverses the 
bdh2-null phenotype, especially those related to E. coli challenge. </p>

<p>Normal cytokine profiles in bdh2-null mice 
Cellular iron levels are altered in siderophore-deficient cells 
(Devireddy et al., 2010) and alterations in cellular iron levels 
have been shown to modulate cytokine production (Wessling- Resnick, 2010). Therefore we evaluated cytokine levels in WT 
or bdh2-null mice challenged with LPS or E. coli strain H9049 
to determine the effect of siderophore deficiency. As expected, 
IL-1, IL-12b, IL-10, IFN-, and TNF were increased in a 
quantitative real-time PCR assay after LPS or E. coli challenge 
in WT mice (Fig. 5). Surprisingly, bdh2 deficiency only affected 
the expression of IFN-, under similar conditions (Fig. 5 A). 
Further, IFN- levels were also induced by challenge with 
PAM3-CSK4, a TLR2 agonist (not depicted). Observation of 
enhanced IFN- in bdh2-null mice upon stimulation with 
TLR ligands is significant because IFN- limits the availabil-
ity of iron in macrophages (Nairz et al., 2008). Thus, differen-
tial regulation of IFN- in bdh2-null mice may aid the host 
by modulating iron availability in phagocytes limiting bacte-
rial proliferation. </p>

<p>TLR ligands regulate the expression of bdh2 
In mammals, distinct combinations of at least 10 toll-like recep-
tors (TLRs) discriminate between a large number of microbial 
components (Beutler, 2009; Kawai and Akira, 2010). Engage-
ment of TLRs by cognate ligands leads to inflammatory and 
innate immune responses. Mammalian siderophore-deficient 
mice are resistant to bacterial infections suggesting that the 
siderophore participates in the innate immune response. We 
assessed TLR-mediated mammalian siderophore expression in 
immune cells by determining levels of bdh2 mRNA and pro-
tein in cultured naive macrophages (RAW264.7), as well as in 
macrophages stimulated with TLR agonists. As expected, cul-
tured naive macrophages showed abundant transcription of 
bdh2 mRNA (Fig. 6 A). However, bdh2 mRNA was reduced </p>

<p>S. aureus-challenged WT and bdh2-null mice were similar 
(not depicted). These results show that 2,5-DHBA defi-
ciency does not alter sensitivity to S. aureus. 
C. albicans does not express FepA and is unaffected by 2,5-
DHBA supplementation (Almeida et al., 2009). Based on this 
observation, we reasoned that bdh2-null mice might not dis-
play altered sensitivity to C. albicans. Bdh2-null mice react very 
similarly to WT mice after C. albicans inoculation (Fig. 3 G). As 
with S. aureus, the microbial load in WT and bdh2-null mice 
are comparable (not depicted). Together these results sug-
gest that bdh2-null mice are neither sensitive nor resistant to 
C. albicans challenge. 
E. coli and S. aureus proliferate in the extracellular milieu 
and cause systemic infection. In contrast, Mycobacterium tubercu-
losis is an intracellular pathogen. To assess the relative resistance 
of the bdh2-null mice to M. tuberculosis (strain H37Rv), control, 
and bdh2-null mice were nebulized with M. tuberculosis H37Rv 
and their survival after infection was determined. The onset of 
mortality in M. tuberculosis-challenged bdh2-null mice trended 
earlier than WT mice, but these differences did not achieve sig-
nificance (P = 0.29; Fig. 3 H). The bacterial burden in the lungs 
of M. tuberculosis infected bdh2-null mice 4 and 20 wk after 
infection was initially very low in bdh2-null mice as compared 
with WT mice; however, at later stages of infection, the CFU 
titers were similar to those observed in WT mice (Fig. 3 J). His-
tological analysis of lungs of infected WT and bdh2-null mice 
at 28 d after infection revealed changes suggestive of an inflam-
matory response, which was exacerbated in bdh2-null mice 
(Fig. 3 I). There were no changes in leukocyte parameters 
in bdh2-null mice, suggesting that the observed sensitivity to 
M. tuberculosis was not caused by alterations in leukocyte num-
bers. These results indicate that 2,5-DHBA deficiency has a 
limited impact on the pathogenesis of M. tuberculosis. </p>

<p>Exogenous supplementation of 2,5-DHBA 
confers bacterial sensitivity to bdh2-null mice 
To determine whether exogenous supplementation with 2,5-
DHBA alters the course of E. coli infection in bdh2-null mice, 
we first assessed the kinetics of 2,5-DHBA absorption, distri-
bution, and clearance using 13 C-labeled 2,5-DHBA and mass 
spectrometry. Fig. 4 A shows the derivation of 13 C 2,5-DHBA 
from 13 C salicylic acid. Proton ( 1 H) and 13 C NMR analyses 
were used to assess the purity of the synthesized compound. 
We injected 13 C-2,5-DHBA at 20 µg/kg i.p. and studied the 
kinetics of clearance by analyzing urine samples collected at 
4, 8, 12, 24, 48, 72, and 96 h after injection. By 12 h after in-
jection, half of the initial dose of 13 C-2,5-DHBA was cleared 
from the plasma (Fig. 4 B). 
To study the effect of exogenously supplied 2,5-DHBA on 
bacterial growth in bdh2-null mice, we pretreated mice with 
2,5-DHBA. Injection of 2,5-DHBA at 20 µg/kg achieves WT 
urine levels (estimated at 5.8 µM; 0.87 µg ml 1 ; Fig. 4 C) as 
judged by MS analysis of urine. Injection of 2,5-DHBA at this 
dose had a minimal effect on serum iron (Fig. 4, D and E). 
Pretreated mice were challenged with E. coli H9049 and the 
bacterial burden was determined. Bacterial loads in untreated </p>



<p>2,5-DHBA augments bacterial growth | Liu et al. </p>

<p>macrophages derived from mouse bone marrow treatment with 
LPS also repressed bdh2 message (Fig. 6 B). 
LPS target genes are either repressed or induced in a tem-
poral cascade. Genes encoding proinflammatory cytokines are 
transiently induced with peak expression at 4 h after LPS </p>

<p>upon stimulation with TLR agonists, except agonists for TLRs 
5 and 7 (Fig. 6 A). Interestingly, among all TLR ligands, treat-
ment with LPS showed the greatest repression of bdh2 expres-
sion (Fig. 6 A). This observation corroborates the finding that 
bdh2-null mice are resistant to LPS producing E. coli. In primary </p>

<p>Figure 4. 2,5-DHBA supplementation confers enhanced sensitivity to E. coli infection. (A) Schematic representation for derivation of 13 C-labeled 
2,5-DHBA from 13 C salicylic acid. (B) Kinetic analysis of 13 C-2,5-DHBA clearance from mice. Mice were injected intraperitoneally with 13 C-2,5-DHBA and 
its elimination from the body was assessed by subjecting urine samples to GC-MS analysis. Data are representative of two independent experiments, each 
with three mice per group. (C) Quantification of 2,5-DHBA levels in urine samples from control and bdh2-null mice. 2,5-DHBA levels were quantitated by 
comparing to known amounts of 2,5-DHBA. Results show pooled data from two independent experiments, each with at least three mice per group. Sta-
tistical analysis by two-tailed unpaired Student's t test: ***, P &lt; 0.001. (D) Serum transferrin saturation in 8-wk old female C57BL/6 (WT) mice injected 
with 2,5-DHBA. Results show pooled data from two independent experiments, each with at least three mice per group. Statistical analysis by two-tailed 
unpaired Student's t test: ns, not significant. (E) Iron levels were measured in nonhemolyzed serum of control and 2,5-DHBA-injected mice. Symbols rep-
resent individual mice. Bars represent the mean values. Results show pooled data from two independent experiments, each with at least three mice per 
group. Statistical analysis by two-tailed unpaired t test: ns, not significant. (F-H) Survival curve comparing WT and bdh2-null mice supplemented with 
2,5-DHBA or iron or 2,5-DHBA + iron and challenged with 2 × 10 8 CFU of E. coli H9049 strain. Data are representative of two independent experiments 
with 4-14 mice per group. Statistical analysis by log-rank test: *, P &lt; 0.05. (I) 2,5-DHBA supplementation augments bacterial growth in mice. WT and 
bdh2-null mice were infected with 0.6 × 10 8 CFU of E. coli H9049 strain and bacterial loads in blood and parenchymal tissues after infection were deter-
mined. Symbols represent individual mice. Bars represent the mean CFU. Data are representative of two independent experiments, each with at least 5 
mice per group. Statistical analysis by two-tailed unpaired Student's t test with Welch's correction: *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 211, No. 6 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>G and H). In contrast, 24p3 levels were significantly induced 
(Fig. 6 I). The 2,5-DHBA level in these mice paralleled bdh2 
levels (Fig. 6 J). Interestingly, S. aureus infection also repressed 
bdh2 and lowered 2,5-DHBA levels, whereas 24p3 levels were 
higher (Fig. 6, G-J). 2,5-DHBA supplementation does not alter 
S. aureus growth and bdh2-null mice display phenotypic char-
acteristics comparable to WT mice upon S. aureus challenge 
(Figs. 1 and 3). The significance of bdh2 repression in S. aureus-
challenged mice is currently unknown. Nonetheless, the higher 
levels of 24p3 may further boost host defense in bdh2-null 
mice, thus explaining, in part, the resistance of bdh2-null mice to 
E. coli infection. 
LPS binds to TLR4 and initiates a signaling pathway culmi-
nating in initiation of inflammation (Lu et al., 2008). To deter-
mine whether LPS-induced repression of bdh2 depends on 
TLR4, we analyzed bdh2 expression in TLR4 / mice. Basal 
levels of bdh2 mRNA were similar in WT and TLR4 / mice 
(Fig. 6 K). Significantly, LPS-dependent repression of bdh2 
mRNA was abolished in the liver and spleen of TLR4 / mice 
(Fig. 6 K). These observations suggest that TLR signaling regu-
lates bdh2 expression. </p>

<p>The transcription factor BLIMP mediates 
LPS-induced repression of bdh2 
We investigated the molecular basis by which TLR4 represses 
bdh2 expression. Because TLR-mediated gene regulation oc-
curs predominantly via transcriptional regulation, we examined </p>

<p>treatment (Aung et al., 2006). Therefore, the observed repres-
sion of bdh2 may be secondary to autocrine effects of cyto-
kines. To test this possibility, we performed a kinetic analysis of 
bdh2 levels in macrophages stimulated with LPS. We first de-
tected repression of bdh2 1 h after LPS treatment, which pre-
ceded detection of cytokines in the medium (Fig. 6 C). Addition 
of cycloheximide, a protein synthesis inhibitor, to LPS-treated 
macrophages resulted in a decrease in bdh2 expression, but in-
hibited synthesis and secretion of IL-6, one of the major cyto-
kines induced by LPS (Fig. 6 D; Akira et al., 1993). However, 
repression of bdh2 in cycloheximide + LPS-treated cells is mod-
erate compared with cells treated with LPS alone (Fig. 6 D). Be-
cause cycloheximide treatment inhibits global protein synthesis, 
this would include transcription factors that repress bdh2 (see 
below). Finally, to directly test the regulatory role of cytokines on 
bdh2 expression, we treated macrophages with recombinant cy-
tokines and analyzed bdh2 expression. We found that most cyto-
kines had no effect on bdh2 expression (Fig. 6 E). Collectively, 
these results suggest that bdh2 is regulated directly by LPS. 
To assess whether LPS stimulation down-regulates bdh2 ex-
pression in vivo, WT mice were challenged with LPS and bdh2 
mRNA was quantitated by real-time PCR analysis. LPS stimu-
lation significantly reduced bdh2 mRNA in liver samples of 
WT mice (Fig. 6 F). Because LPS is a major component of the 
E. coli outer cell wall, we asked whether bdh2 levels are altered 
by E. coli infection. There was a significant reduction of both 
bdh2 mRNA and protein in E. coli-infected mice (Fig. 6, </p>

<p>Figure 5. Analysis of cytokines in bdh2-null mice. (A) Quantification of mRNAs for indicated cytokines in liver samples of control or bdh2-null mice 
36 h after infection with E. coli H9049. Expression levels of cytokine mRNAs as indicated with control mice set at 1. The relative mRNA levels in each sam-
ple were normalized to actin mRNA. Results show pooled data from two independent experiments, each with at least three mice per group. Statistical 
analysis by two-tailed unpaired Student's t test: ns, not significant; *, P &lt; 0.05. (B) Quantitative analysis of mRNAs for indicated cytokines in liver samples 
of control or bdh2-null mice 6 h after LPS injection. Values relative to the liver mRNA from PBS-injected mice. Results show pooled data from two inde-
pendent experiments, each with at least three mice per group. Statistical analysis by one-way analysis of variance followed by the Tukey HSD test for 
multiple comparisons: ns, not significant; *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01. </p>



<p>2,5-DHBA augments bacterial growth | Liu et al. </p>

<p>Figure 6. Bdh2 production is repressed by TLRs. (A) Quantitative analysis of bdh2 mRNA 4 h after treatment of RAW264.7 macrophages with the 
indicated TLR ligands. Expression of levels of bdh2 in naive cells was set at 1. The relative mRNA levels in each sample were normalized to actin mRNA. 
Data are the means of three independent experiments ± SD. Statistical analysis by one-way analysis of variance followed by the Tukey HSD test for mul-
tiple comparisons: *, P &lt; 0.05, **, P &lt; 0.01, ***, P &lt; 0.001. (B) Quantitative analysis of bdh2 mRNA 4 h after treatment of primary bone marrow macro-
phages with LPS. Analysis was as described in A. Results are the means of three independent experiments ± SD. Statistical analysis by two-tailed unpaired 
Student's t test: **, P &lt; 0.01. (C) Time-course analysis of bdh2 mRNA at the indicated time points after LPS treatment of RAW264.7 macrophages. The 
expression level of bdh2 in naive cells was set at 1. Results are the means of three independent experiments ± SD. Statistical analysis by one-way analysis 
of variance followed by the Tukey HSD test: *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01. (D) Analysis of bdh2 mRNA in LPS-treated RAW264.7 macrophages with or without 
cycloheximide. The expression level of bdh2 in cycloheximide only treated cells was set at 1. Inset, IL-6 levels in culture supernatants from the same cells 
determined by ELISA. The results are the means of three independent experiments ± SD. Statistical analysis by one-way analysis of variance followed by 
the Tukey HSD test: *, P &lt; 0.05. (E) Effect of cytokines on bdh2 mRNA level in RAW264.7 macrophages. Cells were treated with the indicated amounts of 
recombinant cytokines for 12 h and bdh2 mRNA levels were determined by qRT-PCR. The expression level of bdh2 mRNA in untreated cells was set at 1. 
The results are the means of three independent experiments ± SD. Statistical analysis by one-way analysis of variance followed by the Tukey HSD test: ns, 
not significant; *, P &lt; 0.05. (F) Quantitative analysis of bdh2 mRNA in liver and spleen samples of 8-wk old female C57BL/6 WT mice after poly (I:C) or LPS 
injection. Values relative to the mRNA from PBS-injected mice. Analysis was as described in A. Results show pooled data from two independent experi-
ments, each with at least three mice per group. Statistical analysis by one-way analysis of variance followed by the Tukey HSD test: ***, P &lt; 0.001. 
(G) Quantitative analysis of bdh2 mRNA in liver samples of 8-wk-old female C57BL/6 WT mice after E. coli or S. aureus infection. Values relative to the 
mRNA from PBS-injected mice. Analysis was as described in A. Results show pooled data from two independent experiments, each with at least three 
mice per group. Statistical analysis by one-way analysis of variance followed by the Tukey HSD test: ***, P &lt; 0.001. (H) Immunoblot analysis of Bdh2 in 
C57BL/6 WT mice after E. coli or S. aureus infection. Actin was used as a loading control. Molecular weight markers are indicated on the right. (I) Quanti-
tative analysis of 24p3 in serum samples of WT and bdh2-null mice after E. coli H9049 or S. aureus infection. Symbols represent individual mice. Bars 
represent the mean values. Data are representative of two independent experiments, each with at least three to four mice per group. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 211, No. 6 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>To rigorously test the role of Blimp-1 in LPS-mediated re-
pression of bdh2, we suppressed endogenous Blimp-1 in LPS-
treated RAW264.7 macrophages by RNAi-mediated silencing. 
Quantitative real-time PCR analysis suggested down-regulation 
of blimp-1 in LPS-treated RAW264.7 cells (not depicted). We 
also confirmed these results by performing immunoblot analy-
sis using an anti-Blimp-1 antibody. We first analyzed endog-
enous bdh2 message in blimp-1 silenced RAW264.7 cells that 
were stimulated with LPS. Bdh2 mRNA levels were unaltered 
despite LPS treatment in blimp-1 knock down cells (Fig. 6 N). 
Next, we transfected a bdh2-luc reporter into blimp-1-silenced, 
LPS-treated RAW264.7 cells. In agreement with the results of 
Fig. 6 N, Blimp-1 deficiency abrogates LPS-mediated repres-
sion of bdh2 (Fig. 6 O). Together, these results confirm that 
Blimp-1 mediates LPS-induced repression of bdh2. </p>

<p>Hepcidin-ferroportin axis is deregulated 
in E. coli-infected bdh2-null mice 
Serum iron levels are decreased during infection to starve the 
invading bacteria of iron (Ganz, 2009). Hypoferremia associated 
with infection is mediated by hepcidin (Ganz and Nemeth,  2012; Drakesmith and Prentice, 2012). Naive bdh2-null mice 
have lower serum iron when compared with WT mice (Fig. 7 A). 
However, upon injection of sublethal doses of E. coli, serum 
iron was even lower in bdh2-null mice compared with E. coli-
injected WT mice (Fig. 7 A). The reduction in serum iron in 
the absence of 2,5-DHBA further restricts bacterial replication 
in bdh2-null mice. 
Hepcidin binds to ferroportin on the plasma membrane 
of enterocytes, macrophages, hepatocytes, and other cells pro-
moting its internalization and eventual lysosomal degradation 
(Nemeth et al., 2004; De Domenico et al., 2007). Hepcidin-
independent mechanisms also regulate ferroportin (Deschemin  and Vaulont, 2013). Inactivation of ferroportin by hepcidin 
leads to intracellular iron retention (Nemeth et al., 2004). We 
therefore assessed the levels of hepcidin and ferroportin in 
liver and spleen samples, respectively, from uninfected as well </p>

<p>the motifs in the promoter region of bdh2 that confer TLR-
dependent down-regulation. We initially analyzed transcriptional 
regulation of the bdh2 gene in naive RAW264.7 macrophages. 
A 5-RACE PCR identified the transcription start site 25 bp 
downstream of a TATA box (Fig. 6 L). We then cloned the 
5-flanking region spanning 5 kb to + 0.5 kb relative to the 
transcription start site into a firefly luciferase reporter plasmid. 
Constitutive reporter gene activity was detectable in RAW264.7 
cells (Fig. 6 L). Consistent with endogenous bdh2 mRNA ex-
pression, stimulation of RAW264.7 cells via the TLR4 pathway 
significantly reduced luciferase activity (Fig. 6 L). To identify the 
cis-acting DNA elements that confer TLR-dependent regula-
tion on bdh2, we constructed progressive 5 deletion mutants of 
the bdh2 promoter and analyzed their activity (Fig. 6 L). All the 
mutants retained basal activity in naive macrophages (Fig. 6 L). 
However, TLR-mediated repression of luciferase activity was 
lost when a deletion from 1.5 kb to 1 kb bp was analyzed, 
indicating positive cis-acting regulatory elements in this re-
gion (Fig. 6 L). 
A careful analysis of this region using Transcription Ele-
ment Search Software identified two putative binding sites for 
Blimp-1 (B lymphocyte-induced maturation protein-1), a 
DNA-binding factor that is critical for the differentiation of 
myeloid cells. Blimp-1 is a transcriptional repressor that recruits 
histone deacetylases, histone lysine/arginine methyltransferases, 
and co-repressors to induce promoter silencing (John and  Garrett-Sinha, 2009). The Blimp-1-binding motif closest to 
the transcription start site bears significant homology to the 
consensus sequence (Fig. 6 L). Significantly, Blimp-1 is induced 
by LPS and mediates silencing of dependent promoters in a 
TLR-dependent manner (Lord et al., 2009). Thus, Blimp-1 
may suppress bdh2 expression. To test this possibility, we mu-
tated the two Blimp-1-binding sites in the mouse bdh2 pro-
moter. Stimulation with LPS failed to repress the bdh2 promoter 
bearing mutations in both the Blimp-1-binding sites, indicat-
ing that Blimp-1-binding sites mediate LPS repression of the 
bdh2 promoter (Fig. 6 M). </p>

<p>by two-tailed unpaired t test: *, P &lt; 0.05; ***, P &lt; 0.001. (J) Assessment of 2,5-DHBA levels in urine samples of control and bdh2-null mice challenged with 
E. coli H9049 or S. aureus. Mass spectrometry analysis of cold ethanol precipitated urine samples. 2,5-DHBA levels were quantitated by comparing to 
known amounts of 2,5-DHBA. Results show pooled data from two independent experiments, each with at least three mice per group. Statistical analysis 
by one-way analysis of variance followed by the Tukey HSD test: **, P &lt; 0.01; ***, P &lt; 0.001. (K) Quantitative analysis of bdh2 mRNA in liver and spleen 
samples of LPS-injected TLR4-null mice. Values relative to the mRNA from PBS-injected mice. Analysis was as described in A. Results show pooled data 
from two independent experiments, each with at least three mice per group. Statistical analysis by two-tailed unpaired Student's t test: P &lt; 0.05 was 
considered significant. (L) The bdh2 promoter is down-regulated by LPS stimulation in RAW264.7 macrophages. Progressive deletions in 5 flanking region 
of the bdh2 gene. (left) Luciferase activity in naive RAW264.7 cells. (right) Luciferase activity in LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 cells. Bottom, predicted tran-
scription factor binding sites. The DNA binding site for Blimp-1 is shown. Results are means of three independent experiments ± SD. (M) Mutations in 
Blimp-1 binding sites in murine bdh2 promoter blunts LPS-mediated repression. Base substitutions are indicated below. RAW264.7 cells were transfected 
with WT (1.5 to +0.5 kb) or mutant bdh2-luc reporter plasmids containing base substitutions and luciferase activity was determined as in G. Results are 
the means of three independent experiments ± SD. Statistical analysis by one-way analysis of variance followed by the Tukey HSD test: ***, P &lt; 0.001. 
(N) Blimp-1 silencing abrogates TLR4-mediated repression of bdh2 in RAW264.7 macrophages. Bdh2 message was quantified in LPS treated and Blimp-1 
deficient RAW264.7 cells. The relative mRNA levels in each sample were normalized to actin mRNA. Results are the means of three independent experi-
ments ± SD. Statistical analysis by one-way analysis of variance followed by the Tukey HSD test: **, P &lt; 0.01. (O) Luciferase activity in Blimp-1 repressed 
cells. RAW264.7 cells were co-transfected with the bdh2-luc reporter (1.5 to +0.5 kb) and with either increasing amounts of blimp-1 siRNA or control 
siRNA and the luciferase activity was determined after LPS stimulation as in G. Results are the means of three independent experiments ± SD. Statistical 
analysis by one-way analysis of variance followed by the Tukey HSD test: ***, P &lt; 0.001. </p>



<p>2,5-DHBA augments bacterial growth | Liu et al. </p>

<p>iron-binding protein in that it lacks the ability to bind iron di-
rectly. Iron binding by 24p3 is mediated by a small molecule, 
e.g., a siderophore (Goetz et al., 2002). By sequestering iron-
laden bacterial siderophores, 24p3 functions as a bacteriostat. As 
predicted, 24p3-null mice are hypersensitive to bacterial septi-
cemia (Flo et al., 2004; Berger et al., 2006). However, this line 
of host defense is limited by 24p3s ability to only sequester a 
subset of bacterial siderophores (Holmes et al., 2005). Addition-
ally, pathogenic bacteria secrete multiple siderophores or chemi-
cally modify them to prevent capture by 24p3 (Fischbach et al.,  2006; Henderson et al., 2009). 
Members of the SDR family of dehydrogenases are impli-
cated in disparate cellular processes (Oppermann et al., 2003). 
Based on a computational design, Bdh2, or DHRS6, was pro-
posed to bind and oxidize ketone bodies in the cytoplasm (Guo  et al., 2006). Several lines of evidence suggest that Bdh2 may be 
dispensable for oxidation of ketone bodies: 1) Bdh2 deficiency 
does not alter ketone body levels; 2) cytosolic Bdh2 is only 20% 
identical to Bdh1, a mitochondrial enzyme involved in NAD + / 
NADPH-dependent oxidation/reduction of ketone bodies 
(Guo et al., 2006; Cotter et al., 2013); 3) a majority of ketone 
bodies are ferried into mitochondria to fuel energy reactions. 
Therefore the contribution of Bdh2 to cytosolic ketone oxida-
tion seems to be minimal. </p>

<p>as E. coli-infected WT and bdh2-null mice. Hepcidin levels 
were the same in uninfected WT and bdh2-null mice (Fig. 7 B). 
Infection with E. coli transiently increased hepcidin levels in 
both WT and bdh2-null mice (Fig. 7 B). However, hepcidin 
levels in E. coli-infected bdh2-null mice were significantly 
higher than in infected WT mice at 3 h after infection (Fig. 7 B). 
Hepcidin levels in both groups of mice decreased by 6 h after 
infection, perhaps in response to lower serum iron (Fig. 7, 
A and B). 
We next assessed ferroportin levels in uninfected and 
E. coli-infected mice from both genotypes. Upon infection with 
E. coli, ferroportin levels in WT mice were decreased at both 
time points after infection (Fig. 7 C). However, in E. coli-
infected bdh2-null mice, ferroportin levels were significantly 
decreased compared with infected WT mice at both time 
points (Fig. 7 C). Collectively, the results of Figs. 7 (B and C) 
suggest that ferroportin levels are decreased in E. coli-infected 
bdh2-null mice. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
To prevent bacterial iron acquisition, mammals deploy an 
elaborate set of mechanisms to withhold iron. One of these 
mechanisms involves TLR regulation of lipocalin 24p3, a chela-
tor of bacterial siderophores (Flo et al., 2004). 24p3 is a unique </p>

<p>Figure 7. Analysis of iron parameters in E. coli H9049-infected WT and bdh2-null mice. (A) Serum iron in naive and E. coli H9049-infected 
C57BL/6 WT and bdh2-null mice. Mice were infected with 6 × 10 7 CFU of E. coli H9049 and serum iron was determined 3 and 6 h after infection. Data are 
representative of two independent experiments, each with at least three mice per group. Statistical analysis by two-tailed unpaired Student's t test: *, P &lt; 0.05. 
(B) Quantification of hepcidin mRNA in WT or bdh2-null mice 3 or 6 h after infection with 6 × 10 7 CFU of E. coli H9049. Expression levels of hepcidin 
mRNA in control mice was set at 1. The relative mRNA levels in each mouse were normalized to actin mRNA. Data are representative of two independent 
experiments, each with at least three mice per group. Statistical analysis by two-tailed unpaired Student's t test: *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01. (C) Immunoblot 
analysis of ferroportin in spleen samples from WT or bdh2-null mice infected with 6 × 10 7 CFU of E. coli H9049. Actin was used as a loading control. 
Spleen samples from three mice were used. Molecular weight markers are indicated on the right. </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 211, No. 6 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>agonists, more so with TLR4 ligand. Negative regulators of 
TLR signaling are often induced after activation. For instance, 
IRAK-M, an inhibitor of IRAK-1 signaling, is induced by 
LPS treatment to promote tolerance to future LPS challenges 
(van 't Veer et al., 2007). Blimp-1 is another LPS-induced tran-
scription factor that down-regulates downstream targets, perhaps 
to induce a full inflammatory response (John and Garrett-Sinha,  2009). So, what is the significance of bdh2 down-regulation by 
Blimp-1? Based on our findings, we hypothesize that bdh2 is 
present before immune stimulation, but that during infection 
its expression is reduced to prevent bacterial utilization of 2,5-
DHBA for iron scavenging. We provided further mechanistic 
detail by showing that Blimp-1 is the major factor that confers 
LPS-mediated transcriptional repression of bdh2. Other factors 
may also play a role in the LPS-mediated down-regulation of 
bdh2. For example, LPS treatment differentially affects a set of 
miRNAs whose function is to change inflammatory status 
(Tili et al., 2007). Finally, down-regulation of bdh2 in S. aureus-
infected mice suggests additional regulatory mechanisms that 
remain to be elucidated. 
We found that serum iron levels are low in bdh2-null mice. 
How bdh2 deficiency contributes to lower serum iron is un-
clear. However, we believe that iron export from the spleen is 
faulty in bdh2-null mice. Several lines of evidence support this 
hypothesis: (1) we found that bdh2-null mice accumulate iron 
in the spleen and to a limited extent in liver (unpublished data); 
and (2) macrophages recycle heme from senescent RBC and 
store iron in ferritin, which is directed to the lysosomal path-
way to meet cellular demands for iron. Ferroportin regulates 
iron egress from macrophages into the circulation (Delaby et al.,  2005). Free heme is very toxic, and lack of the antioxidant 2,5-
DHBA (Joshi et al., 2012) leads to a nonenzymatic destruc-
tion of heme, removing iron from its normal path toward 
ferroportin. The scenario of high iron in liver/spleen and low 
serum iron in bdh2-null mice is reminiscent of anemia of 
chronic disease. 
The mammalian siderophore and 24p3 are reciprocally 
regulated by TLR4 (Flo et al., 2004). This raises the possibility 
that the mammalian siderophore and 24p3 cooperatively pro-
tect mice from infection. The reciprocal regulation of 24p3 and 
bdh2 by TLR4 agonist serves two purposes: (1) down-regulation 
of the mammalian siderophore allows 24p3 to bind only the 
siderophores secreted by invading pathogens because 24p3 
binds both mammalian and bacterial siderophores (Holmes et al.,  2005; Devireddy et al., 2010), thus maximizing the sequester-
ing activity of 24p3; and (2) because 2,5-DHBA augments 
E. coli growth, suppression of 2,5-DHBA by TLR signaling de-
prives the bacteria of the added growth advantage conferred by 
2,5-DHBA. This observation helps to explain an earlier study 
that demonstrated the ability of mammalian cell extracts to po-
tentiate bacterial growth (Jones et al., 1980). </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Cells and reagents. RAW264.7 cells were cultured in Dulbecco's modi-
fied Eagle's medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, 2 mM 
l-glutamine, 100 U of Penicillin, and 100 µg Streptomycin (Invitrogen). LPS </p>

<p>Previously we showed that Bdh2 catalyzes 2,5-DHBA 
synthesis (Devireddy et al., 2010). Our current results confirm 
that cytosolic Bdh2 is important for 2,5-DHBA synthesis and 
that Bdh2 is not involved in ketone body metabolism: first, 
mammalian Bdh2 is highly homologous to bacterial EntA 
(&gt;45% similarity and 31% identical; Devireddy et al., 2010), 
which oxidizes 2,3-dihydro 2,3-DHBA to 2,3-DHBA. The 
high degree of homology suggests that the major function of 
Bdh2 is DHBA synthesis; second, in agreement with the 
above prediction, we showed that the absence of Bdh2 abro-
gates 2,5-DHBA biosynthesis both in vivo and in cultured 
cells (Devireddy et al., 2010; this study); third, contrary to the 
purported function based on a computational study (Guo et al.,  2006), ketone body levels are unchanged in bdh2-null mice; 
finally, the absence of bdh2 results in alterations in cellular iron 
metabolism both in vivo and in cell culture models (Devireddy  et al., 2010). All of these results strongly support a role for 
Bdh2 in the synthesis of 2,5-DHBA in mice. 
Recent studies demonstrated that 24p3 binds to endoge-
nous 2,5-DHBA or catechol (Yang et al., 2003; Bao et al.,  2010; Devireddy et al., 2010). As noted by Jones et al. (1980), 
very little is known about the small molecular weight iron 
binding molecules in mammalian tissues or their interaction 
with bacteria. Further, the role of these compounds in 24p3-
mediated host defense remains elusive. This report supports the 
hypothesis that mammalian siderophore-like molecules aug-
ment bacterial growth by facilitating iron import into bacteria. 
Bacteria secrete a variety of siderophores to acquire iron from 
the host. However, the secreted siderophores are hijacked by a 
variety of host-derived proteins, e.g., 24p3. In this regard, 2,5-
DHBA, which is ubiquitous, may serve as an alternative source 
for invading pathogens to obtain iron. To counter the hijacking 
of 2,5-DHBA, the host suppresses bdh2 expression thus de-
priving the bacteria the added opportunity presented by 2,5-
DHBA. Additionally, serum iron levels are lower in bdh2-null 
mice (unpublished data). The combined effects of lower serum 
iron and the absence of 2,5-DHBA provide an effective re-
sponse by the host. Unlike 2,5-DHBA, catechol adversely 
affects growth of bacteria via an unknown mechanism (Park  et al., 2001); the function of the catechol-24p3 complex in 
host defense is unclear. 
Cytokines, the major effectors of infection, were unaltered 
in bdh2-null mice. We found that IFN- was differentially reg-
ulated in macrophages of bdh2-null mice upon challenge with 
E. coli, but not with LPS. Although the major antigenic deter-
minant of E. coli is LPS, we did not observe altered IFN- in 
response to LPS challenge. The basis for this discrepancy is un-
clear, but it is possible that active replication of E. coli may be 
necessary to alter IFN- in bdh2-null mice. High levels of IFN- 
alter intracellular iron homeostasis in macrophages and promote 
intracellular defenses against invading pathogens (Gordon et al.,  2005). Therefore, higher levels of IFN- in bdh2-null mice may 
in part explain the decrease in M. tuberculosis replication in 
bdh2-null mice. 
In contrast to most innate immune genes, bdh2 expression 
is down-regulated after activation of macrophages with TLR </p>



<p>2,5-DHBA augments bacterial growth | Liu et al. </p>

<p>using a kit from QIAGEN. DNA was then subjected to PCR analysis using 
a cocktail of PCR primers. Amplified fragments were visualized in ethidium 
bromide stained agarose gels. </p>

<p>Bacterial strains and determination of bacterial growth. WT and 
mutant strains bearing mutations or deletions in aroB or fepA or aroB and fepA 
(a gift from by K. Postle, Penn State University, University Park, PA) were 
cultivated in LB for initial propagation. To study the effect of various isoforms 
of DHBA, we cultured bacteria in RPMI supplemented with graded doses 
of DHBA solubilized in water. After overnight incubation, CFU were deter-
mined by plating on LB agar plates. To study the effect of iron and DHBA 
supplementation on bacterial growth, graded doses of FeCl 3 was added to a 
fixed dose of DHBA and CFU were determined as described above. </p>

<p>Animals. All animal protocols were approved by the Institutional Animal 
Care and Use committee of Case Western Reserve University. Animals were 
maintained on standard laboratory diet. Bdh2-null mice were maintained on 
either C57BL/6 or 129 SvimJ genetic background. Age-and sex-matched 
adult mice on comparable genetic background were used for experiments. 
Mice were housed in microisolator cages and received food and water ad li-
bitum. TLR4-null mice were a gift from A. Hise (Center for Global Health 
and Diseases, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, OH). All experi-
mental protocols were performed in accordance with IACUC guidelines and 
were approved by the institutional animal resources center. </p>

<p>Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry. To assess 2,5-DHBA levels in 
WT and bdh2-null mice, urine samples were mixed with cold absolute ethanol. 
Precipitated material was removed by centrifugation. The supernatant was then 
vacuum dried and derivatized with BSTFA-pyridine (N,O-bis[Trimethylsilyl]tri-
fluoroacetamide; Thermo Fisher Scientific) 1:1 at 80°C for 1 h, and then sub-
jected to GC-MS. The NIST library search was performed against 191,436 MS 
spectra. DHBA standards were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich. </p>

<p>Derivation of 13 C labeled 2,5-DHBA. The 13 C-carboxy-salicylic acid 
(Fluka) was solubilized in 0.23 N KOH to yield a 0.4-mM solution. This so-
lution was chilled to 0°C on an ice bath and aqueous solution of K 2 S 2 O 8 
(0.48 mM) was slowly added over a period of 1 h. The reaction mixture was 
then allowed to return to room temperature and stirred for 18 h at room 
temperature. Later, 1.5 ml of concentrated H 2 SO 4 was added to the reaction 
mixture and boiled for 45 min. The reaction mixture was then cooled and 
subjected to ethyl acetate extraction. The combined organic layer was then 
dried over anhydrous Na 2 SO 4 . The end product was purified on a silica gel 
column using MeOH-CH 2 Cl 2 (1:9). The eluted material contained the 
13 C-carboxy-2,5-DHBA. This procedure routinely yielded 13 C-2,5 DHBA 
at 40%. Purity of the derived 13 C-2,5 DHBA was confirmed by 400 MHz 
1 HNMR and 100 MHz 13 CNMR. </p>

<p>derived from E. coli 011:B5 was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich and used at 
100 ng/ml. A set of TLR ligands was obtained from InvivoGen. All DHBAs 
were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich. Stock solutions of DHBAs were made 
in aqueous NaOH. Anti-Bdh2 antibody was purchased from Santa Cruz 
Biotechnology, Inc. Anti-actin antibody was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich. 
Anti-ferroportin antibody was purchased from OriGene. Recombinant cy-
tokines were purchased from PeproTech. Oligonucleotides were purchased 
from Invitrogen. </p>

<p>Targeted mutagenesis of murine bdh2. Catalytic activity of Bdh2 is de-
pendent on NPG and SYK motifs, which are encoded by exon 7 (Guo et al.,  2006). Mutations in this region blunt the enzymatic activity of Bdh2 and abro-
gate the biogenesis of 2,5-DHBA (Devireddy et al., 2010). Additionally, amino 
acid residues encoded by exon 7 of bdh2 form a helix, which is located at a 
dimer interface within the tetramer (Guo et al., 2006). So removal of this 
stretch of helices prevents proper dimer/tetramer formation and within this 
helical stretch of residues are 3 aa, which form the active site: Tyr147 and 
Lys151 interact with the bound NAD + cofactor and Arg144 interacts with a 
sulfate in the active site (Guo et al., 2006). Thus, removal of amino acids, which 
are coded by exon 7, results in abrogation of the enzymatic activity of Bdh2 and 
also destabilizes the structure of Bdh2. Therefore, we replaced exon 7 of bdh2 
gene with a neomycin resistance cassette. 
The targeting strategy modified a 10-kb region containing the exon 7 of 
the murine bdh2 genomic locus (Fig. 2 A). The 129S7/SvEv BAC clone 
(BMQ-320-G12) covering the region of murine mbdh2 was obtained from 
Source BioScience. For targeting construct preparation, we used MCI-TK vector 
(from G. Luo, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, OH). Lox P-flanked 
linker was inserted into Asp718 site in intron 7 and a third Lox P site was in-
serted into XhoI site in intron 8 (Fig. 2 A). Coding sequence for thymidine kinase 
was present outside of the homology regions. The targeting construct was elec-
troporated into Cre expressing (Cre recombinase under the control of Prot-
amine 1 promoter; O'Gorman et al., 1997) R1 ES cells (129 background) and 
transfected cells were selected for resistance to G418 (Invitrogen) and ganciclo-
vir (EMD Millipore). 
Two homologously recombined clones with a normal karyotype were 
injected into C57BL/6 mouse blastocysts, and then were transferred into 
the uteri of pseudopregnant females. Highly chimeric male (&gt;90%) were 
bred with C57BL/6 females to generate F1 offspring carrying the modified 
bdh2 allele. Germline transmission of the modified bdh2 allele was deter-
mined by Southern blot analysis of tail DNA samples. ES cells used for 
gene targeting in this study express Cre recombinase in male germ cells re-
sulting in germline deletion of floxed exon 7 (O'Gorman et al., 1997). 
Conversion to null mutation was confirmed by Southern blotting or PCR 
using primers listed in Table 1. Subsequent genotyping was performed by 
PCR analysis of DNA from tail snips. We then backcrossed bdh2-null mice 
onto C57BL/6 or 129 SvimJ genetic background successively for at least 
nine generations. 
Bdh2-null and wild-type littermates were obtained by intercrosses of 
bdh2 heterozygous mice. To assess the specificity of the bdh2-targeted dele-
tion, we confirmed the deletion of exon 7 by either genomic DNA PCR or 
RT-PCR in bone marrow cells or in kidney. Bdh2-null mice on C57BL/6 
genetic background were analyzed in this report. </p>

<p>Southern blot and PCR genotyping. For Southern blot analysis, 20 µg 
of genomic DNA was digested overnight with Asp718, fractionated on a 0.5% 
agarose gel, and transferred onto Hybond N+ membrane (GE Biosciences). The 
probe for Southern blots was derived by PCR amplification of a region encom-
passing exon 7 using primers 5-TCACTCACTCTTCAAAGGGAAAGCTG-3 
and 5-CTCGAGTGTCCTGGAACTCACTCTGTAGACC-3. The 
amplified PCR product was labeled by random priming in the presence of 
[ 32 P]dCTP using a kit from Stratagene as per the manufacturer's instructions. 
The probe was then hybridized to genomic DNA cross-linked to Nylon 
membrane. Hybridized DNA was visualized by autoradiography. 
We routinely genotyped mice by PCR analysis using primers whose se-
quences are listed in Table 1. Genomic DNA from tail snips was isolated </p>

<p>Table 1. Sequences for primers </p>

<p>PCR primers 
Sequence (5 to 3) 
Notes </p>

<p>P1 
ACCAGACTCGGCTTCAGAGTCTGTG 
Forward 
P2 
TCTTGTCTGAGTTGTAACCTCAAGG 
Reverse 
P3 
GGCAGGCGGATCTCTGAGTTCAAGG 
Forward 
P4 
CTCGCTCTCTTGCGCTCTCGTCTTG 
Reverse 
Hamp 
AGCAGCACCACCTATCTCCATCAA 
Forward 
Hamp 
TGCATTGGTATCGCAATGTCTGCC 
Reverse 
Bdh2 
GATGCAACTGTGTGTGTCCAGGAA 
Forward 
Bdh2 
ACAGGGTTGCCAGTTACATAGGCT 
Reverse 
Actin 
TGTTACCAACTGGGACGACA 
Forward 
Actin 
GGGGTGTTGAAGGTCTCAAA 
Reverse </p>

<p>JEM Vol. 211, No. 6 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>



<p>bacteria were grown to midexponential phase (OD 600 = 0.5  0.7). Bacteria 
were collected by centrifugation, washed twice with sterile PBS, and resus-
pended to 10 8 CFU/100 µl. Mice were inoculated intraperitoneally with in-
dicated CFU. All the injected doses were verified by determining the CFU. 
Mice were examined for signs of disease at regular intervals and the mortality 
was recorded. All mice were sacrificed 7 d after inoculation. 
For determination of bacterial loads, mice were infected with 0.6 × 10 8 
CFU of E. coli H9049 (gift from Dr. Kelly Smith, University of Washington, 
Seattle, WA) and sacrificed 36 h after infection. Bacterial loads in blood, liver, 
and spleen were determined by plating serial dilutions of homogenates on to 
LB agar plates. Bacteria colonies were enumerated after incubation for 24 h 
at 37°C. 
S. aureus (strain ATCC 25923) was cultured in trypticase soy broth 
(TSB), washed three times with PBS, and then resuspended in PBS for animal 
injection. Age-and sex-matched mice from each genotype were intraperito-
neally injected with 1 ml PBS containing 3 × 10 8 S. aureus. The mortality in 
infected mice was recorded and plotted in Kaplan-Meier analysis. 
Stock cultures of C. albicans (ATCC 562) were cultured in YM broth 
(BD). For experimental inoculation, cultures were propagated overnight in 
YM broth at 37°C and the blastoconidia were collected by centrifugation, 
washed with sterile PBS, and suspended in sterile PBS. The number of fungi 
was determined with a hemocytometer and their viability was determined by 
plating the diluted samples on YM agar plates. Mice (10 mice per group) 
were injected intraperitoneally with 7 × 10 7 cells of C. albicans. All the in-
jected doses were verified by determining the CFU. The mortality in in-
fected mice was recorded and plotted in Kaplan-Meier analysis. 
M. tuberculosis (strain H37Rv) was propagated to mid-log phase on 7H10 
agar plates. Colonies were then transferred to liquid GAS Media and grown 
to an absorbance of 1.1 (595 nm). The media was supplemented with 20% 
glycerol, allowed to settle for 5 min, and 3 ml aliquots were frozen at 80°C 
until use. Stock bacterial counts were determined by the CFU method. 
H37Rv infection stocks were prepared by diluting 1-1.5 ml of frozen bacte-
rial stocks with sterile LPS-free water (Sigma-Aldrich). Bacterial clumps 
were disrupted by three sequential aspirations through a sterile 26-gauge hy-
podermic needle, and the 5-ml suspension placed in the glass nebulizer 
chamber of an Inhalation Exposure System (Glas Col) in the animal BSL-3 
facility. Age-and gender-matched mice were aerosolized for 30 min as 
described (Anis et al., 2007). The initial M. tuberculosis inoculum was deter-
mined 1 d after infection and ranged between 100-200 CFU/lung homoge-
nate. The mortality in infected mice was recorded and plotted in Kaplan-
Meier analysis. 
To determine M. tuberculosis loads at indicated points after infection, 
mice were sacrificed and their lungs were aseptically removed, weighed, and 
homogenized in saline. Homogenates were plated in duplicate onto 7H10 
agar plates in 10-fold serial dilutions. Plates were incubated at 37°C and CFU 
were enumerated 14-18 d later. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Statistical analysis was performed using <rs type="software">JMP statistical software</rs>. Data are represented as mean ± SD. Two-tailed Student's t test was 
applied for comparisons of two groups and Welch's correction was applied for 
unequal variance. One-way analysis of variance followed by the Tukey HSD 
(honestly significant difference) was applied for multiple comparisons. Sur-
vival was evaluated by the Kaplan-Meier log-rank test. For all tests, P &lt; 0.05 
was considered significant. </p>

<p>We thank Alan Tartakoff for editorial assistance; Kotty Postle for many helpful 
discussions; and Steve Macha for expert help in analyzing DHBA in mouse 
urine specimens. 
This work is supported by R01DK081395, American Cancer Society Research 
Scholar Award, and Case Western Reserve University startup funds to L. Devireddy 
L. Devireddy is also a recipient of career developmental awards from March of 
Dimes and American Society of Hematology. 
The authors declare no competing financial interest. </p>

<p>Submitted: 18 December 2013 
Accepted: 25 April 2014 </p>

<p>Metabolite measurements in plasma. Plasma samples from WT and bdh2-
null mice were analyzed for 3-hydroxybutyric acid and acetoacetate using a kit 
from Wako diagnostics as per manufacturer's instructions. Plasma triglycerides, 
cholesterol, and free fatty acids were analyzed by Marshfield Laboratories. </p>

<p>Plasmids and molecular cloning strategy. For TLR regulation studies of 
bdh2 promoter, a Luciferase reporter containing the bdh2 upstream regulatory 
region was cloned as indicated below. A PCR generated 5-kb fragment 
containing bdh2 promoter was inserted upstream of the luciferase gene (luc2) 
in pGL4.13 vector (Promega) to generate the bdh2-Luc WT promoter vector. 
We also derived several deletion constructs within the promoter region of bdh2 
promoter by linker scanning mutagenesis. Site-directed mutagenesis was per-
formed to modify Blimp-1-binding sites in bdh2 promoter using a Quik-
Change site-directed mutagenesis kit from Stratagene. All reporter plasmids 
were sequence verified. </p>

<p>Luciferase assays. RAW 264.7 cells at 50-60% confluency cultured in a 6-well 
plate were transiently transfected with the indicated bdh2-luc reporter plasmids 
along with a control Renilla Luciferase plasmid (pGL4.74) using Lipofectamine 
transfection reagent from Invitrogen. An empty vector (pGL4.13) served as a 
negative control. After the removal of DNA complexes, cells were replated in a 
24-well plate and treated for 16 h with LPS (Sigma-Aldrich). Firefly and Renilla 
luciferase activities of lysates were assayed using a Dual Luciferase Assay kit 
from Promega. All Luciferase measurements were normalized to the Renilla 
Luciferase expression to correct for differences in transfection efficiency. </p>

<p>Immunoblot analysis. Liver samples from WT and bdh2-null mice chal-
lenged with E. coli or S. aureus were resolved in discontinuous SDS-PAGE gels, 
transferred onto a Nitrocellulose membrane (Bio-Rad Laboratories) and 
probed with anti-BDH2 polyclonal antibody (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.). 
Blots were stripped and reprobed with anti-actin antibody (Sigma-Aldrich) to 
verify equal loading. Spleen samples from bdh2-null mice challenged with 6 × 10 7 
CFU of E. coli were also resolved in discontinuous SDS-PAGE gels, transferred 
onto a Nitrocellulose membrane (Bio-Rad Laboratories), and probed with 
anti-ferroportin antibody (OriGene). Blots were stripped and reprobed with 
anti-actin antibody (Sigma-Aldrich) to verify equal loading. </p>

<p>ELISA. Serum samples were subjected to ELISA to measure 24p3 levels in 
WT and bdh2-null mice upon infection with E. coli or S. aureus using a kit 
purchased from R&amp;D Systems as per the manufacturer's suggested procedure. 
IL-6 levels in culture supernatant from RAW cells supplemented with LPS 
were measured using a kit obtained from RayBiotech as per the manufactur-
er's instructions. </p>

<p>Serum and iron measurements. Whole blood was collected by terminal 
bleeding. Non-hemolyzed serum was collected and analyzed for total iron 
and transferrin saturation using a serum iron/TIBC (total iron-binding ca-
pacity) kit from Sigma-Aldrich as per manufacturer's instructions. </p>

<p>RNA interference. Control and blimp-1 siRNAs were purchased from Ori-
Gene. Naive or LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 cells were transfected using Oli-
gofectamine (QIAGEN). Knockdown efficiency was assessed by RT-PCR. </p>

<p>RNA isolation and gene expression analysis. Total RNA was isolated 
from naive or treated cells using TRIzol method (Invitrogen). DNase I (Pro-
mega) treated RNA was then reverse transcribed using Superscript III RT 
from Invitrogen as per manufacturer's recommendations. The resulting 
cDNAs were subjected to real time PCR analysis using SYBR Green master 
mix (Promega) following the manufacturer's recommendations. The fold-
change was calculated using CT method. qPCR results were normalized 
to either actin or 18S rRNA. </p>

<p>Experimental infection with E. coli, S. aureus, C. albicans, and M. tuber 
culosis. E. coli strains were propagated in LB and stock cultures were frozen in 
15% glycerol containing growth medium. For inoculation experiments, </p>



<p>2,5-DHBA augments bacterial growth | Liu et al. </p>



<p>JEM Vol. 211, No. 6 </p>

<p>Ar ticle </p>





</text></tei>