<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4282059" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: The objective of this systematic review and meta-analysis was to assess the relationship 
between the chloride content of intravenous resuscitation fluids and patient outcomes in the perioperative 
or intensive care setting. </p>

<p>Methods: Systematic searches were performed of PubMed/MEDLINE, Embase and Cochrane Library 
(CENTRAL) databases in accordance with PRISMA guidelines. Randomized clinical trials, controlled 
clinical trials and observational studies were included if they compared outcomes in acutely ill or surgical 
patients receiving either high-chloride (ion concentration greater than 111 mmol/l up to and including 
154 mmol/l) or lower-chloride (concentration 111 mmol/l or less) crystalloids for resuscitation. Endpoints 
examined were mortality, measures of kidney function, serum chloride, hyperchloraemia/metabolic 
acidosis, blood transfusion volume, mechanical ventilation time, and length of hospital and intensive 
care unit stay. Risk ratios (RRs), mean differences (MDs) or standardized mean differences (SMDs) and 
confidence intervals were calculated using fixed-effect modelling. </p>

<p>Results: The search identified 21 studies involving 6253 patients. High-chloride fluids did not affect 
mortality but were associated with a significantly higher risk of acute kidney injury (RR 1⋅64, 95 
per cent c.i. 1⋅27 to 2⋅13; P &lt; 0⋅001) and hyperchloraemia/metabolic acidosis (RR 2⋅87, 1⋅95 to 4⋅21; 
P &lt; 0⋅001). High-chloride fluids were also associated with greater serum chloride (MD 3⋅70 (95 per cent 
c.i. 3⋅36 to 4⋅04) mmol/l; P &lt; 0⋅001), blood transfusion volume (SMD 0⋅35, 0⋅07 to 0⋅63; P = 0⋅014) and 
mechanical ventilation time (SMD 0⋅15, 0⋅08 to 0⋅23; P &lt; 0⋅001). Sensitivity analyses excluding heavily 
weighted studies resulted in non-statistically significant effects for acute kidney injury and mechanical 
ventilation time. </p>

<p>Conclusion: A weak but significant association between higher chloride content fluids and unfavourable 
outcomes was found, but mortality was unaffected by chloride content. </p>

<p>The administration of intravenous fluids for resuscitation 
occurs routinely in the perioperative setting and in the 
management of critically ill patients. There has been con-
siderable interest in defining optimal fluid resuscitation 
strategies 1 , yet practice patterns and fluid selection vary 
considerably 2 . While much attention has been directed at 
the 'colloid versus crystalloid' debate, increasing evidence 
suggests clinically important differences related to intra-
venous fluid chloride content 3 -7 .  Often referred to as 'normal saline', 0⋅9 per cent saline 
contains sodium and chloride in supraphysiological </p>

<p>concentrations. Balanced solutions, in contrast, contain 
significantly lower concentrations of sodium and chloride, 
making them closer in composition to plasma than 0⋅9 
per cent saline 6 . Despite a lack of evidence supporting the 
superiority of 0⋅9 per cent saline 7 , it is commonly used as a 
resuscitation fluid and has generally served as the 'control 
fluid' in large trials 8,9 . Administration of 0⋅9 per cent 
saline causes hyperchloraemic metabolic acidosis 10 -15 , 
and consequently some guidelines recommend the use 
of balanced solutions as a default during resuscitation 16 . 
Hyperchloraemia has also been associated with decreased 
renal perfusion 17 -21 , impaired immune function 22 -24 and </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. BJS published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of BJS Society Ltd. 
This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and distribution in any 
medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>Chloride content of resuscitation fluids </p>



<p>mortality 25 , suggesting that hyperchloraemia may have 
clinically relevant effects. 
Studies 26,27 have examined differences between groups 
treated with high-chloride versus low-chloride solutions, 
and a Cochrane systematic review 28 of randomized con-
trolled trials (RCTs) examined clinical outcomes following 
the perioperative use of buffered versus non-buffered fluids. 
A recent systematic review 29 of prospective RCTs evalu-
ated the impact of near-isotonic or isotonic crystalloids 
on acid-base status and other physiological, haemody-
namic and clinical outcomes. However, no analyses have 
focused specifically on the chloride content of crystalloids 
administered for resuscitation in the broader context of 
both perioperative and critical care medicine. Therefore, 
a systematic review and meta-analysis was conducted to 
determine whether the chloride content of resuscitation 
fluids used in the operating theatre or intensive care unit 
(ICU) setting is associated with differences in outcomes. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study selection </p>

<p>Approval for the study was obtained from the Duke Uni-
versity Institutional Review Board on 7 August 2013. In 
accordance with the Preferred Reporting Items for System-
atic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) statement 30 , 
systematic searches of the PubMed/MEDLINE, Embase 
and Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials 
Library (CENTRAL) databases were carried out using 
predefined search terms that addressed study design, 
intervention and intravenous fluid type (Appendix S1, 
supporting information). These were supplemented by 
manual searches by the investigators in order to capture as 
much of the literature as possible. Searches were limited 
to published English-language studies in human subjects, 
covering all dates up to and including 22 August 2013. 
Unique articles were screened based on their title/abstract, 
and studies requiring full review were identified. 
Inclusion in the meta-analysis required that a given study 
meet the following criteria: comparison of an isotonic 
crystalloid fluid characterized by a supraphysiological 
chloride concentration (ion concentration greater than 
111 mmol/l up to and including 154 mmol/l, for example 
0⋅9 per cent saline) with a near-isotonic or isotonic 
crystalloid fluid characterized by a near-physiological 
chloride concentration (ion concentration 111 mmol/l or 
less, for example Ringer's lactate), given intravenously 
for the purpose of fluid resuscitation or replacement; 
comparison in either acutely ill patients in the ICU or 
surgical patients in the perioperative period; and evalua-
tion of at least one of the following endpoints: mortality, </p>

<p>acute kidney injury (AKI)/renal failure (including use 
of dialysis), hospital length of stay (LOS), ICU LOS, 
hyperchloraemia/metabolic acidosis, serum creatinine, 
serum chloride, urine output, mechanical ventilation time 
and transfusion. For the purposes of this meta-analysis, 
isotonic crystalloids with supraphysiological chloride con-
centrations are referred to as high-chloride fluids, whereas 
those with near-physiological chloride concentrations are 
referred to as low-chloride fluids. RCTs, controlled clinical 
trials (CCTs) and observational studies were included in 
the analysis. 
Studies that compared a hypertonic crystalloid with 
another solution were excluded from the analysis, as were 
studies comparing a crystalloid with a colloid, or comparing 
two low-chloride crystalloids. Studies were also excluded 
if the intravenous fluids compared were given for mainte-
nance purposes, 'preloading/volume optimization' before 
surgery, priming of the cardiopulmonary bypass circuit, or 
the treatment of ischaemic stroke or subarachnoid haem-
orrhage. Study eligibility for inclusion in the meta-analysis 
was assessed and confirmed by two reviewers, and differ-
ences were resolved by discussion between reviewers. </p>

<p>Risk of bias assessment </p>

<p>Risk of bias was assessed using one of two approaches, 
depending on study design. For RCTs, the seven-category 
Review Manager risk of bias tool was used (<rs id="software-2" type="software">RevMan</rs> ver-
sion <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">5.2</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">The Cochrane Collaboration</rs>, Oxford, UK), with 
risk assessed as either high, unclear or low according 
to criteria outlined in the Cochrane Handbook for Sys-
tematic Reviews of Interventions 31 . For non-RCTs, the 
Newcastle-Ottawa Scale (NOS) 32 was used, in accor-
dance with previously published methodology 33 . Briefly, 
the NOS allots a maximum of nine points based on the 
representativeness of the intervention and control groups, 
ascertainment of intervention, absence of outcomes at 
study start, comparability of groups based on study design 
and analysis, blinded assessment/record linkage to confirm 
outcomes, sufficient length of follow-up and sufficiently 
low withdrawal rate. </p>

<p>Data extraction and outcomes </p>

<p>Data extracted, in duplicate using a standard form, included 
general study characteristics (authors, design), as well as 
information about the study population (age, setting, con-
dition/diagnosis), intervention (fluids compared, interven-
tion timing and volume) and outcomes (author definition of 
outcome, point estimates, summary statistics, author con-
clusions). 
For continuous variables, the mean(s.d.) value was 
extracted or derived from the reported data. When a study </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. BJS published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>www.bjs.co.uk 
BJS 2015; 102: 24-36 </p>

<p>on behalf of BJS Society Ltd. </p>



<p>M. L. Krajewski, K. Raghunathan, S. M. Paluszkiewicz, C. R. Schermer and A. D. Shaw </p>

<p>report did not provide variability data for a point estimate, 
the data were requested from the study's corresponding 
author. Data were included in the meta-analysis only when: 
mean(s.d.) values could be extracted or derived from the 
reported data; or study authors could provide clarification. 
Where ventilator-free days were reported, ventilation time 
was derived using the period over which ventilator-free 
time was measured. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>For dichotomous variables, RR and 95 per cent c.i. 
were calculated using a fixed-effect model and the 
Mantel-Haenszel statistical method. Studies that included 
a count of zero for both intervention groups for a given 
endpoint were not included in the analysis for that 
endpoint 34 . For continuous variables, the effect measure 
and 95 per cent c.i. were calculated using a fixed-effect 
model and the inverse-variance statistical method. The 
mean difference (MD) was used as the effect measure where </p>

<p>all studies reported the endpoint using the same units or 
scale. Alternatively, the standardized mean difference 
(SMD), which assumes that differences in the standard 
deviation reflect differences in measurement scales, was 
used as the effect measure when different studies reported 
the same endpoint using different scales or units. 
For continuous variables not reported as mean(s.d.) 
values, these statistics were derived from the reported data 
using published methodologies or approaches outlined 
in the Cochrane Handbook 31 . For continuous variables 
reported as median (range), the mean(s.d.) values were 
calculated according to methods published by Hozo and 
colleagues 35 . Data presented as the geometric mean (95 
per cent c.i.) of log-transformed data were converted 
to mean(s.d.) on the raw scale using the methodology 
of Higgins et al. 36 . For further details, see Appendix S1 
(supporting information). 
Forest plot generation and statistical analyses were 
performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">RevMan</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.2</rs>. P &lt; 0⋅050 was con-
sidered to be statistically significant. The RevMan program </p>

<p>Records identified through 
database searching 
n = 9964 </p>

<p>Additional records identified 
through other sources 
n = 6 </p>

<p>Records screened 
n = 7330 </p>

<p>Full-text articles 
assessed for eligibility 
n = 492 </p>

<p>Studies included in 
qualitative synthesis 
n = 21 (22 articles) </p>

<p>Studies included in 
quantitative synthesis 
(meta-analysis) 
n = 21 
(includes 1 study with 
2 unique articles) </p>

<p>RCT 
n = 15 </p>

<p>CCT 
n = 1 </p>

<p>Observational study 
n = 5 </p>

<p>Records excluded 
n = 6838 </p>

<p>Articles excluded n = 470 
Did not compare high-versus low-chloride crystalloid n = 286 
Not RCT, CCT or observational study n = 110 
Fluids not given for resuscitation/studied excluded population n = 69 
Did not examine key endpoints n = 5 </p>

<p>Records after duplicates removed 
n = 7330 </p>

<p>Fig. 1 PRISMA flow diagram showing study selection. RCT, randomized controlled trial; CCT, controlled clinical trial </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. BJS published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>www.bjs.co.uk 
BJS 2015; 102: 24-36 </p>

<p>on behalf of BJS Society Ltd. </p>

<p>Chloride content of resuscitation fluids </p>



<p>reports P values to one or two significant digits; where 
requested, a standard normal (Z) table was consulted 
to report P values to three decimal places 37 . For each 
endpoint analysed, statistical heterogeneity was examined 
using the I 2 statistic, which provides an estimate of the 
percentage of variation across studies arising from study 
heterogeneity rather than chance 38 . When substantial 
heterogeneity (I 2 greater than 60 per cent) was detected 
for an endpoint showing a statistically significant effect 
of high-versus low-chloride fluids, this heterogeneity was 
further investigated using a random-effects analysis model 
or subgroup analysis, as appropriate. When visual inspec-
tion of a forest plot suggested that the overall effect was 
driven by a single study (weight greater than 50 per cent), 
sensitivity analysis excluding this study was performed 39 . </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Included studies </p>

<p>In total, the database search yielded 7330 unique articles, 
of which 492 passed the initial screen and were reviewed 
for study inclusion (Fig. 1). Of these, 470 articles were 
excluded and 21 studies (in 22 articles) 10,12,14,26,27,40 -56 
met the inclusion criteria (Table 1). Studies comprised 15 
RCTs and six non-RCTs, and involved 6253 patients. 
The study by Yunos and colleagues reported data in 
two unique articles, with biochemical 55 and clinical 26 
outcomes published separately. Eleven studies examined 
critically ill patients requiring volume resuscitation in the 
ICU setting, and ten examined patients receiving these 
interventions in the perioperative period. In all included 
studies, the high-chloride intravenous crystalloid was 0⋅9 
per cent saline (chloride concentration approximately 
154 mmol/l) and the low-chloride intravenous crystalloid 
was either Ringer's lactate (chloride concentration about 
109 mmol/l), Hartmann's solution (chloride concentration 
about 111 mmol/l) or Plasma-Lyte ® (Baxter Health-
care, Deerfield, Illinois, USA) (chloride concentration 
98 mmol/l). Two studies 
12,40 compared three different 
intravenous fluids (0⋅9 per cent saline, Ringer's lactate 
and Plasma-Lyte ® ). For these studies, patients receiving 
Ringer's lactate and Plasma-Lyte ® were combined into 
a single low-chloride fluids group by deriving pooled 
mean(s.d.) values from the individual group data. </p>

<p>Risk of bias </p>

<p>The overall risk of bias of RCTs meeting study inclusion 
criteria was acceptable (Fig. S1, supporting information). 
None of the included RCTs was judged to have a high risk </p>

<p>of bias with respect to randomization or allocation conceal-
ment, although two studies presented unclear risks of bias, 
as specifics were not discussed. Blinding of participants and 
study personnel was ascertained for most studies; however, 
two reports indicated that study personnel were not blinded 
to the experimental intravenous fluid administered, and 
two additional reports did not adequately address blinding 
for an assessment to be made (Table S1, supporting infor-
mation). All included non-RCTs were allotted at least six 
of nine possible points using the NOS, suggesting an over-
all acceptable risk of bias (Fig. S2 and Table S2, supporting 
information). </p>

<p>Clinical endpoints </p>

<p>Meta-analysis results for clinical endpoints are sum-
marized in Figs 2-4. No statistically significant impact 
on mortality was found in the six studies that included 
this endpoint (RR 1⋅13, 95 per cent c.i. 0⋅92, 1⋅39; 
P = 0⋅230) (Fig. 2). High-chloride crystalloids were asso-
ciated with a significantly increased risk of AKI/renal 
failure (RR 1⋅64, 1⋅27 to 2⋅13; P &lt; 0⋅001) (Fig. 3) and 
hyperchloraemia/metabolic acidosis (RR 2⋅87, 1⋅95 to 
4⋅21; P &lt; 0⋅001) (Fig. 4). AKI/renal failure outcomes were 
defined by criteria set forth by the individual studies and 
were not uniform. For both mortality and AKI/renal 
failure, heterogeneity, estimated by the I 
2 statistic, was 0 
per cent, suggesting a consistent direction and magnitude 
of effect across studies. For hyperchloraemia/metabolic 
acidosis, each study indicated a RR greater than 1 (range 
from 2⋅12 to 16⋅37), but the overall heterogeneity (I 2 = 61 
per cent) led to a re-examination of the association using a 
random-effects model. This re-examination did not mean-
ingfully change the RR (4⋅07, 95 per cent c.i. 1⋅23 to 13⋅53; 
P = 0⋅022), suggesting that the observed heterogeneity was 
probably due to differences in effect magnitude rather 
than effect direction. 
Examination of ICU and/or hospital LOS revealed no 
significant association between chloride content and ICU 
LOS (SMD −0⋅01, 95 per cent c.i. −0⋅10 to 0⋅09; P = 0⋅897; 
I 
2 = 0 per cent) (Fig. S3, supporting information). How-
ever, hospital LOS appeared to favour high-chloride fluids 
(SMD −0⋅07, −0⋅13 to −0⋅01; P = 0⋅017; I 2 = 0 per cent) 
(Fig. S4, supporting information). </p>

<p>Surrogate endpoints </p>

<p>Analysis of surrogate endpoints revealed that high-chloride 
intravenous fluids were associated with significantly higher 
serum chloride levels (MD 3⋅70 (95 per cent c.i. 3⋅36 to 
4⋅04) mmol/l; P &lt; 0⋅001; I 2 = 98 per cent) (Fig. S5, support-
ing information), greater blood transfusion volume (SMD </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. BJS published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>www.bjs.co.uk 
BJS 2015; 102: 24-36 </p>

<p>on behalf of BJS Society Ltd. </p>



<p>M. L. Krajewski, K. Raghunathan, S. M. Paluszkiewicz, C. R. Schermer and A. D. Shaw </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of included studies </p>

<p>Reference 
Year 
Design 
Country Study population </p>

<p>Total study 
population 
size 
Interventions compared 
Key endpoints </p>

<p>Berger et al. 41 
2000 
Retrospective Switzerland Adults with thermal burns 
40 
Bicarbonated 0⋅9% saline versus 
Ringer's lactate </p>

<p>Mortality, acute renal injury, 
ICU LOS, mechanical 
ventilation time, 
hyperchloraemia/metabolic 
acidosis, urine output </p>

<p>Cho et al. 42 
2007 
RCT 
Korea 
Adults with 
rhabdomyolysis </p>

<p>28 
0⋅9% saline versus Ringer's lactate Serum chloride </p>

<p>Chua et al. 43 
2012 
Retrospective 
Australia 
Adults with severe DKA 
23 
0⋅9% saline versus Plasma-Lyte ® 
148 </p>

<p>ICU LOS, urine output </p>

<p>Cieza et al. 44 
2013 
Observational 
Peru 
Adults with severe 
dehydration </p>

<p>40 
0⋅9% saline versus Ringer's lactate Serum creatinine, serum 
chloride </p>

<p>Hadimioglu et al. 12 
2008 
RCT 
Turkey 
Adults undergoing kidney 
transplantation </p>

<p>90* 
0⋅9% saline versus Plasma-Lyte ® 
and Ringer's lactate </p>

<p>Acute renal injury, serum 
creatinine, serum chloride, 
urine output </p>

<p>Hasman et al. 40 
2012 
RCT 
Turkey 
Adults with moderate or 
severe dehydration </p>

<p>90* 
0⋅9% saline versus Plasma-Lyte ® 
and Ringer's lactate </p>

<p>Serum chloride </p>

<p>Khajavi et al. 45 
2008 
RCT 
Iran 
Adults undergoing kidney 
transplantation </p>

<p>52 
0⋅9% saline versus Ringer's lactate Serum creatinine, urine output </p>

<p>Kim et al. 46 
2013 
RCT 
Korea 
Adults undergoing kidney 
transplantation </p>

<p>60 
0⋅9% saline versus Plasma-Lyte ® A Serum creatinine, serum 
chloride, urine output, 
transfusion volume </p>

<p>Mahajan et al. 47 
2012 
RCT 
India 
Children with severe 
dehydration </p>

<p>22 
0⋅9% saline versus Ringer's lactate Mortality, hospital LOS, serum 
chloride </p>

<p>Mahler et al. 48 
2011 
RCT 
USA 
Adults with DKA 
45 
0⋅9% saline versus Plasma-Lyte ® A Serum chloride </p>

<p>Modi et al. 49 
2012 
RCT 
Saudi Arabia Adults undergoing kidney 
transplantation </p>

<p>74 
0⋅9% saline versus Ringer's lactate Serum chloride, serum 
creatinine </p>

<p>O'Malley et al. 50 
2005 
RCT 
USA 
Adults undergoing renal 
transplantation </p>

<p>51 
0⋅9% saline versus Ringer's lactate Acute renal injury, hospital 
LOS, hyperchloraemia/ 
metabolic acidosis, serum 
creatinine, serum chloride, 
urine output </p>

<p>Scheingraber et al. 10 
1999 
RCT 
Germany 
Adults undergoing elective 
abdominal 
gynaecological surgery </p>

<p>24 
0⋅9% saline versus Ringer's lactate Urine output </p>

<p>Shaw et al. 27 
2012 
Retrospective 
USA 
Adult surgical patients 
3704 † 
0⋅9% saline versus Plasma-Lyte ® 
148 or Plasma-Lyte ® A </p>

<p>Mortality, acute kidney injury, 
hospital LOS, mechanical 
ventilation time </p>

<p>Takil et al. 51 
2002 
RCT 
Turkey 
Adult spinal surgery 
patients </p>

<p>30 
0⋅9% saline versus Ringer's lactate Hospital LOS, ICU LOS, serum 
chloride, urine output, 
transfusion volume </p>

<p>Van Zyl et al. 52 
2012 
RCT 
South Africa Adults with DKA 
54 
0⋅9% saline versus Ringer's lactate Hospital LOS, serum 
creatinine, serum chloride </p>

<p>Waters et al. 14 
2001 
RCT 
USA 
Adult patients undergoing 
aortic reconstructive 
surgery </p>

<p>66 
0⋅9% saline versus Ringer's lactate Mortality, acute renal injury, 
hospital LOS, ICU LOS, 
mechanical ventilation time, 
serum creatinine, serum 
chloride, urine output, 
transfusion volume </p>

<p>Wu et al. 53 
2011 
RCT 
USA 
Adults with acute 
pancreatitis </p>

<p>40 
0⋅9% saline versus Ringer's lactate Acute renal injury, hospital LOS </p>

<p>Young et al. 54 
2014 
RCT 
USA 
Adults with traumatic 
injury </p>

<p>65 
0⋅9% saline versus Plasma-Lyte ® A Mortality, acute renal injury, 
hospital LOS, ICU LOS, 
mechanical ventilation time, 
serum creatinine, serum 
chloride, urine output, 
transfusion volume </p>

<p>Yunos et al. 26,55 
2011, 2012 
CCT 
Australia 
Adult ICU patients 
1533 
Chloride-rich fluids (0⋅9% saline, 
4% succinylated gelatin solution, 
4% albumin) versus balanced 
solutions (Hartmann's, 
Plasma-Lyte ® 148, chloride-poor 
20% albumin) </p>

<p>Mortality, acute renal injury, 
hospital LOS, ICU LOS, 
serum chloride, serum 
creatinine, urine output </p>

<p>Zunini et al. 56 
2011 
Retrospective 
Uruguay 
Children undergoing 
craniofacial surgery </p>

<p>122 
0⋅9% saline versus Ringer's lactate Hyperchloraemia/metabolic 
acidosis </p>

<p>*Studies compared three different intravenous fluids: 0⋅9 per cent saline, Ringer's lactate and Plasma-Lyte ® (Baxter Healthcare, Deerfield, Illinois, USA); 
pooled means and variances were derived for the Ringer's lactate and Plasma-Lyte ® groups in both cases.  †Propensity-matched population. ICU, 
intensive care unit; LOS, length of stay; RCT, randomized controlled trial; DKA, diabetic ketoacidosis; CCT, controlled clinical trial. </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. BJS published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>www.bjs.co.uk 
BJS 2015; 102: 24-36 </p>

<p>on behalf of BJS Society Ltd. </p>

<p>Chloride content of resuscitation fluids </p>



<p>Reference </p>

<p>RCTs 
Mahajan et al. 47  Waters et al. 14  Young et al. 54  Subtotal </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: χ 2 = 0·38, 2 d.f., P = 0·82; I 2 = 0% 
Test for overall effect: Z = 0·45, P = 0·65 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: χ 2 = 0·04, 1 d.f., P = 0·84; I 2 = 0% 
Test for overall effect: Z = 0·72, P = 0·47 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: χ 2 = 0·46, 5 d.f., P = 0·99; I 2 = 0% </p>

<p>Test for subgroup differences: χ 2 = 0·05, 2 d.f., P = 0·98; I 2 = 0% </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z = 1·20, P = 0·23 </p>

<p>CCTs </p>

<p>Yunos et al. 26,55 
Subtotal </p>

<p>Berger et al. 41  Shaw et al. 27  Subtotal </p>

<p>Total </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: not applicable 
Test for overall effect: Z = 0·87, P = 0·38 </p>

<p>Observational/retrospective studies </p>

<p>Mortality </p>

<p>High-chloride </p>

<p>1 of 11 
1 of 33 
8 of 33 
10 of 77 </p>

<p>112 of 760 
112 of 760 </p>

<p>4 of 20 
93 of 2778 
97 of 2798 </p>

<p>219 of 3635 
140 of 1795 </p>

<p>3 of 20 
27 of 926 
30 of 946 </p>

<p>2·0 
26·4 
28·4 </p>

<p>1·13 (0·92, 1·39) </p>

<p>1·16 (0.78, 1·74) </p>

<p>1·15 (0.75, 1·75) </p>

<p>1·33 (0·34, 5·21) </p>

<p>1·12 (0·87, 1·43) </p>

<p>1·12 (0·87, 1·43) </p>

<p>1·21 (0·53, 2·72) </p>

<p>1·11 (0·45, 2·70) </p>

<p>1·00 (0·07, 15·33) </p>

<p>3·00 (0·14, 66·53) </p>

<p>100·0 </p>

<p>102 of 773 
102 of 773 </p>

<p>0 of 11 
1 of 33 
7 of 32 
8 of 76 </p>

<p>0·3 </p>

<p>4·6 </p>

<p>0·7 </p>

<p>5·6 </p>

<p>66·0 
66·0 </p>

<p>Low-chloride 
Weight (%) 
Risk ratio </p>

<p>0·2 </p>

<p>Favours high chloride Favours low chloride </p>

<p>1 
5 
20 
0·05 </p>

<p>Risk ratio </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Forest plot illustrating mortality risk following volume resuscitation with high-chloride versus low-chloride intravenous fluids. 
Where necessary, mortality incidence was derived from reported survival. A Mantel-Haenszel fixed-effect model was used for 
meta-analysis. Risk ratios are shown with 95 per cent c.i. RCT, randomized controlled trial; CCT, controlled clinical trial </p>

<p>0.35, 0⋅07 to 0⋅63; P = 0⋅014; I 
2 = 0 per cent) (Fig. 5) and 
longer mechanical ventilation time (SMD 0⋅15, 0⋅08 to 
0⋅23; P &lt; 0⋅001; I 2 = 17 per cent) (Fig. S6, supporting infor-
mation). There was no significant difference between high-
versus low-chloride intravenous fluids with respect to serum 
creatinine levels (SMD 0⋅10, −0⋅02 to 0⋅23; P = 0⋅095; 
I 2 = 18 per cent) (Fig. S7, supporting information) and a 
small effect on urine output (SMD 0⋅17, 0⋅02 to 0⋅32; 
P = 0⋅030; I 
2 = 70 per cent) (Fig. S8, supporting informa-
tion). Given the observed heterogeneity, urine output was 
re-evaluated using a random-effects model, which demon-
strated a non-significant effect of high-versus low-chloride 
intravenous fluids (SMD 0⋅08, −0⋅22 to 0⋅38; P = 0⋅589). </p>

<p>Sensitivity analyses </p>

<p>For some endpoints, forest plot inspection indicated that 
overall effect measures were driven largely by a single 
heavily weighted study (in all cases, either Yunos et al. 26,55 , 
Zunini et al. 56 or Shaw et al. 27 ). To understand how these 
individual studies might influence effect estimates, sensitiv-
ity analyses were repeated after excluding them. Exclusion 
of the Yunos et al. 26,55 and Zunini et al. 56 studies from the </p>

<p>analyses of AKI/renal failure, hyperchloraemia/metabolic 
acidosis and serum chloride did not affect the direction 
of effect, but did convert to a non-statistically significant 
effect for the AKI/renal failure endpoint (Table 2). Exclu-
sion of the Shaw et al. 
27 study from the pooled analysis 
of mechanical ventilation time also resulted in a shift to 
an effect that was not statistically significant. Similarly, 
when the Shaw et al. 27 study was excluded from the LOS 
analyses, no statistically significant effect was observed. 
Exclusion of the Yunos et al. 26 study from the mortality 
analysis had no impact. 
Significant heterogeneity with respect to reported serum 
chloride levels (I 2 = 98 per cent) was investigated by 
subgroup analysis based on timing of chloride measure-
ment and by using a random-effects model. Although 
high-chloride fluids were associated with higher serum 
chloride levels in both RCT subgroups (Fig. S5, supporting 
information), this analysis suggests that subgroup differ-
ences do exist based on time point of measurement (MD 
11⋅18 (95 per cent c.i. 10⋅29 to 12⋅06) mmol/l; P &lt; 0⋅001 
for studies reporting intraoperative or postoperative lev-
els, versus MD 2⋅24 (1⋅60 to 2⋅89) mmol/l; P &lt; 0⋅001 for 
studies reporting levels at other time points). Analysis of </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. BJS published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>www.bjs.co.uk 
BJS 2015; 102: 24-36 </p>

<p>on behalf of BJS Society Ltd. </p>



<p>M. L. Krajewski, K. Raghunathan, S. M. Paluszkiewicz, C. R. Schermer and A. D. Shaw </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>RCTs </p>

<p>CCTs </p>

<p>Hadimioglu et al. 12  O'Malley et al. 50  Waters et al. 14  Wu et al. 53  Young et al. 54  Subtotal </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: χ 2 = 0·31, 4 d.f., P = 0·99; I 2 = 0% 
Test for overall effect: Z = 1·44, P = 0·15 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: χ 2 = 0·16, 1 d.f., P = 0·69; I 2 = 0% 
Test for overall effect: Z = 1·04, P = 0·30 </p>

<p>Yunos et al. 26,55 
Subtotal 
Heterogeneity: not applicable 
Test for overall effect: Z = 3·33, P &lt; 0·001 </p>

<p>Observational/retrospective studies 
Berger et al. 41 
Shaw et al. 27 
Subtotal </p>

<p>Total </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: χ 2 = 0·47, 7 d.f., P = 1·00; I 2 = 0% </p>

<p>Test for subgroup differences: χ 2 = 0·00, 2 d.f., P = 1·00; I 2 = 0% </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z = 3·76, P &lt; 0·001 </p>

<p>AKI/renal failure </p>

<p>High-chloride </p>

<p>3 of 30 
2 of 26 
5 of 33 
2 of 21 
6 of 24 
18 of 134 </p>

<p>105 of 760 
105 of 760 </p>

<p>1 of 20 
23 of 2778 
24 of 2798 </p>

<p>147 of 3692 
82 of 1878 </p>

<p>0 of 20 
5 of 926 
5 of 946 </p>

<p>1·81 (0·18, 18·39) 
1·83 (0·52, 6·46) 
1·66 (0·83, 3·31) </p>

<p>1·64 (1·23, 2·20) 
1·64 (1·23, 2·20) </p>

<p>3·00 (0·13, 69·52) 
1·53 (0·58, 4·02) 
1·63 (0·65, 4·07) </p>

<p>1·64 (1·27, 2·13) </p>

<p>1·25 (0·37, 4·25) </p>

<p>1·92 (0·19, 19·90) </p>

<p>2·00 (0·43, 9·32) 
3 of 60 
1 of 25 
4 of 33 
1 of 19 
3 of 22 
12 of 159 </p>

<p>65 of 773 
65 of 773 </p>

<p>2·4 </p>

<p>4·8 </p>

<p>1·2 </p>

<p>1·3 
3·7 
13·4 </p>

<p>77·0 
77·0 </p>

<p>0·6 
9·0 
9·6 </p>

<p>100·0 </p>

<p>Low-chloride 
Weight (%) 
Risk ratio </p>

<p>0·1 </p>

<p>Favours high chloride Favours low chloride </p>

<p>1 
10 
100 
0·01 </p>

<p>Risk ratio </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Forest plot illustrating acute kidney injury (AKI)/renal failure risk following volume resuscitation with high-chloride versus 
low-chloride intravenous fluids. A Mantel-Haenszel fixed-effect model was used for meta-analysis. Risk ratios are shown with 95 per 
cent c.i. RCT, randomized controlled trial; CCT, controlled clinical trial </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>RCTs 
O'Malley et al. </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>Subtotal </p>

<p>Subtotal </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: not applicable 
Test for overall effect: Z = 1·96, P = 0·05 </p>

<p>Berger et al. </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>Observational/retrospective studies </p>

<p>Zunini et al. </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: χ 
2 = 2·66, 1 d.f., P = 0·10; I 
2 = 62% 
Test for overall effect: Z = 4·78, P &lt; 0·001 </p>

<p>Total </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: χ 
2 = 5·17, 2 d.f., P = 0·08; I 
2 = 61% </p>

<p>Test for subgroup differences: χ 
2 = 1·67, 1 d.f., P = 0·20; I 
2 = 40·1% </p>

<p>Test for overall effect: Z = 5·36, P &lt; 0·001 </p>

<p>Hyperchloraemia/metabolic acidosis </p>

<p>High-chloride </p>

<p>8 of 26 
8 of 26 </p>

<p>13 of 20 </p>

<p>43 of 54 
56 of 74 </p>

<p>2 of 20 </p>

<p>18 of 48 
20 of 68 </p>

<p>9·3 </p>

<p>88·4 
97·6 </p>

<p>64 of 100 
20 of 93 </p>

<p>16·37 (0·99, 269·44) </p>

<p>6·50 (1·68, 25·16) </p>

<p>2·12 (1·44, 3·13) 
2·54 (1·73, 3·72) </p>

<p>2·87 (1·95, 4·21) </p>

<p>16·37 (0·99, 269·44) 
0 of 25 
0 of 25 </p>

<p>2·4 
2·4 </p>

<p>100·0 </p>

<p>Low-chloride 
Weight (%) 
Risk ratio </p>

<p>0·1 </p>

<p>Favours high chloride 
Favours low chloride </p>

<p>1 
10 
1000 
0·001 </p>

<p>Risk ratio </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Forest plot illustrating hyperchloraemia/metabolic acidosis risk following volume resuscitation with high-chloride versus 
low-chloride intravenous fluids. A Mantel-Haenszel fixed-effect model was used for meta-analysis. Risk ratios are shown with 95 per 
cent c.i. RCT, randomized controlled trial; CCT, controlled clinical trial </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. BJS published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>www.bjs.co.uk 
BJS 2015; 102: 24-36 </p>

<p>on behalf of BJS Society Ltd. </p>

<p>Chloride content of resuscitation fluids </p>



<p>Reference </p>

<p>Kim et al. 46   Takil et al. 51   Waters et al. 14   Young et al. 54   Total </p>

<p>Heterogeneity: χ 2 = 0·60, 3 d.f., P = 0·90; I 2 = 0% 
Test for overall effect: Z = 2·45, P = 0·01 </p>

<p>Transfusion volume </p>

<p>High-chloride </p>

<p>459(279) </p>

<p>1280(560) </p>

<p>780(489) </p>

<p>3·2(8·3) </p>

<p>332(314) </p>

<p>960(680) </p>

<p>560(776) </p>

<p>1·8(7·6) </p>

<p>29·6 </p>

<p>14·6 </p>

<p>32·8 </p>

<p>23·1 </p>

<p>0·42 (-0·09, 0·93) </p>

<p>0·50 (-0·23, 1·23) </p>

<p>0·34 (-0·15, 0·82) </p>

<p>0·17 (-0·41, 0·75) </p>

<p>0·35 (0·07, 0·63) 
100·0 </p>

<p>Low-chloride 
Weight (%) 
SMD </p>

<p>-0·5 </p>

<p>Favours high chloride Favours low chloride </p>

<p>0 
0 ·5 
1 
-1 </p>

<p>SMD </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Forest plot illustrating mean(s.d.) blood transfusion volume following volume resuscitation with high-chloride versus low-chloride 
intravenous fluids. All included studies reporting this endpoint were randomized controlled trials. An inverse-variance fixed-effect 
model was used for meta-analysis. Standardized mean differences (SMDs) are shown with 95 per cent c.i. </p>

<p>Table 2 Summary of sensitivity analyses </p>

<p>Overall analysis 
Sensitivity analysis </p>

<p>Excluded study </p>

<p>Effect size 
P 
Reference 
Weight (%) 
Effect size 
P </p>

<p>Clinical endpoints 
Acute kidney injury 
RR 1⋅64 (1⋅27, 2⋅13) 
&lt; 0⋅001 
Yunos et al. 26 
77⋅0 
R R 1 ⋅65 (0⋅95, 2⋅87) 
0⋅078 
Hyperchloraemia/metabolic acidosis 
RR 2⋅87 (1⋅95, 4⋅21) 
&lt; 0⋅001 
Zunini et al. 56 
65⋅5 
R R 8 ⋅50 (2⋅49, 29⋅08) 
0⋅001 
Mortality 
RR 1⋅13 (0⋅92, 1⋅39) 
0⋅230 
Yunos et al. 26  65⋅0 
R R 1 ⋅17 (0⋅81, 1⋅68) 
0⋅401 
ICU LOS 
SMD −0⋅01 (−0⋅10, 0⋅09) 
0⋅897 
Yunos et al. 26 
88⋅7 
S M D−0⋅07 (−0⋅35, 0⋅21) 
0⋅624 
Hospital LOS 
SMD −0⋅07 (−0⋅13, −0⋅01) 
0⋅017 
Shaw et al. 27 
60⋅1 
S M D−0⋅01 (−0⋅10, 0⋅08) 
0⋅849 
Surrogate endpoints 
Serum chloride 
MD 3⋅70 (3⋅36, 4⋅04) 
&lt; 0⋅001 
Yunos et al. 55  55⋅3 
M D 5 ⋅31 (4⋅79, 5⋅82) 
&lt; 0⋅001 
Mechanical ventilation time 
SMD 0⋅15 (0⋅08, 0⋅23) 
&lt; 0⋅001 
Shaw et al. 27 
95⋅1 
S M D−0⋅06 (−0⋅38, 0⋅27) 
0⋅734 </p>

<p>Values in parentheses are 95 per cent c.i. RR, risk ratio; ICU, intensive care unit; LOS, length of stay; SMD, standardized mean difference; MD, mean 
difference. </p>

<p>serum chloride using a random-effects model revealed no 
significant change in effect measure or significance (MD 
5⋅06 (2⋅30 to 7⋅82) mmol/l; P &lt; 0⋅001). 
Two studies 47,56 included in the present analysis involved 
paediatric patients. Although both studies were small (22 
and 122 patients respectively) and therefore unlikely to 
impact significantly on the effect estimates, sensitivity anal-
ysis excluding these two trials was performed in order to 
account for potential differences in fluid physiology in 
paediatric versus adult patients. There was no impact on 
either effect direction or significance for any of the mea-
sured endpoints when these studies were excluded: mor-
tality (RR 1⋅13, 95 per cent c.i. 0⋅92 to 1⋅39; P = 0⋅250), 
hospital LOS (SMD −0⋅07, −0⋅13 to −0⋅02; P = 0⋅013), 
hyperchloraemia/metabolic acidosis (RR 8⋅50, 2⋅49 to 29⋅0; 
P &lt; 0⋅001) or serum chloride (MD 4⋅02 (3⋅66 to 4⋅37) 
mmol/l; P &lt; 0⋅001). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Meta-analysis of all available studies demonstrated a sig-
nificantly higher risk of AKI, metabolic acidosis, blood </p>

<p>transfusion and time on mechanical ventilation with 
high-chloride fluid resuscitation. The association between 
high-chloride fluids, metabolic acidosis and higher serum 
chloride levels is supported by several studies 10,11,54  that did not meet the inclusion criteria for the present 
meta-analysis, and provides face validity for a conceptual 
mechanism of deleterious effects of hyperchloraemia. No 
increased risk for mortality was found. 
High-chloride fluids were significantly associated with 
an increased risk of AKI/renal failure. This endpoint was 
driven heavily by one study 26 , and sensitivity analysis 
excluding this study showed the same direction of effect, 
but loss of statistical significance. Each remaining study 
demonstrated a directionally similar association between 
increased AKI/renal failure and high-chloride fluids. One 
limitation in interpreting these data is the lack of uni-
formity among definitions of AKI. Ideally a standardized 
definition would be applied for the analysis; however, this 
was not possible with the available data. Moreover, serum 
creatinine concentration, a surrogate marker of renal 
function, did not demonstrate an association with the fluid 
chloride content. Failure to detect such an association </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. BJS published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>www.bjs.co.uk 
BJS 2015; 102: 24-36 </p>

<p>on behalf of BJS Society Ltd. </p>



<p>M. L. Krajewski, K. Raghunathan, S. M. Paluszkiewicz, C. R. Schermer and A. D. Shaw </p>

<p>may be related to reporting of serum creatinine levels at 
variable time points, and the possibility that the magnitude 
of differences in serum creatinine concentration may vary 
with time. 
Greater urine output was significantly associated with 
high-chloride fluids, which may appear inconsistent 
with greater risk of AKI. However, the effect of fluid 
chloride content on urinary output may be largely 
time-dependent 57,58 , and in this context urine output 
may not be a useful surrogate measure of renal function. 
Variability in the timing of urine output measurements 
and diuretic use may also confound these results. In light 
of the variability in AKI/renal failure definitions, timing of 
creatinine measurement and effects on urine output, this 
AKI harm signal should be interpreted cautiously. 
No reported difference in mortality may reflect either no 
true difference, variability in the time periods over which 
mortality was reported, inadequate sample size to detect a 
difference, or variability in the risk factors in the included 
patient populations. Because this meta-analysis included 
studies in both perioperative and ICU settings, lower-risk 
patients were included than if the analysis had been limited 
solely to critical illness, lowering the overall mortality rate 
and thus decreasing the likelihood of detecting a possible 
mortality signal. It is also conceivable that an increased risk 
of AKI may occur without an increase in short-term mor-
tality. These factors may help to explain why an increase 
in AKI, but not mortality, was observed with high-chloride 
crystalloid use in this meta-analysis. 
Two recent studies ineligible for this meta-analysis 
have examined the relationship between mortality and 
either hyperchloraemia 25 or crystalloid fluid choice 59 . 
A retrospective, propensity-matched, cohort study 25 of 
surgical patients demonstrated a significant association 
between hyperchloraemia and mortality, as well as AKI. 
Notably, the relationship between serum chloride and fluid 
administered was not assessed. In a propensity-matched 
cohort study 59 of non-operative patients with 
vasopressor-dependent sepsis, use of balanced fluids 
(low-chloride by the present definition) was associated 
with lower in-hospital mortality, but no effect was found 
for AKI. One could infer that, because high-chloride fluids 
lead to hyperchloraemia and hyperchloraemia is associated 
with mortality, high-chloride fluids must be associated 
with mortality. However, the relationship is not clearly 
true in all populations studied and may vary based on risk. 
Among the four eligible studies 14,46,51,54 reporting trans-
fusion outcomes, all reported at least a small or modest 31,60  increase in transfusion volume with high-chloride fluid 
administration. Shaw and co-workers 27 also demonstrated 
an association between high-chloride fluids and greater </p>

<p>transfusion volume, but the study was not included in the 
analysis owing to lack of variability data. Although the total 
number of patients included in the present meta-analysis 
of blood transfusion volume was low (high-chloride, 102; 
low-chloride, 100), the potential for a true difference raises 
relevant questions. Clinicians may consider any difference 
meaningful given the expense and risks associated with 
red cell transfusions 61,62 . Although causality has not been 
established between high-chloride fluids and increased 
transfusion, the potential clinical impact of a true effect is 
hypothesis-generating. 
When administered in large volumes, 0⋅9 per cent saline 
has been shown to cause coagulopathy 63,64 . Total volumes 
of fluid administered did not vary substantially between the 
groups (Table S3, supporting information), suggesting that 
dilutional coagulopathy does not account for the observed 
differences in transfusion. Mechanisms of saline-induced 
coagulopathy are not fully known, and the data lead us 
to consider whether hyperchloraemia/acidosis has an inde-
pendent effect on coagulation. Alternatively, a reverse asso-
ciation cannot be excluded, in that fewer transfusions may 
have been administered in the low-chloride groups owing 
to the possibility of incompatibility with citrated blood. 
However, in two 46,54 of the four studies, the low-chloride 
solution did not contain calcium, and in one 14 of the other 
studies the providers were blinded to the fluid that was 
being administered. 
Findings for additional endpoints investigated should 
not be considered definitive, owing to the low event rate 
and small sample size. Further studies including these 
endpoints are needed to arrive at firm conclusions. 
Combining RCTs, CCTs and observational studies may 
provide more generalizable results and help to offset the 
limitations that accompany the often low event rates in 
smaller RCTs 33,65 -68 . In addition, a recent meta-analysis 68 
demonstrated no significant differences between the 
risks of adverse events between RCTs and observational 
studies, leading the authors to advocate the inclusion of 
a broad range of studies when analysing harm signals. 
The present authors believe that the addition of obser-
vational data strengthens this study and the influence of 
observable confounding variables is specifically reduced by 
propensity-matching. 
Combining RCTs and non-RCTs could alternatively be 
viewed as a limitation of this study, as some advocate that 
data from RCTs and observational studies should not be 
pooled for analysis; rather, if the RCTs and observational 
studies warrant equal confidence, both types of evidence 
should be presented separately 69 . As such, in addition 
to presenting the overall effect in the forest plots, the 
studies are grouped by type so that plots may be visualized </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. BJS published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>www.bjs.co.uk 
BJS 2015; 102: 24-36 </p>

<p>on behalf of BJS Society Ltd. </p>

<p>Chloride content of resuscitation fluids </p>



<p>accordingly. Despite inclusion of observational studies, 
the total number of patients remains low and several out-
comes were examined in only a small number of studies. 
Further limitations include variability in the populations 
studied, the potential for significant bias in observational 
studies, and variability in outcome assessment. There is 
also potential for bias due to the exclusion of abstracts and 
non-English-language manuscripts. Assessment for publi-
cation bias was not possible owing to the small number of 
studies that met the inclusion criteria. 
The present findings argue against the intravenous 
administration of supraphysiological concentrations of 
chloride (above 111 mmol/l), yet most studies were small 
in size, thereby preventing firm conclusions from being 
drawn. These findings underscore the need for large, well 
designed RCTs that are adequately powered to detect 
differences in outcomes such as mortality and morbidity, 
including AKI. This provides an opportunity for interna-
tional collaboration 70 in surgical and critical care research; 
already, the Australian and New Zealand Intensive Care 
Society (ANZICS) Clinical Trials Group has begun enrol-
ment in the SPLIT study 71 comparing 0⋅9 per cent saline 
with Plasma-Lyte ® 148 for fluid therapy in the ICU. 
Future considerations could include a priori subgroup 
distinctions such as comparison of medical versus surgical 
patients, or low-risk versus high-risk surgical patients. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors thank the authors of reviewed studies, who 
kindly provided unpublished data for incorporation into 
the meta-analysis, as well as F. Peyerl of Boston Strategic 
Partners, for managerial support. 
This study was designed and conducted at Boston Strate-
gic Partners, Boston, Massachusetts, USA, in collabo-
ration with Duke University Medical Center, Durham, 
North Carolina, USA, with remote management by Baxter 
Healthcare Corporation, Deerfield, Illinois, USA, which 
funded the study. S.M.P. is an employee of Boston Strategic 
Partners, Inc., funded by Baxter Healthcare Corporation 
to perform the analysis. C.R.S. is an employee of Baxter 
Healthcare Corporation. A.D.S. has received payment for 
consulting services provided to Baxter Healthcare Corpo-
ration. 
Disclosure: The authors declare no further conflict of inter-
est. </p>



<p>© 2014 The Authors. BJS published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>www.bjs.co.uk 
BJS 2015; 102: 24-36 </p>

<p>on behalf of BJS Society Ltd. </p>



<p>M. L. Krajewski, K. Raghunathan, S. M. Paluszkiewicz, C. R. Schermer and A. D. Shaw </p>



<p>© 2014 The Authors. BJS published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>www.bjs.co.uk 
BJS 2015; 102: 24-36 </p>

<p>on behalf of BJS Society Ltd. </p>

<p>Chloride content of resuscitation fluids </p>





<p>© 2014 The Authors. BJS published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>www.bjs.co.uk 
BJS 2015; 102: 24-36 </p>

<p>on behalf of BJS Society Ltd. </p>



<p>M. L. Krajewski, K. Raghunathan, S. M. Paluszkiewicz, C. R. Schermer and A. D. Shaw </p>

<p>Supporting information </p>

<p>Additional supporting information may be found in the online version of this article: </p>

<p>Appendix S1 Electronic health database search terms (Word document) </p>

<p>Fig. S1 Risk of bias graph for randomized controlled trials meeting meta-analysis inclusion criteria 
(Word document) </p>

<p>Fig. S2 Risk of bias graph for non-randomized studies meeting meta-analysis inclusion criteria (Word document) </p>

<p>Fig. S3 Analysis of intensive care unit (ICU) length of stay following volume resuscitation with high-chloride versus 
low-chloride intravenous fluids (Word document) </p>

<p>Fig. S4 Analysis of hospital length of stay following volume resuscitation with high-chloride versus low-chloride 
intravenous fluids (Word document) </p>

<p>Fig. S5 Serum chloride concentration following volume resuscitation with high-chloride versus low-chloride 
intravenous fluids (Word document) </p>

<p>Fig. S6 Analysis of mechanical ventilation time following volume resuscitation with high-chloride versus 
low-chloride intravenous fluids (Word document) </p>

<p>Fig. S7 Analysis of serum creatinine concentration following volume resuscitation with high-chloride versus 
low-chloride intravenous fluids (Word document) </p>

<p>Fig. S8 Analysis of urine output following volume resuscitation with high-chloride versus low-chloride intravenous 
fluids (Word document) </p>

<p>Table S1 Risk of bias of included randomized controlled trials (Word document) </p>

<p>Table S2 Risk of bias of included non-randomized studies (Word document) </p>

<p>Table S3 Study fluid volumes received (Word document) </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. BJS published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>www.bjs.co.uk 
BJS 2015; 102: 24-36 </p>

<p>on behalf of BJS Society Ltd. </p>

</text></tei>