<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4857864" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: Low heart rate variability (HRV) has been confirmed in heroin users, but the effects of heart-rate-variability-biofeed-
back in heroin users remain unknown. This study examined (1) correlations between depression and HRV indices; (2) group 
differences in HRV indices among a heroin-user group, a group with major depressive disorder but no heroin use, and healthy 
controls; and (3) the effects of heart-rate-variability-biofeedback on depressive symptoms, HRV indices, and respiratory rates 
within the heroin group. 
Methods: All participants completed a depression questionnaire and underwent electrocardiogram measurements, and group 
differences in baseline HRV indices were examined. The heroin group underwent electrocardiogram and respiration rate meas-
urements at baseline, during a depressive condition, and during a happiness condition, before and after which they took part 
in the heart-rate-variability-biofeedback program. The effects of heart-rate-variability-biofeedback on depressive symptoms, 
HRV indices, and respiration rates were examined. 
Results: There was a negative correlation between depression and high frequency of HRV, and a positive correlation between 
depression and low frequency to high frequency ratio of HRV. The heroin group had a lower overall and high frequency of 
HRV, and a higher low frequency/high frequency ratio than healthy controls. The heart-rate-variability-biofeedback intervention 
increased HRV indices and decreased respiratory rates from pre-intervention to post-intervention. 
Conclusion: Reduced parasympathetic and increased sympathetic activations were found in heroin users. Heart-rate-variability-
biofeedback was an effective non-pharmacological intervention to restore autonomic balance. </p>

<p>The prevalence of heroin use has increased in recent 
years. 
1-3) Heroin use can cause significant psychosocial 
problems such as unemployment and criminal activity, as 
well as compromising the user's functioning. 
4) A high pro-
portion of heroin users have comorbid psychiatric 
disorders. 
1) The prevalence of major depressive episodes 
among heroin users has been found to be 25% to 26%. </p>

<p>1,5) </p>

<p>Comorbidity with depression compromises the heroin 
user's prognosis, increasing the risk of relapsing into her-
oin use, and suicide. </p>

<p>6) </p>

<p>Previous neurobiological research has found that her-
oin use may damage the user's limbic system and locus 
ceruleus, which causes neurotransmitter changes. </p>

<p>7) </p>

<p>However, few studies have explored the relationships be-
tween psychophysiological responses and heroin use. 
Heroin withdrawal may accompany physiological re-
sponses, such as restlessness, cold sweats, cold flashes, 
goose bumps, an increased heart rate, an elevated temper-
ature, an elevated pulse, a sharp elevation in blood pres-
sure, sweating, shallow breathing, insomnia, muscle and 
bone pain, diarrhea, nausea, and vomiting. 
8,9) Most of 
these heroin withdrawal symptoms involve increased 
sympathetic nervous system (SNS) activation, decreased 
parasympathetic nervous system (PNS) activation, and/or 
decreased cardiac vagal activity. 
10) A meta-analysis of the 
cue-reactivity paradigm found that an increased heart rate, 
an increase in sweat gland activity, and a decreased skin 
temperature were the key physiological indicators of a </p>

<p>Heart Rate Variability Biofeedback in Heroin Users 169 </p>

<p>craving for an addictive substance. 
11) Yu et al. 
12) also 
found that heroin-related imagery scripts and para-
phernalia were able to induce cravings and changes in car-
diovascular function, including an increase in systolic and 
diastolic blood pressure, and an increased heart rate. 
The results of the previous studies described above in-
dicate the importance of studying heart rate variability 
(HRV) among heroin users. HRV measures the variation 
in heart beat intervals, which is influenced by SNS and 
PNS input to the sino-atrial node of the heart. 
13) Increased 
PNS activation (or vagal activity) increases HRV, while 
increased SNS activation (or sympatho-vagal imbalance) 
decreases HRV. 
14) Regarding the interpretation of HRV in-
dices, standard deviation of NN intervals (SDNN) and to-
tal power of HRV are indicated the overall HRV, low fre-
quency (LF) is most likely affected both by cardiac SNS 
and PNS, and high frequency (HF) is an index of PNS 
activation. 
13,14) HRV is related to an individual's overall 
physical condition 
15,16) and/or his or her mental health. </p>

<p>17-19) </p>

<p>Reduced HRV has been found in heroin users 
10) and pa-
tients with major depressive disorder (MDD). 
2,20) Lower 
SDNN and HF indices have been found to be related to 
emotional dysregulation and social disability among pa-
tients with MDD. 
21-23) Compared with healthy controls, 
recently relapsed heroin users show lower heart rate var-
iance, reduced total power, and a lower HF HRV. 
10) How-
ever, few studies have examined the difference in HRV in-
dices between heroin users with depressive symptoms and 
patients with MDD. 
Previous studies have found that methadone main-
tenance therapy is able to affect the HF index among her-
oin users, 
10,24) and bring about an increase in total power 
and the LF index among heroin users with borderline and 
other personality patterns. 
24) However, the effects of a 
non-pharmacological intervention model, such as HRV-
biofeedback (HRV-BF), on HRV indices in heroin users 
has not been examined in detail. The protocol of HRV-BF 
was first described by Lehrer et al. 
25) Its aim is to increase 
respiratory sinus arrhythmia (RSA) amplitude by breath-
ing at the resonance frequency, which is approximately 
0.1 Hz or six breaths per minute. 
26) Lin et al. 
27) modified 
Lehrer et al.'s 
25) HRV-BF protocol and successfully ap-
plied it to patients with coronary artery disease and MDD 
in Taiwanese populations. 
27,28) Lin et al.'s 
27) HRV-BF pro-
tocol followed the Lehrer et al.'s 
25) protocol by determin-
ing the individual's resonance frequency in the first ses-
sion, and then adjusting the respiration rate during the 
HRV-BF training by gradually stepping down to reach the 
participant's resonance frequency, by asking participants </p>

<p>to breathe slowly and regularly. 
27) Breathing at the reso-
nance frequency has been found to cause resonance in the 
cardiovascular system, thereby increasing HRV and in-
ducing a baroreflex gain. 
16) Research has confirmed the 
effects of HRV-BF with respect to increasing cardiac va-
gal activity among patients with cardiovascular dis-
ease 
15,29) and with respect to decreasing depressive symp-
toms among patients with MDD. 
17) However, the effects 
of HRV-BF in increasing HRV indices and decreasing de-
pressive symptoms among heroin users still needs to be 
explored. 
This study consisted of two parts. The aim of the first 
part was to compare the differences in HRV indices 
among heroin users with depressive symptoms, patients 
with MDD but no heroin use, and healthy controls. The 
aim of the second part was to examine the effects of 
HRV-BF on depressive symptoms, HRV indices, and respi-
ratory rates among heroin users with depressive symptoms. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Study 1 </p>

<p>Participants 
A case-control study with matching age and gender was 
conducted. This part of the study consisted of three groups 
of participants, namely heroin users with depressive 
symptoms (the heroin group), patients with MDD but no 
heroin use (the MDD group), and healthy controls. A total 
of 354 male addicts were invited for being screened for 
types of substance use and depressive symptoms by clin-
ical psychologists at Kaohsiung Drug Abuser Treatment 
Center (Kaohsiung, Taiwan). Inclusion criteria were: (1) 
the severity and duration of heroin use fitted the diagnostic 
criteria of heroin dependence found in the Diagnostic and 
Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, fourth edition, 
text revision (DSM-IV-TR) </p>

<p>8) </p>

<p>; (2) the patient had abstained 
from heroin use for at least 1 month; (3) the total score of 
the Beck Depression Inventory-II (BDI-II) 
30) was higher 
than 13; and (4) the patient was motivated and available to 
participate this study. Exclusion criteria included (1) hav-
ing current or past cardiovascular disease; (2) having any 
severe psychiatric disorder except for MDD, such as 
schizophrenia or bipolar disorder; and (3) having a past 
history of head injury, neurological illness, or mental 
retardation. 
The MDD group and healthy controls were selected 
from our data pool based on the criteria of being a male, 
and age matched to within 10 years of that of the heroin </p>



<p>Fig. 1. The experiment 
procedure. </p>

<p>users. The MDD group was recruited from psychiatric 
outpatient clinics of Kaohsiung Medical University 
Hospital (Kaohsiung, Taiwan). The MDD group consisted 
of nine male patients who were diagnosed by psychiatrists 
as having MDD according to the criteria of DSM-IV-TR </p>

<p>8) </p>

<p>and who were confirmed to have never used heroin. Nine 
healthy controls who visited the health center of 
Kaohsiung Medical University Hospital for a health 
checkup were recruited. Each individual's total BDI-II 
score was lower than 13. All participants in the MDD 
group and the healthy controls had no mental or physical 
problems as described in the exclusion criteria for the par-
ticipants in the heroin group. This study was approved by 
the institutional review board of Kaohsiung Medical 
University Hospital (KMUH-IRB-2012-02-09-(I) and 
KMUH-IRB-990255). Written informed consent was ob-
tained from each participant before the study started. </p>

<p>Self-report data 
All participants filled in a questionnaire that collected 
demographic characteristics and depression levels. The 
BDI-II contains 21-item statements that assess cognitive 
and somatic depression during a period of 2 weeks before 
the study. 
30) The score range of the BDI-II is from 0 to 63. 
No significant depression is denoted by scores of 0-13, 
mild depression by 14-19, moderate depression by 20-28, 
and severe depression by 29-63. </p>

<p>30) </p>

<p>Physiological measurements 
All participants were instructed not to exercise ex-
cessively and to refrain from caffeinated beverages, alco-
holic beverages, and smoking for 3 hours before the psy-
chophysiological measurements were collected. A lead II 
electrocardiogram (ECG) was collected for 5 minutes at 
baseline using the <rs id="software-3" type="software">ProComp Infiniti</rs> 
TM system (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Thought Technology Ltd.</rs>., Montreal, Canada), which was installed 
on a laptop. A sampling rate of 2,048/second was set in or-
der to acquire real-time interbeat intervals. The physio-
logical signals were collected between 9:00 to 12:00 a.m. 
and 2:00 to 5:00 p.m. to minimize any effects of biological </p>

<p>circadian variations. The CardiacPro Infiniti HRV analy-
sis module (Thought Technology Ltd.) with fast Fourier 
transformation was used to transform the interbeat inter-
vals into the various frequency domains of the HRV in-
dices, namely LF power (0.04-0.15 Hz), HF power 
(0.15-0.4 Hz), and the LF/HF ratio. The time domain of 
the HRV index of the SDNN was also obtained. </p>

<p>Research design and procedure 
A between-subjects design was used in this study. 
Participants of all three groups completed the ques-
tionnaires in a sound-attenuated and temperature-controlled 
room. After a 10-minute rest, an ECG sensor was placed 
on the participant for measuring the 5-minute period of 
raw ECG signals, which were transformed into the base-
line HRV indices. </p>

<p>Study 2 </p>

<p>Participants 
The nine heroin users with depressive symptoms from 
Study 1 were invited to take part in the HRV-BF program. </p>

<p>Psychophysiological measurement 
The demographic data and information related to her-
oin use, including the history of substance use, the age of 
onset of heroin use, and the number of times the partic-
ipants had tried previously to quit heroin use, were col-
lected among heroin users. The BDI-II total score and 
cognitive and somatic symptoms of depression were ob-
tained at pre-intervention and post-intervention from all 
participants. The HRV-BF was carried out using <rs type="software">ProComp 
Infiniti</rs> 
TM software together with ECG and respiration sen-
sors, which were used to acquire real-time feedback re-
garding respiration rate, breathing patterns, RSA ampli-
tude, and HRV indices. The HRV indices as the outcome 
variables were obtained at pre-intervention and at post-
intervention. </p>

<p>Heart Rate Variability Biofeedback in Heroin Users 171 </p>

<p>Research design and procedure 
The HRV-BF protocol was based on Lin et al., 
27) and in-
cluded self-guided muscle relaxation, diaphragmatic 
breathing, paced breathing, pursed-lips breathing, and 
RSA-biofeedback over a 60-minute session, weekly for 6 
weeks. The aims of HRV-BF were to increase LF power at 
0.1 Hz, increase RSA amplitude, decrease SNS activation, 
increase vagal tone or PNS activation, and restore balance 
of the autonomic nervous system. 
A counterbalanced within-subjects experimental de-
sign was used. We quasi-randomly assigned the ex-
perimental tasks to the participants: they completed the 
conditions in a different order (AB or BA, where [A] the 
depressive condition, and [B] the happiness condition). 
The first person completed the tasks in the order AB, the 
second person in the order BA, and so on (Fig. 1). All par-
ticipants were seated in a sound-attenuated and temper-
ature-controlled room. After 2 minutes of calibration of 
the physiological signals, ECG measurements were ob-
tained during 5 minutes of baseline, during a 10-minute 
depressive condition (5 minutes of depression induction 
that participants were guided to think about a depressive 
event and then 5 minutes of recovery from depression), 
and during a 10-minute happiness condition (5-minute 
happiness induction participants were guided to think 
about a happiness event and 5 minutes of recovery from 
happiness). There was a 5-minute break between the de-
pressive and happiness conditions. HRV indices were 
compared between pre-and post-intervention. </p>

<p>Statistics Analysis </p>

<p>Study 1 
The nonparametric Kruskal-Wallis test with Mann-
Whitney U post-hoc comparisons were used to examine 
the group differences in age, total score, and cognitive/so-
matic symptoms of depression, and HRV indices across 
the three groups. Spearman's rank correlations were used 
to examine the association between depression total 
scores and HRV indices. The statistical analyses were per-
formed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">PASW</rs> Statistics <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">ver. 18.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM Co.</rs>., 
Armonk, NY, USA). </p>

<p>Study 2 
Nonparametric Kruskal-Wallis tests were used to ex-
amine the effects of HRV-BF on the depression total score, 
and cognitive and somatic symptoms of depression that 
were measured by BDI-II; these were compared pre-inter-</p>

<p>vention and post-intervention. The effects of HRV-BF 
were also examined by comparing the HRV indices and 
respiration rates during the various experimental con-
ditions, pre-and post-intervention. Statistical analyses 
were performed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">PASW</rs> Statistics <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">ver. 18.0</rs>. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Study 1 
A total of 90 addicts (25.42%) with depressive symp-
toms were screened; however, only nine male heroin users 
were recruited into the heroin group based on the inclusion 
and exclusion criteria described above. The mean age of 
the participants was 40.33 years (standard deviation 
[SD]=8.50, range from 29 to 54) for the heroin group, 
33.44 years (SD=10.55, range from 21 to 52) for the MDD 
group, and 37.78 years (SD=11.25, range from 21 to 57) 
for the healthy controls. There were no significant differ-
ences in age among these three groups (χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=1.21, p＞ 
0.05). Based on the criteria suggested for the BDI-II by 
Beck et al., 
30) 22.2% (n=2) of the participants in the heroin 
group had mild depression, 55.6% (n=5) had moderate de-
pression, and 22.2% (n=2) had severe depression. Two-
thirds (n=6) of the participants in the MDD group were in 
remission from depression, 11.1% (n=1) had mild depres-
sion, and 22.2% (n=2) had severe depression. All of the 
healthy controls had no significant depression. 
Table 1 shows the results of the Kruskal-Wallis test on 
depression and baseline HRV indices among the heroin 
group, the MDD group, and healthy controls. There were 
significant differences in depression total score, and cog-
nitive and somatic symptoms of depression among the 
three groups (χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=16.51, p＜0.001; χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=13.62, p＜0.001; 
and χ 
2 =12.66, p＜0.01, respectively), as well as for the 
HRV indices SDNN, HF, and the LF/HF ratio (χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=6.08, 
p＜0.05; χ 
2 =9.95, p＜0.01; and χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=6.87, p＜0.05, re-
spectively; Table 1). The Mann-Whitney U post-hoc com-
parison revealed that the heroin and MDD groups had a 
higher depression total score, and cognitive and somatic 
symptoms of depression than the healthy controls. In addi-
tion, the heroin group had lower SDNN and HF values 
than the healthy controls, and there was a higher LF/HF 
ratio in the heroin group than in healthy controls. 
However, there were no significant differences among the 
three groups in LF HRV. 
Spearman's rank correlations showed a negative asso-
ciation between depression total score and HF HRV (r= 
−0.40, p＜0.05), and a positive association between de-
pression total score and the LF/HF ratio (r=0.46, p＜0.05) </p>



<p>Table 1. The Kruskal-Wallis test on depression and baseline HRV indices among heroin, MDD, and healthy control groups (n=27) </p>

<p>Heroin group 
(n=9) </p>

<p>MDD group 
(n=9) </p>

<p>Healthy controls 
(n=9) 
 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Mann-Whitney U 
post-hoc comparison </p>

<p>Age, yr (SD) 
40.33 (8.50) 
33.44 (10.55) 
37.78 (11.25) 
1.21 
Gender, male 
9 
9 
9 
BDI-II 
Depression total score 
20.50 
15.83 
5.67 
16.51*** 
Heroin, MDD＞Healthy 
Cognitive depression 
20.33 
15.00 
6.67 
13.62*** 
Heroin, MDD＞Healthy 
Somatic depression 
17.61 
18.00 
6.39 
12.66** 
Heroin, MDD＞Healthy 
HRV indices 
SDNN (ms) 
9.44 
13.89 
18.67 
6.08* 
Healthy＞Heroin 
LF (ms </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
11.44 
12.78 
17.78 
3.18 
HF (ms </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
8.33 
13.56 
20.11 
9.95** 
Healthy＞Heroin 
LF/HF ratio 
19.22 
13.28 
9.50 
6.87* 
Healthy＜Heroin </p>

<p>HRV, heart rate variability; MDD, major depressive disorder; SD, standard deviation; BDI-II, Beck Depression Inventory-II; SDNN, SD of NN 
intervals; LF, low frequency; HF, high frequency. 
*p＜0.05, **p＜0.01, ***p＜0.001. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. The correlations between depression and the heart rate variability indices. HF, high frequency; LF, low frequency; SDNN, standard 
deviation of NN intervals. </p>

<p>for all participants; however, there was no significant as-
sociation between depression total scores and SDNN or 
LF (r=−0.21, p＞0.05; and r=−0.07, p＞0.05, re-
spectively; Fig. 2). </p>

<p>Study 2 
Four of the heroin users combined heroin use with 
methamphetamine use. The range of body mass indices 
was 20.15 to 33.14, with a mean of 24.09 (SD=4.06). The 
mean years of education was 8.56 (SD=4.06). Five of the </p>

<p>Heart Rate Variability Biofeedback in Heroin Users 173 </p>

<p>Table 2. The effects of HRV-BF on HRV indices and respiration rate under various experimental conditions at pre-versus post-interventions 
for heroin users (n=9) </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Baseline 
z </p>

<p>Depressive 
induction 
z </p>

<p>Depressive 
recovery 
z </p>

<p>Happiness 
induction 
z </p>

<p>Happiness 
recovery 
z </p>

<p>Pre 
Post 
Pre 
Post 
Pre 
Post 
Pre 
Post 
Pre 
Post </p>

<p>SDNN (ms) 
24.97 
(11.82) </p>

<p>33.56 
(12.52) </p>

<p>−1.72 
28.29 
(10.35) </p>

<p>33.38 
(13.39) </p>

<p>−1.96 
29.10 
(9.62) </p>

<p>47.99 
(19.51) </p>

<p>−2.38* 25.53 </p>

<p>(9.91) </p>

<p>32.10 
(11.16) </p>

<p>−1.86 
28.19 
(12.81) </p>

<p>39.72 
(14.30) </p>

<p>−1.52 </p>

<p>LF (ms </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
91.50 
(63.27) </p>

<p>227.88 
(256.25) </p>

<p>−1.13 
88.65 
(70.83) </p>

<p>179.85 
(221.90) </p>

<p>−1.01 
101.35 
(122.04) </p>

<p>575.96 
(755.21) </p>

<p>−2.24* 62.65 </p>

<p>(58.16) </p>

<p>96.83 
(63.98) </p>

<p>−1.35 103.18 </p>

<p>(85.57) </p>

<p>356.15 
(407.20) </p>

<p>−1.01 </p>

<p>HF (ms </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
44.76 
(49.03) </p>

<p>75.00 
(57.53) </p>

<p>−2.67** 42.88 </p>

<p>(35.06) </p>

<p>92.00 
(86.48) </p>

<p>−2.07* 
32.96 
(20.08) </p>

<p>90.14 
(62.05) </p>

<p>−1.96* 42.76 </p>

<p>(21.71) </p>

<p>84.49 
(72.07) </p>

<p>−1.18 
41.84 
(30.26) </p>

<p>73.47 
(62.52) </p>

<p>−0.51 </p>

<p>Respiration 
rate </p>

<p>15.65 
(3.14) </p>

<p>13.16 
(4.86) </p>

<p>−2.67** 18.29 </p>

<p>(3.63) </p>

<p>14.58 
(4.59) </p>

<p>−2.43* 
18.28 
(3.92) </p>

<p>12.04 
(3.89) </p>

<p>−2.55* 18.54 </p>

<p>(3.03) </p>

<p>13.13 
(2.81) </p>

<p>−2.52* 19.23 </p>

<p>(3.65) </p>

<p>12.93 
(4.88) </p>

<p>−2.24* </p>

<p>HRV, heart rate variability; SDNN, standard deviation of NN intervals; LF, low frequency; HF, high frequency. 
*p＜0.05, **p＜0.01. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. The heart rate variability indices (SDNN, LF, and HF) and respiration rate under various experimental conditions at pre-versus 
post-intervention. SDNN, standard deviation of NN intervals; LF, low frequency; HF, high frequency; BL, baseline; D, depressive induction; 
DR, depressive recovery; H, happiness induction; HR, happiness recovery. </p>

<p>group were single (55.60%) and four were divorced or 
separated (44.40%). The mean age of initial heroin use 
was 20.33 years (SD=4.44, range from 14 to 28). The 
average number of attempts to quit heroin use was 2.33 
(SD=1.41, range from 1 to 5 times). 
Regarding the effects of HRV-BF on depressive symp-</p>

<p>toms, the depression total score decreased from 23.00 
pre-intervention to 18.33 post-intervention, and cognitive 
depression decreased from 19.00 to 14.33. However, the 
Kruskal-Wallis test showed that there were no significant 
differences in depression total score, and cognitive and so-
matic symptoms of depression between pre-versus </p>



<p>post-intervention (z=−1.61, p＞0.05; z=−1.72, p＞0.05; 
and z=0.00, p＞0.05, respectively). 
Table 2 and Figure 3 show the pre-versus post-inter-
vention comparisons of the HRV indices and respiration 
rates for the various experimental conditions, using the 
Kruskal-Wallis test. There were significant increases in 
SDNN, LF, and HF for depressive recovery from pre-inter-
vention to post-intervention (SDNN: z=−2.38, p＜0.05; 
LF: z=−2.24, p＜0.05; and HF: z=−1.96, p＜0.05, re-
spectively). The HF HRV for baseline (z=−2.67, p 
＜0.01) and depressive induction (z=−2.07, p＜0.05) 
also increased from pre-to post-intervention. In addition, 
the average pre-intervention respiration rate was 18.60 
breaths per minute, which reduced to 13.17 breaths per 
minute post-intervention. Respiration rates decreased sig-
nificantly pre-to post-intervention for the five experi-
mental conditions (z=−2.67, p＜0.01; z=−2.43, p 
＜0.05; z=−2.55, p＜0.05; z=−2.52, p＜0.05; z=−2.24, 
p＜0.05, respectively). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The first part of this study examined group differences 
in HRV indices between a heroin user group, a MDD 
group, and healthy controls. The heroin group had lower 
SDNN and HF HRV indices than healthy controls. In ad-
dition, our result also confirmed that the heroin group had 
a higher LF/HF ratio than the healthy controls, which is 
consistent with the findings of Chang et al. 
10) for heroin 
users who were receiving methadone maintenance 
therapy. These results indicate that the heroin group had 
decreased PNS activation and increased SNS activation. 
However, we did not find a group difference in HRV in-
dices between the heroin group and the MDD group. It has 
been shown that patients with MDD have decreased 
SDNN and HF, 
31) which may account for this lack of sig-
nificant differences. 
In addition, we also found a negative correction be-
tween depression total score and HF HRV, and a positive 
correlation between depression total score and the LF/HF 
ratio. This result is consistent with the findings of Agelink 
et al., 
32) and indicates that PNS withdrawal occurs in pa-
tients with MDD. The polyvagal theory 
33) emphasizes the 
role of cardiovascular physiology in social behavior 
whereby the vagal brake regulates sympathetic activation. 
Individuals with substance addiction may use addictive 
drugs to reduce this negative effect or to modulate inter-
personal conflicts. As a result, continued drug addiction 
may impair the vagal activity of drug users. </p>

<p>34,35) </p>

<p>Regarding the effects of HRV-BF on HRV indices in 
heroin users, we found a significant increase in HRV in-
dices from pre-to post-intervention, especially for SDNN, 
LF, and HF under recovery from depression, and HF under 
baseline and depressive induction. The increased SDNN 
and LF are consistent with the results of a previous study 
on the effects of HRV-BF among patients with MDD. </p>

<p>17,28) </p>

<p>The effects of HRV-BF with respect to increasing HF ob-
served in this study are also consistent with findings in pa-
tients with coronary artery disease. 
36,37) The present study 
found that heroin users slowed their respiration rates from 
18.60 to 13.17 breaths per minute after HRV-BF 
intervention. Slowing down the respiration rate is known 
to result in a significant increase in PNS activation. 
23) The 
findings of this study support the hypothesis that HRV-BF 
is an effective non-pharmacological intervention that re-
stores parasympathetic activation among heroin users. 
It is noteworthy that we found no significant increase in 
HRV indices for the happiness induction and happiness re-
covery conditions, from pre-to post-intervention. This re-
sult is consistent with a prior study wherein heroin users 
had a greater emotional response to neutral images than to 
pleasant images. 
38) It is possible that this effect in heroin 
users is related to both impaired negative emotional proc-
essing 
39) and to the compromising effect of heroin on the 
brain, such as an effect on amygdala activity. 
40) Conse-
quently, it may be difficult for heroin users to experience 
a positive emotion. The amygdala is thought to play an im-
portant role in processing anxiety and depression related 
to drug dependence via negative reinforcement. 
40) This 
may explain why we were unable to find a significant im-
provement in HRV indices for happiness induction and 
happiness recovery, comparing pre-to post-intervention. 
Overall, heroin users have the difficulty to experience the 
positive emotion may relate to a reduction in PNS in-
hibition of SNS activity, blocking vagal inhibitory proc-
esses and baroreflex feedback. </p>

<p>33) </p>

<p>There were several limitations of our investigation that 
deserve attention. First, the small sample size of our pre-
liminary study limits wide generalization of our results. 
Although we screened 90 addicts from 354 clients whose 
depression total score exceeded 13, only nine heroin users 
participated and completed the 6-week HRV-BF. Numerous 
reasons may have limited participation in this study, such 
as the participant not using heroin, having a routine activ-
ity or other treatment program that was a contraindication 
for study participation, moving to another jail such that 
they could not complete the 6-week program, and a lack of 
motivation to participate in the study. Second, the diag-</p>

<p>Heart Rate Variability Biofeedback in Heroin Users 175 </p>

<p>nosis of MDD was not confirmed by psychiatrists. Only 
one heroin user reported a previous MDD diagnosis by 
psychiatrist and a prior prescription for antidepressants. 
Third, there was no control group in Study 2, which limits 
the interpretation of the effects of HRV-BF. 
In conclusion, this study found that heroin users with 
depressive symptoms show reduced PNS activation and 
increased SNS activation. HRV-BF was found to be an ef-
fective non-pharmacological intervention that was able to 
restore the autonomic balance of heroin users. The 
HRV-BF protocol with breathing training thus may be an 
intervention strategy for heroin users in order to improve 
their cardiac autonomic balance. </p>

<p>This study was partially supported by grant NSC101-
2314-B-037-057-MY3 awarded by the National Science 
Council, Taiwan (ROC). We gratefully thank Yu-Ting 
Chen, Che-Cheng Chu, Hui-Ping Chan, and Hsueh-Chen 
Lu at Kaohsiung Medical University for assistance with 
the experimental procedures. We also thank Yao-Chien 
Chen at Kaohsiung Drug Abuse Treatment Center, 
Agency of Correction, Ministry of Justice. </p>







</text></tei>