<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4784605" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Children in remote or resource-constrained settings 
often fail to enjoy medical advances that are considered 
routine in other parts of the world. Even relatively basic 
technologies may be unavailable for the care of these 
children (eg, weight scales). Accurate patient weights 
are fundamental to nearly every medical and pharmaco-
logic intervention applied in children, yet there exist 
many settings where an accurate and reliable scale is 
simply unavailable. 1-3 Pediatric health care providers 
circumvent the lack of a scale by using any of a number 
of strategies for weight estimation. These strategies are 
typically based on age, although a few rely on length or 
a combination of age and length to derive an estimated 
weight. However, all of the existing strategies are met 
with some limitations; their accuracy drops as children 
increase in age, they are severely biased in children at 
the extremes of weight (eg, underweight, obese), and </p>

<p>they often perform poorly in children that differ racially 
or ethnically from the population of children in whom 
the method was developed. 
Notably, only a handful of pediatric weight estimation 
strategies have been evaluated in Indian children. 
Varghese et al observed that existing age-based and 
length-based strategies (eg, APLS, Argall, Nelson, 
Broselow) tended to overestimate weight in their cohort 
of children and performed better when the study popula-
tion was restricted to young children under 15 kg. 4 </p>

<p>566625G PHXXX10.1177/2333794X14566625Global Pediatric HealthBatmanabane et al </p>

<p>research-article2015 </p>

<p>1 Jawaharlal Institute of Postgraduate Medical Education and 
Research, Puducherry, India 
2 SCB Medical College, Cuttack, India 
3 Children's Mercy Hospital, Kansas City, MO, USA </p>

<p>Corresponding Author: 
Susan Abdel-Rahman, Children's Mercy Hospital, 2401 Gillham 
Road, Kansas City, MO 64108, USA. 
Email: srahman@cmh.edu </p>

<p>Using the Mercy Method for Weight 
Estimation in Indian Children </p>

<p>Gitanjali Batmanabane, MD, PhD 1 , Pradeep Kumar Jena, MBBS, MD 2 , 
Roshan Dikshit, MBBS, MD 2 , and Susan Abdel-Rahman, PharmD 3 </p>

<p>Abstract 
This study was designed to compare the performance of a new weight estimation strategy (Mercy Method) with 
12 existing weight estimation methods (APLS, Best Guess, Broselow, Leffler, Luscombe-Owens, Nelson, Shann, 
Theron, Traub-Johnson, Traub-Kichen) in children from India. Otherwise healthy children, 2 months to 16 years, 
were enrolled and weight, height, humeral length (HL), and mid-upper arm circumference (MUAC) were obtained 
by trained raters. Weight estimation was performed as described for each method. Predicted weights were 
regressed against actual weights and the slope, intercept, and Pearson correlation coefficient estimated. Agreement 
between estimated weight and actual weight was determined using Bland-Altman plots with log-transformation. 
Predictive performance of each method was assessed using mean error (ME), mean percentage error (MPE), and 
root mean square error (RMSE). Three hundred seventy-five children (7.5 ± 4.3 years, 22.1 ± 12.3 kg, 116.2 ± 26.3 
cm) participated in this study. The Mercy Method (MM) offered the best correlation between actual and estimated 
weight when compared with the other methods (r 2 = .967 vs .517-.844). The MM also demonstrated the lowest ME, 
MPE, and RMSE. Finally, the MM estimated weight within 20% of actual for nearly all children (96%) as opposed to 
the other methods for which these values ranged from 14% to 63%. The MM performed extremely well in Indian 
children with performance characteristics comparable to those observed for US children in whom the method was 
developed. It appears that the MM can be used in Indian children without modification, extending the utility of this 
weight estimation strategy beyond Western populations. </p>

<p>Keywords 
pediatric, weight, Mercy TAPE, Broselow, APLS, Luscombe </p>



<p>Global Pediatric Health </p>

<p>Ramarajan et al corroborated these findings and demon-
strated that the extent to which the Broselow tape overes-
timates weight increases with increasing weight and age 
prompting the authors to recommend a correction factor 
of 10% when using this device. 5 Importantly, both stud-
ies restricted analyses to children whose height fell 
within the prespecified range of the tape and neither pro-
posed a solution for weight estimation in children that 
exceed 143 cm. Thus, the methods reviewed above can-
not be broadly applied to the pediatric population as a 
whole, and clinicians charged with the care of children 
that exceed the age or length bounds of these methods are 
left with little guidance on the patients' weight. For this 
reason the provider's guess remains a common, albeit 
flawed, method for weight estimation in pediatric emer-
gency settings. 6 
Recently, investigators developed a new 2-variable 
weight estimation strategy (ie, the Mercy Method) that 
markedly outperforms the weight estimation strategies 
discussed above. It demonstrates less bias and greater pre-
cision than 12 other methods against which it was evalu-
ated and does not contain the same age-and length-based 
restrictions found in many of the other methods. 7 However, 
the Mercy Method (MM), like many weight estimation 
strategies, was developed using data from Western chil-
dren. This study was designed to examine the performance 
of the MM in children from India and compare the perfor-
mance to other weight estimation methods. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Subjects and Study Design </p>

<p>Otherwise healthy children, with constitutionally normal 
growth and development, were eligible for participation 
in this prospective, single-center study. Children were 
required to be between the ages of 2 months and 16 years 
and were excluded from participation for any of the fol-
lowing: (a) known or apparent limb deformities, (b) 
unable to be positioned for height/length measurements, 
and (c) an underlying pathological condition or pharma-
cologic management that would produce abnormal body 
composition for age. Children were stratified in 1-year 
age brackets with the goal of enrolling 20 children per 
bracket. All children were enrolled with informed per-
mission, and assent where applicable, under a protocol 
that was reviewed and approved by the Ethics Committee 
of SCB Medical College and the Ethics Committee of the 
World Health Organization, Geneva. </p>

<p>Data Collection </p>

<p>Anthropometric measurements including weight, height, 
humeral length (HL), and mid-upper arm circumference </p>

<p>(MUAC) were performed by 1 of 2 trained raters. Weight 
was obtained with children weighed in their underwear 
or other light-weight clothing using a portable scale that 
was calibrated daily. Recumbent length in infants was 
measured using an infantometer. In children that were 
able to stand unassisted, height was measured using a 
portable stadiometer with the heels, buttocks, and head 
in contact with the height rule and the head was aligned 
in the Frankfort horizontal plane. HL was measured 
from the upper edge of the posterior border of the acro-
mion process, down the posterior surface of the arm, to 
the tip of the olecranon process with the arm at the 
child's side and the elbow bent at 90°. MUAC was mea-
sured at the midpoint of the humerus with the arm hang-
ing down at the child's side. Both HL and MUAC were 
measured to the nearest millimeter using a standard 
vinyl tape measure. </p>

<p>Rater Qualification </p>

<p>All investigators obtaining measurements were required 
to undergo training prior to making any measurements 
in study participants. Raters performed each of the 
study-related anthropometric measurements in triplicate 
on 3 adult volunteers to assess inter-and intrarater reli-
ability. Intrarater variance was required to be less than 
5% for each anthropometric measure across all volun-
teers in order to qualify as a study rater. </p>

<p>Data Analysis </p>

<p>Electronic data entry was performed by a single 
investigator and independently verified by a second 
study team member against hard copies of the original 
data collection forms. The MM was applied to the 
quality assured data as previously described. 7 The 
MUAC and HL measures for each child were rounded 
up or down to the nearest 1.0 cm and the correspond-
ing fractional weight for each measurement obtained 
from the published table. The fractional weights were 
summed to generate an estimated weight for that par-
ticipant. Data on age, height, and MUAC were used to 
estimate weight using 12 other weight estimation 
methods: Advanced Pediatric Life Support (APLS), 
Best Guess, Broselow, Leffler, Luscombe-Owens, 
Nelson, Shann, Theron, Traub-Johnson, and Traub-
Kichen. 8-19 
The predicted weights as determined by each method 
were regressed against actual weights and the slope, the 
95% confidence interval (CI) for the slope, the inter-
cept, the 95% CI for the intercept, and the Pearson cor-
relation coefficient were estimated. The percent 
agreement between estimated weight and actual weight </p>

<p>Batmanabane et al </p>



<p>was determined visually using Bland-Altman plots 
with log-transformation. Mean error (ME) was calcu-
lated by taking the difference of the predicted and actual 
weights. Mean percentage error (MPE) was calculated 
by dividing the actual weight into the ME and multiply-
ing by 100. Root mean square error (RMSE) was calcu-
lated by taking the square root of the average squared 
error. The intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) was 
determined using a 2-way random effects model and an 
absolute agreement definition to evaluate reliability 
between raters. All mathematical and statistical analy-
ses were performed with <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">Excel</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">2003</rs> and 
<rs type="software">SPSS</rs> v12. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>A total of 375 children (7.5 ± 4.3 years) were enrolled in 
this study with participants evenly split between males 
and females (50.1% vs 49.9%). The anthropometric con-
stitution of the study population is detailed in Table 1. 
The population distribution for height was positively 
skewed and the distribution for weight negatively 
skewed, resulting in an average body mass index (BMI) 
that favored children who were underweight or normal as 
classified by the Centers for Disease Control (Figure 1). 
The MM proved to be the least restrictive of the methods 
evaluated, predicting weight in all but one child whose 
MUAC fell below the lower bound for the method. By 
contrast, prediction rates for other published weight esti-
mation methods ranged from 66% to 93% (Table 2). 
Predictive performance of the MM and the compara-
tor methods are depicted visually in Figures 2 and 3, 
respectively. The regression parameters generated by 
the comparison of actual and predicted weights are 
detailed in Table 2. The MM offered the best correlation 
(r 2 = .967 vs .517-.844) and came closest to achieving 
the desired characteristics of fit (ie, slope approaching 
one, intercept approaching zero) when compared with 
the other methods. When examined for bias and preci-
sion, the MM outperformed the other weight estimation 
strategies, demonstrating a lower ME, MPE, and RMSE 
(Table 2). Finally, the MM estimated weight within 10% 
of actual for the majority of children (70%) and pre-
dicted weight within 20% of actual for nearly all chil-
dren (96%) as opposed to the other methods for which 
these values ranged from 6% to 29% and from 14% to 
63%, respectively (Table 2). 
Given that most of the published weight estimation 
methods tend to perform poorly at the extremes of 
weight, the data were segregated by BMI percentile and 
performance of the Mercy method examined indepen-
dently for infants and children who were underweight, 
normal, overweight, and obese. As illustrated in Figure 4, </p>

<p>the MM appeared to perform with comparable predictive 
power irrespective of BMI classification; however, 
weight for the majority of infants was overestimated by 
this method. Although the ICC was high (0.98) there 
were modest differences in performance of the MM 
observed between study raters (eg, MPE: 1.1% vs 2.2%; 
agreement within 20%: 98% vs 91%). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Weight estimation strategies address a critical medical 
need in settings where there is neither the time nor the 
opportunity to directly weigh patients. To date, no single 
previous method has provided accurate estimates of 
weight across a broad range of ages, weights, and 
lengths. The MM is the first method to address some of 
the limitations inherent in the existing weight estimation 
strategies. By using surrogates for length and girth, the 
MM expands the age range of children to which a single 
weight estimation method can be applied and removes 
some of the restrictions observed in other commonly 
used methods. 
The MM performed extremely well in this Indian 
cohort, demonstrating goodness-of-fit criteria compara-
ble to those observed for the method when applied to 
children in the United States. 7 The average absolute 
error in this study was −0.12 kg, which represented a 
percentage error of −1.5%, suggesting a slight underes-
timation of weight by the MM. There was little loss in 
predictive performance of the MM across BMI in chil-
dren over 2 years of age; however, the method appears 
to overestimate the weight of infants in this population. 
Importantly, the MM predicted weight within 10% of 
actual weight for 70% of the enrolled children and </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic and Anthropometric Characteristics 
of the Children Enrolled in the Study a . </p>

<p>Enrollment, n 
375 
Weight (kg) 
22.1 ± 12.3 
Height (cm) 
116.2 ± 26.3 
Humerus (cm) 
23.7 ± 5.9 
MUAC (cm) 
16.9 ± 3.7 
BMI (kg/m 2 ) 
15.1 ± 2.9 
BMI percentile 
22.9 ± 30.7 
Infant (%) 
12.0 
Underweight (%) 
39.5 
Normal (%) 
40.0 
Overweight (%) 
2.9 
Obese (%) 
5.6 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: MUAC, mid-upper arm circumference; BMI, body 
mass index. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>All data are provided as mean ± standard deviation unless 
otherwise indicated. </p>



<p>Global Pediatric Health </p>

<p>Table 2. Regression Parameters and Predictive Performance of the Mercy Method and 12 Other Weight Estimation 
Methods a . </p>

<p>n 
Slope 
Intercept 
r 2 
ME (kg) 
MPE (%) </p>

<p>RMSE 
(kg) </p>

<p>% Agreement 
within </p>

<p>10% 20% 30% </p>

<p>Mercy 
374 
0.93 [0.91-0.95] 
1.5 [1.0-1.9] 
0.967 −0.12 (2.29) 
1.5 (9.9) 
1.64 
70 
96 
99.2 
APLS 
249 
0.50 [0.44-0.55] 
10.3 [9.1-11.4] 0.531 
1.13 (5.63) 13.9 (24.8) 
4.12 
17 
30 
45 
ARC 
350 
0.78 [0.72-0.84] 
8.0 [6.4-9.5] 
0.646 
2.82 (7.36) 18.1 (27.3) 
5.82 
23 
41 
59 
Argall 
249 
0.74 [0.65-0.83] 
9.4 [7.7-11.1] 0.531 
4.74 (6.10) 31.5 (31.0) 
6.29 
10 
23 
31 
Best Guess 347 
0.97 [0.90-1.04] 
8.0 [6.3-9.7] 
0.669 
7.30 (7.78) 41.3 (33.2) 
8.55 
10 
24 
35 
Broselow 
321 
0.64 [0.57-0.70] 
7.4 [6.0-8.9] 
0.517 
1.22 (3.83) 10.8 (16.3) 
2.95 
28 
60 
79 
Leffler 
247 
0.59 [0.53-0.66] 
9.4 [8.3-10.6] 0.576 
3.00 (5.06) 27.8 (28.5) 
4.70 
11 
23 
34 
Luscombe-
Owens </p>

<p>249 
0.74 [0.65-0.83] 
10.4 [8.7-12.1] 0.531 
5.74 (6.10) 38.0 (31.5) 
7.02 
6 
14 
27 </p>

<p>Nelson 
329 
0.89 [0.82-0.96] 
6.9 [5.2-8.5] 
0.643 
4.63 (7.36) 28.2 (31.6) 
6.52 
18 
31 
45 
Shann 
350 
0.64 [0.59-0.69] 
10.4 [9.1-11.7] 0.652 
2.13 (7.04) 18.4 (27.1) 
5.56 
22 
42 
55 
Theron 
249 
1.14 [1.0-1.27] 
6.5 [3.8-9.2] 
0.518 
8.97 (9.05) 51.4 (42.6) 
9.70 
7 
14 
23 
Traub-
Johnson </p>

<p>350 
0.87 [0.83-0.91] 
4.8 [3.8-5.8] 
0.844 
1.73 (4.71) 11.1 (16.0) 
3.74 
29 
62 
85 </p>

<p>Traub-
Kichen </p>

<p>344 
0.79 [0.75-0.82] 
6.2 [5.2-7.1] 
0.840 
1.17 (4.79) 10.0 (16.4) 
3.68 
28 
63 
84 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ME, mean error; MPE, mean percentage error; RMSE, root mean square error. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation or [95% confidence interval] unless otherwise indicated. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Distribution of pediatric study participants by weight, height, and body mass index (BMI). </p>

<p>within 20% of actual for more than 95% of the children 
that were studied. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>This study was one of the first prospective evaluations of 
the MM in non-US children. The data presented herein 
suggest that the MM does not need to be modified for 
application to children in India, thus extending the utility </p>

<p>of this weight estimation strategy beyond Western popu-
lations. The results of additional studies in geographi-
cally distinct children will further delineate the role of 
the MM in the care of children for whom there is no 
opportunity to obtain an accurate weight. However, inte-
gration of the MM into pediatric practice will require 
training materials that clearly detail how the measure-
ments should be performed so as to generate reliable esti-
mates in the field. </p>

<p>Batmanabane et al </p>



<p>Figure 2. (Left) Actual versus MM-predicted weight. The solid line represents the line of unity. The value on the x-axis 
represents the singular child for whom a weight could not be estimated by the MM. (Right) modified Bland-Altman plot 
depicting the log-transformed difference between predicted weight and actual weight versus average log weight. Dashed lines 
depict the 95% limits of agreements. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Actual versus predicted weight for 12 other weight estimation strategies. The solid lines represent the lines of 
unity. Values on the x-axis represent children for whom weight could not be estimated by the various methods. </p>



<p>Global Pediatric Health </p>

<p>Declaration of Conflicting Interests </p>

<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with 
respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this 
article. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was funded by the World Health Organization. The 
authors alone are responsible for the views expressed in this 
publication and they do not necessarily represent the deci-
sions, policy or views of the World Health Organization. </p>



<p>Batmanabane et al </p>





</text></tei>