<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4234332" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>O </p>

<p>bjective: In the present study, we examined whether 2, 2-bis [4-(2-hydroxy-3-
methacryloxypropoxy) phenyl] propane (Bis-GMA) has effects on LSC2 cells, human 
dental pulp cell line. Material and Methods: The viability, cell cycle, and morphology of 
LSC2 cells were analyzed after exposure to several different concentrations of Bis-GMA. The 
recovery of viability of Bis-GMA exposed cells was also analyzed in the condition without 
Bis-GMA. Further, penetration of Bis-GMA to dentin disc was examined using isocratic 
high-performance liquid chromatography. Results: There was a concentration-dependent 
decrease in cell proliferation and an increase in cell number in the sub-G1 population after 
exposure to Bis-GMA. Furthermore, the cells showed typical characteristics of apoptotic cells 
after the exposure to high concentration of Bis-GMA. In contrast, cells exposed to lower 
concentrations of Bis-GMA recovered their viability after being cultured without Bis-GMA. 
We also found that Bis-GMA is capable of penetrating 1-mm-thick dentin discs, though 
the penetrated concentration was lower than that showing cytotoxicity. Conclusion: These 
results suggest that Bis-GMA has cytotoxic effects, though dental pulp exposed to lower 
concentrations is able to recover their viability when Bis-GMA is removed. </p>

<p>During restorative procedures for a carious tooth, 
dental pulp is exposed to a variety of stimulations 
such as heat stress produced by cavity preparation </p>

<p>2   , 
and hypoxia produced by local anesthesia </p>

<p>1   . 
When composite resin is used as a restorative 
material, dentists sometimes note inflammatory 
responses of dental pulp, which are considered to 
be caused by microleakage at the interface between 
cavity walls and filled composite resin 
8,10 . Other 
studies have suggested that unpolymerized resin 
monomers remaining on the cavity floor may irritate 
dental pulp cells directly or indirectly through 
dentin, resulting in inflammatory responses </p>

<p>9,12   . 
It has previously been reported that apoptosis of </p>

<p>pulp cells was induced during pulp wound healing 
after cavity preparation </p>

<p>5   , and that apoptosis of pulp 
cell line was induced by heat stress 
6 and hypoxia </p>

<p>13   . 
It was also found that capping agents modified 
pulp apoptosis induction </p>

<p>7   . Apoptotic cells induced 
in dental pulp disappear during pulp wound healing 
processes, suggesting cytotoxic effects of external 
stimulations via residual dentin and the recovery of 
dental pulp viability. However, it is largely unknown 
whether dental pulp cells adversely affected by resin 
monomers can recover their viability. In the present 
study, we examined effects of resin monomer, 
2, 2-bis [4-(2-hydroxy-3-methacryloxypropoxy) 
phenyl] propane (Bis-GMA), on the viability of 
human dental pulp cell line. </p>

<p>2011;19(3):218-22 </p>

<p>J Appl Oral Sci. 219 </p>

<p>MATERIAL AND METhODS </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>LSC2 cells, a dental pulp cell line derived from 
human dental pulp </p>

<p>11   , were maintained in Dulbecco's 
modified Eagle's medium (DMEM; Invitrogen Corp., 
Carlsbad, CA, USA) containing 10% heat-inactivated 
fetal calf serum (FCS), 100 μg/mL of streptomycin, 
and 100 U/mL of penicillin, and then incubated in a 
humidified atmosphere of 5% CO 2 at 37˚C. </p>

<p>Cell proliferation assay </p>

<p>LSC2 cells (2x10 
4 cells/well) were cultured in 
96 well plate with a medium containing 5% FCS 
for 24 h, then the medium was exchanged to that 
containing 1% FCS. Several different concentrations 
(0.01, 0.02, 0.03, and 0.04 mmol/L) of Bis-GMA 
(Polyscience Inc., Warrington, PA, USA) diluted by 
dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO; Wako Pure Chemical Inc, 
Osaka, Japan) were added to the culture medium. 
At 48 h after exposure to Bis-GMA, cell proliferation 
was examined using the 5-bromo-2'-deoxyuridine 
(BrdU) assay (The Biotrak cell proliferation ELISA 
system version 2; Ge Healthcare UK Ltd, UK). Cell 
viability was analyzed by measuring optical density 
(OD) using a test wavelength of 540 nm and a 
reference wavelength of 620 nm with a multiscan 
biochromatic microplate reader (Multiscan JX; 
Thermo Fisher Scientific K.K., Yokohama, Japan). </p>

<p>Cell cycle analysis </p>

<p>LSC2 cells were exposed to Bis-GMA for 48 h, 
then suspended in a hypotonic solution (0.1% Triton 
X-100, 1 mmol/L Tris/HCl, pH 8.0, 3.4 mmol/L 
sodium citrate, 0.1 mmol/L eDTA) and stained with 
5 μg/mL of propidium iodide, after which cell-cycle 
distribution was analyzed with a FACScalibur flow 
cytometer EPICS XL (Beckman Coulter Inc., Brea, 
CA, USA). </p>

<p>Detection of cell death by hoechst staining </p>

<p>LSC2 cells were exposed to Bis-GMA in a chamber 
slides for 48 h, then fixed with 1% glutaraldehyde 
for 30 min, washed with 1x phosphate buffered 
saline (PBS), and stained with 5 g/mL of Hoechst 
dye 33342 (Life Technologies Co., CA, USA). Cells 
detached from the coverslips into the medium were 
also recovered by centrifugation and stained. Nuclei 
were observed under a fluorescence microscope 
(OLYMPUS BX50/BX-FLA/DP70; Olympus Co., 
Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>Cell recovery after removal of Bis-gMA from 
culture medium </p>

<p>After exposure of LSC2 cells to Bis-GMA for 48 h, 
the wells were rinsed by PBS, and added a medium 
containing 10% FCS without Bis-GMA. After the 
culture of surviving cells in a humidified atmosphere </p>

<p>of 5% CO 2 at 37˚C for 96 h, cell proliferation and 
cell cycle were analyzed. </p>

<p>Dentin penetration assay </p>

<p>Dentin discs (1 mm thick, minimum diameter: 6 
mm) were cut from freshly extracted sound human 
third molars using a low speed diamond-coated saw 
(Isomet; Buehler, Lake Bluff, IL, USA) under water 
coolant, then etched for 60 s with 35% phosphoric 
acid to completely open dentinal tubules, rinsed 
with ultrasonication for 3 min in distilled water, 
and placed in the PFA tube (Sanplatec, Osaka, 
Japan). The lower chamber was filled with distilled 
water and the upper chamber with 0.2 mmol/L of 
Bis-GMA. After standing in a humid chamber at 
room temperature for 2 weeks, the distilled water 
was collected and mixed with chloroform to isolate 
Bis-GMA. Bis-GMA was detected using isocratic 
high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) 
(Waters, Milford, MA, USA) with a reverse-phase 
column (μ-Bondashere C18, 5 μm, 300 A column, 
JLC010032Y) (Waters) at 280 nm. The peak area </p>

<p>Figure 1-Cytotoxic effects of 2, 2-bis [4-(2-hydroxy-3-
methacryloxypropoxy) phenyl] propane (Bis-GMA) on 
LSC2 cells. (A). Viability of LSC2 cells after exposure to 
Bis-GMA. (B). Cell cycle of LSC2 cells after exposure to 
Bis-GMA </p>

<p>Apoptosis and survivability of human dental pulp cells under exposure to Bis-GMA </p>

<p>2011;19(3):218-22 </p>

<p>J Appl Oral Sci. 220 </p>

<p>of Bis-GMA shown by HPLC tracing was analyzed 
using the Waters 2487 Dual λ absorbance detector 
(Waters), and the amount of Bis-GMA was calculated 
from the calibration curve of known concentrations 
from control experiments. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analysis of the data was performed 
using one-way ANOVA followed by a multiple-
comparison Sheffe's test with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statview</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS software Inc</rs>., Cary, NC, USA). Statistical 
significance was determined at p&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Cell death of human dental pulp cells after 
exposure to Bis-gMA </p>

<p>The viability of LSC2 cells decreased after 
exposure to Bis-GMA in a dose-dependent manner 
(Figure 1A). There was no significant difference 
(p&gt;0.05) in viability between 0 and 0.01 mmol/L 
of Bis-GMA, whereas significant decreases of cell 
viability were observed after being cultured with 
0.02, 0.03, and 0.04 mmol/L of Bis-GMA (p&lt;0.01). 
The effects of exposure to Bis-GMA on cell cycle 
progression of LSC2 cells are shown in Figure 1B. </p>

<p>exposure to Bis-GMA reduced the number of the 
cells in G1, S, and G2/M phases in a dose-dependent 
manner, with a concomitant increase of those in 
the sub-G1 population, implying cell death such 
as apoptosis. 
Morphological changes of LSC2 cells following 
exposure to Bis-GMA are shown in Figure 2. The 
structures of those cells exposed to 0.01 mmol/L 
of Bis-GMA were nearly the same as those of the 
control, whereas the rounding and the detachment 
were observed in cells exposed to 0.04 mmol/L 
of Bis-GMA (Figure 2A). Fluorescent microscopic 
analysis revealed that the nuclei of adhesive cells 
had normal structures, whereas those of cells that 
had fallen into the medium after exposure to 0.04 
mmol/L of Bis-GMA showed fragmentation, a typical 
characteristic of apoptotic cells (Figure 2B). </p>

<p>Recovery of cell viability after the removal 
of Bis-gMA </p>

<p>Following exposure to Bis-GMA, surviving cells 
attached to the bottom of the well were cultured in 
normal condition without Bis-GMA (Figure 3A). The 
proliferation of surviving cells following exposure to 
0.01 and 0.02 mmol/L of Bis-GMA was not different 
after 24 h of cell culture in normal condition, and </p>

<p>Figue 2-Morphological changes of LSC2 cells promoted by 2, 2-bis [4-(2-hydroxy-3-methacryloxypropoxy) phenyl] propane 
(Bis-GMA). (A). Phase-contrast microphotographs of LSC2 cells after exposure to Bis-GMA. Original magnification, x100. 
(B). Fluorescent microphotographs of LSC2 cells after exposure to Bis-GMA. Original magnification, x400 </p>

<p>YANO J, KITAMURA C, NISHIHARA T, TOKUDA M, WASHIO A, CHEN KK, TERASHITA M </p>

<p>2011;19(3):218-22 </p>

<p>J Appl Oral Sci. 221 </p>

<p>then increased at 48 and 96 h, while surviving 
cells exposed to 0.03 mmol/L of Bis-GMA showed 
proliferation at 96 h. In contrast, exposure to 0.04 
mmol/L of Bis-GMA showed great cytotoxicity on 
the viability of the cells, and proliferation was 
not recovered during the culture in the normal 
condition. The recovery of cell-cycle progression 
in surviving cells exposed to 0.01, 0.02, and 0.03 
mmol/L of Bis-GMA was also observed (Figure 
3B). When Bis-GMA-exposed cells were cultured 
in normal condition without Bis-GMA for 96 h, the 
cell cycle distribution pattern of Bis-GMA-insulted 
cells returned to that prior to exposure to Bis-GMA. </p>

<p>Dentin penetration of Bis-gMA through 
dentinal tubules </p>

<p>In the penetration model, Bis-GMA penetrated 
through 1 mm thick dentin disc. From the calibration </p>

<p>curve of known concentrations of Bis-GMA, the 
average concentration of penetrated Bis-GMA was 
0.0043 mmol/L (Figure 4). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In the present study, it was found that exposure 
to high concentrations of Bis-GMA induced an 
increase in cell number in the sub-G1 population in 
cell-cycle, and the cell death with typical structures 
of apoptosis, suggesting that direct exposure to a 
high concentration of Bis-GMA induced apoptosis 
in human dental pulp cells. 
It was also examined whether LSC2 cells 
exposed to Bis-GMA can recover their viability after 
the removal of Bis-GMA. We cultured surviving cells 
after exposure to Bis-GMA in the normal medium 
without Bis-GMA, and found that the cells exposed 
to 0.01, 0,02, and 0.03 mmol/L of Bis-GMA showed 
the recovery of the cell proliferation, whereas 
those exposed to 0.04 mmol/L of Bis-GMA did not 
recover their proliferation. In addition, cell-cycle 
of surviving cells after exposure to 0.01, 0.02, and 
0.03 mmol/L of Bis-GMA returned to the same level 
as the control. These results suggest that even after 
the exposure to Bis-GMA, LSC2 cells have an ability 
to recover their viability when the concentration of 
Bis-GMA is low, whereas the cells exposed to high 
concentration of Bis-GMA lose such recovery ability. 
Another finding of the present study was that the 
average concentration of Bis-GMA that penetrated 
1 mm thick dentin was 0.0043 mmol/L, which was 
lower than the concentration used in the present 
study. These results are consistent with previous 
studies </p>

<p>3,4   , and suggest that an adequate volume of </p>

<p>Figue 3-Survival of LSC2 cells against 2, 2-bis 
[4-(2-hydroxy-3-methacryloxypropoxy) phenyl] propane 
(Bis-GMA). (A). Recovery of viability of LSC2 cells that 
survived after exposure to Bis-GMA. Concentrations of 
Bis-GMA (mmol/L); 0 (black circle), 0.01 (white circle), 0.02 
(white rectangle), 0.03 (black triangle), and 0.04 (white 
triangle). (B). Cell cycle of LSC2 cells that survived after 
exposure to Bis-GMA </p>

<p>Figue 4-Calibration curve of known concentrations of 
2, 2-bis [4-(2-hydroxy-3-methacryloxypropoxy) phenyl] 
propane (Bis-GMA) and concentrations of Bis-GMA that 
penetrated 1 mm dentin discs. White rectangles indicate 
known concentrations of control Bis-GMA for the calibration 
curve. Black rectangles indicate concentrations calculated 
from HPLC results of penetrated Bis-GMA </p>

<p>Apoptosis and survivability of human dental pulp cells under exposure to Bis-GMA </p>

<p>2011;19(3):218-22 </p>

<p>J Appl Oral Sci. 222 </p>

<p>residual dentin thickness would be able to suppress 
the penetration of a harmful concentration of Bis-
GMA. 
Taken together, the findings of the present study 
suggest that dental pulp cells have the tolerance 
against lower concentrations of resin monomers, 
and that polymerized composite resin on the 
sufficient thickness of residual dentin may not be 
harmful to dental pulp. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>These results produced evidence that Bis-GMA 
has cytotoxic effects, though dental pulp exposed to 
lower concentrations is able to recover their viability 
when Bis-GMA is removed. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDgEMENTS </p>

<p>This research was supported by Grants in Aid for 
Scientific Research 18209057 and 20592231 from 
The Ministry of education, Science, and Culture of 
Japan, Tokyo, Japan. </p>



<p>YANO J, KITAMURA C, NISHIHARA T, TOKUDA M, WASHIO A, CHEN KK, TERASHITA M </p>

<p>2011;19(3):218-22 </p>

</text></tei>