<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4264456" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Folate receptor 1 (FOLR1) is expressed in the majority of ovarian carcinomas (OvCa), making it an attractive target 
for therapy. However, clinical trials testing anti-FOLR1 therapies in OvCa show mixed results and require better understanding of 
the prognostic relevance of FOLR1 expression. We conducted a large study evaluating FOLR1 expression with survival in different 
histological types of OvCa. </p>

<p>Methods: Tissue microarrays composed of tumour samples from 2801 patients in the Ovarian Tumour Tissue Analysis (OTTA) 
consortium were assessed for FOLR1 expression by centralised immunohistochemistry. We estimated associations for overall (OS) 
and progression-free (PFS) survival using adjusted Cox regression models. High-grade serous ovarian carcinomas (HGSC) from 
The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) were evaluated independently for association between FOLR1 mRNA upregulation and 
survival. </p>

<p>Results: FOLR1 expression ranged from 76% in HGSC to 11% in mucinous carcinomas in OTTA. For HGSC, the association 
between FOLR1 expression and OS changed significantly during the years following diagnosis in OTTA (P interaction ¼ 0.01, 
N ¼ 1422) and TCGA (P interaction ¼ 0.01, N ¼ 485). In OTTA, particularly for FIGO stage I/II tumours, patients with FOLR1-positive 
HGSC showed increased OS during the first 2 years only (hazard ratio ¼ 0.44, 95% confidence interval ¼ 0.20-0.96) and patients 
with FOLR1-positive clear cell carcinomas (CCC) showed decreased PFS independent of follow-up time (HR ¼ 1.89, 95% CI ¼ 1.10-
3.25, N ¼ 259). In TCGA, FOLR1 mRNA upregulation in HGSC was also associated with increased OS during the first 2 years 
following diagnosis irrespective of tumour stage (HR: 0.48, 95% CI: 0.25-0.94). </p>

<p>Conclusions: FOLR1-positive HGSC tumours were associated with an increased OS in the first 2 years following diagnosis. Patients 
with FOLR1-negative, poor prognosis HGSC would be unlikely to benefit from anti-FOLR1 therapies. In contrast, a decreased PFS 
interval was observed for FOLR1-positive CCC. The clinical efficacy of FOLR1-targeted interventions should therefore be 
evaluated according to histology, stage and time following diagnosis. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
FOLR1 in ovarian cancer </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.567 </p>

<p>Folate receptor 1 (FOLR1) is a member of the folate receptor 
family that has restricted expression in normal epithelial cells, but 
is reported to be highly expressed in various tumours of epithelial 
origin including the majority of ovarian carcinomas (Kelemen et al,  2005; Parker et al, 2005; Chen et al, 2012; Crane et al, 2012;  Despierre et al, 2013; O'Shannessy et al, 2013). FOLR1 has high 
affinity for binding folic acid (Parker et al, 2005). Because folate is 
essential for DNA synthesis and one-carbon transfer, it has been 
hypothesised that FOLR1 might confer a growth advantage to the 
tumour by modulating folate uptake (Kane et al, 1988) or 
generating regulatory signals (Miotti et al, 2000). However, others 
showed that FOLR1 was not the major transport route for 
intracellular accumulation of physiological folates or anti-folates in 
various cell lines including the IGROV-1 ovarian cancer cells 
(Kamen and Smith, 2012), thereby disputing the theory of FOLR1-
medicated tumour uptake of folate for proliferation. 
Studies evaluating the prognostic value of FOLR1 expression in 
ovarian carcinoma have produced conflicting results. Chen et al  (2012) reported that FOLR1 mRNA upregulation was an 
unfavourable prognostic marker in a study of 91 serous ovarian 
carcinomas. In two studies that used immunohistochemistry 
(IHC), women with FOLR1 expressing ovarian carcinomas had 
no difference in survival rate: RR 0.86, 95% CI 0.57-1.31, P ¼ 0.49, 
N ¼ 186 (Kalli et al, 2008) and RR 0.80, 95% CI 0.5-1.1, P ¼ 0.2, 
N ¼ 361 (Crane et al, 2012). These two studies contained a mixture 
of all histological types, which may mask associations when both 
the marker prevalence (Kalli et al, 2008) and survival rates (Kobel  et al, 2008) differ between the histological types. 
The prognostic significance of FOLR1 may have therapeutic 
relevance. FOLR1 selectivity, affinity and restricted tissue distribu-
tion has christened it as a universal target for exploitation (van  Dam et al, 2011) for therapy or imaging of solid tumours (Leamon  and Reddy, 2004) or circulating tumour cells (He et al, 2008). 
Different treatment modalities have been proposed including folic 
acid-conjugated toxins that bind FOLR1 and release the toxin upon 
internalisation to kill tumour cells (Kelemen, 2006), and anti-
tumour immune-based therapies that enhance the body's natural 
immunity against tumour cells (Knutson et al, 2006). However, 
clinical trials testing therapies against FOLR1 in ovarian carcinoma 
have produced mixed results. For example, farletuzumab (Konner  et al, 2010; Spannuth et al, 2010; Armstrong et al, 2013) is a 
humanised monoclonal antibody against FOLR1, which was shown 
to mediate antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity and comple-
ment-dependent cytotoxicity and to inhibit cell growth of a 
Chinese hamster ovary cell line transfected with FOLR1 when 
grown in low-folate medium (Ebel et al, 2007), although 
subsequent studies showed it minimally altered cell growth in cell 
lines naturally expressing FOLR1, including IGROV-1 ovarian 
cancer cells (Kamen and Smith, 2012). The results from a phase III 
clinical trial (NCT00849667) found that farletuzumab in combina-
tion with carboplatin and taxane did not meet the study's primary 
end point of progression-free survival (PFS), and analyses are 
ongoing in patient subsets (Walters et al, 2013). More recently, a 
phase II clinical trial reported longer median PFS among 100 
selected patients with recurrent platinum-resistant ovarian carci-
noma who were treated with a combination of vintafolide, a folic 
acid-desacetylvinblastine conjugate that binds to the folate 
receptor, and pegylated liposomal doxorubicin (PLD) compared 
with 49 patients who received PLD alone (5.0 vs 2.7 months PFS, 
respectively; P ¼ 0.03) (Naumann et al, 2013). The drug was 
particularly effective in patients diffusely positive for FOLR1. No 
difference in overall survival (OS) was detected, although the trial 
was not powered to detect a statistical difference (Naumann et al,  2013). 
To address discrepant findings and to improve upon previous 
study designs, we evaluated tumours from 2801 patients from the 
Ovarian Tumour Tissue Analysis (OTTA) consortium to assess the </p>

<p>prevalence of FOLR1 protein expression and to associate 
prevalence with survival for the different histological types 
separately. The goal of the OTTA consortium is to combine tissue 
microarray resources to overcome the limitations of prognostic 
studies associated with small sample sizes. We also utilised data 
from The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) as a large, independent 
sample to evaluate these associations. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients. Twelve individual studies comprising 2801 patients 
participating in the OTTA consortium were included for FOLR1 
IHC expression analysis. Several of these studies also participated 
in previous OTTA IHC analyses (Kobel et al, 2013; Sieh et al, 2013)  and were assessed using a biomarker-assisted review of patients' 
slides for histological classification (Kobel et al, 2013). Informed 
consent was obtained from patients in seven of 12 studies. For the 
Alberta Ovarian Tumor Types study (AOV), Calgary Serous 
Carcinoma study (CAL), Nottingham Ovarian Cancer study 
(NOT), Toronto Ovarian Cancer study (TOC) and British 
Columbia Cancer Agency study (VAN), the institutional research 
ethics boards waived the need to obtain consent and all local 
human research investigations committees approved each study. 
Key demographical and clinical data on the patients were merged 
into one common data set that was checked for consistency and 
completeness, and discrepancies were addressed with individual 
study investigators. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry (IHC). Centralised IHC was performed 
on a Leica Bond Max platform (Leica Microsystems, Wetzlar, 
Germany). The submitted glass slides from tissue microarrays were 
subjected to heat-induced antigen retrieval for 20 min using the 
Leica Epitope Retrieval Solution 2. Slides were incubated with 
the FOLR1 mouse monoclonal antibody from Novocastra (Leica 
Microsystems) clone BN3.2 (catalogue #NCL-F-FRalpha) for 
15 min at a 1 : 50 dilution. </p>

<p>Scoring. Two observers (MK, JM) scored the FOLR1 staining. We 
combined a measure of the intensity, extent and subcellular 
localisation into a five-tier scoring system: absent or weak staining, 
strong staining of 1-50% of tumour cells irrespective of subcellular 
localisation, strong staining of 450% of tumour cells with 
membranous localisation (with no penalisation for accompanying 
weak cytoplasmic staining), strong staining of 50-95% of tumour 
cells with cytoplasmic staining (and membranous staining 
still present) and strong staining of 495% of tumour cells with 
cytoplasmic staining (Figure 1). The inter-observer reproducibility 
of the five-tier IHC scoring system between the two observers was 
evaluated in a subset of 183 patients and was high (weighted 
Cohen's kappa ¼ 0.91). We also compared the five-tier IHC scores 
for FOLR1 obtained using the BN3.2 antibody with FOLR1 mRNA 
expression data derived by RNA sequencing from a subset of 36 
patients (Shah et al, 2009). The IHC scores correlated reasonably 
well with the mRNA expression values (Pearson r ¼ 0.77). </p>

<p>The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA). We downloaded publicly-
available data from 563 serous ovarian carcinomas from TCGA 
(The Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network, 2011) using the 
cBIOPortal for Cancer Genomics (Cerami et al, 2012) to assess 
prevalence of FOLR1 mRNA expression in tumour relative to 
normal tissue (fallopian tube) and to evaluate expression with 
survival outcomes as described below. Gene expression in TCGA 
was evaluated using the Agilent 244K Custom Gene Expression 
G4502A_07 (Santa Clara, CA, USA) assayed at the University of 
North Carolina and expressed as fold change between tumour and 
normal tissue on the log2 scale (The Cancer Genome Atlas 
Research Network, 2011). </p>

<p>FOLR1 in ovarian cancer 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.567 </p>

<p>
Statistical analysis. We assessed 2801 patients from the OTTA 
consortium for prevalence of FOLR1 expression and included the 
five main histological types: high-grade serous carcinoma (HGSC), 
low-grade serous carcinoma (LGSC), mucinous carcinoma 
(MC), endometrioid carcinoma (EC) and clear cell carcinoma 
(CCC). Patients with absent or weak FOLR1 staining were 
recorded as negative, whereas all the other FOLR1 staining 
patterns were considered positive results. In separate analyses 
using the larger sample size of HGSC in OTTA, we visually 
inspected Kaplan-Meier survival curves and evaluated statistical 
associations between patients using the five-tier scoring system for 
FOLR1 and also with different combinations of scores (e.g., strong 
staining of 450% of tumour cells with cytoplasmic or membra-
nous staining vs all other staining patterns) stratified by the 
FIGO (International Federation of Obstetricians and Gynaeco-
logists) stage. None of these alternate combinations produced 
associations that were materially different from the positive/ 
negative staining comparison (data not shown). 
The Cox proportional hazard model was used to estimate 
hazard ratios (HRs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) between 
positive/negative categories of FOLR1 and OS or PFS stratified by 
histological type. In the OTTA consortium, OS was defined as 
death from any cause after ovarian carcinoma diagnosis and PFS 
was defined as survival without disease progression or recurrence 
determined by radiological, serological or clinical evidence or death 
from any cause, whichever came first. Stage at diagnosis was 
determined using the cancer registry and/or FIGO stage informa-
tion from each site (SEER guidelines: http://seer.cancer.gov/) and 
categorised as FIGO stage I/II (localised and regional) and FIGO 
stage III/IV (distant). Because time from diagnosis to study entry </p>

<p>was variable, we allowed for left truncation with time at risk 
starting on the date of diagnosis and time under observation 
beginning at the time of study entry. Analyses were right censored 
at 5 years after ovarian carcinoma diagnosis in order to reduce the 
number of non-ovarian carcinoma-related deaths. The propor-
tional hazard assumption was evaluated with standard diagnostic 
methods, including likelihood ratio tests comparing models with 
and without terms that modelled covariates as a function of follow-
up time on the natural logarithmic scale (Hosmer and Lameshow,  1999). Final models were fitted using Cox regression stratified by 
study to correct for violations of the proportional hazard 
assumption and adjusted for potential confounding with age at 
diagnosis (o70 or X70 years), FIGO tumour stage (I/II, III/IV or 
missing) and presence of residual disease at primary surgery 
(macroscopic, no macroscopic or missing). An interaction term 
between the aforementioned covariates and follow-up time was 
included, where necessary, to improve model fit. In addition, we 
considered models separately by the FIGO tumour stage. Data for 
regression analyses were available for 2636 patients following the 
exclusion of patients with missing vital status (N ¼ 13), missing 
time from diagnosis to study entry (N ¼ 66), missing follow-up 
time (N ¼ 43), missing FIGO stage (N ¼ 84, excluded for stage-
stratified analyses only) and patients with study entry 45 years 
from diagnosis (N ¼ 43). 
Using TCGA data, FOLR1 mRNA information was available for 
485 patients and we defined mRNA upregulation as 41 s.d. from the 
mean on the log2 scale. Associations with OS and PFS were evaluated 
with follow-up time as described above and adjusted for the FIGO 
tumour stage (I/II, III/IV or missing) and presence of residual disease 
at primary surgery (macroscopic, no macroscopic or missing). 
Separate models also adjusted for platinum therapy sensitivity 
(resistant, sensitive, too early or missing) and treatment response 
(complete response, partial response, progressive disease, stable 
disease or missing). Age at diagnosis was not available in TCGA. 
Statistical tests were two sided and were implemented with 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> (version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">9.1</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, NC, USA) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">Stata/SE</rs> 
(version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version">13.1</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">StataCorp</rs>, College Station, TX, USA). The study 
followed the REMARK guidelines (McShane et al, 2005). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Study and patient characteristics. Table 1 describes the partici-
pating studies and methods of patient ascertainment and 
histological review. Table 2 lists the 2801 women with ovarian 
carcinoma that were included in the FOLR1 expression prevalence 
analysis, stratified by study and histological type. As expected, 
women with HGSC were older, were diagnosed with high tumour 
stage and were more likely to have macroscopic residual disease 
and shorter OS and PFS compared with women with EC (Table 3). 
Women with EC had the best prognosis. </p>

<p>FOLR1 expression across histological types. We observed 
differences in FOLR1 expression by histological type: patients 
with tumours of LGSC, MC, EC or CCC histology were more likely 
to have absent or weak FOLR1 staining compared with patients 
with HGSC tumours (Table 3). FOLR1-positive expression was 
seen in 1149 out of 1507 patients (76.2%) with HGSC, 45 out of 91 
patients (49.5%) with LGSC and 141 out of 446 patients (31.6%) 
with CCC. Normal fallopian tube tissue was included as a control 
on the tissue microarrays and was FOLR1-positive in 8 out of 8 
samples (100%) (Figure 1). </p>

<p>Association between FOLR1 expression in HGSC tumours and 
survival. In OTTA, there were no statistically significant associa-
tions with OS or PFS for HGSC overall or when evaluated 
separately by the FIGO stage; however, the association between 
FOLR1 expression and OS changed when stratified by follow-up </p>

<p>Figure 1. Immunohistochemical staining of FOLR1. (A) No staining in a 
mucinous carcinoma. (B) Strong staining of 1-50% of tumour cells in a 
high-grade serous carcinoma. (C) Strong staining of 450% of tumour 
cells with predominant membranous localisation in a high-grade serous 
carcinoma. (D) Strong staining of 50-90% of tumour cells with 
cytoplasmic staining (and membranous staining still present) in a high-
grade serous carcinoma. (E) Strong staining of 490% of tumour cells 
with cytoplasmic staining in a high-grade serous carcinoma. (F) Strong 
staining of 450% of epithelial cells with predominant membranous 
localisation in normal fallopian tube. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
FOLR1 in ovarian cancer </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.567 </p>

<p>period (P interaction with time ¼ 0.01) (Table 4). FOLR1 
expression was associated with a 29% non-significant increased 
OS (P ¼ 0.08) during the first year following diagnosis and a 50% 
non-significant decreased OS during the fourth year. The pattern 
of changing survival with increasing follow-up time, however, 
was most evident among patients with FIGO stage I/II tumours 
(P interaction with time ¼ 0.02). Among these patients, FOLR1 
expression was associated with a 56% significant increased OS 
during the first 2 years of follow-up only (HR: 0.44, 95% CI: 0.20-
0.96, P ¼ 0.04). An interaction between FOLR1 expression and 
follow-up time was not observed with PFS. 
Among 485 patients with HGSC in TCGA, FOLR1 mRNA 
upregulation was present in 93 patients (19%). The associations 
between FOLR1 mRNA upregulation and survival in TCGA were 
similar to those observed in the OTTA data for HGSC. 
A significant interaction with follow-up time was seen for OS </p>

<p>(P interaction with time ¼ 0.02) (Table 5). Following additional 
adjustment for platinum sensitivity and treatment response, 
FOLR1 mRNA upregulation was associated with a 52% significant 
increased OS during the first 2 years of follow-up only (HR: 0.48, 
95% CI: 0.25-0.94, P ¼ 0.03) (Table 5). Although most of these 
patients had FIGO stage III/IV tumours, the association did not 
strengthen when restricted to advanced stage tumours (P ¼ 0.05). 
A non-significant interaction between FOLR1 mRNA upregulation 
and follow-up time was observed for PFS. </p>

<p>Association between FOLR1 expression in non-HGSC tumours 
and survival in OTTA. No significant interactions were found 
between FOLR1 expression and follow-up time for the other 
ovarian histological types. When stratified by stage, a non-
significant decreased OS interval was observed among patients 
with CCC and FIGO stage I/II (HR: 1.62, 95% CI: 0.97-2.71, </p>

<p>Table 1. Description of 12 participating studies in OTTA </p>

<p>Study </p>

<p>Study 
abbreviation </p>

<p>Study 
location </p>

<p>Recruitment 
period </p>

<p>Ascertainment of patients and 
clinical data 
Pathology data and review </p>

<p>Australian Ovarian Cancer 
Study (Merritt et al, 2008) </p>

<p>AOC 
Australia 
2002-2006 
Treatment centers throughout Australia; 
cancer registries serving Queensland, 
South and Western Australia; longitudinal 
follow-up through regular review of 
medical records </p>

<p>Pathology reports and 
diagnostic slides reviewed by 
a panel of gynaecologic 
pathologists </p>

<p>Alberta Ovarian Tumor 
Types Study (Kelemen 
et al, 2013) </p>

<p>AOV 
Alberta, 
Canada </p>

<p>1998-2009 
Population-based Alberta Cancer 
Registry. Annual updates are performed 
for vital statistics </p>

<p>Pathology reports and 
histological slides reviewed by 
gynaecologic pathologist </p>

<p>Bavarian Ovarian Cancer 
Study (Hein et al, 2013) </p>

<p>BAV 
Southeast 
Germany </p>

<p>2002-2006 
Gynecologic Oncology Center at the 
Comprehensive Cancer Center 
Erlangen-Nuremberg </p>

<p>Centralised review of 
pathology reports and 
histological slides for all cases 
by study pathologists </p>

<p>Calgary Serous Carcinoma 
Study (Bromley et al, 2012) </p>

<p>CAL 
Calgary, 
Canada </p>

<p>2003-2007 
Hospital-based retrospective 
observational study </p>

<p>Histological review of all slides 
by study pathologist 
supported by centralised 
biomarker analysis </p>

<p>Novel risk factors and 
potential early detection 
markers for the Ovarian 
Cancer Study (Lo-Ciganic 
et al, 2012) </p>

<p>HOP 
Western PA, 
Northeastern 
Ohio, 
Western NY, 
USA </p>

<p>2003-2009 
Hospital registries and active surveillance 
of medical practices in three catchment 
areas </p>

<p>Medical chart review for 
all cases </p>

<p>Malignant Ovarian Cancer 
Study (Glud et al, 2004; 
Soegaard et al, 2007) </p>

<p>MAL 
Denmark 
1994-1999 
Gynecological departments in 
Copenhagen, Frederiksberg and seven 
surrounding counties </p>

<p>Pathology reports reviewed 
for all cases and histological 
slides reviewed for 30% by 
gynaecologic pathologist </p>

<p>Mayo Clinic Ovarian 
Cancer Study (Goode et al, 
2011) </p>

<p>MAY þ MAC 
Northcentral 
USA </p>

<p>2000-2009 
Mayo Clinic medical records and State 
death certificates </p>

<p>Review by Mayo Clinic 
gynaecologic pathologists 
supported by centralised 
biomarker analysis </p>

<p>Nottingham Study 
(Williams et al, 2012) </p>

<p>NOT 
UK 
1991-2008 
Hospital records and Trent cancer registry Pathology reports reviewed by 
gynaecologic pathologist </p>

<p>Study of Epidemiology and 
Risk Factors in Cancer 
Heredity (Song et al, 2006) </p>

<p>SEA 
East Anglia 
and West 
Midlands, UK </p>

<p>1998-2008 
East Anglia and West Midlands Cancer 
Registry </p>

<p>Centralised review of 
pathology reports by a 
pathologist </p>

<p>Toronto Ovarian Cancer 
Study (Narod et al, 1998) </p>

<p>TOC 
Ontario, 
Canada </p>

<p>1995-2003 
Ontario Cancer Registry 
Pathology reports and 
histological slides reviewed by 
a study pathologist </p>

<p>United Kingdom Ovarian 
Cancer Population Study 
(Balogun et al, 2011) </p>

<p>UKO 
England, 
Wales and 
Northern 
Ireland, UK </p>

<p>2006-2010 
10 major Gynecologic Oncology NHS 
centers in England, Wales and Northern 
Ireland; cancer registries; NHS Information 
Centre for Health and Social Care 
(England and Wales) and Central Services 
Agency (Northern Ireland) </p>

<p>Centralised review of 
pathology reports by a 
gynaecologic oncologist </p>

<p>Vancouver Ovarian Cancer 
Study (Prentice et al, 2007; 
Kobel et al, 2010b) </p>

<p>VAN 
British 
Columbia, 
Canada </p>

<p>1984-2000 
Ovarian Cancer Registry serving British 
Columbia, and the Cheryl Brown 
Outcomes unit </p>

<p>Histological review of all slides 
by University of British 
Columbia pathologists 
supported by centralised 
biomarker analysis </p>

<p>Abbreviation: OTTA ¼ ovarian tumour tissue analysis. </p>

<p>FOLR1 in ovarian cancer 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.567 </p>

<p>
P ¼ 0.07) (Table 6), whereas a 57% significant decreased PFS 
interval was seen among patients with CCC overall (HR: 1.57, 95% 
CI: 1.06-2.34, P ¼ 0.02), which was more pronounced 
among patients with FIGO stage I/II tumours (HR: 1.89, 95% CI: 
1.10-3.25, P ¼ 0.02) (Table 7). No other associations were found. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our investigation showed that the association between FOLR1 
expression or FOLR1 mRNA upregulation among B1900 patients </p>

<p>with HGSC from two independent data sets changed significantly 
during the years following diagnosis. In OTTA, this translated to 
an increase in OS by 56% among women with FOLR1-positive 
HGSC in the first 2 years of follow-up only and a decrease in PFS 
by 89% among women with FOLR1-positive CCC irrespective of 
follow-up time. Both findings were more pronounced among 
patients with FIGO stage I/II tumours. 
Both our OTTA data and those we analysed from TCGA 
provide evidence, for the first time, that the association between 
FOLR1 expression and OS in HGSC changes with the duration of 
follow-up regardless of whether FOLR1 was measured as protein or 
mRNA. Previous studies reported either unfavourable prognosis </p>

<p>Table 2. Number of patients with invasive ovarian carcinoma across studies and by histological type in OTTA </p>

<p>Study 
abbreviation </p>

<p>Total patients 
N ¼ 2801 </p>

<p>HGSC 
N ¼ 1507 </p>

<p>LGSC 
N ¼ 91 </p>

<p>MC 
N ¼ 193 </p>

<p>EC 
N ¼ 564 </p>

<p>CCC 
N ¼ 446 </p>

<p>AOC 
89 
89 
0 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>AOV 
209 
0 
0 
18 
95 
96 </p>

<p>BAV 
214 
133 
19 
19 
26 
17 </p>

<p>CAL 
68 
63 
5 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>HOP 
34 
25 
1 
0 
7 
1 </p>

<p>MAL 
245 
117 
12 
21 
66 
29 </p>

<p>MAY 
460 
337 
17 
14 
63 
29 </p>

<p>NOT 
196 
106 
9 
16 
39 
26 </p>

<p>SEA 
364 
164 
8 
42 
92 
58 </p>

<p>TOC 
160 
50 
0 
20 
45 
45 </p>

<p>UKO 
102 
68 
7 
5 
7 
15 </p>

<p>VAN 
660 
355 
13 
38 
124 
130 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CCC ¼ clear cell carcinoma; EC ¼ endometrioid carcinoma; HGSC ¼ high-grade serous carcinoma; LGSC ¼ low-grade serous carcinoma; MC ¼ mucinous carcinoma; 
OTTA ¼ ovarian tumour tissue analysis. </p>

<p>Table 3. Characteristics of patients with invasive ovarian carcinoma by histological type in OTTA </p>

<p>Characteristic </p>

<p>HGSC 
N ¼ 1507 </p>

<p>LGSC 
N ¼ 91 </p>

<p>MC 
N ¼ 193 </p>

<p>EC 
N ¼ 564 </p>

<p>CCC 
N ¼ 446 </p>

<p>Age at diagnosis, mean±s.d. 
61.1±11.2 
55.3±13.5 
55.5±13.9 
56.1±11.8 
57.4±11.5 </p>

<p>Total years followed 
a,b , mean ± s.d. 
4.1 ± 3.2 
5.8 ± 4.1 
5.9 ± 4.5 
6.9 ± 4.4 
5.9 ± 4.6 </p>

<p>Overall time to death 
b , years, mean±s.d. 
3.2±2.3 
4.3±3.1 
2.6±2.5 
5.0±3.9 
3.5±3.2 </p>

<p>Vital status 
b , N (%) </p>

<p>Alive 
421 (29.6) 
41 (48.2) 
114 (64.0) 
371 (70.5) 
239 (56.2) 
Died 
1001 (70.4) 
44 (51.8) 
64 (36.0) 
155 (29.5) 
186 (43.8) </p>

<p>Overall time to progression </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>, years, mean ± s.d. 
2.5 ± 2.7 
3.6 ± 4.1 
4.8 ± 4.2 
5.9 ± 4.2 
4.8 ± 4.5 </p>

<p>Progression status 
b , N (%) </p>

<p>Progression-free 
344 (30.0) 
31 (44.9) 
88 (71.5) 
284 (75.3) 
201 (58.9) 
Progressed 
804 (70.0) 
38 (55.1) 
35 (28.4) 
93 (24.7) 
140 (41.0) </p>

<p>Stage </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>, N (%) </p>

<p>FIGO IA, IB, IC, II (localised) 
379 (26.6) 
28 (32.9) 
130 (73.0) 
422 (80.2) 
328 (77.2) 
FIGO III, IV (distant) 
1030 (72.4) 
58 (65.9) 
34 (19.1) 
88 (16.7) 
82 (19.3) 
Unknown 
13 (0.9) 
1 (1.1) 
14 (7.9) 
16 (3.0) 
15 (3.5) </p>

<p>Macroscopic residual disease 
b , N (%) </p>

<p>No 
447 (31.4) 
43 (50.6) 
91 (51.1) 
327 (62.2) 
254 (59.8) 
Yes 
634 (45.6) 
24 (28.2) 
29 (16.3) 
49 (9.3) 
45 (10.6) 
Unknown 
341 (24.0) 
18 (21.2) 
58 (32.6) 
150 (28.5) 
126 (29.6) </p>

<p>FOLR1 expression, N (%) </p>

<p>Absent/weak 
358 (23.8) 
46 (51.0) 
171 (88.6) 
398 (70.6) 
305 (68.3) 
Strong 1-50% 
371 (24.6) 
20 (22.0) 
12 (6.2) 
100 (17.7) 
88 (19.7) 
Strong membranous 450% 
282 (18.7) 
15 (16.5) 
6 (3.1) 
44 (7.8) 
29 (6.5) 
Strong cytoplasmic 50-95% 
367 (24.4) 
8 (8.8) 
2 (1.0) 
17 (3.0) 
21 (4.7) 
Strong cytoplasmic 495% 
129 (8.6) 
2 (2.2) 
2 (1.0) 
5 (0.9) 
3 (0.7) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CCC ¼ clear cell carcinoma; EC ¼ endometrioid carcinoma; FOLR1 ¼ folate receptor 1; HGSC ¼ high-grade serous carcinoma; LGSC ¼ low-grade serous carcinoma; 
MC ¼ mucinous carcinoma; OS ¼ overall survival; OTTA ¼ ovarian tumour tissue analysis; PFS ¼ progression-free survival. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mean years follow-up among cases regardless of vital status or progression status. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Smaller sample size is based on availability of OS and PFS information from patients (1422 HGSC, 85 LGSC, 178 MC, 526 EC and 425 CCC). </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
FOLR1 in ovarian cancer </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.567 </p>

<p>Table 4. Associations 
a between FOLR1 expression 
b and OS and PFS for 1422 high-grade serous ovarian carcinomas in OTTA </p>

<p>Overall survival 
Progression-free survival 
Time period 
Died, N 
HR (95% CI) 
P-value 
Progressed, N 
HR (95% CI) 
P-value </p>

<p>No stratification by follow-up 
825 
0.99 (0.84-1.18) 
0.95 
732 
0.99 (0.81-1.19) 
0.88 </p>

<p>Five-period follow-up </p>

<p>0-1-year follow-up 
134 
0.71 (0.48-1.05) 
0.08 
-
-</p>

<p>1-2-year follow-up 
208 
0.90 (0.65-1.26) 
0.55 
-
-</p>

<p>2-3-year follow-up 
207 
1.23 (0.86-1.74) 
0.26 
-
-</p>

<p>3-4-year follow-up 
174 
0.93 (0.64-1.34) 
0.69 
-
-</p>

<p>4-5-year follow-up 
102 
1.50 (0.87-2.58) 
0.15 
-
-</p>

<p>P interaction with time 
0.01 
0.84 </p>

<p>Three-period follow-up </p>

<p>0-1-year follow-up 
134 
0.71 (0.48-1.05) 
0.08 
-
-</p>

<p>1-4-year follow-up 
589 
1.01 (0.82-1.24) 
0.91 
-
-</p>

<p>4-5-year follow-up 
102 
1.50 (0.87-2.58) 
0.15 
-
-</p>

<p>Stratified by stage </p>

<p>FIGO stage I/II 
No stratification by follow-up 
126 
1.07 (0.72-1.58) 
0.74 
88 
1.04 (0.66-1.65) 
0.84 </p>

<p>Three-period follow-up 
0-2-year follow-up 
29 
0.44 (0.20-0.96) 
0.04 
-
-
2-3-year follow-up 
35 
1.25 (0.58-2.69) 
0.57 
-
-</p>

<p>3-5-year follow-up 
62 
1.62 (0.88-2.96) 
0.12 
-
-
P interaction with time 
0.02 
0.70 </p>

<p>FIGO stage III/IV 
No stratification by follow-up 
692 
1.00 (0.83-1.21) 
0.97 
643 
1.01 (0.82-1.23) 
0.95 
P interaction with time 
0.21 
0.95 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI ¼ confidence interval; HR ¼ hazard ratio; OS ¼ overall survival; PFS ¼ progression-free survival. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>HR and 95% CI estimated using Cox regression stratified by study and adjusted for age at diagnosis, residual disease (not macroscopic, macroscopic or missing) and FIGO stage (I/II, III/IV or 
missing). Models that stratified by stage did not include stage as a confounder. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Positive vs negative staining, where negative is absent or weak staining and positive is all other stains. </p>

<p>Table 5. Associations between FOLR1 mRNA upregulation and OS and PFS for 485 serous ovarian carcinomas in TCGA </p>

<p>Overall 
survival </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Overall 
survival </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Progressed, </p>

<p>Progression-
free survival </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Time period 
Died, N 
HR (95% CI) 
P-value HR (95% CI) P-value 
N 
HR (95% CI) 
P-value </p>

<p>No stratification by follow-up 
238 
0.78 (0.55-1.10) 
0.15 
0.84 (0.60-1.19) 
0.34 
280 
1.08 (0.81-1.45) 
0.59 </p>

<p>Five-period follow-up </p>

<p>0-1-year follow-up 
42 
0.31 (0.10-1.01) 
0.05 
0.42 (0.13-1.38) 
0.15 
-
-
1-2-year follow-up 
53 
0.57 (0.26-1.27) 
0.17 
0.54 (0.24-1.22) 
0.14 
-
-
2-3-year follow-up 
54 
1.26 (0.68-2.36) 
0.74 
1.25 (0.65-2.40) 
0.50 
-
-
3-4-year follow-up 
53 
0.96 (0.48-1.91) 
0.91 
1.06 (0.52-2.15) 
0.87 
-
-
4-5-year follow-up 
70 
0.81 (0.45-1.46) 
0.48 
0.99 (0.42-2.34) 
0.97 
-
-
P interaction with time 
0.02 
0.01 
0.33 </p>

<p>Three-period follow-up </p>

<p>0-2-year follow-up 
95 
0.45 (0.23-0.87) 
0.02 
0.48 (0.25-0.94) 
0.03 
-
-
2-3-year follow-up 
54 
1.26 (0.68-2.36) 
0.74 
1.25 (0.65-2.40) 
0.50 
-
-
3-5-year follow-up 
123 
0.87 (0.56-1.37) 
0.56 
1.01 (0.59-1.73) 
0.98 
-
-</p>

<p>Stratified by stage </p>

<p>FIGO stage I/II 
No stratification by follow-up 
6 
0.83 (0.08-8.29) 
0.87 
0.83 (0.08-8.29) 
0.87 
14 
0.65 (0.17-2.48) 
0.53 
P interaction with time 
0.12 
0.12 
0.07 </p>

<p>FIGO stage III/IV 
No stratification by follow-up 
230 
0.78 (0.56-1.11) 
0.17 
0.85 (0.60-1.21) 
0.37 
266 
1.11 (0.83-1.50) 
0.48 </p>

<p>Three-period follow-up 
0-2-year follow-up 
93 
0.47 (0.24-0.91) 
0.02 
0.52 (0.27-1.01) 
0.05 
-
-
2-3-year follow-up 
53 
1.29 (0.69-2.42) 
0.42 
1.28 (0.67-2.45) 
0.46 
-
-
3-5-year follow-up 
84 
0.87 (0.50-1.50) 
0.61 
0.96 (0.55-1.67) 
0.88 
-
-
P interaction with time 
0.03 
0.02 
0.51 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI ¼ confidence interval; HR ¼ hazard ratio; mRNA ¼ messenger RNA; OS ¼ overall survival; PFS ¼ progression-free survival; TCGA ¼ The Cancer Genome Atlas. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>HR and 95% CI estimated using Cox regression adjusted for residual disease (not macroscopic, macroscopic or missing) and FIGO stage (I/II, III/IV or missing). Models that stratified by stage 
did not include stage as a confounder. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>All models except FIGO stage I/II model additionally adjusted for platinum sensitivity (resistant, sensitive, too early or missing) and treatment response (complete response, partial response, 
progressive disease, stable disease or missing). </p>

<p>FOLR1 in ovarian cancer 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.567 </p>

<p>
(Chen et al, 2012) or no adverse association (Kalli et al, 2008;  Crane et al, 2012) between FOLR1 protein or mRNA and OS. Time 
following diagnosis in those studies ranged from B6.5 years (Chen  et al, 2012) to 15 years (Kalli et al, 2008) and an average of the HR 
would obscure the modifying effect of follow-up time, as observed 
in the current investigation when we did not stratify by follow-up 
time. The change in association between FOLR1 expression and OS 
was more evident among FIGO stage I/II tumours in OTTA, 
whereas TCGA was composed mainly of FIGO stage III/IV 
tumours. For HGSC that did not express FOLR1, patients were 
observed to have an increased rate of death within 2 years after 
diagnosis, which attenuated with follow-up time. We speculated 
whether the absence of FOLR1 expression in the primary HGSC 
tumour was an indicator of tumours that responded poorly to </p>

<p>standard platinum chemotherapy. Inclusion of treatment response 
indicators in statistical models that were available in the TCGA 
data analysis, however, did not weaken the associations with OS 
and did not support this hypothesis. Although it is possible that 
FOLR1 expression itself may have changed with follow-up time to 
explain our observations, this is not supported by studies that 
showed no significant change in FOLR1 expression following 
chemotherapy in patients with HGSC-matched tumour from 
primary surgery and either interval debulking surgery or surgery 
for recurrent disease (Crane et al, 2012; Despierre et al, 2013). It is 
possible, therefore, that differences between patients with FOLR1-
negative poor-prognosis HGSC and FOLR1-positive tumours, 
which showed a survival advantage, may be from differences in 
intrinsic tumour biology. </p>

<p>Table 6. Associations 
a between FOLR1 expression and OS by ovarian carcinoma histological type in OTTA </p>

<p>LGSC 
MC 
EC 
CCC </p>

<p>HR (95% CI) 
HR (95% CI) 
HR (95% CI) 
HR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Alive/died, N 
54/31 
125/53 
435/91 
281/143 </p>

<p>FOLR1 expression </p>

<p>Negative </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) </p>

<p>Positive </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.31 (0.56-3.07) 
0.74 (0.26-2.12) 
0.93 (0.57-1.51) 
1.15 (0.80-1.64) </p>

<p>P-value 
0.53 
0.58 
0.77 
0.45 </p>

<p>Stratified by stage </p>

<p>FIGO stage I/II 
Alive/died, N 
26/2 
107/23 
379/43 
254/73 
Negative </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
Positive </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.58 (0.03-10.2) 
0.28 (0.04-1.71) 
1.32 (0.64-2.71) 
1.62 (0.97-2.71) 
P-value 
0.71 
0.17 
0.45 
0.07 </p>

<p>FIGO stage III/IV 
Alive/died, N 
27/29 
5/29 
41/47 
17/65 
Negative </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
Positive </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.16 (0.44-3.02) 
0.72 (0.18-2.96) 
0.66 (0.33-1.32) 
0.72 (0.41-1.28) 
P-value 
0.77 
0.65 
0.24 
0.21 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CCC ¼ clear cell carcinoma; CI ¼ confidence interval; EC ¼ endometrioid carcinoma; HR ¼ hazard ratio; FOLR1 ¼ folate receptor 1; LGSC ¼ low-grade serous carcinoma; 
MC ¼ mucinous carcinoma; OS ¼ overall survival; OTTA ¼ ovarian tumour tissue analysis. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>HR and 95% CI estimated using Cox regression stratified by study and adjusted for age, residual disease (not macroscopic, macroscopic or missing) and FIGO stage (I/II, III/IV or missing). 
Models that stratified by stage did not include stage as a confounder. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Negative is absent or weak staining and positive is all other stains. </p>

<p>Table 7. Associations 
a between FOLR1 expression and PFS by ovarian carcinoma histological type in OTTA </p>

<p>LGSC 
MC 
EC 
CCC </p>

<p>HR (95% CI) 
HR (95% CI) 
HR (95% CI) 
HR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Progression-free/progressed, N 
32/38 
94/28 
301/77 
210/123 </p>

<p>FOLR1 expression </p>

<p>Negative </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) </p>

<p>Positive </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.14 (0.53-2.44) 
1.10 (0.26-4.74) 
1.02 (0.61-1.69) 
1.57 (1.06-2.34) </p>

<p>P-value 
0.74 
0.89 
0.94 
0.02 </p>

<p>Stratified by stage </p>

<p>FIGO stage I/II 
Progression-free/progressed, N 
14/3 
86/12 
271/34 
191/68 
Negative </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
Positive </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Not estimable 
2.10 (0.21-20.5) 
1.81 (0.82-3.99) 
1.89 (1.10-3.25) 
P-value 
1.00 
0.52 
0.14 
0.02 </p>

<p>FIGO stage III/IV 
Progression-free/progressed, N 
18/35 
8/16 
28/42 
15/52 
Negative </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
1.0 (ref) 
Positive </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.97 (0.43-2.20) 
0.38 (0.03-5.12) 
0.78 (0.38-1.62) 
1.20 (0.60-2.37) 
P-value 
0.94 
0.47 
0.51 
0.60 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CCC ¼ clear cell carcinoma; CI ¼ confidence interval; EC ¼ endometrioid carcinoma; HR ¼ hazard ratio; FOLR1 ¼ folate receptor 1; LGSC ¼ low-grade serous carcinoma; 
MC ¼ mucinous carcinoma; OTTA ¼ ovarian tumour tissue analysis; PFS ¼ progression-free survival. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>HR and 95% CI estimated using Cox regression stratified by study and adjusted for age, residual disease (not macroscopic, macroscopic or missing) and FIGO stage (I/II, III/IV or missing). 
Models that stratified by stage did not include stage as a confounder. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Negative is absent or weak staining and positive is all other stains. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
FOLR1 in ovarian cancer </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.567 </p>

<p>The association between FOLR1 protein expression and 
decrease in PFS interval in patients with CCC and, specifically 
FIGO stage I/II tumours, is potentially interesting and will require 
independent confirmation. FIGO stage I/II tumours comprise the 
majority of CCC (almost 80% of CCC and 12% of all patients in 
our study) and their optimal management represents a clinical 
dilemma, because B20% of patients relapse and are resistant to 
platinum-based chemotherapy (Kobel et al, 2010a; Anglesio et al,  2011). Existing clinical trials that are testing therapies to FOLR1 
expression in ovarian carcinoma are comprised mostly of HGSC 
and one reported a favourable outcome among patients with 
platinum-resistant recurrent ovarian carcinoma (Naumann et al,  2013), which is a clinical profile similar to CCC. Interestingly, that 
study (Naumann et al, 2013) included eight patients with CCC 
(seven in the vintafolide arm). It remains to be evaluated whether 
targeting therapies specifically to FOLR1 in patients with CCC and 
FIGO stage I/II tumours improves their survival. 
We observed that FOLR1 protein was expressed in 
76% of HGSC, which agrees with a recent estimate of prevalence 
by Crane et al (2012) of 82% among 210 patients with HGSC. 
Further, only B30% of CCC and EC, and 11% of MC were positive 
for FOLR1. These estimates are lower than those reported 
previously and may be from the much smaller sample sizes 
evaluated in studies of HGSC (N ¼ 36-73) (Kelemen et al, 2005;  Despierre et al, 2013; O'Shannessy et al, 2013) and of other 
histological types (Kalli et al, 2008; Crane et al, 2012). We also 
observed FOLR1 expression in normal fallopian tube tissue 
samples, which is increasingly accepted as the cell of origin 
for most HGSC (Piek et al, 2001; Crum et al, 2007). Others also 
reported strong FOLR1 expression in normal fallopian tube 
(Veggian et al, 1989; O'Shannessy et al, 2013), postulating 
that FOLR1 tumour expression is maintained from cell type-of-
origin (O'Shannessy et al, 2013). However, at least two 
previous studies found strong FOLR1 expression in normal 
ovarian surface epithelium (Wu et al, 1999; Kelemen et al, 2005), 
including one that prospectively collected ovarian surface 
epithelial samples from healthy postmenopausal women under-
going oophorectomy (Kelemen et al, 2005). Given the difficulty to 
obtain viable normal ovarian surface epithelium, we question 
whether earlier studies (Veggian et al, 1989; Ross et al, 1994; Parker  et al, 2005) found low expression in ovarian stroma rather than 
epithelium. 
There are several strengths to this investigation. We showed the 
novel result that the association between FOLR1 expression and OS 
changes with the duration of follow-up and with histological cell 
type. Our evaluation is the largest assembly of an unselected sample 
of HGSC and other ovarian carcinoma types. We performed a 
centralised IHC assay with excellent inter-observer reproducibility 
that correlated reasonably well with FOLR1 mRNA expression level 
among a subset of patients in our sample. Harmonisation of clinical 
variables contributed to robust statistical analysis and control for 
potential confounding. We also leveraged TCGA data to evaluate the 
association with HGSC in an independent data set and, although the 
direction and magnitude of the associations were similar between 
OTTA and TCGA samples, TCGA had too few tumours with FIGO 
stage I/II to evaluate. 
In summary, we found that FOLR1 protein was widely 
expressed in patients with HGSC in OTTA and that expression 
was associated with increased OS in the first 2 years following 
diagnosis. The association with clinical outcome in CCC was 
opposite to that seen for HGSC with a decreased progression-free 
interval observed for FOLR1-positive CCC. Both findings were 
more pronounced among patients with FIGO stage I/II tumours. 
Our study highlights the need to evaluate FOLR1-targeted 
therapy outcomes by histological type, stage and time following 
diagnosis if FOLR1 is to be used as a target for therapeutic 
intervention. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We wish to thank all of the patients, study centers and personnel 
who participated in this study. We gratefully acknowledge the 
contributions of the AOCS Group (http://www.aocstudy.org) 
(AOC); Mie Konno, Michelle Darago, Faye Chambers, the Tom 
Baker Cancer Centre Translational Laboratories (AOV); Karin 
Goodman, Ashley Pitzer, Mayo Clinic Medical Genome Facility 
(MAY, MAC); Kristy Angell, SEARCH team, the Human Research 
Tissue Bank at Addenbrooke's Hospital that is supported by the 
NIHR Cambridge Biomedical Research Centre (SEA); Ian Jacobs, 
Eva Wozniak, Andy Ryan, Jeremy Ford, Nayala Balogun (UKO); 
and the Cheryl Brown Ovarian Cancer Outcomes Unit (VAN). The 
results published here are in part based upon data generated by 
The Cancer Genome Atlas Project established by the National 
Cancer Institute and National Human Genome Research Institute. 
Information about TCGA and the investigators and institutions 
that constitute the TCGA research network can be found at http:// 
cancergenome.nih.gov/. This manuscript is dedicated to the 
memory of Barton A Kamen for his pioneering work in folate-
binding proteins and anti-folate pharmacology. This work was 
supported by the US Department of Defense (DAMD17-01-1-
0729), Cancer Council Victoria, Queensland Cancer Fund, Cancer 
Council New South Wales, Cancer Council South Australia, 
Cancer Foundation of Western Australia, Cancer Council 
Tasmania and National Health and Medical Research Council of 
Australia (NHMRC, Grants 400413 and 400281) (AOC); the 
Canadian Institutes for Health Research (MOP-86727) (AOV); 
Calgary Laboratory Services (RS10-533) (CAL); the National 
Institutes of Health (R01CA61107), Danish Cancer Society 
(research grant 94 222 52) and Mermaid I project (MAL); 
National Institutes of Health (R01CA122443, P50CA136393), 
Mayo Foundation and Fred C. and Katherine B. Andersen 
Foundation (MAY, MAC); Cancer Research UK (C490/A10119, 
C490/A10124), National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) 
Cambridge Biomedical Research Centre, Cambridge Experimental 
Cancer Medicine Centre (SEA); Eve Appeal (Oak Foundation), and 
NIHR University College London Hospitals Biomedical Research 
Centre (UKO); British Columbia Cancer Foundation, the Carraressi 
Foundation through donations to the Vancouver General Hospital 
and University of British Columbia Hospital Foundation (VAN). BG 
was supported by NHMRC and the Cancer Institute of NSW 
(CINSW), AdeF was supported by the University of Sydney Cancer 
Research Fund, and CINSW through the Sydney-West Translational 
Cancer Research Centre. LEK was supported by a Canadian 
Institutes for Health Research Investigator award MSH-87734. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </p>

<p>MK and LEK designed the overall study and oversaw statistical 
analysis. SJR, DGH, MK and LEK obtained financial support. SJR 
and MPI coordinated the OTTA studies database. MK and JM 
reviewed histological slides. AD, BG and SEJ harmonised the 
clinical variables. MK, BAC, PDPP, SD, DDB, KO, UM, CM, SL, 
WB, LS, MWB, AH, FCT, AH, DLW, MSA, EH, AJ, CH, KRK, 
BLF, GLK, ZCF, RAV, SL, SC, GN, PG, AG-M, SAG, EB, MW, BR, 
MB, HM, AO, PS, MJ-L, KED, JA, MM, JMK, HS, CE, AD, GC-T, 
SF, BG, SEJ, JG, LG, ELG, SKK, DGH, PAF, KBM, JDB and LEK 
coordinated contributing studies. MK, JDB and LEK drafted the 
manuscript, and all authors contributed to the final draft. </p>

<p>FOLR1 in ovarian cancer 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.567 </p>



<p>
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
FOLR1 in ovarian cancer </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.567 </p>



<p>This work is published under the standard license to publish agree-
ment. After 12 months the work will become freely available and 
the license terms will switch to a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. </p>

<p>FOLR1 in ovarian cancer 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.567 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>