<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4316942" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives To examine gender and racial disparities in 
ischaemic heart disease (IHD) mortality related to 
metalworking fluid exposures and in the healthy worker 
survivor effect. 
Methods A cohort of white and black men and 
women autoworkers in the USA was followed from 1941 
to 1995 with quantitative exposure to respirable 
particulate matter from water-based metalworking fluids. 
Separate analyses used proportional hazards models and 
g-estimation. 
Results The HR for IHD among black men was 3.29 
(95% CI 1.49 to 7.31) in the highest category of 
cumulative synthetic fluid exposure. The HR for IHD 
among white women exposed to soluble fluid reached 
2.44 (95% CI 0.96 to 6.22). However, no increased risk 
was observed among white men until we corrected for 
the healthy worker survivor effect. Results from 
g-estimation indicate that if white male cases exposed to 
soluble or synthetic fluid had been unexposed to that 
fluid type, then 1.59 and 1.20 years of life would have 
been saved on average, respectively. 
Conclusions We leveraged the strengths of two 
different analytic approaches to examine the IHD risks of 
metalworking fluids. All workers may have the same 
aetiological risk; however, black and female workers may 
experience more IHD from water-based metalworking 
fluid exposure because of a steeper exposure-response 
or weaker healthy worker survivor effect. </p>

<p>Heart disease is the number one cause of death in 
the USA and also the main contributor to black-
white disparities in mortality. 
1 Mortality rates from 
heart disease have declined in the USA overall since 
the 1970s, however there has been a steeper 
decline for whites compared to blacks, increasing 
the long-standing racial disparity. 
2 Although the 
two genders experience similar rates of heart 
disease incidence, women have higher mortality 
rates after heart attacks, for reasons not yet well 
understood. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Exposure to particulate matter (PM) in ambient 
air pollution is now considered a risk factor for 
heart disease mortality. 
4 Occupational cohorts offer 
the opportunity to study long-term PM exposures 
that can occur at levels an order of magnitude 
higher than those found in the ambient setting. 
The sparse evidence that occupational PM expos-
ure increases the risk of heart disease mortality </p>

<p>derives mostly from studies of industrial cohorts of 
white men. 
5 Blacks and women may have greater 
exposure to occupational hazards in the USA, 
6 so 
an understanding of the impact of occupational 
exposures by race and gender may help lead to 
better protections. 
The differential distribution of workplace factors 
by race and gender may create disparities in the 
healthy worker survivor bias, which can attenuate 
effect estimates in occupational studies. The bias 
arises if less healthy workers reduce exposure or 
self-select out of the work force earlier than their 
healthier counterparts. The healthy worker sur-
vivor effect has been studied mostly in the context 
of white, male cohorts; however, the likelihood of 
self-selection out of employment may well vary by 
race and gender. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>We assess disparities in ischaemic heart disease 
(IHD) and the healthy worker survivor effect using 
the United Autoworkers General Motors cohort-a 
large cohort of white and black men and women 
with individual-level, quantitative metalworking 
fluid exposure. Metalworking fluids are widely 
used in machining operations as coolants and lubri-
cants during cutting or grinding operations. We 
report survival analyses of PM 3.5 (PM &lt;3.5 μm in 
diameter) generated by metalworking fluid on IHD 
mortality by race and gender. In addition to pro-
portional hazards models, we use g-estimation of 
accelerated failure time models to adjust for the 
healthy worker survivor effect and compare the 
relative impact of the bias by race and gender. </p>

<p>Open access 
Scan to access more 
free content </p>

<p>What this paper adds </p>

<p>▸ Occupational particulate matter (PM 3.5 ) and 
ischaemic heart disease (IHD) mortality have 
never before been reported by race and gender 
from a single cohort. 
▸ Black men and white women had increased 
risk of IHD with increased exposure to at least 
one type of metalworking fluid. 
▸ No increased risk was observed among white 
men until we corrected for the healthy worker 
survivor effect. 
▸ There appear to be disparities in the healthy 
worker survivor effect and we cannot rule out 
disparities in heart disease from exposure to 
metalworking fluids. </p>

<p>138 
Costello S, et al. Occup Environ Med 2015;72:138-144. doi:10.1136/oemed-2014-102168 </p>

<p>Methodology </p>

<p>METHODS 
Study population </p>

<p>The study includes 39 412 hourly workers employed in one of 
three Michigan automobile manufacturing plants for at least 
3 years and hired between 1 January 1938 and 31 December 
1981. Follow-up began 3 years after hire and ended at the time 
of death or on December 31, 1994. 
8 Vital status data were avail-
able starting on 1 January 1941. Information on age, gender, 
race and plant was obtained through records provided by the 
employer. Race was not recorded systematically prior to the 
implementation of electronic record keeping in the mid-1970s. 
Race information could be updated for workers who remained 
at work through the record keeping transition, but for others 
race remained unknown. 
9 The 10% of participants with 
unknown race were classified as white based on the racial com-
position of the time-specific and plant-specific workforce; 
however, we conducted sensitivity analyses in which unknown 
race was treated as a separate category. </p>

<p>Exposure assessment </p>

<p>Quantitative levels of exposure to each metalworking fluid class 
for plant, department and job were estimated over time, based 
on 541 personal and area samples for PM 3.5 (mg/m 
3 ) collected 
by industrial hygienists. 
10 11 On the basis of plant records, a 
type of fluid (straight, soluble or synthetic) was assigned to each 
plant-year, department-year, job-year and calendar-year specific 
exposure category. For jobs with mixed exposures, we estimated 
the percentage of time spent using each type of fluid. Scale 
factors were estimated to rank aerosol exposures relative to the 
baseline levels (1984). For example, for each unique combin-
ation of fluid type and operation, the scale factor was less than 
1.0 by 1994, reflecting a continuing downward trend in expos-
ure levels. 
Annual average exposure to each type of fluid and size frac-
tion was calculated for each participant by combining work his-
tories with the estimated exposure concentrations. Cumulative 
exposure is the sum of annual exposures. Gaps in work history 
information for individual particpants were interpolated by 
averaging the exposures from the previous and subsequent jobs. 
Participants missing more than 50% of their work histories 
were excluded (less than 3%). </p>

<p>Health outcome </p>

<p>Data on vital status and cause of death were obtained through 
the Social Security Administration, the National Death Index, 
plant records, death certificates and state mortality files. 
9 The 
outcome of interest for this analysis is mortality from IHD 
(ICD-9 410-414). Since only two black women in the cohort 
died of IHD, supplementary analyses were conducted with car-
diopulmonary disease (ICD-9480-519) as the outcome in this 
stratum. </p>

<p>Data analysis 
Proportional hazards models </p>

<p>Cox proportional hazard models were used to estimate the 
effect of cumulative exposure to soluble and synthetic fluids on 
IHD mortality separately by race and gender. Cumulative expo-
sures to each fluid type were defined as categorical variables. 
Sensitivity analyses were conducted with duration of exposure 
to each fluid type as the main effect. Age was adjusted for as the 
time metric, calendar year (continuous) was included to adjust 
for secular trends, and manufacturing plant and other fluid 
types were included in every model. Supplementary models </p>

<p>were fit with cumulative exposure modelled as penalised splines 
and further restricted to the plants in which there were exposed 
cases. The graphs were truncated at the 99th percentile of the 
exposure distribution. Degrees of freedom were based on 
minimum Akaike's Information Criterion and biological 
plausibility. </p>

<p>G-estimation </p>

<p>G-estimation of a structural accelerated failure time model, first 
described by Robins, 
12 quantifies the relationship between the 
counterfactual survival time if never exposed and certain 
observed quantities: the observed survival time and the observed 
exposure history. Adjustment for confounders is achieved by 
including covariates and prior exposure history in a model pre-
dicting exposure. Under the assumption of no unmeasured con-
founding, 
counterfactual 
outcomes 
are 
conditionally 
independent of observed exposures, within strata of the mea-
sured covariates. G-estimation refers to the use of optimisation 
procedures to achieve this statistical independence, and it repre-
sents one of several statistical g-methods for adjusting for time-
varying confounders affected by prior exposure. 
In this application, exposure in each year is a binary variable 
equal to 1 if a worker was ever exposed to metalworking fluids 
of the corresponding type in that year, and 0 otherwise. The 
analysis therefore concerns duration of exposure rather than 
cumulative exposure. Probability of exposure among the actively 
employed was predicted in a pooled logistic model on the basis 
of age, decade, plant, history of time off work and prior expos-
ure to each fluid type; results are thus 'adjusted' for those vari-
ables. Also included in the exposure model was the maximum 
follow-up time possible for that worker (a variable required by 
g-estimation). Censoring (administrative, loss to follow-up, com-
peting risks) was handled as described in Chevrier et al. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>We stratified by race and gender, and ran separate analyses. 
The effect is expressed in terms of the average number of years 
of life that would have been saved (or lost), among the exposed 
cases, under an intervention banning exposure to the corre-
sponding type of metalworking fluid without intervening on the 
exposures to the other fluid types. 
We also used stratified g-estimation models to assess if syn-
thetic exposure caused people to leave work differentially by 
race and gender. 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.9.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc</rs>, Cary, North Carolina, 
USA) was used for the g-estimation and categorical analyses, 
and R software (R Development Core Team, Vienna, Austria) 
was used for the spline analysis. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The characteristics of the total cohort and the subcohorts by 
race and gender are presented in table 1. White men comprise 
the majority of the cohort (72%) followed by black men (16%), 
white women (9%) and black women (3%). There were 2246, 
295, 119 and 2 IHD deaths in each subcohort, respectively. 
White and black men had similar years of birth and died from 
IHD at similar ages; however, the women were different from 
the men and from each other. White women were older than 
the men and died of IHD at older ages. Black women were 
strikingly younger and hired much later than the other three 
subcohorts. Black men had the longest duration of employment. 
Women had a lower mean exposure to soluble metalworking 
fluid than men, and black male autoworkers had a lower mean 
exposure to synthetic fluid, but higher exposure to soluble fluid, 
than their white counterparts. </p>

<p>Costello S, et al. Occup Environ Med 2015;72:138-144. doi:10.1136/oemed-2014-102168 </p>

<p>
Methodology </p>

<p>In the analyses of cumulative exposure, the proportional 
hazards analysis for white men showed no increased risk of 
IHD associated with either soluble or synthetic metalworking 
fluid. Spline models show a very slightly positive increased risk, 
with very wide confidence bands, among white men who were 
exposed to soluble or synthetic fluids (results not shown). Black 
men, similarly, had no increased risk associated with soluble 
fluid; however, risk appeared greatly elevated for black men 
exposed to synthetic fluid with the HR climbing to 3.29 (95% 
CI 1.49 to 7.31) in the highest category of exposure (table 2). 
Spline models also show an increased risk of IHD among black 
men exposed to synthetic fluid. These models were restricted to 
plants 1 and 2 as there were no black male cases exposed to syn-
thetic fluid in plant 3. The exposure-response pattern for IHD 
in black men was approximately linear with the HR climbing to 
3.5 at 0.80 mg/m 
3 -year and was statistically significant across the 
whole range of exposure (figure 1). 
In the analyses of cumulative exposure for the women, there 
was elevated IHD risk for white women exposed to soluble </p>

<p>fluid with the HR rising to 2.44 (95% CI 0.96 to 6.22) in 
the second to last exposure category before dropping slightly 
(table 2). There was a suggestion of increased risk of IHD for 
women exposed to synthetic fluid with the HR increasing to 
1.37 (95% CI 0.82 to 2.29) in the top category of exposure. 
Spline models also show a positive trend for both fluid types in 
white women. These models were restricted to plants 2 and 3 
since there were no white female cases exposed to synthetic 
fluid in plant 1. The risk of IHD for white women exposed to 
synthetic metalworking fluid rose to twofold at 2 mg/m 
3 -year 
before falling off toward the null, however the confidence bands 
included the null for most of the exposure range (results not 
shown). The risk of IHD for white women exposed to soluble 
fluid rose, levelled off, and rose again to a HR of 2.25 at 8 mg/ 
m 
3 -year with the lower confidence band crossing back and forth 
across the null throughout most of the range of exposure (figure 
2). Sensitivity analyses restricted to workers with known race 
did not change the results for white men or white women 
exposed to synthetic fluid, however the results were stronger for </p>

<p>Table 1 Tabulations of study participants, demographics and exposure to metalworking fluid in a study of autoworkers; subcohorts by race 
and gender </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Total cohort 
White men 
Black men 
White women 
Black women </p>

<p>Number of participants 
39 412 
28 478 
6137 
3517 
1280 
Number of person-years 
967 812 
717 707 
148 228 
80 533 
21 344 
Number of IHD cases 
2662 
2246 
295 
119 
2 
Demographics; median (25th, 75th) 
Year of birth 
1931 (1920, 1945) 
1931 (1920, 1944) 
1930 (1921, 1944) 
1924 (1917, 1945) 
1947 (1939, 1952) 
Year of hire 
1955 (1950, 1968) 
1955 (1950, 1967) 
1959 (1948, 1968) 
1953 (1952, 1976) 
1973 (1972, 1976) 
Case Age (years) 
64 (55, 72) 
64 (55, 72) 
63 (55, 71) 
69 (61, 76) 
55 (54, 55) 
Duration of employment (years) 
20.1 (10.3, 28.6) 
19.8 (9.0, 28.9) 
24.7 (16.8, 30.1) 
17.3 (10.1, 22.1) 
18.7 (16.3, 21.6) 
Soluble metalworking fluid 
Ever exposed; N(%) 
35 031(89%) 
25 444(89%) 
5562 (91%) 
2926 (83%) 
1099 (86%) 
mg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>-year ; median (25th, 75th) 
1.52 (0.56, 3.95) 
1.58 (0.62, 3.88) 
2.41 (0.69, 6.62) 
0.73 (0.23, 1.79) 
0.49 (0.15, 1.03) 
Person-years exposed; N (%) 
359 914(37%) 
271 906(38%) 
59 694(41%) 
20 482(25%) 
7832 (36%) 
Synthetic metalworking fluid 
Ever exposed; N(%) 
13 804(35%) 
10 805(38%) 
1206 (20%) 
1379 (39%) 
414 (32%) 
mg/m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>-year; median (25th, 75th) 
0.18 (0.05, 0.63) 
0.20 (0.05, 0.66) 
0.10 (0.03, 0.34) 
0.16 (0.04, 0.68) 
0.06 (0.02, 0.13) 
Person-years exposed; N (%) 
101 092(10%) 
82 142(11%) 
8886 (6%) 
7601 (24%) 
2463 (11%) </p>

<p>IHD, ischaemic heart disease. </p>

<p>Table 2 Association of cumulative exposure to metalworking fluid with ischaemic heart disease mortality in autoworkers by race and gender </p>

<p>Cumulative 
metalworking 
fluid exposure 
type and 
amount (mg/ 
m </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>-year) </p>

<p>White males 
Black males 
White females </p>

<p>Number 
of cases </p>

<p>Number of 
person-years HR* (95% CI) </p>

<p>Number 
of cases </p>

<p>Number of 
person-years HR* (95% CI) </p>

<p>Number 
of cases </p>

<p>Number of 
person-years HR* (95% CI) </p>

<p>Soluble 
0 
204 
89 559 
1.00 
21 
17 953 
1.00 
6 
14 693 
1.00 
0-0.76 
321 
181 002 
1.01 0.85 to 1.21 
33 
34 343 
1.16 0.67 to 2.01 28 
33 175 
1.84 0.76 to 4.50 
0.77-1.80 
388 
157 196 
1.00 0.84 to 1.19 
25 
21 635 
0.96 0.54 to 1.73 29 
16 045 
2.40 0.97 to 5.91 
1.81-3.44 
362 
112 165 
0.94 0.78 to 1.12 
44 
19 699 
1.33 0.79 to 2.24 27 
8691 
2.44 0.96 to 6.22 
&gt;3.44 
971 
177 784 
1.01 0.87 to 1.18 172 
54 600 
1.01 0.64 to 1.61 29 
7929 
1.89 0.74 to 4.86 
Synthetic 
0 
1449 
485 431 
1.00 
275 
127 499 
1.00 
64 
53 464 
1.00 
0-0.65 
543 
173 166 
1.01 0.90 to 1.13 
10 
17 740 
1.38 0.64 to 2.97 30 
19 764 
1.29 0.80 to 2.07 
&gt;0.65 
254 
59 110 
0.92 0.79 to 1.06 
10 
2991 
3.29 1.49 to 7.31 25 
7305 
1.37 0.82 to 2.29 </p>

<p>*Adjusted for type of metalworking fluid, manufacturing plant, year and age (as time metric). </p>

<p> 
Costello S, et al. Occup Environ Med 2015;72:138-144. doi:10.1136/oemed-2014-102168 </p>

<p>Methodology </p>

<p>white women exposed to soluble fluid (results not shown). In 
additional sensitivity analysis, the apparent lack of effect in 
white men persisted when we calculated the HR for duration of 
exposure to soluble and synthetic fluids (results not shown). 
We evaluated the risk of cardiopulmonary mortality among 
black women with exposure to water-based metalworking fluids 
modelled as continuous exposures. Based on 31 deaths from 
cardiopulmonary disease, the HRs for soluble and synthetic 
fluid were 1.17 (95% CI 0.97 to 1.40) and 3.72 (95% CI 0.94 
to 14.76), respectively. 
In the accelerated failure time models correcting for the 
healthy worker survivor effect, g-estimation indicated that if 
cases exposed to synthetic fluid had been unexposed then 2.77 
(−12.81 to 5.74), 1.20 (0.11 to 2.73) and 1.96 (−1.43 to 4.68) 
years of life would have been saved on average among black 
men, white men and white women, respectively. If the cases had 
been unexposed to soluble fluid, 2.99 and 1.59 (−0.20 to 2.99) 
years of life would have been saved among the white women 
and white men, respectively, whereas an average of 1.63 
(−5.26 to 2.70) years would have been lost among the black 
men. However, the CIs were too wide to draw meaningful </p>

<p>conclusions, except among the white men (figure 3). Statistical 
instability precluded us from calculating CIs at all for white 
women exposed to soluble fluids. 
G-estimation was used to assess whether exposure predicted 
leaving work, a critical component of the healthy worker sur-
vivor effect. Results indicated that white male, black male and 
white female cases exposed to synthetic fluid would have 
worked 1.9, 0.5 and 0 years longer, respectively, had they been 
unexposed. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The risk of IHD in relation to water-based metalworking fluids 
differed by race and gender in this cohort of autoworkers when 
using exposure-response models. Black men and white women 
had increased risk of IHD with increased exposure to at least 
one type of metalworking fluid, however no increased risk was 
observed among white men. We did, however, observe increased 
risk among white men after correcting for the healthy worker 
survivor effect using g-estimation. The healthy worker survivor 
effect arises when susceptible workers leave work or transfer to 
lower exposed jobs; an option that may be more available to 
white, male workers. 
14 Thus, results from the proportional 
hazards models seem to have been most dramatically attenuated 
by the healthy worker survivor bias for white men. All workers 
appear to be at increased risk of IHD with increased exposure; 
however, g-estimation was needed to observe the effect among 
white male autoworkers. 
We estimated the effect of metalworking fluid on IHD in 
strata of autoworkers using two methods that produced some-
what different results. These methods, however, answer differ-
ent questions: the standard proportional hazards model 
estimates the conditional effect of cumulative, quantitative 
exposure on the hazard of IHD on the multiplicative scale while 
the accelerated failure time model estimates the marginal effect 
of duration of exposure on survival time on the additive scale. 
Each method has strengths and weaknesses. The primary 
strength of the standard model is being able to handle quantita-
tive exposure in a familiar way; however, the model cannot 
address healthy worker survivor effect. G-estimation of the 
accelerated failure time, on the other hand, removes the healthy 
worker survivor bias but sacrifices the quantitative exposure 
information. In addition, g-estimation appears to have power 
limitations in the smaller strata. We do not expect either model 
alone to give the definitive answer, but rather combine the 
strengths of each to provide a more complete assessment. 
The combined evidence from both models indicates that there 
is an effect in all subgroups, and thus was inconclusive as to </p>

<p>Figure 1 Association of cumulative exposure to synthetic 
metalworking fluid with ischaemic heart disease mortality in Black 
male autoworkers in plants 1 and 2. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Association of cumulative exposure to soluble metalworking 
fluid with ischaemic heart disease mortality in White female 
autoworkers in plants 2 and 3. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Average years of life saved among ever-exposed ischaemic 
heart disease cases, stratified by race and gender under an intervention 
banning either synthetic or soluble metalworking fluid. </p>

<p>Costello S, et al. Occup Environ Med 2015;72:138-144. doi:10.1136/oemed-2014-102168 </p>

<p>
Methodology </p>

<p>whether disparities exist. Effect measure modification depends 
on the measure of effect, so finding evidence of disparities in 
the proportional hazard, but not accelerated failure time, 
models is not necessarily in conflict. Our results are consistent 
with disparities in the exposure-response or with disparities 
only in the healthy worker survivor effect. We discuss these pos-
sibilities in light of the occupational and social literature. </p>

<p>Gender and racial differences in work organisation and 
healthy worker survivor effect </p>

<p>Women are more likely than men to face discrimination, harass-
ment and lower pay for equal work in a variety of occupational 
settings. 
15 In a cohort of hourly aluminium workers, women 
were more likely to have lower education, less skilled jobs and 
be single parents. 
16 If the female autoworkers in this cohort 
have a similar demographic profile, they may have pressing 
financial incentive to keep their autoworker job, even if ill, and 
less opportunity to find employment with lower exposure. 
However, in the sole study of gender differences in the healthy 
worker effect to date, 
7 female synthetic vitreous fibre workers 
were found to have a higher mortality ratio after leaving 
employment than men. The authors interpreted these results as 
evidence of increased healthy worker survivor effect among 
women. 
Workplace discrimination also occurs for racial minorities. 
Black workers are more likely to experience involuntary job 
loss 
17 and were shown to have greater perceived job insecurity 
in two nationally representative US samples. 
18 Perceived job 
insecurity has been linked to atherosclerosis 
19 on its own, and 
may also influence the decision to stay at work. 
Given the real and perceived differences in job placement and 
insecurity, as well as the additional social and economic burden, 
the black and female autoworkers might have been less likely 
than white men to voluntarily opt out of the workforce for 
health-related reasons, which could lead to differences in the 
observed healthy worker survivor effect. In fact, if black and 
female autoworkers do not opt out of the work force for 
health-related reasons, then there is no time-varying confound-
ing affected by prior exposure and the proportional hazards 
model may provide an unbiased estimate of IHD risk in these 
subgroups. We cannot test this assumption directly, as we do not 
have a measure of time-varying health status. However, our ana-
lysis of whether exposure to synthetic fluid causes people to 
leave work, another necessary piece of the healthy worker 
effect, indicated that white men were more likely to leave work 
for exposure-related reasons than either black men or white 
women. </p>

<p>Gender and racial differences in heart disease </p>

<p>In addition to the disparities apparent in the proportional 
hazards models, the point estimates using g-estimation indicate 
that the years of life lost for black men and white women 
exposed to synthetics may be greater than for white men even 
after correction for the healthy worker survivor effect (though 
the CIs reflect a lack of statistical stability in all but the white 
men in the g-estimation analysis). 
Recent interest in gender differences in cardiovascular disease 
has led to a better understanding of the differences between 
men and women in pathophysiology, diagnosis and treatment. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Likely due to the protective effects of oestrogen, women gener-
ally develop IHD 10 years later than men, 
21 and they typically 
have coexisting or chronic disease. Additionally, non-invasive 
diagnostic tests such as electrocardiogram and the treadmill 
stress test have lower sensitivity and specificity in women </p>

<p>compared to men. Several observational trials have reported 
that women are prescribed and/or utilise recommended inter-
ventions at a lower rate than men, 
22 although the reasons for 
this discrepancy are still not understood. 
Racial disparities are predominant issues in healthcare reform. 
Blacks are 2-3 times more likely to die from heart disease com-
pared to whites, 
23 have more heart disease risk factors, 
24 and 
receive a lower quality of healthcare, even when controlling for 
access-related factors. 
25 Furthermore, research has shown that 
the experience of chronic discrimination can have a negative 
impact on cardiovascular health. </p>

<p>26-28 </p>

<p>Given the gender and racial disparities in heart disease sur-
vival, the exposure-response between metalworking fluid and 
IHD mortality may not be directly comparable between 
subgroups. </p>

<p>Prior literature on occupational PM and IHD </p>

<p>A recent meta-analysis of mostly white, male cohorts comparing 
high/any versus low/no PM exposure found a relative risk of 
1.15 (CI 1.06 to 1.14) for IHD mortality. 
5 Since then, increased 
risk has been reported with PAH exposure in asphalt 
29 and 
smelter workers 
30 from cohorts of white men. In two recent 
studies of Chinese workers, cumulative exposure to cotton dust 
was associated with stroke, but not IHD, among female textile 
workers, 
31 and long-term silica exposure was associated with 
IHD among predominantly male miners. </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>We recently published on the association between oil-based 
straight metalworking fluid and IHD in this cohort, adjusting 
for race and gender. 
33 These findings were driven by the effect 
in the white, male autoworkers with no adjustment for the 
healthy worker survivor effect. In a different publication, we 
demonstrated that g-estimation resulted in higher HRs for IHD 
in relation to straight metalworking fluid, as well as several 
other mortality outcomes, compared to proportional hazards 
models. 
13 However, the use of straight metalworking fluids has 
been phased out in most industries, thus our current focus is on 
the health effects of water-based fluids. 
Water-based metalworking fluids contain endotoxin, biocides, 
nitrosamines, metals and other constitutes 
34 which may lead to 
lung and systemic inflammation. On entering the lungs, fine PM 
may cause systemic inflammatory response 
35-37 which can 
induce progression of atherosclerosis 
38 39 and activate cardiac 
myocytes and adipocytes. 
40 We had no prior that the biological 
pathway would differ by race or gender. 
Smoking is an important risk factor for IHD and would be a 
confounder in this study if it were also associated with expos-
ure. Smoking data were collected in a small cross-section of this 
cohort for a study of asthma. 
41 The cross-section cohort was 
restricted to men actively employed in 1985 and oversampled 
for blacks, unexposed workers and workers exposed to only 
one type of metalworking fluid. We used a multiple imputation 
procedure to impute missing smoking information for the black 
men in this study. Sensitivity analyses (not shown) using 
imputed smoking information did not change the result for 
IHD and synthetic exposure; however, we doubt the validity of 
extrapolating smoking information on current workers in 1985 
to workers in the 1940s. Notably, exposure to water-based 
metalworking fluids was associated with reduced lung cancer 
mortality in this cohort, 
42 suggesting that the positive results 
presented here are not due to confounding by smoking. 
Nonetheless, the lack of information on potential confounders 
is a limitation, especially when considering a multifactorial 
disease like IHD. </p>

<p> 
Costello S, et al. Occup Environ Med 2015;72:138-144. doi:10.1136/oemed-2014-102168 </p>

<p>Methodology </p>

<p>We stratified on race in this analysis and used two techniques 
to handle missing race data: reclassifying those with missing 
race as white and excluding those with missing race from the 
analysis. Although most of these workers were likely white, 
those who were black were never included in their correct 
stratum for this analysis. Excluding black workers with missing 
race status from the black stratum is a form of left truncation 
bias, since they would have been correctly classified as black had 
they stayed at work until the electronic employment record 
system was implemented. Left truncation bias can attenuate the 
observed association between exposure and disease because 
those who stay for longer are more heavily exposed and are less 
susceptible to the exposure-response association. 
43 Missing race 
status is a limitation in this analysis and may have attenuated the 
observed associations for black men. However, only 10% of the 
workers were missing information on race. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>To our knowledge, this is the first time the association between 
occupational exposure to PM 3.5 and IHD mortality has been 
reported by race and gender from a single cohort. Additionally, 
this is the first time g-estimation has been applied to understand 
the race and gender differences in the healthy worker survivor 
effect. We were able to leverage the strengths of two different 
analytic approaches to shed light on the health risks of metal-
working fluids among autoworkers. We found that black men 
and white women had increased risk of IHD with increased 
exposure to at least one of the two types of water-based metal-
working fluids, however no increased risk was observed among 
white men when using proportional hazard models to estimate 
risk. We did, however, observe increased risk among white men 
after correcting for the healthy worker survivor effect, which sug-
gests that the aetiological effect of water-based metalworking 
may be the same in all subsets of our population. Alternatively, 
black and female workers may experience more IHD from water-
based metalworking fluid exposure either because of steeper 
exposure-response or weaker healthy worker survivor effect. </p>

<p>Correction notice The section head of this article has been changed since 
published Online First. </p>

<p>Contributors SC conceived the article topic and design, proportional hazard 
analysis, interpretation of both analytic methods and drafted most of the article. 
SP conducted the g-estimation analysis and contributed to the interpretation and 
writing, especially in regards to her analytic approach. DHR contributed to the 
analytic design and critically reviewed and revised the paper, especially in regards to 
the social disparities content. EAE is the principal investigator of the cohort study 
and contributed substantially to the analytic approach, analysis, interpretation and 
review of this article. All authors had approval of the final version and consider this 
honest work. </p>

<p>Funding This work was supported by the National Institute for Occupational Safety 
and Health, Centers for Disease Control (R01 OH008927). </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval University of California, Berkeley Committee for Protection of 
Human Subjects. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the 
Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, which 
permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, 
and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is 
properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>



<p>Costello S, et al. Occup Environ Med 2015;72:138-144. doi:10.1136/oemed-2014-102168 </p>

<p>
Methodology </p>



<p> 
Costello S, et al. Occup Environ Med 2015;72:138-144. doi:10.1136/oemed-2014-102168 </p>

<p>Methodology </p>

</text></tei>