<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4566509" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Giardia is a major public health concern and considered as reemerging in industrialized countries. The present 
study investigated the prevalence of giardiosis in 202 sheltered dogs using PCR. The infection rate was 33.2% (67/202); 
Gyeongsangbuk-do and Daejeon showed 25.7% (39/152, P &lt; 0.0001) and 56% (28/50), respectively. The prevalence of 
infected female dogs (46.7%, P &lt; 0.001) was higher than in male dogs (21.8%). A higher prevalence (43.5%, P &lt; 0.0001) 
was observed in mixed breed dogs than purebred (14.1%). Although most of the fecal samples collected were from dogs 
of ≥ 1 year of age which showed only 27.4% positive rate, 61.8% (P &lt; 0.001) of the total samples collected from young 
animals (&lt; 1 year of age) were positive for G. intestinalis. A significantly higher prevalence in symptomatic dogs (60.8%, 
P &lt; 0.0001) was observed than in asymptomatic dogs (23.8%). Furthermore, the analysis of nucleotide sequences of the 
samples revealed that G. intestinalis Assemblages A and C were found in the feces of dogs from Gyeongsangbuk-do and 
Daejeon. Since G. intestinalis Assemblage A has been known to infect humans, our results suggest that dogs can act as 
an important reservoir of giardiosis in Korea. Hence, hygienic management should be given to prevent possible transmis-
sion to humans. </p>



<p>nalis cysts [12]. Consequently, the present study examined 202 
canine fecal samples to determine the presence of giardiosis in 
dogs from animal shelters in Korea using PCR. 
A total of 202 canine fecal samples collected from each ani-
mal shelter in Gyeongsangbuk-do (Province) (n= 152) and 
Daejeon city (n = 50) from February 2013 to February 2015 
were used in the study. All cases were grouped according to 
gender, breed (mixed/pure), age group ( ≥ 1 year/ &lt; 1 year), 
and health status (symptomatic/asymptomatic) (Table 1). 
Health status was based on main clinical manifestations of 
giardiosis which can range from asymptomatic (without diar-
rhea), to acute or chronic diarrheal disease (symptomatic) 
[13]. Moreover, the positive genomic DNA of G. intestinalis 
(ATCC no. 30957) was kindly provided by Dr. S. E. Lee in Di-
vision of Malaria and Parasite Diseases, Korea National Insti-
tute of Health, Korea Centers for Disease Control and Preven-
tion, Korea. Total genomic DNA extraction of each fecal sam-
ple was performed using the QIAamp DNA Stool Mini Kit in </p>

<p>accordance with manufacturer's instruction (Qiagen, Hilden, 
Germany). 
A set of primers to amplify a 384 bp fragment of β-giardin </p>

<p>gene of G. intestinalis was amplified using the forward primer 
(5ʹ CAT AAC GAC GCC ATC GCG GCT CTC AGG AA 3ʹ) and 
the reverse primer (5ʹ GAG GCC GCC CTG GAT CTT CGA 
GAC GAC 3ʹ) as previously described [14]. The primers were 
designed based from the complete β-giardin gene of the Port-</p>

<p>land-1 isolate (GenBank no. M36728). The amplification of 
PCR products was performed in a MyGenie96 Thermal Block 
thermal cycler (Bioneer, Seoul, Korea), resolved using 1.5% 
Tris-acetate-EDTA (TAE) in an electrophoresis chamber con-
taining 0.5x TAE buffer, run at 100 V for 25 min or until the 
dye indicator reached the target lane, stained with ethidium 
bromide, and viewed under an ultraviolet trans-illuminator 
machine. The PCR products with the target band size were pu-
rified using MEGAquick-spin 
TM Total Fragment DNA Purifica-</p>

<p>tion Kit (Intron Biotechnology, Seoul, Korea). The representa-</p>

<p>Table 1. PCR results and statistical analysis according to origin, gender, breed, age, and health status of dogs </p>

<p>Historical factor 
Sample size 
No. of positive 
Positive rate (%) 
x </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P* </p>

<p>Origin 
Daejeon 
Gyeongbuk </p>

<p>50 
152 </p>

<p>28 
39 </p>

<p>56 
25.7 </p>

<p>15.63 
0.0001 </p>

<p>Sex 
Male 
Female </p>

<p>110 
92 </p>

<p>24 
43 </p>

<p>21.8 
46.7 </p>

<p>14.04 
0.0002 </p>

<p>Breed 
Mixed 
Pure </p>

<p>131 
71 </p>

<p>57 
10 </p>

<p>43.5 
14.1 </p>

<p>17.99 
0.0000 </p>

<p>Age 
≥ 1 year 
&lt; 1 year </p>

<p>168 
34 </p>

<p>46 
21 </p>

<p>27.4 
61.8 </p>

<p>15.08 
0.0001 </p>

<p>Health status 
Symptomatic 
Asymptomatic </p>

<p>51 
151 </p>

<p>31 
36 </p>

<p>60.8 
23.8 </p>

<p>23.47 
0.0000 </p>

<p>Total 
202 
67 
33.2 </p>

<p>*analyzed by Pearson's chi-square test for independence. </p>

<p>500 
400 </p>

<p>1 
3 
5 
7 
9 
11 
13 
15 
17 
2 
4 
6 
8 
10 
12 
14 
16 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. PCR amplification of G. intestinalis β-giardin genes from fecal samples of dogs from animal shelters in Gyeongsangbuk-do and 
Daejeon. Lane 1: 1,000 bp molecular weight marker, Lanes 2, 5-7: negative samples, Lanes 3-4, 8-16: positive samples, and Lane 17: 
positive control (G. intestinalis, arrow). </p>

<p>Shin et al.: Molecular detection of canine Giardia using PCR, Korea 479 </p>

<p>tive β-giardin gene from 3 fecal samples and a positive control </p>

<p>were submitted for sequencing (Fig. 1). The DNA sequences 
were searched using BLASTN search algorithms (http://www. 
ncbi.nml.nih.gov/blast/) (Table 2) and aligned using <rs id="software-0" type="software">CLUSTAL 
W2</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalw2/</rs>/) (Fig. 2). 
Giardins are a family of structural proteins of approximately 
29-38 kDa in size and the advantage of using giardin genes as 
targets for molecular detection of Giardia cysts is that they are 
considered unique to this parasite [14]. The prevalence accord-</p>

<p>ing to the place of origin, gender, breed, age groups, and 
health status was compared using the chi-square test of Statis-
tical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS, IBM, Redmond, 
Washington, USA). 
In the present study, the fecal samples collected from stray 
dogs in animal shelters of Gyeongsangbuk-do and Daejeon 
showed 25.7% (39 out of 152) and 56% (28 out of 50), re-
spectively, showing that the positive rate was significantly 
higher in Daejeon (P &lt; 0.0001) as compared to Gyeongsang-</p>

<p>Table 2. Analysis and comparison of representative β-giardin gene from 3 canine fecal samples </p>

<p>Sample 
Homology to G. intestinalis (%) Homology to positive control (%) 
Description (GenBank accession no.) </p>

<p>Positive control 
98 
-</p>

<p>G. intestinalis assemblage AI β-giardin gene (KF963547) </p>

<p>Sample 1 
98 
91 </p>

<p>G. intestinalis isolate A21 β-giardin gene (AY545647) </p>

<p>Sample 2 
98 
92 </p>

<p>G. intestinalis isolate A21 β-giardin gene (AY545647) </p>

<p>Sample 3 
99 
92 </p>

<p>G. intestinalis isolate BRAdogD15/BRAdogC2 β-giardin </p>

<p>gene (JF422719) </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Multiple alignments of representative β-giardin genes from fecal samples of dogs from animal shelters in Gyeongsangbuk-do and </p>

<p>Daejeon (samples 1, 2, and 3) using CLUSTAL W2 software in comparison to the positive control (original). Asterisks (*) indicate homolo-
gy among all samples. </p>



<p>buk-do. Sixty-seven out of 202 canine fecal specimens sam-
pled yielded the PCR products of the expected 384 bp frag-
ment of β-giardin gene of G. intestinalis, showing an overall </p>

<p>Giardia infection rate of 33.2% (67/202) (Fig. 1). Three of 
these positive samples and a positive control were sequenced, 
and all of the nucleotide sequences obtained belonged to 
β-giardin sequences of G. intestinalis based on BLASTN search </p>

<p>algorithms of the GenBank database (Table 2). The multiple 
sequence alignment using Clustal W2 software and sequence 
analysis using BLASTN search algorithms revealed that 
β-giardin gene from the 3 representative positive samples </p>

<p>shared 91-92% identity with that of the positive sample (Fig. 2; 
Table 2). The positive control showed 98% homology to G. in-
testinalis Assemblage A subtype AI, 2 of the positive samples 
showed 98% homology to G. intestinalis Assemblage A, and 1 
positive sample showed 99% homology to G. intestinalis iso-
late BRAdogD15/C2 which was reported by Paz e Silva et al. 
[15] to have a 100% homology to G. intestinalis Assemblage C 
(Table 2). 
G. intestinalis Assemblages A and B have a wide range of 
hosts which include humans and animals such as livestock, 
dogs, cats, and other wild animals, while Assemblages C and 
D are dog-specific genotypes [16]. Since G. intestinalis Assem-
blage A has been found in canine fecal samples collected in 
this study which were similar to those that have been reported 
[17], the results indicated potential transmission of Giardia 
from dogs to humans or vice versa. 
In a study done by Huber et al. [18], neither gender nor age 
in clinically healthy dogs has a correlation with Giardia posi-
tive rate although a slightly higher prevalence in male dogs but 
not significant was reported by Liu et al. [19]. In contrast, the 
present study showed a significantly higher prevalence in fe-
male dogs (46.7%) than in male dogs (21.8%), which is in 
agreement with those reported by Pallant et al. [20]. Most of 
the samples tested were obtained from dogs of ≥ 1 year of age 
(83.2%) but only 27.4% were infected with Giardia as com-
pared to the population of younger animals which showed a 
significant positive rate of 61.8%. This result was similar to 
those reported by Jacobs et al. [21] where fecal samples from 
dogs under 1 year of age comprised approximately 73% of 
Giardia cases. Mochizuki et al. [22] reported that the rate of 
Giardia-infected dogs was almost equal in fecal samples ob-
tained from symptomatic or asymptomatic dogs. However, the 
results in our study showed that the prevalence of dogs with 
diarrhea was significantly higher than those without diarrhea </p>

<p>which was similar to those reported by Liu et al. [19]. 
In conclusion, G. intestinalis Assemblages A and C were 
found in the feces of dogs from animal shelters in Gyeong-
sangbuk-do and Daejeon. The prevalence of G. intestinalis in-
fection was observed to be higher in females, mixed-breed, &lt; 1 
year of age, and symptomatic dogs. Therefore, the role of dogs 
as a potential source of human giardiasis, though can be con-
sidered as minor, could not be excluded, and increasing aware-
ness of this possible transmission to patients or clients is im-
portant. Further investigation is recommended to confirm the 
zoonotic potential of G. intestinalis detected in fecal samples 
from dogs in Korea. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors of this paper declare no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>Shin et al.: Molecular detection of canine Giardia using PCR, Korea 481 </p>



</text></tei>