<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4646224" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background-Hypertensive disorders are the most common in pregnancy. Several studies 
showed a positive correlation between elevated maternal serum uric acid (UA), serum creatinine 
and adverse maternal and fetal outcomes, but only a few studies are available on serum cystatin C 
and maternal and fetal outcomes. The present study was undertaken to study the association of 
serum UA, creatinine and cystatin C with maternal and fetal outcomes. </p>

<p>Methods-Out of 116 pregnant women 69 women had no hypertension and 47 had hypertension 
with or without proteinuria. Serum UA, creatinine and cystatin C was measured by modified 
Uricase method, modified kinetic Jaffe's reaction and particle-enhanced immunonephelometric 
assay respectively. Multivariate logistic regression was performed to determine the independent 
effects of serum UA, creatinine and cystatin C on maternal and fetal outcomes using <rs id="software-0" type="software">stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.1</rs>. </p>

<p>Results-The adjusted odds ratio (OR) was 3.73 (95% CI: 1.18-11.75; P=0.024) for UA; 15.79 
(95% CI: 3.04-81.94; P=0.001) for creatinine and 2.03 (95% CI: 0.70-5.87; P=0.192) for cystatin 
C in hypertensive disorders of pregnancy. All the three renal parameters were not significantly 
associated with birth weight, gestational age of delivery and mode of delivery after adjusting for 
the confounding factors. </p>

<p>Conclusions-Serum creatinine and uric acid are independent risk factors for hypertensive 
disorders of pregnancy. High serum uric acid is associated with low birth weight and delivery by 
caesarian section whereas high serum creatinine with preterm delivery only before adjustment for </p>

<p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License, which 
permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Correspondence:padma.md@hotmail.com. 
Conflict of interest: None declared </p>

<p>Ethical approval: The study was approved by the Institutional Ethics Committee </p>

<p>HHS Public Access </p>

<p>Author manuscript </p>

<p>Int J Reprod Contracept Obstet Gynecol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 
November 16. </p>

<p>Published in final edited form as: 
Int J Reprod Contracept Obstet Gynecol. 2015 ; 4(5): 1505-1510. doi: 
10.18203/2320-1770.ijrcog20150737. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>confounding factors and not after adjustment. Serum cystatin C was not significantly associated 
with the maternal and fetal outcomes. </p>

<p>Keywords </p>

<p>Uric acid; Creatinine; Cystatin C; Gestational Hypertension; Preeclampsia; Gestational age; Birth 
weight; Caesarian section; Logistic regression </p>

<p>INTRODUCTION </p>

<p>Hypertensive disorders account for approximately 2%-10% of all pregnancies. 1,2 Among 
these pre-eclampsia (PE) is one of the major causes of maternal and perinatal morbidity and 
mortality worldwide whereas uncomplicated gestational hypertension has a better prognosis. 
Gestational hypertension is defined as the new onset gestational hypertension after the 20 th 
week of gestation but without proteinuria. 3 PE is characterized by new onset gestational 
hypertension after the 20 th week of gestation, proteinuria and impaired renal function. 3 Due 
to hormonal and hemodynamic changes of pregnancy, renal function is altered and more so 
in hypertensive disorders and hence these changes must be considered when assessing renal 
function in pregnancy. Serum Uric acid (UA), serum creatinine and more recently serum 
cystatin C levels are the indices of renal function. Several studies have reported a positive 
correlation between elevated maternal serum UA, serum creatinine and adverse maternal 
and fetal outcomes. 4-10 We found one study showing an association of high plasma cystatin 
C levels and PE which reflects the acute kidney dysfunction associated with PE but we did 
not find studies showing the relationship between serum cystatin C and the fetal outcomes. 11 
We hypothesize that elevated levels of serum UA, serum Creatinine and serum cystatin C 
are associated with adverse maternal and fetal outcomes and hence in our study we would 
like to evaluate the relationship between the above mentioned parameters and the maternal 
and fetal outcomes. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>This pilot study was performed on 116 pregnant women in the Department of obstetrics &amp; 
gynaecology, Mediciti Institute of Medical Sciences, Ghanpur, Ranga Reddy district, 
Telangana, India. Written informed consent was taken from all included participants. 
Among them 69 women did not develop hypertension and 47 developed hypertension with 
or without proteinuria. All of them had no present or past history of hypertension, diabetes 
mellitus or renal disease. 5 ml of non-fasting venous blood samples were collected at the 
time of delivery from all the included participants. 10 </p>

<p>Measuring parameters-mother </p>

<p>The blood pressure was measured using an oscillometric digital sphygmomanometer 
(Model: Omron HEM-780N3). The international society for the study of hypertension in 
pregnancy guidelines were followed for the measurement of blood pressure. 3 Two 
measurements taken 4 hours apart with systolic blood pressure ≥ 140 mm Hg and diastolic 
blood pressure ≥ 90 mm Hg was used as the diagnostic criteria for the hypertension in 
pregnancy. Serum uric acid was measured by modified Uricase method in Dade Behring-</p>

<p>Yalamati et al. </p>

<p>
Int J Reprod Contracept Obstet Gynecol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 16. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Dimension Xpand plus system using uric acid flex reagent cartridge according to the 
manufacturer's instructions. 12 Serum creatinine was measured by modified kinetic Jaffe's 
reaction in Dade Behring-Dimension Xpand plus system using creatinine flex reagent 
cartridge according to the manufacturer's instructions. 13 Serum cystatin C was measured by 
a fully automated particle-enhanced immunonephelometric assay (N Latex cystatin C, Dade-
Behring, Inc) in BN Pro-Spec nephelometer (Dade Behring, Inc, Deerfield, IL) according to 
the manufacturer's instructions. 14 Urinary proteins were measured in random mid-stream 
urine sample by semi-quantitative dip stick method. 15 Two readings of 1+ (30 mg/dl) were 
taken as the diagnostic criteria for pre-eclampsia. 3 Further details regarding the 
methodology were presented previously. 16 </p>

<p>Measuring parameters-new-born </p>

<p>The weight of the new-born was measured by a digital weighing scale (SECA 354/364). </p>

<p>Statistical tools </p>

<p>The data was entered in a MS-Excel database and was analysed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">13.1</rs> statistical 
software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Stata, College Station, Texas USA</rs>). We performed multivariate logistic regression 
to determine the independent effects of serum UA, serum creatinine and serum cystatin C 
before and after adjusting for the possible confounding factors on maternal and fetal 
outcomes. The hypertensive disorders of pregnancy, birth weight, gestational age of delivery 
and mode of delivery were treated as the dependent variables and serum UA, serum 
creatinine and serum cystatin C as independent variables. Both dependent and independent 
variables were dichotomized. Hypertension, birth weight and gestational age of delivery 
were dichotomized using the standard cut-off values. 3,17,18 The cut-offs for dichotomization 
were taken as 5.88 mg/dl for serum uric acid, 19 0.8 mg/dl for serum creatinine 16 and 1.3 
mg/L for serum cystatin c. 16 Serum uric acid ≥ 5.88 mg/dl, serum creatinine ≥ 0.8 mg/dl and 
serum cystatin C ≥ 1.3 mg/L were coded as 1 and those less than the cut-offs were coded as 
0. For each outcome the first model was unadjusted and the second model was adjusted for 
the covariates as possible confounders in the analysis. The possible confounders were age, 
BMI, gestational age, parity and birth weight in the first analysis where hypertensive 
disorders were taken as the dependent variable (Table 2); age, BMI, gestational age, parity 
and hypertensive disorders in the second analysis where birth weight was taken as the 
dependent variable (Table 3); age, BMI, parity, birth weight and hypertensive disorders in 
the third analysis where the gestational age of delivery is the outcome (Table 4); age, BMI, 
parity, birth weight, gestational age and hypertensive disorders in the fourth analysis where 
mode of delivery was taken as the dependent variable (Table 5). A p value of &lt;0.05 was 
considered as statistically significant. </p>

<p>The maternal and child characteristics of the study participants were presented previously in 
Table 1. 16 The included participants were presently categorized as shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>Table 2 Shows the results of multivariate logistic regression analysis for hypertensive 
disorders of pregnancy: pregnant women with high serum uric acid (≥5.88 mg/dl) and high 
serum creatinine (≥0.8 mg/dl) are at over 3.73 times and 15.79 times respectively, the risk of 
developing hypertensive disorders compared to the pregnant women with low serum uric </p>

<p>Yalamati et al. </p>

<p>
Int J Reprod Contracept Obstet Gynecol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 16. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>acid and low serum creatinine after adjusting for the confounding factors. Hence serum uric 
acid and serum creatinine are independent risk factors for the development of hypertensive 
disorders of pregnancy. There was no significant association between serum cystatin C and 
the development of hypertensive disorders. </p>

<p>Table 3 shows the results of multivariate logistic regression analysis for birth weight: 
pregnant women having high serum uric acid levels (≥5.88 mg/dl) are at over 2.49 times the 
risk of giving birth to low birth weight babies (&lt;2.5 Kg) compared to the pregnant women 
with low serum uric acid before adjusting for the confounding factors but not after 
adjustment. We found no significant association between serum creatinine, serum cystatin C 
and the birth weight. </p>

<p>Table 4 shows the results of multivariate logistic regression analysis for gestational age of 
delivery: pregnant women with high serum creatinine (≥0.8 mg/dl) are at over 3.60 times the 
risk of having gestational age of delivery &lt; 37 wks. compared to the pregnant women with 
low serum creatinine before adjusting for the confounding factors but not after adjustment. 
Serum UA and serum cystatin C were not significantly associated with the gestational age of 
delivery. </p>

<p>Table 5 shows the results of multivariate logistic regression analysis for mode of delivery: 
pregnant women with high serum uric acid (≥ 5.88 mg/dl) are at over 2.93 times the risk of 
undergoing cesarean section compared to the pregnant women with low serum uric acid 
before adjusting for the confounding factors but not after adjustment. Serum creatinine and 
serum cystatin C were not significantly associated with the mode of delivery. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The association between raised serum uric acid and preeclampsia was first reported in 
1917. 20 The elevation in serum uric acid and serum creatinine may be attributed to reduced 
uric acid and creatinine clearance secondary to reduced glomerular filtration rate, increased 
reabsorption and decreased secretion in women with pre-eclampsia. 21-23 The 
pathophysiologic mechanisms of pre-eclampsia comprising increased trophoblastic tissue 
shedding, endothelial dysfunction, and reduced blood flow in the fetomaternal unit have also 
been hypothesized as the underlying cause of hyperuricemia in this condition. 24 The 
elevation in serum cystatin C in pregnancy might be due to increased production due to 
increase in the number of nucleated cells. 16 </p>

<p>Several studies have reported a positive correlation between elevated maternal serum uric 
acid levels and adverse maternal and fetal outcomes. 4-8,25-27 There was disagreement in 
serum uric acid and serum creatinine as predictors of hypertensive disorders. Studies done 
by weerasekara D.S et al, Manjareeka M et al concluded that serum uric acid and serum 
creatinine are not predictive of pre-eclampsia and Thangaratinam S et al concluded that 
serum uric acid is not predictive of preeclampsia. 19,23,28 However, Studies done by Roberts 
et al and Bellomo et al found uric acid to be predictive of gestational hypertension. 6,29 Our 
findings of serum uric acid as an independent risk factor for hypertensive disorders of 
pregnancy agree with the study done by Gianni Bellomo et al and Roberts et al. 6,29 We did </p>

<p>Yalamati et al. </p>

<p>
Int J Reprod Contracept Obstet Gynecol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 16. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>not observe any significant association between serum cystatin C and the development of 
hypertensive disorders in contrast to the study done by Franceschini et al. 11 There are 
studies to show the association of high serum uric acid levels with the preterm delivery and 
small for gestational age but in our study we found an association between high serum 
creatinine (≥ 0.8 mg/dl) and preterm delivery but not with high serum uric acid and serum 
cystatin C. 6,30 Also we found in our study that pregnant women with high uric acid levels (≥ 
5.88 mg/dl) are associated with low birth weight (&lt;2.5 kg) similar to the studies done by 
Akahori et al, Sagen et al and Schuster et al but serum creatinine and serum cystatin C were 
not found to be associated with low birth weight. 31-33 Our findings of high uric acid levels 
associated with caesarian section agree with the study done by Patel et al. 30 The variability 
in the findings can be explained by the differences in the population, definitions of 
hypertensive disorders of pregnancy and test cut-off values. Our study is limited by the 
small sample size for each hypertensive disorder group of pregnant women. Also the 
associations of the three renal parameters with maternal outcomes like the complications of 
PE and fetal outcomes like Intra Uterine Growth Retardation (IUGR), still births, neonatal 
deaths, small for gestational age (SGA) and Apgar score have not been studied. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>We have observed that serum creatinine and serum uric acid is independent risk factors for 
developing hypertensive disorders in pregnant women. High serum uric acid levels are 
associated with low birth weight and delivery by caesarian section whereas high serum 
creatinine levels are associated with preterm delivery in pregnant women only before 
adjustment for confounding factors and not after adjustment. Serum cystatin C was not 
found to be significantly associated with the studied maternal and fetal outcomes. Further 
large scale cohort studies are required to study the association between the three renal 
parameters and all the maternal and fetal outcomes. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank the U.S. National Institutes of Health Fogarty-supported (D43 TW009078) SHARE INDIA and 
University of Pittsburgh team for conducting the research method courses which contributed to the conduct and 
publication of this research work. We are very grateful to the nursing staff of the department of Obstetrics &amp; 
Gynecology and the laboratory technicians for their help in collecting and storing the samples. Also we thank Dr P 
S Reddy, Chairman, SHARE INDIA, MIMS and Dr Satyanarayana P, Laboratory In charge, MIMS for their 
support during this work. </p>

<p>Funding: This study was supported by the management of Mediciti Institute of Medical Sciences and partly by 
ICMR Short term studentship (STS) Programme </p>



<p>Yalamati et al. </p>

<p>
Int J Reprod Contracept Obstet Gynecol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 16. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Yalamati et al. </p>

<p>
Int J Reprod Contracept Obstet Gynecol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 16. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Yalamati et al. </p>

<p>
Int J Reprod Contracept Obstet Gynecol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 16. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Categorization of included participants. </p>

<p>No. Dependent variable 
N </p>

<p>1 
Blood pressure &lt;140/90 mm Hg 
69 </p>

<p>Blood pressure ≥140/90 mm Hg with or 
without proteinuria </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>2 
Birth weight (Kg) &lt;2.5 
35 </p>

<p>Birth weight (Kg) ≥2.5 
81 </p>

<p>3 
Gestational age of delivery (wks.) &lt;37 
17 </p>

<p>Gestational age of delivery (wks.) ≥37 
99 </p>

<p>4 
Mode of delivery: vaginal 
87 </p>

<p>Mode of delivery: caesarean section 
29 </p>

<p>Independent variable </p>

<p>1 
Serum uric acid ≥ 5.88 mg/dl 
26 </p>

<p>Serum uric acid &lt;5.88 mg/dl 
90 </p>

<p>2 
Serum creatinine ≥ 0.8 mg/dl 
19 </p>

<p>Serum creatinine &lt; 0.8 mg/dl 
97 </p>

<p>3 
Serum cystatin C ≥ 1.3 mg/L. 
25 </p>

<p>Serum cystatin C &lt; 1.3 mg/L. 
91 </p>

<p>Int J Reprod Contracept Obstet Gynecol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 16. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Yalamati et al. 
Page 9 </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Multivariate logistic regression. </p>

<p>Hypertensive disorders of pregnancy € </p>

<p>Model 1 
Model 2 * </p>

<p>Parameter Unadjusted 
OR (95% 
CI β ) </p>

<p>P-value Adjusted 
OR * 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P-
valu 
e </p>

<p>Serum 
uric acid 
(mg/dl) </p>

<p>2.59 
(1.06-6.32) 
0.036 ♦ </p>

<p>3.73 
(1.18-11.75) </p>

<p>0.02 
4 ♦ </p>

<p>Serum 
creatinine 
(mg/dl) </p>

<p>19.93 
(4.32-91.88) 
0 ♦ </p>

<p>15.79 
(3.04-81.94) </p>

<p>0.00 
1 ♦ </p>

<p>Serum 
cystatin C 
(mg/L) </p>

<p>2.34 
(0.95-5.76) </p>

<p>0.063 
2.03 
(0.70-5.87) </p>

<p>0.19 
2 </p>

<p>* model adjusted for age, BMI, gestational age of delivery, parity &amp; birth weight </p>

<p>€ no hypertension coded as 0 and hypertension with or without proteinuria coded as 1 </p>

<p>β confidence interval </p>

<p>♦ Statistically Significant (P &lt; 0.05) </p>

<p>Int J Reprod Contracept Obstet Gynecol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 16. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Yalamati et al. 
Page 10 </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>Multivariate logistic regression. </p>

<p>Birth weight # </p>

<p>Model 1 
Model 2 * </p>

<p>Parameter 
Unadjusted 
OR 
(95% CI β ) </p>

<p>P-
value </p>

<p>Adjusted 
OR * 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P-
value </p>

<p>Serum uric 
acid (mg/dl) </p>

<p>2.49 
(1.01 -6.17) 
0.047 ♦ 1.53 </p>

<p>(0.40-5.79) </p>

<p>0.531 </p>

<p>Serum 
creatinine 
(mg/dl) </p>

<p>2.45 
(0.89 -6.72) </p>

<p>0.08 
1.58 
(0.33-7.60) </p>

<p>0.565 </p>

<p>Serum 
cystatin C 
(mg/L) </p>

<p>1.40 
(0.55 -3.58) </p>

<p>0.475 
0.94 
(0.25-3.51) </p>

<p>0.937 </p>

<p>* model adjusted for age, BMI, gestational age of delivery, parity &amp; blood pressure </p>

<p># birth weight &lt; 2.5 kg coded as 1 and ≥ 2.5 kg coded as 0 </p>

<p>β confidence interval </p>

<p>♦ Statistically Significant (P &lt; 0.05) </p>

<p>Int J Reprod Contracept Obstet Gynecol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 16. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Yalamati et al. 
Page 11 </p>

<p>Table 4 </p>

<p>Multivariate logistic regression. </p>

<p>Gestational age of delivery δ </p>

<p>Model 1 
Model 2 * </p>

<p>Parameter Unadjusted 
OR 
(95% CI β ) </p>

<p>P-
value </p>

<p>Adjusted 
OR * 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P-
value </p>

<p>Serum uric 
acid 
(mg/dl) </p>

<p>1.54 
(0.49 -4.88) </p>

<p>0.456 
0.79 
(0.13 -
4.66) </p>

<p>0.797 </p>

<p>Serum 
creatinine 
(mg/dl) </p>

<p>3.60 
(1.13 -
11.43) </p>

<p>0.029 ♦ 1.93 </p>

<p>(0.35 -
10.51) </p>

<p>0.445 </p>

<p>Serum 
cystatin C 
(mg/L) </p>

<p>2.29 
(0.75 -6.99) </p>

<p>0.143 
1.97 
(0.41 -
9.35) </p>

<p>0.391 </p>

<p>* model adjusted for age, BMI, birth weight, parity &amp; blood pressure </p>

<p>δ gestational age of delivery &lt; 37 wks. coded as 1 and ≥ 37 wks. coded as 0 </p>

<p>β confidence interval </p>

<p>♦ Statistically Significant (P &lt; 0.05) </p>

<p>Int J Reprod Contracept Obstet Gynecol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 16. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Table 5 </p>

<p>Multivariate logistic regression. </p>

<p>Mode of delivery £ </p>

<p>Model 1 
Model 2 * </p>

<p>Parameter Unadjusted 
OR 
(95% CI β ) </p>

<p>P-
value </p>

<p>Adjusted 
OR * 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P-
valu 
e </p>

<p>Serum uric 
acid 
(mg/dl) </p>

<p>2.93 
(1.15-7.46) 
0.024 ♦ 2.99 </p>

<p>(0.97-9.17) </p>

<p>0.05 
4 </p>

<p>Serum 
creatinine 
(mg/dl) </p>

<p>1.98 
(0.69-5.66) </p>

<p>0.198 
1.13 
(0.30-4.18) </p>

<p>0.84 
9 </p>

<p>Serum 
cystatin C 
(mg/L) </p>

<p>2.52 
(0.98-6.50) </p>

<p>0.055 
2.46 
(0.82-7.42) </p>

<p>0.10 
8 </p>

<p>* model adjusted for age, BMI, birth weight, parity, blood pressure , gestational age of delivery </p>

<p>£ caesarean section coded as 1 and vaginal delivery coded as 0 </p>

<p>β confidence interval </p>

<p>♦ Statistically Significant (P &lt; 0.05) </p>

<p>Int J Reprod Contracept Obstet Gynecol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 November 16. </p>

</text></tei>