<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4623366" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Background: Tabalumab is a human monoclonal </p>

<p>antibody that neutralises B-cell activating factor. </p>

<p>Objectives: To evaluate tabalumab efficacy and safety </p>

<p>in patients with rheumatoid arthritis (RA). </p>

<p>Methods: This phase 3, randomised, double-blind, </p>

<p>placebo-controlled study evaluated 456 patients with 
active RA after 24-week treatment with subcutaneous 
tabalumab (120 mg every 4 weeks (120/Q4W) or 
90 mg every 2 weeks (90/Q2W)) versus placebo, with 
loading doses (240 or 180 mg) at week 0. Patients 
were allowed background disease-modifying 
antirheumatic drugs and previously discontinued ≥1 
tumour necrosis factor α inhibitors for lack of efficacy/ 
intolerance. Primary end point was American College of 
Rheumatology 20% (ACR20) response at 24 weeks. 
This study was terminated early due to futility. </p>

<p>Results: Most patients had moderate-to-high baseline </p>

<p>disease activity. There was no significant difference in 
week 24 ACR20 responses between 120/Q4W, 90/ 
Q2W, and placebo (17.6%, 24.3%, 20%) per non-
responder imputation analysis. Mean percent changes 
in CD20+ B-cell count (−10.8%, −9.6%, +10.9%) 
demonstrated expected pharmacodynamic effects. 
Treatment-emergent adverse events (AEs) were similar 
(59.5%, 51.7%, 52.6%), as were AE discontinuations 
(2.6%, 2.7%, 2.6%), serious AEs (4.6%, 4.1%, 3.9%), 
serious infectious events (1.3%, 0, 0) and events of 
interest: infections (23.5%, 25.9%, 24%), injection site 
reactions (13.1%, 25.8%, 11%) and allergy/ 
hypersensitivity (3.9%, 4.1%, 3.9%) reports. Incidence 
of treatment-emergent antidrug antibodies was similar 
to placebo (3.9%, 4.8%, 3.9%). No deaths or new/ 
unexpected safety findings were reported. </p>

<p>Key messages </p>

<p>What is already known about this subject? </p>

<p>B cells contribute to the immunopathology of auto-
immune disorders including rheumatoid arthritis 
(RA), which may be related to increased B-cell acti-
vating factor (BAFF) signalling. Earlier phase clinical 
trials of anti-BAFF monoclonal antibodies showed a 
clinical effect in RA. </p>

<p>What does this study add? </p>

<p>BAFF targeting via tabalumab did not provide clin-
ical benefit in this phase 3 trial for patients with 
moderate-to-severe RA with prior inadequate 
response to tumour necrosis factor (TNF) 
inhibitors. </p>

<p>How might this impact on clinical practice? </p>

<p>In patients with prior inadequate response to TNF 
inhibitors, targeting the BAFF pathway alone was 
not an effective approach to treating RA. Targeting 
BAFF may not be a viable therapeutic approach. </p>

<p>Schiff M, et al. RMD Open 2015;1:e000037. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2014-000037 </p>



<p>Rheumatoid arthritis </p>

<p>signalling. 
1 Dysregulated BAFF expression contributes to 
autoimmunity primarily via effects on survival of imma-
ture and transitional B cells and the resulting failure to 
eliminate self-reactive B cells. Conversely, blocking BAFF 
has been shown to reverse autoimmune disease in 
animal models. 
2 3 Furthermore, many patients with RA 
have elevated BAFF in blood and synovial fluid. </p>

<p>3 4   Disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs (DMARDs) are 
a part of the standard of care to treat RA, including the 
class of biologics (bDMARDs) that target tumour 
necrosis factor (TNF). 
5 Though numerous RA therapies 
are currently available, 20-50% of patients do not 
achieve significant clinical improvement, 
6-12 or they fail 
to maintain efficacy after initial therapeutic benefit. </p>

<p>13   Thus, new treatment options for RA are needed. 
Tabalumab is a fully human immunoglobulin G sub-
class 4 (IgG4) monoclonal antibody that binds and neu-
tralises both soluble and membrane-bound BAFF. 
14 In 
phase 2 studies, tabalumab demonstrated evidence of 
both biological and clinical activity in patients with 
active RA and inadequate response to methotrexate. </p>

<p>15 16   This phase 3 study was designed to evaluate efficacy and 
safety of tabalumab in patients with RA who had an inad-
equate response to one or more TNF inhibitors. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Study design 
H9B-MC-BCDV (FLEX V; NCT01202773) was a phase 3, 
double-blind, placebo-controlled study comprised of a 
screening period of 7-28 days, a 24-week treatment 
period and post-treatment follow-up for up to 48 weeks. 
Participants were randomly assigned (1:1:1) to treatment 
groups by a computer generated random sequence 
using the <rs type="software">Interactive Voice Response System</rs> (IVRS); the 
randomisation code was held by the vendor performing 
<rs type="software">IVRS</rs> functions. 
This study evaluated two subcutaneous (SQ) tabalu-
mab doses: 120 mg every 4 weeks (120/Q4W) or 90 mg 
every 2 weeks (90/Q2W), versus placebo. At week 0, 
patients assigned to a tabalumab regimen received a SQ 
loading dose that was twice the treatment dose (ie, 
240 mg or 180 mg). </p>

<p>Patient eligibility 
Eligible patients were in American College of 
Rheumatology (ACR) functional class I, II, or III; had at 
least 8/68 tender and at least 8/66 swollen joints; had 
been treated at approved doses with at least 1 biological 
TNF inhibitor therapy; and stopped prior anti-TNF treat-
ment due to either (1) insufficient efficacy or loss of effi-
cacy after ≥90 days of treatment or (2) intolerance to 
treatment regardless of treatment duration. If patients 
were on conventional DMARDs, they were required to 
have been on a stable dose for ≥8 weeks prior to study 
baseline. 
This study was conducted in accordance with local 
institutional review board ethical standards, good clinical </p>

<p>practices and the Declaration of Helsinki. All patients 
provided written informed consent before study 
participation. </p>

<p>Study assessments 
The primary objective was to demonstrate the superiority 
of either tabalumab regimen over placebo as measured 
by a 20% response rate in a core set of measures 
(ACR20) after 24 weeks of treatment. 
Secondary efficacy end points were to demonstrate super-
iority of either tabalumab regimen over placebo after 
24 weeks of treatment as measured by ACR50 and 
ACR70 (ie, 50% and 70% ACR response rates), ACR-N 
( per cent improvement on the ACR), individual compo-
nents of the ACR core set, Disease Activity Score based 
on a 28-joint count (DAS28) and C reactive protein 
(CRP) level (DAS28-CRP), time to ACR20 response and 
European League Against Rheumatism Responder 
Index based on the 28-joint count (EULAR-28). 
Health utilisation and outcomes evaluated as second-
ary end points included the Medical Outcomes Study 
36-Item Short Form Health Survey (SF-36), Brief Fatigue 
Inventory (BFI), Brief Pain Inventory Modified Short 
Form (BPI-SF modified), duration of morning stiffness 
and the use of concomitant medications specifically for 
RA taken during the treatment period. 
Biological activity of tabalumab was assessed over time 
via changes in serum immunoglobulins, CD20+ B-cell 
absolute counts and relative percentages ( percentages 
of the total lymphocyte population), compared between 
each treatment regimen and placebo. 
Safety assessments were treatment-emergent adverse 
events (TEAEs), TEAEs of special interest, clinical 
laboratory tests including immunogenicity testing, vital 
signs and concomitant medications. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses 
A sample size of 555 randomised patients (185 patients 
each per tabalumab regimen and placebo group) was 
calculated to provide ≥99% power to detect a ≥30% dif-
ference in ACR20 response rates at week 24 for each 
tabalumab regimen versus placebo, assuming a placebo 
response rate of 18%. ACR20 significance testing used 
the Dunnett procedure at an overall 2-sided α level of 
0.05, with each tabalumab regimen versus placebo com-
parison made at a two-sided α level of 0.0272. All other 
statistical tests of treatment effects and interaction 
effects were performed at two-sided significance levels of 
0.05 and 0.10, respectively, unless otherwise stated. 
Primary and key secondary analyses followed a gatekeep-
ing testing strategy to control the overall type I error 
rate at a two-sided α level of 0.05. Treatment group com-
parisons used Fisher's exact test for categorical data and 
analysis of variance (ANOVA) for continuous data, 
unless otherwise stated. 
Efficacy and health outcome analyses were conducted 
following the intention-to-treat principle. Primary effi-
cacy analysis was repeated on the per protocol </p>



<p>Schiff M, et al. RMD Open 2015;1:e000037. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2014-000037 </p>

<p>RMD Open </p>

<p>population, a subset of the intent-to-treat (ITT) popula-
tion excluding patients with significant protocol viola-
tions. Safety analyses were conducted on the safety 
population including all patients who received at least 
one dose of assigned study drug. Primary end point ana-
lyses of continuous efficacy and health outcome data 
were conducted using a modified baseline observation 
carried forward (mBOCF) approach; all other analyses 
were conducted using the modified last observation 
carried forward (mLOCF) approach. Non-responder 
imputation (NRI) was used for ACR analyses; non-
responders (NR) were defined by &lt;20% improvement in 
tender joint count and swollen joint count at week 16. 
Non-responders at week 16, patients who discontinued 
study treatment at any time and randomised patients 
with no postbaseline observations were defined as NR 
for all ACR end point analyses. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Patient population 
In total, 456 patients met enrolment criteria and were 
randomised, and comprised the ITT population: 153 
patients in the 120/Q4W group, 148 patients in the 90/ 
Q2W group and 155 patients in the placebo group 
(figure 1). Two randomised patients (1 patient each in 
the 90/Q2W and placebo groups) did not receive study 
treatment and were excluded from the safety population 
of 454 patients. The study was conducted from 28 
January 2011 to 12 March 2013. 
Baseline demographic and disease characteristics are 
summarised for each treatment group in table 1. 
Patients were a mean age of 53 years, the majority 
(84%) were women; most were located in North 
America (58.8%) with a mean time since RA diagnosis 
of 8.2 years. At baseline, most patients (75.4%) were 
seropositive for both RF+ and anti-CCP+. Patients for 
whom data were available had disease severity charac-
terised as very active RA (75.3%), defined by 
DAS28-CRP &gt;5.1, whereas the remaining patients had 
disease that was moderately active RA (24.7%), defined 
as DAS28-CRP &gt;3.2-≤5.1. Demographic variables and 
clinical characteristics were generally balanced between 
treatment groups, with no significant difference between 
placebo and tabalumab treatment groups. </p>

<p>Efficacy assessments 
ACR20 responders at the week 24 end point in the ITT 
population included: 17.6% in the 120/Q4W group, 
24.3% in the 90/Q2W group and 20% in the placebo 
group (figure 2). Fisher's exact test was used at the week 
24 end point because the sample size was not sufficient 
for logistic regression due to week 16 non-response, 
drop out and sponsor decision. There were no signifi-
cant differences in the ACR20 response rate at the week 
24 end point for either tabalumab treatment group 
versus the placebo group; therefore, the primary end 
point of this study was not met. While a significant </p>

<p>ACR20 response rate at week 12 was observed for 
patients in the 90/Q2W treatment group (28.4%) versus 
the placebo group (18.1%; p=0.030), this benefit was 
not sustained at week 24.  In the ITT population, mean changes from baseline at 
the week 24 mBOCF on individual ACR components-
tender and swollen joint count, patient global assess-
ment (PtGA), physician global assessment (PhGA), pain 
VAS-were similar across all treatment groups (data not 
shown). There were no significant differences for either 
tabalumab treatment group versus placebo in ACR50, 
ACR70, CRP, HAQ-DI or DAS28-CRP scores, or propor-
tions of patients who reported a good to moderate 
rating on the EULAR-28 (mLOCF). After an interim 
analysis that was prompted by lack of efficacy in a separ-
ate tabalumab study (H9B-MC-BCDM; FLEX M; 
NCT01198002), the present study was terminated by the 
sponsor due to futility evidenced by insufficient efficacy. </p>

<p>Biological activity 
In the safety population, both tabalumab groups showed 
an expected initial increase in mean CD20+ B-cell abso-
lute counts at week 1 (median per cent change from 
baseline: 37.6-56.3%) compared with placebo (−2.6%), 
followed by a subsequent decrease back to baseline or 
lower starting at week 4 (figure 3). At week 24 (exclud-
ing week 16 non-responders), CD20+ B-cell absolute 
count median per cent change from baseline was 
−43.2%, −53.2% and −1.1% for 120/Q4W, 90/Q2W and 
placebo groups, respectively. Significant differences were 
observed at week 24 (mLOCF) in tabalumab groups 
versus placebo for mean CD20+ B-cell count change 
from baseline (−62.0 cells/µL, −65.2 cells/µL, and −3.8 
cells/µL; p&lt;0.001 vs placebo for each comparison) and 
change from baseline in CD20+ B cells as percentage of 
total lymphocytes (−3%, −3.4%, and 0.1%; p&lt;0.001 vs 
placebo for each comparison). 
For week 16 non-responders initially randomised to 
tabalumab, the patterns of absolute CD20+ B-cell count 
median percent change from baseline and median time 
to B-cell nadir were similar with B-cell changes observed 
for the responders. 
For this study, B-cell recovery was defined as &lt;43 cells/ 
µL and &lt;50% of B-cell baseline values. Fifteen patients 
(excluding week 16 non-responders) had 1 or more low 
B-cell counts: 8, 5 and 2 patients, respectively. These 
patients were further evaluated to determine the time 
from nadir to recovery. The median time from B-cell nadir 
to recovery (Kaplan-Meier estimates, excluding week 16 
non-responders) was 11.9 weeks (95% CI 8.4 weeks to not 
available) for 120/Q4W group and 12.3 weeks (95% CI 
12.1 weeks to 22.4 weeks) for 90/Q2W group. 
In the safety population, both tabalumab groups 
demonstrated decreases in mean serum immunoglobu-
lins over the 24-week treatment period (figure 3B-D). 
At the week 24 end point (mLOCF), the IgA mean per 
cent change from baseline was −9%, −9% and +1.6%, 
respectively ( p&lt;0.001 vs placebo, each comparison); IgG </p>

<p>Schiff M, et al. RMD Open 2015;1:e000037. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2014-000037 </p>



<p>Rheumatoid arthritis </p>

<p>mean per cent change from baseline was −7.2%, −7.9% 
and +1.4%, respectively ( p&lt;0.001 vs placebo, each com-
parison); and IgM mean percent change from baseline 
was −15%, −14.8% and +0.2%, respectively ( p&lt;0.001 vs 
placebo, each comparison). 
No correlation was observed between immunoglobulin 
changes from baseline to the week 24 mLOCF end point 
and number of treatment-emergent infections or anti-
drug (tabalumab) antibodies (ADA) for either tabalu-
mab group versus placebo during the treatment and 
follow-up periods. </p>

<p>Safety profile 
During the 24-week treatment period, the incidence of 
treatment-emergent adverse events (TEAEs) and serious 
AEs were similar across treatment groups (table 2). The 
incidence of TEAEs was 59.5%, 51.7% and 52.6% in the 
120/Q4W, 90/Q2W and placebo groups, respectively. 
The majority of TEAEs were mild or moderate in sever-
ity. The most frequently reported TEAEs (≥5% of 
patients in any group) were exacerbation of RA (5.9%, 
4.8% and 7.8%) and upper respiratory tract infection 
(5.9%, 4.8% and 5.8%; table 2). There were no signifi-
cant differences between either tabalumab group versus 
placebo for either of these events. Possibly-related </p>

<p>TEAEs reported by ≥5% of patients in either tabalumab 
group included infections and infestations (7.2%, 9.5% 
and 11.7%), and general disorders and administration 
site conditions (7.2%, 9.5% and 5.8%). TEAEs were the 
reason for study discontinuation in four patients in each 
treatment group among responders. No significant 
dose-related increase in TEAEs was observed for any 
single event or grouping of TEAEs evaluated. 
AEs of special interest that deserve mention include 
infections, allergic/hypersensitivity events, injection site 
reactions, cardiovascular events and depression. The 
incidence of treatment-emergent infections (23.5%, 
25.9% and 24%) and non-anaphylactic allergic/hyper-
sensitive reactions (3.9%, 4.1% and 3.9%) were similar 
across 120/Q4W, 90/Q2W and placebo groups, respect-
ively. Two major cardiovascular adverse events were 
reported during the treatment period: a serious arrhyth-
mia (1 patient in the 90/Q2W group) and coronary 
revascularisation (1 patient in the placebo group). 
Twenty-one patients who received tabalumab (7 (13.1%) 
in the 120/Q4W group and 14 (25.8%) in the 90/Q2W 
group) and 6 (11%) patients in the placebo group 
reported a treatment-emergent injection site reaction 
during the treatment period. The exposure-adjusted rate 
of injection site reactions per 100 patient-years exposure </p>

<p>Figure 1 Patient disposition. Eligibility was assessed during screening, then randomisation to 24 weeks of treatment 
(or 16 weeks for non-responders) in 1 of 2 tabalumab regimens or placebo and 48 weeks of follow-up. 120/Q4W=120 mg 
subcutaneous (SQ) tabalumab injection every 4 weeks; 90/Q2W=90 mg SQ tabalumab injection every 2 weeks. </p>



<p>Schiff M, et al. RMD Open 2015;1:e000037. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2014-000037 </p>

<p>RMD Open </p>

<p>for the 90/Q2W treatment group (25.8) was almost 
double the rate for the 120/Q4W (13.1) and placebo 
treatment groups (11.0). No patients discontinued study 
treatment due to an injection site reaction. All injection 
site reactions were mild to moderate in severity. The inci-
dence of depression or suicidal ideation was similar 
across the treatment groups (2%, 0.7% and 2.6%). </p>

<p>Serious AEs were reported in seven patients (4.6%) 
in the 120/Q4W group, 6 (4.1%) in the 90/Q2W 
group and 6 (3.9%) in the placebo group, during the 
24-week treatment period. Serious infections (2 cases of 
pneumonia, 1.3%) were reported in the 120/Q4W 
group only. Opportunistic infections were reported in 3 
(2%), 6 (4.1%) and 6 (3.9%) patients, respectively, in </p>

<p>Table 1 Patient baseline characteristics </p>

<p>Baseline characteristic </p>

<p>Tabalumab 120/Q4W 
Tabalumab 90/Q2W 
Placebo 
N=153 
N=148 
N=155 </p>

<p>Age, mean years±SD 
54.2±11.6 
51.3±11.7 
54.0±11.1 
Female, n (%) 
124 (81.0) 
126 (85.1) 
131 (84.5) 
Race, n (%) 
White 
119 (78.8) 
108 (74.0) 
112 (74.2) 
Black 
14 (9.3) 
16 (11.0) 
18 (11.9) 
Asian 
10 (6.6) 
9 (6.2) 
13 (8.6) 
American Indian/Alaska native 
8 (5.3) 
9 (6.2) 
6 (4.0) 
Multiracial 
0 
4 (2.7) 
2 (1.3) 
Geographic region, n (%) 
North America 
89 (58.2) 
90 (60.8) 
89 (57.4) 
Central/South America 
25 (16.3) 
21 (14.2) 
25 (16.1) 
Eastern Europe 
20 (13.1) 
18 (12.2) 
18 (11.6) 
Western Europe 
8 (5.2) 
8 (5.4) 
7 (4.5) 
Rest of world* 
11 (7.2) 
11 (7.4) 
16 (10.3) 
Weight, mean kg 
79.6 
80.3 
77.6 
Body mass index, mean kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>29.9 
29.9 
29.3 
Time since RA diagnosis, mean years±SD 
8.1±4.3 
7.9±3.9 
8.7±4.2 
Swollen joint count (66), mean±SD 
19.5±12.2 
19.8±12.2 
18.3±11.7 
Tender joint count (68), mean±SD 
28.6±15.8 
30.1±17.1 
28.7±15.7 
PhGA (VAS), mean±SD 
62.3±17.3 
63.9±17.0 
62.4±19.0 
PtGA (VAS), mean±SD 
63.7±23.0 
65.3±21.6 
68.1±20.1 
Patient assessment of pain (VAS), mean±SD 
62.8±22.2 
66.0±21.6 
65.1±21.6 
C reactive protein, mg/L, mean±SD 
16.29 
14.57 
19.11 
HAQ-DI, mean±SD 
1.67±0.58 
1.68±0.60 
1.66±0.56 
DAS28-CRP, mean±SD 
5.84±1.02 
5.88±1.04 
5.89±0.97 
Only RF+, n (%) 
11 (7.2) 
8 (5.4) 
9 (5.8) 
Only anti-CCP+, n (%) 
19 (12.4) 
15 (10.1) 
13 (8.4) 
Both RF+ and anti-CCP+, n (%) 
114 (74.5) 
112 (75.7) 
117 (76.0) 
Absolute CD20+ B-cell count (cells/μL) mean±SD 
223±171 
210±154 
223±153 
Number of previous TNF treatment failures, n (%) 
0 
3 (2.0) 
1 (0.7) 
4 (2.6) 
1 
94 (61.4) 
95 (64.2) 
86 (55.5) 
2 
30 (19.6) 
27 (18.2) 
42 (27.1) 
≥3 
26 (17.0) 
25 (16.9) 
23 (14.8) 
Background DMARDS, n (%) 
1 
140 (91.5) 
136 (93.2) 
133 (86.9) 
2 
13 (8.5) 
10 (6.8) 
17 (11.1) 
≥3 
0 
0 
3 (2.0) 
Background corticosteroids, n (%) 
82 (53.6) 
85 (57.4) 
86 (55.5) 
Mean daily dose of background medications 
Methotrexate, mg/week 
15.5 (n=131) 
15.5 (n=126) 
15.8 (n=135) 
Hydroxychloroquine, mg/day 
376.5 (n=17) 
360.0 (n=10) 
336.8 (n=19) 
Sulfasalazine, mg/day 
1419.6 (n=8) 
1900.0 (n=10) 
1590.9 (n=11) </p>

<p>*Rest of world=Russia, Australia, Japan, Korea, Malaysia, New Zealand, South Africa and Taiwan. 
120/Q4W=120 mg subcutaneous (SQ) tabalumab injection every 4 weeks; 90/Q2W=90 mg SQ tabalumab injection every 2 weeks. 
ACR, American College of Rheumatology; CCP, cyclic citrullinated peptide; DAS28-CRP, Disease Activity Score based on a 28 joint count 
and C reactive protein level; DMARD, disease-modifying antirheumatic drug; EULAR-28, European League Against Rheumatism Responder 
Index in 28 joints; HAQ-DI, Health Assessment Questionnaire-Disability Index; PhGA, physician global assessment; PtGA, patient global 
assessment; RA, rheumatoid arthritis; RF, rheumatoid factor; TNF, tumour necrosis factor; VAS, visual analogue scale. </p>

<p>Schiff M, et al. RMD Open 2015;1:e000037. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2014-000037 </p>



<p>Rheumatoid arthritis </p>

<p>the treatment and follow-up periods. Individual events 
included investigator reported pneumonia, nail infec-
tion, herpes zoster, upper respiratory infection, influ-
enza, erysipelas, UTI, nasopharyngitis, sinusitis, cellulitis 
and device-related infection. No deaths were reported 
in this study. </p>

<p>No notable differences or trends were identified for 
vital signs, ECG, or clinical laboratory test results during 
the study treatment period. </p>

<p>Immunogenicity 
Over the 24-week treatment period, 6 (3.9%), 7 (4.8%) 
and 6 (3.9%) patients in the 120/Q4W, 90/Q2W and 
placebo groups, respectively, developed persistent or tran-
sient treatment-emergent ADA (defined as ≥2 dilutions/ 
fourfold increase from baseline). Four patients (2.6%), 2 
(1.4%) and 4 (2.6%) patients, respectively, were classified 
as treatment-emergent ADA-persistent defined as 2 or 
more positive samples of at least 12 weeks duration. 
Blood samples from patients who developed ADA 
were also evaluated for neutralising antidrug antibodies 
(NAb). One (0.3%) tabalumab-treated patient had a 
positive NAb result and 2 (0.7%) had negative results. 
Samples from 13 (4.3%) patients were inconclusive 
because drug concentrations exceeded the drug toler-
ance limit for the assay. Given the low frequency of 
ADA, it was difficult to assess the effect of ADA on the 
serum pharmacokinetics of tabalumab. No association 
was found between patients with treatment-emergent 
ADAs and reports of allergic/hypersensitivity (non-
anaphylaxis) events or injection site reactions in the 
treatment or follow-up period. </p>

<p>Figure 2 ACR20 response rates. ACR20 response rates 
based on non-responder imputation (NRI) for the 120/Q4W, 
90/Q2W and placebo groups over 24 weeks of treatment. 
Response rates are based on the ITT population. 
ACR20=20% improvement in American College of 
Rheumatology criteria; 120/Q4W=120 mg subcutaneous (SQ) 
tabalumab injection every 4 weeks; 90/Q2W=90 mg SQ 
tabalumab injection every 2 weeks. </p>

<p>Figure 3 (A-D). B-cell and Ig changes. Mean changes in total CD3-CD20+ B-cells (A) and immunoglobulin (Ig) subclasses 
levels (B-D) were measured over 24 weeks of treatment. Mean per cent changes are based on the safety population. 120/ 
Q4W=120 mg subcutaneous (SQ) tabalumab injection every 4 weeks; 90/Q2W=90 mg SQ tabalumab injection every 2 weeks; 
mLOCF=modified last observation carried forward. *p&lt;0.001 tabalumab groups versus placebo (both comparisons) at week 24 
(mLOCF). </p>



<p>Schiff M, et al. RMD Open 2015;1:e000037. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2014-000037 </p>

<p>RMD Open </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Prior phase two studies of tabalumab in patients with 
moderate-to-severe RA showed evidence of clinical effi-
cacy, reporting higher ACR20 response rates and signifi-
cant differences in response rates for ACR50, ACR70, 
DAS-28 CRP and EULAR scores in tabalumab groups 
versus placebo. 
15 16 Biological activity was also demon-
strated in these earlier studies, including reductions in 
B-cell counts and serum immunoglobulins. 
While there is no obvious explanation for the discrep-
ant results in this study relative to the earlier phase two 
studies, there are some differences between the phase 2 
and 3 studies to consider. The baseline characteristics 
for disease activity in the earlier phase 2 studies were 
generally comparable to the current study; however, this 
study was a global study, while some of the phase 2 
studies enrolled patients from less diverse geographic 
regions and were smaller in size. In terms of study drug 
administration, in one phase 2 study of patients with 
inadequate response to TNF inhibitors, tabalumab was 
administered as either a 30 mg or 80 mg intravenous 
infusion at weeks 0, 3 and 6, 
17 while the current phase 3 
study evaluated two subcutaneous (SQ) tabalumab doses 
of 120 mg every 4 weeks (120/Q4W) or 90 mg every 
2 weeks (90/Q2W), versus placebo. A separate phase 2 
tabalumab study of patients with inadequate response to 
methotrexate, which also applied intravenous adminis-
tration and the same dosing frequency, demonstrated 
that all tabalumab doses were significantly more effective 
than placebo through week 24. 
15 It is notable that clin-
ical efficacy corresponded to peak drug concentrations 
following infusion of tabalumab. 
The current phase 3 study of patients with 
moderate-to-severe RA and prior treatment failure or 
intolerance to 1 or more TNF inhibitors did not meet its 
primary objective, as tabalumab treatment was not super-
ior to placebo for the primary end point of ACR20 
response at week 24 and did not meet any secondary effi-
cacy objective. The efficacy of tabalumab in special patient 
subgroups (eg, prior prednisolone use, smoking status, 
RF/anti-CCP seropositivity status and number of previous </p>

<p>TNF inhibitor treatment failures), was inconclusive 
because data were insufficient due to early termination of 
the trial. The findings in this study corroborate prelimin-
ary reported data from other BAFF inhibitor trials in 
patients with RA showing a lack of significant efficacy 
18 or 
efficacy that was restricted to a bDMARD-naïve sub-
group. 
19 Despite the lack of efficacy, the biological activity 
of tabalumab was confirmed, but did not differ between 
the 2 dosing regimens in all parameters tested. Over the 
24-week treatment period, CD20+ B-cells initially increased 
then gradually and significantly declined in response to 
tabalumab but not placebo administration, and without 
total B-cell depletion. This was expected, based on the 
mechanism of action of tabalumab: binding and neutralis-
ing BAFF, 
14 an essential B-cell survival signal, and has also 
been reported for other BAFF/B-lymphocyte stimulator 
(BLyS) inhibiting agents (belimumab, atacicept). </p>

<p>20   Notably, these other BAFF blocking agents also showed a 
lack of correlation between different dosages and bio-
marker changes. 
21 22 In the current study, B-cell decline 
correlated with significant decreases in circulating IgA, 
IgG and IgM levels after tabalumab treatment. Despite 
decreases in biological parameters, there was no difference 
in infection rates for either tabalumab group compared 
with placebo. Tabalumab treatment was associated with a 
low incidence of ADA, and there was no association 
between treatment-emergent ADA and any reports of AEs. 
Frequencies of TEAEs and SAEs were similar across 
tabalumab and placebo groups, and the incidence of 
AEs leading to study discontinuation was low across all 
treatment groups. The safety profile of tabalumab in this 
RA population was consistent with prior studies, and no 
new or unexpected safety findings were observed. </p>

<p>15-17   Compared with prior phase 3 studies of other biological 
therapies in patients with RA, the present study of taba-
lumab had a similar incidence of TEAEs (range: 
51.7-59.5%), discontinuations due to TEAEs (range: 2.6-
2.7%), infections (range: 23.5-25.9%) and SAEs (range: 
3.9-4.6%). </p>

<p>6 23-26   There were limitations to the design and interpretation 
of results of this study, which was terminated early. The </p>

<p>Table 2 Summary of adverse events during the treatment period </p>

<p>Events, n (%) </p>

<p>All safety population patients* 
Week 16 
Non-responders † 
Tabalumab 120/Q4W 
Tabalumab 90/Q2W 
Placebo 
N=153 
N=147 
N=154 
N=93 </p>

<p>Patients with ≥1 TEAE 
91 (59.5) 
76 (51.7) 
81 (52.6) 
38 (40.9) 
Discontinuations due to TEAE 
4 (2.6) 
4 (2.7) 
4 (2.6) 
2 (2.2) 
Patients with ≥1 SAE 
7 (4.6) 
6 (4.1) 
6 (3.9) 
4 (4.3) 
Deaths 
0 
0 
0 
0 
TEAEs in ≥5% of patients (any group) 
Rheumatoid arthritis 
9 (5.9) 
7 (4.8) 
12 (7.8) 
4 (4.3) 
Upper respiratory tract infection 
9 (5.9) 
7 (4.8) 
9 (5.8) 
2 (2.2) </p>

<p>120/Q4W=120 mg subcutaneous (SQ) tabalumab injection every 4 weeks; 90/Q2W=90 mg SQ tabalumab injection every 2 weeks. 
*Safety data include events up to week 1 for week 16 non-responders; data are reported for the safety population. 
 †Safety data collected after week 16 are reported. 
SAE, serious adverse event; TEAE, treatment-emergent adverse event. </p>

<p>Schiff M, et al. RMD Open 2015;1:e000037. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2014-000037 </p>



<p>Rheumatoid arthritis </p>

<p>effects of background DMARD treatment, and prior and 
concomitant RA medications, may limit interpretation of 
results. In addition, patients were previously treated with 
1 or more TNF inhibitors and had discontinued due to 
treatment failure or intolerance; there may be patients in 
this population who are refractory to immunomodulatory 
biological therapy for RA, including tabalumab. 
In this phase 3 study in patients with previous failure 
of biological therapy, tabalumab did not demonstrate 
clinical efficacy in either dosing regimen, despite evi-
dence of biological activity. Targeting BAFF may not be 
a viable therapeutic approach. Alternatively, the dose of 
active study drug and/or duration of the study may not 
have been optimal to observe a clinical effect. No new 
or unexpected safety findings were reported for patients 
with RA who received tabalumab. </p>

<p>Author affiliations </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Rheumatology Division, School of Medicine, University of Colorado, Denver, 
USA </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Rheumatology, Lapeyronie Hospital, Montpellier 1 University, 
Montpellier, France </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Medicine/Rheumatology and Clinical Immunology, Charité-
Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Division of Rheumatology, Albany Medical College, Albany, USA </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Department of Rheumatology, Leiden University Medical Center, Leiden, The 
Netherlands </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Global Patient Safety Medical and Benefit-Risk Management, Lilly and 
Company, Indianapolis, USA </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Autoimmune Medical, Bio-Medicines Business Unit, Lilly and Company, 
Indianapolis, USA </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Medical Science-Japan Development, Lilly and Company, Kobe, Japan </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors thank Jennifer N Bodie, PhD and Teresa 
Tartaglione, PharmD (ClinGenuity, LLC, Cincinnati, OH), for medical writing 
support and assistance with preparation and submission of this paper. This 
study was sponsored by Eli Lilly and Company. </p>

<p>Contributors MS, BC, TD, JMK and TWH were study investigators, and 
participated in the interpretation of data and data reporting. MS, AG, WK, 
P-YB, RO and CL contributed to conception of the study design and analysis 
plan, data interpretation and data reporting. All the authors provided critical 
input and approval to the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding This study was sponsored by Eli Lilly and Company. The protocol 
for this trial may be found at: https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/ 
NCT01202773?term=NCT01202773&amp;rank=1. </p>

<p>Competing interests MS reports consultancy fees with AbbVie, Amgen, 
Antares, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Eli Lilly, Horizon, Johnson &amp; Johnson, 
Novartis, Novo Nordisk, Pfizer, Roche and UCB Pharma; is a member of 
AbbVie's speaker bureau; and has received research funding from UCB 
Pharma. BC reports personal fees and other from Eli Lilly during the conduct 
of the study; grants and personal fees from Bristol Myers Squibb; personal 
fees from Janssen; grants and personal fees from Merck; grants and personal 
fees from Pfizer; grants and personal fees from Roche-Chugai; and grants 
from UCB Pharma. TD reports grants and personal fees from UCB Pharma; 
grants and personal fees from Roche/Chugai, grants and personal fees from 
Sanofi; and grants from Janssen and Johnson &amp; Johnson. JMK reports fees 
for research and consulting from Eli Lilly. TWH reports fees for research and 
for serving on the scientific advisory board from Eli Lilly. MV, AG, WK, P-YB, 
RO and CL are all employees and stockholders of Eli Lilly. WK also reports 
owning stocks and receiving dividends from the Pfizer Corporation. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Institutional Review Board at each investigative site. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Schiff M, et al. RMD Open 2015;1:e000037. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2014-000037 </p>

<p>RMD Open </p>



<p>Schiff M, et al. RMD Open 2015;1:e000037. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2014-000037 </p>



<p>Rheumatoid arthritis </p>

</text></tei>