<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4919596" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Although both C-C chemokine receptor 5 (CCR5)-and CXC chemokine receptor 4 (CXCR4)-using HIV-1 strains 
cause AIDS, the emergence of CXCR4-utilizing variants is associated with an accelerated decline in CD4+ T cells. 
It remains uncertain if CXCR4-using viruses hasten disease or if these variants only emerge after profound immu-
nological damage. We show that exclusively CXCR4-as compared to cocirculating CCR5-utilizing variants are less 
sensitive to neutralization by both contemporaneous autologous plasma and plasma pools from individuals that 
harbor only CCR5-using HIV-1. The CXCR4-utilizing variants, however, do not have a global antigenic change 
because they remain equivalently susceptible to antibodies that do not target coreceptor binding domains. Studies 
with envelope V3 loop directed antibodies and chimeric envelopes suggest that the neutralization susceptibility 
differences are potentially influenced by the V3 loop. In vitro passage of a neutralization sensitive CCR5-using 
virus in the presence of autologous plasma and activated CD4+ T cells led to the emergence of a CXCR4-utilizing 
virus in 1 of 3 cases. These results suggest that in some but not necessarily all HIV-1 infected individuals humoral 
immune pressure against the autologous virus selects for CXCR4-using variants, which potentially accelerates 
disease progression. Our observations have implications for using antibodies for HIV-1 immune therapy. 
In nearly all cases HIV-1 infection leads to a progressive loss of 
CD4+ T cells, and both host immunologic factors and viral characteris-
tics influence the rate of progression towards AIDS. Although HIV-1 can 
enter target cells by either using the C-C chemokine receptor 5 (CCR5) 
or CXC-chemokine receptor 4 (CXCR4) co-receptor after CD4 receptor 
engagement (Deng et al., 1996; Feng et al., 1996), presence of syncy-
tium-inducing (SI) CXCR4-using viruses is associated with accelerated 
disease progression (Koot et al., 1993; Richman and Bozzette, 1994; 
Connor et al., 1997). In general, viruses that exclusively utilize the 
CCR5 receptor (termed R5 or non-syncytium-inducing (NSI)) establish 
initial infection, and these viruses persist throughout the course of dis-
ease (Connor et al., 1997; van't Wout et al., 1994; Schuitemaker et al., 
1992). During the chronic phase of infection, some individuals have a 
dual-mixed (DM) population consisting of R5 viruses and CXCR4-</p>

<p>using variants, which can either only use CXCR4 (termed X4) or be 
dual-tropic that can engage both co-receptors (termed dual or R5X4) 
(Schuitemaker et al., 1992; Connor et al., 1997). Previous studies have 
not clarified if CXCR4-using viruses accelerate disease progression or if 
faster CD4+ T cell decline facilitates the emergence of DM virus popu-
lations. Deciphering mechanisms for the emergence of CXCR4-utilizing 
variants will provide insights into this viral factor important for progres-
sion towards AIDS. 
It is generally agreed that R5 variants give rise to R5X4 viruses, 
which can further evolve to X4 HIV-1 (Pastore et al., 2004). Specific 
modifications in the envelope glycoprotein (env) variable loop 3 (V3), 
which binds the co-receptor, are required for the transition from R5 to 
X4 virus (Huang et al., 2007; Chesebro et al., 1996; Cocchi et al., 
1996). The selective pressures which induce the transition from CCR5 
to CXCR4 usage during the natural course of infection remain poorly un-
derstood. It has been suggested that CXCR4-using viruses potentially 
emerge because of a reduced number of susceptible CCR5 + target 
cells or replication differences in various immune cells among the vari-
ants that use different co-receptors (Regoes and Bonhoeffer, 2005; 
Ribeiro et al., 2006). Indeed, individuals heterozygous for a 32 base </p>

<p>EBioMedicine 8 (2016) 237-247 </p>

<p>⁎ Corresponding author at: Boston University, School of Medicine, 650 Albany Street, 
Room 646, Boston, MA 02118-2518, United States. 
E-mail address: msagar@bu.edu (M. Sagar). </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ebiom.2016.04.040 
2352-3964/© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>EBioMedicine </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e b i o m e d i c i n e . c o m </p>

<p>pair deletion in CCR5 gene (CCRΔ32), who have lower levels of the CCR5 
receptor on their cells, have an increased likelihood of harboring 
CXCR4-using viruses compared to people with both wild-type alleles 
(Brumme et al., 2005; Henrich et al., 2014). Other non-mutually exclu-
sive hypotheses argue that CXCR4-utilizing variants arise because of 
random mutations, and these new viruses persist because declining 
adaptive and innate immune responses fail to clear the less fit dual-
tropic and/or X4 HIV-1. Previous studies have also suggested that neu-
tralizing antibody (nAb) pressure do not drive co-receptor switching 
(Trkola et al., 1998; Montefiori et al., 1998; Cecilia et al., 1998; Lacasse 
et al., 1998). Other investigations have argued that CXCR4-using viruses 
are highly neutralization susceptible, and the variants that can use the 
CXCR4 receptor only emerge after collapse of the humoral immune re-
sponse (Bunnik et al., 2007; Ho et al., 2007). Within weeks to months 
after HIV-1 acquisition, infected individuals develop nAbs against their 
autologous viruses, but the virus changes its env to escape this humoral 
response (Richman et al., 2003; Wei et al., 2003). Neutralization resis-
tance is frequently associated with modifications in and around the 
env variable portions, such as the env V1-V2 and V3 loop (Sagar et al., 
2006, Rong et al., 2009, Moore et al., 2009). In a cohort of HIV-1 subtype 
C (HIV-1C) infected individuals, we have previously shown that the env 
quasispecies diversity was significantly higher among individuals with 
DM as compared to strictly R5 viruses (Lin et al., 2012). In addition, 
we observed that all HIV-1C X4 as compared to R5 variants had either 
a 2 amino acid insertion prior to or basic amino acid substitutions in 
the generally invariant V3 loop crown. Together, these observations 
led us to hypothesize that difference in host antibody responses drive 
the greater env diversity observed in individuals with DM as compared 
to R5 virus populations, and the V3 loop genotypic signatures associated 
with X4 variants potentially modify neutralization susceptibility. We 
also postulated that the emergence of specific host antibodies in some 
but not all individuals force env sequence and structural changes. 
These env modifications influence co-receptor switching, and the con-
tinual presence of the specific host antibodies allows for the persistence 
of CXCR4-using viruses. In this study, we examined the role of nAbs on 
HIV-1C co-receptor switching. </p>

<p>2. Materials and Methods </p>

<p>2.1. Subjects </p>

<p>HIV-1 envs were isolated from plasma collected from women in the 
Mashi study previously shown to harbor DM virus (Thior et al., 2006). </p>

<p>2.2. Ethics Statement </p>

<p>The use of samples was approved by the institutional review boards 
at the Harvard School of Public Health, Partners Healthcare Systems, 
Boston University, and by the Botswana Ministry of Health. Investiga-
tors who analyzed the data had no contact with the women enrolled 
in the Mashi study, and thus all analysis was done in an anonymous 
fashion. </p>

<p>2.3. Viruses </p>

<p>The env expression fragments were generated as previously de-
scribed using bulk nested RT-PCRs (Lin et al., 2010). Briefly, RNA was 
isolated from 140 μl of individual plasma samples using QIAamp Viral 
RNA mini kit (Qiagen). For each sample, 1st round RT-PCR was per-
formed in triplicate to limit re-sampling (Liu et al., 1996). In order to 
minimize possible recombination associated with bulk PCR cloning 
(Salazar-Gonzalez et al., 2008; Keele et al., 2008), the RT-PCR reactions 
were performed with long extension times, limited cycle numbers, 
and use of proofreading polymerase (Lahr and Katz, 2009; Judo et al., 
1998; Meyerhans et al., 1990; Fang et al., 1998). Each reaction was 
done with 4 μl of the extracted viral RNA, SuperScript III RT/Platinum </p>

<p>Taq HiFi mix (ThermoFisher Scientific), and an extension time of 
7 min for each of the 20 cycles. These 1st round reactions were com-
bined and cloned using TOPO TA cloning (Invitrogen). A CMV promoter 
was attached to each individually isolated env clone using overlap PCR. 
All primers and amplification conditions have been described previous-
ly (Lin et al., 2010). All env sequences have been submitted to Genbank 
previously (accession numbers KF770248-KF770455, KX060565-
KX060578) (Lin et al., 2012). Pseudotyped viruses were generated by 
co-transfecting HEK293T cells with the CMV promoter PCR product at-
tached to the amplified env and an env deficient HIV-1 backbone 
(pNL4-3R-E-) plasmid expressing luciferase using the Fugene protocol 
(Roche Molecular Biochemicals). </p>

<p>2.4. Generation of Replication Competent Viruses </p>

<p>Replication competent recombinant viruses were generated with 
minor modifications from a previously described protocol 
(Chatziandreou et al., 2012). In the majority of cases, we found that 
full-length HIV-1C envs did not yield replication competent recombi-
nant viruses when incorporated into a NL4-3 (HIV-1B) or Q23-17 
(HIV-1A) background (Etemad et al., 2014; Pena-Cruz et al., 2013). Be-
cause the same envs yielded infectious pseudotypes, we assumed that 
incompatible cis interactions between the env tail and matrix protein 
accounted for the lack of infectious virus (Freed and Martin, 1995). To 
overcome this issue, we generated a plasmid pCMV-Q23-
PBS → LTRΔEnvEcto in which the env ecto-domain was replaced with 
a uracil biosynthesis (URA3) gene. Briefly, the env ecto-domain in 
pCMV-Q23-17-PBS → LTR was replaced with URA3 PCR product, 
which was amplified with the primers AGAAAGAGCAGAAG 
ACAGTGGCAATGATTAATTAAACCACCTTTTCAATTCATC and AAGCCT 
CCTACTATCATTATCTGATATAATTAAATTGAAGC from pRS316. The 
underlined portions correspond to primer sequences used to amplify 
env ectodomains (HXB2 env amino acid numbering 1-692) from sub-
ject samples, and the sequences in italics contain a PacI restriction site. 
Different env ecto-domains were shuttled into Q23 plasmid by 
transforming yeast with pCMV-Q23-PBS → LTRΔEnvEcto linearized 
with PacI and amplified env ecto-domain PCR products from subject 
samples. Replication competent viruses were generated by co-
transfecting HEK293T cells with a plasmid containing the subject env 
ecto-domain within pCMV-Q23-17-PBS → LTR and another plasmid 
with Q23-17 sequences from 5′ LTR to early portion of gag, pCMV-
Q23-17-LTR → Gag4 (Chatziandreou et al., 2012). All virus stocks were 
collected 48 h post transfection and titered on TZM-bl cells. </p>

<p>2.5. Reagents </p>

<p>The pNL4-3R-E-plasmid, U87 and TZM-bl cell lines, and VRC01 and 
10E8 monoclonal antibody (mAb) were obtained through the NIH AIDS 
Reagent Program. The 293T cells were obtained from American Type 
Culture Collection. The PGT128 and 447-52D mAbs were provided by 
International AIDS Vaccine Initiative and Dr. Susan Zolla-Pazner respec-
tively. The CD4-Ig was produced by gene synthesis and cloning into 
pcDNA3.1 (Invitrogen). </p>

<p>2.6. Co-receptor Phenotype </p>

<p>Co-receptor usage was determined by assessing entry capacity in the 
presence and absence of a co-receptor antagonist on U87 cells express-
ing CD4 and either CXCR4 or CCR5 as previously described (Lin et al., 
2010). To examine replication, U87 cells were incubated with virus 
and polybrene (8 μg/ml) for approximately 16 h. Post-incubation, cells 
were washed to remove virus. Culture supernatants were examined 
for p24 
gag antigen 5 days post-infection. In all cases NL4-3 (X4) and </p>

<p>YU-2 (R5) were used as controls. </p>

<p> 
N. Lin et al. / EBioMedicine 8 (2016) 237-247 </p>

<p>2.7. HIV-1 gp120 Expression and Purification </p>

<p>The codon-optimized gene encoding the R5 DM268M full-length 
gp120 was synthesized with a C-terminal Avi-6xHis tag and cloned 
into the pcDNA3.1(−) expression vector (Life Technologies). The X4 
V3 (DM268Y), differed from the R5 V3 (DM268M) by 5 amino acids; 
these modifications and the CD4 knock-out mutation D368R were intro-
duced by sequential site-directed mutagenesis using the TagMaster 
Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit (GM Biosciences) (Lin et al., 2012). The 
gp120 proteins were expressed by transient transfection using the 
expi293 system (Life Technologies). Six days post transfection, culture 
supernatants were harvested, filtered, and buffer-exchanged into PBS, 
and then purified using HisTALON Gravity Column Purification Kit 
(Clontech Laboratories). </p>

<p>2.8. Neutralization Assay </p>

<p>Infection of TZM-bl cells in the absence and presence of 2-fold serial 
dilutions was used to estimate the 50% inhibitory concentration (IC 50 ) 
as previously described (Etemad et al., 2009). All reported IC 50 s are 
mean estimates from a minimum of 3 independent assays. For virus/ 
plasma combinations that failed to achieve more than or equal to 50% 
inhibition at the highest tested dilution, they were assigned values of 
25, which is the midpoint between 0 and highest tested dilution 50. 
For virus/mAb combinations, a value equal to the highest tested concen-
tration was assigned when 50% inhibition could not be achieved. For the 
neutralization competition assays, plasma at various dilutions was incu-
bated with media alone or 500 μg/ml of gp120 for 1 h at 37°C. Virus was 
added, and wells were incubated for an additional 30 min. Then TZM-bls 
were added and infections were allowed to proceed for 48 h. Relative 
light units generated in the absence (positive wells) as compared to 
the presence of plasma were used to estimate % inhibition at specific 
plasma dilutions. For estimating inhibition in the presence DM268M-
R5V3 or DM268M-X4V3 gp120, the positive wells also contained the re-
spective gp120. In all cases, plasmas showed no neutralization capacity 
against NL4-3 pseudovirions with a vesicular stomatitis virus (VSV) en-
velope G protein (data not shown). Thus, observed neutralization was 
specific against the HIV-1 envelope. </p>

<p>2.9. ELISA </p>

<p>Plates were coated with gp120 antigen in PBS (pH 7.4) at 2 μg/ml 
overnight at 4°C, blocked with 1% BSA in PBS for 1 h at 37°C, and 
then incubated with serially diluted plasma or antibodies in blocking 
buffer for 1 h at 37°C. Horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated goat 
anti-human IgG Fc antibody (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories 
Inc.) was added in blocking buffer at 1:10,000 for 1 h at 37°C. Plates 
were washed between each step with 0.1% Tween 20 in PBS and devel-
oped with 3,3′,5,5′-tetramethylbenzidine (TMB) (Life Technologies) for 
20 min at room temperature. 1 M sulfuric acid was added to terminate 
the reaction and the plates were read at 450 nm. </p>

<p>2.10. Virus Passage </p>

<p>Viruses were passaged on CD4+ T cells in the presence of increasing 
concentrations of heat inactivated autologous plasma. Peripheral blood 
mononuclear cells (PBMCs) were isolated from HIV-1 negative blood 
donors' buffy packs using Ficoll-Hypaque density centrifugation meth-
od. CD4 + T cells were isolated from the PBMCs using magnetic bead 
isolation (Stem Cell Technologies). Around 2 × 10 
6 phytohemagglutinin </p>

<p>(PHA) and interleukin-2 (IL-2) activated CD4+ T cells were exposed to 
infectious virus in the presence of 20 μg/ml diethylaminoethyl (DEAE) 
dextran. Plasma was added after infections were established, generally 
two days after infection. Cultures were monitored for viral replication 
twice a week using a p24 
gag antigen assay (Perkin Elmer). The cultures </p>

<p>were fed twice weekly with activated CD4+ T cells, and plasma concen-
tration was doubled if virus showed continued growth. </p>

<p>2.11. Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>In the majority of cases, individual env variant's IC 50 s was a mean of 
3 independent assays. Comparisons within an individual were done 
using Wilcoxon rank sum test. For comparisons across multiple individ-
uals, the median IC 50 for strains with specific co-receptor usage was de-
termined for each subject. Inter-subject comparison were done using 
Kruskal Wallis test, and pair-wise inter-subject comparisons were 
done using the Wilcoxon rank sum test. The matched pairs Wilcoxon 
rank sum test was used when all individuals had variants with the co-
receptor usage being compared. All statistical analysis were done 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 8.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Stata Corporation.</rs>). All p-values are based on 
two sided tests. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Subjects </p>

<p>Previously, we determined the co-receptor usage in 148 HIV-1C in-
fected women in Botswana, and we found that 22 of them harbored 
DM populations while 126 had strictly R5 virus (Lin et al., 2011). Se-
quence characteristics and co-receptor use of individual envs were ex-
amined from 10 of the DM samples that showed relatively high 
CXCR4 usage by the phenotypic assay (Lin et al., 2012). Examination 
of individuals that harbored X4 variants were prioritized because X4 
as compared to co-existing R5 and R5X4 envs were demonstrated to 
harbor unique genotypic features (Lin et al., 2012). In addition, individ-
ual envs were not examined from DM samples that demonstrated low 
amount of CXCR4 usage in the co-receptor assay because it would likely 
require more extensive cloning to isolate CXCR4-using variants. Only 5 
from the original 148 samples fulfilled these criteria. We chose to exam-
ine an additional 2 samples with only co-circulating R5 and R5X4 vari-
ants. We assessed neutralization susceptibility of a median of 11 co-
circulating envs (range: 9-18) from these 7 different women (Table 1). 
The co-existing env populations consisted of X4 and R5 variants in 3 
(DM8, DM178, and DM268), R5X4 and R5 variants in 2 (DM146 and 
DM269), R5X4 and X4 variants in 1 (DM173), and all three co-receptor 
phenotypes in 1 (DM159) of the individuals. An additional 6 DM8 clones 
failed to yield other X4 envs. Intra-individual env variants with the 
different co-receptor usage were phylogenetically related, which ruled 
out contamination and super-infection (Fig. S1). Even though all 88 
primary envs examined in this study were generated using bulk-cloning 
PCR as described previously (Lin et al., 2010; Lin et al., 2012), all variants 
had unique sequences. Thus, we avoided re-sampling the same variant 
multiple times, which is a bias often associated with the bulk PCR cloning 
technique used to isolate the envs in this study (Salazar-Gonzalez et al., 
2008; Keele et al., 2008). </p>

<p>Table 1 
Subject demographics and patient characteristics. </p>

<p>Subject 
Plasma HIV 
(copies/ml) </p>

<p>CD4 count 
(cells/μl) </p>

<p>Previous ART </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Env variants </p>

<p>R5 
Dual 
X4 </p>

<p>DM8 
522,000 
43 
N 
10 
0 
1 
DM146 
653,000 
172 
N 
10 
8 
0 
DM159 
154,000 
116 
N 
5 
2 
3 
DM173 
1290 
316 
N 
0 
6 
3 
DM178 
230,000 
21 
Y 
8 
0 
6 
DM268 
333,000 
375 
Y 
5 
0 
9 
DM269 
10,600 
319 
Y 
9 
3 
0 </p>

<p>a Women were sampled either prior to or a minimum of 6 months after the discon-</p>

<p>tinuation of antiretroviral therapy (ART) because of virological failure. </p>

<p> 
N. Lin et al. / EBioMedicine 8 (2016) 237-247 </p>

<p>3.2. X4 Are Less Neutralization Susceptible to Contemporaneous Plasma </p>

<p>To assess neutralization sensitivity differences among 88 co-circulat-
ing variants with different observed co-receptor usage, we first exam-
ined susceptibility to contemporaneous autologous plasma. In 5 
individuals, X4 strains were less sensitive to contemporaneous autolo-
gous plasma as compared to co-existing R5 (DM8, DM178, DM268, 
DM159) or R5X4 (DM173) viruses (Fig. 1a-e). Indeed, in 3 individuals 
(DM8, DM178, and DM268), the X4 envs were not neutralized above 
50% at the highest tested plasma dilution (1:50) (Fig. 1a-c). These 
virus-plasma combinations were assigned a value of 25, which is the 
mid-point value between 0 and 50, for statistical comparisons. In 3 indi-
viduals (DM178, DM268, and DM173) differences were statistically sig-
nificant (p b 0.05, Wilcoxon rank sum test), while in the other 2 subjects 
(DM8 and DM159), limited number of envs with different co-receptor 
usage potentially limited the power to detect significant differences. In 
2 individuals (DM146 and DM269) co-circulating R5 and dual-tropic 
envs showed similar neutralization sensitivity (p N 0.05, Wilcoxon 
rank sum test) (Fig. 1f-g). Aggregate comparisons were done by esti-
mating a median IC 50 for each individual's envs that used different co-
receptor. In aggregate, neutralization IC 50 s to autologous contempora-
neous plasma was significantly different among R5, R5X4, and X4 envs 
(p = 0.03, Kruskal Wallis test). The median neutralization susceptibility 
to contemporaneous autologous plasma of the X4 viruses (median IC 50 : 
25.0, range: 25.0-140.7) was around 5 fold lower compared to R5 (me-
dian IC 50 : 136.0, range: 94.2-222.7, p = 0.03, Wilcoxon rank sum test) 
and R5X4 viruses (median IC 50 : 156.5, range: 135.2-160.8, p = 0.03, 
Wilcoxon rank sum test) (Fig. 1h). 
In preliminary data, we also found an HIV-1B infected individual also 
harbored X4 as compared to CCR5-using variants that were significantly 
less sensitive to neutralization by autologous contemporaneous plasma 
(Fig. S2). This suggests our observations are not specific to HIV-1C infec-
tions only. Thus, in every individual with isolated X4 viruses (n = 6), the 
X4 as compared to co-existing R5 and/or R5X4 variants had greater neu-
tralization resistance to autologous contemporaneous plasma (Figs. 1 
and S2). Previous studies have noted similar IC 50 fold changes among 
longitudinally collected viruses to sequential autologous plasma 
(Richman et al., 2003). In addition, the observed neutralization response 
against contemporaneous viruses in the individuals examined in this 
study is not necessarily unique because recent work shows that plasma 
and isolated antibodies neutralize some autologous contemporaneous </p>

<p>viruses to a similar extent, which subsequently provides pressure for 
envelope evolution (Moody et al., 2015). In aggregate, this suggests 
that the × X4 as compared to co-existing CCR5-using viruses have 
both statistical and biological meaningful differences in neutralization 
susceptibility. Thus, X4 variants are potentially neutralization escape 
variants to the antibodies present in the contemporaneous autologous 
plasma. </p>

<p>3.3. X4 Are More Resistant to Heterologous Pooled Plasma </p>

<p>We next hypothesized that X4 envs are escape variants from anti-
bodies often present in individuals that harbor only CCR5-using viruses. 
To examine this possibility, we compared sensitivity of X4 and R5 
strains to heterologous pooled R5 plasma, which was generated by 
pooling plasma from 5 women documented to harbor R5 viruses only 
(Lin et al., 2012). We examined 47 envs from the 4 individuals (DM8, 
DM159, DM178, and DM268) in which the median IC 50 against autolo-
gous contemporaneous plasma was lower for the X4 as compared to co-
circulating R5 strains. We did not examine variants from DM146, 
DM173, and DM269 because in these individuals we did not isolate 
co-existing R5 and X4 strains. In all 4 individuals, the X4 viruses demon-
strated decreased sensitivity to this pooled R5 plasma compared to the 
co-existing CCR5 utilizing viruses (Fig. 2a-d). Significant differences 
(p b 0.05, Wilcoxon rank sum test) were observed in 2 cases (DM178 
and DM268) but not in the other 2 individuals (DM8 and DM159) 
with a limited number of envs with different co-receptor usage. In ag-
gregate, X4 (median IC 50 : 161.7, range: 122.8-179.6) as compared to 
R5 (median IC 50 : 425.3, range: 174.5-684.8) viruses showed a statistical 
trend of around 3 fold greater neutralization resistance to the pooled R5 
plasma (p = 0.1, paired Wilcoxon rank sum test) (Fig. 2e). This suggests 
that X4 as compared to co-existing R5 viruses are less neutralization 
susceptible to antibodies commonly circulating in individuals that har-
bor only R5 variants. </p>

<p>3.4. X4 Variants Remain Sensitive to Antibodies Targeting env Non-co-re-
ceptor Binding Sites </p>

<p>It is possible that mutations in the X4 viruses compared to the R5 
variants leads to a "global" antigenic change, similar to some previously 
described strains (del Prete et al., 2009; Roederer et al., 2013). If the X4 
as compared to the R5 variants have an overall antigenic difference, they </p>

<p>Fig. 1. The X4 as compared to co-circulating R5 and R5X4 envs are more neutralization resistant to autologous contemporaneous plasma. (a-g) Figures show neutralization IC 50 s for R5 
(circles), dual-tropic (triangles), and X4 (boxes) viruses against autologous contemporaneous plasma. Symbols represent one of the 88 independent envs from the 7 subjects labeled above 
each graph. Y-axis shows the IC 50 against autologous contemporaneous plasma as reciprocal dilution. Figure h shows the aggregate comparisons in all subjects, and each symbol shows the 
median IC 50 s within a subject for envs with the defined co-receptor phenotype. In every case, the long line represents the median of the dot plots, and the whiskers show the interquartile 
range. Star indicates statistically significant difference (p b 0.05). The dashed line shows the highest tested plasma dilution (1:50). Symbols below the dotted lines are envs that were not 
neutralized by at least 50% at the highest tested plasma dilution. For statistical comparisons, these envs were assigned a midpoint value between 0 and 50. </p>

<p> 
N. Lin et al. / EBioMedicine 8 (2016) 237-247 </p>

<p>may have different neutralization susceptibility to antibodies targeting 
env regions not implicated in co-receptor binding. To explore this pos-
sibility, we assessed sensitivity to two broadly neutralizing antibodies 
(bnAbs), VRC01, which targets the CD4 binding site (CD4bs) (Wu et 
al., 2010, Zhou et al., 2010), and 10E8, which binds the membrane prox-
imal external region (MPER) (Huang et al., 2012). In individual subjects, 
the X4 as compared to R5 viruses demonstrated similar sensitivity to 
neutralization (p N 0.05, Wilcoxon rank sum test) to VRC01 (Fig. 3a-
d) and 10E8 (Fig. 3e-h). Although in some individuals the highest tested 
bnAb concentration failed to yield 50% inhibition, this lack of neutraliza-
tion was observed in both the X4 and co-existing R5 variants. In these 
cases, virus-antibody combination was assigned a value equivalent to 
the highest tested concentration for statistical comparisons. In aggre-
gate, the median VRC01 and 10E8 IC 50 of an individual's X4 and co-
existing R5 variants were not significantly different (p N 0.05, paired 
Wilcoxon rank sum test). Thus, the co-existing X4 and R5 variants dem-
onstrated equivalent sensitivity to antibodies that target env regions not 
involved in co-receptor binding, which suggests that changes that con-
fer co-receptor switching do not lead to overall structural change in CD4 
binding site or domains close to the membrane. Comparing sensitivity 
to other bnAbs that target unique sites, such as the V1-V2 loop or the 
interface between the trans-membrane domain and surface unit, will 
need to be examined to assess structural changes in other env regions. </p>

<p>3.5. Infected Hosts Develop Antibodies Against X4 Variants </p>

<p>A study using a simian-human immunodeficiency virus with a sub-
type B env (SHIV-1B) has suggested that CXCR4-using variants are ex-
quisitely neutralization sensitive, and these viruses potentially arise in </p>

<p>setting where there are limited nAb responses in the infected host (Ho 
et al., 2007). If CXCR4 viruses emerge after immunological collapse 
then infected hosts will potentially not be able to develop antibody re-
sponses against X4 variants over time. We assessed sensitivity to an au-
tologous plasma sample collected around 6 months after the time point 
at which the DM8 X4 and R5 variants were isolated to assess this notion. 
The DM8 X4 compared to the co-circulating R5 variants demonstrated 
similar sensitivity to plasma collected 6 month after env isolation (Fig. 
S3a). Importantly, all R5 and the one X4 env were more susceptible to 
the later compared to the contemporaneous plasma sample (p = 
0.008, paired Wilcoxon rank sum test) (Fig. S3b). Autologous plasma 
samples from later time-points were not available from other individ-
uals to further examine if infected hosts could generate nAbs against 
previously circulating envs after the emergence of DM virus popula-
tions. These observations suggest that subject DM8 with a DM virus 
population continues to develop humoral responses over time against 
previously co-circulating R5 and X4 variants. </p>

<p>3.6. Neutralization Susceptibility Differences Are Influenced by env V3 Loop 
Changes </p>

<p>Our results suggest that X4 variants are relatively insensitive to spe-
cific antibodies present in autologous plasma and heterologous antibod-
ies in individuals with only R5 circulating variants. We hypothesized 
that these antibodies potentially target the env V3 loop because the 
V3 loop is the primary determinant for co-receptor usage (Cann et al., 
1992). We compared sensitivity of co-existing X4 and R5 variants to 
the bnAb, PGT128, because V3 loop stem sequence partially influences 
susceptibility to this bnAb (Walker et al., 2011; Pejchal et al., 2011). In </p>

<p>Fig. 2. The X4 as compared to co-circulating R5 are more neutralization resistant to heterologous pooled R5 plasma. (a-d) Graphs show neutralization IC 50 s (reciprocal plasma dilution) for 
R5 (circles) and X4 (boxes) viruses against heterologous pooled R5 plasma for 4 subjects. Each symbol represents one of the 47 independent envs from the 4 individuals shown above the 
graph. Figure E shows the aggregate comparisons in the 4 subjects, and each symbol shows the median IC 50 s for the R5 or X4 envs within an individual. In every case, the long line 
represents the median of the dot plots with the whiskers showing the interquartile range. Star indicates statistically significant difference (p b 0.05). The dashed line shows the highest 
tested plasma dilution (1:50). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. The X4 variants do not have a "global" antigenic change. Neutralization IC 50 s for R5 (circles), dual-tropic (triangles), and X4 (boxes) viruses to VRC01 (a-d) and 10E8 (e-h). Y-axis 
shows the bnAb concentration in μg/ml. Dotted line shows the highest tested antibody concentration. For statistical comparisons, virus antibody combination that failed to yield N50% 
neutralization at the highest tested antibody concentration were assigned an IC 50 value equivalent to the highest tested antibody concentration. In every case, the long line represents 
the median of the dot plots with the whiskers showing the interquartile range. </p>

<p> 
N. Lin et al. / EBioMedicine 8 (2016) 237-247 </p>

<p>DM268, X4 viruses (median IC 50 : 0.14 μg/ml, range: 0.04-0.22) were 
N100 fold less neutralization susceptible to PGT128 compared to co-cir-
culating R5 (median IC 50 : 0.001 μg/ml, range: 0.001-0.02) variants 
(p = 0.003, Wilcoxon rank sum test) (Fig. 4a). In contrast, neutraliza-
tion sensitivity to PGT128 for the one DM8 X4 variant (IC 50 : 0.41 μg/ 
ml) was within the range for the co-circulating R5 variants (median 
IC 50 : 1.8 μg/ml, range: 0.37-3.67) (Fig. 4b). None of the DM159 and 
DM178 X4 and R5 variants were inhibited N 50% at the highest tested 
PGT128 concentration (5 μg/ml), and thus an IC 50 s could not be calculat-
ed for comparisons. 
To further examine the role of V3 loop in the observed neutralization 
differences among co-circulating R5 and X4 variants, we generated V3 
loop chimeric envs. In 3 subjects (DM8, DM159, and DM268) with doc-
umented differences in neutralization sensitivity among co-existing X4 
and R5 variants, we exchanged V3 loops between a R5 and X4 variant. 
The chimeric DM178 envs with V3 loop exchanges did not yield infec-
tious virus. Swapping the V3 loops resulted in co-receptor changes in 
every case other than in DM8 (Fig. 4c-e) (Lin et al., 2012). The chimeric 
envs with X4 V3s were less sensitive to pooled R5 heterologous plasma 
compared to the envs containing the R5 V3 loops in every case. The dif-
ferences, however, were relatively small especially compared to the sus-
ceptibility differences among the original envs. Furthermore, in both 
DM268 and DM8, introduction of an X4 V3 loop within the R5 back-
ground yielded a virus with greater resistance to PGT128 compared to 
the original env or the recombinant with a R5 V3 loop (Fig. 4f-g). In ag-
gregate, these results suggest that the V3 loop potentially influences the 
observed neutralization differences among co-circulating R5 and X4 
variants. 
ELISAs were used to further examine V3 directed antibody binding 
variation to co-existing DM268 X4 and R5 variants. We only assessed 
DM268 envs because of the observed sensitivity difference to bnAb, 
PGT128. We generated gp120 proteins based on the predicted amino 
acids in a DM268 R5 variant (clone M). One gp120 contained an R5 
V3, DM268-M-R5V3, and the other harbored an X4 V3 from clone Y, 
DM268-M-X4V3. Both contained a D368R mutation to avoid CD4 inter-
ference (Olshevsky et al., 1990). As expected, the CD4 binding site bnAb, 
VRC01, showed no binding to either gp120 because of the D368R muta-
tion (Fig. 5a). On the other hand, both gp120s showed relatively equiv-
alent weak binding to CD4-Ig (Fig. 5b), which is similar to what has been 
shown with other gp120s containing the D368R mutation (Jia et al., 
2016). The DM268-M-R5V3 gp120 as compared to DM268-M-X4V3, </p>

<p>however, showed markedly greater binding to PGT128 (Fig. 5c), V3 
loop crown antibody, 447-52D (Fig. 5d), and contemporaneous autolo-
gous serum (Fig. 5e) (Gorny et al., 1992). Although, 447-52D demon-
strated ELISA binding, this mAb was unable to neutralize any 
DM268M variant at the highest tested concentration (5 μg/ml) (data 
not shown). These ELISA results suggest that the DM268 plasma harbors 
anti V3 loop antibodies that preferentially bind R5 but not X4 envs. 
Neutralization competition experiments were carried out to assess if 
the presence anti V3 loop antibodies in the autologous plasma is respon-
sible for the differential neutralization of DM268 R5 and X4 variants. If 
anti V3 loop antibodies that preferentially bind R5 but not X4 envs 
were primarily responsible for neutralization susceptibility differences 
among DM268 X4 and R5 variants, it would be expected that gp120s 
with R5 but not X4 V3 would prevent autologous contemporaneous 
plasma from neutralizing the virus. In the presence of DM268-M-R5V3 
gp120 (reciprocal plasma dilution IC 50 : 132.1) neutralization of the 
DM268M virus required greater amount of plasma compared to in the 
presence of DM268-M-X4V3 gp120 (reciprocal plasma dilution IC 50 : 
168.3) or the absence of gp120 (reciprocal plasma dilution IC 50 : 
200.0) (Fig. 6). These estimated IC 50 differences, however, were not sta-
tistically significantly different. This suggests that even though the plas-
ma contains anti V3 loop antibodies that preferentially bind R5 but not 
X4 gp120s, these antibodies had a small impact in neutralizing a DM268 
R5 strain. </p>

<p>3.7. Emergence of CXCR4-using Virus With Serial Passage in Plasma </p>

<p>To understand if CXCR4-using variants emerge from R5 viruses as a 
consequence of nAb pressure, we independently passaged a neutraliza-
tion sensitive R5 variant from 3 different subjects (DM8, DM178, and 
DM268) in activated CD4+ T cells in the absence or presence of heat 
inactivated contemporaneous autologous plasma (Fig. 7a-c). While all 
the previous experiments used pseudovirions with full-length envs, 
replication competent recombinant viruses were used in these pas-
sages. These replication competent recombinant viruses incorporated 
an individual's neutralization sensitive R5 env ecto-domain rather 
than the full-length env. Incorporation of full-length envs within a het-
erologous HIV-1 backbone did not yield infectious virus. In all 3 cases, 
virus passaged in the presence as compared to the absence of autolo-
gous plasma yielded virus supernatants that were neutralization resis-
tant (Fig. 7d-f). Passage of DM268M R5 variant in the presence but </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Neutralization susceptibility differences among X4 and R5 viruses are influenced by env V3 loop. Figures a-b show mean IC 50 s (μg/ml) to PGT128 among co-circulating variants with 
different co-receptor usage in DM268 (a) and DM8 (b). Figures c-g show IC 50 against pooled R5 plasma (reciprocal dilution) (c-e) and PGT128 (μg/ml) (f-g) for the original R5 (white), 
original X4 (black), env with a R5 V3 loop in a X4 background (gray) or X4 V3 loop in a R5 background (checkers). In each graph, the subject is denoted above. Label below the x-axis 
denotes the env clone followed by the observed co-receptor usage in parenthesis. Star denotes significant p-value for the comparison (p b 0.05, Wilcoxon rank sum test). DM268 
chimeric env MYM was not infectious (Lin et al., 2012). </p>

<p> 
N. Lin et al. / EBioMedicine 8 (2016) 237-247 </p>

<p>not the absence of serially increasing amounts of contemporaneous au-
tologous plasma led to the emergence of a CXCR4-using virus (Fig. 8a-
b). The day 75 DM268 virus supernatant passaged in the presence as op-
posed to the absence of autologous plasma replicated in U87-CXCR4 
cells that lacked the CCR5 receptor (Fig. 8a). Replication decreased in 
the presence of CXCR4 inhibitor, AMD3100, suggesting that cell entry 
was mediated by engaging the CXCR4 co-receptor. CXCR4 usage was 
highly inefficient because day 75 plasma passaged DM268 virus super-
natant yielded nearly 10 fold less HIV-1 antigen (p24 
gag ) in the U87-</p>

<p>CXCR4 as compared to U87-CCR5 cells (Fig. 8b). Similar results were 
observed with day 68 DM268 virus supernatant passaged in the pres-
ence of autologous plasma (data not shown). In contrast, all other 
virus supernatants passaged either in the absence or presence of plasma 
infected U87-CCR5 cells but not U87-CXCR4 cells. 
We hypothesized that the day 75 DM268 virus stock passaged in the 
presence of plasma (DM268 + plasma-d75) contained a possible mix-
ture of R5, R5X4, and X4 viruses. To efficiently isolate the CCR5-versus 
CXCR4-using viruses in DM268 + plasma-d75, we examined viruses in 
the U87-CXCR4 and U87-CCR5 cell culture supernatants. We reasoned 
that the U87-CXCR4 and the U87-CCR5 cell culture supernatants 
should only contain CXCR4-and CCR5-utilizing viruses respectively. In-
terestingly, the culture supernatants from the U87-CCR5 and U87-
CXCR4 cells exposed to DM268 + plasma-d75 showed identical env 
bulk sequences. This suggests that passage in the presence of autologous 
plasma led to the emergence of a neutralization resistant R5X4 variant 
with relatively inefficient CXCR4 usage. Surprisingly, this R5X4 variant 
had an amino acid change at position 88 (HXB2 numbering), which in-
troduced a predicted asparagine (N) linked glycosylation site (PNGS) 
(Fig. S4). In contrast, passage in the absence of plasma generated virus 
stocks that contained a mixture of amino acids at 2 positions but was 
otherwise invariant from the starting input virus. Interestingly, all 
other R5 and X4 DM268 variants (n = 17) previously isolated from </p>

<p>this individual harbored the PNGS at position 88. Site directed mutagen-
esis could not be used to assess if this modification would change co-re-
ceptor usage in other strains because all other isolated R5 envs 
contained the position 88 PNGS. The effect of the position 88 change 
on co-receptor usage, however, is context dependent because none of 
the other previously isolated DM268 env variants with a position 88 
PNGS were able to use both the CCR5 and CXCR4 co-receptor for cell 
entry. These observations imply that passage in the presence of autolo-
gous plasma led to the emergence of a PNGS at position 88, which sub-
sequently conferred CXCR4 usage. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>This study demonstrates that X4 variants are more neutralization re-
sistant compared to R5 and R5X4 viruses and provides a potential bio-
logical mechanism for HIV-1 co-receptor switching. In multiple 
subjects, we show that co-existing X4 as compared to R5 variants are 
more resistant to antibodies present in autologous contemporaneous 
and heterologous pooled plasma from individuals with only R5 strains. 
This decreased neutralization sensitivity did not result from changes 
that led to a global antigenic change. Thus, this argues that X4 viruses 
are more resistant to certain antibodies, likely against the env V3 loop, 
generated by the infected individual. Furthermore, we show that pas-
sage of neutralization sensitive CCR5-using variants in the presence of 
increasing concentrations of autologous contemporaneous plasma was 
sufficient to force the evolution of a CXCR4-using virus from an R5 strain 
in 1 of 3 subjects. In aggregate, our studies suggest that humoral im-
mune pressure can drive the emergence of CXCR4-utilizing viruses in 
some individuals. 
Studies have suggested that dual-tropic strains evolve from R5 vari-
ants, and X4 viruses arise from the R5X4 strains (Pastore et al., 2004). It 
is unlikely that the emergence of a dual-tropic virus during the passage 
experiments occurred by chance because CXCR4-using variants were 
not detected in the absence of plasma and changes required for co-re-
ceptor switching are generally associated with diminished replication 
fitness (Pastore et al., 2004). The DM268 passage results were surprising 
because we observed no significant neutralization susceptibility differ-
ence to contemporaneous autologous plasma among co-existing R5 
and dual-tropic strains (Fig. 1). Although previous studies have demon-
strated that diverse glycosylation changes can render viruses neutrali-
zation resistant (Sagar et al., 2006, Wei et al., 2003), it remains unclear 
how the addition of PNGS at position 88 leads to low level CXCR4 
usage. It has been shown that co-circulating R5 and R5X4 variants 
often have the same predicted V3 loop sequence (Huang et al., 2007; 
Lin et al., 2012), and thus it possible that modifications in other env seg-
ments lead to a structural change that can influence co-receptor usage. 
Interestingly, DM viruses did not emerge in the other 2 cases (DM8 and 
DM178) even though their X4 as compared to R5 envs were more neu-
tralization resistant to autologous contemporaneous plasma. Our obser-
vations suggest that the passaged DM8 and DM178 env variants </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Co-circulating R5 and X4 viruses have different reactivity to anti-env V3 loop antibodies and autologous plasma. Figure a thru e show ELISA binding profiles of the DM268_D368R 
gp120 with either a R5 V3 loop (circle) or X4 V3 loop (square) to VRC01 (a), CD4-Ig (b), PGT128 (c), 447-52D (d), and autologous contemporary plasma (e). The y-axis shows the OD and 
the x-axis shows the antibody concentration or plasma dilution. </p>

<p>Fig. 6. gp120s with different env V3 loops fails to prevent neutralization. Percent inhibition 
observed in the absence or presence of DM268_D368R gp120 with R5 V3 or X4 V3. The y-
axis shows the percent inhibition and the x-axis shows the reciprocal plasma dilution. </p>

<p> 
N. Lin et al. / EBioMedicine 8 (2016) 237-247 </p>

<p>accommodated changes required for neutralization resistance to autol-
ogous plasma without co-receptor switching. Other R5 variants from 
these individuals, not examined in the passaging experiments, may ac-
quire the ability to use the CXCR4 receptor as they become resistant to 
autologous antibodies. 
The earliest studies implied that lab-adapted SI, presumably CXCR4-
using, strains were more neutralization sensitive compared to NSI-
CCR5-utilizing variants (Mascola et al., 1996; Montefiori et al., 1998; </p>

<p>D'Souza et al., 1997; Sawyer et al., 1994). Subsequent studies showed 
that compared to CCR5-utilizing strains primary as opposed to lab-
adapted CXCR4-using envs displayed a relatively similar range of neu-
tralization susceptibilities to some mAbs and unrelated heterologous 
plasma (Trkola et al., 1998; Montefiori et al., 1998; Cecilia et al., 1998; 
Lacasse et al., 1998). This led to the notion that nAbs are unlikely to be 
the major selection pressure that drives co-receptor switching. Our re-
sults also show that X4 and co-existing R5 variants have equivalent </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Passage in the presence of autologous contemporaneous plasma leads to neutralization resistant virus. Figure a thru c show passage of DM8 clone S (a), DM178 clone A (b), and 
DM268 clone M (c) in the absence (circle) or presence (square) of autologous contemporaneous plasma. In each graph, the x-axis shows the days post-infection. The left y-axis shows 
the estimated p24 concentration in the culture and the right y-axis shows contemporaneous autologous plasma dilution in the culture (triangles). Figures d thru f show neutralization 
susceptibility of passaged virus stock to contemporaneous autologous plasma. The y-axis shows the percent inhibition and the x-axis shows the reciprocal of the autologous plasma 
dilution. Any virus/plasma combination that did not show a positive inhibition value was assigned a % inhibition of 10% to improve visualization on the graph. Virus stocks passaged in 
the presence (square) or absence of (circle) of autologous plasma were from day 34 (DM8) (d), day 92 (DM178) (e), and day 75 (DM268) (f) post-infection. </p>

<p>Fig. 8. A CXCR4-using virus emerged with passage in the presence as opposed to the absence of autologous plasma in DM268. Replication in U87-CD4-CXCR4 (a) and U87-CD4-CCR5 (b) 
cells for day 34 (DM8), day 92 (DM178), and day 75 (DM268) virus stocks. The table below indicates whether the virus stock was from passage in the presence or absence of autologous 
plasma. The table also shows replication observed in the presence (white bars) or absence (black bars) of specific CXCR4 (AMD3100) and CCR5 (TAK779) inhibitors. Graphs also show 
replication of control viruses NL43 (X4) and YU-2(R5). Each bar shows standard error from 2 independent measurements. Dotted line shows the limit of detection (25 pg/ml). 
Cultures in which the p24 antigen level was below the limit of detection were assigned a value midpoint between 0 and 25 to improve visualization on the graph. </p>

<p> 
N. Lin et al. / EBioMedicine 8 (2016) 237-247 </p>

<p>sensitivity to antibodies targeting env domains not involved in co-re-
ceptor binding. More recent investigations with SHIV-1B and HIV-1B in-
fected subjects argue that relatively neutralization sensitive CXCR4-
utilizing variants emerge later in disease after HIV-1 induced immuno-
logical damage has led to a compromised humoral immune response 
(Bunnik et al., 2007; Ho et al., 2007). We, however, observed no case 
in which X4 or R5X4 as compared to co-circulating R5 envs were signif-
icantly more neutralization susceptible to autologous contemporaneous 
plasma, even though we sampled more envs from each subject and ex-
amined a greater number of individuals. Furthermore, the previous 
human study examined PBMC passaged variants (Bunnik et al., 2007), 
which may have led to the different results because passaging virus in 
PBMCs significantly impacts its neutralization properties in a unique 
manner for each virus antibody combination (Etemad et al., 2015; 
Provine et al., 2012). 
Our results also differ from the previous human study (Bunnik et al., 
2007) potentially because we examined HIV-1C versus HIV-1B infected 
individuals. Our preliminary results, however, suggest this is not the 
case (Fig. S2). While HIV-1C constitutes the majority of worldwide in-
fections, emergence of CXCR4 usage occurs at a lower frequency com-
pared to HIV-1B (Lin et al., 2011; Ataher et al., 2012). Reasons for the 
difference in incidence remain uncertain. Although it has been reported 
that CCR5 and CXCR4-using viruses preferentially infect memory and 
naïve T cells respectively (Davenport et al., 2002; Blaak et al., 2000), 
there is no evidence that this preference differs among HIV-1B versus 
HIV-1C variants (Cashin et al., 2014; Ribeiro et al., 2006). While, it is 
known that the CCR5Δ32 allele frequency is higher among Europeans 
than Africans (Galvani and Novembre, 2005), the density of the CCR5 
receptor on CD4 + T cells is not significantly different among people 
with European ancestry who constitute the majority of HIV-1B infec-
tions versus those with African heritage who are predominantly infect-
ed with HIV-1C (Picton et al., 2012). Thus, the higher incidence of DM 
virus population in HIV-1B as compared to HIV-1C infected individuals 
is unlikely because of lower availability of appropriate CCR5 expressing 
target cells. It has been suggested that HIV-1B and HIV-1C envs have 
structural differences, especially in the V3 loop (Patel et al., 2008). Po-
tentially in response to these env structural differences, HIV-1C infected 
individuals develop antibodies targeting the C3-V4 region while those 
with HIV-1B generate responses against the V1-V2 domain and the 
base of the V3 loop (Rong et al., 2009, Moore et al., 2008; Tang et al., 
2011). Interestingly, the main determinants for co-receptor switching 
are located in the V1 to V3 domains (O'Brien et al., 1990; Chesebro et 
al., 1991; Shioda et al., 1992; Groenink et al., 1993; Fouchier et al., 
1995). Greater prevalence of anti-V1-V2 or V3 loop antibodies may cor-
relate with the greater frequency of DM virus populations in HIV-1B as 
compared to HIV-1C infected individuals. 
While most HIV-1 infected individuals develop nAbs against their 
circulating variants and viruses escape this humoral pressure, there 
are potentially two important factors that explain why CXCR4-
using variants do not evolve in everyone. First, CXCR4-utilizing vi-
ruses will not emerge if the circulating env variants cannot accom-
modate changes required for CXCR4 usage regardless of the 
selection pressure. Both laboratory and human studies have docu-
mented that some HIV-1 env variants do not evolve to use the 
CXCR4 receptor even in setting where they are exposed to CCR5 in-
hibitors (Westby et al., 2007; Marozsan et al., 2005; Tsibris et al., 
2008). Second, similar to the observation that some but not all HIV-
1 infected individuals develop cross-neutralizing antibodies (Doria-
Rose et al., 2009), co-receptor switching due to humoral selection 
may only occur in people that develop certain types of antibodies 
over the course of infection. Thus, in people that do not generate an-
tibodies with the appropriate specificity neutralization escape may 
occur without changes in co-receptor usage. Unfortunately, we did 
not have access to live PBMCs to generate mAbs from these individ-
uals, which would have allowed us to map the epitope for the anti-
bodies that neutralize R5 but not co-existing X4 variants. </p>

<p>Interestingly, treatment of HIV-1 infected humanized mice with 
anti-V3 loop bnAb, PGT128, but not anti-CD4bs bnAb, 45-46GW, has 
been predicted to select for a significantly higher proportion of 
CXCR4-using variants (Pfeifer et al., 2014). Furthermore, CXCR4 as com-
pared to CCR5-using variants are overrepresented among variants resis-
tant to env V1-V2 directed bnAbs, PG9 and PG16. Thus similar to our 
suggestions, this investigation implies that antibodies directed against 
the env variable loops potentially select for neutralization resistant 
CXCR4-utilizing variants (Pfeifer et al., 2014). One study has argued 
that this may also be the case during longitudinal HIV-2 infection 
(Marcelino et al., 2012). Even though our conclusions are based on ob-
servations from a small number of individuals, and in some cases only 
a limited number of envs with different co-receptor phenotype, our 
studies strongly support the idea that X4 variants are neutralization es-
cape variants. 
In contrast to the previously proposed mechanisms that lead to co-
receptor switching, such as random mutations, waning immunity, 
and/or decreasing number of CCR5+ T cells, our observations suggest 
that antibody pressure selects for CXCR4-utilizing variants (Regoes 
and Bonhoeffer, 2005). It is likely that in some but not necessarily all in-
dividuals that eventually develop CXCR4-using viruses antibodies force 
env structural changes that directly influence co-receptor switching. 
Continual presence of these humoral responses eventually leads to the 
emergence of X4 variants resistant to these and other host generated 
anti V3 antibodies. This new biological mechanism for co-receptor 
switching has a number of important implications. It is generally agreed 
that presence of CXCR4-using variants leads to faster CD4 decline and 
earlier onset of AIDS (Koot et al., 1993; Richman and Bozzette, 1994; 
Connor et al., 1997), although the causal link is unclear. Our studies 
would argue that an infected individual's humoral immune response 
leads to the emergence of CXCR4-utilizing variants, which results in 
an adverse outcome. Thus, our observations imply that CXCR4-using 
variants cause and are not a result of decreasing immunity. Importantly, 
this suggests that in some individuals, the humoral immune response 
against their autologous virus worsens infection outcome. Although an-
tibodies have been suggested to adversely affect disease progression in 
other viral infections, notably dengue and influenza, no previous study 
has implied this for HIV-1 (Halstead and O'Rourke, 1977; Khurana et 
al., 2013). In addition, in contrast to dengue or influenza where antibod-
ies enhance entry of the infecting virus into host cells, our studies sug-
gest a mechanism where antibodies force phenotypic changes in 
replicating variants to expand the cellular tropism. Finally, our results 
have implications for proposed strategies of using bnAbs as prophylaxis, 
treatment, or cure (Caskey et al., 2015; Lynch et al., 2015). Our results 
and previous studies suggest that specific antibodies may be less potent 
against CXCR4-utilizing variants, which may select for their emergence 
in settings where antibodies are unable to fully inhibit virus replication 
(Pfeifer et al., 2014). Thus, the bnAbs selected for immunotherapy will 
need to be evaluated carefully to ensure that they do not promote the 
emergence of CXCR4-using strains, which can accelerate disease pro-
gression among infected individuals. </p>

<p>Funding Sources </p>

<p>This project was supported by NIH grants AI081545 (NL) and 
AI122209 (MS) and BU Pilot Grant (MS). No author received compensa-
tion from a pharmaceutical company or other agency for completion of 
this manuscript. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest Statement </p>

<p>There are no conflicts of interest associated with this study. The 
funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, deci-
sion to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </p>

<p> 
N. Lin et al. / EBioMedicine 8 (2016) 237-247 </p>

<p>Author Contributions </p>

<p>NL, XW, DRK, and MS designed the study. NL, OG, CB, LR, BE, and HL 
performed all the experiments. SL, ME, and SM oversaw the original trial 
and sample collection. MS wrote the paper with input from co-authors. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We would like to thank all Mashi trial participants, without whom 
this study would not have been possible. </p>

<p>Appendix A. Supplementary Data </p>

<p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at http://dx. 
doi.org/10.1016/j.ebiom.2016.04.040. </p>



<p> 
N. Lin et al. / EBioMedicine 8 (2016) 237-247 </p>



<p> 
N. Lin et al. / EBioMedicine 8 (2016) 237-247 </p>

</text></tei>