<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4389529" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Objective: To establish the determinants of the peak VO 2 in 
heart transplant recipients. 
Methods: Patient's assessment was performed in two 
consecutive days. In the first day, patients performed the heart 
rate variability assessment followed by a cardiopulmonary 
exercise test. In the second day, patients performed a resting 
echocardiography. Heart transplant recipients were eligible 
if they were in a stable condition and without any evidence of 
tissue rejection diagnosed by endomyocardial biopsy. Patients 
with pacemaker, noncardiovascular functional limitations such 
as osteoarthritis and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease 
were excluded from this study. 
Results: Sixty patients (68% male, 48 years and 64 months 
following heart transplantation) were assessed. Multivariate 
analysis selected the following variables: receptor's gender 
(P=0.001), receptor age (P=0.049), receptor Body Mass Index 
(P=0.005), heart rate reserve (P&lt;0.0001), left atrium diameter 
(P=0.016). Multivariate analysis showed r=0.77 and r2=0.6 with 
P&lt;0.001. Equation: peakVO 2 =32.851 -3.708 (receptor gender) -
0.067 (receptor age) -0.318 (receptor BMI) + 0.145 (heart rate 
reserve) -0.111 (left atrium diameter). </p>

<p>Conclusion: The determinants of the peak VO 2 in heart 
transplant recipients were: receptor sex, age, Body Mass 
Index, heart rate reserve and left atrium diameter. Heart rate 
reserve was the unique variable positively associated with 
peak VO 2 . This data suggest the importance of the sympathetic 
reinnervation in peak VO 2 in heart transplant recipients. </p>

<p>Descriptors: Heart Transplantation. Exercise. Exercise 
Tolerance. </p>

<p>Resumo 
Objetivo: Estabelecer os determinantes do VO 2 pico em 
transplantados de coração. 
Métodos: Avaliação do paciente foi realizada em dois 
dias consecutivos. No primeiro dia, os pacientes realizaram 
a avaliação da variabilidade da frequência cardíaca seguida 
de um teste de esforço cardiopulmonar. No segundo dia, 
os pacientes realizaram ecocardiografia de repouso. Os 
transplantados foram elegíveis se estivessem em uma 
condição estável e sem qualquer evidência de rejeição 
diagnosticada por biópsia endomiocárdica. Pacientes com 
marca-passo, limitações funcionais não cardiovasculares, </p>



<p>Braz J Cardiovasc Surg | Rev Bras Cir Cardiovasc </p>

<p>Braz J Cardiovasc Surg 2015;30(1):9-15 
Carvalho VO, et al. -Determinants of peak VO 2 in heart transplant recipients </p>

<p>Heart transplantation is a worldwide procedure indicat-
ed to patients with refractory heart failure. It is well known 
that heart transplant improves patient's survival, quality of 
life and exercise capacity, when compared to pre-transplant 
condition 
[1,2] . 
Although heart transplant recipients have an exercise ca-
pacity greater than before the procedure, it is known that the 
physical capacity restoration to normal levels does not al-
ways occur 
[1,2] . This is attributed to physical deconditioning 
resulting from previous heart failure 
[3] , a low chronotropic 
response (as a result of a cardiac denervation, also accessed 
by heart rate variability) 
[4] and, in many cases, impairment 
in cardiac function after transplantation 
[2] . The cardiac sys-
tolic function of the transplanted heart seems to be normal 
in most patients, while diastolic dysfunction appears to be 
present in most of the transplanted heart. Diastolic dysfunc-
tion was recently identified as one of the factors that seem to 
influence negatively the maximal and submaximal exercise 
capacity in heart transplant recipients 
[5,6] . Despite this, little 
is known about the determinants of exercise capacity in heart 
transplant recipients. 
The aim of this study was to establish the determinants of 
the peak VO 2 in heart transplant recipients. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Study design 
This study was performed in a tertiary cardiology hospital 
in Brazil. Patient's assessment was performed in two con-</p>

<p>tais como osteoartrite e doença pulmonar obstrutiva crônica 
foram excluídos deste estudo. 
Resultados: Sessenta pacientes (68% do sexo masculino, 48 
anos e 64 meses após o transplante cardíaco) foram avaliados. 
A análise multivariada selecionou as seguintes variáveis: </p>

<p>sexo (P=0,001), idade (P=0,049), Índice de Massa Corporal 
(P=0,005), frequência cardíaca de reserva (P&lt;0,0001), diâmetro 
do átrio esquerdo (P=0,016), variáveis do receptor. A análise 
multivariada mostrou r=0,77 e r2=0,6, com P&lt;0,001. Equação: 
VO 2 =32,851 -3,708 (sexo receptor) -0,067 (idade receptor) -
0,318 (IMC receptor) + 0,145 (frequência cardíaca de reserva) 
-0,111 (diâmetro de átrio esquerdo). 
Conclusão: Os determinantes do pico de VO 2 em 
transplantados de coração foram: sexo receptor, idade, Índice 
de Massa Corporal, frequência cardíaca de reserva e diâmetro 
do átrio esquerdo. A frequência cardíaca de reserva foi a única 
variável positivamente associada com o pico de VO 2 . Estes 
dados sugerem a importância da reinervação simpática no pico 
de VO 2 em transplantados de coração. </p>

<p>Descritores: Transplante de Coração. Exercício. Aptidão Física. </p>

<p>Abbreviations, acronyms &amp; symbols </p>

<p>BMI 
Body mass index 
BNP 
B-type Natriuretic Peptide 
DT 
Deceleration time 
ECA 
Angiotensin conversor enzyme inhibitors 
IVRT 
Isovolumic relaxation time 
LF/HF 
Low/high frequency domain in heart rate variability 
RRi 
R-R intervals 
VO 2 
Oxygen consumption </p>

<p>secutive days. In the first day, patients performed the heart 
rate variability assessment followed by a cardiopulmonary 
exercise test. In the second day, patients performed a resting 
echocardiography. </p>

<p>Study population 
Heart transplant recipients were eligible if they were in a 
stable condition (for, at least, 3 months) and without any evi-
dence of tissue rejection diagnosed by endomyocardial biopsy. 
Patients with pacemaker, noncardiovascular functional limita-
tions such as osteoarthritis and chronic obstructive pulmonary 
disease were excluded from this study. Patients were recruited 
from a tertiary cardiology hospital from September 2010 to 
November 2011. Subjects' characteristics are listed in Table 1. 
This protocol was approved by the Ethical Committee of 
our institution. All patients provided informed consent prior 
to participation. </p>

<p>Variables considered to be potentially associated with 
peak VO 2  We considered to be potentially associated with peak 
VO 2 as follows: donor and recipient age and body mass in-
dex (BMI), etiology of heart failure before transplantation 
(Chagas and non-Chagas), recipient heart rate reserve, gen-
der, percentage of age-predicted peak heart rate, percentage 
of heart rate drop in the second minute of recovery in the car-
diopulmonary test, left atrium diameter, cold ischemia time, 
time following heart transplantation, resting heart rate, VE/ 
VCO 2 slope, right ventricle diameter, left ventricle diastolic 
diameter, left ventricle ejection fraction, E/E' ratio and low/ 
high frequency domain in heart rate variability (LF/HF). </p>



<p>Braz J Cardiovasc Surg | Rev Bras Cir Cardiovasc </p>

<p>Braz J Cardiovasc Surg 2015;30(1):9-15 
Carvalho VO, et al. -Determinants of peak VO 2 in heart transplant recipients </p>

<p>Table 1. Characterization of study participants. </p>

<p>Variables 
Etiology: 
Chagas (%) 
Non-Chagas (%) 
Men (%) 
Recipients age (years) 
Donors age (years) 
Donors weight (kg) 
Recipients weight (kg) 
Donors height (cm) 
Recipients height (cm) 
Ischemic time (min) 
Recipients BMI (Kg/m 
2 ) 
Donors BMI (Kg/m 
2 ) 
Time following heart transplant (months) 
Resting heart rate (bpm) 
Recipients heart rate reserve (bpm) 
% of age-predicted peak heart rate 
% of heart rate drop in the second minute of recovery 
Left atrium diameter 
Cold ischemia time (min) 
VE/VCO 2 slope 
Right ventricle diameter (mm) 
Left ventricle diastolic diameter (mm) 
Left ventricle ejection fraction (%) 
E/E' ratio 
LF/HF 
Medication: 
Cyclosporine 
Diuretics 
ACE inhibitors (enalapril) 
Angiotensin receptor antagonist (losartan) 
Corticosteroids (prednisone) 
Azathioprine 
Mycophenolate 
Tacrolimus 
Sirolimus 
Everolimus 
Calcium channel blocker (diltiazem) 
Ezetimibe 
Simvastatin 
Hydralazine 
Metformin 
Fluoxetine 
Gabapentin 
Olanzapine 
Topiramate 
Bromazepam 
Insulin </p>

<p>Number of patients (%), dose(mg/day) </p>

<p>45% 
55% 
68% 
48±15 
31±11 
76±9 
68±13 
176±7 
166±10 
206±115 
25±4 
25±2 
64±54 
82±12 
49±17 
77±12 
8±8 
44±10 
207±115 
30±6 
22±3 
48±4 
62±5 
6.8±2.3 
6.9±8.9 </p>

<p>71%, 174±58 mg/day 
8.3% 
10%, 23±14 mg/day 
10%, 62±31 mg/day 
30%, 5.2±3.4 mg/day 
30%, 76±25 mg/day 
37%, 1096±422 mg/day 
25%, 7±4 mg/day 
1.6%, 1 mg/day 
3.3%, 1±0.35 mg/day 
58%, 126±71 mg/day 
1.6%, 10 mg/day 
68.3%,11.4±4.4 mg/day 
6.6%, 144±116 mg/day 
6.6%,1700±00 mg/day 
3.3%, 32±11 mg/day 
1.6%, 400 mg/day 
5%, 10 mg/day 
3.3%, 125±106 mg/day 
5%, 3 mg/day 
7.5%, 69±53 mg/day </p>

<p>BMI=Body mass index, ECA=Angiotensin conversor enzyme inhibitors. LF/HF=Low/high frequency domain in 
heart rate variability </p>



<p>Braz J Cardiovasc Surg | Rev Bras Cir Cardiovasc </p>

<p>Braz J Cardiovasc Surg 2015;30(1):9-15 
Carvalho VO, et al. -Determinants of peak VO 2 in heart transplant recipients </p>

<p>Cardiopulmonary exercise test 
All patients were asked to refrain from both strenuous 
physical activity and the consumption of any stimulants (e.g., 
coffee, tobacco, alcohol) for 24h prior to the cardiopulmo-
nary exercise test. Patients' last meal was ingested at least 2h 
before the test. Heart transplant recipients underwent the test 
on a programmable treadmill (TMX425 Stress Treadmill; 
TrackMaster, Newton, KS, USA) in a temperature-controlled 
room (21-23°C) between 10-12am with a standard 12-lead 
continuous ECG monitor (CardioSoft 6.5; GE Medical Sys-
tems IT, Milwaukee, WI, USA). Blood pressure monitoring 
was performed by an automatic device. Resting heart rate was 
considered the 20-min average in a supine position. Minute 
ventilation, oxygen uptake, carbon dioxide output and other 
cardiopulmonary variables were acquired breath-by-breath 
by a computerized system (Vmax Encore29; SensorMedics, 
Yorba Linda, CA, USA). 
Metabolic data were computed as the mean of the final 
30 s of the resting period, whereas peak of VO 2 and peak 
heart rate were the mean values of the final 30 s of effort 
before exhaustion. The respiratory exchange ratios were re-
corded as the averaged samples obtained during each stage 
of a modified Naughton protocol. A satisfactory cardiopul-
monary exercise test was characterized by a peak of respira-
tory exchange ratio&gt;1.05 and symptoms of maximum effort. 
Heart rate reserve [bpm] was defined as maximum heart rate 
achieved in the cardiopulmonary exercise test -average of 
10-min resting heart rate in the supine position. Heart rate 
recovery was assessed during the first and second minutes 
after cardiopulmonary exercise test. </p>

<p>Echocardiography 
The assessment followed the recommendations of the 
American Society of Ecocardiography 
[7] . We used a com-
mercially available equipment, model IE 33, Philips Medical 
Systems, Andover, MA, USA. The acquired data considered 
bidimensional echocardiography, pulsed Doppler, continu-
ous wave Doppler, tissue Doppler and color flow mapping. 
It was obtained at least three measurements of each echo-
cardiographic variable and the average was considered. We 
analyzed: left ventricle diameters and volumes, left ventricle 
ejection fraction (Simpson's rule), left ventricle mass index, 
left ventricle diastolic assessment (pulsed Doppler of mitral 
inflow and the study of the flow of pulmonary veins and Tis-
sue Doppler). Thus, we analyzed with pulsed Doppler, E and 
A waves, E/A ratio, deceleration time (DT), isovolumic re-
laxation time (IVRT), systolic component of the pulmonary 
venous flows (S wave), diastolic component of the pulmo-
nary venous flow (D wave), S/D ratio. The analysis with 
tissue Doppler was obtained in apical four and two chambers 
with sample volume of 1 to 2 mm. It was checked to the max-
imum rate of myocardial displacement at the beginning and 
end of the diastole (E' and A' wave respectively) and during </p>

<p>systole (S' wave) at the septal ring, side ring, bottom ring, 
front ring of right ventricle. Measurement of E/E´ratio was 
performed in the left ventricular annulus, from the basal sep-
tal and lateral segments (considered mean values). </p>

<p>Heart rate variability 
Experimental protocol: All the heart transplant recipients 
remained at rest for 10 minutes on the supine position and 
were instructed to breathe spontaneously. Then, instanta-
neous R-R intervals (RRi) were recorded for 10 min with a 
digital telemetry system, consisting of a transmitter placed 
on the patient's chest and a HR monitor (Polar 
 RS800CX; 
Polar Electro Oy, Kempele, Finland) This system detects 
ventricular depolarization, corresponding to the R wave on 
the electrocardiogram, at a sampling rate of 500 Hz, which 
had been previously validated 
[8] . The signals were transmit-
ted to a receiver and then to a computer for subsequent anal-
ysis. Data analysis: The RRi sequence of length n=256 beats 
was selected for each subject. The length of greatest stability 
was chosen from the central region of the time series. The 
mean and variance of the RRi were also calculated. HRV 
spectral analysis: The HRV frequency domain analysis was 
performed with an autoregressive model 
[9,10] , on previously 
selected RRi sequences. Two main spectral components were 
considered: low frequency (LF -from 0.04 to 0.15 Hz) and 
high frequency (HF -from 0.15 to 0.50 Hz) that represent 
the sympathetic and vagal modulations, respectively </p>

<p>[11]   . The 
spectral components are reported as normalized units (LFun 
and HFun) and LF/HF ratio. Normalization consisted of di-
viding the power of a given spectral component (HF or LF) 
by the total power minus the power below 0.04 Hz, and mul-
tiplying the ratio by 100.9 All patients presented a respiratory 
rate in the frequency range of HF band of HRV. </p>

<p>Current medication intake 
Medication profile is shown in Table 1. Patients took an-
giotensin conversor enzyme inhibitors, losartan and isosor-
bide 5-mononitrate two times per day, one half of the daily 
dose in the morning (9:00 am) and the other half at night 
(9:00 pm). Diuretics were taken in the morning (9:00 am). 
All heart transplant recipients were receiving immunosup-
pressive therapy two times per day, one half of the daily dose 
in the morning and the other half at night. Antihypertensive 
drugs were taken, most of the times, in the morning. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Data are presented as mean and standard deviation. We 
evaluated the association of the variables collected in the 60 
selected patients. For this, we used univariate analysis to se-
lect the variables to be used in the multivariate model. For 
the univariate analysis, a significance level of less than 20% 
(P&lt;0.20) was considered. In multivariate analysis, the non-
significant variables were excluded from the model (manual-</p>



<p>Braz J Cardiovasc Surg | Rev Bras Cir Cardiovasc </p>

<p>Braz J Cardiovasc Surg 2015;30(1):9-15 
Carvalho VO, et al. -Determinants of peak VO 2 in heart transplant recipients </p>

<p>ly, one at a time) following the criterion of greater "P" val-
ue. The model was determined when all the variables were 
presented with a significance level less than 5% (P&lt;0.05). 
The dependent variable used was the peak VO 2 
[1,2,5] . After the 
analysis, we established an equation with variables associat-
ed with peak VO 2 . 
For all statistical analyzes, we used <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> (Chicago IL, 
USA) version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.0</rs>. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Participants 
From 176 heart transplant recipients alive in our service, 
109 were not found by phone calls or lived in another city 
that prevented the realization of the protocol. Seven patients 
were excluded due to refusal, pacemaker or sequel of stroke 
(Figure 1). Sixty patients (68% male, 48 years and 64 months 
following heart transplantation) were assessed (Table 1). </p>

<p>Multivariate analysis selected the following variables: re-
ceptor's gender (P=0.001), receptor age (P=0.049), receptor 
BMI (P=0.005), heart rate reserve (P&lt;0.0001), left atrium di-
ameter (P=0.016). Multivariate analysis showed r=0.77 and 
r2=0.6 with P&lt;0.001. 
Equation derived from the multivariate analysis: peak 
VO 2 =32,851 -receptor gender (3,708) -receptor age (0,067) 
-receptor BMI (0,318) + heart rate reserve (0,145) -left atri-
um diameter (0,111) 
Considering: peak VO 2 in mL/Kg/min, gender (0=male 
and 1=female), age in years, BMI in Kg/m 
2 , heart rate reserve 
in beats per minute and left atrium diameter in millimeters. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The main finding of this study was that peak VO 2 of heart 
transplant recipients was determined by receptor gender, age, 
BMI, heart rate reserve and left atrium diameter. 
Our study is the first one to investigate the determinants 
of peak VO 2 in heart transplant recipients using variables that 
are non-invasive and easy to be collected in clinical practice. 
In our study, we observed that the peak VO 2 was nega-
tively associated with gender, BMI and age of the recipient 
and the diameter of the left atrium of the allograft. Of these, 
gender and BMI seemed to be the determinants more strong-
ly associated with exercise capacity. Moreover, the heart rate 
reserve was the unique variable positively associated to peak 
VO 2 . 
Our data strongly suggest that the sympathetic reinnerva-
tion is the main variable that positively influences peak VO 2 
in heart transplant recipients. Nevertheless, the parasym-
pathetic reinnervation does not seem to influence the exer-
cise capacity in heart transplant recipients. Previous studies 
showed that the parasympathetic reinnervation in adults is 
not consistent and may occur only from 5 to 10% of cases. 
Moreover, the sympathetic reinnervation occurs much more 
frequently and is related to exercise capacity in heart trans-
plant recipients from 50 to 60% of cases in 3 years 
[1,12,13] . The 
study by Bernardi et al. 
[14] showed that exercise training can 
improve cardiovascular control in heart transplant recipients. 
The negative influence of BMI, age and gender in exer-
cise capacity is already well established in exercise physiol-
ogy field. It is known that women have lower peak VO 2 than 
men, as well as fatter people compared to skinny and older 
people compared to younger, when we keep all other vari-
ables (such as exercise training levels) constant 
[15] . 
A relatively new data appeared in our research: the negative 
influence of the left atrium diameter in peak VO 2 in heart trans-
plant recipients. The study by Abdul-Waheed et al. 
[16] showed 
that the left atrium of adult heart transplant recipients increased 
in one year of follow-up. Moreover, this study showed an in-
verse association between left atrium and peak VO 2 . The authors 
hypothesized that the surgical scar could be negatively influ-</p>

<p>Fig.1 -Patients flow throughout the study. </p>

<p>Outcome data/main results 
Univariate analysis selected the following variables: re-
ceptor's age (P=0.042), receptor's BMI (P=0.056), heart 
rate reserve (P&lt;0.0001), percentage of age-predicted peak 
heart rate (P=0.052), percentage of heart rate drop in the 
second minute of recovery in the cardiopulmonary exercise 
test (P=0.067), slope VE/VCO 2 (0.115), left atrium diameter 
(P=0.028), right ventricular diameter (P=0.079), E/E' ratio 
(0.144), cold ischemia time (P=0.15), donor's age (P=0.022), 
LF/HF (P=0.18) and receptor's sex (P=0.003). The following 
variables were withdrawn from multivariate analysis model 
(in order of withdrawal): slope VE/VCO 2 (P=0.957), per-
centage of heart rate drop in the second minute of recovery 
in the cardiopulmonary exercise test (P=0.937), percentage 
of age-predicted peak heart rate (P=0.771), right ventricle di-
ameter (P=0.456), LF / HF (P=0.434), donor's age (P=0.51), 
cold ischemia time (P=0.227) and E/E' ratio (P=0.449). </p>



<p>Braz J Cardiovasc Surg | Rev Bras Cir Cardiovasc </p>

<p>Braz J Cardiovasc Surg 2015;30(1):9-15 
Carvalho VO, et al. -Determinants of peak VO 2 in heart transplant recipients </p>

<p>encing left atrium pumping. In agreement with Abdul-Waheed 
et al. </p>

<p>[16]   , our study showed a similar relationship between left 
atrium and exercise capacity. Unfortunately, our study can not 
explain the mechanisms involved in this relationship, but the hy-
pothesis raised by Abdul-Waheed at al. 
[16] seems to be relevant 
and deserves a deep investigation in future studies. 
The lack of influence of the time of transplant and the 
E/E' ratio in peak VO 2 found in this study is an important 
information and deserves some discussion. The E/E' ratio is 
an important echocardiography index in the diagnosis of dia-
stolic dysfunction and has been shown to be related to func-
tional class, cardiac mortality and hospitalization in patients 
with heart failure 
[17,18] . The ratio above 15 is a strong indi-
cator of heart failure with preserved left ventricle ejection 
fraction. The E/E' ratio between 8 and 15 represents a "gray 
zone" for diagnosis of diastolic dysfunction. In these cases, 
B-type Natriuretic Peptide (BNP) seem to have a great im-
portance for the differential diagnosis 
[19] . 
The prevalence of diastolic dysfunction in our study was 
3.4%, which we consider low compared to 33% of the study 
by Roten et al. 
[5] We expected that the prevalence of diastolic 
dysfunction were higher and the E/E' ratio increased along 
the segment after heart transplantation due to the increased 
incidence of co-morbidities such as hypertension. There are 
no data in the literature regarding diastolic function (E/E' ra-
tio) and time of cardiac transplantation. We believe the fact 
that our patients are well treated and compensated for comor-
bidities such as hypertension, the E/E' ratio remained con-
stant throughout the follow-up. In a curious way, our study 
showed no association between peak VO 2 and the time of 
transplantation, but a positive association between peak VO 2 
and cardiac sympathetic reinnervation through heart rate re-
serve. These data are quite relevant for a deeper understand-
ing of the behavior of exercise capacity over time of trans-
plantation. It seems that the real factor influencing exercise 
capacity is sympathetic reinnervation and not simply the time 
of transplantation. This information let us believe that for the 
same time following heart transplant, we will have more and 
less reinnervated patients. Consequently we will have pa-
tients with higher and lower exercise capacity. 
Finally, the study by Roten et al. 
[5] showed that the di-
astolic dysfunction was associated with exercise capacity 
limitation of heart transplant recipients. However, our study 
found no such association. Because of this conflicting data, 
some considerations must be taken into account. In our study, 
the prevalence of diastolic dysfunction was much lower than 
in the study by Roten et al. 
[5] Perhaps if our study had shown 
a higher prevalence of diastolic dysfunction (and consequent 
higher E/E' ratio), our data would have agreed to the study by 
Roten et al. 
[5] Therefore, further studies in this area are neces-
sary for a deeper understanding of the relationship between 
peak VO 2 and the E/E' ratio. 
This study has some limitations. Patients only performed </p>



<p>resting echocardiography. Certainly, the assessment of the 
cardiac function during exercise would bring important infor-
mation to the understanding of the relationship between E/E' 
ratio and in exercise capacity of heart transplant recipients. In 
addition, further investigation of the left atrium would be rel-
evant for a better understanding of the mechanisms involved 
in the limitation of exercise capacity. 
This study was also limited by not assessing the vascu-
lar function and peripheral muscle metabolism (oxygen ex-
traction). Tests such as the kinetics of O 2 , would be useful in 
future research to evaluate the influence of the "periphery" in 
the exercise capacity of transplanted patients. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>In this study, the determinants of the peak VO 2 in heart 
transplant recipients were: receptor gender, age, BMI, heart 
rate reserve and left atrium diameter. Heart rate reserve was 
the unique variable that was positively associated with peak 
VO 2 . This data suggest the importance of the sympathetic re-
innervation in peak VO 2 in heart transplant recipients. </p>

<p>Authors' roles &amp; responsibilities </p>

<p>VOC 
Analysis and/or interpretation of data, statistical analysis, 
final approval of the manuscript, conception and design of 
the study, implementation of operations and/or experiments, 
manuscript writing or critical review of its content 
GVG 
Analysis and/or interpretation of data, final approval of the 
manuscript, design and study design, performance of opera-
tions and/or experiments 
MLCV 
Analysis and/or interpretation of data, final approval of the 
manuscript, current operations and/or experiments, manu-
script writing or critical review of its content 
AMC 
analysis and/or interpretation of data, final approval of the 
manuscript, current operations and/or experiments, manu-
script writing or critical review of its content 
VOC 
Analysis and/or interpretation of data, final approval of the 
manuscript, design and study design, performance of opera-
tions and/or experiments, manuscript writing or critical review 
of its content 
SMAF 
Analysis and/or interpretation of data, final approval of the 
manuscript, current operations and/or experiments 
EAB 
Analysis and/or interpretation of data, final approval of 
the manuscript, design and study design, performance 
of operations and/or experiments, manuscript writing or 
critical review of its content. </p>





</text></tei>