<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4843533" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background--Blood outgrowth endothelial cells (BOECs) mediate therapeutic neovascularization in experimental models, but 
outgrowth characteristics and functionality of BOECs from patients with ischemic cardiomyopathy (ICMP) are unknown. We 
compared outgrowth efficiency and in vitro and in vivo functionality of BOECs derived from ICMP with BOECs from age-matched 
(ACON) and healthy young (CON) controls. </p>

<p>Methods and Results--We isolated 3.6AE0.6 BOEC colonies/100910 6 mononuclear cells (MNCs) from 60-mL blood samples of 
ICMP patients (n=45; age: 66AE1 years; LVEF: 31AE2%) versus 3.5AE0.9 colonies/100910 6 MNCs in ACON (n=32; age: 
60AE1 years) and 2.6AE0.4 colonies/100910 6 MNCs in CON (n=55; age: 34AE1 years), P=0.29. Endothelial lineage (VEGFR2 + / 
CD31 + /CD146 + ) and progenitor (CD34 + /CD133 À ) marker expression was comparable in ICMP and CON. Growth kinetics were 
similar between groups (P=0.38) and not affected by left ventricular systolic dysfunction, maladaptive remodeling, or presence of 
cardiovascular risk factors in ICMP patients. In vitro neovascularization potential, assessed by network remodeling on Matrigel and 
three-dimensional spheroid sprouting, did not differ in ICMP from (A)CON. Secretome analysis showed a marked proangiogenic 
profile, with highest release of angiopoietin-2 (1.4AE0.3910 5 pg/10 6 ICMP-BOECs) and placental growth factor 
(5.8AE1.5910 3 pg/10 6 ICMP BOECs), independent of age or ischemic disease. Senescence-associated b-galactosidase staining 
showed comparable senescence in BOECs from ICMP (5.8AE2.1%; n=17), ACON (3.9AE1.1%; n=7), and CON (9.0AE2.8%; n=13), 
P=0.19. High-resolution microcomputed tomography analysis in the ischemic hindlimb of nude mice confirmed increased 
arteriogenesis in the thigh region after intramuscular injections of BOECs from ICMP (P=0.025; n=8) and CON (P=0.048; n=5) over 
vehicle control (n=8), both to a similar extent (P=0.831). </p>

<p>Conclusions--BOECs can be successfully culture-expanded from patients with ICMP. In contrast to impaired functionality of ICMP-
derived bone marrow MNCs, BOECs retain a robust proangiogenic profile, both in vitro and in vivo, with therapeutic potential for 
targeting ischemic disease. ( J Am Heart Assoc. 2016;5:e002288 doi: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288) </p>

<p>Key Words: arteriogenesis • blood outgrowth endothelial cells • cell transplantation • ischemic heart disease • therapeutic 
neovascularization </p>

<p>B lood outgrowth endothelial cells (BOECs) represent an </p>

<p>easy accessible, culture-expandable cell source with 
endothelial lineage specification. BOECs belong to the family 
of endothelial progenitor cells (EPCs), which harbors a 
heterogeneous selection of different cell types, participating </p>

<p>in and modulating neovascularization. Distinct EPC subtypes 
are defined using different culture techniques and/or combi-
nations of cell surface markers. 1-3 BOECs, also referred to as 
circulating endothelial colony-forming cells (ECFCs) or late 
outgrowth EPCs, are the only cell type featuring the </p>

<p>From the Department of Cardiovascular Sciences, Clinical Cardiology (D.D., A.W., A.-S.W., H.G., E.C., P.P., N.V.D., W.D., J.V.C., J.V., S.J.), Center for Molecular and 
Vascular Biology (K.V., A.L.), Department of Clinical and Experimental Endocrinology (N.v.G., G.C.), Department of Electrical Engineering, Center for the Processing of 
Speech and Images (M.D., F.M.), and Department of Development and Regeneration, Stem Cell Biology and Embryology (C.V.), KU Leuven, Leuven, Belgium; Cell 
Therapy Department, Center for Applied Medicine Research (B.P., F.P.) and Hematology Department (F.P.), Clinica Universidad de Navarra, University of Navarra, 
Pamplona, Spain. 
Correspondence to: Dieter Dauwe, MD, PhD, or Stefan Janssens, MD, PhD, Department of Cardiovascular Diseases, University Hospitals Leuven, KU Leuven, 
Herestraat 49, 3000 Leuven, Belgium. E-mails: dieter.dauwe@med.kuleuven.be; stefan.janssens@med.kuleuven.be </p>

<p>Received July 5, 2015; accepted February 11, 2016. 
ª 2016 The Authors. Published on behalf of the American Heart Association, Inc., by Wiley Blackwell. This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative </p>

<p>Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is 
not used for commercial purposes. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>characteristics of a "true" EPC, given that these cells are self-
renewing, clonogenic, and able to form capillary-like struc-
tures and integrate into functional blood vessels in vitro and 
in vivo, respectively. 4 
Refractory angina is an increasingly prevalent clinical 
syndrome with an estimated incidence between 5% and 10% 
of patients undergoing cardiac catheterization. 5 In patients 
with ischemic heart disease, refractory to optimal medical 
treatment and percutaneous or surgical revascularization, 
progenitor cell transfer may constitute a promising biological 
alternative ("biological bypass"). 6 Autologous BOECs are able 
to induce neovascularization not only by incorporation into 
functional vessels, but also through paracrine modulation. 7,8 
One of the major concerns when envisioning autologous 
(progenitor/stem) cell therapy in cardiovascular medicine, is 
the presumed dysfunctional progenitor cell phenotype in older 
and diseased patients burdened with risk factors, as evi-
denced for early outgrowth EPCs of monocytic origin (also 
known as circulating angiogenic cells), 9-12 CD133 + /VEGFR2+ 
circulating EPCs, 10,13 colony-forming-unit EPCs (CFU-Hill), 13,14 
bone-marrow-derived mononuclear cells (MNCs) 15 and 
hematopoietic stem cells. 11 
Because no data are currently available on BOEC out-
growth and functionality in patients with the greatest unmet 
clinical need, we compared outgrowth efficiency and in vitro 
and in vivo functional characteristics of BOECs from patients 
with severe, but stable, ischemic cardiomyopathy (ICMP) and 
BOECs from both healthy age-matched (ACON) and young 
(CON) control subjects. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study Design </p>

<p>BOECs were isolated from peripheral blood of patients with 
stable ischemic cardiomyopathy (left ventricular ejection 
fraction [LVEF] ≤45%; 18-80 years) (ICMP: n=45; Table 1) 
in follow-up at the outpatient heart failure clinic of the 
Department of Cardiovascular Diseases at University Hospi-
tals (Leuven, Belgium). The study protocol was approved by 
the Medical Ethics Committee (S51940), and informed 
consent was obtained from all patients. The control group 
consisted of healthy individuals (18-80 years; Table 1) with 
no evidence/history of coronary artery disease, divided in an 
age-matched (ACON: n=32) and young (CON: n=55) control 
populations. </p>

<p>BOEC Isolation and Expansion </p>

<p>BOECs were isolated and expanded as previously described, 
with minor modifications. 4,8 In short, the mononuclear 
fraction from 40-to 60-mL venous blood samples was </p>

<p>isolated using Ficoll Paque Plus (GE Healthcare, Little 
Chalfont, UK) density centrifugation. Cells were resuspended 
in EBM 2 supplemented with a bullet kit (Lonza, Basel, 
Switzerland), excluding the provided gentamicin and amfo-
tericin singlequots. In addition, the medium was supple-
mented with an extra 13% of FBS, MEM-NEAA (Gibco, Grand 
Island, NY), 1% penicillin/streptomycin (Gibco), and 1:550 
b-Mercaptoethanol (Gibco). Cells were cultured on collagen </p>

<p>type I precoated dishes (Cellcoat; Greiner Bio-One GmbH, 
Kremsm€ unster, Austria) in a 21% O 2 , 5% CO 2 incubator. </p>

<p>Table 1. Clinical Characteristics of Study Subjects </p>

<p>ICMP 
(n=45) </p>

<p>CON 
(n=55) </p>

<p>ACON 
(n=32) </p>

<p>Age, y 
66AE1 
3 4AE1 
6 0 AE1 </p>

<p>M/F (%) 
91/9 
59/41 
25/75 </p>

<p>LVEF (%) 
31AE2 
-
-</p>

<p>LVEDD, mm 
56AE1 
-
-</p>

<p>Cardiovascular risk factors 
ND </p>

<p>Hypertension 
29/45 
7/32 </p>

<p>Diabetes 
17/45 
0/32 </p>

<p>Hyperlipidemia 
38/45 
7/32 </p>

<p>Obesity 
14/45 
6/32 </p>

<p>Smoking 
38/45 
10/32 </p>

<p>Familial cardiovascular risk 
23/45 
-</p>

<p>Extent of coronary 
artery disease </p>

<p>NA 
-</p>

<p>One-vessel disease 
8/45 </p>

<p>Two-vessel disease 
12/45 </p>

<p>Three-vessel disease 
25/45 </p>

<p>Medical treatment 
0/55 </p>

<p>Aspirin 
26/45 
0/32 </p>

<p>Thienopyridin 
11/45 
0/32 </p>

<p>Statin 
42/45 
2/32 </p>

<p>Beta-blocker 
42/45 
0/32 </p>

<p>ACE inhibitor/ARB 
38/45 
1/32 </p>

<p>Spironolactone 
23/45 
0/32 </p>

<p>Device treatment 
0/55 
0/32 </p>

<p>CRT-P 
3/45 </p>

<p>CRT-D 
8/45 </p>

<p>ICD 
7/45 </p>

<p>Blood outgrowth endothelial cell (BOEC) isolations were performed in 45 patients with 
ischemic cardiomyopathy (ICMP), 55 young healthy controls (CON), and 32 age-matched 
controls (ACON). Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) and left ventricular end-
diastolic diameter (LVEDD) were measured by transthoracic echocardiography. ACE 
inhibitor indicates angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor; ARB, angiotensin receptor 
blocker; CRT-D, cardiac resynchronization therapy incorporating an implantable 
cardioverter defibrillator; CRT-P, cardiac resynchronization therapy without implantable 
cardioverter defibrillator; ICD, implantable cardioverter defibrillator; NA, not applicable; 
ND, not determined. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>ICMP BOECs Retain Neovascularization Potential 
Dauwe et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Individual BOEC colonies were picked at days 21 to 28 and 
pooled for further polyclonal expansion up to passage 7 or 
growth arrest. Phenotyping and functional evaluation was 
performed at passage 3 to 5 (Figure 1). Mycoplasma 
contamination was excluded, using the MycoAlert Myco-
plasma detection kit (Lonza), following the manufacturer's 
instructions. </p>

<p>Confirmation Endothelial Phenotype </p>

<p>Cells were stained with Ulex europeus agglutinin (UEA)-lectin 
(Sigma-Aldrich). Dil-AcLDL uptake (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) 
and cell surface markers were quantified using flow cytometry 
(BD FACS Canto II; BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA). CD309 
(vascular endothelial growth factor receptor 2; VEGFR-2), 
CD146 (melanoma cell adhesion molecule), and CD31 
(platelet endothelial cell adhesion molecule 1) were selected 
as endothelial markers, CD34 and CD133 as progenitor 
markers, and CD45 as a panleukocyte exclusion marker. 
Antibodies and isotype controls were from Miltenyi Biotec 
(Cambridge, MA). Gene expression was studied using real-
time quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR; StepOnePlus; Applied 
Biosystems, Foster City, CA) and TaqMan Gene Expression 
Assays (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA), focusing on angio-
genic growth factors and endothelial markers (Table 2, top). 
Results are expressed as a 2 ÀDCT -value, relative to HPRT as </p>

<p>the housekeeping gene. In addition, the angiogenic secretome 
was studied in 24-hour conditioned medium (EBM 2 /2%FBS) 
by ELISA (PLGF, angiopoietin-2 [ANG-2], fibroblast growth 
factor [FGF] 2, platelet-derived growth factor-BB [PDGF-BB], 
VEGF 165 , insulin-like growth factor 1 [IGF-1], and HGF, 
hepatocyte growth factor [HGF]; Quantikine; all from R&amp;D 
Systems, Minneapolis, MN; Table 2, bottom). </p>

<p>Proliferation Potential </p>

<p>Cell numbers were calculated at every passage in order to 
derive expansion curves and calculate population doubling 
times throughout the entire expansion process. In addition to 
growth kinetics, senescence was quantified by senescence-
associated b-galactosidase staining (Senescence Detection 
Kit; BioVision, Inc., Milpitas, CA). The number of blue cells was 
manually counted and reported as a percentage of the entire 
cell population. </p>

<p>In Vitro Oxidative Stress </p>

<p>Production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) was quantified 
using CM-H 2 DCFDA (Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR) as a 
fluorescent ROS indicator (Ex/Em: 492-495/517-527). Cells </p>

<p>were loaded with a final dye concentration of 10 lmol/L for 
30 minutes at 37°C. Intensity of the fluorescence was </p>

<p>Blood </p>

<p>EBM 2 / 15% FBS </p>

<p>Collagen </p>

<p>21% O 2 
5% CO 2 
37° C </p>

<p>BOEC-CFU: Day 11 </p>

<p>Picking 
Colonies 
Day 21-28 </p>

<p>Day 10-16 </p>

<p>Day 0 </p>

<p>Expansion 
(Passage 5-7) 
1.5-2 Months </p>

<p>Phenotyping 
(Passage 3-5) </p>

<p>Figure 1. BOEC isolation and expansion process. Mononuclear cells (MNCs) were isolated from a single </p>

<p>40-to 60-mL venous blood sample by Ficoll density centrifugation. MNCs were seeded on collagen type I 
precoated dishes and cultured in a 21% O 2 , 5% CO 2 incubator using EBM 2 medium. Medium was changed 
daily during the first week and every other day after. BOEC colonies started to appear at days 10 to 16 
(scale bar, 200 lm). Individual BOEC colonies were picked at days 21 to 28, pooled, and culture expanded 
up to passage 7 or growth arrest. Phenotypic analysis was performed between passages 3 and 5. BOEC 
indicates blood outgrowth endothelial cell; CFU, colony-forming units. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>ICMP BOECs Retain Neovascularization Potential 
Dauwe et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>measured using a fluorescence plate reader at baseline, 10 and 
45 minutes after exposure to 500 lmol/L H 2 O 2 . Additionally, 
cells were exposed to 1000 lmol/L of H 2 O 2 for 24 hours, after 
which cell viability was quantified by flow cytometry using 7-
aminoactinomycin D (7-AAD) as a viability marker. </p>

<p>In Vitro Neovascularization Potential </p>

<p>In a matrigel "network remodeling" (Tube Formation) assay 
(BD Matrigel Basement Membrane Matrix, 354234; BD 
Biosciences), a total of 75 000 BOECs were seeded per 24-
well, coated with 300 lL of Matrigel. Phase contrast mosaic 
images were acquired of the complete well after 6 hours of 
incubation. The cellular network was manually delineated in 
order to semiautomatically quantify total network length and 
the number of intersections using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software (National 
Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD). Additionally, sprouting 
angiogenesis was studied using a three-dimensional (3D) 
spheroid sprouting assay in collagen gel, as previously 
described with minor modifications. 16 In short, BOEC 
spheroids containing 1000 cells were generated by suspen-
sion culture in EBM 2 culture medium containing 0.25% (w/v) 
carboxymethylcellulose, seeded in nonadherent round-bot-
tomed 96-well plates. Under these conditions, all suspended 
cells contribute to the formation of a single BOEC spheroid </p>

<p>per well. These spheroids were harvested within 24 hours and 
embedded in collagen gels (Rat Tail Collagen Type I; Corning, 
Corning, NY), as previously described. 16 The length of the 3 
longest capillary-like sprouts that had grown out of each 
spheroid was measured after 24 hours. A total of 20AE2 
spheroids per sample were analyzed. </p>

<p>In Vivo Neovascularization Potential </p>

<p>All animal procedures were approved by the Ethics Committee 
on Animal Use of KU Leuven (Leuven, Belgium) and conform 
to the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals 
published by the U.S. National Institutes of Health. Female 8-
to 10-week-old athymic NMRI nude mice (Janvier Labs, Le 
Genest-Saint-Isle, France) were anesthetized with an intraperi-
toneal injection of ketamine (100 mg/kg) and xylazine 
(15 mg/kg). The common, superficial, and deep femoral 
artery of the right leg were ligated and transsected in 
between. Laser Doppler measurements (PIM-II; Lisca Devel-
opment AB, Link€ oping, Sweden) were performed under 2% 
isoflurane gas anesthesia and temperature-controlled condi-
tions (37°C) 5 days after hindlimb ischemia surgery to assess 
degree of flow reduction. Only animals with ≥55% flow 
reduction in the ischemic versus nonligated control limb were 
included in the study. </p>

<p>Table 2. Transcriptional Analysis and Secretome of BOECs </p>

<p>RT-qPCR (2 ÀDCT vs HPRT) 
ICMP (n=15) 
CON (n=9) 
ACON (n=10) 
1-Way ANOVA </p>

<p>Endothelial markers </p>

<p>vWF 
7.120AE2.620 
7.330AE4.370 
3.390AE0.655 
P=0.69 </p>

<p>NOS-3 
0.101AE0.029 
0.072AE0.044 
0.184AE0.045 
P=0.05 </p>

<p>Angiogenic/arteriogenic growth factors </p>

<p>PLGF 
1.010AE0.319 
0.639AE0.230 
0.755AE0.216 
P=0.97 </p>

<p>ANG-2 
1.140AE0.592 
0.642AE0.216 
1.47AE0.381 
P=0.06 </p>

<p>FGF-2 
0.337AE0.110 
0.344AE0.082 
0.243AE0.040 
P=0.46 </p>

<p>PDGF-BB 
0.918AE0.362 
0.648AE0.131 
0.809AE0.309 
P=0.65 </p>

<p>VEGF 
0.063AE0.017 
0.087AE0.037 
0.083AE0.015 
P=0.20 </p>

<p>IGF-1 
0.015AE0.008 
0.006AE0.002 
0.016AE0.007 
P=0.81 </p>

<p>HGF 
0.007AE0.004 
0.007AE0.003 
0.031AE0.008 
P&lt;0.05* , † </p>

<p>ELISA 
ICMP (n=15) 
CON (n=9) 
ACON (n=15) 
1-Way ANOVA 
HCAEC Reference (n=3) </p>

<p>hPLGF (pg/10 6 cells) 
5772AE1525 
6133AE1475 
2767AE368 
P=0.13 
2326AE579 </p>

<p>hANG-2 (ng/10 6 cells) 
140AE31 
96AE18 
83AE11 
P=0.66 
12AE4 </p>

<p>hFGF (pg/10 6 cells) 
965AE730 
439AE160 
56AE8 
P&lt;0.05* , † 
133AE54 </p>

<p>hPDGF-BB (pg/10 6 cells) 
170AE50 
184AE90 
37AE8 
P=0.04 
20AE8 </p>

<p>ANG-1, EGF, HGF, IGF1, and VEGF below detection limit of the assay. All transcriptional results are expressed as a 2 ÀDCT -value, relative to HPRT as the housekeeping gene. ACON indicates 
age-matched controls; ANG-1/2, angiopoietin-1/2; BOEC(s), blood outgrowth endothelial cell(s); CON, healthy young controls; FGF, fibroblast growth factor; HCAEC, human coronary 
artery endothelial cells; HGF, hepatocyte growth factor; ICMP, ischemic cardiomyopathy patients; IGF-1, insulin-like growth factor 1; NOS-3, nitric oxide synthase 3; PDGF-BB, platelet-
derived growth factor-BB; PLGF, placental growth factor; RT-qPCR, reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction; VEGF, vascular endothelial growth factor; vWF, von Willebrand factor. 
One-way ANOVA post-test comparison: *P&lt;0.05: ICMP vs ACON;  † CON vs ACON. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>ICMP BOECs Retain Neovascularization Potential 
Dauwe et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Figure 2. BOEC outgrowth characteristics. BOECs can be isolated to the same extent </p>

<p>from patients and controls (A), irrespective of age (B), severity of the disease process (C, 
D, and E), and cardiovascular risk factors (F and G). The linear regression line is 
surrounded by 95% confidence bands (C). 1/2/3-VD indicates 1/2/3-vessel disease; 
ACON, age-matched controls; CON, healthy young controls; CVRF, cardiovascular risk 
factors; DM, diabetes mellitus; ICMP, ischemic cardiomyopathy patients; LVEDD, left 
ventricular end diastolic diameter; LVEF, left ventricular ejection fraction; y, years. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>ICMP BOECs Retain Neovascularization Potential 
Dauwe et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Intramuscular injections of 250 000 BOECs from 
patients (ICMP) or young controls (CON) versus vehicle 
control (PBS) were performed in the ischemic hindlimb, 
5 days after the ligation procedure. Cells were resuspended 
in 100 lL of PBS and subsequently injected into the thigh 
region (5910 lL) and gastrocnemius muscle (5910 lL) 
using a 1-mL 29G syringe. Intraperitoneal anti-asialo-GM1 
injections (Wako Chemicals, Inc., Dallas, TX) were per-
formed once a week to suppress residual natural killer cell 
activity. 
Mice were euthanized 21 days after femoral artery ligation. 
At sacrifice, mice were sedated with an intraperitoneal </p>

<p>injection of Nembutal 70 mg/kg. A midline sternotomy was 
performed to expose the heart, followed by insertion of a 
winged 25G needle (Mycroflex; Vygon, Ecouen, France) into 
the LV apex and removal of the right auriculum. Vessels were 
perfused by the LV cavity with 20 mL of saline, containing 
100 IU/mL of unfractionated heparin, in order to remove the 
blood and prevent clotting. Tissue was subsequently fixed by a 
15-mL perfusion with neutral buffered formalin 10%, followed 
by 20 mL of saline to wash out the fixative. A final perfusion 
with a preheated mixture of 30% barium sulphate (Micro-
paque; Guerbet, France) and 2% gelatin was performed in 
order to visualize the vessel tree on post-mortem angio </p>

<p>CD34 
CD133 
CD309 </p>

<p>CD45 
CD146 
CD31 </p>

<p>Flow Cytometry 
ICMP (n=17) </p>

<p>(% Positive Cells) </p>

<p>CON (n=13) </p>

<p>(% Positive Cells) </p>

<p>P-Value </p>

<p>CD45 
0.0±0.0 
0.0±0.0 
/ </p>

<p>CD146 
98.4±0.3 
96.1±1.4 
0.38 </p>

<p>CD31 
98.5±0.3 
97.9±0.7 
0.26 </p>

<p>CD309 
81.7±2.2 
70.5±6.4 
0.08 </p>

<p>CD34 
57.2±7.3 
71.6±9.3 
0.17 </p>

<p>CD133 
0.1±0.0 
0.0±0.0 
0.72 </p>

<p>Phase Contrast: BOEC Colony </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>CD31 UEA-Lectin DAPI </p>

<p>Dil-AcLDL UEA-Lectin DAPI </p>

<p>Figure 3. BOEC phenotype. BOECs display the typical cobblestone morphology (A) (scale bar, 200 lm), stain positive for UEA-lectin and the </p>

<p>endothelial marker, CD31 (B) (scale bar, 20 lm), and take up acetylated LDL (C) (scale bar, 20 lm). Representative flow cytometry analysis (D) 
for endothelial markers (CD31 + /CD309 + /CD146 + ), progenitor markers (CD34 + /CD133 À ), and a panleukocytic marker (CD45 À ) on ICMP-
BOECs. Flow cytometry data (red line in histogram) are expressed in relation to respective isotype controls (black line in histogram) and a 
quantitative comparison with CON-BOECs is shown in the table. BOEC indicates blood outgrowth endothelial cell; CON, healthy young controls; 
DAPI, 4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole; ICMP, ischemic cardiomyopathy patients; LDL, low-density lipoprotein; UAE, Ulex europeus agglutinin. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>ICMP BOECs Retain Neovascularization Potential 
Dauwe et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>microCT (computed tomography). Mice were stored on ice 
overnight to solidify the gelatin and fix the contrast agent in 
the vessels. 
The hind limbs were scanned with a high-resolution 
microCT (50 kV, 200 lA, 10 W; SkyScan-1172; SkyScan, 
Virginia Beach, VA) at a pixel size of 8 lm, providing highly 
detailed, quantitative 3D structural data of the perfused 
"vessel tree" of the complete limb. The individual two-</p>

<p>dimensional (2D) images were reconstructed into a 3D data 
set with isotropic voxel size of 8 lm using the manufacturer's 
dedicated software (<rs id="software-2" type="software">NRecon</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SkyScan</rs>). Analysis was per-
formed using in-house developed custom-made software 
(<rs id="software-1" type="software">MeVisLab</rs> based; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">MeVis Medical Solutions AG</rs>, Bremen, 
Germany) after an additional downsampling step by a factor of 
4, for reasons of computational feasibility. The 3D vessel tree 
was automatically segmented for semiautomatic quantifica-
tion. Data in the ligated leg were analyzed versus the 
nonligated control leg. </p>

<p>Histology: Arthrobacter luteus Repeats and 
Combined hCD31/BS-I Lectin Staining </p>

<p>Adductor and gastrocnemius muscles, as well as lung, spleen, 
liver, kidney and heart on a separate set of animals not 
perfused with gelatin/barium-sulfate were collected and 
paraffin-embedded to study BOEC incorporation and biodis-
tribution. BOEC-incorporation into the vasculature of adductor 
and gastrocnemius muscles, was studied by combined 
chromogenic in situ hybridization for Arthrobacter luteus 
(ALU)-repeats (ALU Positive Control Probe-II and ISHiVIEW 
Blue Plus Detection Kit; Ventana Medical Systems, Inc., Oro 
Valley, AZ), as the primate-specific sequence, and dual 
immunofluorescence staining for human (h) CD31 (anti-
hCD31 IgG 1,j , m0823; Dako, Carpinteria, CA) and BS-I Lectin 
(L3759; Sigma-Aldrich) on adjacent sections. An initial acute 
retention and biodistribution study was performed, 24 hours 
after intramuscular injections (6 days after ligation) of </p>

<p>Figure 4. BOEC expansion potential. Growth kinetics, studied by population doubling times (A3) and the slope of the log 10 (expansion curves) </p>

<p>(A1,2), showed similar proliferation rates in BOECs from ICMP patients and controls. Growth kinetics were studied from the start of the 
polyclonal phase, defined as day 0, the time point at which individual BOEC colonies were picked and pooled for culture expansion. The number 
of senescent cells, quantified as the percentage of blue cells in the senescence-associated b-galactosidase staining (B1) (scale bar, 200 lm), 
did not differ between patients and controls (B2). ACON indicates age-matched controls; BOEC, blood outgrowth endothelial cell; CON, healthy 
young controls; ICMP, ischemic cardiomyopathy patients. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>ICMP BOECs Retain Neovascularization Potential 
Dauwe et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>250 000 BOECs labeled by lentiviral overexpression of Cherry 
fluorescent protein. Moreover, chronic engraftment was </p>

<p>quantified at 21 days. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>All data are presented as meanAESEM. Intergroup differences 
were analyzed using 2-tailed unpaired t tests or 1-way ANOVA 
followed by a Bonferroni post-hoc test for normally distributed 
data. Non-normally distributed data were compared using 
a nonparametric Mann-Whitney test or nonparametric </p>

<p>Kruskal-Wallis test followed by Dunn's post-hoc test. Pearson 
correlations were performed to analyze linear covariation 
between normally distributed data sets, whereas Spearman 
nonparametric correlation was performed for nonparametric 
datasets. A probability value of P&lt;0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. All analyses were performed using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0a</rs> software (version 5.0a; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software Inc.</rs>., La 
Jolla, CA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Patient Characteristics </p>

<p>BOEC isolations were performed in 45 patients (ICMP, 
66AE1 years) and 32 healthy age-matched (ACON, 
60AE1 years) and 55 healthy young (CON, 34AE1 years) 
controls (Table 1). Global systolic LV function was impaired 
(LVEF 31AE2%) without concomitant adverse LV remodeling 
(left ventricular end diastolic diameter [LVEDD], 56AE1 mm) in 
the majority of patients. Adverse LV remodeling, defined as an 
LVEDD ≥60 mm on a transthoracic acquired echocardiogra-
phy parasternal long axis view, was present in 12 of 45 
(26.7%) patients. Four patients were excluded from the study 
because blood was taken less than 1 month after device 
implantation. </p>

<p>BOEC Outgrowth Efficiency </p>

<p>Starting from 40 to 60 mL of whole blood, a mean of 3.6AE0.6 
BOEC colonies/100910 6 MNCs could be obtained from 
patients versus 3.5AE0.9 from age-matched controls and 
2.6AE0.4 from healthy young controls (P=0.29; Figure 2A). 
Colonies could be obtained in 84% of ICMP, 72% of ACON and 
82% of CON. The number of BOEC colonies obtained in our 
ICMP population increased with age (r=0.42; P&lt;0.01; Fig-
ure 2B), but was not affected by severity of the disease 
process, assessed by LVEF (r=À0.12; Figure 2C) or adverse 
LV remodeling (Figure 2D). BOEC outgrowth was independent 
of the extent of coronary artery disease, number of cardio-
vascular risk factors, and presence of diabetes mellitus 
(Figure 2E through 2G). </p>

<p>BOEC Phenotype </p>

<p>BOECs uniformly expressed CD31, bound lectin, and took up 
Dil-AcLDL (representative examples are shown in Figure 3A 
through 3C). Flow cytometry evaluation of endothelial (CD31 + , 
CD309 + , and CD146 + ) and progenitor (CD34 + , CD133 À ) cell 
surface markers did not differ between groups (Figure 3D). 
The panleukocyte marker, CD45, was absent in all groups. RT-
qPCR neither showed differences in expression for additional 
endothelial markers, such as VWF and NOS3 (Table 2, top). </p>

<p>Figure 5. BOEC response to oxidative stress: ROS production </p>

<p>was quantified using CM-H 2 DCFDA as a fluorescent ROS indicator. 
No differences were noted in baseline ROS production in BOECs 
isolated from ICMP and CON (A). Moreover, induction by 
500 lmol/L of H 2 O 2 showed a similar increase in ROS production 
in ICMP and CON (A). Additionally, 24 hours of exposure to 
1000 lmol/L of H 2 O 2 did not show significant differences in BOEC 
viability between ICMP and CON, quantified by flow cytometry 
using 7-AAD as a viability marker (B). 2-way RM ANOVA indicates 2-
way repeated-measures ANOVA; 7-AAD, 7-aminoactinomycin D; 
BOEC, blood outgrowth endothelial cell; CON, healthy young 
controls; ICMP, ischemic cardiomyopathy patients; ROS, reactive 
oxygen species. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>ICMP BOECs Retain Neovascularization Potential 
Dauwe et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>BOEC Proliferation Potential </p>

<p>We aimed to expand our cells to a target dose of %30910 6 
BOECs from 60 mL of whole blood, a cell number with proven 
functional benefit in our porcine myocardial ischemia/reper-
fusion model. 7 Proliferation potential, studied by growth 
kinetics and senescence-associated b-galactosidase staining, 
did not show differences between BOECs from ICMP and (A) 
CON. Population doubling times (P=0.16) and slopes of the 
log 10 (expansion curves) (P=0.38) showed comparable growth 
kinetics (Figure 4A). The number of senescent cells was 
5.8AE2.1% in ICMP (n=17) versus 3.9AE1.1% and 9.0AE2.8% of 
total BOECs in ACON (n=7) and CON (n=13), respectively 
(P=0.19; Figure 4B). Starting from a single 60-mL blood 
sample in our patient population, expansion up to 30910 6 
BOECs was achieved in 52% of isolations, if initial BOEC 
colonies were obtained. The number of initial BOEC colonies </p>

<p>(P&lt;0.0001) and the time of appearance of the first clone 
(P=0.005) were major predictors of expansion success. If 
expansion up to 30910 6 cells could be achieved, the average 
number of BOEC colonies to start from was 9.9AE2.3/isolation 
with an appearance at day 12AE1. In contrast, if expansion up 
to 30910 6 cells failed, on average only 2.5AE0.5 colonies/ 
isolation were initially obtained with an appearance at day 
16AE1. Clinical, biochemical, or hematological predictors of 
expansion potential could not be identified. </p>

<p>BOEC Response to Oxidative Stress </p>

<p>No differences were noted in baseline reactive oxygen species 
(ROS) production in BOECs isolated from ICMP (n=5) and CON 
(n=6; P=0.37; Figure 5A). Moreover, induction by 500 lmol/L 
of H 2 O 2 showed comparable increase in ROS production in 
ICMP and CON, 10 and 45 minutes after exposure (P=0.60; </p>

<p>Figure 6. BOEC Matrigel network formation potential. Network remodeling was photographed using phase-contrast mosaic acquisition (A, top </p>

<p>panel) and subsequently manually delineated (A, lower panel-network delineation in red) in order to quantify total network length and the 
number of intersections (scale bar, 1000 lm). Total network length (B1) and the number of intersections (B2) in patients did not differ from 
controls. Severity of the disease process, assessed by left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF), did not compromise in vitro network formation 
potential (C1,2). Linear regression lines are surrounded by 95% confidence bands (C1,2). ACON indicates age-matched controls; BOEC, blood 
outgrowth endothelial cell; CON, healthy young controls; ICMP, ischemic cardiomyopathy patients. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>ICMP BOECs Retain Neovascularization Potential 
Dauwe et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Figure 5A). Additionally, 24 hours of exposure to 1000 lmol/ 
L of H 2 O 2 did not show significant differences in BOEC viability 
between ICMP (n=6) and CON (n=6; P=0.11; Figure 5B). </p>

<p>BOEC In Vitro Neovascularization Potential </p>

<p>We subsequently focused on functional neovascularization 
potential of the obtained cell populations. In vitro vasculo-
genic potential, explored using the Matrigel network remod-
eling assay (Figure 6A), did not show differences in the 
number of network intersections between cells from ICMP 
and (A)CON (P=0.32; Figure 6B). Total network length did not 
differ between cells from ICMP and (A)CON. An increase in 
network length was, however, noted in aged versus young 
controls. Severity of the disease process, assessed by LVEF, 
did not impair in vitro network formation potential. On the 
contrary, LVEF inversely correlated with total network length 
(r=À0.57; P=0.01; n=16) and the number of intersections </p>

<p>(r=À0.53; P=0.03; n=16; Figure 6C). Body mass index (BMI) 
was positively correlated with in vitro vasculogenic potential 
(r=0.58; P=0.02; n=16). No other major clinical, biochemical, 
or hematological predictors could be identified. Additionally, 
in vitro angiogenesis potential, explored using a 3D spheroid 
sprouting assay in collagen gel, did not show differences in 
sprouting angiogenesis between BOECs from ICMP and CON 
(P=0.70; Figure 7). 
RTqPCR and ELISA documented a marked proangiogenic 
profile with high expression of angiogenic growth factors 
(ANG-2, PLGF, PDGF-BB, FGF-2, and VEGF) both in BOECs 
from patients and controls (Table 2). ANG-2 and PLGF were 
the most abundant angiogenic growth factors in 24-hour 
conditioned medium, with similar amounts secreted by BOECs 
from ICMP and healthy subjects ([A]CON) (P=0.66 and 0.13 
for ANG-2 and PLGF, respectively). </p>

<p>BOEC In Vivo Neovascularization Potential </p>

<p>Initial acute retention and biodistribution studies, using 
Cherry-labeled BOECs, documented multiple clusters and 
singlets of transplanted cells in the femoral and tibiofibular 
region 24 hours after intramuscular cell delivery (average of 
312 BOECs/4.5 mm 2 ), mainly localized in perimuscular 
connective tissue (Figure 8). No detectable distribution was 
observed in lungs, spleen, liver, kidneys, and heart. 
Doppler flow index at inclusion (5 days after hindlimb 
ischemia surgery) was similar in all groups (vehicle control: 
35.9AE1.5; CON-BOECs: 35.5AE1.8; ICMP-BOECs: 35.9AE2.0; 
P=0.98). High-resolution angio microCT of the upper leg 
confirmed enhanced BOEC-mediated arteriogenesis in com-
parison to vehicle control, 21 days after surgery (Figure 9). 
Although total vessel length and the number of vessel 
branch points tended to be increased after BOEC delivery 
from both CON and ICMP (Figure 9B), therapeutic effects 
were confined to smaller arterioles with a diameter ranging 
from 32 to 64 lm (Figure 9D), corresponding to collateral 
arteries, as documented by Scholz and Schaper. 17,18 
Importantly, increased arteriogenesis was observed after 
transplantation of BOECs from healthy young controls 
(P=0.048) and ICMP patients (P=0.025) over vehicle 
control, both to a similar extent (P=0.831). Clinically, 
BOECs were able to prevent additional amputations after 
cell delivery (5 days after hindlimb ischemia surgery). A 
total of 3 of 14 animals suffered from additional amputa-
tions after injections of vehicle control versus none in the 
BOEC-injected groups. 
Immunostaining for human CD31 and in situ hybridiza-
tion for primate specific ALU-repeat sequences could detect 
incorporation of rare human BOECs into murine vessels in 
the ischemic hindlimb 21 days after surgery (Figure 10). 
Engraftment, studied in 3 versus 3 mice, showed 4AE2 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
C </p>

<p>Figure 7. BOEC 3D spheroid sprouting assay: BOEC spheroids, </p>

<p>containing 1000 cells, were embedded into collagen gels. The 
length of the 3 longest capillary-like sprouts that had grown out of 
each spheroid was measured after 24 hours. No differences were 
noted in average sprout length between ICMP and CON (A). 
Representative images of sprouting BOEC spheroids from ICMP (B) 
and CON (C) (scale bar, 200 lm). 3D indicates three-dimensional; 
BOEC, blood outgrowth endothelial cell; CON indicates healthy 
young controls; ICMP, ischemic cardiomyopathy patients. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>ICMP BOECs Retain Neovascularization Potential 
Dauwe et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>incorporated ICMP-BOECs/4.5 mm 2 versus 3AE2 incorpo-
rated CON-BOECs/4.5 mm 2 . This limited incorporation 
after injection of 250 000 BOECs/mouse suggests a 
concomitant paracrine contribution of the transplanted 
cell population to their documented neovascularization 
potential. 7,8 </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We report that BOECs can be successfully isolated and 
culture-expanded from patients with severe, but stable, </p>

<p>ischemic cardiomyopathy, irrespective of age, severity of 
myocardial systolic dysfunction, or degree of maladaptive LV 
remodeling. These cells show a robust and consistent 
endothelial progenitor phenotype with comparable prolifera-
tion kinetics and without evidence of increased senescence 
when compared to cells isolated from young or age-matched 
healthy subjects. We did not document differences in in vitro 
neovascularization potential of BOECs from patients or 
controls, because they form comparable vascular networks 
in Matrigel, demonstrate similar sprouting potential in a 3D 
spheroid-sprouting angiogenesis assay, and secrete high </p>

<p>Cherry Labeled BOECs 
TOPRO3 </p>

<p>BS1-Lectin 
human-CD31 
DAPI </p>

<p>A1 
A2 </p>

<p>B1 
B2 </p>

<p>Cherry Labeled BOECs 
TOPRO3 </p>

<p>ALU-Repeats </p>

<p>Figure 8. Acute BOEC retention. Confocal microscopy documents multiple clusters (A1) and singlets (A2) of Cherry-labeled BOECs (red), </p>

<p>24 hours after intramuscular injection into the ischemic hindlimb. These findings were confirmed by immunofluorescence microscopy for human 
CD31 (red; labeling only transplanted cells) and BS-I-Lectin (green; labeling host endothelium) (B1) and in situ hybridization for primate-specific 
ALU-repeat sequences (dark blue) on the respective adjacent slides (B2) (scale bar, 100 lm). Clusters and singlets of human BOECs are 
indicated by white arrows. ALU indicates Arthrobacter luteus; BOEC(s), blood outgrowth endothelial cell(s); CON indicates healthy young 
controls; ICMP, ischemic cardiomyopathy patients. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>ICMP BOECs Retain Neovascularization Potential 
Dauwe et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>levels of potent angiogenic and arteriogenic factors. After 
in vivo cell transfer, BOECs from patients and healthy donors 
increase collateral vascular remodeling in the thigh region of 
nude mice, with significant induction of arterioles 32 to 
64 lm in diameter and prevention of imminent amputations 
after cell delivery. 
In contrast to various other EPC subtypes studied as 
biomarkers of cardiovascular risk and disease, 14,19 we did not 
observe inverse correlations between the number of BOEC 
outgrowth colonies and severity of the ischemic atheroscle-
rotic disease process. We did not observe a disease-related 
increase in the number of BOEC colonies obtained, as was 
previously shown during active inflammation, tissue damage, 
and intense vascular remodeling (acute myocardial infarc-
tion, 20 acute ischemic stroke, 21,22 rheumatoid arthritis, 23 
neovascular age-related macular degeneration, 24 or extensive </p>

<p>burns 25 ). In our patient population with stable ischemic heart 
failure, optimally treated according to current guidelines, a 
similar number of BOEC colonies were obtained in patients 
and healthy controls. These findings are consistent with 
earlier data in statin-treated patients with premature coronary 
artery disease. 26 Within our patient cohort, we did, however, 
note a mild positive correlation between age and BOEC 
outgrowth, absent in our control population. 
Because of limited cell retention after intracoronary or 
intramyocardial delivery, a sufficient cell mass is needed to 
obtain therapeutic effects in the target region as previously 
shown in domestic swine. 7 Starting from a single 60-mL blood 
sample, we were able to achieve our expansion goal of 
30910 6 cells in 52% of patients, with similar growth kinetics 
in controls. Given that we showed expansion success to be 
highly dependent on the number of initial BOEC colonies </p>

<p>Figure 9. In vivo neovascularization potential assessed by angio microCT: Representative 3D reconstructions (left panel) and quantitative </p>

<p>analysis (right panel). Representative 3D angio microCT reconstructions illustrate an enhanced neovascularization response in the thigh region 
after intramuscular injections of BOECs from both patients (ICMP) and CON (A). Twenty-one days after hindlimb ischemia surgery, angio microCT 
quantifications documented a trend toward increased vessel length (B1) and number of vessel branch points (B2) in the thigh region (A and C) 
after intramuscular BOEC injections of patients (ICMP) and CON in comparison to vehicle control (PBS). BOEC-mediated effects were confined to 
arterioles 32 to 64 lm in diameter (2-tailed unpaired t tests) (D). All results from the ischemic hindlimb (HLI) are expressed in relation to the 
contralateral control leg (CONT). 3D indicates three-dimensional; BOEC, blood outgrowth endothelial cell; CON indicates healthy young controls; 
CT, computed tomography; ICMP, ischemic cardiomyopathy patients; ROI, region of interest. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>ICMP BOECs Retain Neovascularization Potential 
Dauwe et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>obtained, increasing the number of MNCs by increasing the 
volume of the blood sample or using leukapheresis could 
further enhance expansion success. 
In contrast to various other cell types, we observed 
preserved neovascularization potential of BOECs derived from 
an older patient population with severe ICMP. Ingram et al. 
reported that BOECs contain a complete hierarchy of low-and 
high-proliferation potential cells, analogous to the hematopoi-
etic cell system. 27 Moreover, long-term culture conditions 
may erase the functional "fingerprint" of various microenvi-
ronmental factors, present in the donor milieu. Cell types with 
a previously documented dysfunctional phenotype in an older 
patient population with ischemic heart disease were only 
exposed to short-term in vitro cell culture (eg, circulating 
angiogenic cells and colony-forming-unit EPCs) or no in vitro 
environment at all (eg, CD133 + /VEGFR2 + circulating EPCs </p>

<p>and bone-marrow-derived MNCs). Hence, "weaning off" 
donor microenvironmental influences and positive selection 
based on proliferation potential were only minimally or not 
present. Specific reports on BOEC functionality and prolifer-
ation potential in various other disease states are, however, 
not uniform. Functional impairment has been reported, related 
to age, 28 type 2 diabetes, 29 obesity, 30 pulmonary arterial 
hypertension, 31 and smoking/chronic obstructive pulmonary 
disease. 32 On the other hand, previous reports in treated 
coronary artery disease 26,33,34 and arterial hypertension 35 
documented similar BOEC functionality in comparison 
to healthy controls. Moreover, improved BOEC functional-
ity has been demonstrated in neovascular age-related 
macular degeneration, 24 ischemic stroke, 22 and extensive 
burns. 25,26,33-35 In comparison to healthy controls, our 
findings did not demonstrate differences in BOEC functionality </p>

<p>hCD31 
BS1-Leccn </p>

<p>DAPI </p>

<p>B1 
B2 </p>

<p>B3 
B4 </p>

<p>hCD31 
BS1-Leccn </p>

<p>DAP 
I </p>

<p>A1 
A2 </p>

<p>A3 
A4 </p>

<p>B5 
A5 </p>

<p>Figure 10. Human BOECs incorporate into murine blood vessels. Immunofluorescence costaining for human CD31 (A1,B1), BS-I-Lectin (A2, </p>

<p>B2), and DAPI nuclear counterstain (A3,B3) demonstrates human BOEC incorporation (red) into murine blood vessels (green) in the adductor (A) 
and gastrocnemius (B) region, 21 days after hindlimb ischemia surgery (scale bar, 20 lm). These findings were confirmed by in situ 
hybridization for primate-specific ALU-repeat sequences on adjacent slides, showing incorporated human BOECs in dark blue (A5,B5) (A5 scale 
bar, 100 lm; B5 scale bar, 50 lm). Field of view of the immunofluorescence images is indicated in red. Engrafted human BOECs are indicated 
by white arrows. ALU indicates Arthrobacter luteus; BOEC(s), blood outgrowth endothelial cell(s); DAPI, 4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole. </p>

<p>ICMP BOECs Retain Neovascularization Potential 
Dauwe et al </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>and proliferation potential in a patient population with severe, 
but stable, ischemic heart failure. We noted, however, mild 
positive correlations between Matrigel network formation 
potential and both degree of systolic LV dysfunction and BMI 
within our patient cohort. No differences were noted in 
response to oxidative stress, studied by ROS induction and 
cell viability. 
We studied in vivo cell-mediated neovascularization poten-
tial using high-resolution angio microCT because of its ability 
to quantitatively assess the complete "vessel tree" in 3D. 
Histology is mainly restricted to evaluating vascular density in 
a limited 2D area of view, whereas laser Doppler flowmetry is 
only reporting superficial blood flow (200-300 lm penetra-
tion depth), classically in the foot region. 36 Collateral vascular 
remodeling (arteriogenesis) has been postulated as the most 
important mechanism to compensate for bulk perfusion loss. 
Efficient collateral formation is a critical determinant of tissue 
vulnerability and preservation during ischemia. Occlusion of 
the femoral artery in a hindlimb ischemia model results in 
development of collateral vessels in the upper leg, relatively 
close to the site of occlusion. In contrast, ischemia and 
angiogenesis occur in the lower leg and foot. 37 We conse-
quently focused on the thigh region as the readout for 
collateral vascular remodeling, and observed that cells from 
both patients and controls support the arteriogenesis process 
to a similar extent, especially at the level of arterioles (32-
64 lm in diameter). Extensive (ultra)structural histological 
analysis by Scholz and Schaper in murine hindlimbs previously 
identified collateral arteries in the 40-to 70-lm diameter 
range. 17,18 We documented a significant BOEC-mediated 
increase in vascular length within this specific size range. 
A trend toward a BOEC-mediated increase of vessel length 
and number of branch points of the complete vessel tree in 
the thigh region of the ligated leg was noted. These results 
did, however, not reach statistical significance, given that the 
therapeutic effects were confined to one specific size range 
(arterioles 32-64 lm in diameter). Arteriogenesis relies on a 
complex interplay of many growth factors, of which ANG-2, 
PLGF, FGF, and PDGF-BB were all demonstrated to be 
secreted by BOECs. 37-40 
Acute retention studies documented BOECs, mainly 
clustered within the perimuscular compartment 24 hours 
after intramuscular injection. At 21 days, we noted disap-
pearance of the BOEC clusters in the perimuscular com-
partment and appearance of isolated BOECs in the vascular 
compartment. We observed only limited incorporation/ 
engraftment of BOECs into functional blood vessels after 
intramuscular delivery of 250 000 cells per mouse, suggest-
ing a concomitant paracrine contribution of the transplanted 
cell population to their neovascularization potential. These 
findings indicate migration toward and engraftment within </p>

<p>the vascular compartment to perform their biological effects, </p>

<p>"sustained" release of a proangiogenic/-arteriogenic growth </p>

<p>factor "cocktail" with or without incorporation into functional 
vessels. ANG-2 and PLGF were found to be the most 
abundantly secreted angiogenic growth factors, independent 
of underlying ischemic disease. Both ANG-2 and PLGF play 
an important role in the complex cytokine cocktail, mediat-
ing the overall neovascularization process in ischemic 
disease. 37-47 
In conclusion, we report that BOECs can be isolated and 
culture-expanded from patients with severe, but stable, ICMP 
and offer an easily accessible, clonally expandable cell source 
with profound neovascularization potential. In contrast to 
impaired functionality of other progenitor cell types derived 
from patients with advanced cardiovascular disease, BOECs 
retain a robust proangiogenic profile in vitro and in vivo and 
hold promise for autologous cell therapy in severe or 
refractory ischemic heart disease. </p>

<p>Sources of Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Research Foundation 
Flanders (FWO), a KULeuven Research Grant (PF\10\014) 
and funds from the ISCIII (PI13/02144, CP09/00333). Nick 
van Gastel is funded by BOF-KU Leuven GOA project 
3M120209. Aernout Luttun is supported by an Interuniversity 
Attraction Poles (IUAP) grant (IUAP/P7/07). </p>

<p>Disclosures </p>

<p>None. </p>



<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.115.002288 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>ICMP BOECs Retain Neovascularization Potential 
Dauwe et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>





<p>ICMP BOECs Retain Neovascularization Potential 
Dauwe et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

</text></tei>