<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4015203" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background/Aims 
Hypnotherapy is considered as a promising intervention for irritable bowel syndrome (IBS), but the evidence is still limited. The 
aims of this study were to conduct a systematic review and meta-analysis to estimate the efficacy of hypnotherapy for the 
treatment of IBS. </p>

<p>Methods 
A literature search was performed using MEDLINE (PubMed), Embase, PsycINFO and the Cochrane Central Register of 
Controlled Trials (CENTRAL database). Only randomized controlled trials that compared hypnotherapy with any other conven-
tional treatment or no treatment in patients with IBS were included. Studies had to report outcomes as IBS symptom score 
or quality of life. The mean change in outcome score was used to pool these outcomes for the meta-analysis. Data were syn-
thesized using the standardized mean difference for continuous data. </p>

<p>Results 
Seven randomized controlled trials (6 papers) involving 374 patients with IBS were identified. Performance bias was high in all 
trials because it was impossible to blind participants and therapists in this type of intervention. The outcomes in this meta-anal-
ysis were evaluated at 3 months for short-term effects and at 1 year for long-term effects. The change in abdominal pain score 
at 3 months was significant in the hypnotherapy group (standardized mean difference, -0.83; 95% CI, -1.65 to -0.01). Three 
of the 4 trials showed greater improvement in overall gastrointestinal symptoms in the hypnotherapy group. </p>

<p>Conclusions 
This study provides clearer evidence that hypnotherapy has beneficial short-term effects in improving gastrointestinal symptoms 
of patients with IBS. 
(J Neurogastroenterol Motil 2014;20:152-162) </p>

<p>Irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) is a chronic functional gas-
trointestinal disorder characterized by recurrent abdominal pain 
or discomfort associated with altered bowel movements. 
1 IBS can </p>

<p>be diagnosed only when there is no objective evidence of an un-
derlying organic disorder. 
2 It is one of the most common bowel </p>

<p>disorders diagnosed by gastroenterologists. 
3 The impact of IBS </p>

<p>on quality of life (QOL) is as strong as that observed in other se-
rious disorders such as congestive heart failure or chronic renal 
failure. </p>

<p>4,5 </p>

<p>Treatment options include reassurance, dietary modification, 
and pharmacological treatment. Current pharmacological treat-
ments such as bulking agents, antispasmodics, and antidepressants 
focus mainly on controlling the symptoms of IBS. However, both 
pharmacological and conventional options are unsatisfactory in 
general. </p>

<p>6-8 </p>

<p>Many IBS patients have psychological symptoms such as 
anxiety and depression, 
9 which provide a fundamental rationale </p>

<p>for psychological treatment. A number of studies have been con-
ducted to evaluate the effects of psychological treatment for 
IBS. 
10 Among them, hypnotherapy has gained popularity after </p>

<p>the first randomized controlled trial (RCT) in 1984 demonstrat-
ing notable benefits of hypnotherapy. 
11 Several additional studies </p>

<p>have also reported benefits of hypnotherapy in treating gastro-
intestinal symptoms and QOL of IBS patients. </p>

<p>12-16 </p>

<p>Previous systematic reviews to prove that there are statisti-
cally significant benefits have been based on pooled results of re-
search on the effectiveness of hypnotherapy for IBS patients. </p>

<p>17,18 </p>

<p>These reviews concluded that, although a number of studies have 
shown a beneficial effect of hypnotherapy, insufficient evidence 
existed to recommend widespread use because of limitations in 
the sample sizes and methodological flaws. From these con-
clusions, the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence 
guidelines noted that hypnotherapy is a promising intervention 
for IBS but the evidence remains to be limited. 
19 These un-</p>

<p>certainties justify a systematic review and meta-analysis to de-
termine whether hypnotherapy has significant beneficial effects in 
the treatment of IBS. Well-designed RCTs have been con-
ducted, but there is no ongoing RCT; this prompted us to update 
the previous review. We conducted a comprehensive review of 
RCTs to estimate the efficacy of hypnotherapy for the treatment 
of IBS. </p>

<p>M aterials and M ethods </p>

<p>Eligibility Criteria </p>

<p>The inclusion criteria in this study were specified in advance 
and followed the population, intervention, comparison and out-
come(s) (PICO) study design: patients who had been diagnosed 
with IBS as the population of interest, given hypnotherapy as an 
intervention, or given any other conventional treatment or no 
treatment for comparison. Outcomes were overall gastrointestinal 
symptoms, individual gastrointestinal symptoms (abdominal 
pain, constipation and diarrhea) and QOL, which were measured 
as scores. Any studies that reported at least one of these outcomes 
were included. Only RCTs were included in this meta-analysis to 
provide more unbiased information than that obtained from other 
study designs. There was no limitation on publication language, 
study size or study setting. Patients were not otherwise restricted 
by age or ethics. Studies that included a comparison between dif-
ferent types of hypnotherapy were excluded. </p>

<p>Search Strategy </p>

<p>A literature search was conducted using MEDLINE 
(PubMed), Embase, PsycINFO, and the Cochrane Central 
Register of Controlled Trials (CENTRAL database) from 
January 15, 2013. The search was performed using the Medical 
Subject Headings (MeSH): "colonic diseases," "colonic dis-
eases, functional," "irritable bowel syndrome," and "hypnosis." 
Other free-text search terms used were "irritable bowel syn-
drome," "hypnotherapy," "hypnosis," "mesmerism," "imagery" 
and "autohypnosis." Search terms were adapted according to 
each particular database. The strategy was refined further by a lo-
cal health care librarian to ensure a good balance of sensitivity and 
specificity. Electronic searches were supplemented by manually 
searching the bibliographies of eligible clinical trials and previous 
systematic reviews. </p>

<p>Study Selection and Data Extraction </p>

<p>Two authors (H.H.L. and Y.Y.C.) independently screened 
the titles and abstracts of the papers identified by the initial search 
for relevance to this review. We retrieved the full text for any cita-
tion deemed potentially eligible at this stage. Two authors then 
separately assessed full articles using predetermined inclusion cri-
teria to exclude irrelevant articles. Any disagreements regarding 
study inclusion were resolved by discussion. Data from the in-</p>

<p>Han Hee Lee, et al </p>

<p>Journal of Neurogastroenterology and Motility </p>



<p>Figure 1. Flow diagram of studies iden-
tified in the systematic review. IBS, irri-
table bowel syndrome; RCT, randomiz-
ed controlled trial. </p>

<p>cluded studies were extracted by 2 authors to a <rs id="software-4" type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs> 
spreadsheet (XP Professional; <rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Microsoft Corp</rs>, Redmond, WA, 
USA). Conflicts in data extraction were resolved by consensus af-
ter referring back to the original article. 
Searches of 4 of the electronic bibliographic databases ini-
tially identified 139 potentially relevant citations. Two additional 
studies were found by cross-referencing. Our search strategy 
identified 98 citations after removing duplicates, 30 of which 
were retrieved for full-text assessment, and a total of 7 RCTs ulti-
mately fulfilled our inclusion criteria (Fig. 1). 
11,20-24 One study </p>

<p>reported 2 RCTs being conducted on different settings in one 
publication. 
20 One of the studies that we initially excluded was </p>

<p>published only in abstract form. As we were conducting our 
meta-analysis, advance online publication of this study was re-
ported in February 2013, so we have included it in our review. </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Agreement between authors for trial eligibility was substantial (k 
statistic = 0.79). </p>

<p>Quality Assessment </p>

<p>Two authors independently assessed the methodological 
quality of the included trials using the risk of bias tool recom-
mended by the Cochrane Collaboration. 
25 This included random </p>

<p>sequence generation, allocation concealment, blinding of partic-
ipants and personnel, blinding of outcome assessment, assess-
ment of incomplete data outcome, selective reporting and other 
sources of bias. For each trial, the risk of bias was reported as 
"low risk," "unclear risk" or "high risk." Disagreement was re-
solved by discussion. </p>

<p>Data Analysis </p>

<p>All the assessed outcomes were continuous variables. 
Although the studies included in our review reported similar out-
comes, various measurement instruments were applied to calcu-
late the scores. The mean change in the outcome score was calcu-
lated and used to compare these outcomes by subtracting the 
baseline score from the score after treatment. The standard devia-</p>

<p>Hypnotherapy and IBS </p>

<p>Vol. 20, No. 2 April, 2014 (152-162) </p>



<p>Table 1. </p>

<p>Characteristics of Included Studies </p>

<p>Author 
(yr) </p>

<p>Country 
(setting) Population Definition of </p>

<p>IBS </p>

<p>Exclusion 
criteria </p>

<p>Age 
(range, 
yr) </p>

<p>Sex 
(M:F) 
No. of patients 
(intervention: 
control) </p>

<p>Intervention </p>

<p>Control 
Allowed other 
medication </p>

<p>Outcomes </p>

<p>Scale </p>

<p>Whorwell </p>

<p>et al 11 
(1984) </p>

<p>UK 
(university 
hospital) </p>

<p>Refractory </p>

<p>IBS, at least 
1 year </p>

<p>Abdominal pain, </p>

<p>a disordered 
bowel habit, and 
abdominal 
distention 
(predated the 
Rome criteria) </p>

<p>Organic GI 
disease, 
psychiatric 
disorder </p>

<p>24-53 4:26 </p>

<p>15:15 </p>

<p>GDH: </p>

<p>7 sessions of 
30 min+ 
autohypnosis 
Placebo with 
supportive 
psychotherapy </p>

<p>: 7 sessions of 30 
min </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Abdominal pain 
Abdominal distension </p>

<p>Bowel habit 
General wellbeing </p>

<p>4-graded Likert scale 
(none [0] to severe 
[3]) 
4-graded Likert scale </p>

<p>(no improvement [0] 
to maximum 
improvement [3]) </p>

<p>Galovski </p>

<p>et al 21 
(1998) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>Refractory </p>

<p>IBS, at least 
6 months </p>

<p>Rome I, 
diagnosed by 
physician or 
gastroentero-</p>

<p>logist </p>

<p>Psychiatric 
disorder, 
language barrier </p>

<p>23-58 2:9 </p>

<p>5:6 </p>

<p>GDH: 
12 sessions of 
30-60 min </p>

<p>Symptom 
monitoring </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>CPSR </p>

<p>5-graded Likert scale 
(symptom absent [0] </p>

<p>to debilitating 
symptom [4]) </p>

<p>Palsson 
et al 22 
(2002) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>Refractory </p>

<p>IBS, at least 
1 year </p>

<p>Rome I </p>

<p>Abdominal 
surgery history, 
organic GI 
disease, 
psychotropic 
medication </p>

<p>Mean 
39.1 </p>

<p>9:15 </p>

<p>15:9 </p>

<p>GDH: </p>

<p>7 sessions of 
45 min </p>

<p>Symptom 
monitoring </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Abdominal pain 
Bloating 
Proportion of hard or </p>

<p>loose stools 
Bowel movements per 
day </p>

<p>5-graded Likert scale 
(none [0] to 
incapacitating [4]) </p>

<p>4-graded Likert scale 
(hard, firm, soft and 
watery) </p>

<p>Roberts </p>

<p>et al 23 
(2006) </p>

<p>UK </p>

<p>Refractory </p>

<p>IBS, at least 
6 months </p>

<p>Diagnosed by 
general 
practitioner 
(criteria used 
IBS diagnosis 
not specified) </p>

<p>Atypical GI 
symptoms </p>

<p>Aged over 65 
years </p>

<p>18-65 12:69 </p>

<p>40:41 </p>

<p>GDH: </p>

<p>5 sessions of 
30 min </p>

<p>Symptom 
monitoring 
Usual medical 
therapy </p>

<p>IBS-specific QOL </p>

<p>(8 dimensions: 
dysphoria, inter-
ference with activity, 
body image, health 
worry, food avoi-
dance, social reac-
tion, sexual function 
and relationships) 
Full symptom score 
(3 dimensions: pain, 
constipation and 
diarrhea) </p>

<p>0-100 scale 
(increasing scores 
denoting more severe 
symptoms) </p>

<p>Lindfors </p>

<p>et al 20 
(2012) 
study 1 </p>

<p>Sweden 
(university 
hospital) </p>

<p>Refractory </p>

<p>IBS </p>

<p>Rome II </p>

<p>Organic GI 
disease, severe 
co-existing 
disease, 
psychotropic </p>

<p>drugs or 
antidepressants 
21-68 19:71 </p>

<p>45:45 </p>

<p>GDH 
(Manchester 
protocol): </p>

<p>12 sessions of 
60 min+ 
autohypnosis 
Dietary advice 
Information </p>

<p>about relaxation 
training 
Education 
Nursing support </p>

<p>by telephone </p>

<p>Antidiarrheals, </p>

<p>bulking 
agents, 
spasmolytics </p>

<p>GI-symptom 
questionnaire </p>

<p>(2 domains: sensory 
symptoms score 
[pain, bloating and 
gas] and bowel habit 
score [loose stools, 
urgency, hard stools </p>

<p>and incomplete 
evacuation]) 
IBS-QOL </p>

<p>(9 dimensions: 
emotional function-</p>

<p>ing, mental health, 
sleep, energy, physi-
cal functioning, diet, 
social role, physical 
role and sexual 
relations) </p>

<p>The HAD scale 
(14 items, with 7 
items relating to 
anxiety and 7 items 
related to depression) </p>

<p>7-graded Likert scale 
(none [1] to very 
severe [7]): 
total symptom 
severity score (7-49) 
0-100 scale (100 
representing the best </p>

<p>possible QOL) 
4-graded Likert scale 
(0-3) </p>

<p>Han Hee Lee, et al </p>

<p>Journal of Neurogastroenterology and Motility </p>



<p>Table 1. </p>

<p>Continued </p>

<p>Author 
(yr) </p>

<p>Country 
(setting) Population Definition of </p>

<p>IBS </p>

<p>Exclusion 
criteria </p>

<p>Age 
(range, 
yr) </p>

<p>Sex 
(M:F) 
No. of patients 
(intervention: 
control) </p>

<p>Intervention </p>

<p>Control 
Allowed other 
medication </p>

<p>Outcomes </p>

<p>Scale </p>

<p>Lindfors </p>

<p>et al 20 
(2012) 
study 2 </p>

<p>Sweden 
(county 
hospital) </p>

<p>Refractory </p>

<p>IBS </p>

<p>Rome II </p>

<p>Organic GI 
disease, severe 
co-existing 
disease, 
psychotropic </p>

<p>drugs or 
antidepressants 
21-60 9:39 </p>

<p>25:23 </p>

<p>GDH 
(Manchester 
protocol): </p>

<p>12 sessions of 
60 min+ 
autohypnosis </p>

<p>Symptom 
monitoring </p>

<p>Antidiarrheals, </p>

<p>bulking 
agents, 
spasmolytics </p>

<p>GSRS-IBS </p>

<p>(5 domains: pain, 
bloating, 
constipation, </p>

<p>diarrhea and satiety) 
SF-36 
The HAD scale </p>

<p>7-graded Likert scale </p>

<p>(no discomfort [1] to 
very severe 
discomfort [7]) </p>

<p>0-100 scale (100 
representing the best </p>

<p>possible QOL) 
4-graded Likert scale 
(0-3) </p>

<p>Moser 
et al 24 
(2013) </p>

<p>Austria 
(university 
hospital) </p>

<p>Refractory </p>

<p>IBS </p>

<p>Rome III </p>

<p>Pregnancy, bowel 
surgery, mental 
retardation, 
language barrier, 
psychiatric 
disease, recent 
unstable dose of 
antidepressants 
18-70 19:71 </p>

<p>46:44 </p>

<p>GDH 
(Manchester 
protocol): </p>

<p>10 sessions of 
45 min+ 
autohypnosis </p>

<p>+ SMT </p>

<p>SMT: 
10 sessions of 45 
min </p>

<p>Spasmolytics, 
antidiarrheals 
IBS impact scale 
(5 domains: fatigue, 
impact on daily 
activities, sleep 
disturbance, 
emotional distress </p>

<p>and eating habits) 
IBS single symptoms 
(abdominal pain, 
diarrhea, 
constipation and 
flatulence) </p>

<p>SF-36 
The HAD scale 
7-graded Likert scale 
(decreases with 
increasing IBS 
symptom severity) </p>

<p>0-100 scale 
(increasing scores 
denoting more severe 
symptoms) </p>

<p>0-100 scale (100 
representing the best </p>

<p>possible QOL) 
4-graded Likert scale 
(0-3) </p>

<p>IBS, irritable bowel syndrome; GI, gastrointestinal; FAP, functional abdominal pain; GDH, gut-directed hypnotherapy; NA, not allowed; CPSR, composite primary symptom reduction; QOL, quality of life; GSRS, 
gastrointestinal symptom rating scale; SF-36, short form 36; HAD, hospital anxiety and depression; SMT, supportive talks and medical treatment. </p>

<p>Hypnotherapy and IBS </p>

<p>Vol. 20, No. 2 April, 2014 (152-162) </p>



<p>Figure 2. Assessment of risk of bias in this meta-analysis. Risk of bias summary. (A) Summary of risk of bias for each trial assessed by Cochrane 
Collaboration' tool, plus sign was for a judgment of Yes or low risk of bias, minus sign was for a judgment of No or high risk of bias, and question mark 
was for a judgment of Unclear, or uncertain risk of bias, which meant there was insufficient information to permit a judgment of Yes or No. Risk of 
bias graph. (B) Risk of bias graph about each risk of bias item presented as percentages across all included studies. </p>

<p>tion (SD) is needed for use of the change score in a meta-analysis. 
One trial presented the standard deviation of the changes in their 
report. 
20 From these data, we calculated the correlation co-</p>

<p>efficient by using the following formula. </p>

<p>        ×       ×      
      </p>

<p> </p>

<p>      </p>

<p> </p>

<p>     </p>

<p> </p>

<p>We also used the following formula to calculate the SD of the 
change by using the correlation coefficient in the studies that did 
not report this value. </p>

<p>      </p>

<p>   </p>

<p> </p>

<p>  ×  ×   ×    </p>

<p>To combine the different scales, we used the standardized mean 
difference (SMD) rather than the actual means because the 
SMD does not depend on the measurement scale. To evaluate 
the magnitude of the effect size calculated by SMD, Cohen's cat-
egories were used with 0.0-0.2 = not a substantial effect size, ＞ 
0.2-0.5 = a small effect size, ＞ 0.5-0.8 = a medium effect size, 
and ＞ 0.8 = a large effect size. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>Meta-analysis was performed using the software <rs id="software-1" type="software">Review 
Manager</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 5.2.3</rs> (RevMan for Windows 7; the Nordic 
Cochrane Center, Copenhagen, Denmark) provided by the 
Cochrane Collaboration. Meta-analysis was performed using a 
fixed-effects model and a random-effects model for each out-
come, and the analyses were compared. A P-value ＜ 0.05 was 
considered significant. 
Statistical heterogeneity among studies was assessed using 
the χ 
2 test, defining a significant heterogeneity as a P-value ＜ </p>

<p>0.1, and was quantified by measuring I </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. An I 
2 value ＞ 50% sug-</p>

<p>gested significant statistical heterogeneity. The fixed-effects 
model of meta-analysis was used in the case of statistical homoge-
neity, whereas in the case of statistical heterogeneity, the ran-
dom-effects model was applied. Analysis and reporting followed 
the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and 
Meta-analyses (PRISMA) guidelines. 
27 Forest plots of SMDs </p>

<p>for the assessed outcomes with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) 
and funnel plots were generated. The latter were assessed for evi-
dence of asymmetry and therefore possible reporting bias or pub-
lication bias. </p>

<p>Han Hee Lee, et al </p>

<p>Journal of Neurogastroenterology and Motility </p>



<p>Figure 3. Forest plots of abdominal pain change score. (A) Meta-analysis of 3 months results. (B) Meta-analysis of 1-year results. GDH, gut-directed 
hypnotherapy; Std., standardized. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Description of Included Studies </p>

<p>The characteristics of the included studies are shown in 
Table 1. A total of 374 patients (74 men and 300 women) were 
included in this meta-analysis: 191 patients were in the hyp-
notherapy group and 183 patients were in the control group. 
Gut-directed hypnotherapy (GDH) was applied to the patients 
as an intervention in all 7 trials. The frequency of this inter-
vention varied from 5 to 12 sessions, and the duration of each ses-
sion varied from 30 to 60 minutes. Three of the included trials 
used the Manchester protocol for GDH. 
20,24,28 Moser et al deliv-</p>

<p>ered GDH in group sessions. 
24 Four trials performed GDH </p>

<p>with usual medical therapy or supportive talks and medical 
treatment. 
20,23,24 Various methods were used for the control </p>

<p>groups. Four trials monitored symptoms only in the control 
group, 
20-23 and others provided supportive and medical therapy. </p>

<p>All trials included as outcomes IBS-related gastrointestinal 
symptoms. QOL was assessed in 4 trials. 
20,23,24 No adverse events </p>

<p>were reported in any trial. </p>

<p>Risk of Bias </p>

<p>The quality of RCTs included in our review was assessed by 
the Cochrane risk of bias tool (Fig. 2). Selection bias was shown 
in one trial because its method was not optimal for ensuring ad-
equate allocation concealment. 
21 Performance bias was high in all </p>

<p>trials because it was not possible to blind participants and thera-
pists in this type of intervention. Attrition bias was high in 2 
trials. 
23,24 Other type of bias was high in one trial. Four trials used </p>

<p>intention-to-treat analysis, 
11,20,24 and the others did not. </p>

<p>Effects </p>

<p>The data for 6 of the 7 included RCTs were pooled for 
analysis. 
20-24 The data of one study were not available for analysis </p>

<p>after we tried unsuccessfully to correspond with the author. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>The outcomes were evaluated at 3 months for short-term 
effects. In the cases of short-term effects, although some studies 
reported their results at 2 or 4 months, we regarded them as the 
same period as 3 months. The long-term outcomes were meas-
ured at 1 year. </p>

<p>Abdominal pain </p>

<p>Four RCTs reported an abdominal pain change score. </p>

<p>20, 22-24 </p>

<p>Hypnotherapy and IBS </p>

<p>Vol. 20, No. 2 April, 2014 (152-162) </p>



<p>Figure 4. Forest plots of constipation change score at 3 months (A) and 1 year (B), diarrhea change score at 3 months (C) and 1 year (D). GDH, 
gut-directed hypnotherapy; Std., standardized. </p>

<p>Three reported it at 3 months, 
20,22,23 which showed a significant </p>

<p>difference in favor of the GDH group (SMD -0.83; 95% CI, 
-1.65 to -0.01; P = 0.050) (Fig. 3A). The random-effects model 
was used because there was considerable heterogeneity (I 
2 = </p>

<p>77%, P = 0.010). Based on Cohen's categories, the effect size of 
the abdominal pain change score at 3 months was large. The ab-</p>

<p>dominal pain change score at 1 year was reported by 2 of the 4 
RCTs. 
23,24 Meta-analysis using the fixed-effects model showed a </p>

<p>significant difference in favor of the GDH group (SMD, -0.53; 
95% CI, -0.90 to -0.15; P = 0.006). However, there was consid-
erable heterogeneity (I 
2 = 84%, P = 0.010). When the random-</p>

<p>effects model was used, there was no significant difference </p>

<p>Han Hee Lee, et al </p>

<p>Journal of Neurogastroenterology and Motility </p>



<p>Table 2. Change in Overall Gastrointestinal Symptom Score </p>

<p>Author (yr) 
Outcome measurement 
3 months 
P-value 
12 months 
P-value 
Intervention (SD) Control (SD) 
Intervention (SD) Control (SD) </p>

<p>Galovski et al 21 (1998) 
CPSR a 
-0.55 (0.53) 
0.32 (0.49) 
0.00047 
NA 
NA 
NA 
Roberts et al 
23 (2006) 
Full symptom score 
-13.00 (10.50) 
-4.5 (13.90) 
0.008 
-9.10 (14.00) -6.40 (14.70) 0.440 
Lindfors et al 
20 (2012) study 1 GI-symptom questionnaire 
-4.50 (8.60) 
-0.80 (7.30) ＜ 0.05 
NA 
NA 
NA 
Lindfors et al 20 (2012) study 2 GSRS-IBS 
-0.43 (0.90) 
-0.10 (1.00) 
0.220 
NA 
NA 
NA </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>CPSR was measured at right after end of treatment. 
SD, standard deviation; CPSR, composite primary symptom reduction; NA, not allowed; GSRS, gastrointestinal symptom rating scale; IBS, irritable bowel syndrome. </p>

<p>(SMD, -0.52; 95% CI, -1.47 to 0.44; P = 0.290) (Fig. 3B). </p>

<p>Constipation and diarrhea </p>

<p>The constipation change score was reported by 3 RCTs. </p>

<p>20,23,24 </p>

<p>Two of these 3 trials reported this score at 3 months, 
20,23 and this </p>

<p>value did not change significantly (SMD, -0.12; 95% CI, -0.49 
to 0.25; P = 0.520) (Fig. 4A). The constipation change score at 
1 year was reported by 2 of the 3 RCTs. 
23,24 Meta-analysis </p>

<p>showed no significant difference (SMD, -0.33; 95% CI, -0.70 to 
0.04; P = 0.080) (Fig. 4B). Meta-analysis of the diarrhea change 
score at 3 months was reported by 2 RCTs, 
20,23 and there was no </p>

<p>significant difference (SMD, -0.36; 95% CI, -0.74 to 0.01; P = 
0.060) (Fig. 4C). The diarrhea change score at 1 year was re-
ported by 2 RCTs, 
23,24 and the meta-analysis showed no sig-</p>

<p>nificant difference (SMD, -0.16; 95% CI, -0.52 to 0.21; P = 
0.400) (Fig. 4D). </p>

<p>Overall gastrointestinal symptoms </p>

<p>Four trials attempted to measure the overall gastrointestinal 
symptom score in IBS patients (Table 2). Different studies used 
different assessment tools, and these studies were not eligible to 
be combined for the meta-analysis. Three trials showed that the 
hypnotherapy group had greater improvement in the overall gas-
trointestinal symptom score at 3 months compared with the con-
trol group, whereas the difference in the symptom score did not 
differ significantly between the 2 groups in the other trial. Only 
one trial reported the result at 1 year, and there was no significant 
difference between the hypnotherapy group and control group. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>The studies by Lindfors et al 
20 (studies 1 and 2 in Table 2) did </p>

<p>not report the overall gastrointestinal symptom scores at 12 
months in the control group because it was considered unethical 
to not allow the controls to receive hypnotherapy available in their 
clinical settings. Thus, we could not compare the change in over-
all gastrointestinal symptom scores at 12 months between the </p>

<p>hypnotherapy and control groups. </p>

<p>Quality of life </p>

<p>Four RCTs measured QOL. 
20,23,24 Two used a generic </p>

<p>health-related QOL measure (short-form 36 health survey 
[SF-36]). 
20,24 Study 2 of Lindfors et al 
20 showed no significant </p>

<p>differences in SF-36 scores between the GDH group and control 
group. Moser et al 
24 reported a significant improvement in QOL </p>

<p>scores at 3 months and 1 year in 4 dimensions (role physical, gen-
eral health, vitality and social functioning) and at 1 year in 3 more 
dimensions (physical functioning, bodily pain and mental health) 
compared with the control groups. 
Three trials used disease-specific QOL instruments. </p>

<p>20,23,24 </p>

<p>Roberts et al used an IBS-specific QOL measure 
13 and found no </p>

<p>significant difference in QOL scores between the hypnotherapy 
and control groups at 3 months and 1 year. 
23 Study 1 of Lindfors </p>

<p>et al 
20 used an IBS-specific QOL measure 29 and reported a sig-</p>

<p>nificant improvement at 3 months in the GDH group in the di-
mensions of mental health, sleep, energy and social role versus 
baseline. 
20 This improvement was maintained significantly at 1 </p>

<p>year, and additional improvement in emotional functioning was 
identified. However, there was no significant difference in the 
changes in QOL at 3 months between the GDH group and con-
trol group. Moser et al 
24 used an IBS-impact scale, a dis-</p>

<p>ease-specific documentation of the impact of IBS on patients' 
lives. 
30 In this study, the hypnotherapy group showed a sig-</p>

<p>nificant improvement in IBS-impact scale scores at 3 months and 
1 year compared with the control group. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We reviewed 7 RCTs with a total of 374 patients that com-
pared hypnotherapy with various control treatments to examine 
whether hypnotherapy as treatment for IBS would have sig-</p>

<p>Hypnotherapy and IBS </p>

<p>Vol. 20, No. 2 April, 2014 (152-162) </p>



<p>nificant beneficial effects on gastrointestinal symptoms and QOL. 
This review is the first study to conduct a meta-analysis of the ef-
ficacy of hypnotherapy in IBS patients. This meta-analysis re-
vealed that hypnotherapy significantly improved abdominal pain, 
at least at short-term follow-up. Hypnotherapy also provided 
benefit for overall gastrointestinal symptoms. However, evidence 
for the long-term efficacy of hypnotherapy is lacking because of 
an insufficient number of studies. 
Our search strategy was comprehensive in that we used 4 da-
tabases, distinct inclusion criteria and the Cochrane risk of bias 
tool for each trial. The previous reviews included insufficient evi-
dences because of the small number of RCTs and methodological 
flaws. 
17,18 Our study provides more reliable evidence by includ-</p>

<p>ing 3 recent well-designed RCTs. 
Randomization is especially important in trials of fluctuating 
diseases such as IBS, since recruitment of patients to a trial usu-
ally occurs during a period of increased symptomatology. 
17 The </p>

<p>current study included only RCTs whose aim was to establish the 
effectiveness of hypnotherapy. The calculation of a summary 
measure of effect had been difficult because of heterogeneity in 
the outcome measures in the previous reviews. Likert scales of 
different grades were used to obtain scores for abdominal pain 
and symptoms of defecatory dysfunction in individual trials. In 
this meta-analysis, we used the SMD as a summary statistic for 
studies that assessed the same outcome but measured it with dif-
ferent methods. 
In this meta-analysis, the potential benefits of hypnotherapy 
in treating constipation and diarrhea were not verified because of 
insufficient power and internal validity. In addition, patient-re-
ported ratings of changes in bowel habits were not able to delin-
eate adequately whether any benefits were achieved in all of the 
important subconcepts (i.e., urgency, stool consistency and stool 
frequency). Further trials should include a predefined definition 
and grade for bowel habits such as the British stool scale to eval-
uate benefits precisely. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>GDH involves hypnotic induction by using a variety of tech-
niques, including progressive relaxation, followed by creating im-
agery related to symptom control and normalization of gut 
function. The mechanism through which hypnotherapy improves 
abdominal pain in IBS patients is not well understood. Hypnotic 
reduction of somatic pain is thought to reduce the activation of 
certain areas of the brain, which appears to be exaggerated in 
IBS. 
32 It is also assumed that hypnotherapy normalizes visceral </p>

<p>sensation, decreases colonic phasic contractions, and reverses 
negative thoughts of IBS patients about their condition. </p>

<p>33-35 </p>

<p>Although 3 more RCTs were added in this meta-analysis af-
ter the last systematic review, the number of included studies was 
too small to draw firm conclusions. The control groups varied 
somewhat between studies, from no treatment to supportive ther-
apy; however, separate comparisons of the different control treat-
ments were not conducted because of the limited number of in-
cluded trials. Difficulties in blinding because of the nature of the 
intervention also contribute to the potential for performance bias. 
In conclusion, hypnotherapy may be a useful and safe ther-
apeutic option for refractory IBS in short term. More high-qual-
ity RCTs are needed for evaluating the long-term efficacy of 
hypnotherapy. All of the included studies targeted refractory 
IBS; therefore, the beneficial effects of hypnotherapy cannot be 
generalized to all IBS patients. </p>



<p>Han Hee Lee, et al </p>

<p>Journal of Neurogastroenterology and Motility </p>





</text></tei>