<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4453596" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: As more patients are treated by haematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT), development of secondary 
malignancy (SM) becomes an increasingly common issue in long-term survivors. </p>

<p>Methods: We conducted a nationwide population-based study of the Taiwanese population to analyse patients who 
received HSCT between January 1997 and December 2010. Standardised incidence ratios (SIRs) were used to compare the 
risk of SM in HSCT patients and the general population. Multivariate analysis was performed to identify independent predictors of 
SM. </p>

<p>Results: Patients receiving HSCT had a significantly greater risk of developing SM (SIR 2.00; 95% confidence interval (CI) 1.45-2.69; 
Po0.001). Specifically, the incidence increased for cancers of the oral cavity (SIR 14.18) and oesophagus (SIR 14.75) after allogeneic 
HSCT. Multivariate analysis revealed an increased SIR for cancer in patients who received the immunosuppressant azathioprine. 
The risk of SM also increased with greater cumulative doses of azathioprine. </p>

<p>Conclusions: This study demonstrates an increased incidence of SM in Taiwanese patients who received allogeneic HSCT, 
especially for cancers of the oral cavity and oesophagus. This finding is different from results in populations of Western countries. 
Physicians should be cautious about azathioprine use for graft-vs-host disease after HSCT. </p>

<p>*Correspondence: Dr J-P Gau; E-mail: jpgau@vghtpe.gov.tw or Dr C-J Liu; E-mail: chiajenliu@gmail.com </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>J-P Gau and C-J Liu share co-corresponding authorship. </p>

<p>Received 3 June 2014; revised 1 September 2014; accepted 7 September 2014; published online 14 October 2014 </p>

<p>&amp; 2015 Cancer Research UK. All rights reserved 0007 -0920/15 </p>

<p>FULL PAPER </p>

<p>Keywords: cancer risk; epidemiology; haematopoietic stem cell transplantation; population study; secondary malignancy </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2015) 112, 177-184 | doi: 10.1038/bjc.2014.523 </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.523 </p>

<p>
Since 1983, haematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) has 
been widely used to treat and cure many malignant and benign 
haematological diseases in Taiwan (Chen et al, 2008). Although the 
overall survival after transplantation has gradually improved, 
important concerns remain regarding long-term complications of 
HSCT, such as secondary malignancy (SM), chronic graft-vs-host 
disease (cGVHD), infertility, and quality of life (La Nasa et al, 
2013). Recently, the development of SM has become a serious 
complication resulting in substantial mortality (Yokota et al, 2012). 
Many studies conducted in Western countries have reported 
that HSCT increases the risk of SM, especially in patients receiving 
total body irradiation (TBI) or immunosuppressants and in 
patients with cGVHD (Curtis et al, 1997, 2005; Rizzo et al, 2009; 
Majhail, 2011; Majhail et al, 2011). However, few studies have 
examined SM after HSCT in Asian populations. Moreover, the 
reported incidences and subtypes of secondary cancers are 
different from those reported in Western countries (Shimada 
et al, 2005; Yokota et al, 2012). To explore this issue in Taiwan, we 
conducted a nationwide population-based study using data from 
Taiwan's National Health Insurance (NHI) Research Database 
(NHIRD) to determine the incidence of SM after HSCT in the 
Taiwanese population. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Data sources. Taiwan's NHI is a mandatory universal health 
insurance programme that was established in 1995 to provide 
comprehensive medical care coverage for 499% of Taiwanese 
residents (Wu et al, 2012). The NHI covers prescription 
medications and outpatient, inpatient, emergency, and surgical 
services. The database includes enrollment files, prescription 
information, and coding for major procedures. This study is 
mainly based on data from the NHIRD, which is managed and 
publicly released by the National Health Research Institute (NHRI) 
of Taiwan. 
In Taiwan, patients who receive HSCT or have malignant 
diseases are classified in the 'Catastrophic Illness' group and 
maintained in a separate NHRI database (Catastrophic Illness 
Registry). Assignment to the Catastrophic Illness classification 
requires a definitive diagnosis based on pathological findings or 
clinical evidence that is widely accepted as sufficient to make a 
diagnosis. Confidentiality of data is managed and overseen by 
regulators of the Bureau of the NHI and the NHRI. This study was 
approved by the institutional review board of the Taipei Veterans 
General Hospital (2013-10-002CE). </p>

<p>Identification of patients receiving HSCT. We conducted a 
retrospective cohort study from 1 January 1997 to 31 December 
2010. We identified patients who received a first course of HSCT 
within the observation period based on the reimbursement for 
HSCT. To avoid confusion between primary malignancies treated 
by HSCT and SMs after HSCT, we only included patients receiving 
HSCT for haematologic malignancies, thalassaemia major, or 
severe aplastic anaemia. Patients receiving HSCT for solid organ 
cancers or immune deficiencies, metabolic disorders, or other 
congenital diseases were excluded. To avoid surveillance bias 
(Bilimoria et al, 2013; Chiolero et al, 2013), patients who developed 
cancers within 1 year after HSCT, as well as those who were 
followed for o1 year after HSCT were excluded. The following 
information was collected for all patients: basic data, comorbidities, 
primary diagnosis before HSCT, transplantation type (e.g., 
allogeneic HSCT (allo-HSCT) or autologous HSCT (auto-HSCT)), 
TBI, use of immunosuppressive agents, and cGVHD status. A 
diagnosis of cGVHD was made by an experienced haematologist 
who reviewed data regarding patterns of immunosuppressant use. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses. The main dependent variable was the 
occurrence of solid organ cancers that were recorded in 
the Catastrophic Illness Registry. Patients were followed until the 
development of solid cancer, death, dropout from the NHI 
programme, or the end of 2011. Risk of SM in the HSCT cohort 
was calculated as the standardised incidence ratio (SIR), defined as 
the observed number of SM occurrence divided by the expected 
number of cases. The expected number was determined by 
multiplying the national incidence rate (in 5-year intervals) of 
same cancers stratified by gender, calendar year, and age, by the 
corresponding stratum-specific person-time accrued in this cohort. 
Incidence rates of cancers in the general population were obtained 
from the Taiwan Cancer Registry. The 95% confidence intervals 
(CIs) for the SIRs were estimated under the assumption that the 
number of cancers followed a Poisson probability distribution. We 
determined the SIRs for subgroups defined by age at HSCT, sex, 
follow-up time since HSCT, and stem cell type. In addition, the SIR 
was estimated for each SM subtype. 
Physical comorbidities before HSCT, immunosuppressant use, 
and cGVHD development were analysed to determine hazard 
ratios for SM. Categorical variables were compared by Fisher's 
exact or chi-square tests. Continuous variables were compared with 
the Mann-Whitney U-test. Univariate and multivariate Cox 
proportional hazards models were utilised to identify predictors 
of SM in HSCT patients. All factors with a P-value of o0.1 in the 
univariate analyses were included in the Cox multivariate analysis. 
Effects of immunosuppressant use after HSCT were treated as 
time-dependent variables to prevent an immortal time bias. 
Furthermore, if one type of immunosuppressant had a significant 
effect on SM in the Cox multivariate model, the effects of 
cumulative doses were estimated by time-dependent Cox propor-
tional hazards models using cutoff points at non-use and the 50th 
percentile. 
Data extraction and computations were performed with the <rs id="software-1" type="software">Perl</rs> 
programming language (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 5.12.2</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Perl Foundation, Walnut,CA, USA</rs>). <rs id="software-2" type="software">Microsoft SQL Server 2005</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">(Microsoft Corp., Redmond,WA, USA)</rs>) was used for data linkage, processing, and sampling. All 
statistical analyses were performed with the SAS <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">9.2</rs> software (SAS 
Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA). Statistical significance was defined 
as a P-value of o0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Clinical characteristics of the study population. A total of 4014 
patients who received HSCT between 1997 and 2010 were 
identified. After excluding patients who were treated with HSCT 
for metabolic disorders, severe combined immunodeficiency, or 
solid cancers (n ¼ 230), who had solid cancer before HSCT 
(n ¼ 112), who had o1 year of follow-up (n ¼ 1122), and who 
developed secondary solid cancer within 1 year after HSCT 
(n ¼ 6), a total of 2544 patients met eligibility criteria and were 
enrolled in the study (Supplementary Figure 1). Patient demo-
graphics are detailed in Table 1. Study subjects were predomi-
nantly male (56.6%) and had a median age of 32 years 
(interquartile range, 20-45 years). Chronic obstructive pulmon-
ary disease (COPD; 12.2%), dyslipidemia (12.1%), diabetes 
mellitus (10.4%), and chronic kidney disease (10.0%) were the 
most common comorbidities. </p>

<p>Risk of secondary malignancy according to age, sex, and time 
interval after transplantation. A total of 43 SM occurred within 
the observation period (Tables 2A and B). The incidence of SM in 
those receiving HSCT was higher than the incidence of cancers in 
the general population (SIR 2.00, 95% CI 1.45-2.69; Po0.001). 
Concerning the stem cell type, incidence of cancers in patients 
receiving allogeneic HSCT was higher than in the normal </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Cancer risk of haematopoietic stem cell transplant </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.523 </p>

<p>population (SIR 2.77, 95% CI 1.81-4.05; Po0.001). The increases 
were observed in both male (SIR 2.82, 95% CI 1.54-4.73; 
P ¼ 0.001) and female patients (SIR 2.71, 95% CI 1.40-4.73; 
P ¼ 0.004). In patients who received auto-HSCT, however, only 
males had a higher SIR of SM compared with the general 
population (SIR 1.89, 95% CI 1.03-3.17; P ¼ 0.040). 
In the sub-analysis by age, the risks of SM were greater for 
younger patients. For example, those aged 0-19 years after either 
allo-HSCT (SIR 15.24, 95% CI 1.85-55.07; P ¼ 0.016) or auto-
HSCT (SIR 49.91, 95% CI 1.26-278.07; P ¼ 0.040) had higher 
risk of SM compared with patients over 60 years who received 
allo-HSCT (SIR 2.30, 95% CI 0.28-8.30; P ¼ 0.433) or auto-
HSCT (SIR 1.68, 95% CI 0.55-3.92; P ¼ 0.359). Regarding follow-
up time after transplantation, the risk of SM increased nearly 
four-fold for patients who were followed for 5-10 years after 
allo-HSCT (SIR ¼ 4.56; 95% CI ¼ 2.55-7.53; Po0.001) 
(Table 2A). The cumulative incidence rate of overall SM after 
HSCT is 0.75% (95% CI ¼ 0.42-1.34%) in 5 years and 4.11% 
(95% CI ¼ 2.82-5.96%) in 10 years. The detailed results are 
outlined in Figure 1. </p>

<p>Table 1. Characteristics of patients with haematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) </p>

<p>Total 
Male 
Female </p>

<p>No. of patients 
2544 
1439 
1105 </p>

<p>Person-years at risk 
11 198 
6075.6 
5122.8 </p>

<p>Median follow-up, years (interquartile range) 
4.46 (2.11-7.75) 
4.21 (2.00-7.65) 
4.82 (2.31-8.05) </p>

<p>Median age, years (interquartile range) 
32 (20-45) 
32 (20-45) 
33 (20-46) </p>

<p>Primary disease </p>

<p>Acute lymphoblastic leukaemia 
293 (11.5%) 
167 (11.6%) 
126 (11.4%) 
Acute myeloid leukaemia 
867 (34.2%) 
458 (31.8%) 
409 (37.0%) 
Lymphoma 
678 (26.6%) 
390 (27.1%) 
288 (26.0%) 
Multiple myeloma 
270 (10.6%) 
172 (12.0%) 
98 (8.9%) 
Severe aplastic anaemia 
270 (10.6%) 
162 (11.3%) 
108 (9.9%) 
Thalassaemia 
68 (2.7%) 
30 (2.1%) 
38 (3.4%) 
Others </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>98 (3.8%) 
60 (4.1%) 
38 (3.4%) </p>

<p>Treatment </p>

<p>TBI 
605 (23.8%) 
335 (23.3%) 
270 (24.4%) 
Pre-HSCT Radiotherapy 
841 (33.1%) 
469 (32.6%) 
372 (33.7%) 
Allogeneic 
1514 (59.5%) 
836 (58.1%) 
678 (61.3%) 
Autologous 
1030 (40.5%) 
603 (41.9%) 
427 (38.7%) </p>

<p>cGVHD 
751 (49.6%) 
413 (49.4%) 
338 (49.8%) </p>

<p>Immunosupressants </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Cyclosporin 
1471 (97.1%) 
805 (96.2%) 
666 (98.2%) 
Tacrolimus 
138 (9.1%) 
76 (9.1%) 
62 (9.1%) 
Methylprednisolone 
253 (16.7%) 
134 (16.0%) 
119 (17.5%) 
Mycophenolate 
253 (16.7%) 
145 (17.3%) 
108 (15.9%) 
Sirolimus 
36 (2.3%) 
24 (2.8%) 
12 (1.7%) 
Anti-thymocyte globulin 
381 (25.1%) 
207 (24.7%) 
174 (25.6%) 
Azathioprine 
254 (16.7%) 
153 (18.3%) 
101 (14.8%) 
Cyclophosphamide 
31 (2.0%) 
16 (1.9%) 
15 (2.2%) 
Methotrexate 
41 (2.7%) 
23 (2.7%) 
18 (2.6%) </p>

<p>Comorbidities </p>

<p>Diabetes mellitus 
265 (10.4%) 
162 (11.3%) 
103 (9.3%) 
COPD 
311 (12.2%) 
195 (13.6%) 
116 (10.5%) 
Chronic kidney disease 
255 (10.0%) 
159 (11.0%) 
96 (8.7%) 
Liver cirrhosis 
48 (1.9%) 
27 (1.9%) 
21 (1.9%) 
Autoimmune diseases 
152 (6.0%) 
67 (4.7%) 
85 (7.7%) 
Dyslipidaemia 
309 (12.1%) 
135 (9.4%) 
174 (15.7%) </p>

<p>Age at HSCT, years </p>

<p>0-19 
545 (21.4%) 
302 (21.0%) 
243 (22.0%) 
20-39 
1027 (40.4%) 
567 (39.4%) 
460 (41.6%) 
40-59 
871 (34.2%) 
508 (35.3%) 
363 (32.9%) 
X60 
101 (4.0%) 
62 (4.3%) 
39 (3.5%) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: cGVHD ¼ chronic graft vs host disease; COPD ¼ chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; TBI ¼ total body irradiation. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Others: chronic lymphoid leukaemia; chronic myeloid leukaemia; myelodysplastic syndrome. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Immunosupressants are only indicated in allo-HSCT. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
2 </p>

<p>Number at risk </p>

<p>HSCT patients 2544 
1962 
1374 
947 
604 
380 
215 
60 </p>

<p>4 
6 
8 
Follow-up (years) </p>

<p>10 
12 
14 
Cumulative incidence of cancer (%) </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Figure 1. The cumulative incidence of secondary cancer in patients 
with haematopoietic stem cell transplantation. </p>

<p>Cancer risk of haematopoietic stem cell transplant 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.523 </p>

<p>
Table 2A. Standardised incidence ratios according to sex, age at HSCT, and follow-up time since allogeneic HSCT </p>

<p>Total </p>

<p>Male </p>

<p>Female </p>

<p>Characteristics </p>

<p>Observed </p>

<p>Expected </p>

<p>Person-
years </p>

<p>at risk </p>

<p>SIR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Observed Expected </p>

<p>Person-
years </p>

<p>at risk </p>

<p>SIR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Observed Expected </p>

<p>Person-
years </p>

<p>at risk </p>

<p>SIR (95% CI) </p>

<p>All cancers </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>9.40 </p>

<p>6998.7 
2.77 (1.81-4.05) </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>4.97 </p>

<p>3704.3 
2.82 (1.54-4.73) </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>4.43 </p>

<p>3294.4 
2.71 (1.40-4.73) </p>

<p>Age at HSCT, years </p>

<p>0-19 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>1691.0 
15.24 (1.85-55.07) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>832.0 
30.84 (3.73-111.39) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>859.0 
0.00 (0.00-55.61) </p>

<p>20-39 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>2.00 </p>

<p>3353.4 
4.51 (2.06-8.56) </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0.89 </p>

<p>1816.8 
4.49 (1.22-11.49) </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>1.10 </p>

<p>1536.7 
4.53 (1.47-10.56) </p>

<p>40-59 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>6.39 </p>

<p>1868.0 
2.03 (1.08-3.48) </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>3.28 </p>

<p>992.4 
2.13 (0.86-4.39) </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>3.11 </p>

<p>875.6 
1.93 (0.71-4.20) </p>

<p>X60 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.87 </p>

<p>86.3 
2.30 (0.28-8.30) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.72 </p>

<p>63.1 
1.39 (0.04-7.74) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>23.2 
6.67 (0.17-37.14) </p>

<p>Follow-up time since HSCT </p>

<p>1-5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>4.99 </p>

<p>4078.4 
0.80 (0.22-2.05) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2.60 </p>

<p>2182.3 
1.15 (0.24-3.37) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2.38 </p>

<p>1896.1 
0.42 (0.01-2.34) </p>

<p>5-10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>3.29 </p>

<p>2315.3 
4.56 (2.55-7.53) </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>1.74 </p>

<p>1206.6 
4.59 (1.98-9.04) </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>1.54 </p>

<p>1108.7 
4.54 (1.82-9.34) </p>

<p>X10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>1.12 </p>

<p>605.1 
6.23 (2.50-12.84) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>0.62 </p>

<p>315.4 
4.84 (1.00-14.13) </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>289.6 
7.95 (2.17-20.35) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI 
¼ confidence interval; HSCT 
¼ haematopoietic stem cell transplantation; SIR </p>

<p>¼ standardised incidence ratio. </p>

<p>Table 2B. Standardised incidence ratios according to sex, age at HSCT, and follow-up time since autologous HSCT </p>

<p>Total </p>

<p>Male </p>

<p>Female </p>

<p>Characteristics </p>

<p>Observed </p>

<p>Expected </p>

<p>Person-
years at 
risk 
SIR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Observed Expected </p>

<p>Person-
years at 
risk 
SIR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Observed Expected </p>

<p>Person-
years at 
risk 
SIR (95% CI) </p>

<p>All cancers </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>12.12 </p>

<p>4199.6 
1.40 (0.82-2.25) </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>7.41 </p>

<p>2371.3 
1.89 (1.03-3.17) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4.71 </p>

<p>1828.4 
0.64 (0.13-1.86) </p>

<p>Age at HSCT, years </p>

<p>0-19 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>226.4 
49.91 (1.26-278.07) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>133.3 
89.66 (2.27-499.54) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>93.1 
0.00 (0.00-415.27) </p>

<p>20-39 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.02 </p>

<p>1591.7 
0.98 (0.02-5.47) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.44 </p>

<p>821.5 
2.29 (0.06-12.74) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.58 </p>

<p>770.2 
0.00 (0.00-6.35) </p>

<p>40-59 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8.11 </p>

<p>2052.3 
1.23 (0.59-2.27) </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>4.89 </p>

<p>1219.2 
1.84 (0.84-3.49) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>3.22 </p>

<p>833.1 
0.31 (0.01-1.73) </p>

<p>X60 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>2.97 </p>

<p>329.2 
1.68 (0.55-3.92) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2.07 </p>

<p>197.2 
1.45 (0.30-4.23) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.90 </p>

<p>132.0 
2.22 (0.27-8.01) </p>

<p>Follow-up time since HSCT </p>

<p>1-5 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>7.74 </p>

<p>2667.6 
0.90 (0.36-1.86) </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>4.78 </p>

<p>1523.8 
0.84 (0.23-2.14) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2.96 </p>

<p>1143.8 
1.01 (0.21-2.97) </p>

<p>5-10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>3.45 </p>

<p>1252.4 
2.03 (0.82-4.18) </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>2.08 </p>

<p>701.1 
3.36 (1.35-6.93) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1.37 </p>

<p>551.3 
0.00 (0.00-2.69) </p>

<p>X10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>0.94 </p>

<p>279.6 
3.19 (0.66-9.32) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>0.55 </p>

<p>146.4 
5.43 (1.12-15.86) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.39 </p>

<p>133.2 
0.00 (0.00-9.52) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI 
¼ confidence interval; HSCT 
¼ haematopoietic stem cell transplantation; SIR </p>

<p>¼ standardised incidence ratio. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Cancer risk of haematopoietic stem cell transplant </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.523 </p>

<p>Specific subtypes of cancers. Among the 26 malignancies that 
occurred after allo-HSCT, the most commonly observed cancers 
originated in the head and neck (n ¼ 14), the digestive tract 
(n ¼ 8), and the lung or mediastinum (n ¼ 3). Compared with the 
general population, patients who received allo-HSCT had sig-
nificantly higher SIRs for neoplasms of the oesophagus (SIR 14.75, </p>

<p>95% CI 4.02-37.76; Po0.001) and the oral cavity (SIR 14.18, 95% 
CI 7.55-24.25; Po0.001). Regarding gender, women with 
allo-HSCT were at greater risk of liver and biliary tract 
malignancies (SIR 17.31, 95% CI 3.57-50.58; P ¼ 0.001), but this 
risk was not observed in male patients. Although there was an 
increased incidence of SM in males receiving auto-HSCT, they did </p>

<p>Table 3. Standardised incidence ratios for secondary cancer subtypes among patients with allogeneic HSCT </p>

<p>Total 
Male 
Female </p>

<p>Site of cancers 
Observed Expected SIR (95% CI) Observed Expected SIR (95% CI) Observed Expected SIR (95% CI) </p>

<p>All cancers 
26 
9.40 
2.77 (1.81-4.05) 
14 
4.97 
2.82 (1.54-4.73) 
12 
4.43 
2.71 (1.40-4.73) </p>

<p>Head and neck 
14 
1.65 
8.46 (4.63-14.20) 
9 
1.47 
6.11 (2.79-11.60) 
5 
0.18 
27.59 (8.96-64.37) </p>

<p>Oral cavity 
13 
0.92 
14.18 (7.55-24.25) 
8 
0.85 
9.44 (4.08-18.61) 
5 
0.07 
71.94 (23.36-167.88) 
Pharynx and others 
1 
0.74 
1.36 (0.03-7.55) 
1 
0.63 
1.60 (0.04-8.90) 
0 
0.11 
0.00 (0.00-33.01) </p>

<p>Digestive 
8 
2.88 
2.78 (1.20-5.47) 
3 
2.14 
1.40 (0.29-4.09) 
5 
0.74 
6.78 (2.20-15.82) </p>

<p>Oesophagus 
4 
0.27 
14.75 (4.02-37.76) 
3 
0.26 
11.44 (2.36-33.42) 
1 
0.01 
112.31 (2.84-625.78) 
Stomach 
0 
0.31 
0.00 (0.00-12.01) 
0 
0.19 
0.00 (0.00-19.21) 
0 
0.12 
0.00 (0.00-32.07) 
Colon and rectum, Anus 
1 
1.05 
0.95 (0.02-5.32) 
0 
0.64 
0.00 (0.00-5.74) 
1 
0.40 
2.47 (0.06-13.76) 
Liver and biliary tract 
3 
1.15 
2.62 (0.54-7.64) 
0 
0.97 
0.00 (0.00-3.79) 
3 
0.17 
17.31 (3.57-50.58) 
Pancreas 
0 
0.11 
0.00 (0.00-34.43) 
0 
0.07 
0.00 (0.00-51.50) 
0 
0.04 
0.00 (0.00-103.82) </p>

<p>Lung and mediastinum 
3 
0.70 
4.26 (0.88-12.44) 
1 
0.44 
2.26 (0.06-12.58) 
2 
0.26 
7.64 (0.93-27.61) </p>

<p>Bone and Soft tissue 
0 
0.15 
0.00 (0.00-24.05) 
0 
0.09 
0.00 (0.00-40.57) 
0 
0.06 
0.00 (0.00-59.07) </p>

<p>Skin 
0 
0.12 
0.00 (0.00-29.51) 
0 
0.08 
0.00 (0.00-48.96) 
0 
0.05 
0.00 (0.00-74.30) </p>

<p>Breast 
0 
1.71 
0.00 (0.00-2.16) 
0 
0.00 
0.00 (0.00-752.49) 
0 
1.70 
0.00 (0.00-2.17) </p>

<p>Genitourinary 
0 
1.31 
0.00 (0.00-2.82) 
0 
0.40 
0.00 (0.00-9.28) 
0 
0.91 
0.00 (0.00-4.04) </p>

<p>Thyroid 
0 
0.52 
0.00 (0.00-7.04) 
0 
0.12 
0.00 (0.00-31.75) 
0 
0.41 
0.00 (0.00-9.04) </p>

<p>All others 
1 
0.34 
2.95 (0.07-16.46) 
1 
0.22 
4.50 (0.11-25.10) 
0 
0.12 
0.00 (0.00-31.66) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI ¼ confidence interval; HSCT ¼ haematopoietic stem cell transplantation; SIR ¼ standardised incidence ratio. </p>

<p>Table 4. Risk factors for secondary cancer development in patients with allogeneic HSCT </p>

<p>Univariate analysis 
Multivariate analysis </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Variables 
HR (95% CI) 
P-value 
HR (95% CI) 
P-value </p>

<p>Age X40 
2.79 (1.24-6.27) 
0.013 
2.06 (0.85-4.97) 
0.109 </p>

<p>Sex (male) 
1.04 (0.48-2.24) 
0.931 
0.91 (0.42-1.99) 
0.819 </p>

<p>HSCT </p>

<p>Malignancies vs. benign 
3.10 (0.93-10.32) 
0.066 
2.32 (0.68-7.88) 
0.178 
PBSCT vs BMSCT 
1.83 (0.53-6.29) 
0.339 </p>

<p>Comorbidities </p>

<p>Diabetes mellitus 
0.93 (0.13-6.86) 
0.940 
COPD 
3.23 (1.10-9.48) 
0.033 
2.41 (0.78-7.40) 
0.126 
Chronic kidney disease 
0.73 (0.10-5.41) 
0.756 
Liver cirrhosis </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.989 
Autoimmune diseases 
0.98 (0.13-7.28) 
0.987 
Dyslipidaemia 
2.73 (0.81-9.27) 
0.107 </p>

<p>cGVHD 
2.31 (0.97-5.51) 
0.058 
2.19 (0.91-5.27) 
0.082 </p>

<p>Treatment </p>

<p>TBI 
0.95 (0.41-2.18) 
0.897 
Pre-HSCT radiotherapy 
0.85 (0.38-1.90) 
0.683 </p>

<p>Immunosuppressant </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Cyclosporin </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.991 
Tacrolimus 
2.35 (0.70-7.89) 
0.166 
Methylprednisolone 
1.48 (0.62-3.53) 
0.373 
Mycophenolate 
0.71 (0.17-3.01) 
0.642 
Sirolimus 
5.57 (0.74-41.80) 
0.095 
6.34 (0.81-49.29) 
0.078 
Anti-thymocyte globulin 
0.40 (0.05-2.96) 
0.367 
Azathioprine 
3.14 (1.44-6.88) 
0.004 
2.55 (1.13-5.77) 
0.025 
Cyclophosphamide 
1.13 (0.34-3.79) 
0.841 
Methotrexate 
1.05 (0.36-3.07) 
0.926 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: BMSCT ¼ bone marrow stem cell transplantation; cGVHD ¼ chronic graft vs host disease; CI ¼ confidence interval; COPD ¼ chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; HSCT ¼ 
haematopoietic stem cell transplantation; HR ¼ hazard ratio; PBSCT ¼ peripheral blood stem cell transplantation; TBI: total body irradiation. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>All factors with Po0.1 in univariate analyses and sex were included in the Cox multivariate analysis. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Do not converge. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Immunosuppressant was analysed as a time-dependent covariate in the Cox regression model. </p>

<p>Cancer risk of haematopoietic stem cell transplant 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.523 </p>

<p>
not appear to be at greater risk for any specific cancer subtypes. 
Results of these analyses are detailed further in Table 3 and 
Supplementary Table 1. </p>

<p>Predictors of cancer risk. According to the univariate Cox 
proportional hazards analysis, the following characteristics 
increased the risk of SM after allo-HSCT: age X40 years, HSCT 
for malignant disease, COPD, cGVHD, and use of the immuno-
suppressants sirolimus and azathioprine (Table 4). In the multi-
variate Cox proportional hazards analysis, azathioprine use (HR 
2.55, 95% CI 1.13-5.77; P ¼ 0.025) was the only significant risk 
factor. There were trends for cGVHD (HR 2.19, 95% CI 0.91-5.27; 
P ¼ 0.082) and sirolimus use (HR 6.34, 95% CI 0.81-49.29; 
P ¼ 0.078) to be risk factors. 
Time-dependent Cox proportional hazard models adjusted for 
the variables listed in Table 5 were performed to analyse the 
relationship between azathioprine dose and SM. Using the 50th 
percentile of cumulative doses as the cutoff point, a cumulative 
azathioprine dose of 415 100 mg after HSCT significantly 
increased the risk of SM. Exposure X15 100 mg would induce 
significantly higher risk (HR 3.58, 95% CI 1.37-9.38; P ¼ 0.01) 
than those with o15 100 mg (HR 2.51, 95% CI 0.90-6.99; 
P ¼ 0.079) in comparison with non-use ones (Table 5). Regarding 
auto-HSCT, patients who were 40 years or older, male, or had 
COPD had higher hazard ratios in the univariate analysis 
(Supplementary Table 2), but only age X40 years was significant 
for inclusion in the multivariate analysis (HR 3.74, 95% CI 1.19-
11.80; P ¼ 0.024). 
Receiving TBI as part of the conditioning regimen did not 
increase the risk of SM (HR 0.95, 95% CI 0.41-2.18; P ¼ 0.897) in 
the univariate analysis of allo-HSCT patients. An analysis tried to 
explore the association between TBI or cGVHD and various 
subtypes of SM revealed no association between TBI and any 
cancer subtype (Supplementary Table 3), but cGVHD was a 
significant risk factor for head and neck cancer (HR 2.84, 95% CI 
1.02-7.92; P ¼ 0.046) (Supplementary Table 4). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This nationwide population-based study showed that a cohort of 
2544 adult patients who received HSCT had an B2-fold greater 
risk of SM compared with the general population. The most 
common SMs were cancers of the oral cavity and oesophagus in 
both men and women who received allo-HSCT. The single greatest 
risk factor for development of SM after allo-HSCT was 
azathioprine use, which increased the risk of cancer in a dose-
dependent manner. Although patients under 19 years of age had 
the highest SIR, patients 40 years or older were at greater risk for 
developing SM after auto-HSCT. </p>

<p>In Taiwan, both HSCT and cancer are classified under the 
'Catastrophic Illness' category by the NHI due to their large 
associated costs. The NHI has implemented an extremely strict 
verification process before issuing certification for treatment and 
requires pathological proof of malignancy or a clinical diagnosis 
based on laboratory and imaging evidence. Therefore, the diagnosis 
of malignancies should be accurate and not over-or under-
estimated. In addition, the NHI defines clear and strict indications 
for HSCT, as an expensive procedure. Peer review of cases is 
required to ensure that patient criteria are met. Thus, the diagnoses 
are reliable and precise. 
Several published studies reported an increased risk of 
developing SM after HSCT (Curtis et al, 1997; Rizzo et al, 2009; 
Yokota et al, 2012). The risk ratio differs between studies. Curtis 
et al (1997) reported the risk to be as high as 8.3 times the expected 
incidence in those surviving 410 years after transplantation. A 
recent study of data from the Center for International Blood and 
Marrow Transplant Research (CIBMTR) and the Fred Hutchinson 
Cancer Research Center (FHCRC) database demonstrated that 
patients developed solid cancers after transplantation at twice the 
rate expected in the general population (Rizzo et al, 2009). 
These results are similar to our findings and those reported by 
Yokota et al (2012) in Japan. Of note, the SIR of SM was higher 
in young patients and increased with time. Rizzo et al (2009) 
reported competing risk analyses were 1% (95% CI 0.9-1.3%) at 10 
years, 2.2% (95% CI 1.7-2.7%) at 15 years, and 3.3% (95% CI 
2.4-4.5%) at 20 years after HSCT. Our study also found that the 
SIR of cancer development after HSCT increased with longer 
follow-up times. 
It is well known that use of immunosuppressants increases the 
risk of developing a secondary malignancy. Combination use of 
steroids, azathioprine, and cyclosporine significantly increased the 
risk of skin cancer after renal transplantation (Bouwes Bavinck 
et al, 1996). In HSCT, both chronic inflammation from cGVHD 
and immunosuppressant use may predispose patients to develop-
ing secondary malignancies. In 1996, an analysis of 700 patients 
undergoing HSCT for aplastic anaemia and Fanconi anaemia 
revealed that azathioprine for cGVHD was a definite risk for solid 
tumour development after allo-HSCT (Deeg et al, 1996). Another 
international case-control study identified several major risk 
factors for the development of squamous cell carcinoma after 
HSCT, including prolonged azathioprine use, especially when it 
was combined with cyclosporine and steroids for severe cGVHD 
(Curtis et al, 2005). The risk ratio was 8.44 (95% CI 3.17-22.47; 
Po0.001) in patients receiving cGVHD therapy for 424 months. 
An analysis of different immunosuppressants and therapy duration 
found that azathioprine, cyclosporine, and steroid therapy for 412 
months, with or without other therapies, increased the risk of 
squamous cell carcinoma 38 times (Curtis et al, 2005). However, 
this study did not mention any association between azathioprine 
dose and SM. 
In our study, a total of 128 patients have been treated with 
azathioprine in the 751 documented cGVHD patients, and it 
demonstrated that azathioprine increased SM risk by two-fold, and 
the risk increased with higher cumulative doses. This finding 
suggests that not only duration, but also the cumulative dose of 
azathioprine affects the risk of SM after allo-HSCT. Azathioprine is 
an oral immunosuppressant that requires metabolic activation into 
thioguanine nucleotides. These nucleotide analogues (specifically, 
6-thioguanine (6-TG)) are incorporated into DNA. DNA contain-
ing 6-TG, especially after radiation therapy, is susceptible to 
mutagenic oxidation and carries a risk of therapy-related cancer in 
long-term survivors of transplantation (O'Donovan et al, 2005). 
Regarding the cancer subtypes of patients with allo-HSCT, the 
most common SMs are oral cavity tumours (Curtis et al, 2005; 
Hasegawa et al, 2005; Rizzo et al, 2009; Majhail et al, 2011). 
However, there are some epidemiological differences between </p>

<p>Table 5. Cumulative dose of azathioprine for secondary 
cancer development in patients with allogeneic HSCT </p>

<p>Univariate analysis 
Multivariate analysis </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Variables 
HR (95% CI) P-value HR (95% CI) P-value </p>

<p>Azathioprine </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Non-use 
Reference 
Reference 
o15 100 mg 
2.67 (0.96-7.40) 
0.060 
2.51 (0.90-6.99) 
0.079 
X15 100 mg 
3.68 (1.42-9.51) 
0.007 
3.58 (1.37-9.38) 
0.010 
Dose-response 
relationship </p>

<p>1.97 (1.26-3.09) 
0.003 
1.94 (1.22-3.07) 
0.005 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI ¼ confidence interval; HSCT ¼ haematopoietic stem cell transplantation; 
HR ¼ hazard ratio. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Azathioprine was analysed as a time-dependent covariate in the Cox regression model and 
adjusted with variables listed in Table 4 multivariate analysis. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>With cutoff points at non-use and the 50th percentile of cumulative dose. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Cancer risk of haematopoietic stem cell transplant </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.523 </p>

<p>Western and Eastern countries. Reports of data from the CIBMTR 
and FHCRC, which encompass populations in the United States of 
America and European countries, demonstrated that the sites of 
SMs, in order of decreasing incidence, were as follows: the oral 
cavity, liver, brain and central nervous system, and thyroid (Socie 
et al, 2000; Rizzo et al, 2009). However, our study from Taiwan and 
another from Japan (Yokota et al, 2012) revealed that in addition 
to cancers of the oral cavity, oesophageal cancer is also a common 
SM following allo-HSCT (Hasegawa et al, 2005; Shimada et al, 
2005; Chen et al, 2011). This difference may be related to the 
higher incidence of oesophageal cancer in Asian countries 
(Warnakulasuriya, 2008; Lin et al, 2013; Zhang, 2013). Another 
notable difference is skin cancer, which is more frequent in 
Western countries and usually presents as melanoma rather than 
squamous or basal cell carcinoma. Skin cancer with melanoma was 
reported as an excess absolute risk of 1.5 by the CIBMTR and the 
FHCRC (Rizzo et al, 2009), but squamous or basal cell carcinoma 
is more common in Asian countries (Hasegawa et al, 2005; Yokota 
et al, 2012).Our study and the one by Shimada et al (2005) 
reported that no skin cancer was observed after allo-or auto-
HSCT. 
Use of TBI in HSCT has been described as a major risk factor 
for SM (Curtis et al, 2005; Friedman et al, 2008). However, our 
study and others showed no significant association between SM 
and radiation therapy (Hasegawa et al, 2005; Shimada et al, 2005; 
Yokota et al, 2012). One explanation for this discrepancy is the 
smaller proportion of young patients and shorter follow-up time 
after HSCT in our study. However, other pediatric studies and 
studies with long follow-up periods also found no association 
between SM and age or TBI (Baker et al, 2003; Kunkele et al, 2013). 
Similarly, TBI is associated with increased risk of skin cancers, such 
as melanoma (Rizzo et al, 2009) and basal or squamous cell 
carcinoma (Leisenring et al, 2006; Schwartz et al, 2009), but as 
mentioned above, no skin cancer was observed in our study or a 
study in Japan (Shimada et al, 2005). This discrepancy requires 
further investigation and may be the result of ethnic differences. 
Another significant risk factor for SM in other studies is 
cGVHD (Curtis et al, 2005; Rizzo et al, 2009; Majhail, 2011; 
Majhail et al, 2011).While cGVHD had a hazard ratio of 2.19 for 
SM in our study, it was not significant in the multivariate analysis. 
The lack of statistical significance could be due to small patient 
number, however, the statistical trend may still implicate cGVHD 
as an independent risk factor for SM. There were 751 cases of 
cGVHD in our 1514 patients. This incidence of cGVHD was 
B49%, which is higher than in reports from Western countries 
(Rizzo et al, 2009; Majhail et al, 2011) and another Taiwanese 
study (Bai et al, 2004). Additional evidence comes from the 
significant effects of immunosuppressant use. The demand for 
prolonged use of immunosuppressants reflects the severity and 
duration of cGVHD. It is possible that in addition to immuno-
suppressants being a risk factor, cGVHD is, independently or 
synergistically with immunosuppressants, a risk factor for SM. A 
previous study also showed that cGVHD and the use of 
immunosuppressants are independent risks and the occurrence 
of both factors contributed to higher cancer risk (Curtis et al, 
2005). Finally, patients had a much greater risk of SM following 
allo-HSCT than auto-HSCT, which had only slight increase of risk 
in male patients. This observation suggests that, in addition to 
high-dose chemotherapy-induced DNA damage, immunosuppres-
sants (especially azathioprine) and cGVHD are important risk 
factors for SM. 
Our study is limited as a retrospective analysis and NHI 
database. We were unable to obtain detailed information about 
severity grading of cGVHD, stage of primary disease, and donor-
recipient relationships. However, a multivariate analysis of the 
CIBMTR database conducted by Curtis et al (1997) revealed that 
HLA type or familial relationships did not increase the risk of SM </p>

<p>(Rizzo et al, 2009). No information about conditioning regimen 
was available in our study, but a previous study reported that it did 
not influence the risk of SM development (Hasegawa et al, 2005). 
Majhail et al (2011) reported that conditioning with busulfan-
cyclophosphamide increased SM in the oral cavity and other 
cancers, but that study only focused on busulfan-cyclopho-
sphamide and not on other regimens. The association between 
the conditioning regimen and SM is still inconclusive and requires 
more investigation. Many other potential risk factors, such as 
T-cell depletion and manipulation, anti-thymocyte globulin, and 
lifestyle characteristics such as smoking or alcohol use, were not 
available for our analysis. However, these factors did not affect SM 
development in several previous studies (Curtis et al, 1997, 2005; 
Hasegawa et al, 2005; Rizzo et al, 2009). 
In conclusion, patients receiving HSCT have approximately 
twice the risk of developing SM than the general population, and 
this risk increases with time. The incidence of oral and oesophageal 
cancers in Taiwanese patients significantly increases after allo-
HSCT. This result is a unique clinical feature that is different from 
patients in Western countries, where the oesophageal cancer risk is 
not increased. The use of the immunosuppressant azathioprine, 
especially with cumulative doses exceeding 15 100 mg, increases the 
risk of SM. Taking the autologous transplantation as a reference, 
our study demonstrates the significant effects of cGVHD and 
immunosuppressants as the risk of SM. Physicians should be 
cautious when using azathioprine for GVHD after HSCT. This 
study suggests that long-term survivors who are treated with 
HSCT, especially those with risks mentioned above, should be kept 
under long-term surveillance for early detection of SM. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study is supported by grants from Taipei Veterans General 
Hospital (V103B-022, V102C-202, and V103E10-001). The study is 
based in part on data from the National Health Insurance Research 
Database provided by the Bureau of National Health Insurance, 
Department of Health and managed by National Health Research 
Institutes. The interpretation and conclusions contained herein do 
not represent those of Bureau of National Health Insurance, 
Department of Health or National Health Research Institutes. Miss 
Chiu-Mei Yeh contributed significantly to the calculations and 
interpretations of statistical analyses in this study. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>Cancer risk of haematopoietic stem cell transplant 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.523 </p>



<p>
This work is published under the standard license to publish agree-
ment. After 12 months the work will become freely available and 
the license terms will switch to a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on British Journal of Cancer website (http://www.nature.com/bjc) </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Cancer risk of haematopoietic stem cell transplant </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.523 </p>

</text></tei>