<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4576863" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) is a growth factor 
widely expressed in the nervous system. Changes in its level 
have been found and correlated to the development of several 
human diseases including neurodegeneration, depression, psy-
chiatric disorders, and obesity (Chao et al., 2006; Nagahara and 
Tuszynski, 2011; Lu et al., 2014). The direct relevance of nor-
mal BDNF signaling to human fitness has been validated by 
the use of animal models, which have also allowed the dissec-
tion of the molecular mechanism underlying BDNF function in 
vivo (Rios et al., 2001; Zuccato and Cattaneo, 2009; Baydyuk 
and Xu, 2014). The TrkB gene encodes BDNF high affinity 
receptors that are widely expressed in neuronal tissues (Klein 
et al., 1990; Escandón et al., 1994). This locus generates mul-
tiple TrkB isoforms all of which have the same extracellular 
domain but have different intracellular domains (Stoilov et al., 
2002). The two main isoforms include a full-length receptor 
with a tyrosine kinase domain (TrkB.Kin) used for signaling 
and a truncated TrkB.T1 receptor lacking kinase activity (Klein 
et al., 1990; Dorsey et al., 2006). Although a role for TrkB.Kin 
has been established in neuronal development and function in-
cluding differentiation, outgrowth, and synaptic plasticity, the 
physiological significance of TrkB.T1 intrinsic signaling is still 
unclear despite its high sequence conservation among species 
and its being the most highly expressed TrkB isoform in the 
mature animal. Mice lacking TrkB.T1 have increased anxi-</p>

<p>ety-related behavior that is associated with structural alterations 
in neurites of the amygdala (Carim-Todd et al., 2009). Despite 
reports of TrkB.T1 signaling in isolated glia cells there are no 
obvious deficiencies in this cell population in TrkB.T1 mutant 
mice (Rose et al., 2003; Dorsey et al., 2006; Ohira et al., 2006; 
Carim-Todd et al., 2009). In the cardiovascular system, BDNF 
and its receptor TrkB have been described to have an early de-
velopmental role in cardiac endothelium formation (Anastasia 
et al., 2014). Interestingly, in the adult heart only TrkB.T1-spe-
cific polyadenylated mRNA has been reported, suggesting pro-
tein expression of this particular receptor isoform (Stoilov et 
al., 2002). Our analysis confirms this finding and we further 
show that it mediates BDNF inotropic function by regulating 
Ca 2+ signaling. We found that specific deletion of TrkB.T1 in 
cardiomyocytes causes cardiomyopathy and that BDNF is the 
ligand activating TrkB.T1. We show that BDNF is secreted by 
cardiomyocytes and its specific deletion in cardiomyocytes 
causes a cardiomyopathy resembling that caused by TrkB.T1 
deficiency. Our data unveil a novel nonneuronal function for 
BDNF and uncover the first physiologically relevant direct sig-
naling activity of the TrkB.T1 receptor. These findings identify 
a new pathway regulating cardiac contractility and suggest that 
perturbation in BDNF and TrkB expression may cause car-
diac pathological conditions. </p>

<p>Brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) is critical for mammalian development and plasticity of neuronal circuitries 
affecting memory, mood, anxiety, pain sensitivity, and energy homeostasis. Here we report a novel unexpected role of 
BDNF in regulating the cardiac contraction force independent of the nervous system innervation. This function is medi-
ated by the truncated TrkB.T1 receptor expressed in cardiomyocytes. Loss of TrkB.T1 in these cells impairs calcium sig-
naling and causes cardiomyopathy. TrkB.T1 is activated by BDNF produced by cardiomyocytes, suggesting an autocrine/ 
paracrine loop. These findings unveil a novel signaling mechanism in the heart that is activated by BDNF and provide 
evidence for a global role of this neurotrophin in the homeostasis of the organism by signaling through different TrkB 
receptor isoforms. </p>

<p>BDNF modulates heart contraction force and 
long-term homeostasis through truncated TrkB.T1 
receptor activation </p>

<p>Gianluca Fulgenzi, 1,2 Francesco Tomassoni-Ardori, 1 Lucia Babini, 1 Jodi Becker, 1 Colleen Barrick, 1 Sandrine Puverel, 1 
and Lino Tessarollo 1 </p>

<p>1 Neural Development Section, Mouse Cancer Genetics Program, Center for Cancer Research, National Cancer Institute, Frederick, MD 21702 
2 Department of Molecular and Clinical Sciences, Marche Polytechnic University, Ancona, 60020, Italy </p>

<p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike-No 
Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see http://www.rupress. 
org/terms). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution-
Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, as described at http://creativecommons. 
org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). </p>

<p>Correspondence to Lino Tessarollo: tessarol@mail.nih.gov </p>

<p>Abbreviations used in this paper: BDNF, Brain-derived neurotrophic factor; bpm, 
beats per minute; IP 3 , inositol-1,4,5-trisphosphate; LVDP, left ventricle developed 
pressure; PLB, phospholamban; WT, wild type. </p>

<p>T H E J O U R N A L O F C E L L B I O L O G Y </p>

<p>JCB • Volume 210 • NumBer 6 • 2015 
1004 </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>To address a potential role of BDNF in the mature cardiovas-
cular system we first investigated the pattern of expression of 
its receptor TrkB in the adult mouse heart (Fig. 1). Although 
the full-length TrkB tyrosine kinase receptor is expressed in 
the cardiac endothelium during development (Donovan et al., 
2000), we found that in the adult this isoform is virtually un-
detectable and only trace levels of its mRNA can be found by 
RT-PCR (Fig. 1, B and C). Instead, truncated TrkB.T1 protein 
is the dominant cardiac-expressed isoform as previously shown 
by RNA expression analyses (Fig. 1; Stoilov et al., 2002). The 
presence of TrkB mRNA and protein in the heart suggests an in-
trinsic role for this receptor independent of the nervous system 
cardiac innervation. Thus, we next tested whether BDNF plays 
a role in adult cardiac function in an ex vivo paradigm by per-
fusing isolated mouse hearts (Fig. 2). BDNF injected in the fluid 
streamline of a Langendorff-perfused mouse heart (Broadley, 
1979) induced an increase in the cardiac contraction force as 
shown by an increase in systolic pressure and a decrease of the 
diastolic pressure (Fig. 2, A-D). The effect of BDNF appeared 
exclusively inotropic and lusitropic as it did not affect the spon-
taneous cardiac contraction frequency (Fig. S1). BDNF also did 
not influence the coronary flow (Fig. S2). Perfusion of the heart 
paced at 420 beats per minute (bpm) with 1 ng BDNF causes an 
increase in the left ventricle developed pressure (LVDP; EC 50 of 
0.3 ng BDNF) with a timing similar to that elicited by the con-
trol compound caffeine (Fig. 2 E and Fig. S1). To test whether 
BDNF signaling is mediated by the TrkB tyrosine kinase recep-
tor we attempted to use the TrkBF616A mouse model in which 
TrkB tyrosine kinase activity can be silenced by the specific 
phosphatase inhibitor 1-NMPP1 drug (Chen et al., 2005). How-
ever, in Langerdorff-perfused wild-type (WT) mouse hearts 
we found that 100 nM 1-NMPP1 induced a dramatic increase </p>

<p>in the cardiac contraction force that blunted the BDNF effect, 
thus preventing the use of this model for this application (Fig. 
S3). Nevertheless, pretreatment with the K252a tyrosine kinase 
inhibitor did not prevent the increase in cardiac force elicited 
by BDNF, suggesting a function independent of TrkB kinase 
signaling (Fig. 2, B and D). 
Interestingly, pretreatment with isoproterenol, a nonse-
lective β-adrenergic agonist, did not blunt the BDNF inotropic 
effect but was instead additive, suggesting that BDNF signaling 
does not overlap with the catecholamine pathways (Fig. 3, A 
and B). In addition, when we tested whether BDNF changes the 
phosphorylation level of some of the major molecular players 
involved in cardiac contraction, including CamKII, phosphol-
amban (PLB), and troponin, we found that in Langendorff-per-
fused hearts at the peak of BDNF action phosphorylation levels 
were unchanged contrary to hearts treated with forskolin used 
as positive control (Fig. 3, C-F). These data suggest that BDNF 
exerts cardiac function through other pathways or this effect 
is modulatory and not immediately detectable with conven-
tional biochemical analysis. 
The effect on cardiac contraction force suggests that car-
diomyocytes may be the cell type responding to BDNF with 
Ca 2+ as the possible downstream effector. Therefore, we tested 
adult cardiomyocytes for TrkB expression and their response 
to BDNF (Fig. 1 A and Fig. 2, I-K). We found that isolated 
cardiomyocytes do express TrkB.T1 (Fig. 1 A) and when sub-
jected to direct depolarization they elicited higher Ca 2+ tran-
sients by treatment with BDNF compared with just vehicle 
(Fig. 2 I). Moreover, the Ca 2+ transient increase was reversible 
because it was restored to the basal electrical stimulation level 
after BDNF removal (Fig. 2 J). 
The fast action of BDNF and the finding that K252a does 
not block this function in heart (Fig. 2 B) and cardiomyocytes 
(Fig. 2 K) suggest that this role is not mediated by the TrkB ki-</p>

<p>Figure 1. TrkB.T1 receptor isoform is ex-
pressed in adult mouse heart and cardiomyo-
cytes. (A) Western blot analysis of brain, heart, 
and cardiomyocyte lysates from adult WT and 
TrkB.T1-deficient (T1 −/− ) mice. Lysates were 
incubated with wheat germ lectin agarose to 
enrich for glycoproteins. The wheat germ ag-
glutinated (WGA) precipitates were analyzed 
by Western blot analysis with an antibody 
directed against the extracellular domain of 
TrkB to detect all TrkB isoforms. Note that in 
whole heart and cardiomyocytes (Cardio) 
only a truncated TrkB isoform (80-90 Kd) is 
detected. The absence of the corresponding 
band in the TrkB.T1 knockout animals veri-
fies the identity of the receptor. Brain lysates 
were used as a positive control. Right panel, 
input lysates. (B) Quantification of real-time 
PCR analysis as expressed by the number of 
PCR cycles at which full-length TrkB (TrkB.Kin) 
or TrkB.T1-specific PCR products are equal to 
GAPDH level (Δ Ct) from total cardiomyocyte 
RNA. Note that TrkB.T1 is expressed at a much 
higher level as PCR products appear after only 
5 cycles of GADPH detection versus 11 cycles 
for TrkB.Kin. (C) Ethidium bromide agarose 
gel visualizing the size of the DNA fragments 
from heart RT-PCR analysis. Note that the size 
of the PCR reaction products corresponding 
to TrkB kinase (Kin) and TrkB.T1 (T1) are the 
same as those from brain used as a positive 
control. B, brain; H, heart. </p>

<p>BDNF-TrkB.T1 function in cardiomyocytes • Fulgenzi et al. </p>



<p>nase receptor but by the TrkB.T1 isoform, which is expressed in 
cardiomyocytes and has been shown to regulate Ca 2+ signaling, 
at least in astrocytes (Rose et al., 2003). This prompted us to 
test whether this receptor mediates cardiac BDNF actions by 
using a specific TrkB.T1-deficient mouse model (Dorsey et al., 
2006). Injection of BDNF in the perfusion system of TrkB.T1 
knockout hearts failed to induce the rapid increase in LVDP 
observed in control hearts. However, their response to caffeine 
was normal (Fig. 2, F-H). Similarly, adult cardiomyocytes iso-
lated from TrkB.T1 knockout mice failed to show the increase 
in Ca 2+ transient evoked by BDNF in controls (Fig. 2, I-K). 
These data strongly suggest that the TrkB.T1 receptor isoform 
mediates the inotropic BDNF function in the adult heart and 
may have a role in normal cardiac physiology. To investigate 
the in vivo significance of the findings from the ex vivo and 
cardiomyocyte experiments we performed histological analy-
sis of adult TrkB.T1-deficient hearts. TrkB.T1 knockout hearts 
showed a cardiac dilation characterized by reduced thickness 
of the left ventricular wall (Fig. 4, A and B). Moreover, in 
vivo echocardiography analysis showed an overall enlarged 
ventricular volume and thinner posterior wall thickness in 
TrkB.T1 −/− mice compared with WT controls (Fig. 4, C and D). 
To investigate the significance of the cardiac pathological condi-</p>

<p>tion caused by loss of TrkB.T1 we also looked for the presence 
of mechanisms of cardiac function adaptation including changes 
in L-type-mediated Ca 2+ currents (Benitah et al., 2010). Electro-
physiological recording of isolated cardiomyocytes detected an 
increase in L-type-mediated Ca 2+ current density paired with a 
higher expression level of L-type Ca 2+ channels as shown by the 
biochemical analysis of the CaV1.2 α1c subunit (Fig. 4, E-J). 
These data combined with the significant impairment in some 
functional parameters such as a reduced left ventricle-devel-
oped pressure measured in Langendorff-perfused mutant hearts 
suggest that TrkB.T1 is critical for normal cardiac function and 
its deletion induces secondary changes as a mechanism to com-
pensate for the functional deficits (Table S1). Interestingly, the 
cardiomyopathy developed by TrkB.T1-deficient mice does not 
appear to originate during embryonic or early postnatal devel-
opment as histological analysis of TrkB.T1 mutant mice at post-
natal day 12 shows normal posterior wall thickness and no sign 
of left ventricle dilation (Fig. S4, A and B). 
Several studies have reported a putative role for BDNF 
in central nervous system nuclei controlling cardiac function, 
peripheral innervation, and the vasculature, suggesting that the 
phenotype observed in TrkB.T1 mutant mice could be the result 
of indirect alterations in the microvasculature and/or the sympa-</p>

<p>Figure 2. TrkB.T1 mediates BDNF-induced acute increase in cardiac contraction force and calcium transient increase evoked by direct stimulation in car-
diomyocytes. (A and B) BDNF (1 ng in 50 µl Krebs solution) injected in the fluid streamline of a Langendorff-perfused mouse heart induces an increase in 
systolic pressure and a consequent decrease of the diastolic pressure (A) that is not affected by the TrkB kinase inhibitor K252a (B), Arrows indicate the 
time of BDNF injection and the broken line (B) indicates K252a presence throughout the 80-s duration of the experiment. (C) Representative traces showing 
the changes in LVPD before (baseline) and after BDNF injection. (D) Representative traces showing the changes in LVPD before (baseline) and after BDNF 
injection in the presence of 200 µM K252A. (E and F) Representative traces showing the increase in LVDP caused by BDNF in WT (E) but not in TrkB.T1 
knockout (T1 −/− ; F) hearts. A bolus of 50 µl of 5 mM caffeine in Krebs solution was injected 5 min after BDNF as a positive control. The BDNF and caffeine 
traces were overlapped using the injection time as the starting point (arrow). Note the lack of LVDP change in response to BDNF in the TrkB.T1 mutant 
mouse despite normal response to caffeine. (G and H) Quantification of data in E and F showing the percent change of baseline LVPD in response to BDNF 
(G) and caffeine (H) in WT and T1 −/− hearts. (I) Representative traces of Ca 2+ transients elicited by 2-Hz stimulation in isolated adult cardiomyocytes. 
Ca 2+ transient are increased by BDNF application only in WT (BDNF, light gray; no BDNF, black) but not in T1 −/− cardiomyocytes. (J) Effect of BDNF on 
transient amplitude is reversible as shown in typical time course from a WT and a T1 −/− cardiomyocyte. BDNF effect on Ca 2+ release has a rapid onset 
and is completely reversed in &lt;2 min upon BDNF removal. (K) Quantification of peak amplitude of calcium transient in WT and T1 −/− cardiomyocytes. 
The value for each group represents the transient change in percentage before (considered as 100%) and after BDNF application. 10 transients before 
and 10 transients after BDNF application were measured for each cardiomyocyte analyzed (n is shown within the bar). Values in G-K are indicated as 
the mean ± SEM. *, P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>JCB • Volume 210 • NumBer 6 • 2015 </p>

<p>
thetic tone (Donovan et al., 2000; Clark et al., 2011; Anastasia 
et al., 2014; Wan et al., 2014). Although our ex vivo and in vitro 
analysis support a direct role for BDNF on cardiomyocyte con-
traction, to address this point we selectively deleted TrkB.T1 
in cardiomyocytes by using a transgenic mouse expressing cre 
under the promoter of the murine α myosin heavy chain polypep-
tide 6 (Myh6; Fig. S4 C; Agah et al., 1997). As shown in Fig. 5, 
specific deletion of TrkB.T1 in cardiomyocytes completely 
abolished the inotropic effect of BDNF in Langendorff-per-
fused hearts. Interestingly, deletion of TrkB.T1 in endothelial 
cells using a cadherin5-specific cre mouse line as a control had 
no impact, as these hearts responded to BDNF as well as WT 
controls (Fig. 5, C and F). Most importantly, Myh6-cre/TrkB.T1 
mutant hearts showed dilated cardiomyopathy with signifi-
cantly reduced left ventricle posterior wall thickness, con-
firming an intrinsic cardiomyocyte role for TrkB.T1 in normal 
cardiac physiology (Fig. 5, G-K). Next we sought to determine 
whether BDNF is the ligand for TrkB.T1 in cardiomyocytes or 
whether other neurotrophins or Trk receptors could exert such a 
cardiac inotropic role. Thus, we evaluated the contraction force 
of perfused hearts in the presence of NGF or NT3. Whereas 
NGF had no effect on the heart contractile force, NT3 elicited a 
response, though slightly reduced compared with BDNF (Fig. 
S5, A-C). Because NT3 can also bind TrkB this result was not 
surprising (Coppola et al., 2001). Nevertheless, the lack of an 
NT3 inotropic effect in hearts lacking TrkB.T1 strongly sug-
gests that TrkB.T1 is the only neurotrophin receptor mediat-
ing this function. To further elucidate the source and identity 
of the neurotrophin activating TrkB.T1 we tested whether car-
diomyocytes could secrete a biologically active neurotrophin. 
Isolated embryonic cardiac myocytes were grown in culture for 
7-10 d and the supernatant was tested for its ability to induce 
phosphorylation of TrkB kinase expressed in a cell line. In fact, 
although TrkB full length is not present in cardiomyocytes, a 
ligand that activates it will also activate TrkB.T1 because they 
have an identical extracellular ligand-binding domain (Fig. 6). 
This approach was used because of its biological sensitivity and 
specificity over other assays (Coppola et al., 2001). We found 
that cardiomyocyte-conditioned medium induced in vitro TrkB 
phosphorylation (Fig. 6 C, WT). This result suggested that car-
diomyocytes produce and secrete a biologically active neuro-
trophin. To test if BDNF was the neurotrophic factor secreted in 
the medium we performed an immunoprecipitation experiment 
from medium conditioned by cardiomyocytes derived from 
a mouse model with an HA-tagged BDNF gene (Yang et al., 
2009). Immunoprecipitation with an anti-HA antibody revealed 
the presence of BDNF in the medium, suggesting that BDNF 
can be secreted by cardiomyocytes. Importantly, medium condi-
tioned by BDNF knockout cardiomyocytes was unable to induce 
TrkB phosphorylation, indicating that although NT3 can cause 
the inotropic effect in isolated hearts, BDNF is the TrkB.T1 
physiological ligand. This result also excluded the possibil-
ity that NT4, the other neurotrophin binding TrkB with high 
affinity, was the neurotrophin secreted by cardiomyocytes in 
the media, a result further supported by the very low level of 
NT3-and NT4-specific mRNA detected by RT-PCR in heart 
and cardiomyocytes (Fig. S5, D-F). Western blot analysis of 
adult hearts isolated from mice with the HA-tagged BDNF gene 
also confirmed BDNF expression, again suggesting that this is 
the physiological ligand source of TrkB.T1 in cardiomyocytes 
(Fig. 6 A). Therefore, we tested whether specific deletion of 
BDNF in cardiomyocytes caused cardiomyopathy. Hearts </p>

<p>Figure 3. BDNF signals independently of the catecholaminergic pathway 
and does not increase cardiac CamKII or PLB phosphorylation at the peak 
of its inotropic function. (A) Isoproterenol does not occlude the effect of 
BDNF in Langendorff-perfused hearts. Representative LVDP trace obtained 
from application of 100 nM isoproterenol (ISO) to a Langendorff-perfused 
heart. Once the heart reached stable LVDP a 50 µl (10 ng total) bolus of 
BDNF was applied followed by a second 50 µl (5 mM) bolus of caffeine as 
a positive control 2 min later. (B) Quantification of the effect of BDNF and 
caffeine on baseline LVDP in the absence or presence of ISO. The baseline 
for the values obtained with ISO is considered LVDP in the presence of 
ISO. Values are from four independent experiments. (C-F) BDNF does not 
increase cardiac CamKII or PLB phosphorylation at the peak of its inotropic 
function. (C) Western blot analysis of PLB phosphorylation at Ser16 (PLB 
P-S16) and Thr17 (PLB P-T17), CAMKII phosphorylation at Thr 286/287 
(CAMKII P-S286), and Troponin I at Ser23/24. Langendorff-perfused 
hearts were injected with vehicle (negative control), BDNF, or Forskolin 
(positive control) as described in Material and methods. (D-F) Quantifica-
tion of the bands intensity (±SEM) from C reported as the ratio between 
the phosphorylated form over the specific total protein. Means of the three 
samples ±SEM are shown. *, P &lt; 0.05, calculated with two-tail t test. </p>

<p>BDNF-TrkB.T1 function in cardiomyocytes • Fulgenzi et al. </p>



<p>from two-to three-month-old Myh6-cre-BDNF knockout mice 
showed dilated cardiomyopathy with significantly reduced pos-
terior wall thickness compared with littermate controls (Fig. 5, 
G-K). Strikingly, the similarity between the phenotype ob-
served in Myh6-cre-BDNF-and Myh6-cre-TrkB.T1-deficient 
mice suggests that BDNF-TrkB.T1 signal is intrinsic to cardio-
myocytes and functions by an autocrine/paracrine mechanism. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We have identified a new unexpected role of BDNF in adult car-
diac physiology. This action is mediated by truncated TrkB.T1 
receptors expressed in cardiomyocytes and is independent of 
BDNF function in the nervous system. Although truncated 
TrkB.T1 has an intracellular domain that is extremely con-
served among species, so far there is no data suggesting phys-
iological relevance of its direct signaling in vivo. In isolated 
glial cells, TrkB.T1 evokes Ca 2+ signal, but mice lacking this 
receptor do not show any obvious defect in this cell population 
(Carim-Todd et al., 2009). The lack of a phenotype could be </p>

<p>a result of compensatory mechanisms, redundancy of TrkB.T1 
-mediated Ca 2+ signaling in this cell type, or a function required 
during specific physiological challenges. However, we found 
that in cardiomyocytes Ca 2+ regulation by TrkB.T1 is critical as 
deletion of this receptor causes dilated cardiomyopathy. BDNF 
activation of TrkB.T1 appears modulatory of cardiac function as 
in a Langendorff-perfused heart it causes only a 5% increase in 
cardiac contraction force; yet loss of this pathway leads to car-
diomyopathy over the life of the animal. Indeed, it is not surpris-
ing that even small perturbations in the proper control of Ca 2+ 
levels are deleterious to normal cardiac function as Ca 2+ regula-
tion is central to the function of cardiomyocytes. Moreover, we 
provide evidence that BDNF is the ligand activating TrkB.T1 
in an autocrine/paracrine fashion as it is expressed and released 
by cardiomyocytes and its deletion in this cell type causes a 
cardiomyopathy resembling that caused by TrkB.T1 knock-
out. Most recently, a parallel study has suggested that TrkB is 
required for normal cardiac contraction and relaxation (Feng 
et al., 2015). Contrary to our study that shows that TrkB.T1 
is the receptor for BDNF in the heart, Feng et al. (2015) sug-
gested that instead this function is mediated by the TrkB kinase </p>

<p>Figure 4. TrkB.T1 deletion induces cardiac 
pathological alterations coupled with an in-
crease in L-type Ca 2+ channel level and cur-
rents. (A) WT and TrkB.T1 −/− hematoxylin and 
eosin-stained transversal heart sections show-
ing left ventricle dilation and reduced thick-
ness of left ventricle posterior wall apparent in 
TrkB.T1-deficient animals. (B) Quantification of 
the thickness (arrow) of the posterior wall (PW) 
and left ventricle area (LV); RV, right ventricle; 
n = 4 for each genotype. (C) Representative 
echocardiography recording in M-mode ob-
tained in WT and T1 −/− mice showing the left 
ventricle internal dimension at diastole (double 
head red arrows, LVID) and the left ventricle 
posterior wall (LVPW) thickness delineated 
by blue lines. (D) Quantification of LVID and 
LVPW thickness measured at diastole (dia), 
and fractional shortenings (FS) values ob-
tained from the echocardiography recordings 
(P &lt; 0.05). WT, n = 4; T1 −/− , n = 5. (E-J) 
TrkB.T1 deletion increases L-type calcium levels 
and currents in adult isolated cardiomyocytes. 
(E) I/V curves obtained in whole cell patch-
clamp isolated adult cardiomyocytes showing 
similar activation of L-type calcium channels 
but higher current density in T1 −/− versus 
WT cardiomyocytes. (F) Channel kinetics and 
current decay recordings are comparable in 
T1 −/− and WT cardiomyocytes. (G) Measure-
ments of plasma membrane capacitance are 
similar between WT and T1 −/− cardiomyo-
cytes, suggesting no difference in cell size. 
(H) Graph showing similar calcium-induced 
L-type current inactivation calculated by paired 
pulse protocol in WT and T1 −/− cardiomyo-
cytes. (I) Representative Western blot analysis 
of cardiac lysates from WT and T1 −/− hearts </p>

<p>using an antibody specific for the α 1c sub-</p>

<p>unit of the Cav1.2 channel. (J) Quantification 
of Western blot CaV1.2 a1c band intensity in 
relation to GAPDH; n = 6. Data are indicated 
as the mean ± SEM. *, P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>JCB • Volume 210 • NumBer 6 • 2015 </p>

<p>
receptor isoform. This finding is somewhat surprising because 
we and others have found that in the heart TrkB.T1-encoding 
mRNA is highest, whereas the TrkB kinase messenger RNA is 
virtually undetectable (Stoilov et al., 2002). The discrepancies 
in protein analysis data can be explained by the use of differ-
ent antibodies and appropriate controls. Nevertheless, the most 
important difference relates to the cardiac phenotype observed 
by Feng et al. (2015) in mouse models with specific inactiva-
tion of the kinase domain either by a chemical genetic (i.e., 
the TrkBF616A/1-NMPP1 model) or by a conditional deletion 
approach. We found that in Langendorff-perfused WT mouse 
hearts 100 nM 1-NMPP1 induced a dramatic increase in the 
cardiac contraction force and blunted the BDNF effect. Al-
though Feng et al. (2015) reported that 1-NMPP1 did not alter 
basal cardiomyocyte function they did not include a control to 
test whether 1-NMPP1 blunts BDNF action as we found (Fig. 
S3). Thus, it is possible that such an omission leads to misin-
terpreting the lack of BDNF inotropic function in the TrkB-
F6161A/1-NMPP1 model as a specific phenotype caused by 
loss of TrkB kinase activity. 
Although, we do not have a definitive explanation for the 
results obtained with a conditional deletion of a TrkB tyrosine </p>

<p>kinase-specific exon, it has been reported that targeting the ki-
nase domain of TrkB causes a dramatic down-regulation of the 
TrkB.T1 isoform protein (Klein et al., 1993). Although Klein et 
al. (1993) had no explanation for the disregulation, this finding 
suggests the possibility that a similar targeting of the kinase re-
gion by Feng et al. (2015) generates a TrkB.T1 hypomorph. In 
support of this scenario is the fact that targeting of the kinase 
domain causes only reduced systolic function insufficient to 
trigger chamber dilation (Feng et al., 2015), whereas the com-
plete deletion of TrkB.T1 achieved in our study causes a more 
severe pathology that includes cardiac dilation developed as a 
consequence of impaired Ca 2+ signaling. Importantly, targeting 
of the TrkB.T1-specific exon does not cause changes in the ex-
pression of the TrkB kinase receptor, again suggesting specific-
ity of the phenotype (Fig. 1; Dorsey et al., 2006). Nevertheless, 
the study by Feng et al. (2015) is important because it supports 
the finding that TrkB has an intrinsic role in cardiomyocyte 
function that is independent of cardiac innervation. Moreover, 
despite the possible explanations for the discrepancies between 
the two analyses, we cannot entirely exclude that a very small 
level of the TrkB tyrosine kinase receptor may in part be re-
sponsible for the BDNF effect in the heart. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Specific deletion of TrkB.T1 in car-
diomyocytes abolishes BDNF inotropic effect 
and leads to cardiomyopathy. (A-C) Repre-
sentative traces of LVDP before (baseline con-
sidered as 100%) and after BDNF or caffeine 
injection (arrows) in control myosin 6-specific 
cre transgenic (myh6-cre) mice used as con-
trols (A), double Myh6-cre, TrkB.T1 conditional 
(Myh6-cre/TrkB.T1 loxP ; B), and endothelial-spe-
cific cre (Cdh5-cre) TrkB.T1 conditional (Cdh5-
cre/TrkB.T1 loxP ; C) mutant mice. Caffeine was 
injected 5 min after BDNF as a positive control 
as in Fig. 2. The BDNF and caffeine traces 
were overlapped using the injection time 
(arrow) as a starting point. (D-F) Quantifica-
tion of LVDP recorded from the mice in A (D), 
B (E), and C (F). (G-I) Cardiomyocyte-specific 
deletion of TrkB.T1 or BDNF causes dilated car-
diomyopathy. Representative hematoxylin and 
eosin-stained sections from 2-3-mo-old control 
Myh6-cre transgenic (G; myh6; n = 4), Myh6-
cre/BDNF loxP/loxP (H; Myh6-BDNF; n = 5), or 
Myh6-cre/TrkB.T1 loxP/loxP (I; Myh6-TrkB.T1; 
n = 5) mouse hearts showing dilated left ven-
tricle and reduced left ventricle posterior wall 
thickness caused by BDNF or TrkB.T1 deletion. 
(J and K) Quantification of left ventricle (LV) 
area and posterior wall (PW) thickness was 
measured in heart transverse sections at the 
level and in between the papillary muscles 
(arrow). RV, right ventricle. Data are indicated 
as the mean ± SEM. *, P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>BDNF-TrkB.T1 function in cardiomyocytes • Fulgenzi et al. </p>



<p>An important new contribution of our study relates to 
the fact that we have identified the source and identity of the 
neurotrophin activating TrkB.T1 in the heart. This is relevant 
because other neurotrophins expressed in the heart could be re-
sponsible for this function (Scarisbrick et al., 1993; Emanueli 
et al., 2014). Moreover, our data suggest that BDNF produced 
in loco is a significant determinant of TrkB.T1 cardiac function. 
This was even more surprising considering the relatively low 
level of BDNF present in the heart compared with the brain 
(only ∼5% per gram of tissue; Fig. 6 A). In the future it will be 
of interest to investigate whether BDNF produced by periph-
eral districts (i.e., striatal muscle) can affect cardiac function 
and whether loss of either cardiac or peripheral BDNF is suffi-
cient to cause cardiomyopathy. 
A major question still unresolved relates to how TrkB.T1 
transduces BDNF inotropic function. The fact that the BDNF 
effect is additive to that of isoproterenol, a nonselective β-adr-
energic agonist, suggests that BDNF signaling does not overlap 
with the catecholamine-activated pathway. Moreover, in an ini-
tial analysis of some of the key players in cardiac excitation-</p>

<p>contraction coupling, including CamKII, PLB, and troponin I, 
we found no changes in their level of activation in response to 
BDNF treatment. This result appears to contrast the finding by 
Feng et al. (2015) that BDNF increases PLB, CamKII, and RyR 
receptor phosphorylation. However, their result was obtained 
after a prolonged treatment (10 or 20 min) of cardiomyocytes 
with BDNF, raising the possibility that the increase in the phos-
phorylation of these excitation-contraction coupling players 
may be secondary because it is detected after BDNF inotropic 
effect has already subsided. In our paradigm we found that at 
the peak of BDNF inotropic function in Langendorff-perfused 
hearts there was no increase of PLB or CamKII phosphoryla-
tion, suggesting that they are not directly involved in BDNF 
contraction in cardiomyocytes. 
In glia cells TrkB.T1 mediates inositol-1,4,5-trisphos-
phate (IP 3 )-dependent calcium release from intracellular stores. 
It was proposed that this mechanism involves an as yet uniden-
tified G protein that stimulates PLC production of IP 3 , Ca 2+ re-
lease from stores, and Ca 2+ entry from the extracellular space. It 
is tempting to speculate that a similar mechanism is at work in 
cardiomyocytes where TrkB.T1 induces Ca 2+ release from the 
intracellular stores and increases systolic Ca 2+ transients (Fig. 2). 
Indeed, IP 3 can contribute to systolic Ca 2+ transients through a 
mechanism by which IP 3 receptors are opened by a combination 
of IP 3 and Ca 2+ binding (Missiaen et al., 1994; Bootman et al., 
1995). According to such a model, IP 3 receptors can sit with 
IP 3 bound and wait for an activating Ca 2+ signal to derive from 
voltage-activated channels or neighboring RyRs (Kockskämper 
et al., 2008). In turn, activated IP 3 receptors would cause fur-
ther release of Ca 2+ from the ER, increasing the systolic Ca 2+ 
transients. Importantly, several studies point toward a relevant 
role of PLC-IP 3 signaling in the development and progression 
of cardiac hypertrophy and dilation, further supporting a link 
of BDNF to this pathway (Mende et al., 1998; Kockskämper 
et al., 2008). In the future, it will be important to investigate 
through pharmacological and genetics approaches whether this 
is indeed the TrkB.T1-activated pathway in cardiomyocytes. 
Lastly, considering the importance of BDNF/TrkB sig-
naling in the control of food intake, mood disorders, and neu-
rodegenerative diseases there is a significant effort to develop 
pharmacological agents to harness the activation of this path-
way (Nagahara and Tuszynski, 2011; Lu et al., 2014). Although 
most studies have been focused on the generation of BDNF mi-
metic molecules, which can activate all TrkB receptors (Longo 
and Massa, 2013; Rosenthal and Lin, 2014), the present results 
suggest that any such effort should consider possible effects on 
the function of the cardiovascular system. Nevertheless, our 
data indicate that pharmacological activation of intracellularly 
activated TrkB kinase pathways such as by a transactivation 
mechanism may achieve central nervous system activation of 
TrkB kinase without causing cardiac toxicity (Wiese et al., 
2007; Yanpallewar et al., 2012). </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Mouse models </p>

<p>TrkB.T1 knockout and conditional mutant mice were generated as 
described previously (Dorsey et al., 2006). BDNF-HA mice (Yang et 
al., 2009) were a gift of B. Hempstead (Cornell University, New York, 
NY). BDNF conditional (Rios et al., 2001) mutants as well as Myh6-
cre (Agah et al., 1997) and Cadherin5-cre (Alva et al., 2006) transgenic </p>

<p>Figure 6. BDNF is expressed in the adult heart and is secreted by car-
diomyocytes. (A) Heart (H) and brain (B) lysates obtained from a knock-in 
BDNF HA tagged and a WT mouse used as a control were immunoprecip-
itated and blotted with anti-HA antibodies. 15-kD molecular mass marker. 
Lysate inputs are on the right of the panel. (B and C) Embryonic cardiomy-
ocytes secrete biologically active BDNF. (B) Culture medium from WT and 
BDNF-HA cultured embryonic cardiomyocytes was immunoprecipitated as 
in A. WT and BDNF-HA brains were used as negative and positive con-
trols, respectively. (C) Cells stably expressing TrkB tyrosine kinase were 
used as a sensitive biological assay to test for the presence of secreted 
biologically active BDNF in the medium of cultured cardiomyocytes. After 
a 10-min incubation with the medium from different cardiomyocyte cul-
tures, cells expressing TrkB were lysed and subjected to Western analysis 
with an anti-phospho-TrkB antibody. Anti-TrkB and GAPDH antibodies 
were used as controls for loading. The tested supernatants were from WT, 
BDNF heterozygous (HET), and BDNF knockout cultured cardiomyocytes. 
Unconditioned media supplemented with 1 ng/ml of recombinant BDNF 
(BDNF)F and 1 µg/ml TrkB-Fc BDNF blocking antibody (BDNF+α) were 
used as positive and negative controls, respectively. Ctrl, unconditioned 
media (DMEM). The molecular mass is shown on the right. </p>

<p>JCB • Volume 210 • NumBer 6 • 2015 </p>

<p>
mice were obtained from the Jackson Laboratory. The Rosa26floxed-
LacZ mouse (strain 003474; The Jackson Laboratory) was used as a 
Cre reporter strain to test the tissue/cellular expression pattern of cre 
transgenic mice. Animals were bred in a specific, pathogen-free facility 
with food and water ad libitum. All experimental procedures followed 
the National Institutes of Health guidelines for animal care and use 
and were approved by the National Cancer Institute at Frederick An-
imal Care and Use Committee. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>Mouse hearts were quickly dissected and washed in cold PBS. After 
removal of the atria, ventricles were lysed in a Precellys ceramic lys-
ing kit tube with 1 ml RIPA buffer by two 30-s cycles at 5,000 rpm 
in PRECELLYS 24 (Bertin Technologies). Ventricle or adult cardio-
myocyte lysates (see the Adult mouse cardiomyocyte isolation sec-
tion) were then incubated with wheat germ agglutinin-agarose beads 
in RIPA buffer for 4 h at 4°C. Beads were washed three times with 
RIPA buffer, resuspended in Laemmli sample buffer, and boiled for 
5 min before loading in 4-12% NuPAGE (Life Technologies) precast 
gels for Western analysis. For the analysis of CamKII, PLB, and Tro-
ponin I, hearts were perfused in a Langendorff apparatus as described 
in the Langendorff heart preparation section with a modified Krebs 
solution with or without 20 ng/ml BDNF (PeproTech) or 5 µM For-
skolin (Sigma-Aldrich) used as a positive control. Heart contractility 
was monitored during the perfusion process and at the peak of cardiac 
pressure induced by BDNF or Forskolin the hearts were snap frozen 
with stainless steel clamps cooled in liquid nitrogen and stored fro-
zen before homogenization in RIPA buffer supplemented with prote-
ases (complete mini; Roche) and phosphatase inhibitors (PhosSTOP; 
Roche). Lysates were centrifuged at 15,000 g for 15 min at 4°C and 
the supernatants were diluted in 2× Laemmli sample buffer, boiled, and 
loaded in a gel for Western analysis. Membranes (PVDF; Life Tech-
nologies) were blocked in 5% nonfat milk or 5% BSA in TBS-Tween 
before incubation with a specific antibody. Antibodies were as follows: 
anti-TrkB (against the extracellular domain of TrkB and therefore rec-
ognizing all TrkB isoforms; EMD Millipore), anti-TrkB.T1 (Santa 
Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.), anti-GAPDH (EMD Millipore), anti-CaV 
1.2a1c (L-Type calcium channel subunit a1c,; Alomone Lab), anti-HA 
(for Western, Covance; for immunoprecipitation, Sigma-Aldrich), 
anti-Phospho-TrkB raised against phosphorylated TrkB-Tyr516 (Cell 
Signaling Technology), anti-total CAMKII (Cell Signaling Technol-
ogy), anti-CAMKII P-T286/T287 (Cell Signaling Technology), anti-
total Phospholamban (Thermo Fisher Scientific), anti-Phospholamban 
P-S16 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.), anti-Phospholamban P-T17 
(Badrilla), and anti-total and P-Ser 23/24 Troponin I (Cell Signaling 
Technology). After incubation with the appropriate HRP-conjugated 
secondary antibody, membranes were incubated with ECL substrate for 
detection of HRP enzyme activity (Thermo Fisher Scientific) and visu-
alized in a Syngene gel documentation system. Images were splined 
(Arganda-Carreras et al., 2006) as needed and quantified by <rs id="software-1" type="software">ImageJ</rs> 
analysis (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">National Institutes of Health</rs>). Student's t test was used for 
statistical significance assessment. </p>

<p>RT-PCR </p>

<p>Total RNA was extracted from isolated cardiomyocytes, heart, or 
cultured cells using the RNeasy Mini kit (QIAGEN). Following the 
manufacturer's procedure, cDNA was reverse-transcribed using the 
SuperScript III First-Strand Synthesis System (Life Technologies). 
Real-time PCR was performed with iTaq Universal SYBR-green Su-
permix (Bio-Rad Laboratories) in a MX3000P (Agilent Technologies) 
apparatus with the following program: 95°C for 3 min; 95°C for 10 s, 
60°C for 20 s for 40 cycles; 95°C for 1 min, and down to 55°C (gradient </p>

<p>of 1°C) for 41 cycles (melting curve step). Values were expressed in Δ </p>

<p>Ct using GAPDH as a reference. 
Primers were as follows: TrkB common forward, 5′-AGCAATC-
GGGAGCATCTCT-3′; TrkB.FL reverse, 5′-CTGGCAGAGTCATC-
GTCGT-3′; TrkB.T1 reverse, 5′-TACCCATCCAGTGGGATCTT-3′; 
GAPDH forward, 5′-TGCGACTTCAACAGCAACTC-3′; GAPDH 
reverse, 5′-ATGTAGGCCATGAGGTCCAC-3′; BDNF forward, 
5′-CGACATCACTGGCTGACACT-3′; BDNF reverse, 5′-CAAAGG-
CACTTGACTGCTGA-3′; NT3 forward, 5′-CCCCGTCAGCCAGGA-
TAATG-3′; NT3 reverse, 5′-CGCCTGGATCAGCTTGATGA-3′; NT4 
forward, 5′-TATCCTACAAAGGGGCCCCA-3′; NT4 reverse, 5′-CT-
GGGGAGGAGGAAGAGGAA-3′. RT-PCR products were separated 
in a 2% agarose gel stained with ethium bromide. </p>

<p>Langendorff heart preparation </p>

<p>Male mice (2 mo, 19-25 g) were injected with heparin (5,000 U/kg 
i.p.) and after 10 min were anesthetized with Avertin (150 mg/kg i.p.). 
Hearts were quickly removed from the chest and put into 16-18°C 
calcium-free modified Krebs solution containing 118 mmol NaCl, 23 
mmol NaHCO 3 , 3.2 mmol KCl, 1.2 mmol KH 2 PO 4 , 1.2 mmol MgSO 4 , 
11 mmol glucose, and 2 mmol sodium pyruvate before being mounted 
in a Langendorff perfusion system (Broadley, 1979). Hearts were per-
fused with modified Krebs solution containing 1.5 mM CaCl 2 (37.5°C) 
via the aorta. All solutions were bubbled with 95% O 2 -5% CO 2 , pH 
7.40, and kept at 37°C. An inflatable water-filled balloon was inserted 
into the left ventricle via a small incision in the left atrium for measure-
ment of the left ventricle pressure (BIOPAC Systems Inc.). Perfusion 
pressure and coronary flow were also continuously monitored via a dif-
ferential pressure transducer. All channels were fed to a digidata 1322a 
(Axon) for digitalization storage and analysis using <rs id="software-3" type="software">Igor</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">4.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Wave-Metrics</rs>) or <rs id="software-4" type="software">Clampfit</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Axon</rs>) software. 
After mounting, the hearts were equilibrated for 10 min at a per-
fusion pressure of 80 mmHg and at an end-diastolic pressure of 5-10 </p>

<p>mmHg. Only hearts with a sinus heart rate ≥300 bpm and a left ventri-
cle systolic pressure ≥70 mmHg at the end of the equilibration period </p>

<p>were included in the studies. After the equilibration period, hearts were 
paced by platinum electrode at 420 bpm and the baseline contractile 
parameters and coronary flow were recorded for an additional 10 min. 
Neurotrophins were added to the Krebs solution immediately before 
use from frozen stocks and injected into the flow stream in a T tube 
placed before the temperature control unit. Caffeine (5 mM in Krebs) 
and denatured BDNF (10 ng in Krebs; 95°C for 5 min) were used, 
respectively, as positive and negative control. The total volume from 
the injection point to the tip of the cannula was 1.4 ml and drugs were 
always injected in a 50-µl volume. The effect of any substance on heart 
parameters was calculated as a percentage of the mean value from 20 s 
before the injection. 1-NMPP1 was purchased from EMD Millipore 
and NT3 and NGF were purchased from Alomone Laboratories. </p>

<p>Adult mouse cardiomyocyte isolation </p>

<p>2-mo-old male mice were injected with heparin (5,000 U/kg i.p.) and 
after 10 min were anesthetized with Avertin (150 mg/kg i.p.). Hearts 
were quickly removed from the chest cavity and put into ice-cold calci-
um-free solution in ultrapure H 2 O (specific resistance &gt;21 MOhm) con-
taining 133.5 mM NaCl, 4 mM KCl, 1.2 mM NaH 2 P0 4 , 1.2 mM MgS0 4 , 
10 mM N-2-hydro-xyethylpiperazine-N'-2-ethanesulfonic acid, and 
11 mM glucose, adjusted to pH 7.4 with NaOH. The heart, cannulated 
through the aorta with a round tip 21G needle was mounted in a Langen-
dorff perfusion system and perfused at a pressure of 80 mmHg for 5 min 
with Ca 2+ -free solution containing 1 mg/ml BSA (Sigma-Aldrich) and 
subsequently for 8-15 min with the same solution containing 25 mM 
Ca 2+ together with collagenase type II (200-350 U/mg; Worthington </p>

<p>BDNF-TrkB.T1 function in cardiomyocytes • Fulgenzi et al. </p>



<p>Biochemical Corporation). Collagenase perfusion was determined by 
the coronary flow variation and stopped when it increased consistently. 
Ventricles were then cut into small pieces and gently triturated for 1-3 
min with a fire-polished Pasteur pipette. The resulting cell suspension 
was then passed through a 250-mesh filter and centrifuged at 150 rpm 
for 5 min. After resuspension in fresh control solution with 100 mM 
Ca 2+ , cells were washed again and resuspended in control solution con-
taining 200 mM Ca 2+ at 22-23°C (Wolska and Solaro, 1996). </p>

<p>Measurement of intracellular Ca 2+ transients </p>

<p>Calcium tolerant adult cardiomyocytes were loaded with Indo1-AM for 
1 h, washed with control solution, and left at room temperature for at 
least 45 min to allow deesterification of the dye. Loading solution was 
prepared from a control solution containing 0.2 mM Ca 2+ and 1 mM 
Indo1-AM (1 mM stock in dimethyl sulfoxide; Life Technologies) dis-
solved first in Pluronic surfactant (PowerLoad 100×; Life Technology) 
with 1 mg/ml BSA. Cardiomyocytes were field stimulated (0.5/s) with 
platinum electrodes (FHC Inc.) and recordings were made at 27°C 
in 1 mM Ca 2+ solution. BDNF was applied at 50 ng/ml using a pi-
cospritzer at 30 hPa and a glass pipette with 1-M Ohm tip resistance. 
Excited at 340 nM, indo1-AM emission was split into two channels and 
passed through 405/10-nm (calcium-bound emission) and 488/10-nm 
(calcium-free emission) fluorescence filters. Light collected by photo-
diodes (Till Photonics) was digitally converted at 10 KHz (<rs id="software-5" type="software">pClamp</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">10</rs> 
and Digidata 1322a) and computed and the information was stored. </p>

<p>Calcium current recordings </p>

<p>Ca 2+ -tolerant cardiomyocytes cells were placed in a recording cham-
ber and perfused with a Na + -free solution containing 137 mM tetra-
ethylammonium chloride, 1 mM MgCl 2 , 2 mM CaCl 2 , 10 mM Hepes, 
and 10 mM glucose (pH 7.4 with TEA-OH) at a flux of 1 ml/min at 
27°C. The pipette solution contained 111 mM CsCl, 20 mM tetraeth-
ylammonium chloride, 10 mM glucose, 14 mM EGTA, 10 mM Hepes, 
and 5 mM MgATP (pH 7.3 with CsOH). Pulled borosilicate glass pi-</p>

<p>pettes at ∼3-4 MOhm filled with pipette solution were used to obtain </p>

<p>gigaseal on cardiomyocytes and subsequent whole-cell voltage clamp. 
Currents (I Ca−L ) were elicited by applying depolarizing voltage steps </p>

<p>from a holding potential of −60 mV (-50 mV to +70 mV, 10-mV incre-</p>

<p>ments) and recorded (filtered at 2 kHz through a 4-pole low-pass Bessel 
filter and digitized at 5 kHz) with a Multiclamp 700B (Axon) using 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">pClamp</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Axon</rs>). The maximum absolute value of the current 
obtained (in pA) was divided by the cell capacitance (in pF). </p>

<p>Heart histology </p>

<p>Hearts from anesthetized mice were quickly removed from the chest 
cavity, placed in ice-cold calcium-and magnesium-free PBS, cannu-
lated through the aorta with a 21G needle, and perfused at a constant 
flow of 1 ml/min for 2 min with calcium-and magnesium-free PBS 
containing 20 mM KCl to induce cardiac relaxation. After that, the heart 
was perfused with 4% PFA in PBS for 10 min, cut in half horizontally, 
and fixed overnight at 4°C before paraffin embedding, sectioning at 7 
µm, and staining with hematoxylin and eosin or Masson trichromic. </p>

<p>Mouse embryonic cardiomyocytes </p>

<p>Mouse embryonic cardiomyocytes were prepared as previously de-
scribed (Graciotti et al., 2011). In brief, embryonic 17.5-d hearts were 
dissected, washed with ice-cold DMEM, minced, and incubated in 
0.25% trypsin (Gibco) at 37°C for 13 min. After centrifugation (1,000 
rpm for 5 min), the pellet was resuspended and incubated again in 
0.25% trypsin at 37°C for 13 min, centrifuged, resuspended, and incu-
bated in DMEM with 0.2% collagenase (collagenase type II) at 37°C 
for 30 min. Cells were then plated in a 10-cm dish in DMEM with 10% </p>

<p>FBS media. After 1 h, the floating cells were collected and plated in 
DMEM/10% FBS media at a density of 160,000 cells/cm 2 in 6-well 
plates pretreated with 40 µg/ml laminin for 1 h. Embryonic cardiomyo-
cytes were cultured for at least 7 d to allow differentiation before add-
ing fresh media for a conditioning period of 48 h. Supernatants were 
applied fresh (without freezing/thawing) to C2C12 cells stably express-
ing TrkB.Kin. Recombinant BDNF (Alamone Laboratories) and a re-
combinant TrkB Fc Chimera (R&amp;D Systems) were used as controls. </p>

<p>Echocardiography </p>

<p>Echocardiography was performed on 6-mo-old mice using a Vi-
sualSonic Vevo 770 equipped with a 30-MHz probe as previously 
reported (Gao et al., 2011). </p>

<p>β-Galactosidase staining 
For β-galactosidase staining, adult hearts retro-perfused with 4% PFA </p>

<p>were embedded in OCT mounting medium before freezing and sec-
tioning at 20 µm. Sections were washed three times for 5 min with 
100 mM sodium phosphate buffer, 20 mM MgCl 2 , 0.01% sodium 
deoxycholate, and 0.02% NP-40, and then stained for 2 h at 30°C 
with PBS without Mg 2+ /Ca 2+ , 5 mM K 3 Fe(CN) 6 , 5 mM K 4 Fe(CN) 6 , 
2 mM MgCl 2 , and 1 mg/ml X-gal, rinsed in dH 2 O, and counterstained 
with neutral red for 40 s. After three rinses in 100% ethanol, covers-
lips were mounted in xylene. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material </p>

<p>Fig. S1 shows that BDNF does not alter the spontaneous cardiac beating 
frequency. Fig. S2 shows that BDNF increases systolic and decreases 
diastolic pressure but has no effect on coronary flow. Fig. S3 provides 
evidence that the TrkBF616A mouse model is not suitable for this type 
of analysis because 1-NMPP1 exerts a potent inotropic and lusitropic 
effect in Langendorff-perfused hearts that occludes BDNF effect on 
contractility. Fig. S4 shows that TrkB.T1 deletion does not cause ob-
vious early postnatal cardiac developmental defects. Fig. S5 demon-
strates that BDNF is the main neurotrophin expressed in neonatal and 
adult cardiomyocytes although NT3 but not NGF causes an increase in 
the contraction force of WT but not TrkB.T1-deficient hearts. Table S1 
provides the functional parameters recorded in Langendorff-perfused 
hearts from WT and T1 −/− animals. Online supplemental material is 
available at http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201502100/DC1. 
Additional data are available in the JCB DataViewer at http://dx.doi. 
org/10.1083/jcb.201502100.dv. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Eileen Southon, Sudhir Yanpallewar, Erkan Kiris, and Mary 
Ellen Palko for critical reading of the manuscript and Lisa Riffle and 
Joseph Kalen for echocardiography imaging. </p>

<p>This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health Intramu-
ral Research Program, Center for Cancer Research, and National 
Cancer Institute. </p>

<p>The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Submitted: 26 February 2015 
Accepted: 21 July 2015 </p>



<p>JCB • Volume 210 • NumBer 6 • 2015 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>