<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4428716" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Chemokine is a group of factors to control the activity of 
white blood cells, and serves to control the infiltration of in-
flammatory cells (Yoshie et al., 2001), being closely related 
to various pathological processes, such as inflammation, al-
lergy, and infectious diseases. Chemokine is also known to 
be involved in generation and maturation of immune cells, 
and differentiation of T cells (Yoshie et al., 2001; Baumer et  al., 2004). Macrophage-derived chemokine (MDC/CCL22) is 
a typical inflammatory chemokine and a ligand for CC chemo-
kine receptor 4 (CCR4), which is predominantly expressed on 
Th2 lymphocytes, basophils and natural killer cells (Yamashita  and Kuroda, 2002; Saeki and Tamaki, 2006). Previous studies 
have shown that the MDC level is elevated in the serum and 
skin lesions of patients with atopic dermatitis (AD), suggesting 
that keratinocyte-generated chemokines are key mediators in 
the drawing of inflammatory lymphocytes to the skin (Maeda  et al., 2002; Shimada et al., 2004; Jahnz-Rozyk et al., 2005). </p>

<p>IFN-γ, one of the multifunctional cytokines that have anti-
viral, anti-tumor, and immunomodulatory effects is produced 
predominantly in T cells and NK cells (Farrar and Schreiber,  1993). Upon binding to IFN-γ, the IFN-γ receptor (IFN-γR1 and 
IFN-γR2) rapidly associates with the Janus tyrosine kinases 
JAK1 and JAK2. JAK1 and JAK2 phosphorylate one anoth-
er and then subsequently phosphorylate the IFN-γ receptor, 
which leads to form a docking moiety for the cytoplasmic 
transcription factor named signal transducer and activator of 
transcription (STAT)1, a member of the STAT protein family 
(Ivashkiv and Hu, 2004; Best et al., 2005) . It has been found 
that STAT1 phosphorylation plays a critical role in IFN-medi-
ated innate immunity to microbial infection, especially inflam-
matory responses (Ju et al., 2009). It is also known that IFN-γ 
also stimulates the activation of p38 and extracellular signal-
regulated kinase 1/2 (ERK1/2), NF-κB (Pearson et al., 2001;  Madonna et al., 2008). 
Recently, a lot of effort has been made to discover biologi-
cally active components from marine plants. Ecklonia cava is </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Biomol Ther 23(3), 238-244 (2015) </p>

<p>* Corresponding Author </p>

<p>E-mail: eunsyoo@jejunu.ac.kr 
Tel: +82-64-754-3847, Fax: +82-64-702-2687 
 † The first two authors contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>Received Dec 15, 2014 Revised Jan 31, 2015 Accepted Feb 26, 2015 
Published online May 1, 2015 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2014.141 </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 The Korean Society of Applied Pharmacology </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Com-
mons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licens-
es/by-nc/4.0/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, 
and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>Macrophage-derived chemokine, C-C motif chemokine 22 (MDC/CCL22), is one of the inflammatory chemokines that controls 
the movement of monocytes, monocyte-derived dendritic cells, and natural killer cells. Serum and skin MDC/CCL22 levels are el-
evated in atopic dermatitis, which suggests that the chemokines produced from keratinocytes are responsible for attracting inflam-
matory lymphocytes to the skin. A major signaling pathway in the interferon-γ (IFN-γ)-stimulated inflammation response involves 
the signal transducers and activators of transcription 1 (STAT1). In the present study, we investigated the anti-inflammatory effect 
of dieckol and its possible action mechanisms in the category of skin inflammation including atopic dermatitis. Dieckol inhibited 
MDC/CCL22 production induced by IFN-γ (10 ng/mL) in a dose dependent manner. Dieckol (5 and 10 mM) suppressed the phos-
phorylation and the nuclear translocation of STAT1. These results suggest that dieckol exhibits anti-inflammatory effect via the 
down-regulation of STAT1 activation. </p>

<p>Key Words: Dieckol, Inflammation, Keratinocyte, MDC/CCL22, STAT1 </p>

<p>Dieckol, a Component of Ecklonia cava, Suppresses the 
Production of MDC/CCL22 via Down-Regulating STAT1 Pathway 
in Interferon-γ Stimulated HaCaT Human Keratinocytes </p>

<p>Na-Jin Kang 
1, † , Dong-Hwan Koo 
1, † , Gyeoung-Jin Kang 
2 , Sang-Chul Han 
2 , Bang-Won Lee 
2 , Young-Sang Koh 
1,2 , </p>

<p>Jin-Won Hyun 
1,2 , Nam-Ho Lee 
3 , Mi-Hee Ko 
4 , Hee-Kyoung Kang 
1,2 and Eun-Sook Yoo </p>

<p>1,2, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Departments of 
1 Biomedicine &amp; Drug Development, 
2 Medicine, School of Medicine, 
3 Chemistry, College of Natural Science, Jeju 
National University, Jeju 690-756, 
4 Jeju Biodiversity Research Institute, JejuTechnopark, Jeju 699-943, Republic of Korea </p>

<p>Abstract </p>



<p>Kang et al. Dieckol Alleviates Skin Cell Inflammation </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>one of edible brown algae and is abundant along the coast of 
Jeju island. E. cava has been attended as a potential producer 
of diverse natural materials such as alginic acids, phlorotan-
nins and fucoidans which show useful activities in bio-industri-
al areas including medicine, cosmetics, and functional foods 
(Wijesinghe et al., 2011; Kang et al., 2012b; Kim et al., 2014). 
Phlorotannins (eckol, dieckol, and bieckol) isolated from E. 
species are representative components of marine secondary 
metabolites. Among them, dieckol is a phlorotannin compound 
consisting of a dimeric structure of polyphenolic compound 
eckol (Park et al., 2013). Dieckol has shown anti-oxidant (Lee  et al., 2012), anti-cancer (Park and Jeon. 2012), anti-diabetic 
(Lee et al., 2012; Kang et al., 2013), hepatoprotective (Kang et  al., 2012a), and anti-inflammatory effects (Yayeh et al., 2014). 
There are several studies on the anti-inflammatory effects of 
dieckol in lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-induced murine macro-
phages (RAW264.7 cells) (Choi et al., 2014). However, the bi-
ological effects of dieckol and its action mechanisms in skin in-
flammation including atopic dermatitis are poorly understood. 
In the present study, we aimed to explore the effect of di-
eckol on IFN-γ induced signaling pathways in HaCaT cells, as 
well as the link between specific pathways and inflammatory 
chemokine production. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Reagents </p>

<p>Eckol and dieckol were provided by Professor Nam-Ho 
Lee (Jeju national university, Jeju, Korea) (Fig. 1). Human in-
terferon-γ (hIFN-γ: recombinant E.coli) was purchased from 
Gibco (Grand Island, NY, USA), and MDC enzyme-linked 
immunosorbent assay (ELISA) duoset kit was obtained from 
R&amp;D system (St. Louis, MO, USA). Anti-STAT1 antibody was 
purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Santa Cruz, CA, 
USA). Anti-phospho-STAT1 antibody was purchased from 
Cell signaling (Beverly, MA, USA), and anti-β-actin antibody, 
Epigallocatechingallate (EGCG) and PD98059 were obtained 
from Sigma Chemical Co. (St. Louis, MO, USA). All other 
chemicals and reagents were of reagent grade. </p>

<p>Cell culture and cell viability assay </p>

<p>Human adult low-calcium high-temperature (HaCaT) ke-
ratinocyte was obtained from the Amore Pacific Company 
(Gyeonggi-do, Republic of Korea). The cells were cultured in 
RPMI1640 medium supplemented with 10% FBS and 100 U/ 
mL penicillin-streptomycin. The cells were maintained at 37 
o C 
in an incubator with a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO 2 . Cell 
viability was determined using an EZ-cytox-enhanced cell vi-
ability assay kit (itsBIO, Korea) following the manufacturer's 
protocol. Briefly, cells were seeded into the wells of a 96-well 
plate and treated with IFN-γ (10 ng/mL) in the absence or 
presence of eckol or dieckol for 24 h. A solution (5 mL) of WST 
(2-(4-iodophenyl)-3-(4-nitrophenyl)-5-(2,4-disulfophenyl)-2H-
tetrazolium) was added to each well and incubated for 1 h in 
an incubator. Then, the absorbance of each well was mea-
sured at 450 nm with a VersaMax ELISA microplate reader 
(Molecular Devices Inc., Sunnyvale, CA, USA). </p>

<p>ELISA analysis </p>

<p>Secretion of the MDC protein into the supernatant of cul-
tured cells was measured by using an ELISA kit according </p>

<p>to the manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, HaCaT cells were 
stimulated with IFN-γ in the presence of dieckol or other test 
samples for 24 h. The cell culture medium was transferred to 
a 96-well culture plate coated with MDC antibody and treated 
according to the manufacturer's (R&amp;D Systems) instructions. 
Absorbance at 450 nm was recorded by using the VersaMax 
ELISA microplate reader. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>HaCaT cells were washed twice with ice-cold phosphate 
buffered saline (PBS), and then disrupted in lysis buffer (50 
mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 150 mM NaCl, 1% Nonident P-40, 2 mM 
ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid (EDTA), 1 mM ethylene glycol 
bis (2-aminoethylether)-N,N,N_,N_-tetraacetic acid (EGTA), 1 mM 
NaVO3, 10 mM NaF, 1 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), 1 mM phenyl-
methylsulfonyl fluoride, and 25 mg/mL leupeptin) on ice for 30 
min. Cell lysates were centrifuged at 15,000 rpm for 15 min at 
4 
o C, and the supernatants were used for Western blotting. The 
total protein concentration of each sample was quantified via 
the Bio-Rad assay method (Bio-Rad). Extracts containing 30 
mg of protein were loaded next to a prestained protein-mass 
ladder (Bio-Rad) on a NuPAGE 4-12% bis-Tris gel (Invitrogen, 
Carlsbad, CA, USA). The proteins were elec troblotted onto a 
polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membra ne by using an iBlot 
gel transfer device (Invitrogen). The membrane was blocked 
with blocking buffer (5% skim milk in Tween 20-Tris buffered 
saline (TTBS)) for 1 h at room temperature, followed by over-
night incubation at 4°C with the appropriate primary antibod-
ies (anti-phospho-STAT1, anti-STAT1, anti-phospho-ERK, anti-
ERK, anti-phospho-JNK, anti-JNK, anti-phospho-p38, anti-p38, </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Chemical structures of eckol and dieckol. (A) Eckol (B) Di-</p>

<p>eckol. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>OH 
OH </p>

<p>OH 
O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH 
OH 
OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O 
O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>B </p>



<p>Biomol Ther 23(3), 238-244 (2015) </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2014.141 </p>

<p>and anti-β-actin antibodies). All antibodies were diluted in 1% 
bovine serum albumin (BSA) in TTBS buffer. After washing, 
the membrane was incubated with horseradish peroxidase 
(HRP)-conjugated anti-primary antibody host immunoglobulin 
G (IgG) diluted 1 : 5000 for 1 h at room temperature. After washing 
again, immunoreactive bands were visualized with a western 
blot detection system (iNtRON Biotechnology) according to 
the manufacturer's instructions. </p>

<p>Confocal microscopy analysis </p>

<p>HaCaT cells were seeded onto round coverslips in a 6-well 
plate and incubated were stimulated with IFN-γ in the pres-
ence of dieckol for 24 h. Fixed with freshly prepared 3.7% 
paraformaldehyde for 30 min, and permeabilized with ice-cold 
100% MeOH for 10 min at -20°C. After a 1 h incubation with 
3% BSA/0.1% Triton X-100/PBS, the cells were incubated 
with primary anti-STAT1 antibodies overnight at 4 
o C. The cells 
were washed and then incubated with DyLight488-conjugated 
donkey anti-rabbit (BioLegend, San Diego, CA, USA) sec-
ondary antibody for 30 min at room temperature. After sev-
eral additional washing steps, the coverslips were mounted in 
VECTASHIELD mounting media with DAPI (Vector Labs, Bur-
lingame, CA, USA). Fluorescently labeled STAT1 was visual-
ized by using a FV500 confocal microscope (Olympus Corp., 
Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">ImageJ</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">1.47n</rs> software was used to transform images of 
Western blots into numerical values. Student's t-test was de-
termined the statistical significance of differences. All numeri-
cal data represent the mean ± standard deviation (S.D.). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Effects of eckol and dieckol on MDC production in IFN-γ-
stimulated HaCaT keratinocytes </p>

<p>We first examined the cell cytotoxicity of eckol and dieckol 
against HaCaT cells. The cells were treated with different con-
centrations of eckol and dieckol (12.5, 25, and 50 mM) for 24 
h. Cell viability was determined using an EZ-cytox-enhanced 
cell viability assay kit. As shown in Fig. 2A and 2C, eckol and 
dieckol did not exhibit cytotoxicity to HaCaT keratinocytes 
at the tested concentrations. Then, we evaluated the inhibi-
tory effects of eckol and dieckol on inflammatory chemokine 
(MDC) production in IFN-γ (10 ng/mL)-stimulated HaCaT ke-
ratinocytes. The basal level of MDC production is 118.0 ± 8.3 pg/ 
mL, and 278.6 ± 6.0 pg/mL of MDC was produced by IFN-γ 
treatment (10 ng/mL). Interestingly, eckol failed to inhibit the 
cytokine-stimulated production of MDC (Fig. 2B). However, 
dieckol significantly suppressed the production of MDC by 
IFN-γ in a concentration-dependent manner. Especially, 12.5 
uM dieckol strongly suppressed by 135 ± 12.7 pg/mL (almost 
the basal level) of MDC production in IFN-γ-stimulated HaCaT 
keratinocyte (Fig. 2D). </p>

<p>Effect of dieckol on STAT1 activation in IFN-γ-stimulated 
HaCaT keratinocytes </p>

<p>STAT1 protein is a crucial and specific regulator of IFN-γ-
induced signals that controls the transcription of target genes, 
including MDC (Ivashkiv and Hu. 2004; Best et al., 2005; Kang  et al., 2008; Rauch et al., 2013). Therefore, we tested the effect 
of dieckol on the activation of STAT1 in IFN-γ-treated HaCaT 
keratinocytes and detected a high level of phosphorylated </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Effects of eckol and dieckol on the cell viability and MDC production in HaCaT human keratinocytes. (A) and (C) HaCaT cells were </p>

<p>treated with indicated concentrations of eckol or dieckol (12.5, 25, and 50 mM) for 24 h, and cell viability was assayed by WST assay. (B) 
and (D) HaCaT cells (2.0 × 10 
5 cells/mL) were stimulated with IFN-γ (10 ng/mL) in the presence or absence of eckol or dieckol for 24 h. 
The amounts of MDC were measured from the culture supernatants by ELISA. Data are mean ± S.D. of three independent experiments. 
**p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001 vs. sample-untreated cells in the presence of IFN-γ. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Eckol + 12.5 25 50 ( M) 
m </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 
Cell viability (% of control) 
0 </p>

<p>Dieckol + 12.5 25 50 ( M) 
m </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 
Cell viability (% of control) 
0 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>IFN-g 
Dieckol + 12.5 25 50 ( M) 
m </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 
MDC production (pg/ml) </p>

<p>0 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ (10 ng/ml) </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>IFN-g 
Eckol + 12.5 25 50 ( M) 
m </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 
MDC production (pg/ml) </p>

<p>0 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ (10 ng/ml) </p>

<p>B </p>



<p>Kang et al. Dieckol Alleviates Skin Cell Inflammation </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>STAT1 at 15 min after cytokine treatment. Pre-treatment of 
the cells with dieckol for 30 min dose-dependently suppressed 
STAT1 (serine 727) phosphorylation (Fig. 3A). In addition, mi-
croscopy results showed that IFN-γ led to nuclear transloca-
tion of STAT1 within 1 h, and dieckol (5, 10 mM) suppressed 
the nuclear translocation of phosphorylated STAT1 (serine 
727) (Fig. 3B). These results suggest that the inhibitory effect </p>

<p>of dieckol on the production of MDC occurs through inhibiting 
the activation and nuclear translocation of STAT1. </p>

<p>Effect of dieckol on MAP kinases pathway in IFN-γ-
stimulated HaCaT keratinocytes </p>

<p>The MAPKs pathway is reportedly involved in the produc-
tion of inflammatory chemokines, IFN-γ activates receptor-</p>

<p>Fig. 3. Effect of dieckol on the phosphorylation and nuclear translocation of STAT1 in IFN-γ -stimulated HaCaT human keratinocytes. (A) </p>

<p>HaCaT cells (5.0×10 
5 cells/mL) were pretreated with epigallocatechingallate (EGCG; 10 mM) or dieckol (2.5, 5, 10 mM) for 30 min. The phos-
phorylation of STAT1 was determined in cells stimulated with IFN-γ (10 ng/mL) for 15 min. The phosphorylation or level of each protein in 
whole cell lysates was determined by Western blotting with the indicated antibodies. (B) HaCaT cells were pre-treated with EGCG (10 mM) 
or dieckol (2.5, 5, 10 mM) for 2 h. The nuclear translocation of the STAT1 protein was determined in cells stimulated with IFN-γ for 20 min. 
Immunofluorescence staining for STAT1 was performed by using a primary antibody against STAT1, followed by a DyLight488-conjugated 
secondary antibody. The fluorescence was then identified by using a confocal microscope (FV500, Olympus Corp.), and the images were 
acquired at constant two-photon excitation microscopy (PMT), gain, offset, magnification (40× oil immersion objective with a zoom factor of 
1.5), and resolution. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 
Band density RATIO (p-STAT1/ -actin) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0 
pY-STAT1 </p>

<p>pS-STAT1 </p>

<p>STAT1 </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>91/84 kDa </p>

<p>91 kDa </p>

<p>91/84 kDa </p>

<p>42 kDa </p>

<p>(10 ng/ml) </p>

<p>( M) 
m </p>

<p>IFN-
EGCG 
Dieckol </p>

<p>g 
10 </p>

<p>No stimulated 
IFN-10 ng/ml 
g 
IFN-+EGCG 10 M 
g 
m 
IFN-+Dieckol 2.5 M 
g 
m </p>

<p>p-STAT1 (S727) </p>

<p>IFN-+ 
5 M 
g 
m 
Dieckol 
IFN-+ 
1 0 M 
g 
m 
Dieckol </p>

<p>DAPI </p>

<p>Merged </p>

<p>B </p>



<p>Biomol Ther 23(3), 238-244 (2015) </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2014.141 </p>

<p>associated MAPKs depending on the cell type (Pearson et al.,  2001; Madonna et al., 2008). We thus investigated the involve-
ment of these signaling kinases in IFN-γ induced MDC produc-
tion in HaCaT cells. We first determined time dependent acti-
vation of three MAPKs (ERK, JNK, p38) after IFN-γ treatment. 
As illustrated in Fig. 4A. IFN-γ induced the phosphorylation of 
ERK at 5 min, while there was no effect on the phosphoryla-
tion of JNK and p38. Then we examined the inhibitory effect 
of dieckol on the ERK activation in IFN-γ-stimulated HaCaT 
cells. PD98059 (a specific ERK inhibitor, 10 mM), strongly sup-
pressed ERK phosphorylation, but, dieckol did not inhibit ERK 
phosphorylation (Fig. 4B). To confirm whether MAPKs path-
way associate with MDC production, we determined the MDC 
level after the treatment of known MAPKs inhibitors in IFN-
γ-stimulated HaCaT cells. SP600125 (a specific JNK inhibi-
tor) and PD98059 (a specific ERK inhibitor), and SB203580 
(a specific p38 inhibitor) did not affect on the MDC production 
induced by IFN-γ (Fig. 4C). These results suggest that MAPKs 
pathway does not contribute on the production of MDC in 
IFN-γ stimulated HaCaT cells. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Various marine bio-resources have recently been explored 
because of the investigations of active components in phar-
maceutical and functional food areas (Kim and Himaya. 2011;  Jung et al., 2013). Dieckol was discovered during the determi-
nation of anti-inflammatory materials from marine plants living 
in the Jeju coastal area. Dieckol, one of various bioactive phlo-
rotannins of Ecklonia cava (e.g., eckol, 6, 6-bieckol, dieckol, 
and phloroglucinol), is suggested to elicit anti-diabetic, anti-
oxidant, anti-tumorigenic, and anti-inflammatory activities (Lee  et al., 2012; Park and Jeon. 2012; Kang et al., 2013; Yayeh et  al., 2014; Choi et al., 2014). 
In the present study, we investigated the anti-inflammatory 
effect of dieckol and its possible action mechanisms in the cat-
egory of skin inflammation including atopic dermatitis. First we 
examined the effect of the two phlorotannin compounds (eckol 
and dieckol) on the MDC production in IFN-γ-stimulated Ha-
CaT keratinocytes. Dieckol suppressed MDC production in a 
dose dependent manner, while eckol was not effective. 
The promoter region of the MDC gene contains binding 
units for signal transducers and activators of transcription 
(STAT), activating protein (AP)-1, and NF-κB, and these fac-
tors may mediate the transcription of the MDC (Pearson et  al., 2001; Ivashkiv and Hu. 2004; Best et al., 2005; Madonna  et al., 2008; Qi et al., 2009). IFN-γ acts via two IFN receptors 
subunits (IFNGR1 and IFNGR2), which form a heterotetramer 
on the cell surface, and activates various signaling cascades. 
Phosphorylated STAT1 functions as a transcription factor that 
activates the primary genes related to inflammatory respons-
es. Therefore, the STAT1 protein is a crucial and specific regu-
lator of IFN-γ signaling that controls the transcription of target 
genes, including MDC (Ivashkiv and Hu. 2004; Best et al.,  2005). It has been found that STAT1 phosphorylation plays a 
critical role in IFN-mediated innate immunity to microbial infec-
tion (van den Broek et al., 1995; Han et al., 2002; Semper et  al., 2014). After phosphorylation, STAT1 homodimerizes and 
translocates to the nucleus, and promotes gene transcription 
via binding to IFN-γ-activated genes. STAT1 homodimeriza-
tion is preferentially mediated by the binding of the phosphory-</p>

<p>Fig. 4. Effect of dieckol on the MAPKs pathway in IFN-γ -stimu-</p>

<p>lated HaCaT human keratinocytes. (A) HaCaT cells (5.0×10 
5 cells/ 
mL) were stimulated with IFN-γ (10 ng/mL) for indicated times (0-
360 mins). Whole cell lysates were obtained at indicated time 
points. The phosphorylations of p38, JNK, and ERK were assessed 
by Western blotting from whole cell lysates. (B) HaCaT cells (5.0 
× 10 
5 cells/mL) were pre-treated with PD98059 (a specific ERK in-
hibitor, 10 mM) or dieckol (2.5, 5, 10 mM) for 2 h and stimulated by 
IFN-γ (10 ng/mL) for 5 mins. The phosphorylation of ERK was de-
termined by Western blotting of whole cell lysates. (C) HaCaT cells 
(2.0×10 
5 cells/mL) were stimulated with IFN-γ (10 ng/mL) in the 
presence or absence of the specific MAPK inhibitors (SP600125; 
JNK inhibitor, PD98059; ERK inhibitor, SB203580; p38 inhibitor) 
for 24 h. The amounts of MDC were measured from the culture su-
pernatants by ELISA. Data are mean ± S.D. of three independent 
experiments. </p>

<p>pJNK </p>

<p>JNK </p>

<p>pERK </p>

<p>ERK </p>

<p>p-p38 </p>

<p>p38 </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>IFN-g 
Time </p>

<p>54/46 kDa </p>

<p>54/46 kDa </p>

<p>44/42 kDa </p>

<p>44/42 kDa </p>

<p>43 kDa </p>

<p>43 kDa </p>

<p>42 kDa </p>

<p>(10 ng/ml) 
(min) 
5 
15 30 60 120 240 360 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>160 
140 
120 
100 
80 
60 
40 
20 
Band density RATIO (pERK/ -actin) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0 
pERK </p>

<p>ERK </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>44/42 kDa </p>

<p>44/42 kDa </p>

<p>42 kDa </p>

<p>(10 ng/ml) </p>

<p>( M) 
m </p>

<p>IFN-
PD98059 
Dieckol </p>

<p>g 
10 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 
MDC production 
(% of control) </p>

<p>0 
IFN-
Conc. 
Inhibitor </p>

<p>g 
(10 ng/ml) 
(min) 
5 
10 2 10 
2 
1 
SP600125 PD98059 SB203580 </p>



<p>Kang et al. Dieckol Alleviates Skin Cell Inflammation </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>lated STAT1 (at tyrosine 701) to the Src homology 2 domain 
of another. However, the binding of the phosphorylated serine 
727 of STAT1 is required for maximal transcriptional activity 
(Decker and Kovarik. 2000; Ivashkiv and Hu. 2004; Best et  al., 2005). In our study, dieckol suppressed STAT1 (at serine 
727) phosphorylation induced by IFN-γ in a dose dependent 
manner. The effect of dieckol on the STAT1 phosphorylation 
is stronger than that of EGCG, a specific STAT inhibitor, at the 
same concentration (10 mM). In addition, microscopy results 
showed that dieckol (5, 10 mM) suppressed the nuclear trans-
location of phosphorylated STAT1 (at serine 727). 
The MAPK pathway is reportedly involved in the production 
of inflammatory chemokines. Several plant extracts and com-
pounds have been shown to inhibit the actions of inflammatory 
chemokines via the regulation of mitogen-activated protein ki-
nase (MAPK) cascades. (Pearson et al., 2001; Madonna et  al., 2008; Chae et al., 2013; Yoon et al., 2013). To determine 
whether the MAPKs (ERK, JNK, p38) signaling is involved in 
IFN-γ induced MDC production in HaCaT cells, we first exam-
ined time dependent activation of three MAPKs (ERK, JNK, 
p38) after IFN-γ treatment. IFN-γ induced the phosphorylation 
of ERK at 5 min, while did not affect on the phosphorylation 
of JNK and P-38. Then, we focused on the inhibitory effect 
of dieckol on the ERK activation in IFN-γ-stimulated HaCaT 
cells, but, the effect of dieckol was not significant. To confirm 
whether MAPKs pathway associate with MDC production, 
we determined the MDC levels after the treatment of known 
MAPKs inhibitors in IFN-γ-stimulated HaCaT cells. SP600125 
(a specific JNK inhibitor) and PD98059 (a specific ERK inhibi-
tor), and SB203580 (a specific p38 inhibitor) did not affect on 
the MDC production induced by IFN-γ. These results suggest 
that MAPKs pathway does not contribute significantly on the 
production of MDC in IFN-γ stimulated HaCaT cells. 
Taken together, of the two phlorotannin compounds (eckol 
and dieckol) tested in this study, only dieckol strongly sup-
pressed MDC production in HaCaT human keratinocytes. Di-
eckol also inhibited the activation of STAT1, a major transcrip-
tion factor that activates the primary genes induced by IFN-γ. 
In addition, MAPKs pathway did not affect on the production of 
MDC in IFN-γ stimulated HaCaT cells. These results provide 
new evidence regarding anti-inflammatory potential of dieckol 
and its action mechanism in a skin cell line. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by the National Research Foun-
dation of Korea Grant funded by the Korean Government 
(MEST) (NRF-C1ABA001-2011-0021039). </p>





<p>Biomol Ther 23(3), 238-244 (2015) </p>



</text></tei>