<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4435018" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>). Briefly, 20 µL of plasma plus three 
drops of chase buffer were placed on the pad of the dipstick, and; ii) In 
house immunofluorescent antibody test (IFAT) was performed following 
a standard method using 10 µL of 2 x 10 7 L. infantum promastigotes/ 
mL in 1x PBS per well as antigen (reference strain MHOM/FR/78/ 
LEM-75) and serial two-fold dilutions of plasma for the analysis 3 . The </p>

<p>ACOSTA, L.; DÍAZ, R.; TORRES, P.; SILVA, G.; RAMOS, M.; FATTORE, G.; DESCHUTTER, E.J. &amp; BORNAY-LLINARES, F.J. -Identification of Leishmania infantum in Puerto Iguazú, 
Misiones, Argentina. Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo, 57(2): 175-6, 2015. </p>

<p>176 </p>

<p>IFAT threshold title for positivity was 1/160. From 209 surveyed dogs, 
13 (6.22%) were seropositive by IFI (13/209) and/or by ICT (12/209). </p>

<p>Lymph node samples were washed with 500 µL of PBS and DNA 
was extracted by conventional phenol-chloroform extraction and ethanol 
precipitation 7 , and further eluted in 100 µL sterile distilled water. Purified 
DNA was stored at -80 o C until further use. Parasite DNA detection was 
done by means of PCR targeting the Leishmania intergenic transcript 
spacer (ITS-1) 10 . Amplicons were visualized in seven out of 209 
dogs. A total of 15 (7.17%) dogs were positive by serological and/or 
parasitological methods. </p>

<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">BioEdit</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v7.2.5</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Tom Hall, Ibis Biosciences, Carlsbad, CA</rs>The authors especially acknowledge the essential collaboration of the 
"Mundo Sano" Foundation, the Ministry of Public Health of Misiones 
and the City Land Registry of Puerto Iguazú. </p>

<p>This study was supported by the Agencia Española de Cooperación 
Internacional al Desarrollo (AECID) (A2/037352/11) and Centro de 
Cooperación y Voluntariado of the Universidad Miguel Hernández de 
Elche (UMH), Alicante, Spain. </p>



<p>Received: 26 May 2014 
Accepted: 1 July 2014 </p>

</text></tei>