<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4360221" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: The adolescent brain is sensitive to experience-dependent plasticity and might be more vulnerable than the 
adult brain to the effects of some drugs of abuse. The factors that contribute to these differences are not fully identified. 
We have examined the ability of cannabinoids to induce a form of synaptic plasticity, long-term depression, in the nucleus 
accumbens and dorsolateral striatum of adolescent and adult mice. 
Methods: We measured field excitatory postsynaptic potentials/population spikes in brain slices. 
Results: We found that the cannabinoid receptor agonist WIN 55,212-2 (R)-(+)-[2,3-dihydro-5-methyl-3-(4-morpholinylmethyl) 
pyrrolo[1,2,3-de]-1,4-benzoxazin-6-yl]-1-naphthalenylmethanone mesylate) induced long-term depression in the nucleus 
accumbens of adolescent but not adult mice and failed to induce long-term depression in the dorsolateral striatum of 
adolescent or adult mice. Similar results were obtained with the group I metabotropic glutamate receptor agonist (S)-3,5-
dihydroxyphenylglycine, which has previously been shown to promote the release of endocannabinoids. These age-related 
differences were associated with reduced protein levels of the cannabinoid type 1 receptor and metabotropic glutamate 
receptor 1 in adult nucleus accumbens and dorsolateral striatum and with an increased tone of endocannabinoids in the 
dorsolateral striatum of adult mice. We also found that N-methyl-d-aspartate receptor-dependent long-term depression, 
which was induced in the nucleus accumbens of adolescent mice, was blunted in adult mice, possibly because of decreased 
levels of GluN1, the obligatory subunit of N-methyl-d-aspartate receptors. 
Conclusions: This study identifies region-and age-specific differences in the ability of endogenous and exogenous cannabinoids, 
and of N-methyl-d-aspartate receptors, to induce long-term depression in the striatal complex. These observations might 
contribute to a better understanding of the increased sensitivity of the adolescent brain to drug induced-plasticity. </p>

<p>Keywords: age, nucleus accumbens, striatum, endocannabinoids, long-term depression </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>The brain of adolescents is subject to extensive synaptic and 
neurochemical remodeling in areas involved in emotions, </p>

<p>learning, decision-making, and reward-motivated behav-
iors. These changes may explain why adolescents are more </p>



<p>vulnerable than adults to the effects produced by exposure 
to drugs of abuse (Spear, 2002; Clark et al., 2008; Doremus- Fitzwater et al., 2010; Gulley and Juraska, 2013). A number of 
studies have demonstrated that drugs of abuse modulate long-
term changes in synaptic strength in brain regions involved in 
motivation, reward, and goal-oriented behaviors as well as in 
habit formation (Hoffman et al., 2003; Fourgeaud et al., 2004;  Mato et al., 2004; Yin et al., 2007; Jeanes et al., 2011; Hoffman  and Lupica, 2013). Thus, it is believed that alteration of excita-
tory neurotransmission and plasticity in the ventral striatum, 
or nucleus accumbens (NAc), and dorsal striatum is involved 
in the reinforcing effects of addictive substances (Hyman et al.,  2006; Vengeliene et al., 2008). A well-described form of long-
term depression (LTD) of glutamatergic synaptic transmission 
in the NAc and striatum involves endocannabinoids (eCBs), that 
is, anandamine and 2-arachidonoylglycerol. eCBs are produced 
and released from postsynaptic neurons following the activa-
tion of, for example, metabotropic glutamate receptors (mGluRs) 
or strong depolarization of postsynaptic neurons. eCBs inhibit 
neurotransmitter release through an action on cannabinoid 
type 1 (CB1) receptors located on presynaptic terminals (Robbe  et al., 2001, 2002; Gerdeman et al., 2002; Kreitzer and Malenka,  2005; Ronesi and Lovinger, 2005; Ohno-Shosaku and Kano, 2014). 
Another form of LTD identified in the NAc was shown to be trig-
gered following the activation of N-methyl-d-aspartate (NMDA) 
receptors (NMDA-LTD) (Thomas et al., 2000; Jeanes et al., 2011). 
The possible age-related differences in the ability of eCBs 
or NMDA receptor activation to trigger LTD have not been thor-
oughly addressed. Indeed, most electrophysiological experi-
ments are performed in the brains of adolescent rodents. Given 
that the adolescent brain is sensitive to experience-dependent 
plasticity, the first aim of our study was to determine whether 
age-related differences exist in the induction of 2 different 
forms of LTD, that is, one that is mediated by cannabinoids and a 
second form that is mediated by NMDA receptors. In an attempt 
to identify possible underlying mechanisms for the observed 
age-related differences, we also examined the protein levels of 
the receptors involved in LTD induction. The second aim of this 
study was to determine if the activation of cannabinoid recep-
tors leads to similar LTD in the NAc, a brain region associated 
with reward mechanisms, and in the dorsolateral striatum 
(DLS), a brain region shown to support habitual instrumental 
performance (ie, mediates habit/stimulus-response learning). 
Our results demonstrate that the NAc of adolescent mice is 
more susceptible to long-lasting changes in synaptic strength 
induced by cannabinoids and NMDA receptor activation than 
the NAc of adult mice or the DLS. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Animals and Brain Slice Preparation </p>

<p>Experiments were approved by our local ethical committee 
(Stockholms norra djurförsöksetiska nämnd) and were per-
formed as previously described (Schotanus et al., 2006; Chergui,  2011; Feng et al., 2014). All efforts were made to minimize animal 
suffering. We used male C57BL/6 mice (Harlan Laboratories, The 
Netherlands) aged 22 to 30 days (adolescent) and 5 to 8 months 
(adult). Mice were maintained on a 12-:12-h-light/-dark cycle 
and had free access to food and water. Mice underwent cer-
vical dislocation followed by decapitation. Their brains were 
rapidly removed, and coronal brain slices (400 μm thick) con-
taining the NAc, striatum, and overlying cortex were prepared 
with a microslicer (VT 1000S, Leica Microsystem, Heppenheim, </p>

<p>Germany). Slices were incubated for at least 1 hour at 32°C in 
oxygenated (95% O 2 + 5% CO 2 ) artificial cerebrospinal fluid (aCSF) 
containing (in mM): 126 NaCl, 2.5 KCl, 1.2 NaH 2 PO 4 , 1.3 MgCl 2 , 
2.4 CaCl 2 , 10 glucose, and 26 NaHCO 3 , pH 7.4. Slices were trans-
ferred to a recording chamber (Warner Instruments, Hamden, 
CT; recording chamber from Scientifica Ltd., Uckfield, UK) 
mounted on an upright microscope (Olympus, Solna, Sweden 
and Scientifica Ltd) and were continuously perfused with oxy-
genated aCSF at 28°C. </p>

<p>Electrophysiology in Brain Slices </p>

<p>Extracellular field potentials were recorded using a glass micro-
pipette filled with aCSF positioned on the slice surface. These 
synaptic responses were evoked by stimulation pulses applied 
every 15 seconds to the brain slice through a concentric bipolar 
stimulating electrode (FHC, Bowdoinham, ME) placed near the 
recording electrode on the surface of the slice. Single stimuli 
(0.1-millisecond duration) were applied at an intensity yield-
ing 50% to 60% maximal response as assessed by a stimulus/ 
response curve established for each slice at the beginning of 
the recording session by measuring the amplitude of the field 
excitatory postsynaptic potentials/population spikes (fEPSP/ 
PSs) evoked by increasing stimulation intensities. Signals 
were amplified 500 or 1000 times via an Axopatch 200B or a 
GeneClamp 500B amplifier (Axon Instruments, Foster City, CA) 
acquired at 10 kHz and filtered at 2 kHz. 
Whole-cell patch clamp recordings of medium spiny neurons 
in the NAc were made with the help of infrared-differential inter-
ference contrast video microscopy. Patch electrodes were filled 
with a solution containing (in mM): 120 d-gluconic acid, 20 KCl, 2 
MgCl 2 , 1 CaCl 2 , 10 4-(2-hydroxyethyl)piperazine-1-ethanesulfonic 
acid, N-(2-hydroxyethyl)piperazine-N′-(2-ethanesulfonic acid), 
10 ethylene glycol-bis(2-aminoethylether)-N,N,N′,N′-tetraacetic 
acid, 2 MgATP, and 0.3 Na 3 GTP, pH adjusted to 7.3 with KOH. 
Whole-cell membrane currents and potentials were recorded 
with a MultiClamp 700B (Axon Instruments) acquired at 10 kHz 
and filtered at 2 kHz. Excitatory postsynaptic currents (EPSCs) 
were evoked every 15 seconds by electrical stimulation of the 
slice using a patch electrode filled with aCSF positioned on the 
slice surface in the vicinity of the recorded neuron. The mem-
brane potential was held at −80 mV, and EPSCs were recorded 
in the presence of bicuculline methiodide (10 µM) to inhibit 
γ-aminobutyric acid (GABA A ) inhibitory postsynaptic currents. </p>

<p>Data Acquisition and Analysis of 
Electrophysiological Measurements </p>

<p>Data were acquired and analyzed with the <rs id="software-0" type="software">pClamp</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">10</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Axon Instruments</rs>). Numerical values are shown as means with 
SEM, with n indicating the number of slices or neurons tested. 
Data are expressed as percentage of the baseline response 
measured for each slice or neuron during the 5 to 10 minutes 
preceding the start of perfusion with a compound or 5-Hz stim-
ulation. Statistical significance of the results was assessed by 
using the Student's t test for paired observations (comparisons 
with baseline within single groups) and unpaired (comparisons 
between adolescents and adults). </p>

<p>Chemicals and Drugs </p>

<p>Chemicals and drugs were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich 
(Stockholm, Sweden), Tocris Bioscience (Bristol, UK), and 
Abcam Biochemicals (Cambridge, UK). All compounds were </p>

<p>Zhang et al. | 3 </p>

<p>prepared in stock solutions, diluted in aCSF to the desired final 
concentration, and applied in the perfusion solution. The fol-
lowing compounds were used (final concentrations in μM): 
AM251 
(1-(2,4-dichlorophenyl)-5-(4-iodophenyl)-4-methyl-
N-(piperidin-1-yl)-1H-pyrazole-3-carboxamide) 
(2); 
DL-AP5 
(dl-2-amino-5-phosphonopentanoic acid) (50); bicuculline 
methiodide (10); (S)-3,5-DHPG ((S)-3,5-dihydroxyphenylglycine) 
(100); LY 2183240 (5-[(1,1'-Biphenyl]-4-yl)methyl]-N,N-dime-
thyl-1H-tetrazole-1-carboxamide) (0.5-1); and WIN 55,212-2 
(WIN; 
(R)-(+)-[2,3-dihydro-5-methyl-3-(4-morpholinylmethyl) 
pyrrolo[1,2,3-de]-1,4-benzoxazin-6-yl]-1-naphthalenylmetha-
none mesylate) (1). </p>

<p>Western Blotting </p>

<p>Western blots were performed to analyze the levels of the recep-
tors known to be involved in LTD induction. The DLS and NAc 
were visually identified in brain slices and were dissected with 
the help of a scalpel blade and tweezers. The tissue was frozen 
and stored at −20°C until processed. The samples were soni-
cated in 1% sodium dodecyl sulfate and boiled for 10 minutes. 
Protein concentration was determined in each sample with a 
bicinchoninic acid protein assay (BCA-kit, Pierce, Rockford, IL). 
Equal amounts of protein (30 μg) were resuspended in sample 
buffer and separated by sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide 
gel electrophoresis using a 10% running gel and transferred to 
an Immobilon-P (polyvinylidene difluoride) transfer membrane 
(Sigma-Aldrich). The membranes were incubated for 1 hour at 
room temperature with 5% (wt/vol) dry milk in Tris Buffered 
Saline (TBS)-Tween20. Immunoblotting was carried out with 
antibodies against CB1 (Sigma-Aldrich, 1:500 dilution), mGluR1 
(Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, 1:500), mGluR5 (Upstate 
Biotechnology Inc., Waltham, MA, 1:500), GluN1 (Upstate </p>

<p>Biotechnology Inc., 1:500), and β-actin (Sigma-Aldrich, 1:4000) in 
5% dry milk dissolved in TBS-Tween 20. The membranes were 
washed 3 times with TBS-Tween20 and incubated with second-
ary horseradish peroxidase-linked anti-rabbit immunoglobulin 
G (H+L) (Thermo Scientific; Göteborg, Sweden, 1:6000 dilution) 
for 1 hour at room temperature. At the end of the incubation, 
the membranes were washed 6 times with TBS-Tween 20 and 
immunoreactive bands were detected by enhanced chemilu-
minescence (Perkin Elmer, Waltham, MA). The autoradiograms 
were scanned and quantified with the <rs id="software-1" type="software">NIH Image</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">1.63</rs> software. 
The levels of protein were normalized for the value of β-actin. 
Data were analyzed with the unpaired Student's t test to evalu-
ate statistical differences between protein levels in adolescent 
and adult NAc and striatum. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>LTD Induced by the Cannabinoid Receptor 
Agonist WIN 55,212-2 </p>

<p>We used the cannabinoid receptor agonist WIN 55,212-2 (WIN) 
to examine age-and region-specific differences in the ability 
of an exogenous cannabinoid to trigger LTD of glutamatergic 
neurotransmission in the striatal complex. We have examined 
glutamatergic synaptic transmission in the core region of the 
NAc and in the DLS by recording extracellular fEPSP/PSs evoked 
by brief, single-pulse, electrical stimulation of glutamatergic fib-
ers present in the brain slice, as previously described (Schotanus  et al., 2006; Schotanus and Chergui, 2008). After a stable baseline 
fEPSP/PS was recorded for 20 minutes, we applied WIN (1 µM) in 
the perfusion solution for 15 minutes. We found that the ampli-
tude of the fEPSP/PS, measured 55 to 60 minutes after the start of 
the perfusion with WIN, was decreased to 72.9 ± 5.0% of baseline </p>

<p>Figure 1. The cannabinoid receptor agonist WIN 55,212-2 (WIN) ((R)-(+)-[2,3-dihydro-5-methyl-3-(4-morpholinylmethyl)pyrrolo[1,2,3-de]-1,4-benzoxazin-6-yl]-1-naph-</p>

<p>thalenylmethanone mesylate) induces long-term depression (LTD) in the nucleus accumbens (NAc) of adolescent but not adult mice. Graphs show the time course of </p>

<p>the effect of WIN (1 µM), applied for 15 minutes in the perfusion solution at the time indicated by the black bar, on the mean (±SEM) amplitude of the field excitatory </p>

<p>postsynaptic potentials/population spike (fEPSP/PS) measured in the NAc (a-b). Data is expressed as a percentage of baseline fEPSP/PS in n = 8 slices from adolescent </p>

<p>mice (a) and n = 9 slices from adult mice (b). Insets show records of fEPSP/PSs measured in 2 slices at the time points indicated on the graphs, that is, before (1) and 50 </p>

<p>to 60 minutes after (2) perfusion with WIN. Average magnitude of WIN-induced inhibition measured 55 to 60 minutes after the start of the perfusion of WIN in slices </p>

<p>from adolescent (white bar) and adult (black bar) mice (c). ** P &lt; .01 compared with baseline (paired Student's t test); # P &lt; .05 (unpaired Student's t test). Protein levels </p>

<p>of β-actin (d) and cannabinoid type 1 receptor (CB1) (e) in the NAc of adolescent (n = 12) and adult (n = 8) mice expressed as a percentage of the levels measured in ado-</p>

<p>lescent mice. ## P &lt;.01 (unpaired Student's t test). </p>



<p>amplitude in the NAc of adolescent mice (P &lt; .01 compared with 
baseline; n = 8 slices) (Figure 1a, c). However, in the NAc of adult 
mice, the amplitude of the fEPSP/PS remained unchanged 1 hour 
after perfusion with WIN (1 µM) (percent of baseline: 101.7 ± 11.3, 
P &gt; .05, n = 9 slices) (Figure 1b, c). In addition, WIN did not induce 
LTD in the DLS of adolescent (percent of baseline: 106.7 ± 12.5, 
P &gt; .05, n = 9 slices) (Figure 2a, c) and adult (percent of baseline: 
91.9 ± 9.8, P &gt; .05, n = 11 slices) (Figure 2b, c) mice. We examined 
the protein levels of CB1 receptors given that these receptors 
were shown to be localized to glutamatergic terminals in the 
striatal complex and that they mediate presynaptic inhibition 
(Robbe et al., 2001). We first found that the levels of β-actin were 
similar in adolescent and adult NAc as well as DLS, indicating 
a stable level of this reference protein (Figures 1d and 2d). The 
levels of CB1 were, however, lower in the adult NAc compared 
with adolescent NAc (Figure 1e). The same observation was 
made for the DLS (Figure 2e). These results demonstrate that the 
synthetic cannabinoid receptor agonist WIN triggers LTD in the 
NAc of adolescent mice but not in adult mice. This age-related 
difference is associated with a reduced level of CB1 in the NAc 
of adult mice. In addition, WIN fails to trigger LTD in the DLS of 
adolescent and adult mice. </p>

<p>Effect of eCBs </p>

<p>eCBs, released following various stimulation paradigms, were 
also shown to trigger LTD in the striatal complex (Gerdeman  et al., 2002; Robbe et al., 2002; Adermark and Lovinger, 2007). For 
example, the group I mGluR agonist DHPG induces LTD in the 
NAc via the release of eCBs acting on presynaptic CB1 receptors 
in young rodents (Robbe et al., 2002, 2003; Grueter et al., 2010;  Huang et al., 2011). We examined whether age-and region-spe-
cific differences occurred in LTD induced by eCBs. We first con-
firmed that under our experimental conditions, DHPG (100 µM, 
applied for 10 minutes in the perfusion solution) triggered LTD </p>

<p>in the NAc of adolescent mice (percent of baseline: 79.9 ± 4.9, 
P &lt; .001, n = 14 slices) (Figure 3a, c). However, this treatment did 
not result in LTD in the NAc of adult mice (percent of baseline: 
109.1 ± 7.6, P &gt; .05, n = 16 slices) (Figure 3b, c). In the DLS, DHPG 
induced an initial depression of the fEPSP/PS in adolescent and 
adult mice, but no LTD was observed 1 hour following perfu-
sion with this compound (percent of baseline in adolescent DLS: 
107.1 ± 14.1, P &gt; .05, n = 10 slices [Figure 4a, c]; percent of baseline 
in adult DLS: 79.9 ± 13.7, P &gt; .05, n = 9 slices [Figure 4b, c]). Thus, 
DHPG induces LTD in the NAc of adolescent mice but fails to 
trigger LTD in the NAc of adult mice and in the DLS of both ado-
lescent and adult mice. 
Group I mGluRs include mGluR1 and mGluR5 receptors. We 
found that the levels of mGluR1 were lower in the NAc and DLS 
of adult mice compared with adolescent mice (Figures 3d and 4d). 
However, the levels of mGluR5 were similar in both the NAc and 
DLS of adult mice compared with adolescent mice (Figures 3e and 
4e). Differences in the protein levels of CB1 and mGlu receptors 
might not fully explain the age-and region-related differences in 
the ability of endogenous and exogenous cannabinoids to induce 
LTD in the striatal complex. We therefore attempted to identify an 
additional mechanism that could contribute to these differences. 
We hypothesized that activation of CB1 receptors by a tone of 
eCBs might differ between adolescent and adult mice in a region-
dependent manner. To test this hypothesis, we used the CB1 recep-
tor antagonist/inverse agonist AM251 to reveal the effect of a tone 
of eCBs on glutamatergic synaptic transmission. We found that 
AM251 (2 µM) had no significant effect on the fEPSP/PS amplitude 
in the NAc of adolescent and adult mice (Figure 5a-c) and in the 
DLS of adolescent mice (Figure 5d, f). However, AM251 produced 
a significant decrease in the fEPSP/PS amplitude measured in the 
DLS of adult mice (percent of baseline: 84.5 ± 3.9, P &lt; .01, n = 7 slices) 
(Figure 5e, f). We also tested the hypothesis that increasing the 
concentration of eCBs through blocking eCB uptake might con-
tribute to impairment of LTD. In an attempt to increase the brain </p>

<p>Figure 2. WIN ((R)-(+)-[2,3-dihydro-5-methyl-3-(4-morpholinylmethyl)pyrrolo[1,2,3-de]-1,4-benzoxazin-6-yl]-1-naphthalenylmethanone mesylate) fails to induce long-</p>

<p>term depression (LTD) in the dorsolateral striatum (DLS) of adolescent and adult mice. Time course of the effect of WIN (1 µM for 15 minutes) on the mean (± SEM) </p>

<p>amplitude of the field excitatory postsynaptic potentials/population spikes (fEPSP/PS) measured in the DLS, expressed as a percentage of baseline, in n = 9 slices from </p>

<p>adolescent mice (a) and n = 11 slices from adult mice (b). Insets show records of fEPSP/PSs measured in 2 slices at the time points indicated on the graphs. Averaged </p>

<p>fEPSP/PS amplitude measured 55 to 60 minutes after the start of the perfusion of WIN in slices from adolescent and adult mice (c). Protein levels of β-actin (d) and can-</p>

<p>nabinoid type 1 receptor (CB1) (e) in the DLS of adolescent (n = 11) and adult (n = 8) mice. #P &lt; .05 (unpaired Student's t test). </p>

<p>Zhang et al. | 5 </p>

<p>concentration of eCBs, we used the eCB uptake inhibitor LY 2183240, 
which also inhibits fatty acid amide hydrolase, the enzyme that 
degrades anandamine. LY 2183240 applied in the perfusion solu-
tion did not significantly affect the fEPSP/PS amplitude in the NAc </p>

<p>or DLS of adolescent and adult mice (percent of baseline in NAc: 
90.2 ± 6.9, n = 9 slices from adolescent mice [Figure 6a, c]; 115.3 ± 15.1, 
n = 7 slices from adult mice [Figure 6b, c]; percent of baseline in DLS: 
101.7 ± 11.9, n = 5 slices from adolescent mice [Figure 6d, f]; 98.7 ± 2.0, </p>

<p>Figure 3. The group I metabotropic glutamate receptor (mGluR) agonist ((S)-3,5-dihydroxyphenylglycine) (DHPG) induces long-term depression (LTD) in the nucleus </p>

<p>accumbens (NAc) of adolescent but not adult mice. Time course of the effect of DHPG (100 µM for 10 minutes) on the mean (± SEM) amplitude of the field excitatory </p>

<p>postsynaptic potentials/population spike (fEPSP/PS) measured in the NAc, expressed as a percentage of baseline, in n = 14 slices from adolescent mice (a) and n = 16 </p>

<p>slices from adult mice (b). Insets show records of fEPSP/PSs measured in 2 slices at the time points indicated on the graphs. Average magnitude of DHPG-induced </p>

<p>inhibition measured 55 to 60 minutes after the start of the perfusion of DHPG in slices from adolescent and adult mice (c). ***P &lt; .001 compared with baseline (paired </p>

<p>Student's t test); ##P &lt; .01 (unpaired Student's t test). Protein levels of mGluR1 (d) and mGluR5 (e) in the NAc of adolescent (n = 12) and adult (n = 8) mice. #P &lt; .05 (unpaired </p>

<p>Student's t test). </p>

<p>Figure 4. (S)-3,5-Dihydroxyphenylglycine (DHPG) does not induce long-term depression (LTD) in the dorsolateral striatum (DLS) of adolescent and adult mice. Time </p>

<p>course of the effect of DHPG (100 µM for 10 minutes) on the mean (± SEM) amplitude of the field excitatory postsynaptic potentials/population spike (fEPSP/PS) meas-</p>

<p>ured in the DLS, expressed as a percentage of baseline, in n = 10 slices from adolescent mice (a) and n = 9 slices from adult mice (b). Insets show records of fEPSP/PSs </p>

<p>measured in 2 slices at the time points indicated on the graphs. Averaged fEPSP/PS amplitude measured 55 to 60 minutes after the start of the perfusion of DHPG in </p>

<p>slices from adolescent and adult mice (c). Protein levels of metabotropic glutamate receptor (mGluR)1 (d) and mGluR5 (e) in the DLS of adolescent (n = 12) and adult </p>

<p>(n = 8) mice. #P &lt; .05 (unpaired Student's t test). </p>



<p>n = 6 slices from adult mice [Figure 6e, f]). These results suggest that 
the tone of eCBs cannot be further increased without concurrent 
stimulation to induce the production and release of eCBs. </p>

<p>NMDA Receptor-Dependent LTD in the NAc </p>

<p>We tested whether the age-related differences in the abil-
ity of exogenous and endogenous cannabinoids to induce LTD 
were specific for this type of synaptic plasticity or if similar </p>

<p>differences existed in the induction of another form of LTD, 
that is, NMDA-LTD. In the NAc, a NMDA-LTD has been described 
using whole-cell patch-clamp recordings from medium spiny 
projection neurons (MSNs) (Thomas et al., 2000, 2001; Jeanes  et al., 2011). In the dorsal striatum, however, LTD is independ-
ent of NMDA receptors (Calabresi et al., 2000; Lovinger et al.,  2003). We therefore measured, in individual MSNs in the NAc 
core, EPSCs evoked by local stimulations as previously described 
(Chergui, 2011). To induce NMDA-LTD, we used a moderate </p>

<p>Figure 5. Effect of blocking cannabinoid type 1 (CB1) receptors on the field excitatory postsynaptic potentials/population spike (fEPSP/PS). Time course (a, b, d, e) </p>

<p>and average magnitude (c, f) of the effect of the CB1 receptor antagonist AM251 (1-(2,4-dichlorophenyl)-5-(4-iodophenyl)-4-methyl-N-(piperidin-1-yl)-1H-pyrazole-</p>

<p>3-carboxamide) (2 µM) on the amplitude of the fEPSP/PS measured in the nucleus accumbens (NAc) (a-c) and dorsolateral striatum (DLS) (d-f). Insets show records of </p>

<p>fEPSP/PSs measured in 4 slices at the time points indicated on the graphs. n = 7 to 12 slices in each condition. **P &lt; .01 compared with baseline (paired Student's t test); </p>

<p>#P &lt; .05 (unpaired Student's t test). </p>

<p>Figure 6. Effect of increasing the tone of endocannabinoids (eCBs) on the field excitatory postsynaptic potentials/population spike (fEPSP/PS). Time course (a, b, d, e) </p>

<p>and average magnitude (c, f) of the effect of the eCB uptake inhibitor LY 2183240 (5-[(1,1'-Biphenyl]-4-yl)methyl]-N,N-dimethyl-1H-tetrazole-1-carboxamide) (0.5-1 µM) </p>

<p>on the amplitude of the fEPSP/PS measured in the nucleus accumbens (NAc) (a-c) and DLS (b-f). n = 5 to 9 slices in each condition. Insets show records of fEPSP/PSs </p>

<p>measured in 4 slices at the time points indicated on the graphs. </p>

<p>Zhang et al. | 7 </p>

<p>frequency stimulation protocol that consisted of 3 bouts at 5 Hz, 
3-minute duration, 5-minute inter-train intervals with the same 
stimulation intensity as for evoking EPSCs, paired with a mem-
brane depolarization to −50 mV during the bouts. This stimula-
tion protocol induced a long-lasting decrease in the amplitude 
of the EPSC in the NAc of adolescent mice (percent of baseline: 
57.4 ± 8.6, P &lt; .001, n = 15 MSNs) (Figure 7a, d). In the presence of 
the NMDA receptor antagonist dl-2-amino-5-phosphonopenta-
noic acid (50 µM), a 5-Hz stimulation did not induce LTD (percent 
of baseline: 109.8 ± 21.2, P &gt; .05, n = 5 MSNs) (Figure 7c-d), demon-
strating that this form of LTD was dependent on NMDA recep-
tors. In the NAc of adult mice, the same 5-Hz stimulation did not 
induce LTD (percent of baseline: 96.9 ± 10.4, P &gt; .05, n = 11 MSNs) 
(Figure 7b, d). We analyzed the levels of GluN1, the obligatory 
subunit of NMDA receptors, and found that GluN1 was downreg-
ulated in the NAc of adult mice compared with the levels meas-
ured in the NAc of adolescent mice (Figure 7e). Thus, the reduced 
ability of a 5-Hz stimulation protocol to induce LTD in the NAc of 
adult mice is associated with a reduced level of GluN1. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Previous studies have identified and characterized forms of LTD 
in the striatal complex that are dependent on eCBs and NMDA 
receptors (Thomas et al., 2000; Robbe et al., 2001; Gerdeman  et al., 2002; Kreitzer and Malenka, 2005). These studies were, 
however, performed with brains from adolescent mice, and the 
potential age-related differences in the modulation of synaptic 
strength have not been thoroughly investigated. We have exam-
ined whether the ability of cannabinoids and NMDA receptors 
to induce LTD differed between adolescent and adult mice and 
between the NAc and the DLS. Our results demonstrate that 
cannabinoid-mediated LTD is induced in the NAc, but not in 
the DLS, of adolescent mice and is not induced in adult mice. </p>

<p>In addition, NMDA-LTD in the NAc is observed in adolescent but 
not adult mice. These differences might result from decreased 
protein levels of the receptors involved in LTD induction as well 
as a tone of eCBs in the adult brain. </p>

<p>LTD Is Induced in the NAc of Adolescent but Not 
Adult Mice </p>

<p>We found that, under the same experimental condition, endog-
enous or exogenous cannabinoids reliably induced LTD in the 
NAc of adolescent mice. Cannabinoid-LTD was shown to result 
from the CB1 receptor-mediated inhibition of glutamate release 
but also from the internalization of postsynaptic AMPA recep-
tors (Grueter et al., 2010; Ohno-Shosaku and Kano, 2014). Thus, 
it is likely that the LTD induced by WIN and also by DHPG in the 
NAc of adolescent mice was mediated by CB1 receptors in our 
study. LTD induced by WIN and DHPG in the NAc is age depend-
ent, that is, it is not induced in adult mice. This age-related 
difference in the ability of eCBs to induce LTD might be due to 
downregulation of CB1 receptors and mGluR1. However, eCB-LTD 
induced by DHPG in the NAc was shown to involve mGluR5 and 
not mGluR1 (Robbe et al., 2003; Grueter et al., 2010). Because the 
levels of mGluR5 were similar in the NAc of adult and adolescent 
mice, other mechanisms, which remain to be identified, likely 
underlie the blunted LTD in the NAc of adult mice. It is unlikely 
that a tone of eCBs in the NAc of adult mice occludes LTD induc-
tion, because blocking CB1 receptors or eCB reuptake/degrada-
tion does not result in increased fEPSP/PS amplitude. We also 
found that NMDA-LTD in the NAc is age dependent and that the 
blunted NMDA-LTD in adult mice is associated with a reduced 
level of GluN1. Taken together, our results suggest that the NAc 
of adolescent mice is more sensitive to not only eCB-induced 
plasticity but also to other forms of long-term changes in syn-
aptic strength. </p>

<p>Figure 7. N-methyl-d-aspartate (NMDA) receptor-dependent long-term depression (LTD) in the nucleus accumbens (NAc). Moderate stimulation (3 bouts of 5 Hz, 3 </p>

<p>minutes each, paired with membrane depolarization to −50 mV, applied at the times indicated by the arrows) induces LTD of the excitatory postsynaptic currents </p>

<p>(EPSC) in NAc projection neurons of adolescent mice (n = 15 medium spiny projection neurons [MSNs]) (a). The same stimulation protocol does not induce LTD in adult </p>

<p>mice (n = 11 MSNs) (b) and in adolescent mice in the presence of dl-2-amino-5-phosphonopentanoic acid (n = 5 MSNs) (c). Insets show examples of EPSC recordings in </p>

<p>3 MSNs at the time points indicated on the graphs, that is, before (1) and 35 to 40 minutes after (2) the first 5-Hz bout. Average magnitude of stimulation-induced LTD </p>

<p>in adolescent (control MSNs and MSNs recorded in the presence of AP5) and adult NAc (d). ***P &lt; .001 compared with baseline (paired Student's t test); #P &lt; .05, ##P &lt; .01 </p>

<p>(unpaired Student's t test). Protein levels of GluN1 in the NAc of adolescent (n = 12) and adult (n = 9) mice (d). #P &lt; .05 (unpaired Student's t test). </p>



<p>LTD Is Not Induced in the DLS of Adolescent or 
Adult Mice </p>

<p>In contrast to the effect of WIN and DHPG in the NAc of adolescent 
mice, we found that these compounds failed to induce LTD of the 
fEPSP/PS in the DLS of adolescent and adult mice. A similar lack of 
effect of DHPG and WIN in the striatum has been described in ear-
lier studies, whereas other studies found that WIN induces LTD in 
the striatum (Huang et al., 2001; Kreitzer and Malenka, 2005, 2007;  Sergeeva et al., 2007; Chepkova et al., 2009). The reasons for these 
discrepancies might lie in the experimental protocols used in 
the different studies to induce LTD. Several experimental factors 
such as the region of the striatum where glutamatergic transmis-
sion is measured (ie, DLS vs dorsomedial striatum and the type 
of animals used [species, strain, and age]) could have influenced 
the ability of WIN and DHPG to induce LTD in the striatum. The 
membrane potential of the recorded neurons is also a key deter-
minant in the effects of eCBs. Indeed, DHPG failed to induce LTD 
in MSNs of the striatum when their membrane potential was 
clamped near their resting membrane potential (hyperpolarized) 
but induced LTD at a more depolarized membrane potential, close 
to the UP state measured in vivo (Kreitzer and Malenka, 2005). In 
the striatum, concurrent depolarization of the postsynaptic mem-
brane via, for example, cortical activity, and stimulation of mGluRs 
is therefore required to induce LTD, whereas such a requirement 
does not seem necessary in the NAc. In addition, eCB-LTD is cell-
type specific, that is, it is induced in MSNs of the indirect pathway 
(that express the dopamine D2 receptor) and not in MSNs of the 
direct pathway (that express the dopamine D1 receptor) (Kreitzer  and Malenka, 2007). 
In addition, GABA A receptor antagonists, which are often 
used in electrophysiological experiments, likely affect the abil-
ity of exogenous and endogenous cannabinoids to induce LTD. 
Indeed, low concentrations (50-300 nM) of WIN were shown to 
increase the amplitude of the field potential measured in the 
striatum through inhibition of GABAergic neurotransmission, 
but 1 µM WIN inhibited the field potential in the presence of 
a GABA A receptor antagonist (Clarke and Adermark, 2010). The 
lack of LTD in the DLS of adolescent mice following WIN or DHPG 
might result from a combination of synaptic potentiation and 
inhibition in our experimental conditions, which reflects the 
involvement of GABAergic local circuits. In addition, we found 
that the CB1 receptor antagonist AM251 significantly decreased 
the amplitude of the fEPSP/PS in the DLS of adult mice. Together, 
these observations suggest that a tone of eCBs increases glu-
tamate release from presynaptic terminals in the DLS of adult 
mice. Further modulation of neurotransmission by exogenous 
and endogenous cannabinoids might be occluded or prevented 
by this tone of eCBs. A reduced level of CB1 receptors might also 
contribute to the blunted LTD in the DLS of adult mice. 
In conclusion, our results demonstrate that in adolescent 
mice, cannabinoids induce a form of synaptic plasticity in the 
NAc, a brain region that integrates motivational information, 
but not in the DLS, which is involved in habit formation. They 
also provide further evidence for an increased sensitivity of the 
NAc of adolescent mice to cannabinoid-and NMDA receptor-
dependent synaptic plasticity than the NAc of adult mice. Our 
findings contribute to a better understanding of the increased 
vulnerability of adolescents to drug-induced plasticity. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Swedish Research Council 
(grant 2011-2770), Svenska Läkaresällskapet, and the Karolinska 
Institute. </p>

<p>Statement of Interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>Zhang et al. | 9 </p>



</text></tei>