<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4062317" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Introduction: The aim of the present study was to validate prothrombin time (PT) international normalized ratio (INR) results obtained using Steel-
ex test reagents and a Steelex coagulometer (Steelex Scientifi c Instrument Company, Beijing, China), in comparison with use of a well-established 
standard test employing Pacifi c Hemostasis reagents (Fisher Diagnostics, Middletown, VA, USA) and Teco Coatron A4 coagulometer (Teco Medical 
Instruments GmbH, Neufahrn, Germany). 
Materials and methods: Between-and within-day coeffi cients of variation (CVs) of both assays were calculated using control samples provided 
by the test manufacturers. Samples from 90 subjects were collected and INR values were determined in a double-blind parallel manner employing 
both systems. 
Results: The within-day coeffi cients of variation (CVs) in INR estimates ranged from 2.6% (INR = 1.12) to 3.1% (INR = 2.51) for the Steelex system 
and from 2.1% (INR = 1.09) to 1.8% (INR = 2.8) for the Pacifi c test; the between-day values ran from 3.4% (INR = 1.16) to 7.9% (INR = 2.64) and 
from 3.3% (INR = 1.1) to 2.3% (INR = 2.7), respectively. Passing-Bablok fi t of the of the Steelex and Pacifi c methods yielded the equation: Steelex 
INR = 0.85 (0.79-0.91) × Pacifi c INR + 0.12 (-0.02-0.21), whereas the CUSUM linearity P value was &lt; 0.01. The mean bias as determined by the 
Bland-Altman test was -0.156 (-0.912-0.600). 
Conclusion: The results obtained using Steelex reagents and the M600H coagulometer are not equivalent to those obtained using Pacifi c Hemosta-
sis reagents and a Teco Coatron A4 coagulometer, at least in the therapeutic range. 
Received: August 15, 2011 
Accepted: December 28, 2011 </p>

<p>Evaluation of the Steelex M600H coagulometer prothrombin time-international 
normalized ratio assay with Steelex test reagents </p>

<p>Yasemin U. Budak 1* , Kağan Huysal 2 , Murat Polat 3 , Gülsevil Tarakçı 1 , Hakan Uçar 4 </p>

<p>1 Department of Clinical Laboratory, Sevket Yilmaz Education and Training Hospital, Bursa, Turkey 
2 Department of Clinical Laboratory, Yuksek Ihtisas Education and Training Hospital, Bursa, Turkey 
3 Department of General Surgery, Sevket Yilmaz Education and Training Hospital, Bursa, Turkey 
4 Department of Cardiology, Sevket Yilmaz Education and Training Hospital, Bursa, Turkey </p>

<p>*Corresponding author: yaseminbudak2000@yahoo.com </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Prothrombin time (PT) is the most common coag-
ulation test performed in the clinical laboratory. PT 
is used to detect abnormalities in the extrinsic co-
agulation pathway. PT measurement is critical 
when thrombotic patients are on oral anticoagu-
lant therapy. However, it can be diffi cult to com-
pare PT test results from diff erent laboratories (1); 
standardization is essential. Thromboplastin, the 
principal reagent of the PT assay, is commercially 
available in diff erent forms. To achieve the re-
quired standardization, all thromboplastin prepa-
rations should be calibrated using the Internation-</p>

<p>al Sensitivity Index (ISI) and PT results should be 
presented in International Normalized Ratio (INR) 
units (2). The WHO Expert Committee on Biologi-
cal Standardization has decreed that standardiza-
tion requires a comparison of results yielded by 
the test thromboplastin with those aff orded when 
a reference thromboplastin is employed (2,3). 
However, it is clear that standardization is not uni-
versally performed (4-7). </p>

<p>In Turkey, public procurement law requires that 
the lowest bid be accepted when equipment or 
reagents are ordered. Thus, the choice of a coagu-</p>

<p>Biochemia Medica 2012;22(1):121-6 </p>



<p>Budak YU. et al. 
Evaluation of PT-INR assay </p>

<p>lometer is price-dependent, even though the accu-
racy and reliability of INR measurement is essential. 
The Steelex M600H (Steelex Scientifi c Instrument 
Company, Beijing, China), approved for use in our 
laboratory because the device is inexpensive, is a 
new coagulometer that measures PT and INR. </p>

<p>The aim of the present study was to validate INR 
results obtained using the Steelex M600H coagu-
lometer and Steelex reagents (the PT kit) by com-
paring such data with the results yielded by a Teco 
Coatron A4 coagulometer (Teco Medical Instru-
ments GmbH, Neufahrn, Germany) employing a 
Pacifi c Hemostasis test reagent (Thromboplastin-
DS, Fisher Diagnostics, VA, USA). The latter test is 
standard in the clinical laboratory. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>The present study was conducted in the period 
from June to July 2011 in the clinical laboratory of 
the Şevket Yılmaz Research and Education Hospi-
tal. The study was approved by our institutional 
Ethics Committee and all participants gave written 
informed consent. All procedures were in accor-
dance with the Second Declaration of Helsinki. </p>

<p>PT and INR determination methods </p>

<p>As a reference method, plasma PT was analyzed in 
an automated manner using a Teco Coatron A4 co-
agulator. The PT of citrated plasma was deter-
mined photometrically employing a high-resolu-
tion four-channel optic system (400 nm) and a sus-
pension of rabbit brain thromboplastin (Thrombo-
plastin-DS) prepared in calcium chloride solution. 
The instrument was calibrated employing calibra-
tion reference plasmas with manufacturer-as-
signed INR values (TECal N calibration plasma cat. 
no. P800-010, Teco GmbH, Germany) (8). The 
thromboplastin ISI value assigned by the manufac-
turer was 1.03. This is the method by which PT is 
routinely measured, in INR, in our hospital. </p>

<p>Steelex M600H </p>

<p>PT coagulation time was measured employing a 
new fully automated Steelex M600H coagulom-
eter and Steelex test reagents, and a freeze-dried 
extract of rabbit brain thromboplastin (product </p>

<p>no. SS00110001; lot no. STG20101-LG4) prepared in 
a buff er containing calcium chloride. The ISI as-
signed to this preparation by the manufacturer 
was 1.18. In the Steelex system, light passing 
through a medium in which fi brinogen has been 
converted to fi brin is absorbed by the fi brin stands. 
The instrument identifi es a coagulation endpoint 
by measuring the change in optical density at 470 
nm, and this information is processed, using in-
built software, to determine a clot point. The in-
strument was calibrated employing calibration ref-
erence plasmas with manufacturer-assigned INR 
values (Unicalibrator cat. no. 00675 Diagnostica 
Stago, Inc., France) (8). The INR is calculated and 
automatically displayed by the instruments from 
the prothrombin time using the formula (3): </p>

<p>INR = (PT sample /PT normal ) ISI </p>

<p>The coeffi cients of variation of the regression line 
slopes of calibration curves of both instruments 
were less than 3%, in accordance with the WHO re-
quirements (9). All INRs were calculated using a lo-
cal prothrombin time (PT); this was the mean nor-
mal prothrombin time (MNPT) obtained using 20 
fresh normal samples from healthy individuals (10). </p>

<p>Analytical precision of PT and INR 
determinations </p>

<p>Before specimen analysis, we performed two-level 
quality-control (QC) tests using materials supplied 
by either manufacturer (Steelex ANCP, catalog no. 
SS005711001 and NCP, catalog no. SS000500007; 
Pacifi c Hemostasis INR Control Plasma catalog nos. 
100595 and 100596). Between-day diff erences in 
QC data were determined via analysis of duplicates 
on each of 20 successive days. Within-day preci-
sion was calculated by conducting 20 replicate 
analyses of the QC materials in a single run. Be-
tween-day precision is a measure of random ana-
lytical error (11). </p>

<p>Patients and blood sampling </p>

<p>Venous blood samples were obtained from 90 pa-
tients for whom PT (INR) tests were scheduled as 
part of routine preoperative check-up (N = 14) or for 
monitoring of oral anticoagulant therapy (OAT) (N = 
76). Patients with atrial fi brillation and/or a prosthet-</p>

<p>Biochemia Medica 2012;22(1):121-6 </p>



<p>Budak YU. et al. 
Evaluation of PT-INR assay </p>

<p>ic heart valve, and those prescribed long-term OAT 
were accepted to the study. Of all patients, 35 were 
in their fi rst 3 months of treatment (the dose-adjust-
ment phase) whereas 41 were in a later treatment 
stage (the maintenance phase). Of all patients, the 
INR values of 48 were 1-1.09 units, those of 27 2-2.7 
units, and those of 15 3-4.9 units. Hence, all possible 
anticoagulation phases (pretreatment, dose-adjust-
ment, and steady-state) were included. </p>

<p>Blood samples (each 1.8 mL) were collected into 
citrate coagulation tubes (Vacuette; Greiner 
Labortechnik GmbH, Krems-münster, Austria; cat-
alog no. 454322 9NC) each containing 0.2 mL 3.2% 
(w/v) sodium citrate (0.109 M). Both the WHO and 
the NCCLS state that 3.2% (w/v) citrate is the ap-
propriate anticoagulant level when coagulation is 
to be tested (2,12). Plasma was obtained via cen-
trifugation for 15 min at 1,500 x g. All samples were 
assayed using the two systems within 1 hour of 
blood collection. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Data were evaluated using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 13.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">Analyse-It</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 2.04</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Analyse-It Software</rs>, Leeds, UK). Means, standard 
deviations, and coeffi cients of variation were calcu-
lated. (13-15). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The coeffi cients of variation (CVs) of within-and 
between-day QC data are presented in Table 1. </p>

<p>Passing and Bablok regression analysis yielded an 
intercept of 0.12 units (95% confi dence interval (CI) </p>

<p>= -0.02-0.21) and a slope of 0.85 (95% CI = 0.79-
0.91), suggesting that, a proportional diff erence 
existed between the two methods (Figure 1) (14). 
The cumulative sum linearity test (CUSUM test) re-
vealed signifi cant deviation from linearity (P &lt; 0.01) 
(14). </p>

<p>The Bland-Altman diff erence plot showed that the 
mean bias was -0.156 units and the 95% limits of 
agreement were -0.912 to 0.600 when the Steelex 
and Pacifi c test data were compared (Figure 2). The 
bias was lower in the sub-therapeutic range (INR &lt; 
2.0) and higher in the therapeutic range (INR = 2.0-
4.5) (Figure 1). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Extensive international collaboration has allowed 
laboratory INR measurement to become standard-
ized worldwide; this is an essential feature of qual-
ity control (16,17). To ensure test result accuracy, 
clinical laboratories are required to conduct inter-
nal quality control tests and to participate in exter-
nal quality assurance (EQA) networks. Our labora-
tory is a member of the national external quality 
assessment scheme (KBUDEK, Istanbul, Turkey) 
that evaluates coagulation test data (PT/INR; and 
assays of APTT and fi brinogen). We routinely em-
ploy Pacifi c Hemostasis test reagents. At the time 
of the present study, the average values of the 
Standard Deviation Index (SDI; Mean minus Peer 
Group Mean/SD of Peer Group Mean) obtained 
from 134 laboratories using Pacifi c test reagents 
were 0% for an INR of 1.04 and minus 0.15% for an 
INR of 1.95. The SDI is a parameter for evaluating </p>

<p>TABLE 1: Within-day imprecision data and between-day imprecision data for Steelex test reagent on Steelex M600H coagulometer </p>

<p>and Pacifi c Hemostasis test reagents on Teco Coatron A4 coagulometer. </p>

<p>Steelex test reagents 
Pacifi c Hemostasis test reagents </p>

<p>Within-Day 
Mean (SD) 
(N = 20) </p>

<p>CV 
(%) </p>

<p>Between-Day 
Mean (SD) 
(N = 20) </p>

<p>CV 
(%) </p>

<p>Within-Day 
Mean (SD) 
(N = 20) </p>

<p>CV 
(%) </p>

<p>Between-Day 
Mean (SD) 
(N = 20) </p>

<p>CV (%) </p>

<p>QC1* 
PT(sec) 
13.8 (0.36) 
2.6 
14.2 (0.49) 
3.4 
15.1 (0.32) 
2.1 
15.2 (0.49) 
3.2 </p>

<p>INR 
1.12 (0.03) 
2.6 
1.16 (0.04) 
3.4 
1.09 (0.02) 
2.1 
1.1 (0.03) 
3.3 </p>

<p>QC2** 
PT(sec) 
27.2 (0.71) 
2.6 
28.8 (2.19) 
7.6 
37.6 (0.68) 
1.8 
37.3 (0.86) 
2.3 </p>

<p>INR 
2.51 (0.08) 
3.1 
2.64 (0.21) 
7.9 
2.8 (0.05) 
1.8 
2.7 (0.07) 
2.5 </p>

<p>*QC1, *QC2 = quality control level 1 and level 2 </p>

<p>Biochemia Medica 2012;22(1):121-6 </p>



<p>Budak YU. et al. 
Evaluation of PT-INR assay </p>

<p>We consider that the Pacifi c system is a suitable 
standard for use in validation studies as this meth-
od yielded acceptable quality control data during 
our study period and employs highly sensitive hu-
man thromboplastin (ISI = 1.03), as recommended 
by the College of American Pathologists (12). </p>

<p>Within-run imprecision was satisfactory for both 
systems (CV ≤ 3.1%). The Steelex system had a 
higher between-run CV than did the Pacifi c meth-
od, explained by the fact that use of reagents of 
higher ISI is associated with greater interlaboratory 
INR CVs (18). The level of between-run imprecision 
using the Steelex system (Level 2; CV = 7.9%) was 
unacceptable; the value should be less than 5% 
when an INR assay is performed (19). </p>

<p>Monitoring of PT via calculation of INRs is impor-
tant for patients on oral anticoagulation therapy; 
appropriate doses can thus be prescribed. Accu-
rate INR estimation is crucial (20). Global harmoni-
zation of INR results, and agreement on the thera-
peutic ranges associated with varying clinical indi-
cations, is important (21). Many factors infl uence 
INR values; these include the levels of various co-
agulation factors present and their interaction 
with thromboplastin reagents diff ering in compo-
sition and sensitivity to the actions of such factors 
(22). It can be diffi cult to obtain accurate and pre-
cise INR measurements. Both PT and INR data 
should be identical regardless of the reagents, in-
strument, or test method used. However, agree-
ment among results yielded by many commercial 
INR methods is poor. Such variations may compro-
mise patient care (1,7). </p>

<p>In our present work; Passing and Bablok regression 
analysis yielded the appropriate y-intercept value 
of zero but the slope of the regression line did not 
approximate unity, suggesting that, in addition to 
the presence of a small constant bias, a propor-
tional diff erence existed between the two meth-
ods (14). Our results are in agreement with previ-
ous fi ndings of poor agreement among data ob-
tained using diff erent methods to calculate PT and 
INR (7,23). The variation noted in the present work 
may be attributable to diff erences between any or 
all of methodology, the coagulometers used, and 
thromboplastin source. Many recent reports have 
shown that coagulometer choice has a marked </p>

<p>INR -Pacific Hemostasis INR </p>

<p>INR -Steelex INR </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1,5 </p>

<p>0,5 
0,5 
1,5 
2,5 
3,5 
4,5 </p>

<p>2,5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>3,5 </p>

<p>4,5 
Identity 
Passing &amp; Bablok (1) 
fit 
(0.12 + 0.85x) </p>

<p>Scatter Plot with Passing &amp; Bablok fit </p>

<p>Mean of INR 
Difference (Steelex INR -Laboratory INR) </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-0,5 </p>

<p>-1,5 
0,5 
1,5 
2,5 
3,5 
4,5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0,5 </p>

<p>Identity 
Bias (-0.156) 
95% Limits of agreement 
(-0.912 to 0.600) </p>

<p>Difference Plot </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Passing-Bablok regression analysis for the Steelex INR </p>

<p>results vs. laboratory (Pacifi c) INR results. The solid line indicates 
the regression line. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Bland-Altman plot analysis between compaired </p>

<p>methods. </p>

<p>bias relative to the consensus group. It provides a 
good measure of accuracy because each laborato-
ry's results are compared to the mean value for all 
laboratories, which is assumed to be the true value. </p>

<p>Biochemia Medica 2012;22(1):121-6 </p>



<p>Budak YU. et al. 
Evaluation of PT-INR assay </p>

<p>and unpredictable eff ect on INR value (24). The 
precision of PT testing tends to be greater when 
ISI is lower (24) but end-point reliability is also af-
fected by reagent quality (24). </p>

<p>Quality control is essential; it is recommended that 
analytical imprecision be less than or equal to half 
of intra-individual biological variation (25-27). 
Ricos et al. (28) found intra-individual INR variation 
of 4% and inter-individual variation of 6.8%. Kjeld-
sen (29) recorded in-treatment intra-individual INR 
variation of 10.1%. Via computer simulation of seri-
al INR measurements within the generally accept-
ed therapeutic range (INR 2.0-3.0), the cited author 
concluded that analytical imprecision should be 
less than 5% and analytical bias less than ± 0.2 INR 
units (29). In the present study, the overall analyti-
cal bias was indeed less than ± 0.2 INR units, but, 
in the therapeutic range, the bias was greater than 
± 0.2 INR units, thus signifi cantly higher than cur-
rent recommendations (28,29). It is evident that ISI 
strongly infl uences INR inter-laboratory variability 
(30). Although the ISI assigned by the manufactur-
er of the Steelex M600H coagulometer was rela-
tively low (1.18), a major limitation of our study is 
that local ISI calibration using WHO-certifi ed plas-
ma was not performed. Incorrect assignment of ISI 
values by manufacturers may cause among-meth-
od diff erences in test results. </p>

<p>In particular, we found that INR data obtained us-
ing either the Steelex PT or Pacifi c reagents were 
in acceptable agreement in patients with INR val-
ues close to 1, but variance within the therapeutic 
range (INR 2.0-4.5) was unacceptable, with an ana-
lytical bias over 0.20 INR units (19,29) being evident 
in twenty eight out of 90 patients. Similarly, Horsti 
et al. (7) found that INR values obtained using dif-
ferent methods were very similar when such val-
ues were close to unity but marked variations were 
evident at higher INR values. This is unacceptable, 
because bias of this magnitude may result in pre-
scription of incorrect amounts of anticoagulation 
agents (9). </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In conclusion, reliable PT, INR test data are impor-
tant for proper management of patients on OAT. 
Our results indicate that results obtained from 
Steelex M600H coagulometer using Steelex re-
agents kit are not interchangeable with Teco Coa-
tron A4 coagulation coagulometer using Pacifi c 
Hemostasis reagent kit, in the therapeutic range. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We did not receive any funding for this study. </p>

<p>Potential confl ict of interest </p>

<p>None declared. </p>



<p>Biochemia Medica 2012;22(1):121-6 </p>





</text></tei>