<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4720847" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Chronic total occlusion (CTO) of the coronary arteries is defined 
as lesions with thrombolysis in myocardial infarction (TIMI) flow 
grade 0 with an estimated or known occlusion duration of three 
months or more. 
1) Coronary CTO is present in 18.4 to 52% of </p>

<p>patients with coronary artery disease undergoing coronary 
angiography. 
2-5) CTO percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) can </p>

<p>decrease or eliminate symptoms. 
6)7) Successful PCI performed on a </p>

<p>CTO lesion can decrease the need for anti-anginal medications, 
improve exercise capacity, 
8) decrease the need for coronary artery </p>

<p>bypass graft surgery (CABG), improve left ventricular systolic </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>http://dx.Background and Objectives: Success rates of chronic total occlusion (CTO) percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) have recently been 
reported to range from 80% to 90%. A better understanding of the pathologic characteristics of the CTO lesion may helpful to improving 
CTO PCI success rates. We evaluated the CTO lesion in patients with stable angina (SA) by virtual histology-intravascular ultrasound (VH-
IVUS). 
Subjects and Methods: The study population consisted of 149 consecutive patients with SA underwent VH-IVUS examination. We 
analyzed demographic and VH-IVUS findings in 22 CTO patients (17 males; mean, 62.3 years old) compared with 127 non-CTO patients 
(82 males; mean, 61.3 years old). 
Results: A significantly lower ejection fraction (57.6±13.0% vs. 65.4±8.8%, p=0.007) was detected in the CTO group compared with the 
non-CTO group. Reference vessel lumen area of the proximal and distal segment was significantly less in CTO group than in non-CTO-
group. The lesion length of the CTO group was significantly longer than those of the non-CTO group (24.4±9.6 mm vs. 17.2±7.4 mm, 
p&lt;0.001). Total atheroma volume (224±159 mm 
3 vs. 143±86 mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, p=0.006) and percent atheroma volume (63.2±9.6% vs. 55.8±8.5%, 
p=0.011) of the CTO group were also significantly greater than those of non-CTO group. However, the lesion length adjusted plaque 
composition of the CTO group was not significantly different compared with that of the non-CTO group. 
Conclusion: CTO lesions had a longer lesion length and greater plaque burden than the non-CTO lesion in patients with SA. However, 
lesion length adjusted plaque composition showed similar between the two groups. These results support that plaque characteristics of 
CTO lesions are similar to non-CTO lesions in patients with SA. (Korean Circ J 2016;46(1):33-40) </p>

<p>KEY WORDS: Angina pectoris; Atherosclerotic plaque; Intravascular ultrasonography. </p>

<p>Received: April 15, 2015 
Revision Received: June 8, 2015 
Accepted: June 30, 2015 
Correspondence: Jang-Ho Bae, MD, Cardiology, Heart Center, Konyang 
University Hospital, 158 Gwanjeodong-ro, Seo-gu, Daejeon 35365, Korea 
Tel: 82-42-600-9420, Fax: 82-42-600-9400 
E-mail: janghobae@yahoo.co.kr </p>

<p>• The authors have no financial conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons. 
org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, 
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work 
is properly cited. </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4070/kcj.2016.46.1.33 
www.e-kcj.org </p>

<p>function, 
9) decrease the risk for arrhythmias, 
10) and improve overall </p>

<p>survival of patients. </p>

<p>7) </p>

<p>There have been significant improvements in procedure 
techniques for CTO PCI in recent years, and success rates for CTO 
PCI have risen to greater than 80 to 90%. Major complication rates 
of CTO PCI are acceptable and similar to non-CTO PCI. </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>Interventional cardiologists typically hypothesize that calcium 
deposition within and around the CTO segment is a primary cause 
of CTO PCI failure, particularly during wiring. 
A better understanding of specific lesional characteristics of 
coronary arteries with CTO may improve the results of CTO-PCI. 
However, there is little in vivo data comparing CTO lesions and non-
CTO lesions, and, thus, the differences in lesion characteristics 
between CTO and non-CTO are poorly understood. The virtual 
histology-intravascular ultrasound (VH-IVUS) is a technique that 
can provide detailed qualitative and quantitative information of the 
lesion and can identify four specific plaque components to better 
characterize the lesion. 
10) A recent VH-IVUS study revealed that </p>

<p>plaque composition of acute coronary syndrome was associated 
with a greater component of a necrotic core than those in stable 
angina. 
10) Given that most patients with CTO lesions present with </p>

<p>clinical manifestations of stable angina, we excluded patients with 
acute coronary syndrome (ACS) in this study to avoid any difference 
in plaque composition based on these findings. 
Therefore, the purpose of the present study was to compare the 
micro-anatomic lesional characteristics between the CTO group and 
non-CTO group in patients with stable angina (SA) by VH-IVUS 
modalities. </p>

<p>Subjects and Methods </p>

<p>Study population 
From January 2006 to March 2008, VH-IVUS was performed on 
consecutive patients with coronary arterial disease at Konyang 
University Hospital. VH-IVUS was not performed routinely after 
March 2008, so the patients in during this period were enrolled in 
the study. The study population consisted of 22 native coronary 
artery CTO lesions and 127 non-CTO lesions documented in patients 
with SA after either guidewire crossing or after pre-dilatation using 
a small size balloon (1.5 mm-2.0 mm) by expert interventional 
cardiologists at Konyang University Hospital. The CTO group was 
defined as an obstruction of a native coronary artery with no 
luminal continuity and TIMI flow grade 0 and with an estimated 
occlusion duration of three months or more. The occlusion duration 
was determined by the interval from the first diagnostic coronary </p>

<p>angiogram documenting a CTO or from the duration of ischemic 
symptoms in patients that had not previously undergone 
angiography. 
11) The control group was composed of patients with SA </p>

<p>according to the Canadian Cardiovascular Society classification. 
Most patients with CTO lesions present with clinical manifestation 
of stable angina; thus, we excluded patients with ACS according to 
the Braunwald classification in this study to avoid any underlying 
differences in plaque composition based on the clinical manifestations. 
We also excluded patients with severe calcified and tortuous 
vessels that were impossible to pass with an IVUS catheter; those 
with a history of PCI or coronary artery bypass surgery; as well as 
hemodynamically unstable patients, and those patients who 
declined to participate in the study. All 22 CTO lesions in this study 
underwent VH-IVUS examination without any complication. 
Altogether, the study population consisted of 149 patients; 22 
patients were included in the CTO group, and 127 patients were 
included in the non-CTO group. Demographic data of the study 
population was obtained through review of hospital charts. 
Coronary risk factors included hypertension (blood pressure≥140/90 
mmHg based on the average of repeated readings or patients on 
antihypertensive drugs), dyslipidemia (total cholesterol&gt;200 mg/dL 
and/or triglyceride&gt;150 mg/dL and or low density lipoprotein 
cholesterol&gt;130 mg/dL or patients on lipid lowering therapy), 
diabetes mellitus (DM, controlled with diet, oral hypoglycemic 
agents, or insulin; or fasting glucose level≥126 mg/dL or 2 hour oral 
glucose tolerance test≥200 mg/dL), and cigarette smoking. This 
study was approved by the ethics committee of Konyang University 
Hospital. </p>

<p>Percutaneous coronary intervention 
All patients received aspirin 300 mg and clopidogrel 300-600 mg, 
and 120 IU/kg of unfractionated heparin intravenously before PCI. 
PCI was performed using the femoral or radial approach with a 5, 6, 
or 7 Fr guiding catheter and a 0.014-inch standard or extra-support 
coronary guidewires. The culprit lesion was identified by inspecting 
for ventricular wall motion abnormalities and the appearance of the 
angiographic lesion. 
All study subjects underwent successful PCI of the culprit lesion 
and VH-IVUS examination. </p>

<p>Intravascular ultrasound-examination and analysis 
The VH-IVUS examination was performed on the culprit lesion 
with dedicated 20-MHz, 2.9 F monorail, electronic Eagle Eye Gold 
IVUS catheter (Volcano Therapeutics, Rancho Cordova, CA, USA) and 
VH-IVUS console (Volcano Therapeutics, Rancho Cordova, CA, USA) 
during the CAG after intracoronary administration of 100 to 200 µg </p>



<p>Yo-Han Park, et al. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4070/kcj.2016.46.1.33 
www.e-kcj.org </p>

<p>nitroglycerin. The IVUS catheter was advanced into the target lesion 
after wiring or ballooning and automatic pullback at 0.5 mm/sec 
was performed. The VH-IVUS image was recorded on a DVD-ROM 
for subsequent off-line analysis. 
Both qualitative and quantitative analyses of gray scale IVUS 
images were performed according to the criteria of the American 
College of Cardiology`s Clinical Expert Consensus Document on 
IVUS. 
11-13) The proximal and distal reference segments were the most </p>

<p>normal-appearing cross sectional segments within 10 mm or less 
from the distal and proximal end of the lesion. Measurement of 
lesion length was determined by defining the edge of the lesion as 
the nearest point out of the most normal-looking cross sectional 
foci within 10 mm or less from the distal and proximal end of the 
lesion. 
The external elastic membrane (EEM) and cross-sectional area 
(CSA) was measured with customized software (IVUS Lab., Volcano 
Therapeutics, Rancho Cordova, CA, USA). The remodeling index was 
calculated as the lesion EEM CSA divided by the average reference 
EEM CSA. </p>

<p>Spectral analysis of intravascular ultrasound radiofrequency 
data 
Analysis of spectral data and IVUS radiofrequncy data was 
performed on the target lesion with customized software (IVUS Lab.; 
Volcano Therapeutics, Rancho Cordova, CA, USA) by an examiner 
who was blinded to the gray scale IVUS results. For both the lumen 
and the media-adventitia interface, automatic border detection was 
performed at the predefined lesion segment and manual correction 
was subsequently performed and required the agreement of two 
independent, experienced cardiologists. Disagreements were 
reviewed by a third cardiologist. After confirming the border 
detection, the software automatically calculated and displayed the 
results. For each frame, histologic findings were expressed in colors 
(green for fibrous, green-yellow for fibro-fatty, white for dense 
calcified, and red for necrotic core area). The predictive accuracy of 
this method with tissue mapping has been validated. 
13) The area </p>

<p>(mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) and percent area of each tissue component of plaque were 
analyzed at the minimal luminal area site, and the volume (mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) 
and percent volume of each tissue component of plaque were 
evaluated within the full segment of the culprit lesion. The plaque 
volume was divided by the lesion length to adjust for varying lesion 
lengths and recorded as a corrected volume (mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>/mm). 
Specific histologic features of the lesion, such as pathologic intimal 
thickening, fibrocalcific atheroma, and thin cap fibroartheroma, were 
not analyzed in this study because the specific lesion type could 
have been altered within the CTO lesion due to intervention. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
All analyses were performed with <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 18.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., 
Chicago, IL, USA). All data are expressed as mean±standard 
deviation for continuous variables and as percentage ratio for 
categorical variables. Categorical variables were compared by chi-
square test. If more than 20% of cells had a count less than five in 
the chi-square test, a Fisher's exact test was performed. Continuous 
variables were compared by Student t tests. If the data did not show 
a normal distribution, a Mann-Whitney U test was performed. A p 
less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics 
Of 149 patients, 22 patients were found to have a CTO lesion and 
127 patients a non-CTO lesion. The CTO group had a significantly 
lower ejection fraction (57.6±13.0% vs. 65.4±8.8%, p=0.007) than 
did the non-CTO group. All other demographics showed no 
statistical differences between the two groups. 
Angiographic assessment was performed following VH-IVUS 
examination in all subjects. All CTO lesions underwent VH-IVUS 
investigation after ballooning. In contrast, 23 patients (18.1%) of 
the non-CTO group underwent VH-IVUS study after ballooning and 
the remaining (81.9%) underwent VH-IVUS following wiring. The 
CTO group had a smaller proximal reference lumen area (7.24±3.06 
mm 
2 vs. 8.77±3.11 mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, p=0.035) than did the non-CTO group, and 
the CTO group also had a smaller distal reference lumen area 
(5.49±2.64 mm 
2 vs. 8.55±8.84 mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, p&lt;0.001) compared with the 
non-CTO group. Stent diameter and length of the CTO group was 
smaller (2.77±0.35 mm vs. 3.21±0.42 mm, p&lt;0.001) and longer 
(29.2±4.8 mm vs. 22.0±5.0 mm, p&lt;0.001) than in the non-CTO 
group (Table 1). </p>

<p>Virtual histology-intravascular ultrasound findings 
Lesion analysis of the minimal lumen area revealed that the CTO 
group had a longer overall lesion length (24.4±9.6 mm vs. 17.2±7.4 
mm, p&lt;0.001) than did the non-CTO group (Fig. 1). However, there 
was no significant difference between the two groups in terms of 
remodeling index, plaque area, plaque burden, plaque components, 
and percent plaque composition. The minimal lumen area of the 
CTO group, which was measured after ballooning, was similar to the 
non-CTO group (3.67±1.05 mm 
2 vs. 4.08±1.52 mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, p=0.264). In 
this study, all CTO group patients underwent VH-IVUS after 
ballooning. After ballooning, the lumen area was dilated, which may 
contribute to discrepancies in minimal lumen area of CTO lesions. </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4070/kcj.2016.46.1.33 
www.e-kcj.org </p>

<p>Plaque burden of the proximal (53.0±12.7% vs. 46.3±10.7%, 
p=0.015) and distal reference vessels (47.8±11.3% vs. 41.2±11.4%, </p>

<p>Table 1. Clinical characteristics of the study subjects </p>

<p>Variables 
CTO 
Non-CTO 
p </p>

<p>Patients (n) </p>

<p>22 
127 </p>

<p>Male 
17 (77.3) 
82 (64.6) 
0.330 </p>

<p>Age (years) 
62.3±9.1 
61.3±11.2 
0.681 </p>

<p>Risk factors </p>

<p>Hypertension 
12 (54.5) 
74 (58.3) 
0.817 </p>

<p>Diabetes 
9 (40.9) 
39 (30.7) 
0.459 </p>

<p>Hyperlipidemia 
9 (40.9) 
43 (33.9) 
0.629 </p>

<p>Smoking 
7 (31.8) 
34 (26.8) 
0.797 </p>

<p>Prior myocardial infarction 
2 (9.1) 
13 (10.2) 
1.000 </p>

<p>Peak CK (IU/L) 
108.6±88.4 
107.1±69.0 
0.625 </p>

<p>Peak CK-MB (ng/mL) 
2.8±2.3 
2.3±3.2 
0.094 </p>

<p>Peak Tn-I (ng/mL) 
0.4±0.9 
0.1±0.5 
0.977 </p>

<p>hs-CRP (mg/dL) 
0.76±1.76 
0.37±1.39 
0.076 </p>

<p>Fasting blood glucese (mg/dL) 
131±60 
114±37 
0.166 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin (g/dL) 
12.6±2.0 
13.2±1.9 
0.244 </p>

<p>Total cholesterol (mg/dL) 
185±53 
188±45 
0.765 </p>

<p>Triglyceride (mg/dL) 
183±97 
160±84 
0.290 </p>

<p>LDL-C (mg/dL) 
121±39 
121±35 
0.990 </p>

<p>HDL-C (mg/dL) 
38±7 
44±11 
0.017 </p>

<p>BUN (mg/dL) 
19.2±13.6 
17.4±6.7 
0.915 </p>

<p>Creatinine (mg/dL) 
1.93±3.11 
1.21±1.02 
0.783 </p>

<p>Ejection fraction (%) 
57.6±13.0 
65.4±8.8 
0.007 </p>

<p>Multivessel disease 
15 (68.2) 
61 (48.0) 
0.106 </p>

<p>Time of VH-IVUS examination </p>

<p>After wiring 
0 (0) 
104 (81.9) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>After ballooning 
22 (100) 
23 (18.1) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Angiographic findings </p>

<p>Lesion length (mm) 
24.4±9.6 
17.2±7.4 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Proximal reference lumen area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
7.24±3.06 
8.77±3.11 
0.035 </p>

<p>Distal reference lumen area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
5.49±2.64 
8.55±8.84 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Location (n) </p>

<p>(LAD/LCX/RCA/Ramus/LM) 
12/5/5/0/0 
74/23/18/1/11 </p>

<p>Stent </p>

<p>Number (n) 
1.86±1.08 
2.16±1.29 
0.262 </p>

<p>Diameter (mm) 
2.77±0.35 
3.21±0.42 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Length (mm) 
29.2±4.8 
22.0±5.0 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Maximal pressure, atmosphere 
13.5±2.7 
14.7±2.6 
0.065 </p>

<p>Data are expressed as n (%) or mean±standard deviation. CTO: chronic total occlusion, CK: creatinine kinase, Tn-I: troponin-I, hs-CRP: high sensitivity C-
reactive protein, LDL-C: low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, HDL-C: high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, BUN: blood urea nitrogen, VH-IVUS: virtual his-
tology-intravascular ultrasound, LAD: left anterior descending artery, LCX: left circumflex artery, RCA: right circumflex artery, Ramus: ramus intermedius 
artery, LM: left main artery </p>



<p>Yo-Han Park, et al. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4070/kcj.2016.46.1.33 
www.e-kcj.org </p>

<p>p=0.016) were greater in CTO lesions than in non-CTO lesions. 
Volumetric analysis over the entire lesion length revealed that 
total atheroma volume (224±159 mm 
3 vs. 143±86 mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, p=0.006) 
and percent atheroma volume (63.2±9.6% vs. 55.8±8.5%, p=0.011) 
of the CTO group were both significantly greater than those of the 
non-CTO group. The CTO group had greater fibrous volume 
(81.1±74.0 mm 
3 vs. 51.9±40.1 mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, p=0.031), dense calcified volume 
(14.0±13.3 mm 
3 vs. 7.4±8.0 mm 
3 , p=0.010), and necrotic core </p>

<p>volume (27.7±24.0 mm 
3 vs. 14.4±12.5 mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, p=0.005) compared to 
the non-CTO group (Table 2). 
However, the lesion length adjusted plaque composition of the 
CTO group, which was calculated in order to compensate for the 
difference according to the varying lesion lengths between two 
groups, was not significantly different compared to that of the non-
CTO group (Fig. 2). Dense calcified volume and necrotic core volume 
of CTO lesions in lesion length adjusted volumetric analysis were 
both somewhat larger than in the non-CTO lesions, but these 
differences were not statistically significant. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The main findings of our study were as follows. We found that 
lesion length and plaque burden of the CTO group were significantly 
longer and greater than those of the non-CTO group. In addition, 
the CTO group had greater overall fibrous volume, dense calcified </p>

<p>volume, and necrotic core volume in volumetric analysis performed 
over the whole lesion length, but the lesion length adjusted plaque 
composition showed no significant difference between the two 
groups. These findings suggest that plaque characteristics of the 
CTO lesion were similar to those of non-CTO lesion and that the 
difference of absolute plaque volume, especially in terms of fibrous 
volume, dense calcified volume, and necrotic core volume, was due 
to the difference in large plaque volume caused by the longer lesion 
length in CTO lesion. 
Previous studies have reported that percentage of necrotic core 
had a direct relationship with plaque instability. A compartive study 
of the lesion characteristics in patients with ACS and SA found that 
the necrotic core volume of ACS was significantly greater than 
those of SA. 
10) Therefore, these investigators hypothesized that the </p>

<p>lesion of ACS had more vulnerable plaque composition compared 
with those of SA. Another study on the pathologic findings of CTO 
lesions reported that long duration-CTO lesions were characterized 
by severe negative remodeling, moderate calcification (16.8%), and 
low composition of necrotic core area (7.8%). 
14) Our study revealed </p>

<p>that the necrotic core volume of the CTO lesion (19.8%) was similar 
(p=0.166) to those of non-CTO lesion (17.5%) in lesion length 
adjusted volumetric analysis. This finding suggests that the CTO 
lesion is not more vulnerable than non-CTO lesion. This result is in 
keeping with previous studies that have found a small necrotic core 
volume in the CTO lesion. A prior study that investigated the 
correlation between histology and angiographic findings of CTO 
lesions suggested that the plaque of CTO lesions evolved from a 
cholesterol laden plaque to fibrocalcific plaque as a result of an 
aging process. Formation rates of neovascular channels in intimal 
plaques derived from the tunica adventitia increase with age and 
are also associated with intimal plaque cellular inflammation. </p>

<p>15) </p>

<p>These findings may help explain the adverse events of PCI in elderly 
CTO patients, such as coronary arterial dissection and coronary 
arterial rupture. However, necrotic core volume in lesion length 
adjusted volumetric analysis of CTO lesions was not different in 
those of non-CTO lesions in our study. PCI of CTO may carry a risk 
of adverse events due to neovascular channels derived from the 
tunica adventitia, but plaque composition of CTO lesions was not 
different from those of non-CTO lesion, particularly with respect to 
necrotic core volume, in our study. Thus, CTO lesions may not be 
more vulnerable than non-CTO lesions. 
To date, there have been few studies comparing in vivo plaque 
composition of CTO and non-CTO lesions. Our findings are in 
keeping with a recent study on VH-IVUS findings in CTO lesions and 
non-occlusive lesions, which revealed that the necrotic core 
percentage was similar to non-occlusive lesions. 
16)17) However, these </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Comparison of lesion length of chronic total occlusion (CTO) and 
non-CTO group. The lesion length was measured by virtual histology-
intravascular ultrasound. Lesion length of CTO group was longer than 
those of non-CTO group. Data are expressed as mean±standard deviation. </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Lesion length </p>

<p>CTO 
non-CTO </p>

<p>mm 
p&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>24.4±9.6 </p>

<p>17.2±7.4 </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4070/kcj.2016.46.1.33 
www.e-kcj.org </p>

<p>Table 2. Virtual histology-intravascular ultrasound examination findings </p>

<p>Variables 
CTO 
Non-CTO 
p 
Lesion analysis at MLA 
Remodeling index 
0.99±0.21 
0.94±0.17 
0.222 
Plaque area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
9.50±4.47 
10.27±4.77 
0.456 
Plaque burden 
70.3±7.8 
69.2±10.7 
0.808 
Fibrous area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
3.90±2.46 
4.31±2.77 
0.596 
Fibrofatty area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
0.92±1.11 
1.26±1.51 
0.417 
Dense calcified area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
0.45±0.54 
0.44±0.41 
0.557 
Necrotic core area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
1.32±1.31 
1.15±0.86 
0.957 
Fibrous area 
60.4±13.6 
59.3±13.6 
0.730 
Fibrofatty area 
13.2±10.1 
14.5±11.2 
0.654 
Dense calcified area 
7.5±8.3 
8.0±8.6 
0.675 
Necrotic core area 
18.9±12.4 
18.4±11.4 
0.986 
Lesion analysis at proximal reference site 
Plaque area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
7.96±2.86 
7.77±3.46 
0.442 
Plaque burden 
53.0±12.7 
46.3±10.7 
0.015 
Fibrous area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
2.71±1.72 
2.58±2.07 
0.969 
Fibrofatty area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
0.73±1.02 
0.76±1.54 
0.577 
Dense calcified area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
0.39±0.46 
0.35±0.43 
0.773 
Necrotic core area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
0.75±0.81 
0.59±0.53 
0.935 
Fibrous area 
61.5±14.3 
60.6±16.2 
0.694 
Fibrofatty area 
13.8±11.1 
12.6±10.9 
0.554 
Dense calcified area 
8.8±9.0 
9.9±10.7 
0.281 
Necrotic core area 
16.0±11.8 
15.3±10.7 
0.209 
Lesion analysis at distal reference site 
Plaque area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
5.22±2.96 
5.92±3.70 
0.591 
Plaque burden 
47.8±11.3 
41.2±11.4 
0.016 
Fibrous area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
1.29±1.29 
1.61±2.04 
0.443 
Fibrofatty area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
0.27±0.50 
0.40±0.68 
0.547 
Dense calcified area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
0.31±0.67 
0.21±0.32 
0.940 
Necrotic core area (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
0.44±0.81 
0.38±0.65 
0.575 
Fibrous area 
58.7±23.4 
56.1±24.8 
0.967 
Fibrofatty area 
11.2±10.1 
13.6±13.5 
0.585 
Dense calcified area 
9.4±11.4 
8.6±14.1 
0.750 
Necrotic core area 
14.4±10.3 
12.2±11.5 
0.882 
Volumetric analysis over the entire lesion length 
Total atheroma volume (mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) 
224±159 
143±86 
0.006 
Percent atheroma volume 
63.2±9.6 
55.8±8.5 
0.011 
Fibrous volume (mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) 
81.1±74.0 
51.9±40.1 
0.031 
Fibrofatty volume (mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) 
22.4±30.1 
13.5±15.5 
0.186 
Dense calcified volume (mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) 
14.0±13.3 
7.4±8.0 
0.010 
Necrotic core volume (mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) 
27.7±24.0 
14.4±12.5 
0.005 
Fibrous volume 
56.9±10.6 
59.9±10.6 
0.230 
Fibrofatty volume 
13.1±10.7 
13.5±9.0 
0.623 
Dense calcified volume 
10.3±6.4 
9.0±6.9 
0.310 
Necrotic core volume 
19.8±9.6 
17.5±9.1 
0.340 
Necrotic core/dense calcium ratio 
2.56±1.73 
2.91±3.07 
0.965 </p>

<p>Data are expressed as % or mean±standard deviation. CTO: chronic total occlusion, MLA: minimal lumen area </p>



<p>Yo-Han Park, et al. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4070/kcj.2016.46.1.33 
www.e-kcj.org </p>

<p>investigators reported that the dense calcium in CTO lesions was 
less than that in non-occlusive lesions and, thus, the necrotic core/ 
dense calcium ratio tended to be greater (although statistically 
insignificant) in the CTO lesions than in non-occlusive lesions. They </p>

<p>also reported that a high necrotic core/dense calcium ratio was 
associated with plaque instability and that this ratio was also 
associated with an increased creatinine kinase-MB levels in non-ST 
elevation acute coronary syndrome. 
18)19) We also evaluated for </p>

<p>differences in necrotic core/dense calcium ratio of CTO and non-
CTO lesions. However, we did not detect a significant difference in 
the present study (Table 2). The previously study included ACS 
patients in their study population, while our study included only SA 
patients. In the previous study, they suggested that CTO lesions may 
be more vulnerable than non-occlusive lesions (although there was 
no statistical significance), but our study suggests that CTO lesions 
may not be different from non-CTO lesions in terms of plaque 
vulnerability. 
This study has several limitations. Firstly, this study was a single-
center, retrospective study and included a relatively modest number 
of patients. CTO lesions have been reported that describe the 
proximal, middle, or distal end of the lesion segment having unique 
plaque compositions. 
14) However, we had modest number of CTO </p>

<p>patients, and we analyzed the entire lesion length but did not 
analyze the lesion according to the proximal, middle, or distal 
segment. Alas, this study was done to primarily compare the plaque </p>

<p>characteristics between CTO and non-CTO lesions. Secondly, all 
patients in the CTO group underwent VH-IVUS after ballooning, so 
there was iatrogenic luminal dilatation in CTO lesions, which may 
have decreased plaque burden and, consequently, affect the 
percentage of each component of the plaque. However, this is 
inevitable while performing VH-IVUS in CTO lesions. Thirdly, VH-
IVUS cannot appropriately identify a thrombus. Thrombus is often 
indicated as "green" or "green-yellow" by VH-IVUS, which was 
classified as a fibrous or fibro-fatty plaque. However, our study 
population consisted of patients with SA, which is typically not 
associated with the presence of a coronary thrombus. In addition, 
the study population in this study had all undergone successful PCI, 
and, thus, a modest selection bias is inevitable. However, all 22 CTO 
lesions in this study underwent PCI and VH-IVUS examination 
without any difficulty, so this may add minimal distortion of data. 
Moreover, the distal vessel of CTO lesions is usually contracted and 
we did pre-dilate the CTO lesion before IVUS examination with 
intracoronary nitroglycerin. This iatrogenic channel will contribute a 
bias to the true, pre-dilated lumen diameter of the CTO lesion. 
However, this problem was inevitable given what is required to 
perform VH-IVUS in CTO lesions currently. 
In conclusion, CTO lesions were found to have a longer lesion 
length and greater plaque burden than non-CTO lesions. However, 
lesion length adjusted plaque composition showed no significant 
differences between the two groups. Fibrous, necrotic core, and 
dense calcified volume in volumetric analysis over the entire lesion 
length of CTO lesions were greater than those of non-CTO lesions, 
which, we hypothesize to be related to the longer lesion length in 
CTO lesions. These findings support that plaque characteristics of 
CTO lesions are similar to non-CTO lesions in patients with SA and a 
delicate and professional CTO PCI can increase success rates in the 
future. </p>



<p>Fig. 2. Comparison of lesion length adjusted plaque composition of 
chronic total occlusion (CTO) and non-CTO group. Each plaque volume 
was divided by lesion length to adjust a different lesion length of each 
patient and described as corrected volume (mm 
3 /mm). There was no 
significant difference of plaque composition between CTO and non-CTO 
group. Data are expressed as mean±standard deviation. FV/L: fibrous 
volume (mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>)/lesion length (mm), FFV/L: fibrofatty volume (mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>)/lesion 
length (mm), DCV/L: dense calcified volume (mm 
3 )/lesion length (mm), 
NCV/L: necrotic core volume (mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>)/lesion length (mm). </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Lesion length adjusted each plaque component volume </p>

<p>mm 3 /mm p=0.810 </p>

<p>3.16 
±1.94 </p>

<p>±1.01 </p>

<p>±0.54 </p>

<p>±0.92 </p>

<p>3.10 
±2.02 </p>

<p>±0.85 </p>

<p>±0.37 </p>

<p>±0.59 </p>

<p>p=0.881 
p=0.115 </p>

<p>p=0.166 </p>

<p>CTO 
non-CTO </p>

<p>0.86 0.85 
0.58 
0.41 </p>

<p>1.13 </p>

<p>0.83 </p>

<p>FV/L 
FFV/L 
DCV/L 
NCV/L </p>





</text></tei>