<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4958647" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>BACKGROUND/OBJECTIVES: The purpose of this study was to develop a dish-based semiquantitative food frequency questionnaire 
(FFQ) for Korean adolescents and evaluate its reproducibility and validity. 
SUBJECTS/METHODS: Based on 24-hour dietary recall data from the 4th Korean National Health and Nutrition Examination 
Survey (KNHANES), we developed a FFQ with 71 items. From a quota sample of 160 adolescents recruited using gender and 
age group as stratification variables, 153 participated in the complete data collection process. The FFQ was administered to 
each subject twice, at an interval of 3-4 weeks, to evaluate the test-retest reliability. The validity of the FFQ was assessed 
relative to 8-day food record data. 
RESULTS: The study findings demonstrated the FFQ's satisfactory reproducibility. Spearman correlation coefficients ranged from 
0.64(for β-carotene) to 0.81(for protein). From cross-classification analyses, the proportion of subjects in the same intake quartile 
was highest for protein (65.4%) and lowest for vitamin A(47.1%). With regard to validity analysis, Spearman correlation coefficients 
ranged from 0.27(for vitamin A and fiber) to 0.90 (for energy). The proportions of subjects in the opposite categories between 
the first FFQ and the 8-day food record data were generally low within the range from 0.74% (for energy and carbohydrate) 
to 13.2% (for β-carotene). 
CONCLUSIONS: In conclusion, the dish-based semiquantitative FFQ developed in this study can be useful for grouping Korean 
adolescents according to major macro-and micronutrient intakes with reasonable reproducibility and validity. </p>

<p>Investigations of the effects of diet on the prevention and 
occurrence of diseases require a tool for reasonably assessing 
the dietary intake. In the case of chronic diseases, it is necessary 
to understand the dietary intake over an extended period, and 
the food frequency method, which reflects long-term dietary 
intake, is normally used. The food frequency questionnaire (FFQ) 
also needs to reflect dietary characteristics of the target 
population [1]. 
The results of a recent survey indicate that Korean adolescents 
do not consume the recommended nutrient intakes of calcium, 
vitamin A, riboflavin, and vitamin C. Furthermore, 18%, 21.5%, 
and 80% of adolescents consume more than the dietary reference 
intake levels of energy, fat, and sodium, respectively, which 
indicates the presence of nutritional imbalance problems with 
Korea adolescents [2]. According to an analysis of the 2005 and 
2013 Korean National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 
(KNHANES) applied to representative Korean samples, the 
dietary pattern of Korean adolescents changed rapidly during </p>

<p>the 8-year period: the daily intake of vegetables decreased from 
260 g to 214 g, the intake of fruit increased from 80 g to 140 
g, and the intake of animal foods increased from 279 g to 396 
g. These changes illustrate the dynamic dietary pattern of 
Korean adolescents. Comparing the average daily nutrient and 
dietary intakes between adolescents aged 12-18 years and adults 
aged 30-49 years according to the 2013 KNHANES revealed that 
the intake of certain micronutrients (e.g., calcium, iron, and 
potassium) is much lower for adolescents than for adults. In 
terms of food groups, the intake of plant foods was lower and 
that of animal foods was higher for adolescents than for adults, 
revealing a clear distinction between these two age groups [2,3]. 
Therefore, a dietary research tool is needed for conducting 
systematic research into the nutritional status of adolescents, 
who are characterized by a dynamic and distinct dietary 
consumption relative to other life cycle groups. 
FFQs for adolescents have been widely developed and 
evaluated worldwide [4-7]. Rockett et al. [4] developed an FFQ 
for American adolescents aged 9-18 years with 116 items-
including food that is frequently consumed in this age group-in </p>

<p>This research was supported by the Basic Science Research Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea(NRF) funded by the Ministry of Science, 
ICT &amp; Future Planning (NO. 2010-0002825). 
 § Corresponding Author: Seungmin Lee, Tel. 82-2-920-7671, Fax. 82-2-920-2076, Email. smlee@sungshin.ac.kr </p>

<p>Received: December 2, 2015, Revised: April 13, 2016, Accepted: April 13, 2016 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>



<p>Development and evaluation of FFQ for adolescents </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Sampling process of the study subjects for developing the FFQ </p>

<p>Energy and 15 nutrients 
Number of foods selected </p>

<p>Energy 
21 </p>

<p>Carbohydrate 
14 </p>

<p>Protein 
25 </p>

<p>Fat 
14 </p>

<p>Fiber 
11 </p>

<p>Vitamin A 
5 
β-carotene 
10 </p>

<p>Vitamin C 
5 </p>

<p>Thiamin 
15 </p>

<p>Riboflavin 
13 </p>

<p>Niacin 
28 </p>

<p>Calcium 
4 </p>

<p>Phosphorus 
18 </p>

<p>Sodium 
14 </p>

<p>Potassium 
24 </p>

<p>Iron 
15 </p>

<p>Total No. of selected dish items 
71 </p>

<p>Table 1. Number of dish items selected for the food frequency questionnaire 
(FFQ) by stepwise multiple linear regression for energy and each nutrient </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Selection of dish items for inclusion in the FFQ </p>

<p>order to understand their general diet. The reproducibility over 
a 1-year period was found to be acceptable. Yaroch et al. [5] 
developed an FFQ for low-income African-American adolescents 
aged 11-17 years for application in a dietary survey. In addition 
to FFQs focusing on the overall diet, FFQs have been developed 
for understanding the intake of specific nutrients or food 
groups, and such research has shown that FFQs can be useful 
in evaluating the diet of school-age children and adolescents 
[8-12]. However, the large differences between the food cultures 
of Korea and other countries imply that foreign FFQs cannot 
be applied to Korean adolescents [1]. While several studies have 
(Ed-or 'While extensive research has') been conducted to 
develop FFQs for Korean adults and elderly since the mid-1990s 
[13-19], only a few studies have developed FFQs for Korean 
adolescents [20]. 
Therefore, the present study aimed to develop a semiquan-
titative FFQ for Korean adolescents and evaluate its reproducibility 
and validity. The FFQ was designed to assess intake levels of 
major macro-and micronutrients based on dish-based items. </p>

<p>SUBJECTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Development of the FFQ </p>

<p>Subjects 
The FFQ development stage of this study utilized data from 
the first and second years (2007 and 2008, respectively) of the 
fourth KNHANES. The KNHANES consists of three sections: 
health examination, health interview, and nutrition survey. This 
study used the 24-hour recall data of the KNHANES that were 
obtained through individual interviews by trained nutritionists. 
Out of 14,338 subjects who participated in the health ques-
tionnaire and health examination survey, dietary data from 
1,081 subjects (562 males and 519 females) aged 12-18 years 
who did not have major chronic diseases such as cancer, 
diabetes, or myocardial infarction were used after excluding 
calorie intakes of less than 500 kcal or more than 4,000 kcal 
[4,20,23,30,31] (Fig. 1). 
The KNHANES was approved by the KCDC Institutional Review 
Board (IRB). (IRB: 2007-02CON-04-P; 2008-04EXP-01-C) All 
participants provided written informed consent. Participation 
was voluntary and all records were anonymized before 
analysis. </p>

<p>Selection of FFQ dish items 
Selection of the FFQ items was based on the dish codes of 
the dietary data rather than food codes, due to the common 
use of multiple food ingredients in Korean dishes, the 
convenience of diet recollection, and the accuracy the nutrient 
intake estimation. The food items included in the questionnaire 
were selected by first individually examining each of the 1,560 
dish codes that appeared in the 24-hour recall data of the 1,081 
subjects. In this examination, the 1,560 dish codes were reduced 
to 637 after combining dishes with identical or similar and 
content, and then to 245 after eliminating those consumed by 
fewer than 1% of the subjects [31]. 
In order to select the major items that contribute to the 
absolute nutrient intake, a contribution analysis was conducted 
for energy and 15 nutrients, including macronutrients and 
micronutrients, that are listed in Table 1. Dish codes that 
contribute less than 0.5% of the total intake of each nutrient </p>

<p>Jinhee Yum and Seungmin Lee </p>



<p>Fig. 3. The FFQ format </p>

<p>were then eliminated [1,31,32]. A stepwise multiple regression 
analysis was subsequently conducted with the independent 
variables being the dish codes that remained after the contri-
bution analysis. Dish codes that constituted 80% of the nutrient 
intake were retained. Out of the 16 stepwise multiple regression 
analyses, dish codes that remained at least once were selected 
as the final FFQ items. Also, 4 types of fruit were added to 
the item list because the fruit intake changes markedly accor-
ding to season, resulting in the final selection of 71 items (Fig. 2). </p>

<p>Selection of intake frequency and portion size 
The standard portion size consumed per meal and a represen-
tative recipe for each selected item were derived based on the 
frequency of appearance and average intake of each food code 
implicated in the FFQ item. For the standard portion size, 
non-intakers' data were not taken into account to improve the 
representativeness of actual consumption pattern. When nume-
rous food codes were implicated due to the inclusion of various 
recipes, the food codes were chosen by combining the 
appearance frequency of similar ingredients according to their 
weight. Food ingredients reported by fewer eaters (i.e., less than 
20% of the total appearance frequency for that dish code) were 
eliminated to enhance the simplicity and representativeness of 
the recipes. Hence, overestimation of the food weight was 
prevented by avoiding the simple addition of the average 
amount for each food ingredient used. For each FFQ item, three 
categories of portion size were presented to enhance the 
validity of consumption amount. </p>

<p>Preparation of visual materials for portion size and determination 
of the overall structure 
Visual materials for each FFQ item were produced by conduc-
ting experimental cooking with the average recipes prepared 
as described above, and a photo for each item was taken by 
a professional photographer. The shape and color of the plates 
used in the photograph were chosen based on the advice from 
a food coordinator. A multiple-choice format (i.e., intake 
frequencies as suggested repeatedly for each item) rather than 
the conventional FFQ format (i.e., FFQ items placed in the first 
column and intake frequencies placed in the row) was selected 
for the overall structure of the FFQ based on a preliminary 
study. </p>

<p>Evaluating the Reproducibility and Validity of the Developed FFQ </p>

<p>Subjects 
Quota sampling, which is a type of nonprobability sampling 
method, was used to evaluate the reproducibility and validity 
of the developed questionnaire. With the gender and school 
type (middle school and high school) of adolescents aged 12-18 
years set as stratification variables, 160 subjects were recruited 
in the same ratio for each stratum. Based on the analysis of 
the nutrient consumption according to the FFQ and food record 
data, subjects who had calorie intakes of less than 500 kcal 
and more than 4,000 kcal, and those who did not complete 
the questionnaire were excluded, so that data from 153 
adolescents were included in the final analysis. This study was 
approved by the Institutional Review Board of Sungshin Woman 
University (IRB: sswuirb2011-006). Written informed consents 
were obtained from each subject. </p>

<p>Data collection 
The developed FFQ was administered twice for each subject 
over a 4-week period. During this period the food record data 
were obtained over 8 non-consecutive days (6 weekdays and 
2 weekend days, twice per week). The data collection was 
conducted between September and December in 2011. A 
trained nutritionist provided thorough instructions on how to 
complete the FFQ and the food record sheet to each subject. 
For recording in the food record sheet, photographs of 
commonly used plates, measuring cups, and food photos of 
actual sizes were handed out in advance. 
The food record data for the 8 non-consecutive days were 
reviewed by the trained nutritionist once a week to ensure 
recording in time and data quality. Data that were inadequate, 
imprecise, or contained missing information were augmented 
by phone or face to face interviews. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
A <rs id="software-0" type="software">Can-pro</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.0</rs> (computer-aided nutritional analysis program, 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Korean Nutritional Society</rs>, 2011; Seoul, Korea) was used to 
calculate nutrient intakes from the 8-day food records and FFQ, 
and the reproducibility and validity were analyzed using the 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">Statistical Analysis System</rs> program (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 9.2</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, 
Cary, NC, USA). 
The reproducibility and validity of the FFQ were determined 
by calculating the Spearman rank-order and Pearson correla-
tion coefficients. Since the food records used as comparative 
data in the FFQ validity analysis might have attenuated the 
validity due to day-to-day variations, the de-attenuated correla-
tion coefficients were calculated. The data were divided into 
four categories according to the nutrient intake. Cross-
classification was then conducted to identify the consistency 
between the first and second FFQ data, as well as between 
FFQ and food record data. The corresponding weighted kappa 
values were calculated. In addition, the Bland-Altman plots 
were generated to examine the reproducibility and validity of 
the FFQ. The cutoff for statistical significance was 0.05 in 
two-tailed testing. </p>



<p>Development and evaluation of FFQ for adolescents </p>

<p>Dish group 
(number of items) 
Dish items 
Dish group 
(number of items) 
Dish items </p>

<p>Rice (6) 
Cooked rice 
Cooked rice with brown rice 
Cooked rice with boiled barley 
Cooked rice with other grains 
Cooked rice with beans 
Cooked rice with black rice </p>

<p>One-dish meal (4) 
Stir-fried rice 
Curry and rice 
Bibimbap 
Chicken rice porridge </p>

<p>Noodles (5) 
Banquet noodles 
Ramen 
Noodle soup 
Spaghetti 
Black bean sauce noodles </p>

<p>Poultry (5) 
Spicy stir-fried chicken 
Fried chicken 
Whole chicken soup 
Smoked duck 
Braised spicy chicken </p>

<p>Soup/stew (7) 
Thick beef bone soup 
Soybean paste soup with dried radish leaves 
Soybean paste soup wit curled mallows 
Seaweed soup 
Pork-on-the-bone soup with potatoes 
Kimchi stew 
Soybean paste stew </p>

<p>Bread/Dumpling 
/pizza (7) </p>

<p>Sandwich 
Bread 
Hamburger 
Cereal 
Fried dumpling 
Meat dumpling 
Pizza </p>

<p>Meat (8) 
Napa wraps with pork 
Grilled pork belly 
Pork cutlet 
Sweet and sour pork 
Braised spareribs 
Stir-fried pork 
Beef braised in soy sauce 
Bulgogi </p>

<p>Side dishes (9) 
Stir-fried anchovies 
Rolled omelette 
Fried eggs 
Seasoned dried squid 
Broiled ham 
Seasoned spinach 
Seasoned bean sprouts 
Broiled laver 
Pickled vegetables </p>

<p>Fish (3) 
Grilled mackerel 
Grilled spanish mackerel 
Braised mackerel </p>

<p>Kimchi (3) 
Kimchi 
Radish kimchi 
Young summer radish kimchi </p>

<p>Snacks (3) 
Cracker 
Chocolate cake 
Ice cream </p>

<p>Beverages (4) 
Orange juice 
Coke 
Milk 
Yogurt </p>

<p>Fruit (7) 
Watermelon 
Mandarin 
Persimmon 
Apple 
Banana 
Orange 
Strawberry </p>

<p>Table 2. Food frequency questionnaire (FFQ) items according to dish groups </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Development of the FFQ 
Table 2 lists the 71 finally chosen FFQ items. Considering that 
adolescents can exhibit a low response rate when the assess-
ment tool involves complicated questions(21) and variations in 
the frequency choices between different FFQ items may 
increase the proportion of mistakes, the following eight frequency 
choices were applied to all 71 items: 'less than once a month,' 
'1 to 3 times a month,' 'once a week,' '2 to 3 times a week,' 
'4 to 6 times a week,' 'once a day,' '2 times a day,' and '3 or 
more times a day.' For the portion size option, three choices 
of 'less than the amount in the photo,' 'close to the amount 
in the photo,' and 'more than the amount in the photo' were 
presented. A part of the developed FFQ is shown in Fig. 3. </p>

<p>Reproducibility Analysis and Validity Testing </p>

<p>Reproducibility 
In order to evaluate the reproducibility of the developed FFQ, 
a correlation analysis was conducted on the nutrient consu-</p>

<p>mption between the first and second FFQs (Table 3). The 
Pearson correlation coefficients for energy and the 15 nutrient 
intakes ranged from 0.53 (for β-carotene) to 0.82 (for energy 
and phosphorus), and the Spearman correlation coefficients 
ranged from 0.64 (for β-carotene) to 0.81 (for protein). The 
Pearson and Spearman correlation coefficients were statistically 
significant for all the nutrients and exceeded 0.7 for most of 
them, but were slightly lower for vitamin A, β-carotene, vitamin 
C, and iron. 
From the cross-classification analysis, the proportion of 
subjects in the same intake category was highest for protein 
(65.4%), and lowest for vitamin A (47.1%) (Table 4). The 
proportion of subjects in either same or adjacent categories 
ranged from 81.7% (for energy and β-carotene) to 95.4% (for 
fat). The proportion of subjects in the opposite categories 
between the first and second FFQs ranged from 0.0% (for fat 
and calcium) to 3.3% (for β-carotene). The consistency between 
the first and second FFQs was also assessed using weighted 
kappa values. The highest and lowest values for nutrients were 
0.67 for protein and 0.48 for vitamin A, respectively. 
Fig. 4 shows the Bland-Altman plots for protein, fat, vitamin </p>

<p>Jinhee Yum and Seungmin Lee </p>



<p>Energy and 15 nutrients 
Pearson coefficient 
Spearman coefficient </p>

<p>Energy 
0.82*** 
0.80*** </p>

<p>Carbohydrate 
0.80*** 
0.77*** </p>

<p>Protein 
0.79*** 
0.81*** </p>

<p>Fat 
0.73*** 
0.77*** </p>

<p>Fiber 
0.77*** 
0.75*** </p>

<p>Vitamin A 
0.56*** 
0.66*** 
β-carotene 
0.53*** 
0.64*** </p>

<p>Vitamin C 
0.67*** 
0.72*** </p>

<p>Thiamin 
0.78*** 
0.79*** </p>

<p>Riboflavin 
0.78*** 
0.78*** </p>

<p>Niacin 
0.75*** 
0.74*** </p>

<p>Calcium 
0.77*** 
0.77*** </p>

<p>Phosphorus 
0.82*** 
0.79*** </p>

<p>Sodium 
0.78*** 
0.78*** </p>

<p>Potassium 
0.77*** 
0.77*** </p>

<p>Iron 
0.67*** 
0.70*** </p>

<p>* P &lt; 0.05, ** P &lt; 0.01, *** P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Table 3. Pearson and Spearman correlation coefficients for energy and 15 
nutrients between first and second administrations of the FFQ </p>

<p>Energy and 15 
nutrients </p>

<p>Same quartile 
(%) </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>Same or adjacent 
quartiles (%) </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>Opposite 
quartiles (%) </p>

<p>3) </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>4) </p>

<p>Energy 
47.7 
81.7 
2. 
0.47 </p>

<p>Carbohydrate 
56.2 
90.2 
0.7 
0.57 </p>

<p>Protein 
65.4 
93.5 
0.7 
0.67 </p>

<p>Fat 
54.9 
95.4 
0.0 
0.60 </p>

<p>Fiber 
58.8 
91.5 
1.3 
0.59 </p>

<p>Vitamin A 
47.1 
90.0 
2.0 
0.48 </p>

<p>β-carotene 
51.0 
81.7 
3.3 
0.50 </p>

<p>Vitamin C 
56.9 
94.8 
2.6 
0.59 </p>

<p>Thiamin 
56.2 
92.8 
0.7 
0.59 </p>

<p>Riboflavin 
50.3 
93.5 
0.7 
0.55 </p>

<p>Niacin 
56.9 
91.5 
2.0 
0.57 </p>

<p>Calcium 
53.6 
91.5 
0.0 
0.56 </p>

<p>Phosphorus 
54.9 
90.9 
0.7 
0.56 </p>

<p>Sodium 
56.9 
94.1 
1.3 
0.60 </p>

<p>Potassium 
59.5 
92.2 
1.3 
0.60 </p>

<p>Iron 
51.6 
86.9 
1.3 
0.50 </p>

<p>1) Percentage of subjects in the same quartile of nutrient intakes from FFQ1 and 
FFQ2 
2) Percentage of subjects in the same or adjacent quartiles of nutrient intakes from 
FFQ1 and FFQ2 
3) Opposite (lowest/highest) quartiles 
4) Weighted kappa </p>

<p>Table 4. Agreement proportion in quartile distributions of energy and 15 
nutrients between first and second administration of the FFQ </p>

<p>(A) 
(B) </p>

<p>(C) 
(D) </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Bland-Altman plots showing the relationship between the differences and the averages in daily intake of (A) protein, (B) fat, (C) vitamin A, and (D) ß-carotene 
estimated by first and second administrations of the FFQ </p>

<p>A and ß-carotene intakes between the first and second 
administrations of the FFQ. The narrowest limits of agreement 
were found for protein and fat, and the widest for vitamin A 
and β-carotene. Subject proportions who fell outside of the 
limits of agreement ranged from 4.6% to 7.8% for all the 
nutrients examined, indicating generally good agreement. </p>



<p>Development and evaluation of FFQ for adolescents </p>

<p>Energy and 15 
nutrients </p>

<p>Pearson coefficient 
Spearman coefficient </p>

<p>Crude r De-attenuated r Crude r De-attenuated r </p>

<p>Energy 
0.83*** 
0.91*** 
0.82*** 
0.90*** </p>

<p>Carbohydrate 
0.71*** 
0.79*** 
0.71*** 
0.78*** </p>

<p>Protein 
0.63*** 
0.70*** 
0.61*** 
0.68*** </p>

<p>Fat 
0.57*** 
0.66*** 
0.53*** 
0.62*** </p>

<p>Fiber 
0.37*** 
0.42*** 
0.24** 
0.27** </p>

<p>Vitamin A 
0.18* 
0.22* 
0.22** 
0.27 
β-carotene 
0.10 
0.13 
0.10 
0.12 </p>

<p>Vitamin C 
0.11 
0.13 
0.24** 
0.28** </p>

<p>Thiamin 
0.39*** 
0.44*** 
0.53*** 
0.60*** </p>

<p>Riboflavin 
0.39*** 
0.46*** 
0.48*** 
0.56*** </p>

<p>Niacin 
0.47*** 
0.55*** 
0.44*** 
0.51*** </p>

<p>Calcium 
0.32*** 
0.36*** 
0.36*** 
0.40*** </p>

<p>Phosphorus 
0.58*** 
0.65*** 
0.54*** 
0.60*** </p>

<p>Sodium 
0.34*** 
0.40*** 
0.28*** 
0.33*** </p>

<p>Potassium 
0.41*** 
0.47*** 
0.36*** 
0.41*** </p>

<p>Iron 
0.22*** 
0.27*** 
0.25** 
0.29*** </p>

<p>* P &lt; 0.05, ** P &lt; 0.01, *** P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Table 5. Pearson and Spearman correlation coefficients for energy and 15 
nutrients between first administration of the FFQ and 8-day food records </p>

<p>Energy and 15 
nutrients </p>

<p>Same quartile 
(%) </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>Same or adjacent 
quartiles (%) </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>Opposite 
quartiles (%) </p>

<p>3) </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>4) </p>

<p>Energy 
57.4 
96.3 
0.7 
0.62 </p>

<p>Carbohydrate 
47.8 
87.5 
0.7 
0.48 </p>

<p>Protein 
39.7 
77.9 
2.9 
0.32 </p>

<p>Fat 
33.8 
83.8 
2.9 
0.32 </p>

<p>Fiber 
28.7 
69.8 
7.4 
0.13 </p>

<p>Vitamin A 
33.1 
71.3 
8.8 
0.16 </p>

<p>β-carotene 
26.5 
70.6 
13.2 
0.07 </p>

<p>Vitamin C 
27.9 
72.1 
5.9 
0.15 </p>

<p>Thiamin 
44.9 
83.8 
2.2 
0.41 </p>

<p>Riboflavin 
39.0 
79.4 
3.7 
0.32 </p>

<p>Niacin 
36.0 
74.3 
4.4 
0.25 </p>

<p>Calcium 
34.6 
70.6 
3.7 
0.21 </p>

<p>Phosphorus 
36.8 
84.6 
3.7 
0.34 </p>

<p>Sodium 
30.1 
70.6 
5.9 
0.16 </p>

<p>Potassium 
39.7 
72.8 
5.2 
0.26 </p>

<p>Iron 
32.4 
67.7 
5.9 
0.15 </p>

<p>1) Percentage of subjects in the same quartile of nutrient intakes from FFQ1 and 
8-day food records 
2) Percentage of subjects in the same or adjacent quartiles of nutrient intakes from 
FFQ1 and 8-day food records 
3) Opposite (lowest/highest) quartiles 
4) Weighted kappa </p>

<p>Table 6. Agreement proportions in quartile distributions of energy and 15 
nutrients between first administration of the FFQ and 8-day food records </p>

<p>(A) 
(B) </p>

<p>(C) 
(D) </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Bland-Altman plots showing the relationship between the differences and the averages in daily intake of (A) protein, (B) fat, (C) vitamin A, and (D) ß-carotene 
estimated by first administration of the FFQ and 8-day food records </p>

<p>Validity 
The nutrient intakes as estimated from the 8-day food record 
data and the developed FFQ were compared to test the validity 
of the FFQ. The Pearson correlation coefficients for energy and 
the 15 nutrient intakes ranged from 0.22 (for vitamin A) to 0.91 </p>

<p>Jinhee Yum and Seungmin Lee </p>



<p>(for energy), and the Spearman correlation coefficients ranged 
from 0.27 (for vitamin A and fiber) to 0.90 (for energy). The 
Pearson and Spearman correlation coefficients were statistically 
significant for all the nutrients except for vitamin C and β 
-carotene (Table 5). 
From the cross-classification analysis, the proportion of 
subjects in the same intake category was highest for energy 
(57.4%), and lowest for β-carotene (26.5%) (Table 6). The 
proportion of subjects in either identical or adjacent categories 
ranged from 67.7% (for iron) to 96.3% (for energy). The 
proportion of subjects in the opposite categories between the 
first FFQ and 8-day food record data ranged from 0.74% (for 
energy and carbohydrate) to 13.2% (for β-carotene). The 
consistency between the first FFQ and 8-day food record data 
was assessed using weighted kappa values. The highest value 
for nutrients and energy was 0.62 for energy and the lowest 
was 0.07 for β-carotene (Table 6). 
Fig. 5 shows the Bland-Altman plots for protein, fat, vitamin 
A and ß-carotene intakes between the 8-day food records and 
the first administration of the FFQ. The narrowest limits of 
agreement were found for protein and fat, and the widest for 
vitamin A and β-carotene. Subject proportions who fell outside 
of the limits of agreement ranged from 4.4% to 7.4% for all 
the nutrients examined. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The purpose of this study was to develop and evaluate a 
dish-based semiquantitative FFQ for Korean adolescents. In the 
FFQ, 71 items were chosen by analyzing absolute contributions 
to energy and 15 types of nutrient intake and subsequently 
screening those contributing to intake variations between 
individuals. 
In the test-retest reproducibility evaluation, the correlation 
coefficients ranged from 0.53 (β-carotene) to 0.82 (energy), with 
an average value of 0.74. These relatively high values compared 
to previous studies reflect the superior reproducibility of the 
developed FFQ. Rockett et al. [4] evaluated the test-retest 
reproducibility over 1 year and found that the average correlation 
coefficients for nutrient and food intakes were 0.41 and 0.49, 
respectively. An FFQ consisting of 69 items for Belgian adoles-
cents showed reproducibility correlation coefficients ranging 
from 0.27 to 0.87 (with an average of 0.62) [6]. FFQ development 
and evaluation studies have also been conducted for FFQs 
targeting specific nutrients or food groups. Buzzard et al. [8] 
developed a brief FFQ for understanding the fat, cellulose, fruit, 
and vegetables intakes of adolescents in a rural area, and 
reported that the reproducibility coefficients of the developed 
FFQ were 0.58 for fat, 0.49 for cellulose, and 0.47 for fruit and 
vegetables. The correlation coefficients for the test-retest 
reproducibility of another simple FFQ created for understanding 
the fruit and vegetable intakes of high elementary graders in 
Korea ranged from 0.22 to 0.64 [22]. 
In addition to correlation analysis, the present study also 
investigated the classification consistency of the test-retest 
reproducibility. The consistency rates ranged from 47.1% (for 
vitamin A) to 65.4% (protein), the proximal proportions ranged 
from 81.7% (energy and β-carotene) to 95.4% (fat), and the </p>

<p>inconsistent proportions were in the low range of 0.0% (fat) 
to 3.33% (β-carotene). The corresponding weighted kappa 
values ranged from 0.47 (energy) to 0.67 (protein). These values 
are higher than those reported by Zhuang et al. [23] based on 
classifying the nutrient intake into four groups 0.20-0.44. 
Vereecken and Maes conducted a development and evaluation 
study of a simple FFQ with 15 items focusing on the intakes 
of cellulose, calcium, and some unhealthy food items [9]. 
Among Belgian adolescents, the weighed kappa values ranged 
from 0.43 to 0.70, which are similar to the values found in the 
present study. These literature comparisons indicate that the 
reproducibility was satisfactory in terms of classification 
consistency. 
In order to evaluate the validity of this FFQ, the first FFQ 
and the 8-day dietary records were compared. For the nutrient 
intake measured using these two methods, the de-attenuated 
Spearman correlation coefficients ranged from 0.12 (β-carotene) 
to 0.90 (energy), with an average of 0.48. All the macronutrients 
and several micronutrients such as phosphorus, thiamine, 
riboflavin, and niacin had correlation coefficients of at least 0.5, 
indicating high validity. Fiber, vitamin A, vitamin C, and iron 
had relatively lower correlation coefficients, of less than 0.3, and 
β-carotene did not show a significant correlation. 
An FFQ developed to target low-income African-American 
adolescents was shown to have de-attenuated and energy-
adjusted correlation coefficients of approximately 0.6 for most 
nutrients in comparison with 24-hour recall [5]. An earlier 
Korean study of adolescents' FFQ reported higher validity 
correlation coefficients for macronutrients and micronutrients 
compared to those in the present study [20]. However, it was 
consistent with our study that correlations coefficients for 
macronutrients were generally higher compared to those for 
micronutrients. In other studies, the correlation coefficient of 
vitamin A was 0.36 [24] and 0.37 [25], which is lower than that 
for other nutrients, and for an Iranian FFQ, the correlation 
coefficient for vitamin A was reported to have a negative value 
[26]. This could be partly due to the intake amount varying 
markedly according to the food type for micronutrients in 
comparison to calorie nutrients. 
The validity based on classification consistency revealed that 
the consistent proportion ranged from 26.5% (β-carotene) to 
57.4% (energy), the proximal proportion from 67.7% (iron) to 
96.3% (energy), and the inconsistent proportion from 0.7% 
(energy and carbohydrate) to 13.2% (β-carotene). Willett investi-
gated the classification consistency between dietary recording 
and FFQ, and found that the consistent proportion was 48-49%, 
the proximal proportion was 74-79%, and the inconsistent 
proportion was 3-4% [24]. According to another study [23], the 
consistent, proximal, and inconsistent proportions were 26.6-
44.0%, 34.3-44.4%, and 1.5-9.7%, respectively. The consistent 
and proximal proportions for macronutrients in the present 
study are similar to or higher than those found in the previous 
studies. On the other hand, the inconsistent proportion for β 
-carotene was 13.2%, which is higher than that of previous 
studies. Willet [27] and Kim &amp; Yang [28] reported a value of 
4%, whereas Rimm et al. [29] reported results similar to the 
present study: 12% for vitamins A and B12 Yim et al. [20] found 
that the consistency rate was very high (0.63-0.88) for most </p>



<p>Development and evaluation of FFQ for adolescents </p>

<p>nutrients except for vitamin A (0.26). Several possible reasons 
can be postulated for the low validity levels for a few micronu-
trients for the developed FFQ. First, the validity may have been 
underestimated due to use of the FFQ administered before the 
diet record data collection. Second, the variability between 
seasons for the fruit and vegetables included in the FFQ could 
have resulted in differences in the consumption according to 
the period of investigation. Third, the subject characteristics of 
this study may have lowered the validity. Most adolescents do 
not cook, and so they may not have enough information about 
seasonings and spices, leading to some information not being 
recorded on the dietary record sheet. 
The study findings regarding the reproducibility and validity 
of the FFQ may possess limited generalizability, considering that 
the study subjects were a convenience sample residing in Seoul 
and Gyeonggi Province and possible effect modification of 
socioeconomic factors could not be examined. 
The FFQ developed in this study exhibited generally accep-
table levels of reproducibility and validity in ranking the target 
population's diet according to major macro-and micronutrient 
intake levels. Therefore, this FFQ can be used as a reasonable 
tool in different settings, including screening out high nutritional 
risk subjects and evaluating the effects of nutrition intervention 
programs. Future research can fine tune the proposed FFQ to 
improve its validity for certain micronutrient intakes. </p>



<p>Jinhee Yum and Seungmin Lee </p>





</text></tei>