<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4926004" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>abstract </p>

<p>Background: Incidence of asthma in adolescents leads to variations in family status, roles and 
interaction with peers for them, which could be a source of stress and psychological tensions in them. 
Therefore, the present study was conducted to investigate the effect of Orem's self-care model on 
perceived stress in adolescents with asthma. 
Methods: In this semi-experimental study conducted from April 2013 to February 2014, 64 asthmatic 
adolescents referring Shariati Hospital, Isfahan were enrolled by simple random sampling and the 
patients were assigned to two groups of control and intervention. Then, Orem's self-care model-based 
training was implemented throughout eight sessions of two hours each and the Cohen Perceived Stress 
Scale was administered to both groups prior to and two months after the completion of the training. 
The data were analyzed by descriptive and analytical statistics consisting of paired t-test, independent 
t-test, Chi-square and Mann-Whitney using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 20</rs>. 
Results: Mean age of the participants was 14.15±3.12 years in the intervention group and 15.21±3.09 
years in the control groups. 68.8% and 59.4% of the participants were male in the intervention and 
control groups, respectively. Independent t-test indicated a significant difference in the mean scores 
of perceived stress in the intervention (25.46±5.31) and control groups (28.90±5.27) after the training. 
Also, the result of paired t-test indicated a significant difference in the mean score of perceived stress 
between before (29.18±5.27) and after (25.46±5.31) training. 
Conclusion: As the training based on Orem's model had a positive effect on declining perceived 
stress in asthmatic adolescents, continuation of using these training interventions could contribute to 
ultimately achieving positive outcomes in health functions of these patients. </p>

<p>KeywOrds: Adolescent; Orem's self-care model; Stress </p>

<p>Please cite this article as: Hemati Z, Abasi S, Mosaviasl F, Shakerian B, Kiani D. Effect of Orem's Self-Care 
Model on Perceived Stress in Adolescents with Asthma Referring the Asthma and Allergy Clinic, Isfahan, 2014. 
IJCBNM. 2016;4(3):247-255. </p>



<p>Hemati Z, Abasi S, Mosaviasl F, Shakerian B, Kiani D </p>

<p>ijcbnm.sums.ac.ir </p>

<p>intrOductiOn </p>

<p>Asthma is one of the most prevalent diseases 
in children and adolescents worldwide 1,2 and 
the leading reason for inability in children. 3 
The prevalence of asthma has been reported 
variously in Iran (4-7%) and worldwide 
(8-12%). Also, the prevalence in children is 
so growing worldwide that it has increased 
by 50% in different countries. 4 As shown, 
asthma accounts for approximately 1.6 
million emergency visits, over two million 
hospitalizations, and about 1.1 million days of 
school absence, major activity limitation, and 
unsatisfactory performance in children. 5 
Te incidence of asthma in adolescence 
not only brings about numerous challenges 
for adolescents, but also increases the 
likelihood of symptoms' exacerbation and 
asthma attacks, because significant physical, 
psychological, emotional, sexual, and social 
variations occur in adolescence. 6 Therefore, 
psychological and mental problems in 
adolescence are more prevalent than other life 
periods; for example, the incidence rate of 
such problems in 14 years of age increases by 
10 times as compared to 10 years of age. 7 As a 
result, acquisition of any disease, particularly 
chronic ones such as asthma, could intensify 
the crises of adolescence and lead to various 
complications, including psychological, 
because of the nature of chronic diseases 
which cause many limitations, and affect the 
adolescents' life greatly and hence their group 
activities as well as psychosocial functioning. 8 
More clearly, incidence of chronic diseases 
such as asthma in adolescence results in some 
lack of balance and peace for adolescents 
due to difficulties including repeated 
hospitalizations, side effects of treatment, 
school absence, and decline in academic 
performance culminating in stress. 9 
In this regard, the findings of a study 
demonstrated that stress and depression were 
highly prevalent among the adolescents with 
asthma. 10 Moreover, the results of another 
study indicated that the incidence of asthma 
symptoms and attacks in the asthmatic </p>

<p>adolescents suffering higher stress was 
more than those with lower levels of stress. 
Accordingly, the experience of stress in 
asthmatic adolescents increases the likelihood 
of asthmatic attacks. 11 Therefore, prevention 
of attacks and control of stress and anxiety in 
the adolescents with asthma is an important 
concern of healthcare teams. As the nurses 
spend the greatest amount of time with 
patients, they are often in the best position to 
detect symptoms and prevent complications 
in these patients. 12 
Training is a significant way to promote 
the adolescents' health through implementing 
various projects with reliance on the patients' 
active participation in various health 
behaviors. 13 By relevance, self-care pattern 
is an important training pattern which is 
based on the individual abilities and needs. 
For example, Orem's self-care model is a self-
care pattern which is an appropriate clinical 
guideline to plan for and implement self-care 
principles and could be applied as a conceptual 
framework to design self-care programs. 14 
The Orem Self Care Model is developed in 
three types of care systems with reference to 
the patient's needs and health problems and the 
role of the nurse, namely wholly compensatory 
nursing system, partly compensatory nursing 
system, and supportive-educative nursing 
system. In this model, when the patient is 
going to learn and perform the behavior 
of interest but is not able to do it without 
assistance, the supportive-educative nursing 
system is applied. Here, the role of nurses is to 
advise as required. This system is conducive 
to decision making, behavior management, 
and acquisition of knowledge and skills. In 
this study, the supportive-educative nursing 
system was adopted for the patients. 15 
Findings of a study investigating the effect 
of Orem's model on self-care in adolescents 
with asthma demonstrated that five domains 
of self-care including appropriate drug taking, 
use of exercise techniques, use of functional 
programs for asthma control, careful 
adherence to diet, and protection against 
environmental stimuli of asthma attacks in the </p>



<p>Effect of Orem's self-care model on perceived stress in asthmatic adolescents </p>

<p>IJCBNM July 2016; Vol 4, No 3 </p>

<p>treatment group were significantly different 
from the controls compared with prior to the 
intervention. 16 Also, the results of another 
study demonstrated the effect of supportive-
educative program, based on the Orem's 
theory, on knowledge, asthmatic control and 
self-care behaviors in the adolescents with 
asthma, showing that the control of self-care 
behaviors enhanced after the intervention. 17 
A study of training program and asthma 
control in adolescents showed that attending 
training classes by the adolescents with 
asthma led to a decrease in and mitigation of 
asthma attacks; hence, the incidence of stress 
became less likely in them. 18 Therefore in view 
of sensitive period of adolescence, adverse 
psychological and mental effects of asthma 
on adolescents as well as insufficient number 
of investigations on the Orem-based self-
care model, this study aimed to investigate 
the effect of the Orem's self-care model on 
perceived stress in adolescents with asthma. </p>

<p>Material and MethOds </p>

<p>This semi-experimental study was conducted 
from April 2013 to February 2014 (throughout 
11 months). The sample size was calculated as 
32 in each group based on the data of similar 
studies: (d=0.7s 2 , α=0.05, β=0.2). 19 For ethical 
considerations, ethical approval was issued by 
Research and Technology Deputy of Isfahan 
University of Medical Sciences (291302) and 
relevant authorities for this study. 
The study was conducted at Shariati 
Hospital, asthma and allergy clinic. The 
sampling was done in the patients referring 
Shariati Hospital, Isfahan. The patients were 
enrolled by simple random sampling so that 
the first referring individual with inclusion 
criteria was assigned to the intervention group 
and the second to control and it continued 
till the desired number of participants were 
included in the two groups. The inclusion 
criteria into the study were suffering from 
asthma for 6 months (by definition, chronic 
diseases take three months to interfere in 
daily activities and affect the patient's quality </p>

<p>of life), ability to answer questions and debate 
in training classes, full consciousness, the age 
of 11-21 years, and no previous participation 
in similar training. 
The exclusion criteria were absence in 
two consecutive and/or one fourth of all the 
sessions, no other chronic disease, mental 
health and no mental retardation (by medical 
file and the physician), no history of taking 
drugs with mental effects (by medical file 
and the physician), no emergency conditions 
throughout the study, no stressful incidence, 
for example bereavement during the study 
(based on the patients' statement before 
and during the study as they were already 
informed of the participation in this study) in 
both groups, and withdrawal from the study. 
A physician confirmed that the patients in 
the two groups were matched for the severity 
of asthma and the type of the drug(s) taken. 
The patients training based on the Orem's 
model were considered as independent 
variable and perceived stress as dependent 
variable. Gender, age, disease duration, and 
parental education level and occupation were 
considered as the underlying variables in this 
study. The researcher completed the pre-test 
questionnaires after she described the research 
purposes for the participants and obtained 
their written consent forms. The participants 
over 18 years of age needed no parents' 
permission and hence independently signed 
the letter of consent to participate in the study. 
For younger participants, the parents did it on 
behalf of their children. 
To examine the training needs of each 
participant before the intervention, a 
questionnaire was developed based on the 
Orem's model to investigate and detect some 
domains such as respiratory conditions, 
mood function, social function, and physical 
activity. Therefore, the researcher initially 
administered this questionnaire to the patients, 
and then planning for the intervention in the 
intervention group started with reference to the 
frequency of self-care needs in any domains. 
Among self-care needs, the highest frequency 
was derived for social function followed by </p>



<p>Hemati Z, Abasi S, Mosaviasl F, Shakerian B, Kiani D </p>

<p>ijcbnm.sums.ac.ir </p>

<p>mood function and physical function. 
After needs generation, the training 
materials were judged as appropriate. To 
develop the training materials, we derived 
the content by reviewing the relevant 
literature, and then offered to and confirmed 
by some university teachers who previously 
investigated such patients and a subspecialist. 
The training materials consisted of: 
Asthma and methods of controlling 
its symptoms, effective breathing types 
(diaphragmatic and lip-bud), proper 
application of spray, and ways to relieve 
stress and anxiety based on the Orem's self-
care model were instructed within eight 
2-h sessions. Training was implemented by 
the researcher as a group, individually, and 
face-to-face through speech, brainstorming 
and educational aids including PowerPoint, 
movie and educational replica at clinical skills 
training workshop of Shariati Hospital with a 
pulmonologist's help. 
It is noteworthy that all sessions were 
held in group, but when the parents and/or 
adolescents did not understand a subject and/ 
or raised any questions regarding the disease 
and how to care for, they were individually 
trained by the researcher or a subspecialist. 
In addition, the researcher's phone 
number was given to the patients for further 
advice and support if necessary during the 
follow-up. Therefore, the patients could call 
the researcher if they had any queries. 
For follow-up, all the patients in the 
intervention group were called after the 
educational intervention on an ongoing basis 
once a week (for two months), and the content 
was taught to them and care practices were 
evaluated. 
Two months after the intervention, the 
patients of both groups were requested to 
complete the questionnaire of perceived stress. 
The training in the control group was run as 
routine, so that the patients only received 
recommendations from physician in visits. 
Notably, the researcher trained the patients 
of both groups similarly for observance of 
research ethics. Cohen Perceived Stress </p>

<p>Scale has three versions, 4, 10, and 14-item, 
administered to measure the overall perceived 
stress. This scale measures thoughts, stress-
causing incidence, control, overcoming, coping 
with psychological pressure and experienced 
stresses. The items are scored on a 5-point 
Likert scale as never (0), almost never (1), 
sometimes (2), often (3), and many times (4). 
The items 4-13 are scored inversely ranging 
from never (4) too many times (0). It should 
be noted that for positive statements (4-10, 
and 13), the scores were calculated inversely. 
Overall, the scores ranged from 0 to 56. 
This scale, which was psychometrically 
investigated by Ghorbani et al. in 2002, 
as sesses perceived typical stress over the past 
month. Ghorbani et al. reported Cronbach's 
alpha at 0.84 and 0.86 for this scale. In the 
study done by Ghorbani et al., Cron bach's 
alpha in an American sample was 0.86 and in 
an Iranian sample it was calculated as 0.81. 20 
Cohen et al. calculated Cronbach's alpha for 
this scale as 84% and 86%, respectively. 21 
In addition, its validity was approved in the 
study performed by Khushabi et al. in Iran. 22 
This questionnaire has been already used 
in the studies on students and its validity 
and reliability (Cronbach's alpha: 80%) 
had been confirmed for this population. 23,24 
To investigate the questionnaire's validity, 
concurrent validity with the scales of positive 
and negative emotions, happiness, and 
depression was used. The positive emotion 
was significantly correlated with positive 
(r=0.73) and negative (r=0.53) perceived stress, 
negative emotion was significantly correlated 
with positive (r=0.68) and negative (r=0.68) 
perceived stress, happiness was significantly 
correlated with positive (r=0.68) and negative 
(r=0.43) perceived stress, and depression was 
significantly correlated with positive (r=0.57) 
and negative (r=0.49) perceived stress. 25 
Further, the association between this scale 
and validity criteria is not affected by age and 
gender. 24 
The data were analyzed using descriptive 
and analytical statistics consisting of paired 
t-test, independent t-test, Chi-square and </p>



<p>Effect of Orem's self-care model on perceived stress in asthmatic adolescents </p>

<p>IJCBNM July 2016; Vol 4, No 3 </p>

<p>Mann-Whitney tests in SPSS 20. </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>The results of independent t-test, analysis of 
variance, and Mann-Whitney revealed that there 
was no significant difference in age, duration of 
asthma, gender, fathers and mothers' education, 
and fathers and mothers' occupation between 
the two groups. Therefore, the two groups were 
similar in view of these variables. (Table 1). 
Independent t-test indicated a significant 
difference in the mean score of perceived 
stress after the intervention in both studied 
groups (P=0.01), while no statistically 
significant difference was obtained prior to 
the intervention in the two groups (P=0.79). 
Furthermore, paired t-test indicated a 
significant difference in the mean score of 
perceived stress between before and after 
the intervention in the intervention group 
(P=0.01), but no statistically significant </p>

<p>difference was derived in the control group 
(P=0.68). (Table 2) 
Moreover, independent t-test indicated that 
the mean differences in perceived stress score 
between the intervention and control groups 
were significant before and after training 
(P=0.04) (Table 3). </p>

<p>discussiOn </p>

<p>This study was conducted to investigate 
the effect of the Orem's self-care model on 
perceived stress in adolescents with asthma. As 
to the participants' demographics in the present 
study, most adolescents of intervention and 
control groups were male. 16 In another studym 
the mean age of asthmatic children in treatment 
and control groups was reported 7-15 years. 26 
The present study indicated that although 
there was no significant difference in the mean 
score of perceived stress prior to the training 
in both intervention and control groups, the </p>

<p>Table 1: Demographic characteristics of asthma patients in the two groups 
Demographic variables 
Intervention group 
Control group 
P value 
Age (yrs.), Mean±SD 
14.15±3.12 
15.21±3.09 
0.21 
Duration of asthma (month), Mean±SD 
26.38±19.88 
25.89±23.56 
0.93 
Sex N (%) 
Male 
10 (31.3) 
13 (40.6) 
0.30 
Female 
22 (68.8) 
19 (59.4) 
Father Education 
level N (%) 
Elementary 
7 (21.9) 
9 (28.1) 
0.74 
Secondary 
6 (18.8) 
4 (12.5) 
Diploma 
14 (43.8) 
15 (46.9) 
University degree 
5 (15.6) 
4 (12.5) 
Mother Education 
level N (%) 
Elementary 
10 (31.3) 
9 (28.1) 
0.67 
Secondary 
6 (18.8) 
4 (12.5) 
Diploma 
12 (37.5) 
16 (50) 
University degree 
4 (12.5) 
2 (6.3) 
Father Employment 
status N (%) 
Self-employed 
24 (75) 
23 (71.9) 
0.21 
Employment 
5 (15.6) 
9 (28.1) 
Employees &amp; retirees 
3 (9.4) 
0 (0) 
Mother Employment 
status N (%) 
Housekeeper 
30 (93.8) 
29 (90.6) 
0.5 
Employment 
2 (6.3) 
3 (9.4) </p>

<p>Table 2: Comparison of mean±SD score of perceived stress in the intervention and control groups before and 
after training 
Time 
Group (Mean±SD) 
P value 
Intervention 
Control 
Independent sample t-test 
Before training 
29.18±5.27 
29.62±7.88 
0.79 
After training 
25.46±5.31 
28.90±5.27 
0.01 
P value (Paired sample t-test) 
0.01 
0.68 </p>



<p>Hemati Z, Abasi S, Mosaviasl F, Shakerian B, Kiani D </p>

<p>ijcbnm.sums.ac.ir </p>

<p>difference were significant between the two 
groups after the training. 
This means that the intervention 
implemented in this study reduced perceived 
stress in patients with asthma in the 
intervention group, while the perceived stress 
was not significantly different between the 
two groups before the intervention. Holding 
sessions in the hospital's clinical skills centre, 
use of educational aids such as models, 
PowerPoint and movie, a variety of methods 
including speech and brainstorming and 
above all presence of parents at sessions could 
contribute to the intervention efficacy. 
The important purpose of training is to 
develop appropriate and stable behaviors, and 
if self-care activities are performed through 
active training methods and recognition of 
patients' attitudes and beliefs and also provision 
of an environment laden with confidence and 
comfort for clients, then they may contribute 
sufficiently to promotion of the desired healthy 
behaviors. 27 On the other hand, presentation of 
materials in an understandable manner, based 
on individual needs, and by group training, 
along with questions and answers can lead to 
better results, and above all help to continue 
appropriate caring behaviors. 28 
Since self-care as practiced by the 
adolescents could stimulate regressive and 
forgotten abilities and use them to eliminate 
inabilities, implementation of self-care 
programs could reinforce motivation and self-
esteem in the patients with asthma, so that they 
improve their deficits and inabilities through 
assuming responsibility for self-care and use 
the self-care to remove these difficulties. 
Similarly, a study of peer-centred training 
and health outcomes in the adolescents 
with asthma in Jordan demonstrated that 
the participants in the intervention group, 
as compared with controls, exhibited a </p>

<p>significant improvement of health-related 
quality of life, resistance to smoking, and 
knowledge of asthma self-management. 29 
Moreover, a study of the Orem's self-care 
model in adolescents with asthma indicated 
that self-care skills including use of drugs 
and a codified program, adherence to a daily 
follow-up program, and protection against 
disease-initiating factors such as stress 
significantly increased in the intervention 
group, but they did not cause a change in 
the controls. Also, the number of adolescents 
who accomplished self-care increased in the 
intervention group, who were less dependent 
on parents for self-care. 16 Another study of 
self-management of asthma in adolescents 
indicated that the students who underwent 
self-care intervention had a higher level 
of self-esteem for management of their 
disease and took more measures to prevent 
symptoms compared to the control group. 
Moreover, use of appropriate coping skills, 
decrease in school absence due to asthma, 
improvement of quality of life, and decrease 
in hospitalization turns were reported. 30 A 
study on the effect of interactive teaching of 
children and their families on the control of 
disease symptoms after one-year follow-up 
indicated that the number of children's 
referral to the emergency ward decreased. 31 
In addition, the present study obtained a 
significant difference in perceived stress 
score in the intervention group between 
before and after the training. 
In view of the great contribution of 
psychological factors including stress to 
incidence and/or exacerbation of asthma 
conditions, training of coping strategies to 
the participants by the researcher and their 
physician led to their active participation in 
self-care and hence decline of stress in them. 
Therefore, the Orem's self-care model-based 
training caused a decrease in perceived stress 
in asthmatic adolescents. 
Because this model aimed to prepare the 
patients for and assist them in self-care, then 
we must let them be actively involved in 
decision making and planning for self-care. </p>

<p>Table 3: Difference in mean perceived stress between 
the two groups of the study before and after training 
Group 
Mean±SD 
P value 
Intervention group 
29.34±6.69 
0.04 
Control group 
27.18±5.53 </p>



<p>Effect of Orem's self-care model on perceived stress in asthmatic adolescents </p>

<p>IJCBNM July 2016; Vol 4, No 3 </p>

<p>In this regard, a study of a program of 
stress management in the adolescents with 
asthma demonstrated that the intervention 
developed to control stress and improve 
coping with the disease in the intervention 
group resulted in promotion of physical health 
(lung function) and alleviation of perceived 
stress and depression. 32 Another study of the 
effect of asthma-related training on health 
outcomes in asthmatic children hospitalized 
in emergency ward of the hospital indicated 
that the training caused a significant decrease 
in hospitalization-associated stress in 
children, parents, and/or both compared to 
the controls. 33 
The distinctive point of the present study is 
investigation of self-care needs by the patients' 
needs assessment, because development 
and implementation of a program without 
consideration of the patients' needs yields no 
positive outcomes. Implementation of self-
care program could reinforce motivation and 
self-esteem in these clients, so that they are 
able to improve the disease-derived inabilities 
and utilize self-care capability to remove the 
associated problems by self-care. 
Since in the present study, because of time 
limitations, the effect of the Orem self-care 
programs has not been evaluated within an 
extensive length of time, it is recommended 
that its effect should be investigated more 
longitudinally (about four to six months after 
the intervention) to determine the reliability 
of the intervention. </p>

<p>cOnclusiOn </p>

<p>As the present study indicated, self-care 
training could be addressed as a significant 
factor contributing to the decrease in perceived 
stress. Therefore, the use of the models capable 
of inviting the clients and involving them in 
self-care could provide a valuable model which 
could be used to identify and evaluate the 
healthcare system for these patients. Then, it 
is recommended that this program should be 
considered as a part of treatment program for 
these patients. </p>

<p>acKnOwledgMent </p>

<p>Hereby, we gratefully thank the support of 
nursing and midwifery care research center 
in Isfahan University of Medical Sciences for 
funding this research project (grant no: 291302). </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: None declared. </p>

<p>references </p>

<p>1 Hemati Z, Mosaviasl F, Abasi S, et al. 
Effect of Orem's Self-Care Model on 
Self-Esteem of Adolescents with Asthma </p>









<p>
</p></text></tei>