<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4792212" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Overweight and obesity have been identified as independent risk factors for 
musculoskeletal disorders. However, the association between obesity and low back pain remains 
controversial. Little is known about the effects of overweight and obesity on the angles of the 
lumbosacral spine. The objective of this study was to evaluate the effects of body mass index 
(BMI) and waist-hip ratio (WHR) on lumbosacral angles. 
Methods: The effects of BMI and WHR on the lumbar lordosis angle (LLA), lumbosacral angle 
(LSA), sacral inclination angle (°°), and lumbosacral disc angle (LSDA) of 174 overweight and 
obese subjects (test group) and 126 underweight and normal-weight subjects (control group) 
were analyzed. 
Results: The test group had a significantly higher mean LSA, LLA, sacral inclination angle (SIA), 
and LSDA (P=0.001). A significant correlation was noted between BMI and LSA (P=0.001), 
LLA (P=0.001), SIA (P=0.001), and LSDA (P=0.03). There was also a positive relationship 
between WHR and LSA (P=0.012), LLA (P=0.009), SIA (P=0.02), and LSDA (P=0.01). 
Conclusion: There was an increase in lumbosacral angles in individuals with raised BMI and 
WHR. This may result in biomechanical changes in the lumbosacral spine, which increase the 
incidence of low back pain. 
Overweight and obesity constitute a growing public health problem and contribute 
substantially to the burden of chronic medical conditions globally. 
1 There is evidence 
on the association of obesity with a number of comorbidities including hypertension, 
diabetes mellitus, dyslipidemia, coronary artery disease, obstructive sleep apnea, 
menstrual irregularities, and certain types of cancer. 
2 Overweight and obesity have 
also been shown to be associated with both recurrent and chronic headaches in both 
adolescents and adults. 
3 Increased body mass index (BMI) has been identified as an 
independent risk factor for the development of symptoms of musculoskeletal disorders 
(MSDs). 
4-6 The reported prevalence of osteoarthritis and low back pain (LBP) among 
obese subjects is 34% and 22%, respectively. 
7,8 MSDs represent a considerable health 
problem globally, with LBP as one of the most common MSDs. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>The relationship between overweight and obesity and certain MSDs has been well 
described. Overweight and obesity are known risk factors for osteoarthritis. 
10 They also 
increase the need for and reduce the health outcomes from joint replacement surgery. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>However, the association of obesity with LBP remains controversial. The question 
whether obesity is a risk factor for LBP has given rise to conflicting reports with no 
clear causal link between obesity and LBP. A systematic review of the relationship 
between obesity and LBP revealed inconsistent results. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>correspondence: ndubuisi Oc 
Onyemaechi 
Department of surgery, college of 
Medicine, University of nigeria enugu 
campus, PMB 01129, enugu, nigeria 
Tel +234 80 3550 4767 
email bisionyemaechi@yahoo.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Patient Preference and Adherence 
10 March 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Patient Preference and Adherence 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>292 </p>

<p>Onyemaechi et al </p>

<p>The effect of overweight and obesity on the geometric 
angles of the lumbosacral spine (lumbosacral angles) is of 
clinical importance. The shape and geometry of the lum-
bosacral spine have been reported to be of importance in the 
occurrence of LBP. </p>

<p>12,13 </p>

<p>The impact of overweight and obesity on lumbosacral 
angles could give an insight into the controversial association 
between LBP and overweight and obesity. 
Many studies have examined the relationship between 
changes in the angles of the lumbar spine and LBP. The 
increase in lumbosacral angles was associated with increased 
risk of LBP. </p>

<p>14,15 </p>

<p>These angles include lumbar lordosis angle (LLA), 
lumbosacral angle (LSA), sacral inclination angle (SIA), and 
lumbosacral disc angle (LSDA). Lumbosacral angles could 
be affected by conditions such as age, posture, race, diseases, 
and surgery. 
16-18 However, little is known about the effects 
of overweight and obesity on these angles. 
With the global increase in obesity and rising incidence 
of MSDs, particularly LBP, there is a need to determine 
the effects that increased loading of the lumbosacral region 
caused by overweight and obesity may have on the lum-
bosacral angles. The aim of this study was to evaluate the 
effects of BMI and waist-hip ratio (WHR) on lumbosacral 
angles. BMI and WHR are indices of overweight and 
obesity. 
19 Although BMI assesses general obesity, WHR 
measures central (truncal) obesity. This relationship may 
further elucidate the casual link between obesity and LBP. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>The study was a prospective, cross-sectional study over 
a 1-year period. The test group comprised 174 subjects 
(66 obese, 108 overweight), whereas the control group com-
prised 126 subjects (124 normal weight and two underweight). 
Their age range was 18-65 years. All the subjects were black 
from the Igbo ethnic group of southeastern Nigeria. Only 
subjects who had attained spinal maturity were enrolled in 
the study. Subjects who had sustained macrotrauma to the 
low back region or who had clinically detectable deformity, 
scoliosis, or kyphosis of the lumbar spine were excluded. 
Pregnant women and subjects who had had spine surgery or 
instrumentation were not a part of the study. 
The University of Nigeria Teaching Hospital research 
and ethics committee approved the study protocol. All the 
subjects provided written informed consent to participate in 
the study. The demographic profile of the subjects and certain 
anthropometric measurements were documented using a data 
entry form. The data collected included age, sex, occupation, </p>

<p>weight, height, waist circumference (WC), hip circumstance 
(HC), BMI, and WHR. X-ray imaging of the lumbosacral 
vertebrae of the subjects was done in the supine position. 
Height was measured using a stadiometer, and weight was 
measured with a weighing scale after removal of shoes, with 
light clothing. WC was measured on unclothed abdomen at a 
point midway between the subcostal margin and the iliac crest, 
in standing position. 
20 HC was measured over light clothing at 
the widest diameter of the hip across the greater trochanters. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>BMI was computed as weight (kg)/height (m) 
2 . 
Subsequently, BMI was classified into five categories: 
underweight #18.5 kg/m 
2 ; normal =18.5-24.9 kg/m 
2 ; 
overweight =25-29.9 kg/m 
2 ; obesity $30 kg/m 
2 ; morbid 
obesity .40 kg/m 
2 in accordance with the international clas-
sification system of the World Health Organization. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>WHR is the ratio of WC to HC and is used to assess 
central (truncal) obesity. Central obesity is defined as WHR 
above 0.90 for males and above 0.85 for females. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>The lateral projections of the lumbosacral spine 
ra diographs were evaluated. The criteria for normality of 
the radiographs were as follows: 
1. Presence of five lumbar and five sacral vertebrae 
2. Progressive increase in vertebral height from L 1 to L 5 
3. Preservation of lumbar lordosis 
4. Posterior margins of the lumbar vertebral bodies form a 
smooth curved line 
5. Intervertebral disc spaces increase in thickness from 
L 1 to L 5 
6. No radiographic evidence of congenital abnormality or 
disease. 
The lumbosacral angles measured using an x-ray viewing 
box and a transparent goniometer included the following: 
1. LSA: the angle between the sacral base and the horizontal 
plane (Figure 1A) 
2. SIA: the angle between a vertical plane and a tangential 
line to the posterior border of S I vertebra (Figure 1B) 
3. LSDA: the angle formed by the intersection of two lines 
drawn through the inferior end plate of L 5 and the superior 
end plate of S 1 (Figure 1C) 
4. LLA: the angle formed by the intersection of two perpen-
diculars to lines drawn through the superior end plate of 
L 1 and the inferior end plate of L 5 (Figure 1D). 
Statistical analysis was done using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 17.0</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc., Chicago IL, USA</rs>). Prior to analysis, we verified 
the normality of continuous variables distributions and tested 
the homogeneity of their variances with the Levene's test. 
Continuous variables were expressed as mean and standard 
deviation. Comparison of means of both sets of data was done </p>

<p>Patient Preference and Adherence 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>293 </p>

<p>impact of obesity and being overweight on the musculoskeletal system </p>

<p>using the Student's t-test for independent samples. Statistical 
significance was set at P-value ,0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The data of the 300 subjects who met the inclusion criteria 
were analyzed. The mean age of the test group was 
46.5±13.6 years, whereas that of the control group was 
48±12 years. The age distribution of the subjects is shown 
in Table 1. There were 84 (48.3%) male and 90 (51.7%) 
female subjects in the test group. In the control group, there 
were 60 (47.6%) male and 66 (52.4%) female subjects. The 
distribution of the subjects by BMI is shown in Table 2. 
A total of 130 (43.3%) subjects had a WHR of ,0.90, 
140 (46.7%) subjects had a WHR of 0.90-0.95, and 30 (10%) 
subjects had a WHR of 0.96-1.0 (Table 3). In total, 56 (35.9%) 
of the female subjects had a WHR of ,0.90, and 100 (64.1%) 
had a WHR of .0.90. While 74 (51.4%) male subjects had 
a WHR ,0.90, 70 (48.6%) had a WHR .0.90. 
The mean LSA of the test group was 39.2°±9.2° and that 
of the control group was 34.5°±8.9°; the difference was statis-
tically significant (P=0.001). The mean LLA of the test group 
was 42.8°±11.2° and that of the control group was 37.2°±9.8° 
(P=0.001). The mean SIA of the test group was 40.4°±8.2° 
and that of the control group was 36.3°±7.5° (P=0.001). 
The mean SIA of the male subjects was 36.6°±8.3° and that of 
the female subjects was 39.8°±9.3°. The difference among the 
sexes was statistically significant in both the groups (P=0.03). </p>

<p>The mean LSDA of the test group was 15.0°±3.4° and that of 
the control group was 13.5°±4.5° (P=0.01). Table 4 shows the 
distribution of BMI of subjects by sex and the comparison of 
means of the lumbosacral angles based on BMI. 
A significant correlation was noted between BMI and 
all the lumbosacral angles in both males and females: LSA 
(P=0.001), LLA (P=0.001), SIA (P=0.001), and LSDA 
(P=0.03). There was also a positive relationship between 
WHR and LSA (P=0.012), LLA (P=0.009), SIA (P=0.02), 
and LSDA (P=0.01) in both the sexes. Table 5 shows the 
distribution of WHR of subjects by sex and the comparison 
of the means of the lumbosacral angles based on WHR. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The clinical significance of lumbosacral angles lies majorly 
in their association with LBP, 
14,15,18 design of spinal implants 
and instrumentations, 
22 and spine surgery. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>We noted a positive association between LSA and BMI 
(P=0.001). WHR and LSA also had a significant correlation 
in both the groups (P=0.001). The subjects with increased 
BMI and WHR had significantly higher LSA than the subjects 
with normal BMI and WHR. Braunaugh et al 
24 also noted 
significant correlation among BMI, WHR, and LSA. In 
subjects with increased BMI, particularly those with truncal 
obesity, the weight of the trunk may displace the base of the 
sacrum anteriorly, thus increasing LSA. Thus, overweight </p>

<p>Figure 1 Measurement of geometric angles of the lumbosacral spine. 
Notes: lumbosacral angle (A). sacral inclination angle (B). lumbosacral disc angle (C). lumbar lordosis angle (D). </p>

<p>Table 1 Frequency distribution of subjects by age groups </p>

<p>Age groups (years) 
Frequency 
Percentage </p>

<p>15-24 
16 
5.3 
25-34 
41 
13.7 
35-44 
64 
21.3 
45-54 
68 
22.7 
55-64 
111 
37.0 
Total 
300 
100 </p>

<p>Table 2 Distribution of subjects by BMi </p>

<p>BMI 
Frequency 
Percentage </p>

<p>Underweight 
2 
0.7 
normal 
124 
41.3 
Overweight 
108 
36.0 
Obese 
66 
22 
Total 
300 
100 </p>

<p>Notes: ,18.5 kg/m 
2 , underweight; 18.5-24.9 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, normal; 25-29.9 kg/m 
2 , 
overweight; .30 kg/m 
2 , obese; .40 kg/m 
2 , morbid obesity. 
Abbreviation: BMi, body mass index. </p>

<p>Patient Preference and Adherence 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>294 </p>

<p>Onyemaechi et al </p>

<p>and obesity seem to induce an increase in anterior pelvic tilt. 
The increased anterior pelvic tilt induces a greater flexion of 
the sacroiliac joints, and therefore a higher torque on L 5 -S 1 
joints and discs. This possibly increases shear forces at this 
level and overloads the disc, thus increasing the risk of disc 
degeneration. 
25 Therefore, increased LSA as seen in obese 
and overweight individuals may increase the risk of LBP. 
We observed higher LLAs in obese and overweight 
subjects. This may be due to increased mechanical loading 
of the lumbar spine with consequent exaggeration of LLA. 
This is similar to the postural changes observed in pregnant 
women. 
26 The consequent biomechanical changes may 
produce higher compressive force or increase shear on the 
lumbar spine structures, resulting in an increased incidence 
of mechanical LBP in individuals with raised BMI and 
truncal obesity. Many studies have already reported positive 
associations between increased lumbar lordosis and LBP. </p>

<p>15,27 </p>

<p>These effects of increased BMI and WHR on LLA may 
increase the incidence of LBP among overweight and obese 
individuals. There was no significant variation in the mean 
lordosis angles between the male and female subjects in this 
study. This is in contrast with studies that reported greater 
lordotic angles in women. 
18,28 This contrast may be due to 
racial differences in the study populations. 
The overweight and obese subjects had significantly 
higher SIA than the controls. The female subjects also had 
a higher SIA (P=0.03). These are similar to the studies by 
Fernand and Fox, 
13 Caglayan et al, 
15 and Evcik and Yucel. </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>Caglayan et al 
15 also observed that SIA and BMI were higher </p>

<p>in female patients with LBP in a control study. The position 
of the sacrum in the pelvis affects the pelvic inlet and outlet 
diameters. Therefore, a more inclined sacrum creates a larger 
pelvic outlet diameter in females, which is important during 
childbirth. This may explain the higher SIA in females. Axial 
loading of the sacral base in overweight and obese individuals 
may be responsible for the increased sacral inclination noted 
in this group. Some studies 
15,29 have reported an association 
between increased SIA and LBP. Evcik and Yucel 
29 reported 
that SIA was larger in patients with chronic LBP, with a 
positive relationship between this angle and maximal range 
of lumbar extension in both males and females. Increased 
SIA has been associated with spondylolisthesis and isthmic 
pathologies. 
29 Consequently, this may cause facet joint prob-
lems and spinal stenosis, resulting in increased incidence of 
LBP among individuals with high BMI. 
Our study showed a significant correlation between 
BMI, WHR, and LSDA. This suggests that individuals with 
increased BMI and WHR have higher LSDA. The increased 
sacral inclination noted in the test group may explain the 
higher LSDA values as the sacral inclination directly affects 
LSDA. An increase in LSDA is associated with an increased 
incidence of facet syndrome in subjects with LBP. </p>

<p>30,31 </p>

<p>LSDA .15° has been reported to increase the compressive 
and shearing forces at L 5 /S 1 facet joint. </p>

<p>30,31 </p>

<p>The facet joints in the lumbar vertebrae are not adapted for 
weight bearing but rather for preventing excessive rotation. 
Therefore, minor biomechanical changes in the lumbosacral 
segment will result in exaggerated shearing and compressive 
forces at the lumbosacral facet joints, giving rise to mechanical 
LBP. 
30 The positive association noted among BMI, WHR, 
and LSDA therefore suggests that overweight and obese 
individuals, particularly those with truncal obesity, may have 
an increased risk of facet syndrome and mechanical LBP. 
A major limitation of the study is that it was conducted 
on only one ethnic group in Nigeria. Large multi-ethnic </p>

<p>Table 3 Distribution of subjects by waist-hip ratio </p>

<p>Waist-hip ratio 
Frequency 
Percentage </p>

<p>,0.90 
130 
43.3 
0.90-0.95 
140 
46.7 
.0.96 
30 
10 
Total 
300 
100 </p>

<p>Table 4 comparison of mean lumbosacral angles based on BMi of subjects </p>

<p>Lumbosacral angles 
Male 
Female </p>

<p>Control group 
BMI (n=60) </p>

<p>Test group 
BMI (n=84) </p>

<p>t 
P-value 
Control group 
BMI (n=66) </p>

<p>Test group 
BMI (n=90) </p>

<p>t 
P-value </p>

<p>Mean ± SD 
Mean ± SD 
Mean ± SD 
Mean ± SD </p>

<p>lsA 
34.5±7.0 
39.5±9.6 
-3.47 
0.001 
34.7±6.7 
40.1±10.1 
-3.59 
0.001 </p>

<p>llA 
37.3±9.5 
41.2±11.9 
-2.14 
0.03 
37.4±8.0 
43.1±12.1 
-3.03 
0.003 </p>

<p>siA 
35.9±8.3 
39.3±12.1 
-2.02 
0.03 
37.1±8.3 
41.9±9.0 
-3.22 
0.001 </p>

<p>lsDA 
13.6±3.3 
15.1±3.1 
-2.32 
0.01 
13.5±3.1 
14.7±3.4 
-2.24 
0.02 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: BMi, body mass index; sD, standard deviation; lsA, lumbosacral angle; llA, lumbar lordosis angle; siA, sacral inclination angle; lsDA, lumbosacral 
disc angle. </p>

<p>Patient Preference and Adherence 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>295 </p>

<p>impact of obesity and being overweight on the musculoskeletal system </p>

<p>and multi-racial studies will be needed to validate our 
findings. The sample size in this study was sufficient and 
the methodology was scientific; therefore, the results are 
generalizable to other black ethnic groups. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In this study, subjects with raised BMI and WHR had sig-
nificantly higher mean LSA, LLA, SIA, and LSDA. These 
angles also increased as the BMI and WHR of the subjects 
increased. The increase in lumbosacral angles seen in these 
individuals may result in biomechanical changes in the 
lumbosacral spine, which may increase the incidence of LBP. 
Our study supports the reports that overweight and obesity 
are potential risk factors for LBP. The causal link between 
obesity and LBP has been further elucidated by this study. 
We recommend measurements of lumbosacral angles in 
clinical evaluation of patients with LBP. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Table 5 comparison of mean lumbosacral angles based on Whr of subjects </p>

<p>Lumbosacral angles 
Male 
Female </p>

<p>WHR ,0.90 
(n=74) </p>

<p>WHR .0.90 
(n=70) </p>

<p>t 
P-value 
WHR ,0.90 
(n=56) </p>

<p>WHR .0.90 
(n=100) </p>

<p>t 
P-value </p>

<p>Mean ± SD 
Mean ± SD 
Mean ± SD 
Mean ± SD </p>

<p>lsA 
35.5±6.5 
39.0±10.0 
-2.21 
0.03 
37.8±9.6 
41.6±10.2 
-2.35 
0.003 
llA 
37.5±8.7 
41.8±11.0 
-2.36 
0.02 
38.5±10.1 
43.4±12.5 
-3.12 
0.001 
siA 
37.6±8.1 
40.8±8.7 
-2.13 
0.04 
38.8±8.4 
43.1±9.3 
-2.81 
0.002 
lsDA 
13.7±2.8 
15.3±3.1 
-2.86 
0.005 
13.7±2.7 
15.2±3.1 
-2.72 
0.005 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: Whr, waist-hip ratio; sD, standard deviation; lsA, lumbosacral angle; llA, lumbar lordosis angle; siA, sacral inclination angle; lsDA, lumbosacral disc 
angle. </p>

<p>Patient Preference and Adherence </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/patient-preference-and-adherence-journal </p>

<p>Patient Preference and Adherence is an international, peer-reviewed, 
open access journal that focuses on the growing importance of patient 
preference and adherence throughout the therapeutic continuum. Patient 
satisfaction, acceptability, quality of life, compliance, persistence and their 
role in developing new therapeutic modalities and compounds to optimize </p>

<p>clinical outcomes for existing disease states are major areas of interest for 
the journal. This journal has been accepted for indexing on PubMed Central. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes a very 
quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www. 
dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Patient Preference and Adherence 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>