<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4720104" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Purpose 
We previously reported that forkhead transcription factors of the O class 1 (FOXO1) expres-
sion in gastric cancer (GC) was associated with angiogenesis-related molecules. However, 
there is little experimental evidence for the direct role of FOXO1 in GC. In the present study, 
we investigated the effect of FOXO1 on the tumorigenesis and angiogenesis in GC and its 
relationship with SIRT1. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
Stable GC cell lines (SNU-638 and SNU-601) infected with a lentivirus containing FOXO1 
shRNA were established for animal studies as well as cell culture experiments. We used 
xenograft tumors in nude mice to evaluate the effect of FOXO1 silencing on tumor growth 
and angiogenesis. In addition, we examined the association between FOXO1 and SIRT1 by 
immunohistochemical tissue array analysis of 471 human GC specimens and Western blot 
analysis of xenografted tumor tissues. </p>

<p>Results 
In cell culture, FOXO1 silencing enhanced hypoxia inducible factor-1! (HIF-1!) expression 
and GC cell growth under hypoxic conditions, but not under normoxic conditions. The 
xenograft study showed that FOXO1 downregulation enhanced tumor growth, microvessel 
areas, HIF-1! activation and vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) expression. In addi-
tion, inactivated FOXO1 expression was associated with SIRT1 expression in human GC 
tissues and xenograft tumor tissues. </p>

<p>Conclusion 
Our results indicate that FOXO1 inhibits GC growth and angiogenesis under hypoxic condi-
tions via inactivation of the HIF-1!-VEGF pathway, possibly in association with SIRT1. Thus, 
development of treatment modalities aiming at this pathway might be useful for treating 
GC. </p>

<p>The mammalian forkhead transcription factors of the 
O class (FOXOs) have four members: FOXO1, FOXO3, 
FOXO4, and FOXO6. FOXO1 and FOXO3 are expressed in 
nearly all tissues [1]. When FOXOs are phosphorylated, they 
are exported from the nucleus and do not exhibit transcrip-
tional activity [2]. In recent years, FOXOs have caught much 
research attention for their broad roles in physiological 
process, including cell cycle arrest, apoptosis, angiogenesis, 
stress resistance, energy metabolism, and stem cell differen-
tiation [3]. Dysregulation of FOXOs results in disease, includ-
ing cancer. Inactivation of the FOXO1 occurs in many types 
of human cancer, including endometrial cancer, breast can-
cer, ovarian cancer, prostate cancer, rhabdomyosarcoma, 
hemangiosarcoma and gastric cancer (GC) [1]. 
Sirtuins are NAD 
+ -dependent deacetylase enzymes in 
mammals and consist of SIRT1-7. They are localized in 
different cellular compartments and are capable of many 
catalytic activities [4]. Among them, SIRT1 is the most thor-
oughly studied and is expressed in the brain, heart, liver, 
pancreas, skeletal muscle, spleen, and adipose tissues [5]. 
SIRT1 regulates physiological events that include oxidative 
stress, metabolism, cellular proliferation, and genomic sta-
bility via deacetylation of histone and non-histone proteins 
[5]. Furthermore, SIRT1 targets many transcription factors, 
including p53, FOXO, E2F1 and nuclear factor kB, and 
consequently is involved in diverse functions [6]. 
Currently GC is the second most frequent cause of cancer-
related death [7]. The incidence of GC continues to rise 
despite effective treatment that increases the survival of GC 
patients. However, the prognosis remains poor [8]. Although 
several pathways are suggested as a mechanism of GC 
angiogenesis, the underlying molecular mechanism remains 
largely unknown. We previously reported that FOXO1 inac-
tivation was commonly found in surgically obtained GC 
specimens, associated with angiogenesis-related molecules 
[1]. 
SIRT1 controls the nuclear shuttling and transcriptional 
activity of forkhead transcription factors and regulates FOXO 
activity either positively or negatively depending on the 
target gene or cell type [9]. Though the association between 
FOXO1 and SIRT1 was gradually elucidated in various 
disease conditions, there has not been any study of that 
association in GC, let alone angiogenesis. 
Here, we extended our previous study and further inves-
tigated the direct role of FOXO1 in GC angiogenesis. FOXO1 
expression was suppressed by RNA interference and the 
effects of FOXO1 silencing on the GC growth and angiogen-
esis were assessed in cell culture experiments and a nude 
mouse model of subcutaneous xenografts. In addition, we </p>

<p>assessed the relationship between FOXO1 and SIRT1 using 
human GC tissue array and xenograft tumors. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>1. Cell cultures </p>

<p>Five well-characterized human GC cell lines (SNU-638, 
SNU-601, SNU-216, SNU-484, and SNU-668) were purchased 
from the Korean Cell Line Bank (Seoul, Korea). Cells were 
maintained in RPMI 1640 medium (Life Technologies, Grand 
Island, NY) containing 10% fetal bovine serum, incubated in 
5% CO2, and either 20% (normoxic) or 1% (hypoxic) O2 
atmosphere at 37°C. </p>

<p>2. Western blot analysis </p>

<p>Western blot analysis was performed as we described 
previously [10]. Cell lysates in sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) 
lysis buffer (125 mM Tris-HCl [pH 6.8], 4% SDS, 0.004% 
bromophenol blue, and 20% glycerol) were separated on 10% 
SDS-polyacrylamide gel and electrophoretically transferred 
to PVDF membranes (Millipore Co., Billerica, MA) blocked 
with 5% non-fat dry milk in phosphate buffered saline-
Tween-20 (0.1%, vol/vol) for 1 hour. The membranes were 
then incubated with a primary antibody against FOXO1 
(1:1,000, C29H4, Cell Signaling Technology, Beverly, MA), 
hypoxia inducible factor-1! (HIF-1!; 1:500, H1!67, BD 
Biosciences, San Jose, CA), vascular endothelial growth 
factor (VEGF; 1:1,000, C1, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa 
Cruz, CA), SIRT1 (1:1,000, H300, Santa Cruz Biotechnology), 
or "-actin (1:1,000, C4, Santa Cruz Biotechnology). Horserad-
ish peroxidase-conjugated anti-rabbit IgG (1:2,000, Santa 
Cruz Biotechnology) or anti-mouse IgG (1:2,000, Santa Cruz 
Biotechnology) was used as a secondary antibody. Enhanced 
chemiluminescence (Amersham, Arlington Heights, IL) was 
used to detect the immunoreactive proteins. Equal protein 
loading was confirmed by "-actin. </p>

<p>3. Lentivirus-mediated short hairpin RNA silencing of 
FOXO1 </p>

<p>Lentiviral particles containing FOXO1 short hairpin RNA 
(shRNA) or non-targeting shRNA, control shRNA, were 
purchased (Sigma, St. Louis, MO). The sequence of FOXO1 
shRNA was 5#-CCGGGCCTGTTAT CAATCTGCTAAACTC 
GAGTTTAGCAGATTGAT AACAGGCTTTTTG-3#. The 
control shRNA particles contain four base pair mismatches 
within the short hairpin sequence to any known human or </p>

<p>Sue Youn Kim, FOXO1 in Gastric Cancer Angiogenesis </p>

<p>VOLUME 48 NUMBER 1 JANUARY 2016 347 </p>

<p>mouse gene. Viral infection was introduced by incubating 
GC cells in the culture medium containing lentiviral particles 
for 12 hours in the presence of 5 µg/mL Polybrene (Santa 
Cruz Biotechnology). Pooled puromycin (2 µg/mL)-resistant 
cells were used for further analysis. </p>

<p>4. Luciferase reporter assay </p>

<p>To determine FOXO1 nuclear DNA-binding activity, 
luciferase reporter assay was used as previously described 
with slight modifications [10,11]. Two oligonucleotides 
(GCAAAACAAACTTATTTTGAAGCAAAACAAACT 
TATTTTGA AGCAAAACA AACT TATTTTGAA and TTCA 
AAATAAGTTTGTTTTGCTTCAAAATAAGTTTGTTTTG 
TT CAAAATAAGTTTGTTTTGC) were annealed and lig-
ated into the pGL4.27-Promoter vector (Promega, Madison, 
WI) to create 3XIRS-luciferase (Cosmo GENETECH, Seoul, 
Korea). This construct has three tandem repeats of a FOXO1 
binding element, the insulin-responsive sequence (IRS), 
inserted upstream of the luciferase reporter gene. It is widely 
used as an indicator of FOXO1 transcriptional activity. GC 
cells were cotransfected transiently with 0.4 µg 3XIRS-
luciferase vector and 0.4 µg pSV-"-galactosidase vector 
(Promega), an internal control, using Lipofectamine Plus 
(Life Technologies). Twenty-four hours after transfection, 
assays for luciferase and "-galactosidase were carried out 
using a Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay System (Promega). 
FOXO1 luciferase activity was measured on an AutoLumat 
LB 9505c luminometer (Berthold Analytical Instruments, 
Nashua, Germany) and was normalized by "-galactosidase 
activity. </p>

<p>5. Assessment of cell viability </p>

<p>SNU-638 (2.5!10 
4 cells) and SNU-601 cells (2.5!10 
4 cells) 
were seeded into each well of 24-well plates and were 
allowed to grow for 0 to 24 hours. Cell numbers were meas-
ured indirectly using the method reported by Kim et al. [12]. 
Cells were stained with 0.2% crystal violet aqueous solution 
in 20% methanol for 10 minutes, dissolved in 10% SDS, trans-
ferred into 96-well plates, and the absorbance was measured 
at 570 nm using an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay 
reader (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). </p>

<p>6. Mouse xenograft model </p>

<p>All animal procedures were performed in accordance with 
the procedures described in the Seoul National University 
Laboratory Animal Maintenance Manual (approval No. 
SNU-120412-5). Six-week-old male nude mice (BALB/cSlc-
n/n) were purchased from SLC Inc. (Hamamatsu, Shizuoka, 
Japan) and maintained under specific pathogen-free condi-</p>

<p>tions. For subcutaneous implantation, tumors were estab-
lished by injecting SNU-638 GC cells expressing either con-
trol shRNA or FOXO1 shRNA at the density of 5!10 
6 cells in 
100 µL of Matrigel (R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN) subcu-
taneously into the left flank of each mouse. Mice were 
divided into two groups by FOXO1 expression in GC cells: 
control shRNA or FOXO1 shRNA. Tumor volumes were 
measured every two days using a caliper, and were calcu-
lated by the equation V (mm 
3 )=(length!width!height)! 
("/6). Animals were sacrificed 48 days after cell implanta-
tion, and tumor xenografts were removed and prepared for 
immunohistochemistry or Western blot analysis. </p>

<p>7. Patients and tissue array methods </p>

<p>Four hundred and seventy-one surgically resected human 
GC specimens were obtained from the Department of Pathol-
ogy, Seoul National University College of Medicine from 
January 2 to December 29, 2006. Nine paraffin tissue array 
blocks were prepared as previously described [13]. This 
protocol was reviewed and approved by the Institutional 
Review Board of the Seoul National University (approval 
No. C-1006-035-320). </p>

<p>8. Tumor histology and immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Tissue specimens from clinical GC samples and xenograft 
tumors derived from GC cells were fixed with 10% neutral-
buffered formalin, and 4-µm paraffin sections were prepared. 
After rehydration, sections were stained with hematoxylin 
and eosin for histologic assessment, or were immunostained 
after antigen retrieval using a Bond-max automated immun-
ostainer (Leica Microsystems, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK). 
The primary antibodies used were against FOXO1 (1:40, 
C29H4, Cell Signaling Technology), phospho-FOXO1 </p>

<p>Ser256 </p>

<p>(pFOXO1; 1:60, Cell Signaling Technology), CD31 (1:100, 
M20, Santa Cruz Biotechnology), HIF-1! (1:50, provided by 
Dr. Jong-Wan Park at Seoul National University), VEGF 
(1:200, C1, Santa Cruz Biotechnology), and SIRT1 (1:100, 
H300, Santa Cruz Biotechnology). Antibody binding was 
detected with the Bond Polymer Refine Detection Kit (Leica 
Microsystems). All immunostained sections were lightly 
counterstained with Mayer's hematoxylin. Throughout the 
above analysis, negative controls were prepared by omitting 
the primary antibody. The results of immunostaining were 
evaluated by two pathologists (Y.K. and J.-S.P.), who were 
blinded to the origin of the samples. For statistical analysis, 
the results of immunostaining for proteins were considered 
positive if immunoreactivity was seen in # 10% (cytoplasmic 
pFOXO1 and nuclear SIRT1) or # 5% (nuclear HIF-1!) of the 
neoplastic cells. </p>

<p>Cancer Res Treat. 2016;48(1):345-354 </p>



<p>9. Quantification of microvessel areas </p>

<p>Microvessel areas (MVAs) in subcutaneous xenograft 
tumors were determined by light microscopy/optical image 
analysis after immunostaining xenograft tumor sections with 
anti-CD31 as described previously [10]. The three most 
highly vascularized areas in areas of tumors near the tumor-
normal tissue interface were selected. Photographs of CD31-
immunopositive vessels in tumor sections were taken under 
a light microscope, and the cross-sectional areas of CD31-
immunopositive structures (i.e., microvessel areas) were 
quantified by capturing images, converting them to grey 
scale, and analyzing CD31-stained areas using <rs type="software">NIH Image 
Analysis</rs> software after setting one consistent intensity 
threshold for all slides. CD31-positive areas were expressed 
as pixels squared per high-power field and were measured 
for all tumors. </p>

<p>10. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>For cell culture and animal experiments, data were ana-
lyzed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> software for Windows 7 (ver. 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">4</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>, San Diego, CA). A two-tailed 
Student's t test was used to rule out the role of chance in the </p>

<p>results. For tissue array analysis, statistical analyses were 
conducted using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">ver. 19.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">IBM Co.</rs>., Chicago, IL), and 
the chi-squared test was used to determine the relationship 
between the expressions of pFOXO1 </p>

<p>Ser256 </p>

<p>, SIRT1, and HIF-1!. 
Results were expressed as mean value±standard deviation. 
Null hypotheses of no difference were rejected if p-values 
were less than 0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>1. FOXO1 shRNA expression effectively inhibited FOXO1 
expression and transcriptional activity in GC cell lines </p>

<p>To investigate the molecular effects of FOXO1 in GC, we 
initially examined the expression level of FOXO1 in GC cell 
lines. The protein contents of FOXO1 varied in five different 
cell lines (Fig. 1A). To observe the effect of FOXO1 silencing 
in the GC cell, SNU-638 and 601 cell lines with high levels of 
FOXO1 expression were selected, and FOXO1 expression 
was suppressed using RNA interference. Western blot analy-
sis (Fig. 1B) and luciferase reporter assay (Fig. 1C) verified </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>638 601 216 484 668 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>shCtrl 
shFOXO1 
shCtrl 
shFOXO1 
shCtrl 
shFOXO1 
shCtrl 
shFOXO1 </p>

<p>FOXO1 </p>

<p>β-Actin 
FOXO1 </p>

<p>β-Actin </p>

<p>SNU cell lines </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>(p3XIRS) Iuciferase report assay </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>s h C t r l s h F O X O 1 </p>

<p>SNU-638 </p>

<p>s h C t r l s h F O X O 1 </p>

<p>SNU-601 </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>SNU-638 </p>

<p>H 
N 
H </p>

<p>SNU-601 </p>

<p>Luciferase activity </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>s h C t r l 
s h F O X O 1 
Luciferase activity </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>s h C t r l 
s h F O X O 1 </p>

<p>SNU-638 
SNU-601 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>FOXO1 
HIF-1α 
β-Actin </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Effect of forkhead transcription factors of the O class 1 (FOXO1) expression on hypoxia inducible factor-1! (HIF-1!) expression 
in cultured gastric cancer (GC) cells. (A) Western blot analysis shows that the protein contents of FOXO1 varied in GC cell lines. (B) 
FOXO1 expression in GC cells (SNU-638 and SNU-601) was silenced by infection with lentiviral particles containing non-targeting 
shRNA (shCtrl) or FOXO1 shRNA (shFOXO1). The protein expression of FOXO1 was determined by Western blot analysis. (C) 
FOXO1 transcriptional activity was determined by luciferase reporter assay. *p &lt; 0.05, compared to shCtrl cells. (D) Protein expressions 
of FOXO1 and HIF-1! were measured by Western blot analysis after exposure to normoxia (N) or hypoxia (H) for 8 hours. </p>

<p>Sue Youn Kim, FOXO1 in Gastric Cancer Angiogenesis </p>

<p>VOLUME 48 NUMBER 1 JANUARY 2016 349 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 
Hypoxia (hr) </p>

<p>24 
48 
72 </p>

<p>p=0.0015 
p=0.0099 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>638 </p>

<p>601 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Cell viability (%) 
Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>1,400 </p>

<p>2,100 </p>

<p>2,800 </p>

<p>3,500 </p>

<p>0 
Normoxia (hr) </p>

<p>24 
48 
72 </p>

<p>638 </p>

<p>601 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>Hypoxia (hr) </p>

<p>0 
24 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>shCtrl 
shFOXO1 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>Normoxia (hr) </p>

<p>SNU-638 </p>

<p>0 
24 </p>

<p>shCtrl 
shFOXO1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>Hypoxia (hr) </p>

<p>0 
24 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>shCtrl 
shFOXO1 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>Normoxia (hr) </p>

<p>SNU-601 </p>

<p>0 
24 </p>

<p>shCtrl 
shFOXO1 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Cell viability of gastric cancer (GC) cell lines (SNU-638 and SNU-601) was evaluated by crystal violet assay. (A) Two GC cell 
lines were cultured for 72 hours and cell growth rates were compared between the cell lines. *p &lt; 0.05, compared to SNU-601 cells. 
(B, C) GC cells expressing forkhead transcription factors of the O class 1 (FOX1) shRNA (shFOXO1) show higher cell viability at 24 
hours of hypoxia exposure than those expressing control shRNA (shCtrl). *p &lt; 0.05, compared to shCtrl cells. </p>



<p>Cancer Res Treat. 2016;48(1):345-354 </p>

<p>that transfection of FOXO1 shRNA effectively inhibited 
FOXO1 expression and its transcriptional activity in both cell 
lines. </p>

<p>2. FOXO1 silencing increased the protein expression of 
HIF-1! in GC cells under hypoxic conditions, but not 
under normoxic conditions </p>

<p>HIF-1!, which regulates many genes involved in adapting 
to a hypoxic environment, is important in promoting gastric 
tumor growth and angiogenesis [14]. Therefore, we per-
formed cell culture experiments using GC cell lines SNU-638 
and SNU-601 to examine the direct relationship between the </p>

<p>expressions of FOXO1 and HIF-1!. GC cells expressing 
control shRNA or FOXO1 shRNA were cultured under 
normoxic or hypoxic conditions. By Western blot, FOXO1 
down-regulation corresponded with increased HIF-1! 
protein expression under hypoxic conditions, but not under 
normoxic conditions, in both cell lines (Fig. 1D). </p>

<p>3. FOXO1 silencing increased GC cell viability under 
hypoxic conditions </p>

<p>Fig. 1A shows that FOXO1 expression was higher in 
SNU-601 cells than in SNU-638 cells. In contrast, we found 
that cell growth rate was higher in SNU-638 cells than in </p>

<p>shCtrl shFOXO1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>1,000 </p>

<p>1,500 </p>

<p>2,000 </p>

<p>s h C t r l 
s h F O X O 1 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Tumor weight (mg) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>shCtrl shFOXO1 </p>

<p>FOXO1 </p>

<p>CD31 </p>

<p>HIF-1α </p>

<p>VEGF </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>s h C t r l 
s h F O X O 1 </p>

<p>B 
C </p>

<p>Mean CD31-positive 
area (10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>pixels </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>shCtrl shFOXO1 </p>

<p>FOXO1 </p>

<p>HIF-1α </p>

<p>VEGF </p>

<p>SIRT1 </p>

<p>β-Actin </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Forkhead transcription factors of the O class 1 (FOXO1) shRNA (shFOXO1) promotes tumor growth and angiogenesis in sub-
cutaneous gastric cancer (GC) xenografts. (A) SNU-638 cells expressing control shRNA (shCtrl) or shFOXO1 were subcutaneously 
injected into the left flanks of nude mice. Representative photos of mice were taken after killing at day 48 (left). Tumors were harvested, 
then weighed (right) (n=5 per group). *p &lt; 0.05, compared to shCtrl tumors. The arrows indicate xenografted tumors in mouse flanks. 
(B) Tissue sections were obtained from the xenograft tumors and immunostained for FOXO1, CD31, hypoxia inducible factor-1! 
(HIF-1!) and vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) (left). Microvessel area were quantified by measuring areas of blood vessels 
immunostained for CD31 (right). *p &lt; 0.05, compared to shCtrl cells. (C) Protein expressions of FOXO1, HIF-1!-VEGF, and SIRT1 in 
xenograft tumors were measured by Western blot analysis. </p>

<p>Sue Youn Kim, FOXO1 in Gastric Cancer Angiogenesis </p>

<p>VOLUME 48 NUMBER 1 JANUARY 2016 351 </p>

<p>SNU-601 cells, which became more evident under hypoxic 
conditions (Fig. 2A). To confirm the growth-inhibitory role 
of FOXO1, we compared the viability of GC cell lines under 
normoxic and hypoxic conditions. At 24 hours of hypoxic 
exposure, in both GC cell lines FOXO1 knockdown increased 
cell viability under hypoxic conditions, but not under 
normoxic conditions (p &lt; 0.05) (Fig. 2B and C). These data 
suggest that the effect of FOXO1 on GC cell growth needs a 
hypoxic environment. </p>

<p>4. FOXO1 silencing increased tumor growth, MVA and the 
expression of HIF-1!, VEGF, and SIRT1 proteins in a nude 
mouse model of subcutaneous GC xenografts </p>

<p>Fig. 2A shows that SNU-638 cells grow faster than 
SNU-601 cells. Thus, to examine the role of FOXO1 in GC 
growth, we injected SNU-638 cells rather than SNU-601 cells 
into nude mice. Stable SNU-638 cells expressing non-target-
ing (control) or FOXO1-targeting shRNA were used. We 
found that tumors were successfully formed in all mice. The </p>

<p>tumor weights were markedly higher in mice injected with 
FOXO1 shRNA expressing cells than those injected with 
control shRNA expressing cells (p &lt; 0.05) (Fig. 3A). 
Next, tumor tissues were removed and prepared for 
immunohistochemistry (Fig. 3B, left) and Western blot analy-
sis (Fig. 3C). FOXO1 shRNA tumors showed much lower 
FOXO1 protein expression than the control shRNA tumors 
(Fig. 3B, top row), verifying the direct inhibitory role of 
FOXO1 in tumor growth. Angiogenesis in xenografted 
tumors was assessed using immunohistochemistry for CD31, 
a specific marker of vascular endothelial cells. CD31 
immunoreactivity increased in FOXO1 shRNA tumors 
compared to control shRNA tumors (Fig. 3B, second row). 
Optical image analyses showed that the CD31-positive MVA 
was noticeably larger in FOXO1 shRNA tumors (mean, 
18.56!10 
3 pixels 
2 ) than in control shRNA tumors (mean, 
3.25!10 
3 pixels 
2 ) (Fig. 3B, right). Thus, FOXO1 silencing 
increased MVA in GC xenografts. In addition, FOXO1 
shRNA increased the expression of HIF-1! and VEGF, both 
of which promote GC tumor growth [15], angiogenesis [15] </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Representative immunohistochemical findings in human gastric cancer (GC) tissue specimens. (A) GC cells showing 
cytoplasmic phospho-FOXO1 
Ser256 (pFOXO1) expression with or without nuclear staining. (B) GC cells showing nuclear SIRT1 
expression. (C) GC cells showing nuclear hypoxia inducible factor-1! (HIF-1!) expression with or without cytoplasmic stain-
ing. (D) GC cells without cytoplasmic pFOXO1 expression. (E) GC cells without nuclear SIRT1 expression. (F) GC cells with-
out nuclear HIF-1! expression (A-F, !400). </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>D 
E 
F </p>

<p>Cancer Res Treat. 2016;48(1):345-354 </p>



<p>and metastasis [16] (Fig. 3B, third and fourth rows; Fig. 3C, 
second and third rows). These results strongly suggest that 
FOXO1 functions to inhibit tumor growth through negative 
regulation of tumor angiogenesis mediated by the HIF-1!-
VEGF pathway. 
In addition, the association found between FOXO1 and 
SIRT1 was observed in xenografted tumors. Western blot 
analysis showed that FOXO1 shRNA-tumors showed higher 
SIRT1 expression than control shRNA-tumors (Fig. 3C). </p>

<p>5. FOXO1 shRNA knock-down in GC cells up-regulated 
the expression of SIRT1 </p>

<p>SIRT1 increases gastric tumor growth and angiogenesis 
[17]. Thus, we examined the relationship between the expres-
sions of FOXO1 and SIRT1. In immunohistochemical tissue 
array analysis of human GC samples, pFOXO1 (Fig. 4A and 
D), SIRT1 (Fig. 4B and E), and HIF-1! (Fig. 4C and F) were 
expressed in both the nuclei and cytoplasm of tumor cells. 
Regarding pFOXO1 expression, cells showing distinct cyto-
plasmic staining, with or without the presence of nuclear 
staining, were considered to express the inactive form of 
FOXO1 constitutively. With SIRT1 and HIF-1! expressions, 
nuclear staining was considered to indicate activation of 
these two molecules. We analyzed the association between 
FOXO1 inactivation (pFOXO1 expression) and the activa-
tions of SIRT1 and HIF-1! in 471 human GC specimens. 
Table 1 shows that cytoplasmic pFOXO1 expression was 
found in 359 (77%), nuclear SIRT1 expression in 178 (38%) 
and nuclear HIF-1! expression in 108 of the 471 (23%) of 
human GC cases. This result shows positive associations 
between pFOXO1 and SIRT1 (p &lt; 0.001) and HIF-1! 
(p &lt; 0.001). Moreover, a positive association was found 
between SIRT1 and HIF-1! (p &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Though important tumorigenic processes such as cell 
proliferation or anti-apoptosis are often targeted in conven-
tional anticancer treatments, tumor angiogenesis is consid-
ered the most important predictor of overall survival in GC 
[18]. Therefore, it is obvious that finding a potent therapeutic 
target should be preceded by a detailed understanding of the 
mechanisms underlying angiogenesis. However, the mech-
anisms underlying GC angiogenesis are far from understood. 
A major goal of this study was to confirm our previous 
hypothesis that FOXO1 has an anti-angiogenesis effect 
through inhibition on angiogenesis-related molecules. 
Growing evidence shows that FOXOs are significant in 
angiogenesis. FOXOs are involved intimately in endothelial 
cell development and angiogenesis [19]. Several possible 
pathways might explain FOXOs in angiogenesis. In part, 
FOXOs interact with HIF-1 at multiple levels as hypoxia-
induced FOXO-dependent Cited2 expression blocks HIF-1 at 
transcriptional level [20]. In our previous study, FOXO1 was 
negatively related to several angiogenesis-related molecules 
such as HIF-1! and VEGF in 272 surgical samples of GC [1]. 
In the present study, FOXO1 silencing in GC cell lines 
increased HIF-1! expression and cell viability under hypoxic 
conditions. Consistently, animal studies showed that FOXO1 
shRNA-tumors grew faster and developed larger MVA as 
well as higher expressions of HIF-1! and VEGF than control 
shRNA-tumors. Thus, these data confirm the inhibitory role 
of FOXO1 in the tumor growth and angiogenesis in GC. 
SIRT1 acts paradoxically in tumor angiogenesis, both 
inhibiting [6] and activating [21] angiogenesis. Regarding 
GC, an earlier study showed that VEGF silencing down-reg-
ulated the expression of SIRT1 as well as tumor growth in a 
nude mouse model of subcutaneous xenografts [22]. In the 
present study, a positive association was found between the 
nuclear expressions of SIRT1 and HIF-1! by immunohisto-</p>

<p>Table 1. Expression of pFOXO1, SIRT1, and HIF-1! in human GC specimens </p>

<p>Variable 
pFOXO1 
p-value 
SIRT1 
p-value 
Positive 
Negative 
Positive 
Negative </p>

<p>Total 
359 (77) 
108 (23) 
178 (38) 
293 (62) 
SIRT1 
Positive 
152 (86) 
25 (14) 
&lt; 0.001 
-
-
-
Negative 
207 (71) 
83 (29) 
-
-
HIF-1! 
Positive 
100 (93) 
8 (7) 
&lt; 0.001 
68 (64) 
39 (36) 
&lt; 0.001 
Negative 
260 (72) 
101 (28) 
110 (30) 
254 (70) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%). pFOXO1, phospho-FOXO1 </p>

<p>Ser256 </p>

<p>; HIF-1!, hypoxia inducible factor-1!; GC, gastric cell. </p>

<p>Sue Youn Kim, FOXO1 in Gastric Cancer Angiogenesis </p>

<p>VOLUME 48 NUMBER 1 JANUARY 2016 353 </p>

<p>chemical tissue array analysis of 471 human GC specimens, 
suggesting a positive regulatory role of SIRT1 in GC angio-
genesis. 
During oxidative stress, FOXOs translocate to the nucleus 
and interact with SIRT1, resulting in the deacetylation of 
FOXOs. FOXOs may be tightly modulated by SIRT1 during 
tumorigenesis [23,24]. Dependent upon the post-transla-
tional changes on FOXOs, SIRT1 can inhibit FOXO activity 
to protect cells from oxidative stress [23] or increase the 
activity of FOXOs to lead to gene activation [24]. The present 
study showed a positive association between the expression 
of inactive form of FOXO1 and nuclear expression of SIRT1 
in human GC specimens. Furthermore, animal studies 
showed that FOXO1 silencing increased SIRT1 expression in 
GC xenografts. Thus, our data and those from a previous 
study [22] indicate that FOXO1 suppresses GC angiogenesis 
through HIF-1!/SIRT1 pathway. Although the relationships 
between FOXO1 and HIF-1! and that of SIRT1 and HIF-1! 
have been reported [1,6], the FOXO1-SIRT1 pathway that ties 
to regulation of angiogenesis in GC or any type of cancer has 
not been. FOXO1 may suppress tumors through different 
strategies depending on the tumor type. For the first time, 
we report that FOXO1 suppresses angiogenesis through the 
HIF-1! and VEGF and FOXO1-SIRT1 pathway. 
The pursuit of understanding the mechanisms that regu-
late vascular growth in tumors will continue to expand and 
deliver new ideas for therapeutic exploration. Regulation of 
FOXO1-SIRT1 pathway in GC promises great potential for 
investigating the pathogenesis of GC and identifying a novel 
therapeutic target, as well as a useful biomarker. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In conclusion, this study provided an insight into the 
biological behavior of FOXO1 in GC angiogenesis. Since 
FOXO1 is functionally inactivated in a high percentage of 
GCs, inhibition of angiogenesis through restoration of 
FOXO1 expression and subsequent inactivation of HIF-1!, 
VEGF and/or SIRT1 may be an attractive approach for treat-
ment of GC. </p>

<p>Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>Conflict of interest relevant to this article was not reported. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant from Seoul National 
University Hospital to BL Lee (2014) and a National Research 
Foundation of Korea (NRF) Grant funded by the Korean 
Government (2010-0024702). </p>



<p>References </p>

<p>Cancer Res Treat. 2016;48(1):345-354 </p>





</text></tei>