<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4299502" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Neuroblastoma is a childhood tumour with heterogeneous characteristics and children with metastatic disease often have a poor 
outcome. Here we describe the establishment of neuroblastoma patient-derived xenografts (PDXs) by orthotopic implantation of 
viably cryopreserved or fresh tumour explants of patients with high risk neuroblastoma into immunodeficient mice. In vivo tumour 
growth was monitored by magnetic resonance imaging and fluorodeoxyglucose-positron emission tomography. Neuroblastoma 
PDXs retained the undifferentiated histology and proliferative capacity of their corresponding patient tumours. The PDXs 
expressed neuroblastoma markers neural cell adhesion molecule, chromogranin A, synaptophysin and tyrosine hydroxylase. 
Whole genome genotyping array analyses demonstrated that PDXs retained patient-specific chromosomal aberrations such as 
MYCN amplification, deletion of 1p and gain of chromosome 17q. Thus, neuroblastoma PDXs recapitulate the hallmarks of high-
risk neuroblastoma in patients. PDX-derived cells were cultured in serum-free medium where they formed free-floating neuro-
spheres, expressed neuroblastoma gene markers MYCN, CHGA, TH, SYP and NPY, and retained tumour-initiating and metastatic 
capacity in vivo. PDXs showed much higher degree of infiltrative growth and distant metastasis as compared to neuroblastoma 
SK-N-BE(2)c cell line-derived orthotopic tumours. Importantly, the PDXs presented with bone marrow involvement, a clinical fea-
ture of aggressive neuroblastoma. Thus, neuroblastoma PDXs serve as clinically relevant models for studying and targeting high-
risk metastatic neuroblastoma. </p>

<p>Neuroblastoma is a solid childhood tumour, which accounts 
for 15% of paediatric cancer deaths. The neuroblastoma cell-
of-origin is thought to derive from the sympathoadrenal line-
age of the neural crest and the primary tumour frequently 
arises in the adrenal gland, although it can develop at any </p>

<p>site of the sympathetic nervous system. Patients with Stage 
IV tumours display infiltrative growth and metastasis to dis-
tant sites such as bone marrow, bone, lymph nodes, liver and 
lungs. Patients over 18 months of age with metastatic disease 
or MYCN amplification have a poor prognosis despite </p>

<p>intensive treatment with chemotherapy, surgery and radio-
therapy. 
1,2 Relevant neuroblastoma animal models are thus 
needed to improve the understanding, and ultimately the 
treatment, of high-risk neuroblastoma. 
In current human neuroblastoma xenograft mouse models, 
tumours have been established subcutaneously and by ortho-
topic injection of cell lines or short-term cultured primary 
cells. 
3-9 Orthotopically growing tumours are more prone to 
form vascularised xenografts with increased frequency of 
spontaneous distant metastasis as compared to subcutaneous 
tumours. 
5 It has become increasingly clear that tumour cells 
cultured in vitro can develop aberrant and irreversible genetic 
and phenotypic changes not consistent with the properties of 
the original patient tumour. 
10 In addition, as shown here and 
previously reported, 
5,11 cell line-derived orthotopic neuroblas-
toma xenografts often lack substantial spontaneous metastasis 
to bone marrow. Although results from cell line-derived stud-
ies have been valuable, generation of neuroblastoma patient-
derived xenografts (PDXs) by implantation of viable tumour 
explants from cancer patients is an alternative approach to 
better maintain patient-derived tumour cell features. 
12 By 
implantation of intact patient tumour explants, including 
human tumour stroma, in vitro induced modifications are 
bypassed. PDXs have been established by subcutaneous 
implantation of patient-derived tumour explants from paediat-
ric cancers, including neuroblastoma 
13 and by implantation of 
neuroblastoma samples into human pluripotent stem cell-
derived experimental teratomas. 
14 By subcutaneous and/or 
orthotopic implantation of diverse adult tumours (reviewed in 
Tentler et al. 
10 ), PDX-based tumour models have been 
increasingly utilised for preclinical drug screening. For this 
purpose and for mechanistic studies of metastasis and treat-
ment resistance, it would be important to establish orthotopic 
PDX models of neuroblastoma to faithfully resemble the clini-
cal features of the disease. Establishment of PDXs from rare 
tumours, like neuroblastoma, is however challenging for inves-
tigators with only sporadic access to fresh tumour material. 
We approached this problem by implantation of viably cryo-
preserved neuroblastoma samples. 
Here we present the establishment, in vivo imaging and 
detailed characterisation of neuroblastoma patient-derived 
orthotopic xenografts in immunodeficient mice. Neuroblas-
toma PDXs retain the undifferentiated histology, neuroblas-
toma protein marker profile and gene copy number changes of </p>

<p>their corresponding patient tumours. PDX-derived cells were 
cultured as neurospheres where tumour cells expressed typical 
neuroblastoma gene markers and retained tumour-initiating 
and metastatic capacity in vivo. Importantly, PDXs exhibit 
extensive infiltrative growth into surrounding tissues and dis-
play widespread metastasis to distant organs, including bone 
marrow. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>The human neuroblastoma cell line SK-N-BE(2)c was grown 
in Minimum Essential Medium at 37 
C in 5% CO 2 , 21% O 2 
and 95% air. The media was supplemented with 10% fetal 
bovine serum (FBS), 100 IU/ml penicillin and 100 lg/ml of 
streptomycin. Media and supplements were obtained from 
Invitrogen Life Technologies (Carlsbad, CA). </p>

<p>Processing of primary neuroblastoma explants </p>

<p>Primary neuroblastoma samples were obtained from neuro-
blastoma biopsy or surgery. Intact tumour explants (fragments 
of approximately 2 mm 3 2 mm 3 2 mm) were cryopreserved 
in 90% FBS and 10% dimethyl sulfoxide by stepwise cooling 
using CoolCell (BioCision, Larkspur, CA) and stored in 
280 
C freezer. Tumour explants were thawed either immedi-
ately prior to implantation into mice or one day prior to 
implantation and kept in stem cell media [Dulbecco's Modified 
Eagle's medium (DMEM)/F-12 medium with glutamine, 100 
IU/ml penicillin and 100 lg/ml of streptomycin, 2% B27 sup-
plement, 40 ng/ml of basic fibroblast growth factor (FGF) 2 
and 20 ng/ml of epidermal growth factor (EGF)] in incubator 
at 37 
C in 5% CO 2 and 21% O 2 . The regional ethical review 
board at Lund University approved the study (Dnr. 2011/289) 
and written informed consent was obtained. </p>

<p>Animal procedures </p>

<p>Four-to six-week-old female or male NSG mice were pur-
chased from Charles River (Charles River Laboratories, Wil-
mington, MA). Mice were housed under pathogen-free 
conditions and received autoclaved water and food. Mice 
were anaesthetised using 3% isofluorane inhalation. For the 
orthotopic adrenal gland injection, the skin and the mesen-
tery membrane were cut and exposure of the left adrenal 
gland was achieved by displacement of the spleen. 5 3 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>SK-N-BE(2)c cells in 30 ml phosphate buffered saline were </p>

<p>What's new? 
Neuroblastoma is a childhood tumour with heterogeneous characteristics and children with metastatic disease have a poor 
outcome. Here, the authors established neuroblastoma patient-derived xenografts (PDXs) by orthotopic implantation of viably 
cryopreserved or fresh tumour explants of patients with high-risk neuroblastoma into immunodeficient mice. The PDXs 
retained the genotype and phenotype of patient tumours and exhibited substantial infiltrative growth and metastasis to dis-
tant organs including bone marrow. PDX-derived neuroblastoma cells were expanded in vitro and retained tumourigenic and 
metastatic capacity in vivo. The PDXs may thus represent an important tool for investigating neuroblastoma growth and 
metastasis as well as drug targeting. </p>

<p>Cancer Cell Biology </p>

<p>Braekeveldt et al. </p>

<p>E253 </p>

<p>Int. J. Cancer: 136, E252-E261 (2015) V C 2014 The Authors. Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of UICC </p>

<p>injected into the adrenal gland using a 29G syringe. Intact 
patient-derived tumour explants were incubated in matrigel 
(BD Biosciences, San Jose) for a minimum of 20 min, then 
placed on top of the adrenal gland and immediately covered 
with matrigel. PDX-derived cultured cells were injected either 
as dissociated single cells (1 3 10 
6 cells) or as spheres 
(approximately 1 3 10 
6 cells) into the adrenal gland of NSG 
mice (n 5 3; single cells and n 5 3; spheres). The mesentery 
membrane was sown back together and the skin was closed 
using surgical clips. Mice were sacrificed immediately when 
exhibiting symptoms of tumour growth. Primary tumour, 
liver, kidneys, lungs, femur and tibia were fixed in 4% para-
formaldehyde for histopathological examination. Pieces of the 
primary tumour were snap frozen for genomic assays. All 
animal procedures followed the guidelines set by the Malm€ o-
Lund Ethical Committee for the use of laboratory animals 
and were conducted in accordance with European Union 
directive on the subject of animal rights. </p>

<p>Fluorodeoxyglucose-positron emission tomography 
imaging </p>

<p>FDG-PET scanning was performed to detect orthotopic 
tumours. The </p>

<p>18   F-FDG was produced and provided by Skåne 
University Hospital Cyclotron Unit. For PET-imaging, mice 
were intravenously injected with approximately 30 MBq of 
FDG and were imaged 1 h after administration using a pre-
clinical PET/CT-scanner (Bioscan, USA). Mice were anaesthe-
tised using 2-3% isofluorane and were placed in a temperature 
regulated animal chamber (Minerve, Bioscan, USA) with the 
temperature set to 37 
C (Minerve multistation controller unit) 
during the scanning. During the acquisitions, respiration was 
monitored on PC (SA Instruments, Inc, USA) and anaesthesia 
levels were adjusted accordingly. CT scanning was performed 
using the X-ray exposure of 600 ms and 177 lA, and the 
zoom level set to medium zoom. The CT images were scanned 
with 180 projections/rotation, pitch 1.0 and a binning of 1:4. 
The CT reconstruction was performed utilizing a Butterworth 
filter algorithm. The PET acquisition was performed with the 
coincidence mode set 1-3. The PET data was acquired in list 
mode for 30 minutes, and reconstructed dynamically using the 
OSEM option and rebinning SSRB to 2D LOR with the ring 
difference set to 8. CT and PET images were evaluated and 
created using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">InVivoScope</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">InviCRO</rs>). </p>

<p>Magnetic resonance imaging </p>

<p>Mice were anaesthetised using 2-3% isofluorane in 200 ml/ 
min O 2 / 200 ml/min NO 2 . Animals were restrained to an 
MR bed via head fixation. Breathing was monitored using a 
pressure sensitive pillow, temperature was monitored using a 
rectal probe and heating was regulated during MRI data 
acquisition to keep body temperature at 37 
C (SA instru-
ments, Inc, USA). MRI was performed at a field strength of 
9.4 T (Agilent Technologies, USA). Respiration triggered fat 
suppressed fast spin echo images were acquired using a spin 
echo preparation (10 ms) and an echo spacing of 10 ms </p>

<p>(acceleration factor 4, effective echo time: 27 ms, 4 averages). 
The repetition time was set between 800 and 950 ms depend-
ing on the breathing rate of the animal. The acquisition of 
the data for the 12 slices was spread over 4 respiration phases 
to achieve a T1-weighting corresponding to a repetition time 
of about 3.2-3.5 sec. Coronal and sagittal sections were 
acquired with an in plane resolution of 1563137 lm and a 
slice thickness of 1 mm, while the transversal direction was 
acquired with an in plane resolution of 1373137 lm. <rs id="software-1" type="software">ImageJ</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">1.46r</rs> with a plugin provided by Agilent to import their pro-
prietary format FDF images was used to analyse the images. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Xenograft tumours and mice organs were formalin-fixed and 
bone specimens were decalcified in 10% EDTA (pH 8). 
Tumours and organs were routinely embedded in paraffin and 
4 mm tissue sections were analysed. Haematoxylin &amp; eosin (His-
toLab Products AB, G€ oteborg, Sweden) was used for assessment 
of histopathology. A list of antibodies and their working dilu-
tions are presented in Supporting information Table 1. </p>

<p>Microscopy and quantification </p>

<p>Images were acquired using Olympus BX51 light microscope 
with CCD Olympus DP50 camera along with the <rs type="software">CellA Analysis</rs> Image Processing Program. Ki67 index was calcu-
lated by automatic quantification using the <rs type="software">Image Pro-Plus</rs> 
software as described previously. 
15 Neural cell adhesion mole-
cule (NCAM) positive metastatic cells in liver, lungs and 
bone marrow were manually quantified in 1-2 entire tissue 
sections/mouse at 320 magnification. </p>

<p>Single nucleotide polymorphism analysis </p>

<p>Cultured SK-N-BE(2)c cells, fresh tumour explants from SK-
N-BE(2)c orthotopic tumours, patient tumours and PDXs 
were snapfrozen and stored in 280 
C freezer for single 
nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) array analysis. Briefly, DNA 
was extracted from the cells and tissues using DNeasy Blood 
and Tissue Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) according to the 
instructions. We used the Affymetrix CytoScan HD platform 
for SNP array analysis of cultured SK-N-BE(2)c cells, SK-N-
BE(2)c tumours, PDXs and patient tumour #3. High resolu-
tion microarray analysis was performed by hybridisation of 
genomic DNA on arrays, using equipment and protocols as 
recommended by the manufacturer (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, 
CA). The Affymetrix CytoScan HD chip contains approxi-
mately 2.6 million markers distributed throughout all chro-
mosomes; of these almost 750,000 are SNPs enabling 
detection of copy number neutral loss of heterozygosity. The 
practical resolution of the method is 10-50 kb for deletions 
and 30-150 kb for duplications; depending on the probe den-
sity of each segment. HumanCytoSNP-12 DNA Analysis 
BeadChip (299,140 markers 10 kb average distance) from 
Illumina (Illumina, San Diego, CA) was used for SNP array 
analysis of patient tumour #1 and patient tumour #2. DNA 
amplification, tagging and hybridisation to the chip were </p>

<p>Cancer Cell Biology </p>

<p>E254 </p>

<p>Neuroblastoma PDXs recapitulate patient tumours </p>

<p>Int. J. Cancer: 136, E252-E261 (2015) V C 2014 The Authors. Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of UICC </p>

<p>performed according to the manufacturer's protocol (http:// 
www.illumina.com). Data were analysed using <rs id="software-5" type="software">GenomeStudio Genotyping</rs> Module (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Illumina</rs>). For exclusion of constitutional 
copy number polymorphisms, the Database of Genomic Var-
iants (http://projects.tcaq.ca/variation) was used. Genomic 
position annotations were based on the hg19 build (http:// 
genome.ucsc.edu/) of the human genome sequence. Copy 
number variation analyses were performed using the <rs type="software">Nexus</rs> 
software. </p>

<p>Isolation and in vitro sphere culture of PDX-derived cells </p>

<p>Small tumour pieces were mechanically dissected using sterile 
scalpels and the minced tissue was collected in a petri dish 
containing Accutase (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) and 
incubated for 15-20 min at 37 
C, with pipetting every 5 min 
to dissociate the tissue. The suspension was then transferred 
to serum-free DMEM/High Glucose (Thermo Scientific, Wal-
tham, MA), excluding nondissociated pieces and centrifuged. 
The pellet was re-suspended in stem cell medium; DMEM/ 
GlutaMAX 
TM F-12 (mixed in a 3:1 ratio) supplemented with 
100 IU/ml penicillin, 100 lg/ml streptomycin, 2% B-27 w/o 
vitamin A (Gibco-Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY), 40 
ng/ml basic FGF (Promega, Madison, WI) and 20 ng/ml EGF 
(Gibco Life Technologies). Spheres were passaged once a 
week and cells from early passages (up to the fifth passage) 
were used for quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) 
analysis. PDX-derived cultured cells were injected orthotopi-
cally into mice (described in Animal procedures). </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction </p>

<p>Total RNA was extracted using either RNeasy Mini or Micro 
Kit together with the Qiashredder Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Ger-
many). An on-column DNAse treatment was included during 
the extraction. The following complementary DNA synthesis 
was performed using MultiScribe Reverse Transcriptase enzyme 
(Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA) and random primers. 
Quantitative PCR was carried out in a 7300 Real-Time PCR 
(RT-PCR) System (Applied Biosystems) with SYBR Green PCR 
Master mix (Applied Biosystems). Comparative Ct method was 
used in order to quantify mRNA levels and three reference 
genes (SDHA, UBC, YWHAZ) were included to normalise 
gene-expression levels. Experiments were performed in tripli-
cates. Primers are listed in Supporting information Table 2. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>In vivo imaging of orthotopic neuroblastoma PDXs </p>

<p>To optimise in vivo imaging techniques for observation of 
orthotopic neuroblastoma growth, we injected SK-N-BE(2)c 
neuroblastoma cells into the adrenal gland of NSG mice 
(n 5 9) and tumours were successfully established in all ani-
mals. After optimisation of fluorodeoxyglucose-positron 
emission tomography (FDG-PET) and magnetic resonance 
imaging (MRI) settings, orthotopic tumour growth was dem-
onstrated as seen from the sagittal, coronal and transversal 
views. FDG signal was also seen in nontumour regions like 
brain, heart, kidneys and urinary bladder (Supporting infor-
mation Fig. 1). For establishment of neuroblastoma PDXs, 
we implanted orthotopically fresh or viably cryopreserved 
tumour explants from six patient tumours into NSG mice. 
Patient characteristics are presented in Table 1. Orthotopic 
PDXs from three patient tumours were established and 
detected by in vivo imaging. FDG-PET demonstrated hetero-
geneous uptake of FDG within tumours as seen from the sag-
ittal, coronal and transversal views (Fig. 1a). Orthotopic 
neuroblastoma PDX growth was confirmed by MRI (Fig. 1b). </p>

<p>Histopathological characterisation of orthotopic 
neuroblastoma PDXs </p>

<p>Neuroblastoma PDXs developed as large abdominal solid 
masses with heterogeneous gross morphology, including a 
haemorrhagic cut surface typical of neuroblastoma (Fig. 1c). 
The tumours displayed extensive infiltrative growth into sur-
rounding tissues such as the ipsilateral kidney, muscle and 
fat/connective tissue. In contrast, orthotopic SK-N-BE(2)c 
tumours only displayed moderate infiltrative growth into sur-
rounding tissues like muscle, pancreas and connective/fat tis-
sue (Fig. 1c), and large parts of the tumours showed 
expansive growth pattern without obvious signs of 
infiltration. 
Both PDXs and the original patient tumours were stroma-
poor tumours consisting of densely packed small round blue 
tumour cells with scant cytoplasm (Fig. 1d). The PDXs 
retained the differentiation status of their corresponding 
patient tumours (undifferentiated neuroblastoma for PDX #1 
and #2 and poorly differentiated neuroblastoma for PDX #3). 
SK-N-BE(2)c orthotopic tumours revealed a uniform </p>

<p>Table 1. Patient tumour characteristics </p>

<p>No 
Age 
Origin 
Stage 
Histology 
Patient genomics 
PDX 
Days 
Tissue status </p>

<p>1 
1y4m 
primary (AG) 
IV 
un NB 
MYCN amp, 1p-
yes 
70 
Cryopreserved </p>

<p>2 
2y2m 
cerebral met 
IV 
un NB 
MYCN amp, 1p-,117q 
yes 
102 
Cryopreserved </p>

<p>3 
2y9m 
primary (AG) 
III 
pd NB 
MYCN amp, 1p-, 117q 
yes 
59 
Fresh </p>

<p>4 
4y9m 
primary (AG) 
IV 
pd NB 
MYCN gain, 1p-, 11q-,117q 
no 
NA 
Cryopreserved </p>

<p>5 
2y4m 
primary (AG) 
IV 
pd NB 
1p-,117q 
no 
NA 
Cryopreserved </p>

<p>6 
12y 
primary 
IIb 
pd NB 
117q 
no 
NA 
Cryopreserved </p>

<p>AG 5 adrenal gland, un NB 5 undifferentiated neuroblastoma, pd NB 5 poorly differentiated neuroblastoma. Numbers of days refer to the time 
period from implantation until PDXs were analysed. </p>

<p>Cancer Cell Biology </p>

<p>Braekeveldt et al. </p>

<p>E255 </p>

<p>Int. J. Cancer: 136, E252-E261 (2015) V C 2014 The Authors. Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of UICC </p>

<p>undifferentiated histology; small round blue tumour cells 
with scant cytoplasm and minimal neurofibrillary matrix 
(Fig. 1d). </p>

<p>Similar to high-stage neuroblastoma in patients, both 
PDXs and SK-N-BE(2)c tumours were highly proliferating as 
shown by expression of the cell-cycle marker Ki-67 in a large </p>

<p>Figure 1. In vivo imaging and histopathological characterisation of neuroblastoma PDXs. FDG-PET/CT and MRI of neuroblastoma PDXs were 
performed 3-4 weeks after implantation. Orthotopic PDXs are depicted from the sagittal, coronal and transversal views (a and b). Uptake 
of FDG is also seen in the brain, heart and urinary bladder (a). The PDX is encircled with a yellow line and located above and below the 
ipsilateral kidney, encircled in red (b). Gross morphology of neuroblastoma PDX and SK-N-BE(2)c orthotopic tumour (c). PDXs (n 5 3) dis-
played extensive infiltrative growth into ipsilateral kidney, muscle and fat tissue while orthotopic SK-N-BE(2)c tumours (n 5 8) exhibited 
only moderate or no local infiltration (c). PDXs recapitulated the differentiation status of the corresponding patient tumours while SK-N-
BE(2)c xenografts showed a uniform undifferentiated histology (d). Ki-67 expression in PDX #1, patient tumour #1 and SK-N-BE(2)c tumours. 
One section from each patient tumour and four sections from each PDX model were quantified for Ki-67 expression (e). The shown pictures 
are representative for the mice. Scale bar in C is 100 mm in (c), (d) and (e) and 50 mm in the close-ups of (d) and (e). </p>

<p>Cancer Cell Biology </p>

<p>E256 </p>

<p>Neuroblastoma PDXs recapitulate patient tumours </p>

<p>Int. J. Cancer: 136, E252-E261 (2015) V C 2014 The Authors. Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of UICC </p>

<p>fraction of tumour cells (Fig. 1e). The Ki-67 labelling index 
for SK-N-BE(2)c orthotopic tumours was 60%. The Ki-67 
index was 74, 76 and 82% for patient tumours #1, #2 and #3, 
respectively, and 71 6 7%, 50 6 2% and 62 6 5% for the 
corresponding PDXs. </p>

<p>Expression of neuroblastoma protein markers </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry revealed expression of NCAM (CD 
56) in virtually all tumour cells in patients and the strong 
expression was retained in all PDXs. Chromogranin A 
(CHGA) and synaptophysin (SYP) were expressed in almost 
all tumour cells in patients and heterogeneous expression of 
these markers was retained in PDXs. Tumour expression of 
tyrosine hydroxylase (TH) was heterogeneous in both 
patients and PDXs (Fig. 2). SK-N-BE(2)c orthotopic tumours 
revealed a more atypical differentiation marker profile, most </p>

<p>notably very low number of CHGA and lack of SYP positive 
cells (Fig. 2). 
Because previous in vitro culturing of neuroblastoma 
patient-derived tumour-initiating cells (TICs) resulted in 
overgrowth by EBV-transformed lymphoblasts, 
16 EBNA2 
expression in PDXs was investigated by immunohistochemis-
try. We found no evidence of EBNA2 expression in PDXs 
using EBV-transformed human lymphoblastoid cells as posi-
tive control (Supporting information Fig. 2a). </p>

<p>Patient-specific gene copy number changes are retained in 
neuroblastoma PDXs </p>

<p>Patient tumour #1 and PDX #1 presented with 1p deletion, 
MYCN amplification, 9p deletion and 17q gain (Fig. 3a). 1p 
deletion, MYCN amplification and 17q gain were also present 
in patient tumours #2 and #3 and retained in their </p>

<p>Figure 2. Immunohistochemical expression of neuroblastoma markers in neuroblastoma PDXs. NCAM was retained in virtually all tumour 
cells and CHGA, TH and SYP were heterogenously expressed in PDXs. SK-N-BE(2)c orthotopic tumours exhibited very low numbers of CHGA-
positive cells and lacked SYP-positive cells. The shown pictures are representative for the mice. Scale bar is 100 mm in the overviews and 
50 mm in the close-ups. </p>

<p>Cancer Cell Biology </p>

<p>Braekeveldt et al. </p>

<p>E257 </p>

<p>Int. J. Cancer: 136, E252-E261 (2015) V C 2014 The Authors. Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of UICC </p>

<p>corresponding PDXs (Figs. 3b and 3c). Thus, chromosomal 
aberrations typically found in neuroblastomas were retained 
in their corresponding PDXs. 
SNP array profiling of SK-N-BE(2)c cell cultures has been 
performed previously. 
17,18 Here, SK-N-BE(2)c cell cultures and 
three SK-N-BE(2)c orthotopic xenografts were analysed by 
SNP array. MYCN amplification, 1p deletion, 3p deletion and 
11q copy number neutral imbalance were retained in ortho-
topic SK-N-BE(2)c xenografts (Supporting information Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Neuroblastoma PDXs exhibit widespread metastasis 
to distant organs </p>

<p>Neuroblastoma PDX metastases were demonstrated by 
immunohistochemistry. In liver, metastatic nodules at sub-
capsular as well as central locations were present in all PDXs, 
resembling the appearance and locations of neuroblastoma 
metastatic growth. Widespread micrometastases were found </p>

<p>in the lungs and also, but less frequently, in the ipsilateral 
kidney (Fig. 4). Importantly, we found substantial metastatic 
spread to bone marrow in PDXs from all three patients. 
Bone marrow metastases homogenously expressed NCAM 
and metastatic tumour cells were dividing as demonstrated 
by Ki-67 expression (Fig. 4). SK-N-BE(2)c orthotopic 
tumours metastasised spontaneously to lungs and liver but to 
a much lesser extent as compared to PDXs (Fig. 4). We 
found no evidence of SK-N-BE(2)c metastatic cells in bone 
marrow. Supporting information Table 3 shows the number 
of metastatic cells in lungs, liver and bone marrow for PDXs 
(n 5 7-9 for each PDX model) and for SK-N-BE(2)c-carrying 
mice (n 5 8). </p>

<p>Neurosphere-cultured PDX-derived cells express 
neuroblastoma markers and retain tumourigenic and 
metastatic capacity in vivo </p>

<p>PDX-derived tumour cells were cultured in serum-free, stem 
cell-promoting medium, where they formed free-floating neu-
rosphere-like cell structures (Fig. 5a). These cultures were 
expanded for at least five passages and retained growth and 
phenotypic properties. RT-qPCR showed that these cultured 
PDX-derived cells overexpress MYCN (Fig. 5b) and neuro-
blastoma differentiation markers CHGA, TH, SYP and NPY 
(Fig. 5c). There was no EBV-specific mRNA expression in 
any of the PDX-derived cell cultures (Supporting information 
Fig. 2b). The expression of neuroblastoma gene markers and 
lack of EBV-specific mRNA expression confirmed the iden-
tity of the cultured PDX-derived cells as neuroblastoma cells. 
The tumour-initiating capacity of the cultured PDX-derived 
cells was tested by orthotopic injection of dissociated single 
cells or spheres and all injected animals (n 5 3; single cells, 
and n 5 3; spheres) showed tumour take. The tumours 
exhibited homogenous NCAM expression, heterogenous 
expression of CHGA and TH, and lacked SYP (Fig. 5d). 
Using NCAM immunohistochemistry, we found evidence of 
distant metastases in lungs, liver or bone marrow in all six 
animals (Fig. 5e). Thus, the in vivo tumourigenic and meta-
static capacity of PDX-derived cells were retained after in 
vitro expansion and orthotopic injections. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Here, we present a pipeline for preclinical modelling of meta-
static human neuroblastoma using patient-derived tumour 
material without passaging the tumour cells in vitro. We show 
that it is possible to establish orthotopic neuroblastoma PDXs 
by implantation of fresh and, importantly, viably cryopreserved 
patient tumour samples, which overcomes the tissue shortage-
problem when working with rare tumour forms. Using the 
clinical imaging modalities FDG-PET and MRI, we further 
show that orthotopic tumours within the abdominal cavity can 
be monitored. PDX tumours retained the clinical features of 
the disease such as the protein marker profile and prognosti-
cally significant chromosomal aberrations. Furthermore, PDXs 
were found to be robust models for invasive neuroblastoma </p>

<p>Figure 3. Neuroblastoma PDXs retain patient tumour-specific chro-
mosomal aberrations. Arrows indicate neuroblastoma-typical 
regions; such as 1p deletion, MYCN amplification, 9p deletion and 
17q gain for patient tumours and their corresponding PDXs. </p>

<p>Cancer Cell Biology </p>

<p>E258 </p>

<p>Neuroblastoma PDXs recapitulate patient tumours </p>

<p>Int. J. Cancer: 136, E252-E261 (2015) V C 2014 The Authors. Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of UICC </p>

<p>with substantial metastatic spread to distant organs, including 
bone marrow. Lastly, we show that PDX-derived neuroblas-
toma cells can be established and passaged in vitro as spheres 
where they retained their proliferative capacity, neuroblastoma 
phenotype and tumour-initiating capacity in vivo. 
The tumour model presented here is based on orthotopic 
implantation of tumour tissue on top of the adrenal gland as 
previous findings have shown that an orthotopic location pro-
motes neuroblastoma growth and behaviour to a large extent 
mimicking clinical human neuroblastoma growth properties. </p>

<p>5   Thus, to monitor tumour growth, we had to use in vivo imag-
ing techniques as abdominal tumours are difficult to detect in 
early phases and impossible to quantify in terms of tumour 
spread and tumour volume by using, e.g., calliper. Because 
tumours are established by implantation of explants we could 
not utilise imaging modalities that require pre-labelling of sin-
gle cells for visualisation in vivo. However, as we show here, 
FDG-PET and MRI are powerful imaging techniques suitable 
for detection of orthotopic nonmodified neuroblastoma cells. 
While primary tumours were visualised in all tested tumour-
bearing mice, the next and more challenging step, will be to 
detect metastatic growth in the PDX models. A combination 
of FDG-PET or MIBG-SPECT, and MRI would probably opti-
mise the conditions for detection of metastases in vivo. 
The findings that neuroblastoma PDXs retained clinically 
important features of the disease make the PDXs more suita-
ble as models for aggressive neuroblastoma as compared to 
the commonly used cell line-based xenografts. In the SK-N-</p>

<p>BE(2)c cell model used here, several aberrant features not 
typical for the clinical disease were found, most importantly 
lack of bone marrow involvement. Indeed, one obstacle when 
studying neuroblastoma metastasis has been the scarcity of 
xenograft models that retain the metastatic pattern of the dis-
ease. 
11 Here, we show that orthotopic neuroblastoma PDXs 
are reliable models for human neuroblastoma bone marrow 
metastasis. The presence of liver and lung metastasis in the 
PDX models are also consistent with the findings of liver and 
lung micrometastases in more than half of neuroblastoma 
patients analysed by immunohistochemistry postmortem. </p>

<p>19   Furthermore, we demonstrate that the neuroblastoma protein 
marker profile and neuroblastoma-associated chromosomal 
aberrations MYCN amplification, 1p deletion and gain of 17q 
were retained in PDXs. 
Maintaining patient tumour explant viability is a critical 
parameter for successful establishment of PDXs and the 
workflow and/or transport of fresh tumour tissue from sur-
gery to implantation into mice can potentially decrease tissue 
viability and reduce successful in vivo engraftment. Implanta-
tion of viably cryopreserved tumour explants can solve this 
problem as demonstrated here. Cryopreservation of tumour 
explants further allows for storage of viable primary tumour 
material in biobanks and can be used for establishment of 
many diverse PDXs at any lab with animal facilities. This is 
in particular important for establishment of rare tumours like 
neuroblastoma. Interestingly, previous studies have shown 
that the in vivo take rate of cryopreserved and fresh tumour </p>

<p>Figure 4. Neuroblastoma PDXs exhibit wide-spread metastasis to distant organs including bone marrow. High numbers of NCAM-positive 
metastatic cells were found in lungs, liver, ipsilateral kidney and bone marrow of PDXs (7-9 sections from each PDX model). Bone marrow 
metastases were dividing as shown by Ki-67 expression (inserted field). In contrast, orthotopic SK-N-BE(2)c xenografts (n 5 8) exhibited 
only low numbers of metastatic cells in liver and lungs and no cells in bone marrow. The shown pictures are representative for the mice. 
Scale bar is 100 mm in PDX lung, liver and ipsilateral kidney, and 50 mm in the PDX bone marrow and SK-N-BE(2)c lung and liver. </p>

<p>Cancer Cell Biology </p>

<p>Braekeveldt et al. </p>

<p>E259 </p>

<p>Int. J. Cancer: 136, E252-E261 (2015) V C 2014 The Authors. Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of UICC </p>

<p>tissue (pancreatic and colorectal carcinoma) is compara-
ble </p>

<p>20,21   , although a large divergence in tumour take rates 
between different tumour forms and within a given tumour 
form can be anticipated. In the case of neuroblastoma it is 
likely that the tumour take rate drastically drops if low-stage 
neuroblastomas were implanted. Other parameters that could 
influence successful in vivo engraftment include tissue viabil-</p>

<p>ity, time from biopsy to implantation, tumour type, mouse 
strain, implantation site and the use of co-factors like Matri-
gel. However, given the scarcity of aggressive neuroblastoma 
we have not had the possibility to test the effect of all these 
parameters for engraftment. 
Orthotopic neuroblastoma PDXs will be important tools 
for in vivo drug testing against aggressive neuroblastoma. </p>

<p>Figure 5. PDX-derived cultured cells express neuroblastoma markers and retain tumourigenic and metastatic capacity in vivo. PDX-derived 
cells were cultured in serum-free stem cell medium where they formed free-floating spheres (a). MYCN mRNA expression in negative control 
(the non-MYCN-amplified cell line SH-SY5Y), positive control (the MYCN-amplified cell line SK-N-BE(2)c) and in PDX-derived cells (b). CHGA, 
TH, SYP and NPY mRNA expression in PDX-derived cell cultures and SK-N-BE(2)c (c). Data are expressed as mean 6 SD. Tumours estab-
lished by orthotopic injection of the PDX-derived cultured cells retained expression of NCAM, CHGA and TH (d). Metastases were found in 
lungs, liver and bone marrow as shown by NCAM immunohistochemistry (e). Scale bar is 100 mm in A and 50 mm in (d) and (e). </p>

<p>Cancer Cell Biology </p>

<p>E260 </p>

<p>Neuroblastoma PDXs recapitulate patient tumours </p>

<p>Int. J. Cancer: 136, E252-E261 (2015) V C 2014 The Authors. Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of UICC </p>

<p>Although drug testing using subcutaneously implanted neu-
roblastoma xenografts 
13 is less time-consuming, it appears, 
based on the results presented here and by others 
5,10 that 
orthotopically established neuroblastoma PDXs is the model 
of choice for studying and targeting neuroblastoma invasion 
and metastasis in vivo. For such studies, neuroblastoma 
PDXs should optimally be used in conjunction with neuro-
blastoma transgenic mouse models with substantial metastatic 
capacity. 
22,23 All established PDXs presented here contain 
MYCN amplifications and hence, the PDXs are also suitable 
models for targeting of MYCN in vivo. MYCN is an attractive 
therapeutic target for patients with high-risk neuroblastoma 
as MYCN amplification correlates with aggressive disease </p>

<p>24   and downregulation of MYCN expression results in decreased 
tumour cell proliferation, increased cell death and neuronal 
differentiation of neuroblastoma cells in vitro. 
25 In addition 
to orthotopic neuroblastoma PDX models, zebrafish and 
transgenic mouse models, driven by MYCN alone or in com-
bination with other oncogenes 
22,26-28 are important comple-
mentary preclinical neuroblastoma models. 
In conclusion, we present a workflow for preclinical mod-
elling of aggressive human neuroblastoma by FDG/PET and 
MRI imaging, histopathological examinations and genomic 
characterisation by use of orthotopic PDXs. Future work will 
need to expand the pool of neuroblastoma PDXs in order to </p>

<p>reflect the large diversity of the disease. For instance up to 
now, we have only established tumours carrying MYCN 
amplifications. The PDXs serve as a source for in vivo expan-
sion of patient-derived tumour-initiating cells, which will be 
valuable for in vitro studies. Furthermore, the recurrent find-
ings of patient tumour-specific features, invasive growth and 
bone marrow metastasis in the PDX models demonstrate their 
suitability for mechanistic studies of human neuroblastoma 
growth and metastasis, and for drug testing against aggressive 
metastatic neuroblastoma in vivo. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Lund University Bioimaging Center (LBIC), Lund University, is gratefully 
acknowledged for providing experimental resources. We thank Thuy Tran, 
Gustav Grafstr€ om, Adnan Bibic, Ren e in't Zandt and Carina Siversson for 
technical help with the in vivo imaging studies. This work was supported by 
grants from the Swedish Childhood Cancer Foundation, the Swedish Cancer 
Society, the Swedish Research Council, VINNOVA, the SSF Strategic Center 
for Translational Cancer Research-CREATE Health, the Strategic Cancer 
Research Program, BioCARE, Crafoord Foundation, The Royal Physio-
graphic Society in Lund, Magnus Bergvall Foundation, Gunnar Nilsson's 
Cancer Foundation, The Swedish Society of Medicine, Gyllenstiernska Krap-
perupsstiftelsen, Region Skåne and the research funds of Skåne University 
Hospital, grants from the FIS (contract PI10/15) and RTICC (Red Tematica 
de Investigaci on Cooperativa en Cancer, contracts RD06/0020/0102;RD12/ 
0036/0020), Instituto Carlos III Madrid, and ERDF (European Regional 
Development Fund). </p>



<p>Cancer Cell Biology </p>

<p>Braekeveldt et al. </p>

<p>E261 </p>

<p>Int. J. Cancer: 136, E252-E261 (2015) V C 2014 The Authors. Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of UICC </p>

</text></tei>