<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4166139" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>3 4 </p>

<p>In Australia 36% of the population aged 
65 and above live outside major cities, with 
reported poorer health outcomes and unmet </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ Testing of a theoretically based planning frame-
work for an informal health service network 
across health and social care in the complex 
field of older people's mental health. 
▪ Engagement of health service stakeholder organi-
sations as participants in the study design, 
conduct and use of findings. 
▪ Use and dissemination of findings optimised by 
the participation of service stakeholders. 
▪ Potential for limited transferability due to differ-
ing capacity and context in other health service 
networks. 
▪ Potential for harm in organisational case studies 
using participatory methods where there are 
risks to anonymity and confidentiality. </p>

<p>Fuller J, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e006304. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006304 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Protocol </p>

<p>needs for mental healthcare. 
2 5 People aged 65 years 
and above are less likely to access general practitioner 
mental health services and mental health profes-
sionals. 
6 7 Rural older people are particularly disadvan-
taged by a lack of available local mental health 
professionals; they often rely on visiting psychiatrists and 
can travel large distances to access specialist mental 
health services. 
2 8 The consequences of lack of adequate 
primary mental healthcare for older people includes fre-
quent and longer acute hospitalisation, deterioration of 
physical and mental health, as well earlier admission to 
residential care. </p>

<p>9 10 </p>

<p>An older person with a mental health problem may 
require input from health, aged care and social care ser-
vices, and so there is a need for a well networked range 
of local services, especially in rural locations. Owing to 
the complexity of health problems experienced by older 
people, there is widespread support internationally for 
the provision of a more integrated approach to care, 
with a growing evidence base for the effectiveness of 
this. 
11-15 Benefits of a more integrated approach to care 
include: better outcomes for the client and carer; 
improved access to and experience of services; and 
better use of existing resources. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Governments and professional groups have prioritised 
mental health service delivery based in primary care 
with the need for integration and the provision of the 
'right service' at the 'right time', which includes transi-
tion between various service sectors. 
6 17-20 To address 
the need for more integrated services through planning, 
networking 
and 
coordination, 
the 
Australian 
Government established a model of regional primary 
healthcare organisations, called Medicare Locals. 
i State 
Governments in Australia have also developed Local 
Health Networks to manage the delivery of public hos-
pital as well as some out-of-hospital services. Together, 
Medicare Locals and Local Health Networks, along with 
a range of general practice, aged care and social care 
organisations, plan and provide care for older people 
with mental health problems. 
Despite support for integrated care it is not often 
clear in policies what this means specifically or what is 
needed to effectively integrate services. In part this 
problem relates to the use of the term 'integration' 
without specifying its interpretation, which could cover a 
range of levels from the total integration of organisa-
tions or functions under one umbrella through to the 
formation of loose networks or alliances. 
21 In addition, 
the management of integrated health servicing across 
numerous organisations requires different management 
dynamics than for traditional bureaucratic and market-
based forms of healthcare organisation, because </p>

<p>organisational independence is retained but cooperation 
is required. A network approach, whereby a number of 
independent organisations cooperate to achieve mutual 
goals has been suggested; but to make change in a 
network a manager needs to engage in the ongoing 
negotiation of commitment to the network through 
facilitating the development of trust and reciprocity 
between partners. 
22 A recent review examining the 
effectiveness of links in primary mental healthcare iden-
tified a paucity of real world testing of practical manage-
ment models of integrated health servicing. 
23 This 
means that there are not clear and well-understood pro-
cesses through which a network of organisations can 
work together to meet the mental healthcare needs of 
older people. </p>

<p>METHODS AND ANALYSIS 
In the current Australian context of Medicare Locals and 
Local Health Networks, the aim of this study is to test a 
framework for planning and management of a network 
of services in the provision of primary mental healthcare 
for older people in a rural area. The research was funded 
in October 2013 through a nationally competitive grant 
from the Australian Primary Health Care Research 
Institute. 
24 Data collection started in the field in February 
2014 with analysis to be completed in March 2015. </p>

<p>Framework for network planning using facilitated 
reflection 
The network planning approach using facilitated reflec-
tion is based on inter-organisational relations theory. 
Hibbert et al 
25 make the point that because collaborative 
relationships are idiosyncratic, then the generalisable 
feature of network management is the development of 
'handles for reflective practice' ( p.405) in which part-
ners formulate their actions in light of their own circum-
stances and competencies. From this starting point of 
reflective practice we drew from a previous narrative 
review of the first author on the linkage strategies and 
enablers in primary mental healthcare. Ten linkage strat-
egies were identified 
11 as well as the factors that enable 
the development of these strategies. 
23 Table 1 describes 
the linkage strategies and figure 1 shows the enablers. 
The process that brings the enablers together is evalu-
ation feedback (reflective practice), which in this pro-
posed study will occur through facilitated reflection. We 
will compare this framework to what we find in this case 
study. 
The facilitated reflection involves the collective use of 
feedback on data obtained from a network survey, 
service provider interviews and help seeking journeys 
described by clients or their carer. This reflection will be 
facilitated to enable problem solving in three 1-day work-
shops with service stakeholders. The rationale is that 
network management must make use of collective reflec-
tion more so than in a bureaucracy or a market-based 
arrangement because leadership and authority in a </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>Since beginning this study a change in the national government has 
seen the cancellation of the Medicare Local Program. At the time of 
writing the government has made a commitment to regional primary 
health care organisations but has not determined their form or 
function. </p>



<p>Fuller J, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e006304. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006304 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>network are more distributed among services. </p>

<p>22 25 26 </p>

<p>Sheaff et al 
27 describe this reflective use of feedback as 
the 'evidence basing' incentive that managers can use to 
motivate participation in a network, to show members 
what is working and the outcomes that are being 
achieved. 
28 Hence, our assumption for testing is that the 
implementation of change in a network will be driven 
by the collective reflection on feedback about the 
network. The extent to which information feedback is 
used by the services will be influenced by their level of 
commitment to working together (conducive context) 
and that a conducive context will be created if there are 
linkage enablers. 
29-31 The research design to promote 
collective reflection is shown in figure 2 as the frame-
work for network planning. </p>

<p>Research questions 
The study asks the following five questions: 
1. What organisational links currently exist in a rural 
region for the provision of mental healthcare for 
older people? 
2. What are the gaps, barriers and enablers in linking 
services, as perceived by key service stakeholders, 
older people and their carers? 
3. What is the role of policy in supporting the develop-
ment of linked care for older people in a rural 
region? 
4. What links could be established between services for 
the mental healthcare of older people? 
5. How does the use of facilitated reflection enable an 
informal network to plan and manage linked primary 
mental healthcare for older people in a rural region? </p>

<p>Setting 
The research is a case study located in the southern part 
of the Adelaide Hills, Fleurieu and Kangaroo Island 
rural region in South Australia. This region has a </p>

<p>growing older population with a 52% increase in those 
aged 65 years and above from 2001 to 2011. 
32 The 
region is typical of many Australian rural locations that 
are within 100 km of metropolitan centres, but which 
still face difficulties in service access, coordination and 
follow-up because of differences in funding criteria and 
boundaries between services. While there is no purpos-
ive or managed network of services related to older 
people's mental health in the region, there are a 
number of regular interagency meetings and there is a 
'Positive Ageing Taskforce' involving a range of service 
providers that is managed by the local government and 
funded by the national government. There is no binding 
commitment made by local services to the Taskforce and 
it has no formal decision-making function or specific 
resources. Hence, the network of services is best 
described as loose, informal and not explicitly defined. 
Specialist mental health services are delivered to older 
people living in the region by the local community-
based mental health team with a consultation liaison 
service available at the large mental health hospital 
some 80 kms away in the capital city. Acute inpatient 
units providing psychiatric inpatient treatment for 
persons 65 years and above are also located in the 
capital city, but these are run by metropolitan networks 
of the South Australian Government health system. 
At the request of the Positive Ageing Taskforce we 
recently undertook a study in this region exploring the 
views of health and social care providers about the bar-
riers to mental healthcare for older people. 
33 We found 
a wide range of organisations provide care to older 
people and that while collaborative arrangements 
tended to be informal, these arrangements were well 
regarded. Barriers to more integrated services related to 
the difficulty in getting all relevant agencies to become 
involved in these collaborative arrangements, insufficient 
knowledge about available services, inadequate referral </p>

<p>Table 1 Linkage strategies in primary mental health care </p>

<p>Category 
Strategy 
Description </p>

<p>Direct collaborative 
activities </p>

<p>Link working 
Organisational tasks connecting 2+ services-may involve limited clinical 
intervention but not expert clinical advice or structured liaison 
Co-location 
Face to face-location of mental health worker in primary care-must 
provide treatment in primary care 
Consultation liaison 
Person 1 provides advice about care to person 2 without transfer of care 
-can be via a link worker 
Care management 
Coordination of care-including assessment, review, follow-up and care 
management plan; linking with other services or defined care pathway 
Agreed guidelines 
Protocols 
Agreed treatment algorithm-pharmacotherapy or psychological therapy 
Stepped care 
Treatment escalation or de-escalation procedure to other providers 
Communication 
systems </p>

<p>Enhanced 
communication </p>

<p>Formal process with feedback-meetings, shared medical record </p>

<p>Enhanced referral 
Expedited access-explicit referral criteria/ process. 
Electronic 
communication system </p>

<p>Tele-video conference connecting 2+ services </p>

<p>Service agreement 
Service agreement 
Memorandum of understanding-formal contract/ funding mechanism 
about how services work together </p>

<p>Fuller J, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e006304. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006304 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>processes, competition for funding and also gatekeeping 
that restricts which clients a service will accept. The lack 
of attention to the client's physical and mental health 
issues by services was thought to be a problem. </p>

<p>Participants 
A governance group will be established comprising 
three to five key senior staff with management responsi-
bilities in rural mental health, regional primary health-
care planning and social care related to older persons' 
mental health in the region. This will be a small 
decision-making group that will also include the project 
investigators. The group will meet throughout the 
project to establish research governance and inform 
network planning. Meetings will occur before and fol-
lowing each of three service stakeholder workshops and </p>

<p>also at the conclusion of the project in order to review 
the effectiveness of the framework for network planning 
for broader application. 
Up to 30 participants for service key informant inter-
views and stakeholder workshops will be recruited via 
purposive snowball sampling starting first from the gov-
ernance group. We will identify organisations and key 
staff across mental health, primary care, aged care and 
social care services that provide mental health and 
related services to older people in the region. 
Ten older people (aged 65 and older) and/or their 
carers who have sought mental healthcare in the region 
will be interviewed to explore their journeys to care. 
These participants will be purposively recruited with the 
assistance of the service providers in the key informant 
interviews and stakeholder workshops. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Linkage enablers in 
primary mental healthcare. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Framework for network 
planning. </p>



<p>Fuller J, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e006304. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006304 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Findings from the project will be presented to the 
service stakeholders progressively throughout the project 
to facilitate improved service coordination. This will </p>

<p>occur at management (governance group) and opera-
tions (stakeholder workshops) levels in order to maxi-
mise engagement and opportunities for change. </p>

<p>Table 2 Research questions and associated data collection and analysis methods </p>

<p>Question 1 
What organisational links currently exist in a 
rural region for the provision of mental 
healthcare for older people? </p>

<p>Organisational network analysis (interview survey) 
Up to 30 key informants from relevant health and human service 
organisations (identified through the governance group) will be interviewed 
using organisational network analysis to explore the regional service network 
structure. Organisational network analysis, also known as social network 
analysis, gathers information about which organisations are linked, in this 
case on the activities of information sharing, referrals and the management, 
planning and operation of services for the mental healthcare of older 
people. 
34 35 This provides quantitative information specific to the local 
network and to the unique and complex interactions between these 
organisations. See online supplementary appendix 1 for the survey and 
interview guide. </p>

<p>Measures of organisational network analysis will be used to provide 
information about which organisations are linked, the number of links in the 
network, the types of interactions between organisations (eg, exchanging 
information, referrals and planning), and the level and strength of each 
relationship. 
34 35 Maps displaying the patterns of connections between 
organisations will be generated utilising the <rs type="software">UCINET</rs> software. 
36 The visual 
and detailed nature of organisational network maps serves as a powerful 
heuristic device for discussion about the structure of the network, about which 
services are linked and on which activities. See online supplementary 
appendix 2 for a hypothetical map. </p>

<p>Question 2 
What are the gaps, barriers and enablers in 
linking services, as perceived by key service 
stakeholders, older people and their carers? </p>

<p>Qualitative interviews: key informant service providers and care seeking 
journeys 
Qualitative interviews will explore the above 30 service key-informants' 
perspectives on the linkage gaps, barriers and enablers between services. </p>

<p>In addition 10 older people and their carers will be interviewed using the 
Pathways Interview Schedule. 
37 This is a semistructured instrument designed 
for the systematic gathering of information on their routes to and sources of 
care. Two groups will be purposively selected with the assistance of the 
service key informants: those who have successfully negotiated a care 
journey and those who have not. </p>

<p>Framework analysis will be used to explore the present linkage strategies and 
management gaps, barriers and enablers between mental health, aged care, 
primary care and social care services, and how these affect people's help 
seeking experience and journey. Framework analysis is a qualitative method 
that is suited to applied research with specific questions, a limited timeframe, 
a predesigned sample, and a priori issues that are to be explored. 
38 The 
<rs type="software">NVivo</rs> software package will be used to manage and assist analysis of the 
qualitative data. </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>Question 3 
What is the role of policy in supporting the 
development of linked care for older people 
in a rural region? </p>

<p>Policy analysis 
Policy documents at the national, state and the local operational levels will be 
examined for their relevance to the development of integrated mental 
healthcare for older people in the region. The national and state level policies 
will be identified through online searches and advice from the governance 
group, while operational policies (eg, service plans, local guidelines and 
protocols etc.) will be identified though the service key informant interviews. 
The local operational policies from the various sectors (primary care, mental 
health, aged care, social care services) will be examined for congruence, 
direction and resource opportunities. </p>

<p>Continued </p>

<p>Fuller J, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e006304. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006304 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Data collection and analysis 
The following table 2 shows the five research questions 
and the methods that will be used to collect and analyse 
the data: </p>

<p>ETHICS, BENEFIT AND DISSEMINATION 
The ethical risk to key informants from health and 
human service organisations is likely to be minimal; 
however, a risk to organisations relates to the display of </p>

<p>their links with other organisations identified on 
network maps. Ethical guidelines for the use of network 
analysis within organisations have been developed cover-
ing fully informed consent and negotiated governance 
of research processes. 
40 While the data will be 
de-identified in public documents there is a potential 
for embarrassment during the workshops about the 
mapped position of organisations in the network as 
being prominent or not. To manage such risk, the gov-
ernance group will provide advice and guidance </p>

<p>Table 2 Continued </p>

<p>Question 4 
What links could be established between 
services for the mental healthcare of older 
people? </p>

<p>Facilitated network reflection 
Data from the methods above will be fed back in the governance group and in 
the three service stakeholder workshops held over 12 months. The purpose of 
each workshop is to progressively work towards the final goal of securing 
commitment among a group of stakeholder services for a network problem 
solving approach to the delivery of mental healthcare to older people in the 
region. 
▸ Workshop 1: Comment on and adapt the network planning framework, 
identify potential champions and begin to explore organisational readiness 
and capacity for change. Data pertaining to participants' perceptions of 
current as well as ideal links will also be collected. 
▸ Workshop 2: Findings related to the organisational network analysis, 
service key informant interviews and policy analysis will be fed back. This 
information will provide the participants with the opportunity to consider 
network strengths and weaknesses and explore early opportunities for 
change. After the organisational network analysis and key informant data 
are fed back, small group discussion will be guided by the following 
prompts: (1) Does the network look as you would expect on the maps/ 
what stands out/ what seems missing? (2) What else do you want to know 
-the maps show the links, not what goes down them? (3) Do the maps 
suggest what might be working and what else might be needed? 
▸ Workshop 3: Final analysis will be added to that presented at workshop 2 
and will include the data on older people's care seeking journeys. The 
current state of the network will be examined against the theory on linkage 
strategies and enablers to identify strengths, weaknesses and 
opportunities for change. From this examination the priorities for action will 
be proposed to the governance group for improved integration in regional 
mental health servicing for older people. 
Workshop discussions will be recorded and used along with other data in the 
case study analysis to answer question 5. </p>

<p>Question 5 
How does the 'framework for network 
planning' enable an informal network to plan 
and manage linked primary mental 
healthcare for older people in a rural region? </p>

<p>Case study 
Data will be collected throughout the study to evaluate the utility of the 
'framework for network planning' for an informal network to develop more 
integrated mental healthcare for older people in this rural region. These data 
will include records of the governance group and service stakeholder 
workshops. In addition, further service key informant interviews will be 
conducted at the end of the project to explicitly explore whether they have 
found the framework useful or not using the following prompts: 
1. Can you describe how you found the facilitated reflective process 
(workshops, survey, interviews) as a way to manage the range of services 
as a network, in terms of the following: 
▸ Acceptability of the process 
▸ Ability to identify and act on issues 
2. Did the project achieve what you expected? 
3. Would you use this process again-would you change anything? 
Engagement at senior management (governance group) and operational (key 
stakeholder) levels will be essential to develop the trust and insight to 
accurately assess the applicability of the network planning framework. </p>



<p>Fuller J, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e006304. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006304 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>throughout the project and manage sensitivities that 
may arise. 
The research will benefit participating services 
through describing the existence and frequency of 
service links, which can then be used to improve links as 
needed. The main outcome will be a tested planning 
framework that can be used in an informal network to 
engage rural health and social care services in the 
improvement of service coordination for older persons' 
mental healthcare. If effective, the model should 
achieve the following outcomes: 
▸ Better coordination of clinical and other supports to 
meet the mental health needs of older people. 
▸ Collective ownership of innovative older persons' 
mental health service solutions. 
▸ Strengthened partnerships between mental health, 
primary care, aged care and community support 
services. 
▸ Improved and agreed referral pathways and local pro-
tocols between services. 
▸ Evaluation feedback and accountability processes. 
The manner in which these outcomes can be achieved 
in other regions will differ according to local contexts; 
however, the transferable outcome will be the network 
framework for integrated planning. The research team 
will develop recommendations for the application of the 
framework that will be fed up at a national level through 
peak bodies such as the National Primary Health Care 
Partnership, the Mental Health Council of Australia and 
the National Mental Health Consumer and Carer 
Forum. The involvement of senior staff from the main 
service stakeholders (the Medicare Local, the Positive 
Ageing Taskforce and the Country Health SA Local 
Health Network) will facilitate the implementation of 
the findings locally and more broadly across respective 
jurisdictions in mental health, primary care, aged care 
and community services. 
The findings of the research will be produced using 
the Australian Primary Health Care Research Institute 
1:3:25 format to policy makers for research reports. </p>

<p>Author affiliations </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>School of Nursing &amp; Midwifery, Flinders University, Adelaide, Australia </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>School of Medicine, Flinders University, Adelaide, Australia </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Southern Fleurieu &amp; Kangaroo Island Positive Ageing Taskforce, Victor 
Harbor, Australia </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Southern Adelaide-Fleurieu-Kangaroo Island Medicare Local, Bedford Park, 
Australia </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Country Health South Australia Local Health Network Mental Health Services, 
Adelaide, Australia </p>

<p>Contributors JF, CO and EMC designed the study. DOK, JH, SL, JH, AG and 
RR provided methodological input to the study design. AN, PG and RM 
provided input to the feasibility of the study and stakeholder engagement and 
data collection processes. CO and SD undertook the literature review. All 
authors contributed to the writing of the paper and all have approved the final 
version. </p>

<p>Funding The research reported in this paper is a project of the Australian 
Primary Health Care Research Institute, which is supported by a grant from 
the Commonwealth of Australia as represented by the Department of Health 
and Ageing. The information and opinions contained in it do not necessarily </p>

<p>reflect the views or policy of the Australian Primary Health Care Research 
Institute or the Commonwealth of Australia (or the Department of Health and 
Ageing). Additional funding was also provided by a grant from the Nurses' 
Memorial Centre of South Australia and the Faculty of Medicine, Nursing and 
Health Sciences, Flinders University of South Australia. </p>

<p>Competing interests At the time of the study establishment AN, PG and RM 
were all employed in organisations that were a part of the service network that 
is the focus of this study. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Human Research Ethics Committees of the South Australian 
Health Department (HREC/13/SAH/126) and Flinders University (notification 
10/2014). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; internally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement The raw data are to be securely stored in a password 
protected server at the Flinders University of South Australia available to the 
research team only. In line with the participatory nature of the research 
design, analysed data in a de-identified form will be made available to 
participants. Hence these data along with the reporting to the funder will be 
available to other researchers on application to the corresponding author. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Open Access </p>





<p>Fuller J, et al. BMJ Open 2014;4:e006304. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006304 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>