<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4366701" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background Surgical site infections (SSIs) result in significant patient morbidity following 
immediate tissue expander breast reconstruction (ITEBR). This study determined a single ins 
titution's 30day SSI rate and benchmarked it against that among national institutions par 
ticipating in the American College of Surgeons National Surgical Quality Improvement Pro 
gram (ACSNSQIP). 
Methods Women who underwent ITEBR with/without acellular dermal matrix (ADM) were 
identified using the ACSNSQIP database between 2005 and 2011. Patient characteristics 
associated with the 30day SSI rate were determined, and differences in rates between our 
institution and the national database were assessed. 
Results 12,163 patients underwent ITEBR, including 263 at our institution. SSIs occurred in 
416 (3.4%) patients nationwide excluding our institution, with lower rates observed at our 
institution (1.9%). Nationwide, SSIs were significantly more common in ITEBR patients with 
ADM (4.5%) compared to nonADM patients (3.2%, P = 0.005), and this trend was observed 
at our institution (2.1% vs. 1.6%, P = 1.00). A multivariable analysis of all institutions identified 
age ≥ 50 years (odds ratio [OR], 1.4; confidence interval [CI], 1.1-1.7), body mass index ≥ 30 
kg/m 
2 vs. &lt; 25 kg/m 
2 (OR, 3.4; CI, 2.6-4.5), and operative time &gt; 4.25 hours (OR, 1.9; CI, 1.5-
2.4) as risk factors for SSIs. Our institutional SSI rate was lower than the nationwide rate (OR, 
0.4; CI, 0.2-1.1), although this difference was not statistically significant (P = 0.07). 
Conclusions The 30day SSI rate at our institution in patients who underwent ITEBR was 
lower than the nation. SSIs occurred more frequently in procedures involving ADM both 
nationally and at our institution. </p>

<p>Implant-based breast reconstruction rates continue to increase 
across the United States as a percentage of total breast recon-
structions [1-3]. Immediate tissue expander breast reconstruc-
tion (ITEBR) with or without acellular dermal matrix (ADM) 
remains the most common form of post-mastectomy reconstruc-
tion [4]. Many studies have demonstrated that surgical site in-
fections (SSIs) following ITEBR result in significant patient mor-
bidity and health care costs [5]. The American College of Sur-
geons National Surgical Quality Improvement Program (ACS-
NSQIP) database provides outcome data from a wide range of 
centers, thereby creating national standards for postoperative 
complications. As a result, individual institutions are increasing-
ly interested in benchmarking their outcomes against national 
standards in an attempt to improve quality of care and patient 
safety. This study aims to determine the 30-day SSI rate of a sin-
gle institution and benchmark it against that among participat-
ing national institutions for quality improvement purposes. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Data source </p>

<p>Women who underwent mastectomies followed by ITEBR 
with or without ADM between 2005 and 2011 were identified 
using the ACS-NSQIP database. The ACS-NSQIP program has 
developed a large, prospective, nationally validated, multi-insti-
tutional database that collects variables from patients undergo-
ing inpatient and outpatient procedures at over 250 participat-
ing university and private hospitals. The variables analyzed in 
this study included patient demographics, preoperative comor-
bidities, intraoperative proceedings, and postoperative morbidi-
ties for the 30-day period after the procedure. The definitions of 
the variables collected by the ACS-NSQIP program can be found 
on their website [6]. Current audits have shown a disagreement 
rate of less than 2% for program variables using this database 
[7]. Although the ACS-NSQIP program and participating insti-
tutions have collected these data, they are not responsible for 
the statistical validity or the authors' interpretations and/or con-
clusions of the data. </p>

<p>Cohort identification </p>

<p>Women over the age of 18 who underwent mastectomies fol-
lowed by ITEBR were identified using the Current Procedural 
Terminology codes for mastectomies (codes 19180, 19182, 
19240, 19301, 19302, 19303, 19304, 19305, 19306, or 19307) 
for their primary procedure, and their concurrent tissue expand-
er placement procedures (code 19357) were identified in the </p>

<p>ACS-NSQIP database. In addition, those who received acellular 
dermal matrix were identified (code 15330). The subset of these 
patients treated at our institution was also identified. Patient 
variables included age, body mass index (BMI) ( &lt; 25, 25-29.9, 
and ≥ 30 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>), smoking status, steroid use, diabetes mellitus, 
preoperative radiation, year of operation, and operative time 
( &gt; 4.25 hours vs. ≤ 4.25 hours quartiles), focusing on the lon-
gest operations. The primary goal of this study was to assess the 
postoperative 30-day SSI rate. Three types of SSIs have been de-
fined: superficial (limited to the skin and subcutaneous tissue), 
deep (involving deep tissues including fascia and muscle), and 
organ space (involving the surrounding organs) [8]. Unless oth-
erwise specified, patients from our institution were excluded 
from any nationwide data reported in this study. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Demographic, clinical, and procedural characteristics of patients 
who did and did not develop SSIs were compared using chi-
square tests; Fisher's exact tests were used when low expected 
cell counts were observed. Multivariable logistic regression was 
used to determine patient characteristics independently predic-
tive of 30-day SSIs and to assess the difference in likelihood of 
SSIs at our institution compared to other institutions in the 
ACS-NSQIP database. Results were considered significant if P-
values were less than 0.05. Patient characteristics that resulted in 
a P &lt; 0.05 in the univariate analysis or that were deemed to be 
clinically relevant were included in the multivariable logistic re-
gression model as independent variables, with the SSI rate as 
the dependent variable. Statistical analyses were performed in 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., Cary, NC, USA). </p>

<p>Characteristic 
All 
(n = 12,426) </p>

<p>Acellular dermal matrix 
P-value 
ADM 
(n = 2,030) </p>

<p>No ADM 
(n = 10,396) </p>

<p>Nationwide vs. our institution 
&lt; 0.001 
Nationwide 
12,163 
1,890 (15.5) 10,273 (84.5) 
Our institution 
263 
140 (53.2) 
123 (46.8) 
Year of operation 
&lt; 0.001 
2005 
171 
0 (0.0) 
171 (100.0) 
2006 
597 
25 (4.2) 
572 (95.8) 
2007 
1,401 
145 (10.3) 1,256 (89.7) 
2008 
2,007 
291 (14.5) 1,716 (85.5) 
2009 
2,677 
383 (14.3) 2,294 (85.7) 
2010 
2,905 
572 (19.7) 2,333 (80.3) 
2011 
2,668 
614 (23.0) 2,054 (77.0) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%). </p>

<p>Table 1. Those with acellular dermal matrix (ADM) compared 
to those with no ADM in our institution, nationwide, and 
each year between 2005 to 2011 </p>

<p>Winocour S et al. SSI in breast reconstruction </p>



<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>A total of 12,163 patients underwent ITEBR between 2005 and 
2011, including 263 patients at our institution (Table 1). Over 
that period, ADM was used in 15.5% of all ITEBR procedures 
across the nation excluding our institution, and the percentage 
of cases with ADM steadily increased from 4.4% in 2006 to 22.5% 
in 2011 (Table 2). At our institution, 53.2% of patients received 
ADM from 2005 to 2011, with an increase in ADM use from 
57.7% to 86.4% among cases recorded in 2008 and 2011, re-
spectively (Table 2). ADM was not used in breast reconstruc-
tions at our institution before 2008, and the use of ADM during 
breast reconstructions was not seen in the NSQIP participant 
use data file until 2006. 
Nationwide, SSIs occurred in 416 patients (3.4%) compared 
to five patients (1.9%) at our institution (Table 3). The annual 
SSI rate across national institutions from 2005 to 2011 varied </p>

<p>Year of operation 
Acellular dermal matrix </p>

<p>ADM 
No ADM </p>

<p>Nationwide 
2005 
0 (0) 
171 (100.0) 
2006 
25 (4.4) 
541 (95.6) 
2007 
145 (10.6) 
1,218 (89.4) 
2008 
250 (12.9) 
1,686 (87.1) 
2009 
330 (12.6) 
2,281 (87.4) 
2010 
545 (19.0) 
2,325 (81.0) 
2011 
595 (22.5) 
2,051 (77.5) 
Our institution 
2005 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
2006 
0 (0) 
31 (100.0) 
2007 
0 (0) 
38 (100.0) 
2008 
41 (57.7) 
30 (42.3) 
2009 
53 (80.3) 
13 (19.7) 
2010 
27 (77.1) 
8 (22.9) 
2011 
19 (86.4) 
3 (13.6) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%). </p>

<p>Table 2. Those with acellular dermal matrix (ADM) compared 
to those with no ADM by year in our institution and nationwide </p>

<p>Characteristic 
All patients 
No SSI 
SSI 
P-value </p>

<p>All institutions (n) 
12,426 
12,005 
421 
Nationwide vs. our institution 
0.18 
Nationwide 
12,163 
11,747 (96.6) 
416 (3.4) 
Our institution 
263 
258 (98.1) 
5 (1.9) 
National institutions excluding our institution (n) 
12,163 
11,747 
416 
Year of operation 
0.50 
2005 
171 
161 (94.2) 
10 (5.8) 
2006 
566 
551 (97.3) 
15 (2.7) 
2007 
1,363 
1,315 (96.5) 
48 (3.5) 
2008 
1,936 
1,873 (96.7) 
63 (3.3) 
2009 
2,611 
2,521 (96.6) 
90 (3.4) 
2010 
2,870 
2,778 (96.8) 
92 (3.2) 
2011 
2,646 
2,548 (96.3) 
98 (3.7) 
Age category 
&lt; 0.001 
18-49 yr 
5,875 
5,713 (97.2) 
162 (2.8) 
≥ 50 yr 
6,551 
6,292 (96.0) 
259 (4.0) 
Body mass index category </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 25 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>5,574 
5,477 (98.3) 
97 (1.7) 
25.0-29.9 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3,380 
3,266 (96.6) 
114 (3.4) 
≥ 30 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3,104 
2,901 (93.5) 
203 (6.5) 
Current smoker </p>

<p>b) </p>

<p>0.21 
No 
10,487 
10,137 (96.7) 
350 (3.3) 
Yes 
1,675 
1,609 (96.1) 
66 (3.9) 
Radiotherapy in the previous 90 days </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>1.00 
No 
10,926 
10,550 (96.6) 
376 (3.4) 
Yes 
40 
39 (97.5) 
1 (2.5) 
Steroid use for a chronic condition 
1.00 
No 
12,052 
11,639 (96.6) 
413 (3.4) 
Yes 
111 
108 (97.3) 
3 (2.7) 
Total operation time quartiles 
&lt; 0.001 
0-150 min (0 to 2.5 hr) 
3,322 
3,238 (97.5) 
84 (2.5) 
151-195 min ( &gt; 2.5 to 3.25 hr) 
2,870 
2,787 (97.1) 
83 (2.9) 
196-255 min ( &gt; 3.25 to 4.25 hr) 
2,997 
2,902 (96.8) 
95 (3.2) 
≥ 256 min ( &gt; 4.25 hr) 
2,974 
2,820 (94.8) 
154 (5.2) 
Diabetes mellitus 
0.001 
None 
11,837 
11,450 (96.7) 
387 (3.3) 
Insulin or non-insulin/oral 
589 
555 (94.2) 
34 (5.8) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%). 
a) Body mass index was unavailable for 105 patients; 
b) Smoking status was unavailable for 1 patient. Current smokers were those who had reported smoking during the 
previous year; </p>

<p>c) </p>

<p>Radiotherapy data were unavailable for 1,197 patients. </p>

<p>Table 3. Factors associated with surgical site infections (SSIs) </p>

<p>Vol. 42 / No. 2 / March 2015 </p>



<p>from 2.7% to 5.8%, but this variation was not statistically signifi-
cant (P = 0.50). The occurrence of 30-day SSIs was significantly 
greater in ADM patients compared to non-ADM patients na-
tionally (4.3% vs. 3.2%, respectively; P = 0.010). This trend was 
also observed at our institution (2.1% vs. 1.6%, respectively), al-
though it was not statistically significant (P = 1.00) (Table 4). 
Of the three types of SSIs, the most common was superficial, 
followed by deep, and finally organ space SSI (Table 4). A four-
level SSI variable (none, organ space, deep, and superficial) was 
then created and patients with more than one type of SSI were 
assigned to the most serious category, which was organ, followed 
by deep, and then superficial. SSIs still proved to be significantly 
more common in ADM patients when compared to non-ADM 
patients (P = 0.038). However, despite the low numbers of pa-
tients, this trend was not observed at our institution (P = 1.00) 
(Table 4). 
Across the nation, the univariate analysis identified age ≥ 50 
years (P&lt; 0.001), a higher BMI (P&lt; 0.001), diabetes (P= 0.001), </p>

<p>and a greater total operative time (P &lt; 0.001) as risk factors for 
SSIs. In addition, the absence of current smoking was associated 
with lower SSI rates, but this trend was not statistically signifi-
cant. Radiotherapy and the absence of steroid use did not ap-
pear to affect the SSI rate (P = 1.00 and P = 1.00, respectively) 
(Table 3). 
The multivariable analysis including all institutions identified 
age ≥ 50 years (odds ratio [OR], 1.4; confidence interval [CI], 
1.1-1.7), BMI ≥ 30 kg/m 
2 vs. &lt; 25 kg/m 
2 (OR, 3.4; CI, 2.6-
4.5), and operative time &gt; 4.25 hours (OR, 1.9; CI, 1.5-2.4) as 
risk factors for SSIs. Univariate and multivariable analysis of SSI 
risk factors could not be performed separately for patients at our 
institution due to an insufficient total number of cases of SSIs 
during this period. After adjusting for clinical and procedural 
characteristics, our institutional SSI risk was lower than other 
institutions in the ACS-NSQIP database (OR, 0.4; CI, 0.2-1.1), 
although this difference was not statistically significant (P = 0.07) 
(Table 5). </p>

<p>Characteristic 
All patients 
No SSI 
SSI 
P-value 
Organ space 
SSI 
Deep SSI 
Superficial 
SSI 
P-value </p>

<p>ADM vs. no ADM nationwide 
No. of patients 
12,163 
11,747 
416 
86 
135 
195 
Acellular dermal matrix 
0.005 
0.038 
Yes 
1,890 
1,805 (95.5) 
85 (4.5) 
18 (1.0) 
25 (1.3) 
42 (2.2) 
No 
10,273 
9,942 (96.8) 
331 (3.2) 
68 (0.7) 
110 (1.1) 
153 (1.5) 
ADM vs. no ADM at our institution 
No. of patients 
263 
258 
5 
3 
0 
2 
Acellular dermal matrix 
1.00 
1.00 
Yes 
140 
137 (97.9) 
3 (2.1) 
2 (1.4) 
0 (0.0) 
1 (0.7) 
No 
123 
121 (98.4) 
2 (1.6) 
1 (0.8) 
0 (0.0) 
1 (0.8) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%). 
SSI, surgical site infections; ADM, acellular dermal matrix. </p>

<p>Table 4. SSIs between those with an ADM compared to those without </p>

<p>Variable 
Level 
P-value 
OR estimate </p>

<p>Lower 95% 
confidence limit 
for OR </p>

<p>Upper 95% 
confidence limit 
for OR </p>

<p>Nationwide vs. our institution 
Nationwide vs. our institution 
0.07 
0.4 
0.2 
1.1 
Acellular dermal matrix 
Dermal matrix vs. other 
0.26 
1.2 
0.9 
1.5 
Age (yr) 
≥ 50 vs. 18-49 
0.005 
1.4 
1.1 
1.7 
Body mass index (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
25.0-29.9 vs. &lt; 25 
&lt; 0.001 
1.9 
1.4 
2.5 
≥ 30 vs. &lt; 25 
&lt; 0.001 
3.4 
2.6 
4.5 
Current smokers </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Yes vs. no 
0.36 
1.1 
0.9 
1.5 
Radiotherapy for malignancy in the previous 90 days 
Yes vs. no 
0.79 
0.8 
0.1 
5.6 
Steroid use for a chronic condition 
Yes vs. no 
0.82 
0.9 
0.3 
2.8 
Total operation time (top quartile vs. the three 
remaining quartiles) </p>

<p>≥ 256 min ( &gt; 4.25 hr) vs. 
0-255 min (0-4.25 hr) </p>

<p>&lt; 0.001 
1.9 
1.5 
2.4 </p>

<p>Diabetes 
Yes vs. no 
0.45 
1.2 
0.8 
1.7 </p>

<p>OR, odds ratio. </p>

<p>a) </p>

<p>Within one year. </p>

<p>Table 5. Results of the multivariable logistic regression for the prediction of surgical site infections </p>

<p>Winocour S et al. SSI in breast reconstruction </p>



<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>ITEBR is the most common modality for breast reconstruction 
in the United States, with several studies showing increasing 
rates in recent years [1-3]. The use of ADM as an adjunct in 
ITEBR has also become more common, with numerous studies 
demonstrating its benefits [9-11], including increased expander 
fill volume on initial operation. These benefits reduce the need 
for additional postoperative expansions, improve the lower pole 
coverage, and enhance the inframammary fold definition [9-
11]. However, other studies have demonstrated increased rates 
of postoperative complications such as SSIs and seroma among 
this patient population [12,13]. 
Our goal was to determine the 30-day SSI rate of our institu-
tion among patients who underwent ITEBR with or without 
the use of ADM and to compare our institution's rate to that of 
other institutions on a national level. We identified an overall 
SSI incidence of 3.4% in other ACS-NSQIP institutions, com-
pared to 1.9% at our institution (P = 0.18). SSIs were significant-
ly more common in ADM patients compared to non-ADM pa-
tients nationally (4.5% vs. 3.2%, respectively; P = 0.005), and 
this trend was also observed at our institution (2.1% vs. 1.6%, 
respectively; P = 1.00). Unsurprisingly, organ space SSIs, which 
is the most invasive and severe type of SSI, were observed less 
frequently than deep and superficial SSIs were nationwide. When 
analyzed by subtype, SSIs were still more common in ADM pa-
tients than non-ADM patients (P = 0.038). Several studies have 
demonstrated similar findings [14,15]. Chun et al. [15] showed 
increased seroma and infection rates in patients reconstructed 
with ADM, although they proposed that the increased infection 
rate may have been mediated by seroma and/or native breast 
skin flap necrosis in this group of patients. 
Many modalities have been implemented to reduce these com-
plications, including judicious drain placement with strict crite-
ria for removal [14], the consistent use of perioperative antibi-
otics [16], and a strict sterile technique in the operating room 
[16]. More recently, the use of sterile ready-to-use ADM has been 
advocated [15]. Weichman et al. [17] compared ready-to-use 
ADM to aseptic ADM in a patient cohort of 546 reconstructed 
breasts and demonstrated that ready-to-use ADM was associat-
ed with a decrease in the overall infection rate, major infection 
rate, and the need for implant explantation. They concluded that 
the use of ready-to-use ADM mitigates the risk of infectious com-
plications when compared with aseptic ADM [17]. At our insti-
tution, a strict sterile technique and consistent administration of 
perioperative antibiotics while performing these procedures are 
routine. We also change our gloves before handling the prosthe-
sis and avoid contact between the ADM and the patient's skin </p>

<p>before insertion and placement. The use of drains is also routine 
in ITEBR, with strict criteria for removal when the output is 
&lt; 30 mL per day for two consecutive days. Finally, oral antibiot-
ics are routinely administered until the drains are removed. Over-
all, there has been a shift towards the use of sterile ready-to-use 
ADM at our institution in the last few years, although this is not 
reflected in the ACS-NSQIP database. It is possible that some of 
these modalities help explain the lower SSI rates at our institu-
tion when compared to the national average. However, we rec-
ognize that the possible effect of these institutional practices is 
anecdotal and have not been confirmed by a rigorous trial. 
Several risk factors for SSIs were identified in this study, includ-
ing increased BMI, age, and total operative time. Obesity is a well-
established risk factor for surgical complications and wound heal-
ing. We found that across all institutions, patients with a BMI 
&lt; 25 kg/m 
2 had a 1.7% SSI rate, compared to a 6.5% SSI rate in 
patients with a BMI ≥ 30 kg/m 
2 (P &lt; 0.001). These findings cor-
roborate those of other publications [18,19]. According to Fischer 
et al. 's [18] review of the impact of obesity on breast reconstruc-
tion outcomes, patients with higher BMIs had a higher incidence 
of comorbidities and experienced higher complication rates, in-
cluding wounds, medical complications, infectious complica-
tions, major surgical complications, prosthesis loss, and return 
to the operating room, all of which were statistically significant. 
Increasing age ( ≥ 50 years) was also associated with higher SSI 
rates by both univariate analysis (P &lt; 0.001) and multivariable 
logistic regression (OR, 1.4; CI, 1.1-1.7). The univariate analy-
sis allows us to infer that this patient group has a higher incidence 
of comorbidities that would make them more susceptible to 
SSIs. However, the statistically significant results of the multi-
variable analysis suggest that age in itself is an intrinsic risk factor 
or that we did not or could not control for other risk factors in 
our model. This finding corresponds to the findings of other 
previously published studies [20,21]. Shermak et al. [20], in their 
study of 2,156 reduction mammoplasties, found that women 
older than 50 years were more likely to experience infection and 
wound healing problems. They concluded that hormonal defi-
ciencies might partially account for this finding. 
Longer total operative times were also associated with a pro-
gressively higher SSI rate nationally (excluding our institution). 
Procedures lasting &lt; 2.5 hours had a 2.5% SSI occurrence com-
pared to those that lasted &gt; 2.5-3.25 hours (2.9%), &gt; 3.25-4.25 
hours (3.2%) and &gt; 4.25 hours (5.2%), P &lt; 0.001. An associa-
tion between prolonged operative time and complications is well 
established in the general surgery literature [22,23]. However, 
Procter et al. [22] show that the determinants of prolonged op-
erative time are multifactorial; therefore, we should interpret 
these results with caution. In contrast, Fogarty et al. [24] suggest </p>

<p>Vol. 42 / No. 2 / March 2015 </p>



<p>that operative time alone is not a major determinant of postop-
erative complications, and that the type of surgery and the pa-
tient's overall condition are more important predictors of the 
outcome. 
This study has several limitations. First, this analysis was limit-
ed to 30-day outcomes and a potentially significant group of pa-
tients can present with SSIs more than 30 days after the opera-
tion. These patients may also have drains in place, theoretically 
increasing their risk of SSIs. Nevertheless, we would expect that 
patients with SSIs more than 30 days after the operation would 
present equally frequently at our institution and other institu-
tions nationwide, resulting in a similar trend in SSI rates. How-
ever, including data from SSIs occurring more than 30 days after 
surgery might have provided us with a sufficient number of cas-
es to evaluate SSI risk factors specific to our institution. Another 
limitation is selection bias in the ACS-NSQIP database. Hospi-
tal participation in NSQIP is voluntary, and although the data-
base includes a large number of both university and private hos-
pitals, there may be a selection bias that affects the accuracy of 
the data when benchmarking against national averages. In addi-
tion, only a percentage of patient cases within any given partici-
pating institution are included in the database. Although this se-
lection is random, it does not completely eliminate bias. Finally, 
many important postoperative complications relevant to our pa-
tient population are not captured by the ACS-NSQIP, such as 
mastectomy skin flap necrosis and seroma. 
Overall, the 30-day SSI rate at our institution in patients un-
dergoing ITEBR was lower than the nationwide rate as reflected 
in the ACS-NSQIP database. Instances of SSIs were more com-
mon in procedures involving ADM both nationally and at our 
institution. National risk factors for SSIs include increasing age, 
obesity, and longer operative times; however, the insufficient 
number of cases at our institution did not allow for the bench-
marking of these risk factors at a national level. Further work is 
under way to confirm whether SSI risk factors at our institution 
are similar to those across the nation. Retrospective cohort stud-
ies outside of the ACS-NSQIP database would be necessary to 
obtain sufficient patient numbers to benchmark SSI rates against 
that in the rest of the nation. Nevertheless, ongoing comparisons 
between individual institutions and the national ACS-NSQIP 
database are important to identify roles for quality improvement 
projects to improve surgical outcomes. </p>



<p>Winocour S et al. SSI in breast reconstruction </p>





</text></tei>