<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4377530" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Urinary catheterization is one of the main measures used to treat and care for hospitalized patients. Several complications 
have been attributed to the presence of latex with routine Foley catheters. Therefore, some studies have recommended that Nelatone 
catheters be substituted for the ordinary Foley catheters to prevent these complications. 
Objectives: This study aimed to compare the rates of urinary tract infection (UTI) in rabbits catheterized either with Foley or with Nelatone 
catheters. 
Materials and Methods: A randomized controlled trial was conducted on 60 rabbits that were randomly assigned to three groups of 
twenty. The first group was catheterized using Nelatone catheter; the second group was catheterized using Foley catheter and the third 
group was studied without performing any catheterization. After seven days, urine samples were collected using suprapubic aspiration 
and were sent to the laboratory for culture. Descriptive statistics were calculated. Moreover, chi-square and Fisher's exact tests were used 
for data analysis. 
Results: At the end of the study, four cases in the Nelatone group and 12 cases in the Foley group presented with UTI (P = 0.01). No positive 
urine cultures were found in the control group. 
Conclusions: The Nelatone catheters, compared with the Foley ones, had a lower risk of UTI in the long term use. Verifying this claim by 
further studies can have an important role in reducing UTIs in patients using urinary catheters. </p>

<p>Keywords: Urinary Tract Infection; Urinary Catheterization; Catheters; Rabbit </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015, Kashan University of Medical Sciences. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non-
Commercial 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial 
usages, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>In several studies carried out on the incidence of noso-
comial infections, urinary tract infections (UTI) were the 
most frequent and consisted more than 40% of all hospi-
tal infections (1-7). In spite of the broad spectrum antibi-
otics use, UTIs are still a cause of considerable morbidity 
and mortality in the modern medicine. UTIs are usually 
associated with urinary catheters (UC) or urologic proce-
dures (8-10). Urinary catheterization is one of the main 
measures used for the treatment and caring for hospital-
ized patients. It is associated with the emergence of bac-
teria in the urine, unpleasant symptoms, and complica-
tions that can reduce the quality of health care services 
(11). Despite considerable advancements in manufactur-
ing medical devices such as UCs, infections caused by 
these devices are common, costly, and can cause signifi-
cant patient morbidity (2, 12). 
The pathogenesis of infections caused by medical de-
vices is not well understood and a variety of factors are 
considered such as susceptibility of the host and the mi-</p>

<p>croorganisms' ability to attach to the medical devices (8). 
Biofilm formation along the catheter surface is the most 
important cause of bacteriuria. Biofilm formation begins 
immediately after catheter insertion, when organisms 
adhere to a conditioning film of host proteins which 
forms along the catheter surface. Both the interior and 
exterior catheter surfaces are involved. Bacteria usually 
originate from the periurethral area or ascend the drain-
age tubing following colonization of the drainage bag 
(13). There are different types of UCs in terms of their ma-
terials, sizes and shapes and each of them is made for a 
specific purpose. The aim of this diversity is to reduce the 
risk of UTI (4, 14). UCs are also categorized considering 
their location and duration of use (15). Due to the fact that 
in some patients, such as those admitted to the intensive 
care units, the UCs should long remain in the bladder, a 
variety of specialized antiseptic/antibiotic impregnated 
catheters have been designed to reduce the risk of UTI; 
but they are expensive and not available in some medical </p>

<p>Nouri S et al. </p>

<p>Nurs Midwifery Stud. 2015;4(1):e24363 </p>

<p>
centers (16) and some studies showed these catheters did 
not reduce symptomatic UTI (17). 
Therefore many specialists use ordinary Foley catheters 
in these circumstances (14). However, due to the existence 
of latex with these catheters, changes in bladder tissue, 
infections, and in some cases hemorrhagic cystitis has 
been reported. Thus, in some studies it has recommend-
ed that Nelatone catheters should be substituted for ordi-
nary Foley catheters to prevent these complications (18). </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>Due to the fact that there are no studies to compare the 
complications of these two types of UCs according to the 
laboratory tests and urine cultures, this study aimed to 
compare the rates of UTI in rabbits catheterized either 
with Foley or Nelatone catheters. </p>

<p>3. Materials and Methods </p>

<p>This experimental study was conducted at Kashan 
University of Medical Sciences from July to September 
2013. In this study, 60 five-months-old New Zealand male 
rabbits weighing 2 to 2.5 kilograms were randomly as-
signed to three groups of twenty. One week before study, 
animals were fed similarly and were kept at 21 ± 1˚C with 
12 hour light/dark cycle (lights on from 8:00 AM to 8:00 
PM). Twenty rabbits were catheterized using Nelatone 
catheters (No: 8, made by VRP Co, Malaysia); the second 
group were catheterized using Foley catheters (No: 8, 
made by VRP Co, Malaysia). Rabbits in the third group 
were selected as control group and were not catheter-
ized. For catheterization, the animal was placed in a 
horizontal dorsal decubitus position on the surgical 
table and its paws were fixed to the extremities of the 
table with thin ropes. The catheters were installed by 
a surgery resident using correct technique of aseptic 
catheter insertion and measures for instant, adhesive 
fabric for fixation and use of lubricant gel for insert-
ing the catheter into urethra were carefully performed 
under sterile condition. The catheters were kept inside 
the bladder for seven days. Then urine samples (i.e.1 mL) 
were collected from all the three groups through supra-
pubic method under aseptic conditions. The specimens 
were immediately sent to the laboratory and cultured 
on blood agar medium. Based on the result of urine cul-
tures, a UTI was diagnosed when one or more organisms 
were present at quantitative counts of greater than or 
equal to 100 colony-forming units (CFU) per milliliter. 
Then the causative organisms were determined. All data 
were documented in a checklist consisting items on the 
name of group, the code of rabbit, the number of CFU 
in the urine culture and the type of the bacteria grew in 
the culture medium. </p>

<p>3.1. Ethical Considerations </p>

<p>Animal handling and all experiments were performed </p>

<p>in accordance with the international guidelines set out 
in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals 
(Institute of Laboratory Animal Resources, 1996) (19) and 
the Helsinki declaration has been respected. The study 
protocol was approved by the local research council and 
the research ethics committee at Kashan University of 
Medical Sciences, Kashan, Iran. </p>

<p>3.2. Data Analysis </p>

<p>All information was extracted from data registration 
forms and the data were entered into <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.0</rs> software. 
Chi-square and Fisher's exact tests were used for data 
analysis. Statistical significance was considered at P value 
&lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>No positive urine cultures were found in the control 
group. The number of UTI were four cases in the Nelatone 
group and 12 cases in the Foley group (P = 0.01) (Table 1). 
The frequency of entrococcal infection was less in the 
Nelatone group (3 cases) compared with the Foley group 
(nine cases) and this difference was statistically signifi-
cant (P = 0.038). Moreover, three cases of staphylococcal 
UTI were observed in the Foley group compared to only 
one case in the Nelatone group (P = 0.605) (Table 2). </p>

<p>Table 1. The Numbers of Urinary Tract Infection in the Nela-
tone Group and the Foley Group a </p>

<p>Groups 
P Value b </p>

<p>Nelatone 
Foley </p>

<p>Urinary tract infection </p>

<p>No 
16 (80) 
8 (40) 
0.01 </p>

<p>Yes 
4 (20) 
12 (60) 
0.01 </p>

<p>a All Values are Presented as No. (%). 
b Chi Square Test. </p>

<p>Table 2. The Frequency of Organism in the Nelatone Group 
Compared with the Foley a </p>

<p>Bacteria Isolated from 
the Urine Culture </p>

<p>Groups 
P Value </p>

<p>Foley 
Nelatone </p>

<p>Entrococcal Infection 
0.038 b </p>

<p>No 
11 (55) </p>

<p>Yes 
9 (45) </p>

<p>Staphylococcal 
infection 
0.605 c </p>

<p>No 
17 (85) 
19 (95) </p>

<p>Yes 
3 (15) 
1 (5) </p>

<p>a All Values are presented as No. (%). 
b Chi Square Test. 
c Fisher's Exact Test Performed. </p>

<p>Nouri S et al. </p>



<p>Nurs Midwifery Stud. 2015;4(1):e24363 </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, UTI was observed in the both interven-
tion groups but no infection was observed in the con-
trol group. There were significant differences between 
the two types of catheters in causing UTI and the Nela-
tone catheter was associated with a lower risk of UTI. 
Few studies have published in this field. These studies 
only assessed the risk of developing UTI after inserting 
a UC and have reported conflicting results. Uckay et al. 
have studied 8169 patients with UCs and reported that 
the long-term exposure to a UC is a definite risk factor 
for development of UTI. They suggest that further in-
vestigation is warranted to determine the other factors 
affecting UC associated UTIs (20). Consistent with re-
sults of the present study, Uckay et al. confirmed that a 
higher rate of UTI should be expected in patients who 
undergo urinary catheterization. However, they did not 
investigate the difference in the rates of UTI in patients 
with different types of UCs. On the other hand, Smarick 
et al. studied the incidence of catheter-associated UTI 
in dogs and reported that placement of an indwelling 
UC is associated with a low risk of UTI in dogs. They also 
reported that the results of bacterial culture of UC tips 
cannot predict the development of catheter-associated 
UTIs (21). Hosseinpour et al. (16) and Nicolle (13) have also 
observed no significant difference between silicone and 
latex catheters regarding the risk of UTI. This finding is 
similar to Schumm et al. (4) who reported that there is 
not enough evidence on superiority of different types 
of catheters on each other considering the risk of UTI in 
hospitalized patients with short-term catheterization. 
These studies along with our results show the necessity 
to determine the factors affecting the rate of TUIs in cath-
eterized patients. 
The most effective way to prevent infection is to limit 
catheter use and discontinue the catheter when no lon-
ger needed. Catheter removal or exchange might also 
be useful in management of UTI associated with UCs 
(7). Nurses can help to prevent catheter-associated UTIs 
through using aseptic technique on insertion, follow 
best practice in ongoing care and prompt removing of 
catheters (22). 
Some researchers indicate that antibiotic prophylaxis 
significantly reduced the rate of catheter-associated UTIs 
(23, 24) but guidelines do not recommend routine use of 
antibiotics (23, 25) or antimicrobial coated catheters (13,  25) to prevent catheter-associated UTIs. 
In the present study, the microorganisms isolated from 
the rabbits with UTI, were enterococcus and staphylo-
coccus. However, in a study on patients with symptom-
atic UTI, Escherichia coli (E. coli), Klebsiella pneumoniae, 
Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Acinetobacter spp, Staphylococ-
cus, Enterococcus and Gram-negative bacteria were the 
most common isolated organisms (26). In two other 
human studies, E. coli was the predominant organism 
isolated from catheterized patients (27, 28). Nonethe-</p>

<p>less, in an animal study, E. coli and Proteus spp. were more 
frequent in non-catheterized dogs, whereas Enterobacter 
spp. and Staphylococcus spp. were more frequent in cath-
eterized dogs (29). Evidence show that the patients' skin 
and high-touch environmental surfaces are important 
sources for contamination of UCs in place, in hospital-
ized patients (30). 
In this study, we conducted an investigation to iden-
tify the most appropriate catheter (Foley vs. Nelatone) 
for short-term urinary catheterization in animal model. 
We did not evaluate bladder histological changes in our 
animals and this would be one of the weaknesses of the 
present study. In conclusion, there was a significant dif-
ference between Nelatone and Foley catheters in pro-
ducing UTIs. Using Nelatone catheters bear a far lower 
risk of infection. Considering the high prevalence of UTI 
after long-term use of a UCs in hospitalized patients and 
the subsequent prolonged hospitalization and health 
care financial burdens, it can be suggested that Nelatone 
catheters may be used instead of Foley ones. Further in-
vestigation is warranted to determine the effectiveness 
of the type of the UC and the appropriate type of catheter 
for each patient. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors would like to appreciate the kind assistance 
and financial support provided by the Vice-Chancellor for 
Research at Kashan University of Medical Sciences. </p>

<p>Funding/Support </p>

<p>This study was supported financially by the Vice-Chan-
cellor for Research of Kashan University of Medical Sci-
ences (Grant number: 9067). </p>

<p>Financial Disclosure </p>

<p>No benefits in any form were received or would be 
re¬ceived from a commercial party related directly or 
indi¬rectly to the subject of this manuscript. </p>

<p>Authors' Contribution </p>

<p>Saeed Nouri: Acquisition of data, analysis and inter-
pretation of data, study supervision, study concept and 
design and statistical analysis, technical, and material 
support. Mohammad Reza Sharif: Drafting of the manu-
script, critical revision of the manuscript for important 
intellectual content, administrative, technical, and ma-
terial support. Mehrdad Hosseinpour: Drafting of the 
manuscript and critical revision of the manuscript for 
important intellectual content. Shima Farokhi: Drafting 
of the manuscript, critical revision of the manuscript for 
important intellectual content administrative, techni-
cal, and material support. Mohammad Hossein Sharif: 
Drafting of the manuscript, critical revision of the man-
uscript for important intellectual content administra-
tive, technical, and material support. </p>

<p>Nouri S et al. </p>

<p>Nurs Midwifery Stud. 2015;4(1):e24363 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>