<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4934460" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA Version 
13</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StataCorp LP, College Station, TX, USA</rs>Figure 2 OS extrapolation result, using a piecewise model. 
Abbreviation: OS, overall survival. </p>

<p>ClinicoEconomics and Outcomes Research 2016:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>329 </p>

<p>Extrapolating OS for RR-DTC from placebo-controlled trial </p>

<p>Using the KM + exponentially extrapolated tail, the 
benefit associated with lenvatinib, relative to placebo, was 
4.45 months pre-extrapolation and estimated at 11.13 months 
postextrapolation -giving a total OS benefit of 15.58 months 
with lenvatinib treatment over the 120-month (10-year) 
time-horizon. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>OS is a key outcome in determining the efficacy of cancer thera-
pies in clinical trial settings. 19 An OS benefit can be difficult to 
demonstrate due to the limited duration of clinical trials and 
the potential confounding due to subsequent treatments that 
patients may receive. 11 This was the case in the SELECT, in 
which ~50% of patients remained alive at the 34-month data 
cutoff point, and 87.8% of patients originally randomized to 
receive placebo had switched over to lenvatinib following docu-
mented disease progression. The purpose of this analysis was 
to extrapolate OS data from the SELECT, in order to estimate 
the potential long-term benefits of lenvatinib for use in future 
cost-effectiveness evaluations. Our work is novel in that it uses 
a holistic approach in the selection of the most appropriate 
model for the long-term extrapolation of survival when a high 
percentage of individuals are still alive at the end of follow-up. 
The extrapolation of OS data used an RPSFT model to cor-
rect for potential confounding due to crossover 14 and followed </p>

<p>a previously published, systematic method to determine the 
most suitable approach to extrapolate OS data. 13 The use of this 
systematic method (involving five criteria) 13 was considered a 
strength of this analysis. Testing of Criterion 1 regarding the 
PT assumption was inconclusive as the log-cumulative hazard 
OS plots from SELECT were relatively straight but not paral-
lel, while the global test for a PT effect was not significant. 
While some researchers would not consider the evidence 
regarding the use of the PT assumption to be prohibitive, it 
is the opinion of the authors that, if using a PT assumption, 
proof should be presented that individual models and piece-
wise models (such as the KM model + extrapolated tail) are 
inferior. Piecewise models use the observed hazard from the 
clinical trial data by applying the KM survivor estimator over 
the trial period; thus, they can be superior to parametric mod-
els and individual models when their underlying assumptions 
are inappropriate. Therefore, a piecewise model (ie, KM + 
extrapolated tail) appeared to be a suitable alternative. 
A potential limitation of this analysis is that OS for the 
placebo arm of the SELECT was obtained by fitting an 
RPSFT model. Although this approach can be used to correct 
for potential confounding due to the crossover design of the 
SELECT, a key assumption in RPSFT models is that the treat-
ment is acting by multiplying survival time by a given factor 
once patients start receiving active treatment. Therefore, OS </p>

<p>Table 5 Summary statistics of pre-and post-cutoff OS (120-month time-horizon) -survival difference (months) </p>

<p>This analysis and publication were funded by Eisai Inc. 
We thank Brigitte Moore (DRG Abacus) for help with the 
preparation of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>GT is an employee of Eisai Inc. AB received an honorarium 
for his validation of the analysis. There are no other conflicts 
of interest in this work. </p>



<p>ClinicoEconomics and Outcomes Research 2016:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>332 </p>

<p>Tremblay et al </p>

<p>Supplementary materials </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>-3 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-8 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-3 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>-1 
0 
1 
2 
ln(time) </p>

<p>Exponential </p>

<p>Log-Logistic 
Log-Normal </p>

<p>Log-cumulative hazard -proportional treatment models </p>

<p>Weibull </p>

<p>Gamma 
Gompertz </p>

<p>3 
4 </p>

<p>-1 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>ln(time) </p>

<p>Placebo Kaplan-Meier 
Lenvatinib Kaplan-Meier 
Placebo fitted model 
Lenvima fitted model </p>

<p>3 
4 
-1 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>ln(time) </p>

<p>3 
4 
-1 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>ln(time) </p>

<p>3 
4 </p>

<p>-1 
0 
1 
2 
ln(time) </p>

<p>3 
4 
-1 
0 
1 
2 
ln(time) </p>

<p>3 
4 
ln[-ln(survival probability)] 
ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>ln[-ln(survival probability)] 
ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>Figure S1 Log-cumulative hazard plots for OS comparing observed (KM) with fitted estimates obtained from PT models. 
Abbreviations: KM, Kaplan-Meier; OS, overall survival; PT, proportional treatment. </p>

<p>ClinicoEconomics and Outcomes Research 2016:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>ClinicoEconomics and Outcomes Research </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: https://www.dovepress.com/clinicoeconomics-and-outcomes-research-journal </p>

<p>ClinicoEconomics and Outcomes Research is an international, peer-
reviewed open-access journal focusing on health technology assess-
ment, pharmacoeconomics and outcomes research in the areas of 
diagnosis, medical devices, and clinical, surgical and pharmacological 
intervention. The economic impact of health policy and health systems </p>

<p>organization also constitute important areas of coverage. The manu-
script management system is completely online and includes a very 
quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>333 </p>

<p>Extrapolating OS for RR-DTC from placebo-controlled trial </p>

<p>Log-cumulative hazard -individual models </p>

<p>Exponential </p>

<p>Log-Logistic </p>

<p>Gamma 
Gompertz </p>

<p>ln(time) 
ln(time) 
ln(time) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>-1 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
-1 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
-1 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>Log-Normal 
Weibull </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>-1 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>ln(time) </p>

<p>3 
4 
-1 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>ln(time) </p>

<p>3 
4 
-1 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>ln(time) </p>

<p>3 
4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-8 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>Placebo Kaplan-Meier 
Lenvatinib Kaplan-Meier 
Placebo fitted model 
Lenvima fitted model </p>

<p>ln[-ln(survival probability)] 
ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>ln[-ln(survival probability)] 
ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>ln[-ln(survival probability)] </p>

<p>Figure S2 Log-cumulative hazard plots for OS comparing observed (KM) with fitted estimates obtained from individual models. 
Abbreviations: KM, Kaplan-Meier; OS, overall survival. </p>

</text></tei>