<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4589266" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>We explored the prognostic value of diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) parameters of selected white matter (WM) tracts in 
predicting neuropsychological outcome, both at baseline and 6 months later, among well-characterized patients diagnosed with 
mild traumatic brain injury (mTBI). Sixty-one patients with mTBI (mean age = 27.08; standard deviation [SD], 8.55) underwent 
scanning at an average of 10 h (SD, 4.26) post-trauma along with assessment of their neuropsychological performance at an 
average of 4.35 h (SD, 7.08) upon full Glasgow Coma Scale recovery. Results were then compared to 19 healthy control 
participants (mean age = 29.05; SD, 5.84), both in the acute stage and 6 months post-trauma. DTI and neuropsychological 
measures between acute and chronic phases were compared, and significant differences emerged. Specifically, chronic-phase 
fractional anisotropy and radial diffusivity values showed significant group differences in the corona radiata, anterior limb of 
internal capsule, cingulum, superior longitudinal fasciculus, optic radiation, and genu of corpus callosum. Findings also 
demonstrated associations between DTI indices and neuropsychological outcome across two time points. Our results provide 
new evidence for the use of DTI as an imaging biomarker and indicator of WM damage occurring in the context of mTBI, and 
they underscore the dynamic nature of brain injury and possible biological basis of chronic neurocognitive alterations. </p>

<p>M ild traumatic brain injury (mTBI) constitutes ap-</p>

<p>proximately 75-85% of all brain trauma cases. 1 The long-
term outcome of mTBI, however, is not well characterized owing to 
its considerable heterogeneity. One difficulty in accurately diag-
nosing mild neurotrauma relates to the frequent lack of radiological 
evidence to support the diagnosis, which often leads clinicians to 
diagnose mTBI based on clinical or cognitive symptoms known to 
overlap with other clinical conditions 2 (e.g., hypoglycemic or va-
sovagal attacks and certain subtypes of mood disorders). Among 
the neuropsychological alterations that are commonly reported in 
patients with mTBI include impairment in attention, memory, 
psychomotor speed, and executive functions. </p>

<p>Mild neurotrauma is associated with traumatic axonal injury 
(TAI), which is described as a progressive event gradually evolving 
from focal axonal alteration to delayed axonal disconnection. 3 
Importantly, TAI is thought to represent one of the more common 
injuries observed in the aftermath of mTBI. 2 These subtle alter-
ations of brain tracts or fiber pathways have been visualized using 
diffusion tensor imaging (DTI), which enables better visualization 
of the extent of early microstructural changes post-mTBI. 2,4-6 A 
variety of metrics can be generated through DTI scans, including 
fractional anisotrophy (FA), which is a per-voxel indication of the 
directionality of underlying water diffusion. FA values range from 
0 to 1, where FA = 0 would indicate nondirectional diffusion (com-
pletely isotropic) and FA = 1 would indicate a single direction of 
diffusion where the water molecules are restricted to diffusion only </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Division of Neurosurgery, Department of Surgery, University of Malaya, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>University Malaya Research Imaging Center, University of Malaya, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>VA San Diego Healthcare System, San Diego, California. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Department of Psychiatry, University of California San Diego, San Diego, California. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Julius Center University Malaya, Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, University of Malaya, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. </p>

<p>ª Vigneswaran Veeramuthu, Vairavan Narayanan, Tan Li Kuo, Lisa Delano-Wood, Karuthan Chinna, Mark William Bondi, Vicknes Waran, 
Dharmendra Ganesan, Norlisah Ramli; 2015; Published by Mary Ann Liebert, Inc. This Open Access article is distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution Noncommercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and 
reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited. </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF NEUROTRAUMA 32:1497-1509 (October 1, 2015) 
Mary Ann Liebert, Inc. 
DOI: 10.1089/neu.2014.3750 </p>



<p>along a single axis (completely anisotropic). 2,7 Reduced FA in the 
white matter (WM) is believed to reflect a loss of integrity, indicating 
possible damage to myelin or the axon membrane, reduced axonal 
packing, and/or decreased axonal coherence. 2,8 Mean diffusivity 
(MD), on the other hand, describes the per-voxel average magnitude 
of water diffusion, regardless of diffusion direction. Differences in 
MD are thought to reflect overall restrictions to the movement of 
water diffusion, examples being the variations within the intra-and 
extracellular space. 9 Radial diffusivity (RD) is defined as the diffu-
sion of water perpendicular to WM fibers, 10 which increases in re-
sponse to demyelination 11 and dysmyelination. 12 Changes in axonal 
diameter or density can also influence changes observed in RD. 13 FA 
and MD values are usually inversely correlated with one another, 
given that myelination, which enforces directionality (thus increasing 
FA), also represents a restriction to overall movement (thus lowering 
MD). 14,15 The demyelinating changes, as evinced by the changing 
RD, however, are not expected to occur in the first week post-mTBI, 
despite the presence of axonal swelling and synaptic disruption. 16 
In mTBI, widespread changes in FA are frequently observed, 
especially in the frontal, mid-line, and temporal regions. Studies 
have shown that these changes can be detected as early as a few 
days to weeks after neurotrauma, as well as months or even a year 
after the initial insult. 14,15,17 The shearing forces of trauma can 
breach the vascular permeability of vessels (hence rupturing them), 
sever fibers, and lyse cells, which deregulates the normal homeo-
stasis of the blood-brain barrier, and usually manifests as cerebral 
vasogenic and cytotoxic edema. 18 Evaluation of DTI indices en-
ables the differentiation of these edemas, 19 which is crucial to 
predicting long-term neurological outcomes, including neu-
ropsychological performance (NP). Vasogenic edema commonly 
observed in mTBI is characterized by reduced FA, increased MD, 
and RD and is considered reversible. In contrast, cytotoxic edema, 
characterized by an increased FA, reduced MD, and RD, is con-
sidered irreversible and therefore confers a poor prognosis. 2,19,20 
To date, there are few studies that have been conducted longi-
tudinally with acute mTBI samples to help elucidate the evolution 
of these DTI-based changes in mTBI over time. 21-25 Unfortunately, 
existing studies have yielded generally equivocal findings. 2,15,26-29 
For example, some studies have reported decreased integrity of 
several tracts at different time intervals (acute and chronic), 30-35 
although others report elevated FA and reduced MD in the acute 
stage. 16,21,36 Given that these findings may be inconsistent owing to 
various methodological differences, including patient recruitment, 
imaging protocol differences, varying intervals studied, sample-
size differences, and heterogeneity of injury severities, we aimed to 
clarify these longitudinal DTI changes using a whole-brain WM 
measurement strategy with tract-based spatial statistics (TBSS) 37 in 
mTBI and control groups. From the TBSS WM skeleton of com-
parison across subjects, we identified significant tract changes and 
correlated these regions with neuropsychological performances, 
both at admission and 6 months postinjury, in patients with mTBI. 
We also examined the relationship between anatomical correlates 
of tracts and cognition in an effort to improve prognostic values of 
DTI parameters in mTBI care. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Participants </p>

<p>Sixty-one patients with mTBI who presented to the emergency 
department (ED) of University of Malaya Medical Center (Kuala 
Lumpur, Malaysia) for a consecutive 11-month period between 
April 1, 2013 and March 1, 2014 were prospectively recruited for </p>

<p>this study. Patients were selected based on the inclusion and ex-
clusion criteria as presented in Figure 1. For the purposes of this 
study, mTBI was defined as acute TBI, consisting of nonpenetrat-
ing head trauma resulting in one or more of the following: confu-
sion/disorientation; loss of consciousness (LOC) less than 30 min; 
post-traumatic amnesia (PTA; less than 24 h in duration) and/or 
transient focal neurological signs or seizures; and Glasgow Coma 
Scale (GCS) of 13-15 upon acute clinical evaluation. The flow of 
the study is presented in Figure 2. Nineteen healthy age-matched 
control participants were also recruited for this study. 
All subjects meeting criteria for the study underwent computed 
tomography (CT) scans of the brain in the ED using a Siemens 
Somatom Sensation 16 CT scanner (Siemens AG, Berlin, Germany). 
Cross-sectional images of the brain were obtained craniocaudally 
from the base of skull to vertex. Scan parameters used were 120 kVp, 
300 mAs, and collimation of 16 · 0.75 mm with standard brain and 
bone windowing. A neuroradiologist (N.R.) and a neurosurgeon 
(V.N.) who were blinded to the clinical diagnosis independently 
evaluated the images for each patient, and only patients who were 
deemed not requiring surgical intervention were included in this 
study. All subjects gave informed consent as required by the insti-
tutional research ethics committee and the hospital ethics committee 
(UM/EC Ref: 947.15) </p>

<p>Study protocols </p>

<p>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and neuropsychological 
assessments were performed at admission and repeated again at 6 
months post-trauma (Fig. 2). Healthy control participants were 
subjected to the same protocols as patients upon admission (i.e., 
MRI and neuropsychological assessment). </p>

<p>Magnetic resonance imaging data acquisition </p>

<p>All consented subjects were imaged on a 3T MRI scanner (Signa 
HDx; General Electric, Harvey, IL) using an eight-channel head </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Inclusion and exclusion criteria for patients with mTBI. 
mTBI, mild traumatic brain injury; GCS, Glasgow Coma Scale; 
CNS, central nervous system. </p>

<p>1498 
VEERAMUTHU ET AL. </p>

<p>coil. The imaging protocol included: 1) axial T1-weighted three-
dimensional fast spoiled gradient echo (FSPGR; repetition time 
[TR] = minimum 6.7 ms; echo time [TE] = minimum 1.9 ms; field of 
view [FOV] = 31 mm; matrix = 256 · 256; slice thickness = 1.2 mm; 
slice overlap = 0.6 mm with image scan time of 3 min 48 sec); 2) axial 
T2-weighted fast spin echo; TR = 4240 ms; TE = 102 ms; FOV = 24 
mm; matrix = 512 · 384; thickness = 5 mm; spacing = 1.5 mm; and 
image scan time of 2 min 30 sec; and 3) coronal gradient echo 
(TR = 655 ms; TE = 20 ms; flip angle = 15 degrees; bandwidth = 31.25; 
FOV = 24 cm; matrix = 320 · 256; thickness = 5.0 m; spacing = 1.5 mm; 
and image scan time of 2 min 7 sec. The DTI sequence was obtained 
using these parameters: TR = 13,000 ms; TE = 81.2 ms; FOV = 24 mm; 
matrix = 128 · 128; slice thickness = 3.0 mm; 32 directions; diffusion-
weighted factor, b = 700 s/mm 2 ; and image scan time of 7 min 22 sec. </p>

<p>Magnetic resonance imaging analysis </p>

<p>Tract-based spatial statistics. Voxel-wise statistical analy-
sis of the diffusion-weighted data was carried out using TBSS, 37 
part of the <rs id="software-5" type="software">FSL</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">v5.0.6</rs>; University of Oxford, Oxford UK) software 
package. Initial preprocessing involved corrections for head 
movement and eddy currents, brain tissue extraction, and fitting of 
the diffusion tensor model. These were carried out using the <rs type="software">FSL</rs> 
<rs type="software">eddy_correct</rs>, <rs type="software">bet</rs>, and <rs type="software">dtifit</rs> tools, respectively. The standard TBSS 
analysis workflow was followed (V 1.2; http://fsl.fmrib.ox.ac.uk/ 
fsl/fslwiki/TBSS/UserGuide), with the following specific options: 
nonlinear registration to the FMRIB58_FA standard-space image; </p>

<p>generation of a study-specific mean FA image for skeletonization; 
and a 0.2 threshold for the mean FA skeleton. 
The voxel-wise statistical analysis was carried out using the <rs type="software">FSL</rs> 
<rs type="software">randomize</rs> tool. A two-group unpaired t-test design was used for 
comparing admission scans of control and mTBI subjects. A paired 
t-test design was used for comparing admission and follow-up 
scans of mTBI subjects. These statistical analyses were carried out 
separately for FA, MD, and RD values. In all cases, cluster-based 
thresholding was used, and 0.05 was adopted as the threshold for 
significant clusters. </p>

<p>Region of interest. In addition, we obtained mean FA, MD, 
and RD for all tracts identified on TBSS using region of interest 
(ROI) analysis. The image-processing pipeline consisted of pre-
processing, image registration, and analysis, utilizing the <rs id="software-12" type="software">FSL</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-12" type="version-number">v5.0.6</rs>; University of Oxford) and <rs id="software-2" type="software">AFNI</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">v2011_12_21_1014</rs>; 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">National Institute of Mental Health</rs>, Bethesda, MD) software 
packages. Initial preprocessing involved corrections for head 
movement and eddy currents, brain tissue extraction, and fitting of 
the diffusion tensor model. These were carried out using the <rs type="software">FSL</rs> 
<rs type="software">eddy_correct</rs>, <rs type="software">bet</rs>, and <rs type="software">dtifit</rs> tools, respectively. For image regis-
tration, the FSL tool <rs type="software">fnirt</rs> was used to carry out nonlinear spatial 
registration of each subject to the FMRIB58_FA standard-space 
image, using the built-in FA_2_FMRIB58_1mm config file. This 
was assumed to be spatially compatible with the International 
Consortium of Brain Mapping (ICBM) DTI-81 atlas. Post-
registration, composite axial slice images of the underlying FA and </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Complete flowchart of the study protocols, patient and healthy control recruitment, and neuroimaging and neuropsychological 
assessments. TBI, traumatic brain injury; CT, computed tomography; mTBI, mild traumatic brain injury; MRI, magnetic resonance 
imaging; FLAIR, fluid-attentuated inversion recovery; DTI, diffusion tensor imaging; DWI, diffusion-weighted imaging; FSPGR, fast 
spoiled gradient echo; S-NAB, Neuropsychological Assessment Battery-Screening. </p>

<p>DTI PARAMETERS IN MTBI: A LONGITUDINAL STUDY </p>

<p>
ICBM atlas tract outlines were generated at z = 42 and z = 82 for 
each subject. An experienced neuroradiologist (N.R.) verified the 
overall registration quality of these images. Finally, the AFNI 
3dROIstats tool was used to map the predefined ROIs to each in-
dividual subject and calculate the median FA, MD, and RD values 
for each tract. </p>

<p>Neuropsychological assessment </p>

<p>All subjects underwent cognitive assessment using the Screen-
ing Module of the Neuropsychological Assessment Battery (S-
NAB Form 1), which was performed by the neuropsychologist once </p>

<p>the patient had recovered to a GCS score of 15, which occurred with 
an average turnaround time of 4.35 h (SD, 7.08) between time of 
trauma and full GCS recovery. The S-NAB comprises a compre-
hensive set of neuropsychological tests (refer to Table 1), with 
demographically corrected norms for adults between the ages of 18 
and 97 years, assessing orientation and five cognitive domains (i.e., 
attention, memory, language, and visuospatial and executive 
functions). This battery consists of 12 individual tests across the 
five domains aforementioned. From these 12 tests, a total of 16 T 
scores are derived, 14 of which contribute toward five separate 
Screening Index (domain-specific) scores and one Total Screening 
Index score. 38 The same subtests were repeated at 6 months by the 
same neuropsychologist using the S-NAB Form 2 in order to 
minimize practice effects. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>An independent-samples t-test was used to establish whether 
mean values of FA, MD, and RD of selected WM tracts were 
significantly different between healthy control and mTBI groups 
during the acute phase (or baseline exam). The same test was also 
used to investigate whether patients (at admission) performed dif-
ferently from healthy control participants on the neuropsycholo-
gical assessment. A paired t-test was used thereafter to ascertain 
how the WM tracts had changed over time. TBSS skelotonized 
image of the significant changes observed over time were processed 
to better visualize any signifcant changes. Spearman's rho corre-
lation coefficient was used to examine the association between WM 
ROIs (nine selected tracts) and NP over the different phases. Last, a 
simple frequency analysis of neuropsychological performance at 6 
months post-trauma was performed to determine the types of 
changes observed in neuropsychological status longitudinally 
(improved, unchanged, or worsened). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Demographic and clinical data </p>

<p>The demographic characteristics of study patients and healthy 
controls are presented in Table 2. The TBI group ranged in age 
between 18 and 53 years (mean, 27.08; standard deviation [SD], 
8.55), was predominantly male (88.5%), and had a mean age of 
29.05 (SD, 5.84). There was no significant difference in the mean </p>

<p>Table 1. List of S-NAB Module Subtests and Areas 
of Cognitive Domains Assessed </p>

<p>Neuropsychological assessment (S-NAB Form 1 and Form 2) </p>

<p>List of S-NAB module tests 
Domains assessed </p>

<p>Screening Orientation 
Orientation 
Screening Digits Forward 
Attention 
Screening Digits Backward 
Attention/Working 
Memory 
Screening Numbering and Letters 
Attention 
Screening Shape Learning Immediate 
Recognition </p>

<p>Memory </p>

<p>Screening Story Immediate Recall 
Memory 
Screening Delayed Shape Learning 
Delayed Recognition </p>

<p>Memory </p>

<p>Screening Story Learning Delayed 
Recall </p>

<p>Memory </p>

<p>Screening Naming 
Language 
Screening Auditory Comprehension 
(three subtests) </p>

<p>Language </p>

<p>Screening Design Construction 
Visuospatial 
Screening Visual Discrimination 
Visuospatial 
Screening Word Generation 
Executive Function/ 
Verbal Fluency 
Mazes 
Executive Function </p>

<p>S-NAB, Neuropsychological Assessment Battery-Screening. </p>

<p>Table 2. Demographics and Clinical Data of Patients and Healthy Controls at Admission/Baseline </p>

<p>TBI (n = 61) 
Healthy control (n = 19) </p>

<p>Median 
Mean 
SD 
Range 
Median 
Mean 
SD 
Range </p>

<p>Age 
24.0 
27.08 
8.55 
18-53 
29.0 
29.05 
5.83 
18-43 
Education (years) 
11.0 
11.52 
1.94 
6-19 
11.0 
15.95 
2.01 
11-20 
Time to scan (hours/months) 
9.0 
10.01 
4.26 
0-23 
n/a 
n/a 
n/a 
n/a 
GCS 
15.0 
14.44 
0.74 
13-15 
15 
15 
0 
0 
Time to full GCS (hours) 
0.5 
4.35 
7.08 
0-23 
n/a 
n/a 
n/a 
n/a 
LOC (%) 
77.0 
n/a 
PTA (%) 
73.8 
n/a 
Gender (% male) 
88.5 
78.9 
Ethnicity (% Polynesian Malay) 
73.8 
57.9 
Handedness (% right-handed) 
86.9 
89.5 
GOSE 8 at discharge (%) 
88.5 
n/a 
GOSE 8 at follow-up (%) 
n/a 
n/a 
Types of MVAs involved: 
-Motorcycle vs. car (%) 
49.2 
n/a 
-Motorcycle vs. motorcycle (%) 
32.8 
n/a 
-Others (%) 
18.00 
n/a </p>

<p>GCS, Glasgow Coma Scale; LOC, loss of consciousness; PTA, post-traumatic amnesia; GOSE, Glasgow Outcome Score Extended; MVAs, motor 
vehicle accidents; TBI, traumatic brain injury; SD, standard deviation; n/a, not applicable. </p>

<p>1500 
VEERAMUTHU ET AL. </p>

<p>age of healthy controls versus the TBI patient group (t (78) = 0.937; 
p = 0.256). However, the mean years of education differed signifi-
cantly between groups (TBI, 11.52 [SD, 1.94] vs. controls: 15.95 
[SD, 2.01] years). Admission GCS scores of patients were within 
the range of 13-15 (mean = 14.44; SD, 0.74). Seventy-seven per-
cent of patients had experienced transient LOC whereas 73.8% 
reported PTA. Average time to scan of patients during the acute 
phase was 10.01 h (SD, 4.26), whereas the chronic phase scan was 
performed at 6 months postinjury (mean = 6.05; SD, 0.12). Of the 
61 patients, 33 underwent the chronic phase repeat scans (3 patients 
were later dropped during the postscan processing because their 
scans had major artifacts in echo planar imaging). All healthy 
controls had no significant neurological findings. </p>

<p>Diffusion metrics, intergroup differences, 
and intragroup changes over time </p>

<p>Table 3 presents mean FA, MD, and RD values of both patients and 
healthy control participants during the acute phase. At baseline, the 
mTBI group showed significantly lower splenium FA (t (78) = 2.196; 
p = 0.04), when compared to the control group, whereas the MD a value 
was significantly higher in the mTBI versus control group in the 
posterior limb of the internal capsule (PLIC; (t (78) = -2.179; p = 0.03); 
cingulum (CG; t (78) = -2.29; p = 0.02); optic radiation (OR; t (78) = 
-3.176; p = 0.002); and splenium (SCC; t (78) = -2.514; p = 0.02). 
Group differences for the RD a values were observed only in the OR 
(t (78) = 2.637; p = 0.02) and SCC (t (78) = 2.519; p = 0.02). See Figure 3 
for the TBSS skeletonized image reflecting the significant area of 
differences between the groups. 
The paired t-test results (FA, MD, and RD) of patients' WM 
pathway changes, as observed at 6 months (chronic phase) against 
the baseline (acute phase) values, are presented in Table 4a, 4b, and 
4c, along with their effect sizes (Cohen's d with &lt;0.2 = small effect, </p>

<p>&gt;0.2 &lt;0.8 = moderate effect, and &gt;0.8 = large effect). Various dif-
ferences were observed in all DTI parameters, with greater alter-
ations noted in FA values across regions. Specifically, FA of the 
corona radiata (CR; t (28) = 3.497; p = 0.002; d = 0.661), anterior 
limb of internal capsule (ALIC; t (28) = 2.582; p = 0.016; d = 0.488), 
CG (t(28) = 2.973; p = 0.006; d = 0.562), superior longitudinal fas-
ciculus (SLF; t (28) = 2.404; p = 0.024; d = 0.454), OR (t (28) = 2.643; 
p = 0.014; d = 0.499), and the genu of corpus callosum (GCC; 
t (28) = 2.732; p = 0.011; d = 0.516) were significantly lower in the 
TBI group. Almost all of the MD values across the phases showed no 
significant changes, except the CG (t (28) = 3.189; p = 0.004; d = 0.603), 
which was significantly higher in the TBI group. Although the changes 
in PLIC across the phases were found to be statistically nonsignificant 
(t (28) = 1.494; p = 0.15), the effect size, however, suggests a moderate 
level of change (d = 0.282). Finally, there were no significant dif-
ferences in RD values across time points. However, Cohen's d 
effect-size calculation indicated moderate effect sizes for changes in 
the RD of CR (t (28) = 1.582; p = 0.126; d = 0.299), CG (t (28) = 1.54; 
p = 0.136; d = 0.291), OR (t (28) = 1.87; p = 0.073; d = 0.353), and GCC 
(t(28) = 1.975; p = 0.059; d = 0.373). 
All the above-stated significant differences were reflected in the 
TBSS images of the skeletonized tracts as well (see Fig. 4). </p>

<p>Neuropsychological performance </p>

<p>Table 5 presents the mean interpretive categories score compari-
son for the domain-specific NP among mTBI and healthy control 
groups. During the acute phase, patients with mTBI performed poorly 
across all domains, in comparison to the healthy control group. The 
independent-samples t-tests of both groups and their NPs indicated 
that the mTBI group was significantly poorer (all p values, &lt;0.001) on 
all but one of the neuropsychological domains (visuospatial func-
tions, t (78) = 0.055; p = 0.956). Meanwhile, during the chronic phase, </p>

<p>Table 3. Differences of DTI Metrics (FA, MD, and RD) between Patients 
with mTBI Acutely and Baseline Scans of Healthy Controls </p>

<p>FA 
MD 
RD </p>

<p>DTI metrics vs. tracts 
Group N Mean 
SD 
p value Mean 
SD 
p value Mean 
SD 
p value </p>

<p>Middle cerebellar peduncle 
CTRL 19 0.611 0.032 
0.869 
0.698 0.034 
0.168 
0.432 0.038 
0.514 
TBI 
61 0.612 0.025 
0.711 0.036 
0.438 0.033 
Corona radiata 
CTRL 19 0.532 0.028 
0.435 
0.792 0.019 
0.104 
0.535 0.029 
0.785 
TBI 
61 0.538 0.025 
0.802 0.025 
0.537 0.028 
Anterior limb of internal capsule 
CTRL 19 0.636 0.024 
0.297 
0.791 0.018 
0.147 
0.462 0.023 
0.130 
TBI 
61 0.629 0.026 
0.800 0.027 
0.474 0.029 
Posterior limb of internal capsule CTRL 19 0.719 0.028 
0.315 
0.784 0.028 
0.028 
0.392 0.031 
0.110 
TBI 
61 0.712 0.025 
0.800 0.027 
0.406 0.030 
Cingulum 
CTRL 19 0.560 0.029 
0.561 
0.757 0.028 
0.020 
0.495 0.027 
0.064 
TBI 
61 0.555 0.030 
0.777 0.032 
0.510 0.032 
Superior longitudinal fasiculus 
CTRL 19 0.522 0.024 
0.656 
0.769 0.022 
0.280 
0.528 0.028 
0.325 
TBI 
61 0.519 0.024 
0.775 0.024 
0.535 0.025 
Optic radiation 
CTRL 19 0.631 0.036 
0.154 
0.848 0.039 
0.002 
0.494 0.048 
0.015 
TBI 
61 0.619 0.029 
0.878 0.035 
0.521 0.039 
Genu of corpus callosum 
CTRL 19 0.766 0.030 
0.499 
0.811 0.027 
0.309 
0.360 0.039 
0.519 
TBI 
61 0.760 0.031 
0.820 0.036 
0.368 0.043 
Splenium of corpus callosum 
CTRL 19 0.855 0.028 
0.038 
0.737 0.034 
0.016 
0.233 0.045 
0.020 
TBI 
61 0.842 0.023 
0.757 0.030 
0.258 0.037 </p>

<p>Variances in the group were similar for all comparisons. 
DTI, diffusion tensor imaging; FA, fractional anisotropy; MD, medial diffusivity; RD, radial diffusivity; mTBI, mild traumatic brain injury; SD, 
standard deviation; CTRL, control; TBI, traumatic brain injury. </p>

<p>DTI PARAMETERS IN MTBI: A LONGITUDINAL STUDY </p>

<p>
patients with mTBI continued to perform poorly across most do-
mains, in exception of visuospatial functions, where the patients 
outperformed healthy controls (t (48) = -2.373; p = 0.021). </p>

<p>Associations between diffusion tensor imaging 
parameters and neuropsychological performance </p>

<p>Longitudinal analysis of WM tract changes against the NP at 
different intervals among a subset of study patients (n = 30) are 
presented in Table 6. Most of the observed FA associations with 
neurocognitive status (acute and chronic) represented negative 
associations. FA a negatively correlated with the following acute 
NP a : attention versus CR (r = -0.429; p &lt; 0.05); language versus 
CR (r = -0.375; p &lt; 0.05); language versus SLF (r = -0.557; 
p &lt; 0.01); and language versus GCC (r = -0.443; p &lt; 0.05). Acute 
FAs (FA a ) were also negatively correlated with NP c , as follows: 
language versus middle cerebelar peduncle (MCP; r s = -0.440; 
p &lt; 0.05); attention versus CR (r s = -0.441; p &lt; 0.05); language 
versus CR (r s = -0.415; p &lt; 0.05); attention versus SLF (r s = 
-0.417; p &lt; 0.05); language versus SLF (r s = -0.409; p &lt; 0.05); 
spatial versus CG (r s = -0.489; p &lt; 0.05). The two positive corre-
lations observed in the chronic phase were the spatial versus CG 
(r s = 0.489; p &lt; 0.05) and spatial versus SCC (r = 0.402; p &lt; 0.05). 
The significantly reduced FA c had only two associations with the 
NP c : language versus CR (r = -0.400; p &lt; 0.05) and spatial versus 
SCC (r = 0.402; p &lt; 0.05) </p>

<p>MD a showed limited associations with the NP c . The following 
were the only MD a values associated with the NP c : attention versus 
SLF (r s = 0.404; p &lt; 0.05); spatial versus CG (r s = -0.390; 
p &lt; 0.05); and spatial versus GCC (r s = -0.404; p &lt; 0.05). No asso-
ciations between the MD c and NP c were observed. 
The RD of seven of nine tracts studied was significantly as-
sociated with attention, language, spatial, and executive function 
in both phases of the study. Specifically, RD a was associated with 
three NP a scores: attention versus CR (r = 0.485; p &lt; 0.05), at-
tention versus SLF (r = 0.487; p &lt; 0.05); and spatial versus OR 
(r = -0.378; p &lt; 0.05). Additional associations were subsequently 
observed between RD a and NP c , which were as follows: language 
versus MCP (r = 0.398; p &lt; 0.05); language versus CR (r s = 0.529; 
p &lt; 0.01); attention versus SLF (r = 0.450; p &lt; 0.05); language 
versus SLF (r = 0.491; p &lt; 0.05); language versus CG (r = 0.423; 
p &lt; 0.05); spatial versus CG (r = 0.626; p &lt; 0.01); and attention 
versus GCC (r = -0.378; p &lt; 0.05). Increased RD c values were 
also associated with some domains of the NP c , including language 
versus MCP (r s = 0.438; p &lt; 0.05), executive function versus CR 
(r s = 0.389; p &lt; 0.05); executive function versus CG (r s = -0.404; 
p &lt; 0.05); and executive function versus SCC (r s = -0.391; 
p &lt; 0.05). No association was found between the domains of 
memory and any of the WM tracts investigated in this study. We 
also found no associations between the DTI parameters (FA, MD, 
and RD) and any domains of the NP in the healthy control group 
(kindly refer to Table 6b). </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Tract-based spatial statistics (TBSS) showing composite of fractional anisotropy/mean diffusivity/radial diffusivity (FA/MD/ 
RD) voxels of the white matter tracts that showed significant difference between control and mild traumatic brain injury. (mTBI). </p>

<p>1502 
VEERAMUTHU ET AL. </p>

<p>Neuropsychological outcomes </p>

<p>Table 7 presents the neuropsychological profiles of the subset of 
patients (n = 30) who had completed neuropsychological evalua-
tions, as well as imaging, both at admission and at month 6 follow-
up. Within the domain of attention, 56.7% of the patients remained 
impaired at 6 months post-trauma, 3.33% worsened, and the re-
maining improved or remained unaffected. Within the domain of 
language function, 63.3% of patients remained impaired, 26.7% 
improved, 6.67% remained unaffected, and 3.33% worsened. Ap-
proximately 33.3% of patients remained impaired within the do-
main of memory 6 months post-trauma with essentially equivocal 
changes (26.7% worsened, 26.7% remained unaffected, and 13.3% 
with improved memory status). The majority of patients (53.3%) </p>

<p>remained unaffected for spatial function, although 23.3% showed 
signs of delayed impairments in the chronic phase. A total of 70.0% 
of the subset patient group remained impaired with respect to ex-
ecutive functioning, with only 20.0% of these patients showing 
signs of improvement or recovery after the 6-month period post-
trauma. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We examined the relationship between microstructural changes 
and neuropsychological functioning that takes place in the imme-
diate aftermath of an mTBI as well as 6 months post-TBI. Speci-
fically, the initial neuropsychological assessment was completed, 
on average, 4.35 h after full GCS recovery, and the neuroimaging </p>

<p>Table 4a. Paired t-Test Analysis of FA Changes (Acute vs. Chronic) in Tracts 
of Interest and Cohen's d Effect-Size Calculation </p>

<p>Acute 
Chronic 
Effect size 
Mean -SD 
Mean -SD 
t 
d f 
pvalue 
d </p>

<p>Middle cerebellar peduncle 
0.612 -0.025 
0.607 -0.020 
1.412 
28 
0.170 
0.267 
Corona radiata 
0.538 -0.025 
0.531 -0.027 
3.497 
28 
0.002 
0.661 
Anterior limb of internal capsule 
0.629 -0.026 
0.627 -0.025 
2.582 
28 
0.016 
0.488 
Posterior limb of internal capsule 
0.712 -0.025 
0.710 -0.028 
1.524 
28 
0.140 
0.288 
Cingulum 
0.555 -0.030 
0.550 -0.034 
2.973 
28 
0.006 
0.562 
Superior longitudinal fasiculus 
0.519 -0.024 
0.516 -0.022 
2.404 
28 
0.024 
0.454 
Optic radiation 
0.619 -0.029 
0.614 -0.034 
2.643 
28 
0.014 
0.499 
Genu of corpus callosum 
0.760 -0.031 
0.749 -0.034 
2.732 
28 
0.011 
0.516 
Splenium of corpus callosum 
0.842 -0.023 
0.841 -0.029 
0.307 
28 
0.762 
0.058 </p>

<p>FA, fractional anisotropy; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Table 4b. Paired t-Test Analysis of the MD Changes (Acute vs. Chronic) 
in Tracts of Interest and Cohen's d Effect-Size Calculation </p>

<p>Acute 
Chronic 
Effect size 
Mean -SD 
Mean -SD 
t 
d f 
pvalue 
d </p>

<p>Middle cerebellar peduncle 
0.711 -0.036 
0.714 -0.025 
0.095 
28 
0.93 
0.018 
Corona radiata 
0.802 -0.025 
0.805 -0.024 
0.683 
28 
0.50 
0.129 
Anterior limb of internal capsule 
0.800 -0.027 
0.797 -0.020 
0.487 
28 
0.63 
0.092 
Posterior limb of internal capsule 
0.800 -0.027 
0.793 -0.019 
1.494 
28 
0.15 
0.282 
Cingulum 
0.777 -0.032 
0.765 -0.026 
3.189 
28 
0.00 
0.603 
Superior longitudinal fasiculus 
0.775 -0.024 
0.773 -0.022 
0.288 
28 
0.78 
0.054 
Optic radiation 
0.878 -0.035 
0.880 -0.036 
0.028 
28 
0.98 
0.005 
Genu of corpus callosum 
0.820 -0.036 
0.828 -0.031 
0.622 
28 
0.54 
0.118 
Splenium of corpus callosum 
0.757 -0.030 
0.756 -0.028 
0.262 
28 
0.80 
0.050 </p>

<p>MD, medial diffusivity; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Table 4c. Paired t-Test Table of RD Changes (Acute vs. Chronic) in Tracts 
of Interest and Cohen's d Effect-Size Calculation </p>

<p>Acute 
Chronic 
Effect size 
Mean -SD 
Mean -SD 
t 
d f 
pvalue 
d </p>

<p>Middle cerebellar peduncle 
0.438 -0.033 
0.443 -0.027 
0.427 
28 
0.673 
0.081 
Corona radiata 
0.537 -0.028 
0.542 -0.026 
1.582 
28 
0.126 
0.299 
Anterior limb of internal capsule 
0.474 -0.029 
0.473 -0.024 
0.818 
28 
0.421 
0.155 
Posterior limb of internal capsule 
0.406 -0,030 
0.403 -0.030 
0.049 
28 
0.961 
0.009 
Cingulum 
0.510 -0.032 
0.504 -0.030 
1.540 
28 
0.136 
0.291 
Superior longitudinal fasiculus 
0.535 -0.025 
0.535 -0.022 
1.429 
28 
0.165 
0.270 
Optic radiation 
0.521 -0.039 
0.528 -0.044 
1.870 
28 
0.073 
0.353 
Genu of corpus callosum 
0.368 -0.043 
0.382 -0.041 
1.975 
28 
0.059 
0.373 
Splenium of corpus callosum 
0.258 -0.037 
0.258 -0.043 
0.037 
28 
0.971 
0.007 </p>

<p>RD, radial diffusivity; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>DTI PARAMETERS IN MTBI: A LONGITUDINAL STUDY </p>

<p>
FIG. 4. Tract-based spatial statistics (TBSS) showing composite of fractional anisotropy/mean diffusivity/radial diffusivity (FA/MD/ 
RD) voxels of the white matter tracts that showed significant different between acute and chronic phase (for patients with mild traumatic 
brain injury [mTBI]). </p>

<p>Table 5. Mean of S-NAB Interpretive Categories Score at Acute and Chronic Phase 
of Both Patients and Controls and Intergroup Differences (Independent t-Test) 
in Domain-Specific Neuropsychological Performance </p>

<p>Acute 
Chronic </p>

<p>Group 
N 
Mean 
SD 
t 
d f 
pvalue 
N 
Mean 
SD 
t 
d f 
pvalue </p>

<p>Attention 
CTRL 
19 
6.263 
1.24 
4.497 
78 
0.000 
19 
6.263 
1.240 
1.735 
48 
0.090 
TBI 
60 
4.367 
1.697 
30 
5.519 
1.553 
Language 
CTRL 
19 
7.368 
1.461 
5.408 
78 
0.000 
19 
7.368 
1.461 
5.237 
48 
0.000 
TBI 
60 
4.367 
2.27 
30 
4.222 
2.309 
Memory 
CTRL 
19 
6.842 
1.214 
2.832 
78 
0.006 
19 
6.842 
1.214 
2.039 
48 
0.047 
TBI 
60 
5.633 
1.727 
30 
5.889 
1.761 
Spatial 
CTRL 
19 
6.158 
1.302 
0.055 
78 
0.956 
19 
6.158 
1.302 
-2.373 
48 
0.021 
TBI 
60 
6.133 
1.790 
30 
7.111 
1.368 
Executive 
CTRL 
19 
6.316 
1.565 
5.881 
78 
0.000 
19 
6.316 
1.565 
2.937 
48 
0.005 
TBI 
60 
3.900 
1.559 
30 
4.815 
1.798 
Overall 
CTRL 
19 
6.421 
1.387 
6.014 
78 
0.000 
19 
6.421 
1.387 
3.547 
48 
0.001 
TBI 
60 
4.017 
1.557 
30 
4.852 
1.537 </p>

<p>Interpretive category score legend: 1 = severely impaired; 2 = severe to moderately impaired; 3 = moderately impaired; 4 = mildly to moderately 
impaired; 5 = mildly impaired; 6 = below average; 7 = average; 8 = above average; 9 = superior; and 10 = very superior. 
S-NAB, Neuropsychological Assessment Battery-Screening; SD, standard deviation; CTRL, control; TBI, traumatic brain injury. </p>

<p>1504 
VEERAMUTHU ET AL. </p>

<p>Table 6a. Spearman's Rho Correlation Coefficient Table (n = 30) of Neuropsychological Performance 
Against Changes in FA, MD, and RD of the Various Brain Tracts Both at Acute and Chronic Phase </p>

<p>Acute 
Chronic </p>

<p>DTI metrics 
White matter tracts of interest 
Attention Language Spatial Attention Language Spatial Executive </p>

<p>FA 
Middle cerebelar peduncle (acute) 
-0.440* 
Corona radiata (acute) 
-0.429* -0.375* 
-0.441* -0.415* 
Corona radiata (chronic) 
-0.400* 
Superior longitudinal fasiculus (acute) 
-0.557 { 
-0.417* -0.409* 
Cingulum (acute) 
0.489* 
Genu of corpus callosum (acute) 
-0.443* 
Splenium of corpus callosum (chronic) 
0.402* 
MD 
Superior longitudinal fasiculus (acute) 
0.404* 
Cingulum (acute) 
-0.390* 
Genu of corpus callosum (acute) 
-0.404* </p>

<p>RD 
Middle cerebelar peduncle (acute) 
0.398* 
Middle cerebelar peduncle (chronic) 
0.438* 
Corona radiata (acute) 
0.485* 
0.529 { 
Corona radiata (chronic) 
0.389* 
Superior longitudinal fasiculus (acute) 
0.487* 
0.450* 
0.491* 
Cingulum (acute) 
0.423* -0.626 { 
Cingulum (chronic) 
-0.404* 
Optic radiation (acute) 
-0.378* 
Genu of corpus callosum (acute) 
0.378* 
Splenium of corpus callosum (chronic) 
-0.391* </p>

<p>*Correlation is significant at p &lt; 0.05 (two-tailed). 
{ Correlation is significant at p &lt; 0.01 (two-tailed). 
DTI, diffusion tensor imaging; FA, fractional anisotropy; MD, medial diffusivity; RD, radial diffusivity. </p>

<p>Table 6b. Spearman's Rho Correlation Coefficient Table (n = 19) of Neuropsychological Performance 
Against FA, MD, and RD of the Various Brain Tracts in Healthy Controls </p>

<p>Cognitive domains </p>

<p>Correlations 
Group 
Tracts vs. DTI parameters 
Attention Language Memory Spatial Executive Overall </p>

<p>Spearman's rho Control Middle cerebellar peduncle_FA 
-0.262 
-0.157 
-0.344 -0.100 
0.071 
-0.327 
Corona radiata_FA 
0.000 
0.282 
-0.301 
0.000 
0.000 
0.065 
Anterior limb of internal capsule_FA 
0.022 
0.282 
-0.301 
0.100 
0.118 
-0.044 
Posterior limb of internal capsule_FA 
0.022 
0.031 
0.172 
0.020 
0.212 
0.218 
Cingulum_FA 
-0.196 
0.000 
0.129 
0.299 
0.071 
0.000 
Superior longitudinal fasiculus_FA1 
-0.240 
-0.063 
-0.172 -0.080 
0.000 
0.087 
Optic radiation_FA 
-0.349 
0.188 
-0.344 -0.279 
-0.212 
-0.327 
Genu of corpus callosum_FA 
-0.109 
0.344 
-0.129 
0.139 
-0.212 
0.218 
Splenium of corpus callosum_FA 
-0.065 
0.282 
-0.344 -0.040 
-0.094 
-0.240 
Middle cerebellar peduncle_MD 
-0.240 
-0.031 
0.344 -0.010 
-0.083 
0.142 
Corona radiata_MD 
0.175 
-0.282 
0.086 -0.219 
0.012 
-0.131 
Anterior limb of internal capsule_MD 
0.131 
0.094 
0.172 -0.220 
-0.189 
0.022 
Posterior limb of internal capsule_MD 
0.186 
0.220 
-0.302 -0.060 
0.047 
0.197 
Cingulum_MD 
0.000 
-0.141 
0.345 
0.040 
-0.035 
0.218 
Superior longitudinal fasiculus_MD 
0.372 
-0.125 
0.000 -0.060 
-0.236 
-0.109 
Optic radiation_MD 
0.295 
-0.282 
0.387 
0.319 
0.094 
0.218 
Genu of corpus callosum_MD 
-0.022 
-0.282 
0.387 -0.020 
-0.047 
-0.131 
Splenium of corpus callosum_MD 
0.164 
-0.031 
0.345 
0.249 
0.283 
0.426 
Middle cerebellar peduncle_RD 
0.044 
0.063 
0.344 
0.120 
-0.189 
0.240 
Corona radiata_RD 
0.131 
-0.251 
0.301 -0.040 
-0.035 
-0.022 
Anterior limb of internal capsule_RD 
0.055 
-0.110 
0.172 -0.229 
-0.177 
-0.055 
Posterior limb of internal capsule_RD 
0.175 
0.125 
-0.302 
0.060 
-0.260 
-0.131 
Cingulum_RD 
0.109 
-0.141 
0.129 -0.179 
0.035 
0.131 
Superior longitudinal fasiculus_RD 
0.284 
-0.094 
0.043 -0.020 
-0.024 
-0.153 
Optic radiation_RD 
0.371 
-0.219 
0.344 
0.259 
0.165 
0.240 
Genu of corpus callosum_RD 
0.044 
-0.376 
0.258 -0.100 
0.047 
-0.262 
Splenium of corpus callosum_RD 
0.044 
-0.235 
0.345 
0.060 
0.165 
0.251 
N 
1 9 
1 9 
1 9 
1 9 
1 9 
1 9 </p>

<p>DTI, diffusion tensor imaging; FA, fractional anisotropy; MD, medial diffusivity; RD, radial diffusivity. </p>



<p>procedure was completed within an average of 10 h post-trauma in 
order to identify the structural changes at a very early stage before 
they were subject to confounds, such as changes specific to envi-
ronmental and recovery parameters. Subsequently, both a repeat 
imaging and neuropsychological assessment were performed at an 
average of 6 months post-trauma to characterize any pertinent 
changes over time. 
Results showed associations between DTI and neuropsychological 
indices at both acute and chronic phases. Specifically, in the acute 
phase, the TBI group showed significantly poorer WM integrity across 
several tracts, including the splenium (SCC), PLIC, CG, and OR. 
Several other WM tracts beyond those initially affected also showed 
reduced FA at 6 months post-injury (i.e., CR, ALIC, SLF, and GCC). 
Interestingly, moderate effect sizes for changes in RD were observed 
from baseline to follow-up in the following regions: CR, CG, and OR. 
Finally, with respect to neuropsychological functioning, patients with 
mTBI performed more poorly across all domains in the acute stage, 
when compared to healthy control participants. The majority of pa-
tients remained impaired with respect to executive functioning, and a 
sizable portion of the sample worsened over time on tasks of attention 
and language. Moreover, longitudinal analysis of WM tract changes, 
as they relate to cognition, showed several associations, indicating that 
reduced WM integrity was associated with specific neuropsycholo-
gical decrements. Indeed, DTI indices in both acute and chronic stages 
related to cognition at both time points, and RD values in seven of the 
nine tracts studied was significantly associated with attention, lan-
guage, spatial, and executive function in both phases of the study. 
Interestingly, no association was found between the domains of 
memory and any of the WM tracts investigated in this study. 
Our findings of reduced FA, coupled with increased MD and RD 
in the acute phase, is considered indicative of vasogenic brain 
edema, which refers to the release of intracellular proteins into the 
brain parenchyma, also known as extracellular edema. 18 An in-
creased FA a , reduced MD a , and RD a in the acute phase, on the other 
hand, may be indicative of cytotoxic edema, 2,36 also known as 
intracellular edema. This type of cerebral edema in the early course 
of injury has been implicated in poor outcome, 2,18 which could 
explain frequently observed neuropsychological impairment 
months or even years after the initial trauma event. The increased 
FA, MD, and rather an unchanged RD in the acute phase of this 
study is most likely indicative of reactive astrogliosis, which is a 
process where fibrous astrocytes migrate to the site of injury, lo-
cally increasing the density of the cells 39 and diffusivity of the 
affected tissue. 39,40 
Vasogenic edema occurs in the acute phase, whereas demye-
lination occurs later. 16 As such, even though the DTI markers for 
these pathogenic processes are the same, the timeframe of imaging </p>

<p>changes rather indicate an ongoing vasogenic edema. These 
changes in DTI parameters were observed in the SCC, PLIC, CG, 
and OR (with statistically significant changes in most parameters). 
Other tracts, including the ALIC, SLF, and GCC, showed similar 
trends, although they did not reach statistical significance. Results 
showing minimally reduced FA a in the context of significantly 
increased MD of the SLF and GCC in the patient group, and its 
negative association with language function, are similar to those 
reported by Ingelese and colleagues 33 and Arfanakis and col-
leagues. 24 Cognitive impairment observed acutely in this group of 
patients coupled with the changing DTI metrics are likely imme-
diate signs reflecting an ongoing edematous process, which is not 
observed by conventional CT or MRI. 
In contrast, changes observed in CR a and MCP a were more 
suggestive of reactive astrogliosis and dovetails with findings re-
cently reported by Croall and colleagues. 41 Although some of these 
changes did not reach statistical significance, the effect size of 
0.299 for the RD changes in CR, coupled with the effect size of 
0.661 for the FA changes of CR, for instance, does provide some 
moderate-to-large evidence of significant change in this tract. 
Higher FA value of the CR also negatively correlated with attention 
and language functions acutely. Its corresponding positive associ-
ation with RD at baseline best explains the influence of reactive 
astrogliosis on cognition in the acute stage, as previously stated. 40-
42 The importance of the above finding cannot be understated given 
that specific types of cerebral edema and gliosis in the acute phase 
have been implicated to negatively influence long-term neu-
ropsychological performance in patients with mTBI. 43-46 
We also found that acute-phase DTI parameters in selected WM 
tracts were significantly associated with chronic domain-specific 
cognitive deficits. This includes those of the MCP, CR, SLF, CG, 
GCC, and SCC and their association with specific neurocognitive 
functions chronically, similar to findings of other studies. 39-42,47,48 
Miles and colleagues, for instance, noted that decreased FA values 
and increased MD values of the GCC, SCC, and PLIC during the 
acute phase were significantly related to executive dysfunction at 6 
months follow-up. 2,47 Kumar and colleagues and Matshushita and 
colleagues reported similar findings involving the GCC, SCC, and 
NP c in their studies of mild and moderate head injury. 48,49 The 
mostly positive association between the unchanged or raised RD a 
of the MCP, CR, SLF, and CG with specific chronic deficits in 
attention, language, and spatial function likely reflect the long-term 
effects of acute vasogenic edema and reactive astrogliosis, a well-
known immune response in the immediate aftermath of central 
nervous system (CNS) injury. 41 It is important to note that cerebral 
edema and cascading gliosis usually occur concurrently and are not 
necessarily independent of each other. </p>

<p>Table 7. Frequency Table of Neuropsychological Performance Status at 6 Months 
Post-Trauma in Comparison to Their Performance at Admission </p>

<p>Neuropsychological performance status categories </p>

<p>Domains 
1,1 (%) 
1,2 (%) 
2,1 (%) 
2,2 (%) 
Fisher's exact </p>

<p>Attention 
17 (56.7) 
9 (30.0) 
1 (3.33) 
3 (10.0) 
0.269 
Language 
19 (63.3) 
8 (26.7) 
1 (3.33) 
2 (6.67) 
0.234 
Memory 
10 (33.3) 
4 (13.3) 
8 (26.7) 
8 (26.7) 
0.253 
Spatial 
4 (13.3) 
3 (10.0) 
7 (23.3) 
16 (53.3) 
0.181 
Executive 
21 (70.0) 
6 (20.0) 
2 (6.67) 
1 (3.33) 
0.530 
Overall 
24 (80.0) 
4 (13.3) 
0 (0.0) 
2 (6.67) 
0.026 </p>

<p>Interpretive categories: impaired = 1; not impaired = 2. </p>

<p>1506 
VEERAMUTHU ET AL. </p>

<p>Chronically, the continued alteration of DTI parameters, espe-
cially the FA c and RD c , implies significant changes in WM integ-
rity, where the myelin sheath or the axonal membrane or both may 
have been permanently damaged. 19,20,36 This disruption may be 
irreversible, especially when a reduced FA c and elevated MD c and 
RD c are noted. 2,19 Conversely, a reduced FA c , unchanged MD, and 
subtly altered RD c would mean that the microstructural changes to 
the WM are independent of gross tissue loss. 43-46 The subtly altered 
RD c in this context would imply minor fiber damage without gross 
tissue loss. 44 Such changes have also been implicated as a part of 
the dual effects of gliosis. 46,50,51 
FA measured at follow-up was significantly reduced, in compar-
ison to the acute phase, with mostly unchanged MD c and subtly 
increased RD c across six tracts (i.e., CR, ALIC, CG, SLF, OR, and 
GCC). Whereas the changes observed in the ALIC and OR are in-
dicative of possible minor fiber damage and thus vasogenic edema, 
the change pattern observed in CR suggests irreversible consequences 
of astrogliosis. The mixed association between certain neurocognitive 
performances in the chronic stage (e.g., executive, spatial, and lan-
guage function) and FA and RD of several tracts (i.e., MCP, CR, CG, 
and SCC), though possibly paradoxical, is not completely unex-
pected. Similar observations were found in a recent study with at-
tribution to the multifaceted chronic phase findings. 41 This included 
neuronal network reorganisation, 52 spurting of axons with smaller 
calibres, 53 glial scarring, 46,50,51,54 effects of accumulated phosypho-
larated neurofilaments, 55-59 and disruptive neurofibrillary tangles. 60 
Taken together, our findings further strengthen evidence for physio-
genic influences on the prolonged functional and neuropsychological 
sequelae in patients with mTBI. 61 Clearly, disruption of the con-
nectomes (i.e., the connectivities between specific cortical and sub-
cortical structures) by various neuropathological 62,63 events post-
trauma and the recovery process over time requires further study. 
Interestingly, a common finding in our study was that the more 
severely affected fibers were generally the long tract fibers (SLF, 
CR, and CG) and commisural fibers (SCC and GCC). These fibers 
have an increased susceptibility to injury 64 given their relatively 
long length and high membrane-to-cytoplasmic ratios. 65,66 The 
corpus callosum, for example, as noted by Aoki and colleagues, is 
the major fiber bundle that enables communication between the 
hemispheres and is topographically organized. 27,67 The CC in 
general is divided into the genu (GCC), the body, and the splenium 
(SCC). 27 The CC has been long recognized as a frequently injured 
region owing to shear strain, 68 and topographical location and ex-
ternal accelerational forces can seriously injure the fiber. 69,70 The 
posterior region of the CC, namely, the SCC, often noted to be more 
vulnerable to injury than the anterior part (GCC), 67,71-74 was rep-
licated in this study as well; and the SCC was the only tract that 
showed statistically significant changes in all three DTI parameters 
at the acute stage. 
Our findings lend support to the theory that microstructural 
changes occur within hours after the initial insult and affect the 
integrity of the WM, therefore leading to the varied manifestation 
of neuropsychological impairments, in agreement with some of the 
earlier studies reported in the literature. 31,34,41,75,76 Strengths of our 
study include examination within a short timeframe from time of 
injury to imaging and neuropsychological testing within the acute 
phase, as well as consistent test-retest interval at 6-month follow-
up. Although FA and MD have been shown to be very sensitive in 
detecting subtle WM changes that correlate with neuropsycholo-
gical findings, one other parameter that has been included in this 
study, namely, RD, 77 provides further insight into the presumed 
nature of the microstructural changes 75,78,79 given that it is sensitive </p>

<p>to myelin integrity 23,76,80 and also other CNS immune response, 
such as gliosis. 41 These parameters enabled us to detect the early 
deep WM microstructural changes, which might otherwise be 
confounded by ongoing secondary damage or recovery mecha-
nisms. Additionally, the current study is unique in its longitudinal 
follow-up of DTI indices and cognitive functioning at 6 months 
post-trauma in a large cohort of well-characterized patients with 
relatively homogenous types of injuries. That said, findings may be 
limited owing to the significant heterogenity of the trauma observed 
in our sample as well as possible obscuring of certain differences 
owing to the nature of brain morphing and averaging, which is 
inherent in template-based analyses. Specifically, any deviation 
present in a small number of voxels within a region may be hidden 
by the averaging and therefore lead to low sensitivity to detect FA 
and MD changes. 81,82 </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>DTI is a useful technique used to assess the integrity of WM tracts 
in patients who have sustained mTBI. This study found significant 
correlations between neuropsychological deficits and WM tract in-
tegrity both within hours of neurotrauma and again 6 months later. 
These associations are likely attributable to alterations in the integrity 
of connectomes between specific cortical areas and subcortical 
structures, which is not evident in conventional MRI or CT proce-
dures. Specific WM changes, as observed through the DTI parameters, 
especially in the acute period, and the corresponding neuropsycholo-
gical impairments among the patients in the chronic phase, highlights 
the need to introduce appropriate imaging techniques early in patient 
management protocols for early prognostication and rehabilitative 
intervention. Further, our findings underscore the dynamic nature of 
brain injury and possible biological basis of cognitive dysfunction in 
the context of the postconcussive syndrome. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This research is partially funded by a University Malaya 
Research Grant (UMRG; RG008C-13HTM) and a High Impact 
Research Grant of University of Malaya (HIR-UM.C/625/1/HIR-
MOHE/12). </p>

<p>Author Disclosure Statement </p>

<p>No competing financial interests exist. </p>



<p>DTI PARAMETERS IN MTBI: A LONGITUDINAL STUDY </p>



<p>
 
VEERAMUTHU ET AL. </p>



<p>Address correspondence to: 
Vigneswaran Veeramuthu, MEdPsych 
Division of Neurosurgery 
Department of Surgery 
University of Malaya 
50603 Kuala Lumpur 
Wilayah Persekutuan 
Malaysia </p>

<p>E-mail: vicveera@gmail.com </p>

<p>DTI PARAMETERS IN MTBI: A LONGITUDINAL STUDY 
1509 </p>

</text></tei>