<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5279962" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background: Pain relief during labour is one of the major concerns in obstetrics; severe labor pain causes fear of 
the next pregnancy, and interferes with the mother's family relationship. 
Objective: The aim of this study was to evaluate the analgesic effects of Entonox during labor on reducing the 
need for pethidine (Meperidine) and fetal-maternal complications. 
Methods: This double-blind randomized clinical trial was conducted on pregnant women who were candidates 
for vaginal delivery in Educational Hospitals of Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Iran between January 
2014 and November 2015. After entering into the inactive phase of labor, participants were randomly allocated to 
receive inhaled Entonox gas (n=200) or inhale Oxygen (n=200) as a control group. Mothers inhaled the gas at 
commencement of pain, and ceased as soon as the pain diminished, up to the end of the second stage of labor 
which was the neonate's birth. Main outcomes were pain score based on NRS (numerical rating scale), duration of 
delivery, required pethidine, maternal complications and satisfaction during labour. Chi-square and Independent 
T-test were used via <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> for data analysis and P-value less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. 
Results: Four-hundred pregnant women with a mean age of 26.4±5.9 years were studied. Complications such as 
nausea, vomiting, dizziness, and drowsiness were reported in 25% of the Entonox group and 23% in the control 
group (p=0.640). Mean of pain severity score during labor in the Entonox and control groups was 4.5±1.2 and 
5.2±1.4, respectively (p&lt;0.001). Pethidine requirement, significantly was lower in the Entonox group (31.6±11.8 
versus 35.7±12.4; p&lt;0.001). 
Conclusion: In our study, Entonox significantly reduced pain during delivery without significant increase in 
maternal and neonatal complications. 
Trial registration: The trial is registered at the Iranian Clinical Trial Registry (IRCT.ir) with the IRCT 
identification number IRCT2015102713159N6. 
2. Material and Methods 
2.1. Research design and setting 
This double-blind clinical trial study was performed on pregnant women who were candidates for vaginal 
delivery in three main referral teaching hospitals of Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran 
between January 2014 and November 2015. </p>

<p>2.2. Sampling and sample size determination 
The sample size was an estimated 210 patients for each group, considering Alfa= 0.05, Beta= 0.2, Z1-a/2=1.96, Z1-</p>

<p>β= 0.84, P1= 0.80, P2= 0.68, P= 0.74. Based on aforementioned information the sample size was measured as 400 
divided in two equal groups. Final samples were selected based on simple random sampling method s (Figure 1). </p>

<p>2.3. Randomization, allocation and blinding 
By using random number tables, the mothers were randomly allocated to one of the two groups: Entonox: 
intervention group or Oxygen: control group. The surgeons were blind to the groups of intervention and just one 
research assistant was aware of precipitants group. Moreover, patients and statistician were also blind to the types 
of interventions. </p>

<p>2.4. Selection criteria 
Nulliparous women aged 18-40 years, term pregnancy (37-42 weeks), singleton, normal fetus, no medical and 
midwifery complications of mother (heart problems or other internal diseases), no use of other anesthesia or 
analgesia drugs, cephalic presentation, no restrictions for Entonox gas inhalation (respiratory diseases, 
pneumothorax, history of head trauma), having a dilatation of 4 cm at the beginning of the active phase of 
delivery when entering into the study, and normal fetal heart pattern were included in this study, and patients with 
any complication during childbirth, lack of consent to enter the project, and those who required cesarean delivery 
were excluded from the study. </p>

<p>2.5. Data collection 
A check list was used for data collection. At the beginning of admittance to the hospital, after the standard 
monitoring of mothers' vital signs including heart rate, pulse oximetry, blood pressure and respiratory rate, fetal 
heart rate was also measured and recorded in checklist as well as maternal primary vital signs. </p>

<p>Electronic physician </p>



<p>Figure 1. Follow-up diagram of patients (According to consort statement) </p>

<p>2.6. Interventions 
The Entonox group received inhaled gas containing 50% oxygen and 50% nitric oxide and the Oxygen group 
received 4-6 lit/min oxygen only. After entering the active phase of labor (cervical dilatation of 4 cm), both 
groups were given the masks of which the intervention group inhaled Entonox and the control group inhaled 
oxygen. Mothers began inhaling through the masks at the beginning of pain, and as soon as the pain receded, the 
gas inhalation ended. Mothers would frequently receive gas up to the end of the second stage of lab or which was 
neonate's birth. The patients were frequently controlled by an anesthesia assistant. If (NSR&gt;4), 0.5 mg/kg, 
intravenous pethidine was administered for patients of the two groups in severe pain, and was recorded. </p>

<p>2.7. Outcomes 
Pain intensity and maternal hemodynamics status (while receiving gas, and recorded every fifteen minutes), fetal 
heart rate, duration of the active phase and second stage of labor, 1 and 5 minutes Apgar score, infant's saturation 
(by pulse oximetry), and infant's cord pH (by arterial blood gas analysis after birth) was recorded and compared 
between the two groups. Also, the need for additional pethidine (in case of NSR &gt;4) in both groups during 
childbirth was recorded. In addition, any adverse effects such as nausea, vomiting, dizziness, or drowsiness was 
mentioned in our check list and compared between the two groups. 
2.7.1. Pain assessment 
Pain assessment scale was numeric scale rating (NRS). Pain intensity was measured using the numbers of 0 to 10 
that 0 represents complete analgesia and 10 represents the maximum pain that can be imagined. 
2.7.2. Satisfaction 
In our study, satisfaction level was studied in two main categories; complete satisfaction and relative satisfaction. 
Patients were assumed to be completely satisfied if there was no nausea, vomiting, dizziness drowsiness, or 
intolerance during and after interventions. On the other hand, they were assumed relative ly satisfied, if there were 
any degree of the mentioned parameters. </p>

<p>2.8. Research ethics 
After approval by the ethics committee of Mashhad University of Medical Sciences (Code: 966778) and 
registration in IRCT system (IRCT2015102713159N6) and obtaining the written consent of mothers, this study 
began in maternities of Mashhad University Educational Hospitals. In case of appearance of any gas inhalation </p>

<p>http://www.ephysician.ir </p>



<p>related complications, interventions were stopped and were recorded in the checklist, and then when the 
complication disappeared, the mask was again used, if it was needed. </p>

<p>2.9. Statistical analyses 
Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 16</rs>. For nominal variables, chi-square test was 
used and if needed, Fisher's exact test was performed. Kolmogorov-Simonov was used to determine normality of 
distribution. For comparative dependent data, paired T-test (parametric) and if non-parametric, Wilcoxon test 
were used. For comparing the independent data, independent-samples t-test (parametric) was used and if non-
parametric, Mann-Whitney U test was used. In all measurements p-value less than 0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. </p>

<p>3. Results 
In this study, 400 women with mean age of 26.4 ± 5.9 years, 200 in control (Oxygen) and 200 in intervention 
group (Entonox) were studied. The frequency of age groups &lt;18 years, 18 to 30 years, and &gt; 30 years was 3%, 
72.2% and 24.8%, respectively. The mean gestational age was 38.7 ± 2.6 weeks. The mean of pain severity in 
total of patients when referring was 7.7 ± 1.7. Two groups were homogenous according to maternal age, mother's 
pain severity and vital signs at the time of study entrance (Table 1). Results revealed that, patients in the Entonox 
group experienced less pain (p = &lt;0.001) and they also had less duration of delivery in the first (p = &lt;0.001) and 
second (p = 0.004) stage (Table 2). In addition, the required dosage of pethidine needed during labor was 
significantly lower in the Entonox group (p = &lt;0.001) (Table 2). However, there was no significant difference 
between the two groups in terms of Neonate's Apgar scores and artery oxygen saturation (Table 2). The 
incidence of complications of nausea, vomiting, dizziness and drowsiness were observed in 24.5% of the Entonox 
group patients and 23% of Oxygen group patients, but the difference was not statistically significant (p = 0.640) 
(Table 3). In Table 3, the frequency of complications and maternal satisfaction of analgesia method s were 
compared. </p>

<p>Table 1. Comparison of baseline maternal characteristics between two groups of Entonox and Oxygen intervention 
Variables, mean ± SD 
Oxygen 
(n = 200) 
Entonox 
(n = 200) 
p-value </p>

<p>Maternal age (year) 
26.9±5.7 26±6 
0.138 
Pain severity when entering to the study (score) 7.74±1.7 7.76±1.7 0.089 
Mother's systolic blood pressure (mmHg) 
98.8±5.8 99.5±4.8 0.261 
Mother's diastolic blood pressure (mmHg) 
62.9±9 
68.4±3.8 0.248 
Maternal pulse rate (min) 
86.3±8.1 86.9±8 
0.663 
Maternal respiratory rate (min) 
13.9±3.2 14±1.1 
0.678 
Maternal artery oxygen saturation (%) 
97.5±1.4 97.9±0.6 0.137 </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of maternal and neonatal outcomes between two groups of Entonox and Oxygen intervention 
Variables, mean ± SD 
Oxygen (n = 200) Entonox (n = 200) p-value 
Pain severity during labor (score) 
5.2±1.4 
4.5±1.2 
&lt;0.001 
Duration of delivery first stage (min) 
150.5±69.2 
103.4±56.6 
&lt;0.001 
Duration of delivery second stage (min) 25±14.1 
21.9±14 
0.004 
Needed pethidine during labor, mg/dl 
35.7±12.4 
31.6±11.8 
&lt;0.001 
Neonate's first Apgar score 
8.7±0.6 
8.7±0.7 
0.507 
Neonate's fifth Apgar score 
9.7±0.5 
9.6±0.7 
0.343 
Neonate's cord Apgar score 
7.32±0.77 
7.33±0.076 
0.116 
Neonatal artery oxygen saturation (%) 
96.5±2.9 
96.4±2 
0.133 </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparison of the frequency of complications and maternal satisfaction of analgesia method </p>

<p>Electronic physician </p>



<p>Variables, n (%) 
Entonox (n = 200) Oxygen (n = 200) p-value 
Nausea 
Negative 192 (96) 
183 (91.5) 
0.097 
Positive 
8 (4) 
17 (8.5) 
Vomiting 
Negative 194 (97) 
195 (97.5) 
0.999 
Positive 
6 (3) 
5 (2.5) 
Dizziness 
Negative 182 (91) 
181 (90.5) 
0.999 
Positive 
18 (9) 
19 (9.5) 
Drowsiness Negative 187 (93.5) 
189 (94.5) 
0.674 
Positive 
13 (6.5) 
11 (5.5) 
Satisfaction Complete 134 (67) 
155 (77.5) 
0.019 
Relative 
66 (33) 
45 (22.5) </p>

<p>4. Discussion 
Pain relief is one of the main parts of midwifery, as one of the benefits of labor at the hospital is providing more 
technical pain relief. Severe labor pain can cause long-term emotional disturbance for a mother, and affects her 
mental health and has a negative impression on maternal-neonatal relationships in the first critical days after 
delivery. Moreover it might interfere with family relationships by causing fear of next pregnancy (10). Labor pain 
also reduces oxygenation of the fetus and subsequently leads to abnormal fetal heart rate patterns and decreased 
Apgar score, and this increases the need for obstetrical interventions and its relevant complications. Fear of labor 
pain is one of the main reasons of high demand for cesarean section (11). Due to the fact that delivery is a 
physiological process and promotion of natural vaginal delivery is considered as one of the principal policies of 
the health care systems, this important goal can be achieved by reducing labor pain. To reduce labor pain, we 
should resort to safe and secure methods for mother and fetus which, while are effective, do not cause 
interference with the labor process, maternal alertness or straining reflex and the mother's physiological functions 
(12). One of these methods is inhaled analgesia using Entonox gas (a mixture of 50% oxygen and 50% N2O). The 
benefits of Entonox are that they are fast acting, give rapid clearance from the body, there is no need for 
sophisticated and expensive devices, no need for highly-skilled personnel, and finally mothers have greater 
tolerance (13-15). For nearly fifty years, Entonox has been approved for pain relief, and is used especially in 
England. Most studies in Europe and the United States have compared Entonox as a standard method with other 
relieving methods or medicines, rather than evaluate its effects on labor pain (16-18). In the present study, 
complications were observed in 24.5% of patients in the Entonox group and 23% of patients in the oxygen group, 
but the difference was not statistically significant (P=0.640). The most common side effects included nausea, 
vomiting, dizziness, and drowsiness that often make Entonox intolerable for parturient (16). In a review article, 
Entonox compared with other analgesia methods caused more nausea, vomiting, dizziness, and drowsiness (17). 
In the study of Rezaeipour, some possible side effects caused by inhaling Entonox, such as drowsiness and dry 
mouth were more commonly observed in the intervention group than the control group (P&lt;0.001), but no 
statistically significant differences were observed in other complications (18). In our study, dizziness and 
drowsiness were slightly more common in patients of the Entonox group, but the difference was not statistically 
significant (P=0.744), and the most likely cause of these complications in the oxygen group was higher need to 
use pethidine. A study in 2011 showed that Entonox is safe for mothers and neonates, and people working in the 
environment if it is used with oxygen at a proportion of 50:50 (19). In the study of Pazande, Entonox had no 
negative effects on the mother and fetus (20). In our study, the hemodynamic changes in mother and infant during 
labor, were not significantly different between the two groups, which confirmed the safety of Entonox for mother 
and neonate. In the study of Zare, the mean length of first stage of delivery was shorter in the Entonox group than 
the control group, but the mean length of the second stage of delivery showed no significant difference between 
case and control groups (21). The study of Parashi showed that nitrous oxide reduces labor duration (22). In our 
study, the mean duration of the first and second stage was significantly lower in the Entonox group than the 
oxygen group. It seems that inhalation of Entonox to reduce labor pain, also decreases the labor duration. It is 
known that pain increases production of catecholamines and decreases blood supply to the uterus and uterine 
contractions. The subsequent weakness and ineffectiveness of these contractions result in i nappropriate delivery 
progress. In the study of Pazande, the mean of pain intensity was significantly lower in the Entonox group than 
other methods (23). The study of Parashi showed that nitrous oxide reduces labor pain (24). In the study of Agah, 
pain severity was not significantly different in the groups of continuous and discontinuous use of Entonox gas 
(22). In our study also, the mean pain intensity during labor was 4.5 ± 1.2 in the Entonox group and 5.2 ± 1.4 in 
the oxygen group, and this difference was statistically significant. In our study, Entonox was administered as </p>

<p>http://www.ephysician.ir </p>



<p>discontinuous for the patients. Entonox gas has no effect on uterine contractions and does not cause malignant 
hyperthermia. Its side effects included nausea, vomiting, dizziness, and low reward. In terms of blood oxygen 
saturation for mothers and infants during delivery, the results of present study showed that SpO2 was not less 
than 90% in any of the methods, and that is similar to the study of Masoudi (25). In our study, maternal 
hemodynamic findings were not significantly different between Entonox and oxygen groups. But in a study in 
Lorestan, hemodynamic findings were lower in the Entonox group than other groups (25). One of the 
complications of acute/severe pain caused by response of sympathetic nervous system, is increased pulse rate and 
blood pressure; the cause of difference between our study and other studies may be due to differences in the 
consumption of pethidine, because the oxygen group received pethidine during pain. In a study in Tehran, Iran, 
no statistically significant difference was observed between the two groups in first and fifth minute Apgar score 
(22). In our study, the mean first and fifth minute Apgar scores in the Entonox group were not statistically 
significant. Therefore, it seems that Entonox decreases maternal pain and severe anxiety and consequently 
reduces the incidence of abnormal fetal heart rate and leads to an improved Apgar score. In the study of Jafari, 
the use of Entonox increased maternal satisfaction (26). In our study, none of the patients were dissatisfied from 
the used analgesia methods. Full satisfaction was observed in 53.6% of the Entonox group and 46.4% of the 
oxygen group, and relative satisfaction in 40.5% of the Entonox group and 59.5% of the oxygen group was 
observed, and this difference was statistically significant. According to the study findings, it seems that the use of 
Entonox is an effective and safe method for labor pain relief which is associated with increased maternal 
satisfaction, therefore, delivery satisfaction has a direct relationship with pain relief and lack of severe side 
effects of Entonox. Several studies have indicated that 80% of patients tend to reuse Entonox in the next 
pregnancies (27-28). In order to reduce the rate of caesarean sections and encourage parturient women to vaginal 
delivery, it is recommended that the benefits of Entonox be provided in training sessions during pregnancy, for 
mothers or in the form of print material in doctors' offices and clinics; and this method might be an important step 
in improving the health of mothers and children. One of the minor limitations of this study was a short duration of 
study follow-up. It would be more advantageous if a follow-up of our patients could be carried out for at least one 
week after their discharge. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions 
In our study, Entonox significantly improved labor pain during delivery without significantly i ncreasing maternal 
complications. The three main principles of pain relief in obstetrics which are simplicity, safety and fetus 
homeostasis maintaining are considered. Since the use of Entonox, especially in intermittent form, reduces labor 
pain without causing complications for the mother, and also is associated with more maternal satisfaction, this 
gas can be used during labor in order to reduce the number of cesarean deliveries occurring due to labor pain and 
as a result, the complications of surgery and anesthesia and its high costs can be decreased. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments: 
The authors appreciate the research chancellor of Mashhad University of Medical Sciences which supported this 
study financially. This article is obtained from Anesthesiology Specialty student thesis by Dr. Atefeh Shirinzadeh 
Feizabadi (approval number 966778). </p>

<p>Trial registration: 
The trial is registered at the Iranian Clinical Trial Registry (IRCT.ir) with the IRCT identification number 
IRCT2015102713159N6. </p>

<p>Funding: 
This research has been financially supported by Research Council of Mashhad University of Medical Sciences. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: 
There is no conflict of interest to be declared. </p>

<p>Authors' contributions: 
All authors contributed to this project and article equally. All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </p>

<p>References: </p>

<p>Electronic physician </p>





<p>http://www.ephysician.ir </p>





</text></tei>