<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5215597" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>SUMMARY </p>

<p>Objective: In vivo studies of epilepsy typically use prolonged status epilepticus to gen-
erate recurrent seizures. However, reports on variable status duration have found dis-
crete differences in injury after 40-50 min of seizures, suggesting a pathophysiologic 
sensitivity to seizure duration. In this report we take a multivariate cluster analysis to 
study a short duration status epilepticus model using in vivo 7T magnetic resonance 
spectroscopy (MRS) and histologic evaluation. 
Methods: The Hellier Dudek model was applied with 45 min of status epilepticus after 
which the animals were imaged twice, at 3 days and 3 weeks post-status epilepticus. 
Single voxel point resolved spectroscopy (PRESS) MRS was used to acquire data from 
the dentate gyrus and CA3 region of the hippocampus, assessing metabolite ratios to 
total creatine (tCr). In a subset of animals after the second imaging study, brains were 
analyzed histologically by Nissl staining. 
Results: A hierarchical cluster analysis performed on the 3-day data from 21 kainate-
treated animals (dentate gyrus voxel) segregated into two clusters, denoted by KM 
(more injured, n = 6) and KL (less injured, n = 15). Although there was no difference in 
kainate dosing or seizure count between them, the metabolic pattern of injury was dif-
ferent. The KM group displayed the largest significant changes in neuronal and glial 
parameters; the KL group displayed milder but significant changes. At 3 weeks, the KL 
group returned to normal compared to controls, whereas the KM group persisted with 
depressed N-acetyl aspartate (NAA)/tCr, glutamate/tCr, and increased inositol/tCr 
and glutamine/tCr. The classification was also consistent with subsequent histologic 
patterns at 3 weeks. 
Significance: Although a short status period might be expected to generate a continu-
ous distribution of metabolic injury, these data show that the short Hellier Dudek 
model appears to generate two levels of injury. The changes seen in segregated groups 
persisted into 3 weeks, and can be interpreted according to neuronal and glial 
biomarkers consistent with histology results. 
(HSP72) staining appeared in the dentate gyrus only after 
40-50 min of status epilepticus, with subsequent appear-
ance in cortex coincident with recurrent motor seizures. 
Using an electrical dentate gyrus stimulation protocol, Nor-
wood 2010 2 reported a similar 40-50 min delay with hilar 
Fluoro-Jade B staining. It is unclear whether such nonlinear 
behavior relates to human epidemiologic data (e.g., does the 
duration of status in febrile seizures influence the probabil-
ity of development of epilepsy?). 3,4 However, these experi-
mentally observed delays have raised the notion that in rat 
models, different physiologic or pathophysiologic processes 
are provoked with progressively longer periods of status 
epilepticus. 
In this report we used magnetic resonance spectroscopy 
(MRS) with a multivariate analysis approach to evaluate the 
metabolic changes in the setting of variable injury. This 
metabolomics approach uses the numerous measurements 
commonly available from MRS without bias to identify the 
programmatic changes that may be provoked by the sei-
zures. Given that earlier studies have found substantial 
metabolic changes during the acute postseizure and epilep-
togenesis period, 5,6 this approach may show coherent 
changes between the metabolites that reflect their known 
roles in neuronal and glial compartments. N-Acetyl aspar-
tate (NAA) has been closely identified with neuronal mito-
chondrial function, 7 whereas glutamate is the dominant 
excitatory neurotransmitter and intermediate in the genera-
tion of ATP within the neuronal-glial metabolic cycle. 8,9 
Although there is extensive contact between the neurotrans-
mitter and metabolic pools of glutamate, 10 the amount of 
extracellular neurotransmitter glutamate is small (&lt;3 lM 11 ), 
and thus the large majority arises from intracellular pools of 
glutamate. c-Aminobutyric acid (GABA), which provides 
important inhibitory balance to neurotransmitter glutamate 
(Glu), has a comparatively smaller direct role in energy </p>

<p>metabolism than glutamate 12 and is found primarily in 
GABAergic neurons. For the glial biomarkers, increased 
myo-inositol (Ins/tCr) and glutamine (Gln/tCr) have been 
linked with reactive astrocytic activation consistent with the 
known postseizure changes in osmolarity and increased glu-
tamate clearance. 5,13,14 In several of these studies and as dis-
cussed by Connett, 15 metabolite ratios taken relative to total 
creatine (tCr) provide an informative assessment of metabo-
lites that interact with ATP and are supported by the creatine 
kinase system. These measurements are thus considered not 
as absolute concentrations but rather as an index of its func-
tion that needs to be compared to control. 
The Hellier Dudek incremented kainate model 16,17 is 
based on 3 h of status epilepticus to consistently generate 
recurrent seizures and temporal lobe epilepsy pathology. In 
this study, we take the Hellier Dudek approach applied with 
a short status epilepticus period of 45 min. With this time 
frame, we are very close to the apparent pivot point found 
by Motte 1998 and Norwood 2010. Furthermore, given the 
known variation due to the bioavailability of intraperitoneal 
kainate injections (e.g., resulting from differences in local 
kainate absorption and brain penetration), we hypothesize 
that a 45-min Hellier Dudek model will generate a spectrum 
of injury. This report describes results from in 21 kainate-
treated rats, at 3 days and 3 weeks post-status epilepticus 
and 10 control rats. In a subgroup of animals, we obtained 
histology with Nissl staining after the 3-week time point to 
provide histologic context for the metabolic measurements. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Animal model 
A short version of the Hellier Dudek 16,17 incremented 
kainate (KA) model of temporal lobe epilepsy was used. 
Male Sprague-Dawley rats (180-200 g) were housed indi-
vidually and handled daily during a 5-day acclimation per-
iod until model preparation. At the time of injection, rats 
weighed 212.8 AE 10.0 g (mean and standard deviation). 
Animals were injected intraperitoneally and hourly with 
5 mg/kg kainate prepared in sterile saline until a stage 3/4/5 
seizure (Racine 1972 18 ) was elicited. The timing of status 
epilepticus (SE) started after this first stage 3/4/5 seizure 
and ended 45 min after this first seizure (typical duration of 
process for injection and status, 3-4 h). Figure 3 shows the 
total doses of kainate. Control rats were treated equivalently 
with sterile saline. Seizures were terminated with subcuta-
neous 20 mg/kg diazepam, which eliminated all behavioral 
seizures and resulted in apparent sedation. Rats were then 
given 5 ml warmed subcutaneous Lactated Ringer's solu-
tion and returned to their home cage. After SE, rats were 
weighed daily and given 5 ml warmed Lactated Ringer's 
and moistened rat chow to facilitate recovery. Up to the 
completion of imaging, we experienced a mortality rate of 
14%, which is consistent with the anticipated 15% projected 
for this model. 16 All animal experiments were approved by </p>

<p>Key Points 
• The Hellier Dudek model applied with 45 min status </p>

<p>epilepticus duration generates a mild-to-moderate 
range of metabolic injury as measured by MRS </p>

<p>• There was no apparent difference in these animals </p>

<p>based on kainate dosing or seizure count </p>

<p>• A multivariate cluster analysis of MRS changes per-</p>

<p>formed 3 days after the status epilepticus segregated 
the animals into mild and moderate injury groups </p>

<p>• Three weeks after status epilepticus, cerebral meta-</p>

<p>bolic changes consistent with the 3-day segregation of 
mild or moderate injury were found </p>

<p>• Histologic assessment 3 weeks after status epilepticus </p>

<p>showed differences in neuronal loss and gliosis that 
was also consistent with the 3-day cluster analysis </p>

<p>Epilepsia, 57(12):1978-1986, 2016 
doi: 10.1111/epi.13588 </p>



<p>A Variable Rat Model of Post-Status Injury </p>

<p>the institutional animal care and use committee at the 
University of Pittsburgh (PHS Assurance A3187-01) and 
Carnegie Mellon University and were conducted in accor-
dance with the U.S. Public Health Service's Policy on 
Humane Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. No adverse 
events were noted during this study. 
A total of 21 kainate-treated animals were studied, of 
which 19 survived to complete the 3-week post-status imag-
ing study. In addition, 10 control rats were studied. Two 
imaging studies were performed: 3 days after SE and 
3 weeks after SE. All values are reported as mean and stan-
dard deviation. Control rats weighed 246.2 AE 11.7 g at 
3 days and 382 AE 27.2 g at 3 weeks, whereas the 45-min 
kainate-treated animals weighed 221.8 AE 10.7 and 
372.9 AE 22.3 g at 3 days and 3 weeks, respectively. All 
imaging studies were performed between 8 a.m. and 
3 p.m.. Rats were briefly anesthetized with isoflurane, intu-
bated, and secured in a cradle for MR imaging. Anesthesia 
was maintained by adjusting isoflurane 2%, N 2 O at 50 PSIG 
and O 2 at 200 pounds per square inch gauge. A rectal ther-
mal probe monitoring temperature was linked with feedback 
control to a warmed air source to maintain a 37°C body tem-
perature. A subset of eight kainate-treated animals and four 
controls were evaluated after the 3-week imaging study with 
Nissl histologic analysis. </p>

<p>Magnetic resonance 
A Bruker Biospec 7T 40 cm horizontal MR system was 
used with a 72-mm volume transmit coil and two-element 
receiver array. After initial three-direction localizer acquisi-
tions, T 2 -weighted RARE (rapid acquisition with relaxation 
enhancement multiple spin echo) acquisitions were 
acquired for optimal hippocampal slice positioning 
(Fig. 1A). Single-voxel point resolved spectroscopy 
(PRESS) 8 ll (2 9 2 9 2 or 2 9 1.8 9 2.2 mm 3 ) acquisi-
tions (17 min/voxel) at echo time (TE) 10 msec/TR 1.8 s 
were performed separately over the left and right dentate 
gyrus and CA3 regions of the hippocampus. Water suppres-
sion was performed using a VAPOR sequence. Linear com-
bination model (LCM) 19 analysis was performed for 
determination of the metabolite measurements, taken as a 
ratio to total creatine. Analyses were performed without 
identification as to animal grouping, and metabolites with a 
Cramer-Rao lower bound &gt;15% were omitted from further 
analysis. At TE = 10 msec, the metabolite ratios are mini-
mally affected by transverse relaxation values (for a typical 
T2 of 130 msec, this is 8%) but are affected by T1 and 
should largely be compared between control and experi-
mental groups. For each animal, the homologous left and 
right measurements were averaged. </p>

<p>Cluster analyses 
To assess the metabolic changes induced in this protocol, 
a multivariate analysis was performed. Initially, a hierarchi-
cal clustering was performed on the 3-day MRS data, with </p>

<p>the 21 kainate-treated animals. Eight MRS-identified com-
pounds were used: NAA, Glu, Ins, Gln, GABA, Glc, and 
Lac, all taken as a ratio to total Cr. This exploratory multi-
variate approach uses the MRS data to define a linear dis-
tance between all possible pairs of animals, and then groups 
the animals according to their distance values into "agglom-
erative" clusters to minimize the variance of distances 
within any given cluster. These subgroups were then evalu-
ated for their group metabolic characteristics. To further 
validate the clustering process, a machine learning approach 
was used with all of the clustered animal data to indepen-
dently classify each animal using a leave-one-out analysis. 
As the definition of the clusters was determined by the MRS 
data, effectively all the spectroscopic data analysis was 
blinded. 
Comparing the three groups (control and two kainate 
clusters), analysis of variance (ANOVA) statistics with 
Dunn-Sidak multiple comparisons testing correction was 
calculated, accepting significance at p &lt; 0.05. All analyses 
were calculated using <rs id="software-1" type="software">MATLAB</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">2013b</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">MathWorks</rs>, Nat-
ick, MA, U.S.A.) and <rs type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs>. R1.1 A separate t-
test was performed between the control and grouped kainate 
animals, with significance accepted at p &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Histology 
Eight kainate-treated and four control brains were taken 
after the 3-week imaging time point to provide histologic 
context to the spectroscopy. This was performed by tran-
scardial perfusion with phosphate-buffered saline pH 7.4 
followed by 4% buffered paraformaldehyde. After over-
night postfixation, brains were cut on a Vibratome into 50-
lm-thick serial sections and stored in a cryoprotectant solu-
tion until staining. At 300-lm intervals through the dorsal 
hippocampus, sections were stained with cresyl violet, 
which stains the Nissl substance in all neurons and the 
DNA of all nuclei including glia. Stained sections were 
evaluated with bright-field microscopy using a subjective 
semiquantitative ordinal scale to indicate the degree of 
neuronal loss in the separate subregions of the dorsal 
hippocampus relative to controls. Although the analysis 
of the semiquantitative histologic was performed with 
knowledge of the total animal group proportions, specific 
samples were blinded. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Spectra and group results 
Figure 1A,B show the positions of the dentate gyrus 
(DG), CA3 voxels, and the performance of the LCM analy-
sis for a 3-day animal. As a group at 3 days, all 45-min rats 
showed significantly decreased NAA/tCr, increased Ins/tCr, 
Gln/tCr and Lac/tCr in comparison to control (Fig. 3). 
These changes are consistent with the occurrence of sei-
zures, with evidence for neuronal mitochondrial injury (de-
creased NAA/tCr), glial activation with osmotic changes </p>

<p>Epilepsia, 57(12):1978-1986, 2016 
doi: 10.1111/epi.13588 </p>



<p>P. S. Pearce et al. </p>

<p>and glutamine synthetase activation (Ins/tCr, Gln/tCr 
respectively), and glycolytic energy production (Lac/tCr) 
commonly seen in seizures and post-status. However, as 
anticipated, there was variability with the kainate-treated 
animals, seen from the 3-day and 3-week spectra (see 
Fig. 1C,D). Because data from the CA3 locus did not sub-
stantially change these results, these data are available in 
Supporting Information. </p>

<p>Cluster analysis 
With the possibility that a wide range of injuries might be 
identified with the 45-min status period, we evaluated the 
animals using a hierarchical cluster approach on the 3-day 
MRS results. The dentate gyrus voxel was used, as this 
receives much of the hippocampal input and is a known 
locus for establishment of recurrent excitatory circuits. 20 
The analysis was performed using a two-cluster structure 
where each animal is one data point (averaging the left and 
right). Figure 2A shows the 3-day two-cluster result, sepa-
rating the 21 kainate-treated animals into groups of 6 and 
15. For clarity, the three-dimensional plot is shown with two 
perspectives, showing the metabolite differences in NAA/ 
tCr, Glu/tCr, and GABA/tCr. Control data (blue) are also 
included on this plot for comparative purposes. The largest 
change was identified in the 6 (red) animals that had NAA/ 
tCr values below the value of 1.0, whereas the 15 (green) 
animals show a small increase in Glu/tCr. The 6 animals </p>

<p>were identified as kainate group KM ("more" injured), and 
the 15 as kainate group KL ("less" injured). The two-cluster 
analysis taken with the CA sector voxel could segregate five 
of the six same animals (data not shown). 
Given that the cluster analysis on the 3-day MRS data 
was able to segregate the animals, it was of interest to under-
stand whether the same clusters could be used in a machine-
learning approach to discriminate between the animals. 
With a leave-one-out method for cross validation, each ani-
mal was tested as a new sample point against the remainder 
of the animals. The cross validation error with this approach 
was small, at 3.23%, consistent with the data shown in Fig-
ure 2A with the relatively large distances between the three 
clusters, the largest distance parameter being NAA/tCr. </p>

<p>Metabolic differences between the clusters 
The cluster analysis of the kainate-treated animals at 
3 days identified 6 and 15 animals in terms of their meta-
bolic patterns, suggesting two levels of injury. The n = 6 
KM group showed a 28.7% decline in NAA/tCr compared 
to the 10 controls animals, whereas the n = 15 KL group 
showed a 6.0% decline. From this segregation, the KM 
group generally shows worse changes in the other metabolic 
parameters. This is manifest with a greater decline in Glu/ 
tCr, and larger changes in glial biomarkers, with increased 
inositol Ins/tCr, glutamine Gln/tCr, and also increased lac-
tate Lac/tCr (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Figure 1. 
Scout (A) showing typical loci for the dentate gyrus (DG) and CA3 (CA) voxels. (B) LCM analyzed DG spectrum from a KA-treated ani-
mal, showing individual metabolites. Corresponding spectra acquired at 3 days (C) and 3 weeks (D) are shown from single (all survival) 
rats, showing matched control and two KA rats. Identified metabolites are shown in the control 3-day spectrum. The 3-day spectra from 
the two KA rats show variability, consistent with a "less" and "more" injured grouping. The arrows on the "more injured" 3-day spectra 
show a decreased NAA and increased Ins. The "less injured" 3-day spectra show primarily the increased Ins. 
Epilepsia ILAE </p>

<p>Epilepsia, 57(12):1978-1986, 2016 
doi: 10.1111/epi.13588 </p>



<p>A Variable Rat Model of Post-Status Injury </p>

<p>The KL group showed similar but milder changes, with 
the exception of the 3-day glutamatergic biomarker Glu/ 
tCr, which increased rather than decreased. For the 3-week 
studies, one animal from each of the groups (control, KM, 
KL) did not successfully complete the study. Both the KM 
and KL groups exhibited recovery after the status period 
such that the differences in metabolites were generally 
smaller at 3 weeks than at 3 days. For NAA/tCr, the KL 
group had returned to control values at 1.28 AE 0.12, 
whereas in the KM group it stayed depressed at 
1.00 AE 0.12 (control, 1.30 AE 0.15). The 3-week KM 
group also continued to show a significantly increased Ins/ 
tCr and a decreased Glu/tCr. In contrast, the 3-week KL 
group had largely normalized all of its metabolic parame-
ters, including NAA/tCr, Ins/tCr, and Gln/tCr, with Glu/ 
tCr decreasing to a normal level. To show the multivariate 
evolution of these data, Figure 2B shows the same three-
dimensional plot of NAA/tCr, Glu/tCr, and GABA/tCr 
tracking the KL, KM, and control animals into the 3-week 
study. Consistent with Figure 3, the KM group displays 
persistently low NAA/tCr, with simultaneous declines in 
Glu/tCr and GABA/tCr. A separate cluster analysis of the 
3-week dentate gyrus data co-identified four of the five 
KM animals as separate from the other animals; these ani-
mals are identified by asterisks in Figure 2B. </p>

<p>Histology 
To provide histologic context to the KM and KL 
groups, a subset (n = 8) of animals from the KM (n = 4) 
and KL (n = 4) groups was analyzed with Nissl staining 
in comparison to n = 4 controls. Table 1 summarizes 
these data with their 3-day dentate gyrus spectroscopic 
data. Animals from the KL group have a dorsal hip-
pocampus that is largely intact in all subregions, although 
two animals in this group showed minimal neuron loss in 
the hilus. In contrast, the KM animals show significant 
neuronal loss most apparent in area CA1 and in some 
cases extending into the subiculum. In these regions, neu-
rons of the pyramidal cell layers are largely replaced by 
glia. Increased glial proliferation is also seen in the adja-
cent stratum radiatum. Neuronal loss is evident in the 
hilus and CA3 regions. In general, the patterns on neu-
ronal loss on the left and right sides are similar. This is 
evident in the photo micrographs shown in Figure 4 from 
KL 77 and 92, KM 81 and 87 which are from the animals 
that showed the least and most damage from each of the 
two groups respectively. In the KM group, the two ani-
mals with the greatest dorsal gliosis (80 and 81) had the 
lowest NAA/tCr values. In the KL group, the two animals 
with any degree of abnormality (88 and 92) exhibited the 
greatest Gln/tCr but also the largest Glu/tCr values. </p>

<p>Figure 2. 
Cluster analysis of kainate-treated animals (n = 21 total), showing three-dimensional plots of NAA/tCr, Glu/tCr, and GABA/tCr from 
the DG locus. For comparison, control animals are also shown. (A) Three-day data; (B) 3-week data. For both (A and B), the plots are 
shown from two rotated perspectives to show the relationships between NAA/tCr with GABA/tCr (left) and between Glu/tCr with 
GABA/tCr (right) more clearly. The largest separation between KL and KM is in the 3-day data with NAA/tCr (panel A, left). Red repre-
sents the KM group; green are the KL group; blue are the control group. Four (asterisked) of the 5 KM animals in the 3-week data are ani-
mals that were segregated by a separate cluster analysis of 3-week data alone. 
Epilepsia ILAE </p>

<p>Epilepsia, 57(12):1978-1986, 2016 
doi: 10.1111/epi.13588 </p>



<p>P. S. Pearce et al. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Cluster analysis of a variable model 
These data show that the short Hellier Dudek model 
generates a wide range of metabolic dysfunction, ranging 
from mild to more severe injury. It is also consistent with 
the practice of using longer periods of status to generate a 
high rate of recurrent seizures. A multivariate cluster ana-
lysis is able to separate within the kainate-treated group to 
define more injured versus less injured (KM vs. KL 
respectively) animals, even though there was no apparent </p>

<p>difference in seizure severity or required kainate doses in 
these groups. The relevance of this analysis is supported 
by the Nissl analysis from the dorsal hippocampus and by 
the consistency and persistence of these changes at 
3 weeks after status. </p>

<p>Metabolic shifts in the cluster groups 
It is worth considering the magnitude of differences rela-
tive to control in the two groups. At 3 days, the KL group 
exhibits a 6.0% decline in NAA/tCr accompanied by a 6.7% 
increase in Glu/tCr, retrospectively hypothesized as a </p>

<p>Figure 3. 
Bar plots showing the mean values and standard deviations from the two cluster (KM n = 6, KL n = 15) and control (n = 10) groups from 
3 days (solid bars) and the same animals from 3 weeks (KM, n = 5; KL n = 14; control n = 9; cross-hatched bars). The KM and KL groups 
are also combined to show the group statistics from the summed KA-treated group. All data are from the DG locus. (A) NAA/tCr; (B) 
Glu/tCr; (C) Ins/tCr; (D) Gln/tCr; (E) GABA/tCr; (F) GSH/tCr; (G) Lac/tCr; (H) KA dosing and seizure counts from model preparation. 
For the KM, KL, and control groups, significance testing is performed using a one-way ANOVA with multiple testing corrections (Dunn-
Sidak), p &lt; 0.05. *Significant differences p &lt; 0.05 between control and KM or KL group; ^Significant difference p &lt; 0.05 between KM 
and KL. For the combined KM + KL versus control groups, significance testing is performed using a t-test (p &lt; 0.05); *Significant differ-
ences p &lt; 0.05 between the control and KM + KL groups. 
Epilepsia ILAE </p>

<p>Epilepsia, 57(12):1978-1986, 2016 
doi: 10.1111/epi.13588 </p>



<p>A Variable Rat Model of Post-Status Injury </p>

<p>metabolically "healthy" response to SE. This is accompa-
nied by a 6.7% rise in Ins/tCr and 19.1% rise in Gln/tCr. 
3 weeks later; the metabolic changes in this group return to 
normal. It would appear that although the 3-day changes are 
significant, at 3 weeks, the animals display metabolic 
recovery with minimal histologic changes. 
In the KM group, there are larger changes in both NAA/ 
tCr (À28.7%) and Glu/tCr (À8.6%), whereas Ins/tCr 
(12.6%) and Gln/tCr (36.5%) increase, consistent with a 
broad injury across both neuronal and glial compartments. 
There is a more than doubling of the tissue Lac/tCr (+147% 
rise) in these animals. Considering that these studies were 
acquired 3 days after status, these are persistent metabolic 
changes, and may be a result of permanent injury, prolonged 
recovery, or responses that reflect post-status processes. At 
3 weeks, the KM group does not exhibit normalization of 
Glu/tCr, NAA/tCr; Ins/tCr and Gln/tCr remain increased. 
The histologic data in the KM group bear out substantial 
injury with gliosis and neuronal loss. 
The glutamate/tCr (Glu/tCr) parameter is of particular 
interest given its splay between the KL and KM groups. 
The 3-day KL group displayed increased Glu/tCr 
(1.38 AE 0.12), whereas the 3-day KM group showed 
decreased Glu/tCr (1.18 AE 0.10; control 1.29 AE 0.08, 
both significantly different from control). It is possible 
that T2 relaxation changes could contribute to this obser-
vation; however, use of a short 10-msec TE sharply lim-
its such effects. Thus the alternative needs to be 
considered, that is, that the observed Glu/tCr increase in 
KL is a response to excitatory injury, supporting 
increased resistance to ictogenic insult. 21 There is evi-
dence for this, such as excitatory synapse redistribution, 22 
increased gene expression for inflammation, oxidative 
stress, and calcium signaling. 23 Furthermore, given that 
glutamate is an intermediate in energy generation, 
increased pool size for energy production could result in 
increased glutamate content and thus be a potentially 
"healthy" response to a (presumptively mild) seizure 
insult. Three weeks later both Glu/tCr and NAA/tCr nor-
malize, this being consistent with the overall healthier 
KL group, and its fewer histologic abnormalities. In con-
trast, the KM group's decrease in NAA/tCr is three-fold 
higher than the drop in Glu/tCr and may reflect perma-
nent injury, consistent with its histology and the persis-
tently low NAA/tCr (À20.9% compared with control) at 
3 weeks. 
From a glial perspective, the KL data define a range 
of variability for Ins/tCr and Gln/tCr from which meta-
bolic recovery appears possible. As is well known, glu-
tamine is in balance between several systems of 
glutamate neurotransmission, ammonia homeostasis, and 
oxidative flux. Thus there are many factors that may 
influence Gln/tCr. From the KM group, our observations 
of sizable increases in Gln/tCr (36.5%, approximately 
twofold larger than the KL group at 19.1%) is consistent </p>

<p>Table 1. Semiquantitative Nissl-staining analysis </p>

<p>Rat no. </p>

<p>GC </p>

<p>Hilus </p>

<p>CA3 prox </p>

<p>CA3 distal </p>

<p>CA1 </p>

<p>Sub </p>

<p>Gliosis </p>

<p>NAA 1.23 </p>

<p>AE 0.08 </p>

<p>Glu 1.29 </p>

<p>AE 0.08 </p>

<p>Ins 0.94 </p>

<p>AE 0.07 </p>

<p>Gln 0.33 </p>

<p>AE 0.07 </p>

<p>GABA 0.40 </p>

<p>AE 0.05 </p>

<p>KL76 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1.08 </p>

<p>1.22 </p>

<p>1.17 </p>

<p>0.33 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>KL77 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1.19 </p>

<p>1.33 </p>

<p>0.88 </p>

<p>0.26 </p>

<p>0.43 </p>

<p>KL88 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1.11 </p>

<p>1.43 </p>

<p>0.92 </p>

<p>0.41 </p>

<p>0.38 </p>

<p>KL92 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1.26 </p>

<p>1.57 </p>

<p>0.97 </p>

<p>0.48 </p>

<p>0.37 </p>

<p>KM80 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.83 </p>

<p>1.11 </p>

<p>1.02 </p>

<p>0.49 </p>

<p>0.34 </p>

<p>KM81 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.86 </p>

<p>1.18 </p>

<p>1.11 </p>

<p>0.43 </p>

<p>0.33 </p>

<p>KM87 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ + </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>0.92 </p>

<p>1.14 </p>

<p>1.04 </p>

<p>0.47 </p>

<p>0.32 </p>

<p>KM98 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>0.90 </p>

<p>1.17 </p>

<p>1.01 </p>

<p>0.37 </p>

<p>0.36 </p>

<p>GC, granule cell layer; CA3 px, CA3 proximal; CA3 dist, CA3 distal; Sub, subiculum. 
All animals were killed after the 3-week imaging study, and preserved using 4% buffered paraformaldehyde. Data are presented as the differences compared to control. Left seven columns: histologic region of analysis. 
Right five columns: corresponding metabolite ratios taken to total creatine from the dentate gyrus; left/right values averaged per animal. Control MRS values are shown in top header row. Top four rows KL; bottom four 
rows KM. </p>

<p>Epilepsia, 57(12):1978-1986, 2016 
doi: 10.1111/epi.13588 </p>



<p>P. S. Pearce et al. </p>

<p>with results of Van der Hel 24 and may be due partially 
to conversion of excitatory glutamate (which decreased 
by 8.6%) into glutamine, given that the normal Glu-Gln 
neurotransmission cycling is most likely not occurring in 
the injured KM group. 25 This dysfunctional cycling is 
likely to also contribute to observations from human tem-
poral lobe epilepsy cases showing normal levels of extra-
cellular glutamine even in the face of decreased 
glutamine synthetase and known gliosis. 26,27 </p>

<p>Caveats 
The major caveat in this work is that of the use of 
metabolite ratios with total creatine. The theoretical basis 
for its use has been discussed by Connett, 15 who proposed 
it as a thermodynamically useful normalization in the anal-
ysis of bioenergetic processes in tissues that use the cre-
atine kinase system as a mechanism for ATP buffering. In 
this analysis, a ratio with total creatine provides a measure </p>

<p>of its dispersion from baseline, which we would argue that 
for the metabolites discussed in this work is highly perti-
nent. Nonetheless, if the creatine transport system itself 
becomes distorted in the post-status period, such ratios will 
be problematic. There are relatively few data on this issue, 
but Gupta et al. 28 found no significant change in total cre-
atine at 3 days in an acetylcholinesterase model of sei-
zures; and Melo, 29 using a pilocarpine model, similarly 
found no significant changes at 1 month in chronically 
epileptic rats. We would argue that the 45-min duration of 
status is comparatively brief and believe that as biomarkers 
of physiologic functions, the observed metabolic changes 
stand. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Overall, these results are consistent with programmatic 
metabolic processes that are variably instigated by the 45-</p>

<p>Figure 4. 
Nissl-stained sections through the dorsal hippocampus for a control and two KL and KM animals (see Table 1 for matching identifiers). 
The arrows separate the various CA sectors. The neuronal loss in CA1 is marked for the bottom two KM animals, and asterisks mark the 
extensive gliosis in the stratum radiatum. S, subiculum; GC, granule cell layer; H, hilus, CA3p, CA3 proximal, CA3d, CA3 distal. 
Epilepsia ILAE </p>

<p>Epilepsia, 57(12):1978-1986, 2016 
doi: 10.1111/epi.13588 </p>



<p>A Variable Rat Model of Post-Status Injury </p>

<p>min status, consistent with a range between extreme versus 
pathologic neurotransmission. The generation of the two 
discrete groups (rather than a conglomeration of one injured 
group) is the notable observation. That these metabolically 
identified groups appear to propagate into the 3-week time 
point argues for the notion that the short &lt;1 h status period 
seems to generate a tipping point, as discussed earlier. It will 
be of interest to understand whether these metabolic 
changes, reflecting their neuronal and glial sources, link 
with cellular processes of gene expression, remodeling, and 
inflammation, which may be related to the ultimate devel-
opment of spontaneous recurrent seizures. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health R21 
NS083035, R01 NS090417, and R01 EB116309. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>None of the authors has any conflicts of interest to disclose. We confirm 
that we have read the Journal's position on issues involved in ethical publi-
cation and affirm that this report is consistent with those guidelines. </p>



<p>Supporting Information </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the 
online version of this article: 
Table S1. Group means of metabolite ratios from CA3 
voxels. </p>

<p>Epilepsia, 57(12):1978-1986, 2016 
doi: 10.1111/epi.13588 </p>



<p>P. S. Pearce et al. </p>

</text></tei>