<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5314818" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>It is recognised that ovarian factors, including steroid and protein hormones, are 
critical in the feedback regulation of pituitary gonadotropins; however, their individual 
contributions are less defined. The aim of this study was to explore the reciprocal 
relationships between ovarian and pituitary hormones across the normal ovulatory 
menstrual cycle as women age. FSH, LH, oestradiol, progesterone, inhibin A, inhibin B 
and anti-mullerian hormone (AMH) were measured in serum collected every 1-3 days 
across one interovulatory interval (IOI) from 26 healthy women aged 18-50 years. 
The antral follicle count (AFC) for follicles 2-5 mm, &gt;6 mm and 2-10 mm were tabulated 
across the IOI. Independent associations between ovarian hormones/AFC vs pituitary 
follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and luteinising hormone (LH) were investigated using 
multivariate regression analysis. The data were sub-grouped based on the presence or 
absence luteal phase-dominant follicles (LPDF). Serum oestradiol and AMH were inversely 
correlated with FSH in both follicular and luteal phases. Inhibin B correlated inversely with 
FSH and LH in the late follicular phase and directly in the luteal phase. AFC, inhibin A and 
progesterone were not key predictors of either FSH or LH. The strong association between 
AMH and FSH with age implies that AMH, as well as oestradiol and inhibin B are important 
regulators of FSH. The change in feedback response of inhibin B with both FSH and LH 
across the cycle suggests two phases of the negative feedback. </p>

<p>It is well recognised that ovarian hormones exert a strong 
inhibitory effect on the pituitary secretion of FSH and 
LH, as reflected by a 6-to 12-fold increase in the human 
pituitary secretion of FSH and LH after ovariectomy (1). 
The key ovarian factors believed responsible are the 
steroids, oestradiol and progesterone, and the protein </p>

<p>hormones, inhibin A and B. However, their respective 
roles are not clearly understood. 
In a previous study ((2), and (3) designated in this 
article as the 2009 study), attempts were made to identify 
the key ovarian hormone factors that are responsible 
for the feedback regulation of pituitary FSH and LH in </p>

<p>Correspondence 
should be addressed 
to D M Robertson 
Email 
david.robertson@hudson. 
org.au </p>

<p>Key Words </p>

<p>f anti-mullerian hormone </p>

<p>f inhibin B </p>

<p>f FSH </p>

<p>f LH </p>

<p>f oestradiol </p>

<p>Endocrine Connections 
(2016) 5, 98-107 </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1530/EC-16-0077 </p>

<p>http://www.endocrineconnections.org 
© 2016 The authors 
Published by Bioscientifica Ltd </p>

<p>Research 
D M Robertson et al. 
Ovarian:pituitary feedback 
mechanisms </p>

<p>Endocrine Connections </p>

<p>99-107 
5:99 </p>

<p>women by exploring their independent associations using 
a multivariate regression analysis. This study consisted of 
76 asymptomatic women aged between 21 and 55 years 
investigated over one complete menstrual cycle. Serum 
FSH, LH, oestradiol, progesterone, inhibin A, inhibin B 
and AMH were measured every 3 days across the cycle. 
The data were then analysed across the follicular and 
luteal phases. The results indicated that in the follicular 
phase, both inhibin B and AMH were inversely associated 
with FSH and inhibin B with LH. In comparison, in the 
luteal phase, oestradiol and progesterone were inversely 
associated with both serum FSH and LH. There appeared 
to be a 3-day lagged response between inhibin B and 
FSH. The apparent inverse relationships between ovarian 
and pituitary hormones were surprising as there is little 
evidence to support many of these roles, particularly 
AMH as feedback regulators of FSH and LH. 
A number of questions arose from this study: 
(a) Is the close association between AMH and FSH 
due to the possibility that AMH may directly 
regulate FSH or act as a proxy for another ovarian 
factor (perhaps unknown)? Would the association 
between AMH and FSH weaken if follicle size and 
number were included as factors in the analysis? 
(b) The AMH ELISA used in the 2009 study had 
limited sensitivity and was only able to detect 
serum AMH in 36% of advanced reproductive 
aged women. Would the availability of more 
sensitive AMH ELISAs (reported to detect AMH in 
&gt;95% of samples, (4)) provide a more complete </p>

<p>AMH data set? 
(c) To what extent does the presence of hormone-
secreting luteal phase-dominant follicles (LPDFs) 
influence feedback relationships between ovarian 
and pituitary hormones? It has been previously 
shown (5, 6) that there are 2-3 follicular waves 
across each interovulatory interval (IOI). A 
dominant follicle (i.e., ≥10 mm) may develop 
from any of the waves that emerge during the IOI. 
In women of reproductive age, only one wave of 
the IOI has been shown to result in ovulation. 
In comparison, as women approach menopause, 
the waves preceding the late follicular phase 
ovulatory wave of the IOI can result in the 
development of luteal phase-dominant follicles 
(LPDFs, ≥10 mm), which may regress or ovulate. 
In older women, LPDFs grow larger over a longer 
period of time, in some cases extending into the 
subsequent follicular phase. </p>

<p>A recent independent study (7) was undertaken 
to characterise age-related changes in antral follicle 
dynamics and hormone production across the IOI. This 
study consisted of 26 women between the ages of 18 
and 50 years. Serum FSH, LH, oestradiol, progesterone, 
inhibin A, inhibin B, AMH, antral follicle count (AFC) 
and follicle diameter were determined every 1-3 days 
across the IOI. Cycles were sub-grouped according to 
whether they exhibited LPDFs. LPDFs in women of 
advanced reproductive age were associated with elevated 
serum oestradiol and inhibin B levels as well as reduced 
inhibin A and progesterone in the luteal phase (7). These 
studies have provided to date an increased understanding 
into age-related associations between follicle diameter, 
number and hormone production as women age. 
However, the precise regulatory mechanisms between 
ovarian vs pituitary hormones as women age remain 
poorly understood. 
The present study provided an opportunity to further 
explore the relationships between ovarian and pituitary 
hormones, as a progression from our previous work (2, 3). 
The inclusion of data to characterise antral follicular 
dynamics, AFC and AMH (using a more sensitive assay) 
provided additional insights about the physiological 
regulation of the human menstrual cycle. 
The objectives of the present study were to (a) confirm 
the previously observed relationships between pituitary 
and ovarian hormones, (b) clarify the role of additional 
ovarian factors (follicle diameter and AFC) as possible 
variables in feedback mechanisms, (c) assess whether a 
clearer picture of hormone regulation is observed with 
the introduction of a highly sensitive AMH ELISA and 
(d) explore whether the presence of a LPDF affects the 
ovarian-pituitary hormone feedback relationships. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>The study protocol was approved by the Biomedical 
Research Ethics Board at the University of Saskatchewan 
and the Strategic Priorities and Planning Committee 
of the Saskatoon Health Region. Study procedures 
were conducted in accordance with the Tri-Council 
Policy Statement on the Ethical Conduct for Research 
Involving Humans. Healthy women (aged 18-50, 
n = 26) with ovulatory menstrual cycles were recruited 
from the Saskatoon Health Region, University of 
Saskatchewan, and the Women's Midlife Health Centre 
of Saskatchewan. Informed consent was obtained from </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1530/EC-16-0077 </p>

<p>http://www.endocrineconnections.org 
© 2016 The authors 
Published by Bioscientifica Ltd </p>

<p>Research 
D M Robertson et al. 
Ovarian:pituitary feedback 
mechanisms </p>

<p>Endocrine Connections </p>

<p>100-107 
5:100 </p>

<p>all participants before study procedures were initiated. 
Details of the subjects, study design, hormone 
measurements, antral follicle dynamics and AFC 
assessments used in this study have been published 
previously (7). In brief, healthy women (aged 18-50, 
n = 26) with ovulatory menstrual cycles were recruited 
for this study. Selection criteria and ethics approvals 
were outlined previously (7). Blood samples were 
collected every 1-3 days over one IOI. An IOI was 
defined as the time interval from one ovulation to 
the subsequent ovulation. Sera were assayed for FSH, 
LH, oestradiol, progesterone, inhibin A, inhibin B and 
AMH. AMH was assayed using two different ELISAs: 
AMH-Gen-II (Beckman Coulter, Chaska, USA) and AMH 
24/32 (Anshlabs, Webster, Texas, USA (4)). The AMH 
24/32 ELISA is a much more sensitive assay compared 
to AMH-Gen-II ELISA, enabling the detection of serum 
AMH in women of advanced reproductive age. The AFC 
for 3 different diameter categories (i.e., AFC 2-5 mm, 
2-10 mm and ≥6 mm) was quantified using serial 
transvaginal ultrasonography every 1-3 days across the 
IOI as previously described (7). </p>

<p>Analyses </p>

<p>Hormone and follicle data across the IOI were binned into 
10 groups. Ovulation 1 (Ov1, days −1, Ov, +1), early luteal 
phase (ELP, +2, +3, +4), mid-luteal phase (MLP, +5, +6, +7), 
late luteal phase (LLP, +8, +9, +10) and very late luteal 
phase (VLLP, +11, +12, +13), menstruation (Men, −1, Men, 
+1), early follicular phase (EFP, +2, +3, +4), mid follicular 
phase, (MFP, +5, +6, +7), late follicular phase (LFP, +8, +9, 
+10) and ovulation 2 (OV2, −1, Ov2, +1). 
The statistical procedures employed were consistent 
with those used previously (3) to provide continuity 
and provide a basis for comparison between studies. The 
data were analysed initially using multiple regression 
analysis by assessing the associations between ovarian 
hormones (FSH and LH) as independent variables 
and ovarian hormones/AFC as dependent variables. 
A multivariate regression model with FSH and LH 
as dependent variables and other ovarian factors as 
predictors was also developed. Data were evaluated in 
3-day windows across the entire follicular phase, in two 
divisions of the follicular phase termed FP1 (including 
Men and EFP groups) and FP2 (MLP and LFP groups) and 
the luteal phase. In some analyses, age was sub-grouped 
into &lt;40 years and ≥40 years. The slope coefficients for </p>

<p>the various comparisons were determined following 
log transformation (referred to as ln_outcome) of both 
outcome and predictors. Data transformation permitted a 
comparison of the magnitude of the slope values between 
different outcome and predictors. A significant slope value 
for a given comparison was established when its 95% CIs 
did not include 0, as previously reported (3). All statistical 
analyses were conducted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v 9.4</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">2013</rs>; 
Cary, NC, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Independent relationships between ovarian factors 
(hormones and antral follicle count) and pituitary 
factors (FSH and LH) </p>

<p>Associations with age and FSH Scatter plots 
between serum FSH, oestradiol, inhibin B, AMH (24/32) 
and AFC (2-10 mm) vs age are presented in Fig. 1. Using 
a multivariate model ((lnfsh, lnlh, lne2, lnprog, lninha, 
lninhb, lnamh (24-32) and ln_b2 to 10) ~ age), a direct 
association was observed between serum FSH and age; 
inverse associations were noted among inhibin B, AFC 
(2-10 mm) and AMH (24/32) vs age (Fig. 1). In addition, 
significant inverse associations were observed among FSH 
vs inhibin B, AMH (24/32) and AFC (2-10 mm) (Fig. 2). 
More specifically, as FSH increased with age, inhibin B 
and AFC (2-10 mm) decreased (Fig. 2). Network plots of 
these data presenting interactions between the pituitary 
and ovarian factors in the follicular and luteal phases are 
presented in Fig. 3. </p>

<p>Associations 
across 
the 
interovulatory 
interval Associations between FSH and LH (as 
independent variables) vs the ovarian hormones and AFC 
(as outcome or dependent variables) were assessed across 
the IOI (Fig. 4) using multi-regression analysis. Significant 
differences were noted across the cycle with oestradiol 
inversely proportional to FSH in the luteal phase, inhibin 
B inversely proportional to FSH and LH in follicular phase 
and AMH inversely proportional to FSH across the cycle 
and with LH in the luteal phase. 
To assess the associations between ovarian hormones/ 
AFC (as independent variables) vs FSH and LH (as 
dependent or outcome variables), the data were analysed 
using multivariate regression methods either across the 
full follicular phase (Table 1) or within two subdivisions 
(FP1 and FP2) of the follicular phase (Figs 5 and 6). 
Significant inverse relationships were observed across the </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1530/EC-16-0077 </p>

<p>http://www.endocrineconnections.org 
© 2016 The authors 
Published by Bioscientifica Ltd </p>

<p>Research 
D M Robertson et al. 
Ovarian:pituitary feedback 
mechanisms </p>

<p>Endocrine Connections </p>

<p>101-107 
5:101 </p>

<p>follicular and luteal phases between FSH and oestradiol; 
however, the significance of this relationship was lost 
when the follicular phase was sub-grouped into FP1 and 
FP2 (Figs 5, 6 and Table 1). FSH and LH were inversely 
related to inhibin B in the late follicular phase but were 
directly related in the luteal phase. FSH and AMH (24/32) 
showed an inverse response in both phases of the cycle. 
LH and AMH were inversely associated in the luteal 
phase. The patterns between gonadotropins and ovarian 
hormones were similar when AFC (2-5 mm and &gt;6 mm) 
was included in the multivariate regression model </p>

<p>Figure 2 
Representative scatterplots between ovarian and pituitary hormones. 
Serum hormone levels were averaged across one interovulatory interval. 
The red line in each graph is a regression line between X and log Y. </p>

<p>Figure 1 
Representative scatterplots between ovarian and pituitary hormones and 
age. Serum hormone levels presented were averaged across one 
interovulatory interval (i.e. between successive ovulation events). 
The red line on each graph indicates the line of best fit using a piecewise 
modelling approach. Age is divided into two intervals (before 40 and 
after 40) with linear regression lines fitted to the data between 
0-40 and &gt;40 years. </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1530/EC-16-0077 </p>

<p>http://www.endocrineconnections.org 
© 2016 The authors 
Published by Bioscientifica Ltd </p>

<p>Research 
D M Robertson et al. 
Ovarian:pituitary feedback 
mechanisms </p>

<p>Endocrine Connections </p>

<p>102-107 
5:102 </p>

<p>(data not shown). A summary of ovarian and pituitary 
interactions are presented in Table 2. </p>

<p>Associations in women with vs without 
LPDFs The relationships between ovarian factors and 
FSH/LH in cycles with and without a LPDF were also 
assessed (Figs 5 and 6). Generally speaking, similar patterns 
of association were observed between FSH and the various 
ovarian factors in the presence or absence of a LPDF across 
the cycle. In contrast, differences in association between 
LH and ovarian factors were detected in the presence of 
a LPDF. Follicular phase LH was negatively associated </p>

<p>with inhibin B in women with LPDFs but not in women 
without LPDFs. In addition, follicular phase LH correlated 
positively with AMH and negatively with AFC 2-10 mm 
in women without LPDFs. The presence of a LPDF did not 
appear to alter the association between LH and ovarian 
factors in the luteal phase. 
The relationships between FSH/LH and the ovarian 
hormones, oestradiol, progesterone, inhibin A, inhibin 
B and AMH-Gen-II were compared in both the 2009 
(2, 3) and present studies. In both analyses, the serum 
levels of all hormones were compared using similar 
cycle data binning and multivariate regression statistical </p>

<p>Figure 3 
Network plots showing significant associations 
between serum hormones and antral follicle 
count (AFC 2-10 mm) in the follicular and luteal 
phases of the menstrual cycle. Positive and 
negative correlations are coloured blue and red, 
respectively. The strength of the correlation 
between groups is presented as follows; the thick 
line P &lt; 0.001, medium thick line P &lt; 0.01, 
least thick line P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Figure 4 
The independent relationships of ovarian hormones and AFC (2-5 mm and &gt;6 mm) with FSH and LH across the menstrual cycle. The serum hormone and 
AFC values were binned in 3-day groups across the luteal phase of one cycle beginning at the first ovulation (OV1) and progressing into the follicular 
phase of the next cycle ending with ovulation (OV2). Slopes and 95% CL are presented. Ovulation 1 (Ov1, days −1, Ov, +1), early luteal phase 
(ELP, +2, +3, +4), mid-luteal phase (MLP, +5, +6, +7), late luteal phase (LLP, +8, +9, +10) and very late luteal phase (VLLP, +11, +12, +13), menstruation 
(Men, −1, Men, +1), early follicular phase (EFP, +2, +3, +4), mid follicular phase, (MFP, +5, +6, +7), late follicular phase, (LFP, +8, +9, +10 ) and ovulation 
2 (OV2, −1, Ov2, +1). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1530/EC-16-0077 </p>

<p>http://www.endocrineconnections.org 
© 2016 The authors 
Published by Bioscientifica Ltd </p>

<p>Research 
D M Robertson et al. 
Ovarian:pituitary feedback 
mechanisms </p>

<p>Endocrine Connections </p>

<p>103-107 
5:103 </p>

<p>analyses. The slope coefficients and their significances are 
presented in Table 1. Key observations seen in both studies 
included: (a) significant inverse associations between FSH 
vs oestradiol and AMH (Gen-II) in the follicular and luteal 
phases and (b) an inverse association between FSH and 
inhibin B in the follicular phase. In contrast, the direct 
relationship between progesterone and FSH/LH in the 
follicular phase and inverse relationship in the luteal 
phase observed in the 2009 study were not noted in the 
present study. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, the relationships between ovarian factors 
and pituitary hormones were examined in two ways; 
first, with FSH and LH as independent variables and each 
ovarian hormone and AFC as outcome or dependent 
variable; and second, between each ovarian factor 
(as independent variable) and FSH and LH (as outcome 
variables). The first approach provides a means to assess 
the independent relationships between FSH and LH and 
each ovarian factor; these relationships were assessed </p>

<p>across the menstrual cycle (Fig. 4). The second approach 
provides a means to identify which of the ovarian 
factors predict FSH and LH (Figs 5 and 6). Thus, these 
approaches attempt to differentiate between the effects 
of individual pituitary hormones on ovarian factors in 
contrast to the effects of individual ovarian factors on 
pituitary function. </p>

<p>Comparison between the 2009 study and the 
present study </p>

<p>The associations observed between serum ovarian 
hormones vs FSH and LH showed close agreement between 
the 2009 study (3) and the present study (Table 2). Inverse 
relationships were confirmed among oestradiol, AMH and 
FSH in both follicular and luteal phases of the cycle and 
between inhibin B and FSH/LH in the follicular phase. 
However, the inverse relationship observed between 
serum progesterone and FSH in both phases of the cycle 
in the 2009 study was not confirmed in the present study. 
No ready explanation can be provided. In contrast, direct 
relationships between inhibin B vs FSH and LH in the 
luteal phase in the present study were novel findings. </p>

<p>Table 1 Slope values of regression lines between ovarian and pituitary hormones across the follicular and luteal phases of </p>

<p>women with normal menstrual cycles for two independent studies; 2009 study (3) and the present analysis. </p>

<p>Study </p>

<p>FSH follicular phase 
FSH luteal phase 
LH follicular phase 
LH luteal phase </p>

<p>2009 
2015 
2009 
2015 
2009 
2015 
2009 
2015 </p>

<p>Oestradiol 
−0.35*** 
−0.22** 
0.25*** 
−0.27** 
−0.1 
0.1 
−0.3 
0.07 
Progesterone 
0.9* 
0.056 
−0.2*** 
−0.013 
0.2** 
0.21 
−1.0*** 
0.018 
Inhibin A 
−0.05 
−0.057 
0.1 
0.08 
0.1* 
0.10 
0.2 
−0.06 
Inhibin B 
−0.1* 
−0.3** 
−0.05 
0.13** 
−0.2** 
−0.43*** 
0.01 
0.18* 
AMH Gen-II 
−0.1*** 
−0.13*** 
−0.1*** 
−0.21*** 
−0.05 
0.055 
0.01 
−0.1 </p>

<p>Significance of regression, *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01 and ***P &lt; 0.005. </p>

<p>Figure 5 
Relationships among ovarian hormones, antral 
follicle count and FSH. The independent 
relationships between ovarian hormones and 
antral follicle count (AFC, 2-10 mm) as outcome 
variables vs FSH as independent variable in the 
follicular and luteal phases of the menstrual cycle 
and those cycles divided into those with and 
without luteal phase-dominant follicles (LPDFs). 
Slopes and 95% CL are presented. </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1530/EC-16-0077 </p>

<p>http://www.endocrineconnections.org 
© 2016 The authors 
Published by Bioscientifica Ltd </p>

<p>Research 
D M Robertson et al. 
Ovarian:pituitary feedback 
mechanisms </p>

<p>Endocrine Connections </p>

<p>104-107 
5:104 </p>

<p>The inclusion of AFC and the more sensitive AMH ELISA 
has not changed our previous observations that FSH is 
inversely correlated with oestradiol and AMH across the 
cycle or that FSH and LH are inversely correlated with 
inhibin B in the follicular phase. </p>

<p>Inhibin B and FSH/LH </p>

<p>The inverse relationship between inhibin B and FSH 
in the follicular phase previously reported in the 2009 
study was confirmed in this study; however, the more 
recent investigations demonstrated that the relationship 
is confined to the late follicular phase. A similar inverse 
relationship with LH was less well established but was 
noted in the 2009 study. It is surprising to note that 
serum inhibin B but not inhibin A showed a reciprocal </p>

<p>relationship with FSH. This may be explained in part by 
the temporal changes in inhibin B followed by inhibin 
A across the follicular phase in relation to FSH. It also 
should be noted that human inhibin B has higher in vitro 
and in vivo bioactivities than human inhibin A, at least 
in rats (8), which may be reflected in its apparent potent 
in vivo activity in humans. In addition, it is unknown to 
what extent inhibin B in contrast to inhibin A regulates 
pituitary LH in vivo. 
It was also noted that inhibin B was directly 
correlated with FSH and LH in the luteal phase in 
contrast to the inverse relationship observed in the 
follicular phase. One explanation is that as inhibin 
B levels are low in the luteal phase, it can no longer 
exert a negative feedback on FSH and LH. One may 
presume that inhibin B is stimulated by FSH and LH </p>

<p>Figure 6 
Relationships among ovarian hormones, antral 
follicle count and LH. The independent 
relationships between ovarian hormones and 
antral follicle count (AFC, 2-10 mm) as outcome 
variables vs LH as independent variable in the 
follicular and luteal phases of the menstrual cycle 
and those cycles divided into those with and 
without luteal phase-dominant follicles (LPDFs). 
Slopes and 95% CL are presented. </p>

<p>Table 2 Summary of relationships between ovarian factors and pituitary hormones in the follicular and luteal phases of the </p>

<p>menstrual cycle. </p>

<p>FSH 
LH </p>

<p>FP1 
FP2 
LP 
FP1 
FP2 
LP </p>

<p>All cycles 
Estradiol 
-
-
Inverse** 
-
-
-
Progesterone 
-
-
-
-
-
-
Inhibin A 
-
-
-
-
-
-
Inhibin B 
-
Inverse* 
Direct** 
-
Inverse* 
Direct* 
AMH (24/32) 
Inverse*** 
Inverse*** 
Inverse*** 
Inverse*** 
AFC 2-10 mm 
-
-
-
-
-
-
Cycles without LPDF Inhibin B 
-
-
-
Direct* </p>

<p>AMH (24/32) 
Inverse*** 
Inverse*** 
Inverse*** 
Inverse* 
Direct** 
Inverse*** 
AFC 2-10 mm 
-
-
-
Direct* 
Inverse** 
Direct* 
Cycles with LPDF 
Inhibin B 
-
-
-
Inverse** 
Direct* 
AMH (24/32) 
-
-
-
-
-
-
AFC 2-10 mm 
-
-
-
Direct* 
-
-</p>

<p>Significance of regression *P ≤ 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01 and ***P ≤ 0.001. 
AFC, antral follicle count; FP1, follicular phase (menstruation + early FP); FP2, follicular phase (mid + late FP); LP, luteal phase; LPDF, luteal phase 
dominant follicles. </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1530/EC-16-0077 </p>

<p>http://www.endocrineconnections.org 
© 2016 The authors 
Published by Bioscientifica Ltd </p>

<p>Research 
D M Robertson et al. 
Ovarian:pituitary feedback 
mechanisms </p>

<p>Endocrine Connections </p>

<p>105-107 
5:105 </p>

<p>in the luteal phase, whereas in the follicular phase, the 
capacity of the growing follicles to produce inhibin B 
is increased leading to an increased inhibitory feedback 
action on FSH and LH. This suggests that the same 
control mechanisms operate in both phases of the cycle. 
We thus postulate that inhibin B rather than inhibin 
A plays a role in regulating both FSH and LH, and its 
reciprocal action is evident in both the follicular and 
luteal phases. However, it is unclear how inhibin B in 
contrast to inhibin A exerts its action. </p>

<p>AMH and FSH </p>

<p>As seen in the 2009 study, serum FSH (as an outcome 
variable) showed a strong inverse relationship with AMH 
across the menstrual cycle and with age, suggesting 
serum AMH was predictive of FSH. This observation 
was surprising and provided the impetus for the present 
analysis. The inclusion of a more-sensitive AMH ELISA 
was intended to establish a more reliable set of AMH 
values, particularly in the lower ranges. The inclusion of 
AFC for follicles of various diameters was to establish if 
AMH was a proxy or substitute for another AFC factor 
based on the very high correlation between serum AMH 
and AFC (4). The inclusion of AFC did not change the 
independent inverse association of AMH and FSH. There is 
limited evidence available to substantiate any postulated 
age-related feedback role of AMH on FSH. AMH has been 
shown to inhibit FSHβ subunit synthesis in a mouse 
anterior pituitary (LβT2) cell line and rat pituitary cells 
in vitro (9); presumably, this is likely although not yet 
shown in the human pituitary. By comparison, there is no 
evidence that FSH stimulates AMH synthesis by the ovary 
(10), a key component in any ovarian:pituitary negative 
feedback mechanism. 
AMH is produced by granulosa cells from 
gonadotropin-unresponsive preantral follicles under 
stimulation by oocyte-specific factors (e.g. BMP2, 6, 7, 15, 
GDF9) from the oocyte (11, 12). AMH has been shown 
to inhibit the progression of primordial to preantral 
follicles (13, 14, 15) in mice but stimulates progression in 
primate monkeys (16). AMH has been shown to inhibit 
FSH-induced oestradiol production by human and 
primate granulosa cells (16, 17, 18, 19, 20). Moreover, 
oestradiol has been shown to inhibit AMH synthesis 
in vitro suggesting an indirect action of FSH on AMH 
synthesis (20). 
It is hypothesised that as AFC and serum AMH 
decrease with age, FSH and oestradiol production by </p>

<p>FSH-sensitive follicles increase (3). Oestradiol is thought 
to exert an inhibitory role on FSH, whereas the reduced 
AMH levels may lead to elevated FSH levels. It would 
appear that if oestradiol and AMH are two of the major 
factors in regulating FSH, the effects of AMH are more 
pronounced with age. It is recognised that as oestradiol 
exerts its inhibitory role at the hypothalamus, whereas 
AMH is probably at the pituitary, different biological 
actions are likely involved. AMH and oestradiol have 
been shown to be reciprocally related in follicular fluid 
(15, 21, 22). 
A number of clinical studies have observed an 
inverse relationship between serum FSH and AMH (23, 
24, 25, 26, 27). However, with the exception of Pigny 
(26), these analyses did not differentiate AMH's role from 
the effects of other ovarian feedback factors. The studies 
of Pigny (26) investigated the feedback relationship 
between AMH and FSH in women with polycystic 
ovarian syndrome (PCOS) where serum AMH levels were 
elevated. A significant inverse relationship has been 
observed between serum AMH and FSH in both PCOS and 
control women; however, this association between AMH 
and other ovarian hormones vs FSH was lost following 
multivariate regression analysis. We hypothesise that 
these studies do not exclude an inverse relationship 
between AMH and FSH but that owing to the multiple 
interactions between ovarian and pituitary hormones, 
an in-depth analysis of ovarian and pituitary hormones 
in PCOS women similar to this study is required to clarify 
this relationship. 
In summary, we hypothesise that from early stages 
in reproductive life, AMH, produced by the preantral/ 
antral follicles, suppresses FSH secretion using similar 
intracellular TGFβ inhibitory pathways to that observed 
with inhibin B and that this inhibition decreases in 
parallel with the decrease in folliculogenesis with age. 
The role of AMH within the ovary is important in 
regulating the release of follicles from the preantral 
pool. 
It is interesting that including AFC as a variable had 
minimal effect on the multivariate regression analysis. 
Its inclusion was introduced to identify if AFC (as a 
surrogate or proxy for other ovarian factors) would also 
show a reciprocal relationship with FSH. We conclude 
that probably all the ovarian factors involved in these 
interactions with FSH have been identified. The inverse 
relationship observed between AFC (2-10 mm) and 
FSH is attributed to the close relationship between AFC 
(2-10 mm) and AMH, with AMH as the key factor. </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1530/EC-16-0077 </p>

<p>http://www.endocrineconnections.org 
© 2016 The authors 
Published by Bioscientifica Ltd </p>

<p>Research 
D M Robertson et al. 
Ovarian:pituitary feedback 
mechanisms </p>

<p>Endocrine Connections </p>

<p>106-107 
5:106 </p>

<p>Luteal phase-dominant follicles </p>

<p>The presence of dominant follicles in the luteal phase 
were associated with elevated oestradiol, inhibin B and 
AFC (&gt;6 mm) (6, 7), which may have resulted in changes 
to their feedback actions on FSH and LH. In this study, 
we showed that the inverse associations between FSH 
vs oestradiol and AMH were similar in women with and 
without a LPDF. The presence of a LPDF resulted in altered 
relationships between LH and the other ovarian hormones 
and AFC, and further studies with a larger sample size 
are required to confirm these findings. The impact of 
the presence of LPDF on ovarian:pituitary feedback 
mechanisms is unclear. However, it has been shown that 
LPDF cycles are associated with elevated and prolonged 
oestradiol patterns (7), particularly with women of 
advanced reproductive age, which may be a consequence 
of this reduction in ovarian control of pituitary FSH and 
LH secretion. </p>

<p>Summary </p>

<p>We now postulate the following: 
(a) AMH is independently and inversely correlated 
with FSH but not LH, and probably plays a role in 
conjunction with oestradiol (and to a less extent, 
inhibin B) in regulating FSH across the menstrual 
cycle throughout adult reproductive life. 
(b) Inhibin B plays an important role in both the 
follicular and luteal phases in regulating FSH 
and LH. 
(c) Oestradiol specifically regulates FSH throughout 
the cycle. 
(d) The inclusion of AFC in the analysis provided little 
additional information, suggesting that the key 
ovarian factors have been identified. 
(e) The impact of the presence of a LPDF on 
ovarian:pituitary feedback mechanisms is unclear. 
Further studies are required to clarify their 
involvement. </p>

<p>Declaration of interest 
The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest that could be 
perceived as prejudicing the impartiality of the research reported. </p>

<p>Funding 
This study was supported by research grants from the Canadian 
Institutes of Health Research; Canadian Foundation for Women's Health; 
Establishment Grant from the University of Saskatchewan; the National </p>

<p>Health and Medical Research Council of Australia (Program Grant # 
494802 and Research Fellowships, D.M.R. #169201) and the Victorian 
Government's Operational Infrastructure Support Program. </p>



<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1530/EC-16-0077 </p>

<p>http://www.endocrineconnections.org 
© 2016 The authors 
Published by Bioscientifica Ltd </p>

<p>Research 
D M Robertson et al. 
Ovarian:pituitary feedback 
mechanisms </p>

<p>Endocrine Connections </p>



<p>Received in final form 8 November 2016 
Accepted 17 November 2016 
Accepted Preprint published online 17 November 2016 </p>

</text></tei>