<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5304233" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>a b s t r a c t 
Low dose CT (LDCT) for lung cancer screening is an evidence-based, guideline recommended, and Medicare ap-
proved test but uptake requires further study. We therefore conducted patient and provider surveys to elucidate 
factors associated with utilization. Patients referred for LDCT at an academic medical center were questioned 
about their attitudes, knowledge, and beliefs on lung cancer screening. Adherent patients were defined as 
those who met screening eligibility criteria and completed a LDCT. Referring primary care providers within 
this same medical system were surveyed in parallel about their practice patterns, attitudes, knowledge and be-
liefs about screening. Eighty patients responded (36%), 48 of whom were adherent. Among responders, non-His-
panic patients (p = 0.04) were more adherent. Adherent respondents believed that CT technology is accurate 
and early detection is useful, and they trusted their providers. A majority of non-adherent patients (79%) self-re-
ported an intention to obtain a LDCT in the future. Of 36 of 87 (41%) responding providers, only 31% knew the 
correct lung cancer screening eligibility criteria, which led to a 37% inappropriate referral rate from 2013 to 
2015. Yet, 75% had initiated lung cancer screening discussions, 64% thought screening was at least moderately ef-
fective, and 82% were interested in learning more of the 33 providers responding to these questions. Overall, pa-
tients were motivated and providers engaged to screen for lung cancer by LDCT. Non-adherent patient 
"procrastinators" were motivated to undergo screening in the future. Additional follow through on non-adher-
ence may enhance screening uptake, and raising awareness for screening eligibility through provider education 
may reduce inappropriate referrals. 
Lung cancer remains the leading cause of cancer death in the U.S. for 
both men and women with a staggering 200,000 new cases and 150,000 
deaths expected in 2016 alone (Torre et al., 2015; Siegel et al., 2015). 
Screening for lung cancer by imaging has been an active area of investi-
gation for decades with equivocal results (Fontana et al., 1984;  Henschke et al., 1999; International Early Lung Cancer Action Program  I et al., 2006) until the National Lung Screening Trial (NLST) in 2011 </p>

<p>provided a definitive answer (National Lung Screening Trial Research  T et al., 2011). The NLST was a large, multi-center, randomized trial 
that reported a 20% reduction in the risk of lung cancer-specific mortal-
ity for three annual low dose CT (LDCT) screens among active or prior 
heavy smokers aged 55 to 74 years old. Based on this result, LDCT 
lung cancer screening for patients at high risk of lung cancer is now an 
evidence-based recommendation by the United States Preventive Ser-
vices Task Force (USPSTF), and a covered test by the Centers for Medi-
care and Medicaid Services (CMS). 
The public has positively viewed evidence-based cancer screening 
enthusiastically for years, (Schwartz et al., 2004) and national colon, 
breast and cervical cancer screening rates are currently 58%, 73% and 
81% respectively (http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/ 
mm6417a4.htm?s_cid=mm6417a4_w). Despite national guideline </p>

<p>Preventive Medicine Reports 6 (2017) 17-22 </p>

<p>⁎ Corresponding author at: Stanford University School of Medicine, Division of 
Pulmonary &amp; Critical Care Medicine, 300 Pasteur Drive, S021 Grant Bldg, Stanford, CA 
94305-5236, United States. 
E-mail address: viswamnair@stanford.edu (V.S. Nair). </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pmedr.2017.01.012 
2211-3355/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>Preventive Medicine Reports </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : h t t p : / / e e s . e l s e v i e r . c o m / p m e d r </p>

<p>recommendations for lung cancer screening with LDCT, the adoption of 
this evidenced-based screening at the national policy level, endorse-
ments by multiple professional societies, and studies demonstrating 
cost-effectiveness (Black et al., 2014), uptake in many academic centers 
-which is governed by physician practices and patient volition -still re-
mains low in the initial years following the publication of the NLST 
(Hoffman et al., 2015; Lewis et al., 2015). Since the uptake of LDCT 
and best practices to drive its adoption remains to be determined, we 
sought to investigate LDCT screening uptake within an academic setting 
by surveying patients and providers on their attitudes, knowledge, and 
beliefs regarding LDCT. Our goal was to identify facilitators and barriers 
to lung cancer screening within our medical center for improved adop-
tion moving forward. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>We evaluated 221 patients and 81 primary care providers from the 
Stanford Health Care (SHC) system and administered two separate, 
structured surveys for each group. Patients were interviewed by 
phone and providers completed an online survey. Survey implementa-
tion was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Qualtrics</rs> software (Qualtrics, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Provo UT</rs>). All 
study related processes and materials were approved by the Stanford 
Institutional Review Board. </p>

<p>2.1. Study recruitment &amp; data collection </p>

<p>2.1.1. Patient survey 
We conducted a survey from August 2015 to January 2016 for pa-
tients referred for LDCT screening from 2013 to 2015 through Stanford's 
Lung Cancer Screening Program. Referrals were based on the NLST and 
National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) LDCT eligibility 
criteria. To identify eligible patients (those who actually were LDCT eli-
gible by these consensus guidelines regardless of whether or not they 
were referred), we reviewed the electronic medical record 
(EMR) from patient charts (Fig. 1). NLST criteria were defined by 
patients 55-74 years old with a current or past smoking history (within 
15 years) of at least 30 pack years (National Lung Screening Trial </p>

<p>Research T et al., 2011). NCCN criteria were defined by patients 
N50 years old with a smoking history of at least 20 pack years (ever) 
and one additional risk factor such as Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary 
Disease (COPD), pulmonary fibrosis, a family member with lung cancer, 
major exposure to substances associated with lung cancer (i.e. radon, 
asbestos, or silica), or a past history of lymphoma, esophageal cancer, 
lung or head and neck cancer (Wood et al., 2015). 
The patient survey consisted of 38 questions derived from previous 
work (http://www.cpic.org/page/stars/) and internal discussions 
among our study group with expertise in conducting survey research 
and lung cancer screening. All LDCT eligible patients were mailed an in-
vitation letter to participate and were contacted by phone up to 5 times 
on a weekly basis in order to complete the survey. Two trained inter-
viewers (DKD, HN) administered the surveys in a standardized fashion 
with questions covering past screening for lung and other cancers, rea-
sons for undergoing or not undergoing LDCT, smoking behavior, and 
general socio-demographic information (Appendix 1). The average 
completion time for the survey was 11 min. 
We based ethnicity and race on self-report for survey responders. 
Multi-racial patients were classified according to their minority race. 
We obtained patient information on age at the time of screening, sex, 
cancer history, insurance status, provider location, county of residence 
and ethnicity (but not race) from the EMR for non-responders to com-
pare these data to responders. </p>

<p>2.1.2. Provider survey 
Stanford primary care providers were recruited by e-mail from a 
study author (BS). An on-line link to the self-administered survey in-
strument was included in the e-mail correspondence after on-line 
consent. This survey was designed from previous literature and internal 
discussion among our study group with expertise in conducting survey 
research and lung cancer screening (Lewis et al., 2015; Henderson et al.,  2011; http://healthcaredelivery.cancer.gov/screening_rp/screening 
_rp_colo_lung_inst.pdf). The on-line provider survey took an average 
of 15 min to complete, and included 27 questions on the following 
topics: knowledge of LDCT screening guidelines, LDCT referral practice, 
barriers and facilitators to LDCT referral, interest in learning more about </p>

<p>Fig. 1. We screened our program's lung cancer screening LDCT database to identify 221 patients, of which 139 were considered eligible by current guidelines. Eighty patients participated 
(response rate = 80/139; 58%) 48 of whom adhered to a prescribed LDCT and 32 who did not adhere. These two groups were analyzed for differences in patient demographics (Table 2). 
We then examined responses for those who were adherent and compared them to those who were not adherent but intended to make an appointment (Fig. 2). </p>

<p> 
D.K. Duong et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 6 (2017) 17-22 </p>

<p>LDCT screening, and questions regarding providers' primary care prac-
tice setting, training, and socio-demographic characteristics (Appendix 
2). </p>

<p>2.2. Analysis </p>

<p>We compared socio-demographic characteristics between patient 
respondents (i.e. those who completed the survey) and non-respon-
dents (i.e. those who did not) for LDCT eligible patients. Among respon-
dents, we compared socio-demographic and clinical characteristics 
between LDCT adherent (i.e., those who completed the survey AND 
followed through with a prescribed LDCT) and non-adherent patients 
(i.e., those who completed the survey AND DID NOT follow through 
with a prescribed LDCT). 
Self-reported LDCT adherence was verified by the EMR (Fig. 1). Facil-
itators to screening adherence were then examined among patients 
who were LDCT adherent and those who were non-adherent. Our sam-
ple size was too small to execute a meaningful analysis (n = 4) for those 
who had not adhered to a prescribed LDCT and did not intend to get 
screened. We therefore examined reasons for LDCT adherence between 
those who were adherent and "procrastinators" (those who were not 
adherent but intended to make an appointment in the future) to eluci-
date whether there may be differences in attitudes and beliefs between 
these two groups. 
For providers, responses were tabulated and analyzed descriptively. 
We defined knowledgeable providers as those who correctly identified 
criteria for either NLST or NCCN LDCT screening. Appropriate CT refer-
rals were defined as those placed by providers for patients who met 
LDCT eligibility. We stratified these data by the year of the prescribed 
order for further analysis. 
For both surveys, descriptive statistics were computed using the 
mean and standard deviation or median and interquartile range (IQR) 
for continuous variables, and frequency counts and percentages for cat-
egorical variables. To test for statistical differences across the compari-
son groups, we used a Student's t-test for continuous variables and 
Chi-squared or Fisher's Exact tests for categorical variables as 
appropriate. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Patients </p>

<p>From 2013 to 2015, 221 patients had a LDCT ordered at SHC, 211 
were contacted and invited to respond to the survey, 139 met criteria 
for LDCT by NLST or NCCN guidelines, and 80 of these 139 (58%) 
responded to the survey by phone (Fig. 1). Of the 80 patients who 
were LDCT eligible and responsive to our survey, 48 (60%) received 
LDCT screening, and 32 (40%) did not. Seventy-seven respondents 
(96%) underwent some form of cancer screening (Table 1), and 98% of 
LDCT adherent respondents were aware they had undergone a test spe-
cifically for lung cancer screening. Survey respondents' mean age was </p>

<p>65 ± 7 years, 45 (56%) were male and 74 (93%) were non-Hispanic. 
The majority of respondents lived locally, had public insurance, and 
were cared for by Stanford providers. 
Although not statistically significant, younger, white, and female pa-
tients showed trends towards better adherence. On the other hand, His-
panics were significantly more non-adherent (p = 0.04) (Table 2). 
When comparing those who adhered to a LDCT physician's order and 
those who did not, no significant differences or trends were found for </p>

<p>Table 1 
General screening adherence for survey respondents </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Breast/mammogram 
n = 35 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Cervical/PAP 
n = 35 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Colon/colonoscopy 
n = 80 </p>

<p>Survey respondents 
91% 
94% 
86% 
California data </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>83% 
75% 
67% 
National data </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>79% 
75% 
69% </p>

<p>PAP -Papanicolaou smear. 
a n = 80; n = 35 for female specific screening. 
b 50+ years old. 
c 18+ years old. 
d National Cancer Institute, state cancer profiles in 2014 (https:// </p>

<p>statecancerprofiles.cancer.gov/; 
http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/ 
mm6417a4.htm?s_cid=mm6417a4_w). </p>

<p>Table 2 
Characteristics of survey respondents. </p>

<p>All patients, 
n (%) 
n = 80 </p>

<p>Non-adherent 
patients, n (%) 
n = 32 </p>

<p>Adherent 
patients, n (%) 
n = 48 </p>

<p>p-Value </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Age (y) 
65 ± 7 
64 ± 6 
66 ± 7 
0.11 
Gender 
0.07 
Male 
45 (56) 
22 (69) 
23 (48) 
Female 
35 (44) 
10 (31) 
25 (52) 
Ethnicity 
0.04 
Hispanic 
6 (7) 
5 (16) 
1 (2) 
Not Hispanic 
74 (93) 
27 (84) 
47 (98) 
Race </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>0.08 
White 
65 (81) 
23 (72) 
42 (87.5) 
Black 
3 (4) 
2 (6) 
1 (2) 
Asian 
3 (4) 
2 (6) 
1 (2) 
Hispanic 
6 (8) 
5 (16) 
1 (2) 
Multi-racial 
3 (4) 
0 (0) 
3 (6) 
History of 
cancer </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>0.38 </p>

<p>Yes 
5 (6) 
3 (9) 
2 (4) 
No 
75 (94) 
29 (91) 
46 (96) 
County </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>0.92 
Local 
57 (72.5) 
23 (72) 
34 (71) 
Distant 
23 (27.5) 
9 (28) 
14 (29) 
Foreign born 
Yes 
15 (19) 
7 (22) 
8 (17) 
0.56 
No 
65 (81) 
25 (78) 
40 (83) 
Education </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.36 
bBachelor's 
degree </p>

<p>20 (25) 
10 (31) 
10 (21) </p>

<p>College graduate 25 (31) 
11 (34) 
14 (29) 
≥Graduate 
degree </p>

<p>35 (44) 
11 (34) 
24 (50) </p>

<p>Insurance </p>

<p>b,f </p>

<p>0.35 
Public 
(government) </p>

<p>50 (62.5) 
18 (56) 
32 (67) </p>

<p>Private (HMO, 
PPO etc.) </p>

<p>30 (37.5) 
14 (44) 
16 (33) </p>

<p>Occupation </p>

<p>b,g </p>

<p>Health care 
related </p>

<p>10 (12.5) 
4 (12.5) 
6 (12.5) 
1.00 </p>

<p>Not health care 
related </p>

<p>70 (87.5) 
28 (87.5) 
42 (87.5) </p>

<p>Provider 
location </p>

<p>0.83 </p>

<p>Stanford 
61 (76) 
24 (75) 
37 (77) 
Not Stanford 
19 (24) 
8 (25) 
11 (23) </p>

<p>HMO -Healthcare Maintenance Organization; PPO -Preferred Provider Organization. 
a Between adherent and non-adherent groups using a Student's t-test for continuous </p>

<p>variables and a Chi-squared analysis (or Fisher's exact test for n ≤ 5) for categorical 
variables. 
b Self-reported. 
c p-Value shown is for comparison of white vs all other races combined. 
d Excluded non-melanoma skin cancers. 
e Local counties include Santa Clara and San Mateo. Distant counties include Alameda, </p>

<p>Solano, Monterey, San Francisco, Santa Cruz, Merced, San Benito, Napa, Humboldt, 
Stanislaus, Out of State, San Diego, Marin, Sonoma, Lake County, Mariposa, Nevada County, 
Fresno, San Joaquin, and Butte. 
f Public insurance included government plans Medicare, MediCal, Covered California </p>

<p>plan, and Worker's Comp. Private included employer-provided health care or individual/ 
family private insurances. If a patient had multiple insurances, we defaulted to their Medi-
care plan followed by private plan for analysis. 
g Health care related professions included physicians, nurse practitioners, nurses, oc-</p>

<p>cupational therapist, phlebotomist, and administrators in medical offices. </p>

<p> 
D.K. Duong et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 6 (2017) 17-22 </p>

<p>cancer history, residential area, level of education, type of insurance, oc-
cupation, being of foreign birth, and provider location. 
In Fig. 2 we show patients' knowledge and attitudes via self-report 
towards LDCT between these two groups. LDCT adherent patients re-
ported feeling that CT technology is accurate, early detection is useful, 
and trusting their providers as the most common reasons to undergo 
LDCT. They also reported wanting to know if they might have cancer 
as an important reason to adhere. Twenty-two of 28 patients (79%) 
who had not had their prescribed LCDT reported wanted to do one in 
the future. Overall, the attitudes between those who were adherent 
and patient "procrastinators" were very similar. Additionally, those 
who quit smoking or who smoke less than they used to were more ad-
herent with a prescribed LDCT (p = 0.03). Of note and as displayed in 
Fig. 1, participants who had a discrepancy in their adherence per self-re-
port versus EMR review were excluded from these analyses. 
In Table 3 we show characteristics of LDCT eligible respondents and 
non-respondents using data obtained from the EMR. Patient respon-
dents were similar to non-respondents, but respondents were more 
likely to be publicly insured (p = 0.03). Importantly, LDCT adherence 
between the respondent and non-respondent groups was not signifi-
cantly different (60% vs 51%, p = 0.28). Thirteen eligible non-respon-
dents had unknown insurance status and were excluded from analysis 
for this variable. </p>

<p>3.2. Providers </p>

<p>Thirty-six of the 87 providers from the SHC primary care group 
responded to the survey (41%), and 31 completed the survey in its en-
tirety (36%). Of these 31, twenty-four (77%) of these providers were fe-
male and 17 (55%) were white. Experience was broadly distributed, 
with 7 (23%) having practiced medicine for b 4 years, 6 (19%) from 5 
to 9 years, 3 (10%) from 10 to 14 years, and 15 (48%) for 15 or more 
years. 
Thirty-two providers (89%) reported either being aware or influ-
enced by USPSTF lung cancer screening guidelines in their practice, 
but their awareness of appropriate NCCN or NLST guidelines was low. 
Only 11 providers (31%) answered age and smoking eligibility criteria 
correctly. Despite this fact, 27 (75%) providers had initiated a discussion 
regarding lung cancer screening and 21 (58%) had ordered a LDCT for 
lung cancer screening. 
Many providers (64%) believed current screening guidelines were at 
least moderately effective and 82% were interested in learning more 
about lung cancer screening with an on-line lecture being the preferred 
method of education (59%) lasting up to 30 min (52%). </p>

<p>Providers surveyed did not show a high degree of concern for false 
positive results. 
(never/rarely/sometimes concerned -85%), potential harm to pa-
tients from these false positive results (never/rarely/sometimes con-
cerned -86%), and patient co-morbidities (never/rarely/sometimes </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Facilitators for LDCT were compared between those who were adherent and those who were non-adherent but intended to make an appointment. Many patient "procrastinators" 
who were non-adherent after missing an appointment (n = 22/28; 79%) reported wanting to perform a LDCT and their attitudes towards screening were similar to adherent patients. The 
reported p-value was calculated using Chi-squared analysis. </p>

<p>Table 3 
Characteristics of patients eligible for low-dose CT screening. </p>

<p>Eligible for 
screening </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, n (%) 
n = 139 </p>

<p>Survey 
respondents, n 
(%) 
n = 80 </p>

<p>Survey 
non-respondents, 
n (%) 
n = 59 </p>

<p>p-Value </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Age (y) 
65 ± 6 
65 ± 7 
65 ± 6 
0.44 
Gender 
0.11 
Male 
86 (61) 
45 (56) 
41 (70) 
Female 
53 (38) 
35 (44) 
18 (31) 
Ethnicity 
0.21 
Hispanic 
12 (9) 
6 (7.5) 
6 (10) 
Non-Hispanic 127 (91) 
74 (92.5) 
53 (90) 
History of 
cancer </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.53 </p>

<p>Yes 
11 (8) 
5 (6) 
6 (10) 
No 
128 (92) 
75 (94) 
53 (90) 
County </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>0.66 
Local 
97 (70) 
57 (71) 
40 (68) 
Distant 
42 (30) 
23 (29) 
19 (32) 
Insurance </p>

<p>e,f </p>

<p>0.03 
Public 
71 (56) 
51 (64) 
20 (43) 
Private 
55 (44) 
29 (36) 
26 (57) 
Provider 
location </p>

<p>0.37 </p>

<p>Stanford 
102 (73) 
61 (76) 
41 (70) 
Not Stanford 37 (27) 
19 (23) 
18 (31) 
Received 
LDCT </p>

<p>0.28 </p>

<p>Yes 
78 (56) 
48 (60) 
30 (51) 
No 
61 (44) 
32 (40) 
29 (49) </p>

<p>a Between group comparison performed using a Student's t-test for continuous vari-</p>

<p>ables and a Chi-squared analysis (or Fisher's exact test for n ≤ 5) for categorical variables. 
b Low-Dose CT eligibility based on National Lung Screening Trial or National Compre-</p>

<p>hensive Cancer Network criteria for lung cancer screening. 
c Excluded non-melanoma skin cancers. 
d Local counties include Santa Clara and San Mateo. Distant counties include Alameda, </p>

<p>Solano, Monterey, San Francisco, Santa Cruz, Merced, San Benito, Napa, Humboldt, 
Stanislaus, Out of State, San Diego, Marin, Sonoma, Lake County, Mariposa, Nevada County, 
Fresno, San Joaquin, and Butte. 
e Public insurance included government plans Medicare, MediCal, Covered California </p>

<p>plan, and Worker's Comp. Private included employer-provided health care or individual/ 
family private insurances. If a patient had multiple insurances, we defaulted to their Medi-
care plan followed by private plan for analysis. 
f 13 subjects without known insurance information were excluded from this analysis. </p>

<p> 
D.K. Duong et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 6 (2017) 17-22 </p>

<p>concerned -78%). Perceived barriers to provider care included lack of 
patient awareness of LDCT screening (sometimes/usually concerned -
100%) and not having enough time during a patient visit to discuss the 
screening test (sometimes/usually concerned -92%) (Table 4). </p>

<p>3.3. Referral rates for LDCT </p>

<p>Since we reviewed the charts of all patients who were referred for 
LDCT from 2013 to 2015 as part of this study (n = 221), we were able 
to identify the subgroup of patients referred by Stanford primary care 
providers only (n = 163). One-hundred-and-two of 163 patients 
(63%) were appropriately referred by Stanford providers which was 
similar in proportion to the 37 of 58 patients (64%) that were appropri-
ately referred by non-Stanford providers from 2013 to 2015. 
For all referrals, 35 patients (16%) were referred in 2013, 49 in 2014 
(22%), and 136 (62%) in 2015 (one patient was excluded as the year of 
referral was not clear). Appropriate referrals for Stanford providers only 
increased slightly from 59% in 2013 to 63% in 2015 (p = 0.93). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>Survey respondents who qualified for lung cancer screening from 
2013 to 2015 adhered to LDCT screening at a frequency of 60% at our 
medical center. In general, our patients were receptive to screening, 
and younger, white and female patients were more likely to follow 
through with a prescribed CT, and Hispanics were less likely to follow 
through with a prescribed CT. Patient "procrastinators" who failed to 
undergo an initial prescribed LDCT were still interested in obtaining 
one and providers were under informed but aware and engaged in 
lung cancer screening. Importantly, the vast majority of primary care 
providers were willing to learn more about LDCT screening. 
Previously published qualitative studies on LDCT screening prior to 
CMS coverage showed that patients' fatalistic beliefs, fear of radiation 
exposure, and anxiety related to CT scans were all significantly associat-
ed with decreased intention to screen (Jonnalagadda et al., 2012), but 
these factors did not appear influential on our post CMS coverage 
study group. At our medical center, patients had an overall positive out-
look on lung cancer screening with LDCT. These results are in-line with 
historical public perceptions and one very recent study reporting that 
77% of 338 patients who qualified for lung cancer screening would 
"agree to a CT today" (Cataldo, 2016). The high proportion of willing-
ness to screen may also be attributed to the education level of our 
study population that consisted of 75% college graduates (Meissner et  al., 2006). 
Our study also suggests that those who quit smoking or do not 
smoke as much as they used to were more likely to be adherent (p = 
0.03). This is consistent with existing literature noting that smokers 
are less likely to seek out care for lung cancer (Corner et al., 2006;  Friedemann Smith et al., 2016). Thus, abstinence from smoking could 
be a useful indicator of a patient's likelihood to follow through with 
screening. In addition, more effort should be devoted to current 
smokers to increase screening adherence since they are the population 
at the highest risk for lung cancer (Bach et al., 2003). </p>

<p>Patient adherence clearly relies on primary care provider practices. 
The similarity in patients' attitudes and perceptions between adherent 
and non-adherent respondents who intended on getting one in the fu-
ture is promising and suggests that repeat referrals and ongoing encour-
agement through shared decision making between primary care 
physicians and patients could improve adherence. To this end, a recent 
lung cancer screening study among Korean men showed that providers 
who discussed the benefits of LDCT screening with their patients in-
creased screening participation from 10% to 95% (Nhung et al., 2015). 
While our providers were engaged, they were not fully informed on 
the actual screening criteria. Our providers reported a high awareness of 
USPSTF lung cancer screening guidelines that influenced their practice, 
but only 31% accurately identified the appropriate criteria for screening. 
This likely resulted in the observed 37% inappropriate referral rate from 
2013 to 2015. 
Lung cancer screening practice for primary care providers may be 
evolving. Prior to the release of the NLST and high-quality evidence to 
support LDCT screening, one quarter of 962 family practice providers, 
general internists and general practitioners that responded to a national 
mail survey in 2010 thought there was sufficient evidence to warrant 
screening, and 26% of this sub-group would do so with LDCT 
(Klabunde et al., 2010). Surprisingly, this rate has not increased in 
more contemporary studies following the publication of the NLST, 
where one study tracked primary care providers practice patterns at 
an academic medical center in 2013 and another at federally qualified 
community health centers in 2014 (Hoffman et al., 2015; Lewis et al.,  2015). Our providers, surveyed in 2015 after the release of the USPSTF 
grade B recommendation and CMS's decision to cover lung cancer 
screening, were markedly more engaged in screening. The 58% of pro-
viders who ordered a LDCT at our center was much higher than prior re-
ports from another academic medical center from 2013 (12%) (Lewis et  al., 2015) and a national survey results of family practitioners prior to 
current guideline recommendations (22%) (Klabunde et al., 2012). 
Difficulties with the appropriate selection of patients and adoption 
of screening are not unique to lung cancer screening and have been ob-
served during the initial roll-out of colorectal cancer screening 
(Klabunde et al., 2003). Recognition of ongoing work to improve knowl-
edge gaps for providers will be crucial to optimize lung cancer screening 
delivery. Encouragingly, four out of five of our providers were interested 
in learning more about LDCT screening for lung cancer, regardless of 
whether or not they had ordered one. They were most interested in re-
ceiving education on screening in an on-line format. 
Our study has several strengths including its use of contemporane-
ous study populations, and the parallel sampling of patients and pro-
viders during the same time period using de novo survey instruments 
for analysis (Appendices 1, 2). In addition, we used the EMR to capture 
information on patient characteristics of survey non-responders that 
would not be available otherwise. There are limitations with our 
study, however. The modest study sample of 139 eligible patients and 
80 survey respondents may have resulted in an underpowered study 
that did not detect true differences between adherent and non-adher-
ent groups. Similarly, we surveyed a modest group of providers that 
were based solely at an academic referral center. Additionally, our </p>

<p>Table 4 
Concerns and perceived barriers regarding lung cancer screening among referring providers </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Survey question 
Never 
Rarely 
Sometimes 
Usually </p>

<p>Not enough time (n = 25) 
0 (0%) 
2 (8%) 
18 (72%) 
5 (20%) 
Patient unaware of lung cancer screening (n = 25) 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
7 (28%) 
18 (72%) 
Patient can't afford/lacks insurance (n = 25) 
5 (20%) 
7 (28%) 
12 (48%) 
1 (4%) 
Shortage of trained providers (n = 14) 
7 (50%) 
3 (21%) 
3 (21%) 
1 (7%) 
High false positives (n = 14) 
0 (0%) 
3 (21%) 
9 (64%) 
2 (14%) 
Potential harm of unnecessary diagnostic procedures (n = 14) 
0 (0%) 
4 (29%) 
8 (57%) 
2 (14%) 
Patient co-morbidities (n = 14) 
0 (0%) 
3 (21%) 
8 (57%) 
3 (21%) 
Patient unwillingness to undergo screening or treatment (n = 14) 
0 (0%) 
8 (57%) 
5 (36%) 
1 (7%) </p>

<p>a Out of 36 Stanford providers, the number who answered is reported in parentheses next to the relevant question. </p>

<p> 
D.K. Duong et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 6 (2017) 17-22 </p>

<p>surveyed group of patients underwent breast, colon, and cervical cancer 
screening with greater adherence than California or U.S. populations 
(Table 1), which likely speaks to the high compliance of our patient pop-
ulation and may limit the generalizability of this study. We also had a 
small number of underrepresented minorities, who are known to have 
different attitudes towards lung cancer screening (Jonnalagadda et al.,  2012). Last, both surveys had a modest response rate (58% for LDCT el-
igible patients and 36% for providers). Although within the range of the 
previous studies (20-71%) (Lewis et al., 2015; Cataldo, 2016; Klabunde  et al., 2012; Zeliadt et al., 2015), response rate bias cannot be excluded. 
Selection bias should be minimal since respondents and non-respon-
dents had similar characteristics and LDCT adherence rates (Table 3). </p>

<p>5. Conclusion </p>

<p>Based on positive patient attitudes and providers' overall endorse-
ment of LDCT screening at our medical center, we infer that education 
for providers, shared decision making for eligible patients, and addition-
al counseling for eligible patients who fail to show up for a prescribed CT 
will increase the accuracy and efficacy of screening within our program. 
A study of more socio-economically diverse sample populations for pa-
tients and providers is warranted to allow for a broader interpretation of 
these results. These data will ultimately help improve the uptake and 
utilization of LDCT screening to lower lung cancer mortality in high 
risk populations. 
Supplementary data to this article can be found online at http://dx. 
doi.org/10.1016/j.pmedr.2017.01.012. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>Genentech Independent Research Grant. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest </p>

<p>None. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank Dr. Chris Berg for providing recommendations on 
initiating this type of study and Dr. Sanjiv "Sam" Gambhir for providing 
departmental research support to complete this study. We also thank 
the primary care providers and patients of Stanford Health Care for par-
ticipating. Several authors (BS, AL, AH and VSN) received support from a 
Genentech Independent Research Grant for this work. </p>



<p> 
D.K. Duong et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 6 (2017) 17-22 </p>

</text></tei>