<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5440121" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Our study was aimed to investigate anesthetic effects of propofol in patients with different blood groups. 
A total of 72 participants were enrolled from patients arranged for surgeries of cholecystectomy, tonsillectomy, and spinal 
operation. Each blood group (A, B, AB, and O) contained 18 participants. Mean arterial pressure (MAP), heart rate (HR), and 
bispectral index (BIS) were assayed with Philips monitor. These indexes were observed before propofol anesthesia (T 0 ), and then 
were recorded when concentration of propofol was 1 mg/mL (T 1 ), 2 mg/mL (T 2 ), 3 mg/mL (T 3 ), and 4 mg/mL (T 4 ). The differences in 
MAP, HR, and BIS at T 0 among groups were compared with the x 2 test. Multiple comparisons were adopted to calculate the 
differences in MAP, HR, and BIS between groups at T 1 , T 2 , T 3 , and T 4 . 
No significant differences in age, sex, and weight of all groups were found (P &gt; .05). Before propofol anesthesia (T 0 ), all the 
participants exhibited no differences in MAP, HR, and BIS (P &gt; .05). Subsequently, we found obvious differences in DMAP, DHR, and 
DBIS between groups. The patients in the B blood group showed highest DMAP and DHR at each time point (P &lt; .05 for both). As for 
DBIS, patients in A blood group exhibited highest value at T 3 and T 4 (P &lt; .05). 
The blood group remarkably affects the anesthetic effects of propofol. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: BIS = bispectral index, HR = heart rate, IR = ischemia-reperfusion, MAP = mean arterial pressure, RSE = 
refractory status epilepticus, VWF = Von Willebrand factor. </p>

<p>Propofol, 2, 6-disopropylpphenol, is the most popular intrave-
nous anesthetic drug. [1] It has many advantages above other 
anesthetic drugs: rapid onset, short duration, few side effects, and 
prompt recovery. [2] The sedative efficacy of propofol for children 
has been confirmed in clinical trials since the 1900s. [3-5] 
However, most patients experience unpleasant pain at its 
injection site. Apart from anesthesia effects, many articles 
reported the nonanesthetic roles of propofol, such as antiemetic 
effects, anxiolytic effects, immunomodulatory activity, and 
analgesia. [6,7] Meanwhile, propofol and thiopental sodium are 
commonly used for managing refractory status epilepticus 
(RSE). [8,9] Until now, propofol, as an anesthestic agent, is widely 
used in various surgeries. </p>

<p>In the study of Hari Keerthy et al, [10] propofol behaved better 
than midazolam in minor oral surgery for fast recovery and onset 
of action. Chen et al [11] reported that propofol used for the 
maintenance of general anesthesia greatly reduced the incidence 
of postoperative nausea and vomiting and improved the 
postoperative patient well-being. Moreover, it resulted in obvious 
cost reductions. After the hernia surgery of children, propofol 
could impair short-term memory postoperatively, compared to 
sevoflurane. [12] For the patients undergoing donor hepatectomy, 
propofol exerted protective effects against ischemia-reperfusion 
(IR) injury. [13] 
According to previous studies, the efficacy of propofol is affected 
by many factors. Obesity is potentially associated with the 
pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic profile of anesthetic 
drugs. [14] The study of Olutoye et al [15] suggested that obese 
children require lower dose of propofol for induction of anesthesia 
than normal-weight children. Meanwhile, elderly patients might 
need lower doses of propofol for procedural sedation in the 
Emergency Department, compared with younger adults. [16] 
Choong et al [17] concluded that more rapid propofol metabolism 
may occur in women than men. However, no research investigated 
the influence of ABO blood group on the efficacy of propofol. 
The patients with different blood group arranged for surgeries 
were enrolled in the present research. Propofol was used as an 
anesthetic agent and the changes of mean arterial pressure (MAP), 
heart rate (HR), and bispectral index (BIS) indexes represented the 
influences of ABO blood group on efficacy of propofol. </p>

<p>2. Method </p>

<p>2.1. Patients' enrollment </p>

<p>The study was approved by ethics committee of The Affiliated 
Hospital of Inner Mongolia Medical University. Written </p>

<p>Editor: Kazuo Hanaoka. </p>

<p>YD and HS equally contributed to this study. </p>

<p>The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>

<p>Department of Anesthesiology, The Affiliated Hospital of Inner Mongolia Medical 
University, Huhhot, Inner Mongolia Autonomous Region, PR China. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Correspondence: Jianshe Yu, Department of Anesthesiology, The Affiliated 
Hospital of Inner Mongolia Medical University, Huhhot, Inner Mongolia 
Autonomous Region, PR China (e-mail: vksdfh@163.com). </p>

<p>Copyright © 2017 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. 
This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-Non Commercial License 4.0 (CCBY-NC), where it is 
permissible to download, share, remix, transform, and buildup the work provided 
it is properly cited. The work cannot be used commercially without permission 
from the journal. </p>

<p>Medicine (2017) 96:20(e5616) </p>

<p>Received: 10 September 2016 / Received in final form: 8 November 2016 / 
Accepted: 9 November 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000005616 </p>

<p>Observational Study </p>

<p>Medicine ® </p>

<p>OPEN </p>



<p>informed consent was obtained from each patient. The 
participants were enrolled from patients arranged for surgeries 
of cholecystectomy, tonsillectomy, and spinal operation. The 
participants were required without cardiovascular and endocrine 
metabolic diseases. A total of 72 participants were enrolled. Each 
blood group (A, B, AB, O) contained 18 participants. </p>

<p>2.2. Anesthesia performance </p>

<p>Venous access was established on all the participants and no 
medicine was provided before anesthesia. MAP, HR, and BIS 
were assayed with Philips monitor. After 10 minutes, MAP, HR, 
and BIS were determined before propofol anesthesia (T 0 ). Then, 
1 mg/mL propofol was injected at the initial time. The target 
concentration was 4 mg/mL. MAP, HR, and BIS were determined 
when the concentration of propofol was 1 mg/mL (T 1 ), 2 mg/mL 
(T 2 ), 3 mg/mL (T 3 ), and 4 mg/mL (T 4 ). When the concentration 
reached 4 mg/mL, fentanyl (2 mg/kg) and rocuronium bromide 
(0.6 mg/kg) were intravenously endotracheal intubated. Anesthe-
sia maintenance was performed with target-controlled infusion of 
propofol and remifentanil. Rocuronium bromide was used to 
keep muscle relaxation. </p>

<p>2.3. Statistics </p>

<p>The differences in MAP, HR, and BIS at T 0 were compared with 
the x 2 test. The same analysis was performed in age, sex, and 
weight. Multiple comparison was adopted to calculate the 
differences in MAP, HR, and BIS between group at T 1 , T 2 , T 3 , 
and T 4 . P &lt; .05 indicates significant differences. The analysis was 
conducted in the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18.0</rs> software. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Baseline characteristics of participants </p>

<p>As shown in Table 1, there were no obvious differences in age, 
sex, and weight of all groups (P &gt; .05). Meanwhile, MAP, HR, 
and BIS values at T 0 point were analyzed. Before propofol 
anesthesia, all the participants showed no differences in MAP, 
HR, and BIS (P &gt; .05). </p>

<p>3.2. MAP, HR, and BIS changes of each group </p>

<p>Multiple comparisons of MAP, HR, and BIS indexes between 
groups were performed. The results were exhibited in Table 2. No 
significant differences of MAP, HR, and BIS values at each time 
point between groups were found. However, we observed 
differences in DMAP, DHR, and DBIS between groups. The 
patients in the B blood group showed highest DMAP at each time 
point (P &lt; .05). Similar result was observed in DHR (P &lt; .05). 
As for DBIS, patients in A blood group exhibited highest value at 
T 3 and T 4 (P &lt; .05). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>MAP, HR, and BIS are important indexes representing the 
efficacy of anesthesia. MAP represents the hemodynamic 
responses. Decrease in arterial blood pressure is a main adverse 
reaction during propofol sedation. Erdman et al [18] found severe 
hypotension and bradycardia occurred in neurocritical care 
patients received dexmedetomidine or propofol, which was also 
observed by Yokoe et al. [19] BIS is valuable in guiding the 
administration of propofol intraoperatively. [20-23] The decreased </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics of participants. </p>

<p>Index 
A 
B 
AB 
O 
P </p>

<p>Age, y 
52.11 ± 7.67 
51.17 ± 5.68 
48.44 ± 6.64 
51.89 ± 4.87 
.579 
Sex, female/male 
10/8 
9/9 
11/7 
9/9 
.893 
Weight, kg 
62.38 ± 6.95 
60.44 ± 5.50 
61.50 ± 6.20 
60.78 ± 6.90 
.808 
MAP, mm Hg, T 0 
93.50 ± 6.51 
93.11 ± 6.95 
93.38 ± 6.68 
96.06 ± 9.07 
.604 
HR, beats min À1 , T 0 
82.50 ± 4.59 
86.06 ± 3.83 
84.11 ± 4.30 
85.56 ± 5.47 
.097 
BIS, T 0 
94.78 ± 7.88 
95.94 ± 8.03 
97.06 ± 8.05 
96.56 ± 6.66 
.829 </p>

<p>BIS = bispectral index, HR = heart rate, MAP = mean arterial pressure. </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Comparison of MAP, HR, and BIS between groups. </p>

<p>Index 
Group 
T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 </p>

<p>DMAP, mm Hg 
A 
14.72 ± 3.94 
18.89 ± 5.97 
18.67 ± 4.00 
26.06 ± 3.89 
B 
19.06 ± 5.78 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>23.06 ± 4.90 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>24.06 ± 4.90 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>32.17 ± 5.82 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>AB 
14.89 ± 3.08 
19.50 ± 3.76 
19.72 ± 2.63 
24.11 ± 5.95 
O 
15.78 ± 2.53 
19.94 ± 2.71 
21.11 ± 2.68 
25.28 ± 19.94 
DHR, beats min À1 
A 
6.39 ± 3.33 
9.72 ± 3.66 
12.50 ± 4.11 
12.39 ± 4.84 
B 
12.56 ± 4.13 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>16.06 ± 4.70 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>18.39 ± 5.41 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>18.50 ± 5.25 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>AB 
6.17 ± 1.72 
9.00 ± 3.69 
11.50 ± 5.36 
12.83 ± 3.88 
O 
7.06 ± 1.95 
11.33 ± 5.44 
12.83 ± 2.46 
13.33 ± 2.79 
DBIS 
A 
21.11 ± 5.10 
35.11 ± 5.77 
46.00 ± 5.80 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>51.06 ± 5.78 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>B 
22.28 ± 5.70 
35.00 ± 4.72 
40.11 ± 6.49 
44.06 ± 5.80 
AB 
22.50 ± 5.34 
34.61 ± 5.17 
39.89 ± 6.04 
44.72 ± 6.46 
O 
21.06 ± 5.78 
33.94 ± 5.97 
41.11 ± 5.77 
43.61 ± 6.24 </p>

<p>BIS = bispectral index, HR = heart rate, MAP = mean arterial pressure. 
 *  P &lt; .05 compared to other 3 groups. </p>

<p>Du et al. Medicine (2017) 96:20 
Medicine </p>



<p>BIS level is observed in the anesthesia treatments of propofol 
and sevoflurane. [24] In our research, changes of MAP, HR, and 
BIS were also used to figure out the influences of ABO blood 
group. 
The results indicated that the patients in the B blood group 
showed highest DMAP at T 1 , T 2 , T 3 , and T 4 . Meanwhile, the B 
blood group also exhibited highest DHR at each time point. In 
terms of DBIS, patients of A blood group showed highest value at 
T 3 and T 4. Above mentioned results indicated that the ABO blood 
group might exert strong effects on anesthetic efficacy of 
propofol. 
However, the function mechanism of blood group in regulating 
the efficacy of propofol is unclear. As we all know, decreased 
blood flow velocity, hypercoagulable blood, and injuried vessel 
wall usually occurred during anesthesia performance in surgeries. 
Moreover, the patients with different ABO blood groups 
exhibited significantly different levels of Von Willebrand factor 
(VWF). The patients of O blood group had obviously lower 
content of VWF than the non-O blood group, which was directly 
related with incidence of thrombosis. [25-28] VWF is an adhesive 
glycoprotein synthesized by megakartocytes and endothelial 
cells. [29,30] It shows crucial roles in primary hemostasis and, 
moreover, has a pivotal role in thrombogenesis. [31] It has been 
demonstrated that the increased level of VWF is an important risk 
factor of thrombosis. [32,33] In vitro experiment suggested that 
removal of A and B antigens from purified plasma decreased 
VWF activity. [34] Moeller et al [35] thought that ABO antigens in 
vivo affected synthesis rate or proteolysis of VWF molecule rather 
than its structure and function. Meanwhile, many studies have 
demonstrated a tight correlation between the ABO blood group 
and hemostasis. The patients of group O are more likely to suffer 
bleeding complications. [36] Moreover, a number of studies 
reported the increased risk of venous thromboembolism in 
non-O individuals. [37,38] All the above-mentioned information 
suggests that ABO blood group might involve in the pharmaco-
kinetic and pharmacodynamics, which was demonstrated in our 
study. 
However, there existed deficits in our study. The specifically 
regulatory mechanism of ABO blood group on pharmacody-
namics of propofol was not studied, which helps in understand-
ing individual difference in response to propofol anesthesia. In 
addition, the sample size was relatively small. The broad-range 
investigation contributes to more accurate and reliable results. 
In conclusion, the ABO blood group was related with the 
efficacy of propofol. Patients of B blood group showed highest 
DMAP and DHR at each time point. Patients of A blood group 
exhibited highest value of DBIS at T 3 and T 4 . </p>









</text></tei>