<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5018703" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objectives: To study age specific rates of hepatitis B 
virus (HBV) carriage in the eastern region of Saudi 
Arabia following a 24 year immunization program. </p>

<p>Methods: Hepatitis B surveillance data between 
January 2004 and December 2013 were analyzed in </p>

<p>a retrospective study, which included 24,504,914 
patients. Seropositive cases of hepatitis B were 
reported by laboratory personnel as part of various 
investigations. Hepatitis B cases including acute 
and chronic carriers were identified upon serological 
positivity of hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg). </p>

<p>Results: The study shows that the overall prevalence 
rate decreased from 18.8 to 9.9/100,000 population 
between 2004 and 2013 (p=0.01). It was also 
found that the prevalence rate increased with age. 
For instance, the highest prevalence of hepatitis B 
was seen among patients &gt;15 years of age and the 
lowest was seen among children &lt;15 years of age. 
Over the period, the prevalence rate decreased in all 
age groups with the greatest decline among the age 
groups &lt;4 years old. However, this was statistically 
insignificant (p&gt;0.05). Another significant reduction 
in the prevalence rate occurred among age groups 
5-14 years old (p=0.00). An insignificant decrease in 
the rate by 43% was also seen among older patients of 
15-44 years old and 35% in &gt;45 years old. The overall 
prevalence of hepatitis B is significantly higher in men 
than in women (p=0.00). </p>

<p>Conclusion: There is a particular decreased trend 
in the prevalence of HBV infection in different age 
groups over a decade of surveillance following more 
than 20 years of the universal HBV vaccination 
program. </p>

<p>865 </p>

<p>www.smj.org.sa Saudi Med J 2016; Vol. 37 (8) </p>

<p>Declined rates of hepatitis B in Saudi Arabia ... Al-Jubran et al </p>

<p>H epatitis B virus (HBV) is a public health concern </p>

<p>world-wide and a major cause of chronic hepatitis, 
liver cirrhosis, and hepatocellular carcinoma. The 
burden of HBV infection varies geographically and 
depends on the different modes of transmission and the 
age at the infection, which determines the probability 
of progression to chronic infection. 1,2 Several studies 3-9 
reported the prevalence of HBV in Saudi Arabia among 
the general public, school students, blood donors, 
health care workers, and pregnant women. Several 
studies have shown that HBV infection in Saudi Arabia 
is acquired mainly through horizontal and vertical 
transmission similar to what is observed in other 
endemic countries. 10,11 It has been reported that 5-10% 
of the population were infected with HBV. 12 However, 
despite a significant decline in the prevalence of HBV 
infection in Saudi Arabia, the disease continues to cause 
significant morbidity and mortality and imposes a great 
burden on the country's health care system. 12 Compared 
with other parts of Saudi Arabia, a higher prevalence of 
hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) was found in the 
eastern region of the country. 13 Since October 1989, 
the HBV vaccine has been integrated into the children's 
extended program of immunization. 13 Hepatitis B 
surveillance in Saudi Arabia was especially conducted 
to measure disease frequencies, direct prevention 
and control activities, and to evaluate the impact of 
these activities. Furthermore, a periodic and regular 
evaluation of surveillance data for quality, completeness, 
and timeliness was also implemented. This resulted 
in a marked decline in HBsAg seroprevalence, which 
was reported several times. 14,15 Most of the previous 
reports 16 on HBV infection in Saudi Arabia were based 
on prevalence studies, while very few were concerned 
with the actual disease risk in the community, or the 
effectiveness of immunization programs. Reports on the 
age specific prevalence of HBV especially in the eastern 
region of Saudi Arabia are very much lacking. Most 
of the previously mentioned studies have investigated 
the prevalence of HBV at country level. However, this 
study is the first one to assess the impact of a long term 
strict control measures on the rate of HBV carriage in 
the eastern region of Saudi Arabia, which was found 
to have the second highest prevalence in the country. 17 
The main objective of this study is to describe the trend 
in prevalence of HBV infection in 14 sectors affiliated 
to the eastern region of Saudi Arabia over a decade of </p>

<p>surveillance (2004-2013) following the introduction of 
a vaccination program in 1989. </p>

<p>Methods. The primary goals of conducting 
surveillance for hepatitis B are to directly prevent and 
control activities for these diseases and to evaluate the 
impact of these activities. 
The Eastern Province is the biggest province in 
Saudi Arabia. It borders the Arabian Gulf, Iraq, Kuwait, 
Oman, Qatar, the United Arab Emirates, and Yemen. 
In 2012 the population of the eastern region was 
4,414,278, which includes 3,065,883 Saudi nationals 
and 1,348,395 expatriates mainly from other Arab 
and Asian countries with an annual growth rate of 
3.19 between 2004 and 2010. 18,19 Hepatitis B virus 
diagnostic reports were collected retrospectively in 
a cross-section study, which included 24,504,914 
patients between 2004 and 2013 from 14 sectors in 
the eastern region involving participants visiting health 
facilities of the study area. All recorded cases indicated 
the unique medical record number of the patients 
to avoid duplication. Seropositive cases of hepatitis 
B were reported by a laboratory personnel as part of 
the investigations, which included medical care of 
clinically compatible illness, routine screening of blood 
donors, antenatal care, prenuptial tests, HBV-infected 
patients' contacts, prisoners, intravenous drug users, 
patients with other sexually transmitted infections, and 
expatriates doing pre-employment tests. 
Furthermore, HBV cases, including acute and 
chronic carriers, were identified upon serological 
positivity of HBsAg. The HBV markers were detected by 
standard enzyme immunosorbent assay (ELISA) using 
commercial kits for HBsAg according to manufacturers' 
instructions. Any subject with positive HBsAg 
confirmed by a neutralization test was considered to be 
HBV-infected. However, ethical approval for the study 
was obtained from the Ethics Committee of Prince 
Sultan Military College of Health Sciences, Dhahran, 
Saudi Arabia. All subjects were assured of confidentiality 
of personal data. 
According to the Ministry of Health Annual 
statistical books 2004-2013, 18 the annual population 
of the eastern region during the surveillance period 
ranged from 2,113,533 in 2004 to 2,941,236 in 2011. 
The distribution of the population by age groups 
was calculated according to the age structure of the 
population reported by the 2007 census of Saudi Arabia. 
This was estimated as 2.3% for &lt;1, 8.2% for 1-4, 20.4% 
for 5-14, 55.9% for 15-44, and 13.2% for and &gt;45 </p>

<p>Disclosure. Authors have no conflict of interests, and the 
work was not supported or funded by any drug company. </p>



<p>Declined rates of hepatitis B in Saudi Arabia ... Al-Jubran et al </p>

<p>Saudi Med J 2016; Vol. 37 (8) www.smj.org.sa </p>

<p>years. 18 Gender distributions was estimated according 
to the 2009 population census of Saudi Arabia, which 
reported a male to female ratio of 1.25: 1. 19 
Statistical analysis. For the purpose of this report, 
hepatitis B surveillance data between January 2004 
and December 2013 were analyzed. Prevalence trends 
refer to rates over time of diagnosed seropositive cases 
of hepatitis B. The carriage rate for a certain yea, or 
demographic group (gender, age group) was calculated 
by dividing the number of reported seropositive cases 
for hepatitis B for that year, or demographic group by 
the corresponding estimated population for that year, 
or demographic group, then multiplied to give the rate 
per 100,000. All data were analyzed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical 
Package for Social Sciences version</rs> 20.0 (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">(SPSS Inc.</rs>., 
Chicago, IL, USA) to calculate the odds ratios (OR) 
and the respective 95% confidence interval (CI) for 
the decline in hepatitis B prevalence between 2004 and 
2013. We used the 2004 prevalence for reference to 
calculate the OR and p-values compared with this year. 
Data were analyzed using univariate analysis. We used 
5% (p&lt;0.05) as a level of significance. </p>

<p>Results. The estimated number of 4053 HBV 
infections by age groups and population at risk in the 
eastern region of Saudi Arabia during 2004-2013 are 
shown in Table 1. Tables 2 &amp; 3 summarize the prevalence 
rate per 100 000 population (R/10 5 ) and the OR with 
the 95% CI, and the p-value among younger and 
older age groups. The highest prevalence of hepatitis 
B was seen among persons &gt;44 years of age and the 
lowest among children &lt;15 years of age. The overall </p>

<p>prevalence has decreased from 18.8 in 2004 to 9.9% 
in 2013 (Table 3). During the surveillance period, the 
prevalence decreased in all age groups with the greatest 
decline of almost 100% at the age groups &lt;1 and 1-4 
years, although statistically insignificant. A significant 
reduction of 96.5% of the prevalence occurred among 
age groups 5-14 years. A less dramatic, statistically 
insignificant (p&gt;0.05) decrease in the prevalence of 43% 
was seen among older persons of 15-44 and 35% in 
&gt;45 years old. The average prevalence of HBV infection 
in the eastern region during the 10 year surveillance 
period ranged from 0.3 cases per 100 000 population 
for the age group 1-4 years to 25 cases per 100 000 
population for the age group &gt;45 years. The total 
number of HBV infections among patients &lt;14 years 
old was 106 cases compared with 3947 cases detected 
among those &gt;24 years old. There was a clear decline 
in the prevalence among all 3 pediatric age groups, 
namely infants &lt;1 year of age, children 1-4 years of age, 
and children 5-14 years of age, although there was no 
noticeable decline in the overall prevalence (Figure 1). 
From 2004 to 2013, 4053 cases of HBV infection 
(HBsAg-positive) were estimated according to the data 
collected from 14 sectors affiliated to the eastern region 
of Saudi Arabia, of whom 2665 (65.7%) cases were 
males and 1388 (34.2%) were females. Prevalence rates 
among males were 10.6 per 100 000 and females were 
6.0 per 100 000 (Table 4). 
In the &lt;1 year age group, the prevalence among 
females is insignificantly higher than males (p=0.59). In 
the 1-4 years old age group, although slightly higher, it 
was not statistically significant (p=0.78). At 5-14 years, </p>

<p>Table 1 -Hepatitis B surface antigen virus cases by age groups in the Eastern Province of Saudi Arabia during 2004-2013 and the 
population at risk between parentheses. </p>

<p>Years 
Age 
Total 
&lt;1 year 
1-4 year 
5-14 year 
15-44 year 
&gt;45 year 
2004 
2 (48611) 
3 (173310) 
37 (431161) 
303 (1181465) 
53 (278986) 
398 (2113533) 
2005 
0 (49201) 
0 (175414) 
17 (436395) 
252 (1195807) 
75 (282373) 
344 (2139190) 
2006 
1 (49792) 
1 (177517) 
12 (441629) 
215 (1210149) 
41 (285760) 
270 (2164847) 
2007 
0 (51528) 
1 (183708) 
6 (457029) 
265 (1252348) 
73 (295724) 
345 (2240338) 
2008 
1 (52572) 
0 (187432) 
6 (466294) 
440 (1277738) 
139 (301720) 
586 (2285756) 
2009 
0 (53608) 
0 (191124) 
3 (475480) 
477 (1302907) 
101 (307663) 
581 (2330782) 
2010 
1 (61012) 
0 (217519) 
3 (541146) 
393 (1482845) 
124 (350153) 
521 (2652675) 
2011 
1 (63849) 
1 (227636) 
8 (566313) 
303 (1551809) 
81 (366438) 
394 (2776046) 
2012 
0 (65791) 
0 (234561) 
0 (583544) 
264 (1599290) 
60 (377587) 
324 (2860511) 
2013 
0 (67649) 
0 (241181) 
2 (600012) 
240 (1644151) 
48 (388243) 
290 (2941236) 
Total 
6 (563613) 
6 (2009402) 
94 (4999003) 
3152 (13698509) 
795 (3234647) 
4053 (24504914) 
Chi-square 
8.41 
16.57 
143.97 
295.15 
134.21 
134.21 
P-value 
0.68 
0.12 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 </p>



<p>www.smj.org.sa Saudi Med J 2016; Vol. 37 (8) </p>

<p>Declined rates of hepatitis B in Saudi Arabia ... Al-Jubran et al </p>

<p>Table 2 -Hepatitis B surface antigen virus rate per 100 000 (R/10 5 ) and the odds ratio (OR) with the 95% confidence interval (CI) and P-value 
among younger age groups. </p>

<p>Year 
Age 
&lt; 1 year 
1-4 years 
5-14 years 
R/10 5 
OR (95% CI) 
P-value 
R/10 5 
OR (95% CI) 
P-value 
R/10 5 
OR (95% CI) 
P-value 
2004 
4.1 
1 
1.7 
1 
8.6 
1 
2005 
0.0 
0.20 (0.01-4.22) 
0.30 
0.0 
0.14 (0.01-2.73) 
0.20 
3.9 
0.45 (0.26-0.81) 
0.01 
2006 
2.0 
0.49 (0.04-5.38) 
0.56 
0.6 
0.33 (0.03-3.13) 
0.33 
2.7 
0.32 (0.17-0.61) 
0.00 
2007 
0.0 
0.19 (0.01-3.93) 
0.28 
0.5 
0.31 (0.03-3.02) 
0.32 
1.3 
0.15 (0.06-0.36) 
0.00 
2008 
1.9 
0.46 (0.42-5.10) 
0.53 
0.0 
0.13 (0.01-2.56) 
0.18 
1.3 
0.15 (0.06-0.36) 
0.00 
2009 
0.0 
0.18 (0.01-3.78) 
0.27 
0.0 
0.13 (0.01-2.51) 
0.18 
0.6 
0.07 (0.02-0.24) 
0.00 
2010 
1.6 
0.40 (0.04-4.39) 
0.45 
0.0 
0.11 (0.01-2.20) 
0.13 
0.6 
0.06 (0.02-0.21) 
0.00 
2011 
1.6 
0.38 (0.03-4.20) 
0.43 
0.4 
0.25 (0.03-2.44) 
0.23 
1.4 
0.16 (0.08-0.35) 
0.00 
2012 
0.0 
0.15 (0.01-3.08) 
0.22 
0.0 
0.11 (0.01-2.404 
0.14 
0.0 
0.01 (0.00-0.06) 
0.00 
2013 
0.0 
0.14 (0.01-2.30) 
0.21 
0.0 
0.10 (0.01-1.99) 
0.13 
0.3 
0.04 (0.01-0.16) 
0.00 
Mean 
1.1 
0.19 (0.03-1.03) 
0.05 
0.3 
0.09 (0.02-0.47) 
0.00 
2.1 
0.15 (0.10-0.22) 
0.00 </p>

<p>Table 3 -Hepatitis B surface antigen virus rate per 100 000 (R/10 5 ) and the odds ratio (OR) with the 95% confidence interval (CI) and P-value 
among older age groups. </p>

<p>Year 
Age 
15-44 years 
&gt;45 years 
Total 
R/10 5 
OR (95% CI) 
P-value 
R/10 5 
OR (95% CI) 
P-value 
R/10 5 
OR (95% CI) 
P-value 
2004 
25.6 
1 
19.0 
1 
18.8 
1 
2005 
21.1 
0.82 (0.70-0.97) 
0.02 
26.6 
1.40 (0.98-1.99) 
0.6 
16.1 
0.85 (0.74-0.99) 
0.03 
2006 
17.8 
0.69 (0.58-0.83) 
0.00 
14.3 
0.76 (0.50-1.14) 
0.18 
12.5 
0.66 (0.57-0.77) 
0.00 
2007 
21.2 
0.83 (0.70-0.997 
0.02 
24.7 
1.30 (0.91-1.85) 
1.47 
15.3 
0.82 (0.57-0.77) 
0.00 
2008 
34.4 
1.34 (1.16-1.55) 
0.00 
46.1 
2.42 (1.77-3.33) 
0.00 
25.6 
1.36 (1.20-1.54) 
0.00 
2009 
36.6 
1.43 (1.16-1.55) 
0.00 
32.8 
1.73 (1.24-2.41 
0.00 
24.9 
1.35 (1.19-1.53) 
0.00 
2010 
26.5 
1.03 (0.89-1.20) 
0.67 
35.4 
1.86 (1.35-2.57) 
0.00 
19.6 
1.04 (0.92-1.89) 
0.53 
2011 
19.5 
0.76 (0.65-0.89) 
0.00 
22.1 
1.16 (0.83-1.65) 
0.39 
14.2 
0.75 (0.66-0.87) 
0.00 
2012 
16.5 
0.64 (0.55-0.76) 
0.00 
15.9 
0.84 (0.58-1.21) 
0.31 
11.3 
0.60 (0.45-0.61) 
0.00 
2013 
14.6 
0.57 (0.48-0.67) 
0.00 
12.4 
0.65 (0.44-0.96) 
0.03 
9.9 
0.52 (0.45-0.61) 
0.00 
Mean 
23.4 
0.89 (0.79-1.00) 
0.05 
25.0 
1.32 (1.00-1.75) 
0.05 
16.8 
0.87 (0.78-0.96) 
0.01 </p>

<p>Figure 1 -Yearly hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) virus rate/100 000 of hepatitis 
B among all age groups. </p>



<p>Declined rates of hepatitis B in Saudi Arabia ... Al-Jubran et al </p>

<p>Saudi Med J 2016; Vol. 37 (8) www.smj.org.sa </p>

<p>the prevalence was higher in males and statistically 
significant (p=0.00). For the older age groups &gt;15 years 
old, the prevalence among males was noticeably higher 
than females and statistically significant (p=0.00). </p>

<p>Discussion. The current study showed the trend 
in prevalence of HBV infection in different age groups 
over a decade of surveillance following 24 years of the 
universal HBV vaccination program. The age group that 
included children and adolescents &lt;15 years showed the 
greatest HBV prevalence decline, mainly due to the 
universal infant/child immunization program started in 
1989 in Saudi Arabia. 
The average prevalence of HBV infection during 
2004-2013 among children was 1.1, 0.3, and 2.1/100 
000 population, for the age groups of &lt;1, 1-4, and 5-14. 
The relatively higher prevalence among children &lt;1 year 
than the subsequent age group of 1-4 year may indicate 
that a sporadic vertical transmission is taking place. The 
study also indicated that horizontal childhood HBV 
transmission is very low in children, and suggested 
that schools may not form any risk of horizontal 
transmission of HBV. Similar findings were detected in 
very low-prevalence countries. 20 The prevalence of HBV 
was more than 20-fold higher in those who were aged 
&gt;15 years compared with those who were &lt;15 years old 
(annual average prevalence of 24.2 and 1.2 per 100, 000 
population). 
Prior to the introduction of vaccinations in 1989, 
the overall prevalence of HBsAg of 6.7% was steady 
in all age groups, and the highest prevalence was seen 
in children between 1-3 years in the study area. 21 The 
overall prevalence of hepatitis B in the eastern region 
declined by 47.34% from 18.8 to 9.9 per 100,000 
population between 2004 and 2013. 
The total number of cases detected between 
1990-1999, a decade prior to our analysis, was 6101 
hepatitis B cases compared with 4053 detected between 
2004 and 2013, namely, a 33.57% reduction. 13 The </p>

<p>highest annual prevalence of 25.6/100,000 population 
reported in 2008 and 24.9/100,000 in 2009 was 
less than the estimated average annual prevalence of 
46.0 and 53.2/100,000 population for HBV during 
the same period, possibly due to a population size 
estimate of those studies. 16 The reduction in HBV 
prevalence in Saudi Arabia may be attributed to 
several measures implemented since 1989. 13 However, 
the foremost of these measures is the vaccination 
of infants beginning at birth. Vaccination coverage 
as reported monthly by the Ministry of Health was 
&gt;95.5% since its commencement. 18 Other preventive 
measures include routine screening of all pregnant 
women for HBsAg for preventing perinatal infection, 
provision of immunoprophylaxis to infants born to 
HBsAg positive women, and routine vaccination of 
previously unvaccinated children and adolescents, 
although evidence for the declining protective effect of 
the vaccine in late adolescence has been proved. 10,11,13 
The vaccination of previously unvaccinated adults at 
increased risk for infection such as healthcare workers, 
dialysis patients, household contacts, and gender 
partners of persons with chronic HBV infection and 
others have also contributed to the incidence reduction. 
In addition, health education, routine screening of 
blood and organ donors for HBsAg, proper sterilization 
of surgical and dental equipment, and routine screening 
of high-risk subjects were implemented in HBV 
prevention strategy. 22 Consequently, awareness for the 
public to practice good hygiene in barbers shops and 
traditional therapy settings is also important in Saudi 
Arabia. Routine pre-employment screening for HBV 
infection of expatriates who wish to be employed 
in Saudi Arabia was also implemented. The higher 
prevalence of HBV seroprevalence among adults in 
the current study, which accounts for 97.4% of the 
total cases between 2004-2013 may partly be due to 
intensive observations during prenuptial screening, </p>

<p>Table 4 -Hepatitis B surface antigen virus of hepatitis B virus per 100 000 
population and number of infections by gender and the odds ratio and the 
95% confidence interval (CI) at the different age groups. </p>

<p>Age in years 
Male 
Female 
Odds ratio 
(95% CI) 
P-value </p>

<p>&lt;1 
2 (0.4) 
4 (1.4) 
0.6 (0.11-3.41) 
0.59 
1 to 4 
3 (0.2) 
3 (0.3) 
1.25 (0.25-6.19) 
0.78 
5 to 14 
65 (2.1) 
29 (1.2) 
2.80 (1.81-4.34) 
0.00 
15 to 44 
2059 (24.0) 
1093 (15.9) 
2.35 (2.19-2.53) 
0.00 
&gt;45 
536 (26.4) 
259 (11.3) 
2.59 (2.23-3.00) 
0.00 
Total 
2665 (10.6) 
1388 (6.0) 
2.40 (2.25-2.56) 
0.00 </p>



<p>www.smj.org.sa Saudi Med J 2016; Vol. 37 (8) </p>

<p>Declined rates of hepatitis B in Saudi Arabia ... Al-Jubran et al </p>

<p>blood donors, and the recruitment of new military or 
civilian employees. It is estimated that 50% of the Saudi 
population is less than 24 years of age. 19 Accordingly, it 
could be assumed, therefore, that at least 50% of the 
Saudi population has been vaccinated for HBV either at 
birth or as an entry requirement for primary school. As 
such, this particular group would have an insignificant 
prevalence of infection as indicated in this study. 
In general, the overall prevalence of hepatitis B is 
significantly higher in men than in women. In the 
age group &lt;1 year, the prevalence among females is 
insignificantly higher than males (p=0.59). At the 
age of 1-4 years, although slightly higher, it was not 
statistically significant (p=0.79). At 5-14 years, the 
prevalence was higher in males but again statistically 
insignificant. For the older age groups, above 15 years, 
the prevalence among males was markedly higher than 
females, which is statistically very significant (p=0.00). 
The OR of female to male in this study was 1:2.40, 
and statistically insignificant. In a previous report, the 
prevalence of HBV seropositivity stratified by gender 
showed a higher prevalence of 123.0 cases per 100,000 
population in males compared with 85.5 per 100,000 
population in females. 16 Nevertheless, the impact of 
gender on hepatitis B has been reported also in China. 22 
Long time implementation of universal infant 
vaccination against HBV in other endemic areas has 
resulted not only in decreasing the disease prevalence, 
but also in the reduction of liver cancer. 23 Evidence of 
the decrease in the prevalence of HBV-associated HCC 
in Saudi Arabia has been previously demonstrated. 24 
In conclusion, the prevalence of HBV infection 
in Saudi Arabia has markedly decreased among 
children as a result of the universal childhood HBV 
vaccination program that was implemented in 1989. 
It is expected that the prevalence of HBV infection 
and its complications (cirrhosis and hepatocellular 
carcinoma) will also greatly decrease among adults 
in the near future as the vaccinated individuals grow 
older. 25 Although the occurrence of hepatitis B among 
children below one year of age indicates an incidence 
of new cases, a prospective study is required in order 
to determine the actual incidence of hepatitis B in 
the area. Another limitation of this study is that it is a 
hospital based surveillance that may not reflect the real 
population incidence. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment. This work is fully supported by the Prince 
Sultan Military College of Health Sciences, Dhahran, Saudi Arabia. 
The data presented in this manuscript were generously provided by 
the Eastern Region Health Affairs Directorate to whom we are greatly 
indebted. We wish to thank Mr. Abdul T. Baker and Mr. Charles Janicki, </p>

<p>of the English Department for assisting in the proof-reading of the 
manuscript. </p>







<p>Ethical Consent </p>

<p>All manuscripts reporting the results of experimental investigations involving 
human subjects should include a statement confirming that informed consent 
was obtained from each subject or subject's guardian, after receiving approval of 
the experimental protocol by a local human ethics committee, or institutional 
review board. When reporting experiments on animals, authors should indicate 
whether the institutional and national guide for the care and use of laboratory 
animals was followed. </p>

</text></tei>