<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5266113" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Chronic rhinosinusitis (CRS) is one of the most common 
chronic diseases, with an estimated prevalence of 12% in the 
United States. 
1 CRS has a substantial influence on the quality of 
life and is a burden to the social economy. 
2 Clinically, there are 
2 types of CRS: chronic rhinosinusitis without nasal polyps 
(CRSsNP) and chronic rhinosinusitis with nasal polyps 
(CRSwNP). These different types of CRS have distinct inflam-
matory features and tissue remodeling patterns. CRSsNP is 
characterized predominantly by a T-helper type 1 (Th1)-in-
duced neutrophilic inflammation with elevated expressions of 
transforming growth factor (TGF)-β1 and tissue inhibitors of 
metalloproteinase (TIMPs), which result in remodeling that in-
cludes excessive extracellular matrix (ECM) deposition, inter-
stitial fibrosis, basement membrane thickening and goblet cell 
hyperplasia without obvious pseudocyst formation. 
3 CRSwNP 
is featured by a T-helper type 2 (Th2)-skewed eosinophilic in-</p>

<p>flammation that involves prominent edema formation and a 
decreased level of TGF-β1, which lead to fibrosis and increased 
levels of metalloproteinases (MMPs), which in turn lead to 
pseudocyst formation. 
3 According to the inflammatory pattern, 
CRSwNP is further divided into eosinophilic CRSwNP (Eos 
CRSwNP) and non-eosinophilic CRSwNP (non-Eos CRSwNP). 
There are differences between the two subtypes of CRSwNP. </p>

<p>Vγ1 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>γδT Cells Are Correlated With Increasing Expression of 
Eosinophil Cationic Protein and Metalloproteinase-7 in Chronic 
Rhinosinusitis With Nasal Polyps Inducing the Formation of Edema </p>

<p>Luo-ying Yang, Xia Li, Wen-ting Li, Jian-cong Huang, Zhi-yuan Wang, Zi-zhen Huang, Li-hong Chang,* Ge-hua Zhang* </p>

<p>Department of Otorhinolaryngology, the Third Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, China </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits 
unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Purpose: We have found that expression of γδT cells is increased in pathological mucosa of chronic rhinosinusitis with nasal polyps (CRSwNP) 
compared with normal nasal mucosa. This increase is correlated with the infiltration of eosinophils in CRSwNP. Here, we investigated the expres-
sion of γδT cells, inflammation and tissue remodeling factors as well as their probable relationships in different types of chronic rhinosinusitis (CRS) 
in China. Methods: A total of 76 surgical tissue samples that included 43 CRSwNP samples (15 eosinophilic and 28 non-eosinophilic), 17 CRS sam-
ples without nasal polyps (CRSsNP), and 16 controls were obtained. Quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) was used 
to measure the mRNA expression levels of Vγ1 
+ γδT cells, Vγ4 
+ γδT cells, eosinophil cationic protein (ECP), interleukin (IL)-8, transforming growth 
factor (TGF)-β2, metalloproteinase (MMP)-7, tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase (TIMP)-4 and hypoxia-inducible factor (HIF)-1α. Enzyme linked im-
munosorbent assay (ELISA) was used to measure the protein level of ECP and MMP-7 in CRSwNP. The eosinophils were counted and the level of 
edema was analyzed with HE staining. Results: The mRNA expression levels of the Vγ1 subset, ECP and MMP-7 were significantly increased in 
CRSwNP with histological characteristics of eosinophilic infiltration and edema. The expression of the Vγ1 gene in CRSwNP correlated positively 
with the expression of both ECP and MMP-7. No significant decreases in the mRNA expression levels of TGF-β2, TIMP-4 or HIF-1α were observed 
in the CRSwNP samples. The expression levels of Vγ1 gene, ECP and MMP-7 were significantly increased in eosinophilic CRSwNP compared to 
non-eosinophilic CRSwNP. Conclusions: Our results suggest the associations between Vγ1 
+ γδT cells, ECP and MMP-7 in CRSwNP, indicating that 
Vγ1 
+ γδT cells can induce the eosinophilic inflammation, which has a further effect on the formation of edema. </p>

<p>Key Words: Chronic rhinosinusitis; nasal polyps; γδT cells; inflammation; tissue remodeling </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Ge-hua Zhang, PhD, Department of Otorhinolaryngology, 
the Third Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University, No. 600, Tianhe Road, 
Guangzhou 510630, Guangdong Province, China. 
Tel: +86-18-922102653; E-mail: gehuazh@hotmail.com </p>

<p>Co-Correspondence to: Li-hong Chang, PhD, Department of 
Otorhinolaryngology, the Third Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University, No. 
600, Tianhe Road, Guangzhou 510630, China. 
Tel: +86-18-122299875; E-mail: changlihong19840719@126.com 
Received: April 14, 2016; Revised: July 16, 2016; Accepted: August 25, 2016 </p>

<p>•There are no financial or other issues that might lead to conflict of interest. 
•Luo-ying Yang and Xia Li contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2017 March;9(2):142-151. 
https://doi.org/10.4168/aair.2017.9.2.142 
pISSN 2092-7355 • eISSN 2092-7363 </p>

<p>γδT cells are correlated with ECP and MMP-7 in CRSwNP </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2017 March;9(2):142-151. https://doi.org/10.4168/aair.2017.9.2.142 </p>

<p>AAIR </p>

<p>http://e-aair.org </p>



<p>Non-Eos CRSwNP is more likely to involve neutrophilic inflam-
mation and fibrosis and shares some of the characteristics of 
both CRSsNP and Eos CRSwNP. 
3 The exact mechanisms re-
sponsible for the differences remain unclear. 
γδT cells are a small but distinctive subset of T cells that were 
first recognized by Brenner in 1986. 
4 These cells primarily colo-
nize in the mucosa and skin where they play an important role 
in immune regulation. 
4 γδT cells have been suggested to medi-
ate inflammatory cell infiltration and remodeling in a murine 
model via interleukin (IL)-17A, which has been proven to be a 
crucial regulator of cardiac fibrosis. 
5-8 However, the links be-
tween γδT cells, inflammation and tissue remodeling in CRS 
appear to be unknown. 
In our previous study, we found that the expression of γδT 
cells is elevated in the pathological mucosa of CRSwNP com-
pared with normal nasal mucosa and that γδT cell expression is 
positively correlated with the infiltration of eosinophils in Eos 
CRSwNP. </p>

<p>9   Previous studies have shown that different subsets of γδT cells 
play distinct roles. The Vγ1 subset has been demonstrated to 
promote inflammation particularly due to the enhancement of 
eosinophilic infiltration via Th2 cytokines and airway hyperre-
sponsiveness (AHR). 
10 The Vγ4 subset has been demonstrated 
to suppress inflammation. 
10 Our studies have indicated that 
Vγ1 
+ γδT cells might be a dominant subset in the nasal mucosa 
of CRSwNP. 
9 However, whether similar mechanisms are re-
sponsible for the pathogenesis of CRS or not remains unclear. 
Thus, the present work aimed to investigate the relationships 
between γδT cells, particularly the Vγ1 subset, inflammation 
and tissue remodeling in different types of CRS. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Subjects and study design 
A total of 76 patients were selected from the inpatients (be-
tween 2011 and 2014) of the Department of Otolaryngology-
Head and Neck Surgery, the Third Affiliated Hospital of Sun 
Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, China. The subjects included 
17 with CRSsNP, 43 with CRSwNP (15 with Eos CRSwNP and 28 
with non-Eos CRSwNP), and 16 control subjects. Detailed char-
acteristics of these subjects are provided in Table 1. The diagno-
ses and classification of CRS were based on the European Acad-
emy of Allergy and Clinical Immunology (EAACI) guidelines 
(EPOS2012). 
11 Patients with allergic diseases, fungal rhinosi-
nusitis, or severe pulmonary and cardiac diseases were exclud-
ed from this study. None of the enrolled patients had histories 
of surgery or the use of corticosteroids or antibiotics within the 
month prior to surgery. The nasal polyps (NPs), diseased eth-
moid sinus mucosa or uncinate processes of the patients with 
CRS were collected during functional endonasal sinus surgery 
as the case group. The normal nasal mucosa of the inferior tur-
binate, ethmoid sinus or uncinate process were taken from the </p>

<p>patients with deviations of the nasal septum, cerebrospinal flu-
id rhinorrhea or traumatic optic neuropathy who presented 
with no sinus inflammation as the control group. All tissue sam-
ples were stored as duplicates at -80°C after rapid freezing in 
liquid nitrogen; one sample was used for quantitative reverse 
transcription-polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR), and the 
other was used for histological analysis. CRSwNP was regarded 
as eosinophilic when the percentage of eosinophils in the tis-
sue exceeded 10% of total infiltrating cells as mentioned else-
where. </p>

<p>12   This study was approved by the Ethical Committee of the 
Third Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University (File No. 
[2013] 2-9). All patients were informed of the purposes and pro-
cedures of the study and provided written informed consent. </p>

<p>Quantitative RT-PCR 
The total RNA of each tissue sample was extracted using 
RNAiso Plus (TaKaRa, Dalian, Japan) and reverse-transcribed 
to cDNA with random hexamer primers and RT-PCR kits (Ta-
KaRa DDR036S, Dalian, Japan). The Vγ1 and Vγ4 subsets of γδT 
cells and the levels of eosinophil cationic protein (ECP), IL-8, 
TGF-β2, MMP-7, TIMP-4, hypoxia-inducible factor (HIF)-1α 
cytokines were detected. PCR was performed with an ABI 7500 
FAST instrument (Foster City, CA, USA) using a SYBR Premix 
Ex Taq kit (TaKaRa DDR420A, Dalian, Japan) with the appro-
priate primers (Table 2) as reported elsewhere. 
3,13,14 The relative 
gene expressions were calculated with the comparative CT 
method. β2 microglobulin (β2M) was used as the housekeep-
ing gene for normalization, and a no-template sample was 
used as the negative control. </p>

<p>Elisa for ECP and MMP-7 in CRSwNP 
Tissue samples were grinded in mortar with liquid nitrogen, 
then each tissue dry powder was weighed, and 100 μL PBS sup-
plemented with 10% protease inhibitor cocktail (MedChem Ex-
press, Shanghai, China) was added per 10 mg tissue. After ho-
mogenization, the suspensions were centrifuged at 3,000 rpm 
for 15 minutes at 4°C. Supernatants were separated and stored </p>

<p>Table 1. Clinical data of the subjects </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Control 
CRSsNP 
Non-Eos 
CRSwNP </p>

<p>Eos 
CRSwNP </p>

<p>Subjects, n 
16 
17 
28 
15 
Age (yr), mean±SD 
34.2±16.0 40.9±15.9 33.1±16.8 42.7±13.8 
Sex: female/male, n 
8/8 
5/12 
6/22 
7/8 
Smoking, n (%) 
2 (12.5) 
5 (29.4) 
7 (25.0) 
3 (20.0) 
CT score (Lund-Mackay), 
mean±SD </p>

<p>0.8±1.7 
8.1±3.1 11.9±7.0 12.3±6.4 </p>

<p>CRS, chronic rhinosinusitis; CRSsNP, CRS without nasal polyps; non-Eos 
CRSwNP, non-eosinophilic CRS with nasal polyps; Eos CRSwNP, eosinophilic 
CRSwNP; n, number; SD, standard deviation; CT, computed tomography. </p>

<p>Yang et al. </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2017 March;9(2):142-151. https://doi.org/10.4168/aair.2017.9.2.142 </p>

<p>Volume 9, Number 2, March 2017 </p>



<p>at -80°C until analyzed. 
ECP (Cusabio Biotech, CSB-E11729h, Wuhan, China) and 
MMP-7 (OriGene Technologies, EA100322, Beijing, China) lev-
els were measured with commercially available ELISA kits. The 
minimal detection limits for these kits are 1.560 and 0.156 ng/ 
mL, respectively. All procedures followed the manufacturer's 
recommendations. Concentrations of ECP and MMP-7 in the 
tissue homogenate were normalized to the concentration of to-
tal protein. </p>

<p>Histological analysis 
For histological analysis, each sample was fixed in 10% neutral 
buffered formalin and subsequently embedded in paraffin. Par-
affin sections (5 mm) were stained with hematoxylin and eosin 
(HE) dyes. All of the stained sections were examined by 2 inde-
pendent physicians who were blind to the clinical data. Eosino-
phils were counted under high-power (HP) magnification (400-
fold). Five fields per sample were randomly selected for analysis. 
The sample was regarded as Eos CRSwNP when the percentage 
of eosinophils exceeded 10% of the total infiltrating cells. 
12 The 
HE-stained sections were used to determine the general patho-
logic features at 200-fold magnification. According to Hellquist's 
classification, each tissue sample was classified as edematous, 
glandular hyperplastic, fibrotic, or atypical based on the remod-
eling features. 
15 A 3-point scale was used to semiquantitatively 
score the level of edema; 0 represented the least amount of ede-</p>

<p>ma, and 2 indicated the most extensive edema. </p>

<p>16   Statistical analysis 
The statistical analyses were performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">16.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). For the continuous variables, the results 
are expressed as the medians and interquartile ranges or with 
Tukey box-and-whisker plots. The Kruskal-Wallis H-test was 
used to assess the significance of intergroup variability. Two-
tailed Mann-Whitney U tests were used for between group 
comparisons. The differences in proportions between groups 
were evaluated with χ 
2 tests. Bonferroni corrections were ap-
plied to adjust for multiple comparisons (i.e., α=0.05/3=0.016). 
Spearman tests were used to examine the correlations. The lev-
el of significance was set at P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The expression of Vγ1 gene was elevated in the CRSwNP 
samples 
Vγ1 and Vγ4 genes were detected in this study, and the differ-
ences between the groups were significant (P=0.005). The ex-
pression of Vγ1 gene in the CRSwNP samples was significantly 
greater than those in the CRSsNP and control samples, and no 
significant difference between the CRSsNP and control sam-
ples was observed (Fig. 1A). Furthermore, as illustrated in Fig. 
1B, no significant differences of Vγ4 gene were observed be-
tween the groups. </p>

<p>The expression of ECP was elevated in CRSwNP 
Fig. 1C illustrates the relative expression levels of ECP in the 
different groups. This level was significantly increased in the 
CRSwNP samples, and a significant difference between groups 
was detected (P=0.002). Moreover, the expression of IL-8 var-
ied significantly between groups (P=0.008), and the difference 
between the CRSsNP and control groups was significant (Fig. 
1D). No significant differences between the other groups were 
observed. </p>

<p>The expression of MMP-7 was increased in the CRSwNP 
samples 
Similarly, significant differences in MMP-7 expression be-
tween groups were detected (P=0.003). The relative expression 
level of MMP-7 in the CRSwNP samples was significantly great-
er than those of the other two groups (Fig. 1E). Nevertheless, no 
significant differences were observed when we compared the 
relative mRNA expression levels of TGF-β2, TIMP-4, and HIF-
1α across the groups (Fig. 1F-H). </p>

<p>CRSwNP was primarily characterized by correlated eosinophils 
infiltration and edema 
The inflammatory type of CRSwNP was proven to be associat-
ed with eosinophilic infiltration compared to CRSsNP (Fig. 2). </p>

<p>Table 2. Primers for quantitative RT-PCR analysis </p>

<p>Gene 
Sequence </p>

<p>Vγ1 
(F)TACCTACACCAGGAGGGGAAG 
Vγ4 
(F)GATTGCTCAGGTGGGAAGACT 
Cγ 
(R)GTTGCTCTTCTTTTCTTGCC 
ECP 
(F)5´-TCGGAGTAGATTCCGGGTG-3( 
R)5´-GAACCACAGGATACCGTGGAG-3Í 
L-8 
(F)5´-GAATGGGTTTGCTAGAATGTGATA-3( 
R)5´-CAGACTAGGGTTGCCAGATTTAAC-3T 
GF-β2 
(F)5´-CTCCTACAGACTTGAGTCACAAC-3( 
R)5´-CTCCATAAATACGGGCATGCTCC-3Ḿ 
MP-7 
(F)5´-GAGGCATGAGTGAGCTACAGTG-3( 
R)5´-CATCTCCTTGAGTTTGGCTTCT-3T 
IMP-4 
(F)5´-TTTTGACTCTTCCCTCTGTGGT-3( 
R)5´-CTGTGTAGCAGGTGGTGATTTG-3H 
IF-1α 
(F)5´-CAGCCGCTGGAGACACAATC-3( 
R)5´-TTTCAGCGGTGGGTAATGGA-3β 
2M 
(F)5´-TACACTGAATTCACCCCCAC-3( 
R)5´-CATCCAATCCAAATGCGGCA-3Ŕ </p>

<p>T-PCR, reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction; Vγ1, Vγ4, subsets of 
γδT cells; Cγ, reverse sequence of both Vγ1 and Vγ4; ECP, eosinophil cationic 
protein; IL-8, interleukin-8; TGF-β2, transforming growth factor-β2; MMP-7, me-
talloproteinase-7; TIMP-4, tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-4; HIF-1α, hy-
poxia-inducible factor-1α; β2M, β2 microglobulin. </p>

<p>3,13,14 </p>

<p>γδT cells are correlated with ECP and MMP-7 in CRSwNP </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2017 March;9(2):142-151. https://doi.org/10.4168/aair.2017.9.2.142 </p>

<p>AAIR </p>

<p>http://e-aair.org </p>



<p>First, a significant between-group difference was detected 
(P&lt;0.001). The eosinophils accounted for a greater percentage 
of the total inflammatory cells in the CRSwNP samples than in 
the CRSsNP samples (P =0.038) and the control samples 
(P&lt;0.001), and the percentage of eosinophils in the CRSsNP 
samples was also significantly greater than in the control sam-
ples (P&lt;0.001; Fig. 3B). Additionally, the proportion of Eos 
CRSwNP in the CRSwNP samples was 34.9% (15/43), and the 
proportion of non-Eos CRSwNP was 65.1% (28/43). 
The semiquantitative edema scores were also assessed. The 
edema scores of the CRSwNP and CRSsNP samples were sig-
nificantly greater than those of the control samples (P&lt;0.001 
and P=0.001, respectively), and the scores for the CRSwNP 
samples were greater than those for the CRSsNP samples, al-
though this difference was not statistically significant (Fig. 3A). 
Positive correlations were observed between the percentages </p>

<p>of eosinophils and edema scores (rs=0.482, P&lt;0.001). 
According to the abovementioned Hellquist's classification, 
the majority of the histological patterns observed in the CRS tis-
sue samples were fibrotic and edematous types, a small num-
ber of samples showed the glandular hyperplastic type, and 
none of the samples showed the atypical type (Fig. 4). The 
edematous type was more frequently observed in the CRSwNP 
samples (46.5%) than the CRSsNP samples (29.4%). The pro-
portion of edematous-type CRSwNP was similar to that of fi-
brotic-type samples (51.2%). Moreover, the primary type of 
CRSsNP was the fibrotic one (58.8%). When the CRSwNP sam-
ples were further classified as non-Eos CRSwNP and Eos 
CRSwNP according the number of eosinophils as previously 
mentioned, the edematous type was found to be more frequent 
among the Eos CRSwNP samples (66.7%) than the non-Eos 
CRSwNP (35.7%) and CRSsNP samples. The percentage of fi-</p>

<p>Fig. 1. The relative mRNA expression levels for Vγ1 
+ γδT cells, Vγ4 
+ γδT cells, ECP, IL-8, TGF-β2, MMP-7, TIMP-4, and HIF-1α. Vγ1, Vγ4, subsets of γδT cells; ECP, 
eosinophil cationic protein; IL-8, interleukin-8; TGF-β2, transforming growth factor-β2; MMP-7, metalloproteinase-7; TIMP-4, tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-4; 
HIF-1α, hypoxia-inducible factor-1α. </p>

<p>The relative expresstion level </p>

<p>The relative expresstion level </p>

<p>The relative expresstion level </p>

<p>The relative expresstion level </p>

<p>The relative expresstion level </p>

<p>The relative expresstion level </p>

<p>The relative expresstion level </p>

<p>The relative expresstion level </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>CRSwNP </p>

<p>CRSwNP </p>

<p>CRSwNP </p>

<p>CRSwNP </p>

<p>CRSwNP </p>

<p>CRSwNP </p>

<p>CRSwNP </p>

<p>CRSwNP </p>

<p>CRSsNP </p>

<p>CRSsNP </p>

<p>CRSsNP </p>

<p>CRSsNP </p>

<p>CRSsNP </p>

<p>CRSsNP </p>

<p>CRSsNP </p>

<p>CRSsNP </p>

<p>Vγ1 
+ γδT cells </p>

<p>IL-8 </p>

<p>TGF-β2 </p>

<p>Vγ4 
+ γδT cells </p>

<p>MMP-7 </p>

<p>HIF-1α </p>

<p>ECP </p>

<p>TIMP-4 </p>

<p>0.0015 </p>

<p>0.0010 </p>

<p>0.0005 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>P=0.003 </p>

<p>P=0.036 
P=0.039 </p>

<p>P=0.008 
P=0.008 </p>

<p>P=0.006 </p>

<p>P=0.001 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>H </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>Yang et al. </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2017 March;9(2):142-151. https://doi.org/10.4168/aair.2017.9.2.142 </p>

<p>Volume 9, Number 2, March 2017 </p>



<p>Fig. 2. A large amount of eosinophil infiltration in the subepithelial tissue of a CRSwNP sample compared to CRSsNP and control (HE-stained section). (A) CRSwNP: 
epithelial cell damage and basement membrane thickness (200× magnification). (B) CRSwNP: eosinophils scattered in the subepithelial tissue with pseudocyst for-
mation and edema, a lack of collagen and the disappearance of blood vessels and glands (400× magnification). (C) CRSsNP: lymphocytes and neutrophils scattered 
with increased collagen and fibrosis (400× magnification). (D) Control: normal nasal mucosa (400× magnification of a control sample). CRSwNP, chronic rhinosi-
nusitis with nasal polyps; CRSsNP, chronic rhinosinusitis samples without nasal polyps; HE, hematoxylin and eosin. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Semiquantitative edema scores and eosinophil infiltrations in the different CRS types and controls. (A) Edema: the semiquantitative score of the severity of 
edema. (B) Eosinophil: the percentage of eosinophils relative to the total inflammatory cells. CRS, chronic rhinosinusitis. </p>

<p>Semiquantitative score </p>

<p>Percentage of eosinophils (%) </p>

<p>Control 
Control 
CRSwNP 
CRSwNP 
CRSsNP 
CRSsNP </p>

<p>Edema 
Eosinophils </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>P=0.001 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001 
P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>P=0.038 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>γδT cells are correlated with ECP and MMP-7 in CRSwNP </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2017 March;9(2):142-151. https://doi.org/10.4168/aair.2017.9.2.142 </p>

<p>AAIR </p>

<p>http://e-aair.org </p>



<p>brotic-type Eos CRSwNP (33.3%) was much lower than that of 
the other 2 groups; i.e., the non-Eos CRSwNP (60.7%) and 
CRSsNP more frequently presented as the fibrotic type. There 
were no significant differences between the groups. </p>

<p>The relationships of γδT cells, inflammation and remodeling 
The correlations between the percentage of eosinophils and 
the mRNA expression level of ECP, as well as the mRNA expres-
sion levels of ECP and MMP-7 were examined to identify posi-
tive correlations, and the results are illustrated in Fig. 5. Similar </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Hellquist's classification of CRS. HE-stained tissue sections at 200× magnification. (A) Edematous type: subepithelial edema, a lack of collagen, and the dis-
appearance of glands and blood vessels with inflammatory cell infiltration. (B) Fibrotic type: thickened basement membrane, subepithelial collagen deposition, and 
inflammatory cell infiltration. (C) Glandular hyperplastic type: increased amounts of glands and blood vessels. CRS, chronic rhinosinusitis; HE, hematoxylin and eosin. </p>

<p>A 
C 
B </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Correlations between γδT cells, inflammation and remodeling. (A) The correlation coefficient for the relationship of Eos and ECP: rs=0.386, 0.011≤P&lt;0.05. 
(B) The correlation coefficient for the association between MMP-7 and ECP: rs=0. 418, 0.030≤P&lt;0.05. (C) The correlation coefficient for the association between 
ECP and Vγ1 
+ γδT cells: rs=0.368, 0.019≤P&lt;0.05. (D) The correlation coefficient for the association between MMP-7 and Vγ1 
+ γδT cells: rs=0.353, 0.032≤ 
P&lt;0.05. The data (x) regarding the relative mRNA expression levels of ECP, MMP-7 and Vγ1 
+ γδT cells were transformed with same equation {x'=log10 (10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>x+1)}. 
Eos, eosinophils; ECP, eosinophil cationic protein; MMP-7, metalloproteinase-7. </p>

<p>EOS (%) </p>

<p>ECP </p>

<p>MMP-7 </p>

<p>MMP-7 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>ECP </p>

<p>Vγ1 
+ γδT cells </p>

<p>ECP </p>

<p>Vγ1 
+ γδT cells </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Yang et al. </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2017 March;9(2):142-151. https://doi.org/10.4168/aair.2017.9.2.142 </p>

<p>Volume 9, Number 2, March 2017 </p>



<p>outcomes were obtained when the same analysis was applied 
to Vγ1 
+ γδT cells, ECP and MMP-7. The relative expression level 
of Vγ1 gene was positively correlated with those of ECP and 
MMP-7. </p>

<p>The expression level of Vγ1 gene, ECP and MMP-7 in Eos 
CRSwNP and non-Eos CRSwNP 
The relative mRNA expression level for Vγ1 
+ γδT cells was sig-
nificantly increased in Eos CRSwNP compared to non-Eos 
CRSwNP. Moreover, the protein levels of both ECP and MMP-7 
in Eos CRSwNP were significantly increased compared to non-
Eos CRSwNP (Fig. 6). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Based on the differential expression of the T cell receptor 
(TCR), T cells are divided into αβT and γδT cell subsets. αβT 
cells are primarily peripheral blood mononuclear cells, and γδT 
cells account for less than 10% (approximately 3%-5%) of all 
lymphoid cells in the secondary lymphoid tissues and blood. </p>

<p>17   γδT cells are a distinctive subset of T cells. Nevertheless, γδT 
cells are much more prevalent in mucosal and epithelial sites. 
In these sites, γδT cells comprise as much as 50% of the total in-
traepithelial lymphocyte populations. 
18 These cells play an im-
portant role in innate immune responses, which ultimately 
lead to adaptive immune responses. These cells are the first im-
mune cells that are found in the fetus and provide immunity to 
newborns prior to the activation of the adaptive immune sys-
tem. 
19 Subsets of γδT cells have been found in both mice and 
humans. The distinct subsets of γδT cells with different γ and δ 
TCR chains that colonize specific epithelial locations in diseas-
es of the lungs, intestines, skin, uterus, vagina and tongue need 
to be identified. 
17,20-24 As the epithelial cells of nasal mucosa is 
the first mechanical barrier of the airway, it has a great effect on 
the mucosal immune system. Therefore, γδT cells are likely to 
act on the pathological process of CRS. 
Distinct histological features were present in different types of 
CRS. Previous studies based on Caucasian patients have sug-</p>

<p>gested that CRSwNP is primarily characterized by eosinophilic 
inflammation and edematous remodeling patterns. 
2,25 Howev-
er, this situation is different from that of Asian patients. Recent-
ly, a few studies based on Asians have shown that minor eosin-
ophilic inflammation accounts for the distinctive features of 
CRSwNP. 
16,26,27 Moreover, the expanding racial differences that 
have been reported indicate that Caucasian patients with 
CRSwNP and comorbid asthma are more common than Chi-
nese patients with both conditions. 
28 Studies have shown that 
the NP samples from Caucasians exhibit Th2-skewed and eo-
sinophilic inflammation patterns, and NP samples from Chi-
nese people exhibit both Th1/Th17 and Th2 cell patterns with 
neutrophilic and eosinophilic inflammation. 
12,16,27 In the pres-
ent study, the CRSwNP samples from Chinese patients also ex-
hibited similar characteristics and a greater proportion of non-
eosinophilic inflammatory patterns. Moreover, it is noteworthy 
that evidence indicates that γδT cells participate in Th2 im-
mune responses. In contrast, the available data suggest that a 
small fraction of γδT cells act as effective suppressors. 
10,29,30 Tak-
en together, distinct subsets of γδT cells likely produce certain 
cytokines that induce the infiltration of different inflammatory 
cells, such as eosinophils and neutrophils. However, the func-
tions and capacities are not yet clear. 
Correspondingly, our previous reports proved that γδT cell 
numbers are increased in CRSwNP pathological mucosa and 
positively correlated with the infiltration of eosinophils. The 
Vγ1 gene expression is also increased in CRSwNP pathological 
mucosa. 
9 A study conducted by Hahn et al. 
10 demonstrated 
similar results; these authors found that Vγ1 
+ γδT cells appeared 
to strongly enhance AHR and airway inflammation, whereas 
Vγ4 
+ γδT cells unambiguously suppressed AHR. The mRNA ex-
pression of Vγ1 
+ γδT cells was proven to positively correlate with 
that of ECP in CRSwNP in the present study, but the expression 
of Vγ4 
+ γδT cells was not found to be negatively correlated with 
either ECP or eosinophils. Again, these findings support the hy-
pothesis that distinct subsets of γδT cells can be inhibitors or 
enhancers depending on the specific γ and δ TCR chains. Addi-
tional support for this notion is provided by the increasing </p>

<p>Fig. 6. The relative mRNA expression levels for (A) Vγ1 
+ γδT cells, (B) the protein level of ECP, and (C) MMP-7 in Eos CRSwNP compared to non-Eos CRSwNP. ECP, 
eosinophil cationic protein; MMP-7, metalloproteinase-7; CRSwNP, chronic rhinosinusitis with nasal polyps; non-Eos CRSwNP, non-eosinophilic CRSwNP. </p>

<p>The relative expresstion level </p>

<p>ng/mL 
ng/mL </p>

<p>Eos CRSwNP 
Eos CRSwNP 
Eos CRSwNP 
Non-Eos CRSwNP 
Non-Eos CRSwNP 
Non-Eos CRSwNP </p>

<p>Vγ1 
+ γδT cells 
ECP 
MMP-7 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>P=0.035 
P=0.004 
P=0.002 </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>γδT cells are correlated with ECP and MMP-7 in CRSwNP </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2017 March;9(2):142-151. https://doi.org/10.4168/aair.2017.9.2.142 </p>

<p>AAIR </p>

<p>http://e-aair.org </p>



<p>number of studies based on murine models or humans that 
suggest that γδT cells mediate inflammatory cell infiltration and 
remodeling in many diseases, such as liver inflammation and 
fibrosis, cardiac fibrosis, lung inflammation, asthma, allergic 
rhinitis, psoriasis and atopic dermatitis. 
5,6,24,31,32 However, stud-
ies of the relationships of γδT cells, inflammation and remodel-
ing in CRS are scarce. Hence, additional observations and data 
are needed to address this question. 
Tissue remodeling is a dynamic process that is closely related 
to the extracellular matrix (ECM). If the balance between the 
formation and degradation of the ECM is disrupted, the re-
building process occurs. When the body is attacked by exoge-
nous or endogenous stimulation, the immune system pro-
motes the accumulation and production of inflammatory cells 
including eosinophils, which are activated to release a variety of 
proteins and cytokines, including ECP, TGF-β, MMPs, TIMPs 
and ILs. Eosinophils and ECP have been clearly suggested to 
initiate the formation of edema. Flood-Page et al. 
33 showed that 
anti-IL-5 treatment reduces eosinophils and fibrosis in the air-
ways of asthmatics. Moreover, TGF-β has been indicated to be a 
key regulator of ECM production and tissue remodeling, 
whereas MMPs are known to be important regulators of the 
degradation of the ECM. Matrilysin MMP-7 is upregulated, 
which disturbs the tissue homeostasis and progresses to the 
formation of edema. TIMPs act as inhibitors of MMPs. Finally, 
all of these confounding and multiple regulators may ultimate-
ly contribute to tissue remodeling. 
3,34 Eosinophilic inflamma-
tion with the index by ECP can lead to the downregulation of 
TGF-β1 and TGF-β2, and the decreased expression of TIMP-4. 
Without the inhibitor of MMPs, the activity of MMP-7 and 
MMP-9 increased, which promoting degradation of ECM and 
formation of edema. 
3,12,35 And vice versa, neutrophilic inflam-
matory may release IL-8 and lead to the increased expression of 
TGF-β1 and TGF-β2, as well as TIMP-4, which finally result in 
the deposition of collagen and fibrosis. 
3,35 Moreover, studies 
have shown that under anoxic conditions, HIF-1α distributed 
in the airway of patients can be activated and lead to epithelial-
to-mesenchymal transition. </p>

<p>36   The current study revealed that the general histological fea-
tures of CRSwNP are characterized by correlated edema and 
eosinophil infiltration, with the increased expressions of Vγ1 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>γδT cells, ECP, and MMP-7, and a positive correlation between 
the two. No significant difference in the expressions of Vγ4 
+ γδT 
cells was observed in the different groups. As previously men-
tioned, Vγ4 mRNA expression should have decreased. The fail-
ure to observe this phenomenon might have been due to the 
patients themselves or the progression of chronic disease. In 
long-term CRS, the body has defended against the course of 
disease and has received some treatment. Furthermore, no sig-
nificant increases in the mRNA expression levels of TGF-β2, 
TIMP-4 or HIF-1α were found in the CRSsNP samples in this 
study, and these results are inconsistent with the results of oth-</p>

<p>er studies. 
3,35 Because the mRNA expression levels of these reg-
ulators in mucosa are minimal, and the majority of the CRSwNP 
samples belonged in the non-eosinophilic subset, there were 
no substantial differences between the CRSwNP and CRSsNP 
groups. 
Thus, these results indicate that γδT cells may play a role in 
the mechanism of CRS pathogenesis which should not to be ig-
nored. Moreover, these distinct cells appear to mediate eosino-
phil infiltration and eventually lead to the formation of edema 
in CRS. However, the detailed mechanisms remain unclear. 
It has been suggested that γδT cells are activated in the pres-
ence of pathogens, antigens and stimulation by damage-asso-
ciated molecular patterns (DAMPs) because macrophages pro-
mote NF-κB signaling that results in the release of IL-23, which 
is recognized by the corresponding receptor IL-23R of the γδT 
cells and activates nuclear translocator RORγt to produce IL-
17A. This process leads to inflammatory cell infiltration or re-
cruitment, which eventually causes edema or fibrosis. 
5,6,37 IL-
17A has been suggested to induce MMPs secretion. 
36 Several 
studies have demonstrated that IL-17A upregulates Th2 cell-
mediated eosinophilic airway inflammation and plays an im-
portant role in the remodeling of nasal polyps. 
37,38 Additional 
evidence found in our previous study indicated that the expres-
sion of IL-17A is upregulated in CRSwNP. However, the role and 
the related mechanisms of IL-17A in remodeling have not been 
fully elucidated. Therefore, all of the current studies have dem-
onstrated the potential significant mechanism by which γδT 
cells are related to inflammation and remodeling in CRS. In ad-
dition to benefiting scientific research, these findings provide 
another pathway for the management and intervention for CRS 
patients. However, the mechanisms underlying IL-17A produc-
tion and the roles of IL-17A in inflammation and the early dam-
age and remodeling of the mucosa in CRS remain unclear. 
The significance of γδT cells in the pathogenesis of CRS and 
their effects on inflammation and remodeling require further 
investigations and evidences in murine models and humans. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by the Program of National Natural 
Science Foundation of China (NSFC 81371073) and Science 
and Technology Planning Project of Guangdong Province, Chi-
na (2013B021800081). </p>



<p>Yang et al. </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2017 March;9(2):142-151. https://doi.org/10.4168/aair.2017.9.2.142 </p>

<p>Volume 9, Number 2, March 2017 </p>





<p>γδT cells are correlated with ECP and MMP-7 in CRSwNP </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2017 March;9(2):142-151. https://doi.org/10.4168/aair.2017.9.2.142 </p>

<p>AAIR </p>

<p>http://e-aair.org </p>





</text></tei>