<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5371709" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Aim of the study: To was to deter-
mine the impact of chronic obstructive 
pulmonary disease (COPD) and active 
smoking on the efficacy of chemother-
apy and complete blood count (CBC) in 
patients with non-small cell lung cancer 
(NSCLC). 
Material and methods: The retrospec-
tive evaluation included 50 patients 
with stage IIIB-IV NSCLC, who started 
cisplatin-based chemotherapy. Periph-
eral blood CBC values were collected for 
testing before chemotherapy and after 
the first and third cycles. 
Results: COPD was diagnosed in 49% 
of patients, while 42% of those enrolled 
were current smokers. Current smoking 
(p = 0.92) and COPD (p = 0.91) status 
did not affect the response to treat-
ment. The non-COPD population pre-
sented a significantly higher pretreat-
ment absolute lymphocyte count (ALC) 
than the COPD population (2.31 vs. 
1.81 × 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l; p = 0.0374). Also, only the 
non-COPD group demonstrated an ele-
vated absolute monocyte count (AMC) 
following the first and third cycles of 
chemotherapy (p = 0.004). In current 
smokers, pretreatment values for white 
blood cells (WBC), absolute neutrophil 
count (ANC), and platelets (PLT) were 
higher than in the ex-smoker popula-
tion (WBC 9.94 vs. 8.7 (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l); p = 0.01; 
ANC 6.47 vs. 5.61 (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l); p = 0.037; 
PLT 316 vs. 266 (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l); p = 0.049). 
Ex-smokers demonstrated AMC level 
elevation after the first cycle of chemo-
therapy and PLT level elevation after the 
third cycle, while current smokers also 
demonstrated an early decrease in LMR. 
Conclusions: COPD and smoking induce 
chronic systemic inflammation and ox-
idative stress, which influence the re-
sults of standard laboratory tests, but 
do not change the response rate of lung 
cancer on chemotherapy. </p>

<p>Lung cancer is the most common newly-diagnosed malignancy other 
than non-melanoma skin cancer, and the leading cause of cancer-related 
death worldwide. In 2012, 1.8 million people developed lung cancer and ap-
proximately 1.6 million died because of it [1]. The following year, lung cancer 
was detected in about 21,000 patients in Poland, and about 22,000 died. 
Non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) accounts for 85% of all lung cancers and 
has a strong aetiological association with smoking. About 10-20% of chronic 
smokers develop lung cancer, and about 20% of smokers suffer from chronic 
obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). Cigarette smoking generates chronic 
inflammation in the airways and systemic oxidative-stress reactions. The 
pro-inflammatory and immunosuppressive properties of cigarette smoke 
impair the immune response [2]. Inflammation seems to play a crucial role in 
the development and progression of many tumours by promotion of prolif-
eration, cell survival, angiogenesis, and migration [3]. 
The prognosis in NSCLC is poor, with only an 18% five-year survival rate 
observed in the general population in the USA [4]. As detection is usually 
quite late, the tumours are found to be in stages III or IV for 2/3 patients with 
newly-diagnosed lung malignancy. Standard treatment for this population 
involves systemic therapy: induction chemotherapy in stage IIIA, chemo-
radiotherapy (concurrent or sequential) in stage IIIB, or palliative systemic 
treatment when distant metastases are present. Epidermal growth factor 
receptor (EGFR) activating mutations are present in 10% of Caucasians [5], 
whereas EML4-ALK translocation is present in 2-3% of the non-Asian NSCLC 
population [6, 7]. As most cases of NSCLC do not present a defined target 
for molecular orientated therapy, platinum-based chemotherapy is the stan-
dard approach in the treatment of lung cancer. The objective response rate 
(ORR), defined as a complete or partial response for cytostatic treatment of 
advanced disease, ranges from 30% to 40%. 
Lung cancer prognosis is connected with tumour-related (stage, grade) 
and host-related factors. Established adverse clinical prognostic factors in 
advanced NSCLC are weight loss and poor performance status, which are 
also negative predictive factors of response to chemotherapy. Although </p>



<p>contemporary oncology </p>

<p>the interaction between the immune system and cancer 
could play a crucial role in malignancy progression, the 
relationship remains poorly understood. As the morbidity 
and mortality rates are so high, it is important to explore 
the mechanisms that could modify the disease course and 
sensitivity to systemic treatment. 
Because many anti-cancer drugs exert their activity by 
free radical-mediated mechanisms [8], COPD-associated 
oxidative stress and inflammation may influence the effi-
cacy of chemotherapy. In addition, in vitro and in vivo stud-
ies indicate that cigarette smoking worsens the response 
of cancer to chemotherapy [9]. 
The purpose of this study was to investigate the impact 
of COPD and active smoking on the efficacy of chemother-
apy and on complete blood count (CBC) in patients with 
advanced NSCLC, with regard to systemic inflammatory 
response and oxidative stress. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Population </p>

<p>Retrospective evaluation was carried out using the 
medical documentation of 50 patients with NSCLC clas-
sified as stage III or IV, who began chemotherapy at the 
Department of Chemotherapy, Medical University of Lodz, 
in the Copernicus Memorial Hospital of Lodz from 2013 to 
2014. The analysis included only patients treated with cis-
platin-based chemotherapy doublets, with gemcitabine or 
vinorelbine as a second drug, and with a present smoking 
status or a known history of smoking. 
COPD was confirmed by spirometry: a positive result 
was indicated when the ratio of post-bronchodilator 
forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV 1 ) to forced 
vital capacity (FVC) was less than 0.7, as given in the Glob-
al Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) 
guidelines 
Patient characteristics included demographic data (age, 
sex), tumour response to treatment, complete blood cell 
count (CBC), and clinicopathological features: subtype of 
NSCLC, histological grade, performance status, weight 
loss, FEV 1 value, FEV 1 /FVC ratio, and smoking status and 
number of pack-years in smokers. Tumour response to 
treatment was assessed after 2-3 cycles of chemotherapy, 
based on the rules established by the RECIST 1.1 (Response 
Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours). In two cases, disease 
progression (PD) was established based only on clinical 
presentation. The recruitment was approved by the Medi-</p>

<p>cal University of Lodz Bioethics Committee (RNN 45/12/KE 
and 46/12/KE). </p>

<p>Assessment of blood tests </p>

<p>The initial CBC from peripheral blood was measured 
before the first treatment cycle. During treatment, CBC 
was assessed every three weeks (with tolerance from -3 
to +8 days) on day one of each cycle before treatment 
administration. Blood tests were performed by the Syn-
evo laboratory, Copernicus Memorial Hospital, Lodz; spi-
rometry (in 37 prospective cases) was performed using 
a MasterScreen Body (JAEGER) in the Chair of Experimental 
and Clinical Physiology, Medical University of Lodz. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>All statistical analyses were performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">StatsDirect</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StatsDirect Ltd.</rs>., Altrincham, UK). 
The Friedman test was used to assess the significance 
of changes in blood parameters during treatment. The 
comparisons of baseline parameters between different 
groups were assessed using the χ 
2 test or Fisher's exact 
test as appropriate, or the Mann-Whitney test. A p-value 
&lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Among 50 patients enrolled in the analysis, spirometry 
was assessed in 43 of them. COPD was diagnosed in 21 of 
those examined (48.8%), with GOLD stage 1 identified in 
nine, stage 2 in seven, and stage 3 in three cases. No data 
about COPD stage was given in two cases. Table 1 sum-
marises the clinical characteristics of the study population 
according to COPD status. 
At the start of chemotherapy, 21 patients (42%) contin-
ued to smoke, 27 (54%) reported quitting smoking in the 
past; two patients had never smoked (Table 2). 
When data collection was complete, four patients con-
tinued chemotherapy -each patient received at least one 
cycle. Response to treatment was assessed in 45 cases. 
One patient died due to toxicity before computed to-
mography examination. In total, a partial response was 
demonstrated in 18 (40%) patients, stable disease in 19 
(42%), and cancer progression in eight (18%). </p>

<p>No-COPD vs. COPD </p>

<p>Partial remission was observed in seven of the 18 pa-
tients eligible for response assessment in the COPD group </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographical and clinical characteristics of the study population with COPD and no-COPD subgroups </p>

<p>n 
Age 
(years) 
median </p>

<p>Sex 
M/F </p>

<p>Smoking 
Y/N/never </p>

<p>DCC 
median </p>

<p>Pack-
years 
median </p>

<p>Stage 
III/IV </p>

<p>Subtype 
nonS/S/U </p>

<p>PS 
0/1/2 </p>

<p>weight loss 
&gt; 10% (Y/N) </p>

<p>FEV 1 (%) 
median </p>

<p>FVC (%) 
median </p>

<p>All patients 
50 
62 
30/20 
21/27/2 
0 
38 
18/32 20/22/8 13/30/7 
14/36 
81.85 
96.5 </p>

<p>COPD 
21 
62 
12/9 
9/12/0 
0 
40 
6/15 
8/9/4 
5/11/5 
6/15 
68.9 
98.15 </p>

<p>No-COPD 
22 
62 
12/10 
9/11/2 
0 
30 
11/11 
8/10/4 
6/14/2 
6/16 
88.8 
93 </p>

<p>p value 
0.8 
0.86 
0.6 
0.97 
0.37 
0.15 
&gt; 0.99 
0.49 
0.92 
0.03 
0.67 </p>

<p>COPD -chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; n -number of participants; M -male, F -female, DCC -daily cigarette consumption, Y -yes; N -no; nonS -non-
squamous carcinoma (adenocarcinoma or large-cell carcinoma); S -squamous carcinoma; U -unable to assess, PS -ECOG performance status </p>



<p>A retrospective evaluation of associations between chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, smoking, and efficacy of chemotherapy 
and selected laboratory parameters in patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancer </p>

<p>Table 2. Demographical and clinical characteristics of the study: smokers and ex-smokers subgroups </p>

<p>n 
Age (years) 
median </p>

<p>Sex 
M/F </p>

<p>DCC 
median </p>

<p>Pack-years 
median </p>

<p>Stage 
III/IV </p>

<p>Subtype 
nonS/S/U </p>

<p>PS 
0/1/2 </p>

<p>Weight loss 
&gt; 10% (Y/N) </p>

<p>Smokers 
21 
62 
15/6 
10 
40 
6/15 
7/10/4 
4/14/3 
12/9 </p>

<p>Ex-smokers 
29 
62 
15/14 
0 
30 
11/18 
13/12/4 
9/16/4 
2/27 </p>

<p>p value 
0.54 
0.16 
&lt; 0.0001 
0.09 
0.49 
0.74 
0.66 
&lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>COPD -chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; n -number of participants; DCC -daily cigarette consumption; M -male; F -female; nonS -non-squamous carci-
noma (adenocarcinoma or large-cell carcinoma); S -squamous carcinoma; U -unable to assess; PS -ECOG performance status </p>

<p>Table 3. Differences of analysed parameters (median value and change after treatment) depending on variables and time point during 
chemotherapy </p>

<p>Entire population 
No-COPD 
COPD 
No-COPD vs. 
COPD </p>

<p>Smokers 
Ex-smokers 
Smokers vs. 
ex-smokers </p>

<p>WBC (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) 
9.27 
9.65 
8.83 
NS 
9.94 
8.7 
p = 0.01 </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p = 0.0002) 
↓ (p = 0.001) 
↓ (p = 0.002) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt;0.0001) 
↓ (p = 0.0001) 
↓ (p = 0.001) 
↓ (p = 0.001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) </p>

<p>neutrophils (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) 
5.84 
6.275 
5.66 
NS 
6.47 
5.61 
p = 0.037 </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) ↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) ↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) </p>

<p>lymphocytes (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) 
2.05 
2.31 
1.81 
p = 0.0374 
2.05 
2.03 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
NS 
↑ NS (p = 0.053*) 
NS 
NS 
↑ NS (p = 0.08) </p>

<p>post 3c. vs 0 
NS 
NS 
NS 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>monocytes (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) 
0.86 
0.9 
0.85 
NS 
0.88 
0.85 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↑ (p = 0.005) 
↑ (p = 0.004*) 
NS 
↑ NS (p = 0.059*) ↑ (p = 0.004*) </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↑ (p = 0.01) 
↑ (p = 0.004*) 
NS 
↑ NS (p = 0.059*) ↑ NS (p = 0.087*) </p>

<p>eosynocytes (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) 
0.16 
0.195 
0.14 
NS 
0.2 
0.16 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↓ (p = 0.0001) 
↓ (p = 0.002) 
↓ (p = 0.008) 
↓ (p = 0.002) 
↓ (p = 0.003) </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p = 0.001) 
↓ (p = 0.025) 
↓ (p = 0.001) 
↓ (p = 0.001) </p>

<p>basocytes (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) 
0.04 
0.045 
0.04 
NS 
0.05 
0.04 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
NS 
NS 
NS 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↓ (p = 0.046**) 
NS 
NS 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>haemoglobin (g/dl) 
13.2 
13.65 
12.8 
NS 
12.8 
13.9 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p = 0.008) 
↓ (p = 0.0002) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) ↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) </p>

<p>PLT (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) 
304 
304 
298 
NS 
316 
266 
p = 0.049 </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↑ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↑ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↑(p = 0.027*) 
↑ (p = 0.001) 
↑ (p &lt; 0.0001) </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
NS 
NS 
NS 
NS 
↑ (p = 0.046) </p>

<p>NLR 
28.5 
2.71 
2.97 
NS 
3.3 
2.8 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) ↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) ↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) </p>

<p>LMR 
2.47 
2.54 
2.28 
NS 
2.20 
2.57 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↓ (p = 0.018) 
NS 
NS 
↓ (p = 0.045) 
NS </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↓ (p = 0.0001) 
↓ (p = 0.016*) 
↓ (p = 0.005) 
↓ (p = 0.019) 
↓ (p = 0.003) </p>

<p>PLR 
146.91 
136.19 
162.38 
NS 
161.63 
137.02 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↑ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↑ (p = 0.002) 
↑ (p = 0.016*) 
↑ (p = 0.016) 
↑ (p &lt; 0.0001) </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
NS 
NS 
NS 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>* without significant change of values in general Friedman test: only one value tends to be different to another (p: 0.05-0.1) 
** without significant change of values in general Friedman test: only one value tends to be different to another (p ≥ 0.1) 
0 -baseline; 1c. -first cycle of chemotherapy; 3c. -third cycle of chemotherapy; WBC -white blood cells; PLT -platelets; UA -uric acid; LDH -lactate 
dehydrogenase; NLR -neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio; LMR -lymphocyte-to-monocyte ratio; PLR -platelet-to-lymphocyte ratio; NS -non-significant; 
↑ -increase; ↓ -decrease. COPD -chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; NS -not statistically significant </p>



<p>contemporary oncology </p>

<p>compared to 10 of the 20 patients without COPD. Stable 
disease occurred in 8/18 COPD patients and 7/20 non-
COPD patients. Disease progression was observed in 3/18 
COPD and 3/20 non-COPD patients. The differences were 
non-significant (p = 0.91). 
The non-COPD population demonstrated a higher 
pretreatment absolute lymphocyte count (ALC) than the 
COPD population (2.31 vs. 1.81 × 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l; p = 0.0374). An insig-
nificant tendency for increased ALC was found in the non-
COPD patients after the first cycle of chemotherapy (p = 
0.053) but not in the COPD group. Similarly, the non-COPD </p>

<p>group also demonstrated elevated absolute monocyte 
count (AMC) after the start of the treatment and after the 
third cycle (both p = 0.004). Both populations demonstrat-
ed NLR reduction after the fist and third cycles, LMR reduc-
tion after the thirrd cycle, and PLR enlargement after the 
first cycle. A detailed comparison is presented in Table 3. </p>

<p>Smokers vs. ex-smokers </p>

<p>Of the patients eligible for response assessment, partial 
remission was documented in 7 of the 19 members of the </p>

<p>Table 4. Differences of analysed parameters (median value and change after treatment) depending on tumour response and time point 
during chemotherapy </p>

<p>PR 
SD 
PD 
PR vs. SD 
PR vs. PD </p>

<p>WBC (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) 
9.58 
9.24 
7.56 
NS 
NS (p = 0.078) </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p = 0.001) 
NS </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p = 0.002) 
NS </p>

<p>neutrophils (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) 
6.39 
5.61 
4.67 
NS 
NS (p = 0.064) </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
NS </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p = 0.032*) </p>

<p>lymphocytes (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) 
2.04 
2.27 
2.16 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
NS 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
NS 
NS 
↑ (p = 0.003) </p>

<p>monocytes (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) 
0.97 
0.87 
0.65 
NS 
p = 0.021 </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
NS 
↑ (p = 0.002) 
NS </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
NS 
↑ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
NS </p>

<p>eosynocytes (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) 
0.16 
0.15 
0.2 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↓ (p = 0.01) 
↓ (p = 0.008) 
↓ (p = 0.032*) </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↓ (p = 0.0005) 
↓ (p = 0.003) 
NS </p>

<p>basocytes (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) 
0.05 
0.04 
0.05 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
NS 
NS 
↓ NS (p = 0.07**) </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↓ (p = 0.023*) 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>haemoglobin (g/dl) 
13.15 
13.9 
13.1 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↓ (p = 0.001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p = 0.012) </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.003) </p>

<p>PLT (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) 
279.5 
298 
325.5 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↑ (p = 0.001) 
↑ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
NS </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
NS 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>NLR 
2.88 
3.12 
2.28 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
NS </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
↓ (p = 0.003) </p>

<p>LMR 
1.94 
2.69 
3.09 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
NS 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
NS </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
NS 
↓ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
NS </p>

<p>PLR 
150.23 
147.52 
153.96 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>post 1c. vs. 0 
↑ (p = 0.001) 
↑ (p &lt; 0.0001) 
NS </p>

<p>post 3c. vs. 0 
↑ (p = 0.024) 
NS 
↓ (p = 0.003) </p>

<p>* without significant change of values in general Friedman test: only one value tends to be different to another (p: 0.05-0.1) 
** without significant change of values in general Friedman test: only one value tends to be different to another (p ≥ 0.1) 
0 -baseline; 1c. -first cycle of chemotherapy; 3c. -third cycle of chemotherapy; WBC -white blood cells; PLT -platelets; UA -uric acid; LDH -lactate 
dehydrogenase; NLR -neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio; LMR -lymphocyte-to-monocyte ratio; PLR -platelet-to-lymphocyte ratio; NS -non-significant; 
↑ -increase; ↓ -decrease. COPD -chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; NS -not statistically significant </p>



<p>A retrospective evaluation of associations between chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, smoking, and efficacy of chemotherapy 
and selected laboratory parameters in patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancer </p>

<p>current smoker population, and in 11 of the 26 ex-smok-
ers. Stable disease was observed in 8/19 smokers and 
11/26 ex-smokers. Disease progression was seen in 4/19 
of smokers and 4/26 of ex-smokers. The differences were 
non-significant (p = 0.92). 
Pretreatment scores for WBC, absolute neutrophil count 
(ANC), and platelet number (PLT) were higher in the smoker 
than in the ex-smoker population: WBC 9.94 vs. 8.7 (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l); 
p = 0.01; ANC 6.47 vs. 5.61 (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l); p = 0.037; PLT 316 vs. 
266 (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l); p = 0.049. Increases in PLT level following the 
third cycle were observed in the ex-smokers but no change 
was observed in the smokers. A non-significant trend 
(p = 0.08) towards early ALC increase was noted only in the 
ex-smokers. Early LMR decrease was demonstrated only in 
active smokers. The results are presented in Table 3. </p>

<p>Differences in laboratory parameters between the 
groups depending on response to treatment </p>

<p>Baseline AMC was significantly higher in the PR group 
than in the PD group: 0.97 vs. 0.65 (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) (p = 0.021). 
A non-significant trend towards higher WBC and ANC was 
observed in the PR group: 9.58 vs. 7.56 (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) for WBC 
(p = 0.078); 6.39 vs. 4.67 (× 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l) for ANC (p = 0.064). No 
other differences were observed in baseline parameters 
(Table 4). Contrary to patients with PR or SD, the PD group 
demonstrated no significant decrease in WBC after cycles 
1 and 3, no decrease in ANC or NLR (after 1 cycle), and no 
early increase of PLT or PLR during chemotherapy. On the 
other hand, a noticeable decrease of PLR was observed after 
three cycles as a result of elevated ALC in the poor response 
group. AMC elevation and consequent LMR reduction was 
reported only in the SD group, while greater PLR was ob-
served in three cycles of treatment only in the PR group. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is ob-
served in about 50% of patients diagnosed with lung can-
cer [10, 11]. Airflow limitation is an indicator of greater risk 
of respiratory complications and cardiac arrhythmias that 
may potentially affect the process of diagnosis and treat-
ment of lung cancer [12, 13]. An analysis of studies based 
on NSCLC patients following surgery revealed an associa-
tion between the coexistence of both diseases and poorer 
prognosis [11, 14]. However, a prospective trial of 324 pa-
tients diagnosed with advanced NSCLC treated with sys-
temic therapy revealed no significant differences in sur-
vival between the COPD and non-COPD groups [10]. Thus, 
the coexistence of COPD may adversely affect prognosis 
only in patients with early NSCLC, who are candidates for 
radical surgery. Our results are concordant with these ob-
servations. 
Cigarette smoking generates about 6000 toxic com-
pounds, carcinogens, radical solids, and oxidants [15]. To-
bacco components affect the respiratory system by the 
generation of oxidative stress and promotion of inflam-
mation. Consequently, these mechanisms induce epithe-
lial cell damage or cell death with simultaneous activation 
of reactive damage repair and enhanced proliferation [16]. 
The dichotomous influence of smoking is a cause of COPD </p>

<p>(cell death) and lung cancer proliferation. Cigarette smok-
ing has also been found to have a negative impact on the 
response to anti-cancer therapy, both in vitro and in vivo 
[9]. However, no differences have been found in response 
to chemotherapy depending on current smoking status. 
COPD is accompanied by chronic inflammation in the 
airways. This inflammation has a specific pattern with 
increased numbers of cytotoxic T lymphocytes and coex-
isting infiltration by neutrophils and macrophages that 
release inflammatory mediators and oxidants [17]. The 
conception of the protective role played by the immune 
system against cancer has already been documented [18]; 
however, the proposition by Virchow (1863) that cancer de-
velopment and progression are connected with inflamma-
tion has yet to be disproved [3, 19]. 
A convincing body of evidence suggests that mac-
rophages located in the tumour microenvironment (tu-
mour-associated macrophages -TAM) can kill tumour cells 
or foster cancer promotion by the modulation of cytotox-
ic T-cell activity [20]. The presence of a higher number of 
monocytes, circulating blood precursors of macrophages, 
corresponds with poor prognosis and worse response to 
treatment in many malignancies [21-23]. Lin et al. note 
that AMC ≥ 0.45 × 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/l is a significant adverse prognos-
tic factor in metastatic NSCLC (OS HR = 2.04) [24]. Our 
findings indicate no difference in AMC between the COPD 
and non-COPD groups, or between current smokers and 
ex-smokers. However, higher baseline AMC was found in 
patients with better response to chemotherapy than those 
with progression of cancer (p = 0.021). 
The presence of a lower lymphocyte-to-monocyte ratio 
(LMR) was an adverse prognostic biomarker for resected 
NSCLC (OS HR = 1.51; DFS HR = 1.34) [25] and for other ma-
lignancies [26, 27]. In metastatic NSCLC, LMR ≥ 4.56 was 
found to correlate with better PFS (HR = 0.66) and OS (HR 
= 0.53) [24]. In our analysis, no differences in pretreatment 
LMR values were observed between groups, and LMR did 
not predict response to therapy. 
Lymphocytes play a crucial role in the cell-mediated 
host immune response to tumours. Infiltration of tumours 
by lymphocytes (tumour-infiltrating lymphocytes -TILs) 
correlates with better prognosis in triple-negative breast 
cancer [28] or ovarian cancer [29]. Several trials investigat-
ing whether peripheral lymphocyte level can be used as 
a marker to predict the course of cancer found that high-
er levels are associated with a positive effect on outcome 
[30], and lower lymphocyte counts with a poor outcome 
[21]. Such results were obtained both in early-stage and 
advanced NSCLC [31, 32]. Higher baseline ALC was found 
in the absence of COPD, but no baseline difference was 
found between groups depending on response to treat-
ment. Nevertheless, disease progression was associated 
with an increase of ALC during treatment. 
Pretreatment absolute neutrophil count (ANC) is known 
to be an independent indicator of poor prognosis in lung 
cancer patients [31]. An analysis by Teramukai et al. found 
that in patients diagnosed with stage IIIB or IV NCSLC treat-
ed with chemotherapy, with a cut-off value of 4.5 × 10 
9 neu-
trophils/l measured before treatment, low-neutrophil count 
was significantly associated with longer survival (median </p>



<p>contemporary oncology </p>

<p>OS 19.3 for the low-neutrophil group vs. 10.2 months for the 
high-neutrophil group) [33]. Higher pretreatment ANC was 
found in current smokers than ex-smokers. Patients who 
had better response to chemotherapy tended to have high-
er baseline ANC than those who had progression (p = 0.06); 
however, a significant decline in ANC was observed only in 
those with disease control. 
Many trials have evaluated the prognostic impact of 
NLR (defined as absolute neutrophil count divided by ab-
solute lymphocyte count) as a surrogate marker of sys-
temic inflammatory response in malignancy. Based on 
these results it has been proposed that NLR be assessed 
as an independent prognostic factor for survival, regard-
less of cancer localisation [34-36]. In non-small cell lung 
cancer patients treated with EGFR-TKIs (tyrosine kinase 
inhibitors), elevated NLR (≥ 3.5) was associated with low-
er objective response rate (52% vs. 79%), and shorter PFS 
(median 8.2 vs. 10.6 months; HR = 3.90) and OS (17.2 vs. 
23.2 months; HR = 3.29) [37]. Among patients enrolled in 
the First-SIGNAL prospective study (non-smokers with ad-
enocarcinoma treated with chemotherapy or EGFR-TKI), 
NLR was assessed at two points in time: at baseline and 
after one cycle of treatment. The study showed that sig-
nificant reduction of NLR during treatment was associ-
ated with better tumour response (in the chemotherapy 
arm, median percentage changes of NLR in PR, SD, and 
PD subgroups were 50%, 41%, and 20%, respectively) and 
longer survival time (median OS 20.7 vs. 7.9 months) [38]. 
Another trial conducted in a typical population of patients 
with advanced NSCLC, with an NLR cut-off point of 2.63, 
documented that lower pretreatment NLR and its decline 
during chemotherapy correlated significantly with better 
response to chemotherapy [39]. Our analysis confirms the 
association between early NLR reduction and disease con-
trol: the change was observed in patients with PR and SD 
after the first cycle of chemotherapy, although a signifi-
cant decrease was also observed after the third cycle in 
the PD population. 
In a meta-analysis of trials, pretreatment platelet-to-lym-
phocyte ratio (PLR) was found to be an adverse prognostic 
factor in gastric cancer, colorectal cancer, ovarian cancer, 
and NSCLC [40]. In a prospective study of 210 patients with 
advanced NSCLC, the cut-off value for NRL at pretreatment 
was defined as 152.6. The study showed that elevated NLR 
was associated with poor response to first-line chemother-
apy (OR = 4.50) and worse OS (HR = 2.03) [41]. Despite no 
differences in baseline PLR, our study showed early increase 
of PLR in the PR and SD groups. After the third cycle, PLR 
was higher than baseline in the PR group but lower in the 
PD population. COPD or smoking status did not affect PLR. 
A major limitation of our study is that it is a retrospective 
study involving a relatively small number of patients. In ad-
dition, as the analysed variables could be influenced by oth-
er factors, it is important to validate the proposed predictive 
and prognostic factors and their correlation with COPD or 
smoking status in future prospective studies. 
In conclusion, COPD and smoking induce chronic sys-
temic inflammation and oxidative stress, which influence 
standard laboratory tests. Our findings indicate that these 
processes did not change the response rate of lung can-</p>

<p>cer to chemotherapy. A literature review reveals that some 
CBC parameters may act as potentially useful biomarkers 
of tumour response to chemotherapy and patient surviv-
al. However, as this is a retrospective study with a limited 
population size, further prospective studies are warranted. </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>





<p>A retrospective evaluation of associations between chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, smoking, and efficacy of chemotherapy 
and selected laboratory parameters in patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancer </p>



<p>Address for correspondence </p>

<p>Rafał Czyżykowski 
Chemotherapy Department 
Mikołaja Kopernika Memorial Hospital in Lodz 
Medical University of Lodz 
Pabianicka 62 
93-513 Lodz, Poland 
e-mail: rafal.czyzykowski@wp.pl </p>

<p>Submitted: 30.04.2015 
Accepted: 22.06.2016 </p>

</text></tei>