<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5037241" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Depression and bipolar illness are associated with a 2-3 fold </p>

<p>increase in the prevalence of diabetes. However, it is unknown whether variation in </p>

<p>mood affects glucose metabolism. The aim of this study was to assess whether 
changes in affect were related to fasting plasma glucose and glycated haemoglobin. 
Methods: 379 men and 441 women who took part in the 2003 Health Survey for </p>

<p>England and had valid data for GHQ12 and fasting blood glucose were included. 
Mood variability was assessed by the General Health Questionnaire 12 (GHQ12). </p>

<p>Fasting plasma glucose and glycated haemoglobin (HbA 1c ) were measured by 
standard laboratory methodology and their relationship to variability assessed </p>

<p>using linear regression. 
Results: There was a significant inverse relationship between fasting blood </p>

<p>glucose, but not HbA 1c , and variability score (R 
2 = 0.327, p = 0.02) after adjusting </p>

<p>for sociodemographic factors, anthropometric measurements, lifestyle, and use of 
medication. 
Conclusion: This study has shown an inverse association between changes in </p>

<p>affect and fasting plasma glucose. This unexpected finding suggests that the </p>

<p>association between affect and glucose is more complex than previously thought. </p>

<p>Fasting blood glucose may reflect the operation of homeostatic mechanisms that 
are disturbed in certain mental states and are associated, therefore, with altered risk </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>of diabetes and related metabolic conditions. This may have implications for the </p>

<p>management of those with such conditions and with mental disorders. </p>

<p>The prevalence of depression and depressive symptoms is approximately two-fold 
higher in people with diabetes while epidemiological studies have demonstrated </p>

<p>that this association is bi-directional (Holt et al., 2014). A meta-analysis of 11 
studies found that adults with depression had a 37% increased risk of developing </p>

<p>type 2 diabetes (Knol et al., 2006) while two further meta-analyses indicated that </p>

<p>incident depression was increased by 15-24% in people with diabetes (Mezuk  et al., 2008; Nouwen et al., 2010). The mechanisms and pathogenesis underlying </p>

<p>the association are unclear but a variety of explanatory theoretical models have 
been proposed, including a psychological response to the diagnosis and treatment </p>

<p>demands, common biological and environmental pathways and possible treatment </p>

<p>effects. </p>

<p>Variability of mood which leads to mood instability ("lability") is an important and </p>

<p>clinically significant symptom (Marwaha et al., 2013). For example, studies 
suggest that there is greater positive affect during the day and greater diurnal mood </p>

<p>variation in negative affect in people with major depression compared to matched 
controls (Marwaha et al., 2013). Mood instability, when assessed by the question 
"Do you have a lot of sudden mood changes?", increased the odds of experiencing </p>

<p>non-psychotic symptoms by nearly 10 fold (Marwaha et al., 2013). Lability or 
mood instability is also associated with a number of psychiatric conditions </p>

<p>including attention deficit disorders (Stringaris and Goodman, 2008; Marwaha  et al., 2013), borderline personality disorder and bipolar disorder (Marwaha et al.,   2014), and major depression (Marwaha et al., 2013). </p>

<p>Few studies have examined variability of mood in relation to glucose metabolism. </p>

<p>Kotani et al. (2007) found a significant positive relationship between "mood </p>

<p>change tendency" and fasting blood glucose in a group of healthy people. Skaff  et al. (2009) looked at the daily emotional "ups and downs" in a group of </p>

<p>participants with type 2 diabetes. After adjusting for sociodemographic 
characteristics, BMI, time with diabetes, medicines and indices of depression, </p>

<p>they found that, in men, when negative affect was greater than the individual's own 
average level on one day, the fasting glucose was higher than the mean value the </p>

<p>next morning. </p>

<p>The aim of the present study was to examine the relationship between mood </p>

<p>variability, assessed using the GHQ12 (Goldberg and Williams, 1988), and fasting </p>

<p>blood glucose in a general population sample in which it was possible to control for </p>

<p>Article No~e00160 </p>

<p>2 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2016.e00160 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2016 Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>potential confounders. As mood variability predisposes to depression and a number </p>

<p>of other psychiatric illnesses which are associated with increased rates of diabetes, 
we hypothesised that mood variability would be associated with increased glucose </p>

<p>concentration. </p>

<p>2. Method </p>

<p>2.1. Participants </p>

<p>The Health Survey for England is a national survey carried out each year on a fresh 
sample of the population of England living in private households. The sample is </p>

<p>chosen using a stratified, random sampling technique and is representative of the </p>

<p>population from which it is drawn. Since 1993 it has included participants aged 2 
years upwards, and in 2003 there were 14,836 participants who were aged 16 or </p>

<p>over (mean age 46 yrs: see Table 1). 6602 were men and 8234 were women. 
Ethical approval for the Survey was granted by the London Multi-Centre Research </p>

<p>Ethics Committee (MREC) and informed consent obtained from all participants, </p>

<p>which in the case of blood samples was in writing (Sproston and Primatesta, 2004). </p>

<p>2.2. Measures </p>

<p>The 2003 Survey focused on cardiovascular disease and its risk factors, and </p>

<p>included the General Health Questionnaire (GHQ12) as well as questions on 
smoking, alcohol intake, diet and physical activity, relevant medical history and </p>

<p>medication (Sproston and Primatesta, 2004). The questionnaires, including the </p>

<p>GHQ12, were administered during an initial interview. </p>

<p>2.2.1. Lifestyle questions </p>

<p>Alcohol consumption was assessed by answers to the question "Whether drinks </p>

<p>nowadays", smoking by answers to the question "Whether smokes cigarettes 
nowadays", dietary salt intake by answers to the question "Salt added when </p>

<p>cooking?" and consumption of cakes, chocolates, crisps, nuts or biscuits by </p>

<p>answers to questions "How often eat cakes?" and "How often eat chocolate, crisps 
or biscuits?". </p>

<p>Fruit and vegetable intake was assessed by portions of fruit (including orange 
juice) and vegetables yesterday. Physical activity level was coded as low, medium </p>

<p>or high depending on the responses to questions about specific forms of physical 
activity-including sports, walking, manual work, and housework. </p>

<p>2.2.2. GHQ12 questionnaire </p>

<p>The GHQ12 questionnaire was completed by all those aged 13 years and above. </p>

<p>The GHQ12 is intended to detect possible mental illness in the general population </p>

<p>Article No~e00160 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2016.e00160 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2016 Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Table 1. Comparing gender, age and prevalence of doctor-diagnosed diabetes amongst those with valid values of fasting glucose, HbA 1c and variability of </p>

<p>mood with the total sample aged 35 (or 16) and over in the 2003 Health Survey for England. </p>

<p>35 and over with valid values for GHQ12 and fasting glucose All 35 and over 16 and over with valid values for GHQ12 and HbA 1c All 16 and over </p>

<p>% Males 
46% 
44% 
46% 
45% </p>

<p>Mean age 
55 yrs 
56 yrs 
49 yrs 
49 yrs </p>

<p>% with doctor-diagnosed diabetes 3.0% 
5.4% 
3.4% 
4.1% </p>

<p>n 
820 
10,890 
7872 
14,836 </p>

<p>Article No~e00160 </p>





<p>(Goldberg and Williams, 1988), and within community or non-psychiatric clinical </p>

<p>settings such as primary care or general medical out-patients. </p>

<p>There are six "negative" questions with responses ranging from "Not at all", "No </p>

<p>more than usual;" "Rather more than usual" to "Much more than usual". The 
GHQ12 also includes "positive" questions, with possible responses including 
"Better than usual", "Same as usual", "Less than usual", and "Much less than </p>

<p>usual". In conventional scoring methods, the first two answers to positive questions </p>

<p>are usually collapsed so that improvements in positive affect do not contribute to </p>

<p>the score (cf. Huppert and Whittington, 2003; Ploubidis et al., 2007). </p>

<p>The GHQ was originally developed on the premise that it focused on breaks in </p>

<p>normal function rather than on lifetime traits and therefore may underestimate the 
prevalence of chronic illness (Goodchild and Duncan-Jones, 1985). We used the </p>

<p>measures of change in normal function to our advantage. In order to assess 
variability in mood, any participant who responded "Rather more than usual" or 
"Much more than usual" to one of the negative items received a score of "1" for </p>

<p>that question. If they responded "Better than usual", "Less than usual", or "Much 
less than usual" to one of the positive questions they received a score of 1 for that </p>

<p>question. </p>

<p>We considered using a scale of 0, 1 and 2 to differentiate the size of the change but </p>

<p>this would have incorrectly implied that the categories were equidistant from one 
another (e.g. that the difference between "Rather more than usual" and "Much </p>

<p>more than usual" was the same as that between "Rather more than usual" and "No </p>

<p>more than usual"), and so we chose a simple bimodal scale of 0 or 1 instead. </p>

<p>Scores thus reflected change whether in response to a negative question or a </p>

<p>positive one, and in the case of the latter regardless of whether it represented an 
increase or a decrease of positive affect. The total change score was defined as 
"variability" and any participant could obtain a score of between 0 and 12. </p>

<p>2.2.3. Anthropometry and blood test </p>

<p>A number of anthropometric measurements were also taken, including weight, </p>

<p>height and waist and hip circumference to calculate the waist-hip ratio. </p>

<p>A blood sample for HbA 1c was obtained from those aged 16 years or above at a </p>

<p>second, nurse visit. A fasting blood glucose sample was also taken in those aged 35 
years or above by a nurse. The average interval between the interviewer visit, at </p>

<p>which the self-completion booklet containing the GHQ12 was administered, and </p>

<p>the nurse visit at which the fasting blood sample was taken was 31 ± 24 days. </p>

<p>Article No~e00160 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2016.e00160 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2016 Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>2.3. Statistics </p>

<p>Data are reported as mean ± SD. The data were analysed with <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> Statistics </p>

<p>19 using a linear regression analysis in which fasting plasma glucose was the </p>

<p>dependent variable and variability of mood the independent variable. The 
regression was then repeated with the following additional variables included as </p>

<p>covariates: </p>

<p>• Age </p>

<p>• Gender </p>

<p>• Medication for central nervous system (CNS), cardiovascular or endocrine </p>

<p>disease </p>

<p>• Alcohol </p>

<p>• Smoking </p>

<p>• Diet </p>

<p>○ Addition of salt to cooking </p>

<p>○ Consumption of cakes, chocolate, crisps, nuts or biscuits </p>

<p>○ Fruit and vegetables intake </p>

<p>○ Fat intake </p>

<p>• Physical activity </p>

<p>• Waist-hip ratio </p>

<p>• Doctor diagnosed diabetes (excluding gestational diabetes) </p>

<p>A separate regression analysis was carried out with mood variability as the </p>

<p>independent variable and HbA 1c as the dependent variable, restricting the analysis 
to those aged 16 or over as HbA 1c was only carried out on those in this age range. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Participant characteristics </p>

<p>854 participants had valid fasting blood glucose measurements (5.2 ± 1.0 mmol/L 
range: 3.0-17.5 mmol/L). 14,490 participants had valid values for mood variability </p>

<p>(1.7 ± 2.5, range 0-12). </p>

<p>There were 379 men and 441 women for whom data were available for both </p>

<p>GHQ12 and fasting blood glucose (Age: 55.1 ± 13.0 yrs; range: 35-89). Table 1 
below compares this sample with the overall sample of those aged 35 or over in the </p>

<p>2003 Health Survey. </p>

<p>8199 participants had valid HbA 1c measurements (mean ± SD = 5.3% ± 0.7%; 34 </p>

<p>mmol/mol. ± 8 mmol/mol). 3614 men and 4258 women had valid values for both </p>

<p>GHQ12 and HbA 1c (Age: 49.25 ±17.1 yrs; range:16-98). </p>

<p>Article No~e00160 </p>

<p>6 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2016.e00160 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2016 Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Table 1 shows how this sample compares with the overall sample of those aged 16 </p>

<p>or over in the 2003 Health Survey. </p>

<p>3.2. Relationship between fasting glucose, HbA 1c and variability 
score </p>

<p>There was a significant inverse relationship between fasting blood glucose and </p>

<p>variability score (p = 0.013; t = −2.477; R = 0.086; R square = 0.007) in the 
bivariate analysis. </p>

<p>In the multivariate analysis, age and a diagnosis of diabetes were significantly 
related to fasting glucose (age: p = 0.001; doctor diagnosed diabetes: p &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>The association between mood variability and fasting glucose remained after 
adjustment for all covariates (p = 0.02; R square = 0.327) (Table 2). </p>

<p>By contrast there was no significant association between variability of mood and 
HbA 1c. </p>

<p>Table 2. Ordinary least squares (OLS) regression of fasting blood glucose on </p>

<p>mood variability and potential confounders (* p &lt; 0.05; ** p &lt; 0.01). </p>

<p>Explanatory variables 
Coefficients 
Standard 
errors </p>

<p>Mood variability 
-0.033* 
0.014 </p>

<p>Age 
0.011** 
0.003 </p>

<p>Gender 
0.100 
0.093 </p>

<p>Taking CNS medicine 
-0.075 
0.098 </p>

<p>Taking cardiovascular medicine 
0.110 
0.092 </p>

<p>Taking endocrine medicine 
-0.007 
0.114 </p>

<p>Doctor diagnosed diabetes 
-2.329** 
0.211 </p>

<p>Drink alcohol 
-0.220 
0.118 </p>

<p>Current smoker 
-0.010 
0.082 </p>

<p>Salt added in cooking 
-0.020 
0.069 </p>

<p>Cakes often eaten 
0.061 
0.040 </p>

<p>Chocolate, crisps, nuts or biscuits often eaten 
0.017 
0.039 </p>

<p>Portions of fruit and vegetables eaten the previous day 
0.003 
0.016 </p>

<p>Fat intake score 
0.008 
0.005 </p>

<p>Physical activity level 
-0.002 
0.046 </p>

<p>Waist/hip ratio 
1.088 
0.570 </p>

<p>Constant 
7.854 
0.818 </p>

<p>Adjusted r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.306 </p>

<p>F(16,503) 
15.277** </p>

<p>Article No~e00160 </p>

<p>7 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2016.e00160 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2016 Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>Although set up primarily to monitor the health of the country (Gupta, 1994), the </p>

<p>Health Survey for England also has considerable potential to be used as a research </p>

<p>tool. This afforded us the opportunity to examine a general population sample, 
representative of those living in private households in England in 2003. Amongst </p>

<p>this group, contrary to our initial hypothesis, there was a significant inverse 
relationship between mood change scores (variability) and subsequent fasting </p>

<p>blood glucose. By contrast, there was no relationship between variability and </p>

<p>HbA 1c which reflects the average plasma glucose concentration over a longer 
period of 6-8 weeks, as opposed to fasting glucose, which largely reflects hepatic </p>

<p>glucose output. </p>

<p>Variability of mood to a degree that leads to mood instability ("lability") is an </p>

<p>important and common clinically significant symptom. The present study used the 
12 item GHQ12 questionnaire which has been shown to be valid and reliable in </p>

<p>many different countries and cultures (e.g. see Piccinelli et al., 1993). The scoring </p>

<p>method used in this study has not, to our knowledge, been used in this way before 
but the method has face and construct validity. However, further research will be </p>

<p>needed to determine whether mood variability as assessed in this way is a stable, 
enduring trait, and also to replicate the findings of the present study. </p>

<p>In the light of the associations between type 2 diabetes and psychiatric disorder, we 
had hypothesised that increased variability of mood (which may be a marker of </p>

<p>increased emotional/behavioural reactivity and a predictor of psychiatric illness) </p>

<p>would be associated with increased fasting plasma glucose. We were therefore 
surprised to find the opposite. However, this finding is not unprecedented. For </p>

<p>example, a US study (Golden et al., 2008) found evidence that obesity and insulin 
resistance might be associated with a lower risk of developing depression and they </p>

<p>confirmed that individuals with impaired fasting glucose had a reduced risk of </p>

<p>incident depressive symptoms. On the other hand, a later paper from the Whitehall 
Study (Kivimaki et al., 2009) found a U-shaped association between fasting </p>

<p>glucose and depression with the lowest depression risk seen among those in the 
normoglycemic range of HbA 1c . </p>

<p>Possible explanations for the observed paradoxical inverse association between 
variability of mood and diabetes risk emerge when one considers the literature on </p>

<p>atypical depression. People with bipolar disorder show greater short-term mood </p>

<p>fluctuations when depressed than people with unipolar depression (e.g. Aheam and  Carroll, 1996), while nearly three quarters of people with atypical major depression </p>

<p>meet the criteria for bipolar disorders (Perugi et al., 1998). Thus, atypical depression 
appears to be associated with more labile and reactive mood. Atypical depression is </p>

<p>associated with hypoactivity of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis, low </p>

<p>Article No~e00160 </p>

<p>8 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2016.e00160 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2016 Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>cortisol concentration, less CRF, and reduced activation of noradrenergic pathways </p>

<p>(Juruena and Cleare 2007; Lamers et al., 2013). </p>

<p>Another study of glucose disposal in depression showed that people with atypical </p>

<p>depression had lower sympathoadrenal responses and higher insulin concentrations 
than healthy controls (Schweiger et al., 2008). Reduced sympathetic nervous </p>

<p>system responsiveness and hyperinsulinaemia could lead to lower fasting blood 
glucose levels. Schweiger et al. (2008) suggest that overeating (a feature of </p>

<p>atypical depression) may be a way of maintaining an adequate supply of glucose to </p>

<p>the brain and that changes in eating behaviour in depression are secondary to 
alterations in brain glucose metabolism and glucose allocation. This has been </p>

<p>found to be associated with abnormalities of cortisol regulation at certain points of 
the day (Thorn et al., 2011), and the diurnal physiology and metabolism of both </p>

<p>blood pressure and blood glucose are known to be under the influence of circadian </p>

<p>clocks (Singh et al., 2016). </p>

<p>Lability of mood may reflect the emotional reactivity of the individual to </p>

<p>psychosocial stress. It has features in common with atypical depression and it is 
possible that it may also be associated with reduced activity of the HPA axis and/or </p>

<p>of noradrenergic pathways. These in turn are involved in homeostatic mechanisms 
which come into operation in the fasting state in response to physiological stress. </p>

<p>Insensitivity of such biological mechanisms could lead to lower levels of fasting </p>

<p>glucose and hence explain the inverse relationship between the latter and 
variability of mood. HbA 1c , on the other hand, reflects average plasma glucose </p>

<p>concentration over a longer period, rather than the short term response to the 
withdrawal of food, and this may explain why there is no association with </p>

<p>variability of mood. </p>

<p>The present study does not permit conclusions about the direction of any causative </p>

<p>pathway between mood variability and low fasting glucose. Nevertheless, it is </p>

<p>interesting that Yehuda et al. (1990) found that the mean cortisol level in a post-
traumatic stress disorder group was significantly lower, and the range narrower, </p>

<p>than that observed in healthy volunteers (cf. Meewisse et al., 2007). They suggest 
that this is due to physiological adaptation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal </p>

<p>axis to chronic stress. It is possible, therefore, that increased emotional reactivity </p>

<p>results in repeated activation of the HPA axis and the sympathetic nervous system 
which eventually leads to a state of physiological decompensation. The related </p>

<p>atypical depression may be initially associated with lower levels of fasting glucose, 
but hyperphagia, inactivity and possibly reduced cortisol may over time lead to </p>

<p>increased BMI, waist-hip ratio and inflammation (Lamers et al., 2013), which in 
turn could result in insulin resistance and type 2 diabetes. Thus, whilst elevated </p>

<p>levels of catecholamines and cortisol may cause damage to the cardio-and </p>

<p>Article No~e00160 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2016.e00160 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2016 Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>cerebro-vascular system (Singh et al., 2012), abnormally low levels may also have </p>

<p>pathological effects in the long term. </p>

<p>There are a number of limitations to the study. In the interests of confidentiality, </p>

<p>the GHQ is self-administered rather than by a trained interviewer, and does not 
specifically ask about mood, though many of the questions are related to mood and </p>

<p>we used it as a proxy measure of mood variability. The association between the 
latter and fasting glucose is small in real terms (and based on low numbers </p>

<p>compared with those for HbA 1c ). This may be because a general population sample </p>

<p>was used, and a stronger relationship might emerge in clinical populations (with 
the caveat, that the relationships in clinical populations may not necessarily be the </p>

<p>same as in non-clinical ones). The relationship is cross-sectional. Longitudinal 
studies could clarify the relationship. A further limitation is that fasting glucose </p>

<p>was not measured at the same time as mood variability; however, this might also be </p>

<p>considered a strength because it suggests that the relationship may not simply 
result from the direct impact of low glucose on mood (or vice versa), but rather </p>

<p>both may be due to common underlying mechanisms. Glucose was measured at 
just one point in time when in fact there is also evidence for disorders which relate </p>

<p>to the extent of variability of glucose (Singh et al., 2014). Some of the covariates </p>

<p>(e.g. dietary measures) were based on self-report and it is conceivable, therefore, 
that they, or other variables, may have produced residual confounding of the </p>

<p>results. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>There is evidence from this study that variability of mood is associated with lower 
fasting glucose. There is considerable evidence for an association of psychiatric </p>

<p>morbidity and metabolic disorders, and the results of this study may shed light on </p>

<p>the relationship between them, and the mechanisms underlying these associations. </p>

<p>Declarations </p>

<p>Author contribution statement </p>

<p>Sunjai Gupta: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experi-</p>

<p>ments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis 
tools or data; Wrote the paper. </p>

<p>Robert Anderson: Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; 
Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper. </p>

<p>Richard IG Holt: Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper. </p>

<p>Article No~e00160 </p>

<p>10 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2016.e00160 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2016 Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Funding statement </p>

<p>This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the </p>

<p>public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors. </p>

<p>Competing interest statement </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Data associated with this study can be accessed at https://discover.ukdataservice. </p>

<p>ac.uk/catalogue/?sn=5098 </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Health Survey 2003 data: Copyright 
© 2003, Re-used with the permission of The </p>

<p>Health and Social Care Information Centre. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>The authors are grateful to Allan Young, Andrew Pickles, Nick Di Paolo and to </p>

<p>members of Public Health England and the Department of Health (England) for 
their comments on an earlier version of this paper. </p>



<p> </p>

<p>
 </p>

<p>
Article No~e00160 </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2016.e00160 </p>

<p>2405-8440/© 2016 Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license </p>

<p>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

</text></tei>