<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5088916" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Liver biopsy is an invasive procedure that is currently still necessary for predicting underlying hepatic injury related 
to chronic viral hepatitis B (CVHB). To date, none of the studied non-invasive methods have been able to replace liver biopsy. An 
apoptotic serum marker, M30, which has been reported to indicate ongoing liver fibrosis, has been popular in recent years. </p>

<p>Objectives: We aimed to investigate the possible role of M30 in predicting CVHB-associated hepatic injury and its severity. 
Methods: Forty-eight patients undergoing liver biopsy for evaluation of the severity of CVHB-related liver injury and 40 healthy 
controls were included in this cross-sectional study. M30 levels were determined for all CVHB patients and controls, and other lab-
oratory parameters and demographic features were obtained from our hospital's database. </p>

<p>Results: The mean ages of patients and controls were 39.7 and 45.7 years, respectively, and 35% of the controls and 52% of the patients 
were male. In contrast to lower platelet counts, transaminase and M30 levels were both higher in the patient group than in the 
controls. Among the investigated parameters, only transaminase increased as the fibrosis stage changed from mild to moderate; 
however, none of the laboratory parameters, including M30, differed as the histological activity index (HAI) score increased. </p>

<p>Conclusions: M30 levels were higher in CVHB patients compared to healthy controls. However, M30 levels were similar in the mild 
and moderate stages of fibrosis, so they did not indicate the severity of underlying fibrotic or inflammatory processes in CVHB 
patients. </p>

<p>Keywords: M30, Chronic Hepatitis B, Liver Fibrosis </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>Chronic viral hepatitis B (CVHB) remains a common 
health problem throughout the world. In recent years, due 
to increased information about the transmission of hepati-
tis B virus (HBV) and the application of precautions, such 
as routine HBV vaccination programs, HBV prevalence has 
been declining (1, 2). However, with increasing life ex-
pectancy, the use of antiviral medications is prolonged and 
therefore drug resistance is increasing. This is an emerging 
problem in the field of chronic liver disease. 
Liver biopsy is still necessary for predicting underly-
ing HBV-related liver injury and for deciding whether to 
initiate antiviral medication (3). Liver biopsy is an inva-
sive procedure with certain risks, which forces investiga-
tors to focus on non-invasive methods to replace percuta-
neous biopsy (4). Assessing liver stiffness with ultrasound 
and measuring serum biomarkers are inadequate for de-
termining the severity of liver fibrosis or for grading the </p>

<p>inflammatory process in the liver. </p>

<p>The programmed cell death of apoptosis is a protective 
mechanism in infected hepatocytes, not only to prevent 
spread of the virus to other hepatocytes and to control vi-
ral replication (5), but also to decrease pro-inflammatory 
cytokine release from injured hepatocytes (6). Upregula-
tion of apoptosis has been shown to have a critical role in 
inducing inflammation and fibrogenesis in the liver. The 
amount of cytokeratin-18 fragments cleaved by caspases 
during apoptosis seems to be a good marker of apoptosis 
(7), and can easily be measured with a sandwich ELISA tech-
nique (M30-based ELISA) (8). M30 determines the degree 
of apoptotic cells in epithelial organs and tissues. Serum 
M30 levels were higher in chronic HBV patients compared 
to healthy controls, and M30 levels were able to be used 
to discriminate mild from advanced liver fibrosis (9, 10). 
In addition, Giannousis et al. showed a decrease in serum 
M30 levels after six months of antiviral therapy (11). </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016, Kowsar Corp. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial usages, provided the original work is properly 
cited. </p>

<p>Yilmaz B et al. </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>The aim of this study was to investigate the utility of 
serum M30 levels in predicting the hepatic fibrosis stage 
in CVHB patients. </p>

<p>3. Methods </p>

<p>Forty patients admitted to our clinic between January 
and December 2011, who underwent liver biopsy with a di-
agnosis of CHB, were included in this cross-sectional study. 
The inclusion criterion was age over 18 years. The exclu-
sion criteria were co-infection with hepatitis C virus or 
human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), alcohol abuse (40 
g/day for men and 20 g/day for women), biopsy-proven 
non-alcoholic steatohepatitis, or any immunological liver 
disease. The decision to perform liver biopsy was based on 
the EASL HBV guidelines (3). Approval for the study was 
granted by the local clinical research ethics committee, 
and informed consent was obtained from each patient. 
The baseline characteristics of the patients and their 
laboratory results, including alanine aminotransferase 
(ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), platelet count, 
and HBV DNA, were collected from the computerized hos-
pital database. Blood samples were obtained from the pa-
tients after informed consent on the same day as the liver 
biopsy, and were stored at -80°C until the procedure was 
completed. M30 values were measured using an M30 ELISA 
kit (Peviva; Bromma, Sweden) according to the manufac-
turer's recommendations. 
The severity of fibrosis was assessed as mild (F0 and F1), 
moderate (F2 and F3), or advanced (F4 and F5), and the his-
tological activity index (HAI) was classified as mild (1 -5), 
moderate (6 -8), or severe (9 -12). 
Forty healthy controls were also included in the study 
for comparison with the patient group's laboratory param-
eters, including M30, ALT, AST, and platelet count. All of the 
controls completed a questionnaire to determine whether 
they had any chronic illness that could affect the results, 
and digital data from our hospital were used to evaluate 
the presence of chronic hepatitis and possible etiologic fac-
tors, such as viral hepatitis or HIV. 
The statistical package for the social sciences (<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> soft-
ware <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 17.0</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) was used for 
all statistical analyses. Baseline demographic values were 
calculated with the Kruskal-Wallis test, then the post-hoc 
test was performed. The continuous variables were sum-</p>

<p>marized as mean ± standard deviation (SD), or minimum </p>

<p>(min) and maximum (max) for certain categorized values. 
Correlation analyses were done with Pearson's correlation 
test. P values of &lt; 0.05 were accepted as statistically signif-
icant. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>Twenty-five (52%) of the CVHB patients were male, and 
their mean age was 45.7 years, which were both higher 
than in the controls (Table 1). Five of these patients (10%) 
were HBeAg-positive and the remainder were negative. 
Baseline laboratory evaluations revealed that the CVHB 
patients had higher ALT, AST, and M30 levels and lower 
platelet counts compared to the controls. 
Mean age, duration of disease, and platelet count did 
not differ according to the severity of liver fibrosis (Table 
2). M30 levels were also similar in each group. However, 
AST and ALT levels were prominently increased in the mod-
erate group compared to the mild fibrosis group. In con-
trast, HBV DNA levels decreased as the severity of fibrosis 
increased (P = 0.007). 
Transaminase level, HBV DNA level, platelet count, 
mean age, and duration of disease were all similar among 
the groups (Table 3). M30 levels were also the same in each 
group in terms of HAI. 
The correlation analysis revealed a weak correlation be-
tween M30 and HBV DNA levels (r = 0.354, P = 0.013), but 
no correlation was observed among ALT and AST values (r 
= 0.270, P = 061 and r = 0.244, P = 0.92; respectively). </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>The main target of antiviral medication therapy 
against HBV is the prevention of HBV-related morbidities, 
which are mainly liver insufficiency and hepatocellular 
carcinoma (3). Since recent studies have shown a corre-
lation between HBV DNA and HBV-associated disorders, 
monitoring the HBV DNA load has become a crucial part 
of HBV therapy. However, apart from monitoring the HBV 
DNA viral load and transaminase levels, there are no other 
serological markers for predicting the severity of ongoing 
inflammatory or fibrotic processes. However, some stud-
ies of non-invasive markers for predicting the severity of 
liver fibrosis are available in the medical literature (12-15). 
Unfortunately, none of these parameters reflect the real 
status of the liver, which is only possible with liver biopsy. 
Apoptosis, programmed cell death, is crucial when it 
becomes dysregulated in chronic hepatitis, such as in vi-
ral hepatitis, alcoholic and non-alcoholic steatohepatitis, 
cholestatic processes, and Wilson's disease (16-19). The in-
crease of apoptotic cells results in cytokine secretion, lead-
ing to induction of inflammatory and fibrotic processes 
(Figure 1) (6). Downstream from the cell-death receptor, 
the proteolytic cascade leads to activation of caspases 3, 6, 
and 7 (16, 20). The activation of caspases may be related </p>

<p> 
Hepat Mon. 2016; 16(9):e35640. </p>

<p>Yilmaz B et al. </p>

<p>Table 1. Comparison of Baseline Characteristics of CHBV Patients and Healthy Controls </p>

<p>Control Group (n = 40) 
Patient Group (n = 48) 
P Value </p>

<p>Age, y, mean (min -max) 
39.7 (20 -79) 
45.7 (20 -71) 
0.003 </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Male 
14 
25 </p>

<p>Female 
26 
23 
0.041 </p>

<p>ALT, U/L (min -max) 
18.4 (7 -46) 
57.0 (10 -401) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>AST, U/L (min -max) 
19.5 (8 -36) 
42.7 (6 -255) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Platelets/mm 3 (min -max) 
252.5 (149-366) 
193.574 (28.000-455.000) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>M30, U/L (min -max) 
135.6 (79.2-254.2) 
154.1 (92.84-278.9) 
0.017 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase. </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of M30 Levels and Other Parameters According to Severity of Liver Fibrosis </p>

<p>Severity of Fibrosis 
Mild (n = 21) 
Moderate (n = 26) 
P Value* </p>

<p>Age, y, mean (min -max) 
43.8 (25 -60) 
47.0 (20 -71) 
0.298 </p>

<p>Duration of disease, y, mean (min -max) 
4.8 (1 -16) 
7.1 (1 -23) 
0.518 </p>

<p>HBV DNA, U/L, mean (min -max) 
974,530 (2,690 -18,900,000) 
12,930,000 (2,756 -59,800,000) 
0.007 </p>

<p>ALT, U/L, mean (min -max) 
33.7 (15 -121) 
75.0 (10 -401) 
0.019 </p>

<p>AST, U/L, mean (min -max) 
27.1 (15 -72) 
54.1 (6 -255) 
0.006 </p>

<p>Platelets/mm 3 , mean (min -max) 
191,950 (28,000 -362,000) 
193,850 (111,000 -455,000) 
0.470 </p>

<p>M30, U/L, mean (min -max) 
149,600 (92.8 -278.9) 
157,900 (93.4 -261.1) 
0.811 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase. </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparison of M30 Levels and Other Parameters According to Degree of HAI in the Liver </p>

<p>Severity of HAI 
Mild (n = 20) 
Moderate (n = 23) 
P Value* </p>

<p>Age, y, mean (min.-max.) 
45.9 (25 -71) 
45.5 (20,66) 
0.713 </p>

<p>Duration of disease, y, mean (min -max) 
6.1 (1 -16) 
5.2 (1 -11) 
0.386 </p>

<p>HBV DNA, U/L, mean (min -max) 
20,000,000 (2,756 -59,800,000) 
1,214,114 (2,690 -15,800,000) 
0.072 </p>

<p>ALT, U/L, mean (min -max) 
49.5 (15 -121) 
52.0 (10 -178) 
0.200 </p>

<p>AST, U/L, mean (min -max) 
35.7 (6 -72) 
39.7 (15 -97) 
0.059 </p>

<p>Platelets/mm 3 mean (min -max) 
187,900 (28,000 -255,000) 
203,340 (114,000 -455,000) 
0.715 </p>

<p>M30, U/L, mean (min -max) 
159.5 (103.7 -278.9) 
149.6 (92.8 -246.4) 
0.674 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: HAI, histological activity index; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase. </p>

<p>to mitochondrial dysfunction, leading to cytochrome c re-
lease or direct cleavage (20, 21). The susceptibility to apop-
totic cell death may depend on the HBV genotype, as well 
(22). Not only apoptotic cell death, but also autophagic 
cell death, may be good predictors for defining the level of 
liver injury at the beginning of treatment and during the 
follow-up period (23). </p>

<p>Similar to our results, M30 levels in the healthy popu-</p>

<p>lation were found to be lower than in CHB patients (6, 10, 
18, 23). As expected, Eren et al. found similar M30 values 
in healthy controls and inactive CHB carriers (10). Higher 
M30 values in CHB patients compared to healthy individu-
als is understandable, due to ongoing liver inflammation. </p>

<p>Serum M30 levels were found to be significantly higher 
in chronic HBV patients compared to healthy subjects 
(10, 18, 23). Moreover, one study found that M30 values </p>

<p>Hepat Mon. 2016; 16(9):e35640. 
3 </p>

<p>Yilmaz B et al. </p>

<p>Chronic Liver Injury </p>

<p>Death Receptor Activation ( Fas/ CD 95, TRAIL I-II, TNF RI) </p>

<p>Caspases 8, 10 </p>

<p>Caspases 3, 6, 7 </p>

<p>Apoptoticell Death; 
Moderate, But Long Term </p>

<p>Cytochromc </p>

<p>Mytochondrial Dysfunction </p>

<p>Figure 1. Chronic Liver Injury Triggers Death Receptors, Leading to Apoptotic Cell Death </p>

<p>increased with increasing severity of liver fibrosis, and 
reached their highest level in cirrhotic patients (23). How-
ever, the role of apoptotic markers for replacing liver 
biopsy in CHB patients and the utility of M30 levels for dis-
tinguishing inactive CHB carriers from CHB patients are 
still controversial. Papatheodoridis et al. gave a cut-off 
value of 240 U/L for predicting CHB with 60% sensitivity 
and 100% specificity (9). Rather than grading liver inflam-
mation, Joka et al. determined a cut-off value of 157.5 U/L 
for predicting mild fibrosis from significant fibrosis (≥ F2) 
in the liver (64% sensitivity and 61% specificity) (18). Differ-
entiating ongoing high-inflammation processes and high 
fibrosis scores in the liver is crucial for the initiation of an-
tiviral medication without requiring liver biopsy. Similar 
to Eren et al. and Joka et al., we were unable to identify any 
relationship between M30 values and the mild to moder-
ate stages of liver fibrosis (10, 18). </p>

<p>This was a cross-sectional study performed during a 
specific time period. Therefore, we could not find a suf-
ficient number HBV patients with advanced liver fibrosis. 
This was an important limitation of the current investiga-
tion. </p>

<p>The ALT-to-platelet ratio (the APRI index) and the FIB-4 
scores, which are based on ALT, AST, platelet count, and age 
of the patient, have been widely investigated. Although 
there were some promising results, large-scale database 
studies revealed that the APRI index and FIB-4 scores may 
not be adequate for predicting the severity of underlying 
liver disease in HBV patients (24, 25). Our results support 
the idea that the APRI index and FIB-4 scores are not corre-
lated with the severity of liver fibrosis (unpublished data). 
In conclusion, although M30 levels were higher in 
CVHB patients than in healthy controls, our results do not 
support the use of M30 levels for predicting the severity of 
underlying fibrotic or inflammatory processes in CHB pa-
tients. Further studies are necessary in order to clarify the 
role of apoptotic mechanisms in hepatic injury due to HBV, 
and to establish the utility of M30 in replacing liver biopsy. </p>

<p>Footnote </p>

<p>Authors' Contribution: Concept, Baris Yilmaz, Akif Alt-
inbas; design, Baris Yilmaz, Akif Altinbas; supervision, Za-
hide Simsek, Sahin Coban, Omer Basar, Osman Yuksel; re-</p>

<p> 
Hepat Mon. 2016; 16(9):e35640. </p>

<p>Yilmaz B et al. </p>

<p>sources, Baris Yilmaz, Akif Altinbas; materials, Baris Yil-
maz, Akif Altinbas; data collection and processing, Baris 
Yilmaz, Bora Aktas, Fuat Ekiz, Serta Kilincalp, Murat De-
veci; analysis and interpretation, Akif Altinbas, Zeynep Gi-
nis, Gulfer Ozturk; literature search: Baris Yilmaz, Akif Al-
tinbas; writing of the manuscript, Baris Yilmaz, Akif Altin-
bas; critical review, Akif Altinbas, Bora Aktas, Fuat Ekiz. </p>

<p> </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>