<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5132076" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>PURPOSE. A majority of genes associated with inherited retinal diseases (IRDs) have been 
identified in patients of European origin. Indigenous African populations exhibit rich genomic 
diversity, and evaluation of reported genetic mutations has yielded low returns so far. Our goal 
was to perform whole-exome sequencing (WES) to examine variants in known IRD genes in 
underrepresented African cohorts. </p>

<p>METHODS. Whole-exome sequencing was performed on 56 samples from 16 families with 
diverse IRD phenotypes that had remained undiagnosed after screening for known mutations 
using genotyping-based microarrays (Asper Ophthalmics). Variants in reported IRD genes 
were identified using WES and validated by Sanger sequencing. Custom TaqMan assays were 
used to screen for identified mutations in 193 unrelated indigenous Africans with IRDs. </p>

<p>RESULTS. A total of 3494 variants were identified in 217 known IRD genes, leading to the 
identification of seven different mutations (including six novel) in six genes (RHO, PRPF3, 
PRPF31, ABCA4, CERKL, and PDE6B) in six distinct families. TaqMan screening in additional 
probands revealed identical homozygous CERKL and PDE6B variants in four more patients. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS. This is the first report of WES of patients with IRDs in indigenous African 
populations. Our study identified genetic defects in almost 40% of the families analyzed, 
significantly enhancing the molecular diagnosis of IRD in South Africa. Thus, WES of 
understudied cohorts seems to present an effective strategy for determining novel mutations 
in heterogeneous retinal diseases. </p>

<p>identified for IRDs (https://sph.uth.edu/Retnet/sum-dis.htm; in 
the public domain). Recent studies using animal models have 
finally begun to uncover some of the underlying disease 
mechanisms and pathways that affect photoreceptor develop-
ment or function. 7-9 Furthermore, it is estimated that only 50% 
to 70% of the cases with RP (depending on geographical 
regions or populations) can be attributed to the known 
genes, 10-12 indicating that a considerable number of as yet 
unknown mutations and genes remain to be identified. Such a 
vast clinical and genetic heterogeneity displayed by IRDs 
confounds molecular diagnosis and investigation of the 
pathogenic mechanisms. 
Identification of the specific genetic defect in a patient with 
IRD affords several potential benefits. First, overlapping 
phenotypes and clinical variability of IRDs do not always 
permit a clear clinical (ophthalmologic) diagnosis/prognosis. 
Genetic analysis is unequivocal and provides clinical utility as 
diagnostic, predictive, and carrier testing can be offered to 
family members. Second, genetic tests may also influence the 
clinical management of the disease. The IRD research program 
in South Africa (SA), initiated in 1990, 13 has a strong 
translational and service component. 14 Lastly, the knowledge 
of precise genetic defects can allow development of gene-
based therapies for treatment of IRDs. 15 
The reported prevalence of IRDs is approximately 1 in 
3500 11 in populations where epidemiologic data are available. 
No data exist on the prevalence of IRDs in Africa. Nonetheless, 
using SA's 2011 population census (http://www.statssa.gov.za/; 
in the public domain), one may extrapolate that approximately 
14,500 individuals suffer from IRD-related visual impairment/ 
blindness in SA; of these (taking population demographics into 
account), as many as 11,600 are expected in the indigenous 
African population. However, a high frequency of unaffected 
carriers of IRD gene mutations could exist because of local 
founder effects and further elevate the potential burden of 
disease. 11 
Demographic information, biological material, clinical 
details, and diagnoses have been archived for 3237 individuals 
in 1430 SA families with distinct IRDs in the University of Cape 
Town (UCT) registry, which contains information and biolog-
ical material primarily from individuals of Caucasian origin; 
indigenous Africans currently comprise only 19% of the 
collection (n ¼ 275 families). Understandably, this does not 
reflect the population demographics of SA and is due to 
ascertainment bias and the lack of resources in rural areas 
where a large proportion of the indigenous populations reside. 
To date, 249 families (249/1430 ¼ 17%), mostly Caucasian (n ¼ 
204/249; 82%), are in diagnostic mode, with clear pathogenic 
mutations having been identified using a variety of methods. 16 
The most prevalent reported genetic defects in IRDs exhibit an 
almost insignificant incidence in the SA patient cohort. 17-20 
Investigation of the indigenous African subcohort for reported 
mutations through the use of Asper Ophthalmics microarrays 
(http://www.asperbio.com/asper-ophthalmics; in the public 
domain) has produced lower returns in the indigenous African 
IRD subcohort than in the Caucasian subcohort. Approximate-
ly 41.2% of Caucasian samples (n ¼ 279) have been diagnosed 
by microarray screening as opposed to only 12.8% of 
indigenous African samples (n ¼ 109) because each Asper 
Ophthalmics microarray specifically tests for reported muta-
tions that have been identified predominantly in patients of 
European/Caucasian origin. Novel mutations are detected only 
if they occur at a nucleotide position(s) where a mutation has 
already been reported, as only select nucleotides are assayed. 
Thus, either SA indigenous IRD patients harbor novel 
mutations in known genes that are not included in the Asper 
arrays or causative genes are novel. </p>

<p>The advent of next-generation sequencing technologies has 
revolutionized the speed and cost at which disease mutations 
can be identified. An increased number of mutations are now 
being identified in different populations using high-throughput 
methods such as whole-exome sequencing (WES). 21,22 Im-
proved molecular diagnosis in patients is important, given the 
number of clinical trials and treatments currently under 
investigation for this group of disorders. 23 We therefore 
resorted to a comprehensive WES approach, followed by 
targeted analysis of all reported IRD genes, toward understand-
ing the genetic architecture of IRD in the indigenous SA 
population. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patient Cohort </p>

<p>Informed consent was obtained according to the 2008 
Declaration of Helsinki for all members from whom samples 
have been archived in the UCT IRD registry. Ethics approval 
was granted by the Human Research Ethics Committee of the 
UCT Faculty of Health Sciences (Rec Ref. 226/2010 and 768/ 
2013). Samples from indigenous African families were selected 
from the registry if DNA was available from at least three family 
members and if a proband had been screened using the 
appropriate microarray but no molecular diagnosis had been 
obtained. A total of 16 families met the selection criteria, 
comprising 109 individuals; of these, 56 were chosen for WES. 
The selected 16 families originated from diverse, self-identified, 
indigenous African ethnolinguistic groups: 5 Xhosa, 3 Zulu, 2 
Tswana, 1 Shangaan, 1 Venda, 1 Tsonga/Ndebele, 1 Xhosa/ 
Sotho, and 2 Unknown. Two of the 16 families had been 
clinically diagnosed with autosomal recessive MD (one of 
whom had a subsequent diagnosis of Leber congenital 
amaurosis) and 14 with RP. </p>

<p>Whole-Exome Sequencing </p>

<p>Genomic DNA samples were quantified using the QuantiFluor 
dsDNA system (Promega, Madison, WI, USA), according to 
manufacturer's instructions. Whole-exome capture was per-
formed on 50 ng DNA using the Nextera Rapid Capture 
Expanded Exome kit (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA), and 125-
bp paired-end sequences were obtained on a HiSeq2500 
platform (Illumina), according to manufacturer's instructions. 
Details of WES analysis are described elsewhere. 24 <rs id="software-12" type="software">FastQC</rs> 
(available at <rs corresp="#software-12" type="url">http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/;</rs>/; in the public domain) was used to confirm 
quality of sequencing, after which adapter indexes were 
removed using <rs type="software">Trimmomatic</rs>. 25 Reads were mapped to the 
human reference sequence (hg19, GRCH37) using <rs type="software">BWA</rs>, 26 and 
<rs type="software">GATK</rs> 27,28 was used for variant calling, local realignment, base 
quality recalibration, and variant recalibration. Annotation of 
variants was performed with <rs type="software">ANNOVAR</rs>. 29 </p>

<p>Variant Prioritization and Validation </p>

<p>Sequence variants present in genes (Supplementary Table S1) 
listed on the RetNet database (https://sph.uth.edu/Retnet/sum-
dis.htm; in the public domain; accessed 12 November 2014) 
were extracted for further analysis. Variants with a minor allele 
frequency (MAF) of &lt;0.1 in the 1000 Genomes Project 30 
(October 2014 annotation) were prioritized, as were exonic or 
splicing variants. The variants were subsequently selected 
based on cosegregation with the disease phenotype within 
each family. For nonsynonymous variants, a minimum thresh-
old of three pathogenic predictions was applied to the 
dbNSFP 31 annotation of <rs type="software">ANNOVAR</rs>, for either of the following </p>

<p>Whole Exome Analysis of South African IRD Families 
IOVS j November 2016 j Vol. 57 j No. 14 j 6375 </p>

<p>predictor subsets: (<rs type="software">SIFT</rs>, <rs type="software">PolyPhen2-HDIV</rs>, <rs type="software">PolyPhen2-HVAR</rs>, 
<rs type="software">LRT</rs>, <rs type="software">MutationTaster</rs>, <rs type="software">MutationAssessor</rs>, <rs type="software">FATHMM</rs>, <rs type="software">MetaSVM</rs>, 
and <rs type="software">MetaLR</rs>), or (<rs type="software">VEST3</rs> <rs type="software">CADD-raw</rs>, <rs type="software">CADD-phred</rs>, GERPþþ, 
<rs type="software">phyloP46way-placental</rs>, <rs type="software">phyloP100way-vertebrate</rs> and <rs type="software">SiPhy-
29way-logOdds</rs>). Variants were then assessed for their pres-
ence in the remainder of the cohort. High-priority candidate 
variants were finally evaluated by examining RetNet and 
<rs id="software-28" type="software">Ensembl</rs> <rs corresp="#software-28" type="version-number">release 8</rs> 32 with particular emphasis on population 
data for 1000 Genomes African subpopulations and NHLBI 
Exome Sequencing data (http://evs.gs.washington.edu/EVS/; 
in the public domain) in African Americans, as well as reported 
phenotypes associated with the genes. 
Wherever possible, additional familial samples not subject-
ed to WES were included for validation of candidate variants by 
Sanger Sequencing on a 3130xl Genetic Analyzer (Applied 
Biosystems, ThermoFisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). 
Finally, validated variants were checked for MAF in the African 
Genomes Variation Project 33 data, which include low-coverage 
whole-genome sequences from 100 Bagandan of Uganda, 100 
Zulu of SA, and 120 Ethiopian individuals. </p>

<p>Screening of SA Cohort </p>

<p>Custom TaqMan assays (primer and reporter sequences in 
Supplementary Table S2) were designed to determine the allele 
frequency of seven variants identified by WES, in a larger 
cohort of 193 unrelated indigenous African probands with 
IRDs but no known causative mutation. In order to determine 
the optimal template concentration, two control samples were 
screened for each assay (including a positive control for each), 
at 8, 6, 4, 3, 2, and 1.5 ng/lL. It was empirically determined 
that 2 ng/lL was optimal, allowing for effective allele 
discrimination for each assay. 
The final volume in each assay reaction was 5 lL, composed 
of 2.5 lL TaqMan GT mastermix (23) (Applied Biosystems), 
0.25 lL assay mix (203), 2.25 lL DNA (at 2 ng/lL, that is, total 
input of 4.5-ng template). Each assay included at least two no-
template controls and two positive controls. Thermal cycling 
was performed using the ABI 7900HT instrument (Applied 
Biosystems) and the following conditions: 958C, 10 minutes; 
(958C, 15 seconds; 608C, 1 minute) 3 40 cycles. If fluorescence 
values dictated after this cycling, a second cycling of 103 
(958C, 15 seconds; 608C, 1 minute) cycles and subsequent 
postread analysis were performed. Sanger sequencing was used 
to validate all candidate variants. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Whole-exome sequencing was performed for 56 samples that 
included at least three individuals from each of the 16 families. 
On average, 92% of the exome was captured at 253 coverage, 
and a total of 1,816,031 variants were identified. We excluded 
intergenic (n ¼ 759,459), intronic (n ¼ 710,303), and 
synonymous (n ¼ 59,723) variants from further analysis and 
identified 3494 candidate variants in 217 reported IRD genes. 
We then filtered out variants that were present upstream or 
downstream (n ¼ 298) of the coding exons, in the 5 0 or 3 0 
untranslated region (n ¼ 1813), or in the noncoding RNA 
(ncRNA) regions (n ¼ 96). Of the remaining IRD variants (1266 
exonic and 21 splice site), 561 variants were potentially 
pathogenic (Supplementary Table S3). At least three prediction 
algorithms identified 498 variants as pathogenic, and 63 
variants were deletions, insertions, gain/loss of stop codons, 
or variants of unknown effect. The candidate variants 
remaining after each filtering step are shown in Table 1. 
We identified seven different likely mutations in six IRD 
families; of these, six had not been reported previously (Table 
2; Fig. 1). Four of the variants are missense, one is predicted to 
affect splicing, and two are predicted to result in frameshift 
and protein truncation. None of the variants has been reported 
in the whole-genome sequence data of 100 Zulu, 100 
Bagandan, or 120 Ethiopian individuals in the AGVP study. 33 
Additionally, these variants are not detected in 97 Luyha or 88 
Yoruba individuals in the 1000 Genomes data. 30 Therefore, the 
seven variants identified in IRD families are not present in 505 
control African individuals (1010 chromosomes), providing 
additional evidence in support of their pathogenicity. The 
previously reported autosomal recessive RP (arRP) mutation 
p.(His620GlnfsTer23) in PDE6B was present only once in 4266 
alleles in the NHLBI WES dataset (ESP) of African Americans 
(rs769671323, as of 27 October 2015); this frameshift mutation 
is predicted to generate a truncated protein lacking over 200 C-
terminal amino acids. 34 The second frameshift mutation 
identified in ABCA4 is predicted to truncate the protein by 
612 C-terminal amino acids. The c.698-1G&gt;A variant in the 
acceptor splice site of exon 8 of PRPF31, interrogated by 
Human Splicing Finder 3.0, 35 is predicted to activate an 
intronic cryptic acceptor site while simultaneously disrupting 
an exon splicing silencer site and creating an exon splicing 
enhancer site. Therefore, all seven variants were computation-
ally predicted to be pathogenic, cosegregated with disease in </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Candidate Variants in Each of the 16 Families After Prioritization Filters </p>

<p>Family ID </p>

<p>No. of IRD 
Variants 
&lt;0.1 MAF 
Exonic/Splicing </p>

<p>Cosegregating 
Within Family </p>

<p>Pathogenic, 
&gt;3 Predictions </p>

<p>Candidate Gene, 
Rare and Cosegregating </p>

<p>RPD 55 
1351 
749 
280 
17 
7 
0 
RP 583 
1431 
796 
302 
8 
8 
0 
RPD 94 
1181 
599 
198 
10 
1 
0 
RP 391 
1224 
607 
209 
25 
13 
PRPF3 
RPD 401 
1183 
619 
234 
30 
11 
0 
RPD 799 
1309 
686 
259 
15 
5 
0 
RPD 1001 
1416 
805 
316 
8 
4 
0 
RPD 1005 
1285 
679 
223 
5 
3 
0 
RPD 1010 
1217 
628 
234 
5 
3 
RHO 
RPD 1339 
1153 
579 
194 
21 
10 
PRPF31 
RPM 537 
1130 
550 
191 
9 
5 
ABCA4 (x2) 
RPM 1167 
1086 
552 
198 
2 
0 
0 
RPR 397 
1063 
525 
199 
19 
3 
PDE6B 
RPR 624 
1200 
620 
217 
3 
0 
0 
RPR 917 
1154 
574 
203 
4 
1 
CERKL 
RPX 54 
1432 
760 
259 
1 
1 
0 </p>

<p>Whole Exome Analysis of South African IRD Families 
IOVS j November 2016 j Vol. 57 j No. 14 j 6376 </p>

<p>the respective families, verified by Sanger sequencing, and 
exhibited conservation across vertebrates (Fig. 2). According 
to ACMG guidelines for the interpretation of sequence 
variants, 36 the frameshift truncations identified in this study 
have sufficient evidence to classify them as ''pathogenic,'' 
while each of the splice site or missense variants meets the 
criteria of ''likely pathogenic'' variants in the absence of 
functional studies. 
We then performed TaqMan assays for these seven 
pathogenic or likely pathogenic variants, identified here, in 
an additional 193 indigenous Africans with IRDs. Five of these 
variants were not detected in this cohort. The PDE6B 
c.1860delC mutation was identified in a homozygous state in 
one additional individual (diagnosed with arRP, from infancy) 
and in a heterozygous state in four individuals (two sporadic 
RP, one arRP, and one with an apparent dominant family 
history). In addition, we identified the homozygous CERKL 
c.365T&gt;G variant in three patients with different IRD 
phenotypes: one each of sporadic RP, sporadic STGD, and 
arRP. This c.365T&gt;G variant was also identified in the 
heterozygous state in one RP proband. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The use of indigenous SA populations, combined with next-
generation sequencing platforms, provides an enriched re-
source for discovering novel IRD genes and mutations. Due to 
the vast clinical and genetic heterogeneity, traditional candi-
date gene-based approaches have been less effective for the 
molecular diagnosis of IRDs. Targeted capture of specific IRD 
genes, associated with particular retinal phenotypes, is a 
strategy being used for molecular diagnosis with increasing 
frequency. 37-41 Both targeted capture and WES allow for the 
detection of novel mutations in genes (in contrast to micro-
arrays). Recently targeted capture of known IRD genes in 
panel-based testing was reportedly more successful than 
WES, 42 probably due to better coverage of the genes of 
interest. We believe that panel-based testing is especially not 
suitable for the research on understudied populations, like the 
indigenous Africans, where WES with targeted bioinformatic 
analysis could enhance molecular diagnosis and even lead to 
novel gene discovery. Collaborative and combined analysis of </p>

<p>WES data from different groups can yield genetic evidence for 
novel IRD genes. In addition, WES data from unresolved 
families can be reanalyzed when novel IRD genes are reported 
without redesigning diagnostic gene panels and performing 
new experiments. The latter is an important consideration 
when providing a molecular diagnosis for patients in resource-
limited settings. 
Our targeted analysis approach was successful in assigning 
molecular diagnosis in 38% of the indigenous African families, a 
clear improvement on the 13% detection rate using the 
commercially available arrays that test for specific reported 
variants. Six of seven (85%) variants discovered were novel, 
supporting the high genetic heterogeneity in IRDs as well as 
genetic diversity among indigenous Africans. Analysis of a 
larger cohort of unrelated indigenous African probands 
revealed that five out of seven variants were rare and detected 
in a single family each, further advocating the use of WES-based 
diagnosis instead of the genotyping-based microarrays used 
previously to screen this population group. Nonetheless, the 
detection rate is still much lower than the reported 83% of 
European families interrogated using a similar approach. 43 
Other population groups investigated in a comparable manner 
include Saudi Arabian, 44 Chinese, 45 Thai, 46 and Israeli, 22,47 
with detection rates ranging from 49% to 83% and the number 
of analyzed genes ranging from 60 to 226. 
The relatively low detection of causal mutations in the SA 
cohort of IRD families can be attributed to multiple factors. 
Whole-exome sequencing is a capture-based method with 
genomic regions of low coverage and poor detection of large 
genomic alterations. Additionally, WES will not detect less 
obvious pathogenic variants, such as ncRNA or regulatory 
variants and those present in the untranslated regions or 
introns. The clinical complexity of IRDs, that is, nonpene-
trance, frequent manifestation in carriers of X-linked disorders, 
and variable expressivity within families, could result in an 
incorrect inheritance pattern being assumed and hence 
incorrect variant filtering during cosegregation analysis. This 
problem is exacerbated in SA, where frequently sparse clinical 
information accompanies the samples particularly from the 
more rural areas of the country, and where language barriers 
can often result in misinformation. However, it is also plausible 
that causative mutations in many families reside in an as yet </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Potential Causative Mutations in Indigenous African Families With IRDs </p>

<p>Family Disorder Ethnicity Gene 
Variant: cDNA; Protein 
Comment </p>

<p>Pathogenicity, 
ACMG Category 36 Reported/Novel </p>

<p>RP 391 
adRP 
Tswana 
PRPF3 c.1480A&gt;G; p.(Thr494Ala) 
Heterozygous, 9 
pathogenic 
predictions </p>

<p>Likely pathogenic 
Novel </p>

<p>RPD 1010 adRP 
Xhosa 
RHO 
c.154T&gt;G; p.(Phe52Val) 
Heterozygous, 4 
pathogenic 
predictions </p>

<p>Likely pathogenic 
Novel </p>

<p>RPD 1339 adRP 
Zulu 
PRPF31 c.698-1G&gt;A; p.(?) 
Heterozygous 
Likely pathogenic 
Novel 
RPM 537 
arSTGD 
Venda 
ABCA4 c.4832delC; p.(Thr1611MetfsTer51) Compound 
heterozygous, 9 
pathogenic 
predictions for 
nonsynonymous 
p.(Phe348Cys) </p>

<p>Pathogenic 
(frameshift 
truncation), 
likely pathogenic 
(missense) </p>

<p>Both novel 
c.1043T&gt;G; p.(Phe348Cys) </p>

<p>RPR 397 
arRP 
Shangaan PDE6B c.1860delC; p.(His620GlnfsTer23) 
Homozygous 
Pathogenic 
Reported, 
Danciger et al. 34 
RPR 917 
arRP 
Xhosa 
CERKL c.365T&gt;G; p.(Leu122Arg) 
Homozygous, 4 
pathogenic 
predictions </p>

<p>Likely pathogenic 
Novel </p>

<p>adRP, autosomal dominant RP; arRP, autosomal recessive RP; arSTGD, autosomal recessive STGD. </p>

<p>Whole Exome Analysis of South African IRD Families 
IOVS j November 2016 j Vol. 57 j No. 14 j 6377 </p>

<p>unreported IRD gene. We believe that the use of previously 
understudied populations is a sensible approach for ascertain-
ing missing heritability in genetically heterogeneous diseases 
such as IRDs. 
PDE6B mutations have been associated with autosomal 
dominant congenital stationary night blindness (adCSNB) and 
arRP. 48 In our patient samples, two probands with arRP carried 
the homozygous c.1860delC mutation of PDE6B. In addition, 
we identified four IRD patients (two sporadic RP, one arRP, and 
one with an apparent autosomal dominant [adRP] family 
history) with a heterozygous PDE6B c.1860delC allele. The 
relatively high frequency of this allele (1.9%; n ¼ 8/418 alleles) 
in the SA IRD cohort could imply compound heterozygosity for 
PDE6B, digenic inheritance, or enhanced genetic burden. The 
individual RPR 397.1 (in the WES cohort) had been tested 
previously by the arRP microarray; however, this array platform </p>

<p>was designed to detect the c.1857_1858delC PDE6B variant 
and not c.1860. We also noted the relatively frequent 
occurrence of the CERKL c.365T&gt;G variant in SA IRD patients 
(n ¼ 9/418 alleles; 2.2%). The four homozygous cases with this 
mutation displayed varying phenotypes: two arRP, one 
sporadic RP, and one sporadic STGD. CERKL mutations are 
shown to result in autosomal recessive forms of cone 
dystrophy, cone-rod dystrophy and RP (RetNet). In our study, 
an identical CERKL mutation is associated with distinct IRD 
phenotypes, implying the existence of modifier variants or the 
impact of vastly different environmental and epigenetic 
landscape in this genetically diverse cohort compared to the 
reported Caucasian patients. Given the existence of the large 
number of sequence variants in native Africans, 2,3 it would be 
prudent to perform WES on carriers of PDE6B and CERKL 
variants to identify causal IRD mutation(s). </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Pedigrees of IRD families showing cosegregation of the variants identified by WES. Squares represent males, and circles, females. Shaded 
symbols indicate individuals with IRD. Identifier codes show individuals from whom biological material is available, and those selected for whole-
exome sequencing are noted with an asterisk. Segregation of mutation(s) in the families is indicated as þ/þ, homozygous for wild-type allele; M/þ, 
heterozygous; M/M, homozygous for mutation. Clinical information is presented in Supplementary Table S4. </p>

<p>Whole Exome Analysis of South African IRD Families 
IOVS j November 2016 j Vol. 57 j No. 14 j 6378 </p>

<p>Our study shows that genetic investigations of the SA 
indigenous population present considerable challenges and 
unique opportunities in human disease gene discovery. 49 
Africans have smaller haplotype blocks and low levels of 
linkage disequilibrium compared to non-African populations, 
as well as evidence of genetic admixture, leading to unique 
diversity. 3,4 Whole-exome sequencing of RP families in the 
United States has yielded a greater number of novel variants 
(both single nucleotide variants and small indels) in the 
families of African ancestry compared with families of 
European ancestry. 50 In this study, the number of variants 
novel to the National Center for Biotechnology Information 
Short Genetic Variations database (dbSNP) was reportedly &gt;6-
fold larger in a family of African American descent (n &gt; 2500) 
than in Caucasian U.S. families (n ~400). Given that genome-
wide ancestry estimates show an average proportion of only 
~73% African ancestry in African Americans, 51 the exomes of 
indigenous Africans are expected to yield even more novel 
variants. Therefore, inclusion of African populations in </p>

<p>genomics research should facilitate the discovery of genetic 
defects associated with human disease. 52 
This study employs the first next generation sequencing 
(NGS)-based approach in an indigenous SA cohort as an 
opportunity for improved understanding of the genetic 
architecture of IRDs. We have shown that success of diagnosis 
is enhanced considerably using WES, and have identified 
important genes and novel variants for genetic counseling for 
IRD patients. Our study provides valuable insight into the 
etiology of IRD in SA, and contributes toward more compre-
hensive understanding of this heterogeneous group of disor-
ders by cataloguing novel causative variants. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank patients and family members for participation 
and Linn Gieser and Ash-Police Reddy for technical assistance with 
WES. This study made use of data generated by the African 
Genomes Variation Project, for the African Partnership for Chronic </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Sequence alignments across vertebrate species demonstrating nucleotide conservation of each identified variant (highlighted in red). 
Right: the corresponding Sanger sequencing electropherogram. Arrow indicates the position of the mutation. </p>

<p>Whole Exome Analysis of South African IRD Families 
IOVS j November 2016 j Vol. 57 j No. 14 j 6379 </p>

<p>Disease Research. A full list of the investigators and funders who 
contributed to the generation or collation of the data is available 
from www.apcdr.org. </p>

<p>Research in South Africa was funded by Retina South Africa and 
the Medical Research Council of South Africa. WES and data 
analysis were supported by the Intramural Research Program 
(EY000546) of the National Eye Institute and utilized computa-
tional resources of the National Institutes of Health High-
Performance Computing Biowulf cluster (https://hpc.nih.gov). </p>

<p>Disclosure: L. Roberts, None; R. Ratnapriya, None; M. du 
Plessis, None; V. Chaitankar, None; R.S. Ramesar, None; A. 
Swaroop, None </p>



<p>Whole Exome Analysis of South African IRD Families 
IOVS j November 2016 j Vol. 57 j No. 14 j 6380 </p>



<p>Whole Exome Analysis of South African IRD Families 
IOVS j November 2016 j Vol. 57 j No. 14 j 6381 </p>

</text></tei>