<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5373906" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Objective: In the present study an attempt 
was made to estimate coefficients of dose response 
curves for PCC aberrations induced by CalyculinA and 
Okadaic acid, using </p>

<p>60 Co gamma radiation and 8 MeV 
pulsed electron beam for biodosimetry application. 
Materials and Methods: The modified method out-
lined by Puig et al. 2013 was used to conduct Caly-
culin A and Okadaic acid induced PCC assay in hu-
man blood lymphocytes. Chemical treatment was 
given for the last 1 h of a 48 h culture. The study was 
carried out in the dose range 2.5 to 20 Gy using 
60 Co 
gamma rays and 8 MeV pulsed electron beam. Re-
sults and Conclusions: Results show a linear dose 
dependent increase with a slope of 0.047 ± 0.001 
from Calycalin A PCC and 0.048 ± 0.002 form Oka-
daic acid PCC. The slope of the fragments curve 
was 0.327 ± 0.006 from Calyculin A and 0.328 ± 
0.006 from Okadaic acid PCC. Further, dose calibra-
tion studies were carried out for 8 MeV electron us-
ing Calyculin A PCC assay and the obtained slope 
from ring yield was 0.054 ± 0.002 and 0.427 ± 0.009 
from fragment yield. 
The conventional cytogenetic dosimetry, the gold stan-
dard chromosomal aberration assay, fails to estimate high 
radiation dose exposure due to mitotic delay and severe 
leukopenia. Therefore, it is not always possible to make 
chromosome preparations containing a sufficient number 
of metaphase cells necessary for the dose estimation. 
Hence, there is a need to establish a reliable, easier, and 
quicker method for biodosimetry, which depends on in-
terphase chromosomes. When cycling cells enter mitosis, 
the chromatin condenses into chromosomes. Techniques 
have been developed to cause chromatin to condense at 
earlier stages in the cell cycle (before mitosis) and dose 
estimation can be done by measuring ring frequency. The 
technique is termed as the Premature Chromosome Con-
densation (PCC) assay. The PCC assay was first reported 
by Johnson and Rao in 1970 
1) . The premature condensa-
tion was induced by fusing the interphase cells to mitotic 
CHO or HeLa cells using Sendai virus or polyethylene 
glycol (PEG) as fusing agents. Fusion by means of Sendai 
virus requires cells with membranes, especially receptive 
to the virus particles. G0lymphocytes cannot be satisfacto-
rily fused using Sendai virus. This difficulty was over-
come for the purpose of biological dosimetry with the use 
of PEG for PCC induction. However, this fusion method 
has several disadvantages, such as complicated operation, 
low PCC index, and the requirement of mitotic and fusing 
cells. In 1993, Dyban et al. 
2) reported that Okadaic acid, a 
specific inhibitor of PP1 and PP2A phosphoprotein phos-
phatases, induced PCC in mouse embryo cells. Further-
more, Gotoh et al. 
3) reported that PCC was also inducible 
by the protein phosphatise Calyculin A in many types of 
cells with high efficiency. In addition, Kanda et al. 
4 ) re-
ported the dose response relationship of PCC rings in </p>

<p>Received February 27, 2016; Accepted July 18, 2016 
Published online in J-STAGE October 7, 2016 
Correspondence to: R K. Nairy, Department of Studies in Physics, P.A 
College of Engineering, Mangalore, India (e-mail: rajesh.nairy@gmail.c 
om) </p>

<p>Journal of Occupational Health is an Open Access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International </p>

<p>License. To view the details of this license, please visit (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/). </p>

<p>J Occup Health, Vol. 58, 2016 </p>

<p>lymphocytes and proposed an easy method of scoring 
PCC rings in Giemsa stained PCC spreads induced by 
Okadaic acid (OA). They also estimated the doses in three 
Tokaimura criticality accident victims using this assay 
5 ) . 
Recently, many groups used chemically induced PCC as-
say for dose estimation 
6-10 ) . The present study deals with 
standardization of CalyculinA and Okadaic acid induced 
PCC assay, and dose response studies with 
60 Co gamma 
rays in the dose range 0 to 20 Gy. The study also involves 
standardization CalyculinA induced PCC assay for 8 
MeV pulsed electron beam. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Chemicals 
Phytohaemagglutinin (PHA), CalyculinA, and Okadaic 
acid were purchased from Sigma chemicals ( St. Louis, 
Mo, USA ) . Roswell Park Memorial Institute medium 
(RPMI) and Fetal Bovine Serum (FCS) were purchased 
from Gibco chemicals. The rest of the chemicals were 
analytical grade and purchased from HiMedia. </p>

<p>Radiation source and Dosimetry 
In the present study, the dose response studies were 
carried out using 
60 Co-gamma radiation and 8 MeV 
pulsed electron beam. The gamma radiation was taken 
from 
60 Co-gamma chamber-1200 supplied by the Isotope 
Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Center, and 8 MeV 
pulsed electron beam from Microtron Accelerator at Man-
galore University. The details of the Microtron are given 
elsewhere 
11 ) . Fricke dosimeter was used to calibrate and 
optimize the absorbed dose as described elsewhere 
12-17 ) . 
The dose rate of the gamma chamber and Microtron ac-
celerator was determined by the same method and was 
found to be 1.5 Gy.min 
-1 and 100 Gy.min 
-1 respectively. </p>

<p>Blood collection and Irradiation 
Peripheral blood samples were collected by venipunc-
ture in heparinized vials from healthy male donors having 
no pre-history of radiation. Immediately after the collec-
tion of blood, the vials were gently agitated to mix the 
blood with heparin to avoid coagulation. Aliquots of 
heparinized blood were irradiated to different doses of 0, 
2.5, 5, 7.5, 10, 15, 20 Gy of gamma radiation and electron 
beam. </p>

<p>Cell culture and PCC assay 
PCC assay employed in the present study is a modified 
technique described by Puig et al 
10) . The peripheral blood 
lymphocytes were incubated for 2 h at 37 before and 
after irradiation for repair. Ficoll Histopaque density gra-
dient method was used to separate lymphocytes from 
whole blood cells. Blood lymphocyte cultures were set up 
with RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 20% FCS 
and 0.2 ml of PHA (final concentration of 20 μg/ml) and </p>

<p>incubated 37 for 48 h. One hour before harvesting i.e., 
after 47 h of incubation, cultures were centrifuged, culture 
volume was adjusted to 2.5 cm 
3 , and Calyculin A (50 nM) 
or Okadaic acid (500 nM) was added to the culture. After 
about 1 h of incubation with the drug, cultures were har-
vested and centrifuged at 900 rpm for 8 min to get a firm 
pellet with a clear supernatant. Supernatant was discarded 
and a pellet was disturbed and mixed thoroughly using a 
vertex. Pre-warmed (37 ) hypotonic solution (0.075 M 
KCl) was added to the pellet with constant vortex mixing. 
The pellets in the hypotonic solution were incubated at 
37 for 6 min in a pre-warmed water bath and then cen-
trifuged at 900 rpm for 8 min. The cells were fixed by 
cold fixative solution with 1: 3 mixtures of acetic acid 
and methanol after removing the supernatant and gentle 
agitation. To prepare the chromosome spread on slides, 
the cells were mixed thoroughly and dropped on a pre-
cleaned frozen slide from a certain height (~30 cm) fol-
lowed by quick warm and air blow on the slide surface to 
get better spread of metaphase chromosomes. The slides 
were stained using giemsa stain for 10 to 12 min by dip-
ping in staining solution and washing 3 to 4 times with a 
d.d.w. The slides were mounted with a cover slip using 
Deepex before scoring. PCC spreads were analyzed at 
100X magnification with an Olympus BX 51 fluorescent 
microscope coupled to a Jenoptik C5 cooled CCD camera 
with <rs id="software-0" type="software">ProgRes Capture Pro</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">2.8</rs> software. 100rings per dose 
were scored. Two scoring criteria were used; one as sug-
gested by Kanda et al. 
4 ) , which includes all spherical 
shaped PCC rings, and another suggested by Lamadrid et 
al. 
18) , which strictly limits ring evaluation to those which 
clearly defined open space. Extra fragments were re-
corded as those exceeding 46 pieces in G2/M PCC cells 
and 92 pieces in case of M/A PCC cells. For each ring, 
one fragment was not considered as extra fragment. For 
curve fitting, the minimum Chi-square method using Ori-
gin package was used. The distribution of PCC rings were 
analyzed by Papworth's u test 
19 ) . The detailed statistical 
analysis is given elsewhere 
20 ) . Briefly, the mean number 
of observed rings per cell (y) is given for each dose (D) 
along with relative variance (σ 
2 /y) and the dispersion in-
dex (u). The u values are calculated using the relation; </p>

<p>(σ 
2 /y-1)(N-1) 
u= 
2(N-1)(1-1Ny) </p>

<p>where, N is the number of cells scored. σ 
2 is the variance 
calculated by the relation; </p>

<p>(0-y) 
2 No + (1-y) 
2 N1 + (2-y) 
2 N2 +......+ (i-y) 
2 Ni 
σ 
2 = 
(N0 + N1 + N2 +......+ Ni)-1 </p>

<p>where, N0, N1, N2 Ni refer to the number of cells carry-
ing 0, 1, 2 i rings, respectively. The positive and nega-
tive 'u' value indicates overdispersion and underdisper-
sion respectively, as compared to perfect Poisson distribu-</p>

<p>Rajesha K Nairy, et al.: Standardization of CalyculinA induced PCC assay and its advantages over Okadaic acid PCC assay in Biodosimetry applications </p>

<p>Table 1. Frequencies and ring distribution after irradiating with gamma radiation in hu-
man lymphocytes assessed using Calyculin A PCC assay </p>

<p>Dose 
(Gy) </p>

<p>No. of 
cells </p>

<p>Centric rings frequency 
No. of 
Centric 
rings </p>

<p>Centric 
rings yield 
S.D 
u-value </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>0 
1000 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
2.5 1500 
104 
0 
0 
0 
104 
0.069 
0.007 
1.88 
5 
520 
99 
1 
0 
0 
101 
0.194 
0.019 
1.53 
7.5 
370 
97 
3 
1 
0 
106 
0.286 
0.028 
1.34 
10 
208 
85 
6 
1 
0 
100 
0.481 
0.048 
1.49 
15 
152 
80 
7 
3 
1 
107 
0.704 
0.068 
1.002 
20 
110 
66 13 
3 
2 
109 
0.991 
0.095 
0.98 </p>

<p>Table 2. Frequencies and ring distribution after irradiating with gamma radiation in human 
lymphocytes assessed using Okadaic acid PCC assay </p>

<p>Dose 
(Gy) </p>

<p>No. of 
cells </p>

<p>Centric rings frequency 
No. of 
Centric 
rings </p>

<p>Centric 
rings yield 
S.D 
u-value </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>0 
1000 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
2.5 
1499 
105 
0 
0 
0 
105 
105 
0.07 
0.007 
1.90 
5 
515 
102 
1 
0 
0 
102 
104 
0.202 
0.019 
1.70 
7.5 
374 
99 
3 
1 
0 
99 
108 
0.289 
0.028 
1.219 
10 
204 
88 
6 
2 
0 
88 
106 
0.520 
0.050 
1.75 
15 
145 
83 
6 
3 
1 
83 
108 
0.745 
0.072 
0.09 
20 
114 
71 
11 
3 
2 
71 
110 
0.965 
0.092 
0.08 </p>

<p>tion (u = 0). If the value of u is greater than ± 1.96, then 
the dispersion is significant at 95% confidence level. 
Only a 5% probability exists that the magnitude of u will 
be greater than 1.96 when the underlying distribution fol-
lows Poisson statistics </p>

<p>19) </p>

<p>. The yield y was calculated using 
the relation; </p>

<p>Total number of rings 
y= Total number of cells scored </p>

<p>The Poisson error in yield was calculated using the rela-
tion; </p>

<p>Total number of rings 
Error in yield= Total number of cells scored </p>

<p>Results and Discussion </p>

<p>The ring frequency and their distribution are summa-
rized in Table 1 and 2 after the gamma radiation treat-
ment. Fig. 1 shows the Giemsa stained G2/M PCC spread 
with 2 centric rings. Cells with attached sister chromatid 
are G2/M PCC and cells with separate sister chromatid 
are G2/A PCC. The dose response of the centric rings and </p>

<p>excess fragments induction after gamma and electron 
beam treatment is shown in Fig. 2 to 5. 
The results show a linear dose dependent increase in 
centric rings, excess fragments frequency for gamma ra-
diation in Calyculin A and Okadaic acid induced prema-
ture chromosomes. From Table 1 and 2, it may be noted 
that the u-values for the studied doses are between ± 1.96, 
which confirms that the ring frequency follows a Poisson 
distribution. The Poisson distribution is a characteristic 
feature of low LET radiation exposure. Many investiga-
tors have reported perfect Poisson distribution of ring fre-
quency for low LET radiation in vitro 
6,7,9,10,21 ) . Since ring 
and fragment yield varies linearly with the dose, results 
were fit to a linear model and the coefficients of the linear 
model are shown in Table 3. The obtained α value, when 
rings are considered, were found to be 0.047 ± 0.001 Gy </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>from Calycalin A PCC and 0.048 ± 0.002 Gy 
-1 form Oka-
daic acid PCC, which are comparable with the reported 
results. Recently, Romero et al. 
9) obtained an α value of 
0.044 ± 0.0012 Gy 
-1 from Calycalin A PCC, which is 
comparable with the present results. The α value reported 
by Puig et al. 
10 ) and Lindhom et al. 
7) was 0.027 ± 0.003 
Gy 
-1 and 0.021 ± 0.01 Gy </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>, respectively, which are lower </p>

<p>J Occup Health, Vol. 58, 2016 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. G2/M PCC spread with twocentric rings </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Comparative study between Calyculin A centric 
rings yield ( ) and Okadaic acid centric rings yield 
( ) after irradiating with the gamma radiation </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Dose response of the fragment yield in Calyculin A 
( ) and Okadaic acid ( ) induced PCC assay after 
irradiating with the gamma radiation </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Dose response of the centric rings after irradiating 
with the gamma ( ) and 8 MeV electron ( ) radia-
tions </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Dose response of the fragments after irradiating with 
the gamma ( ) and 8 MeV electron ( ) radiations </p>

<p>values compared to the present study. The less α value in 
their case may be because of the combined treatment of 
colcemid and Calyculin A. In the present study, the ob-
tained α value from Okadaic acid PCC was 0.048 ± 0.002 
Gy 
-1 , which is comparable with the α value reported by 
Daniela et al. 
6 ) (0.0489 ± 0.006 Gy 
-1 ), Lindhom et al. </p>

<p>7 ) </p>

<p>(0.049 ± 0.01 Gy 
-1 ) and Balakrishnan et al. 
8) (0.054 ± 0.01 
Gy 
-1 ). 
From Fig. 1 and 2, it is clear that there is no significant 
difference between Calyculin A and Okadaic acid PCC 
curves. The slope of the fragments curve is 0.327 ± 0.006 
Gy 
-1 from Calyculin A and 0.328 ± 0.006 Gy 
-1 from Oka-
daic acid PCC. The fragments curve slopes are slightly 
less compared to the reported results, 0.41 ± 0.04 Gy 
-1 by </p>

<p>Rajesha K Nairy, et al.: Standardization of CalyculinA induced PCC assay and its advantages over Okadaic acid PCC assay in Biodosimetry applications </p>

<p>Table 3. Coefficients of the linear model after irradiation of blood lymphocytes with 
60 Co 
gamma radiation </p>

<p>Parameter </p>

<p>Centric rings 
Fragments </p>

<p>PCC 
(Calyculin A) </p>

<p>PCC 
(Okadaic acid) </p>

<p>PCC 
(Calyculin A) </p>

<p>PCC 
(Okadaic acid) </p>

<p>Slope (α) (Gy </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) 
0.047 ± 0.001 
0.048 ± 0.002 
0.327±0.006 
0.328 ± 0.006 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.99 
0.99 
0.999 
0.999 
P 
&lt;0.0001 
&lt;0.0001 
&lt;0.0001 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>Table 4. PCC spreads (%) after irradiating with gamma radiation </p>

<p>Donor 1 </p>

<p>Dose (Gy) 
0 
2.5 
5 
7.5 
10 
15 
20 </p>

<p>No. of cells 
1013 1002 1006 1005 1018 1002 1004 
G2/M 
913 
926 
948 
978 
974 
977 
975 
M/A 
100 
76 
58 
27 
44 
25 
29 </p>

<p>PCC Spreads (%) 
(Calyculin A) 
48 
47 
56 
68 
64 
57 
54 
(Okadaic acid) 
17 
19 
21 
16 
13 
11 
7 </p>

<p>Donor 2 </p>

<p>No. of cells 
1007 1003 1006 1008 1008 1012 1001 
G2/M 
847 
867 
904 
921 
914 
927 
912 
M/A 
160 
136 
102 
87 
94 
85 
89 </p>

<p>PCC Spreads (%) 
(Calyculin A) 
36 
38 
42 
47 
41 
43 
32 
(Okadaic acid) 
12 
14 
14 
9 
10 
11 
6 </p>

<p>Table 5. Frequency and ring distribution after irradiating with 8 MeV electron radia-
tion in human lymphocytes assessed using Calyculin A PCC assay </p>

<p>Dose 
(Gy) </p>

<p>No. of 
cells </p>

<p>Centric rings frequency 
No. of 
Centric 
rings </p>

<p>Centric 
rings yield 
S.D 
u-value </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>0 
1000 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
2.5 
1523 
110 
1 
0 
0 
112 
0.074 
0.007 
0.59 
5 
502 
108 
3 
0 
0 
114 
0.23 
0.021 
0.47 
7.5 
370 
104 
3 
1 
0 
113 
0.31 
0.029 
0.72 
10 
203 
93 
6 
3 
0 
114 
0.56 
0.053 
1.77 
15 
141 
88 
6 
3 
1 
110 
0.78 
0.075 
0.71 
20 
101 
75 
10 
4 
2 
115 
1.139 
0.106 
1.54 </p>

<p>Puig et al. 
10) and 0.45 ± 0.03 Gy 
-1 by Balakrishnan et al 
8) . 
The fragments slope may be less because of more G2/M 
PCC cells observed in this study. 
The percentage of PCC spreads induced by Calyculin 
A and Okadaic acid at various doses of gamma radiation 
was calculated and presented in Table 4. The percentage 
of PCC spread was calculated using following equation. </p>

<p>(Number of PCC cells) </p>

<p>PCC Spreads(%)= </p>

<p>×100 
(Number of stimulated lymphocytes) </p>

<p>The observed PCC spread (%) was much higher in Ca-
lyculin A compared to Okadaic acid PCC assay. From 
Table 4, it may be noted that the increase in G2/M PCC 
spreads until 7.5 Gy followed by a plateau, whereas de-
crease in M/A PCC spreads with the radiation dose. A 
similar observation was reported by Miura et al. 
22 ) , who </p>

<p>J Occup Health, Vol. 58, 2016 </p>

<p>observed an increase in G2/M PCC spread until 8 Gy and 
thereafter it attained a plateau and decrease in M/A PCC 
cells. A higher PCC index was observed for Calyculin A 
compare to Okadaic acid, which restricted 8 MeV elec-
tron studies on Calyculin A. The results show a linear 
dose dependent increase in centric rings and excess frag-
ments frequency, and the ring distribution follows the 
Possion distribution (Fig. 4 and 5). A similar dose re-
sponse relation was observed in gamma radiation studies. 
The dose response relation can be represented as, Ycentric rings 
= (0.054 ± 0.002) D (with R 
2 = 0.99 and P &lt;0.0001) and 
Yfragments = ( 0.427 ± 0.009 ) D ( with R 
2 = 0.99 and P 
&lt;0.0001). From Fig. 4 and 5, it is clear that there is a sig-
nificant difference in ring yield and fragment yield be-
tween 8 MeV electrons and 
60 Co-gamma radiation. The 
obtained α value for ring yield is 0.047 ± 0.001 Gy 
-1 for 
gamma radiation and 0.054 ± 0.002 Gy 
-1 for 8 MeV elec-
trons. The α values from fragment yield is 0.327 ± 0.006 
Gy 
-1 for gamma radiation and 0.427 ± 0.009 Gy 
-1 for 8 
MeV electrons. The obtained higher α values for electron 
beam may be because of higher RBE value of the radia-
tion. The higher RBE values of the 8 MeV electron beam 
have been reported elsewhere </p>

<p>15,20,23) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>The present study reveals that the CalyculinA and Oka-
daic acid induces similar ring and fragment yield. But 
PCC spreads percentage is higher in CalyculinA PCC as-
say, which is an important parameter in biodosimetry. 
Dose calibration studies confirm that the ring and frag-
ment yield increases linearly with the doses and slightly 
higher yields were obtained for 8 MeV pulsed electron 
beam compared to gamma radiation. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments: The authors are grateful to Board of 
Research in Nuclear Sciences, Department of Atomic En-
ergy, Government of India, for the financial support. 
Authors are thankful to Dr. Pradeep Kumar, Director, 
HSE &amp; G, BARC, Mr. D.A.R. Babu, Head, RP &amp; AD, 
BARC, India for technical discussions, support, and help. 
Technical assistance during the experiments by Mr. U. B. 
Thorat, Mr. S. Jagtap, and Mr. P. Tondlekar are thank-
fully acknowledged. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest: The authors declare that there are 
no conflicts of interest. </p>



<p>Rajesha K Nairy, et al.: Standardization of CalyculinA induced PCC assay and its advantages over Okadaic acid PCC assay in Biodosimetry applications </p>



</text></tei>