<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5104181" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. The objective of the present study was to investigate 
whether cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) is associated with malig-
nancy, and to investigate its molecular mechanisms in human 
lung cancer tumor malignancy. The present study used RNA 
interference (RNAi) methodology and celecoxib, a COX-2 
inhibitor, to investigate the effect of COX-2 knockdown on 
the proliferation and invasion abilities of lung cancer cells 
and the molecular mechanisms involved. Human lung adeno-
carcinoma A549-si10 and LTEPLung cancer is one of the most common malignant tumors in 
the world. Its incidence rate the highest of all human tumors 
and there are ~1.2 million novel cases each year (1). In addi-
tion, lung cancer also has the highest mortality rate of all 
human cancers, with 15,600 people succumbing to the disease 
each year, which accounts for 19.4% of the total number of 
cancer-associated mortalities (1,2). For &gt;80% of lung cancer 
patients admitted to hospital, the ideal time to receive surgery 
and multidisciplinary radical cure has already passed (2,3). 
Although the concept and means of lung cancer treatment in 
recent years has made considerable progress, the overall effect 
is not satisfactory. 
An association between carcinogenesis and chronic 
inflammation has long been suspected (4). The accepted 
hypothesis is that chronic inflammation more often stimulates 
than inhibits tumor development (5-9). As a rate-limiting 
enzyme, cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) is involved in the conver-
sion of arachidonic acid into prostaglandin (PG) and other 
bioactive lipids. With the exception of being involved in 
inflammation, COX-2 produces large amounts of PGE2 in 
tumor tissues (10-13), and is extremely important in the devel-
opment of tumors (10,14-19). COX-2 inhibitors have produced 
encouraging results in preventing and treating certain diges-
tive system cancers (20-22). The present study hypothesized 
that COX-2 is associated with malignant cell phenotype in 
lung cancer. Therefore, the present study investigated whether 
silencing of COX-2 and the use of celecoxib, an inhibitor of 
COX-2, affects lung cancer cell proliferation and invasive-
ness (21,22). The present results demonstrated that silencing 
of COX-2 and use of celecoxib inhibited the growth of lung 
cancer cells and decreased their invasive abilities. In addition, 
the present results revealed that the inhibition of a malignant 
cell phenotype may be associated with an alteration in vascular 
endothelial growth factor (VEGF), matrix metalloproteinase 
(MMP)-2 and endothelial growth factor receptor (EGFR) 
expression. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Cell culture. Human lung adenocarcinoma A549 and 
LTEP-A2 cells were purchased from the Cell Center of </p>

<p>Cyclooxygenase-2 is associated with malignant 
phenotypes in human lung cancer </p>

<p>WEIYING LI 
* , WENTAO YUE 
* , HUI WANG, BAITANG LAI, XUEHUI YANG, </p>

<p>CHUNYAN ZHANG, YUE WANG and MENG GU </p>

<p>Department of Cellular &amp; Molecular Biology, Beijing Tuberculosis and Thoracic Tumor Research Institute, 
Beijing Chest Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing 101149, P.R. China </p>

<p>Received April 10, 2015; Accepted July 12, 2016 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/ol.2016.5207 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Dr Weiying Li, Department of Cellular </p>

<p>&amp; Molecular Biology, Beijing Tuberculosis and Thoracic Tumor 
Research Institute, Beijing Chest Hospital, Capital Medical 
University, 97 Machang, Tongzhou, Beijing 101149, P.R. China 
E-mail: li_weiying412@aliyun.com </p>

<p>* Contributed equally </p>

<p>Key words: COX-2, lung cancer, malignant phenotype, celecoxib </p>

<p>LI et al: COX-2 IS ASSOCIATED WITH MALIGNANT PHENOTYPES IN HUMAN LUNG CANCER </p>



<p>Peking Union Medical College (Beijing, China). The cells 
were cultured in RPMI-1640 medium (Gibco </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>; Thermo Fisher 
Scientific, Inc., Waltham, MA, USA) supplemented with 10% 
fetal bovine serum (FBS; Gibco </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>), 100 U/ml of penicillin and 
100 U/ml of streptomycin in a humidified 37˚C incubator with 
5% CO 2 . </p>

<p>RNA interference (RNAi) vector transfection. The specific 
RNAi vector psi10 and empty vector pU6 were constructed 
in a previous study, in which the construction process and 
the interference effect of the vectors were observed (23). In 
total, 3x10 
5 cells were seeded into 35 mm culture plates. When 
the cells were 70-80% confluent, the cells were transfected 
with plasmids (pU6 and psi10) using Lipofectamine 2000 
(Invitrogen™; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.), according to 
the manufacturer's protocol. Complete RPMI-1640 medium 
supplemented with geneticin (800 µg/ml) was used to screen 
the clones. The transfected A549 and LTEP-A2 cell strains 
were named A549-pU6, A549-si10, LTEP-A2-pU6 and 
LTEP-A2-si10. </p>

<p>Western blotting. Protein was extracted using conven-
tional protocols (9 M urea, 4% 3-[(3-cholamidopropyl) 
dimethylammonio]-1-propanesulfonate, 1% dithiothreitol, 
0.5% carrier ampholytes and cocktail of protease inhibi-
tors). Protein concentrations were determined using Pierce™ 
BCA Protein Assay kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.) with 
bovine serum album as a standard. Subsequently, proteins 
were separated on 12% polyacrylamide gels using standard 
sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis 
techniques and then transferred to nitrocellulose membranes. 
The membranes were blocked by 5% milk (Invitrogen; 
Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.) for 1 h and probed with 
specific antibodies for 4˚C overnight. Mouse anti-COX-2 poly-
clonal antibodies (dilution, 1 µg/ml; catalog no., 3362R-100; 
BioVision, Inc., Milpitas, CA, USA) were used, and mouse 
anti-glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase monoclonal 
antibodies (dilution, 0.3 ng/µl; catalog no., 60004-1-Ig; 
ProteinTech Group, Rosemont, IL, USA) were used as an 
internal reference. After three washing steps of 15 min each 
with Tris-buffered saline and Tween (TBST), the membranes 
were probed with horseradish peroxidase-conjugated 
goat anti-mouse IgG antibodies (dilution, 1:5,000; catalog 
no., sc-2005; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc., USA) at 37˚C for 
1 h. After three washing steps of 15 min each with TBST, the 
protein was tested by chemiluminescence detection (catalog 
no., 29100; Engreen Biosystem Co., Ltd., Beijing, China). The 
protein expression was analyzed by <rs id="software-0" type="software">Image-Pro Plus</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">6.0</rs> soft-
ware (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Media Cybernetics, Inc.</rs>., Rockville, MD, USA). </p>

<p>Cell growth curve assays. Tumor cells (3,000 cells/well) were 
seeded in flat-bottom 96-well plates. Cell activity was assessed 
by a 3-(4,5-dimethyl-thiazol-2yl)-5-(3-carboxymethoxyphen 
yl)-2-(4-sulfophenyl)-2H-tetrazolium (MTS) assay (Promega, 
Madison, WI, USA). The growth of cells was detected for 
5 days. Subsequently, 20 µl MTS was added into each well 
and then incubated with the cells for 3 h. The absorbance 
was recorded at 490 nm with an ELx800 Absorbance Reader 
(Bio-Tek Instruments, Winooski, VT, USA). This experiment 
was repeated three times. </p>

<p>Colony formation assays. A total of 300 cells were seeded 
in 6-well plates. The cells were cultured for 10 days. On the 
10th day, the number of colonies with &gt;50 cells was recorded 
using the trypan blue exclusion method. The experiment was 
repeated three times in triplicate. </p>

<p>Cell migration assay. Cell motility was evaluated by two 
experiments. In the wound healing experiment, channels were 
created by making a scratch in a 6-well plate. Subsequently, 
8x10 
5 cells per channel were seeded into the 6-well plates and 
cultured for 24 h. At 0, 12 and 24 h, the wounds were observed 
and pictures were taken using a phase-contrast microscope. 
The areas of the scratch were calculated using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Alpha View 
Analysis Tools</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version1.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">ProteinSimple</rs>, San Jose, 
CA, USA), and this was used to calculate the percentage of 
wound closure. 
In addition, a migration experiment was performed in a 
24-well Transwell unit (Corning, Inc., Corning, NY, USA), as 
previously reported (24). The cells were starved for 12 h and 
8x10 
5 cells were seeded in the upper compartment of the Tran-
swell unit with serum-free medium. The lower compartment 
was filled with medium containing 10% FBS. Subsequent to 
24 or 48 h, the cells in the upper chamber were removed by 
gentle swabbing. The number of cells migrating to the lower 
surface of the membrane was determined using crystal violet. 
Five microscopic fields were randomly selected and viewed at 
x200 magnification. Three repeats were performed. </p>

<p>Invasion assay. Cell invasion was analyzed using Boyden 
chambers polyvinylpyrrolidone-free polycarbonate filters 
(8 µm) coated with 5 µg/ml Matrigel (BD Biosciences, 
Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA). The cells were starved for 12 h 
and 2x10 
6 cells were seeded in the upper compartment of the 
Transwell unit with serum free medium. The lower compart-
ment was filled with medium containing 10% FBS. The filters 
were stained with crystal violet solution. Crystal violet stained 
invading cells were viewed at x400 magnification. For each 
filter, cells in 10 randomly chosen fields were counted and 
expressed as the number of invading cells per high-power field. </p>

<p>COX-2 inhibitor celecoxib functional studies. Cell prolifera-
tion, migration and invasion assays were also evaluated in the 
presence of celecoxib (Selleck, Houston, TX, USA). Briefly, 
A549 and LTEP-A2 cells were incubated in 96-well plates 
or 6-well plates with celecoxib (45 µg/ml) for 3 h. Dimethyl 
sulfoxide (0.3 µl/ml) was used as a control. </p>

<p>Tumor growth in nude mice. The mice used in the present 
study were 4-week-o1d male BALB/c nude mice (Vital River 
Laboratories Co., Ltd, Beijing, China). The average weight of 
the mice was 17 g. Each group included 6 mice. Nude mice 
were raised in a specific pathogen-free level room and all feed 
was sterilized. The housing was maintained at a temperature 
of 26-28˚C. The relative humidity was maintained at 40-60%. 
The daily light/dark cycle consisted of 10 h of light and 14 h of 
dark. All animal experiments and maintenance were approved 
by the Ethics Committee of the Beijing Chest Hospital, Capital 
Medical University, Beijing, China, and conformed to the 
guidelines of the Animal Care and Use Committee and the 
Chinese Association of Laboratory Animal Care. </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY LETTERS 12: 3836-3844, 2016 </p>



<p>A549, A549-pU6 and A549-si10 cells were collected and 
resuspended in 10% RMPI-1640 at a density of 1.5x10 
7 cells/ml. 
In total, 3x10 
6 cells were injected subcutaneously into the flanks of 
4-week-o1d male BALB/c nude mice. The date at which a palpable 
tumor first arose was recorded. On the 60th day following tumor 
injection, the mice were euthanized using a standard carbon 
dioxide method, and tumors were harvested and weighed. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry. For immunohistochemistry, 
4-µm-thick tumor sections were immersed in 0.3% hydrogen 
peroxide for 10 min, microwaved in citrate phosphate buffer 
(pH 6.0) and incubated with 10% normal goat serum (Maixin 
Biotech. Co., Ltd., Fuzhou, China) for 30 min. The tumor slices 
were incubated overnight at 4˚C with the following primary 
monoclonal antibodies (Maixin Biotech. Co., Ltd.): Rabbit 
anti-COX-2 monoclonal antibodies (catalog no., RMA-0549); 
mouse anti-MMP-2 monoclonal antibodies (catalog 
no., MAB-0244); and mouse anti-VEGF monoclonal anti-
bodies (catalog no., MAB-0243). Secondary anti-mouse/rabbit 
antibodies from Kit-5030 (Maixin Biotech. Co., Ltd.) were 
then incubated with the samples at 37˚C for 15 min. Primary 
and secondary antibodies were working solution and were not 
diluted. A standard staining procedure was finished by using 
a 3,3'-diaminobenzidine kit (Kit-0014; Maixin Biotech. Co., 
Ltd.). Immunostaining was evaluated blindly by a board-certi-
fied pathologist (Capital Medical University), who assigned the 
intensity and prevalence score as described previously (25). 
Five microscopic fields were randomly selected and viewed at 
a magnification of x100. Briefly, the intensity of staining was 
scored as follows: 0, negative; 1, weak staining; 2, moderate 
staining; and 3, strong staining. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. All statistical analyses were performed 
using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version13.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SPSS, Inc.</rs>., Chicago, </p>

<p>IL, USA). Quantitative variables were compared using the 
one-way analysis of variance. The χ 
2 test was used to assess 
qualitative variables. P&lt;0.05 was considered to indicate a 
statistically significant difference. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Reduced expression of COX-2 in RNAi transfected cell lines. 
The levels of COX-2 protein and mRNA were examined in the 
transfected lines (Fig. 1A and B). Following RNAi transfec-
tion, the expression level of COX-2 was significantly reduced 
in LTEP-A2-si10 and A549-si10 cells. Compared with the 
parental cells, the levels of COX-2 mRNA were reduced by 
60.0% (P=0.005) and 62.1% (P=0.004) and COX-2 protein 
by 68.2% (P=0.002) and 75.3% (P=0.001) in A549-si10 and 
LTEP-A2-si10 cells, respectively. </p>

<p>Altered proliferation rates of LTEP-A2 and A549 cells due 
to knockdown of COX-2 in vitro. To determine the result of 
silencing COX-2, cell proliferation and colony formation 
assays were performed. As indicated in Fig. 2A, the growth 
of LTEP-A2-si10 cells was reduced on the third day. On the 
fourth and fifth day, proliferation of LTEP-A2-si10 cells 
was considerably reduced compared with parental cells 
(P=0.037). Similarly, proliferation of A549-si10 cells was 
clearly reduced compared with parental cells (P=0.041). To 
further confirm these results, a COX-2 inhibitor, celecoxib, 
was used to inhibit COX-2 expression and revealed that 
COX-2 inhibition plays a role in cell proliferation. COX-2 
expression was clearly reduced by 89.5 (P=0.045) and 87.5% 
(P=0.043) in A549 and LTEP-A2 cells, respectively, when 
45 µg/ml celecoxib was used (Fig. 2B). Therefore, 45 µg/ml 
celecoxib was used in following experiments. An MTS assay 
was performed, which demonstrated that the proliferation </p>

<p>Figure 1. COX-2 expression in transfected cells. (A) mRNA (left and right panel, *P=0.032 and 0.036) and (B) protein expression (left and right panel, *P=0.021 
and 0.029, respectively) of COX-2 in human lung adenocarcinoma LTEP-A2 and A549 cells transfected with si10 and pU6. COX-2, cyclooxygenase-2; si10, 
small interfering RNA against COX-2. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>LI et al: COX-2 IS ASSOCIATED WITH MALIGNANT PHENOTYPES IN HUMAN LUNG CANCER </p>



<p>ability of A549 and LTEP-A2 cells was similar to A549-si10 
and LTEP-A2-si10 cells following treatment with celecoxib 
(Fig. 2B). </p>

<p>Cell tumorigenisis was inhibited following suppression of 
COX-2. To investigate the effect of COX-2 on tumor growth, 
cell tumorigenesis was evaluated by colony formation assay. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Colony formation assays in transfected cells and cells treated with CXB. (A) Colony formation assays of human lung adenocarcinoma LTEP-A2 
( </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.026) and A549 ( </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.021) cells transfected with si10 and pU6. (B) Colony formation assays of LTEP-A2 ( </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.043) and A549 ( </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.019) parental cells 
treated with 45 µg/ml CXB. CXB, celecoxib; si10, small interfering RNA against cyclooxygenase-2. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 2. Cell growth assays in transfected cells and cells treated with CXB. (A) Cell growth curves of human lung adenocarcinoma LTEP-A2 ( </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.037) and 
A549 ( </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.041) cells transfected with si10 and pU6. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. parental cells. (B) Cell growth curves of LTEP-A2 ( </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.043) and A549 ( </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.045) parental 
cells treated with 45 µg/ml CXB. CXB, celecoxib; si10, small interfering RNA against cyclooxygenase-2; MTS, 3-(4,5-dimethyl-thiazol-2yl)-5-(3-carboxyme 
thoxyphenyl)-2-(4-sulfophenyl)-2H-tetrazolium; OD, optical density. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY LETTERS 12: 3836-3844, 2016 </p>



<p>The colony formation rates of A549-si10 (P=0.021) and 
LTEP-A2-si10 (P=0.026) cells were significantly reduced 
compared with the parental cells after 10 days (Fig. 3A). This 
suggests that COX-2 may overcome the density-dependent 
inhibition of growth in tumor cells. When celecoxib was 
used, the colony formation rates of parental A549 (P=0.019) </p>

<p>and LTEP-A2 (P=0.043) cells were significantly reduced 
compared with the control cells after 10 days (Fig. 3B). </p>

<p>Cell metastasis was decreased by COX-2 suppression. Metas-
tasis is a major characteristic of cancer cells. To further study 
the effect of COX-2 on LTEP-A2 and A549 cell metastasis, </p>

<p>Figure 4. Wound healing, invasion and migration Transwell assays in transfected cells. (A) Wounding healing (left and right panel, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.036 and 0.027, 
respectively), (B) invasion Transwell (Matrigel) (left and right panel, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.032 and 0.028, respectively) and (C) migration Transwell (without Matrigel) (left 
and right panel, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.033 and 0.019, respectively) assays of human lung adenocarcinoma LTEP-A2 and A549 cells transfected with si10 and pU6. si10, small 
interfering RNA against cyclooxygenase-2. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Table I. Growth of mouse xenografts from human lung adenocarcinoma A549 and LTEP-A2 cells transfected with pU6 and si10. </p>

<p>Groups 
Tumor weights, g 
Average tumor weight, g </p>

<p>A549 
0.55 
0.30 
0.30 
0.10 
0.55 
0.40 
0.37±0.17 
A549-pU6 
0.35 
0.60 
0.20 
0.15 
0.15 
0.35 
0.30±0.17 
A549-si10 
0.20 
0.30 
0.05 
0.05 
0.20 
0.00 
0.13±0.11 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P=0.008 vs. A549 and A549-pU6 xenografts. si10, small interfering RNA against cyclooxygenase-2. </p>

<p>LI et al: COX-2 IS ASSOCIATED WITH MALIGNANT PHENOTYPES IN HUMAN LUNG CANCER </p>



<p>the present study examined its effect on cell migration and 
invasion. Wound healing (Fig. 4A), invasion (Fig. 4B) and 
migration (Fig. 4C) were inhibited in A549-si10 (P=0.036, 
0.033 and 0.032, respectively) and LTEP-A2-si10 (P=0.027, 
0.019 and 0.028, respectively) cells compared with parental 
control cells. When parental cells were treated with celecoxib, 
the cell migration and invasion of A549 and LTEP-A2 cells 
were significantly reduced compared with the control groups 
after 10 days (Fig. 5). These results reveal that COX-2 may 
promote tumor cell metastasis. </p>

<p>Tumor growth in vivo was slowed by COX-2 suppression. 
Tumor growth of mouse xenografts was substantially slowed 
following COX-2 treatment compared with control groups 
(Table I). Tumors developed three weeks following inocula-
tion: 6 tumors in A549 group; 4 tumors in A549-pU6 group; 
1 tumor in A549-si10 group. In the fourth week, there were 
6 tumors in A549 group, 6 in A549-pU6 group and 3 in 
the A549-si10 group. By the 45th day, there were 6 tumors 
in A549 group, 6 in A549-pU6 group, and 5 in A549-si10 
group. </p>

<p>VEGF, MMP-2 and EGFR expression was downregulated 
following COX-2 suppression in vivo. The expression levels 
of COX-2 were primarily evaluated in tumor tissues excised 
from the mice xenografts. The findings were consistent with 
those in vitro (data not shown). COX-2 expression in A549 and 
A549-pU6 xenografts was moderately positive and scored 2, 
but this was clearly reduced in A549-si10 xenografts, which 
were weakly positive and scored 1 (Fig. 6A). The expres-
sion of VEGF, MMP-2 and EGFR in A549-si10 xenografts 
was clearly reduced compared with A549 and A549-pU6 
(Figs. 6B, C and 7A). The expression of hypoxia-inducible 
factor-α and MMP-9 in A549-si10 xenografts did not clearly 
alter compared with A549 and A549-pU6 (Fig. 7B and C). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Recently, numerous studies have demonstrated that COX-2 
is not only involved in tumorigenesis and tumor develop-
ment, but also plays a role in inflammation (26-28). In tumor 
tissues, overexpression of COX-2 is a common phenomenon. 
Previously published results of the associations between </p>

<p>Figure 5. Wound healing, invasion and migration Transwell assays in cells treated with CXB. (A) Wounding healing (left and right panel, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.039 and 0.035, 
respectively), (B) invasion Transwell (Matrigel) (left and right panel, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.026 and 0.021, respectively) and (C) migration Transwell (without Matrigel) (left 
and right panel, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P=0.028 and 0.020, respectively) assays of human lung adenocarcinoma LTEP-A2 and A549 cells treated with CXB. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. cells not 
treated with CXB. CXB, celecoxib. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY LETTERS 12: 3836-3844, 2016 </p>



<p>COX-2 and clinicopathological factors are not consistent for 
lung cancer (19,29-31). Our previous results demonstrated 
that COX-2 was associated with malignant pathology, </p>

<p>tumor-node-metastasis stage, lymph node metastasis, degree 
of differentiation and smoking (32). These results are also 
supported by the literature (29-31). </p>

<p>Figure 7. Immunohistochemistry of mouse xenografts from human lung adenocarcinoma A459 cells transfected with si10 and pU6 (magnification, x100). 
(A) Intensity of epidermal growth factor receptor expression staining was scored in the xenografts as follows: A459, 1; A459-pU6, 1; A459-si10, 0. (B) Intensity of 
matrix metalloproteinase-9 expression staining was scored in the xenografts as follows: A549, 2; A549-pU6, 2; A549-si10, 2. (C) Intensity of hypoxia-inducible 
factor-α expression staining was scored in the xenografts as follows: A549, 0; A549-pU6, 0; A549-si10, 0. Scale bar, 200 µm. si10, small interfering RNA against 
cyclooxygenase-2. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Figure 6. Immunohistochemistry of mouse xenografts from human lung adenocarcinoma A459 cells transfected with si10 and pU6 (magnification, x100). 
(A) Intensity of COX-2 expression staining was scored in the xenografts as follows: A549, 1; A549-pU6s, 1; A549-si10, 0. (B) Intensity of matrix metallopro-
teinase-2 expression staining was scored in the xenografts as follows: A549, 3; A549-pU6, 3; A549-si10, 1. (C) Intensity of vascular endothelial growth factor 
expression staining was scored in the xenografts as follows: A549, 2; A549-pU6, 2; A549-si10, 1. Scale bar, 200 µm. COX-2, cyclooxygenase-2; si10, small 
interfering RNA against COX-2. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>LI et al: COX-2 IS ASSOCIATED WITH MALIGNANT PHENOTYPES IN HUMAN LUNG CANCER </p>



<p>Since COX-2 is associated with numerous clinicopatholog-
ical parameters, it may be extremely important in the occurrence 
and development of lung cancer. To confirm this hypothesis, the 
present study used RNAi technology to investigate whether 
interfering with COX-2 expression affects lung cancer cell 
proliferation and invasion. The present results revealed that 
COX-2 knockdown significantly slowed the proliferation and 
invasion of LTEP-A2 and A549 lung cancer cells. In mouse 
xenografts, tumor growth was slowed following silencing of 
COX-2, which further confirmed our hypothesis. In addition, 
the present results demonstrated that silencing COX-2 in lung 
cancer cells inhibited cell proliferation and increased cell sensi-
tivity to density-dependent inhibition. This is consistent with 
previous studies (33,34). Notably, COX-2 knockdown clearly 
inhibited cell migration and invasion, suggesting that COX-2 
has an important effect on the metastasis of non-small cell lung 
cancer (NSCLC) cells (35-37). The present results indicate that 
COX-2 plays a key role in the proliferation, motility and inva-
sion of lung cancer cells. In order to further confirm the role of 
COX-2 in tumorigenesis and development, a COX-2 inhibitor, 
celecoxib, was used by the present study in migration, invasion 
and proliferation assays, which had similar results compared 
with COX-2 interference. 
Subsequently, the present study investigated the molecular 
mechanisms by which COX-2 is key in tumor malignancy. The 
expression of COX-2 was primarily detected in mouse xeno-
grafts to verify the changes following the silencing of COX-2. 
Since, COX-2 is associated with proliferation, migration and 
vascular lumen formation of endothelial cells (23,28), VEGF, 
MMP-2, MMP-9 and EGFR were investigated by the present 
study. The expression of MMP-2, VEGF and EGFR was clearly 
reduced following silencing of COX-2. MMP is a protein that 
degrades the extracellular matrix (38,39), and previous studies 
have verified the involvement of MMPs in NSCLC (40-42). 
In addition, MMP-2 is associated with the lymphatic and 
vascular invasion of NSCLC, and its expression may predict 
a poor prognosis of early-stage patients with NSCLC (43). In 
addition, studies have reported that COX-2 inhibitors inhibit 
the expression of MMP-2 and MMP-9 in prostate cancer (44). 
In the present study, silencing of COX-2 resulted in decreased 
levels of MMP-2; however, there was no alteration in MMP-9 
expression in COX-2-silenced cells (A549). These results are 
consistent with a previous study (45). 
It is well known that VEGF is important in normal and 
abnormal angiogenesis, since it is involved in almost every step 
in the angiogenic process (46). A previous study demonstrated 
that COX-2 inhibitors inhibit tumor growth via an antiangio-
genic mechanism (47). In addition, there is a close association 
between COX-2 expression and tumor angiogenesis (48). As a 
result, COX-2 overexpression may increase tumor blood supply 
and contribute to tumor growth. The present data suggested 
that silencing COX-2 reduced VEGF expression in A549 cells. 
EGFR is a member of the epidermal growth factor receptor 
family. Once activated, it leads to cell division, proliferation, 
invasion and angiogenesis (49-51). The present study observed 
that silencing COX-2 lead to a reduction in EGFR expression 
in A549 cells. 
VEGF, MMP-2 and EGFR are associated with tumor 
angiogenesis (52-54). In the present study, the growth of 
cancer cells was slowed and the migration and invasion ability </p>

<p>reduced following COX-2 silencing. These phenotypic changes 
may have been caused by the alterations in the expression of 
VEGF, MMP-2 and EGFR following COX-2 silencing. To the 
best of our knowledge, this is the first study to report the direct 
association between VEGF, MMP-2 and EGFR expression 
and COX-2 in lung cancer cells. 
In conclusion, the present study revealed that COX-2 is very 
important in lung tumor growth, infiltration and metastasis via 
regulating VEGF, MMP-2 and EGFR expression. COX-2 may 
be a potential target for lung cancer prevention and treatment. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This study was financed by the Beijing Natural Science Foun-
dation (Beijing, China; grant no. 7153162). </p>



<p>ONCOLOGY LETTERS 12: 3836-3844, 2016 </p>





</text></tei>