<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5153420" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>a b s t r a c t </p>

<p>A 26-year-old pregnant woman in her first trimester presented with progressive fatigue. Her Electro-
cardiogram showed second degree heart block (Mobitz type II) with intermittent complete heart block. 
We decided to proceed with dual-chamber permanent pacemaker implantation using <rs type="software">CARTO</rs> mapping 
system to avoid fluoroscopy exposure. A mapping catheter was inserted through the right femoral vein. 
An electro-anatomical map of cardiac chambers was created using the mapping catheter. Through left 
axillary vein access, the two pacemaker leads were successfully positioned guided by the electro-
anatomical map. No complications were noted post procedure. Pacemaker was functioning appropri-
ately at follow-up visits. 
Fluoroscopy is the main imaging technique currently used for 
various cardiovascular procedures. However, use of fluoroscopy in 
pregnant women constitutes substantial hazards to the fetus. We 
present a case of a young pregnant woman with a complete 
Atrioventricular (AV) block in whom a permanent pacemaker 
(PPM) insertion was performed without fluoroscopy using electro-
anatomical mapping (EAM) system. </p>

<p>2. Case report </p>

<p>A 26-year-old pregnant woman in her first trimester presented 
with progressive fatigue and lightheadedness. Her past medical 
history was unremarkable. On presentation, she had regular heart 
rate of 38 beats-per-minute, blood pressure of 117/76 mmHg, res-
piratory rate of 16 breaths-per-minute, and temperature of 98.2 F. 
Pulse oximetry revealed an oxygen saturation level of 95% on room 
air. On physical examination she had bilateral 1 þ pitting pedal 
edema. Lung exam showed normal breath sounds. Cardiac exam 
showed normal heart sounds with 2/6 ejection systolic murmur </p>

<p>heard maximally at right upper sternal border with no radiations. 
The rest of the exam was unremarkable. Chest X-ray was normal. 
Electrocardiogram showed second degree heart block (Mobitz type 
II), right bundle branch block and intermittent third degree heart 
block (Fig. 1). Transthoracic echocardiogram (TTE) revealed normal 
left ventricular ejection fraction (65%), normal heart valves and 
normal right ventricular size and function. Pertinent laboratory 
studies revealed hemoglobin 13.8 g/dl, white blood count 
7.2 Â 10 
3 cells/ul, negative troponin and normal metabolic panel. </p>

<p>Exercise tolerance test was done and revealed worsening degree 
of heart block with exercise confirming infra-nodal conduction 
disease. Patient met class I indication for PPM implantation, and 
decision was made to proceed with dual-chamber PPM insertion 
using <rs type="software">CARTO</rs> mapping system (Biosense, Webster, Inc.) to avoid 
fluoroscopy exposure. 
A mapping catheter (Biosense, Webster, Inc.) was inserted 
through the right femoral vein. An EAM of the inferior vena cava, 
superior vena cava, right atrium (RA), coronary sinus ostium, 
tricuspid valve annulus (TVA) and the right ventricle (RV) septum 
was created using the mapping catheter. The right brachiocephalic 
trunk and the left innominate vein anatomy were further defined 
with the mapping. Following this, we proceeded with pacemaker 
implantation. Under local anesthesia, an oblique infra-clavicular 
incision was made on the skin and the pocket was subsequently 
created in the left pectoral area. Using ultrasound guidance, the left 
axillary vein was punctured, and two 6 French venous sheaths were 
advanced over separate guide wires. A 58 cm Ingevity (Boston </p>

<p>* Corresponding author. Department of Medicine, Rochester General Hospital, 
1425 Portland Avenue, Rochester, NY, 14621, United States. 
E-mail address: Ayman.Elbadawi@rochesterregional.org (A. Elbadawi). 
Peer review under responsibility of Indian Heart Rhythm Society. </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>Indian Pacing and Electrophysiology Journal </p>

<p>jo u rn a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / I P E J </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ipej.2016.11.003 
0972-6292/Copyright © 2016, Indian Heart Rhythm Society. Production and hosting by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Indian Pacing and Electrophysiology Journal 16 (2016) 172e174 </p>

<p>Scientific) pace-sense lead was connected to the CARTO mapping 
system to allow visualization of the lead tip in relation to the EAM. 
The first lead was advanced through the axillary vein and using 
EAM guidance was advanced across the TVA and positioned on the 
RV septum. Once adequate R wave sensing was noted the active 
fixation screw was deployed. Similarly a 52 cm lead was advanced 
using EAM guidance into the RA and positioned in the region of the 
RA appendage. Acceptable sensing, threshold and impedances of 
both leads were confirmed. The leads were attached to the device, 
and the device was inserted into the pocket which was closed with 
sutures. No complications were noted post procedure. Fig. 2 shows </p>

<p>successful placement of the pacemaker leads. Pacemaker was 
checked and was functioning appropriately at the follow-up visit. </p>

<p>3. Discussion </p>

<p>The incidence of heart block requiring PPM implantation in 
pregnancy is rare. Standard fluoroscopic-guided pacemaker im-
plantation carries considerable radiation risk to the fetus [1]. To 
overcome this major adverse effect, various techniques have been 
investigated as alternative guiding tools. Trans-esophageal echo-
cardiographic guidance have been suggested as an alternative to </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Electrocardiogram showing second degree heart block (Mobitz type II). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Right and left anterior oblique views using CARTO, showing successful placement of pacemaker leads. SVC ¼ superior vena cava; IVC ¼ inferior vena cava; RA ¼ right atrium; 
RV ¼ right ventricle; HB: His-bundle. </p>

<p>A. Elbadawi et al. / Indian Pacing and Electrophysiology Journal 16 (2016) 172e174 </p>

<p>
fluoroscopy; however, it has the disadvantages of lengthening the 
procedure-time, risk of aspiration and lack of accurate visualization 
of pacemaker leads during procedure [2,3].The other promising 
technique was the use of electro-anatomical navigation systems. 
These are devices which can guide catheter movement inside car-
diac chambers. They have been traditionally used for electrophys-
iological studies, and have been established to be effective and safe 
for these purposes [4]. Among the widely used EAM systems, is the 
Biosense Webster CARTO 
® system, which uses a magnetic field to </p>

<p>help pinpointing the exact location and orientation of catheters in 
the heart during procedures [5]. In addition to avoiding the harms 
of fluoroscopy, EAM systems offer the advantage of creating a 3D 
image which can efficiently guide catheters through different car-
diac chambers, compared to the 2D image offered by fluoroscopy 
[4]. 
We report a case of successful dual chamber PPM in a pregnant 
woman guided by non-fluoroscopic EAM system. Few case-series 
exist on using EAM guidance for PPM insertion in general popula-
tion [4,6]. To the best of our knowledge this is the third case of dual 
chamber PPM in a pregnant women using EAM system [3,7]. The 
EAM helped creating a geometric image of cardiac chambers, and 
with help of intracardiac recordings and pacing maneuvers, we 
were able to navigate our catheters properly. Specifically, we didn't 
appreciate difficulty crossing tricuspid valve annulus with the right 
ventricular (RV) lead or in placing the lead in RV apex with optimal 
pacing settings. 
In summary, we present a rare case of dual-chamber PPM im-
plantation in a pregnant woman, guided by EAM using <rs type="software">CARTO</rs> </p>

<p>system. The EAM system helped in creating 3D image of the heart 
and in guiding the pacemaker leads positioning. This case dem-
onstrates the use of EAM system as a safe alternative to fluoroscopy 
in pregnant women requiring PPM insertion. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest </p>

<p>Authors have no conflicts of interest to declare. </p>



<p>A. Elbadawi et al. / Indian Pacing and Electrophysiology Journal 16 (2016) 172e174 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>