<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5091022" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>r e v b r a s o r t o p . 2 0 1 6;5 1(5):547-554 </p>

<p>SOCIEDADE BRASILEIRA DE 
ORTOPEDIA E TRAUMATOLOGIA </p>

<p>w w w . r b o . o r g . b r </p>

<p>article 
under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>



<p>r e v b r a s o r t o p . 2 0 1 6;5 1(5):547-554 </p>

<p>A espessura do dreno suctor importa? Análise do sangramento após 
artroplastia total do joelho comparando drenos suctores de diferentes 
calibers </p>

<p>Palavras-chave: </p>

<p>Perda sanguínea cirúrgica </p>

<p>Artroplastia do joelho </p>

<p>Drenagem </p>

<p>r e s u m o </p>

<p>Objetivos: Avaliar o sangramento através do dreno suctor (DS) e a perda sanguínea estimada </p>

<p>em pacientes submetidos à artroplastia total do joelho (ATJ) com DS de diferentes calibers </p>

<p>(3,2 mm e 4,8 mm). </p>

<p>Métodos: Ensaio clínico randomizado com 22 pacientes submetidos à ATJ, divididos em </p>

<p>dois grupos; no grupo I, os pacientes recebiam o DS 3,2 mm e no Grupo II, o DS 4,8 mm. O </p>

<p>hematócrito foi aferido 24, 48 e 72 horas após a cirurgia, a fim de calcular a perda sanguínea </p>

<p>estimada. O débito do dreno foi medido 3, 6, 12, 24 e 48 horas após a ATJ e os dois grupos </p>

<p>foram comparados. </p>

<p>Resultados: Em relação ao hematócrito, não se observaram diferenças estatisticamente </p>

<p>significativas entre os grupos nos períodos aferidos (24, 48 e 72 horas pós-operatória). O </p>

<p>sangramento total medido no DS nas 48 horas foi maior no grupo II, com diferença esta-</p>

<p>tisticamente significativa (p = 0,005); nas primeiras 24 horas, houve maior sangramento no </p>

<p>grupo II (média 893 mL), com diferença significativa (p = 0,004). Entre 24 e 48 horas, não foram </p>

<p>observadas diferenças estatisticamente significativas em ambos os grupos (p = 0,710). O san-</p>

<p>gramento total estimado foi maior no Grupo I, com média de 463 mL, enquanto no Grupo II </p>

<p>esse valor foi de 409 mL, sem significância estatística (p = 0,394). </p>

<p>Conclusões: O sangramento foi maior no grupo que usou DS 4,8 mm, sem diferenças no </p>

<p>hematócrito e na perda sanguínea estimada. </p>

<p>The use of a wooden tube as a drain into a wound is credited 
to Hippocrates, at around 400 BC. 1 
Total knee replacement (TKR) is a standardized surgi-
cal procedure with high success rates in the treatment of 
advanced degenerative osteoarthritis (OA) and rheumatoid 
arthritis of this joint. Substantial bleeding can occur in 
the subcutaneous and intra-articular space after TKR; this 
event can lead to blood transfusions, with their potential 
complications. 2 Drainage is commonly used with the the-
oretical purpose of preventing hematomas, which, in turn, 
may decrease joint mobility and reduce local tissue perfusion, 
increasing the possibility of infection. Thus, drains can also be 
used to lower the risk of infection and prevent healing delay 
in TKR. 3 
Primary TKR can lead to a reduction in the erythrocyte 
levels. Various strategies have been used in order to reduce 
the need for blood products, such as tourniquet placed at 
the thigh root, coagulation diathermy, knee position, clamped 
drains, infiltration with vasoconstrictor solutions, antifibri-
nolytics (tranexamic acid, Floseal ® ), and computer-assisted 
surgeries. 4 
The use of suction drains (SD) in arthroplasties is still 
controversial. It is believed that the drainage is limited only 
to a restricted area, failing to prevent infection if retro-
grade migration of bacteria occurs. Drains can also hamper 
rehabilitation in the immediate postoperative period. There </p>

<p>is no obvious advantage of using SDs, other than lower 
need for dressing changes during surgery; moreover, in 
patients undergoing TKR with SDs, the risk of transfusion is 
higher. 5 
With the aging population, there has been increasing 
demand for joint replacements, which are effective meth-
ods to improve the quality of life with recovery of movement 
and improvement in pain, although these surgeries cause 
large blood loss and lead to dramatic consequences in 
patients with chronic illnesses; in prosthesis revision surger-
ies, the losses may be higher. There are formulas to better 
estimate blood loss; they are applied in studies to com-
pare blood loss between different techniques performed in 
surgery. 6 
To date, it is known that there is no difference regarding 
rate of surgical site infection and problems with surgi-
cal wound or postoperative rehabilitation, whether or not 
drains are used; there is a tendency to greater blood loss, 
hematoma formation, higher rate of use of blood products, 
and delay in recovery of joint function when they are used. 7 
In most publications that address TKRs with or without 
the use of SD, the study focus is bleeding and the rate of 
complications. 5 
The present study aimed to evaluate bleeding through the 
SD and the estimated blood loss, comparing patients who 
underwent TKR with SDs of different gauges (3.2 mm and 
4.8 mm), as well as to observe the period in which the major 
bleeding occurs, which is justified by the lack of data in the 
literature on this particular topic. </p>

<p>r e v b r a s o r t o p . 2 0 1 6;5 1(5):547-554 </p>



<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>This randomized clinical trial with 22 patients undergoing TKR 
was conducted between April and October 2015. 
A protocol was created for the study. Patients who met eligi-
bility criteria for TKR were assigned randomly into two groups 
(regardless of age, gender, and deformity): Group I used a 3.2-
mm diameter Portovac SD, and Group II, a 4.8-mm diameter 
Portovac SD, installed in the joint space prior to the closure of 
the capsule. 
The study included patients regularly registered in the 
institution where the study was performed, who met the 
classical indication for TKR advocated by Camanho et al. 8 : 
medial or lateral impingement with obliteration of the joint 
space, varus femorotibial alignment greater than 15 • ; valgus 
femorotibial alignment greater than 10 • ; tibiofemoral sublux-
ation in the frontal plane greater than 10 mm; anteriorization 
of the tibia relative to the femur in the profile X-ray; severe 
impairment of two of the three joint compartments of the knee 
(medial tibiofemoral, lateral tibiofemoral, or patellofemoral), 
and failed conservative treatment for at least three months 
when these criteria were not met. Patients with primary 
degenerative osteoarthritis of the knee. For this assessment, 
patients with osteoarthritis of the knee ≥stage III (Ählback 
modified by Keys) were considered. 9,10 
Exclusion criteria comprised patients undergoing revision 
surgery, those in whom the medial joint access was not used, 
those who were not operated by the senior surgeon, those with 
rheumatoid arthritis or multiple scars, and those who refused 
to sign or did not understand the informed consent form. 
Any patient with decompensated diabetes mellitus (fasting 
blood glucose &gt;140 mg/dL), uncontrolled hypertension (SBP 
&gt;200 mmHg), peripheral vascular disease, previous throm-
boembolism, neoplasia, active infection, rheumatoid arthritis, 
obese with a body mass index greater than 35 kg/m 2 , or those 
with a high surgical risk (American Society of Anesthesiolo-
gists [ASA] score &gt;III) had their medical condition re-evaluated 
and surgery was postponed. 
Patients who met inclusion criteria for this study (22) were 
randomized into groups accordingly to the waiting list for the 
procedure. Upon admission, the first patient was assigned to 
Group I, second, to Group II and so on; thus, odd-numbered 
patients were assigned to Group I and even-numbered, to 
Group II. The researcher had no influence on the decision 
process of who would be operated; only at the moment of 
drain insertion was he made aware of which group the patient 
belonged to. 
The night before surgery, hemoglobin and hematocrit 
(Hb-pre, Ht-pre) levels were measured. These values were con-
sidered as controls; patients were weighed in kilograms and 
their height was measured in centimeters. 
Patients underwent spinal anesthesia and received a 
prophylactic dose of antibiotics -cefazolin 2 g -by the anes-
thesiologist. A pneumatic tourniquet was applied on the root 
of the thigh of the limb to be operated, with a pressure of 
300 mmHg for all patients. Surgical technique adopted was the 
standard TKR with joint access via a classic trans-quadriceps 
approach and patellar eversion. Authors' routine is the use </p>

<p>of intramedullary guides for femoral cuts and extramedullary 
guides for tibial cuts. The posterior cruciate ligament (PCL) was 
resected in all procedures. The patella was not resurfaced, and 
was prepared in all cases as follows: after local denervation 
and synovectomy, to avoid clunk syndrome, the patella was 
eburnated and neurotized, and a lateral fasciotomy was per-
formed. The prosthesis used was the AKS Modular Bloqueada ® 
(Baumer, Mogi Miring, SP, Brazil), a non-PCL-sparing prosthe-
sis. Portovac SDs of 3.2 mm and 4.8 mm were placed in the 
joint space before capsular closure. In order to standardize the 
drainage area, all the ends of the drains were cut so that they 
were 10 cm long in the joint and the lateral recess. The Por-
tovac drain is a post-operative polyethylene closed drainage 
system, whose resistance is designed for a continuous and 
mild suction. It has a vacuum pump with a capacity of 500 mL, 
with an attachment cord, an intermediate section made of 
polyvinyl chloride (PVC), a clamp, a two-or three-way con-
nector, and a drainage catheter with a surgical-grade stainless 
steel needle (3.2 mm, 4.8 mm, or 6.4 mm), used to puncture 
the drain passage site. 11 After wound closure, an inguinal-
malleolar compressive occlusive Robert Jones dressing was 
applied. If surgery lasted over 2 h, the tourniquet was deflated 
and the ischemia was released; subsequently, hemostasis was 
assessed, inserting drains, sutures, and dressings. All surger-
ies were always performed by the principal investigator or 
under his direct assistance. Blood loss was measured though 
serial Hb and Ht counts at 24, 48, and 72 h (the last measure-
ment was considered as the Hb-post and Ht-post) and through 
blood volume, serially measured on the SD at 3, 6, 12, 24 and 
48 h after the end of the surgical procedure. In this last mea-
surement, the SD was removed and dressing was changed. The 
surgeon was not involved in the measurement of SD volumes. 
All patients received thromboprophylaxis with enoxaparin 
sodium at a dose of 40 mg subcutaneous 6 h after the proce-
dure, administered once a day for 15 days. All patients received 
prophylaxis for surgical site infection with cefazolin sodium 
at a dose of 1 g every 8 h for five days. 
With the data on weight, height, and Ht-pre, Hb-pre, Ht-
post, and Hb-post, blood volume of the patient was calculated 
according to the formula of Nadler et al., 12 and blood loss 
was estimated according to the method proposed by Mercuri-
ali and Inghilleri. 13 In the present study, the authors chose to 
use the three-day postoperative hematocrit for calculation of 
blood loss, instead of the five-day originally described. 
Blood volume = Males: 604 + 0.0003668 × height (cm 3 ) 
+ 32.2 × weight (kg). 
Women: 183 + 0.000356 × height (cm 3 ) + 33 × weight (kg). 
Estimated blood loss: =blood volume × (Ht-pre − Ht-
post) + red blood cell volume (CH). 
Data were presented in graphs and tables, in which the 
simple and relative absolute frequencies were calculated for 
categorical data in the group comparison. In the analysis of 
quantitative data, mean, standard deviation (SD), and 95% 
confidence intervals (95% CI) were calculated, as the normal-
ity hypothesis was accepted according to the Shapiro-Wilk 
test, at a significance level of 5% (p &gt; 0.05). When comparing 
means, Student's t-test was used; categorical data were com-
pared using Fisher's exact test. The significance level was set 
at 5%. 14 </p>



<p>r e v b r a s o r t o p . 2 0 1 6;5 1(5):547-554 </p>

<p>Table 1 -Distribution by frequency of gender and age in relation to suction drain group (3.2 mm × 4.8 mm). </p>

<p>Variables 
Drain 
Total 
p </p>

<p>3.2 
(n = 11) </p>

<p>4.8 
(n = 11) </p>

<p>f i 
% 
f i 
% </p>

<p>Gender 
0.998 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Female 
0 
81.8 
8 
72.7 
17 
Male 
2 
18.2 
3 
27.3 
5 </p>

<p>Age (years) 
0.283 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>&lt;60 
3 
27.3 
3 
27.3 
6 
60-70 
5 
45.4 
7 
63.6 
12 
≥60 
3 
27.3 
1 
9.1 
4 
Mean ± SD 
65.8 ± 6.6 
62.8 ± 6.1 
Min.-Max. 
56-78 
54-74 </p>

<p>f i , simple absolute frequency; SD, standard deviation. 
a Fisher's exact test. 
b Student's t-test was used to compare the means. </p>

<p><rs id="software-2" type="software">The Epi-Info</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 7.1.5</rs> for Windows, which is 
developed and freely distributed by the <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">www.cdc.gov/epiinfo/7</rs>), was used for 
statistical analysis. 15 
All patients read and signed a informed consent form; the 
study was submitted to the Research Ethics Committee (REC) 
of the institution, with Certificate of Presentation for Ethi-
cal Assessment (CAAE) No. 43085615.8.0000.0007, and received 
REC opinion No. 1019123. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Group I consisted of 11 patients, nine females and two males, 
aged 56-78 years, with a mean of 65.8 years and SD ± 6.6 years. 
Group II consisted of eight female patients and three males, 
with a mean age of 62.8 years (54-74, SD ± 6.1 years). Epidemi-
ological data are summarized in Table 1. 
In the observation of the SD bleeding curve at 3, 6, 12, 24, 
and 48 h (Fig. 1), a decrease was observed from 3 h onwards; 
no statistically significant differences were observed for both 
groups, except for the interval between 3 and 6 h, with 
increased bleeding in Group II (p = 0.001). 
Regarding hematocrit, according to Fig. 2, no statistically 
significant differences were observed between the groups in 
the measured periods (24, 48, and 72 h postoperative), and the 
downward curve remained stable from 24 h onwards, with a 
constant pattern. 
The total bleeding measured in the SD within 48 h (Fig. 3) 
was higher in Group II (mean 920 mL) than in Group I (680 mL), 
with statistically significant difference (p = 0.005); when such 
bleeding was stratified into 24 and 48 h, it was observed that 
within the first 24 h (Fig. 4), there was a higher bleeding in 
Group II (mean 893 mL), with statistically significant differ-
ences (p = 0.004). Between 24 and 48 h (Fig. 5), no statistically 
significant differences were observed in both groups (Group I: 
24 mL × Group II: 27 mL), p = 0.710. </p>

<p>Drain </p>

<p>48h 
24h 
12h 
6h 
3h </p>

<p>4.8 
3.2 
4.8 
3.2 
4.8 
3.2 
4.8 
3.2 
4.8 
3.2 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>mL </p>

<p>401 </p>

<p>356 </p>

<p>241 </p>

<p>127 </p>

<p>151 </p>

<p>111 
100 </p>

<p>62 </p>

<p>27 
24 </p>

<p>10.06 </p>

<p>44.49 </p>

<p>10.79 </p>

<p>36.48 
59.58 </p>

<p>140.42 </p>

<p>32.26 </p>

<p>91.38 
111.00 </p>

<p>190.82 </p>

<p>75.81 </p>

<p>146.92 
184.42 </p>

<p>297.39 </p>

<p>88.75 </p>

<p>164.89 </p>

<p>301.42 </p>

<p>500.39 </p>

<p>287.70 </p>

<p>425.02 </p>

<p>*P=.421 
*P=.001 
.710 
= 
*P 
.115 
= 
*P 
*P=.105 </p>

<p>* Student's t-test. Bold and italic p-values indicate statistically significant difference 
at the 5% level. </p>

<p>Fig. 1 -Distribution, according to the mean and 95% CI, of 
bleeding at 3, 6, 12, 24, and 48 h, in relation to SD thickness. 
CI, confidence interval; SD, suction drain. </p>

<p>Drain </p>

<p>72h 
48h 
24h 
Pre </p>

<p>4.8 
3.2 
4.8 
3.2 
4.8 
3.2 
4.8 
3.2 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>36.1 </p>

<p>37.3 </p>

<p>28.8 
29.1 </p>

<p>26.7 
27.3 </p>

<p>28.1 
27.7 </p>

<p>26.22 </p>

<p>30.02 </p>

<p>24.92 </p>

<p>30.39 </p>

<p>24.87 </p>

<p>28.48 </p>

<p>23.95 </p>

<p>30.63 </p>

<p>26.67 </p>

<p>30.91 </p>

<p>25.22 </p>

<p>32.89 
33.79 </p>

<p>38.43 </p>

<p>34.96 </p>

<p>39.64 </p>

<p>*P=.430 
*P=.894 
*P=.760 
*P=.720 </p>

<p>* Student's t-test </p>

<p>Fig. 2 -Distribution, according to the mean and 95% CI, of 
preoperative hematocrit at 24, 48, and 72 h postoperatively 
in relation to SD. 
CI, confidence interval; SD, suction drain. </p>

<p>r e v b r a s o r t o p . 2 0 1 6;5 1(5):547-554 </p>



<p>4.8 
3.2 </p>

<p>1.100 </p>

<p>1.000 </p>

<p>900 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>Drain </p>

<p>P=.005 (Student's t-test). </p>

<p>mL </p>

<p>920 </p>

<p>680 </p>

<p>789.00 </p>

<p>1051.00 </p>

<p>576.14 </p>

<p>783.86 </p>

<p>Fig. 3 -Distribution, according to the mean and 95% CI, of 
the total blood loss in relation to SD thickness in patients 
who underwent total knee replacement. 
CI, confidence interval; SD, suction drain. </p>

<p>Estimated blood loss by the formula proposed by Mercuriali 
and Inghilleri 14 (Fig. 6) was higher in Group I, with a mean of 
463 mL versus Group II, 409 mL, with no statistical significance, 
p = 0.394. The use of blood products was similar in both groups 
-two units of red blood cells with 300 mL each unit. In the 
study period, there was only one case of complication in Group </p>

<p>II: blister formation in the wound of a patient who required two 
concentrated units of red blood cells. 
Student's t-test was used to assess whether there was a 
correlation between bleeding and height, and between weight 
and bleeding. No correlations were observed between these 
variables (Tables 2 and 3), in which the values of the coefficient 
closest to 1 and −1 indicate a strong evidence of correlation. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Although there is no established evidence to confirm the 
use of drains in TKR, it is postulated that it can reduce 
hematoma formation and the incidence of deep infection. 
Esler et al. 16 suggest that these perceptions are incorrect, as </p>

<p>4.8 
3.2 </p>

<p>1.100 </p>

<p>1.000 </p>

<p>900 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>Drain </p>

<p>mL </p>

<p>893 </p>

<p>656 </p>

<p>766.72 </p>

<p>1018.74 </p>

<p>554.69 </p>

<p>758.04 </p>

<p>P=.004 (Student's t-test). </p>

<p>Fig. 4 -Distribution, according to the mean and 95% CI, of 
bleeding in the first 24 h in relation to SD thickness. 
CI, confidence interval; SD, suction drain. </p>

<p>4.8 
3.2 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Drain </p>

<p>mL </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>10.06 </p>

<p>44.49 </p>

<p>10.79 </p>

<p>36.48 </p>

<p>P=.710 (Student's t-test). </p>

<p>Fig. 5 -Distribution, according to the mean and 95% CI, of 
bleeding in between 24 and 48 h in relation to SD thickness. 
CI, confidence interval; SD, suction drain. </p>

<p>4.8 
3.2 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>550 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>450 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>Drain </p>

<p>mL </p>

<p>409 </p>

<p>463 </p>

<p>309.37 </p>

<p>507.90 </p>

<p>364.96 </p>

<p>561.58 </p>

<p>P=.394 (Student's t-test). </p>

<p>Fig. 6 -Distribution, according to the mean and 95% CI, of 
the estimated blood loss (Mercurialli and Inghilleri 13 ) in 
relation to SD gauge in patients who underwent total knee 
replacement. 
CI, confidence interval; SD, suction drain. </p>

<p>their study failed to demonstrate a statistically significant ben-
efit with the use of intra-articular drain on cemented TKR. 
The use of SDs may even be harmful. Surgeons are used to 
place drains and the fear of morbidity of deep infection is </p>

<p>Table 2 -Correlation of bleeding time and height of 
patients who underwent total knee replacement. </p>

<p>Bleeding 
Height </p>

<p>r 
p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>3 hours 
0.12 
0.594 
6 hours 
0.5 
0.815 
12 hours 
−0.10 
0.658 
24 hours 
0.2 
0.935 
Up to 24 hours 
0.7 
0.744 
48 hours 
0.1 
0.955 
Blood loss 
0.7 
0.746 </p>

<p>r, correlation coefficient. 
a t-Test for correlation. </p>



<p>r e v b r a s o r t o p . 2 0 1 6;5 1(5):547-554 </p>

<p>Table 3 -Correlation of bleeding time and weight (in kg) 
of patients who underwent total knee replacement. </p>

<p>Bleeding 
Weight </p>

<p>r 
p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>3 hours 
0.3 
0.886 
6 hours 
0.39 
0.72 
12 hours 
−0.1 
0.977 
24 hours 
−0.12 
0.568 
Up to 24 hours 
0.16 
0.486 
48 hours 
0.23 
0.295 
Blood loss 
0.18 
0.430 </p>

<p>r, correlation coefficient. 
a t-Test for correlation. </p>

<p>understandable; therefore, there is resistance to changing this 
practice. 
Parker et al. 17 found that the only definite advantage of 
using drains, demonstrated in a meta-analysis, was to reduce 
the bleeding through the wound, as shown by the smaller 
number of dressings in the group in which drains were used. 
Furthermore, the use of drains reduced local lesions at the 
surgical site. 
The number of blood transfusions in this study was simi-
lar in both groups (two concentrated units of red blood cells in 
each). In studies until 2004, the authors reported that closed 
suction drainage increased transfusion requirements after 
elective hip and knee arthroplasties, and greater benefits were 
not observed. 17 
Only SDs were used in the joint cavity. The data in the study 
by Seo et al. 2 suggest that subcutaneous drainage is similar 
to that used for closed suction intra-articular drainage, with 
equivalent blood loss and without adverse effects on func-
tional results; therefore, the use of SD in the subcutaneous 
is a reasonable option against intra-articular. 
Higher bleeding was observed in both groups within the 
first 6 h, with a higher value in the group of patients with 
the 4.8-mm drain, but without a statistically significant differ-
ence (p = 0.421). Goes et al. 18 compared the laboratory results of 
opening the drain at six and 12 h after TKR, and did not observe 
statistically significant differences in laboratory values. How-
ever, the volume of drained blood was higher when the drain 
was opened after 6 h. Those authors only used 4.8-mm drains. 
Roy et al. 19 conducted a study with immediate drain open-
ing 1 h after the end of surgery; they observed blood loss and 
increased need for blood products in the group where the 
drain was opened immediately. These authors did not men-
tion the thickness of the drain; they stated that two access 
routes were placed in the joint space and were removed after 
48 h. 
It was observed that the bleeding after 24 h becomes 
insignificant; in 1991, Willemen et al. 20 concluded that the 
clinical evaluations of surgical wound healing were similar 
for all groups (drain removed after 24 and 48 h) and clearly 
showed no advantage in continuing use of the drain after 
24 h; if drainage is maintained for a longer period, there is 
an increased risk of bacterial contamination. 85% of the total </p>

<p>volume was drained during the first 24 h; in the following 24 h, 
an average of only 50 mL of blood was drained, but the authors 
did not mention the gauge of the drains. Drinkwater and Neil 21 
recommend that drains in hip or knee replacements should 
also be removed after 24 h. 
Beer et al., 3 in their classical publication from 1991, went 
further, demonstrating that there is no difference regarding 
the incidence of edema or persistent draining through the 
wound. The return to active quadriceps function and knee 
range of motion in patients who underwent TKR was also not 
affected by the use of SDs. They concluded that the routine 
use of drains in uncomplicated surgery is unnecessary. Sim-
ilarly, Zhang et al., 22 in a meta-analysis published in 2014, 
concluded that, for primary surgery without major compli-
cations, it is preferable to not use SDs; the surgeon should 
assess the benefits and drawbacks. In the present study, 
there was only one complication (blisters) in the 4.8-mm SD 
group. 
Andrade et al., 23 in a Brazilian publication that compared 
the use or non-use of 3.2-mm SDs, came to the conclusion 
that, beyond six months post-operative, there is no benefit 
in the use of closed SD in TKR. However, range of motion 
at the end of the first month was better in the group that 
used SD. 
In the present study, bleeding was higher within the first 
6 h after surgery for both groups, as the drains remained 
open. Yildiz et al. 24 took into account the clamping of the 
drain for 6 h after TKR and observed that, in the group 
in which the tourniquet was released after the sutures 
and bandages were applied and the drain was closed for 
6 h, there was less blood loss. Souza Leão et al. 25 did not 
take into account clamping of the SD in TKR, and com-
pared blood loss with early or late release of the tourniquet; 
they found no statistically significant differences in bleed-
ing, but there was no mention of the diameter of the drains. 
Hemoglobin and hematocrit levels also were similar for both 
groups. 
In a recent meta-analysis, Li at al. 26 concluded that, 
through the current evidence, the use or non-use of SDs has 
similar utility and clinical significance in primary TKR. How-
ever, due to some limitations (few patients involved in each 
study and only three randomized controlled trials), their find-
ings should be interpreted with caution. Therefore, future 
studies of high methodological quality and long-term follow-
up are necessary to update the meta-analysis, in order to 
better assess the importance and effectiveness of the use of 
drains. 
It is well established that the total number of hip replace-
ments, and especially TKRs, will increase over the next 25 
years. 27 These operations are known to have a high volume 
of blood loss; however, it is difficult to compare the amount 
of these losses given the fact that many different formulas 
are used to calculate losses. A precise method for calculat-
ing estimated blood loss in joint replacements is essential 
for a better assessment of the perioperative losses estimates. 
With this in mind, in 1996 Mercuriali and Inghilleri 13 devel-
oped an algorithm to calculate probable losses and the need 
for blood transfusions. This formula is based on preoperative 
hematocrit (Ht-pre) and hematocrit on the fifth postoperative </p>

<p>r e v b r a s o r t o p . 2 0 1 6;5 1(5):547-554 </p>



<p>day (Ht-post). The hematocrit should be written in deci-
mal units. This formula requires the patient's blood volume 
to be calculated by the formula postulated by Nadler at 
al. 13 (in milliliters of blood) and also requires the volume 
of blood (red blood cells) transfused. The estimate obtained 
by the Mercuriali formula is given in milliliters of red blood 
cells. 
The limiting factors of the present study include the small 
follow-up time (only during admission), in which no differ-
ences were observed in joint function and the rate of infection; 
other complications were not the object of this study, which 
probably would show further advantages of one method over 
the other and could abound for further research. Pain was 
also not quantified. A sample with a larger number of patients 
would provide more robustness to the statistical analysis. As 
patients were on the first three days of intravenous hydration 
and blood count also depends on the hydration status, per-
haps numbers were higher than the noted, proving the low 
use of blood products; however, a theoretical framework that 
takes into account the hydration of patients was not retrieved. 
A group without SD -control -would be ideal to compare the 
blood count and the estimated blood loss, and hence justify 
the use or non-use of SD. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>The present data allows for the conclusion that patients 
undergoing TKR have higher bleeding when they have a 4.8-
mm SD inserted. Estimated blood loss is similar, regardless 
of the thickness of the drains used. Bleeding is higher in the 
first 24 h after surgery, especially in the first 6 h; during the last 
24 h, bleeding is negligible, and therefore the use of the drain 
is unnecessary. Reduction in hematocrit was similar for both 
groups and was more pronounced on the first day, remaining 
stable thereafter. Bleeding through SD in TKR is a reality that 
cannot be underestimated; the surgeon should be aware of 
possible complications of this event and promptly resolve it. 
Rational use of the drain and choice of its gauge are at the 
surgeon's discretion, bearing in mind that thicker drains can 
cause increased bleeding. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>r e f e r e n c e s </p>





<p>r e v b r a s o r t o p . 2 0 1 6;5 1(5):547-554 </p>



</text></tei>