<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5436475" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Stroke remains the leading cause of death and disability worldwide. This fact highlights the need to 
search for potential drug targets that can reduce stroke-related brain damage. We showed 
recently that a glycogen synthase kinase-3β (GSK-3β) inhibitor attenuates tissue plasminogen 
activator-induced hemorrhagic transformation after permanent focal cerebral ischemia. Here, we 
examined whether GSK-3β inhibition mitigates early ischemia-reperfusion stroke injury and 
investigated its potential mechanism of action. We used the rat middle cerebral artery occlusion 
(MCAO) model to mimic transient cerebral ischemia. At 3.5 h after MCAO, cerebral blood flow 
was restored, and rats were administered DMSO (vehicle, 1% in saline) or GSK-3β inhibitor 
TWS119 (30 mg/kg) by intraperitoneal injection. Animals were sacrificed 24 h after MCAO. 
TWS119 treatment reduced neurologic deficits, brain edema, infarct volume, and blood-brain 
barrier permeability compared with those in the vehicle group. TWS119 treatment also increased 
the protein expression of β-catenin and zonula occludens-1 but decreased β-catenin 
phosphorylation while suppressing the expression of GSK-3β. These results indicate that GSK-3β 
inhibition protects the blood-brain barrier and attenuates early ischemia-reperfusion stroke injury. 
This protection may be related to early activation of the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway. </p>

<p>Stroke is a leading cause of death and disability 
worldwide. Thus, identifying potential new drug 
targets is critical to developing therapies that will 
reduce stroke-related brain damage. It is known that 
early disruption of the blood-brain barrier (BBB) 
contributes to acute cerebral ischemia-reperfusion 
injury 1 In recent years, new strategies, such as delayed 
inhibition of VEGF signaling 2 , and new drug 
candidates, such as a novel analog of ginkgolide B 
(XQ-1H) 3 a novel adhesion molecule CEACAM1 4 , </p>

<p>orosomucoid 5 , and lavandula officinalis ethanolic 
extract 6 , have been tested for their potential to protect 
the BBB in ischemic stroke models. Because the results 
from these studies have been promising, increasing 
attention is turning toward the identification of 
potential drug targets to protect the BBB after 
ischemic stroke. 
The Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway is 
involved in development of the BBB 7 , and its 
dysfunction could lead to BBB breakdown in </p>

<p>Ivyspring </p>

<p>International Publisher </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2017, Vol. 14 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Alzheimer's disease 8 . Furthermore, activation of 
Wnt/β-catenin signaling enhances neurogenesis and 
improves neurologic function after focal ischemic 
injury 9 . However, the role of the Wnt/β-catenin 
signaling pathway in BBB breakdown and its effects 
on stroke outcomes are unknown. 
Studies have shown that the serine-threonine 
kinase glycogen synthase kinase-3β (GSK-3β) is 
involved in the phosphorylation and degradation of 
β-catenin 10 , the key molecule of the Wnt/β-catenin 
pathway 11 . Therefore, inhibition of GSK-3β may 
increase the level of β-catenin and further activate the 
Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway. TWS119, a 
4,6-disubstituted pyrrolo-pyrimidine, is a potent 
inhibitor of GSK-3β 12 . We have recently shown that 
TWS119 attenuates tissue plasminogen activator 
(tPA)-induced hemorrhagic transformation after 
permanent middle cerebral artery occlusion 
(MCAO) 13 . 
In the present study, we used a rat model of 
transient MCAO to mimic the clinical scenario of 
acute ischemic stroke, and administered TWS119 to 
activate the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway. We 
hypothesized that GSK-3β inhibition would protect 
the BBB and reduce early ischemia-reperfusion stroke 
injury. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>All protocols used in this study were approved 
by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee 
at Wuhan University. Adult male Sprague-Dawley 
rats weighing 250-280 g were purchased from Wuhan 
University Center for Animal Experiments and 
housed under standard conditions with a 12:12 h 
light/dark cycle. Food and water were provided to all 
animals ad libitum. The operators were blinded to the 
treatment status of the animals in all experiments. </p>

<p>MCAO Model </p>

<p>Focal cerebral ischemia was produced by 
endovascular occlusion of the left middle cerebral 
artery (MCA) as described previously 14-16 Briefly, rats 
were anesthetized by intraperitoneal injection with 
pentobarbital sodium (Dainippon Sumitomo Pharma, 
Osaka, Japan). Body temperature was maintained at 
36.5°C to 37.5°C throughout surgery. After a midline 
neck incision, the left common carotid artery (CCA) 
was isolated under a microscope and ligated with a 
4-0 silk suture (Ethicon, Issy-Les-Moulineaux, France). 
The external and internal carotid arteries were 
temporarily ligated with a 4-0 silk suture. An 
arteriotomy was performed proximal to the 
bifurcation of the CCA. A silicone-coated nylon 
monofilament (40 mm long, 0.26 mm diameter, </p>

<p>Beijing Sunbio Biotech, China) was introduced 
through the arteriotomy and advanced into the 
internal carotid artery up to a distance of 18-20 mm to 
occlude the origin of the MCA. At 3.5 hours after this 
procedure, the rats were reanesthetized, the nylon 
monofilament was withdrawn to restore MCA blood 
flow, and TWS119 (30 mg/kg in 1% dimethy 
sulfoxide, Selleck, Houston, TX, USA) 17, 18 or an equal 
volume of vehicle (DMSO) was administered. After 
surgery, the rats were returned to their home cages 
with free access to food and water. A third group of 
sham control rats underwent the same surgical 
procedure but the monofilament was not inserted and 
they were administered only DMSO. </p>

<p>Neurologic Deficit Score </p>

<p>An investigator blinded to the experimental 
groups performed a neurologic examination of the 
rats at 24 h after MCAO using a modified version of 
the scoring system developed by Longa 19 : 0, no 
deficits; 1, difficulty in fully extending the 
contralateral forelimb; 2, unable to extend the 
contralateral forelimb; 3, mild circling to the 
contralateral side; 4, severe circling; 5, falling to the 
contralateral side. The higher the neurologic deficit 
score, the more severe the impairment of motor 
motion. </p>

<p>Brain Water Content </p>

<p>Brain water content was measured with the 
standard wet-dry ratio method 20 . Rats were 
anesthetized and killed by decapitation at 24 h after 
MCAO. The brains were quickly removed and placed 
on a dry surface. A 4-mm-thick section of the frontal 
pole was dissected free before the brain was cut by a 
brain slicer (Beijing Sunny Instruments Co., Ltd., 
Beijing, China) and divided into the ipsilateral and 
contralateral hemispheres. The two hemisphere slices 
were packaged in preweighed aluminum foil and 
immediately weighed on an electronic balance to 
obtain the wet weight. The hemispheres were then 
dried for 24 h in an oven at 100°C and reweighed to 
obtain the dry weight. Brain water content was 
calculated as a percentage with the following formula: 
(wet weight − dry weight)/wet weight × 100% 21 </p>

<p>Brain Infarct Volume </p>

<p>Infarct volume after MCAO was determined by 
2, 3, 5-triphenyltetrazolium chloride (TTC, Sigma, 
Santa Clara, CA) at 24 h after MCAO. Animals were 
euthanized, and the brains were quickly collected. 
Brain tissue was sliced into seven coronal sections 
(2-mm thick) and stained with a 2% solution of TTC at 
37°C for 20 min, followed by fixation with 4% 
paraformaldehyde. TTC stains normal tissue red, but 
the infarct area remains a pale gray color. TTC-stained </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2017, Vol. 14 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>sections 
were 
photographed, 
and 
Image-J 
image-processing software was used to calculate the 
infarct volume. The ratio of infarct volume = infarct 
area of the ipsilateral hemisphere/total area of the 
ipsilateral hemisphere × 100% 22 . </p>

<p>Evaluation of BBB Permeability </p>

<p>Evans blue (EB) dye (2%, 3 ml/kg, Sigma) was 
administered intravenously 3 h before the brain was 
collected. After being perfused with saline, each 
hemisphere was weighed and homogenized in 4 ml of 
50% trichloroacetic acid solution. The homogenates 
were centrifuged at 10,000×g for 30 min, and the 
supernatants were collected and diluted with ethanol 
(1:3). EB content was determined on a 
spectrophotometer (Epoch™&amp;Take3™, Biotek, USA) 
at 620 nm and calculated from a standard curve of EB. 
EB extravasation was expressed as EB extravasation 
index (EBI): the ratio of absorbance intensity in the 
ischemic hemisphere to that in the nonischemic 
hemisphere 23 . </p>

<p>Western Blotting </p>

<p>Based on our established protocol 24, 25 , the total 
protein were prepared using Cytoplasmic and 
Nuclear Protein Extraction Kit (Feremants, Shanghai, 
China) and equal amounts of total protein were 
separated by Tris-glycine SDS-PAGE and transferred 
to polyvinylidene difluoride membranes. Membranes 
were blocked with 5% skim milk and then incubated 
with the following primary antibodies overnight at 
4°C: (1) rabbit polyclonal anti-GAPDH antibody 
(1:1000, Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, 
USA); (2) rabbit polyclonal anti-β-catenin antibody 
(1:5000, Abcam, Cambridge, MA, USA); (3) rabbit 
polyclonal anti-phosphorylated β-catenin (Ser 552) 
antibody (1:1000, Cell Signaling Technology, 
Cambridge, MA, USA); 
(4) mouse polyclonal 
anti-GSK-3β 
antibody 
(1:1000, Cell Signaling 
Technology); (5) rabbit 
polyclonal anti-zonula 
accludens-1 
(ZO-1) 
antibody (1:100, Santa 
Cruz 
Biotechnology, 
Dallas, TX, USA). After 
incubation with the 
secondary 
antibody 
(1:1000, Cell Signaling 
Technology) for 2 h, 
membranes 
were 
washed three times with 
phosphate-buffered 
saline (10 min each), and </p>

<p>the relative density of bands was analyzed on an 
Odyssey infrared scanner (LICOR Bioscience, Lincoln, 
NE, USA). </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>All data are expressed as mean ± SD. <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> for 
<rs type="software">Windows</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">16.0</rs> software package was used to analyze 
the data. Differences among groups were determined 
by one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey post-hoc 
tests. Student's t-test was used to compare the 
difference between two groups. Differences were 
considered significant at P values less than 0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Mortality Rates </p>

<p>Mortality was 0% (0/24) in the sham group, 
12.5% (3/24) in the vehicle group, and 4.2% (1/24) in 
the TWS119 group. Mortality rate was not 
significantly different among the three groups (P &gt; 
0.05). </p>

<p>GSK-3β Inhibition by TWS119 Improved 
Neurologic Function, Cerebral Edema, and 
Infarction Volume After Transient MCAO </p>

<p>Neurologic deficit, brain water content, and 
infarct volume were evaluated 24 h after MCAO. 
TWS119 significantly reduced the neurologic deficit 
scores compared with those in the vehicle group 
(n=24 rats/group, P &lt; 0.05; Fig. 1.A). No neurologic 
deficit was observed in the sham group (data not 
shown). Similarly, brain water content was lower and 
infarct volume was smaller in the TWS119-treated 
group than in the vehicle-treated group (n=6 
rats/group, both P&lt;0.05; Figs. 1.B and 2), suggesting 
that GSK-3β inhibition attenuates brain edema and 
infarct volume after transient MCAO. The sham 
group exhibited no cerebral edema or infarction. </p>

<p>Figure 1. A. Neurologic deficit score at 24 h after transient middle cerebral artery occlusion (MCAO). Rats were treated 
with vehicle or TWS119 (n=24 rats/group). The data are expressed as means ± SD. *P&lt;0.05 vs. vehicle group. B. Brain water 
content at 24 h after transient middle cerebral artery occlusion (MCAO). The data are expressed as means ± SD. *P&lt;0.05, 
**P&lt;0.01 vs. sham group. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2017, Vol. 14 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Figure 2. Infarct volume at 24 h after transient middle cerebral artery 
occlusion (MCAO). Rats were treated with vehicle or TWS119 (n=6 
rats/group). A. Representative TTC-stained, 2-mm coronal brain sections. B. 
Quantification of the infarct volume in groups that underwent MCAO and 
treatment with vehicle or TWS119. Infarct volume was calculated as a 
percentage as follows: infarct area of the ipsilateral hemisphere/total area of the 
ipsilateral hemisphere × 100%. No infarction was detected in the sham group. 
The results are expressed as means ± SD. *P&lt;0.05 vs. vehicle group. </p>

<p>GSK-3β Inhibition by TWS119 Decreased BBB 
Permeability After Transient MCAO </p>

<p>In our study, EB dye leakage was concentrated 
mainly in the regions of ischemic hemisphere, and 
BBB leakage was shown with the EBI. We found that 
EBI of the TWS119-treated group was significantly 
lower than that of the vehicle-treated group (n=6 
rats/group, P&lt;0.05; Fig. 3), indicating that GSK-3β 
inhibition protects the BBB after transient MCAO. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Blood-brain barrier permeability as measured by Evans blue leakage 
at 24 h after transient middle cerebral artery occlusion (MCAO). Rats were 
treated with vehicle or TWS119 (n=6 rats/group). The Evans blue index (ratio 
of absorbance intensity in the ischemic hemisphere to that in the nonischemic 
hemisphere) was used to evaluate blood-brain barrier permeability. The results 
are expressed as means ± SD. *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01 vs. sham group. </p>

<p>GSK-3β Inhibition by TWS119 Activated the 
Wnt/β-Catenin Signaling Pathway and 
Increased the Expression of ZO-1 After 
Transient MCAO </p>

<p>Western blot quantification showed that the total 
protein expression of β-catenin was upregulated, 
whereas phosphorylated β-catenin (p-β-catenin) and 
GSK-3β expression were downregulated in the 
TWS119-treated group compared with that in the 
vehicle-treated group (n=6 rats/group, P&lt;0.05; Fig. 4). 
And the ratio of p-β-catenin to the total β-catenin was 
reduced significantly after TWS119 treatment(n=6 
rats/group, P&lt;0.05; Fig. 4). Additionally, the 
expression of ZO-1 was significantly higher in the 
TWS119-treated group than in the vehicle-treated 
group (n=6 rats/group, P&lt;0.05; Fig. 4). These data 
indicate that GSK-3β inhibition by TWS119 might 
activate the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway, which 
is associated with increased ZO-1 expression and 
attenuated BBB disruption. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, GSK-3β inhibition by TWS119 
reduced neurologic deficit score, brain edema, infarct 
volume, and BBB disruption. This protection was 
associated with an early activation of Wnt/β-catenin 
signaling and an increase in ZO-1 expression. 
Together, these findings suggest that GSK-3β 
inhibition by TWS119 attenuates early ischemia-
reperfusion injury and protects the BBB. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2017, Vol. 14 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Figure 4. Western blot analysis of proteins in the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway and tight junctions of the blood-brain barrier 24 h after transient MCAO (n=6 
rats/group). Representative Western blots and densitometric analysis of (A) total β-catenin, (B) phosphorylated β-catenin, (C) The ratio of p-β-catenin to the total 
β-catenin, (D) GSK-3β and (E) zonula accludens-1 (ZO-1). GAPDH was used as a loading control. The expression of β-catenin and ZO-1 increased in the 
TWS119-treated group compared to that in the vehicle-treated group. TWS119 treatment reduced the expression of phosphorylated β-catenin and GSK-3β. Data 
are representative of at least three independent experiments. The results are expressed as means ± SD. </p>

<p>Ischemic stroke remains a significant health 
problem worldwide 26 . Previous studies have shown 
that thioredoxin 27 , anfibatide 28 , and inhibition of 
CD36-mediated inflammation 29 mitigate ischemic 
stroke injury. Recently, Luo et al. 30 demonstrated that 
interleukin-33 ameliorates ischemic brain injury by 
promoting Th2 response and suppressing Th17 
response. 
Nicotinamide 
mononucleotide 
adenylyltransferase 1 is another molecule that has 
exhibited potential neuroprotective effects in vitro and 
in vivo models of cerebral ischemia 31 . We have 
recently shown that GSK-3β inhibitor TWS119 with 
reported dose and treatment regimen 17 attenuates 
tPA-induced hemorrhagic transformation after 
permanent focal cerebral ischemia 18 . Here, we showed 
that TWS119 reduced early ischemia-reperfusion 
injury and protected the BBB. 
Although many efforts have been made to 
attenuate ischemic stroke injury, there is no effective 
therapy that can be used clinically to protect the BBB. 
The BBB is a key factor that affects acute stroke 
outcome 12 and should be targeted for protection. The 
European Cooperative Acute Stroke Study (ECASS)-3 
has shown that rtPA alteplase has a safe therapeutic </p>

<p>window of 3-4.5 h after the onset of stroke 
symptoms 32 . Therefore, in our study, we administered 
TWS119 at 3.5 h after MCAO and found that it 
reduced the permeability of the BBB. This finding 
suggests that TWS119 has a protective effect on the 
BBB after ischemic stroke, and GSK-3β could be a 
potential target for brain protection, which was 
consistent with other studies 33, 34 . 
Previous studies have demonstrated the role of 
the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway in the brain's 
vascular development and BBB formation 35 . 
Dickkopf-1, a negative modulator of the Wnt 
pathway, is involved in the development of ischemic 
neuronal death 36 . Growing evidence indicates that 
Wnt signaling protects the BBB in several brain 
diseases 37 . However, the relationship between 
Wnt/β-catenin signaling and BBB integrity in acute 
ischemic stroke is still unclear. 
To elucidate the underlying mechanisms of 
action of TWS119, we examined the expression of key 
proteins in the Wnt/β-catenin pathway as well as 
tight junction protein ZO-1 at 24 h after MCAO. While 
suppressing the expression of GSK-3β, TWS119 
inhibited phosphorylation of β-catenin and increased </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2017, Vol. 14 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>its total protein expression 38 . β-catenin is a key 
component for activating the Wnt/β-catenin 
pathway 39 , and phosphorylation at Ser552 has been 
shown to induce beta-catenin accumulation in the 
nucleus and increases its transcriptional activity. 
However, other studies found that the Ser-552 
phosphorylation site did not seem important for 
modulation of β-catenin transcriptional activity 40, 41 . In 
our study, we found that β-catenin was upregulated, 
whereas 
GSK-3β 
and 
p-β-catenin 
were 
downregulated in the TWS119-treated group 
compared with levels in the vehicle-treated group, 
indicating that TWS119 may activate the 
Wnt/β-catenin pathway by inhibiting GSK-3β 
expression, reducing p-β-catenin, and enhancing 
β-catenin expression. The tight junction protein ZO-1 
participates in the maintenance of BBB integrity and is 
the major transmembranal protein of tight junctions in 
the BBB 42 . ZO-1 controls angiogenesis and barrier 
formation 43 . However, whether Wnt/β-catenin 
signaling can regulate ZO-1 expression after BBB 
disruption in ischemic stroke is unknown. Our results 
showed that in the TWS119-treated group, a reduction 
in BBB permeability was associated with activation of 
Wnt/β-catenin signaling and upregulation of ZO-1 
expression. The sequence of the signaling may need 
additional research in both in vitro and in vivo 
models of the BBB. 
In summary, our study showed that GSK-3β 
inhibition with TWS119 protected the BBB and 
attenuated early ischemia-reperfusion stroke injury. 
This protection may be related to an early activation 
of the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway and an 
increase in ZO-1 expression. Thus, the activation of 
Wnt/β-catenin signaling has potential to protect the 
BBB after ischemic stroke. However, the specific 
mechanism needs additional research. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by grants from the 
National Natural Science Foundation of China 
(81171112, 81371272 to M.C.L., 81372683 to Q.X.C.) 
and grants from the National Institutes of Health 
(R01NS078026, R01AT007317 to J. W.). </p>

<p>Competing Interests </p>

<p>The authors have declared that no competing 
interest exists. </p>



<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2017, Vol. 14 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>





</text></tei>