<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5216448" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Neural stem cells (NSCs) reside in a unique microenvi-
ronment within the central nervous system (CNS) called 
the NSC niche. Although they are relatively rare, niches 
have been previously characterized in both the brain 
and spinal cord of adult animals. Recently, another 
potential NSC niche has been identified in the filum ter-
minale (FT), which is a thin band of tissue at the caudal 
end of the spinal cord. While previous studies have 
demonstrated that NSCs can be isolated from the FT, 
the in vivo architecture of this tissue and its relation to </p>

<p>other NSC niches in the CNS has not yet been estab-
lished. In this article we report a histological analysis of 
the FT NSC niche in postnatal rats and humans. Immu-
nohistochemical characterization reveals that the FT is 
mitotically active and its cells express similar markers 
to those in other CNS niches. In addition, the organiza-
tion of the FT most closely resembles that of the adult 
spinal cord niche. J. Comp. Neurol. 525:661-675, 
2017. </p>

<p>et al. (1992), and Miller (1968). More recently, Rethelyi 
et al. (2004) used immunohistochemistry to confirm the 
existence of neuronal precursors and glial cells in the 
rat FT. Based on this cellular organization, they specu-
lated that the FT may contain neural stem cells (Rethe-
lyi et al., 2004). 
Recently, several laboratories including our own have 
isolated neural progenitor cells from the FT of both rats 
and humans. These cells have been shown to express 
neural progenitor cell markers such as Nestin, Dlx-2, Sox-
2, and Musashi-1. They have also been passaged multiple 
times as neurospheres and differentiated into neurons, 
astrocytes, and oligodendrocytes (Varghese et al., 2009; 
Arvidsson et al., 2011; Jha et al., 2013a,b). FT-derived 
neurospheres have been differentiated into motor neurons 
capable of innervating muscle tissue in vitro (Jha et al., 
2013a,b), and FT-derived progenitors that have been 
transplanted into the chick or rat CNS survive and 
become migratory (Varghese et al., 2009; Jha et al., 
2013a). 
The specific microenvironment that harbors neural 
stem cells (NSCs) has been well characterized else-
where in the CNS, most notably in the subventricular 
zone (SVZ) (Alvarez-Buylla and Garcia-Verdugo, 2002), 
the hippocampal subgranular zone of the dentate gyrus 
(Seri et al., 2004), and the spinal cord (Hamilton et al., 
2009; Hugnot and Franzen, 2011; Marichal et al., 
2012). While each of these stem cell niches has its 
own unique architecture, they all share similarities in 
terms of the types of cells present and the immunocy-
tochemical markers they express (Fuentealba et al., 
2012). We were interested in determining whether the 
FT-derived progenitor cells that we have isolated in vitro 
reside in an in vivo niche that is similar to those 
described elsewhere in the CNS. Because the FT is a 
derivative of the embryonic spinal cord, we were partic-
ularly interested in comparing its histology to that of 
the adult spinal cord stem cell niche. 
In this article we report a histological analysis in 
both rats and humans using markers that have been 
characterized in progenitor cell niches elsewhere in the 
CNS. We find that FT is mitotically active, that cells in 
FT have immunocytochemical profiles similar to what is 
seen in other CNS niches, and that its organization 
closely resembles that of the spinal cord. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Animals </p>

<p>Postnatal Sprague-Dawley rats (RRID:RGD_734476, 
Charles River, Wilmington, MA) aged 1, 10, or 82-367 
days were housed at a controlled temperature and kept 
on a 12-hour light/dark cycle with food and water </p>

<p>available ad libitum. All experiments were approved by the 
Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at Harvard 
Medical School and were conducted in accordance with 
the NIH Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. </p>

<p>Human autopsy tissue </p>

<p>Tissue from the FT was obtained from human autop-
sies (subjects aged 51-81 years old) that were per-
formed in the autopsy suite at Brigham and Women's 
Hospital (Boston, MA). Each FT was removed, placed in 
ice-cold Hanks solution, and transported to the lab on 
ice where it was fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) 
for 2 hours before being processed as described below. </p>

<p>EdU (5-ethynyl-2 
0 -deoxyuridine) labeling </p>

<p>Postnatal day (P)10 Sprague-Dawley rats were 
weighed, anesthetized with isoflurane (Phoenix Pharma-
ceuticals, Burlingame, CA), and injected subcutaneously 
with EdU (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) at a concentration of 
10 lg/g body weight. After a 4-hour incubation period, 
the animals were euthanized and the tissue was proc-
essed for detection of EdU labeling with the Click iT Alexa 
Fluor Azide system (Invitrogen). Both frozen sections and 
whole mounts were incubated in the detection solution 
for 2 hours, washed extensively in phosphate-buffered 
saline (PBS), and mounted on Superfrost slides (VWR, 
Radnor, PA) using Vectashield Mounting Medium (Vector 
Laboratories, Burlingame, CA). </p>

<p>EdU/Ki67 double labeling </p>

<p>To assess proliferation rates, P2 Sprague-Dawley 
rats were weighed and injected subcutaneously with 
EdU (Invitrogen) at a concentration of 10 lg/g body 
weight. The rats were then euthanized after 2 hours, 3 
days, or 7 days and the FT of each animal was dissect-
ed, postfixed in 4% PFA for 2 hours, cryoprotected in a 
30% sucrose solution, and embedded in O.C.T. (Tissue-
Tek, Torrance, CA). Frozen sections were cut, mounted 
on Superfrost slides (VWR), and incubated in a blocking 
solution that contained 0.2% bovine serum albumin 
(BSA), 10% goat serum, and 0.3% Triton X-100 in PBS 
(all reagents from Sigma, St. Louis, MO). A monoclonal 
mouse anti-human Ki67 antibody (RRID:AB_393778, BD 
Biosciences, San Jose, CA) was diluted in the same 
blocking solution (1:200) and applied to the frozen sec-
tions overnight at 48C. After being washed in PBS, the 
slides were incubated for 2 hours at room temperature 
in a goat antimouse IgG Alexa Fluor 568 secondary 
antibody (RRID:AB_143011, Invitrogen) that had been 
diluted in the same blocking solution. Finally, after 
numerous, extensive washes with PBS, EdU labeling 
was detected with the Click iT Alexa Fluor Azide system 
(Invitrogen). </p>

<p>R. Chrenek et al. </p>

<p>662 </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>Tissue preparation </p>

<p>Postnatal rats were anesthetized with isoflurane and 
sacrificed by cervical dislocation. Ventral laminectomies 
were performed, and the FT was dissected, washed 
once in Hanks Balanced Salt Solution (Lonza, Hopkin-
town, MA), and fixed in 4% PFA for 2 hours. After fixa-
tion, the FT were washed three times in PBS, and some 
samples were set aside for use as whole mounts. Both 
human and rat FT tissue underwent cryoprotection in a 
30% sucrose solution in preparation for frozen section-
ing. After sinking (thus ensuring tissue saturation), the 
tissue was transferred to a 50:50 30% sucrose/O.C.T. 
(Tissue-Tek) solution for 24 hours. Next, the tissue was 
incubated in O.C.T. for 2 hours, rapidly frozen with 5-
methylbutane and liquid nitrogen, and stored at -208C. 
Finally, the tissue was sectioned at 20 lm using a 
Leica CM3050S Crysotat (Leica Microsystems, Buffalo 
Grove, IL) and stored at -208C. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Slides holding frozen sections were placed on a slide 
warmer for 2 hours and washed twice with PBS. Both 
frozen sections and whole mounts were then incubated 
for 1 hour in a permeabilization/blocking solution that 
contained 0.2% BSA, 2% fish skin gelatin, 10% goat 
serum, 0.3% Triton X-100, and 0.25% NaN 3 in PBS (all 
reagents from Sigma). Primary antibodies (polyclonal 
rabbit anti-GFAP (glial fibrillary acidic protein) IgG [RRI-
D:AB_10013382, DAKO, Carpinteria, CA], monoclonal 
mouse anti-Nestin IgG [RRID:AB_94911, Millipore, Biller-
ica, MA], monoclonal mouse anti-3CB2 IgM [RRI-
D:AB_531888, Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank, 
University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA], polyclonal rabbit anti-
Olig-2 IgG [RRID:AB_10141047, Millipore], polyclonal 
rabbit anti-human Nestin IgG [Chemicon, Temecula, 
CA], and monoclonal mouse anti-human GFAP IgG [RRI-
D:AB_864007, Lifespan, Billerica, MA]) were diluted in 
the same blocking solution (see Table 1 for details) and 
centrifuged at 13,000 rpm for 30 minutes at 48C prior 
to application. Once applied, frozen sections were </p>

<p>incubated in primary antibody at room temperature for 
24 hours, and whole mounts were incubated at 48C for 
4-5 days on a gentle agitator. 
After an extensive wash in PBS, appropriate second-
ary antibodies (donkey antimouse IgG Alexa Fluor 594, 
RRID:AB_141633; donkey antirabbit IgG Alexa Fluor 
488, RRID:AB_141708; donkey antirabbit IgG Alexa Flu-
or 594, RRID:AB_141637; goat antimouse IgM Alexa 
Fluor 594, RRID:AB_141424; goat antimouse IgM Alexa 
Fluor 488, RRID:AB_141357; goat antirabbit IgG Alexa 
Fluor 568, RRID:AB_143011; and goat antimouse IgG 
Alexa Fluor 594, RRID:AB_141372; all from Invitrogen) 
were diluted in blocking solution along with 4,6-dia-
mino-2-phenylindole (DAPI; Sigma) and centrifuged simi-
lar to primary antibodies. After a 2-hour incubation, 
specimens were washed once with 3% BSA and exten-
sively with PBS and mounted on Superfrost slides 
(VWR) using Vectashield mounting medium (Vector 
Laboratories). </p>

<p>Antibody characterization </p>

<p>The GFAP mouse antiserum detects a single 51-kDa 
band from purified spinal cord that corresponds to the 
GFAP protein on a western blot (Debus et al., 1983). 
This antibody has been shown to recognize astrocytes 
in the adult CNS (Castellano et al., 1991) along with a 
subpopulation of ependymal cells in both the SVZ and 
the central canal of the adult spinal cord (Alfaro-Cer-
vello et al., 2012). 
The Nestin mouse antiserum detects a single 200-
220 kDa protein by western blot of newborn rat and 
mouse cell extracts (manufacturer's data sheet) and 
has been previously identified as a marker for neuroepi-
thelial progenitor cells in both the embryonic rat brain 
(Hockfield and McKay, 1985; Lendahl et al., 1990) and 
the SVZ of adult animals (Doetsch et al., 1997). 
The 3CB2 mouse antiserum recognizes an intracellu-
lar, 55-kDa protein expressed in the developing and 
adult CNS of several vertebrate species including rats 
(Prada et al., 1995). This antibody has previously been </p>

<p>TABLE 1. 
Antibodies Used </p>

<p>Antibody 
(Isotype) 
Company 
Dilution 
Host 
Immunogen 
Description </p>

<p>GFAP (IgG) 
Dako Z0334 
1:5,000 Mouse monoclonal Intermediate Filament Marker of astrocytes, Type B cells of SVZ 
Nestin (IgG) Millipore MAB353 
1:100 
Mouse monoclonal Intermediate filament 
Marker of undifferentiated neural cells 
3CB2 (IgM) 
Development Studies 
Hybridoma Bank </p>

<p>1:10 
Mouse monoclonal Intermediate filament 
Marker of radial glia </p>

<p>Olig-2 (IgG) 
Millipore AB9610 
1:500 
Rabbit polyclonal 
bHLH Transcription 
Factor </p>

<p>Marker of oligodendrocyte precursors, 
Type C cells of SVZ 
Ki67 (IgG) 
BD Biosciences 
550609 </p>

<p>1:200 
Mouse monoclonal Nuclear cell 
proliferation-
associated protein </p>

<p>Marker of cell proliferation, expressed in 
all active stages of the cell cycle </p>

<p>Filum terminale NSC niche </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>used to identify radial glia in the developing rat spinal 
cord in vivo (Shibuya et al., 2003; Barry and McDer-
mott, 2005) along with progenitor cell-containing neuro-
spheres (Marchal-Victorion et al., 2003) and SVZ-
derived explants of ependymal cells (Perez-Martin et al., 
2003) in vitro. 
The Olig-2 rabbit antiserum detects a single 32-kDa 
protein by western blot of CNS tissue from rat/mouse 
brain and spinal cord (manufacturer's data sheet). Pre-
vious studies have established its specificity by noting 
the absence of staining in tissue that lacks oligodendro-
cytes as well as the presence of signal in a characteris-
tic nuclear localization pattern in tissues that contain 
oligodendrocytes (Cai et al., 2007). 
The mouse Ki67 antiserum detects a nuclear antigen 
that is expressed by all proliferating cells during late 
G1, S, M, and G2 phases of the cell cycle, and its utility 
as a marker for cells undergoing neurogenesis in the 
adult CNS has previously been established (Kee et al., 
2002), including cells in the SC stem cell niche (Hamil-
ton et al., 2009). This antibody recognizes two bands 
(345 and 395 kDa) by western blot, which are consis-
tent with the molecular weights of alternatively spliced 
Ki67 (Schluter et al., 1993). Its specificity has been 
confirmed by an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay 
(ELISA) (Kubbutat et al., 1994) and also by flow cytom-
etry (manufacturer's data sheet). </p>

<p>Image acquisition and processing </p>

<p>Images were captured using a Zeiss <rs type="software">LSM</rs> 510 Meta 
laser scanning confocal microscope with LSM software. 
In some cases, images were transferred to <rs id="software-1" type="software">ImageJ</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">NIH</rs>, 
Bethesda, MD), where the "despeckle" feature was 
used to decrease nonspecific background fluorescence 
levels. Finally, images were exported into Adobe Photo-
shop (San Jose, CA) for cropping, resizing, and adjust-
ment of brightness and contrast levels. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>To characterize the FT NSC niche, we stained sec-
tions from different ages of postnatal rats and humans 
for both cell proliferation markers and progenitor/stem 
cell markers, taking careful note of cellular morphology 
and orientation. For our initial characterization of the 
FT, we used P10 rats, and to observe changes in the 
niche over time, we examined the niche at various post-
natal stages. First, we determined whether the FT was 
mitotically active and which cell types were involved. 
We then focused on the presence of the different clas-
ses of niche cells, their morphology and location, and 
the degree to which they expressed multiple markers. 
Finally, we examined the organization of the FT at four </p>

<p>developmental timepoints. In this study, we report the 
appearance of proliferating cells that express Nestin, 
GFAP, 3CB2, and Olig-2 in the FT, and we propose a 
model for the in vivo architecture of this tissue. </p>

<p>Presence, location, identity, and 
characterization of proliferative cells in P10 
rat </p>

<p>The ability to produce new cells is an essential fea-
ture of the stem cell niche. With this in mind, we deter-
mined the extent to which the postnatal FT preserves 
its proliferative ability. The presence and location of 
proliferating cells in the P10 rat FT were assessed by 
EdU labeling. Animals were injected with 5 mg/mL EdU 
and sacrificed 4 hours postinjection (n 5 12). Whole-
mount longitudinal sections revealed abundant prolifer-
ating cells throughout the FT (Fig. 1A). In transverse 
sections, EdU 
1 nuclei were observed at a high frequen-</p>

<p>cy in both the ependymal zone and the subependymal 
zone. At 4 hours postinjection, the majority of EdU </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>cells existed singly. Occasionally, doublets and small 
clusters of even-numbered cells were also observed 
(Fig. 1B). Using random sections, we counted the num-
ber of EdU 
1 cells per 20 lm section and found </p>

<p>12.6 6 4.5 (n 5 17). 
Next, the identity of the proliferating cells in the 
postnatal FT was determined by immunohistochemistry 
using established stem/progenitor cell markers that are 
expressed in other niches, including the spinal cord and 
the SVZ niches. First, we assessed Nestin immunoreac-
tivity. Nestin, a marker of undifferentiated neural pro-
genitor cells, has been detected in all previously 
described NSC niches. Many of the EdU 
1 nuclei in the </p>

<p>FT colocalized with Nestin. These double-labeled cells 
were distributed throughout the FT and were particular-
ly prominent in the subependymal zone (Fig. 1C; n 5 3). 
Because radial glia have been shown to play an integral 
role in the stem cell niche in the SVZ, the presence of 
this cell type among the proliferating cells in the FT 
was also examined using the selective marker 3CB2 
(Prada et al., 1995). Although EdU 
1 nuclei were often </p>

<p>found in close association with 3CB2 
1 processes, diffi-</p>

<p>culty in identifying 3CB2 
1 cell bodies made it difficult </p>

<p>to discern whether the processes originated from the 
somas of dividing cells (Fig. 1D; n 5 3). Olig-2 is a 
marker that is expressed by niche cells in both the SVZ 
and the spinal cord. In the SVZ, Olig-2 labels Type C 
transit amplifying cells, but in the spinal cord niche, it 
is instead a marker for oligodendrocyte and motor neu-
ron progenitors (Menn et al., 2006; Hamilton et al., 
2009). While we observed extensive Olig-2 staining, 
only on very rare occasions was EdU seen to colocalize </p>

<p>R. Chrenek et al. </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>with Olig-2 (Fig. 1E; n 5 3). Finally, we determined 
whether any cells coexpress EdU and GFAP. GFAP, a 
marker of differentiated astrocytes, is also expressed in 
the SVZ by the quiescent stem cell population (Type B 
Cells) (Alvarez-Buylla et al., 2002). In the SVZ, GFAP </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>cells (either differentiated astrocytes or Type B cells) 
are found in the subependymal zone and have been 
shown to act as postnatal NSCs. We detected a small 
number of GFAP 
1 /EdU 
1 cells, which were located in </p>

<p>the subependymal zone and exhibited a highly branched 
morphology (Fig. 1F; n 5 3). 
The pattern of EdU staining revealed in Figure 1 does 
not distinguish between neural stem cells and transient 
amplifying cells, which have differing rates of prolifera-
tion. To determine whether the cells we had identified 
as EDU 
1 cells had the slow-cycling character of neural </p>

<p>stem cells, we performed double-labeling experiments 
with Ki67 at different timepoints. As a thymidine </p>

<p>analog, EdU is incorporated into the DNA of a dividing 
cell during the S-phase of mitosis. Ki67, on the other 
hand, is a marker for proliferation that is present in all 
cells during active phases of the cell cycle. To identify 
any slow-cycling progenitors in the FT, P2 rats were sub-
cutaneously injected with 5 mg/ml EdU (n 5 12), and 
then a group of these EdU-labeled rats was sacrificed at 
each of the following timepoints postinjection: 2 hours 
(n 5 4), 3 days (n 5 4), and 7 days (n 5 4). Transverse 
sections were first labeled with Ki67 followed by fluores-
cent detection of the EdU-labeled cells. Figure 2A shows 
cells at 2 hours post-EdU injection that were either EdU </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(1), Ki67 
1 (2), or positive for both markers (3). </p>

<p>By 2 hours postinjection, virtually all cells that had 
incorporated EdU were also labeled with Ki67 
(93 6 1.5%), suggesting that they are still in an active 
phase of the cell cycle. After 3 days, 66 6 2.6% of the 
cells were double-labeled, and after 7 days, 30 6 3.3% </p>

<p>Figure 1. Identification of proliferating cells in the P10 rat FT. Proliferating cells are labeled with EdU (green), and the overall distribution 
of cell nuclei is indicated by DAPI (blue). A: Longitudinal section under low magnification reveals proliferating cells that have incorporated 
the EdU label (green) throughout the FT. B: Transverse section at the central canal; nuclei that incorporated EdU were located in both 
ependymal and subependymal regions with the highest numbers in the ependymal zone. Arrows indicate examples of EdU 
1 stained epen-</p>

<p>dymal cell doublets. C: Transverse section through central canal; EdU 
1 cells often expressed Nestin (red), a marker of neural progenitor </p>

<p>cells. D: Proliferating nuclei were frequently found in close association with fibers expressing 3CB2 (red), a marker of radial glial cells. E: 
On rare occasions, proliferating cells also expressed Olig-2 (arrow, red), a marker of motor neuron and oligodendrocyte precursors. F: A 
subset of GFAP 
1 cells (red) located in the subependymal zone with complex morphology was also labeled with EdU. Scale bars 5 100 lm </p>

<p>in A; 20 lm in B-D,F; 50 lm in E. </p>

<p>Filum terminale NSC niche </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>of EDU 
1 cells also expressed Ki67, suggesting that this </p>

<p>represents a population of slow-dividing progenitors 
(Fig. 2B) (Ponti et al., 2013). </p>

<p>Progenitor cell morphology and distribution </p>

<p>Next, we wished to determine the distribution and 
morphology of the various cell types in the FT niche. In 
the P10 rat FT (n 5 10), GFAP 
1 cells exhibited various </p>

<p>morphologies. Large cells with ramified processes were 
often observed (Fig. 1F). These cells were always locat-
ed in the subependymal zone and infrequently pro-
jected an apical process toward the lumen of the 
central canal. GFAP 
1 fibers were noted to wind through </p>

<p>the ependymal zone, ultimately contacting the lumen of 
the central canal (Fig. 3A). Rarely, GFAP 
1 cell bodies </p>

<p>were located directly in the ependymal zone (Fig. 3B). 
These cells appeared to send out long basal processes 
that often spanned the entire diameter of the FT and 
ultimately reached the pial surface. Whole-mount stain-
ing revealed that there was also a prominent level of 
GFAP staining among cells with a more superficial loca-
tion (Fig. 5A). Interestingly, GFAP reactivity occurred 
homogeneously throughout the FT just below the level 
of the conus but restricted itself to the ventral half 
more caudally, and this transition occurred in the ros-
tral third of the tissue (Fig. 3C). </p>

<p>The distribution of additional stem and progenitor 
cell markers was also investigated in both transverse 
and whole-mount longitudinal sections. Nestin reactivity 
occurred predominantly in subependymal cell bodies 
and radially oriented processes (Fig. 4A; n 5 5). Stain-
ing for Nestin was stronger in the dorsal half of the FT 
in comparison to other regions of the tissue, which can 
be seen in Figure 4A,B. In contrast to GFAP 
1 cells, </p>

<p>Nestin 
1 cells prominently projected their apical pro-</p>

<p>cesses into the central canal (Figs. 4B, 5B). 3CB2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>immunoreactivity, directed against radial glia, also 
stained radially oriented processes (Fig. 4C; n 5 3). 
Olig-2 reactivity was observed primarily in the subepen-
dymal zone and in peripheral locations, although on 
rare occasions, Olig-2 
1 nuclei were detected in the </p>

<p>ependymal zone (Fig. 4D; n 5 5). </p>

<p>Colocalization of progenitor cell markers </p>

<p>We were also interested in the extent to which the 
niche cells expressed multiple developmental markers. 
Examination of both whole-mount and transverse sec-
tions (n 5 4) revealed that Nestin and GFAP are 
expressed by different populations of cells. No colocali-
zation of these markers was observed (Figs. 5A, 6A). In 
fact, at P10 the strongest staining for each marker was 
observed in different regions of the FT. GFAP 
1 immuno-</p>

<p>reactivity predominated in the ventral FT, while Nestin </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Identification of a population of slow-dividing progenitors in the FT. A: In a transverse section at the central canal 2 hours after 
EdU injection, cells in S-phase are labeled with EdU (green, 1) and cells in all active stages of the cell cycle are labeled with Ki67 (red, 2). 
Most Edu 
1 cells are also Ki67 
1 (merged image in 3). B: The graph displays the number of cells colabeled with Ki67 and EdU in the FT at </p>

<p>either 2 hours, 3 days, or 7 days after EdU injection. Individual counts from 16 tissue sections from four different animals are shown, and 
the dots represent the average number of colabeled cells at each timepoint. A population of doubled-labeled cells, which represents slow-
dividing progenitors, can be identified even after 7 days. Scale bar 5 50 lm in A. </p>

<p>R. Chrenek et al. </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>cells were primarily located in the dorsal half. When we 
compared Nestin staining with that for 3CB2, we found 
a high degree of overlap. At P10, the majority of radial 
processes were positive for both Nestin and 3CB2 (Fig. 
6B,1-3). We did not detect 3CB2 and GFAP costaining 
in P10 animals, although there were some examples of 
coreactivity in aged rats. Olig-2 staining did not overlap 
with any of the other markers. </p>

<p>Effect of age on niche architecture </p>

<p>In the SVZ, the NSC niche changes with the age of 
the animal (Conover and Shook, 2011). With this in 
mind, we examined the FT niche architecture as a func-
tion of age. Sections of FT were stained for Nestin, 
3CB2, GFAP, and Olig-2 at stages P1 (n 5 16), P10 
(n 5 12), and rats aged &gt;P82 (n 5 4). Additionally, the 
P5 FT was examined in whole mount. All markers 
remained present in the tissue throughout the entire 
age range. However, the architecture of the niche 
changed over time, as revealed by a modification in the 
frequency of appearance, intensity, and morphology of </p>

<p>stained cells (Fig. 7). The number of Nestin 
1 processes </p>

<p>and intensity of staining decreased with age (Fig. 7A,1-
3). Furthermore, the morphology of the Nestin 
1 cells </p>

<p>changed throughout development. In P1 rats, Nestin 
expression was observed in immature, radial glial-like 
processes that spanned the distance from the ependy-
mal zone to the pial surface, and there was a higher 
density of processes at both the dorsal and ventral 
poles of the central canal ependymal and subependy-
mal zones (Fig. 7A,1). By P10, the intensity of Nestin 
staining had decreased, especially in the ventral zone, 
and the strongest staining occurred in cell bodies in 
the region of the dorsal pole of the central canal (Figs. 
4A,B, 7A,2). In aged rats, a small number of cells 
retained Nestin reactivity; however, these cells often 
lost contact with the pial surface while maintaining con-
tact with the central canal (Fig. 7A,3). 
While age did not affect the morphology of radial 
3CB2 
1 processes, it did affect their distribution (Fig. </p>

<p>7B). These processes contacted both the central canal 
and pial surface of the FT in P1 rats (Fig. 7B,1), where-
as processes in older rats did not fully retain these </p>

<p>Figure 3. GFAP expression in the P10 rat FT. Differentiated astrocytes or Type B cells are identified by GFAP (red), and the overall distri-
bution of cells is indicated by DAPI (blue). A: Transverse section through central canal (CC); GFAP processes with radial morphology were 
noted to wind through the ependymal zone and contact the canal lumen (arrows). B: Transverse section through central canal showing 
ependymal cell bodies with basal processes that are GFAP 
1 . C: GFAP reactivity was limited to the ventral portion of the FT in caudal </p>

<p>regions with the transition occurring in the rostral third of the FT. Rostral, caudal, dorsal, and ventral are indicated in lower case. Scale 
bars 5 10 lm in A,B; 100 lm in C. </p>

<p>Filum terminale NSC niche </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>contacts (Figs. 6B-D, 7B,(2 and 3)). GFAP reactivity 
was observed in only a small number of radial process-
es in P1 pups (Fig. 7C,1). This staining increased with 
age, and by P10 GFAP 
1 processes had significantly </p>

<p>increased in number and complexity of shape. Addition-
ally, as noted earlier, these processes were more abun-
dant in the ventral FT (Fig. 7C,2). In the adult, GFAP 
reactivity was abundant throughout the FT, and pro-
cesses were highly branched (Fig. 7C,3). In contrast to 
the other markers, the pattern of Olig-2 reactivity 
remained consistent throughout development (Fig. 7D), 
with Olig-2 
1 cells dispersed throughout the FT, includ-</p>

<p>ing both the ependymal and subependymal zones. 
We were interested in comparing the staining pat-
terns for progenitors observed in the rat FT to those in 
the adult human FT. Transverse and longitudinal sec-
tions from autopsy specimens aged 51-81 years 
(n 5 4) were examined for Nestin and GFAP immunore-
activity. Nestin 
1 cells were detected in the ependymal </p>

<p>and subependymal zones as well as in more lateral 
locations (Fig. 8A). GFAP 
1 cells were observed in the </p>

<p>subependymal zone and were dispersed more laterally 
throughout the FT. Their processes projected both </p>

<p>radially and longitudinally (Fig. 8B). When sections were 
examined for colocalization of GFAP and Nestin, we 
detected a small proportion of cells and processes that 
were double-labeled and sometimes colocalized with 
GFAP. In contrast, this colocalization was never 
observed in the rat FT (Fig. 8A,B,3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We find that the rat FT contains the same cell types 
as those found in the other CNS NSC niches. Each cell 
type has a unique distribution. The numbers and mor-
phologies of these cells along with the niche character-
istics change with the age of the animal. For P10 and 
younger, the GFAP 
1 and Nestin 
1 cells represent sepa-</p>

<p>rate populations, with the GFAP 
1 cells located more </p>

<p>ventrally and the Nestin 
1 cells biased dorsally. At this </p>

<p>stage, there is a high degree of costaining for Nestin 
and 3CB2, suggesting that the Nestin 
1 cells are radial </p>

<p>glia. Interestingly, the Nestin 
1 cells extend their pro-</p>

<p>cesses the entire diameter of the FT and maintain con-
tact with the lumen of the central canal. This is 
reminiscent of NSCs that have been described in other </p>

<p>Figure 4. Expression of additional neural progenitor cell markers in the P10 rat FT. Nuclei are indicated by DAPI incorporation (blue) in all 
panels. A: Longitudinal section showing Nestin (red) reactivity in ependymal cell bodies and processes that radiate toward the pial surface 
of the FT. Dorsal is on top. B: In transverse section, a higher concentration of Nestin staining (red) in the dorsal region of the FT was evi-
dent. Dorsal and ventral are indicated by lower case letters. C: Longitudinal section, 3CB2 
1 processes (red) exhibited radial morphology </p>

<p>along the longitudinal axis of the FT. D: Transverse section, Olig-2 (red), a marker of motor neuron and oligodendrocyte precursors, 
occurred mostly in the subependymal region but also in rare nuclei located directly in the ependymal zone (arrow). Scale bars 5 20 lm in 
A,C; 10 lm in B,D. </p>

<p>R. Chrenek et al. </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>CNS niches (Fuentealba et al., 2012). The overall orga-
nization of the FT niche (Fig. 9) is similar to that 
described for the spinal cord (Hamilton et al., 2009; 
Hugnot and Franzen, 2011; Marichal et al., 2012). This 
is not unreasonable, given that the FT is a vestigial 
form of the spinal cord and might be expected to have 
a corresponding organization (Streeter, 1919). </p>

<p>FT histology </p>

<p>The histology of the FT has been examined in many 
species using light microscopy, electron microscopy, 
immunocytochemistry, and confocal microscopy. This tis-
sue is a mixture of longitudinally oriented fibrous struc-
tures that are interspersed with primitive SC elements, 
which consist of ependymal cells, glia, and neurons. The 
fibrous aspect results from an abundance of Type 1 colla-
gen bundles and elastic fibers, and it is hypothesized that 
the elastic property of the FT provides a buffering capacity 
against the stretching of the spinal cord during flexion of 
the spine (Fontes et al., 2006). </p>

<p>The human FT was originally studied by Harmeier 
(1933) and by Tarlov (1938). Harmeier observed that 
the FT contained all the elements found in the spinal 
cord, including ependymal cells, neurons, and glia. In 
addition, he noted the presence of neuroblasts scat-
tered throughout the tissue and a high density of small 
blood vessels. Tarlov confirmed these findings, and he 
also noted the presence of many small neurons, which 
he thought likely to be neuroblasts. In addition, he not-
ed the absence of anterior horn cells; he observed 
astrocytes in close association with blood vessels; he 
noted the presence of oligodendrocytes; and he 
described amorphous clusters of cells. His summary 
diagram bears a striking resemblance to modern 
descriptions of the NSC niche (Tarlov, 1938). These 
human studies were extended by Choi et al. (1992) 
using electron microscopy and immunocytochemistry. 
They noted GFAP 
1 glial cells, NSE 
1 neurons, and </p>

<p>Vimentin 
1 precursor cells. They also noted large clus-</p>

<p>ters of peri-ependymal glial cells that formed acinar-like 
structures. Miller (1968) used electron microscopy to 
characterize the ependymal cells and the neuropil of 
the FT in both cats and monkeys (Miller, 1968). The 
frog FT has been studied by three groups (Gonzalez-
Robles and Glusman, 1979; Chesler and Nicholson, 
1985; Chvatal et al., 2001). Using light and electron 
microscopy, Gonzalez-Robles and Glusman (1979) iden-
tified three regions of the FT: a central region that con-
tains ependymal and subependymal cells, an 
intermediate zone where astrocytes predominate, and a 
peripheral zone that contains neuronal fibers astrocyte 
processes. Chesler and Nicholson (1985) elaborated on 
this, describing a radial arrangement of the FT orga-
nized around the central canal. In addition, they noted 
the presence of TH 
1 CSF-contacting neurons abutting </p>

<p>the central canal. Chavatal's group (2001) confirmed 
the presence of astrocytes and oligodendrocytes using 
immunocytochemistry for GFAP and Rip staining, 
respectively. They also identified neurons using electro-
physiology followed by dye-filling (Chvatal et al., 2001). 
A similar organization of cellular elements around the 
central canal has also been observed in the FT of rab-
bits, guinea pigs, and rats by Nakayama (1976). 
George and colleagues conducted an extensive 
immunohistochemical study of both the normal and 
tethered human FT (Cummings and George, 2003; 
George et al., 2003). They stained the FT for caudal 
neural tube developmental, neuroglial, neural crest, epi-
thelial and mesenchymal markers and confirmed the 
presence of an abundance of ependymal, neural, and 
glial tissue. R ethelyi's group studied the FT in the rat, 
where they observed that it represented a continuation 
of the spinal cord's periventricular gray matter (Rexed's </p>

<p>Figure 5. Costaining for GFAP and Nestin. A: Whole mount of ros-
tral FT staining for Nestin (red) and GFAP (green) with DAPI 
(blue). No colocalization was observed. B: Longitudinal section 
through the central canal for Nestin (red) and GFAP (green) with 
DAPI (gray). Extensive Nestin 
1 processes penetrate the lumen of </p>

<p>the central canal. Occasional GFAP 
1 processes also extend into </p>

<p>the central canal (arrow). Scale bars 5 200 lm in A; 20 lm in B. </p>

<p>Filum terminale NSC niche </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>Lamina X) accompanied by a loss of the dorsal and ven-
tral columnar structure (Rethelyi et al., 2004, 2008; 
Boros et al., 2008). Using NeuN staining, they identified 
clusters of small neurons in close apposition to the 
ependymal cells and raised the possibility that they 
may represent neurons in an early phase of differentia-
tion (Rethelyi et al., 2004). Subsequently, they distin-
guished three groups of neurons, a small group just 
dorsal to the central canal and two lateral clusters on 
either side of the central canal (Boros et al., 2008). 
Additionally, they found a radial arrangement of GFAP </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>astrocytic processes that extended from the central 
canal to the pial surface. In a later study, Attia and 
Shehab (2010) conducted an immunohistochemical 
analysis that was consistent with the findings of 
R ethelyi's group, and more recently, Gaddam et al. 
(2012) reported the presence Nestin 
1 cells in the FT </p>

<p>from two postmortem human specimens. </p>

<p>Neural stem cell niches </p>

<p>NSC niches have previously been described in the 
SVZ (Alvarez-Buylla and Garcia-Verdugo, 2002), the sub-
granular zone of the dentate gyrus in the hippocampus 
(Seri et al., 2004), and the spinal cord (SC) (Hamilton </p>

<p>et al., 2009; Hugnot and Franzen, 2011; Marichal et al., 
2012). Here, we add a fourth location to the list, the 
FT. Although these four niches all share many key fea-
tures, their subcellular organization also contains some 
distinct elements. Previous studies have described the 
localization of cells that express GFAP, Nestin, and 
Olig-2 along with proliferating cells in the various NSC 
niches. Unsurprisingly, given its developmental origins, 
the expression pattern of these markers in the FT niche 
is most similar to the previously described SC niche in 
adult animals. For example, proliferating cells were 
observed in these two niches in both the ependymal 
and subependymal layers, and the proliferating cells pri-
marily expressed Nestin, with few GFAP 
1 proliferating </p>

<p>cells being identified in either case (Hamilton et al., 
2009). Nestin 
1 cells are also similarly distributed in the </p>

<p>SC and FT niches. In the SC niche, Nestin 
1 cells are </p>

<p>located dorsally and have long, basally projecting pro-
cesses (Hamilton et al., 2009). Similarly, in FT, we 
observed a dorsal bias of Nestin 
1 cells that extend pro-</p>

<p>cesses to span the entire diameter of the FT. Addition-
ally, Nestin expression appears to be downregulated in 
all regions of the SC by age P6 (Barry and McDermott, 
2005), which corresponds to our observation in the FT </p>

<p>Figure 6. Colocalization of pro-
genitor cell markers in the P10 
rat FT. A: Transverse section. 
GFAP (green) and Nestin (red) 
each labeled different popula-
tions of cells and processes 
(central canal: cc). B: Trans-
verse section. In radially orient-
ed fibers, Nestin (1, red) and 
3CB2 (2, green) frequently 
colocalized (3) merged. DAPI 
staining 
in 
blue. 
Scale 
bars 5 20 lm. </p>

<p>R. Chrenek et al. </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>that the intensity of Nestin staining decreased by P10 
and was only retained in a small number of cells in 
aged rats. 
The localization of Olig-2 
1 and GFAP 
1 cells was simi-</p>

<p>lar among the SVZ, SC, and FT niches. In the SC stem 
cell niche, Olig-2 
1 cells are most often observed in the </p>

<p>subependymal layer closely bordering ependymal cells, 
which also corresponds to the organization of the SVZ 
niche. Although we occasionally observed Olig-2 
1 nuclei </p>

<p>in the ependymal zone, Olig-2 
1 cells are also primarily </p>

<p>located outside the ependyma in the FT. GFAP 
1 cells </p>

<p>are located subependymally in both the SVZ (Alvarez-</p>

<p>Buylla et al., 2002) and the SC niche (Hamilton et al., 
2009). Although Hamilton et al. could not always identi-
fy the location of the GFAP 
1 cell bodies, they did note </p>

<p>that GFAP 
1 fibers extended into the ependymal layer. </p>

<p>Similarly, we observed GFAP 
1 cells that were located </p>

<p>subependymally and extended processes that wind 
through the ependymal zone and ultimately contact the 
lumen of the central canal. 
There are some key differences between the archi-
tectures of the SC and FT niches. Hamilton et al. 
(2009) noted an asymmetric distribution of proliferating 
cells, with a higher concentration at the dorsal pole of </p>

<p>Figure 7. Age-related changes in progenitor cell marker expression in the rat FT. Nuclei are indicated by DAPI incorporation (blue) in all panels. 
Cross-sections with ventral left and dorsal on right. Left: P1; Middle: P10; Right: aged rats &gt;P82. A: Nestin (red) reactivity decreased markedly 
with age, especially after P10, and processes progressively lost their basal contacts with the pial surface of the FT. B: 3CB2 (green) expression 
was consistently observed in radial processes across the age range studied. C: GFAP (red) reactivity increased with age, and the GFAP 
1 cell </p>

<p>morphology changed from radial to highly branched. D: Olig-2 (green) expression remained unchanged. Scale bars 5 A: 20 lm in (1), 10 lm in 
(2) and (3); B: 20 lm in (1), 10 lm in (2), 20 lm in (3); C,D: 20 lm in (1-3). </p>

<p>Filum terminale NSC niche </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>the SC niche. In contrast, we observed EdU 
1 cells dis-</p>

<p>tributed uniformly throughout the entire FT, although in 
both cases the proliferating cells were primarily 
Nestin </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>. Additionally, while Hamilton et al. (2009) iden-
tified a subpopulation of Vimentin 
1 cells in the SC </p>

<p>niche that coexpressed GFAP and Nestin, we observed 
a distinct segregation between the populations of cells 
that expressed the two markers. In the FT, GFAP </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>immunoreactivity is restricted to the ventral half, and 
Nestin 
1 cells are primarily located in the dorsal half. </p>

<p>The functional consequence of this segregation of cell 
populations remains unclear. Interestingly, Hamilton 
et al. (2009) noted that 51% of the BrdU-retaining 
cells remained proliferative after 21 days as determined 
by double labeling with Ki67. We also found a signifi-
cant number (30%) of double-labeled cells 7 days 
postinjection. 
This study relied extensively on the use of markers 
to identify various cells types in the FT niche. Marker 
analyses can sometimes be misleading because many 
antigens are expressed by multiple cell types, and the 
presence of a marker does not necessarily dictate the 
function of that cell. For example, GFAP is commonly </p>

<p>used to identify astrocytes, but it is also expressed by 
adult NSCs, including the quiescent stem cell popula-
tion (Type B cells) in the SVZ (Alvarez-Buylla and 
Garcia-Verdugo, 2002). Similarly, the nuclear transcrip-
tion factor Olig-2 is involved in regulating progenitor 
cell fate of both SC oligodendrocytes and motor neu-
rons. Therefore, conclusive identification of a cell type 
using a single marker can be problematic. To combat 
this, we looked for colocalization of markers whenever 
possible. For example, the coexpression of Nestin and 
3CB2 in a single cell suggests that these cells are most 
likely radial glial neural progenitors. 
There is still a great deal to be done in order to 
effectively compare the FT niche with other previously 
established neural stem cell niches. For example, we 
and others have noted Dlx2 expression in the FT (Var-
ghese et al., 2009; Jha et al., 2013b). Because this 
marker is normally restricted to the forebrain's stem 
cell niche (Bulfone et al., 1993), it will be important to 
establish the identity of the FT neurons produced in 
terms of their anterior-posterior identity. We are cur-
rently investigating this by examining HOX gene expres-
sion in the FT (Jessell, 2000). </p>

<p>Figure 8. Expression of Nestin and GFAP in human postmortem tissue. Nuclei are indicated by DAPI (blue) in all panels. A: Transverse sec-
tion of FT from a 61-year-old showing Nestin (1, green) and GFAP (2, red). A costained cell is indicated by arrows. A merged image is 
shown in (3). B: Longitudinal section of FT from an 81-year-old, labeled with Nestin (1, green) and GFAP (2, red). A merged image is shown 
in (3). Scale bars 5 50 lm. </p>

<p>R. Chrenek et al. </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>An additional level of complexity is introduced by our 
lack of understanding of the functionality of the FT in 
postnatal animals. In the SVZ stem cell niche, adult 
neurogenesis is known to occur in a stepwise fashion 
and to contribute to the continuous production of inter-
neurons destined for the olfactory bulb. In that niche, 
Olig-2 is expressed by a subpopulation of cells that has 
been identified as transit-amplifying progenitors (Type C 
cells), which are named for their properties of prolifera-
tion and differentiation within a finite life span. In con-
trast, the fate of the NCS in the SC and FT is still not 
established. Consequently, identifying distinct functional 
populations of cells based on markers alone is not pos-
sible. One possibility is that the FT cells are destined to 
migrate into the spinal cord and differentiate into motor 
neurons. In that case, Olig-2 might play a role in deter-
mining their fate as motor neurons. However, it is </p>

<p>equally possible that these cells remain relatively quies-
cent and do not continuously generate new neurons, 
which would require an alternate explanation for Olig-2 
expression. Further studies are needed to construct a 
functional map of the FT and determine the fate of the 
cells contained within this structure before any marker-
based subpopulations can be conclusively named. 
Along with the niche cell types we examined, the 
extracellular matrix (ECM) and the vasculature are both 
emerging as key components of the stem cell niche. 
These components not only contribute to the health of 
the niche cells by delivering nutrients and anchoring 
cells to the niche, but they can also influence stem cell 
fates through diffusible signals and/or direct contact. 
Therefore, careful characterization of the ECM and the 
surrounding vasculature in the FT will be a necessary 
component of a more complete description of the 
niche. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Here we analyzed the distribution of cells in the FT 
niche and identified many key features of the forebrain 
and SC niches that are also present in the FT. Addition-
ally, the FT niche has some unique organizational ele-
ments that set it apart from the other niches. 
Understanding the interactions and eventual fate of 
these FT cells in healthy animals may help to unlock 
their therapeutic potential for future applications involv-
ing cell replacement strategies. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank the members of the Cepko laboratory in the 
Department of Genetics for valuable assistance along with 
all of our colleagues in the Department of Neurobiology at 
Harvard Medical School. We also thank Dr. Joseph Mad-
sen and his colleagues in the Department of Neurosurgery 
at the Children's Hospital Boston for their excellent advice 
and for their help in acquiring human FT tissue samples. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors report no conflict of interest. The fun-
ders of this study had no role in study design, data col-
lection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation 
of the article. </p>

<p>ROLE OF AUTHORS </p>

<p>All authors had full access to all the data in the 
study and take responsibility for the integrity of the 
data and the accuracy of the data analysis. Study con-
cept and design: RC, LMM, GRH, RMJ, DLC. Acquisition 
of data: RC, LMM, and GRH. Analysis and interpretation 
of data: RC, LMM, and DLC. Drafting of the article: RC, </p>

<p>Figure 9. Proposed model of the progenitor cell niche in the P10 
rat FT (transverse plane). Proliferating cells (green) are located in 
all regions of the FT. Nestin 
1 cells (blue) are also labeled with </p>

<p>EdU and exhibit radial morphology with some of their nuclei locat-
ed in the ependymal zone. GFAP 
1 cells (red) exhibit various mor-</p>

<p>phologies ranging from radial to ramified. GFAP 
1 cells with </p>

<p>complex morphology are located in the subependymal region and 
rarely contain EdU 
1 nuclei. Radial 3CB2 
1 fibers (brown) frequent-</p>

<p>ly colocalize with Nestin. Finally, Olig-2 
1 nuclei (yellow) can be </p>

<p>found in both ependymal and subependymal regions, although 
they are rarely labeled with EdU in the subependymal zone. </p>

<p>Filum terminale NSC niche </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>





<p>R. Chrenek et al. </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>





</text></tei>