<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5041470" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>During DNA damage response (DDR), certain gene 
rich chromosome territories (CTs) relocate to newer 
positions within interphase nuclei and revert to their 
native locations following repair. Such dynamic re-
location of CTs has been observed under various 
cellular conditions, however, the underlying mecha-
nistic basis of the same has remained largely elusive. 
In this study, we aim to understand the temporal and 
molecular details of such crosstalk between DDR sig-
naling and CT relocation dynamics. We demonstrate 
that signaling at DNA double strand breaks (DSBs) 
by the phosphorylated histone variant (ϒ-H2AX) is 
a pre-requisite for damage induced CT relocation, 
as cells deficient in ϒ-H2AX signaling fail to exhibit 
such a response. Inhibition of Rad51 or DNA Ligase 
IV mediated late steps of double strand break repair 
does not seem to abrogate CT relocation completely. 
Upon DNA damage, an increase in the levels of chro-
matin bound motor protein nuclear myosin 1 (NM1) 
ensues, which appears to be functionally linked to 
ϒ-H2AX signaling. Importantly, the motor function of 
NM1 is essential for its recruitment to chromatin and 
CT relocation following damage. Taking these obser-
vations together, we propose that early DDR sensing 
and signaling result in NM1 recruitment to chromo-
somes which in turn guides DNA damage induced CT 
relocation. </p>

<p>Both endogenous as well as exogenous DNA damage can 
lead to genomic instability and may even be lethal if they are 
not repaired accurately and timely. When faced with DNA 
damage, cells generally respond by a two-step strategy: cells 
undergo cell cycle arrest and try to repair them (1,2), but </p>

<p>if the damages are too severe to be repaired, apoptosis is 
induced leading to cell death (3,4). 
Double strand breaks (DSBs) in the DNA can be re-
paired by two major repair pathways namely -the non ho-
mologous end joining (NHEJ) or homologous recombina-
tion (HR) (5,6). DSBs are sensed by ATM kinase, which in 
turn gets activated and phosphorylates a number of down-
stream protein targets that participate in the DSB repair 
pathways (7). One such phosphorylation target of ATM ki-
nase is H2AX (8), a histone H2A variant that represents 
about 2-25% of the H2A complement in the genome (9). 
H2AX present in the chromatin, flanking a DSB, gets phos-
phorylated at its Ser139 residue in mammalian cells also 
by several other members of the phosphatidylinositol 3-
kinase-like kinases (PI3KK) family, such as ATR, DNAPK 
(8,10) and the phosphorylated version of H2AX is referred 
to as ϒ-H2AX (9). Once formed ϒ-H2AX via downstream 
signaling leads to the recruitment of ATM kinase at the 
DSB sites, ultimately resulting in the formation of more ϒ-
H2AX molecules in the chromatin, thereby generating an 
important 'hub' of protein-protein interactions required for 
DNA repair (11,12). Such ϒ-H2AX foci spanning up to 1 
Mb can form on either side of the break (9,13) and signal 
the recruitment of several repair proteins such as MDC-1, 
RNF8/UBC13, 53BP1, BRCA1, etc. (14,15) and chromatin 
modifiers such as IN080 and NuA4 to the DSBs (16-18). As 
expected, H2AX deficient cells are hypersensitive to DNA 
damage and show defective cell cycle checkpoint activity 
(19-21). In such cells, DSB repair by HR is inefficient even 
though the NHEJ repair pathway seems to be unaffected 
(22). 
In yeast, DSBs have been shown to cause increased lo-
cal mobility of chromatin, which is implicated in enhanc-
ing the search for homology, thus leading to HR based re-
pair (23,24). Such enhanced mobility in chromatin is known 
to require active repair proteins such as Mec1 (ATR ho-
molog) and HR proteins like Rad51, Rad54 (25). In con-
trast, a study in mammalian cells has shown that DNA 
ends at a single targeted DSB appear to be positionally sta-</p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +91 22 22782606; Fax: +91 22 22804610; Email: bjrao@tifr.res.in </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>The Author(s) 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which 
permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 17 8273 </p>

<p>ble, which might attenuate illegitimate joining of breaks, 
genomic instability and consequent inaccurate repair (26). 
Even though single DSBs are ascribed to be positionally sta-
ble, chromatin domains containing multiple random breaks 
seem to undergo spatial movements, which in turn depend 
on higher order organization of chromatin (27). Moreover, 
relocation of chromatin domains may also contribute to 
multiple DSBs clustering together at repair foci as observed 
in yeast and mammalian cells (28,29). Such dynamic clus-
ters of repair foci are thought to represent repair centres or 
even factories (28-31). 
In mammalian interphase cells, every chromosome oc-
cupies a specific position within the nucleus, referred to as 
chromosome territory (CT) (32-35). Such non-random ar-
rangement of chromosomes within the nucleus has been 
studied in several different species such as humans, apes, 
chicken, bovine, etc. (34,36,37) and it has been found that 
the organization of the CTs is based on gene density, where 
the gene dense chromosomes position in the centre of the 
nucleus and the gene poor chromosomes toward the nuclear 
periphery (38,39). Several studies have shown that certain 
CTs relocate to new locations within the nucleus under spe-
cific conditions such as serum starvation, disease, differenti-
ation, etc. (40-45). We have previously reported that certain 
CTs reposition in the nucleus in response to DNA damage 
induced by agents such as cisplatin and hydrogen peroxide 
that lead to production of DNA DSBs during DNA dam-
age response (DDR) (46-54). Such DNA damage induced 
CT repositioning is dependent on sensing and repair of the 
damage (46). Previous studies have demonstrated that open 
chromatin and gene rich chromosomes are more suscepti-
ble to DNA damage (55,56). CT relocation following DNA 
damage seems to be somehow linked to the gene density sta-
tus of the chromosomes since only the relatively gene-rich 
CTs show such damage induced relocation (46). DNA dam-
age induced CT relocation spans over a distance of several 
microns similar to that of long-range clustering together of 
repair foci observed in mammalian cells (29,30). We surmise 
that radiation induced multiple damage containing chro-
matin domains from different CTs coalesce into repair cen-
tres (29,30), and this may be akin or mechanistically linked 
to the dynamic changes associated with damage induced CT 
relocations. Importantly, CT relocation is reversible upon 
repair, i.e. the CTs return to their 'native positions' after the 
damaging agent is removed and the cells are allowed to re-
cover (46). 
Nuclear motors such as actin and myosin have been 
shown to play an important role in the relocation of CTs fol-
lowing serum starvation (40) and also in the repositioning 
of a gene locus (57), or a chromosome site upon gene acti-
vation (58). Nuclear myosins are encoded by several classes 
of myosin genes including MYO1C that expresses three dif-
ferent protein isoforms -isoform A, isoform B or nuclear 
myosin 1 (NM1) and isoform C that get translocated into 
the nucleus via an NLS present in all the three isoforms (59-
62). NM1 was the first nuclear myosin to be identified (63) 
and is the predominant nuclear isoform, whereas isoform 
C is primarily localized in the cytoplasm (60). Isoform C is 
the shortest isoform and differs from NM1 by the absence 
of 16 amino acids from the N-terminus of NM1 (59,60). 
The longest MYO1C gene encoded isoform is A, which was </p>

<p>identified recently by Ihnatovych et al. (60). Interestingly 
nuclear isoforms A and B seem to have diverse functions 
as the former co-localizes only with Pol II, while the latter 
interacts with both Pol I and Pol II (60). NM1 and nuclear 
actin have been shown to function in transcription mediated 
by RNA polymerase I and II (64-71). It was discovered as 
early as 2004 that an actomyosin motor complex is physi-
cally coupled to RNA pol I machinery (72), but it is only 
recently that the direct interactions of NM1 with rDNA 
chromatin and Pol II promoters were demonstrated using 
ChIP/qPCR and ChIP Seq techniques (69,70,73). More-
over, these studies have shown that NM1 interacts with 
rDNA through its C-terminus, which in turn is regulated by 
GSK3 mediated phosphorylation of NM1 (69,73). Such 
chromatin bound NM1 functions together with RNA Pol 
I-associated actin to regulate rDNA transcription (66,69). 
NM1 also participates in chromatin remodeling through in-
teractions with WSTF and SNFh2 components of the B-
WICH remodeler complex (64,69). Almuzzaini et al. have 
also provided insights about how NM1 helps in the mainte-
nance and preservation of Pol II activating histone modifi-
cations such as H3K9Ac and H3K4me3 by directly recruit-
ing histone acetyl transferase PCAF and histone methyl 
transferase Set1/Ash2 to the chromatin (70). 
Despite the extensive mechanistic knowledge of DDR 
pathways and nuclear motor protein functions in transcrip-
tion, it is still unclear if and how DDR signaling, nuclear 
motor proteins are involved in DNA damage induced CT 
relocation. Here, using cisplatin as an inducer of DNA dam-
age, we report that the early signaling by ϒ-H2AX is re-
quired for the repositioning of CTs within the nucleus fol-
lowing DNA damage. Later stages of repair catalyzed by 
proteins such as DNA ligase IV and Rad51 do not seem to 
play as critical a role as early sensors in programming the 
CT relocation events. We have also found that recruitment 
of the nuclear motor protein NM1 to chromatin increases 
after cisplatin or hydrogen peroxide induced DNA dam-
age; which seems to be functionally coupled with ϒ-H2AX 
signaling and dependent upon the sensors of DNA dam-
age such as ATM, ATR, PARP-1 and DNAPK. Knocking 
down of NM1 levels by RNAi or motor function defects in 
NM1 also lead to the failure of CT relocation during DDR. 
All these results put together, for the first time, suggest that 
early events of DDR and the DNA damage induced NM1 
recruitment to chromosomes drive the spatial changes in 
CTs following DNA damage. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Cell culture, treatments </p>

<p>Early passage Normal Human Dermal Fibroblasts 
(NHDFs) from Sigma-Aldrich were cultured in Dulbecco's 
Modified Eagl's Medium (DMEM) supplemented with 
15% fetal bovine serum (FBS), 200 mM glycine and 1X 
antimycotic antibiotic (Gibco). 
For inducing DNA damage, cells were treated with 25 
M cisplatin (Calbiochem) for 4 h. H 2 O 2 treatment was 
carried out with 1 mM H 2 O 2 for 90 min. Cells were 
treated with 10 M of ATM (KU55933), ATR (Inhibitor 
IV/VE821), DNAPK (Inhibitor II/NU7026) or PARP (In-
hibitor III/DPQ) (all from Calbiochem) for 1 h. DNA ligase </p>



<p>IV inhibition was done by treating cells with 1 M SCR7 
(kindly provided by Prof. Sathees C. Raghavan, Indian In-
stitute of Science) for 24 h. LiCl was added to cells at a con-
centration of 20 mM for 3 h for inhibiting GSK3 kinase. 
All damage or inhibitor treatments were performed at 37 • C. </p>

<p>Plasmid constructs and transfections </p>

<p>FLAG tagged wild-type H2AX and H2AX S139A mutant 
constructs (kindly provided by Prof. Junya Kobayashi, Ky-
oto University) were transfected into NHDFs using lipo-
fectamine 2000 (Life technologies) and stable cells were se-
lected 48 h post transfection using 1 mg/ml of the antibiotic 
G418 for 1 week followed by ∼0.5 mg/ml G418 for at least 
6-8 weeks. The imposed selection leads to about 40-50% of 
cells as FLAG positive in the population. 
For experiments involving motor defective form of 
myosin protein, V5 tagged nuclear myosin constructs--wild 
type and G126S (motor function mutant) (kindly provided 
by Prof. Ingrid Grummt, German Cancer Research Cen-
tre) were over-expressed in NHDFs and stable cells were se-
lected using G418. </p>

<p>RNAi </p>

<p>For Rad51 knock down studies, Rad51 siRNA from Dhar-
macon (ON-TARGETplus SMARTpool-Human RAD51 
L-003530-00-0005) and control siRNA from Sigma 
(MISSION R 
siRNA Universal Negative Control #1) were 
used. A total of 100 nM of these siRNAs were transfected 
into cells using lipofectamine 2000 (Life Technologies) and 
samples were collected at 72 h post transfection. 
For nuclear myosin knock down experiments, 100 nM 
of MYO1C siRNA from Dharmacon (ON-TARGETplus 
SMARTpool-Human MYO1C L-015121-00-0005) and 
control siRNA 5 -UUCUCCGAACGUGUCACGU-3 
were used (74). Since MYO1C siRNA is a mixture of 
oligonucleotide probes directed against entire MYO1C 
gene, the siRNA effects are not specific to any particular 
isoform of myosin 1C. siRNAs were transfected into cells 
using lipofectamine 2000 (Life Technologies) and samples 
were collected at 48 h post transfection. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence assay </p>

<p>Cells were grown on coverslips and following cisplatin dam-
age, cells were fixed with 4% PFA (1X PBS) for 10 min, 
permeabilized with 0.1% Triton X-100 (1X PBS) for 15 
min. Cells were then incubated with antibodies to ϒ-H2AX 
(Abcam), 53BP1 (Santacruz), FLAG (Abcam) or Nuclear 
myosin1 [for detecting NM1] (Sigma) dissolved in 1% 
BSA (1X PBS) for an hour, followed by washes in 1X PBS 
and incubation with Alexa secondary antibodies (Invitro-
gen)(dissolved in 1% BSA) for 45 min. The coverslips were 
washed again in 1X PBS and stained with DAPI in Vec-
tashield mounting media. Cells were imaged using a Zeiss 
Axiovert 200 microscope. </p>

<p>Immuno-fluorescence in situ hybridization (Immuno-FISH) </p>

<p>Immuno-FISH was carried out using a previously pub-
lished protocol (75). Briefly, cells were grown on slides and </p>

<p>fixed with 4% PFA (1X PBS) for 10 min. The slides were 
then washed thrice in 0.05% Triton X-100 (1X PBS) for 5 
min each time and cells were permeabilized in 0.5% Triton 
X-100 (1X PBS) for 10 min. For FLAG Immuno-FISH, 
FISH was done before immunostaining. The slides were 
incubated in 20% glycerol (1X PBS) for 30 min and then 
freeze-thawed in liquid nitrogen 4 times. The slides were 
again washed in 0.05% Triton X-100 (3 × 5 min). Depuri-
nation was carried out in 0.1 N HCl for 10 min and again 
washing was done for 3 × 5 min in 0.05% Triton X-100. 
Equilibration was carried out in 2X SSC for 5 min and then 
in 50% formamide (2X SSC) over night at room tempera-
ture. Slides were denaturated in 70% and 50% formamide 
for 3 min and 1 min, respectively, at 73 • C. A total of 10 l 
of labeled total human chromosome specific DNA probes 
(Applied Spectral imaging) was denatured for 7 min at 
80 • C, re-annealed at 37 • C for 20 min and hybridized onto 
the slides for 2-3 days at 37 • C. Post hybridization, washes 
were done at 73 • C in 0.4X SSC (3 × 3 min) and 4X SSC 
with 0.1% Tween20 (3 × 3 min). Immunostaining for the 
FLAG tag was done as described earlier in order to identify 
the H2AX construct expressing cells. The slides were then 
stained with TO-PRO-3 (Life Technologies) and confocal 
images with stacks of 0.3 m optical sections of at least 
30 nuclei (in 2 independent experiments), were obtained us-
ing a Zeiss confocal laser scanning microscope (LSM510) at 
100x magnification. The distance between the nuclear cen-
tre and the centre of the chromosome territory (centre here 
refers to the center of mass) was measured using <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Bitplane</rs> 
<rs id="software-3" type="software">Imaris</rs> software. 
For NM1 Immuno-FISH, immunostaining was done be-
fore FISH. All the steps were same as described above. Af-
ter immunostaining, the cells were fixed by using 4% PFA 
for 10 min, washed with PBS and then subjected to all the 
FISH steps, starting with incubation in 20% glycerol and fi-
nally the cells were mounted in Vectashield mounting media 
containing DAPI. </p>

<p>Two-dimensional Fluorescence in situ hybridization (2D-
FISH) </p>

<p>2D-FISH was performed using a protocol described earlier 
(46). Briefly, cells were trypsinized and the pellet was resus-
pended in hypotonic 0.075 M KCl solution. This was fol-
lowed by their fixation in 3:1(v/v) methanol: acetic acid. 
Cells were dropped on slides and subjected to sequential 
70%, 90%, 100% ethanol treatment. Denaturation was per-
formed at 70 • C for 2 min in 70% formamide (2X SSC). 
Ten microliters of labeled human chromosome DNA probe 
(Applied Spectral Imaging) that had been denatured at 
80 • C for 7 min and re-annealed at 37 • C for 20 min, was 
applied to the denatured cells. Hybridization was done at 
37 • C overnight. Post hybridization, washes were performed 
at 72 • C in 0.4X SSC (3 × 3 min) and 4X SSC with 0.1% 
Tween20 (3 × 3 min). Cells were mounted in Vectashield 
containing DAPI. At least 100 nuclei were imaged on a Zeiss 
Axiovert 200 microscope at 100x magnification and pro-
cessed through the software package <rs type="software">IMACULAT</rs> (76,77) 
for quantitation of the probe signal. One-way ANOVA and 
t-tests were performed. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 17 8275 </p>

<p>Nuclear fractionation and Western blotting </p>

<p>A previously described nuclear fractionation protocol was 
used (78). Cells (1 × 10 6 ) were resuspended in buffer A [10 
mM HEPES (pH = 7.9), 1.5 mM MgCl 2 , 10 mM KCl, 1 
mM DTT, 1X protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche)] and were 
incubated on ice for 5 min. Nuclei were collected in the pel-
let fraction by centrifuging at 1300 g, 4 min, 4 • C. The nuclei 
were washed once with buffer A, followed by the addition 
of buffer B [3 mM EDTA, 0.2 mM EGTA, 1 mM DTT, 
1X protease inhibitor cocktail] for 10 min to lyse the nu-
clei. Centrifugation at 1700 g, 4 min, 4 • C was used to col-
lect the insoluble chromatin fraction in the pellet and the 
nuclear soluble fraction (NS) in the supernatant. The pel-
let was washed once with buffer B and centrifuged again. 
The final chromatin enriched pellet (CP) was dissolved in 
Laemmli buffer and sonicated thrice (15 s pulse) using a 
Branson sonicator. 
For salt extraction, chromatin pellets from cells were in-
cubated in 200, 400 and 800 mM NaCl containing buffer B, 
kept on ice for 30 min and centrifuged at 20 000 g for 10 min. 
Equal volumes of supernatant (soluble fraction) and pellet 
were loaded on the gel for subsequent Western blotting. 
For whole cell lysates, cells were washed with 1X PBS 
twice. The pellet was resuspended in 1X RIPA buffer con-
taining protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche) and incubated 
on ice for 30 min. The lysate was centrifuged at 14 000 r. p. 
m. for 10 min at 4 • C. 
Protein concentrations were determined by using the 
BCA assay (Pierce BCA kit) and 30 g of protein was 
used for immunoblotting. Western blotting of the nu-
clear soluble (NS) and the CP fractions was done by 
separating the proteins on a SDS PAGE gel (8% re-
solving gel for NM1, INO80, ALDHIAI and 15% re-
solving gel for H2AX, FLAG, actin) and blotting onto 
PVDF membrane. The membrane was then probed with 
antibodies for Nuclear myosin1 [for detecting NM1] 
(Sigma-Aldrich), actin (Sigma-Aldrich), -Tubulin (Sigma-
Aldrich), FLAG (Sigma-Aldrich), INO80 (Abcam), ALD-
HIAI (Abcam), Rad51 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology), H2AX 
(Abcam), GSK3 (Cell Signaling) or PhosphoSer9GSK3 
(Cell Signaling) as mentioned in the figure legends. NM1, 
INO80 or actin levels in the nuclear fractions were quan-
tified using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software, by normalizing the Western 
blot band intensity with the total coomassie protein load 
intensity (after subtracting the equivalent background of 
the blank) for the fraction and plotted as fold change. Total 
coomassie protein load was used as a loading control (79-
81) instead of conventional loading controls such as actin, 
tubulin because we observed changes in actin (Supplemen-
tary Figure S4: Panel E) and tubulin levels in the nuclear 
fractions upon DNA damage. Because of this observed vari-
ability, we could not use these markers as reliable loading 
controls. Histones also could not be used as a loading con-
trol in the Western blots for the nuclear fractionation ex-
periments as they showed up in only the chromatin pellet 
fraction and not in the nuclear soluble fraction. For whole 
cell lysates, -tubulin was used as a loading control. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Blocking ϒ-H2AX signaling leads to inhibition of DNA dam-
age dependent chromosome territory relocation </p>

<p>Certain gene rich chromosomes have been shown to relo-
cate upon induction of DNA damage (46). However, how 
DNA damage signals such a response is not very clear. 
In order to understand the same, we decided to assess 
the role of ϒ-H2AX -an early chromatin modification at 
DSBs. ϒ-H2AX signaling was down regulated using a non-
phosphorylatable mutant of H2AX. FLAG tagged H2AX 
wild type or mutant H2AX S139A was transfected into nor-
mal human dermal fibroblasts (NHDFs) and the cells ex-
pressing these constructs in the pool of transfected cells 
(∼40-50% of the total selected population) were identified 
by immunostaining for the FLAG tag. 
As expected, the overexpressed FLAG tagged H2AX 
proteins were incorporated into the chromatin fraction 
(∼50% of the total H2AX) of the nuclei as observed by im-
munoblotting of the FLAG tag in the CP (Supplementary 
Figure S1: Panel A and B). To ensure that following cis-
platin damage cells expressing the H2AX constructs are not 
undergoing cell death, cells showing apoptotic changes such 
as nuclear fragmentation, membrane blebbing and DNA 
condensation were quantified (82,83). Since the percent-
age of apoptotic nuclei in the H2AX wild type and H2AX 
S139A expressing cells in the absence or presence of cis-
platin damage (25 M for 4 h) was found to be under 12% 
(Supplementary Figure S1: Panel C), subsequent studies on 
CT positions in these cells following DNA damage were car-
ried out using the same regime. 
Cells expressing the mutant H2AX S139A showed fewer 
number of ϒ-H2AX foci upon cisplatin damage than those 
in either untransfected or H2AX wild type transfected con-
trol cells (Figure 1A-C). Since only half of H2AX in the 
chromatin comprises of mutant form of protein (Supple-
mentary Figure S1: Panel B), therefore we surmise that the 
same must have acted as dominant-negative in order to 
show a decrease in the overall ϒ-H2AX foci count. It was 
also assessed whether such decrease in ϒ-H2AX levels in 
the mutant cells leads to a concomitant drop in its down-
stream protein signaling targets. After DNA damage, levels 
of 53BP1 levels have been observed to increase (84-86), fol-
lowing which ϒ-H2AX signaling leads to the accumulation 
of 53BP1 at DSB sites (18,86). It has been suggested that the 
role of phosphorylated 53BP1 can be uncoupled from DSB 
repair, as the binding of 53BP1 to DSBs has been found to 
be independent of its phosphorylation status (87). We there-
fore monitored total 53BP1 levels in H2AX S139A cells and 
compared the same with untransfected and H2AX wild type 
transfected cells following DNA damage. Similar to ear-
lier reports in normal human fibroblasts (85,88), we also 
observed that untransfected, H2AX wild type or H2AX 
S139A mutant expressing NHDFs without any damage ex-
hibited faint immunostaining of 53BP1. Moreover, as ex-
pected, nearly all the nuclei (∼100%) in the case of un-
transfected NHDFs or H2AX wild type expressing control 
cells showed high levels (mean intensity &gt; 27 a.u.) of total 
53BP1 following cisplatin damage. In contrast, only 21.8% 
of H2AX S139A expressing cells displayed high levels of </p>

<p>8276 Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 17 </p>

<p>Figure 1. ϒ-H2AX foci are reduced in H2AX S139A transfected cells. H2AX transfected NHDFs were identified by staining for FLAG (red). ϒ-H2AX 
staining (green) was visualized in untransfected, H2AX wild type and H2AX S139A transfected NHDFs under undamaged or Cp (cisplatin) damaged 
conditions. (A) Images were taken at 40x magnification in order to show the effect of H2AX S139A mutant construct in a population of cells. Arrows point 
to FLAG positive nuclei in Cp treated H2AX wild type or S139A transfected cells. (B and C) Quantitation of ϒ-H2AX foci in untransfected, H2AX wild 
type and H2AX S139A expressing cells was performed on confocal images taken at 100x magnification using <rs type="software">Imaris</rs> software. N = 2, n = 25. Error bars 
represent the s.e.m. * indicates P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 17 8277 </p>

<p>53BP1 (Figure 2A and B) and the remaining large fraction 
of nuclei in these cells showed only basal levels of 53BP1 
even after DNA damage. Recruitment of chromatin remod-
eler INO80 has been shown to ensue via direct interaction 
with ϒ-H2AX foci at the DSB sites (17). Therefore, we as-
sessed the protein levels of the INO80 in the nuclear sol-
uble and chromatin fractions in H2AX S139A cells before 
and after cisplatin damage. In nuclear fractionation experi-
ments, the total coomassie protein load was used as a load-
ing control (79-81) instead of conventional loading controls 
such as actin, tubulin because we observed changes in actin 
(Supplementary Figure S4: Panel E) and tubulin levels in 
the nuclear fractions upon DNA damage. The recruitment 
of INO80 to the chromatin pellet fraction did not increase 
in mutant cells upon DNA damage, which contrasted from 
that of untransfected or wild type H2AX expressing cells 
where INO80 levels were increased in the chromatin frac-
tion following damage (Figure 2C-F). All these results put 
together confirmed that the decrease in ϒ-H2AX foci num-
ber led to a concomitant reduction of its downstream sig-
naling in the mutant H2AX expressing cells following DNA 
damage. 
In order to understand the role of ϒ-H2AX in DNA 
damage induced CT relocations, the positions of chromo-
somes 19, 15 and 11 were monitored in cells expressing mu-
tant ϒ-H2AX and compared with their control counter-
parts. Positions of these chromosomes were not significantly 
changed in the untransfected and H2AX transfected cells 
(Supplementary Figure S2: Panel D) in the absence of any 
DNA damage. Upon DNA damage, in control cells the re-
location of chromosome 19 from nuclear interior to nuclear 
periphery and chromosome 15 from nuclear periphery to 
the interior was observed and this corroborated our ear-
lier results (46) (Figure 3A and B). However, such DNA 
damage induced relocation of both these chromosomes was 
not observed in the cells expressing mutant H2AX S139A 
construct (Figure 3C). Chromosome 11 whose position (pe-
ripheral to intermediate within the nucleus) remains unal-
tered following DNA damage (46) was taken as a negative 
control and as expected its position remained unchanged 
in the untransfected cells as well as the H2AX construct 
expressing cells following DNA damage. Volumes of the 
CTs were not significantly altered in undamaged versus cis-
platin damaged conditions in the control cells (untrans-
fected, H2AX wild type transfected) and H2AX S139A 
transfected cells (Supplementary Figure S3: Panel A-C). 
Since cisplatin damage induced CT relocation fails to oc-
cur in H2AX S139A mutant expressing cells, this indicates 
that ϒ-H2AX signaling is required for the CT relocation 
during DDR. ϒ-H2AX recruits chromatin remodelers such 
as INO80 and NuA4 near the DSB sites, thus rendering 
them more accessible to the repair machinery (16-18,89). 
Therefore, it can be speculated that by remodeling chro-
matin at multiple DSB sites, ϒ-H2AX signaling may lead 
to a concerted structural change at a whole chromosomal 
level, finally guiding DNA damage induced CT relocation. </p>

<p>Inhibition of late steps of repair catalyzed by Rad51 or DNA 
ligase IV do not fully abrogate damage dependent CT reloca-
tion </p>

<p>Earlier we had reported that initial sensing and repair of the 
DSBs by ATM kinase and DNAPK play an important role 
in damage induced relocation of CTs (46). In order to assess 
what happens to CT relocation when later stages of DSB re-
pair are inhibited, we analyzed cells in which the function 
of DNA ligase IV or Rad51 [repair proteins that function 
during relatively later stages of NHEJ and HR pathways, re-
spectively (90-93)] is inhibited or knocked down. The tech-
nique of 2D-FISH was used for the analysis of CT positions 
in these experiments. 2D-FISH is a relatively more facile 
technique in comparison to 3D-FISH and when statistically 
high number of nuclei (at least 100 per experiment) are ana-
lyzed, 2D-FISH does indeed corroborate the CT positions 
uncovered by 3D-FISH (40,46,77). 
Inhibition of DNA ligase IV by a specific chemical in-
hibitor SCR7 (94-96), resulted in partial relocation of CT 
19 and near complete relocation of CT 15 following 4 h of 
cisplatin damage (Figure 4A). A similar result was observed 
in the case of Rad51 siRNA treated cells in comparison to 
the control siRNA treated cells (Figure 4B). It is plausible 
that CT 19 being most gene dense chromosome is more sen-
sitive to inhibition of late repair steps (NHEJ or HR), lead-
ing to some effect on its CT dynamics. But clearly CT 15 dy-
namics were relatively unaffected by inhibition in these late 
repair steps. Expectedly, position of the negative control CT 
11 (peripheral to intermediate) remained unchanged post 
cisplatin damage under all these conditions. Since cisplatin 
damage treatment exceeding 6-7 h resulted in significantly 
higher level of cell death in DNA ligase IV inhibitor treated 
and Rad51 knockdown conditions, CT positioning analy-
ses at longer time points of damage treatment were not car-
ried out. The partial (CT 19) or nearly complete (CT 15) 
relocation of CTs in response to DNA damage, when the 
function of late repair proteins DNA ligase IV or Rad51 
are inhibited/knocked down suggests that the early steps 
of DSB repair play a more important role in CT relocation 
than the later stages of repair. In fact such partial effects 
on CT repositioning might be an indirect consequence of 
repair inhibition impacting the early sensors and effectors. 
Initiation of damage sensing and signaling that does not ac-
complish DNA repair (due to inhibition of late players of 
repair) may feedback inhibit ongoing CT relocation lead-
ing to partial inhibitory effects. </p>

<p>Nuclear myosin 1 (NM1) recruitment to chromatin is en-
hanced by DNA damage treatment </p>

<p>DNA damage induced CT relocation is specific to certain 
gene rich chromosomes and therefore, does not seem to be 
a random diffusion based process. The motor protein NM1 
has been implicated in whole chromosome repositioning 
during serum starvation (40) and also in the repositioning 
of a chromosomal domain (58). To assess if the same mo-
tor protein is involved in the context of DNA damage in-
duced CT repositioning, the levels of this protein were an-
alyzed before and after DNA damage. NM1 levels in the 
chromatin fraction were already high in control NHDFs 
even in the absence of DNA damage (Figure 5A). Such </p>



<p>Figure 2. ϒ-H2AX signaling is reduced in H2AX S139A transfected cells. (A) Total 53BP1 staining in untransfected, H2AX wild type and H2AX S139A 
transfected NHDFs under undamaged or Cp (cisplatin) damaged conditions. Images were taken at 63x magnification. Arrows point to FLAG positive 
nuclei in the FLAG-H2AX transfected population. (B) Quantification of nuclei that showed high levels (Mean intensity &gt; 27 a.u.) of total 53BP1 following 
damage. N = 2, n = 55. (C) Representative images of INO80 Western blots in untransfected, (D) H2AX WT and H2AX S139A transfected NHDFs in the 
absence or presence of cisplatin treatment. NS = Nuclear soluble, CP = Chromatin pellet. Lanes in the blot have been spliced together in the sample order 
same as that of the coomassie gel loading control in (D). N = 3 for Western blots. (E) Quantitation of INO80 levels in nuclear fractions of untransfected, (F) 
H2AX WT and H2AX S139A transfected NHDFs in the absence or presence of cisplatin treatment. INO80 levels in the nuclear fractions were quantified 
using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software, by normalizing the Western blot band intensity with total coomassie protein load intensity (loading control) for the fraction and 
plotted as fold change. NS = Nuclear soluble, CP = Chromatin pellet. N = 3. P-values calculated using Student's t-test. Error bars represent the s.d., * 
indicates P &lt; 0.05, n.s. = not significant. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 17 8279 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
1 0 1 1 </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>Distance between chromosome territory centre 
and nuclear centre (µm) </p>

<p>Chromosome 11 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
1 0 1 1 </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>Distance between chromosome territory centre 
and nuclear centre (µm) </p>

<p>Chromosome 15 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
1 0 1 1 </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>Distance between chromosome territory centre 
and nuclear centre (µm) </p>

<p>Chromosome 19 </p>

<p>Untreated </p>

<p>Cp treated </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
1 0 1 1 </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>Distance between chromosome territory centre 
and nuclear centre (µm) </p>

<p>Chromosome 11 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
1 0 1 1 </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>Distance between chromosome territory centre 
and nuclear centre (µm) </p>

<p>Chromosome 15 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
1 0 1 1 </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>Distance between chromosome territory centre 
and nuclear centre (µm) </p>

<p>Chromosome 19 </p>

<p>Untreated </p>

<p>Cp treated </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
1 0 
1 1 </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>Distance between chromosome territory centre 
and nuclear centre (µm) </p>

<p>Chromosome 11 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
1 0 
1 1 </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>Distance between chromosome territory centre 
and nuclear centre (µm) </p>

<p>Chromosome 15 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
1 0 
1 1 </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>Distance between chromosome territory centre 
and nuclear centre (µm) </p>

<p>Chromosome 19 </p>

<p>Untreated </p>

<p>Cp treated </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Untransfected NHDFs </p>

<p>Undamaged 
Cp damaged </p>

<p>Chr19 </p>

<p>Chr11 </p>

<p>H2AX WT </p>

<p>H2AX S139A </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Undamaged 
Cp damaged </p>

<p>Undamaged Cp damaged </p>

<p>Chr19 
Chr19 </p>

<p>Chr15 </p>

<p>Chr11 </p>

<p>Chr15 </p>

<p>Chr11 
Chr11 </p>

<p>Chr11 
Chr11 </p>

<p>Chr15 
Chr15 </p>

<p>Chr19 </p>

<p>Chr15 
Chr15 </p>

<p>Chr19 </p>

<p>Chr19 </p>

<p>Distance between territory centre and nuclear centre (µm) </p>

<p>NHDFs Untreated Chr11 </p>

<p>NHDFs Cp treated Chr11 </p>

<p>H2AX WT Untreated Chr11 </p>

<p>H2AX WT Cp treated Chr11 </p>

<p>H2AX S139A Untreated Chr11 </p>

<p>NHDFs Untreated Chr19 </p>

<p>NHDFs Cp treated Chr19 </p>

<p>H2AX WT Untreated Chr19 </p>

<p>H2AX WT Cp treated Chr19 </p>

<p>H2AX S139A Untreated Chr19 </p>

<p>NHDFs Untreated Chr15 </p>

<p>NHDFs Cp treated Chr15 </p>

<p>H2AX WT Untreated Chr15 </p>

<p>H2AX WT Cp treated Chr15 </p>

<p>H2AX S139A Untreated Chr15 </p>

<p>H2AX S139A Cp treated Chr19 </p>

<p>H2AX S139A Cp treated Chr15 </p>

<p>H2AX S139A Cp treated Chr11 </p>

<p>Distance between territory centre and nuclear centre (µm) </p>

<p>Distance between territory centre and nuclear centre (µm) </p>

<p>C 
P </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P 
C 
C </p>

<p>C 
P 
C 
P </p>

<p>C 
P 
C 
P </p>

<p>n.s. 
n.s. </p>

<p>n.s. </p>

<p>n.s. </p>

<p>n.s. </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Figure 3. Chromosome territory repositioning requires ϒ-H2AX signaling. Immuno-FISH was performed, where H2AX wild type and S139A expressing 
cells were identified by FLAG (blue) immunostaining, followed by FISH for chromosome 19 (red), 15 (yellow) and 11 (green). Nuclei were visualized by 
TO-PRO-3 staining (grey). Territory position is expressed as a frequency distribution of either (A) untransfected or (B and C) FLAG positive transfected 
nuclei. Distance (in m) between the nuclear centre and CT centre in 3D confocal images (63x magnification) was quantitated using <rs type="software">Imaris</rs> software. N 
= 2, n = at least 30 nuclei. P-values were calculated using Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. * and ** indicate P &lt; 0.05 and P &lt; 0.01 respectively. n. s. = not 
significant. (D) Box plots generated using the web tool BoxPlotR (113) for the same data are displayed. The box plots span the second quartile, median 
and the fourth quartile of the distances, while negative and positive error bars represent the minimum and maximum distances. On box plot Y-axis Cp = 
Cisplatin damaged. On frequency distribution graphs C = Centre of nucleus, P = Periphery of nucleus. </p>

<p>8280 Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 17 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>Undamaged </p>

<p>Cp damaged </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>Undamaged </p>

<p>Cp damaged </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>% Probe </p>

<p>Shell Number 
Shell Number 
Shell Number </p>

<p>Undamaged </p>

<p>Cp damaged </p>

<p>Without DNA Ligase IV inhibitor </p>

<p>10 µm </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Control siRNA 
Rad51 siRNA </p>

<p>Undamaged </p>

<p>Cp damaged </p>

<p>Chr19 
Chr19 
Chr15 
Chr11 
Chr15 
Chr11 </p>

<p>Undamaged </p>

<p>Cp damaged </p>

<p>Undamaged </p>

<p>Cp damaged </p>

<p>Chr19 
Chr19 
Chr15 
Chr11 
Chr15 
Chr11 </p>

<p>Shell Number 
Shell Number 
Shell Number </p>

<p>Chr19 </p>

<p>C 
C 
C 
C 
C 
C 
P 
P 
P 
P 
P 
P </p>

<p>5µm </p>

<p>5µm 
5µm </p>

<p>With DNA Ligase IV inhibitor </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* * </p>

<p>* * 
* 
* </p>

<p>* * 
* * </p>

<p>Chr15 
Chr11 
Chr19 
Chr15 
Chr11 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>5µm </p>

<p>% Probe </p>

<p>% Probe </p>

<p>Shell Number 
Shell Number 
Shell Number 
Shell Number 
Shell Number 
Shell Number </p>

<p>Chr19 </p>

<p>C 
C 
C 
C 
C 
C 
P 
P 
P 
P 
P 
P </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* * </p>

<p>* * 
* </p>

<p>* * 
* * </p>

<p>Chr15 
Chr11 
Chr19 
Chr15 
Chr11 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>% Probe </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>Figure 4. Partial or no effect on CT relocation upon inhibition of DNA ligase IV or Rad51 function. Positions of chromosomes 19, 15 and 11 were 
assessed by 2D-FISH in (A) cells treated with or without DNA ligase IV inhibitor; (B) control siRNA and Rad51 siRNA treated cells. 2D-FISH images 
were analyzed and quantitated by using the computational script <rs type="software">IMACULAT</rs> (76,77). X-axes of the graphs depict the nuclear shell number, with 1 being 
as the outermost and 5 being the innermost shell. Y-axes of the graphs show the percentage of probe normalized to DAPI. N = 2, n &gt; 100 nuclei. Error 
bars represent the s.e.m. P-values calculated using Student's t-test.* and ** indicate P &lt; 0.05 and P &lt; 0.01, respectively; n.s. = not significant. On graphs 
C = Centre of nucleus, P = Periphery of nucleus. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 17 8281 </p>

<p>Figure 5. Nuclear myosin 1 level increases in chromatin fraction upon DNA damage which depends on ϒ-H2AX function. (A) Levels of NM1 in nuclear 
fractions of untransfected NHDFs were assessed by Western blotting before and after cisplatin damage and plotted as (i) fold change or (ii) percentage of 
total NM1 intensity. N = 3. (B) Salt extraction of NM1 from insoluble chromatin pellet fraction with increasing concentrations of NaCl. Histone H4 was 
taken as a control. S = Soluble fraction, P = Pellet fraction. N = 2 (C) Representative Western blot for H2AX wild type and H2AX S139A expressing cells 
under undamaged and cisplatin treated conditions. N = 3. The image is an under exposure to prevent oversaturation of the signal in the Cp treated H2AX 
wild type chromatin pellet fraction lane. NS = Nuclear soluble, CP = Chromatin pellet. NM1 levels in the nuclear fractions were quantified using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> 
software, by normalizing the Western blot band intensity with total coomassie protein load intensity (loading control) for the fraction and plotted as fold 
change or percentage of total NM1 in the nucleus. P-values calculated using Student's t-test. Error bars represent the s.d., * indicates P &lt; 0.05 and n.s. = 
not significant. </p>

<p>high levels of chromatin bound NM1 are consistent with its 
functional roles in nuclear processes such as transcription 
and chromatin remodeling, etc. (64-66,68,97). Interestingly 
upon cisplatin damage, the levels of NM1 in chromatin frac-
tion showed a measurable increase (∼1.5-to 2-fold) as com-
pared to undamaged control (Figure 5A (ii)). However, sur-
prisingly the levels of NM1 in the whole cell lysates (Supple-
mentary Figure S4: Panel B) or whole nuclei (Supplemen-
tary Figure S4: Panel C) did not seem to change after cis-
platin damage. The relative levels of NM1 in undamaged 
cells (the nuclear soluble (NS) versus chromatin pellet (CP) 
fraction with respect to the total nuclear NM1 after normal-
ization for differential protein load) showed ∼55% of NM1 
in the CP fraction, while the remaining was in NS form. 
Following cisplatin damage, the chromatin bound NM1 in-
creased to ∼76% of the total nuclear NM1 (Figure 5A (iii)). 
These results were also corroborated by immunostaining 
experiments, where high number of NM1 puncta within 
the nucleus were observed even in undamaged state, with 
an increase in the number of puncta following DNA dam-
age (Supplementary Figure S6: Panel A and B). Marginal 
increase in NM1 puncta following DNA damage is con-
sistent with ∼1.5-to 2-fold increase in chromatin bound </p>

<p>NM1 observed in the Western analysis. Such an increase in 
chromatin bound NM1 occurred after at least two types of 
DNA damages, as cells treated with hydrogen peroxide also 
showed similar (∼1.5-fold) increase in the chromatin bound 
protein (Supplementary Figure S4: Panel D). 
To assess the strength of interactions of NM1 with chro-
matin, salt extraction of NM1 from the chromatin pellet 
was done with increasing concentrations of NaCl (Figure 
5B). NM1 started dissociating from the chromatin pellet 
into the soluble fraction at 400 mM NaCl, but most of the 
protein was still associated with the pellet fraction of chro-
matin even at 800 mM NaCl concentration. Histone H4, a 
tightly bound protein in the chromatin, was taken as an in-
ternal control and as expected it did not elute into the sol-
uble fraction even at 800 mM NaCl. These data indicated 
that NM1 is a stably bound component of chromatin frac-
tion, but starts eluting at a NaCl concentration lower than 
that required for a core histone such as H4. Cisplatin dam-
aged nuclei exhibited an essentially similar elution profile 
of NM1 and H4 proteins as the undamaged control nuclei. 
Interestingly, the nature of association of NM1 with chro-
matin does not seem to get affected following DNA damage. </p>

<p>8282 Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 17 </p>

<p>However, uncovering the details of the same need further 
experimental probing. 
Surprisingly, in untransfected NHDFs the levels of actin 
in both the nuclear soluble and the chromatin fraction de-
creased upon cisplatin induced DNA damage (Supplemen-
tary Figure S4: Panel E). It has been reported that nuclear 
actin and myosin have uncoupled roles in the nuclear func-
tions (67,68). Therefore, the damage induced increase in 
chromatin bound NM1 and the decrease in actin levels in 
the nucleus that we have observed may reflect a differential 
regulation of activities of the two motor proteins in the nu-
cleus. How DNA damage signaling regulates the activity of 
these proteins differentially during DDR remains to be in-
vestigated. </p>

<p>DNA damage dependent increase of NM1 recruitment to 
chromatin is mediated by ϒ-H2AX signaling and requires 
DNA damage sensors </p>

<p>In the previous experiment, we showed that induction of 
DNA damage leads to enhanced recruitment of NM1 to 
chromatin. In order to test if ϒ-H2AX signaling has any 
role in the recruitment of NM1 to the chromatin as well as 
the repositioning of CTs following DNA damage, we an-
alyzed the levels of NM1 in the chromatin fraction in ϒ-
H2AX wild type and compared it with that in H2AX S139A 
mutant expressing cells. The wild type H2AX construct ex-
pressing cells showed the expected increase in NM1 recruit-
ment to the chromatin fraction just like the untransfected 
NHDFs. Surprisingly, such an increase in chromatin bound 
NM1 was not observed in H2AX S139A expressing cells 
and the recruitment of NM1 to the chromatin fraction re-
mained unchanged in these cells before and after cisplatin 
damage (Figure 5C). Therefore, these results suggest that ϒ-
H2AX signaling is functionally coupled with the cisplatin 
damage induced enhanced chromatin recruitment of NM1. 
In our previous study (46), we had shown that the recogni-
tion of DNA damage by sensor and repair proteins, such as 
ATM kinase and DNAPK precedes CT relocation. There-
fore, we tested if such DNA damage induced recruitment 
of NM1 to the chromatin fraction also requires the func-
tion of DSB sensors such as ATM, ATR kinase, PARP-1 
and DNAPK. As reported earlier (98-100), ϒ-H2AX im-
munostaining was found to decrease in cells pretreated with 
ATM, ATR or DNAPK inhibitor following cisplatin dam-
age (Supplementary Figure S5: Panel A-C). Interestingly, 
we observed that cells upon prior treatment with inhibitors 
for not only sensor proteins ATM, ATR and DNAPK, but 
also PARP-1 failed to exhibit enhanced chromatin recruit-
ment of NM1 following cisplatin damage (Figure 6A-D), 
thereby suggesting that general sensing of DNA damage 
seems to be mechanistically coupled to the process of NM1 
recruitment to the chromatin following DNA damage. </p>

<p>NM1 is essential for chromosome territory repositioning fol-
lowing DNA damage </p>

<p>NM1 is the predominant nuclear isoform encoded by 
MYO1C gene (59). In order to check if this nuclear motor 
is essential for CT relocation during DDR, we employed 
siRNA mediated knockdown of the MYO1C gene (Supple-</p>

<p>mentary Figure S7: Panel A-C). The siRNA knockdown re-
sulted in ∼60-70% reduction in NM1 levels as assessed by 
Western analysis. By using chromosome-specific 2D-FISH 
analysis (46,76,77), we assessed the positions of chromo-
some 19, 15 and 11 in cells transfected with control and 
MYO1C siRNA. Such analyses corroborated our results 
that control NHDFs (treated with the control siRNA) ex-
hibited the expected relocation of chromosome 19 from the 
nuclear interior to the periphery upon cisplatin damage and 
vice versa for chromosome 15. However, in the same experi-
mental conditions, MYO1C knockdown cells failed to show 
any damage induced relocation of chromosome 19 and 15 
(Figure 7). Expectedly, chromosome 11 taken as a nega-
tive control did not show any spatial relocation following 
DNA damage in cells treated with either siRNA. Since, the 
MYO1C siRNA that has been used for RNAi experiment 
(Figure 7) is a mixture of oligonucleotide probes directed 
against entire MYO1C gene and thus siRNA effects may 
not be specific to any particular isoform of myosin 1C, as 
any of or all three isoforms (a, b or c -all of which are 
found in the nucleus) might have been down regulated in the 
siRNA experiment. Since NM1 levels certainly decrease fol-
lowing the siRNA treatment as observed by Western blot-
ting and IF analyses (Supplementary Figure S7: Panel A-
C), it is clear that NM1 is definitely required for the process 
of CT relocation during DDR. The specific participation of 
the myosin 1C isoforms, if any, in CT relocation remains 
to be investigated and it would be interesting to uncover 
if these three nuclear isoforms cross-talk/coordinate with 
each other in the context of DNA damage and repair. 
NM1 mutants that have impaired motor function are 
unable to associate with RNA polymerase I and rDNA 
(66,69). To understand how the motor activity of NM1 in-
fluences its enhanced chromatin binding and CT relocation 
post DNA damage, cells over-expressing V5 tagged NM1 
motor function defective mutant (G126S-that has defec-
tive ATPase function) or wild type NM1 were analyzed (66). 
As expected, in the control cells expressing wild type NM1, 
damage induced increase in chromatin recruitment of NM1 
and CT relocation were observed (Figure 8). In contrast, the 
NM1-G126S mutant expressing cells failed to show such 
DNA damage induced changes (Figure 8), indicating that 
the motor function of NM1 was important for its binding 
to chromatin following damage and for the subsequent CT 
relocation. This is a significant mechanistic insight high-
lighting the importance of nuclear myosin's motor function 
not only for its association with Pol I transcriptional ma-
chinery (66) but also for its binding to chromatin following 
DNA damage and mediating CT repositioning. It is impor-
tant to note here that the resident level of NM1-G126S in 
chromatin fraction prior to DNA damage does not seem to 
change compared to wild type NM1 (Figure 8A). Moreover, 
a previous study has shown that an impaired motor activ-
ity mutant of NM1 protein (RK605AA) fails to recruit to 
rDNA chromatin; we believe that our bulk chromatin frac-
tionation assay does not seem to capture such finer details of 
NM1 recruitment (69). However, the results of experiments 
involving dominant negative G126S mutant of NM1 (Fig-
ure 8) do seem to reinforce the result of siRNA experiment 
(Figure 7) that isoform NM1 certainly does participate in 
the CT relocation occurring post cisplatin damage. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 17 8283 </p>

<p>Figure 6. Increased nuclear myosin 1 recruitment to chromatin requires DNA damage sensors. Representative Western blots for NM1 in cells subjected to 
treatment with inhibitors of (A) ATM, (B) ATR, (C) PARP-1 and (D) DNAPK before cisplatin damage and the quantitation of the blots. NS = Nuclear 
soluble, CP = Chromatin pellet. NM1 levels in the nuclear fractions were quantified using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software, by normalizing the Western blot band intensity 
with total coomassie protein load intensity (loading control) for the fraction and plotted as fold change. N = 3. Lanes from the same blot and gel have 
been merged together in (D). P-values calculated using Student's t-test. Error bars represent the s.d., * indicates P &lt; 0.05 and n.s. = not significant. </p>

<p>8284 Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 17 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>Undamaged </p>

<p>Cp damaged </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>Undamaged </p>

<p>Cp damaged </p>

<p>Control siRNA </p>

<p>Undamaged </p>

<p>Cp damaged </p>

<p>Chr19 
Chr19 
Chr15 
Chr11 
Chr15 
Chr11 </p>

<p>MYO1C siRNA </p>

<p>10 µm 
10 µm </p>

<p>% Probe </p>

<p>Shell Number 
Shell Number 
Shell Number 
Shell Number 
Shell Number 
Shell Number </p>

<p>Chr19 </p>

<p>C 
C 
C 
C 
C 
C 
P 
P 
P 
P 
P 
P </p>

<p>* * </p>

<p>Chr15 
Chr11 
Chr19 
Chr15 
Chr11 </p>

<p>% Probe </p>

<p>* 
* * 
* * * * 
* * </p>

<p>* * </p>

<p>Figure 7. Nuclear myosin 1 (NM1) is required for the relocation of chromosome territories. Positions of chromosomes 19, 15 and 11 were assessed by 2D-
FISH in control siRNA and MYO1C siRNA treated cells. 2D-FISH images were analyzed and quantitated by using the computational script <rs type="software">IMACULAT</rs> 
(76,77). X-axes of the graphs depict the nuclear shell number, with 1 being as the outermost and 5 being the innermost shell. Y-axes of the graphs show 
the percentage of probe normalized to DAPI. N = 2, n &gt; 100 nuclei. Error bars represent the s.e.m. P-values calculated using Student's t-test. * and ** 
indicate P &lt; 0.05 and P &lt; 0.01, respectively; n.s. = not significant. On graphs C = Centre of nucleus, P = Periphery of nucleus. </p>

<p>The phosphorylation of NM1 by GSK3 kinase has been 
reported to regulate NM1 binding to rDNA (73). In or-
der to test if such phosphorylation of NM1 is also required 
for the increased chromatin binding of NM1 and subse-
quent CT relocation following DNA damage, we inhibited 
GSK3 kinase using LiCl, a commonly used specific in-
hibitor of this kinase (101-107). We confirmed the inhibi-
tion of GSK3, by monitoring its inactive form Phospho-
Ser-9 GSK3 (103,104,107). In cells treated with LiCl, the 
inactive phospho-form of GSK3 increased in comparison 
with the untreated cells (Supplementary Figure S9), imply-
ing that addition of LiCl inhibited GSK3 in our experi-
mental conditions. Following this, we compared NM1 lev-
els in chromatin fraction as well as CT positions, before and 
after cisplatin damage. It was observed that the damage in-
duced increase in NM1 recruitment to chromatin and CT 
relocation occurred in both untreated control as well as LiCl 
treated cells (Figure 9), suggesting that the phosphorylation 
of NM1 by GSK3 does not seem to impact DNA dam-
age induced NM1 functions. We also probed for changes 
in phospho-NM1 using a phospho-serine-threonine specific 
antibody on immunoprecipitated NM1 from nuclear solu-</p>

<p>ble and chromatin fractions. The bulk phosphorylation sta-
tus of NM1 (nuclear soluble or chromatin-bound) was not 
affected by cisplatin damage treatment (data not shown). 
Although the bulk phosphorylation of nuclear myosin does 
not seem to change following DNA damage, this aspect 
needs further detailed analyses of whether phosphoryla-
tion at specific sites of NM1, if any, change in contrast to 
bulk phosphorylation post DNA damage. It is likely that 
the analysis of NM1 phosphorylation spectrum may un-
cover interesting differences specific to transcriptional ver-
sus DNA damage induced functional states of NM1 in 
chromatin. 
NM1 immuno-FISH experiments revealed that though 
the number of NM1 puncta on chromosome 19 (∼19) (Fig-
ure 10) which relocates in response to damage, is slightly 
higher than that on chromosomes 15 and 11 (∼12) (Fig-
ure 10), but there is no statistically significant increase in 
the number of puncta on these chromosomes following cis-
platin damage (Figure 10). Interestingly, the NM1 puncta 
normalized to chromosome size revealed a higher count for 
CT 19 (∼0.3) in comparison with that of CTs 15 and 11 
(∼0.1). Since the number of NM1 puncta per CT was not </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 17 8285 </p>

<p>Figure 8. Motor function of NM1 is required for damage induced increase in chromatin binding of myosin and CT relocation. (A) Representative Western 
blots for NM1 in cells overexpressing V5 tagged NM1 wild type or motor mutant G16S. NS = Nuclear soluble, CP = Chromatin pellet. N = 3. P-values 
calculated using Student's t-test. Error bars represent the s.d. (B) 2D-FISH was used to analyze the positions of CTs 19, 15 and 11 in the NM1 wild type 
or motor defective over-expressing cells. X-axes of the graphs depict the nuclear shell number, with 1 being the outermost and 5 being the innermost shell. 
Y-axes of the graphs show the percentage of probe normalized to DAPI. N = 2, n = at least 100 nuclei. On graphs C = Centre of nucleus, P = Periphery of 
nucleus. Error bars represent the s.e.m. P-values calculated using Student's t-test. * and ** indicate P &lt; 0.05 and P &lt; 0.01 respectively; n.s. = not significant. </p>

<p>significantly different following DNA damage, it was not 
possible to address if the increased pan-chromatin NM1 
recruitment (∼1.5-to 2-fold) that we observed earlier fol-
lowing DNA damage could be mapped to specific chro-
mosomes by immuno-FISH analyses. We believe that cap-
turing of contours of CTs by immuno-FISH is not accu-
rate enough to map the myosin puncta to specific territo-
ries. Therefore, we cannot address nuclear myosin puncta 
increase vis-` a-vis specific CTs with the current resolution 
of images. Much improved resolution and analyses of CT-
conformations/contours is required to address this issue. </p>

<p>Alternately, in order to comprehensively analyze the levels 
of NM1 on specific chromosomes, one needs to employ a 
whole-genome based NM1 ChIP Seq method that will be a 
part of a separate study. 
Since we observed that ϒ-H2AX signaling (Figure 3) as 
well as NM1 recruitment are required for CT relocation, we 
were prompted to check whether NM1 distribution in the 
nuclei is in any manner correlated with that of ϒ-H2AX. We 
observed that while both NM1 and ϒ-H2AX showed DNA 
damage induced puncta, but these two proteins showed very 
little, or no spatial co-localization in cisplatin treated cells </p>



<p>Figure 9. Phosphorylation of NM1 by GSK3 does not seem to be important for damage induced increase in chromatin binding of NM1 and CT 
relocation. (A) Western blotting was used to check the levels of NM1 in cells treated with or without 20mM LiCl (inhibitor of GSK3 kinase) for 3 h. NS 
= Nuclear soluble, CP = Chromatin pellet. N = 3. Error bars represent the s.d. (B) 2D-FISH analysis for CTs 19, 15 and 11 in cells treated with or without 
20 mM LiCl. N = 2, n &gt; 100 nuclei. On graphs C = Centre of nucleus, P = Periphery of nucleus. Error bars represent the s.e.m. P-values calculated using 
Student's t-test. * and ** indicate P &lt; 0.05 and P &lt; 0.01 respectively; n.s. = not significant. </p>

<p>(Pearson correlation coeff. &lt; 0.005) (Figure 11). Since NM1 
and ϒ-H2AX fail to co-localize, the enhanced recruitment 
of the former to CTs following ϒ-H2AX signaling during 
DDR must be functionally coupled, but perhaps indirectly 
mediated via some chromatin remodeler, downstream sig-
naling proteins or even nucleoskeletal proteins. The nature 
of such functional coupling and its eventual culmination 
into CT relocation changes needs to be probed further. 
As described earlier, NM1 is reported to bind to rDNA 
chromatin as well as Pol II promoters to participate in 
transcription (69,70,73) and NM1 also mediates chromatin 
modifications via chromatin remodelers/modifiers such as </p>

<p>WSTF-SNFh2, PCAF and Set1/Ash2 that make chromatin 
suitable for Pol I or Pol II transcription (64,69,70). It would 
be interesting to study what happens to such NM1 medi-
ated activating chromatin modifications and NM1 binding 
to rDNA, Pol II promoters upon DNA damage as global 
transcription is known to decrease following DNA damage 
(99,108-111). Moreover, there is also a possibility that some 
other kind of chromatin remodeling mediated by NM1 fol-
lowing DNA damage could help in the CT remodeling lead-
ing to large scale CT relocation during DDR, which is an 
aspect that also needs further investigation. Moreover the 
mechanistic role of NM1 in the context of nuclear actin dur-</p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 17 8287 </p>

<p>Figure 10. Analyses of NM1 levels in specific CTs by immuno-FISH. Representative images (100x magnification) of NHDF nuclei for NM1 Immuno-
FISH, whereby staining for NM1 was combined with 3D-FISH for chromosomes (A) 19, (B) 15 and (C) 11. NM1 puncta on these CTs were counted 
in 3D confocal images using <rs type="software">Imaris</rs>. Number of NM1 puncta were normalized to the chromosome length (Mbp). N = 2, n = at least 30 nuclei. NM1 
Immuno-FISH revealed that NM1 puncta did not significantly increase on these CTs post cisplatin damage. </p>



<p>Figure 11. NM1 does not co-localize with ϒ-H2AX. 3D projections of confocal images taken at 100x magnification, showing no co-localization between 
ϒ-H2AX (green) and NM1 (red) in cisplatin treated NHDFs. Co-localization analysis by computing the Pearson correlation co-efficient, was carried out 
in 3D images after background subtraction (to make the puncta more prominent) on at least 20 nuclei in 2 independent experiments using <rs type="software">Imaris</rs> software. </p>

<p>ing DDR also needs to be interrogated in detail. It is likely 
that just as nuclear actin has been implicated in the func-
tions of repair proteins such as SMARCAL1 (112), NM1 
might engage in novel interactions specific to DDR. NM1 
function during DDR poses certain fundamental mechanis-
tic questions: Does DDR encompass specific post transla-
tional modification changes in NM1 leading to enhanced 
recruitment to chromatin? What is the role of ATPase mo-
tor function in NM1 vis-` a-vis actin involvement in the dam-
age induced CT relocation? All these questions remain open 
for detailed investigation as a part of a separate study. 
In conclusion, our previous work (46) and the current re-
sults using cisplatin as a DNA damage inducer, shows that 
early sensing, repair and signaling at DSBs by ATM kinase, 
DNAPK and ϒ-H2AX (Figure 3) seem to play an impor-
tant role in DNA damage induced CT relocation. But when 
relatively later stages of DSB repair catalyzed by Rad51 or 
DNA ligase IV were blocked by using inhibitor or RNAi, 
damage induced CT relocation was only partially (CT 19) 
or not (CT 15) abrogated (Figure 4), indicating that later 
phases of repair do not seem to be as critical as the early 
phases of repair for orchestrating CT repositioning. 
CT repositioning during serum starvation (40) and also 
the movement of a chromosomal domain (58) during tran-
scriptional activation are thought to be mediated by nuclear 
motors such as actin and NM1. The functions of NM1 in 
the context of DDR are largely unknown. Our study for the 
first time delves into the involvement of NM1 in DDR in 
mammalian cells. In particular, we demonstrate that human 
fibroblasts are enriched with nuclear myosin that is tightly 
bound to chromatin (Figure 5A and B) and this association 
of NM1 to the chromatin is enhanced upon the induction of 
DNA damage using cisplatin or hydrogen peroxide-agents 
that lead to production of DNA DSBs during the DDR 
(Figure 5A), implying its functional relevance in DDR. This 
is further corroborated by two more lines of evidence: firstly, 
inhibition of upstream damage sensors such as ATM, ATR, 
DNAPK and PARP-1 led to the loss of DDR-associated </p>

<p>recruitment of NM1 (Figure 6) and secondly, down regu-
lation of ϒ-H2AX signaling itself also led to a concomi-
tant loss in NM1 recruitment to chromatin (Figure 5C). 
We surmise that large-scale chromatin remodeling associ-
ated with multiple ϒ-H2AX sites might trigger loading of 
DDR-induced NM1 on to chromatin. Indeed, siRNA medi-
ated knockdown of NM1 levels or motor function defects in 
NM1 abrogated DNA damage induced CT relocation (Fig-
ures 7 and 8). NM1 has been implicated in relocation of CTs 
(40) as well as repositioning of a chromosomal domain (58). 
Our results in the current study are not only consistent with 
these findings, but are also an important step forward in un-
derstanding the mechanistic basis of NM1 recruitment to 
chromatin upon induction of DNA damage. We speculate 
that a co-ordination between early DDR sensing and sig-
naling by ATM kinase, DNAPK and ϒ-H2AX; subsequent 
chromatin remodeling and NM1 recruitment to the chro-
matin, is required for DNA damage induced CT relocation, 
which is an integral part of DDR. CT relocation perhaps 
is a means by which the cell orchestrates large-scale remod-
eling of nuclear milieu, thereby rewiring the transcriptional 
program to efficiently perform DDR in order to maintain 
its genomic stability. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors are thankful to Prof. Junya Kobayashi (Kyoto 
University) for providing the H2AX constructs, Prof. Ingrid 
Grummt (German Cancer Research Center) for V5 tagged 
NM1 constructs and Prof. Sathees C. Raghavan (Indian In-
stitute of Science) for the DNA ligase IV inhibitor SCR7. 
The authors would also like to thank Dr Sarosh N. Fatakia 
(from BJR lab) for performing all Kolmogorov-Smirnov 
statistical tests. The authors would like to thank Prof. Ul-</p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2016, Vol. 44, No. 17 8289 </p>

<p>las Kolthur (TIFR) for his valuable inputs and ideas on the 
project. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research (Department of 
Atomic Energy, India) [12P0123]; JC Bose Award Grant 
[10X-217 to B.J.R.]; DST-Inspire Faculty Award [to I.S.M.]. 
Funding for open access charge: Tata Institute of Funda-
mental Research (Department of Atomic Energy, India) 
[12P0123]. 
Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



</text></tei>