<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5078595" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:27+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: </p>

<p>Background: </p>

<p>Leg length discrepancies following total hip arthroplasty (THA) may necessitate subsequent interventions, from heel lifts to revision 
surgery. Current intraoperative methods of determining leg length are either inaccurate or expensive and invasive. </p>

<p>Objective: </p>

<p>The objective of the current study was to investigate the ability of a novel, intraoperative smart tool (Intellijoint HIP 
® , Intellijoint 
Surgical 
® , Inc., Waterloo, ON) to provide accurate, real-time leg length measurements during THA. </p>

<p>Methods: </p>

<p>We retrospectively reviewed the medical records of 25 patients who underwent THA utilizing the Intellijoint HIP smart tool between 
February and August 2014. Intraoperative leg length data was compared with radiographic leg length calculations. Two observers 
blinded to the Intellijoint HIP findings independently assessed all post-procedure radiographs. </p>

<p>Results: </p>

<p>The mean difference between smart tool and radiographic measurements was 1.3 mm [CI: -0.1, 2.7]. 88% (22/25) of intraoperative 
measurements were within 5 mm of radiographic measurements; 100% (25/25) were within 10 mm. A Bland-Altman analysis 
showed excellent agreement, with 96% (24/25) of measurements within the statistical limit for acceptable agreement, and 84% 
(21/25) within the clinically acceptable range (± 5 mm). Removal of the first 13 procedures (surgeon training) decreased the mean 
difference between methods to 0.6 mm [-0.6, 1.9]. All post-training procedures were associated with a difference of &lt;5 mm. There 
were no reported adverse events related to the use of the smart tool. </p>

<p>Conclusion: </p>

<p>The Intellijoint HIP smart tool is a safe and accurate tool for providing intraoperative measurements of leg length in real-time. </p>

<p>Keywords: Cup position, Intraoperative, Intellijoint HIP, Leg length discrepancy, Navigation, Total hip arthroplasty. </p>

<p>INTRODUCTION </p>

<p>Leg length discrepancies (LLDs) following total hip arthroplasty (THA) are reported in up to 30% of primary </p>

<p>* Address correspondence to this author at the Intellijoint Surgical, Inc., 60 Bathurst Dr., Suite 6, Waterloo, ON N2V 2A9, Canada; Tel: +519 342 
3178; Fax: 226 317 0471; E-mail: j.muir@intellijointsurgical.com, </p>

<p>Smart tool for THA </p>

<p>The Open Orthopaedics Journal, 2016, Volume 10 491 </p>

<p>procedures [1, 2], varying from 3 to 70 mm [3]. Post-THA LLD is associated with sequelae such as gait alteration 
[4 -7], low back pain [8], neurological deficits [9 -11] and patient dissatisfaction [12]. Leg length inequalities often 
necessitate corrective procedures, ranging from the use of contralateral heel lifts to full revision surgery, and have been 
associated with an increased risk of medical malpractice litigation [13, 14]. The hospital costs related to revision 
surgery can be substantial, with per-procedure costs reaching $29,000 in the United States [15] and £22,000 in Europe 
[16]. </p>

<p>Surgeons traditionally lack accurate intraoperative data regarding changes in leg length during HTA procedures. 
Leg length has historically been assessed intraoperatively via manual methods, such as mechanical pins, osteotomy or 
tissue tensioning, methods that are subject to inaccuracies due to flexion contractures and inconsistencies in patient 
position during the procedure [17, 18]. Errors of up to 8 mm have been noted intraoperatively when introducing only 5 
degrees of flexion or abduction to the leg [19]. </p>

<p>In an attempt to improve intraoperative accuracy, sophisticated navigation devices have been developed to more 
accurately track changes in leg length. These devices, modified from their initial applications in neurological surgery 
[20 -22], improve accuracy but have several drawbacks. The cumbersome and time-consuming nature of navigation 
systems can significantly increase surgical time [23, 24] while also increasing the risk of infection [25]. The costs 
associated with navigation, including capital costs of up to $250,000 USD, plus software costs and service contracts [26 
-28], result in increased per-procedure costs [27, 29] that can be prohibitive [28]. These limitations have contributed to 
the low rate of use for navigation in THA procedures, currently estimated at only 1-3% [30, 31]. </p>

<p>To address the shortcomings of the existing technology, a novel miniature navigation tool has been developed to 
provide real-time, intraoperative data regarding leg length to surgeons. The Intellijoint HIP 
® smart tool (Intellijoint 
Surgical 
® , Inc., Waterloo, ON) is an intraoperative guidance tool used to assist orthopaedic surgeons in assessing leg 
length and offset changes during total hip arthroplasty. With minimal invasiveness and without altering surgical 
techniques or workflow, the device enables faster decision-making (fewer trial reductions) and minimizes leg length 
discrepancies. The Intellijoint HIP smart tool has been shown in cadaveric studies (data not published) to match the 
accuracy of radiographic leg length measurement. The purpose of this study was to investigate the ability of the 
Intellijoint HIP smart tool to accurately measure leg length intraoperatively, when compared with radiographic 
measurement, and to document any complications and/or adverse events associated with the device. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Study Design </p>

<p>This study was a retrospective review of patients who underwent total hip arthroplasty, performed by two surgeons 
(PG, MS), utilizing the Intellijoint HIP smart tool. </p>

<p>Patient Eligibility </p>

<p>Patients eligible for inclusion in this study underwent a primary total hip arthroplasty procedure between February 
2014 and August 2014 at a single community hospital. Specific inclusion criteria included: primary total hip 
arthroplasty; use of the Intellijoint HIP smart tool; ability to obtain pre and post-operative standing anterior-posterior 
(AP) radiographs. Patients were deemed ineligible for the study if they fulfilled any of the following criteria: 
intraoperative removal of the Intellijoint HIP smart tool prior to measurements being taken with trial components which 
matched the final implant geometry; instability in the native operative hip such that the attending surgeon was unable to 
reproduce the radiographic position during baseline and follow-up measurements; inability to properly reproduce and/or 
identify radiographic measurement landmarks on pre and post-surgical radiographs; and, radiographs unable to be 
properly scaled in pre and post-operative analysis. </p>

<p>Intellijoint HIP Smart Tool </p>

<p>The Intellijoint HIP smart tool is an intraoperative digital guidance tool, used to assist orthopaedic surgeons in the 
assessment of leg length and offset changes during total hip arthroplasty (Fig. 1). The smart tool relies on 
miniature/optical infrared technology and integrated microelectronics to provide real-time intraoperative tracking of 
femoral leg length. The system incorporates pelvic and femoral platforms, fixed via bone screws to the ipsilateral iliac 
crest and greater trochanter, respectively. A camera, magnetically attached to the pelvic platform, and a tracker, 
magnetically attached to the femoral platform, relay data to laptop-based control software. During use, the workstation </p>



<p>Grosso et al. </p>

<p>computes the positional relationship between the camera and the tracker and provides this information in real-time on 
the display. </p>

<p>Fig. (1). The Intellijoint HIP surgical smart tool in use. The camera (A) is magnetically attached to a pelvic platform (B) fixed to the 
iliac crest. The camera captures movements of the tracker (C), magnetically attached to a femoral platform fixed to the greater 
trochanter. Data is transferred in real-time to a workstation placed outside of the sterile field. The system is self-contained and 
portable, requiring no system-specific installation of equipment in the OR. </p>

<p>Surgical Procedure </p>

<p>Hip arthroplasty was performed using standard posterolateral approach techniques. No alterations to the surgical 
workflow are required and surgeons are able to integrate the smart tool into their workflow with minimal training. 
Intraoperatively, the Intellijoint HIP camera is coupled to the pelvis via a pelvic platform, which consists of two bone 
screws and a camera attachment mechanism. The bone screws are attached to the ipsilateral iliac crest or the superior 
acetabular dome. The tracker is coupled to the femur via a femur platform and attached to femur via a bone screw 
within the primary surgical wound. </p>

<p>The principle of operation of the Intellijoint HIP smart tool is as follows: </p>

<p>Prior to hip dislocation, patient specific leg length and offset measurements of the native hip are captured using 
1. 
the camera and software, 
During trial reduction, a range of motion is conducted and tracker measurements are taken. This step is used to 
2. 
map the patient's hip anatomy, and 
During trialing of the femoral stem, neck and head, measurements of leg length are provided to the surgeon on 
3. 
the display in real-time. Leg length data assist with the selection of correct implant size based on quantitative 
data and pre-operative planning. </p>

<p>Data Collection and Calculations </p>

<p>Data regarding final leg length was collected intraoperatively and stored by the Intellijoint HIP software. Patient 
records were reviewed for relevant patient history and to determine if any complications related to the use of the smart 
tool were reported. Post-operative radiographs were scaled using the known diameter of the head implant. Pre-operative 
radiographs were not scaled due to a lack of a suitable scaling object. </p>

<p>Two independent observers trained in radiographic assessment and blinded to the smart tool measurements 
performed the leg length calculations from the AP radiographs. Each observer was a trained orthopaedic surgeon with 
experience performing total hip arthroplasty using the posterolateral approach. Changes in leg length were calculated 
using the perpendicular distance between the inter-teardrop line and the most prominent aspect of the ipsilateral lesser </p>

<p>C 
C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Smart tool for THA </p>

<p>The Open Orthopaedics Journal, 2016, Volume 10 493 </p>

<p>trochanter [32]. The difference between the pre-operative and post-operative leg length for each patient was calculated 
by each observer and then averaged to provide the final leg length change. An established software program 
(<rs id="software-2" type="software">MATLAB</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Mathworks</rs>, Natick, MA) was used to select radiographic landmarks and scale images. Pre and post-
operative radiographs were corrected for abduction in order to minimize the artifact. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Alpha was set a priori at 0.05 for all statistical comparisons. Means were compared using independent samples t-
tests and/or single-factor ANOVA. All mean values are presented as mean [95% confidence interval] or mean (standard 
deviation). Intra-observer validity was assessed via the intraclass correlation (ICC) [33]. An independent statistician 
uninvolved in the radiographic analysis or surgical procedures completed the statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Comparisons between radiographic and smart tool measurements of leg length were made using both Pearson's r 
and the Bland-Altman technique [34, 35]. The Bland-Altman analysis provides a validated method for evaluating 
agreement between two methods of measurement when neither method is considered the "gold standard". It is designed 
to determine the level of agreement between two methods of measuring a clinical outcome. The resulting Bland-Altman 
plot allows for determination of bias between mean differences of two methods of measurement and creates an 
agreement interval (the "statistical limit"), within which 95% of the difference of one method, as compared with a 
second method, falls [36]. A limit for clinically relevant leg length discrepancy (the "clinical limit") was also included 
in the Bland-Altman plots. For the purposes of this analysis, this limit was set at ±5 mm to reflect the current clinical 
expectation [18, 37]. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Patient Population </p>

<p>From an initial cohort of 31 potentially eligible patients, 25 were eligible for inclusion in this study. Of the six 
patients excluded from the study, 3 did not have reproducible landmarks on radiographs, 2 patients had poor bone 
quality that precluded the use of the Intellijoint HIP smart tool and 1 patient did not return for post-operative 
radiographs. </p>

<p>The mean age of included patients was 64.3 years (SD: 11.3, range: 44-85). Females comprised 50% (11/22 
recorded) of patients. Mean body mass index (BMI) was 31.5 (SD: 7.2, range: 23.4-42.8). Mean procedural time was 
76.2 mins (SD: 12.3, range: 59-98 mins). Demographic data are summarized in Table I. </p>

<p>Table I. Summary of demographic data. </p>

<p>Item 
Result 
Patient demographics 
Age, years (mean (SD)) 
BMI (mean, (SD)) 
Female, n/N 
1 (%) 
Male, n/N (%) </p>

<p>64.3 (11.3) 
31.5 (7.2) 
11/22 (50) 
11/22 (50) </p>

<p>Surgery type, n/N (%) 
Primary 
Revision 
Surgery location, n/N (%) 
Left 
Right </p>

<p>24/25 (96) 
1/25 (4) </p>

<p>11/25 (44) 
14/25 (56) </p>

<p>Indication, n/N 
2 (%) 
Osteoarthritis 
Avascular necrosis 
Post-traumatic arthritis </p>

<p>21/23 (91) 
1/23 (4.5) 
1/23 (4.5) </p>

<p>Procedural time, minutes (mean, SD) 
76.2 (12.3) 
1. Gender not available for 3 patients. 
2. Indication not available for 2 patients. </p>

<p>There was strong inter-rater agreement regarding leg length measurements calculated from radiographs (ICC: 0.83). </p>

<p>Leg Length Measurement </p>

<p>The mean difference between radiographic measurement and smart tool assessment of leg length was 1.3 mm [95% </p>



<p>Grosso et al. </p>

<p>CI: -0.1 to 2.7]. A strong positive correlation was noted between leg length measurements calculated intraoperatively 
with the smart tool and radiographically (r=0.76) (Fig. 2A). There was no statistically significant difference between the 
mean leg length measurements as determined by radiographic and smart tool measurements (radiograph: 6.4 mm [4.3, 
8.5] vs. smart tool: 7.7 mm [5.8, 9.6], p=0.41). The smart tool leg length measurement was within 5 mm of the 
radiographic measurement in 22/25 (88%) cases and within 10 mm of the radiographic measurement in 25/25 (100%) of 
cases. </p>

<p>Fig. (2). Correlation between leg length differential measured intraoperatively by the Intellijoint HIP smart tool versus pre-and post-
operative radiographs. With the entire cohort included in the analysis, there was a strong correlation (r=0.76) between radiographic 
and smart tool measurements (A). A sensitivity analysis excluding patients who were part of the surgeons' training demonstrated a 
slightly improved correlation (r=0.82) (B). </p>

<p>Placement of the pelvic platform varied within the cohort, due to the learning curve associated with the surgeons' 
use of the smart tool. The initial 12 cases were performed with the platform fixed to the supra-acetabular region; the 
subsequent 13 were performed with the platform attached to the iliac crest. A post-hoc sensitivity analysis indicated that 
with the platform fixed to the iliac crest, the mean difference between the smart tool measurements and the radiographic 
measurements decreased to 0.6 mm (-0.6, 1.9) and the correlation between measurements improved to 0.82 (Fig. 2B). 
With the pelvic platform fixed to the iliac crest, 100% (13/13) of leg length differences were less than 5 mm. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Intellijoint HIP ΔLL (mm) </p>

<p>Intellijoint HIP ΔLL (mm) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>15.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>25.0 </p>

<p>-5.0 </p>

<p>-5.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>15.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>25.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>Ra </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>5.0 
10 </p>

<p>adiographic Δ </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>Radiograph </p>

<p>0.0 
15.0 </p>

<p>ΔLL (mm) </p>

<p>15.0 </p>

<p>ic ΔLL (mm) </p>

<p>0 
20.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>25.0 </p>

<p>25.0 </p>

<p>Smart tool for THA </p>

<p>The Open Orthopaedics Journal, 2016, Volume 10 495 </p>

<p>A Bland-Altman analysis of the radiographic and smart tool methods of measuring leg length demonstrated 
excellent agreement. When all 25 eligible patients were included in the analysis, 96% (24/25) of measurements fell 
within the statistical limits of acceptability, while 84% (21/25) of measurements fell within the clinically acceptable 
range of ±5 mm (Fig. 3A). In patients where the pelvic platform was attached to the iliac crest, 100% (13/13) of 
measurements fell within both the statistical and clinical limits of acceptability (Fig. 3B). </p>

<p>Fig. (3). Bland-Altman plots demonstrating the agreement between the radiographic (RAD) and smart tool (IJH) methods of leg 
length measurement. With all eligible patients included, 96% (24/25) of measurements fell within the statistical limit for strong 
agreement and 84% (21/25) fell within the limits of clinical relevance (A). Excluding those patients from the surgeons' training 
period, 100% (13/13) of patients fell within both the statistical and clinically relevant limits (B). Dotted line: upper and lower 
statistical limits; dashed line: upper and lower clinical limit; solid line: mean leg length discrepancy difference. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Leg length discrepancies following total hip arthroplasty can have significant consequences, substantially impacting 
patient quality of life and increasing the risk of medical malpractice litigation. Current intraoperative methods of 
monitoring leg length changes rely on either manual techniques such as tissue tensioning or mechanical outriggers, or 
advanced surgical navigation systems that, while accurate, are both expensive and cumbersome. The Intellijoint HIP 
smart tool is an intraoperative guidance tool providing accurate and precise measurements of leg length that was </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Difference (RAD-IJH) (mm) </p>

<p>Difference (RAD-IJH) (mm) </p>

<p>-10.0 </p>

<p>-5.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>-5.0 </p>

<p>( </p>

<p>) ( </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>-10.0 </p>

<p>-5.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>5.0 
10 
Average (RA </p>

<p>10.0 
Average (RA </p>

<p>0.0 
15.0 
AD, IJH) (mm </p>

<p>15.0 
AD, IJH) (mm </p>

<p>0 
20.0 
m) </p>

<p>20.0 
m) </p>

<p>25.0 </p>

<p>25.0 </p>



<p>Grosso et al. </p>

<p>recently evaluated in a cohort of 25 patients undergoing total hip arthroplasty. The smart tool successfully provided 
accurate intraoperative measurements with no device-related or procedure-related adverse events reported. </p>

<p>The gait alterations associated with LLD following THA result in compensatory changes in hip geometry and 
altered gait biomechanics [38], leading to low back pain [8] and potential neurological deficits [9 -11], among other 
consequences. Current manual methods of managing LLD intraoperatively are based on landmarking and crude 
measurements, and are susceptible to slight variations in patient position during surgery [18]. Femoral abduction as 
minor as 5 degrees has been noted to induce leg length errors of up to 8 mm [19]. Additionally, a recent study found 
that 74% of THA patients with a LLD of greater than 5 mm perceived that difference post-operatively, with the 
majority of those patients reporting significantly worse pain and Oxford scores, as compared with patients who were 
unaware of a LLD and/or those with a LLD less than 5 mm [39]. </p>

<p>Pre-operative planning offers an opportunity for careful measurement prior to entering the surgical suite; however, 
intraoperative measurement remains the preferred method of managing leg length. Even crude intraoperative 
measurements have been shown to be more successful than pre-operative planning at minimizing LLDs, with one recent 
study observing that simple ruler measurement of leg length intraoperatively was associated with a smaller LLD (2±2 
mm) than pre-operative planning (7±4 mm) [40]. Computer-assisted navigation, while providing improved 
intraoperative accuracy, requires multiple landmarking steps and significant pre-operative planning. The resulting 
increase in procedural time [23], pre-operative planning time and the cumbersome nature of navigation have limited its 
use to only 1-3% of orthopaedic procedures [30, 31]. </p>

<p>The limit for acceptable leg length discrepancy following THA has been suggested at 10 mm [41 -43], although 
differences of 5 mm represent better accuracy and are generally targeted by surgeons [18, 38]. The smart tool utilized in 
this study provided accurate data regarding pre and post-operative leg length, measuring leg length to within 5 mm of 
radiographic values in 88% of patients. Importantly these findings were achieved with a device that is no more intrusive 
or disruptive to the surgical workflow than any of the manual methods traditionally utilized. Indeed, in our study, the 
average procedure time was 76 minutes, which compares favourably with procedures utilizing mechanical measurement 
techniques, which range in duration from 73 [23, 44] to 104 minutes [45]. Conversely, computer-assisted navigation is 
associated with significant increases in procedural time, reported between 12 [46, 47] and 23 added minutes [23, 44, 45, 
48]. </p>

<p>Increased surgical time is associated with increased cost, and navigation systems are known to increase procedural 
costs, due to both the capital costs associated with the systems [26 -28] and the per-procedure costs [27, 29]. At a cost 
of between $500-995 USD per case, and with no initial capital costs, the smart tool offers accuracy rivalling that of 
navigation systems at a substantially lower cost. The combined improvement in procedural time-add and the lower costs 
associated with the Intellijoint system suggest that it is a cost-effective option for THA. Robust cost-effectiveness 
studies are necessary to evaluate the potential cost savings associated with this system. </p>

<p>LIMITATIONS </p>

<p>This study has limitations. The retrospective nature of the study design and the lack of a control group decrease the 
veracity with which the conclusions can be extrapolated. The retrospective nature of the study also necessitated the use 
of standard radiographs to measure leg length. As such, no study-specific radiographic protocol was utilized. Also, 
pelvic radiographs, due to their 2-dimensional nature, are known to be susceptible to errors due to pelvic orientation, 
magnification, femoral abduction and femoral rotation [19, 49, 50]. Additionally, the pre-operative radiographs did not 
utilize a scaling object in the image. As a result, observers were required to assume that both pre and post-operative 
radiographs were to the same scale. These difficulties notwithstanding, AP radiographs are part of the standard of care 
for THA, as is their use for measurement of leg length and offset. The results of this study therefore mirror those of 
other studies in this field. To minimize the artifact associated with radiographs, future prospective studies will utilize 
strict radiographic protocols and pre and post-surgical scaling objects to minimize such errors. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>The Intellijoint HIP smart tool accurately measured leg length intraoperatively, without significantly altering 
surgical workflow, increasing procedure time or requiring large capital investments prior to its use. This novel 
technology represents a safe and effective method of providing real-time data to surgeons and minimizing the effects of 
leg length discrepancies following total hip arthroplasty. Future studies will compare the smart tool prospectively to 
current intraoperative methods and will include robust investigations into the cost-effectiveness of the smart tool, in </p>

<p>Smart tool for THA </p>

<p>The Open Orthopaedics Journal, 2016, Volume 10 497 </p>

<p>comparison to current manual and navigation methods. </p>

<p>LIST OF ABBREVIATIONS </p>

<p>ΔLL 
= 
change in leg length </p>

<p>ANOVA 
= 
analysis of variance </p>

<p>AP 
= 
anterior-posterior </p>

<p>BMI 
= 
body mass index </p>

<p>CI 
= 
confidence interval </p>

<p>ICC 
= 
intraclass correlation </p>

<p>IJH 
= 
Intellijoint HIP </p>

<p>LLD 
= 
leg length discrepancy </p>

<p>OR 
= 
operating room </p>

<p>RAD 
= 
radiographic measurement </p>

<p>SD 
= 
standard deviation </p>

<p>THA 
= 
total hip arthroplasty </p>

<p>USD 
= 
United States dollar </p>

<p>DISCLOSURES </p>

<p>Drs. Grosso and Snider are paid consultants for Intellijoint Surgical. Dr. Grosso is an investor in Intellijoint 
Surgical. Dr. Muir is an employee of Intellijoint Surgical. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors confirm that this article content has no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>Declared none. </p>





<p>Grosso et al. </p>



<p>Smart tool for THA </p>

<p>The Open Orthopaedics Journal, 2016, Volume 10 499 </p>



<p>© Grosso et al.; Licensee Bentham Open </p>

<p>This is an open access article licensed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non-Commercial 4.0 International Public License 
(CC BY-NC 4.0) (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/legalcode), which permits unrestricted, non-commercial use, distribution and 
reproduction in any medium, provided the work is properly cited. </p>

</text></tei>