<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5348473" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Objective: To explore the association of membrane-associated guanylate kinase inverted 1 (MAGI1) with gastric </p>

<p>cancer (GC) and the related molecular mechanisms. </p>

<p>Methods: The reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and immunohistochemistry (IHC) </p>

<p>were utilized to measure the MAGI1 expression level in GC tissues. Quantitative real-time PCR and Western </p>

<p>blotting were used to ensure the MAGI1 expression in GC cell lines. Small hairpin RNA (shRNA) was applied for </p>

<p>knockdown of endogenous MAGI1 in GC cells. MTT assay and colony formation assay, scratch wounding </p>

<p>migration assay and transwell chamber migration assay, as well as transwell chamber invasion assay were employed </p>

<p>respectively to investigate the GC cell proliferation, migration and invasion in MAGI1-knockdown and control GC </p>

<p>cells. The potential molecular mechanism mediated by MAGI1 was studied using Western blotting and RT-PCR. </p>

<p>Results: RT-PCR and IHC verified MAGI1 was frequently expressed in matched adjacent noncancerous mucosa </p>

<p>compared with GC tissues and the expression of MAGI1 was related to clinical pathological parameters. Functional </p>

<p>assays indicated that MAGI1 knockdown significantly promoted GC cell migration and invasion. Further </p>

<p>mechanism investigation demonstrated that one pathway of MAGI1 inhibiting migration and invasion was mainly </p>

<p>by altering the expression of matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) and epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT)-</p>

<p>related molecules via inhibiting MAPK/ERK signaling pathway. </p>

<p>Conclusions: MAGI1 was associated with GC clinical pathological parameters and acted as a tumor suppressor </p>

<p>via inhibiting of MAPK/ERK signaling pathway in GC. </p>

<p>Gastric cancer (GC) remains one of the most common </p>

<p>malignancies and is responsible for the third leading cause </p>

<p>of cancer-related deaths in China (1). Because the early </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>© Chinese Journal of Cancer Research. All rights reserved. 
www.cjcrcn.org 
Chin J Cancer Res 2017;29(1):25-35 </p>

<p>stages of GC are normally asymptomatic and a majority of 
GC patients are often diagnosed in advanced stages, there 
is still high morbidity and mortality of GC patients (2). 
Metastasis is recognized as an essential factor that 
responsible for the poor prognosis in GC. However, it's 
most regrettable that so far no efficient target drug has 
been reported to directly inhibit the process of metastasis. 
Therefore, a better understanding of the clinical 
biomarkers and the molecular underpinnings involved in 
metastasis still remains challenging, and it is an urgent task 
for further GC therapy (3,4). 
Membrane-associated guanylate kinase inverted 1 
(MAGI1) is a member that belongs to MAGI subfamily of 
membrane-associated guanylate kinase (MAGUK) family. 
MAGI2 and MAGI3 are two other close members in the 
MAGI subfamily, which contain similar molecular 
structures to MAGI1 (5). Previous reports have 
demonstrated that MAGI1 was down-regulated in diverse 
cancers and acted as a tumor suppressor in colorectal 
cancer, hepatocellular carcinoma and cervical cancer (6-8). 
Nevertheless, the molecular mechanisms of MAGI1 in 
inhibiting metastasis were disparate in different kinds of 
cancers. Zhang et al. demonstrated that MAGI1 inhibited 
cell migration and invasion by up-regulating the expression 
of phosphatase and tensin homolog deleted on 
chromosome 10 (PTEN) in hepatocellular carcinoma, and 
a similar result was found by Hu et al. in the study of 
MAGI2, another MAGI family member in the same cancer 
(9,10). In addition, MAGI1 could also interact with some 
proteins by its different PDZ (PSD-95, DLG, ZO-1) 
domains to further alter the expression level of these 
proteins. The interacted proteins always have special 
functions in the biological process such as cell junction, 
adhesion and invasion. For instance, Dobrosotskaya et al. 
demonstrated that MAGI1 interacted with β-catenin and 
E-cadherin during the formation of cell-cell junctions in 
MDCK cells. Ridgway et al. also revealed that MAGI1 
could also regulate the steady-stage of the surface BK(Ca) 
channels by the interaction with Slo1 (11,12). Other MAGI 
family members were also revealed to regulate cell 
migration and invasion via some signaling pathways such as 
c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK), Wnt/β-catenin and 
PI3K/PKB (13-15). Although metastasis is likely to be the 
main biological process regulated by MAGI1, the other 
biological occurrence and progression are also increasingly 
reported in recent years. Zaric et al. indicated that over-
expression of MAGI1 repressed not only cell metastasis but 
the proliferation by inhibiting Wnt/β-catenin signaling </p>

<p>pathway in colorectal cancer, and in some cases, MAGI1 
could also participate in the regulation of apoptosis (6,8). 
Ma et al. even suggested MAGI3 suppressed cell 
proliferation via up-regulating PTEN expression in 
galioma, a similar way of MAGI1 and MAGI2 inhibiting 
cell migration and invasion in hepatocellular carcinoma 
(16). Although previous reports have already revealed the 
role of MAGI and its family members in different tumor 
types, there were few reports to confirm the biological 
function of MAGI1 in GC. Hence, this study aims to 
clarify the biological role of MAGI1 in GC and to provide 
further understanding of the molecular mechanisms 
mediated by MAGI1 in GC. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Patients and gastric tissue specimens </p>

<p>A total of 58 paraffin-sectioned gastric cancer tissues were 
collected from GC patients from Peking University Cancer 
Hospital between 1998 and 2008, and 10 surgically 
removed frozen GC samples in 2014 were obtained from 
the BioBank of Peking University Cancer Hospital. Some 
patients received chemotherapy or radiation therapy before 
surgery. All human samples were obtained through written 
informed consent from patients, and the Ethics Committee 
of Peking University Cancer Hospital approved these 
tissues for research use. The following clinicopathological 
information was obtained from patient data. GC staging 
was classified according to the 1997 Union for 
International Cancer Control (UICC)-TNM criteria. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry (IHC) </p>

<p>For IHC, 4 μm-thick sections cut from the formalin-fixed 
paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tissue blocks were 
deparaffinized and rehydrated using xylene and a graded 
ethanol wash. Antigen retrieval was performed in 10 mmoL 
sodium citrate buffer (pH 6.0) for 20 min, and endogenous 
peroxidase activity was blocked with 3% hydrogen peroxide 
for 15 min. The sections were then blocked with normal 
sheep serum at room temperature for 90 min, and 
incubated with MAGI1 rabbit polyclonal antibody (Santa 
Cruz, sc-25663), diluted at 1:100, overnight at 4 °C. The 
sections were incubated at room temperature for 1 h with 
the horse radish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated secondary 
antibody and then were incubated with peroxidase substrate 
solution. Finally, the sections were counterstained with 
hematoxylin, dehydrated in ethanol and cleared with </p>

<p> 
Jia et al. MAGI1 inhibits migration and invasion in GC </p>

<p>© Chinese Journal of Cancer Research. All rights reserved. 
www.cjcrcn.org 
Chin J Cancer Res 2017;29(1):25-35 </p>

<p>xylene. GC specimens were defined as MAGI1-negative 
expression when less than 10% cancer cells had cytoplasmic 
MAGI1 staining or MAGI1-positive expression when 10% 
or more cancer cells were stained. Negative control was 
prepared by substituting phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) 
for the primary antibody. </p>

<p>Cell lines and cell culture </p>

<p>All the GC cell lines were provided by the Peking 
University Cancer Hospital &amp; Institute. SGC7901, 
MGC803, AGS and NCI-N87 cell lines were cultured in 
Dulbecco's modified Eagle medium (DMEM; MAC 
GENE) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS; 
HyClone) and BGC823 cell line was cultured in DMEM 
supplemented with 5% FBS. All the GC cell lines were 
maintained at 37 °C, 5% CO 2 . </p>

<p>RNA interference </p>

<p>Small hairpin RNA (shRNA) was used for the knock-
down of endogenous MAGI1 in AGS cells. The target 
sequences were as follows: shMAGI1-1: 5'-GAGGTTA 
TCCATTGCCTTT-3'; shMAGI1-2: 5'-ACCTAT 
GAAGGAAACTATT-3'. GV248 was used as sh-control. 
The shRNA was transfected into AGS cells by 
electrotransfection. Cells with depleted endogenous 
MAGI1 expression were selected by culturing in 
puromycin at the final screening concentration of 2 μg/mL. </p>

<p>RNA extraction and reverse transcription-polymerase 
chain reaction (RT-PCR) </p>

<p>Total RNA was extracted from tissue samples and cell lines 
using the Trizol reagent (Ambion, 15596-026) according to 
the manufacturer's instructions. RT-PCR was used to 
determine the mRNA level of MAGI1 in the gastric 
carcinoma tissue and its adjacent gastric tissue. Glycer-
aldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) was used 
as a control. PCR was performed in PCR reaction mixes 
with initial heating at 94 °C for 5 min, followed by 30 
cycles at 94 °C for 30 s, 60 °C for 30 s and 72 °C for 30 s, 
and finally 72 °C for 10 min. The primer pairs used for 
MAGI1 and GAPDH amplification were MAGI1, forward: 
CCTTCAGTCTGGCTCTAAGC, reverse: GTGTGCT 
CCTCTTGTTCACC; GAPDH, forward: GCATCCT 
GGGCTACACT, reverse: CACCACCCTGTTGCTGT. </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time PCR </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time PCR was performed with the ABI </p>

<p>PRISM 7500 Sequence Detection System (Applied 
Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) using the SYBR Green 
method. The mRNA levels of all detected genes were 
normalized to GAPDH. Specific primers used in PCR 
amplification were as follows: MAGI1, forward: CCTT 
CAGTCTGGCTCTAAGC, reverse: GTGTGCTC 
CTCTTGTTCACC; matrix metalloproteinase 2 (MMP2), 
forward: AGTTTCCATTCCGCTTCCAG, reverse: 
CGGTCGTAGTCCTCAGTGGT; MMP7, forward: 
CATGATTGGCTTTGCGCGAG, reverse: AGAC 
TGCTACCATCCGTCCA; MMP9, forward: CCAACT 
ACGACACCGACGAC, reverse: TGGAAGATGAA 
TGGAAACTGG; MMP14, forward: AGCCATATTG 
CTGTAGCCAG, reverse: GTTGTCTCCTGCTC 
CCCCT; E-cadherin, forward: TGAAAAGAGAG 
TGGAAGTGTCCGAG, reverse: GATTAGGGC 
TGTGTACGTGCTGTTC; N-cadherin, forward: 
CAATCCTCCAGAGTTTACTGCCATG, reverse: 
GATTGGTTTGACCACGGTGACTAAC; GAPDH, 
forward: GCATCCTGGGCTACACT, reverse: 
CACCACCCTGTTGCTGT. </p>

<p>Western blotting </p>

<p>Cells were lysed completely in lysis buffer (50 mmol/L 
Hepes pH 7.5, 150 mmol/L NaCl, 2 mmol/L EDTA, 2 
mmol/L EGTA, 1% TritonX-100, 50 mmol/L NaF, 5 
mmol/L sodium pyrophosphate, 50 mmol/L sodium β-
glycerophosphate, 1 mmol/L dithiothreitol (DTT), 1 
mmol/L phenylmethanesulfonyl fluoride (PMSF), 10 
μg/mL leupeptin, 10 μg/mL aprotinin) at 4 °C. The 
protein content was determined using a BCA Protein Assay 
Kit (Thermo, USA). Total proteins were separated by 
sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis 
(SDS-PAGE) and then transferred onto polyvinylidene 
fluoride (PVDF) membranes (Millipore, USA). The blotted 
membranes were incubated with primary antibodies and 
then with corresponding secondary antibody. Extracellular 
signal-regulated kinase 1/2 (ERK1/2) rabbit polyclonal 
(Santa Cruz, sc-93), p-ERK1/2 mouse monoclonal (Santa 
Cruz, sc-136521), p-JNK mouse monoclonal (Santa Cruz, 
sc-6254), JNK rabbit polyclonal (Santa Cruz, sc-571) and 
GAPDH mouse monoclonal (Santa Cruz, sc-166545) 
antibodies were purchased from Santa Cruz. Antibody 
against MAGI1 (Sigma, M5691) was purchased from 
Sigma. The p-p38 rabbit monoclonal (CST, #4511) and 
p38 rabbit monoclonal (CST, #8690) antibodies were 
purchased from Cell Signal Technology. </p>

<p>Chinese Journal of Cancer Research, Vol 29, No 1 February 2017 </p>

<p>
© Chinese Journal of Cancer Research. All rights reserved. 
www.cjcrcn.org 
Chin J Cancer Res 2017;29(1):25-35 </p>

<p>Cell proliferation assay </p>

<p>The cell proliferation was detected by 3-(4,5-dimethy-
lthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) 
assay. AGS cells were seeded into 96-well plates at 1×10 3 
per well and incubated at 37 °C with 5% CO 2 for 24 h, 48 
h, 72 h and 96 h. At the detected time points, MTT 
solution was added to each well and the plates were 
incubated for another 4 h. The formazan crystals were 
dissolved with 100 μL dimethyl sulfoxide per well. The 
absorbance of individual wells was read using a microplate 
reader (Bio-Rad, USA). </p>

<p>Colony formation </p>

<p>For colony formation assay, 500 of AGS cells were seeded 
in triplicate in 60-mm dishes. After appropriate time of 
growth, the cells were washed with PBS for three times, 
fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 20 min, and stained 
with 0.1% crystal violet for 20 min. The dishes were then 
washed with PBS for three times. Photographs were 
captured and cell clones were counted. </p>

<p>Scratch wounding migration assay </p>

<p>Scratch wounding migration assay was detected by the 
IncuCyte HD system (<rs type="software">IncuCyte ZOOM</rs>, Essen BioScience, 
USA). AGS cells were grown in 96-well culture plates. Cell 
layers were scraped with a pin block and then incubated at 
37 °C. Photographs were taken at set time points by 
IncuCyte HD system. </p>

<p>Transwell chamber migration and invasion assay </p>

<p>Transwell chamber migration assay was measured using a 
transwell chamber with 8 μm filter inserts (BD Biosciences, 
USA) without Matrigel. For transwell chamber-based 
invasion assay, transwell inserts with 8 μm filter were pre-
coated with 50 μg of Matrigel (Becton Dickinson, USA), 
and 5×10 4 cells were seeded to the upper chamber 
containing serum-free DMEM medium. The lower 
chamber was filled with 600 μL DMEM medium with 10% 
FBS. After 24 h of incubation for AGS cells (both 
migration and invasion), the upper chamber was cleaned 
thoroughly with a cotton swab to remove any un-migrated 
or un-invasive cells, and the migrated and invasive cells 
were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 20 min before 
being stained with 0.1% crystal violet for 20 min. 
Photographs were captured and the migrated cells were </p>

<p>counted in at least 3 random fields. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Chi-square test was utilized to compare the differences in 
MAGI1 protein expression between GC tissues and 
adjacent noncancerous tissues. The association of MAGI1 
protein expression with clinicopathological features in GC 
patients was analyzed by Chi-square test and Kruskal-
Wallis test. Other data were analyzed using Student's t-test. 
All the statistical analyses were carried out using the IBM 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> Statistics (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">Version 21.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM corp., New York, USA)</rs>). All data were represented as ±s. Two-tailed P&lt;0.05 
was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>MAGI1 was weakly expressed in primary GC </p>

<p>RT-PCR was employed for semiquantitative analysis of 
MAGI1 mRNA expression in primary GC. Initial 
screening of surgically resected GC from 10 patients 
revealed that MAGI1 was down-regulated in 8 cases (Figure 
1A). To further confirm this result, we also examined the 
protein expression of MAGI1 in primary GC by IHC with 
the anti-MAGI1 antibody in 58 GC tissue samples. As 
shown in Figure 1B, MAGI1 was weakly expressed in GC 
tissue cells, whereas highly expressed in noncancerous 
tissues. The statistical data indicated that MAGI1 was 
frequently observed in matched adjacent noncancerous 
mucosa compared with GC tissues (63.8% vs. 32.8%, 
P=0.039) (Table 1). </p>

<p>Association of MAGI1 expression with clinicopathological 
parameters in GC patients </p>

<p>To investigate the clinical role of MAGI1 in GC 
progression, we analyzed the correlations between MAGI1 
expression and clinicopathological parameters of GC 
patients. As shown in Table 2, MAGI1 was more frequently 
expressed in the intestinal or mixed GC tissues than the 
diffused ones (P=0.003). The ratio of the negative and 
positive expression of MAGI1 indicated that MAGI1 was 
significantly associated with the degree of differentiation, 
since it was seldom observed in poorly differentiated GC 
tissues compared with moderately-well differentiated ones 
(P=0.008). Furthermore, MAGI1 expression was also 
correlated with the distant metastasis (P=0.049). </p>

<p> 
Jia et al. MAGI1 inhibits migration and invasion in GC </p>

<p>© Chinese Journal of Cancer Research. All rights reserved. 
www.cjcrcn.org 
Chin J Cancer Res 2017;29(1):25-35 </p>

<p>MAGI1 knockdown promoted GC cell migration and 
invasion </p>

<p>Functional assays were performed to explore the biological 
role of MAGI1 in GC. We assessed the MAGI1 expression 
level in 5 GC cell lines (Figure 1C) and utilized a loss of 
function approach in the AGC cells that exhibited the 
highest expression of MAGI1. The MAGI1 expression </p>

<p>which infected with a lentivirus expressing anti-MAGI1 
shRNA was confirmed by real-time PCR and Western 
blotting (Figure 2A). MTT assay and clone formation assay 
were utilized to detect the effect of MAGI1 on the 
proliferation in AGS cells. As shown in Figure 2B and 2C, 
MAGI1 knockdown enhanced the proliferation of AGS 
cells in comparison to the respective sh-control cells to a 
certain degree; however, the influence of MAGI1 on the 
GC cell proliferation was limited. 
Migration and invasion are essential factors that 
accelerate the malignant biological occurrence and 
progression. As shown in Figure 2D and 2E, scratch 
wounding and transwell chamber migration assays 
indicated that decreased MAGI1 expression promoted GC 
cell migration (Scratch wounding assay, P&lt;0.05; transwell 
chamber migration assay, sh-MAGI1-1: P&lt;0.001, sh-</p>

<p>Table 1 Expression of MAGI1 in gastric tissues (N=58) </p>

<p>Tissues </p>

<p>MAGI1 expression 
[n (%)] 
χ 2 
P 
Negative Positive </p>

<p>Adjacent 
noncancerous tissues 
21 (36.2) 37 (63.8) 
4.27 
0.039 
Gastric cancer tissues 39 (67.2) 19 (32.8) </p>

<p>MAGI1, membrane-associated guanylate kinase inverted 1. </p>

<p>Figure 1 MAGI1 expression in primary gastric cancer (GC) tissues. (A) MAGI1 mRNA expression in adjacent noncancerous tissues and </p>

<p>GC samples by reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR); (B) MAGI1 expression by immunohistochemical staining. N, </p>

<p>adjacent noncancerous tissues; T, GC tissues; original magnification, 200× and 400×; (C) MAGI1 expression in different GC cell lines. </p>

<p>Chinese Journal of Cancer Research, Vol 29, No 1 February 2017 
29 </p>

<p>© Chinese Journal of Cancer Research. All rights reserved. 
www.cjcrcn.org 
Chin J Cancer Res 2017;29(1):25-35 </p>

<p>MAGI1-2: P&lt;0.01). Furthermore, MAGI1 down-
regulation also induced the invasion progression of GC 
cells when compared MAGI1 knockdown cells with sh-
control cells (P&lt;0.01) in transwell chamber invasion assay 
(Figure 2F). These results were in accordance with our 
clinicopathological parameters analysis, which showed that 
MAGI1 expression was significantly associated with the 
distant metastasis (M1 staging) in patients with GC (Table 2). </p>

<p>MAGI1 altered expression of MMPs and epithelial-
mesenchymal transition (EMT)-related molecules by 
inhibiting mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK)/ 
ERK signaling pathway </p>

<p>Migration and invasion are complex biological processes 
which are involved in complicated multi-stages of 
regulations mediated by various signaling pathways. MAPK </p>

<p>Figure 2 MAGI1 knockdown promoted migration and invasion in AGS cells. (A) mRNA and protein expressions of MAGI1 were </p>

<p>significantly reduced in AGS cells transfected with sh-MAGI1, detected by real time PCR and Western blotting. Sh-control served as the </p>

<p>negative control; (B, C) The MTT proliferation assay (B) and colony formation assay (C) revealed the proliferation of AGS cells after </p>

<p>MAGI1 knockdown; (D) MAGI1 knockdown increased wound closure in scratch wounding migration assay in AGS cells. Photographs were </p>

<p>taken at 12 h and 20 h in AGS cells; (E) MAGI1 knockdown accelerated migration though transwell chamber migration assay; (F) MAGI1 </p>

<p>knockdown promoted GC cell invasion ability by transwell chamber invasion assay. The data are expressed as ±s. *, P&lt;0.05; **, P&lt;0.01; ***, </p>

<p>P&lt;0.001. </p>

<p> 
Jia et al. MAGI1 inhibits migration and invasion in GC </p>

<p>© Chinese Journal of Cancer Research. All rights reserved. 
www.cjcrcn.org 
Chin J Cancer Res 2017;29(1):25-35 </p>

<p>signaling pathway has been widely reported as one of the 
most important signaling pathway that participated in the 
network regulation on cell migration and invasion in 
various cancers (17-19). As shown in Figure 3A, ERK was 
effectively activated after MAGI1 knockdown, whereas 
neither JNK nor p38 was activated (Figure 3B, C). 
The expression of MMP family and EMT markers was 
also examined by RT-PCR. As shown in Figure 3D, down-
regulated MAGI1 resulted in stronger expression of 
MMP2, MMP14, especially MMP7 and MMP9; up-
regulated N-cadherin was also found in MAGI1 
knockdown AGS cells, whereas the expression of E-</p>

<p>cadherin was reduced. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>GC is a common type of cancer with poor prognosis. 
Metastasis is one crucial factor in the progression and 
prognosis of GC patients (20). Though new drugs have 
emerged increasingly with the combination of the latest 
clinical researches and already been shown to alleviate the 
progression of GC, whereas they still fail to develop 
efficient target drugs that directly reduced the progression 
of metastasis in GC treatment because of the complexity in </p>

<p>Table 2 Relationship between MAGI1 protein expression and clinicopathological features in GC patients (N=58) </p>

<p>Clinicopathological features 
Case No. 
MAGI1 expression [n (%)] 
χ 2 
P 
Negative 
Positive </p>

<p>Gender 
0.330 
0.566* </p>

<p>Male 
32 
22 (68.8) 
10 (31.2) </p>

<p>Female 
26 
16 (61.5) 
10 (38.5) </p>

<p>Age (year) 
0.190 
0.663* </p>

<p>≤60 
37 
25 (67.6) 
12 (32.4) </p>

<p>&gt;60 
21 
13 (61.9) 
8 (38.1) </p>

<p>Lauren classification 
9.005 
0.003* </p>

<p>Intestinal/mixed 
25 
11 (44.0) 
14 (56.0) </p>

<p>Diffused 
33 
27 (81.8) 
6 (18.2) </p>

<p>Depth of invasion 
0.074 
0.786* </p>

<p>T1 
10 
5 (50.0) 
5 (50.0) </p>

<p>T2-4 
48 
33 (68.8) 
15 (31.2) </p>

<p>Lymph node status 
1.288 
0.256* </p>

<p>N0 
10 
5 (50.0) 
5 (50.0) </p>

<p>N1-3 
48 
33 (68.8) 
15 (31.3) </p>

<p>Distant metastasis 
3.874 
0.049* </p>

<p>M0 
47 
28 (59.6) 
19 (40.4) </p>

<p>M1 
11 
10 (90.9) 
1 (9.1) </p>

<p>TNM staging 
6.012 
0.111** </p>

<p>I 
5 
3 (60.0) 
2 (40.0) </p>

<p>II 
16 
7 (43.8) 
9 (56.2) </p>

<p>III 
23 
16 (69.6) 
7 (30.4) </p>

<p>IV 
14 
12 (85.7) 
2 (14.3) </p>

<p>Differentiation 
11.914 
0.008** </p>

<p>High-medium 
2 
1 (50.0) 
1 (50.0) </p>

<p>Medium 
8 
1 (12.5) 
7 (87.5) </p>

<p>Medium-low 
7 
5 (71.4) 
2 (28.6) </p>

<p>Low 
41 
31 (75.6) 
10 (24.4) </p>

<p>MAGI1, membrane-associated guanylate kinase inverted 1; GC, gastric cancer; *, Chi-square test; **, Kruskal-Wallis test. </p>

<p>Chinese Journal of Cancer Research, Vol 29, No 1 February 2017 </p>

<p>
© Chinese Journal of Cancer Research. All rights reserved. 
www.cjcrcn.org 
Chin J Cancer Res 2017;29(1):25-35 </p>

<p>these series of biological processes (21). Therefore, a 
comprehensive understanding of the GC metastasis is an 
urgent requirement to develop effective therapeutic drugs. 
From the outset of this study, we confirmed the down-
regulation of MAGI1 in GC tissues and GC cell lines. This 
is in agreement with the previous studies in colorectal 
cancer, hepatocellular carcinoma and cervical cancer (6-9). 
Further analysis on the relationship between MAGI1 
expression and clinicalpathological parameters indicated 
that the MAGI1 expression was significantly associated 
with pathological typing, degree of differentiation and 
distant metastasis in GC patients. Pathological typing and 
differentiation are not only utilized to reflect the tumor 
biological behavior, but also important for the better 
evaluation of pathogenesis, potential characteristics of the 
related disease and even the patient prognosis (22,23). Our 
results found that MAGI1 was more frequently expressed 
in the moderately-well differentiated intestinal or mixed 
GC types than the poorly differentiated diffused ones. 
Because diffused GC always origins from gastric mucosa 
with poor differentiation and is especially characterized as 
absence of cell junction, our result was potentially 
consistent with the biological functions of MAGI1 that had 
been demonstrated by previous studies, such as the 
functions of maintaining cell-cell junctions and cell </p>

<p>adhesion (11,12). 
Furthermore, considering the association of MAGI1 
expression with distant metastasis, we then explored the 
biological role of MAGI1 in GC progression. MAGI1 
knockdown promoted migration and invasion in GC cells, 
but its influence on the cell proliferation was limited. Our 
study was partially in agreement with the previous study 
which investigated MAGI1 in other kinds of cancer, such as 
hepatocellular carcinoma (10). Based on the functional 
analysis, we further investigated the potential molecular 
mechanism on metastasis progression that mediated by 
MAGI1. Our studies demonstrated that MAGI1 not only 
repressed the expression of MMPs, especially MMP7 and 
MMP9, but also altered the expression of typical EMT 
molecules (suppressed N-cadherin expression and 
enhanced E-cadherin expression), and then inhibited the 
migration and invasion of GC cells. MMPs and EMT are 
two types of essential pathways that commonly participate 
in metastasis progression in different tumor types (24-26). 
MMP family plays an important role in extracellular matrix 
remodeling, which is implicated to have the ability to 
accelerate tumor aggressiveness in various cancers (27,28). 
EMT is another key process along with cell phenotypic 
changes to achieve the migration and invasion ability, and 
thus finally promote the metastasis progression (29). 
However, the early initiations of these two essential 
pathways are always mediated by different signaling 
transduction pathways in different tumor types. MAPK is 
one of the important families that is always constitutively 
activated in cancers and mediates the signaling transduction 
pathways to regulate different biological processes such as 
proliferation, apoptosis and metastasis in various cancers, in 
addition, ERK, JNK and p38 are three main sub-members 
of MAPK (30-32). Previous studies revealed that the 
expression of MAGI family members was correlated with 
the further regulation of MAPK signaling pathways, 
whereas which MAPK family signaling pathway being 
specifically regulated was mainly depended on the MAGI 
family member types or tumor types. Zhang et al. indicated 
that silencing of MAGI3, another member of MAGI family 
with particular similar molecular structure to MAGI1, 
could inhibit LPA2-induced ERK signaling pathway in 
colon cancer cells (33). Besides, MAGI3 was also found to 
regulate ERK signaling pathway though β2-adrenoreceptor 
(β2AR) in COS-7 cell model and the inhibition of JNK 
signaling pathway by MAGI3 was demonstrated in 
HEK293 cell model (34,35). In this study, we detected 
these three main signaling pathways of MAPK family and </p>

<p>Figure 3 MAGI1 inhibited matrix metalloproteinase (MMP) </p>

<p>expression and epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) </p>

<p>progression by blocking mitogen-activated protein </p>

<p>kinases/extracellular signal-regulated kinase (MAPK/ERK) </p>

<p>signaling pathway in gastric cancer (GC) cells. (A, B, C) MAGI1 </p>

<p>knockdown activated ERK but not JNK or P38 in AGC cells; (D) </p>

<p>The expression of MMPs and EMT molecules detected by reverse </p>

<p>transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) in AGS cells. </p>

<p> 
Jia et al. MAGI1 inhibits migration and invasion in GC </p>

<p>© Chinese Journal of Cancer Research. All rights reserved. 
www.cjcrcn.org 
Chin J Cancer Res 2017;29(1):25-35 </p>

<p>revealed that knockdown of MAGI1 could only activate 
ERK signaling pathway, but not JNK or p38 signaling 
pathway in AGS GC cells, which was similar to the 
previous studies in colon cancer cells and COS-7 cell 
model. The role of ERK signaling pathway in regulating 
cell biological behavior was complicated, and ERK 
signaling pathway was reported that it functioned as a 
trigger signal to further accelerate some biological 
processes such as proliferation, migration and invasion. 
One way of ERK signaling pathway involved in invasion 
and metastasis is by up-regulating the expression of MMPs 
and EMT-related molecules (27,28,36). Therefore, our 
study preliminarily revealed that MAGI1 acted as a tumor-
suppressor to inhibit the metastasis progression through 
the suppression of ERK signaling pathway, which further 
repressed the expression of MMPs and impaired EMT 
progression. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Our study demonstrated that MAGI1 was down-regulated 
in GC and was associated with the distant metastasis of 
clinicopathological parameters in GC patients. Moreover, 
we also discovered that MAGI1 acted as a key regulator in 
repressing cell migration and invasion through blocking 
MAPK/ERK signaling mediated MMP expression and 
EMT progression. However, further studies are required to 
clarify the specific mechanisms involved in this process. A 
more comprehensive understanding of the role of MAGI1 
in GC metastasis may contribute to the development of 
novel drugs and expand new horizon for the investigation 
on GC in clinical therapy. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Young Talents of Science 
and Technology Support Project of Colleges and 
Universities of Inner Mongolia Autonomous Region 
(NJYT-12-B21, 2012), the Great Project of the Affiliated 
Hospital of Inner Mongolia Medical University (No. 
NYFY ZD 2012014), the National Natural Science 
Foundation of China (No. 81260363), Beijing Municipal 
Administration of Hospitals' Youth Programme (No. 
QML20151003), the Project supported by National 
Science and Technology Ministry (No. 2014BAI09B02) 
and Beijing Municipal Administration of Hospitals Clinical 
Medicine Development of Special Funding Support (No. 
ZYLX201701). </p>

<p>Footnote </p>

<p>Conflicts of Interest: The authors have no conflicts of interest 
to declare. </p>

<p> </p>

<p>
© Chinese Journal of Cancer Research. All rights reserved. 
www.cjcrcn.org 
Chin J Cancer Res 2017;29(1):25-35 </p>



<p> 
Jia et al. MAGI1 inhibits migration and invasion in GC </p>

<p>© Chinese Journal of Cancer Research. All rights reserved. 
www.cjcrcn.org 
Chin J Cancer Res 2017;29(1):25-35 </p>



<p>Cite this article as: Jia S, Lu J, Qu T, Feng Y, Wang X, Liu </p>

<p>C, Ji J. MAGI1 inhibits migration and invasion via blocking </p>

<p>MAPK/ERK signaling pathway in gastric cancer. Chin J </p>

<p>Cancer Res 2017;29(1):25-35. doi: 10.21147/j.issn.1000-</p>

<p>9604.2017.01.04 </p>

<p>Chinese Journal of Cancer Research, Vol 29, No 1 February 2017 
35 </p>

<p>© Chinese Journal of Cancer Research. All rights reserved. 
www.cjcrcn.org 
Chin J Cancer Res 2017;29(1):25-35 </p>

</text></tei>