<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5283079" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>PURPOSE. To investigate the effectiveness of antimicrobial blue light (aBL) as an alternative or 
adjunctive therapeutic for infectious keratitis. </p>

<p>METHODS. We developed an ex vivo rabbit model and an in vivo mouse model of infectious 
keratitis. A bioluminescent strain of Pseudomonas aeruginosa was used as the causative 
pathogen, allowing noninvasive monitoring of the extent of infection in real time via 
bioluminescence imaging. Quantitation of bacterial luminescence was correlated to colony-
forming units (CFU). Using the ex vivo and in vivo models, the effectiveness of aBL (415 nm) 
for the treatment of keratitis was evaluated as a function of radiant exposure when aBL was 
delivered at 6 or 24 hours after bacterial inoculation. The aBL exposures calculated to reach 
the retina were compared to the American National Standards Institute standards to estimate 
aBL retinal safety. </p>

<p>RESULTS. Pseudomonas aeruginosa keratitis fully developed in both the ex vivo and in vivo 
models at 24 hours post inoculation. Bacterial luminescence in the infected corneas 
correlated linearly to CFU (R 2 ¼ 0.921). Bacterial burden in the infected corneas was rapidly 
and significantly reduced (&gt;2-log 10 ) both ex vivo and in vivo after a single exposure of aBL. 
Recurrence of infection was observed in the aBL-treated mice at 24 hours after aBL 
exposure. The aBL toxicity to the retina is largely dependent on the aBL transmission of the 
cornea. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS. Antimicrobial blue light is a potential alternative or adjunctive therapeutic for 
infectious keratitis. Further studies of corneal and retinal safety using large animal models, in 
which the ocular anatomies are similar to that of humans, are warranted. </p>

<p>the superficial nature of keratitis make keratitis an ideal 
candidate for aBL therapy. 
Despite of the advantages of aBL, this optical approach has 
yet to become established as a treatment of infections. In the 
present study, we investigated the effectiveness of aBL (415 
nm) for the treatment of infectious keratitis using an ex vivo 
rabbit model and an in vivo mouse model. A bioluminescent 
strain of P. aeruginosa was used as the causative pathogen, 
allowing noninvasive monitoring of the extent of infection in 
real time. Because sufficiently high exposure to aBL is toxic to 
the retina, we compared the retinal exposure during aBL 
irradiation to the safety threshold published by the American 
National Standards Institute (ANSI; American National Standard 
for Safe Use of Lasers 136.1). 19 Our study demonstrated that 
bacteria were rapidly and significantly reduced both ex vivo 
and in vivo after a single exposure of aBL, and the aBL toxicity 
to the retina is largely dependent on the aBL transmission of 
the cornea. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Blue Light Source </p>

<p>Antimicrobial blue light was delivered using a light-emitting 
diode (LED) (Vielight, Inc., Toronto, Canada) with peak 
emission at 415 nm and full-width half maximum of 20 nm. 
The LED was mounted on a heat sink to prevent thermal 
effects. The irradiance on the corneal surface was 100 mW/ 
cm 2 throughout the study as measured using a PM100D 
power/energy meter (Thorlabs, Inc., Newton, NJ, USA). 
Varying aBL exposures were delivered by varying the 
irradiation time. </p>

<p>Bacterial Strain </p>

<p>Pseudomonas aeruginosa American Type Culture Collection 
(ATCC) 19660 (strain 180), an ExoU expression strain, 20 was 
used as the representative causative pathogen. The strain was 
made bioluminescent by transfecting lux operon into the 
bacterial strain as described previously. 21 This allowed 
noninvasive and real-time monitoring of bacterial biolumines-
cence, which is related to the corresponding colony-forming 
units (CFU) of bacteria, by using bioluminescence imaging. 22 
Bacteria were routinely grown in brain-heart infusion (BHI) 
medium (Fisher Scientific, Agawam, MA, USA) supplemented 
with 50 lg/mL kanamycin in an orbital incubator (378C; 0.14g; 
New Brunswick Scientific, Edison, NJ, USA). </p>

<p>aBL Therapy for Keratitis in the Ex Vivo Rabbit 
Model </p>

<p>Enucleated whole mature New Zealand white rabbit eyes with 
clear corneas were purchased from Pel-Freez Biologicals 
(Rogers, AR, USA) and thawed on the day of the experiment. 
The central area of corneal epithelium (11-mm diameter) was 
surgically removed using a sterile surgical blade. Subsequently, 
a 20-lL aliquot of bacterial suspension containing 2 3 10 6 CFU 
P. aeruginosa in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) was topically 
inoculated onto the de-epithelized corneas. The infected eyes 
were then incubated at 378C for 6 or 24 hours. Biolumines-
cence imaging was performed to monitor the extent of 
infection. 
Eighteen infected ex vivo rabbit eyes were randomly 
divided into three groups of six eyes each. Two groups were 
subjected to aBL exposure and the other group served as the 
untreated control. Antimicrobial blue light was delivered at 6 
or 24 hours after bacterial inoculation (six rabbit eyes for each </p>

<p>time point) to investigate its effectiveness against early-stage or 
fully developed infections. </p>

<p>aBL Therapy for Keratitis in the In Vivo Mouse 
Model </p>

<p>Female C57BL/6 mice, aged 8 weeks and weighing 18 to 20 g, 
were purchased from Charles River Laboratories (Wilmington, 
MA, USA). All animal procedures were approved by the 
Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) at the 
Massachusetts General Hospital (protocol no. 2014N000016) 
and were in accordance with the ARVO Statement for the Use 
of Animals in Ophthalmic and Vision Research. 
Under anesthesia, corneas of mice were scarified using a 
30.5-guage needle to produce three parallel incisions that did 
not penetrate beyond the superficial stroma. 21 A 5-lL aliquot of 
bacterial suspension containing 5 3 10 5 CFU P. aeruginosa in 
PBS was then topically inoculated onto the wounded area of 
the corneas. Only one cornea was wounded and infected in 
each mouse. Bioluminescent imaging was performed to 
monitor the extent of infection. 
Eighteen infected mice were then randomly divided into 
three groups of six mice each. Two groups were subjected to 
aBL exposure, and the other group served as the untreated 
control. Similar to the procedure for the ex vivo study using 
rabbit models, aBL was delivered at 6 or 24 hours after bacterial 
inoculation (six mice for each time point) to investigate its 
effectiveness against early-stage and fully developed infections, 
respectively. 
The mouse corneas were also photographed daily using a 
digital camera (Nikon D90 with a AF Micro Nikkor 60mm 
1:2.8D lens; Tokyo, Japan). To statistically analyze the 
pathologic changes in the corneas, photographs were scored 
by three ophthalmologists who were unaware of the treat-
ments given. The scoring system used is described in the 
Table. 23 </p>

<p>Bioluminescence Imaging of Infections </p>

<p>The bacterial luminescence in the infected corneas was 
detected using a Hamamatsu bioluminescence imaging 
system (Hamamatsu Photonics KK, Bridgewater, NJ, USA). 
This system included an intensified charge-coupled device 
(ICCD) camera (C2400-30H, Hamamatsu) developed for 
imaging under extremely low light levels, a camera controller, 
a specimen chamber, and an image processor (C5510-50, 
Hamamatsu). Rabbit or mouse corneas were placed on an 
adjustable stage in the specimen chamber, and were 
positioned directly under the ICCD camera. When set for 
photon counting, the camera controller's automatic amplifi-
cation circuit was employed for maximum sensitivity. An 
integration time of 2 minutes was used for image acquisition. 
For each measurement, the background signal was subtracted 
from the bioluminescent signal. The bioluminescence mea-</p>

<p>TABLE 1. Corneal Pathology Scores of Mice 23 </p>

<p>Score 
Pathologic Change </p>

<p>0 
Eye macroscopically identical with the uninfected contralateral 
control eye 
1 
Faint opacity partially covering the pupil 
2 
Dense opacity covering the pupil 
3 
Dense opacity covering the entire anterior segment 
4 
Perforation of the cornea, phthisis bulbi (shrinkage of the 
globe after inflammatory disease), or both </p>

<p>Blue Light for Keratitis 
IOVS j January 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 1 j 587 </p>

<p>surement of infections was quantified using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Argus</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Hamamatsu</rs>). </p>

<p>Quantitative Correlation of Bacterial 
Luminescence to Bacterial CFU in the Infected 
Corneas </p>

<p>To quantitatively correlate bacterial CFU to the corresponding 
bacterial luminescence (relative light units: RLU), ex vivo 
rabbit corneas infected with P. aeruginosa were used. In brief, 
rabbit corneas were inoculated with a 20-lL aliquot of bacterial 
suspension containing 2 3 10 6 CFU P. aeruginosa in PBS. After 
incubation overnight at 378C, infected rabbit corneas were 
exposed, respectively, to varying aBL exposures (0, 36, 72, 108, 
and 144 J/cm 2 ) and then subjected to bioluminescence 
imaging. After imaging, each rabbit cornea was homogenized 
in 1 mL sterile PBS at 48C. Suspensions were collected and 
plated on BHI agar after serial 10-fold dilutions. 24 Total CFU 
were counted and plotted versus the corresponding bacterial 
luminescence measured. </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>Data are presented as the mean 6 SD, and differences between 
groups were tested for significance by using an unpaired, 2-
tailed Student's t-test. Differences in corneal pathology scores 
between different groups of mice were analyzed using the 
general linear model. Values of P &lt; 0.05 were considered 
significant for all statistical analyses. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Bacterial Luminescence Was Linearly Correlated to 
CFU </p>

<p>To test whether measuring the RLU of bacterial biolumines-
cence in the infected eyes after aBL exposure accurately 
reported the corresponding bacterial CFU, bacterial lumines-
cence measurements were made after varying radiant expo-
sures of aBL, and bacteria were cultured from the same eyes. 
Figure 1 shows a fairly good linear correlation (y ¼ 11.353x) 
between the bacterial luminescence measurement (RLU) of P. 
aeruginosa and the corresponding CFU (determination </p>

<p>coefficient R 2 ¼ 0.921, correlation coefficient r ¼ 0.9621, P ¼ 
0.0001). </p>

<p>P. aeruginosa Keratitis Fully Developed in Both 
the Ex Vivo Rabbit Model and the In Vivo Mouse 
Model </p>

<p>To characterize the development of P. aeruginosa infection in 
the cornea, the bacterial luminescence was measured for up to 
24 hours in the ex vivo rabbit model and up to 72 hours in the 
in vivo mouse model. In the ex vivo rabbit corneas, the mean 
bacterial luminescence increased steadily until approximately 
9 hours, then remained relatively stable (Fig. 2A, solid line; n ¼ 
6). This result was qualitatively apparent from the bacterial 
luminescence images of a single cornea followed over the same 
time period. 
To characterize the distribution of P. aeruginosa in the 
rabbit cornea, histology with Gram and hematoxylin and eosin 
(H&amp;E staining) was performed at 3, 6, and 24 hours post 
inoculation. At 3 hours post inoculation, P. aeruginosa was 
primarily located on the surface of corneal tissue. However, the 
bacteria rapidly proliferated into the stroma and destroyed the 
structure of cornea at 24 hours post inoculation, due to the 
lack of an immune response in this ex vivo model (Fig. 2B). 
Similarly, after inoculating bacteria onto the scratched in 
vivo corneas of mice, a 24-hour period of more rapid increase 
in bacterial luminescence was followed by a more stable level 
of infection that lasted at least 72 hours. These changes were 
characterized by both quantitative bioluminescence imaging 
(Fig. 2C, solid line; n ¼ 6) and photography (Fig. 2C, inset). The 
photographs of a representative infected mouse eye showed an 
increased opacity of the mouse cornea with the time post 
inoculation. </p>

<p>aBL Effectively and Rapidly Reduced P. aeruginosa 
Burden in the Infected Ex Vivo Rabbit Corneas </p>

<p>Infected rabbit corneas were treated at either 6 or 24 hours 
post inoculation to investigate the effectiveness of aBL therapy 
for early-stage or fully established infection. When aBL was 
delivered at 6 hours post inoculation, the bacterial lumines-
cence decreased with increasing aBL exposure and an 
approximately 3-log 10 inactivation was achieved, compared 
to untreated control, by exposure to 84 J/cm 2 aBL (arrow in 
Fig. 3A; 14 minutes irradiation). In contrast, when aBL was 
delivered at 24 hours post inoculation, exposure to 84 J/cm 2 
aBL elicited less than 1-log 10 inactivation (Fig. 3B). Exposure to 
304 J/cm 2 aBL (~50 minutes irradiation) was required to 
achieve approximately 3-log 10 inactivation. No bacterial 
regrowth was observed in any rabbit cornea after aBL 
exposure. </p>

<p>aBL Effectively and Rapidly Reduced P. aeruginosa 
Burden in Infected Mouse Corneas In Vivo </p>

<p>When aBL was delivered at 6 hours post inoculation, an 
increase in aBL exposure decreased the bacteria level in in vivo 
mouse corneas, and an approximately 2.0-log 10 inactivation of 
P. aeruginosa was achieved when an exposure of 36 J/cm 2 aBL 
was delivered (Fig. 4A; 6 minutes irradiation). In contrast, in 
the untreated mice, bacterial luminescence remained almost 
unchanged during the equivalent period of time (data not 
shown). Corneal pathology, as shown in Figure 4B, was scored 
at 6, 24, and 48 hours after bacterial inoculation, respectively, 
for both aBL-treated and untreated mice. 23 It was observed that 
the eyes of aBL-treated mice had significantly lower mean 
corneal pathology scores as compared to the eyes of untreated </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Correlation of the bacterial luminescence intensity of 
infected ex vivo rabbit corneas to the corresponding colony-forming 
units (CFU). Bacterial luminescence intensity is presented in relative 
light units (RLU). </p>

<p>Blue Light for Keratitis 
IOVS j January 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 1 j 588 </p>

<p>mice (P ¼ 0.0048, Fig. 4C). In addition, the analysis of the 
interaction between ''aBL treatment'' and ''time post infection'' 
shows that the effect of aBL treatment increased with the time 
post infection. </p>

<p>When aBL was delivered at 24 hours after P. aeruginosa 
inoculation, the bacterial luminescence was completely 
eradicated after an exposure of 144 J/cm 2 aBL (Fig. 4D). The 
aBL killing curve of P. aeruginosa shows that a &gt;2.5-log 10 </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Ex vivo rabbit model and in vivo mouse model of P. aeruginosa keratitis. (A) Time course for the bacterial luminescence intensity of ex 
vivo rabbit eyes infected with 2 3 10 6 CFU of P. aeruginosa (solid line; n ¼ 6). Successive bacterial luminescence images are shown from a 
representative infected ex vivo rabbit eye. The pseudo-color scale bar indicates the bioluminescence intensity value of a single pixel in the 
bioluminescence images. (B) Gram-stained (320) and H&amp;E-stained histologic sections (310) of representative ex vivo rabbit eyes infected with 2 3 
10 6 CFU of P. aeruginosa and sampled at 3, 6, and 24 hours after bacterial inoculation. The Gram stain demonstrated the presence of P. aeruginosa 
in the corneal tissue, with bacteria invaded deeper into the corneal tissue over this time period. The areas in the depicted boxes in 310 H&amp;E images 
are shown in 320 Gram images. The areas in the depicted boxes in 320 Gram images are illustrated in the insets of 3100 oil lens images. (C) Time 
course for the bacterial luminescence intensity of in vivo mouse eyes infected with 5 3 10 5 CFU of P. aeruginosa (solid line; n ¼ 6). Bars: standard 
deviation. The inset shows the bacterial luminescence images and photographs taken at 0, 24, 36, and 72 hours post inoculation from a 
representative infected in vivo mouse eye. The pseudo-color scale bar indicates the bioluminescence intensity value of a single pixel in the 
bioluminescence images. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Influence of radiant exposure on aBL therapy for keratitis in the ex vivo rabbit model. (A) aBL (180 J/cm 2 ) delivered at 6 hours after 
inoculation with 2 3 10 6 CFU of P. aeruginosa (solid line; n ¼ 6). Bars: standard deviation. Bacterial luminescence images of the infected rabbit eyes 
were taken when 0, 12, 36, 84, and 180 J/cm 2 aBL had been delivered (irradiance ¼ 100 mW/cm 2 ) and at the same times in untreated controls. The 
bacterial luminescence images of representative infected rabbit eyes, treated with aBL or not treated, are shown. The pseudo-color scale bar 
indicates the bioluminescence intensity value of a single pixel in the bioluminescence images. (B) aBL (372 J/cm 2 ) delivered at 24 hours after 
inoculation with 2 3 10 6 CFU of P. aeruginosa (solid line; n ¼ 6). Bars: standard deviation. The bacterial luminescence images were taken when 0, 
12, 36, 84, 180, and 372 J/cm 2 aBL had been delivered to the infected rabbit eyes (irradiance ¼ 100 mW/cm 2 ) and at the same times in untreated 
controls. The bacterial luminescence images of representative infected rabbit eyes treated with aBL (372 J/cm 2 ) or not treated are shown. The 
pseudo-color scale bar indicates the bioluminescence intensity value of a single pixel in the bioluminescence images. </p>

<p>Blue Light for Keratitis 
IOVS j January 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 1 j 589 </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Influence of radiant exposure on aBL therapy for keratitis in the in vivo mouse model. (A) Influence of radiant exposure of aBL on the 
bacterial luminescence intensity of mouse eyes infected with 5 3 10 5 P. aeruginosa and treated with 36 J/cm 2 aBL at 6 hours post inoculation (n ¼ 
6). The inset shows the bacterial luminescence images from a representative mouse eye infected with 5 3 10 5 CFU of P. aeruginosa and treated with 
36 J/cm 2 aBL at 6 hours post inoculation. Bacterial luminescence images were taken when 0, 9, 18, 27, and 36 J/cm 2 aBL had been delivered 
(irradiance ¼ 100 mW/cm 2 ). The pseudo-color scale bar indicates the bioluminescence intensity value of a single pixel in the bioluminescence 
images. (B) Photographs of two representative mouse eyes infected with 5 3 10 5 CFU of P. aeruginosa, treated with aBL (36 J/cm 2 ) at 6 hours post 
infection (top row) or not treated (bottom row), indicating less opacity and damage in the aBL-treated mouse eye than in the untreated one. (C) 
Corneal pathology scores of the infected mouse eyes treated with 36 J/cm 2 aBL at 6 hours post infection (n ¼ 6) or not treated (n ¼ 6), showing the 
higher mean corneal pathology scores of the untreated mouse eyes than the aBL-treated mouse eyes (P ¼ 0.0048). In addition, the analysis of the 
interaction between aBL treatment and time post infection shows that the effect of aBL treatment increased with the time post infection. Data were 
analyzed using the general linear model. (D) The bacterial luminescence images of representative mouse eyes infected with 5 3 10 5 CFU of P. 
aeruginosa, treated with 144 J/cm 2 aBL 24 hours later or left untreated. The pseudo-color scale bar indicates the bioluminescence intensity value 
of a single pixel in the bioluminescence images. (E) Influence of radiant exposure of aBL on the bacterial luminescence intensity of the mouse eyes 
infected with 5 3 10 5 P. aeruginosa, treated with 144 J/cm 2 aBL at 24 hours post inoculation (n ¼ 6), or left untreated (n ¼ 6). Bars: standard 
deviation. Bacterial luminescence images were taken when 0, 18, 36, 54, 72, 90, 108, 126, and 144 J/cm 2 aBL had been delivered (irradiance ¼ 100 
mW/cm 2 ). </p>

<p>Blue Light for Keratitis 
IOVS j January 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 1 j 590 </p>

<p>inactivation was achieved when an exposure of 144 J/cm 2 aBL 
was delivered (Fig. 4E; 24 minutes irradiation), compared to 
untreated control. 
However, recurrence of infection was observed in the mice 
treated with aBL at both 6 and 24 hours post inoculation after 
aBL exposure. The recurrent infection was more severe in mice 
treated at 24 hours post inoculation than at 6 hours post 
inoculation. </p>

<p>Toxicity of aBL to the Retina is Largely Dependent 
on aBL Transmission of the Cornea </p>

<p>Retinal safety is a very important concern for developing aBL as 
a treatment of keratitis since aBL, in sufficient amount, is highly 
toxic to the retina. 25 Antimicrobial blue light that is not 
absorbed by the cornea or lens and is not blocked by the iris is 
transmitted through the pupil and reaches the retina. The 
wavelengths in aBL are absorbed by the chromophores in the 
retina and retinal pigment epithelium (e.g., proteins in 
photoreceptor cells, flavin proteins, heme proteins, melano-
somes), and subsequently may produce both photothermal and 
photochemical damage. 25 
Using the formula described by Delori et al., 26 we calculated 
the aBL exposures to reach the retina with the aBL treatment 
parameters that reduced the bacterial luminescence in the ex 
vivo rabbit model by approximately 3-log 10 (84 J/cm 2 for 6 
hours post inoculation and 304 J/cm 2 for 24 hours post 
inoculation; see Fig. 3). The initial calculation assumed that the 
cornea was clear (100% transmission), and subsequent 
calculations assumed partial cloudiness that decreased the 
aBL transmission by 50% and 90%. The obtained aBL exposures 
to reach the retina were compared to the safety thresholds for 
photothermal and photochemical damage previously estab-
lished by experimental studies. 19 The retinal aBL exposure was 
calculated for corneal irradiance ¼ 100 mW/cm 2 and pupil 
diameter ¼ 2 mm, and a 10-mm retinal image diameter was 
assumed. For a clear cornea (100% transmission), the retinal 
aBL exposure exceeds the retinal safety threshold (i.e., is 
unsafe) by factors of 1.43 and 5.13 for 84 and 304 J/cm 2 aBL, 
respectively. For a cloudy cornea that blocks 50% of the aBL, 84 
J/cm 2 aBL delivered to the cornea is below the retina safety 
threshold by a factor of 1.4 (i.e., 1/1.4 ¼ 0.71-fold of the retina 
safety threshold), but 304 J/cm 2 is above the threshold by a 
factor of 2.53. If a very cloudy cornea only transmits 10% of the 
aBL, 84 and 304 J/cm 2 aBL are below the limit by factors of 
7.13 and 2.03, respectively. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we developed an ex vivo rabbit model and an in 
vivo mouse model of infectious keratitis by using a biolumi-
nescent strain of P. aeruginosa and found a good linear 
correlation between the bacterial luminescence and the 
corresponding bacterial CFU in the infected corneas. Our 
results demonstrated that a single exposure of aBL rapidly and 
significantly reduced bacterial burden in both the ex vivo and 
in vivo models. The infections treated at 24 hours post 
inoculation were more resistant to aBL than they were at 6 
hours post inoculation. The possible reason is that, at 24 hours 
post inoculation, infections had fully established and bacteria 
existed predominantly as biofilms. 27 The biofilm matrix could 
block aBL and render bacterial cells less susceptible to aBL. 
Other investigators reported the effectiveness of aBL (420 nm) 
against bacterial biofilms. 28 Additionally, when infections had 
fully established, bacteria might have proliferated into the 
deeper layers of the corneal tissue (as shown in Fig. 2B), where 
the aBL transmission was further attenuated. In a previous </p>

<p>study of aBL therapy for P. aeruginosa burn infection in mice, 
we observed that, when aBL was applied 30 minutes post 
inoculation, an average 3.5-log 10 inactivation of P. aeruginosa 
in mouse burns was achieved when an exposure of 55.8 J/cm 2 
aBL had been delivered. 
Recurrence of infection was observed in mice (but not in 
the rabbit corneas) after a single exposure of aBL. One possible 
reason of infection recurrence is that bacteria in the infected 
corneas were not completely eradicated after aBL exposure 
even when bacterial luminescence was eliminated due to the 
sensitivity limitation of the bioluminescence imaging system 
(&gt;10 2 CFU). Another possible reason is that part of the corneal 
area was shielded by eyelids and this prevented aBL from 
irradiating this area, rendering the shielded area actually 
untreated. The bacteria surviving from the aBL exposure 
subsequently induced recurrence of infection. This hypothesis 
was supported by the results obtained from the study using the 
ex vivo rabbit corneas. In the ex vivo study, the whole area of 
excised rabbit corneas was exposed to aBL and no bacterial 
regrowth was found in any aBL-treated cornea after aBL 
exposure. Several approaches could be considered to improve 
the effectiveness of aBL therapy, such as repeated aBL 
treatments (two or three times) and combined therapy using 
aBL and subtherapeutic dose of antibiotics (antimicrobial eye 
drops), which can reach the corneal area under the eyelids 
after topical application. 
Corneal safety is a very important concern for developing 
aBL as a therapeutic for keratitis. In our previous in vitro 
studies, we demonstrated that bacteria (P. aeruginosa ATCC 
19660) were much more resistant to 415-nm aBL than were 
human keratinocytes. When 109.9 J/cm 2 aBL had been 
delivered, an approximately 7.64-log 10 CFU inactivation of P. 
aeruginosa was achieved. In contrast, under the same aBL 
irradiation condition, only a 0.16-log 10 loss of viability of 
human keratinocytes was observed. 29 Other investigators 
reported that when 100 J/cm 2 blue light at 410 nm had been 
delivered, the viability of corneal epithelial cells in vitro 
decreased by approximately 1-log 10 . 30 Further study on the 
potential toxicity of aBL on the cornea (i.e., corneal epithelial, 
endothelial, and keratocyte cells) is needed. 
There are also limitations of the in vivo mouse model used 
in the present study since mouse eyes differ substantially from 
human eyes. The human cornea is approximately 11 mm in 
diameter, whereas mouse corneas have a 2.2-to 3.5-mm 
diameter. 31,32 The axial length of human eyes is approximately 
eight times longer than that of mouse eyes, and the corneal 
thickness is greater for humans than for mice. The arrangement 
of corneal collagen and the properties of corneal epithelial 
cells also differ between mice and humans, 32,33 which could 
produce alternate reactions of the cornea to invading 
pathogens. Descemet's and Bowman's membranes are sub-
stantially thinner in mice than in humans, 32,34 and mouse 
corneas have a higher ratio of corneal epithelial cells to stroma 
than humans and more cell layers in the corneal epitheli-
um. 31,32 All of these anatomic differences have an effect on aBL 
delivery, bacterial adherence and possible invasion, suscepti-
bility to bacterial enzymes and other virulence factors, and 
availability of host defense molecules in the tear film. As a 
result, the effectiveness of aBL against keratitis needs to be 
further investigated using large in vivo animal models, for 
example, a rabbit or dog model, which are more similar to 
humans in ocular anatomy. 
In addition, aBL potentially can produce both photothermal 
and photochemical damage in the retina. According to the 
ANSI 136.1, we estimated the aBL toxicity to the retina under 
different aBL transmission of the corneal conditions. The 
calculations indicated that the aBL toxicity to the retina is 
largely dependent on the aBL transmission of the cornea. The </p>

<p>Blue Light for Keratitis 
IOVS j January 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 1 j 591 </p>

<p>corneal opacity of infected corneas means that more light 
would be blocked by infected corneas than by intact corneas. 
Apparently, to validate the results obtained from the theoretical 
calculation, further experimental study using animal models 
and clinical study are essential. 
Overall, our study suggests that aBL is a potential alternative 
or adjunctive approach for the treatment of infectious keratitis, 
in particular those caused by drug-resistant pathogens. 
Successful treatment of keratitis using aBL requires optimal 
timing, careful regulation of aBL exposure, and adequate 
concomitant antibacterial medication. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank Hang Lee, PhD, from the Harvard Catalyst 
Biostatistical Consulting Program for his generous help with 
statistical analysis. 
Supported in part by the Smith Infectious Diseases Foundation 
(Research Grant Award to TD), the Air Force Office of Scientific 
Research (FA9550-16-1-0479 to TD), and the National Institutes of 
Health (1R21AI109172 and 1R01AI123312 to TD). 
Disclosure: H. Zhu, None; I.E. Kochevar, None; I. Behlau, None; 
J. Zhao, None; F. Wang, None; Y. Wang, None; X. Sun, None; 
M.R. Hamblin, None; T. Dai, None </p>



<p>Blue Light for Keratitis 
IOVS j January 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 1 j 592 </p>



</text></tei>