<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5459276" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Introduction: One of the biggest disadvantages of dental amalgam is that gaining its ultimate strength is a slow 
process. The use of a rapid-setting amalgam with high early compressive strength could be a better option in 
preventing early fractures in pediatric dentistry. The aim of this study was to determine the effect of diode laser 
irradiation on compressive strength of dental amalgam. 
Methods: A case-control study was performed on 180 amalgam samples made at the Tehran Dental Material 
Research Center in 2014. Fifteen and thirty minute compressive strength of regular setting and fast setting 
amalgams were measured as control. In case groups, the samples were irradiated by 810nm diode laser with 
power of 1 and 2 watt and in pulsed and continuous mode, and compressive strength was measured after 15 and 
30 minutes. Statistical analysis was performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18</rs> using one and two way ANOVA and Scheffe 
multiple comparisons test and p&lt;0.05 was considered significant. 
Results: Numerous kinds of laser irradiation led to a significant increase in compressive strength compared to 
regular setting control groups. Fifteen minutes-compressive strength of regular-setting amalgam irradiated by 2 
watt laser was significantly more than fast-setting control group (p&lt;0.05). 
Conclusion: Irradiation by 810nm diode laser can significantly increase the compressive strength of dental 
amalgam especially in the first 15 minutes. 
Electronic physician </p>



<p>change at 37 °C, the process has not stopped at 150 h. Tensile strength has been shown to increase to at least 100 h, 
similar to results for compressive strength (5). High primary compressive strength can be an important benefit of 
dental amalgam, because it decreases the potential of early fractures due to heavy occlusal forces before the ultimate 
compressive strength is gained (6). Premature loading can result in minute fractures that are not apparent for weeks 
or even months. The use of a rapid setting amalgam with a high primary compressive strength should be considered 
when treating a pediatric patient in whom compliance with instructions to refrain from biting down hard on freshly 
placed amalgam is in question (1). Laser hardening is one of the methods of strengthening metals and alloys in 
industry. With the interaction of the laser beam and its movement over the surface, very rapid heating of metal 
workpieces can be achieved and subsequent to that, also very rapid cooling down or quenching. The cooling rate, 
which in conventional hardening defines quenching, has to ensure martensitic phase deformation. In laser hardening 
the martensitic transformation is achieved by self-cooling (7). In laser hardening, some characteristics such as 
hardness, strength, fatigue and wear resistance are improved and favorable characteristics such as toughness and 
ductility remain unchanged (8). We considered that laser irradiation can improve the compressive strength of dental 
amalgam; thus the aim of this study was to determine the effect of 810nm diode laser irradiation on compressive 
strength of dental amalgam. </p>

<p>2. Material and Methods 
2.1. Research design and materials 
This study is in the category of case-control studies performed in Tehran Dental Material Research Center in 2014. 
Two series of 2-spill amalgam capsules (Sepalloy, Septodont, France) were used; 150 regular setting amalgam 
capsules composed of 46% Ag, 31.3% Sn, 22.7% Cu and mercury to alloy ratio of 1.2; and 30 fast setting amalgam 
capsules composed of 66.8% Ag, 18.5% Sn, 12.7% Cu and mercury to alloy ratio of 1.1. </p>

<p>2.2. Sample preparation 
Amalgam capsules were triturated by an amalgamator (Ultramat 2, Australia) at the speed of 4800rpm for 8 seconds 
due to manufacturer's instructions. Standard amalgam samples were made by molding method under a load of 14±1 
MPa using a prefabricated mold. Height of all samples was 8mm and their width was 4mm. Prior compressive 
strength test, all samples were put in 37 °C incubator (Kavosh Mega, Iran) to simulate the temperature of oral 
environment. </p>

<p>2.3. Compressive strength testing 
Compressive strength test was carried out with universal testing machine (Zwick-Roell, Germany) at the speed of 
0.5 mm/min and under a load of 50N (Figure 1). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Schematic diagram for compressive strength testing. </p>

<p>2.4. Control groups 
In control groups, compressive strength of regular and fast setting amalgam was measured 15 and 30 minutes after 
trituration. Definition of control groups is as below (Table 1): 
• CR15: Compressive strength of regular setting amalgam after 15 minutes. </p>

<p>http://www.ephysician.ir </p>



<p>• CR30: Compressive strength of regular setting amalgam after 30 minutes. 
• CF15: Compressive strength of fast setting amalgam after 15 minutes. 
• CF30: Compressive strength of fast setting amalgam after 30 minutes. </p>

<p>Table 1. Summary of characteristics of each group 
Group 
Amalgam 
Laser power 
(watt) 
Mode of 
irradiation 
Irradiation 
time (seconds) 
Waiting time † 
(minutes) 
1 
CR15 
Regular setting 
---
---
---
15 
2 
CR30 
Regular setting 
---
---
---
30 
3 
CF15 
Fast setting 
---
---
---
15 
4 
CF30 
Fast setting 
---
---
---
30 
5 
RC115 
Regular setting 
1 
Continuous 
30 
15 
6 
RC130 
Regular setting 
1 
Continuous 
30 
30 
7 
RC215 
Regular setting 
2 
Continuous 
15 
15 
8 
RC230 
Regular setting 
2 
Continuous 
15 
30 
9 
RP115 
Regular setting 
1 
Pulsed 
30 
15 
10 
RP130 
Regular setting 
1 
Pulsed 
30 
30 
11 
RP215 
Regular setting 
2 
Pulsed 
30 
15 
12 
RP230 
Regular setting 
2 
Pulsed 
30 
30 
 †Waiting time: Time elapsed between the end of trituration and compressive strength testing </p>

<p>2.5. Optimization and lasing procedure 
In case groups, 810nm pulsed and continuous diode laser (GaAlAs, Gigga, China) with the power of 1 and 2 watt 
was used. Primarily, a pilot study was performed using different powers of diode laser and it was concluded that 
these powers have less probability for thermal changes. As laser irradiation can induce thermal changes in amalgam 
samples and more than 5.5 °C thermal changes have the potential to harm the pulp (9-12), first we optimized laser 
irradiation time in each group. An amalgam sample connected to the electrode of a thermometer (Fahm Co, Iran) 
and baseline temperature was registered. Temperature rise was measured during laser irradiation. Pulsed 1 watt laser 
caused 5.4°C temperature rise after 65 seconds and pulsed 2 watt laser caused the same change after 40 seconds. 
One watt continuous laser caused 5.3 °C increase in temperature while 2 watt continuous laser caused 5.7 °C 
increase after just 20 seconds. Regarding the results of the optimization test, the following physical parameters were 
considered to minimize the potential of thermal damage: irradiation time was considered 30 seconds for 1 and 2 watt 
pulsed and 1 watt continuous laser and 15 seconds for 2 watt continuous laser. To keep the same distance, 800µm 
fiber optic end was adjusted to the center of each sample and fixed at 4mm distance to its upper surface. One side of 
an electrode was connected to the lower surface of amalgam sample and the other side was connected to a 
thermometer to measure the increase in sample's temperature during laser irradiation and the highest temperature 
was registered for each sample. Figure 2 shows the lasing and temperature measuring model used in this study. 
Table 1 shows the characteristics of each group in this experiment. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Illustration of lasing and temperature measuring used in this experiment. </p>

<p>Electronic physician </p>



<p>2.6. Statistical analysis 
Data were processed by <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 18</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, Illinois, USA) and statistical analysis was performed 
using one-way and two-way ANOVA and Scheffe multiple comparisons and p&lt;0.05 was considered significant. </p>

<p>3. Results 
One hundred eighty amalgam samples were tested consisting of 60 samples in 4 control groups and 120 samples in 8 
case groups. Figure 3 shows mean compressive strength of studied samples. Statistical analysis showed that all types 
of laser irradiation caused significant increase in 15 and 30 minutes compressive strength of study samples 
compared to regular setting control groups (p&lt;0.05). Although the compressive strength of lased regular setting 
amalgam samples was more than fast setting control groups, the difference was statistically significant just for 15 
minute compressive strength after 2 watt pulsed and continuous irradiation (p&lt;0.05). There was no significant 
difference in the effect of pulsed and continuous lasers of the same power (p&gt;0.05). Each sample was connected to 
the electrode of a thermometer during lasing procedure and increase in temperature was registered. Table 2 shows 
minimum, maximum and mean temperature rise of lased amalgam samples in each group. Except for group RC230, 
temperature rise in all other groups was below the critical point. </p>

<p>Table 2. Minimum, maximum and mean temperature rise in lased amalgam groups 
Group 
Min (˚C) Max (°C) Mean (°C) 
5 
RC115 4.8 
5.8 
5.6 
6 
RC130 4.3 
5.9 
5.4 
7 
RC215 5.1 
6.7 
5.9 
8 
RC230 5.3 
6.4 
6.1 
9 
RP115 4.3 
5.3 
4.8 
10 RP130 4.1 
5.4 
4.3 
11 RP215 4.8 
5.7 
5.1 
12 RP230 4.7 
5.9 
5.2 </p>

<p>Figure 3. Mean compressive strength (MPa) of each group </p>

<p>4. Discussion 
Amalgam fillings constitute a great portion of dental fillings in children and adolescents (1). Ease of use, low 
technical sensitivity, clinical durability and cost-effectiveness of amalgam, makes it an acceptable filling in this age </p>

<p>http://www.ephysician.ir </p>



<p>group (1, 2). One of the most important problems while performing an amalgam restoration for children is lack of 
compliance with instructions to avoid biting hard objects in the first hours after placing an amalgam filling. So, it 
would be beneficial to use a rapid-setting amalgam when treating a pediatric patient (1). In the present study, we 
used diode laser irradiation to increase early compressive strength of amalgam. The rationale to use this type of laser 
was more absorbability in amalgam and less reflection that together can increase the temperature even in the inferior 
part of the amalgam sample. Diode laser equipment is relatively inexpensive and can be used in other procedures in 
pediatric dentistry such as pulpotomy and soft tissue surgeries. If clinically applicable, this procedure can be added 
to the aforementioned applications. According to the results of our study, two-watt pulsed and continuous diode 
laser irradiation resulted in a significant increase in 15-minutes compressive strength of regular setting amalgam, to 
the amounts even more than fast setting control amalgam samples (p&lt;0.05). One-watt pulsed and continuous laser 
caused an increase in compressive strength of amalgam samples which was statistically significant just compared to 
regular setting control samples (p&lt;0.05). As we know, hardening of dental amalgam is a consequence of a reaction 
between mercury and amalgam alloy particles that forms intermetalic compounds. This reaction results in δ1 
(Ag3Hg2) and δ2 (Cu3Sn6) phase formation that surround unreacted δ particles (Ag3Sn). The more the unreacted δ 
phase, the better the mechanical properties of amalgam such as compressive strength (6). There is a probability that 
laser beam causes heat and therefore accelerates the mercury-alloy reaction. As a result, intermetalic compounds 
make a lattice around the unreacted δ particles quickly which causes a more rapid hardening of amalgam, and limits 
the accessibility of alloy particles by mercury. Thereupon, more remained unreacted δ particles increase the 
compressive strength of amalgam. Further studies using thermocycling can reveal the effects of this strengthening 
procedure on long term stability and longevity of amalgam filling in oral environment. In the current study, 30-
minutes compressive strength of all irradiated amalgam samples was more than regular and fast setting control 
samples, but the difference was statistically significant just for regular setting amalgam. It seems that after laser 
irradiation and heating the amalgam sample, a rapid increase in compressive strength occurs and then, a hardening 
process progresses at a lower speed; whereas, compressive strength of fast setting amalgam, increases in a more 
constant mode. So, as time goes on, the significant difference in compressive strength of irradiated and fast setting 
amalgam becomes less pronounced. To the best of our knowledge, there is only a single study that used laser 
irradiation on dental amalgam and measured hardness enhancement after laser was used. Almuslet et al irradiated 
the amalgam mixture by 675nm diode laser at the power of 15mW for 2 minutes. They found 24% increase in 
hardness of amalgam after irradiation and 6 h hardness of irradiated amalgam was equal to 24 h hardness of non-
irradiated one (13). As it did not measure the changes in compressive strength of the studied samples, its results are 
not comparable to our study. According to the results of previous studies, more than 5.5 °C increase in pulpal 
temperature can exert adverse effects (9-12). In our study, the mean increase in temperature after irradiating 1-watt 
pulsed and continuous and 2-watt pulsed laser was below the critical point and just 2-watt continuous laser caused 
more than 5.5 °C increase in temperature of some of the amalgam samples. Regarding the lack of significant 
difference in compressive strength of amalgam after pulsed and continuous laser irradiation, it seems logical to use 
pulsed laser, due to lower risk of pulpal damage. Further studies using different kinds of lasers, make it possible to 
compare the effects of different lasers on compressive strength of dental amalgam. Unawareness of exact structural 
changes in amalgam is one of the limitations of this study and further studies using microscopic evaluation is 
recommended. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions 
According to the results of our study, 810nm, 2-watt, pulsed and continuous diode laser irradiation can significantly 
increase the early compressive strength of amalgam. Due to less heat production by pulsed laser and lower risk of 
pulpal damage, using this mode of irradiation can be beneficial in clinical success of amalgam fillings. Further 
studies on eventual effects of laser on structure and arrangement of amalgam alloy particles would be helpful in 
explaining the results of current study. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments: 
The study was funded by Dental Material Research Center, Babol University of Medical Sciences, Babol, Iran. The 
authors are grateful to the staff of Dental Research Center and Laser Research Center of Dentistry, Tehran 
University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: 
There is no conflict of interest to be declared. </p>

<p>Electronic physician </p>



<p>Authors' contributions: 
All authors contributed to this project and article equally. All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </p>



</text></tei>