<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5421174" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>with GJB1 mutations. Their clinical records and laboratory findings were retrospectively 
collected and reviewed. Mutations in the GJB1 gene were analyzed by targeted next-generation sequencing (NGS). Nucleotide alternations 
were confirmed with Sanger sequencing. 
Results: The CMT1X patients predominantly showed distal muscle weakness of lower limbs with mild sensory disturbance. The mean age 
of onset was 15.6 ± 8.7 years (ranging from 1 year to 42 years). The sudden onset of cerebral symptoms appeared in four patients (18.2%); 
two were initial symptoms. One case had constant central nervous system (CNS) signs. There were 19 different heterozygous mutations, 
including 15 known mutations and four novel mutations (c.115G&gt;T, c.380T&gt;A, c.263C&gt;A, and c.818_819insGGGCT). Among the 
22 Chinese patients with CMT1X, the frequency of the GJB1 mutation was 4.5% in transmembrane domain 1 (TM1), 4.5% in TM2, 
22.7% in TM3, 9.1% in TM4, 4.5% in extracellular 1 (EC1), 27.3% in EC2, 9.1% in intracellular loop, 13.6% in the N-terminal domain, 
and 4.5% in the C-terminal domain. CMT1X with CNS impairment appeared in five (22.7%) of these patients. 
Conclusions: This study indicated that CNS impairment was not rare in Chinese CMT1X patients. Mutations in the EC2 domain of the 
GJB1 gene were hotspot in Chinese CMT1X patients. </p>

<p>Key words: Connexin 32; Gap Junction Beta-1 Protein; Neuropathy; X-linked Charcot-Marie-Tooth Type 1 </p>

<p>Access this article online </p>

<p>Quick Response Code: 
Website: 
www.cmj.org </p>

<p>DOI: 
10.4103/0366-6999.204925 </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Address for correspondence: Prof. Yun Yuan, 
Department of Neurology, Peking University First Hospital, 
8 Xishiku Street, Xicheng District, Beijing 100034, China 
E-Mail: yuanyun2002@126.com </p>

<p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, 
tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited 
and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms. </p>

<p>For reprints contact: reprints@medknow.com </p>

<p>© 2017 Chinese Medical Journal ¦ Produced by Wolters Kluwer -Medknow </p>

<p>Received: 15-11-2016 Edited by: Xin Chen 
How to cite this article: Lu YY, Lyu H, Jin SQ, Zuo YH, Liu J, Wang ZX, 
Zhang W, Yuan Y. Clinical and Genetic Features of Chinese X-linked 
Charcot-Marie-Tooth Type 1 Disease. Chin Med J 2017;130:1049-54. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ May 5, 2017 ¦ Volume 130 ¦ Issue 9 </p>

<p>
Patients </p>

<p>Ninety-two patients with CMT from unrelated families 
were diagnosed by next-generation sequencing (NGS) at the 
Department of Neurology, Peking University First Hospital 
from January 2005 to January 2016. Among them, a total 
of 22 patients with GJB1 mutations were recruited in this 
study, which comprised 23.9% of the total CMT patients. 
As for the other CMT genes, the mutation frequency was 
35.9% in peripheral myelin protein 22 gene, 17.4% in 
mitofusin 2 gene, 2.2% in myelin protein zero gene, 5.4% in 
inverted formin, FH2 and WH2 domain containing (INF2) 
gene, 4.3% in ganglioside-induced differentiation associated 
protein 1 gene, 2.2% in neurofilament light gene, 2.2% in 
periaxin gene, 1.1% in SH3 domain and tetratricopeptide 
repeats 2 gene, 1.1% in early growth response 2 gene, 
1.1% in glycyl-tRNA synthetase gene, 1.1% in leucine rich 
repeat and sterile alpha motif containing 1 gene, 1.1% in 
FIG4 phosphoinositide 5-phosphatase (FIG4) gene, 1.1% in 
alanyl-tRNA synthetase gene, and 1.1% in dehydrogenase 
E1 and transketolase domain containing 1 gene. </p>

<p>The clinical records and electrophysiological characteristics 
of these 22 CMT1X patients with GJB1 mutations were 
retrospectively collected and reviewed. Muscle weakness 
was evaluated using the Medical Research Council score. All 
patients were interviewed and examined by two neurologists. </p>

<p>Mutation analysis </p>

<p>Genomic DNA was extracted from the peripheral blood 
samples of all patients. Mutations in the GJB1 gene were 
analyzed by targeted NGS. NGS panel covered all of the exons 
and their flanking sequences of genes known to be associated 
with hereditary neuropathies (gene list available on request). 
The exons and their flanking splice sites were captured 
and subsequently sequenced on an Illumina HiSeq 2500 
Sequencer (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA). The sequencing 
files were mapped to reference sequences with Burrows-
Wheeler Aligner and Picard tools and then called with control 
samples with the <rs id="software-0" type="software">GATK</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.0</rs> HaplotypeCaller (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Broad Institute</rs>, 
USA). Nucleotide alternations were confirmed with Sanger 
sequencing. The segregation analyses of the mutations were 
confirmed in the parents and the affected family members. For 
the novel mutations, 1000 healthy controls of Chinese origin 
were screened. The biological relevance of the novel amino 
acid changes was studied using both <rs id="software-1" type="software">PolyPhen</rs>-<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://www. genetics.bwh.harvard.edu/pph2</rs>/) and <rs id="software-2" type="software">Mutation Taster</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">http:// www.mutationtaster.org</rs>/) programs. </p>

<p>resulTs </p>

<p>Patients' clinical and electrophysiological characteristics </p>

<p>These 22 patients came from unrelated families, including 
20 males and 2 females. The clinical and electrophysiological 
characteristics of these CMT1X patients are shown in 
Table 1. The mean age of onset was 15.6 ± 8.7 years (ranging 
from 1 year to 42 years). Fifteen (68.2%) patients exhibited 
first symptoms in their second decade. Five (22.7%) of them 
presented symptoms after 20 years old. Two patients (9.1%) </p>

<p>had an earlier onset before 10 years old, including one from 
infancy. The mean duration from onset to diagnostic time 
was 8.2 ± 4.5 years (ranging from 2 years to 18 years). </p>

<p>All patients showed distal muscle wasting and weakness of 
the lower limbs, with the involvement of the upper limbs 
in 13 cases. Muscle strength ranged from III to V in distal 
upper limbs and from 0 to V in distal lower limbs. Sensory 
loss in distal limbs appeared in eight cases. Pes cavus 
occurred in 16 cases. CNS involvement appeared in five 
patients (22.7%), including four cases with transient CNS 
symptoms and one case with constant CNS signs. Four cases 
(18.2%) with transient symptoms presented with sudden 
onset of cerebral symptoms including aphasia, dysphagia, 
quadriplegia, or paralysis induced by fever or infection. 
The symptoms usually lasted from hours to days, and the 
patients completely recovered without special treatment. 
CNS symptoms in two patients appeared initially before 
the development of peripheral neuropathy. One case with 
constant CNS involvement additionally presented with 
nystagmus and ataxia on physical examination. </p>

<p>In median nerves, the mean motor nerve conduction 
velocity (MCV) was 35.0 ± 4.8 m/s (range: 27.3-43.9 m/s), 
the mean amplitude of compound muscle action 
potential (CAMP) was 2.3 ± 1.5 mV (range: 0.2-5.2 mV), 
the mean sensory nerve conduction velocity (SCV) was 
42.0 ± 9.6 m/s (range: 32.1-66.0 m/s), and the mean sensory 
nerve action potential (SNAP) amplitude was 5.0 ± 4.2 mV 
(range: 1.4-12.1 mV). In ulnar nerves, the mean MCV was 
33.6 ± 5.7 m/s (range: 27.7-46.7 m/s), the mean CAMP 
amplitude was 3.7 ± 3.2 mV (range: 0.3-10.3 mV), the 
mean SCV was 40.4 ± 12.8 m/s (range: 30.3-71.0 m/s), 
and the SNAP mean amplitude was 3.3 ± 3.3 mV (ranging 
from −1.47 mV to 9.6 mV). In tibial nerves, the mean MCV 
was 32.5 ± 5.5 m/s (range: 23.0-39.2 m/s) and the mean 
CAMP amplitude was 1.1 ± 1.7 mV (range: 0.0-4.8 mV). </p>

<p>The cranial magnetic resonance imagings (MRIs) of patient 
2 revealed abnormal signals in the splenium and genu of 
the corpus callosum in the first episode and in the bilateral 
posterior limbs of the internal capsule and splenium of the 
corpus callosum in the second episode. The cranial MRIs of 
patient 3 revealed abnormal signals in the centrum semiovale 
bilaterally in the first episode, the signals enlarged at the 
same location in the second episode, and widened at the third 
episode; the abnormal signals were resolved at intervals. The 
cranial MRIs of patient 4 revealed abnormal signals in the 
posterior limb of the internal capsule and the periventricular 
area bilaterally. The MRIs of patient 13 revealed abnormal 
signals in the bilateral centrum semiovale and splenium of 
the corpus callosum [Figure 1]. </p>

<p>Gap junction beta-1 protein mutations </p>

<p>This study identified 19 different heterozygous mutations 
in these 22 CMT1X patients [Table 2]. The c.44G&gt;T, 
c.59T&gt;G, c.62G&gt;A, c.194A&gt;G, c.379A&gt;T, C.403_404insT, 
c.424C&gt;T, c.425G&gt;A, c.490C&gt;T, c.533A&gt;G, c.548G&gt;A, 
c.547C&gt;T, c.556G&gt;A, c.590C&gt;T, and c.614A&gt;G mutations </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ May 5, 2017 ¦ Volume 130 ¦ Issue 9 </p>



<p>were reported previously. Four (c.115G&gt;T, c.263C&gt;A, 
c.380T&gt;A, and c.818_819insGGGCT) were novel 
mutations. Patient 22 with a c.818_819insGGGCT mutation 
had an X-linked family history. Five family members had </p>

<p>peripheral neuropathy. Patients with c.115G&gt;T, c.380T&gt;A, 
and c.263C&gt;A mutations were sporadic, and the mutation 
was not found in their parents. All novel mutations were 
not found in 1000 healthy controls and also not found in </p>

<p>Table 1: The clinical and electrophysiological characteristics of 22 Chinese CMT1X patients in this study </p>

<p>Patient 
number </p>

<p>Age 
(years) </p>

<p>Gender 
Onset 
age 
(years) </p>

<p>Muscle 
strength in 
distal UL </p>

<p>Muscle 
strength in 
distal LL </p>

<p>Sensory 
loss </p>

<p>CNS 
lesions </p>

<p>CMAP in 
median 
nerves (mV) </p>

<p>MCV in 
median 
nerves (m/s) </p>

<p>SNAP in 
median 
nerves (mV) </p>

<p>1 
34 
Male 
21 
IV 
II 
− 
− 
2.7 
35.5 
NE 
2 
14 
Male 
11 
IV 
IV 
− 
+ 
2.5 
36.0 
12.1 
3 
23 
Male 
8 
V </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>I-II 
− 
+ 
NE 
NE 
NE 
4 
13 
Male 
10 
III 
I-II 
− 
+ 
0.8 
28.9 
NE 
5 
20 
Female 
15 
IV 
0-II 
− 
− 
2.1 
38.0 
NA 
6 
24 
Male 
14 
V 
V </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>− 
− 
2.7 
43.9 
8.7 
7 
17 
Male 
14 
V 
IV 
− 
− 
5.2 
34.5 
3.6 
8 
18 
Female 
12 
V </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>IV 
− 
− 
3.0 
35.0 
1.87 
9 
37 
Male 
24 
V </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>I-II 
− 
+ 
0.3 
27.3 
2.3 
10 
19 
Male 
10 
V </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>IV 
UL, LL 
− 
NA 
NA 
NA 
11 
50 
Male 
32 
IV 
II 
UL, LL 
− 
2.3 
38.9 
NE 
12 
34 
Male 
24 
V </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>IV </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>LL 
− 
NA 
NA 
NA 
13 
15 
Male 
10 
V 
0-V </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>− 
+ 
NA 
NA 
NA 
14 
24 
Male 
14 
V 
0-V </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>LL 
− 
4.7 
38.0 
8.7 
15 
13 
Male 
11 
V 
IV 
UL, LL 
− 
NA 
28.0 
NA 
16 
44 
Male 
42 
V 
IV 
− 
− 
NA 
NA 
NA 
17 
26 
Male 
18 
V 
I 
LL 
− 
3.4 
39.8 
NE 
18 
27 
Male 
15 
IV 
II 
UL, LL 
− 
0.2 
NA 
1.4 
19 
19 
Male 
12 
IV 
I-II 
UL, LL 
− 
0.8 
28.9 
NE 
20 
21 
Male 
11 
V 
I-IV 
− 
− 
1.8 
33.9 
1.4 
21 
19 
Male 
14 
V 
0-IV 
− 
− 
NA 
NA 
NA 
22 
12 
Male 
1 
IV 
IV 
− 
− 
NA 
37.9 
NA </p>

<p>Patient 
number </p>

<p>SCV in median 
nerves (m/s) </p>

<p>CMAP in ulnar 
nerves (mV) </p>

<p>MCV in ulnar 
nerves (m/s) </p>

<p>SNAP in ulnar 
nerves (mV) </p>

<p>SCV in ulnar 
nerves (m/s) </p>

<p>CMAP in tibial 
nerves (mV) </p>

<p>MCV in tibial 
nerves (m/s) </p>

<p>1 
NE 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
2 
41.0 
1.8 
31 
1.8 
34.0 
NA 
NA 
3 
NE 
4.7 
33.1 
NE 
NE 
NE 
NE 
4 
NE 
10.3 
27.7 
NE 
NE 
3.5 
38.4 
5 
NA 
0.7 
46.7 
NA 
NA 
0.3 
38.4 
6 
43.0 
4.8 
33.1 
4.6 
37.6 
1.0 
NA 
7 
40.6 
NA 
NA 
2.9 
35.3 
0.2 
32.4 
8 
38.6 
4.4 
32 
−1.47 
35.8 
0.1 
27.7 
9 
32.1 
1.9 
30.9 
2.0 
30.3 
0.1 
29.2 
10 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
11 
NE 
NA 
NA 
NE 
NE 
NE 
NE 
12 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
13 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
14 
66.0 
1.5 
32 
9.6 
71.0 
0.6 
32.0 
15 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
4.8 
32.4 
16 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
17 
NE 
3.2 
41.7 
5.7 
37.6 
NE 
NE 
18 
42.0 
0.3 
NA 
1.4 
41.7 
0.2 
NA 
19 
NE 
9.1 
27.7 
NE 
NE 
NA 
NA 
20 
36.4 
1.8 
34 
NE 
NE 
0.0 
23.0 
21 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
22 
38.2 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
NA 
39.2 
CMT1X: X-linked Charcot-Marie-Tooth type 1; LL: Low limbs; UL: Upper limbs; +: Positive; −: Negative; CNS: Central nervous system; MCV: Motor 
conduction velocity; CMAP: Compound motor action potential; SCV: Sensory conduction velocity; SNAP, Sensory nerve action potential; NE: Not 
elicited; NA: Not available. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ May 5, 2017 ¦ Volume 130 ¦ Issue 9 </p>

<p>
NCBI SNP database, indicating that they were not benign 
polymorphisms. The novel missense mutations (c.115G&gt;T, 
c.380T&gt;A, and c.263C&gt;A) were highly conserved in 
the Cx32 proteins across all mammalian species. The 
pathogenicities of the novel missense mutations were 
predicted to be possibly damaging (c.380T&gt;A) and probably 
damaging (c.115G&gt;T and c.263C&gt;A) by <rs id="software-3" type="software">Polyphen</rs>-<rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">2</rs> and 
disease causing by <rs type="software">Mutation Taster</rs> software. Patient 12 
with pure peripheral neuropathy and patient 13 with CNS 
impairment had the same c.425G&gt;A mutations. </p>

<p>Among 22 patients, the frequency of the GJB1 mutations 
was 4.5% in transmembrane domain 1 (TM1), 4.5% in 
TM2, 22.7% in TM3, 9.1% in TM4, 4.5% in extracellular 
1 (EC1), 27.3% in EC2, 9.1% in intracellular loop, 13.6% 
in the N-terminal domain, and 4.5% in the C-terminal 
domain [Figure 2]. </p>

<p>discussion </p>

<p>This study confirmed that CMT1X was a common form 
of inherited neuropathy in Chinese patients with CMT </p>

<p>Table 2: GJB1 mutations in 22 CMT1X patients from unrelated families in this study </p>

<p>Patient number 
Nucleotide changes 
Amino acid changes 
Domain 
Novel mutation </p>

<p>1 
c.44G&gt;T 
R15L 
N-terminal domain 
No 
2 
c.59T&gt;G 
I20T 
N-terminal domain 
No 
3 
c.62G&gt;A 
G21D 
N-terminal domain 
No 
4 
c.115G&gt;T 
A39S 
TM1 
Yes 
5 
c.194A&gt;G 
Y65C 
EC1 
No 
6 
c.263C&gt;A 
A88D 
TM2 
Yes 
7 
c.379A&gt;T 
I127F 
IC 
Yes 
8 
c.380T&gt;A 
I127N 
IC 
No 
9 
C.403_404insT 
Y135fsX146 
TM3 
No 
10 
c.424C&gt;T 
R142W 
TM3 
No 
11 
c.424C&gt;T 
R142W 
TM3 
No 
12 
c.425G&gt;A 
R142Q 
TM3 
No 
13 
c.425G&gt;A 
R142Q 
TM3 
No 
14 
c.490C&gt;T 
R164W 
EC2 
No 
15 
c.533A&gt;G 
D178G 
EC2 
No 
16 
c.548G&gt;A 
R183H 
EC2 
No 
17 
c.548G&gt;A 
R183H 
EC2 
No 
18 
c.547C&gt;T 
R183C 
EC2 
No 
19 
c.556G&gt;A 
E186K 
EC2 
No 
20 
c.590C&gt;T 
A197V 
TM4 
No 
21 
c.614A&gt;G 
N205S 
TM4 
No 
22 
c.818_819insGGGCT 
L273fs 
C-terminal domain 
Yes 
CMT1X: X-linked Charcot-Marie-Tooth type 1; EC: Extracellular domain; TM: Transmembrane domain; IC: Intracellular loop; GJB1: Gap junction 
beta-1 protein. </p>

<p>Figure 1: Brain magnetic resonance imagings of a male patient with X-linked Charcot-Marie-Tooth type 1 (patient 13) revealed abnormal signals in 
the bilateral centrum semiovale (a-d) and splenium of the corpus callosum (e-h). (a and e): T1 weighted; (b and f): T2 weighted; (c and d): Fluid 
attenuated inversion recovery; and (d and h): Diffusion-weighted magnetic resonance imaging. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ May 5, 2017 ¦ Volume 130 ¦ Issue 9 </p>



<p>because 23.9% of all 92 CMT families were CMT1X. 
This study observed that the proportion of CMT1X in 
Chinese population was greater than other reports. The 
proportion of CMT1X patients for all CMTs was 10.7% in 
Europe (n = 997), 
[21] 15.2% in the USA (n = 527), 
[22] 12.0% in 
Australia (n = 224), 
[23] and 10.9% in Japan (n = 128). 
[24] In a 
study of multi-ethnic Malaysian patients with CMTs (n = 25), 
CMT1X patients were all Chinese and accounted for 24% 
of the total CMT patients. </p>

<p>[25]   In this study, all CMT1X patients showed distal muscle 
weakness predominantly in the lower limbs with a mean 
onset age of 15.6 ± 8.7 years, similar to other reports. </p>

<p>[22]   Most patients began presenting their symptoms in their 
second or third decade. Patients with an earlier onset before 
10 years old or in infancy were rare in the present study and 
other reports. 
[22,26,27] Electrophysiological findings of our 
patients further confirmed that CMT1X is an intermediate 
neuropathy. </p>

<p>Several types of hereditary neuropathies were associated with 
other organ involvement, such as distal motor neuropathy 
with optic atrophy, 
[28] hereditary transthyretin amyloidosis 
with cardiomyopathy, 
[29] and dominant inherited intermediate 
CMT with focal segmental glomerulosclerosis. 
[30] This 
study confirmed that CNS involvement was common in 
Chinese CMT1X. Dysarthria and hemiparesis were the 
main symptoms of our patients, and other similar symptoms 
have been occasionally reported in other countries. </p>

<p>[31-36]   CNS symptoms developed after peripheral neuropathy 
symptoms in some patients in the present study, which has 
also been reported in previous studies. 
[32,36] Brain MRIs 
showed abnormal transient lesions involving bilateral 
white matter in all patients. However, the involvement of 
the corpus callosum which was frequently reported did not 
appear in all cases in the present study. 
[34,37] The isolated 
involvement of the centrum semiovale, internal capsule, and 
the periventricular area appeared in the present study as well 
as in other reports. </p>

<p>[38,39]   We found that the EC2 domain of Cx32 protein was more 
affected in our patients. The EC2 domain was a hotspot 
mutation domain and was affected in 44% of Korean 
patients, 
[40] which was more frequent compared to our 
patients. Mutations in the EC1 and EC2 domains of Cx32 
were in 65% of the patients with Spanish or Portuguese </p>

<p>descent. 
[41] However, EC1 and EC2 were not hotspot 
mutation domains in Japanese 
[24] and Malaysian 
[25] patients. 
We found no relationship between the position of mutations 
and CNS involvement in CMT1X. In the present series, 
mutations of five patients with CNS involvement were 
located in the N-terminal, TM1, and TM3 domains of 
GJB1 gene. The c.425G&gt;A mutation was found in patients 
with pure peripheral neuropathy as well as in patients with 
additional CNS involvement. Four novel mutations in GJB1 
gene were found in our cohort, which expands the spectrum 
of mutations in CMT1X. </p>

<p>In summary, CNS impairment was not rare in Chinese 
CMT1X patients. The CMT1X diagnosis should be considered 
in children with transient CNS impairment with or without any 
signs of peripheral neuropathy. Mutations in the EC2 domain 
of the GJB1 gene were hotspot in Chinese CMT1X patients. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We would like to thank the participating patients and their 
families for their cooperation. We also thank Ms. Jing Liu, 
Ms. Yue-Huan Zuo and Ms. Qiu-Rong Zhang for their 
technical assistance in the preparation of nerve biopsies. </p>

<p>Financial support and sponsorship </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant from the National 
Science Foundation of China (No. 81471185). </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest </p>

<p>There are no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>references </p>



<p>Figure 2: Distribution of the respective amino acid changes on the connexin 32 protein structure identified in 22 patients with X-linked 
Charcot-Marie-Tooth type 1. Different domains are indicated by rectangles with different colors. The positions of novel mutations are indicated in red. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ May 5, 2017 ¦ Volume 130 ¦ Issue 9 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>