<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5300027" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: Investigate and confirm the association between sympathoadrenal 
activation, endotheliopathy and poor outcome in trauma patients. 
Background: The association between sympathoadrenal activation, endo-
theliopathy, and poor outcome in trauma has only been demonstrated in 
smaller patient cohorts and animal models but needs confirmation in a large 
independent patient cohort. 
Methods: Prospective observational study of 424 trauma patients admitted to 
a level 1 Trauma Center. Admission plasma levels of catecholamines (adrenaline, 
noradrenaline) and biomarkers reflecting endothelial damage (syndecan-1, throm-
bomodulin, and sE-selectin) were measured and demography, injury type and 
severity, physiology, treatment, and mortality up till 28 days were recorded. 
Results: Patients had a median ISS of 17 with 72% suffering from blunt 
injury. Adrenaline and noradrenaline correlated with syndecan-1 (r ¼ 0.38, 
P&lt;0.001 and r ¼ 0.23, P&lt;0.001, respectively) but adrenaline was the only 
independent predictor of syndecan-1 by multiple linear regression adjusted for 
age, injury severity score, Glascow Coma Scale, systolic blood pressure, base 
excess, platelet count, hemoglobin, prehospital plasma, and prehospital fluids 
(100 pg/mL higher adrenaline predicted 2.75 ng/mL higher syndecan-1, 
P &lt; 0.001). By Cox analyses adjusted for age, sex, injury severity score, 
Glascow Coma Scale, base excess, platelet count and hemoglobin, adrenaline, 
and syndecan-1 were the only independent predictors of both &lt; 24-hours, 7-
day and 28-day mortality (all P &lt; 0.05). Furthermore, noradrenaline was an 
independent predictor of &lt; 24-hours mortality and thrombomodulin was an 
independent predictor of 7-day and 28-day mortality (all P &lt; 0.05). 
Conclusions: We confirmed that sympathoadrenal activation was strongly 
and independently associated with endothelial glycocalyx and cell damage 
(ie, endotheliopathy) and furthermore that sympathoadrenal activation and 
endotheliopathy were independent predictors of mortality in trauma patients. </p>

<p>24,25 </p>

<p>The aim of the current study was therefore to validate and 
confirm our preliminary findings presented above in a larger, and 
independent, cohort of trauma patients and to more comprehensively 
characterize the endothelium by analyzing also soluble thrombomo-
dulin (sTM), an endothelial cell damage marker, and soluble 
E-selectin (sE-selectin), an endothelial cell activation marker, which 
both have been significantly associated with poor outcome in patients 
with other types of acute critical illness. </p>

<p>26-28 </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Setting and Patients </p>

<p>This prospective observational study was conducted under an 
approved Institutional Review Board (IRB) (Universal Study, HSC-
GEN-12-0059), which included all adult trauma patients (!16 yrs) 
at the highest level of activation at Memorial Hermann Hospital 
Texas Medical Center (MHH-TMC). The criteria for highest acti-
vation include: Glasgow Coma Score 10, heart rate &gt;120 beats 
per minute, systolic blood pressure 90, respiratory rate &lt;10 or &gt; 29 
per minute, intubation, penetrating injury to torso, groin, head or 
neck, amputation proximal to ankle or wrist, paraplegia, quadriple-
gia, uncontrolled external hemorrhage, fracture to pelvis or two or 
more long bone fractures, and receiving blood en route. The study 
took place over 18 months from March 2012 to September 2013. This 
was an opportunistic prospective study that ran parallel to three other 
clinical studies at MHH-TMC; patients admitted to the other studies 
were not included in this analysis. Samples were collected when 
research staff was not directly involved in the other studies and 
available to process the samples. The IRB approval was obtained for 
delayed consent, obtained from the patient or their legally authorized 
representative within 72 hours of admission, or as soon as possible. 
For patients who were discharged or died within 24 hours of admis-
sion, a waiver of consent was obtained. If consent could not 
be obtained, the patient was excluded from the study and their 
blood samples destroyed. The study excluded pregnant women 
and prisoners. 
In the current study, plasma biomarkers from a total of 
561 patients were investigated. Of these, only patients suffering 
from blunt or penetrating injury were included with the requirement 
that data on ISS and adrenaline, noradrenaline, syndecan-1, and 
thrombomodulin were available. This excluded burn injury patients 
(n ¼ 64) and an additional 73 patients [ie, nontrauma (n ¼ 2), missing 
ISS (n ¼ 42), and missing biomarkers (n ¼ 29)]. The excluded 
nonburn injury patients (n ¼ 73) did not differ significantly from 
the 424 included patients with regard to age median 43 years 
(interquartile range, IQR 27-55), sex (73% males), and &lt;24-hours, 
7-day, and 28-day mortality (4%, 14%, and 15%, respectively). </p>

<p>Clinical Data and Blood Samples </p>

<p>Information on baseline demography, clinical, physiologic, 
and laboratory tests were retrospectively collected from patient </p>

<p>records and the institutional trauma registry. The data included 
admission vital signs, blood count test results, pH, base excess 
(BE), conventional plasma based coagulation tests [prothrombin 
time (PT), activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT), inter-
national normalized ratio (INR)], prehospital fluids, 24-hour blood 
transfusions (packed RBCs, plasma, and apheresis platelets), 24-hour 
crystalloid infusions, complications, injury severity score (ISS), and 
patient outcomes (mortality up to 28 days). 
Blood samples were collected in citrated tubes from each 
patient immediately upon hospital admission. Patients from whom 
blood samples could not be obtained were excluded from analysis. 
Upon hospital admission, 20 mL of blood was obtained. Blood was 
transferred into vacutainer tubes containing 3.2% citrate and inverted 
to ensure proper anticoagulation. After spinning, plasma was 
aliquoted and frozen for later analysis. The enzyme linked immu-
nosorbent assay (ELISA) analyses were conducted by trained labora-
tory technicians, according to the manufactures recommendations 
at the Hemostasis Research Laboratory, Section for Transfusion 
Medicine, Capital Region Blood Bank, Copenhagen University 
Hospital, Rigshospitalet, Copenhagen, Denmark. </p>

<p>ELISA </p>

<p>Soluble biomarkers of sympathoadrenal activation (adrena-
line, noradrenaline), endothelial cell activation (sE-selectin), </p>

<p>29,30 </p>

<p>endothelial glycocalyx (syndecan-1), </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>and cell (thrombo-
modulin) 
29-31 damage were measured by commercially available 
immunoassays in EDTA plasma according to the manufactures 
recommendations. Adrenaline and noradrenaline (2-CAT ELISA, 
Labor Diagnostica Nord GmbH &amp; Co. KG, Nordhorn, Germany) 
have lower limit of detection (LLD) 10 pg/mL (adrenaline, normal 
reference &lt;100 pg/mL) and 50 pg/mL (noradrenaline, normal refer-
ence &lt;600 pg/mL), respectively. Syndecan-1 (Diaclone Nordic 
Biosite, Copenhagen, Denmark) has LLD 4.94 ng/mL, soluble 
thrombomodulin (sTM, Nordic Biosite, Copenhagen, Denmark) 
has LLD 0.31 ng/mL, sE-selectin (IBL International GMBH, Ham-
burg, Germany) has LLD 0.3 ng/mL, and sVE-cadherin (R&amp;D 
Systems Europe, Ltd., Abingdon, UK) has LLD 0.113 ng/mL. </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was performed using SAS <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.4</rs> (SAS Insti-
tute Inc., Cary, NC) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">22</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>, New York, NY). 
Simple correlations were investigated by Pearson correlations 
with results displayed as the product-moment correlation coefficient 
Pearson?s r (or r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) and P values. To investigate the independent 
association between sympathoadrenal activation and endothelial 
glycocalyx and cell damage (syndecan-1, thrombomodulin, and 
sE-selectin), univariate and multivariate adjusted linear regression 
analysis were performed, including variables that were either found 
to correlate with or were expected to influence endothelial damage: 
age, ISS, GCS, SBP, BE, platelet count, hemoglobin, prehospital 
plasma, and administered prehospital fluids (Table 2). Results 
are presented as regression coefficients (b) with 95% confidence 
intervals (CI) and P values. 
The predictive value of sympathoadrenal activation (adrena-
line, noradrenaline) and endothelial damage (syndecan-1, thrombo-
modulin) for &lt;24-hour, 7-day, and 28-day mortality was investigated 
by univariate and multivariate adjusted Cox proportional-hazards 
models, the latter after adjusting for age, sex, ISS, GCS, BE, platelet 
count, and hemoglobin. Data are presented as relative hazard ratio 
(HR) with 95% CI, Walds x 
2 and P values. To reveal the influence of 
missing values on the results, multiple imputation analysis (five 
imputed dataset and a merge of these) were conducted and the linear 
regression analysis and Cox proportional-hazards models were 
repeated on imputed data. This did not change the results for any </p>

<p>Johansson et al 
Annals of Surgery Volume 265, Number 3, March 2017 </p>

<p>598 | www.annalsofsurgery.com 
ß 2016 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. </p>

<p>of the analyses and results from the raw data are displayed in the 
manuscript. Data are presented as medians with IQR or as n 
(proportions). P values &lt;0.05 were considered significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>A total of 424 patients were included in the current study 
with a median age of 40 years, 77% were male, median ISS was 
17, and 72% suffered from blunt injury (Table 1). Further details 
on demography, injury severity and type, admission physiology, 
biomarker levels, transfusions, and outcome are displayed in 
Table 1. </p>

<p>Sympathoadrenal Activation and Endothelial 
Damage </p>

<p>To investigate the association between sympathoadrenal acti-
vation and endothelial damage, we investigated simple correlations 
between catecholamine levels and biomarkers reflecting endothelial 
damage followed by linear regression analysis. 
By simple correlations, plasma adrenaline and noradrenaline 
correlated with plasma syndecan-1 (r ¼ 0.38, P &lt; 0.001 and r ¼ 
0.23, P &lt; 0.001, respectively) whereas neither adrenaline nor nor-
adrenaline correlated with thrombomodulin (r ¼ 0.06, P ¼ 0.213 
and r ¼ 0.07, P ¼ 0.149, respectively) or sE-selectin (r ¼ -0.09, 
P ¼ 0.094 and r ¼ -0.01, P ¼ 0.886, respectively). When stratifying 
patients according to injury type, the correlation between plasma 
adrenaline and syndecan-1 levels persisted within in both blunt </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Demography, Injury Type and Severity, Admission Physiology, Biomarker Levels, Transfusions, and Outcome in 424 
Prospectively Enrolled Trauma Patients Admitted to a Level I Trauma Centre in the United States </p>

<p>Unit 
Median (IQR) </p>

<p>Demography 
N 
424 
Age 
yrs 
40 (27-55) 
Sex 
male [n (%)] 
326 (76.9%) 
Race 
W / BL /H /Others 
231 (54%) / 67 (16%) / 103 (24%) / 23 (6%) 
Injury type and severity 
MOI 
Blunt injury 
306 (72%) 
ISS 
score 
17 (9-26) 
Severe TBI (AIS head !3) 
n (%) 
180 (42%) 
GCS 
score 
12 (3-15) 
Transfer 
n (%) 
168 (40%) 
Mode of Transport 
HEL/AMB/Others 
238 (56%) / 168 (40%) / 18 (4%) 
Admission physiology and biochemistry 
SBP (ED) 
mmHg 
124 (106-142) 
BE (ED) 
mEq/L 
À3 (-6-1) 
pH (ED) 
7.32 (7.25-7.37) 
Platelet count (ED) 
10 
9 /L 
220 (180-269) 
Hemoglobin (ED) 
g/dL 
13.1 (11.9-14.4) 
PT 
sec 
14.2 (13.4-15.3) 
INR 
ratio 
1.1 (1-1.2) 
aPTT 
sec 
29.2 (26.3-32.5) 
Biomarkers 
Adrenaline 
pg/mL 
162 (53-364) 
Noradrenaline 
pg/mL 
848 (332-1501) 
Syndecan-1 
ng/mL 
25 (13-60) 
Thrombomodulin 
ng/mL 
5.2 (3.84-7.19) 
sE-selectin 
ng/mL 
39 (23-58) 
Transfusions 
Transfused 
n (%) 
138 (61.1%) 
RBC (prehospital) 
n (%) 
38 (10.4%) 
Plasma (prehospital) 
n (%) 
29 (7.9%) 
Platelets (prehospital) 
n (%) 
0 (0%) 
Crystalloids (prehospital) 
n (%) 
156 (39.6%) 
Crystalloids volume (prehospital) 
mL 
0 (0-200) 
Outcome 
Hospital LOS 
days 
5 (1-15) 
ICU LOS 
days 
1 (0-5) 
Ventilator 
days 
1 (0-3) 
Mortality (&lt;24 hrs) 
n (%) 
19 (4.9%) 
Mortality (7days) 
n (%) 
62 (16.1%) 
Mortality (28 days) 
n (%) 
73 (17.2%) </p>

<p>Data are presented as medians (IQR) or n (%). 
AIS head &gt;3. 
AIS indicates Abbreviated Injury Score; AMB, ambulance; aPTT, activated partial thromboplastin time; BE, base excess; BL, Blacks; ED, emergency department; GCS, Glascow 
Coma Scale; H, Hispanics; HEL, helicopter; ICU, intensive care unit; INR, international normalized ratio; IQR, interquartile range; ISS, injury severity score; LOS, length of stay; MOI, 
mechanism of injury; PH, prehospital; PT, prothrombin time; RBC, red blood cells; SBP, systolic blood pressure; TBI, severe traumatic brain injury; W, Whites. </p>

<p>Annals of Surgery Volume 265, Number 3, March 2017 
Endotheliopathy of Trauma </p>

<p>ß 2016 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. 
www.annalsofsurgery.com | 599 </p>

<p>(r ¼ 0.43, P &lt; 0.001) and penetrating (r ¼ 0.24, P ¼ 0.013) 
injury patients. 
By linear regression analysis, univariate predictors of higher 
syndecan-1 were higher ISS and lower GCS, SBP, BE, platelet count 
and hemoglobin, and prehospital plasma and higher adrenaline but in 
the adjusted model, higher plasma adrenaline was the only inde-
pendent predictor of higher syndecan-1 levels (Table 2). Univariate 
predictors of higher thrombomodulin were higher age and ISS 
and lower BE and hemoglobin (whereas adrenaline was not) 
but only higher age and lower hemoglobin were independent pre-
dictors of higher thrombomodulin (Table 2). We did not perform 
linear regression analysis for sE-selectin as this biomarker neither 
correlated with catecholamines nor were predictive for mortality 
(see below). 
As depicted in Figure 1, the combined highest level plasma 
adrenaline, injury severity, shock, inhospital transfusion, and 28-day 
mortality were associated with excessively increased syndecan-1 
levels (Figure 1A-D). </p>

<p>Outcome </p>

<p>The predictive value of sympathoadrenal activation and endo-
thelial damage for mortality was investigated by univariate and 
adjusted Cox proportional-hazards models. 
In the Cox proportional-hazards analyses, higher age, higher 
ISS, and lower GCS, BE and hemoglobin, and higher adrenaline, 
noradrenaline (P ¼ 0.007, P ¼ 0.137, and P ¼ 0.032, respectively) 
syndecan-1 and thrombomodulin levels were univariate predictors of 
&lt;24-hour, 7-day, and 28-day mortality. The only exceptions were 
that GCS did not predict &lt;24-hours mortality; noradrenaline did not 
predict 7-day mortality and hemoglobin did not predict 7-day and 
28-day mortality (Table 3). Plasma sE-selectin did not predict 
mortality (data not shown). 
In the adjusted models, only adrenaline and syndecan-1 were 
independent biomarker predictors of early &lt;24-hour mortality 
together with age and BE (Table 3). Adrenaline, syndecan-1, 
and thrombomodulin levels were independent predictors of 7-day 
and 28-day mortality together with age (Table 3). In the adjusted 
models, noradrenaline predicted &lt;24-hours mortality (P ¼ 0.048) 
but not 7-day or 28-day mortality (data not shown). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The main findings of the current study were that plasma 
catecholamine levels at admission correlated with circulating levels 
of syndecan-1, an endothelial glycocalyx constituent, and that adre-
naline levels independently predicted higher syndecan-1 levels-that 
is, a surrogate marker of glycocalyx degradation (endotheliopathy of 
trauma). Furthermore, admission adrenaline and syndecan-1 were 
independent predictors of both early and late mortality. 
The finding here of an independent association between 
higher syndecan-1 levels and mortality of trauma patients under-
scores the importance of the state of the endothelium and its related 
constituents for outcome in these critically ill patients, and is in 
alignment with our previous findings in smaller cohorts of trauma 
patients. 
16,17 The results are also in agreement with findings in other 
patient groups facing acute critical illness. In a large cohort of 
patients with varying degrees of sepsis, we found a dose-dependent 
increase in syndecan-1 levels with increased sepsis severity and 
mortality. 
26 Moreover, syndecan-1 was here independently associ-
ated with organ failure, such as hepatic and renal failure. 
26 In patients 
with acute myocardial infarction, being an acute critical illness 
though with minute tissue damage but where cardiogenic shock 
have systemic manifestations, we also found that higher syndecan-1 
levels were independently associated with increased all-cause 
TABLE 2. Univariate and Multivariate Linear Regression Analysis of Variables Associated With Circulating Levels of Biomarkers Reflecting Endothelial Glycocalyx 
and Cell Damage in 424 Trauma Patients Trauma Patients Admitted to a Level I Trauma Centre in the United States </p>

<p>Predictors of Syndecan-1 </p>

<p>Predictors of Thrombomodulin </p>

<p>Univariate </p>

<p>Adjusted (R 
¼ 0.40) </p>

<p>Univariate </p>

<p>Adjusted (R 
¼ 0.29) </p>

<p>b (95%CI) </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>b (95%CI) </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>b (95 CI) </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>b (95%CI) </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>Age </p>

<p>10 yrs 
0.45 (À4.25-5.16) </p>

<p>0.851 
0.34 (À4.01-4.68) </p>

<p>0.879 
0.36 (0.20-0.52) </p>

<p>0.000 
0.32 (0.15-0.5) </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>ISS (ED) </p>

<p>1 point </p>

<p>1.73 (1.06-2.41) </p>

<p>0.000 
0.48 (À0.30-1.25) </p>

<p>0.229 
0.03 (0.00-0.05) </p>

<p>0.019 
0.00 (À0.03-0.03) </p>

<p>0.890 </p>

<p>GCS (ED) </p>

<p>1 point 
À1.92 (À3.49-0.36) </p>

<p>0.016 
0.17 (À1.48-1.83) </p>

<p>0.837 
À0.05 (À0.10-0.01) </p>

<p>0.088 
À0.01 (À0.07-0.06) </p>

<p>0.879 </p>

<p>SBP (ED) </p>

<p>10 mmHg 
À6.23 (À8.93-3.53) </p>

<p>0.000 
À2.69 (À5.51-0.14) </p>

<p>0.062 
À0.03 (À0.13-0.06) </p>

<p>0.507 
À0.01 (À0.12-0.1) </p>

<p>0.857 </p>

<p>BE (ED) </p>

<p>1 mEg/L </p>

<p>À4.24 (À5.9-2.58) </p>

<p>0.000 
À0.91 (À2.73-0.91) </p>

<p>0.325 
À0.07 (À0.13-0.01) </p>

<p>0.029 
À0.03 (À0.11-0.04) </p>

<p>0.375 </p>

<p>Platelet count (ED) </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L 
À1.31 (À2.36-0.26) </p>

<p>0.014 
À0.62 (À1.62-0.37) </p>

<p>0.220 
À0.04 (À0.07-0.00) </p>

<p>0.068 
À0.03 (À0.07-0.01) </p>

<p>0.113 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin (ED) </p>

<p>1 g/dL 
À5.15 (À9.41-0.89) </p>

<p>0.018 
À2.17 (À6.31-1.98) </p>

<p>0.305 
À0.19 (À0.34-0.04) </p>

<p>0.014 
À0.17 (À0.33-0.00) </p>

<p>0.048 </p>

<p>Plasma (prehospital) </p>

<p>1 unit 
42.48 (19.22-65.75) </p>

<p>0.000 
6.02 (À16.78-28.81) </p>

<p>0.604 
0.72 (À0.15-1.59) </p>

<p>0.104 
0.36 (À0.55-1.27) </p>

<p>0.432 </p>

<p>Crystalloids (prehospital) </p>

<p>100 mL 
1.23 (À0.47-2.93) </p>

<p>0.155 
À0.64 (À2.55-1.27) </p>

<p>0.508 
À0.01 (À0.07-0.05) </p>

<p>0.758 
À0.01 (À0.09-0.06) </p>

<p>0.758 </p>

<p>Adrenaline </p>

<p>100 pg/mL </p>

<p>3.68 (2.79-4.57) </p>

<p>0.000 
2.75 (1.54-3.96) </p>

<p>0.000 
0.02 (À0.01-0.06) </p>

<p>0.213 
0.02 (À0.02-0.07) </p>

<p>0.328 </p>

<p>Regression coefficients (b) with 95% CI and P 
(and R, for the multivariate models) are displayed. Predicted change in plasma syndecan-1 (ng/mL) or soluble thrombomodulin (ng/mL) levels associated with one unit increase in: </p>

<p>Age (10 yrs older), ISS 1 point higher, GCS score, SBP 10 mmHg higher, BE 1 mEq/L higher, 1 point higher, platelet count (10 platelets </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L higher), hemoglobin 1 g/dL higher, plasma (prehospital, per 1 unit transfused), </p>

<p>crystalloids volume (prehospital, per 100 mL administered) and plasma adrenaline level (100 pg/mL higher). </p>

<p>BE indicates base excess; CI, confidence intervals; ED, emergency department; GCS, Glascow Coma Scale; ISS, injury severity score; SBP, systolic blood pressure. </p>

<p>Johansson et al 
Annals of Surgery Volume 265, Number 3, March 2017 </p>

<p> 
ß 2016 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. </p>

<p>mortality at 30 days. 
27 From a pathophysiological and mechanistic 
point of view, it could be speculated that the increased shedding of 
glycocalyx results in an increased activation and damage of the 
endothelial cells resulting in a prothrombotic phenotype that leads to 
microvascular thrombosis and ensuing organ failure. 
8 Here, this is 
supported by an independent association of the endothelial cellular 
damage marker sTM and increased 7-day and 28-day mortality. 
Johansen et al 
26 reported in patients with sepsis that the level of 
sTM independently predicted organ failure of the liver and the 
kidneys and multiorgan failure and mortality; and in resuscitated 
out of hospital cardiac arrest patients, sTM was also a strong and 
independent predictor of 30-day mortality. 
28 Moreover, loss of 
endothelial integrity causes capillary leakage with fluid extravasa-
tion, hypotension and shock, and in the current study we found that 
lower systolic blood pressure and BE were strongly associated with 
circulating syndecan-1, supporting this notion. 
Traumatic injury immediately activates the sympathoadrenal 
system with release of large amounts of catecholamines that exert 
widespread dose-dependent effects on metabolism and the vascular 
system. 
32,33 We proposed that patients with excessive trauma 
activation, the sympathoadrenal system becomes maladaptive and 
contribute to organ damage. 
8 Thus, in high concentrations, catechol-
amines directly damage the endothelium resulting in local edema, 
endothelial cell swelling, necrosis, and progressive deendotheliali-
zation. 
34 In the current study, we found that plasma catecholamines 
correlated strongly with plasma syndecan-1 and higher adrenaline 
was the only independent predictor of higher syndecan-1 levels. 
Moreover, the combined highest level plasma adrenaline, injury 
severity, and transfusions (and mortality) was associated with exces-
sively increased syndecan-1, confirming our previous findings 
that sympathoadrenal activation is of critical importance for develop-
ment of traumatic endotheliopathy. Furthermore, adrenaline and </p>

<p>syndecan-1 were independent predictors of early &lt;24-hours 
mortality and late 7-day and 28-day mortality, whereas sTM only 
independently predicted 7-day and 28-day mortality. The finding 
here, of a strong correlation between levels of catecholamines upon 
admission and outcome, is in alignment with findings from other 
patient groups suffering from acute critical illness. In patients 
resuscitated from out-of-hospital cardiac arrest, we reported that 
high plasma adrenaline was associated with increased 7-day, 30-day, 
and 180-day mortality. 
28 Similarly, in patients with acute myocardial 
infarction, stratified into quartiles based on plasma adrenaline levels, 
one quartile higher plasma adrenaline was independently associated 
with both increased 30-day and long-term mortality. 
27 In patients 
with varying degree of infection, including sepsis, we also found that 
catecholamines together with syndecan-1 and sTM independently 
predicted increased 28-day mortality. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>According to our proposed hypothesis, sympathoadrenal acti-
vation is a pivotal driver of the traumatic endotheliopathy, so 
modulation of this response by limiting the catecholamine surge, 
is expected to be beneficial for outcome in these patients. Interest-
ingly, Bukur et al 
35 recently reported that in 663 critically injured 
patients (ISS!25) admitted to the intensive care unit, those 98 
patients receiving beta-blockers upon admission, had significantly 
lower inhospital mortality (11% vs 19%, P ¼ 0.006). Stepwise 
logistic regression identified beta-blocker use as an independent 
protective factor for mortality these patients. Similarly, Cotton 
et al 
36 reported that in patients with severe traumatic brain injury, 
beta-blocker exposure before the trauma was associated with a 
significant reduction in mortality, which was even more impressive, 
considering that the group on beta-blocker therapy was older, more 
severely injured, and had lower predicted survival than the compa-
rators. 
36 Together, these findings support that downstream effects of 
excessive sympathoadrenal activation may also be harmful in </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. 3-D plots displaying associ-
ations between plasma adrenaline, injury 
severity, base excess, transfusions, 
mortality, and plasma levels of endo-
thelial glycocalyx damage in 424 trauma 
patients admitted to a Level I Trauma 
Centre in the United States. Injury 
severity score (ISS) were categorized into 
four groups (ISS &lt;9, ISS 9-15, ISS 16-
25, and ISS &gt;25) and plasma adrenaline 
were categorized into quartiles (Q1 
28 pg/mL (IQR 16-28), Q2 93 pg/mL 
(IQR 77-124), Q3 263 pg/mL (IQR 
217-316), and Q4 884 pg/mL (IQR 
659-1901). Transfusions refers to inhos-
pital transfusions (yes, no). The 3-D plots 
display: (A) ISS, adrenaline quartile, and 
syndecan-1 (ng/mL); (B) Base excess, 
adrenaline quartile, and syndecan-
1 (ng/mL); (C) Transfusions, adrenaline 
quartile, and syndecan-1 (ng/mL); and 
(D) 28-day mortality, adrenaline quar-
tiles, and syndecan-1 (ng/mL). </p>

<p>Annals of Surgery Volume 265, Number 3, March 2017 
Endotheliopathy of Trauma </p>

<p>ß 2016 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. 
www.annalsofsurgery.com | 601 </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Univariate and Multivariate Cox Proportional Hazards Models of Variables Associated With 24-Hours, 7-Day, and 28-Day Mortality in 424 Trauma 
Patients Trauma Patients Admitted to a Level I Trauma Centre in the United States </p>

<p>Covariable </p>

<p>Biomarker: Adrenaline </p>

<p>Biomarker: Syndecan-1 </p>

<p>Biomarker: Thrombomodulin </p>

<p>Univariate </p>

<p>Adjusted </p>

<p>Adjusted </p>

<p>Adjusted </p>

<p>HR (95%CI) </p>

<p>Wald </p>

<p>P 
HR (95%CI) </p>

<p>Wald </p>

<p>P 
HR (95%CI) </p>

<p>Wald </p>

<p>P 
HR (95%CI) </p>

<p>Wald </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>&lt;24-hour </p>

<p>mortality </p>

<p>Biomarker </p>

<p>Univariate </p>

<p>1.06 (1.03-1.09) </p>

<p>19.0 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.06 (1.03-1.09) </p>

<p>18.0 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.09 (0.98-1.21) </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>0.116 </p>

<p>Biomarker </p>

<p>Adjusted </p>

<p>1.06 (1.02-1.09) </p>

<p>10.5 
0.001 1.04 (1.00-1.08) </p>

<p>3.9 </p>

<p>0.047 
1.03 (0.9-1.17) </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.674 </p>

<p>Age 
10 Yrs 1.26 (1.02-1.57) </p>

<p>4.5 
0.034 1.30 (1.02-1.66) </p>

<p>4.5 </p>

<p>0.035 
1.2 (0.95-1.51) </p>

<p>2.3 </p>

<p>0.132 
1.20 (0.95-1.51) </p>

<p>2.3 </p>

<p>0.131 </p>

<p>Sex </p>

<p>Male 0.52 (0.20-1.31) </p>

<p>1.9 
0.163 0.69 (0.23-2.10) </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.519 
0.7 (0.25-1.97) </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.495 
0.78 (0.28-2.19) </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.636 </p>

<p>ISS 
1 Point 1.03 (1.00-1.06) </p>

<p>4.1 
0.042 1.00 (0.96-1.04) </p>

<p>0.0 
0.833 1.00 (0.96-1.04) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.994 
1.01 (0.97-1.05) </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.690 </p>

<p>GCS (ED) 
1 Point 0.92 (0.85-1.01) </p>

<p>3.3 
0.070 0.98 (0.88-1.08) </p>

<p>0.2 
0.627 0.98 (0.88-1.08) </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.673 
0.98 (0.89-1.09) </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.726 </p>

<p>BE (ED) 
1 mEq/L 0.90 (0.84-0.95) </p>

<p>12.7 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
0.93 (0.86-1.01) </p>

<p>2.9 
0.088 0.94 (0.88-1.00) </p>

<p>3.3 </p>

<p>0.069 
0.92 (0.86-0.98) </p>

<p>6.4 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>Platelet count (ED) </p>

<p>10Ã10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L 0.94 (0.88-1.00) </p>

<p>3.6 
0.058 0.97 (0.9-1.04) </p>

<p>0.9 
0.348 0.97 (0.91-1.04) </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.439 
0.96 (0.90-1.03) </p>

<p>1.1 </p>

<p>0.295 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin (ED) 
1 g/dL 0.83 (0.69-1.00) </p>

<p>4.0 
0.046 0.96 (0.76-1.23) </p>

<p>0.1 
0.767 0.96 (0.76-1.22) </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.758 
0.95 (0.75-1.22) </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.710 </p>

<p>7-day mortality 
Biomarker </p>

<p>Univariate </p>

<p>1.06 (1.04-1.08) </p>

<p>34.3 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.04 (1.02-1.06) </p>

<p>12.9 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.11 (1.05-1.17) </p>

<p>13.9 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Biomarker </p>

<p>Adjusted </p>

<p>1.06 (1.03-1.08) </p>

<p>25.1 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.03 (1.00-1.05) </p>

<p>4.9 </p>

<p>0.027 
1.07 (1.00-1.14) </p>

<p>4.3 </p>

<p>0.037 </p>

<p>Age 
10 Yrs 1.48 (1.30-1.67) </p>

<p>37.5 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.46 (1.28-1.67) </p>

<p>30.8 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.44 (1.26-1.64) </p>

<p>28.2 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.4 (1.23-1.61) </p>

<p>24.3 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Sex </p>

<p>Male 0.61 (0.36-1.04) </p>

<p>3.3 
0.070 0.68 (0.38-1.23) </p>

<p>1.6 
0.207 0.83 (0.47-1.47) </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.529 
0.84 (0.47-1.48) </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.539 </p>

<p>ISS 
1 Point 1.03 (1.02-1.05) </p>

<p>15.7 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.00 (0.98-1.02) </p>

<p>0.2 
0.692 1.01 (0.99-1.03) </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>0.158 
1.02 (1.00-1.04) </p>

<p>3.8 </p>

<p>0.051 </p>

<p>GCS (ED) 
1 Point 0.94 (0.90-0.98) </p>

<p>7.5 
0.006 0.96 (0.91-1.01) </p>

<p>2.7 
0.099 0.97 (0.92-1.02) </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.272 
0.97 (0.92-1.03) </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.307 </p>

<p>BE (ED) 
1 mEq/L 0.95 (0.91-1.00) </p>

<p>4.3 
0.038 1.00 (0.94-1.05) </p>

<p>0.0 
0.865 0.97 (0.93-1.02) </p>

<p>1.3 </p>

<p>0.250 
0.97 (0.93-1.02) </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>0.241 </p>

<p>Platelet count (ED) </p>

<p>10Ã10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L 0.97 (0.94-1.01) </p>

<p>2.8 
0.094 0.97 (0.94-1.01) </p>

<p>2.4 
0.124 0.98 (0.95-1.02) </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.312 
0.98 (0.95-1.02) </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>0.339 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin (ED) 
1 g/dL 0.91 (0.82-1.02) </p>

<p>2.5 
0.117 0.98 (0.86-1.11) </p>

<p>0.1 
0.724 1.00 (0.88-1.14) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.976 
1.00 (0.88-1.13) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.996 </p>

<p>28-day mortality 
Biomarker </p>

<p>Univariate </p>

<p>1.05 (1.03-1.07) </p>

<p>36.5 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.04 (1.02-1.06) </p>

<p>14.3 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.10 (1.04-1.15) </p>

<p>12.3 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Biomarker </p>

<p>Adjusted </p>

<p>1.06 (1.04-1.08) </p>

<p>27.5 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.03 (1.00-1.05) </p>

<p>5.2 </p>

<p>0.022 
1.06 (1.00-1.13) </p>

<p>3.9 </p>

<p>0.049 </p>

<p>Age 
10 Yrs 1.41 (1.26-1.59) </p>

<p>34.3 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.41 (1.24-1.60) </p>

<p>28.9 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.39 (1.23-1.58) </p>

<p>27.4 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.36 (1.20-1.54) </p>

<p>22.7 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Sex </p>

<p>Male 0.63 (0.38-1.03) </p>

<p>3.4 
0.066 0.66 (0.38-1.15) </p>

<p>2.2 
0.139 0.83 (0.49-1.43) </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.507 
0.82 (0.48-1.4) </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.460 </p>

<p>ISS 
1 Point 1.03 (1.02-1.05) </p>

<p>15.4 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 
1.00 (0.98-1.02) </p>

<p>0.0 
0.841 1.01 (0.99-1.03) </p>

<p>1.9 </p>

<p>0.171 
1.02 (1.00-1.04) </p>

<p>3.4 </p>

<p>0.065 </p>

<p>GCS (ED) 
1 Point 0.94 (0.90-0.98) </p>

<p>8.5 
0.004 0.96 (0.91-1.00) </p>

<p>3.3 
0.070 0.97 (0.92-1.02) </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>0.203 
0.97 (0.93-1.02) </p>

<p>1.3 </p>

<p>0.250 </p>

<p>BE (ED) 
1 mEq/L 0.96 (0.92-1.01) </p>

<p>2.8 
0.097 1.01 (0.96-1.07) </p>

<p>0.3 
0.583 0.98 (0.94-1.03) </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.442 
0.98 (0.94-1.03) </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.463 </p>

<p>Platelet count (ED) </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L 0.97 (0.94-1) </p>

<p>2.9 
0.090 0.97 (0.94-1.01) </p>

<p>2.7 
0.098 0.98 (0.95-1.01) </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.270 
0.98 (0.95-1.01) </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.284 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin (ED) 
1 g/dL 0.92 (0.83-1.02) </p>

<p>2.3 
0.132 1.00 (0.89-1.13) </p>

<p>0.0 
0.953 1.01 (0.90-1.13) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.862 
1.01 (0.90-1.14) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.830 </p>

<p>Relative hazards (HR) with 95% CI, Wald and P 
values are displayed. The HR (95% CI) are associated with one unit increase in: Age (10 yrs older), Sex (male sex), ISS 1 point higher, GCS 1 point higher, BE 1 mEq/L higher, </p>

<p>platelet count (10 platelets </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L higher), hemoglobin (1 g/dL higher) and either adrenaline (100 pg/mL higher), syndecan-1 (10 ng/mL), and thrombomodulin (1 ng/mL higher). </p>

<p>BE indicates base excess; CI, confidence intervals; ED, emergency department; GCS, Glascow Coma Scale; ISS, injury severity score; SBP, systolic blood pressure. </p>

<p>Johansson et al 
Annals of Surgery Volume 265, Number 3, March 2017 </p>

<p> 
ß 2016 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. </p>

<p>shocked patients </p>

<p>8,37 making it tempting to speculate if low-dose 
beta-blockers may be beneficial in these patients. 
The current study has important limitations inherent to its 
design. Being an observational study precludes from cause and effect 
conclusions but merely points towards significant associations that 
requires further investigation. Moreover, as a single-center study, this 
limits the generalizability of the results, although our findings here 
support previous reports from independent trauma cohorts. </p>

<p>16,18,19 </p>

<p>Furthermore, the selection of biomarkers analyzed in this study does 
not preclude that other markers may also be of importance for the 
development and progression of traumatic endotheliopathy. Unique 
for the current study $10% of the patients received transfusions 
prehospital and the median prehospital crystalloid use was 0. This 
may have influenced the levels of endothelial biomarkers at admis-
sion given that administration of crystalloids has been shown to 
increase the circulating levels of these markers and contribute to 
endothelial damage. 
In conclusion, the finding of the current study supports the 
critical role of endotheliopathy for outcome in severely traumatized 
patients and that sympathoadrenal activation is an important driver of 
this condition. Future randomized controlled trials investigating the 
effect of sympathoadrenal modulation and endothelial protection and 
repair are highly warranted. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank laboratory technicians Karen 
Dyeremose, Marie Helena Stjernkvist, and Mehwish Jubeen Hussain 
for their skilled technical assistance. </p>



<p>Annals of Surgery Volume 265, Number 3, March 2017 
Endotheliopathy of Trauma </p>

<p>ß 2016 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. 
www.annalsofsurgery.com | 603 </p>

</text></tei>