<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5013290" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Mycobacterium tuberculosis is the major pathogen of tuberculosis, which affects approximately one-third of the 
world's population. The 6 kDa early secreted antigenic target (ESAT6) and the 10 kDa culture filtrate protein (CFP10), which are 
secreted by the ESX-1 system in M. tuberculosis, can contribute to mycobacterial virulence. 
Objectives: The aim of this study was to research the effects of M. tuberculosis ESAT6-CFP10 protein on macrophages during a host's 
was first and second exposures to M. tuberculosis. 
Materials and Methods: In this study, the ESAT6 and CFP10 genes were amplified to create a fusion gene (ESAT6-CFP10) and cloned 
into the pET-32a(+) and pEGFP-N1 expression vectors, respectively. The recombinant pET-32a(+)-ESAT6-CFP10 plasmid was trans-
formed into the Escherichia coli Origami strain, and the fusion protein was expressed and confirmed by SDS-PAGE and Western blot 
analysis. The recombinant pEGFP-N1-ESAT6-CFP10 plasmid was transfected into rat alveolar macrophage cells (NR8383). The cell line 
expressing the ESAT6-CFP10 protein was selected with RT-PCR and designated as NR8383-EC. Finally, the effects of the ESAT6-CFP10 
fusion protein on the NR8383 cell line, as well as on the newly constructed NR8383-EC cells, were further assessed. 
Results: The recombinant ESAT6-CFP10 protein was expressed in E. coli and in NR8383 rat alveolar macrophages. This protein affected 
the proliferation and nitric oxide (NO) generation of the NR8383 and NR8383-EC cells. Although NO generation was inhibited in both 
cell lines, proliferation was inhibited in NR8383 while it was increased NR8383-EC. 
Conclusions: The data indicate that ESAT6-CFP10 could support the survival of M. tuberculosis in the host through altering the host 
immune response. It also indicates that the host may gain some level of protection from a second exposure to M. tuberculosis, as 
evidenced by increased proliferation of NR8383-EC. </p>

<p>Keywords: ESAT6-CFP10 Fusion Protein, Macrophages, Cell Proliferation, Immune Protection, Mycobacterium tuberculosis </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>Despite attempts to understand and control Mycobac-</p>

<p>terium tuberculosis for more than a century, this pathogen 
remains a pressing public health threat, infecting more 
than one-third of the world's population and causing al-
most two million deaths yearly (1). Understanding the 
molecular mechanism of the host/pathogen interaction 
is believed to be vital for controlling M. tuberculosis infec-
tions. 
Previous research showed that vaccines constructed 
based on ESAT6 and CFP10 could reduce the M. tubercu-</p>

<p>losis burden in guinea pigs and non-human primates (2, 
3). However, substantial evidence indicates that ESAT6 and 
CFP10 are also virulence factors. The Rv3875 gene that en-
codes ESAT6 is located within the region of difference 1 
(RD1), which is present in all pathogenic mycobacteria, in-
cluding M. tuberculosis and M. bovis, but not in attenuated </p>

<p>M. bovis bacillus Calmette-Gue'rin (BCG) (4). ESAT6 and </p>

<p>CFP10 are secreted as 1:1 dimers through a specific secre-
tion system, ESX-1 (5-7). Studies of M. bovis BCG and RD1-
complemented M. bovis BCG have demonstrated that the 
secretion of ESAT6 and CFP10 are required for the virulence, 
pathogenicity, and growth of M. bovis in macrophages and 
in mice (8, 9). In addition, ESAT6 and CFP10 are produced in 
the lungs of infected mice (10). The mechanisms by which </p>

<p>ESAT6 and CFP10 contribute to virulence are not fully de-
fined, but are believed to be involved in the cytolysis of 
alveolar epithelial cells and macrophages (11), favoring the 
intercellular spread of M. tuberculosis (12). </p>

<p>Nitric oxide (NO) is formed when the guanidine nitro-
gen of L-arginine is oxidized by a family of isoenzymes 
known as NO synthases. The high expression of NO in re-
sponse to cytokines or to pathogen-derived molecules is 
important for host defense against intracellular microor-
ganisms, such as Toxoplasma gondii, Listeria monocytogenes, </p>

<p>Ectromelia virus, and M. tuberculosis (13-15). Recent studies 
showed that exposure of M. tuberculosis to NO at low con-</p>

<p>Copyright © 2016, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in 
noncommercial usages, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Xie X et al. </p>

<p>centrations killed more than 99% of the bacteria in culture 
(16), indicating that NO may induce macrophage apopto-
sis. In a TB-infection murine model, NO played an essential 
role in the mononuclear phagocyte killing of M. tuberculo-</p>

<p>sis (17). </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>Considering that understanding the interactions be-
tween M. tuberculosis and macrophages may be propitious 
for controlling tuberculosis (TB), we discussed the differ-
ent effects of the recombinant ESAT6-CFP10 protein on 
macrophages with the host's first and second exposures to </p>

<p>M. tuberculosis. </p>

<p>3. Materials and Methods </p>

<p>3.1. Expression and Purification of Recombinant ESAT6-CFP10 
Protein </p>

<p>The recombinant fusion ESAT6-CFP10 gene was gener-
ated using overlap PCR. First, the CFP10 and ESAT6 genes 
were amplified from the genome of M. bovis strain C68201 
(provided by Dr. Ding Jiabo, China institute of veterinary 
drug control) with two pairs of gene-specific primers (Ta-
ble 1 (P1 and P2, P3 and P4, respectively)), which was synthe-
sized by BGI Tech (China). The two resultant PCR products 
were gel-purified, then used as templates for the fusion 
gene ESAT6-CFP10, which was created with overlap PCR us-
ing the gene-specific primers P1 and P4. The PCR amplified </p>

<p>ESAT6-CFP10 gene product was then cloned into the BamHI 
and HindIII sites of the pET-32a(+) expression vector. The re-
combinant plasmid was transformed into Escherichia coli 
BL21 (DE3) host cells for histidine (His)-tagged ESAT6-CFP10 
protein expression. 
The expression of the His-tagged ESAT6-CFP10 pro-</p>

<p>tein was induced by the addition of isopropyl β-D-l-</p>

<p>thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG). The expression of the 
His-ESAT6-CFP10 protein was detected by SDS-PAGE with 
Coomassie Blue staining. The recombinant fusion protein 
was purified using a His-bind purification kit (Qiagen, 
Germany) according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
The contaminating endotoxin (lipopolysaccharide) was 
removed from the purified recombinant protein using a 
ProteoSpin 
TM Endotoxin Removal Micro kit (Norgen Biotek </p>

<p>Corporation, Canada) following the standard protocols 
provided by the manufacturer. The purified proteins 
were quantified with the Enhanced BCA Protein Assay Kit 
(Beyotime, China). </p>

<p>3.2. Western Blotting </p>

<p>The His-ESAT6-CFP10 protein was verified by Western 
blotting. In brief, the purified protein was electrophoresed 
on 12% SDS-PAGE, then electrotransferred to nitrocellulose 
membranes. The membranes were incubated at room 
temperature for 2 hours in PBST containing 5% skimmed 
milk to block non-specific membrane binding. This was 
followed by probing the membranes with bovine serum 
raised against M. bovis at room temperature for 2 hours. 
The membranes were then washed 3 times with PBST and 
subsequently incubated at room temperature for 2 hours 
with horse radish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated goat anti-
bovine IgG (Sigma, USA) as the secondary antibody. The 
membranes were then washed again in PBST and signals 
were detected using super signal west pico chemilumi-
nescent substrate (Pierce, USA), according to the manufac-
turer's instructions. </p>

<p>3.3. Construction of Recombinant Eukaryotic Expression Vector 
pEGFP-N1-ESAT6-CFP10 </p>

<p>The ESAT6-CFP10 gene was amplified with gene-specific 
primers (Table 1 (P5 and P6)) synthesized by BGI Tech 
(China), then cloned into the BamHI and HindIII sites of the 
pEGFP-N1 expression vector to generate the recombinant 
eukaryotic plasmid designated as pEGFP-N1-ESAT6-CFP10, 
containing a green fluorescent protein (GFP). The plasmid 
was confirmed by restriction analysis and gene sequenc-
ing. </p>

<p>3.4. Generation of the Rat Alveolar Macrophage Cell Line Ex-
pressing ESAT6-CFP10 Protein </p>

<p>NR8383 rat alveolar macrophages (purchased from Life 
and science research institute of Shanghai) were used in 
these experiments. The NR8383 cells were cultured in com-
plete RPMI-1640 medium (Hyclone, USA) supplemented </p>

<p>with 10% fetal bovine serum (Gibco, USA) and 100 µg/mL </p>

<p>of penicillin and streptomycin. In order to obtain NR8383 
cells expressing ESAT6-CFP10, the NR8383 cells were trans-
fected with the recombinant eukaryotic plasmid pEGFP-N1-</p>

<p>ESAT6-CFP10. One day before transfection, 2.0 × 10 </p>

<p>5 /mL </p>

<p>cells were seeded onto 24-well plates and cultured at 37°C 
in a humidified incubator with 5% CO 2 . The transfections 
were performed with Lipofectamine® 2000 reagent (In-
vitrogen, USA), according to the manufacturer's instruc-
tions. Subsequently, the transfected cells were cultured 
with complete RPMI-1640 medium for 18 hours. The trans-</p>

<p>fected cells were selected using 10 µg/mL of G418 (Gibco, </p>

<p>USA) until a stable NR8383 cell line expressing ESAT6-CFP10 
was obtained. In addition, to further confirm and charac-
terize the stable cell line, green fluorescence signals were 
detected with a fluorescence microscope (Nikon, Japan). </p>

<p> 
Jundishapur J Microbiol. 2016; 9(6):e33264. </p>

<p>Xie X et al. </p>

<p>Table 1. Primer Sequences for ESAT6-CFP10 PCR Amplification </p>

<p>Primer 
Sequence (5'-3') 
Restriction Sites </p>

<p>P1 
ccGGATCCatggcagagatgaagac 
BamH I </p>

<p>P2 
GCTGCCGCCACCGCCGCTTCCGCCACCGCCGCTTCCACCGCCACCgaagcccatttgcgaggacagcgcct 
-</p>

<p>P3 
GGTGGCGGTGGAAGCGGCGGTGGCGGAAGCGGCGGTGGCGGCAGCatgacagagcagcagtggaatttcgcgg 
-</p>

<p>P4 
ccAAGCTTtgcgaacatcccagtga 
Hind III </p>

<p>P5 
ccAAGCTTgccaccatggcagagatgaagac 
Hind III </p>

<p>P6 
ccGGATCCcgtgcgaacatcccagtga 
BamH I </p>

<p>The stable NR8383 cell line expressing ESAT6-CFP10 protein 
was named NR8383-EC. </p>

<p>3.5. Detection of ESAT6-CFP10 mRNA in NR8383-EC Cells by RT-
PCR </p>

<p>The total RNA was extracted from the cells using TRI-
zol® Reagent (Invitrogen, USA). To avoid contamination 
with genomic DNA, the total RNA samples were treated 
with RNase-Free DNase I (Takara, Japan). First-strand cDNA 
was synthesized using M-MLV reverse transcriptase (Invit-
rogen, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
Using the cDNA as a template, the ESAT6-CFP10 mRNA was 
amplified by PCR with gene-specific primers P1 and P4 (Ta-
ble 1). The PCR products were run on a 1.0% (w/v) agarose 
gel and detected with ethidium bromide under UV light. </p>

<p>3.6. Cell Proliferation Assay </p>

<p>The proliferation of NR8383 or NR8383-EC in response 
to recombinant protein His-ESAT6-CFP10 was determined 
with a WST-1 assay using a WST-1 Cell proliferation and cy-
totoxicity assay kit (Beyotime, China). In brief, the NR8383 
or NR8383-EC cells were seeded onto 96-well plates at a den-</p>

<p>sity of 2 × 10 </p>

<p>4 cells/well and stimulated with recombinant </p>

<p>protein His-ESAT6-CFP10 at concentrations of 10 µg/mL. At </p>

<p>the same time, the purified product from the BL21 (DE3) 
(pET-32a) vector was used as a control. The cells were in-
cubated at 37°C with 5% CO 2 for 24 hours, followed by in-</p>

<p>cubation with 10 µL of WST-1 for 1 hour. The absorbance </p>

<p>was determined at 450 nm using an automatic microplate 
reader (Biotech, USA). The relative proliferation rate was </p>

<p>calculated as OD treated cells /OD untreated cells × 100%. The exper-</p>

<p>iments were conducted in triplicate, at least 3 times. </p>

<p>3.7. Measurement of NO Synthesis </p>

<p>The effect of recombinant protein His-ESAT6-CFP10 on 
NO generation by NR8383 and NR8383-EC cells was deter-
mined with the NO assay kit (Beyotime, China) according 
to the manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, the NR8383 and </p>

<p>NR8383-EC cells were seeded onto 96-well plates at a den-</p>

<p>sity of 2 × 10 </p>

<p>4 cells/well, and pre-treated with or with-</p>

<p>out LPS (1 µg/mL) for 4 hours. The cells were then stimu-</p>

<p>lated with or without purified recombinant protein His-</p>

<p>ESAT6-CFP10 (10 µg/mL) for 24 hours. Subsequently, Griess </p>

<p>reagent I and Griess reagent II were added into the cell su-
pernatants, and the optical density was measured at 540 
nm using an automatic microplate reader. Sodium nitrite 
(NaNO 2 ) was used to generate a standard cure. The experi-
ments were conducted in triplicate, at least 3 times. </p>

<p>3.8. Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>All results were presented as mean ± standard devi-</p>

<p>ation (SD) from at least three independent experiments. 
Statistical analyses were performed with a two-tailed Stu-
dent's t test. Significant differences were assigned P values 
of &lt; 0.05, &lt; 0.01, and &lt; 0.001, which were denoted by *, **, 
and ***, respectively. All statistical values were calculated 
with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">19.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs>, USA). </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>4.1. Expression and Purification of Recombinant His-ESAT6-
CFP10 Protein </p>

<p>The ESAT6-CFP10 fusion gene was generated from the 
genome of M. bovis strain c68201 by overlap PCR ampli-
fication. It was then inserted into a pET-32a(+) expres-
sion vector, thereby generating a recombinant expression 
plasmid pET-32a-ESAT6-CFP10. The recombinant expres-
sion plasmid vector was confirmed by gene sequencing. 
The recombinant plasmid was transformed into E. coli BL21 
(DE3) for His-ESAT6-CFP10 production. Expression of the 
His-ESAT6-CFP10 protein was induced with the addition 
of 1 mM IPTG. The expressed proteins were analyzed with 
SDS-PAGE and Western blotting (Figure 1). A Coomassie 
Blue-stained protein band was observed migrating with a 
molecular weight of about 43.7 KDa, which was consistent 
with the expected molecular weight (Figure 1A), indicating 
that the ESAT6-CFP10 gene was successfully expressed in E. </p>

<p>Jundishapur J Microbiol. 2016; 9(6):e33264. </p>

<p>
Xie X et al. </p>

<p>coli BL21(DE3). Western blotting analysis with bovine posi-
tive serum raised against M. bovis further validated the ex-
pression of the recombinant His-ESAT6-CFP10 fusion pro-
tein (Figure 1C). The His-ESAT6-CFP10 protein was purified, 
and SDS-PAGE showed that a high-purity recombinant His-
ESAT6-CFP10 was obtained (Figure 1B). </p>

<p>4.2. Generation of Rat Alveolar Macrophage Cell Line NR8383-
EC Expressing ESAT6-CFP10 Protein </p>

<p>The recombinant eukaryotic expression plasmid 
pEGFP-N1-ESAT6-CFP10 was constructed, then confirmed by 
restriction analysis and gene sequencing. The ESAT6-CFP10 
gene was fused to the N terminal of GFP in the recom-
binant plasmid. For generating the NR8383 rat alveolar 
macrophage cell line expressing the ESAT6-CFP10 protein, 
the NR8383 cells were transfected with pEGFP-N1-ESAT6-
CFP10 using Lipofectamine 2000, and were screened with </p>

<p>10 µg/mL of G418. The green fluorescence signals were de-</p>

<p>tected in NR8383-EC rat alveolar macrophages transfected 
with recombinant pEGFP-N1-ESAT6-CFP10 plasmid, but not 
in the non-transfected NR8383 macrophages (Figure 2A), 
which indirectly showed the expression of the ESAT6-CFP10 
fusion protein in the NR8383-EC cells. The expression of 
ESAT6-CFP10 mRNA in NR8383-EC cells was analyzed by 
RT-PCR. PCR products of predicted sizes for ESAT6-CFP10 
(630 bp) were obtained from the NR8383-EC cells (Figure 
2B). </p>

<p>4.3. Cell Proliferation and NO Production Capacity Assays </p>

<p>The NR8383-EC cell line and NR8383 rat alveolar 
macrophages were stimulated using His-ESAT6-CFP10 pro-
tein and His protein, respectively. WST-1 analysis and Griess 
reactions showed that recombinant protein His-ESAT6-
CFP10 affected the cell proliferation and NO generation, 
respectively. The ESAT6-CFP10 protein inhibited the pro-
liferation of NR8383 rat alveolar macrophages (Figure 
3A), but promoted the proliferation of NR8383-EC cells 
(Figure 3B). However, it also inhibited the NO generation 
of both NR8383 rat alveolar macrophages (Figure 3C) and 
NR8383-EC cells (Figure 3D). </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>Mycobacterium tuberculosis is the primary causative 
agent of human tuberculosis, which remains a major 
global health problem. M. tuberculosis is a typical intracel-
lular pathogen that resides within the host macrophages 
and dendritic cells. Invasion of macrophages by M. tu-</p>

<p>berculosis is a critical step in the establishment of tuber-
culosis (TB) infections. Macrophage apoptosis is a host 
defense mechanism against M. tuberculosis infection (18, </p>

<p>19). On the other hand, M. tuberculosis could survive in 
the host macrophages by inhibiting their apoptosis. Some 
researchers have indicated that avirulent mycobacterial 
species, such as the attenuated M. bovis BCG, cause consid-
erably higher rates of macrophage apoptosis than do the 
virulent M. tuberculosis species (20). Comparative analyses 
of the genomic sequences of M. tuberculosis (21) and M. bo-</p>

<p>vis (22) with that of the attenuated M. bovis BCG strain have 
identified a number of proteins deleted in BCG. These in-
clude the small secreted ESAT6 and CFP10, which are known 
to contribute to microbial virulence. Therefore, the effects 
of ESAT6 and CFP10 on macrophage apoptosis are very im-
portant for studying and understanding the mechanisms 
of tuberculosis. 
In this study, the His-ESAT6-CFP10 fusion protein was 
expressed in an E. coli system, which was confirmed by SDS-
PAGE and Western blot analysis. The SDS-PAGE analysis con-
firmed the successful production of the fusion protein in 
soluble form. This form was thought to be the best con-
dition for the test, because of its complete natural struc-
ture. The Western blot analysis confirmed that the im-
munogenicity of the fusion protein was in good condition. 
These results also indicated that the fusion expression of </p>

<p>ESAT6 and CFP10 has no negative effect on the biological ac-
tivity of these key proteins involved in tuberculosis viru-
lence. 
Obtaining a cell line that expresses the ESAT6-CFP10 fu-
sion protein is very important for the study of the inter-
actions between these proteins and macrophages during </p>

<p>M. tuberculosis infections. In this study, using a eukaryotic 
expression plasmid pEGFP-N1-ESAT6-CFP10, a NR8383-EC rat 
alveolar macrophage cell line that expresses ESAT6-CFP10 
protein was constructed. It was verified by RT-PCR and flu-
orescence assay. The ESAT6-CFP10 gene was amplified from 
the NR8383-EC cDNA by RT-PCR, and fluorescence was de-
tected in the NR8383-EC cells. Hence, these combined re-
sults showed that the NR8383-EC cell line expressing the 
ESAT6-CFP10 protein was constructed successfully. 
To understand the effects of M. tuberculosis on 
macrophages when the host is challenged with M. tu-</p>

<p>berculosis the first and second times, the His-ESAT6-CFP10 
protein was used to stimulate the response of the NR8383 
rat alveolar macrophages and the NR8383-EC macrophage 
cell line that expressed ESAT6-CFP10 protein. The effects 
of recombinant His-ESAT6-CFP10 protein on NR8383 and 
NR8383-EC were then determined by measuring the cell 
proliferation and NO generation. 
The results of NO generation showed that the recom-
binant His-ESAT6-CFP10 protein inhibited the NO gener-
ation of both the NR8383 rat alveolar macrophages and 
the NR8383-EC cell line. However, the cell proliferation 
results showed that the recombinant protein His-ESAT6-</p>

<p> 
Jundishapur J Microbiol. 2016; 9(6):e33264. </p>

<p>Xie X et al. </p>

<p>Figure 1. SDS-PAGE and Western Blotting Analysis of Recombinant His-ESAT6-CFP10 Fusion Protein Expression </p>

<p>A, the SDS-PAGE analysis of the recombinant protein. M, middle-range protein marker; lane 1, BL21(DE3)(pET-32a-ESAT6-CFP10) in the absence of IPTG; lane 2, BL21(DE3)(pET-
32a-ESAT6-CFP10) induced by IPTG; lane 3, BL21(DE3)(pET-32a) induced by IPTG. B, the purified His-ESAT6-CFP10 protein analyzed by SDS-PAGE. M, unstained protein molecular 
weight marker; lanes 1 -2, purified His-ESAT6-CFP10 protein; C, the Western blotting analysis of recombinant protein using bovine positive serum raised against M. bovis; lane 
1, purified recombinant fusion His-ESAT6-CFP10 protein; lane 2, His protein. Arrows indicate the positions of the target proteins. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Identification of the NR8383-EC Cell Line Expressing the ESAT6-CFP10 Pro-
tein With Fluorescence and RT-PCR </p>

<p>The ESAT6-CFP10 was fused to the N terminal of GFP of the pEGFP-N1 expression vec-
tor. A, the expression of the fusion protein was detected with fluorescence signals, 
using a fluorescence microscope; 1, NR8383 transfected with the recombinant eu-
karyotic plasmid pEGFP-N1-ESAT6-CFP10; 2, NR8383 non-transfected with the recom-
binant eukaryotic plasmid pEGFP-N1-ESAT6-CFP10; B, the mRNA level of ESAT6-CFP10 
was analyzed with RT-PCR using total RNA extracted from cells; lane 1, the gene 
amplified from the NR8383-EC cells; lane 2, the gene amplified from NR8383 cells 
transfected with pEGFP-N1 plasmid; Lane 3, the gene amplified from non-transfected 
NR8383 rat alveolar macrophages. </p>

<p>CFP10 inhibited the proliferation of NR8383 rat alveo-
lar macrophages, but promoted the proliferation of the 
NR8383-EC cell line. Therefore, these results indicated that </p>

<p>M. tuberculosis could escape the host immune defense by 
continuous inhibition of NO generation, but it could pro-
mote or inhibit the apoptosis of macrophages in order to 
regulate the number of cells by some responses or interac-
tions (23) when the host is first infected by M. tuberculosis 
or when it again comes into contact M. tuberculosis. This 
was evidenced by differences in proliferation between the 
NR8383-EC cell line, which carried the ESAT6-CFP10 fusion 
protein, and NR8383, which did not. These findings lead us 
to believe that significantly different responses protect the 
host from M. tuberculosis infections between the first and 
second M. tuberculosis exposures. 
In conclusion, the NR8383-EC cell line and recombinant 
His-ESAT6-CFP10 protein were successfully constructed. 
The His-ESAT6-CFP10 protein stimulation of the NR8383-
EC cell line and of the NR8383 rat alveolar macrophages 
showed different effects. These results provide novel valu-
able information and new ideas for studying the mecha-
nisms of infection and the diagnostic methods for tuber-
culosis. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We would like to thank Ding Jiabo from the China in-
stitute of veterinary drug control, Beijing, China, for provi-
sion of heat-killed Mycobacterium bovine isolates. </p>

<p>Jundishapur J Microbiol. 2016; 9(6):e33264. </p>

<p>
Xie X et al. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Cell Proliferation and NO Production Capacity Assays </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>100 ± 2.14 
91.42 ± 0.29 </p>

<p>68.40 ± 0.38 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>his </p>

<p>his-ESAT6-CFP10 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>210 </p>

<p>100 ± 1.64 </p>

<p>165 ± 2.56 </p>

<p>190 ± 3.05 </p>

<p>his-ESAT6-CFP10 </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>Tranfection </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** 
** </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>12.30 ± 0.97 
8.96 ± 0.67 </p>

<p>24.34 ± 0.39 23.32 ± 0.59 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>LPS </p>

<p>his-ESAT6-CFP10 </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>-
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>12.93 ± 1.35 </p>

<p>8.96 ± 1.39 </p>

<p>25.8 ± 1.68 </p>

<p>20.63 ± 0.81 
* </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>LPS </p>

<p>his-ESAT6-CFP10 </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>-
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
-
-</p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>F 
D </p>

<p>Relative Proliferation Rate, % 
Relative Proliferation Rate, % </p>

<p>Nitric Oxide Concentration, µM 
Nitric Oxide Concentration, µM </p>

<p>A, the proliferation of NR8383 or B, NR8383-EC in response to recombinant protein His-ESAT6-CFP10 was determined by WST-1 assay. The cells were stimulated with recombinant </p>

<p>protein His-ESAT6-CFP10 at concentrations of 10 µg/mL, then proliferation was determined. At the same time, the purified product from BL21(DE3) (pET-32a) was used as a </p>

<p>control. The NO generation effect of recombinant protein His-ESAT6-CFP10 on C, NR8383 or D, NR8383-EC was determined by the NO assay kit, according to the manufacturer's </p>

<p>instructions. The cells were pre-treated with or without LPS (1 µg/mL) for 4 hours, and were then stimulated with or without purified recombinant protein His-ESAT6-CFP10 
(10 µg/mL) for 24 hours. NO generation was then determined. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, ***P &lt; 0.001. The experiment was repeated three times. </p>

<p>Footnotes </p>

<p>Authors' Contributions: The core idea of this work came 
from Hongjun Yang. Xiaoli Xie and Liang Zhang were ad-
visors on the project and contributed to the analysis of 
the data. Meng Han collected the data, cultured the cells, 
and performed the molecular tests, and also wrote the 
manuscript in collaboration with Xiaoli Xie. Laixing Liu 
and Zuye Gu assisted in the molecular tests. Mei Yang as-
sisted in culturing the cells. </p>

<p>Funding/Support: This work was financed by the 
natural science foundation of Shandong province 
(NO.ZR2015YL069) and the natural high technol-
ogy research and development program of China 
(NO.2012AA101302-6). </p>



<p> 
Jundishapur J Microbiol. 2016; 9(6):e33264. </p>

<p>Xie X et al. </p>



<p>Jundishapur J Microbiol. 2016; 9(6):e33264. </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>