<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5108428" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>STUDY OBJECTIVE To examine the effect of increased gastric pH on exposure to evacetrapib, a choles-
teryl ester transfer protein inhibitor evaluated for the treatment of atherosclerotic heart disease. 
DESIGN Open-label, two-treatment, two-period, fixed-sequence crossover study. 
SETTING Clinical research unit. 
SUBJECTS Thirty-four healthy subjects. 
INTERVENTION In period 1, subjects received a single oral dose of evacetrapib 130 mg on day 1, followed 
by 7 days of analysis for evacetrapib plasma concentrations. In period 2, subjects received a once/day 
oral dose of omeprazole 40 mg on days 8-20, with a single oral dose of evacetrapib 130 mg adminis-
tered 2 hours after the omeprazole dose on day 14, followed by 7 days of pharmacokinetic sampling. 
Subjects were discharged on day 21 and returned for a follow-up visit at least 14 days after the last dose 
of evacetrapib in period 2. Gastric pH was measured before subjects received each evacetrapib dose. 
MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS Noncompartmental pharmacokinetic parameters were estimated from 
plasma concentration-time data and compared between periods 1 and 2. Geometric mean ratios 
with 90% confidence intervals (CIs) were reported. Safety and tolerability were also assessed. The 
mean age of the 34 subjects was 40.9 years; mean body mass index was 27.2 kg/m 
2 . Omeprazole 
treatment increased mean gastric pH across all subjects by 2.80 and increased evacetrapib area 
under the concentration versus time curve from time zero extrapolated to infinity (AUC 0-∞ ) and 
maximum observed drug concentration (C max ) by 15% (90% CI À2 to 35) and 30% (90% CI 3-63), 
respectively. For both parameters, the upper bound of the 90% CI of the ratio of geometric least-
squares means exceeded 1.25 but was less than 2, indicating a weak interaction. To assess the effect 
of gastric pH on subjects who responded best to omeprazole treatment, the analyses were repeated 
to include only the 22 subjects whose predose gastric pH was 3.0 or lower in period 1 and 4.0 or 
higher in period 2. In this subpopulation, mean gastric pH increased by 4.15 during omeprazole 
treatment, and evacetrapib AUC 0-∞ and C max increased by 22% (90% CI 4-42) and 35% (90% CI 
1-80), respectively. Despite the small mathematical differences between the analyses, the overall 
effect in both was a minimal increase in evacetrapib exposure. Of 35 adverse events reported during 
the study, 4 (11.4%) were considered to be treatment-related, and most were mild in severity. 
CONCLUSION The impact of increased gastric pH on evacetrapib pharmacokinetics would not be expected 
to be clinically relevant. The magnitude of change in pH did not affect the degree of the interaction. 
Epidemiologic evidence indicates that high-den-
sity lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C) levels are 
inversely correlated with cardiovascular disease 
risk, 
2, 3 suggesting that agents that raise HDL-C 
levels may offer important benefits in treating 
cardiovascular disease. 
Compounds that inhibit cholesteryl ester trans-
fer protein (CETP) can increase HDL-C levels 
and may provide favorable benefits toward lower-
ing cardiovascular risk. 
4-6 Evacetrapib, a potent 
and selective inhibitor of CETP, demonstrated its 
ability to increase HDL-C and decrease LDL-C 
levels and was hypothesized to reduce the risk of 
major adverse cardiovascular events in patients 
with high-risk vascular disease. 
7-10 On October 
12, 2015, however, Eli Lilly and Company 
announced the termination of its phase III evace-
trapib trial due to insufficient efficacy following a 
recommendation by the independent data moni-
toring committee (https://investor.lilly.com/re-
leasedetail.cfm?relea seid=936130). 
The intended patient population for evace-
trapib potentially included those taking proton 
pump inhibitors, such as omeprazole, for the 
treatment of gastrointestinal ulcers and gastric 
reflux. Omeprazole inhibits gastric acid secretion 
and thereby increases the pH of the gastric envi-
ronment, which may alter the absorption of 
drugs with pH-dependent solubility. 
11 Omepra-
zole is a potent inhibitor of cytochrome P450 
(CYP) 2C19, but there is no drug-drug interac-
tion risk with evacetrapib because its clearance 
is mediated by CYP3A and CYP2C8, and not 
CYP2C19. 
12 Oral dosing with omeprazole once/ 
day achieves maximum suppression of gastric 
acid secretion within~4 days of treatment. After 
dosing with omeprazole 40 mg once/day for 
7 days, median 24-hour gastric pH was 
increased in healthy subjects from 1.68 to 4.93, 
with the largest increases in gastric pH occurring 
2-10 hours after the omeprazole dose. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>The current study examined the impact of 
increased gastric pH on systemic exposure to 
evacetrapib, whose solubility is pH dependent. 
The results of gastric pH evaluations and the 
pharmacokinetics, safety, and tolerability of a 
single oral dose of evacetrapib 130 mg given 
alone and with omeprazole are presented. The 
treatment of healthy subjects with omeprazole 
likened the gastric environment to that of condi-
tions similar to others with achlorhydria 
(Table S1). Although evacetrapib development 
has been discontinued, the methods and analyses 
described in this study may be relevant to 
researchers wanting to conduct gastric pH-drug 
interaction studies with other drug candidates. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study Design and Treatment Protocol </p>

<p>This was an open-label, two-treatment, two-
period, fixed-sequence crossover study evaluat-
ing the effect of increased gastric pH on the 
pharmacokinetics of evacetrapib in healthy 
human subjects. Each subject participated in a 
screening visit, two dosing periods, and a post-
study follow-up visit. Subjects were admitted to 
the clinical research unit on day 1 and remained 
resident until completion of period 2. In period 
1, subjects received a single oral dose of evace-
trapib 130 mg on day 1 followed by 7 days of 
pharmacokinetic sampling. In period 2, an oral 
dose of omeprazole 40 mg (Kremers Urban 
Pharmaceuticals, Inc., Princeton, NJ) was admin-
istered once/day on days 8-20, with a single oral 
dose of evacetrapib 130 mg administered 
2 hours after the omeprazole dose on day 14. 
Omeprazole 20 mg/day achieves maximal acid 
suppression within~4 days, 
11 and the effect of a 
40-mg dose was expected to follow a similar 
time course. Therefore, the second dose of </p>

<p>Declaration of Conflicting Interests: The authors declared a potential conflict of interest (e.g., a financial relationship with 
the commercial organizations or products discussed in this article) as follows: David Small, Ellen Cannady, Ming-Dauh Wang, 
Delyn Downs, and Jeffrey Suico are employees of, and may hold stock in, Eli Lilly and Company. Jane Royalty and Christine 
Hale are employees of Covance Inc. 
Funding: The authors received financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article from Eli 
Lilly and Company. 
*Address for correspondence: David S. Small, Lilly Research Laboratories, Eli Lilly and Company, Lilly Corporate Center, 
Indianapolis, IN 46285; e-mail: dsmall@lilly.com. 
The copyright line for this article was changed on 29 July 2016 after original online publication. 
Ó 2016 Eli Lilly and Company. Pharmacotherapy published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of Pharmacotherapy Publica-
tions, Inc. 
This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License, which permits 
use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not used for 
commercial purposes. </p>

<p> 
PHARMACOTHERAPY Volume 36, Number 7, 2016 </p>

<p>evacetrapib was administered 6 days after the 
first omeprazole dose to ensure that subjects had 
attained maximal suppression of gastric acid 
secretion. Subjects were discharged on day 21 
and returned for a follow-up visit at least 
14 days after the last dose of evacetrapib in 
period 2. </p>

<p>Subjects </p>

<p>Eligible subjects included healthy men and 
women not of childbearing potential, 18-
65 years of age, with a body mass index of 
18.0-32.0 kg/m 
2 . Use of over-the-counter or 
prescription medication was prohibited within 
14 days prior to dosing and during the study, 
with the exception of occasional acetaminophen 
use. 
All subjects provided written informed con-
sent before beginning any study procedures. The 
study protocol was approved by the institutional 
review board (Schulman Associates Institutional 
Review Board, Inc., Cincinnati, OH) and was 
conducted in accordance with regulatory guid-
ances and good clinical practice guidelines. </p>

<p>Gastric pH Evaluations </p>

<p>The ZepHr Impedance/pH Reflux Monitoring 
System with AirFLOW Sphincter Locator (Sand-
hill Scientific, Highlands Ranch, CO) and corre-
sponding ComforTec PLUS single-use infused 
2.3-mm pH probes (Sandhill Scientific) were 
used to test the pH of the gastric environment. 
The ZepHr recorder was set up and calibrated 
according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
Then the recorder and probe were connected to 
the AirFLOW Sphincter Locator, and the sphinc-
ter locator was pumped up to~7.5 psi. The 
nasogastric probe was then inserted to~60 cm 
so that the probe's infusion port was below the 
lower esophageal sphincter (LES) and in the 
stomach. Pressure on the recorder screen was 
set to zero. The probe was then pulled back in 
1-cm increments while observing the pressure 
and pH on the recorder screen. As the locator 
infusion port entered the LES, there would be 
an increase in pressure to a two-digit positive 
number. After identifying the high pressure of 
the LES, the probe was advanced~5 cm so the 
pH sensor was positioned~10 cm below the 
LES. The probe was taped in position, and pH 
was recorded for~15 minutes prior to adminis-
tration of evacetrapib on days 1 and 14. </p>

<p>Bioanalysis and Pharmacokinetic Assessments </p>

<p>Blood samples were collected for pharmacoki-
netic analysis of evacetrapib before and 1, 2, 3, 4, 
6, 8, 12, 24, 36, 48, 72, 96, 120, 144, and 
168 hours after the evacetrapib doses were given 
on days 1 and 14. Plasma samples were analyzed 
for evacetrapib by using a validated liquid chro-
matography with the tandem mass spectrometric 
method at Covance Laboratories Inc. (Madison, 
WI). The lower and upper limits of quantification 
were 1.00 and 1000 ng/ml, respectively. The 
interassay accuracy, defined as the closeness of 
the mean value obtained by the method to the 
actual nominal value of the analyte and expressed 
as a percent, ranged from À2.9 to 1.5% during 
validation. The interassay precision, defined as 
the closeness of repeated individual measures of 
the analyte and expressed as the coefficient of 
variation, ranged from 2.9 to 6.4% during valida-
tion. Both precision and accuracy measures met 
the predefined acceptance criteria consistent with 
regulatory guidances, 
14, 15 thus confirming the 
robustness of the bioanalytical assay. 
The potential for omeprazole to interfere with 
evacetrapib in the bioanalytical assay was 
assessed at an omeprazole concentration of 
650 ng/ml. There was no significant interference 
in the chromatographic regions of interest for 
evacetrapib, indicating that the evacetrapib 
method had acceptable selectivity in the pres-
ence of omeprazole. 
Pharmacokinetic parameter estimates for evace-
trapib were calculated by using standard noncom-
partmental methods of analysis using <rs id="software-0" type="software">WinNonlin</rs> 
software, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v.6.2.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Pharsight Corp.</rs>., Mountain 
View, CA). The primary parameters for analysis 
were area under the concentration versus time 
curve (AUC) from time zero to the last time point 
with a measurable concentration (AUC 0-tlast ); 
AUC from time zero extrapolated to infinity 
(AUC 0-∞ ); maximum observed drug concentra-
tion (C max ); and the time to reach maximum con-
centration (T max ). The AUC was calculated by 
using a combination of the linear and logarithmic 
trapezoidal methods (linear-log trapezoidal rule). 
The linear trapezoidal method was applied up to 
T max , and then the logarithmic trapezoidal 
method was used after T max . The minimum 
requirement for the calculation of AUC was the 
inclusion of at least three consecutive plasma con-
centrations above the lower level of quantitation, 
with at least one of these concentrations following 
C max . The C max and T max were reported from 
visual inspection of the concentration versus time </p>

<p>GASTRIC PH AND EVACETRAPIB PHARMACOKINETICS Small et al </p>

<p>
curve. The apparent terminal elimination half-life 
(t 1/2 ), apparent clearance, and apparent volume of 
distribution during the terminal phase were also 
estimated. The t 1/2 was calculated, when appropri-
ate, based on the apparent terminal log-linear por-
tion of the concentration-time curve. The start of 
the terminal elimination phase for each subject 
was determined by visual inspection and generally 
was the first point at which there was no system-
atic deviation from the log-linear decline in 
plasma concentrations. The t 1/2 was estimated 
only when at least three concentrations were 
available for its calculation in the terminal phase. 
Descriptive statistics, including geometric mean 
and coefficient of variation (CV), were calculated. </p>

<p>Safety Assessments </p>

<p>Safety was assessed by monitoring treatment-
emergent adverse events, physical examinations, 
vital sign measurements, 12-lead electrocardio-
grams (ECGs), and clinical laboratory evaluations. 
Clinical laboratory safety parameters included 
hematology, urinalysis, and biochemistry panels. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Sample Size </p>

<p>The sample size was based on a calculation of 
precision of the estimated AUC 0-∞ . Using an 
intrasubject variability estimate of 36.5% for 
evacetrapib (ClinicalTrials.gov identifier NCT 
01903434; data on file), 
16 a sample size of 30 
subjects completing the trial provided~90% cov-
erage probability that the half-width of the 90% 
CI for the ratio of geometric mean AUC 0-∞ was 
within 0.18 in the log scale, which corresponded 
to~20% in the natural scale. </p>

<p>Pharmacokinetic Analysis </p>

<p>The effects of gastric pH on evacetrapib 
AUC 0-∞ and C max were analyzed by using a 
mixed-effects analysis of variance model. Param-
eters were log-transformed prior to analysis. The 
model included a fixed effect for treatment 
(evacetrapib alone or evacetrapib + omeprazole) 
and a random effect for subject. The ratios of 
geometric least-squares (LS) means for evace-
trapib + omeprazole (test treatment) compared 
with evacetrapib alone (reference treatment) 
were calculated along with the 90% CIs of the 
ratios. The ratios of geometric LS means were 
considered statistically significant if the 90% CIs </p>

<p>did not contain 1. The T max for evacetrapib was 
analyzed by using SAS procedure <rs type="software">PROC UNI-
VARIATE</rs> software. The median of differences 
and~90% CI for the median of differences be-
tween evacetrapib + omeprazole and evacetrapib 
alone were calculated. The difference in T max 
was considered statistically significant if the 90% 
CI did not contain zero. 
These analyses were repeated for subjects 
whose predose gastric pH was 3.0 or lower on 
day 1 and 4.0 or higher on day 14. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Study Population </p>

<p>Thirty-four healthy subjects (30 male and 4 
female), aged 22-61 years with a mean body 
mass index of 27.2 kg/m 
2 , entered the study and 
received at least one dose of evacetrapib. The 
enrolled subjects were white (19 subjects), black 
or African American (14 subjects), and Asian (1 
subject). Thirty-two subjects completed the 
study; two subjects did not complete the study 
for the following reasons: one subject did not 
attend the follow-up visit after receiving all 
scheduled doses of evacetrapib and omeprazole, 
and one subject was discontinued due to an 
adverse event of hematuria that was considered 
unrelated to evacetrapib. </p>

<p>Gastric pH Measurements </p>

<p>Gastric pH was measured prior to evacetrapib 
administration alone on day 1 and on day 14 
after omeprazole administration but before 
evacetrapib administration. Mean gastric pH for 
all subjects had increased by 2.80 (range À2.1 
to 5.8) after 7 days of omeprazole treatment 
(Table 1). A subpopulation of 22 subjects had 
predose gastric pH of 3.0 or lower on day 1 and 
4.0 or higher on day 14; mean gastric pH in this 
subpopulation had increased by 4.15 (range 1.9-
5.8) after omeprazole treatment. </p>

<p>Pharmacokinetics </p>

<p>Figure 1A shows the mean plasma concentra-
tion-time profiles of evacetrapib given alone (day 
1) and with omeprazole 40 mg once/day (day 
14). Predose concentrations of evacetrapib were 
quantifiable for 14 of the 33 subjects in period 2 
and were likely due to carry over from period 1. 
These concentrations ranged from 0.06 to 1.22% 
of C max and were included in the analysis. Given </p>

<p> 
PHARMACOTHERAPY Volume 36, Number 7, 2016 </p>

<p>the magnitude of these predose concentrations 
relative to postdose concentrations, their effect 
on AUC estimates was considered negligible. </p>

<p>Table 2 summarizes the geometric mean phar-
macokinetic parameter estimates. Omeprazole 
treatment increased the geometric LS mean </p>

<p>Table 1. Gastric pH Measurements Prior to a Single Dose of Evacetrapib 130 mg Administered Alone or with Omeprazole 
40 mg Once/Day </p>

<p>Gastric pH before evacetrapib 
130 mg administered alone on day 1 </p>

<p>Gastric pH before evacetrapib 
130 mg administered with omeprazole 
40 mg on day 14 </p>

<p>All subjects 
n=34 
n=33 
Mean AE SD 
2.01 AE 0.98 
4.81 AE 2.01 
Range 
1.2-6.1 
1.3-7.4 
Subjects with pH ≤ 3.0 
on day 1 and ≥ 4.0 on day 14 </p>

<p>n=22 
n=22 </p>

<p>Mean AE SD 
1.80 AE 0.45 
5.95 AE 0.91 
Range 
1.2-3.0 
4.2-7.4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>Time postdose (h) </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 
72 
96 
120 
144 
168 </p>

<p>Linear scale </p>

<p>Evacetrapib Plasma 
Concentration (ng/mL) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>Time postdose (h) </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 
72 
96 
120 
144 
168 </p>

<p>Linear scale </p>

<p>Evacetrapib Plasma 
Concentration (ng/mL) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>Time postdose (h) </p>

<p>0 
4 
8 
1 2 
1 6 
2 0 
2 4 
Evacetrapib Plasma 
Concentration (ng/mL) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>Time postdose (h) </p>

<p>0 
4 
8 
1 2 
1 6 
2 0 
2 4 
Evacetrapib Plasma 
Concentration (ng/mL) </p>

<p>130 mg evacetrapib 
130 mg evacetrapib + 40 mg omeprazole </p>

<p>Figure 1. Arithmetic mean AE SD plasma concentration versus time profiles of evacetrapib following evacetrapib 130 mg given 
without omeprazole on day 1 (filled circles) and with omeprazole 40 mg once/day on day 14 (open circles). Panel A includes 
data from all subjects. Panel B includes data only from subjects whose predose gastric pH was 3.0 or lower on day 1 and 4.0 or 
higher on day 14. Insets show the data for 0-24 hours after evacetrapib dosing for better visualization of that interval. </p>

<p>GASTRIC PH AND EVACETRAPIB PHARMACOKINETICS Small et al </p>

<p>
AUC 0-∞ and C max of evacetrapib by 15% (90% 
CI À2 to 35) and 30% (90% CI 3-63), respec-
tively (Table 3). The between-subject CV for 
AUC 0-∞ was 40.9% (90% CI 30.8-63.3) and for 
C max was 49.7% (90% CI 35.6-88.5). There was 
no statistically significant difference in T max 
between the treatments. 
The statistical analysis was repeated to include 
only the 22 subjects whose predose gastric pH 
was 3.0 or lower on day 1 and 4.0 or higher on 
day 14. The purpose of analyzing this subgroup 
was to assess the effect of increased gastric pH 
on subjects who responded best to omeprazole 
treatment, which represents a so-called worst 
case scenario for the effect of increased gastric 
pH on evacetrapib pharmacokinetics. Figure 1B 
shows the mean plasma concentration-time pro-
files for evacetrapib following evacetrapib 
130 mg with and without omeprazole in this 
subgroup. Table 2 summarizes the geometric 
mean pharmacokinetic parameter estimates for 
this subgroup. In this subgroup, omeprazole 
treatment increased the geometric LS mean 
AUC 0-∞ and C max of evacetrapib by 22% (90% 
CI 4-42) and 35% (90% CI 1-80), respectively 
(Table 3). The subgroup's between-subject CV 
for AUC 0-∞ was 50.7% (90% CI 38.2-78.8) and 
for C max was 61.7% (90% CI 43.1-120). As in 
the analysis including all subjects, for both 
parameters the upper bound of the 90% CI of 
the ratio of geometric LS means exceeded 1.25 
but was less than 2, and there was no statisti-
cally significant difference in T max between the 
treatments. </p>

<p>Safety and Tolerability </p>

<p>The number of subjects reporting treatment-
emergent adverse events was generally low across 
the treatment periods and was similar when 
evacetrapib was administered alone and with 
omeprazole. Thirty-five events were reported dur-
ing the study, four (11.4%) of which were con-
sidered by the investigator to be treatment 
related. Following evacetrapib alone, two subjects 
each reported a headache, and one subject expe-
rienced a mild tremor. During administration of 
omeprazole alone, one subject reported constipa-
tion. Most events were mild in severity, except 
for three moderate events of furuncle, headache, 
and hematuria that were considered by the inves-
tigator to be related to other medical conditions. 
There were no clinically meaningful findings in 
safety assessments from clinical laboratory param-
eters, vital sign measurements, or 12-lead safety 
ECGs for individual subjects during the study 
that were considered related to the study drugs. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study determined the effect of increased 
gastric pH on the pharmacokinetics of evace-
trapib in healthy subjects. Seven doses of 
omeprazole 40 mg once/day increased mean gas-
tric pH values across all subjects by 2.80 and 
increased the geometric LS mean AUC 0-∞ and 
C max of evacetrapib by 15% and 30%, respec-
tively. Given the range of the 90% CIs for 
AUC 0-∞ and C max , the magnitudes of these 
increases 
are 
comparable. 
For 
both </p>

<p>Table 2. Pharmacokinetic Parameter Estimates Following a Single Dose of Evacetrapib 130 mg Alone or with Omeprazole 
40 mg Once/Day </p>

<p>Parameter </p>

<p>Geometric mean (CV%) </p>

<p>All subjects </p>

<p>Subjects with predose gastric pH ≤ 3.0 on 
day 1 and ≥ 4.0 on day 14 </p>

<p>Evacetrapib 130 mg 
alone (n=34) </p>

<p>Evacetrapib 
130 mg + omeprazole 
40 mg (n=33) </p>

<p>Evacetrapib 130 mg 
alone (n=22) </p>

<p>Evacetrapib 
130 mg + omeprazole 
40 mg (n=22) </p>

<p>AUC 0-tlast , ng9hr/ml 
11,700 (49) 
13,000 (63) 
11,200 (52) 
13,400 (63) 
AUC 0-∞ , ng9hr/ml 
12,400 (52) 
14,100 (66) 
12,000 (55) 
14,600 (67) 
%AUC tlast-∞, % 
4.65 (95) 
6.06 (95) 
4.87 (94) 
6.37 (82) 
C max, ng/ml 
748 (79) 
959 (88) 
682 (89) 
923 (98) 
T max </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, hrs 
3.00 (2.00-6.00) 
3.00 (1.00-6.00) 
3.00 (2.00-6.00) 
2.54 (1.00-6.00) 
t 1/2 
b , hrs 
44.0 (26.9-80.6) 
49.8 (27.1-87.6) 
44.4 (26.9-80.6) 
50.3 (27.6-87.6) 
CL/F, L/hr 
10.5 (52) 
9.20 (66) 
10.9 (55) 
8.92 (67) 
V z /F, L 
664 (45) 
661 (49) 
696 (44) 
647 (46) </p>

<p>AUC = area under the concentration versus time curve; AUC 0-∞ = AUC from time zero extrapolated to infinity; AUC 0-tlast = AUC from time 
zero to the last time point with a measurable plasma concentration; %AUC tlast-∞ = percentage of AUC 0-∞ derived from extrapolation; CL/ 
F = apparent clearance; C max = maximum observed drug concentration; CV = coefficient of variation; t 1/2 = apparent terminal elimination 
half-life; T max = time to reach C max ; V z /F = apparent volume of distribution during the terminal phase. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Data are median (range). </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Data are geometric mean (range). </p>

<p> 
PHARMACOTHERAPY Volume 36, Number 7, 2016 </p>

<p>pharmacokinetic parameters, the upper bound of 
the 90% CI of the ratio of geometric LS means 
exceeded 1.25 but was less than 2, indicating a 
weak interaction according to U.S. Food and 
Drug Administration guidance. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>The study's objective was to determine the 
effect of increased gastric pH on the pharmacoki-
netics of evacetrapib, not to determine the speci-
fic effect of concomitant omeprazole treatment 
on evacetrapib's pharmacokinetics. Omeprazole 
was the tool used to increase gastric pH, but 
because omeprazole did not accomplish this in 
every subject, it diluted the effect of omeprazole 
in the analysis across all subjects that included 
the subjects who did respond. To better evaluate 
the objective, given the poor response to omepra-
zole in some subjects, a subgroup analysis was 
conducted that included only the 22 subjects 
whose gastric pH was 3.0 or lower on day 1 and 
4.0 or higher on day 14. By these criteria, each 
subject in the analysis had a pH increase of at 
least 1.0, and, in fact, the analysis included all 
subjects who had a pH increase of at least 1.0 
except for one subject, whose pH increased from 
6.1 at baseline to 7.3 on omeprazole. In this sub-
population, mean gastric pH increased by 4.15 
during 7 days of omeprazole treatment, and geo-
metric LS mean AUC 0-∞ and C max of evacetrapib </p>

<p>increased by 22% and 35%, respectively. These 
increases were similar to the respective 15% and 
30% increases across all subjects, which indicates 
that the analysis across all subjects was not sig-
nificantly influenced by including subjects who 
did not respond well to omeprazole. Despite the 
small mathematical differences in the two analy-
sis groups, the overall effect is a minimal increase 
in evacetrapib exposure. 
Several steps were taken to determine accurate 
gastric pH measurements for individual subjects 
during the study. After positioning the probe 
using the AirFLOW Sphincter Locator, gastric pH 
measurements were collected using the ZepHr 
Monitoring System and averaged over 15 min-
utes. This system is used clinically for measuring 
pH in the lower esophagus during gastric reflux 
episodes, and it was adapted in this study to mea-
sure pH in the stomach. The ZepHr System uses 
a thin flexible probe that is more comfortable 
and less likely to coil compared with standard 
nasogastric tubes often used for monitoring gas-
tric pH. To ensure that pH measurements were 
being collected in the stomach, a three-tiered 
approach was used to confirm placement of the 
probe. First, the sphincter locator allowed identi-
fication of increased pressure at the LES so that 
the pH probe could be positioned about 10 cm </p>

<p>Table 3. Statistical Analysis of Pharmacokinetic Parameter Estimates of Evacetrapib Following Evacetrapib 130 mg Admin-
istered Alone or with Omeprazole 40 mg Once/Day </p>

<p>Parameter 
Treatment </p>

<p>All subjects </p>

<p>Subjects with predose gastric pH ≤ 3.0 on day 1 
and ≥ 4.0 on day 14 </p>

<p>No. of 
subjects </p>

<p>Geometric 
LS means </p>

<p>Ratio of geometric 
LS means 
(evacetrapib + 
omeprazole-
to-evacetrapib; 
90% CI) </p>

<p>No. of 
subjects </p>

<p>Geometric 
LS means </p>

<p>Ratio of geometric 
LS means (evacetrapib + 
omeprazole-to-evacetrapib; 
90% CI) </p>

<p>AUC 0-∞ , 
ng9hr/ml </p>

<p>Evacetrapib 
34 
12,438 
22 
11,979 
Evacetrapib + 
omeprazole </p>

<p>33 
14,313 
1.15 (0.982-1.35) 
22 
14,575 
1.22 (1.04-1.42) </p>

<p>C max , ng/ml 
Evacetrapib 
34 
748 
22 
682 
Evacetrapib + 
omeprazole </p>

<p>33 
969 
1.30 (1.03-1.63) 
22 
923 
1.35 (1.01-1.80) </p>

<p>Parameter 
Treatment </p>

<p>No. of 
subjects Median </p>

<p>Median of 
differences 
(evacetrapib + 
omeprazole -evacetrapib; 
90% CI) </p>

<p>No. of 
subjects Median </p>

<p>Median of differences 
(evacetrapib + omeprazole -
evacetrapib; 90% CI) </p>

<p>T max , hrs </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Evacetrapib 
33 
3.00 
22 
3.00 
Evacetrapib + 
omeprazole </p>

<p>33 
3.00 
0.00 (À1.00-0.00) 
22 
2.54 
0.00 (À1.00-0.00) </p>

<p>AUC 0-∞ = area under the concentration versus time curve from time zero extrapolated to infinity; CI = confidence interval; C max = maxi-
mum observed drug concentration; LS = least squares; T max = time to reach C max . 
Model: Log (PK) = Subject + Treatment + Random Error, where subject is fitted as a random effect. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>T max analyzed nonparametrically by using SAS procedure <rs type="software">PROC UNIVARIATE</rs> software. </p>

<p>GASTRIC PH AND EVACETRAPIB PHARMACOKINETICS Small et al </p>

<p>
below it, well into the stomach. Although posi-
tioning the pH probe using the AirFLOW Sphinc-
ter Locator takes slightly longer, it did not appear 
to cause additional discomfort to the subjects. 
Second, the pH gradient from the esophagus to 
the stomach was assessed on the recorder as the 
device was inserted. The pH gradient was most 
obvious in period 1 but was still present after 
7 days of omeprazole administration in period 2. 
Lastly, the length of the pH probe at the nose 
was recorded for each subject at the time of pH 
recording in each period. The probe length at the 
nose after insertion in period 2 was compared 
with that of period 1 because this is unlikely to 
change significantly for individual subjects if the 
probe is placed similarly. Using these three meth-
ods to confirm proper placement into the stom-
ach ensured that valid pH measurements were 
recorded for both periods. 
Subjects were kept at the clinical research unit 
for the duration of the study to ensure compliance 
with study restrictions and dose administration. 
While in the clinical research unit, subjects were 
given standardized meals and were fasted prior to 
pH measurements and evacetrapib dosing to mini-
mize any effect of dietary variations between treat-
ments. The recommended dose of omeprazole 
20 mg once/day achieves maximal acid suppres-
sion within about 4 days, and the 40-mg omepra-
zole dose used in this study was expected to have 
a similar effect. Therefore, the evacetrapib dose 
administered on day 14 after the seventh dose of 
omeprazole was given after maximal suppression 
of gastric acid secretion had been attained. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Increased gastric pH during treatment with 
omeprazole 40 mg once/day increased evace-
trapib AUC 0-∞ and C max by 15% and 30%, 
respectively. For both parameters, the upper 
bound of the 90% CI of the ratio of geometric LS 
means exceeded 1.25 but was less than 2, indicat-
ing a weak interaction. The effect of increased 
gastric pH on evacetrapib pharmacokinetics 
would not be expected to be clinically relevant. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors wish to thank the subjects who partic-
ipated in this study, Teresa Middleton and Jonathan 
Semrad of Covance Inc. (Madison, WI) for their 
assistance in the technical operations of study con-
duct, and Amanda Hodgson of Covance Inc. for pro-
viding writing assistance. </p>



<p>Supporting Information </p>

<p>The following supporting information is available in the online 
version of this paper: 
Table S1. Causes of Achlorhydria </p>

<p> 
PHARMACOTHERAPY Volume 36, Number 7, 2016 </p>

</text></tei>