<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5262502" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T19:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A B S T R A C T </p>

<p>Bisphosphonates (BPs) have recently been shown to have direct anti-tumor properties. Systemic treatment with 
BPs can have multiple adverse effects such as osteonecrosis of the jaw and BP induced bone fracturing and spine 
instability. While benefits of systemic BP treatments may outweigh risks, local treatment with BPs has been 
explored as an alternate strategy to reduce unwarranted risk. In the present study, we examined whether local 
delivery of BPs inhibits tumor-induced osteolysis and tumor growth more effectively than systemic treatment in 
an animal model of tumor-induced bone disease. Following establishment of an intra-tibial model of bone 
metastases in athymic mice, the experimental group was treated by local administration of zoledronate into the 
tibial lesion. A comparison of the effect of local versus systemic delivery of zoledronate on the formation of 
tumor-induced osteolysis was also carried out. A significant increase in mean bone volume/tissue volume % 
(BV/TV) of the locally treated group (12.30 ± 2.80%) compared to the control group (7.13 ± 1.22%) (P &lt; 0.001). 
Additionally, there was a significant increase in the BV/TV (10.90 ± 1.25%) in the locally treated group 
compared to the systemically treated group (7.53 ± 0.75%) (P=0.005). These preliminary results suggest that 
local delivery of BPs outperforms both systemic and control treatments to inhibit tumor-induced osteolysis. </p>

<p>Bone metastases are the most common bone tumor, and they are 
often derived from solid tumours of the breast, prostate, lung and 
bladder [1]. Bone metastases are also the most common cause of 
cancer-related bone pain and often lead to additional complications 
such as pathological fracture and spine compressions, all of which can 
severely diminish patients' quality of life [2]. Treatment of bone 
metastases imposes a huge burden on the healthcare system, and with 
the advancement in healthcare and increase in cancer life expectancy, 
metastatic bone disease is projected to increase dramatically [3]. 
Current treatment options for bone metastases are surgical therapy, 
radiotherapy, anti-receptor activator of nuclear factor-kappaB ligand 
(RANKL) antibody, and systemic bisphosphonates (BPs). 
During bone turnover, osteoblasts build bone while osteoclasts are 
responsible for bone removal [4]. BPs are potent anti-resorptive agents 
that reduce bone resorption by inhibiting osteoclastic cell activity. </p>

<p>Many studies have shown that there is an increase in osteoclast 
numbers and activity in metastatic bone disease. As such, the anti-
resorptive activity of BPs has been explored to reduce bone cancer pain, 
bone destruction, and bone tumor growth [5]. Interestingly, BPs have 
also been suggested to have anti-tumor properties by negatively 
regulating macrophages, endothelial cells and tumor cells [4,6]. BPs 
have also been shown to elicit combinatorial effects with chemother-
apeutic agents. They are often administered to breast or prostate 
cancer patients with metastatic bone disease as a single intravenous 
dose or course of treatment as part of the standard care regimen [7,8]. 
Local delivery of BPs by elution from porous materials can be used to 
enhance bone formation, suggesting a different approach to systemic 
treatment [9]. 
Due to close proximity to vital structures, incomplete surgical 
resection of bone metastases is common. The remaining tumor can 
promote osteolysis of the surrounding bone. While systemic BP 
treatment is often given to these patients, several complications such </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jbo.2017.01.001 
Received 6 October 2016; Received in revised form 7 January 2017; Accepted 7 January 2017 </p>

<p>⁎ Correspondence to: McGill University Health Centre, Montreal General Hospital, 1650 Cedar Ave, A5-169, Montreal, Quebec, Canada H3G 1A4. </p>

<p>E-mail address: Michael.weber@hotmail.com (M.H. Weber). </p>

<p>Journal of Bone Oncology 6 (2017) 8-15 </p>

<p>Available online 13 January 2017 
2212-1374/ © 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/BY-NC-ND/4.0/). </p>

<p>MARK </p>

<p>as osteonecrosis of the jaw, atrial fibrillations, hypocalcemia and acute 
inflammatory response may render systemic BPs administration un-
suitable for some patients [10]. Therefore, we sought to examine 
whether local delivery of BPs can inhibit tumor-induced osteolysis 
and tumor growth in an animal model of tumor-induced bone disease. 
We also sought to determine whether the efficacy of local delivery of 
BPs is comparable to that of systemic BPs on disrupting tumor-induced 
osteolysis. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Study subjects and participants </p>

<p>MDA-MB-231/LUC cell line (Cedarlane, ON, Canada) were cul-
tured in a DMEM cell culture medium (Gibco, Invitrogen) supplemen-
ted with 10% fetal bovine serum and 1% antibiotics (HyClone brand 
from Thermo Scientific) at 37°C in a humidified atmosphere of 5% 
carbon dioxide (CO2). Zoledronic acid was purchased from Sigma, 
USA, and D-luciferin was purchased from PerkinElmer, USA. The 
experimental design used 35 female athymic nude mice (490, 
Homozygous), aged 9-12 weeks, purchased from Charles River, USA. 
The average weight was 25 g (range, 22.7-27.6 g). The mice were 
maintained in pathogen-free conditions. The Mcgill Animal Care and 
Use Committee approved all the experimental procedures. </p>

<p>2.2. Establishment of an intra-tibial mice model of bone metastasis </p>

<p>MDA-MB-231/LUC cell line (N=10 
5 ) were resuspended in 20 μl of </p>

<p>Phosphate buffered saline (PBS) and injected into the marrow space of 
the right tibia using a 27½ gauge needle coupled to a Hamilton syringe 
under imaging guidance [11]. Five days following inoculation, the 
presence of tumor cells was confirmed using in vivo bioluminescence 
imaging (IVIS spectrum, PerkinElmer, USA). Mice were randomly 
assigned to different groups according to the design of each experi-
ment. At the end of each experiment, the mice were sacrificed using the 
American Association for Laboratory Animal Science (IACUC) ap-
proved method (CO2 asphyxiation). </p>

<p>2.3. Intra-tibial administration of zoledronate </p>

<p>Mice were anesthetised using gas anesthetics and were placed in 
supine position over a heated pad to avoid hypothermia. The site of the 
injection was draped in a sterile fashion and cleaned by 70% ethanol 
swab. The ipsilateral knee was flexed to 90 degrees. Following this a 
27½ gauge (½ inch long) needle attached to a 1 ml syringe was 
inserted percutaneously through the knee joint. The syringe axis was 
kept in alignment to the axis of the tibia. The advancement of the 
needle was carried on under image guidance to make sure that we are 
in the metaphyseal bone of the proximal tibia. Proximal tibia was 
drilled by rotating the syringe half to ¾ run. Then, another syringe 
loaded with zoledronate was inserted at the tract made by drilling. 
After successful administration of zoledronate, animals were mon-
itored till complete recovery from anesthesia. Systemic analgesia was 
administered for 48-72 h following the procedure. 
After successful inoculation of MDA-MB-231/LUC cell line, mice 
were divided randomly into two separate groups, the treatment group 
(2 μg of zoledronate suspended in PBS (30 μl) /mice, delivered intra-
tibially three times/week for three weeks, N =11), and the control 
group (PBS (30 μl) /mice, intra-tibially three times/week for three 
weeks, N=5), as described above. Zoledronate treatment was started 
one week after the successful implantation of tumor cells. The tumor 
growth was monitored weekly using in vivo bioluminescence imaging 
and clinically for any signs of tumor development. After three weeks of 
treatment, the mice were sacrificed and tibias were removed and 
dissected for micro-computed tomography (Skyscan1172, Skyscan, 
Belgium) and histological analysis. </p>

<p>2.4. Local versus systemic administration </p>

<p>Following successful injection of MDA-MB-231/LUC cell line, 
nineteen athymic nude mice were divided randomly into two groups: 
the local treatment group (0.025 mg/kg of zoledronate in PBS (30 μl), 
delivered intra-tibially once/week for four weeks, N=6), the systemic 
treatment group (0.025 mg/kg zoledronate in PBS (100 μl), delivered 
sub-cutaneously once/week for four weeks, N=5). Doses were calcu-
lated based on an average weight of 25 g. [12] The treatment was 
started one week following successful inoculation of the breast cancer 
cells. After four weeks of treatment, the mice were sacrificed, and tibias 
were removed and dissected for micro-computed tomography and 
histological analysis. </p>

<p>2.5. In vivo bioluminescence imaging </p>

<p>The growth of MDA-MB-231 derived tibial lesions was assessed by 
longitudinal bioluminescence imaging. The mice were imaged using 
IVIS spectrum following an intra-peritoneal injection of D-luciferin 
solution (PerkinElmer, USA) (150 mg/kg body weight) under gas 
anesthetic. Bioluminescence images were taken 20 min after D-lucifer-
in injection and acquired until the peak signal was reached. Photon 
emission was quantified using <rs type="software">Living Image</rs> software and graphed 
according to the average radiance (photons/s/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>/sr). </p>

<p>2.6. Micro-computed tomography (μ -CT) analysis </p>

<p>Tibiae were dissected from mice at necropsy and excised tibia 
scanned using a high-resolution micro-tomographic system. Each of 
the three-dimensional images was constructed from approximately 550 
individual micro-CT images (8.9 μm/image) starting from the growth 
plate of the tibia and moving distally. Image reconstruction was 
performed using NRecon (Version 1.6.2.0; SkyScan). The CT analyzer 
(1.11.8.0; SkyScan) was used to measure static histomorphometric 
parameters of the region of interest including bone volume/ tissue 
volume % (BV/TV), trabecular number, trabecular thickness and 
trabecular separation. </p>

<p>2.7. Histology and immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Histological analysis of tumor burden was performed on hematox-
ylin and eosin (H &amp; E) stained sections of tibias. <rs id="software-1" type="software">Imagescope</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Aperio</rs>) was used to quantify tumor area in mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. Tumor burden was 
expressed as the proportion of tumor occupying the total area. Tissue 
fixation and immunohistochemical (IHC) staining were carried out as 
previously described. [13] The proliferative index in the bone meta-
static lesions was assessed by staining with a Ki67 antibody (1 μg/ml; 
Abcam, Toronto, ON, Canada). Anti-Cleaved-Caspase 3 staining 
(0.2 μg/ml dilution; Cell Signaling, Whitby, ON, Canada) was per-
formed to quantify apoptosis within the bone lesions. Following 
incubation with the primary antibody, secondary biotin-conjugated 
antibody (Jackson Laboratories) was applied for 30 min. After washing 
with distilled water, slides were developed with diaminobenzidine 
(Dako) as the chromogen. All slides were counterstained using Harris 
haematoxylin before being scanned using a Scanscope XT digital slide 
scanner (Aperio). Quantification was performed by analyzing bone 
metastases with <rs id="software-2" type="software">Imagescope</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Aperio</rs>) using positive pixel 
count algorithm for Ki67 and Cleaved Caspase-3 staining. For quanti-
fication of Ki67 and Cleaved Caspase-3 staining, positively stained 
nuclei were represented as a percentage of total nuclei per field. </p>

<p>2.8. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>All statistical analyses were conducted using SPSS Version 21 
(Armonk, NY: IBM Corp). All data were expressed as Mean ± SEM. 
Non-parametric two-sided Mann-Whitney U-tests was applied to test </p>

<p>A. Nooh et al. 
Journal of Bone Oncology 6 (2017) 8-15 </p>



<p>the difference in μ-CT markers, tumor burden and immunohistochem-
istry staining. Repeated measures two-way ANOVA with interactions 
was used to calculate the difference in bioluminescence data between 
the two groups. A p-value of less than 0.05 was considered statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Local administration of zoledronate suppresses breast cancer-
induced osteolysis </p>

<p>Following 3 weeks of zoledronate treatment, the treated group 
demonstrated a statistically significant increase in the BV/TV (12.30 ± 
2.80%) compared to the control group (7.13 ± 1.22%) (P &lt; 0.001); net 
increase is 72.51% (Fig. 1A). Additionally, the treated group revealed 
an increase in the trabecular number, compared to the control group 
(P &lt; 0.001) (Table 1). Three-dimensional (3D) reconstruction of μ-CT </p>

<p>images, established using the coronal (midline) and axial cut (5 mm 
from the growth plate), demonstrated complete absence of the 
osteolytic lesions and an increase in trabecular bone formation in the 
zoledronate-treated tibiae compared to the control group (Fig. 1B). To 
quantify tumor growth, mice were imaged weekly by longitudinal 
bioluminescence imaging. The control group showed an increase in </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Quantitative and qualitative assessment of BV/TV using μ-CT. A) The treated group showed a significant increase in the BV/TV as compared to the control group **P &lt; 0.001. B) 
3D constructed coronal and axial μ-CT images demonstrated a qualitative increase in the trabecular bone volume in the treated tibia when compared to the control. </p>

<p>Table 1 
Histomorphometric parameters of the locally treated group, compared to the control 
group. </p>

<p>μ-CT markers 
Local 
Control 
P-value </p>

<p>BV/TV (%) 
12.30 ± 2.80 
7.13 ± 1.22 
&lt; 0.001 
Trabecular number (1/mm) 
0.70 ± 0.20 
0.41 ± 0.11 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Trabecular thickness (mm) 
0.21 ± 0.01 
0.21 ± 0.01 
0.20 
Trabecular separation (mm) 
1.51 ± 0.21 
1.50 ± 0.11 
1.00 </p>

<p>A. Nooh et al. 
Journal of Bone Oncology 6 (2017) 8-15 </p>



<p>photon emission (expressed as average radiance) from day five 
onwards, unlike the treatment group which showed a slowing of tumor 
growth. However, a comparison between the mean photon emissions at 
the end of the experiment demonstrated no significant difference </p>

<p>between the two groups (P=0.30) (Fig. 2). Histologically, mice treated 
with locally delivered BPs experience a decrease in the tumor burden 
(12 ± 7.7%), compared the control group (23 ± 20%), however the 
difference did not reach statistical significance (P = 0.34). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Real Tumours growth during local zoledronate treatment in intra-tibal breast cancer model. A) Representative images of tumours growth obtained from each group at different 
time points. B) Graph showed the BIL measurements according to the average radiance. Treatment with zoledronate showed an insignificant statistical difference (P=0.3). </p>

<p>A. Nooh et al. 
Journal of Bone Oncology 6 (2017) 8-15 </p>



<p>Additionally, an examination of the effect of zoledronate on apoptosis 
and tumor cell proliferation using antibody active against cleaved 
caspase 3 (marker of cell apoptosis) and Ki-67 antibody (marker of cell 
proliferation), revealed a significant increase in the mean percentage of 
apoptosis (3.6 ± 2.8%) in the treatment group when compared to the 
control group (0.14 ± 0.08%) (P=0.07,) (Fig. 3). The increase in the 
apoptosis in the treated group was mirrored with decrease in the mean 
percentage of proliferation (29.4 ± 14.4%) in the treatment group when 
compared to the control group (44.9 ± 7.7%) (P = 0.10) (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>3.2. Local versus systemic administration of zoledronate is superior 
for reducing cancer-induced osteolysis </p>

<p>Since direct treatment with zoledronate showed significantly re-</p>

<p>duced osteolysis compared to control treatment, we determined 
whether local BP treatment was also superior to systemic treatment 
for disrupting osteolysis in vivo. Upon comparison, BV/TV was found 
to be significantly higher in the local group (10.90 ± 1.25%) compared 
to the systemic group (7.53 ± 0.75%) (P=0.005) resulting in a net 
increase of 44.8% (Fig. 4A). Moreover, the locally treated group 
demonstrated an increase in the trabecular number when compared 
to the systemically treated group (P=0.005) (Table 2). Three-dimen-
sional (3D) reconstruction of μ-CT images, established using the 
coronal (midline) and axial cut (5 mm from the growth plate), further 
demonstrated an increase in trabecular bone volume in the locally-
treated tibiae when compared to the systemically-treated group 
(Fig. 4B). Together, these data indicate that local treatment with BP 
has greater benefit to retaining bone volume than systemic treatment in </p>

<p>Fig. 3. The effect of zoledronate (2 μg, three times/week for three weeks) on tumor cells proliferation and apoptosis using immunohistochemistry. (A) Ki-67 antibody (marker of cell 
proliferation) revealed a statistically insignificant decrease in Ki-67-positive cells (29.4 ± 14.4%) in the treatment group when compared to the control group (44.9 ± 7.7%) (P=0.10). (B) 
Anti CC-3 antibody (marker of cell apoptosis) demonstrated a statistically insignificant significant increase in the number of caspase-3-positive cells (3.6 ± 2.8%) in the treatment group 
when compared to the control group (0.14 ± 0.08%)(P=0.07). Scale bar, 20 µm. </p>

<p>A. Nooh et al. 
Journal of Bone Oncology 6 (2017) 8-15 </p>



<p>our mouse model of tumor-induced bone disease. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>Local drug delivery recently gained wide popularity in the field of </p>

<p>orthopaedic oncology. Multiple studies have investigated the potential 
of local delivery of therapeutic agents in at the site of bone tumor 
mainly for palliative measures [14,15-18]. Gangi et al. reported the use 
of percutaneous alcohol injection directly into bone tumours in 25 
patients with painful vertebral metastases, which resulted in effective 
pain reduction and improved quality of life [14]. On the other hand, 
several studies reported local delivery of BPs for treating multiple bone 
pathologies [19,20]. Local elution of zoledronate from titanium im-
plants in animal studies showed to increase in the net bone formation 
with clear signs of improved vascularity, maturity, and remodelling 
[19]. Locally-delivered BP was also used to improve mechanical 
stability of implants [21] and to enhance bone formation in an 
osteoporotic model [22]. Nevertheless, this is the first study to examine 
the effect of direct delivery of BPs into the site of bone metastasis. 
In this study, we have used an intra-tibial model of tumor-induced </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Quantitative and qualitative assessment of BV/TV using μ-CT. A) Our results showed a significant statistical difference in the BV/TV between the local group (and the systemic 
group **P &lt; 0.005. B) 3D constructed coronal and axial μ-CT images demonstrate an increase in the trabecular bone volume in the locally treated tibia when compared to the 
systemically treated tibia. </p>

<p>Table 2 
Histomorphometric parameters of the locally treated and systemically treated groups. </p>

<p>μ-CT markers 
Local 
Systemic 
P-value </p>

<p>BV/TV (%) 
10.90 ± 1.25 
7.53 ± 0.75 
0.005 
Trabecular number (1/mm) 
0.64 ± 0.11 
0.44 ± 0.10 
0.005 </p>

<p>Trabecular thickness (mm) 
0.21 ± 0.01 
0.20 ± 0.01 
0.80 
Trabecular separation (mm) 
1.51 ± 0.11 
1.51 ± 0.10 
1.00 </p>

<p>A. Nooh et al. 
Journal of Bone Oncology 6 (2017) 8-15 </p>



<p>bone disease that represents late events in the bone metastatic process 
and allows us to examine the effect of localized delivery of BPs on the 
progression of established metastatic bone disease [23,24]. We have 
used a high dose (2 μ) of BP three times/week to simulate a sustained 
release of BP from an implant. Our results demonstrated that local 
delivery of BPs significantly inhibited tumor-induced osteolysis in the 
treatment group; in fact, it preserved the bone completely. We also 
observed a substantial effect of BPs on tumor-induced osteolysis, as 
well as a trend for inhibition of tumor cell proliferation. A comparison 
between the local and the systemic delivery of BPs demonstrated that 
the anti-osteolytic effect of local delivery of BPs in a model of tumor-
induced bone disease exceeds that of the systemic effect. Several 
studies have investigated the effect of systemic zoledronate on tumor-
induced osteolysis [23,25-27]. Buijs et al. [23] examined the effect of 
systemic zoledronate in an intra-tibial model of bone metastasis and 
demonstrated a significant inhibition of tumor-induced osteolysis in an 
intra-tibial model of bone metastasis. Similarly, Peyruchaud et al.[26] 
showed that 3 μg of zoledronate given daily, inhibited the formation of 
new lytic lesions and the progression of the established lesions [26]. 
The underlying mechanism of the inhibition of osteolysis has been 
mainly found to be due to the inhibition of osteoclast-mediated bone 
resorption [28]. In the present study, local delivery also likely blocked 
osteolysis by inhibiting osteoclast function. 
Despite using a relatively high dose of zoledronate (2 μg) directly at 
the site of bone tumor one week after cancer cell implantation, our 
results showed a trend that tumor growth was less in the treatment 
versus control groups. These results were somewhat consistent with 
what is reported in the literature [29,30]. Buijs et al. [23] demonstrated 
that zoledronate significantly inhibited tumor-induced bone resorption. 
However, it did not inhibit local tumor growth. In addition, Pluijm 
et al. [31] examined the effect of pamidronate and olpadronate in an 
intra-tibial model of bone metastases. Treatment regimen started at 
day three after cancer cell implantation. Their results showed that BPs 
inhibited osteolysis, yet it did not affect tumor growth. From the review 
of the literature, it seems that BPs treatment inhibits tumor growth in 
preclinical animal models only when treatment starts before the 
establishment of bone metastases. However, once the tumor reaches 
a certain size, it is difficult to control the tumor growth with just BPs 
administration [31]. Moreover, it has been suggested that the BPs' high 
affinity for bone minerals bound their direct anti-tumor effect on the 
tumor cells in vivo [32]. 
To further justify the use of local delivery, we compared the local 
delivery of zoledronate to the systemic delivery with equal dose 
(0.025 mg/kg), which represents the clinical dosage used in humans 
for treatment of bone metastases [12]. To minimize bias, we divided 
the mice into two control groups, one for systemic and one for local 
drug delivery. The rationale behind this randomization is a hypothe-
tical effect of the increase in bone formation in the local group due to 
the repeated micro-fractures caused by our injection. However, the 
comparison between the two controls revealed no significant statistical 
difference (P=0.30). On the other hand, we observed a significant 
increase in the BV/TV in the local group compared to the systemic 
group, with a net increase of 44.8%. These results showed that the 
effect of local delivery of zoledronate in bone metastases model is 
superior that of the systemic treatment. This has been explained by the 
fact that half the dose of systemic zoledronate reaches the bone with a 
short half-life of ten days [33]. Our results suggest that a larger 
percentage of the dose reaches the bone; however, to our knowledge, 
there are no studies on the pharmacokinetics of direct injection of 
zoledronate. 
Two major factors favor the use of local over systemic delivery with 
BPs. Given the anti-osteolysis effect of zoledronate, it can be utilized in 
cases where complete resection of bone tumor is not possible due to 
vital structures invasion. It can be delivered by local elution from 
implants or by image guidance injections in case surgical intervention 
is not feasible. The effect on tumor growth, however, is still question-</p>

<p>able and needs further investigation. On the other hand, high doses of 
systemic BP is required to achieve clinical efficacious concentration for 
neoplastic bone metastasis. This required high systemic BP route can 
cause severe renal toxicity, while oral administration is complicated by 
poor bioavailability ( &lt; 1% in humans) and poor gastrointestinal 
tolerability. In addition, other side effects of systemic BPs treatment 
have been reported in the literature include joint pain, jaw osteone-
crosis [10], ocular inflammation [34], and compromised bone growth 
in children [35]. Local delivery can provide direct delivery of zoledro-
nate to the site of bone tumor without passing the systemic circulation, 
thus, avoiding undesirable side effects and ensuring better bioavail-
ability. 
In conclusion, intra-tumor delivery of zoledronate demonstrated a 
substantial inhibitory effect of tumor-induced osteolysis and a trend for 
reduced tumor cell proliferation. Additionally, the comparison between 
local and systemic delivery unexpectedly revealed that local delivery 
was more effective in osteolysis inhibition. Although tumor growth was 
not significantly inhibited, the noted effect on apoptosis of intra-tumor 
delivery of zoledronate triggers the need for further assessment of its 
anti-tumor properties. Also, further work needs to be performed to 
compare systemic effects of zoledronate in the non-affected skeleton as 
well as a dose reduction study to determine the minimum effective 
treatment for lysis inhibition. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement </p>

<p>The authors declare there are no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported in part by the Canadian Cancer Society 
Research Institute (CCSRI) innovation grant # 702555, MITACS grant 
# IT02931 and Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of 
Canada (NSERC) grant # 312809-11. We thank Mrs. Zhifeng Dong for 
her valuable technical assistance with the immunohistochemistry. </p>



<p>A. Nooh et al. 
Journal of Bone Oncology 6 (2017) 8-15 </p>







</text></tei>