<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5056991" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Dynamin 2 (DNM2) is a large GTPase involved in endocy-
tosis, intracellular membrane trafficking and cytoskeleton 
organization. 1 DNM2 is ubiquitously expressed with higher 
abundance in heart and skeletal muscle. 2 DNM2 oligomer-
izes around the neck of nascent vesicles and regulates 
membrane fission events from plasma membrane 3,4 and 
intracellular compartments. 5,6 The DNM2 transcript encodes 
a protein composed of 5 domains: a N-terminal catalytic 
GTPase domain responsible for GTP binding and hydrolysis, 
a middle domain (MID) involved in DNM2 self-assembly, a 
pleckstrin homology (PH) domain that interacts with phos-
phoinositides and targets dynamin to membranes, a GTPase 
effector domain requires for GTPase activation and DNM2 
self-assembly, and a C-terminal Proline rich-domain (PRD) 
that mediates protein-protein interactions. 
Heterozygous mutations in DNM2 gene are responsible 
for the autosomal dominant centronuclear myopathy (MIM# 
160150). 7 Autosomal dominant centronuclear myopathy is a 
rare congenital myopathy exhibiting a large clinical spectrum, 
and characterized by the presence of centrally located nuclei 
in a large number of muscle fibres. 7,8 No curative treatment is 
available and the pathophysiological mechanisms of the dis-
ease are still poorly understood. The human DNM2 (OMIM 
#602378) gene is composed of 22 exons encoding four major 
splice isoforms by using a combination of two alternative 
splice sites. 9 To date, more than 20 mutations, affecting six 
exons spread over the MID, PH, and GTPase effector domain </p>

<p>domains, have been identified in centronuclear myopathy 
patients. 8 The most frequent mutation located in exon 11 
(p.Arg465Trp in the MID) accounts for 30% of patients. 8 The 
same mutation, also harbored by exon 11 in mouse, was 
used to develop a Knock-In-Dnm2 R465W mouse model of the 
disease. 10 
The knock-out of Dnm2 in mouse is lethal during embry-
onic stage while heterozygous Dnm2 knock-out mice do not 
develop phenotype. 11,12 Besides, overexpression of wild-type 
Dnm2 is also deleterious in mouse tissues. 13 These data 
argue for a tight regulation of the DNM2 expression level 
compatible with cell homeostasis. Consequently, future ther-
apeutic strategies for DNM2-linked autosomal dominant cen-
tronuclear myopathy will require maintenance of the DNM2 
gene product in physiological range. Spliceosome-mediated 
RNA trans-splicing (SMarT) appears suitable to reach such 
a requirement. 
Trans-splicing is a natural process which consists in splic-
ing reaction between two independently transcribed pre-
mRNAs using the cellular spliceosome machinery. 14 SMarT 
has been developed to correct mutated mRNAs by trans-
splicing with an exogenous RNA provided by an engineered 
pre-trans-splicing molecule (PTM). 15 SMarT converts the 
mutant mRNA into wild-type mRNA and maintains natu-
ral regulation of the target mRNA providing a spatially and 
quantitatively appropriate level of expression. 16,17 Additionally, 
SMarT strategy can cover distinct mutations with a unique 
molecular tool as it allows the replacement of large part of 
the targeted RNA. SMarT technology was used to reprogram </p>

<p>Received 21 April 2016; accepted 20 July 2016; published online 13 September 2016. doi:10.1038/mtna.2016.67 </p>

<p>Dynamin 2 (DNM2) is a large GTPase, ubiquitously expressed, involved in membrane trafficking and regulation of actin and 
microtubule cytoskeletons. DNM2 mutations cause autosomal dominant centronuclear myopathy which is a rare congenital 
myopathy characterized by skeletal muscle weakness and histopathological features including nuclear centralization in 
absence of regeneration. No curative treatment is currently available for the DNM2-related autosomal dominant centronuclear 
myopathy. In order to develop therapeutic strategy, we evaluated here the potential of Spliceosome-Mediated RNA Trans-
splicing technology to reprogram the Dnm2-mRNA in vitro and in vivo in mice. We show that classical 3′-trans-splicing strategy 
cannot be considered as accurate therapeutic strategy regarding toxicity of the pre-trans-splicing molecules leading to low 
rate of trans-splicing in vivo. Thus, we tested alternative strategies devoted to prevent this toxicity and enhance frequency of 
trans-splicing events. We succeeded to overcome the toxicity through a 5′-trans-splicing strategy which also allows detection 
of trans-splicing events at mRNA and protein levels in vitro and in vivo. These results suggest that the Spliceosome-Mediated 
RNA Trans-splicing strategy may be used to reprogram mutated Dnm2-mRNA but highlight the potential toxicity linked to the 
molecular tools which have to be carefully investigated during preclinical development. 
Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids (2016) 5, e362; doi:10.1038/mtna.2016.67; published online 13 September 2016 </p>

<p>Subject Category: siRNAs, shRNAs, and miRNAs </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Research Center for Myology, Institute of Myology, UPMC Univ Paris, Paris, France Correspondence: Marc Bitoun, Research Center for Myology, Institute of Myology, 
Groupe Hospitalier Pitié-Salpêtrière, UMRS974, 47, boulevard de l'Hôpital, 75651 Paris cedex 13, France. E-mail: m.bitoun@institut-myologie.org 
Keywords: 3′-trans-splicing; 5′-trans-splicing; in vivo reprogramming; Dynamin 2; PTM toxicity; spliceosome-mediated RNA-trans-splicing </p>

<p>Reprogramming the Dynamin 2 mRNA by 
Spliceosome-mediated RNA Trans-splicing </p>

<p>Delphine Trochet 1 , Bernard Prudhon 1 , Arnaud Jollet 1 , Stéphanie Lorain 1 and Marc Bitoun 1 </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids </p>

<p>Trans-splicing Strategies to Reprogram Dnm2 mRNA 
Trochet et al. </p>



<p>5′, 18 3′ 19 or internal 20 mRNA sequences. In this study, we 
assessed the feasibility of 3′-and 5′-trans-splicing strategies 
to reprogram Dnm2 transcripts in vitro and in vivo. We show 
that 5′-SMarT is a suitable approach for reprograming the 
Dnm2 transcript. However, assessment of optimized strate-
gies to increase efficiency and avoid the PTM self-translation 
will be crucial for further preclinical development. </p>

<p>Results 
Design of Dnm2 3′-PTM 
Given that the majority of the published reports has been con-
centrated on the 3′-trans-splicing approach, we first designed 
3′-PTM targeting intron 10 in order to reprogram Dnm2 tran-
script from the exon 11 to the last exon. PTM contain: (i) a 
cytomegalovirus (CMV) promoter, (ii) antisense sequences 
(AS) complementary to intron 10 except for the negative con-
trol lacking the AS sequence (noAS-PTM), (iii) a conserved 
yeast branch point sequence (BP), (iv) a polypyrimidine tract, 
(v) a strong canonical 3′ acceptor splice site (3′-SS), 15 and 
(vi) the wild-type cDNA sequence of the mouse Dnm2 (exons 
11 to 22) fused with a Flag epitope motif. The sequence from 
exon 12 to exon 22 was modified by codon optimization. 
These nucleotide modifications, preserve the translated pro-
tein sequence, increase the transgene expression, and allow 
detection of chimeric trans-spliced sequence by reverse tran-
scriptase-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR). Sequence of 
exon 11 was unchanged in order to retain putative endoge-
nous Exonic Splice Enhancer sites (Figure 1a). We designed 
five distinct AS (AS2 to AS6) of ~150 nucleotides in the 3′ 
part of intron 10 (from −450 to +2 relative to exon 11). The 
AS3 masks the endogenous BP, polypyrimidine tract, 3′-SS, 
and the 3′ intron/exon boundary of exon 11 (Figure 1b). The 
targeted intron is involved in alternative splicing. Therefore, 
the expected trans-spliced product would contain the Dnm2 
endogenous sequence from exon 1 to 11 including either 
exon 10 or 10 bis followed by Dnm2 optimized sequence 
(exons 12 to 22) and the Flag sequence. </p>

<p>3′-trans-spliced transcripts were detectable in cells 
despite unexpected multiple translation from the PTM 
3′-PTM plasmids were transiently transfected into NIH3T3 
fibroblasts and trans-splicing events were analyzed by RT-
PCR 48 hours after transfection. Taking advantage of the 
Dnm2 modified sequence in PTM, we used oligonucleotides 
which amplify specifically trans-spliced transcripts (E8-F/ 
E14Opt-R) or both cis-and trans-spliced transcripts (E8-F/ 
E11-R) (Figure 1b). Trans-spliced mRNA was amplified after 
two rounds of PCR in cells transfected with AS2-and AS3-3′-
PTM but not in untransfected cells (Figure 2a). Sequencing 
confirmed trans-splicing in both cases occurring either after 
endogenous exon 10 (isoform 1) or 10 bis (isoform 2) (not 
shown). 
Trans-splicing events were also assessed by western blot 
using an anti-Flag antibody. We did not detect any protein 
at the expected molecular weight (~100 kDa). Dnm2 immu-
noprecipitation performed to increase the amount of Dnm2 
in protein extracts, also failed to detect trans-spliced protein 
whatever the 3′-PTM (data not shown). However, western 
blot detected several additional bands migrating at molecular </p>

<p>weight ranging from ~25 to 50 kDa (Figure 2b). Their pres-
ence for all the 3′-PTM, with or without AS, suggested that 
these bands came from the PTM itself rather than illegiti-
mate trans-splicing events. We identified 11 putative open 
reading frames (ORFs) in-frame with the Flag epitope in the 
3′-PTM (Figure 2c), four of them with a predicted molecu-
lar weight compatible with our observations (i.e., 39, 35, 33, 
and 26 kDa) (Figure 2a,b). Finally, Flag immunofluorescence 
detects these peptides everywhere in the cytoplasm prevent-
ing the discrimination of trans-spliced protein by this tech-
nique (not shown). </p>

<p>The 3′-PTM self-translation is associated with muscle 
toxicity in vivo 
Recombinant adeno-associated viruses (AAV) expressing the 
5 AS-3′-PTM and the noAS-PTM were produced and injected 
in Tibialis anterior (TA) skeletal muscles of three month-old 
wild-type mice (~ 4.10 11 viral genomes (vg)/muscle). Muscle 
integrity was evaluated by Hematoxylin-Eosin staining on TA 
transverse sections 1.5 months later. Saline-injected control 
TAs showed normal myofibres except in small areas showing 
nuclear centralization compatible with muscle regeneration 
induced by needle injury. The number of fibres with nuclear 
centralization was drastically more important in TAs injected 
with AAV-PTM regardless of the AS sequence (reaching the 
totality of the muscle for the AS5 and AS6) (Figure 3a and 
Supplementary Figure S1a,b). To ensure that the nuclear 
centralization resulted from fibres regeneration, we looked 
at muscle integrity earlier after the injection. Indeed, a mas-
sive necrosis occurred 15 days after injection (Figure 3a). An 
intermediate level of regeneration was observed with AAV-
AS2-3′-PTM and AAV-noAS-3′-PTM (see Supplementary 
Figure S1a,b). 
The monitoring of the amount of AAV-AS5-3′-PTM particles 
over time by qPCR showed a relatively high level after 1 week 
(812 vg/ng of DNA), which then dropped at 2 weeks (333 vg/ 
ng) to reach values close to the range of saline-control after 
1.5 months (Figure 3b). These observations attested the 
virus loss in accordance with the regeneration level observed 
in Hematoxylin and Eosin (Figure 3b and Supplementary 
Figure S1a,b). However, 1.5 months after the injection, low 
level of viral particles was still detectable for AAV-AS2-3′-PTM 
and AAV-AS4-3′-PTM (58 and 21 vg/ng, respectively) (See 
Supplementary Figure S1c). Consequently, further RT-PCR 
and western blot analyses were performed to determine if 
these low remaining amounts of viral particles sustain trans-
splicing events. The trans-splicing specific primers detect 
trans-spliced mRNA at the expected size for TA injected 
with AAV-AS2-3′-PTM and AAV-AS4-3′-PTM (Figure 3c). 
Even after a second round of PCR, no trans-spliced mRNA 
was detected for the other AS, the noAS and saline-injected 
TA (not shown). Sequencing of the trans-spliced products 
obtained for AS2 and AS4 confirmed the trans-splicing reac-
tion in both cases. Trans-splicing occurred either after the 
Dnm2 endogenous exon 10 (isoform 1) or 10 bis (isoform 2) 
for both AAV-AS2-3′-PTM and AAV-AS4-3′-PTM (Figure 3d 
and Supplementary Figure S2a). The unexpected amplicon 
obtained for the AAV-AS5-3′-PTM (15 days after the injec-
tion) corresponds to an illegitimate trans-splicing event join-
ing exon 8 to exon 11 (see Supplementary Figure S2b). </p>

<p>www.moleculartherapy.org/mtna </p>

<p>Trans-splicing Strategies to Reprogram Dnm2 mRNA 
Trochet et al. </p>



<p>A sequence alignment between intron 8 and AS5 has shown 
that the largest region of similarity encompasses only 28 bp 
with 67% of identity (see Supplementary Figure S2c). This 
suggests that illegitimate trans-splicing reaction does not 
necessarily required high degree of similarity between untar-
geted regions and the binding sequence. 
No trans-spliced protein was detected in muscle extracts 
even after Dnm2 immunoprecipitation. PTM expression is 
detectable by western blot only for AAV-AS4-3′-PTM and AAV-
AS2-3′-PTM (barely detectable for AS2 before immunopre-
cipitation) (see Supplementary Figure S2d and not shown) 
in accordance with the vg loss secondary to muscle necrosis. 
Consequently, alternative strategies to avoid translation from 
PTM and bypass PTM-related toxicity were developed. </p>

<p>Design of modified 3′-PTM succeeded to avoid PTM 
translation but not the toxicity 
With the objective to force the translation of nontoxic mole-
cule, the Green Fluorescent Protein (GFP) ORF was inserted 
between the antisense sequence and the splice site of our pre-
vious 3′ constructs. The GFP ORF starts with a Kozak initiation 
context and ends with a series of three successive STOP codons 
to optimize the translation ending. It was therefore expected that 
only the GFP (and not the toxic peptides) is translated from the 
mRNA exported to the cytoplasm, with no consequence on 
trans-splicing events occurring in the nucleus (Figure 4a). We 
produced these constructs for AS2 and noAS previously used in 
the 3′ classic strategy and called them "GFP-inserted 3′-PTM". 
PTM translation was assessed using anti-Flag western blot 
on protein extract from 3T3 cells transfected with AS2-GFP-
inserted-3′-PTM construct. The GFP insertion succeeded 
to avoid the multiple PTM translation (Figure 4b). How-
ever, we have detected novel bands around 65 kDa. In silico </p>

<p>analysis identified three potential donor splice sites in the GFP 
sequence that could lead to cis-splicing with predicted GFP-
Dnm2 fusion peptides compatible in size with the observed 
bands (Figure 4b and Supplementary Figure S3b). 
Moreover, immunofluorescence showed a partial colocaliza-
tion of Flag and GFP in the cytoplasm (not shown), in agree-
ment with coexpression of GFP and cis-spliced GFP-Dnm2. 
Finally, we failed to detect a band at the expected molecular 
weight for a trans-splicing event, even after Dnm2 immuno-
precipitation (see Supplementary Figure S3a). 
AAV viruses expressing AS2-and NoAS-GFP-inserted-
3′-PTM were injected into TA muscle of three-month-old 
wild-type mice (1.10 11 vg/muscle). After 1 month, Hema-
toxylin-Eosin staining showed a toxicity similar to the one 
observed for the 3′-classical strategy. Indeed, a large major-
ity of fibres presented a nuclear centralization reflecting mus-
cle regeneration (Figure 4c,d). In addition, no trans-splicing 
event was detected neither by RT-PCR nor western blot in 
muscles (data not shown). </p>

<p>Design of Dnm2 5′-PTM 
Therefore, we developed 5′-trans-splicing strategy allowing 
the deletion of the polyadenylation site of the PTM (supplied 
by the endogenous RNA when trans-splicing occurs). Indeed, 
the polyadenylation contributes to mRNA stability, nuclear 
export and translation. 21 We produced 5′-PTM expression 
plasmids containing: (i) a CMV promoter, (ii) an optional 150 
base-pair-length sequence mimicking presence of intronic 
sequence known to enhance expression of the constructs 22 
and called "intron" thereafter, (iii) the 5′ part of optimized wild-
type Dnm2 cDNA sequence (exons 1 to 13 including exon 10 
bis) fused in 5′ to Flag tag, (iv) a strong 5′ donor splice site 
(5′-SS) followed by a downstream intronic splice enhancer </p>

<p>Figure 1 The 3′ trans-splicing strategy. (a) Schematic illustration of the 3′-PTM constructs containing CMV promoter, the AS sequence, 
the 3′ splice site, the wild-type Dnm2 cDNA (optimized sequence of exons 11 to 22 with exon 13 bis) in frame with Flag epitope, and the 
polyadenylation site. (b) Schematic illustration of 3′ trans-splicing reaction between the endogenous Dnm2 mRNA and the 3′-PTM correcting 
the mutation in exon 11. Locations of AS sequences are shown in the dotted line square. Primers used for trans-spliced mRNA amplification 
by RT-PCR are depicted by arrows on the trans-spliced mRNA. CMV, cytomegalovirus promoter; AS, antisense sequence; SS, splice site; 
pA, polyadenylation site; Dnm2, Dynamin 2; PTM, pre-trans-splicing molecules; RT-PCR, reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction. </p>

<p>Linker+3′ss </p>

<p>Target Dnm2 pmRNA </p>

<p>CMV </p>

<p>Ex10/10bis 
Intron 10-11 </p>

<p>−450 −300 −150 −96 +2 </p>

<p>Exon 11 </p>

<p>Ex11 </p>

<p>WT-Ex12−22 
WT-Ex1-10/10bis </p>

<p>Dnm2-3′-PTM </p>

<p>BP:TACTAAC 
PPT+3′SS </p>

<p>PPT 3′SS </p>

<p>Trans-spliced mRNA </p>

<p>3′ </p>

<p>WT-Ex1−10/10bis 
Ex11−22pt </p>

<p>Ex12−22Opt 
E8-F 
E11R E14Opt-R </p>

<p>E14endo-R </p>

<p>pA </p>

<p>3′ </p>

<p>pA </p>

<p>pA </p>

<p>AS </p>

<p>5′ </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>BP </p>

<p>AUG </p>

<p>AUG </p>

<p>AS4 </p>

<p>AS2 </p>

<p>AS5 </p>

<p>AS6 </p>

<p>AS3 </p>

<p>AS 
E11 
Ex12-22Opt 
3′UTR+polyA </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids </p>

<p>Trans-splicing Strategies to Reprogram Dnm2 mRNA 
Trochet et al. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>sequence previously reported to enhance the 5′ trans-splic-
ing efficiency, 20 (v) a 150 nucleotides AS complementary to 
intron 13, and (vi) an optional 3′-UTR with polyadenylation 
site (Figure 5a). We designed three consecutive AS starting 
from the exon intron junction (AS1, AS2, and AS3). The AS1 
masks the endogenous 5′-SS and the 3′ exon/intron bound-
ary of exon 13 (Figure 5b). For each AS, four constructs 
were made including or not the intron and polyadenylation 
site (i.e. ± pA and ± int). These constructs were named AS-5′-
PTM, AS+int-5′-PTM, AS-∆pA-5′-PTM, AS+int-∆pA-5′-PTM 
(Figure 5a). Since Dnm2 alternative splicing occurs in the 
targeted region, the expected trans-spliced products would 
contain the Flag sequence and Dnm2 optimized sequence 
(exons 1 to 13) followed by endogenous Dnm2 sequence 
starting from exon 13 bis or 14 to exon 22. </p>

<p>5′-PTM are not translated and trans-spliced transcripts 
are detectable in vitro 
The four constructs for each AS were transfected in NIH3T3 
cells. No PTM translation was detected by western blot 
using anti-Flag antibody, regardless of the presence of 
polyadenylation site or intron (Figure 6a and not shown). In 
addition, trans-spliced protein was detected at the expected 
molecular weight for the AS3+int-5′-PTM construct after </p>

<p>Dnm2 immunoprecipitation (Figure 6a and Supplementary 
Figure S4a). 
Expression of Dnm2 trans-spliced transcripts was 
assessed by nested RT-PCR 48 hours after transfection. We 
amplified bands at the expected size for most of the 5′-PTM 
constructs using trans-spliced Dnm2 specific primers (Fig-
ure 6b). No product was amplified in untransfected cells and 
with the two noAS control PTM (with or without pA). Semi-
quantitative RT-PCRs amplifying cis-spliced endogenous 
Dnm2-mRNA, PTM-RNA, and Gapdh mRNA showed similar 
expression level in the different conditions (Figure 6b). Ampli-
con sequencing confirmed trans-splicing events between 
optimized exon 13 and endogenous Dnm2 sequence (Figure 
6c and data not shown). Moreover, sequencing revealed that 
the natural alternative splicing of exon 13 bis is preserved 
since we observed exclusively heterozygous sequences cor-
responding to isoform 2 (including exon 13 bis) mixed with 
isoform 4 (without exon 13 bis) (Figure 6b,c and not shown), 
except for cells transfected with AS2-∆pA-5′-PTM showing 
only isoform 2. 
We detected flag expression by immunofluorescence in 
3T3 cells transfected with AS1-, AS2-, and AS3-5′-PTM con-
taining or not the polyadenylation site (+pA-PTM: ~1-4% of 
cells; ∆pA-PTM:&lt;1% of cells, Supplementary Figure S5). </p>

<p>Figure 2 Expression of the 3′-PTM in vitro. (a) RT-PCR detection of trans-spliced Dnm2 transcripts in 3T3 transfected cells. Trans-spliced 
mRNA were detected after two rounds of PCR (E8-F/E14Opt-R) in cells transfected with AS2-and AS3-3′-PTMs. Total Dnm2 mRNAs 
(endogenous and trans-spliced mRNAs) are amplified using E8-F/E11-R primers. TS, trans-spliced; endo, endogenous. (b) AntiFlag western 
blot on total extracts from 3T3 transfected cells. The red arrow indicated the expected molecular weight for trans-spliced protein. A 43 kDa 
nonspecific band (asterisk) associated with the antiFlag antibody observed in both NT and PTM-transfected cells is used as a loading control. 
AS, antisense sequence; NT, nontransfected cells. 3T3 cells were transfected three times in duplicates. (c) Location of the "Flagged" ORFs 
relative to the PTM sequence. Eleven ATG are in frame with the Flag sequence, their Kozak score (Ks) obtained on the <rs type="software">ATGPR</rs> software 
are indicated. Their positioning relative to the Dnm2 domains and the predicted polypeptide weight are indicated. Possible cryptic CUG start 
codons are shown in red. M, methionine; L, leucine; MD, middle domain; PH: Plekstrin homology domain; GED, GTPase effector domain, 
PRD, proline rich domain; Dnm2, Dynamin 2; ORF, open reading frame; PTM, pre-trans-splicing molecules; RT-PCR, reverse transcription-
polymerase chain reaction. </p>

<p>NT </p>

<p>TS </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c 
b </p>

<p>3′-PTM </p>

<p>KDa </p>

<p>130 
95 </p>

<p>72 </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>AS2 AS3 AS4 AS5 AS6 NT NT 
noAS </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ATG2 
Ks:0.15 </p>

<p>ATG4 
Ks:0.3 </p>

<p>ATG6 
Ks:0.21 
ATG8 
Ks:0.21 
ATG9 
Ks:0.26 
ATG10 
Ks:0.1 
ATG11 
Ks:0.17 </p>

<p>Dnm2 Ex11-22Opti </p>

<p>MD </p>

<p>MD </p>

<p>L443 </p>

<p>449 474-5 </p>

<p>PH </p>

<p>M534 
M564 
M580 
M645 
M675 
M680 
M683 
M709 
M722 
M725 
M796 </p>

<p>GED 
PRD </p>

<p>KDa </p>

<p>49,48,45 
39 
35 
33 
26 
22 
21,5 
21 
18 
17 
16 
9 </p>

<p>ATG7 
Ks:0.1 </p>

<p>ATG5 
Ks:0.13 
ATG3 
Ks:0.14 
ATG1 
Ks:0.32 </p>

<p>3′-PTM </p>

<p>Endo+TS </p>

<p>AS2 
AS3 C − </p>

<p>www.moleculartherapy.org/mtna </p>

<p>Trans-splicing Strategies to Reprogram Dnm2 mRNA 
Trochet et al. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Rare cells are flag-positive with the noAS-PTM containing pA 
site suggesting a weak PTM translation but no flag-positive 
cell was detected using the noAS-∆pA-PTM. We thus assume 
that flag staining observed in cells transfected with AS-∆pA-
PTM represents trans-spliced Dnm2 protein. The flag staining 
pattern is compatible with normal Dnm2 subcellular localiza-
tion and colocalization between trans-spliced and endog-
enous Dnm2 was confirmed by confocal imaging (Figure 6d). </p>

<p>5′-PTM is not toxic and trans-splicing events occurred 
in vivo 
The AS1-, AS2-, AS3-, and noAS-5′-PTMs and their coun-
terpart devoid of polyadenylation site (∆pA) were produced 
in recombinant AAV. We injected 1.10 11 vg or phosphate-buff-
ered saline (PBS) into TA muscles of 3-month-old wild-type 
mice that were analyzed 1 month later. Hematoxylin-Eosin 
staining showed that areas containing fibres with internal-
ized nuclei were similar for PBS-injected TAs (i.e., ~5% of 
the muscle section) and TAs injected with AAV-5′-PTM with </p>

<p>or without pA site (i.e., 0.75-13% of the muscle section) 
(Figure 7a). 
Nested RT-PCR was performed on RNA extracted from 
muscles using cis-and trans-splicing specific primers 
described above (Figure 5b). We detected Dnm2 trans-
spliced transcripts at the expected size only in muscles 
injected with AS1, AS1-∆pA, and AS2-∆pA (Figure 7b). 
Semi-quantitative RT-PCR amplifying endogenous Dnm2-
mRNA, PTM-RNA, and Gapdh mRNA showed comparable 
level of expression in all conditions (Figure 7b). Sequenc-
ing of trans-spliced transcripts showed expected chime-
ric sequence with splice between optimized exon 13 and 
endogenous sequence. RT-PCR amplified specifically either 
isoform 4 (without exon 13 bis) or isoform 2 (with exon 13 
bis) for muscle transduced with AAV-AS1-and AAV-AS2-5′-
PTMs, respectively (Figure 7c). 
Flagged and endogenous Dnm2 colocalized in restricted 
area of transversal TA-sections injected with AAV-AS1-5′-
PTM and AAV-AS1-∆pA-5′-PTM (1-3 groups of around 20 </p>

<p>Figure 3 Evaluation of Dnm2 3′ trans-splicing strategy in transduced muscles. (a) Muscle integrity after AAV-AS5-3′-PTM injection in TA 
muscle. HE staining shows the extent of the necrosis process 15 days after injection (top) and the regenerated areas 1.5 months postinjection 
(bottom). Scale bar = 500 µm (left panel) and 50 µm (right panel). (b) Quantification of AAV viral genomes (vg) by quantitative PCR (qPCR) 
showing the loss of viral particles during the necrosis/regeneration process. AAV genome copy number is expressed as an absolute value per 
ng of DNA (mean + SD). (c) RT-PCR detection of trans-spliced Dnm2 transcripts in muscles transduced with AAV-3′-PTM. PCR1-TS/PCR2-
TS: First and second RT-PCR using primers Ex8-F/E14OptR amplifying the trans-spliced mRNA. Dyna-Endo: RT-PCR using primers Ex8-F/ 
E14EndoR amplifying the endogenous dynamin 2. TS, trans-spliced; Endo, endogenous. (d) Trans-spliced sequence showing endogenous 
Dnm2 ex10 bis followed by PTM exon 11 and optimized exon 14 sequence (detected after AAV-AS2-3′-PTM injection). Two TAs were analyzed 
for each AAV-PTM. AAV, adeno-associated viruses; DNM2, dynamin 2; HE, Hematoxylin-Eosin; PTM, pre-trans-splicing molecules; RT-PCR, 
reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction; TA, Tibialis anterior. </p>

<p>AS5-3′-PTM-AAV-2,510^11vg </p>

<p>15 days 
postinjection </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c 
d </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>45 days 
postinjection </p>

<p>PCR1-TS </p>

<p>AS2-2m </p>

<p>PBS 
PBS 
AS4-1.5m 
AS5-15D </p>

<p>H20 </p>

<p>PCR2-TS </p>

<p>Dyna-Endo </p>

<p>1,000 
812 </p>

<p>333 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Viral genome number/ng 
of DNA </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Ex10 endogeneous sequence </p>

<p>Ex12 optimized sequence </p>

<p>Ex11 endogeneous sequence from PTM </p>

<p>Trans-splice juection </p>

<p>7 days </p>

<p>AAV-AS5-3′-PTM 
PBS </p>

<p>15 days 
45 days 
45 days </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids </p>

<p>Trans-splicing Strategies to Reprogram Dnm2 mRNA 
Trochet et al. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>fibres per muscle section) (Figure 7d). There was no flag-
positive area in muscle injected with the noAS constructs. The 
presence of Dnm2 trans-spliced protein in muscle injected 
with AAV-AS1-5′-PTM was further confirmed by western 
blot after Dnm2 immunoprecipitation (see Supplementary 
Figure S4b). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Among the existing platform technologies developed for gene 
therapy, SMarT combines major advantages including main-
tenance of endogenous regulation of the corrected mRNA, 
absence of overexpression, and correction of multiple muta-
tions using a single therapeutic molecule. SMarT was suc-
cessfully used in vitro 23-27 and in vivo 18,19,28-36 to repair mRNA 
in several context of genetic diseases. In particular, functional 
improvement was reached in cystic fibrosis, 24 hemophilia 
A, 29 X-linked immunodeficiency 36 and Spinal muscular atro-
phy. 30,35 With the objective to correct DNM2 mutations caus-
ing centronuclear myopathy, our aim was here to evaluate 
the feasibility of SMarT-induced reprograming of the mouse 
Dnm2-mRNA in vitro and in vivo. 
The most striking result obtained in the 3′-replacement 
strategy is the expression of several peptides fused with the </p>

<p>flag epitope. The presence of 11 putative AUG-ORF in frame 
with the flag in the PTM coding sequence argues for PTM 
self-translation as already indicated in 3′-replacement stud-
ies. 15,33,34 Monjaret and collaborators recently demonstrated 
undesirable ORFs translation as well as PTM internal cis-
splicing from Titin-and Dysferlin-PTMs. 33 Given that ORF 
prediction does not account for all the bands observed with 
the Dnm2 3′-PTM, similar cis-splicing events cannot be rule 
out in this study despite of absence of putative donor splice 
site. It may be hypothesized that some observed peptides 
come from the use of cryptic CUG start codons (see Figure 
1b) as already reported in mammals 37 or from post-transla-
tional modifications of canonical AUG-ORF. 
Regardless of their mechanism of production, the major 
concern relative to the 3′-PTM expression is their huge toxic-
ity in vivo. Similar observations using the noAS-PTM, sug-
gest toxicity linked to PTM translation rather than illegitimate 
trans-splicing. Parts or totality of Dnm2 PH, GTPase effector 
domain, and proline-rich domain domains can be translated 
from the 3′-PTM coding sequence depending of the start 
codon used (Figure 1b). Therefore, we can hypothesize that 
truncated peptides can trap Dnm2 partners or act as domi-
nant negative mutants to impair Dnm2 functions. In addition, 
muscle toxicity could be linked to other mechanisms such </p>

<p>Figure 4 The GFP-inserted-3′ trans-splicing strategy. (a) Schematic illustration of the "GFP-inserted" PTM containing the AS sequence, 
the GFP ORF, the 3′ splice site (SS), and the Dnm2 wild-type sequence (exons 11 to 22) fused to the Flag. CMV, cytomegalovirus promoter; 
ORF, Open Reading Frame; AS, antisense sequence; SS, Splice site. 3T3 cells were transfected three times in duplicates. (b). Flag western 
blot on 3T3 transfected cells showing the lack of PTM expression in cells transfected with the "GFP-inserted" constructs, while a ~65 kDa 
protein is expressed. (c) HE staining obtained 1 month after TA injection with AAV-AS2-GFP-ins-3′-PTM and the AAV-noAS-GFP-ins-3′-PTM. 
Scale bar = 50 µm. (d) Histogram showing quantification of the regeneration extent on muscles section. The area containing fibres with internal 
nuclei was measured and divided by the total area of the muscle section (mean + SD, n = 3 sections counted for each condition). GFP, Green 
Fluorescent Protein; AAV, adeno-associated viruses; DNM2, dynamin 2; HE, Hematoxylin-Eosin; PTM, pre-trans-splicing molecules; RT-PCR, 
reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction; TA, Tibialis anterior. </p>

<p>Nucleus </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>d 
c </p>

<p>ORF1 </p>

<p>Cytoplasm </p>

<p>Kosak </p>

<p>StopStopStop </p>

<p>StopStopStop </p>

<p>26kDa nontoxic 
GFP protein </p>

<p>ORFs-DNM2 </p>

<p>Linker+SS </p>

<p>EGFP </p>

<p>EGFP </p>

<p>AS 
CMV </p>

<p>ORF2 </p>

<p>pA 
Dnm2 WT Ex11−22 </p>

<p>pA </p>

<p>pA </p>

<p>3′ </p>

<p>95 
72 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>100 
90 
80 
70 
60 
50 
40 
30 
20 
10 
0 </p>

<p>AS2-GFPins-AAV noAS-FFPins-AAV 
PBS </p>

<p>Centrally nuclei area(%) </p>

<p>Exon 12-22 </p>

<p>Flag </p>

<p>AS2-GFPlns 
AS2-classic </p>

<p>NT 
DynaFlag </p>

<p>Dnm2-3′ </p>

<p>ATG </p>

<p>Exon 1-10bis 
5′ </p>

<p>Kosak 
ARNm </p>

<p>AS </p>

<p>www.moleculartherapy.org/mtna </p>

<p>Trans-splicing Strategies to Reprogram Dnm2 mRNA 
Trochet et al. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>as proteasome dysregulation or expression of undetectable 
peptides from others phases. 
Despite of massive viral loss secondary to necrosis-regen-
eration, 38 low level of 3′ trans-spliced mRNAs was detected 
indicating that intron 10 is an accurate targetable region for 
Dnm2 3′-trans-splicing. This result led us to assess alter-
native ways to avoid PTM translation. The "GFP-inserted 
3′-PTM" strategy was developed based on the monocistronic 
rule for gene expression in eukaryotes stating that only the 
protein encoded closest to the 5′ end gets expressed. 39 This 
approach partially succeeded since the translation of multiple 
truncated peptides from the PTM was suppressed, support-
ing their translational origin, but did not significantly reduce 
muscle toxicity. One may hypothesize that toxicity results from 
the production of toxic peptides identified by western-blot and 
generated by cis-splicing of the GFP-inserted 3′-PTM. How-
ever, this modified 3′ strategy may be a good path to prevent 
PTM expression for future SMarT development. 
We also explored alternative way to reduce PTM self-
translation by deleting the polyadenylation site (polyA) in a 
5′-replacement strategy. This strategy was recently devel-
oped in a mouse model of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. 32 
Using this strategy to reprogram Dnm2-mRNA, PTM expres-
sion is not detectable, in vivo toxicity is avoided, and trans-
spliced mRNA and protein are detected both in cells and 
muscles. However, contrasting with the results gained for 
the Mybpc3 mRNA, 32 trans-splicing efficacy is not correlated 
with presence or absence of intron and polyA for the Dnm2 
mRNA. On the other hand, we show discrepancies between 
in vitro and in vivo efficacy for the different PTM. This may 
be due to intrinsic differences between 3T3 fibroblasts and </p>

<p>muscle tissue, and highlights importance of in vivo validation 
of trans-splicing inducing molecular tools. 
Four major DNM2 isoforms are expressed using a combi-
nation of two alternative splice sites (i.e., exons 10 and 10 bis 
are alternatively spliced and an exon 13 bis can be included 
or not). 9 These four isoforms are ubiquitously expressed 9 but 
exhibit different intracellular distribution and support distinct 
cellular functions. 9,40 Consequently, their preservation in a 
therapeutic approach is an important issue. The two intronic 
regions targeted in our study are involved in alternative 
splicing (i.e., intron 10 and 13 in the 3′-and 5′-replacement 
strategies, respectively). In the 3′-replacement study, an 
exclusive alternative splicing after either exon 10 or 10 bis 
is observed in vitro and in vivo suggesting that the loca-
tion of the AS guides the spliceosome in favor of one event. 
Conversely, the chosen AS for 5′-replacement do not bias 
the natural splicing, since the large majority of trans-spliced 
product sequences shows both splice isoforms in vitro. How-
ever, contrasting again with our in vitro results, the splicing is 
altered in vivo, since either trans-spliced isoform 4 or isoform 
2 are produced. The reasons of this discrepancy between in 
vitro and in vivo contexts are unclear and could rely on dif-
ferences between splicing regulations between 3T3 cells and 
muscle. Therefore, maintenance of natural alternative splic-
ing in region targeted by SMarT needs to be carefully consid-
ered in future in vitro screening as well as in in vivo models 
which do not always mirror the in vitro situation. 
In conclusion, we provide here the first evidence that 
Dnm2 transcript may be reprogrammed by 5′-SMarT tech-
nology without significant PTM expression and toxicity 
in vitro and in vivo. Future developments will be required </p>

<p>Figure 5 The 5′ trans-splicing strategy. (a) Schematic illustration the 5′-PTM constructs containing a CMV promoter, the wild-type Dnm2 
cDNA (optimized sequence of exons 1 to 13 including exon 10 bis), a 5′ splice donor site followed by the AS and with or without polyadenylation 
site and intron. (b) Schematic illustration of the 5′ trans-splicing reaction between the 5′-PTM and the endogenous Dnm2 mRNA correcting 
the mutation in exon 11. Location of AS sequences is shown above the dotted line square. The predicted translation of the PTM (i.e., a peptide 
containing the Flag, the Dnm2 GTPase and Middle domain (525 aa) plus few amino acids encoded by the linker and a part of the AS sequence 
(59 to 64 kDa) is shown below the PTM. Primers used for RT-PCR mRNA amplification are depicted by arrows below the TS mRNA. CMV, 
cytomegalovirus promoter; AS, antisense sequence; SS, splices site; DISE, Downstream intronic splice enhancer; pA, polyadenylation site. 
PTM, pre-trans-splicing molecules; RT-PCR, reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction; TA, Tibialis anterior. </p>

<p>CMV </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>CMV 
intron </p>

<p>Dnm2 Ex 1-13-Opti 
AS 3′UTR+polyA </p>

<p>3′UTR+polyA 
+int 
CMV </p>

<p>CMV 
Dnm2 Ex 1-13-Opti </p>

<p>Dnm2 Ex 1-13-Opti 
intron 
AS </p>

<p>Intron 13−14 </p>

<p>AS1 </p>

<p>Exon 13 
EX13bis </p>

<p>R465W 
EX11 </p>

<p>AS2 AS3 </p>

<p>−3 
+ 147 +285 +416 </p>

<p>EX13bis </p>

<p>AS </p>

<p>DISE </p>

<p>5′SS </p>

<p>Flag </p>

<p>5′PTM </p>

<p>5′ </p>

<p>Target Dnm2 pmRNA </p>

<p>WT-Exon 1−10 </p>

<p>WT Ex1−13-Opti 
WT-Ex 1−13-Opti </p>

<p>E8OptF </p>

<p>E10EndoF </p>

<p>E11OptF </p>

<p>E11OptR </p>

<p>E12endoR </p>

<p>E14endoF E17EndoR 
pA 
AUG 
Ex 13bis/14−22 </p>

<p>WT-Exon 14−22 
3′ 
pA </p>

<p>Trans-spliced mRNA </p>

<p>E12−12 </p>

<p>AUG </p>

<p>GTPase 
Middle </p>

<p>59 to 64 Kda PTM peptide </p>

<p>AS 
∆pA </p>

<p>∆pA+Int 
AS </p>

<p>Linker+5′SS </p>

<p>Linker+5′SS 
Linker+5′SS </p>

<p>Linker+5′SS </p>

<p>Dnm2 Ex 1-13-Opti </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids </p>

<p>Trans-splicing Strategies to Reprogram Dnm2 mRNA 
Trochet et al. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>to increase efficiency of DNM2-mRNA reprogramming 
to correct pathogenic DNM2 mutations in patient-derived 
cells and animal models of the autosomal dominant cen-
tronuclear myopathy, two important steps of preclinical 
development. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>PTM constructs. The 5′-and 3′-PTM coding sequences were 
optimized by GeneArt technology (GeneArt, Regensburg, Ger-
many). For the 3′-PTM constructs, the Dnm2 coding sequence 
(i.e., endogenous exon 11 followed by exons 12 to 22 optimized 
sequence) was generated by a PCR-Fusion from mouse cDNA 
and Dnm2 optimized cDNA (GeneArt) and cloned into pGEMT-
Easy vector (Promega, Charbonnieres, France). The linker 
including the branching point, the polypyrimidine tract and the 
splice acceptor site (5′-ccgcggaacattattataacgttgctcgaaTACT 
AACTGATATCTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTTAATTAACAG-3′) </p>

<p>preceded by a KpnI restriction site was added by PCR in 5′ of 
the PTM coding sequence. The Flag sequence followed by 
EcoRI restriction site were added by PCR in 3′ of the PTM cod-
ing sequence. The insertion into the pSMD2 vector was done 
by KpnI-EcoRI digestion and ligation between a CMV promoter 
and the polyA signal. The AS2-AS6 in intron 10 were amplified 
by PCR from mouse genomic DNA using forward and reverse 
primers both containing a KpnI restriction site and introduced 
in the KpnI site of the pSMD2 vector located upstream of the 
linker sequence. The locations of AS in intron 10 are as fol-
lows: AS2 (IVS10 −300 to −150); AS3 (IVS10 −150 to +2); AS4 
(IVS10 −450 to −298), AS5 (IVS10 −252 to −96), AS6 (IVS10 
−320 to −96) (where nucleotide +1 is the first nucleotide of 
exon 11). 
For the GFP-inserted 3′-PTM constructs, the full length 
GFP sequence was amplified from a GFP plasmid using a 
forward primer introducing a Kosak sequence and a reverse 
primer introducing three stop codons (both primers also </p>

<p>Figure 6 Detection of 5′ trans-splicing in vitro. (a) Left: Anti-Flag Western Blot on total proteins from 3T3 cells transfected with 5′-PTM or a 
plasmid expressing full length Dnm2-Flag fusion protein as control (Dynaflag). NT: nontransfected. Right: Dnm2 immunoprecipitation followed 
by Flag western blot on 3T3 cells transfected with 5′-PTM. The image is overexposed and over contrasted to enhance the detection of the 
band indicated by an asterisk. (b) RT-PCR analysis on mRNA extracted from 3T3 cells transfected with 5′-PTM. Dyna-endo: endogenous 
Dnm2 transcripts amplified using E10EndoF/E12endoR primers, TS: trans-spliced RNA amplified using E8OptiF/Ex17endoR and Ex11OptiF/ 
Ex14endoR primers; PTM are amplified using E8OptF/Ex11OptiR primers. C−: negative PCR control. The isoform of Dnm2 identified 
after sequencing for each band is indicated below (i.e., isoform 2 or 4 or both). 3T3 cells were transfected three times. (c) Top: Schematic 
representation of Dnm2 alternative splicing leading to isoforms 2 and 4, locations of primers used for PCR amplification are depicted. 
Bottom: Example of heterozygous trans-spliced sequence showing Ex13 optimized sequence followed by ex13 bis and ex14 endogenous 
sequence. The orange squares show the optimized nucleotides. (d) Anti-Flag and anti-DNM2 immunofluorescence on 3T3 cells 48 hours after 
transfection with AS2-, AS3-, noAS-∆pA-5′-PTM and full length Dnm2-Flag fusion constructs (scale bar = 10 µm). PTM, pre-trans-splicing 
molecules; RT-PCR, reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction. </p>

<p>noAS-5′ 
noAS-5′+int </p>

<p>AS3+int </p>

<p>AS3 
NT 
DynaFlag </p>

<p>noAS-5′ 
noAS-5′+int 
DynaFlag </p>

<p>NT 
AS3+int </p>

<p>AS3 
DynaFlag </p>

<p>95 kda </p>

<p>350 pb </p>

<p>250 pb </p>

<p>200 pb </p>

<p>500 pb </p>

<p>Merge 
Dynamin 
Flag </p>

<p>AS2∆pA </p>

<p>AS3∆pA </p>

<p>DynaFlag </p>

<p>Nested TS </p>

<p>AS1 
AS1+int 
AS2+int 
AS3+int 
noAS-5′ </p>

<p>NT 
C-
noAS-5′+int </p>

<p>AS1 
∆ pA 
AS2 
∆ pA 
AS2 
∆ pA+int 
AS1 
∆ +int 
AS2 
AS3 </p>

<p>Dyna-Endo </p>

<p>PTM </p>

<p>Gapdh </p>

<p>isoform 
2 
4 
Input </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>d 
c </p>

<p>Isoform 2 </p>

<p>Isoform 4 </p>

<p>WB anti Flag </p>

<p>IP-dnm2 
2 
4 </p>

<p>2 
4 </p>

<p>2 
4 </p>

<p>2 2 
4 </p>

<p>2 
4 </p>

<p>2 
4 
4 </p>

<p>72 kda </p>

<p>9 10bis 11 12 13 13bis </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Ex14 endo </p>

<p>Ex13bis endo </p>

<p>Ex13-Opti </p>

<p>10bis 11 12 13 14 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>www.moleculartherapy.org/mtna </p>

<p>Trans-splicing Strategies to Reprogram Dnm2 mRNA 
Trochet et al. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>contain SacII restriction site). The PCR product was then 
cloned into the pSMD2-3′-PTM between the AS and the 
linker sequence after SacII digestion. 
For the 5′-PTM constructs, the Dnm2 coding sequence (i.e., 
Dnm2 exons 1 to 13) was generated by PCR from Dnm2 opti-
mized cDNA. The forward primer contains a KpnI restriction 
site followed by an ATG in a Kosak context, the Flag sequence 
and the first 27 nucleotides of the optimized Dnm2 exon 1. 
The reverse primer contains a SalI restriction site, the down-
stream intronic splicing enhancer element from the rat FGFR2 
gene 20 and the strong canonical 5′ donor splice site sequence </p>

<p>(GTAAGAACAG) followed by the last 25 nucleotides of Dnm2 
exon 13 (optimized). The PCR product was introduced into 
the pSMD2 vector between the CMV promoter and the polyA 
signal by ligation after KpnI-SalI digestion. The AS for 5′-PTM 
were amplified by PCR from mouse genomic DNA using prim-
ers both containing a SalI restriction site and introduced in 
pSMD2-5′-PTM in SalI site downstream to the linker sequence. 
The locations of AS in intron 13 are as follow: AS1 (IVS13 from 
−3 to +147); AS2 (IVS13 from +126 to +285); AS3 (IVS13 from 
+264 to +416) (where nucleotide −1 is the last nucleotide of 
exon 13). To remove the SV40 polyA signal, a supplementary </p>

<p>Figure 7 Detection of 5′ trans-spliced Dynamin 2 mRNA and protein in muscles. (a) Muscle integrity after AAV-mediated AS1-5′-PTM 
transduction; Histogram showing the area of muscle sections with internal or central nuclei (%). The area of fibres with internal nuclei was 
normalized by the total area of the muscle section (Mean + SD, n = 3 sections counted for each condition). (b) RT-PCR analysis on mRNA 
extracted from transduced muscles using specific primers for trans-spliced and cis-spliced mRNA TS: Trans-spliced PCR amplicon, Endo: 
endogenous. (c) Electropherogram of trans-spliced amplicons showing Ex13 optimized sequence followed by ex13 bis (isoform 2, top) or 
ex14 endogenous sequence (isoform 4, bottom). The orange squares show the optimized nucleotides (d). Immunofluorescence analysis 
on TA transverse sections from mice injected of AAV-AS1-5′-PTM. Fibres were double-stained with anti-FLAG (red) and anti-DNM2 (green) 
antibodies. Scale bar = 50 µm. AAV, adeno-associated viruses; DNM2, dynamin 2; PTM, pre-trans-splicing molecules; RT-PCR, reverse 
transcription-polymerase chain reaction; TA, Tibialis anterior. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>PCR2-TS 
-350 pb </p>

<p>-250 pb </p>

<p>-250 pb </p>

<p>-500 pb </p>

<p>AS1 
AS2 
AS3 
AS1∆pA 
AS2∆pA 
AS3∆pA 
noAS∆pA </p>

<p>noAS 
PBS 
C-</p>

<p>Dyna-Endo </p>

<p>PTMs </p>

<p>Gapdh </p>

<p>Isoform </p>

<p>Dnm2 </p>

<p>As1 </p>

<p>As1∆PA </p>

<p>Flag 
Merge </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Isoform 2 </p>

<p>Isoform 4 </p>

<p>Ex13-Opti 
Ex13bis endo </p>

<p>Splice junction </p>

<p>Ex13-Opti 
Ex14Endo </p>

<p>Splice junction </p>

<p>4 
2 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>16 
14 
12 </p>

<p>Centrally located nuclei area (%) </p>

<p>10 
8 
6 
4 
2 
0 </p>

<p>A S 1 -P T M </p>

<p>5 ′ -A A V </p>

<p>A S 1 ∆ p A -P T M </p>

<p>5 ′ -A A V </p>

<p>A S 2 ∆ p A -P T M </p>

<p>5 ′ -A A V </p>

<p>A S 3 ∆ p A -P T M </p>

<p>5 ′ -A A V </p>

<p>n o A S -P T M </p>

<p>5 ′ -A A V 
P B S </p>

<p>A S 2 -P T M </p>

<p>5 ′ -A A V </p>

<p>A S 3 -P T M </p>

<p>5 ′ -A A V </p>

<p>Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids </p>

<p>Trans-splicing Strategies to Reprogram Dnm2 mRNA 
Trochet et al. </p>



<p>XbaI restriction site was inserted downstream of the antisense 
sequence and upstream of the SV40 polyA signal via the 
introduction of a polylinker obtained from the pSL1180 plas-
mid in XhoI-BglII sites. Thus, the subsequent XbaI digestion 
excised the SV40 polyA signal and a fragment spanning from 
the CMV promoter to the end of the AS sequence. The latter 
fragment was then reinserted in a pSMD2 vector previously 
XbaI digested. For the others 5′-PTM sequences (i.e., AS1, 
AS2, and noAS) the coding sequence followed by the splic-
ing sites and AS sequence were directly replaced in the latter 
∆pA construct using HindIII/XhoI digestion. All constructs were 
validated by DNA sequencing. Sequences of primers used for 
cloning are available on request. </p>

<p>Cell culture and transfection. Mouse embryonic fibroblast 
NIH3T3 cells (from ATCC) were grown in Dulbecco's modi-
fied Eagle's media (Life Technologies, Villebon sur Yvette, 
France) supplemented with fetal bovine serum 10%, peni-
cillin 100 U/ml, and streptomycin 100 µg/ml. The cells were 
maintained in 37°C humidified incubators containing 5% CO 2 
and ambient oxygen. For transfection, cells were grown to 
70% confluency in six-well plates and transfected with 1.5 µg 
of pSMD2-Dnm2-PTM plasmids using Exgen 500 transfec-
tion reagent according to the manufacturer's protocol (Euro-
medex, Strasbourg, France). Cells were transfected three 
times per condition and harvested 48 hours later for RNA or 
Protein analysis. </p>

<p>In vivo AAV injection. Experiments were performed on adult 
three-month-old C57/BL6 mice. Anesthesia was achieved 
with a mix of 100 mg/kg ketamine and 10 mg/kg xylasine. Two 
intramuscular injections (30 µl/TA, within 24 hours interval) of 
AAV-PTM (1.10 11 -4.10 11 vg/muscle) were performed in two 
TA using 29G needle. The control muscles were injected with 
PBS using the same procedure. Mice were sacrificed by cer-
vical dislocation under isoflurane anesthesia. Animal studies 
conform to the French laws and regulations concerning the 
use of animals for research and were approved by an external 
Ethical committee (approval No. 00351.02 delivered by the 
French Ministry of Higher Education and Scientific Research). </p>

<p>RNA isolation and cDNA analysis. Total RNA was isolated 
using RNA easy or RNA easy Fibrous tissue mini kits (Qia-
gen, Courtaboeuf, France) for cells and muscles, respectively, 
according to the manufacturer's protocol. Cells or tissue sec-
tions were passed through a 22G syringe several times for 
disruption in the lysis buffer. Total RNA (1 µg) was submitted 
to reverse transcription using the Superscript III reverse tran-
scriptase kit (Life Technologies) using random primers. cDNA 
were amplified by PCR under the following conditions: 96°C 
for 5 minutes, cycles of 30 seconds at 96°C, 30 seconds at the 
appropriate temperature (58 to 61°C), 30 seconds to 1 min-
ute at 72°C, and a final step of 7 minutes at 72°C. Thirty five 
cycles were performed to amplify trans-spliced Dnm2 tran-
scripts, 28 for endogenous Dnm2, 23 for Gapdh, and 27 for 
the PTM. The sequences of the Dnm2 primers for the 5′ and 
3′ strategies are: E8endoF: 5′-TGGAGCCCGCATCAATCG 
TATCTT-3′, E14OptiR: 5′-GTCCTTGTACCAGCTCAGGCT-3′, 
Ex14endoR: 5′-ATCCTTGTACCAAGACAATGA-3′, E8-OptiF: 
5′-AGGTTCCCTTTCGAGCTGGTG-3′, Ex11OptiF: 5′-TGCG </p>

<p>CCGAGAAGCTGTCCAGC-3′, Ex10endoF: 5′-GGTGGTCAA 
GCTGAAAGAGC -3′, E12endoR: 5′-GGTTTGTGTTGATGTA 
CGACTGC-3′ , and Ex17Endo-R: 5′-CCCAGCGCGCAGGA 
ACGAAG-3′. The 5′-PTM is amplified using E8OptiF and 
ex11OptiR (5′-TGTCACGATCCGCTCTGTTTC-3′). Gapdh 
primers are F: 5′-ACCACAGTCCATGCCATCAC-3′ and R: 
5′-TCCACCACCCTGTTGCTGTA-3′. 
For nested PCR or when two rounds of PCR were done, the 
first PCR was diluted to 1/50 and 1µl was used for the second 
round for 35 cycles. DNA sequencing of 20 ng DNA/100 bp 
with 5 pmol of the respective primers was performed by Euro-
fins (Paris, France). </p>

<p>Western blot and immunoprecipitation. For in vitro experi-
ments, cell pellets were homogenized in lysis buffer contain-
ing 50 mmol/l of Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 150 mmol/l NaCl, 1mmol/l 
ethylenediaminetetraacetate (EDTA, NP40 1%) supple-
mented with protease inhibitor cocktail 1% (Sigma-Aldrich, 
Saint Quentin Fallavier, France) by sonication (10 seconds). 
For in vivo experiments, 50 muscle tissue sections (15 µm 
thickness) or one TA for immunoprecipitation were mechani-
cally homogenized in the lysis buffer using Fastprep Lysing 
Matrix D and Fastprep apparatus (MP Biomedical, Illkirch, 
France). After centrifugation (14,000×g, 4°C, 15 minutes), 
protein concentration in the supernatant was determined 
with the BCA Protein Assay Kit (Thermo Scientific Pierce, 
Villebon sur Yvette, France). 40 µg of protein were mixed 
with loading buffer (50 mmol/l Tris-HCl, sodium dodecyl 
sulfate (SDS) 2%, glycerol 10%, beta-mercaptoethanol 1% 
and bromophenol blue) and denaturated at 90°C for 5 min-
utes. Protein samples were separated on sodium dodecyl 
sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) 
10% and transferred onto polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) 
membranes (0.45 µm pore size, Life Technologies) overnight 
at 100 mA at 4°C. Membranes were blocked for 1 hour at 
room temperature in PBS containing nonfat dry milk (5%) 
and Tween20 (0.1%) and then exposed to the following 
primary antibodies: mouse monoclonal anti-Flag (Sigma 
F1804), rabbit polyclonal anti-DNM2 (Abcam ab3457, Cam-
bridge, UK) in PBS-Tween20 (0.1%), milk (1%) overnight at 
4°C. Membranes were rinsed in PBS-Tween20 (0.1%) and 
incubated 1 hour with secondary horseradish peroxidase-
conjugated antibodies (antimouse or antirabbit from Jackson 
ImmunoResearch, Suffolk, UK) in PBS-Tween20 (0.1%). 
Chemiluminescence were detected using ECL detection Kit 
(Merck-Millipore, Darmstadt, Germany). Acquisition was per-
formed on G-Box (Ozyme, Montigny-le-Bretonneux, France). 
For immunoprecipitation, cell or muscle protein extracts 
(1,200 µg) were diluted in 400 µl of lysis buffer (containing 50 
mmol/l of Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 150 mmol/l NaCl, 1mmol/l EDTA, 
NP40 1%, protease inhibitor 1%) and precleared with 30 µl 
washed protein G-Sepharose (PGS 4 fast flow; GE Healthcare, 
Orsay, France). Precleared lysates were then gently rolled over-
night at 4°C with 3 µg anti-DNM2 antibody (Abcam ab3457). 
Then, 30 µl washed PGS was added and gently rolled for 1 
hour at 4°C. Pelleted PGS was taken up in loading sample buf-
fer, boiled at 95°C for 5 minutes and submitted to western blot. </p>

<p>AAV production. AAV2/1 pseudotyped vectors were prepared 
by transfection in 293 cells as described previously 41 using the </p>

<p>www.moleculartherapy.org/mtna </p>

<p>Trans-splicing Strategies to Reprogram Dnm2 mRNA 
Trochet et al. </p>



<p>pSMD2-Dnm2-PTM plasmid, the pXX6 plasmid coding for the 
adenoviral sequences essential for AAV production, and the 
pRepCAp plasmid coding for AAV1 capsid. Vector particles 
were purified on iodixanol gradient and concentrated on Ami-
con Ultra-15 100K columns (Merck-Millipore). The particle titer 
(number of vg/ml) was determined by quantitative PCR. </p>

<p>Immunocytochemistry. For immunostaining, transfected 3T3 
cells were fixed 10 minutes at −20°C in methanol 48 hours 
after transfection. Cells were blocked 1 hour at room tempera-
ture in Tween 0.1%, Goat Serum 5%, Bovine serum albumin 
(BSA) 5% in PBS. Cells were then exposed to primary anti-
bodies: rabbit anti-C-terminal DNM2 (Abcam ab3457) and 
mouse anti Flag (Sigma F1804) in PBS containing BSA 1% 
and Tween 0.1% overnight at 4°C. Cells were rinsed in PBS 
and incubated 1 hour at room temperature with the secondary 
antibodies (Goat antimouse Alexa-Fluor 568 and Goat anti-
rabbit Alexa-Fluor 488, Life Technologies) and mounted using 
VECTASHIELD mounting medium with 4',6-diamidino-2-
phenylindole (DAPI) (Vector Laboratories, Peterborough, UK). 
For immunofluorescence on TA sections, cryosections (8 µm 
thick) were fixed in paraformaldehyde 4% (15 minutes at 
room temperature). After washing in PBS, cryosections were 
permeabilized in Triton X-100 (0.5%) in PBS for 10 minutes at 
room temperature and blocked in PBS-Triton X-100 (0.1%), 
BSA (5%) and Donkey serum (5%) for 30 minutes. Sections 
were incubated with primary antibodies: rabbit anti-C-terminal 
DNM2 (Abcam) and Goat anti Flag (Abcam) overnight at 4°C, 
in PBS with Triton X-100 (0.1%) and BSA (1%). After PBS-Tri-
ton X100 (0.1%) washes, sections were incubated with sec-
ondary antibodies (Donkey anti-Goat Alexa 568 and Donkey 
antirabbit Alexa 488, Life Technologies) added simultaneously 
for 60 minutes at room temperature. The slides were mounted 
with VECTASHIELD mounting medium (Vector Laboratories). 
Images were acquired using either axiophot microscope 
(Zeiss) or confocal microscope (Olympus FV-1000). </p>

<p>Histological analysis. Muscle cryosections (8 µm thickness) 
were stained with Hematoxylin-Eosin by standard method. 
Light microscopy was performed using an upright microscope 
(DMR, Leica, Nanterre, France). Images were captured using 
a monochrome camera (DS-Ri1; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Nikon</rs>) and <rs id="software-0" type="software">NIS-Elements 
BR</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.2</rs> software (Nikon). The area of fibres with internal 
nuclei was measured using the <rs type="software">NIS-Elements BR</rs> software 
and divided by the total area of the muscle section (n = 3 
cryosections for each condition). </p>

<p>Vg quantification. Genomic DNA was extracted from mouse 
muscles sections using DNA purification kit (Promega) 
according to the manufacturer's protocol. Copy numbers of 
AAV genome were measured on 100 ng of genomic DNA by 
quantitative real-time PCR on a LightCycler480 (Roche diag-
nostic, Meylan, France) by using TaqMan probe. A plasmid 
containing a part of the titin cDNA were tenfold serially diluted 
(from 10 7 to 10 1 copies) and used as a control to establish the 
standard curve for absolute quantification. The sequences of 
primers and Taqman probes are available on request. AAV 
genome copy number was expressed as an absolute value 
per ng of genomic DNA. All genomic DNA samples were ana-
lyzed in triplicates. </p>

<p>Supplementary material </p>

<p>Figure S1. Toxicity of 3′-PTM constructs in muscles. 
Figure S2. Events identified after 3′-PTM transduction in 
muscles. 
Figure S3. Events identified after expression of GFP-
inserted-3′-PTM in cells. 
Figure S4. Detection of 5′-trans-spliced Dynamin 2 protein in 
cells and muscles. 
Figure S5. Anti-Flag and anti-dynamin 2 immunofluores-
cence on 3T3 transfected cells. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments We thank the Pitié-Salpêtrière Imaging 
Platform (PICPS) for confocal imaging acquisition facilities. 
We thank the Penn Vector Core, Gene Therapy Program 
(University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia) for providing the 
plasmids for AAV construction and the vectorology platform 
of the Centre of Research in Myology-UMRS974 (Paris, 
France) for AAV production. This work was supported by 
the Institut National de la Santé et de la Recherche Médi-
cale (INSERM), the Association Institut de Myologie (AIM), 
the Université Pierre et Marie Curie-Paris6 (UPMC), the 
Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS) and 
a research grant from the Myotubular Trust (UK). Delphine 
Trochet was recipient of a Myotubular Trust fellowship. </p>



<p>Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids </p>

<p>Trans-splicing Strategies to Reprogram Dnm2 mRNA 
Trochet et al. </p>





<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International 
License. The images or other third party material in this article are 
included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated 
otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the 
Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission 
from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of 
this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>© The Author(s) (2016) </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on the Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids website (http://www.nature.com/mtna) </p>

</text></tei>