<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5129524" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:41+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Regeneration has captured the interest and imagination of people 
for centuries. Popularized in myths, science fiction, and even hor-
ror movies, regeneration of missing and damaged tissue is a com-
mon reality in the animal kingdom. Nearly every animal phyla 
contains at least some species that consistently regenerate all or 
certain tissues and structures (Bely and Nyberg, 2010; Somorjai  et al., 2012; Giangrande and Licciano, 2014). All deuterostome 
groups, with the possible exception of Xenoturbella, have at least 
some species with the capacity to regenerate (S anchez Alvarado,  2000). Numerous chordates, including lancelets, tunicates, frogs, 
fish, salamanders, and even humans are able to regenerate to 
some degree (Brown et al., 2009; Bely and Nyberg, 2010; Somor- jai et al., 2012; Giangrande and Licciano, 2014). Every extant </p>

<p>class of echinoderms have been reported to regenerate (Candia  Carnevali et al., 2009), while some species of hemichordates, which 
are a sister group to the echinoderms, undergo asexual reproduc-
tion and regenerate all anterior and posterior body parts when 
amputated (Willey 1899; Dawydoff 1902; Rao 1954; Rychel and  Swalla, 2008; Humphreys et al., 2010; Miyamoto and Saito, 2010). 
When and in what animal lineage did the ability to regenerate 
first evolve? Was regeneration a stem metazoan trait that was 
subsequently lost or reduced in numerous taxa or has regenera-
tion evolved independently several times across the metazoans? 
Porifera (Bely and Nyberg, 2010; Giangrande and Licciano,  2014), Cnidaria (Bosch, 2007; Dubuc et al., 2014), Ctenophora 
(Ryan et al., 2013; Moroz et al., 2014), and Placozoa (Bely and  Nyberg, 2010) have extensive regenerative abilities and, as basal 
metazoans, these lineages suggest an ancient and ancestral 
mechanism of regeneration. Comparing gene regulatory networks 
used during regeneration across various animal phyla will help to 
elucidate common molecular mechanisms of regeneration. 
Understanding the morphological and genetic basis of regener-
ation may yield clues to unlocking regeneration in animals with 
limited or no regenerative abilities, like humans. Millions of </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Com-
mons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits 
use and distribution in any medium, provided the original work is 
properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or 
adaptations are made. 
Grant sponsor: DGE; Grant number: 1256082; Grant sponsor: NIH; 
Grant number: R37GM057260; Grant sponsor: HHMI; Grant spon-
sor: DBI; Grant number: 0939454; Grant sponsor: Seeley Fund for 
Ocean Research on Tetiaroa. 
*Correspondence to: Billie J. Swalla, Biology Department, University of 
Washington, Seattle, WA 98195-1800. E-mail: bjswalla@u.washington. 
edu </p>

<p>Article is online at: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/dvdy. 
24457/abstract 
V C 2016 The Authors. Developmental Dynamics published by Wiley 
Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of American Association of Anatomists </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS 245:1159-1175, 2016 
DOI: 10.1002/DVDY.24457 </p>



<p>people suffer from neurodegenerative diseases, spinal cord inju-
ries, and limb amputations (Brown et al., 2005; Ziegler-Graham  et al., 2008; Mahabaleshwarkar and Khanna, 2014). Furthermore, 
aging and age-related diseases will eventually affect everyone. 
Regeneration may slow the aging process and stem cells present 
one feasible way to combat a multitude of diseases and injuries 
(Rando and Wyss-Coray, 2014). If regeneration is a stem deutero-
stome trait, it is likely that humans possess many, if not all, of 
the genetic switches controlling regeneration, but those switches 
have been modified or inactivated in some way over evolutionary 
time. It may, therefore, be possible to re-activate those pathways 
in humans using information gained from studying genetic mod-
els made from animals with extensive regenerative capabilities. 
We are seeking to identify the morphological and genetic 
underpinnings controlling regeneration in the solitary hemichor-
date, Ptychodera flava (Eschscholtz, 1825), which is a basal deu-
terostome and capable of regenerating all anterior and posterior 
structures when bisected (Rychel and Swalla, 2008; Humphreys  et al., 2010). It is critical to know when internal structures regen-
erate to use genetic knock downs and knock outs, as well as over-
expression, to characterize the function of genes directing the 
regeneration process. Moreover, hemichordates are the only deu-
terostome known to be able to regenerate an anterior head-like 
structure and entire central nervous system (CNS). Ptychodera 
flava progresses from a fertilized embryo to a planktonic, feeding 
larva that can remain in the water column for up to 300 days 
(Hadfield, 1978; Lin et al., 2016). Upon metamorphosis, the larva 
develops into a juvenile worm that settles to the ocean floor to 
begin a benthic lifestyle. Solitary hemichordates are exclusively 
marine and adult animals have a tripartite body plan with an 
anterior proboscis that is used for digging and burrowing in the 
sand and mud, a middle collar region with a hollow, dorsal neural 
tube in ptychoderid hemichordates, a ventral mouth between the 
proboscis and collar, and a long posterior trunk with pharyngeal 
gill slits and gonads in the anterior trunk, a hepatic region in the 
mid-trunk and a terminal anus (Balser and Ruppert, 1990; Brown  et el., 2008; Luttrell and Swalla, 2014). 
The hemichordate nervous system is quite interesting. Upon 
embryogenesis in direct developing hemichordates and metamor-
phosis in indirect developers, dorsal and ventral nerve cords 
develop along the full length of the trunk and nerve rings form 
around the base of the collar and the base of the proboscis (Balser  and Ruppert, 1990; Kaul and Stach, 2010; Miyamoto et al., 2010;  Miyamoto and Wada, 2013; Kaul-Strehlow et al., 2015). Adult 
echinoderms also develop nerve cords throughout each arm and a 
circumferential nerve ring around the central disc; however, it 
still remains to be determined whether echinoderm and hemi-
chordate nerve cords are homologous structures (Sly et al., 2002;  Holland et al., 2013). In addition to nerve cords, P. flava also 
develops a hollow, neural tube that is positioned dorsally in the 
collar region. Our lab has shown this structure forms from ecto-
derm that invaginates and rolls up forming a hollow tube, similar 
to chordate neurulation (Morgan, 1894; Luttrell et al., 2012;  Miyamoto and Wada, 2013; Luttrell and Swalla, 2014). 
Lastly, hemichordates have a diffuse nerve net throughout the 
ectoderm, similar to the adult tunicate, Ciona intestinalis (Balser  and Ruppert, 1990; Lowe et al., 2003; Dahlberg et al., 2009;  Miyamoto et al., 2010; Kaul-Strehlow et al., 2015). The adult 
acorn worm, in light of these similarities, has aspects of the dif-
ferent types of nervous systems that are present in the deuteros-
tomes. Remarkably, P. flava is able to regenerate all of these </p>

<p>structures, making hemichordates a model system to study nervous 
system evolution and regeneration in this clade of animals. Further-
more, as invertebrates, hemichordates lack the numerous genome 
duplications events present in the vertebrates (Dehal and Boore,  2005; Hughes and Liberles, 2008), thereby making functional studies 
of the regeneration genes more tractable in this animal. 
Here, we report the spatial and temporal regeneration of inter-
nal body structures to complement the previously published 
external morphology regeneration data (Willey, 1899; Rao, 1954;  Nishikawa, 1977; Rychel and Swalla, 2008; Humphreys et al.,  2010). We also include analyses of the transcriptome from regen-
erating P. flava animals. In total, eight different stages of regen-
eration were sequenced, assembled, and annotated to track 
changes in early gene expression that direct regeneration of ante-
rior structures. We document expression profiles and gene ontol-
ogies of hundreds of putative genes associated with anterior head 
regeneration. These data build a foundation for future experi-
ments that may show what genes are sufficient and necessary to 
start the regeneration program in P. flava. Our morphological 
data shows the regenerative response to these early changes in 
gene expression and we document complete anterior regeneration 
of the proboscis, collar, and anterior trunk. Furthermore, we 
uncovered morphological differences between early development 
and regeneration of anterior structures, including the neural tube. 
The assembled transcriptomes reported here not only complement 
recent P. flava developmental transcriptomes (Shu-Hwa et al.,  2014; Tagawa et al., 2014; Simakov et al., 2015), but also open 
the door to systematic comparisons of embryonic processes to 
regenerative events in hemichordates specifically, and deuteros-
tomes in general. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Regeneration of External and Internal Anterior 
Features in P. flava </p>

<p>Intact, healthy, adult worms (Fig. 1A) were bisected in the trunk 
between the branchial region and the hepatic sacs (Fig. 1B) and the 
posterior piece was monitored for regeneration signs at the cut site 
(Fig. 1C). The first observable change in tissue composition in Pty-
chodera flava is wound healing. This process is relatively rapid and 
takes place within the first 2 days following amputation at 26 
C. 
Wound healing culminates in ectoderm covering and sealing the 
open cut site (Fig. 1D-F). Over the next 3 days, a regeneration blas-
tema forms at the anterior end (Fig. 1G,H). Cells accumulate and 
proliferate in the blastema to yield a new, rudimentary anterior 
head, or proboscis (Fig. 1I). Between days 4 and 5 post bisection, the 
mouth has opened on the ventral side (Figs. 1J, 3D1-3). 
Over the next several days, cells continue to proliferate enlarg-
ing the proboscis and the collar begins to wrap around the base 
of the proboscis (Fig. 1K-T). The collar regenerates in the ventral 
and lateral positions first (Fig. 1K-P). Gill slits and gill bars start 
to form in the anterior most region of the trunk after 10 to 12 
days, before the collar ectoderm completely regenerates and 
closes on the dorsal side (Fig. 1Q-T). At 13 days post bisection, 
the ventral and lateral collar ectoderm has fully regenerated (Fig. 
2). The dorsal most region of the collar has not yet formed, but 
will continue to regenerate and finally close forming a continu-
ous ring around the neck region after approximately 2 weeks of 
regeneration. The epibranchial nerve ring that that wraps around 
the posterior collar is visible in the newly regenerated tissue and </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>



<p>forms as the collar regrows and not after the collar has fully 
shaped (Fig. 2). 
The internal regeneration morphology of P. flava is striking 
after the first day the animal is bisected. Both ectoderm and 
endoderm of the trunk region come together at the cut site and 
form a near continuous layer (Fig. 3A1). The folds of pre-existing 
endoderm are still present and the neural net is maintained below 
the ectoderm (Fig. 3A1). Existing muscle fibers of the trunk are 
still obvious at the anterior end where the wound has sealed (Fig. 
3A1). Hepatic collagen is visible below the ectoderm at the cut </p>

<p>site, denoting endoderm of the existing hepatic sacculations are 
taking part in wound healing (Fig. 3A1). On day 2 of regenera-
tion, the wound has completely healed and the ectoderm epitheli-
um is smooth and continuous (Fig. 3B1,B2). Dorsal and ventral 
blood vessels run the length of the animal, allowing blood cells 
to circulate. Blood is visible in the dorsal and ventral endoderm 
of the cut site, indicating that both blood vessels are likely sup-
plying blood to this region (Fig. 3B2). 
Hepatic collagen is still visible in the dorsal endoderm, sugges-
ting that at least parts of this tissue have not undergone apoptosis </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Regenerating anterior structures on Ptychodera flava. A: An intact, live animal. Anterior is to the left. The arrow indicates where the animal 
will be bisected. a ¼ anterior, p ¼ posterior. B: A bisected animal. AA, anterior end of the anterior half; PA, posterior end of the anterior half; AP, 
anterior end of the posterior half; PP, posterior end of the posterior half. C: The posterior half of the animal. The boxed area is the site of regenera-
tion. D: The cut site of the posterior half of the animal. E-H: One day (1d) through 4 days (4d) postcut, showing the open wound has healed and a 
regeneration blastema has formed in two different animals. The arrow in (G) marks the blastema. I,J: At 5 days post bisection (5d), the blastema 
has formed a rudimentary proboscis (PR) and the mouth (MO) is open on the ventral side. K-T: Six days (6d) through 15 days (15d) show the pro-
boscis (PR) the collar (CO) regenerating around the proboscis stalk in a ventral to dorsal manner. All views are dorsal and anterior is to the top 
except I, J, which are ventral views. Scale bars ¼ 1 mm. </p>

<p>HEAD REGENERATION IN HEMICHORDATES 1161 </p>

<p>or have been remodeled at this stage. By day 3 of regeneration, 
the blastema has formed a rudimentary proboscis (Fig. 3C1-4). A 
nerve net is present below the ectoderm in this region, at least 
partially originating from the existing trunk tissue and not whol-
ly regenerated de novo (Fig. 3C1-4). At this stage, a structure 
resembling the presumptive stomochord appears posterior to the 
rudimentary proboscis and also appears to be derived from endo-
dermal tissue (Fig. 3C3,C4). The hepatic sacculations are clearly 
visible in the existing trunk denoting the dorsal side and a thick 
nerve net is still present on the ventral side below the ectoderm 
posterior to the cut site (Fig. 3C1-C4). 
As the proboscis grows, anterior internal tissues continue to be 
elaborated. Hemichordates are tricoelomates, having separate 
coeloms in the proboscis, collar, and trunk regions. The proboscis 
coelom is fully formed after 4 days of regeneration (Fig. 3D1-3). 
The dorsal blood vessel flows anteriorly from the trunk, through 
the collar, ultimately forming the heart in the posterior proboscis 
(Benito and Pardos, 1997). The dorsal vessel has regenerated into 
the proboscis, filling the coelom with blood at 4 days postampu-
tation (Fig. 3D1-3). The mouth, which was visible in the external 
morphology at day 5, is clearly open in sagittal sections at day 4 
(Fig. 3D1-3). The stomochord is a stiff, rod-like structure in the 
posterior proboscis and provides structural support for the super-
imposing heart/kidney complex (Balser and Ruppert, 1990;  Rychel and Swalla, 2008; Miyamoto and Wada, 2013). The sto-
mochord is apparent in sections after 5 days of regeneration (Fig.  3E2-4). At this stage, the stomochord forms between the bound-
ary where ectoderm and endoderm meet. At this time, the heart-
kidney complex regenerates in the lateral and dorsal positions 
around the stomochord (Fig. 3E1-4). The dorsal blood vessel is 
obvious at this stage, flowing into the proboscis just above the </p>

<p>stomochord where the heart/kidney complex is regenerating (Fig. 
3E1-4). The ventral blood vessel is supplying blood and cells to 
the presumptive ventral collar coelom as well (Fig. 3E1-4). One 
day later, the regenerated collar coeloms can be seen in the dorsal 
and ventral regions (Fig. 3F1-4). The proboscis skeleton provides 
structure and support for the collar and overlying dorsal blood 
vessel and neural tube (Luttrell et al., 2012). The proboscis skele-
ton regenerates from endoderm in the collar region and is visible 
in endodermal inpocketing at 13 days postamputation (Fig. 4P). 
The hollow, dorsal neural tube, which is found only in the collar 
region in ptychoderid hemichordates, begins to form in the poste-
rior collar as the ectoderm closes on the dorsal side at 13 days 
postbisection (Fig. 4T). These morphological regenerative events 
are summarized in Table 1. </p>

<p>Dynamic and Discrete Cohorts of Gene Expression 
Patterns Are Observed During Early Stages of Head 
Regeneration </p>

<p>Regeneration of these morphological structures is driven by a sig-
nificant change in gene expression as evidenced by the transcrip-
tome data. A line graph was constructed to show clusters of up-
regulated, putative genes showing similar expression profiles 
along all time points sampled (Fig. 5A). Nearly all genes in cluster 
A are significantly up-regulated 2 hr after the animal is bisected; 
however, the expression level of these genes steadily and drasti-
cally declines beginning 6 hr into the regeneration process. A 
heatmap of cluster A identifies the individual, putative genes and 
their expression profile across all time points (Fig. 5B). Heatmaps 
of the genes in cluster B shows overall expression is near baseline </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Regenerating collar on Ptychodera flava at 13 days (13d) postamputation. A: An illustration showing the cut site in the trunk between the 
genital wings and the hepatic sacs. B: Dorsal view showing the collar has not completely closed and regeneration is incomplete. Three gill slits 
have formed in the anterior trunk. C: Ventral view of the collar on the same animal showing complete closure and regeneration of the ectoderm. 
Arrows indicate the dorsal nerve cord in the trunk in (B) and the ventral nerve cord in (C). The arrowheads indicate the epibranchial nerve ring 
formed at the base of the collar. Scale bars are 1mm. </p>



<p>values at the 2-hr time point, but then expression increases sig-
nificantly after 6 hr and is elevated approximately 8-fold higher 
than control animals after 4 days of regeneration (Fig. 5C). 
Heatmaps of the cluster C and cluster D genes show similar 
expression profiles, both being only slightly elevated after 2 hr of 
regeneration and then progressively increasing until the 24-hr 
time point, at which time both clusters begin to show decreased 
expression levels, with cluster C displaying the most dramatic 
decrease (Fig. 5D,E). However, expression of putative genes in 
both clusters still remain over two log fold change higher than 
controls after 4 days of regeneration. 
Down-regulated, putative genes were also identified and 
grouped into clusters of similar expression domains. A line graph </p>

<p>shows four clusters of predicted genes with very different expres-
sion profiles (Fig. 6A). Heatmaps of cluster A show overall expres-
sion levels slightly below baseline values between 2 and 6 hr of 
regeneration and then expression gradually decreases with a steep 
decline between 3 and 4 days of regeneration. A detailed listing of 
these putative genes is included in Figure 7. Cluster B genes also 
start off at near baseline values and expression steadily decreases; 
however, this group of genes reverses at the 48-hr time point and 
expression levels begin to increase, although overall expression 
of this cluster remains significantly down-regulated at the 96-hr 
time point compared with control animals (Fig. 8). 
Predicted genes in cluster C show an interesting expression 
pattern along all sampled time points. Expression is initially </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>

<p>Fig. 3. A1-F4: Sagittal sections of Ptychodera flava anterior regeneration days 1-6 (A-F). Sections were made through the mid-sagittal area 
showing the internal morphology of proboscis and early collar regeneration. cc, collar coelom; dv, dorsal vessel; E, ectoderm; En, endoderm; hc, 
hepatic collagen; hs, hepatic sacculations; m, muscle; mo, mouth; nn, nerve net; p, proboscis; pc, proboscis coelom; pst, presumptive stomo-
chord; st, stomochord; vv, ventral vessel. Scale bars ¼ 1 mm and all sections are at the same magnification. All sections are anterior up and dor-
sal to the right and ventral to the left. All sections are stained with Milligan's trichrome stain. Collagen ¼ green; nuclei, muscle ¼ magenta. </p>

<p>HEAD REGENERATION IN HEMICHORDATES 1163 </p>

<p>significantly reduced by over three log fold compared with con-
trol animals at the 2-hr time point and then expression sharply 
increases over the next 2 hr, only to abruptly decrease again to 
nearly an 8-fold change from control animals at the 6-hr time 
point. Expression levels then steadily elevate again over the next 
18 hr, at which point expression sharply declines again between 
24 and 48 hr of regeneration, with expression values greater than 
8-fold lower than control animals. Expression then rebounds </p>

<p>over the next 48 hr and returns to around the same levels mea-
sured at the 2-hr time point, which is still nearly four log fold 
lower than expression in control animals (Fig. 6B). Cluster D 
genes are initially down-regulated after 2 hr of regeneration, but 
are significantly up-regulated from baseline levels at the 96-hr 
time point (Fig. 6C). Additionally, a heatmap was constructed for 
putative transcription factors and their relative expression com-
pared with control animals over all time points (Fig. 9). </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Cross-sections of Ptychodera flava anterior regeneration days 9-15. All sections are stained with Milligan's trichrome at four different 
stages of regeneration: 9 days, 11 days, 13 days, and 15 days postamputation. A: Diagram of P. flava showing approximate locations of sections. 
Row (1) is taken through the posterior proboscis in all four regeneration stages. Row (2) is taken through the anterior collar. Row (3) is taken 
through the mid collar. Row (4) is taken through the posterior collar. dv, dorsal vessel; E, ectoderm; En, endoderm; h-k, heart-kidney complex; Nt, 
neural tube; ps, proboscis skeleton; st, stomochord. Scale bars ¼ 1 mm in B-E; 0.1 mm in F-U. B-U: Dorsal views with anterior to the right in (B-
E) and dorsal to the top in (F-U). All sections are stained with Milligan's trichrome stain. Collagen, green; nuclei, muscle ¼ magenta. </p>



<p>Gene Activity Associated With Cell Proliferation and 
Metabolic Changes is Prominently Detected in the 
Early Stages of P. flava Head Regeneration </p>

<p>Gene ontology (GO) analysis was completed to categorize the 
function of differentially expressed putative genes. We display 
the number of genes per significantly enriched GO term for 72 hr 
and 96 hr and no other time points because there was no enrich-
ment for the other time points. Over half of the significantly 
enriched genes for which we have GO annotations play a role in 
cell proliferation and differentiation, as well as organ morpho-
genesis (Fig. 10A). Approximately 12% of the significantly 
enriched genes for which we have GO annotations are involved 
with cell signaling (Fig. 10A). Predicted orthologs of highly con-
served developmental pathways were detected, including mem-
bers of the Wnt signaling pathway, the fibroblast growth factor 
signaling pathway, and the Notch signaling pathway (Fig. 10A). 
We further classified the amount of both up-and down-
regulated genes at the 72-hr time point and 96-hr time point 
into biological processes, molecular function, and cellular com-
ponent categories (Fig. 10B). The vast majority of up-regulated 
genes at the 3-and 4-day time points are involved with extra-
cellular space and matrix roles (Fig. 10B). At 72 hr post bisection, 
hundreds of genes are up-regulated for biological processes, 
such as cell adhesion and lipid metabolism (Fig. 10B). Genes 
regulating small molecule and single organism metabolic pro-
cesses on the other hand are down-regulated after 72 hr of 
regeneration, as well as numerous genes involved with oxidore-
ductase activity (Fig. 10B). Biological process genes aligned with 
aging, extracellular structure organization and matrix organiza-
tion are down-regulated at the 96-hr time point (Fig. 10B). The 
cellular component categories of extracellular space and region 
part, as well as oxidoreductase activity in the molecular func-
tion category are also down-regulated at 96 hr post bisection 
(Fig. 10B). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>External Regeneration Morphology </p>

<p>Ptychoderid hemichordate regeneration is a remarkable process 
that results in external structures regenerating in an anterior to 
posterior manner patterned off the existing body axis. This is 
similar to juvenile worm development in P. flava and another 
ptychoderid hemichordate, Balanoglossus simodensis, when the 
proboscis forms first during metamorphosis (Miyamoto et al.,  2010; Lin et al., 2016). The collar and trunk then differentiate 
and the trunk elongates. One difference between development 
and regeneration, however, is that gill slits start to regenerate 
before the collar has fully formed, unlike early development in 
direct developing hemichordates when gill slits form after the 
collar and trunk have delineated from one another (Kaul-Streh- low and Stach, 2013; Kaul-Strehlow et al., 2015). 
Furthermore, during direct development, the neural tube also 
starts to invaginate from dorsal, collar ectoderm in the posterior 
region of the collar before the first gill slit formation (Kaul-Streh- low and Stach, 2013); however, we show in this study that the 
first gill slit regenerates at least 2 days before the neural tube 
begins to form in the indirect developing P. flava. Few studies 
directly compare development or regeneration of the neural tube 
and gill slits in ptychoderid worms, but two studies state that the 
collar develops or regenerates before the branchial region (Niel- sen and Hay-Schmidt, 2007: Humphreys et al., 2010). This is not 
evidence that the neural tube specifically has developed at this 
point and future studies will need to confirm the timing of devel-
opment of the neural tube compared with development of the 
branchial region in P. flava. These differences, however, do show 
a potential temporal plasticity during regeneration of anterior 
structures in P. flava. 
During regeneration, cells proliferate and accumulate to form a 
blastema at the cut site, which then differentiate to replace </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Regeneration Timetable in Ptychodera flava at 26°C </p>

<p>Ptychodera flava anterior regeneration timetable at 26 
C </p>

<p>Days of regeneration </p>

<p>Regeneration events 
1-2 
3-4 
5-6 
7-8 
9-10 
11-12 
13-15 </p>

<p>Wound healing 
X 
PCNA positive cells (Rychel &amp; Swalla, 2008)  X 
X 
X 
X 
Nerve net 
X 
X 
Blastema 
X 
Proboscis 
X 
X 
X 
Proboscis coelom 
X 
Dorsal vessel 
X 
Mouth 
X 
X 
Stomochord 
X 
X 
Collar coelom 
X 
Ventral and lateral collar 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Heart/kidney complex 
X 
X 
X 
Proboscis skeleton 
X 
X 
Gill slits 
X 
X 
Dorsal collar 
X 
Neural tube 
X </p>

<p>PCNA, proliferating cell nuclear antigen. </p>

<p>HEAD REGENERATION IN HEMICHORDATES 1165 </p>

<p>missing or damaged tissue. The question remains whether these 
proliferating cells are bona fide stem cells occupying an unknown 
niche that are recruited to the cut site or are these somatic cells 
that have undergone de-differentiation and returned to a </p>

<p>progenitor cell state and then assigned new fates in the regener-
ating tissue? Numerous genes in P. flava are both up-and down-
regulated beginning just 2 hr after the animal is bisected. Differ-
ential gene expression increases rapidly during the early time </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Up-regulated gene cluster expression patterns in regenerating Ptycodera flava. A: The line graph shows all putative genes that are initially 
up-regulated and cluster together in their expression profiles along all time points sampled. Red, cluster A genes; green, cluster B genes; blue, 
cluster C genes; and purple, cluster D genes. The X-axis is time of regeneration and the Y-axis is the log2 fold change in gene expression com-
pared with control animals. B-E: Heatmaps showing the individual genes identified in clusters A, B, C, D, respectively. </p>



<p>points sampled in this study resulting in wound healing and may 
drive regeneration through the recruitment of stem cells to the 
cut site forming the regeneration blastema within 3 to 4 days </p>

<p>postamputation. Rychel and Swalla (2008) showed that prolifer-
ating cell nuclear antigen positive cells are found in scattered 
mesenchyme cells throughout the tissue near the cut site by day 2 
of regeneration at 28 
C in P. flava. There is some slight variation 
in wound healing and blastema growth times between the results 
reported by Rychel and Swalla (2008) and here, but the overall 
results are consistent. Our lab is currently working to determine 
the origin and molecular profile of these proliferating cells to ver-
ify whether these are stem cells or de-differentiated somatic cells. 
We are using stem cell markers in regenerating and nonregener-
ating animals to detect molecular signatures consistent with 
known stem cell lines. </p>

<p>Internal Regeneration Morphology </p>

<p>While epidermal tissue regenerates anterior to posterior, internal 
structures appear to regenerate based on need and function. The 
mouth, which is critical to feeding and thereby supports the high 
metabolic cost of regeneration, forms and opens after just 4 days. 
The worm does not burrow and ingest sand to deposit feed at this 
point; however, they are likely taking in organic nutrients sus-
pended in the water column. Regenerating worms start to burrow 
in sand around 10 days postbisection. Blood vessels and mechan-
ical support elements for vital organs and tissues also seem to be 
essential as these are among the first internal structures in the 
new tissue. 
The stomochord in the posterior proboscis is vacuolated and 
acts as a hydrostatic skeleton, providing support for the heart-
kidney complex (Miyamoto and Wada, 2013). Several studies 
have shown that, in both direct and indirect developing acorn 
worms, the stomochord is elaborated from endoderm during 
juvenile worm development (Kaul-Strehlow and Stach, 2013;  Miyamoto and Wada, 2013; Satoh et al., 2014). At 3 days postbi-
section, we show what may be the presumptive stomochord 
regenerating from endoderm; however, the identity of this struc-
ture is not clear. At this stage, it is not positioned directly below 
the future heart/kidney complex in the proboscis as the stomo-
chord should be, but rather it is more internal in the presumptive 
collar region. This structure could also be the hydropore, which is 
a rounded tube, but that is also not in the correct position, as the 
hydropore is in the dorsal proboscis/collar ectoderm region and 
expels circulating waste from the proboscis coelom to the envi-
ronment (R€ ottinger and Martindale, 2011). It may be that the 
angle of the sections is not exactly sagittal, at which point inter-
nal structures may appear skewed. It may also be that regenerat-
ing structures look out of place during the early stages. Future 
studies will be needed using molecular markers to confirm the 
identity of this structure. 
This study does clearly show, however, that the stomochord is 
elaborated from tissue at the ectoderm/endoderm boundary at 5 
days postbisection. Tracing the anterior proboscis ectoderm to the 
anterior stomochord shows that ectoderm is definitely connected 
to this structure. Conversely, tracing the endodermal tissue to the 
posterior stomochord also shows that it is definitely connected to 
this tissue. So the question remains; at what point does endoderm 
become ectoderm? Our lab is using endodermal and ectodermal 
molecular markers to answer this provocative question and deter-
mine from what tissue type the stomochord regenerates. 
The proboscis skeleton is cartilaginous and provides a rigid 
framework to protect the collar and overlying dorsal blood vessel 
and neural tube. The proboscis skeleton regenerates from </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Down-regulated gene cluster expression patterns in regenerating 
Ptycodera flava. A: The line graph shows all putative genes that are initially 
down-regulated and cluster together in their expression profiles along all 
time points sampled. Red, cluster A genes; green, cluster B genes; blue, 
cluster C genes; and purple, cluster D genes. The X-axis is time of regen-
eration and the Y-axis is the log2 fold change in gene expression com-
pared with control animals. B,C: Heatmaps showing the individual genes 
in clusters C and D, respectively. Heatmaps and identities of genes in 
clusters A and B are included in Figures 7 and 8, respectively. </p>

<p>HEAD REGENERATION IN HEMICHORDATES 1167 </p>

<p>endoderm, similar to early development (Luttrell et al., 2012;  Miyamoto and Wada, 2013). A key difference is that the probos-
cis skeleton and dorsal vessel regenerate before neural tube 
regeneration. During normal development this process is reversed 
and the dorsal vessel and neural tube develop before the probos-
cis skeleton (Luttrell et al., 2012). Another major difference is the 
way the neural tube regenerates. During normal development, 
dorsal collar ectoderm invaginates, rolls up forming a hollow 
tube. During regeneration, the neural tube begins to form at day </p>

<p>13 as the collar ectoderm nears closure on the dorsal side. It is the 
closure of this ectoderm that actually forms the tube and not 
from invaginating ectoderm after the collar fully regenerates and 
closes. 
This study shows that regeneration in P. flava does not strictly 
follow the developmental program and there are morphological 
steps that are regeneration specific. Furthermore, Arimoto and  Tagawa (2015) showed that the hedgehog gene, which is highly 
conserved in the metazoans (Adamska et al., 2007) and involved </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Down-regulated gene cluster A expression patterns in regenerating P. flava. The heatmap shows the individual genes in cluster A of Figure 
6 and their expression profile along all time points sampled compared with control animals. </p>

<p>1168 LUTTRELL ET AL. </p>

<p>with both morphogenesis and regeneration (Huangfu and Ander- son, 2006; Rink et al., 2009), is expressed in both the pharyngeal 
endoderm and anterior tip of P. flava larvae, however, it is only 
expressed in the pharyngeal region during regeneration in P. 
flava. The regenerating proboscis tip does not express hedgehog 
and this evidence suggests there are different gene expression 
patterns that are regeneration specific in P. flava as well. 
In the vertebrates, the notochord and dorsal vessel secrete sig-
naling molecules to partially pattern the neural tube and </p>

<p>peripheral nervous system, respectively. The notochord secretes 
sonic hedgehog, signaling the overlying ectoderm to become 
neural, invaginate and roll up forming the neural tube, while the 
dorsal blood vessel secretes bone morphogenetic protein mole-
cules that signal neural crest cells to become peripheral neurons 
(Rickmann et al., 1985; Altaba et al., 1995; Briscoe et al., 1999;  Schneider et al. 1999; Young et al., 2004). Hemichordates lack a 
notochord; therefore, the dorsal vessel may play a pivotal role in 
guiding CNS formation in the collar region during early </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>

<p>Fig. 8. Down-regulated gene cluster B expression patterns in regenerating P. flava. The heatmap shows the individual genes in cluster B of Fig-
ure 6 and their expression profile along all time points sampled compared with control animals. </p>

<p>HEAD REGENERATION IN HEMICHORDATES 1169 </p>

<p>development. The dorsal vessel may still be directing this process 
during regeneration as this structure is formed and has regener-
ated into the proboscis by day 4. The tissue directly above the </p>

<p>dorsal vessel in the collar region is thickened with a rich nerve 
net by 9 days postbisection and this tissue will become the ven-
tral part of the neural tube. It is likely that signals directing a </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>

<p>Fig. 9. Differential gene expression of putative transcription factors in regenerating P. flava. A heatmap showing the identity and expression pro-
file of all transcription factors that were both up and down-regulated across all time points sampled compared with control animals. </p>

<p>Fig. 10. Select GO terms of differentially expressed genes in regenerating P. flava. A: The X-axis is the percentage of genes that are differentially 
expressed in the biological processes on the Y-axis. B: The X-axis is the number of genes that were grouped into each gene ontology term on the Y-axis. </p>



<p>neural tube fate are coming on early during collar regeneration, 
before the dorsal, collar ectoderm being present, and these signals 
may be emanating from the dorsal vessel. 
Regeneration of the branchial region starts to occur before the 
collar closes dorsally and the neural tube forms. Between days 10 
and 12, the first gill slit appears directly between the regenerating 
collar and the existing hepatic sacs. The regenerating branchial 
region in P. flava contains both pigmented and unpigmented 
cells. The anterior most branchial region closest to the collar is 
clear to white, while the posterior regenerating branchial region 
closest to the original cut site contains pigmented cells. Rychel  and Swalla (2008) used a TUNEL (terminal deoxynucleotidyl 
transferase-mediated deoxyuridinetriphosphate nick end-label-
ing) assay to show numerous apoptotic cells in the endoderm of 
the hepatic sacs near the cut site 8 days after amputation. This 
suggests that, while the anterior most branchial tissue is likely 
elaborated from newly generated, unpigmented proliferating 
cells, the cells in the tissue closest to the cut site undergo apopto-
sis and the tissue is remodeled from the existing cells in the 
hepatic region. This hypothesis remains to be confirmed, but it 
will be exciting if internal structures regenerate using both stem 
cells and somatic cells in P. flava because it will provide a model 
to study two different modes of regenerating tissue in a stem 
deuterostome. </p>

<p>Expression of Putative Vertebrate Anterior Head Genes </p>

<p>Understanding the genetic and morphological basis of regenera-
tion in hemichordates is vital to unlocking more extensive neural 
regeneration in humans. No vertebrate has been shown to be able 
to regenerate an anterior head or an entire CNS. Vertebrates that 
are capable of regenerating a small part of their CNS, like fish 
and amphibians (Slack et al., 2008; Sîrbulescu and Zupanc, 2010;  Kroehne et al., 2011; Lau et al., 2013), possess numerous copies 
of single genes due to whole genome duplication events (Dehal  and Boore, 2005; Hughes and Liberles, 2008). This genetic redun-
dancy complicates functional studies of key genes controlling the 
regeneration process. Hemichordates not only lack whole genome 
duplications, but consistently regenerate their anterior head and 
complete CNS and, therefore, present a remarkable model system 
to study and uncover key genetic switches directing regeneration 
of anterior structures in the deuterostomes. 
Several studies have detailed expression of genes involved 
with chordate brain and spinal cord development in the direct 
developing hemichordate, Saccoglossus kowalevskii (Lowe et al.,  2003; Pani et al., 2012: R€ ottinger and Lowe, 2012). These orthol-
ogous genes show a similar spatial distribution of chordate pat-
terning along the anterior-posterior body axis in S. kowalevskii. 
Numerous chordate forebrain genes are expressed in the develop-
ing hemichordate proboscis region while chordate midbrain genes 
are expressed in the hemichordate collar region and chordate 
hindbrain and spinal cord genes are expressed in the hemichor-
date trunk region (Lowe et al., 2003; Pani et al., 2012; R€ ottinger  and Lowe, 2012). These overlapping similarities suggest that at 
least parts of the gene regulatory networks that pattern the chor-
date CNS were likely present in the common ancestor of the deu-
terostomes and the hemichordate proboscis and collar could be 
considered an early representation of the chordate head. No chor-
date has been shown to regenerate an anterior head or CNS after 
complete amputation and, therefore, hemichordates are vital to </p>

<p>revealing gene networks regulating CNS regeneration in the 
deuterostomes. 
We compared regeneration in P. flava and identified several 
putative orthologs of chordate CNS patterning genes that are up-
regulated after 3 and 4 days of regeneration. The regeneration 
blastema has formed at these time points, and cells continue to 
proliferate to generate a rudimentary proboscis at 3 to 4 days 
postbisection of the animal. Sine oculis homeobox 3 (six3), dis-
tal-less (dll), paired box homeobox 6 (pax6), and frizzled-5 are all 
significantly up-regulated at the 96-hr time point, which is just 
as the proboscis begins to form. Six3, Pax6, and dll are transcrip-
tion factors that are involved with patterning the chordate fore-
brain (Echevarria et al., 2003; Wilson and Houart, 2004; Paek  et al., 2009). Frizzled-related Wnt antagonists have been shown 
to be necessary and sufficient to establish the telencephalon 
region of the chordate brain (Houart et al., 2002; Paek et al.,  2009). Of the 26 putative transcription factors identified as being 
differentially expressed in this study, 7 of them are known to be 
involved in head and neural development and they are all signifi-
cantly up-regulated 3 and 4 days into regeneration as the rudi-
mentary proboscis is beginning to form. It is likely that other 
chordate head genes are up-regulated during anterior regenera-
tion in P. flava, but they are possibly expressed at later time 
points as the proboscis continues to regenerate and the collar 
begins to form. Future studies will be aimed at identifying these 
transcripts and their expression domains. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>We have shown that Ptychodera flava regeneration is not strictly 
a morphological recapitulation of development. There is exten-
sive temporal plasticity during regeneration, as well as different 
modes of acquiring the same anterior structures. Putative ortho-
logs of chordate head genes are also significantly up-regulated 
just before anterior proboscis regeneration. It will be interesting 
and informative to discover whether additional head genes are 
expressed as the proboscis and collar undergo regeneration and 
we will then use in situ hybridization to localize gene expression 
in regenerating tissues. 
The origin of blastemal cells in P. flava still remains to be 
determined. Our lab is currently working to determine whether 
this animal uses genuine stem cells or dedifferentiated somatic 
cells to propagate missing tissue. In humans, when a cell differ-
entiates into a particular cell type, the cell fate assignment nor-
mally cannot be reversed or transformed. If hemichordates are 
using dedifferentiated cells to elaborate new tissue, this may 
reveal cell signaling pathways necessary for the gain and loss of 
cell fates in the deuterostomes. </p>

<p>Experimental Procedures </p>

<p>Animal Collection and Management </p>

<p>Ptychodera flava were collected at Paiko Peninsula in Honolulu, 
Hawaii, in early November. During low tide, when the water level 
was approximately 3 feet deep, animals were removed from the 
coral beds by snorkeling. The light sand cover was fanned by 
hand to expose the underlying coral and hemichordates. Animals 
were collected into 50-ml tubes and carried back to the lab with 
the tubes immersed in a cooler with sea water. </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>

<p>HEAD REGENERATION IN HEMICHORDATES 1171 </p>

<p>Animals were bisected at the level of the anterior hepatic sacs 
and allowed to regenerate for various time points (Figs. 1 and 2). 
Regenerating worms were kept in running seawater tanks at 
Kewalo Marine Laboratory at 27 
C during regeneration. Some 
worms were collected and shipped to the University of Washing-
ton in Seattle, Washington, and kept at 26 
C while regenerating. 
Animals were immersed in a 1:1 solution of sea water and 7.5% 
MgCl 2 for 15 min to relax muscles and constrain movement and 
then observed with a Nikon 1000 dissecting microscope and pho-
tographed with a Cool Snap camera. Pictures were taken daily for 
15 days and near daily thereafter until 55 days post bisection. </p>

<p>Histology </p>

<p>Regenerating animals were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde in 
phosphate-buffered saline overnight at room temperature and 
stored at -20 
C in 100% methanol. They were placed into 100% 
ethanol for, 20 min at room temperature and then moved to a 1:1 
mixture of 100% ethanol and polyester wax (nine parts Poly (eth-
ylene glycol) [400] distearate and one part 1-hexadecanol, (Poly-
sciences, Warrington, PA) (Steedman, 1957; Norenburg and  Barrett 1987) at 40 
C for 1 hr. The animals were then moved to 
100% polyester wax at 40 
C for 1 hr and then embedded in fresh 
100% polyester wax. Next, 7-mm sections were cut on a Spencer 
829 microtome and mounted on gelatin subbed slides. Slides 
were deparaffinized, and processed through Milligan's trichrome 
staining, a histological stain that differentiates muscle cells, 
nuclei, and cartilage (Fig. 3; Presnell and Schreibman, 1997). 
Slides were rinsed in 95% ethanol and treated for 5 min with 
potassium dichromate HCl mordant and then rinsed in distilled 
water. Slides were then stained for 5 min in acid fuchsin (Sigma, 
St. Louis, MO) and rinsed again in distilled water. Slides were 
then stained 5 min in phosphomolybdic acid (Sigma) followed by 
5 min in Orange G (Sigma) and then rinsed in distilled water. 
Finally, slides were treated for 2 min in 1% glacial acetic acid 
and stained 5 min with Fast Green FCF (Sigma) and then treated 
again for 3 min with 1% glacial acetic acid. Slides were dehy-
drated with ethanol and mounted with Permount (Fisher Scientif-
ic, Pittsburgh, PA). Sections were photographed using a Nikon 
Eclipse E600 microscope mounted with a Cool Snap camera. </p>

<p>RNA Isolation and cDNA Preparation </p>

<p>Following bisection, animals were allowed to regenerate for 
either 2 hr, 4 hr, 6 hr, 12 hr, 24 hr, 48 hr, 72 hr, or 96 hr. Between 
50 and 100 mg of tissue were removed with a sterile, feather sur-
gical blade from the cut site of the posterior segment in four 
regenerating animals at each time point (Fig. 1A-C). Four 
healthy, intact animals were bisected and total RNA was isolated 
from the cut site of the posterior half to serve as reference con-
trols. RNA was isolated from the tissue using either a Promega 
SV Total RNA Isolation System, catalog number Z3100, or a USB 
PrepEase RNA Spin Kit, part number 78766 1 KT. RNA was ana-
lyzed on a NanoDrop ND-1000 spectrophotometer for nucleic 
acid concentration and purity and then stored at -80 
C until 
cDNA was synthesized using the SuperScriptV R III First-Strand 
Synthesis System for RT-PCR by Invitrogen. </p>

<p>cDNA Library Preparation and Sequencing </p>

<p>mRNAseq libraries for sequencing were generated from 1 to 1.5 
mg of high quality total RNA, as assessed using the Agilent 2100 
Bioanalyzer. RNA was purified using poly-T oligo-attached mag-
netic beads. Libraries were made according to the manufacturer's 
directions for the TruSeq RNA Sample Prep Kit v2 (Illumina, RS-
122-2101). Resulting short fragment libraries were checked for 
quality and quantity using the Bioanalyzer. Equal molar libraries 
were pooled, requantified and sequenced as 100 bp paired read 
on the Illumina HiSeq, 2000 instrument using <rs id="software-9" type="software">HiSeq Control</rs> 
Software <rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-number">1.5.15</rs>. Following sequencing, Illumina Primary Analy-
sis version RTA 1.13.48 and <rs id="software-11" type="software">Secondary Analysis</rs> version 
<rs corresp="#software-11" type="version-number">CASAVA-1.8.2</rs> were run to demultiplex reads for all libraries and 
generate FASTQ files. </p>

<p>Transcriptome Assembly and Annotation </p>

<p>To create a reference for expression analysis, paired end sequence 
files from all P. flava experimental time points were pooled 
(605,821,125 pairs totaling 122,164,225,000 bp) and assembled 
using Trinity, version r2013-02-25, (Grabherr et al., 2011), with 
default parameters. We vector clipped and contaminate filtered 
the resulting assembly with SeqClean, version, 2011-02-22, (Seq- Clean, 2011). The resulting transcriptome reference contained 
527,715 sequences, with an average length of 1,022, and N50 of 
1,961, 208,773 of these sequences contain an ORF of at least 60 
amino acids. All sequences were used for expression analysis 
with sequences from the same Trinity "component," roughly 
equal to a gene, treated as a single gene. 
To maximize the utility of this transcriptome assembly, 
sequences were annotated with the best BLASTx (Camacho et al.,  2008) hit to Swissprot (UniProt, 2015) and NCBI's NR database, 
using an e-value cutoff of 0.001. We also identified PFAM (Finn  et al., 2014) domains present in P. flava transcripts using 
<rs id="software-14" type="software">hmmscan</rs>, version <rs corresp="#software-14" type="version-number">3.1b1</rs>, from the <rs id="software-15" type="software">HMMER package</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-15" type="creator">Eddy</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-15" type="version-date">2011</rs>)  with an e-value cutoff of 0.01. In addition, we annotated these 
transcripts with tmhmm, version 2.0c, (Krogh et al., 2001) signalP 
version 4.1 (Petersen et al., 2011), and ncoils (Lupas et al., 1991). 
We identified putative transcription factors based on PFAM 
domain hits using a list from transcriptionfactor.org. For tran-
scripts with multiple isoforms, annotations were collapsed to the 
gene level as determined by Trinity. </p>

<p>Differential Expression Analysis </p>

<p>To identify differentially expressed genes, single end reads from 
each time point were aligned to the transcriptome using Bowtie2 
(Langmead and Salzberg, 2012) with default parameters. Align-
ments were quantified using Samtools (Li et al., 2009). Isoform 
counts were summed to generate a "per gene" count. Differential 
expression analysis and normalization was performed using the 
R package DESeq2 (Love et al., 2014). All time points were con-
trasted with the zero hour (0 hr) time point. Data used for the 
gene expression analysis have been deposited in the Gene 
Expression Omnibus (GEO) under accession number GSE70295. </p>

<p>Hierarchical Clustering and Heatmaps </p>

<p>To select genes of interest for clustering, differentially expressed 
genes (P &lt; 1e-5), having an expression level log2 fold change 
greater than one or less than negative one, for one or more time </p>

<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>



<p>points, and having a hit to the Swissprot protein database were 
identified. These genes were hierarchically clustered on the dis-
tances of the Pearson correlation of the log2 fold change, using 
the complete linkage method to find similar clusters (Figs. 5 and  6, 7, 8). Significantly differentially expressed genes (P &lt; 1e-5) 
that had transcription factor domains were clustered on the dis-
tances of the Pearson correlation of the log2 fold change, using 
Ward's minimum variance method to find similar clusters (Fig. 
9). All heatmaps were created using the R package <rs id="software-20" type="software">pheatmap</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-20" type="creator">Kolde</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-20" type="version-date">2013</rs>). </p>

<p>Gene Ontology Analysis </p>

<p>Gene Ontology (GO) (Gene Ontology, 2015) terms were assigned 
to each P. flava gene based upon homologous PFAM domains 
and significant Swissprot hits. These terms were used to impute 
functional categories of differentially expressed genes and calcu-
late categorical enrichment. The GO slim terms used were from 
the generic GO slim terms list available at the Gene Ontology 
Web site. GO term enrichment was performed using the R pack-
age <rs id="software-21" type="software">topGO</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-21" type="creator">Alexa and Rahnenfuhrer</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-21" type="version-date">2010</rs>). To examine higher-
level GO terms, significantly enriched (P &lt; 0.01) GO terms were 
mapped to select higher-level GO terms using GO.db. These select 
GO terms were then mapped to the significantly differentially 
expressed genes (P &lt; 1e-5) (Fig. 10). </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Dr. Michael Hadfield for allowing us to use his seawater 
tanks, microscopes, and lab space at Kewalo Marine Laboratory. 
We also thank the Seeley family for their encouragement and their 
generous donation from the Seeley Fund for Ocean Research on 
Tetiaroa. This work was also funded in part by NIH to Dr. Alejandro 
S anchez Alvarado. Dr. Alejandro S anchez Alvarado is a Howard 
Hughes Medical Institute and Stowers Institute for Medical 
Research Investigator. This material is based upon work supported 
by the National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship 
Program to Shawn Luttrell. Additionally, this material is also based 
in part upon work supported by the National Science Foundation. 
Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations 
expressed in this material are those of the author(s) and do not nec-
essarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation. 
Shawn Luttrell is a Ph.D. candidate in the Swalla Lab at the Univer-
sity of Washington and collected all animals and performed all 
regeneration experiments, RNA isolation, sectioning and histolo-
gy, constructed the figures, and wrote the manuscript, including 
the figure legends. Dr. Billie J. Swalla is a Principal Investigator 
and oversaw all aspects of animal collection and disposition, 
regeneration experiments, histology, and manuscript preparation 
and editing. Dr. Alejandro S anchez Alvarado is a Principal Investi-
gator at the Stowers Institute for Medical Research in Kansas City, 
Missouri, and oversaw all aspects of the sequencing, assembly, and 
annotation of the transcriptome. Eric Ross is a Bioinformatics Spe-
cialist in the S anchez Lab who, along with Kirsten Gotting, a Bio-
informaticist also in the S anchez Lab assembled and analyzed the 
transcriptome data. They also wrote the methods for the transcrip-
tome sequencing, assembly and annotation and generated the 
heatmaps, transcriptome line graphs, and gene ontology graphs. 
All authors were involved in the writing of this manuscript and 
page proofs. S.M.L. was funded by the DGE, A.S.A. was funded by 
the NIH and HHMI, B.J.S was funded by the DBI, and B.J.S. and </p>

<p>S.M.L. were funded by the Seeley Fund for Ocean Research on 
Tetiaroa </p>



<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>

<p>HEAD REGENERATION IN HEMICHORDATES 1173 </p>



<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>





<p>DEVELOPMENTAL DYNAMICS </p>

<p>HEAD REGENERATION IN HEMICHORDATES 1175 </p>

</text></tei>