<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5318538" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Introduction: Neuroinflammation and cerebrovascular disease (CeVD) have been implicated in 
cognitive impairment and Alzheimer's disease (AD). The present study aimed to examine serum in-
flammatory markers in preclinical stages of dementia and in AD, as well as to investigate their asso-
ciations with concomitant CeVD. 
Methods: We performed a cross-sectional case-control study including 96 AD, 140 cognitively 
impaired no dementia (CIND), and 79 noncognitively impaired participants. All subjects underwent 
neuropsychological and neuroimaging assessments, as well as collection of blood samples for mea-
surements of serum samples interleukin (IL)-6, IL-8, and tumor necrosis factor a levels. Subjects 
were classified as CIND or dementia based on clinical criteria. Significant CeVD, including white-
matter hyperintensities (WMHs), lacunes, and cortical infarcts, was assessed by magnetic resonance 
imaging. 
Results: After controlling for covariates, higher concentrations of IL-8, but not the other measured 
cytokines, were associated with both CIND and AD only in the presence of significant CeVD (CIND 
with CeVD: odds ratios [ORs] 4.53; 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.5-13.4 and AD with CeVD: OR 
7.26; 95% CI 1.2-43.3). Subsequent multivariate analyses showed that among the types of CeVD 
assessed, only WMH was associated with higher IL-8 levels in CIND and AD (WMH: OR 2.81; 
95% CI 1.4-5.6). 
Discussion: Serum IL-8 may have clinical utility as a biomarker for WMH in AD. Longitudinal 
follow-up studies would help validate these findings. 
Alzheimer's disease (AD), characterized by progressive 
loss of memory and cognitive function, is the most com-
mon form of dementia in the elderly [1], and a major </p>

<p>*Corresponding author. Tel.: 65 6601 2678; Fax: 65 6873 7690. 
E-mail address: mitchell.lai@dementia-research.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.dadm.2017.01.001 
2352-8729/ Ó 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. on behalf of the Alzheimer's Association. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND 
license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Alzheimer' s &amp; Dementia: Diagnosis, Assessment &amp; Disease Monitoring 7 (2017) 41-47 </p>

<p>source of health care burden worldwide. By 2050, the 
worldwide prevalence of AD will be quadruple that in 
2006, which translates to 1 in every 85 people worldwide 
having AD [2]. 
Originally regarded as an "immune privileged" organ, 
the brain is now well known to exhibit key features of 
inflammation. Accumulating evidence suggests that neuro-
inflammation plays an essential role in AD pathogenesis 
[3], with alterations of brain cytokine levels reported 
[4,5]. Furthermore, activated microglia and astrocytes as 
well as increased concentrations of inflammatory 
mediators have been detected in the vicinity of amyloid 
plaques and neurofibrillary tangles in AD brain [3]. 
Indeed, meta-analyses of observational studies indicate a 
significant association between the long-term use of 
nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs and lowered risk of 
AD [6]. 
Neuroinflammation, when occurring in the acute phase 
and resolved in a timely manner, is beneficial in combating 
pathogens and in tissue repair. But a chronic neuroinflam-
matory response may contribute to neurodegeneration [7]. 
Cytokines released from such neuroinflammatory processes 
are known to be mirrored in the periphery, thus allowing 
measurements of potential biomarkers [8,9], which at 
present include cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) markers 
(combined phosphotau and b-amyloid 38/42) and 
neuroimaging (hippocampal atrophy, amyloid positron 
emission tomography) [10-12]. However, the invasiveness 
and high costs associated with neuroimaging and CSF 
investigations have hindered their wide clinical 
application. In contrast, the minimal invasiveness and 
relative low cost of blood-based investigations have stimu-
lated research into assessments of their feasibility as diag-
nostic and prognostic biomarkers. Indeed, several studies 
of circulating cytokines have been reported (albeit with 
inconsistent findings), with the majority of these studies 
focused on staging after a diagnosis of dementia has 
been made [4,5,13-16]. As neuroinflammation is thought 
to be involved in disease pathogenesis in early stages, it 
is important to also investigate inflammatory markers in 
predementia stages such as mild cognitive impairment or 
cognitive impairment no dementia (CIND), which are 
associated with increased risk of AD but may also 
represent better prospects for treatment and/or prevention 
[17,18]. 
Besides b-amyloid mismetabolism and tau hyperphos-
phorylation, vascular disease has been suggested to play a 
role in AD [19]. Several neuroimaging markers of cerebro-
vascular disease (CeVD), such as white-matter hyperinten-
sities (WMHs), cortical infarct, and lacunes, have been 
shown to be associated with AD [20], and may exacerbate 
the severity of dementia [21,22]. However, in previous 
inflammatory marker studies, the impact of CeVD was 
generally neglected. In this study, we aimed to measure 
serum proinflammatory cytokines, including interleukin 6 
(IL-6), IL-8, and tumor necrosis factor a (TNFa), in a mem-</p>

<p>ory clinic cohort of CIND and AD who underwent neuroi-
maging assessments for CeVD. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>2.1. Study cohort </p>

<p>A case-control design was used. Cases (CIND and demen-
tia) with subjective complaints of memory loss and cognitive 
impairment on neuropsychological assessment were recruited 
from memory clinics from National University Hospital and 
Saint Luke's Hospital in Singapore. Controls were recruited 
from both memory clinics and the community and were 
defined as those with subjective memory impairment com-
plaints but who were cognitively normal on objective neuro-
psychological assessment. All subjects underwent clinical, 
physical, and neuropsychological assessments and neuroi-
maging at the National University of Singapore from August 
2010 till May 2014. Ethics approval for this study was ob-
tained from the National Healthcare Group Domain-
Specific Review Board (DSRB reference: 2010/00017; study 
protocol number: DEM4233), and written informed consent 
had been obtained from participants or their next-of-kin 
before study recruitment and procedures. The study was con-
ducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. </p>

<p>2.2. Questionnaires </p>

<p>Relevant demographic and medical information was 
collected by administration of a detailed questionnaire. Data 
collected included age, gender, education, marital status, 
occupation, smoking, alcohol intake, ability to live indepen-
dently, handedness, previous head trauma, and family history 
of dementia. Inquiries on medical history included stroke, car-
diovascular diseases, hypertension, hyperlipidemia, diabetes 
mellitus, vitamin B12 deficiency, thyroid disease, urinary, 
and bowel incontinence, Parkinson disease, depressive symp-
toms, and psychiatric illnesses and were subsequently verified 
by review of the medical records. Barthel activities of daily 
living indices were assessed for functional status. </p>

<p>2.3. Neuroimaging </p>

<p>As previously described [23,24], a 3T Siemens Magnetom 
Trio Tim scanner with a 32-channel head coil was used for 
magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) at the Clinical Imaging 
Research Center of the National University of Singapore. 
CeVD was assessed using MRI markers for lacunes, cortical 
infarcts, and WMHs. Briefly, the presence and quantification 
of lacunes and cortical infarcts were defined on FLAIR and 
T2 sequences using the STRIVE criteria [25], whereas 
WMH grading was based on the Age-Related White Matter 
Changes (ARWMC) scale [26]. Significant CeVD was 
defined as the presence of cortical infarct and/or presence 
of two or more lacunes, and/or confluent WMH (ARWMC 
score 8) in two regions of the brain [23,24]. </p>

<p>Y. Zhu et al. / Alzheimer's &amp; Dementia: Diagnosis, Assessment &amp; Disease Monitoring 7 (2017) 41-47 </p>

<p>
2.4. Assessments for cognitive impairment and AD </p>

<p>Diagnosis of cognitive impairment and dementia were 
made at weekly consensus meetings attended by clinicians 
and neuropsychologists, where clinical histories, psycho-
metrics, and neuroimages were reviewed. CIND cases 
were diagnosed by clinical judgment and further confirma-
tion by neuropsychological tests, namely, impairment in at 
least one domain of the neuropsychological test battery con-
sisting of executive function, attention, language, visuomo-
tor speed, visuoconstruction, verbal memory, and visual 
memory, in patients who did not meet the criteria for demen-
tia [23,24]. AD cases were diagnosed using the National 
Institute of Neurological and Communicative Disorders 
and Stroke and the Alzheimer's disease and Related 
Disorders Association criteria. Noncognitively impaired 
(NCI) subjects were those assessed to be normal by 
neuropsychological tests. </p>

<p>2.5. Peripheral inflammatory markers </p>

<p>Nonfasting blood samples collected in serum-separating 
tubes were centrifuged at 2000 rcf for 10 minutes at 4 C, 
after which aliquots of serum were mixed well and stored 
at 280 C until use. All samples were subject to only one 
freeze-thaw cycle. Concentrations of interleukin 6 (IL-6), 
IL-8, and TNFa were measured in duplicate by multiplex 
xMAPÒ-based Luminex assays (Millipore Corp., Billerica, 
MA, USA) per manufacturer's instructions. The detectable 
concentration range of inflammatory markers is from 0.2 
to 15,000 pg/mL (IL-6), 0.3 to 10,000 pg/mL (IL-8), and 
0.3 to 10,000 pg/mL (TNFa). </p>

<p>2.6. Covariates </p>

<p>Demographic information and information about risk fac-
tors such as hypertension, hyperlipidemia, diabetes, smok-
ing, and cardiovascular diseases were collected from 
physical and clinical interview and medical records and clas-
sified as absent or present. Hypertension was defined as sys-
tolic blood pressure 140 mmHg and/or diastolic blood 
pressure 90 mmHg or use of antihypertensive medications. 
Cardiovascular diseases were classified as a previous history 
of atrial fibrillation, congestive heart failure, and/or myocar-
dial infarction. Apolipoprotein E (APOE) genotyping using 
DNA extracted from the buffy coat of blood samples were as 
previously described [27] for the determination of APOE ε4 
carrier status (presence of at least one APOE ε4 allele). </p>

<p>2.7. Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 21</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Inc.</rs>., Armonk, NY, USA). For group com-
parisons, one-way analyses of variance (ANOVAs) were 
used for normally distributed continuous variables (age); 
chi-square tests for categorical variables (gender, education, 
APOE ε4, hypertension, hyperlipidemia, smoking, diabetes, </p>

<p>cardiovascular disease); nonparametric Kruskal-Wallis 
ANOVA with Dunn's post hoc were used for skewed distrib-
uted continuous variables (inflammatory markers). Binary 
logistic regression was used to assess the association 
between inflammatory markers and primary diagnosis 
(NCI, CIND, or AD). The levels of inflammatory markers 
were included as determinants in the logistic models and 
were categorized into tertiles, whereas CIND and AD were 
listed as outcomes. Odds ratios and 95% confidence intervals 
were reported for both CIND and AD. All the models were 
adjusted for age, gender, education, APOE ε4 carrier status, 
diabetes mellitus, hypertension, and cardiovascular diseases. 
A P-value of ,.05 was considered statistically significant 
for all analyses. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>A total of 383 elderly subjects (95 NCI, 164 CIND, 124 
AD) were recruited, of whom 315 (79 NCI, 140 CIND, 
and 96 AD) had available blood samples and MRI data. Of </p>

<p>Table 1 
Demographic characteristics and inflammatory markers stratified by 
baseline diagnosis </p>

<p>Characteristics </p>

<p>NCI, 
n 5 79 </p>

<p>CIND, 
n 5 140 </p>

<p>AD, 
n 5 96 
P-value </p>

<p>Age, year, mean (SD) 
68.27 (6.0) 71.23 (8.1) 77.25 (7.3) ,.001* 
Female, n (%) 
41 (51.9) 
67 (47.9) 
60 (62.5) .08 
Low education, n (%) 
24 (30.4) 
67 (47.9) 
73 (76) ,.001 y 
APOE genotype z 
APOE ε2 carrier, n (%) 
8 (10.1) 
16 (11.4) 
16 (16.7) .36 
APOE ε3 carrier, n (%) 
76 (96.2) 134 (95.7) 
88 (91.7) .31 
APOE ε4 carrier, n (%) 
14 (17.7) 
42 (30.0) 
32 (33.3) .06 
Diabetes mellitus, n (%) 
17 (21.5) 
53 (37.9) 
44 (45.8) .003 y 
Hypertension, n (%) 
43 (45.4) 
96 (68.6) 
81 (84.4) ,.001 y 
Hyperlipidemia, n (%) 
53 (67.1) 106 (75.7) 
70 (72.9) .39 
Smoking, n (%) 
18 (22.8) 
42 (30.0) 
27 (28.1) .51 
Cardiovascular disease, 
n (%) </p>

<p>4 (5.1) 
23 (16.4) 
18 (18.8) .02 y </p>

<p>Inflammatory markers 
IL-6, pg/mL, median 
(range) </p>

<p>0.78 (11.9) 1.03 (45.3) 1.59 (59.8) .046 x </p>

<p>IL-8, pg/mL, median 
(range) </p>

<p>4.53 (12.2) 5.42 (20.2) 5.90 (44.8) ,.001 k </p>

<p>TNFa, pg/mL, 
median (range) </p>

<p>4.05 (12.9) 4.51 (15.2) 5.28 (16.6) .001 { </p>

<p>Abbreviations: NCI, noncognitively impaired; CIND, cognitive impair-
ment no dementia; AD, Alzheimer's disease; SD, standard deviation; IL, 
interleukin; TNFa, tumor necrosis factor a; ANOVA, analysis of variance. 
NOTE. Bold text indicates P values ,.05. 
*Significant one-way ANOVA with post hoc Bonferroni tests: NCI versus 
CIND, P 5 .01; NCI versus AD, P , .001; CIND versus AD, P , .001. 
y Significant chi-square tests. 
z APOE genotype: APOE ε2, APOE ε3, APOE ε4 carrier denotes presence </p>

<p>of at least one APOE ε2, APOE ε3, or APOE ε4 alleles, respectively. 
x Significant Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA with post hoc Dunn's tests: NCI </p>

<p>versus AD, P 5 .02. 
k Significant Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA with post hoc Dunn's tests: NCI </p>

<p>versus CIND, P , .01; NCI versus AD, P , .001. 
{ Significant Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA with post hoc Dunn's tests: NCI </p>

<p>versus AD, P 5 .001. </p>

<p>Y. Zhu et al. / Alzheimer's &amp; Dementia: Diagnosis, Assessment &amp; Disease Monitoring 7 (2017) 41-47 </p>

<p>
these, 17 NCI (21.5%), 68 CIND (48.6%), and 53 AD 
(55.2%) subjects had significant CeVD on MRI. Table 1 
shows the demographic variables of the study cohort. In 
comparison to NCI, CIND and AD were older, had lower ed-
ucation levels, higher prevalence of diabetes, hypertension, 
and cardiovascular disease. The concentration values of in-
flammatory markers in the samples ranged from 0.3 to 
60.0 pg/mL for IL-6, 1.3 to 47.0 pg/mL for IL-8, and 0.9 
to 17.5 pg/mL for TNFa. The lowest detectable values 
were used in statistical analyses for cases whose concentra-
tions fell below detectable range (0.2 pg/mL was used for IL-
6 for 28 cases in NCI group, 50 cases in CIND group, and 20 
cases in AD group; 0.3 pg/mL was used for TNFa for two 
cases in NCI group and 1 case in CIND group). As shown 
in Table 1, levels of IL-6, IL-8, and TNFa were highest in 
AD and lowest in NCI, with intermediate levels in CIND. 
The differences were statistically significant for IL-8 in 
both CIND and AD, whereas IL-6 and TNFa were signifi-
cantly raised only in AD. 
Table 2 shows the multivariate analyses of associations 
between serum inflammatory markers and clinical diagno-
ses. There was no association between IL-6 and CIND or 
AD after adjustment for covariates of age, gender, education, 
APOE ε4 carrier, diabetes mellitus, hypertension, and car-
diovascular diseases, whereas the highest tertile of IL-8 
was associated with CIND and AD. In contrast, the highest 
tertile of TNFa was associated with AD but not CIND 
when unadjusted (data not shown), but the association did 
not remain after adjusting for covariates. Interestingly, 
when stratified by the presence or absence of significant 
CeVD (Table 3), the highest tertile of IL-8 was associated 
with both CIND and AD only in the presence of CeVD, 
whereas no associations were found for IL-6 and TNFa in 
the presence or absence of CeVD. Finally, to uncover </p>

<p>whether IL-8 was associated with a specific type of CeVD, 
we performed separate logistic regression analyses for 
WMH, presence of cortical infarcts and lacunes with adjust-
ment for unmatched demographic and risk factors, as well as 
the corresponding nontested MRI markers. Table 4 shows 
the association between the highest tertile of IL-8 and 
MRI markers was with WMH (ARWMC total score 8), 
but not with presence of cortical infarct nor lacunes (two 
or more). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>Although all three inflammatory markers (IL-6, IL-8, and 
TNFa) were found to be significantly different among NCI, 
CIND, and AD patients, only elevated IL-8 was associated 
with CIND and AD after adjustment for age, gender, educa-
tion, APOE ε4 carrier, diabetes mellitus, hypertension, and 
cardiovascular diseases. Furthermore, the associations with 
IL-8 were significant only in the presence of CeVD, and 
more specifically, with the presence of WMH when adjusted 
for covariates. 
IL-8 (also known as CXCL8) is a chemokine which in-
duces chemotaxis in target cells, migrating neutrophils, ba-
sophils, and T cells to the site of infection [28]. In this 
study, we found that high-serum IL-8 was associated with 
both CIND and AD only in the presence of CeVD, specif-
ically with significant WMH, independent of age, gender, 
education, APOE ε4 carrier status, diabetes mellitus, hyper-
tension, cardiovascular diseases, as well as cortical infarct 
and lacunes. This finding corroborates previous work 
showing high IL-8 in cognitively impaired patients associ-
ated with vascular cognitive impairment [29]. IL-8 has 
been known to initiate acute inflammation, and our data sup-
port the involvement of elevated IL-8 in the chronic neuro-
inflammation of AD which may be related to 
cerebrovascular damage [30]. Actually, significant eleva-
tions in plasma IL-8 levels in cognitive impairment have 
also been reported by others [5,13], although there are also 
conflicting data showing lower IL-8 level in mild cognitive 
impairment and AD [31]. The mechanism underlying asso-
ciations of IL-8 with WMH is at present unclear. The disease 
processes may be related to microglial activation-associated 
upregulation of cytokines besides inducible nitric oxide syn-
thase [32], which in turn trigger increases in proinflamma-
tory and pro-oxidant nitric oxide, affect brain microvessel 
endothelia, and result in white-matter lesions detectable as 
WMH by MRI [33,34]. Although these lesions have been 
shown to be associated with, and predict for, cognitive 
impairment [35-37], whether such processes actually link 
IL-8 with white-matter lesions will require follow-up 
studies. 
IL-6 can be produced by a variety of immune cells as 
well as endothelial cells and fibroblasts and is a primary 
inducer of acute proteins and hormones which mediate fe-
ver and immune cell expansion in response to infection or 
injury [28]. Interestingly, IL-6 also has anti-inflammatory </p>

<p>Table 2 
Association of inflammatory markers (in tertiles) with CIND and AD, 
expressed as odds ratios with 95% confidence intervals </p>

<p>Inflammatory 
markers </p>

<p>CIND odds ratio 
(95% CI)* </p>

<p>AD odds ratio 
(95% CI)* </p>

<p>IL-6 
1st tertile 
1 
1 
2nd tertile 
0.72 (0.4-1.5) 
1.29 (0.5-3.6) 
3rd tertile 
0.95 (0.5-2.0) 
1.15 (0.4-3.4) 
IL-8 
1st tertile 
1 
1 
2nd tertile 
0.81 (0.4-1.6) 
0.57 (0.2-1.6) 
3rd tertile 
2.80 (1.2-6.7) 
2.41 (0.7-8.9) 
TNFa 
1st tertile 
1 
1 
2nd tertile 
1.27 (0.6-2.7) 
1.00 (0.3-2.9) 
3rd tertile 
1.17 (0.5-2.5) 
1.23 (0.4-3.6) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CIND, cognitive impairment no dementia; AD, Alz-
heimer's disease; CI, confidence interval; IL, interleukin; TNFa, tumor ne-
crosis factor a. 
NOTE. N values for CIND 5 140; AD 5 96. Bold text indicates P values 
,.05. </p>

<p>*Adjusted for age, gender, education, APOE ε4 carrier, diabetes mellitus, 
hypertension, and cardiovascular diseases. </p>

<p>Y. Zhu et al. / Alzheimer's &amp; Dementia: Diagnosis, Assessment &amp; Disease Monitoring 7 (2017) 41-47 </p>

<p>
effects [38]. This functional dichotomy may underlie con-
flicting results where a few studies have shown increased 
levels of serum or plasma IL-6 levels in AD [4,15], 
whereas other studies reported unchanged peripheral 
levels of IL-6 between control, mild cognitive impairment, 
and AD [14,39-41]. In the present study, although higher 
IL-6 was found in AD, subsequent multivariate analyses 
did not support associations of serum IL-6 with AD or 
concomitant CeVD. 
TNFa is a proinflammatory cytokine, produced primarily 
by activated macrophages, T cells, and NK cells. It is a medi-
ator of both acute and chronic inflammation and can activate 
vascular endothelium and increase vascular permeability 
[28]. Similar to the other markers, there are inconsistent re-
sults on the status of peripheral TNFa in AD with reports 
of significantly lower [14,42], unchanged [43,44], or 
increased [45,46] TNFa in mild cognitive impairment and/ 
or AD. The present study showed that, like the other two 
markers, serum TNFa was increased in AD, although the 
association was not statistically significant when adjusted 
for covariates. This suggests confounding by concomitant 
risk factors. Indeed, there is evidence of TNFa involvement </p>

<p>in cardiovascular disease [47-49] which was included as a 
covariate in our study. 
The strengths of this study include the following: (1) a 
relatively large cohort; (2) inclusion of covariates such as 
age, gender, education, APOE ε4 carrier status, diabetes 
mellitus, hypertension, and cardiovascular diseases in ana-
lyses; and (3) use of neuroimaging to classify cases with 
CeVD and hence allowing the assessment of CeVD impact. 
However, our study has several limitations as well. First, 
because of the case-control design of the study, it is not 
possible to establish the temporal association between 
these markers and the development of cognitive impair-
ment. Further follow-up prospective validation studies 
will address these limitations. Furthermore, the cases and 
controls, though representative of the elderly population 
in Singapore, were derived from two settings, that is, mem-
ory clinic and community. Finally, the control group was 
relatively younger and had lower CeVD burden compared 
to cases which could have resulted in selection bias and re-
sidual confounding. 
In conclusion, the present study suggests that IL-8 has po-
tential clinical utility as a biomarker of small vessel CeVD </p>

<p>Table 4 
Associations of IL-8 (in tertiles) with MRI markers of CeVD, expressed as odds ratios with 95% confidence intervals </p>

<p>Inflammatory marker 
WMH (ARWMC 8), odds ratio (95% CI)* 
Cortical infarct, odds ratio (95% CI) y 
2 lacunes, odds ratio (95% CI) z </p>

<p>IL-8 
1st tertile 
1 
1 
1 
2nd tertile 
1.28 (0.7-2.5) 
2.10 (0.6-7.6) 
0.94 (0.3-3.2) 
3rd tertile 
2.81 (1.4-5.6) 
3.50 (0.9-13.1) 
2.70 (0.9-8.4) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: IL, interleukin; MRI, magnetic resonance imaging; CeVD, cerebrovascular disease; WMH, white-matter hyperintensity; ARWMC, age-
related white-matter changes; CI, confidence interval; CIND, cognitive impairment no dementia. 
NOTE. N values for CIND with CeVD 5 68; AD with CeVD 5 53. N values for significant WMH (ARWMC 8) 5 118, cortical infarcts 5 28, lacunes 
(2) 5 37. Bold text indicates P values ,.05. 
*Adjusted for age, gender, education, APOE ε4 carrier, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, cardiovascular diseases, presence of cortical infarct, and lacunes. </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>Adjusted for age, gender, education, APOE ε4 carrier, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, cardiovascular diseases, WMH, and presence of lacunes. </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>Adjusted for age, gender, education, APOE ε4 carrier, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, cardiovascular diseases, WMH, and presence of cortical infarct. </p>

<p>Table 3 
Associations of inflammatory markers with CIND and AD stratified by the presence of CeVD, expressed as odds ratios with 95% confidence intervals </p>

<p>Inflammatory markers </p>

<p>With CeVD* 
Without CeVD* </p>

<p>CIND odds ratio (95% CI) 
AD odds ratio (95% CI) 
CIND odds ratio (95% CI) 
AD odds ratio (95% CI) </p>

<p>IL-6 
1st tertile 
1 
1 
1 
1 
2nd tertile 
0.73 (0.3-1.8) 
0.84 (0.2-3.4) 
0.65 (0.3-1.6) 
2.12 (0.6-7.7) 
3rd tertile 
0.89 (0.4-2.1) 
0.96 (0.3-3.6) 
0.86 (0.4-2.1) 
1.14 (0.3-4.6) 
IL-8 
1st tertile 
1 
1 
1 
1 
2nd tertile 
1.00 (0.4-2.4) 
0.31 (0.1-1.5) 
0.58 (0.3-1.3) 
0.74 (0.2-2.6) 
3rd tertile 
4.53 (1.5-13.4) 
7.26 (1.2-43.3) 
1.99 (0.7-5.4) 
1.09 (0.2-5.7) 
TNFa 
1st tertile 
1 
1 
1 
1 
2nd tertile 
1.17 (0.5-2.9) 
0.86 (0.2-3.6) 
1.31 (0.6-3.0) 
0.99 (0.3-3.7) 
3rd tertile 
1.42 (0.6-3.5) 
1.32 (0.3-5.6) 
1.00 (0.4-2.5) 
1.12 (0.3-4.3) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CIND, cognitive impairment no dementia; AD, Alzheimer's disease; CeVD, cerebrovascular disease; CI, confidence interval; IL, interleukin; 
TNFa, tumor necrosis factor a. 
NOTE. N values for CIND with CeVD 5 68; AD with CeVD 5 53. Bold text indicates P values ,.05. 
*Adjusted for age, gender, education, APOE ε4 carrier, diabetes mellitus, hypertension, and cardiovascular diseases. </p>

<p>Y. Zhu et al. / Alzheimer's &amp; Dementia: Diagnosis, Assessment &amp; Disease Monitoring 7 (2017) 41-47 </p>

<p>
such as WMH in cognitive impairment and AD. However, 
follow-up longitudinal studies are needed for validation. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank the patients and their fam-
ilies for their participation in this study, which is funded 
by the National Medical Research Council of Singapore 
(NMRC/CSA/032/2011 and NMRC/CG/013/2013) and 
Yong Loo Lin School of Medicine, National University of 
Singapore (R-184-000-223-133). The funding organizations 
played no role in the conduct or design of this research. </p>

<p>RESEARCH IN CONTEXT </p>

<p>1. Systematic review: Although neuroinflammation is 
widely considered to play a pathogenic role in Alz-
heimer's disease (AD), the extent to which changes 
in peripheral inflammatory markers may reflect 
concomitant cerebrovascular disease (CeVD) has not 
been studied in either cognitive impairments no de-
mentia (CIND), a predementia stage, or in AD, despite 
evidence in the literature indicating the exacerbating 
effects of concomitant CeVD on dementia severity. </p>

<p>2. Interpretation: Of the three acute inflammatory 
markers investigated, only elevated IL-8 was asso-
ciated with white-matter hyperintensities in CIND 
and AD, suggesting that interleukin-8 is a potential 
biomarker for small vessel CeVD in cognitive 
impairment and AD. </p>

<p>3. Future directions: A case-control design was used 
for our study. Follow-up longitudinal studies are 
needed for validation. </p>



<p>Y. Zhu et al. / Alzheimer's &amp; Dementia: Diagnosis, Assessment &amp; Disease Monitoring 7 (2017) 41-47 </p>



<p>
Y. Zhu et al. / Alzheimer's &amp; Dementia: Diagnosis, Assessment &amp; Disease Monitoring 7 (2017) 41-47 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>