<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5149064" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>In the United States, the National School Breakfast (SBP) and School Lunch Program (NSLP) meals are provided for 
free or at a reduced price to eligible children, and are a nutrition safety net for low income children. Consuming both 
meals could provide 58% of daily intake. This paper evaluates the contribution of SBP and NSLP meals to the dietary 
intakes of 5-18 year old children participating in the National Health and Nutrition Examination Surveys (NHANES) 
from 2007 through 2012. The participants completed 24-hour dietary recalls. Least-square means and standard er-
rors of the mean for energy and food group intakes for the total day and by school meal, and the percent of daily 
energy and food groups contributed by school meals were computed by analysis of covariance, with BMI, ethnicity, 
sex, age and poverty level as covariates. Of the 7800 participating children aged 5-18 years in the entire dataset, 448 
consumed both SBP-NSLP meals on a weekday. Almost one-half (47%) of the day's energy intake was provided by 
the two school meals. For the major food groups, the contribution of school meals ranged from between 40.6% for 
vegetables to 77.1% for milk. Overall, these results provide important information on contribution of the SBP and 
NSLP meals to low income children's daily dietary intake. 
The National School Lunch Program (NSLP) was the first federally 
funded meal program in the United States, created in 1946 as a "measure 
of national security, to safeguard the health and well-being of the Nation's 
children…" (Food and Nutrition Service -U.S. Department of Agriculture. 
Program History -National School Lunch Program (NSLP), 2014). The 
School Breakfast Program (SBP) began as a pilot project in 1966, and 
was made permanent in 1975 (Food and Nutrition Service -U.S. 
Department of Agriculture. School Breakfast Program Fact Sheet, 2013). 
Both programs provide meals for free or at a reduced price (FRP) to chil-
dren who are eligible according to income guidelines, as well as full price 
meals for children who do not qualify for the FRP meals. School districts 
receive monetary reimbursements for providing these meals. In fiscal 
year 2014, approximately 30.5 million children received an NSLP meal 
each day of which 71.6% were FRP meals (Food and Nutrition Service -
U.S. Department of Agriculture. National School Lunch Program: 
Participation and Lunches Served, 2016); 13.6 million children ate a SBP 
meal each day of which 84.9% were FRP meals (Food and Nutrition 
Service -U.S. Department of Agriculture. School Breakfast Program 
Participation and Meals Served, 2016). The annual cost of these two pro-
grams was $16.3 billion (Congressional Budget Office, 2015). </p>

<p>All SBP and NSLP meals must meet federal nutrition standards that 
are consistent with the Dietary Guidelines for Americans (DGA) 
(Government Accountability Office, 2014). The SBP and NSLP meal pat-
terns include fruit, vegetables, grains, protein foods, and milk; these 
standards have changed over the years in response to new DGA 
(Government Accountability Office, 2014). The current school nutrition 
standards and meal patterns were implemented in the fall of 2012 
(Food and Nutrition Service -U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2012). 
The menu patterns provide specifications for fruit, vegetables, whole 
grains, lean proteins, and nonfat or low fat milk (Crepinsek and 
Paxton, 2015). 
The contribution of school meals to the total dietary intake of chil-
dren in the United States has been documented in only one national 
study, the School Nutrition Dietary Assessment Study III (SNDA III), con-
ducted during the 2004-2005 school year. The SBP and NSLP meals 
accounted for 22% and 31%, respectively, of school children's daily ener-
gy intake; 51% for those eating both meals (Gordon et al., 2007). No data 
on the contribution of the foods offered at those meals to the day's daily 
total was provided. Based on the nutrition standards in effect at that 
time, SBP and NSLP meals were to offer 25% and 33% of daily energy in-
take, respectively (Fox et al., 2012). 
This study assessed the contribution of school meals to the daily 
dietary intakes for children ages 5-18 who consumed both the SBP 
and NSLP meals, using the 2007 to 2012 National Health and Nutrition 
Examination Survey data (NHANES). During these years, the menu </p>

<p>Preventive Medicine Reports 5 (2017) 82-85 </p>

<p>E-mail address: kcullen@bcm.tmc.edu (K.W. Cullen). </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pmedr.2016.11.016 
2211-3355/© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>Preventive Medicine Reports </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : h t t p : / / e e s . e l s e v i e r . c o m / p m e d r </p>

<p>patterns followed the old guidelines (Government Accountability Office, 
2014; Fox et al., 2012; Food and Nutrition Service -U.S. Department of 
Agriculture. Menu planning in the School Lunch Program, 2009). </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>The NHANES is a cross-sectional survey conducted by the National 
Center for Health Statistics of the Centers for Disease Control and Pre-
vention. The NHANES uses a sampling design to be representative of 
the US civilian non-institutionalized population, aged 2 months and 
older. The survey included administration of an in-person household in-
terview and a full medical examination in a special mobile examination 
center (Centers for Disease Control and Prevention -National Center for 
Health Statistics, 2015). The datasets from cycles 2007-2008, 2009-
2010, and 2011-2012 were combined and analyzed in this study. 
The NHANES 24-hour dietary intake data were obtained utilizing a 
multi-pass method (Blanton et al., 2006; Moshfegh et al., 2008). Two 
24-hour dietary recalls were collected for most of the participants. The 
first recall was completed in-person at the mobile examination centers, 
while the second recall was completed over the telephone some days 
later, but from a smaller subsample. Parents assisted with the recalls 
for the young children. Only data from the first in-person dietary recall 
was used in the present analysis, which is acceptable as noted in 
NHANES documentation (U. S. Department of Health and Human 
Services, Centers for Disease Control -National Center for Health 
Statistics, n.d.). The use of only the first in-person recall has been used 
in previous published papers (Mesirow and Welsh, 2015; Powell et al., 
2016; Storey and Anderson, 2016; Slining and Popkin, 2013). 
The family monthly poverty level index category served the indica-
tor of socioeconomic status. Less than or equal to 1.85 was classified 
as low income and those above 1.85 as higher income. 
Height and weight were measured according to NHANES protocols 
(Centers for Disease Control and Prevention -National Center for 
Health Statistics, 2015). Body Mass Index (BMI) was calculated using 
the standard formula (weight [kg]/height [m 2 ]) and the gender-and 
age-specific standardized percentile scores were translated using the 
<rs type="software">SAS</rs> program for Growth Charts for the United States available from 
the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (Centers for Disease 
Control -National Center for Health Statistics. CDC Growth Charts: 
United States, 2000). Children were classified into one of three weight 
categories: healthy weight (b85th percentile for BMI), overweight 
(≥85th percentile and b 95th percentile for BMI), and obese (≥95th per-
centile for BMI). </p>

<p>2.1. Participants </p>

<p>The participants were children and adolescents aged 5-18 who had 
consumed school breakfast and/or lunch (responded "Breakfast" and/or 
"Lunch" to question "Name of Eating Occasion"), and reported "Cafete-
ria in a K-12 school" for the question "Where did you get (this/most of 
the ingredients for this) **Foodname**?" on weekdays. A school meal 
was defined as "a) ate 3 or more meal components (fruit, vegetables, 
grains, meat/meat alternate, milk) from the school cafeteria and b) ate 
2 meal components from the school cafeteria and no food from outside 
of the school cafeteria" (Cole and Fox, 2008). The NHANES 2007-2012 
data included 7800 children aged 5-18 years; 3883 reported breakfast 
or lunch data on a weekday, 1035 reported only eating an NSLP meal, 
and 448 reported consuming both the SBP and NSLP meals on the day 
of the recall (5.7% of the sample). </p>

<p>2.2. Procedures </p>

<p>The NHANES dietary recall data were linked with the USDA 
MyPyramid Equivalents Database (MPED 2.0) and the Center for 
Nutrition Policy and Promotion Addendum to the MPED 2.0, to obtain 
the number of MyPyramid equivalents for major food groups and </p>

<p>subgroups (Bowman et al., 2008). The output included the food groups 
in the school menu patterns: total grains [ounce equivalents (oz eq)], in-
cluding whole and non-whole grains; fruit [cups]; total vegetables 
[cups], plus dark-green, red-orange, other, and starchy vegetables; le-
gumes [cups]; total milk [cup equivalents (cup eq)], including milk, yo-
gurt, and cheese; milk; and total lean protein from meat, poultry, and 
fish (oz eq). </p>

<p>2.3. Data analyses </p>

<p>All statistical analyses were conducted using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 9.4</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SAS In-stitute Inc.</rs>. Cary, NC: 2014). Frequencies were calculated using PROC 
SURVEYFREQ. The descriptive analyses of energy and food group con-
sumption for the entire day, for the SBP and NSLP meals, and the percent 
of energy and food groups contributed by school meals were calculated 
using PROC SURVEYMEAN. All the results were weighted by the esti-
mated sample weights to account for the complex sample design of 
NHANES, and to enable inferences to the total U.S. population. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>Four hundred and forty-eight students reported eating both a SBP 
and NSLP meal on the day of the recall: 64% were in elementary school, 
57% were male, 30% Hispanic, 32% non-Hispanic Black, and 33% non-
Hispanic White. Approximately 82% were classified as low income, 
with 59% normal weight, 16% overweight and 17% obese. 
Mean breakfast intake did not meet the federal breakfast meal pat-
terns (Table 1), and accounted for only 21% of the daily energy intake. 
Less than 0.50 cup of fruit or 100% fruit juice was consumed and only 
about 70% of the dairy products. 
On average, only 27% of daily energy intake was consumed from the 
school lunch meal (Table 1). Vegetable and protein consumption was 
low. 
Almost one-half of the days' energy intake (47%) was supplied for 
those eating both school meals. The range for the major food groups 
was 40.6% for total vegetables to 77.1% for milk (Table 1). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>This is one of the first studies to assess the contribution of SBP and 
NSLP meals to the daily dietary intake of energy and food groups of 5-
18 year old children in the United States using 24-hour dietary recalls 
from the 2007-2012 NHANES. Because the SBP and NSLP meals were 
planned to provide 25% and 33% of student daily energy needs, respec-
tively, children who consumed both meals could have received 58% of 
their daily intake at school (Fox et al., 2012). The primarily low income 
students (82%) in the current study group obtained 47% of their daily 
total energy intake, 58% of fruit, 41% of total vegetables, 52% of total 
grains, 70% of total milk and 77% of milk from school meals (Table 1). 
These results suggest that school meals were a safety net for these stu-
dents, but could provide even more of these important food groups if all 
the foods in the meal were consumed. 
These results can be compared to data from the SNDA III national 
study conducted in the 2004-2005 school year (Gordon et al., 2007), 
and one conducted in Minnesota (Robinson-O'Brien et al., 2010). The 
SNDA III study included a single 24-hour dietary recall from a random 
sample of 2314 children in grades 1 through 12 attending a nationally 
representative sample of US schools (Gordon et al., 2007). The race/eth-
nicity (22% Hispanic, 17% non-Hispanic Black, 54% non-Hispanic White), 
and weight status (~ 59% normal weight, ~ 15% overweight and 24% 
obese) of the SNDA III sample were also similar to the current 
NHANES study results (Gordon et al., 2007). Up to 51% of daily energy 
intake was supplied for the SNDA III students who consumed both 
SBP-NSLP meals, compared to the 47.2% in our study, but no data 
were provided on the contribution of food groups consumed to total 
daily intake (Briefel et al., 2009). </p>

<p> 
K.W. Cullen, T.-A. Chen / Preventive Medicine Reports 5 (2017) 82-85 </p>

<p>The mean daily intake for the SNDA III students who consumed an 
NSLP meal was 2149 kcal (kcal) (Gordon et al., 2007). This is slightly 
higher than the daily intake for children from the current study 
(2031 kcal). The SNDA III SBP intake of 451 kcal provided approximately 
22% of total daily energy intake (Gordon et al., 2007). Children in the 
current study consumed 387 kcal from the SBP, providing 20.6% of 
daily energy intake. The SNDA III NSLP intake was approximately 
633 kcal, and provided about 31% of total daily energy intake (Gordon 
et al., 2007). The students in the current study reported lower NSLP in-
takes (538 kcal), representing 27.3% of total daily energy from the NSLP 
meal. 
The study conducted in Minnesota in 2006 assessed the proportion 
of fruit and vegetables consumed at school for 103 primarily low income 
(90%) children ages 9-12 years (Robinson-O'Brien et al., 2010). Their 
mean daily fruit and vegetable intake was 3.6 servings; 64% of daily 
fruit and 44% of daily vegetables consumed were provided by school 
meals. These proportions for the total daily intake are close to the 
NHANES results (57.7% fruit and 40.6% vegetables). 
Differences between the current study and the two previous studies 
may be due to the dietary assessment methods. All used the 24-hour di-
etary recall, but the SNDA III and Minnesota study had the school menus 
and could identify school foods in the dietary recalls. In the NHANES 
data, food source was by self-report with no school menus, a method 
that has been used in previous studies with NHANES data (Cole and 
Fox, 2008). 
The SBP and NSLP intakes reported by the students in the current 
study did not meet the previous school meal guidelines in place before 
2012. The new meal patterns and nutrition standards that were imple-
mented in the fall of 2012 might improve children's dietary intakes at 
school as they provide fruit, more vegetables (with specific subgroups 
required over a week), and whole grains, compared with the previous 
nutrition standards and meal patterns (Food and Nutrition Service -
U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2012). Students have to select at least 
one serving of a fruit or vegetable for the SBP or NSLP meal to count as 
a reimbursable meal, under the offer versus serve option, which is op-
tional for elementary schools, but not for middle and high schools 
(Food and Nutrition Service -U.S. Department of Agriculture, 2012). 
The opportunity to select more fruit and vegetables at meals may in-
crease student fruit and vegetable consumption. Evaluating the impact 
of the new school meal patterns on school dietary intakes as well as 
over 24 h is an important area for future study. </p>

<p>A major weakness of this study is that the NHANES data did not di-
rectly identify whether each food was obtained from the school meal 
program, but was defined by eating occasion, place, food source, and 
day of week as reported by each participant. The nutrient composition 
of specially formulated foods for school meal programs might not 
have been available in the USDA Food and Nutrient Database for Dietary 
Studies (Bowman et al., 2008). In addition, measurement errors are as-
sociated with self-reported dietary intake. Only 5.7% of the NHANES 
child participants consumed both a school breakfast and lunch on the 
recall day and 57% were male, reducing generalizability. Strengths of 
this study include the use of the nationally representative NHANES 
study data and dietary intake collected with the multiple pass method. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>These results provide data on the contribution of the SBP and NSLP 
meals on the daily dietary intake of children in the United States who 
ate both the school meals prior to the implementation of the new school 
meal patterns. These meals serve as a nutrition safety net for low in-
come children; the school lunch program is the second largest food as-
sistance program in the US (Congressional Budget Office, 2015; 
Government Accountability Office, 2014). Research assessing the im-
pact of the federal meals program on children's dietary intake should 
continue. Similar analyses could be undertaken with future NHANES 
data collected after the new school meal rules were implemented in 
the fall of 2012. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>No conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>Financial support </p>

<p>This work was supported in part by federal funds from the USDA/ 
ARS (Cooperative Agreement 58-3092-5-001). The contents of this pub-
lication do not necessarily reflect the views or policies of the USDA, nor 
does mention of trade names, commercial products, or organizations 
imply endorsement from the U.S. Government. </p>

<p>Table 1 
Mean daily dietary intake and percent of daily intake contributed from consuming both SBP a and NSLP b meals for 448 children ages 5-18 years participating in NHANES 2007-2012. </p>

<p>Daily dietary intake 
School breakfast intake 
School lunch intake 
Percent of daily intake from 
SBP + NSLP meals </p>

<p>Mean 
SE 
Mean 
SE 
Mean 
SE 
Mean 
SE </p>

<p>Energy (kilocalories) 
2031 
53 
387 
27 
538 
16 
47.2 
0.9 
Total fruit (cup eq) 
1.37 
0.12 
0.24 
0.04 
0.56 
0.07 
57.7 
2.7 
Total vegetable (cup eq) (excludes legumes) 
1.02 
0.08 
na 
0.38 
0.04 
0.38 
40.6 
1.9 
Dark-green vegetables 
0.04 
0.01 
na 
0.01 
0.01 
0.01 
43.0 
7.2 
Orange tomato vegetables 
0.31 
0.03 
na 
0.15 
0.01 
0.15 
48.2 
3.4 
Starchy vegetables 
0.39 
0.05 
na 
0.11 
0.03 
0.11 
28.6 
2.8 
Other vegetables 
0.27 
0.04 
na 
0.10 
0.01 
0.10 
35.1 
3.0 
Legumes (cup eq) 
0.03 
0.01 
na 
0.01 
0.00 
0.01 
37.8 
12.2 
Total grains (oz eq) 
6.96 
0.26 
1.42 
0.18 
2.47 
0.16 
52.4 
1.5 
Whole grains (oz eq) 
0.36 
0.05 
0.16 
0.05 
0.10 
0.02 
44.1 
5.1 
Non-whole grains (oz eq) 
6.60 
0.25 
1.27 
0.18 
2.37 
0.15 
51.3 
1.5 
Total dairy (milk, yogurt, cheese) (cup eq) 
2.56 
0.13 
0.72 
0.08 
1.40 
0.07 
69.9 
1.7 
Milk 
1.77 
0.09 
0.63 
0.08 
1.07 
0.06 
77.1 
3.1 
Total lean proteins (oz eq) 
3.77 
0.30 
0.32 
0.13 
1.11 
0.15 
37.9 
3.0 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: SBP, School Breakfast Program; NSLP, National School Lunch Program; SE, standard error; cup eq, cup equivalent; oz eq, ounce equivalent. 
a School breakfast menu pattern: 1 serving of fruit or 100% fruit juice (1/2 cup), 2 grain servings (or 1 grain and 1 oz eq of protein), and 1 cup of milk; 25% of daily energy; Grades K-12: </p>

<p>2318 554 kcal; Grades 7-12: 618 kcal (Government Accountability Office, 2014; Fox et al., 2012; Food and Nutrition Service -U.S. Department of Agriculture. Menu planning in the School 
Lunch Program, 2009). 
b School lunch meal pattern: 2 servings of fruit and/or vegetables (up to 1/2 cup each), 1 serving (2 oz eq) of a protein food, 1-2 servings of grains and 1 cup of milk; 33% daily energy. </p>

<p>Kindergarten to Grade 3: (633 kcal); Kindergarten to Grade 6: 664 kcal; Grade 4 to Grade 8: 785 kcal; Grade 7 to Grade 12: 825 kcal (Government Accountability Office, 2014; Fox et al., 
2012; Food and Nutrition Service -U.S. Department of Agriculture. Menu planning in the School Lunch Program, 2009). </p>

<p> 
K.W. Cullen, T.-A. Chen / Preventive Medicine Reports 5 (2017) 82-85 </p>



<p> 
K.W. Cullen, T.-A. Chen / Preventive Medicine Reports 5 (2017) 82-85 </p>

</text></tei>