<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5384723" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T14:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>central laboratory, liaocheng 
People's hospital, liaocheng clinical 
school of Taishan Medical University, 
liaocheng, shandong Province, 
People's republic of china </p>

<p>*These authors contributed equally 
to this work </p>

<p>Background: Immunotherapy based on cytokine-induced killer cells or combination of dendritic 
cells and cytokine-induced killer cells (CIK/DC-CIK) showed promising clinical outcomes for 
treating esophageal cancer (EC). However, the clinical benefit varies among previous studies. 
Therefore, it is necessary to systematically evaluate the curative efficacy and safety of CIK/ 
DC-CIK immunotherapy as an adjuvant therapy for conventional therapeutic strategies in the 
treatment of EC. 
Materials and methods: Clinical trials published before October 2016 and reporting CIK/ 
DC-CIK immunotherapy treatment responses or safety for EC were searched in Cochrane 
Library, EMBASE, PubMed, Wanfang and China National Knowledge Internet databases. 
Research quality and heterogeneity were evaluated before analysis, and pooled analyses were 
performed using random-or fixed-effect models. 
Results: This research covered 11 trials including 994 EC patients. Results of this meta-
analysis indicated that compared with conventional therapy, the combination of conven-
tional therapy with CIK/DC-CIK immunotherapy significantly prolonged the 1-year overall 
survival (OS) rate, overall response rate (ORR) and disease control rate (DCR) (1-year OS: 
P=0.0005; ORR and DCR: P,0.00001). Patients with combination therapy also showed 
significantly improved quality of life (QoL) (P=0.02). After CIK/DC-CIK immunotherapy, 
lymphocyte percentages of CD3 
+ and CD3 
-CD56 
+ subsets (P,0.01) and cytokines levels </p>

<p>of IFN-γ, -2, TNF-α and IL-12 (P,0.00001) were significantly increased, and the percent-
age of cluster of differentiation (CD)4 
+ CD25 
+ CD127 
-subset was significantly decreased, </p>

<p>whereas analysis of CD4 
+ , CD8 
+ , CD4 
+ /CD8 
+ and CD3 
+ CD56 
+ did not show significant </p>

<p>difference (P.0.05). 
Conclusion: The combination of CIK/DC-CIK immunotherapy and conventional therapy is 
safe and markedly prolongs survival time, enhances immune function and improves the treat-
ment efficacy for EC. 
Esophageal cancer (EC) is a global common cancer, with 450,000 new cases and 
400,000 estimated deaths per year. 
1,2 The incidence of EC has increased exponentially 
over the past few decades and the 5-year survival rate remains bleak. 
3 At present, 
surgery, radiotherapy and chemotherapy are most widely used for EC. 
4 However, their </p>

<p>correspondence: changhui Zhou; 
Yingxin Zhang 
central laboratory, liaocheng People's 
hospital, liaocheng clinical school of 
Taishan Medical University, Dongchang 
West road, no 67, liaocheng 252000, 
shandong Province, People's republic 
of china 
Tel +86 135 6207 8772; 
+86 139 6351 0009 
email zhouch2006@163.com; 
zhangyingxin77@163.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
29 March 2017 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1898 </p>

<p>liu et al </p>

<p>application is limited by the failure to thoroughly eliminate 
tumor cells, drug resistance and other adverse effects. </p>

<p>5,6 </p>

<p>Therefore, a more effective and safer therapeutic method is 
urgently required. 
In recent years, immunotherapy has been rising rap-
idly and is considered the fourth powerful therapeutic 
method after surgery, radiotherapy and chemotherapy. </p>

<p>6   Cancer immunotherapy is accomplished in multiple ways, 
including manipulation of the immune system through 
the use of immune agents, such as vaccines, 
7 cytokines, </p>

<p>8   checkpoint inhibitors (including anti-programmed death 
1 [PD-1]/PD-ligand 1 [PD-L1] antibodies and anti-cytotoxic 
T-lymphocyte-associated antigen (CTLA)-4 antibodies), </p>

<p>9,10   kinase inhibitors (such as apatinib and gefitinib) 
11,12 and 
immune cells. 
13-19 However, their applications have the 
following hurdles. Simply activating the immunity via 
vaccination is not able to thoroughly eliminate tumor cells 
because cancer patients are usually in immunosuppression. </p>

<p>19   Promotion of molecule-targeted treatment for tumors is also 
confined only to cancer patients bearing specific antigen-
expressing cells. 
13 Notably, adoptive cellular immunotherapy 
has been flourishing in cancer treatment. Its effectiveness 
relies on the application of dendritic cells (DCs), 
14 tumor-
infiltrating lymphocytes (TILs), 
15 natural killer (NK) cells, </p>

<p>16   cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTLs), 
17 cytokine-induced killer 
(CIK) cells 
18 and other immune cells. CIK cells, which consist 
primarily of the CD3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>CD56 
+ subset, are induced by interferon 
(IFN)-γ, interleukin (IL)-1, cluster of differentiation (CD)3 
monoclonal antibodies (OKT3) and IL-2 in vitro. 
5 Compared 
with other immune cells, CIK cells are easy to obtain from 
peripheral blood and umbilical cord blood mononuclear cells, 
and they possess higher in vitro proliferation capacity, stron-
ger antitumor activity and broader antitumor spectrum. 
6 The 
tumoricidal ability of CIK cells is implemented by inducing 
tumor cell apoptosis through direct contact and secretion 
of cytokines such as IL-2, tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α 
and IFN-γ. 
20 CIK cells have shown promising prospects in 
immunotherapy for cancers. On the one hand, the cytotoxicity 
of CIK cells is not affected by immune inhibitors such 
as cyclosporin A (CsA) and FK506. 
21 On the other hand, 
CIK cell-mediated cytotoxicity does not rely on the major 
histocompatibility complex (MHC). As in most cancers, 
these cells do not express MHC or human leukocyte antigen 
(HLA); this property of CIK cells is a great advantage over 
other immune cells in adoptive cell therapy. </p>

<p>22   DCs are the most potent antigen-presenting cells and are 
essential in CIK activation, proliferation, phenotype expres-
sion and cytokine secretion. 
5,23,24 The cytotoxicity of CIK </p>

<p>cells is remarkably enhanced when cocultured with DCs, 
indicated by the increased proportion of CD3 
+ CD56 
+ cells 
and the improved levels of cytokines such as IL-2, IFN-γ, 
IL-12 and TNF-α. 
6,23 Meanwhile, cocultured DCs also 
downregulate the expression of negative regulatory factors, 
including transforming growth factor (TGF)-β and IL-10, 
as well as the proportion of CD4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>CD25 
+ regulatory T cells 
(Tregs) among CIK cells, which suppress the antitumor 
activity of CIK. 
5,24 Several research reports have shown that 
the combination of DCs and CIKs (DC-CIK) is more effec-
tive and has indicated more promising clinical prospects than 
single CIK treatment. </p>

<p>6   In EC treatment, there are emerging data indicating CIK 
or DC-CIK (CIK/DC-CIK) immunotherapy in combina-
tion with conventional therapy exhibited better therapeutic 
efficacy than conventional therapy alone. 
25-37 However, CIK/ 
DC-CIK immunotherapy clinical application is still in its 
infancy. In this research, we conducted a meta-analysis to 
investigate the efficacy and safety of CIK/DC-CIK combined 
with conventional therapy in comparison with conventional 
therapy alone for EC, in order to provide scientific evidence 
for future clinical trials. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
search strategy and selection criteria </p>

<p>Literature reports were searched across Cochrane Library, 
EMBASE, PubMed, Wanfang and China National Knowl-
edge Internet databases with the key terms "dendritic 
cells", "immunotherapy", "cytokine-induced killer cells" or 
"DC-CIK" combined with "esophageal cancer". No language 
limits were applied. The initial search was performed in 
April 2016 and updated in October 2016. 
Studies selected in our research were randomized con-
trolled clinical trials for EC. The included studies were all 
performed with comparison between the combination of CIK/ 
DC-CIK and conventional treatment (defined as combination 
therapy group) and conventional regimens alone (defined as 
conventional therapy-alone group). </p>

<p>Data collection and quality assessment </p>

<p>Two authors independently searched and collected litera-
tures from the databases according to our inclusion criteria, 
and they extracted the data from all the selected articles. 
Discrepancy was resolved by discussion with a third author. 
The collected information included the first authors' names, 
the years of publication, the numbers of subjects, patient 
ages, tumor stages, experiment regimens, in vitro cell 
culture conditions and dosages of the utilized immune cells. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1899 </p>

<p>cytokine-induced killer cells for the treatment of esophageal cancer </p>

<p>The quality of the included articles was evaluated according 
to the Cochrane Handbook. </p>

<p>38   Definition of outcome measurements </p>

<p>Treatment efficacy was assessed in terms of overall survival 
(OS), overall response rate (ORR; ORR = complete response 
rate + partial response rate), disease control rate (DCR; DCR = 
complete response rate + partial response rate + stable disease 
rate), patients' quality of life (QoL) and adverse events. OS 
was defined as the length of time from the initiation of treat-
ment to death from any cause. 
39 The immune function of EC 
patients before and after treatment was determined by the 
status of the lymphocyte subsets (CD3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, CD4 
+ , CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, CD3 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>CD56 
+ , CD3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>CD56 
+ and CD4 
+ CD25 
+ CD127 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>) and cytokine 
secretion (IFN-γ, IL-2, TNF-α and IL-12). </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data were analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Review Manager</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">5.2</rs> 
provided by <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Cochrane Collaboration</rs>. P,0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. Heterogeneity among the studies was 
assessed to determine the most suitable model. 
40 A random-
effects method was applied when heterogeneity existed; 
otherwise, a fixed-effects method was used. Cochran's Q-test 
was performed in order to evaluate homogeneity among 
studies, and I </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>,50% or P.0.1 was considered homogeneous. 
Odds ratios (ORs) were the principal measurements for 
therapeutic effects and were presented with 95% confidence 
intervals (CIs). </p>

<p>Results 
search results </p>

<p>A total of 1,405 articles were identified by initial retrieval. 
After title and abstract review, 1,381 articles were excluded 
because they did not focus on clinical trials (n=1,261), were in 
duplication and repetition (n=107) or were unrelated studies 
(n=13), and 24 studies remained as potentially relevant. After 
reading the full texts, 8 papers with insufficient data and 
5 reviews or meta-analyses were excluded. Finally, 11 trials 
that included 994 EC patients met the inclusion criteria for 
our meta-analysis (Figure 1). </p>

<p>Patient characteristics </p>

<p>In all, 11 eligible trials including 994 EC patients were 
included in this analysis. All trials were conducted in 
mainland China. In total, 501 patients were treated by 
CIK/DC-CIK in combination with conventional therapy 
(combination therapy), while 493 patients were treated 
by conventional therapy alone. Detailed clinical information 
of the trials is presented in Table 1. DC and CIK cells used 
in the 11 trials were all obtained from autologous peripheral 
blood. In 4 trials, DC-CIK immunotherapy was applied, 
whereas in the other 7 trials, only CIK cells were used. 
In most studies, patients were transfused with .1×10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>immune cells, and other studies did not provide accurate 
cell numbers. Tumor size and injection modes were not 
analyzed in this article due to the lack of sufficient data in 
the included studies. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Flow diagram of the selection process. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1900 </p>

<p>liu et al </p>

<p>Quality assessment </p>

<p>The assessment for risk of bias is shown in Figure 2A and B. 
The quality of the involved studies ranged from moderate 
to high: 9 studies were low in risk of bias, while the other 
2 studies did not have a clear description of the randomization 
process. The allocation, performance, detection and attrition 
risks of the involved studies were low; 3 trials were consid-
ered to be of unclear risk owing to their selective reporting, 
while 3 other studies were considered as high risk as they 
did not show primary outcome data. </p>

<p>Efficacy assessments </p>

<p>This analysis indicated that OS, ORR and DCR were sig-
nificantly improved in patients who underwent combination 
therapy compared to those treated by conventional therapy 
alone (Figure 3, 1-year OS: OR =2.59, 95% CI =1.52-4.40, 
P=0.0005; ORR: OR =2.18, 95% CI =1.57−3.02, P,0.00001; 
DCR: OR =3.83, 95% CI =2.47−5.92, P,0.00001). More-
over, the pooled results showed that patients in the combina-
tion therapy group had significantly improved QoL (Figure 4, </p>

<p>QoL: OR =1.94, 95% CI =1.13−3.33, P=0.02). The fixed-
effects model was applied in this analysis considering the 
slightly significant heterogeneity. </p>

<p>immune function evaluation </p>

<p>The immune status of patients was examined before and after 
the treatment. After CIK/DC-CIK treatment, the proportions 
of CD3 
+ and CD3 
-CD56 
+ in patients were significantly 
increased (Figure 5, CD3 
+ : OR =9.48, 95% CI =6.19−12.77, 
P,0.00001; CD3 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>CD56 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>: OR =6.57, 95% CI =2.00−11.14, 
P=0.005), CD4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>CD25 
+ CD127 
-proportion was significantly 
decreased (CD4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>CD25 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>CD127 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>: OR =-1.72, 95% CI =-2.15 
to -1.28, P,0.00001), whereas the proportions of CD4 
+ , 
CD8 
+ and CD3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>CD56 
+ and the CD4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>/CD8 
+ ratio did not show 
much differences (CD4 
+ : OR =2.93, 95% CI =-2.42 to 8.29, 
P=0.28; CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>: OR =2.00, 95% CI =-4.11 to 8.11, P=0.52; 
CD4 
+ /CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>: OR =-0.01, 95% CI =-0.53 to 0.51, P=0.97; 
CD3 
+ CD56 
+ : OR =6.24, 95% CI =-2.48 to 14.97, P=0.16). 
On the other hand, patients' cytokines levels were 
also significantly increased after CIK/DC-CIK therapy </p>

<p>Table 1 clinical information from the eligible trials used in the meta-analysis </p>

<p>Authors 
Year Stage Exp 
regimens </p>

<p>Patients, Con/ 
Exp groups </p>

<p>Age, years 
Culture 
conditions </p>

<p>Cell dose (cycles) </p>

<p>Con 
Exp </p>

<p>chang et al </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>2013 iii-iV 
cT, ciK 
33/33 
66 (median) 
66 (median) 
iFn-γ, il-2, OKT-3 1×10 
9 /cycle (2 cycles) </p>

<p>hu </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>2012 iii-iV 
cM, cT, ciK 25/37 
nD 
nD 
iFn-γ, il-1, il-2 
.1×10 
9 /cycle (nD) </p>

<p>liu et al </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>2011 iii-iV 
cT, ciK 
20/20 
62 (median) 
62 (median) 
iFn-γ, il-2, OKT-3 (0.6-1.6)×10 
10 /cycle 
(3 cycles) 
Qu et al </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>2015 iV 
cT, ciK 
100/100 
56.3±7.5 (mean) 56.3±7.5 (mean) iFn-γ, OKT-3, 
il-2, il-12 </p>

<p>nD (nD) </p>

<p>shu et al </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>2015 ii-iii 
rT, cT, ciK 30/30 
59 (median) 
57 (median) 
iFn-γ, OKT-3, il-2 5×10 
10 /cycle (nD) </p>

<p>Wang et al </p>

<p>33,41 </p>

<p>2014 i-iV 
cT, Dc-ciK </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>62/62 
nD 
nD 
iFn-γ, il-2, OKT-3 
(ciK) </p>

<p>2×10 
10 /cycle (nD) </p>

<p>gM-csF, il-4, 
iFn-γ (Dc) 
Xi et al </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>2015 ii-iiiB surgery, cT, 
Dc-ciK </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>26/26 
62 (median) 
60 (median) 
iFn-γ, il-1, il-2, 
OKT-3 (ciK) </p>

<p>3-4×10 
9 /cycle 
(2 cycles) 
gM-csF, il-4, 
TnF-α, il-1 (Dc) 
Xu et al </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>2010 iii-iV 
cT, ciK 
25/21 
42 (mean) 
45 (mean) 
iFn-γ, il-1α, il-2, 
OKT-3 </p>

<p>.5×10 
9 /cycle 
(4 cycles) 
Yan et al </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>2015 i-iV 
rT, Dc-ciK </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>34/34 
71.6±2.2 (mean) 70.5±2.9 (mean) iFn-γ, il-1α, il-2, 
OKT-3 (ciK) </p>

<p>5×10 
9 /cycle (ciK) </p>

<p>gM-csF, il-4 
(Dc) </p>

<p>5×10 
7 /cycle (Dc) 
(nD) 
Yang et al </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>2015 nD 
cT, Dc-ciK </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>100/100 
72.3±6.9 (mean) 70.2±7.3 (mean) nD 
nD (1-2 cycles) 
Zhu and 
Zhang </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>2014 nD 
cT, ciK 
38/38 
59.8±1.4 (mean) 59.6±1.3 (mean) nD 
nD (nD) </p>

<p>Notes: The table summarizes patients' basic information regarding the tumor stage, treatment regimens, cases, age and details of the immunotherapy (culture conditions, 
cell doses and the treatment courses). </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Dcs cultivated with ciK before injection; </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>coinjection of Dcs with ciKs. 
Abbreviations: cD, cluster of differentiation; ciK, cytokine-induced killer cell; cM, chinese medicine (huisheng oral liquid); con, control group; cT, chemotherapy; 
Dc, dendritic cell; exp, experimental group; gM-csF, granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor; iFn, interferon; il, interleukin; OKT-3, cD3 monoclonal antibodies; 
nD, not determined; rT, radiotherapy; TnF, tumor necrosis factor. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1901 </p>

<p>cytokine-induced killer cells for the treatment of esophageal cancer </p>

<p>Figure 2 review of authors' judgments about each risk of bias item for included studies. 
Notes: (A) risk of bias summary. (B) risk of bias graph: review of authors' judgments about each risk of bias item presented as percentages across all included studies. </p>

<p>Figure 3 (Continued) </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1902 </p>

<p>liu et al </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>Figure 4 Forest plot for the comparison of Qir. 
Note: The fixed-effects meta-analysis model (Mantel-Haenszel method) was used. 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; CIK/DC-CIK, immunotherapy with cytokine-induced killer cells or combination of dendritic cells and cytokine-induced killer cells; 
cont, conventional therapy; M-h, Mantel-haenszel method; Qir, quality-of-life improved rate. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Forest plots of the comparisons of (A) Os and (B) Orr and Dcr. 
Note: The fixed-effects meta-analysis model (Mantel-Haenszel method) was used. 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; CIK/DC-CIK, immunotherapy with cytokine-induced killer cells or combination of dendritic cells and cytokine-induced killer cells; 
cont, conventional therapy; Dcr, disease control rate; M-h, Mantel-haenszel method; Orr, overall response rate; Os, overall survival. </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1903 </p>

<p>cytokine-induced killer cells for the treatment of esophageal cancer </p>

<p>τ 
χ </p>

<p>τ 
χ </p>

<p>τ 
χ </p>

<p>τ 
χ </p>

<p>τ 
χ </p>

<p>τ 
χ </p>

<p>τ 
χ </p>

<p>τ 
χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>Figure 5 Forest plot of immunophenotype assessment before and after treatment with ciK/Dc-ciK. 
Note: The random-effects meta-analysis model (Mantel-haenszel method) was used in this analysis. 
Abbreviations: CD, cluster of differentiation; CI, confidence interval; CIK/DC-CIK, immunotherapy with cytokine-induced killer cells or combination of dendritic cells and 
cytokine-induced killer cells; sD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1904 </p>

<p>liu et al </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>γ </p>

<p>α </p>

<p>Figure 6 Forest plot of cytokines before and after treatment with ciK/Dc-ciK. 
Note: The fixed-effects meta-analysis model (Mantel-Haenszel method) was used in this analysis. 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; CIK/DC-CIK, immunotherapy with cytokine-induced killer cells or combination of dendritic cells and cytokine-induced killer cells; 
iFn, interferon; il, interleukin; sD, standard deviation; TnF, tumor necrosis factor. </p>

<p>(Figure 6, IFN-γ: OR =36.30, 95% CI =31.54−41.06, P,0.00001; 
IL-2: OR =13.00, 95% CI =9.88−16.12, P,0.00001; TNF-α: 
OR =15.10, 95% CI =12.31−17.89, P,0.00001; IL-12: 
OR =56.30, 95% CI =51.32−61.28, P,0.00001). </p>

<p>assessment of adverse events </p>

<p>The safety of CIK/DC-CIK therapy in the treatment of EC 
was evaluated in this meta-analysis. As shown in Figure 7, 
no serious adverse events or death occurrence was reported 
in the involved literature. The most common side effect was 
fever, which subsided naturally within 24 hours. Except the 
higher incidence of fever in the combination therapy group 
than in the conventional therapy group (fever: OR =6.46, 
95% CI =2.42-17.21, P=0.0002), no significant difference 
was observed in terms of leukopenia, gastrointestinal adverse 
reaction and peripheral neurotoxicity (leukopenia: OR =0.91, 
95% CI =0.39-2.12, P=0.83; gastrointestinal adverse reac-
tion: OR =0.51, 95% CI =0.22-1.22, P=0.13; peripheral 
neurotoxicity: OR =0.75, 95% CI =0.26-2.15, P=0.59). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Clinical trials have been conducted on CIK/DC-CIK immu-
notherapy for the treatment of EC. 
26,31 In this study, we 
performed an extensive online search, followed by rigorous </p>

<p>meta-analysis, in order to evaluate its therapeutic efficacy 
and safety. Our meta-analysis revealed that the combination 
of CIK/DC-CIK immunotherapy and conventional therapy 
was a safe and effective regimen for the treatment of EC. 
Compared to conventional regimens alone, patients with 
combination therapy demonstrated higher OS rate, ORR and 
DCR, as well as improved immune function and QoL. 
This study confirmed the safety of CIK/DC-CIK immu-
notherapy for EC patients, and the adverse events caused 
were tolerated by all patients. Fever was the most common 
side effect when patients were treated with combination 
conventional-plus-CIK/DC-CIK therapy, and its incidence 
was higher than when treated by conventional therapy alone 
(P,0.05). No significant difference was observed in terms 
of other adverse events, such as leukopenia, gastrointestinal 
adverse reaction and peripheral neurotoxicity between the 
2 groups (P.0.05). CIK/DC-CIK immunotherapy enhanced 
the efficiency of conventional therapy in the treatment of EC. 
Compared with the conventional therapy-alone group, 1-year 
OS, ORR and DCR of patients in the combination therapy 
group were improved remarkably (P,0.01). Moreover, the 
combination therapy improved patients' QoL (P,0.05) by 
relieving pain, reducing fatigue and insomnia as well as 
improving appetite. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1905 </p>

<p>cytokine-induced killer cells for the treatment of esophageal cancer </p>

<p>Health status is closely related to human immune function, 
and a healthy human body has a robust immune system to 
detect and kill cancer cells. 
5,6 However, the immune function 
in cancer patients is compromised, and the percentage of 
T-lymphocyte subsets in the peripheral blood is usually 
disordered. 
5,6 Immune system reconstruction is one of the key 
factors to effectively treat malignant tumors. 
6 The antitumor 
activity of CIK/DC-CIK is mainly attributed to CD3 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>CD56 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>and CD3 
+ CD56 
+ cells. 
41 Our analysis indicated that the 
proportions of CD3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, CD3 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>CD56 
+ and CD3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>CD56 
+ T cells 
were increased after CIK/DC-CIK treatment, although the 
percentages of CD3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>CD56 
+ T cells did not reach statistical 
significance. However, no significant differences were found 
in the percentages of CD4 
+ , CD8 
+ and CD4 
+ /CD8 
+ ratios 
before and after immunotherapy. This may be caused by the </p>

<p>different time points when the T-lymphocyte subsets were 
tested in these trials. 
6,19,42,43 Our analysis revealed a decreased 
proportion of CD4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>CD25 
+ CD127 
-Tregs. This is consistent 
with a previous study that illustrated a negative role of Tregs 
in the implementation of CIK's antitumor activity. 
44 Besides, 
the balance between the 2 helper T-cell (Th1 and Th2 cells) 
classes is also important in immunotherapy. 
5,41 Th1 cells 
enhance killer cells' cytotoxicity and trigger delayed-type 
hypersensitivity, whereas Th2 cells are associated with 
tumor immune escape. 
5,45 Our analysis showed that after 
CIK/DC-CIK immunotherapy, the levels of Th1 cytokines, 
including IFN-γ, IL-2, TNF-α and IL-12, were significantly 
increased (P,0.00001), indicating a strong association 
between Th1 cytokines and efficacy of CIK/DC-CIK immu-
notherapy. Although our results indicated that CIK/DC-CIK </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>Figure 7 Forest plot of the comparison of adverse effects. 
Note: The random-effects meta-analysis model (Mantel-haenszel method) was used in this analysis. 
Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; CIK/DC-CIK, immunotherapy with cytokine-induced killer cells or combination of dendritic cells and cytokine-induced killer cells; 
cont, conventional therapy; M-h, Mantel-haenszel method. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1906 </p>

<p>liu et al </p>

<p>immunotherapy enhanced the immune function in EC patients, 
the exact underlying mechanism of action of CIK/DC-CIK 
immunotherapy on hosts' immune system remains unclear, 
which requires further studies on its mechanism. 
This meta-analysis has some limitations. First of all, 
although CIK/DC-CIK immunotherapy has been applied to 
treat malignancies worldwide for its outstanding curative 
effects, 
46-48 all of the clinic trials that met our inclusion criteria 
were carried out in the Chinese population. We will follow 
updated publications on CIK/DC-CIK immunotherapy for 
EC conducted both in China and other countries and subse-
quently perform further systematic research on it. Moreover, 
the analysis performed in this study was not subjected to an 
open external evaluation procedure, which may lead to an 
overestimation of treatment effects. In addition, insufficient 
information regarding some patients, small sample sizes and 
other variables may have introduced bias into our conclu-
sions. Besides, the clinical application of adoptive CIK/ 
DC-CIK immunotherapy was limited due to the low speci-
ficity, although it is a promising strategy for the treatment of 
malignant tumors. Many new methods of immunotherapy, 
such as chimeric antigen receptor-modified T cells and T-cell 
receptor-modified T cells, have been developed currently, </p>

<p>49-51   limiting the importance of this study. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Taken together, this meta-analysis suggests that the combi-
nation of CIK/DC-CIK immunotherapy and conventional 
regimens is safe and effective in treating patients with EC, 
with markedly prolonged survival time, enhanced immune 
function and improved therapeutic efficacy. Considering the 
limitations of our research, further analysis on studies con-
ducted in countries other than China with larger sample sizes 
and going through open external evaluation procedure will 
be valuable to verify the credibility of our conclusions. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>This research work was supported by grants from the Natural 
Science Foundation of Shandong (No 2015ZRA15027 to 
Changhui Zhou), National Natural Science Foundation 
of China (No 81600087 to Shaoda Ren), Natural Science 
Foundation of Shandong (No ZR2016HB45 to Shaoda Ren), 
Medical Science Foundation of Shandong (No 2014WS0300 
to Weihua Wang) and Wu Jieping Medical Foundation 
(No 320.6750.15043 to Weihua Wang). </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>Changhui Zhou and Yingxin Zhang conceived and des-
igned the experiments. Yan Liu, Ying Mu and Shaoda Ren </p>

<p>performed the experiments. Weihua Wang and Jiaping Xie 
analyzed the data. Yan Liu and Ying Mu drafted the manu-
script. All authors contributed toward data analysis, drafting 
and critically revising the paper and agree to be accountable 
for all aspects of the work. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open 
access journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1908 </p>

<p>liu et al </p>

</text></tei>