<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5111494" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background and aims. To assess and compare the effects of different oral 
hygiene procedures on the reduction of morning bad breath, plaque and gingival status 
in healthy subjects. 
Methods. A four step cross-over trial was performed on 32 study subjects. They 
were allocated into four groups: Group I: tooth brushing; Group II: tooth brushing 
and tongue scraping; Group III: tooth brushing and mouth washing; and Group IV: 
tooth brushing, tongue scraping and use of mouthwash. A washout interval of 7 days 
was employed. At the beginning and at the end of all intervention periods, breath score 
was measured by hand held sulfide monitor (Breath Alert) at four time intervals. The 
Plaque and Gingival status was evaluated using Plaque and Gingival Index. 
Results. The highest reduction in mean breath score (2.12±0.65), plaque score 
(0.75±0.47) and gingival score (0.67±0.41) were found in the Group IV followed 
by Group II and Group III. A significant positive correlation was observed between 
plaque scores and gingival scores before intervention (r=0.443; p value&lt;0.001) and 
after intervention (r=0.846; p value&lt;0.001). 
Conclusion. The study findings suggest that mechanical aids in conjunction 
with chemical regimens are considered as the most effective method for reducing 
the morning bad breath in healthy subjects and should be incorporated in daily oral 
hygiene practices. </p>

<p>Keywords: bad breath, dental plaque, gingivitis, mouthwash, sulfide monitor, 
tongue scraping </p>

<p>exposed necrotic tooth pulps, pericoronitis, mucosal 
ulcerations, healing wounds, impacted food or debris, 
imperfect dental restorations, unclean dentures and factors 
causing decreased salivary flow rate [3-5]. Non-oral sources 
of breath odor are generally related to systemic problems 
and/or medications including conditions such as diabetes, 
liver and kidney disorders, and pulmonary disease. Some 
medications, especially those that reduce salivary flow such 
as antidepressants, antipsychotics, narcotics, decongestants, 
antihistamines, and antihypertensive drugs contribute 
towards non-oral sources of breath odor [6]. 
The main contributor to halitosis is known to be the 
volatile sulfur compounds (VSC): hydrogen sulfide, methyl </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Halitosis, oral malodor, fetor oris, or bad breath 
are the common terms which are used to depict obnoxious 
breath emitted from a person's mouth, in spite of whether 
the malodorous substances in the breath are derived from 
oral or non-oral sources, and it can have major detrimental 
impact on normal social interactions [1,2]. The cause of 
halitosis have been attributed to a number of factors, i.e 
source could be from oral causes i.e. tongue coating, peri-
implant disease, periodontal disease, deep carious lesions, </p>

<p>DOI: 10.15386/cjmed-627 </p>

<p>Manuscript received: 01.01.2016 
Received in revised form: 21.01.2016 
Accepted: 03.02.2016 
Address for correspondence: shaijal1901@gmail.com </p>

<p>526 </p>

<p>Dental Medicine </p>

<p>Clujul Medical Vol.89, No.4, 2016: 525-533 </p>

<p>mercaptan and dimethyl sulfide). VSCs are produced 
by the degradation of food debris, desquamated cells, 
saliva proteins, dental plaque and microbial putrefaction 
by a variety of oral anaerobic organisms which include 
Porphyromonas gingivalis, Prevotella intermedia, 
Treponema 
denticola, 
Fusobacterium 
nucleatum, 
Tannerella forsythensis, Porphyromonas endodontalis and 
Eubacterium species [2,6]. These organisms are recoverable 
in huge numbers from the periodontal pockets, gingival 
crevicular fluid, tongue, predominantly where coating 
of tongue is prominent [7]. The dorsum of the tongue 
provides an appropriate environment for the development 
of these microorganisms, as deep crypts of tongue provide 
the favourable redox potentials and offer a best milieu for 
the initiation of VSCs and other volatile compounds that 
contribute to bad breath [8,9]. 
There are various side effects associated with H 2 S, 
such as localized halitosis, periodontal tissue disorders and 
discoloration and corrosion of metal restorations. A study 
by Yamaguchi T et al. [10] suggests that H 2 S can cause tooth 
wear by triggering changes to enamel surface structure and 
crystal morphology, and also bond strength of enamel and 
composite restorations could be affected by H 2 S. 
Halitosis exists in various diverse clinical situations. 
Malodorous breath on arising after a night's sleep is a 
condition which is commonly known as ''morning bad 
breath''. This appears to result from the excessive quantities 
of volatile gases containing sulphur of bacterial origin 
and also due to reduced salivation during sleep promotes 
abundance of bacterial proliferation that release obnoxious 
gases [11]. 
Currently there is no accepted protocol intended 
for the reduction of bad breath. Patients mostly mask bad 
breath through habitual brushing or with a wide range of 
methods like mints, chewing gums, liquid drops, and the 
use of mouthwashes. But most of these simply provide 
a momentary smell that is able to mask the unfavorable 
malodor [12]. 
Both mechanical and chemical methods are available 
for controlling bad breath. For example, oral malodor can 
be reduced by diminishing the amount of contributory 
bacteria present in the oral cavity or by converting VSCs to 
non-volatile products [13]. Mechanical tooth cleaning aids, 
such as tooth brushing or interdental flossing, is considered 
as an important routine oral hygiene practice, but many 
studies found out that individual tooth brushing will not 
significantly decrease oral malodorous breath. While, on 
the other hand, tongue cleaning and mouth rinsing can 
reduce level of volatile sulphur compounds [14]. 
Reduction of the contributing oral microorganisms 
could also be achieved by improving oral hygiene in addition 
to tongue cleaning. This can be achieved by scraping the 
tongue dorsum with the help of tongue scrapers to remove 
trapped bacteria and food from the filiform papillae [8]. 
To target the anaerobic micro-organisms and thus </p>

<p>reduce bad breath, various topical anti-bacterial agents have 
been used. Anti-microbial compounds such as chlorhexidine 
(CHX), cetylpyridinium chloride (CPC), triclosan, chlorine 
dioxide, essential oils, zinc salts, hydrogen peroxide and 
sodium bicarbonate have been used, either individually or in 
different combinations, or collectively with the mechanical 
aids, for their effectiveness to reduce bad breath [15]. 
There are various therapies that reduce morning 
bad breath but they do not imply efficacy in the treatment 
of halitosis; yet, morning bad breath has often been used 
as a model to test the efficacy of various therapies on oral 
malodor as a substitute for working with true halitosis 
patients [16]. Various studies of tongue cleaning procedures 
and mouth rinse applications have been conducted. Though 
there are few studies which have compared the effect of 
combination of mechanical and chemical oral hygiene 
procedures on the reduction of bad breath in healthy 
subjects [17]. Therefore, this study aim at assessing and 
comparing the effects of different oral hygiene procedures, 
i.e., tooth brushing, tongue cleaning and mouth washing 
alone and in combination, on the reduction of morning bad 
breath, plaque and gingival status in healthy subjects. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study subjects 
The study was conducted in the Department of Public 
Health Dentistry at Sri Aurobindo College of Dentistry, 
from May 2015 to July 2015. The permission was obtained 
from the Dean of Sri Aurobindo College of Dentistry to 
carry out the study among dental students. Ethical approval 
was obtained from the Institutional Ethical Committee 
of Sri Aurobindo College of Dentistry. All participants 
volunteered to participate in the study and were given oral 
and written information about the purpose of the study. All 
the participants gave informed consent. 
A pilot study was conducted and based upon the 
findings of the pilot study, a statistical software (PASS13) 
was used to determine the final sample size. Under the 
assumption that α=0.05 and power at 80%, size of 24 in 
the experimental groups was calculated. Therefore, under 
consideration of dropout rate a sample size of 32 per group 
was designed. 
Thirty two dental students, 16 females and 16 males 
(aged 20-28 years) gave their consent to participate in the 
present study. All subjects underwent an oral examination 
prior to the start of study, which included whole mouth 
periodontal probing and caries assessment. 
The subjects with good oral hygiene and the subjects 
willing to participate and provide the informed consent 
prior to start of the study were included in the study. 
The subjects with dental caries, medical disorders, 
undergoing antibiotic therapy, smokers, pregnant women 
and those subjects on pre-study screening (screening of 
individuals before the participants were allocated into the 
groups), presented a probing pocket depth&gt;4mm were </p>



<p>Original Research </p>

<p>Clujul Medical Vol.89, No.4, 2016: 525-533 </p>

<p>excluded from the study. 
Study Design and Procedures 
The present study was designed as a prospective 
cross over, single-blind study with an examination period 
of 8 weeks. CONSORT (Consolidated Statement of 
Reporting Trials) guidelines were used in reporting of the 
present study. 
Study subjects were divided into 4 groups, which 
underwent four trial periods of 7 days. In each period, 
every volunteer performed the following oral hygiene 
procedures: 
Group I: tooth brushing only; 
Group II: tooth brushing and tongue scraping; 
Group III: tooth brushing and use of mouthwash; 
and 
Group IV: tooth brushing, tongue scraping and use 
of mouthwash. 
A coordinator organized a hygiene kit containing 
toothbrushes, tongue scrapers and mouthwashes and was 
liable for giving the kits to the volunteers. Investigator 
was carefully trained The investigator was responsible 
for evaluating and recording the breath scores, plaque and 
gingival scores. Theinvestigator was blinded to treatment 
assignment for the study duration andwas trained in plaque 
and gingival measurement. The several measurements of 
plaque and gingival levels concealed an intra-examiner 
kappa value of 0.80. This cross over trial comprised of two 
phases that is pre-experimental and experimental phase. 
Pre-experimental phase 
One week prior the commencement of the study, 
study subjects underwent motivation sessions in which 
standard oral hygiene instructions were given. They were 
not permitted to use any type of mouthwash, perform 
interdental flossing, and tongue scraping from the week 
before the first experimental period. 
Baseline assessment 
Following the pre-experimental phase the study 
subjects were scheduled in the morning for baseline 
evaluation of breath scores, in agreement with the following 
criteria: the night before the appointment, volunteers were 
asked to avoid the consumption of foods which produce a 
strong odor like ginger, garlic, onions, eggs, and cabbages 
as well as intake of alcoholic beverages. They were 
instructed to refrain from oral hygiene measures for 20 
hours before commencement of the experiments. In the 
morning, subjects should be in complete fasting situation 
without performing any type of oral hygiene and they 
should not use any type of cosmetics that liberates odors/ 
perfumes. 
According to cross-over design, the subjects 
received one of assigned experimental group that they were 
allowed to use during the following 7 days period. 
Experimental phase 
Each experimental phase was for one week duration </p>

<p>followed by 7 days wash out interval. In between the 
experimental periods the study subjects maintained the 
standard oral hygiene that was practiced by them throughout 
pre-experimental phase. Compliance was assessed by 
calling the subjects after 7 
th day of each experimental phase 
by an investigator. </p>

<p>Evaluation Criteria </p>

<p>Breath evaluations 
At the start and at the end of all experimental periods, 
breath scores were measured by asking the volunteers to 
expel air through their mouths into a hand-held sulfide 
monitor, Breath Alert™ (Tanita Corporation®-Japan), 
according to the manufacturer's instructions as performed 
previously in a study done by Pedrazzi et al and Jeronimo 
M et al. [18,19]. 
The breath of each volunteer was examined at the 
following time intervals: 
• T 00 = before using the product (baseline data) 
• T 0 = immediately after using the product. 
• T 1 = after 1 hour 
• T 3 = after 3 hours on day 1 and day 7 
Oral health examination 
Following the breath evaluation, the Plaque and 
Gingival status were evaluated with the use of Plaque Index 
by Silness.P and Loe.H and Gingival Index by Loe and 
Sillness respectively. 
Clinical Assessment was done on 1 
st day before the 
intervention used and on day 7 </p>

<p>th </p>

<p>, after one week of each 
experimental period, Plaque Index and Gingival Index 
were reassessed. </p>

<p>Measurement tools </p>

<p>A structured proforma was developed consisting 
of socio-demographic details and oral hygiene practices 
of study participants. It also included the formats for 
recording breath scores day 1 and day 7 at each time 
interval (T00, T0, T1, T3), Plaque index 1967 and Gingival 
index 1963 to record the plaque status and gingival status 
respectively. Hand held sulfide monitor (Breath Alert) was 
used to measure breath scores at four time intervals. The 
mouth mirror, a light source, dental explorer, William's 
periodontal probe and air drying of the teeth and gingiva 
were used for the scoring of Plaque and Gingival index. The 
trial was performed under the strict sterilization protocol. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analyses was performed using the 
Statistical Package for Social Sciences for Windows 
(<rs id="software-3" type="software">SPSS</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">Version 20.0</rs>). According to the cross over 
design, the mean breath scores, plaque and gingival scores 
were compared within the groups using Paired sample t test 
and between the groups applying the ANOVA (Analysis 
of variance) with Post hoc Tukey's test. The relationship 
between the plaque scores and gingival scores day 1 and 
7 
th day was obtained by Pearson's correlation. Level of 
significance was set at p≤0.05. </p>



<p>Dental Medicine </p>

<p>Clujul Medical Vol.89, No.4, 2016: 525-533 </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>All the selected subjects (n=32) completed the 
study so response rate obtained was 100%. The distribution 
of study participants with respect to the age, gender and 
education and there oral hygiene practices is shown in Table 
I. Mean Age of study subjects was found to be 23.65±1.94 
and there was an equal distribution of females and males 
among the study subjects. 
Table II shows within group comparison of mean 
values of breath scores and difference in scores before and 
after for each intervention group. The highest mean values 
of breath scores were found in groups 1 and 3 in which 
tongue scraping was excluded (Fig 1). While the highest 
reduction in mean values of breath scores was found in 
groups 4 and 2 in which tongue scraping was performed. 
Group 1 did not differ significantly from baseline i.e. (T 00 ) 
to each time interval i.e. (T 0 , T 1 , T3) before and after the 
intervention used. 
Table III shows group comparisons of mean 
values of breath scores before intervention (day 1) and 
after intervention (day 7). Prior to the intervention, there 
were no significant differences (p&gt;0.05) for breath scores 
between the four groups from baseline i.e. (T 00 ) to each 
time interval i.e. (T 0 , T 1 , T3). Additionally, considering the 
washout periods, it was noticed that no carryover effect 
occurred between the interventions. The comparison of the </p>

<p>interventions after 7 days revealed that breath scores at each 
time interval were most inhibited in Group 4 (p&lt;0.001) 
followed by Group 2 (p&lt;0.001) followed by Group 3 and 
Group 1. Post Hoc analysis showed significant difference 
between Group 4 and Group1, Group 2 and Group 3 at each 
time interval i.e. T 00 , T 0 , T 1 , T 3. 
The comparison of mean plaque and gingival 
scores on day 1 and day 7 within and between the groups 
is presented in Table IV and V respectively. The highest 
reduction in mean plaque value (0.75±0.47) and mean 
gingival value (0.67±0.41) was found for Group 4 which 
shows that Group 4 was significantly (p&lt;0.001) more 
effective than Groups 1, 2 and 3 in reducing plaque, while 
scores recorded onday 7 i.e. after the intervention used 
and Post Hoc analysis also showed a significant difference 
between Group 4 and Groups 1, 2 and 3. The results also 
demonstrated that no significant difference was observed 
in the plaque scores (p value=0.146) and gingival scores 
(p value=0.850) recorded on day 1 between the groups. A 
significant reduction (p&lt;0.001) was observed in the plaque 
and gingival scores recorded on day 7 between the groups. 
Furthermore, a significant positive correlation was 
observed between plaque scores and gingival scores before 
intervention (day 1 ) (r=0.443; p value&lt;0.001) and after 
intervention (day 7) (r=0.846; p value&lt;0.001). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Mean Breath scores before the intervention (Pi) and after the intervention (Po) of Group1, 2, 3, 4 at four 
time intervals. </p>



<p>Original Research </p>

<p>Clujul Medical Vol.89, No.4, 2016: 525-533 </p>

<p>FACTORS 
N (%) </p>

<p>Age </p>

<p>Mean Age 
23.65±1.94 </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Male 
16 (50%) </p>

<p>Female 
16 (50%) </p>

<p>Education </p>

<p>B.D.S II 
nd Year 
9 (28.1%) </p>

<p>Interns 
12 (37.5%) </p>

<p>Post-Graduates 
11 (34.4%) </p>

<p>Tooth Brushing Method </p>

<p>Horizontal-scrub 
5 (15.6%) </p>

<p>Horizontal+ Circular 
18 (56.2%) </p>

<p>Horizontal+ Vertical 
3 (9.4%) </p>

<p>Other Technique 
6 (18.8%) </p>

<p>Dentifrice </p>

<p>Yes 
32 (100%) </p>

<p>No 
0 (0%) </p>

<p>Other Oral Hygiene Practices Used </p>

<p>Yes 
5 (15.6%) </p>

<p>No 
27 (84.4%) </p>

<p>Table I. Demographic characteristics and Oral hygiene 
practices of participants (N=32). </p>

<p>Groups 
Pre-Intervention (day 1) 
Post-Intervention (day 7) </p>

<p>T 00 
T 0 
T 1 
T 3 
T 00 
T 0 
T 1 
T 3 </p>

<p>Group 1 
3.00±0.43 
1.96±0.47 
2.25±0.56 2.84±0.57 2.96±0.47 
1.93±0.50 
2.46±0.62 
2.84±0.57 </p>

<p>Group 2 
2.96±0.40 
1.93±0.43 
2.18±0.59 2.78±0.55 2.15±0.44 
0.62±0.49 
0.65±0.48 
0.75±0.43 </p>

<p>Group 3 
2.87±0.42 
1.87±0.42 
2.12±0.60 2.75±0.50 2.31±0.47 
0.96±0.40 
1.12±0.42 
1.96±0.30 </p>

<p>Group 4 
2.75±0.50 
1.71±0.52 
2.03±0.53 2.56±0.56 1.78±0.42 
0.31±0.47 
0.34±0.48 
0.43±0.50 </p>

<p>P-value 
.111 
.145 
.477 
.206 
&lt;0.001* 
&lt;0.001* 
&lt;0.001* 
&lt;0.001* </p>

<p>Table III. Inter group comparison of mean values of breath scores before intervention (day 1) and after intervention (day 7) (mean±SD; 
n=32). </p>

<p>ANOVA and Post Hoc Tukey's test;*p value &lt;0.05 </p>



<p>Dental Medicine </p>

<p>Clujul Medical Vol.89, No.4, 2016: 525-533 </p>

<p>Groups </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>-P </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>P-
value </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>-P </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>P-
value </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>-P </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>P-
value </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>-
P </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>P-
value </p>

<p>Group 
1 </p>

<p>3.00±0.43 </p>

<p>2.96±0.47 </p>

<p>0.03±0.17 </p>

<p>0.325 
1.96±0.47 1.93±0.50 </p>

<p>0.03±0.07 </p>

<p>0.662 </p>

<p>2.25±0.56 
2.46±0.62 -.21 ±0.79 </p>

<p>0.129 
2.84±0.57 2.84±0.57 0.00±0.35 </p>

<p>1.000 </p>

<p>Group 
2 </p>

<p>2.96±0.40 </p>

<p>2.15±0.44 </p>

<p>0.81±0.39 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001* 
1.93±0.43 0.62±0.49 </p>

<p>1.31±0.47 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001* </p>

<p>2.18±0.59 </p>

<p>0.65±0.48 </p>

<p>1.53±0.56 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001* 
2.78±0.55 0.75±0.43 2.03±0.53 &lt;0.001* </p>

<p>Group 
3 </p>

<p>2.87±0.42 </p>

<p>2.31±0.47 </p>

<p>0.56±0.50 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001* 
1.87±0.42 0.96±0.40 </p>

<p>0.90±0.39 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001* </p>

<p>2.12±0.60 </p>

<p>1.12±0.42 </p>

<p>1.00±0.56 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001* 
2.75±0.50 1.96±0.30 0.78±0.42 &lt;0.001* </p>

<p>Group 
4 </p>

<p>2.75±0.50 </p>

<p>1.78±0.42 </p>

<p>0.96±0.30 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001* 
1.71±0.52 0.31±0.47 </p>

<p>1.40±0.55 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001* </p>

<p>2.03±0.53 </p>

<p>0.3±0.48 </p>

<p>1.68±0.73 </p>

<p>&lt;0.001* 
2.56±0.56 0.43±0.50 2.12±0.65 &lt;0.001* </p>

<p>Table II. Intra group comparison of mean values of breath scores before intervention (day 1) and after intervention (day 7) and difference in changes (▲ scores) before and after for each 
intervention (mean±SD; n=32). </p>

<p>Paired t test;*p value &lt;0.05; Pi=Pre-intervention; Po=Post-intervention </p>



<p>Original Research </p>

<p>Clujul Medical Vol.89, No.4, 2016: 525-533 </p>

<p>Groups </p>

<p>Plaque score 
day 1 
(Mean± SD) </p>

<p>Plaque score day 7 
(Mean± SD) </p>

<p>Mean Difference in 
plaque scores at 1 </p>

<p>st </p>

<p>and 7 
th day </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>Group 1 
1.75±0.38 
1.66±0.35 
0.08±0.27 
0.079 </p>

<p>Group 2 
1.68±0.26 
1.45±0.26 
0.22±0.14 
&lt;0.001* </p>

<p>Group 3 
1.60±0.51 
1.07±0.20 
0.53±0.49 
&lt;0.001* </p>

<p>Group 4 
1.51±0.47 
0.76±0.14 
0.75±0.47 
&lt;0.001* </p>

<p>P value 
0.146 
&lt;0.001* 
__ 
__ </p>

<p>Table IV. Intra and Inter Group comparison of mean plaque scores before intervention (day 1) and after 
intervention (day 7). </p>

<p>Paired t test, ANOVA and Post Hoc Tukey's test;*p value &lt;0.05 </p>

<p>Groups </p>

<p>Gingival score 
day 1 
(Mean± SD) </p>

<p>Gingival score 
day 7 
(Mean± SD) </p>

<p>Mean Difference in 
Gingival scores at 1 </p>

<p>st </p>

<p>and 7 
th day </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>Group 1 
1.50±0.15 
1.40±0.14 
0.09±0.12 
&lt;0.001* </p>

<p>Group 2 
1.47±0.18 
1.33±0.20 
0.14±0.11 
&lt;0.001* </p>

<p>Group 3 
1.44±0.32 
0.97±0.18 
0.46±0.36 
&lt;0.001* </p>

<p>Group 4 
1.44±0.44 
0.77±0.45 
0.67±0.41 
&lt;0.001* </p>

<p>P value 
0.850 
&lt;0.001* 
__ 
__ </p>

<p>Table V. Intra and Inter group comparison of mean gingival scores before intervention (day 1) and after 
intervention (day 7). </p>

<p>Paired t test, ANOVA and Post Hoc Tukey's test;*p value &lt;0.05 </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this cross-over trial, the contributions of various 
oral hygiene procedures in reducing morning bad breath 
like tooth brushing, tongue scraping, use of mouthwash 
and combined use of all these oral hygiene aids in healthy 
subjects were investigated. 
In this study, intra group analysis showed significant 
difference in reduction of breath scores in groups 2, 3 and 
4 from baseline (T00) to each time interval (T0, T1, T3) 
Group 1 showed no significant difference from baseline 
(T00) to each time interval (T0, T1, T3) . This could be 
attributed to the fact that in Group 1 (tooth brushing) was 
performed by the participants which may have disrupted 
the formation of plaque biofilm present on the tooth surface 
thereby increasing the breath scores at each time interval. 
Similar findings were reported in previous studies carried 
out by Jeronimo M et al. [19] and Newby et al. [20]. 
The Post Intervention analysis (day 7) revealed 
significant difference in reducing the breath scores from 
baseline (T00) to each time interval (T0, T1, T3) in every 
group. The highest reduction in breath scores at each time 
interval was observed in Group 4 involving combined use 
of brushing, tongue scraping and mouthwash followed by </p>

<p>Group 2 involving use of tongue scraping method followed 
by group 3 and group 1. The findings are in the accordance 
with the findings of the previous study by Aung Ei et al. 
[14]. They reported that individual mechanical oral hygiene 
aid was able to immediately reduce bad breath, but for 
short duration, whereas combined use of Chlorhexidine 
with mechanical aids like brushing and tongue scraping 
significantly reduced breath for longer period of time. This 
suggests that the chemical action of a mouthwash reduces 
bad breath by reaching those areas that are difficult to be 
accessed by tongue cleaning procedure, in particular the 
posterior one-third of the tongue and are suggestive of 
the beneficial impact of combined use of mechanical and 
chemical oral hygiene aids on morning breath and should 
therefore be integrated into daily oral hygiene procedure. 
In the present study the results also demonstrated 
that the subjects who performed tongue cleaning showed 
significantly lower mean breath values compared with Groups 
3 and 1.This could be explained on the basis that the tongue 
has a larger surface area and its papillary structure represents 
an anaerobic environment in the oral cavity, favoring the 
accretion of oral debris and growth of microorganisms 
which are in turn responsible for the formation of VSC. </p>



<p>Dental Medicine </p>

<p>Clujul Medical Vol.89, No.4, 2016: 525-533 </p>

<p>The results of the present study are in agreement with other 
studies performed by Faveri et al. [11] and Pedrazzi et al. 
[18] that have demonstrated that the tongue is considered 
as the major site for the initiation of VSCs and removal of 
tongue coating improves oral malodour. In contrast to our 
results a study done by Carvalho et al. [16] and Jeronimo M 
et al. [19] reported that use of Chlorhexidine mouth rinse 
offered the best results in reducing morning bad breath for 
the prolonged duration of the time. 
Intra and inter group analysis of mean plaque 
scores recorded before the intervention (day 1 ) and after 
the intervention (day 7) showed significant reduction in 
group 2 , group 3 and group 4. The highest reduction in 
mean plaque scores was obtained in group 4, suggestive 
of the fact that the use of mouthwash in conjunction with 
mechanical aids is useful in improving the oral hygiene of 
the individual. Similar findings were reported in previous 
studies carried out by Bhopale D [21] and Yates et al. [22]. 
The present study results also demonstrated that Group 
3 (involving the individual use of mouthwash) was also 
found to be effective in reducing the mean plaque scores 
from baseline to each time interval. This finding is in 
agreement with the previous studies by Grundemann et al. 
[23], Francetti et al. [24] and Waghmere et al. [25]. This 
may be due to the property of substantivity and anti-plaque 
property of Chlorhexidine which suggest that individual 
use of Chemical oral hygiene aids i.e. use of mouthwash is 
superior to the use of mechanical aids in improving the oral 
hygiene status of the individual. 
The present study compared the mean gingival 
scores on the 1 
st and 7 
th days. Significant reduction was 
observed between the gingival scores recorded onday 1 1 
and day 7 in all the groups. Group 4 showed significantly 
higher reduction in gingival scores compared to other 
groups. This can be explained by the fact that combined 
use of mechanical and chemical oral hygiene aids is 
useful in reducing gingival bleeding as well as gingival 
inflammation. Group 3 was also found to be effective in 
reducing gingival scores in the individuals which is similar 
to the findings of Najafi M et al. [26], Neto C et al. [27] 
and J.L Lyes et al. [28]. This is suggestive of the fact that 
the chemical agents are superior to mechanical means in 
reducing gingival inflammation. 
Pearson's correlation coefficient test was performed 
to observe correlation between the Plaque scores and 
Gingival Scores before intervention (day 1) and after the 
intervention (day 7) and a positive correlation of plaque 
scores with gingival scores on days 1 and 7 was observed. 
This shows that the individuals with a higher plaque score 
at baseline also had more marked gingival inflammation 
Thus, the present study suggests an association between 
plaque and gingival status. This finding is in agreement 
with the study by Neto C et al. [27]. In which they found 
that increase in plaque score is associated with increased 
gingival inflammation. </p>

<p>The limitation of the present study could be that 
Volatile sulphur compound monitors (i.e. Halimeter) were 
not used for the present study due to the financial and time 
constraints. Although every effort has been taken by the 
authors to include and standardize the factors affecting bad 
breath, there might be other confounding factors that could 
have influenced the study results. Also, the small number 
of the study subjects in each group limits the generalization 
of the results; therefore further studies with larger sample 
size are warranted. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The results of the present study indicate that both 
tongue cleaning as the mechanical method and use of 
mouth wash as chemical method significantly reduce bad 
breath. However, combining both mechanical and chemical 
regimens are the most effective way in the reduction of 
morning bad breath in healthy subjects and should be 
considered as part of daily oral hygiene practices. This study 
also demonstrated that use of mouthwash in conjunction 
with mechanical aids are effective in reducing plaque and 
gingival scores and also the individual use of Chemical oral 
hygiene aids, i.e. use of mouthwash is superior to the use 
of mechanical aids in reducing plaque status and gingival 
inflammation. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We gratefully thank the study subjects for 
participating in the study. </p>







</text></tei>