<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5446083" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The modulation of canonical macroautophagy/autophagy for therapeutic benefit is an emerging strategy 
of medical and pharmaceutical interest. Many drugs act to inhibit autophagic flux by targeting lysosome 
function, while others were developed to activate the pathway. Here, we report the surprising finding that 
many therapeutically relevant autophagy modulators with lysosomotropic and ionophore properties, 
classified as inhibitors of canonical autophagy, are also capable of activating a parallel noncanonical 
autophagy pathway that drives MAP1LC3/LC3 lipidation on endolysosomal membranes. Further, we provide 
the first evidence supporting drug-induced noncanonical autophagy in vivo using the local anesthetic 
lidocaine and human skin biopsies. In addition, we find that several published inducers of autophagy and 
mitophagy are also potent activators of noncanonical autophagy. Together, our data raise important issues 
regarding the interpretation of LC3 lipidation data and the use of autophagy modulators, and highlight the 
need for a greater understanding of the functional consequences of noncanonical autophagy. </p>

<p>The canonical autophagy pathway is an evolutionarily con-
served lysosomal degradation pathway, through which intracel-
lular proteins and organelles are degraded and recycled. 
Autophagy plays a major role in cell and organismal homeosta-
sis and autophagic dysfunction contributes to the pathology of 
many diseases, including cancer and neurodegenerative disor-
ders. 
1 Recent research efforts have focused on the development 
of drugs to either activate or inhibit the canonical autophagy 
pathway, with many high-throughput drugs screens having 
been performed to identify new targets. </p>

<p>2-6   Canonical autophagy can be initiated by various cellular 
stresses, including nutrient withdrawal. The pathway is orches-
trated by multiple proteins including an upstream complex 
(ULK1/2, RB1CC1/FIP200, ATG13 and ATG101) hereafter 
referred to as the ULK complex, a class III phosphatidylinositol 3-
kinase (PIK3C3/VPS34) and a ubiquitin-like conjugation system 
(including ATG3, 4, 5, 7, 9, 10, 12 and 16L1). These autophagy 
proteins act in concert to form compartments termed phago-
phores that engulf intracellular constituents; completion and mat-
uration into double-membrane autophagosomes allows them to 
be targeted for degradation. 
7 Upon fusion with lysosomes, auto-
phagosomes and their contents are degraded and essential 
nutrients recycled. As such, the canonical autophagy pathway can 
be split into 2 stages; first, initiation of autophagosome formation 
and second, their flux through the lysosome. Autophagosome for-
mation, and therefore autophagy itself, is often measured using </p>

<p>the protein MAP1LC3/LC3 (microtubule-associated protein 1 
light chain 3). LC3 is a cytosolic ubiquitin-like protein that 
becomes conjugated to the membrane lipid phosphatidylethanol-
amine (PE) on forming autophagosomes. Therefore, the appear-
ance of LC3 puncta by microscopy, or the intensity of faster-
migrating lipidated LC3 (LC3-II) on SDS-PAGE gels, gives an 
indication of pathway activity, and are widely used to assay auto-
phagy. Autophagosome number, and levels of lipidated LC3, can 
differ depending on the point at which the pathway is disrupted. 
Inhibition of early formation, for instance via inhibition of or 
depletion of the ULK complex, will reduce autophagosome num-
bers. Conversely, inhibition of flux, via lysosome inhibition, will 
accumulate lipidated LC3 on undegraded autophagosomes. </p>

<p>8   It is now well established that autophagy proteins can also tar-
get and modify non-autophagosome compartments through a 
noncanonical pathway. 
9-11 This noncanonical autophagy path-
way mediates the lipidation of LC3 to single-membrane intracel-
lular compartments, including those of the endolysosomal 
system, following a range of macroendocytic engulfment events. 
The noncanonical autophagy pathway functions during the phys-
iological process of LC3-associated phagocytosis (LAP); 
11-15 dur-
ing which LC3 is lipidated to phagosomes housing a variety of 
pathogens or dead cells. Similar endolysosomal LC3 lipidation is 
observed on macropinosomes and during entosis, 
9 a live-cell 
engulfment process. 
10 LC3 lipidation in these processes is 
thought to regulate the fusion of vesicles with lysosomes. In the 
case of LAP this has important implications regarding the killing </p>

<p>CONTACT Oliver Florey 
oliver.florey@babraham.ac.uk 
Babraham Institute, Cambridge, CB22 3AT, United Kingdom. 
Color versions of one or more of the figures in the article can be found online at www.tandfonline.com/kaup. 
Supplemental data for this article can be accessed on the publisher's website. </p>

<p>© 2017 Elise Jacquin, St ephanie Leclerc-Mercier, Celine Judon, Emmanuelle Blanchard, Sylvie Fraitag, and Oliver Florey. Published with license by Taylor &amp; Francis. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which permits unre-
stricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The moral rights of the named author(s) have been asserted. </p>

<p>AUTOPHAGY 
2017, VOL. 13, NO. 5, 854-867 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/15548627.2017.1287653 </p>

<p>and clearance of pathogens, processing of antigens and macro-
phage cytokine responses following phagocytosis. </p>

<p>11,14-17   Mechanisms underlying regulation of the noncanonical 
pathway are now being explored. Recently, we reported that 
noncanonical autophagy and endolysosomal LC3 lipidation 
can be promoted by certain lysosomotropic drugs, such as chlo-
roquine, and the bacterial toxin VacA. 
18 Osmotic imbalances 
generated in endolysosomal compartments by these agents pro-
mote the recruitment of some autophagy proteins and lipida-
tion of LC3. Indeed, simply altering extracellular tonicity 
induces an osmotic flux of water into endolysosomal compart-
ments, which is sufficient to promote noncanonical autophagy. 
Physiological and drug-induced examples of noncanonical 
autophagy share the same features of being morphologically 
and genetically distinct from canonical autophagy. Indeed, 
noncanonical autophagy and endolysosomal LC3 lipidation 
proceed in the absence of autophagosomes. 
Here we present evidence that activation of noncanonical 
autophagy is a surprisingly common feature of therapeutically 
relevant lysosomotropic agents and ionophores and provide 
evidence that this can occur in vivo. Importantly, we also show 
that carbonyl cyanide m-chlorophenylhydrazone (CCCP), a 
commonly used inducer of mitophagy, and amiodarone, an 
activator of autophagy with applications to anticancer thera-
pies, are capable of activating noncanonical autophagy in paral-
lel. This raises important issues in the interpretation of 
experiments where LC3 is used as a marker for autophagy, and 
highlights the need for greater understanding of the functional 
consequences of noncanonical autophagy. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Ionophores and lysosomotropic drugs raise lysosomal pH </p>

<p>Lysosomes are acidic intracellular compartments where low pH 
is generated and maintained by the vacuolar-type H </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>-translo-
cating ATPase (V-ATPase) proton pump and an array of ion 
channels. 
19 We tested the effect of a range of ionophores and 
lysosomotropic drugs (Table S1) for their effect on lysosomal 
pH by measuring LysoTracker Red fluorescence in MCF10A 
human breast epithelial cells. As expected, direct inhibition of 
V-ATPase activity using bafilomycin A 1 (Baf) raised lysosomal 
pH and reduced LysoTracker Red staining (Fig. 1A and 1B). 
Nigericin (Nig) and monensin (Mon) are ionophores that drive 
the exchange of potassium and sodium, respectively, for hydro-
gen ions across membranes. In agreement with published work 
both nigericin and monensin dissipated lysosome pH (Fig. 1A 
and 1B). 
20 Lysosomotropic drugs are basic lipophilic com-
pounds with certain physiochemical properties that promote 
their accumulation in acidic compartments. 
21 Some classic 
lysosomotropic drugs include chloroquine (CQ) and its deriva-
tive hydroxychloroquine (HCQ), which are weak base amines 
used therapeutically as antimalarials and more recently as anti-
cancer drugs. 
22 Ammonium chloride (NH 4 Cl) is another weak 
base amine lysosomotropic drug. All 3 act to raise lysosome pH 
by sequestering hydrogen protons (Fig. 1A and 1B), and are 
extensively used to inhibit the canonical autophagy flux. Several 
pharmaceuticals also fall into the lysosomotropic drug category. 
Lidocaine hydrochloride (LH) and procainamide (ProA) are </p>

<p>local anesthetics, also commonly used as antiarrhythmic drugs. 
Betahistine (BH) is a histamine receptor antagonist with lysoso-
motropic properties, used in the treatment of vertigo. 
23 Lido-
caine hydrochloride, procainamide and betahistine all raised 
lysosomal pH (Fig. 1A and 1B). Alongside raising lysosomal 
pH, all of the drugs tested induced extensive formation of 
vacuoles (vacuolation) in cells. This observation has previously 
been reported and attributed to osmotic swelling of endolysoso-
mal compartments driven by ionic imbalances or increased sol-
ute content of the compartments. </p>

<p>24   These data demonstrate that the panel of commonly used 
drugs, of different classes, all raise lysosomal pH, and, impor-
tantly, achieve this without inhibiting the V-ATPase directly. </p>

<p>Ionophores and lysosomotropic drugs induce LC3 
lipidation independently from canonical autophagy </p>

<p>Inhibition of lysosome function, by raising lysosomal pH, 
results in the inhibition of autophagic flux and accumulation of 
autophagosomes. Monitoring LC3 lipidation is one of the 
major research methodologies used to assess the canonical 
autophagy pathway. All of the drugs tested in Fig. 1, which raise 
lysosomal pH, have been implicated in inhibiting autophagic 
flux and increasing LC3 lipidation levels (Table S1). However, 
in light of recent work demonstrating that LC3 lipidation can 
be induced independently of canonical autophagy, 
18 we sought 
to test whether these drugs also activated a noncanonical auto-
phagy pathway. 
To differentiate between LC3 lipidation associated with auto-
phagosomes and that associated with endolysosomal membranes 
during noncanonical autophagy, an autophagosome-deficient 
HEK293 cell line was generated using CRISPR/Cas9 to delete 
ATG13. ATG13 is part of the upstream ULK complex, which is 
essential for autophagosome formation. 
25,26 As shown by western 
blotting, wild-type cells displayed robust LC3 lipidation upon 
activation of canonical autophagy by starvation or inhibition of 
MTOR by PP242, whereas ATG13 
¡/¡ cells did not respond 
(Fig. S1A and S1B). Using confocal microscopy, GFP-LC3-
expressing wild-type cells displayed an increased LC3 puncta 
number following starvation, which represents autophagosome 
structures, and which was not seen in ATG13 
¡/¡ cells. Impor-
tantly, adding back mCherry-tagged ATG13 in ATG13 
¡/¡ cells 
restored GFP-LC3 puncta formation upon starvation (Fig. S1B), 
confirming this is a specific effect. Thus, ATG13 
¡/¡ HEK293 cells 
provide an effective model to detect potential LC3 lipidation 
events not associated with autophagosomes. 
To screen for noncanonical LC3 lipidation, dose responses were 
performed where wild-type and ATG13 
¡/¡ HEK293 cells were 
treated for 2 h with drugs at the indicated concentrations, in full 
medium. Cell lysates were then probed for LC3 and GAPDH by 
western blotting. As expected, the V-ATPase inhibitor bafilomycin 
A 1 induced an increase in lipidated LC3 (LC3-II) in wild-type cells, 
via inhibition of basal autophagic flux, while having no effect on 
LC3-II levels in autophagosome-deficient ATG13 
¡/¡ cells (Fig. 2A 
and 2B and Fig. S2A and S2B). Monensin, nigericin, chloroquine, 
hydroxychloroquine, NH 4 Cl, procainamide, lidocaine hydrochlo-
ride and betahistine all induced LC3 lipidation in wild-type cells 
(Fig. 2A and Fig. S2A). Strikingly, all of these drugs promoted LC3 </p>

<p>AUTOPHAGY </p>

<p>
lipidation in ATG13 
¡/¡ cells (Fig. 2B and Fig. S2B), indicating that 
they activate noncanonical autophagy. 
Together, these data indicate that a wide range of drugs activate 
noncanonical autophagy and promote LC3 lipidation in an 
ATG13-independent manner, in parallel to their known effects on 
inhibiting autophagic flux. These findings build on our previous 
studies of lysosomotropic drugs and extend this observation to 
include a wider range of drugs and ionophores. Interestingly, we 
note that LC3 lipidation in ATG13 
¡/¡ cells tends to require higher 
drug concentrations as compared with wild-type cells, indicating 
that inhibition of autophagic flux and activation of noncanonical 
autophagy may be achieved at different concentrations. </p>

<p>Ionophore-and lysosomotropic drug-induced LC3 
lipidation is dependent on V-ATPase activity </p>

<p>Inhibition of V-ATPase by bafilomycin A 1 does not affect the LC3 
lipidation step during autophagosome formation. In contrast, 
unconventional LC3 lipidation during noncanonical autophagy 
such as for LC3-associated phagocytosis (LAP) and entosis, are 
completely inhibited by bafilomycin A 1 . 
18 These data point to a 
more direct role for the V-ATPase in activating the LC3 lipidation 
machinery during noncanonical autophagy, although the mecha-
nism of V-ATPase action in this process remains unknown. 
To determine the effect of V-ATPase inhibition on LC3 lipi-
dation induced by our panel of drugs we pretreated ATG13 </p>

<p>¡/¡ </p>

<p>HEK293 cells with bafilomycin A 1 before treatment with the 
indicated drugs. Bafilomycin A 1 pretreatment completely abol-
ished drug-induced LC3 lipidation in all cases, supporting the 
conclusion that these drugs activate a noncanonical autophagy 
response (Fig. 2C). </p>

<p>Ionophores and lysosomotropic drugs activate 
noncanonical autophagy and promote LC3 lipidation to 
endolysosomal compartments </p>

<p>The data above clearly show that the panel of drugs tested induced 
ATG13-independent LC3 lipidation. To establish whether this LC3 
lipidation was associated with noncanonical autophagy and endo-
lysosomal membranes, we used confocal microscopy to image LC3 
localization during drug treatment. Using Atg13 (atg13 </p>

<p>¡/¡ </p>

<p>) and 
Atg9 (atg9 
¡/¡ ) knockout mouse embryonic fibroblast (MEF) cell 
lines, both of which are deficient in autophagosome biogenesis, </p>

<p>26,27   we stained endogenous LC3 and the lysosome marker LAMP1 fol-
lowing drug treatments. In both knockout cell lines, bafilomycin A 1 
has no obvious effect, whereas the other drug treatments induce 
dramatic LC3 relocalization (Fig. 3 and 4). LC3 was frequently 
colocalized with enlarged LAMP1 compartments (Fig. 3 and 4 
crops). Similar results have been found in epithelial cells, using a 
GFP-LC3-expressing MCF10A cell line in which ATG13 has been 
deleted (Fig. S1C and S1D and Fig. S3A). These structures are 
unlikely to be autophagosomes in nature given their large size and 
the genetic backgrounds of the cell lines used. Corroborating this, 
there is no detectable increase in the early autophagosome marker 
WIPI2 following drug treatment (Fig. S4). Together, these findings 
indicate that a range of drugs induce LC3 lipidation of endolysoso-
mal compartments distinct from autophagosomes. Interstingly, 
activation of lipidation did not appear to be restricted to LC3 family 
members as we also detected relocalization of GFP-GABARAPL2 
in atg9 
¡/¡ MEFs upon drug treatment (Fig. S5). 
To confirm that the drug-induced LC3 lipidation and relocali-
zation observed was associated with noncanonical autophagy, 
additional experiments were performed. Drug-induced effects on 
LC3 were lipidation dependent, as no lipidated LC3 was observed 
by western blot in ATG16 
¡/¡ MCF10A cells upon drug treatment 
(Fig. S6A and S6B), and the lipidation-defective GFP-LC3 </p>

<p>G120A </p>

<p>mutant showed no relocalization (Fig. S6C). In line with these 
results we also detected colocalization of the ATG12-ATG5-
ATG16L1 complex to GFP-LC3-positive endomembranes in 
ATG13 
¡/¡ cells upon drug treatment (Fig. S6C). Finally, GFP-
LC3 was found to localize to V-ATPase-positive compartments 
following drug treatment, consistent with the proposed role that 
the V-ATPase functions in noncanonical autophagy (Fig. S6D). 
Lysosomotropic drugs have the potential to damage lyso-
somes, which can then be targeted for engulfment by newly 
formed phagophores. 
28 To exclude the possibility that the 
observed LC3 response was due to autophagosomal targeting of 
damaged lysosomes, LGALS3/galectin-3 was used as a recently 
described marker of damaged endomembranes 
28 LGALS3 is a 
cytosolic protein that recognizes glycoproteins present on the 
extracellular side of the plasma membrane and lumenal side of 
intracellular vesicles. Damage of lysosome membranes allows 
LGALS3 to access lumenal glycoproteins. We monitored 
mCherry-LGALS3 and GFP-LC3 in autophagosome-deficient 
ATG13 
¡/¡ MCF10A cells. Using glycyl-L-phenylalanine 2-
naphthylamide (GPN) as a positive control for lysosome rup-
ture, 
29 we detected potent induction of LGALS3 puncta 
(Fig. S7A). However, none of the lysosomotropic drugs used in 
this study induced any obvious LGALS3 translocation. Indeed, 
the GFP-LC3-positive vacuoles formed upon drug treatment 
were LGALS3 negative (Fig. S7B). These data rule out a role for </p>

<p>Figure 1. Effects of lysosomotropic and ionophore drugs on lysosome pH using 
LysoTracker. MCF10A cells were labeled with LysoTracker Red for 2 h in the pres-
ence of absence of bafilomycin A 1 (Baf, 100 nM), monensin (Mon, 50 mM), nigericin 
(Nig, 10 mM), chloroquine (CQ, 100 mM), hydroxychloroquine (HCQ, 100 mM), 
NH 4 Cl (10 mM), betahistine (BH, 5 mM), procainamide (ProA, 5mM) or lidocaine 
hydrochloride (LH, 2.5 mM). (A) Quantification of LysoTracker fluorescence. Data 
are mean  § SD of 8 fields of view from 2 independent experiments. One-way 
ANOVA, P&lt;0.0001. AU, arbitrary units. (B) Representative inverted grayscale 
images of LysoTracker staining in cells. Bar: 20 mm for all images. </p>

<p> 
E. JACQUIN ET AL. </p>

<p>autophagosome targeting of damaged vesicles in the observed 
LC3 response to the tested drugs. 
Using multiple cell lines and genetic backgrounds, these data 
demonstrate that LC3 can be lipidated to endolysosomal mem-
branes upon treatment with a range of ionophores and lysoso-
motropic drugs, independently of the canonical autophagy 
pathway. Colocalization of LC3 and LAMP1 is not complete 
suggesting that these drugs may also induce LC3 lipidation to 
other intracellular membranes in addition to endolysosomes. 
Taken together, the genetic requirements, morphological data </p>

<p>and V-ATPase dependence of drug-induced LC3 lipidation 
demonstrate that these drugs are capable of activating a nonca-
nonical autophagy pathway and endolysosomal LC3 lipidation. </p>

<p>Topical application of local anesthetics induces 
noncanonical autophagy in vivo </p>

<p>To determine whether lysosomotropic drug-induced noncanoni-
cal autophagy occurs in vivo, human skin biopsies were exam-
ined from control patients and those that had received a topical </p>

<p>Figure 2. Lysosomotropic and ionophore dugs activate ATG13-independent, V-ATPase-dependent LC3 lipidation. Representative western blots for LC3 and GAPDH in (A) 
wild-type and (B) ATG13 
¡/¡ HEK293 cells treated with drugs at the indicated concentrations for 2 h. Ratios of lipidated LC3-II:nonlipidated LC3-I were quantified and 
graphed. (C) ATG13 
¡/¡ HEK293 cells were pretreated with bafilomycin A 1 (Baf, 100nM) for 20 min before drug treatments. Representative western blots for LC3 and 
GAPDH are shown. </p>

<p>AUTOPHAGY </p>

<p>
application of the local anesthetic EMLA before biopsy. EMLA 
cream is an anesthetic containing the active ingredients lidocaine 
and prilocaine, and has previously been reported to induce cellu-
lar vacuolation of subcutaneous keratinocytes and epithelial cells 
at the site of application. 
30,31 Using ATG13 
¡/¡ MCF10A cells, we 
confirmed that lidocaine can activate noncanonical autophagy by 
promoting GFP-LC3 recruitment to swollen LAMP1-positive 
vesicles (Fig. 5A). We next stained control and EMLA-treated 
skin biopsies for LC3 by immunofluorescence. In agreement with 
published work, we found the most intense LC3 staining within 
the stratum granulosum (SG) layer. 
32,33 In 5/5 control samples, 
LC3 staining appeared as a diffusely grainy pattern. However, in 
8/11 EMLA-treated samples LC3 localized to larger punctate </p>

<p>compartments often observed as ring-like LC3 structures 
(Fig. 5B), reminiscent of those seen in lidocaine-treated MCF10A 
cells. To attempt to determine the identity of these EMLA-
induced LC3-positive structures, we stained samples for CDSN 
(corneodesmosin), a marker for lamellar granules. Lamellar gran-
ules are acidic single-membrane lysosome-related organelles 
found in SG cells, 
34,35 and, as such, represent the type of com-
partment that can be targeted by noncanonical autophagy. Simi-
lar to LC3, EMLA treatment promoted a swelling of CDSN-
positive structures (Fig. 5C). By costaining samples for LC3 and 
CDSN, we observed LC3 staining on some enlarged CDSN-posi-
tive structures following EMLA treatment (Fig. 5D). Finally, 
using transmission electron microscopy, we detected enlarged </p>

<p>Figure 3. Activation of noncanonical autophagy and endolysosomal LC3 lipidation by lysosomotropic and ionophore drugs in atg13 
¡/¡ MEFs. Confocal images of endoge-
nous LC3 and LAMP1 immunostaining in atg13 
¡/¡ MEFs treated with drugs at the indicated concentrations for 1-2 h. Inserts show zoomed regions highlighting colocali-
zation of the LC3 and LAMP1 signal. Bar: 5 mm, for all images. </p>

<p> 
E. JACQUIN ET AL. </p>

<p>single-membrane compartments in EMLA-treated samples 
(Fig. 5E). Together these data support the idea that EMLA appli-
cation promotes LC3 lipidation to non-autophagosome mem-
branes, likely to represent lamellar granules in skin epidermal 
cells. These data are the first to propose that lysosomotropic 
drug-induced noncanonical autophagy and endolysosomal LC3 
lipidation can be induced in vivo. This raises important questions 
regarding the consequences following activation of this pathway 
in vivo, which need to be addressed in the future. </p>

<p>CCCP induces endolysosomal LC3 lipidation </p>

<p>Considering our data using inhibitors of canonical auto-
phagy flux, we next sought to test whether published </p>

<p>activators of canonical autophagy have any effect on the 
noncanonical pathway. CCCP is a proton uncoupler that 
acts as an ionophore for hydrogen. 
36 Treatment of cells 
with CCCP promotes mitochondrial dysfunction by dissi-
pating proton gradients between inner and outer mitochon-
drial membranes. The E3 ubiquitin ligase PARK2/parkin is 
then recruited and regulates the engulfment and degrada-
tion of damaged mitochondria through a selective autopha-
gic process termed mitophagy. 
37 Previously, LC3 lipidation 
observed following CCCP treatment has been attributed to 
ATG13-dependent autophagosome formation during 
mitophagy or bulk autophagy. 
38,39 However, in addition to 
eliminating proton gradients at mitochondria, CCCP will 
also dissipate proton gradients at lysosomes. 
40 In light of </p>

<p>Figure 4. Activation of noncanonical autophagy and endolysosomal LC3 lipidation by lysosomotropic and ionophore drugs in atg9 
¡/¡ MEFs. Confocal images of endoge-
nous LC3 and LAMP1 immunostaining in atg9 
¡/¡ MEFs treated with drugs at the indicated concentrations for 1-2 h. Inserts show zoomed regions highlighting colocaliza-
tion of the LC3 and LAMP1 signal. Bar: 5 mm, for all images. </p>

<p>AUTOPHAGY </p>

<p>
our results using the ionophores nigericin and monensin, 
we questioned whether CCCP could induce noncanonical 
autophagy and endolysosomal LC3 lipidation. We found 
that CCCP induced LC3 lipidation in a dose-dependent </p>

<p>manner in both wild-type and ATG13 
¡/¡ HEK293 cells, 
which could be inhibited by bafilomycin A 1 pretreatment 
(Fig. 6A and 6B). Entotic corpse vacuoles are single-mem-
brane acidic compartments formed following the live </p>

<p>Figure 5. Local anesthetic EMLA promotes noncanonical autophagy in vivo. (A) Confocal images of GFP-LC3 and endogenous LAMP1 immunostaining in ATG13 </p>

<p>¡/¡ </p>

<p>MCF10A cells treated with lidocaine (2.5 mM) for 4 h. Inserts show zoomed regions highlighting colocalization of the LC3 and LAMP1 signal. Bar: 5 mm. Confocal imaging 
of (B) LC3 and (C) CDSN immunostaining in formalin-fixed paraffin embedded skin biopsies from (i) control patients and (ii) patients treated with the local anesthetic 
EMLA. Bar: 10 mm. Zoomed regions of representative maximal intensity Z-projections of stacks are shown (iii, iv). Bar: 4 mm. Swollen LC3-and CDSN-positive compart-
ments (arrows) are observed in samples from patients treated with EMLA. (D) LC3 (green) and CDSN (white) and DAPI (blue) costaining of control and EMLA-treated skin 
biopsies. Colocalized signals (arrows) are observed in EMLA samples. Bar: 10 mm. (E) TEM images of an EMLA-treated biopsy. Arrows denote swollen compartments. N, 
nucleus. A cropped region is shown in the insert. </p>

<p> 
E. JACQUIN ET AL. </p>

<p>engulfment and killing of epithelial cells by the process 
entosis. These vacuoles represent the type of compartment 
that can be targeted by noncanonical autophagy. 
9,18 Using 
confocal microscopy we observed that CCCP promoted the 
robust recruitment of GFP-LC3 to LAMP1-positive entotic 
corpse vacuoles in wild-type and ATG13 
¡/¡ MCF10A cells, 
in a bafilomycin A 1 -sensitive manner (Fig. 6C and 6B and 
Fig. S4B). We also noted a strong colocalization of GFP-
LC3 with LAMP1-positive lysosomes upon CCCP treat-
ment, which was resistant to a PIK3C3/VPS34 inhibitor 
(IN-1) able to inhibit starvation-induced GFP-LC3 puncta 
(Fig. 6E). Taken together, the ATG13-and PIK3C3/VPS34-</p>

<p>independent lipidation of LC3 to non-autophagosome mem-
branes clearly demonstrates that CCCP can activate nonca-
nonical autophagy. CCCP did induce WIPI2 puncta in 
wild-type but not atg13 
¡/¡ MEFs suggesting some activation 
of canonical autophagy (Fig. 6F). Bafilomycin A 1 inhibited 
CCCP-induced LC3 lipidation (Fig. 6B and 6D) but not 
CCCP-mediated mitochondria depolarization and fragmen-
tation (Fig. 6G). Thus, CCCP's ability to activate noncanon-
ical autophagy is separate to its ability to promote 
mitochondria dysfunction. These data strengthen the con-
clusion that while CCCP does induce mitophagy, it is also a 
potent inducer of endolysosomal LC3 lipidation in parallel. </p>

<p>Figure 6. CCCP activates noncanonical autophagy. (A) Representative western blots of LC3 and GAPDH in wild-type and ATG13 
¡/¡ HEK293 cells treated with increasing 
concentrations of CCCP. (B) ATG13 
¡/¡ HEK293 cells were treated with Baf, CCCP or Baf C CCCP and lysates probed for LC3 and GAPDH. Ratios of lipidated LC3-II:nonlipi-
dated LC3-I were quantified below. (C) Confocal images of GFP-LC3 and LAMP1 immunostaining on entotic corpse vacuoles in MCF10A cells treated with CCCP (100 mM) 
for 1 h. Arrow indicates lipidated LC3 on vacuoles. Bar: 10 mm for all images. (D) Quantification of GFP-LC3 recruitment to LAMP1-positive entotic vacuoles in cells treated 
with Baf (100 nM), CCCP (50 mM) or Baf C CCCP; data are mean  § SEM from 3 independent experiments, P&lt;0.0003. (E) Confocal images of GFP-LC3 and LAMP1 immu-
nostaining in MCF10A cells starved with HBSS or treated with CCCP (100 mM) for 2 h C/¡ PIK3C3 inhibitor IN-1 (5 mM) pre-treatment for 1 h. Zoomed regions highlight 
colocalization of LC3 and LAMP1 signals. Bar: 5 mm for all images. (F) Confocal images of WIPI2 staining in wild-type and atg9 
¡/¡ MEFs C/¡ CCCP (100 mM) for 1 h. Bar: 
20 mm for all images. (G) Confocal images of MCF10A cells labeled with Mito-TMRE treated with Baf (100 nM), CCCP (50 mM) or Baf C CCCP). Bar: 20 mm for all images </p>

<p>AUTOPHAGY </p>

<p>
Amiodarone induces endolysosomal LC3 lipidation </p>

<p>Amiodarone is an FDA-approved antiarrhythmic drug used in 
the treatment of cardiac dysrhythmias. Amiodarone was identi-
fied via multiple microscopy-based screens as an inducer of 
GFP-LC3 puncta. 
6,41 Through its action as an L-type Ca </p>

<p>2C </p>

<p>channel antagonist, amiodarone can decrease intracellular cal-
cium levels, which inhibits the calcium-dependent cysteine pro-
teases called calpains. This in turn activates autophagy, 
potentially through an MTOR-independent pathway. 
42 How-
ever, amiodarone also has lysosomotropic properties, accumu-
lating in lysosomes and inducing their osmotic swelling. </p>

<p>43   Considering our new data, we investigated whether noncanoni-
cal autophagy participates in amiodarone-induced LC3 
lipidation. 
In line with previous reports, we find that amiodarone raised 
lysosome pH as detected by loss of LysoTracker Red staining in 
MCF10A cells (Fig. 7A). We also noted swelling of intracellular 
LAMP1-positive vacuoles. Using wild-type and ATG13 </p>

<p>¡/¡ </p>

<p>HEK293 cells we found that amiodarone could induce a dose-
dependent induction of LC3 lipidation in both cell lines by 
western blotting, which was inhibited by bafilomycin A 1 pre-
treatment. (Fig. 7A-C). By immunofluorescence staining of 
endogenous LC3 we found that amiodarone could promote the 
relocalization of LC3 to swollen LAMP1 compartments in 
autophagy-deficient atg13 
¡/¡ and atg9 
¡/¡ MEFs (Fig. 7D). 
Amiodarone-induced GFP-LC3 relocalization was not inhib-
ited by a PIK3C3/VPS34 inhibitor (Fig. 7E). These data provide 
clear and strong evidence that amiodarone can activate nonca-
nonical autophagy. However, as with CCCP, we do detect 
amiodarone-induced WIPI2 puncta in wild-type, but not in 
atg9 
¡/¡ MEFs, indicating that amiodarone induces both canon-
ical and noncanonical autophagy in parallel (Fig. 7F). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we report that a range of drugs with lysosomo-
tropic or ionophore properties activate a noncanonical auto-
phagy pathway, that directs LC3 lipidation to single-membrane 
endolysosomal compartments independently of the canonical 
autophagy pathway. Increased LC3 lipidation by these drugs 
has previously been attributed to inhibition of canonical auto-
phagic flux or promotion of autophagosome formation 
(Table S1). However, our data clearly shows that these drugs 
can also induce LC3 lipidation in the absence of ATG13 and 
ATG9 or PIK3C3/VPS34 activity, all of which are required for 
autophagosome formation. It is highly unlikely that the 
observed LC3 lipidation is a result of alternative routes of auto-
phagosome formation, such as BECN1/Beclin 1-or ULK1/2-
independent pathways, as these mechanisms still require some 
autophagy machinery not necessary for the described nonca-
nonical pathway. Instead our data indicate that LC3 is lipidated 
directly onto non-autophagosome membranes associated with 
the endolysosomal system. 
In this study, we provide the first evidence supporting lyso-
somotropic drug-mediated activation of noncanonical auto-
phagy in vivo. In human skin biopsy samples where the 
anesthetic cream EMLA containing lidocaine had been applied 
topically, we observed swollen LC3-positive vesicles in </p>

<p>epidermal cells of the stratum granulosum layer, which bear 
markers of lamellar granules, lysosome-like organelles in skin. 
While we cannot exclude a role for canonical autophagy in 
these human samples, the single-membrane, low pH nature of 
the lamellar granules represents the characteristic type of com-
partment targeted by noncanonical autophagy. Indeed EMLA 
has previously been shown to induce vacuolation of single-
membrane structures based on electron microscopy. </p>

<p>30   We also report that CCCP, commonly used to induce 
mitophagy, can activate noncanonical autophagy in parallel. 
Interestingly, one study reported CCCP-induced LC3 lipidation 
occurring in the absence of RB1CC1/FIP200, ATG13 and 
ATG14; however, the authors did not determine what this lipi-
dated LC3 represented. 
44 We now demonstrate that CCCP can 
promote LC3 lipidation to endolysosomal membranes 
completely independent from canonical autophagy. This is 
achieved at higher concentrations than those reported to 
induce mitophagy, but are still within levels commonly used in 
the study of autophagy. The requirement for higher concentra-
tions may reflect the differences in sensitivity between mito-
chondria and lysosomes to proton permeability. 
Amiodarone has been reported by several groups to be an 
activator of autophagosome formation. 
41-43,45,46 Amiodarone 
can promote autophagy via MTOR inhibition, possibly linked 
to its effect on lysosome function, 
42 and has also been proposed 
to activate an MTOR-independent autophagy pathway. As 
such it represents a drug of clinical interest where autophagy 
activation may be achieved, without further complicating 
effects of MTOR inhibition. For instance, induction of auto-
phagy by amiodarone has been implicated in enhancing sur-
vival in mice following hepatectomy, 
47 and supressing 
hepatocellular carcinoma. 
48 In our study we clearly show that 
amiodarone is capable of activating noncanonical autophagy 
and endolysosomal LC3 lipidation in parallel to its effects on 
autophagosome formation, a parallel activity that will be 
important to consider. 
We recently reported that osmotic imbalances within endo-
lysosomal compartments can activate noncanonical autophagy 
and endolysosomal LC3 lipidation in a V-ATPase-dependent 
manner. 
18 This osmotic mechanism has been proposed to 
underlie physiological examples of endolysosmal LC3 lipidation 
such as LC3-associated phagocytosis and entosis. Considering 
that all of the drugs tested in our study have previously been 
shown to induce an osmotically driven swelling of single-mem-
brane endolysosomal compartments, and our new data show 
that drug-induced LC3 lipidation is suppressed by inhibitors of 
the V-ATPase, we conclude that the same mechanism activat-
ing noncanonical autophagy is functional. 
The results presented here raise important questions regard-
ing the use and interpretation of LC3-based autophagy assays. 
Many genetic and pharmaceutical based high-throughput 
screens for autophagy modulators have been conducted with 
LC3 lipidation or puncta formation used as the readout. It 
should now be appreciated that LC3 is not a specific autopha-
gosome marker and can be lipidated to non-autophagosome 
membranes. While not applicable to all known autophagy 
modulators, our results show that many drugs used to modu-
late the canonical autophagy pathway, primarily with lysoso-
motropic or ionophore properties, can also act as potent </p>

<p> 
E. JACQUIN ET AL. </p>

<p>Figure 7. Amiodarone activates noncanonical autophagy. (A) Quantification of LysoTracker fluorescence intensity in MCF10A cells treated with amiodarone (Ami, 50 mM) 
for 2 h. Dashed line represents background fluorescence. Levels are mean C/¡ standard deviation. AU, arbitrary units. (B) Representative western blots of LC3 and GAPDH 
in wild-type and ATG13 
¡/¡ HEK293 cells treated with increasing concentrations of amiodarone. (C) ATG13 
¡/¡ HEK293 cells were treated with Baf (100 nM), amiodarone 
(Ami, 50 mM) or Baf C Ami and lysates probed for LC3 and GAPDH. Ratios of lipidated LC3-II:nonlipidated LC3-I were quantified below. (D) Confocal images of endoge-
nous LC3 and LAMP1 immunostaining in atg13 
¡/¡ and atg9 
¡/¡ MEFs treated with amiodarone (50 mM) for 2 h. Inserts show zoomed regions highlighting colocalization 
of LC3 and LAMP1 signals. Bar: 10 mm for all images. (E) Confocal images of GFP-LC3 and LAMP1 immunostaining in MCF10A cells starved with HBSS or treated with 
amiodarone (50 mM) for 2 h C/¡ PIK3C3 inhibitor IN-1 (5 mM) pre-treatment for 1 h. Zoomed regions highlight colocalization of LC3 and LAMP1 signals. Bar: 5 mm for 
all images. (F) Confocal images of WIPI2 staining in wild-type and atg9 
¡/¡ MEFs treated with C/¡ amiodarone (50 mM) for 2 h. Bar: 20 mm for all images. </p>

<p>AUTOPHAGY </p>

<p>
inducers of noncanonical autophagy and endolysosomal LC3 
lipidation. This finding is an important consideration in the 
design and interpretation of future autophagy screens. Related 
to this, tandem RFP-GFP-LC3 constructs are now commonly 
used to measure autophagosome flux, whereby an increased 
dual signal is assumed to reflect a block in autophagosome-
lysosome fusion. However, considering that LC3 associated 
with endolysosomal membranes will also retain both RFP and 
GFP signals, our findings on noncanonical autophagy further 
complicate the interpretation of such results. Therefore, we 
would recommend that in addition to assays measuring LC3 
lipidation, autophagy screens should include other markers 
associated with autophagosome formation, such as autophago-
some-associated phosphatidylinositol-3-phosphate effectors 
ZFYVE1/DFCP1 and WIPI2, to infer an effect on canonical 
autophagy induction. Similarly, measurement of autophago-
some receptors such as SQSTM1/p62 or protein aggregates 
would give an accompanying indication on the degradation 
capacity of the autophagy pathway. 
Our results highlight the need for further understanding of 
the functions and implications of noncanonical autophagy, 
which remain to be fully understood. LC3 lipidation to phago-
somes during LAP is thought to modulate the fusion of lyso-
somes with the phagosome and degradation of its cargo. 
However, the exact mechanisms underlying this event are not 
known. Similarly, how LC3 on phagosomes directs the cytokine 
response in macrophages and dendritic cells remains to be 
determined. LC3 present on autophagosomes and endosomes 
have recently been shown to modulate MAPK/ERK signaling, 
enabling these compartments to act as a signaling platform. </p>

<p>49,50   Whether noncanonical autophagy could generate similar endo-
lysosomal signaling hubs would be of great interest and possi-
bly inform on the efficacy and function of some autophagy-
modulating drugs that possess endolysosomal LC3 lipidation 
properties. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Antibodies and reagents </p>

<p>The following primary antibodies were used at the indicated 
dilutions: anti-LC3A/B (1:1000 for western blotting and 1:100 
for immunofluorescence; Cell Signaling Technology, 4108), 
anti-LC3A (1:100 for immunohistofluorescence; Abgent, 
1805a), anti-ATG12 (1:100; Cell Signaling Technology, 2010), 
anti-ATG13 (1:1000; Cell Signaling Technology, 6940), anti-
ATG16L1 (1:1000; Cell Signaling Technology, 8089), anti-
human LAMP1 and anti-mouse LAMP1 (1:100; Becton Dickin-
son, 555798 and 553792), anti-WIPI2 (1:100; Bio-Rad, 
MCA5780GA), anti-CDSN/corneodesmosin (R&amp;D Systems, 
AF5725), anti-GAPDH (1:2000; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, sc-
25778), and anti-ATP6V0D1 (1:50; ABCAM, ab56441). The 
following inhibitors and reagents were used: Amiodarone 
hydrochloride (Sigma, A8423), bafilomycin A 1 (Tocris Bio-
sciences, 1334), betahistine dihydrochloride (Sigma, B4638), 
chloroquine (Sigma, C6628), CCCP (Sigma, C2759), HBSS 
(Gibco, 14025-092), hydroxychloroquine (Sigma, H0915), lido-
caine (Sigma, L7757), lidocaine hydrochloride monohydrate 
(Sigma, L5647), monensin (Sigma, M5273), NH 4 Cl (Sigma, </p>

<p>213330), nigericin (Sigma, N7143), PP242 (Tocris, 4257), pro-
cainamide hydrochloride (Sigma, P9391). Mito-TMRE (abcam, 
113852), PIK3C3/VPS34 inhibitor (IN-1) was kindly provided 
by Dr I. Ganley, University of Dundee. </p>

<p>Cell culture and transfection </p>

<p>MCF10A cells stably expressing GFP-LC3 were cultured in 
DMEM/F12 (Gibco, 11320-033) supplemented with 5% horse 
serum (Gibco, 16050-122), 20 ng/mL EGF (Peprotech, AF-
100-15), 10 mg/mL insulin (Sigma, I9278), 0.5 mg/mL hydro-
cortisone (Sigma, H0888), 100 ng/mL cholera toxin (Sigma, 
C8052) and 100 U/mL penicillin and 100 mg/mL streptomycin 
(Gibco, 15140-122). MEF cell lines were maintained in DMEM 
(Gibco, 41966029) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum 
(Sigma, F9665) and 100 U/mL penicillin and 100 mg/mL strep-
tomycin. Wild type, atg13 
¡/¡ and atg9 
¡/¡ MEFs and HEK293 
cells stably expressing GFP-LC3 (kindly provided by N. Ktista-
kis, Babraham Institute) were cultured in complete DMEM 
supplemented with 0.4 mg/mL G418 (Melford Laboratories, 
G0175). Transfections of HEK293 GFP-LC3 cells were per-
formed using the Lipofectamine 
Ò 2000 Transfection Reagent 
(Invitrogen, 11668-019). Transfections of MCF10A GFP-LC3 
cells were performed using a Nucleofector II instrument 
(Lonza) and Lonza nucleofection kit V (Lonza, VCA-1003) fol-
lowing the manufacturer's guidelines. Electroporated cells were 
selected with 2.5 mg/mL puromycin (Sigma, P8833). The 
mCherry-LGALS3 expression plasmid was kindly provided by 
Dr. Felix Randow (MRC-LMB, Cambridge, UK). The pBabe. 
puro-DU-GFP GABARAPL2 (40072) expression plasmids were 
purchased from MRC-PPU Reagents. The pBabe.puro-GFP-
LC3 
G120A expression plasmid was kindly provided by Dr. Noor 
Gammoh, University of Edinburgh, UK. </p>

<p>CRISPR/Cas9-mediated ATG13 and ATG16L1 knockout </p>

<p>To generate ATG13 knockout (KO) in HEK293 GFP-LC3 cells, 
CRISPR guide RNA (gRNA) forward and reverse sequences 
(Table S2) with overhangs for ligation into AflII restriction site 
were annealed and the resulting 100 base pair double-strand 
DNA fragment was cloned into the gRNA Cloning Vector 
(Addgene, 41824; deposited by Dr George Church) linearized 
with AflII restriction enzyme (NEB, R0520) using the Gibson 
Assembly 
Ò Master Mix (NEB, E2611). The recombinant 
ATG13 gRNA vector was co-transfected with a Cas9 expression 
vector (Addgene, 43861; deposited by Dr Keith Joung) in 
HEK293 GFP-LC3 cells. Single cell clones were generated fol-
lowing limiting dilution in 96-well plates. 
To generate ATG13 and ATG16L1 KO in MCF10A GFP-
LC3 cells, gRNA sequences with overhangs for containing a 
BpiI site were annealed and cloned into the pSpCas9(BB)-2A-
GFP (Addgene, 48138; deposited by Dr Feng Zhang) digested 
with the BpiI restriction enzyme (Thermo Scientific, ER1011). 
The recombinant plasmid was electroporated in MCF10A 
GFP-LC3 cells along with a pBABE-puro construct (Addgene, 
1764; deposited by Dr Hartmut Land). Cells were selected with 
2.5 mg/ml puromycin (Sigma, P8833) for 48 h and single cells 
seeded into each well of 96-well plates. </p>

<p> 
E. JACQUIN ET AL. </p>

<p>After clonal expansion, KO clones were selected based on 
the absence of ATG13 or ATG16L1 protein detection by west-
ern blot. The rescue of a canonical autophagy response after 
MTOR inhibition and autophagic flux inhibition was verified 
in selected cells following transient transfection of an ATG13 
expression vector (pmCherry-C1-ATG13 plasmid kindly pro-
vided by N. Ktistakis, Babraham Institute, UK). </p>

<p>Lysosomal pH measurement </p>

<p>To assess intracellular pH, cells were grown on 35-mm glass 
bottom dishes (MatTek, P35G-1.5-
14 C) and incubated in cul-
ture medium containing 67 nM LysoTracker Red DND-99 
(Life Technologies, L-7528) for 2 h in the absence or presence 
of lysosomotropic and ionophore drugs. Confocal live-cell 
imaging was performed with the Confocal Zeiss LSM 780 (Carl 
Zeiss Ltd) equipped with a 40x oil immersion 1.40 numerical 
aperture (NA) objective and an incubation chamber set at 37 
C 
and 5% CO 2 . Image acquisition was performed with Zen soft-
ware (Carl Zeiss Ltd). All image processing (brightness and 
contrast) was performed on all pixels in each image and intra-
cellular fluorescence intensity was measured using ImageJ soft-
ware (NIH). </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence </p>

<p>For fluorescence immunocytology, cells were grown on glass 
coverslips, incubated as described in the figure legends, fixed in 
ice-cold methanol at ¡20 
C for 5 min and washed in phos-
phate-buffered saline (PBS; Sigma, D8537). Samples were 
blocked in 5% bovine serum albumin (BSA; Sigma, A7906) in 
PBS for 1 h at room temperature (RT) before overnight incuba-
tion with primary antibodies in blocking buffer at 4 
C. Follow-
ing PBS washes samples were incubated with Alexa Fluor 488/ 
568 goat anti-rabbit (H </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>L) or anti-mouse (H </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>L) secondary 
antibodies (1:500; Invitrogen, A-11034 and A-11031) for 1 h at 
RT. DNA was stained with DAPI (1 mg/mL; Sigma, D8417) 
before mounting coverslips with ProLong 
Ò Gold antifade 
mounting medium (Life Technologies, P36930). Image acquisi-
tion was performed with the Confocal Zeiss LSM 780 micro-
scope (Carl Zeiss Ltd) equipped with a 40x oil immersion 1.40 
numerical aperture (NA) objective using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Zen</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Carl Zeiss Ltd</rs>). Images used in figures are representative of at least 3 
independent repeats. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence of skin biopsies </p>

<p>For fluorescence immunohistology, formalin-fixed paraffin 
embedded skin biopsy sections were dewaxed in xylene and 
rehydrated through descending ethanol concentrations. Anti-
gen retrieval was performed by heating the sections at 100 
C in 
citrate-based buffer, pH 6 (Vector laboratories, H-3300) for 
20 min. Samples were then blocked in TBS-T (20 mM Tris, 
140 mM NaCl, pH 7.6, 1% Tween 20 [Sigma, T9416]) supple-
mented with 5% BSA and 0.1 M glycine for 45 min at RT before 
overnight staining in primary antibodies diluted in blocking 
buffer at 4 
C. Following washes in TBS-T, samples were incu-
bated with Alexa Fluor 488 donkey anti-rabbit IgG (H </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>L) 
and/or TRITC donkey anti-sheep IgG (H 
C L) (Jackson </p>

<p>ImmunoResearch, 711-545-152 and 713-025-147, respec-
tively) secondary antibodies (1:400 in blocking buffer) for 
45 min at RT. DNA was stained with DAPI (1 mg/mL) before 
mounting coverslips with ProLong 
Ò Gold antifade mounting 
medium. Confocal imaging of fixed samples was performed as 
above. All image processing (brightness and contrast) was per-
formed on all pixels in each image. </p>

<p>TEM of skin biopsies </p>

<p>The skin biopsy sample was immersed in a fixative solution of 
4% paraformaldehyde and 1% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M phos-
phate buffer (pH 7.2) for 48 h at 4 
C. The skin biopsy slices 
were then washed in PBS, postfixed by incubation for 1 h with 
2% osmium tetroxide and dehydrated in a graded series of eth-
anol solutions. Samples were embedded in Epon resin (Electron 
Microscopy Sciences, 14120), which was allowed to polymerize 
for 48 h at 60 
C. Ultrathin sections were cut, stained with 2.5% 
uranyl acetate, 1% lead citrate, and deposited on EM grids for 
examination under a JEOL 1011 transmission electron micro-
scope (TEM). </p>

<p>Western blotting </p>

<p>Cells were scraped into ice-cold RIPA buffer (150 mM NaCl, 
50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 1 mM EDTA, 1% Triton X-100 
(Sigma, T8787), 0.1% SDS (Sigma, L3771), 0.5% sodium deoxy-
cholate (Sigma, D6750) and lysed on ice for 10 min. Lysates 
were centrifuged for 10 min at 10,000 g at 4 
C. Supernatants 
were then separated on 15% or 10% polyacrylamide SDS-
PAGE gels and transferred to polyvinylidene difluoride mem-
branes. Membranes were blocked in TBS-T supplemented with 
5% BSA for 1 h at room temperature and incubated overnight 
at 4 
C with primary antibodies diluted in blocking buffer. They 
were then incubated with a horseradish peroxidase-conjugated 
secondary antibody (Cell Signaling Technology, 7074S) and 
proteins were detected using enhanced chemiluminescence 
(GE Healthcare Life Sciences, RPN2209). Densitometry analy-
sis was performed using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software. </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>Indicated P values were obtained using the Student t test or 
one-way ANOVA using <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Graphpad</rs> <rs id="software-2" type="software">Prism</rs> software. </p>

<p>Abbreviations </p>

<p>ATG 
autophagy-related 
Baf 
bafilomycin A 1 
BH 
betahistine 
CCCP 
carbonyl cyanide m-chlorophenyl 
hydrazone 
CDSN 
corneodesmosin 
CRISPR 
clustered regularly interspaced short pal-
indromic repeats 
CQ 
chloroquine 
EMLA 
eutectic mixture of local anesthetics 
GFP 
green fluorescent protein 
GPN 
glycyl-L-phenylalanine 2-naphthylamide </p>

<p>AUTOPHAGY </p>

<p>
HCQ </p>

<p>hydroxychloroquine 
LAMP1 
lysosomal-associated membrane protein 
1 
LAP 
LC3-associated phagocytosis 
LD 
lidocaine 
MAP1LC3/LC3 
microtubule-associated protein 1 light 
chain 3 
MEF 
mouse embryonic fibroblast 
Mon 
monensin 
LGALS3/galectin-3 lectin, galactose, soluble 3 
MTOR 
mechanistic target of rapamycin 
Nig 
nigericin 
ProA 
procainamide 
RB1CC1 
RB1-inducible coiled-coil 1 
V-ATPase 
vacuolar-type H </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>-translocating ATPase 
WIPI2 
WD repeat domain, phosphoinositide 
interacting 2 </p>

<p>Disclosure of potential conflicts of interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest were disclosed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We would like to thank the members of the Florey laboratory for their 
comments on the manuscript and the imaging and genome targeting facili-
ties at the Babraham Institute for their assistance. We thank Dr Nicholas 
Ktiskatis for sharing cell lines, antibodies and plasmids and Dr Ian Ganley 
for the VPS34 inhibitor IN-1. Electron Microscopy data were obtained 
with the technical assistance of C. Hayot and J. Rousseau at the IBiSA Elec-
tron Microscopy Facility of University François Rabelais of Tours. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by a Cancer Research UK fellowship C47718/ 
A16337. </p>



<p> 
E. JACQUIN ET AL. </p>



<p>AUTOPHAGY </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>