<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5065646" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Corynebacterium phoceense strain MC1 (= CSUR P1905 = DSM 100570) is a novel Corynebacterium species isolated from the urine of a kidney </p>

<p>transplant recipient as a part of a culturomics study. Corynebacterium phoceense is a Gram-positive, sporogenous, strictly aerobic, and </p>

<p>nonmotile coccobacillus. Here we describe strain MC1 and provide its complete annotated genome sequence according to the </p>

<p>taxonogenomics concept. Its genome is 2 793 568 bp long and contains 2575 protein-coding genes and 67 RNA genes, including eight </p>

<p>rRNA genes. </p>

<p>The genus Corynebacterium was described in 1896 by Lehmann 
and Neumann and belongs to the Actinobacteria class [1]. 
Currently it consists of a heterogeneous group of Gram-positive, 
non-spore-forming, rod-shaped bacteria with a high DNA G+C 
content [2]. In the genus Corynebacterium many species are 
involved in human and animal diseases, whereas many others are 
normal flora on skin and mucous membranes [3-5]. Cor-
ynebacteria are found in different environments such as water, 
soil, plants and human samples [6-10]. Among corynebacteria, 
the most significant human pathogen is Corynebacterium diph-
theriae, which causes diphtheria worldwide [11]. However, most 
corynebacteria are opportunistic pathogens [6]. Bacteria found in 
urine are occasionally associated with urinary infection [12,13]. </p>

<p>Currently bacterial classification is focused on a polyphasic 
approach with phenotypic and genotypic characteristics such as 
DNA-DNA hybridization, G+C content and 16S rRNA 
sequence similarity [14-16]. This classification system has its 
limitations, such as the high cost of the DNA-DNA hybridiza-
tion technique and its low reproducibility [14,17]. A new bac-
terial description concept was developed in our laboratory 
[18-22] with the recent development of genome sequencing 
technology [23]. This concept, taxonogenomics [24], is a 
combination of proteomic description and matrix-assisted laser 
desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry 
(MALDI-TOF MS) profile [25] associated with a phenotypic 
description and the sequencing, annotation and comparison of 
the complete genome of the new bacteria species [26]. 
Here we describe Corynebacterium phoceense sp. nov., strain 
MC1 (= CSUR P1905 = DSM 100570), according the tax-
onogenomics concept. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Organism information 
Corynebacterium phoceense was isolated from culture of a 
midstream urine specimen from a 25-year-old kidney transplant </p>

<p>New Microbe and New Infect 2016; 14: 73-82 
© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/) 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.nmni.2016.09.001 </p>

<p>recipient from Comoros. He underwent transplantation to 
treat faecal and segmental glomerulosclerosis in Marseille, 
France. A urine sample was collected 2 years after his kidney 
transplantation without clinical signs of urinary tract infection. 
The patient did not receive antibiotics at the time of urine 
collection. Informed consent was obtained from the patient, 
and the study was approved by the Institut Fédératif de 
Recherche 48, Faculty of Medicine, Marseille, France, under 
agreement 09-022. </p>

<p>Strain identification by MALDI-TOF MS and 16S rRNA 
sequencing 
Among the 18 culture conditions previously selected by cul-
turomics [27], strain MC1 grew on sheep's blood-enriched 
Colombia agar (bioMérieux, Marcy l'Etoile, France). The col-
onies were obtained by spreading samples on a solid medium. 
They were then purified by subculture and identified by 
MALDI-TOF MS [28,29]. Colonies were deposited in duplicate 
on a MTP 96 MALDI-TOF MS target plate (Bruker Daltonics, 
Leipzig, Germany), which was analysed with a Microflex spec-
trometer (Bruker). The 12 spectra obtained were matched 
against the references of the 7567 bacteria contained in the 
database by standard pattern matching (with default parameter 
settings), with <rs id="software-1" type="software">MALDI BioTyper</rs> database software <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">2.0</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">bruker</rs>). An identification score over 1.9 with a validated 
species allows identification at the species level, and a score 
under 1.7 does not enable any identification. When identifica-
tion by MALDI-TOF MS failed, the 16S rRNA was sequenced 
[30]. Stackebrandt and Ebers [31] suggest similarity levels of 
98.7% with the 16S rRNA sequence as a threshold to define a 
new species without performing DNA-DNA hybridization. </p>

<p>Growth conditions 
To establish our strain's optimal growth conditions, different 
temperatures (25, 28, 37, 45 and 56°C) and atmospheres </p>

<p>(aerobic, microaerophilic and anaerobic) were tested. GENbag 
anaer and GENbag microaer systems (bioMérieux) were used 
respectively to test anaerobic and microaerophilic growth. 
Aerobic growth was carried out with and without 5% CO 2 . </p>

<p>Morphologic, biochemical and antibiotic susceptibility 
testing 
Gram staining, motility, catalase, oxidase and sporulation were 
tested as previously described [27]. To perform a biochemical 
description, according to the manufacturer's instructions, we 
use API Coryne (bioMérieux) to identify coryneiforms, API 
ZYM (bioMérieux) to search enzymatic activities and API 50CH 
(bioMérieux) to estimate capacity to ferment different carbo-
hydrates. Cellular fatty acid methyl ester (FAME) analysis was 
performed by gas chromatography/mass spectrometry (GC/ 
MS). Two samples were prepared with approximately 60 mg of 
bacterial biomass per tube collected from several culture plates. 
FAMEs were prepared as previously described (http://www. 
midi-inc.com/pdf/MIS_Technote_101.pdf), and GC/MS analyses 
were carried out as previously described [32]. Briefly, FAMEs 
were separated using an Elite 5-MS column and monitored by 
mass spectrometry (Clarus 500-SQ 8 S; Perkin Elmer, Cour-
taboeuf, France). A spectral database search was performed 
using MS Search 2.0 operated with the Standard Reference 
Database 1A (NIST, Gaithersburg, MD, USA) and the FAMEs 
mass spectral database (Wiley, Chichester, UK). 
Antibiotic susceptibility testing was performed using the disk 
diffusion method according to the European Committee on 
Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing (EUCAST) 2015 recom-
mendations (http://www.eucast.org/). Corynebacterium pho-
ceense resistance and susceptibility are estimated with 22 
antibiotic treatments (vancomycin 30 μg, rifampicin 30 μg, 
doxycycline 30 IU, erythromycin 15 IU, amoxicillin 25 μg, 
nitrofurantoin 300 μg, gentamicin 15 μg, ciprofloxacin 5 μg, 
ceftriaxone 30 μg, amoxicillin 20 μg + clavulanic acid 10 μg, 
penicillin G 10 μg, gentamicin 500 μg, trimethoprim 1.25 
μg + sulfamethoxazole 23.75 μg, oxacillin 5 μg, imipenem 10 μg, </p>

<p>tobramycin 10 g, metronidazole 4 μg, amikacin 30 μg, linezolid 
30 μg, clindamycin 15 μg, daptomycin in stripe 0.016-256 μg 
(bioMérieux) and chloramphenicol 5 mg, (Sigma-Aldrich, St. 
Louis, MO, USA)). The bacterial suspension (0.5 McFarland 
standard) is made in 2 mL NaCl 0.85% medium. Petri dishes 
with Mueller-Hinton + 5% sheep's blood (Becton Dickinson, 
San Diego, CA, USA) are seeded by swabbing with bacteria 
suspension. Different antibiotic dishes (SirScan) are dispensed 
on petri dishes. Electron microscopy figure was obtained by 
performing a negative staining of strain MC1. Detection 
Formvar-coated grids were deposited on a 40 μL bacterial 
suspension drop, then incubated at 37°C for 30 minutes and on 
ammonium molybdate 1% for 10 seconds. The dried grids on </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Classification and general features of </p>

<p>Corynebacterium phoceense strain MC1 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>Property 
Term </p>

<p>Current classification 
Domain: Bacteria 
Phylum: Actinobacteria 
Class: Actinobacteria 
Order: Actinomycetales 
Family: Corynebacteriaceae 
Genus: Corynebacterium 
Species: Corynebacterium phoceense 
Type strain: MC1 
Gram stain 
Positive 
Cell shape 
Rod 
Motility 
Nonmotile 
Sporulation 
Non-spore forming 
Temperature range 
Mesophilic 
Optimum temperature 
37°C </p>



<p>New Microbes and New Infections, Volume 14 Number C, November 2016 </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 14, 73-82 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>blotted paper were observed with a Tecnai G20 transmission 
electron microscope (FEI Company, Limeil-Brevannes, France). </p>

<p>Growth conditions and genomic DNA preparation 
Corynebacterium phoceense strain MC1 (= CSUR P1905 = DSM 
100570) was grown on 5% sheep's blood-enriched Columbia </p>

<p>agar (bioMérieux) at 37°C in aerobic atmosphere. Bacteria 
grown on three petri dishes were collected and resuspended in 
4 × 100 μL of Tris-EDTA (TE) buffer. Then 200 μL of this 
suspension was diluted in 1 mL TE buffer for lysis treatment 
that included a 30-minute incubation with 2.5 μg/μL lysozyme 
at 37°C, followed by an overnight incubation with 20 μg/μL </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Phylogenetic trees highlighting position of Corynebacterium phoceense strain MC1 (=CSUR P1905 = DSM 100570) relative to other strains </p>

<p>within genus Corynebacterium. Sequences of 16S rRNA gene (A) and rpoB genes (B) were aligned by CLUSTALW. Scale bar represents 1 and 2% </p>

<p>nucleotide sequence divergence for (A) and (B) respectively. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>2500 
Intens. [a.u.] </p>

<p>2000 
4000 
6000 
8000 
10000 
12000 
14000 
16000 
18000 
m/z </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Reference mass spectrum from Corynebacterium phoceense strain MC1. Spectra from 12 individual colonies were compared and reference </p>

<p>spectrum was generated. </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>Cresci et al. Corynebacterium phoceense sp. nov. </p>



<p>© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 14, 73-82 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>proteinase K at 37°C. Extracted DNA was then purified using 
three successive phenol-chloroform extractions and ethanol 
precipitations at −20°C overnight. After centrifugation, the 
DNA was resuspended in 160 μL TE buffer. </p>

<p>Genome sequencing and assembly 
Genomic DNA (gDNA) of Corynebacterium phoceense was 
sequenced on the MiSeq Technology (Illumina, San Diego, CA, 
USA) with the mate pair strategy. The gDNA was barcoded in 
order to be mixed with nine other projects with the Nextera 
Mate Pair sample prep kit (Illumina). 
gDNA was quantified by a Qubit assay with the high sensi-
tivity kit (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA) to 59.1 ng/μL. </p>

<p>The mate pair library was prepared with 1.5 μg of genomic 
DNA using the Nextera mate pair Illumina guide. The genomic 
DNA sample was simultaneously fragmented and tagged with a 
mate pair junction adapter. The fragmentation pattern was 
validated on an Agilent 2100 BioAnalyzer (Agilent Technolo-
gies, Santa Clara, CA, USA) with a DNA 7500 lab chip. The 
DNA fragments ranged in size from 1.5 to 11 kb, with an </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Gel view comparing Corynebacterium phoceense strain MC1 (= CSUR P1905 = DSM 100570) to other species within Corynebacteriaceae family. </p>

<p>Gel view displays raw spectra of loaded spectrum files arranged in pseudo-gel-like look. x-axis records m/z value. Left y-axis displays running spectrum </p>

<p>number originating from subsequent spectra loading. Peak intensity is expressed by greyscale scheme code. Colour bar and right y-axis indicate relation </p>

<p>between colour peak displayed and peak intensity in arbitrary units. Displayed species are indicated at left. </p>

<p>FIG. 4. Gram staining of Corynebacterium phoceense strain MC1. </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Transmission electron microscopy of Corynebacterium pho-</p>

<p>ceense strain MC1 
T with Morgani 268D (Philips, Amsterdam, the </p>

<p>Netherlands) at operating voltage of 60 kV. Scale bar = 500 nm. </p>



<p>New Microbes and New Infections, Volume 14 Number C, November 2016 </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 14, 73-82 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>optimal size at 7.364 kb. No size selection was performed, and 
600 ng of tagmented fragments were circularized. The circu-
larized DNA was mechanically sheared to small fragments with 
an optimal at 589 bp on the Covaris S2 device in T6 tubes 
(Covaris, Woburn, MA, USA). The library profile was visualized 
on a High Sensitivity Bioanalyzer LabChip (Agilent Technolo-
gies), and the final concentration library was measured at 
25.29 nmol/L. 
The libraries were normalized at 2 nM and pooled. After a 
denaturation step and dilution at 15 pM, the pool of libraries 
was loaded onto the reagent cartridge and then onto the in-
strument along with the flow cell. Automated cluster genera-
tion and sequencing runs were performed in a single 39-hour 
run in a 2 × 151 bp read length. 
Total information of 0.7 Gb was obtained from a 129K/mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>cluster density with a cluster passing quality control filters of 
80.3% (2 435 000 passing filter paired reads). Within this run, </p>

<p>the index representation for Corynebacterium phoceense was 
determined to 11.16%. The 271 698 paired reads were trim-
med, then assembled in 14 scaffolds. </p>

<p>Genome annotation and comparison 
Genome annotation and comparison open reading frames 
(ORFs) were predicted using Prodigal [33] with default pa-
rameters, but the predicted ORFs were excluded if they 
spanned a sequencing gap region (contains N). The predicted 
bacterial protein sequences were searched against the Clusters 
of Orthologous Groups (COGs) database using BLASTP (E 
value 1e-03, coverage 70%, identity percentage 30%). If no hit 
was found, it searched against the NR database using BLASTP 
with an E value of 1e-03 coverage 70% and identity percentage 
of 30%. If sequence lengths were smaller than 80 amino acids, 
we used an E value of 1e-05. The tRNAScanSE tool [34] was 
used to find tRNA genes, whereas rRNAs were found using 
RNAmmer [35]. Lipoprotein signal peptides and the number of 
transmembrane helices were predicted using Phobius [36]. 
ORFans were identified if all the performed BLASTP proced-
ures did not give positive results (E value smaller than 1e-03 for 
ORFs with sequence size higher than 80 aa or E value smaller 
than 1e-05 for ORFs with a sequence length smaller than 80 aa). 
Such parameter thresholds have already been used in previous 
work to define ORFans. 
Genomes were automatically retrieved from the 16s RNA 
tree using <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Xegen</rs>'s <rs id="software-2" type="software">PhyloPattern</rs> software [37]. For each 
selected genome, complete genome sequence, proteome and </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Cellular fatty acid composition (%) </p>

<p>Fatty acid 
Name 
Mean relative % </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>18:1n9 
9-Octadecenoic acid 
51.1 ± 0.5 
16:0 
Hexadecanoic acid 
46.0 ± 0.3 
18:0 
Octadecanoic acid 
2.1 ± 0.2 
15:0 
Pentadecanoic acid 
TR 
14:0 
Tetradecanoic acid 
TR 
18:2n6 
9,12-Octadecadienoic acid 
TR 
16:1n7 
9-Hexadecenoic acid 
TR 
17:0 
Heptadecanoic acid 
TR 
16:1n5 
11-Hexadecenoic acid 
TR </p>

<p>a Mean peak area percentage; TR = trace amounts &lt;1%. </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Differential characteristics of Corynebacterium phoceense strain MC1 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>, Corynebacterium freiburgense strain 1045 
T , </p>

<p>Corynebacterium mastitidis strain CECT 4843 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>, Corynebacterium terpenotabidum strain Y-1 I </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>, Corynebacterium lactis strain RW2-</p>

<p>5 
T , Corynebacterium aurimucosum strain IMMIB D-1488 
T and Corynebacterium mustelae strain 3105 
T [41-46] </p>

<p>Property 
C. phoceense 
C. freiburgense 
C. mastitidis 
C. terpenotabidum 
C. lactis 
C. aurimucosum 
C. mustelae </p>

<p>Cell diameter (μm) 
0.5 
0.5 
0.5 
0.7 
0.6 
0.5 
0.5 
Oxygen requirement 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
Gram stain 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
Salt requirement 
− 
− 
− 
− 
− 
− 
− 
Motility 
− 
− 
− 
− 
− 
− 
− 
Endospore formation 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
− 
− 
− 
Production of: 
Alkaline phosphatase </p>

<p>+ 
− 
+ 
N A 
+ 
+ 
− </p>

<p>Catalase 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
Oxidase 
− 
NA 
− 
− 
− 
NA 
− 
Nitrate reductase 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
NA 
− 
− 
Urease 
− 
− 
v 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
β-Galactosidase 
− 
+ 
− 
NA 
− 
− 
− 
N-acetyl-glucosamine 
− 
− 
− 
+ 
− 
− 
+ 
Ribose 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
+ 
− 
+ 
Pyrazinamidase 
+ 
− 
+ 
N A 
+ 
+ 
+ 
Pyrrolidonyl arylamidase 
+ 
− 
− 
NA 
− 
− 
− 
Mannose 
+ 
+ 
NA 
+ 
+ 
− 
+ 
Mannitol 
− 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
− 
− 
Sucrose 
− 
+ 
− 
− 
NA 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>D-Glucose </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
− 
− 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>D-Fructose </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
NA 
− 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>D-Maltose </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>D-Lactose </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
− 
− 
Habitat 
Human 
Human 
Sheep's milk 
Soil 
Cow's milk 
Human 
Human </p>

<p>+, positive result; −, negative result; NA, data not available. </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>Cresci et al. Corynebacterium phoceense sp. nov. </p>



<p>© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 14, 73-82 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>ORFeome genome sequence were retrieved from the National 
Center for Biotechnology Information FTP site. All proteomes 
were analysed with proteinOrtho [38]. Then for each couple of 
genomes a similarity score was computed. This score is the 
mean value of nucleotide similarity between all orthologue 
couples between the two genomes studied (AGIOS) [26]. 
The entire proteome was annotated to define the distribution 
of functional classes of predicted genes according to the clusters </p>

<p>of orthologous protein groups (using the same method as for the 
genome annotation). To evaluate the genomic similarity among 
the compared strains, we determined two parameters: digital 
DNA-DNA hybridization, which exhibits a high correlation with 
DNA-DNA hybridization (DDH) [39,40], and AGIOS [26], 
which was designed to be independent from DDH. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Strain identification and phylogenetic analyses 
Strain MC1 (Table 1) was first isolated in February 2015 by 
spreading a urine sample on 5% sheep's blood-enriched 
Colombia agar (bioMérieux) in an aerobic atmosphere at 37°C 
after 48 hours of incubation. 
Using MALDI-TOF MS for identification, no significant score 
was obtained for strain MC1, suggesting that this isolate's spec-
trum did not match any spectra in our MALDI-TOF MS database. 
The nucleotide sequences of the 16S rRNA and the rpoB genes of 
strain MC1 (GenBank accession nos. LN849777 and LN849778 
respectively) showed 96.3% similarity with Corynebacterium sim-
ulans, the phylogenetically closest species with a validly published 
name (Fig. 1), therefore defining it as a new species within the </p>

<p>TABLE 4. Nucleotide content and gene count levels of </p>

<p>genome </p>

<p>Attribute </p>

<p>Genome (total) </p>

<p>Value 
% of total </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Size (bp) 
2 793 868 
100.0 
G+C content (bp) 
1 753 790 
63.2 
Coding region (bp) 
2 265 533 
81.1 
Total of genes 
2575 
100.0 
RNA genes 
67 
2.6 
Protein-coding genes 
2508 
100.0 
Protein with function prediction 
1804 
71.9 
Protein assigned to COGs 
1511 
60.2 
Genes with peptid signals 
313 
12.4 
Genes with transmembrane helices 
612 
24.4 </p>

<p>COGs, Clusters of Orthologous Groups database. 
a Total is based on either size of genome in base pairs or total number of protein 
coding genes in annotated genome. </p>

<p>FIG. 6. Graphical circular map of chromosome. From outside to centre: genes on forward strain coloured by COGs categories (only gene assigned to </p>

<p>COGs), RNA genes (tRNAs green, rRNAs red), GC content and GC skew. </p>

<p>78 </p>

<p>New Microbes and New Infections, Volume 14 Number C, November 2016 </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 14, 73-82 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>genus Corynebacterium. C. phoceense spectra (Fig. 2) were incre-
mented in our database. The reference spectrum for C. phoceense 
was then compared to the spectra of phylogenetically close spe-
cies within the genus Corynebacterium, and the differences were 
exhibited in a gel view photo (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Phenotypic description 
Growth was observed from 25 to 56°C on 5% sheep's 
blood-enriched Columbia agar (bioMérieux), with optimal 
growth at 37°C in aerobic conditions after 48 hours of 
incubation. 
Weak cell growth was observed under microaerophilic and 
anaerobic conditions. The motility test was negative, and after 
thermal shock, we observed bacterial growth, which means </p>

<p>Corynebacterium phoceense is sporogenous. Cells were Gram-
positive coccobacillus (Fig. 4). On Columbian blood agar, col-
onies are circular with entire margin, up to 1.0 mm in diameter 
after 48 hours' growth at 37°C. Under electron microscopy, cells 
had a mean diameter of 0.5 μm and a length of 3 μm (Fig. 5). 
The major fatty acids were 9-octadecenoic acid (51%) and 
hexadecanoic acid (46%). The other fatty acids described were 
below 3% (Table 2). 
The presence of catalase was tested using 3% (v/v) H 2 O 2 and 
gave a positive result. The oxidase test was also negative for 
strain MC1. Corynebacterium phoceense strain MC1 was capable 
of fermenting glucose, ribose, maltose, saccharose, D-ribose, D-
galactose, D-glucose, D-fructose, D-mannose, arbutin, ferric 
citrate esculin, D-maltose and D-saccharose. Nitrates were 
reduced into nitrites. Alkaline phosphatase, esterase (C4), 
esterase lipase (C8), leucine arylamidase, cystine arylamidase, 
trypsin, α-chymotrypsin, acid phosphatase, β-glucosidase, pyr-
azinamidase, pyrrolidonyl arylamidase and naphthol-AS-BI-
phosphohydrolase activities were highlighted. 
Corynebacterium phoceense strain MC1 was susceptible to all 
antibiotic treatments tested except nitrofurantoin and metro-
nidazole, to which it was resistant. 
The biochemical and phenotypic features of strain MC1 were 
compared to the corresponding features of other close rep-
resentatives of the genus Corynebacterium (Table 3). We 
particularly observed the absence of endospores forming in the 
closest Corynebacterium spp. </p>

<p>Genome properties 
The genome is 2 793 868 bp long with 63.23% GC content 
(Table 4, Fig. 6). It is composed of 14 scaffolds (composed of 71 
contigs). Of the 2575 predicted genes, 2508 were protein-
coding genes and 67 were RNAs (four genes are 5S rRNA, 
three genes are 16S rRNA, three genes are 23S rRNA and 57 
genes are tRNA genes). A total of 1804 genes (71.93%) were 
assigned as putative function (by COGs or by NR BLAST). One 
hundred fifty-one genes were identified as ORFans (6.02%). The 
remaining 475 genes were annotated as hypothetical proteins 
(18.94%). The National Center for Biotechnology Information 
ID is PRJEB14666, and the genome is deposited under accession 
number FLTI01000001. The distribution of genes into COGs 
functional categories is presented in Table 5. </p>

<p>Genome comparison 
Table 6 compares Corynebacterium phoceense's genomic char-
acteristics to other close species. The draft genome sequence 
of C. phoceense is smaller than those of Corynebacterium mus-
telae, Corynebacterium freiburgense and Corynebacterium aurimu-
cosum (2.794, 3.474, 2.91 and 2.905 Mb respectively), but larger 
than those of Corynebacterium lactis, Corynebacterium ulcerans, </p>

<p>TABLE 5. Number of genes associated with 25 general COGs </p>

<p>functional categories </p>

<p>Code Value </p>

<p>% of 
total </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Description </p>

<p>J 
153 
6.10 
Translation 
A 
1 
0.04 
RNA processing and modification 
K 
106 
4.22 
Transcription 
L 
68 
2.71 
Replication, recombination and repair 
B 
0 
0 
Chromatin structure and dynamics 
D 
18 
0.71 
Cell cycle control, mitosis and meiosis 
Y 
0 
0 
Nuclear structure 
V 
56 
2.23 
Defense mechanisms 
T 
55 
2.19 
Signal transduction mechanisms 
M 
57 
2.27 
Cell wall/membrane biogenesis 
N 
3 
0.11 
Cell motility 
Z 
0 
0 
Cytoskeleton 
W 
3 
0.11 
Extracellular structures 
U 
17 
0.67 
Intracellular trafficking and secretion 
O 
66 
2.63 
Posttranslational modification, protein turnover, 
chaperones 
X 
53 
2.11 
Mobilome: prophages, transposons 
C 
94 
3.74 
Energy production and conversion 
G 
129 
5.14 
Carbohydrate transport and metabolism 
E 
172 
6.85 
Amino acid transport and metabolism 
F 
74 
2.95 
Nucleotide transport and metabolism 
H 
105 
4.18 
Coenzyme transport and metabolism 
I 
73 
2.91 
Lipid transport and metabolism 
P 
123 
4.90 
Inorganic ion transport and metabolism 
Q 
44 
1.75 
Secondary metabolites biosynthesis, transport and 
catabolism 
R 
131 
5.22 
General function prediction only 
S 
78 
3.11 
Function unknown 
-
997 
39.75 
Not in COGs </p>

<p>COGs, Clusters of Orthologous Groups database. 
a Total is based on total number of protein-coding genes in annotated genome. </p>

<p>TABLE 6. Genome comparison of closely related species to </p>

<p>Corynebacterium phoceense strain MC1 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>Species </p>

<p>Size 
(Mb) </p>

<p>G+C 
(%) </p>

<p>Total 
genes </p>

<p>Corynebacterium lactis strain RW2-5 
2.76 
60.5 
2364 
Corynebacterium ulcerans strain NCTC_7910 
2.61 
53.3 
2296 
Corynebacterium mustelae strain 3105 
3.47 
52.5 
3146 
Corynebacterium freiburgense strain 1045 
2.91 
49.8 
2667 
Corynebacterium mastitidis strain S-8 CECT_4843 2.37 
68.9 
2241 
Corynebacterium aurimucosum strain IMMIB D-
1488 </p>

<p>2.90 
59.2 
2769 </p>

<p>Corynebacterium phoceense strain MC1 
2.79 
63.2 
2508 
Corynebacterium terpenotabidum strain Y-11 IFO 
14764 </p>

<p>2.75 
67 
2369 </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>Cresci et al. Corynebacterium phoceense sp. nov. </p>



<p>© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 14, 73-82 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Corynebacterium mastitidis and Corynebacterium terpenotabidum 
(2.77, 2.61, 2.37 and 2.75 Mb respectively). 
The G+C content of Corynebacterium phoceense is smaller 
than those of Corynebacterium mastitidis and Corynebacterium 
terpenotabidum (63.23, 68.9 and 67.02% respectively), but larger 
than those of Corynebacterium lactis, Corynebacterium ulcerans, 
Corynebacterium mustelae, Corynebacterium freiburgense and 
Corynebacterium aurimucosum (60.53, 53.39, 52.57, 49.82 and 
59.21% respectively). 
The gene content of Corynebacterium phoceense is smaller 
than those of Corynebacterium mustelae, Corynebacterium frei-
burgense and Corynebacterium aurimucosum (2508, 3146, 2667 
and 2769 respectively), but larger than those of Corynebacterium 
lactis, Corynebacterium ulcerans, Corynebacterium mastitidis and </p>

<p>Corynebacterium terpenotabidum (2364, 2296, 2241 and 2369 
respectively). 
Finally, the distribution of genes into COGs categories was 
similar in all compared genomes except for those corre-
sponding to the cell cycle control, mitosis and meiosis category, 
which were only present in C. mastitidis, C. mustelae and 
C. ulcerans (Fig. 7). C. phoceense strain MC1 shared 2667, 1358, 
1332, 1248, 1128, 1211 and 1442 orthologous genes with 
C. freiburgense, C. aurimucosum, C. ulcerans, C. lactis, C. terpeno-
tabidum, C. mastitidis and C. mustelae respectively (Table 7). 
Among species with standing in nomenclature, AGIOS values 
ranged from 54.12% between C. terpenotabidum and 
C. freiburgense to 74.86% between C. aurimucosum and 
C. phoceense. When C. phoceense was compared to the other </p>

<p>FIG. 7. Distribution of functional classes of predicted genes according to COGs of proteins. </p>

<p>TABLE 7. Numbers of orthologous protein shared between genomes (upper right) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>C. freiburgense 
C. aurimucosum 
C. ulcerans 
C. lactis 
C. phoceense 
C. terpenotabidum 
C. mastitidis 
C. mustelae </p>

<p>Corynebacterium freiburgense 
strain 1045 </p>

<p>2667 
1358 
1332 
1248 
1232 
1128 
1211 
1442 </p>

<p>Corynebacterium aurimucosum 
strain IMMIB </p>

<p>63.97 
2769 
1336 
1252 
1407 
1189 
1315 
1392 </p>

<p>Corynebacterium ulcerans 
strain NCTC 7910 </p>

<p>57.66 
58.26 
2296 
1197 
1221 
1091 
1213 
1354 </p>

<p>Corynebacterium lactis 
strain RW2-5 </p>

<p>57.63 
60.50 
58.47 
2364 
1116 
1105 
1149 
1249 </p>

<p>Corynebacterium phoceense 
strain MC1 </p>

<p>63.56 
74.86 
58.13 
61.48 
2508 
1079 
1194 
1264 </p>

<p>Corynebacterium terpenotabidum 
strain Y-11 IFO 14764 </p>

<p>54.12 
58.32 
54.92 
56.16 
59.86 
2369 
1123 
1146 </p>

<p>Corynebacterium mastitidis 
strain S-8 CECT 4843 </p>

<p>63.90 
69.01 
57.33 
61.39 
70.81 
60.55 
2241 
1252 </p>

<p>Corynebacterium mustelae 
strain 3105 </p>

<p>65.46 
64.85 
58.55 
58.25 
64.48 
55.39 
64.16 
3146 </p>

<p>a Average percentage similarity of nucleotides corresponding to orthologous protein shared between genomes (lower left) and numbers of proteins per genome (bold). </p>



<p>New Microbes and New Infections, Volume 14 Number C, November 2016 </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 14, 73-82 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>species, AGIOS values ranged from 58.13% with C. ulcerans to 
74.86% with C. aurimucosum. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>On the basis of phenotypic, phylogenetic and genomic analyses, 
we formally propose the creation of Corynebacterium phoceense 
which contains the type strain MC1 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>. This bacterial strain has 
been isolated from the urine of a kidney transplant recipient. </p>

<p>Description of Corynebacterium phoceense 
type strain MC1 
T sp. nov. </p>

<p>Corynebacterium phoceense (pho.ce'en'se, L. gen. masc., pho-
ceense, "of Phoceen," the old Latin name of the city of Marseille, 
where strain MC1 
T was isolated). Cells have mean diameter of </p>

<p>0.5 μm and a mean length of 3 μm. Colonies are round and 
1.0 mm in diameter on 5% sheep's blood-enriched Columbia 
agar (bioMérieux). Positive reactions are observed for glucose, 
ribose, maltose, saccharose, alkaline phosphatase, esterase (C4), 
esterase lipase (C8), leucine arylamidase, cystine arylamidase, 
trypsin, α-chymotrypsin, acid phosphatase, β-glucosidase, pyr-
azinamidase, pyrrolidonyl arylamidase and naphthol-AS-BI-
phosphohydrolase. D-Ribose, D-galactose, D-glucose, D-fruc-
tose, D-mannose, arbutin, D-maltose and D-saccharose were 
metabolized. Cells were susceptible to vancomycin, rifampicin, 
doxycycline, erythromycin, amoxicillin, nitrofurantoin, genta-
micin, ciprofloxacin, ceftriaxone, amoxicillin + clavulanic acid, 
penicillin G, gentamicin, trimethoprim + sulfamethoxazole, 
oxacillin, imipenem, tobramycin, metronidazole, amikacin, line-
zolid, clindamycin, daptomycin and chloramphenicol. 
The G+C content of the genome is 63.23%. The 16S rRNA 
gene sequence and whole-genome shotgun sequence of 
C. phoceense strain MC1 
T are deposited in GenBank under </p>

<p>accession numbers LN849777 and FLTI01000001, respectively. 
The type strain MC1 
T (= CSUR P1905 = DSM 100570) was </p>

<p>isolated from the urine of a kidney transplant recipient. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors thank the Xegen Company (www.xegen.fr) for 
automating the genomic annotation process. This study was 
funded by the Fondation Méditerranée Infection. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>None declared. </p>



<p>NMNI </p>

<p>Cresci et al. Corynebacterium phoceense sp. nov. </p>



<p>© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 14, 73-82 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>





<p>New Microbes and New Infections, Volume 14 Number C, November 2016 </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 14, 73-82 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

</text></tei>