<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5321584" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>PURPOSE. The aim of this study was to compare the retention of mini implant overdenture by the number, the 
type of magnetic attachment, and the directions of applied dislodging force. MATERIALS AND METHODS. The 
experimental groups were designed by the number and type of magnetic attachment. Twenty samples were tested 
with Magden implants. Each attachment was composed of the magnet assembly in overdenture sample and the 
abutment keeper in a mandibular model. Dislodging forces were applied to the overdenture samples (50.0 mm/ 
min) in 3 directions. The loading was repeated 10 times in each direction. The values of dislodging force were 
analyzed statistically using SPSS at 95% level of confidence. RESULTS. The retentive force of group 2 was greater 
than that of group 1 in both types of attachment in every direction (P &lt; .05). Oblique retentive force of flat type 
magnetic attachment was higher than that of cushion type attachment in both groups (P &lt; .05). In group 1, 
oblique retentive force showed the highest and anterior-posterior retentive force showed the lowest value in both 
attachment types (P &lt; .05). In group 2, both types of attachment showed the lowest retentive force with anterior-
posterior direction of dislodging force (P &lt;.05). CONCLUSION. Proper retentive properties for implant 
overdenture were obtained, regardless of the number and type of magnetic attachment. In both types of magnetic 
attachment, the greater retentive force was attained with more implants. Oblique retentive force of flat type 
magnetic attachment was greater than that of cushion type. Among all subgroups, anterior-posterior retentive 
force was the lowest among three different directions of dislodging force. [ J Adv Prosthodont 2017;9:14-21] </p>

<p>The retention and stability of complete denture can influ-
ence a patient's ability to function and are directly related to 
patient's confidence and comfort. 
1 However, it is difficult to 
achieve optimal denture retention and stability with severely 
resorbed mandibular ridge. 
2,3 Thus, the overdenture assisted 
by osseointegrated implant is an attractive treatment </p>

<p>because of its relative simplicity, minimal invasiveness, and 
economic feasibility. For overdenture supported by both 
implants and oral mucosa, fewer implants are necessary 
compared to the prosthesis supported only by implants. 
Usually, overdenture consists of 2 or more implants placed 
on upper and lower arch. 
1 An attachment device (male part) 
connected to the implant has a corresponding coupling unit 
(female part) fixed to the tissue surface of the complete 
denture. When the attachment components are correctly 
connected, the complete denture can be provided appropri-
ate support, retention, and stability by both implant and 
mucosa. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Since the concept of overdenture fixation for the over-
denture introduced in Switzerland in 1898, 
5 different attach-
ment systems have been used to retain mandibular overden-
ture. Bars with clips, studs, and magnets were reported as 
viable treatment options. For implant overdenture, Mensor </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>also reported that bar, stud, and magnetic attachments were 
the most common attachment systems. It has been shown 
that solitary attachments are less technique sensitive and </p>

<p>Corresponding author: 
Soo-Yeon Shin 
College of Dentistry, Dankook University, 119 Dandae-ro, Dongnam-gu, 
Cheonan-si, Chungnam 31116, Republic of Korea 
Tel. +82415500251: e-mail, syshin@dankook.ac.kr 
Received January 26, 2016 / Last Revision October 14, 2016 / Accepted 
December 20, 2016 </p>

<p>© 2017 The Korean Academy of Prosthodontics 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons. 
org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, 
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original 
work is properly cited. </p>

<p>pISSN 2005-7806, eISSN 2005-7814 </p>

<p>The Journal of Advanced Prosthodontics 15 </p>

<p>easier to clean compared to bar attachments. 
7 Due to their 
simple application, studs and magnets have gained a wide 
popularity in clinical practice. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Application of the magnet in dentistry has been attempt-
ed to enhance the stability of the denture by repulsive force 
of magnet on both side of complete denture since 1930. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Since then, several investigations have been performed to 
increase the retention of denture. Magnet was surgically 
implanted in the mandible of edentulous patients to get 
magnetic attraction. 
10-12 Freedman 
13 tried to use repulsive 
force between magnets placed in upper and lower complete 
dentures. It was rarely succeeded to obtain adequate force 
to aid denture retention, and exposure of the magnet in 
wound area was also reported. 
With the introduction of powerful rare earth magnets 
such as Samarium-Cobalt (Sm-Co) and Neodymium (Nd-
Fe-B), the use of implanted magnets to aid denture reten-
tion was investigated actively again. 
12,14,15 These magnets 
could be produced in dimensions small enough to be used 
in dental applications, while still providing the necessary 
force. Several investigators reported clinically satisfying 
results by using implants and magnetic attachments in 
patients unsatisfied with the existing mandibular complete 
denture. The results were permanent retention and proper 
dispersion of occlusal force of the magnetic attachment 
compared to other attachment systems. 
16-18 Also, magnetic 
attachment is easily dislodged by lateral force, which pre-
vents the damage of implant. Clinical application of mag-
netic attachment has become easier as several types of mag-
netic attachment have been introduced. Flat type with thin 
disk form performed high retention force, and cushion type 
with 0.4 mm of gap between magnet assembly and resin cap 
showed shock-absorbing effect on implant fixture. 
In case of conventional dental implants with diameters 
from 3.4 to 5.8 mm, patients need sufficient bone width for 
implant placement. Thus, conventional implants may not be 
chosen for some patients with severely resorbed mandibular 
ridge because of their narrow ridges and lack of keratinized 
mucosa. In this situation, mini dental implants, which have 
diameters ranging from 1.8 to 3.3 mm, serve as alterna-
tives. </p>

<p>19,20 </p>

<p>The purpose of this study was to compare the retention 
of mini implant overdenture by the number and the type of 
magnetic attachments and by the vertical, oblique, and ante-
rior-posterior directions of applied dislodging force to over-
denture. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Specimens were divided into 2 groups by the number of 
implants placed, group 1 with 2 implants and group 2 with 
4 implants. In group 1 model, two implants were bilaterally 
placed on each canine area, 15 mm distal to the center of 
mandible. In group 2 model, 4 implants were bilaterally 
placed on lateral incisor and first premolar area, 8 mm and 
20 mm distal to center of mandible (Fig. 1). According to 
the types of magnetic attachment, each group was divided </p>

<p>into 2 subgroups. Two kinds of magnetic attachment were 
used in this study: flat type (DX 600, Aichi steel, Tokai, 
Japan) and cushion type (SX-L, Aichi steel, Tokai, Japan). 
Mini implant fixtures, 2.7 mm in diameter and 10.0 mm 
in length (Magden, Shinwon Dental, Seoul, Korea), were 
placed in mandibular edentulous model (CHS-EDS1, 
M.Tech Korea, Seoul, Korea) with experimental soft tissue. 
Magnetic keepers (Magden, Shinwon Dental, Seoul, Korea) 
with 4.0 mm in diameter and 2.0 mm in length were 
installed with torque of 20 N. 
A cobalt-chrome metal framework was fabricated to fit 
both mandibular models (Fig. 2). To apply dislodging tensile 
force to metal framework, loops were formed on buccal and 
lingual sides of midline and in both first molar area of the 
framework, 4 nuts of 3 mm diameter were soldered to con-
nect the framework with overdenture housing. 
Placing the metal framework on mandibular model, 
overdenture housing was fabricated by pouring self-curing 
resin (Ortho-Jet Orthodontic Acrylic Resin, Lang dental 
Mfg Co., Inc., Wheeling, WV, USA). Implants and under-
cuts were blocked-out and resin separator was applied. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Magnetic attachment overdenture sample seated 
on a mandibular model with nuts and bolts securely 
fastened. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Two experimental models with two and four 
implants placed in the interforamen area of mandible. (A) 
group 1, (B) group 2. </p>

<p>The influence of the number and the type of magnetic attachment on the retention of mandibular mini implant overdenture </p>



<p>Overdenture housings were duplicated with putty type 
impression material (Silagum Putty soft, DMG, Hamburg, 
Germany) as duplicating molds. Self-curing resin was mixed 
according to manufacturer's instruction, poured into fabri-
cated mold, and polymerized under 3 bar (43.5 psi), 55°C, 
for 30 minutes. Four connecting holes for stainless steel volt 
(2.0 mm diameter, 7.0 mm length) were formed on the sur-
face of overdenture housing. Ten samples were used in each 
group and a total of 20 samples were fabricated. 
Keeper screws were installed on the implant fixture by 
torque of 20 N, and mounting ring was mounted on the 
keeper. Magnetic attachment was placed on the keeper and 
fixed to the overdenture housing by self-curing resin. Venting 
hole was formed on overdenture housing. 
Three directions of tensile force, vertical, oblique and 
anterior-posterior, were applied to measure retentive force. 
Metal framework was seated on the mandibular model fixed 
to Instron testing machine (Model 3344, Instron Co., 
Norwood, MA, USA). Overdenture housing with magnetic 
attachment was connected to the framework by stainless-
steel volts and nuts. Four 16.00 cm Stainless-steel metal 
chains were mounted on upper jig of Instron by custom-
fabricated molds, and 2 of the metal chains were connected 
to the loops placed on buccal and lingual side of midline 
and another 2 chains to the loops placed on the first molar 
area. All chains were adjusted to achieve tight connection. 
Tensile test was performed at a cross-head speed of 50.0 
mm/min, the dislodging speed of denture from ridge, to 
measure retentive force. Overdenture samples were tested 
10 times with 3 different directions, a total of 30 times on 
each sample. The retentive forces were determined and 
recorded. 
Statistical analysis was performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">IBM SPSS Statistics</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v. 22.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). The mean and the 
standard deviation of each group were calculated. All data 
were analyzed with Mann-Whitney U test to check for sig-
nificant differences among the groups. Wilcoxon signed-
rank tests were also used to analyze the effects of the direc-
tion of the dislodging force within the groups. All analyses 
were performed at 95% level of confidence (α = .05). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Five overdenture samples were fabricated for each sub-
group. Averages of each sample were calculated and ana-
lyzed statistically (Table 1). 
In group 1, oblique retentive force of flat type magnetic 
attachment, 1.65 N, was shown as the highest value. By 
oblique direction of dislodging force, flat type magnetic 
attachment was more retentive than cushion type magnetic 
attachment (P &lt; .05). Oblique retentive force of both mag-
netic attachments was higher than vertical and anterior-pos-
terior retentive force (P &lt; .05). 
In group 2, flat type magnetic attachment showed higher 
retentive force than cushion type in oblique direction of dis-
lodging force applied (P &lt; .05). Vertical retentive force of 
flat type magnetic attachment, 5.1 N, was shown as the high-
est retentive force. The lowest retentive force was shown in 
anterior-posterior direction in both magnetic attachments (P 
&lt; .05) (Table 2, Fig. 3). 
In group 1, oblique retentive force of flat type magnetic 
attachment was higher than cushion type magnetic attach-
ment (P &lt; .05). No significant difference was observed in 
vertical and anterior-posterior retentive forces. 
When 4 implants were placed (group 2), cushion type 
magnetic attachment showed lower oblique retentive force 
than flat type attachment (P &lt; .05). In vertical and anterior-
posterior retentive forces, no significant difference was 
observed (Table 3, Fig. 4). 
The influence of the direction of dislodging force to reten-
tion of mandibular overdenture was analyzed by Wilcoxon 
signed rank test. Oblique retentive force of flat type mag-
netic attachment showed the highest value in group 1, fol-
lowed by vertical and anterior-posterior retentive force (P &lt; 
.05). In cushion type group, oblique retentive force was the 
highest and anterior-posterior retentive force was the lowest 
(P &lt; .05). 
Concerning the direction of force applied, vertical 
retentive force of group 2 was higher than oblique retentive 
force in both flat and cushion type magnetic attachment. 
However, no significant difference was observed. With 
anterior-posterior direction of dislodging force, flat type 
and cushion type magnetic attachment showed the lowest 
retentive force (P &lt; .05) (Table 4, Fig. 5). </p>

<p>Table 1. Means and standard deviations of retentive forces of experimental groups (unit: N) </p>

<p>Group 1 
Group 2 </p>

<p>Flat type 
Cushion type 
Flat type 
Cushion type </p>

<p>Mean 
SD 
Mean 
SD 
Mean 
SD 
Mean 
SD </p>

<p>Vertical 
1.06 
0.21 
1.01 
0.13 
5.10 
1.01 
3.99 
0.43 </p>

<p>Oblique 
1.65 
0.21 
1.37 
0.18 
4.66 
0.46 
3.71 
0.43 </p>

<p>Ant-Post 
0.81 
0.12 
0.75 
0.12 
1.77 
0.42 
1.52 
0.51 </p>

<p>J Adv Prosthodont 2017;9:14-21 </p>

<p>The Journal of Advanced Prosthodontics 17 </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of retentive force according to the 
number of implant by Mann-Whitney U test </p>

<p>Flat type 
Cushion type </p>

<p>Group 1 -Group 2 
Group 1 -Group 2 </p>

<p>Vertical 
.008* 
.008* </p>

<p>Oblique 
.008* 
.008* </p>

<p>Anterior-Posterior 
.008* 
.008* </p>

<p>*denotes the significance at the 0.05 level </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparison of retentive force according to the 
type of magnetic attachment by Mann-Whitney U test </p>

<p>Group 1 
Group 2 </p>

<p>Flat type -Cushion 
type </p>

<p>Flat type -Cushion 
type </p>

<p>Vertical 
.548* 
.056* </p>

<p>Oblique 
.008* 
.008* </p>

<p>Anterior-Posterior 
.841* 
.421* </p>

<p>*denotes the significance at the 0.05 level </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Comparison of retentive force according to the number of implant. </p>

<p>6.00 </p>

<p>5.00 </p>

<p>4.00 </p>

<p>3.00 </p>

<p>2.00 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>Retentive force (unit: N) </p>

<p>Group 1 
Group 2 
Group 1 
Group 2 </p>

<p>Flat type 
Cushion type </p>

<p>Vertical 
Oblique 
Ant-Post </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Comparison of retentive force according to the type of magnetic attachment. </p>

<p>6.00 </p>

<p>5.00 </p>

<p>4.00 </p>

<p>3.00 </p>

<p>2.00 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>Retentive force (unit: N) </p>

<p>Flat type 
Cushion type 
Flat type 
Cushion type </p>

<p>Group 1 
Group 2 </p>

<p>Vertical 
Oblique 
Ant-Post </p>

<p>The influence of the number and the type of magnetic attachment on the retention of mandibular mini implant overdenture </p>



<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The implant overdenture concept has advantages for 
patients with severely resorbed mandibular ridges. It would 
be possible to provide a stable denture and increased load-
bearing capacity to the edentulous patient. If osseous con-
dition precludes a standard sized implant approach, such as 
of patients with inadequate interdental space, reduced inter-
occlusal space, or narrow atrophic osseous contour, 
19 mini 
implants may provide an alternative treatment. With mini 
implants, 6-year survival rate of 95.5% for single tooth res-
torations and stabilization of overdenture was reported. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Meanwhile, permanent magnets have been used to 
improve retention and stability of dentures for many years, </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>and magnetic attachments have become one of the most 
common attachments used for these purposes. 
23 Many 
authors have described procedures regarding the use of 
magnets and a high degree of patient satisfaction has been 
reported. 
24 The implant overdenture is a two-component 
system that consists of an implant keeper and a magnet 
built into the denture. When the denture is seated, the keep-
er becomes an induced magnet by contacting with the mag-
net in the denture. Due to the attractive force of this mag-</p>

<p>net, the retention of overdenture is enhanced significantly. 
In case of overdenture, retention of prosthesis and 
retentive force of magnetic attachment are highly correlat-
ed. Gillings 
25 reported that proper attractive force to retain 
overdentures is about 400 -600 gf (3.91 -5.88 N), and that 
attractive force less than 140 -310 gf (1.37 -3.03 N) is 
insufficient for retention of implant overdenture. When 
oblique retentive force is 53 -94 gf (0.52 -0.92 N), it is 
reported that magnetic attachment may not be able to resist 
horizontal movement of denture. 
26 In this study, 50.0 mm/ 
min of cross-head speed was set to measure the retentive 
force, which is the rate of the mandible as it moves away 
from the denture base during mastication. 
27 Usually, slower 
speed of 0.5 mm/min is chosen to measure maximum 
attraction force, and this speed of separation was also used 
in the study of Gillings. 
Testing the magnetic components at 50.0 mm/min 
speed decreased the retentive force by 3 times compared to 
the result upon application of slow speed of separation. </p>

<p>28,29 </p>

<p>Thus, the values of retentive force observed in this study 
are sufficient to retain overdenture, especially when retained 
by 4 implants. Oblique retentive forces obtained in every 
subgroup of this study were found to be enough to resist </p>

<p>Table 4. Comparison of retentive force according to vertical (V), oblique (O), anterior-posterior (AP) directions by 
Wilcoxon signed-rank test </p>

<p>Group 1 
Group 2 </p>

<p>V-O 
O-AP 
AP-V 
V-O 
O-AP 
AP-V </p>

<p>Flat type 
.043* 
.043* 
.043* 
.686 
.043* 
.043* </p>

<p>Cushion type 
.043* 
.043* 
.042* 
.345 
.043* 
.043* </p>

<p>*denotes the significance at the 0.05 level </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Comparison of retentive force according to vertical (V), oblique (O), anterior-posterior (AP) directions. </p>

<p>6.00 </p>

<p>5.00 </p>

<p>4.00 </p>

<p>3.00 </p>

<p>2.00 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>Retentive force (unit: N) </p>

<p>Vertical 
Oblique 
Ant-Post 
Vertical 
Oblique 
Ant-Post </p>

<p>Group 1 
Group 2 </p>

<p>Flat type 
Cushion type </p>

<p>J Adv Prosthodont 2017;9:14-21 </p>

<p>The Journal of Advanced Prosthodontics 19 </p>

<p>the horizontal movement of denture. As the number of 
implants increased from 2 to 4, retentive force of magnetic 
attachment is significantly increased in every direction and in 
all types of magnetic attachments (P &lt; .05). In case of flat 
type, vertical retentive force increased by 4.81 times, while 
oblique and anterior posterior retentive force increased by 
2.82 times and 2.19 times, respectively. Cushion type is 
reported to show similar tendency; vertical retentive force 
increases by 3.95 times, oblique retentive force by 2.71 
times, and anterior-posterior retentive force by 2.03 times. 
This result is consistent with the findings of Seo, 
5 and Ma 
and Shin, 
30 which concluded that as number of fixture 
increased, the displacement of overdenture was decreased. 
As several types of magnetic attachment have been 
developed, clinicians have a chance to choose the most 
appropriate type of magnetic attachment suitable for various 
clinical situations. Open-field and closed-field magnetic sys-
tems have been used to retain dentures for many years. 
Although the open-field system is the first of the magnets 
used for the retention of the overdentures, 
23,31 many com-
mercial systems now consist of the closed-field type. All 
magnetic assemblies investigated in this study were closed-
field systems, so the retention reduced rapidly with increased 
separation. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Comparing flat type magnet with cushion type, flat type 
magnet is more retentive than other types, and cushion type 
has shock-absorbing effects and permits vertical movement 
of dentures. Although it was not discussed in this study 
because of its incompatibility with mini-implant, dome type 
of magnet was reported to permit lateral movement of den-
tures. 
5 In this study, 2 types, flat and cushion type of mag-
netic attachment, were investigated to compare the reten-
tion and stability of the implant overdenture by the number 
and the type of magnetic attachment and the direction of 
applied force. Cushion type of magnetic attachment was 
found to be less retentive in oblique direction of dislodging 
force compared to flat type. Similar result was observed in 
the study of Seo. 
5 Soe stated that it would be the result of a 
bigger dimension of cushion type magnetic attachment. As 
cushion type magnetic assemblies contain resin cap, the big-
ger dimension of magnetic attachment could easily cause 
dislocation of the magnetic attachment when excessive self-
curing resin is applied and relief of denture is insufficient. 
The difference of net dislodging force direction applied on 
the magnetic attachment between flat type and cushion type 
attachment could also influence the results. Attractive force 
of magnet is generally stronger to vertical direction of dis-
lodging force than to lateral direction. In this study, the dis-
lodging force is transmitted via resin cap, and therefore dis-
lodging force of oblique direction has more lateral than ver-
tical component of force to magnetic attachment in cushion 
type attachment. The dislodging force of cushion type 
attachment was more lateral than that of flat type attach-
ment. This is the reason for lower retentive force of cush-
ion type attachment to oblique dislodging force than that of 
flat type attachment. Cushion type attachment can be 
appropriate treatment option for the abutment, which is </p>

<p>vulnerable to lateral force. 
The highest value of retentive force was observed when 
oblique retentive force was applied on flat type magnetic 
attachment in group 1. Also, both flat and cushion type 
magnetic attachments were found to provide the highest 
resistance to oblique dislodgement followed by vertical and 
anterior-posterior direction. In group 2, both vertical and 
oblique retentive forces were significantly higher than ante-
rior-posterior retentive force regardless of the type of mag-
netic attachment (P &lt; .05). The lowest retentive force was 
observed when anterior-posterior dislodging force was 
applied on cushion type of magnetic attachment (P &lt; .05). 
This result can be misunderstood that magnetic attachment 
is much retentive to lateral movement of denture than to 
vertical movement, but oblique or anterior-posterior dis-
lodging force did not reproduce the lateral movement of 
denture in clinical situation. These directions of dislodging 
force are rather similar with movement of denture when 
patients chew sticky food or masticate food unilaterally. 
However, with high value of oblique retentive force, it can 
be considered that the magnetic attachments used in this 
study may provide appropriate stability of denture. Further 
studies are needed to determine the influencing factors of 
the stability of denture. 
To achieve the sufficient stability of denture, the break-
away force of magnetic retainers must exceed the displacing 
force applied to denture. When vertical retentive force is 
greater than anterior-posterior retentive force, stability of 
denture is reported to be sufficient to maintain the denture 
in position on its basal seat. 
24,27 Gillings 
32 reported that such 
displacing forces may be as low as 0.22 to 0.53 N. In present 
study, both flat and cushion type of magnetic attachment 
are reported to have greater vertical retentive force than the 
displacing forces, regardless of the number of implants. 
Thus, the magnetic attachment used in this study may be 
useful to retain denture in position. 
From the limited data of this study, implant overden-
tures with 2-4 implants were observed that it had clinically 
proper retentive force, and overdenture with more implants, 
if possible, can be considered as more effective and satisfac-
tory treatment. Especially for patients with severely resorbed 
mandibular ridge, mini implants with no need for additional 
surgery and magnetic attachments with shock-absorbing 
effect to lateral force 
33 can be an appropriate treatment 
choice. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>This in vitro study tested the influence of the type and the 
number of magnetic attachment of the retention of man-
dibular mini implant overdenture. Measurements of reten-
tive force were performed by 3 different directions of dis-
lodging force. Experimental groups were classified by the 
numbers of implant, 2 or 4, and each groups were divided 
into 2 subgroup by the types of magnetic attachment, flat 
or cushion type. With five overdenture samples of each 
subgroup, a total of 20 samples were fabricated. Within the </p>

<p>The influence of the number and the type of magnetic attachment on the retention of mandibular mini implant overdenture </p>



<p>parameters of this study design, following conclusions may 
be made. First, In every subgroup of experimental group, 
magnetic attachment has proper retentive properties for 
implant overdenture. Second, the more implant placed, the 
greater retentive force achieved regardless of the type of 
magnetic attachment. Third, when oblique direction of dis-
lodging force is applied, flat type of magnetic attachment is 
more retentive than cushion type of magnetic attachment. 
Finally, regardless of the type and number of implants, 
anterior-posterior retentive force is the lowest among 3 dif-
ferent directions of dislodging force. 
According to these conclusions, the mini implant overden-
ture with magnetic attachment can be the treatment of 
choice, when patient is with extremely resorbed mandibular 
edentulous ridge. With mini implant overdenture, esthetic 
and functional rehabilitation are expected to be achieved. 
With appropriate circumstances of patients, better retention 
and stability of overdenture could be expected to implant 
overdenture with 4 implants. </p>

<p>ORCID </p>

<p>Eunjee Lee http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2843-3636 
Soo-Yeon Shin http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6160-7277 </p>



<p>J Adv Prosthodont 2017;9:14-21 </p>

<p>The Journal of Advanced Prosthodontics 21 </p>



<p>The influence of the number and the type of magnetic attachment on the retention of mandibular mini implant overdenture </p>

</text></tei>