<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5440001" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: This randomized controlled trial (RCT) evaluated a 6-month peer-led 
community education and mentorship program to improve the diagnosis and management of 
osteoporosis. 
Methods: Ten seniors (74-90 years of age) were trained to become peer educators and mentors 
and deliver the intervention. In the subsequent RCT, 105 seniors (mean age =80.5±6.9; 89% 
female) were randomly assigned to the peer-led education and mentorship program (n=53) or 
control group (n=52). Knowledge was assessed at baseline and 6 months. Success was defined 
as discussing osteoporosis risk with their family physician, obtaining a bone mineral density 
assessment, and returning to review their risk profile and receive advice and/or treatment. 
Results: Knowledge of osteoporosis did not change significantly. There was no difference in 
knowledge change between the two groups (mean difference =1.3, 95% confidence interval [CI] 
of difference -0.76 to 3.36). More participants in the intervention group achieved a successful 
outcome (odds ratio 0.16, 95% CI 0.06-0.42, P,0.001). 
Conclusion: Peer-led education and mentorship can promote positive health behavior in 
seniors. This model was effective for improving osteoporosis risk assessment, diagnosis, and 
treatment in a community setting. 
The sequelae resulting from osteoporosis and osteoporotic fractures are significant 
and include functional impairment, 
1 institutionalization, 
2 and death. 
3 Despite the 
adverse outcomes, osteoporosis is largely underdiagnosed, with as few as 13%-25% 
of patients who experience a fragility fracture being investigated for osteoporosis by 
bone mineral density (BMD) assessment. 
4,5 Similarly, the management of osteoporosis 
is less than optimal, with those at high risk for fractures often remaining untreated. </p>

<p>6-8   It is a challenge to improve the management of osteoporosis since, in the absence of an 
osteoporotic fracture, osteoporosis is symptomless and is dependent on risk assessment 
and screening for diagnosis. Successful risk screening not only depends on educating 
physicians but also relies on increasing public awareness of osteoporosis. 
Self-management approaches to prevention and management of health conditions 
have been lauded as effective ways to improve health outcomes in adults and to reduce 
health care costs. 
9-11 Although self-management may be an effective strategy for younger </p>

<p>Correspondence: Marita Kloseck 
sam Katz Community health and 
Aging research Unit, Faculty of health 
sciences, Arthur and sonia labatt 
health sciences Bldg, room hsB 218, 
Western University, london n6A 5B9, 
On, Canada 
Tel +1 519 661 2111 ext 81230 
Fax +1 519 850 2432 (shared) 
email mkloseck@uwo.ca </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Clinical Interventions in Aging 
16 May 2017 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>824 </p>

<p>Kloseck et al </p>

<p>age groups, it poses a challenge for seniors in advanced age 
who have multiple problems and reduced physical and mental 
capacity. Well-documented barriers include a large number 
of care recommendations, 
12 limited knowledge of medical 
conditions, 
13 cultural and communication factors and trans-
portation issues, 
14 poor recall, 
15 and comorbidity and com-
pounding effects of conditions. 
16 It has been suggested that 
self-help models of community development, in which some 
of the responsibility for health care planning and provision 
is placed not just in the hands of individuals but also on the 
community as a whole, may provide the greatest benefit. </p>

<p>17,18   In particular, building community capacity using a peer 
support model (neighbors helping neighbors) may expand 
the potential pool of health and supportive services within a 
local setting. 
19,20 In the context of seniors, younger-old age 
groups may assist in supporting the oldest-old and friends 
and neighbors helping each other may extend the reach of 
the health system and assist the frail elderly to successfully 
age in place. 
19-21 The use of knowledgeable and skilled senior 
volunteers trained to educate their peers on health-related 
topics, although not new, is gaining popularity and support 
as an effective method of health promotion. </p>

<p>22-24   This paper reports results from a pragmatic randomized 
controlled trial (RCT) of a participatory community devel-
opment approach that actively engaged seniors in providing 
peer-led osteoporosis education and mentoring within 
a naturally occurring retirement community (NORC) in 
Ontario, Canada. Findings are reported in accordance with 
the Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) 
checklist for the reporting of pragmatic trials. </p>

<p>25   study context </p>

<p>This study consisted of two phases: 1) the recruitment and 
training of 10 osteoporosis peer educators and mentors to 
deliver the intervention and 2) an RCT to test the efficacy of 
the peer-led community osteoporosis education and mentor-
ing program. Participants were recruited from a NORC in 
a major urban center in Ontario. This community consists 
of 12 privately owned apartment buildings housing over 
2,500 seniors (mean age =79, standard deviation [SD] =9.53) 
and 64 local businesses housed in a public mall adjacent to the 
apartment buildings. A previous survey showed that 54% of 
the population in this community were .80 years of age. </p>

<p>Training of peer educators/mentors to deliver the 
intervention </p>

<p>A town hall meeting was held to inform the community of the 
osteoporosis study, the need for peer educators and mentors, </p>

<p>and the role that they would have to perform. Community 
members interested in the project were invited to establish 
contact. No specific inclusion or exclusion criteria were 
applied. After providing informed consent, 10 participants, all 
female, aged from 74 to 90 years, committed to becoming peer 
educators and mentors and entered Phase I of the study. All 10 
peer educators/mentors participated in the education program 
presented over a 2-week period, after which four withdrew 
(two due to health issues, one due to family obligations, and 
one due to time constraints). The education program for peer 
educators/mentors consisted of five osteoporosis education 
modules presented at the level of a lay person and delivered 
by local experts. A detailed description of the education 
modules, including objectives, curriculum, and instructors, 
is provided in Table 1. Each education session was 1 hour in 
length followed by a question and answer period. 
In addition, peer educators/mentors attended an educa-
tion session focused on enhancing public presentation skills. 
This presentation was delivered by the project coordinator 
and focused on 1) confidently speaking in front of audiences, 
2) effectively eliciting audience interest, participation, and 
feedback, 3) beginning your presentation, 4) delivering your 
presentation (encouraging audience involvement, keys to 
developing good listening skills, speaker's nonverbal com-
munication, how to handle difficult situations), 5) concluding 
your presentation, and 6) key attributes of a senior-friendly 
presentation. Consistent with principles of community 
capacity building, once trained these peer educators/mentors 
formed the Community Osteoporosis Advisory Committee. 
Peer educators/mentors, as a group, took the information they 
were provided within the five training modules and, with the 
help of the research team, synthesized and repackaged the 
information in a way they felt comfortable presenting. This 
was an iterative process between the peer educators/mentors 
and the research team that took place over the course of 
2 weeks. Once peer educators/mentors were comfortable, the 
repackaged material was presented to the local osteoporosis 
experts to check for clarity and accuracy. </p>

<p>The intervention </p>

<p>For the RCT, the intervention involved a 2-hour education 
program delivered to small groups of participants by pairs 
of peer educators/mentors (for mutual support), using the 
educational materials they had developed. The first hour 
consisted of the peer-led osteoporosis education program 
where participants learned about osteoporosis, assessment, 
and treatment using the repackaged presentation of the 
five education modules. During the second hour, each peer </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>825 </p>

<p>Improving the diagnosis and treatment of osteoporosis </p>

<p>Table 1 Description of the education modules, including objectives, curriculum, and instructors </p>

<p>Module </p>

<p>Instructor </p>

<p>Objectives </p>

<p>(upon completion of this session participants will be able to) </p>

<p>Curriculum </p>

<p>(topics included) </p>

<p>1. What is </p>

<p>osteoporosis? </p>

<p>geriatrician 
Answer the question "what is osteoporosis?"; recognize causes of bone loss; discuss the 
relationship between osteoporosis and fractures and the consequences of osteoporotic 
fractures in terms of one's health and quality of life; assess their own, and others', risk of 
osteoporosis; outline action plans for individuals at varying levels of osteoporosis risk (ie, 
suggestions for successful patient-physician interactions); understand the medical assessments </p>

<p>used to diagnose osteoporosis, who should be assessed, and what to expect during a BMD or 
heel ultrasound </p>

<p>1) What is osteoporosis?; 2) bone formation and bone 
loss; 3) osteoporosis and fractures; assessing your 
osteoporosis risk factors; 4) action plans for individuals </p>

<p>at risk of osteoporosis; 5) diagnosing osteoporosis: what 
to expect </p>

<p>2. Physical activity and </p>

<p>osteoporosis </p>

<p>Physiotherapist 
explain how physical activity affects bone mass (at the level of a lay person); provide practical 
examples of weight-bearing and resistance exercises; highlight the exercise precautions that 
should be taken by individuals with osteoporosis </p>

<p>1) effect of physical activities on bone health; 2) exercise 
precautions for people with osteoporosis; 3) practical 
examples of weight-bearing and resistance exercises; 4) 
maintaining good posture to protect your back </p>

<p>3. Drug therapies 
for the treatment 
and prevention of 
osteoporosis </p>

<p>endocrinologist 
Understand how drug therapies work (at the level of a lay person); provide a brief overview </p>

<p>of the primary classes and brands of drug therapies used to prevent and treat osteoporosis 
(at the level of a lay person); emphasize the significant increase in the incidence of male 
osteoporosis </p>

<p>1) how drug therapies work; 2) common osteoporosis 
medications; 3) what about male osteoporosis?; 4) how </p>

<p>long should I continue taking my medication? </p>

<p>4. nutrition and </p>

<p>osteoporosis </p>

<p>registered 
dietician 
explain the role of calcium and vitamin D in preventing and treating osteoporosis; inform their 
peers of their required amount of daily calcium; recommend methods of maximizing dietary 
calcium intake; understand the role of calcium and vitamin D supplements in preventing and 
treating osteoporosis, when calcium and vitamin D intake should be supplemented, how to 
choose and how to take a supplement </p>

<p>1) Calcium is essential for healthy bones; 2) using diet to 
maximize your daily calcium intake; 3) vitamin D's role in 
preventing osteoporosis; 4) when you cannot get enough 
calcium and vitamin D from your diet </p>

<p>5. living with 
osteoporosis and 
protecting your back </p>

<p>Occupational </p>

<p>therapist 
Discuss the physical consequences and challenges of living with osteoporosis; provide 
practical suggestions to effectively practice safe movements, complete household chores 
safely, and eliminate fall hazards in one's home; provide contact information for Osteoporosis 
Canada. </p>

<p>1) Physical consequences of living with osteoporosis; 2) 
protecting your bones; 3) how to move safely; 4) how </p>

<p>to safely complete your household activities; 5) eliminate 
fall hazards from your home. </p>

<p>Abbreviation: BMD, bone mineral density. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>826 </p>

<p>Kloseck et al </p>

<p>educator/mentor was assigned up to nine participants to 
mentor. A risk assessment tool and action plan was designed 
to facilitate participants' discussions with their family physi-
cian (Figure 1). Peer educators/mentors worked one-on-one 
with their assigned participants to complete Part 1 of the tool 
(Figure 1) that included questions about past fractures, family 
history, drug use, and other factors known to increase risk 
of fractures. These risk factors were consistent with those 
outlined in the Canadian guidelines for the diagnosis and 
management of osteoporosis at the time of the study. </p>

<p>26   Participants who had not had a BMD assessment done 
were requested to arrange an appointment with their family 
physician to request a BMD assessment. If, and when, this 
was obtained, and for those who already had a BMD assess-
ment done but had not discussed results with their physician, 
a further appointment with their physician was advised to 
discuss the results. 
During this visit, the physician was presented with Part 1 
of the risk assessment and action plan tool (Figure 1) and 
was requested to complete Part 2. If the physician did not 
complete the risk tool and therefore did not provide the BMD 
result, the participant subsequently requested, via a release 
of information form, that the BMD result be faxed to one 
of the study physicians (RC). Each participant was tutored 
by their peer educator/mentor on the questions to ask their 
family physician, the information they should obtain, and to 
discuss appropriate management based on the information 
recorded on their risk assessment tool. The objective of the 
RCT was to test whether a participatory community devel-
opment approach that actively engages seniors in providing 
peer-led osteoporosis education and mentoring could be used 
to improve the diagnosis and management of osteoporosis. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>The study reported in this paper involved a pragmatic two-arm 
RCT conducted over a 2-year period from 2007 to 2009. 
To ensure the study was as inclusive as possible, indi-
viduals were eligible to participate if they were $65 years of 
age and lived within the NORC. Recruitment was confined 
to English speaking individuals. Potential participants were 
recruited by the peer educators/mentors using a number 
of strategies: word-of-mouth, notices posted in the public 
shopping mall and in the mail and laundry rooms of the 
12 apartment buildings, a mall table display, and advertising 
on the internal community television channel. Potential 
participants identified by the peer educators/mentors were 
provided with an information package containing a letter of 
information about the study, a consent form, and a baseline </p>

<p>demographic, risk and knowledge questionnaire (further 
details below). The peer educators/mentors provided potential 
participants with assistance in completing the forms if it was 
required. Informed consent was obtained from each partici-
pant. The study coordinator reviewed all completed consent 
forms and questionnaires for completeness prior to enrolling 
and randomizing the participants to the peer-led education 
program (n=53) or to a control group (n=52). Participants 
were randomized using the sequentially numbered, opaque 
sealed envelope method of randomization and allocation con-
cealment. 
27 Three education sessions for 14 participants and 
one final session for up to 12 participants were planned. To 
maintain balanced allocation throughout recruitment, a batch 
approach was used. One batch of 28 envelopes (14 for the 
intervention and 14 for the control) was created by the study 
coordinator and used for the first 28 participants enrolled. 
A second batch of 28 envelopes was used for the second wave 
of participants recruited, a third batch of 28 for the third wave, 
and fourth batch of 22 for the final wave (recognizing that 
one of the allocation envelopes would not be required for a 
sample of 105 participants). It was not possible to blind the 
involved parties to their allocation due to the nature of the 
intervention and the study design. 
The knowledge questionnaire (provided as Supplementary 
material) included multiple choice and true or false questions 
related to the five key content areas to be covered by the 
education modules: what is osteoporosis; physical activity 
and bone health; drug therapies for the prevention and 
treatment of osteoporosis; nutrition and bone health; and 
living with osteoporosis and protecting your bones. The risk 
questionnaire was derived by the research team based on a 
review of published material. The knowledge questionnaire 
was developed by the research team based on the information 
being delivered in the education modules and subsequently 
reviewed for face validity by the osteoporosis content experts. 
The knowledge questionnaire is assumed to have face and 
content validity as the questionnaire and the correct responses 
are based on up-to-date expert knowledge reflecting recent 
guidelines and clinician expertise. The knowledge question-
naire was self-administered and scored by the research coor-
dinator. Test scores were calculated by summing the correct 
number of responses minus the incorrect responses. To ensure 
that all scores were positive values, 25 was added to each 
score for a maximum possible score of 44 points. Participants 
allocated to the control group received usual care, that is, 
the care which would normally be provided without this 
intervention, while the intervention group attended a peer-led </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>827 </p>

<p>Improving the diagnosis and treatment of osteoporosis </p>

<p>Figure 1 risk assessment and action plan tool. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>828 </p>

<p>Kloseck et al </p>

<p>osteoporosis education session followed by a 6-month 
personalized peer mentoring period which involved risk 
assessment, encouraging participants to visit their family 
physician, and encouraging compliance with physician rec-
ommendations. Following completion of the intervention, 
all trial participants in both intervention and control groups 
completed a second knowledge questionnaire. </p>

<p>Data collection </p>

<p>The planned sources of data collection were: 
1. Participant submitted data: demographic, risk, and 
knowledge information were provided by all participants 
upon recruitment to the study. 
Given the tightly-knit composition of this com-
munity, potential contamination of the control group 
was considered to be a significant risk. To determine 
whether information from the study had an impact upon 
the control group participants, this cohort was asked to 
complete a questionnaire at the end of the study to deter-
mine whether their behavior or knowledge had changed 
during the course of the study by assessing whether they 
had sought out their own information about osteoporosis 
and BMD testing from their family or friends, had started 
taking calcium or vitamin D supplements, had started 
exercising, or had spoken to their friends or neighbors 
about osteoporosis. 
2. Peer educator/mentor collected data: the peer educator/ 
mentor provided their mentees with carbonless duplicate 
forms (Figure 1) asking participants to confirm their 
age, whether they had undertaken a BMD assessment 
in the past 5 years, and whether they had any of eight 
osteoporosis risk factors prior to the participant schedul-
ing an appointment with their physician. Following the 
appointment and BMD assessment, participants were 
instructed to complete the second half of the duplicate 
form with their doctor. In their next meeting, the peer 
educator/mentor reviewed the BMD scores; whether or 
not the participant was at high risk of fracture; what, 
if any, treatment the participant was recommended by 
their physician; what, if any, changes to the participants 
diet had been recommended by their physician; whether 
calcium or vitamin D supplements had been recom-
mended, and at what dosage; what, if any, lifestyle 
changes had been recommended; and whether a BMD 
assessment should be undertaken again in the future, 
and if so, when. Top copies of the duplicate form were 
handed back to the participant, and the lower copy was </p>

<p>retained by the peer advisor and returned to the study 
coordinator. 
On completing their intervention, the peer educator/ 
mentor also asked members of the intervention group to 
complete a second self-administered risk and knowledge 
information questionnaire. </p>

<p>sample size </p>

<p>The initial RCT sample size calculation was based on 
achieving a significant improvement in the proportion of 
participants obtaining a BMD test, reviewing the results and 
their fracture risk profile with their family physician, and 
obtaining advice on treatment, if necessary. It was assumed 
that ~30% would have had a BMD assessment done and have 
had appropriate follow-up at the start of the study and 40% 
of the control group may have achieved this by the end of 
the study, with an increase in the intervention group to about 
75%. Without any idea of what to expect for the composite 
outcome, this seemed both a feasible and clinically mean-
ingful expectation. Using the Kelsey method, the effect size 
would be 0.725 with a total of 32 participants in each group 
to have 80% power at the 5% level of significance. Using 
the Fleiss method with continuity correction gives a required 
sample size of 36 per group to have 80% power at the 5% 
level of significance. Given the often frail nature of older 
subjects, and the potential for loss to follow-up for various 
reasons in people of this age, the overall recruitment target 
was increased to 100. On review of the first cohort recruited, 
the recruitment target was revised to 105 participants as 
further protection against potential loss to follow-up and to 
ensure adequate power of the study. 
Targeted recruitment by the peer educators/mentors 
ensured that all potential participants met the eligibil-
ity criteria, and recruitment was completed within a 
6-month period. </p>

<p>Follow-up </p>

<p>Peer educators/mentors conducted formal follow-up mentoring 
sessions with intervention group participants monthly and 
more frequently informally as required. This was face-to-face 
or by telephone and aimed to encourage compliance with 
medication and lifestyle recommendations and to problem 
solve any barriers to compliance. Data were collected on an 
ongoing basis, as participants reached the goals. There were 
no specific time points beyond the 6-month termination time, 
as each participant's trajectory was different. Follow-up with 
the control group took place at the 6-month point. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>829 </p>

<p>Improving the diagnosis and treatment of osteoporosis </p>

<p>Outcome measures </p>

<p>Two outcome measures were identified and analyzed: 
1. At the 6-month follow-up, the proportion of participants 
making a change in behavior related to their osteoporosis 
risk (obtaining a BMD assessment; returning to their 
family physician to review their risk profile and to obtain 
BMD results; and receiving treatment recommendations 
including calcium, vitamin D, and osteoporosis medica-
tion). For this study, appropriateness of the recommen-
dation is not reported as the focus was on completion of 
the process and not to evaluate the knowledge base of 
the physicians. All components had to be met to achieve 
what was a composite outcome. Each participant could 
have been at different points in the outcome achievement 
at the start of the study. For example, a participant could 
have had a BMD done already but have had no follow-up 
with their family physician. The BMD had to have been 
done within the previous 2 years. All three of the com-
posite outcomes had to be achieved to meet the endpoint. 
Participants already on osteoporosis medication were not 
specifically excluded on the basis that treatment did not 
necessarily mean that the other outcomes (such as BMD 
and fracture risk assessment) had been completed. 
2. The improvement in participants' knowledge related to 
osteoporosis, including physical activity, drug thera-
pies for the prevention and treatment of osteoporosis 
and nutrition. </p>

<p>Analysis </p>

<p>The between-groups difference in the proportion of partici-
pants making a change in behavior related to their osteo-
porosis risk was analyzed using the odds ratio and 95% 
confidence interval (CI). The between-group difference in 
knowledge change score was analyzed using an independent 
group t-test and 95% CI of the difference score. McNemar's 
chi-square was used to analyze the change from baseline 
to follow-up in the proportion of the treatment group with 
adequate vitamin D intake. Study outcomes were analyzed 
on a per protocol basis. All analyses were conducted using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">OpenEpi</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.03a</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">www.openepi.com</rs>). </p>

<p>ethics </p>

<p>Ethical approval was obtained from The University of 
Western Ontario Research Ethics Board for Health Sciences 
Research Involving Human Subjects, organized and 
operating according to the Tri-Council Policy Statement 
on the Ethical Conduct of Research Involving Humans and </p>

<p>the Health Canada International Conference on Harmoni-
zation Good Clinical Practices Consolidated Guidelines 
(reference 12835E). </p>

<p>Results 
recruitment </p>

<p>The CONSORT 
25 flow chart for the trial is shown in Figure 2. 
In all, 105 participants were recruited, enrolled, and random-
ized within the study period. 
The mean age of participants was 80.5 years (SD =6.9) 
and the majority (88.6%) were female. Characteristics of the 
intervention and control groups are presented in Table 2. The 
groups were well-balanced on several factors including age, 
gender, medication, and vitamin/mineral use, although the 
control group had more fractures than the intervention group 
and had already had more BMD tests performed. Surpris-
ingly, 61% of participants had already had a BMD assessment 
performed but of these, only 22% knew what the result was 
and had discussed the results with their family physician. 
Of the 105 participants, nine subjects from each group 
were lost to follow-up or chose not to complete the inter-
vention (Figure 2). From the control group, two subjects 
declined to participate post-survey. Additionally, follow-up 
was incomplete for five participants in the control group and 
three in the intervention group. Three participants moved 
out of the community, one from the control and two from 
the intervention group. Within the intervention group, four 
participants withdrew from the study, one as a result of a 
fractured hip. One participant in the control group died prior 
to completing the follow-up. </p>

<p>Achievement of outcomes </p>

<p>Outcome 1: change in osteoporosis behavior </p>

<p>Compared with 30 (73%) of the intervention group, only 
13 (30%) of the control group achieved a successful out-
come (defined as obtaining a BMD assessment; returning 
to their family physician to review their risk profile and to 
obtain BMD results; receiving treatment recommendations) 
with regard to their osteoporosis behavior (χ 
2 [1] =10.84, 
P,0.001) (Table 3). 
There was an increase in the number of the intervention 
group taking adequate vitamin D (800 IU/day) as defined by 
the Osteoporosis Canada Guidelines. 
26 The dose was checked 
by the peer educator/mentor reviewing the actual medication 
being consumed. Table 4 shows the change in adequacy of 
vitamin D intake in the intervention group. There was an 
improvement in the number of subjects taking an adequate </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>830 </p>

<p>Kloseck et al </p>

<p>dose of vitamin D (at least 800 IU/day) from 24.4% to 46.3% 
at follow-up (McNemar's chi-square P=0.02). As the same 
level of certainty could not be assured for the control group, a 
similar analysis is not possible. However, there was a change 
in the behavior of the control group in that 31 (73%) reported 
starting taking vitamin D supplements although the dosage 
could not be verified. </p>

<p>Outcome 2: change in osteoporosis knowledge </p>

<p>There was minimal improvement in knowledge in the inter-
vention group (Table 3) and a minimal decline in the control 
group at the end of the 6-month intervention for a net between-
group change of 1.3 points (95% CI of difference -0.76 to 
3.36). This difference was not statistically significant. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, providing peer-led instruction, support, 
and guidance had a beneficial effect. Peer mentoring was </p>

<p>successful in increasing the participant's willingness to 
approach the family physician to review their risk and treat-
ment. It may be that the provision of the "cue" card (risk 
assessment tool) containing the relevant information, rather 
than expecting the patient to remember the salient informa-
tion when face-to-face with the family doctor, made the 
appointment discussion both easier and more productive. 
There was no statistically significant change in the 
participants' knowledge of osteoporosis prevention and 
management suggesting that change in knowledge was 
not the driving force behind the change in behavior. This 
observation raises doubts about the feasibility of using an 
awareness or educational model to change behavior and it 
does question the value of such an approach alone in the 
attempt to improve self-management of chronic condi-
tions. Although the self-management model has gained 
widespread popularity, numerous limitations with this 
approach, particularly for frailer, older individuals, have </p>

<p>• 
• </p>

<p>• 
• 
• </p>

<p>• </p>

<p>• 
• </p>

<p>• 
• 
• </p>

<p>• 
• </p>

<p>• 
• 
• 
• </p>

<p>Figure 2 Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials 2010 flow diagram. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>831 </p>

<p>Improving the diagnosis and treatment of osteoporosis </p>

<p>been identified. 
11,28-30 In particular, the short-term focus of 
current education programs and the difficulty in maintaining 
positive change after program completion when supportive 
resources are no longer available have been identified as 
major shortcomings. 
28 This approach, using peer educators 
and mentors, does however present some challenges as the 
pool of volunteers needs replenishment given the age, and 
sometimes the level of frailty, of senior peer leaders. </p>

<p>Green and Kreuter's 
31 model of health promotion outlines 
enabling factors (conditions and resources that allow or 
enable behavior change) and reinforcing factors (those that 
cue, remind, or reinforce behavior change), which are critical 
to facilitating changes in health-related behaviors. In this 
intervention, the peer mentorship component along with the 
risk assessment and action form served as the enabling and 
reinforcing factors that improved participants' behaviors 
targeted at osteoporosis assessment, prevention, and manage-
ment. It is well-documented in the literature that education 
programs for health professionals that incorporate enabling 
and reinforcing factors are more effective in creating behavior 
change than those only aimed at disseminating informa-
tion and increasing knowledge. 
32-34 It is also possible that 
providing the family physician with the information, as well 
as a summary of the risk factors highlighted in the guidelines, 
facilitated their response. 
Pragmatic trials, undertaken in real-world settings, strive 
to provide evidence on the effectiveness of interventions 
within usual care settings to make their findings more gener-
alizable. The development and undertaking of these trials is 
recognized to be more complex, and the 2008 extension of the 
CONSORT guidelines 
25 addresses the consistent reporting of 
many of the issues associated with pragmatic trials. However, 
it would seem that there are additional issues to consider when 
conducting a trial within a community setting. It is for these 
reasons that it could be argued that community-based trials 
provide an inferior level of evidence. If researchers are aware 
of the risks associated with conducting community-based tri-
als, and if identified risks are appropriately addressed, these 
studies can provide high-quality evidence. For example, a 
recently published pragmatic pilot study 
35 on telehealth inter-
ventions in the UK identified problems with obtaining and 
maintaining care pathway fidelity. This issue was addressed 
by clinician education, clear messaging regarding the need 
to adhere to protocol, and vigilant analysis of care delivery 
to ensure that protocols were followed. </p>

<p>Table 2 Baseline characteristics of participants </p>

<p>Variables 
Intervention 
group (n=53) </p>

<p>Control 
group (n=52) </p>

<p>sociodemographic variables 
Female n (%) 
47 (88.7) 
46 (88.5) 
Mean age in years (sD) 
81 (6.9) 
80 (7.0) 
Marital status n (% married) 
11 (20.8) 
14 (26.9) 
level of education n 
(% postsecondary) </p>

<p>19 (35.8) 
21 (40.4) </p>

<p>risk assessment n (% yes) 
Previous fractures 
16 (30.2) 
23 (44.2) 
spine 
2 (3.8) 
3 (5.8) 
Wrist 
8 (13.2) 
15 (28.8) 
Upper arm 
3 (5.7) 
5 (9.6) 
hip 
3 (5.7) 
2 (3.8) 
Pelvis 
3 (5.7) 
3 (5.8) 
rib(s) 
6 (11.3) 
5 (9.6) 
Maternal hip fracture 
6 (11.3) 
4 (7.7) 
has become shorter with age 
32 (60.4) 
39 (75.0) 
has fallen in the past year 
23 (43.4) 
18 (34.6) 
has ever had a BMD completed 
28 (52.8) 
36 (69.2) 
Takes calcium supplements 
35 (66.0) 
36 (69.2) 
Takes vitamin D supplements 
36 (67.9) 
35 (67.3) 
Takes a multivitamin pill 
25 (47.2) 
28 (53.8) 
Prescription medication n (% yes) 
Osteoporosis medication use* 
13 (26.4) 
14 (28.8) 
Fosamax (alendronate) 
3 (5.7) 
8 (15.4) 
Actonel (risedronate) 
6 (11.3) 
5 (9.6) 
Didrocal (etidronate/calcium) 
3 (5.7) 
1 (1.9) 
evista (raloxifene) 
1 (1.9) 
1 (1.9) 
Miacalcin nasal spray (calcitonin) 0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
estrogen or hrT 
2 (3.8) 
1 (1.9) </p>

<p>Note: *some participants were on .1 medication. 
Abbreviations: sD, standard deviation; BMD, bone mineral density; hrT, hormone 
replacement therapy. </p>

<p>Table 3 Change in osteoporosis behavior and knowledge </p>

<p>Variables 
Intervention 
group (n=41) </p>

<p>Control 
group (n=43) </p>

<p>Odds ratio 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Mean difference*** 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Frequency of successful outcome* (outcome 1) n (% yes) 30 (73) 
13 (30) 
0.16 (0.06-0.42) 
,0.001 
Knowledge test (outcome 2) mean points** (sD) 
Baseline 
30.9 (5.3) 
31.9 (4.0) 
6-month follow-up 
31.8 (4.7) 
31.1 (4.7) 
Knowledge change score**** 
0.3 (4.7) 
-1.0 (4.8) 
1.3 (-0.76 to 3.36) 
0.21 </p>

<p>Notes: *Defined as obtaining a BMD assessment; returning to their family physician to review their risk profile and to obtain BMD results; receiving treatment 
recommendations. **Test scores were calculated by summing correct responses minus the incorrect responses and adding 25; maximum total score =44. ***Two-sample 
independent t-test of difference in knowledge change scores; t 82df =1.25. ****The baseline score is for all participants whereas the change score represents the participants 
who completed both tests. 
Abbreviations: SD, standard deviation; BMD, bone mineral density; CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>832 </p>

<p>Kloseck et al </p>

<p>For the current study, the selection of a NORC as the 
location ensured an adequate number of participants and 
peer mentors could be recruited perhaps more readily than 
in a standard community. However, the nature of this com-
munity posed a challenge to the researchers as a result of the 
proximity and frequent interaction between participants; so 
risk of contamination of the control group could hardly be 
avoided. While the risk of contamination of the control group 
could be seen as a methodological weakness, in reality it may 
have been an asset, as the control group also changed their 
behavior with regard to osteoporosis. This demonstrated the 
value of the informal networking and communications that 
the control group was exposed to, an important finding of 
the study that could have been lost if strict separation had 
been achieved. 
While the educational component of the intervention 
may have been inadequate to effect a change in knowledge 
in the intervention group, behavior change still took place. 
Furthermore, while the study did not attempt to educate the 
physicians directly, the present approach allowed seniors to 
approach the family physician armed with information that 
could effect a change in physician action. Consequently, it is 
possible that participant behavior change along with physi-
cian education initiatives may have proved more effective 
than either one alone. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Osteoporosis is undertreated and patients with, or at risk of, 
fractures are frequently not assessed, let alone treated when 
appropriate. 
5,8,36,37 The participatory community development 
initiative reported here may have the potential to reduce the 
osteoporosis care gap and, importantly, be applicable to 
improving management of other chronic conditions. There 
are many clusters of older adults living in high concentra-
tions in urban settings, and while these communities may 
sometimes challenge health care delivery, they are also an 
opportunity, appropriately developed, to manage significant 
health problems such as osteoporosis. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This article presents independent research funded by an unre-
stricted grant from the Alliance for Better Bone Health. The 
authors acknowledge the contributions of research assistants 
H Hanson and M van Zandvoort who assisted with subject 
recruitment and data collection. It is further acknowledged 
that the abstract for this paper was presented at the 31st 
Annual Meeting of the American Society for Bone and Min-
eral, and published online at http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/ 
doi/10.1002/jbmr.565 0241305/full (abstract MO0263). 
One of the authors of this paper (DAF) is supported by 
the National Institute for Health Research Collaboration 
for Leadership in Applied Health Research and Care for 
Yorkshire and The Humber (NIHR CLAHRC YH). The 
views and opinions expressed are those of the author, and 
not necessarily those of the National Health Service, the 
NIHR, or the Department of Health. CLAHRC YH would 
also like to acknowledge the participation and resources of 
partner organizations. Further details can be found at http:// 
clahrc-yh.nihr.ac.uk/. This trial was registered with Current 
Controlled Trials on September 11, 2013; registration number 
ISRCTN44810824. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>MK conceived of the study, participated in the design, coor-
dinated the conduct of the study, supervised the research 
assistants, participated in the data analysis and carried out 
revisions to the manuscript. DAF was responsible for the 
design, management and data analysis of the UK Tele-
health intervention study, and developed and finalized this 
manuscript. MS directed the design of the study, contributed 
towards data analysis and carried out revisions to the manu-
script. MYS contributed towards data analysis and provided 
critical revision of the paper. RGC assisted in the conception 
and design of the study, participated in the peer mentor's 
education, participated in the analysis and carried out revi-
sions to the manuscript. All authors read and approved the 
final manuscript and agree to be accountable for all aspects 
of the work. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Table 4 Adequacy of vitamin D intake in the intervention group </p>

<p>Follow-up </p>

<p>Adequate 
Inadequate/none 
n </p>

<p>Baseline 
Adequate 
7 
3 
10 
Inadequate/none 
12 
19 
31 
n 
19 
22 
41 </p>

<p>Note: There was an increase in the number of participants taking adequate vitamin D 
from 10/41 (24.4%) to 19/41 (46.3%) (Mcnemar's chi-square P=0.02). </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/clinical-interventions-in-aging-journal </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging is an international, peer-reviewed journal 
focusing on evidence-based reports on the value or lack thereof of treatments 
intended to prevent or delay the onset of maladaptive correlates of aging 
in human beings. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, MedLine, </p>

<p>CAS, Scopus and the Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The manuscript 
management system is completely online and includes a very quick and fair 
peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress. 
com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2017:12 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>833 </p>



</text></tei>