<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5084642" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: The aim of this study was to evaluate the association of mental 
well-being with outcomes among patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus 
(T2DM). Methods: Seven thousand eight hundred fifty-two adults with 
T2DM were identified from a national, Internet-based study. Mental well-
being [SF-36v2 mental component summary (MCS)] was categorized as good 
(MCS ! 50), poor (40 MCS &lt; 50), and very poor (MCS &lt; 40). Outcomes 
included past 6 months of health care resource use and lost productivity (Work 
Productivity and Activity Impairment questionnaire). Results: Respondents 
with very poor/poor versus good mental well-being were more likely to visit 
the emergency room (27%/18% vs 11%, P &lt; 0.001) or be hospitalized (19%/ 
14% vs 9%, P &lt; 0.001). Among labor force participants, those with very poor/ 
poor versus good mental well-being experienced greater overall work impair-
ment (43.7/26.0 vs 10.7, P &lt; 0.001). Conclusions: Greater resource use and 
work productivity impairment associated with poorer mental well-being 
among patients with T2DM has cost implications. </p>

<p>The MCS is normed to the general U.S. population. This is achieved 
by transforming the raw scores for the items to a mean of 50 and a 
standard deviation (SD) of 10. Higher scores indicate better mental 
well-being. The MCS scores were categorized on the basis of the 
mean and SD of the general population and distribution of the MCS 
score within the analytic sample. Final categories were as follows: 
good mental well-being (above the population mean; MCS ! 50), 
poor mental well-being ( 1 SD below the population mean; 40 
MCS &lt; 50), and very poor mental well-being (&gt;1 SD below the 
population mean; MCS &lt; 40). 
Consideration was given to defining the cutoff between poor 
and very poor mental well-being using a score of 35, which is a more 
traditional cutoff indicative of depression. However, a cutoff of 40 was 
a more conservative approach and yielded a more even distribution 
across categories. Sensitivity analyses were subsequently conducted 
using the more liberal cut-off of 35 and did not demonstrate sub-
stantial change in the results. In addition, the defined mental well-
being categories were further supported by their statistical association 
with other mental health indicators (eg, depression diagnosis or 
generalized anxiety disorder diagnosis). Those with very poor mental 
well-being reported more depression and anxiety diagnoses and </p>

<p>prescription history than those with poor or good mental well-being. 
Those with poor mental well-being reported more depression and 
anxiety diagnoses and prescription history than those with good 
mental well-being (see Table 1 in Appendix, Supplemental Digital 
Content 1, http://links.lww.com/JOM/A310). </p>

<p>Covariates: Demographics and Health Characteristics </p>

<p>The following demographic variables were examined for 
differences between mental well-being categories: age, gender, 
race/ethnicity, education, and household income. The following 
health characteristics were also examined: BMI, smoking status, 
and comorbidity burden, measured via the Charlson Comorbidity 
Index (CCI). 
30 In addition, diabetes-related characteristics were 
examined: history of hypoglycemia, diabetes-related complications, 
years since diagnosis, and current treatment. </p>

<p>Outcome Variables </p>

<p>Resource Use: Health care resource was measured for all 
respondents in the analytic sample for the past 6 months and 
included number of health care provider (HCP) visits, number of 
emergency room (ER) visits, and number of hospitalizations. </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Demographics and Health Characteristics for Patients With T2DM by Mental Well-Being Category </p>

<p>Mental Well-Being </p>

<p>Good (n ¼ 4,370) 
Poor (n ¼ 1,781) 
Very Poor (n ¼ 1,701) 
Omnibus P </p>

<p>Age, mean (SD) 
62.9 (10.8) 
57.6 (13.0) 
54.4 (13.0) 
&lt;0.001 
Female, % 
35.1 
39.6 
43.6 
&lt;0.001 
Race/ethnicity, % 
&lt;0.001 
White 
78.5 
72.2 
71.7 
Black 
11.6 
12.6 
11.9 
Hispanic 
4.5 
8.0 
8.9 
Other 
5.4 
7.2 
7.5 
Education (4-year degree or more), % 
40.8 
32.7 
28.0 
&lt;0.001 
Annual household income, % 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;$25,000 
14.9 
24.1 
34.3 
$25,000-$49,999 
28.1 
30.0 
29.0 
$50,000-$74,999 
22.5 
18.9 
17.3 
!$75,000 
27.9 
20.6 
15.3 
Declined to answer 
6.6 
6.4 
4.2 
Body mass index category, % 
&lt;0.001 
Underweight (&lt;18.5 kg/m 
2 ) 
0.3 
0.2 
0.8 
Normal (!18.5 kg/m 
2 and &lt;25.0 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
10.4 
9.9 
8.0 
Overweight (!25.0 kg/m 
2 and &lt;30.0 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
30.1 
24.8 
22.5 
Obese (!30.0 kg/m 
2 and &lt;40.0 kg/m 
2 ) 
44.9 
43.6 
43.0 
Morbidly obese (&gt;40.0 kg/m 
2 ) 
12.5 
19.3 
23.6 
Unknown 
1.8 
2.2 
2.1 
Smoking status, % 
&lt;0.001 
Current smoker 
12.3 
16.4 
24.1 
Former smoker 
47.3 
41.1 
35.6 
Never smoked 
40.4 
42.5 
40.3 
Charlson comorbidity index, mean (SD) 
1.59 (1.14) 
1.77 (1.30) 
1.99 (1.75) 
&lt;0.001 
Years diagnosed, mean (SD) 
11.3 (8.7) 
10.9 (8.4) 
9.7 (8.3) 
&lt;0.001 
Current T2D treatment, % 
&lt;0.001 
No treatment 
14.6 
16.3 
19.2 
1 noninsulin 
34.6 
31.6 
31.3 
2 noninsulin 
20.2 
17.3 
14.4 
3þ noninsulin 
7.9 
7.2 
5.5 
Insulin only 
6.8 
9.0 
8.8 
Insulin and noninsulin (s) 
15.8 
18.6 
20.8 
Experienced hypoglycemia, % 
47.3 
56.8 
58.1 
&lt;0.001 
Diagnosed with diabetes complications, % 
Foot or leg ulcer 
2.8 
5.4 
5.7 
&lt;0.001 
Kidney disease 
3.6 
5.3 
5.3 
&lt;0.001 
Macular edema/diabetic retinopathy 
3.9 
5.9 
6.4 
&lt;0.001 
Neuropathic pain 
16.7 
26.1 
30.7 
&lt;0.001 
End-stage organ damage 
0.6 
1.2 
2.2 
&lt;0.001 
None of the above complications 
78.1 
68.6 
64.1 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Bolge et al 
JOEM Volume 58, Number 11, November 2016 </p>

<p> 
ß 2016 American College of Occupational and Environmental Medicine </p>

<p>Labor Force Participation and Work Productivity Loss: Labor 
force participation (employed full time, employed part-time, or self-
employed) was examined via a single item. Work productivity loss 
and activity impairment were measured using the Work Productivity 
and Activity Impairment-General Health questionnaire (WPAI-
GH). 
31 The WPAI measures the percentage work loss due to 
absenteeism (time missed from work), presenteeism (lost pro-
ductivity while at work), and overall work impairment (absenteeism 
and presenteeism) for those respondents currently in the labor force. 
It also measures the percentage of activity impairment for all 
respondents in the analytic sample. </p>

<p>Statistical Analyses </p>

<p>Demographics, health characteristics, and outcomes differ-
ences were examined for the three mental well-being groups. For 
continuous variables, means and SDs were reported and one-way 
analysis of variances (ANOVAs) were used to determine statistical 
significance. For categorical variables, frequencies and percentages 
were reported and Chi-square tests were used to determine 
statistical significance. 
Following initial comparisons, generalized linear models 
(GLMs) were used, which test whether the adjusted (accounting 
for covariates) relative counts of the outcomes differ among well-
being groups. Covariates included demographic and health charac-
teristics defined above. All analyses were carried out using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">20</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Demographics and Health Characteristics </p>

<p>The analytic sample consisted of 7852 respondents diagnosed 
with T2DM. Of these, 22% (n ¼ 1701) experienced very poor 
mental well-being, 23% (n ¼ 1781) poor mental well-being, and 
56% (n ¼ 4370) good mental well-being. 
Patients with very poor and poor mental well-being were 
more likely to be younger, female, Hispanic or other ethnicity, less 
educated, and had lower household income than those with good 
mental well-being. In addition, those with very poor mental well-
being were more likely to be younger, Hispanic or other ethnicity, 
less educated, and had lower income than those with poor mental 
well-being (see Table 1). 
Generally patients with very poor mental well-being had 
unhealthier health characteristics and more comorbidity burden than </p>

<p>those with poor mental well-being and good mental well-being. Those 
with poor mental well-being had unhealthier health characteristics and 
more comorbidity burden than those with good mental well-being. 
Specifically, patients with very poor mental well-being were more 
likely to be morbidly obese, more likely to smoke, and had higher CCI 
scores than those with poor mental well-being and good mental well-
being. In addition, those with poor mental well-being were more likely 
to be morbidly obese, current smokers, and had higher comorbidity 
burden than those with good mental well-being (see Table 1). 
A similar relationship was observed for diabetes-related 
complications and treatment. Patients with very poor mental 
well-being were more likely to experience diabetes-related com-
plications and to be treated with a combination of insulin and 
noninsulins than those with poor or good mental well-being. Among 
patients with very poor or poor mental well-being, there was a 
greater likelihood of experiencing hypoglycemia and diabetes-
related complications as well as to be treated with a combination 
of insulin and noninsulin(s) than among those with good mental 
well-being (see Table 1). </p>

<p>The Association of Mental Well-being With Health 
Care Resource Use and Work Productivity </p>

<p>Overall, patients with very poor mental well-being reported 
greater health care resource use than those with poor and good 
mental well-being as indicated by a greater number of doctor visits, 
ER visits, and hospitalizations in the past 6 months. Also, those with 
poor mental well-being reported higher resource use than those with 
good mental well-being (see Table 2). These results held after 
controlling for covariates for resource use (Covariates included 
age, gender, ethnicity, income, education, smoking status, BMI, 
CCI, years since diagnosis, diabetes-related complications, hypo-
glycemia status, and current treatment.) Those with very poor 
mental well-being reported more resource use than those with good 
well-being and more HCP and ER visits than those with poor mental 
well-being. Those with poor mental well-being reported more 
resource use than those with good mental well-being (see 
Table 3; individual regression tables located in Appendix: doctor 
visits-see Tables 6a and 6b, ER visits-see Tables 7a and 7b, and 
hospitalizations-see Tables 8a and 8b, Supplemental Digital Con-
tent 1, http://links.lww.com/JOM/A310). 
For the whole sample, activity impairment was measured. 
Those with very poor and poor mental well-being had higher 
activity impairment than those with good mental well-being. Those </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Health Care Resource Use, Labor Force Participation, and Work Productivity Loss for Patients With T2DM by Mental 
Well-Being Category </p>

<p>Mental Well-Being </p>

<p>Good (n ¼ 4,370) 
Poor (n ¼ 1,781) 
Very Poor (n ¼ 1,701) 
Total </p>

<p>One-Way ANOVA P 
Mean (SD) 
Mean (SD) 
Mean (SD) 
Mean (SD) </p>

<p>Resource use (number of visits in the past 6 months) 
Traditional health care provider 
5.20 a (5.30) 
6.25 b (7.16) 
8.06 c (10.44) 
6.06 (7.22) 
&lt;0.001 
Emergency room 
0.16 a (0.64) 
0.33 b (1.21) 
0.54 c (1.35) 
0.28 (0.99) 
&lt;0.001 
Hospitalizations 
0.12 a (0.57) 
0.24 b (1.31) 
0.35 c (1.04) 
0.19 (0.90) 
&lt;0.001 
Work productivity and activity impairment 
Activity impairment 
21.96 a (26.54) 
40.39 b (29.60) 
60.23 c (28.56) 
34.43 (31.72) 
&lt;0.001 
Currently in labor force % 
35.1% a 
40.5% b 
30.9% c 
35.4% 
&lt;0.001 
Overall work impairment </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>10.66 a (20.17) 
26.05 b (27.66) 
43.68 c (32.31) 
20.80 (27.92) 
&lt;0.001 
Absenteeism </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>2.62 a (12.34) 
5.33 b (16.66) 
10.74 c (22.11) 
4.84 (16.02) 
&lt;0.001 
Presenteeism </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>8.79 a (16.77) 
23.16 b (24.61) 
40.14 c (30.11) 
18.31 (25.01) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Values in the same row and subtable not sharing the same subscript are significantly different at P &lt; 0.05. 
ANOVA, analysis of variance. </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>Asked only of the employed sample: Good mental well-being (N ¼ 1,466), Poor mental well-being (N ¼ 682), Very poor mental well-being (N ¼ 493). </p>

<p>JOEM Volume 58, Number 11, November 2016 
Poor Mental Well-being in T2DM </p>

<p>ß 2016 American College of Occupational and Environmental Medicine </p>

<p>
with poor mental well-being had greater activity impairment than 
those with good mental well-being (see Table 2). Presenteeism, 
absenteeism, and overall work impairment were asked only of those 
participating in the labor force. Overall, approximately one-third of 
patients with T2DM were participating in the labor force. Patients 
with very poor mental well-being were less likely to participate in 
the labor force than those with poor mental well-being and good 
mental well-being. In addition, those with poor mental well-being 
were more likely to participate in the work force than those with 
good mental well-being (see Table 2). Those with very poor mental 
well-being had higher presenteeism, absenteeism, and overall work 
impairment than those with poor and good mental well-being. 
Likewise, those with poor mental well-being had higher presentee-
ism, absenteeism, and overall work impairment than those with 
good mental well-being. Controlling for potential confounders, the 
findings were consistent with the unadjusted comparisons (Cova-
riates included age, gender, ethnicity, income, education, smoking 
status, BMI, CCI, years since diagnosis, diabetes related compli-
cations, hypoglycemia status, and current treatment.) Those with 
very poor mental well-being reported more work and activity 
impairment than those with poor and good mental well-being. 
Similarly, those with poor mental well-being reported more activity 
and work impairment than those with good mental well-being 
(see Table 3; individual regression tables located in Appendix: 
absenteeism-see Tables 2a and 2b, presenteeism-see Tables 3a 
and 3b, overall work impairment-see Tables 4a and 4b, and 
activity impairment-see Tables 5a and 5b, Supplemental Digital 
Content 1, http://links.lww.com/JOM/A310). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Patients with T2DM and very poor or poor mental well-being 
were more likely to be younger, female, nonwhite, less educated, 
and have lower income than patients with T2DM and good mental 
well-being. The demographic groups associated with poor and very 
poor mental well-being tend to be consistent with previous liter-
ature. Typically, women and younger populations have a greater 
prevalence of anxiety and depression. 
32,33 The pattern is a little bit 
less clear when it comes to ethnicity and well-being, as it is difficult 
to disentangle the relationship between socioeconomic status and 
ethnicity. Previous research has found a strong relationship between 
ethnicity/socioeconomic status and health disparities that can often 
be attributed to differences in health behaviors, cultural factors, and 
access to treatment. 
34-38 In addition, a previous study looked at </p>

<p>overall NHWS data and results showed that whites had higher 
mental well-being, measured by MCS scores, than ethnic minority 
groups, which is consistent with the results from the current study. </p>

<p>39   However, once demographic factors such as income were controlled 
for in the previous study, the differences between ethnic groups and 
well-being were not as clear. Given certain groups are at a greater 
risk for poor and very poor mental well-being, it is important to note 
as they may benefit from intervention. 
The burden of poor and very poor mental well-being among 
patients with T2DM was demonstrated for all examined outcome 
variables. Even after adjusting for differences in social, health, and 
disease status, patients with poor and very poor mental well-being 
reported a greater number of health care practitioner visits, emer-
gency room visits, and hospitalizations than patients with good 
mental well-being. Patients with very poor mental well-being also 
experienced the lowest work force participation. Interestingly, those 
with poor mental well-being experienced higher work force 
participation than those with good mental well-being. Demographic 
and socioeconomic characteristics may contribute to this difference. 
Those with good mental well-being were older, on average, than 
those with poor and very poor mental well-being. Older individuals 
have a higher likelihood of being retired from the workforce 
regardless of mental well-being status. In addition, those with poor 
mental well-being had lower educational levels and lower annual 
household incomes than those with good mental well-being. Those 
with poor mental well-being may have to work to survive finan-
cially, necessitating greater workforce participation. Those with 
very poor mental well-being have the lowest annual household 
income levels and the lowest levels of workforce participation. 
Regardless of financial need, those with very poor mental well-
being may simply be unable to work or may be eligible for disability 
benefits to survive financially. Those with poor and very poor 
mental well-being who participated in the labor force experienced 
greater work productivity loss including greater absenteeism and 
presenteeism than those with good mental well-being. Displaying 
the greatest burden, patients with very poor mental well-being, who 
participated in the workforce, experienced even greater health care 
resource use and more pronounced work productivity loss than 
patients with poor mental well-being. 
The study corroborates previous research by demonstrating 
that mental health has a substantial impact on health care resource 
use and work productivity among T2DM patients. Although we 
would expect this pattern to be consistent among those with T2DM, </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Health Care Resource Use and Work Productivity Loss for Patients With T2DM by Mental Well-Being Category 
Controlling for Confounders </p>

<p>Mental Well-Being </p>

<p>Good (n ¼ 4,370) 
Poor (n ¼ 1,781) 
Very Poor (n ¼ 1,701) </p>

<p>Estimated Mean (SE) 
Estimated Mean (SE) 
Estimated Mean (SE) </p>

<p>Resource use (number of visits in the past 6 months) 
Traditional health care provider 
5.09 a (0.09) 
5.81 b (0.15) 
7.33 c (0.19) 
Emergency room 
0.16 a (0.01) 
0.25 b (0.02) 
0.35 c (0.03) 
Hospitalizations 
0.11 a (0.01) 
0.19 b (0.02) 
0.24 b (0.02) 
Work productivity and activity impairment 
Activity impairment 
21.32 a (0.34) 
37.21 b (0.91) 
54.36 c (1.40) 
Overall work Impairment </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>10.31 a (0.44) 
23.02 b (1.42) 
37.86 c (2.79) 
Absenteeism </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>1.92 a (0.24) 
4.08 b (0.74) 
10.05 c (2.14) 
Presenteeism </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>8.49 a (0.37) 
20.68 b (1.31) 
34.32 c (2.60) </p>

<p>Values in the same row and subtable not sharing the same subscript are significantly different at P &lt; 0.05. Covariates included age, gender, ethnicity, income, education, smoking 
status, BMI, CCI, years since diagnosis, diabetes-related complications, hypoglycemia status, and current treatment. 
SE, standard error. </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>Asked only of the employed sample: Good mental well-being (N ¼ 1,466), Poor mental well-being (N ¼ 682), Very poor mental well-being (N ¼ 493). </p>

<p>Bolge et al 
JOEM Volume 58, Number 11, November 2016 </p>

<p> 
ß 2016 American College of Occupational and Environmental Medicine </p>

<p>given the substantial burden already associated with T2DM, having 
poor and very poor mental well-being could exacerbate the negative 
effects. In particular, prior studies showed that patients with T2DM 
and depression had greater outpatient costs as well as a greater 
probability of having primary care, specialty care, inpatient care, 
emergency room visitation, and hospitalizations than patients with 
T2DM and no depression. 
5,23,40,41 Prior studies also showed that 
patients with T2DM and depression had greater odds of functional 
disability, 
18,21,22,42 and were more likely to miss at least 7 workdays 
in a given year, 
22 compared with patients with T2DM but no 
depression. It is important to note that 40.5% of those with poor 
and 30.9% of those with very poor mental well-being were actively 
participating in the labor force. It is very possible that the negative 
impact that mental well-being had on workplace performance may 
extend beyond what has been measured in this study. For instance, 
we are not capturing details about the circumstances of those not 
currently in the labor force. 
As T2DM is a major driver of health care and indirect costs, </p>

<p>2   these findings suggest that poor and very poor mental well-being 
among patients with T2DM is a major economic burden. The greater 
use of health care resources found in patients with poor and very poor 
mental well-being indicates greater direct costs for patients and 
payers, including self-insured employers. To put the cost burden into 
perspective, an average hospitalization in the U.S. costs $18,012. </p>

<p>43   Those with poor mental well-being had 0.70 hospitalizations (unad-
justed) annually that equates to $12,608 in annual hospitalization 
costs, that is, an increase of approximately $8286 in annual costs 
attributable to hospitalizations per patient with very poor mental well-
being compared with a patient with good mental well-being and an 
additional $3962 compared with a patient with poor mental well-
being. Considering that nearly half of patients with T2DM can be 
categorized as experiencing either very poor or poor mental well-
being, direct health care costs for resource utilization are substantial. 
To put the burden of lost work productivity in perspective, the median 
individual weekly salary in the U.S. is $768, 
44 which amounts to 
$39,936 annually assuming 52 work-weeks a year. Given those with 
very poor mental well-being report roughly 10.7% absenteeism 
(unadjusted), the amount attributable to lost wages due to missing 
work is $4273 annually. Those with very poor mental well-being have 
$3227 greater annual costs attributable to absenteeism than those with 
good mental well-being and $2144 greater absenteeism costs than 
those with poor mental well-being. Indirect costs associated with the 
greater presenteeism associated with very poor and poor mental well-
being will add to the economic burden on employers. 
Notably, the current study finds that, while patients with 
T2DM who were classified as having poor mental health (MCS of 
40 to 50) may not necessarily meet criteria for diagnoses of 
depression, anxiety, or other psychiatric conditions, they have 
significantly greater health care resource use and experience sig-
nificantly more work impairment than those with good mental well-
being. As patients who were classified as having poor mental well-
being represented nearly a quarter of the sample, the findings 
suggest previous estimates, which focused on patients with very 
poor mental health status (via diagnoses of psychiatric conditions) 
may have underestimated the total impact of mental health impair-
ment in patients with T2DM. </p>

<p>5,6,18,21-23,40 -42   Prior findings suggesting that poor mental health, and particu-
larly diabetes-related distress, is negatively associated with self-care, 
treatment adherence, and glycemic control, 
5,6,8-10,15,16,45 further 
highlighting the importance of the current findings. Clinicians should 
take care to address the mental well-being of patients in addition to the 
physical aspects of T2DM in order to prevent patients from devel-
oping poor or very poor mental well-being. This is particularly 
notable, as prior research suggests that there is discordance between 
patients and their physicians, with patients rating mental health 
symptoms as a higher treatment priority than their physicians. </p>

<p>45   Limitations </p>

<p>The current study benefited from using a large sample 
representative of the Internet-using U.S. population. Because the 
study employed an internet sampling methodology, older and ill 
patients not able to complete online surveys may have been under-
sampled. This may have led to the current study's sample being 
younger and healthier than would be the case if the sampling could 
have included these patients, which may have biased the study to 
underestimate the prevalence of very poor and poor mental well-
being among patients with T2DM and the impact of mental well-
being on health care and work productivity costs. 
Because of the cross-sectional nature of the study, a causal 
relationship between mental well-being and outcomes could not be 
established. Although poorer mental well-being may lead to greater 
resource use and work productivity loss, greater resource use and 
work productivity loss may exacerbate poor mental well-being. All 
measures were self-reported and patients may have misclassified 
their disease status or treatment status, potentially causing 
measurement error. 
Lastly, we were not able to assess diabetes-related distress in 
this study, as the data were not available in the National Health and 
Wellness Survey. Future research should focus on the relationship 
between diabetes-related distress, mental health conditions includ-
ing depression and anxiety, and overall mental well-being. In 
addition, this study only focused on patients with T2DM. Future 
research should consider the relationship of overall mental well-
being with health care resource use and work productivity in the 
general population, as well as in populations with other chronic 
health conditions. </p>

<p>Conclusions and Future Directions </p>

<p>The current study found that patients with T2DM and poor or 
very poor mental well-being experience greater health care resource 
use and work productivity impairment than patients with T2DM and 
good mental well-being. The consequences of such impairment for 
those with poor or very poor mental well-being have real-world 
implications for associated costs to employers and health plans. 
In contrast with prior research, the current study highlights 
that patients who are not necessarily clinically diagnosed with a 
mental health condition, but have poor mental well-being, may 
experience impairment, indicating prior research may have under-
estimated the total impact of diabetes-related mental health impair-
ments. Clinicians should pay special attention to populations at a 
greater risk for poor and very poor mental well-being such as low 
income, women, and non-Whites. It is important that clinicians take 
care in developing individualized treatment strategies tailored to 
mental health status and focus on those with poor and very poor 
mental well-being, as both groups may have different needs and 
require different interventions. </p>



<p>JOEM Volume 58, Number 11, November 2016 
Poor Mental Well-being in T2DM </p>

<p>ß 2016 American College of Occupational and Environmental Medicine </p>



<p>
Bolge et al 
JOEM Volume 58, Number 11, November 2016 </p>

<p> 
ß 2016 American College of Occupational and Environmental Medicine </p>

</text></tei>