<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5324669" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Aim: Respiratory distress syndrome (RDS) is a major cause of mortality and morbidity in </p>

<p>premature infants. By the time symptoms appear, it may already be too late to prevent a 
severe course, with bronchopulmonary dysplasia or mortality. We aimed to develop a rapid 
test of lung maturity for targeting surfactant supplementation. </p>

<p>Methods: Concentrations of the most surface-active lung phospholipid </p>

<p>dipalmitoylphosphatidylcholine and sphingomyelin in gastric aspirates from premature 
infants were measured by mass spectrometry and expressed as the lecithin/sphingomyelin 
ratio (L/S). The same aspirates were analysed with mid-infrared spectroscopy. 
Subsequently, L/S was measured in gastric aspirates and oropharyngeal secretions from 
another group of premature infants using spectroscopy and the results were compared 
with RDS development. The 10-minute analysis required 10 lL of aspirate. </p>

<p>Results: An L/S algorithm was developed based on 89 aspirates. Subsequently, gastric </p>

<p>aspirates were sampled in 136 infants of 24-31 weeks of gestation and 61 (45%) 
developed RDS. The cut-off value of L/S was 2.2, sensitivity was 92%, and specificity was 
73%. In 59 cases, the oropharyngeal secretions had less valid L/S than gastric aspirate results. </p>

<p>Conclusion: Our rapid test for lung maturity, based on spectroscopy of gastric aspirate, </p>

<p>predicted RDS with high sensitivity. </p>

<p>Abbreviations </p>

<p>CI, Confidence interval; DPPC, Dipalmitoylphosphatidylcholine; 
FiO 2 , Fraction of oxygen in inspired gas; FTIR, Fourier transform 
infrared spectroscopy; L/S, Lecithin/sphingomyelin ratio; MS, 
Mass spectroscopy; nCPAP, Nasal continuous positive airway 
pressure; RDS, Respiratory distress syndrome. </p>

<p>Key notes </p>

<p>Respiratory distress syndrome (RDS) is a major cause of 
mortality and morbidity in premature infants, and when 
symptoms appear, it may already be too late to prevent 
a severe course 
We developed a rapid mid-infrared spectroscopy test to 
predict the development of RDS and accurately target 
treatment. 
A low lecithin/sphingomyelin ratio in gastric aspirate 
was a sensitive predictor for RDS and may be useful for 
targeting early surfactant supplementation. </p>

<p>430 </p>

<p>©2016 The Authors. Acta Paediatrica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Foundation Acta Paediatrica 2017 106, pp. 430-437 
This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and distribution in any medium, 
provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>Acta Paediatrica ISSN 0803-5253 </p>

<p>premature infants with a gestational age of less than 
30 weeks have immature lungs and approximately half still 
require treatment with surfactant when treated with nCPAP 
or mechanical ventilation (1,2). In recent years, there have 
been several improvements in treatment, which have 
helped reduce the incidence and severity of RDS and 
bronchopulmonary dysplasia. Minimal use of oxygen in 
the delivery room (3) and in the neonatal period is an 
important development in care. Very early treatment with 
nCPAP, combined with minimal use of mechanical venti-
lation, especially during initial treatment, reduces ventila-
tor-induced lung damage and is now widely used (4,5). 
Over the years, early rescue treatment with surfactant has 
been strongly associated with a more favourable outcome 
compared to late rescue treatment (6-8). Better outcomes 
are also seen with a combination of nCPAP and surfactant 
(7,8). Finally, less invasive administration of surfactant 
via a thin catheter has emerged as an alternative method, 
especially in the most preterm infants (9). However, we 
need to treat selectively with surfactant, and very soon after 
birth, in order to substantially improve the prognosis of 
RDS and bronchopulmonary dysplasia. In many cases, this 
needs to happen before symptoms are present. In order to 
do so, we need a bedside test that can quickly identify which 
infants have surfactant deficiency to target treatment 
effectively (10). Prophylactic treatment has been widely 
used, but it has been shown to increase the combined 
mortality and incidence of bronchopulmonary dysplasia 
(11). 
Biomarkers expressing lung maturity have been identified 
in amniotic fluid (12), gastric aspirate (13) and hypopha-
ryngeal secretions (14). These fluids are partially produced 
in the foetal lungs as well as in the kidneys and the amniotic 
sac and therefore contain lung surfactant (15). The classic 
method to determine surfactant in amniotic fluid has been 
measuring lecithin/sphingomyelin ratio (L/S) with thin-
layer chromatography (12,16). Sphingomyelin secretion 
remains fairly constant during pregnancy, whereas lecithin 
secretion increases in parallel with lung maturation. Con-
sequently, L/S reflects lung maturity independently of 
dilution sampling effects (12). However, this well-known 
diagnostic procedure to measure lung surfactant is slow and 
complex (16). 
Gastric aspirate and oropharyngeal secretion are easier to 
obtain and measure than amniotic fluid (17,18). Previously, 
we have measured the surfactant content in gastric aspirate 
with microbubble stability tests (19) and with lamellar body 
counts (20). We also conducted a randomised trial in very 
preterm infants with early surfactant guided by lamellar 
body counts in gastric aspirate versus traditional surfactant 
treatment (21). Use of lamellar body counts as a guide for 
early surfactant treatment led to a significant reduction in 
the need of oxygen at six hours of age and by day 28. 
Furthermore, the time on oxygen therapy was reduced and 
there was a trend towards a lower incidence of bronchopul-
monary dysplasia. The earlier that the lamellar body counts 
were measured, the better the outcome. Dilution, however, 
was a problem with both the microbubble stability test and </p>

<p>lamellar body counts. Furthermore, both these methods, 
and similar tests, are labour and laboratory intensive and 
require a minimum of two to three hours for analysis. This 
makes these methods less suitable for use as bedside tests. 
The aim of this study was to predict the risk of RDS by 
measuring lung maturity. To achieve this, we developed a 
rapid test using spectroscopic analysis of L/S in small 
volumes of oropharyngeal secretion and from gastric aspi-
rate obtained from gastric tubes placed as part of routine 
neonatal management. Subsequently, we validated this 
method in a number of premature infants by comparing 
the appearance of RDS with L/S. </p>

<p>PATIENTS AND METHODS 
Study design 
The study was a multicentre nonintervention diagnostic 
study with two phases. 
In the method development phase, which was phase one 
of the study, gastric aspirate samples from a group of 
premature infants were analysed by mass spectroscopy 
(MS) to obtain reference values for the concentration of 
lecithin, which is also called phosphatidylcholine, and 
sphingomyelin. The same gastric aspirate samples were 
then measured by Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy 
(FTIR), and an algorithm was developed to quantify 
phosphatidylcholine and sphingomyelin concentrations by 
spectroscopy. These are detailed below and in Appendix S1. 
The concentration determined by MS of the lecithin species 
with the highest surface activity, dipalmitoylphosphatidyl-
choline (DPPC), was used to calculate the L/S. This 
phospholipid is only present at very low concentrations in 
blood or meconium. 
During the clinical phase, which was phase two of the 
study, another population of premature infants had gastric 
aspirate and oropharyngeal samples obtained shortly after 
birth. These infants were monitored for the first five days of 
life and all clinically relevant data captured. L/S from this 
population was then determined by spectroscopy and 
analysed by the algorithm. The results were subsequently 
compared with the prevalence and severity of RDS. 
The trial was approved by the research ethics committees 
of each centre. Informed oral and written parental consent 
was obtained either before birth or immediately following 
birth. </p>

<p>Pre-analytical handling of samples 
The gastric aspirates were frozen at À20°C shortly after they 
were drawn. Gastric aspirate may contain blood, cells, 
meconium, particular matters and mucus. Before the anal-
yses in both phases of the study, the samples were thawed 
and mixed thoroughly followed by mild centrifugation of 
300 g for three minutes. Cells and particulate matter 
precipitated and mucus gathered in the upper part of the 
sample. Sample aliquots for the analyses were taken from 
the clear midsection of the sample. 
Oropharyngeal secretions were frozen at 
_ 20°C shortly 
after they were drawn. Before the analysis was carried out, </p>

<p>©2016 The Authors. Acta Paediatrica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Foundation Acta Paediatrica 2017 106, pp. 430-437 </p>



<p>Verder et al. 
Rapid test for lung maturity </p>

<p>the samples were thawed and 50 lL of distilled water was 
added to each oropharyngeal secretion sample due to the 
low volume available for analysis. The diluted oropharyn-
geal secretion samples were processed in the same way as 
the gastric aspirates. </p>

<p>Phase one: method development 
To develop the L/S algorithm, 89 newborn infants from 
Denmark, UK and Sweden had gastric aspirate sampled 
from gastric tubes placed for routine clinical reasons shortly 
after birth. The infants had a median gestational age of 29.5, 
with a range of 24.2-33.7 weeks. </p>

<p>Mass spectroscopy 
MS, which was the reference method, was carried out on 
the 89 gastric aspirate samples. 125 lL of aspirate was 
mixed with 10 lL of antioxidant (butylated hydroxytoluene, 
50 g/L). Internal standards in chloroform to a final con-
centration of 1.0 nmol dimyristoylphosphatidylcholine per 
sample were then added. Once this was complete, samples 
were lipid-extracted using dichloromethane and methanol 
(22) and the lipid-containing lower organic phase removed 
and dried under warmed nitrogen gas. Once they were 
dried, the samples were capped with an airtight seal and 
stored at </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>20°C until analysis. Immediately prior to MS, the 
samples were reconstituted in 300 lL solvent comprising 
methanol, dichloromethane, water and concentrated 
ammonia (66:30:3:1, v:v). 
MS analysis of the individual molecular species of 
lecithin, including DPPC and sphingomyelin, was per-
formed by direct infusion on a Xevo TQ MS (Waters, 
Manchester, UK) fitted with an electrospray ionisation 
source with sample delivery at eight lL/min. Full 
positive and full negative scans were taken, followed 
by diagnostic tandem MS/MS precursor ion spec-
tra for phosphatidylcholine (P184) and sphingomyelin 
(P168). </p>

<p>FTIR spectroscopy 
Spectra were recorded in the mid-infrared region (3200-
900 cm 
À1 ) by a Tensor 27 FTIR spectrometer (Bruker, </p>

<p>Massachusetts, USA). A nitrogen-cooled mercury cadmium 
telluride detector and an attenuated total reflection cell, 
Harric BioATRcell 
II , with a silicon crystal were used. The 
temperature of the attenuated total reflection cell was 30°C. 
Spectra were recorded using <rs id="software-0" type="software">OPUS</rs> software version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">7.2</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Bruker</rs>, Massachusetts, USA). Gastric aspirate (20 lL) was 
transferred to a fresh vial containing 20 lL of internal 
standard (potassium thiocyanate 1 g/L). Then, 6 lL of this 
mixture was applied to the attenuated total reflection 
crystal. The sample was dried for two minutes under a 
gentle stream of air (40-45°C). Each sample was applied 
twice, and for each application, two spectra were recorded. 
The mean value of the four spectra was calculated, and 
the baseline was corrected and normalised with respect to 
the potassium thiocyanate peak at 2.000-2.110 cm </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>. The 
spectroscopy after pre-analytic handling of each sample was 
completed in less than 10 minutes. </p>

<p>Calibration of the FTIR methods 
Calibration of the FTIR methods was carried out with the 
89 gastric aspirate samples with reference concentrations of 
DPPC and total sphingomyelin measured by MS. 
For each analyte, the spectra were processed using a 
stepwise selection of wave numbers giving the optimal least 
squares correlation between the measured mid-infrared 
signal and the analyte concentration measured by the 
reference method. At each step of the analysis, a partial 
least square regression was evaluated by average cross-
validation. Wave numbers showing no or a small correlation 
between the mid-infrared signal and measured concentra-
tion were excluded. The detection of the sample outliers was 
performed by leaving-one-out analysis, whereby calibration 
samples that deviated by more than 3.5 standard deviations 
from their measured concentration were excluded from the 
calibration set. 
Algorithms for the quantification of DPPC and sphin-
gomyelin were developed chemometrically to produce 
adequate correlation coefficients between the reference 
values and the associated computed values. 
A more detailed overview of the stepwise calibration 
procedure is given in Appendix S1 in the online supplement 
section and has previously been published (23,24). </p>

<p>Study phase two: L/S analyses 
Infants with a gestational age from 24 to 31 completed 
weeks were eligible. Oropharyngeal secretion samples 
(30-100 lL) were secured from between the root of the 
tongue and the cheek with a 1-mL syringe within a few 
minutes after birth. Gastric aspirate samples (0.3-2.5 mL) 
were drawn within half an hour after birth using a feeding 
tube attached to a 10-mL syringe or a suction catheter (Ch 
6) connected to a tracheal suction set. The feeding tube or 
suction catheters were placed while establishing nCPAP 
for respiratory stabilisation or intubation. Immediate 
treatment with nCPAP was the primary method of 
respiratory stabilisation at birth, and intubation was only 
carried out for resuscitation. Gastric aspirate and oropha-
ryngeal secretion, as detailed in the section about 
pre-analytical handling above, were stored at </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>20°C 
within one hour of birth for later analyses by FTIR 
spectroscopy. 
RDS was diagnosed when at least two of the four 
classical symptoms were present: the need for supplemen-
tal oxygen, tachypnoea, intercostal retractions and grunt-
ing, and a chest x-ray consistent with RDS excluded other 
causes of respiratory distress. The severity of RDS was 
graded in four groups (19). It was graded as non-RDS if 
the fraction of inspired oxygen (FiO 2 ) was &lt;0.40 in 
maximal nine hours after birth, with no need for supple-
mental oxygen later on. Mild RDS was when the FiO 2 was 
0.22-0.40 for more than nine hours after birth, but there 
was no need for surfactant or mechanical ventilation. 
Moderate RDS was the need for surfactant or FiO 2 &gt;0.40, 
but no mechanical ventilation. Severe RDS was the need 
for mechanical ventilation within the five-day study. FiO 2 
was registered every hour for the first 24 hours and every </p>

<p>432 </p>

<p>©2016 The Authors. Acta Paediatrica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Foundation Acta Paediatrica 2017 106, pp. 430-437 </p>

<p>Rapid test for lung maturity 
Verder et al. </p>

<p>second hour for the following 48 hours and twice on days 
4 and 5. 
The calculation of the L/S values by the DPPC and 
sphingomyelin algorithms was performed without any 
knowledge of the clinical outcomes. 
Different factors in addition to the neonatal treatment of 
lung symptoms are known to influence the development of 
RDS and possibly also surfactant analyses. The factors 
considered in the following include the following: multiple 
births, birth by Caesarean section, gestational diabetes, 
asphyxia, antenatal steroid treatment and contamination with 
blood, meconium and mucus and viscous gastric aspirate. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
We estimated that 135 infants with a gestational age of 24-
31 weeks, with an estimated 55 with RDS (19), would be 
sufficient to evaluate the method. 
We chose cut-off values that maximised the sum of the 
sensitivity and specificity to improve the usability of L/S to 
diagnose RDS (25). The 95% confidence intervals (CI) for 
sensitivity and specificity were calculated. The L/S data 
were stratified into groups based on gestational ages of 24-
25, 26-29 and 30-31 weeks. 
Pearson's chi-square test was used to examine the 
possible influence of Caesarean section on the accuracy of 
L/S as a predictor of RDS and the sensitivity of L/S versus 
gestational age. Two-tailed p values of &lt;0.05 were consid-
ered to indicate statistical significance. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Infants were enrolled in the second phase of the study from 
March 2014 to January 2015 from eight Danish and three 
Swedish neonatal units. Gastric aspirate samples were 
obtained from 143 of the 144 enrolled infants. Seven cases 
were excluded -four due to prophylactic surfactant treat-
ment before sampling, two due to severe infections and one 
due to congenital lung malformation -leaving 136 infants 
with gastric aspirates in the final cohort. Oropharyngeal 
secretions were available from 59 infants. For 58 infants, 
oropharyngeal secretions were available in addition to gastric 
aspirate, and for one infant, only oropharyngeal secretion 
was available. Of the included 136 infants, seven infants (5%) 
died before the end of the five-day study period. 
Table 1 shows the clinical characteristics of the infants 
who had gastric aspirates included in the analyses. </p>

<p>In Figure 1, the L/S values from the gastric aspirates are 
compared with the development of RDS. RDS developed in 
61 (45%) of the 136 infants and was classified as mild in 10 
(16%), as moderate in 31 (51%) and as severe in 20 (33%). 
The optimal cut-off value (25) of L/S was 2.2. The 
developed L/S method as a predictor of RDS from gastric 
aspirate had a sensitivity of 92% (95% CI: 82-97), a </p>

<p>Table 1 Demographic and clinical characteristics of the patients </p>

<p>Characteristics 
(N = 136) </p>

<p>GA, median (interquartile range), week 
29.8 (27.3-31.0) 
Birth weight, median (interquartile range), g 
1260 (902-1506) 
Apgar score at five minute, median 
(interquartile range), </p>

<p>10 (8-10) </p>

<p>Antenatal corticosteroids, n (%) 
117 (86) 
Caesarean section, n (%) 
85 (63) 
Male gender, n (%) 
71 (52) </p>

<p>Figure 1 Lecithin/sphingomyelin ratio (L/S) in gastric aspirates determined by 
mid-infrared spectroscopy in 61 infants with RDS and 75 infants with non-RDS. 
The best cut-off value is 2.2 moles/mole. </p>

<p>©2016 The Authors. Acta Paediatrica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Foundation Acta Paediatrica 2017 106, pp. 430-437 </p>



<p>Verder et al. 
Rapid test for lung maturity </p>

<p>specificity of 73% (95% CI 62-83), a positive predictive 
value of 74% (95% CI: 66-85) and a negative predictive 
value of 92% (95% CI: 82-97). Gestational age was 24-
25 weeks for 12 infants (9%), 26-29 weeks for 62 infants 
(46%) and 30-31 weeks for a further 62 infants (46%). The 
sensitivity was high in all three gestational age groups, and 
only one or two infants with RDS in each group had an L/S 
above the cut-off 2.2. Gestational age and L/S with different 
degrees of RDS severity are shown in Table 2. Infants 
without RDS had L/S below 2.2 in 20 cases: eight of these 
(40%) needed extra oxygen and no infants diagnosed 
without RDS, with an L/S above 3.2. required extra oxygen. 
One set of triplets and 19 pairs of twins were included in 
the study: the triplets and 12 of the 19 pairs of twins 
accounted for the 65% of the multiple births born by 
Caesarean section. In 12 pairs, the lowest L/S was found in 
the second twin, while in one pair, the L/S was the same in 
both twins. Twins and triplets were correctly diagnosed 
in 81% of cases compared with 82% of all infants in the 
cohort. 
The RDS predictions from L/S were significantly more 
precise with a p value of just below 0.05 in infants born by 
the vaginal route, which accounted for 37% of the deliver-
ies, than by Caesarean section (Table 3a and b). None of the 
mothers of the included infants had gestational diabetes. No 
difference in specificity was found between the infants with 
Apgar scores of 10 and lower scores at five minutes. L/S 
predicted the development of RDS with the same precision 
in cases with and without antenatal corticosteroid treat-
ment. Gastric aspirate was visually contaminated with 
blood in 32 (24%) of the cases. In 29 of these 32 cases, 
L/S correctly diagnosed the development of RDS. In 
addition, one case with RDS and two cases without RDS 
and blood contamination of the gastric aspirates were 
diagnosed incorrectly. Visual meconium contamination of 
the gastric aspirate was only seen in four cases, and all were 
diagnosed accurately without RDS. Mucus was found in 
different amounts in about half of the samples. Viscous 
gastric aspirate was not seen in any case. 
The optimal cut-off value (25) of L/S in oropharyngeal 
secretion was 3.7. The sensitivity, specificity and predictive 
values are shown in Table 4. 
Predicting RDS using the L/S ratio was significantly 
better than using the gestational age as a predictive 
indicator (Table 5a). When gestational age was used as a </p>

<p>guide for predicting RDS, 43 (70%) of the 61 infants with 
RDS had a gestational age of less than 30 weeks, compared 
to 56 (92%) of the 61 infants with L/S below the cut-off 
value when L/S was used to predict RDS. Both sensitivity 
and specificity were highest when predicted by L/S. 
Table 5b shows that the age from birth was median of six 
hours before the infants were treated with surfactant based 
on the clinical observations. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
For more than 50 years, clinicians have searched for a test 
to determine lung maturity in premature infants, and from 
the 1970s, several laboratory tests have been developed. 
Only a few are still in use, and they all have significant 
drawbacks, such as lack of specificity and sensitivity or a 
demand for skilled laboratory personnel and a long delay 
before the test results are available. Therefore, there is still 
an urgent unmet need for a quick and safe test to identify </p>

<p>Table 2 Gestational age and L/S ratio in different degrees of severity of RDS </p>

<p>RDS severity 
n </p>

<p>(N = 136) </p>

<p>Gestational age (weeks) 
L/S ratio (moles/mole) 
Median (range) 
Median (range) </p>

<p>Non-RDS 
75 
30.4 (25.0-31.9) 
3.0 (0-40.0) 
Mild 
10 
28.1 (25.0-31.9) 
1.3 (0.4-2.1) 
Moderate 
31 
30.0 (24.3-31.6) 
0.6 (0-5.3) 
Severe 
20 
26.2 (24.1-29.9) 
0.7 (0-4.5) 
RDS (all degrees) 
61 
28.7 (24.1-31.9) 
0.8 (0-5.3) </p>

<p>Table 3 L/S in gastric aspirates from infants born by Caesarean section vs. vaginal 
delivery </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(N = 85) </p>

<p>Caesarean section </p>

<p>(N = 51) </p>

<p>Vaginal delivery </p>

<p>+ RDS 
n </p>

<p>À RDS 
n </p>

<p>+ RDS 
n </p>

<p>À RDS 
n </p>

<p>L/S &lt; 2.2 
33* 
15 
23 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>5 
L/S ≥ 2.2 
5 
32 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0 
2 3 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>(N = 136) </p>

<p>Prediction of RDS </p>

<p>Right 
n </p>

<p>Wrong 
n </p>

<p>Caesarean section 
65 
20 
Vaginal delivery 
46 
5 </p>

<p>Prediction was significantly better in the vaginal group, p &lt; 0.05, relative risk 
0.85 (CI 95%, 0.73-0.98). 
*Sensitivity 87% (CI 95%, 72-96). </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Sensitivity 100% (CI 95%, 85-100). </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Specificity 68% (CI 95%, 53-81). </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>Specificity 82% (CI 95%, 63-94). </p>

<p>Table 4 L/S in oropharyngeal secretions (N = 59) </p>

<p>The cut-off value for L/S (moles/mole) </p>

<p>RDS 
n </p>

<p>Non-RDS 
n </p>

<p>L/S &lt; 3.7 
21* 
9 
L/S ≥ 3.7 
8 
21 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Positive predictive value: 70% (CI 95%, 51-85). 
Negative predictive value: 72% (CI 95%, 53-87). 
*Sensitivity 72% (CI 95%, 53-87). </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Specificity 70% (CI 95%, 51-85). </p>

<p>434 </p>

<p>©2016 The Authors. Acta Paediatrica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Foundation Acta Paediatrica 2017 106, pp. 430-437 </p>

<p>Rapid test for lung maturity 
Verder et al. </p>

<p>which newborn infants require surfactant. We have devel-
oped a fast method that does not require highly trained 
laboratory personnel and can be further developed to a 
point-of-care test. We chose to use gastric aspirates and 
oropharyngeal secretions, which are easy to obtain, and a 
process that does not require the use of complicated 
reagents. 
More clinical factors may influence the development of 
RDS and the lung maturity test. For example, the second 
twin often has a lower L/S than the first-born infant. This 
tendency is also seen in the actual study. 
Blood contamination of the gastric aspirate does not 
appear to influence measurements of L/S. This could be due 
to phosphatidylcholine being measured as DPPC, which is 
only sparsely present in blood and meconium. Gastric 
aspirates were contaminated with meconium in four cases. 
This was too few to draw conclusions about the effect, 
although L/S accurately predicted RDS in all cases. As 
mentioned, we did not analyse the mucus in gastric 
aspirates. Detailed lipid analyses of mucus in fresh, frozen 
and thawed gastric aspirate are planned before the L/S 
analysis is introduced as a bedside test. Viscous gastric 
aspirate was not a problem in the actual study, and it is 
probable that the phenomenon is only seen at term. 
Predicting RDS by L/S analyses of gastric aspirate was 
significantly poorer in infants born by Caesarean section 
compared to those born through the vaginal route. A 
possible explanation is that L/S in gastric aspirate after 
Caesarean section originates from a mix of amniotic fluid 
and newly produced lung fluid, both with different L/S, in 
contrast to L/S in gastric aspirate from infants born 
vaginally. We found it conceivable that swallowed amniotic 
fluid to some degree may be squeezed out of the stomach 
during natural birth as opposed to birth by Caesarean </p>

<p>section. Accordingly, gastric aspirate obtained immediately 
after a vaginal birth may contain a higher proportion of 
newly swallowed fluid from the lungs. 
The actual L/S test was found to have a lower 
specificity than sensitivity, and we found it likely that this 
might have been mainly explained by the fact that all the 
included infants were stabilised with nCPAP within a few 
minutes of birth. The efficacy of nCPAP may alleviate or 
mask symptoms of RDS, making the diagnosis of RDS 
challenging, but it would be unethical to withhold treat-
ment with nCPAP. In our study, 40% of the infants with 
non-RDS and L/S values below the cut-off required 
supplemental oxygen during the first nine hours of life, 
while infants with non-RDS and higher L/S values had no 
need for oxygen. This makes it probable that some infants 
with low L/S values, who were graded as non-RDS, 
actually had subclinical surfactant deficiency. It has also 
been shown that nCPAP can increase L/S in repeated 
hypopharyngeal secretions (26). We previously developed 
two different methods for early diagnosis of RDS on 
gastric aspirate from infants similar to the population in 
the present study receiving early nCPAP (18,19). These 
previously developed tests, like our new method, had 
specificity that was lower than sensitivity, supporting the 
suggestion that nCPAP may mask less pronounced sur-
factant deficiency. 
The analysis of gestational age and L/S in the different 
classifications of RDS supports the conclusion that our 
method correctly predicted the pulmonary outcome in 
these groups. Gestational age and L/S were lower in all 
groups of RDS compared to non-RDS. What is also 
remarkable is that there was no distinct correlation between 
gestational age and L/S, probably reflecting that gestational 
age only accounted for a smaller fraction of the total 
variation in the result of the lung maturity test (20,27). This 
was also supported by the higher sensitivity and specificity 
of L/S compared to gestational age when used as a 
predictor of RDS. Surfactant treatment in the actual study, 
as judged by clinical observations, was given after a median 
of six hours and only four infants were treated an hour or 
less after birth. This indicates that fast determination of L/S 
by a bedside test is likely to allow earlier diagnosis of RDS 
and earlier rescue treatment with surfactant compared to 
rescue surfactant treatment based on routine clinical 
criteria. 
L/S varied in amniotic fluid, depending on the locations 
it was sampled from, and it had the strongest correlation 
with the development of RDS when it was taken near to the 
infant's mouth (28). Consequently, we also analysed L/S in 
oropharyngeal secretion. The fluid was taken noninvasively 
and close to the oral cavity. The specificity of L/S in the 
oropharyngeal secretions was equal to the specificity in the 
gastric aspirates, but the sensitivity for the oropharyngeal 
secretions was lower than for the gastric aspirates. We 
expect that the sampling technique can be optimised and 
that fresh oropharyngeal secretions and gastric aspirates 
will be easier to process than frozen ones. Stichtenoth et al. 
(29) measured surface tension in upper airway aspirates and </p>

<p>Table 5 (a) Comparison of L/S and gestational age for prediction of RDS. 
(b) Characteristics of infants treated with surfactant </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>N = 136 of which 61 developed RDS </p>

<p>L/S in gastric aspirate 
determined spectroscopically </p>

<p>Gestational age 
(week 24-31) </p>

<p>Best cut-off 
2.2 moles/mole* 
&lt;30 week's* 
Sensitivity 
92%* 
70%* p &lt; 0.01 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Specificity 
73%* 
60%* 
Time to diagnosis 
Less than one hour after birth </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>At birth 
(b) </p>

<p>(N = 51) </p>

<p>Main indication for surfactant treatment: FiO 2 &gt;0.40 
Time from birth to surfactant treatment: median six hours, range 0.1-48 h 
Four infants were treated ≤one hour </p>

<p>*The best cut-off value was that with the highest sum of sensitivity and 
specificity. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>By the planned bedside test. </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>The p-value was calculated by chi-square test. </p>

<p>©2016 The Authors. Acta Paediatrica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Foundation Acta Paediatrica 2017 106, pp. 430-437 </p>



<p>Verder et al. 
Rapid test for lung maturity </p>

<p>found acceptable correlations to lung maturity. However, 
the processing time was rather long and the dilution of the 
surfactant may have interfered with the surface tension 
measurements. Others have also successfully performed 
L/S analyses on hypopharyngeal secretions (14,26), but by 
using methods that were slower and less accurate. The use 
of spectroscopy to measure L/S on amniotic fluid was 
initially explored by Liu et al. (30). This method held 
promise for rapid measurements of lung maturity in the 
laboratory, but the low accuracy of the reference method, 
which was carried out by thin-layer chromatography, 
proved to be a fundamental problem (16). The increased 
foetal loss after amniocentesis, together with improvements 
in newborn respiratory care, obviates wide use of the 
method. 
The spectroscopic part of our L/S method was very rapid, 
but at present, the method is still a laboratory test. To 
contribute to clinical decision-making, results should be 
available within minutes after birth and a bedside version of 
the test is needed for our method to become useful in 
clinical settings. A new stand-alone device is currently being 
developed with the aim that it will be used as a point-of-
care test in neonatal wards, using custom-made equipment 
for easy sampling and processing of gastric aspirate and 
potentially oropharyngeal secretions. The bedside test will 
be introduced in a randomised study, which will measure 
the benefit of this new method on clinical outcomes 
compared to standard treatment. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
We have developed a rapid test to measure lung maturity on 
small volumes of gastric aspirate and oropharyngeal secre-
tion in premature infants at birth. This test could help 
identify which infants will benefit from very early surfactant 
treatment, with the potential to significantly improve 
clinical outcomes resulting in less severe RDS, less need 
of mechanical ventilation and oxygen and less severe 
bronchopulmonary dysplasia. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS 
We would like to thank Holbaek Hospital and Region 
Zealand, Denmark, for their vital co-operation on this 
project and Paul Townsend and Kewi Zhang for technical 
assistance with the mass spectroscopy analyses. We also 
want to thank the nurses and doctors in the participating 
neonatal departments and the Department of Clinical 
Biochemistry, Holbaek Hospital, Vivi Kuhr Christensen 
for creating the database, Morgaine Matthews for helping 
with the manuscript and Ahmet Cizmeli for helping with 
the development of the algorithms. </p>

<p>FUNDING 
This project received funding from the European 
Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation 
programme. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST 
Henrik Verder and Agnar H€ oskuldsson hold part of a 
patent for the spectroscopic analysis of biological samples. 
The authors have no other conflict of interest. </p>





<p>©2016 The Authors. Acta Paediatrica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Foundation Acta Paediatrica 2017 106, pp. 430-437 </p>

<p>Rapid test for lung maturity 
Verder et al. </p>



<p>SUPPORTING INFORMATION 
Additional Supporting Information may be found in the 
online version of this article: </p>

<p>Appendix S1. Development of the algorithms for quantifi-
cation of phosphatidylcholine (PC16:0/16:0) and sphin-
gomyelin (SM) by FTIR. 
Figure S1. Calibration result according to the developed 
algorithm for determination of the concentration of 
PC16:0/16:0. 
Figure S2. Calibration result according to the developed 
algorithm for determination of the concentration of sphin-
gomyelin. 
Table S1. Comparison of L/S-values measured on the same 
cases by mass spectrometry and by infrared spectroscopy. </p>

<p>©2016 The Authors. Acta Paediatrica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Foundation Acta Paediatrica 2017 106, pp. 430-437 </p>



<p>Verder et al. 
Rapid test for lung maturity </p>

</text></tei>