<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5413303" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Citation: Tan ACS, Astroz P, Dansingani 
KK, et al. The evolution of the plateau, 
an optical coherence tomography 
signature seen in geographic atrophy. 
Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 
PURPOSE. Histologic details of progression routes to geographic atrophy (GA) in AMD are 
becoming available through optical coherence tomography (OCT). We studied the origins and 
evolution of an OCT signature called plateau in eyes with GA and suggested a histologic correlate. </p>

<p>METHODS. Serial eye-tracked OCT scans and multimodal imaging were acquired from eight 
eyes of seven patients with GA and plateau signatures over a mean follow-up of 7.7 years 
(range, 3.7-11.6). The histology of unrelated donor eyes with AMD was reviewed. </p>

<p>RESULTS. Drusenoid pigment epithelial detachment (PED) on OCT imaging progressed into 
wide-based mound-like signatures with flattened apices characterized by a hyporeflective yet 
heterogeneous interior and an overlying hyperreflective exterior, similar to outer retinal 
corrugations previously ascribed to persistent basal laminar deposit (BLamD) but larger. These 
new signatures are described as ''plateaus.'' An initial increase of the PED volume and 
hyporeflectivity of its contents was followed by a decrease in PED volume and thinning of an 
overlying hyperreflective band attributable to the loss of the overlying RPE leaving persistent 
BLamD. Both imaging and histology revealed persistent BLamD with defects through which 
gliotic Müller cell processes pass. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS. Plateaus can be traced back to drusenoid PEDs on OCT imaging. We hypothesize 
that during progressive RPE atrophy, Müller cell extension through focal defects in the 
residual persistent BLamD may contribute to the heterogeneous internal reflectivity of these 
entities. The role of Müller cell activation and extension in the pathogenesis of AMD should be 
explored in future studies. </p>

<p>atrophy over drusen and PEDs. In turn, an accurate and 
comprehensive timeline can prompt new mechanistic hypoth-
eses of cell death that are experimentally testable in model 
systems, leading to new therapeutic strategies. 
Recently, Querques et al. 17 described an uncommon 
''wedge-shaped subretinal hyporeflectivity'' within areas of 
atrophy delimited externally by the hyperreflective bands 
representing BrM and internally by the synaptic portion of the 
outer plexiform layer (OPL). It should be noted that this 
description differed markedly from the common ''hyporeflec-
tive wedge-shaped band'' described by Monés et al., 
18 which 
develops in the axonal portion of the OPL (Henle fiber layer) at 
the junction between normal and atrophic retina. 6,19 The 
descriptor ''hyporeflective wedge'' applied to two different 
structures in GA has caused some confusion in recent 
literature. 19,20 Histologic correlates have not been proposed 
for either of these OCT signatures. 
The purpose of our study was to examine the origins and 
evolution of the Querques' ''wedge-shaped subretinal hypore-
flectivity'' 
17 using serial eye-tracked OCT imaging and to 
propose a histologic correlate. The term ''wedge'' suggested to 
us a triangle-shaped structure. After studying many such 
lesions in detail, we observed that most are not triangular 
but instead are mound-like with a flattened apex and a wide 
base, resembling a ''plateau'' (Fig. 1). Based on these 
observations, and to avoid further confusion in terminology, 
we propose ''plateau'' (plural plateaus or plateaux) as a more 
accurate descriptor than ''wedge.'' Of note, plateaus should be 
differentiated from other tomographic signatures seen in eyes 
with GA such as ORT, refractile drusen, and HPS (Fig. 1). 15,16,21  We find that plateau natural history can be differentiated from 
that described for PED collapse, thus providing a basis for 
considering outer retinal corrugations and plateaus a contin-
uum of OCT signatures involving persistent BLamD. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>This retrospective observational study was approved by the 
Western Institutional Review Board (Olympia, Washington, </p>

<p>USA). It complied with the Health Insurance Portability and 
Accountability Act of 1996 and followed the tenets of the 
Declaration of Helsinki. Informed consent was obtained from 
the subjects after explanation of the nature and possible 
consequences of the study. </p>

<p>Study Cohort </p>

<p>Patients with GA were identified from the tertiary practice of 
retinal specialists (KBF, JS, and LY) if they exhibited plateau 
signatures in at least one eye (study eye) on OCT imaging and if 
they also had at least 3 years' follow-up with consecutive eye-
tracked spectral-domain (SD)-OCT scans taken at least every 6 
months. Eyes with macular neovascularization, other retinal 
pathology, or media opacity preventing adequate imaging were 
excluded. </p>

<p>Imaging Protocol and Analysis </p>

<p>Medical records and multimodal imaging, including color 
fundus photography (CFP), red-free photography (RF), fundus 
autofluorescence (FAF), near-infrared reflectance scanning 
laser ophthalmoscopy (NIR), and SD-OCT was performed on 
all the patients. CFP and RF were performed with a TRC-50IX 
flood-illuminated fundus camera (Topcon Medical Systems, 
Oakland, NJ, USA). FAF was performed with either the 
Spectralis HRA þ OCT (Heidelberg Engineering, Heidelberg, 
Germany) or the Topcon TRC-50IX fundus camera. SD-OCT 
imaging with corresponding NIR images was performed on the 
<rs type="software">Spectralis</rs>. OCT scans taken before the acquisition of eye-
tracked Spectralis scans were assessed qualitatively but not 
included in the quantitative analysis. The SD-OCT protocol 
used in all eyes comprised 208 horizontal raster line scans over 
the area of interest, ranging from 19 to 49 B-scans per eye, with 
each scan spaced 115 to 250 lm apart, and automatic real-time 
averaging set between 4 and 23. 
To study the origin and progression of plateaus, the most 
recent SD-OCT with this signature was identified. Then, serial 
eye-tracked B-scans of the region of interest were tracked back 
to baseline. In cases in which the scanning protocol varied 
during the course of follow-up, the B-scan closest to the area of 
interest was matched manually and extracted for analysis. 
These extracted SD-OCT images were then stacked, aligned, 
and saved as a video file using the Fiji distribution (''Fiji is just 
Image J,'' http://fiji.sc; in the public domain) 22 for the 
qualitative analysis of the progression of the lesion (see 
Supplementary Video). At each time point, the plateau 
appearance on SD-OCT was correlated to the appearance in 
CFP, NIR, and FAF. 
Three patients had en face OCT and OCT angiography 
(OCTA) imaging with 3 3 3-mm macular cubes (RTVue XR 
''Avanti''; Optovue, Fremont, CA, USA). The review software 
(ReVUe, Version 2015.1.0.90; Optovue, Fremont, CA, USA) 
displays flow signals superimposed in red on a cross-sectional 
structural SD-OCT image. </p>

<p>SD-OCT Terminology </p>

<p>In a healthy eye, the fourth outer retinal hyperreflective band 
includes the RPE and BrM. 
23 In a PED, by definition, the RPE is 
separated from the BrM. In the course of this separation, either 
a basal lamina (BL) of 0.15-lm thickness 
24 or a BLamD of 
variable thickness adheres to the RPE and not to the BrM. 
Therefore, we call the hyperreflective band that anteriorly 
delimits a PED the RPE-BL complex. The definition of a 
''plateau'' was a distinct OCT signature where a mound-like 
structure with a flattened apex and a wide base was observed 
within an area of GA after complete loss of the overlying RPE. </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Multimodal imaging shows differences between the 
appearance of the plateau, refractile drusen and HPS. CFP (A) taken 
at baseline, follow-up NIR (C), and OCT images (B, D) taken 7 years 
later. Green lines (C) show corresponding cross-sectional OCT images 
(B, top green arrow; D, bottom green arrow). Boundaries of the 
plateau base are well demarcated on OCT but appear isoreflective on 
NIR (B, C, red dotted lines). Other structures that are distinct from the 
plateau include a closed outer retinal tubulation (pink arrowhead) and 
HPS (D, yellow arrowheads) that appear as refractile drusen on CFP 
and hyperreflective on NIR (A, C, yellow arrowheads). Some HPS 
contain a hyporeflective core surrounded by hyperreflective dots. </p>

<p>The Evolution of the Plateau 
IOVS j April 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 4 j 2350 </p>

<p>Quantification of Volume Changes During 
Progression </p>

<p>To determine the volume of the drusenoid PED and ensuing 
plateau (Fig. 2), the Cavalieri principle of stereology was </p>

<p>applied to SD-OCT volumetric data acquired at each 
visit, 
10,25,26 as follows. (1) Each B-scan in the volume was 
scaled to a 1:1 pixel aspect ratio. The caliper function within 
the Heidelberg Eye Explorer software (version 6.3.4.0; 
Heidelberg Engineering) was used to measure the area </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Origin and evolution of a plateau, as revealed by NIR (A) and OCT (B) images. NIR images show progressive GA. Green arrows on NIR 
images show the levels of corresponding OCT cross-sectional images. Baseline images show several elevations of the RPE with largely hyporeflective 
interiors. At 3 years after baseline, punctate hyperreflectivity (red arrowhead) is seen in the sub-RPE compartment. At 4 years, progressive loss of 
the ONL has caused the OPL (yellow arrows) to approach the surface of the PED. Also at 4 years, a ''Monés hyperreflective wedge'' (blue 
arrowheads) appears at the GA border. At 5 years, the downwardly deflected OPL is seen to move progressively toward the edge of the plateau 
following the advancing border of GA. Formation of the plateau at 5 years was characterized by the loss of the overlying RPE causing marked 
thinning of the hyperreflective RPE-basal lamina complex now reduced to just BLamD, compared with at 4 years. At 7 years, a closed ORT (pink 
arrowhead) is present adjacent to the plateau. </p>

<p>The Evolution of the Plateau 
IOVS j April 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 4 j 2351 </p>

<p>between the outer boundary of RPEþBL and the inner 
boundary of BrM. (2) the volume between two consecutive 
OCT slices (hereafter called a segment) was then determined 
using the following formula: </p>

<p>d A x þ A x þ 1 
ð 
Þ 
ð 
Þ =2 
ð 
Þ ; </p>

<p>where d is the distance between consecutive slices in lm, A is 
the area between the RPEþBL and BrM in lm 
2 , and x is the 
OCT slice number. (3) Total PED volume was calculated by 
summing the volumes of individual segments. The number of 
segments in the OCT volume was (n À 1), where n is the total 
number of slices that spanned the PED. Graphical plots of 
PED volume with respect to time were generated using 
interval data. </p>

<p>Histology Study </p>

<p>The institutional review board at University of Alabama at 
Birmingham (UAB) approved the laboratory study, which 
complied with the Health Insurance Portability and Account-
ability Act and adhered to the tenets of the Declaration of 
Helsinki. AMD eyes were identified through an ex vivo imaging 
screen of eyes accessioned for research purposes from 
nondiabetic white donors to the Alabama Eye Bank during 
the period 1996 to 2012. Median death-to-preservation time 
was 3:49 hours (range, 0:40-11:40 hours). Thirteen eyes with 
GA were reviewed for examples suitable for this study. 
Ophthalmic health records were not available for these donors. 
Eyes were preserved by immersion in 1% paraformaldehyde 
and 2.5% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M phosphate buffer following 
anterior segment excision. After vitreous removal, maculas 
were photographed in color on a stereomicroscope (SMZ-U; 
Nikon, Melville, NY, USA). 27 When prepared for histology 
(2011-2013) and uploaded to the Project MACULA Web site 
(http://projectmacula.cis.uab.edu, in the public domain), eyes 
underwent additional multimodal ex vivo imaging. From each 
globe, an 8-mm-diameter full-thickness tissue punch containing 
the fovea and temporal portion of the optic nerve head was 
held in a tissue holder mounted on a Spectralis, as described. </p>

<p>27   A 308 3 208 SD-OCT volume (143 scans, 30-lm spacing, 
automated real-time averaging [ART] ¼ 25) was captured along 
with red-free and near-infrared reflectance scanning laser 
ophthalmoscopic images. Tissue punches were postfixed by 
osmium tannic acid paraphenylenediamine to accentuate 
extracellular lipid and embedded in epoxy resin (PolyBed 
812; Polysciences, Warrington, PA, USA). 28 Sub-micrometer-
thick (0.8 lm) sections at 25-to 30-lm intervals were stained 
with 1% toluidine blue for polychromaticity, scanned with a 
340 objective, and reviewed and photodocumented with a 360 
oil-immersion objective (numerical aperture ¼ 1.4) and digital 
camera (XC10; Olympus, Center Valley, PA, USA). Images were 
adjusted for exposure, contrast, and sharpness (<rs id="software-3" type="software">Photoshop</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-3" type="version">CS6</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Adobe</rs>, San Jose, CA, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Patient Characteristics </p>

<p>Plateau signatures were observed in eight eyes of seven 
patients, of whom six were female. Mean age was 75 years 
(range, 60-89) and mean follow-up period was 7.7 years 
(range, 3.7-11.6). Baseline visual acuity (VA) was logMAR 0.42 
(Snellen equivalent 20/52) (range, 0.18-1). Final VA was 
logMAR 1.16 (Snellen equivalent 20/289) (range, 0.18-2.3). 
In two eyes, GA spared the fovea throughout the entire course 
of the follow-up. </p>

<p>Baseline Features </p>

<p>At baseline, the presence of a drusenoid PED with homoge-
neous hyperreflective contents and an intact overlying RPE 
was noted in six eyes (75%; Figs. 2, 3). One eye (patient 5, left 
eye) had an extremely large PED measuring 2.24 mm 3 with 
mostly hyporeflective contents and an overlying vitelliform 
lesion. In another eye (patient 4, left eye), the plateau was 
already present at baseline. Pigmentary changes noted on CFP 
were also found on NIR, RF, and FAF in six eyes, and these 
corresponded to intraretinal hyperreflective foci on OCT (Fig. 
3). Overlying the PED surface, the ellipsoid zone and outer 
nuclear layer (ONL) were thin, with the OPL nearly apposed to 
the surface of the PED. </p>

<p>Characteristics Seen During Progression of 
Drusenoid PED into the Plateau </p>

<p>During follow-up, ONL thinning resulted in the OPL approx-
imating the surface of the PED in all cases in which the PED was 
present at baseline (Figs. 2, 3). 
6 As GA progressed, this point of 
approximation moved toward the edges of the PED base, 
following the advancing border of GA (Supplementary Video). 
In all eyes, there was also progressive thinning of the 
hyperreflective RPE-BL complex and diminution of its reflectiv-
ity, beginning at the apex of the PED and advancing toward its 
edges. This likely represents RPE loss leaving persistent BLamD. 
After RPE loss occurred over the entire PED surface, the plateau 
(i.e., a thin hyperreflective inner surface and an interior of 
heterogeneous and overall reduced reflectivity) appeared. 
The plateau surface was highly reflective on both cross-
sectional and en face OCT (Fig. 4, en face OCT surface) and 
showed the presence of focal defects (Fig. 4, yellow arrows). 
On cross-sectional OCT, the inner contents of the plateau 
consisted of round, hyporeflective areas (Fig. 4, blue arrows) 
that were usually accompanied by smaller hyperreflective foci 
seen beneath the hyperreflective border. These hyperreflective 
foci also could be observed within the area of GA as 
hyperautofluorescent foci on FAF and hyperreflective foci on 
en face OCT (Fig. 4, green arrows). Accordingly, on en face 
OCT, plateau contents were seen as honeycomb-like structures 
with hyporeflective spaces interspersed with hyperreflective 
foci (Fig. 4, en face OCT). The punctate hyperreflective foci 
(Fig. 4, green arrows) increased in abundance within the 
plateau interior during follow-up in all eyes as seen on cross-
sectional and en face OCT (Figs. 2, 3, 4). On both cross-
sectional and en face OCTA, no abnormal flow signals were 
noted within plateaus (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>Changes in Volume of the Drusenoid PED and 
Plateau Signature With Time </p>

<p>In seven of eight eyes, the plateau was located in the macula. 
In one eye, a plateau was located just inferior to the macula at 
the vascular arcade. A single plateau was seen in all eyes 
except for one (patient 2) that had two separate plateaus (Fig. 
2). Patient 6 had one plateau in each eye. In the seven eyes 
with a baseline PED, PED volume gradually increased (Fig. 5) 
due to an increase in the hyporeflective interior. The thinning 
of the hyperreflective band over the PED surface after RPE loss 
(at which point we consider the plateau to be formed) was 
preceded by a sharp decrease in PED volume (Fig. 5). 
Subsequently, the volume of the residual plateau appeared 
very stable over time (Fig. 5). </p>

<p>Illustrative Histologic Case </p>

<p>Figure 6 shows histology of a donor eye with GA, for which 
local relationships and cellular processes in the interior of </p>

<p>The Evolution of the Plateau 
IOVS j April 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 4 j 2352 </p>

<p>outer retinal corrugations were particularly clear yet also 
representative of other GA eyes available for review. Atrophy 
spared the fovea in this eye, as seen with ex vivo CFP and 488-
nm autofluorescence, and small reflective puncta in the 
atrophic area were apparent on NIR (Figs. 6A-C). In a 
panoramic view (Fig. 6E), BLamD was seen as discontinuous, 
being present at three separate locations. Pigmented cells were 
of the ''subducted'' phenotype, 
29 that is, RPE-originated cells 
located external to BLamD, in contact with BrM. For reference, 
in the Henle fiber layer of a normal eye, obliquely oriented 
Müller cell processes are parallel to, and interleaved with, inner 
fibers of cone and rod photoreceptors. 30,31 In the presence of 
severe photoreceptor degeneration, including ORT in this GA 
eye, the trajectories of gliotic Müller cell processes were 
oriented in many directions, as indicated by arrows in Figure 
6E. In one instance, processes seemed to enter an outer retinal 
corrugation horizontally through an opening in the BLamD and 
sweep the ''subducted'' cells off BrM (Fig. 6D). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Through a retrospective review of AMD patients with long-
term serial eye-tracked SD-OCT, we identified a series of eyes in 
which drusenoid PEDs progressed into plateau signatures 
within areas of GA. Plateaus were seen on OCT to contain 
heterogeneous reflectivity enclosed by a thin overlying hyper-
reflective surface. A focal defect in the hyperreflective surface, 
in addition to intraretinal and sub-RPE hyperreflective dots, 
was observed during the evolution of PED into plateau 
signatures. OPL subsidence was noted to begin at the surface 
of the PED and progress toward the edge following the areas of 
expanding atrophy. There was a gradual increase in volume 
due to an increase in hyporeflective contents initially, followed 
by complete loss of the RPE and a sharp decrease in PED 
volume, at which time the plateau was considered to have 
formed. 
The study of drusen life cycles and PED evolution are 
important to improve our understanding of the pathogenesis of </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Multimodal imaging of two patients (A, B) at baseline and follow-up (A, 4 years; B, 7 years). (A) At baseline, patient 3 has a drusenoid 
PED with overlying pigment hyperplasia and hyperautofluorescent vitelliform material. The OCT B-scan shows intraretinal hyperreflective foci (red 
arrowhead) and loss of outer retinal bands over the apex of the PED. The OPL (yellow arrow) bends downward toward the PED surface. Four years 
later, a region of hypoautofluorescent GA contains a plateau that cannot be appreciated in the CFP, NIR, RF, or FAF. The OCT B-scan shows a plateau 
with a shape similar to the baseline PED. Further loss of ONL has caused the OPL to drape over the plateau. The downwardly deflecting OPL (yellow 
arrow) has moved laterally as it follows the border of the advancing GA. There was marked attenuation and decreased reflectivity of the RPE-BL 
band. Hyporeflective areas (A, blue arrowhead) are visible within the plateau interior. (B) At baseline, patient 6 has a drusenoid PED with overlying 
pigment hyperplasia that is located inferior to an area of GA. The OCT B-scan shows a bilobed drusenoid PED. Bottom row: Seven years later, the GA 
has markedly enlarged, and the PED is no longer visible on CFP, NIR, RF, or FAF. The OCT B-scan shows that following progressive loss of the ONL, 
the OPL (yellow arrow) appears draped over a plateau with a shape similar to the baseline PED. There was marked attenuation and decreased 
reflectivity of the RPE-BL band. Hyporeflective areas (blue arrowhead) are visible within the plateau interior. </p>

<p>The Evolution of the Plateau 
IOVS j April 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 4 j 2353 </p>

<p>AMD. Understanding the origins and evolution of various OCT 
findings and correlating these findings to histology enable the 
in vivo study of microscopic cellular changes occurring in 
these eyes with progressive GA. 
32-34 The development of GA 
has been previously reported to occur in 19% of eyes with 
drusenoid PEDs and to be associated with specific features 
such as subsidence of the OPL and inner nuclear layer and the 
development of a hyporeflective ''wedge-shaped band'' within 
the Henle fiber layer described by Monés et al.  18,20 Half of our 
study eyes exhibited this wedge. The appearance of plateaus 
should be distinguished from other signatures previously 
described in GA, such as ORT, ghost drusen, hyperreflective 
crown-like structures, HPS, and refractile drusen (Figs. 1, 
2). 
15,16,21 Plateau boundaries are difficult to distinguish from 
the surrounding atrophy using CFP, NIR, RF, and FAF (Figs. 1, 3, 
4, 6). Previous studies have reported focal areas of hyper-
autofluorescence within GA, 17 and in our study these 
correlated with hyperreflective foci seen on en face OCT 
(Fig. 4). The presence of many pigmented cells of apparent 
RPE origin within atrophic areas is now well-documented </p>

<p>35,36   (Fig. 6), and such cells could give rise to both autofluorescence 
and OCT hyperreflectivity signals. Plateaus do not contain the 
highly refractile material as seen on CFP and NIR in eyes with 
spherules in calcifying drusen. 21 These refractile drusen 
instead appear to correlate with HPS seen on OCT (Fig. 1), 
the composition of which is the focus of our ongoing studies. </p>

<p>14   However, both the plateau signatures and HPS (Fig. 1) have a 
similar overlying thin hyperreflective layer consistent with an 
overlying BLamD drape, as previously observed in OCT 14 and 
in histology (Fig. 26 of Sarks et al., 
34 and Fig. 3B of 
Balaratnasingam et al. 
37 ). 
Our current data support a previous study that suggested 
that plateaus occur at a low frequency in eyes with GA 
(7.5%). 
17 The plateau is a signature of a residual structure seen 
on OCT once the RPE has progressed into complete atrophy. In 
our study, after plateau formation as defined by loss of the 
overlying RPE layer exposing the underlying BLamD that then 
persists, minimal changes in plateau volume were observed on 
subsequent follow-up, as previously seen. 
17 In all eyes of our 
series, a drusenoid PED was noted to precede the appearance </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Multimodal imaging of two patients (A, B). (A) A plateau located within the area of GA features internal hyporeflective areas on cross-
sectional OCT (blue arrowhead), which appear to be organized in a honeycomb-like pattern on en face OCT (blue arrowhead). On cross-sectional 
OCT, OCTA, and on OCT surface (an en face OCT slab at the level of the RPE-BL atop the plateau), the plateau interior is bounded by a distinct 
hyperreflective band that continues as a thick and highly reflective RPE band. This hyperreflective surface shows transient hyporeflective defects 
(yellow arrows) during the evolution of these lesions. An en face OCT image of the plateau surface allows better appreciation of the focal defects 
(yellow arrow). OCTA does not show flow within the plateau. (B) A plateau located within the area of GA features internal hyporeflective areas on 
cross-sectional OCT (blue arrowhead), which appear to be organized in a honeycomb-like pattern on en face OCT (blue arrowhead). On cross-
sectional OCT and OCTA, a distinct hyperreflective surface surrounds the plateau interior and focal defects (yellow arrows) can be seen in some 
areas. An en face OCT taken at the plateau surface allows better appreciation of focal defects in this hyperreflective layer (en face OCTA: surface 
yellow arrow). Deep to these focal defects are hyperreflective features (FAF and en face OCT: green arrowheads) that are also seen on FAF as 
punctate hyperfluorescence within the confluent area of hypoautofluorescence. OCTA does not show flow within the plateau. </p>

<p>The Evolution of the Plateau 
IOVS j April 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 4 j 2354 </p>

<p>of the plateau. In a prior description, plateaus were thought to 
evolve in the outer retina and the hyperreflective line that is 
likely persistent BLamD was attributed to the OPL. 
17 In 
contrast, serial eye-tracked OCT imaging in our cases shows 
that changes occurred in the sub-RPE compartment, defined in 
atrophic eyes as the space external to persistent BLamD. 38,39  During development of a plateau, its thin hyperreflective 
surface, having emerged after RPE atrophy, is readily distin-
guishable from the overlying subsiding OPL (Figs. 1, 2). 
Plateaus are one route from drusenoid PED to atrophy, and 
they can be contrasted with a route via PED growth and 
collapse, which we recently described. 
10 Growth and collapse 
of large PED appear to be on a continuum with similar changes 
described for smaller drusen. 10 Why a PED in any one eye 
proceeds to a plateau or to collapse is not known at present. 
Our detailed description of plateaus will facilitate mechanistic 
thinking and guide the design of future studies with more 
patients to investigate associated risk factors that may have 
prognostic value. Evolution of a plateau entails at least four 
processes that are discernible at the histologic level and also in 
SD-OCT. In approximately chronologic order, the sequence of 
the evolution is as follows: loss of RPE, persistence of BLamD, 
followed by concurrent clearing of druse contents and 
occupation of druse space by cellular processes. The loss of </p>

<p>RPE is the point at which a drusenoid PED becomes a plateau, 
and it is marked by a thick, roughened, and highly hyper-
reflective band becoming thinner, smoother, and moderately 
hyperreflective. Hyperreflective foci over PED destined for 
plateaus were noted in our series, suggestive of anterior RPE 
migration, as also seen over PED destined for collapse. 10 The 
development of GA is hypothesized to proceed via two main 
pathways of RPE fate, 
29 including migration of fully pigmented 
and nucleated RPE into the retina (called ''sloughed'' and 
''intraretinal'') and shedding of non-nucleated granule aggre-
gates, possibly apoptotic remnants, into underlying BLamD. 
Our previous studies correlated intraretinal hyperreflective 
foci seen on in vivo and ex vivo OCT with anteriorly migrating 
RPE cells. 
10,11,35 Thus, we have good reason to suspect that the 
spherical hyperreflective intraretinal foci directly internal to 
the plateaus are also migrating RPE cells. 
The thin, moderately hyperreflective band draped over 
plateaus is persistent BLamD that maintains the shape of the 
original PED. BLamD is a stereotypically structured thick layer 
of basement membrane material that was initially used by Sarks 
et al. 34 to stage AMD eyes and has been recently shown to be 
clinically visible by SD-OCT. 
14,40,41 A basement membrane is a 
defining feature of an epithelium, as is the RPE. BLamD is 
composed of basement membrane proteins and carbohydrate-</p>

<p>FIGURE 5. Volume (mm 3 ) of PED measured in OCT over time. The point at which the plateaus form (complete loss of RPE from the hyperreflective 
RPE-BL complex over the PED) is shown by the dotted line. Patient 2 has two separate PEDs that evolve to two separate plateaus (A, B). Patient 6 
has a plateau in both the right eye (R) and the left eye (L). Only patients with an intact hyperreflective RPE-BL complex baseline were included in 
this analysis. When the plateau signature is first observed (black dotted line), a decrease in the volume that stabilizes on further follow-up. </p>

<p>The Evolution of the Plateau 
IOVS j April 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 4 j 2355 </p>

<p>bearing moieties. It is crossed by lipoprotein particles en route 
to BrM and choriocapillaris for apparent egress to the systemic 
circulation. 
42-44 BLamD observed on OCT is typically shad-
owed by the RPE. When BLamD is thick enough to be visible, it 
is observable as a hyporeflective layer. 14,40,41 After the RPE 
atrophies and can no longer cast a shadow, BLamD emerges as 
a moderately hyperreflective line of overall horizontal orienta-
tion that is sometimes corrugated. Outer retinal corrugations 
were proposed to be contraction folds of persistent BLamD 
created by loss of neovascular tissue or drusen/basal linear 
deposit previously located in the sub-RPE space. 
14 Here we 
extend this model to large drusenoid PED, on the grounds that 
corrugations and plateaus represent a continuum of OCT 
signatures involving persistent BLamD. Further, we propose on 
the basis of prior pathology literature a possible mechanism for 
how sub-RPE material may be cleared and the shape of 
persistent BLamD established. Thus, our observations on a 
histologic case with an apparent corrugation (Fig. 6) can be 
cautiously extrapolated to a plateau, which is larger. </p>

<p>Our clinical series showed that most of the PEDs that 
evolved into plateaus were drusenoid, and druse contents (e.g., 
lipids, proteins, and minerals 
24,45 ) appear to be removed, 
replaced, or both, over time. The cells and secreted factors 
(e.g., metalloproteinases, lipases) responsible for druse remov-
al are not established. Müller cells are candidates, because 
previous studies have shown that Müller cell processes may 
protrude into the sub-RPE space, 
14,34 extend over BrM, </p>

<p>46,47   and break up persistent BLamD. 
14,48 Müller cells are instru-
mental in forming ORT 
13 and delimiting the border of 
photoreceptor atrophy. 
39 Gliosis indicated by intense glial 
fibrillary acidic protein immunoreactivity is prominent in areas 
of severe photoreceptor loss and RPE atrophy, 
46,47,49 and 
Müller cells remain when all photoreceptors have died. 
13 In 
our exemplar histologic case, proteinaceous PED contents 
appear to be replaced by invading cellular processes (Fig. 6) 34  that are consistent with designation as Müller cells based on 
this literature. We hypothesize that plateau and corrugation 
formation requires extension of Müller cell processes through </p>

<p>FIGURE 6. Persistent BL deposit and Müller cell processes in GA in a 95-year-old white man. Submicrometer epoxy section with toluidine blue stain. 
Tissue was postfixed in osmium tannic acid paraphenylenediamine. (A-C) Ex vivo imaging of postmortem fundus. (A) CFP (top row left) shows a 
large area of atrophy of RPE extending to the optic nerve head but sparing the fovea. Choroidal vessels emptied of blood are visible due to 
intervening stromal melanocytes. Green arrowheads approximate the level of the histologic section shown in the top far right and bottom. (B) Ex 
vivo 488-nm autofluorescence shows loss of signal in the atrophic area. (C) Ex vivo NIR imaging shows small and highly reflective puncta in the 
atrophic area. Detailed (D) and panoramic (E) views of the atrophic area in histology. Red arrowheads: BLamD. Black arrowheads: BrM. NFL, nerve 
fiber layer; GCL, ganglion cell layer; IPL, inner plexiform layer; Dr, calcified druse. (D) Processes from Müller cells under a corrugation of persistent 
BLamD in the atrophic area. This corrugation overlies ''subducted'' cells of RPE origin 29 (teal arrowheads), which contain nuclei, spindle-shaped 
melanosomes, and lipofuscin, and are located external to BLamD, on BrM. Müller cell processes appear to enter the corrugation horizontally from 
the left (yellow arrow) and sweep the pigmented cells away. (E) BLamD is discontinuous and present at three separate locations (red arrows). All 
visible pigmented cells are ''subducted.'' In the normal Henle fiber layer, Müller cell processes are obliquely oriented (outer-center to inner-
periphery), and they are parallel to, and interleaved with, inner fibers of cone and rod photoreceptors. 31 In the presence of severe photoreceptor 
degeneration, the trajectories of gliotic Müller cell processes and remaining photoreceptors are oriented in many directions (yellow arrows). </p>

<p>The Evolution of the Plateau 
IOVS j April 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 4 j 2356 </p>

<p>defects in the RPE/BLamD complex (Figs. 4, 6) that occur 
during the life cycle of drusenoid PEDs. We further hypothe-
size that increasing hyporeflectivity observed within the sub-
RPE space during the progression of drusenoid PEDs repre-
sents a change in composition of the sub-RPE material that 
encourages the entry of these processes. 
The strength of this research is the long follow-up period for 
our patient cohort, with serial eye-tracked SD-OCT imaging for 
up to 7 years and notably dating back to before the 
development of GA in all but one eye. Another strength is 
the availability of up to nine separate imaging technologies, 
each specifically highlighting different tissue features in any 
one case and the availability of one illustrative histology case. 
Limitations include the small number of eyes and the absence 
of direct correlation of in vivo imaging to postmortem 
histology; hence, although our hypothesis of Müller cells 
involvement in plateau formation is credible and testable, </p>

<p>50   whether these cellular activities are directly visible in OCT is 
currently unknown. Our technique of volume measurement 
may be subject to variations according to OCT B-scan density 
between patients, but for our purpose of studying progression 
on a per-patient basis, this limitation was acceptable. To 
minimize inconsistencies, all patients in our study had eye-
tracked scans at each follow-up visit with similar density scan 
patterns available for analysis. 
Our study adds value to existing literature on PED by 
suggesting a role of Müller cell gliosis, elongation, and 
elaboration in the pathogenesis of AMD, which should be 
further explored in future studies. It is important for clinicians 
to be aware of plateaus and to distinguish them from OCT 
findings related to neovascular AMD, such as vascularized PEDs 
or signs of exudation, as OCTA imaging of three eyes in our 
study showed no evidence of neovascular flow within plateaus 
(Fig. 4). Plateau structures should not be confused with areas 
of subretinal fluid and treatment is not indicated for this 
finding. Finally, the distinctive reflectivity of persistent BLamD 
in outer retinal corrugations, and, now, plateaus, provides 
strong motivation for renaming the fourth outer retinal 
hyperreflective band of normal eyes, which is currently called 
the RPE-BrM complex, 23 to the RPE-BLam-BrM complex 
(abbreviated as RBB) 
26 to accommodate the appearance of 
PED and persistent BLamD in eyes with AMD. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank Jeffrey D. Messinger, DC, who performed the ex 
vivo imaging and histology in Figure 6. </p>

<p>Supported by the Macula Foundation, Inc., New York, NY, USA. 
CAC's research and the Project MACULA Web site has been 
supported by National Institutes of Health Grant R01EY06019, 
EyeSight Foundation of Alabama, International Retinal Research 
Foundation, Edward N. and Della L. Thome Foundation, the Arnold 
and Mabel Beckman Initiative for Macular Research, and Research 
to Prevent Blindness. </p>

<p>Disclosure: A.C.S. Tan, Bayer (R), Zeiss (R); P. Astroz, None; K.K. 
Dansingani, None; J.S. Slakter, Ohr Pharmaceutical (E), Gen-
entech/Roche (F), GSK (F), Janssen Cell Therapy (F), Regeneron 
(F), Sanofi (F), Santen (F), Thrombogenics (F); L.A. Yannuzzi, 
None; C.A. Curcio, Genentech (C), Novartis (C), Merck (C), 
Janssen Cell Therapy (C), Ora Clinical (C); K.B. Freund, 
Genentech (C), Optovue(C), Optos (C), Bayer Healthcare (C), 
Heidelberg Engineering (C) </p>



<p>The Evolution of the Plateau 
IOVS j April 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 4 j 2357 </p>



<p>The Evolution of the Plateau 
IOVS j April 2017 j Vol. 58 j No. 4 j 2358 </p>

</text></tei>