<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5112610" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. Tubulin tyrosine ligase like 12 (TTLL12), a member 
of the tubulin tyrosine ligase (TTLL) family, has not been 
completely characterized to date. It is reported that histone 
methylation, tubulin modifications, mitotic duration and chro-
mosome ploidy play crucial roles in a variety of cancers, and 
are related to tumorigenesis and cancer progression. A recent 
study showed that TTLL12 may be a pseudo-enzyme which 
has a SET-like domain and a TTL-like domain. In the present 
study, we first used 3'-rapid amplification of cDNA ends 
(3'-RACE) to amplify the transcripts of the TTLL12 gene from 
a human lung cancer cell line H1299, and unexpectedly discov-
ered a new transcript isoform characterized with an additional 
108-bp nucleotide sequence inserted at the location from 902 
to 903 bases of the TTLL12 coding sequence (CDS), where it 
also locates between exons 5 and 6. Next, utilizing RT-PCR 
and Sanger sequencing, we further confirmed the existence 
of such a new transcript isoform of TTLL12 in more human 
cancer cells including lung cancer cells and other cancer cells. 
Moreover, several lung cancer cell lines were found to display 
a much higher proportion of the new isoform compared with 
TTLL12 wild-type transcript. These results suggest that 
the new TTLL12 isoform may be of importance for proper 
maintenance of lung cancer cells. Therefore, the new isoform 
of TTLL12, with the inserted sequences probably acting as 
a disordered region, provides a novel perspective regarding 
TTLL12 functions in human cancers including lung cancer. </p>

<p>Tubulin tyrosine ligase like 12 (TTLL12) is the least character-
ized and the most divergent member of the TTLL family, which 
possesses catalytic functions in tubulin post-translational 
modifications (1-3). However, TTLL12 is said to be a pseudo-
enzyme having a phylogenetically conserved association 
of two nonfunctional domains including a SET-like domain 
and TTL-like domain, for which several differences exist in 
the structure, compared with other members of the TTLL 
family (4). These two domains are associated with histone 
methylation and tubulin modification, respectively. Recent 
studies have shown that TTLL12 could affect histone methyla-
tion, tubulin modification, mitotic duration and chromosome 
ploidy in human larynx cancer cells (5-8). In addition, there are 
numerous studies that have revealed that the TTLL family is 
closely linked to human cancer, such as neuroblastomas (9-11). 
For example, the TTLL family is often suppressed in human 
cancer (10) and is positively correlated with a poor prognosis 
in breast cancer (11). In prostate cancer, the level of TTLL12 
expression was found to be increased in the proliferating layer 
of benign tissue and during cancer progression to metas-
tasis (12,13). These findings suggest that TTLL12 may display 
the same pattern in other types of cancers, and it could play a 
crucial role in tumorigenesis and tumor progression. 
In the present study, we found a new transcript isoform 
of the TTLL12 gene, namely the 36 amino acid (AA) plus 
isoform, with an additional 108-bp nucleotide sequence 
inserted between exons 5 and 6 of the wild-type. This new 
isoform may be the result of alternative splicing, and we identi-
fied it in several lung cancer cell lines as well as other cancer 
cell lines. Notably, some of the lung cancer cell lines presented 
a much higher proportion of the 36AA plus isoform compared 
with the wild-type TTLL12 transcript, implying the potential 
role of the new isoform in lung cancer cells. Moreover, the 
inserted 36AA was predicted to be part of a disordered region, 
which can alter the molecular structure of the whole protein, 
and could affect adaptive and deleterious-on gene expression 
and function. 
Collectively, our discovery of a new transcript isoform of 
TTLL12 with an additional 108 bp, predicted to be a disordered </p>

<p>Identification of a novel transcript isoform of 
the TTLL12 gene in human cancers </p>

<p>RuILING WEN 
1,2* , YINGYING XIAO </p>

<p>1* </p>

<p>, YuHuA ZHANG 
2 , MIN YANG </p>

<p>2,3 </p>

<p>, YONGPING LIN 
3 and JuN TANG </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 KingMed Diagnostics and KingMed School of Laboratory Medicine, Guangzhou Medical university, Guangzhou, </p>

<p>Guangdong 510330; 
2 Cytate Institute for Precision Medicine and Innovation, Guangzhou Cytate Biomedical </p>

<p>Technologies Inc., Guangzhou, Guangdong 510663; 
3 Department of Clinical Laboratory and Research Center </p>

<p>of Translational Medicine, The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University, 
Guangzhou, Guangdong 510120, P.R. China </p>

<p>Received June 16, 2016; Accepted July 28, 2016 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/or.2016.5135 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Professor Jun Tang, KingMed Diagnostics </p>

<p>and KingMed School of Laboratory Medicine, Guangzhou 
Medical university, 2429 XinGang Dong Road, Guangzhou, 
Guangdong 510330, P.R. China 
E-mail: jtanguc@gmail.com </p>

<p>* Contributed equally </p>

<p>Key words: TTLL12, 3'-RACE, alternative splicing, disordered </p>

<p>region, cancers </p>

<p>WEN et al: A NOvEL TRANSCRIPT ISOFORM OF THE TTLL12 GENE </p>



<p>region, provides an alternative prospective to study the func-
tions of TTLL12 in tumor development and progression. In 
addition, our findings may also open a new window to explore 
potential targets related to post-translational modification of 
tubulin, which may eventually contribute to the development 
of more selective agents for cancer therapy. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Cell culture. Human lung cancer cell lines (H1299, 95-D, 
SPCA-1, A549, SK-MES-1, PC-9, H2170 and Hcc-827), human 
esophageal cancer cell lines (TE-11 and EC-109), human 
normal esophageal cell lines (HET-1A and HEEpiC), human 
acute monocytic leukemia cell line (THP-1), and human breast 
cancer cell line (MCF-7) were purchased from the Cell Bank 
of the China Academy of Science (Shanghai, China). THP-1, 
EC-109 and all the human lung cancer cell lines were grown 
in RPMI-1640 medium (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, 
uSA) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS; 
Gemini, Woodland, CA, uSA), 100 Iu/ml penicillin and 
100 µg/ml streptomycin. TE-11 and MCF-7 cells were grown 
in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM) culture 
medium (Life Technologies) supplemented with 10% FBS, 
100 Iu/ml penicillin and 100 µg/ml streptomycin. HET-1A 
and HEEpiC were grown in EpiCM-2 complete medium 
(ScienCell, Carlsbad, CA, uSA) with 100 Iu/ml penicillin and 
100 µg/ml streptomycin. All of the cells were cultured at 37˚C 
in a humidified incubator with 5% CO 2 . </p>

<p>RNA isolation. Total RNA was isolated from the cell cultures 
using TRIzol (Life Technologies) according to the manufac-
turer's instructions. The total RNA was quantified based on 
absorbance at 260 nm and the integrity of purified RNA was 
confirmed by agarose gel electrophoresis with a 28S/18S ratio 
not &lt;1. The total RNA was stored at -80˚C. </p>

<p>3'-Rapid amplification of cDNA ends (3'-RACE). As displayed 
in Fig. 1, the full length of TTLL12 cDNA was amplified by 
3'-RACE (SMARTer RACE 3' kit; Takara, Dalian, China). 
First-strand cDNA synthesis from total RNA of H1299 was 
performed using a traditional reverse transcription procedure, 
but with a special oligo(dT) primer: [3'-RACE CDS primer, 
5'-AAGCAGTGGTATCAACGCAGAGTAC (T) 30vN-3'; 
N=A, C, G or T; V=A, G, or C]. The first-strand cDNA synthesis 
reaction products were diluted with 10 µl Tricine-EDTA 
Buffer (Takara). The diluted first-strand cDNA was used as 
template and second-strand synthesis was amplified with a 3' 
gene-specific primer (3' GSP, 5'-GATTACGCCAAGCTTAG 
AGCACACAGACGGCGCGGGTG-3') and universal primer 
mix A (uPM; long, 5'-CTAATACGACTCACTATAGGGCA 
AGCAGTGGTATCAACGCAGAGT-3' and short, 5'-CTAAT 
ACGACTCACTATAGGGC-3'). The 3'-RACE DNA samples 
were electrophoresed on an agarose gel. The position of the 
desired fragment was located under uv light and the products 
were extracted with the NuceloSpin Gel and PCR Clean-up 
kit (Takara). </p>

<p>In-fusion cloning of RACE products. The 3'-RACE products 
were cloned into a puC19 vector by the In-Fusion HD Cloning 
kit (Takara) according to the protocol. The recombinant vectors </p>

<p>were then transformed into Stellar Competent Cells (Takara) 
and the bacteria was spread on LB plates containing 100 µg/ 
ml of ampicillin. All of the plates were incubated overnight at 
37˚C and individual isolated colonies were randomly selected 
from each experimental plate. Plasmid DNA was isolated 
using HiPure Plasmid EF Micro kit (Magen, Suzhou, China) 
according to the manufacturer's instructions. </p>

<p>RT-PCR. First-strand cDNA from total RNA was constructed 
by Transcript II All-in-One First-Strand cDNA Synthesis 
SuperMix kit (Life Technologies) following the manufacturer's 
instructions. The first-strand cDNA was then used as a template 
for PCR and the specific primers used were as follows: TTLL12 
sense primer 1, 5'-GAAGATGCCGGTGTGGTATA-3' and 
TTLL12 antisense primer 1, 5'-CACGTCCGTGTAGACCT 
TGA-3'; TTLL12 sense primer 2, 5'-GAGACTTTGCCTACG 
GAGAGA-3' and TTLL12 antisense primer 2, 5'-GCTGAG 
TTTCCTGTAGTCCTTGA-3'. Meanwhile, we used puC19 
vectors inserted with TTLL12 wild-type or TTLL12 36AA 
plus isoform as positive templates for PCR amplification of 
TTLL12 wild-type or 36AA plus isoform, respectively. PCR 
products were characterized by electrophoresing on agarose 
gel. The desired position was determined under uv light and 
PCR products were isolated by NuceloSpin Gel and PCR 
Clean-up kit. </p>

<p>Cloning and sequencing. PCR products were cloned into 
a pMD18-T Simple vector (Takara) and transformed into 
chemically competent cells. Individual colonies were grown 
overnight at 37˚C and plasmid DNA was isolated using HiPure 
Plasmid EF Micro kit according to the protocol, and processed 
to Sanger sequencing (Life Technologies). </p>

<p>Bioinformatics analysis. Protein structures of the TTLL12 wild-
type and new TTLL12 36AA plus isoform were predicted by 
bioinformatics softwares. The mRNA CDS and AA sequence 
of wild-type TTLL12 were gained in NCBI (http://www.ncbi. 
nlm.nih.gov/blast). In addition, the new transcript of TTLL12 
was translated into a new AA sequence using <rs type="software">DNAStar 
EditSeq</rs>. Then, the AA sequence of the new TTLL12 36AA 
plus isoform was aligned with the wild-type by NCBI protein 
blast (http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/). Physicochemical proper-
ties of the wild-type and new isoform were predicted by online 
tools <rs id="software-2" type="software">ProtParam</rs> and <rs type="software">ProtScale</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">http://www.expasy.ch/tools/protscale.html</rs>), respectively. Secondary structures of the 
wild-type and new isoform AA sequences were predicted by 
DNAStar Protean and online tool <rs id="software-4" type="software">CFSSP</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="url">http://www.biogem.org/tool/chou-fasman</rs>/). To further investigate the function of 
the new isoform of the TTLL12 transcript, we also used the 
online prediction tool <rs id="software-5" type="software">DisPort search</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="url">http://www.disport.org/search.php</rs>) to predict whether the additional 36 AA sequence 
is in a disordered region of TTLL12. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The full length of TTLL12 cDNA amplified by 3'-RACE from 
total RNA of H1299 cells. To gain the full length cDNA of 
TTLL12, we first generated the first-strand cDNA from total 
RNA of H1299 cells, and then the first-strand cDNA was used 
as the template to amplify the second-strand cDNA using </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY REPORTS 36: 3172-3180, 2016 </p>



<p>3'-RACE (Fig. 1). We aligned the 3'-RACE sequences with the 
consensus Homo sapiens TTLL12 genomic sequence (wild-
type) from GenBank, and then found an additional 108-bp 
nucleotide sequence located at CDS from 902 to 903 bases, 
between exons 5 and 6 (Fig. 2). This new isoform was called 
the 36AA plus isoform of TTLL12. </p>

<p>Detection of the new TTLL12 36AA plus isoform in both lung 
cancer cell lines and other cancer cell lines. To determine 
whether the TTLL12 36AA plus isoform exists in human 
cancers, we isolated total RNAs from 8 human lung cancer cell 
lines (H1299, 95-D, SPCA-1, A549, SK-MES-1, PC-9, H2170 
and Hcc-827), 2 human esophageal cancer cell lines (TE-11 
and EC-109), 2 human normal esophageal cell lines (HET-
1A, HEEpiC), human acute monocytic leukemia cell line 
THP-1 and human breast cancer cell line MCF-7. The reverse 
transcriptase-PCR products were then used as the template for 
PCR. In PCR, the plasmids harboring the 36AA plus isoform 
and wild-type of the TTLL12 gene sequence were used as the </p>

<p>positive templates for the 36AA plus isoform and wild-type, 
respectively. All the PCR products were electrophoresed on 
agarose gel. We then located the position of the desired frag-
ment under uv light and extracted the PCR products from 
the gel. Extracted PCR products were subsequently cloned into 
a pMD18-T Simple vector and transformed into chemically 
competent cells. All the plasmids from the positive clone were 
sequenced and aligned with the TTLL12 36AA plus isoform 
and TTLL12 wild-type. As a result, we found the product of the 
TTLL12 36AA plus isoform in all of the detected cell lines, and 
3 lung cancer cell lines (H1299, H2170 and Hcc-827) showed 
the highest proportion of the 36AA plus isoform compared to 
the wild-type (Fig. 3). In addition, the sequencing results of the 
plasmids extracted from the positive clone were aligned, and 
demonstrated that the PCR products were from the TTLL12 
36AA plus isoform (Fig. 4). Significantly, the TTLL12 36AA 
plus isoform was expressed more abundantly than the wild-
type in the human cancer cell lines, particularly in the human 
lung cancer cell lines, as compared with the human normal </p>

<p>Figure 2. Diagrams for DNA sequences of the TTLL12 wild-type and the new TTLL12 36AA plus isoform. The new TTLL12 36AA plus isoform was found 
to contain an additional 108-bp nucleotide sequence which was located in the CDS from nucleotides 902 to 903, between exons 5 and 6, when aligned with the 
GenBank consensus Homo sapiens TTLL12 genomic sequence. </p>

<p>Figure 1. The procedure of the 3'-rapid amplification of cDNA ends. The 3'-RACE first-strand cDNA was synthesized using a traditional reverse transcription 
procedure, but with a special oligo(dT) primer (3' CDS). The first-strand cDNA was used as the template for the second-strand synthesis. The second-strand 
cDNA was generated with a distinct gene-specific primer (GSP) and universal primers mix A (UPM, containing long universal primer and short universal 
primer). The GSP and uPM ensure the full length of TTLL12 cDNA can be synthesized. </p>

<p>WEN et al: A NOvEL TRANSCRIPT ISOFORM OF THE TTLL12 GENE </p>



<p>esophageal cell lines. The findings indicate that the new 
TTLL12 36AA plus isoform may play an important role in the 
development of various tumors. </p>

<p>Physicochemical properties of the TTLL12 wild-type and 
new 36AA plus isoform. The AA sequence of the TTLL12 
36AA plus isoform was obtained using DNAStar EditSeq 
and translating the DNA sequences. Then, the AA sequence 
of the new isoform was aligned with the TTLL12 wild-type, 
and we found an additional 36AA inserted at the location of 
281AA of the TTLL12 wild-type (Fig. 5A). Next, we predicted 
the physicochemical properties by <rs type="software">ProtParam</rs> and <rs type="software">ProtScale</rs>. 
The properties of TTLL12 wild-type and 36AA plus isoform 
AA sequences were predicted (Table I) as follows: the total 
number of negatively charged residues (Asp + Glu) was </p>

<p>93 and 96; and grand average of hydropathicity (GRAvY) 
was -0.390 and -0.338. In addition, the total hydropath-
icities of the two types of TTLL12 proteins are displayed in 
diagram (Fig. 5B and C). These results suggest that the two 
types of TTLL12 proteins are hydropathical molecules, and 
the 36AA plus isoform is more stable than the wild-type. </p>

<p>Secondary structures of TTLL12 wild-type and new 36AA 
plus isoform. Secondary structures of the TTLL12 wild-type 
and TTLL12 36AA plus isoform were predicted by DNAStar 
Protean and online tool CFSSP. As a result, the total residues 
of α-Helix , β-sheet and β-turn in the TTLL12 wild-type were 
476, 428 and 72, and the corresponding percentages were 73.9, 
66.5 and 11.2%, respectively (Fig. 6A). While total residues of 
α-Helix, β-sheet and β-turn in the TTLL12 36AA plus isoform </p>

<p>Figure 3. Detection of the new TTLL12 36AA plus isoform in human cancer cell lines. RT-PCR was employed in a series of cell lines including human lung 
cancer cell lines (H1299, 95-D, SPCA-1, A549, SK-MES-1, PC-9, H2170 and Hcc-827), human esophageal cancer cell lines (TE-11 and EC-109), human normal 
esophageal cell lines (HET-1A and HEEpiC), human acute monocytic leukemia cell line THP-1, and human breast cancer cell line MCF-7. PCR was performed 
using (A) TTLL12 sense primer 1 and TTLL12 antisense primer 1, and (B) TTLL12 sense primer 2 and TTLL12 antisense primer 2. The PCR product for posi-
tive control of the 36AA plus isoform was 484 bp in size while the size of the wild-type product was 376 bp, when the pair of primer 1 was used. The product 
for positive control of the 36AA plus isoform was 434 bp in size while the wild-type was 326 bp in size as the pair of primer 2 was used. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Alignment of DNA sequences of the TTLL12 PCR products. DNA sequences of the TTLL12 PCR products were aligned between (A) TTLL12 
wild-type and (B) new TTLL12 36AA plus isoform. </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY REPORTS 36: 3172-3180, 2016 </p>



<p>were 504, 455 and 75, and the corresponding percentages were 
74.1, 66.9 and 11.0%, respectively (Fig. 6B). The results showed 
that the proportions of different types of secondary structures 
in these two TTLL12 proteins were slightly different (Table II). </p>

<p>The additional 36AA is involved in a disordered region of 
TTLL12. To ascertain whether the additional 36AA in the </p>

<p>TTLL12 36AA plus isoform is in a disordered region of 
TTLL12, we firstly sought the disordered regions of the TTLL12 
36AA plus isoform by the opening accessible online resources 
DisProt search, and found that the peptide of 260AA to 299AA 
in the TTLL12 36AA plus isoform was highly identical to the 
disordered region of Bcl-2-like protein 11 (B2L11) (Fig. 7A), 
suggesting this peptide could act as a disordered region in the </p>

<p>Figure 5. Analysis of the amino acid sequences of the TTLL12 wild-type and new TTLL12 36AA plus isoform. The amino acid sequence of the new TTLL12 
36AA plus isoform was aligned with the TTLL12 wild-type by NCBI protein blast, and an additional 36 amino acid sequence was found (A). Hydropathicity 
of the wild-type (B) and the new 36AA plus isoform (C, red box indicates the inserted 36AA peptide) of TTLL12 was predicted by <rs type="software">ProtParam</rs> and <rs type="software">ProtScale</rs>, 
respectively. </p>

<p>WEN et al: A NOvEL TRANSCRIPT ISOFORM OF THE TTLL12 GENE </p>



<p>TTLL12 36AA plus isoform. As the additional 36AA are located 
between 281AA and 282AA in the TTLL12 36AA plus isoform, </p>

<p>we further explored whether the additional 36AA was in the 
disordered region of the protein. using <rs type="software">DisProt search</rs>, we found </p>

<p>Figure 6. Secondary structures of the TTLL12 wild-type and the new TTLL12 36AA plus isoform. Secondary structures of the (A) wild-type and (B) new 
36AA plus isoform of TTLL12 protein were predicted by online tool CFSSP. The orange box indicates the inserted 36AA peptide. </p>

<p>Figure 7. Analysis of the disordered region of the new TTLL12 36AA plus isoform. (A) The disordered region of the TTLL12 36AA plus isoform was predicted 
by entering the total TTLL12 amino acid sequence length into the opening accessible online resource <rs type="software">DisProt search</rs>. The region from amino acids 260-299 
of TTLL12 was highly aligned with the disordered region of Bcl-2-like protein 11 (B2L11). (B) The additional 36AA in the TTLL12 36AA plus isoform was 
pasted into <rs type="software">DisProt search</rs> and showed that it was partly aligned with the disordered region of brain natriuretic peptide-32 (BNP-32). </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY REPORTS 36: 3172-3180, 2016 </p>



<p>that the additional 36AA was partly identical to the disordered 
region of brain natriuretic peptide-32 (BNP-32) (Fig. 7B), giving 
the possibility that the 36AA could endow TTLL12 with new 
functions by acting as part of the disordered region. However, 
the biological functions of the new TTLL12 isoform in cancers 
remain to be further investigated. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The tubulin tyrosine ligase (TTLL) family is a superfamily 
consisting of 14 members and they mainly catalyze ligation 
of amino acids to tubulins (1-3). TTLL12 is the least charac-
terized and a most special member of the TTLL family, and 
it plays an important role in histone and tubulin modifica-
tions (14), mitotic duration and chromosome ploidy (5-8). It 
is the only member of the TTLL family without an assigned 
enzymatic function (15-17), and is said to be a pseudo-enzyme 
that has a phylogenetically conserved association of two 
domains including the SET-like domain and TTL-like domain 
in the N-and C-terminal of TTLL12, respectively. These two 
domains are related to histone methylation (18-22) and tubulin 
modifications (23-25) and then may contribute to tumori-
genesis (4). The TTLL family is often suppressed in human 
cancers (10) and is closely connected with the poor prognosis 
of breast cancer (11), suggesting that TTLL12 could also play 
roles in human cancers. It is reported that TTLL12 increases 
its expression in the proliferating layer of benign human 
prostate and more apparently during cancer progression to 
metastasis (12), suggesting that TTLL12 may be of importance 
in tumor progression. </p>

<p>In the present study, we found an aberrant TTLL12 tran-
script with an additional 108-bp nucleotide sequence inserted 
between exons 5 and 6. This new isoform, named the TTLL12 
36AA plus isoform, exhibited much more abundance, as 
compared with the TTLL12 wild-type, in human cancer cells 
as to normal cells, particularly in human lung cancer cells, 
suggesting it could be be considered a new mechanism of 
human cancer development. 
Alternatively splicing, by removing non-coding sequences 
(introns) and joining a coding part (exons) (26), plays an 
important role in gene expression (27-29). By the alternative 
splicing of precursor mRNAs (pre-mRNAs), multiple mRNAs 
and proteins can be generated from a single gene, and then the 
coding capacity of genomes is expanded through such a major 
mechanism (27-31). Furthermore, it has been reported that 
aberrant alternative splicing underlies various pathological 
processes, in particular tumorigenesis and tumor progres-
sion (32-34). The new TTLL12 36AA plus isoform may be 
the result of aberrant alternative splicing. Analysis by bioin-
formatics software showed that there are some differences in 
peptide physicochemical properties and protein secondary 
structure between the TTLL12 36AA plus isoform and the 
TTLL12 wild-type, suggesting that the new 36AA plus isoform 
could add some distinguished functions to TTLL12. 
The traditional pattern analysis of protein structural biology 
indicates that the well-defined three-dimensional structures 
are pivotal to biological functions of proteins. However, it has 
been reported that the disordered regions of proteins are chal-
lenging this traditional structure-function paradigm (35,36). 
Disordered regions are ubiquitous in cellular processes and </p>

<p>Table I. Physicochemical properties of the wild-type and new 36AA plus isoform of TTLL12. </p>

<p>Physicochemical properties 
Wild-type 
New 36AA plus isoform </p>

<p>Number of amino acids 
644 
680 
Molecule formulas 
C 3359 H 5101 N 905 O 959 S 28 
C 3537 H 5388 N 950 O 1006 S 29 
Molecular weight 
74,403.6 
78,245.1 
PI 
5.33 
5.34 
Instability index 
50.17 
49.77 
Aliphatic index 
79.18 
82.01 
Negatively charged residues (Asp + Glu) 
93 
96 
Positively charged residues (Arg + Lys) 
65 
68 
GRAvY 
-0.390 
-0.338 </p>

<p>TTLL, tubulin tyrosine ligase; PI, isoelectric point; GRAvY, grand average of hydropathicity. </p>

<p>Table II. Secondary structures of the TTLL12 wild-type and new 36AA plus isoform. </p>

<p>α-Helix </p>

<p>β-sheet 
β-turn </p>

<p>---------------------------------------------------
-----------------------------------------------------
---------------------------------------------------
TTLL12 type 
Total residues 
% 
Total residues 
% 
Total residues 
% </p>

<p>Wild-type 
476 
73.9 
428 
66.6 
72 
11.2 
New 36AA plus isoform 
504 
74.1 
455 
66.9 
75 
11.0 </p>

<p>TTLL, tubulin tyrosine ligase. </p>

<p>WEN et al: A NOvEL TRANSCRIPT ISOFORM OF THE TTLL12 GENE </p>



<p>human pathological conditions, but lack a well-defined, stable 
three-dimensional fold (37,38). Proteins with disordered 
regions often go through disorder-to-order when binding to 
their partners and they can remain partially or fully flexible 
in their bound state, and form fuzzy complexes (37,39-41). In 
contrast, proteins with disordered regions are mainly involved 
in enzymatic activity (37,42), including cell cycle regula-
tion (43), cell division and differentiation (42,44), which play 
critical roles in different types of cancers (45). In the present 
study, we report that the additional 36AA in the newly found 
TTLL12 protein isoform is a part of the disordered region, 
with the identity of those disordered regions identified in 
other functional proteins. Whether the 36AA is the binding 
site for certain proteins, such as those participating in post-
translational modification of tubulin or other important cell 
process, still needs to be investigated. 
The TTLL family has been shown to be partially co-local-
ized with vimentin and tubulin, which causes post-translational 
modifications of tubulin (5-8). Tubulin is a well acknowledged 
and important target for tumor therapy (46), but the precise 
functions of TTLL12 in tubulin modification are still poorly 
understood. Proteins related to post-translational modification 
are targets for new cancer therapeutic agents (47,48), thus 
the new 36AA plus isoform of TTLL12 protein may have 
the potential to become a novel strategy for cancer treatment 
involving tubulin post-translational modifications. Therefore, 
the functions and molecular mechanisms of the new 36AA 
plus isoform in cancer development remain to be investigated. 
In conclusion, our findings unveil a novel transcript isoform 
of TTLL12 with an additional 108-bp nucleotide sequence in 
the CDS. This TTLL12 36AA plus isoform could shed light on 
a novel mechanism of TTLL12 in human carcinogenesis and 
tumor progression, which may lead to a breakthrough of new 
potential targets for human cancer therapeutics. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The present study was supported by grants from the 
Science and Information Technology Bureau of Guangzhou 
(2011Y1-00022 and 2012-224-8, to J.T.), the Science and 
Information Technology Bureau of Guangzhou Haizhu District 
(2012-ZD-02, to J.T.), and the Guangzhou Medical university 
(B147048, to J.T.). </p>



<p>ONCOLOGY REPORTS 36: 3172-3180, 2016 </p>





</text></tei>