<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5293301" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Reconstructive procedures with pedicled and free flaps are associated 
with a risk of ischemia. Prostaglandin E1 (PGE1) is a hormone-like substance with 
known antiischemic and tissue-protective effects. The aim of this study was to evalu-
ate the effect of PGE1 on the microcirculation in random pattern skin flaps on rats. 
Methods: Twenty-four rats were divided into 2 groups: an intervention group given 
PGE1 for 6 hours and a control group given saline. The flap (2 × 10 cm) was created 
on the back of the rats, and the microcirculation was monitored with laser Doppler 
perfusion imaging in 5 different zones (1, proximal; 5, distal) before surgery and 
after 60, 180, and 360 minutes postoperatively. 
Results: Before surgery, there was no difference in the perfusion in any zones be-
tween the intervention group and the control group. The mean perfusion values 
in zone 1 in the intervention group were significantly higher than those in the 
control group at 60, 180, and 360 minutes postoperatively (P = 0.02, P = 0.05, and 
P = 0.04, respectively). At 360 minutes, we also found significantly higher levels of 
perfusion in the intervention group in zones 4 and 5 (P = 0.05 and P = 0.03, respec-
tively) compared with the controls. Comparing the perfusion at 360 to 60 minutes 
in the intervention group, we found a significant increase in microcirculation in all 
zones, which were not seen in the control group. 
Conclusion: PGE1 increased perfusion in the dermal random pattern flaps on rats. 
ExpErimEntal </p>



<p>PRS Global Open • 2017 </p>

<p>To clarify whether PGE1 could be a treatment option 
in ischemic flaps, we aimed to analyze the effect of PGE1 
on microcirculation in random pattern skin flaps by using 
LDPI in an experimental rat model. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>The research protocol was approved by the local ethics 
committee. </p>

<p>Experimental Procedure </p>

<p>Twenty-four female Wistar rats were included in the 
study, 12 in each group (mean weight, 270 g [209-308 
g]). They were divided into intervention and control 
groups and were anaesthetized with a commercial solu-
tion of 50% fentanyl and fluanisone (Hypnorm, 5 mg/ 
mL; Abbott Healthcare Products) and 50% midazolam 
(Dormicum, 5 mg/mL; Roche), which both first had 
been diluted separately with equal parts of sterile wa-
ter. The solution was administered subcutaneously 
(0.35 mL/100 g bodyweight), and maintenance doses 
of 0.1 to 0.2 mL were administered by titration. After 
anesthesia and shaving (with an electric shaver) of the 
rat's back to expose the skin, an intravenous line was 
inserted in the tail vein for administration of PGE1. A 
cranial-based random-pattern skin flap was then drawn 
on the back (width, 2 cm; length, 10 cm) and divided 
into 5 numbered zones (width, 2 cm; length, 2 cm); 
number 5 was the most distal part (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>LDPI and PGE Administration </p>

<p>In our study, LDPI (PIM 3; Perimed, Järfälla, Sweden) 
was used to measure cutaneous blood flow in the dorsal 
flap of the rat. The laser source of the PIM 3 emits a near-
infrared 670-nm laser beam. LDPI scans were made with 
high resolution, under appropriate light at the same light 
intensity and at a constant room temperature of 22°C. The 
distance between the scanner and the flap was 20 cm, and 
the area scanned was 40 × 110 mm. LDPI was first used to 
measure perfusion in the area drawn on the intact skin 
before skin incision (Fig. 2). The flap was subsequently 
elevated according to the drawing and immediately fixed 
(with staples) into its original position. 
PGE1 was then administered through the tail vein; the 
intervention group was given 4 μg/kg/h PGE1 (equiva-
lent to 0.3 mL/h) for 6 hours and the control group sa-
line 0.3 mL/h for 6 hours. The LDPI measurement was 
repeated after 60, 180, and 360 minutes (Fig. 3). 
The measurements quantify differences in flow within 
a single image in perfusion units. Perfusion and the area 
of each perfusion zone were calculated using the software 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">LDPI</rs> win <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.1</rs> (Perimed). </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Schematic illustration of the laser Doppler perfusion imag-
ing device and the planned flap on the dorsum of the rat. the pim 
3 scans a near-infrared 670-nm laser beam over the skin surface. a 
mirror moves the laser beam stepwise between successive measure-
ment points in a depth of 0.5 to 1 mm depending on the tissue prop-
erties. the laser Doppler probe emits and detects light scattered in 
the tissue. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. the picture shows an lDpi scan before the flap is raised. mov-
ing blood in the microvasculature causes a Doppler shift of scattered 
laser light, which is photodetected and then processed to build a 
color map of the blood flow. a digital camera records a colored clini-
cal photograph at the same time, which corresponds closely with 
the blood flow image both in size and aspect. note that the color 
code shift toward red indicates higher perfusion. </p>



<p>Tønseth et al. • The Effect of Prostaglandin E1 on Microcirculation </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>The Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (<rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 21</rs>; Armonk, N.Y.) was used for data analysis. 
Nonparametric tests were used because of relatively few 
samples. The Mann-Whitney U test was used to compare 
the intervention and control groups with respect to micro-
circulation for the different zones measured in perfusion 
units. The Wilcoxon signed rank test was used to compare 
microcirculation at 60 and 360 minutes for the different 
zones for each group. In addition, we have performed a 
Freidman test for intragroup comparison for the differ-
ent time intervals for each zone; P value less than 0.05 was 
considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>During the study, 3 rats died: 2 in the intervention 
group (after 240 and 300 minutes) and 1 in the control 
group (after 300 minutes). The groups were comparable 
in all zones, at baseline, with respect to perfusion in the 
planned flaps (Table 1). Mean perfusion values in zone 1 
were higher in the intervention group than in the control 
group at all measurement points (Table 1). In zones 4 to 
5, after 360 minutes, the intervention group had signifi-</p>

<p>cantly higher levels of perfusion than the control group 
(Table 1). For the intervention group, unlike the con-
trol group, microcirculation increased significantly in all 
zones after 360 minutes compared with the measured mi-
crocirculation at 60 minutes (Table 1). When performing 
an intragroup comparison for all different time intervals, 
we found significant differences only for the PGE1 group 
in zone 2 (P = 0.025), 3 (P = 0.004), 4 (P = 0.027), and 5 
(P = 0.045). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We found a significantly higher level of perfusion in 
the proximal zone in the intervention group compared 
with the control group at all time points and in the 2 most 
distal zones at 360 minutes. In the intervention group, we 
found significantly higher perfusion in all zones after 360 
minutes compared with 60 minutes. The increase that we 
found in superficial perfusion in the most distal parts of 
random flaps is credible because it is where perfusion is 
lowest and subsequently where ischemia most likely oc-
curs. The lack of increase before 6 hours after the start of 
infusion could indicate a delayed tissue-protective effect 
of PGE1. 
PGE1 is an endogenous acidic lipid that is derived 
enzymatically from fatty acids. When given intravenous-
ly, PGE1 is primarily metabolized by the lung and has a 
short half-life and must therefore be given as a continu-
ous infusion. The metabolites, 13,14-dihydro-PGE1 and 
15-keto-13,14-dihydro-PGE1, are excreted renally. 
20 The 
exact mechanism of PGE1 increasing microcirculation 
and preventing ischemia is not fully known. Kuwahara 
et al 
21 have shown that PGE1 induces vasodilatation and 
increases vascular flow in axial pattern flaps in rabbits. A 
study on ischemia-reperfusion injuries in musculocuta-
neous flaps in rats indicate that PGE1 downregulates the 
expression of intercellular adhesion molecules on the 
vascular endothelium and thereby reduces the endothe-
lial leukocyte adhesion in ischemic tissue. 
22 Furthermore, 
PGE1 has antiplatelet and fibrinolytic properties. 
10 All of 
these mechanisms could contribute to the antiischemic 
and tissue-protective effects of PGE1. 
Our decision to start infusion at the onset of the surgi-
cal procedure was based on findings by Emerson et al, </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>that is, that prostaglandins improved flap survival in rats 
when treatment started during surgery and continued af-
terward but had no effect when used as pretreatment. Our 
decision to use a dose of 4 μg/kg/h was based on a study 
by Suzuki et al, 
24 that is, in an experimental rat model, 
they found that 3 μg/kg/h of PGE1 resulted in increased 
flow and that 20 μg/kg/h resulted in an decreased flow 
in the flap. 
Many noninvasive clinical tools have been developed 
to assess the microcirculation of the skin. LDPI is an ex-
tension of the laser Doppler fluximetry (LDF) and has 
several advantages compared with LDF. LDPI is developed 
for horizontal mapping of cutaneous blood flow in a large 
area of the skin. It provides a noninvasive measurement of 
the capillary blood flow and is used both clinically and for 
research purposes. 
25,26 LDPI scans a larger area with better </p>

<p>Fig. 3. the picture shows the same rat after the flap is elevated. the 
black and blue colors indicate lower perfusion. </p>



<p>PRS Global Open • 2017 </p>

<p>spatial resolution than LDF and allows the researcher to 
measure the blood perfusion in a specified region of tis-
sue. Thus, reproducibility is probably increased compared 
with LDF. Furthermore, LDPI is better suited for interin-
dividual comparisons than LDF. 
27 The inability of LDPI to 
measure deep subcutaneous parts of flaps (limited to 0.5-
to 1-mm depth) was not a problem for our study because 
the outcome measure was the effect of PGE1 on microcir-
culation of the skin (not the subcutaneous tissue)-also, 
the depth measured was equal in both groups. Because 
temperature affects microcirculation of the skin, LDPI 
measurements have to be done at constant temperature </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>; 
all scans in our study were made under the same light in-
tensity and at a constant room temperature of 22°C. To 
avoid that hemodynamic differences in the rats affected 
the microcirculation and LDPI measurements, we infused 
the same amount of fluid in both groups. To reduce po-
tential pain and discomfort in the animals, we chose to 
evaluate the early effect of PGE1 before doing survival 
studies. 
Because the effect of PGE1 was assessed within the first 6 
hours after raising the flap, we were not able to determine if 
flaps developed necrosis in the distal part. To further inves-
tigate the effect of PGE1 in flaps, animal studies with longer 
observation times and histological samples are needed be-
fore clinical trials. We cannot out rule that biological varia-
tions have had an impact on our results and that a higher 
number of rats would have resulted in more consistent re-
sults. Additional studies addressing these issues are planned. </p>

<p>Kim Alexander Tønseth, MD, PhD 
Department of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery 
Oslo University Hospital 
Postboks 4950 Nydalen 
N-0424 Oslo, Norway 
E-mail: ktonseth@ous-hf.no </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Dr. Tindholdt for his advice and encouragement 
and the Department of Comparative Medicine, Oslo University 
Hospital, for their kind and helpful assistance with this study. We 
also thank statistician Are Hugo Pripp, Oslo University Hospital, 
Oslo, Norway, for his assistance with the statistical analyses. </p>



<p>Table 1. Microcirculation (Mean Values [±SD]) in Perfusion Units and Mean Differences (±SD) between Microcirculation at 
360 Minutes and 60 Minutes within Different Zones </p>

<p>Zone </p>

<p>Before Surgery </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>60 min </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>180 min </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>360 min </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>Δ 360 vs 60 min </p>

<p>PGE1 Control 
PGE1 Control 
PGE1 Control 
PGE1 Control 
PGE1 
P 
Control P </p>







</text></tei>