<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5287949" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The study of the etiological agents of community-acquired pulmonary infections is important to guide empirical therapy, requires 
constant updating, and has a substantial impact on the prognosis of patients. The objective of this study is to determine prospectively 
the etiology of community-acquired pulmonary infections in hospitalized adults living with HIV. Patients were submitted to an 
extended microbiological investigation that included molecular methods. The microbiological findings were evaluated according to 
severity of the disease and pneumococcal vaccine status. Two hundred twenty-four patients underwent the extended 
microbiological investigation of whom 143 (64%) had an etiology determined. Among the 143 patients with a determined etiology, 
Pneumocystis jirovecii was the main agent, detected in 52 (36%) cases and followed by Mycobacterium tuberculosis accounting for 
28 (20%) cases. Streptococcus pneumoniae and Rhinovirus were diagnosed in 22 (15%) cases each and influenza in 15 (10%) 
cases. Among atypical bacteria, Mycoplasma pneumoniae was responsible for 12 (8%) and Chlamydophila pneumoniae for 7 (5%) 
cases. Mixed infections occurred in 48 cases (34%). S pneumoniae was associated with higher severity scores and not associated 
with vaccine status. By using extended diagnostics, a microbiological agent could be determined in the majority of patients living with 
HIV affected by community-acquired pulmonary infections. Our findings can guide clinicians in the choice of empirical therapy for 
hospitalized pulmonary disease. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CAP = community-acquired pneumonia, HAART = highly active antiretroviral therapy, PCP = Pneumocystis 
jirovecii pneumonia, PCR = polymerase chain reaction, PLHIV = people living with the human immunodeficiency virus, PSI = 
pneumonia severity index. </p>

<p>Pneumonia is a major cause of morbidity and mortality in people 
living with the human immunodeficiency virus (PLHIV). Its 
incidence has decreased after the introduction of highly active 
antiretroviral therapy (HAART), but these patients still have a 
higher risk of acquiring this type of infection than the general 
population and have higher mortality rates. [1] </p>

<p>The epidemiology of HIV-associated pulmonary disease is 
complex and influenced by various factors, notably the regional 
prevalence of pathogens, such as tuberculosis, and the accessibil-
ity to health care, mainly the access to effective antiretroviral 
therapy and antimicrobial prophylaxis. [2] 
The study of the etiological agents of community-acquired 
pneumonia (CAP) is important to guide empirical therapy, 
requires constant updating, and has a substantial impact on the 
prognosis of patients. [3] However, few studies have systematical-
ly investigated the etiology of pneumonia in PLHIV and there is 
no consensus on a diagnostic algorithm for these patients. [4] 
A recently studied algorithm among non-HIV patients showed 
that, by supplementing traditional diagnostic methods with new 
polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-based methods, a high 
microbial yield is achieved among adults admitted to a general 
hospital due to CAP. This study also showed that mixed 
infections are frequent in this setting. [5] 
The main purpose of this study was to determine prospectively 
the etiology of community-acquired pulmonary infections in 
hospitalized adults living with HIV. This study also aimed to 
analyze the contribution of different diagnostic methods, 
including those PCR-based, as well of the impact of different 
approaches to microbiological evaluation and to evaluate the 
microbiological findings in relation to the CD4+ T-cell count, the 
severity of disease, and pneumococcal vaccine status. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>This is a subanalysis of a clinical trial that evaluated the treatment 
of CAP in 228 patients with HIV (Brazilian Clinical Trials </p>

<p>Editor: Chiyu Zhang. </p>

<p>This study was supported by FAPESP, São Paulo Research Foundation (grant 
number 2012/03834-7). </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>

<p>Supplemental Digital Content is available for this article. </p>

<p>a Scientific Division, Instituto de Infectologia Emílio Ribas, São Paulo, SP, Brazil, 
b Department of Medicine Solna, Infectious Diseases Unit, Karolinska Institutet, 
c Department of Infectious Diseases, Karolinska University Hospital, Stockholm, 
Sweden, d Emilio Ribas Institute of Infectious Diseases, e Department of Infectious 
Diseases, University of São Paulo Medical School, São Paulo, SP, Brazil. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Correspondence: Claudia Figueiredo-Mello, Avenue Doutor Arnaldo, 165, CEP 
01246-900, São Paulo, SP, Brazil (e-mail: claudiamello@ymail.com). </p>

<p>Copyright © 2017 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. 
This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-Non Commercial License 4.0 (CCBY-NC), where it is 
permissible to download, share, remix, transform, and buildup the work provided 
it is properly cited. The work cannot be used commercially without permission 
from the journal. </p>

<p>Medicine (2017) 96:4(e5778) </p>

<p>Received: 13 June 2016 / Received in final form: 5 December 2016 / Accepted: 
6 December 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000005778 </p>

<p>Observational Study </p>

<p>Medicine ® </p>

<p>OPEN </p>



<p>Registry: RBR-8wtq2b) carried out at "Instituto de Infectologia 
Emílio Ribas," a tertiary teaching infectious diseases hospital in 
São Paulo, Brazil. 
The eligibility criteria for participants were: patients 18 years 
of age or older with clinically and radiologically suspected CAP 
(cough and dyspnea or chest pain or sputum production and lung 
opacity detected by a radiologic method) who required antibiotic 
treatment (denoting a clinical diagnosis of bacterial pneumonia) 
and hospitalization, as decided by the attending physician. 
Patients were excluded if they fulfilled the following criteria: 
risk factors for healthcare-associated pneumonia as defined by 
the American Thoracic Society, [6] an etiology established prior to 
admission that justified all the symptoms, previously included, 
pregnancy, or breastfeeding (based on the exclusion criteria of the 
clinical trial). 
All patients provided written informed consent. The study 
occurred from September 2012 through July 2014 and was 
approved by the Institutional Committee of Ethics in Research 
(number 17/11). 
Data collected on admission included demographic, clinical 
characteristics, and pneumococcal vaccine status as reported by 
the patient. HIV viral load and CD4+ T-cell count were registered 
if collected within 3 months before admission or during 
hospitalization. 
Severity was evaluated using 2 scoring systems: pneumonia 
severity index (PSI) [7] and CURB-65, [8] as recommended by the 
American and British Thoracic Societies, respectively. The scores 
are able to stratify patients according to their risk of mortality. 
PSI is based on clinical, laboratory, and radiologic criteria, while 
CURB-65 is remarkable due to its simplicity, with only 5 criteria. 
Our Institute's CAP protocol states that all patients should 
have blood samples collected for bacterial (2 samples), fungal, 
and mycobacterial cultures. Sputum should be collected for direct 
examination for Pneumocystis jirovecii and acid-alcohol-resis-
tant bacilli and cultured for fungi and mycobacteria. 
Nasopharyngeal swabs were collected as indicated by the 
attending physician and tested for influenza A viruses (including 
H1N1) by PCR. Pleural effusion, tracheobronchial aspirates, 
bronchoalveolar lavage fluid, and biopsies were collected if 
clinically indicated. 
For analytic purposes, this approach was considered the 
routine investigation. All patients in this study also had at their 
disposal a wider microbiological investigation, considered here as 
the extended investigation (the extended investigation also 
included the tests available in the routine investigation). 
Blood samples were collected for serology for Chlamydophila 
pneumoniae and Mycoplasma pneumoniae. The first 50 patients 
had blood samples tested for Streptococcus pneumoniae and 
Haemophilus influenzae by PCR. 
For this study, sputum was also cultured for bacteria and 
urinary antigen test for Legionella pneumophila serogroup 1 was 
performed. 
Nonquantitative PCR methods were also used to investigate C 
pneumoniae, L pneumophila, M pneumoniae, P jirovecii, and 
adenovirus in respiratory samples. L pneumophila was only 
investigated in respiratory samples of the first 100 patients enrolled. 
A 100 consecutive patients who had nasopharyngeal swabs 
available were tested by real time-PCR for the following agents: 
parainfluenza viruses 1 to 3, respiratory syncytial virus, influenza 
viruses A and B, human coronaviruses CoV NL63, HKU1, 
OC43, and 229E, enterovirus, rhinovirus, adenovirus, bocavirus, 
human metapneumovirus, C pneumoniae, Bordetella pertussis, 
and M pneumoniae. [9] </p>

<p>Due to operational reasons, including difficulties in obtaining 
biological samples and scarcity of tests, not all the available 
microbiological analyses were performed for every included 
patient. 
The diagnostic criteria are outlined in the Supplemental Digital 
Content 1, http://links.lww.com/MD/B529. 
Categorical variables were compared using the x 2 test or Fisher 
exact test, the level of significance was set at P = 0.05 (2-tailed). 
Analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">10.1</rs>. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Enrolment </p>

<p>Two hundred twenty-eight patients were consecutively enrolled. 
Four patients were excluded after this stage: 1 withdrew consent, 
1 had no pneumonia (mistaken inclusion), 1 revealed an 
exclusion criterion after inclusion, and 1 had been previously 
included. Thus, 224 cases were included in the analyses. </p>

<p>3.2. Patients' characteristics </p>

<p>The mean age of the 224 patients was 40.3 years, with a standard 
deviation of 11.6 years, 154 (69%) were males, comorbidities 
were referred by approximately one-third of the patients, wherein 
liver disease and hypertension were the 2 most frequent. 
Approximately one-third of the patients who knew about their 
vaccination status referred antipneumococcal vaccination. 
The majority of patients never used, abandoned or referred 
irregular use of HAART. The CD4+ T-cell count was available 
for 90% of the patients, whereas 73% of cases were under 200 
cells/mm 3 . 
Regarding severity of pneumonia, 63 (28%) patients had a 
CURB-65 score greater than 1 and 88 (39%) had PSI above 3. 
The detailed baseline characteristics of the 224 patients are 
shown in the Supplementary Table 1, http://links.lww.com/MD/ 
B529. </p>

<p>3.3. Microbiological findings </p>

<p>The microbiological routine investigation was able to 
determine the etiological agents in 92 (41%) patients (Table 1). 
Based on this investigation, the main etiological agent was 
Mycobacterium tuberculosis accounting for 28 cases (30% of 
those with an etiology determined); followed by S pneumoniae, 
with 21 (23%) cases; influenza, 13 (14%) cases; and P jirovecii, 
11 (12%) cases. 
On the other hand, when including the extended microbiolog-
ical investigation a microbiological agent was determined in 143 
(64%) patients (Table 1). Among the 143 patients with 
microbiological findings, P jirovecii was the main agent, 
responsible for 52 (36%) cases. M tuberculosis was the cause 
of 28 (20%) cases, the same number as in the routine 
investigation. S pneumoniae and Rhinovirus were diagnosed in 
22 (15%) cases each, followed by influenza in 15 (10%) cases. 
Atypical bacteria were also diagnosed: M pneumoniae was 
responsible for 12 (8%) and C pneumoniae for 7 (5%) cases. 
Mixed etiology was found in a large proportion of cases (34%) 
by the extended microbiological investigation, the multiple 
combinations are detailed in the Supplementary Table 2, http:// 
links.lww.com/MD/B529 and the most frequent of which were: 
M pneumoniae + P jirovecii, P jirovecii + Rhinovirus, P jirovecii + 
M tuberculosis, and S pneumoniae + Rhinovirus. </p>

<p>Figueiredo-Mello et al. Medicine (2017) 96:4 
Medicine </p>



<p>The contribution of the different methods to the etiological 
diagnosis of the 7 most frequent agents is shown in Table 2, PCR-
based methods were essential for the diagnosis of atypical 
bacteria and viruses, besides contributing to ameliorate P jirovecii 
detection. 
Sputum cultures for bacteria were collected for 120 patients 
(54%), but in many cases this occurred after the beginning of 
antibiotic therapy, which hampers the interpretation of results 
difficult (the detailed results are presented in the Supplemental 
Digital Content 2, http://links.lww.com/MD/B529). The sputum 
cultures were used to corroborate diagnoses made by other 
methods and to provide antibiotic susceptibilities, but were not 
considered sufficient for a definitive diagnosis. 
Performing an analysis of causative agents based on CD4+ 
T-cell count, we found that the etiology of pneumonia in those 
severely immunosuppressed (CD4+ T-cell count&lt;200 cells/mm 3 ) 
was similar to those who were not. P jirovecii is the only agent 
more frequent in the former group, an expected finding taking 
into account our diagnostic criteria (the detailed analysis is 
available in the Supplementary Table 3, http://links.lww.com/ 
MD/B529). </p>

<p>Frequencies of the 7 most common agents were compared 
between patients admitted during the summer and winter (as 
shown in the Supplementary Table 4, http://links.lww.com/MD/ 
B529). Due to the limited amount of included patients we were 
not able to fully consider seasonal variation but we found that 
Mycoplasma pneumonia was detected exclusively during the 
summer season (P = 0.01). 
In relation to severity of disease, bacteria were most frequent 
among patients with higher scores, notably S pneumoniae, which 
was associated with severe cases as stratified by CURB-65 and PSI 
(Fig. 1). S pneumoniae infection frequency between individuals 
who referred pneumococcal vaccination when compared with 
individuals who denied having been vaccinated was not 
statistically different (6% vs 12%, P = 0.23). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>This study resorted to an extended microbiological investigation 
that included molecular methods; therefore, an etiological 
diagnosis was found in a high proportion of cases (64%). Our 
224 patients represent one of the largest cohorts of community-
acquired pulmonary infections in adults living with HIV and is 
the largest cohort in South America. The most frequently 
identified agents in this study were P jirovecii, M tuberculosis, 
and S pneumoniae. 
Although all patients included in the study had a clinical 
diagnosis of bacterial pneumonia on admission, bacterial disease 
was only confirmed microbiologically in 21% of them. There are 
recent studies that propose predictors and scores that could help 
the clinicians to distinguish between bacterial pneumonia and 
tuberculosis or P jirovecii pneumonia (PCP) in PLHIV, but their 
results are based on retrospective analyses; thus, their accuracy is 
not completely reliable. [10,11] It is difficult to predict the etiology 
of a pulmonary infiltrate in PLHIV based on clinical findings. 
In our study, we found that bacteria were more frequent among 
patients with higher severity scores and S pneumoniae was more 
common in patients with severe disease. This finding could be due 
to the fact that bacterial infections tend to produce more 
pronounced alterations of vital signs. It is noteworthy that no 
severity score is validated for PLHIV and that a specific mortality 
risk score in this population must be further investigated. [1] 
An elevated rate of mixed diagnosis (34%) was observed due to 
our extended investigation. This finding highlights the complexi-
ty involved in the choice of the empiric treatment for these 
patients and the need to perform extensive microbiological 
diagnosis. Mixed etiology had already been described as 
relatively common in PLHIV (around 11%) [10,12] and in the 
general population with CAP (35%). [5] A combination of viruses 
and bacteria was the most frequently found in those studies; 
however, our study stands out by encountering a large variety of 
different combinations. 
As expected, since tuberculosis is endemic in Brazil, we found a 
higher proportion of cases (20%) than in nonendemic countries, 
such as the United States (4.3%) [12] and Spain (8.5%). [10] A small 
Chilean study also found a lower frequency of tuberculosis (5%) 
but a higher percentage of Mycobacterium avium complex 
infection (12%). [13] The regional prevalence of specific diseases, 
such as tuberculosis, can guide clinicians on the different possible 
diagnoses for hospitalized PLHIV affected by pulmonary disease. 
In high prevalence settings, tuberculosis should be always 
investigated. 
Another interesting finding of our study is that, as we 
systematically investigated the atypical bacteria (M pneumoniae, </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Findings of microbiological investigation in 224 cases of commu-
nity-acquired pulmonary infections in hospitalized patients living 
with HIV. </p>

<p>Etiology </p>

<p>Routine 
investigation N (%) </p>

<p>Routine + extended 
investigation N (%) </p>

<p>Fungi 
17 (8) 
58 (26) 
Pneumocystis jirovecii 
11 
52 
Histoplasma spp. 
5 
5 
Cryptococcus spp. 
1 
1 
Bacteria 
27 (12) 
48 (21) 
Streptococcus pneumoniae 
21 
22 
Mycoplasma pneumoniae 
0 
1 2 
Chlamydophila pneumoniae 
0 
7 
Staphylococcus aureus 
4 
4 
Proteus spp. 
1 
1 
Rhodococcus spp. 
1 
1 
Bordetella pertussis 
0 
1 
Virus 
14 (6) 
48 (21) 
Rhinovirus 
0 
22 
Influenza A non H1N1 
9 
7 
Influenza A H3N2 
0 
2 
Adenovirus 
0 
4 
Influenza A H1N1 
4 
4 
Coronavirus 
0 
2 
Influenza B 
0 
2 
Metapneumovirus 
0 
2 
Bocavirus 
0 
1 
Cytomegalovirus 
1 
1 
Enterovirus 
0 
1 
Mycobacteria 
35 (16) 
35 (16) 
Mycobacterium tuberculosis 
28 
28 
Mycobacterium avium complex 
4 
4 
Mycobacteria 
2 
2 
Nonchromogenic slowly 
growing mycobacteria </p>

<p>1 
1 </p>

<p>Noninfectious causes 
13 (6) 
13 (6) 
Pulmonary thromboembolism 
4 
4 
Neoplastic diseases (except 
Kaposi sarcoma) </p>

<p>4 
4 </p>

<p>Kaposi sarcoma 
5 
5 
Mixed etiology 
13 (6) 
48 (21) 
Nonidentified etiology 
132 (59) 
81 (36) </p>

<p>Figueiredo-Mello et al. Medicine (2017) 96:4 
www.md-journal.com </p>



<p>C pneumoniae, and L pneumophila), we founded high rates of 
atypical bacterial infections (13%) in comparison with previous 
studies (&lt;3%), [10,12,13] although we did not find any cases of L 
pneumophila. Our finding of high rates of atypical bacterial 
infections may support atypical coverage in the empirical 
treatment of these patients. 
In Brazil, for PLHIV, the use of 23-valent polysaccharide 
vaccine is recommended. In this study, approximately one-third 
of the patients who knew about their vaccination status referred 
antipneumococcal vaccination. The frequency of S pneumoniae 
infection was similar for vaccinated and nonvaccinated 
individuals. This finding is in agreement with a systematic 
review that concluded that clinical evidence provides only 
moderate support for recommendation of pneumococcal 
polysaccharide vaccination in PLHIV, [14] however the number 
of confirmed pneumococcal pneumonias in our study was small 
and this may have limited the statistical power to detect 
differences. 
The time between the diagnosis of the HIV infection and 
admission in our study was long (median: 8.9 years) and the rates 
of regular use of HAART and of viral suppression were low (less 
than 20%), as well as the CD4+ T-cell counts (73% had CD4 
+&lt;200 cells/mm 3 ). Thus, our population were late presenters and 
presented poor adherence to HAART, as described previous-
ly [10,15] in CAP cohorts of PLHIV and that appears to be the 
general profile of PLHIV who require hospitalization. The 
immunosuppression of these patients probably contributed to the 
high proportion of mixed infections and to the difficulty in 
differentiating clinical and radiological features of the various 
etiological agents. 
In our study, we performed an extensive laboratory investiga-
tion, using a variety of molecular methods. Following our 
institutional routine investigation, we would have been capable 
of establishing the etiology in 41% of cases, which was increased 
to 64% with our extended investigation. This was particularly 
important for PCP and viral infections. </p>

<p>Molecular methods can improve the diagnosis of viral 
respiratory infections in hospitalized patients with lower 
respiratory tract infections [5,16] but bring us the challenge of 
how to interpret these findings since is difficult to define the virus 
as the causative agent of pneumonia. [17] A recent review suggests 
that the persistence of positive PCR for virus is infrequent (5%) 
in asymptomatic subjects among the general population. [18] This 
indicates that the finding of viral agents in symptomatic patients 
reflects the presence of viruses that often contribute to the disease, 
but further studies in symptomatic and asymptomatic PLHIV are 
needed to clarify this. 
When considering the diagnosis of PCP, the difficulty lies in 
distinguishing colonization from infection, [19] to date there has 
been no validated method described. In our study, we used CD4+ 
T-cell counts and clinical criteria to define PCP infection and in 
only 4 cases the diagnosis of PCP pneumonia was excluded by 
these criteria. 
Our study has limitations. First, not all patients who met the 
criteria for inclusion were enrolled in the study as we used 
convenience sampling. Second, the specimen collection was not 
complete for all enrolled patients. These issues are inherent to all 
trials enrolling patients with CAP. We have no reason to believe 
that the group of patients who were not included would have 
been substantially different from the group of patients that we 
studied. Selection bias is possible but unlikely. 
As in patients living with HIV mixed infections are very 
common we relied on at least 2 CAP definition criteria and the 
clinical judgment of the attending physician for the identification 
of possible bacterial CAP, expressed by the administration to 
treatment directed for bacteria. We believe this definition is valid 
since it reflects that real clinical situation and it is difficult to 
differentiate between bacterial and nonbacterial causes of 
community-acquired pulmonary infections in PLHIV. 
Our study is a single-center study, limiting its external 
validation, but this is attenuated by the fact that "Instituto de 
Infectologia Emílio Ribas" is the reference hospital for the </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>Contribution of different methods to the etiological diagnosis of the 7 most frequent pathogens causing community-acquired pulmonary 
infections in hospitalized patients living with HIV. </p>

<p>Pathogen </p>

<p>Pneumocystis 
jirovecii </p>

<p>Mycobacterium 
tuberculosis Rhinovirus </p>

<p>Streptococcus 
pneumoniae Influenza </p>

<p>Mycoplasma 
pneumoniae </p>

<p>Chlamydophila 
pneumoniae </p>

<p>No. (%) of patients with positive 
findings (n = 224) </p>

<p>52 (23%) 
28 (12%) 
22 (10%) 
22 (10%) 
15 (7%) 
12 (5%) 
7 (3%) </p>

<p>Blood 
Culture (n = 223) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>-
5 
-
21 
-
-
-
Serology (n = 180)  † 
-
-
-
-
-
7 
7 
PCR (n = 54)  † 
-
-
-
3 
-
-
-
Direct visualization (n = 121) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>5 
-
-
-
-
-
-
Sputum 
PCR (n = 141)  † 
38 
-
-
-
-
5 
0 
Culture for mycobacteria (n = 179) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>-
20 
-
-
-
-
-
Nasopharyngeal swab PCR for influenza A (n = 206) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>-
-
-
-
13 
-
-
PCR for multiple agents (n = 94)  † 
-
-
22 
-
4 
1 
1 
Endotracheal aspirate Direct visualization (n = 16) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>2 
-
-
-
-
-
-
PCR (n = 14)  † 
8 
-
-
-
-
0 
0 
Culture for mycobacteria (n = 31) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>-
3 
-
-
-
-
-
Bronchoalveolar lavage Direct visualization (n = 22) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>4 
-
-
-
-
-
-
PCR (n = 14)  † 
7 
-
-
-
-
0 
0 
Culture for mycobacteria (n = 30) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>-
5 
-
-
-
-
-
Lung 
Biopsy (n = 19) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>2 
-
-
-
-
-
-
Pleural fluid 
Culture for mycobacteria (n = 10) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>-
4 
-
-
-
-
-</p>

<p>n = number of cases in which each test was performed, PCR = polymerase chain reaction. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Methods performed in routine microbiological investigation. 
 † Methods performed in extended microbiological investigation. </p>

<p>Figueiredo-Mello et al. Medicine (2017) 96:4 
Medicine </p>



<p>metropolitan region of São Paulo (approximately 20 million 
inhabitants) and PLHIV comprise approximately 70% of the 
hospitalized patients. 
In conclusion, resorting to an extended microbiological 
evaluation, this study was capable of defining the etiological 
diagnosis of a high proportion of cases of community-acquired 
pulmonary infections in hospitalized patients living with HIV. 
The main agents were P jirovecii, M tuberculosis, and S 
pneumoniae. Mixed infections were very frequent. Prospective 
studies of the etiological agents of community-acquired pulmo-
nary infections in different settings and populations are 
important to guide clinical practices. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank all medical assistants and residents of 
"Instituto de Infectologia Emílio Ribas" who helped identify 
and care for patients, Edilene Silveira of "Instituto Adolfo Lutz" </p>

<p>Serology Section, Vera Lucia Pagliusi Castilho and all "Instituto 
de Infectologia Emílio Ribas" laboratory staff for their 
contribution with diagnostic issues, Adriana Coucolis and the 
pharmaceutics of "Instituto de Infectologia Emílio Ribas," who 
were crucial to the success of randomization. </p>



<p>25% 
24% </p>

<p>15% </p>

<p>5% 
6% </p>

<p>2% </p>

<p>21% </p>

<p>11% </p>

<p>7% </p>

<p>15% </p>

<p>12% </p>

<p>25% </p>

<p>22% </p>

<p>29% </p>

<p>22% </p>

<p>3% </p>

<p>5% </p>

<p>16% </p>

<p>8% </p>

<p>5% </p>

<p>14% 
13% </p>

<p>F u n g i 
P n e u m o c y s t i s 
j i r o v e c i i </p>

<p>B a c t e r i a 
S t r e p t o c o c c u s 
p n e u m o n i a e </p>

<p>M y c o p l a s m a 
p n e u m o n i a e </p>

<p>C l a m y d o p h i l a 
p n e u m o n i a e </p>

<p>V i r u s 
R h i n o v i r u s 
I n f l u e n z a 
M y c o b a c t e r i a M y c o b a c t e r i u m 
t u b e r c u l o s i s </p>

<p>ACCORDING TO CURB-65 SCORE </p>

<p>CURB-65 &lt; 2 
CURB-65 ≥ 2 </p>

<p>p &lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>Pneumocysss 
jirovecii </p>

<p>Streptococcus 
pneumoniae </p>

<p>Mycoplasma 
pneumoniae </p>

<p>Clamydophila 
pneumoniae </p>

<p>Mycobacterium 
tuberculosis </p>

<p>Fungi 
Bacteria 
Virus 
Influenza 
Rhinovirus 
Mycobacteria </p>

<p>N = 161 
N = 63 </p>

<p>p = 0.93 </p>

<p>p = 0.83 </p>

<p>p = 0.02 </p>

<p>p = 0.36 
p = 0.40 </p>

<p>p = 0.37 </p>

<p>p = 0.55 </p>

<p>p = 0.47 </p>

<p>p = 0.82 </p>

<p>p = 0.95 </p>

<p>26% </p>

<p>24% </p>

<p>18% </p>

<p>7% 
6% </p>

<p>4% </p>

<p>21% </p>

<p>9% </p>

<p>7% </p>

<p>18% </p>

<p>15% </p>

<p>24% </p>

<p>22% </p>

<p>20% </p>

<p>15% </p>

<p>5% </p>

<p>1% </p>

<p>18% </p>

<p>11% </p>

<p>6% </p>

<p>10% </p>

<p>8% </p>

<p>F u n g i 
P n e u m o c y s t i s 
j i r o v e c i i </p>

<p>B a c t e r i a 
S t r e p t o c o c c u s 
p n e u m o n i a e </p>

<p>M y c o p l a s m a 
p n e u m o n i a e </p>

<p>C l a m y d o p h i l a 
p n e u m o n i a e </p>

<p>V i r u s 
R h i n o v i r u s 
I n f l u e n z a 
M y c o b a c t e r i a M y c o b a c t e r i u m 
t u b e r c u l o s i s </p>

<p>ACCORDING </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>TO PNEUMONIA SEVERITY INDEX </p>

<p>PSI &lt; III 
PSI ≥ III </p>

<p>Pneumocysss 
jirovecii </p>

<p>Streptococcus 
pneumoniae </p>

<p>Mycoplasma 
pneumoniae </p>

<p>Clamydophila 
pneumoniae </p>

<p>Mycobacterium 
tuberculosis </p>

<p>Fungi 
Bacteria 
Virus 
Influenza 
Rhinovirus 
Mycobacteria </p>

<p>p = 0.75 </p>

<p>p = 0.64 </p>

<p>p = 0.60 </p>

<p>p = 0.66 </p>

<p>p = 0.25 </p>

<p>p = 0.66 </p>

<p>p = 0.53 </p>

<p>p = 0·62 </p>

<p>p = 0.10 </p>

<p>p = 0.10 
p = 0.04 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Microbiological findings in relation to severity of community-acquired pulmonary infections in hospitalized patients living with HIV. 
 *  *  Analyses restricted to </p>

<p>the seven most common microbiological agents. </p>

<p>Figueiredo-Mello et al. Medicine (2017) 96:4 
www.md-journal.com </p>







</text></tei>