<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5061105" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-12T00:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: MR fingerprinting (MRF) can be used for quantitative 
estimation of physical parameters in MRI. Here, we extend the 
method to incorporate B1 estimation. 
Methods: The acquisition is based on steady state free pre-
cession MR fingerprinting with a Cartesian trajectory. To 
increase the sensitivity to the B1 profile, abrupt changes in flip 
angle were introduced in the sequence. Slice profile and B1 
effects were included in the dictionary and the results from 
two-and three-dimensional (3D) acquisitions were compared. 
Acceleration was demonstrated using retrospective undersam-
pling in the phase encode directions of 3D data exploiting 
redundancy between MRF frames at the edges of k-space. 
Results: Without B1 estimation, T2 and B1 were inaccurate by 
more than 20%. Abrupt changes in flip angle improved B1 
maps. T1 and T2 values obtained with the new MRF methods 
agree with classical spin echo measurements and are inde-
pendent of the B1 field profile. When using view sharing 
reconstruction, results remained accurate (error &lt;10%) when 
sampling under 10% of k-space from the 3D data. 
Conclusion: The methods demonstrated here can successfully 
measure T1, T2, and B1. Errors due to slice profile can be sub-
stantially reduced by including its effect in the dictionary or 
acquiring data in 3D. Magn Reson Med 76:1127-1135, 2016. 
Physical properties of tissue contributing to MRI signal 
are significantly modified by disease. Quantitative 
changes in longitudinal (T1) and transverse (T2) relaxa-</p>

<p>tion times in discrete brain regions have been described in 
a host of different pathologies (1). However, reproducibil-
ity for quantitative MRI measurements has proved a 
challenge and requires lengthy scan times to obtain 
parameters sequentially. Consequently, quantitative 
parameters are rarely acquired, and most evaluations of 
MRI images are based on visual inspection without quan-
titative evaluation of underlying values of T1 and T2. 
Recently, a new approach of estimating multiple param-
eters at once, called MR fingerprinting (MRF), has been 
proposed (2). This method has the potential to be used for 
quantitative MRI routinely in both clinical and preclinical 
environments, enabling new tools for research and diag-
nosis. MR fingerprinting is based on the response of tis-
sues to repeated acquisition sequences without attaining 
the steady state. Voxel-wise responses are compared with 
a dictionary of simulated responses calculated from par-
ticular parameters (including, but not limited to, T1 and 
T2) and voxels are assigned the parameters from the best 
match to produce multiparametric maps. 
To date, MRF has been performed with fast gradient 
echo sequences based on steady state free precession 
(SSFP). For fully rewound sequences, the simulations for 
the fingerprint database must include an estimate of the 
voxel-wise frequency inhomogeneity for the correct sig-
nal evolution (2). Estimates of frequency offsets are not 
required for gradient-spoiled sequences (3). MRF meth-
ods have also been demonstrated in preclinical scanning 
of rodents (4). To apply the technique of MRF in small 
animals, where less B0 homogeneity is usually achieved, 
a gradient-spoiled approach has been used. 
Due to data redundancy between frames, MRF is well-
suited to acceleration by means of undersampling. When 
undersampling with a pseudorandom scheme, acquisi-
tions are affected by noise-like aliasing. The MRF tech-
nique has been shown to be remarkably robust to aliasing 
(2). This characteristic can be used to achieve alias-free 
maps in short times. However, anti-aliasing the MRI 
images before MRF pattern recognition is also possible 
(5,6). Here, we tested a reconstruction method with a sim-
ple anti-aliasing technique, sharing the edges of k-space 
between neighboring MRF frames before comparing signal 
evolution traces with the fingerprint database. 
Current MRF methods, both in the clinical and preclini-
cal environment, have been demonstrated assuming a per-
fectly rectangular slice profile and homogeneous 
excitation. However, these assumptions are violated in 
most practical MRI experiments. Indeed, it has been 
shown that different pulse shapes used for slice selection 
produce different T2 values (4). In addition, inhomogene-
ous radiofrequency excitation profiles are a common prob-
lem in both preclinical and clinical high-field scanners. 
We have extended the MRF approach by including a 
parameter for B1 in the signal evolution dictionary. In </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Istituto Nazionale di Fisica Nucleare (INFN), sezione di Pisa, Largo B. Pon-
tecorvo, Pisa (PI), Italy. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Wolfson Brain Imaging Centre, Department of Clinical Neurosciences, Uni-
versity of Cambridge, Addenbrooke's Hospital, Hills Road, Cambridge, 
United Kingdom 
Grant sponsor: INFN CNS 5; Grant number: 16555/2014. 
*Correspondence to: Guido Buonincontri, PhD, Istituto Nazionale di Fisica 
Nucleare (INFN), sezione di Pisa, Largo B. Pontecorvo, 3, 56127 Pisa (PI), 
Italy. E-mail: guido.buonincontri@pi.infn.it </p>

<p>Received 14 August 2015; revised 14 September 2015; accepted 14 
September 2015 
DOI 10.1002/mrm.26009 
Published online 28 October 2015 in Wiley Online Library (wileyonlinelibrary. 
com). 
V C 2015 The Authors Magnetic Resonance in Medicine published by Wiley 
Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of International Society for Magnetic Resonance in 
Medicine. This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use 
and distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the 
use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>Magnetic Resonance in Medicine 76:1127-1135 (2016) </p>



<p>addition, we have implemented a three-dimensional (3D) 
acquisition and tested a new anti-aliasing strategy 
applied before pattern recognition. The 3D acquisition 
has the advantage of broader coverage (particularly 
important for whole brain imaging) and the considerable 
reduction of slice profile effects. As well as B1 estima-
tion, we incorporated slice profile correction into the 
MRF reconstruction algorithm. All of these advances are 
demonstrated in a rodent head using a small-bore 
scanner. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>MRF Acquisition </p>

<p>Our scheme builds on SSFP MRF as recently reported 
(3). Briefly, an inversion pulse is applied before a train 
of fast imaging with steady state precession readouts 
with variable flip angles and repetition time delays. 
These rapid changes prevent a steady state from being 
achieved, but rather lead to signal variations dependent 
on local magnetic properties and the applied B1 field. 
Phase encoding is applied before each readout and 
rewound afterward so that each train of readouts has the 
same phase encoding value and the whole sequence is 
repeated for each phase encoding step. In our implemen-
tation, we used a train of 1000 frames taking 10 s to 
acquire a single k-line for all frames. To allow for return 
to equilibrium, we inserted a delay of 5 s before repeat-
ing the acquisition with a different level of phase 
encoding. 
To increase the sensitivity to different B1 values, we 
changed the final part of the sequence from the original 
MRF approach as shown in Figure 1. By using abrupt 
changes of the nominal excitation flip angle, our scheme 
introduces oscillations of signal the frequency of which 
is proportional to the obtained flip angle (Fig. 2), and 
independent from T2. This phenomenon has been previ-
ously described to perform B1 mapping using SSFP 
sequences (7). We used alternating blocks of 15 pulses of 
flip angle 90 followed by 15 pulses of flip angle 0 to </p>

<p>exploit the oscillatory behavior of the signal to resolve 
the B1 field. </p>

<p>Phantom Experiments </p>

<p>Two different phantoms were used, one to investigate 2D 
MRF and another to assess the accuracy of the measure-
ments across partitions of a 3D acquisition. First, we 
investigated 2D MRF. We imaged agarose gel samples 
with different T1s and T2s. We used a Bruker BioSpec 
47/40 system (Bruker Inc., Ettlingen, Germany) equipped 
with 400 mT/m gradients and a 12 cm diameter quadra-
ture birdcage coil used as a transceiver. We used sinc 
pulse of 2 ms for excitation. Each signal acquisition was 
preceded by an adiabatic inversion pulse (15 ms hyper-
bolic secant). MRF acquisitions were performed at the 
magnet isocenter on a single slice (3 mm slice thickness; 
field of view 7 cm; 64 Â 64 matrix yielding 1.1 mm reso-
lution with 50 kHz receiver bandwidth). 
To assess 3D MRF acquisitions, we used a matrix of 64 
Â 64 Â 64 for 0.5 mm isotropic resolution of a uniform 
gel with a T1 of 640 ms and a T2 of 74 ms. We measured 
the average value obtained in a region of interest through 
the slice direction (z). We compared the following meth-
ods: the original MRF method (with no B1 in the diction-
ary); the original MRF scheme including B1 in the 
dictionary; our new method with abrupt changes in flip 
angle; and classical methods (described below). </p>

<p>FIG. 1. SSFP MRF schemes. A: the TR pattern used in all acquisi-
tions. B: The FA pattern from the original SSFP MRF paper. C: 
The modified FA pattern demonstrated here, including abrupt 
changes in flip angle to increase the sensitivity to the B1 field. </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Simulation of the signal obtained with our novel MRF 
scheme (T1 ¼ 160 ms T2 ¼ 44 ms) at the end of the MRF train, in 
correspondence with abrupt changes in flip-angle. Flip angle 
changes between blocks of 45 and 0 (A), between 90 and 
0 (B), between 135 and 0 (C). </p>

<p> 
Buonincontri and Sawiak </p>

<p>Brain Experiments </p>

<p>A formalin-fixed Lister-hooded adult rat brain was 
imaged using a 35-mm-diameter linear birdcage coil for 
both signal transmission and reception. For 2D MRF, we 
tried three different excitation pulse shapes: sinc, her-
mite, and gauss each of 2 ms and bandwidth factors 
6.21, 5.40, and 2.74, respectively. Each slice had 0.5 mm 
thickness with a matrix of 64 Â 64. For 3D acquisitions, 
we used a 64 Â 64 Â 64 matrix with 0.5 mm isotropic 
resolution (a 2 ms sinc excitation pulse as above was 
used). 
As in the phantom acquisitions, each signal acquisi-
tion was preceded by an adiabatic inversion pulse 
(hyperbolic secant, length 15 ms, bandwidth factor 
77.86). The receiver bandwidth was 50 kHz in each case. </p>

<p>Undersampling and Anti-aliasing </p>

<p>The scan time for the fully sampled 3D acquisition was 
17 h 4 min (10 s MRF train þ 5 s recovery time) Â (64 Â 
64) phase encoding steps. To test our acceleration strat-
egy, we retrospectively undersampled the 3D acquisition 
of the ex vivo rat brain. Our undersampling scheme con-
sisted of a binary mask in the phase encode directions 
(k y -k z plane) as shown in Figure 3. Nonlinear sampling </p>

<p>based on a Gaussian distribution around the k-space cen-
ter was used with a uniform angular distribution. The 
Gaussian function had a standard deviation of 45% of 
the full k y and k z axes. Masks were created independ-
ently for each image frame. This could be implemented 
readily on a scanner by acquiring a list of pre-planned k-
lines varying for each frame. 
We tested three different approaches for reconstructing 
the data. First, zero-filling of the unsampled points was 
used. Second, zero-filling was combined with density-
correction for the sampled regions. Here, the correction 
was obtained using the inverse of the sampling probabil-
ity density function used for generating the k-space 
masks. Finally, we implemented a view-sharing strategy 
where unacquired k-space points were borrowed from 
the nearest frame with an acquired point at that location. 
As a result of our sampling density, points closer to the 
center, containing most of the contrast information, were 
acquired with higher temporal resolution. On the other 
hand, the edges of k-space, changing less during the 
MRF signal evolution, were acquired at lower temporal 
resolution. 
To test our undersampling strategy we prepared multi-
parametric MRF maps using data from the fully sampled 
k-space. We compared maps obtained from 18%, 9%, 
and 5% of k-space to values found using the full dataset. 
Values were measured in the whole brain and muscle 
tissue, which were automatically masked using thresh-
olding. The thresholding criterion was of a T1 between 0 
and 1 s, which included all brain and muscle for our 
formalin-fixed sample. 
To perform a time-matched comparison of our view 
sharing technique, we compared the use of only 8% of 
k-space for all frames with fully acquiring only the first 
80 frames of the MRF sequence. We compared root mean 
square errors relative with full sampling. For this experi-
ment, aimed at evaluating the efficiency of the acquisi-
tion only, we excluded B1 from the dictionary. </p>

<p>MRF Reconstruction </p>

<p>Signal simulations were performed using extended phase 
graphs (8), including gradient de-phasing as well as 
radiofrequency pulses and signal evolution. The pattern 
recognition reconstruction was implemented following 
(2). All code for simulation and pattern recognition was 
written in <rs id="software-0" type="software">Matlab</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Mathworks, Natick, MA</rs>). The diction-
ary contained values of T1 ranging from 80 ms to 1000 
ms in steps of 20 ms, and from 1 to 2.5 s in steps of 50 
ms. Values of T2 ranged from 10 ms to 100 ms in steps 
of 2 ms and from 105 ms to 250 ms in steps of 5 ms. B1 
was modelled by a flip-angle factor, a linear factor equal 
to the obtained flip angle divided by the desired flip 
angle. Values for this parameter were simulated from 50 
to 150% in 2% increments. </p>

<p>Comparison with Classical Estimation of T1, T2, and B1 </p>

<p>The quantitative maps using each scheme were com-
pared with standard estimation of T1, T2 and B1 using 
manufacturer-provided sequences. T1 and T2 were esti-
mated using spin-echo sequences with the same field of 
view (FOV) and matrix as the MRF acquisitions. The </p>

<p>FIG. 3. A: The undersampling scheme used for our accelerated 
3D acquisitions acquiring 9% of k-space. k-Space was retrospec-
tively undersampled in the phase encode directions ky and kz. B: 
The sampling density of k-space with our undersampling method. 
C: The values corresponding to the k-space location (32, 15, 15) 
for all frames when zero-filling. D: k-space data for the same loca-
tion as (C) when using our view-sharing method, applying a 
nearest-neighbor interpolation through time. </p>

<p>MRF with B1 Estimation </p>

<p>
MRF scan times were compared with scan times from 
the manufacturer-provided T1þT2 RARE relaxometry 
sequence, with unchanged sequence parameters [multie-
cho spin echo; echo time (TE): 11, 33, 55, 77, 99 ms; rep-
etition time (TR) 200, 400, 800, 1500, 3000, 4500 ms; 
number of excitations (NEX), 1] on the same geometry. 
For more accuracy, in our classical measurements we 
increased the number of sampled points and averages 
and used single echoes rather than multiecho to reduce 
the impact of system imperfections. However, for com-
parison of the time taken we used the acquisition time of 
the unmodified sequence. T1 was estimated with a spin 
echo sequence with variable TR (TR: 10,000, 3000, 1500, 
800, 400, 200 ms; TE: 11 ms; receiver bandwidth 48 kHz, 
3 NEX). T2 was estimated with single-echo spin-echo 
acquisitions with variable TE (TR: 2500 ms; TE: 12, 36, 
48, 60, 84, 108, 216, 324, 500 ms; receiver bandwidth 60 
kHz, 1 NEX). The B1 field was estimated using the 
double-angle method (7). Two gradient echo images were 
acquired with a flip angle of 45 and 90 on with the 
same FOV of the MRF acquisitions (TR/TE 15,000/2.9 
ms, excitation with sinc pulse of 2 ms duration, receiver 
bandwidth 78 kHz, 1 NEX). </p>

<p>Slice Profile Correction for 2D MRF </p>

<p>Due to slice profile imperfections, the flip angle seen by 
spins varies across the slice and includes some contribu-
tion from spins outside the slice. To account for these 
effects in the MRF dictionary, a novel correction method 
was developed. The Shinnar-Le Roux algorithm (15) was 
used to create a slice profile of 128 partitions based on the 
pulse waveforms used by the scanner. The extended phase 
graph simulation was performed for the central flip angle 
of each of the 128 partitions producing an MRF train for 
each. The signal of each frame was summed over each par-
tition to create a dictionary for each pulse waveform that 
takes account of the variability in flip angles experienced 
across the slice. We compared MRF maps derived from 
slice-profile corrected and the original dictionaries. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Reconstruction time for the parametric maps (including 
B1) from each slice was less than 1 min. Figure 4 com-
pares estimates of T1, T2, and B1 from our acquisitions 
with the original MRF train of delays and flip angles, 
our modified scheme and the standard spin echo 
method. Good agreement was seen between techniques 
for T1 with less than 5% discrepancy between methods. 
We found that the previously reported MRF sequences 
did not successfully resolve T2 and B1 effects with sub-
stantial errors in the estimation of both. Our new 
method, as a result of abrupt changes in flip angle, was 
able to better discriminate between these parameters. 
However, this 2D MRF acquisition did not provide a 
complete separation of T2 and B1 due to slice profile 
effects, and B1 maps systematically underestimated 
(&gt;10%) the true values when using a 2D acquisition. 
The effect of slice profiles on MRF results is clear in 
Figure 5 which shows MRF maps from the rat brain 
without slice profile correction for sinc, hermite, and 
gauss pulses with 3D MRF and spin echo methods for </p>

<p>comparison. As in the phantom, MRF-derived T1 meas-
urements do not appear to be sensitive to the slice pro-
file but the estimates for T2 and B1 vary considerably. 
Compared with 3D for sinc, hermite, and gauss shapes, 
T1 values differ by 3.8%, 3.8%, and 4.3%; T2 values dif-
fer by 6.5%, 17%, and 8.7%, and B1 differs by 8.4%, 
6.7%, and 36% (RMS errors). 
The discrepancies in the B1 estimation are consider-
ably reduced when slice profiles are taken into account 
(Fig. 6). The corresponding discrepancies for T1 values 
are 3.8%, 3.8%, and 4.6%; for T2 24%, 14.9%, and 7.7% 
and B1 4.0%, 2.6%, and 5.3% for sinc, hermite, and 
gauss shapes, respectively (RMS compared with 3D). 
Figure 7 shows profile plots of T1, T2, and B1 meas-
ured from a uniform phantom with the original MRF 
approach, MRF with correction for B1 with and without 
the abrupt flip angle changes in addition to the standard 
measurements. T1 measurement is accurate for MRF 
methods across the slice, where the spin-echo measure-
ment is inaccurate away from the center. Without model-
ing B1 in the dictionary, MRF overestimates the T1 
value. For T2 and B1, results are similar to Figure 4 with 
confounded estimates unless abrupt flip angle changes 
are introduced into the scheme. 
Figure 8 compares the different approaches to deal 
with undersampled data, and it can be seen that view-
sharing significantly outperforms the other methods. A 
comparison of the view-sharing method on 8% kspace 
with a time-matched acquisition fully acquiring just the 
first 80 MRF frames revealed that spatial undersampling 
has a high efficiency. A view sharing method using only 
8% of k-space gave lower errors (DT1 ¼ 35 ms; DT2 ¼ 
4 ms; RMS compared with full) than a time-matched 
comparison using only the first 80 elements of the MRF 
sequence (DT1¼ 450 ms; DT2¼ 50 ms; RMS compared 
with full). </p>

<p>FIG. 4. Results comparing the original MRF scheme, our modified 
scheme with abrupt changes in flip angle (dFA) and the maps 
using classical methods (described in methods). The original 
scheme confounds T2 and B1 effects, while scheme 2 can, 
though here with 2D acquisitions a systematic underestimation of 
B1 is seen relative to the double angle method. </p>

<p> 
Buonincontri and Sawiak </p>

<p>FIG. 6. Comparison between MRF results for T2 and B1 with and without slice profile correction (labeled SLR). The 3D measurements 
are also reported for comparison. </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Comparison between 2D MRF with different slice profiles, our 3D MRF acquisition, and classical methods. When performing 2D 
imaging, only using a sinc excitation agreed with the 3D acquisition, despite a constant negative bias in B1. 3D MRF slightly underesti-
mated both T1 and T2 compared with spin echo measurements, but agreed well with double-angle B1 measurements. </p>

<p>MRF with B1 Estimation </p>

<p>
Acquisitions using 18% of k-space (3 h long) and 9% 
of k-space (1.5 h long), generated quantitative maps 
(Fig. 9) within 10% error of the fully sampled case. All 
the undersampled MRF scans were faster than the </p>

<p>manufacturer-provided 
T1þT2 
RARE 
relaxometry 
sequence on the same geometry (4.5 h). Further accelera-
tion factors still generated acceptable results. MRF maps 
from only 5% of k-space are shown in Supporting Figure 
S1, which is available online. This corresponds to an 
acquisition of approximately 50 min for the whole brain. 
For this acquisition, some areas of the B1 and T2 maps 
presented errors superior to 10%, mostly in remote areas 
of the head where B1 is changing more rapidly and in 
areas with low SNR (e.g., due to the inclusion of air in 
the ex vivo sample). 
Values for mean error due to undersampling, as well 
as 5% and 95% percentiles are reported in Table 1. 
Undersampling the acquisitions did not significantly 
bias the T1, T2, and B1 estimates. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We have shown that B1 estimation can be used in an 
MRF framework and that this acquisition can be 
extended to 3D. This is particularly important for the 
application of MRF to small-bore preclinical scanners 
where small RF coils may have significant inhomogene-
ity. The inclusion of B1 effects will be of growing impor-
tance, as these are problematic for body imaging at both 
3T and 7T (10,11) and brain imaging at 7T (12). 
Images in MRF scans can be reconstructed from under-
sampled k-space, as the MRF reconstruction "sees 
through" aliasing (2). However, anti-aliasing strategies 
may permit higher undersampling factors. Here we have 
successfully demonstrated a simple strategy to deal with 
undersampled k-space acquisitions. In our scheme, non-
acquired k-space points in one frame are "borrowed" 
from neighboring frames where these had been acquired. 
This concept, similar to keyhole imaging (13), is based 
on the fact that the image contrast is mainly in the center 
of k-space, while the image details, which are unchanged 
between frames, are in the edges of k-space. Therefore, 
the signal evolution is estimated well when only the cen-
tral part of k-space is updated in subsequent frames. 
When doing slice selective imaging, different locations 
in the slice are excited with a different flip angle leading 
to partial volume effects. In MRF, partial volume effects 
have a different behavior with respect to conventional 
imaging (14). In conventional imaging, different sub-
voxel areas are averaged within a voxel, while MRF </p>

<p>FIG. 7. Quantitative measurements on a uniform phantom plotted 
through the 3D slice direction. Classical estimates of T1 and T2 
were biased due to imperfect B1. The original MRF scheme with 
no B1 estimate (in blue) presented a bias dependent on B1. The 
original scheme including B1 estimation (dotted green) could not 
discriminate between T2 and B1 effects. Our new MRF acquisition 
including abrupt changes in flip-angle (black, labelled dFA) had no 
significant bias, and compared well with the expected values 
(magenta). At the edges of the slice, some T2 underestimation 
can be observed. </p>

<p>FIG. 8. Quantitative T1 maps from an axial slice of our multiparametric 3D MRF acquisition, comparing fully sampled data with maps 
obtained acquiring only 8% of k-space. Zero filling generates artifacts due to nonuniform sampling of k-space; density correction of the 
zero-filled data recovers the details in the image but results in a noisy map; sharing k-space points between neighboring time frames 
reduces the noise. </p>

<p> 
Buonincontri and Sawiak </p>

<p>tends more toward the most represented sub-voxel area, 
as it can be noted when using different pulses in Figure 
5, where B1 is not homogeneous throughout the voxel. 
We demonstrated that the slice profile can be directly 
included in the simulation, performing independent cal-
culations for single sub-voxel areas using slice profiles 
derived from the Shinnar-Le Roux algorithm (15). Resid-</p>

<p>ual errors in T2 are likely due to nonideal behavior of 
the RF transmission pipeline. To check this, we used 
actual flip angle imaging (16) to measure the mean flip 
angle in a uniform phantom achieved when different 
pulse shapes were used. The measured flip angles were 
found to be factors of 1.07 for sinc, 1.06 for hermite, and 
0.96 for gauss pulses. Introducing these factors for flip </p>

<p>FIG. 9. Comparison of a full 3D dataset of a fixed rat brain with the maps reconstructed using only 18% of the data and 9% of the 
data. The undersampled sets agree well with the fully sampled dataset. </p>

<p>Table 1 
Error of Undersampled Acquisitions with Respect to Full, Calculated on a Mask Including the Brain and Muscle a </p>

<p>Error (full -undersampled), mean [5% percentile ; 95% percentile] </p>

<p>T1(ms) 
T2(ms) 
B1 </p>

<p>18% k-space 
À1.8 [À40; 40] 
0.9 [À7; 4] 
0.003 [À0.04; 0.03] 
9% k-space 
À6 [À60; 60] 
À1.9 [À11;5] 
À0.003 [À0.06; 0.05] 
5% k-space 
À11 [À100; 80] 
À3.2 [À18; 9] 
0.0008 [À0.09; 0.1] </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Data are expressed as mean error [5% percentile; 95% percentile]. </p>

<p>MRF with B1 Estimation </p>

<p>
angles into the dictionary reduced the errors but further 
investigation of imperfect RF transmission was beyond 
the scope of this study. 
The adverse effects of slice distortion can be largely 
mitigated when selecting a large slab for 3D imaging, as 
in this case the slice profile problem becomes part of the 
B1 estimation. When estimating parameters through the 
slice, we saw unbiased results with our new method. 
However, we still observed underestimation of T2 in the 
outermost partitions. Future acquisitions with non-
selective pulses could offer a better solution for an 
extended coverage. Previous work in the context of 
radial k-space acquisition found that 3D scans offer more 
possibility of undersampling the k-space with respect to 
2D slices (17). Another advantage of 3D imaging is its 
applicability to brain imaging cohort studies. Brain imag-
ing methods to compare groups of subjects usually bene-
fit from isotropic 3D acquisitions to meaningfully 
compare regions after image registration (18). In addition, 
whole-brain coverage can be achieved in a single acquisi-
tion when using 3D MRF methods. 
By accelerating the acquisition more than 10-fold, our 
method is significantly faster than MRF protocols cur-
rently available for small animals (4). The undersampling 
technique described here can be used to significantly 
shorten scan times, and achieve acquisition durations 
suitable for in vivo imaging of rodents. Current techni-
ques for voxel-wise comparison of rodent brains include 
voxel-based morphometry (19) and tensor-based mor-
phometry (20). However, both approaches are more con-
cerned with image geometry rather than the signal levels 
seen, as a consistent wide-spread approach for quantita-
tive imaging between centers has not appeared to date in 
the literature. Fully quantitative, 3D acquisitions could 
be used in this context to obtain standardized multicen-
ter data for analysis of different disease models and 
treatments. 
The scan times obtained here, of the order of 1.5 h, 
can be used in the preclinical environment, however, 
they would be prohibitive in human studies. The effi-
ciency of our method is limited when compared with 
the gold standard of human quantitative imaging featur-
ing acceleration with compressed sensing and parallel 
imaging. The introduction of array coils, as well as more 
sophisticated anti-aliasing strategies, could be used to 
further accelerate MRF acquisitions. Using iterative 
reconstruction such as compressed sensing is a promis-
ing strategy for anti-aliasing the images before pattern 
recognition (5,6). However, the large size of 4D datasets 
represents a challenge for iterative algorithms, and new 
strategies are needed to deal with the high computa-
tional demand. For instance, new compressed sensing 
algorithms based on fast, dedicated processing units of 
high-performance graphics cards (GPUs) developed for 
cardiac MRI hold promise for reconstruction of large 
MRF datasets (17). In addition, fast algorithms such as 
split Bregman could be used to accelerate compressed 
sensing of large datasets (21), perhaps including spatio-
temporal total variation constraints (22). 
In the current implementation, we waited for full 
relaxation (5 Â T1) between acquiring k-space lines. 
However, this is not necessary to perform MRF. In the </p>

<p>future, optimized MRF acquisitions could be used to fur-
ther shorten scan times. In addition, non-Cartesian meth-
ods have been demonstrated in the preclinical 
environment as well as for clinical scanners. Non-
Cartesian acquisitions yield better efficiency and anti-
aliasing of undersampled data with respect to Cartesian 
in several preclinical applications, e.g., Buonincontri 
et al (23). MR fingerprinting has already been demon-
strated using arbitrary gradient waveforms, for instance 
derived from music to increase patient's comfort (24). 
Although the use of spiral trajectories has shown great 
speed benefits for MRF in clinical scanners, we are 
unaware of implementations of spiral MRF in small-bore 
MRI scanners. The use of novel 3D non-Cartesian strat-
egies could further accelerate the acquisition bringing 
3D, isotropic MRF methods into both preclinical and 
clinical applications. Direct reductions in scan time can 
also be achieved by reducing the number of frames (25). 
Including the slice profile correction increased the 
computational burden of the dictionary creation propor-
tionally to the number of partitions used. However, this 
correction had no impact on the pattern recognition algo-
rithm, as the dictionary size remained unchanged. It 
took approximately a minute per slice to reconstruct the 
MRF data here, and this is a reasonable time frame. It is 
possible to include further parameters in the reconstruc-
tion though this is prohibitive as the reconstruction time 
will scale exponentially with the number of parameters. 
Reconstruction times and memory occupancy represent 
the largest current limitation of MRF. New methods to 
meaningfully compress the dictionary (26) and perform 
more sophisticated matching (27) are currently being 
studied. New reconstruction methods could permit the 
measurement of more parameters simultaneously, such 
as T2* and diffusion, enhancing the sensitivity of novel 
MRF techniques. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>We have demonstrated a method for incorporating B1 
estimation into MRF and extended the protocol to 3D 
imaging. Our methods greatly reduced problems seen 
with particular pulse shapes and B1 inhomogeneity, 
improving the accuracy of parameters estimated from 
MRF. We showed that view sharing between MRF frames 
produces accurate results acquiring less than 10% of the 
full dataset. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENT </p>

<p>G.B. was funded by INFN CNS 5. </p>



<p> 
Buonincontri and Sawiak </p>



<p>SUPPORTING INFORMATION </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the online version of 
this article. 
Supporting Figure S1. Performance of 3D MRF acquiring only 5% of k-
space per frame (50 min), compared with full acquisition (17 h). Some 
sparse areas of the T2 and B1 maps have errors between 10 and 20% 
compared with the full acquisition. </p>

<p>MRF with B1 Estimation </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>