<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5098113" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: The effects of exercise volume on the pattern of muscle activity is one of the most important factors in training man-
agement and injury risk reduction. In the lower limb, the quadriceps muscle which plays a determining role in performing the 
stance and other karate techniques could be injured in intensive exercise and may induce anterior knee pain in athletes. </p>

<p>Objectives: The aim of this study was to determine the relationship between training volume and muscle activity of vastus medialis 
and vastus lateralis and its association with anterior knee pain in karate elites. </p>

<p>Patients and Methods: Male and female athletes from national junior and cadet karate team (14 to 18 years) were invited to partici-
pate in the study at the beginning and the end of the training camps. Studies involved measurement of electromyographic muscle 
activity of vastus medialis and vastus lateralis in both lower extremities with surface electromyography device and assessment of 
movement by electrogoniometery. Muscle activity was recorded in three tests of dachi, walking up and walking down stairs. Simul-
taneously, anterior knee pain was evaluated using visual analogue scale and anterior knee pain scale questionnaire. </p>

<p>Results: Eight athletes of a total number of 23 reported increased ratings of pain in their right knees. No differences in muscle 
activity were observed in tests of Dachi and stairs between the groups with and without pain. Comparing Dachi task pattern at 
the beginning and end of training camps, there was no significant difference in pattern of biomechanical movement; however, 
reducing the amount of muscle activity in early and late phases of tasks was observed in electromyographic assessment. </p>

<p>Conclusions: The results showed that performing the same task after a six-week training period, less muscle activity was required 
in all phases in two groups of tasks, including karate-specific movement (dachi) and activities of daily living (up or down stairs). </p>

<p>Keywords: Vastus Medialis, Vastus Lateralus, Exercise Volume, Karate </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>A comprehensive understanding of muscle activity 
pattern during execution of different maneuvers and tech-
niques is one of the most important factors in set-out of 
exercise volume and reducing the risk of injury in profes-
sional athletes. Among the lower limb muscles, quadri-
ceps has a main role in implementation of karate tech-
niques and can be susceptible to overtraining addressed 
by anterior knee pain. Anterior knee pain is a common de-
bilitating complaint in athletes and one of the most im-
portant differential diagnoses is patellofemoral pain syn-
drome (PFPS) (1, 2). </p>

<p>Although PFPS is the most common cause of knee pain, 
many studies have been conducted to investigate the un-
derlying pathomechanics (1). Several causes are involved 
in the pathogenesis of the syndrome, which is mainly di-
vided into two categories: internal and external factors 
(1). Imbalanced forces exerted on patella by VMO and 
VL, improper activation time, tightness of lateral retinac-
ulum, hypermobile patella and abnormal patellar track-
ing due to structural malalignment in lower extremity are 
the most important internal factors. Kinematic errors, in-
crease in the duration and frequency of physical activity 
and training volume are external factors (1). One of the </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016, Sports Medicine Research Center. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 
International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial usages, provided the 
original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Safar Cherati A et al. </p>

<p>highly regarded basic pathomechanics in PFPS is delay in 
the activation of vastus medialis (VM) to vastus lateralis 
(VL) Which in theory could induce laterally pulled patella 
and anterior knee pain (3, 4). 
Surface electromyography (sEMG) is a non-invasive 
technique for measuring electrical activity of muscles. 
Moreover, it reveals the onset and amplitude of muscle ac-
tivity during voluntary dynamic contraction (5). Although 
most of the previous studies investigated the difference in 
onset timing between the VM and VL, some sEMG studies 
have shown that the ratio of the electrical activity of the VM 
to VL is different in healthy subjects versus patients with 
patellofemoral pain (6-11). 
The role of overload on VM/VL activity was evaluated by 
Herrington et al. They assessed sEMG activity of muscles 
during different load (12) but few prospective studies have 
been conducted on PFPS in athletes. 
PFPS is common in karate mainly due to overstress on 
knee. Proper execution of techniques in this sport suppli-
cates muscle balance and strengths (13-15). 
Allegorically, stand or dachi indicates lower part of the 
body position, which is used to carry the upper part of 
body. For correct technique, dachi should be done har-
monically and strongly. Many techniques in karate over-
load the patellofemoral joint; therefore, an increase in the 
volume of training can lead to the development of ante-
rior knee pain. Due to the negative impact of pain on ath-
letic performance, identification and correction of path-
omechanical factors could improve the function of profes-
sional athletes. 
A prospective study by Witvrouw et al. showed that one 
of the risk factors of patellofemoral syndrome is reschedul-
ing muscle reflex of VM (16). However, there are also studies 
with inconsistent results concerning VM/VL ratio and the 
timing onset of the muscles, including imbalance in the 
electric activity and abnormal recruitment pattern, with 
greater delay and lower amplitude of activation of the VM 
(17-26). The meta-analyses by Chester (20) and Wong (21) 
demonstrated heterogeneous finding regarding any corre-
lation between timing of activation of VMO to VL and ante-
rior knee pain. 
One of the major obstacles in investigating the role of 
imbalance between activation of VM and VL in PFPS is the 
temporal priority of knee pain or delay of VM activation. 
Hodges et al. found that pain is the source not the conse-
quence of muscle imbalance. Thus, anterior knee pain con-
trol is fundamental during exercise (27). 
The main objective of this study was to determine the 
relationship between training volume and VM and VL activ-
ity and its correlation to anterior knee pain in elite karate 
athletes. It deems that amplitude and pattern of muscle 
recruitment could be changed regarding training volume. </p>

<p>Furthermore, it would be aimed to investigate other func-
tional parameters of electromyographic properties of VM 
and VL as well as time domain index and electrogoniome-
try. </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>Regarding limited evidence in karate, this type of study 
deems essential for improving training programs and re-
ducing the risk of injury in elites. Understanding the fac-
tors in the development of knee pain and altered muscle 
activity during high-volume training in professional ath-
letes could be helpful in definition of prevention and treat-
ment strategies. </p>

<p>3. Patients and Methods </p>

<p>3.1. Subjects </p>

<p>All junior and cadet athletes (14 -18 years old) of Iranian 
national karate team were recruited to participate in this 
quasi-experimental study. They were required to provide 
informed consent. 
The subjects were included if they had no history of 
significant injury to the lower extremities; no history of 
patellar subluxation or meniscal or ligamentous injury; 
and normal radiological findings. They were excluded if 
the athlete left the team due to being crossed out. A total 
of 29 subjects, including 15 boys and 14 girls, took part in 
the first session of assessment; however, after 6 weeks of 
training, 23 of them-10 boys and 13 girls-had the criteria to 
complete the study. </p>

<p>3.2. Procedure </p>

<p>After arrival at the laboratory, data of acute and re-
cent knee pain was recorded by a 10-cm visual analog scale 
(VAS) and anterior knee pain scale (AKPS) questionnaire, 
respectively (28, 29). The skin was prepared by shaving, 
if necessary, and the subject started the session by a 10-
minute warm-up by a stationary bike and quadriceps and 
hamstring exercises and a few performance trials. It was 
explained to the athletes to keep the intensity of warm-
up including bike-riding at a comfortable level and keep 
their heart rate less than 100 bpm. Quadriceps and ham-
string exercises consisted of hip and knee flexion and ex-
tensions with no resistance and each exercise was repeated 
10 times. Each participant practiced dachi and stair-up and 
down tasks 2 or 3 times, intended for familiarization with 
the process. Then the skin was cleaned by isopropyl alco-
hol and surface electrodes were set according to SENIAM 
recommendations (30). Silver/silver chloride disposable </p>

<p> 
Asian J Sports Med. 2016; 7(3):e35289. </p>

<p>Safar Cherati A et al. </p>

<p>electrodes (Skintact, Austria) were placed with an inter-
electrode distance of 30 mm on VM and VL muscles of right 
and left thigh. 
Electrogoniometer was positioned on the lateral as-
pect of right knee and centered on lateral femoral condyle. 
It was attached to the lower limb by a double-sided ad-
hesive stick. Movement of right knee was continuously 
measured by the electrogoniometer. The sEMG data was 
synchronously sampled using a Mega receiver (ME 6000, 
Mega Electronics Ltd., Kuopio, Finland). Obtaining data 
from electrogoniometer, the points of changes in flexion 
and extension of right knee were determined on the plot. 
The intervals between the points were defined as phases of 
tasks. Signals were collected from 6 channels, including 4 
channels for sEMG electrodes and 2 channels for electrogo-
niometer. Signals of sEMG were pre-amplified 10 times and 
raw data was collected without filtering at a sampling fre-
quency of 1000 Hz. The data was recorded in Megawin soft-
ware, version 2.4. 
Data was collected under three different conditions: 
1, Zenkutsu-dachi: with the left foot forward, with hear-
ing the command, the subjects moved forward at a self-
selected pace (31). Data was recorded simultaneously; 2, 
climb up and down the stairs: subjects were instructed to 
come up and down three steps with a height of 20 cm for 
each step, placing only one foot on each step, starting with 
the left foot. The stepping rate was adjusted at 96 steps per 
minute which is, approximately, the usual stepping rate 
(32). Ascending and descending trials were performed sep-
arately; 3, maximal voluntary isometric contraction (MVIC) 
of quadriceps, which was an isometric contraction done 
after dynamic tasks. It was performed in sitting position 
with full knee extension. The subject was requested to keep 
their muscle contracted as forcefully as possible for 5 sec-
onds. They were encouraged by continuous verbal com-
mands (Prepare! Go! Hold! Hold! Hold! Relax!) 
At the end of each test signal accuracy and absence of 
noise were reviewed. The tests were repeated to record 
three sets of acceptable signals. All tests have been taken 
by one person (second author S.L (sports medicine special-
ist)). </p>

<p>3.3. Data Analysis </p>

<p>During later off-line analysis, raw data was first visually 
checked in <rs id="software-0" type="software">Megawin</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">2.4</rs> to select one of three repetitions of 
each task with minimal noise and best signal accuracy. The 
selected file was saved as a binary file in <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> for further 
analysis. 
The tasks were divided into different phases. In Dachi 
three phases of movement were determined which is dis-
cussed in another article. The phases correspond to the be-
ginning of the movement, maximum flexion and return to </p>

<p>extension respectively (31). Step up and down phases are 
shown in Figure 1. The frequency spectrum was assessed in 
these phases. For each individual muscle maximal mean 
root mean square (RMS) of activity (50 millisecond time-
constant) was used to identify peak sEMG. Mean RMS of 
amplitude of muscle activity of each one of the four mus-
cles was calculated. Then it was normalized to the maxi-
mal RMS data obtained during MVIC, as it is the preferred 
method of normalization (33, 34). To investigate the level 
of activity of the muscles, VM/VL ratio was measure in all 
tasks as: 
• If it was more than 1, means VM had more activity dur-
ing the specified phase of task. 
• If it was equal to 1, VM and VL had the same level of 
activity. 
• If it was less than 1, means VM had less activity during 
the specified phase of task. </p>

<p>3.4. Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Data was analyzed using the statistical software pack-
age <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 14</rs>). To compare variables with nor-
mal distribution parametric tests and to compare vari-
ables with non-normal distribution, non-parametric test 
of Wilcoxon signed rank test was used with statistical sig-
nificance set as 0.05. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>The mean age of subjects was 16.10 ± 1.26 years and 
the mean BMI was 20.86 ± 0.40. Their BMI did not change </p>

<p>during the study because the athletes should stay in their 
weight categories. The training course lasted 6 weeks, with 
a training volume equivalent to 16.5 hours per week. 
Acute pain score, measured by VAS, increased signifi-
cantly (P &lt; 0.001), from a mean (SD) of 0.61 (1.29) to 1.87 
(1.89). However, the changes in AKPS score were not sig-
nificant (P = 0.080). Therefore, sEMG data was compared 
between participants with and without increase in acute 
knee pain. No significant difference was found in all 4 
muscles activity between these groups, at the beginning 
and at the end of training course. In intra-group compari-
son of participants who experienced acute knee pain there 
was no significant change in muscle amplitude in different 
tasks. 
Comparing the movement pattern of dachi, there was 
no change in motion at the beginning and the end of the 
camp. It was expected because of their proficiency and 
longtime of training karate (31). Normalized muscle activ-
ity in the task of dachi was compared at the beginning and 
end of 6 weeks of training. The results are presented in Ta-
ble 1, which shows a decrease in total muscle activity that is </p>

<p>Asian J Sports Med. 2016; 7(3):e35289. </p>

<p>
Safar Cherati A et al. </p>

<p>Right Knee Electrogoniometer </p>

<p>Right Vastus Medialis </p>

<p>Right Vastus Lateralis </p>

<p>Left Vastus Medialis </p>

<p>Left Vastus Lateralis </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-1000 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-1000 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-1000 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-2000 </p>

<p>mV </p>

<p>mV </p>

<p>mV </p>

<p>mV </p>

<p>Degree </p>

<p>0 
500 1000 1500 2000 2500 3000 3500 4000 4500 5000 5500 6000 6500 7000 7500 8000 </p>

<p>0 
500 1000 1500 2000 2500 3000 3500 4000 4500 5000 5500 6000 6500 7000 7500 8000 </p>

<p>0 
500 1000 1500 2000 2500 3000 3500 4000 4500 5000 5500 6000 6500 7000 7500 8000 </p>

<p>0 
500 1000 1500 2000 2500 3000 3500 4000 4500 5000 5500 6000 6500 7000 7500 8000 </p>

<p>0 
500 1000 1500 2000 2500 3000 3500 4000 4500 5000 5500 6000 6500 7000 7500 8000 </p>

<p>Phase 
1 
2 
3 
4 
Mili Second </p>

<p>Figure 1. Phasing EMG and Electro-Goniometer Signals During Walk Up The Stairs in MATLAB </p>

<p>significant in right VL and left VM. When comparing ampli-
tude of muscle activity in the first phase of the movement 
(dachi), decrease in muscle activity was statistically signif-
icant in right VM (P = 0.002), right VL (P = 0.007) and left 
VM (P = 0.042) except for left VL (P = 0.346), after 6 weeks of 
training. </p>

<p>Table 1. Comparison of Normalized Muscle Activity in Dachi at the Beginning and 
End of Training </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Muscle Activity 
At the Beginning 
After 6 Weeks 
P Value </p>

<p>RVM 
1.77 (1.37) 
1.29 (1.30) 
0.078 </p>

<p>RVL 
1.56 (1.34) 
0.98 (0.81) 
0.010* </p>

<p>LVM 
0.93 (0.65) 
0.72 (0.45) 
0.026* </p>

<p>LVL 
1.04 (0.74) 
0.78 (0.49) 
0.089 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: LVL, left vastus lateralis; LVM, left vastus medialis; RMV, right vas-
tus medialis; RVL, right vastus lateralis. 
a Values are expressed as mean (SD). </p>

<p>Total muscle activity during the tasks of stair-up and </p>

<p>down was compared at the beginning and end of 6 weeks 
of training. The results are presented in Tables 2 and 3 re-
spectively. </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of Normalized Muscle Activity in Stair Up at the Beginning and 
End of Training </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Muscle Activity 
At the Beginning 
After 6 Weeks 
P Value </p>

<p>RVM 
0.67 (0.66) 
0.40 (0.33) 
0.050* </p>

<p>RVL 
0.59 (0.65) 
0.36 (0.26) 
0.011* </p>

<p>LVM 
0.59 (0.57) 
0.28 (0.13) 
0.004* </p>

<p>LVL 
0.48 (0.33) 
0.30 (0.13) 
0.036* </p>

<p>a Values are expressed as mean (SD). </p>

<p>Muscle activity was also compared before and after the 
training period in weight-bearing phases of stair tasks, 
which were separated according to data of electrogoniom-
etry. Weight-bearing phases of right lower limb were 2 and 
4 ones in stair-up and 1 and 3 in stair-down task (Figure 
1). Decrease in normalized amplitude of muscle during </p>

<p> 
Asian J Sports Med. 2016; 7(3):e35289. </p>

<p>Safar Cherati A et al. </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparison of Normalized Muscle Activity in Stair Down at the Beginning 
and End of Training </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Muscle Activity 
At the Beginning 
After 6 Weeks 
P Value </p>

<p>RVM 
0.56 (0.68) 
0.34 (0.37) 
0.039* </p>

<p>RVL 
0.48 (0.50) 
0.30 (0.31) 
0.012* </p>

<p>LVM 
0.51 (0.47) 
0.26 (0.27) 
0.005* </p>

<p>LVL 
0.47 (0.43) 
0.34 (0.35) 
0.026* </p>

<p>a Values are expressed as mean (SD). </p>

<p>weight-bearing phases was significant in right VL in stair-
up (P = 0.033) and stair-down (P = 0.023). Muscle activity of 
right VM decreased in the specified phases of stair-up (P = 
0.036) and stair-down (P = 0.036). For the left lower limb 
weight-bearing phases consisted of 1 and 3 ones in stair-up 
and 2 and 4 in stair-down task. Decrease of muscle activ-
ity was statistically significant in left VM in these phases of 
stair-up (P = 0.039) and stair-down (P = 0.013). 
VM/VL ratio in right and left quadriceps was compared 
at the beginning and end of 6 weeks of training which is 
presented in Table 4. As it is shown, the changes of ratio 
was not statistically significant. </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>This study aimed to investigate correlation between 
training volume and activity of the VM and VL and its con-
tribution to anterior knee pain in karate elites. 
Although several studies have evaluated the elec-
tromyographic activity of VMO and VL, few of them settled 
activity level and muscle contraction in their analysis. In 
the present study, the activity level was appraised as well 
as time domain index. Goniometeric measurement was ap-
plied for evaluation of dynamic movement in athletes. 
To our knowledge, this is the first time that the elec-
tromyographic activity of VMO and VL were addressed dur-
ing a sport-specific task in karate, so the result could be 
applied for proper pattern of muscle recruitment and im-
proving performance in elites. 
One of the important variables in this study is the mus-
cle activity in different phases of dachi. Decrease of mus-
cle activity voltage in all phases of the dachi after six weeks 
of training was demonstrated and this reduction in the 
start and finish was significant. Regarding the first phase 
of movement, it would be hypothesized that after six weeks 
of training, the explosive start needs low levels of muscle 
activity and at the end of motion, control becomes possi-
ble with less muscle activity. Since changes in VM/VL ratio 
was not significant, it could be concluded that this reduc-
tion was uniform in both parts of quadriceps. </p>

<p>In the Irish study the effect of open and close kinetic 
chain exercises on VL to VMO activity was compared and it 
was demonstrated that lounge and squatting are effective 
in strengthening of VMO (35). As lounge is similar to dachi 
in karate, their results are consistent with our study. 
According to Collado's study if there is no significant 
impairment in physical examination, the most important 
cause of anterior knee pain is overuse (1).This is a common 
phenomenon at national athletes who experience high vol-
ume of training. 
Comparing two groups with and without increase in 
VAS Score, no difference was observed before and after six 
weeks of training in different phases of dachi. This in-
consistent response might be due to short time follow up 
in our study. Previous studies showed that closed kinetic 
exercises improve sport performance and strength better 
than open kinetic knee exercises but open kinetic chain ex-
ercises could be applicable and effective in anterior knee 
pain rehabilitation. However, regarding the sample size, 
the clinical interpretation of the results should be done 
cautiously. 
Hodges et al. found out that by inducing pain in the 
infrapatellar fat pad, muscle activity of VL decreased sig-
nificantly during stair-up test (27). However in our study 
the decline in muscle activity was not different between 
the two with and without pain groups. However, regarding 
differences in methodology of the two studies, comparing 
deems difficult. 
There are some limitations in our study. While this 
study had a sample containing the total available popu-
lation, the sample size is still small. In order to decrease 
the effect of small sample size in future study, recruit-
ment of more subjects can be helpful. Since this study was 
conducted with a six-week interval, it is proposed to per-
form biomechanical tests with more frequency and longer 
follow-up. 
The advantages of the present study are subject pop-
ulation that is all professional athletes. The other strong 
point is the precise signal processing, evaluation of several 
functional parameters and electromyographic data analy-
sis in <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> software. 
Since prospective studies in this area, especially in ath-
letes are limited, it is suggested to conduct basic and ap-
plied studies including kinematics and kinetics of specific 
movements of karate, featuring a variety of techniques of 
movement, kicks and hand strikes. Finally, long term fol-
low up study of athletes can determine the impact of the 
training camp of the national team. The main challenge 
that which training program could improve the athlete's 
performance is also worth exploring. 
The results showed that after a six-week training pe-
riod for performing the same task, less muscle activity was </p>

<p>Asian J Sports Med. 2016; 7(3):e35289. 
5 </p>

<p>Safar Cherati A et al. </p>

<p>Table 4. Comparison of VM/VL Ratio at the Beginning and End of Training </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Tasks 
Right Quadriceps 
Left Quadriceps </p>

<p>At the Beginning 
After 6 Weeks 
P Value 
At the Beginning 
After 6 Weeks 
P Value </p>

<p>Dachi 
1.29 (0.63) 
1.31 (0.70) 
0.951 
0.97 (0.42) 
1.50 (1.08) 
0.078 </p>

<p>Stair-up 
1.34 (0.95) 
1.20 (0.47) 
0.685 
1.33 (0.71) 
0.95 (0.27) 
0.058 </p>

<p>Stair-down 
1.40 (0.86) 
1.19 (0.48) 
0.330 
1.22 (0.64) 
0.97 (0.50) 
0.144 </p>

<p>a Values are expressed as mean (SD). </p>

<p>required in all phases in both sport-specific movement 
(dachi) and activities of daily living (up or down stairs). </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Sports sciences research institute of Iran and Iran 
Karate federation. </p>

<p>Footnotes </p>

<p>Authors' Contribution: Study concept and design, Sara 
Lotfian; Afsaneh Safar Cherati; acquisition of data, Sara 
Lotfian; analysis and interpretation of data, Sara Lotfian, 
Aliashraf Jamshidi, Mohammad Ali Sanjari; drafting of 
the manuscript, Sara Lotfian, Mohammad Razi; critical re-
vision of the manuscript for important intellectual con-
tent, Sara Lotfian, Afsaneh Safar Cherati; statistical analy-
sis, Sara Lotfian, Aliashraf Jamshidi, Mohammad Ali San-
jari; administrative, technical, and material support, Sara 
Lotfian, Afsaneh Safar Cherati; study supervision, Afsaneh 
Safar Cherati, Mohammad Razi. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interests: None declared. </p>



<p> 
Asian J Sports Med. 2016; 7(3):e35289. </p>

<p>Safar Cherati A et al. </p>



</text></tei>