<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5132031" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>SUMMARY. Transthoracic esophagectomy (TTE) is believed to have advantages for mediastinal 
lymphadenectomy in the treatment of resectable esophageal cancer despite its association with a greater incidence 
of pulmonary complications and postoperative mortality. Transhiatal esophagectomy is regarded as less invasive, 
though insufficient in terms of lymph node dissection. With the aim of achieving lymph dissection equivalent to that 
of TTE, we have developed a nontransthoracic esophagectomy (NTTE) procedure combining a video-assisted 
cervical approach for the upper mediastinum and a robot-assisted transhiatal approach for the middle and lower 
mediastinum. We prospectively studied 22 accumulated cases of NTTE and verified feasibility by analyzing 
perioperative and histopathological outcomes. We compared this group's short-term outcomes with outcomes of 
139 equivalent esophageal cancer cases operated on at our institution by conventional TTE (TTE group). In the 
NTTE group, there were no procedure-related events and no midway conversions to the conventional surgery; the 
mean operation time was longer (median, 524 vs. 428 minutes); estimated blood loss did not differ significantly 
between the two groups (median, 385 mL vs. 490 mL); in the NTTE group, the postoperative hospital stay was 
shorter (median, 18 days vs. 24 days). No postoperative pneumonia occurred in the NTTE group. The frequencies 
of other major postoperative complications did not differ significantly, nor were there differences in the numbers of 
harvested mediastinal lymph nodes (median, 30 vs. 29) or in other histopathology findings. NTTE offers a new 
radical procedure for resection of esophageal cancer combining a cervical video-assisted approach and a transhiatal 
robotic approach. Although further accumulation of surgical cases is needed to corroborate these results, NTTE 
promises better prevention of pulmonary complications in the management of esophageal cancer. </p>

<p>Whether a transthoracic or a transhiatal approach is 
better in esophageal cancer surgery is debated. 
Transthoracic esophagectomy (TTE) offers sufficient 
mediastinal lymph node (LN) clearance but is asso-
ciated with such thoracotomy-related adverse events 
as postoperative pneumonia and empyema. </p>

<p>1-5 </p>

<p>Transhiatal esophagectomy reduces these complica-
tions and operative mortality, 
6 but compromises 
mediastinal LN dissection due to poorer access to the 
mediastinal surgical field. 
7,8 Recently, Kutup et al. 
asked whether the benefits of transthoracic media-</p>

<p>stinal lymphadenectomy outweighed the increased 
operative morbidity; their study concluded that TTE 
was beneficial for cT3, pT3, and node-positive 
patients. 
9 Another large international study has also 
shown that the number of dissected LNs was an inde-
pendent predictor of survival after esophagectomy 
for cancer. 
10 Whether or not the benefits of TTE are 
disputable, the transthoracic approach to extended 
mediastinal dissection is indisputably more likely to 
achieve extended LN dissection. 
Access to the mediastinal field via a transhiatal 
approach has been improved, however, by both 
robot-assisted and video-assisted surgery. Robot-
assisted surgery is now widely used; its utility is most 
apparent in such narrow operative fields as the pelvic 
cavity or the mediastinum, where conventional lapa-
roscopic or thoracoscopic manipulations are subject </p>

<p>Address correspondence to: Professor Yasuyuki Seto, MD, 
Department of Gastrointestinal Surgery, Graduate School of 
Medicine, University of Tokyo, Hongo 7-3-1, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 
113-8655, Japan. Email: seto-tky@umin.ac.jp </p>

<p>Diseases of the Esophagus (2015) ••, ••-•• 
DOI: 10.1111/dote.12345 </p>

<p>© 2015 International Society for Diseases of the Esophagus 
1 
V C 2015 The Authors Diseases of the Esophagus published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of International Society for Diseases of the Esophagus. 
This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and distri-
bution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. 
429 </p>

<p>Address correspondence to: Professor Yasuyuki Seto, MD, 
Department of Gastrointestinal Surgery, Graduate School of 
Medicine, University of Tokyo, Hongo 7-3-1, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 
113-8655, Japan. Email: seto-tky@umin.ac.jp 
The copyright line for this article was changed on 17 November 
2016 after original online publication </p>

<p>Diseases of the Esophagus (2016) 29, 429-434 
DOI: 10.1111/dote.12345 </p>

<p>to severe restrictions. Robot-assisted transhiatal 
esophagectomy is reportedly feasible for transhiatal 
mediastinal LN dissection. </p>

<p>11,12 </p>

<p>Video-assisted 
transcervical dissection of the upper mediastinal LNs, 
which are distant from the hiatus, is another example 
of a nontransthoracic approach. </p>

<p>13,14 </p>

<p>The combination of transhiatal robotic manipula-
tion and a video-assisted transcervical procedure 
makes nontransthoracic esophagectomy (NTTE) 
potentially as radical as and equivalent to TTE. We 
have developed this combined surgery technique with 
the aim of achieving mediastinal lymphadenectomy 
outcomes equivalent to those of TTE, and to estab-
lish its feasibility, we conducted a study of this NTTE 
for the first time in a prospective cohort of patients. 
Here, we demonstrate the short-term outcomes of 
this NTTE. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>From November 2012 to July 2014, 22 patients 
underwent NTTE at The University of Tokyo Hos-
pital. Because we intended with this study to confirm 
the feasibility, safety, and effectiveness of NTTE, we 
excluded patients with disease possibly invading adja-
cent organs or fibrous changes caused by previous 
neoadjuvant therapies. The indications by were (i) 
written informed consent to undergo robot-assisted 
surgery without receiving financial support from the 
national health insurance system, (ii) histologically 
proven esophageal cancer, (iii) sufficiently good 
general condition to tolerate conventional open 
esophagectomy, and (iv) a tumor clinically staged 
T1-3 N0-1 M0 according to the 6th edition of the 
American Joint Committee on Cancer tumor-node-
metastasis (TNM) classification. The exclusion crite-
ria were (i) locally advanced cancer with suspicion of 
invasion to adjacent organs, (ii) prior chemotherapy 
or radiotherapy to the operative field, and (iii) patient 
age over 80 years. </p>

<p>We compared short-term outcomes in the NTTE 
series (NTTE group) with outcomes in transthoracic 
esophagectomies (the control TTE group), which 
consisted of a series of 139 patients operated on by 
the same surgical team at our institution from May 
2008 to July 2014 using a standard TTE technique 
(McKeown's or Ivor-Lewis esophagectomy); these 
patients were selected according to inclusion and 
exclusion criteria identical to those of the NTTE 
group with the exception of the informed consent 
form. The institutional review board of The Univer-
sity of Tokyo Hospital had approved this study. </p>

<p>Surgical method </p>

<p>NTTE was performed in three stages, all with the 
patient in the supine position. In the first stage, LN 
dissections in the cervical and abdominal fields were 
performed simultaneously by two surgical teams. In 
the second, the robotic surgical device, da Vinci S 
(Intuitive Surgical, Sunnyvale, CA, USA), was 
brought in to perform the transhiatal robotic proce-
dure; upon completion of the mediastinal dissection, 
the da Vinci S robotic system was moved away from 
the surgical field. The last stage included harvesting 
of surgical specimens, reconstruction with a gastric 
tube conduit, and cervical anastomosis. 
The cervical procedure was performed via a collar 
incision under mediastinoscopic guidance. The 
abdominal procedure and the mediastinal robotic 
procedure were performed using a laparoscopic 
approach. Figure 1a,b show, respectively, the opera-
tive fields as viewed using the endoscope inserted via 
the cervical wound and using the da Vinci S system 
camera. The robotic mediastinal dissection provided 
excellent visualization of the middle mediastinal 
lymph stations including such features as the pulmo-
nary ligament LN, the main bronchus LN, and the 
subcarinal LN. Figure 2 illustrates which mediastinal 
LN stations are to be dissected during the cervical, 
robotic mediastinal, and abdominal procedures. 
During the lymphadenectomy, LNs and surrounding </p>

<p>(a) 
(b) </p>

<p>Fig. 1 (a) Lymph nodes (LNs) along the left recurrent laryngeal nerve (RLN) are being dissected en bloc with the esophagus (Eso), 
exposing the left main bronchus (LMB) and the aortic arch (AoArch). (b) An inverted V-shaped cluster of LNs is dissected en bloc 
with the Eso from the LMB. The cluster includes the bilateral main bronchus LNs and subcarinal LNs and forms a V shape molded by 
the bronchi. </p>



<p>© 2015 International Society for Diseases of the Esophagus </p>

<p>430 Diseases of the Esophagus </p>

<p>V C 2015 The Authors Diseases 
of the Esophagus published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of International Society for Diseases of the Esophagus </p>

<p>adipose fat were dissected together with the esopha-
gus from the bilateral mediastinal pleura. The robotic 
middle mediastinal dissection has been described in 
our previous report. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Short-term surgical outcomes and their evaluation </p>

<p>The main purpose of this study was the comparison 
of LN retrieval rates using robot-assisted NTTE with 
conventional TTE. Additional outcomes analyzed in 
this study included estimated blood loss, operation 
time, occurrence of procedure-related complications, </p>

<p>frequency of postoperative morbidity, length of post-
operative hospital stay, and histopathological fea-
tures. <rs id="software-0" type="software">JMP</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">11.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>. Cary, NC.) was 
used for statistical analysis. Wilcoxon's rank-sum test 
was used for the analysis of group differences and 
Fisher's exact test was used for the proportional dif-
ferences. </p>

<p>Definition of postoperative complications </p>

<p>Postoperative complications were categorized using a 
modified Clavien-Dindo classification. 
16 The diagno-
sis of postoperative pneumonia was made in accor-
dance with the Japanese Respiratory Society's 
Guidelines for Hospital Acquired Pneumonia in 
Adults. 
17 This diagnosis was contingent on the pres-
ence of pulmonary infiltrates in the standard chest 
radiography and at least two of the three criteria (i) 
pyrexia (&gt;38.0 degrees), (ii) leukocytosis (&gt;12 000/ 
mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) or leukocytopenia (&lt;4000/mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>), and (iii) puru-
lent airway exudates. </p>

<p>Category of LN station </p>

<p>Mediastinal LNs were defined as the regional LNs 
located caudal to the lower aspect of the thyroid 
gland and cranial to the hiatus. Supraclavicular 
nodes were not included in the harvested LN count. 
The upper, middle, and lower mediastinal stations 
were generally identical to the three groups shown in 
Figure 2. The borderlines of the upper-middle and 
the middle-lower stations were the bronchial bifurca-
tion and the left pulmonary vein, respectively. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The clinicopathological characteristics of the two 
groups are shown in Table 1. No significant differ-
ences were observed between the two groups, 
although advanced disease accounted for a larger 
proportion of the TTE group. None of the 22 patients 
experienced procedure-related events or conversions </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Fields of lymphadenectomy by nontransthoracic 
esophagectomy. Black, gray, and white circles represent lymph 
nodes to be retrieved by the cervical, transhiatal robotic, and 
abdominal procedures, respectively. Nodes within the gray tone 
area were not considered to be mediastinal lymph nodes. This 
illustration is a modification of figures 1-4 in the Japanese 
Classification of Esophageal Cancer 10th Edition. </p>

<p>Table 1 Clinicopathological characteristics </p>

<p>NTTE (n = 22) 
TTE (n = 139) 
P-value </p>

<p>Median age (range) 
64 (46-79) 
64 (39-80) 
0.652 
Gender (M/F) 
20/2 
106/33 
0.166 
Median BMI (range) 
21.4 (12.8-31.4) 
22.5 (18.4-26.7) 
0.146 
Histological type 
SCC/AC/Other 
20/0/2 
122/10/7 
0.345 
Location, TN factors 
Proximal/Middle/Distal/EGJ 
2/10/9/1 
16/60/47/16 
0.863 
cT (1/2/3) 
12/5/5 
52/25/62 
0.128 
cN (0/1) 
12/10 
69/70 
0.819 </p>

<p>AC, adenocarcinoma; BMI, body mass index; cN, clinical nodal status; cT, clinical tumor depth; EGJ, esophagogastric junction; NTTE, 
nontransthoracic esophagectomy; SCC, squamous cell carcinoma; TN factors, American Joint Committee on Cancer Tumor Node 
Metastasis Classification, 7th Edition; TTE, transthoracic esophagectomy. </p>

<p>Nontransthoracic radical esophagectomy 3 </p>

<p>© 2015 International Society for Diseases of the Esophagus </p>

<p>Nontransthoracic radical esophagectomy 431 </p>

<p>V C 2015 The Authors Diseases 
of the Esophagus published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of International Society for Diseases of the Esophagus </p>

<p>to the conventional operation. Twenty patients were 
extubated in the operating room; two patients were 
not immediately extubated because of delayed recov-
ery from general anesthesia or vocal cord paralysis. 
Table 2 shows the perioperative outcomes of NTTE 
and TTE with frequencies of the postoperative com-
plications categorized as grade II or more by the 
Clavien-Dindo classification. 
The operation time was significantly extended and 
anastomotic leakage was more frequent (though not 
significantly) in the NTTE group (18%) than in the 
TTE group (9.4%). In the TTE group, 23 patients 
underwent cervical anastomosis and 116 patients 
intrathoracic anastomosis. Fifteen among the 23 
underwent the same retromediastinal gastric conduit 
reconstruction as the NTTE group; the remaining 
eight underwent either subcutaneous or retrosternal 
reconstruction. Four (27%) of the 15 patients who 
underwent retromediastinal gastric conduit recon-
struction developed an anastomotic leakage, com-
pared with only five (4.3%) of the 116 patients who </p>

<p>underwent intrathoracic anastomosis. Postoperative 
pneumonia, ventilator dependency, empyema, and 
other postoperative life-threatening events were not 
observed in the NTTE group. Postoperative hospital 
stays were shorter in the NTTE group than in the 
TTE group. 
The histopathological features of the surgery are 
summarized in Table 3. The comparison between the 
NTTE and the TTE groups showed no significant 
differences in the TNM category, the R category, or 
the frequency of nodal metastasis in each station. 
The numbers of LNs retrieved from each locus of 
the mediastinal lymph stations are plotted in 
Figure 3. The median numbers of the retrieved LNs 
from the mediastinal stations were 30 (NTTE) versus 
29 (TTE) (12 vs. 12, 9 vs. 11, and 5 vs. 4 in the upper, </p>

<p>Table 2 Short-term outcomes </p>

<p>NTTE 
(n = 22) </p>

<p>TTE 
(n = 139) </p>

<p>P-value* 
Median (Range) </p>

<p>Operation 
Duration of 
operation 
(minutes) </p>

<p>524 (445-724) 428 (250-786) &lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>Blood loss (mL) 
385 (30-890) 490 (20-2830) 
0.117 
Postoperative course 
Hospital stay (days) 18 (11-41) 
24 (13-204) 
0.0013 </p>

<p>Number of cases (%) 
P value** </p>

<p>Morbidity 
Pneumonia 
0 (0) 
20 (14) 
0.078 
Anastomotic leakage 
4 (18) 
13 (9.4) 
0.256 
Empyema 
0 (0) 
7 (5.0) 
0.595 
Ventilator dependency 
0 (0) 
11 (7.9) 
0.364 
RLN palsy 
1 (4.5) 
12 (8.6) 
1.000 
Small bowel obstruction 1 (4.5) 
1 (0.7) 
0.132 
Chylothorax 
1 (4.5) 
3 (2.2) 
0.448 
In-hospital mortality 
0 (0) 
2 (1.4) 
0.571 </p>

<p>*Wilcoxon rank sum test, **Fisher's exact test. NTTE, 
nontransthoracic esophagectomy; RLN, recurrent laryngeal nerve; 
TTE, transthoracic esophagectomy. </p>

<p>Table 3 Pathology findings </p>

<p>NTTE (n = 22) 
TTE (n = 139) 
P-value* </p>

<p>TNM 
T category 
1/2/3/4 
16/2/4/0 
70/12/53/4 
0.22 
N category 
0/1 
12/10 
67/72 
0.650 
Nodal metastasis 
Upper mediastinum 
Yes/No 
4/18 
40/99 
0.441 
Middle mediastinum 
Yes/No 
1/21 
21/118 
0.314 
Lower mediastinum 
Yes/No 
1/21 
11/128 
1.000 
R category 
0/1 
21/1 
134/5 
0.592 </p>

<p>*Fisher's exact test. N, node; NTTE, nontransthoracic esophagectomy; R, resection; T, tumor; TTE, transthoracic esophagectomy. </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Box-and-whisker plot of the lymph node yield (numbers) 
by the two approaches. The distributions of the lymph node 
yield by the two approaches were quite similar to each other in 
the three loci of the mediastinum. </p>



<p>© 2015 International Society for Diseases of the Esophagus </p>



<p>V C 2015 The Authors Diseases 
of the Esophagus published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of International Society for Diseases of the Esophagus </p>

<p>middle, and lower mediastinum, respectively). There 
was no significant difference between the NTTE and 
TTE groups in such histopathological features as the 
number of retrieved mediastinal LNs. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In the history of esophageal cancer treatment, achiev-
ing an optimal balance between radicality on the one 
hand and reduction of postoperative pulmonary 
complications with quality of life improvement on the 
other has presented a dilemma that we sought to 
overcome by developing NTTE. In this study, an 
equivalent number of LNs were retrieved from each 
level of the mediastinal lymph stations in comparison 
with the historical control group, although survival 
analyses of the long-term outcomes will be needed to 
confirm oncological equivalence. The number of 
retrieved mediastinal nodes by NTTE was compa-
rable to the numbers reported (from 23 to 33) in 
literature on TTE. </p>

<p>18-21 </p>

<p>In our series of patients, no reduction was observed 
in the operation time or in the blood loss. Prolon-
gation of operation time has been reported in 
robotic surgeries and, together with high running 
costs, is considered a disadvantage of the robotic 
approach. 
22,23 However, no postoperative respiratory 
complications have been observed in the current 
series of patients, and there were no severe postop-
erative events requiring intensive care. In addition, 
the median hospital stay of 18 days was shorter than 
the median length reported in Japan (22 to 35 
days). 
24-26 Although these advantages may reflect the 
small proportion of advanced disease in the NTTE 
group, the extent of lymph dissection was clearly not 
compromised in the NTTE group, given that LN 
retrievals were virtually identical (30 [NTTE] vs. 29 
[TTE]) in both groups. If these findings are replicated 
with a larger population of patients, the low incidence 
of pulmonary complications and shorter hospital 
stays observed in the NTTE group in this study will 
outweigh the disadvantages (prolongation of opera-
tion time, cost, etc.) of using the robotic device. The 
length of hospital stay is longer in Japanese studies 
reflecting differences between Japanese and Western 
cultures and medical systems. Therefore, the advan-
tages of the shorter hospital stays found in this Japa-
nese study might not be universally generalizable and 
will require verification in Western settings. Another 
potential discrepancy stems from differences in body 
mass index (BMI): the participants in this study were 
all Japanese, whose median BMI is approximately 
22.5. The perioperative data, such as estimated blood 
loss or operation time, and the complication rate 
should be re-validated with Western patients to better 
establish NTTE's feasibility. </p>

<p>In the NTTE group, estimated blood loss was not 
decreased and anastomotic leakage was more fre-
quent. However, with better understanding of the 
mediastinal structures viewed transhiatally, the blood 
loss was decreased (to median 260 mL) in the 10 
most recent cases (data not shown). The increased 
anastomotic leakage might be attributable to the cer-
vical anastomosis, as the anastomotic site is, on 
average, more distant from the feeding vessels of the 
gastric conduit, as reported in previous studies com-
paring transhiatal esophagectomy and TTE. 
27,28 In 
our current study, the anastomotic leakage was 
highest among the subgroup of TTE patients 
who underwent cervical anastomosis. Leakage of 
intrathoracic anastomosis often results in empyema 
with occasionally life-threatening consequences, but 
did not in our series of patients, in whom none of 
these anastomotic failures led to lethal complications 
or required surgical interventions. 
In this study, both the NTTE and the TTE groups' 
histopathological findings showed that the upper 
station was the most frequent site of mediastinal LN 
metastases. A majority of surgeries in the previous 
radical esophagectomy for esophageal squamous 
cell carcinoma series included upper mediastinal 
dissection. 
18,19,21,29-31 Therefore, without transcervical 
upper mediastinal dissection, NTTE that is oncolo-
gically equivalent to TTE is not feasible. 
Conventional minimally invasive esophagectomy 
(MIE) has been reported to reduce mortality and 
morbidity </p>

<p>18,19 </p>

<p>; however, a recent report on the Japa-
nese national database revealed that MIE prolongs 
operation times and increases the rate of surgical 
complications. 
32 Notably, this study also reported 
that postoperative pneumonia was not decreased 
in MIE (15.0% in MIE vs. 15.4% in open 
esophagectomy). Meanwhile, in our current study, 
the occurrence of postoperative pneumonia was 
decreased in the NTTE group with a statistically 
marginal difference (0% in NTTE vs. 14% in TTE). 
Although our current findings did not attain statis-
tical significance due to the small number of cases, 
they nonetheless showed that the nontransthoracic 
approach is feasible and may help to prevent post-
operative pulmonary complications. Further accu-
mulation of NTTE cases should be continued to 
conclusively establish the method's perioperative 
safety and confirm the reduction in pulmonary 
complications; we are confident that the non-
transthoracic approach is at least equivalent to the 
conventional transthoracic approach in obtaining 
sufficient surgical control over the mediastinal 
lymph stations. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>None declared. </p>

<p>Nontransthoracic radical esophagectomy 5 </p>

<p>© 2015 International Society for Diseases of the Esophagus </p>

<p>Nontransthoracic radical esophagectomy 433 </p>

<p>V C 2015 The Authors Diseases 
of the Esophagus published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of International Society for Diseases of the Esophagus </p>





<p>© 2015 International Society for Diseases of the Esophagus </p>



<p>V C 2015 The Authors Diseases 
of the Esophagus published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of International Society for Diseases of the Esophagus </p>

</text></tei>