<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5010096" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Normal-appearing white matter (NAWM) surrounding WMHs is associated with decreased structural integrity and 
perfusion, increased risk of WMH growth, and is referred to as the WMH penumbra. Studies comparing structural 
and cerebral blood flow (CBF) penumbras within the same individuals are lacking, however, and would facilitate our 
understanding of mechanisms resulting in WM damage. This study aimed to compare both CBF and structural WMH 
penumbras in non-demented aging. Eighty-two elderly volunteers underwent 3T-MRI including fluid attenuated inversion 
recovery (FLAIR), pulsed arterial spin labeling and diffusion tensor imaging (DTI). A NAWM layer mask was generated 
for periventricular and deep WMHs. Mean CBF, DTI-fractional anisotropy (DTI-FA), DTI-mean diffusivity (DTI-MD) and 
FLAIR intensity for WMHs and its corresponding NAWM layer masks were computed and compared against its mean 
within total brain NAWM using mixed effects models. For both periventricular and deep WMHs, DTI-FA, DTI-MD and 
FLAIR intensity changes extended 2-9 mm surrounding WMHs (p 0.05), while CBF changes extended 13-14 mm 
(p 0.05). The CBF penumbra is more extensive than structural penumbras in relation to WMHs and includes WM 
tissue both with and without microstructural changes. Findings implicate CBF as a potential target for the prevention of 
both micro and macro structural WM damage. </p>

<p>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) T2-weighted white 
matter hyperintensities (WMHs) are commonly 
observed in aging brains, grow over time 1-4 and are 
associated with cognitive decline, 5-10 motor impair-
ment, 8 stroke, 6,11,12 and mortality. 6 White matter 
hyperintensity (WMH) is characterized pathologically 
by demyelination, axonal loss, and rarefaction, 13 often 
attributed to vascular ischemia, 14-17 and associated 
with arteriolosclerosis. 4 It has been related to cerebral 
hypoperfusion or blood-brain barrier (BBB) dysfunc-
tion. 13,18-20 Altered cerebral blood flow (CBF) and 
white matter (WM) integrity in WMHs has been 
widely reported. 21-27 </p>

<p>1 Department of Neurology, Oregon Health &amp; Science University, 
Portland, USA 
2 Department of Neurology, Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Portland, 
USA 
3 Advanced Imaging Research Center, Oregon Health &amp; Science 
University, Portland, USA </p>

<p>Corresponding author: 
Nutta-on Promjunyakul, Layton Aging and Alzheimer's Disease Center, 
Department of Neurology, Oregon Health &amp; Science University, 3181 
SW Sam Jackson Park Road, Portland, OR 97239, USA. 
Email: promjuny@ohsu.edu </p>

<p>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; 
Metabolism 
2016, Vol. 36(9) 1528-1536 
! Author(s) 2016 
Reprints and permissions: 
sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav 
DOI: 10.1177/0271678X16651268 
jcbfm.sagepub.com </p>

<p>There is increasing interest in the physiological 
changes not only within visible WM lesions but also in 
the surrounding normal-appearing white matter 
(NAWM), referred to as the WMH penumbra. This 
area demonstrates similar MRI characteristics as WM 
lesions, but to a lesser degree, and is at risk for further 
damage over time. 26 Previous studies have characterized 
WMH penumbras using either cerebral perfusion or 
structural changes. The WMH structural integrity pen-
umbras defined by diffusion tensor imaging-fractional 
anisotropic (DTI-FA) and fluid attenuated inversion 
recovery (FLAIR) intensity were approximately 
3-8 mm around WMHs. 26,27 Others have similarly 
demonstrated low DTI-FA and high DTI-mean diffusiv-
ity (DTI-MD) in the NAWM immediately surrounding 
WMHs. 24 These findings demonstrating the presence of 
microstructural degeneration surrounding WMH lesions 
implicate visually observed white matter damage as being 
indicative of a much larger region of tissue disturbance. 
Longitudinal studies have further validated cross-sec-
tional findings that altered DTI-FA and FLAIR signal 
in the tissue surrounding NAWM at baseline predict inci-
dent WMHs at follow-up. 28,29 
Pulsed arterial spin labeling (PASL) can quantify 
white matter (WM) and WMH CBF, which is compar-
able with what has been reported in others using differ-
ent perfusion imaging techniques. 25,30-32 A previous 
report from our laboratory has shown that lower ASL 
CBF in the NAWM surrounding WMH lesions extends 
approximately 12 mm from both periventricular 
(PVWMH) and deep WMHs (DWMH). This is more 
extensive compared with previously reported structural 
penumbras, defined by DTI and FLAIR data, suggest-
ing that altered CBF may be a primary contributor to 
the formation of T2-weighted MRI WM lesions. Similar 
to structural WMH penumbras, the CBF penumbra has 
also been demonstrated to be associated with expansion 
of WMH lesions over time. 21,25 
Studies comparing both structural and CBF penum-
bras within the same individuals are lacking. While 
structural penumbra identification provides insight 
into the full scope of microstructural white matter 
integrity disruption associated with WMHs, it does 
not clearly provide insight into its etiology. The CBF 
penumbra may provide insight into the etiological 
mechanisms underlying visible MRI WM lesion forma-
tion, but, in isolation, does not impart critical informa-
tion regarding the degree of subtle microstructural WM 
integrity disruption surrounding such lesions. 
The aim of this study was to facilitate our under-
standing of mechanisms resulting in WM damage 
by directly comparing the WMH penumbra defined 
by both CBF and structural imaging data in the same 
aging cohort. Based on previous studies demonstrating 
the likelihood that a major component of WMHs is </p>

<p>vascular in origin and that altered perfusion should pre-
cede the WM integrity changes, we, therefore, hypothe-
sized that penumbra area defined by CBF would cover a 
more extensive area from the WMHs than the penum-
bras defined by structural integrity measures. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Subjects </p>

<p>Eighty-two cognitively intact community dwelling elderly 
subjects currently participating in a Layton Aging and 
Alzheimer's Disease Center longitudinal aging study 
were recruited. Subjects' age ranged from 66.2 to 101.1 
years old (mean age was 84.13 years old; standard devi-
ation (SD) was 8.3 years old). A hundred percent of all of 
our subjects had some degree of PV WMHs on 
MRI (mean volume was 11 cc; SD was 11.2 cc; range 
was 0.3-62.6 cc), while 87% of the subjects had some 
degree of deep WMHs (mean volume was 1.3 cc; 
SD was 1.5 cc; range was 0.1-9.0 cc). Entry inclusion cri-
teria included seniors age 65 or above with a score of 0 on 
the Clinical Dementia Rating Scale (CDR) 33 and ! 24 on 
the Mini-Mental State Examination. 34 MRI exclusion cri-
teria included a history of clinical stroke or evidence of 
cortical stroke on MRI, claustrophobia, inability to lie in a 
supine position for 90 min, and implanted metallic objects. 
All subjects signed written informed consent and approval 
from the Institutional Review Board of Oregon Health &amp; 
Science University was obtained. Table 1 describes partici-
pant characteristics. </p>

<p>MRI sequences </p>

<p>MRI data were obtained using a 3.0T MRI scanner 
(TIM Trio System, Siemens Medical Solutions). </p>

<p>Table 1. Summary of participant characteristics at baseline. </p>

<p>Variables 
Mean (SD) </p>

<p>Number of subjects 
82 
Age (years) 
84 (8.2) 
Female (%) 
76 
CDR 
0 
MMSE 
28.8 (1.6) 
Periventricular WMH volume (cc) 
11.0 (11.2) 
Deep WMH volume (cc) 
1.3 (1.5) 
Intracranial volume (cc) 
1850.0 (219.4) 
Subjects with history of hypertension (%) 
74 
Subjects with history of atrial fibrillation (%) 
16 
Subjects with history hypercholesterolemia (%) 72 
Subjects with history diabetes (%) 
13 
Subjects with history smoking (%) 
49 </p>

<p>Promjunyakul et al. </p>

<p>
Each subject underwent T 1 -weighted magnetization 
prepared rapid gradient echo (MPRAGE), FLAIR, 
QUIPSS II with thin-slice TI periodic saturation 
(Q2TIPS) PASL, 35 and diffusion tensor imaging 
(DTI). T 1 -weighted images was acquired using repeti-
tion time (TR) ¼ 2300 ms, echo time (TE) ¼ 3.4 ms, 
inversion time (TI) ¼ 1200 ms, spatial resolution ¼ 
1 mm isotropic; and field of view (FOV) ¼256 mm. 
Axial 2D FLAIR data sets was acquired using 
TR ¼ 9000 ms, TE ¼ 87 ms, TI ¼2500 ms, in-plane reso-
lution was 0.969 mm Â0.969 mm, slice thickness ¼ 
2 mm, number of slices ¼ 95. PASL sequence was 
obtained covering the basal ganglia inferiorly, through 
the centrum semiovale superiorly with following par-
ameters: resolution ¼ 3 Â 3 Â 4 mm 3 , 2 mm gap, time 
between the inversion pulse and beginning of the peri-
odic saturation pulse train 1 (TI 1 ) ¼ 700 ms, the post TI 
periodic saturation stop time (TI 1s ) ¼ 1600 ms, the 
time between the inversion pulse and the initial EPI 
read pulse (TI 2 ) ¼1800 ms, 36 TR ¼ 3000 ms, and TE ¼ 
13 ms. The sequence acquired 720 images in three sep-
arate runs. Subjects were instructed to stay awake with 
their eyes closed. The DTI sequence includes TR ¼ 9500 
ms, TE ¼ 95 ms, in-plane resolution was 2 mm Â 2 mm, 
slice thickness ¼2.0 mm, and 30 diffusion weighted dir-
ections with b ¼ 1000 s/mm 2 . </p>

<p>Image analysis </p>

<p>MRI processing to identify WMHs and to calculate 
WM-CBF has been described previously. 21 In brief, 
to determine the WMH area, a WM-FLAIR intensity 
histogram was generated and a 45% intensity threshold 
was used as a cutoff to differentiate the WMH and 
NAWM. A custom cluster-growing algorithm was 
used to expand each cluster. To ensure the accuracy 
of the WMH detection, the WMH clusters were visually 
examined and manually corrected. Last, WMH clusters 
contiguous with the ventricles were labeled periven-
tricular WMHs (PVWMHs) and all others were 
considered deep WMHs (DWMH). To derive the sub-
ject-specific CBF map, each of the three runs of PASL 
images was inspected, and data found to have excessive 
head movement (!2 mm or 2 degrees) were discarded, 
and the three runs were concatenated. Quantitative 
CBF was then calculated on a voxel basis according 
to Wang et al. 37 Voxel-wise partial volume correction 
was performed. 38 
DTI analysis comprised of registering raw DTI 
images to correct for eddy current distortions and 
applying ''dtifit'' command, a FSL subroutine, 39,40,41 
to reconstruct diffusion tensors, including FA and 
MD images. Figure 1 shows ASL-CBF map, FLAIR, 
DTI-FA, and DTI-MD image from a representative 
subject. </p>

<p>Spatial relationship between WMH and NAWM </p>

<p>To determine the WMH penumbra for each measure, a 
NAWM layer mask for each individual dataset was 
created by linearly aligning the defined WMHs to the 
T 1 -weighted image. Each layer was dilated away 
from the WMHs by 1 voxel (approximately 1 mm), 
for a total of 15 NAWM layers for PVWMH and 
DWMH separately, see Figure 2(a) and (b). The inner-
most layer, closest to WMH was layer 1 (NAWM-L1) 
and the outermost layer was layer 15 (NAWM-L15), 
see Figure 2(b). To prevent overlapping of voxels 
between layers, before creating the next layer, the 
WMH and the previous NAWM layers were merged 
together to create a new ''seed.'' To avoid the partial 
volume effects of the GM and CSF, the GM and ven-
tricular masks were dilated by 2 voxels, and subtracted 
from the NAWM layers. 
The NAWM layer mask was individually applied 
to the CBF, FLAIR, and DTI maps, which were pre-
viously linearly aligned to their T 1 -weighted image 
and was resampled to 1 mm Â 1 mm Â 1 mm. Last, for 
each individual subject, the mean CBF, FLAIR inten-
sity, DTI-FA, and DTI-MD for WMHs and each 
NAWM layer was computed for PVWMH and 
DWMH separately, and compared with the respective 
mean total brain NAWM value. Each mean value was 
adjusted for age. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v.20</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs>), <rs id="software-2" type="software">SAS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">v.9.3</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>.) and R 
(v.2.11, R Foundation). The extent of the WMH pen-
umbra was determined by identifying the plateau phase 
of each dataset by comparing each CBF, FLAIR inten-
sity, and DTI layer to its corresponding mean 
total brain value within NAWM using a mixed effects 
model. We created 15 dummy variables indicating each 
NAWM layer with total brain NAWM as a reference. 
The difference in coefficients between two adjacent 
layers were compared to examine the plateau phase. 
There is a ''location effect'' of white matter association 
and commissural fibers surrounding the ventricles 
resulting in high DTI-FA in NAWM surrounding 
PVWMH compared with the mean NAWM DTI-FA 
of the entire brain. 24 Because of this anatomical 
phenomenon, the plateau phase of this data was deter-
mined by comparing adjacent data points using paired 
t-tests. The first of two neighboring layers whose values 
were not significantly different from each other was 
defined as the outer boundary for the PVWMH 
DTI-FA penumbra. Significant difference was set at 
p &lt; 0.05. The analysis was performed for PVWMH 
and DWMHs separately. </p>

<p> 
Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism 36(9) </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The extent of the DWMH penumbras are as follows: 
NAWM-L14 for CBF; NAWM-L8 for FLAIR inten-
sity; NAWM-L9 for DTI-FA; and NAWM-L5 for 
DTI-MD (Figure 3). The extent of the PVWMH pen-
umbras are as follows: NAWM-L13 for CBF; NAWM 
L3 for FLAIR intensity; NAWM-L2 for DTI-FA; and 
NAWM-L5 for DTI-MD (Figure 4). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Results of the present study demonstrate reduced CBF 
and DTI-FA, and increased FLAIR intensity and DTI-
MD, of WMH and its surrounding NAWM for 
both periventricular and deep WMH lesion subtypes. </p>

<p>Our results also show that the WMH CBF penumbra is 
more extensive than structural penumbras, as defined 
by FLAIR, DTI-FA, and DTI-MD, confirming that 
age-related white matter injury is primarily associated 
with cerebral hypoperfusion. 
The CBF penumbra exists approximately 13-14 mm 
surrounding WMHs, while DTI-FA and DTI-MD pen-
umbras cover approximately 2-9 mm from WMHs, 
which is consistent with previous reports. 21,26,27 It is 
important to note that approximately half of the CBF 
penumbra consisted of NAWM in which no micro-
structural degeneration was observed, a finding that 
supports the likelihood that compromised CBF pre-
cedes brain microstructural WM integrity changes. 
Longitudinal analysis of these data is being conducted 
to more definitively address this question. </p>

<p>Figure 1. PASL-CBF, FLAIR, DTI-FA, and DTI-MD image from a representative subject. </p>

<p>Promjunyakul et al. </p>

<p>
The findings of decreased CBF and DTI-FA and 
increased DTI-MD and FLAIR intensity within the 
WMH and its surrounding NAWM areas are consistent 
with several previous reports. 21,22,25-29,42,43 The low blood </p>

<p>flow in WMHs provides further evidence that age-related 
white matter injury is likely attributed to vascular ische-
mia, 14-16 caused by arteriolosclerosis, 4,44,45 chronic hemo-
dynamic insufficiency contributed by watershed blood </p>

<p>Figure 3. Group mean (AESE) of DWMH and its outer NAWM layers in relation to total brain NAWM. (a) CBF, (b) FLAIR intensity, 
(c) DTI-FA, and (d) DTI-MD. The solid horizontal and dotted lines represent the mean and standard error of total brain NAWM CBF, 
FLAIR, and DTI values, respectively. Red arrows indicate the outer end of WMH penumbra for each dataset. </p>

<p>Figure 2. NAWM layer masks. The red areas represent WMHs. The light blue, blue, and white layers represent NAWM layer masks 
for (a) deep WMH and (b) periventricular WMH. The innermost layer adjoining WMHs is NAWM layer 1 and the outermost layer 
away from the WMHs is NAWM layer 15. </p>

<p> 
Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism 36(9) </p>

<p>supply in the area adjacent to the ventricles, 14-16 and/or 
impaired BBB permeability, which leads to decreased 
fractional blood volume and increased fluid in the 
vessel wall, accompanied formation of WM injury. 46 It 
is uncertain if the blood flow reduction is causing the 
brain tissue damage or if it is a secondary mechanism 
in response to diminished tissue to supply. 
DTI findings of decreased FA and increased MD 
indicate the presence of compromised microstructural 
WM integrity and altered water mobility in the inter-
stitial space within WM lesions and their surrounding 
NAWM. 47 Clinically, this deterioration may affect the 
integrity of white matter tracts connecting cortical and 
subcortical areas, leading to a disconnection syndrome 
and may attribute to age-related cognitive decline. 48 
The degree of sensitivity of the different DTI param-
eters used to investigate the structural WMH penum-
bra was different between PVWMH and DWMHs. 
Previous work has indicated that MD provides better 
differentiation of WMH associated integrity disruption 
within NAWM than FA, showing more alteration in 
surrounding NAWM from the WMH. 24 Our result 
shows this to be the case only for PVWMH. It is not 
clear whether previous work investigated only 
PVWMH or combined WMH subtypes, which may 
be mostly comprised of PVWMH. Our results may 
imply that mean water diffusivity is more sensitive in 
detecting the extent of periventricular WM integrity </p>

<p>disruption than FA, with the opposite being true for 
the DWMH. Anatomical differences may explain the 
varying DTI penumbra characteristics between 
PVWMHs and DWMHs. PVWMHs are located near 
highly organized myelinated structures, such as the 
corpus callosum, where water diffusion will be highly 
restricted and dependent on fiber direction. As our result 
demonstrated, unlike the other parameters, DTI-FA of 
the PV NAWM layers did not plateau at the total brain 
NAWM DTI-FA mean. Instead, DTI-FA values of the 
inner PV WMH NAWM layers plateaued at a value 
greater than the mean (Figure 4(c)). Meanwhile, the 
location of DWMHs is more sporadic, do not abut the 
ventricle, and therefore are not inherently susceptible to 
systematic anatomical influences on MRI WM integrity 
measures. Thus, the location-independent aspect of 
DWMHs makes them important targets, in addition to 
PVWMHs, in investigations studying the etiology of 
age-related WMHs. 
Delineation of the WMH penumbra could provide a 
potentially modifiable biomarker that could have 
several important clinical implications. First, ASL CBF 
technique is preferable to other investigations of cerebral 
perfusion in an aging population, because it is noninva-
sive, reliable, and compatible with routine clinical scan-
ning. Second, ASL CBF can be used to monitor 
treatment effects aimed at restoring cerebral perfusion, 
such as those involving exercise 49 or meditation. 50 Third, </p>

<p>Figure 4. Group mean (AESE) of PVWMH and its outer NAWM layers in relation to total brain NAWM. (a) CBF, (b) FLAIR intensity, 
(c) DTI-FA, and (d) DTI-MD. The solid horizontal and dotted lines represent the mean and standard error of total brain NAWM CBF, 
FLAIR, and DTI values, respectively. Red arrows indicate the outer end of WMH penumbra for each dataset. </p>

<p>Promjunyakul et al. </p>

<p>
cerebral perfusion can be used to more directly assess the 
effects of blood pressure management in the elderly, as it 
has been previously shown that lower blood pressure can 
repress the progression of developing WMH over 
time, 51,52 but can potentially decrease brain perfusion 
in those with impaired cerebral autoregulation. 53 Last, 
ASL CBF measures may be used to investigate cerebral 
perfusion as a potential mechanism explaining the rever-
sal of microstructural WM integrity disruption, which 
has been reported previously in some longitudinal 
studies. 8,29,54 </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>This study is the first to provide a direct comparison of 
CBF, DTI WM integrity, and FLAIR intensity penum-
bras in a cognitively intact aging population. This study 
is limited in that it consists of cross-sectional data only. 
It has been shown previously that the ASL-CBF pen-
umbra predicts future WMH expansion. 21 Future lon-
gitudinal analysis of this cohort is needed, however, to 
determine whether perfusion or structural sequences 
best predict the growth of WMHs. Studies to assess 
relationships between WMH penumbras and cognitive 
and motor performance would shed further insight into 
the clinical implications of age-related WM degener-
ation. Future study should also focus on the rate of 
WMH growth and whether the CBF penumbra can 
predict the rate of WM integrity changes. Last, future 
studies including methods to examine the relationships 
between BBB permeability, hypometabolism, and cere-
bral perfusion in the WMH penumbra are needed. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>In conclusion, the present study provides important 
implications regarding the etiology of WMH expansion, 
a phenomenon commonly observed in older individuals, 
and associated with significant morbidity. Decreased 
CBF and DTI-FA and increased DTI-MD and 
FLAIR intensity of the NAWM surrounding WMHs 
indicates that the scope of WM injury extends beyond 
visible lesions commonly observed on clinical MRI. CBF 
penumbra is more extensive than the DTI WM integrity 
and FLAIR intensity penumbras, suggesting that ASL 
CBF may provide information regarding ''at risk'' tissue 
preceding the occurrence of microstructural WM integ-
rity disruption. Given these findings, the WMH CBF 
penumbra should be considered as a potentially modifi-
able biomarker in future studies aimed at preventing 
vascular cognitive impairment in the elderly. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial sup-
port for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this </p>

<p>article: NIH (1RO1AG036772, P30 AG008017, RO1 
AG024059) and the Department of Veterans Affairs. </p>

<p>Declaration of conflicting interests </p>

<p>The author(s) declared the following potential conflicts of 
interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publi-
cation of this article: Dr. Kaye receives research support from 
the NIH (P30 AG008017, R01 AG024059, P30 AG024978, 
P01 AG043362, U01 AG010483); directs a center that receives 
research support from the NIH, CDC, Roche and Esai; serves 
on the editorial advisory board of the journal, Alzheimer's &amp; 
Dementia and as Associate Editor, and Frontiers of Aging 
Neuroscience. Dr. Deniz Erten-Lyons receives research sup-
port from the Department of Veterans Affairs (Career 
Development Award grant). She serves as site PI for clinical 
trials funded by EISAI, Roche, Lundbeck, and Elli-Lilly. Dr. 
Lisa Silbert receives research support from the NIH 
(1R01AG036772, P30 AG008017, P50 NS062684). </p>

<p>Authors' contributions </p>

<p>Dr. Nutta-on Promjunyakul drafted and revised the manu-
script, participated in study concept and design, conducted 
the statistical analyses, analyzed and interpreted the data. 
Mr. David Lahna participated in study design, and made a 
substantial contribution in revising the manuscript. Dr. 
Jeffrey Kaye made a substantial contribution in revising the 
manuscript for intellectual content, assisted in the study con-
cept. Dr. Hiroko Dodge assisted the statistical analyses. Dr. 
Deniz Erten-Lyons made a substantial contribution in revis-
ing the manuscript. Dr. Bill Rooney assisted in study concept 
and in designing the MRI sequences. Dr. Lisa Silbert made a 
substantial contribution in revising the manuscript for intel-
lectual content, participated in study concept and design, ana-
lyzed and interpreted the data. </p>



<p> 
Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism 36(9) </p>



<p>Promjunyakul et al. </p>



<p>
 
Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism 36(9) </p>

</text></tei>