<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5015294" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background--Cardiac surgery-associated acute kidney injury (CSA-AKI) is a common complication with a poor prognosis. In order 
to identify modifiable perioperative risk factors for AKI, which existing risk scores are insufficient to predict, a dynamic clinical risk 
score to allow clinicians to estimate the risk of CSA-AKI from preoperative to early postoperative periods is needed. </p>

<p>Methods and Results--A total of 7233 cardiac surgery patients in our institution from January 2010 to April 2013 were enrolled 
prospectively and distributed into 2 cohorts. Among the derivation cohort, logistic regression was used to analyze CSA-AKI risk 
factors preoperatively, on the day of ICU admittance and 24 hours after ICU admittance. Sex, age, valve surgery combined with 
coronary artery bypass grafting, preoperative NYHA score &gt;2, previous cardiac surgery, preoperative kidney (without renal 
replacement therapy) disease, intraoperative cardiopulmonary bypass application, intraoperative erythrocyte transfusions, and 
postoperative low cardiac output syndrome were identified to be associated with CSA-AKI. Among the other 1152 patients who 
served as a validation cohort, the point scoring of risk factor combinations led to area under receiver operator characteristics 
curves (AUROC) values for CSA-AKI prediction of 0.74 (preoperative), 0.75 (on the day of ICU admission), and 0.82 
(postoperative), and Hosmer-Lemeshow goodness-of-fit tests revealed a good agreement of expected and observed CSA-AKI 
rates. </p>

<p>Conclusions--The first dynamic predictive score system, with Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes (KDIGO) AKI definition, 
was developed and predictive efficiency for CSA-AKI was validated in cardiac surgery patients. ( J Am Heart Assoc. 2016;5: 
e003754 doi: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003754) </p>

<p>Key Words: acute kidney injury • cardiac surgery • risk factor • risk score </p>

<p>A cute kidney injury (AKI) is a common complication after </p>

<p>cardiac surgery, with reported incidences between 8.9% 
and 39% as well as mortality of 3.8% to 54.4%, and even slight 
renal function changes were reported to affect short-and 
long-term outcome after cardiac surgery. 1-3 Because early 
prediction in those patients at high risk of developing cardiac 
surgery-associated acute kidney injury (CSA-AKI) may enable </p>

<p>prevention of complications, in the last 2 decades various 
predictive models have been developed to forecast CSA-AKI 
or renal replacement therapy (RRT)-AKI after cardiac 
surgery, 4-9 in which adequate predictive power was validated 
among whites. 10,11 However, by now, the predictive value for 
estimating AKI, RRT-AKI, or death incidence of 5 established 
models, including the method published by Palomba et al, 7 
the Cleveland Clinic score, 8 the scoring system published by 
Mehta et al, 6 the simplified renal index score, 9 and the EURO 
score 12 in other racial cohorts after cardiac surgery is 
uncertain. Possible reasons might include the following. (1) 
There was no consensus in the definition of AKI when those 
models were developed. In the AKICS score, AKI was defined 
as "an increase of serum creatine (Cr) levels above 2.0 mg/ 
dL in patients with baseline serum Cr lower than 1.5 mg/dL." 
In patients with baseline serum Cr between 1.5 and 3.0 mg/ 
dL, AKI was defined as "a serum Cr increase of 50% over the 
baseline value." In the new 2012 Kidney Disease: Improving 
Global Outcomes (KDIGO) AKI definition, 13 urine output, as 
another indicator besides serum creatine, was not utilized to 
define AKI in Palomba's study, and AKI may be missed. (2) 
With the recognition of intraoperative and postoperative risk </p>

<p>From the Departments of Nephrology (W.J., J.T., J.X., B.S., Y.W., Y.F., Z.Z., J.J., 
X.D.), Cardiac Surgery Intensive Care Unit (Y.Z., L.L., Z.L.), and Cardiovascular 
Surgery (C.W.), Zhongshan Hospital, Shanghai Medical College, Fudan Univer-
sity, Shanghai, China; Shanghai Kidney and Dialysis Institute, Shanghai, China 
(W.J., J.T., J.X., B.S., Y.W., Y.F., Z.Z., J.J., X.D.); Shanghai Kidney and Blood 
Purification Laboratory, Shanghai, China (J.T., Y.F., X.D.). 
*Dr Jiang and Dr Teng contributed equally to this work. 
Correspondence to: Xiaoqiang Ding, MD, Department of Nephrology, 
Zhongshan Hospital, Shanghai Medical College, Fudan University, No 180 
Fenglin Rd, Shanghai, China. E-mail: ding.xiaoqiang@zs-hospital.sh.cn </p>

<p>Received April 21, 2016; accepted July 8, 2016. 
ª 2016 The Authors. Published on behalf of the American Heart Association, </p>

<p>Inc., by Wiley Blackwell. This is an open access article under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License, which permits use, 
distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is 
properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003754 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>factors, especially the modifiable factors, contributing to CSA-
AKI, risk scores 6,8,9 including only preoperative risk factors 
can hardly meet the predictive requirement. (3) In some 
developing countries such as China, the proportions of valve 
surgery, comorbidities, and population race 14 are quite 
different from those of the existing model derivation cohorts. 
With the development of medical technology, cardiac surgery 
in developing countries is booming. Meanwhile complications 
of surgery and economic burdens are also increasing due to 
restriction of medical technology and management. We aimed 
to develop a dynamic predictive model for CSA-AKI based on 
the recent KDIGO AKI definition, which was devised to predict 
the incidence of CSA-AKI from preoperative to early postop-
erative periods and to validate its predictive capacity for 
improved clinical application. </p>

<p>Patients and Methods </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>In our prospective study we included 7233 patients who were 
divided into a derivation cohort (6081 patients between 
January 2010 and October 2012) and a validation cohort 
(1152 patients between November 2012 and April 2013); all 
were admitted to the Zhongshan Hospital, Shanghai Medical 
College, Fudan University. The study was approved by the 
ethical committee of the Zhongshan Hospital, and all partic-
ipants provided written informed consent. 
Inclusion criteria were adult patients who underwent coro-
nary artery bypass grafting (CABG), off-pump coronary artery 
bypass (OPCAB), valve surgery, or valve combined with CABG 
surgery. Excluded were patients with previous heart transplan-
tation, preoperative mechanical ventilation or tracheotomy, 
preoperative defibrillator or ventricular assist devices, preoper-
ative RRT, preoperative liver dysfunction, or sepsis. </p>

<p>Data Collection </p>

<p>The clinical characteristics of both derivation and validation 
cohorts have been collected and were extracted from the 
database of Zhongshan Hospital cardiac surgery. All data 
were checked twice by medical personnel (postgraduate and 
resident doctor) before being admitted to the database. We 
collected data including sex, age, weight, length of stay, 
length of ICU stay, and outcome; preoperative data including 
diagnosis, comorbidities including hypertension, diabetes 
mellitus, atrial fibrillation, endocarditis, coronary artery 
disease, cerebral vascular disease, anemia, chronic obstruc-
tive pulmonary disease, kidney disease without renal 
replacement therapy; and laboratory reports including esti-
mated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR), which were calcu-
lated with CKD-EPI formulas, 15 in addition to New York Heart </p>

<p>Association (NYHA) functional classification, left ventricular 
ejection fraction (LVEF), preoperative congestive heart 
failure, preoperative intra-aortic balloon pump (IABP), previ-
ous cardiac surgery history, recent contrast media (CM) 
exposure, and renal toxic drug exposure. Intraoperative data 
included emergency surgery, procedure type, cardiopul-
monary bypass (CPB) application and time, transfusion, 
and fluid balance; postoperative data comprised low cardiac 
output syndrome (LCOS), central venous pressure, medicine 
application, mechanical ventilation, RRT, and renal recov-
ery. AKI was defined according to the KDIGO guideline 13 as 
any of the following: increase in SCr by ≥0.3 mg/dL 
(≥26.5 lmol/L) within 48 hours; or increase in SCr to 
≥1.5 times baseline that is known or presumed to have </p>

<p>occurred within the prior 7 days or urine volume &lt;0.5 mL/ 
kg per hour for 6 hours. If there were more than 1 cardiac 
surgery procedures performed during the same hospitaliza-
tion, only the data on the first surgery were considered. If 
there were more than 1 hospitalization between January 
2010 and April 2013, only the data on the first hospital-
ization were considered. </p>

<p>Statistical Analyses </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were carried out by <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> statistics for 
Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 20.0.</rs>. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corp, Armonk, NY</rs>). Continuous 
variables were expressed as meanAESD and analyzed by 
unpaired t tests, with Welch adjustment when necessary. 
Continuous variables that violated the normality assumption 
were expressed as median and 25th to 75th percentiles and 
analyzed by a Mann-Whitney U test. Categorical variables 
were expressed as absolute (n) and relative (%) frequency and 
were analyzed by the Pearson 2-test or the Fisher exact test 
whenever appropriate. Significant level was considered with 
P&lt;0.05. Univariate analysis was carried out for patient data, 
and multivariate analysis by logistic regression was used to 
obtain data about the risk factors for AKI at the 3 time points: 
preoperative, ICU admittance, and 24 hours after ICU admit-
tance. In the multivariate analysis, results were expressed by 
the odds ratio and the 95% confidence interval. The regression 
b of those variables obtained from logistic regression were </p>

<p>used to develop the final 3 stage scores to predict CSA-AKI. 
The 1152 patients in the validation cohort were scored for 
validation, and the area under the receiver operating charac-
teristic curves (AUROC) as well as Hosmer-Lemeshow good-
ness-of-fit test were applied to estimate the reliability of the 
scoring for predicting CSA-AKI. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The derivation cohort consisted of 6081 patients, and the 
validation cohort consisted of 1152 patients. The </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003754 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>AKI Prediction After Cardiac Surgery 
Jiang et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>characteristics of both cohorts were showed in Table 1. The 
incidence of CSA-AKI and mortality in the derivation cohort 
were 35.5% (2159/6081) and 2.8% (170/6081), whereas in 
the validation cohort they were 33.0% (380/1152) and 3.4% 
(39/1152). </p>

<p>Risk Factor Analysis </p>

<p>The perioperative characteristics of the derivation cohort are 
presented in Table 2. We categorized the following variables 
for subgroup observation: age (≤40, 41-60, 61-80, ≥81), 
estimated GFR (&gt;60, &gt;30 to ≤60, ≤30 mL/min), and LVEF 
(&gt;50, 36-50, ≤35). There were statistically significant 
differences between the CSA-AKI patients and the unaf-
fected group regarding sex, age, preoperative kidney func-
tion, some comorbidities such as hypertension and COPD, 
preoperative heart function, CM exposure, procedure type, 
perioperative erythrocyte transfusion, postoperative central 
venous pressure, and short-term mortality (Table 2). All 
these risk factors were brought into a multivariate analysis 
for predicting CSA-AKI. The multivariate logistic regression 
analysis was conducted at 3 time points: preoperative, ICU 
admittance, and 24 hours after ICU admittance; the statis-
tically significant risk factors identified by the analysis are 
shown in Table 3, which shows that male sex, age, kidney 
disease without RRT, NYHA score &gt;2, previous cardiac 
surgery, valve and CABG procedure, application of CPB, 
erythrocyte transfusion, and postoperative LCOS at the 
indicated time points were risk factors for CSA-AKI devel-
opment (Table 3). </p>

<p>Score Development </p>

<p>Next we developed a point system for predicting CSA-AKI 
occurrence with the regression coefficient data from the 
multivariable regression analyses of the derivative cohort 
patients (Table 4). Depending on the scores, the risks of 
CSA-AKI development were categorized into low, medium, 
and high in accordance with the practically observed 
incidence of CSA-AKI (Table 5). The preoperative predictive 
risks of CSA-AKI occurrence were low with 0 to 1 patient 
(9.5%), medium with 2 to 3 patients (22.1%), and high with 
≥4 patients (37.3%). The predictive risks of CSA-AKI devel-</p>

<p>opment at the day of ICU admission were low with 0 to 
4 patients (11.5%), medium with 5 to 9 patients (42.6%), and 
high with ≥10 patients (83.3%). The postoperative predictive 
risks for developing CSA-AKI were low with 0 to 4 patients 
(11.6%), medium with 5 to 9 patients (44.2%), and high with 
≥10 patients (88.8%). The efficiency of the scores for </p>

<p>predicting medium and high risk for CSA-AKI improved with 
the procedure progress and additional risk factors being 
added. We further analyzed the score models at the 3 time </p>

<p>Table 1. Clinical Characteristics of Derivation and Validation 
Cohort </p>

<p>Derivation 
Cohort (N=6081) </p>

<p>Validation Cohort 
(N=1152) </p>

<p>Preoperative </p>

<p>Male 
3767 (61.9%) 
725 (62.9%) </p>

<p>Age, y 
58 (48, 65) 
60 (52, 66) </p>

<p>Renal function </p>

<p>Serum creatinine, 
lmol/L </p>

<p>77 (65, 89) 
78 (66, 90) </p>

<p>eGFR, mL/min 
per 1.73 m 2 </p>

<p>88.7 (69.7, 
99.6) </p>

<p>86.5 (67.6, 
101.6) </p>

<p>Comorbidities </p>

<p>Hypertension 
2012 (33.1%) 
403 (34.9%) </p>

<p>DM 
763 (12.5%) 
200 (17.4%) </p>

<p>COPD 
43 (0.7%) 
9 (0.8%) </p>

<p>CVD 
83 (1.4%) 
14 (1.2%) </p>

<p>Kidney disease 
without RRT </p>

<p>217 (3.6%) 
11 (1.0%) </p>

<p>Heart function </p>

<p>NYHA classification &gt;2 
3428 (56.4%) 
648 (56.2%) </p>

<p>NYHA classification ≤2 
2653 (43.6%) 
504 (43.7%) </p>

<p>LVEF &gt;50% 
5030 (82.7%) 
978 (84.9%) </p>

<p>35&lt; LVEF ≤50 
968 (15.9%) 
157 (13.6%) </p>

<p>LVEF ≤35% 
83 (1.3%) 
17 (1.5%) </p>

<p>Previous cardiac 
surgery </p>

<p>84 (1.4%) 
25 (2.2%) </p>

<p>CM exposure 
2464 (40.5%) 
395 (34.3%) </p>

<p>Intraoperative </p>

<p>Emergency 
11 (0.2%) 
3 (0.3%) </p>

<p>Procedure </p>

<p>Valve 
3975 (65.4%) 
794 (68.9%) </p>

<p>CABG 
1527 (25.1%) 
325 (28.2%) </p>

<p>OPCAB 
286 (4.7%) 
45 (3.9%) </p>

<p>Valve and CABG 
293 (4.8%) 
47 (4.1%) </p>

<p>CPB 
4083 (67.1%) 
792 (68.8) </p>

<p>Erythrocyte transfusion, U 
1 (0, 2) 
1 (0, 2) </p>

<p>Postoperative </p>

<p>LCOS 
158 (2.6%) 
35 (3.1%) </p>

<p>CVP, cm H 2 O 
9 (7, 11) 
10 (8, 10) </p>

<p>Prognosis </p>

<p>28-day mortality 
170 (2.8%) 
39 (3.4%) </p>

<p>AKI indicates acute kidney injury; CABG, coronary artery bypass grafting; CM, contrast 
media; COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; CPB, cardiopulmonary bypass; 
CVD, cerebral vascular disease; CVP, central venous pressure by ICU admittance; DM, 
diabetes mellitus; eGFR, estimated glomerular filtration rate, as was calculated based on 
the CKD-EPI formulas; LCOS, low cardiac output syndrome; LVEF, left ventricular ejection 
fraction; NYHA, New York Heart Association; OPCAB, off-pump coronary artery bypass. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003754 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>AKI Prediction After Cardiac Surgery 
Jiang et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>points by AUROC determinations and derived 0.75 (preop-
erative), 0.81 (ICU admittance), and 0.82 (24 hours after ICU 
admittance) area under curve (AUC) values. The calibrations </p>

<p>of them by Hosmer-Lemeshow statistics resulted in 0.569 
(preoperative), 0.684 (ICU admittance), 0.829 (24 hours 
after ICU admittance). </p>

<p>Table 2. Characteristics of the Patients in the Derivation Cohort </p>

<p>Entire Cohort (N=6081) 
No AKI (N=3922) 
AKI (N=2159) 
P Value </p>

<p>Preoperative </p>

<p>Male 
3767 (61.9%) 
2254 (57.5%) 
1513 (70.1%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Age, y 
58 (48, 65) 
57 (46, 65) 
60 (52, 67) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Kidney function </p>

<p>Serum creatinine, lmol/L 
77 (65, 89) 
73 (63, 86) 
81 (70, 97) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>eGFR, mL/min per 1.73 m 2 
88.7 (72.3, 101.9) 
92.0 (76.7, 104.6) 
81.7(65.5, 96.3) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>&gt;60 mL/min 
5373 (88.3%) 
3635 (92.7%) 
1738 (80.5%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>30&lt; eGFR ≤60 mL/min 
659 (10.8%) 
273 (6.9%) 
386 (17.9%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>≤30 mL/min 
49 (0.9%) 
14 (0.4%) 
35 (1.6%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Comorbidities </p>

<p>Hypertension 
2012 (33.1%) 
1164 (29.7%) 
848 (39.3%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>DM 
763 (12.5%) 
471 (12.0%) 
292 (13.5%) 
0.09 </p>

<p>COPD 
43 (0.7%) 
2 (0.1%) 
41 (1.9%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>CVD 
83 (1.4%) 
15 (0.4%) 
68 (3.1%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Kidney disease without RRT 
217 (3.6%) 
90 (2.3%) 
127 (5.9%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Cardiac function </p>

<p>NYHA classification &gt;2 
3428 (56.4%) 
2075 (52.9%) 
1353 (62.7%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>NYHA classification ≤2 
2653 (43.6%) 
1847 (47.1%) 
806 (37.3%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>LVEF &gt;50% 
5030 (82.7%) 
3412 (87.0%) 
1618 (74.9%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>35&lt; LVEF ≤50 
968 (15.9%) 
482 (12.3%) 
486 (22.5%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>LVEF ≤35% 
83 (1.3%) 
28 (0.7%) 
55 (2.5%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Previous cardiac surgery 
84 (1.4%) 
42 (1.2%) 
42 (1.9%) 
0.008 </p>

<p>CM exposure 
2464 (40.5%) 
1600 (40.8%) 
864 (40.0%) 
0.567 </p>

<p>Intraoperative </p>

<p>Emergency 
11 (0.2%) 
8 (0.2%) 
3 (0.2%) 
0.06 </p>

<p>Procedure </p>

<p>Valve 
3975 (65.4%) 
2642 (67.4%) 
1333 (61.7%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>CABG 
1527 (25.1%) 
1109 (28.3%) 
418 (19.4%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>OPCAB 
286 (4.7%) 
23 (0.6%) 
263 (12.2%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Valve and CABG 
293 (4.8%) 
148 (3.8%) 
145 (6.7%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>CPB 
4083 (67.1%) 
2550 (65.0%) 
1533 (71.0%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Erythrocyte transfusion, U 
1 (0, 2) 
1 (0, 2) 
1 (0, 2) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Postoperative </p>

<p>LCOS 
158 (2.6%) 
19 (0.5%) 
139 (6.4%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>CVP, cm H 2 O 
9 (7, 11) 
8 (6, 11) 
10 (8, 12) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Prognosis </p>

<p>28-day mortality 
170 (2.8%) 
31 (0.8%) 
139 (6.4%) 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>AKI indicates acute kidney injury; CABG, coronary artery bypass grafting; CM, contrast media; COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; CPB, cardiopulmonary bypass; CVD, cerebral 
vascular disease; CVP, central venous pressure by ICU admittance; DM, diabetes mellitus; eGFR, estimated glomerular filtration rate, as was calculated based on the CKD-EPI formulas; 
LCOS, low cardiac output syndrome; LVEF, left ventricular ejection fraction; NYHA, New York Heart Association; OPCAB, off-pump coronary artery bypass. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003754 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>AKI Prediction After Cardiac Surgery 
Jiang et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Score Validation </p>

<p>The clinical characteristics of the 1152 patients in the 
validation cohort are shown in Table 1. Application of the 
scoring system led to AUC values of 0.74 (preoperative), 0.75 
(at ICU admission), and 0.82 (postoperative) (Figure 1). The 
calibration of the scores is shown in Figure 2. There was no 
statistically significant difference between the predicted and 
observed CSA-AKI incidences in the validation cohort </p>

<p>(preoperative v 2 =6.346, P=0.175; at the day of ICU admit-
tance v 2 =4.65, P=0.703; and postoperative v 2 =3.669, 
P=0.886). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In our study we utilized the KDIGO definition of AKI to 
establish the dynamic risk score to predict CSA-AKI. With the </p>

<p>Table 3. Multivariate Logistic Regression Analysis of Factors for CSA-AKI* </p>

<p>Variables 
b 
P Value 
OR 
95% CI </p>

<p>Preoperative </p>

<p>Male 
0.533 
&lt;0.01 
1.704 
1.516 
1.914 </p>

<p>Age, y  † </p>

<p>41 to 60 
0.747 
&lt;0.01 
2.110 
1.622 
2.745 </p>

<p>61 to 80 
0.884 
&lt;0.01 
2.422 
1.862 
3.149 </p>

<p>≥81 
0.947 
0.013 
2.579 
1.221 
5.449 </p>

<p>Kidney disease (without RRT) 
0.754 
&lt;0.01 
1.932 
1.692 
3.105 </p>

<p>NYHA classification &gt;2 
0.364 
&lt;0.01 
1.487 
1.304 
1.665 </p>

<p>Previous cardiac surgery 
0.388 
0.011 
1.475 
1.093 
1.990 </p>

<p>ICU admittance </p>

<p>Male 
0.677 
&lt;0.01 
2.032 
1.698 
1.876 </p>

<p>Age, y  † </p>

<p>41 to 60 
0.877 
&lt;0.01 
2.405 
1.816 
3.184 </p>

<p>61 to 80 
1.122 
&lt;0.01 
3.071 
2.300 
4.099 </p>

<p>≥81 
1.367 
&lt;0.01 
3.923 
1.666 
9.235 </p>

<p>Kidney disease (without RRT) 
0.936 
&lt;0.01 
2.076 
1.845 
2.547 </p>

<p>NYHA classification &gt;2 
0.332 
&lt;0.01 
1.347 
1.342 
1.523 </p>

<p>Previous cardiac surgery 
0.354 
&lt;0.01 
1.452 
1.187 
1.842 </p>

<p>Valve and CABG 
0.643 
&lt;0.01 
1.887 
1.452 
1.872 </p>

<p>Erythrocyte transfusion (per unit) 
0.652 
&lt;0.01 
1.652 
1.025 
1.176 </p>

<p>24 hours after ICU admittance </p>

<p>Male 
0.651 
&lt;0.01 
1.918 
1.639 
2.244 </p>

<p>Age, y  † </p>

<p>41 to 60 
0.868 
&lt;0.01 
2.382 
1.788 
3.173 </p>

<p>61 to 80 
1.173 
&lt;0.01 
3.233 
2.397 
4.358 </p>

<p>≥81 
1.315 
&lt;0.01 
3.726 
1.565 
8.875 </p>

<p>Kidney disease (without RRT) 
1.029 
&lt;0.01 
2.799 
2.001 
3.914 </p>

<p>CPB application 
0.489 
&lt;0.01 
1.631 
1.39 
1.914 </p>

<p>Previous cardiac surgery 
0.468 
&lt;0.01 
1.596 
1.309 
1.946 </p>

<p>Valve and CABG 
0.626 
&lt;0.01 
1.833 
1.579 
2.232 </p>

<p>Erythrocyte transfusion (per unit) 
0.856 
&lt;0.01 
2.376 
1.588 
2.365 </p>

<p>LCOS 
1.387 
&lt;0.01 
3.542 
2.234 
4.763 </p>

<p>CABG indicates coronary artery bypass grafting; CSA-AKI, cardiac surgery associated acute kidney injury; LCOS, low cardiac output syndrome; NYHA, New York Heart Association; RRT, 
renal replacement therapy. 
*Only the statistically significant risk factors in the logistic regression were contained in this table. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>The variable age was categorized and (age ≤40) was set as the reference level. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003754 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>AKI Prediction After Cardiac Surgery 
Jiang et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>KDIGO guideline, which is accepted by the global nephrology 
community, some authors carried out risk factor analysis for 
CSA-AKI 16,17 with the new AKI definition. To the best of our 
knowledge, there were no dynamically designed risk scores </p>

<p>for predicting CSA-AKI from preoperative to early postoper-
ative periods. Not only pre-op risk factors but also the intra-op 
and post-op risk factors were enrolled in the analysis for 
better predictive efficiency. The result of our study showed 
that the predictive value of the dynamic risk scores was close 
to that of the previous scores and improved as the intra-op 
(AUC=0.75) and post-op (AUC=0.82) risk factors were 
admitted into the multivariate regression analysis and the 
subsequent scores. These risk scores can help clinicians to 
evaluate the risk of CSA-AKI from preoperative to early 
postoperative periods. 
In this study all the major risk factors of CSA-AKI were 
collected to derive the predictive score system, including the 
intra-op and post-op risk factors. </p>

<p>Table 4. Factor Scoring for Predicting of CSA-AKI 
Development </p>

<p>Variables 
Points </p>

<p>Preoperative </p>

<p>Male 
1 </p>

<p>Age, y </p>

<p>≤40 
0 </p>

<p>41 to 60 
1 </p>

<p>61 to 80 
2 </p>

<p>≥81 
3 </p>

<p>Kidney disease (without RRT) 
1 </p>

<p>NYHA classification &gt;2 
1 </p>

<p>Previous cardiac surgery 
1 </p>

<p>ICU admittance </p>

<p>Male 
1 </p>

<p>Age, y </p>

<p>≤40 
0 </p>

<p>41 to 60 
1 </p>

<p>61 to 80 
2 </p>

<p>≥81 
3 </p>

<p>Kidney disease (without RRT) 
1 </p>

<p>NYHA classification &gt;2 
1 </p>

<p>Previous cardiac surgery 
1 </p>

<p>Valve and CABG 
1 </p>

<p>Erythrocyte transfusion 
1/unit </p>

<p>24 hours after ICU admittance </p>

<p>Male 
1 </p>

<p>Age, y </p>

<p>≤40 
0 </p>

<p>41 to 60 
1 </p>

<p>61 to 80 
2 </p>

<p>≥81 
3 </p>

<p>Kidney disease (without RRT) 
1 </p>

<p>CPB application 
1 </p>

<p>Previous cardiac surgery 
1 </p>

<p>Valve and CABG 
1 </p>

<p>Erythrocyte transfusion (per unit) 
1/unit </p>

<p>LCOS 
1 </p>

<p>CABG indicates coronary artery bypass grafting; CPB, cardiopulmonary bypass; CSA-AKI, 
cardiac surgery associated acute kidney injury; ICU, intensive care unit; LCOS, low 
cardiac output syndrome; NYHA, New York Heart Association. </p>

<p>Table 5. Risk Stratification of CSA-AKI Development at 
Indicated Time Points </p>

<p>Sum Points 
Preoperative </p>

<p>ICU 
Admittance </p>

<p>24 Hours After 
ICU Admittance </p>

<p>0 to 1 pts 
Low 
Low 
Low </p>

<p>2 to 3 pts 
Medium 
Low 
Low </p>

<p>4 pts 
High 
Low 
Low </p>

<p>5 to 9 pts 
High 
Medium 
Medium </p>

<p>≥10 pts 
High 
High 
High </p>

<p>The distinction of low/medium/high was based on the incidence of CSA-AKI in each 
sector; eg, the incidence of AKI in the sector of ≥10 pts in the 24 hours after ICU 
admittance column was 88.8%, which meant in the patients who scored ≥10 points at 
the time of 24 hours after admission, the incidence of CSA-AKI was 88.8%. CSA-AKI 
indicates cardiac surgery-associated acute kidney injury. </p>

<p>Figure 1. ROC curves for predicting CSA-AKI in the validation </p>

<p>cohort with point scores from Table 5. *Application of the scoring 
system led to AUC values of 0.74 (preoperative), 0.75 (at ICU 
admission), and 0.82 (postoperative). </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003754 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>AKI Prediction After Cardiac Surgery 
Jiang et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Male sex and age were risk factors for CSA-AKI in all 3 time 
points, and with increasing age, the incidence of CSA-AKI also 
increased. Age-associated AKI was reported to occur more 
frequently in the elderly due to structural changes such as 
vascular sclerosis, increased percentages of sclerosing 
glomeruli, and other degenerative changes that occur with 
increasing age, 18,19 and our finding is in agreement with other 
publications from Fang et al, 20,21 who noted that the 
incidence of CSA-AKI in the older patients was higher than 
that in younger patients. In our cohort we conducted a 
subgroup analysis according to the categorized age and found </p>

<p>significant differences in CSA-AKI incidence between groups 
(Figure 3). The risk factor of male sex is in disagreement with 
other publications in which female sex was a risk factor, 22,23 
which needs further analysis. 
Another CSA-AKI risk factor was preoperative kidney 
disease without renal replacement therapy. Preoperative renal 
dysfunction was related to CSA-AKI in several other stud-
ies. 4,8,23 However, we excluded preoperative RRT patients and 
also drew the same conclusion. In Table 2, the eGFR was 
statistically significantly different between AKI and non-AKI 
cohorts (P&lt;0.01). In the subsequent subgroup analysis, we 
found significant differences in the incidence of CSA-AKI 
among subgroups. However, unlike age, categorized eGFR were 
eliminated through logistic regression. The possible reason 
may be that we brought many more parameters, such as 
"previous kidney disease without RRT," into our study in order </p>

<p>to improve prediction, so the relationship between eGFR and 
CSA-AKI could be somehow diluted in the multivariate analysis. 
Another possible reason was that the kidney function (preop-
erative serum creatine and eGFR) in our cohorts was better 
than that of existing model derivation cohorts. 
The predictors above were also listed in the previous 
scores; the innovation and superiority of our scores result 
from our inclusion of intra-op and post-op predictors. With the 
awareness of intra-op and post-op risk factors contributing to 
CSA-AKI, the risk stratification based on only pre-op risk 
factors does not take into account the patients' physiological 
response to the surgeon and post-op treatment as well as the 
occurrence of adverse events in the intra-op and post-op 
periods, which increase the risk of CSA-AKI. Patients under-
going cardiac surgery typically exhibit complex syndromes 
with numerous pathways that affect renal function and involve 
hemodynamic changes, tissue breakdown, reactive oxygen 
species, infection, and drug toxicity. All of these factors can </p>

<p>Figure 2. Score calibrations for predicting CSA-AKI (A) preop-</p>

<p>erative, (B) at the day of ICU admittance, (C) postoperative. 
*There was no statistically significant difference between the 
CSA-AKI incidences predicted by point scores and those observed 
in the validation cohort (preoperative v 2 =6.346, P=0.175; at the 
day of ICU admittance v 2 =4.65, P=0.703; and postoperative 
v 2 =3.669, P=0.886). CSA-AKI indicates cardiac surgery-associ-</p>

<p>ated acute kidney injury. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Subgroup analysis between categorized age groups </p>

<p>for CSA-AKI incidence. *The CSA-AKI incidence was statistically 
significantly different within the subgroups, and increased with 
age. CSA-AKI indicates cardiac surgery-associated acute kidney 
injury. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003754 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>AKI Prediction After Cardiac Surgery 
Jiang et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>result in endothelial dysfunction, blood dynamics disorders, 
inflammatory responses, and tubular cell damage. 
Intraoperative erythrocyte transfusion was recognized as 
predictor for CSA-AKI in our study. Previous studies also 
found a correlation of erythrocyte transfusion and CSA-
AKI, 24,25 and it has been reported that the posttransfusion 
recovery of red blood cells is lower after long-term storage 26 ; 
the morphological and biochemical changes during storage 
have been suggested to promote a proinflammatory state, 
impair tissue oxygen delivery, and exacerbate tissue oxidative 
stress due to free iron, which in turn is an AKI risk factor for 
susceptible CPB patients. 27 Some studies suggest that each 
unit of perioperative blood transfusion is significantly asso-
ciated with a 10% to 20% increase in the risk of AKI after 
cardiac surgery with CPB 25,28 in spite of the different AKI 
definitions. Some surgical teams trying to reduce the potential 
renal harm of erythrocyte transfusion have found promising 
options, 29 including reducing perioperative hemodilution by 
minimizing fluid administration and retrograde autologous 
priming of the cardiopulmonary circuit, salvage of shed blood, 
tolerance of moderate hemodilution, and early identification 
and treatment with erythropoietin-stimulating agents and iron 
therapy. 
In previous studies some complex procedures, especially 
valve surgery combined with CABG, were found to increase 
the incidence of CSA-AKI. 6-9 This conclusion was also proven 
in our study, in which valve combined with CABG was one of 
the risk factors. Perioperative cardiac function has a definite 
impact on CSA-AKI. Chetow et al 4 found local renal ischemia 
injury due to insufficient perfusion contributes to CSA-AKI. 
Preoperative NYHA scores &gt;2, previous cardiac surgery, and 
postoperative LCOS were also found to be risk factors for 
CSA-AKI in our study. Among the above factors, preoperative </p>

<p>NYHA scores &gt;2 and previous cardiac surgery are not 
modifiable. The LCOS may result from delayed recovery of 
post-op cardiac function and cause pulmonary edema and 
pulmonary infection, which in turn aggravate LCOS in a 
vicious circle. 30 For those CSA-AKI patients who were unable 
to eliminate excess fluid and adverse inflammatory factors, 
either LCOS or pulmonary infection would result in a worse 
prognosis. Some studies 31 were carried out to break this 
vicious circle by means of "perioperative goal-directed 
hemodynamic resuscitation therapy," which was considered 
to be useful in reducing adverse complications including LCOS 
as well as 30-day mortality in high-risk patients undergoing 
cardiac surgery. 
AKI is one of the common complications after cardiac 
surgery. The lack of a consensus AKI definition has led to 
inaccuracy in data regarding the actual incidence of this 
complication, as can be confirmed by the large variation (1% 
to 30%) in the reported incidence of AKI following cardiac 
surgery. 22 By the time of this study, no consensus AKI 
definition was utilized in the risk scores above, and so their 
worldwide applicability is suspect. The KDIGO criterion, 
published in 2012, was regarded as a complement to 
previous AKI definitions. 32,33 Sampaio et al compared the 
KDIGO AKI definition with AKIN and RIFLE criteria and 
validated its superiority, especially for prognoses in unstable 
hemodynamic cardiac surgery patients. 34 Therefore, risk 
scores with the KDIGO AKI definition were better for 
predicting CSA-AKI. 
Cardiac surgery in developing countries such as China, 
India, and Brazil has grown at a steady pace for decades, but 
most centers performing open heart surgery are located in the 
major cities, which is a common problem for most developing 
countries. Although as the economy has developed, and </p>

<p>Table 6. Comparison of Derivation Cohort and Other Risk Scores in Comorbidities and Procedures </p>

<p>Derivation Cohort (n=6081) 
AKICS (n=603) 
Cleveland (n=15 838) 
Mehta (n=449 524) 
SRI (n=10 751) </p>

<p>Comorbidities </p>

<p>Hypertension 
2012 (33.1%) 
500 (82.6%) 
-
75.2% 
5891 (54.8%) </p>

<p>DM 
763 (12.5%) 
169 (28%) 
3857 (24.3%) 
33.2% 
2381 (22.1%) </p>

<p>COPD 
43 (0.7%) 
-
1326 (8.4%) 
19.6% 
427 (3.9%) </p>

<p>CVD 
83 (1.4%) 
28 (4.6%) 
2713 (17.1%) 
13.8% 
968 (9%) </p>

<p>Kidney disease without RRT 
217 (3.6%) 
-
-
-
-</p>

<p>Procedure </p>

<p>Valve 
3975 (65.4%) 
794 (37%) 
4086 (25.8%) 
10.3% 
1755 (16.3%) </p>

<p>CABG* 
1813 (29.8%) 
319 (53%) 
8314 (52.5%) 
78.6% 
7005 (65.1%) </p>

<p>Valve and CABG 
293 (4.8%) 
61 (10%) 
2594 (16.4%) 
10.1% 
1991 (18.5%) </p>

<p>CABG indicates coronary artery bypass grafting; COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; CVD, cerebral vascular disease; DM, diabetes mellitus; RRT, renal replacement therapy; SRI, 
simplified renal index. 
*Including off-pump coronary artery bypass. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003754 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>AKI Prediction After Cardiac Surgery 
Jiang et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>cardiac surgery has become affordable for more patients, its 
complications are adding to the social economic burden in 
developing countries. 35,36 Considering the tremendous pop-
ulation in developing countries, this is worthy of concern. 
The occurrence of valve surgery is becoming higher in 
developing countries such as China than it was in previous 
risk stratification development centers, in which CABG is 
the major procedure (Table 6). This change may be due to 
the lack in early diagnosis and imbalanced distribution of 
medical resources; it is also one of the reasons why CSA-
AKI incidence was high in our cohort. Compared to CABG, 
the pathophysiology and pathological impairment are diver-
sified. Patients who undergo valve surgery typically demon-
strate low stroke volume related to regurgitation, which 
increases the vulnerability of the kidney to injury during 
cardiac surgery. The comorbidities in developing countries 
such as China are also different from those in the Western 
population. In our derivation cohort, the ratios of hyper-
tension and diabetes mellitus are also remarkably lower 
than those in the previous developmental populations 
(Table 6). 
Therefore, the difference in ethnicity, comorbidities, 
and underlying disease may affect the efficacy of the 
existing models predicting CSA-AKI in patients of developing 
countries. 
As in Thakar's and Palomba's studies, 7,8 the present risk 
scores are validated in a sample extracted from the original 
population with good discrimination and calibration. For 
simpler clinical application, the scores are stratified in 
categories according to the predictive risk of CSA-AKI. The 
maximum predictive risk of 88.8%, which is higher than those 
in other studies, may be attributed to the KDIGO AKI 
definition, which was verified with better efficacy, and the 
inclusion of intra-op and post-op predictors, with which the 
course of disease can be well simulated. 
The limitation of this study was that the data were derived 
from a single-center Chinese database, implying differences in 
procedures and comorbidities with other existing risk scores, 
so their predictive efficiency should be prospectively validated 
in more centers and on a larger scale. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>We carried out this study prospectively and developed 
dynamic predictive scores for CSA-AKI in cardiac surgical 
patients with the KDIGO definition for AKI. This may improve 
the early recognition and intervention against CSA-AKI, fix 
those modifiable factors, reduce the incidence of CSA-AKI, 
and improve the renal and overall prognosis. Embedding these 
scores into the electronic medical record (EMR) system may 
improve their clinical practical utility. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We are grateful for the contribution of the study personnel from the 
Departments of Nephrology, Cardiac Surgery, and Critical Care for 
persistent contribution to the maintenance of the cardiac surgery 
database. </p>

<p>Sources of Funding </p>

<p>The study was funded by Natural Science Foundation of China 
(No. 81430015). </p>

<p>Disclosures </p>

<p>None. </p>





<p>AKI Prediction After Cardiac Surgery 
Jiang et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>



<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.116.003754 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>AKI Prediction After Cardiac Surgery 
Jiang et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

</text></tei>