<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5098131" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Human bone marrow contains a population of non-hematopoietic stromal stem/progenitor cells (BMSCs), 
which play a central role for bone marrow stroma and the hematopoietic microenvironment. However, the 
precise characteristics and potential stem cell properties of defined BMSC populations have not yet been 
thoroughly investigated. Using standard adherent colony-forming unit fibroblast (CFU-F) assays, we have 
previously shown that BMSCs were highly enriched in the nonhematopoietic CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg fraction 
of normal adult human bone marrow. In this study, we demonstrate that prospectively isolated CD271 pos / 
CD140a low/neg BMSCs expressed high levels of hematopoiesis supporting genes and signature mesenchymal 
and multipotency genes on a single cell basis. Furthermore, CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg BMSCs gave rise to non-
adherent sphere colonies (mesenspheres) with typical surface marker profile and trilineage in vitro differenti-
ation potential. Importantly, serial transplantations of CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg BMSC-derived mesenspheres 
(single cell and bulk) into immunodeficient NOD scid gamma (NSG) mice showed increased mesensphere 
numbers and full differentiation potential after both primary and secondary transplantations. In contrast, BMSC 
self-renewal potential decreased under standard adherent culture conditions. These data therefore indicate that 
CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg BMSCs represent a population of primary stem cells with MSC phenotype and sphere-
forming capacity that fulfill stringent functional stem cell criteria in vivo in a serial transplantation setting. </p>

<p>H uman bone marrow contains a population of non-</p>

<p>hematopoietic stromal stem/progenitor cells (BMSCs), 
which are important components of the hematopoietic stem 
cell niche, give rise to the hematopoietic stroma upon trans-
plantation, and possess in vivo multilineage differentiation 
capacities toward skeletal lineages [1-3]. Despite their key 
role in bone marrow physiology, little is known about BMSC 
stem cell characteristics, which is mainly due to the fact that 
primary BMSCs have thus far been elusive for a precise 
phenotypical definition. However, recent progress has led 
to the identification of suitable markers/marker combinations 
to effectively enrich BMSCs [1,2,4-6], and furthermore, 
recently-developed non-adherent mesensphere cultures al-
lowed to assay and amplify potent hematopoiesis-supporting 
BMSCs while preserving their undifferentiated phenotype [7]. 
Using these tools, the current study therefore aimed to 
investigate key phenotypical and, importantly, functional </p>

<p>stem cell properties of prospectively isolated human 
BMSCs. Our results clearly demonstrate for the first time 
that non-hematopoietic CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg cells are 
stromal stem cells with in vivo self-renewal and differenti-
ation potential in a serial transplantation setting. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Bone marrow mononuclear cells </p>

<p>In total, bone marrow samples (60 mL) were aspirated from 
the iliac crest bone of consenting healthy adult donors (n = 41, 
median age 25 years, and range 19-35). The study was ap-
proved by the local ethics committee. Bone marrow mono-
nuclear cells (BM-MNCs) were isolated by density gradient 
centrifugation (Ficoll-Paque Premium; GE Healthcare Life 
Sciences) following incubation with RosetteSep Human 
Mesenchymal Stem Cell Enrichment Cocktail (StemCell 
Technologies) for lineage depletion (CD3, CD14, CD19, 
CD38, CD66b, and glycophorin A). </p>

<p>1 Lund Stem Cell Center, University of Lund, Lund, Sweden. 
2 Division of Molecular Hematology, Department of Laboratory Medicine, University of Lund, Lund, Sweden, 
3 Department of Hematology,  University Hospital, Lund, Sweden. </p>

<p>Ó Roshanak Ghazanfari et al., 2016; Published by Mary Ann Liebert, Inc. This Open Access article is distributed under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits any noncommercial 
use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited </p>

<p>STEM CELLS AND DEVELOPMENT 
Volume 25, Number 21, 2016 
Mary Ann Liebert, Inc. 
DOI: 10.1089/scd.2016.0169 </p>



<p>Fluorescence-activated cell sorting </p>

<p>Lineage-depleted BM-MNCs were incubated in blocking 
buffer [DPBS w/o Ca 2+ , Mg 2+ , 3.3 mg/mL human normal 
immunoglobulin (Octapharma)] and 1% fetal bovine serum 
(Life Technologies), followed by staining with monoclonal 
antibodies against CD45, CD271, and CD140a (for detailed 
information on the antibodies used in this study, please see 
Supplementary Materials and Methods; Supplementary Data 
are available online at www.liebertpub.com/scd). Sorting gates 
were set according to the corresponding fluorescence-minus-
one (FMO) controls. Cells were sorted on a fluorescence ac-
tivated cell sorting (FACS)Aria II or a FACSAria III cell sorter 
(BD Biosciences). Dead cells were excluded by 7-amino-
actinomycin (7-AAD; Sigma) staining, and doublets were ex-
cluded by gating on FSC-H versus FSC-W and SSC-H versus 
SSC-W. A description of the flow cytometric analysis is pro-
vided in the Supplementary Materials and Methods. </p>

<p>Non-adherent mesensphere cultures </p>

<p>Sorted BM-MNCs were plated at low density (&lt;1,000 
cells/cm 2 ) in ultralow adherence plates (Corning) in sphere 
growth medium as described before [8]. The medium com-
position is described in detail in the Supplementary Materials 
and Methods. To prevent cell aggregation, cultures were left 
untouched for 1 week. Thereafter, half-medium changes were 
performed twice weekly. Spheres were passaged following 
enzymatic digestion with 0.25% type I collagenase (StemCell 
Technologies) for 30 min at 37°C, followed by washing with 
PBS, and replating at clonal density. </p>

<p>Generation of adherent marrow stromal cells 
and colony-forming unit fibroblast assays </p>

<p>Sorted BM-MNCs were cultured in standard MSC culture 
medium [StemMACS MSC Expansion Medium (Miltenyi 
Biotec, Bergisch Gladbach) plus 1% antibiotic-antimycotic 
solution (Sigma)]. Medium was changed weekly and pas-
saged as described [2]. Colony-forming unit fibroblast 
(CFU-F) assays were performed as before [2] and as de-
scribed in the Supplementary Materials and Methods. </p>

<p>In vitro differentiation assays </p>

<p>Stromal cells derived from adherent and sphere cultures 
were differentiated toward the adipogenic, osteogenic, and 
chondrogenic lineages as described [2]. Briefly, for adipogenic 
differentiation, cells were cultured for 14 days in AdipoDiff 
medium (Miltenyi Biotec) and stained with Oil red O (Sigma) </p>

<p>following fixation. For osteogenic differentiation, cells were 
cultured in osteogenesis induction medium (see Supplementary 
Materials and Methods) for 21 days and calcium depositions 
were visualized by alizarin red staining (Sigma). Chondrogenic 
differentiation was induced by culturing cell pellets for 28 days 
in chondrogenesis-induction medium (see Supplementary 
Materials and Methods). Cryosections of fixed pellets were 
stained with goat anti-human aggrecan, and nuclei were stained 
with 4', 6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI; Life Technolo-
gies). Sections were analyzed with an Axiovert 200 M fluo-
rescence microscope equipped with an AxioCam HRm camera 
(both from Carl Zeiss). </p>

<p>In vivo transplantation </p>

<p>For primary in vivo transplantations, sorted lin neg /CD45 neg / 
CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg cells were expanded under non-
adherent and adherent conditions. Spheres and colonies, re-
spectively, were generated both from bulk sorted cells (seeded 
at clonal densities) and from single sorted cells. After expan-
sion, cells were harvested and loaded overnight on hydroxy-
apatite/tricalcium phosphate ceramic powder (HA/TCP; 
Triosite, Zimmer) and then implanted s.c. into 8-week-old 
NOD.Cg-Prkdcscid Il2rgtm1Wjl/SzJ (NSG) mice. 
To evaluate in vivo self-renewal, implants were removed after 
8 weeks, digested in 0.25% type I collagenase (STEMCELL 
Technologies) for 2 h at 37°C, and the harvested cells were 
stained with anti-mouse CD45 and anti-human CD90 and 
CD105 antibodies for FACS sorting. CD45 neg CD90 pos CD105 pos 
sorted live cells (7AAD exclusion) were plated at clonal density 
for sphere and CFU-F colony formation. Spheres and CFU-Fs 
were enumerated after 10 and 14 days, respectively, and further 
expanded for secondary transplantations. 
To assess the in vivo differentiation capacities, implants 
were removed after 8 weeks after primary and secondary 
sections were either stained with hematoxylin/eosin and an-
alyzed as described [9] or prepared for immunohistochemistry 
as described below. The animal procedures were approved by 
the local ethics committee on animal experimentation. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Paraffin-embedded implanted samples were cut into 5 mm 
thick sections. Sections were deparaffinized and rehydrated 
following standard protocols [6]. Following antigen retrieval and 
blocking, sections were stained with primary antibodies (anti-
vimentin, anti-mitochondria, and anti-CD45) and secondary 
antibodies followed by signal visualization (EnVision labeled 
polymer HRP; Dako) and microscopic examination using an </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Highly enriched CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg BMSCs display typical stromal cell characteristics. (A) Cytospin prep-
arations of sorted human bone marrow (BM) CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg cells showed a typical primary BMSC morphology, that 
is, large immature nuclei with an open chromatin pattern and cytoplasmic vacuoles (May-Grunwald/Giemsa staining, scale bar 
represents 20 mm). (B) Flow cytometric surface marker co-expression analysis on primary CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg BMSCs. 
2 · 10 6 events were acquired and plotted for CD271 versus the marker listed on the top after FSC/SSC gating, doublet, and 
dead cell exclusion (the gating strategy is illustrated in Supplementary Fig. S1A). A representative dataset is shown. (C, D) 
Single-cell gene expression analysis was performed on sorted CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg from three donors. The results are 
shown as heatmap, in which each of the 39 columns represents an individual cell (C) and as violin plots illustrating the 
expression level of the genes across the samples based on ANOVA (D). Genes are listed according to function and cell type. 
Group I: hematopoietic supporting genes, group II: commonly expressed MSC genes, group III: differentiation-related genes, 
group IV: mesodermal markers, group V: neural crest markers, and group VI: signaling pathway genes. (E) Gene expression 
analysis of sorted single lin neg /CD45 neg /CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg cells compared with non-CFU-F-containing lin neg /CD45 neg / 
CD271 neg /CD140a neg cells from the same donors. The results are shown as Principal Component Analysis (PCA). </p>

<p>‰ </p>

<p>BMSC PHENOTYPE AND STEM CELL FUNCTION 
1653 </p>



<p>Olympus camera (BX51) and the <rs id="software-0" type="software">cellSens Dimension software</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Olympus</rs>). Details of the staining procedure are provided in the 
Supplementary Materials and Methods. </p>

<p>Quantitative RT-PCR </p>

<p>RNA from sorted CD90 pos CD105 pos , CD90 neg CD105 neg , 
and mouse CD45 pos cells recovered from implants after 
primary transplantation was isolated from four individual 
donors. cDNA was synthesized, and quantitative real-time 
PCR analysis was performed (for more details, see Sup-
plementary Materials and Methods). </p>

<p>Single-cell real-time PCR (Fluidigm) </p>

<p>Primary BM-MNCs were sorted based on the expression of 
CD271 and CD140a. Lin neg /CD45 neg /CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg 
and lin neg /CD45 neg /CD271 neg /CD140a neg single cells were 
sorted directly into lysis buffer containing low EDTA TE 
buffer (Teknova), NP-40 (Sigma), and SUPERaseIn (Life 
Technologies). cDNA synthesis of single cells was per-
formed using the qScript cDNA SuperMix Kit (Quanta 
Bioscience). Specific Target Amplification of 48 genes of in-
terest (genes are listed in Supplementary Table S1) was carried 
out using the TATAA PreAmp GrandMaster Mix Kit (TATAA 
Biocenter) and the final product underwent exonuclease 
treatment (Exonuclease I Kit; New England Biolabs). The 
samples were mixed with EvaGreen Supermix-low ROX (Bio-
Rad) and DNA binding dye and loading reagent (both from 
Fluidigm), loaded onto the 48.48 Dynamic Array IFC chip, 
and run on the BioMarkÔ (Fluidigm) system. Data analysis 
was performed using the <rs type="software">BioMark Real-Time PCR Analysis</rs> 
and <rs id="software-2" type="software">Singular Analysis Toolset software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Fluidigm</rs>). The 
grouping of the genes as presented in the violin plot analysis 
was based on published information on gene functions. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data are expressed as mean -standard deviation (mean -SD). 
Student's t-test and ANOVA were used for statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Results and Discussion </p>

<p>Phenotypical and sphere-forming properties 
of primary CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg BMSCs </p>

<p>In the last years, considerable progress has been made in 
the identification of human primary BMSC markers [3,5]. 
We have previously reported that lin neg /CD45 neg /CD271 pos / 
CD140a low/neg human bone marrow cells (hereinafter referred 
to as CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg cells) represented a (close to) 
pure population of stromal progenitor cells [6]. 
As reported, freshly-sorted CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg cells 
showed typical morphological BMSC features (Fig. 1A) [2,10] 
and expressed a typical ''mesenchymal'' stromal cell (MSC) 
surface marker profile (Fig. 1B) [5,6,11]. Expression of CD56, 
which was reported to identify bone-lining BMSCs [5], was 
limited to a small fraction of the cells (Fig. 1B). Thus, CD56 
might be a possible positive marker for endosteal niche 
BMSCs, complementary to the negative expression of CD146 
that we previously reported for this cell population [2]. Ex-
pression of integrin a6 (CD49f) on cultured MSC has been 
implicated in enhancing stem cell properties [12]. Interest-
ingly, CD49f was clearly expressed in about one third of the </p>

<p>CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg cells (Fig. 1B), which might indicate 
a possible role of CD49f in maintaining stemness of primary 
BMSCs. Certainly, this is an interesting point that will be 
addressed in future experiments. 
Gene expression profiling of prospectively enriched BMSC 
has been reported for bulk sorted cells [6,13,14], which has 
obvious limitations when aiming to characterize highly-purified 
BMSCs. We therefore investigated the expression of a panel of 
selected BMSC-relevant genes in single-sorted CD271 pos / 
CD140a low/neg cells (Fig. 1C, D and Supplementary Table S1). 
CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg cells showed a high and homoge-
neous expression of CXCL12 and ANGPT (Fig. 1D, group I), 
the majority of common MSC-related genes (group II), most of 
the differentiation genes (group III), as well as Wnt signaling 
pathway-related genes (group VI), which are in accordance 
with published data on bulk sorted cells [13,14]. Interestingly, 
IL-7 expression was heterogeneous (group I), which might 
point to a differential function of BMSC subsets in bone mar-
row lymphopoiesis. Furthermore, variances in expression of 
chondrocyte differentiation marker SOX9 (Fig. 1D, group III) 
are likely to reflect differentiation potential differences. Low 
expression levels were observed for NES (group II), SOX10 
(group V), as well as several group IV and VI genes. Finally, 
CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg cells clearly formed a distinct popu-
lation as identified by principal component analysis compared 
with the non-CFU-F-containing CD271 neg cells (Fig. 1E). 
In vitro, CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg cells formed typical 
spheres (Fig. 2A) and CFU-F (not shown), the latter being the 
standard classical assay for clonogenic BM stromal cells. 
Progenitor cell frequencies of sorted CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg 
BMSCs were comparable in both assays (Fig. 2B), and 
crossover replating experiments demonstrated that spheres and 
CFU-Fs had similar capacities to form secondary and tertiary 
CFU-Fs and spheres, respectively (Fig. 2C). Furthermore, 
CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg -derived spheres exhibited a typical 
surface marker profile and in vitro differentiation pattern 
(Fig. 2D, E), and increasing sphere numbers in vitro were 
observed up to the second passage (Fig. 2F), which was 
comparable to standard CFU-F cultures (Fig. 2G). 
Taken together, these data indicate that CD271 pos / 
CD140a low/neg cells represent a highly enriched population 
of BMSCs with phenotypical stroma cell properties and in 
vitro mesensphere-forming capacity. </p>

<p>In vivo stem cell functions of CD271 pos / 
CD140a low/neg BMSCs </p>

<p>Previous reports demonstrated in vitro stem/progenitor cell 
properties of human BMSCs [15,16]. However, true stem cell 
properties cannot be assessed in vitro, but only in vivo by 
proving that a putative stem cell can generate cells that are 
functionally equivalent to the original. 
Evidence that primary BMSCs are stem cells comes from 
seminal studies demonstrating that single CFU-F-derived 
clonal cells were capable of generating bone and hemato-
poietic stroma in vivo and that secondary CFU-F could be 
recovered from the transplants [1]. Furthermore, in vivo 
self-renewal of clonogenic cells was demonstrated for fetal 
human and adult murine BMSCs using the mesensphere 
assay [8,17]. However, whether or not adult human BMSCs 
fulfill stringent stem cell criteria in a serial transplantation 
setting has not been thoroughly addressed thus far, although </p>

<p>BMSC PHENOTYPE AND STEM CELL FUNCTION </p>

<p>
FIG. 2. In vitro potential of lin neg /CD45 neg /CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg human bone marrow stromal cells. (A) CD271 pos / 
CD140a low/neg BMSCs were sorted and assayed as spheres. The morphology of typical spheres is shown in (A) (scale bar indicates 
200 mm). (B) Frequencies of CFU-F and spheres in bulk-sorted lin neg /CD45 neg /CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg cells were comparable 
(data are presented as mean -SD, n = 6). (C) Sorted lin neg /CD45 neg /CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg cells were assayed in standard 
adherent culture as CFU-F and as sphere colonies in sphere cultures. CFU-F and sphere colonies were then harvested and replated 
under both, CFU-F and sphere conditions, for two additional passages. Data are given for individual experiments with spheres and 
CFU-F indicated by circles (B) and triangles (D), respectively. Arrows used in the x-axis labels indicate switch to the next culture 
condition, for example, ''sph/CFU-F/sph'' indicates that cells initially cultured under sphere conditions were recultured as 
CFU-F, and finally cultured as tertiary colonies under sphere conditions. (D) Spheres showed a typical MSC surface marker 
profile; a representative set of data with passage 3 cells of a total of three experiments is shown. Blue line: spheres; red line: 
corresponding isotype control. (E) Trilineage in vitro differentiation potential of CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg BMSC-derived 
spheres. A representative set of pictures from a total of three experiments with passage 2 cells is shown; scale bars represent 
100 mm (adipocyte) and 200 mm (osteoblast and chondrocyte). (F) CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg BMSC-derived spheres were har-
vested and replated up to four times. A net increase of sphere numbers was observed for the first and second passages, 
respectively. Data are presented as -fold change from three independent experiments indicated by different symbols. (G) 
CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg BMSC-derived CFU-Fs were harvested and replated up to four times. Data are presented as -fold change 
from four independent experiments indicated by different symbols. Sph, spheres. </p>



<p>this is an important aspect when characterizing the nature 
and function of primary native BMSCs. 
We therefore short-term expanded single-cell and bulk-
sorted CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg BMSCs as spheres followed 
by subcutaneous implantation into immunodeficient mice 
(Fig. 3A). After 8 weeks, implants were harvested, assayed for 
human spheres, and then retransplanted into secondary recip-
ients. FACS-isolation of human transplanted cells was per-
formed based on the expression of human CD90 and CD105 
(Supplementary Fig. S2A). CD90 and CD105 were chosen as 
sorting markers because of their relative stable expression in 
the transplanted cells in contrast to other markers. The sorting 
strategy and detection approach were validated by qPCR </p>

<p>analysis of human and mouse housekeeping genes (Supple-
mentary Fig. S2B). 
In vivo self-renewal of CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg BMSCs 
was demonstrated by increasing number of spheres after 
primary and secondary transplantation compared with pre-
transplantation values for both bulk-sorted (1.16 -0.06 and 
2.34 -0.13-fold, respectively, n = 3) and single cell-derived 
spheres (1.54 -0.28 and 2.51 -0.72-fold, n = 3) (Fig. 3B and 
Supplementary Table S2). In contrast, implantation of ad-
herently cultured CFU-Fs resulted in a more than 100-fold 
reduction of colony numbers after primary transplantation 
(Supplementary Fig. S2C), and therefore, secondary CFU-F 
transplantations were not performed. 
In addition to in vivo sphere self-renewal, CD271 pos / 
CD140a low/neg BMSCs demonstrated serial in vivo differ-
entiation capacity. Transplanted spheres generated human 
bone, adipocytes, and stromal tissues after primary and 
secondary implantation, with murine hematopoietic cells 
invading the implants (Fig. 3C, D, respectively). There is 
cumulating evidence that differentiation potentials differ 
between stromal cells depending on their tissue of origin 
[18-20]. Our current work focused on BMSC and it there-
fore remains to be investigated whether or not stromal cell 
preparations from other sources have similar sphere for-
mation and serial in vivo transplantation capacities. 
Taken together, these results indicate that primary 
CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg BMSCs are capable of in vivo self-
renewal and differentiation. Cultures, which contained growth 
factors and prevented adherence to plastic, but not standard </p>

<p>FIG. 3. In vivo self-renewal and differentiation capacity of 
lin neg /CD45 neg /CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg human bone marrow 
stromal cells. (A) Lin neg /CD45 neg /CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg 
cells were sorted (bulk and single cell) and tested for in vivo 
self-renewal and differentiation as depicted in the schematic 
drawing. CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg -derived spheres (or CFU-
Fs) were injected s.c. into NSG mice, explanted, sorted for 
human cells, analyzed, and retransplanted. Following another 
8 weeks after secondary transplantation, cells were sorted 
again based on the expression of human-specific markers and 
analyzed (A). As shown in (B), bulk and single cell-derived 
spheres from sorted CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg cells clearly 
demonstrated in vivo self-renewal indicated by increased 
numbers of total spheres after primary and secondary trans-
plantations (data are given as mean -SD, n = 3, **P &lt; 0.01, 
and ***P &lt; 0.001). In contrast, numbers of CD271 pos / 
CD140a low/neg -derived CFU-F decreased after primary 
transplantation (Supplementary Fig. S2C). (C, D) Formation 
of ectopic tissues following primary and secondary trans-
plantations of spheres derived from CD271 pos /CD140a low/neg 
cells. Spheres were implanted subcutaneously with HA carrier 
into NSG mice. Representative sections 8 weeks after primary 
and secondary transplantation are shown in (C) and (D), res-
pectively. The photomicrographs in the upper row left dem-
onstrated generation of bone (b), adipocytes (a), and stromal 
tissues (Hematoxylin eosin staining, HE). Dark brown areas 
represent HA/TCP particles. Immunohistochemical staining 
with anti-human vimentin (upper row, right), anti-human 
mitochondria (lower row, left), and anti-mouse CD45 anti-
bodies (lower row, right) indicates human and murine origin of 
the stromal tissues and hematopoietic cells, respectively. Scale 
bars represent 100 mm for HE and anti-CD45 staining, and 
50 mm for anti-vimentin and anti-mitochondria staining. For 
controls, see Supplementary Figure S2D. </p>

<p>‰ </p>

<p>BMSC PHENOTYPE AND STEM CELL FUNCTION </p>

<p>
adherent cultures, enhanced stem cell properties and allowed 
to expand transplantable stromal stem cells, which is certainly 
an important finding for future studies aiming to design stroma 
stem cell replacement and repair strategies. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by funds from the  
and Stem Therapy Program, the Swedish Cancer Founda-
tion, the Swedish Childhood Cancer Foundation, Gunnar 
Nilsson's Cancer Foundation, Gunnel 's Testament, 
ALF (Government Public Health Grant), and the  
County Council's Research Foundation. The authors thank 
Helene Larsson and Anna Jonasson for help with the bone 
marrow samples, the Lund Stem Cell Center FACS facility 
for excellent technical assistance, and Dr.  -
Ferrer (Wellcome Trust-Medical Research Council Cam-
bridge Stem Cell Institute and NHS Blood and Transplant, 
Cambridge, United Kingdom) for critical discussions. </p>

<p>Author Disclosure Statement </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>



<p>Address correspondence to: 
Stefan Scheding, MD 
Division of Molecular Hematology 
Department of Laboratory Medicine 
University of Lund 
BMC B12, Klinikgatan 26 
Lund 22184 
Sweden </p>

<p>E-mail: stefan.scheding@med.lu.se </p>

<p>Received for publication June 10, 2016 
Accepted after revision August 12, 2016 
Prepublished on Liebert Instant Online August 12, 2016 </p>

<p>1658 
GHAZANFARI ET AL. </p>

</text></tei>