<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5440848" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: The primary objective of this study was to analyze the relationships between bone microstructure and 
strength, and male osteoporosis risk factors including age, body mass index, serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D level, 
and testosterone level. A secondary objective was to compare microstructural and strength parameters between 
men with normal, low, and osteoporosis-range areal bone mineral density (aBMD). 
Methods: Seventy-eight healthy male volunteers (mean age 62.4 ± 7.8 years, range 50-84 years) were recruited. 
The participants underwent dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) and high-resolution peripheral quantita-
tive computed tomography (HR-pQCT) of the ultra-distal radius and tibia. From the HR-pQCT images, volumetric 
bone mineral density (BMD) and cortical and trabecular bone microstructure were evaluated, and bone strength 
and cortical load fraction (Ct.LF) were estimated using micro-finite element analysis (μFEA). 
Results: Age was more strongly correlated with bone microstructure than other risk factors. Age had significant 
positive correlations with cortical porosity at both ultra-distal radius and tibia (r = 0.36, p = 0.001, and r = 
0.47, p b 0.001, respectively). At the tibia, age was negatively correlated with cortical BMD, whereas it was pos-
itively correlated with trabecular BMD. In μFEA, age was negatively correlated with Ct.LF, although not with bone 
strength. Compared with men with normal aBMD, men with low or osteoporosis-range aBMD had significantly 
poor trabecular bone microstructure and lower bone strength at the both sites, while there was no significant dif-
ference in cortical bone. 
Conclusions: Cortical bone microstructure was negatively affected by aging, and there was a suggestion that the 
influence of aging may be particularly important at the weight-bearing sites. 
Osteoporosis is a serious health problem not only in women but also 
in men. According to the National Osteoporosis Foundation, about one 
out of two women and one out of four men over 50 years old will 
have an osteoporosis-related fracture in their remaining lifetime 
(National Osteoporosis Foundation, 2002). While the incidence rate is 
lower in men, men with osteoporosis-related fracture have higher mor-
bidity and mortality rates than women (Center et al., 1999; Morin et al., 
2010). As the average age of the population continues to increase, the 
incidence of male osteoporosis is expected to increase significantly. </p>

<p>Although many studies of prevention and treatment have been per-
formed in recent years, the pathogenesis of skeletal fragility in men re-
mains unclear. 
High-resolution peripheral quantitative computed tomography 
(HR-pQCT) is a noninvasive approach which enables in vivo 3D analysis 
of bone microstructure at the appendicular skeleton (Laib et al., 1998; 
Müller et al., 1996); this allows the analysis of geometric, microstructur-
al, densitometric, and mechanical properties of the trabecular and corti-
cal bone architecture in the distal radius and tibia (Burghardt et al., 
2007; Boyd, 2007). In addition, the application of micro finite-element 
(μFE) analysis permits the estimation of bone strength (Boyd, 2008). 
How these microstructural and strength parameters relate to areal 
bone mineral density (BMD) in men is unclear. Further, it is unclear 
how microstructural and strength parameters are affected by male </p>

<p>Bone Reports 5 (2016) 312-319 </p>

<p>⁎ Corresponding author at: 1-7-1 Sakamoto, Nagasaki 852-8501, Japan. 
E-mail address: n.okazaki@nagasaki-u.ac.jp (N. Okazaki). </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bonr.2016.10.005 
2352-1872/© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>Bone Reports </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / b o n r </p>

<p>osteoporosis risk factors including advanced age, low body weight, 
physical inactivity, hypogonadism, heavy smoking, excessive alcohol 
consumption, vitamin D deficiency, and inadequate calcium intake 
(Papaioannou et al., 2008; Ebeling, 2008; Bartl and Frisch, 2009). 
In this study, we used HR-pQCT to determine bone microstructure 
and strength at the distal radius and tibia in 78 older men. (1) We ana-
lyzed the relationships between bone microstructure and strength, and 
male osteoporosis risk factors including age, body mass index (BMI), 
25-hydroxyvitamin D (25(OH)D) level, and testosterone level. In addi-
tion, we estimated 10-year fracture risk using the fracture risk assess-
ment tool (FRAX) (World Health Organization, 1994) and analyzed 
the relationships between bone microstructure and FRAX score. (2) Fi-
nally, we compared bone microstructure and strength measures of 
men with normal, low, and osteoporosis-range areal BMD (aBMD). </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Subjects </p>

<p>The subjects consisted of 78 healthy male volunteers. The recruit-
ment was done using electronic kiosk announcements and flyers posted 
in the San Francisco VA Medical Center (San Francisco, USA), and week-
ly internet advertisements. We excluded men who had been treated 
with either an oral bisphosphonate or teriparatide in the last year or 
for N12 months ever, and those who had diseases or took medications 
known to affect bone metabolism, including current use of testosterone 
therapy, and use of prednisone N5 mg daily or the equivalent glucocor-
ticoid for N10 days in the last 3 months. Other exclusion criteria includ-
ed alcohol use N 3 drinks/day, serum calcium level N 10.2 mg/dL, and 
estimated glomerular filtration rate b 30 mL/min/1.73m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. 
The study protocol was approved by the UCSF Committee on Human 
Research and complied with the Declaration of Helsinki of 1975, revised 
in 2000, and written informed consent was obtained before 
participation. </p>

<p>2.2. Biochemical measurements </p>

<p>Blood samples were collected from all subjects. Serum calcium and 
creatinine levels were measured on the Beckman Coulter (Fullerton, 
CA) DXC800 instrument using a Synchron assay. 25(OH)D was mea-
sured by electrochemiluminescent immunoassay (DiaSorin LIAISON). 
Serum total testosterone was determined using the Access testosterone 
assay (Beckman Coulter). </p>

<p>2.3. Areal bone mineral density and FRAX </p>

<p>Areal BMD (aBMD) was measured by dual-energy X-ray absorpti-
ometry (DXA) (GE Lunar DXA, GE Healthcare Systems, Wauwatosa, 
WI, USA) at the lumbar spine (L1 to L4), non-dominant hip (total hip 
and femoral neck), and radius (distal one-third, ultra distal, and total). 
The 10-year probabilities of major osteoporotic fracture (hip, proxi-
mal humerus, distal radius, or clinical spine fracture) and hip fracture 
were estimated using FRAX (version 3.9). </p>

<p>2.4. HR-pQCT and image-based μFEA of the ultra-distal radius and tibia </p>

<p>All subjects were imaged in a clinical HR-pQCT system (XtremeCT, 
Scanco Medical AG, Brüttisellen, Switzerland) using the manufacturer's 
standard in vivo protocol described in previous patient studies 
(Sornay-Rendu et al., 2007; Kazakia et al., 2008; Melton et al., 2007). 
The subject's forearm and ankle were immobilized in a carbon fiber 
cast that was fixed within the gantry of the scanner. A single dorsal-pal-
mar projection image of the distal radius and tibia was acquired to de-
fine the tomographic scan region. This region spanned 9.02 mm in 
length (110 slices) and was fixed starting proximally at 9.5 and 
22.5 mm from a joint margin reference line for ultra-distal radius </p>

<p>(UDR) and ultra-distal tibia (UDT), respectively. For tomography, 750 
projections were acquired over 180 degrees with a 100-ms integration 
time at each angular position. The 12.6-cm field of view (FOV) was re-
constructed across a 1536 × 1536 matrix using a modified Feldkamp al-
gorithm, yielding 82-μm voxels (Feldkamp et al., 1984). Total scan time 
was 2.8 min with an equivalent dose of approximately 4.2 μSv for each 
site. </p>

<p>2.5. Image analysis </p>

<p>2.5.1. Image quality grading for motion artifacts 
The severity of motion artifacts was graded according to the manu-
facture-suggested image quality grading system. Grading was per-
formed in 3 slices (at the middle and both proximal and distal end 
slices) of the reconstructed images, and the images with grades 4 and 
5 were excluded (Pialat et al., 2012). One case in UDR was excluded 
due to motion artifact. Therefore, 77 cases of UDR and 78 cases of UDT 
were available for analysis. </p>

<p>2.6. Standard analysis </p>

<p>All image analysis was performed using the standard clinical evalu-
ation protocol in <rs id="software-2" type="software">Image Processing Language</rs> (IPL <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">Version 5.08b</rs>, Scanco 
Medical AG), as described in detail in previous publications (Kazakia et 
al., 2008; Tjong et al., 2012). Contours identifying the periosteal perim-
eter of the bone were drawn semiautomatically using a chaperoned it-
erative contouring procedure. All contours were examined manually 
and modified as necessary to delineate the periosteal boundary. Integral 
volumetric BMD was quantified based on the periosteal segmentation. A 
threshold-based process was used to segment cortical and trabecular 
regions for compartment-specific measurements of density and struc-
ture (Laib et al., 1998). Trabecular bone volume fraction (BV/TV) was 
calculated based on trabecular BMD (Tb.BMD) assuming a tissue miner-
al density of 1200 mg HA/cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>. Trabecular number (Tb.N) was calculat-
ed directly by a model-independent sphere fitting technique 
(Hildebrand et al., 1999; Laib et al., 1997). Based on the calculated BV/ 
TV and Tb.N values, trabecular separation (Tb.Sp) and trabecular thick-
ness (Tb.Th) were derived using standard histomorophometric rela-
tions assuming a plate model (Laib and Rüegsegger, 1999). </p>

<p>2.7. Cortical analysis </p>

<p>Cortical bone microstructure parameters at ultra-distal sites were 
assessed using an extended cortical bone analysis that provides direct 
calculation of cortical thickness, as well as measures of porosity (Buie 
et al., 2007; Burghardt et al., 2010). Values for the following structural 
parameters were calculated: cortical BMD (Ct.BMD), cortical thickness 
(Ct.Th), cortical porosity (Ct.Po), and cortical pore diameter (Po.Dm). 
Ct.BMD was calculated as the mean value of all voxels within the cortical 
compartment, following partial volume suppression (2 voxels) at the 
periosteal and endosteal surfaces. Ct.Po was defined as the fraction of 
the segmented pore volume over the sum of the pore and cortical 
bone volume. </p>

<p>2.8. Micro-finite element analysis (μFEA) </p>

<p>Linear μFEA was used to calculate apparent biomechanical proper-
ties at each site. Homogeneous mechanical properties were assumed 
for all bone elements. The binary image data set was converted to a 
mesh of voxels (isotropic) using a conversion technique (Müller and 
Rüegsegger, 1995), and each element was assigned an elastic modulus 
of 6.829 GPa (Boyd, 2008) and a Poisson's ratio of 0.3 (van Rietbergen 
et al., 1996). Cortical and trabecular bone elements were labeled as dif-
ferent materials, with identical material properties to facilitate calcula-
tion of compartmental load distribution. A uniaxial compression test 
in the axial direction (superior-inferior) was performed with an applied </p>

<p> 
N. Okazaki et al. / Bone Reports 5 (2016) 312-319 </p>

<p>uniaxial compressive strain of 1%. An iterative solver (<rs id="software-3" type="software">Scanco FE soft-
ware</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">v.1.15</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Scanco Medcal AG</rs>, Brüttisellen, Switzerland) was used to 
compute reaction forces at the proximal and distal ends of the scan re-
gion for the proscribed displacements. For each model, stiffness (K), ap-
parent modulus (E), and the load fraction for the cortical compartment 
at the distal boundary (Ct.LF dist) and the proximal boundary (Ct.LF 
prox) were calculated. Furthermore, failure load (F) was estimated 
using methods previously described by Mueller et al. (2011). </p>

<p>2.9. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-4" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">version 16.0</rs> (SPSS, 
Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>(1) The relationships between the bone microstructure and μFEA pa-
rameters, and age, BMI, 25(OH)D, and testosterone were ana-
lyzed by Pearson's correlation coefficient test. The relationships 
between the bone microstructure and μFEA parameters, and 
FRAX score (the 10-year probability of a major osteoporotic frac-
ture and of a hip fracture) were analyzed in the same way. The 
level of statistical significance was established at p b 0.05. 
(2) All subjects were classified as having normal, low, or osteoporo-
sis-range BMD according to World Health Organization (WHO) 
categories based on DXA T-score at lumbar spine, total hip and 
femoral neck: normal aBMD if lowest T-score ≥ −1.0; low bone 
mass ("osteopenia") if − 2.5 b T-score b − 1.0; osteoporosis if 
T-score ≤ −2.5 (World Health Organization, 1994). We com-
pared the bone microstructure and μFEA parameters between 
the normal group and osteopenic or osteoporotic groups. A 
Bonferroni correction was used to account for multiple compari-
sons, therefore the level of statistical significance was set at 
p b 0.025. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>The mean age of 78 subjects was 62.4 ± 7.8 years (range 50-
84 years). Forty-four men (56%) were white, 18 (23%) were African 
American, 11 (14%) were Asian, 4 (5%) were Hispanic, and 1 (1%) was 
American Indian. The mean BMI was 27.1 ± 3.2 kg/m 
2 , testosterone </p>

<p>was 423.2 ± 165.1 ng/dL, and 25(OH)D level was 23.2 ± 9.6 ng/mL. Tra-
becular and cortical bone microstructure parameters and μFEA parame-
ters at UDR and UDT are displayed in Table 1, with representative 3D 
images of cortical bone in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>3.1. The relationships between bone microstructure parameters and risk 
factors of male osteoporosis. </p>

<p>BMI was significantly correlated with total hip, femoral neck, total 
radius, and 1/3 radius T-scores by DXA, such that those with higher 
BMI had higher DXA T-scores (Table 2). By HR-pQCT, at the UDR, age 
had a significant positive correlation with Ct.Po (r = 0.36, p = 0.001, 
Table 2, Fig. 2), such older participants had greater cortical porosity. At 
the UDT, age was positively correlated with Ct.Po (r = 0.47, p b 0.001, 
Table 2, Fig. 2) and negatively correlated with Ct.BMD (r = − 0.40, 
p b 0.001), whereas it was positively correlated with Tb·BMD (r = 
0.30, p = 0.008). BMI was correlated with Tb.N, Tb.Sp, and Ct.Th at 
UDT, such that those with higher BMI had higher Tb.N, lower Tb.Sp, 
and higher Ct.Th. Cortical porosity was increased significantly with 
aging, particularly at the UDT. In addition, age was negatively correlated 
with Ct.LF-prox and Ct.LF-dist (r = − 0.48, p b 0.001 and r = − 0.36, 
p = 0.001, respectively). Age was not correlated with stiffness, apparent 
modulus, or failure load. 
At the UDR, those with lower Tb.BMD, Ct.BMD, and Ct.Th, and higher 
Ct.Po had higher FRAX scores for major osteoporotic fracture; those 
with lower Tb.BMD and Tb.N, and higher Tb.Sp and Ct.Po had higher 
FRAX scores for hip fracture. On the other hand, at the UDT, those 
with lower Ct.BMD and Ct.Th had higher FRAX score for major osteopo-
rotic fracture and hip fracture; those with lower Tb.BMD had also higher 
FRAX score for hip fracture. At both the UDR and UDT, those with lower 
stiffness, apparent modulus, and failure load had higher FRAX score for 
major osteoprotic fracture and hip fracture, such that those with lower 
estimated bone strength had higher FRAX scores. 
When bone microstructure and μFEA parameters were examined 
with DXA T-scores, DXA T-scores were significantly correlated with tra-
becular bone parameters (Tb.N, Tb.Sp, and Tb.BMD) and Ct.Th at the 
spine, proximal femur, and radius (Table 3). In addition, T-score at the 
total and ultradistal radius had a significant correlation with Tb.Th and 
Ct.BMD at the UDR, and with Ct.BMD and Po.Dm at the UDT. In contrast, 
there was no significant relationship between DXA T-score and Ct.Po at 
either anatomic site. In μFEA parameters, DXA T-score of all sites had 
significant correlation with stiffness, apparent modulus, and failure 
load, such that those with higher T-scores had greater estimated bone 
strength. </p>

<p>3.2. Comparison of men with normal, low, and osteoporosis-range aBMD. </p>

<p>Of the 78 men studied, 40 had normal aBMD on DXA, 32 had low 
bone mass on DXA, and 6 had osteoporosis-range aBMD (Table 4). 
There was no significant difference in age or BMI between the three 
groups. 
At the UDR, men with low bone mass and osteoporotic men had sig-
nificantly lower Tb.N, higher Tb.Sp, and lower stiffness and failure load 
than normal men. At the UDT, men with low bone mass and osteoporot-
ic men had lower Tb.N and Tb.BMD, higher Tb.Sp, and lower stiffness 
and failure load. In addition, men with low bone mass had lower mod-
ulus. At both UDR and UDT, there was no significant difference in corti-
cal bone microstructure parameters (Ct.Th, Ct.Po, Po.Dm, and Ct.BMD). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>In the present study, we examined not only the relationships be-
tween bone microstructure, aBMD by DXA, FRAX scores, and risk factors 
for male osteoporosis in healthy men over 50 years old, but also micro-
structural differences between men with normal, low, and osteoporo-
sis-range aBMD. 
Aging is recognized as the most important risk factor for male oste-
oporosis (Bartl and Frisch, 2009). We observed that age had a correla-
tion with microstructure; cortical porosity and cortical bone mineral 
density were affected by age, especially at the tibia, a weight-bearing 
site (Table 2). Our findings were similar to those of Nicks et al. (2012), </p>

<p>Table 1 
Bone microstructure and μFEA parameters of the ultra distal radius and the ultra distal 
tibia. </p>

<p>Parameter 
Radius (n = 77) 
Tibia (n = 78) </p>

<p>Mean SD 
Min 
Max 
Mean SD 
Min 
Max </p>

<p>Tb.Th (μm) 
75 
11 
53 
101 
79 
12 
52 
108 
Tb.N (/mm) 
2.00 
0.28 1.36 2.46 
1.94 
0.31 1.21 
2.66 
Tb.Sp (μm) 
434 
76 
320 
651 
448 
88 
294 
725 
Tb.BMD (mg/cm 
3 ) 
181 
37 
104 
258 
184 
35 
109 
263 
Ct.Th (mm) 
0.97 
0.17 0.61 1.53 
1.40 
0.26 0.89 
2.21 
Ct.Po (%) 
2.9 
1.3 
1.1 
8.2 
7.0 
2.6 
1.9 
16.7 
Po.Dm (μm) 
172 
21 
143 
240 
191 
23 
152 
307 
Ct.BMD (mg/cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) 
924 
45 
735 
1017 881 
55 
735 
1001 
Stiffness, K (kN/mm) 68.6 
13.1 38.6 105.3 172.8 30.2 103.7 281.4 
Modulus, E (N/m 
2 ) 
1290 285 696 
1985 1614 304 
861 
2186 
Failure load, F (N) 
4057 726 2350 6176 9982 1697 6275 16112 
Ct.LF-dist (%) 
41.2 
7.4 
28.7 67.1 
44.1 
7.3 
28.0 
62.5 
Ct.LF-prox (%) 
79.1 
5.8 
63.3 90.9 
66.6 
6.9 
50.0 
84.9 </p>

<p> 
N. Okazaki et al. / Bone Reports 5 (2016) 312-319 </p>

<p>who compared the bone microstructure of the distal radius and tibia in 
men under vs. over the age of 50 using HR-pQCT; they reported that cor-
tical porosity was significantly higher in older men, while there was not </p>

<p>a significant difference between younger and older men in trabecular 
bone microstructure. In contrast, when Hansen et al. (2013) reported 
age-related change of bone microstructure at the radius and tibia in </p>

<p>Fig. 1. 3D visualization of cortical bone at the ultra-distal radius (A and B) and tibia (C and D). Intracortical porosity was increase in elderly subjects (B and D). </p>

<p>Table 2 
Correlation between DXA T-score and bone microstructure, and age, BMI, serum testosterone, 25(OH)D levels, and FRAX score. </p>

<p>Age 
BMI 
Testosterone 
25(OH)D 
FRAX score </p>

<p>Major osteoporotic fracture 
Hip fracture </p>

<p>DXA 
L1-L4 
0.08 
0.13 
0.12 
0.03 
-
-
Total Hip 
0.07 
0.36 ** 
0.09 
−0.02 
-
-
Femoral Neck 
−0.03 
0.30 ** 
0.09 
−0.07 
-
-
Total Radius 
−0.09 
0.28 * 
0.01 
−0.12 
-
-
1/3 Radius 
−0.11 
0.25 * 
0.03 
−0.10 
-
-
UDR T-Score 
0.00 
0.18 
0.00 
−0.09 
-
-</p>

<p>Radius 
Tb.Th 
0.04 
−0.09 
−0.02 
0.07 
−0.15 
−0.16 
Tb.N 
0.12 
0.19 
0.11 
−0.11 
−0.20 
−0.27 * 
Tb.Sp 
−0.17 
−0.17 
−0.09 
0.08 
0.20 
0.28 * 
Tb.BMD 
0.11 
0.08 
0.05 
−0.01 
−0.22 * 
−0.28 * 
Ct.Th 
−0.02 
−0.04 
0.15 
−0.04 
−0.37 ** 
−0.22 
Ct.Po 
0.36 ** 
0.04 
−0.09 
0.04 
0.30 ** 
0.27 * 
Po.Dm 
0.26 * 
−0.04 
0.06 
0.18 
0.20 
0.22 
Ct.BMD 
−0.18 
−0.09 
0.16 
0.05 
−0.27 * 
−0.17 
Stiffness, K 
0.04 
0.04 
0.13 
−0.01 
−0.50 ** 
−0.42 ** 
Modulus, E 
0.04 
−0.03 
0.11 
0.07 
−0.34 ** 
−0.27 * 
Failure load, F 
0.05 
0.06 
0.12 
−0.03 
−0.50 ** 
−0.44 ** 
Ct.LF-dis 
−0.28 * 
0.03 
0.10 
−0.09 
−0.17 
−0.06 
Ct.LF-prox 
−0.25 * 
−0.01 
0.00 
−0.10 
0.06 
0.20 </p>

<p>Tibia 
Tb.Th 
0.15 
−0.08 
−0.04 
0.20 
−0.04 
−0.14 
Tb.N 
0.24 * 
0.33 ** 
0.00 
−0.12 
−0.20 
−0.18 
Tb.Sp 
−0.25 * 
−0.32 ** 
−0.01 
0.13 
0.18 
0.19 
Tb.BMD 
0.30 ** 
0.22 
−0.02 
0.06 
−0.19 
−0.25 * 
Ct.Th 
−0.11 
0.31 ** 
−0.07 
−0.17 
−0.46 ** 
−0.37 ** 
Ct.Po 
0.47 ** 
0.02 
−0.03 
0.29 * 
0.22 
0.20 
Po.Dm 
0.20 
−0.15 
0.06 
0.29 * 
0.18 
0.14 
Ct.BMD 
−0.40 ** 
0.04 
0.07 
−0.22 * 
−0.34 ** 
−0.29 ** 
Stiffness, K 
0.09 
0.22 * 
0.02 
−0.11 
−0.48 ** 
−0.46 ** 
Modulus, E 
0.02 
0.15 
−0.05 
−0.03 
−0.35 ** 
−0.35 ** 
Failure load, F 
0.10 
0.22 * 
0.02 
−0.11 
−0.47 ** 
−0.45 ** 
Ct.LF-dist 
−0.48 ** 
0.19 
0.03 
−0.30 ** 
−0.24 * 
−0.08 
Ct.LF-prox 
−0.36 ** 
0.16 
−0.02 
−0.22 
−0.17 
−0.09 </p>

<p>Pearson's correlation coefficient *p b 0.05, **p b 0.01. </p>

<p> 
N. Okazaki et al. / Bone Reports 5 (2016) 312-319 </p>

<p>men aged 20 to 80 years using HR-pQCT, they showed that trabecular 
bone as well as cortical bone were weakened with aging. In our study, 
tibial cortical bone microstructure was weakened and load fraction for 
the cortical compartment was decreasing with aging. Conversely, tra-
becular bone microstructure became stronger with aging, albeit with a 
weak correlation. Furthermore, there was no relationship between 
bone strength and age. Therefore, these findings raise the possibility 
that while cortical bone is weakened with aging, bone strength is </p>

<p>maintained with compensatory strengthening of trabecular bone mi-
crostructure. However, our observations were limited to a cohort of 
men ages 50-84 years. 
Aging presumably affects the bones in a number of ways, including 
telomere shortening (Bekaert et al., 2005), reduced secretion of the 
sex steroids such as testosterone or estrogen (Khosla et al., 1998), and 
a decrease in muscle mass (Szulc et al., 2012). We did not observe a sig-
nificant relationship between serum testosterone levels and bone </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Correlation between Ct.Po and age. Ct.Po changed significantly with aging, particularly at the tibia. </p>

<p>Table 3 
Correlation between bone microstructure and μFEA parameters, and DXA T-score. </p>

<p>L-spine 
Hip 
Radius </p>

<p>L1-L4 
Total hip 
Neck 
Total radius 
1/3 Radius 
UDR </p>

<p>Radius 
Tb.Th 
0.12 
0.10 
0.08 
0.44 ** 
0.21 
0.53 ** 
Tb.N 
0.33 ** 
0.52 ** 
0.44 ** 
0.33 ** 
0.17 
0.46 ** 
Tb.Sp 
−0.35 ** 
−0.54 ** 
−0.45 ** 
−0.37 ** 
−0.19 
−0.51 ** 
Tb.BMD 
0.30 ** 
0.43 ** 
0.35 ** 
0.53 ** 
0.26 * 
0.68 ** 
Ct.Th 
0.34 ** 
0.27 * 
0.31 ** 
0.54 ** 
0.34 ** 
0.60 ** 
Ct.Po 
0.01 
−0.07 
−0.06 
−0.11 
−0.07 
−0.16 
Po.Dm 
−0.09 
−0.05 
−0.01 
−0.17 
−0.08 
−0.16 
Ct.BMD 
0.13 
0.12 
0.13 
0.29 ** 
0.18 
0.38 ** 
Stiffness, K 
0.57 ** 
0.57 ** 
0.61 ** 
0.79 ** 
0.63 ** 
0.87 ** 
Modulus, E 
0.37 ** 
0.32 ** 
0.30 ** 
0.58 ** 
0.33 ** 
0.71 ** 
Failure load, F 
0.57 ** 
0.59 ** 
0.63 ** 
0.79 ** 
0.64 ** 
0.86 ** 
Ct.LF-dis 
0.04 
−0.04 
0.00 
0.04 
0.00 
0.02 
Ct.LF-prox 
−0.27 * 
−0.33 ** 
−0.29 * 
−0.23 * 
−0.22 
−0.28 * </p>

<p>Tibia 
Tb.Th 
0.12 
0.20 
0.11 
0.16 
0.09 
0.24 * 
Tb.N 
0.39 ** 
0.60 ** 
0.54 ** 
0.43 ** 
0.32 ** 
0.49 ** 
Tb.Sp 
−0.40 ** 
−0.60 ** 
−0.52 ** 
−0.42 ** 
−0.31 ** 
−0.50 ** 
Tb.BMD 
0.43 ** 
0.64 ** 
0.53 ** 
0.48 ** 
0.33 ** 
0.59 ** 
Ct.Th 
0.34 ** 
0.55 ** 
0.53 ** 
0.62 ** 
0.49 ** 
0.58 ** 
Ct.Po 
−0.04 
−0.02 
−0.02 
−0.16 
−0.13 
−0.14 
Po.Dm 
−0.14 
−0.15 
−0.13 
−0.29 ** 
−0.18 
−0.27 * 
Ct.BMD 
0.18 
0.24 * 
0.23 * 
0.37 ** 
0.30 ** 
0.35 ** 
Stiffness, K 
0.61 ** 
0.71 ** 
0.74 ** 
0.72 ** 
0.63 ** 
0.74 ** 
Modulus, E 
0.35 ** 
0.50 ** 
0.44 ** 
0.55 ** 
0.41 ** 
0.60 ** 
Failure load, F 
0.60 ** 
0.71 ** 
0.74 ** 
0.71 ** 
0.62 ** 
0.73 ** 
Ct.LF-dist 
−0.12 
−0.06 
−0.03 
0.05 
0.02 
−0.02 
Ct.LF-prox 
−0.19 
−0.07 
−0.08 
0.03 
0.02 
−0.05 </p>

<p>Pearson's correlation coefficient *p b 0.05, **p b 0.01. </p>

<p> 
N. Okazaki et al. / Bone Reports 5 (2016) 312-319 </p>

<p>microstructure, but it has been shown previously that the age-related 
decline of estrogen has a stronger effect on the bone compared to tes-
tosterone (Khosla et al., 2001). 
Looker and Mussolino (2008) reported that lower serum vitamin D 
levels significantly increase the risk of hip fracture in men and women 
over 65 years old. In that study of people over the age of 65, the preva-
lence of vitamin D deficiency is high; 26% of them had serum 25(OH)D 
level under 20 ng/mL (Orwoll et al., 2009). In our study, 30% of all cases 
had serum vitamin D deficiency (data not shown). We also detected 
25(OH)D level had an unexpected modest positive association with cor-
tical porosity, and a negative association with Ct.BMD at the tibia. We 
suspect that these associations may have been confounded by age, as 
age was positively associated with both 25(OH)D level (r = 0.26, p = 
0.02, data not shown) and cortical porosity, and negatively associated 
with Ct.BMD. 
Although BMI was weakly correlated with BMD of the hip and radi-
us, it was not correlated with BMD at the lumbar spine (Table 2). Addi-
tionally, in microstructure parameters, BMI was weakly correlated with 
Tb.N, Tb.Sp and Ct.Th in UDT (Table 2). It is reported that BMI is positive-
ly associated with BMD of femoral neck in men and women (Lloyd et al., 
2014). Furthermore, low BMI is recognized as a risk factor for hip frac-
ture being independent of BMD, while low BMI is not an independent 
risk factor for the fracture of the other sites (De Laet et al., 2005). In 
our study, we recognized the relationships between BMI and bone mi-
crostructure at the tibia but not at the radius; BMI might have more in-
fluence on the bone microstructure at the weight-bearing site than at 
the non weight-bearing site. 
There has been no published report showing the relationship be-
tween the FRAX score and bone microstructure. The 10-year probability 
of a major osteoporotic or hip fracture had significant relationships with 
cortical parameter, especially at the UDT. Similarly, FRAX score had </p>

<p>significant relationships with bone strength. Future research should de-
termine whether cortical bone microstructure and strength may actual-
ly improve the predictive ability of the FRAX model or be an alternate 
tool for fracture risk prediction. 
Cortical porosity is attributed to bone resorption on the endocortical 
surface and on the surface of Haversian and Volkman canals (Keshawarz 
and Recker, 1984; Zebaze et al., 2010). As the cortical porosity pro-
gresses, bone mechanical strength is lowered (Schaffler and Burr, 
1988). Nishiyama et al. (2010) compared the microstructure differences 
between postmenopausal women with normal, low, or osteoporosis-
range aBMD; it was shown that women with both low bone mass and 
osteoporosis had lower Ct.Th and greater Ct.Po. In the present study, 
we compared men over 50 years old with normal, low, or osteoporo-
sis-range aBMD. Men with osteoporosis and low bone mass had trabec-
ular bone fragility and lower bone strength in both distal radius and 
tibia; however, there were no significant differences in cortical bone mi-
crostructure at the both sites (Table 4). In addition, DXA T-score had no 
correlation with Ct.Po (Table 3); therefore, DXA is likely not sensitive 
enough to capture differences in cortical porosity in elderly men. We 
observed a relatively strong relationship between DXA aBMD and tra-
becular bone parameters. However, the FRAX score had a stronger rela-
tionship with cortical bone parameters compared to trabecular bone 
parameters, despite the fact that FRAX was calculated from aBMD. A co-
hort study by Bala et al. (2014) found Ct.Po at the ultra-distal radius was 
an independent discriminator of forearm fracture in osteopenic, but not 
osteoporotic women. Therefore, Ct.Po measured by HR-pQCT could pro-
vide unique information relevant to fracture discrimination, while tra-
becular bone microstructure measures may not add significant power 
beyond aBMD. 
This study has several limitations. First, our sample size is small, par-
ticularly in the category of men with osteoporosis-range bone mass on </p>

<p>Table 4 
Mean values ± SD and differences between normal, osteopenia and, osteoporosis. </p>

<p>Radius 
Normal (1) 
(n = 39) </p>

<p>Osteopenia (2) 
(n = 32) </p>

<p>Osteoporosis (3) 
(n = 6) </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>1 vs 2 
1 vs 3 </p>

<p>Age (years) 
63.1 ± 7.1 
62.0 ± 8.3 
62.0 ± 9.1 
NS 
NS 
BMI 
27.5 ± 3.1 
26.9 ± 3.5 
25.7 ± 2.3 
NS 
NS 
Tb.Th (μm) 
75.0 ± 9.6 
74.3 ± 11.9 
76.0 ± 15.5 
NS 
NS 
Tb.N (/mm) 
2.10 ± 0.22 
1.94 ± 0.30 
1.77 ± 0.21 
* 
* 
Tb.Sp (μm) 
407 ± 54 
454 ± 86 
498 ± 75 
* 
* 
Tb.BMD (mg/cm 
3 ) 
191± 31 
173 ± 40 
158 ± 39 
NS 
NS 
Ct.Th (mm) 
1.00 ± 0.16 
0.95 ± 0.18 
0.88 ± 0.18 
NS 
NS 
Ct.Po (%) 
2.9 ± 1.1 
2.8 ± 1.4 
3.4 ± 1.7 
NS 
NS 
Po.Dm (μm) 
172 ± 23 
170 ± 17 
183 ± 30 
NS 
NS 
Ct.BMD (mg/cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) 
928 ± 39 
923 ± 51 
910 ± 53 
NS 
NS 
Stiffness, K (kN/mm) 
74.4 ± 12.3 
64.5 ± 10.6 
53.3 ± 11.2 
** 
** 
Modulus, E (N/m 
2 ) 
1369 ± 248 
1226 ± 284 
1118 ± 390 
NS 
NS 
Failure load, F (N) 
4380 ± 679 
3829 ± 579 
3165 ± 568 
** 
** 
Ct.LF-dis (%) 
40.8 ± 7.0 
42.1 ± 7.8 
38.5 ± 8.3 
NS 
NS 
Ct.LF-prox (%) 
77.6 ± 5.1 
80.6 ± 6.0 
80.8 ± 7.0 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>Tibia 
Normal (1) 
(n = 40) </p>

<p>Osteopenia (2) 
(n = 32) </p>

<p>Osteoporosis (3) 
(n = 6) </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>1 vs 2 
1 vs 3 </p>

<p>Age (years) 
62.9 ± 7.3 
62.0 ± 8.3 
62.0 ± 9.1 
NS 
NS 
BMI 
27.4 ± 3.1 
26.9 ± 3.5 
25.7 ± 2.3 
NS 
NS 
Tb.Th (μm) 
81.0 ± 10.5 
77.8 ± 13.6 
77.3 ± 13.3 
NS 
NS 
Tb.N (/mm) 
2.07 ± 0.30 
1.85 ± 0.26 
1.62 ± 0.08 
** 
** 
Tb.Sp (μm) 
413 ± 79 
476 ± 84 
540 ± 38 
** 
** 
Tb.BMD (mg/cm 
3 ) 
200 ± 31 
171 ± 32 
151 ± 29 
** 
** 
Ct.Th (mm) 
1.47 ± 0.26 
1.34 ± 0.23 
1.27 ± 0.37 
NS 
NS 
Ct.Po (%) 
6.8 ± 2.5 
7.2 ± 2.2 
7.6 ± 4.6 
NS 
NS 
Po.Dm (μm) 
187 ± 18 
193 ± 20 
206 ± 52 
NS 
NS 
Ct.BMD (mg/cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) 
891 ± 53 
869 ± 54 
867 ± 71 
NS 
NS 
Stiffness, K (kN/mm) 
188.3 ± 28.1 
160.9 ± 21.3 
132.9 ± 19.8 
** 
** 
Modulus, E (N/m 
2 ) 
1709 ± 254 
1524 ± 298 
1458 ± 469 
* 
NS 
Failure load, F (N) 
10853 ± 1585 
9324 ± 1176 
7684 ± 1000 
** 
** 
Ct.LF-dist (%) 
43.3 ± 7.1 
44.3 ± 7.4 
48.1 ± 8.3 
NS 
NS 
Ct.LF-prox (%) 
65.4 ± 6.4 
67.5 ± 7.1 
69.7 ± 9.3 
NS 
NS </p>

<p>Boneferroni correction, *p b 0.025, **p b 0.005, NS = not significant. </p>

<p> 
N. Okazaki et al. / Bone Reports 5 (2016) 312-319 </p>

<p>DXA. Second, this was cross-sectional study with men over 50 years of 
age, which precluded comparisons with a cohort of women, as well as 
age related changes in bone microstructure. Third, the voxel size of 
82 μm is greater than the diameter of some cortical pores and therefore 
the porosity measures do not reflect small pores; the approach was also 
limited by the established accuracy and reproducibility of porosity mea-
sures using HR-pQCT (Tjong et al., 2012; Burghardt et al., 2010; 
Nishiyama et al., 2010). However macroscopic porosity is well correlat-
ed to integral porosity across all scales (Tjong et al., 2012). 
In conclusion, age had a stronger correlation with bone microstruc-
ture than other risk factors for male osteoporosis. Cortical bone micro-
structure was negatively affected by aging, and there was a suggestion 
that the influence of aging may be particularly important at the 
weight-bearing sites. Bone strength might be maintained during aging 
by means of the compensatory strengthening of trabecular bone. 
When we compared the men with normal, low, and osteoporosis-
range aBMD, men with osteoporosis and low bone mass had significant-
ly weak trabecular bone microstructure and bone strength at both the 
distal radius and tibia, but no significant differences in cortical bone pa-
rameters at both sites. Tb.BMD is not really independent of aBMD and 
therefore will not likely identify those in these groups that are at high 
risk of fracture. On the other hand, Ct.Po may provide unique discrimi-
natory power in addition to aBMD, based on its poor correlation to 
aBMD and strong correlation with aging. </p>

<p>Authors' roles </p>

<p>Study design: SM, ALS and AJB. Data collection: NO, AB and KC. Data 
analysis: NO, AJB and KC. Data interpretation: NO, AJB, KC, ALS and SM. 
Drafting manuscript: NO. Revising manuscript content: AJB, KC, ALS and 
SM. Approving final version of manuscript: NO, AJB, KC, ALS and SM. AJB 
and KC take responsibility for the integrity of the data analysis. </p>

<p>Disclosures </p>

<p>Conflict of interest: The authors declare that they have no conflict of 
interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The study was funded by Merck Pharmaceuticals. Additional support 
was provided by NIH/NIAMS R01 AR060700 to AJB, and the US Depart-
ment of Veterans Affairs, VHA, CSR&amp;D Service (CDA-2 5 IK2 CX000549 ), 
to ALS, SFVAMC. </p>



<p> 
N. Okazaki et al. / Bone Reports 5 (2016) 312-319 </p>



<p> 
N. Okazaki et al. / Bone Reports 5 (2016) 312-319 </p>

</text></tei>