<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5005113" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT Wood processing workers are exposed to wood-associated microbiological contaminants, 
including fungi. Our aim was to study the potential association between sputum fungus and adverse 
respiratory effects in such workers. 
In a group of sawmill workers, we administered a respiratory questionnaire, performed lung function 
testing and quantified the proportions of leukocytes in spontaneously expectorated sputum samples. We 
identified fungal species by DNA sequencing. 
Of 54 sawmill workers, 19 yielded fungal positive sputum samples (mean age 42.5±10.4 years) and 35 
were negative for fungus (mean age 36.9±5.2 years). The fungus was identified as Candida sp. in all 
samples. Those with fungal-positive sputum, compared to others, reported more cough (26% versus 63%) 
and haemoptysis (6% versus 37%) (both p&lt;0.05), manifested reduced forced midexpiratory flow rates 
(FEF25-75%) (82.3±4.5 versus 69.2±9.9% predicted, p&lt;0.001), and had higher sputum eosinophil counts 
(median 9.25 versus 3.25%, p&lt;0.01). Reduction of FEF25-75% was associated both with fungus detection in 
sputum (−12.7%, 95% CI−8.5-−16.9%) and sputum eosinophils (−2.1% per 1% increase in eosinophils, 
95% CI −1.5-−2.8%) (both p&lt;0.001). 
In sawmill workers, Candida sp. detectable in sputum was associated with respiratory symptoms, 
sputum eosinophilia and reduced FEF25-75%. </p>

<p>@ERSpublications 
Candida sp. contamination in the airways is associated with adverse respiratory effects in 
sawmill workers http://ow.ly/RHAqe </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Lumber and wood processing and manufacturing is a common industry worldwide. Wood dust, a major 
byproduct of such production, has been associated with a range of adverse respiratory effects among those 
occupationally exposed in milling, carpentry, cabinet making and a number of other related trades. 
Adverse effects include wood dust exposure-related respiratory tract symptoms, airflow limitation and 
bronchial hyperresponsiveness [1-10]. </p>

<p>Aside from the adverse effects of the wood itself, microbial contamination has also been shown to be a 
major exposure factor in this industry, particularly in the initial phases of lumber milling. Exposures of 
concern include both bacteria and fungi, with airborne endotoxin presumed to be a major mediator of at 
least some wood dust-associated adverse effects [6, 11-13]. Multiple investigators have quantified the load 
of airborne microorganisms in the working environment of wood processing [6, 14-21]. </p>

<p>Although bacteria and bacterially derived endotoxins have been a dominant hygiene concern in this 
industry, a number of investigators have shown that fungal contamination also contributes to respiratory 
symptoms, lung function impairment and airway hyperresponsiveness among wood processing workers [1, 
13, 18, 20-23]. Despite the potentially important role of fungal contamination of wood dust, however, the 
presence of fungal spores in the sputum of exposed wood workers has not been assessed, either as a 
measure of exposure or as a potential correlate of adverse effects of this working environment. </p>

<p>We became interested in possible fungal exposure in wood mill workers when a preliminary study of sputum 
cell viability from one such facility demonstrated the presence, in multiple samples, of what appeared to be 
yeast. We hypothesised that the presence of fungus in sputum samples would serve as a biomarker of exposure 
to sawmill dust potentially associated with symptoms and lung function impairment. To test this hypothesis, 
we studied a group of wood industry workers heavily exposed to dust among whom we systematically 
evaluated respiratory health and characterised the fungal species, if any, in their sputum samples. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study design and study population 
The wood processing facilities studied were all primary mills where logs were stripped, trimmed and sawn 
into lumber boards primarily used for furniture making. Prior to milling, the logs are stored in an outdoor 
holding area that is subject to ambient environmental conditions, including drenching precipitation during 
the rainy season. The major species processed were predominantly hardwoods such as margosa 
(Azadirachta indica), mango (Mangifera indica), sal (Shorea robusta), teak (Tectona grandis) and 
mahogany (Toona ciliata). The four wood mills were chosen as a convenience sample based on their 
proximity to the laboratory at which the sputum the samples were analysed. </p>

<p>We carried out this study in Kalyani ( population ∼450 000) in West Bengal, India. We identified four small 
wood working mills employing, in total, 79 workers. We attempted to recruit the entire workforce. The 
final study group included those who consented to participation, completed the study question, performed 
adequate spirometry and were able to produce an adequate sample of expectorated sputum for analysis. </p>

<p>Although airborne dust sampling was not carried out to quantify exposure levels, grossly, the work process 
was extremely dusty, generating visible piles of settled saw dust several feet high near the production lines. 
There were no specific dust suction collection systems in place at any of the sites and nothing beyond 
makeshift personal respiratory protection (e.g. mouth-covering scarves) was employed. The study was 
carried out over a 2-3-week period in the dry season. Lung function studies and sputum collections were 
carried out on site at each mill. Routine work operations continued during study times. The study was 
approved by the Departmental Research Committee of the Dept of Physiology, University of Kalyani, and 
we obtained signed informed consent from the participants before participation. </p>

<p>Respiratory questionnaire 
We used an English-Bengali back-translated version of European Community Respiratory Health Survey 
(ECRHS-II) questionnaire to inquire about respiratory health, occupational exposure and lifestyle factors 
of the participants. Although the translated version of this questionnaire has not been validated by formal 
assessment, we have employed this questionnaire in our previous studies [24-26]. Subjective respiratory 
complaints in the previous 12 months included: 1) acute or chronic wheezing or whistling of the chest; 
2) production of phlegm; 3) acute or chronic cough; 4) breathing trouble; 5) appearance of blood in 
sputum (haemoptysis); and 6) skin symptoms such as dryness, rash or irritation. </p>

<p>Lung function testing 
We measured lung function using a computerised spirometer (Maestros Mediline Systems Limited, 
Mumbai, India) according to the American Thoracic Society (ATS)/European Respiratory Society (ERS) </p>

<p>ERJ Open Res 2015; 1: 00023-2015 | DOI: 10.1183/23120541.00023-2015 </p>

<p>
OCCUPATIONAL LUNG DISEASE | A. ADHIKARI ET AL. </p>

<p>guidelines for spirometry [27]. We calibrated the spirometer prior each testing day with a 3-L 
fixed-volume calibration syringe. We calculated the predicted values of lung function variables using 
prediction equations for the Indian population [28]. The quality of each spirogram was evaluated for 
acceptability and repeatability in accordance with the ATS/ERS criteria [27]. To achieve accurate and 
replicable spirograms, each participant completed between three and eight spirometry manoeuvres. 
Spirometry was performed at a distance sufficiently removed from the mills to avoid any marked 
interference from workplace contaminants. </p>

<p>Assessment of sputum 
We collected spontaneously expectorated sputum samples by asking each participant to expectorate into a 
sterile polypropylene tube (Tarsons Ltd, Kolkata, India). Sputum samples were processed using the 
method of POPOV et al. [29] as modified and previously reported in detail elsewhere [30]. In brief, the 
sputum samples were poured into a Petri dish and all visible white cloudlets with no squamous cell 
contamination were carefully picked out and processed with freshly prepared 0.1% dithiothreitol (DTT) 
(Sisco Research Laboratories, Mumbai, India). The suspension was filtered through a 25-μm nylon filter, 
as described previously [30], to remove all squamous or epithelial cell contamination. Cell viability was 
assessed by trypan blue staining. Cytospin slides were prepared and Leishman stained according to the 
method of SARAIVA-ROMANHOLO et al. [31]. We performed differential cell counts of the sputum samples 
after achieving ⩾80% intact nonsquamous cells, irrespective of the degree of cell viability or squamous cell 
contamination during viability determination. </p>

<p>Fungal characterisation 
In order to characterise fungal contamination of the expectorated sputum, an aliquot of each crude 
sputum sample (without adding DTT) was placed in a clean polypropylene tube and mixed with PBS 
( pH 7.4). The ratio of PBS to sputum was kept at 1:1. A 100-µL aliquot of thoroughly mixed sputum 
sample was incubated in potato dextrose agar medium for 24 h at 37°C. All the fungal colonies on the 
agar plates were similar in morphology; one of the colonies was selected from the plate and grown in 
potato dextrose liquid broth under the same incubation conditions as noted above. We also collected saliva 
as a control from each of the workers to test for the presence of fungus in the oral cavity that might 
account for the sputum finding. We collected the saliva samples from the cheek, gum and sublingual areas 
using a sterile cotton swab (Himedia, Mumbai, India) prior to sputum expectoration. We directly 
examined sputum samples for the presence of fungus and cultured these samples using the same methods 
as for sputum. </p>

<p>To confirm whether the colonies represented homogenous species, we sequenced additional colonies from 
the agar plates randomly. For identification of the isolated culture, sequencing of the conserved genomic 
region was carried out using standard primer pair for the amplification (sequencing service was provided 
by Amnion Biosciences Pvt Ltd, Bengaluru, India). The amplicon used for the identification was 18S 
ribosomal RNA gene, partial sequence; internal transcribed spacer 1 and 5.8S ribosomal RNA gene, 
complete sequence; and internal transcribed spacer 2, partial sequence. The 488-base pair amplicon 
sequence was then searched for the similarity in US National Center for Biotechnology Information 
(NCBI) nucleotide collection database using the Nucleotide Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (<rs type="software">BLASTN</rs>) 
using standard search parameters [32]. A phylogenetic tree was constructed later using first 10 hits from 
NCBI <rs type="software">BLASTN</rs> search results and the query sequence using Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis 
version 4.1 [33]. The evolutionary history was inferred using the neighbour-joining method. The bootstrap 
consensus tree inferred from 500 replicates was taken to represent the evolutionary history of the taxa 
analysed. Branches corresponding to partitions reproduced in &lt;50% bootstrap replicates were collapsed. 
The percentage of replicate trees in which the associated taxa clustered together in the bootstrap test (500 
replicates) is shown next to the branches. The tree was drawn to scale, with branch lengths in the same 
units as those of the evolutionary distances used to infer the phylogenetic tree. The evolutionary distances 
were computed using the Maximum Composite Likelihood method and are in the units of the number of 
base substitutions per site. All positions containing gaps and missing data were eliminated from the 
dataset (Complete Deletion option). There were a total of 365 positions in the final dataset. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses 
Participants were dichotomised into those who had or did not have detectable fungus in their sputum. We 
used the Chi-squared or Fisher's exact test to compare categorical variables and the t-test or Wilcoxon 
rank sum test to compare continuous variables (the latter for body mass index and employment duration, 
which were not normally distributed). We used ANOVA to test the overall difference in the distributions 
of sputum leukocyte cell types in fungal positive versus fungal negative samples. We assessed colinearity 
among the sputum cell type percentages for the entire study group using Pearson correlations. </p>

<p>ERJ Open Res 2015; 1: 00023-2015 | DOI: 10.1183/23120541.00023-2015 </p>

<p>
OCCUPATIONAL LUNG DISEASE | A. ADHIKARI ET AL. </p>

<p>We used linear regression analysis to test the associations between selected independent variables (fungal 
status, and eosinophil and lymphocyte percentages) and forced midexpiratory flow (FEF25-75%) 
% predicted as the dependent variable. All linear regression models also took into account the covariates 
age, smoking status (current versus former or never) and duration of employment. In addition to testing 
models in which only one of the independent predictors of interest was included along with the adjusting 
covariates, we also tested models including both fungal status and either eosinophil or lymphocyte 
percentage in the same model. We did so in order to assess the potential mediation of any fungal 
association with lung function by the presence of sputum eosinophils or lymphocytes. Because sputum 
eosinophil and lymphocyte percentages were strongly correlated with one another (r=0.72, p&lt;0.01) and 
both inversely correlated with the percent of macrophages (r= −0.63 and r= −0.55, respectively; both 
p&lt;0.01), we did not include any of these in multivariate models. Eosinophil and lymphocyte percentages, 
however, were only weakly negatively correlated with the percent neutrophils (r= −0.22 ( p&lt;0.05) and 
r= −0.24 ( p&lt;0.10), respectively), allowing us to test whether inclusion of that variable had a substantive 
impact on the mediation by eosinophils of the association of fungal contamination with lung function. All 
analyses were performed using <rs id="software-3" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">version 20</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">IBM Corp.</rs>., Armonk, NY, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Out of the targeted population of 79 males, we did not study those who did not provide consent (n=7), 
did not include those ineligible based on current antibiotic use (n=4) and excluded those without 
reproducible quality spirometry (n=8) or who were unable to expectorate adequate sputum samples (n=6). 
We ultimately analysed data for 54 (68%) wood process workers employed at the four targeted worksites. 
Of those studied, 19 (35%) produced a sputum sample in which fungus was detected, while 35 (65%) were 
sputum fungus negative. In the genomic fungal characterisation, hits generated using standard search 
parameters indicated the fungus belonged to the genus Candida. A phylogenetic tree constructed from the 
hits of NCBI <rs type="software">BLASTN</rs> search results is presented in figure 1. The sequence has been submitted to NCBI 
database and can be accessed through the accession number GenBank KF483576.1. Fungus was not 
detected in saliva sample stains or cultures (figure 1). </p>

<p>The characteristics of the participants by fungal status are presented in table 1. The fungus-positive group 
was, on average, 5.6 years older ( p=0.04) but there were no other statistically significant differences in 
height, weight, smoking status, employment duration or history of parental asthma. </p>

<p>Respiratory symptoms 
The prevalence of reported respiratory symptoms based on questionnaire responses is presented in figure 2. 
Although all of respiratory symptoms elicited were more prevalent among the participants with 
fungus-positive sputum, the differences were statistically significant only for phlegm, cough and haemoptysis 
(p&lt;0.05). Although the latter was the least common complaint, it was reported by seven (37%) participants 
in the fungus-positive group but only by two (6%) among the others. Dermatological complaints, which we 
also ascertained as a possible adverse health effect of fungal contamination, were also was twice as common 
among the fungus-positive group (68.4% versus 37.1%; p=0.06) (figure 2). </p>

<p>Lung function 
Lung function is presented in table 2. There were nonsignificant deficits of 60 mL in forced vital capacity 
(FVC) and 80 mL in forced expiratory volume in 1 s (FEV1) associated with fungal positive status. 
FEF25-75%, however, was significantly reduced in the fungus-positive group, both in absolute terms as and 
a percentage of the predicted value (13% difference, p&lt;0.01). </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 Phylogenetic tree for 11 
taxa of Candida (see Methods 
section for further details). </p>

<p>gi|242253910|emb|FM178339.1|Candida xyl 
gi|166239761|gb|EU315758.1|Candida inco 
gi|388894631|gb|JQ726601.1|Candida inco 
gi|539184692|gb|KF483576.1|Candida sp. 
gi|166239760|gb|EU315757.1|Candida inco 
gi|452056218|ref|NR077074.1|Candida xy 
gi|349587278|gb|JF896575.1|Candida inco 
gi|6333962092|gb|KJ546152.1|Candida inco 
gi|3888894634|gb|JQ726604.1|Candida xylo 
gi|349587277|gb|JF896574.1|Candida xylo 
gi|407196275|gb|JX169806.1|Candida sp. </p>

<p>0.0002 </p>

<p>ERJ Open Res 2015; 1: 00023-2015 | DOI: 10.1183/23120541.00023-2015 </p>

<p>
OCCUPATIONAL LUNG DISEASE | A. ADHIKARI ET AL. </p>

<p>Cellular distribution in sputum 
The distribution of sputum leukocytes by fungal status is presented in table 3. The overall patterns of the 
proportions of eosinophils, lymphocytes, macrophages and neutrophils differed significantly between the 
two groups (ANOVA p&lt;0.01). The median eosinophil percentage in the sputum samples of the 
fungus-positive workers was almost three-fold higher than in the fungus-negative group (9.25% versus 
3.25%). The proportion of sputum lymphocytes was also higher in the in the fungus-positive workers 
compared with the fungus-negative (median 4.25% versus 1.75%) while, conversely, the alveolar 
macrophage percentage was lower (22.5% versus 31.25%). The median neutrophil percentage was similar 
between the two groups. </p>

<p>The associations between fungal detection, sputum eosinophil percentage and FEF25-75% % predicted are 
presented in table 4. The presence of sputum fungus and eosinophils were each independently associated 
with reduced FEF25-75% % predicted, with the associated model explanatory power (R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) ranging from 0.45 
to 0.49. When combined in the same model (model 3), the association of sputum fungus with reduced 
FEF25-75% was markedly attenuated, while the relationship of eosinophil percentage to the dependent lung 
function variable was only modestly weakened, consistent with mediation of the observed fungal effect by 
eosinophil percentage. The addition of sputum macrophage percent to model 3 had little effect on the 
overall R 
2 (0.48) and was not statistically associated with FEF25-75% (β=0.19, 95% CI −0.30-0.69). When 
fungal contamination and percentage lymphocytes were tested together, fungus remained associated with 
FEF25-75% (β= −10.8, 95% CI −17.9-−3.7) while the percentage lymphocytes did not (β= −0.7, 95% CI 
−2.7-1.3) (data not shown). </p>

<p>TABLE 1 Characteristics of 54 wood mill worker study participants </p>

<p>Parameters 
Fungus positive 
Fungus negative 
p-value </p>

<p>Participants n 
19 
35 
Age years 
42.5±10.4 
36.9±5.2 
0.04 
Height cm 
172.05±4.76 
173.20±5.42 
0.43 
BMI kg·m </p>

<p>−2 </p>

<p>21.9±3.3 
21.2±2.3 
0.44 
Ever-smokers 
8 (42.1) 
12 (34.3) 
0.79 
Employment years 
15.8±8.1 
13.0±4.2 
0.18 
Parental asthma 
6 (31.6) 
7 (20.0) 
0.54 </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean±SD or n (%), unless otherwise stated. All participants were male. p-values are 
based on t-test for age and height, Wilcoxon rank sum test for body mass index (BMI) and employment 
years, and Chi-squared test for smoking status and parental asthma. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2 Prevalence of symptoms 
among the sawmill workers 
comparing those with and without 
fungus-positive sputum samples. </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>p=0.06 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Frequency % </p>

<p>Any respiratory </p>

<p>symptom </p>

<p>≥3 respiratory </p>

<p>symptoms 
Wheezing/whistling </p>

<p>in chest 
Acute/chronic 
phlegm </p>

<p>Persistent cough 
Breathing trouble 
Haemoptysis </p>

<p>Skin problems </p>

<p>p=0.01 </p>

<p>p=0.15 </p>

<p>p=0.02 </p>

<p>p=0.04 </p>

<p>p=0.12 
p&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>p=0.61 </p>

<p>Fungus positive </p>

<p>Fungus negative </p>

<p>ERJ Open Res 2015; 1: 00023-2015 | DOI: 10.1183/23120541.00023-2015 </p>

<p>
OCCUPATIONAL LUNG DISEASE | A. ADHIKARI ET AL. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Sawmill workers are occupationally exposed to a range of airborne contaminants. We detected fungal 
contamination by Candida sp. in the sputum samples of approximately one-third of the sawmill workers 
that we studied. Those sputum fungus-positive workers also had more frequent respiratory symptoms, 
increased sputum eosinophils and impaired lung function as measured by their flow at mid-lung volumes 
(FEF25-75%). Moreover, fungal contamination with Candida was linked to the percentage of sputum 
eosinophils, with the latter appearing to mediate the observed association with lung function decrement. </p>

<p>Mould is commonly found in wood processing environments and is presumed to be a major risk factor in 
allergic responses that have been seen in workers in this industry [1, 21, 23]. Contamination of sputum by 
Candida sp., if present on repeated examination, is presumed to reflect airway contamination and this can 
be clinically relevant. The syndrome of allergic bronchopulmonary mycosis (ABPM), for example, even 
though most commonly associated with Aspergillus sp., is also seen with chronic airway candidiasis, and 
includes eosinophilia and airflow obstruction [34]. In the occupational milieu, chronic inhalational 
exposure to fungus is more closely linked to extrinsic allergic alveolitis than ABPM. Multiple occupational 
studies have quantified airborne fungal contamination in working environments in which various organic 
materials are processed, including wood products [6, 14-21]. Systematic assessment of fungal sputum 
contamination in occupational cohorts also has been studied but to a much more limited extent in 
selected high-risk cohorts other than woodworkers, such as malt, sugar cane and flax workers [35-37]. 
These studies have identified a high proportion of sputum samples positive for fungus although, unlike 
our study, the contamination was polymicrobial for a range of fungal species, and Candida sp., although 
present in 3-6%, was not dominant in any of the cohorts [35, 37]. An earlier study of a nonexposed 
occupational population (urban telephone company employees) found that a minority produced 
fungus-contaminated sputum samples and that Candida sp. also was uncommon among those [38]. </p>

<p>The limitations in this study should be kept in view. We visually observed homogenous fungal spores 
(with lactophenol cotton blue stain) in sputum samples prior to culture. Nonetheless, the growth of 
Candida would have been promoted under the incubation conditions used (both by temperature and 
relatively short duration), which could have contributed to its dominance in the genotyping component of 
the analysis. Although we identified an association between sputum fungal contamination and both 
sputum eosinophilia and a lung function decrement, we cannot exclude the latter being a simply a marker </p>

<p>TABLE 2 Comparison of lung function by fungal status among 54 woodworkers </p>

<p>Parameters 
Fungus positive 
Fungus negative 
p-value </p>

<p>Participants n 
19 
35 
FVC L 
2.83±0.30 
2.89±0.24 
0.44 
FVC % predicted 
79.0±8.2 
78.0±8.3 
0.70 
FEV1 L 
2.12±0.29 
2.20±0.28 
0.36 
FEV1 % predicted 
76.7±10.2 
75.2±11.2 
0.61 
FEV1/FVC 
0.75±0.04 
0.76±0.06 
0.47 
FEF25-75% L·s </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>2.59±0.55 
2.98±0.47 
0.01 
FEF25-75% % predicted 
69.2±9.95 
82.3±4.53 
&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean±SD unless otherwise stated. FVC: forced vital capacity; FEV1: forced expiratory 
volume in 1 s; FEF25-75%: forced expiratory flow at 25-75% of FVC. </p>

<p>TABLE 3 Comparison of inflammatory cellular profile in the sputum between the study groups </p>

<p>Sputum 
cell type </p>

<p>Fungus positive </p>

<p># </p>

<p>Fungus negative </p>

<p> ¶ </p>

<p>Median 
(interquartile range) </p>

<p>Range 
Median 
(interquartile range) </p>

<p>Range </p>

<p>Neutrophils % 
62.75 (58.0-67.25) 
52.25-69.5 
63.25 (62.25-66.25) 
57.75-72.25 
Eosinophils % 
9.25 (8.5-10.25) 
6.75-11.5 
3.25 (2.5-4.25) 
1.5-5.25 
Macrophages % 
22.5 (18.75-28.5) 
16.75-33.75 
31.25 (29.5-32.625) 
24.0-35.5 
Lymphocytes % 
4.25 (3.75-4.875) 
3.5-7.5 
1.75 (1.25-2.125) 
0.5-4.25 </p>

<p>Group-wise comparison (ANOVA), p&lt;0.01. </p>

<p># </p>

<p>: n=19; </p>

<p> ¶ </p>

<p>: n=35. </p>

<p>ERJ Open Res 2015; 1: 00023-2015 | DOI: 10.1183/23120541.00023-2015 </p>

<p>
OCCUPATIONAL LUNG DISEASE | A. ADHIKARI ET AL. </p>

<p>of another unmeasured and confounding coexposure. Such an exposure could be to other microbes, 
endotoxins, glucans or wood dust itself, none of which we measured. We did not have industrial hygiene 
sampling data or other direct exposure measures quantifying airborne concentrations of these exposures. 
Moreover, adequate characterisation of such exposures would have required multiple assessments at a 
number of different time-points given the likely variability in such bioaerosol exposures. </p>

<p>Despite observing a decrement in the spirometric measure of FEF25-75%, we did not detect an 
exposure-related decrement in FEV1 or the ratio of FEV1 to FVC, lung function variables of clinical 
relevance to asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). Radiographic imaging, which was 
not available, could have provided valuable additional data, for example, computed tomography-assessed air 
trapping or even the detection of fungus-associated changes that might have correlated with the sputum 
fungus-associated complaint of haemoptysis [39]. Although reduced FEF25-75% indeed could be an early 
marker of airway disease that would later progress, our cross-sectional study cannot assess that prospective 
outcome. Furthermore, we did not have any clinical diagnostic assessment of the participants to assess the 
presence or absence of lung diseases such as asthma, COPD, bronchiectasis or tuberculosis. </p>

<p>Another study limitation is our lack of characterisation of the potential bacterial contents of the sputum, for 
example, by using bacterial ribosomal RNA sequencing or quantitative PCR techniques. We also acknowledge 
that we did not have access to a formal external control group of non-sawmill workers for sputum Candida 
testing and thus cannot comment on what the general population prevalence of such fungal detection might 
be. Rather, our analysis was more analogous to a nested design in which the Candida-positive workers were 
"cases" and those that were negative served as "referents" for comparison. Although we ultimately studied 
68% of the target population, it is possible that those not studied differed in systematic ways that could have 
impacted the estimated prevalence of fungal detection. For example, spirometry test failure has been 
associated with airway disease [40]. In contrast, inability to produce sputum could theoretically be associated 
with an absence of disease, having the opposite association with fungal prevalence. </p>

<p>Because of these limitations, we cannot assume a causal association between the fungal contamination of the 
sawmill workers' sputum that we detected and airway inflammation or dysfunction. We can conclude, 
however, that contamination of the respiratory tract by Candida sp. in this study identified a group with a 
greater symptom burden, elevated sputum eosinophils and a decreased airflow at mid-lung volumes. These 
findings suggest that fungal contamination in this work environment may be linked to adverse health effects 
and that this question merits additional assessment, in particular, through targeted exposure assessment and 
longitudinal study of potential evolution in airflow deficits in those occupationally exposed in sawmills. </p>



<p>TABLE 4 Mediation analysis for the association between fungal appearance, lung function and 
sputum inflammatory cells </p>

<p>Model 
Predictors 
FEF25-75% % predicted </p>

<p>β (95% CI) 
p-value 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Model 1 
Fungus positivity 
−12.7 (−16.9-−8.5) 
&lt;0.001 
0.45 
Model 2 
Eosinophil % 
−2.1 (−2.8-−1.5) 
&lt;0.001 
0.49 
Model 3 
Fungus positivity 
−3.5 (−13.9-6.9) 
0.51 
0.48 
and eosinophil % 
−1.6 (−3.3-0.06) 
0.06 </p>

<p>All models included age, smoking status (current versus former or never) and years of employment. 
FEF25-75%: forced expiratory flow at 25-75% of forced vital capacity; β: adjusted regression coefficient; R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>: 
determination coefficient. </p>

<p>ERJ Open Res 2015; 1: 00023-2015 | DOI: 10.1183/23120541.00023-2015 </p>

<p>
OCCUPATIONAL LUNG DISEASE | A. ADHIKARI ET AL. </p>





<p>ERJ Open Res 2015; 1: 00023-2015 | DOI: 10.1183/23120541.00023-2015 </p>

<p>
OCCUPATIONAL LUNG DISEASE | A. ADHIKARI ET AL. </p>

</text></tei>