<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5198113" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
The semaphorins and the plexins are a family of large, cysteine-rich proteins originally identified as regulators of 
axon growth and lymphocyte activation that are now known to provide motility and positional information for a 
number of cell and tissue types. For example, our group and others have shown that some malignancies over 
express Semaphorin 4D (S4D), which acts through its receptor Plexin-B1 (PB1) on endothelial cells to attract blood 
vessels from the surrounding stroma for the purpose of supporting tumor growth. While plexins are the known 
functional receptors for the semaphorins, there is evidence that transmembrane semaphorins may transmit a 
signal themselves through their short cytoplasmic tail, a phenomenon known as 'reverse signaling.' We used 
computational methods based upon correlated evolution of sequences of interacting proteins, mutational analysis 
and in vitro and in vivo measurements of tumor aggressiveness to show that when bound to PB1, transmembrane 
S4D associates with the Rac GTPase exchange factor T lymphoma invasion and metastasis (Tiam) 1, which 
activates Rac and promotes proliferation, invasion and metastasis in oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC) cells. 
These results suggest that not only can S4D production by tumor cells affect the microenvironment, but 
engagement of this semaphorin at the cell surface activates a reverse signaling mechanism that influences tumor 
aggressiveness in OSCC. </p>

<p>receptors themselves and signal to the cell expressing them through a 
short C-terminal cytoplasmic tail, resulting in a bi-directional or 
'reverse' signaling mechanism when bound by plexins. Both Class 4 </p>

<p>www.neoplasia.com </p>

<p>Volume 19 Number 2 
February 2017 
pp. 65-74 65 </p>

<p>Address all correspondence to: John R. Basile, Department of Oncology and Diagnostic 
Sciences, University of Maryland Dental School, 650 West Baltimore Street, 7-North, 
Baltimore, MD 21201. 
E-mail: jbasile@umaryland.edu 
Received 12 August 2016; Revised 1 December 2016; Accepted 5 December 2016 </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. on behalf of Neoplasia Press, Inc. This is an open 
access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
1476-5586 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.neo.2016.12.004 </p>

<p>and 6 semaphorins exist in a transmembrane form and have been 
shown to associate with adaptor proteins and phosphorylation activity 
that is important for immune cell maturation and cardiac muscle 
development [8,9]. Moreover, Class 4 semaphorins have been 
reported to possess a motif capable of binding to post synaptic 
density protein/Drosophila disc large tumor suppressor/zonula 
occuldens-1 protein (PDZ) domains [10,11], a common component 
of many proteins that is involved in the sorting, targeting and 
assembly of supramolecular signaling complexes [12]. 
T lymphoma invasion and metastasis (Tiam) 1 is a GTPase 
exchange factor (GEF) that activates Rac1, a Rho GTPase controlling 
actin polymerization, membrane ruffling, lamellipodia extension and 
focal adhesion formation in the cell [13]. An important downstream 
effector of Rac1 is p21-activated kinase (PAK), which signals through 
the MAP kinases to promote gene transcription and cell division. 
Therefore, Rac activation through Tiam1 not only promotes cell 
migration but also cell division, and Tiam1 is unsurprisingly found to 
be over expressed in many malignancies including metastatic breast 
cancer and T cell lymphomas, which gave the protein its name 
[13-15]. Like other GEFs, Tiam1 contains multiple signaling 
domains that enable it to receive upstream signals as well as recruit 
downstream components of the Rho GTPase pathway [16]. These 
domains include a Ras-binding domain (RBD), Dbl homology and 
pleckstrin homology domains (DH/PH), which are necessary to 
catalyze the exchange of GDP for GTP, and a PDZ domain that the 
protein uses for temporal and spatial control and to recruit other 
proteins [16]. PDZ domains are highly efficient at interacting with 
transmembrane proteins that have the C-terminus facing the 
cytoplasm, even if the cytoplasmic tails of those proteins are short. 
Our lab and others have shown previously that Semaphorin 4D 
(S4D), also known as CD100, is a potent pro-angiogenic molecule 
expressed by the cells of oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC) and 
other solid tumors for the purposes of attracting blood vessels into a 
developing malignancy [3,4,17]. There is additional evidence that 
S4D acts through its high affinity receptor Plexin-B1 (PB1) to 
enhance the invasive ability of tumor cells, leading to a poor prognosis 
in tumors expressing this protein [2,18-20]. S4D is proteolytically 
cleaved from the surface of cells [21-23] but also exists in a 
transmembrane form, with a C-terminal intracytoplasmic segment of 
over 100 amino acids that may participate in reverse signaling by 
associating with kinase or phosphatase activity in T and B 
lymphocytes [8,24,25]. To investigate how membrane bound S4D 
might alter cancer cell physiology in the context of binding to PB1, </p>

<p>we studied the intracellular segment of the protein for new binding 
partners using the Mirrortree method. This technique attempts to 
predict protein interactions by focusing on correlated evolution of 
sequences of two or more proteins based upon the principle that they 
will co-evolve over time in order to maintain their interactions [26]. 
Among the potential candidates, Mirrortree predicted Tiam1 to have 
the greatest likelihood of association with the intracellular segment of 
S4D. 
Here we show that upon binding to PB1, S4D transiently 
associates with Tiam1, which results in the activation of Rac1 and 
enhanced proliferation, migration, and invasion of OSCC cell lines. 
This association also promotes transendothelial migration of cancer 
cells, suggestive of a more aggressive and metastatic phenotype. 
Indeed, both S4D and Tiam1 are expressed at high levels in biopsies 
of oral cancer tissues, and localize to the same areas of these tumors, 
and we show that HN cancer cell lines expressing full length, 
membrane bound S4D exhibit greater metastasis in an in vivo tumor 
xenograft model than those lacking the intracellular C-terminal 
segment. Taken together, these results demonstrate that not only can 
S4D production by tumor cells affect the microenvironment to 
enhance growth through promotion of angiogenesis, but engagement 
of this semaphorin at the cell surface by PB1 activates a reverse 
signaling mechanism that promotes aggressive behavior and metas-
tasis in OSCC. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Mirrortree Analysis </p>

<p>To predict protein interaction partners for the C-terminus of 
S4D, we first created a database of orthologous proteins, defined 
as the proteins with the smallest average E-value from forward and 
reciprocal <rs type="software">BLAST</rs> searches for two species and the largest 
sequence overlap, from 184 species in the NCBI Entrez database 
[27], while restricting E-values to those less than 1e-5 and 
sequence overlap to greater than 80%. Using this ortholog 
database, we calculated the Pearson's correlation coefficient for 
domain-domain interactions between S4D and PDZ domains 
found in human proteins using the Mirrortree methodology as 
described previously [26,28,29]. Briefly, the full protein multiple 
sequence alignments (MSAs) were broken at the domain start and 
end positions. These reduced domain MSAs were used as the 
input for the Mirrortree method, along with the PDZ domains 
found in all other human proteins. </p>

<p>Table 1. Results of the Mirrortree Analysis, Looking for Proteins That are Predicted to Interact With the Intracellular Portion of S4D (Amino Acids 756-862). The Amino Acids for the Domain of Each 
Protein Predicted to Bind are Shown in the Third Column </p>

<p>Gene 
symbol </p>

<p>Gene 
description </p>

<p>Domain predicted 
to bind </p>

<p>Correlation 
coef. 1e-5 </p>

<p>Function 
NCBI Gene Link 
GeneCards Link </p>

<p>TIAM1 
T-cell lymphoma 
invasion and 
metastasis 1 </p>

<p>843-925 
0.87 
Regulation of small GTPase mediated 
signal transduction; receptor signaling 
protein activity </p>

<p>www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/7074 
http://www.genecards.org/cgi-bin/ 
carddisp.pl?gene=TIAM1 </p>

<p>FRMPD2 FERM and PDZ 
domain containing 2 </p>

<p>948-1032 
0.86 
tight junction assembly; cytoskeleton 
www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/143162 http://www.genecards.org/cgi-bin/ 
carddisp.pl?gene=FRMPD2 
PDZD8 
PDZ domain 
containing 8 </p>

<p>364-446 
0.74 
metal ion binding; intracellular 
signal transduction </p>

<p>www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/118987 http://www.genecards.org/cgi-bin/ 
carddisp.pl?gene=PDZD8 
RGS12 
regulator of G-protein 
signaling 12 </p>

<p>20-96 
0.71 
regulation of G-protein coupled receptor 
signaling pathways; GTPase regulator activity </p>

<p>www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/6002 
http://www.genecards.org/cgi-bin/ 
carddisp.pl?gene=RGS12 
PDZK1 
PDZ domain 
containing 1 </p>

<p>133-212 
0.71 
transporter activity; scavenger receptor binding; 
positive regulation of ion transmembrane 
transport; drug transport </p>

<p>www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/5174 
http://www.genecards.org/cgi-bin/ 
carddisp.pl?gene=PDZK1 </p>

<p> 
Rac activation by Semaphorin 4D reverse signaling 
Zhou et al. 
Neoplasia Vol. 19, No. 2, 2017 </p>

<p>Cell Culture, Plasmids, and Transfections </p>

<p>Human Microvascular Endothelial Cells (HMVECs, Promocell, 
Heidelberg, Germany) were grown to confluency in Endothelial Cell 
Growth Medium (Promocell). HN lines 6, 12 [30] and 13 (gifts of 
Dr. J. Silvio Gutkind) and human embryonic kidney (HEK) 293 T 
cells were cultured in DMEM (Sigma, St. Louis, MO) supplemented 
with 10% fetal bovine serum and 100 units/ml penicillin/ 
streptomycin/amphotericin B (Sigma). Cells were treated with soluble 
PB1 (sPB1, see below) or Rac inhibitor (Sigma) where indicated. 
HN6 cells, controls and a bioluminescent clone, were developed after 
transfection with a luciferase-expressing retroviral construct as 
previously described [31]. 
The full length S4D construct has been described previously [23]. 
HA-tagged full length Tiam1 was the generous gift of Dr. Angeliki 
Malliri [32]. The Tiam1 truncation mutants ΔN (845aa-1591aa), 
ΔC (908aa-1591aa), and the S4D mutants ΔPDZM and ΔC were 
generated by PCR and subcloned into pCMV. The primers used 
for PCR were as follows: Tiam1 ΔN: Forward: 5′-ATAA-
GAATGCGGCCGCTATCCACATTGAGAAGTCAGA-3′ and re-
v e r s e : 5 ′ -T G C A G G A T A T C T C A G A T C T C A G T G T T -
CAGTTTC-3′; Tiam1 ΔC: Forward: 5′-ATAAGAATGCGGCC 
GCTTCTATGCTCAAAGATTTCC-3′ and reverse: 5′-TGCAG-
GATATCTCAGATCTCAGTGTTCAGTTTC-3′; S4D ΔPDZM: 
Forward: 5′-CGGGATCCTCAGTCTGAGTCAGCGAACTT-
CAGCTC-3′ and reverse: 5′-CGGGATCCTCAGTCTCCATCT </p>

<p>GCGTCTGAGTC-3′; S4DΔC: Forward: 5′-CGGGATCCTCAA-
TAGCAGTTGTAGAAAAAGAGGCAGAGG-3′ and reverse: 5′-
CGGGATCCTCAGTCTCCATCTGCGTCTGAGTC-3′. The ex-
pression vectors were transfected using FugeneHD (Promega, CA, 
USA) according to manufacturer's instructions. </p>

<p>Production of sPB1 </p>

<p>The extracellular portion of human PB1 was subjected to PCR 
with the following primers: Forward: 5′-CCCAAGCT-
TATGCCTGCTCTGGGCCCAGCTCTT-3′ and reverse: 
5′-CCGGAATTCCCAAGCCCACCTGGGCTGCCACA-3′. The 
resulting product was cloned into the plasmid pSecTag2B (Invitro-
gen, Carlsbad, CA). This construct was transfected into 293 T cells 
growing in serum free media. Media was collected 65 hours 
post-transfection and purified with TALON metal affinity resin 
(Clontech Laboratories, Palo Alto, CA) according to manufacturer's 
instructions. Concentration and purity of the TALON eluates was 
determined by SDS PAGE analysis followed by silver staining 
(Amersham Life Science, Piscataway, NJ) and the Bio-Rad protein 
assay (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). In all cases, media collected from cells 
transfected with the empty pSecTag2B vector were used as control. </p>

<p>Immunoprecipitation and Immunoblot Analysis </p>

<p>Cells were transfected with the indicated constructs or infected 
with the short hairpin (sh)RNA lentiviruses shown (see below), </p>

<p>Figure 1. Ligation of S4D with PB1 induces its association with Tiam1. (A) A soluble form of the extracellular portion of PB1 (sPB1) was 
detected in media conditioned by 293 T transfected with this construct (His tag). (B) Immunoprecipitation of endogenous Tiam1 in HN12 
cells treated with purified sPB1 for the times indicated reveals an association with S4D at 5 minutes. (C) Immunoprecipitation of full length 
HA tagged Tiam1 (upper two panels), transfected into 293 T cells along with His tagged S4D, full length (FL), constructs missing the PDZ 
binding motif (ΔPDZM), or the entire C-terminal intracellular segment (ΔC), reveals association between these proteins except where the 
C-terminal segment has been deleted (His, top panel). Tiam1 is also successfully precipitated (HA-Tiam, second panel). An immunoblot in 
whole cell lysates (WCL) reveals expression of all proteins (lower panels). (D) Immunoprecipitation of full length His tagged S4D (upper 
two panels), transfected into 293 T cells along with HA tagged Tiam-1, full length (FL), constructs missing the N-terminal PH and RBD 
domains (ΔN), or the C-terminal PDZ domain (ΔPDZ), reveals association between these proteins except where the PDZ domain has been 
deleted (second panel). S4D is successfully precipitated (His-S4D, top panel). An immunoblot in whole cell lysates reveals expression of 
all proteins (lower panels). </p>

<p>Neoplasia Vol. 19, No. 2, 2017 
Rac activation by Semaphorin 4D reverse signaling 
Zhou et al. </p>

<p>
treated appropriately and lysed in lysis buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, 150 
mM NaCl, 1% NP 40) supplemented with protease inhibitors (0.5 
mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride, 1 μl/ml aprotinin and leupeptin, 
Sigma) and phosphatase inhibitors (2 mM NaF and 0.5 mM sodium 
orthovanadate, Sigma) for 15 minutes at 4°C. After centrifugation, 
protein concentrations were measured using the Bio-Rad protein 
assay (Bio-Rad) and each sample was subjected to immunoprecip-
itation by incubation with the indicated antibody for 1 hour at 4°C, 
and/or subjected to SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. Gels 
were transferred onto a PVDF membrane (Immobilon P, Millipore 
Corp., Billerica, MA) which was stained with Ponceau red (Sigma), 
cut into sections containing the proteins of interest and probed </p>

<p>using the following antibodies: HA, His, and GAPDH (Santa Cruz 
Biotech, Santa Cruz CA); Tiam1 (Abcam, Cambridge MA); S4D 
(BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA); Rac1 (Pierce, Rockford, IL). Proteins 
were detected using the ECL chemiluminescence system (Pierce). </p>

<p>shRNA and Lentiviral Infections </p>

<p>The shRNA sequences for S4D and Tiam1 were obtained from 
Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory's RNAi library (RNAi Central, 
http://cancan.cshl.edu/RNAi_central/RNAi.cgi?type=shRNA) 
[16,17]. The sequence used as PCR templates for S4D has been 
previously reported [18]. The sequence for Tiam1 shRNA was 
5′-TGCTGTTGACAGTGAGCGAGGAACCGAAGCTGTAAA-
GAAATAGTGAAGCCACAG ATGTATTTCTTTACAGC 
TTCGGTTCCCTGCCTACTGCCTCGGA-3′. Oligos were syn-
thesized (Invitrogen) and cloned into pWPI GW, a Gateway 
compatible CSCG based lentiviral destination vector, as previously 
described [18-20]. Viral stocks were prepared and infections 
performed as previously reported [18,21,22]. Control infections 
were performed with viruses manufactured with empty expression 
vectors. </p>

<p>Rac Assay </p>

<p>Activation of Rac was analyzed using a GST-PBD pulldown kit 
(Pierce) according to manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, cell 
monolayers were washed twice with PBS and lysed for 5 minutes in 
GTPase Activation Buffer (50 mM Tris, pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 1% 
(v/v) Triton X-100, 10 mM MgCl2, 10% (v/v) glycerol), complete 
protease inhibitor cocktail (5 mM sodium fluoride and 1 mM sodium 
orthovanadate; Sigma). Approximately 20 μg of GST-PBD fusion 
protein was added to the lysate and rotated for 1 hour at 4°C. The 
beads were washed three times, eluted with SDS sample buffer and 
immunoblotted for Rac. Equivalent amounts of each lysate were 
removed prior to GST-PBD addition and analyzed by immunoblot to 
normalize total Rac levels. </p>

<p>Migration and Invasion Assay </p>

<p>Cell motility was assayed using Transwell chamber inserts 
(Millipore) with a porous polycarbonate membrane (8 μ pore 
size). To allow tumor cell migration, the lower side of the filter was 
coated with 10 μg/ml fibronectin. Cells were harvested from culture 
dishes by treatment with 1 mM EDTA and resuspended in 0.2% 
BSA-containing medium. Approximately 1 × 10 
5 cells were added 
in the upper chamber and allowed to migrate through the filter 
toward the lower chamber (including regulatory molecules, when 
indicated) for 6-8 hours in a cell culture incubator. The cells 
adherent to the upper side of the filter were mechanically removed, 
while those that migrated to the lower side of the filter were fixed in 
glutaraldehyde and stained with crystal violet. Following photo-
graphs, the dye was then solubilized in 10% acetic acid to measure 
absorbance at 595 nm in a microplate reader. For the invasion 
assays, 5 × 10 
5 tumor cells were added to the upper chamber of a 
Transwell insert coated with 20 μg of Cultrex Reduced Growth 
Factor Basement Membrane Extract, PathClear (Trevigen, 
Gaithersburg, MD, Cat#: 3433-010-01), a material consisting of 
laminin, collagen type IV, entactin, and heparin sulfate proteoglycan 
that mimics a basement membrane. Cells were incubated in medium 
containing 1% FBS for 16 h, after which the cells adherent to the 
lower side of the porous membrane were fixed and analyzed as 
above. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Ligation of S4D with PB1 causes Tiam1-dependent 
activation of Rac1. (A) A Rac assay was performed on HN12 and 13 
cells, untreated, treated with GTP gamma S (positive control), or 
grown in the presence of sPB1, looking for GTP-bound, and hence 
active Rac. sPB1 is capable of activating Rac in all cells (active 
Rac1, top panel). (B) Endogenous S4D protein (top panel) is 
decreased in an immunoblot in OSCC cells infected with lentivirus 
coding for S4D shRNA. (C) Endogenous Tiam1 (top panel) is 
decreased in an immunoblot in OSCC cells infected with lentivirus 
coding for Tiam1 shRNA. GAPDH was used as the loading control 
in both blots (bottom panels). (D) A Rac assay was performed in 
HN12 (left panel) and HN13 (right panel), controls, and in the 
presence of sPB1 with or without S4D and Tiam1 silenced by 
infection with lentivirus coding for the appropriate shRNA (S4Dsh 
and Tiam1sh, respectively). Once again sPB1 is capable of 
activating Rac, except when S4D or Tiam1 are silenced. GDP and 
GTP were the negative and positive controls, respectively. Total 
Rac1 is used as loading controls in all Rac assays (bottom panels). </p>

<p> 
Rac activation by Semaphorin 4D reverse signaling 
Zhou et al. 
Neoplasia Vol. 19, No. 2, 2017 </p>

<p>Proliferation Assay </p>

<p>Cell growth was determined using a Cell Proliferation Reagent 
WST-1 (Roche, Basel, Switzerland). Briefly, HN lines were grown in 
100 μl of culture medium in 96-well plates at a concentration of 
3 × 10 
3 cells/well. A450 nm and A690 nm were measured using a 
plate reader (Biotek, Luminex, Austin, TX). </p>

<p>Transendothelial Migration Assay </p>

<p>Approximately 1 × 10 
5 HMVECs were added to type I 
collagen-coated 24-well Transwell inserts with 5 μ pore size and 
grown to confluence over 3 days, with daily replacement of fresh 
culture medium, until they formed a tightly packed monolayer. Then, 
7 × 10 
5 GFP expressing HN12 and HN13 cells, resuspended in 
HMVEC culture medium, were added to the upper chamber. After 
incubation for 16 hours, the cells were fixed with glutaraldehyde, and 
the upper side of the membranes gently scraped with a cotton swab to 
remove non-migrated cells. Transmigrated tumor cells were quanti-
fied based on green fluorescence in 5 random fields under Nikon 
Eclipse 800 microscope. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Individual paraffin blocks of formalin-fixed OSCC biopsies were 
obtained from the Department of Oncology and Diagnostic Sciences, 
University of Maryland Dental School (Baltimore, MD) and </p>

<p>processed for immunohistochemistry as previously described [18]. 
Briefly, tissues were deparaffinized, hydrated through graded alcohols 
and incubated in 3% hydrogen peroxide for 10 minutes to quench 
the endogenous peroxidase. Sections were then incubated in 
blocking solution (Power Block, BioGenex, Fremont, CA), and 
incubated overnight at 4°C with primary antibodies diluted in a 
2% BSA/0.1% Tween 20 solution in PBS. The following 
antibodies were used: anti-Tiam1 (1:50 dilution, Abcam), 
anti-PB1 (Santa Cruz A8, 1:10 dilution). Slides were then washed 
in PBS, incubated with biotinylated secondary antibody (Bio-
tinylated Link Universal, DAKO North America) for 45 minutes, 
and treated with strepavidin-HRP (DAKO North America) for 30 
minutes at room temperature. The slides were developed in 
3,3-diaminobenzidine (FASTDAB tablets; Sigma), counterstained 
with dilute Mayer's hematoxylin, dehydrated, and mounted. 
Images were taken with an Aperio ScanScope CS scanner (Aperio, 
Vista, CA). </p>

<p>Tumor Cell injections and Animal Studies </p>

<p>1×10 
5 HN6 cells, stably expressing luciferase and transfected with 
the FL S4D or the ΔC truncation mutant constructs were injected 
into the tail veins of immunocompromised (nude) mice. Mice were 
intraperitoneally injected with 100 mg/ml D-luciferin (Perkin Elmer, 
Waltham, MA) in PBS 10 minutes before bioluminescence imaging </p>

<p>Figure 3. PB1 induces S4D-and Tiam1-dependent migration and invasion in OSCC. (a) Cells with or without silenced S4D, Tiam1, or 
pre-treated with Rac inhibitor were used in a migration assay toward sPB1. Both HN12 and 13 exhibited migration much higher than that 
of controls, unless either S4D, Tiam1, or both were silenced by shRNA, or in the presence of the Rac inhibitor. (B) Results from (A) are 
quantified relative to untreated controls (Y-axis). (C) Identically treated cells were used in an invasion assay toward sPB1. Both HN12 and 
13 exhibited invasion through transwell membranes coated with reconstituted basement membrane extract at levels much higher than 
that of controls, unless either S4D, Tiam1, or both were silenced by shRNA, or in the presence of Rac inhibitor. (D) Results from (C) are 
quantified relative to untreated controls (Y-axis). For all bar graphs, the error bars represent the standard deviation from the averages of 
three experiments (*, P b .05). </p>

<p>Neoplasia Vol. 19, No. 2, 2017 
Rac activation by Semaphorin 4D reverse signaling 
Zhou et al. </p>

<p>
(BLI), which was used to track development of lung lesions. 
Images were acquired with a Xenogen IVIS 200 imaging system 
(Perkin Elmer). For analysis, total photon flux (photons per second) 
was measured from the lung tumors. All animal studies were approved 
by the University of Maryland Office of Animal Welfare, Institutional 
Animal Care and Use Committee, in accordance with the NIH Guide 
for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Student's paired t tests were performed on means, and p values 
calculated: *, P b .05; **, P b .01. A Kaplan-Meier survival curve was 
calculated from in vivo data and subjected to a log-rank test. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The C-terminal Intracellular Portion of S4D 
Associates With the PDZ Domain of Tiam1 
When Ligated to PB1 </p>

<p>Class 4 semaphorins have been reported to possess a PDZ 
binding motif (PDZM) that can interact with proteins possessing 
PDZ domains, which are responsible for helping to assemble 
supramolecular signaling complexes [12]. To investigate potential 
reverse signaling pathways activated by S4D in OSCC cells upon 
binding to PB1, we used Mirrortree to predict potential protein 
interactions with the cytoplasmic tail of S4D, paying particular 
attention to binding partners that might contain PDZ domains. 
There were 5 domain-domain interactions within the intracellular 
segment of S4D that had a Pearson's correlation greater than 0.70, 
with the interaction between the S4D and Tiam1 as the first hit 
with a correlation coefficient of 0.87 (Table 1). To look for this 
relationship in OSCC cells, we generated His-tagged soluble 
(s)PB1, which includes the extracellular portion of the receptor 
with the SEMA domain, purified this protein (Figure 1A) and 
used it to treat the OSCC cell line HN12. As predicted, when we 
immunoprecipitated Tiam1 from sPB1 treated cells, we noted a 
transient association with S4D at 5 minutes (Figure 1B). To 
determine which portion of S4D is responsible for binding, we 
over expressed full length S4D (FL) and truncation mutants 
lacking the last eight amino acids (including the PDZ binding 
motif; ΔPDZM) and the entire intracellular portion of the 
molecule (ΔC) in 293 T cells along with full length Tiam1, 
immunoprecipitating for the HA tag on Tiam1. As expected, FL 
S4D precipitated with Tiam1, but surprisingly so did the ΔPDZM 
mutant, while only the ΔC mutant failed to bind (Figure 1C, IP 
(HA), upper panel). Tiam1 was observed in the IP (IP (HA), 
second panel) and both proteins were shown to be expressed in the 
whole cell lysate (WCL, lower panels). We performed a similar 
analysis for Tiam1, expressing full length protein, a construct 
lacking the N-terminal PH and RBD domains (ΔN) and one 
lacking the C-terminal PDZ domain (ΔPDZ), along with FL S4D, 
precipitating for the His tag on S4D. We found that both FL and 
ΔN precipitated with S4D, while the ΔPDZ mutant failed to do so 
(Figure 1D, IP (His), second panel). S4D was detected in the 
immunoprecipitation (IP (His), upper panel) and all constructs 
were shown to be expressed in the immunoblot (WCL, lower 
panels). These results show that the PDZ domain of Tiam1 is 
necessary to bind to S4D, but do not specify where this association 
occurs on the S4D protein, only that the PDZM is not required. </p>

<p>PB1 Induces Rac1 Activation in OSCC in a S4D and Tiam1-
dependent Manner </p>

<p>Because Tiam1 activates Rac [13], we wanted to determine if 
binding of PB1 to S4D elicited this response. First we subjected OSCC 
cells to a Rac assay, looking for GTP bound and hence activated Rac1 
when treated with sPB1. HN12 and 13 cells did indeed show active 
Rac1, similar to the level observed in positive controls, when incubated 
with sPB1 (Figure 2A). We then silenced S4D (Figure 2B) and Tiam1 
(Figure 2C) by infection with short hairpin (sh)RNA-expressing 
lentivirus and observed that GTP-bound Rac was greatly reduced or 
lost in sPB1 treated HN12 and HN13 cells when either of these 
proteins were silenced (Figure 2D). These results show that S4D and 
Tiam1 are necessary for PB1-mediated Rac activation. </p>

<p>Figure 4. PB1 induces S4D-and Tiam1-dependent proliferation and 
trans-endothelial migration in OSCC. (A) Proliferation assay of sPB1 
treated HN12 cells relative to controls (Y-axis) with and without 
silencing of Tiam1 (sPB1 + Tiam1sh) and S4D (sPB1 + S4Dsh), 
measured out to 4 days. (B) Transendothelial migration assay with 
HN12 and 13 cells stably expressing GFP, controls or cells treated 
with sPB1 but with silenced S4D (S4Dsh), Tiam1 (Tiam1sh) or Rac1 
inhibitor, passing through a HMVEC monolayer. Representative 
photos are shown. (C) Quantification of the results in (B), with 
experimental populations compared to untreated controls (Y-axis; 
the error bars represent the standard deviation from the averages 
of three experiments (*, P b .05; **, P ≤ .01)). </p>

<p> 
Rac activation by Semaphorin 4D reverse signaling 
Zhou et al. 
Neoplasia Vol. 19, No. 2, 2017 </p>

<p>PB1-mediated Activation of Rac Results in Enhanced In vitro 
Migration and Invasion of OSCC </p>

<p>Activation of Rac leads to alterations in the cytoskeleton and the 
formation of invadopodia, a phenotype that promotes tumor cell 
invasion [13]. To determine the biological significance of Rac 
activation by PB1 in OSCC, we performed a Boyden chamber 
migration assay measuring the passage of HN12 and 13 cells through 
a porous membrane toward sPB1, with or without silenced S4D, 
Tiam1, or treatment with Rac inhibitor. In the presence of sPB1, 
HN12 and 13 cells exhibited robust migration, which was suppressed 
when S4D was silenced and the cells could not detect PB1, when 
Tiam1 was silenced, and when Rac1 was inhibited (Figure 3A). These 
results are quantified in the bar graph in Figure 3B. A similar 
experiment was performed, this time using membranes coated with 
reconstituted basement membrane extract to mimic the basement 
membrane that would be separating the epithelial compartment from 
the underlying connective tissue. The number of cells present on the 
underside of the porous membrane would therefore be a measure of 
tumor aggressiveness and invasive potential. HN12 and 13 cells 
exhibited invasion toward PB1, except when S4D and Tiam1 were 
silenced and where Rac1 was inhibited (Figure 3C). The results of the 
invasion assay are quantified in Figure 3D. Taken together, these 
results suggest that PB1 can induce HN cancer cells to exhibit 
Rac-dependent migration and invasion into the microenvironment 
when bound to S4D. </p>

<p>PB1-mediated Activation of Rac Results in Enhanced 
Proliferation and Transendothelial Migration of OSCC </p>

<p>Rac1 activates PAK, which promotes cell division [13]. To see if 
this occurs in OSCC, we grew cells in sPB1, with and without 
silencing S4D and Tiam1, now known to be necessary for Rac1 </p>

<p>Figure 5. Biopsies of OSCC exhibit high levels of expression of S4D and Tiam1 in the same areas of tumor. (A) Representative sections of 
formalin fixed, paraffin embedded OSCC, with immunohistochemistry performed for S4D (left) and Tiam1 (right), demonstrating 
expression of these proteins in the same areas of the tumor in serial sections (Original magnification 20X). (B) Quantification of 
immunohistochemical staining for 54 tumors. </p>

<p>Figure 6. Full length S4D promotes OSCC metastasis and shortens 
survival in vivo. (A) HN6 cells stably expressing luciferase and either 
full length S4D (FL S4D), or the C-terminal truncation mutant that 
cannot bind to Tiam1 and activate Rac1 (S4DΔC) were introduced 
into the tail veins of immunocompromised mice and developing 
lung metastases tracked by BLI. Representative lesions are shown 
at day 38. (B) Mice grafted with HN6 expressing S4DΔC exhibited 
fewer metastatic lesions (tumor burden, 10 
6 photons/sec, Y-axis) 
compared to those expressing the full length construct (*, P b .05). 
(C) Kaplan-Meier curve reveals that mice grafted with HN6 
expressing S4DΔC exhibited longer survival compared to HN6 FL 
S4D cells. </p>

<p>Neoplasia Vol. 19, No. 2, 2017 
Rac activation by Semaphorin 4D reverse signaling 
Zhou et al. </p>

<p>
activation. sPB1 induced HN12 cells to divide more rapidly than 
controls out to 4 days, except when S4D and Tiam1 were silenced 
(Figure 4A), a result suggestive of a more aggressive tumor phenotype. 
To determine possible effects of Rac1 activation on metastasis, we 
grew HN12 and 13 cells stably expressing GFP on a monolayer of 
HMVECs, with and without sPB1, silenced S4D, silenced Tiam1, or 
a Rac inhibitor. OSCC cells migrated through the layer of endothelial 
cells, mimicking invasion into a capillary bed or small blood vessel, 
except where S4D or Tiam1 were silenced or where Rac1 was 
inhibited (Figure 4B). These results are quantified in the bar graph in 
Figure 4C. Taken together, these results show that PB1-mediated 
activation of Rac1, occurring through S4D and Tiam1, results in a 
more rapidly growing and possibly more metastatic malignancy. </p>

<p>Protein Expression Profile in OSCC Biopsies </p>

<p>One possible way PB1 could be inducing a S4D signal in OSCC is 
through an autocrine or paracrine mechanism, resulting in Tiam1 
activation and more aggressive tumor behavior. For this to be true, 
OSCC would have to express all of these proteins simultaneously. We 
have previously shown that S4D is expressed at moderately high to 
high levels in a wide variety of carcinomas, and in particular in over 
80% of OSCC biopsies examined [17]. To look for the presence of 
Tiam1 and PB1 as well, we performed immunohistochemistry on 
these proteins, looking for their presence in 54 OSCC biopsies. We 
detected expression of both proteins in the same areas of tumor 
(representative examples are shown in Figure 5A). Among all samples 
analyzed, we recorded 75.6% and 86.8% that exhibited moderate to 
strong expression of PB1 and Tiam1, respectively (Figure 5B). 
Therefore, these proteins are expressed in most OSCC, confirming in 
vitro results obtained in the OSCC cell lines. </p>

<p>Expression of Functional, Full Length S4D in OSCC Leads to 
a More Metastatic Tumor </p>

<p>HN6 cells are one of the few OSCC cell lines that express very low 
levels of endogenous S4D [33]. Not coincidentally, they induce only 
a mild pro-angiogenic response and do not grow well as xenografts in 
nude mice, but growth potential can be rescued with forced S4D 
expression [33]. To determine the significance of the ability of the 
C-terminal segment of S4D to recruit Tiam1 for tumor metastasis, we 
took HN6 stably expressing luciferase and over expressed either full 
length S4D or the ΔC mutant, both of which would be capable of 
being shed and inducing angiogenesis [23], and injected then into the 
tail veins of immunocompromised (nude) mice. We tracked the 
development of lung lesions by bioluminescence (BLI). Mice injected 
with HN6 cells expressing full length S4D exhibited more and larger 
lung metastases by BLI than the ΔC mutants (Figure 6A). A 
measurement of the photons captured from lesions in all mice 
confirms these results (Figure 6B). Correlating with enhanced 
metastasis and larger tumor burden, mice injected with HN6 cells 
expressing full length S4D also exhibited a shortened life expectancy, 
as shown in the Kaplan-Meier curve (Figure 6C). </p>

<p>Discussion 
We have observed that S4D is strongly pro-angiogenic, similar to 
VEGF, and have shown that OSCC xenografts expressing high levels 
of S4D grow more rapidly than when it is silenced or otherwise 
inhibited [17]. Promotion of angiogenesis no doubt plays a role, as 
these tumors are invariably more vascular, but we could not rule out </p>

<p>autocrine or paracrine signaling between S4D and PB1 as having an 
effect on tumor cell proliferation, migration or metastasis. Indeed, 
there are numerous examples in the literature demonstrating a 
correlation between S4D and PB1 expression and tumor aggressive-
ness that do not specifically point to tumor-induced angiogenesis as 
being responsible [34-38]. While PB1 has been studied with regard 
to its expression, activity and tumor behavior [39], less is known 
about the reverse signaling pathways engaged by S4D and what effect 
this may have on cancer cells. 
Previous studies have shown that S4D is associated with the 
protein-tyrosine phosphatase CD45, helping to regulate T cell and B 
cell activation [24,25], and a cellular serine kinase activity, also in T 
cells [8]. We decided to examine reverse signaling not in immune cells 
but in cancer, using Mirrortree analysis to predict which protein or 
proteins may initiate reverse signaling, and then determining 
biological significance, if any. Tiam1 was a novel and interesting 
discovery because this Rac-specific GEF is associated with many 
cancer types [40]. Activation of Rac leads to a signaling cascade that 
generally supports tumor growth and invasion by inducing cell 
division and the formation of lamellipodia. For example, PAK is a part 
of this cascade, and its phosphorylation and activation is associated 
with activation of NF-κB, promotion of survival, and propagation 
through the cell cycle [40]. Specific to our studies, PAK activity is 
associated with aggressive tumor behavior and poor prognosis in head 
and neck cancer [41]. Interestingly, although we confirmed the 
binding of Tiam1 to S4D upon ligation with PB1, as well as the 
importance of the PDZ domain of Tiam1 for this interaction, the 
PDZ binding motif at the C-terminal portion of S4D was not 
necessary. Further detailed analysis will be required, though this 
might be difficult since the intracellular portion of S4D has no 
specific domain architecture to suggest sites for deletion or mutation, 
though it does possess Ser/Thr and Tyr consensus phosphorylation 
sites that may be involved in binding. 
We also show that recruitment of Tiam1 to S4D was significant in 
OSCC, as it led to Rac-dependent migration, invasion, cell division 
and transendothelial migration of cells in vitro, results suggestive of a 
more aggressive and possibly more metastatic tumor phenotype. This 
behavior was confirmed in a mouse model of metastasis. While we 
couldn't silence Rac or Tiam1 in OSCC cells without globally 
affecting cancer cell metabolism or express mutants of these proteins 
incapable of participating in S4D signaling in the presence of high 
levels of endogenous wild-type protein, we did identify a line of HN 
cells expressing low levels of S4D that are known to grow poorly in 
experimental animals [33], thus interrupting the S4D-Tiam1-Rac 
signaling axis at its most apical point and allowing for selective 
restoration with a truncated or full length form of S4D. HN6 cells 
expressing the full length S4D construct were more likely to form 
metastatic deposits in the lung compared to cells expressing the ΔC 
truncation mutant that could not recruit Tiam1 or activate Rac. 
In previous studies we examined the relative contributions of 
VEGF and S4D to tumor-induced angiogenesis and observed that 
when S4D was silenced in OSCC, tumors exhibited not only less 
vascularity but also a slightly greater reduction in proliferation, as 
determined by Ki-67 immunohistochemistry, compared to when 
VEGF was silenced [42]. At the time we suspected that more than just 
promotion of angiogenesis was the cause, since VEGF is potently 
pro-angiogenic (perhaps more so than S4D), and that expression of 
S4D might itself also promote proliferation. Here we demonstrate 
evidence supporting these suspicions, both in in vitro proliferation </p>

<p> 
Rac activation by Semaphorin 4D reverse signaling 
Zhou et al. 
Neoplasia Vol. 19, No. 2, 2017 </p>

<p>assays and when studying metastasis in mice, because both forms of 
S4D, full length and the ΔC truncation mutant, are still capable of 
being shed and acting on endothelial cells to promote angiogenesis, 
but only the full-length protein can signal to the cell expressing it, 
meaning any differences between these two populations in 
proliferation, invasion and metastasis would be due to Rac activation 
and its downstream effectors and not the tumor microenvironment. 
We will continue to investigate these findings in future experiments. 
In conclusion, we have identified a novel reverse signaling pathway 
acting through Tiam1 and Rac that promotes aggressive behavior in 
OSCC expressing S4D and PB1. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements 
The authors would like to thank Daniel Martin and Silvio Gutkind 
of the National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research, NIH, 
for contributing the head and neck cancer cell lines and assisting in 
the generation of shRNA lentiviruses, and Dr. Angeliki Malliri for 
the Tiam1 plasmid. This work was supported by the National 
Cancer Institute grant R01-CA133162 (J.R. B) and a National 
Institutes of Health grant 1K22CA143148 (M.G.K.). </p>



<p>Neoplasia Vol. 19, No. 2, 2017 
Rac activation by Semaphorin 4D reverse signaling 
Zhou et al. </p>



<p>
 
Rac activation by Semaphorin 4D reverse signaling 
Zhou et al. 
Neoplasia Vol. 19, No. 2, 2017 </p>

</text></tei>