<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5007093" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT The ubiquitin-proteasome system (UPS) influences gene transcription in multiple 
ways. One way in which the UPS affects transcription centers on transcriptional activators, the 
function of which can be stimulated by components of the UPS that also trigger their destruc-
tion. Activation of transcription by the yeast activator Gcn4, for example, is attenuated by 
mutations in the ubiquitin ligase that mediates Gcn4 ubiquitylation or by inhibition of the 
proteasome, leading to the idea that ubiquitin-mediated proteolysis of Gcn4 is required for 
its activity. Here we probe the steps in Gcn4 activity that are perturbed by disruption of the 
UPS. We show that the ubiquitylation machinery and the proteasome control different steps 
in Gcn4 function and that proteasome activity is required for the ability of Gcn4 to bind to its 
target genes in the context of chromatin. Curiously, the effect of proteasome inhibition on 
Gcn4 activity is suppressed by mutations in the ubiquitin-selective chaperone Cdc48, reveal-
ing that proteolysis per se is not required for Gcn4 activity. Our data highlight the role of 
Cdc48 in controlling promoter occupancy by Gcn4 and support a model in which ubiquity-
lation of activators-not their destruction-is important for function. </p>

<p>Regulated proteolysis by the ubiquitin (Ub)-proteasome system 
(UPS) is crucial for a myriad of processes, including control of gene 
transcription (Geng et al., 2012). In many cases, actions of the UPS 
in transcription follow the canonical paradigm in which ubiquitin li-
gases and the proteasome inhibit protein activity by reducing intra-
cellular levels of target proteins. In the case of transcriptional activa-
tors, however, a counterintuitive scenario can play out in which 
components of the UPS stimulate the function of the activators they 
destroy. Transcription factors such as Gal4 (Muratani et al., 2005; 
Collins et al., 2009), Gcn4 (Lipford et al., 2005), and nuclear hor-
mone receptors (Perissi et al., 2004), for example, have been shown 
to require their cognate Ub-ligases-and/or proteasomal proteoly-</p>

<p>sis-for full activity, suggesting that Ub-mediated turnover of activa-
tor proteins promotes their function. 
Precisely how ubiquitin-mediated destruction of an activator 
stimulates its activity is unclear. To account for the concept of how 
destruction of a protein could make it more active, we (Geng et al., 
2012) and others (Lipford et al., 2005) hypothesized that the require-
ment for the UPS in transcription reflects the need for activators to 
cycle on chromatin to drive multiple rounds of transcriptional activa-
tion. We proposed that activator ubiquitylation occurs on promoter 
DNAs after transcription has initiated and that the modified activa-
tor remains bound to chromatin in an inactive configuration that 
must be cleared by the proteasome in order for subsequent rounds 
of activation to occur. This model assumes that activator ubiquity-
lation and proteolysis converge on a single mechanistic step in the 
activation process and that there is no difference between blocking 
activator ubiquitylation and inhibiting activator destruction. More-
over, this model was developed at a time when little was known 
about the role of factors that lie between ubiquitylation and prote-
olysis, such as complexes containing the Ub-dependent chaperone 
Cdc48 (Meyer et al., 2012), which extract ubiquitylated substrates 
from protein complexes for proteasomal destruction. The potential 
effect of Cdc48 on activator function is particularly intriguing, as 
Cdc48 was recently shown to mediate proteolysis-independent 
stripping of a Ub-fusion activator from its target DNA sites in vivo 
(Ndoja et al., 2014). </p>

<p>Monitoring Editor 
Thomas Sommer 
Max Delbrück Center for 
Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>Received: Mar 22, 2016 
Revised: Jun 17, 2016 
Accepted: Jun 28, 2016 </p>

<p>This article was published online ahead of print in MBoC in Press (http://www 
.molbiolcell.org/cgi/doi/10.1091/mbc.E16-03-0192) on July 6, 2016. 
*Address correspondence to: William P. Tansey (william.p.tansey@vanderbilt 
.edu). </p>

<p>© 2016 Howard and Tansey. This article is distributed by The American Society for 
Cell Biology under license from the author(s). Two months after publication it is 
available to the public under an Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Un-
ported Creative Commons License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc 
-sa/3.0). 
"ASCB ® ," "The American Society for Cell Biology ® ," and "Molecular Biology of 
the Cell ® " are registered trademarks of The American Society for Cell Biology. </p>

<p>Abbreviations used: ChIP, chromatin immunoprecipitation; RT-qPCR, reverse-
transcription quantitative PCR; Ub, ubiquitin; UPS, ubiquitin-proteasome system. </p>

<p>Gregory C. Howard and William P. Tansey* </p>

<p>Department of Cell and Developmental Biology, Vanderbilt University School of Medicine, Nashville, TN 37232 </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION 
Full induction of Gcn4 target genes depends on SCF Cdc4 
and the proteasome </p>

<p>A previous study (Lipford et al., 2005) reported that activation of 
Gcn4 target genes is reduced by mutations in the Cdc34 and Cdc4 
components of the SCF Cdc4 Ub ligase (Chi et al., 2001), as well as by 
inhibition of proteasomal proteolysis. To confirm these findings, we 
monitored the effects of SCF Cdc4 or proteasome perturbation on ac-
tivation of Gcn4 target genes by sulfometuron methyl (SM), an agent 
that induces Gcn4 synthesis by blocking branched-chain amino acid 
production (Jia et al., 2000). Three sets of experiments were per-
formed. First, we asked whether temperature-sensitive mutations in 
Cdc34 or Cdc4 (Patton et al., 1998) affect expression of the Gcn4 
target gene ARG1. Here we found that shifting yeast to the restric-
tive temperature of 37°C reduced the expression of ARG1 in both 
the cdc34-2 (Figure 1A) and cdc4-1 (Figure 1B) strains. Second, we 
used the "anchor-away" technique (Haruki et al., 2008) to exclude 
Cdc34 from the nucleus via a rapamycin-induced interaction with a 
subunit of the ribosome. Here, treatment of the anchored Cdc34 
strain with rapamycin reduced the expression of ARG1 (Figure 1C) to 
a level comparable to that observed in the cdc34-2 strain. Finally, we 
combined point mutations in the tryptic and caspase sites of the 
proteasome (Heinemeyer et al., 1997) with 
MG132-mediated inhibition of the chymo-
tryptic site (Howard et al., 2012) to probe 
the effect of 20S proteasome inhibition on 
Gcn4 activity. Here, inhibition of proteasome 
activity blocked induction of ARG1 (Figure 
1D), as well as of ARG4 (Figure 1E) and HIS4 
(Figure 1F). Induction of Gcn4 protein by SM 
was not blocked by proteasome inhibition 
(Figure 1G), showing that this blockade is 
not at the level of Gcn4 synthesis. We did 
note, however, that proteasome inhibition 
promoted the accumulation of high-mole-
cular weight Gcn4 species in total cell ly-
sates, consistent with an increase in the level 
of ubiquitin-Gcn4 (Chi et al., 2001) or 
SUMO-Gcn4 (Rosonina et al., 2012) conju-
gates, or a combination of both. On the 
basis of these results, we conclude that in-
duction of Gcn4 target genes is sensitive to 
mutations in SCF Cdc4 and chemical-genetic 
inhibition of proteasomal proteolysis. </p>

<p>Proteasome inhibition disrupts the 
ability of Gcn4 to engage target gene 
chromatin </p>

<p>We next used chromatin immunoprecipita-
tion (ChIP) to quantify the effect of Cdc4 or 
proteasome inactivation on binding of hem-
agglutinin (HA) epitope-tagged Gcn4 to 
target gene promoters. Consistent with a 
previous study (Lipford et al., 2005), Gcn4 
binding to ARG1 was not different in the 
cdc4-1 strain versus its control strain at the 
restrictive temperature (Figure 2A). When 
we examined the effect of proteasome inhi-
bition, however, we discovered that binding 
of Gcn4 to the ARG1 UAS was disrupted 
by proteasome inhibition (Figure 2B). The 
failure of Gcn4 to bind chromatin was </p>

<p>The purpose of this study was to challenge the assumption that 
ubiquitylation and proteolysis target the same step in activator func-
tion and ask how Cdc48 features in the control of a native Saccharo-
myces cerevisiae transcriptional activator, Gcn4. Gcn4 is induced in 
response to amino acid starvation and drives the expression of 
genes encoding amino acid biosynthetic enzymes (Hinnebusch, 
2005). Like a majority of transcriptional activators, Gcn4 carries an 
overlapping transcriptional activation domain and degron (Geng 
et al., 2012) and is targeted for Ub-mediated proteolysis by the 
SCF Cdc4 Ub ligase (Chi et al., 2001). Of importance, genetic inhibi-
tion of SCF Cdc4 or inhibition of the proteasome reduces Gcn4 activ-
ity (Lipford et al., 2005), making Gcn4 an excellent focal point for our 
studies. 
Here we confirm that full activity of Gcn4 is dependent on both 
SCF Cdc4 and the proteasome but show that disrupting the function 
of each affects Gcn4 activity in different ways. We also show that 
inhibiting the proteasome blocks the ability of Gcn4 to bind target 
genes in vivo and that this phenotype is suppressed by mutations 
in Cdc48. These observations reveal that proteasomal proteolysis 
per se is not required for the function of Gcn4 and highlight the 
importance of Cdc48 in controlling the activity of a native yeast 
activator. </p>

<p>FIGURE 1: Stimulation of Gcn4 target genes by SCF Cdc4 and the proteasome. (A) CDC34 
(W303-1a) and cdc34-2 (MT670) yeast were grown to log phase at 30°C in minimal medium and 
then shifted to 37°C or maintained at 30°C for 1 h as indicated. Strains were then treated with 
SM or DMSO for 1.5 h, at which time RNA was collected and ARG1 mRNA levels quantified by 
RT-qPCR. Relative mRNA levels for ARG1 were normalized to the CDC34 strain treated with SM 
at 30°C. n = 3. (B) As in A, except using CDC4 (W303-1a) and cdc4-1 (MT668) strains. n = 3. 
(C) Anchor-away strains expressing HA-tagged Gcn4 (GHY139), FRB-tagged Cdc34 (GHY149), or 
FRB-tagged Gcn4 (GHY145) were grown to log phase in minimal medium, treated with either 
DMSO or rapamycin for 1 h, and then further treated with either DMSO or SM for 1.5 h. RNA 
was collected, and ARG1 mRNA levels were measured by RT-qPCR, as in A. Relative mRNA levels 
for ARG1 were normalized to the GCN4-HA strain treated with SM at 30°C. n = 3. (D-F) Yeast 
bearing the pup1-T30A pre3-T20A mutations (GHY010) were grown to log phase in minimal 
medium and treated with either DMSO or MG132 for 1 h. Strains were then treated with SM or 
DMSO for 1.5 h, at which time RNA was collected and ARG1 (D), ARG4 (E), and HIS4 
(F) mRNA levels quantified by RT-qPCR. Relative mRNA levels were then normalized to the 
SM-induced, DMSO-treated sample for each gene. n = 4. Error bars represent SEM. (G) Yeast 
expressing either native Gcn4 (GHY010) or HA-tagged Gcn4 (GHY025) were grown to log phase 
in minimal medium and treated with DMSO or MG132 for 1 h. Strains were then treated with SM 
or DMSO for 1.5 h, at which time protein was extracted, resolved by SDS-PAGE, and subject to 
Western blotting with antibodies against the HA epitope or β-actin (Act). </p>

<p>Volume 27 September 1, 2016 </p>

<p>Control of Gcn4 by the proteasome | 2737 </p>

<p>accompanied by loss of binding of the TATA box-binding protein 
TBP to the ARG1 TATA box (Figure 2B) and was not restricted to 
ARG1, as we observed the same phenomenon at UAS elements in 
another 10 Gcn4 target genes (Figure 2C). Of importance, there was 
no obvious alteration in the cellular distribution of Gcn4 in response 
to proteasome inhibition (Figure 2D and Supplemental Figure S1), 
demonstrating that Gcn4 remained in the nucleus under these con-
ditions but was unable to associate with target gene chromatin as 
measured by ChIP. 
Our finding that Gcn4 fails to associate with its cognate UAS ele-
ments when the proteasome is inhibited is at odds with a report by 
Lipford et al. (2005), who showed that Myc epitope-tagged Gcn4 
robustly binds its target genes in the presence of MG132. This dis-
crepancy raises the possibility that differential epitope tagging of 
Gcn4 is responsible for the disagreement between these studies. 
We therefore repeated our experiments with untagged Gcn4 using 
a polyclonal anti-Gcn4 antibody and with Myc-tagged Gcn4, as 
used in the Lipford et al. (2005) study. For untagged Gcn4 (Supple-
mental Figure S2A), we observed that proteasome inhibition re-
duced the level of Gcn4 binding at the ARG1 UAS to that observed 
in the uninduced state, mirroring the effect of proteasome inhibition 
on ARG1 gene induction (Figure 1D) and what we observed for HA-
tagged Gcn4 (Figure 2B). When we examined Myc-tagged Gcn4, 
however, we found that proteasome inhibition had little if any effect 
on its binding to the ARG1 UAS (Supplemental Figure S2B). These 
results are consistent with the Lipford et al. (2005) study but also 
demonstrate that Myc tagging of Gcn4 changes the behavior of the 
protein-as measured by ChIP-in a way that does not recapitulate 
that of the native Gcn4 protein. 
In sum, the contrasting effects of Cdc4 versus proteasome dis-
ruption on the ability of Gcn4 to bind DNA in vivo suggest that 
ubiquitylation and proteolysis influence distinct steps in Gcn4 func-
tion and that the profound effects of proteasome inhibition on Gcn4 
target gene induction result from a failure of Gcn4 to stably bind 
chromatin when proteasome function is blocked. </p>

<p>Proteasome inhibition does not act via the ArgR repressor 
or by modulating nucleosome occupancy </p>

<p>The simplest explanation for how proteasome inhibition disables 
the ability of Gcn4 to bind chromatin is that it induces a state on 
chromatin that is refractory to Gcn4 binding by either inducing an 
unstable repressor protein or perhaps altering nucleosome position-
ing. To address these possibilities, we first asked whether the ArgR 
repressor complex-which binds to DNA elements in the ARG pro-
moters and inhibits their transcription (Messenguy et al., 1991)-
mediates the effects of proteasome inhibition we observe. We 
found, however, that deletion of the gene encoding the Arg80 sub-
unit of this complex (Dubois et al., 1987) had no detectable effect </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Inhibiting the proteasome impedes the ability of Gcn4 to 
bind target gene chromatin. (A) CDC4 (W303-1a), CDC4 GCN4-HA 
(GHY107), cdc4-1 (MT668), and cdc4-1 GCN4-HA (GHY107) strains 
were grown to log phase at 30°C in minimal medium, shifted to the 
restrictive temperature of 37°C for 1 h, and then induced with SM for 
an additional 1.5 h. At this time, ChIP was performed with an antibody 
against the HA-epitope tag. Coprecipitating ARG1 promoter DNA 
was quantified by qPCR, expressed relative to the percentage of 
input DNA. n = 3. (B) GCN4-HA (GHY025) yeast were grown to log </p>

<p>phase at 30°C in minimal medium, treated with either DMSO or 
MG132 for 1 h, and induced with SM for 1.5 h. ChIP was performed 
using antibodies against the HA-epitope tag or TBP. Coprecipitating 
ARG1 promoter DNA was quantified by qPCR. n = 3. (C) As in B, 
except that coprecipitating DNAs from the anti-HA ChIP were 
quantified by qPCR, using primer pairs that amplify Gcn4-binding 
sites in the indicated genes. n = 3. Error bars represent SEM. 
(D) GCN4-GFP HTB2-mCherry (GHY339) yeast were grown to log 
phase at 30°C in minimal medium, treated with either DMSO or 
MG132 for 1 h, and induced with SM for 1.5 h. Samples were imaged 
using either fluorescence (top) or differential interference contrast 
microscopy (bottom). Scale bars, 5 μm. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>(Figure 4, E and F). Suppression of the effects of proteasome inhibi-
tion on Gcn4 activity in the cdc48-3 strain is due to the mutations in 
CDC48, as expression of wild-type Cdc48 in this strain background 
restored proteasome sensitivity (Figure 4G). The ability of mutations 
in Cdc48 to suppress the effects of proteasome inhibition supports 
the concept that proteasome inhibition drives the accumulation of </p>

<p>on the sensitivity of ARG1 to proteasome inhibition (Figure 3A), ex-
cluding the possibility that accumulation of this known repressor 
complex inhibits Gcn4 when proteasome function is blocked. 
We next performed nucleosome scanning analysis (Sekinger 
et al., 2005) to ask whether proteasome inhibition alters nucleo-
some occupancy across the ARG1 (Figure 3B) and HIS4 (Figure 3C) 
genes. Consistent with a previous report (Crisucci and Arndt, 2012), 
we found that Gcn4-binding sites in the ARG1 (Figure 3B) and HIS4 
(Figure 3C) promoters lack nucleosomes and that SM induction re-
duces the density of nucleosomes within the transcribed portions of 
ARG1 and HIS4, as expected when their transcription is induced. 
Proteasome inhibition increased the levels of nucleosomes across 
the ARG1 and HIS4 open reading frames-again consistent with a 
decrease in transcriptional activity-but had no detectable effect on 
nucleosome position or density across the "nucleosome-free" re-
gion bound by Gcn4. Of interest, nucleosome density at the HIS4-
adjacent gene BIK1, which is not regulated by Gcn4, is markedly 
increased in response to MG132, demonstrating that proteasome 
function is involved in mediating some aspect of nucleosome dy-
namics that is yet to be described. In terms of Gcn4, however, these 
data exclude the notion that accumulation of nucleosomes in re-
sponse to proteasome inhibition mediates the failure of Gcn4 to 
access its cognate sites on chromatin. </p>

<p>Mutation of Cdc48 suppresses the effects of proteasome 
inhibition on Gcn4 activity </p>

<p>Our data support the concept that ubiquitylation and proteolysis 
play distinct roles in controlling Gcn4 activity. One possibility is that 
ubiquitylation of chromatin-bound Gcn4 stimulates a step in the ac-
tivation process but that once Gcn4 is ubiquitylated, it is unable to 
stably associate with chromatin. In this scenario, proteasome inhibi-
tion could force Gcn4 to accumulate off chromatin via the accrual of 
ubiquitylated Gcn4 species. Indeed, direct analysis of Gcn4-Ub 
conjugates via the His-Ub method (Yaglom et al., 1996) revealed 
that proteasome inhibition promotes a striking increase in the level 
of ubiquitylated Gcn4 protein (Figure 4A), suggesting that accumu-
lation of Ub conjugates could underlie the defects in Gcn4 function 
we observe when the proteasome is inhibited. 
We attempted to challenge this notion by producing a form of 
Gcn4 that cannot be ubiquitylated. We engineered alanine-substi-
tution mutations in Gcn4 (Supplemental Figure S3A) that block 
phosphorylation events required for ubiquitylation by SCF Cdc4 (Chi 
et al., 2001). Unfortunately, this form of Gcn4 still accumulated a 
single Ub-conjugated form in response to proteasome inhibition 
(Supplemental Figure S3B) and remained sensitive to proteasome 
inhibition (Supplemental Figure S3, C and D). We also constructed a 
version of Gcn4 in which all 23 lysine residues are simultaneously 
mutated to arginine (K0). Although this mutation blocked the ubiq-
uitylation of Gcn4 (Supplemental Figure S3E), we were unable to 
detect binding of K0 Gcn4 to the UAS of ARG1 by ChIP (Supple-
mental Figure S3F) and thus did not pursue this mutant further. 
Instead, we considered the possibility that the Gcn4-Ub conju-
gates that accumulate in response to proteasome inhibition are re-
moved from chromatin by Cdc48, as previously reported for a Ub-
fusion activator (Ndoja et al., 2014). Coimmunoprecipitation assays 
demonstrated that Gcn4 interacts with Cdc48 (Figure 4B) and that 
this interaction is disrupted by the K0 mutation in Gcn4, which dis-
rupts ubiquitylation (Figure 4B). Moreover, a temperature-sensitive 
mutant of CDC48 (cdc48-3; Sato and Hampton, 2006), assayed at 
the semipermissive temperature, suppressed the effects of protea-
some inhibition on transcription at both ARG1 and HIS4 (Figure 4, C 
and D), as well as restored binding of Gcn4 to these genes </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: The effect of proteasome inhibition on Gcn4 activity is not 
mediated via the ArgR repressor or changes in nucleosome 
occupancy. (A) GCN4 ARG80 (GHY010), gcn4 ARG80 (GHY004), 
GCN4 arg80 (GHY081), and gcn4 arg80 (GHY079) strains were grown 
to log phase in minimal medium and treated with DMSO or MG132. 
After 1 h, strains were treated with DMSO or SM for 1.5 h and RNA 
harvested, and ARG1 mRNA levels were quantified by RT-qPCR. Each 
qPCR was normalized to the SM-treated GCN4 ARG80 sample. Error 
bars represent SEM. n = 4. (B) GCN4 yeast (GHY010) were grown to 
log phase at 30°C in minimal medium, treated with DMSO or MG132, 
and induced with SM or a DMSO control for an additional 1.5 h, and 
nucleosome occupancy was mapped by MNase digestion, coupled 
with tiled primer sets spanning ARG1. qPCR data were normalized to 
the signal from a GAL1-10 promoter-localized nucleosome. Data 
points represent an average of two independent experiments. (C) As 
in B, except monitoring nucleosome positioning surrounding the HIS4 
locus. Data points represent an average of two independent 
experiments. </p>

<p>Volume 27 September 1, 2016 </p>

<p>Control of Gcn4 by the proteasome | 2739 </p>

<p>Gcn4-Ub conjugates that are prevented from stably binding chro-
matin by Cdc48. 
In addition to suppressing defects associated with proteasome 
inhibition, we observed that the cdc48-3 mutation increased levels 
of Gcn4 target gene activity in the absence of MG132 (Figure 4, C 
and D). This result contrasts with our report that Cdc48 stimulates 
the activity of the yeast activator Gal4 (Bonizec et al., 2014). To con-
firm that Gcn4 and Gal4 are affected differently by the cdc48-3 mu-
tation, we examined Gal4 activity in the cdc48-3 mutant strain; we 
also examined the effect of GAL80 deletion in this context, which 
has been argued to be a point of Gal4 regulation by the UPS (Ang 
et al., 2012). Supporting our previous study (Bonizec et al., 2014), 
mutation of Cdc48 reduced activation of the GAL10 locus (Figure 
4H), whereas the GAL80 deletion did not affect the sensitivity of 
GAL10 transcription to the cdc48-3 mutation. Thus, despite many 
parallels in how Gcn4 and Gal4 are regulated by the UPS, the effect 
of Cdc48 on the function of these two activators is different. Further 
work will be required to determine the mechanistic basis for the dif-
ferences between Gcn4 and Gal4 in terms of the role that Cdc48 
plays in their function. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In this study, we confirmed the importance of an intact UPS to the 
ability of Gcn4 to activate transcription of select target genes but 
made the surprising discovery that ubiquitylation and proteasomal 
destruction appear to control distinct steps in the activation process. 
On one hand, disrupting the activity of the SCF Cdc4 Ub ligase re-
duces the expression of Gcn4 target genes via a process that is most 
likely downstream of target gene recognition by Gcn4, as previously 
suggested (Lipford et al., 2005). On the other hand, inhibition of the 
proteasome inhibits Gcn4 target gene activation at a step that is 
apparently upstream of chromatin recognition by Gcn4 and in a 
manner that can be suppressed by a mutation in the Ub-selective </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: Mutation of Cdc48 suppresses the effect of proteasome 
inhibition on Gcn4 activity. (A) GCN4-HA (GHY356) yeast carrying a 
copper-inducible His-Ub expression plasmid (pUB221) were grown to 
log phase in minimal medium and treated with CuSO 4 and DMSO or 
MG132 for 1 h. Yeast were induced with SM or DMSO for an additional 
1.5 h, at which time protein lysates were collected under denaturing 
conditions. Ubiquitin-conjugates were captured by nickel-resin 
(Ni-NTA) chromatography, resolved by SDS-PAGE, and probed for 
HA-tagged Gcn4 protein by Western blotting. A sample of the input 
material to the nickel resin was also probed for HA-tagged Gcn4. IB, </p>

<p>immunoblot. (B) GCN4 CDC48-MYC (GHY285), GCN4-HA CDC48 
(GHY025), GCN4-HA CDC48-MYC (GHY287), K0-GCN4-HA CDC48 
(GHY124), and K0-GCN4-HA CDC48-MYC (GHY293) yeast were grown 
to log phase at 30°C in minimal medium and treated with DMSO or 
MG132. After 1 h, Gcn4 was induced with SM for 1.5 h. Protein lysates 
were collected and Gcn4-HA immunoprecipitated (IP) via an anti-HA 
antibody, and IPs were probed with antibodies against the Myc-
epitope (Cdc48) and HA-epitope (Gcn4) tags. A sample of the input 
material to the IP was also probed for Myc-tagged Cdc48. 
(C, D). CDC48 (RHY2455) and cdc48-3 (RHY2457) strains were grown 
to log phase at 30°C in minimal medium and treated with DMSO or 
MG132. After 1 h, strains were treated with DMSO or SM for 1.5 h, 
RNA harvested, and processed as described to measure mRNA levels 
from the ARG1 (C) and HIS4 (D) loci. n = 4. (E, F). CDC48 GCN4-HA 
(GHY116) and cdc48-3 GCN4-HA (GHY118) strains were grown to log 
phase at 30°C in minimal medium, treated with either DMSO or 
MG132 for 1 h, and induced with SM for 1.5 h. ChIP was then 
performed using antibodies against the HA-epitope tag. 
Coprecipitating ARG1 (E) or HIS4 (F) promoter DNAs were quantified 
by qPCR, expressed relative to the percentage of input DNA. n = 3. 
(G) CDC48 (RHY2455), cdc48-3 (RHY2457), and cdc48-3::CDC48 
(GHY279) strains were grown and treated as described in C and RNA 
harvested, and RT-qPCR was performed to quantify ARG1 transcripts. 
n = 3. (H) CDC48 GAL80 (RHY2455), cdc48-3 GAL80 (RHY2457), CDC48 
gal80 (GHY304), and cdc48-3 gal80 (GHY305) yeast were grown in 
raffinose medium and treated with water or 2% galactose for 1.5 h. 
RNA was collected and used for RT-qPCR for GAL10. Each qPCR was 
internally normalized to ACT1 and then normalized to the galactose-
treated CDC48 GAL80 sample. Error bars represent SEM. n = 3. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>RNA isolation and analysis </p>

<p>For Gcn4-based experiments, yeast were grown overnight in yeast 
extract/peptone/adenine/dextrose (YPAD), washed with sterile wa-
ter, and diluted to an OD 600 of 0.3 in minimal medium (0.67% yeast 
nitrogen base without amino acids and 2% dextrose, supplemented 
with amino acids as appropriate). Yeast were grown for 5 h and 
treated with 0.5 μg/ml SM (or dimethyl sulfoxide [DMSO] control) 
before RNA was harvested by the hot-phenol method (Leung et al., 
2011). If proteasome inhibition was part of the experiment, yeast 
were grown for 4 h and treated with 50 μM MG132 (or DMSO con-
trol) plus 0.004% SDS (Liu et al., 2007) for 1 h before SM induction. 
For anchor-away experiments, yeast were grown for 4 h in minimal 
medium and treated with 1.0 μg/ml rapamycin (or DMSO control) 
for 1 h before SM induction. For Gal4-based experiments, yeast 
were grown overnight in YPAD, washed with sterile water, and di-
luted to an OD 600 of 0.3 in CSM-RAF medium (0.67% yeast nitrogen 
base without amino acids, 2% raffinose) supplemented with CSM. 
After 5 h, cultures were induced with 2% galactose for 90 min before 
RNA was isolated. In all cases, mRNA levels were quantified by re-
verse-transcription quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR) as described (Leung 
et al., 2011) and normalized to an ACT1 primer pair. Supplemental 
Table S2 lists primer sequences. </p>

<p>Western blotting, coimmunoprecipitation, 
and ubiquitylation assays </p>

<p>For Western blotting, yeast pellets were resuspended in buffer A (6 M 
guanidine-HCl, 0.1 M Na 2 HPO 4 /NaH 2 PO 4 , pH 8.0, 10 mM Imidazole) 
to a final OD 600 of ∼150, and proteins were extracted by bead beat-
ing. For each protein preparation, 20 μg was ethanol precipitated to 
remove guanidine, resolved by SDS-PAGE, and transferred to nitro-
cellulose membranes. Membranes were probed using the appropri-
ate antibodies: anti-HA-horseradish peroxidase (HRP; 12013819001; 
Roche, Basel, Switzerland), anti-c-Myc-HRP (11814150001; Roche), or 
anti-β-actin (ab8224; Abcam, Cambridge, MA). For coimmunopre-
cipitation assays, cell pellets from 100-ml cultures were resuspended 
in 800 μl of yeast lysis buffer (10 mM Na 2 HPO 4 /NaH 2 PO 4 , pH 8.0, 
150 mM NaCl, 2 mM EDTA, 0.1% NP-40, 50 mM NaF, 0.1 mM 
Na 3 VO 4 , 1× Roche Complete, EDTA-free Protease Inhibitor Cocktail; 
0.4 mg/ml Pefabloc SC, 50 μM MG132, 2 mg/ml iodoacetamide, and 
200 μM 1,10-phenanthroline). Cells were lysed by bead beating at 
4°C for 40 s, followed by incubation in ice water for 2 min, for a total 
of five times. Cell lysate was collected and cleared by centrifugation. 
Immunoprecipitation reactions were performed using the anti-HA an-
tibody 12CA5 as described (Daulny et al., 2008). Ubiquitylation as-
says were performed using the His-tagged Ub method essentially as 
described (Daulny et al., 2008). Copper-inducible, His-tagged Ub 
was expressed from the plasmid pUB221 (Yaglom et al., 1996). </p>

<p>Chromatin immunoprecipitation </p>

<p>For each reaction, 100-ml cultures of yeast were processed as de-
scribed for RNA isolation and analysis and cross-linked with 1% 
formaldehyde, and ChIP was performed as described (Geng and 
Tansey, 2012). The 12CA5 anti-HA antibody, 9E10 anti-Myc anti-
body, anti-Gcn4 antibody (sc-50443; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, 
Dallas, TX), or anti-TBP antibody (a gift from P. A. Weil, Vanderbilt 
University, Nashville, TN), was used to immunoprecipitate chromatin 
as indicated. Coprecipitating DNAs were quantified by qPCR using 
primer sets that amplify TATA box-proximal Gcn4-binding sites in 
each gene (for detection of Gcn4-promoter interaction) or the TATA 
box of the ARG1 gene. In each case, signal is calculated as equiva-
lent to percentage of the input to the ChIP reaction. Primer se-
quences are listed in Supplemental Table S2. </p>

<p>chaperone Cdc48. Although we have been unable to test whether 
the actions of SCF Cdc4 and the proteasome in this context are medi-
ated directly on Gcn4, the simplest conclusion from these data is 
that ubiquitylation of Gcn4 stimulates two distinct processes, pro-
moting the inherent transcriptional activity of the protein while at 
the same time limiting activation by triggering the Cdc48-mediated 
extraction of Gcn4 from target gene promoters. In this way, disrup-
tion of SCF Cdc4 reduces the level of Gcn4-target gene transcription 
without affecting Gcn4-promoter binding, whereas proteasome in-
hibition promotes the accumulation of ubiquitylated Gcn4, which is 
then either stripped off chromatin or prevented from stably binding 
once it dissociates (Supplemental Figure S4). 
The foregoing scenario is thematically similar to the previously 
proposed "licensing" (Salghetti et al., 2001) and "Ub-clock" (Wu 
et al., 2007) models, in that activator ubiquitylation sets an inherent 
limitation on the functional lifetime of transcriptional activators but 
differs profoundly in the role of proteasomal proteolysis in this pro-
cess. Indeed, the ability to suppress the effect of proteasome inhibi-
tion on Gcn4 activity by inactivation of Cdc48 strongly implies that 
proteasomal proteolysis per se cannot play a positive role in Gcn4-
mediated transcriptional activation, irrespective of whether Gcn4 or 
some other factor is the relevant substrate. Instead, the effects of 
proteasome inhibition on Gcn4 must be indirect, perhaps a result of 
the accumulation of ubiquitylated Gcn4 species, as we propose. A 
revised view of how the proteasome features in transcriptional acti-
vation is more consistent with work from the Laney (Wilcox and 
Laney, 2009) and Yao (Ndoja et al., 2014) laboratories, which pin-
point Cdc48-mediated extraction of ubiquitylated activators as a 
limiting point in the activation process, and implies that the wide-
spread and intimate relationship between activation and destruc-
tion elements in transcription factors (Salghetti et al., 2000; Geng 
et al., 2012), if anything, reflects the functional importance of activa-
tor ubiquitylation over destruction. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Yeast manipulations </p>

<p>Yeast strains are described in Supplemental Table S1. Gene dele-
tions were performed via homologous recombination using PCR-
amplified auxotrophic markers or antibiotic resistance genes from 
plasmids, as indicated. Epitope tagging of endogenous loci was 
performed similarly (Knop et al., 1999; Sheff and Thorn, 2004). 
mCherry tagging of endogenous Htb2 was performed as described 
except using an mCherry-tagging cassette amplified from SWY5678 
genomic DNA (Lord et al., 2015). Strains carrying the 3T2S-GCN4 
allele were generated through deletion of endogenous GCN4 with 
the URA3 cassette followed by insertion of PCR-amplified 3T2S-
GCN4 through homologous recombination. PCR genotyping was 
used to confirm all genomic manipulations. Replacement of the 
cdc48-3 allele for wild-type CDC48 was performed through homol-
ogous recombination of a PCR fragment encoding wild-type CDC48 
and spanning the sites of the two mutations in cdc48-3 (P257L, 
R387K). Colonies were selected for ability to grow at the restrictive 
temperature of 37°C, and restoration of the wild-type CDC48 se-
quence was confirmed by PCR amplification of the locus and Sanger 
DNA sequencing. For anchor-away strains, epitope tagging of 
GCN4 and deletion of PDR5 were performed as described. CDC34 
and GCN4 were tagged with FKBP12-rapamycin-binding domain 
(FRB) as described for epitope tagging except using an FRB-tag-
ging construct (Haruki et al., 2008). A high-efficiency yeast transfor-
mation protocol was used for genomic manipulations and introduc-
tion of plasmids (Gietz and Schiestl, 2007). Supplemental Table S2 
lists primer sequences. </p>

<p>Volume 27 September 1, 2016 </p>

<p>Control of Gcn4 by the proteasome | 2741 </p>

<p><rs type="software">ImageJ</rs></p>

<p>Micrococcal nuclease protection assay </p>

<p>The micrococcal nuclease (MNase) protection assay was performed 
as described (Crisucci and Arndt, 2012). Briefly, 185-ml yeast cul-
tures were processed as described for RNA isolation and analysis 
and cross-linked with a final concentration of 2% formaldehyde 
while being shaken at 30°C for 30 min. Formaldehyde was quenched 
with glycine, cells collected, and spheroplasts prepared by Zymoly-
ase treatment. Spheroplasts (300 μl) were treated with increasing 
concentrations of MNase (10107921001; Roche) at 0, 1.0, 2.5, 5.0, 
10, or 20 U MNase at 37°C for 45 min on a nutator. Reactions were 
stopped by addition of SDS (1% final concentration) and EDTA (10 
mM final concentration), DNA purified by phenol-chloroform extrac-
tion, and recovered by ethanol precipitation. The efficiency of each 
MNase digestion was determined using a qPCR primer set flanking 
a region in the GAL1-10 upstream activating sequence (UAS) pro-
tected from MNase digestion by a nucleosome and a primer set 
flanking a region in the GAL1-10 UAS not protected from MNase 
digestion. Samples with MNase digestion efficiency of ∼95% were 
used for subsequent qPCR analysis using tiled primer sets. Primer 
sequences are listed in Supplemental Table S2. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank R. Adams, K. Arndt, L. Burns, R. Deshaies, D. Finley, M. 
Funk, R. Hampton, S. Lorey, J. MacGurn, and P. A. Weil for reagents 
and experimental assistance. We thank R. Deshaies, A. Weissmiller, 
P. A. Weil, and S. Wenzel for advice and guidance. This work is sup-
ported by National Institutes of Health Grant GM067728 and 
Vanderbilt Ingram Cancer Center Support Grant P30CA68485. </p>



</text></tei>