<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5225149" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background and Aims: The role of miR-34a in hepatocellular 
carcinoma (HCC) is controversial and several unresolved 
issues remain, including its expression pattern and relevance 
to tumor etiology, tumor stage and prognosis, and finally, its 
impact on apoptosis. Methods: miR-34a expression was 
assessed in hepatitis C virus (HCV)-induced non-metastatic 
HCC tissues by RT-Q-PCR. Huh-7 cells were transfected with 
miR-34a mimics and the impact of miR-34a was examined on 
84 pro-apoptotic/anti-apoptotic genes using PCR array; its net 
effect was tested on cell viability via MTT assay. Results: miR-
34a expression was up-regulated in HCC tissues. Moreover, 
miR-34a induced a large set of pro-apoptotic/anti-apoptotic 
genes, with a net result of triggering apoptosis and repressing 
cell viability. Conclusions: HCC-related differential expression 
of miR-34a could be etiology-based or stage-specific, and low 
expression of miR-34a may predict poor prognosis. This study's 
findings also emphasize the role of miR-34a in apoptosis. 
Introduction </p>

<p>microRNA (miR)-34a has emerged as an important miR in 
comprehensive research studies, and numerous studies have 
proposed its considerable impact on cell proliferation and 
survival. 
1 miR-34a has several experimentally validated 
downstream target genes involved in cell cycle regulation, 
including NMYC, 
2 CCND1, 
3 CCNE2, CDK4, CDK6, 
4 and 
C-MET. 
4,5 These genes promote cells to proceed through G1 
phase into S phase via the Rb-E2F signaling pathway, and </p>

<p>ectopic expression of miR-34a was shown to induce cell cycle 
arrest in the G1 phase. 
6 Moreover, it was reported that over-
expression of miR-34a could down-regulate CDC25C and 
phosphorylated CDC2 expression, which in turn inhibits cell 
proliferation via cell cycle G2 phase arrest. 
7,8 miR-34a was 
reported to directly target YY1, a negative regulator of the 
tumor suppressor p53, 
9 and induce apoptosis in neuroblas-
toma cell lines. 
10 Furthermore, miR-34a ectopic expression in 
breast cancer cells suppressed cell proliferation and invasion, 
and induced apoptosis, and miR-34a expression was found 
to be inversely correlated to BCL-2 and SIRT1 expression. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>In hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC), two independent 
studies reported that miR-34a had no impact on apoptosis. </p>

<p>5,12 </p>

<p>On the contrary, another research group showed that miR-34a 
increased caspase-3 and -7 activity and induced apoptosis. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Thus, the role of miR-34a in apoptosis in HCC is ambiguous. 
Another controversial aspect of miR-34a regards its pattern of 
expression and its relevance to the tumor etiology and stage. 
miR-34a was found to exhibit a different pattern of expression 
in hepatitis C virus (HCV)-related HCC 
14 than in hepatitis B 
virus (HBV)-induced HCC. 
5,15 In addition, the expression 
level of miR-34a was found to vary between HCC tissues in 
clinical TNM stages III and IV as compared to that in stages I 
and II. 
13 It was also reported that metastatic HCC tissues 
showed a significantly different miR-34a expression profile 
compared to non-metastatic tissues. 
5,13 Despite these con-
troversies, miR-34a has entered phase I clinical trials for 
liver cancer. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Thus, in this study, we first aimed to elucidate the 
discrepancies regarding miR-34a expression pattern via inves-
tigating miR-34a expression in a cohort of patients with HCV-
progressed non-metastatic HCC. Then, we aimed at dissecting 
the potentially related apoptotic pathways through investigat-
ing the impact of miR-34a on several downstream apoptotic 
and anti-apoptotic genes in HCC. Finally, we assessed the net 
impact of miR-34a on cell viability. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study patients </p>

<p>This study comprised 22 HCC patients who underwent liver 
transplant surgery at the Kasr El Ainy Hospital, Cairo </p>

<p> 
Journal of Clinical and Translational Hepatology 2016 vol. 4 | 300-305 </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial 4.0 Unported License, 
permitting all non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Keywords: MicroRNA; Hepatocellular carcinoma; Apoptosis; PCR array. 
Abbreviations: miRNA or miR, microRNA; HCC, hepatocellular carcinoma; HCV, 
hepatitis C virus; HBV, hepatitis B virus. 
Received: 24 August 2016; Revised: 29 November 2016; Accepted: 22 December 
2016 
q DOI: 10.14218/JCTH.2016.00031. </p>

<p>*Correspondence to: Ahmed Ihab Abdelaziz, School of Medicine, Health Sciences 
Research Center (HSRC), New Giza University (NGU), Office: 2.26, New Giza km 22 
Cairo-Alex desert road, Cairo 11835, Egypt. Tel: +20-2-38277847, E-mail: aihab@ 
ngu.edu.eg </p>

<p>University, Egypt. In addition, 19 healthy liver biopsies were 
obtained. The healthy liver tissues were obtained from liver 
donors who volunteered for lobar transplantation surgery for 
HCC patients. Healthy livers represented non-cirrhotic tissues, 
and all donors were negative for HCV and HBV infection. 
Written consent, from both the patient and the donor, to take 
liver tissues during the transplantation was obtained prior 
to the surgery. Patients were subjected to clinical assessment 
(results presented in Table 1). HCC was diagnosed in all 
patients by examining the stage and grade of the tumor. 
Liver function enzymes (aspartate aminotransferase, alanine 
aminotransferase, and alkaline phosphatase) and albumin 
levels in serum were measured. Also the presence of hepato-
tropic infections, such as presence of HCV or HBV, was 
checked. All patients were confirmed as non-metastatic with 
no extra-hepatic manifestations and no vascular invasion, 
in order to comply with the expanded Milan criteria (UCSF 
criteria) for liver transplantation (i.e. single tumor of &lt;6.5 cm 
in diameter, or 2 or 3 tumors, each of #4.5 cm in diameter or 
with total tumor diameter #8 cm) as shown in Table 2. The 
majority of the patients (63.6%) had more than one focal 
lesion, as indicated in the pathology report. All experiments 
were performed in compliance with the guidelines of the Insti-
tutional Review Board of Kasr El Ainy Medical School in Cairo 
University and the ethical committee of the German University 
in Cairo and in accordance to the ethical standards of the 
Declaration of Helsinki. </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>Huh-7 cells were maintained in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's 
medium (DMEM) (Lonza, Switzerland) supplemented with 
4.5 g/L glucose, 4 mmol/L L-glutamine, 10% fetal bovine 
serum, 1% penicillin/streptomycin and Mycozap (1:500; 
Lonza) at 37 
8 C in 5% CO 2 atmosphere. </p>

<p>Transfection of miRNA oligonucleotides </p>

<p>Huh-7 cell lines were transfected with miR-34a mimics 
(Catalog #MSY0000255; Qiagen, Germany). Transfection 
experiments were carried out in triplicate, using the HiPerfect 
Transfection Reagent (Qiagen) according to the manufac-
turer's protocol which called for 37.5 ng oligonucleotides for 
Huh-7 cells transfected in a 24-well plate; the experiment was 
repeated 3 times. Cells that were only exposed to transfection 
reagent are designated as Mock cells, while cells transfected 
with miR-34a mimics are designated as miR-34a cells. </p>

<p>mRNA and miRNA extraction </p>

<p>Total cellular mRNA and miRNA were extracted from the liver 
biopsies. Fresh liver samples (HCC and healthy tissues) were 
collected during surgery and snap-frozen immediately in 
liquid nitrogen. The specimens were then manually pulverized 
in liquid nitrogen and approximately 100 mg of tissue powder 
was used for large and small RNA extraction with the mirVana 
miRNA Isolation Kit (Ambion, USA), according to the manu-
facturer's protocol. 
For extraction of total cellular mRNA from cultured cells, 
Huh-7 cells were harvested 48 hours post-transfection and 
lysed using Bizol Reagent (Invitrogen). Chloroform was added 
and the aqueous phase containing the RNA was collected. 
RNA was precipitated using isopropyl alcohol. The RNA pellet </p>

<p>Table 1. Clinical characteristics of the 22 hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) 
patients </p>

<p>Age: mean 
49 6 13.5 </p>

<p>range 
35.5-62.5 </p>

<p>Sex: male/female 
21/1 </p>

<p>Aspartate 
aminotransferase (U/L) </p>

<p>100.5 6 65.8 </p>

<p>Alanine aminotransferase 
(U/L) </p>

<p>85.6 6 95.6 </p>

<p>Alkaline Phosphatase (U/L) 
110.2 6 60.7 </p>

<p>Serum albumin (g/dL) 
4.6 6 1.5 </p>

<p>Serum alpha-fetoprotein 
(ng/mL) </p>

<p>155.7 6 22.3 </p>

<p>HCV status </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>100% (22 HCC patients) </p>

<p>HBV status </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>18.2% (4/22 HCC 
patients) </p>

<p>a HCV status was determined using anti-HCV antibody and/or HCV viral RNA </p>

<p>quantification. 
b HBV status was determined using anti-HBc and anti-HBs antibodies and by </p>

<p>detection of HBsAg. </p>

<p>Table 2. Number/sizes of focal lesions according to expanded Milan 
criteria </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>Number of 
focal lesions 
Size of focal lesions </p>

<p>Patient 1 
Unifocal 
2.5 cm </p>

<p>Patient 2 
3 focal lesions 
2 cm, 2.5 cm and 3 cm </p>

<p>Patient 3 
3 focal lesions 
2 cm, 2 cm and 3.5 cm </p>

<p>Patient 4 
Unifocal 
1.5 3 2 cm </p>

<p>Patient 5 
3 focal lesions 
3 3 4 cm, 1 cm and 1 cm </p>

<p>Patient 6 
Unifocal 
4 cm </p>

<p>Patient 7 
3 focal lesions 
4 cm, 1 cm and 1 cm </p>

<p>Patient 8 
3 focal lesions 
1 cm, 1 cm and 1.5 cm </p>

<p>Patient 9 
Unifocal 
2.5 cm </p>

<p>Patient 10 
2 focal lesions 
1 cm and 1.7 cm </p>

<p>Patient 11 
3 focal lesions 
1 cm each </p>

<p>Patient 12 
Unifocal 
3 cm </p>

<p>Patient 13 
3 focal lesions 
3 cm, 1.5 cm and 2 cm </p>

<p>Patient 14 
3 focal lesions 
1 cm, 1 cm and 4 cm </p>

<p>Patient 15 
2 focal lesions 
3 cm and 1.5 cm </p>

<p>Patient 16 
2 focal lesions 
1.5 cm and 3 cm </p>

<p>Patient 17 
3 focal lesions 
2.5 cm, 2.5 cm and 1.5 cm </p>

<p>Patient 18 
3 focal lesions 
1.5 cm, 1 cm and 1 cm </p>

<p>Patient 19 
Unifocal 
2 cm </p>

<p>Patient 20 
Unifocal 
1.5 cm </p>

<p>Patient 21 
3 focal lesions 
3 cm, 2.5 cm and 1 cm </p>

<p>Patient 22 
Unifocal 
3 cm </p>

<p>Journal of Clinical and Translational Hepatology 2016 vol. 4 | 300-305 </p>

<p>
Yacoub R. et al: miR-34a in HCC </p>

<p>was then washed using 75% ethanol and dissolved in DPEC-
treated water. </p>

<p>RNA concentration and integrity </p>

<p>RNA concentration was measured using a NanoDrop spectro-
photometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA) and was found to 
be &gt;500 ng/mL. In addition, RNA integrity was confirmed by 
18S rRNA band detection on 1% agarose gel electrophoresis. 
RNA samples with optical density (260/280) of &gt;2 were 
excluded from the study. </p>

<p>miRNA and mRNA quantification by TaqMan Real-Time 
Q-PCR </p>

<p>The miRNA extracted from liver tissues was reverse tran-
scribed into single-stranded cDNA using the TaqMan 
® Micro-
RNA Reverse Transcription Kit (ABI, USA) with specific primers 
for hsa-miR-34a and RNU6B. Relative expression of miR-34a 
and RNU6B (internal control for normalization) was quantified 
using TaqMan Real-Time Q-PCR (ABI Assay IDs: 000426 and 
001093, respectively) with the StepOne™ Real-Time PCR 
System (ABI). Relative expression was calculated using the 
2 
−DDCT method. All PCR reactions, including controls, were 
run in duplicate. </p>

<p>PCR array </p>

<p>Total RNA extracted from Huh-7 cells was reverse transcribed 
into cDNA using the RT2 First-Strand Kit (SA Biosciences, 
Germany). The cDNA was then combined with RT2 SYBR 
Green qPCR Master Mix (SA Biosciences) and equal aliquots 
of this mixture were added to 96-well plates of the Human 
Apoptosis RT2 Profiler PCR Array (SA Biosciences) that con-
tained the gene-specific primers, human ATGs PAHS012z 
(SA Biosciences). PCR was performed using the 7500 Fast 
Real-Time PCR System (ABI) with the following thermal 
cycling conditions: 15 min at 95 
8 C for 1 cycle, 10s at 95 
8 C, 
and 1 min at 60 
8 C for 40 cycles. Expression of 84 key genes 
involved in apoptosis and 5 housekeeping genes (B2M, ACTB, 
GAPDH, HPRT1 and RPLPO) was profiled. Threshold cycle 
data obtained was analyzed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">RT2 Profiler</rs> Software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 3.5</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SA Biosciences</rs>). Relative gene expression was 
calculated using the 2 
−DDCT method. </p>

<p>Cell viability assay (MTT) </p>

<p>For the MTT (3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetra-
zolium bromide) assay, 160,000 Huh-7 cells were seeded in 
500 mL of media per well in a 24-well plate and incubated for 
24 hours prior to transfection with 37.5 ng oligonucleotides 
(according to the HiPerfect protocol). Forty-eight hours post-
transfection, 1 mL of MTT solution (5 mg/mL MTT in 10% 
PBS) was added to each well. After incubation for 5 hours, 
formazan (MTT metabolic product) was resuspended in 1 mL 
of lysis solution (DMSO: absolute ethanol). Then, 200 mL from 
each well was transferred to a 96-well plate and colorimetric 
measurements and absorbances (572 nm) were measured 
using the Wallac 1420 Victor2 Multilabel Counter (Perkin 
Elmer, USA). To eliminate any intensifying absorption that 
the culture medium itself could cause, culture medium without 
cells was assayed with the MTT solution and the subsequent 
reading was subtracted from all other values. The experiment 
was performed in triplicate and repeated three times. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>All data are presented as mean with standard error of the 
mean (SEM). <rs type="software">GraphPad Prism 5.0</rs> was used to prepare all 
figures. Statistical significance of the data was analyzed using 
unpaired Student's t-test, and determined at a p value of 
&lt;0.05 (*p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>miR-34a screening in HCV-induced non-metastatic 
HCC liver tissues </p>

<p>The pattern of expression of miR-34a was investigated in 
HCC tissues taken from 22 patients with HCV-induced non-
metastatic HCC and in 19 liver tissues obtained from healthy 
donors undergoing liver transplantation. The relative expres-
sion of miR-34a was significantly higher in HCC tissues 
compared to healthy tissues (p = 0.02*) (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>Effect of miR-34a on a set of pro-and anti-apoptotic 
genes involved in apoptosis </p>

<p>In order to investigate the impact of miR-34a on apoptosis, 
Huh-7 cells were transfected with miR-34a mimics, and effect 
of miR-34a ectopic overexpression was observed on the 
expression of 84 genes with critical roles in apoptosis. PCR 
array revealed that forcing the expression of miR-34a in Huh-7 
cells resulted in altered gene expression of a set of pro-
apoptotic/anti-apoptotic genes. Specifically, it up-regulated 
the expression of 26 pro-apoptotic genes (Fig. 2a) and 10 
anti-apoptotic genes (Fig. 2c); in addition, it repressed the 
expression of 17 pro-apoptotic genes (Fig. 2b) as well as 
8 anti-apoptotic genes (Fig. 2d), while the remaining genes 
were unaffected. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Expression pattern of miR-34a in HCV-induced non-metastatic 
HCC tissues. miR-34a expression pattern was investigated using RT-Q-PCR in 
liver tissues obtained from 22 patients with HCV-induced non-metastatic HCC and 
19 healthy donors. miR-34a showed significantly increased expression in HCC 
tissues, compared to healthy liver tissues. Expression of miR-34a was normalized, 
in each sample, to the housekeeping gene RNU6B. Results were analyzed using 
unpaired Student's t-test where p &lt; 0.05*, p &lt; 0.01**, p &lt; 0.001***. </p>

<p> 
Journal of Clinical and Translational Hepatology 2016 vol. 4 | 300-305 </p>

<p>Yacoub R. et al: miR-34a in HCC </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Impact of miR-34a on the expression of pro-apoptotic and anti-apoptotic genes. Huh-7 cells were transfected with miR-34a mimics, and the expression of 
several apoptosis-relevant genes was evaluated using PCR array in transfected cells as compared to Mock (untransfected) cells. (a) Ectopic overexpression of miR-34a up-
regulated the expression of 26 pro-apoptotic genes (b) and down-regulated the expression of 17 pro-apoptotic genes. (c) Expression of 10 anti-apoptotic genes was induced, 
(d) while expression of 8 anti-apoptotic genes was repressed. Experiments were performed in triplicate and repeated 3 times. Expression of each gene was normalized 
to 5 housekeeping genes (B2M, ACTB, GAPDH, HPRT1 and RPLPO). Each bar represents the mean ± SEM, and results were analyzed using unpaired Student's t-test where 
p &lt; 0.05*, p &lt; 0.01**, p &lt; 0.001***. </p>

<p>Journal of Clinical and Translational Hepatology 2016 vol. 4 | 300-305 </p>

<p>
Yacoub R. et al: miR-34a in HCC </p>

<p>Impact of miR-34a on cell viability </p>

<p>MTT assay was used for investigating cell viability. Forced 
expression of miR-34a in the Huh-7 cell line showed marked 
repression of cellular viability (p = 0.0006***) as compared 
to the Mock cells (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>miR-34a is a crucial miRNA that has been investigated in 
cancers and also subject to clinical trials. miR-34a has been 
investigated in HCC, yielding controversial results and raising 
several questions that encompass diverse aspects: first, the 
expression pattern of miR-34a and its relevance to the tumor 
etiology; second, the relevance of its expression pattern to 
the tumor stage and prognosis; and finally, its impact on 
apoptosis. 
In order to answer the first question that has been raised 
regarding the pattern of miR-34a expression and its associ-
ation with the tumor etiology, we focused on HCV-induced 
HCC. In this study, miR-34a expression was shown to be up-
regulated in HCV-induced HCC tissues (Fig. 1). This finding 
coincides with previous studies showing that miR-34a was 
up-regulated in HCV-related HCC, compared to normal liver 
tissues. 
14,17 On the contrary, miR-34a expression was found 
to be down-regulated in HBV-positive HCC tissues. 
5,13,15,18 In 
light of these findings, it may be presumed that the miR-34a 
expression pattern might depend on the etiology of HCC. 
Another imperative question was the correlation between 
miR-34a expression pattern and the prognosis of HCC. In 
this study, results showed that miR-34a expression was 
up-regulated in HCV-induced non-metastatic HCC tissues 
(Fig. 1). In a previous study, miR-34a was found to be over-
expressed in non-metastatic tissues, compared to metastatic 
ones, and in clinical TNM stages I and II, compared to stages 
III and IV. 
5,13 Taken together, these findings suggest that 
the miR-34a expression pattern might be stage-specific and 
miR-34a low expression may predict poor prognosis. </p>

<p>In an attempt to unveil the role of miR-34a in apoptosis, 
providing an answer for the third inquiry, the expression of 
miR-34a was forced in Huh-7 cells, and by using PCR array the 
expression of a set of 84 pro-apoptotic and anti-apoptotic 
genes was investigated. Interestingly, the expression of 26 
pro-apoptotic genes was found to be up-regulated, while 
another 17 pro-apoptotic genes were found to be repressed 
(Fig. 2a and 2b). Regarding the anti-apoptotic genes, miR-
34a increased the expression level of 10 genes, although it 
down-regulated the expression of 8 genes (Fig. 2c and 2d). 
miR-34a did not show a significant impact on the expression 
of the 23 remaining genes. Our results showed that miR-34a 
induced the expression of key players involved in the activa-
tion of the intrinsic apoptotic pathway, such as BAK (Fig. 2a). 
BAK triggers mitochondrial outer membrane permeabiliza-
tion, which leads to the release of cytochrome C into the cyto-
plasm. Then, APAF1 and cytochrome C form the apoptosome, 
which activates caspase-9 ultimately resulting in apoptotic 
cell death. 
19 In our study, miR-34a was found to not only </p>

<p>increase BAK expression but also to induce the expression 
of the downstream mediators of intrinsic apoptosis cyto-
chrome C, APAF1 and caspase-9 (Fig. 2a). 
PCR array revealed that miR-34a may have also induced 
extrinsic apoptosis via increasing the levels of TNF signaling 
pathway mediators (Fig. 2a). TNF-alpha leads to apoptosis via 
binding to the TNF receptor (TNFR), which in turn activates 
the Fas-associated protein with death domain (FADD), which 
then binds to caspase-8 to form the apoptotic death-inducing 
signaling complex (DISC). 
20,21 The findings of the current </p>

<p>study indicate that the levels of TNF, TNFR, and caspase-8 
are elevated by miR-34a ectopic expression (Fig. 2a). 
Induction of both intrinsic and extrinsic apoptotic path-
ways leads to activation of caspases-3, -6 and -7. 
22 These </p>

<p>executioner caspases mediate the cleavage of several pro-
teins critical to cell survival, including actin, lamin, poly 
(ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP) and inhibitor of caspase-
activated DNase (ICAD). Cleavage of these proteins leads 
to molecular and morphological changes characteristic to 
apoptosis, including cell shrinking and membrane blebbing, 
disruption of nuclear membrane integrity, DNA fragmentation 
and impaired DNA repair. 
23 Executioner caspases-3, -6 and -7 </p>

<p>were all found to be induced by miR-34a in the present study 
(Fig. 2a). This finding corroborates a previous study in which 
miR-34a ectopic overexpression in Hep3B cells and SNU449 
cells was shown to promote apoptosis and induce caspase-3 
and -7 activity. 
13 Nonetheless, these findings challenge pre-</p>

<p>vious reports which did not observe any impact on apoptosis 
upon overexpressing miR-34a in HepG2 cells. </p>

<p>5,12 </p>

<p>Finally, this study aimed to evaluate the net impact of miR-
34a on cell viability using MTT assay. Results showed that 
forcing the expression of miR-34a in Huh-7 cells reduced the 
cell viability significantly (Fig. 3). This finding is in line with 
other studies reporting that after forcing miR-34a expression 
in HCC cells, a decrease in cell viability is observed. 
13,15 In the </p>

<p>current study, the decrease in cell viability could be explained 
by the induction of apoptosis, as revealed by the results of the 
PCR array. In addition, it is possible that the effect of miR-34a 
on cell viability could also occur via targeting of cell cycle 
genes, since previous studies have reported that miR-34a 
has validated targets involved in cell cycle regulation, includ-
ing NMYC, 
2 CCND1, 
3 CCNE2, CDK4 and CDK6. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Impact of miR-34a on cell viability (MTT assay). miR-34a mimics 
remarkably inhibited cellular growth and viability in Huh-7 cells. Experiments were 
performed in triplicate and repeated 3 times. Absorbance was measured at 
572 nm. Each bar represents the mean ± SEM, and results were analyzed using 
unpaired Student's t-test where p &lt; 0.05*, p &lt; 0.01**, p &lt; 0.001***. </p>

<p> 
Journal of Clinical and Translational Hepatology 2016 vol. 4 | 300-305 </p>

<p>Yacoub R. et al: miR-34a in HCC </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>This study provides possible explanations for the controversial 
findings regarding the expression pattern of miR-34a and its 
role in apoptosis in HCC. Together with findings from previous 
reports, the current data suggests that miR-34a expression 
pattern could be etiology-based and stage-specific, and low 
expression of miR-34a may predict poor prognosis. In this 
study, it was shown that miR-34a activates dozens of pro-
apoptotic and anti-apoptotic genes, with a net effect of inducing 
apoptosis and repressing cell viability and, hence, emphasizing 
the role of miR-34a in apoptosis. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>None </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>Contributed in study concept and design, execution of experi-
ments, acquisition of data, statistical analysis and interpre-
tation of data, and writing of the manuscript (RY), assisted 
in experiments, interpretation of data, and revision of the 
manuscript (IF), assisted in experiments and interpretation of 
data (RA), provided tissue samples and clinical data (KH, GE), 
performed PCR array experiment and contributed in critical 
revision of the manuscript (ARZ), contributed reagents (HET), 
contributed in study concept and design and study super-
vision and provided critical revision of the manuscript for 
important intellectual content (AIA). </p>



<p>Journal of Clinical and Translational Hepatology 2016 vol. 4 | 300-305 </p>

<p>
Yacoub R. et al: miR-34a in HCC </p>

</text></tei>