<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5050532" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">


<p>Uncoupling proteins (UCPs) are mitochondrial inner mem-
brane proteins that function to dissipate proton motive 
force and mitochondrial membrane potential. One UCP 
has been identified in Caenorhabditis elegans (C. elegans), 
namely UCP-4. In this study, we examined its expression 
and localization using a GFP marker in C. elegans. ucp-4 
was expressed throughout the body from early embryo to 
aged adult and UCP-4 was localized in the mitochondria. It 
is known that increased mitochondrial membrane proten-
tial leads to a reactive oxygen species (ROS) increase, 
which is associated with age-related diseases, including 
neurodegenerative diseases in humans. A ucp-4 mutant 
showed increased mitochondrial membrane protential in 
association with increased neuronal defects during aging, 
and the neurons of ucp-4 overexpressing animals showed 
decreased neuronal defects during aging. These results 
suggest that UCP-4 may be involved in neuroprotection 
during aging via relieving mitochondrial membrane proten-
tial. We also investigated the relationship between UCP-4 
and innate immunity because increased ROS can affect 
innate immunity. ucp-4 mutant displayed increased re-
sistance to the pathogen Staphylococcus aureus com-
pared to wild type. The enhanced immunity in the ucp-4 
mutant could be related to increased mitochondrial mem-
brane protential, presumably followed by increased ROS. 
In summary, UCP-4 might have an important role in neu-
ronal aging and innate immune responses through mediat-
ing mitochondrial membrane protential. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Uncoupling proteins (UCPs) are a small family of mitochondrial 
carrier proteins with five identified members in mammalian </p>

<p> </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Biology Education, College of Education, Chosun Uni-
versity, Gwangju 61452, Korea, 2 These authors contributed equally to 
this work 
*Correspondence: renocho@chosun.ac.kr </p>

<p>Received 13 May, 2016; revised 19 July, 2016; accepted 1 August, 
2016; published online 20 September, 2016 </p>

<p>Keywords: C. elegans, innate immune, mitochondrial membrane poten-
tial (ψ m ), neuronal defects, ucp-4 </p>



<p>
systems. The first discovered UCP1 was localized in brown 
adipose tissue and was shown to dissipate the proton gradient, 
which generated heat through uncoupling of oxidative phos-
phorylation from the electron transport chain (Nicholls and 
Locke, 1984). Several studies suggest that UCPs might be 
involved in many metabolic functions, including fatty acid 
transport, regulation of insulin secretion, and regulation of mito-
chondrial superoxide generation (Echtay, 2007). UCP2 was 
suggested to be a negative regulator of insulin secretion and 
acted through a mild uncoupling mechanism (Chan et al., 1999). 
Moreover, UCP2 and UCP3 are activated by superoxide from 
the mitochondrial inner membrane (Echtay et al., 2002; Talbot 
et al., 2004). It was proposed that UCPs could reduce mito-
chondrial reactive oxygen species (ROS) generation, and 
therefore attenuate damage derived from these molecules 
(Murphy et al., 2003). In a recent study, endothelial UCP2 was 
shown to function mainly in the control ROS generation in mito-
chondria during hyperglycemia (Koziel et al., 2015). Moreover, 
the recently identified UCP4 and UCP5 were specifically local-
ized in the brain, and their roles were suggested to be in the 
modulation of energy production and mitochondrial ROS levels 
(Mao et al., 1999; Sanchis et al., 1998; Yu et al., 2000). Ectopic 
expression of these proteins resulted in lower mitochondrial 
membrane potential (ψ m ) and ROS content. It was proposed 
that high ψ m is strongly correlated with increases in ROS in 
mitochondria, and consequently mitochondrial oxidative dam-
age (Boveris et al., 1972; Echtay, 2007; Erlanson-Albertsson, 
2003). It was indeed demonstrated that 4-hydroxynonenal 
(HNE), derived from lipid peroxidation, reduced mitochondrial 
ROS production, through uncoupling, and decreased ψ m 
(Echtay and Brand, 2007; Echtay et al., 2003). 
Under restricted diet conditions, UCP2, 4, and 5 levels were 
shown to increase, which was associated with decreased ROS 
production and reduced neurodegeneration in models of Par-
kinson's disease (Duan and Mattson, 1999; Echtay, 2007; 
Sullivan et al., 2004). It has been suggested that UCPs regulate 
pathways involved in neurodegeneration, and protect against 
neurodegenerative diseases and aging through controlling 
ROS-induced oxidative stress. In addition, it was reported that 
Ucp2 knockout mice have enhanced resistance to the parasite 
Toxoplasma, presumably through increased ROS production in 
macrophages (Arsenijevic et al., 2000). 
Surprisingly there are few studies on UCP in Caenorhabditis 
elegans (C. elegans), despite this species providing a good 
research model. C. elegans has only one UCP, UCP-4, which is </p>

<p>Molecules 
and 
Cells </p>

<p>http://molcells.org </p>

<p>Established in 1990 </p>

<p>eISSN: 0219-1032 
The Korean Society for Molecular and Cellular Biology. All rights reserved. 
This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. To 
view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/. </p>

<p>ucp-4 Involvement in Neuronal Aging and Innate Immunity 
Injeong Cho et al. </p>



<p>http://molcells.org 
Mol. Cells 681 </p>



<p>
a homologue of mammalian UCP4 (Iser et al., 2005). According 
to a study by Iser et al. (2005), despite elevated ATP levels, 
there were no significant differences between wild type and 
ucp-4 mutants in terms of life span, temperature tolerance, and 
resistance to applied oxidative stress. However, the ucp-4 mu-
tant was sensitive to cold stress. This indicates that ucp-4 in C. 
elegans has a role as a thermogenin. In addition, it was sug-
gested that ceUCP4 controls succinate transport to achieve 
regulation of complex II-mediated oxidative phosphorylation 
(Pfeiffer et al., 2011). Given that mammals have multiple UCPs 
with multiple functions, the single C. elegans UCP could be 
multifunctional and involved in several mechanisms. However, 
its role in neuronal aging and innate immunity is not known. We 
therefore investigated the role of C. elegans UCP4 in neuronal 
aging and pathogen resistance. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Strains and constructs 
Wild type Bristol N2 strain, ucp-4 deletion mutant (ok195), and 
CZ10175 zdIs5 (Pmec-4::gfp) were obtained from the Caeno-
rhabditis Genetics Center (CGC) at the University of Minnesota. 
The ucp-4 deletion mutant was crossed to zdIs5 to obtain ucp-4 
(ok195);zdIs5 (Pmec-4::gfp). We cultured C. elegans according 
to published protocols (Brenner, 1974). 
To clone the ucp-4 promoter region, approximately 1.9 kb of 
the 5 -upstream region of ucp-4 gene was amplified by poly-
merase chain reaction (PCR) using genomic DNA from worm 
lysate as a template. The amplified DNA was inserted into the 
Fire vector, pPD95.79 to generate Pucp-4::gfp. The amplified 
1.6 kb ucp-4 genomic DNA was combined with Pucp-4::gfp to 
construct Pucp-4::ucp-4::gfp. To obtain ucp-4 overexpression 
constructs, the amplified 1.6 kb ucp-4 fragment was cloned into 
the Fire vector, pPD49.83, Phs::ucp-4. Subsequently, the heat-
shock promoter of the vector was replaced by the 1.9 kb ucp-4 
promoter region to generate Pucp-4::ucp-4. Microinjection was 
performed as previously described (Mello and Fire, 1995) and 
the plasmid pRF4 containing a dominant gene (rol-6) was co-
injected. 
For RNAi bacterial feeding constructs, ucp-4 cDNA was ob-
tained by reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-
PCR) followed by PCR. The amplified 1 kb ucp-4 cDNA was 
inserted into the Fire feeding vector (L4440). The RNAi con-
struct was introduced to HT115 (DE3) bacteria. Feeding exper-
iments were performed as described by Kamath et al. (2001). </p>

<p>MitoTracker and TMRE experiments 
MitoTracker Red CMXRos (Invitrogen, Life Technologies Cor-
poration, USA) was prepared following the manufacturer's pro-
tocol and added to the growth media plate at a final concentra-
tion of 2 μg/ml. The worms were transferred to the media and 
incubation proceeded for 16 h. 
Tetramethylrhodamine (TMRE, Invitrogen) is a cell-permeable 
and cationic fluorescent dye that is an indicator of mitochondrial 
membrane potential (ψ m ) (Farkas et al., 1989; Loew et al., 
1993; Yoneda et al., 2004). TMRE in DMSO (50 μM) was ap-
plied to the worm plates at a final concentration of 0.1 μM. 
Worms were incubated on TMRE plates for 16 h and then pre-
pared for observation after washing with M9 buffer (Yoneda et 
al., 2004). For ectopic overexpression experiments, heat shock 
was performed for 2 h at 30°C, 12 h before observation. </p>

<p>Observation of neuronal defects 
We scored an individual adult worm as one neuronal defect </p>

<p>when it displayed at least one defect such as an outgrowth in 
the anterior lateral microtubule cells (ALM) or branching, 
blebbing, and waving in the posterior lateral microtubule cells 
(PLM) (Cho et al., 2015). All observations were conducted us-
ing a fluorescent microscope (80i-DS-Fi1, Nikon). For as-
sessing neuronal defects, animals with ectopic overexpression 
of target proteins were subjected to a mild heat shock at 25°C 
for 2 h every 24 h. </p>

<p>Pathogen experiments 
Staphylococcus aureus was cultured overnight at 37°C in BHI 
media, after which the culture was diluted 1:10 with the same 
media. This diluted solution (100 μl) was spread onto plates 
and incubated at 37°C for 6 h, followed by 6 h of cooling at 
20°C. For treatment with heat-killed pathogens, plates were 
incubated at 65°C for 6 h to kill the pathogen. Worms were 
transferred to prepared media (previously seeded with heat-
killed or live pathogens) and the live worms were counted every 
6 h until no living worms remained. Data are presented as 
mean survival days, which were calculated using the <rs id="software-3" type="software">OASIS</rs> 
program (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Yang et al</rs>., 2011). </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>ucp-4 is expressed ubiquitously and UCP-4 is localized in 
the mitochondria in C. elegans 
A previous study reported that ucp-4 was expressed in the 
head muscles, pharynx, and body wall muscles of C. elegans 
(Iser et al., 2005). We investigated ucp-4 expression and UCP-
4 localization. Using a transcriptional reporter (Pucp-4::gfp), 
GFP expression indicated that ucp-4 was expressed through-
out the body of adult worms and that expression was initiated at 
an early developmental stage (Figs. 1A and 1B, respectively). 
ucp-4 expression was observed in several tissues, including 
pharyngeal muscle, body wall muscle, and head sensory neu-
rons (Figs. 1C, 1D, and 1E respectively). These results suggest 
that ucp-4 was expressed in most tissues throughout the life of 
the worm. Regarding UCP-4 localization, a translational report-
er (Pucp-4::ucp-4::gfp) was used. In UCP-4::GFP transgenic 
animals, GFP-tagged UCP-4 was specifically localized in the 
mitochondria of the body wall muscle and hypodermis (Figs. 1F 
and 1G). MitoTracker staining, overlaid with green fluorescence 
in the hypodermis, suggested that UCP-4 might be located 
inside the mitochondria, and probably in the inner membrane 
(Fig. 1H). </p>

<p>ucp-4 mutant reveals increased mitochondrial membrane 
potential (ψ m ) 
It has been suggested that increased mitochondrial membrane 
potential (ψ m ) is positively associated with reactive oxygen spe-
cies (ROS) generation in the mitochondria (Hansford et al., 
1997; Korshunov et al., 1997; Votyakova and Reynolds, 2001). 
Moreover, UCPs dissipate the mitochondrial proton gradient, 
resulting in decreased ψ m (Korshunov et al., 1997). To deter-
mine if UCP-4 is involved in regulating ψ m , we used TMRE 
staining to visualize ψ m in wild type, ucp-4 mutant, and ucp-4 
overexpressing animals. As shown in Fig. 2, ψ m was increased 
in the ucp-4 mutants compared to that of wild type worms (Figs. 
2A and 2B, respectively); this result was consistent with previ-
ous studies (Iser et al., 2005; Ji et al., 2012). To confirm the 
involvement of ucp-4 in ψ m , ucp-4 was overexpressed using a 
heat shock promoter, Phs::ucp-4, and the worms were stained 
by TMRE. TMRE intensity in overexpressing animals was low-
est among all strains (Fig. 2D). Wild type animals with the heat </p>

<p>ucp-4 Involvement in Neuronal Aging and Innate Immunity 
Injeong Cho et al. </p>



<p>682 Mol. Cells 
http://molcells.org </p>



<p>
Fig. 1. ucp-4 expression and UCP-4 
localization in C. elegans. ucp-4 was 
expressed throughout the entire body 
(A) and in a comma stage embryo (B) 
in the transgenic animal carrying 
Pucp-4::gfp. Higher magnification 
showed intense expression of ucp-4 
in pharyngeal muscle and head neu-
rons (C, arrows and arrowheads, 
respectively), body wall muscle (D), 
and head neurons (E, arrows). UCP-4 
was localized in the body wall mus-
cles and in the hypodermis (F and G 
respectively) in the transgenic worm 
carrying the Pucp-4::ucp-4::gfp con-
struct. (H) The same hypodermis 
image in G stained with MitoTracker is 
presented. Scale bars = 50 μm. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>G 
H </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>Fig. 2. The ucp-4 mutant shows increased mitochondrial mem-
brane potential (ψ m ). ψ m was assessed by TMRE. WT, wild type (A); 
ucp-4, ucp-4 mutant (B); Phs::gfp (C); Phs::ucp-4, ucp-4 overex-
pression under control of the heat shock promoter (D). Scale bar = 
100 μm. </p>

<p>shock promoter showed no difference in TMRE intensity com-
pared to wild type animals; therefore, the heat shock promoter 
itself did not affect ψ m (Fig. 2C). Low ψ m in ucp-4 overexpress-
ing worms could be the result of proton gradient dissipation. 
Therefore, UCP-4 could lead to low energy efficiency and low 
ROS levels. </p>

<p>ucp-4 mutant displays increased neuronal defects 
Increased ROS, probably in the context of oxidative damage, is 
correlated with neuronal diseases such as Parkinson's and </p>

<p>Alzheimer's (Fahn and Cohen, 1992; Lin and Beal, 2006). Hu-
man UCP2 was shown to protect neurons against oxidative 
stress (Mattiasson and Sullivan, 2006). We therefore examined 
if UCP-4 is involved in neuronal defects during the aging pro-
cess. In recent reports, mechanosensory touch receptor neu-
rons, anterior lateral microtubule cells (ALM) and posterior lat-
eral microtubule cells (PLM), showed neuronal degenerations 
during aging, which included soma outgrowth, axon blebbing, 
and wavy processes (Pan et al., 2011; Tank et al., 2011; Toth et 
al., 2012). In addition, ALM and PLM cells are well-studied and 
easily observed (Chen et al., 2013). Therefore, We used the 
zdIs5 (Pmec-4::gfp) background to observe and score ALMs 
and PLMs during aging. Imaging of touch receptor neurons in 
zdIs5 worms showed ALM and PLM cells on day 1 (Fig. 3A). 
Fig. 3B shows standard ALM outgrowth and PLM wavy defects 
in the 10-day control animal. On day 15, severe ALM outgrowth 
and PLM waving and blebbing phenotypes were observed as 
aging progressed in control worms (Figs. 3C, 3D, and 3E). 
To understand ucp-4 function in neuronal aging, ucp-4 defi-
cient and ucp-4 overexpressing worms were examined. First, 
both ucp-4 deletion mutants and ucp-4 RNAi treated animals 
were used for neuronal observation during aging to determine 
whether effects are the result of ucp-4 itself. For RNAi treatment 
in worms, ucp-4 RNAi was applied to zdIs5 animals (Figs. 3F 
and 3G). Figures 3F and 3G show that ALM and PLM defects 
progressed in an age-dependent manner regardless of the 
presence of ucp-4 (comparing day 1 to day 15). For example, 
ALMs in the 15-day control showed a 67% defect, which was 
much greater than the 14% defect in 1-day animals (Fig. 3F). 
Moreover, the ucp-4 mutant showed markedly increased ALM 
defects, specifically, 22% on day 1 and 89% on day 15 (Fig. 3F). 
Animals treated with ucp-4 RNAi showed similar results to 
those of the ucp-4 mutant. 
For PLMs, neuronal defects gradually increased with aging in 
control and ucp-4 deficient animals (Fig. 3G). However, PLM 
waving phenotypes were much more severe in ucp-4 mutants </p>

<p>ucp-4 Involvement in Neuronal Aging and Innate Immunity 
Injeong Cho et al. </p>



<p>http://molcells.org 
Mol. Cells 683 </p>



<p>
A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D 
E </p>

<p>F 
G </p>

<p>H 
I </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Neuronal defects are increased in the ucp-4 mutant. (A-E) A representative image of a mechanosensory neuron from a control worm is 
presented on day 1 (A), 10 (B), and 15 (C, D, and E). An arrow indicates ALM outgrowth and arrowheads indicate PLM waving in B. Arrows 
show ALM outgrowth in C; arrows indicate PLM branching in D. Arrows indicate PLM blebbing and arrowheads show PLM waving in E. Scale 
bars = 50 μm. (F and H) ALM neuronal defects in the ucp-4 mutant and in ucp-4 RNAi treated worms (F) and ucp-4 overexpressing animals 
(H) are presented as a percentage relative to that of control animals. (G and I) PLM neuronal defects in the ucp-4 mutant and in ucp-4 RNAi 
treated worms (G) and ucp-4 overexpressing animals (I) are presented as a percentage relative to that of the control. zdIs5, zdIs5 (Pmec-
4::gfp); zdIs5;ucp-4 (ok195), ucp-4 in zdIs5; zdIs5 + vector (L4440), empty vector (L4440) in zdIs5; zdIs5 + ucp-4 RNAi, zdIs5 treated with ucp-
4 RNAi (F and G). zdIs5 + Pucp-4::gfp, Pucp-4::gfp in zdIs5; zdIs5 + Pucp-4::ucp-4, Pucp-4::ucp-4 in zdIs5; zdIs5 + Phs::gfp, Phs::gfp in zdIs5; 
zdIs5 + Phs::ucp-4, Phs::ucp-4 in zdIs5 (H and I) n &gt; 100 worms per line in each experiment. Four independent experiments were performed. 
Error bars represent SD. *p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01, based on a Student's t-test. </p>

<p>compared to that of control worms (Fig. 3G). Quantification 
indicated that both ucp-4 mutants and ucp-4 RNAi treated 
worms resulted in more neuronal defects compared to that in 
controls at all time points tested (Figs. 3F and 3G). These re-
sults suggest that only ucp-4 contributes to neuronal defects 
during aging. For confirmation, ucp-4 overexpressing animals 
were also studied during aging. Pucp-4::ucp-4 and Phs::ucp-4 
constructs were injected into zdIs5 for observation in overex-
pressing worms (Figs. 3H and 3I). On day 1, ALM and PLM 
phenotypes were not significantly different between controls 
(Phs::gfp) and ucp-4 overexpressing animals (Pucp-4::ucp-4 
and Phs::ucp-4). As aging progressed, all animals showed a 
gradual increase in neuronal defects (Figs. 3H and 3I). Howev-
er, both ucp-4 overexpressing animals (Pucp-4::ucp-4 and 
Phs::ucp-4) consistently presented a lower number of defects 
compared to that in either group of control animals (Pucp-4::gfp 
and Phs::gfp) (Figs. 3H and 3I). These results led us to con-
clude that UCP-4 attenuates neuronal defects during aging, </p>

<p>probably by lowering the mitochondrial membrane potential 
(ψ m ) and consequently lowering ROS levels. 
According to the free radical theory, ROS might cause aging 
and aging-related disease (Harman, 1972). Mild uncoupling by 
UCPs resulting in lowered ROS levels can alleviate aging and 
aging-associated diseases such as Parkinson's and Alz-
heimer's disease that are driven by oxidative damage. However, 
this has not yet been clearly proven (Beckman and Ames, 
1998; Divakaruni and Brand, 2011). The quantification of a mild 
uncoupling effect requires the development of specific methods 
to measure physiological ROS content, especially in native 
conditions (Divakaruni and Brand, 2011). Despite technical 
difficulty, the application of mild uncoupling has shown benefi-
cial results. For example, mice expressing muscle-specific 
UCP1 showed decreased adiposity, increased metabolic rate, 
and diminished age-related diseases (Gates et al., 2007). Ucp2 
overexpressing mice showed neuronal protection after global 
ischemia and after transient focal ischemia (Deierborg et al., </p>

<p>ucp-4 Involvement in Neuronal Aging and Innate Immunity 
Injeong Cho et al. </p>



<p>684 Mol. Cells 
http://molcells.org </p>



<p>
A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>E </p>



<p>Fig. 4. Deficiency of UCP-4 results in resistance to S. aureus. Mito-
chondrial membrane potential (ψ m ) was measured by TMRE after 
wild type worms were fed heat-killed or live S. aureus (A and B, 
respectively). (C) and (D) represent TMRE stained ucp-4 mutants 
feeding on either heat-killed or live S. aureus, respectively. Scale 
bar = 100 μm. (E) Mean survival days of the wild type and the 
ucp-4 mutant after exposure to pathogen-seeded plates. Each 
experimental result was calculated by <rs type="software">OASIS</rs>. The average of five 
experimental replicates was plotted. n &gt; 300 worms per line in 
each experiment. WT, wild type; ucp-4, ucp-4 mutant; egg, ani-
mals were exposed to the pathogen at the egg stage; L1-2, at L1-
2 stage; L3-4, at L3-4 stage; adult day 1, 5, and 10, at day 1, 5, 
and 10, respectively. Error bars = SD. *p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01, based 
on a Student's t-test. </p>

<p>2008; Haines and Li, 2012) Moreover, our results suggest that 
ucp-4 overexpression in C. elegans alleviates neuronal defects 
that occur during aging. Therefore, UCPs can regulate ψ m , 
which protects neurons during aging. Proper application of mild 
uncoupling might be useful to treat metabolic or age-related 
diseases. Further studies are required to establish mild uncou-
pling and determine how it is regulated during age-related neu-
rodegeneration. </p>

<p>The ucp-4 mutant is resistant to the pathogen S. aureus 
Increased ROS can cause oxidative damage, especially in the 
mitochondria (Harman, 1956). However, an increase in ROS 
can be beneficial for innate immunity as a major defense sys-
tem against pathogens (Arsenijevic et al., 2000; Basu Ball et al., 
2011). Moreover, in C. elegans, increased ROS levels were 
shown to occur in the intestine at the site of pathogen infection 
(Chavez et al., 2007). Because UCP-4 is involved in regulating 
mitochondrial membrane potential (ψ m ), we investigated the 
function of UCP-4 in the response to pathogens. First, we com-
pared ψ m using TMRE staining in wild types and in ucp-4 mu-</p>

<p>tants upon exposure to either live (pathogenic) or heat-killed 
(non-pathogenic) Staphylococcus aureus (S. aureus). As seen 
in Fig. 4, the ucp-4 mutant had high ψ m compared to that of the 
wild type without pathogen exposure (Figs. 4A and 4C, respec-
tively). After pathogen exposure, there was no significant 
change in ψ m between live and heat-killed pathogen exposed 
ucp-4 mutants (Fig. 4D). In contrast, wild type worms showed 
an increase in ψ m upon exposure to live pathogens (Fig. 4B). 
This increased ψ m could be related to pathogen resistance; 
we therefore assayed worm survival. We placed animals on 
pathogen-seeded plates during each developmental stage, 
specifically egg, L1-2, L3-4, and adult day 1, 5, and 10. After 
the worms were transferred, surviving animals were counted 
each day until all were dead. We used the <rs type="software">OASIS</rs> program to 
calculate mean survival days based on the raw data (Yang et 
al., 2011). As seen in Fig. 4E, the ucp-4 mutant survived 
longer than the wild type when exposed to the pathogen at 
the egg stage, L1-2, L3-4, and the young adult stage (day 1). 
However, exposure at the aged adult stages (days 5 and 10) 
produced different results. Specifically, the ucp-4 mutants 
were more susceptible to the pathogen compared to wild type 
at this stage. 
Considering the increase in ψ m in wild type animals upon 
pathogen exposure, the resulting increase in ROS could serve 
to initiate an immune response. However, the ucp-4 mutant 
displayed high ROS levels without the presence of the patho-
gen, which could account for the observed resistance. As 
shown in Fig. 4, ucp-4 mutants exposed to pathogens at an 
early stage showed increased resistance, but were susceptible 
when exposed to the pathogen in an aged adult stage. This 
inconsistency between young and aged animals might be due 
to the free radical aging process and/or gradual ROS response 
(Hekimi et al., 2011). It was shown that silencing UCP2 in mac-
rophages resulted in increased ROS production that could kill 
the pathogen via direct oxidative damage. As a result, the 
UCP2 knocked-down macrophage showed enhanced re-
sistance to the Leishmania parasite (Basu Ball et al., 2011). 
When young ucp-4 mutants were exposed to the pathogen, the 
increased ROS could function as microbicidal molecules. In 
addition, increased ROS could facilitate an immune response-
during pathogen attack. Indeed, a recent study showed that 
moderately increased ROS in the mitochondria enhances im-
munity against pathogens via a feedback mechanism involving 
hypoxia-inducible factor 1 (HIF-1) and AMP-activated protein 
kinase (AMPK) in C. elegans (Hwang et al., 2014). 
Alternatively, high levels of ROS can cause oxidative damage. 
It was observed that various organisms accumulated oxidative 
damage of macromolecules such as DNA, proteins, and lipids 
during aging (Back et al., 2012; Harman, 1956; 1972; 2009; 
Sohal and Weindruch, 1996). When ucp-4 mutants aged, their 
macromolecules could be progressively damaged by increased 
ROS. The cumulative damage via ROS and aging in the ucp-4 
mutant could cause susceptibility to the pathogen. ROS in-
creases can thus function in two opposite ways. The initial ROS 
increase against a pathogen attack could be beneficial to kill the 
pathogen and trigger an immune response. However, the con-
stant high level of ROS could cause deterioration of structures 
consisting of physical barriers to infection by pathogen. Since 
ROS can exert both positive and negative responses, the regu-
lation of ROS levels could be critical for innate immunity. This 
dual role is probably tightly linked to ROS balance; therefore, 
further studies are necessary to elucidate how the ROS bal-
ance in the innate immune system is sensed and regulated 
during pathogen exposure. </p>

<p>ucp-4 Involvement in Neuronal Aging and Innate Immunity 
Injeong Cho et al. </p>



<p>http://molcells.org 
Mol. Cells 685 </p>



<p>
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank the Caenorhabditis Genetics Center (CGC) at the 
University of Minnesota, USA, for the worm strains and Andrew 
Fire for the Fire vectors. The study was supported by a re-
search fund from Chosun University, 2011. </p>



</text></tei>