<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5308435" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Objective: To assess the effect of renal denervation (RDT) on micro-and macro-vascular function in patients with heart 
failure with preserved ejection fraction (HFpEF). 
Design: A prospective, randomised, open-controlled trial with blinded end-point analysis. 
Setting: A single-centre London teaching hospital. 
Participants: Twenty-five patients with HFpEF who were recruited into the RDT-PEF trial. 
Main outcome measures: Macro-vascular: 24-h ambulatory pulse pressure, aorta distensibilty (from cardiac magnetic 
resonance imaging (CMR), aorta pulse wave velocity (CMR), augmentation index (peripheral tonometry) and renal artery 
blood flow indices (renal MR). Micro-vascular: endothelial function (peripheral tonometry) and urine microalbuminuria. 
Results: At baseline, 15 patients were normotensive, 9 were hypertensive and 1 was hypotensive. RDT did not lower 
any of the blood pressure indices. Though there was evidence of abnormal vascular function at rest, RDT did not affect 
these at 3 or 12 months follow-up. 
Conclusions: RDT did not improve markers of macro-and micro-vascular function. </p>

<p>Heart failure with preserved ejection fraction (HFpEF) 
is a prevalent phenotype of heart failure for which no 
treatment has, as yet, been shown to improve progno-
sis. 1 Its underlying pathophysiology is multifactorial. 
Abnormal micro-and macro-vascular function have 
been observed in HFpEF and their presence is asso-
ciated with increased cardiovascular events 2 as well as 
exercise intolerance. 2,3 
The sympathetic nervous system (SNS) is a modu-
lator of arterial function. 4 Renal denervation (RDT) 
is a novel technique that has been shown to reduce 
central sympathetic outflow and hence may promote 
vascular remodelling. 5 The Renal DenervaTion in 
heart failure with Preserved Ejection Fraction </p>

<p>(RDT-PEF) was conducted to investigate the effect 
of RDT upon symptoms, exercise function, left ven-
tricular filling and cardiac remodelling in patients </p>

<p>1 Cardiovascular Biomedical Research Unit, Royal Brompton Hospital and 
Imperial College, London, UK 
2 Department of Cardiac MRI, Royal Brompton Hospital, London, UK 
3 Department of Cardiology, St Thomas' Hospital, London, UK 
4 Department of Non-Invasive Cardiology, Royal Brompton Hospital, 
London, UK 
5 Department of Cardiology, Ealing Hospital, Southall, UK </p>

<p>Corresponding author: 
Hitesh C Patel, Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute, 75 Commercial 
Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004, Australia. 
Email: dochiteshpatel@hotmail.com </p>

<p>Journal of the Royal Society of 
Medicine Cardiovascular Disease 
6: 1-9 
! The Author(s) 2017 
Reprints and permissions: 
sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav 
DOI: 10.1177/2048004017690988 
journals.sagepub.com/home/cvd </p>

<p>Creative Commons CC-BY-NC: This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 License (http://www. 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the 
original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage). </p>

<p>with HFpEF. 6 A vascular function substudy 
involving the same participants of the parent trial 
was prospectively designed to test the hypothesis 
that the vasculature might be a therapeutic target in 
HFpEF. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Trial design </p>

<p>The RDT-PEF trial was an investigator initiated, 
randomised, controlled, open-label trial with blinded 
endpoint analysis. 6 The primary endpoints of this 
study were symptomatic improvement (Minnesota 
Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire-MLWHFQ), 
exercise performance (peak oxygen uptake on 
exercise-peak VO2), B-type natriuretic peptide levels 
(BNP), left ventricular filling pressures assessed by E/ 
e' on echocardiogram, indexed left atrial volume 
(LAVi) on cardiac magnetic resonance (CMR) and 
indexed left ventricular mass index (LVMi). The ration-
ale, design and results of the RDT-PEF trial have been 
published. 6 
This vascular substudy was prospectively designed 
and received approval from the National Research 
Ethics Service (12/LO/1941). All patients gave 
informed consent to participate in the study. </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>Eligible patients were 18-85 years of age and were New 
York Heart Association class II/III. The recruited 
patients fulfilled the European Society of Cardiology 
Heart Failure 1 diagnostic guidelines for HFpEF and 
had either left ventricular hypertrophy or left atrial 
dilatation and either a raised natriuretic peptide level 
or tissue Doppler echocardiographic evidence of raised 
filling pressures. 6 Detailed criteria have been pub-
lished. 6 Importantly, patients with atrial fibrillation 
were not excluded. </p>

<p>Study protocol </p>

<p>At the initial visit, all patients underwent 24-h ambu-
latory blood pressure monitoring (24-h ABPM), CMR 
to derive aortic distensibility and pulse wave velocity, 
digital tonometry to assess endothelial function and 
augmentation index (AI), renal magnetic resonance 
(MR) to calculate renal artery flow, resistive index 
and pulsatility index and finally a urine assay for albu-
minuria. The protocol was then repeated after 3 and 
12 months (renal MR was repeated at 12 months 
only) following either renal denervation or on-going 
medical therapy. Assessments were performed blinded 
to allocation. </p>

<p>Renal denervation </p>

<p>Access to the renal artery was obtained via the femoral 
artery using an 80 cm 6 Fr guide catheter (RDC or 
IMA curve). The Symplicity TM single-electrode cath-
eter was then advanced and positioned in the most 
distal aspect of the renal artery proximal to bifurca-
tions, good vessel wall contact was obtained by deflect-
ing the electrode tip and confirmed by an impedance of 
250-300 on the power generator. We then applied a 
minimum of four ablations to each main renal artery in 
a circumferential distribution as has been described 
elsewhere. 6-8 </p>

<p>24-h Ambulatory blood pressure monitor </p>

<p>A Spacelabs 90207 ambulatory blood pressure monitor 
was attached using an appropriately sized cuff to the 
non-dominant arm of the patient. It was attached for a 
period of 24 h and was analysed using automated and 
proprietary software. Twenty-four hour, day time 
(0800-2200) and night time (2200-0800) averages of 
blood pressure were obtained. </p>

<p>Aortic distensibility </p>

<p>This was derived from a MR axial dataset of the aorta 
at the level of the bifurcation of the main pulmonary 
artery. The maximum and minimal cross sectional areas 
of the ascending and descending aorta were calculated 
using Art-FUN (Laboratoire d'Imagerie Biome´dicale, 
UPMC-CNRS-INSERM, France), an automated edge-
detection software for assessment of arterial function. 9 
Aortic strain was defined as: (max cross-sectional aorta 
area À min cross-sectional aorta area)/min cross-sec-
tion aortic area. 10 Aortic distensibility (10 À3 mmHg À1 ) 
was defined as: aortic strain/brachial artery pulse 
pressure. 10 </p>

<p>Pulse wave velocity </p>

<p>Velocity encoded phase contrast sequences were 
acquired from a MR axial dataset of the aorta at the 
level of the bifurcation of the main pulmonary artery 
perpendicularly transecting both the ascending and des-
cending aorta. A non-breath-hold sequence was used 
and 128 phases were captured during the cardiac 
cycle. The transit time of the propagation of the vel-
ocity waveform was calculated between the ascending 
and descending aorta using the <rs type="software">Art-FUN</rs> software with 
the least squares minimisation approach using all data 
points on the systolic upslope of the aorta flows after 
peak flow normalisation. 9,10 The aortic path length was 
calculated from the double-oblique view of the thoracic 
aorta. Pulse wave velocity (m/s) was derived as aortic 
path length divided by the transit time. </p>

<p> 
Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine Cardiovascular Disease 0(0) </p>

<p>Endothelial function </p>

<p>This was assessed using the EndoPAT TM 2000 device 
(Itamar Medical, Israel). It recorded the arterial wave-
form at the fingertip (one probe on each arm). A rapid 
cuff inflator (E20, Hokanson, USA) was placed on upper 
right arm of each patient and set to inflate to a pressure 
of 200 mmHg or 50 mmHg above the patient's systolic 
pressure (whichever was greater). A 6-min rest period 
was recorded, followed by 5 min when the cuff was 
inflated to occlude the right brachial artery, and finally 
5 min of recovery with the cuff deflated (hyperaemic 
period). The proprietary software calculated the reactive 
hyperaemia index (RHI) and AI based upon these read-
ings. AI was calculated as the difference between the 
second and first systolic peak of a pressure waveform 
expressed as a percentage of the pulse pressure. </p>

<p>Renal blood flow </p>

<p>Images were acquired using the Siemens Skyra 
(3.0 Tesla) MR scanner. Renal artery blood flow was 
assessed by applying a bespoke breath-hold spiral 
phase contrast sequence on a through-plane image of 
the proximal renal artery. 11 In patients with sinus 
rhythm retrospective cardiac gating was used to acquire 
data throughout the entire cardiac cycle while for 
patients with atrial fibrillation, prospective cardiac 
gating was used with imaging over approximately 2/3 
of the cardiac cycle. Scan parameters were replicated 
for follow-up scans on an individual patient basis. 11 
Resistive index was calculated as (peak systolic velocity 
À minimum systolic velocity)/peak systolic velocity. 11 
Pulsatility index was calculated as (peak systolic vel-
ocity À minimum systolic velocity)/mean velocity. 11 
For the majority of these variables, normal cut-off 
values have not been derived. Abnormal vascular func-
tion is associated with an increased pulse pressure, pulse 
wave velocity, AI, resistive index, pulsatility index, albu-
minuria and a decreased aortic distensibility and RHI. </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>Data were assessed for normality both subjectively 
using histograms and statistically using the Shapiro-
Wilk test. Parametric data are presented as 
mean AE standard 
deviation; 
between 
group 
comparisons were performed using the independent 
samples t-test and within group comparisons using 
the paired t-test. Non-parametric data are presented 
as median with interquartile range; between group com-
parisons were performed using the Mann-Whitney U 
test and within group comparisons using the paired 
Wilcoxon-signed rank. Correlation between the vascu-
lar parameters, the primary endpoints 6 and the safety 
endpoint of estimated glomerular filtration rate </p>

<p>(eGFR) 6 was assessed using Spearman's rho. P &lt; 0.05 
was used as the threshold for statistical significance and 
a P &lt; 0.01 was used for the multiple correlation assess-
ments. A prospective power calculation was not per-
formed as this was a sub-study. </p>

<p>Result </p>

<p>Recruited patients </p>

<p>A total of 25 patients were randomised (17 received 
RDT and 8 were control) between July 2013 and 
December 2014 before the trial was stopped because 
of difficulty in recruitment despite nationwide screen-
ing. 6,12 Baseline characteristics are shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>Ambulatory blood pressure monitoring </p>

<p>At baseline, nine patients (two were in control arm) 
were hypertensive and had an ambulatory systolic 
blood pressure (SBP) reading ! 130 mmHg and one 
patient had an average SBP &lt; 100 mmHg (in RDT 
arm). There were no between group differences in 
ambulatory blood pressure changes at 3 and 12 
months after RDT (Table 2). There was no significant 
correlation between baseline 24-h average SBP and 
change at 3 (r ¼ À0.46, P ¼ 0.361) or 12 months 
(r ¼ À0.05, P ¼ 0.923) in the seven patients who had 
baseline averages ! 130 mmHg and were allocated to 
denervation. </p>

<p>Aorta function and endothelial function </p>

<p>Table 3 details the findings. At baseline 15 patients (12 
RDT, 3 control) had a LnRHI 0.51 and 10 patients (8 
RDT, 2 control) had an ACR &gt; 30 mg/g. RDT did not 
improve any of the measured markers of vascular func-
tion at 3 or 12 months follow-up. </p>

<p>Renal blood flow </p>

<p>At baseline, the average blood flow per kidney was 
0.22 AE 0.06 l/min, pulsatility index was 1.89 (1.43, 
2.99) and resistive index was 0.87 AE 0.09. At 12 
months, RDT did not result in a change in renal 
blood flow, resistive index or pulsatility index as 
assessed by MR (Table 4). </p>

<p>Effects of age on vascular function </p>

<p>There was a trend for age to be associated with baseline 
ascending aorta strain (rho ¼ À0.46, P ¼ 0.02) and dis-
tensibility (rho ¼ À0.42, P ¼ 0.04) as well as descending 
aorta strain (rho ¼ À0.45, P ¼ 0.03). No correlations 
were seen with any of the other parameters. </p>

<p>Patel et al. </p>

<p>
Correlations between baseline vascular function and 
primary endpoints and eGFR </p>

<p>At baseline, patients with higher pulse pressures 
reported worse symptoms on questionnaire assessment 
and lower peak oxygen uptake on exercise (Table 5). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The main finding of this body of work is that RDT did 
not improve vascular function in patients with HFpEF. 
It is therefore important to review: (a) the evidence </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline characteristics of the RDT-PEF population. </p>

<p>Total (n ¼ 25) 
RDT (n ¼ 17) 
Control (n ¼ 8) </p>

<p>P (RDT vs. 
Control) </p>

<p>Demographics 
Age 
74.3 AE 6.1 
74.1 AE 6.8 
74.6 AE 4.8 
0.852 
Male 
15 (60%) 
11 (64.7%) 
4 (50.0%) 
0.667 
BMI (kg/m 2 ) 
30.6 AE 5.5 
30.5 AE 4.6 
30.8 AE 7.4 
0.911 
Past medical history 
Hypertension 
18 (72%) 
14 (82.4%) 
4 (50%) 
0.156 
Diabetes 
10 (40%) 
8 (47.1%) 
2 (25%) 
0.402 
CVA 
1 (4%) 
1 (5.9%) 
0 (0.0%) 
1.000 
CHD 
6 (24%) 
5 (29.4%) 
1 (12.5%) 
0.624 
AF 
15 (60%) 
10 (58.8%) 
5 (62.5%) 
1.000 
Medications 
ACEi/ARB 
23 (92%) 
16 (94.1%) 
7 (87.5%) 
1.000 
Beta-blockers 
18 (72%) 
12 (70.6%) 
6 (75%) 
1.000 
CC-blockers 
8 (32%) 
7 (41.2%) 
1 (12.5%) 
0.205 
Loop diuretics 
21 (84%) 
16 (94.1%) 
5 (62.5%) 
0.081 
Spironolactone 
6 (24%) 
6 (35.3%) 
0 (0.0%) 
0.129 </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean AE standard deviation or count (%). 
BMI: body mass index; CVA: cerebrovascular accident; CHD: coronary heart disease; AF: atrial fibrillation; NYHA: New York Heart Association; A: 
ambulatory; SBP: systolic blood pressure; ACEi: angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitor; ARB: angiotensin receptor blocker; CC: calcium channel. </p>

<p>Table 2. Change of average systolic (SBP) and diastolic (DBP) blood pressure in mmHg within the RDT-PEF trial at 3 and 12 months 
follow-up. </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>Baseline 
Change at 3 months 
Change at 12 months </p>

<p>RDT (n ¼ 17) </p>

<p>Control 
(n ¼ 8) 
P </p>

<p>RDT 
(n ¼ 16) </p>

<p>Control 
(n ¼ 8) 
P 
RDT (n ¼ 17) </p>

<p>Control 
(n ¼ 7) 
P </p>

<p>Ambulatory blood pressure monitoring (mmHg) 
24 h 
SBP 
126.8 AE 15.9 
121.1 AE 7.5 0.349 
À1.1 AE 13.2 þ0.9 AE 11.2 0.727 À2.4 AE 9.7 
þ1.3 AE 9.4 
0.410 
DBP 
71.5 AE 9.1 
70.0 AE 6.2 0.672 
À2.0 AE 7.9 
À1.4 AE 6.2 
0.847 À2.9 AE 5.8 
À1.7 AE 7.4 
0.684 
PP 
55.2 AE 14.3 
51.1 AE 7.6 0.457 
þ1.1 AE 6.3 
þ2.0 AE 5.9 
0.746 þ1.2 AE 6.8 
þ7.1 AE 13.7 0.166 
Day (0800-2200) 
SBP 
128.1 AE 15.9 
123.0 AE 7.9 0.400 
À1.0 AE 12.7 þ1.6 AE 11.4 0.628 À2.7 AE 10.4 
þ2.1 AE 11.0 0.318 
DBP 
72.9 AE 10.4 
72.3 AE 5.7 0.863 
À2.1 AE 7.6 
À1.4 AE 7.0 
0.817 À3.7 AE 6.7* 
À1.9 AE 7.5 
0.558 
PP 
55.2 AE 14.4 
50.8 AE 8.2 0.424 
þ1.0 AE 6.6 
þ3.3 AE 5.4 
0.413 þ0.8 AE 7.1 
þ3.7 AE 6.4 
0.360 
Night (2200-0800) 
SBP 
121.2 AE 18.1 
113.7 AE 6.7 0.164 
þ2.0 AE 16.7 À5.9 AE 8.2 
0.256 À0.3 AE 12.0 
À1.6 AE 9.5 
0.800 
DBP 
67.9 AE 8.0 
63.6 AE 6.8 0.225 
À0.7 AE 9.9 
À3.0 AE 6.9 
0.580 À0.1 AE 6.6 
À2.7 AE 9.1 
0.438 
PP 
53.6 AE 14.5 
50.3 AE 7.3 0.480 
þ2.5 AE 8.0 
À2.9 AE 3.6 
0.111 À0.5 AE 6.9 
þ0.7 AE 3.5 
0.669 </p>

<p>*P &lt; 0.05 for within group change. </p>

<p> 
Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine Cardiovascular Disease 0(0) </p>

<p>supporting the initial hypothesis that vascular dysfunc-
tion plays an important role in HFpEF and (b) 
whether, if demonstrated, vascular dysfunction in 
HFpEF can be improved. 
The literature promoting the biological plausibility 
of both large and small vessel dysfunction driving 
HFpEF has been extensively reviewed. 13 Increased 
arterial stiffness predicts incident cardiovascular 
dysfunction including hypertension, heart failure and 
peripheral organ damage. 14 In heart failure, an associ-
ation between increased stiffness and premature death 
has been demonstrated albeit predominately in the 
reduced ejection fraction cohort. 15 Ageing is associated 
with a decrease in the elasticity of large conduit blood 
vessels, 16 however, this decline is accelerated in patients 
with HFpEF. 17 Indeed in the RDT-PEF population, 
age trended with pulse pressure, a crude index of 
large artery stiffness. 13 
Increased myocardial wall stress, systolic and dia-
stolic dysfunction, left ventricular hypertrophy and 
left atrial dilatation 17,18 are commonly observed conse-
quences of increased arterial stiffness and these features 
mirror those seen in patients with HFpEF. 19 
Furthermore, aorta stiffening in selected populations 
of HFpEF is correlated positively with natriuretic pep-
tide level and negatively with peak oxygen uptake on 
exercise. 2,3,18 Similarly in the RDT-PEF cohort, pulse 
pressure was correlated with heart failure symptoms 
and exercise performance. 
The large conduit blood vessels function to trans-
form pulsatile flow generated from the heart to a con-
tinuous uniform flow at a lower pressure throughout 
systole and diastole enabling downstream organ perfu-
sion. 20 Arterial stiffness shifts the transition point from 
pulsatile flow to continuous, distally from the macro-
vasculature to the microvasculature, which causes end-
organ damage and has been extensively demonstrated 
in the kidneys. 21 This is important, as HFpEF is a 
condition driven by both cardiac and non-cardiac 
pathology. 22 
Based on these previously published data, it is rea-
sonable to hypothesize that therapies to reverse arterial 
stiffness and improve ventricular-arterial coupling 
might be beneficial in patients with HFpEF. 3 In heart 
failure (both HFpEF and HFrEF), neurohumoral acti-
vation (including the SNS) and inflammation leading to 
endothelial dysfunction have been identified as explana-
tory mechanisms (and hence targets) for increased vas-
cular stiffness. 3,22 
Randomised controlled trials in HFpEF have failed 
to identify an intervention that can reduce aorta stiff-
ness in patients with HFpEF. Therapies investigated to 
date include angiotensin-converting-enzyme inhibi-
tors, 23 alagebrium, 24 sildenafil 25 and exercise training. 26 
The RDT-PEF trial joins this long list of neutral trials, </p>

<p>Table 3. Macro-and micro-vascular function. </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>Baseline </p>

<p>Change at 3 months </p>

<p>Change at 12 months </p>

<p>RDT </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>RDT </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>RDT </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>Macro-vascular function </p>

<p>AA strain (%) </p>

<p>3.6 (2.2, 7.6) </p>

<p>3.6 (2.6-5.2) </p>

<p>0.977 </p>

<p>þ0.8 
(À1.0, 1.4) </p>

<p>þ0.1 
(À2, 2.7) </p>

<p>0.881 </p>

<p>À0.0 
(À2.6, 0.8) </p>

<p>þ1.3 
(À2.4, 3.0) </p>

<p>0.260 </p>

<p>AA disten. 
(10 À3 </p>

<p>mmHg À1 </p>

<p>) 
0.66 (0.41-1.19) </p>

<p>0.76 (0.42-0.87) </p>

<p>0.798 </p>

<p>þ0.06 
(À0.15, 0.40) </p>

<p>þ0.12 
(À0.40, 0.61) </p>

<p>0.976 </p>

<p>þ0.02 
(À0.24, 0.25) </p>

<p>þ0.25 
(À0.26, 0.38) </p>

<p>0.455 </p>

<p>DA strain (%) </p>

<p>8.0 (6.8-10.0) </p>

<p>8.2 (4.8-9.6) </p>

<p>0.711 </p>

<p>þ1.0 
(À2.2, 2.5) </p>

<p>þ1.0 
(À0.1, 1.3) </p>

<p>1.000 </p>

<p>þ0.2 
(À1.5, 1.1) </p>

<p>À0.3 
(À0.7, 1.5) </p>

<p>0.664 </p>

<p>DA disten. 
(10 À3 </p>

<p>mmHg À1 </p>

<p>) 
1.44 (1.09-1.76) </p>

<p>1.22 (1.06-1.31) </p>

<p>0.262 </p>

<p>þ0.34 
(À0.37, 0.61) </p>

<p>þ0.07 
(À0.31, 0.77) </p>

<p>0.928 </p>

<p>þ0.16 
(À0.14, 0.42) </p>

<p>þ0.02 
(0.00, 0.42) </p>

<p>0.932 </p>

<p>Pulse wave 
velocity (m/s) </p>

<p>9.61 (5.62-11.7) </p>

<p>9.03 (6.73-19.66) </p>

<p>0.466 </p>

<p>þ0.87 
(À0.65, 2.16) </p>

<p>þ1.26 
(À3.61, 10.86) </p>

<p>0.815 </p>

<p>þ1.49 
(À0.09, 3.21)* </p>

<p>þ0.36 
(À2.51, 3.44) </p>

<p>0.447 </p>

<p>AI (at 75 bpm) (%) </p>

<p>4 (À7, 20) </p>

<p>8 (À3, 17) </p>

<p>0.921 </p>

<p>À3 
(À10, 11) </p>

<p>À4 
(À13, 17) </p>

<p>0.831 </p>

<p>À2 
(À9, 8) </p>

<p>þ2 
(À3, 15) </p>

<p>0.341 </p>

<p>Micro-vascular function </p>

<p>Ln RHI </p>

<p>0.39 AE </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>0.56 AE </p>

<p>0.34 </p>

<p>0.133 </p>

<p>þ0.03 AE </p>

<p>0.24 </p>

<p>À0.13 AE </p>

<p>0.14 </p>

<p>0.098 </p>

<p>À0.03 AE </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>þ0.00 AE </p>

<p>0.42 </p>

<p>0.788 </p>

<p>Urine ACR (mg/mg) </p>

<p>40 (10-139) </p>

<p>32 (9-75) </p>

<p>0.665 </p>

<p>þ3 
(À88, 42) </p>

<p>À2 
(À17, 21) </p>

<p>0.949 </p>

<p>þ10 
(À3, 199) </p>

<p>À0 
(À26, 12) </p>

<p>0.357 </p>

<p>AA: ascending aorta; DA: descending aorta; AI: augmentation index; LnRHI: natural log of reactive hyperaemic index; ACR: albumin:creatinine; disten.: distensibility. 
*P &lt; 
0.05 (for within group change). </p>

<p>Patel et al. </p>

<p>
even though there was a signal for improvement in 
exercise performance and E/e' at 3 months (albeit not 
sustained to 12 months follow-up) in those patients 
randomised to RDT this was not associated with an 
improvement in vascular function. A common theme 
in the discussions following all of these trials is that 
patients with HFpEF are heterogeneous and that 
future trials should target therapies according to the 
underlying dominant pathophysiology, e.g. a trial of a 
new therapy that improves vascular function should 
recruit HFpEF patients who all have proven abnormal 
vascular responsiveness, which historically has not been 
done. </p>

<p>An important observation is that all these trials have 
used different modalities (invasive pressure catheters, 
echocardiography, MR, tonometry, oscillometric 
cuffs) as well as different parameters (carotid femoral 
PWV, carotid-radial PWV, brachial-ankle, PWV, 
ascending-thoracic aorta PWV, aorta distensibility, 
AI, reactive hyperaemic index, albuminuria) to measure 
arterial stiffness and function. The difficulty with this is 
that each combination has varying repeatability and 
furthermore provides a different insight into the 
macro-and micro-vasculature function that is not com-
parable. The American Heart Association have recently 
published a guidance document on how to assess </p>

<p>Table 4. Renal magnetic resonance derived markers of blood flow. </p>

<p>Renal blood flow 
parameters </p>

<p>Baseline 
Change at 12 months </p>

<p>RDT 
Control 
P 
RDT 
Control 
P </p>

<p>Right renal artery 
Flow (L/min) 
0.21 AE 0.06 
0.26 AE 0.06 
0.181 
þ0.08 AE 0.23 
À0.04 AE 0.07 
0.240 
Pulsatility index 
2.84 (1.34-4.05) 
1.49 (1.33-2.22) 
0.180 
À0.5 (À1.85, 0.42) 
þ0.20 (À0.12, 0.90) 
0.125 
Resistive index 
0.90 AE 0.12 
0.78 AE 0.07 
0.038 
À0.05 AE 0.16 
þ0.06 AE 0.14 
0.160 
n 
12 
6 
12 
6 
Left renal artery 
Flow (L/min) 
0.24 AE 0.09 
0.16 AE 0.09 
0.121 
þ0.02 AE 0.12 
þ0.06 AE 0.13 
0.524 
Pulsatility index 
2.15 (1.53-3.75) 
1.60 (1.57-2.09) 
0.221 
þ0.20 (À0.97, 0.64) 
À0.13 (À0.33, 0.64) 
0.743 
Resistive index 
0.90 AE 0.10 
0.84 AE 0.06 
0.198 
þ0.07 AE 0.17 
þ0.03 AE 0.15 
0.679 
n 
11 
5 
11 
5 </p>

<p>Table 5. Spearman's correlation between baseline vascular function and baseline primary efficacy endpoints and estimated glom-
erular filtration rate (eGFR). </p>

<p>MLWHFQ 
Peak VO2 
BNP 
E/e' 
LAVi 
LVMi 
eGFR </p>

<p>rho 
P 
rho 
P 
rho 
P 
rho 
P 
rho 
P 
rho 
P 
rho 
P </p>

<p>24-h SBP 
0.33 
0.11 À0.27 0.19 
0.23 
0.27 0.23 
0.26 0.17 
0.41 0.04 
0.85 À0.03 0.89 
24-h DBP 
À0.14 0.51 0.35 
0.09 
À0.04 0.84 À0.17 0.42 0.32 
0.12 À0.09 0.68 0.11 
0.60 
24-h PP 
0.50 
0.01 À0.52 0.008 0.21 
0.31 À0.42 0.04 0.15 
0.48 0.10 
0.65 À0.12 0.58 
AA distensibility À0.33 0.11 0.05 
0.82 
0.16 
0.44 0.15 
0.48 À0.03 0.89 À0.08 0.71 0.31 
0.13 
DA distensibility À0.12 0.57 À0.06 0.77 
0.43 
0.03 À0.11 0.59 À0.25 0.23 À0.07 0.73 0.03 
0.88 
PWV 
0.04 
0.87 0.01 
0.98 
À0.23 0.29 À0.09 0.67 0.17 
0.44 À0.41 0.05 À0.38 0.07 
AI (75 bpm) 
0.22 
0.29 À0.26 0.21 
À0.10 0.64 0.14 
0.52 À0.01 0.97 À0.02 0.93 0.18 
0.38 
Ln RHI 
À0.08 0.77 0.20 
0.33 
À0.27 0.19 0.42 
0.04 0.00 
0.99 0.02 
0.95 0.16 
0.46 
UACR 
0.38 
0.11 À0.23 0.36 
À0.06 0.80 0.12 
0.63 0.13 
0.61 0.21 
0.38 À0.23 0.34 
Mean RBF 
À0.28 0.27 0.25 
0.31 
0.06 
0.82 À0.27 0.28 À0.10 0.71 À0.55 0.02 0.12 
0.65 
Mean PI 
0.30 
0.23 À0.20 0.42 
0.12 
0.63 0.03 
0.89 À0.26 0.29 0.45 
0.06 0.08 
0.75 
Mean RI 
0.32 
0.20 À0.35 0.16 
0.36 
0.15 0.02 
0.95 0.01 
0.97 0.23 
0.36 À0.04 0.88 </p>

<p>The numbers in bold are the values that reached statistical significance. 
AA: ascending aorta; DA: descending aorta; AI: augmentation index; LnRHI: natural log of reactive hyperaemic index; UACR: urine albumin:creatinine; 
RBF: renal blood flow; PI: pulsatility index; RI: resistive index. </p>

<p> 
Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine Cardiovascular Disease 0(0) </p>

<p>arterial stiffness in research and discuss the lack of a 
widely adopted and rigorous method of vascular func-
tion investigation. 27 They promote the carotid-femoral 
PWV technique for non-invasive assessment of arterial 
stiffness. Though this is valuable guidance, it is sobering 
to note that using data from the RDT-PEF cohort, 
approximately 536 patients would need to be recruited 
for an intervention to detect a 15% change in PWV 
(80% power, P ¼ 0.05, standard deviation ¼ 6.2 m/s), 
which for many research units seeking to investigate a 
HFpEF population might be prohibitive. 
It is possible that arterial stiffness is not an ideal 
endpoint to use in an HFpEF clinical trial. The major-
ity of the evidence showing that an intervention can 
improve arterial stiffness has been in the context of 
hypertension trials; it is unknown whether the aorta 
can be 'unstiffened' independent of a blood pressure 
reduction. 27 Also, patients recruited into HFpEF 
trials tend to be older than those in hypertension 
trials and consequently reversal of aorta stiffening 
with an intervention may take longer to manifest 
(requiring prolonged trial follow-up) or may be impos-
sible reflecting an irreversible stage of the disease 
process. 
We have demonstrated that RDT did not have an 
effect on blood pressure up to 12 months of follow-up, 
which is an important safety finding as the majority of 
patients with heart failure are not hypertensive. This 
has previously only been demonstrated in an uncon-
trolled study of seven patients with heart failure and 
reduced ejection fraction at 6 months follow-up. 28 
Finally, improvement in renal blood flow is one of 
the purported mechanisms of action of RDT. In nine 
pigs, Tsioufis and colleagues showed that RDT both 
acutely and chronically after a month increased renal 
blood flow and reduced resistive index, assessed by an 
invasive Doppler wire. We were not able to reproduce 
this finding in 25 humans using spiral renal MR. 
Similarly in resistant hypertension, improvements in 
renal perfusion and oxygenation as assessed by MR 
have not been demonstrated following RDT, 5 though 
one group showed a decrease in resistive index (derived 
from ultrasound). 7 These neutral findings might just 
reflect the fact that the kidneys are well auto-regulated 
via multiple regulatory mechanisms, which are not all 
dependent on the SNS. In our population, the high 
burden of atrial fibrillation may have further compli-
cated imaging and flow assessments. 
The main limitation of study is its small size. 
However, this is the first report of RDT in an 
HFpEF population and hence the data presented 
should be used as valuable pilot data to inform 
sample size calculation for future work in this 
field. Several controversies remain that need to be 
addressed before the future role if any of RDT can be </p>

<p>ascertained: first, with the technology (multi-electrode 
vs. single-electrode systems) and how best to apply it 
(number and location of ablations in the renal artery). 
When this study was conceived, the Symplicity TM 
single-electrode device was the only system with support-
ing efficacy and safety data, which is why it was used. 
Over the subsequent years, it has become apparent that 
multi-electrode systems are more likely to achieve a com-
prehensive denervation. 8 Furthermore, it is likely that the 
initial technique, which limited four to six ablations in the 
proximal renal artery prior to any bifurcations may have 
been too conservative with current data supporting more 
ablations that also extend to distal branch vessels. 29 
Consequently, it remains unknown what the efficacy or 
safety of contemporary RDT on patients with heart 
failure are. 30 Finally, until an approach to accurately 
quantify the effects of RDT on renal sympathetic nerves 
is developed, it will remain difficult for future phase II 
studies to show a 'dose-response' effect, which will limit 
the credibility of any findings. 6 </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Renal denervation did not reduce blood pressure in a 
population of HFpEF, the majority of whom were 
normotensive; this is an important safety consideration. 
The intervention did not improve markers of vascular 
dysfunction, though with the limited numbers, in this 
study, it was underpowered to do so. It remains 
unknown whether pulse wave velocity is a modifiable 
risk marker in HFpEF. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We are grateful to the cardiovascular imaging team from the 
Laboratoire d'Imagerie Biome´dicale, INSERM, France for 
supplying the <rs type="software">ART-FUN</rs> software for analysis. We are 
indebted to the teams at Imperial College Healthcare trust 
and Guys and St Thomas Healthcare trust who identified 
patients suitable for inclusion in this trial. We are grateful 
to Iulia Munteanu and Sally-Ann McNae who served as the 
research nurses on this study. </p>

<p>Declaration of conflicting interests </p>

<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with 
respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this 
article. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial sup-
port for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this 
article: This study was sponsored by the Royal Brompton and 
Harefield NHS trust. The work was supported by the National 
Institute of Health Research (NIHR) Cardiovascular 
Biomedical Research Unit, Royal Brompton Hospital and 
Imperial College, London, UK. ARL is supported by a 
British Heart Foundation Intermediate Research Fellowship. </p>

<p>Patel et al. </p>

<p>
Ethical approval </p>

<p>National Research Ethics Service (12/LO/1941). </p>

<p>Guarantor </p>

<p>HCP. </p>

<p>Contributorship </p>

<p>HCP, CH, JK, PDG, RHM, RK, SDR, ARL and CDM 
contributed to the design of the study. HCP, JK, PDG, 
RR, RHM and RK were involved in data collection. HCP 
wrote the first draft. All authors contributed to and approved 
the final version. </p>



<p> 
Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine Cardiovascular Disease 0(0) </p>



<p>Patel et al. </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>