<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5108413" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) is a common cause of signs of gastrointestinal disease in cats. A subset of 
cats with IBD has neutrophilic inflammation of the intestinal mucosa. 
Hypothesis: Neutrophilic enteritis in cats is associated with mucosal invasion by microorganisms, and specifically Campy-
lobacter spp. 
Animals: Seven cats with neutrophilic IBD and 8 cats with lymphoplasmacytic IBD. 
Methods: Retrospective review of duodenal biopsy specimens that were collected endoscopically for histologic examina-
tion. Cases were identified and selected by searching the histopathology archive for cats with a diagnosis of neutrophilic and 
lymphoplasmacytic IBD. Fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) targeting either all eubacteria or individual Campylobacter 
spp. was performed on archived samples. Neutrophils were detected on the same samples using a FISH probe for neutrophil 
elastase. 
Results: Campylobacter coli was present in (6/7) cats with neutrophilic IBD and in (1/8) cats with lymphoplasmacytic 
IBD (P = .009). Cats with neutrophilic IBD had significantly higher number of C. coli (median bacteria 0.7/hpf) in the 
mucosa than cats with lymphoplasmacytic IBD (median bacteria 0/hpf) (P = 0.002). Colocalization of neutrophils and C. coli 
was demonstrated, with C. coli closer to the neutrophils than any other bacteria (P &lt; .001). 
Conclusions and clinical importance: Identification of C. coli associated with neutrophilic inflammation suggests that 
C. coli is able either to produce compounds which stimulate neutrophils or to induce feline intestinal cells to produce neu-
trophil chemoattractants. This association should allow a directed therapeutic approach in cats with neutrophilic IBD, poten-
tially improving outcome and reducing any zoonotic risk. 
I </p>

<p>nflammatory bowel disease (IBD) is a common cause 
of chronic signs in cats with gastrointestinal disease. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Intestinal biopsies are needed to confirm intestinal 
inflammation, but cases are deemed idiopathic if no 
underlying cause is found. 
1-3 Typically, lymphoplasma-
cytic inflammation is found in biopsy specimens, but a 
subset of cats with IBD has neutrophilic inflammation 
of the intestinal mucosa. The clinical relevance of neu-
trophilic infiltration is unclear. It might be secondary to 
bacterial infection, but neutrophilic colitis is seen with 
Tritrichomonas foetus infection 
4 and a case of suppura-
tive colitis in a cat was described </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>, where no bacterial 
infection could be identified. Mucosal friability and ero-
sions might also induce neutrophilic infiltrates because 
of the loss of mucosal barrier integrity. If no etiological 
agent is identified, directed or appropriate treatment is </p>

<p>unclear and empirical antibacterial treatment might be 
prescribed. 
Using more traditional diagnostic techniques, the evi-
dence for infectious agents causing neutrophilic intesti-
nal inflammation is poor. The clinical relevance of 
identifying bacteria in fecal samples is unclear as they 
might be found in the feces of healthy cats as well as in 
those with diarrhea. </p>

<p>6-9 </p>

<p>The use of fluorescent in situ hybridization (FISH) 
has enabled detection and visualization of intact bacte-
ria within tissues and their localization as part of under-
standing the ecology of a disease process. 
10 In small 
animal gastrointestinal research, FISH has been used to 
demonstrate gastric Helicobacter spp. infections and 
clearance of these bacteria with treatment, 
11 and that 
attaching and invasive E. coli (AIEC) are associated 
with granulomatous colitis in Boxers and can be eradi-
cated with prolonged antibiotics, 
12,13 Janeczko 
14 used 
FISH and showed higher number of mucosa-associated </p>

<p>From the School of Veterinary Sciences, University of Bristol, 
Langford, UK (Maunder, Reynolds, Peacock, Hall, Day, Cogan). 
The work in this study was performed at the School of Veterinary 
Sciences, University of Bristol and supported by a grant from the 
Langford Trust. The abstract from this paper was presented at the 
European College of Veterinary Internal Medicine Congress in Lis-
bon, Portugal 2015. 
Corresponding author: C. Maunder, Small Animal Hospital, 
School of Veterinary Sciences, University of Bristol, Langford House, 
Langford, Bristol, BS40 5DU, UK; e-mail: C.Maunder@bristol.ac.uk </p>

<p>Submitted October 21, 2015; Revised February 19, 2016; 
Accepted June 11, 2016. </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016 The Authors. Journal of Veterinary Internal 
Medicine published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of the Ameri-
can College of Veterinary Internal Medicine. 
This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License, which permits use, 
distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original 
work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes. 
DOI: 10.1111/jvim.14374 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: </p>

<p>12-LOX 
12-lipoxygenase 
AIEC 
attaching and invasive E. coli 
DNA 
deoxyribonucleic acid 
FCEAI 
feline chronic enteropathy activity index 
FISH 
fluorescence in situ hybridization 
H &amp; E 
hematoxylin and eosin 
HPF 
high-powered field 
IBD 
inflammatory bowel disease 
IL-8 
interleukin 8 
NF-jB 
nuclear factor kappa beta 
PCR 
polymerase chain reaction 
rRNA 
16S ribosomal ribonucleic acid 
WSAVA 
World Small Animal Veterinary Association </p>

<p>J Vet Intern Med 2016;30:996-1001 </p>

<p>Enterobacteriaceae in cats with gastrointestinal signs 
compared with healthy cats, although it was not clear 
whether this association was the cause of the inflamma-
tion or a consequence of the mucosal disruption and 
altered environment selecting for bacterial dysbiosis. 
The aims of this study were: (1) to determine the 
presence, and identity of intact bacteria within feline 
intestinal biopsy specimens using FISH and (2) to deter-
mine the location of neutrophils and their proximity to 
any bacteria to demonstrate an association and possible 
bacterial etiology. </p>

<p>Materials &amp; Methods </p>

<p>Study Population </p>

<p>Cases from which there was histopathologic assessment of 
endoscopic intestinal biopsy specimens at the University of Bristol, 
School of Veterinary Sciences, were identified from the pathology 
archive and the biopsy specimens were reviewed. The inclusion 
criteria were that duodenal biopsy specimens had a diagnosis of 
neutrophilic or lymphoplasmacytic inflammation and were of ade-
quate quality and size for FISH to be performed requiring at least 
3 well-oriented villi with subvillus lamina propria extending to the 
muscularis mucosa in each section. 
Samples from 15 cats (7 with neutrophilic IBD and 8 with lym-
phoplasmacytic IBD) met the inclusion criteria for the study and 
also had sufficient intestinal tissue archived as formalin-fixed and 
paraffin wax-embedded material. The signalment of these cats was 
documented, but the clinical severity and response to treatment 
was not uniformly reported. Ethical approval for the study was 
granted by the University of Bristol Ethics Committee. Samples 
from all cats were retrospectively analyzed for intestinal bacterial 
pathogens by PCR as detailed below. </p>

<p>Histopathologic Analysis </p>

<p>In every case, hematoxylin and eosin-stained sections of the 
duodenal biopsy specimens were reviewed, without knowledge of 
the case history, by a Board-certified veterinary pathologist 
(MJD). The histopathologic changes were graded according to the 
scoring system developed by the World Small Animal Veterinary 
Association (WSAVA) Gastrointestinal Standardization Group. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Five parameters of inflammation (ie, intraepithelial lymphocytes, 
lamina propria lymphocytes, plasma cells, eosinophils and neu-
trophils, and other inflammatory cell types within the lamina pro-
pria) were evaluated. Morphologic features of mucosal 
inflammation (villus stunting, epithelial injury, crypt dilatation/dis-
tortion, lacteal dilatation, and mucosal fibrosis) were also evalu-
ated. Changes in morphological features were noted, but there was </p>

<p>no appreciable difference between groups, with a range of none-
moderate within each group. The final diagnosis was categorized 
as 1 of 8 different histopathologic diagnoses: no abnormalities 
detected (NAD), lymphoplasmacytic inflammatory, eosinophilic 
inflammatory, neutrophilic inflammatory, lymphangiectasia, lym-
phoma, mucosal atrophy/fibrosis (noninflammatory) and other. 
Only samples from cats with lymphoplasmacytic inflammatory 
histopathologic changes and neutrophilic inflammatory histopatho-
logic changes were included in the study. </p>

<p>Fluorescence In Situ Hybridization-Bacteria </p>

<p>Fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) was performed on 
formalin-fixed and paraffin wax-embedded duodenal biopsy speci-
mens using a method slightly modified from that previously 
reported in the literature, in that hybridization buffer containing 
25% formamide was used as opposed to buffer containing 30% 
formamide in the previous study. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>16S ribosomal RNA (rRNA)-directed fluorescence-labeled 
oligonucleotide probes were used (Table 1). Successive sections from 
each biopsy specimen were analyzed in steps, each employing a dif-
ferent probe mix. Steps one and two were general probes for Eubac-
teria and Firmicutes using three different probes for each bacterial 
group. A mixture of probes with slight base variations were used to 
maximize the spectrum of coverage of each probe mix. The third step 
used specific probes for Campylobacter species. These were used in 
combination with one probe labeling C. upsaliensis, another probe 
for C. jejuni, and a final probe labeling all thermophilic Campylobac-
ter spp. Bacteria labeled solely by this last probe could either be 
C. lari or C. coli and were speciated by subsequent polymerase chain 
reaction (PCR). We did not examine the sections for E. coli and 
would not, using these methods, have been able to detect AIEC. 
Processed slides were mounted with glass cover slips with hard-
set Vectashield mounting medium containing DAPI. Once set, 
slides were examined with a Leica DMR-A Microscope equipped 
with a monochrome Hamamatsu 8-bit digital camera. Bacterial 
cells in the epithelium and lamina propria were counted at 9400 
magnification by a single blinded observer across 10 fields of view, 
and an average count was obtained. Fields of view were chosen as 
being central to a biopsy and including epithelium and so that not 
more than 2 were viewed for a single biopsy. </p>

<p>Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) </p>

<p>DNA was extracted from pooled multiple sections of tissue 
using a DNeasyTM blood and tissue kit (Qiagen, Manchester, 
UK). This was screened by Langford Veterinary Services (Bristol, 
UK) for the presence of Salmonella, pathogenic E. coli, Campy-
lobacter spp., and Clostridium spp. A 153-bp DNA fragment 
unique to Campylobacter was amplified by PCR 
17 and sequenced 
to confirm the Campylobacter species present. </p>

<p>Table 1. FISH oligonucleotide probes. Details of sequences of oligonucleotide probes used for in situ localization 
of bacterial species within duodenal biopsy tissues. </p>

<p>Probe name 
Bacterial target 
Sequence (5 
0 -&gt;3 
0 ) 
5 
0 -Modification </p>

<p>EUB338 
Eubacteria 
GCTGCCTCCCGTAGGAGT 
FITC 
Step 1 
EUB338-II 
Eubacteria 
GCAGCCACCCGTAGGTGT 
FITC 
Step 1 
EUB338-III 
Eubacteria 
GCTGCCACCCGTAGGTGT 
FITC 
Step 1 
LGC354A 
Firmicutes 
TGGAAGATTCCCTACTGC 
Texas Red 
Step 2 
LGC354B 
Firmicutes 
CGGAAGATTCCCTACTGC 
Texas Red 
Step 2 
LGC354C 
Firmicutes 
CCGAAGATTCCCTACTGC 
Texas Red 
Step 2 
Catherm 
Thermophilic Campylobacter 
GCCCTAAGCGTCCTTCCA 
Texas Red 
Step 3 
Cajej 
Campylobacter jejuni 
AGCTAACCACACCTTATACCG 
FITC 
Step 3 
CaUp 
Campylobacter upsaliensis 
CTCTACAGAATTTGTTGGAT 
AF350 
Step 3 </p>

<p>Neutrophilic IBD in Cats </p>

<p>
Fluorescent In Situ Hybridization-Colocalization of 
Bacteria and Neutrophils </p>

<p>Campylobacter jejuni and thermophilic Campylobacter spp. 
probes were used in combination with a FISH probe designed to 
detect feline neutrophil elastase mRNA. The feline neutrophil elas-
tase probe 5 
0 CAGAGGCTGCTGAACGACATCGTGATTCTC 
CAGCTCAAT3 
0 was used concurrently with Campylobacter spp. 
probes (Thermophilic Campylobacter spp. 5 
0 GCCCTAAGCGTCC 
TTCCA 3 
0 and C. jejuni 5 
0 AGCTAACCACACCTTATACCG 3 
0 ). 
Slides were viewed under fluorescence using a DMRB micro-
scope (Leica) equipped with a Retiga EXi camera (QImaging) 
and <rs id="software-0" type="software">Volocity</rs> imaging software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">PerkinElmer</rs>) and searched for 
the expression of feline neutrophil elastase and Campylobacter. 
Images were taken when a field of view (9400 objective) con-
tained a neutrophil elastase expressor and one or both of the 
Campylobacter expressors. A record was made of any neutrophil 
elastase expressors that did not have a Campylobacter expressor 
in the same field, as well as the overall presence of C. jejuni and 
thermophilic Campylobacter. <rs id="software-1" type="software">Image J</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij</rs>) was used after images had been captured to 
allow automated measurement of the distance between two points 
selected by the user-neutrophil and Campylobacter. The dis-
tance was measured in pixels on the digital images. The maxi-
mum field size used was 1850 pixels. The use of this software 
allowed multiple accurate measurements to be taken and com-
piled for statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>Analysis was performed using statistical software; <rs id="software-2" type="software">GraphPad 
Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 5.03</rs>. The presence of bacteria in the cats with neu-
trophilic and lymphoplasmacytic IBD was compared and tested 
for statistical significance using Chi-squared testing. </p>

<p>Differences between the group with neutrophilic inflammation 
and the group with lymphoplasmacytic inflammation in the num-
ber of bacteria of different species found in tissue were analyzed 
using a Mann-Whitney U-test. Similarly, differences in the pixel 
distance between C. jejuni and neutrophils or C. coli and neu-
trophils were analyzed using the same test. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Fifteen cats met the inclusion criteria: 8 were domes-
tic short hair (DSH), 1 was domestic long hair (DLH), 
and 5 were pure breeds (Maine Coon, Birman, Oriental, 
and 2 Siamese). There was no breed recorded for one of 
the biopsy specimens. The age range was 2-15 years 
(median 9 years). There were 11 male cats and 4 female 
cats. Bacterial DNA extraction results for all the cats 
showed than none were positive for Salmonella or 
pathogenic genotypes of E. coli (a definition which 
excludes AIEC). One animal in each group was positive 
for Clostridium spp. All were Campylobacter positive. 
Sequencing for Campylobacter to separate the ther-
mophilic species showed that C. lari and C. upsaliensis 
could not be detected in tissues (data not shown). Only 
the species C. coli and C. jejuni were present in tissues. 
The PCR speciation results concurred with FISH results 
(Fig 1). </p>

<p>Presence of Bacteria in the Cats with Neutrophilic 
IBD and the Cats with Lymphoplasmacytic IBD </p>

<p>Bacteria were identified within the mucosa of cats 
with either neutrophilic or lymphoplasmacytic </p>

<p>Fig 1. A Shows the number of C. jejuni within the mucosa of the cats with neutrophilic inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) and the cats 
with lymphoplasmacytic IBD. B Shows the number of C. coli within the mucosa of the cats with neutrophilic IBD and the cats with lym-
phoplasmacytic IBD. C Frequency of finding C. jejuni within the mucosa of the cats with neutrophilic IBD and the cats with lymphoplas-
macytic IBD. D Frequency of finding C. coli within the mucosa of the cats with neutrophilic IBD and the cats with lymphoplasmacytic 
IBD </p>

<p> 
Maunder et al </p>

<p>inflammation. There was no significant difference in 
the number of Eubacteria seen in specimens from 
either of the two groups. There were few C. upsalien-
sis and further statistical analysis was not possible. 
C. jejuni and C. coli were present in greater number 
and so the distribution of these organisms between 
the neutrophilic group and lymphoplasmacytic group 
of cats was compared. There was no significant differ-
ence between the presence of C. jejuni within the 
mucosa of the cats with neutrophilic or lymphoplas-
macytic inflammation. However, C. coli was more 
prevalent in the mucosa of cats with neutrophilic 
inflammation (6/7) compared with cats with lympho-
plasmacytic inflammation (1/8) and this distribution 
was significant (P = .009) (Fig 1). </p>

<p>Number of Bacteria in the Cats with Neutrophilic IBD 
and the Cats with Lymphoplasmacytic IBD </p>

<p>The number of C. jejuni and C. coli within the mucosa 
of the cats with neutrophilic inflammation and cats with 
lymphoplasmacytic inflammation were then compared. 
For C. jejuni the numbers were similar in both groups 
and there was no significant difference in distribution. 
However, for C. coli the numbers were greater within 
the cats with neutrophilic inflammation (median number 
of bacteria per high-powered field of view [9400 magni-
fication] was 0.7) compared to the cats with lymphoplas-
macytic inflammation (median number of bacteria per 
high-powered field of view was 0) and this difference was 
significant (P = 0.002). (Fig 1). </p>

<p>Coocalization of Bacteria with Neutrophils </p>

<p>There was an insufficient number of neutrophils within 
the mucosa of cats with lymphoplasmacytic inflammation 
to investigate the association with microorganisms, as 62 
of the 63 fields of view examined did not show Campy-
lobacter and a neutrophil in the same field of view. 
Within the mucosa of cats with neutrophilic inflamma-
tion, only 6 of the 63 fields of view examined did not 
show Campylobacter and a neutrophil in the same field of 
view. Cells expressing neutrophil elastase had typical 
PMN morphology on light microscopy. 
Within the mucosa of cats with neutrophilic inflam-
mation the colocalization of C. jejuni and C. coli was 
analyzed; C. upsaliensis numbers were again too few for 
statistical analysis. For C. jejuni there was no evidence 
of an association between location of the bacteria and 
that of the neutrophils and often no organism was seen 
within the same field of view as a neutrophil (&gt;1850 pix-
els). For C. coli, there was an association between the 
location of the organism and that of the neutrophils 
(P &lt; .001) (Fig 2). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Inflammatory bowel disease is one cause of chronic 
signs of gastrointestinal disease in cats, others include 
adverse food reactions, antibiotic responsive enteropathy, 
and infection (virus, fungi, bacterial, protozoal, or </p>

<p>parasitic). Cases with histopathologic changes consistent 
with neutrophilic inflammation may result from mucosal 
invasion by microorganisms, develop secondary to muco-
sal defects, or Tritrichomonas foetus infection or be idio-
pathic. The aims of this study were to use FISH to 
elucidate the presence of mucosal bacterial invasion in 
feline IBD, and to identify any association between 
Campylobacter invasion and neutrophilic inflammation 
(Picture 1). 
Bacteria were identified within the mucosa of cats 
with both neutrophilic and lymphoplasmacytic inflam-
mation, suggesting mucosal disruption. There was no 
clear pattern to their localization (mucosa/submucosa/ 
lamina propria) within the tissue. The total numbers of 
bacteria did not differ between groups and for two </p>

<p>Fig 2. Proximity of Campylobacter coli is closer to neutrophils as 
compared to C. jejuni. Data show pixel distance of neutrophils to 
Campylobacter as measured by <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software. The maximal 
pixel distance per field is 1850 pixels; when a field of view did not 
contain both a Campylobacter and a neutrophil distance was 
recorded as 1850 pixels. </p>

<p>Picture 1. Fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) demonstrat-
ing red fluorescence for a thermophilic Campylobacter species 
(C. coli) and blue fluorescence for neutrophil elastase. Not all bac-
teria are highlighted in a single sectional view as organisms outside 
the plane of focus are not visible in a single image. </p>

<p>Neutrophilic IBD in Cats </p>

<p>
bacterial species (C. jejuni and C. upsaliensis) there was 
also no difference in distribution between the two 
groups. A significant difference was found between the 
two groups regarding the presence of C. coli. This in 
itself is simply an observation and merely demonstrates 
an increased presence of C. coli in cats with neu-
trophilic inflammation. However, FISH neutrophil elas-
tase probes demonstrated close proximity to neutrophils 
and confirmed the possible association with C. coli. No 
association between neutrophil location and other spe-
cies of bacteria was demonstrated. This association sup-
ports the hypothesis that C. coli is particularly 
associated with a specific neutrophilic form of inflam-
mation in the duodenal mucosa of cats with enteric dis-
ease compared with other microorganisms. 
Campylobacter species are known to be powerful 
chemoattractants for neutrophils. Previous in vitro stud-
ies with porcine and human epithelial cells have shown 
that C. jejuni and C. coli induce neutrophilic intestinal 
inflammation via activation of NF-jB and subsequent 
production of the neutrophil chemokine IL-8 and also 
induce migration of neutrophils across the epithelium 
via the production of chemotactic n-formyl peptides in 
concert with metabolites of 12-LOX. 
18,19 In the present 
retrospective study there was evidence that C. coli, but 
not C. jejuni, appears to colocalize with neutrophils and 
therefore might be acting as the etiological agent in this 
particular subset of feline inflammatory bowel disease, 
although other cell types and mechanisms could be 
involved. In vitro studies using feline neutrophils 
similarly to previous work on porcine neutrophils </p>

<p>18,19 </p>

<p>would be necessary to determine a mechanism for 
chemoattraction. 
Limitations of the study mostly relate to its retrospec-
tive nature and the lack of clinical data. Once the inclu-
sion criteria were met, the numbers recruited to each 
group were small because samples had to be of suffi-
cient quality for histopathological review and of ade-
quate volume for the subsequent molecular diagnostic 
tests to be performed. 
We were unable to document any differences in 
clinical presentation between the two groups or to 
assess data relating to treatment and outcome as the 
cases were not always treated in our hospital; these 
were drawn from a pathology archive so the remit of 
this study is specifically to associate bacteria with 
pathology. The lack of clinical data means we are 
unable to determine if any of the cats received antibi-
otic treatment before endoscopic biopsy collection. 
This is a potential confounding effect but prior antibi-
otic treatment would be expected to reduce bacterial 
numbers and the likelihood of finding a significant dif-
ference between the groups, except in the unlikely 
event that all the cats with lymphoplasmacytic IBD 
were treated with antibiotics and none of the cats 
with neutrophilic IBD were. Fecal analysis from each 
cat might also have been useful to determine whether 
Campylobacter spp. had been identified on culture. A 
prospective study based on the findings of this work 
would be necessary to evaluate clinical and treatment 
factors. </p>

<p>The histopathologic classification and subsequent 
analysis was performed on duodenal biopsy specimens 
and these may not reflect the nature of the inflamma-
tory changes elsewhere in the gastrointestinal tract. A 
previous study 
20 showed that in dogs with enteropathy 
that there was poor agreement between histopathologic 
findings in ileal and duodenal biopsy specimens. 
Another study 
21 also showed poor agreement on diag-
nosis between duodenal and ileal biopsy specimens in 
cats; although this distinction, between lymphoplasma-
cytic inflammation and small cell lymphoma, is more 
problematic than simply identifying neutrophilic inflam-
mation. Although it is possible that inflammatory 
changes elsewhere in the gastrointestinal tract were dif-
ferent to the duodenum, our hypothesis related to an 
infectious etiology for the localized neutrophilic inflam-
mation and so our findings remain valid. 
The preliminary findings from this retrospective 
study highlight a need for prospective investigation to 
understand the relevance of the C. coli tissue localiza-
tion. This would allow investigation into whether this 
subset of cats have a different clinical presentation 
and FCEAI score or different endoscopic lesions iden-
tified on endoscopy. Identification of C. coli as a 
potential etiological agent for this subset of cats 
would allow directed treatment and would potentially 
improve the outcome and also reduce any zoonotic 
risk. 
8,22 Further in vitro molecular studies would also 
help determine by what means C. coli induces the 
neutrophilic response: whether it produces compounds 
which stimulate neutrophils or induces feline intestinal 
cells to produce neutrophil chemoattractants. A 
prospective study would also allow an epidemiological 
study of risk factors and the interaction of these cats 
with their owners. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest declaration: Authors declare no 
conflict of interest. 
Off-label Antimicrobial Declaration: Authors declare 
no off-label use of antimicrobials. </p>



<p> 
Maunder et al </p>



<p>Neutrophilic IBD in Cats </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>