<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5130055" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>This study aimed to utilize micro-computed tomography (micro-CT) analysis to compare new bone formation in rat calvarial defects 
using chitosan/fibroin-hydroxyapatite (CFB-HAP) or collagen (Bio-Gide) membranes. Fifty-four (54) rats were studied. A circular bony 
defect (8 mm diameter) was formed in the centre of the calvaria using a trephine bur. The CFB-HAP membrane was prepared by 
thermally induced phase separation. In the experimental group (n518), the CFB-HAP membrane was used to cover the bony defect, 
and in the control group (n518), a resorbable collagen membrane (Bio-Gide) was used. In the negative control group (n518), no 
membrane was used. In each group, six animals were euthanized at 2, 4 and 8 weeks after surgery. The specimens were then analysed 
using micro-CT. There were significant differences in bone volume (BV) and bone mineral density (BMD) (P,0.05) between the 
negative control group and the membrane groups. However, there were no significant differences between the CFB-HAP group and the 
collagen group. We concluded that the CFB-HAP membrane has significant potential as a guided bone regeneration (GBR) membrane. 
4 </p>

<p>The properties required of a GBR barrier membrane are bioactivity 
(osteoinductivity), bioresorption, biocompatibility, a lack of cytotoxicity 
and space-maintaining ability, which is related to mechanical stability 
during the bone healing process. 
1-3 A number of polymeric materials 
have been developed for GBR membranes, including non-degradable 
expanded polytetrafluoroethylene and degradable synthetic (polylactic 
acid and polyglycolic acid) or natural (such as collagen and chitosan) 
polymers. Thin expanded polytetrafluoroethylene membranes have been 
used as barriers that can be safely applied as biologically inert materials. 
However, a non-degradable membrane must be removed by a secondary 
operation including an incision. 
5-6 Degradable polymers are favoured 
for their benefits of being totally degradable within the body and not </p>

<p>requiring a secondary surgical procedure for removal; however, the 
mechanical strength of such membranes is typically low and is difficult 
to adjust. 
6-8 Although bioresorbable collagen membranes have excellent 
cell affinity and biocompatibility, they have the problem of being poten-
tially antigenic and moreover, carry a risk of bovine spongiform ence-
phalopathy transmission. </p>

<p>9-10 </p>

<p>Of the known natural biopolymers considered for biomedical appli-
cations, one greatly attractive material is chitosan, which is a polyhe-
terosaccharide composed of glucosamine and N-acetyl glucosamine 
units linked by 1-4 glucosidic bonds. Much attention has been paid to 
chitosan-based biomedical materials, given their unique properties 
such as biodegradability, non-toxicity, antibacterial effects and bio-
compatibility. </p>

<p>1,11 </p>

<p>Recently, silk fibroin has been considered for a wide variety of 
applications in biomedical materials ranging from skin and vascular 
grafts to substrates for mammalian cell cultures. Fibroin is a linear 
polypeptide that is composed of 17 amino acids and has a b-sheet 
structure because its main components are simple non-polar amino 
acids such as alanine and glycine. It has been reported that silk fibroin 
acts as an enzyme immobilisation matrix with good mechanical pro-
perties and has blood compatibility and good dissolved oxygen per-
meability in the wet state. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>1 Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, School of Dentistry, Pusan National University, Yangsan, Korea and 
2 Department of Biomaterial Science, Pusan National 
University, Miryang, Korea 
Correspondence: Dr SH Shin, Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, School of Dentistry, Pusan National University, Mulgeum-eup, Yangsan 626-787, Korea 
E-mail: ssh8080@pusan.ac.kr 
Accepted 26 January 2014 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science (2014) 6, 87-93 
ß 2014 WCSS. All rights reserved 1674-2818/14 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/ijos </p>

<p>Hydroxyapatite is a major inorganic component of natural bone 
and, owing to its bioactive, biodegradable and osteoconductive pro-
perties, has been used extensively in biomedical implant and bone 
regeneration applications. It is also known to be biocompatible, non-
toxic, non-inflammatory, and non-immunogenic, and it is capable of 
forming a direct chemical bond with surrounding hard tissues. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>In a previous study, we fabricated a chitosan/fibroin-hydroxyapa-
tite (CFB-HAP) composite membrane for bone regeneration because 
of the biocompatibility, resorbability, hemostasis, anti-infectivity, 
plasticity and adhesiveness 
1 of this material. In the present study, we 
employed X-ray micro-computed tomography (micro-CT) analysis to 
compare the new bone formation and healing properties of the CFB-
HAP membrane to those of a collagen (Bio-Gide) membrane that is 
widely used as a barrier membrane in dental practice. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Preparation of CFB-HAP membrane 
The CFB-HAP membrane was prepared by thermally induced phase 
separation and subsequent compression of the thermally induced 
phase separation matrix. The membrane was composed of 56% 
(m/m) chitosan, 14% (m/m) fibroin and 30% (m/m) hydroxyapatite, 
which in a previous paper was ascertained to be the optimum ratio to 
achieve the properties (such as relatively low crystallinity and high 
water absorptivity) of a biomedical matrix. 
1 The chitosan was purified 
by reprecipitation to a degree of deacetylation of 97% and a weight-
averaged molecular weight of 400 000. The fibroin was obtained by 
dialysis from a calcium chloride solution of a degummed Bombyx mori 
silk. The HAP was synthesized to a Ca/P stoichiometric ratio of 1.55 
and an ultimate average particle size of approximately 2 mm. Variations 
of the matrix properties, including chemical composition, pore mor-
phology, microstructure, simulated body fluid absorptivity, protein 
permeability and tenacity were investigated. HAP incorporation 
improved the simulated body fluid absorptivity, protein permeability 
and mechanical strength of the composite while maintaining its high 
porosity and microstructure 
1 (Figure 1). </p>

<p>Collagen membrane 
A collagen membrane is naturally bioresorbable. Bio-Gide (Geistlich 
AG, Wolhusen, Switzerland) is composed of porcine type I and type III 
collagen fibres without any organic components and/or chemicals, 
and it has a bilayer structure composed of one 'compact' and one 
'porous' layer. The compact layer has a smooth and condensed surface </p>

<p>to protect against connective-tissue infiltration, whereas the porous 
layer permits cellular invasion. </p>

<p>Experimental animals 
Fifty-four (54) Sprague-Dawley albino male rats (15 weeks old; 
Koatech, Pyeong-taek, Korea) weighing between 600 g and 800 g were 
used in the experiment. The animals were housed individually in 
standard rat cages maintained under an ambient temperature of 24-
26 6 C and a 12 h light-12 h dark cycle. The animals had free access to 
drinking water and standard laboratory pellets. This study was con-
ducted at the Laboratory Animal Resource Center of Pusan National 
University (Yangsan Campus) and was licensed by the Pusan National 
University Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (PNU-
2011-000219). 
The CFB-HAP membrane was used in the experimental group 
(n518), a resorbable collagen membrane (Bio-Gide) was used in the 
positive control group (n518) and no membrane was used in the 
negative control group (n518). </p>

<p>Anaesthesia and surgical procedure 
The animals were anaesthetized with a mixture of 10 mg?kg 
21 of 
xylazine hydrochloride (Rumpun; Bayer, Seoul, Korea) and 
100 mg?kg 
21 of ketamine chloride (Ketalar; Yuhan, Seoul, Korea). 
The dorsal area of the rat cranium was shaved before surgery, and 
the surgical field was prepared with an iodine solution. A midline skin 
incision was made on the skull, and the periosteum with the tempor-
alis muscle was reflected laterally. A round (8 mm diameter) bony 
defect was then formed in the centre of the calvaria with a trephine 
bur (Hee Sung, Seoul, Korea). This defect was considered a critical-
size bone defect, in that it would not spontaneously heal during the 
lifetime of the animal. 
8,18 Each membrane was trimmed to be suffi-
ciently rectangular (10 mm310 mm) to cover the outer surface of the 
bony defect and then placed over the defect. After obtaining adequate 
haemostasis, the muscle layer was closed with 4-0 Vicryl sutures in a 
continuous fashion, and the skin was closed with 3-0 Vicryl sutures 
(Figure 2). Gentamycin at 5 mg?kg 
21 was injected to prevent infec-
tion after surgery. 
In each group, six animals were euthanized by CO 2 at 2, 4 and 8 
weeks after surgery. Subsequently, the calvaria of the rats were har-
vested and immediately immersed in a 10% tempered solution of 
formaldehyde. </p>

<p>20 kV 
50 mm 
100 mm 
20 kV </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>×100 
×350 </p>

<p>Figure 1 SEM image from the surfaces of CFB-HAP membrane. (a) Magnification 3100; (b) 3350. The irregular pores ranged from several microns up to a few 
hundred microns. The HAP particles, ranging from 0.5 to 2 mm in size, were well dispersed in the pore walls, presumably due to the high porosity of the polymeric 
solution. CFB-HAP, chitosan/fibroin-hydroxyapatite; SEM, scanning electron microscopy. </p>

<p>Comparative study of chitosan/fibroin-hydroxyapatite and collagen 
JM Song et al 
88 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science </p>

<p>In vivo micro-CT 
Specimen scans were performed with a SkyScan 1172 high-resolution 
micro-CT (SkyScan N.V., Kontich, Belgium). Prior to scanning the 
specimens, a calibration scan was performed using synthetic bone, 
water, and air samples. The exposure parameters were 70 kV and 
140 mA. The number of projections was 481 and there were 938 
cross-sections. The total scan time was 20 min. The scanned images 
were reconstructed using <rs type="software">SkyScan CT-Analyser</rs> software and a modi-
fied cone-beam algorithm 
14 with 0.027 mm30.027 mm30.027 mm 
isotropic voxel spacing. The reconstructed three-dimensional (3D) 
image was then traced to the circumference of the original defect 
margins. This allowed the creation of a 3D reconstruction of the defect, 
which here after was referred to as the region of interest. The region of 
interest of each specimen was analysed for tissue volume (TV), bone 
volume (BV), bone volume fraction (BVF, BV/TV) and bone mineral 
density (BMD). </p>

<p>Histology 
After taking the micro-CT scans, the specimens were decalcified in 
formic acid for 48 h and embedded in paraffin. Serial cross-sections 
(5 mm) were cut through the larger diameter of the defect and stained 
with haematoxylin-eosin (HE). HE staining reveals the cellular reac-
tions that indicate bone formation. The slides were photographed with 
the use of a virtual slide system (Scanscope CS System; Aperio 
Technologies, Vista, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
For the purposes of a statistical analysis, the bone defect was regarded as a 
statistical unit. Data were expressed as the mean (6standard deviation). </p>

<p>The quantitative data distribution was assessed using the Kolmogorov-
Smirnov test. Because a non-normal distribution was detected, a 
Kruskal-Wallis one-way analysis of variance by ranks was performed. 
When the Kruskal-Wallis test result was significant (P,0.05), a post hoc 
Tukey test was used to identify the significantly different group means. 
The statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">18.0</rs> software (SPSS, 
Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Histology 
HE staining. At 2 weeks after surgery, the early phase of new bone 
formation was observed at the margin of the calvarial defect in the 
control and experimental groups. However, in the negative control 
group, inflammatory cells and collagen fibres were observed. At 4 
weeks, increased bone formation and calcification were observed in 
all three groups. Inflammatory cells and capillaries were decreased in 
the negative control group. At 8 weeks, the experimental and control 
groups showed more advanced calcification, and the defects were 
nearly filled with new bone. In the negative control group, new bone 
formation was detected but did not fill half of the defects, unlike in the 
other two groups (Figure 3). </p>

<p>Degrees of inflammatory response. The inflammatory response was 
evaluated for each group. We examined the specimens at 2 weeks in 
each group because most of the inflammatory phase and the healing 
process are completed within 2 weeks. In the experimental and control 
groups, no remarkable inflammatory reactions were observed, but 
mild inflammation was observed in the negative control group 
(Figure 4 and Table 1). </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>d 
c </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Figure 2 Surgical procedures. (a) The rat calvarium was exposed. (b) A round (8 mm diameter) bony defect was made in the centre of the skull with a trephine bur. The 
dura and superior sagittal vein were not irritated. (c) A 10 mm310 mm membrane was placed on the bony defect. (d) Layered sutures were made with absorbable silk. </p>

<p>Comparative study of chitosan/fibroin-hydroxyapatite and collagen 
JM Song et al 
89 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science </p>

<p>Micro-CT analysis 
TV. The TV measurements in the region of interests did not show 
significant differences between the membrane groups. However, the 
TV increased in a time-dependent manner (Tables 2 and 3). </p>

<p>BV. The BV of the new bone that filled the bony defects showed 
significant differences (P,0.05). The control and experimental groups 
showed larger BV measurements than the negative control group. In </p>

<p>addition, the post hoc test revealed no significant differences between 
the two membranes. </p>

<p>BVF. The BVF, defined as the ratio of new bone to total tissue, 
showed a significant difference (P,0.05). Compared with the 
negative control group, the control and experimental groups 
showed significantly larger values, and there was no difference 
between the two membranes. </p>

<p>a 
b 
c </p>

<p>g 
h 
i </p>

<p>f 
d 
e </p>

<p>Figure 3 Histological view at 2, 4 and 8 weeks. (a) 2-week experimental group; (b) 2-week control group; (c) 2-week negative control group; (d) 4-week experimental 
group; (e) 4-week control group; (f) 4-week negative control group; (g) 8-week experimental group; (h) 8-week control group; (i) 8-week negative control group. At 2 
weeks, osteoblast proliferation and early-phase new bone formation was observed. In the negative control group, an inflammatory reaction was predominantly 
observed. Magnification 3100. </p>

<p>New bone </p>

<p>New bone Mother bone </p>

<p>Mother bone </p>

<p>New bone </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Mother bone </p>

<p>New bone </p>

<p>Mother bone </p>

<p>Mother bone </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c 
d </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Figure 4 Comparison of inflammatory reaction in each group at 2 weeks. (a) View of the entire specimen; (b) experimental group; (c) control group; (d) negative 
control group. In the negative control group, inflammatory cells and capillaries were observed. Magnification 3100, bar5300 mm. *Inflammatory cells and capillaries. </p>

<p>Comparative study of chitosan/fibroin-hydroxyapatite and collagen 
JM Song et al 
90 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science </p>

<p>BMD. The BMD measurements also showed significant differences 
over the weeks (P,0.05). The negative control group was significantly 
different from the membrane groups, and there was no significant 
difference between the control and experimental groups. </p>

<p>3D image reconstruction 
Figure 5 shows 3D reconstruction images of the rat calvarial defects. 
New bone was formed from the margin and its growth increased in a 
time-dependent manner. The images also indicate the differences 
among the three groups. </p>

<p>Table 1 Comparison of inflammatory reactions in each groups </p>

<p>Time 
Control group 
Experimental group 
Negative control group </p>

<p>2 week 
6 
6 
1 </p>

<p>6, minimal inflammation; 1, mild inflammation; 11, moderate inflammation; 
111, severe inflammation. </p>

<p>a 
b 
c </p>

<p>d 
e 
f </p>

<p>g 
h 
i </p>

<p>Figure 5 3D reconstruction images of each group at 2, 4 and 8 weeks. (a) 2-week experimental group; (b) 2-week control group; (c) 2-week negative control group; 
(d) 4-week experimental group; (e) 4-week control group; (f) 4-week negative control group; (g) 8-week experimental group; (h) 8-week control group; (i) 8-week 
negative control group. More new bone formation was observed in the two membrane groups than in the negative control group. This increased in a time-dependent 
manner and could be detected in the 3D images. 3D, three-dimensional. </p>

<p>Table 2 Measurements of the rat calvarial defect </p>

<p>Measure-
ment </p>

<p>Time/ 
week </p>

<p>Membrane </p>

<p>P value 
Void 
Bio-gide 
CFB-HAP </p>

<p>TV/mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 
145.83621.53 147.3669.85 150.18618.01 0.153 
4 
152.14631.49 155.6065.81 154.22639.13 0.992 
8 
162.05617.61 162.2862.64 168.29624.05 0.588 
BV/mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 
1.7960.83 
5.3361.95 
4.3761.10 
0.029* 
4 
3.1660.76 
6.4963.43 
5.6661.62 
0.027* 
8 
4.7862.03 
8.5961.66 
8.7063.57 
0.019* 
BVF/% 
2 
1.1360.41 
4.4962.27 
3.1960.72 
0.034* 
4 
2.2560.76 
4.7361.98 
4.1561.19 
0.019* 
8 
3.1560.51 
5.5061.10 
5.3061.67 
0.010* 
BMD/ 
(mg?mL 
21 ) </p>

<p>2 
0.4560.06 
0.6260.04 
0.6360.05 
0.034* 
4 
0.5860.07 
0.7560.06 
0.7360.04 
0.005* 
8 
0.6760.08 
0.8860.04 
0.8360.13 
0.032* </p>

<p>BMD, bone mineral density BV, bone volume BVF, bone volume fraction; CFB-HAP, 
chitosan/fibroin-hydroxyapatite; TV, tissue volume. 
* P,0.05. </p>

<p>Comparative study of chitosan/fibroin-hydroxyapatite and collagen 
JM Song et al 
91 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Among the resorbable polymers, chitosan has recently gained interest 
for its utility in GBR membranes. 
1,11-12 Many papers, in fact, have 
reported its use as a GBR membrane material. 
13,15,16 Chitosan, derived 
from the natural polymer chitin, is a polyheterosaccharide composed 
of glucosamine and N-acetyglucosamine units linked by 1-4 glucosi-
dic bonds. 
Chitosan has unique properties such as non-toxicity, flexibility, 
antibacterial activity, solubility in organic acid solutions, biocompa-
tibility and resistance to alkali environments and heat. 
17-18 As chitosan 
is also one of the biodegradable polymers found in nature, it can be 
hydrolysed by lysozyme. Furthermore, chitosan has a hydrophilic sur-
face that promotes cell adhesion, proliferation and differentiation, and 
unlike synthetic polymers, it evokes a minimal foreign-body reaction 
on implantation. </p>

<p>19,20 </p>

<p>Silk fibroin acts as an enzyme immobilisation matrix with good 
mechanical properties, blood compatibility and good dissolved oxy-
gen permeability in the wet state. Indeed, there have been reports on 
silk fibroin/chitosan blend membranes with positive mechanical 
properties forming an interpenetrating polymer network. </p>

<p>21-23 </p>

<p>Hydroxyapatite, due to its bioactive, biodegradable and osteocon-
ductive properties, has been used extensively in biomedical implant 
and bone regeneration applications. 
24 For the treatment of peri-
odontal osseous defects and alveolar ridge augmentation, hydroxya-
patite has been used in the form of a particulate. 
25,26 One complication 
that arises when using hydroxyapatite is the migration from the 
implant site into the surrounding tissue because its manipulation 
properties are comparable to those of sand. 
27,28 Therefore, for the 
purposes of hard-tissue generation, it is desirable to develop a hybrid 
material that combines the favourable properties of a chitosan-based 
biopolymer and hydroxyapatite. We hypothesized that when CFB-
HAP membranes are implanted as a tissue scaffold, the relatively fast 
degradation of chitosan makes room for the growth of new tissue and 
increases the opportunity for the host bone to assimilate the hydro-
xyapatite. </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>Bio-Gide is a well-known and commonly used collagen membrane. 
Membrane-derived collagen fibres can trap some osteoinductive fac-
tors such as bone morphogenetic proteins, transforming growth fac-
tors, insulin-like growth factors and fibroblast growth factors that are 
easily released from the bone matrix when an artificial bone cavity is 
formed. Because connective tissue facing the compact layer of the 
membrane does not show any osteogenesis, some osteoinductive fac-
tors accumulate on the collagen fibres of the porous layer that faces the 
cavity. Even if collagen itself has no ability to bind these osteoinductive </p>

<p>factors, it can bind several extracellular matrix proteins that have a 
high affinity for these factors. 
30 If so, it is possible that several osteoin-
ductive factors would be trapped by the collagen fibres of the mem-
brane, making previously migrated cells differentiate into an 
osteoblastic lineage. Additionally, Type I collagen can play a direct 
and important role in osteoblastic differentiation. 
31-32 For the reasons 
noted above, many clinicians have reported high success rates when 
using Bio-Gide for GBR. 
A previous study established that the CFB-HAP matrix induces 
bone regeneration in bony defects. 
33-34 In the present study, we 
processed the CFB-HAP matrix for use as a barrier membrane. To 
ascertain its effectiveness, we conducted micro-CT and measured 
regenerated osseous tissue by means of a reconstruction program. 
Micro-CT and reconstruction analysis offers a key advantage: experi-
mental bone regeneration results can be quantified. 
In this study, TV did not show any difference between the mem-
brane types and increased with time. In the control and experimental 
groups, the BV and the BMD, which are indexes of bone regeneration, 
showed significant differences compared with the negative control 
group, although there was no significant difference between the two 
membranes. From these results, we can conclude that the CFB-HAP 
membrane has a similar bone regeneration capacity to that of the 
collagen membrane, and furthermore, that the absorbable chitosan 
membrane offers the possibility for use as a barrier membrane in GBR. 
In HE staining, no remarkable inflammatory reaction was induced 
by membrane in the membrane groups. The neutrophil chemotaxis of 
chitosan is known from many studies. 
35-37 However, in this experi-
ment, the CFB-HAP membrane group did not show any obvious 
inflammatory reaction, which can affect the success of the GBR. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS 
In this study, we employed micro-CT to compare CFB-HAP and 
absorbable collagen (Bio-Gide) membranes for their bone-healing 
effects on rat calvarial defects. We obtained many measurements indi-
cating new bone formation and drew the following conclusions. </p>

<p>(i) The total tissue volume results did not show significant diffe-
rences among the CFB-HAP, Bio-Gide and negative control 
groups. 
(ii) The BV and BMD data indicated significant differences between 
the membrane groups and the negative control group. However, 
no significant differences were found between the CFB-HAP 
and Bio-Gide groups. 
(iii) Micro-CT can be a useful analytical tool for measuring new 
bone formation. In addition to the various measurements from 
the micro-CT data, the 3D reconstruction images effectively 
quantified the new bone formation. </p>

<p>1 
Kim HS, Kim JT, Jung YJ et al. Preparation of a porous chitosan/fibroin-hydroxyapatite 
composite matrix for tissue engineering. Macromol Res 2007; 15(1): 65-73. 
2 
Ueyama Y, Ishikawa K, Mano T et al. Usefulness as guided bone regeneration 
membrane of the alginate membrane. Biomaterials 2002; 23(9): 2027-2033. 
3 
Ignatius AA, Ohnmacht M, Claes LE et al. A composite polymer/tricalcium phosphate 
membrane for guided bone regeneration in maxillofacial surgery. J Biomed Mater Res 
2001; 58(5): 564-569. 
4 
Carvalho RS, Nelson D, Kelderman H et al. Guided bone regeneration to repair an 
osseous defect. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop 2003; 123(4): 455-467. 
5 
Piattelli A, Scarano A, Russo P et al. Evaluation of guided bone regeneration in rabbit 
tibia using bioresorbable and nonresorbable membranes. Biomaterials 1996; 17(8): 
791-796. </p>

<p>Table 3 Post hoc test results (Tukey HSD) </p>

<p>Measurement 
Membrane </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>2 weeks 
4 weeks 
8 weeks </p>

<p>BV/mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Void 
Bio-Gide 
0.007* 
0.030* 
0.011* 
CFB-HAP 
0.065* 
0.018* 
0.025* 
Bio-Gide 
CFB-HAP 
0.375 
0.999 
0.997 
BVF/% 
Void 
Bio-Gide 
0.011* 
0.019* 
0.002* 
CFB-HAP 
0.062 
0.009* 
0.012* 
Bio-Gide 
CFB-HAP 
0.545 
0.999 
0.895 
BMD/(mg?mL </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>) Void 
Bio-Gide 
0.032* 
0.001* 
0.026* 
CFB-HAP 
0.028* 
0.003* 
0.055 
Bio-Gide 
CFB-HAP 
0.964 
0.147 
0.994 </p>

<p>BMD, bone mineral density; BV, bone volume; BVF, bone volume fraction. 
* P,0.05. </p>

<p>Comparative study of chitosan/fibroin-hydroxyapatite and collagen 
JM Song et al 
92 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science </p>





<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. The images or other third 
party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless 
indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative 
Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce 
the material. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>Comparative study of chitosan/fibroin-hydroxyapatite and collagen 
JM Song et al 
93 </p>

<p>International Journal of Oral Science </p>

</text></tei>