<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5103916" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. The extracellular pH is lower inside solid tumors 
than in normal tissue. The acidic environment inhibits the 
cytotoxicity of lymphocytes in vitro and promotes tumor cell 
invasion. In the present study, both in vitro and in vivo experi-
ments were conducted to investigate how NaHCO 3 would 
affect the antitumor activities of cytokine-induced killer 
(CIK) cells against hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) cells. For 
the in vitro experiments, HepG2 cells were cultured at pH 6.5 
and 7.4 in the presence of CIK cells or CIK cell-conditioned 
medium (CM CIK ). For the in vivo experiments, nude mice 
were xenografted with HepG2-luc cells and divided into four 
groups: i) CIK cells injection plus NaHCO 3 feeding; ii) CIK 
cells injection plus drinking water feeding; iii) normal saline 
injection plus NaHCO 3 feeding; and iv) normal saline injec-
tion plus drinking water feeding. The results indicated that 
the viability and growth rate of HepG2 cells were remarkably 
suppressed when co-cultured with CIK cells or CM CIK at 
pH 7.4 compared with those of HepG2 cells cultured under 
the same conditions but at pH 6.5. In the xenograft study, a 
marked synergistic antitumor effect of the combined therapy 
was observed. NaHCO 3 feeding augmented the infiltration 
of cluster of differentiation 3-positive T lymphocytes into 
the tumor mass. Taken together, these data strongly suggest 
that the antitumor activities of CIK cells against HepG2 cells 
were negatively affected by the acidic environment inside the 
tumors, and neutralizing the pH (for example, via NaHCO 3 </p>

<p>administration), could therefore reduce or eliminate this influ-
ence. In addition, it should be recommended that oncologists 
routinely prescribe soda water to their patients, particularly 
during CIK cell therapy. </p>

<p>Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC), the most frequent primary 
tumor of the liver, is one of the leading causes of cancer-
associated mortality worldwide (1). Regarding treatment 
options for HCC, immunotherapy remains an important adju-
vant treatment, despite advances in surgery, chemotherapy and 
radiotherapy (2). Cytokine-induced killer (CIK) cell therapy is 
currently one of the most commonly used immunotherapies (3). 
In order to improve the efficacy of CIK cell therapy, numerous 
strategies, including gene transfection (4), stimulation with 
certain growth factors (5), pretreatment with antitumor 
drugs (6), or combination with genetically modified dendritic 
cells (7), have been attempted in practice. However, a number 
of clinical trials of CIK cell therapies failed to demonstrate 
any noticeable improvement over other therapeutic regimens, 
neither in terms of HCC control rates nor long-term survival 
rates (8), suggesting that other factors, such as the environment 
where CIK cells are functioning, should also be considered for 
immunotherapies. 
It has been demonstrated that the high metabolic demand 
of rapidly proliferating cancer cells, in conjunction with a shift 
toward glycolytic metabolism reflecting both tumor hypoxia 
and oncogene-induced changes in gene expression, leads to 
an often greatly increased production and extrusion of acid 
by cancer cells (9,10). Therefore, the extracellular pH (pHe) 
of malignant solid tumors is usually acidic, ranging from 
6.5 to 6.9, whereas the pHe of normal tissues is significantly 
more alkaline, ranging from 7.2 to 7.5 (11). This disturbance of 
the acid-base balance is able to remodel various physiological 
functions, and results in solid tumors becoming more invasive 
and metastatic (12). In addition, it may also induce undesired 
resistance to immunotherapy (13). By contrast, inhibition of 
the acid extrusion of tumor cells may alleviate their resistance 
to immunotherapy (14). However, none of these speculations 
has ever been confirmed for CIK cell immunotherapy in vitro </p>

<p>NaHCO 3 enhances the antitumor activities of cytokine-induced 
killer cells against hepatocellular carcinoma HepG2 cells </p>

<p>YA HONG YUAN 1* , CHUN FANG ZHOU 2* , JIANG YUAN 3 , LI LIU 4 , XING RONG GUO 1 , 
XIAO LI WANG 1 , YAN DING 1 , XIAO NAN WANG 4* , DONG SHENG LI 1* and HAN JUN TU 1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Hubei Key Laboratory of Embryonic Stem Cell Research, Taihe Hospital; 2 Department of Gastroenterology, 
Renmin Hospital; 3 Department of Neurology, Taihe Hospital, Hubei University of Medicine, Shiyan, Hubei 442000; </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Department of Infectious Diseases, Tianyou Hospital, Wuhan University of Science and Technology, 
Wuhan, Hubei 430000, P.R. China </p>

<p>Received May 11, 2015; Accepted July 28, 2016 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/ol.2016.5112 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Professor Dong Sheng Li, Hubei Key </p>

<p>Laboratory of Embryonic Stem Cell Research, Taihe Hospital, Hubei 
University of Medicine, Renmin Road 32, Shiyan, Hubei 442000, 
P.R. China 
E-mail: dsli1698@126.com </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Contributed equally </p>

<p>Key words: NaHCO 3 , cytokine-induced killer cells, HepG2, </p>

<p>extracellular pH, acidic microenvironment </p>

<p>YUAN et al: NaHCO 3 ENHANCES THE ANTITUMOR ACTIVITIES OF CIK CELLS </p>



<p>or in vivo. In the present study, the antitumor activities of CIK 
cells against HepG2 cells were evaluated both in vitro and 
in vivo under environments with acidic and alkaline pH. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Cell culture. HepG2 cells (ATCC, Manassas, VA, USA) or 
HepG2-luc cells (HepG2 cells stably transfected with a firefly 
luciferase gene), were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's 
medium (Invitrogen; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc., Waltham, 
MA, USA) containing 10% fetal bovine serum (Hyclone; GE 
Healthcare Life Sciences, Logan, UT, USA) in an incubator at 
37˚C with humidified atmosphere and 5% CO 2 in air. Cells were 
adapted in acidic (pH 6.5) or alkaline (pH 7.4) environments for 
three passages prior to be used for experiments. The pH values 
of the medium were accordingly adjusted with lactic acid, 
NaHCO 3 and 4-(2-hydroxyethyl)-1-piperazineethanesulfonic 
acid. </p>

<p>Preparation of CIK cells. Peripheral blood mononuclear cells 
(PBMCs) were isolated from peripheral blood by standard 
Ficoll separation, as previously described (5). Human periph-
eral blood samples were obtained with full informed consent 
from patients with HCC. In total, six samples were collected 
between January 2014 and July 2014 at the Department of 
Gastroenterology of Renmin Hospital, Hubei University of 
Medicine (Shiyan, China). The isolated cells were resuspended 
in RPMI-1640 medium supplemented with 1,000 U/ml inter-
feron (IFN)-γ (R&amp;D Systems, Inc., Minneapolis, MN, USA) 
and incubated at 37˚C for 24 h. Then, recombinant human 
interleukin (IL)-2 protein (cat. no. 202-IL-050; R&amp;D Systems, 
Inc.) and mouse anti-cluster of differentiation (CD)3 mono-
clonal antibody (cat. no. MAB100; dilution, 1:1,000; R&amp;D 
Systems, Inc.) were added at 500 U/ml and 50 ng/ml, respec-
tively. Subsequently, the cells were refreshed with RPMI-1640 
medium supplemented with IL-2 (500 U/ml) every other day 
for 10 days prior to being subjected to flow cytometry analysis. </p>

<p>Flow cytometry. A set of conjugated monoclonal antibodies 
(BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA), including 
anti-CD3-fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC; cat. no. 561806; 
dilution, 1:20) as a T-cell marker, anti-CD4-phycoerythrin (PE; 
cat. no. 565999; dilution, 1:20) as a helper T-cell marker, 
anti-CD8-PE (cat. no. 561950; dilution, 1:20) as a cytotoxic 
T-cell marker and anti-CD56-PE (cat. no. 561903; dilu-
tion, 1:20) as a natural killer (NK) cell-marker, were used to 
define the phenotypes of CIK cells. In total, 1x10 6 CIK cells 
were harvested and washed once with phosphate-buffered 
saline (PBS) containing 1% bovine serum albumin (BSA; 
Beyotime Institute of Biotechnology, Haimen, China), and 
resuspended in 100 µl PBS/BSA. The cells were then incubated 
with the above conjugated monoclonal antibodies separately 
for 20 min at 4 o C, washed twice with PBS and resuspended in 
400 µl PBS. Flow cytometric analysis was performed with a 
BD FACSCalibur™ flow cytometer (BD Biosciences), and the 
data were analyzed using the WinMDI software, version 2.9 
(The Scripps Research Institute, La Jolla, CA, USA). The dead 
cells and debris were gated out. 
HepG2 cell apoptosis was analyzed using the annexin V/prop-
idium iodide (PI) double staining method. HepG2 cells were </p>

<p>plated at a density of 3x10 5 cells/well in a BD Falcon ® 12-well 
plate (BD Biosciences) and cultured in CIK cell-conditioned 
medium (CM CIK ), HepG2 cell-conditioned medium (CM control ) or 
a 1:1 mixture of the two conditioned media (thus, the percentages 
of CM CIK in the above media were 100, 0 and 50%, respectively). 
The pH of the media was adjusted to 6.5 or 7.4, correspondingly. 
After 48 h of incubation, the cells were collected, washed and 
resuspended in PBS. Then, annexin V-FITC and PI (Nanjing 
KeyGen Biotech Co., Ltd., Nanjing, China) were added to the 
cells, which were incubated at 4˚C for 20 min prior to being 
subjected to flow cytometer analysis. All the experiments were 
performed in triplicate. </p>

<p>3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide 
(MTT) assay. The MTT colorimetric assay was used to deter-
mine the cytotoxic activity of CIK cells against HepG2 cells 
in vitro (15). The CIK cells [effector (E) cells] and the HepG2 
cells [target (T) cells] were co-cultured in a 96-well plate with 
medium at pH 6.5 or 7.4. The ratios of CIK and HepG2 cells (E/T 
ratio) were set as 10:1, 20:1, 40:1 and 80:1. In addition, E cells 
or T cells alone were used as controls. The MTT assay was 
performed 20 h later to evaluate the cell viability, and the optical 
density (OD) values were measured at 570 nm. The assays were 
conducted in triplicate. The cytotoxic activity was calculated as 
follows: Cytotoxic activity (%) = [1-(OD E+T -OD E )/OD T ] x 100%. </p>

<p>Fluorescence assay of cytotoxic effects of CIK cells on 
HepG2-luc cells. HepG2-luc cells were co-cultured with CIK 
cells or in CM CIK at pH 6.5 or 7.4 respectively. The viability 
of HepG2-luc cells was assessed fluorescently using the IVIS ® 
Spectrum in vivo imaging system (Caliper Life Sciences; Perki-
nElmer, Inc., Waltham, MA, USA). In co-culture, HepG2-luc 
cells were plated at a density of 8,000 cells/well into a BD 
Falcon ® 96-well plate (BD Biosciences), and CIK cells were 
then added to the 96-well plate at E/T ratios of 0:1, 10:1, 20:1, 
40:1 and 80:1. In culture with CM CIK , HepG2-luc cells were 
plated at a density of 1,500 cells/well in a BD Falcon ® 96-well 
plate (BD Biosciences) with medium containing 0, 25, 50, 
75 and 100% CM CIK . The assays were performed in triplicate. 
After 20 h of co-culture or 48 h of culture in CM CIK , 0.15 mg/ml 
D-luciferin was added into each well, and the luminescence 
activity (LA) was measured after additional 5-min incubation. 
Based on the LA values, the cytotoxicities of CIK cells were 
calculated according to the following formula: CIK cytotoxicity 
(%) = [(LA 0:1 -LA x:1 )/LA 0:1 ] x 100%, where LA 0:1 is the LA of 
HepG2-luc cells cultured in the absence of CIK cells, and LA x:1 
is a variable that refers to the LA of HepG2-luc cells co-cultured 
with 10, 20, 40 or 80-fold CIK cells. The cytotoxicities present 
in the CM CIK were calculated according to the following 
formula: CM CIK cytotoxicity (%) = [(LA 0 -LA y )/LA 0 ] x 100%, 
where LA is the LA of the HepG2-luc cells, LA 0 is the LA of 
HepG2-luc cells cultured in the absence of CM CIK , and LA y is 
a variable that represents the LA of HepG2-luc cells cultured 
with 25, 50, 75 and 100% CM CIK. </p>

<p>Xenograf t assay. A total of 20 female nude mice 
(6-8 weeks-old) were purchased from the Animal Experi-
ment Center of Wuhan University (Wuhan, China). All mice 
were maintained in the Animal Experiment Center of the 
Hubei University of Medicine (Shiyan, China) at a controlled </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY LETTERS 12: 3167-3174, 2016 </p>



<p>temperature and humidity, under a 12-h light/dark cycle, with 
ad libitum access to sterile food and water. The present study 
was performed with the approval of the Hubei University of 
Medicine ethical committee, and all the experiments were 
performed according to the National Institutes of Health 
Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. In order 
to eradicate residual NK cells, the nude mice were adminis-
tered 200 cGy of whole body irradiation and subcutaneously 
injected with 1x10 7 HepG2-luc cells. Subsequently, the 
mice were randomly divided into four groups according to 
the different treatments received: i) CIK cells injection plus 
oral administration of NaHCO 3 ; ii) CIK cells injection plus 
drinking water feeding; iii) normal saline injection plus oral 
administration of NaHCO 3 ; and iv) normal saline injection 
plus drinking water feeding (which served as control). CIK 
cells (1.5x10 7 cells/injection) or an equivalent volume of 
normal saline were intravenously injected in the mice through 
their tail veins on days 0, 7, 14, 21 and 28, while NaHCO 3 
(200 mmol/l) or drinking water feeding were conducted 
on a daily basis. The LA of the tumors was monitored and 
measured with the IVIS ® Spectrum in vivo imaging system 
on days 0, 10, 20 and 30. The mice were sacrificed on day 30, 
and the tumor weights were measured. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemical analysis. The grafted tumor masses 
were fixed in 10% formalin, embedded in paraffin and 
sectioned with a thickness of 3 µm for immunohistochemical 
studies. Rabbit anti-human CD3 polyclonal antibody (cat. 
no. ab828; dilution, 1:50; Abcam, Cambridge, MA, USA) 
and mouse anti-human perforin monoclonal antibody 
(cat. no. ab47225; dilution, 1:50; Abcam) were used for 
immunostaining. Horseradish peroxidase-conjugated goat 
anti-rabbit (cat. no. ab6721; dilution, 1:1,000; Abcam) and 
goat anti-mouse (cat. no. ab6789; dilution, 1:1,000; Abcam) </p>

<p>secondary antibodies were used for detection of the primary 
antibodies. All procedures were conducted according to the 
manufacturer's protocol. Images of the sections were acquired 
using an Olympus BX-60 microscope (Olympus Corpora-
tion, Tokyo, Japan) to determine the CD3 + and perforin + cell 
densities. The number of positive cells was blindly counted in 
10 randomly selected independent fields (0.16 mm 2 at x400 
magnification) for each section by two independent observers. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Differences between groups were 
compared using analysis of variance, and the least significant 
difference test was used for multiple mean comparisons. 
P&lt;0.05 was considered to indicate a statistically significant 
difference. Statistical analysis was conducted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS 
software</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v13.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Characteristics of CIK cells. The CIK cells induced with 
the method described above appeared regular, round, 
transparent and variable in size when observed under 
a microscope. They exhibited the ability of growth in 
suspension, and multiple characteristic cell clusters were 
formed (Fig. 1A and B). After 14 days, the absolute number 
of human PBMCs cultured in the presence of IL-2 and 
anti-CD3 antibody increased by &gt;250-fold, from 5 million 
PBMCs to 1,300 million CIK cells. When the phenotypes 
of the cultured cell population were examined by fluores-
cence-activated cell sorting analysis, the cell population was 
observed to be composed of 92% CD3 + , 34% CD3 + CD56 + , 
14% CD4 + and 73% CD8 + cells (Fig. 1C). </p>

<p>The cytotoxic activity of CIK cells is significantly compro-
mised under an acidic environment. Both the MTT assay </p>

<p>Figure 1. Characterization of CIK cells. (A) Morphology of CIK cells under a phase-contrast microscope after 10 days of induction (magnification, x200). 
(B) A cluster of CIK cells were observed under a phase-contrast microscope (magnification, x200). (C) Flow cytometry analysis revealed that the percentages 
of CD8 + , CD4 + and CD3 + CD56 + cells were 73, 14 and 34%, respectively. CIK, cytokine-induced killer; CD, cluster of differentiation. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B 
A </p>

<p>YUAN et al: NaHCO 3 ENHANCES THE ANTITUMOR ACTIVITIES OF CIK CELLS </p>



<p>and the fluorescence assay demonstrated that CIK cells had a 
significantly higher cytotoxic activity against HepG2-luc cells 
in the medium with pH 7.4 than in the medium with pH 6.5. In 
the fluorescence assay, HepG2-luc cells were co-cultured with 
CIK cells at an E/T ratio of 0:1 10:1, 20:1, 40:1 or 80:1 at pH 6.5 
or pH 7.4. The fluorescence intensities were significantly lower 
with pH 7.4 than with pH 6.5 for each paired cultures (P&lt;0.05; 
Fig. 2A and B). The cytotoxic activity calculated based on the 
fluorescence intensity showed that the cytotoxicity of CIK 
cells were significantly higher with pH 7.4 than with pH 6.5 
(P&lt;0.05; Fig. 2C). 
In the MTT assay, 19, 38, 60 and 80% of HepG2-luc cells 
died when co-cultured with CIK cells at an E/T ratio of 10:1, 
20:1, 40:1 and 80:1, respectively, in the medium with pH 7.4. 
However, only 4, 18, 30 and 45% of HepG2 cells died, respec-
tively, at the same E/T ratios with pH 6.5 (P&lt;0.05; Fig. 2D). 
Highly consistent with the results of CIK cells in fluorescence 
assay, the CM CIK displayed stronger cytotoxicity activities in 
pH 7.4 condition than in pH 6.5 condition. The fluorescence 
intensities of HepG2-luc cells cultured in medium containing 
50, 75 and 100% CM CIK were significantly lower with pH 7.4 
than with pH 6.5 (P&lt;0.05; Fig. 3A and B). The cytotoxicity of 
CM CIK in pH 7.4 condition was stronger than that in the pH 6.5 
condition (Fig. 3C). 
In addition, the annexin V/PI double staining method 
was used to determine the percentage of cells that exhibited </p>

<p>apoptosis and necrosis (Fig. 4). At a CM ratio of 50%, the 
CM CIK -induced apoptosis and necrosis in pH 6.5 and pH 7.4 
medium were 15 and 26%, respectively. Furthermore, at a 
CM CIK ratio of 100%, the percentage of apoptosis and necrosis 
in pH-6.5 and pH-7.4 medium were 25 and 45%, respectively. 
These results indicated that the acidic environment inhibits the 
antitumor activity of CIK cells. </p>

<p>The activity of CIK cells against HCC is enhanced by 
NaHCO 3 feeding in nude mice. In order to further inves-
tigate whether NaHCO 3 treatment would enhance the 
antitumor activity of CIK therapy in vivo, HepG2-luc 
carcinoma-bearing nude mice were grouped and treated as 
above described. Nude mice were selected due to their lack 
of cellular immunity (16). The results revealed that there 
was no difference between the NaHCO 3 feeding group and 
the control group in terms of luminescence intensities from 
the tumors. The luminescence intensities of the tumors in 
the CIK group were significantly reduced compared with 
those in the control group, while those in the CIK plus 
NaHCO 3 feeding group were also significantly reduced 
compared with those in the CIK group (Fig. 5A and B). 
The tumor masses were isolated on day 30 (Fig. 5C) after 
grafted from each group, and the average weights of the 
tumors were consistent with the luminescence intensity 
analysis (Fig. 5D). </p>

<p>Figure 2. Cytotoxicity of cytokine-induced killer cells against HepG2-luc cells under alkaline and acidic environments. (A-C) Fluorescence assay. 
(A) Fluorescence images were captured at 0 and 20 h. (B) The fluorescence activities measured after 20 h of co-culture decreased in an alkaline environment, 
while the E/T ratios (C) and the percentages of dead HepG2-luc cells increased. These results were highly consistent with the (D) 3-(4,5-dimethylthi-
azol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide assay results. All the experiments were performed in triplicate. Error bars indicate the mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05, ** P&lt;0.01 in t test. E, effector cells; T, target cells; luc, luciferase. </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D 
C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY LETTERS 12: 3167-3174, 2016 </p>



<p>NaHCO 3 enhances the infiltration of CIK cells within the 
tumor tissue. Since CD3 + T lymphocytes are the main 
components of CIK cells and perforin is important in the </p>

<p>antitumor effects of CIK cells (17), an immunohistochem-
ical study was further performed on the excised tumor tissue 
with anti-CD3 and anti-perforin antibodies. The results </p>

<p>Figure 3. Cytotoxicity of CM CIK against HepG2-luc cells under alkaline and acidic environments. HepG2-luc cells were cultured with different ratios of CM CIK 
at pH 6.5 and 7.4. (A) Fluorescence images were captured at 0 and 48 h. (B) Luciferase activities were measured at 48 h. (C) The percentages of dead HepG2-luc 
cells were calculated based on their luminescence activity at 48 h. The experiment was performed in triplicate. Error bars indicate the mean ±standard devia-
tion. * P&lt;0.05 in t test. CM CIK , CIK cell-conditioned medium; CIK, cytokine-induced killer; luc, luciferase. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Apoptosis and necrosis analysis of HepG2 cells cultured with CM CIK by annexin V/PI staining. Increased apoptosis and necrosis in an alkaline envi-
ronment were observed when the proportions of CM CIK were 50 and 100%. (A) Flow cytometry assay. (B) Histogram comparing the percentages of apoptosis 
and necrosis of HepG2 cells at pH 6.5 and 7.4. The experiment was performed in triplicate. Error bars indicate the mean ± standard deviation. * P&lt;0.05, ** P&lt;0.01 
in t test. CM CIK , CIK cell-conditioned medium; CIK, cytokine-induced killer; PI, propidium iodide. </p>

<p>C 
B </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>YUAN et al: NaHCO 3 ENHANCES THE ANTITUMOR ACTIVITIES OF CIK CELLS </p>



<p>revealed that there was significantly more accumulation of 
CD3 + T lymphocytes and perforin in tumor tissue treated 
with CIK cells plus NaHCO 3 compared with tumor tissue 
treated with CIK cells alone (Fig. 6). There were almost 
no accumulation of CD3 + T lymphocytes or perforin in the 
tumor tissue from the other two groups. This result could 
explain why tumor growth was remarkably suppressed in the 
CIK+NaHCO 3 group. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The acidic pH of the extracellular environment has a direct 
influence on a broad range of immunological functions (18). 
Previous studies on polymorphonuclear leukocytes demon-
strate that this acidic pH mainly causes inhibition of chemotaxis, 
respiratory activity and bactericidal capacity (19,20). Evidence 
of impaired lymphocyte cytotoxicity and proliferation at 
acidic pH is also beginning to emerge (21). In addition, 
clinical acidosis is accompanied by immunodeficiency (22). 
Furthermore, other evidence has suggested that acidic micro-
environments may play a role during neoplastic growth and 
invasion (23). 
CIK cells are ex vivo-expanded T lymphocytes that share 
phenotypic and functional properties with both NK and 
T cells (24). In view of the conclusions of previous studies, it 
is reasonable for us to infer that acidic microenvironments of </p>

<p>solid tumors will affect the antitumor activity of CIK cells. 
Based on the mechanism underlying the antitumor effects of 
CIK cells, including the fact that CIK cells bind to T cells, 
form cellular conjugates with tumor cells and secrete a large 
number of cytotoxic cytoplasmic granules that are cytolytic 
to T cells (25), and the fact that CIK cells secrete a number of 
cytokines (including IFN-γ, IL-2 and tumor necrosis factor) 
that attack tumor cells (26), the present study compared the 
antitumor activities of CIK cells or CM CIK against HCC at 
pH 6.5 and 7.4. The results revealed that the antitumor activi-
ties of both CIK cells and CM CIK against HepG2 cells were 
significantly compromised under an acidic environment, with 
35 and 25% reduction in cytotoxicity and tumor inhibition, 
respectively. These results strongly suggested that neutraliza-
tion of the acidic environment in the tumor tissue should be 
equally important as the CIK cell therapy itself. CIK cells 
would not be fully active unless the acidic environment in 
tumor tissue is neutralized. 
Previous experimental and mathematical models have 
successfully demonstrated that it is possible to upregulate the 
pHe of tumors with little effect on systemic pH by chronic 
administration of sodium bicarbonate (27,28). In addition, 
recent studies documented that oral administration of HCO 3 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>could actually inhibit tumor metastasis in prostate, breast and 
colon cancer cell line-derived tumors (29-31). This appar-
ently occurred by reducing the extracellular acidity of the </p>

<p>Figure 5. Xenograft experiments. (A) In vivo fluorescence images of HepG2-luc-derived tumors of nude mice from four different experimental groups. 
(B) Histogram revealing that the fluorescence activities were reduced in the CIK+NaHCO 3 group. Each experimental group was composed of 5 mice. Error 
bars indicate the mean ±SD. * P&lt;0.05, ** P&lt;0.01 in t test. (C) Size of the tumor mass from the mice in the four different experimental groups. (D) Histogram 
revealing that the average weight of the tumor mass was significantly reduced in the CIK+NaHCO 3 group. Error bars indicate the mean ± SD. * P&lt;0.05 in t test. 
ROI, regions of interest; CIK, cytokine-induced killer; CON, control; luc, luciferase; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>ONCOLOGY LETTERS 12: 3167-3174, 2016 </p>



<p>acid-extruding tumors, in the absence of changes in the pH 
of the blood or normal tissues (29-31). Previous findings 
suggested that certain enzymes such as cathepsins and matrix 
metalloproteases, which are involved in tumor invasion, 
were inhibited by alkalinization (32). In the present study, 
oral administration of NaHCO 3 was combined with CIK cell 
therapy in HCC-bearing nude mice to investigate whether 
NaHCO 3 could enhance the antitumor activity of CIK cells 
against HCC. The present data revealed a remarkable synergy 
between oral administration of NaHCO 3 and CIK cell 
therapy in treating grafted HepG2-luc carcinomas in nude 
mice, suggesting that oral NaHCO 3 administration may be 
sufficient to reduce the acidity of the tumor microenviron-
ment, eventually enhancing the efficacy of CIK cell therapy. 
These findings and the in vitro results could explain one of 
the reasons why tumor cells thrive in the acidic environment, 
that is, due to the fact that the immune system is compromised 
in the acidic environment, thus facilitating the survival of 
tumor cells. Notably, oral administration of NaHCO 3 alone 
failed to inhibit the growth of the tumor in nude mice. This 
result was consistent with a previous study (28), in which 
NaHCO 3 administration was observed to have no effect on 
the growth of primary tumors in severe combined immunode-
ficiency mice. Thus, although NaHCO 3 inhibits spontaneous 
metastases by attenuating the function of certain enzymes, 
without the immune system, NaHCO 3 is unable to inhibit the 
primary tumor growth. However, this is not the true situation 
of the patients with tumors in the clinic, since the majority 
of these patients are immunologically intact (33). Therefore, 
even without receiving any immunotherapy such as CIK cell 
therapy, it would be beneficial for these patients to ingest </p>

<p>alkaline food or drinks, since it may aid the T lymphocytes to 
fight against the tumor cells in their bodies. 
The present immunohistochemical studies on the tumor 
tissue from each group revealed a significantly augmented 
number of CD3 + T lymphocytes infiltrating into the tumor 
mass when NaHCO 3 feeding was combined with CIK cell 
therapy, compared with CIK cell therapy alone. In addition, 
the perforin secreted by T lymphocytes, which is important in 
killing T cells, was also abundantly detected by immunohis-
tochemistry. These results suggest that the acidic environment 
appeared to prevent CIK cells from migrating into the tumor 
tissue, which may partially explain why immune cells such as 
CIK cells could not function well in an acidic environment. 
However, there may be other mechanisms involved, such as the 
acidic environment inhibiting the cytokine secretion of CIK 
cells, thus compromising their binding ability to the T cells. 
Further studies to explore the exact molecular mechanisms are 
warranted. 
In summary, both the in vitro and in vivo experiments of 
the present study demonstrated that the antitumor activities 
of CIK cells against HepG2 cells were significantly enhanced 
under alkaline or relatively less acidic environments, although 
the molecular mechanism involved require to be further inves-
tigated. The present results have provided novel insights for 
oncologists to treat their cancer patients, particularly when 
immunotherapy is considered. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The present study was supported by grants from the Ministry of 
Education of China (Beijing, China; grant no. 20151092900), </p>

<p>Figure 6. Immunohistochemical study. Sections were prepared from the tumors isolated from the mice in the four different treatment groups on day 30 after 
HepG2-luc cells were injected into mice. (A) Immunostaining with anti-CD3 and anti-perforin antibodies revealed that there was more infiltration of T lympho-
cytes in the CIK+NaHCO 3 group than in the CIK only group. A total of 10 individual microscopic fields (0.16 mm 2 ; magnification, x400; scale bar, 25 µm) around 
the apoptotic areas were randomly selected to count the positive cells for (B) CD3 and (C) perforin, and the average numbers were summarized in a histogram 
(boxes, 75% percentile; lines, median; bars, standard deviation). * P&lt;0.05 in t test. CIK, cytokine-induced killer; CON, control; CD, cluster of differentiation. </p>

<p>C 
B </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>YUAN et al: NaHCO 3 ENHANCES THE ANTITUMOR ACTIVITIES OF CIK CELLS </p>



<p>the Science and Technology Department of Hubei Province 
(Wuhan, China; grant no. 2014CFA068) and the Science and 
Technology Department of Shiyan City (Shiyan, China; grant 
no. 16Y01). </p>



</text></tei>