<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5191619" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T03:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: Use of nonopioid analgesics (including nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs) 
for postoperative pain management can reduce opioid consumption and potentially prevent 
opioid-related adverse events. This study examined the postoperative opioid-sparing effect 
of repeated-dose injectable diclofenac formulated with hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin 
(HPβCD)-diclofenac. 
Patients and methods: Pooled data from two double-blind, randomized, placebo-and active 
comparator-controlled Phase III trials were analyzed. Patients received HPβCD-diclofenac, pla-
cebo, or ketorolac by intravenous injection every 6 hours for up to 5 days following abdominal/ 
pelvic or orthopedic surgery. Rescue opioid use was evaluated from the time of first study drug 
administration to up to 120 hours following the first dose in the overall study population and in 
subgroups defined by baseline pain severity, age, and HPβCD-diclofenac dose. 
Results: Overall, 608 patients received ≥1 dose of study medication and were included in the 
analysis. While 93.2% of patients receiving placebo required opioids, the proportion of patients 
requiring opioids was significantly lower for patients receiving HPβCD-diclofenac (18.75, 37.5, 
or 50 mg) or ketorolac (P&lt;0.005 for all comparisons). Mean cumulative opioid dose and number 
of doses were significantly lower among patients receiving HPβCD-diclofenac versus placebo 
for the 0-24 through 0-120 hour time periods (P&lt;0.0001), as well as versus ketorolac for the 
0-72 through 0-120 hour time periods (P&lt;0.05). HPβCD-diclofenac significantly reduced 
opioid consumption versus placebo in subgroups based on baseline pain severity (moderate, 
severe) and age (&lt;65 years, ≥65 years) from the 0-24 hour period onward. When compared to 
ketorolac, HPβCD-diclofenac also significantly reduced cumulative opioid consumption among 
patients with moderate baseline pain (0-72 through 0-120 hours) and opioid dose number among 
patients ≥65 years old (0-24 through 0-120 hours). 
Conclusion: HPβCD-diclofenac can reduce postoperative opioid requirements. As this analysis 
was not powered to compare opioid-related adverse event rates, follow-up studies examining 
the clinical impact of HPβCD-diclofenac's opioid sparing are warranted. 
Postoperative opioid-sparing effect of injectable HPβCD-diclofenac </p>

<p>study were not blinded, however. Patients in the abdominal/ 
pelvic surgery study received 18.75 or 37.5 mg HPβCD-
diclofenac (based on randomization), 30 mg ketorolac, or 
placebo. Patients in the orthopedic surgery study received 
either 18.75, 37.5, or 50 mg HPβCD-diclofenac, based on 
the presence of defined risk factors. The standard dose was 
37.5 mg; however, patients weighing &lt;50 kg, aged ≥65 years, 
or with NSAID-related gastrointestinal risk factors, hepatic 
impairment, or renal insufficiency (based on serum creati-
nine and blood urea nitrogen measures being greater than 
the upper limit of normal) received the 18.75 mg dose, and 
patients ≥95 kg with no predefined risk factors received 50 
mg. Dose adjustment of ketorolac in the orthopedic surgery 
study was similar. Patients &lt;65 years old and without renal 
insufficiency received a standard dose of 30 mg, while high-
risk patients received 15 mg. 
Study medication was given as an IV bolus injection, with 
the first dose given ≤6 hours following surgery to patients 
reporting moderate to severe pain on the VAS. The time 
of first study drug administration was taken as time 0, and 
subsequent doses were given every 6 hours until discharge 
or withdrawal/discontinuation. In the abdominal/pelvic 
surgery population, patients were observed for at least 48 
hours following the first study drug dose, and for up to 5 
days; in the orthopedic surgery population, patients were 
observed for at least 24 hours, and for up to 5 days. Safety was 
monitored throughout both studies by physical examinations, 
laboratory testing, vital signs, ECG, AEs, and evaluation of 
thrombophlebitis and wound healing (safety data previously 
reported </p>

<p>39,40,43 </p>

<p>). </p>

<p>Assessments of opioid use </p>

<p>In both studies, rescue medication (IV morphine, bolus, 
maximum 7.5 mg every 3 hours) was made available upon 
patient request any time after the initial dose of study drug 
was given. However, patients were encouraged to wait for 
at least 30 minutes after study drug administration in the 
orthopedic surgery study and at least 1 hour after study 
drug administration in the abdominal/pelvic surgery study 
to request for opioids. Patients in the abdominal/pelvic 
surgery study received a 5 mg IV bolus of morphine upon 
request, followed by titration to 7.5 mg, every 3 hours if 
needed. Patients in the orthopedic surgery study received 
IV bolus morphine in 2.5 mg increments, up to 7.5 mg, 
every 3 hours. Though encouraged to wait, patients were not 
denied rescue opioids in the event of requests made prior to 
30 minutes (orthopedic surgery) or 1 hour (abdominal/pel-
vic surgery) after the first study drug dose was given. If the </p>

<p>rescue opioids did not provide adequate analgesia, the patient 
was withdrawn from the study and given pain medication in 
accordance with the investigator's usual practice. Opioid use 
was recorded throughout the treatment period (from the time 
of first study drug administration to up to 120 hours [5 days] 
following first administration). The outcomes examined in 
this pooled analysis were: 1) proportion of patients requir-
ing opioids; 2) cumulative opioid dose for the 0-24, 0-48, 
0-72, 0-96, and 0-120 hour intervals following first study 
drug administration; and 3) cumulative number of opioid 
doses received for the 0-24, 0-48, 0-72, 0-96, and 0-120 
hour intervals following first study drug administration. 
Comparisons were made between patients receiving either 
active treatment (HPβCD-diclofenac, ketorolac) and placebo, 
as well as between patients receiving either active treatment. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Sample size in each study was established by defining 
values for the number of patients required to detect a clini-
cally significant difference in the study's primary efficacy 
measure. Analyses of rescue opioid use were performed on 
the combined intent-to-treat population from both studies 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Analysis System</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., Cary, 
NC, USA) version 9.1 or later. Pooled data are presented as 
mean ± standard deviation (SD), unless otherwise noted. 
Data were analyzed for the pooled study population, as well 
as subgroups based on dose (HPβCD-diclofenac 18.75, 
37.5, and 50 mg), baseline pain (moderate or severe, based 
on 0-100 mm VAS), and age (&lt;65 and ≥65 years). P-values 
for demographic data were calculated using analysis of vari-
ance for numerical variables and Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel 
test for categorical variables. P-values for efficacy outcomes 
(rescue opioid use; HPβCD-diclofenac and ketorolac vs 
placebo; HPβCD-diclofenac vs ketorolac) were calculated 
using least-square mean difference based on an analysis of 
covariance model with treatment, study, and center as factors 
and baseline pain as a covariate. </p>

<p>Results 
Study population </p>

<p>Patient disposition for the pooled population has been 
previously reported in Gan et al. 
44 In total, 608 surgical 
patients were included in the analysis (HPβCD-diclofenac: 
n=318; ketorolac: n=142; placebo: n=148). Within the 
HPβCD-diclofenac group, n=132 patients received HPβCD-
diclofenac 18.75 mg, n=150 received HPβCD-diclofenac 
37.5 mg, and n=36 received HPβCD-diclofenac 50 mg. 
Within the ketorolac group, n=18 patients received ketorolac </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Gan et al </p>

<p>15 mg and n=124 patients received ketorolac 30 mg. Patients 
receiving HPβCD-diclofenac, ketorolac, or placebo did not 
differ significantly with respect to age, sex, or procedure type 
or duration (Table 1). As per the individual study inclusion 
criteria, all patients had moderate or severe baseline pain. 
The proportion of patients with severe baseline pain was 
similar across treatment groups (HPβCD-diclofenac: 41.8% 
[n=133/318]; ketorolac: 40.8% [n=58/142]; placebo: 38.5% 
[n=57/148]). </p>

<p>Rescue opioid consumption: all patients </p>

<p>In total, 93.2% of patients in the placebo group required res-
cue opioids (Figure 1). The proportion of patients receiving 
opioids was significantly lesser than that receiving placebo 
for all HPβCD-diclofenac dose groups (18.75 mg: 79.5% 
[P=0.0017]; 37.5 mg: 68.0% [P&lt;0.0001]; 50 mg: 72.2% 
[P&lt;0.0001]; all dose groups: 73.3% [P&lt;0.0001]) (Figure 1). 
Similarly, significantly lesser number of patients in the 
ketorolac group required opioids as compared to placebo 
(68.3%, P&lt;0.0001). 
Overall, the majority of opioid consumption across all 
treatment groups occurred in the first 24 hours following the 
first study drug administration (Figure 2; Table S1). Over the 
0-120 hour period, patients in the HPβCD-diclofenac 18.75, 
37.5, and 50 mg groups received an average of 9.31±10.35, 
7.41±9.48, and 8.94±10.00 mg of rescue opioids, respectively 
(8.37±9.92 mg for all HPβCD-diclofenac patients combined), 
while patients in the ketorolac group received, on average, 
10.61±14.68 mg and patients in the placebo group received </p>

<p>17.69±14.94 mg of rescue opioids. All HPβCD-diclofenac 
doses, as well as ketorolac were associated with significantly 
lower mean cumulative opioid consumption versus placebo 
for the 0-24 through 0-120 hour time periods (P&lt;0.0001). 
Patients receiving HPβCD-diclofenac required, on aver-
age, significantly lower cumulative opioid doses than those 
receiving ketorolac for the 0-72 through 0-120 hour periods 
(8.34±9.85 vs 10.57±14.64 mg, P=0.034 for 0-72 hours) 
(Figure 2; Table S1), but there was no significant differ-
ence between the HPβCD-diclofenac and ketorolac groups 
for the 0-24 hour period (P=0.30) or the 0-48 hour period 
(P=0.068). In addition, patients receiving HPβCD-diclofenac 
37.5 mg required significantly lower cumulative amounts 
of opioid than the patients receiving ketorolac (30 or 15 
mg), beginning with the 0-48 hour period (7.25±9.22 vs 
9.74±11.80 mg; P=0.020) and through the 0-120 hour period 
(7.41±9.48 vs 10.61±14.68 mg; P=0.009). 
Similar to total cumulative dose, the majority of opioid 
doses were received during the 0-24 hour period and patients 
in all HPβCD-diclofenac dose groups as well as in the 
ketorolac group required significantly fewer opioid doses than 
patients in the placebo group for all time periods (P&lt;0.0001) 
(Figure 3; Table S1). Patients receiving HPβCD-diclofenac 
required significantly fewer opioid doses than those receiving 
ketorolac for the 0-72 through 0-120 hour periods (2.83±3.26 
doses vs 3.43±3.98 doses; P=0.038 for 0-120 hours), but 
not for the 0-24 hour period (P=0.20) or the 0-48 hour 
period (P=0.052). Furthermore, patients receiving HPβCD-
diclofenac 37.5 mg required significantly fewer opioid doses </p>

<p>Table 1 Summary of baseline demographics and surgical characteristics </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac (n=318) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Ketorolac (n=142) 
Placebo (n=148) 
P-value </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Mean age, years (SD) 
48.9 (14.1) 
48.0 (14.7) 
48.6 (14.1) 
0.81 
&lt;65, n (%) 
276 (86.8) 
124 (87.3) 
124 (83.8) 
0.65 </p>

<p>≥65, n (%) 
42 (13.2) 
18 (12.7) 
24 (16.2) 
-
Sex 
Female, n (%) 
233 (73.3) 
107 (75.4) 
107 (72.3) 
0.83 
Male, n (%) 
85 (26.7) 
35 (24.6) 
41 (27.7) 
-
Procedure type </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Abdominal/pelvic, n (%) 
173 (54.4) 
82 (57.7) 
76 (51.4) 
0.55 
Orthopedic, n (%) 
145 (45.6) 
60 (42.3) 
72 (48.6) 
-
Mean procedure duration, hours (SD) 
1.17 (0.69) </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>1.13 (0.65) </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>1.19 (0.71) 
0.76 
VAS pain score at baseline 
Moderate, 
f n (%) 
183 (57.5) 
82 (57.7) 
91 (61.5) 
0.76 
Severe, 
g n (%) 
133 (41.8) 
58 (40.8) 
57 (38.5) 
-
Missing, n (%) 
2 (0.6) 
2 (1.4) 
0 
-</p>

<p>Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Includes n=132 patients receiving HPβCD-diclofenac 18.75 mg, n=150 patients receiving HPβCD-diclofenac 37.5 mg, and n=36 patients receiving HPβCD-diclofenac 
50 mg. 
b From ANOVA for numerical variables and Cochran-Mantel-Haenszel test for categorical variables. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Most common procedures (&gt;5% of subjects in all treatment 
groups): abdominal hysterectomy, abdominal surgery, bunionectomy/foot bone, inguinal hernia repair, knee replacement, vaginal hysterectomy. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>n=316, 
e n=141. 
f Baseline 
reported pain ≥50 and &lt;70 mm on 0-100 mm VAS. </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>Baseline reported pain ≥70 mm on 0-100 mm VAS. 
Abbreviations: ANOVA, analysis of variance; HPβCD, hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin; SD, standard deviation; VAS, visual analog scale. </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Postoperative opioid-sparing effect of injectable HPβCD-diclofenac </p>

<p>Cumulative amount of rescue opioid (mg) </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0-24 
0-48 
0-72 
0-96 
0 -120 </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac 18.75 mg 
(n=132) 
HPβCD-diclofenac 37.5 mg 
(n=150) 
HPβCD-diclofenac 50 mg 
(n=36) 
HPβCD-diclofenac, all doses 
(n=318) 
Ketorolac 
(n=142) 
Placebo 
(n=148) </p>

<p>igure 2 Total rescue opioid consumption among patients receiving intravenous HPβCD-diclofenac, ketorolac, or placebo for acute postsurgical pain. 
Notes: Data from the combined ITT populations are presented. *P&lt;0.0001 versus placebo, 
^P &lt;0.05 versus ketorolac from least-square mean difference based on ANCOVA 
model with treatment, study, and center as factors and baseline pain as a covariate. For mean values and SDs, see Table S1. 
Abbreviations: ANCOVA, analysis of covariance; HPβCD, hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin; ITT, intent to treat; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Rescue opioid use among patients receiving intravenous HPβCD-diclofenac, ketorolac, or placebo for acute postsurgical pain. 
Notes: Data from the combined ITT populations are presented. *P&lt;0.005 versus placebo, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt;0.0001 versus placebo from least-square mean difference based on ANCOVA 
model with treatment, study, and center as factors and baseline pain as a covariate. There was no significant difference between any HPβCD-diclofenac dose and ketorolac. 
Abbreviations: ANCOVA, analysis of covariance; HPβCD, hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin; ITT, intent to treat. </p>

<p>Proportion of patients receiving rescue opioids (%) </p>

<p>Treatment group </p>

<p>79.5% </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>85 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>68.0% </p>

<p>72.2% 
73.3% </p>

<p>68.3% </p>

<p>93.2% </p>

<p>HPβCD-
diclofenac 
18.75 mg 
(n=132) </p>

<p>HPβCD-
diclofenac 
37.5 mg 
(n=150) </p>

<p>HPβCD-
diclofenac 
50 mg 
(n=36) </p>

<p>HPβCD-
diclofenac, 
all doses 
(n=318) </p>

<p>Ketorolac 
(n=142) </p>

<p>Placebo 
(n=148) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p># 
# </p>

<p># </p>

<p>than the patients receiving ketorolac, beginning at the 0-48 
hour interval (2.29±2.98 doses vs 3.22±3.55 doses; P=0.021) 
and through the 0-120 hour interval (2.34±3.04 doses vs 
3.43±3.98 doses; P=0.013) (Figure 3; Table S1). HPβCD-</p>

<p>diclofenac was associated with a significantly longer median 
time to first rescue opioid dose than placebo (194.0 minutes 
[95% confidence interval {CI}: 143.0-240.0 minutes] vs 
74.5 minutes [95% CI: 57.0-96.0 minutes]; P&lt;0.0001). </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Gan et al </p>

<p>Similarly, ketorolac significantly reduced median time to first 
rescue opioid dose versus placebo (203.0 minutes [95% CI: 
145.0-397.0 minutes]; P&lt;0.0001), but there was no signifi-
cant difference between HPβCD-diclofenac and ketorolac 
(P=0.38). </p>

<p>Rescue opioid consumption: by baseline 
pain and age subgroups </p>

<p>For patients with moderate baseline pain (≥50 and &lt;70 
mm on the VAS), all HPβCD-diclofenac groups and the 
ketorolac group were associated with significantly reduced 
mean cumulative opioid consumption versus placebo for 
all time periods (all P&lt;0.005 vs placebo) (Figure 4A; Table 
S2). Patients who received HPβCD-diclofenac had reduced 
opioid consumption versus patients who received ketorolac 
for the 0-72 hour period (7.36±9.22mg vs 9.72±15.73 mg; 
P=0.034) to 0-120 hour period (7.42±9.35 mg vs 9.78±15.80 
mg; P=0.035), but not for 0-24 hours (P=0.39) or 0-48 
hours (P=0.071). Patients receiving HPβCD-diclofenac 
37.5 mg had significantly reduced mean cumulative opioid 
consumption versus patients receiving ketorolac, beginning 
at the 0-48 hour period (5.67±8.00 mg vs 8.70±11.85 mg; 
P=0.043) and persisting through the 0-120 hour period 
(5.77±8.15 mg vs 9.78±15.80 mg; P=0.018). For patients 
with severe baseline pain (≥70 mm on the VAS), all active 
treatment groups were associated with significantly lower 
mean cumulative opioid consumption versus placebo (all 
P&lt;0.005). However, there was no significant opioid-sparing 
effect of HPβCD-diclofenac versus ketorolac (Figure 4B; </p>

<p>Table S2). In both subgroups based on baseline pain, all 
active treatment groups received significantly fewer opi-
oid doses versus placebo (P&lt;0.005 for all time periods); 
however, no opioid-sparing effect of HPβCD-diclofenac 
versus ketorolac with respect to dose number was observed 
(Figure 5; Table S3). 
Among patients &lt;65 years old, all HPβCD-diclofenac 
dose groups as well as the ketorolac group required signifi-
cantly fewer opioid doses than the placebo group (P≤0.0001 
for all time periods) (Figure 6A; Table S4). No opioid-sparing 
effect was observed for HPβCD-diclofenac versus ketorolac. 
Patients ≥65 years old received lower, risk-adjusted HPβCD-
diclofenac and ketorolac doses. Patients in the HPβCD-
diclofenac 18.75 mg group required significantly fewer 
opioid doses than those receiving placebo and ketorolac for 
all time periods (P&lt;0.05 vs placebo, P&lt;0.05 vs ketorolac) 
(Figure 6B; Table S4). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The goal of postoperative analgesia is to optimally manage 
pain while minimizing the potential for adverse effects that 
can delay recovery or present risks to the patient. While 
opioids are efficacious analgesics, AEs associated with this 
drug class can be wide ranging and represent an important 
concern for clinicians and patients. 
2,4-9,45 Furthermore, 
opioid-related AEs in postsurgical patients are associated 
with increased hospital length of stay and added costs which 
recent studies have estimated to range from $4,707 to $13,737 
per patient. 
9-11,46,47 Thus, multimodal pain management </p>

<p>Cumulative number of rescue opioid doses </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
0-24 
0-48 
0-72 
0-96 
0-120 </p>

<p>Time interval (hours) </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac 18.75 mg 
(n=132) </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac 37.5 mg 
(n=150) </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac 50 mg 
(n=36) </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac, all doses 
(n=318) </p>

<p>Ketorolac 
(n=142) </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac 18.75 mg 
(n=84) 
HPβCD-diclofenac 37.5 mg 
(n=76) </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac 50 mg 
(n=23) 
HPβCD-diclofenac, all doses 
(n=183) 
Ketorolac 
(n=82) 
Placebo 
(n=91) </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac 18.75 mg 
(n=47) 
HPβCD-diclofenac 37.5 mg 
(n=73) 
HPβCD-diclofenac 50 mg 
(n=13) 
HPβCD-diclofenac, all doses 
(n=133) 
Ketorolac 
(n=58) </p>

<p>Placebo 
(n=57) </p>

<p>Time interval (hours) </p>

<p>0-24 
0-48 
0 -72 
0-96 
0 -120 
Cumulative amount of rescue 
opioid (mg) </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Figure 4 Total rescue opioid consumption, by baseline pain severity, among patients receiving intravenous HPβCD-diclofenac, ketorolac, or placebo for acute postsurgical 
pain. 
Notes: Data are presented for patients with (A) moderate baseline pain (≥50 and &lt;70 mm) and (B) severe baseline pain (≥70 mm) within 6 hours following surgery, as 
assessed on the 0-100 mm VAS. Data from the combined ITT populations are presented. *P&lt;0.005 versus placebo, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt;0.0001 versus placebo, 
^P &lt;0.05 versus ketorolac 
from least-square mean difference based on ANCOVA model with treatment, study, and center as factors and baseline pain as a covariate. For mean values and SDs, 
see Table S2. 
Abbreviations: ANCOVA, analysis of covariance; HPβCD, hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin; ITT, intent to treat; SD, standard deviation; VAS, visual analog scale. </p>

<p>approaches that make use of analgesics with different mecha-
nisms of action, such as the NSAIDs, are recommended. </p>

<p>31,48 </p>

<p>The results of this analysis of data from two Phase III tri-
als reveal that repeated-dose HPβCD-diclofenac was associ-
ated with a significant opioid-sparing effect when given for up 
to 5 days for moderate to severe pain following abdominal/ 
pelvic or orthopedic surgery. In addition, HPβCD-diclofenac 
(37.5 mg dose groups and all dose groups combined) dem-
onstrated significant opioid-sparing effects in comparison 
to the active comparator ketorolac, a drug currently used in 
clinical practice, with respect to both cumulative rescue opi-
oid dose and the number of doses. There were no discernible 
differences in baseline pain level (moderate, severe) between 
comparator groups, suggesting that the observed differences 
are not likely due to differences in baseline pain. Notably, 
opioid consumption appeared to be lowest in the HPβCD-</p>

<p>diclofenac 37.5 mg group. While potential reasons for this 
were not investigated, it is noteworthy that 37.5 mg is the 
standard HPβCD-diclofenac dose and was given to patients 
without defined risk factors, while the 50 mg dose was given 
to patients weighing ≥95 kg. The results of this analysis 
expand upon previously reported data from the individual 
studies, which showed that HPβCD-diclofenac was associ-
ated with increased time to rescue opioid administration and 
reduced opioid consumption over 72 hours versus placebo in 
abdominal/pelvic surgery patients, 
39 as well as increased time 
to rescue opioid administration and reduced opioid consump-
tion over 120 hours versus placebo in orthopedic surgery 
patients. </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Pooled analysis allowed for in-depth examination of 
opioid consumption in terms of cumulative dose and num-
ber of doses, both in the entire population as well as in </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Gan et al </p>

<p>Moderate baseline pain </p>

<p>Cumulative number of rescue 
opioid doses </p>

<p>Cumulative number of rescue 
opioid doses </p>

<p>Time interval (hours) </p>

<p>Time interval (hours) </p>

<p>Severe baseline pain </p>

<p>0-24 
0-48 
0-72 
0 -96 
0-120 </p>

<p>0-24 
0-48 
0 -72 
0-96 
0-120 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac 18.75 mg 
(n=84) </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac 37.5 mg 
(n=76) </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac 50 mg 
(n=23) </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac, all doses 
(n=183) </p>

<p>Ketorolac 
(n=82) </p>

<p>Placebo 
(n=91) </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac 18.75 mg 
(n=47) 
HPβCD-diclofenac 37.5 mg 
(n=73) 
HPβCD-diclofenac 50 mg 
(n=13) 
HPβCD-diclofenac, all doses 
(n=133) 
Ketorolac 
(n=58) 
Placebo 
(n=57) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Figure 5 Total number of rescue opioid doses, by baseline pain severity, among patients receiving intravenous HPβCD-diclofenac, ketorolac, or placebo for acute postsurgical 
pain. 
Notes: Data are presented for patients with (A) moderate baseline pain (≥50 and &lt;70 mm) and (B) severe baseline pain (≥70 mm) within 6 hours following surgery, as 
assessed on the 0-100 mm VAS. Data from the combined ITT populations are presented. *P&lt;0.005 versus placebo, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P≤0.0001 versus placebo versus ketorolac from least-
square mean difference based on ANCOVA model with treatment, study, and center as factors and baseline pain as a covariate. For mean values and SDs, see Table S3. 
Abbreviations: ANCOVA, analysis of covariance; HPβCD, hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin; ITT, intent to treat; SD, standard deviation; VAS, visual analog scale. </p>

<p>the key patient subgroups defined by HPβCD-diclofenac 
dose received, baseline postsurgical pain, and age. This 
stratification revealed that HPβCD-diclofenac provided 
postoperative opioid-sparing advantages over ketorolac 
in patients with moderate pain (lower cumulative opioid 
consumption, 0-72 through 0-120 hour periods), as well as 
in patients ≥65 years old (fewer opioid doses, 0-24 through 
0-120 hour periods). This analysis did not compare opioid 
consumption in patients with moderate versus severe pain 
specifically; however, the results do indicate significant 
reduction in total consumption and the number of doses for 
both active treatments in comparison to placebo, independent 
of the baseline pain level. This is consistent with previously 
reported efficacy measures from the two Phase III trials. </p>

<p>39,40 </p>

<p>In addition, this study examined only patients undergoing </p>

<p>a single surgical procedure during their admission. The 
opioid-sparing effects of HPβCD-diclofenac in patients 
undergoing multiple procedures, which might necessitate 
increasingly complex pain management regimens, remain to be 
elucidated. 
It is important to note that the analgesic properties of 
NSAIDs are not solely attributable to their anti-inflammatory 
effects, and there is growing evidence that diclofenac has 
a range of mechanisms of action that differ from other 
drugs in the NSAID class. 
33 In addition to the well-known 
anti-inflammatory mechanism of action of NSAIDs, puta-
tive mechanisms of action of diclofenac include inhibi-
tion of leukotriene synthesis, inhibition of phospholipase 
A2, and modulation of arachidonic acid levels, as well as 
stimulation of peripheral nitric oxide-cyclic guanosine </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Postoperative opioid-sparing effect of injectable HPβCD-diclofenac </p>

<p>monophosphate-potassium channel pathways. 
33 Reasons 
for the observed differences with respect to opioid spar-
ing between HPβCD-diclofenac and ketorolac were not 
examined in the present analysis. However, future studies 
examining the clinical implications of mechanistic dif-
ferences between NSAIDs could provide critical insight 
into the differences between NSAIDs observed in clinical 
practice. 
While the total number of opioid doses was evaluated 
in patient subgroups based on age (&lt;65 and ≥65 years), it 
is important to note that cumulative opioid dose was not 
examined in the context of age in the present analysis. Based 
on the individual study inclusion criteria, the vast majority 
of patients ≥65 years old in the pooled population (n=82/84, 
97.6%) were the patients who participated in the ortho-
pedic surgery study, and the effect of HPβCD-diclofenac </p>

<p>on cumulative opioid dose in this patient subgroup has 
been previously reported. 
40 In line with the current results, 
Daniels et al 
40 reported that total opioid consumption was 
significantly reduced with HPβCD-diclofenac versus both 
placebo and ketorolac in patients aged ≥65 years over 0-24, 
0-48, 0-72, and 0-120 hours. In addition to its effects when 
given as part of a repeated-dose regimen, the opioid-sparing 
effects of single-dose HPβCD-diclofenac have also been 
demonstrated. Most notably, time to rescue opioid adminis-
tration following dental surgery was significantly prolonged 
by a range of HPβCD-diclofenac doses (9.4-75 mg) versus 
placebo. </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>The results of the current analysis are also in agreement 
with evidence for the general opioid-sparing actions of 
NSAIDs and acetaminophen. 
2,12,22,23,49-53 Administration of 
oral or IV diclofenac (Voltarol 
™ [Novartis Pharmaceuticals </p>

<p>Age &lt;65 years </p>

<p>Age ≥65 years </p>

<p>Time interval (hours) </p>

<p>Time interval (hours) </p>

<p>0-24 
0-48 
0-72 
0 -96 
0-120 </p>

<p>0-24 
0-48 
0-72 
0-96 
0 -120 </p>

<p>Cumulative number of rescue 
opioid doses </p>

<p>Cumulative number of rescue 
opioid doses </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac 18.75 mg 
(n=90) 
HPβCD-diclofenac 37.5 mg 
(n=150) 
HPβCD-diclofenac 50 mg 
(n=36) 
HPβCD-diclofenac, all doses 
(n=276) 
Ketorolac 
(n=124) 
Placebo 
(n=124) </p>

<p>HPβCD-diclofenac 18.75 mg 
(n=42) 
Ketorolac 
(n=18) 
Placebo 
(n=24) </p>

<p>Figure 6 Total number of rescue opioid doses, by age group, among patients receiving intravenous HPβCD-diclofenac, ketorolac, or placebo for acute postsurgical pain. 
Notes: Data are presented for patients aged (A) ≥18 and &lt;65 years and (B) ≥65 years. Data from the combined ITT populations are presented. *P&lt;0.05 versus placebo, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P≤0.0001 versus placebo, 
^P &lt;0.05 versus ketorolac from least-square mean difference based on ANCOVA model with treatment, study, and center as factors and baseline 
pain as a covariate. For mean values and SDs, see Table S4. 
Abbreviations: ANCOVA, analysis of covariance; HPβCD, hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin; ITT, intent to treat; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Gan et al </p>

<p>UK Ltd]; formulated with propylene glycol and benzyl 
alcohol) has been previously demonstrated to reduce 
patient-controlled analgesia oxycodone consumption and 
postoperative nausea and vomiting incidence following knee 
surgery. 
52 While opioid-sparing effects of ketorolac in the 
postoperative setting have been demonstrated 
12,14,22,53 -and 
indeed were evident in the present analysis as well -the 
results of this study suggest that HPβCD-diclofenac may 
be able to support greater opioid sparing than ketorolac in 
broader surgical practice, an observation consistent with 
previous findings that diclofenac can provide superior 
opioid-sparing effects when compared to other NSAIDs. </p>

<p>52 </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In summary, data from this pooled analysis demonstrate that 
use of HPβCD-diclofenac in the postoperative setting was 
associated with reduced opioid consumption in comparison 
to placebo, and that the standard HPβCD-diclofenac dose 
(37.5 mg) was associated with significant postoperative 
opioid sparing over ketorolac in terms of cumulative dose 
and number of doses, for the 0-48 through 0-120 hour 
postoperative time periods. While pooled analyses can 
present challenges due to between-study heterogeneity, the 
studies included in the present analysis were amenable to 
this approach, given their high degree of similarity with 
respect to study design, inclusion and exclusion criteria, 
comparators, drug dosages, dosing schedules, and outcome 
assessment methods. </p>

<p>54-56 </p>

<p>Though the current study provides an in-depth examina-
tion of the opioid-sparing effect of HPβCD-diclofenac, it 
does not address the important question of the clinical impact 
of opioid sparing afforded by this diclofenac formulation 
(ie, impact on opioid-related AEs). Higher postoperative 
opioid doses have been associated with increased AE risk, </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>suggesting potentially significant clinical implications of 
the findings of this analysis. An in-depth examination of 
opioid-related AEs in patients receiving HPβCD-diclofenac 
versus other analgesics will require a larger population than 
that encompassed by these two studies. Future studies, such 
as retrospective analyses of deidentified patient data from 
large electronic health records, would provide additional 
insight into this important question. Furthermore, such 
studies could examine the key factors related to recovery 
from surgery, such as pain upon movement, time to mobil-
ity, and length of hospital stay, as well as the outcomes in 
highly specific patient risk groups, including, for example, 
patients ≥75 years old. </p>

<p>Editorial/medical writing support was provided by Scott 
Paluszkiewicz, PhD and Tejaswi Worlikar, MS, MSE of 
Boston Strategic Partners, Inc., and was funded by Hospira, 
Inc., which was acquired by Pfizer Inc. in September 2015. 
The studies included in the pooled analysis were spon-
sored by Javelin Pharmaceuticals, Inc., Cambridge, MA 
(acquired in 2010 by Hospira, Inc., Lake Forest, IL, USA) 
and Hospira, Inc., which was acquired by Pfizer in September 
2015. The present analysis was funded by Hospira, Inc., a 
Pfizer company. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>TJG, NS, and SED were paid investigators for the studies 
included in the analysis. PGL was an employee of Hospira, 
Inc. at the time the study was initiated. CRDR is an employee 
of Hospira, Inc., a Pfizer company. DAH was the full-time 
Chief Operating Officer for the study sponsor during the trials 
included in the present study, and served as a consultant to 
Hospira, Inc. following its acquisition of Javelin Pharmaceu-
ticals in 2010. DBC was the full-time Chief Medical Officer 
for the study sponsor during the trials included in the present 
study, and served as a consultant to Hospira, Inc. following 
its acquisition of Javelin Pharmaceuticals in 2010. </p>



<p>Journal of Pain Research 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Gan et al </p>



<p>Journal of Pain Research 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Postoperative opioid-sparing effect of injectable HPβCD-diclofenac </p>

<p>Supplementary materials </p>

<p>Table S1 Total rescue opioid consumption and total number of rescue opioid doses among patients receiving intravenous HPβCD-
diclofenac, ketorolac, or placebo for acute postsurgical pain </p>

<p>Cumulative rescue opioid consumption, mg (SD) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
18.75 mg (n=132) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
37.5 mg (n=150) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
50 mg (n=36) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
all doses (n=318) </p>

<p>Ketorolac 
(n=142) </p>

<p>Placebo 
(n=148) </p>

<p>Time interval (hours) 
0-24 
7.36 (7.47)* 
6.11 (7.04)* 
6.64 (6.91)* 
6.69 (7.21)* 
7.41 (8.03)* 
13.13 (9.55) 
0-48 
8.89 (9.79)* 
7.25 (9.22)* 
,^8 .04 (8.65)* 
8.02 (9.40)* 
9.74 (11.80)* 16.82 (13.42) 
0-72 
9.22 (10.20)* 
7.41 (9.48)* 
,^8 .94 (10.00)* 
8.34 (9.85)* 
,^1 0.57 (14.64)* 17.67 (14.94) 
0-96 
9.31 (10.35)* 
7.41 (9.48)* 
,^8 .94 (10.00)* 
8.37 (9.92)* 
,^1 0.59 (14.66)* 17.69 (14.94) 
0-120 
9.31 (10.35)* 
7.41 (9.48)* 
,^8 .94 (10.00)* 
8.37 (9.92)* 
,^1 0.61 (14.68)* 17.69 (14.94) </p>

<p>Cumulative number of rescue opioid doses (SD) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
18.75 mg (n=132) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
37.5 mg (n=150) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
50 mg (n=36) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
all doses (n=318) </p>

<p>Ketorolac 
(n=142) </p>

<p>Placebo 
(n=148) </p>

<p>Time interval (hours) 
0-24 
2.59 (2.42)* 
1.95 (2.38)* 
2.56 (2.73)* 
2.28 (2.45)* 
2.53 (2.78)* 
4.34 (3.20) 
0-48 
3.11 (3.13)* 
2.29 (2.98)* 
,^3 .00 (3.14)* 
2.71 (3.08)* 
3.22 (3.55)* 
5.42 (4.28) 
0-72 
3.22 (3.27)* 
2.34 (3.04)* 
,^3 .33 (3.61)* 
2.82 (3.23)* 
,^3 .42 (3.95)* 
5.70 (4.81) 
0-96 
3.26 (3.34)* 
2.34 (3.04)* 
,^3 .33 (3.61)* 
2.83 (3.26)* 
,^3 .42 (3.97)* 
5.70 (4.82) 
0-120 
3.26 (3.34)* 
2.34 (3.04)* 
,^3 .33 (3.61)* 
2.83 (3.26)* 
,^3 .43 (3.98)* 
5.70 (4.82) </p>

<p>Notes: *P&lt;0.0001 versus placebo, 
^P &lt;0.05 versus ketorolac from least-square mean difference based on ANCOVA model with treatment, study, and center as factors and 
baseline pain as a covariate. 
Abbreviations: ANCOVA, analysis of covariance; HPβCD, hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Table S2 Total rescue opioid consumption, by baseline pain severity, among patients receiving intravenous HPβCD-diclofenac, 
ketorolac, or placebo for acute postsurgical pain </p>

<p>Cumulative rescue opioid consumption (SD) </p>

<p>Moderate baseline pain (≥50 and &lt;70 mm on 0-100 mm VAS) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
18.75 mg (n=84) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
37.5 mg (n=76) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
50 mg (n=23) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
all doses (n=183) </p>

<p>Ketorolac 
(n=82) </p>

<p>Placebo 
(n=91) </p>

<p>Time interval (hours) 
0-24 
6.81 (7.83) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>4.83 (6.38) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>6.04 (6.49) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>5.89 (7.12) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>6.30 (7.48) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>12.31 (9.26) 
0-48 
7.99 (9.05) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>5.67 (8.00) 
#,^7 .72 (8.92)* 
6.99 (8.64) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>8.70 (11.85) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>15.20 (12.34) 
0-72 
8.36 (9.58) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>5.77 (8.15) 
#,^8 .96 (10.73)* 
7.36 (9.22) 
#,^9 .72 (15.73)* 15.85 (13.60) 
0-96 
8.49 (9.85) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>5.77 (8.15) 
#,^8 .96 (10.73)* 
7.42 (9.35) 
#,^9 .75 (15.76)* 15.87 (13.59) 
0-120 
8.49 (9.85) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>5.77 (8.15) 
#,^8 .96 (10.73)* 
7.42 (9.35) 
#,^9 .78 (15.80)* 15.87 (13.59) </p>

<p>Severe baseline pain (≥70 mm on 0-100 mm VAS) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
18.75 mg (n=47) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
37.5 mg (n=73) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
50 mg (n=13) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
all doses (n=133) </p>

<p>Ketorolac 
(n=58) </p>

<p>Placebo 
(n=57) </p>

<p>Time interval (hours) 
0-24 
8.23 (6.83)* 
7.44 (7.53) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>7.69 (7.75)* 
7.74 (7.26) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>9.27 (8.55)* 
14.44 (9.94) 
0-48 
10.35 (10.96)* 
8.89 (10.20) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>8.62 (8.47)* 
9.38 (10.28) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>11.59 (11.68)* 19.40 (14.72) 
0-72 
10.62 (11.23)* 
9.13 (10.54) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>8.92 (8.98)* 
9.64 (10.60) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>12.18 (13.06)* 20.58 (16.58) 
0-96 
10.62 (11.23)* 
9.13 (10.54) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>8.92 (8.98)* 
9.64 (10.60) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>12.18 (13.06)* 20.58 (16.58) 
0-120 
10.62 (11.23)* 
9.13 (10.54) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>8.92 (8.98)* 
9.64 (10.60) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>12.18 (13.06)* 20.58 (16.58) </p>

<p>Notes: *P&lt;0.005 versus placebo, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt;0.0001 versus placebo, 
^P &lt;0.05 versus ketorolac from least-square mean difference based on ANCOVA model with treatment, study, 
and center as factors and baseline pain as a covariate. 
Abbreviations: ANCOVA, analysis of covariance; HPβCD, hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin; SD, standard deviation; VAS, visual analog scale. </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>Gan et al </p>

<p>Table S3 Total number of rescue opioid doses, by baseline pain severity, among patients receiving intravenous HPβCD-diclofenac, 
ketorolac, or placebo for acute postsurgical pain </p>

<p>Cumulative number of rescue opioid doses (SD) </p>

<p>Moderate baseline pain (≥50 and &lt;70 mm on 0-100 mm VAS) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
18.75 mg (n=84) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
37.5 mg (n=76) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
50 mg (n=23) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
all doses (n=183) </p>

<p>Ketorolac 
(n=82) </p>

<p>Placebo 
(n=91) </p>

<p>Time interval (hours) 
0-24 
2.37 (2.45) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>1.67 (2.47) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.26 (2.24) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.07 (2.44) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.17 (2.42) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>4.25 (3.22) 
0-48 
2.79 (2.92) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>1.99 (3.15) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.83 (3.00) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.46 (3.04) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.93 (3.49)* 5.15 (4.34) 
0-72 
2.89 (3.06) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.01 (3.18) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.30 (3.72)* 
2.58 (3.22) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.15 (3.97)* 5.40 (4.96) 
0-96 
2.95 (3.19) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.01 (3.18) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.30 (3.72)* 
2.61 (3.28) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.16 (4.00)* 5.41 (4.96) 
0-120 
2.95 (3.19) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.01 (3.18) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.30 (3.72)* 
2.61 (3.28) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.17 (4.02)* 5.41 (4.96) </p>

<p>Severe baseline pain (≥70 mm on 0-100 mm VAS) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
18.75 mg (n=47) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
37.5 mg (n=73) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
50 mg (n=13) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
all doses (n=133) </p>

<p>Ketorolac 
(n=58) </p>

<p>Placebo 
(n=57) </p>

<p>Time interval (hours) </p>

<p>0-24 
2.91 (2.34)* 
2.21 (2.27) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.08 (3.48)* 
2.54 (2.44) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.12 (3.17)* 4.47 (3.21) 
0-48 
3.60 (3.40)* 
2.59 (2.79) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.31 (3.50)* 
3.02 (3.10) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.74 (3.62)* 5.84 (4.20) 
0-72 
3.70 (3.55)* 
2.66 (2.89) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.38 (3.55)* 
3.10 (3.21) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.91 (3.93)* 6.18 (4.58) 
0-96 
3.70 (3.55)* 
2.66 (2.89) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.38 (3.55)* 
3.10 (3.21) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.91 (3.93)* 6.18 (4.58) 
0-120 
3.70 (3.55)* 
2.66 (2.89) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.38 (3.55)* 
3.10 (3.21) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.91 (3.93)* 6.18 (4.58) </p>

<p>Notes: *P&lt;0.005 versus placebo, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt;0.0001 versus placebo versus ketorolac from least-square mean difference based on ANCOVA model with treatment, study, and center 
as factors and baseline pain as a covariate. 
Abbreviations: ANCOVA, analysis of covariance; HPβCD, hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin; SD, standard deviation; VAS, visual analog scale. </p>

<p>Table S4 Total number of rescue opioid doses, by age group, among patients receiving intravenous HPβCD-diclofenac, ketorolac, or 
placebo for acute postsurgical pain </p>

<p>Cumulative number of rescue opioid doses (SD) </p>

<p>Age &lt;65 years </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
18.75 mg (n=90) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
37.5 mg (n=150) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
50 mg (n=36) </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
all doses (n=276) </p>

<p>Ketorolac 
(n=124) </p>

<p>Placebo 
(n=124) </p>

<p>Time interval (hours) </p>

<p>0-24 
2.29 (2.17) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>1.95 (2.38) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.56 (2.73) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.14 (2.37) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.20 (2.55) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>4.16 (3.28) 
0-48 
2.74 (2.94) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.29 (2.98) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.00 (3.14) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.53 (2.99) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.85 (3.35) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>5.27 (4.39) 
0-72 
2.86 (3.08) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.34 (3.04) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.33 (3.61) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.64 (3.14) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.02 (3.75) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>5.50 (4.88) 
0-96 
2.86 (3.08) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.34 (3.04) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.33 (3.61) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.64 (3.14) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.02 (3.75) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>5.50 (4.88) 
0-120 
2.86 (3.08) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.34 (3.04) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.33 (3.61) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>2.64 (3.14) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>3.02 (3.75) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>5.50 (4.88) </p>

<p>Age ≥65 years </p>

<p>HPbCD-diclofenac 
18.75 mg (n=42) </p>

<p>Ketorolac (n=18) 
Placebo (n=24) </p>

<p>Time interval (hours) </p>

<p>0-24 
3.24 (2.81)* 
,^4 .78 (3.32) 
5.25 (2.67) 
0-48 
3.90 (3.39)* 
,^5 .78 (3.92) 
6.21 (3.65) 
0-72 
4.00 (3.55)* 
,^6 .11 (4.36) 
6.71 (4.43) 
0-96 
4.12 (3.73)* 
,^6 .17 (4.42) 
6.75 (4.43) 
0-120 
4.12 (3.73)* 
,^6 .22 (4.49) 
6.75 (4.43) </p>

<p>Notes: *P&lt;0.05 versus placebo, </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P≤0.0001 versus placebo, 
^P &lt;0.05 versus ketorolac from least-square mean difference based on ANCOVA model with treatment, study, 
and center as factors and baseline pain as a covariate. 
Abbreviations: ANCOVA, analysis of covariance; HPβCD, hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin; SD, standard deviation; VAS, visual analog scale. </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: https://www.dovepress.com/journal-of-pain-research-journal </p>

<p>The Journal of Pain Research is an international, peer reviewed, open 
access, online journal that welcomes laboratory and clinical findings 
in the fields of pain research and the prevention and management 
of pain. Original research, reviews, symposium reports, hypoth-
esis formation and commentaries are all considered for publication. </p>

<p>The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Postoperative opioid-sparing effect of injectable HPβCD-diclofenac </p>

</text></tei>