<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5133663" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A B S T R A C T </p>

<p>Cholesterol is a main lipid component of sperm cell that is essential for sperm membrane fluidity, capacitation, 
and acrosomal reaction. Recent data obtained in bovine sperm showed that sperm capacitation is associated to 
the formation of oxysterols, oxidized products of cholesterol. The aim of this study was to profile oxysterol 
content in human semen, and to investigate their potential role in sperm pathophysiology. Among the 12 
oxysterols analyzed, 25-hydroxycholesterol (25-HC) resulted the most represented in normozoospermic 
samples, and its concentration positively correlated with spermatozoa number. We detected Cholesterol 25-
hydroxylase, the enzyme responsible for 25-HC production, in human spermatozoa at the level of the neck and 
the post acrosomal area. Upon incubation with spermatozoa, 25-HC induced calcium and cholesterol transients 
in connection with the acrosomal reaction. Our results support a role for 25-HC in sperm function. </p>

<p>Spermatozoa are immotile and unable to fertilize an oocyte at the 
stage of releasing from the seminiferous epithelium. Fertilizing capa-
city of sperm cells is acquired during their passage through the 
epididymis [1]. Cholesterol, a main component of cell membrane 
system, affects sperm membrane fluidity, and promotes the complex 
mechanism leading to the evolution of a capacitated state, which is 
ultimately completed in the female reproductive tract. Cholesterol 
excreted from the epididymal epithelium contributes to the maturation 
of transiting sperm [2], and cholesterol content in sperm membrane is 
tight regulated during epididymal transit [1]. 
Capacitation is a process consisting of several steps leading to 
changes in sperm motility and acrosomal responsiveness; these events 
are highly dependent upon changes in plasma membrane cholesterol 
[3]. One of the key steps of capacitation is the loss of cholesterol from 
the sperm plasma membrane [4] in a process that can be promoted by 
albumin and bicarbonate, which facilitate lipoprotein-mediated cho-</p>

<p>lesterol efflux [5-7]. 
De Lamirande and Gagnon [8] highlighted the role of reactive 
oxygen species (ROS) concentration in sperm capacitation. Mild ROS 
formation would favor signaling events that are involved in sperm 
capacitation [9,10]; on the other hand, higher rates of ROS formation 
would result in irreversible deterioration of sperm cell function [11]. 
Concerning ROS-mediated mechanisms in sperm function, most 
attention has been reserved to phospholipid peroxidation [12]. Little 
attention has been devoted to cholesterol by-products generated by 
autoxidation, i.e. oxysterols, notwithstanding cholesterol is the most 
abundant lipid component of sperm cells, and is an excellent sensor of 
lipid peroxidation [13]. In addition, cholesterol can be transformed 
enzymatically into oxysterols that collectively are recognized as potent 
bioactive molecules [13]. Recently, Brouwers et al. [14] reported on the 
presence and formation of oxysterols in bovine sperm, and showed the 
formation of oxysterols during capacitation. These results represent a 
significant advance in our understanding of the redox regulation of 
sperm capacitation, opening new perspectives of study on the mechan-</p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.redox.2016.11.008 
Received 18 September 2016; Received in revised form 7 November 2016; Accepted 8 November 2016 </p>

<p>⁎ Correspondence to: Department of Medico-Surgical Sciences and Biotechnologies, Vascular Biology &amp; Mass Spectrometry Lab, corso della Repubblica 79, 04100 Latina. Italy. </p>

<p>E-mail address: luigi.iuliano@uniroma1.it (L. Iuliano). </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CTC, chlortetracycline; ROS, reactive oxygen species; BHT, butylated hydroxytoluene; 7α-HC, 7α-hydroxycholesterol; 7β-HC, 7β-hydroxycholesterol; 7KC, 7-
Ketocholesterol; 4β-HC, 4β-hydroxycholesterol; 4α-HC, 4α-hydroxycholesterol; 5α, 6α-EC, 5α,6α-epoxycholesterol; 5β, 6β-EC, 5β,6β-epoxycholesterol; ,5α,6β-triol, Triol, cholestane-
3β; 6-OCDO, 6-oxo-cholestan-3β,5α-diol; 25-HC, 25-hydroxycholesterol; and 27-HC, 27-hydroxycholesterol; Ch25H, Cholesterol-25-hydroxylase </p>

<p>Redox Biology 11 (2017) 111-117 </p>

<p>Available online 22 November 2016 
2213-2317/ © 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/BY-NC-ND/4.0/). </p>

<p>MARK </p>

<p>isms that regulate the male fertility physiology. Since oxysterols are 
more hydrophilic than cholesterol, they move more freely out of the 
membrane and may account for most of the actions currently attrib-
uted to cholesterol. 
The main objective of the present study was to identify and 
quantify, for the first time, the different species of oxysterols in human 
semen from normozoospermic, oligoasthenoteratozoospermic and 
asthenozoospermic patients. The secondary aim was to investigate 
the potential role of oxysterols in sperm pathophysiology. </p>

<p>2. Material and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Study population and design </p>

<p>To investigate the profile of human sperm oxysterols in subjects 
with normal and altered sperm characteristics, we recruited 150 
consecutive subjects referring at the Centre of Andrology of S.M. 
Goretti Hospital (Latina) for analysis of seminal fluid between 
January 2012 and June 2014. Was performed a clinical history to 
collect personal information including lifestyle factors, sexual and 
reproductive status and medical history. Eligible patients were men, 
18-50 years-old. Exclusion criteria included past medical history of 
epididymoorchitis, prostatitis, genital trauma, testicular torsion, ur-
inary tract infection, presence of other genital endocrine or andrologic 
diseases. None of the subjects had been treated medically or surgically 
in the 3 months prior to the study. In order to investigate the possible 
correlation to oxidative stress and semen oxysterols profile we included 
a group of patients with varicocele given the demonstrated relationship 
between varicocele and oxidative stress [15,16]. Varicocele was diag-
nosed by scrotal color-doppler ultrasound during rest and Valsalva 
maneuver. According to physical examination, the varicocele was 
graded as grade ≥II. Semen examination was performed in all patients. 
The study procedure was developed according to the guidelines of 
the referring Ethic Committee, which approved the protocol, and the 
Helsinki Declaration of 1975. The study was registered at clinical-
trials.gov with identifier # NCT02062229. </p>

<p>2.2. Semen analysis </p>

<p>Semen samples were collected by masturbation after 3-5 days of 
sexual abstinence and analyzed after liquefaction for 60 min at 37 °C. 
Semen analysis was assessed by light microscope according to World 
Health Organization guidelines (WHO, 2010). Informed consent to the 
processing of data was obtained from all patients included in the study. 
The following variables were taken into consideration: ejaculate 
volume (mL), total sperm number (x 10 6 /ejaculate), progressive 
motility (%), and morphology (% abnormal forms). Nine semen 
samples containing &gt; 1×10 6 leukocytes/mL were excluded because 
leukocytes are recognized as another major source of ROS in semen 
[17]. Moreover we excluded from our study seven azoospermic 
samples. Therefore we investigated 134 semen samples from the same 
number of patients, aged 34.5 ± 7.5. Patients were classified according 
to the sperm parameters: Group 1≥50th percentile (33 normozoos-
permic men), Group 2≤5th percentile (32 oligoasthenoteratozoosper-
mic men), Group 3 only progressive motility ≤5th percentile (25 
asthenozoospermic men) and Group 4 (44 patients with varicocele). 
An aliquot of semen were stored at −80 °C until GC-MS analysis. </p>

<p>2.3. GC-MS analysis </p>

<p>Oxysterols were determined by GC-MS using deuterium-labeled 
internal standards as described by Dzeletovic et al. and Iuliano et al. 
[18,19]. In brief, for the oxysterols analysis was used 1 mL of semen 
and were added 10 µL BHT in ethanol (5 mg/mL), 50 µL EDTA 
(10 mg/mL) and 10 µL of ethanol containing deuterium labeled 
internal standards. Alkaline hydrolysis was performed on the samples </p>

<p>for 2 h at room temperature with stirring. Then sterols were extracted 
in chloroform: methanol (2:1,v/v). Solvent was evaporated under a 
stream of nitrogen, the sample was dissolved in 1 mL of toluene. 
Oxysterols were separated from cholesterol by solid phase extraction 
(silica cartridges 100 mg). The solvent was evaporated under a stream 
of nitrogen and after samples were converted to trimethylsilyl ethers by 
treatment with 130 µL Sylon HTP (hexamethyldisilylazane:trimethyl-
chlorosilane:pyridine, 3:1:9) (Supelco, Bellafonte, PA) at 60 °C for 
30 min. After incubation, the solution was evaporated under a stream 
of nitrogen, and the residue dissolved in n-hexane and transferred to 
an autosampler vial. Analyses were performed on an Agilent 6890N GC 
equipped with a 7683 series automatic liquid sampler, and interfaced 
with an Agilent 5973 Mass Spectrometer (Agilent Technologies; Palo 
Alto, CA). Separation was carried out on a 30 m capillary column (HP-
5MS 30 m 0.25 mm ID, 0.25 µm thickness). Quantification of oxyster-
ols was made by the isotope dilution method. </p>

<p>2.4. Western blot analysis </p>

<p>To demonstrate the presence of Cholesterol-25-hydroxylase 
(Ch25H) in human spermatozoa we used Western blot analysis in 3 
different normozoospermic patients. To separate spermatozoa, we 
performed a density gradient using the whole semen sample. The 
gradient was made up of the following layers/gradients 55%, 80%, and 
100% (SupraSperm, Origio, Denmark). The semen was gently stratified 
on top of the discontinuous gradient and centrifuged for 25 min at 
800g; the seminal plasma was discarded and spermatozoa were 
collected from the lower gradient (100% layer), resuspended in 2 mL 
PBS, and centrifuged at 800g for 10 min. Spermatozoa were lysed with 
Ripa Buffer (Tris HCl pH 8 50 mM, NaCl 130 mM, EDTA 1 mM, Triton 
X-100 1%, SDS 0.1%, Sodium Deoxycholate 0.1%) mixed with protease 
inhibitor cocktail (Clontech, Cat.#635673). Protein concentration were 
determined using Bio-Rad Protein Assay (Bio-Rad Cat.#112792). 
Equal amounts of protein samples (80 μg/well) were separated elec-
trophoretically by a 12% SDS-PAGE and transferred to PVDF mem-
branes (Amersham Hybond-P). The membranes were blocked for 1 h 
in T-TBS with 5% Bovine non-fat dry milk. After membranes were 
incubated with primary antibody against Ch25H (Abcam, Cambridge, 
UK) 1:250, and against α-tubulin (Abcam, Cambridge, UK) 1:50000 as 
control, overnight at 4 °C. Then the blots were incubated with anti-
Mouse HRP antibody (1:10000) and visualized using WesternBright 
ECL Kit (Advasta K-12045-D20). As positive control for Ch25H 
detection we used THP-1 cell line (ATCC TIB-202). </p>

<p>2.5. Immunofluorescence assay </p>

<p>To determine the localization of Ch25H, we performed immuno-
fluorescence assay of three normozoospermic patients. Sperm cells </p>

<p>were recovered from density gradient, as described above, and were 
rinsed with PBS Buffer. Cells (6×10 5 ) were cytospun for 5 min at 100 x 
g onto a glass slide. Cells spot was fixed in PFA 4% for 15 min at RT. 
After the spots were incubated with PBS-NH 4 Cl 50 mM to quench PFA 
autofluorescence and permealized with Triton X100 0.5%. Cells were 
blocked with PBS-gelatin 0.2% for 45 min and incubated with primary 
antibody against Ch25H (1:50) in PBS-gelatin 0.2% o/n at 4 °C in a wet 
chamber. After cells were incubated with anti-mouse 488 Alexafluor 
secondary antibody (1:500) for 45 min at RT in the dark. Nuclei were 
counterstained with DAPI (1:1000) for 5 min. To exclude unspecific 
fluorescence signal, negative control experiments were carried out </p>

<p>using the secondary antibody in the absence of the antibody against 
cholesterol 25-hydroxylase. As positive control for Ch25H detection we 
used THP-1 cell line (ATCC TIB-202), as they are known to express the 
enzyme. The slides were examined under a fluorescence microscope 
(Leica DM4000 B) with 1000X magnification. </p>

<p>C. Zerbinati et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 111-117 </p>



<p>2.6. Viability test </p>

<p>To test the spermatozoa tolerance to the 25-HC a sperm vitality test 
was carried out to differentiate cell death by staining with eosin Y 0,5% 
in saline solution. We evaluated at least 200 spermatozoa in 10 semen 
samples. This test was performed on spermatozoa incubated for 0, 60, 
150 min with ethanol (control cells) or 25-HC (treated cells) at 
different concentrations (160-1280 ng/mL). </p>

<p>2.7. Chlortetracycline (CTC) fluorescence test </p>

<p>To evaluate if 25-HC was able to induce changes in sperm 
intracellular Ca 2+ concentration we used four normozoospermic semi-
nal samples. Sperm cells were recovered from swim-up separation 
technique performed as follows: 3 mL of each seminal sample was 
divided in three Falcon tube and centrifuged for 10 min at 300×g. The 
supernatant was discarded and on the top of the pellet were layered 
three different conditions: 0.3 mL of capacitating medium (Sperm 
Preparation Medium (SPM), Origio-Denmark), as positive control, 
0.3 mL of only patient's seminal plasma (negative control) or 0.3 mL 
of seminal plasma plus 25-HC (320 ng/mL final concentration). 
Autologous seminal plasma was used as negative control in spermato-
zoa migration studies instead of media containing bicarbonate, which 
may favor Ca 2+ and membrane cholesterol redistribution. Seminal 
plasma for migration studies was obtained by centrifugation at 
18,000×g. Spermatozoa were allowed to migrate for 30 min at 37 °C 
and supernatants were gently aspirated and processed for CTC assay 
according to Fraser et al. [20]. CTC fluorescence measurements were 
carried out on a Leica DM4000 B microscope, 400-440 nm excitation 
and 470 nm emission wavelengths, by counting a minimum of 200 
spermatozoa per slide. </p>

<p>2.8. Filipin fluorescence staining </p>

<p>To evaluate if 25-HC was able to induce cholesterol efflux from the 
sperm plasma membrane for acrosome reaction we used two normo-
zoospermic seminal samples. Sperm cells were recovered and treated 
as described for CTC test. Distribution of cholesterol in plasma 
membrane was determined using filipin, a fluorescent polyene macro-
lide antibiotic that binds specifically to cholesterol [5]. The method 
used to prepare spermatozoa for Filipin assay was a modification of the 
one described by Shadan [21]. Briefly, samples were transferred to 1.5-
mL Eppendorf tubes and were centrifuged at 5000g for 4 min at RT. 
The supernatant was removed, 500 µL of PBS were added to each tube, 
and the pellet was carefully resuspended. A stock solution of 1 mg/mL 
of filipin was prepared in 100% ethanol; 5 µL of this solution were 
added to 200 µL of the sperm solution yielding a final concentration of 
25 µg/mL of filipin and 2.5% ethanol. The samples were incubated in 
the dark at RT for 60 min, washed twice by centrifugation (5000g for 
4 min at RT) in 500 µL of PBS, and the pellet was resuspended in 40 µL 
of PBS. The slides were examined under a fluorescence microscope 
(excitation 365 nm, emission 420 nm) (Leica DM4000 B), and a 
minimum of 200 spermatozoa per slide was scored. </p>

<p>2.9. Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Immunohistochemical detection of Ch25H expression was achieved 
with standard streptavidin-biotin-peroxidise on histological sections 
of testicular tissue. Histological sections used for this test were in 
excess from diagnostic testicular biopsy from patient with suspect 
testicular cancer. 
Histological sections were deparaffinized and rehydrated in graded 
ethanol. Endogenous peroxidase activity was blocked by 3% hydrogen 
peroxide for 10 min. Antigen retrieval was performed in 10 mM 
sodium citrate buffer (pH 6.0) for 15 min. The histological sections 
were incubated with blocking serum (Dako, Cytomation Block serum-</p>

<p>Free) at room temperature for 5 min, and then with rabbit IgG 
polyclonal antibody anti-Ch25H (clone LS-B9764) 1:50, at room 
temperature for 1 h. After incubation, specimens were washed with 
PBS-Tween buffer and incubated with the secondary biotinylated 
antibody and subsequently with the streptavidin-biotin-peroxidase 
(DAKO LSAB Kit peroxidase; DAKO, CA, USA). The samples were 
then washed with PBS-Tween buffer and incubated with freshly 
prepared DAB plus substrate-chromogenic buffer at room tempera-
ture. After gently rinsing with distilled water, slides were counter-
stained with haematoxylin and mounted with permanent mounting 
media. Negative controls were carried out by omitting the incubation 
with primary antibody against Ch25H. Both positive and negative 
controls were used in each experiment. </p>

<p>2.10. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>A descriptive analysis was conducted to show the characteristics of 
the 134 subjects. Data were summarized as mean and standard 
deviation, median and interquartile range, or frequencies and percen-
tages as appropriate. Comparisons among groups on the crude values 
of oxysterols were made using one-way ANOVA. Tukey's multiple 
comparison post-hoc test was then used to determine significant 
differences between the groups. All statistical analyses were conducted 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 21</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>). </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Semen analysis </p>

<p>Table 1 summarizes the demographics, clinical features and sperm 
characteristics of 134 subjects enrolled in the study. The four groups 
did not differ in term of ejaculate volume. As expected from the 
enrolling procedure, semen parameters were significantly different 
between the four groups. </p>

<p>3.2. Oxysterols identification and quantification in human semen </p>

<p>Complete oxysterol profile was obtained in 134 human semen of 
normozoospermic, oligoasthenoteratozoospermic, asthenozoospermic 
and varicocele patients. Oxysterols analyzed included seven autoxida-
tion-and five enzymatically-generated oxysterols (Fig. 1). We found 
nine ring oxysterols, including 7α-hydroxycholesterol (7α-HC), 7β-
hydroxycholesterol (7β-HC), 7-Ketocholesterol (7KC), 4β-hydroxycho-
lesterol (4β-HC), 4α-hydroxycholesterol (4α-HC), 5α,6α-epoxycholes-
terol (5α,6α-EC), 5β,6β-epoxycholesterol (5β,6β-EC), cholestane-
3β,5α,6β-triol (Triol), 5α-OH-6oxocholesterol (6-OCDO). We also 
found 2 side-chain oxygenated oxysterols: 25-hydroxycholesterol (25-
HC) and 27-hydroxycholesterol (27-HC) (Table 2); 24-hydroxycholes-
terol was below the detection limit (Table 2). 
25-HC resulted the most abundant oxysterol in normozoospermic 
subjects, and turned out to be the only one that differed significantly (p 
&lt; 0.0001) among the 4 groups. It was higher in normozoospermic 
group (21.63 ± 18.47 ng/mL, mean ± SD) than oligoasthenoteratozoos-
permic (2.59 ± 2.93, ng/mL, mean ± SD), asthenozoospermic (5.59 ± 
3.17) and varicocele (13.48 ± 11.81, ng/mL, mean ± SD) group 
(Table 2). Furthermore, 25-HC positively correlated with the sperma-
tozoa number (r=0.72, p &lt; 0.0001) (Fig. 2). </p>

<p>3.3. Identification and localization of cholesterol 25 hydroxylase </p>

<p>25-HC is produced by cholesterol 25-hydroxylase (Ch25H), an 
enzyme that utilize di-iron cofactors to catalyze the hydroxylation of 
hydrophobic substrates such as cholesterol [22]. 
By using Western blot analysis, we revealed the presence of 
cholesterol 25-hydroxylase in human spermatozoa (Fig. 3A). 
Immunofluorescence showed that the enzyme is detected in human </p>

<p>C. Zerbinati et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 111-117 </p>



<p>Table 1 
Demographic and semen characteristics of the study population. </p>

<p>group 1 (n=33) 
group 2 (n=32) group 3 (n=25) 
group 4 (n=44) 
p value (*) 1 vs. 2 
1 vs. 3 
1 vs. 4 
2 vs. 3 
2 vs. 4 
3 vs. 4 </p>

<p>Age 
35.9 ( ± 6.9) 
35.8( ± 7.4) 
37.1 ( ± 7.4) 
30.9 ( ± 7.0) 
&lt; 0.01 
n.s 
n.s. 
0.003 
n.s 
0.004 
0.001 
BMI 
24.8 (22.3-27.0) 26.4 (23.7-
30.1) </p>

<p>26.5 (25.7-27.7) 24.5 (22.8-26.8) 0.04 
n.s 
0.04 
n.s 
n.s 
0.03 
0.02 </p>

<p>Smoking habit 
never 
24 (72.7) 
24 (75.0) 
24 (72.0) 
27 (61.4) 
n.s. 
former 
5 (15.2) 
8 (25.0) 
5 (28.0) 
16 (36.4) 
current 
4 (12.1) 
0 (0.0) 
4 (0.0) 
1 (2.3) 
Ejaculate volume 
(mL) </p>

<p>4.0 (3.0-5.0) 
4.0 (3.0-5.0) 
4.0 (3.0-4.0) 
4.0 (3.0-4.3) 
n.s </p>

<p>Sperm/ejaculate (x 
10 6 ) </p>

<p>325 (265-482) 
12 (2-29) 
90 (60-140) 
124 (65-219) 
&lt; 0.0001 
&lt; 0.0001 &lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 &lt; 0.001 
n.s </p>

<p>Progressive motility 
(%) </p>

<p>55.0 (50-55) 
15.0 (1-25) 
30.0 (27-35) 
42.5 (35-45) 
&lt; 0.0001 
&lt; 0.0001 &lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.0001 &lt; 0.001 &lt; 0.0001 &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>A typical forms (%) 75 (72-78) 
90 (85-100) 
80 (78-86) 
78 (76-83) 
&lt; 0.0001 
&lt; 0.0001 &lt; 0.0001 n.s 
&lt; 0.001 &lt; 0.0001 n.s </p>

<p>Values are expressed as mean ( ± SD), median (interquartile range) or frequencies (percentage). 
(*) Continuous variables among the different groups were compared with analysis of variance or Kruskal-Wallis test; categorical variables were compared with the use of chi-square </p>

<p>test or Fisher exact test. Group 1, normozoospermic; group 2, oligoasthenoteratozoospermic; group 3, asthenozoospermic; group 4, varicocele. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Molecular structure of oxysterols analyzed in the study. Red arrows depicts autoxidation-generated oxysterols, blue arrows indicates oxysterols generated by enzymatic 
conversion of cholesterol. Enzymes involved are of the cytochrome family but cholesterol 25-hydroxylase. </p>

<p>Table 2 
Oxysterols concentration in human semen of study population. </p>

<p>Oxysterols (ng/mL) 
group 1 
group 2 
group 3 
group 4 
p value </p>

<p>7α-hydroxycholesterol 
ng/mL 
3.34 ± 1.72 
2.92 ± 1.47 
2.81 ± 0.89 
3.06 ± 1.31 
n.s 
7β-hydroxycholesterol 
ng/mL 
11.73 ± 8.20 
9.89 ± 7.83 
10.41 ± 5.22 
10.65 ± 7.93 
n.s 
5β,6β-epoxycholesterol 
ng/mL 
9.39 ± 3.12 
9.60 ± 3.13 
9.42 ± 3.13 
9.89 ± 6.14 
n.s 
4β-hydroxycholesterol 
ng/mL 
7.96 ± 2.92 
7.80 ± 4.99 
7.29 ± 4.16 
8.55 ± 4.52 
n.s 
4α-hydroxycholesterol 
ng/mL 
14.41 ± 6.78 
14.89 ± 12.57 
11.24 ± 7.70 
13.51 ± 8.40 
n.s 
5α,6α-epoxycholesterol 
ng/mL 
5.96 ± 2.94 
5.41 ± 1.45 
5.08 ± 1.19 
5.48 ± 2.94 
n.s 
Triol 
ng/mL 
1.70 ± 0.67 
1.59 ± 0.50 
1.63 ± 0.43 
1.63 ± 0.49 
n.s 
7-ketocholsterol 
ng/mL 
7.08 ± 5.06 
6.30 ± 2.76 
6.29 ± 2.06 
6.67 ± 2.87 
n.s 
27-hydroxycholesterol 
ng/mL 
2.17 ± 0.93 
1.66 ± 0.84 
1.52 ± 0.46 
2.04 ± 1.18 
n.s 
5α-hydroxy,6-oxocholesterol 
ng/mL 
4.01 ± 3.13 
2.59 ± 1.96 
3.04 ± 2.93 
3.80 ± 3.68 
n.s 
25-hydroxycholesterol 
ng/mL 
21.63 ± 18.47 
2.59 ± 2.93 
5.59 ± 3.17 
13.48 ± 11.81 
&lt; 0.0001 (*) 
24-hydroxycholesterol 
ng/mL 
n.d. 
n.d. 
n.d. 
n.d. 
-</p>

<p>Group 1, normozoospermic; group 2, oligoasthenoteratozoospermic; group 3, asthenozoospermic; group 4, varicocele. 
Values are expressed as mean ( ± SD), statistical difference assessed by Kruskal-Wallis test. n.d., not detectable; 
(*) post-hoc test for 25-hydroxycholesterol: 1 vs. 2, p &lt; 0.0001; 1vs. 3, p &lt; 0.0001; 1 vs. 4, p=0.018; 2 vs. 3, p n.s.; 2 vs. 4, p &lt; 0.0001; 3 vs. 4, p p=0.026. </p>

<p>C. Zerbinati et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 111-117 </p>



<p>spermatozoa and localizes preferentially at the level of neck and post 
acrosomal area (Fig. 3C 3 ). The Fig. 3B 2 showed that the enzyme is 
detected in THP-1 cells, used as positive control; THP-1 cells and 
spermatozoa stained with DAPI were showed in Fig. 3B 1 , 3B 3 and 3C 1 . 
In Fig. 3B 4 and C 2 , the negative control of THP-1 and spermatozoa did 
not show any unspecific fluorescence signal. Streptavidin-biotin-
peroxidase staining on histological sections showed that Cholesterol 
25-hydroxylase was expressed in seminiferous tubules of human 
testicular tissue (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>3.4. 25-HC and spermatozoa function </p>

<p>Viability test showed 66% viable sperm cells in non treated samples 
under prolonged incubation time (150 min), 64% in samples treated 
with 320 ng/mL 25-HC and 67% in samples treated with 640 ng/mL 
25-HC under the same incubation time. A significant decrease in living 
cell number (55%) was observed with 1280 ng/mL 25-HC, under 
prolonged incubation time ( &gt; 150 min). 
Therefore viability tests showed that 25-HC was well tolerated by 
spermatozoa; no significant toxic effect was observed after incubating 
spermatozoa with 25-HC up to 320 ng/mL for 150 min (results not 
shown). 
To explore the potential role of 25-HC on sperm function, we 
investigated calcium content using chlortetracycline (CTC) fluores-
cence analysis [20]. CTC fluorescence depicts two main patterns, i.e. 
uniform fluorescence in the head reflecting uniform calcium ions 
distribution in spermatozoa head, which is characteristic of non-
capacitated cells; and low or absent fluorescent signal throughout the 
sperm head reflecting calcium ions depletion in spermatozoa head, 
which is characteristic of capacitated cells. CTC fluorescence was 
evaluated in purified spermatozoa re-suspended in the capacitating 
medium (Sperm Preparation Medium, positive control) or in non-
capacitating medium (autologous seminal plasma, negative control). 
In normozoospermic samples treated with capacitating medium, 
77% spermatozoa showed loss of fluorescence signal in the head 
compared to 30% cells treated with autologous seminal plasma. 
Spermatozoa treated with seminal plasma in the presence of 25-HC 
resulted in loss of fluorescence signal in the head, which was in a 
comparable amount (72%) as observed with capacitating medium 
(Fig. 5A). 
Identical conditions were used to evaluate cholesterol efflux, which 
is considered a key event associated with capacitation, by filipin 
fluorescence assay. Depending on the functional status, filipin returns </p>

<p>two staining patterns, i.e. uniform fluorescence in the head, reflecting 
uniform cholesterol distribution in the spermatozoa head, character-</p>

<p>istic of uncapacitated cells; and low or absent fluorescent signal 
throughout the sperm head, reflecting cholesterol depletion character-
istic of capacitated cells. 
In normozoospermic samples treated with capacitating medium, 
74% spermatozoa showed loss of fluorescence signal in the head, 
compared to 33% cells treated with autologous seminal plasma. </p>

<p>0 
50 
100 
150 
200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>sperm/mL (10 6 ) 
25-hydroxycholesterol (ng(mL) </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Correlation between 25-hydroxycholesterol and sperm number. 25-
hydroxycholesterol significantly correlates with total sperm number (Pearson, r=0.72; p 
&lt; 0.0001). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Localization of cholesterol 25-hydroxylase in human spermatozoa. 
Cholesterol 25-hydroxylase detected by western blot analysis (A) and immunofluores-
cence (B, C). THP-1 cells (B1-B3) were used as positive control as they are known to 
express the enzyme. Staining with DAPI (B 1 , B 3 ), with antibody against cholesterol 25-
hydroxylase (B 2 ), and in the presence of the secondary antibody without antibody 
against cholesterol 25-hydroxylase (negative control, B 4 ) (400x magnification). 
Spermatozoa stained with DAPI (C 1 ) and with secondary antibody without antibody 
against cholesterol 25-hydroxylase (negative control, C 2 ). Bright fluorescence at neck and 
post acrosomal area of spermatozoa showing localization of cholesterol 25-hydroxylase 
(C 3 ) (1000x magnification).. </p>

<p>C. Zerbinati et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 111-117 </p>



<p>Spermatozoa treated with seminal plasma in the presence of 25-HC 
resulted in loss of fluorescence signal in the head in a comparable 
amount (74%) as observed with capacitating medium (Fig. 5B). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>The main goal in this study was to explore the different species of 
oxysterols in human semen. We also evaluated the variations of 
concentration of identified oxysterols in semen samples from patients 
with different sperm parameters (normozoospermic, oligoasthenoter-
atozoospermic and asthenozoospermic), and in patients with varico-
cele. 
For the first time, 11 out of 12 oxysterols were identified and 
quantitated in human semen. 24-hydroxycholesterol was not detected, 
i.e. was below the detection limit of our method. We found a positive 
correlation between 25-HC concentration and spermatozoa number. 
Even if 25-HC can be potentially formed by autoxidation mechanisms 
[23,24], it's produced almost entirely by the enzyme Cholesterol 25-
hydroxylase [22]. We showed that Cholesterol 25-hydroxylase protein 
is widely expressed in the seminiferous area of the testis, and perdured 
in matured spermatozoa, where the enzyme is located in the neck and 
the post acrosomal area. In addition, we provided evidence for a </p>

<p>functional role of 25-HC in sperm male fertility. In fact, this oxysterol 
was able to induce calcium and cholesterol trafficking compatible with 
a capacitating activity. The most fully characterized biochemical event 
during capacitation is the modification of intracellular concentration of 
calcium ions (Ca ++ ). Increase in Ca ++ transients during capacitation 
has been reported in several mammalian species, including human 
[25]. The process of spermatogenesis is characterized by morphological 
transformation, which occurs in the testis where round germ cells 
undergo division, meiosis and differentiation to form haploid, elon-
gated spermatids. During spermatogenesis, dynamic changes occur in 
membrane lipid composition, including a significant accumulation of 
cholesterol and its precursors as a result of stage-specific expression of 
cholesterol synthesis genes [26]. The functional role of sterols in sperm 
maturation is supported by changes in sterol composition in sperma-
tozoa membranes during epididymal transit [1], which is also con-
trolled by epididymal epithelium that possesses the ability to synthesize 
and extrude cholesterol [2,27]. Therefore, the role of cholesterol and 
related sterols in sperm maturation and male fertility has since long 
been recognized but the mechanism/s involved remains elusive. In 
particular, little is known about oxysterols, compounds derived from 
cholesterol transformation by enzymatic and autoxidation mechan-
isms. To date, these molecules have been identified only in animal </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Immunohistochemical detection of cholesterol 25-hydroxylase in human testis. Human testicular tissue sections were treated with antibody against cholesterol 25-
hydroxylase, showing expression of the enzyme in the seminiferous tubules. A, negative control; B, positive control (400x magnification). </p>

<p>S P 
S P M </p>

<p>S P + 2 5 -H </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>CTC fluorescence (%) </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>n.s. </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>S P 
S P M </p>

<p>S P + 2 5 -H </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Cholesterol depletion (%) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>n.s. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Calcium and cholesterol depletion from spermatozoa head induced by 25-hydroxycholesterol. Chlortetracycline (CTC) assay was used to measure Ca ++ transients 
(panel A), and filipin assay was used to measure cholesterol depletion (panel B) in spermatozoa challenged with a capacitating medium (SPM), non-capacitating medium (autologous 
seminal plasma, SP), and non-capacitating medium plus 320 ng/mL (f.c.) of 25-hydroxycholesterol (SP+25-HC).(*) p &lt; 0.003); (**) p &lt; 0.0001. </p>

<p>C. Zerbinati et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 111-117 </p>



<p>models [2]. 
Spermatozoa complete their fertilizing capacity in the female 
reproductive tract by capacitation. During this process some of the 
major changes involve sterol oxidation and their efflux from the plasma 
membrane, changes in the surface expression of a variety of proteins 
and receptors for the zona pellucida, the induction of tyrosine 
phosphorylation, and the expression of hyper activated motility [28]. 
One of the first changes in spermatozoa capacitation process is a loss of 
cholesterol and related sterols from the sperm plasma membrane [29]. 
Cholesterol is a powerful de-capacitation factor according to the 
notion that it is removed from the sperm surface by acceptor molecules 
such as albumin. In some cellular models the presence of 25-HC 
changes the position, orientation, and solvent accessibility of choles-
terol, shifting it into the water interface and thus increasing its 
availability to external acceptors [30]. Moreover, some studies demon-
strated that 25-HC is able to affect calcium levels in endothelial cells 
[31]. 
Considering these findings, we investigated if 25-HC was able to 
induce calcium and cholesterol depletion in the acrosome region. We 
showed that 25-HC was able to induce both these processes and thus 
behaving as a capacitating factor. The complex mechanisms governing 
the process needed to make sperm functional for egg fertilization are 
still unclear. The finding that 25-HC affects calcium and cholesterol 
trafficking is very suggestive of a role of 25-HC in the context of 
acrosomal reaction and sperm function. 
Reduced levels of 25-HC -and, eventually, its related enzyme 
cholesterol 25-hydroxylase -could potentially negatively affect calcium 
and cholesterol movements into the acrosome region, resulting into 
ineffective acrosome reaction with the egg cell. 
Given the poor knowledge of mechanisms governing the first stages 
of fusion of the two gametes, future studies are demanded to 
investigate the role of 25-HC in male infertility and its potential as 
therapeutic target. 
In conclusion, to the best of our knowledge, this is the first study 
providing evidence for the feasibility of detection and quantitation of 
oxysterols in human semen samples. 
We found in spermatozoa the presence of cholesterol 25-hydro-
xylase and its preferential accumulation in the neck and the post 
acrosomal area. 25-HC was able to induce calcium ions and cholesterol 
depletion in the acrosomal region, in a extent comparable to that of a 
capacitating medium. These finding offers the opportunity to identify a 
new molecular player involved in pre-fertilization processes. </p>

<p>Competing interests </p>

<p>The authors declare that there are no competing interests to 
disclose. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The study supported in part by a grant from Sapienza University of 
Rome, Italy (Grant Ateneo 2015#C26A15M78W to LI). </p>



<p>C. Zerbinati et al. 
Redox Biology 11 (2017) 111-117 </p>



</text></tei>