<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5453893" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Patient-controlled analgesia (PCA) is used to manage postoperative pain. Postoperatively, some patients 
need to be re-instructed on its correct use. This study explores the efficacy of re-instruction and illustrates a comprehen-
sive version of the Silverman integrated approach (C-SIA), based on the integration of static and dynamic pain scores, 
morphine consumption, and the ratio between demanded and delivered PCA boluses (the DD ratio). 
Methods: In total, 50 patients operated on for colorectal surgery were studied retrospectively. The change in DD ratio 
after re-instruction was analyzed as the primary endpoint. Re-instructed and not re-instructed subjects were compared 
according to DD ratio, pain scores, and morphine consumption. A secondary comparison was performed using the SIA 
and C-SIA scores, to illustrate the reliability of the latter tool. Agreement between C-SIA and SIA score was assessed us-
ing a Bland-Altman analysis. 
Results: In re-instructed patients, the DD ratio decreased after re-education (P = 0.011). Re-instructed patients had 
higher DD ratios (P = 0.018) and pain scores at rest (P = 0.024) and movement (P = 0.012) at 24 h after surgery than not 
re-instructed subjects. These differences disappeared at the 48 h visit. Both the SIA and C-SIA scores reflected these find-
ings. C-SIA scores showed a higher coefficient of correlation with the DD ratio (r = 0.815; P &lt; 0.001) than SIA scores (r 
= 0.663; P &lt; 0.001). The C-SIA scores, in absolute values, being based on more variables, were, on average, 2.5 times the 
SIA score. 
Conclusions: Re-instruction is effective for optimizing PCA therapy. The C-SIA is an alternative to the SIA score that 
gives an overall measure of PCA therapy efficacy. </p>

<p>Patient-controlled analgesia (PCA) is the best technique for 
the management of acute postoperative pain when intravenous 
(iv) opioid administration is used [1,2]. Appropriate use of PCA 
devices is crucial to ensure adequate pain relief. However, some 
patients do not use these devices correctly, reducing their ef-
ficacy. Pain therapy and appropriate PCA usage are difficult to 
assess objectively. 
Studies evaluating PCA therapy usually assess distinct vari-
ables including pain scores through subjective scales and opioid 
consumption [3,4]. Analgesic demand is an indirect measure of 
pain. However, side and secondary effects limit analgesic con-
sumption measurements, despite their clinical relevance [5]. 
The ratio between demanded and delivered PCA boluses in 
24 h (the so-called demand/delivery ratio or DD ratio) [6] is a 
simple, objective method of analgesic assessment. It can be use-
ful for evaluating the 'correct' use of a PCA device, but it is rarely 
considered in the literature. 
The Silverman integrated approach (SIA) is a sensitive meth-
od for the assessment of overall pain relief and morphine con-
sumption [7]. This approach provides a combined rank-based 
analysis of pain score and opioid consumption and may be help-
ful for evaluating correct PCA device use. In addition, the SIA 
score can be upgraded to include other variables. 
In this study, we retrospectively investigated the effects of re-
instruction on proper PCA device usage on the first postopera-
tive day visit after colorectal surgery. The analyses were based on 
single-variable (DD ratio, pain scores, morphine consumption) 
comparisons between the 24 and 48 h visits in patients need-
ing re instruction. We also compared the data for re-instructed 
patients with a control group of not re-instructed patients. Ad-
ditionally, we tested the new comprehensive-SIA score (C-SIA 
score) based on the integration of subjective measures (at rest 
and movement pain scores) and objective ones (morphine daily 
consumption and DD ratio). For this, original SIA and C-SIA 
score comparisons were performed between groups. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Data concerning patients undergoing morphine PCA therapy 
after open colorectal surgery were analyzed from a previous 
retrospective study, based on a sample of patients collected 
between May 2008 and December 2011 [8]. A separate Institu-
tional Review Board authorization was obtained for the current 
study. 
All patients who underwent open colorectal surgery be-
tween September 2011 and December 2011 at the Fondazione 
IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori of Milan were reviewed. 
We selected the last 4 months of the primary study [8] to enroll </p>

<p>patients treated as homogeneously as possible. In fact, during 
that period, the acute pain service was made up of dedicated 
staff nurse and senior residents. Only complete data for opioid-
naïve adult patients treated with morphine iv PCA for at least 
2 days were collected. Patients treated with methadone PCA or 
epidural analgesia or transferred to the intensive care unit post-
operatively were not included. The DD ratio, pain scores at rest 
and movement (verbal numerical scale, VNS, an 11-point scale 
from 0 = no pain to 10 = insufferable pain), and morphine daily 
consumption at 24 and 48 h after surgery were reviewed. Data 
were retrieved from the electronic acute pain service database 
and collected in a Microsoft Excel spreadsheet. Patients were 
grouped according to whether they needed re-instruction on the 
correct use of the PCA pump device at the 24 h visit. Physicians 
in the acute pain service provided re-instruction according to 
their own clinical evaluation of subjects at the first postopera-
tive visit (24 h after surgery). Generally, high pain scores (VNS 
at rest &gt; 3 and movement &gt; 6), low morphine consumption 
(&lt; 20-30 mg during the first 24 h after surgery) [1,7,9], and DD 
ratios &gt; 1 indicated patients needing re-instruction. 
PCA pumps were programmed as previously suggested [10-12]: 
a demand morphine dose of 1 mg, a lock-out interval of 6 min, 
no hourly bolus limit, and no continuous basal infusion. Patients 
who received different PCA treatment protocols were excluded 
from the analysis. In addition to PCA treatment, all patients re-
ceived ketorolac 30 mg iv 30 min before skin closure and every 8 
h after intervention. No loco-regional anesthetic technique was 
used. 
To assess the re-instruction intervention, the primary end-
point was the DD-ratio change between the 24 h postoperative 
visit and the 48 h visit (after the re-instruction intervention) in 
re-instructed patients. The same comparison was performed 
according to pain scores at rest and movement, and morphine 
consumption, as commonly reported in the literature. Then 
same data were compared between re-instructed and not re-
instructed patients at equal time points. Secondarily, the two 
groups were compared according to the SIA and the C-SIA 
scores to show agreement with the standard analytical approach. 
The C-SIA score was calculated extending the SIA approach of 
Silverman et al. [6], which integrates the pain score and mor-
phine consumption. The C-SIA score was obtained integrating 
VNS at rest and movement, morphine consumption, and the 
DD ratio. The computation of SIA and C-SIA scores was per-
formed as follows. First, patients were ranked and the mean 
rank (MR) was calculated: MR = (N + 1) / 2 (where N is the to-
tal number of subjects). Then pain scores at rest and movement, 
morphine consumption, and DD ratio were ranked from lowest 
to highest. Next, the percentage difference (X* n ) of each variable 
from the mean rank on a per-subject basis (n) was computed as 
follows: </p>

<p> 
Online access in http://ekja.org </p>

<p>KOReAN J ANeSTHeSIOL </p>

<p>Piccioni et al. </p>

<p>X* n(i) = 100% × ([X n(i) /MR] − 1) </p>

<p>where the variable ranks are represented as X n(i) (i stands for 
VNSr for VNS at rest, VNSm for VNS in movement, MC for 
morphine consumption, and DD for DD ratio). Finally, SIA and 
C-SIA scores were calculated as a summed percentage difference 
for each variable, as follows: </p>

<p>SIA = X* n(VNSr) + X* n(MC) 
and 
C-SIA = X* n(VNSr) + X* n(VNSm) + X* n(MC) + X* n(DD) </p>

<p>The Kolmogorov-Smirnov test showed a skewed distribution 
of continuous variables, so, non-parametric tests were used to 
analyze these data. Intra-group variability between 24 and 48 h 
after surgery was analyzed using the Wilcoxon signed-rank test. 
The Mann-Whitney U test was used for inter-group compari-
sons for both single variables and SIA and C-SIA scores. Discrete 
variables were compared to Fischer's exact test. The correlations 
between pain scores, morphine consumption, DD ratio, C-SIA 
score, and SIA score were assessed using Spearman's rank coef-</p>

<p>ficient. To detect multicollinearity between C-SIA score factors, 
step-wise linear regression analyses with multicollinearity tests 
were performed using variance inflation factors (VIF) analysis. 
A VIF &gt; 4 warranted further investigations while a VIF &gt; 10 was 
considered a sign of serious multicollinearity. Finally, a Bland 
Altman analysis and linear regression were used to assess the 
agreement between the C-SIA and SIA scores. 
Data are reported as medians (25th-75th percentiles). A P 
value of &lt; 0.05 was considered to indicate statistical significance 
for paired comparisons. Statistical analyses were performed with 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">ver. 19.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM Corp.</rs>., Armonk, NY, USA) and 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">Prism</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">ver. 5.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>, La Jolla, CA, USA). Two-
tailed post hoc power analyses were performed with <rs id="software-3" type="software">G*Power</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">ver. 3.1</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-3" type="url">http://www.gpower.hhu.de</rs>) [13]. Graphs were drawn 
with <rs type="software">Prism</rs>. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>From September 1 to December 31, 2011, 91 patients un-
derwent elective open colorectal surgery for cancer at the Fon-
dazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori of Milan, Italy. Of </p>

<p>Table 1. Patient Characteristics </p>

<p>Re-instructed patients 
(n = 16) </p>

<p>Not re-instructed patients 
(n = 34) 
P value </p>

<p>Sex (M/F) 
8/8 
14/20 
0.761 
Age (yr) 
61.5 (52.5, 72.7) 
64 (55.0, 72.2) 
0.892 
BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
25.8 (24.0, 29.7) 
24.2 (22.5, 28.0) 
0.240 
Intraoperative iv morphine (mg) 
13.5 (12, 15) 
13 (11.5, 14.0) 
0.447 
Recovery room iv morphine (mg) 
2 (0, 2) 
0 (0.0, 2.3) 
0.363 </p>

<p>Data are expressed as numbers or median (Q1, Q3). BMI: body mass index, iv: intravenous. </p>

<p>Table 2. Pain Scores, Morphine Consumption, Demand-delivery Ratio, and C-SIA Score Data of the Two Study Groups </p>

<p>Re-instructed patients 
Not Re-instructed patients </p>

<p>24 h 
48 h 
24 h 
48 h </p>

<p>DD ratio 
1.25 
1* 
1.1 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>1 
(1.0, 2.7) 
(1, 1) 
(1.0, 1.3) 
(1.0, 1.3) 
VNS at rest 
1 
1.5 
0 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0 
(0.0, 1.7) 
(0, 2) 
(0, 1) 
(0, 3) 
VNS in movement 
5 
5* 
3 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>4 
(4.2, 7.0) 
(4, 6) 
(2, 4) 
(2, 6) 
Morphine consumption (mg) 
28 
5* 
11 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>6.5* 
(11.0, 46.5) 
(1.5, 16.5) 
(6, 19) 
(3.0, 13.3) 
SIA score 
74 
22* 
−24 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>−3 
(−29, +113) 
(−43, +43) 
(−88, +20) 
(−64, +36) 
C-SIA score 
155 
17* 
−69 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>−1* 
(−3, +185) 
(−109, +54) 
(−154, +72) 
(−100, +78) </p>

<p>Data are expressed as median (Q1, Q3) percentile. DD ratio: demand-delivery ratio, VNS: verbal numerical scale, SIA: Silverman integrated approach, 
C-SIA: comprehensive-Silverman integrated approach. *P &lt; 0.05 for intragroup comparison. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 for intergroup comparison. </p>



<p>Online access in http://ekja.org </p>

<p>VOL. 70, NO. 3, JuNe 2017 </p>

<p>C-SIA score for PCA therapy evaluation </p>

<p>these, 41 were excluded from the study because of postoperative 
intensive care unit recovery (5), epidural analgesia treatment 
(15), methadone PCA (10), and incomplete records (11). Thus, 
data from 50 patients (16 re-instructed vs. 34 not re-instructed) 
were extracted from the acute pain service electronic database 
(Table 1). Table 2 summarizes data collected regarding DD ra-
tios, pain scores, morphine consumption, and SIA and C-SIA 
scores. The DD ratio decreased significantly from the 24 h to the 
48 h visit in re-instructed patients (P = 0.011; mean difference 
[95% CI] = −0.9 [−1.571 to −0.245]; Fig. 1). Conversely, it did 
not change in not re-instructed patients (P = 0.427; mean dif-
ference [95% CI] = 0.14 [−0.222 to 0.513]). The DD ratio was 
higher for re-instructed patients than not re-instructed patients 
24 h after intervention (P = 0.018), and equal in both groups 
at 48 h (P = 0.154). Morphine consumption was higher for re-
instructed patients at 24 h (P = 0.011) and equal for both groups 
in the subsequent 24 h (P = 0.511). VNS at rest and movement 
were higher for re-instructed patients 24 h after surgery (P = 0.024 
and P = 0.012, respectively) but not after 48 h (P = 0.173 and P = 
0.185). Both SIA and C-SIA scores decreased significantly after 
re-instruction intervention (P = 0.034 and P = 0.006, respec-
tively). The SIA and C-SIA scores were each significantly differ-
ent between study groups only at 24 h after intervention (Table 
2, Fig. 2). In addition, 25% (4/16) of re-instructed patients and 
61.8% (13/34) of not re-instructed patients had a negative C-SIA 
score (P = 0.032). 
The DD ratio showed a moderate correlation with VNS at 
rest at 24 h (r = 0.485, P &lt; 0.001) and a strong correlation with 
morphine consumption at 24 h (r = 0.583, P &lt; 0.001). At the 48 </p>

<p>h time point, a moderate correlation was observed between DD 
ratio and morphine consumption (r = 0.328, P = 0.020). VNS at 
rest and morphine consumption at 24 h showed a weak correla-
tion (r = 0.292, P = 0.039). A strong correlation was found be-
tween VNS at rest and in movement 48 h after surgery (r = 0.692, 
P &lt; 0.001). 
The C-SIA score showed a higher coefficient of correlation 
with the DD ratio (r = 0.815, P &lt; 0.001) than the SIA score 
(r = 0.663, P &lt; 0.001). A strong correlation was also observed 
between the C-SIA and SIA scores (r = 0.863, P &lt; 0.001). The 
independent factors of the C-SIA score (VNS scores, morphine 
consumption and DD ratio) were not affected by multicollinear-
ity (all VIF values &lt; 2.5). 
The Bland-Altman analysis showed an almost null mean dif-
ference between C-SIA score and SIA-score with a wide agree-
ment range (−170.3, 170.3) and a proportional difference vari-
ability across the range of the average (Fig. 3A). The correlation 
coefficient between the C-SIA and SIA difference and their mean 
was 0.779 (P &lt; 0.001) and the resulting regression equation was 
y = 0.581x (intercept = 0, slope [95% CI] = 0.581 [0.445-0.716]; 
P &lt; 0.001). The Bland-Altman was rearranged, and the ratio be-
tween C-SIA and SIA-score was plotted against their average [14]. 
This gave a constant mean ratio of 2.51 between the two scores 
through their mean (Fig. 3B). 
Finally, post hoc power analyses were performed, adopting a 
two-tailed test and setting the alpha error to 0.05. A group sam-
ple size of 16 achieved 80% power to reject a difference in 0.9 (SD 
= 1.2) among DD-ratio means (the primary outcome) between 
the 24 h and 48 h postoperative visits in re-instructed patients. </p>

<p>5.5 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>4.5 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 
Re-instr. </p>

<p>24 h 
4 8 h </p>

<p>Demand/delivery ratio </p>

<p>Not Re-instr. 
Not Re-instr. 
Re-instr. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Demand/delivery ratio (DD ratio) of re-instructed (gray boxes) 
and not re-instructed (white boxes) patients at 24 and 48 h after surgery. 
The bands in the boxes represent the median value, the bottom and top 
of the boxes indicate the 25th and 75th percentiles, and the ends of the 
whiskers indicate the minimum and maximum of all data. *P = 0.018, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>P = 0.011. </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 
Re-instr. </p>

<p>24 h 
4 8 h </p>

<p>C-SIA score </p>

<p>Not Re-instr. 
Not Re-instr. 
Re-instr. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Fig. 2. C-SIA score of re-instructed (gray boxes) and not re-instructed 
(white boxes) patients at 24 and 48 h after surgery. The bands in the 
boxes represent the median value, the bottom and top of the boxes 
indicate the 25th and 75th percentiles, and the ends of the whiskers 
indicate the minimum and maximum of all data. *P &lt; 0.001. </p>

<p> 
Online access in http://ekja.org </p>

<p>KOReAN J ANeSTHeSIOL </p>

<p>Piccioni et al. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study demonstrated the efficacy of re-instruction inter-
vention 24 h after surgery for patients who did not use the PCA 
device properly. We compared DD ratios in patients needing re-
instruction before and after the re-instruction. As expected, re-
instructed patients showed a decrease in median DD ratio at the 
48 h visit (P = 0.011), suggesting the efficacy of the re-education. 
Furthermore, to better evaluate the intervention, we compared 
re-instructed patients with a not re-instructed sample of pa-
tients, as a control group. Re-instructed patients showed higher 
median DD ratios 24 h after the operation than not re-instruct-
ed patients (P = 0.018) but this difference was not observed 24 
h later (P = 0.154). Similarly, VNS scores at rest and movement 
were higher in re-instructed patients 24 h after surgery. These 
data indicate that re-instructed patients failed to self-administer 
the necessary amount of morphine to achieve adequate pain re-
lief. Furthermore, the median DD ratio of re-instructed patients 
(1.26) was close to 1.35, the cut-off value previously proposed to 
re-instruct patients or adjust PCA therapy plans [7]. 
Differences in VNS scores at rest between groups were sta-
tistically, but not clinically, different. That is, there was no clear 
clinical difference between the groups despite the need for re-
instruction in some patients. Pain scores were not different be-
tween study groups at 48 h after intervention. Thus, a standard 
analytical approach did not seem to completely justify re-edu-
cation. In fact, the postoperative visit was based on VNS scores, 
drug consumption, and DD ratio assessment, but not on the 
verification of a correct understanding of PCA device use. Seek-
ing to increase the overall assessment of patients for descriptive </p>

<p>purposes, we proposed an approach that expands the original 
SIA score, presenting a comprehensive score, named C-SIA. 
The C-SIA score, useful for the evaluation of iv PCA therapies, 
is based on the integration of four main variables: static and 
dynamic pain scores, morphine consumption, and the DD ratio. 
This overall score gives a modern global quantitative summary 
of variables that can be used for the comparisons of different 
treatments in clinical research. 
SIA and C-SIA scores were each significantly higher in re-
instructed patients at 24 h, indicating the worst pain relief, unfa-
vorable morphine consumption, and poor DD ratios. Thus, both 
the SIA and C-SIA scores reflected the sum of differences among 
the single variables. Similarly, the two scores correctly revealed 
overall equality between the study groups at 48 h after surgery. 
As mentioned, the C-SIA score reflected the overall differ-
ences or equalities between the study groups, confirming its 
reliability as a summary score. This score depends strictly on 
the variables, giving an overview of PCA therapy. Being the sum 
of the ranked values of those variables, the C-SIA score directly 
reflects their overall trends. In our study, at 24 h after surgery, all 
variables were significantly different between the two groups. C-
SIA scores were consistently different in similar ways and, more-
over, showed a statistical significance comparable to the original 
SIA score (Table 2) [15]. 
C-SIA score consistency was confirmed by the absence of 
multicollinearity between underlying factors. High VNS scores 
at rest were not linked directly to high VNS in movement or 
high DD ratios. Similarly, morphine consumption did not nec-
essarily correlate with DD ratios. This finding highlights the 
complexity of the efficacy analysis of PCA protocols. </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>Average of C-SIA and SIA score 
C-SIA score -SIA-score difference </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>300 
200 
100 
0 
100 
200 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Average of C-SIA and SIA score 
C-SIA score/SIA score ratio </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>300 
200 
100 
0 
100 
200 
300 </p>

<p>1.96 SD </p>

<p>0.0001 </p>

<p>Mean </p>

<p>+1.96 SD </p>

<p>+1.96 SD </p>

<p>1.96 SD </p>

<p>2.51 </p>

<p>Mean </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Bland-Altman analysis: (A) the difference between C-SIA score and SIA-score is plotted versus the mean of the two measures. Despite an 
almost null bias between variables, the limits of agreement are wide. Furthermore, the difference between the two scores changed through the mean 
increasing values to the extremes. (B) The ratio between C-SIA and SIA score is plotted versus the mean of the two scores. The plot shows a quite 
constant ratio between C-SIA and SIA through the mean. This finding is consistent with the derivation of the two scores: the C-SIA is always higher 
because it is based on the sum of four variables while the SIA is based on two. </p>



<p>Online access in http://ekja.org </p>

<p>VOL. 70, NO. 3, JuNe 2017 </p>

<p>C-SIA score for PCA therapy evaluation </p>

<p>Using a Bland-Altman analysis, first, the difference between 
the C-SIA score and SIA-score was plotted versus the mean of 
the two measures. This revealed an almost null mean differ-
ence between C-SIA score and SIA-score and a wide agreement 
range. After seeing the variability in proportional difference 
across the range of the average difference between the two scores 
highlighted by the classic Bland-Altman analysis, we also plotted 
the ratio between the C-SIA and SIA scores versus the mean of 
the two scores. This analysis revealed a constant ratio between 
the two scores: in particular, the C-SIA score was, on average, 2.5 
times the SIA score. This is consistent with the high correlation 
and linear regression relationship found between the difference 
and the mean of the two scores. These data highlight the exis-
tence of a constant proportional bias between the two scores. 
Indeed, the absolute value of the C-SIA score, being based on 
more variables, always tended to be higher than the SIA score. 
It is important to understand the relationship between 
variables and the derived C-SIA score. The difference between 
ranked variable values and median rank results was negative 
for low original values (i.e., low pain scores, low morphine con-
sumption, low DD ratio) and positive for high ones. As Silver-
man et al. [6] proposed for the SIA score, the enhanced C-SIA 
score is a summary of these clinical variables and can be plotted 
on a graph reporting the overall score and individual data on 
VNS at rest and movement (subjective variables) and data on 
morphine consumption plus DD ratio (objective variables) to 
characterize a sample of patients (Fig. 4). A negative C-SIA score 
indicates patients with lower pain scores and DD ratios that </p>

<p>require less morphine consumption. By contrast, higher pain 
scores, DD ratios, and morphine consumption will give a higher 
C-SIA score. 
If the DD ratio is high, this means that the patient has re-
quested more opioid doses than those permitted or used by 
most patients. This suggests incorrect use of the PCA device or 
an inadequate analgesia protocol (i.e., too low bolus dose or a 
too long lock-out period). The C-SIA score includes such data 
together with pain scores and morphine consumption. Thus, it 
enables an overall evaluation of the pain therapy. A high C-SIA 
value means inadequate pain relief, high morphine consump-
tion, and a high DD ratio. However, while the DD ratio can 
be used at bedside to evaluate pain therapy, the C-SIA is not 
intended as a diagnostic tool but rather as a descriptive variable 
useful for characterizing groups of patients. 
Our work had some limitations. First, this study was retro-
spective. Second, re-instruction was performed according to our 
daily practice, without a specific protocol. However, our criteria 
to identify patients needing re-instruction were well defined 
(i.e., high DD ratio and a high pain score with concurrent low 
morphine consumption) and were applied to all patients in the 
study. Third, the C-SIA score, similar to the SIA score, weights 
pain scores, morphine consumption, and the DD ratio equally. 
Other weighting methods might be more appropriate. 
In conclusion, re-instruction is a primary and effective aim 
to optimize PCA therapy. The proposed C-SIA score is a simple 
and complete instrument to summarize several assessment vari-
ables in PCA therapy. This score correctly distinguishes between 
re-instructed and not re-instructed patients for the correct use 
of the PCA device. The calculation of this score using common 
statistical software is simple and its performance is comparable 
to the SIA score. Research study designs on pain management 
usually focus on a specific end-point, such as pain scores or 
morphine consumption. The C-SIA score allows the setting of a 
global end-point (as a composite outcome), based on both pain 
scores and PCA data. Thus, researchers can enrich their analyses 
and merge subjective (pain scores) and objective (morphine 
consumption and the DD ratio) data in an overall score that can 
substitute for the original SIA score. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank Luigi Mariani of the Unit of Clinical Epi-
demiology and Trial Organization (Fondazione IRCCS Istituto 
Nazionale dei Tumori, Milan, Italy) for valuable help in the data 
analysis. </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>Patients 
% Difference vs. mean overall rank </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>15 16 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Normalized (%) rank difference (vs. median overall rank of 50) 
for summed VNS at rest and in movement (blank circles), for summed 
PCA usage data (morphine consumption and DD ratio, blank squares) 
and their sum, the C-SIA score (black diamonds) of re-instructed 
patients at the first postoperative visit 24 h after surgery. Patients with 
the worst C-SIA scores (i.e., n. 1, 2, 4, and 6) have high pain scores and 
very high PCA usage scores (high morphine and/or DD ratio). In a 
large cohort, these data could be useful to evaluate the PCA protocol 
settings or to analyze such a subgroup of patients. </p>

<p> 
Online access in http://ekja.org </p>

<p>KOReAN J ANeSTHeSIOL </p>

<p>Piccioni et al. </p>



</text></tei>