<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5241585" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>a b s t r a c t </p>

<p>Malaria, schistosomiasis and leishmaniases are among the most prevalent tropical parasitic diseases and 
each requires new innovative treatments. Targeting essential parasite pathways, such as those that 
regulate gene expression and cell cycle progression, is a key strategy for discovering new drug leads. In 
this study, four clinically approved anti-cancer drugs (Vorinostat, Belinostat, Panobinostat and Romi-
depsin) that target histone/lysine deacetylase enzymes were examined for in vitro activity against 
Plasmodium knowlesi, Schistosoma mansoni, Leishmania amazonensis and L. donovani parasites and two for 
in vivo activity in a mouse malaria model. All four compounds were potent inhibitors of P. knowlesi 
malaria parasites (IC 50 9e370 nM), with belinostat, panobinostat and vorinostat having 8e45 fold 
selectivity for the parasite over human neonatal foreskin fibroblast (NFF) or human embryonic kidney 
(HEK 293) cells, while romidepsin was not selective. Each of the HDAC inhibitor drugs caused hyper-
acetylation of P. knowlesi histone H4. None of the drugs was active against Leishmania amastigote or </p>

<p>promastigote parasites (IC 50 &gt; 20 mM) or S. mansoni schistosomula (IC 50 &gt; 10 mM), however romidepsin 
inhibited S. mansoni adult worm parings and egg production (IC 50~1 0 mM). Modest in vivo activity was </p>

<p>observed in P. berghei infected mice dosed orally with vorinostat or panobinostat (25 mg/kg twice daily 
for four days), with a significant reduction in parasitemia observed on days 4e7 and 4e10 after infection 
(P &lt; 0.05), respectively. 
Tropical parasitic diseases cause significant morbidity and 
mortality, infecting hundreds of millions of people globally, 
particularly in developing countries (Lozano et al., 2012; Murray 
et al., 2012). In 2015 alone there were~214 million clinical cases 
of malaria and 438,000 deaths associated with this disease (World 
Health Organization). On an annual basis 1-2 million and~250 
million people are reported to be infected with Leishmania (World 
Health Organization, 2008; Pigott et al., 2014) and Schistosoma </p>

<p>parasites, respectively (Colley et al., 2014). Although drugs for each 
of these parasitic infections are available, prevention and treatment 
is often difficult due to side-effects (Sundar and Chakravarty, 2015) 
or ineffective due to drug-resistant parasites (Croft et al., 2006; 
Dondorp et al., 2009; Dondorp and Ringwald, 2013; Berg et al., 
2015; Takala-Harrison et al., 2015). There is no vaccine that is 
clinically available or widely effective for any of the human parasitic 
diseases. Thus, the discovery of novel drug targets, and new che-
motherapies with novel mechanisms of action, are high priorities. 
Small molecules that act on epigenetic regulatory proteins, such as 
those responsible for post-translational modifications of histones, 
are of increasing interest as chemical tools for dissecting funda-
mental mechanisms of parasite growth and as possible new drug 
leads (Andrews et al., 2012b; Ay et al., 2015; Cheeseman and 
Weitzman, 2015). Clinically approved drugs are also attracting </p>

<p>* Corresponding author. Griffith Institute for Drug Discovery, Don Young Road, 
Building N.75, Griffith University, Nathan, Queensland, Australia 4111. 
E-mail address: k.andrews@griffith.edu.au (K.T. Andrews). 
1 These authors contributed equally. </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>International Journal for Parasitology: 
Drugs and Drug Resistance </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o me p a g e : w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m/ l o ca t e / i j p d d r </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijpddr.2016.12.005 
2211-3207/© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of Australian Society for Parasitology. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>International Journal for Parasitology: Drugs and Drug Resistance 7 (2017) 42e50 </p>

<p>interest for repurposing for new uses since this can shorten time to 
market and reduce costs compared to de novo drug discovery for 
malaria or Neglected Tropical Diseases (NTDs). Alternatively, they 
may be used as new starting points for the rational development of 
parasite targeting compounds (Andrews et al., 2014). 
Histone deacetylases (HDACs) are now known to target both 
histone proteins and many non-histone proteins and thus are 
sometimes described as lysine deacetylases (KDACs). Histone/ 
lysine deacetylases and acetyltransferases, respectively, remove 
and add acetyl groups from histones and other proteins, just as 
corresponding demethylases and methyltransferases remove and 
add methyl groups to lysine sidechains of proteins (Arrowsmith 
et al., 2012). These posttranslational modifications contribute to 
the regulation of numerous essential biological processes in eu-
karyotes including transcriptional regulation (Heintzman et al., 
2009), cell cycle progression (Montenegro et al., 2015) and 
apoptosis (Bose et al., 2014; Zhang and Zhong, 2014). Aberrant 
expression of these proteins is a feature of some human diseases, 
such as cancers, making these epigenetic regulatory enzymes 
"druggable" targets (Arrowsmith et al., 2012; Falkenberg and 
Johnstone, 2014; Brien et al., 2016). Likewise, some epigenetic 
regulatory proteins have been shown to play essential roles in 
proliferation and life cycle stage progression of parasite pathogens 
(Azzi et al., 2009; Coleman et al., 2014), with the proteins having 
low homology to human proteins (Andrews et al., 2012b, 2012c) or 
significant differences in important catalytic domains (Marek et al., 
2013; Melesina et al., 2015) that make them attractive anti-parasitic 
drug targets. HDAC homologues have been identified in all major 
human parasitic pathogens and different classes of HDAC inhibitors 
have also been shown to have activity against some of these par-
asites, including Plasmodium species that cause malaria and the 
causative agents of selected NTDs including Leishmania and Schis-
tosoma parasites (reviewed in (Andrews et al., 2012b, 2012c; Marek 
et al., 2015)). 
Several HDAC inhibitors have been clinically approved for hu-
man use for different cancers and these drugs are potential leads for 
application to parasitic diseases. Vorinostat (SAHA; Sigma Aldrich, 
USA), Romidepsin (FK228; Istodax; Selleck Chemicals, USA), and 
Belinostat (PXD101; Beleodaq; Spectrum Pharmaceuticals, Inc., 
USA) are approved for cutaneous or peripheral T-cell lymphoma 
(Grant et al., 2007; Prince and Dickinson, 2012; Thompson, 2014), 
while Panobinostat (LBH-589; Selleck Chemicals, USA) is approved 
for combination therapy of multiple myeloma (Garnock-Jones, 
2015). In this study, we assessed the capacity of all four drugs to 
inhibit the growth of parasites that cause malaria (P. knowlesi), 
leishmaniasis (L. amazonensis and L. donovani) and schistosomiasis 
(S. mansoni). We also investigated the in vivo antimalarial potential 
of orally administered vorinostat and panobinostat in a murine 
model of malaria. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Compounds </p>

<p>Vorinostat (SAHA) and chloroquine diphosphate salt were pur-
chased from Sigma-Aldrich (USA). Romidepsin (FK228), Belinostat 
(PXD101), and Panobinostat (LBH589) were purchased from Selleck 
Chemicals. All HDAC inhibitors were prepared as 10e20 mM stock 
solutions in 100% DMSO. Chloroquine was prepared as a 10e20 mM 
stock in phosphate buffered saline (PBS). </p>

<p>2.2. Plasmodium in vitro growth inhibition assays </p>

<p>P. knowlesi A1H.1 (Moon et al., 2013) and P. falciparum 3D7 
parasites were cultured in O positive human erythrocytes in RPMI </p>

<p>1640 media (Gibco, USA) supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated </p>

<p>pooled human sera (AB for P. knowlesi) and 5 mg/mL gentamicin, as </p>

<p>previously described (Trager and Jensen, 1976; Moon et al., 2013). </p>

<p>P. knowlesi culture media also included 50 mg/mL hypoxanthine and </p>

<p>5 g/L Albumax II. In vitro activity of drugs was determined using 
previously described </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>H-hypoxanthine incorporation assays for 
P. knowlesi A1H.1 (Arnold et al., 2016) and P. falciparum (Skinner-
Adams et al., 2007). Briefly asynchronous Plasmodium infected 
erythrocytes (0.25% parasitemia and 2% haematocrit for P. knowlesi; 
1% parasitemia and 1% haematocrit for P. falciparum) were seeded 
into 96-well tissue culture plates, with test compounds or controls, 
in hypoxanthine-free culture media. Chloroquine was used as a 
positive control in all assays. For P. knowlesi, after incubating for </p>

<p>24 h, 0.5 mCi </p>

<p>3 H-hypoxanthine (PerkinElmer </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, USA) was added to 
each well and cells were cultured for a further 24 h and then har-
vested onto 1450 MicroBeta filter mats (Wallac, USA). For </p>

<p>P. falciparum, 0.5 mCi </p>

<p>3 H-hypoxanthine was added at the start of the </p>

<p>assay and after 48 h incubation cells were harvested as above. In 
each case 
3 H-hypoxanthine incorporation was determined using a </p>

<p>1450 MicroBeta liquid scintillation counter (PerkinElmer </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, USA) 
and percentage inhibition of growth determined compared to 
matched 0.5% DMSO vehicle controls included in each assay plate. 
Each independent experiment was carried out in triplicate and 
performed at least three times. 50% inhibitory concentrations 
IC 50 (s) were determined via log linear interpolation (Huber and 
Koella, 1993). </p>

<p>2.3. Leishmania growth inhibition assays </p>

<p>L. donovani parasites (MHOM/SD/62/1S-CL2D) were cultured in 
modified M199 media as previously described (Pescher et al., 2011). 
Lesion-derived amastigotes of L. amazonensis (MPRO/BR/1972/ 
M1841) were used for macrophage infection or differentiated into 
promastigotes in L. donovani promastigote medium (Pescher et al., 
2011). Cell-cycling promastigotes of both Leishmania species were 
taken from the logarithmic growth phase for viability assays. Anti-
leishmanial activity of compounds was evaluated against host cell-
free parasites using a resazurin reduction assay (adapted from 
(Durieu et al., 2016)) and on intramacrophagic L. amazonensis 
amastigotes using a High-Content phenotypic Assay (HCA) (Aulner 
et al., 2013). For the dye reduction assay, compounds were tested in </p>

<p>quadruplicate at 20, 4 and 0.8 mM at 26 C and 37 C for promas-</p>

<p>tigotes and amastigotes, respectively. Briefly, parasites growing in 
logarithmic phase (5 Â 10 
4 /well) were seeded in 384-well plates </p>

<p>containing compound dilutions and controls including DMSO </p>

<p>vehicle and amphotericin B (0.5 mM). Two days later, resazurin was 
added (10 mL per well at 25 mg/mL) and fluorescence intensity was </p>

<p>measured 24 h after resazurin addition using a Tecan Safire 2 reader 
(excitation 558 ± 4.5 nm; emission 585 ± 10 nm). Following 
background subtraction (complete parasite culture medium with 
resazurin without parasites), data were expressed as percentage 
growth of DMSO-treated controls. For HCAs, mouse bone marrow-
derived macrophages were infected with lesion-derived 
L. amazonensis amastigotes. These parasites were genetically 
modified by chromosomal integration of the fluorescent mCherry 
molecule using pLEXSY-cherry-sat2 vector (Jena Bioscience) and 
propagated in Swiss nu/nu mice to keep virulence feature. One day 
after macrophage infection, compounds were added in quadrupli-</p>

<p>cates at 10 or 1 mM final concentration for 3 days. Controls included 
DMSO vehicle, anti-leishmanial amphotericin B (1 mM) and cyto-
toxic cycloheximide (50 mg/mL). Fluorescent reporters were added </p>

<p>for 1 h to stain macrophage nuclei (Hoechst 33342) and para-
sitophorous vacuoles (LysoTracker Green DND26) and images of 
living macrophage cultures were acquired using the automatic 
Opera QEHS confocal reader (Perkin Elmer Technology). Images </p>

<p>M.J. Chua et al. / International Journal for Parasitology: Drugs and Drug Resistance 7 (2017) 42e50 </p>

<p>
were analysed using Acapella™ and both anti-leishmanial activity 
and toxicity to host cells were determined for each compound. </p>

<p>2.4. S. mansoni viability assays </p>

<p>A resazurin-based fluorescence assay was used to determine the 
inhibitory activity of compounds against Newly-Transformed 
S. mansoni Schistosomula (NTS) (Marxer et al., 2012), as previ-
ously described (Heimburg et al., 2016). Negative and positive 
controls, including untreated schistosomula, killed larvae (70% 
ethanol) and schistosomula exposed to praziquantel (PZQ) were 
included in each assay. The stability of adult worm pairs and egg 
laying in culture were measured as previously described 
(Vanderstraete et al., 2013). All assays were performed in triplicate 
on two separate occasions. </p>

<p>2.5. Protein hyperacetylation assays </p>

<p>P. knowlesi protein hyperacetylation assays were carried out as 
previously described for P. falciparum (Sumanadasa et al., 2012; 
Trenholme et al., 2014). Briefly, trophozoite stage infected-
erythrocytes were incubated with test compounds (1Â or 5Â 
IC 50 ), chloroquine negative control, or vehicle control (0.2% DMSO) 
for 3 h under standard culture conditions. Cells were then pelleted, 
lysed with 0.15% saponin and the resulting parasite pellets washed 
with PBS before resuspension in 1Â SDS-PAGE loading dye. 
Following heat denaturation (94 C, 3 min) protein was analysed by 
SDS-PAGE and Western blot using anti-(tetra) acetyl histone H4 
antibody (1:2000 dilution; Millipore; 06e866) and goat anti-
rabbite594 dye secondary antibody (Alexa Fluor </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>). Anti-(tetra) 
acetyl histone H4 antibody is reported by the manufacturer to 
recognize acetylated forms of histone H4 and to cross-react with 
acetylated histone H2B and possibly other acetylated histones. 
Anti-(tetra) acetyl histone H4 antibody has previously been vali-
dated for P. falciparum (e.g (Sumanadasa et al., 2012; Engel et al., 
2015).) (PlasmoDB gene ID PF3D7_1105000 (Aurrecoechea et al., 
2009)) and the P. knowlesi H4 amino acid sequence (PlasmoDB 
gene ID PKNH_0902600 (Aurrecoechea et al., 2009)) is identical. 
Membranes were imaged using an FLA-5000 imaging system 
(FUJIFILM, USA). As an appropriate antibody loading control was 
not available at the time this work was carried out (those normally 
used in this laboratory for P. falciparum did not cross-react with this 
species; data not shown), protein loading was assessed by Coo-
massie blue-staining of samples separated by SDS-PAGE. </p>

<p>2.6. Homology modelling and docking </p>

<p>As there is no reported crystal structure of HDAC(s) from any 
Plasmodium species, a homology model of the PkHDAC1 was built 
using the homology modelling suite in Maestro (Schr€ odinger 
Release, 2016-1). The BLAST search engine within the suite was 
used for template searching before model construction. Human 
HDAC2 (pdb code:3MAX) was chosen as the most suitable template 
due to its high overall sequence identity (62%) and similarity (81%) 
with the PkHDAC1 protein, and its high resolution (2.1 Å) crystal 
structure in complex with a small molecule inhibitor. The energy-
based approach was used to build the final model. The homology 
model created from Maestro was checked for model quality and 
stereochemistry using SwissModel (Kiefer et al., 2009). For ligand 
docking experiments, 2D-structures of vorinostat, panobinostat 
and belinostat were drawn in ChemBioDraw 14.0 and saved as sdf 
files. The 3D coordinates of the ligands were prepared in Maestro 
using the Ligand Preparation suite at physiological pH using the 
OPLS (2005) force field. GOLD (version 5.2.2) was used for ligand 
docking and Chemscore for scoring the relative affinities of ligand </p>

<p>poses. Ligands were docked in the active site defined by a 15 Å 
radius around the OD2 atom of Asp 262. Each ligand was docked 20 
times using scaffold constraint settings to ensure that each 
hydroxamate mimicked the native binding mode of vorinostat 
bound in the crystal structure human HDAC2 (pdb code: 4LXZ) 
during ligand docking simulations. </p>

<p>2.7. In vivo anti-Plasmodium efficacy studies </p>

<p>In vivo anti-Plasmodium activity was examined using groups of 
six female BALB/c mice (6e8 weeks old; Animal Resources Centre, 
Perth, Australia) infected via intra-peritoneal (i.p.) injection with 
10 
5 P. berghei QIMR (Saul et al., 1997) infected erythrocytes taken </p>

<p>from an infected passage mouse. Mice were treated by oral gavage </p>

<p>with 100 mL test compounds (25 mg/kg) or vehicle control (50% </p>

<p>DMSO in PBS) twice daily for four days, beginning 2 h post infection 
(p.i.) and with a 4 h interval between doses (as published for the 
hydroxamate HDAC inhibitor SB939 (Sumanadasa et al., 2012)). 
Chloroquine (10 mg/kg in PBS) was a positive control administered 
via oral gavage twice daily for three days beginning 2 h p.i. Pe-
ripheral parasitemia was monitored daily from day 4 p.i. by 
microscopic examination of Giemsa-stained thin blood smears 
prepared from tail snip bleeds. Mice were euthanized according to 
an approved scorecard of criteria and all animal work was con-
ducted using protocols approved by National Health and Medical 
Research Council (NHMRC) of Australia Animal Code of Practice, as 
approved by the Griffith University Animal Ethics committee. Data 
were analysed using two-tailed Student's t-Test using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Graph Pad 
Prism</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 5</rs>). </p>

<p>3. Results and discussion </p>

<p>Targeting epigenetic regulatory enzymes to combat parasitic 
diseases is of growing interest (Andrews et al., 2012b, 2012c; Marek 
et al., 2015). However, progress on HDAC inhibitors for use in the 
parasite field lags behind cancer research where HDAC(s) have been 
targets for clinically approved drugs since 2007 (Grant et al., 2007). 
New HDAC inhibitors that have been developed for cancer therapy 
are therefore of potential interest in the anti-parasitic drug dis-
covery arena, either from a potential repurposing approach or as 
starting points for discovery of parasite-selective inhibitors. Here 
the comparative anti-parasitic profiles of four HDAC inhibitors 
(Vorinostat, Romidepsin, Belinostat and Panobinostat) were 
assessed in vitro against the zoonotic P. knowlesi malaria parasite 
species, leishmania parasites (L. amazonensis and L. donovani) and 
schistosomal parasites (S. mansoni). Two of the compounds were 
also examined in vivo in a murine model of malaria. 
Until recently, in the malaria field the ability to easily and 
rapidly perform in vitro drug testing on Plasmodium species was 
limited to P. falciparum (Trager and Jensen, 1976). However, the 
adaptation of the zoonotic P. knowlesi species to continuous in vitro 
culture in human erythrocytes (Lim et al., 2013; Moon et al., 2013; 
Gruring et al., 2014) and modification of the standard 
3 H-hypo-</p>

<p>xanthine-uptake assay method for P. knowlesi (Arnold et al., 2016) 
has changed this situation, allowing the four clinically used HDAC 
inhibitors to be tested against P. knowlesi for the first time. All four 
compounds are sub-micromolar inhibitors of P. knowlesi growth 
(IC 50 9e370 nM), and as for P. falciparum (included as a control; 
Table 1) the most potent compound against P. knowlesi was Pan-
obinostat (Table 1; IC 50 9 (±1) nM). These data extend the human-
infecting Plasmodium species targeted by HDAC inhibitors in vitro or 
ex vivo to include P. falciparum (Engel et al., 2015), P. vivax (Marfurt 
et al., 2011) and now P. knowlesi. A comparison of the P. knowlesi 
and P. falciparum IC 50 values with cytotoxicity against human 
Neonatal Foreskin Fibroblast (NFF) and Human Embryonic Kidney </p>

<p>M.J. Chua et al. / International Journal for Parasitology: Drugs and Drug Resistance 7 (2017) 42e50 </p>

<p>
(HEK 293) cells (Engel et al., 2015) demonstrated that the three 
hydroxamate-based HDAC inhibitors Vorinostat, Panobinostat and 
Belinostat are modestly selective for Plasmodium parasites (Table 1; 
SI 8e45), while the cyclic tetrapeptide HDAC inhibitor Romidepsin 
lacks selectivity (Table 1; SI &lt; 1). 
In contrast to the activity observed against malaria parasites, no 
activity was observed for any compound against L. amazonensis </p>

<p>promastigotes (Fig. 1A), and when assessed at 1 mM or 10 mM </p>

<p>against intramacrophagic amastigotes all compounds were either 
toxic to macrophages or had no anti-leishmanial activity (data not 
shown). Only weak activity was observed for belinostat, pan-
obinostat and vorinostat against free L. donovani promastigotes </p>

<p>(20e35% inhibition at 20 mM; Fig. 1A), with no growth inhibition </p>

<p>observed for romidepsin (Fig. 1A). Likewise, poor activity was 
observed for all compounds against L. donovani axenic amastigotes 
(Fig. 1A). No anti-leishmanial activity was seen at concentrations </p>

<p>below 20 mM for either Leishmania species at all developmental </p>

<p>stages examined (data not shown). The activity of these drugs 
against S. mansoni was more variable (Fig. 1B). While the 
hydroxamic acid HDAC inhibitors were generally poor inhibitors of 
S. mansoni, panobinostat demonstrated modest inhibitory activity </p>

<p>against adult worm pairing (30e40% at 10 mM; P ¼ 0.001) and egg 
production (~50% at 10 mM; P ¼ 0.008; Fig. 1B). In the same assay 
conditions PZQ (10 mM) induced the death of adult worms (and in </p>

<p>consequence abolished pairing and egg-laying) but only very 
weakly affected the viability of schistosomula (8% viability </p>

<p>Table 1 
In vitro activity of anti-cancer HDAC inhibitors against Plasmodium parasites. </p>

<p>Compound 
Structure 
P. falciparum 3D7 
a IC 50 (nM) 
P. knowlesi A1H.1 
IC 50 (nM) </p>

<p>NFF </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>IC 50 (nM) </p>

<p>HEK 293 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>IC 50 (nM) </p>

<p>Plasmodium 
SI range </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Romidepsin 
140 (±4) 
210 (±20) 
1 (±1) 
&lt;5 
&lt;1 </p>

<p>Belinostat 
170 (±4) 
190 (±20) 
2370 (±1610) 
1420 (±50) 
7e14 </p>

<p>Panobinostat 
4 (±0.2) 
9 (±1) 
70 (±10) 
180 (±30) 
8e45 </p>

<p>Vorinostat 
250 (±140) 
370 (±20) 
5500 (±1310) 
5170 (±640) 
14e22 </p>

<p>Chloroquine 
10 (±1) 
10 (±3) 
48,930 (±19,220) 
nd 
4893 </p>

<p>a No significant difference (P &gt; 0.05; Student's t-Test) in IC 50 observed in this study (48 h assay) compared to previously published values (72 h assay) (Engel et al., 2015) for </p>

<p>vorinostat, panobinostat or romidepsin (belinostat P ¼ 0.01). 
b Previously published (Engel et al., 2015). 
c Selectivity Index (SI) is shown as a range for mammalian cell IC 50 /Plasmodium IC 50 . Values &gt; 1 indicate greater parasite selectivity; nd, not determined. </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>O 
V </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>R 
P </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>M 
B </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 0 </p>

<p>4 0 </p>

<p>6 0 </p>

<p>8 0 </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>1 2 0 </p>

<p>F lu o r e </p>

<p>s c e n </p>

<p>c e 
( % ) </p>

<p>L . a m a z o n e n s is P ro m a stig o tes </p>

<p>L . d o n o v a n i P ro m a s tig o te s </p>

<p>L . d o n o v a n i A x en ic A m a stig o tes </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>O 
V </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>R 
P </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>M 
B </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 0 </p>

<p>4 0 </p>

<p>6 0 </p>

<p>8 0 </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>1 2 0 </p>

<p>% 
D M 
S O c o n tr o l </p>

<p>S . m a n s o n i s c h is to s o m u la </p>

<p>S . m a n s o n i a d u lt w o r m p a ir s </p>

<p>S . m a n s o n i e g g s </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Fig. 1. In vitro activity of anti-cancer HDAC inhibitors against Leishmania species and S. mansoni. (A) Activity of vorinostat (VOR), panobinostat (PAN), romidepsin (ROM) and </p>

<p>belinostat (BEL) at 20 mM against Leishmania parasites. Data are presented as mean % fluorescence (±SD) relative to the DMSO control (100%) as determined by resazurin reduction 
assay. The leishmanicidal action of amphothericin B (AmpB; 1 mM) is shown as a positive control. (B) Activity of HDAC inhibitors at 10 mM against S. mansoni schistosomula (mean % </p>

<p>fluorescence (±SEM) as determined by resazurin reduction assay) and adult worms (mean % pairing and egg laying (±SEM)) relative to the DMSO control (100%). The control </p>

<p>compound praziquantel (10 mM) induced the death of adult worms (10% viability) but, as expected (Panic et al., 2015), only weakly affected the viability of schistosomula (not </p>

<p>shown). </p>

<p>M.J. Chua et al. / International Journal for Parasitology: Drugs and Drug Resistance 7 (2017) 42e50 </p>

<p>
reduction; P &gt; 0.05; data not shown), consistent with previous </p>

<p>observations (Panic et al., 2015). In addition, at 10 mM the cyclic </p>

<p>tetrapeptide Romidepsin completely inhibited adult worm pairing 
and egg production (Fig. 1B), an inhibitory activity that was also </p>

<p>seen at 1 mM and accompanied by tegumental damage (data not </p>

<p>shown). The greater effect of romidepsin on adult worm pairing 
and egg production as compared to the other inhibitors may be 
linked to the fact that romidepsin is a prodrug, requiring intracel-
lular reduction to generate a reactive sulfhydryl group that interacts 
with the zinc ion in the HDAC catalytic pocket (Furumai et al., 
2002). Previous studies have reported poor activity for vorinostat 
(used as a control in this work) against Leishmania and Schistosoma 
(Dubois et al., 2009; Patil et al., 2010) and this was hypothesized to 
be due to protection mechanisms such as higher efflux or lower 
influx of compounds, poor cell permeability or low levels of target 
proteins (Melesina et al., 2015), although none of these mecha-
nisms have been confirmed. 
The effects of the clinical HDAC inhibitors on P. knowlesi was 
further investigated using Western blot, with all drugs causing 
hyperactylation of P. knowlesi histone H4 (Fig. 2), indicating inhi-
bition of PkHDAC activity, either directly or indirectly. Hyper-
acetylation assays showed four distinct bands ranging from~11 kDa 
(the expected size of H4) to~16 kDa and relative density analysis 
showed a hyperacetylation effect using only the~11 kDa band or all 
bands combined (Fig. 2B). The higher molecular weight bands likely 
correspond to hyperacetylated forms of H2B/H2Bv (~13e14 kDa) 
and H2A.Z (~16 kDa) (Miao et al., 2006) as this antibody is reported 
to cross-react with acetylated forms of histones other than H4 (see 
Section 2.5). The hyperacetylation effect observed here for the first 
time in P. knowlesi is consistent with that previously reported for 
these and other HDAC inhibitors (Miao et al., 2006; Dow et al., 
2008; Trenholme et al., 2014; Engel et al., 2015) against 
P. falciparum and is considered a marker of HDAC inhibition in the 
parasite (e.g (Darkin-Rattray et al., 1996; Andrews et al., 2008, 
2012a; Chaal et al., 2010).). In P. falciparum, three class I/II HDAC 
homologues (encoded by Pfhdac1, Pfhdac2 and Pfhdac3 genes) have 
been annotated in the PlasmoDB (Aurrecoechea et al., 2009) 
genome database. Two additional class III homologues are also 
present (Aurrecoechea et al., 2009), but are not essential in asexual 
intraerythrocytic stage parasites (Freitas-Junior et al., 2005; Tonkin 
et al., 2009). While recombinant forms of PfHDAC2 and PfHDAC3 
are not currently available, the activity of PfHDAC1 can be inhibited 
by anti-Plasmodial HDAC inhibitors (Patel et al., 2009). Although no 
recombinant PkHDACs are available to assess direct enzyme inhi-
bition, it is likely that a PkHDAC is a target of these anti-cancer 
HDAC inhibitor compounds in P. knowlesi. Homologues of each of 
the P. falciparum class I/II HDACs, (amino acid sequence identities 
ranging from 43% to 95%; Supplemental Table S1) are annotated in 
the P. knowlesi genome (Aurrecoechea et al., 2009). The highest 
homology is between PfHDAC1 and its homologue PkHDAC1 (95%), 
a finding which fits well with our Western blot data demonstrating 
that PfHDAC1 polyclonal antibody (Trenholme et al., 2014; Engel 
et al., 2015) cross-reacts with P. knowlesi protein lysates 
(Supplemental Figure S1). 
As PfHDAC1 (PlasmoDB gene ID PF3D7_0925700) is inhibited by 
these clinically approved HDAC inhibitors (Engel et al., 2015), a 
three dimensional homology structural model of PkHDAC1 was 
generated (Fig. 3A) to examine the predicted binding mode of these 
ligands to the P. knowlesi homologue (PkHDAC1; PlasmoDB 
(Aurrecoechea et al., 2009) gene ID PKH_072280). The model of 
PkHDAC1, which was almost identical to that for PfHDAC1 
(Wheatley et al., 2010; Sumanadasa et al., 2012), adopted a ca-
nonical HDAC fold. A Ramachandran plot of the homology model 
(Supplemental Figure S2) showed 91.2% and 8.2% of residues from 
the model located in most favoured or allowed regions, </p>

<p>respectively. The QMEANscore6 and dfire_energy of the model was 
0.75 and À599.2, indicating that the homology model was stereo-
chemically favourable and energetically similar to native protein 
structures. For comparison, amino acids that differ between 
P. falciparum and P. knowlesi (corresponding to sequence compari-
son in Supplemental Figure S1) are coloured in red. The three HDAC 
inhibitors that showed some selectivity for P. knowlesi versus 
mammalian cells (vorinostat, panobinostat, belinostat) were 
docked into the PkHDAC1 model to investigate possible binding 
modes within the enzyme active site (Fig. 3B). All ligands showed 
their hydroxamate bound to zinc in the active site, with the linker 
occupying the active site tunnel of the enzyme and making hy-
drophobic and van der Waals interactions with residues Tyr301, 
Phe148, Phe203. The terminal group at the non-hydroxamate end 
of each inhibitor varied in the orientation towards the loop residues </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Hyperacetylation of P. knowlesi histones by HDAC inhibitors. (A) Western 
blot analysis of protein lysates prepared from trophozoite-stage P. knowlesi infected 
erythrocytes exposed to 1Â or 5Â IC 50 (see Table 1 for 1Â IC 50 values) vorinostat (VOR), 
panobinostat (PAN), belinostat (BEL) or romidepsin (ROM) for 3 h. Negative controls 
are parasites exposed to the antimalarial drug chloroquine (CQ; 5Â IC 50 for 3 h) or 
compound vehicle only (0.2% DMSO) taken at the start of the experiment (C-0h) or the 
3 h time point (C-3h). Western blot (top panel) was carried out with anti-(tetra) acetyl-
histone H4 antibody and goat anti-Rabbit, Alexa Fluor 
® 594 conjugate secondary </p>

<p>antibody. Sizes in kDa are indicated. The~11 kDa band corresponds to the correct size 
of histone H4 (arrow) and the higher molecular weight bands are likely cross reactivity 
with acetylated forms of H2B/H2Bv (~13e14 kDa) and H2A.Z (~16 kDa). Aliquots of the 
protein lysates were separated by SDS-PAGE and stained with Coomassie blue to show 
equivalent loading. (B) Graph shows relative density of all bands (white; Total) or H4 
only (grey; H4) as detected in Western blot (A; top panel) by anti-(tetra) acetyl-histone 
H4 antibody and normalised to total protein density on the corresponding Coomassie-
blue stained SDS-PAGE and then shown as fold change relative to the C-3h DMSO 
control (set to 1.0). </p>

<p>M.J. Chua et al. / International Journal for Parasitology: Drugs and Drug Resistance 7 (2017) 42e50 </p>

<p>
of the protein. The most potent inhibitor (panobinostat) of </p>

<p>P. knowlesi made p-p interactions between its terminal indole ring </p>

<p>and Phe203. Interestingly, the loop spanning residues 91e99 in 
both PkHDAC1 and PfHDAC1 have two extra residues (Ala95, 
Thr96) compared to human HDAC2. This repositions the sidechain 
of conserved loop residue Asp97, pushing it further into solvent and 
the backbone carbonyl oxygen of Thr96 occupies the location of the 
Asp97 sidechain of human HDAC2. As a result, the free amine group 
of panobinostat makes a hydrogen bond with the backbone 
carbonyl oxygen atom of Thr96. Previous modelling of PfHDAC1 
suggested that Asp97 is in a position similar to hHDAC8 (Wheatley 
et al., 2010). More interestingly, panobinostat docked in the current </p>

<p>model adopted a G-shaped binding mode (Fig. 3B), which is similar 
to the findings from Melesina et al. (2015) reporting that G-shaped </p>

<p>compounds are more favourable for selective inhibitors of parasitic 
HDACs. These modelling results provide support for binding to, and 
inhibition of, both PkHDAC1 and PfHDAC1 by these drugs and also 
rationalizes the stronger inhibition observed for panobinostat. 
Given the in vitro activity of the anti-cancer HDAC inhibitors 
against Plasmodium, we extended our in vitro findings to investigate 
for the first time in vivo antimalarial efficacy of vorinostat and 
panobinostat using a mouse model of malaria. A significant 
reduction in peripheral blood parasitemia was observed for mice 
treated by oral gavage twice daily with 25 mg/kg vorinostat 
compared to vehicle-only control mice (p &lt; 0.01 (day 4e6) and 
p &lt; 0.05 (day 7)), however this only resulted in a one day delay in 
parasitemia progression (Fig. 4A). A significant reduction in pe-
ripheral blood parasitemia was also observed for mice treated by 
oral gavage twice daily with 25 mg/kg panobinostat (p &lt; 0.05 (day 
4) and p &lt; 0.01 (day 5e10), corresponding to a 2e3 fold reduction 
in mean peripheral parasitemia on these days compared to vehicle-
only control mice (Fig. 4B). The survival (based on euthanizing 
according to ethics approved scorecard criteria) of mice treated </p>

<p>with panobinostat was also significantly improved compared to the 
vehicle control group (p ¼ 0.0013; Fig. 4D). Mice treated orally with 
the antimalarial drug chloroquine (10 mg/kg; twice daily for four 
days beginning 2 h p.i.) did not develop detectable peripheral blood 
parasitemia for the duration of the experiment (data not shown). 
While additional studies would be required to investigate why the 
in vivo activity of panobinostat is greater than for vorinostat in the 
mouse malaria model, panobinostat does have a 40e60 fold greater 
inhibitory potency against Plasmodium parasites in vitro (Table 1). 
However the direct in vitro activity of these drugs against P. berghei 
parasites is not known and pharmacokinetic properties are also 
likely to play a role. For example, preclinical studies in mice dosed 
orally with 50 mg/kg vorinostat or panobinostat have shown that 
these drugs have substantially different pharmacokinetic profiles, 
with panobinostat having a &gt;2-fold longer half-life (Table 2) (Yeo 
et al., 2007). While these in vivo data suggest that vorinostat has 
limited anti-Plasmodium activity, the data obtained for panobino-
stat may be of interest given the reported improvement in phar-
macokinetics for this drug in humans versus mice. Panobinostat has 
an approximately five-fold greater oral bioavailability (F%) in 
humans compared to mice with a 6e10 fold greater half-life (t 1/2 ; 
2.9 h and 16e30 h; Table 2) (Yeo et al., 2007). Humans receiving a 
single oral dose of panobinostat (at the recommended daily dose 
for cancer patients of 20 mg) have a reported mean C max of 24.3 
(±12) ng/mL (~70 nM) (European Medicines Agency, 2015), &gt;7-fold 
higher than the in vitro IC 50 of this compound against Plasmodium 
parasites. However, as adverse effects are commonly reported at 
this dose (FARYDAK 
® product sheet (Novartis)) repurposing pan-</p>

<p>obinostat for malaria would be difficult to justify. Nevertheless, 
these data raise the possibility of developing panobinostat ana-
logues with similar pharmacokinetic profiles but improved Plas-
modium-specific potency and selectivity. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. PkHDAC1 homology model structure with docked ligands. A) Secondary structure representation of the homology model of PkHDAC1, highlighting amino acids (red) that 
differ in PfHDAC1 e they are not in the ligand-binding site. These residues are: V15/I15, V69/I69, M77/L77, D82/E82, C85/Y85, I212/V212/, H215/N215, I230/M230, A241/V241, L256/ 
I256, S349/N349, I364/M364, and N372/H372 in PkHDAC1/PfHDAC1 respectively. Residues 374 to 448 of PkHDAC1 were not modelled due to lack of structural information from the 
template. (B) Docking poses of ligands with carbon atoms in white (vorinostat), yellow (panobinostat) and pink (belinostat) in PkHDAC1. Key interactions with orange zinc atom </p>

<p>(magenta dots), p-p interactions (red dots) and hydrogen bonds (black dots) are shown. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to </p>

<p>the web version of this article.) </p>

<p>M.J. Chua et al. / International Journal for Parasitology: Drugs and Drug Resistance 7 (2017) 42e50 </p>

<p>
Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We acknowledge the Australian Red Cross Blood Service for the 
provision of human blood and sera for culture of Plasmodium par-
asites and thank Professor Michael Blackman and Dr Robert Moon, 
Medical Research Council UK, for providing P. knowlesi parasites. 
The authors' work was supported by Australian National Health and 
Medical Research Council (APP1093378 and APP1074016 to KTA 
and DPF), the A-PARADDISE program funded under the European 
Union's Seventh Framework Programme (grant agreement no. 
602080 to KTA, DPF, JL, RJP, EP, GFS and SL) and Griffith University 
(GUIPRS and GUPRS scholarships to MJC). DF acknowledges an </p>

<p>NHMRC Senior Principal Research Fellowship (1027369) and ARC 
grant (CE140100011). The work of JL and RP was supported by 
institutional funds from the CNRS, the Institut Pasteur de Lille and 
the Universit e de Lille. </p>

<p>Appendix A. Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data related to this article can be found at http:// 
dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijpddr.2016.12.005 </p>

<p>References </p>

<p>Andrews, K.T., Fisher, G., Skinner-Adams, T.S., 2014. Drug repurposing and human 
parasitic protozoan diseases. Int. J. Parasitol. Drugs Drug Resist 4 (2), 95e111. 
Andrews, K.T., Gupta, A.P., Tran, T.N., Fairlie, D.P., N, G.G., Bozdech, Z., 2012a. 
Comparative gene expression profiling of P. falciparum malaria parasites 
exposed to three different histone deacetylase inhibitors. PLoS One 7 (2), 
e31847. 
Andrews, K.T., Haque, A., Jones, M.K., 2012b. HDAC inhibitors in parasitic diseases. 
Immunol. Cell Biol. 90 (1), 66e77. 
Andrews, K.T., Tran, T.N., Fairlie, D.P., 2012c. Towards histone deacetylase inhibitors 
as new antimalarial drugs. Curr. Pharm. Des. 18 (24), 3467e3479. 
Andrews, K.T., Tran, T.N., Lucke, A.J., Kahnberg, P., Le, G.T., Boyle, G.M., Gardiner, D.L., 
Skinner-Adams, T.S., Fairlie, D.P., 2008. Potent antimalarial activity of histone 
deacetylase inhibitor analogues. Antimicrob. Agents Chemother. 52 (4), 
1454e1461. 
Arnold, M.S., Engel, J.A., Chua, M.J., Fisher, G.M., Skinner-Adams, T.S., Andrews, K.T., 
2016. Adaption of the [3H]-hypoxanthine uptake assay for in vitro cultured 
Plasmodium knowlesi malaria parasites. Antimicrob. Agents Chemother. 60 (7), 
4361e4363. 
Arrowsmith, C.H., Bountra, C., Fish, P.V., Lee, K., Schapira, M., 2012. Epigenetic 
protein families: a new frontier for drug discovery. Nat. Rev. Drug Discov. 11 (5), 
384e400. 
Aulner, N., Danckaert, A., Rouault-Hardoin, E., Desrivot, J., Helynck, O., 
Commere, P.H., Munier-Lehmann, H., Spath, G.F., Shorte, S.L., Milon, G., Prina, E., 
2013. High content analysis of primary macrophages hosting proliferating </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
6 
8 10 12 14 16 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 0 </p>

<p>4 0 </p>

<p>6 0 </p>

<p>8 0 </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>1 2 0 </p>

<p>D a y p o s t in fe c tio n 
% S u r v iv a l </p>

<p>P = 0 .0 2 2 </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
6 
8 1 0 1 2 1 4 1 6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 0 </p>

<p>4 0 </p>

<p>6 0 </p>

<p>8 0 </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>1 2 0 </p>

<p>P = 0 .0 0 1 3 </p>

<p>D a y p o st in fec tio n </p>

<p>% 
S u r v iv a l </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>* * </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
6 
8 10 12 14 16 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>2 0 </p>

<p>3 0 </p>

<p>4 0 </p>

<p>5 0 </p>

<p>6 0 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>D a y p o st in fe c tio n 
M e a n % P a r a s ite m ia 
0 
2 
4 
6 
8 10 12 14 16 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>2 0 </p>

<p>3 0 </p>

<p>4 0 </p>

<p>5 0 </p>

<p>6 0 </p>

<p>* * </p>

<p>D a y p o st in fe c tio n 
M e a n % P a r a s ite m ia </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Fig. 4. In vivo activity of orally administered vorinostat and panobinostat in Plasmodium berghei infected BALB/c mice. Female 6e8 week old BALB/c mice (n ¼ 6) were 
injected i.p. with 10 
5 P. berghei QIMR infected erythrocytes. Mice were treated by oral gavage with 25 mg/kg vorinostat (A and C; dashed line) or panobinostat (B and D; dashed line) </p>

<p>twice daily for four days beginning 2 h post infection, with 4 h between first and second dose (100 mL/dose diluted freshly in 10% DMSO in PBS). Control mice (A-D; solid black line) 
received 100 mL vehicle only (10% DMSO in PBS) under the same dosing schedule. Parasitemia was monitored daily starting day 4 p.i. via microscopic examination of Giemsa-stained </p>

<p>thin blood smears. Panels A and B show mean number of parasites per 100 erythrocytes (mean % parasitemia; &gt;800 erythrocytes counted for each mouse) for 6 mice per treatment 
group (dashed lines) versus control group (solid black lines). Panels C and D show survival rates (mice were euthanized when parasitemia reached~!25%) for treated (dashed lines) 
versus DMSO vehicle-only control (solid black lines) mice. </p>

<p>Table 2 
Pharmacokinetic parameters of oral vorinostat and panobinostat in mice and 
humans. </p>

<p>Parameter 
Mice </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Humans </p>

<p>vorinostat </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>panobinostat </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>vorinostat </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>panobinostat </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>AUC 0À∞ (ng,h/mL) 619 
126 
1698 
183e373 
t 1/2 (h) 
0.75 
2.90 
1.5 
16e30 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>C max (ng/mL) 
501 
116 
658 
23e71 
F (%) 
8.33 
4.62 
43 
21 </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>a Female BALB/c nude mice (18e22 g; 8e10 weeks old) dosed orally with 50 mg/ </p>

<p>kg vorinostat or panobinostat (Yeo et al., 2007). 
b Human subjects administered 200e600 mg oral vorinostat (Kavanaugh et al., </p>

<p>2010). 
c Human subjects administered 15e80 mg oral panobinostat ((Prince et al., 2009) </p>

<p>and references therein). 
d t 1/2 30 h in advanced cancer patients (n ¼ 4) receiving a single 20 mg dose of </p>

<p>panobinostat (Clive et al., 2012). 
e FARYDAK 
® prescribing information sheet (Novartis). </p>

<p>M.J. Chua et al. / International Journal for Parasitology: Drugs and Drug Resistance 7 (2017) 42e50 </p>



<p>
M.J. Chua et al. / International Journal for Parasitology: Drugs and Drug Resistance 7 (2017) 42e50 </p>



<p>
M.J. Chua et al. / International Journal for Parasitology: Drugs and Drug Resistance 7 (2017) 42e50 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>