<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5355527" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:41+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The nature of work has changed considerably in many sectors of 
industry over the past decades [1]. Modern organizations consider 
job stress and job satisfaction of their employees as two important 
workplace issues [2]. According to recent studies, occupational 
stress accounts for 50e60% of all lost working days [3]. Work-
related stress is considered to be harmful when physical and 
emotional responses occur when there is a mismatch between job 
requirements and the workers' capabilities, resources, or needs [4]. 
Most researchers agree that workplace factors can cause work-
related stress [5]. These factors are divided into physical and </p>

<p>psychosocial hazards. Exposure to physical hazards in the work-
place can be associated with anxiety that, in turn, drives experi-
encing work-related stress. Psychosocial hazards include factors 
related to work design, organization, and management, together 
with workplace social structure that can have negative effects on 
individuals [6]. Work-related stress usually influences individual 
and organizational issues including behavioral, mental, as well as 
physical outcomes, performance, job satisfaction, and organiza-
tional commitment [7]. 
Applied research indicates strong correlations between di-
mensions of workplace, stress, and job satisfaction. High levels of 
work stress are associated with low levels of job satisfaction. Job </p>

<p>* Corresponding author. Department of Ergonomics, School of Health, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, P.O. Box: 71465-111, Shiraz, Iran. </p>

<p>E-mail address: alrchoobin@sums.ac.ir (A. Choobineh). </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>Safety and Health at Work </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e -s h a w . o r g </p>

<p>2093-7911/$ e see front matter Ó 2016, Occupational Safety and Health Research Institute. Published by Elsevier. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.shaw.2016.07.002 </p>

<p>Safety and Health at Work 8 (2017) 67e71 </p>

<p>stressors are predictive for job dissatisfaction and a greater pro-
pensity to leave the organization [8]. 
Job satisfaction is the affective orientation that an employee has 
towards his/her work. It can be considered as an overall feeling 
about the job or as a related constellation of attitudes about various 
aspects of the job [9]. There is growing evidence that current trends 
in employment conditions may have negative effects on job satis-
faction and deteriorate the physical and mental health of em-
ployees [10]. Affective disposition on job satisfaction consists of two 
facets: positive affectivity and negative affectivity. High energy, 
eagerness, and pleasurable involvement represent positive affec-
tivity while distress, unpleasant involvement, and nervousness 
show negative affectivity [11]. 
Work-related stress is a vital factor to job satisfaction. When 
functioning as a motivator, work-related stress results in creativity 
and satisfaction and consequently removes boredom and 
mundanity. Stress leads to aggression and low job satisfaction 
when it functions as a negative factor [2]. Job satisfaction may 
protect workers from stressors. Satisfaction is a regulating factor for 
stress. During the neoclassical period (1920e1950), theories sup-
ported the fact that employees' satisfaction directly affected pro-
ductivity. They believed that there was a cause-effect relationship 
between satisfaction and productivity. This answered the question 
why organizations tried to improve their employees' productivity 
by different ways. These two factors (work-related stress and job 
satisfaction) may have a negative impact on the productivity of a 
working group and consequently cause an added cost to expenses 
of a company [2]. The analysis of the present situation at the in-
ternational level has revealed, among others, the necessity of 
improving work quality and productivity, as well as providing 
safety and health in the work place [12]. 
The petrochemical industry is an important industry in Iran 
from the viewpoints of economics and employment. There are 
critical jobs in the petrochemical industry, such as control room 
operation, maintenance, site operation, firefighting, etc. In such an 
industry, job stress and dissatisfaction may have a negative impact 
on productivity and safety of employees. 
Given the above, since there is little study on such issue among 
petrochemical employees, the present study was carried out to 
investigate the impact of job stress and job satisfaction on em-
ployees' productivity in an Iranian petrochemical company. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>This cross-sectional study was conducted from October 2014 to 
May 2015, in an Iranian petrochemical company with 325 em-
ployees, located at Asalouyeh, in the southern part of Iran in which 
methanol was produced as the final product. The sample size was 
determined with reference to a study by Naqvi et al [13]. Taking </p>

<p>the b (power) of 80% and a (the first type error) ¼ 5% into </p>

<p>consideration, using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Medcalc</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">MedCalc Software</rs> bvba, 
Ostend, Belgium) the sample size was calculated to be 125. Par-
ticipants were randomly selected from the personal list provided 
by the company. </p>

<p>2.1. Data gathering tools </p>

<p>An anonymous self-administered questionnaire was used to 
collect the required data for each participant. The questionnaire 
consisted of the following four parts: 
(1) a demographic questionnaire was used for collecting personal 
details including age, weight, height, work experience, daily work 
hours, gender, marital status, level of education, type of employment 
and working schedule; (2) the Persian version of Osipow occupational 
stress inventory was used to investigate the level of job stress among </p>

<p>the study population. Occupational stress was measured by six sub-
scales, i.e., role overload, role insufficiency, role ambiguity, role 
boundary, responsibility, and physical environment. Each subscale 
contains 10 items. There are 60 items in total in the scale. Each item is 
scored on a 5-point Likert scale (1 ¼ never, 2 ¼ occasionally, 
3 ¼ sometimes, 4 ¼ usually, and 5 ¼ most of the time). A high subscale 
score depicts a greater level of role stressor. The obtained scores are 
classified as: low (10e19), low-moderate (20e29), moderate-high 
(30e39), and high (40e50) [14]. The total score of the job stress 
questionnaire is also divided into four levels, as follows: low (60e119), 
low-moderate (120e179), moderate-high (180e239), and high (240e 
300) [14]. The validity and reliability of this questionnaire were 
assessed in a study by Sharifian et al [15] and cronbach alpha coeffi-
cient was calculated to be 0.83; (3) the Persian version of Job 
Descriptive Index (JDI) was used to investigate job satisfaction. The JDI 
consists of 39 items in five subscales, i.e., work (10 items), pay (6 
items), promotion (5 items), supervision (8 items), and coworkers (10 
items). Each part measures one particular area of job satisfaction. A 
response was collected to each item on a 5-point Likert scale 
(1 ¼ never, 2 ¼ occasionally, 3 ¼ often, 4 ¼ usually, and 5 ¼ most of the 
time). The scores of each subscale were added together for each 
respondent to obtain a JDI total score reflecting the overall job satis-
faction. No cutoff point has been reported to define the upper and the 
lower limits of job satisfaction index in the scientific literature, 
therefore, we used the minimum and the maximum attainable scores 
of JDI (39e195) to judge about the level of job satisfaction in the study 
population. Regarding this, if the mean score of JDI was near the lower 
limit score (39), near the midpoint (117), and near the upper limit 
score (195), job satisfaction was considered as low, moderate, and 
high, respectively. The validity and reliability of this questionnaire 
were assessed in a study by Norbakhsh and Mirnaderi in which the 
cronbach alpha coefficient was 0.88 [16]; and (4) the Persian version 
of the Hersey and Goldsmith questionnaire was applied to investigate 
workers' productivity. This questionnaire consists of 26 items in seven 
subscales: ability (3 items), occupational identification (4 items), or-
ganization support (4 items), motivation (4 items), performance 
feedback (4 items), credit (4 items), and environment compatibility (3 
items). Each item was scored on a 5-point Likert scale (1 ¼ never, 
2 ¼ occasionally, 3 ¼ often, 4 ¼ usually, and 5 ¼ true most of the time). 
Similar to JDI, no cut-off point has been indicated to define the upper 
and the lower limits for productivity index in the scientific literature, 
therefore, the minimum and the maximum attainable scores of this 
index (29e130) were used to judge about the level of productivity of 
the study population. Based on this, if the mean score of productivity 
score was near the lower limit score (29), near the midpoint (79.5), 
and near the upper limit score (130), productivity was considered as 
lower, moderate, and high, respectively. The validity and reliability of 
this questionnaire were assessed in a study by Nasirpour et al [17] in 
which the cronbach alpha coefficient was 0.81. </p>

<p>2.2. Data analysis </p>

<p>Upon completion of the field survey and data collection, data 
were transferred into the computer for statistical analysis. Statis-
tical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 19</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM</rs>, Armonk, 
NY, USA). Pearson correlation analysis was used to examine the 
relationship between quantitative variables such as stress, job 
satisfaction, and productivity scores. To assess the factors affecting 
productivity, linear regression analysis was applied. In all tests, the 
significance level was set at 0.05. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>Table 1 summarizes personal details of the employees who 
participated in the study. According to Table 1, mean age of the </p>

<p>Saf Health Work 2017;8:67e71 </p>

<p>
study participants was 30.95 AE 5.26 years, ranging from 22 years 
to 48 years. The employees' mean work experience was 
7.04 AE 3.81 years (1e21 years). A large majority of the participants 
had university education (73.6%). Some 70.4% of the study popu-
lation was married and 55.2% of the participants were shift 
workers. 
According to Table 2, the mean score of job stress was calcu-
lated to be 181.27 AE 24.17 indicating "moderate-high" level of 
stress. One-way ANOVA, independent t test and Pearson coeffi-
cient statistical procedures did not show any significant rela-
tionship between the mean job stress score and demographic 
characteristics of the participants. Additionally, the statistical 
analyses revealed no significant relationship between the mean 
scores of job stress and job satisfaction (p ¼ 0.152) and 
productivity. 
The mean job satisfaction score was found to be 129.96 AE 18.84 
indicating "moderate" level of job satisfaction. One-way ANOVA 
test showed a significant U shape relationship between the mean 
score of job satisfaction and age (p ¼ 0.024). A post hoc test indi-
cated that there was a significant difference in job satisfaction 
means score among the three age groups, such that the mean job 
satisfaction score in the 31e38 years age group was lower than 
those of the other two groups (i.e., 22e30 years and 39e48 years). 
Independent t test also showed that the mean job satisfaction score </p>

<p>Table 1 
Demographic characteristics of the employees studied (N ¼ 125) </p>

<p>Age (y) 
Mean AE SD 
MineMax </p>

<p>30.95 AE 5.26 
22e48 </p>

<p>Weight (kg) 
Mean AE SD 
MineMax </p>

<p>77.16 AE 8.51 
60e105 </p>

<p>Height (cm) 
Mean AE SD 
MineMax </p>

<p>176 AE 6.00 
160e188 </p>

<p>BMI (kg/m 2 ) 
Mean AE SD 
MineMax </p>

<p>24.92 AE 2.59 
18.39e34.29 </p>

<p>Work experience (y) 
Mean AE SD 
MineMax </p>

<p>7.04 AE 3.81 
1e21 </p>

<p>Working hours/day (h) 
Mean AE SD 
MineMax </p>

<p>10.65 AE 1.48 
8e15 </p>

<p>Sex 
Male 
Female </p>

<p>112 (89.6) 
13 (10.4) </p>

<p>Marital status 
Single 
Married </p>

<p>37 (29.6) 
88 (70.4) </p>

<p>Education 
Under diploma/Diploma 
B.Sc. 
M.Sc. </p>

<p>33 (26.4) 
54 (43.2) 
38 (30.4) </p>

<p>Working schedule 
Shift working * 
Day working </p>

<p>69 (55.2) 
56 (44.8) </p>

<p>Data are presented as n (%) 
* An arrangement of working hours that uses two or more teams (shifts) of 
workers, in order to extend the hours of operation of the work environment beyond 
that of conventional office hours. </p>

<p>Table 2 
Statistical analyses for assessment indices (N ¼ 125) </p>

<p>Variable 
Job stress (Mean AE SD) 
Job satisfaction (Mean AE SD) 
Productivity (Mean AE SD) </p>

<p>181.27 AE 24.17 
129.96 AE 18.84 
70.52 AE 11.89 </p>

<p>Mean AE SD 
p 
Mean AE SD 
p 
Mean AE SD 
p </p>

<p>Age groups (y) y 
22e30 
175.84 AE 22.37 
0.06 
133.38 AE 20.2 
0.024 
69.44 AE 10.96 
0.37 
31e38 
165.66 AE 24.34 
125.59 AE 17.34 
72.11 AE 13.39 
39e48 
175.75 AE 30.78 
137.55 AE 15.69 
67.63 AE 5.20 </p>

<p>Marital status * 
Single 
173.92 AE 24.96 
0.43 
123.38 AE 17.24 
0.011 
71.95 AE 10.55 
0.38 
Married 
170.16 AE 23.89 
132.73 AE 18.88 
69.92 AE 12.42 </p>

<p>Educational level y 
Diploma 
176.62 AE 24.93 
0.319 
134.88 AE 18.09 
0.089 
68.58 AE 12.35 
0.55 
Associate diploma 
168.98 AE 23.71 
130.26 AE 19.28 
71.02 AE 11.38 
B.Sc. 
169.68 AE 24.03 
125.13 AE 17.67 
71.44 AE 12.33 </p>

<p>Working schedule * 
Shifts working 
170.30 AE 26.81 
0.57 
129.10 AE 19.50 
0.51 
68.64 AE 11.27 
0.024 
Day working 
172.83 AE 19.37 
131.33 AE 17.83 
73.54 AE 11.56 </p>

<p>Daily working time (h) * 
1e8 
152.5 AE 14.84 
0.31 
133/00 AE 15/55 
0.82 
84.05 AE 12/02 
0.094 
9e16 
171.58 AE 24.21 
129.91 AE 18.94 
70.29 AE 11.80 </p>

<p>Stress dimensions 
Role overload y 
Low 
e 
e 
71.70 AE 7.81 
0.95 
Low-moderate 
70.64 AE 12.89 
Moderate-high 
70.03 AE 10.40 
High 
72.03 AE 9.5 
Role insufficiency y 
Low 
e 
e 
69.33 AE 4.72 
0.06 
Low-moderate 
73.92 AE 10.33 
Moderate-high 
68.07 AE 12.73 
High 
66.02 AE 0.5 
Role ambiguity y 
Low 
e 
e 
75.93 AE 11.75 
0.0001 
Low-moderate 
72.83 AE 9.96 
Moderate-high 
70.98 AE 10.82 
High 
51.33 AE 20.41 
Role boundary y 
Low 
e 
e 
68.73 AE 5.72 
0.54 
Low-moderate 
71.84 AE 11.05 
Moderate-high 
69.19 AE 13.71 
High 
79.51 AE 0.68 
Responsibility y 
Low 
e 
e 
69.33 AE 4.72 
0.325 
Low-moderate 
72.06 AE 11.06 
Moderate-high 
68.82 AE 12.92 
High 
66.90 AE 11.1 
Physical environment y 
Low 
e 
e 
69.00 AE 6.68 
0.182 
Low-moderate 
71.51 AE 9.86 
Moderate-high 
71.48 AE 10.80 
High 
64.50 AE 19.46 </p>

<p>Satisfaction dimensions 
Work z 
e 
e 
0.025 
Supervision z 
e 
e 
0.001 
Coworkers z 
e 
e 
0.007 
Promotion z 
e 
e 
0.08 
Payment z 
e 
e 
0.789 </p>

<p>* Independent sample t test. 
y One-way ANOVA test. 
z Pearson correlation coefficient. </p>

<p>N. Hoboubi et al / Job Stress and Satisfaction in Petrochemical Industry </p>

<p>
was significantly higher in married individuals than in single in-
dividuals (p ¼ 0.009). 
The mean score of productivity index was found to be 
70.52 AE 11.89, indicating "moderate" level of productivity. A one-
way ANOVA test showed a significant relationship between the 
mean productivity score and the third dimension of job stress (role 
ambiguity) (p ¼ 0.0001). The mean score of productivity index 
showed a direct significant relationship with the first, the second, 
and the third dimensions of job satisfaction index (work, supervi-
sion, and coworkers) (p &lt; 0.05). This indicated that higher scores of 
the mentioned dimensions of job satisfaction index were related to 
higher productivity. 
Also, an independent t test indicated that the mean score of 
productivity index was significantly lower in shift workers than in 
fixed day workers (p ¼ 0.024). No statistical significant relationship 
was found between the mean score of productivity index and other 
demographic characteristics. 
In order to investigate the correlation between job stress and job 
satisfaction indices and productivity index in the study partici-
pants, Pearson correlation coefficient was used. The result of this 
analysis showed that although the correlation between job stress 
index and productivity index was not statistically significant 
(p &gt; 0.05), the correlation between job satisfaction index and 
productivity index was statistically significant (p ¼ 0.04). This 
relationship was positive and the correlation coefficient (r ¼ 0.37) 
indicated a weak correlation between these two variables. This 
means that with an increase in the mean job satisfaction score, the 
mean productivity score would increase. 
In order to investigate factors affecting productivity index, 
multiple linear regression analysis was used. Based on the results of 
one-way ANOVA and univariate analyses, it was found that work 
schedule (shift or fixed), working hours, the second, the third, and 
the sixth dimensions of job stress index (role insufficiency, role 
ambiguity, and physical environment) and the first, the second, the 
third, and the fourth dimensions of job satisfaction index (work 
load, supervision, coworkers, and promotion) were eligible to enter 
the linear regression model (p &lt; 0.25) [18]. 
The results of regression modeling revealed that the variables of 
shift schedule, the second and the third dimensions of job stress 
(role insufficiency and role ambiguity), and the second dimension 
of job satisfaction (supervision) remained in the model. According 
to the coefficient of determination (R 2 ), 22.3% of the changes 
related to productivity index could be explained by current vari-
ables (Table 3). The final score of the job stress index is classified 
into four levels (low, low-moderate, moderate-high, and high). That 
is why a dummy variable was defined in order to correctly interpret 
the dimensions of stress; low job stress was regarded to be the base 
in the model. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>The results showed that the mean productivity score in shift 
workers was significantly lower than that of fixed day workers, </p>

<p>which was in line with the results of other studies [19,20]. This 
decline may be due to factors such as health problems, impaired 
social life, sleep disorders, and circadian misalignment during shift 
work [21]. One reason could be that when people work outside of 
their normal sleep-wake cycle, a mismatch occurs between the 
body's biological clock and events taking place in the environment, 
and consequently affects the individual's activities [22]. 
The results showed a U shape significant relationship between 
the mean job satisfaction score and age, so that the mean job 
satisfaction score in the 31e38 years age group was significantly 
lower than those of the two other age groups ( i.e., 22e30 years and 
39e48 years). This finding is in agreement with the results of other 
studies [23,24]. One possible reason is that young people are highly 
motivated during the first years of employment which can lead to a 
high job satisfaction. This level of job satisfaction declines during 
the middle years of employment due to job repetitiveness and job 
restrictions; after this period, job satisfaction continuously in-
creases with age [24]. This increase is justified based on Herzberg's 
"modified expectation" theory. On the basis of this theory, when 
age and job experience increase, the individual's expectations of 
her/his work begin to become more realistic. This may result in job 
satisfaction increment. In a study, a direct linear relationship was 
reported between age and job satisfaction which was not in 
agreement with Herzberg's hypothesis of the U-shaped relation-
ship between these variables [25]. 
The results of the present study showed that job satisfaction in 
married individuals was higher than single ones, which was in 
agreement with the results of some other studies [26,27]. Ac-
cording to Bowen, single young people hesitate in decision-
making on how to keep their jobs and do not know whether 
they have selected the jobs they are currently working in for their 
entire life or just for a certain period. Thus, job satisfaction in 
these individuals is lower than in older and married ones [27]. It is 
to be noted that these findings are not consistent with the results 
of other studies [28e30]. 
The results demonstrated a significant negative relationship 
between role insufficiency and productivity in such a way that 
when role insufficiency increased, productivity decreased. Meleis 
[31] defined role insufficiency as any kind of problem in identi-
fying the role, playing a role, or role-related goals understood by 
the individual or others. This finding is similar to a study by Wu 
et al [32]. In this study, role insufficiency was determined as one of 
the factors which had a direct and significant impact on depression. 
Depression is a common mental health problem in the world which 
increases employees' absenteeism and reduces productivity [32]. It 
was also reported in a study that increased job stress was associ-
ated with increased role insufficiency [33]. Increased stress can lead 
to reduced job satisfaction and productivity of individuals [2]. 
The present study showed that there was a significant negative 
relationship between role ambiguity and productivity such that 
increased role ambiguity would cause reduced productivity in in-
dividuals. Role ambiguity is a state during which individuals have 
no clear and direct understanding about their roles in the organi-
zation [34]. It appears when the duties are not clearly defined for 
the individual and she/he is frightened of doing things or accepting 
responsibility. Role stressors mainly include role ambiguity and role 
conflict which can lead to increased employees absenteeism and 
frequent work delays, increase in employees' turnover and reduced 
workforce productivity [35]. In a study by Rizwan et al, a significant 
positive relationship was observed between role ambiguity and job 
stress such that role ambiguity was reported to cause 15% increase 
in job stress [28]. Increased job stress is accompanied with reduced 
performance and job satisfaction, which finally leads to lower 
productivity of individuals and increased costs incurred by the or-
ganization [2]. </p>

<p>Table 3 
Regression model indicating factors with influence on employees' productivity </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Standard error 
t 
p 
R 2y </p>

<p>Shift working * 
4.075 
2.00 
2.032 
0.045 </p>

<p>Supervision 
0.565 
0.269 
2.09 
0.038 </p>

<p>Role insufficiency z 
À5.43 
2.59 
2.09 
0.038 
0.223 </p>

<p>Role ambiguity x 
À17.64 
6.71 
À2.62 
0.01 </p>

<p>* Shift workers were considered as reference group. 
y R 2 Adjusted R square. 
z Poor fit between the participants' skills and their job. 
x Participants are unclear about what they are expected to do. </p>

<p>Saf Health Work 2017;8:67e71 </p>

<p>
The results of the regression modeling indicated that supervision 
could have an effective role in increasing productivity, which was in 
agreement with the results of a study by Frimpong et al [36]. In this 
study, a strong interaction was reported between the workers' 
perceived supervisor support and productivity, in such a way that 
workers who were not supported by their supervisors had lower 
productivity as compared to those who were provided with adequate 
support [36]. Providing appropriate support in the workplace by the 
supervisor would cause reduced stress on the individuals and protect 
her/him against adverse effects of job demands, job dissatisfaction, 
and depression [33]. </p>

<p>4.1. Limitations </p>

<p>Regarding the cross-sectional nature of the present study and 
data gathering based on self-report, the findings should be 
considered cautiously. In the self-report method, there may be 
problems will deception, denial, or recall. Additionally, in this study 
job stress and productivity were not examined using objective 
methods. The results of the study could be more conclusive if 
objective measures were included. </p>

<p>5. Conclusion </p>

<p>The findings of the present study showed that the employees' 
perceived job stress and job satisfaction were moderate-high and 
moderate, respectively. Also, their productivity was assessed as 
moderate. According to the study results, shift working, "role 
insufficiency", and "role ambiguity" were determined as the 
contributing factors for reduced productivity; "supervision sup-
port" was also found to be an effective factor for increased pro-
ductivity. Based on the study findings, to achieve lower job stress, 
higher job satisfaction, and productivity in the workplace, the 
following supportive measures are recommended: </p>

<p>Identifying and optimizing the factors influencing job stress 
and job satisfaction 
Providing direct staff support by management 
Employing individuals according to their expertise and abilities 
Providing exact definition and description of jobs for 
employees 
Selecting fit employees for shift working </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest </p>

<p>All authors have no conflicts of interest to declare. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This study was financially supported by Shiraz University of 
Medical Science (grant no. 93-01-42-7387). The authors wish to 
thank all petrochemical employees who participated in this study. </p>



<p>N. Hoboubi et al / Job Stress and Satisfaction in Petrochemical Industry </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>