<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5381479" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Analyzing sizes of DNA via electrophoresis using a gel has played an important role in the recent, rapid 
progress of biology and biotechnology. Although analyzing DNA over a wide range of sizes in a short time is 
desired, no existing electrophoresis methods have been able to fully satisfy these two requirements. Here we 
propose a novel method using a rigid 3D network structure composed of solid nanowires within a 
microchannel. This rigid network structure enables analysis of DNA under applied DC electric fields for a 
large DNA size range (100 bp-166 kbp) within 13 s, which are much wider and faster conditions than those 
of any existing methods. The network density is readily varied for the targeted DNA size range by tailoring 
the number of cycles of the nanowire growth only at the desired spatial position within the microchannel. 
The rigid dense 3D network structure with spatial density control plays an important role in determining the 
capability for analyzing DNA. Since the present method allows the spatial location and density of the 
nanostructure within the microchannels to be defined, this unique controllability offers a new strategy to 
develop an analytical method not only for DNA but also for other biological molecules. </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>ince researchers have revealed the critical role played by information stored within DNA molecules in the 
complex biological activities occurring in living systems </p>

<p>1-3 </p>

<p>, various methodologies have been developed to 
analyze DNA molecules 
4,5 . Among them, gel electrophoresis is the most prominent and commercially 
available standard method to analyze the size of DNA molecules due to the great controllability of pore sizes 
and also the inexpensiveness of electrophoresis devices 
6 . On the other hand, the limitations of gel electrophoresis 
have also been pointed out, and they are the difficulty in analyzing relatively long DNA molecules in a short time, 
the high skill required for appropriately preparing the gel, and the requirement of gel concentration control for 
each targeted DNA size </p>

<p>7-9 </p>

<p>. Recently, data for a wide range of DNA size have been obtained using the hydrodyn-
amic chromatography method </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>. Although the analysis time using this method is faster than that using gel 
electrophoresis, it still takes several tens of minutes for the fastest analysis. To realize an analysis on the time 
scale of seconds, nanostructure electrophoresis has attracted much attention as a novel method to overcome the 
above issues with gel electrophoresis </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>. 
Nanostructure electrophoresis under DC and AC electric fields has been used to analyze DNA molecules by 
separating differently sized DNA molecules in a short time, which is impossible in gel electrophoresis </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>. Since 
Volkmuth and Austin 
13 first proposed to utilize highly-ordered sieving nanostructures as an alternative for 
conventional randomly-ordered gel or polymer sieving matrices, many lithography-based nanostructures, such 
as nanopillar arrays </p>

<p>13-16 </p>

<p>, nanowall arrays </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>, nanofilter arrays </p>

<p>18-21 </p>

<p>, and nanochannels </p>

<p>22-24 </p>

<p>, have been applied for 
analysis of DNA molecules. For example, Kaji et al. 
15 demonstrated that a nanopillar structure could separate 5 
components from a mixture of l-DNA (48.5 kbp) digested by HindIII under a DC electric field, however it took 
more than 600 s and the DNA size range had to be over 2 kbp. Huang et al. 
14 also obtained good separation of 
large DNA molecules (61-209 kb) in 15 s, however, the nanopillar arrays required AC electric fields and DNA 
size range was limited to over 60 kb. In a third example from a study by Fu et al. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>, continuous separation of DNA </p>

<p>OPEN </p>

<p>SUBJECT AREAS: </p>

<p>NANOSTRUCTURES </p>

<p>BIOANALYTICAL CHEMISTRY </p>

<p>molecules was realized in a wide range (0.1-20 kbp), however it was 
essentially impossible to separate 0.1 and 20 kbp at the same time 
because of different required separation conditions, which Fu et al. 
attributed to different separation regimes for 0.1 and 20 kbp. As 
discussed above, intensive efforts have been devoted to developing 
new types of nanostructure electrophoresis </p>

<p>11,12 </p>

<p>. Although these arti-
ficial nanostructures realize analysis of DNA molecules with fewer 
time-and labor-intensive operations </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>, the use of lithography tech-
niques intrinsically limits the available size range (usually over 
1 kbp) and also the formation of three-dimensionally (3D) designed 
spatial nanostructures. Nanostructure electrophoresis needs a rela-
tively long time to analyze short DNA molecules due to the sparse-
ness of geometrical nanostructures compared with 3D gel network 
structures </p>

<p>18,26,27 </p>

<p>. 
A self-assembled nanoparticle array within a microchannel is 
another candidate methodology, which offers a 3D-ordered nano-
porous sieving matrix </p>

<p>28-32 </p>

<p>. Interesting features of nanoparticle arrays 
have been demonstrated by separating DNA molecules under AC 
electric fields </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>. Zeng and Harrison 
30 reported DNA separations ran-
ging from 100 bp to 2 kbp using the nanoparticle array, and the 
separation time was 10 min, and Tabuchi et al. 
29 showed DNA sepa-
rations up to 15 kbp within 100 s using nanospheres. Compared 
with lithography-defined nanostructure electrophoresis, the DNA 
size range is much wider due to 3D-ordered sieving matrices, how-
ever, the spatial controllability of such nanoparticle arrays within 
microchannels is rather poor due to the intrinsic difficulties in con-
trolling the spatial positions and forming the sparse structures due to 
the naturally occurring aggregation events of nanoparticles. Addi-
tionally, these techniques require special instruments such as AC 
electric fields generators or a combination of electric fields and pres-
sure application. These limitations, especially as to the spatial con-
trollability, are detrimental to analyze and separate relatively long 
DNA molecules (over 20 kbp) in a short time; we have seen a general 
difference between gel electrophoresis and nanostructure electro-
phoresis. Thus, no existing methods are able to analyze fully a wide 
range of DNA molecules in a short time. 
To overcome these long-standing issues in DNA analysis, here we 
propose a novel electrophoresis method, which utilizes a rigid 3D 
network structure composed of solid nanowires only at the desired 
position within a microchannel. This method allows analysis of DNA 
molecules under DC electric fields in a much wider range and in a 
faster time than any other existing methods. Our approach to realize 
the rigid 3D network structure at the desired spatial position within 
the microchannel is to use cycling nanowire growth by applying a 
vapor-liquid-solid (VLS) method with a metal catalyst. Two note-
worthy features of this method are: (1) the spatial selectivity of VLS 
nanowire growth and (2) the density control of the network struc-
tures by cycling the supply of metal catalyst. </p>

<p>Results and Discussion 
The scheme in Figure 1 summarizes the fabrication procedures; also 
included are a photo of a fabricated device and SEM and TEM images 
of the nanowire network structure within the microchannel when 
varying the number of growth cycles. We fabricated the microchan-
nel on a fused silica substrate by conventional photolithography and 
utilized Au catalyst for VLS growth of SnO 2 nanowires (typical dia-
meter of 10-20 nm) </p>

<p>33-35 </p>

<p>. It should be noted that we intentionally did 
not use electron beam lithography as we wanted to target future 
commercial use. Other details of the fabrication procedures can be 
seen in Methods and Supplementary Fig. S1. The nanowire surface 
can be modified by forming a shell layer on the nanowire sidewall as a 
core-shell nanowire structure </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>; and here we utilized the SiO 2 shell 
layer </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>, which generates a negatively charged surface on the nano-
wires to avoid the undesired adhesion of negatively charged DNA. 
The network density is readily controllable by varying the number of 
growth cycles of the nanowires as shown in Figure 1b, due to the </p>

<p>increased number of branched nanowires. Figure 1f shows the pore 
size distribution data measured from the cross-sectional SEM 
images. The average pore size decreases with increasing network 
density via the cycling nanowire growth. It should be noted that 
the present method allows users to define the spatial location, surface 
properties, density and pore size of the rigid network nanostructure 
within the microchannel, which are not attainable by other methods. 
Figure 2 and Supplementary Fig. S2 show the electropherogram 
data for various DNA mixtures, ranging from 100 bp-166 kbp, 
obtained using the fabricated rigid 3D network structure when vary-
ing the number of nanowire growth cycles. The clear dependence of 
the electropherogram data on the number of cycles can be seen. In 
the microchannel with 1-cycle growth nanowires (Type I), the DNA 
mixtures ranging from 10 kbp to 166 kbp were separable; in particu-
lar, the DNA mixture of T4-DNA and l-DNA was separable within 
just 3 s with an applied voltage field of 500 V/cm (see Supplementary 
Fig. S3), which is the fastest time reported to date. The DNA mixtures 
with DNA sizes smaller than 10 kbp could not be separated within 
the present experimental range, possibly due to the sparse nanowire 
density. The network structure with the 3-cycle growth nanowires 
(Type II) could well separate DNA mixtures down to 5 kbp. In the 
microchannel with the 5-cycle growth nanowires (Type III), the 
DNA mixtures down to 100 bp were separable within 20 s. Thus, 
the nanowire spatial density of the present network structure crit-
ically determined the electrophoretic behaviors of different sized 
DNA molecules. Denser network structures could separate smaller 
DNA molecules, i.e. there was a correlation between the network 
density and the separable DNA size range. Since the electrophoretic 
mobility determined the capability of DNA separation and analysis, 
we measured the mobility of DNA molecules that ranged from 
100 bp to 166 kbp with an applied DC electric field of 500 V/cm. 
Figure 2c shows the mobility data measured for the network struc-
ture with 1-, 3-or 5-cycle growth nanowires (see Supporting 
Information Movies-1, 2, and 3). These data clearly demonstrate 
the significant DNA size dependence on the electrophoretic mobility, 
and they also indicate the network density critically affects the size 
dependence. The shape of the mobility curves for 1-and 3-cycle 
growth nanowires was identical but shifted in absolute value of 
mobility (y axis), while the shape of the mobility curve for the 5-cycle 
growth nanowires was qualitatively different from other two curves 
and it shifted in absolute value of DNA size (x axis). This seems to 
indicate that there are two different separation mechanisms as to the 
change of the pore size in the present network structure. Thus, these 
experimental data highlight that the present network structure com-
posed of solid nanowires is capable of analyzing a wide range of DNA 
molecules within a short time. 
This DNA size dependence on the electrophoretic mobility is in 
effect similar to the trend for gel electrophoresis when varying the gel 
concentration </p>

<p>6-9 </p>

<p>. It is well known that a denser gel concentration can 
separate shorter DNA base pairs due to the decreased average pore 
sizes. In this sense, the spatial density dependence of the present rigid 
3D network structure in the DNA separation is quite similar to that 
of gel electrophoresis. However, there is a significant difference 
between the present rigid network structure and the soft gel, which 
is the capability of the former to separate and analyze relatively long 
DNA molecules within a short time. This is similar to the capability 
of nanostructure electrophoresis </p>

<p>11-12 </p>

<p>. Thus, the present rigid network 
structures possess the advantages of both the soft gel and the rigid 
lithography-defined nanostructures in DNA electrophoresis due to 
their tailored network structure density, namely the present network 
structure behaves as a hard gel. 
When compared with nanostructure electrophoresis, the present 
rigid 3D network structure can form 3D confined small pores. The 
present rigid 3D network structure can enhance the probability 
of collisions between small DNA molecules and a rigid object 
more than conventional lithographically defined nanostructures </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5252 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05252 </p>

<p>
including nanopillars and nanowalls can </p>

<p>15,17,38 </p>

<p>; these collisions might 
possibly enhance Ogston sieving effects (DNA size , the pore size; 
m u , exp(-N), where m u is the mobility and N is the DNA length, and 
m u , m u0 exp(-KC), where m u0 is the free solution mobility, K is 
the constant of proportionality, and C is the concentration of 
the network-forming matrix) for shorter DNA molecules (see 
Supplementary Figs. S4a and S4b) </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>. On the other hand, there would 
be an argument against Ogston sieving, which stems from the result 
that the time for transport through the pores (T transportation 5 d/ 
(m u E), where d is the pore size and E is the applied DC electric field) 
in the microchannel with the 5-cycle growth nanowires was shorter 
than the time for diffusion (T diffusion 5 d 
2 /D, where D is the diffusion </p>

<p>coefficient of the DNA molecules) (see Supplementary Fig. S4c) </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>. 
In addition, within the dense network structure, the deformed 
DNA molecules might collide with another rigid post before they 
contract, and this should affect the electrophoretic mobility and 
also the DNA size dependence on the mobility. Since these results 
are inconclusive about whether there is Ogston sieving in the 
matrix, with some evidences in favor and other evidences against 
the theoretical description, we can say that the presence of 3D con-
fined small rigid pores in the present network structure seems to be 
responsible for the ability to separate DNA mixtures of wider size 
ranges than conventional lithographically defined nanostructure 
electrophoresis. </p>

<p>Figure 1 | 3D nanowire network structure. (a) Schematic illustrations showing nanowire structure after: (I) 1-cycle growth; (II) 3-cycle growth, (III) 5-</p>

<p>cycle growth; and (lower row) the overall fabrication procedure. The microchannel and nanowire network structure are formed on fused silica substrate. 
(b) SEM images (scale bar, 1 mm) of the nanowire network structure showing: (I) 1-cycle growth; (II) 3-cycle growth; and (III) 5-cycle growth. The insets 
show vertical cross-sectional SEM images; scale bar, 1 mm. (c) Photograph of a fabricated device; scale bar, 1 cm. (d) SEM image of the nanowire network 
structure embedded in the microchannel; scale bar, 10 mm. (e) TEM images of the nanowire network structure; scale bars, 100 nm (left) and 50 nm 
(right). Black arrows highlight branched positions. (f) Pore size distribution of the nanowire network structure after (I) 1-cycle growth, (II) 3-cycle 
growth, and (III) 5-cycle growth. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5252 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05252 </p>

<p>
Based on only the pore sizes and the spatial network structure, the 
present network structure is quite similar to that of conventional gel 
structures </p>

<p>37,41,42 </p>

<p>. However, our single molecule imaging experiments 
revealed a difference between the present network structure and 
agarose gel regarding the electrophoretic behaviors of 38-kbp 
DNA, as shown in the video data of the Supporting Information 
Movie 4. Although their pore sizes are controlled to be similar for 
both structures, the DNA molecules in the nanowire network struc-
ture showed more frequent elongation and contraction by colliding 
with the rigid nanowire framework and faster migration than those 
in agarose gel. Thus, a scenario based on the pore size alone cannot 
explain the present results. One major difference between the present 
rigid network structure and the conventional gels is the stiffness of </p>

<p>the network structures. The present network structure is much more 
rigid than the conventional gel network structures </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>; for example, 
typically the Young's modulus of agarose gel is 0.1-1 MPa, whereas 
that of the solid nanowires is 100 6 20 GPa </p>

<p>44,45 </p>

<p>. Since the deforma-
tion of DNA molecules must be larger when softer DNA molecules 
collide with a stiffer object, collision with the rigid nanowire network 
structure must amplify the DNA deformation more than for the soft 
gel, considering the stiffness of the DNA molecules. Ou et al. 
46 have 
proposed that such mechanical collisions with rigid posts are as 
important as the large sized DNA separation mechanism. Thus, 
the different collision behaviors of DNA molecules might cause the 
different electrophoretic results between the present network struc-
ture and the gels, especially for separating mixtures of relatively long </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Separation and mobility data in the network structure. (a) Separation of 166 kbp DNA (20 ng/mL) and 48.5 kbp DNA (50 ng/mL) in </p>

<p>the nanowire network structure with the (I) 1-cycle growth nanowires, (II) 3-cycle growth nanowires, and (III) 5-cycle growth nanowires. The 
electropherogram was obtained at 3 mm from the entrance of the microchannel with the nanowire network structure. The applied DC electric field in the 
separation channel was 500 V/cm. (b) Separation of (I) 48.5 kbp DNA (20 ng/mL) and 10 kbp DNA (40 ng/mL) in the nanowire network structure with 
the 1-cycle growth nanowires at the applied DC electric field of 500 V/cm, (II) 10 kbp DNA (30 ng/mL) and 5 kbp DNA (30 ng/mL) in the nanowire 
network structure with the 3-cycle growth nanowires at the applied DC electric field of 500 V/cm, and (III) 1 kbp DNA (30 ng/mL) and 100 bp DNA 
(30 ng/mL) in the nanowire network structure with the 5-cycle growth nanowires at the applied DC electric field of 500 V/cm. The electropherogram was 
obtained at 3 mm from the entrance of the microchannel with the nanowire network structure. (c) Dependence of electrophoretic mobility on DNA size 
in the nanowire network structure with 1-cycle growth nanowires (red circles), 3-cycle growth nanowires (blue circles), and 5-cycle growth nanowires 
(green circles). Error bars show the standard deviation for a series of measurements (N 5 3). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5252 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05252 </p>

<p>
DNAs within a short time. The spatial controllability of the present 
network structure might also be another factor responsible for the 
faster analytical time due to the spatially concentrated DC electric 
field. Since the exact separation mechanism of wide-range DNA 
mixtures in the present network structure must be rather complex, 
such novel DNA electrophoretic behaviors are an interesting subject 
for theoreticians and experimentalists alike. </p>

<p>Next we explored the feasibility of using the present network 
structure to analyze and separate multicomponent DNA mixtures. 
Figure 3a shows the electropherogram data of a mixture composed of 
four components including T4-DNA (166 kbp), l-DNA (48.5 kbp), 
10 kbp-DNA and 5 kbp-DNA separated in the microchannel having 
a network structure formed with 3-cycle growth nanowires. The DC 
electric field of 500 V/cm was utilized in the electrophoresis. The 
multicomponent DNA mixtures are clearly separable using the pre-
sent network structure device and surprisingly within just 4 s, which 
is the fastest time reported so far </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>. By using a denser network struc-
ture formed with 5-cycle growth nanowires, we can analyze and 
separate the mixtures composed of even smaller sized DNA mole-
cules 100 bp-DNA, 1 kbp-DNA, 5 kbp-DNA, 20 kbp-DNA, and l-
DNA (48.5 kbp), as shown in Figure 3b. Under the DC electric field 
of 500 V/cm, the five differently sized DNA molecules are readily 
separated within only 7 s, which is also the fastest time reported so 
far. 
To further demonstrate the capability of the present network 
structures for analyzing and separating DNA molecules, we sepa-
rated l-DNA digested by HindIII, which consists of eight different 
DNA size fragments, using the microchannel having the network 
structure formed with 5-cycle growth nanowires (Figure 3c). 
Measurements were made under an applied DC electric field of 
500 V/cm. The DNA fragments were separated as six distinct peaks. 
Each peak was assigned to a DNA band as indicated in Figure 3c 
based on peak height and comparison with previous data </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>. 
Comparison with the previous top data showed the nanowire net-
work structure had much faster separation time, comparable theor-
etical plate number and theoretical plate number per column length, 
and lower resolution (Table 1). It should be emphasized that the 
present DNA separation is superior to that for the previous data in 
terms of the separation time. The present separation time is 13 s, 
which is much faster than the previous top time of 680 s obtained 
using a nanopillar structure </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>. Thus our experimental data prove that 
the present rigid 3D network structure can well analyze a wide range 
(100 bp-166 kbp) of multicomponent DNA mixtures within a short 
time, and the results are superior to those of any existing meth-
ods </p>

<p>5,6,11,12 </p>

<p>. Since the present concept based on the rigid 3D network 
structure in a microchannel has the potential to overcome the long-
standing weaknesses in the existing DNA electrophoresis methods, 
we expect it will open up new research avenues for not only analyzing 
DNA molecules but also for developing analytical methods for vari-
ous biological molecules, which are not attainable by existing 
methods. 
In summary, we have demonstrated a novel method based on the 
rigid 3D network structure comprised of solid branched nanowires 
within a microchannel, which enables analysis of DNA molecules for 
a much wider of DNA sizes (100 bp-166 kbp) than any previous 
methods within a much shorter time (13 s). The network density is 
readily tunable for the targeted DNA size range by controlling the 
number of cycles for nanowire growth only at the desired spatial 
position within a microchannel; this level of flexibility cannot be 
attained by other methodologies. The rigid 3D network structure 
with the spatial density control plays an important role in attaining 
better analysis of DNA molecules. Since the present method allows 
users to define the spatial location and density of the network nanos-
tructure within the microchannel, such spatial controllability will 
offer a new strategy to develop analytical methods not only for 
DNA molecules but also for other biological molecules. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Fabrication of cycling nanowire growth devices. To fabricate cycling nanowire 
growth devices, we have utilized a conventional photolithography process, electron 
beam lithography, and vapor-liquid-solid (VLS) growth technique for the nanowires 
(Supplementary Fig. S1). First, a Cr layer (250 nm thick) was deposited on a substrate 
by RF sputtering (SVC-700LRF, Sanyu Denshi); this layer was a mask for the dry 
etching process to fabricate a microchannel. Positive photoresist (TSMR V50, Tokyo </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Separation of multicomponent DNA mixtures in the network </p>

<p>structure. (a) Separation of 166 kbp DNA (20 ng/mL), 48.5 kbp DNA 
(20 ng/mL), 10 kbp DNA (20 ng/mL), and 5 kbp DNA (20 ng/mL) in the 
nanowire network structure with 3-cycle growth nanowires. The 
electropherogram was obtained at 1 mm from the entrance of the 
microchannel with the nanowire network structure. The applied DC 
electric field in the separation channel was 500 V/cm. (b) Separation of 
48.5 kbp DNA (20 ng/mL), 20 kbp DNA (20 ng/mL), 5 kbp DNA 
(20 ng/mL), 1 kbp DNA (20 ng/mL), and 100 bp DNA (40 ng/mL) in the 
nanowire network structure with 5-cycle growth nanowires. The 
electropherogram was obtained at 1 mm from the entrance of the 
microchannel with the nanowire network structure. The applied DC electric 
field in the separation channel was 500 V/cm. (c) Separation of lambda 
DNA digested by HindIII in the nanowire network structure with 5-cycle 
growth nanowires. The electropherogram was obtained at 3 mm from the 
entrance of the microchannel with the nanowire network structure. The 
applied DC electric field in the separation channel was 500 V/cm. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5252 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05252 </p>

<p>
Table 1 | Quantification of separation performance using theoretical plate number, height equivalent to a theoretical plate (HETP), theoretical plate number per column length, and resolution in 
Figure 3. Each standard deviation was obtained by 3 consecutive runs </p>

<p>Figure 3a </p>

<p>DNA size/bp </p>

<p>5 k </p>

<p>10 k </p>

<p>48.5 k </p>

<p>166 k </p>

<p>Theoretical plate number </p>

<p>5300 6 </p>

<p>820 </p>

<p>1400 6 </p>

<p>110 </p>

<p>730 6 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>2300 6 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>HETP (310 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>)/mm </p>

<p>1.9 6 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>7.1 6 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>14 6 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>4.6 6 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>Theoretical plate number per column length 
(310 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>)/plates m </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>5.3 6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.4 6 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.7 6 </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>2.3 6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>Resolution </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>5k-10k </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>10k-48.5k </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>48.5k-166k </p>

<p>0.66 6 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>0.35 6 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>0.91 6 </p>

<p>0.12 </p>

<p>Figure 3b </p>

<p>DNA size/bp </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>1 k </p>

<p>5 k </p>

<p>20 k </p>

<p>48.5 k </p>

<p>Theoretical plate number </p>

<p>710 6 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>990 6 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>1500 6 </p>

<p>130 </p>

<p>3700 6 </p>

<p>660 </p>

<p>4500 6 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>HETP (310 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>)/mm </p>

<p>14 6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>10 6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>6.5 6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>2.8 6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>2.2 6 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>Theoretical plate number per column length 
(310 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>)/plates m </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>0.7 6 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>1.0 6 </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>1.5 6 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>3.7 6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>4.5 6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>Resolution </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>100-1k </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>1k-5k </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>5k-20k </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>20k-48.5k </p>

<p>0.81 6 </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>1.01 6 </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>0.67 6 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.69 6 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>Figure 3c </p>

<p>DNA size/bp </p>

<p>125 or 564 </p>

<p>2.0&amp;2.3 k </p>

<p>4.4 k </p>

<p>6.6 k </p>

<p>9.4 k </p>

<p>23 k </p>

<p>Theoretical plate number </p>

<p>24000 6 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>12000 6 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>2300 6 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>6800 6 </p>

<p>900 </p>

<p>4100 6 </p>

<p>280 </p>

<p>2800 6 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>HETP (310 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>)/mm </p>

<p>1.2 6 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>2.6 6 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>13 6 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>4.5 6 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>7.4 6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>11 6 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>Theoretical plate number per column length 
(310 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>)/plates m </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>8.1 6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>3.9 6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.8 6 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>2.3 6 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>1.4 6 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.9 6 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>Resolution </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>125 or 564-2.0&amp;2.3k </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>2.0&amp;2.3k-4.4k </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>4.4k-6.6k </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>6.6k-9.4k </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>9.4k-23k </p>

<p>0.98 6 </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.26 6 </p>

<p>0.39 </p>

<p>0.52 6 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>0.29 6 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>0.32 6 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>Nano pillar* </p>

<p>DNA size/bp </p>

<p>125 or 564 </p>

<p>2.0&amp;2.3 k </p>

<p>4.4 k </p>

<p>6.6 k </p>

<p>9.4 k </p>

<p>23 k </p>

<p>Theoretical plate number </p>

<p>600-17000 </p>

<p>Theoretical plate number per column length 
(310 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>)/plates m </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>0.07-2.1 </p>

<p>Resolution </p>

<p>Not available </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>2.0&amp;2.3k-4.4k </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>4.4k-6.6k </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>6.6k-9.4k </p>

<p>Rs </p>

<p>9.4k-23k </p>

<p>0.93 </p>

<p>1.08 </p>

<p>1.04 </p>

<p>2.39 </p>

<p>*From 
Ref. 15. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5252 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05252 </p>

<p>
Ohka Kogyo Co.) was spin-coated on the Cr layer. Then the microchannel pattern 
with a width of 25 mm was formed by photolithography. After development of the 
resist, the patterned Cr area was etched by immersing in Cr etchant 
(H 2 O:Ce(NH 4 ) 2 (NO 3 ) 6 :HClO 4 , 8551055 by weight percent) for 5 min. The 
microchannel was formed by etching using reactive ion etching (RIE-10NR, Samco 
Co.) under CF 4 gas ambient. The microchannel depth was controlled to be 2 mm, 
which is larger than the radius of gyration of T4 DNA (970 nm). The inlet and outlet 
via holes (1.5 mm diameter) for the microfluidic system were drilled with an 
ultrasonic driller (SOM-121, Shinoda Co.). We also patterned the metal catalysts to 
define the spatial position of the nanowires within the microchannel. A Cr layer 
(10 nm thick) was deposited within the microchannel. Positive resist (ZEP520 A7, 
Zeon Corp.) was coated on the microchannel by spin-coating, and then the pattern 
was drawn by electron beam lithography (SPG-724, Sanyu Electron Co.). After 
developing the resist, the Cr layer pattern was removed with Cr etchant. An Au metal 
catalyst layer (3 nm thick) for nanowire growth was deposited within the 
microchannel by DC sputtering. And then the resist was lifted off using 
dimethylformamide, acetone and isopropanol, sequentially. The SnO 2 nanowires 
were fabricated in the microchannel by a pulse laser deposition (PLD) system. Details 
of the nanowire fabrication conditions can be found elsewhere </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>. To prepare 
nanowire branches, the Au catalyst particles were deposited along the nanowire by 
DC sputtering and the SnO 2 nanowires were grown cyclically using the PLD system to 
increase the density of nanowires in the microchannel. The Cr layer was lifted off with 
Cr etchant. It should be noted that a 40 nm layer of SiO 2 was deposited onto the SnO 2 
nanowires to avoid charge attraction of the negatively charged DNA molecules. 
Finally, the microchannel was sealed using a fused silica cover plate (130 mm thick) by 
the literature method </p>

<p>17,38 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>DNA observations using the cycling nanowire growth devices. The electrophoretic 
DNA mobility measurements in the nanowire array structure were done using T4, 
l, 20 kbp, 10 kbp, 5 kbp, 2 kbp, 1 kbp, 500 bp, and 100 bp DNA molecules 
(Nippon Gene Co., Ltd.) stained with the dye, YOYO-1 (Invitrogen), at a dye-to-
base pair ratio of 1515 contained in concentrated buffer solution (5 3 TBE; 
445 mM Tris-Borate and 10 mM EDTA, pH 8.2, Sigma-Aldrich, Inc.). An 
inverted fluorescent microscope (Eclipse TE-300, Nikon) equipped with a high 
voltage sequencer (HVS448-1500, Lab Smith) was used to apply the DC electric 
fields and a Hg lamp was used to observe fluorescently stained DNA molecules. 
Fluorescence images were captured with an EB-CCD camera (C7190-43, 
Hamamatsu Photonics K.K.) through a 10 3/1.40 NA objective lens (Nikon). The 
images were recorded on a DV tape (DSR-11, Sony) and then analyzed by image-
processing software (<rs id="software-0" type="software">Cosmos</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">32</rs>, Library, Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>DNA observations using the agarose gel. l-DNA digested Apa I, stained 
with YOYO-1 at a dye-to-base pair ratio of 1515, was observed in a 
polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS) microchannel (650 mm width; 50 mm height), 
which was filled with 5% agarose gel (Pulsed Field Certified Agarose, Bio-Rad 
Laboratories, Inc.) in 53 TBE. Under the DC electric field of 300 V/cm, l-DNA 
molecules were observed through a 1003/1.40 NA objective lens on an inverted 
fluorescent microscope (Eclipse TE-300) equipped with a high-voltage sequencer 
(HVS448-1500), 488 nm wavelength laser (FLS-488-20), and EB-CCD camera 
(C7190-43). The images were recorded on a DV tape (DSR-11) and then analyzed 
by image-processing software (<rs id="software-1" type="software">Cosmos</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">32</rs>). </p>



<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This research is supported by the Cabinet Office, Government of Japan and the Japan 
Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS) through the Funding Program for 
World-Leading Innovative R&amp;D on Science and Technology (FIRST Program), JSPS 
Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research (A) 24241050, JSPS Grant-in-Aid for Young Scientists </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5252 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05252 </p>



<p>
Author contributions </p>

<p>S.R., T. Yasui, T. Yanagida, T.K. and Y.B. designed the experiments. S.R., T. Yasui, 
T. Yanagida, K.N., M.K., A.K., M.G., H.Y., F.Z. and N.K. performed experiments. S.R., 
T. Yasui and T. Yanagida analyzed the data. T. Yasui and T. Yanagida wrote the paper. 
All authors discussed the results and commented on the manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Rahong, S. et al. Ultrafast and Wide Range Analysis of DNA 
Molecules Using Rigid Network Structure of Solid Nanowires. Sci. Rep. 4, 5252; 
DOI:10.1038/srep05252 (2014). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in 
this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated 
otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative 
Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder 
in order to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5252 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05252 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>