<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5098543" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Camellia mistletoe, Korthalsella japonica (Thunb.) Engl. 
(Loranthaceae), a parasitic plant that grows on the stems and 
branches of Camellia japonica L., Ilex integra (Thunb.), and 
Vaccinium bracteatum (Thunb.), is distributed throughout Ja-
pan, Republic of Korea, Taiwan, China, and India (Kim, 2007). 
This mistletoe species has a cactus-like morphology, grows 
up to 15 cm in length, and has a flat appearance. This spe-
cies has branches that are internodes to opposite with vari-
ous lengths and their degraded leaves are quite small and 
arranged in a snake scale-like pattern in two ranks (Devkota 
and Joshi, 2008). The phytochemical constituents of Camellia 
mistletoe are not as well known as those of other species, and 
a few reports have identified the presence of chrysoeriol-4ʼ-O-
glucoside, fatty acids, phytosterol, and oleanolic acid (Fuku-
naga et al., 1989; Hayashi et al., 1996). The extensive evalua-
tion of other mistletoe species, especially Viscum album L. var. 
coloratum has revealed various biological activities including </p>

<p>antitumor, antihypertensive, antibacterial, antiviral, antioxida-
tive, and cardiac effects (Hayashi et al., 1996; Karagoz et al., 
2003). However, the biological activity of Camellia mistletoe 
has not been reported yet. 
Inflammation is part of the immune response of tissues to 
various stimuli (Fontes et al., 2015). The inflammatory pro-
cess is associated with the activation of inflammatory cells 
such as macrophages, which release inflammatory mediators 
including nitric oxide (NO), cytokines, and chemokines (de la 
Fuente et al., 2012). Among these mediators, NO is an impor-
tant cellular molecule, which is involved in various inflamma-
tory processes including cell proliferation and differentiation, 
as well as the stimulation of numerous proteins and enzymes 
that are crucial for mediating inflammatory reactions (Predon-
zani et al., 2015; Schwentker et al., 2002). Furthermore, NO 
production is known to be regulated by inducible NO synthase 
(iNOS), which is the enzyme that catalyzes the production of 
NO from L-arginine (Koppula et al., 2012; Grimm et al., 2013). 
Another key enzyme involved in the inflammatory process is </p>

<p>* Corresponding Author </p>

<p>E-mail: ypjang@khu.ac.kr 
Tel: +82-2-961-9421, Fax: +82-2-966-3885 </p>

<p>Received Jan 27, 2016 Revised Mar 2, 2016 Accepted Mar 24, 2016 
Published Online Nov 1, 2016 
https://doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2016.019 </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016 The Korean Society of Applied Pharmacology </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Com-
mons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licens-
es/by-nc/4.0/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, 
and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>Anti-Inflammatory Properties of Flavone di-C-Glycosides as 
Active Principles of Camellia Mistletoe, Korthalsella japonica </p>

<p>Min Kyoung Kim 1 , Kwang Jun Yun 2 , Da Hae Lim 2 , Jinju Kim 2 and Young Pyo Jang 1,2, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Departments of 1 Life and Nanopharmaceutical Sciences, 2 Oriental Pharmaceutical Science, College of Pharmacy, 
Kyung Hee University, Seoul 02447, Republic of Korea </p>

<p>The chemical components and biological activity of Camellia mistletoe, Korthalsella japonica (Loranthaceae) are relatively un-
known compared to other mistletoe species. Therefore, we investigated the phytochemical properties and biological activity of this 
parasitic plant to provide essential preliminary scientific evidence to support and encourage its further pharmaceutical research 
and development. The major plant components were chromatographically isolated using high-performance liquid chromatography 
and their structures were elucidated using tandem mass spectrometry and nuclear magnetic resonance anlysis. Furthermore, 
the anti-inflammatory activity of the 70% ethanol extract of K. japonica (KJ) and its isolated components was evaluated using a 
nitric oxide (NO) assay and western blot analysis for inducible NO synthase (iNOS) and cyclooxygenase (COX)-2. Three flavone 
di-C-glycosides, lucenin-2, vicenin-2, and stellarin-2 were identified as major components of KJ, for the first time. KJ significantly 
inhibited NO production and reduced iNOS and COX-2 expression in lipopolysaccharide-stimulated RAW 264.7 cells at 100 mg/ 
mL while similar activity were observed with isolated flavone C-glycosides. In conclusion, KJ has a simple secondary metabolite 
profiles including flavone di-C-glycosides as major components and has a strong potential for further research and development 
as a source of therapeutic anti-inflammatory agents. </p>

<p>Key Words: Camellia mistletoe, Korthalsella japonica, Flavone di-C-glycosides, Anti-inflammation, iNOS, COX-2 </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Biomol Ther 24(6), 630-637 (2016) </p>

<p>631 </p>

<p>Kim et al. Anti-Inflammatory Principles of Camellia Mistletoe </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>the pro-inflammatory cyclooxygenase (COX)-2, which produc-
es prostaglandin E2 (PGE2) that mediates numerous biologi-
cal functions such as the regulation of immune responses and 
blood pressure (Seibert and Masferrer, 1994; Murakami and 
Ohigashi, 2007). Inflammation is known to be associated with 
degenerative brain diseases, obesity, metabolic syndrome, 
cardiovascular disease, diabetes, and cancer (Dubois, 2015). 
Therefore, the evaluation of the anti-inflammatory efficacy of 
natural products has become a frequent inclusion and choice 
in bioassays associated with drug research and development. 
In this study, the phytochemical profile of the 70% ethanol 
extract of K. japonica (KJ) was studied using ultra-perfor-
mance liquid chromatography-electrospray ionization-mass 
spectrometry (UPLC-ESI-MS) analysis and its major compo-
nents were further analyzed using high-performance liquid 
chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry (HPLC-MS/MS) 
and proton nuclear magnetic resonance ( 1 H-NMR) to eluci-
date their chemical structures. Furthermore, we explored the 
biological efficacy of KJ using an NO production assay in li-
popolysaccharide (LPS)-stimulated RAW 264.7 cells. Finally, 
the expressions of two key enzymes in the inflammatory pro-
cess, iNOS and COX-2, were also evaluated using western 
blot analysis to reveal the potential mechanisms underlying 
the anti-inflammatory activity of KJ. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Chemicals and materials </p>

<p>The acetonitrile, methanol, and formic acid used were of 
HPLC grade and supplied by Duksan Pure Chemicals (Seoul, 
Republic of Korea). The high-purity nitrogen and argon gas-
ses for the UPLC as well as UPLC-ESI-MS and HPLC-MS/ 
MS analyses, respectively were provided by Shinyang Oxy-
gen Co (Seoul, Republic of Korea). The samples for analysis 
were filtered using a 0.2-mm (PVDF) filter (Advantec, Dublin, 
CA, USA) before being injected into the UPLC or HPLC sys-
tem. The dexamethasone (≥97%) was purchased from Sigma-
Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). The LPS used was from Esche-
richia coli 0127:B8) and penicillin-streptomycin were obtained 
from Sigma-Aldrich. The Griess reagent was purchased from 
Promega (Madison, WI, USA) while Dulbecco's modified Ea-
gle's medium (DMEM) was a product of WelGene (Seoul, Re-
public of Korea). The fetal bovine serum (FBS) was supplied 
by Atlas Biologicals (Fort Collins, CO, USA), the primary an-
tibodies against iNOS and COX-2 were obtained from Santa 
Cruz Biotechnology (Dallas, TX, USA), and the protein assay 
kit was provided by Bio-Rad (Hercules, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Plant material </p>

<p>The K. japonica herbal medicine samples used in this study 
were certified by the Korea Food and Drug Administration 
(KFDA) and purchased from Seoul Herbal Medicine Mart, 
Seoul, Republic of Korea in March 2013. The taxonomical 
authenticity was confirmed by one of the authors (Jang YP) 
by comparing its organoleptic characteristics with those in ref-
erence books (Lee, 1996), and a voucher specimen (KHUP-
0803) was deposited at the Herbarium of Korean Traditional 
Herbal Medicines located at the College of Pharmacy, Kyung 
Hee University, Seoul, Republic of Korea. </p>

<p>Extraction and isolation </p>

<p>The dried leaves, stems, and branches of K. japonica (143 g) 
were reflux extracted four times with 70% ethanol (1.5 L) for 2 
h. The extract was filtered using membrane filter paper (Hyun-
dai Micro Co., Seoul, Republic of Korea), and the filtrate was 
concentrated in vacuo at 50°C using a rotary vacuum evapo-
rator (EYELA, Tokyo, Japan). A dark brown powder (43 g) was 
obtained, and the final yield was calculated as 30% of the dried 
plant material. The extract obtained (KJ) was subsequently 
analyzed using a Diaion HP-20 column (7×75 cm, Sigma-Al-
drich), with a gradient elution system consisting of acetonitrile/ 
water (H2O) run at 0:100→15:85→40:60→100:0, at 10 L per 
gradient. A 15% acetonitrile fraction (3.5 g) was subsequently 
separated using a preparative HPLC system to yield flavone 
C-glycosides. Then, 1 mL of the 0.45-mm PVDF-filtered 15% 
acetonitrile fraction (100 mg/mL) was injected repeatedly into 
a YMC-Pack ODS-A reversed-phase HPLC column (20×250 
mm, 120 Å, 5 mm, YMC Co., Kyoto, Japan). The flow rate was 
10 mL/min and the ultraviolet visible (UV/Vis) detection wave-
length was set at 330 nm. The mobile phase was composed 
of methanol (MeOH) in H2O run using the following gradient 
schedule: 30% (0-10 min), 30-40% (10-25 min), 40-100% 
(25-35 min), 100% (35-45 min) and 100-30% (45-50 min). 
The peak 1, 2, and 3 (KJ-1, KJ-2, and KJ-3; 10, 24, and 22 
mg, respectively) were collected between 15.5 and 20.5, 20.5 
and 24, and 24 and 26.5 min, respectively. The purity of the 
three compounds was ≥95% as determined by the UPLC and 
NMR analyses. </p>

<p>UPLC-ESI-MS analysis </p>

<p>The UPLC-ESI-MS analysis was carried out using an Wa-
ters Acquity UPLC H-Class system operated with the Empow-
er software (Milford, MA, USA) and AccuTOF ® single-reflection 
time-of-flight mass spectrometer with an ESI operated using 
the <rs id="software-1" type="software">Mass Center system</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 1.3.7b</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">JEOL</rs>, Tokyo, Japan). 
The photodiode array (PDA) detector was recorded between 
210-450 nm and the monitoring wavelength was set to 330 
nm. The Brownlee SPP C18 column (2.1 mm×75 mm i.d., 2.7 
mm, PerkinElmer, Waltham, MA, USA) used was placed in a 
column oven set at 25°C. The KJ sample was dissolved in 
15% acetonitrile to a final concentration of 30 mg/mL, filtered 
using a 0.2-mm PVDF filter, and then injected into the UPLC 
system with an injection volume of 1 mL and flow rate of 0.25 
mL/min. The mobile phase was composed of a linear gradi-
ent of acetonitrile in H2O acidified with acetic acid (0.1%) and 
run as follows: 2-5% (0-2.5 min), 5-15% (2.5-10 min), 15-20% 
(10-15 min), 20-50% (15-25 min), 50-100% (25-27 min), 100% 
(27-37 min), and 100-2% (37-38 min). The operating param-
eters of the mass spectrometer were set as follows. In the 
negative ion mode, the needle electrode was set to 2000 V; 
nitrogen gas was used as the nebulizer and desolvating agent 
at flow rates of 1 and 3 L/min, respectively; and the desolvat-
ing chamber and orifice 1 temperatures were 250 and 80°C, 
respectively. The atmospheric pressure interface potentials 
for the orifice 1, ring lens, and orifice 2 were 80, 10, 5 V, re-
spectively. The mass scale calibration was performed using a 
Yokudelna calibration kit (JEOL) for ensuring accurate mass 
measurements while the scan range of the MS acquisition 
was set at m/z 100-2000. </p>

<p>HPLC-MS/MS analysis of flavone di-C-glycosides </p>

<p>The HPLC-MS/MS analysis was carried out using an Agi-</p>



<p>https://doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2016.019 </p>

<p>lent Technologies 1200 series HPLC (Santa Clara, CA, USA) 
coupled to a Waters Quattro Micro TM atmospheric pressure 
ionization (API) mass spectrometer equipped with an ESI in-
terface. A Brownlee SPP C18 column (2.1 mm×75 mm i.d., 
2.7 mm) was used, and the mobile phase was 5% acetonitrile 
in H2O acidified with 0.1% acetic acid run at a flow rate of 0.3 
mL/min. The KJ was dissolved in 5% acetonitrile to a final con-
centration of 30 mg/mL, filtered using a 0.45-mm PVDF filter, 
and then injected at a volume of 30 mL. The operating param-
eters of the mass spectrometer were as follows. In the nega-
tive ion mode, source and desolvation temperatures were 120 
and 350°C, respectively; capillary voltage was 3000 V; cone 
voltage was 47 V; and collision energy was 30, 50 V. Nitrogen 
gas was used as the nebulizing and desolvation agents with 
flow rates of 50 and 350 L/h, respectively. The mass scan was 
set from m/z 100-800. The MS/MS acquisition was scanned 
at the same mass range to detect the daughter ions and the 
MassLynx software version 4.1 was used to operate the MS 
instruments. </p>

<p>NMR study of flavone di-C-glycosides </p>

<p>The NMR spectra were recorded and measured using a 
Bruker Avance 500 MHz spectrometer (Billerica, MA, USA). 
Deuterated dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO-d6, Sigma-Aldrich) was 
used as the NMR solvent and tetramethylsilane (TMS, Sigma-
Aldrich) was the internal standard (IS). The samples were 
placed in 5-mm NMR sample tubes (Sigma-Aldrich), and the 
analysis was performed at an elevated temperature of 60°C to 
improve the spectral resolution. </p>

<p>Cell culture and cell viability assay </p>

<p>RAW 264.7, a murine monocyte/macrophage cell line, was 
purchased from the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC) 
and cultured in DMEM supplemented with heat-inactivated 
FBS and 1% penicillin-streptomycin under an atmosphere of 
5% CO2 at 37°C and 100% humidity. The cytotoxicity of KJ 
and isolated flavone glycosides was evaluated against RAW 
264.7 cells was using the 3-(4, 5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2, 5-di-
phenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) assay (Denizot and Lang, 
1986). Briefly, the cells were plated into 96-well plates at a 
density of 1×10 5 cells/mL in fresh medium. After incubating 
overnight, the medium was replaced with FBS-free medium 
containing 1 mg/mL of dexamethasone and graded concen-
trations of KJ and the flavone glycosides (0, 1, 10, and 100 
mg/mL). After 25 h incubation, 50 mL of a 2 mg/mL MTT solu-
tion was added to each well, incubated for a further 4 h, and 
then 100 mL of DMSO was added to each well to dissolve the 
formazan crystals. The optical density of the resulting reaction 
solution was measured using an enzyme-linked immunosor-
bent assay (ELISA) plate reader at 570 nm (Bio-Rad). </p>

<p>NO assay </p>

<p>To study the effects of KJ and the isolated flavone glyco-</p>

<p>sides on NO production, RAW cells were seeded onto 24-well 
plates at a density of (1×10 5 cells/mL) and incubated over-
night. Then, the medium was replaced with FBS-free medium 
containing 1 mg/mL dexamethasone or graded concentrations 
of KJ or the flavone glycosides (1, 10, and 100 mg/mL). After 
1 h, the cells were stimulated with 1 mg/mL LPS for 24 h, and 
then the NO concentration of the supernatant was measured 
using the Griess reagent (Sigma-Aldrich). The optical density 
was measured using an ELISA plate reader at 540 nm. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>RAW cells were seeded into 6-well plates at a density of 1× 
10 5 cells/mL, incubated overnight, and then the medium was 
replaced with FBS-free medium with 1 mg/mL dexamethasone 
or three graded concentrations of KJ (1, 10, and 100 mg/mL). 
After 1 h, the cells were treated with 1 mg/mL LPS for 6 h and 
then the medium was discarded. Then, radioimmunoprecipita-
tion assay (RIPA) buffer containing a proteinase inhibitor was 
used to lyse the cells and extract the cell protein. The protein 
concentration was subsequently measured using a Bio-Rad 
protein assay kit. The lysates (20 mg/lane) were resolved us-
ing sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophore-
sis (SDS-PAGE) and transferred onto a nitrocellulose mem-
brane, which was incubated overnight with primary antibodies 
against β-actin, iNOS, and COX-2 (1:1000 in Tris-buffered 
saline plus Tween (TBS-T). Then, the membrane was washed 
thrice with TBS-T buffer and incubated with secondary anti-
bodies for 2 h. After washing, the protein bands in the mem-
brane were detected using an enhanced chemiluminescence 
western blot analysis system (abClon, Seoul, Republic of Ko-
rea) as described previously (Lee et al., 2013). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The statistical analysis of the data was carried out using 
the GraphPad Prism version 4.00 (GraphPad Software Inc., 
La Jolla, CA, USA). The data are presented as means ± stan-
dard error of the mean (SEM), and multiple comparisons were 
performed using a one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA). 
Furthermore, differences with p&lt;0.05 were considered statisti-
cally significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The optimal chromatographic profile of the KJ was estab-
lished using UPLC analysis and three major peaks were iden-
tified using UPLC-ESI-MS analysis. The UV/Vis spectra of the 
three major peaks were characterized with two absorption 
maxima around 270 and 350 nm that are characteristic of fla-
vonoids (Fig. 1A). The chromatogram of the chemical profile of 
the total KJ was relatively simple and the three flavonoid-like 
compounds were the major components that were identified 
by the peak heights and areas of the three peaks. When the </p>

<p>Biomol Ther 24(6), 630-637 (2016) </p>

<p>Table 1. Observed and calculated mass numbers of major peaks of Korthalsella japonica 70% ethanol extract (KJ) </p>

<p>Peak No. 
ID 
Rt (min) 
Theoretical mass [M-H] -
Observed mass [M-H] -Mass difference (mmu) Molecular formula </p>

<p>1 
KJ-1 
17.46 
609.14556 
609.13926 
-6.30 
C 27 H 29 O 16 
2 
KJ-2 
18.58 
593.15064 
593.15446 
3.82 
C 27 H 29 O 15 
3 
KJ-3 
18.90 
623.16121 
623.16772 
6.51 
C 28 H 31 O 16 </p>



<p>Kim et al. Anti-Inflammatory Principles of Camellia Mistletoe </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>chromatogram was monitored using other short wavelengths 
such as 220 and 254 nm, the profile did not vary significantly 
(data not shown). The retention time, as well as the observed </p>

<p>and theoretical mass numbers with their proposed molecular 
formulae is listed in Table 1. 
The chemical structure of the isolated compounds from KJ </p>

<p>Fig. 1. (A) Representative ultra-performance liquid chromatography (UPLC) chromatogram of 70% ethanol extract of Korthalsella japonica </p>

<p>(KJ) monitored at 330 nm and (B) and tandem mass spectrometry (MS/MS) spectra of three peaks in negative ionization mode. Peaks 1-3 
were identified as lucenin-2 (KJ-1), vicenin-2 (KJ-2) and stellarin-2 (KJ-3). </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.10 
AU </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>7.00 
14.00 
21.00 
28.00 
35.00 </p>

<p>330 nm </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 3 </p>

<p>Minutes </p>

<p>17.464 Peak 1 </p>

<p>269.8 
349.6 </p>

<p>213.0 213.0 </p>

<p>18.582 Peak 2 </p>

<p>270.5 
335.3 </p>

<p>216.0 216.0 </p>

<p>18.902 Peak 3 </p>

<p>270.5 
347.1 </p>

<p>214.8 214.8 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>[(M-H)-120] 
489.13 
100 </p>

<p>% 
1 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>0 
400 
500 
600 
m/z </p>

<p>[(M-H)-120-90] 
399.33 </p>

<p>[(M-H)-90] 
519.02 </p>

<p>[M-H] 
609.18 
[(M-H)-120-120] 
369.09 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>% 
3 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>0 
400 
500 
600 
m/z </p>

<p>[(M-H)-120-90] 
413.26 
[(M-H)-90] 
533.37 </p>

<p>[M-H] 
623.02 </p>

<p>[(M-H)-120-120] 
383.07 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>% 
2 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>0 
400 
500 
600 
m/z </p>

<p>[(M-H)-120-90] 
383.37 </p>

<p>[(M-H)-90] 
503.27 </p>

<p>[M-H] 
593.03 </p>

<p>[(M-H)-120-120] 
353.34 </p>

<p>[(M-H)-120] 
473.27 </p>

<p>HO 
HO </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH O </p>

<p>HOH C </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>HO 
HO </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>[(M-H)-120] 
m/z 489 </p>

<p>[(M-H)-90] 
m/z 519 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>CH OH </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>HO 
HO </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH O </p>

<p>HOH C </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>HO 
HO </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>[(M-H)-120] 
m/z 473 </p>

<p>[(M-H)-90] 
m/z 503 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>CH OH </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>HO 
HO </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OCH 3 </p>

<p>OH O </p>

<p>HOH C </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>HO 
HO </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>[(M-H)-120] 
m/z 503 </p>

<p>[(M-H)-90] 
m/z 533 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>CH OH </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>[(M-H)-120] 
503.01 </p>



<p>https://doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2016.019 </p>

<p>were elucidated by comparing their physicochemical data in-
cluding UV/Vis spectra, MS and MS/MS data, and 1 H-NMR 
spectra with those previously described in the literature (Su-
zuki et al., 2003; Xie et al., 2003; Erel et al., 2011). The com-
pounds were identified as lucenin-2, vicenin-2, and stellarin-2 
(KJ-1, KJ-2, and KJ-3, respectively). The 1 H-NMR showed 
signal broadening at an ambient temperature owing to the 
limited rotation of the C-glycosidic bond, which was sterically 
hindered by the bulky ortho-substituents and, therefore, the 
experiments were performed at an elevated temperature of 
60°C to improve spectral resolution (Kumazawa et al., 2001). 
Compound 1 (KJ-1) was obtained as a dark green amor-
phous powder and the ESI-TOF-MS gave the molecular for-
mula C27H30O16. The UV/Vis spectrum of KJ-1 showed absorp-
tion maxima at 269.8 and 349.6 nm in CH3CN while the MS/ 
MS spectra in the negative ionization mode showed the de-
protonated molecular ion at m/z 609 [M-H] -and product ions 
at m/z 519 [(M-H)-90] -, m/z 489 [(M-H)-120] -, 399 [(M-H)-120-
90] -also analyzed as (286 [luteolin, aglycone]+113) -and 369 
([M-H]-120-120) -(Fig. 1B-1). The cross-ring cleavage of the 
hexose residue of the C-glycoside yielded numerous charac-
teristic product ions such as m/z [(M-H)-90] -, [(M-H)-120] -loss-
es pattern (Vukics and Guttman, 2010). The MS/MS results 
suggest the presence of a luteolin (286)+hexose (162)+hex-
ose (162) structure. The 1 H NMR at 60°C revealed a 3ʼ,4ʼ,5,7-
tetra-hydroxyl-substituted flavone from the aromatic spin sys-
tems: δH 7.43 (s), 6.83 (d, J=8.1 Hz), and 7.46 (d, J=8.0 Hz), 
corresponding to H-2ʼ, H-5ʼ, and H-6ʼ, respectively, and δH 6.57 
(s) corresponding to H-3 (Table 2). The hexosides were as-
signed as C-β-D-glucosides because the characteristic chemi-
cal shift and coupling constant were identical with that found </p>

<p>in the literature (Erel et al., 2011). The hexoside linkage was 
also assigned to C-6 and C-8 because the vicinal coupling 
constants were 8.0-9.7 Hz, including the anomeric protons at 
δH 4.75 (d, J=9.6 Hz) of 6-C-β-Glc and δH 4.86 (d, J=9.7 Hz) of 
8-C-β-Glc, and H-2ʼʼ at δH 3.77 (brs) of 6-C-β-Glc and δH 3.74 
(brs) of 8-C-β-Glc. Therefore, compound 1 was elucidated as 
luteolin 6,8-di-C-β-D-glucopyranoside (lucenin-2). 
Compound 2 (KJ-2) was obtained as a yellow green amor-
phous powder and the ESI-TOF-MS gave the molecular for-
mula C27H30O15. The UV/Vis spectrum of KJ-2 showed absorp-
tion maxima at 270.5 and 335.3 nm in CH3CN. The one less 
oxygen of the molecular formula compare to KJ-1 and the 
hypsochromic shift of its long wavelength absorption maxima 
indicated that KJ-2 had an apigenin aglycone moiety, which 
had one less hydroxyl group compared to luteolin. The MS/MS 
spectra of KJ-2 in the negative ionization mode showed the 
precursor ion at m/z 593 [M-H] -and product ions at m/z 503 
([M-H]-90) -, m/z 473 ([M-H]-120) -, 383 ([M-H]-120-90) -also 
analyzed as (270 [apigenin, aglycone]+113) -and 353 ([M-H]-
120-120) -. The cross-ring cleavage of the hexose residue of 
the C-glycoside was also revealed [19]. The MS/MS results 
suggest the presence of an apigenin (270)+hexose (162)+hex-
ose (162) structure (Fig. 1B-2). The 1 H NMR revealed a 4ʼ,5, 
7-tri-hydroxyl-substituted flavone from the aromatic spin sys-
tems: the chemical shift at δH 7.92 (d, J=8.7 Hz) and 6.88 (d, 
J=8.8 Hz) corresponded to H-2ʼ,6ʼ and H-3ʼ,5ʼ, respectively. 
The proton at δH 6.52 (s) corresponded to H-3 (Table 2). The 
hexosides were assigned as C-β-D-glucosides because the 
characteristic chemical shift and coupling constants were 
identical to those found in the literature (Xie et al., 2003). The 
hexoside linkage was also assigned to C-6 and C-8 because </p>

<p>Biomol Ther 24(6), 630-637 (2016) </p>

<p>Table 2. Proton nuclear magnetic resonance ( 1 H-NMR, 500 MHz, dimethyl sulfoxide, DMSO-d6) data of flavone C-glycosides isolated from 70% ethanol </p>

<p>extract of Korthalsella japonica (KJ) </p>

<p>Position of proton 
KJ-1 δ H (J in Hz) 
KJ-2 δ H (J in Hz) 
KJ-3 δ H (J in Hz) </p>

<p>3 
6.57 s 
6.52 s 
6.69 s 
2ʹ 
7.43 s 
7.92 d (8.7) 
7.53 s 
3ʹ 
-
6.88 d (8.8) 
-
5ʹ 
6.83 d (8.1) 
6.88 d (8.8) 
6.90 d (8.0) 
6ʹ 
7.46 d (8.0) 
7.92 d (8.7) 
7.59 d (8.1) 
3ʹ-OMe 
-
-
3.89 s 
6-glucose 
1ʹʹ 
4.75 d (9.6) 
4.69 d (9.9) 
4.71 d (9.7) 
2ʹʹ 
3.77 bs 
3.90 brs 
3.88 brs 
3ʹʹ 
3.37* 
3.25* 
3.29* 
4ʹʹ 
3.37* 
3.26* 
3.31* 
5ʹʹ 
3.32* 
3.23* 
3.26* 
6ʹʹ 
3.66* 
3.65 dd (2.2, 11.5) 
3.67 dd (2.3, 11.4) 
3.59 dd (5.1, 11.8) 
3.54 dd (5.9, 11.2) 
3.53 dd (4.4, 11.7) 
8-glucose 
1ʹʹ 
4.86 d (9.7) 
4.84 d (9.9) 
4.88 d (9.8) 
2ʹʹ 
3.74 bs 
3.83 t (9.2) 
3.82 brs 
3ʹʹ 
3.41* 
3.34* 
3.35* 
4ʹʹ 
3.41* 
3.35* 
3.36* 
5ʹʹ 
3.36* 
3.30* 
3.32* 
6ʹʹ 
3.69* 
3.73* 
3.72 dd (2.1, 11.4) 
3.59 dd (5.1, 11.8) 
3.54 dd (5.9, 11.2) 
3.53 dd (4.4, 11.7) </p>

<p>*Signal pattern was unclear due to overlapping; KJ-1, lucenin-2; KJ-2, vicenin-2; KJ-3, stellarin-2. </p>



<p>Kim et al. Anti-Inflammatory Principles of Camellia Mistletoe </p>



<p>the vicinal coupling constants were 8.7-9.9 Hz, including the 
anomeric protons at δH 4.69 (d, J=9.9 Hz) of 6-C-β-Glc and δH 
4.84 (d, J=9.9 Hz) of 8-C-β-Glc, and H-2ʼʼ at δH 3.90 (brs) of 
6-C-β-Glc and δH 3.83 (t, J=9.2 Hz) of 8-C-β-Glc. Therefore, 
compound 2 was elucidated as apigenin 6,8-di-C-β-D-gluco-
pyranoside (vicenin-2). 
Compound 3 (KJ-3) was obtained as a yellow-green amor-
phous powder and the ESI-TOF-MS gave the molecular for-
mula C28H32O16. The UV/Vis spectrum of KJ-3 showed absorp-
tion maxima at 270.5 and 347.1 nm in CH3CN. The MS/MS 
spectra in the negative ionization mode showed the precursor 
ion at m/z 623 [M-H] -and product ions at m/z 533 [(M-H)-90] -, 
m/z 503 [(M-H)-120] -, 413 [(M-H)-120-90] -also analyzed as 
(300 [chrysoeriol, aglycone]+113) -and 383 ([M-H]-120-120) -. 
The MS/MS results suggest the presence of a chrysoeriol 
(300)+hexose (162)+hexose (162) structure (Fig. 1B-3). The </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>H NMR revealed a 3ʼ,4ʼ,5,7-tetra-hydroxyl-substituted flavone 
from the aromatic spin systems: chemical shift at δH 7.53 (s), 
6.90 (d, J=8.0 Hz) and 7.59 (d, J=8.1 Hz) corresponding to </p>

<p>H-2ʼ, H-5ʼ, and H-6ʼ, respectively. The proton at δH 6.69 (s) 
corresponded to H-3 (Table 2). The hexosides were also as-
signed as C-β-D-glucosides because of the characteristic 
chemical shift and coupling constant (Xie et al., 2003; Erel 
et al., 2011). Similar to the other compounds, the hexosides 
linkage was assigned to C-6 and C-8. Compound 3 was identi-
fied as chrysoeriol 6,8-di-C-β-D-glucopyranoside (stellarin-2). 
All these flavone C-glycosides were identified in the Camellia 
mistletoe for the first time. 
The effect of KJ on cell viability was studied using an MTT 
assay before the evaluation of its biological efficacy. Cells in-
cubated with varying concentrations of KJ (1, 10, and 100 mg/ 
mL) for 25 h did not show any significant cytotoxicity in the 
MTT assay up to the highest concentration of 100 mg/mL (Fig. 
2A). We chose to perform anti-inflammatory assays on the 
extract of this species because other mistletoe species have 
known anti-inflammatory effects (Patil et al., 2011; Bock et al., 
2014). The NO production level was determined as a marker 
of the inflammatory response and was measured using the </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 
Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>0 
KJ ( g/mL) 
Dex (1 </p>

<p>m 
mg/mL) </p>

<p>1 10 100 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 
Nitric oxide ( M) m </p>

<p>0 
LPS (1 g/mL) 
KJ ( g/mL) 
Dex (1 </p>

<p>m 
m 
mg/mL) </p>

<p>1 10 100 </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>LPS (1 g/mL) 
m 
KJ ( g/mL) 
Dex (1 g/mL) </p>

<p>m 
m </p>

<p>1 
10 100 </p>

<p>i-NOS </p>

<p>COX-2 </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>i-NOS/ ratio b-actin </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 
LPS (1 g/mL) 
KJ ( g/mL) 
Dex (1 </p>

<p>m 
m 
mg/mL) </p>

<p>1 10 100 </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>COX-2/ ratio 
b-actin </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Effects of 70% ethanol extract of Korthalsella japonica (KJ) on (A) cell viability, (B) NO production, (C) inducible NO synthase (iNOS), </p>

<p>and cyclooxygenase (COX)-2 protein levels in lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-stimulated RAW 264.7 cells. Dexamethasone (Dex, 1 mg/mL) was 
positive control. Values are means ± standard error of the mean (SEM). Statistical analysis, using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA); 
*p&lt;0.05 and ***p&lt;0.001. </p>



<p>https://doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2016.019 </p>

<p>Griess reagent. RAW 264.7 cell stimulated with LPS (1 mg/ 
mL) exhibited a significant increase in NO production up to 
62.6 ± 0.7 mM from the basal level of 0.18 ± 0.1 mM (1×10 5 
cells/mL in a 12-well plate, n=6). As shown in Fig. 2B, the high-
dose groups (10 and 100 mg/mL) of KJ showed a significant 
reduction in NO production (11.6 and 71.7%, respectively) 
compare to the LPS-stimulated group. However, KJ reduced 
NO production by only 1.8% at the low dose of 1 mg/mL. Dexa-
methasone (1 mg/mL) as the positive control also inhibited NO 
production significantly and the potency was slightly less than 
that of KJ 100 mg/mL. Considering that KJ is a crude plant ex-
tract, which likely contains a mixture of numerous metabolites, 
the anti-inflammatory efficacy of KJ was relatively comparable 
to that of dexamethasone. 
Two key enzymes involved in the inflammatory process, 
iNOS and COX-2, were quantitated using western blot analy-
sis to evaluate the inhibitory effects of KJ on their expression. 
Compare to the negative control, the LPS-stimulated group 
showed significantly increased levels of iNOS and COX-2 
(Fig. 2C). Compared with the LPS-stimulated group, the ex-
pression of iNOS was significantly reduced only in the 100 mg/ 
mL KJ group to 42.9%. In contrast, COX-2 was significantly 
reduced in all KJ-treated groups (1, 10, and 100 mg/mL) with 
rates of 12.6, 35.3, and 75.1%, respectively. Dexamethasone 
(1 mg/mL) also reduced iNOS and COX-2 expression to 66.2 
and 69.5%, respectively. The results showed that the anti-
inflammatory activity of KJ was directly linked to the inhibition 
of the expression these two key enzymes involved in NO pro-
duction and inflammatory responses. Further investigations of 
other mechanisms underlying the anti-inflammatory activity of 
KJ need to be performed including determination of the possi-
ble involvement of nuclear factor kappa-light-chain-enhancer 
of activated B cells (NF-κB) activation and modulation by its 
subunit (Surh et al., 2001). </p>

<p>To identify the active principles of mediating the anti-inflam-
matory Camellia mistletoe, the isolated flavone C-glycosides 
were evaluated for their inhibitory activities on NO production. 
The cytotoxicity of KJ-1, KJ-2, and KJ-3 was evaluated us-
ing an MTT assay before the NO assay was performed. As 
shown in Fig 3A, none of the flavone C-glycosides showed 
any significant cytotoxicity up to a concentration of 100 mg/ 
mL. Furthermore, all three flavone C-glycosides significantly 
inhibited NO production at 100 mg/mL while KJ-2 and KJ-3 
showed concentration-dependency (Fig. 3B). Although the fla-
vone glycosides did not show a higher potency than the crude 
KJ did, their significant inhibition of NO production and relative 
contents in the UPLC chromatogram suggests that these fla-
vone C-glycosides are active principles of Camellia mistletoe. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>To the best of our knowledge, this study is the first report 
of the phytochemical profile and anti-inflammatory activity of 
Camellia mistletoe. The 70% ethanol extract of K. japonica 
showed a simple chemical profile in the UPLC analysis. The 
major components and active principles of KJ were identi-
fied as the flavone di-C-glucosides, lucenin-2, vicenin-2, and 
stellarin-2. Flavonoid C-glycosides have chemical structures 
with highly polar sugar portions and phenolic hydroxyl groups. 
However, it was previously demonstrated that these com-
pounds could be absorbed unchanged and underwent entero-
hepatic recirculation in addition to hydrolysis, reduction, and 
conjugation to form a bioavailable glucuronide (Angelino et al., 
2013). Previous studies on the biological efficacy of isolated 
flavonoid C-glycosides have shown antibacterial activity (Sor-
bo et al., 2004), antioxidant property (Barreca et al., 2011), 
anti-inflammatory activity (Erel et al., 2011), and anti-hepa-</p>

<p>Biomol Ther 24(6), 630-637 (2016) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 
Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>0 
KJ-1 ( g/mL) 
m 
1 10 100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 
Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>0 
KJ-2 ( g/mL) 
m 
1 10 100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 
Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>0 
KJ-3 ( g/mL) 
m 
1 10 100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 
Nitric oxide ( M) </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>0 
LPS (1 g/mL) 
KJ-1 ( g/mL) 
m 
m 
1 10 100 </p>

<p>** 
*** </p>

<p>*** 
* </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 
Nitric oxide ( M) </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>0 
LPS (1 g/mL) 
KJ-2 ( g/mL) 
m 
m 
1 10 100 </p>

<p>*** 
*** 
*** </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 
Nitric oxide ( M) </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>0 
LPS (1 g/mL) 
KJ-3 ( g/mL) 
m 
m 
1 10 100 </p>

<p>* 
*** </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Effects of flavone di-C-glycosides on (A) cell viability and (B) nitric oxide (NO) production (B) in lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-stimulated </p>

<p>RAW 264.7 cells. Statistical analysis, one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA); *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, and ***p&lt;0.001. </p>



<p>Kim et al. Anti-Inflammatory Principles of Camellia Mistletoe </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>totoxic activity (El-Toumy et al., 2011). However, anti-inflam-
matory activity of these compounds against NO pathway was 
revealed for the first time in this study. Our investigation of the 
biological activity of KJ revealed that the treatment with this 
extract significantly inhibited NO production in LPS-stimulated 
RAW cells. NO is one of the main inflammatory mediators and 
has important functions as a signaling molecule in various 
physiological processes (Schwentker et al., 2002). Therefore, 
based on its obvious effects on NO production, KJ can be con-
sidered as a potential natural resource for the development of 
anti-inflammatory agents. Moreover, the significant inhibition 
of iNOS and COX-2 expression by KJ confirmed the biological 
efficacy of this unfamiliar mistletoe species on various inflam-
matory mediators, and possibly against associated disease. 
Collectively, these results suggest that Camellia mistletoe has 
the potential to be the source of active compounds for devel-
opment as useful pharmaceutical agents targeting inflamma-
tory diseases. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant (No.: KHU-20121730) 
from Kyung Hee University, Seoul, Republic of Korea. </p>



</text></tei>