<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5419106" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:32+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: To evaluate the effect of 'Bernoulli maneuver' (bringing the access sheath to horizontal plane) on operative time and 
stone free rates in patients undergoing mini-percutaneous nephrolithotomy (PCNL). 
Materials and Methods: All consecutive patients with a solitary kidney stone undergoing a mini-PCNL between 2015 and 2016 
were included into this study. Patients were randomized either to standard prone or control (C) group patients or to tilted prone 
with 'Bernoulli maneuver' group (B) patients. Pre-, intra-, and postoperative characteristics of these 2 groups were recorded and 
analyzed. 
Results: A total of 67 patients were included in the study. Of these, 40 patients were randomized to group C and 27 to group B. The 
mean (95% confidence limits) stone size (mm) in group C and B was 14 (13, 15) and 13 (11, 14), respectively (p=0.26). Nephroscopy 
time was shorter in Bernoulli group (35 minutes vs. 23 minutes, p=1.5•10 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>, and Bayes factor BF 10 =2,340, and Cohen standardized 
effect size d st =1.2). The difference made it up 12 minutes (with 95% confidence interval from 8 to 18 minutes). There were no sta-
tistically significant differences between groups regarding white blood cell, creatinine level and stone-free status defined by com-
puted tomography on the first postoperative day. 
Conclusions: In our study the 'Bernoulli maneuver' led to a shorter nephroscopy time in mini-PCNL. This maneuver can significant-
ly reduce nephroscopy time and save significant amount of operative time, especially in tertiary referral centers with high-volume 
mini-PCNL procedures. </p>

<p><rs type="software">PAST</rs><rs id="software-6" type="software">BoxPlotR</rs><rs corresp="#software-6" type="url">http://boxplot.tyerslab.com</rs><rs type="software">G*Power</rs><rs id="software-9" type="software">LePrep</rs><rs corresp="#software-9" type="url">http://lmrs.univrouen. fr/Persopage/Lecoutre/PAC.htm</rs>RESULTS </p>

<p>Total of 67 patients were included in the study; of these, 
40 patients were randomized to group C and 27 patients to 
group B. Their ratio 1.5 with 95% confidence limits from 
0.9 to 2.4 did not differ statistically from the expected 1:1 
(p=0. 14). Data in group C appeared not agree with a normal 
distribution (Table 1). So all statistical estimations and tests 
used were nonparametric. In group B the nephroscopy time 
was significantly shorter than in group C (Fig. 3). 
The time difference between studying groups was 12.6 
minutes (with 95% confidence interval from 8 to 18 minutes). 
Bayes factor BF 10 =2,340 means that the probability to </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Standard prone (A), tilted prone (B), and tilted prone (C) with hand assistance. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Nephroscopy time in control (C) and Bernoulli (B) groups. </p>



<p>Gadzhiev et al </p>



<p>receive the observed effect under the alternative hypothesis 
is 2,340 times larger than under the null hypothesis. At the 
same time, it means that the posterior odds in favor of the 
alternative hypothesis against the null hypothesis are 2,340 
times larger then prior odds. This result agrees well with the 
high value of achieved power (Pow=0.998) and with a high 
probability of replication psrep=0.97. Prediction analysis 
shows that in replication the Cohen effect size d st will be 
not less than 0.49 and pvalue will not exceed 0.027 with the 
probability 95% (Table 2). 
Moderate positive correlation was observed between 
stone size and nephroscopy time, where linear Pearson </p>

<p>correlation coefficient appeared to be r=0.53 (4.5•10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) and 
Spearman correlation coefficient was r s =0.55 (1.4• 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) (Fig. 4A) 
as well as between nephroscopy time and haemoglobin drop 
(Fig. 4B), r=0.66 (1.5• 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>) and r s =0.55 (5• 10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>We would like to thank Dr. Nikita KhromovBorisov for 
his assistance with statistical analysis. </p>





<p>Investig Clin Urol 2017;58:179-185. 
www.icurology.org </p>



</text></tei>