<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5096434" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background. Dysglycemia (encompassing impaired glucose tolerance and diabetes mellitus) arising after renal transplan-
tation is common and confers a significant cardiovascular mortality risk. Nonetheless, the pathophysiology of posttransplant 
dysglycemia is not well described. The aim of this study was to prospectively and comprehensively assess glucose handling in 
renal transplant recipients from before to 12 months after transplantation to determine the underpinning pathophysiology. 
Materials and Methods. Intravenous and oral glucose tolerance testing was conducted before and at 3 and 12 months 
posttransplantation. An intravenous glucose tolerance test was also performed on day 7 posttransplantation. We followed up 16 
transplant recipients for 3 months and 14 recipients for 12 months. Insulin secretion, resistance and a disposition index (DI (IV)), a 
measure of β cell responsiveness in the context of prevailing insulin resistance, were also determined. Results. At 12 months, 
50% of renal transplant recipients had dysglycemia. Dysglycemia was associated with a dramatic fall in DI (IV) and this loss in β cell 
function was evident as early as 3 months posttransplantation (23.5 pretransplant; 6.4 at 3 months and 12.2 at 12 months 
posttransplant). Differences in the β cell response to oral glucose challenge were evident pretransplant in those destined to de-
velop dysglycemia posttransplant (2-hour blood glucose level 5.6 mmol/L versus 6.8 mmol/L; P &lt; 0.01). Conclusions. 
Dysglycemia after renal transplantation is common, and the loss of insulin secretion is a major contributor. Subclinical differences 
in glucose handling are evident pretransplant in those destined to develop dysglycemia potentially heralding a susceptible β cell 
which under the stressors associated with transplantation fails. </p>

<p>(Transplantation Direct 2016;2: e107; doi: 10.1097/TXD.0000000000000618. Published online 7 October, 2016.) </p>

<p>D iabetes mellitus and impaired glucose tolerance (IGT) </p>

<p>after renal transplantation are associated with an in-
creased risk of mortality and major cardiovascular 
events. 1-5 These dysglycemic states may be preexisting or arise 
de novo after transplantation. Diabetes first diagnosed posttrans-
plantation has previously been called new-onset diabetes after 
transplantation; however, an international consensus recently 
recommended the use of the term posttransplant diabetes mellitus 
(PTDM) 6 to describe diabetes after transplantation. This is 
due to the difficulty in identifying those recipients with unrec-
ognized diabetes pretransplantation. 7-10 Importantly, the 
consensus group also acknowledged that further research 
into the pathophysiology of PTDM was essential and that 
it should be considered a distinct pathological and clinical en-
tity from type 1 or type 2 diabetes. 
Dysglycemia after transplantation (encompassing PTDM 
and IGT) often develops within the first year posttransplanta-
tion; however, the true prevalence is difficult to ascertain be-
cause few studies use established diagnostic criteria for 
diabetes and fewer still the criterion standard oral glucose tol-
erance test (oGTT). 11 A large proportion of dysglycemia is detect-
able within the first 3 to 6 months posttransplantation 10,12,13 
coinciding with the time of greatest immunological risk and </p>

<p>Received 14 July 2016. </p>

<p>Accepted 25 July 2016. </p>

<p>1 Department of Nephrology, St. Vincent's Hospital, Melbourne, Australia. </p>

<p>2 Department of Nephrology, Northern Health, Melbourne, Australia. </p>

<p>3 Department of Medicine, University of Melbourne, Melbourne, Australia. </p>

<p>4 Department of Endocrinology and Diabetes, St. Vincent's Hospital, 
Melbourne, Australia. </p>

<p>5 Immunology Research Centre, St. Vincent's Hospital, Melbourne, Australia. </p>

<p>6 School of Medicine, Deakin University, Victoria, Australia. </p>

<p>K.M.D. received funding from CARG (Cellcept Australian Research Grants) and Kidney 
Health Australia. 
The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>K.M.D. and F.A. conceived the project. D.L., J.T., and K.M.D. recruited recipients and 
performed testing. V.O. performed the analysis. S.V. performed the statistics. D.L. 
and K.M.D. wrote the article. G.W., R.M., and F.A. provided expertise on analysis 
and interpretation of data. </p>

<p>Correspondence: David Langsford, MBBS, FRACP, Department of Nephrology, Northern 
Health, 185 Cooper Street, Epping, VIC 3076, Australia. (david.langsford@nh.org.au). </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016 The Authors. Transplantation Direct. Published by Wolters Kluwer 
Health, Inc. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0 (CCBY-NC-ND), 
where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. 
The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially. </p>

<p>ISSN: 2373-8731 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1097/TXD.0000000000000618 </p>

<p>Kidney Transplantation </p>

<p>Transplantation DIRECT ■ 2016 </p>

<p>www.transplantationdirect.com </p>

<p>
immunosuppressive burden. Calcineurin inhibitors (CNI) 
and glucocorticoids form the backbone of most immuno-
suppressive regimens and are well described risk factors 
for posttransplant dysglycemia. 14,15 The diabetogenic po-
tential of glucocorticoids is well established and encom-
passes both increased insulin resistance and reduced 
insulin secretion. In addition, CNI reduce insulin secretion 
through a direct toxic effect on the β cell. 16 Balancing the im-
munological with the metabolic risks by modifying CNI levels 
and/or ceasing glucocorticoids within the first year posttrans-
plantation remains a challenge. The early identification of 
those recipients at higher risk of developing a posttransplant 
dysglycemic state may assist with pretransplantation planning 
for the prevention of dysglycemia in a manner that would not 
compromise the graft immunologically. A proof of concept 
of such prevention of dysglycemia has been described by 
Hecking et al. 17 
The objectives of this study were two-fold: First, to exam-
ine the changes in metabolic indices that occur after trans-
plantation to define the underpinning pathophysiology and 
second, identify factors evident pretransplant that may be 
predictive of posttransplant dysglycemia. To this end, we un-
dertook a comprehensive assessment of changes in β-cell 
function and insulin resistance in renal transplant recipients. 
We used a rigorous testing protocol that included both intra-
venous GTT (IV GTT) and oGTT to quantitate β-cell function, 
before transplantation and at 3 and 12 months posttrans-
plantation. IV GTT was also performed day 7 posttransplan-
tation. The data available from these tests allowed us to 
evaluate insulin secretion and resistance and calculate the dis-
position index (DI (IV)), a measure of β cell responsiveness in 
the context of prevailing insulin resistance. 18-20 Finally, by 
stratifying recipients according to their posttransplant glyce-
mic state we sought to identify deficits in glucose or insulin 
indices present at study entry that may serve as early markers 
of those at higher risk of posttransplant dysglycemia. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Twenty-five patients with end-stage kidney disease (ESKD) 
from a single hospital network planned for a living (un)re-
lated donor transplant were recruited (Figure 1). None of 
the patients were known to be diabetic at the time of recruit-
ment into the study. The exclusion criteria were inability to 
participate in the study over 12 months, known diabetes </p>

<p>pretransplant or previous transplantation. Six patients did 
not go onto to receive a transplant within 2 months of testing; 
3 withdrew from the study after transplantation. Of the 16 
remaining patients, who are referred to as recipients, and 2 
recipients had not reached 12 months by the conclusion of 
the study, leaving 14 recipients with a complete data set. 
We also recruited 9 potential living kidney donors to undergo 
single IV GTT and oGTT tests before donation to act as a 
comparator group. The study was approved by the human 
ethics committees of the relevant hospitals within the net-
work and signed informed consent was obtained from each 
participant before commencing the study. 
All participants had demographic, BMI, waist-hip ratio, 
blood pressure and glucometabolic (cholesterol, triglycerides, 
BSL, HbA1c, oGTT and IV GTT) data collected at baseline. 
In addition, the renal transplant recipients had renal specific 
and transplant specific data collected pretransplant and at 3 
and 12 months posttransplantation. As outlined in Figure 2, 
all patients had baseline IV GTT and oGTT tests. Results for 
glucose and insulin from multiple time points enabled the cal-
culation of glucose metabolism, insulin resistance, insulin se-
cretion and disposition index. Each test was conducted on a 
different day and after an overnight fast. The renal transplant 
recipients had these tests conducted within 2 months of renal 
transplantation. This group also had an IV GTT and oGTT 
conducted at 3 and 12 months posttransplantation. IV GTT 
was also performed on day 7 posttransplantation. Any recipi-
ent who had been commenced on a hypoglycemic agent had 
that agent withheld for 72 hours before each test. The oGTT 
test was conducted by administering 75 g of oral glucose and 
drawing a venous sample from an intravenous cannula placed 
in the cubital fossa of the nonarteriovenous fistula arm at 0, 
30, 60 and 120 minutes. The IV GTT test was conducted by 
administering 0.3 mg/kg intravenous glucose to a maximum 
dose of 25 g, diluted in normal saline to a maximum volume 
of 100 mL. Venous samples were drawn from an intravenous 
cannula placed in the cubital fossa of the non-arteriovenous 
fistula arm at −10, −1, +2, +4, +6, +8, +10, +12, +14, +19, 
+25, +40 minutes. It has previously been established that this 
dose of intravenous glucose elicits the maximal pancreatic re-
sponse over this period 21 and similar protocols have been 
successfully used. 22 
Glucose metabolism was assessed by 2 different approaches. 
Firstly, a comprehensive descriptive analysis was aided by the 
area under the curve (AUC) of oGTT of each recipient at 
pretransplant, 3 and 12 months posttransplant. Secondly, an 
improved understanding of the pathophysiology was gained 
by assessing the first phase insulin release (FPIR), insulin resis-
tance and β cell responsiveness. FPIR is an index of the β cell re-
sponse to intravenous glucose (insulinogenic index) and 
was calculated using the IV GTT by FPIR = (AUC insulin 
t0-10 minutes)/(Glucose t0minutes − (Av(t-10 minutes 
and t-1 minutes)) as previously described. 23 Insulin resis-
tance was determined using paired insulin and glucose re-
sults obtained from IV GTT, which were then applied to 
the homeostatic model assessment 2 (<rs id="software-1" type="software">HOMA2</rs>) calculator, 
available from <rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">https://www.dtu.ox.ac.uk/homacalculator/download.php</rs>. This has previously been validated in 
ESKD patients. 24 Insulin sensitivity is the inverse of insulin 
resistance. The DI (IV) was calculated as the FPIR/insulin 
resistance. The DI (IV) is a measure of β cell responsiveness 
and has been shown in the general population to be </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Recipient recruitment. </p>



<p>Transplantation DIRECT ■ 2016 </p>

<p>www.transplantationdirect.com </p>

<p>predictive of the development of type 2 diabetes mellitus in 
those at clinically increased risk. 25 Disposition index re-
lates insulin sensitivity and insulin resistance in a hyper-
bolic relationship such that an increase an insulin 
resistance is associated with a compensatory increase in in-
sulin secretion to maintain normoglycemia. 18 
At the time of transplantation, recipients received 20 mg 
basiliximab on days 0 and 4, 500 mg intravenous methyl-
prednisolone on day 0 followed by 30 mg daily of oral pred-
nisolone which was weaned after 3 weeks by 2.5 mg every 
2 weeks to a target dose of 5 mg daily. All recipients received 
1 g twice a day of mycophenolate mofetil and a CNI, how-
ever, the choice of agent was at the discretion of the treating 
transplant physician. For those who received cyclosporin, 
the starting dose was 4 mg/kg twice a day with a C2 target 
of 1200 for the first month, 800 to 1000 at 3 months and 
400 to 600 at 12 months. For those who received tacrolimus, 
the starting dose was 0.075 mg/kg twice a day with a trough 
tacrolimus target of 8 to 10 for the first month and 5 to 8 at 
3 months. All recipients received protocol cytomegalovirus 
and Pneumocystis jiroveci pneumonia prophylaxis. Renal 
transplant biopsies were conducted as protocol at 3 months 
or as indicated by clinical criteria. Acute cellular rejection 
was treated with oral prednisolone 300, 200, and 100 mg 
over 3 consecutive days. To comprehensively assess immuno-
suppression burden weekly therapeutic drug levels for CNI 
agents were collected and the cumulative exposure deter-
mined by calculating the AUC. 
Dysglycemia, encompassing IGT and diabetes, was de-
fined using oGTT as the diagnostic test and the World Health 
Organization diagnostic criteria of 2 hour oGTT result of 
≥7.8 mmol/L (140 mg/dl) for impaired glucose tolerance 
and ≥11.1 mmol/L (200 mg/dl) for diabetes applied. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Data is represented as median and interquartile ranges for 
continuous variables and as frequencies and percentages for 
categorical variables. Continuous variables between groups 
were compared using Kruskal-Wallis and Wilcoxon rank 
sum test. Categorical variables were compared using Fisher 
exact test. Significance level of 0.05 was not corrected for </p>

<p>multiple comparisons due to explorative nature of the study. 
All analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13</rs>. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Data from 9 healthy donors (forming the comparator 
group) and sixteen recipients were analyzed. The demo-
graphic and routine clinical parameters at entry into the 
study are outlined in Table 1. All participants were Caucasian. 
Recipients were well matched to the comparator group with 
respect to age, sex, waist to hip ratio, body mass index and 
fasting lipid profile, although systolic blood pressure was sig-
nificantly lower in the comparator group. The cause of renal 
failure in the recipients was primarily attributable to glomeru-
lonephritis and 75% of the recipients had already commenced 
dialysis. All but 1 recipient was cytomegalovirus positive and 
there were no participants with hepatitis C infection. 
Using standard screening tests for dysglycemia of fasting 
blood glucose level (F BGL) or HbA1c we did not observe 
any differences between the recipient and comparator groups 
(Table 2A). However, oGTT testing revealed unrecognized 
dysglycemia in 3 recipients (Table 2B). All 3 patients were in-
cluded in the subsequent analysis. In addition, none of the 
glucometabolic tests as measured by FPIR (insulin secretion), 
HOMA2IR (insulin resistance), and DI (IV) (β cell respon-
siveness) aided in discriminating between normoglycemic 
versus dysglycemic recipients pretransplant (Table 2B), or 
all recipients versus comparator group (Table 2A). 
At 12 months posttransplant 14 recipients had data 
available for analysis. Seven (50%) recipients had evidence 
of dysglycemia (Table 3) which was evident only on 2 hour 
BGL testing. Fasting BGL and HbA1c testing performed 
poorly as a screening tool in identifying these recipients 
(all dysglycemic patients had a F BGL &lt; 7 mmol/L and </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Study protocol. </p>

<p>TABLE 1. </p>

<p>Demographic, renal specific and glucometabolic data at 
entry into study </p>

<p>Variable at entry 
into study </p>

<p>Comparator group 
(n = 9) </p>

<p>All recipients 
(n = 16) 
P </p>

<p>Age 
48 (44,54) 
42.5 (34, 52.5) 
0.223 
Sex M/F 
6/3 
10/6 
1.000 
ESKD etiology PCKD 
3 
N/A 
Glomerulonephritis 
8 
Other 
5 
Waist-hip ratio 
0.89 (0.83,0.97) 
0.90 (0.87, 1.06) 
0.439 
Body mass index, kg/m 2 
28.0 (22.1,28.4) 
26.8 (24.2, 30.1) 
0.624 
Blood pressure-systolic 
115 (110, 120) 
130 (120, 150) 
0.019 
Blood pressure-diastolic 
80 (75, 85) 
80 (70, 91.5) 
0.605 
Total cholesterol, mmol/L 
5.5 (5.0, 5.8) 
5.0 (4.1, 5.5) 
0.105 
Total cholesterol, mg/dl 
212 (193, 224) 
193 (158, 212) 
Triglycerides, mmol/L 
1.3 (1.0, 1.4) 
1.6 (1.2, 2.2) 
0.057 
Triglycerides, mg/dl 
115 (89, 124) 
142 (106, 195) 
Prior hemodialysis 
5 
N/A 
Prior peritoneal dialysis 
7 
Preemptive transplantation 
4 
Hepatitis C positive 
0 
CMV positive 
15 
N/A </p>

<p>All values expressed as median (25%,75% percentile) unless specified. 
Dysglycemia is defined by 2 hour oGTT result of ≥7.8 mmol/L (140 mg/dl). 
CMV, cytomegalovirus. </p>

<p>© 2016 Wolters Kluwer 
Langsford et al </p>

<p>
HbA1c &lt; 6.3%), although the HbA1c was significantly 
higher in the dysglycemic compared to normoglycemic 
groups. We observed dysglycemia in recipients on both cy-
closporine and tacrolimus. A prior episode of rejection re-
quiring pulse steroids occurred in only one recipient. The 
most striking feature on detailed analysis was the drop in 
DI (IV) in the dysglycemic recipients (P = 0.007). A modest 
increase in weight was observed in the 2 groups: 
normoglycemia median 71 kg (64.5 kg, 81.4 kg 25%-
75% quartile) at study entry and 77.7 kg (65.2, 83.5 kg, 
25-75% quartile) at 12 months and dysglycemia median 
80 kg (75.5 kg, 84.5 kg 25%-75% quartile) at study entry 
and 83 kg at 12 months (78 kg, 94.1 kg 25% -75% quar-
tile). Despite these differences in weight the 12 month 
HOMA2IR measured insulin resistance in both groups 
was comparable with each other the comparator group. 
Thus, the reduction in DI (IV) is most consistent with a fall 
in insulin secretion and β cell function. </p>

<p>We then analyzed recipient data at 3 months posttrans-
plantation stratified according to 12 month glycemic status 
(Table 4A). At 3 months posttransplantation those who were 
classified as dysglycemic at 12 months had a higher 2 hour </p>

<p>TABLE 2A. </p>

<p>Glucometabolic data at entry in study of comparator 
versus recipient groups </p>

<p>Variable at entry 
into study </p>

<p>Comparator 
(n = 9) </p>

<p>Recipients 
(n = 16) 
P </p>

<p>F BGL, mmol/L 
4.9 (4.6, 5.3) 
4.5 (4.3, 4.9) 
0.174 
F BGL, mg/dl 
88 (83, 95) 
81 (77, 88) 
2-h oGTT, mmol/L 
5.4 (4.8, 6.4) 
6.3 (5.5, 6.9)# 
0.311 
2-h oGTT, mg/dL 
97 (86, 115) 
113 (99, 124) 
oGTT AUC 
798 (785, 911) 
846 (788, 934)^ 
0.713 
HbA1c% 
5.2 (5.0, 5.4) 
5.1 (4.8, 5.6)# 
0.568 
HbA1c, mmol/mol 
33.3 (31.1,35.5) 
32.2 (29, 37.7) 
HOMA2IR 
1.2 (1.2, 1.6) 
1.1 (0.8, 1.4)# 
0.698 
FPIR 
29.4 (22.8, 33.3) 
38.7 (18.8, 36.7)# 
0.531 
DI 
24.5 (22.7, 40.0) 
25.5 (18.8, 28.7)^ 
0.493 </p>

<p>All values expressed as median (25%,75% percentile) unless specified. 
Dysglycemia is defined by 2 hour oGTT result of ≥7.8 mmol/L (140 mg/dl). 
DI (IV), intravenous disposition index and is a measure of β cell responsiveness. </p>

<p># </p>

<p>1missing value. </p>

<p>^ </p>

<p>3 missing values. </p>

<p>TABLE 2B. </p>

<p>Glucometabolic data at entry into study of recipients </p>

<p>Variable at 
entry into study </p>

<p>Normoglycemic 
recipients (n = 13) </p>

<p>Dysglycemic 
recipients (n = 3) 
P </p>

<p>Age 
46 (34,54) 
35 (30, 50) 
0.381 
Waist-hip 
0.9 (0.88, 1.05) 
0.86 (0.73, 1.1) 
0.545 
Body mass index, kg/m 2 
26.3 (25.3, 30.1) 
27.4 (21.8, 30.1) 
0.947 
F BGL, mmol/L 
4.6 (4.4, 4.8) 
4.3 (4.1,6.1) 
0.737 
F BGL, mg/dL 
83 (79, 86) 
77 (74, 110) 
2-h oGTT, mmol/L 
5.9 (5.2,6.7) 
11.2 (8.1,13.8) 
0.009 
2-h oGTT, mg/dL 
106 (94, 121) 
202 (146, 284) 
oGTT AUC 
828 (761,908) 
1448 (1336,1560) 
0.030 
HbA1c, % 
5.2 (4.9,5.6) 
4.9 (4.8,5.0) 
0.348 
HbA1c, mmol/mol 
35.3 (30.1,37.7) 
30.1 (29,31.1) 
HOMA2IR 
1.0 (0.8, 1.4) 
1.3 (1.1,2.0) 
0.218 
FPIR 
25.4 (19.8, 33.7) 
29.8 (15.8, 51.8) 
0.773 
DI (IV) 
23.3 (19.4,27.9) 
25.9 (14.4,31.6) 
1.000 </p>

<p>All values expressed as median (25%,75% percentile) unless specified. 
Dysglycemia is defined by 2 hour oGTT result of ≥7.8 mmol/L (140 mg/dl). </p>

<p>TABLE 3. </p>

<p>Recipient results at 12 months posttransplantation </p>

<p>Variable 
at 12 mo 
Subgroup </p>

<p>Normoglycemic 
at 12 mo 
(N = 7) </p>

<p>Dysglycemic 
at 12 mo 
(N = 7) 
P </p>

<p>Age 
35 (32, 46) 
51 (39, 59) 
0.096 
Calcineurin inhibitor Tacrolimus 
6 (85.7%) 
3 (42.9%) 
0.133 
Cyclosporine 
1 (14.3%) 
4 (57.1%) 
Prior rejection 
3 (42.9%) 
1 (14.3%) 
0.280 
Creatinine at 12 mo, 
μmol/L </p>

<p>119 (92, 141) 
113 (112, 127) 
0.360 </p>

<p>Creatinine at 12 mo, 
mg/dL </p>

<p>1.3 (1.0, 1.6) 
1.3 (1.3, 1.4) </p>

<p>F BGL, mmol/L 
5.0 (4.5, 5.2) 
6.0 (4.9, 6.8) 
0.084 
F BGL, mg/dL 
90 (81, 94) 
108 (88, 122) 
2-h oGTT glucose, 
mmol/L </p>

<p>5.7 (4.7, 6.5) 
10.0 (9.2, 11.2) 
0.002 </p>

<p>2-h oGTT glucose, 
mg/dL </p>

<p>103 (85, 117) 
180 (166, 202) </p>

<p>oGTT AUC 
863 (785, 901) 1198 (1099, 1351) 0.006 
HbA1c % 
5.3 (5.2, 5.5) 
5.6 (5.5, 6.2) 
0.040 
HbA1c, mmol/mol 
34.4 (33.3,36.6) 37.7 (36.6,44.3) 
HOMA2IR 
1.2 (1.0, 1.5) 
1.4 (1.2, 2.9) 
0.198 
FPIR 
31.1 (25.3, 34.9) 17.2 (3.2, 32.7) 
0.159 
DI (IV) 
23.0 (21.0, 34.6) 12.2 (3.2, 18.3) 
0.007 </p>

<p>All values expressed as median (25%,75% percentile) unless specified. 
Dysglycemia is defined by 2 hour oGTT result of ≥7.8 mmol/L (140 mg/dl). </p>

<p>TABLE 4A. </p>

<p>Recipient results at 3 months stratified by 12 month 
glycemic state </p>

<p>Variable at 3 mo </p>

<p>Normoglycemic 
at 12 mo 
(N = 7) </p>

<p>Dysglycemic 
at 12 mo 
(N = 7) 
P </p>

<p>Tacrolimus exposure 
(AUC for 3 mo, n = 9) </p>

<p>90 (87, 96) 
95 (82, 109) 
0.696 </p>

<p>Cyclosporine Exposure 
(AUC for 3 mo, n = 5) </p>

<p>10544 (N = 1) 
13529 (12773, 14921) 
N/A </p>

<p>Median Creatinine 
over 3 mo, μmol/L </p>

<p>121 (90, 131) 
137 (114, 153) 
0.142 </p>

<p>Median creatinine 
over 3 mo, mg/dL </p>

<p>1.4 (1.0, 1.5) 
1.5 (1.3, 1.7) </p>

<p>F BGL, mmol/L 
5.2 (4.8, 6.0) 
5.5 (4.8, 8.2) 
0.443 
F BGL, mg/dL 
94 (86, 108) 
99 (86, 148) 
2-h oGTT, mmol/L 
6.8 (5.1, 8.0) 
12.1 (9.1, 16.1) 
0.009 
2-h oGTT, mg/dL 
122 (92, 144) 
218 (164, 290) 
oGTT AUC 
897 (773, 1034) 
1411 (1047, 1689) 
0.009 
HbA1c% 
5.4 (4.7, 5.6) 
6.2 (5.4, 8.4) 
0.098 
HbA1c, mmol/mol 
35.5 (27.9,37.7) 
44.3 (35.5,68.3) 
HOMA2IR 
1.3 (1.1, 1.4) 
1.7 (0.9, 2.0) 
0.564 
FPIR 
32.4 (28.9, 38.8) 
7.8 (1.9, 48.0) 
0.180 
DI (IV) 
27.0 (21.6, 35.1) 
6.4 (1.4, 22.9) 
0.025 </p>

<p>All values expressed as median (25%,75% percentile) unless specified. 
Dysglycemia is defined by 2 hour oGTT result of ≥7.8 mmol/L (140 mg/dl). </p>



<p>Transplantation DIRECT ■ 2016 </p>

<p>www.transplantationdirect.com </p>

<p>oGTT (P = 0.035) and oGTT AUC (P = 0.0009). Significant 
separation (P = 0.018) of the glycemic response was evident 
at 60 minutes after an oral glucose load (Figure 3). Neither 
the 3-month F BGL nor HbA1c were discriminatory, and there 
were no significant differences in HOMA2IR. However, a 
striking decline in 3 month DI (IV) (27 vs 6.4, P = 0.025) 
was observed in those dysglycemic at 12 months. As depicted 
in Figure 4, a fall in DI (IV) by 3 months predicted dysglycemia 
at 12 months whereas a preserved DI (IV) at 3 months pre-
dicted normoglycemia at 12 months. Thus, recipients with 
similar CNI exposure and graft function at 3 months who 
are deemed dysglycemic at 12 months could be distinguished 
at 3 months from those normoglycemic at 12 months by fea-
tures indicative of β cell dysfunction. We note that glucose 
handling was dynamic in 4 recipients: 2 recipients who were 
normoglycemic at 3 months subsequently became dysglycemic 
by 12 months, whereas 2 recipients who were dysglycemic at 
3 months became normoglycemic at 12 months. Of the former 
group one recipient had a low DI (IV) (6.35) whereas the 
other had a preserved DI (IV) (28.3) at 3 months. The recip-
ients who reverted to normoglycemia at 12 months both had 
preserved DI (IV) at 3 months (31.73 and 21.56). 
β cell responsiveness changed quickly and we observed 
marked variance in DI (IV) in individuals at day 7 posttransplant, 
presumably reflecting surgical stress, high dose immunosuppres-
sion and dramatic changes in renal physiology. No recipients 
were receiving treatment for hyperglycemia at the time testing. 
We did not detect any correlation with the results at day 7 and 
the eventual development of dysglycemia. Furthermore, F BGL 
remained normal and did not distinguish between the 12 month 
glycemic states (Table 4B). 
To identify individuals pretransplant at risk persistent of 
posttransplant dysglycemia we stratified recipients according 
to 3 month metabolic state and analyzed the data at study </p>

<p>entry (Table 5). Three months posttransplantation was cho-
sen as the underpinning pathophysiological changes account-
ing for 12 month dysglycemia, as measured by DI (IV), were 
evident by 3 months. We note the median 2 hour oGTT re-
sult was higher in those who progressed to dysglycemia at 
3 months posttransplantation compared to those who 
remained normoglycemic (6.89 mmol/L vs 5.56 mmol/L 
(124 mg/dl vs 100 mg/dl), P = 0.01). The HbA1c was also 
higher in those that progressed to dysglycemia. Notably, 
although elevated compared to those who remained 
normoglycemic, neither parameter fulfilled the diagnostic 
criteria for diabetes in the general population. Although 
the FPIR, DI (IV) and HOMA2IR at study entry were similar 
between groups, these results suggest subtle baseline β cell 
abnormalities, which are exaggerated and made clinically ap-
parent by the physiological stress of transplantation. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Oral glucose tolerance at 12 months. </p>

<p>TABLE 4B. </p>

<p>Recipient results at day 7 stratified by 12-month 
glycemic state </p>

<p>Variable 
at day 7 </p>

<p>Normoglycemic 
at 12 mo (N = 7) </p>

<p>Dysglycemic 
at 12 mo (N = 7) 
P </p>

<p>F BGL, mmol/L 
5.7 (5.1, 5.8) 
5.0 (4.7, 5.8) 
0.198 
F BGL, mg/dL 
103 (92, 104) 
90 (85, 104) 
DI (IV) 
14.4 (11.1, 30.6) 
12.6 (10.2, 39.6) 
1.000 </p>

<p>TABLE 5. </p>

<p>Recipient results at entry into study according to 
3 month glycemic status </p>

<p>Variable at 
study entry </p>

<p>Normoglycemic 
at 3 mo (N = 9) </p>

<p>Dysglycemic 
at 3 mo (N = 7) 
P </p>

<p>Age 
39 (34, 49) 
50 (32, 59) 
0.314 
Waist-hip ratio 
.89 (.86, .99) 
1.05 (0.87, 1.08) 
0.153 
Body mass index, kg/m 2 
25.5 (21.8, 29.9) 29.7 (25.4, 30.1) 
0.315 
Systolic blood pressure, mm Hg 130 (120, 150) 
130 (115, 150) 
0.831 
Diastolic blood pressure, mm Hg 
80 (80, 93) 
80 (60, 90) 
0.307 
Total cholesterol, mmol/L 
5.4 (4.4, 6.2) 
4.2 (3.8, 5.0) 
0.089 
Total cholesterol, mg/dL 
209 (170, 239) 
162 (147, 193)1 
Triglycerides, mmol/L 
1.3 (1.2, 1.6) 
2.1 (1.6, 2.7) 
0.138 
Triglycerides, mg/dL 
115 (106, 142) 
186 (142, 239) 
F BGL, mmol/L 
4.6 (4.4, 4.8) 
4.5 (4.1, 5.0) 
0.491 
F BGL, mg/dL 
83 (79, 86) 
81 (74, 90) 
2-h oGTT, mmol/L 
5.6 (4.8, 6.2) 
6.8 (6.7, 8.1) 
0.010 
2-h oGTT, mg/dL 
101 (86, 112) 
122 (121, 146) 
oGTT AUC 
828 (788, 901) 
1921 (834.5, 1247) 0.280 
HbA1c% 
4.9 (4.7, 5.1) 
5.3 (5.2, 5.6) 
0.051 
HbA1c, mmol/mol 
30.1 (27.9, 32.2) 34.4 (33.3, 37.7) 
HOMA2IR 
1.0 (0.9, 1.4) 
1.2 (0.8, 1.4) 
0.768 
FPIR 
28.7 (18.8, 36.7) 25.5 (20.7, 30.7) 
0.906 
DI (IV) 
25.5 (20.0, 28.7) 23.5 (18.8, 26.7) 
0.906 </p>

<p>All values expressed as median (25%,75% percentile) unless specified. 
Dysglycemia is defined by 2 hour oGTT result of ≥7.8 mmol/L (140 mg/dL). </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Disposition index over 12 months. </p>

<p>© 2016 Wolters Kluwer 
Langsford et al </p>

<p>
DISCUSSION 
The development of dysglycemia post renal transplanta-
tion is highly prevalent and confers an increased risk of cardio-
vascular disease that manifests rapidly. 1-5 There is, however, a 
paucity of literature documenting the dynamic changes and 
underlying pathophysiological mechanisms occurring in glu-
cose metabolism that accompany transplantation. The stress 
of surgery, exposure to multiple diabetogenic medications 
and improved renal function are all likely to alter glucose me-
tabolism. We analyzed longitudinally over the course of a year 
the glucometabolic parameters of renal transplant recipients. 
Importantly, our data suggests that a major contributor to 
dysglycemia after renal transplantation is impaired insulin se-
cretion due to progressive reduction in β-cell responsiveness. 
In addition, our findings highlight that recipients at risk for 
posttransplant dysglycemia may have subtle abnormalities of 
glucose handling evident on pretransplant oGTT and these re-
cipients may be further stratified at 3 months with reference to 
tests of the underlying pathophysiology. 
We compared our recipient cohort with a group of poten-
tial living donors who are typical of a healthy general popu-
lation. No differences could be found pretransplant between 
either of these groups on the basis of routine glucose han-
dling tests, such as F BGL and HbA1c. Within the recipient 
cohort there were 3 cases of unrecognized dysglycemia, diag-
nosed only by oGTT. As we observed, and consistent with 
others, 8-10 pretransplant dysglycemia was not necessarily as-
sociated with posttransplant dysglycemia highlighting the 
important contribution of renal function to insulin sensitivity 
and glucose handling. In patients with end stage renal failure 
relative insulin resistance may manifest with fasting hyper-
glycemia and abnormal glucose responses during oGTT 
and IV GTT, whereas others maintain normoglycemia with 
hyperinsulinemia. 26 These findings highlight the difficulty 
that transplant clinicians encounter when attempting to as-
sess risk for posttransplant dysglycemia using standard clini-
cal investigations. 
We defined the glycemic state posttransplantation as 
dysglycemic or normoglycemic because the clinical ramifica-
tions of cardiovascular mortality accrue with either IGT or 
PTDM. 1-5 Furthermore, by defining glycemic state with ref-
erence to 12 month data we excluded transient dysglycemia 
as recommended by the International Consensus on Post-
transplant Diabetes. 6 Consistent with others, 10,14 we noted 
changes in definitional states (IGT vs PTDM) over the first 
year; however, found stability in the more granular definition 
of persistent dysglycemia. 
Our hypothesis was that the underlying mechanism of per-
sistent dysglycemia posttransplantation was a reduction in β 
cell responsiveness. Reduced FPIR to a glucose bolus has been 
recognized as a critical factor in the genesis of dysglycemia in 
the general population particularly in the presence of ongoing 
insulin resistance. 20 In transplantation, some have described 
an increase in insulin resistance as the predominant cause 
for impairment in glucose metabolism posttransplantation, 10 
others have emphasized the importance of reduced insulin se-
cretion. 5,15,27,28 Our results build on these previous findings 
by prospectively studying the changes in glucometabolic 
physiology pre, early and late posttransplantation. In 
our recipients, insulin resistance was comparable be-
tween normoglycemic and dysglycemic groups through-
out the 12 month period. Dysglycemia was however </p>

<p>associated with a fall in DI (IV), which in light of 
dysglycemic recipient insulin resistance being comparable 
to our comparator group (1.4 vs 1.2), reflects a loss of β cell 
responsiveness. consistent with a marked decline in β cell re-
sponsiveness as the primary lesion for the dysglycemic state. 
Our findings also suggest that it is possible to detect at 
3 months those who will be dysglycemic at 12 months. The 
fall in DI was evident early posttransplantation making it 
possible to detect at 3 months those who will be dysglycemic 
at 12 months. Such findings are supported by other published 
results; for example, the findings of Porrini et al 29 suggest 
that recipients who are normoglycemic at 3 months on oGTT 
testing rarely develop diabetes later posttransplantation. We 
add to this finding firstly by investigating all dysglycemic 
states and not diabetes mellitus exclusively. By doing so, we 
show that those who are dysglycemic at 12 months are signif-
icantly likely to have higher 2 hour oGTT results at 3 months. 
Furthermore, the 12 month dysglycemic patients have signif-
icantly higher 1 hour results on 3 month oGTT. These find-
ings are consistent with those in the general population 
when attempting to identify those at highest risk of the devel-
opment of type 2 diabetes mellitus 30 and highlight reduced β 
cell function as the primary lesion in persistent (12 month) 
dysglycemia. Together these findings suggest that early 
posttransplant is an opportune time for the implementation 
of interventions that may potentially preserve insulin secre-
tion. Such a strategy has been implemented by Hecking et al 17 
who showed that a reduction in PTDM could be achieved 
through the early administration of insulin. 
Ideally, clinicians would have reliable tests that could de-
tect pre, or very early posttransplant those recipients at 
greatest risk of dysglycemia. Some groups have reported that 
different clinical tests of glucose handling within the first 
week posttransplantation may be a strong predictor for the 
development of posttransplant diabetes. 31-35 We found that 
tests of glucose handling at this time point have low discrim-
inative value for later dysglycemia. Indeed, only one recipient 
had an abnormal F BGL at day 7 (6.91 mmol/L (124 mg/dl)) 
and this recipient did not have evidence of dysglycemia 
pretransplant, or at 3 and 12 months posttransplant. Con-
versely all recipients who later developed dysglycemia had a 
normal fasting BGL at day 7. 
Although early posttransplant testing was not discrimina-
tory, pretransplant testing did aid in detecting those dysglycemic 
at 3 months. Using 2 hour oGTT testing, we detected significant 
differences in glucose handling pretransplant in those who 
progressed to dysglycemia at 3 months with an associated de-
cline in DI (IV). Interestingly the 2 hour BGL remained within 
normal limits for healthy individuals but was significantly 
greater than in those individuals who did not progress to 
dysglycemia. Others have described similar data: Nam 
et al used oGTT pretransplant and at 9 to 12 months 
posttransplant and found that recipients with higher, albeit 
normal, pretransplant 2 hour oGTT were significantly more 
likely to have posttransplant dysglycemia. 28 A retrospective 
analysis of 145 recipients who underwent a pretransplant 
oGTT (but without posttransplant oGTT) found that the 5 
time point 2 hour oGTT AUC identified those recipients at 
highest risk for PTDM. Once more, consistent with findings 
in the general population, the authors also identified that non-
diabetic patients with higher 1 hour oGTT had increased risk 
of PTDM. 36 Although we are limited by our small sample size, </p>



<p>Transplantation DIRECT ■ 2016 </p>

<p>www.transplantationdirect.com </p>

<p>our similar findings may indicate subclinical pretransplant β 
cell susceptibility, which fails under the stressors of transplan-
tation. Despite different groups demonstrating potential sus-
ceptibility by oGTT testing, we and others 5 have not been 
able to identify pretransplant pathophysiological changes that 
may account for this susceptibility. 
The above findings suggest that the pretransplant thresh-
olds for at risk individuals may differ from the general popu-
lation. Indeed, Rosettenstein et al 37 used the combination of 
fructosamine and lower HbA1c thresholds to identify at risk 
patients who proceed to formal oGTT. Yates et al 38 have 
shown that lower HbA1c thresholds assist in detection of at 
risk individuals by increasing negative predictive values. It 
should be noted however that HbA1c results are limited by 
anemia, which can be found posttransplant, and oGTT 
remains the gold standard tests. We suggest that altered 
physiology associated with ESKD pretransplant and 
CKD posttransplant may warrant changes in the diagnos-
tic values that define clinically important glycemic states, 
similar to the example of gestational diabetes. 39 
Transplant specific immunosuppressive medications alter 
glucose handling: Glucocorticoids increase insulin resis-
tance 15,40 and CNI use has been associated with decreased 
insulin secretion. 5,28,41-43 In this study all patients had on-
going, albeit reducing, exposure to glucocorticoids. Although 
a modest increase in median weight was documented over 
12 months, we did not detect any clinically relevant change 
in insulin resistance. Our cohort contained patients treated 
with both tacrolimus and cyclosporine; however, the small 
sample size precluded comparisons between the groups. A 
higher incidence of PTDM 15,44-46 and greater reduction in in-
sulin secretion has been reported in patients treated with tacro-
limus compared to cyclosporin. 15 Consistent with this effect 
our data implicated a reduction in insulin secretion as a major 
contributor to dysglycemia. 
The strengths of our study are that it is the first prospective 
study using intravenous and oGTT of renal transplant recip-
ients. As the pretransplant test was conducted within 2 months 
of transplantation, there was minimal risk of change in the gly-
cemic state pretransplant and we were able to compare the 
recipients with healthy kidney donors. The combination of 
intravenous and oral glucose testing enabled a descriptive 
longitudinal analysis of β cell responsiveness in relation to 
changing insulin resistance in individual recipients to be doc-
umented. We have also accounted for the CNI exposure over 
the first 3 months in a more comprehensive manner than by 
reference to drug level measurements alone. The main limita-
tion of this study is that the recipient numbers are small lim-
iting the ability to analyze the interaction between variables 
and indeed may account for the lack of significance of clini-
cally relevant investigations, such as BMI and HbA1c. Our 
results are drawn from a single transplant consortium that 
while used a standard and protocolized triple therapy immu-
nosuppression regimen allowed for choice between CNI 
agents and may not be generalizable to all transplant popula-
tions. The small numbers limits our ability to draw conclu-
sions with regard to the alternative CNI agents. This was 
not a study designed to distinguish the diabetogenic effects 
of specific immunosuppression agents we did not withhold 
agents in the period immediately before testing; however, 
this zis only a relative limitation as this reflects actual clinical 
practice. Furthermore, although there is some evidence of </p>

<p>glycemic benefit through the use of DPP-4 inhibitors 47,48 we 
did not address the role of incretins in PTDM. There is data 
in the general healthy population and relatives of Type 2 dia-
betics that glucocorticoid exposure may impair the incretin ef-
fect. 49 There is also some data on the impairment of incretins 
in dialysis recipients, 50 however, to date there is no data on 
the incretin effect in the renal transplant population. 
In conclusion, we have shown that posttransplant 
dysglycemia is common and difficult to recognize with-
out oGTT testing. In addition, standard pretransplant 
clinical assessment alone is not sufficient for identifying 
those at high risk of developing dysglycemia. Importantly a 
subclinical β-cell deficiency, which is unmasked by trans-
plant related factors, may be detected by pretransplant 
oGTT. In addition, rigorous testing at 3 months may reliably 
predict permanent dysglycemia. We have shown that intrave-
nous glucose tolerance testing can be used in renal transplant 
recipients and the indices derived from such tests (in particu-
lar DI (IV)) demonstrate that a loss of β-cell responsiveness is 
a major contributing factor to dysglycemia posttransplant. 
Validation of these results in larger cohorts would enable the 
reliable identification of higher risk patients (potentially 
pretransplant and/or at 3 months), which then permits the im-
plementation of strategies to reduce permanent dysglycemia. 
Such strategies may include closer therapeutic drug moni-
toring, the utilization of alternative immunosuppressive 
regimens or planned and prophylactic posttransplant insu-
lin administration. 17 </p>



<p>© 2016 Wolters Kluwer 
Langsford et al </p>





<p>
Transplantation DIRECT ■ 2016 </p>

<p>www.transplantationdirect.com </p>

</text></tei>