<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5359128" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Colorectal cancer (CRC) has become a major public health problem, ranking as the 
third most common type of cancer. Our previous study has revealed that TCF21 is frequently 
silenced by promoter hypermethylation in both CRC cell lines and primary CRC, with TCF21 
methylation being significantly correlated with lymph node invasion. In this study, we further 
analyze the expression of TCF21 in CRC tissues and investigate the role of TCF21 in CRC in vitro 
and in vivo. We also explore the possible pathway regulated by TCF21. We thus demonstrate 
that decreased levels of TCF21 are associated with the pathological stage, clinical stage and 
lymph node metastasis, indicating a poor prognosis in CRC patients; overexpression of TCF21 
inhibits cell proliferation, migration and invasion in the colorectal cell lines HCT116 and HT29. 
Furthermore, TCF21 functions as a tumor suppressor probably through inactivation of PI3K/ 
AKT signaling and inhibition of MMPs. Our results suggest that enhancement of TCF21 levels 
may be a potential strategy to facilitate the prevention and treatment of CRC in the clinic. 
Colorectal cancer (CRC) has become a major public health problem, ranking as the 
third most common among all cancer types, which is responsible for 8%-9% of 
cancer-related deaths in the world. 
1 TCF21, located in 6q23, is known to function as 
a tumor suppressor and is deregulated in several types of cancers, including breast 
cancer, gastric cancer and clear cell renal cell carcinoma (ccRCC). 
2-5 The loss of func-
tion of TCF21 is associated with epigenetic alterations in different types of human 
cancers. For example, the methylation level of TCF21 in gastric cancer samples is 
much higher than that in samples of normal adjacent tissue; moreover, treatment with 
DNA methyltransferase can upregulate the expression of TCF21 in gastric cancer 
cells. 
5 TCF21 genetic polymorphisms are associated with the risk of breast cancer in 
Chinese women. 
6 Our previous study has revealed that TCF21 is frequently silenced by 
promoter hypermethylation in both CRC cell lines and primary CRC and that TCF21 
methylation is significantly correlated with lymph node invasion. 
7 However, the role 
of TCF21 in CRC and the underlying mechanism remain unclear. 
In this study, we analyze the expression of TCF21 in CRC tissues and investigate 
the role of TCF21 CRC in vitro and in vivo. We also explore the possible pathway 
regulated by TCF21. We demonstrate that decreased levels of TCF21 indicate a poor 
prognosis in CRC patients and that TCF21 functions as a tumor suppressor probably 
through inactivation of PI3K/AKT signaling and inhibition of MMPs. Our results suggest </p>

<p>correspondence: liangfang shen 
Department of Oncology, Xiangya 
hospital, central south University, 
87 Xiangya road, changsha, 
410008 hunan, People's 
republic of china 
email 3153559525@qq.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
14 March 2017 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1604 </p>

<p>Dai et al </p>

<p>that enhancement of TCF21 may be a potential strategy to 
facilitate the prevention and treatment of CRC in the clinic. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Tissue samples </p>

<p>All patients signed an informed consent, approved by the 
Independent Ethical Committee of Central South University 
(number 2010-S124). Tissues used for Western blot, namely, 
the CRC and the adjacent normal colorectal epithelial tis-
sues used in the study, were collected from 4 patients. All 
samples were stored in liquid nitrogen until tissue section. 
These tissues were also used for immunohistochemical 
staining. In total, 82 samples of CRC cancer tissues (47 males 
and 35 females; average age: 60 years) and paired adjacent 
normal colorectal mucosa used in the study were collected 
from January 2011 to January 2014 in Xiangya Hospital 
of Central South University, Hunan, People's Republic of 
China, and the tumor stages were classified according to 
National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN 2009) 
staging criteria. 
8 Information related to the specimens was 
obtained from surgical and pathological records, and use 
of these samples was approved by the ethics committee of 
Xiangya Hospital of Central South University. The clinical 
features of patients are shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>cell culture </p>

<p>Human CRC cell lines HCT116 and HT29 were obtained 
from the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC). All </p>

<p>the cells were cultured in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's 
Medium (DMEM) (Invitrogen Life Technologies, Carlsbad, 
CA, USA) supplemented with 10% (v/v) fetal bovine serum 
(FBS) and 100 U/mL penicillin/streptomycin (Invitrogen Life 
Technologies) at 37°C in a humidified 5% CO 2 incubator. </p>

<p>cell transfection </p>

<p>Cell transfection was conducted using Lipofectamine 3000 
(Invitrogen Life Technologies), according to the manu-
facturer's instruction. The lentivirus (Lv) used to overexpress 
TCF21 was designed and purchased from RiboBio (Guangzhou 
RiboBio Co, Ltd, Guangzhou, People's Republic of China). 
Lv-TCF21 and Lv-NC were added into cell culture medium 
at MOI (multiplicity of infection) =40 for along with 5 µg/ 
mL polybrene. Twelve hours after infection, culture medium 
was refreshed and cells were cultured for another 24 hours 
before ready for further treatments. Subsequently, the mixtures 
were added into the cell suspensions. After incubation for 6 h, 
the medium was replaced by DMEM with 10% FBS. After 
transfection for 48 h, the cells were used for further analysis. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>The protein was extracted using radioimmunoprecipitation 
assay (RIPA) lysis buffer (Auragene, Changsha, People's 
Republic of China) from the indicated cells, and the Bradford 
Protein Assay Kit (Beyotime Biotechnology, Shanghai, 
People's Republic of China) was used to measure the pro-
tein concentration. After separation on 10% sodium dodecyl 
sulfate polyacrylamide gels by electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE), 
the protein was transferred to nitrocellulose membranes. 
Membranes were then blocked with 5% bovine serum 
albumin, incubated overnight at 4°C with primary antibody. 
The membranes were washed with Tris-buffered saline plus 
Tween (TBST) and then incubated with appropriate horse-
radish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated secondary antibodies. 
Enhanced chemiluminescence (ECL) reagent was used to 
detect the signal on the membrane. </p>

<p>immunohistochemical staining </p>

<p>The human cancer tissues and matched adjacent normal 
tissues were used for immunohistochemistry analysis, as 
described previously. 
9 Tissues were subjected to citrate-based 
antigen retrieval using 10 mM sodium citrate buffer 
(pH 6.0). The tissues were then stained with TCF21 anti-
body (ImmunoWay Biotechnology, Plano, TX, USA) and 
visualized using a 3,3′-diaminobenzidine (DAB) staining 
kit (Abcam, New Territories, Hong Kong, China), followed 
by counterstaining with hematoxylin. The staining was 
scored by 2 independent pathologists who were blinded to </p>

<p>Table 1 association between TcF21 expression and clinico 
pathologic characteristics in colorectal cancer </p>

<p>Features 
Number 
of cases </p>

<p>TCF21 
expression </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Low 
High </p>

<p>age, years 
0.508 
.60 
45 
23 
22 
#60 
37 
22 
15 
sex 
0.112 
Female 
35 
16 
19 
Male 
47 
29 
18 
Pathological stage 
0.033* 
T1 + T2 
57 
27 
30 
T3 + T4 
25 
18 
7 
clinical stage 
0.020* 
i+ii 
61 
29 
32 
iii+iV 
21 
16 
5 
lymph node status 
0.008** 
Metastasis 
44 
30 
14 
no metastasis 
38 
15 
23 </p>

<p>Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>χ 
2 test. Significant values: *P,0.05; **P,0.01. T1, the tumor has grown 
through the muscularis mucosa into the submucosa; T2, the tumor has grown into 
the muscularis propria; T3, the tumor has grown into the outermost layers of the 
colon or rectum but has not gone through them; T4, the tumor has invaded lumen 
surrounding tissues and organs. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1605 </p>

<p>TcF21 functions as a tumor suppressor in colorectal cancer </p>

<p>clinicopathologic features. TCF21 staining intensity was 
scored as 0 (negative, -), 1 (weak, +), 2 (moderate, ++) and 
3 (strong, +++). The extent of staining was scored as 0-1.0 
(0%-100%). The final staining score (0-3) was calculated 
as the multiplication product of the intensity score and the 
extent score. A final score $1 was defined as indicating high 
expression; otherwise, the score was said to be indicative of 
low expression. </p>

<p>3(4,5Dimethylthiazol2yl)2,5 
diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) assay </p>

<p>Cell growth and inhibition of viability were measured by the 
MTT assay. Thus, 3,000 indicated cells were seeded in each 
96-well plate for 6 h and further incubated for 0, 24, 48 and 
72 h. Then, 1 h before the end of incubation, 100 µL MTT 
was added into each well at given time points followed by an 
additional 4 h incubation at 37°C. And then the supernatant 
was removed and replaced with 150 µL dimethyl sulfoxide 
(DMSO) in each well for 15 min. Subsequently, the optical 
density (OD) at 570 nm for each well was determined by an 
enzyme immunoassay analyzer. </p>

<p>scratch assay </p>

<p>Cells in each group were collected and resuspended in 
DMEM. Each well of a 6-well plate was seeded with 
1×10 
5 cells and cultured for 24 h to 100% confluence. The 
cells were scratched with the head of a 20 µL tip and washed 
with serum-free medium. These cells were further cultured 
for 24 h in DMEM containing 3% FBS; then, the cells in 
each group were photographed for analysis. </p>

<p>Transwell assay </p>

<p>The indicated cells were starved for 12 h, resuspended in 
serum-free medium and added to the upper chamber of 
the transwell device. The lower chamber was filled with 
completed medium containing 10% FBS. Following 48 h 
culture, cells attached to the bottom were fixed and stained 
with crystal violet for 30 min. </p>

<p>Tumorigenicity assay in nude mice </p>

<p>The protocol of this study was approved by the Committee 
on the Ethics of Animal Experiments of Xiangya Hospital 
of Central South University. All animal experiments were 
performed in accordance with the guidelines of the Animal 
Care Committee, Xiangya Hospital, Central South University. 
A total of 9 male BALB/c nude mice (3 weeks old) were 
purchased from the Animal Center of the Chinese Academy 
of Sciences (Shanghai, People's Republic of China) and 
randomized into 3 groups, including mock, Lv-NC (negative </p>

<p>control) and Lv-TCF21. After 7 days' habitation, mice were 
injected subcutaneously with 2×10 
6 indicated cells into the 
flanks. Tumor volumes were monitored once every 5 days. 
Tumor volume was calculated according to the following 
formula: tumor volume = length × (width) 
2 /2. After 30 days, 
the mice were sacrificed, and the tumor tissues were retrieved 
for further analysis. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed using GraphPad <rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Graphpad Software, Inc</rs>, La Jolla, CA, USA), and 
the data are presented as the mean ± standard deviation. 
Kaplan-Meier analysis with log-rank test was used to ana-
lyze the overall survival rate. Multivariate prognostic factors 
were examined using Cox's proportional-hazards model. An 
unpaired 2-tailed Student's t-test or 1-way analysis of vari-
ance (ANOVA) was used to analyze the in vitro and in vivo 
data. P,0.05 was considered to be statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results 
Downregulated TcF21 predicts a poor 
prognosis in crc patients </p>

<p>To investigate the role of TCF21 in the development of 
CRC, we analyzed the expression of TCF21 in CRC tissues 
as well as the association between its expression and overall 
survival. As shown in Figure 1A and B, we found that the 
protein levels of TCF21 were significantly downregulated 
in CRC compared with the levels in the paired adjacent 
tissues. Among 82 cases of adjacent tissues, 76 cases showed 
positive expression of TCF21, with a 92.7% (76/82) positive 
expression rate. However, among 82 cases of CRC, only 
59 cases showed positive expression of TCF21, with a 72.0% 
(59/82) positive expression rate, which was significantly 
lower than in adjacent tissues. The association between 
TCF21 protein expression and clinicopathologic features in 
patients with CRC was analyzed using the χ 
2 test. As shown 
in Table 1, the TCF21 protein expression had no association 
with the patient's age and sex (P.0.05). However, its protein 
expression showed association with the pathological stage, 
clinical stage and lymph node metastasis (P,0.05). 
Furthermore, we also analyzed the association between 
TCF21 expression and overall survival in patients with 
CRC. The Kaplan-Meier curves showed a worse overall 
survival rate for CRC patients with low TCF21 expression 
compared with the survival rate for patients with high TCF21 
expression (Figure 1C). 
In addition, we performed multivariate Cox model 
analysis, and our data suggested that the depth of invasion, 
the lymph node metastasis, the tumor-node-metastasis (TNM) </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1606 </p>

<p>Dai et al </p>

<p>stage and the TCF21 protein expression were independent 
prognostic factors for patients with colorectal carcinomas 
(Table 2). These results indicate that TCF21 may play an 
important role in the development of CRC. </p>

<p>Upregulation of TcF21 inhibits cell 
proliferation and represses the ability 
of migration and invasion in hcT116 
and hT29 cells </p>

<p>To further investigate the role of TCF21 in CRC cells, we 
overexpressed the expression of TCF21 in HCT116 and 
HT29 cells by infecting the cells with Lv. We found that 
overexpression of TCF21 inhibited cell proliferation in </p>

<p>HCT116 and HT29 cells (Figure 2). In addition, we also 
assessed the role of TCF21 in cell migration and invasion. 
Upregulation of TCF21 significantly reduced the migration and 
invasion ability, compared with the negative control, in HCT116 
and HT29 cells (Figures 3 and 4), indicating that TCF21 was 
able to inhibit the movement of CRC cells. Thus, TCF21 is able 
to repress the growth and ability of invasion in CRC cells. </p>

<p>TcF21 inactivates Pi3K/aKT signaling 
and inhibits the expression of genes 
encoding MMPs </p>

<p>Furthermore, we explored the possible downstream molecules 
of TCF21. As shown in Figure 5, we found that upregulation 
of TCF21 significantly induced the expression of Kiss-1 while 
decreasing the expression of PI3K and p-AKT, indicating an 
inactivation of PI3K/AKT signaling. In addition, overexpres-
sion of TCF21 also inhibited the expression of MMP9 and 
MMP2, which are involved in cancer cell invasion. </p>

<p>TcF21 inhibits growth of human crc 
cells in nude mice </p>

<p>We further validated the effects of upregulated TCF21 of 
HCT116 cells on the growth of human CRC xenograft in 
nude mice. Nude mice were subcutaneously inoculated </p>

<p>Figure 1 Downregulation of TcF21 is associated with poor prognosis in patients with colorectal cancer. 
Notes: (A) Western blot analysis for TCF21 in colorectal tumor tissues and their paired adjacent tissues (left panel), as well as the quantification (right panel). Data are 
presented as mean ± sD. **P,0.01, ***P,0.001. (B) representative immunohistochemical staining for high and low TcF21 expression levels in colorectal tumor tissues. 
scale bar =100 µm. (C) Kaplan-Meier curves showed worse overall survival rates for colorectal cancer patients with low TcF21 expression, compared with that in patients 
with high TcF21 expression. 
Abbreviations: n, normal adjacent tissue; T, tumor tissue; sD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>β </p>

<p>Table 2 Multivariate cox model analysis </p>

<p>Variables 
RR 
95% CI 
P-value </p>

<p>Depth of invasion 
(T1 + T2 vs T3 + T4) </p>

<p>1.529 
0.634-3.637 
0.039 </p>

<p>TnM stage (i+ii vs iii+iV) 
2.330 
1.189-4.565 
0.014 
lymph node metastasis 
(yes vs no) </p>

<p>5.247 
2.791-9.866 
,0.001 </p>

<p>TcF21 protein 
expression (low vs high) </p>

<p>0.271 
0.142-0.517 
,0.001 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; RR, relative risk; TNM, tumor-node-
metastasis. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1607 </p>

<p>TcF21 functions as a tumor suppressor in colorectal cancer </p>

<p>Figure 2 Overexpression of TcF21 inhibits cell proliferation in hcT116 and hT29 cells. 
Notes: MTT assay was used to measured cell proliferation in (A) hT29 and (B) hcT116 cells after transfection with TcF21expressing lentivirus. The cells without any 
treatment were used as mock control, and the cells treated with empty lentivirus were used as negative control. Data are presented as mean ± sD. **P,0.01. hcT116 and 
hT29, human colorectal cancer cell lines. 
Abbreviations: lv, lentivirus; MTT, 3(4,5dimethylthiazol2yl)2,5diphenyltetrazolium bromide; nc, negative control; OD, optical density. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Upregulation of TcF21 represses the ability of migration of hcT116 and hT29 cells. 
Notes: scratch assay was used to analyze cell migration in (A) hcT116 and (B) hT29 cells after transfection with TcF21expressing lentivirus. (a) scratch assay; (b) width 
of gap for (a). The cells without any treatment were used as mock control, and the cells treated with empty lentivirus were used as negative control. Data are presented as 
mean ± sD. **P,0.01. hcT116 and hT29, human colorectal cancer cell lines. 
Abbreviations: lv, lentivirus; nc, negative control. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1608 </p>

<p>Dai et al </p>

<p>Figure 4 Overexpression of TcF21 represses the ability of invasion of hcT116 and hT29 cells. 
Notes: Transwell assay was used to analyze cell invasion in hT29 and hcT116 cells after transfection with TcF21expressing lentivirus. The cells without any treatment 
were used as mock control, and the cells treated with empty lentivirus were used as negative control. (A) transwell assay with Matrigel. Magnification ×100. (B) data 
histogram of transwell assay. Data are presented as mean ± sD. ***P,0.001. hcT116 and hT29, human colorectal cancer cell lines. 
Abbreviations: lv, lentivirus; nc, negative control; OD, optical density. </p>

<p>Figure 5 TCF21 regulates key molecules of PI3K signaling and MMPs. 
Notes: (A) Western blot analysis for TcF21, Kiss1, Pi3K, aKT, paKT, MMP2 and MMP9 in hT29 and hcT116 cells after transfection with TcF21, and the results of 
quantification in (B) hcT116 and (C) HT29 cells. The cells without any treatment were used as mock control, and the cells treated with empty lentivirus were used as 
negative control. Data are presented as mean ± sD. **P,0.01, ***P,0.001. hcT116 and hT29, human colorectal cancer cell lines. 
Abbreviations: lv, lentivirus; nc, negative control. </p>

<p>β </p>

<p>with human CRC HCT116 cells infected with blank Lv 
and TCF21-expressing Lv, respectively. The cells without 
any treatment were used as mock control. The volumes of 
the tumors were monitored every 5 days. After 30 days, the 
mice were sacrificed to remove the tumors. The average </p>

<p>tumor volume in the Lv-NC group was significantly higher 
than that in the Lv-TCF21 group (Figure 6A and B). These 
results of the in vivo experiments suggest that TCF21 
could significantly inhibit human CRC xenograft growth 
in nude mice. Furthermore, we also analyzed the expression </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1609 </p>

<p>TcF21 functions as a tumor suppressor in colorectal cancer </p>

<p>Figure 6 TcF21 suppresses tumorigenicity of human colorectal cancer cells in vivo. 
Notes: The hcT116 cells that were transfected with TcF21expressing lentivirus were subcutaneously injected into nude mice. The cells without any treatment were 
used as mock control, and the cells treated with empty lentivirus were used as negative control. (A) The tumor volume was monitored every 2 days. (B) The tumors were 
obtained from the mice. (C) Western blot analysis for TcF21, Kiss1, Pi3K, paKT, aKT, MMP2 and MMP9 in the xenografted tumor tissues, as well as (D) the quantification 
results of the Western blot. Data are presented as mean ± sD. **P,0.01, ***P,0.001. hcT116, human colorectal cancer cell line. 
Abbreviations: lv, lentivirus; nc, negative control. </p>

<p>β </p>

<p>of downstream molecules of TCF21 in xenograft tumor tis-
sues. We confirmed that upregulation of TCF21 significantly 
increased the expression of Kiss-1 while decreasing the 
expression of PI3K and p-AKT, indicating an inactivation 
of PI3K/AKT signaling (Figure 6C). In addition, overex-
pression of TCF21 also inhibited the expression of MMP9 
and MMP2, which are involved in cancer cell invasion 
(Figure 6C). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we find that TCF21 is significantly decreased 
in CRC tissues, which is associated with the pathological 
stage, clinical stage and lymph node metastasis; furthermore, 
downregulated levels of TCF21 predict a poor prognosis in 
CRC patients. In addition, we also suggest that TCF21 func-
tions as a tumor suppressor in vitro and in vivo, in addition 
to being involved in PI3K/AKT signaling. </p>

<p>TCF21 is located at chromosome location 6q23, a region 
that frequently loses heterozygosity either genetically or 
through epigenetic events. 
10 TCF21 is frequently lost in 
human malignancies. It has been demonstrated that TCF21 
was aberrantly methylated and silenced in the majority of 
head-and-neck squamous cell carcinomas and non-small-cell 
lung cancers (NSCLCs). 
11 And restoration of exogenous 
expression of TCF21 in cells that have silenced the endog-
enous TCF21 results in a reduction of tumor properties both 
in vitro and in vivo. 
11 By using the DNA sequencing tech-
nique and quantitative methylation-specific polymerase chain 
reaction (PCR) assays, Shivapurkar et al 
12 found that the CpG 
island within exon 1 of the TCF21 gene was unmethylated 
in normal lung epithelial cells but predominantly methylated 
in lung cancer cell lines, which has been found in multiple 
other malignancies. Hypermethylation and decreased expres-
sion of TCF21 may be tumor specific and very frequent in </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1610 </p>

<p>Dai et al </p>

<p>all NSCLCs, even early-stage disease. 
13 It is important for 
the early detection and surveillance of lung cancer as well as 
multiple other malignancies. TCF21 methylation levels have 
been reported to provide a sensitivity rate of 92% for blad-
der cancer, 67% for renal cell tumors and 96% for prostate 
cancer. 
14 TCF21 methylation level is significantly increased 
in ccRCC. Moreover, the Kaplan-Meier survival analysis 
demonstrates that low expression of TCF21 is an independent 
prognostic factor for poor survival in patients with ccRCC. </p>

<p>4,15   Emerging evidence also demonstrates that hypermethylation 
of TCF21 is observed in breast cancer, gastric cancer and 
head-and-neck squamous cell carcinoma, 
2,5,16,17 which is in 
line with our previous results on CRC, 
7 indicating that aber-
rant methylation is an important reason for the downregula-
tion of the expression of TCF21 and may be associated with 
tumorigenesis in multiple types of cancer. 
We herein confirm that upregulation of TCF21 greatly 
inhibits CRC cell proliferation and cell invasion in vitro, as 
well as repressing tumorigenesis in nude mice. Our results 
further indicate that the inhibitory effects of TCF21 on CRC 
cancer are routed through Kiss-1, PI3K/AKT signaling 
and MMPs. 
The KiSS-1 gene was initially described as a suppressor 
of metastasis in malignant melanoma. Subsequent research 
has revealed that KiSS-1 is the strongest independent prog-
nostic factor among the conventional prognosticators for 
gastric cancer, ovarian cancer, breast cancer, hepatocellular 
carcinoma and pancreatic cancer. 
18-21 Furthermore, KiSS-1 
has an antiproliferative effect on cancer cells and could be 
responsible for decreased tumor growth and increased cancer 
patient survival. </p>

<p>18   MMPs can degrade the extracellular matrix and thus 
promote the process of tumor metastasis. MMP9 and MMP2, 
two of the most important proteases related with tumor 
metastasis, are capable of degrading the primary structure of 
the extracellular matrix and basement membrane to promote 
tumor metastasis. 
22 Induced overexpression of KiSS-1 in 
HT-1080 cells resulted in reduced transcription and activity 
of MMP9 and thereby a marked reduction in invasion in 
vitro. Consequently, the reduced synthesis of MMP9 induces 
certain inhibitory effects on the mobility and invasion of 
cancer cells. 
23 In addition, KiSS-1 treatment has been shown 
to elicit a strong and sustained phosphorylation of ERK1/2 
and pAKT. 
24 Recently, Arab et al 
25 have found that TCF21 
binds the promoter of the melanoma metastasis-suppressing 
gene, KiSS1, and enhances its expression through interaction 
with E12 and with TCF12. Loss of TCF21 expression results 
in loss of KiSS1 expression through loss of direct interaction </p>

<p>of TCF21 at the KiSS1 promoter. Additionally, microRNA 
(miR)-21 can downregulate the expression of TCF21, and 
the expression of KiSS-1 is downregulated in Caki-1 cells 
with TCF21 gene silencing. 
3 In CRC, KiSS-1 overexpression 
significantly decreases the cell proliferation and invasiveness 
of HCT-119 cells as well as enhancing cell apoptosis. Over-
expression of KiSS-1 also results in blockade of synthesis of 
MMP9 and PI3K, as well as the inhibition of phosphorylation 
of Akt. Furthermore, treatment with PI3K and Akt agonists 
attenuates the effect of KiSS-1 on the biological activity of 
CRC cells. 
24 Taken together, our results suggest that TCF21 
induces Kiss-1 expression and subsequently results in down-
regulation of MMPs and inactivation of PI3K/AKT signaling 
to exert its inhibitory function on CRC. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Collectively, our data reveal that decreased levels of TCF21 
predict a poor prognosis in CRC patients and that overexpres-
sion of TCF21 can suppress the proliferation and invasiveness 
of CRC cells; moreover, the TCF21 gene exerts its function 
probably by inducing Kiss-1 and reducing the expression of 
MMPs by blocking the PI3K/Akt pathway. Restoration of 
TCF21 levels may become a potential strategy to modulate 
CRC growth and metastasis in the clinic. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>This work was supported by grants: National Natural Science 
Foundation of China (81372792 and 81602683, Major 
Projects of Science and Technology in Hunan Province 
(2015SK2044, Science and Technology Planning Project of 
Hunan Provincial Health Department (B2014-090). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>OncoTargets and Therapy </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargetsandtherapyjournal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open 
access journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2017:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1611 </p>



</text></tei>