<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5374131" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>AIM 
To observe the natural course of 1-3 cm gastric 
submucosal tumors originating from the muscularis 
propria (SMTMPs). </p>

<p>larger tumor size (&gt; 14.0 mm) and irregular border. </p>

<p>Due to advances in endoscopy and its widespread 
use, detection of submucosal tumors (SMTs) of 
the gastrointestinal (GI) tract is not uncommon. In 
the evaluation of SMTs of the GI tract, endoscopic 
ultrasound (EUS) is a useful tool for identifying the 
tumor's layer of origin, measuring its size, providing the 
details of tumor echotexture, and differentiating it from 
external compression </p>

<p>[1] </p>

<p>. Among SMTs in the stomach, 
gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) are the most 
common </p>

<p>[2] </p>

<p>. When EUS reveals a hypoechoic submucosal 
tumor originating from the muscularis propria (SMTMP) 
in the stomach, GIST is considered first followed by 
leiomyoma </p>

<p>[3-9] </p>

<p>. Because all GISTs have a malignant 
potential and leiomyomas have a benign nature, tissue 
acquisition is often recommended for such tumors. At 
present, EUS-guided fine needle aspiration (EUS-FNA) is 
a feasible method. However, the diagnostic rate may be 
limited when the tumor is smaller or the tumor location 
is difficult to approach </p>

<p>[10-12] </p>

<p>. 
Based on the National Institute of Health Consensus, 
tumor size and mitotic activity are the two most 
important factors for predicting malignant potential of 
a GIST </p>

<p>[13] </p>

<p>. Obviously, tissue obtained by EUS-FNA can 
demonstrate GISTs only but cannot provide further 
information regarding mitotic activity. EUS features 
suggestive of a malignant GIST include larger tumor 
size, heterogeneous hypoechotexure, irregular tumor 
border, and internal cystic or calcified changes </p>

<p>[8,14,15] </p>

<p>. At 
present, a GIST &gt; 3 cm is considered to have higher 
malignant potential and is recommended for surgical </p>

<p>resection </p>

<p>[16] </p>

<p>. As for GISTs &lt; 1 cm, they are frequently 
considered to harbor a low risk of malignancy and 
tissue acquisition in these cases is controversial </p>

<p>[17] </p>

<p>. 
Notably, GISTs in the stomach are often indolent and 
rapid progression is uncommon. It should be considered 
whether all the myogenic submucosal tumors in the 
stomach are necessary for pathologic demonstration to 
differentiate GISTs from leiomyomas, especially in 1-3 
cm tumors. Until now, associated discussions regarding 
the natural course and management of 1-3 cm gastric 
SMTMPs are limited. Here, we reviewed computerized 
medical records over a period of 14 years from our 
institution to study the natural behaviors of such tumors. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patient selection </p>

<p>All the patients who underwent at least two EUS 
examinations to follow gastric SMTMP during a period 
of 14 years between January 2000 and December 2013 
were retrospectively reviewed using the computerized 
medical record system of Kaohsiung Chang Gung 
Memorial Hospital, a tertiary medical center in Kaohsiung 
City in Taiwan. </p>

<p>EUS modality and examination </p>

<p>In all patients, EUS was performed using a miniprobe 
with a 12 MHz radial scan (Olympus UM-2R, Tokyo, 
Japan). When EUS showed a myogenic tumor with 
hypoechoic echotexture originating from the muscularis 
propria in the stomach, it was regarded as a gastric 
GIST first or leiomyoma. We used the maximal tumor 
diameter as tumor size. The intervals of EUS follow-up 
were not defined, mainly depending upon the clinician's 
discretion. </p>

<p>Inclusion and exclusion criteria </p>

<p>If the tumor size exceeded 3 cm, we recommended 
FNA or surgical resection. When a tumor was &lt; 1 cm, 
we considered it to be benign. Therefore, we excluded 
the patients with an initial tumor size larger than 3 cm 
or persistently smaller than 1 cm. We also excluded 
the patients who underwent EUS only once without 
subsequent follow-up. We also enrolled the patients 
whose small tumors subsequently grew to 1 cm or 
more during surveillance. Therefore, only the patients 
with 1-3 cm myogenic tumors under EUS surveillance 
were enrolled in this study. </p>

<p>Pathological classification to predict malignant potential 
of GISTs </p>

<p>If a patient underwent surgery to remove a GIST, the 
pathology of GIST was classified into "very low risk", 
"low risk", "intermediate risk", or "high risk" using 
tumor size and mitotic count based on the National 
Institute of Health consensus </p>

<p>[13] </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Data collection and analysis </p>

<p>We defined a ratio of follow-up tumor size to initial </p>

<p> 
March 28, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 12| 
WJG|www.wjgnet.com </p>

<p>Hu ML et al . EUS surveillance in small gastric SMTMPs </p>

<p>tumor size ≥ 1.2 as tumor progression based on the 
Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumor (RECIST) </p>

<p>[18] </p>

<p>. 
Patients were then divided into a progressive subgroup 
and a stationary subgroup. Baseline characteristics of 
each subgroup, initial tumor size, echotexture, border 
and location of myogenic tumors, the number of 
surveillance procedures, and the interval and duration 
of EUS were recorded and further analyzed. </p>

<p>Second review for patients with progressive tumors </p>

<p>We followed the patients in the progressive subgroup 
again in 2016 by medical record review and phone call 
contact. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Continuous variables were analyzed using the Mann 
Whitney U test and categorical variables analyzed </p>

<p>using the Pearson χ </p>

<p>2 test. The sensitivity and specificity </p>

<p>of various tumor sizes were analyzed using a receiver 
operating characteristic (ROC) curve, and the optimal 
cutoff value was determined. All statistical analyses 
were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS statistical software</rs> (SPSS 
for Windows, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 13</rs>; SPSS Inc., IL). A P-value &lt; 
0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>During the 14 years between 2000 and 2013, 6755 
EUS procedures were performed by four endosono-
graphers. Of these, 1725 EUS results were associated 
with gastric SMTMPs. Based on the inclusion and 
exclusion criteria, 88 patients (44 males and 44 
females) were identified and enrolled in the study. 
The initial patient age was 57.1 ± 11.0 years (mean 
± SD) and the initial tumor size was 14.7 ± 4.9 mm. </p>

<p>Both the duration and interval of EUS surveillance 
ranged from 1.1 mo to 144.9 mo. The number of 
EUS surveillance procedures ranged from 2 to 9. Of 
the 88 patients, 25 (28.4%) were in the progressive 
subgroup and 63 (71.6%) in the stationary subgroup 
(Figure 1). The basic characteristics and EUS findings 
in each subgroup are shown in Table 1. By comparing 
the progressive and stationary subgroups, initially 
larger tumor size and irregular tumor border were 
identified to be predictors of tumor progression. 
Regarding initial tumor size, we performed an ROC 
curve analysis to determine the optimal cut-off 
size for predicting potential tumor progression. We 
found 1.4 cm to be the optimal cut-off tumor size 
associated with tumor progression, with a sensitivity 
of 68.0%, a specificity of 66.7%, and an accuracy of 
67.0 % (Figure 2). The interval of EUS surveillance in 
the progressive subgroup is shown in Figure 3. The 
interval of most EUS examinations was ≥ 3 mo (66/73 
= 90.4%). A total of 17 patients underwent surgery. 
Of these, 13 patients from the progressive subgroup 
were confirmed to have GISTs and 4 patients from </p>

<p> 
March 28, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 12| 
WJG|www.wjgnet.com </p>

<p>Indicated patients 
(n = 88) </p>

<p>Stationary tumors 
(n = 63) </p>

<p>Progressive tumors 
(n = 25) </p>

<p>Operation 
(n = 4) </p>

<p>Observation 
(n = 59) </p>

<p>Operation 
(n = 13) </p>

<p>Observation 
(n = 12) </p>

<p>Leiomyoma 
(n = 4) </p>

<p>GIST 
(n = 13) </p>

<p>Figure 1 Flow chart of management of 88 indicated patients with submucosal 
tumors originating from the muscularis propria in the stomach. EUS: 
Endoscopic ultrasound; GIST: Gastrointestinal stromal tumor. </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 
0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1.0 
1 -specificity 
Diagonal segments are produced by ties </p>

<p>Sensitivity </p>

<p>ROC curve </p>

<p>Figure 2 Receiver operating characteristic curve analysis of tumor size 
for predicting potential tumor progression. Initial tumor size of 1.4 cm was 
determined as the optimal cut-off size, with a sensitivity of 68.0%, a specificity 
of 66.7%, and an accuracy of 67.0%. </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 
0-3 mo 
3-6 mo 
6-12 mo 
&gt; 12 mo 
EUS follow-up interval 
EUS procedure sessions </p>

<p>Figure 3 Intervals of endoscopic ultrasound follow-up in 25 patients 
with 1-3 cm gastric submucosal tumors originating from the muscularis 
propria in tumor progression. EUS: Endoscopic ultrasound. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Hu ML et al . EUS surveillance in small gastric SMTMPs </p>



<p>March 28, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 12| 
WJG|www.wjgnet.com </p>

<p>patient was found to have malignant transformation or 
distant metastasis during surveillance. Notably, tumor 
progression (tumor enlargement ≥ 1.2 times) was 
only shown in the cases with GISTs. Among another 
12 patients in the progressive subgroup, we followed 
them until 2016. Two patients eventually underwent 
surgery due to gradually enlarged tumors and were 
confirmed to have GISTs with a low malignant 
potential. Two patients refused EUS surveillance due to 
old age (&gt; 80 years). Seven patients who took regular 
follow-ups remained condition stable without tumor 
metastasis. One patient was lost to follow-up. The flow 
chart of these 12 patients in the progressive subgroup 
is shown in Figure 4. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>GISTs are the most common mesenchymal tumors in 
the GI tract. Pathologically, most GISTs are composed 
of spindle cells and epithelioid cells which are de-
rived from interstitial cells of Cajal </p>

<p>[19-21] </p>

<p>. Most GISTs 
(approximately 65%) occur in the stomach, followed 
by 30%-35% in the small intestine and 5%-10% 
in the colon. About 95% of GISTs are characterized 
by the positive expression of c-kit receptor tyrosine 
kinase (CD117), whereas approximately 60%-70% 
of the tumors are positive for CD34 </p>

<p>[22-24] </p>

<p>. Most gastric 
GISTs are asymptomatic and are detected incidentally 
as submucosal tumors during endoscopy. Therefore, 
the real incidence of GISTs in the stomach remains 
unclear. EUS is the most common modality for the 
evaluation of submucosal tumors. A suspected GIST is 
a hypoechoic and myogenic tumor originating mostly 
from the muscularis propria and occasionally from 
the muscularis mucosae. Similar to GISTs in terms of </p>

<p>the stationary subgroup were confirmed to have 
leiomyomas. Basic characteristics and EUS findings 
for patients with confirmed GISTs and leiomyomas 
are shown in Tables 2-4. CD117 was positive in all 
13 patients with confirmed GISTs (100%), whereas 
CD34 was positive in 11 (84.6%). Pathology results 
for confirmed cases suggested 4 GISTs with a very low 
malignant potential, 6 with a low potential, 2 with an 
intermediate potential, and 1 with a high potential. No </p>

<p>Table 1 Basic characteristics and endoscopic ultrasound 
findings in 88 patients with suspected gastrointestinal stromal 
tumors in the stomach </p>

<p>Basic characteristic or EUS 
finding </p>

<p>Stationary </p>

<p>group n = 63 </p>

<p>Progressive </p>

<p>group n = 25 </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>Age (mean ± SD, yr) 
57.4 ± 10.6 
56.4 ± 12.4 
0.690 
Sex (M/F) 
35/28 
9/16 
0.100 
Location 
0.650 
Cardia 
16 
5 
Fundus 
16 
8 
Body 
24 
11 
Antrum 
7 
1 
EUS tumor size and 
echotexture 
Initial tumor size 
(mean ± SD, mm) </p>

<p>13.9 ± 4.5 
16.6 ± 5.5 
0.020 </p>

<p>Homogeneous/ 
heterogeneous 
hypoechoicity </p>

<p>44/19 
12/13 
0.060 </p>

<p>Smooth/irregular tumor 
border </p>

<p>56/7 
15/10 
0.002 </p>

<p>With/without internal cystic 
change or calcification </p>

<p>8/55 
4/21 
0.680 </p>

<p>EUS surveillance 
Surveillance duration 
(mean ± SD, mo) </p>

<p>24.6 ± 20.3 
30.7 ± 21.7 
0.220 </p>

<p>EUS: Endoscopic ultrasound. </p>

<p>Progressive subgroup 
(n = 25) </p>

<p>Operation 
(n = 13) </p>

<p>GIST 
(n = 13) </p>

<p>Observation 
(n = 12) </p>

<p>1 
st review in </p>

<p>2000-2013 </p>

<p>No recurrence 
(n = 12) 
Loss of follow up 
(n = 1) </p>

<p>Operation 
(n = 2) </p>

<p>GIST 
(n = 2) </p>

<p>Follow up 
(n = 7) </p>

<p>Stationary 
(n = 7) </p>

<p>Loss of follow up 
(n = 3) including 
too old (n = 2), 
fail to contact 
(n = 1) </p>

<p>2 
nd review in </p>

<p>2016 </p>

<p>Figure 4 Flow chart of patients in the progressive subgroup. These patients were reviewed twice; the first was based on medical records in 2013 and the second 
was performed by phone calls as well as based on medical records in 2016. </p>

<p>Hu ML et al . EUS surveillance in small gastric SMTMPs </p>



<p>March 28, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 12| 
WJG|www.wjgnet.com </p>

<p>EUS findings, leiomyomas are also tumors of muscular 
origin. Unlike GISTs, leiomyomas are negative for 
CD117 and CD34, but positive for smooth muscle actin 
(SMA) and desmin on immunohistochemical staining. 
Moreover, leiomyomas are completely benign. 
Recent studies have demonstrated that all GISTs 
have a malignant potential. Therefore, suspected 
GISTs should be confirmed histologically and managed 
accordingly. However, GISTs often behave differently </p>

<p>at different locations. A GIST in the stomach is often 
more indolent than a GIST with a similar size and 
mitotic count located in another GI tract site 
[25] . </p>

<p>Therefore, EUS surveillance alone is feasible for a small 
suspected GIST in the stomach that does not require 
immediate tissue proof or resection </p>

<p>[2,26] </p>

<p>. 
Most GISTs &lt; 1 cm harbor a very low malignant 
potential, while GISTs ≥ 3 cm with irregular tumor 
borders, heterogeneous hypoechogenicity, and internal </p>

<p>Table 2 Basic characteristics and endoscopic ultrasound findings in13 patients with confirmed gastrointestinal stromal tumors in the 
stomach </p>

<p>Case 
Age (yr)/ 
sex </p>

<p>Location Heterogeneous 
hypoechoic 
echotexture </p>

<p>Irregular 
border </p>

<p>Internal cystic 
change or 
calcification </p>

<p>Initial size 
(I , mm) </p>

<p>Final size 
(F , mm) </p>

<p>Tumor 
progression 
(F/I ≥ 1.2) </p>

<p>Surveillance 
procedures </p>

<p>Surveillance 
duration 
(mo) </p>

<p>Malignant 
potential </p>

<p>1 
41/F 
Body 
+ 
-
-
15 
23 
+ 
4 
82.1 
Very low 
2 
67/F 
Fundus 
+ 
-
+ 
15 
23 
+ 
5 
66.5 
Very low 
3 
50/F 
Cardia 
-
+ 
-
16 
20 
+ 
4 
22.8 
Very low 
4 
70/M 
Body 
-
-
-
15 
20 
+ 
8 
37.9 
Very low 
5 
57/F 
Cardia 
+ 
+ 
-
28 
50 
+ 
3 
19.3 
Low 
6 
46/M 
Fundus 
+ 
+ 
-
30 
35 
+ 
2 
3.4 
Low 
7 
55/F 
Antrum 
-
-
-
18 
23 
+ 
2 
63.0 
Low 
8 
69/F 
Body 
-
-
-
21 
28 
+ 
2 
3.7 
Low 
9 
49/M 
Body 
+ 
+ 
-
24 
30 
+ 
3 
47.9 
Low 
10 
61/F 
Fundus 
+ 
+ 
-
24 
33 
+ 
6 
41.9 
Low 
11 
54/M 
Body 
+ 
+ 
-
21 
28 
+ 
5 
32.1 
Intermediate 
12 
59/F 
Body 
+ 
+ 
-
18 
23 
+ 
2 
5.5 
Intermediate 
13 
60/F 
Fundus 
+ 
+ 
-
30 
51 
+ 
2 
31.3 
High </p>

<p>Table 3 Basic characteristics and endoscopic ultrasound findings in 4 patients with confirmed leiomyomas in the stomach </p>

<p>Case 
Age (yr)/ 
sex </p>

<p>Location Heterogeneous 
hypoechoic 
echotexture </p>

<p>Irregular 
border </p>

<p>Internal cystic 
change or 
calcification </p>

<p>Initial size 
(I , mm) </p>

<p>Final size 
(F , mm) </p>

<p>Tumor 
progression 
(F/I ≥ 1.2) </p>

<p>Surveillance 
procedures </p>

<p>Surveillance 
duration 
(mo) </p>

<p>1 
69/F 
Body 
-
-
-
10 
10 
-
2 
3.5 
2 
52/M 
Fundus 
-
-
-
10 
9 
-
2 
3.7 
3 
64/F 
Antrum 
+ 
-
-
13 
13 
-
3 
21.3 
4 
50/M 
Cardia 
+ 
+ 
+ 
18 
20 
-
2 
3.0 </p>

<p>Table 4 Comparison of basic characteristics and endoscopic ultrasound findings between patients with gastrointestinal stromal </p>

<p>tumors and leiomyomas by the Mann -Whitney U test </p>

<p>Basic characteristic or EUS finding </p>

<p>GIST n = 13 
Leiomyoma n = 4 
P value </p>

<p>Age (median, range, yr) 
57 (41-70) 
58 (50-69) 
0.785 
Sex (M/F) 
4/9 
2/2 
0.482 
Location 
0.868 
Cardia 
2 
1 
Fundus 
4 
1 
Body 
6 
1 
Antrum 
1 
1 
EUS tumor size and echotexture 
Initial tumor size (median, mm) 
21 
11.5 
0.015 
Final tumor size (median, mm ) 
28 
11.5 
0.003 
Homogeneous/heterogeneous hypoechoicity 
4/9 
2/2 
0.482 
Smooth/ irregular tumor border 
5/8 
0/4 
0.682 
With/without internal cystic change or calcification 
1/12 
0/4 
0.567 
EUS surveillance 
Surveillance duration (median, range, mo) 
31.3 (3.1-81.0) 
3.6 (3.0-21.4) 
0.023 
Surveillance procedure (median, range, times) 
3 (2-8) 
2 (2-3) 
0.163 
Tumor progression 
13 
0 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>GISTs: Gastrointestinal stromal tumors; EUS: Endoscopic ultrasound. </p>

<p>Hu ML et al . EUS surveillance in small gastric SMTMPs </p>



<p>March 28, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 12| 
WJG|www.wjgnet.com </p>

<p>cystic or calcified changes suggest a higher malignant 
potential. All leiomyomas are benign. Therefore, 
we were interested in the natural course of 1-3 cm 
SMTMPs in the stomach. To evaluate tumor growth, 
we calculated the ratio of follow-up tumor size to 
initial tumor size on EUS and defined the ratio of ≥ 
1.20 as tumor progression based on RECIST. Among 
88 patients with 1-3 cm gastric myogenic tumors, 
we found that most tumors were indolent and tumor 
progression was detected in 25 (28.4%) patients. No 
patients suffered from major complications such as 
tumor bleeding, obstruction, perforation or malignant 
transformation during surveillance. A total of 19 (17 + 
2) patients underwent surgery. Of these, 15 patients 
had GISTs and 4 patients had leiomyomas. Notably, 
tumor progression (tumor enlargement ≥ 1.2 times) 
was found only in GISTs but not in leiomyomas. 
Therefore, tumor progression may be a good predictor 
for differentiating GISTs from leiomyomas. Moreover, 
we found that larger tumors with irregular margins 
showed a tendency toward progressive change and 
should be monitored more closely. From the ROC 
curve analysis, we found 1.4 cm to be the optimal 
cut-off tumor size associated with tumor progression. 
The same 1.4 cm cut-off size was reported by Fang 
et al 
[27] in their study, which is similar to that reported </p>

<p>by Lachter et al 
[28] who found tumor size larger than </p>

<p>1.7cm to be indicative of tumor progression. Tumors 
with heterogeneous hypoechotexture showed no 
statistical significance for predicting tumor progression 
(P = 0.06) in our study, but the finding is limited by 
our small number of cases and requires clarification in 
a larger study. Regarding the appropriate interval of 
EUS surveillance, it is difficult to conclude how often 
a suspected gastric GIST should be followed since 
malignant GISTs were not detected during surveillance 
in our study. Although an evidences-based optimal 
EUS surveillance policy remains lacking for small 
GISTs, yearly EUS follow-up for small sized GISTs (&lt; 3 
cm) should be considered from a study of Prachayakul 
et al 
[26] in 2012. At present, a guideline from European </p>

<p>society of medical oncology recommended that an 
interval of 3 mo in the first follow-up and then annual 
EUS surveillance may be optimal for small suspected 
GISTs if no tumor growth occurs during surveillance </p>

<p>[29] </p>

<p>. 
In this review of 1725 EUS surveillances for gastric 
submucosal tumors from the 14 years of medical 
records, we found that most 1-3 cm SMTMPs in the 
stomach were indolent with only 28.4% of patients 
experiencing tumor progression (tumor enlargement ≥ 
1.2 times). EUS surveillance is optimal for small gastric 
myogenic submucosal tumors without immediately 
obtaining tissue. Tumor progression is a good predictor 
for differentiating GISTs from leiomyomas. Risk 
factors for tumor progression include larger tumor 
and irregular borders. Initial tumor size &gt; 14.0 mm 
may be considered a cut-off size for predicting tumor 
progression. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank the staff for contributing to the 
study accomplishment including data collection, writing 
recommendation and statistical assistance. The study 
was accomplished without any potential conflicts 
of interests, and without any support of grants or 
funding. </p>

<p>COMMENTS </p>

<p>Background </p>

<p>Most gastric submucosal tumors originating from muscularis propria (SMTMPs) 
are gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) and leiomyomas. Leiomyoma is 
benign but GIST has a malignant potential. Surgery is recommended if GISTs 
larger than 3 cm. Endoscopic ultrasound (EUS) fine needle aspiration is helpful 
to differentiate between GISTs and leiomyomas, but sometimes it is difficult to 
obtain tissue and cannot provide mitotic activity of GISTs. </p>

<p>Research frontiers </p>

<p>Because studies regarding the natural behaviors of 1-3 cm gastric SMTMPs are 
limited, the authors made a retrospective study by reviewing the past 14 years 
of computerized medical records in a tertiary medical center between 2000 and 
2013. </p>

<p>Innovations and breakthroughs </p>

<p>Most gastric SMTMPs are indolent from our study. Risk factors for tumor 
progression include larger tumor size and irregular border. </p>

<p>Applications </p>

<p>Initial tumor size &gt; 14.0 mm may be considered a cut-off size for predicting 
tumor progression. Therefore, a gastric SMTMP with irregular border or ≥ 14.0 
mm in size should be observed closely and treated accordingly. </p>

<p>Terminology </p>

<p>GISTs are the common submucosal tumors arising from the muscularis propria 
in the stomach and have a malignant potential though the behavior of most 
tumors is indolent. EUS is a useful tool to detect submucosal tumors of the 
gastrointestinal tract. </p>

<p>Peer-review </p>

<p>This study provides important information (long term surveillance, EUS 
surveillance interval, a cut-off value of tumor size of &gt; 14.0 mm) in the 
management of gastric small SMTMPs. </p>



<p>COMMENTS </p>

<p>Hu ML et al . EUS surveillance in small gastric SMTMPs </p>



<p>March 28, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 12| 
WJG|www.wjgnet.com </p>



<p>P-Reviewer: Bordas JM, Kobara H S-Editor: Qi Y 
L-Editor: Wang TQ E-Editor: Wang CH </p>

<p>Hu ML et al . EUS surveillance in small gastric SMTMPs </p>

<p>© 2017 Baishideng Publishing Group Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>Published by Baishideng Publishing Group Inc 
8226 Regency Drive, Pleasanton, CA 94588, USA 
Telephone: +1-925-223-8242 
Fax: +1-925-223-8243 
E-mail: bpgoffice@wjgnet.com 
Help Desk: http://www.wjgnet.com/esps/helpdesk.aspx 
http://www.wjgnet.com </p>

<p>I S S N 1 0 0 7 -9 3 2 7 </p>

<p>9 7 7 1 0 07 9 3 2 0 45 </p>

<p>1 2 </p>

</text></tei>