<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5091065" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The aim of present study was to compare blood lipid postprandial pro-
file response in two modes of high-intensity intermittent exercise. 
Twelve individuals (6 men and 6 women) were submitted to a maximal 
incremental test (to determine maximal aerobic power [MAP] and V 
. 
O2pe-</p>

<p>ak [peak oxygen uptake]), high-intensity intermittent all-out exercise 
(60× 8-sec bouts interspersed by 12-sec passive recovery) and fixed 
high-intensity intermittent exercise (100% maximal aerobic speed, con-
sisted of 1-min repetitions at MAP [70 rpm] separated by 1-min of pas-
sive recovery). Blood samples were collected pre, immediately, 45 and 
90-min postexercise. Serum was analyzed for total cholesterol and its 
ratio, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-c), low-density lipopro-
tein cholesterol (LDL-c), very low-density lipoprotein (VLDL) cholesterol, </p>

<p>and triacylglycerol (TAG). For TAG there was a main effect of moment 
with higher values immediately postexercise compared to 45-min 
postexercise. For VLDL there was a main effect to moment with higher 
values immediately post exercise than pre and 45-min postexercise; 
higher values 90-min postexercise than 45-min postexercise. There was 
no effect for HDL-c, LDL-c, and cholesterol. For area under the curve 
there was no difference for any variable. Our results indicated that both 
kinds of acute exercise session lead to no improvement in the acute re-
sponse of serum lipid profile of healthy young. </p>

<p>Subjects 
Twelve physically active men (n=6) and women subjects (n=6) 
(28±2 years; 173±12 cm; 73±12 kg; peak oxygen uptake 
[V 
. 
O2peak], 2.9 ±0.8 L/min; maximal aerobic power [MAP]: 
245±71 W) participated in this study. Specific physical activities 
of the participants included strength training, recreational sports, 
cycling or running (2-3 times per week). Participants were in-
cluded if they did not report any health problems and/or neuro-
muscular disorders that could affect their ability to complete the 
study protocol. Furthermore, all were free of any drug or ingestion 
of nutritional supplements during the period of the study and had </p>

<p>stable body mass 6 months before study (±5% of body mass). 
Participants took part voluntarily in the study after being in-
formed about the procedures, risks, and benefits and signed an in-
formed consent form. This study was approved by the local ethics 
committee (2012/133.609). The women were tested in the follic-
ular phase (1-10 days after the onset of menstruation) of the men-
strual cycle. </p>

<p>Study design 
Subjects completed four experimental sessions separated by at 
least 72 hr. During the first session, anthropometric and V 
. 
O2peak 
test measurements on a cycle ergometer were taken. In the second 
session, the participants were submitted to a high-intensity, inter-
mittent, all-out exercise protocol (60 bout of 8 sec: 12 sec) to de-
termine the total work performed (kJ). As all-out exercise perfor-
mance is difficult to predict and in order to guarantee that the re-
sults obtained were related to the type of exercise performed and 
not affected by the differences in exercise volume, total work per-
formed was equalized based in total work done in this session. This 
value (kJ) was used to equalize the subsequent exercise sessions. 
The two experimental sessions remaining were applied in random-
ized order: a high-intensity intermittent exercise performed all-out 
and a high-intensity intermittent exercise with fixed load. </p>

<p>Anthropometric measurements 
Height was measured using a stadiometer with a metric scale 
affixed to the floor, and body mass were measured using an elec-
tronic body-weight scale (precision 0.01 kg). </p>

<p>Maximum oxygen uptake test 
The participants performed an incremental test to volitional ex-
haustion on a cycle ergometer (Lode B.V., Groningen, The Neth-
erlands). The initial load was set at 30 W and it was increased by 
25 W/min for men and 15 W/min for women. Cadence was set at 
70 rpm, and subjects were instructed to perform the test until 
they could no longer continue. The test was finished when sub-
jects could not maintain the load for 5 sec in the fixed cadence. 
Strong verbal encouragement was given during the test. The oxy-
gen uptake was measured (MetaMax 3B, Cortex, Leipzig, Germa-
ny) throughout the test and the average of the last 30 sec was de-
fined as V 
. 
O2peak. The maximal load reached in the test was defined 
as the maximal intensity attained (MAP). When the subject was 
not able to finish the 1-min stage, the power was expressed ac-
cording to the permanence time in the last stage, determined as 
the following: MAP=power of last stage completed + [(time, in </p>

<p>https://doi.org/10.12965/jer.1632666.333 </p>

<p>Panissa VLG, et al. • Lipoprotein profile and high-intensity exercise </p>



<p>seconds, remaining in the last stage multiplied by 25 W or 15 
W)/60 sec]. </p>

<p>Experimental protocol 
Each experimental protocol started upon the arrival of the par-
ticipant at approximately 8 a.m., and with the participant having 
fasted for at least 10 hr previously. A cannula was inserted in an 
antecubital vein, then a fasting blood sample was taken (time=ze-
ro). After this, participants received a standardized breakfast (25% 
of the estimated daily energy needs for each participant on a sed-
entary day (Mifflin et al., 1990). This meal was composed of 
cheese, toast and strawberry yogurt and serial blood samples were 
taken at regular intervals for a period of 4 hr (2, 2.5, 3.25, and 4 
hr). The exercise was performed at approximately 2-2.5 hr of the 
experiment. </p>

<p>Exercise protocols 
In all exercise sessions participants performed a warm-up at 
50% MAP for 5 min, and after a 2-min interval they started the 
exercise. To estimate the energy expenditure of all exercises the 
sum of the contribution of the three energy systems (phosphagen, 
glycolytic, and oxidative energy systems) was used (di Prampero 
and Ferretti, 1999). Estimates of oxidative, glycolitic, and phos-
phagen systems use were carried out through the measurement of 
oxygen consumption during activity, peak blood lactate concen-
tration (measured from the ear lobe were taken to determine the 
lactate concentration -Yellow Spring 1500 Sport, Yellow Springs, 
United States) and the fast phase of excess oxygen consumption 
after exercise, respectively. The caloric quotient of 5.00 kcal was 
used in all three different energy systems. 
Two high-intensity intermittent exercises were performed, an all 
out (HIIE-AO) and with fixed intensity (HIIE-F), equalized by 
the total work done that totalized 26.1±9.8 kcal. The HIIE-F 
consisted of 1-min repetitions at MAP (70 rpm) separated by 1 
min of passive recovery on a cycle ergometer until the completion 
of the previously determined exercise. The time spent on this exer-
cise protocol was 17±2 min (9 min of effort and 8 min of pause), 
and energy expenditure 161.9±57.5 kcal. The HIIE-AO consist-
ed in to cycle as fast as possible 60 times for 8 sec interspersed by 
12 sec of passive recovery, totaling 20 min (8 min of effort and 12 
min of pause), and energy expenditure 201.8±64.1 kcal. The load 
used was 4% (men) and 2.5% (women) of body mass. </p>

<p>Blood samples and analysis 
Blood samples were collected pre, immediately, 45-and 90-</p>

<p>min postexercise. The blood samples (10 mL) were immediately 
allocated into two 5-mL vacutainer tubes (Becton Dickinson, Juiz 
de Fora, MG, Brazil) containing ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid 
for plasma separation and into one 6-mL dry vacutainer tube for 
serum separation. The tubes were centrifuged at 3,500 rpm for 15 
min at 4ºC, and plasma and serum samples were stored at -20ºC 
until analysis. Total cholesterol, HDL-c (mg/dL), and triacylglyc-
erol (mg/dL) were assessed using commercial kits (Labtest, São 
Paulo, Brazil). LDL-c (mg/dL) and very low-density lipoprotein 
(VLDL) cholesterol (mg/dL) was calculated according to Friede-
wald et al. (1972). To eliminate inter-assay variance, all samples 
were analyzed in identical runs. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
The data were presented as means and standard deviation. Lin-
ear mixed models were used to compare the lipid profile in differ-
ent exercises across time (condition×time). The Tukey post hoc was 
conducted if a significant difference was found. A paired t-test was 
conducted to compare area under curve (calculate by a trapezoidal 
method) between exercises. Statistical significance was set at P&lt; 
0.05. The data was analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., 
Cary, NC, USA). Standardized effect sizes were also calculated by 
the Cohen equations (Cohen, 1988) with the following threshold 
values: &lt;0.2, trivial; &gt;0.2 and &lt;0.6, small; &gt;0.6 and &lt;1.2, mod-
erate; &gt;1.2 and &lt;2.0, large; &gt;2.0 and &lt;4.0, very large; &lt;4.0, 
nearly perfect (Hopkins, 2002). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Fig. 1 presents blood levels of lipoprotein in the two modes of 
high-intensity intermittent exercise. 
For postprandial triglyceride (TG) there was a tendency to main 
effect to condition (F [1, 76]=3.58, P=0.062) with higher values 
in HIIE-AO than HIIE-F (P=0.062, d=0.416 [small]). There was 
main effect of moment (F [3, 76]=5.18, P=0.002) with higher 
values immediately postexercise compared to 45-min postexercise 
(P&lt;0.001, d=0.307 [small]). For VLDL there was a main effect of 
moment (F [3, 69]=3.08, P=0.033) with higher values immedi-
ately postexercise than pre (P=0.047, d=0.211 [small]), and 45-
min postexercise (P=0.020, d=0.281 [small]); higher values 90-
min postexercise than 45-min postexercise (P=0.027, d=0.164 
[trivial]) and tendency to difference from pre exercise (P=0.063, 
d=0.066 [trivial]). There was no effect for HDL-c, LDL-c, and 
cholesterol. For area under the curve there was no difference for 
any variable. </p>

<p>Panissa VLG, et al. • Lipoprotein profile and high-intensity exercise </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The main findings of the present study were that HIIE-F exercise 
seems to decrease TG when compared with HIIE-AO, and both 
exercises protocols induced similar responses for VLDL (increase 
postexercise). However, no other statistical significant improvement 
of lipoprotein profile was found in both exercise protocols. 
These findings are in agreement with a recent study, which 
showed that a session composed by 20 all-out sprint lasting 6 sec 
of effort interspersed with 24-sec recovery did not change post-
prandial triacylglycerol, glucose and insulin in healthy men (Allen 
et al., 2014). The authors suggested that the lack of improvement 
for postprandial triacylglycerol was due the low energy expendi-
ture of the exercise session (120 kcal approximately). In line with 
this results, the two modes of HIIE of the present study showed 
slight higher energy expenditure (162 to 202 kcal approximately) 
than the previous study (Allen et al., 2014), which may be one 
explanation for the lack of positive results in lipid profile. </p>

<p>However, a study showed that to achieve the positive effects of 
HIIE upon lipoprotein profile, especially in VLDL-TG secretion, 
the exercise should be performed for, at least, 2 months (Tsekouras 
et al., 2008), showing the importance of regular exercise in these 
outcomes. In addition, Lira et al. (2009) showed that high-inten-
sity exercise (90% VO2max) performed continuously, with low en-
ergy expenditure (~124 kcal), decreased total cholesterol and 
LDL-c levels in young males. 
Recently, Bellou et al. (2013) reported that HIIE (4 times of 4 
min at 90% of V 
. 
O2peak interspersed with 4 min at 60% of V 
. 
O2peak 
for a total of 32 min; gross energy expenditure ~500 kcal) reduced 
fasting plasma VLDL concentrations in nonobese men the next 
day (14 hr after exercise bout) by augmenting VLDL clearance, 
just like a single bout of continuous endurance exercise. Therefore, 
further studies are clearly needed to identify the mechanisms un-
derlying the beneficial effects of HIIE to help in the designing of 
optimal exercise protocols. 
Alongside, energy expenditure seems to be a determinant in the </p>

<p>LDL (mg/dL) </p>

<p>This study was supported by FAPESP (2011/22862-9). Ursula 
Ferreira Julio is supported by FAPESP (2011/22105-3), Fabio 
Santos Lira thanks Fapesp for their support (2013/25310-2). </p>



<p>https://doi.org/10.12965/jer.1632666.333 </p>

<p>Panissa VLG, et al. • Lipoprotein profile and high-intensity exercise </p>



<p>van Loon LJ, Greenhaff PL, Constantin-Teodosiu D, Saris WH, Wagen-</p>

<p>makers AJ. The effects of increasing exercise intensity on muscle fuel </p>

<p>utilisation in humans. J Physiol 2001;536(Pt 1):295-304. </p>

</text></tei>