<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5423319" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>We report the main characteristics of 'Actinomyces provencensis' strain SN12 
T sp. nov., 'Corynebacterium bouchesdurhonense' strain SN14 
T sp. </p>

<p>nov., 'Corynebacterium provencense' strain SN15 
T sp. nov. and 'Xanthomonas massiliensis' strain SN8 
T sp. nov., which were all isolated from </p>

<p>stool samples from obese French patients. </p>

<p>The study of the human gut microbiota experienced a new rev-
olution with culturomics, a new concept that enables exploring, as 
comprehensively as possible, the viable population of prokaryotes 
associated with the human gastrointestinal tract [1,2]. In 2015, 
using this culturomics approach, we isolated four bacteria which 
were not identified by matrix-assisted desorption ionization-
time of flight mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS) (Bruker 
Daltonics, Bremen, Germany) [1,2]. These species were isolated 
by culture on Columbia agar supplemented with 5% sheep's blood 
(bioMérieux, Marcy l'Etoile, France) at 37°C under micro-
aerophilic conditions using CampyGen (Thermo Scientific, 
Villebon-sur-Yvette, France) for 48 hours, all from stool samples 
from obese French patients. All subjects provided written 
informed consent, and the study was validated by the ethics 
committee of the IFR48 Federative Research Institute under 
number 09-022. The strains are anaerobic and facultative, but </p>

<p>growth was better under aerobic conditions. The failure of 
identification by MALDI-TOF MS of these four strains led us to 
sequence their 16S rRNA gene using fD1-rP2 primers as 
described previously using a 3130-XL sequencer (Applied Bio-
sciences, Saint-Aubin, France) [3]. 
Strain SN12 showed colonies bright grey and nonhaemolytic, 
with a diameter of 0.5 to 1 mm on 5% sheep's blood-enriched 
Columbia agar (bioMérieux) after 48 hours of incubation under 
aerobic conditions. It is a facultative anaerobic bacteria. Cells were 
Gram-positive, rod-shaped bacilli, spore forming and motile. The 
strain had positive catalase activity, but oxidase was negative. 
Strain SN12 had a 16S rRNA gene sequence identity of 95.04% 
with Actinomyces odontolyticus strain JCM 14871 (Genbank acces-
sion number NR_114395), the phylogenetically closest species 
with standing in nomenclature [4] (Fig. 1). This &lt;98.65% similarity 
leads us to putatively classify SN12 as a member of the Actinomyces 
genus and belonging to Actinobacteria phylum [5]. Therefore, we 
propose the creation of the new species 'Actinomyces provencensis' 
(pro.ven.cen 
0 sis, N.L. adj. neut., from Provence, the region in </p>

<p>France, where the strain was isolated). SN12 
T is the type strain of </p>

<p>the species 'Actinomyces provencensis'. 
The colonies of the strain SN14 on 5% sheep's blood-
enriched Columbia agar (bioMérieux) at 37°C under aerobic </p>

<p>New Microbe and New Infect 2017; 18: 24-27 
conditions were white, circular, nonhaemolytic and opaque, 
1 mm in diameter after 48 hours of incubation. Bacterial cells 
were Gram positive, rod shaped, facultative anaerobic, spore 
forming and nonmotile. Under electron microscopy, cells had a 
mean length and diameter of 0.8 and 1.8-5.0 μm respectively. 
Catalase and oxidase activities were positive. The strain SN14 
exhibited a 97.3% sequence identity with Corynebacterium tus-
caniense strain ISS-5309 (NR_043093), the phylogenetically 
closest species with standing in nomenclature (Fig. 2). Coryne-
bacterium tuscaniense strain ISS-5309 was isolated from culture 
of human blood [6]. This &lt;98.65% similarity with its phyloge-
netically closest species with a validly published name leads us 
to putatively classify SN14 as a representative strain of a new 
species within the genus Corynebacterium in the Actinobacteria 
phylum [5]. On the basis of the 16S rRNA gene sequence re-
sults and its phylogenetical position with the others closest 
species, we propose the creation of the new species 'Coryne-
bacterium bouchesdurhonense' (bou.ches.du.rho.nen 
0 se, N.L. adj. </p>

<p>neut., from Bouches du Rhône, the county in France where the 
strain was isolated). SN14 
T is the type strain of the species </p>

<p>'Corynebacterium bouchesdurhonense'. </p>

<p>The colonies of the strain SN15 were milky white, circular, 
nonhaemolytic and opaque, 1 to 1.5 mm in diameter after 48 hours 
of incubation on 5% sheep's blood-enriched Columbia agar (bio-
Mérieux) under aerobic conditions. Cells were Gram positive, rod 
shaped (0.6 × 1.2-1.7 μm), facultative anaerobic, motile and spore 
forming. Strain SN15 exhibited catalase positivity and oxidase 
negativity. The strain SN15 had a 16S rRNA gene sequence identity 
of 97.3% with Corynebacterium tuscaniense strain ISS-5309 
(NR_043093), the phylogenetically closest species with standing 
in nomenclature [6] (Fig. 2). This &lt;98.65% similarity leads us to 
putatively classify SN15 as a new species in the Actinobacteria phylum 
[5]. From these results, we propose the creation of the new species 
'Corynebacterium provencense' (pro.ven.cen 
0 se, N.L. adj. neut., from </p>

<p>Procence, the region in France where the strain was isolated). 
SN15 
T is the type strain ofthe species 'Corynebacterium provencense'. </p>

<p>The colonies of the strain SN8 were khaki green, circular, 
viscous and nonhaemolytic, 1 to 2 mm in diameter on 5% sheep's 
blood-enriched Columbia agar (bioMérieux) under aerobic 
conditions after 48 hours of incubation. Bacterial cells were Gram 
negative, rod shaped, motile and non-spore forming. Observed 
under electron microscopy, bacterial cells measure 0.6 μm in </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Phylogenetic tree showing positions of 'Actinomyces provencensis' strain SN12 
T relative to other phylogenetically close neighbours. Sequences </p>

<p>were aligned using <rs type="software">CLUSTALW</rs>, and phylogenetic inferences were obtained with Kimura two-parameter models using maximum-likelihood method </p>

<p>within <rs type="software">MEGA</rs> software. Numbers at nodes are percentages of bootstrap values obtained by repeating analysis 1.000 times to generate majority </p>

<p>consensus tree. Scale bar indicates 1% nucleotide sequence divergence. </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>Ndongo et al. Four new bacterial species isolated from human gut </p>



<p>© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 18, 24-27 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>diameter and 1.8-2.0 μm in length. Catalase activity test was 
positive. Oxidase activity test was negative. The strain SN8 had a 
16S rRNA gene sequence identity of 98.08% with Xanthomonas 
campestris strain ATCC 33913 (NR_074936), the phylogenetically 
closest species with standing in nomenclature [7] (Fig. 3), which 
putatively classifies strain SN8 as a member of a new species 
within the genus Xanthomonas in the phylum Proteobacteria [5]. 
Thus, we propose the creation of the new species 'Xanthomonas 
massiliensis' (ma.ssi.li.en 
0 sis, N.L. adj. neut., from Massilia, the antic </p>

<p>name of Marseille, France, where the strain was isolated). SN8 
T is </p>

<p>the type strain of the species 'Xanthomonas massiliensis'. </p>

<p>MALDI-TOF MS spectrum </p>

<p>The MALDI-TOF MS spectra of these species are available 
online 
(http://mediterranee-infection.com/article.php?laref= 
256&amp;titre=urms-database). </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Phylogenetic tree showing position of 'Corynebacterium bouchesdurhonense' strain SN14 
T and 'Corynebacterium provencense' strain SN15 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>relative to other phylogenetically close neighbours. Alignment and phylogenetic inferences were done as described in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>New Microbes and New Infections, Volume 18 Number C, July 2017 </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 18, 24-27 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Nucleotide sequence accession number </p>

<p>The 16S r RNA gene sequence was deposited in GenBank under 
the following accession numbers: 'Actinomyces provencensis' 
strain SN12 
T (LN881591), 'Corynebacterium bouchesdurhonense' </p>

<p>strain SN14 
T (LN881599), 'Corynebacterium provencense' strain </p>

<p>SN15 
T (LN890283) and 'Xanthomonas massiliensis' strain SN8 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>(LN881611). </p>

<p>Deposit in a culture collection </p>

<p>The strains were deposited in the Collection de Souches de 
l'Unité des Rickettsies (CSUR, WDCM 875) under numbers 
P2166 ('Actinomyces provencensis' strain SN12 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>), P2067 ('Coryne-
bacterium bouchesdurhonense' strain SN14 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>), P2161 ('Corynebac-
terium provencense' strain SN15 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>) and P2129 ('Xanthomonas 
massiliensis' strain SN8 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>). </p>

<p>Acknowledgement </p>

<p>This study was funded by the Fondation Méditerranée Infection. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>None declared. </p>



<p>FIG. 3. Phylogenetic tree showing position of 'Xanthomonas massiliensis' strain SN8 
T relative to other phylogenetically close neighbours. Alignment and </p>

<p>phylogenetic inferences were done as described in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>NMNI </p>

<p>Ndongo et al. Four new bacterial species isolated from human gut </p>



<p>© 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NMNI, 18, 24-27 
This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

</text></tei>