<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5473125" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:41+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Core tip: Biliary complications represent a leading cause 
of morbidity and mortality in liver transplant recipients. To 
date, endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography 
still remains the gold standard for diagnosing and treating 
such complications. The present study examined the 
benefit of complementary single-operator cholangioscopy. 
Our results are encouraging and demonstrate strong 
evidence for a diagnostic and therapeutic advantage of 
additional cholangioscopy for management of biliary 
disorders following liver transplantation. </p>

<p>Hüsing-Kabar A, Heinzow HS, Schmidt HHJ, Stenger C, Gerth 
HU, Pohlen M, Thölking G, Wilms C, Kabar I. Single-operator 
cholangioscopy for biliary complications in liver transplant 
recipients. Over the last few decades, the long-term outcome, 
morbidity, and mortality of liver transplant (LT) 
recipients have markedly improved because of advances 
in surgical techniques, modern immunosuppressive 
medication, and close follow-up. However, biliary 
complications after LT are still common </p>

<p>[1,2] </p>

<p>. Biliary 
complications affect 10%-25% of adult LT recipients </p>

<p>[3-5] </p>

<p>. 
In the majority of cases, patients present with biliary 
leakage and bile duct strictures. The latter can be 
subdivided into anastomotic and non-anastomotic 
strictures </p>

<p>[6] </p>

<p>, with anastomotic strictures responding 
well to endoscopic treatment 
[3,7] . Additional biliary 
complications are biliary stones, cast, and sludge. 
Because of several disadvantages of first generation 
direct peroral cholangioscopy (e.g., high costs, 
fragility, and the prerequisite of two experienced 
endoscopists), introduction of this technique in 1976 
initially failed to gain widespread acceptance. However, 
currently, cholangioscopy has become an established 
modality in diagnosing and treating pancreaticobiliary 
diseases </p>

<p>[8,9] </p>

<p>. In 2007, the digital single-operator per oral 
cholangioscopy system SpyGlass™ (Boston Scientific 
Corp., Natick, MA, United States) was introduced. This 
system featured crucial improvements in visualization 
and technical tools, leading to revived interest in the 
field of cholangioscopy for diagnosis and management 
of biliary disorders 
[10,11] . In 2015, high-resolution 
cholangioscopy (SpyGlass DS </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>) was introduced by 
Boston Scientific (Boston Scientific Corp.), enabling 
high-definition imaging of bile ducts. The wide range 
of potential indications and therapeutic procedures 
for SpyGlass DS, such as diagnosis of indeterminate 
biliary strictures, lithotripsy of bile duct stones, 
ablative techniques for intraductal malignancies, 
removal of foreign bodies, and gallbladder drainage, 
have led to more widespread use of this procedure. 
A study by Chen et al 
[12] showed that single-operator 
cholangioscopy using SpyGlass was feasible and safe 
for diagnosis and therapy of biliary disorders. Because 
of the possibility of direct high-resolution imaging of 
bile ducts, single-operator cholangioscopy has recently 
attracted attention in the field of management of 
biliary complications after LT </p>

<p>[13] </p>

<p>. However, only a few 
case reports and small case series have analyzed the 
role of single-operator cholangioscopy for management </p>

<p> 
June 14, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 22| 
WJG|www.wjgnet.com </p>

<p>Hüsing-Kabar A et al . Cholangioscopy after liver transplantation </p>

<p>of biliary complications after LT </p>

<p>[14-16] </p>

<p>. Moreover, most 
of these case series were performed using the earlier 
generation of the SpyGlass system. To the best of 
our knowledge, data on the effect of cholangioscopy 
using the high-resolution SpyGlass DS system on 
management of biliary complications in LT recipients 
are still unavailable. 
Therefore, this study aimed to examine the role of 
complementary single-operator cholangioscopy using 
the SpyGlass DS system during endoscopic retrograde 
cholangiopancreaticography (ERCP) for management 
of biliary complications following LT. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>This prospective, observational study was performed 
at the University Hospital Muenster, Germany. The 
study was performed in accordance with the guidelines 
of the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by 
the local ethics committee. All patients gave prior 
written informed consent. Patients with LT and duct-
to-duct biliary anastomosis who presented with clinical 
or biochemical signs of biliary complications, and/or 
suspected biliary complications based upon imaging 
and/or histology between April and December 2016 
were consecutively included in the study. Initial imaging 
included transabdominal Ultrasound in all cases. 
In case of inconclusive findings on transabdominal 
ultrasound and absence of clinical evident cholangitis, 
additional endoscopic ultrasound was performed 
followed by ERCP in case of documented biliary tract 
alterations. During the procedures, patients received 
conscious sedation using propofol and piritramide 
with or without midazolam. All of the patients first 
received ERCP followed by cholangioscopy during the 
same procedure. ERCP was performed using a large-
diameter channel duodenoscope (TJF-180V, Olympus 
Corp., Tokyo, Japan). Intubation of the bile duct was 
guidewire-assisted (0.025 inches, VisiGlide </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>, Olympus 
Corp.) using either a catheter (StarTip2V </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>, Olympus 
Corp.) or a sphincterotome (CleverCut2V </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>, Olympus 
Corp.). If necessary, biliary sphincterotomy was 
performed. 
Cholangioscopy was carried out using a single-
operator cholangioscopy device (SpyGlass DS; Boston 
Scientific Corp.) that was pushed along the guidewire 
through the working channel of the duodenoscope into 
the bile duct. The guidewire was then removed and 
cholangioscopy was continued under visual guidance. 
A biopsy was performed in case of unclear bile duct 
mucosal lesions. After the intervention, patients 
remained at least 3 d in hospital. 
The interventions were performed by two inves-
tigators rated as highly experienced with a case 
volume above 200 endoscopic biliary interventions/ 
year. Procedure related complications were evaluated 
according to the ASGE guidelines </p>

<p>[17] </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Peri-interventional antibiotics </p>

<p>Standard antibiotic prophylaxis included intravenous 
piperacillin/tazobactam at least 2 h before the 
procedure, and up to 3 d thereafter. During ERCP/ 
cholangioscopy, bile was collected for microbial analysis 
and for antibiotic susceptibility testing. </p>

<p>Immunosuppression </p>

<p>All of the patients were maintained on a calcineurin 
inhibitor only or in combination with either an m-TOR-
inhibitor or mycophenolate mofetil. </p>

<p>Interpretation of ERCP findings </p>

<p>Strictures were determined as an abrupt narrowing 
of the bile duct with delayed outflow of contrast 
media through the stricture. Bile strictures were 
fluoroscopically subdivided into anastomotic strictures 
at the site of biliary anastomosis and non-anastomotic 
strictures affecting donor bile ducts that were proximal 
to the biliary anastomosis. Bile duct stones and biliary 
cast were evident as intraluminal filling defects of 
contrast media. </p>

<p>Interpretation of cholangioscopy findings </p>

<p>Strictures were determined as above and were 
visible as an abrupt substantial narrowing of bile 
ducts compared with distal and proximal segments 
of the bile duct. Biliary cast was determined as dark 
smooth foreign bodies mostly adhering to the bile wall, 
whereas stones were determined as free-moving, 
hard, foreign bodies in the bile duct. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was conducted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">24</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, United States). All data are presented 
as absolute and relative frequencies and reported 
as median (minimal-maximal) values. Categorical 
variables were compared using Fisher's exact test. P 
values ≤ 0.05 were considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Over the period covered by our study, 26 consecutive 
patients underwent ERCP followed by cholangioscopy. 
Their median age was 54.5 years (25-75 years), 
and 14 (53.8%) patients were women. Procedures 
were carried out after a median of 18.5 mo (1-159 
mo) after LT. The patients' clinical and demographic 
data, their primary underlying disease, as well as the 
findings of ERCP and cholangioscopy, are shown in 
Table 1. 
A total of 33 biliary tract complications were 
diagnosed in 22 patients. Anastomotic strictures were 
observed in 14 (53.8%) patients, non-anastomotic 
strictures in seven (26.9%), biliary cast in three 
(11.5%), and stones in six (23.1%). 
In four patients, no bile tree abnormalities were </p>

<p> 
June 14, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 22| 
WJG|www.wjgnet.com </p>

<p>Hüsing-Kabar A et al . Cholangioscopy after liver transplantation </p>



<p>June 14, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 22| 
WJG|www.wjgnet.com </p>

<p>14 patients, non-anastomotic in seven, and stones in 
three. One patient showed bile duct kinking. In seven 
patients, ERCP showed no pathological results. </p>

<p>Findings of cholangioscopy </p>

<p>Cholangioscopy showed anastomotic strictures in 14 
patients (Figure 1), non-anastomotic strictures in </p>

<p>detected. Final diagnoses were confirmed by clinical 
follow-up, further liver biopsies, and biochemical tests. 
In these cases, graft rejection, drug-induced liver 
injury, and infections were the causative disorders. </p>

<p>Findings of ERCP </p>

<p>During ERCP, anastomotic strictures were observed in </p>

<p>Table 1 Patients' characteristics and findings of endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography/SpyGlass DS </p>

<p>Patient no. Age (yr) Sex 
Indication for LT 
Findings of 
ERCP </p>

<p>Findings of 
cholangioscopy </p>

<p>Endoscopic Intervention </p>

<p>1 
64 
M 
Caroli syndrome 
AS, non-AS 
AS, non-AS 
Stent insertion 
2 
65 
M 
Cryptogenic liver cirrhosis 
AS 
AS 
Balloon dilation 
3 
28 
M 
Cryptogenic liver cirrhosis 
AS, non-AS 
AS, non-AS 
Balloon dilation 
4 
48 
M 
Transplant dysfunction 
Normal 
Bile duct erythema 
None 
5 
30 
M 
Alcoholic liver cirrhosis 
AS, non-AS 
AS, non-AS 
Balloon dilation 
6 
63 
M 
Hepatocellular carcinoma, alcoholic liver 
cirrhosis </p>

<p>Normal 
Normal 
None </p>

<p>7 
56 
F 
Alcoholic liver cirrhosis 
AS 
AS 
Balloon dilation 
8 
48 
F 
Autoimmune hepatitis and primary 
sclerosing cholangitis </p>

<p>Non-AS 
Non-AS 
Balloon dilation </p>

<p>9 
46 
M 
Acute liver failure 
Stones 
Stones 
Extraction of stones 
10 
70 
M 
Hepatocellular carcinoma/hepatits C 
AS 
AS, stones 
Balloon dilation, extraction of stones 
11 
75 
F 
Autoimmune hepatitis and primary biliary 
cholangitis </p>

<p>AS 
AS, stones 
Extraction of stones, stent insertion </p>

<p>12 
51 
F 
Cryptogenic liver cirrhosis 
AS, non-AS 
AS, non-AS 
Balloon dilation, bougienage of 
stricture 
13 
57 
M 
Alcoholic liver cirrhosis 
AS 
AS 
Balloon dilation 
14 
30 
F 
Transplant dysfunction after LT for Wilson 
disease </p>

<p>AS, stones 
AS, stones 
Balloon dilation, extraction of stones </p>

<p>15 
60 
F 
Drug-induced liver injury 
None 
None 
None 
16 
57 
F 
Hepatitis C 
Stones 
Stones 
Extraction of stones 
17 
52 
F 
Hepatocellular carcinoma/hepatitis B 
None 
None 
None 
18 
44 
F 
Acute liver failure 
AS 
AS 
Balloon dilation 
19 
60 
M 
Alcoholic liver cirrhosis 
AS, non-AS AS, non-AS, biliary cast Balloon dilation, extraction of cast 
20 
53 
F 
Alcoholic liver cirrhosis 
Non-AS 
Non-AS, biliary cast 
Extraction of cast 
21 
25 
F 
Acute liver failure 
None 
None 
None 
22 
63 
M 
Non-alcoholic steato-hepatitis 
AS 
AS 
Balloon dilation 
23 
37 
M 
Hepatitis C/Wilson disease 
AS 
AS, stones 
Balloon dilation, extraction of stones 
24 
63 
F 
Non-alcoholic steato-hepatitis 
None 
Hiliar ulcer 
None 
25 
66 
F 
Primary biliary cholangitis 
None 
Biliary cast 
Extraction of cast 
26 
34 
F 
FAP 
Bile duct 
kinking </p>

<p>Bile duct kinking 
Stent insertion </p>

<p>AS: Anastomotic stricture; non-AS: Non-anastomotic stricture; ERCP: Endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreaticography; FAP: Familiar amyloid 
polyneuropathy; LT: Liver transplant. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Figure 1 Anastomotic stricture (arrows) as shown by fluoroscopy (A) and a corresponding cholangiographic image (B) showing high-grade fibrotic 
stenosis that initially could not be passed by the cholangioscope. </p>

<p>Hüsing-Kabar A et al . Cholangioscopy after liver transplantation </p>



<p>June 14, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 22| 
WJG|www.wjgnet.com </p>

<p>seven (Figure 2), biliary cast in three, and stones in 
six. All cases of non-anastomotic strictures showed a 
fibrotic obstruction and signs of inflammation, such 
as hyperemia, erosions, and polyp-like tissue growth. 
In one case, a fungal ulcer confirmed by microbiology 
was detected. In another case, bile duct hyperemia of 
intrahepatic bile ducts was found (Figure 3). </p>

<p>Comparison between ERCP and cholangioscopy </p>

<p>Benefits of cholangioscopy over ERCP were found 
in 12 of 26 (46.2%) patients. In four cases of failed 
cannulation of biliary strictures during ERCP, selective 
guidewire placement was successful by cholangioscopy </p>

<p>under direct vision. Furthermore, cholangioscopy was 
superior to ERCP for detecting stones in three patients 
(P &lt; 0.008) and cast in three patients (P &lt; 0.001) 
that ERCP failed to detect in these patients. In one 
patient, a fungal bile duct ulcer that was confirmed 
by microbiology (candidiasis) was detected, and this 
resulted in targeted antifungal therapy. In another 
patient, strong hyperemia of intrahepatic bile ducts 
due to acute cholangitis was observed. </p>

<p>Histological findings </p>

<p>A total of 11 biopsies were obtained. Histological 
samples showed fibrotic shrinkage without inflammation </p>

<p>Figure 2 Non-anastomotic strictures in seven. A: High-grade, long-segment stenosis of the main bile duct between biliary anastomosis and the hilus region. The 
biliary hilus appears to be involved in the stenosis; B: Cholangioscopic image of biliary anastomosis with slight stenosis; C: High-grade stricture of the bile duct beyond 
the biliary stricture that could not be passed using a cholangioscope; D: Bile duct above the biliary anastomosis after balloon dilation with marked erythema and 
polypoid growth of the bile duct wall, and signs of pronounced inflammation; E: Bile duct at the height of the hilus (arrow) with inflammation involving the left hepatic 
bile duct (right side of the image). </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D 
E </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>Figure 3 Bile duct hyperemia of intrahepatic bile ducts. A and B: Marked bile duct erythema caused by cholangitis; C: White plaque-coated bile duct ulcer. </p>

<p>Hüsing-Kabar A et al . Cholangioscopy after liver transplantation </p>



<p>June 14, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 22| 
WJG|www.wjgnet.com </p>

<p>in case of anastomotic strictures. In a patient with 
non-anastomotic strictures, signs of acute and chronic 
inflammation with mixed infiltration of lymphocytes, 
plasmacytes, and granulocytes, as well as granulation 
tissue and scars, were observed. In a patient with 
hyperemia, inflammation with predominantly granu-
locytes was observed. In this patient, bacterial 
cholangitis was confirmed by the clinical course and 
microbiologically. </p>

<p>Endoscopic treatment </p>

<p>In patients with biliary complications, a total of 13 
balloon dilatations, six extractions of stones, three 
stent insertions, one bougienage of a tight stricture, 
and three extractions of biliary cast were performed. 
Only one procedure-related complication (cholangitis) 
occurred and was managed antibiotically. </p>

<p>Microbial analysis of bile </p>

<p>Bile was collected from 23 patients. In seven (30.4%) 
patients, the bile showed no microbial growth. In 
16 (69.6%) patients, bacteria and/or fungi were 
detected. In nine (39.1%) patients, Candida species 
were observed (Candida albicans in six cases, and C. 
duliniensis, C. glabrata, and C tropicalis in one patient 
each). 
A total of 37 microorganisms were isolated from 
the bile. Of these, 16 were gram-positive (43.2%), 
whereas 12 (32.4%) were gram-negative bacteria. 
Candida species accounted for 24.3% of all isolates. 
The microorganisms that were found in bile are listed 
in Table 2. 
In patients with evidence of bile colonization, 
standard antibiotic prophylaxis using piperacillin/ 
tazobactam was effective in only 48.6% of all isolates. 
Susceptibility testing for ciprofloxacin showed that 
36.1% of isolates were sensitive, whereas 58.3% were 
resistant and 5.6% were intermediate susceptible. For </p>

<p>ceftriaxone, 70.3% of microorganisms were resistant 
and 29.7% were sensitive. Among all specimens, 
54.1% were sensitive to carbapenems. For gentamicin, 
32.4% were resistant, 55.6% were sensitive, and 
11.1% were intermediate susceptible to this antibiotic. 
For vancomycin, 87.5% of the tested gram-positive 
bacteria were sensitive. For tigecycline, 62.5% of all 
tested specimens were also sensitive. 
Of all fungal isolates, eight were sensitive to 
triazoles, while one was intermediate susceptible. 
All isolated Candida species were susceptible to 
amphotericin B and echinocandins. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Despite improvements in surgical techniques, biliary 
complications are common and still considered the 
"Achilles heel" of LT </p>

<p>[18,19] </p>

<p>. To date, ERCP represents 
the gold standard for diagnosis and treatment of 
biliary complications after LT </p>

<p>[20,21] </p>

<p>. However, increasing 
evidence is currently emerging of the major benefits of 
using cholangioscopy in management of these biliary 
disorders. 
In our study, an advantage of cholangioscopy 
over ERCP was observed in 12 of 26 (46.2%) 
patients. In one case series by Woo et al 
[13] SpyGlass 
cholangioscopy showed a high performance in 
visualization of strictures, but a poor performance 
of cholangioscopy-assisted guidewire placement 
in 60% of cases. In contrast to these findings, we 
were able to selectively steer the guidewire over the 
stricture in every patient prior to planned treatment. 
An explanation of the poor success of guidewire 
placement in Woo et al 
[13] study could be that their 
study was performed in patients after living donor LT, 
with special and sometimes complex anatomy of bile 
ducts. However, most of our patients underwent whole 
cadaveric LT prior to the procedure (only one patient in 
our cohort had a living donor LT). The use of the new 
generation of high-resolution cholangioscopy (SpyGlass 
DS </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>) in our study may have provided an additional 
advantage. 
In our study, cholangioscopy was superior to ERCP 
in detection of stones and biliary cast. Several previous 
studies showed that the sensitivity of ERCP in detecting 
bile duct stones ranged between 89% and 93%. 
Especially in cases of small stones and dilated bile 
ducts, false negative ERCP has been observed </p>

<p>[22-24] </p>

<p>. In 
a previous study at our center, we found that biliary 
cast appear to be underdiagnosed using ERCP only </p>

<p>[21] </p>

<p>. 
Biliary stones and cast can be masked by dense 
contrast media during ERCP. Furthermore, stones 
and cast in bile ducts may be easily misinterpreted as 
biliary air. In the present study, ERCP failed to identify 
biliary cast in three patients and biliary stones in a 
further three patients. In two of the three patients 
with failed diagnosis of cast, further biliary tract 
disorders were coincident. In one of these patients, </p>

<p>Table 2 Species found in bile </p>

<p>Microorganism 
Frequency 
Percentage </p>

<p>Stenotrophomonas 
1 
2.7% 
Enterococcus faecium 
7 
18.9% 
Escherichia coli 
5 
13.5% 
Streptococcus viridans 
2 
5.4% 
Micrococcus luteus 
1 
2.7% 
Enterococcus faecalis 
2 
5.4% 
Klebsiella oxytoca 
2 
5.4% 
Enterobacter cloacae 
2 
5.4% 
Raultella ornithinolytica 
1 
2.7% 
Enterobacter aerogenes 
1 
2.7% 
Staphylococcus haemolyticus 
1 
2.7% 
Pedicoccus pentosaceus 
1 
2.7% 
Enterococcus avium 
2 
5.4% 
Candida albicans 
6 
16.2% 
Candida duliniensis 
1 
2.7% 
Candida tropicalis 
1 
2.7% 
Candida glabrata 
1 
2.7% 
Total 
37 
100% </p>

<p>Hüsing-Kabar A et al . Cholangioscopy after liver transplantation </p>



<p>June 14, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 22| 
WJG|www.wjgnet.com </p>

<p>anastomotic stricture and multiple non-anastomotic 
strictures were found. In another of these patients, 
multiple non-anastomotic strictures were observed. 
These additional conditions could have made it even 
more difficult to identify biliary cast. In the third 
patient, biliary cast was detected only in the intra-
hepatic bile ducts and was adhered to the bile duct 
wall without completely occluding the whole bile duct 
lumen. In all patients in whom ERCP failed to detect 
stones, anastomotic stricture was also present, and 
small stones were detected by cholangioscopy directly 
proximal to the anastomosis. This was most likely as 
a consequence of bile stasis caused by stenosis. The 
coincident anastomotic stricture and bile duct dilation 
could have masked the small stones in these special 
cases. One further advantage for cholangioscopy was 
found in patients in whom pathological changes in bile 
ducts (e.g., hyperemia and bile duct ulcers; Figure 1) 
were only detectable by direct visualization of bile duct 
walls, but not by fluoroscopy. In these special cases, 
there were therapeutic consequences. In the current 
study, ERCP was highly effective in detecting bile duct 
strictures. In these cases, cholangioscopy offered no 
further benefits. 
In our study, additional histological information 
that was obtained by tissue samples of the bile duct 
was of minor clinical relevance. In the case of non-
anastomotic strictures, fibrosis and inflammation 
were simultaneously evident in every patient. This 
finding supports the role of ongoing inflammation for 
the pathogenesis of non-anastomotic strictures. Our 
findings are consistent with the results of previous 
studies suggesting immunological aspects in the 
pathogenesis of non-anastomotic strictures </p>

<p>[3,25] </p>

<p>. 
During endoscopic procedures, we obtained bile 
samples for microbial analysis in the majority of 
patients. Several studies have identified LT as a risk 
factor for increasing microbial colonization of bile. 
In these studies, an increased incidence of gram-
positive bacteria with increasing antibiotic resistance, 
such as enterococci and Candida species, in patients 
with LT was found 
[26-29] . In our study, we found a 
remarkably high prevalence of Candida species 
(39.1%), whereas the prevalence of enterococci was 
29.7%. In a minority of isolates (48.6%), specimens 
that were found in bile were sensitive to administered 
prophylactic antibiotics. These findings are important 
because microbial colonization of bile has been 
identified to be the origin of post-ERCP cholangitis and 
cholangiosepsis </p>

<p>[26] </p>

<p>. Even though microbial analysis 
was not the focus of the present study, these findings 
suggest that bile colonization during endoscopic 
interventions in the bile duct of LT recipients should be 
monitored. The resulting resistogram can be helpful 
in choosing effective antibiotics in case of endoscopy-
related septic complications. Because of the high 
prevalence of enterococci and Candida species, 
empirical antimicrobial treatments should include </p>

<p>vancomycin/linezolid and an antifungal agent in case of 
post-procedural septic complications. Isolated Candida 
species showed no relevant resistance to common 
antifungal agents in our study. However, selection of 
an antibiotic regimen should always be based on local 
microbial resistance patterns. 
In conclusion, high-resolution cholangioscopy 
using the SpyGlass DS system is safe and feasible 
in LT recipients with biliary complications, and offers 
useful diagnostic information in addition to ERCP. 
Cholangioscopy is superior to ERCP in diagnosing 
biliary cast and stones, and optimizes treatment in 
the patients concerned. Therefore, we recommend 
performing cholangioscopy in LT recipients who 
have negative ERCP results and suspected biliary 
complications. 
Use of a general peri-interventional antibiotic 
prophylaxis in patients with LT based on the general 
increase in microbial resistance should be critically 
examined in future studies. Furthermore, microbial 
analysis of bile collected during bile duct interventions 
should be regularly performed to adapt anti-infective 
treatments in case of post-ERCP septic complications. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We also acknowledge the support of Deutsche 
Forschungsgemeinschaft and Open Access Publication 
Fund of University of Muenster. </p>

<p>COMMENTS </p>

<p>Background </p>

<p>Despite improvements in surgical techniques, biliary complications still 
remain common in liver transplant (LT) recipients influencing their morbidity 
and mortality. Nowadays, endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography 
(ERCP) represents the gold standard for diagnosis and treatment of biliary 
complications following LT. Until now, data evaluating the utility and value of 
cholangioscopy for management of biliary disorders after LT are still lacking. </p>

<p>Research frontiers </p>

<p>The present study explores the benefit of modern digital single-operator 
cholangioscopy (SpyGlass DS™) in addition to ERCP for the management of 
biliary complications after LT. </p>

<p>Innovations and breakthroughs </p>

<p>The results of our study indicate that use of cholangioscopy provides valuable 
diagnostic information which is able to improve the management of biliary 
complications after LT. </p>

<p>Applications </p>

<p>These data demonstrate that cholangioscopy is effective for selective guidewire 
placement in high-grade biliary strictures that failed to be cannulated using 
ERCP alone. Furthermore, cholangioscopy offers diagnostic superiority in 
comparison to ERCP in detecting biliary cast and stones and therefore should 
be used in LT recipients with clinical signs of biliary complications despite 
negative ERCP results. </p>

<p>Terminology </p>

<p>Single-operator cholangioscopy is an innovative tool that enables high-
resolution imaging of bile ducts. </p>

<p>COMMENTS </p>

<p>Hüsing-Kabar A et al . Cholangioscopy after liver transplantation </p>



<p>June 14, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 22| 
WJG|www.wjgnet.com </p>

<p>Peer-review </p>

<p>The manuscript is fine and well written. In addition the manuscript is useful for 
physician facing with post liver transplant complication clearly documenting the 
superiority of cholangioscopy with respect to ERCP. Interestingly the superiority 
is clearly documented for biliary stones, casts and unusual, but diverse finding 
as micotic ulcer. </p>



<p>P-Reviewer: Kawakami H, Salvadori M S-Editor: Qi Y 
L-Editor: A E-Editor: Wang CH </p>

<p>Hüsing-Kabar A et al . Cholangioscopy after liver transplantation </p>

<p>© 2017 Baishideng Publishing Group Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>Published by Baishideng Publishing Group Inc 
7901 Stoneridge Drive, Suite 501, Pleasanton, CA 94588, USA 
Telephone: +1-925-223-8242 
Fax: +1-925-223-8243 
E-mail: bpgoffice@wjgnet.com 
Help Desk: http://www.f6publishing.com/helpdesk 
http://www.wjgnet.com </p>

<p>I S S N 1 0 0 7 -9 3 2 7 </p>

<p>9 7 7 1 0 07 9 3 2 0 45 </p>



</text></tei>