<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC5462257" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Methods 
Mosquito surveillance data provided by DPH was analyzed 
for years 2015 and 2016 to date. The geographical distribution of 
counties conducting surveillance, total number and percentage by 
mosquito species collected in 2015 were compared to 2016 data. 
The distribution of counties conducting surveillance was mapped 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">ArcMap</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">10.4.1</rs> for pre and post Zika response. Autochthonous 
vector transmission risk was evaluated based on the overall numbers 
and percentages of Aedes aegypti and Aedes albopictus mosquitoes 
collected for 2016. </p>

<p>Results 
In 2015, Georgia had 14 counties conducting mosquito 
surveillance, with a DPH entomologist providing direct surveillance 
in 4 of these counties. In 2016, DPH expanded surveillance capacity to 
34 counties, a 142% increase, geographically dispersed across the 
State in urban and rural areas. A total of 76,052 mosquitoes were 
trapped and identified in 2015 compared to 91,261 mosquitoes trapped 
to date in 2016, representing a 20% increase. A total of 37 mosquito 
species were identified in both years with Culex quinquefasciatus, 
Georgia's primary WNV vector, representing the highest percentage 
(2015-79.45% and 2016-70.41%) of mosquitoes trapped overall. 
In addition, Aedes aegypti represented only 0.108% and 0.007% of 
the total mosquitoes trapped respectively each year and was found in 
one county. Aedes albopictus represented only 1.50% and 1.82% of 
the total mosquitoes trapped respectively each year and was found in 
a majority of the counties conducting surveillance. </p>

<p>Conclusions 
DPH was able to rapidly expand its surveillance capacity statewide 
by maximizing existing grant funds to hire new surveillance staff 
while also collaborating with academic institutions, military bases, </p>

<p>Georgia Mosquito Control Association, and local health departments 
to provide training and funding for surveillance and data sharing. This 
expanded surveillance network provided a clearer picture of the types 
of mosquitoes potentially exposing the public to mosquito-borne 
disease risks. 
Historical data for the primary vector of Zika virus, Aedes 
aegypti has been isolated to just two counties in Georgia. Expanded 
surveillance in 2016 confirmed a low abundance of Aedes aegypti, 
suggesting the primary vector for Zika has been displaced by Aedes 
albopictus. This may suggest a reduced risk of autochthonous 
transmission of Zika virus in Georgia due to Aedes albopictus' 
affinity for feeding on both humans and animals. This should be 
interpreted with caution due to limitations in the data related to 
unstandardized reporting techniques for each county. DPH is working 
with all counties to improve the quality of data collected and reported 
and continues to educate the public on ways they can reduce their 
individual risk of mosquito bites, which in turn reduces the risk of 
other mosquito-borne diseases such as WNV. 
In conclusion, DPH's response to Zika virus allowed it to rapidly 
increase its surveillance footprint and with new data, make sound 
public health decisions regarding mosquito-borne disease risks. </p>

<p>Keywords 
Zika; Surveillance; Autochthonous transmission; Aedes aegypti; 
Aedes albopictus </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank the Georgia Department of Public Health for providing 
data and consultation on this study. </p>

<p>*Chris Rustin 
E-mail: rrustin@georgiasouthern.edu </p>

<p>Online Journal of Public Health Informatics * ISSN 1947-2579 * http://ojphi.org * 9(1):e103, 2017 </p>

</text></tei>